<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Paraphilia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23592</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520936426</id>
      <parentid>520904131</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T18:58:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jokestress</username>
        <id>62694</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Undid revision 520904131 by [[Special:Contributions/108.69.64.244|108.69.64.244]] ([[User talk:108.69.64.244|talk]]) wrong. &quot;normative&quot; is the term used for a reason, per DSM IV-TR</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36700">{{Redirect|Sexual perversity|the play by [[David Mamet]]|Sexual Perversity in Chicago}}
{{Infobox disease
 | Name           = Paraphilia
 | Image          = 
 | Caption        = (Sexual Perversions)
 | DiseasesDB     = 
 | ICD10          = 
 | ICD9           = 
 | ICDO           = 
 | OMIM           = 
 | MedlinePlus    = 
 | eMedicineSubj  = 
 | eMedicineTopic = 
 | MeshID         = D010262
}}
'''Paraphilia''' (from [[Greek language|Greek]] ''para'' παρά = beside and ''[[-phil-|-philia]]'' φιλία = friendship, meaning love) is [[sexual arousal]] to objects, situations, or individuals that are not part of [[normative]] stimulation.  Paraphilia involves sexual arousal and gratification, involving a sexual behavior that is atypical or extreme.&lt;ref name=&quot;DSMTR&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = American Psychiatric Association | authorlink = American Psychiatric Association | title = [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders|Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-IV (Text Revision)]] | pages = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=3SQrtpnHb9MC&amp;pg=PA566&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 566–76] | date = 2000-06 | publisher = American Psychiatric Publishing, Inc. | location = Arlington, VA, USA | isbn = 978-0-89042-024-9 | doi = 10.1176/appi.books.9780890423349 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The term was coined by [[Wilhelm Stekel]] in the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;stekel&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Stekel | first = W | authorlink = Wilhelm Stekel | year = 1930 | title = Sexual Aberrations: The Phenomenon of Fetishism in Relation to Sex | edition = translated from the 1922 original German edition by S. Parker | publisher = Liveright Publishing }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sexologist [[John Money]] later popularized the term as a nonpejorative designation for [[Kink (sexual)|unusual sexual interests]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wiederman2003&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Weiderman |first=M. |year=2003 |title=Paraphilia and Fetishism |journal=The Family Journal |volume=11 |issue=3 |pages=315–321 |doi=10.1177/1066480703252663 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bullough1995&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Bullough| first =  VL | year = 1995 | url = http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/GESUND/ARCHIV/LIBRO.HTM | title = Science in the Bedroom: A History of Sex Research| pages = 281 | publisher = [[Basic Books]] | isbn = 978-0-465-07259-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;moser2001&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Moser | first = C | year = 2001 | chapter = Critiques of conventional models of sex therapy | editor = Kleinplatz PJ | title = New directions in sex therapy: innovations and alternatives | publisher = [[Taylor &amp; Francis|Psychology Press]] | isbn =  978-0-87630-967-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mccammon2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = McCammon | first = S | coauthors = Knox D &amp; Schacht C | year = 2004 | title = Choices in sexuality | pages = 476 | publisher = Atomic Dog Publishing | isbn =  978-1-59260-050-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He described paraphilia as &quot;a sexuoerotic embellishment of, or alternative to the official, ideological norm.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;money1990&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Money | first = J | authorlink = John Money | year = 1990 | title = Gay, Straight, and In-Between: The Sexology of Erotic Orientation | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]] | isbn = 978-0-19-506331-8 | pages = [http://books.google.ca/books?id=nCvBoIr4eTYC&amp;pg=PA139#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 139]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 19th century, psychologists and psychiatrists started to categorize various paraphilias as they wanted a more descriptive system than the legal and religious constructs of [[sodomy]]&lt;ref name=&quot;dailey1989 &quot;&gt;Dailey, Dennis M. (1989). ''The Sexually Unusual: Guide to Understanding and Helping.'' Haworth Press ISBN 978-0-86656-786-2, pp. 15-16&lt;/ref&gt; and [[perversion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;purcell2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Purcell | first = CE | coauthors = Arrigo BA | year = 2006 | title = The psychology of lust murder: paraphilia, sexual killing, and serial homicide | publisher = [[Academic Press]] | isbn = 978-0-12-370510-5 | pages = 16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before the introduction of the term paraphilia in the DSM-III (1980), the term '''''sexual deviation''''' was used to refer to paraphilias in the first two editions of the manual.&lt;ref&gt;Laws and, O'Donohue (2008) p. 384&lt;/ref&gt; In 1981 an article published in ''[[American Journal of Psychiatry]]'' described paraphilia as &quot;recurrent, intense sexually arousing fantasies, sexual urges, or behaviors generally involving:&lt;ref name=&quot;AJP&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid |7457641}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Non-human objects
# The suffering or humiliation of oneself or one's partner
# Children
# Non-consenting persons&lt;ref name = DSM/&gt;

The view of paraphilias as disorders is not universal. Some groups seeking greater understanding and acceptance of sexual diversity have lobbied for changes to the legal and medical status of unusual sexual interests and practices. [[Charles Allen Moser]], a physician and advocate for sexual minorities, has argued that the diagnoses should be eliminated from diagnostic manuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;moser2005&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | author = Moser C, Kleinplatz PJ | year = 2005 | title = DSM-IV-TR and the Paraphilias: An argument for removal | url = | journal = Journal of Psychology and Human Sexuality | volume = 17 | issue = 3/4| pages = 91–109 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Psychiatrist [[Glen Gabbard]] writes that despite efforts by Stekel and Money, &quot;the term ''paraphilia'' remains [[pejorative]] in most circumstances.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gabbard2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Gabbard | first = GO | year = 2007| title = Gabbard's Treatments of Psychiatric Disorders| publisher = American Psychiatric Press | isbn = 978-1-58562-216-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the current version of the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]] (DSM-IV-TR), a paraphilia is not diagnosable as a [[psychiatric disorder]] unless it causes distress to the individual or harm to others.&lt;ref name = &quot;DSMTR&quot;/&gt; The [[DSM-5]] draft adds a terminology distinction between the two cases, stating that &quot;paraphilias are not ''[[ipso facto]]'' psychiatric disorders&quot;, and defining ''paraphilic disorder'' as &quot;a paraphilia that causes distress or impairment to the individual or harm to others&quot;.&lt;ref name=dsm5/&gt; This is purported by the draft to make a clear distinction between a healthy person with a non-normative sexual behavior and a person with a psychopathological non-normative sexual behavior. (On the other hand, a similar position was claimed to justify the inclusion of &quot;Sexual orientation disturbance (Homosexuality)&quot; in DSM II and &quot;Ego-dystonic homosexuality&quot; in DSM III {{cn|date=September 2012}}, before disorders related to homosexuality were finally dropped completely.)

==General concerns==
===Terminological===
Paraphilial [[psychopathology]] is not the same as [[psychology|psychologically]] normative adult [[human sexual behavior]]s, [[sexual fantasy]], and sex play.  These terms have been used in interchangeable ways which can allow for cognitive and clinical diagnostic misjudgment to occur. [[consent|Consensual]] adult activities and [[adult entertainment]] that may involve some aspects of [[sexual roleplay]], novel, superficial, or trivial aspects of [[sexual fetishism]], or may incorporate the use of [[sex toys]] are not necessarily paraphilic.&lt;ref name = DSM&gt;American Psychiatric Association. (2000). ''Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders'' (4th ed., text rev.). Washington, DC: Author.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Classification===
It is not known how many different kinds of paraphilias exist; one source lists as many as 549 paraphilias.&lt;ref name=&quot;aggrawal&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Anil | last=Aggrawal | coauthors= | title=Forensic and Medico-legal Aspects of Sexual Crimes and Unusual Sexual Practices | publisher=[[CRC Press]] | location=Boca Raton | year=2009 | isbn=1-4200-4308-0 | curly=true}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because so many paraphilias exist, one needs to classify them in an orderly and meaningful way. It has long been argued that the [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]] (DSM) system of classification makes unjustified categorical distinctions between disorders, and between normal and abnormal. Although the DSM-5 may move away from this categorical approach in some limited areas, some argue that a fully dimensional, spectrum or complaint-oriented approach would better reflect the evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Maser | first = JD | year = 2002 | url = http://download.journals.elsevierhealth.com/pdfs/journals/0193-953X/PIIS0193953X02000345.pdf | title = Spectrum concepts in major mental disorders | journal = Psychiatric Clinics of North America| volume = 25 | issue = 4 | pages = xi–xiii | author-separator =, | author2 = Akiskal HS | display-authors = 1 | pmid = 12462854 | doi=10.1016/S0193-953X(02)00034-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Krueger | first = RF | coauthors = et al | year = 2005 | url = http://content.apa.org/journals/abn/114/4 | doi = 10.1037/0021-843X.114.4.491 | title = Introduction to the Special Section: Toward a Dimensionally Based Taxonomy of Psychopathology | journal = Journal of Abnormal Psychology | volume = 114 | issue = 4 | pages = 491–3 | pmid=16351372 | pmc=2242426}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is scientific and political controversy regarding the continued inclusion of sex-related diagnoses such as the paraphilias in the DSM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Kleinplatz | first = PJ | coauthors = Moser C | year = 2005 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=gcZDghztlpMC&amp;pg=PA135#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | title = Politics versus science: An addendum and response to Drs. Spitzer and Fink | journal = Journal of Psychology and Human Sexuality | volume = 17 | issue = 3/4 | pages = 135–139 | doi = 10.1300/J056v17n03_09 | isbn = 9780789032140 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Homosexuality===

[[Homosexuality]] was at one time categorized as a form of paraphilia.&lt;ref name=&quot;hutchinson&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Hutchinson | first = GE | year = 1959 | title = A speculative consideration of certain possible forms of sexual selection in man | journal = [[American Naturalist]] | volume = 93 | issue = 869 | pages = 81–91 | doi = 10.1086/282059 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sigmund Freud]] and his proponents considered homosexuality and paraphilias to be forms of [[psychosexual infantilism]]. In a 1951 symposium discussing psychiatrist [[Benjamin Karpman]]'s paper &quot;The Sexual Psychopath,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;karpman1951&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid | 14832048}}&lt;/ref&gt; psychiatrist [[Emil Gutheil]] said, &quot;Looking back upon my own experience with so-called psychopaths, I find one characteristic they all have in common, and that is their infantilism. Take the man who is a homosexual. In his paraphilia he regresses to the time he was bisexual, that is, to his infantile level.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;karpman1951&quot;/&gt;

By the mid-20th century, mental health practitioners began formalizing &quot;deviant sexuality&quot; classifications into categories. Researcher [[Anil Aggrawal]] writes that the 1952 first edition of the ''[[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders]]'' (DSM) specified &quot;the type of the pathological behavior, such as homosexuality, transvestism, pedophilia, fetishism, and sexual sadism, including rape, sexual assault, mutilation).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aggrawal2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Aggrawal | first = A | year = 2008 | title = Forensic and medico-legal aspects of sexual crimes and unusual sexual practices | pages = 47 | publisher = [[CRC Press]] | isbn = 978-1-4200-4308-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally coded as 000-x63, homosexuality  was the top of the classification list (Code 302.0) until the [[American Psychiatric Association]] removed homosexuality from the DSM in 1973. Other organizations followed suit, including the [[American Psychological Association]] in 1975, and the [[National Association of Social Workers]].&lt;ref name=amici&gt;[http://www.courtinfo.ca.gov/courts/supreme/highprofile/documents/Amer_Psychological_Assn_Amicus_Curiae_Brief.pdf Case No. S147999 in the Supreme Court of the State of California, In re Marriage Cases Judicial Council Coordination Proceeding No. 4365(…)]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Martin Kafka]] writes, &quot;Sexual disorders once considered paraphilias (e.g., homosexuality) are now regarded as variants of normal sexuality.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;kafka1996&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Kafka | first = MP | year = 1996 | title = Therapy for Sexual Impulsivity: The Paraphilias and Paraphilia-Related Disorders | journal = Psychiatric Times | volume = 13 | issue = 6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2012 literature study comparing homosexuality with paraphilias confirmed that homosexuality was sufficiently dissimilar from the paraphilias as to be considered an unrelated construct.&lt;ref name = Cantor2012&gt;{{cite pmid | 22282324 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Clinical views==

===Neurodevelopmental correlates in men===
The causes of paraphilic sexual preferences in men are unclear, although a growing body of research points to a possible prenatal neurodevelopmental correlation. A 2008 study analyzing the sexual fantasies of 200 heterosexual men by using the Wilson Sex Fantasy Questionnaire exam, determined that males with a pronounced degree of fetish interest had a greater number of older brothers, a high 2D:4D [[digit ratio]] (which would indicate excessive prenatal estrogen exposure), and an elevated probability of being [[Left-handedness|left-handed]], suggesting that disturbed hemispheric [[Lateralization of brain function|brain lateralization]] may play a role in deviant attractions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/s10508-007-9255-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Classifications and theories===
[[Albert Eulenburg]] (1914) noted a commonality across the paraphilias, using the terminology of his time, &quot;All the forms of sexual perversion...have one thing in common: their roots reach down into the matrix of natural and normal sex life; there they are somehow closely connected with the feelings and expressions of our physiological erotism. They are...hyperbolic intensifications, distortions, monstrous fruits of certain partial and secondary expressions of this erotism which is considered 'normal' or at least within the limits of healthy sex feeling.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Albert Eulenburg|Eulenburg]] (1914). ''Ueber sexualle Perversionen. Ztschr. f. Sexualwissenschaft,'' Vol. I, No. 8. translated in [[Wilhelm Stekel|Stekel, Wilhelm]]. (1940). ''Sexual aberrations: The phenomena of fetishism in relation to sex.'' New York: Liveright, p. 4. {{OCLC|795528}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The clinical literature contains reports of many paraphilias, only some of which receive their own entries in the diagnostic taxonomies of the [[American Psychiatric Association]] or the [[World Health Organization]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://psyweb.com/Mdisord/DSM_IV/jsp/Axis_I.jsp psyweb.com &quot;Axis I. Clinical Disorders, most V-Codes and conditions that need Clinical attention&quot;. Retrieved: 23 November, 2007.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;World Health Organization, International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, (2007), [http://www.who.int/classifications/apps/icd/icd10online/ Chapter V, Block F65; Disorders of sexual preference.] Retrieved 2007-11-29.&lt;/ref&gt; There is disagreement regarding which sexual interests should be deemed paraphilic disorders versus normal variants of sexual interest. For example, as of May 2000, per DSM-IV-TR, &quot;Because some cases of Sexual Sadism may not involve harm to a victim (e.g., inflicting humiliation on a consenting partner), the wording for sexual sadism involves a hybrid of the DSM-III-R and DSM-IV wording (i.e., &quot;the person has acted on these urges with a non-consenting person, or the urges, sexual fantasies, or behaviors cause marked distress or interpersonal difficulty&quot;)&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dsmivtr.org/2-3changes.cfm Summary of Practice-Relevant Changes to the DSM-IV-TR] from [http://www.dsmivtr.org/ Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders===
==== DSM-I and DSM-II ====
In American psychiatry, prior to the publication of the DSM-I, paraphilias were classified as cases of &quot;psychopathic personality with pathologic sexuality&quot;. The DSM-I (1952) included [[sexual deviation]] as a [[personality disorder]] of [[sociopathic]] subtype. The only diagnostic guidance was that sexual deviation should have been &quot;reserved for deviant sexuality which [was] not symptomatic of more extensive syndromes, such as schizophrenic or obsessional reactions&quot;. The specifics of the disorder were to be provided by the clinician as a &quot;supplementary term&quot; to the sexual deviation diagnosis; examples of this supplementary term provided in the DSM-I included homosexuality, transvestism, pedophilia, fetishism, and sexual sadism, including rape. There were no restrictions in the DSM-I on what this supplementary term could be.&lt;ref&gt;Laws and, O'Donohue (2008) pp. 384-385 citing DSM-I pp. 7, 38-39&lt;/ref&gt;

The DSM-II (1968) continued to use the term &quot;sexual deviations&quot;, but no longer ascribed them under personality disorders, but rather them alongside them in a broad category titled &quot;personality disorders and certain other nonpsychotic mental disorders&quot;. The types of sexual deviations listed in the DSM-II were: [[sexual orientation disturbance]] (homosexuality), fetishism, pedophilia, transvestitism (sic), exhibitionism, voyeurism, sadism, masochism, and &quot;other sexual deviation&quot;. No definition or examples were provided for &quot;other sexual deviation&quot;, but the general category of sexual deviation was meant to describe the sexual preference of individuals that was &quot;directed primarily toward objects other than people of opposite sex, toward sexual acts not usually associated with [[coitus]], or toward coitus performed under bizarre circumstances, as in necrophilia, pedophilia, sexual sadism, and fetishism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Laws and, O'Donohue (2008) p. 385 citing DSM-II p. 44&lt;/ref&gt; Except for the removal of homosexuality from the DSM-III onwards, this definition provided a general standard that has guided specific definitions of paraphilias in subsequent DSM editions, up to DSM-IV-TR.&lt;ref name=&quot;Laws and, O'Donohue 2008 p. 386&quot;&gt;Laws and, O'Donohue (2008) p. 386&lt;/ref&gt;

==== DSM-III through DSM-IV-TR ====
The term &quot;paraphilia&quot; was introduced in the DSM-III (1980) as a subset of the new category of &quot;psychosexual disorders&quot;. The types of paraphilias listed were: fetishism, transvestism, zoophilia, pedophilia, exhibitionism, voyeurism, sexual masochism, sexual sadism, and &quot;atypical paraphilia&quot;. The DSM-III-R (1987) renamed the broad category to [[sexual disorder]]s, renamed atypical paraphilia to paraphilia NOS (not otherwise specified), finessed transvestism as [[transvestic fetishism]], added [[frotteurism]], and removed zoophilia, relegating it to the NOS category. It also provided seven nonexhaustive examples of NOS paraphilias, which besides zoophilia included [[telephone scatologia]], necrophilia, [[partialism]], [[coprophilia]], [[klismaphilia]], and [[urophilia]].&lt;ref&gt;Laws and, O'Donohue (2008) p. 385&lt;/ref&gt;

The DSM-IV (1994) retained the sexual disorders classification for paraphlias, but added an even broader category, &quot;sexual and [[gender identity disorder]]s&quot;, which includes them. The DSM-IV retained the same types of paraphilias listed in DSM-III-R, including the NOS examples, but introduced some changes to the definitions of some specific types.&lt;ref name=&quot;Laws and, O'Donohue 2008 p. 386&quot;/&gt;

Paraphilias are defined by DSM-IV-TR as sexual disorders characterized by &quot;recurrent, intense sexually arousing fantasies, sexual urges or behaviors generally involving (1) nonhuman objects, (2) the suffering or humiliation of oneself or one's partner, or (3) children or other nonconsenting persons that occur over a period of 6 months&quot; (Criterion A), which &quot;cause clinically significant distress or impairment in social, occupational, or other important areas of functioning&quot; (Criterion B). DSM-IV-TR describes 8 specific disorders of this type (exhibitionism, fetishism, frotteurism, pedophilia, sexual masochism, sexual sadism, voyeurism, and transvestic fetishism) along with a ninth residual category, paraphilia not otherwise specified (NOS).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/display/article/10168/55266 Paraphilias: Clinical and Forensic Considerations, April 15, 2007  Psychiatric Times. Vol. 24 No. 5] from [http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/home Psychiatric Times]&lt;/ref&gt; Criterion B differs for exhibitionism, frotteurism, and pedophilia to include acting on these urges, and for sadism, acting on these urges with a nonconsenting person.&lt;ref name = DSM&gt;American Psychiatric Association (2000). Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (4th ed., text revision). pgs. 569,570,572,574, Washington, DC: Author.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some paraphilias may interfere with the capacity for sexual activity with consenting adult partners.&lt;ref name = DSM&gt;American Psychiatric Association (2000). Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (4th ed., text revision). Washington, DC: Author.&lt;/ref&gt;  According to the DSM, &quot;Paraphilias are almost never diagnosed in females,&quot;&lt;ref name = DSM/&gt; but some case studies of females with paraphilias have been published.&lt;ref&gt;Fedoroff, J. P., Fishell, A., &amp; Fedoroff, B. (). A case series of women evaluated for paraphilic sexual disorders. ''Canadian Journal of Human Sexuality, 8.''&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders|DSM]] provides clinical criteria for these paraphilias:
*[[Exhibitionism]]: the recurrent urge or behavior to expose one's genitals to an unsuspecting person, or to perform sexual acts that can be watched by others.
*[[Sexual fetishism|Fetishism]]: the use of inanimate objects to gain sexual excitement. ''Partialism'' refers to fetishes specifically involving nonsexual parts of the body.
*[[Frotteurism]]: recurrent urges of behavior of touching or rubbing against a nonconsenting person.
*[[Pedophilia]]: strong sexual attraction to  [[prepubescent]] children.&lt;ref name=WHOPaedophilia &gt;World Health Organization, [http://www.who.int/classifications/apps/icd/icd10online/ ''International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems: ICD-10]''  Section F65.4: Paedophilia (online access via  ICD-10 site map table of contents)&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Sadism and masochism as medical terms|Sexual Masochism]]: the recurrent urge or behavior of wanting to be humiliated, beaten, bound, or otherwise made to suffer for sexual pleasure.
*[[Sadism and masochism as medical terms|Sexual Sadism]]: the recurrent urge or behavior involving acts in which the pain or humiliation of a person is sexually exciting.
*[[Transvestic fetishism]]: arousal from wearing &quot;clothing associated with members of the opposite sex.&quot;&lt;ref name = DSM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hirschfeld, M. (1910). ''Die tranvestiten'' [Transvestites]. Berlin: Alfred Pulvermacher.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Voyeurism]]: the recurrent urge or behavior to observe an unsuspecting person who is naked, disrobing, or engaging in sexual activities, or who is engaging in activities usually considered to be of a private nature.&lt;ref&gt;Hirschfeld, M. (1938). ''Sexual anomalies and perversions: Physical and psychological development, diagnosis and treatment'' (new and revised edition). London: Encyclopaedic Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Smith R. S. | year = 1976 | title = Voyeurism: A review of the literature | url = | journal = Archives of Sexual Behavior | volume = 5 | issue = 6| pages = 585–608 | doi = 10.1007/BF01541221 | pmid = 795401 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under ''Paraphilia NOS'', the DSM mentions [[Obscene phone call|telephone scatologia]] (obscene phone calls), [[necrophilia]] (corpses), [[partialism]] (exclusive focus on one part of the body), [[zoophilia]] (animals), [[coprophilia]] (feces), [[klismaphilia]] (enemas), [[Urolagnia|urophilia]] (urine), [[emetophilia]] (vomit).  The DSM's Paraphilia NOS is equivalent to the ICD-9's ''Sexual Disorder NOS''.

[[Sexual arousal]] in association with objects that were designed for sexual purposes is not diagnosable in DSM-IV (DSM, p.&amp;nbsp;570).&lt;ref name = DSM/&gt;

==== DSM-5 draft ====
The DSM-5 Paraphilias Subworkgroup reached a &quot;consensus that paraphilias are not ''ipso facto'' psychiatric disorders&quot;, and proposed &quot;that the DSM-V make a distinction between ''paraphilias'' and paraphilic ''disorders''. A paraphilia by itself would not automatically justify or require psychiatric intervention. A ''paraphilic disorder'' is a paraphilia that causes distress or impairment to the individual or harm to others. One would ''ascertain'' a paraphilia (according to the nature of the urges, fantasies, or behaviors) but ''diagnose'' a paraphilic disorder (on the basis of distress and impairment). In this conception, having a paraphilia would be a necessary but not a sufficient condition for having a paraphilic disorder.&quot; The 'Rationale' page of any paraphilia in the electronic DSM-5 draft continues: &quot;This approach leaves intact the distinction between normative and non-normative sexual behavior, which could be important to researchers, but without automatically labeling non-normative sexual behavior as psychopathological. It also eliminates certain logical absurdities in the DSM-IV-TR. In that version, for example, a man cannot be classified as a transvestite—however much he cross-dresses and however sexually exciting that is to him—unless he is unhappy about this activity or impaired by it. This change in viewpoint would be reflected in the diagnostic criteria sets by the addition of the word &quot;Disorder&quot; to all the paraphilias. Thus, Sexual Sadism would become Sexual Sadism Disorder; Sexual Masochism would become Sexual Masochism Disorder, and so on.&quot;&lt;ref name=dsm5&gt;http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevisions/Pages/proposedrevision.aspx?rid=186 (click 'Rationale' tab).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bioethics]] professor Alice Dreger interpreted these changes as &quot;a subtle way of saying sexual kinks are basically okay – so okay, the sub-work group doesn’t actually bother to define paraphilia. But a paraphilic disorder is defined: that’s when an atypical sexual interest causes distress or impairment to the individual or harm to others.&quot; Interviewed by Dreger, [[Ray Blanchard]], the Chair of the Paraphilias Sub-Work Group, explained: &quot;We tried to go as far as we could in depathologizing mild and harmless paraphilias, while recognizing that severe paraphilias that distress or impair people or cause them to do harm to others are validly regarded as disorders.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Alice Dreger (19 Feb 2010) ''[http://www.thehastingscenter.org/Bioethicsforum/Post.aspx?id=4494 Of Kinks, Crimes, and Kinds: The Paraphilias Proposal for the DSM-5]'', [[Hastings Center]]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charles Allen Moser]] pointed out that this change is not really substantive as DSM-IV already acknowledged a difference between paraphilias and non-pathological but unusual sexual interests, a distinction that is virtually identical to what is being proposed for DSM-5, and it is a distinction that, in practice, has often been ignored.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Moser C | year = 2010 | title = Problems with Ascertainment | url = | journal = Archives of Sexual Behavior | volume = 39 | issue = 6| pages = 1225–1227 | doi = 10.1007/s10508-010-9661-9 | pmid = 20652734 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Linguist]] A. C. Hinderliter argued that &quot;Including some sexual interests—but not others—in the DSM creates a fundamental asymmetry and communicates a negative value judgment against the sexual interests included,&quot; and leaves the paraphilias in a situation similar to ego-dystonic homosexuality, which was removed from the DSM because it did not meet the DSM's definition of mental disorder.&lt;ref&gt;A. C. Hinderliter. (2010) Defining paraphilia: excluding exclusion. Open Access Journal of Forensic Psychology. 2, 241-271. http://web.me.com/gregdeclue/Site/Volume_2__2010_files/Hinderliter%202010.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian and philosopher of science Patrick Singy claims that the DSM-5 is about to drastically loosen the criteria for paraphilias and to make them directly dependent on cultural values. The DSM-5 will then be closer to the DSM-I and DSM-II than to their successors, which all were at least trying to separate the concept of &quot;mental disorder&quot; from cultural norms, and which made &quot;harm&quot; or &quot;distress&quot; a necessary condition for having a mental disorder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Singy P | year = 2010 | title = What's Wrong With Sex? | url = | journal = Archives of Sexual Behavior | volume = 39 | issue = 6| pages = 1231–1233 | doi = 10.1007/s10508-010-9650-z | pmid = 20625808 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intensity and specificity===
Clinicians distinguish between optional, preferred and exclusive paraphilias,&lt;ref name = DSM/&gt; though the terminology is not completely standardized. An &quot;optional&quot; paraphilia is an alternative route to sexual arousal. For example, a man with otherwise unremarkable sexual interests might in some cases seek or enhance sexual arousal by wearing women's underwear. In preferred paraphilias, a person prefers the paraphilia to conventional sexual activities, but also engages in conventional sexual activities. For example, a man might prefer to wear women's underwear during sexual activity, whenever possible. In exclusive paraphilias, a person is unable to become sexually aroused in the absence of the paraphilia.{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}

The literature includes single-case studies of exceedingly rare and idiosyncratic paraphilias. These include an adolescent male who had a strong fetishistic interest in the exhaust pipes of cars, a young man with a similar interest in a specific type of car, and a man who had a paraphilic interest in sneezing (both his own and the sneezing of others).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=Psychiatry|volume=6|issue=3|month=March | year=2007|pages=130&amp;ndash;134|title=Sexual disorder and psychosexual therapy|author=Padmal de Silva|doi=10.1016/j.mppsy.2006.12.009|publisher=Elsevier Ltd|url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B82Y7-4N0GJN5-6&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=03%2F31%2F2007&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=0e747196d9865801e85db7b1c2942c5b}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=King, M.B.|title=Sneezing as a fetish object|journal=[[Sexual and Marital Therapy]]|volume=5|year=1990|pages=69&amp;ndash;72|doi=10.1080/02674659008407999|issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; See also [[List of paraphilias]].

===Drug treatments===
The treatment of paraphilias and related disorders has been challenging for patients and clinicians. In the past, surgical [[castration]] was advocated as a therapy for men with pedophilia, but has been abandoned for the time being because most governments consider it a cruel punishment where the express willingness and consent of the patient is not objectively indicated. Psychotherapy, [[Support group|self-help groups]], and [[pharmacotherapy]] (including anti-androgen hormone therapy sometimes referred to as &quot;[[chemical castration]]&quot;) have all been used. Other drug treatments for these disorders do exist, however.&lt;ref name=Williams1&gt;M. Williams. [http://www.brainphysics.com/paraphilias.php Sexual Compulsivity: Defining Paraphilias and Related Disorders &quot;Psychoactive Drug Treatments&quot;]. Retrieved 23 November 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/19/magazine/how-do-you-cure-a-sex-addict.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm How do you cure a sex addict?] Lauren Slater, NYTimes, 19 Nov 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

====Hormonal====
[[Antiandrogen]]ic drugs such as medroxyprogesterone (also known as the long-acting [[contraceptive]] [[Depo Provera]]) have been widely used as therapy in these men to reduce sex drive. However, their efficacy is limited and they have many side effects, including breast growth, headaches, weight gain, and reduction in bone density. Even if compliance is good, only 60 to 80 percent of men benefit from this type of drug. Long-acting gonadotropin-releasing hormones, such as Triptorelin (Trelstar) which reduces the release of gonadotropin hormones, are also used. This drug is a synthetic hormone which may also lead to reduced sex drive.&lt;ref name=Williams1 /&gt;

====Psychoactive====
[[Psychostimulant]]s have been used recently to augment the effects of [[serotonergic]] drugs in paraphiliacs. In theory, the prescription of a psychostimulant without pretreatment with an SSRI might further disinhibit sexual behavior, but when taken together, the psychostimulant may actually reduce impulsive tendencies. Methylphenidate ([[Ritalin]]) is an [[amphetamine]]-like stimulant used primarily to manage the symptoms of [[attention deficit hyperactivity disorder]] (ADHD). Recent studies imply that methylphenidate may also act on [[serotonergic]] systems; this may be important in explaining the paradoxical calming effect of stimulants on ADHD patients. Amphetamine is also used medically as an adjunct to [[antidepressant]]s in refractory cases of [[clinical depression|depression]].&lt;ref name=Williams1 /&gt;

==United States legal cases==
In the United States, following a series of landmark cases in the [[Supreme Court of the United States]], persons diagnosed with paraphilias and a history of [[anti-social behavior]], particularly pedophilia (''[[Kansas v. Hendricks]]'', 1997) and exhibitionism (''[[Kansas v. Crane]]'', 2002), can be held indefinitely in [[civil confinement]] under various state legislation generically known as [[Sexually violent predator laws]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid |19092060 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning | pages = [http://books.google.com/books?id=6MQj-mjHgBIC&amp;pg=PA248 248] | title = Legal aspects of corrections management | isbn = 978-0-7637-2545-7 | author1 = Cripe | first1 = Clair A | last2 = Pearlman | first2 = Michael G | year = 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the federal [[Adam Walsh Act]] (''[[United States v. Comstock]]'', 2010).&lt;ref name=apabc&gt;JESSE J. HOLLAND, [http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/wireStory?id=10666088 Court: Sexually dangerous can be kept in prison], [[Associated Press]]. Retrieved 5-16-2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://capcentral.org/civil/svpa/svpa_article_USsupreme.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Psychology|Sexuality|Psychiatry}}
*[[Courtship disorder]]
*[[Developmental psychology]]
*[[Dorian Gray syndrome]]
*[[Erotic target location error]]
*[[Human development (biology)|Human development]]
*[[Human sexuality]]
*[[Labeling theory]]
*[[Linguistic relativity]]
*[[List of paraphilias]]
*[[Lovemap]]
*[[Psychosexual development]]
*[[Richard von Krafft-Ebing]] for history of classifying sexual object choice as a disease
*[[Sex and the law]]
*[[-phil-]] (list of philias)
*[[:Category:Paraphilias]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

;Bibliography
* D. Richard Laws, [[William T. O'Donohue]] (ed.), ''Sexual Deviance: Theory, Assessment, and Treatment'', 2nd ed., Guilford Press, 2008, ISBN 978-1-59385-605-2

;Further reading
* Kenneth Plummer, ''Sexual stigma: an interactionist account'', Routledge, 1975, ISBN 0-7100-8060-3
* [[Elisabeth Roudinesco]], ''Our Dark Side, a History of Perversion'', Polity Press, 2009, ISBN 0-7456-4593-3

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Commons category|Paraphilias}}
*[http://www.behavenet.com/capsules/disorders/paraphilias.htm DSM-IV and DSM-IV-TR list of paraphilias]
*[http://www.dsm5.org/ProposedRevisions/Pages/SexualandGenderIdentityDisorders.aspx Proposed diagnostic criteria for sex and gender section of DSM5]

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{paraphilia}}
{{sex}}

[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Identity disorders]]
[[Category:Men and sexuality]]
[[Category:Paraphilias]]
[[Category:Psychiatric diagnosis]]
[[Category:Psychology]]
[[Category:Sex]]
[[Category:Sexology]]
[[Category:Sexual and gender identity disorders]]
[[Category:Sexual attraction]]
[[Category:Sexual fetishism]]
[[Category:Sexual orientation]]
[[Category:Sexual roleplay]]
[[Category:Sexuality]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]

[[ar:انتكاس نوعي]]
[[az:Parafiliya]]
[[be:Сексуальныя дэвіяцыі]]
[[bg:Парафилия]]
[[bs:Parafilija]]
[[ca:Parafília]]
[[cs:Parafilie]]
[[cy:Paraffilia]]
[[da:Parafili]]
[[de:Paraphilie]]
[[et:Parafiilia]]
[[el:Παραφιλία]]
[[es:Parafilia]]
[[eo:Parafilio]]
[[fa:انحراف جنسی]]
[[fr:Paraphilie]]
[[gl:Parafilia]]
[[ko:성도착]]
[[hr:Parafilija]]
[[id:Parafilia]]
[[it:Parafilia]]
[[he:פאראפיליה]]
[[ka:პარაფილია]]
[[lv:Seksuālā novirze]]
[[lt:Lytinis nukrypimas]]
[[hu:Parafília]]
[[arz:بارافيليا]]
[[mzn:اختلالات جنسی]]
[[nl:Parafilie]]
[[ja:性的倒錯]]
[[no:Parafili]]
[[pl:Parafilia]]
[[pt:Parafilia]]
[[ro:Perversiune sexuală]]
[[ru:Сексуальные девиации]]
[[simple:Paraphilia]]
[[sk:Porucha voľby sexuálneho objektu]]
[[sr:Парафилија]]
[[sh:Parafilija]]
[[fi:Parafilia]]
[[sv:Parafili]]
[[tr:Parafili]]
[[uk:Парафілія (сексологія)]]
[[vi:Lệch lạc tình dục]]
[[zh:性欲倒错]]</text>
      <sha1>h9nummkbr9jo472yc9y28sje7b93tn2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
