<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Polyamory</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24591</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517842769</id>
      <parentid>516330150</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-15T01:43:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zujua</username>
        <id>15652108</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>punct.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="73214">{{Redirect|Polyamorous|the [[Breaking Benjamin]] song|Polyamorous (song)}}
{{For|the use and analysis of a triad relationship in sociology|Triad (sociology)}}
[[File:Polyamory.svg|thumb|right|The infinity heart is a widely used symbol of polyamory.&lt;ref name=&quot;ILIC&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hevanet.com/alexwest/parrots/symbolist.html |title=A List of Poly Symbols |accessdate=2002-05-11 |author=[http://www.hevanet.com/alexwest/mail_me.html West, Alex] |date=2001-02-06 |quote=variations on Pi-and-the-three-colors the ILIC symbol&amp;nbsp;... The symbol that started this category, Jim Evans' Poly Pride Flag. He has put this image in the public domain&amp;nbsp;... &quot;ILIC&quot; stands for Infinite Love in Infinite Combinations (a reference to Star Trek's IDIC credo --- the D in the Star Trek version stands for &quot;Diversity&quot;).}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Close relationships}}

'''Polyamory''' (from [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|el|πολύ}} [''{{lang|el-Latn|poly}}''], meaning &quot;many&quot; or &quot;several&quot;, and [[Latin language|Latin]] ''{{lang|la|amor}}'', &quot;[[love]]&quot;) is the practice, desire, or acceptance of having more than one intimate relationship at a time with the knowledge and [[consent]] of everyone involved. Many{{Who|date=October 2012}} contend that it is distinct from both [[swinging]] (which often emphasizes sex with others as merely recreational) or with [[polysexuality]] (which is attraction towards multiple [[genders]] and/or [[sexes]]){{Citation needed|date=October 2012}}.

Polyamory, often abbreviated as ''poly'', is often described as ''consensual,'' ''ethical,'' or ''responsible non-monogamy''. The word is sometimes used in a broader sense to refer to sexual or romantic relationships that are not sexually exclusive, though there is disagreement on how broadly it applies; an emphasis on ethics, honesty, and transparency all around is widely regarded as the crucial defining characteristic. 

The term &quot;polyamorous&quot; can refer to the nature of a relationship at some point in time or to a [[philosophy]] or relationship orientation (much like gender or sexual orientation). It is sometimes used as an [[umbrella term]] that covers various forms of multiple relationships; polyamorous arrangements are varied, reflecting the choices and philosophies of the individuals involved. Polyamory is a less specific term than [[polygamy]], the practice or condition of having more than one [[spouse (disambiguation)|spouse]].  The majority of polygamous cultures are traditionally [[polygynous]], where one husband has multiple wives.  [[Polyandrous]] societies, in which one wife has multiple husbands, are less common but do exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Palm&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Polyandry Practice Fascinates Prince |first=Dee |last=Whittington |newspaper=[[The Palm Beach Post]] |date=December 12, 1976 |url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=blc0AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=CcwFAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2638,6668094&amp;dq=polyandry+sri+lanka&amp;hl=en |accessdate=October 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marriage is not a requirement in polyamorous relationships. The &quot;knowledge and consent of all partners concerned&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;oed.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oed.com/help/updates/pleb-Pomak.html |title=New edition: ''pleb'' to ''Pomak'' |accessdate=2007-02-16 |date=2006-09-14 |work=Quarterly updates to OED Online}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a defining characteristic of polyamorous relationships. Distinguishing polyamory from traditional forms of non-monogamy (e.g., &quot;[[infidelity|cheating]]&quot;) is an ideology that openness, goodwill, truthful communication, and ethical behavior should prevail among all the parties involved.&lt;ref&gt;Alan M. [http://polyinthemedia.blogspot.com/2008/10/more-speeches-from-poly-pride-weekend.html &quot;Five Speeches from Poly Pride Weekend&quot;], ''Polyamory in the News'', Oct. 20, 2008 (retrieved Feb. 21, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.polyamoryleadershipnetwork.org/ &quot;Welcome to the Polyamory Leadership Network&quot;], Oct. 2010 (retrieved Feb. 21, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; As of July 2009, it was estimated that more than 500,000 polyamorous relationships existed in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Bennett |first=Jessica |title=Polyamory—relationships with multiple, mutually consenting partners—has a coming-out party. |newspaper=Newsweek Magazine Online |date=June 29, 2009 |url=http://www.newsweek.com/id/209164 |accessdate=2009-09-15 |quote=[http://google.com/search?q=cache:HQ7XSHMfV_0J:www.newsweek.com/id/191012)%3Freload%3Dtrue+polyamory+site:newsweek.com&amp;cd=5&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=us Editor's note in TOC: &quot;Polyamory is a thriving phenomenon in the United States, with over half a million families openly living in relationships that are between multiple consenting partners.&quot;]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=George |first=Robert P. |title=Gay Marriage, Democracy, and the Courts |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204619004574322084279548434.html |quote=This week's Newsweek reports more than 500,000 polyamorous households in the U.S. |accessdate=13 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

People who identify as polyamorous typically reject the view that sexual and relational exclusivity are necessary for deep, committed, long-term [[loving relationship]]s. Those who are open to, or emotionally suited for, polyamory may embark on a polyamorous relationship when single or already in a [[monogamy|monogamous]] or [[open relationship]].  [[Sexual intercourse|Sex]] is not necessarily a primary focus in polyamorous relationships, which commonly consist of people seeking to build long-term relationships with more than one person on mutually agreeable grounds, with sex as only one aspect of their relationships. In practice, polyamorous relationships are highly varied and individualized according to those participating.  For many, such relationships are ideally built upon [[Value (personal and cultural)|values]] of [[Trust (social sciences)|trust]], [[loyalty]], the [[negotiation]] of boundaries, and [[compersion]], as well as overcoming [[jealousy]], possessiveness, and the rejection of restrictive cultural standards.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian1&quot;&gt;In [http://www.guardian.co.uk/women/story/0,3604,1085003,00.html ''When two just won't do''], ''The Guardian'', November 14, 2003, Helen Echlin states: &quot;For most people, the biggest stumbling block to polyamory is jealousy. But polys try to see jealousy less as a green-eyed monster than as an opportunity for character-building.&quot; Retrieved March 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  Powerful intimate bonding among three or more persons may occur. The skills and attitudes needed to manage polyamorous relationships add challenges that are not often found in the traditional &quot;[[dating]]-and-[[marriage]]&quot; model of long-term relationships.  Polyamory may require a more fluid and flexible approach to love relationship, and yet operate on a complex system of boundaries or rules.  Additionally, participants in a polyamorous relationship may not have, nor expect their partners to have, preconceptions as to the duration of the relationship, in contrast to monogamous marriages where a lifelong union is generally the goal.  However, polyamorous relationships can and do last many years.

==Terminology==

{{Main|Terminology within polyamory}}
''Polyamory'' is a [[hybrid word]]: ''poly'' is [[Greek (language)|Greek]] for ''many'' (or ''multiple'') and ''amor'' is [[Latin]] for [[love]].  The article entitled &quot;A Bouquet of Lovers,&quot; written by [[Morning Glory Zell-Ravenheart]] and first published in ''[[Green Egg|Green Egg Magazine]]'' (Spring 1990), a publication founded by her husband [[Oberon Zell-Ravenheart]], is widely cited as the original source of the word, although &quot;polyamory&quot; does not appear in the article.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=CAWeb |title=Church of All Worlds Clergy |url=http://original.caw.org/clergy/mg/index.html |accessdate=2006-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A Bouquet of Lovers&quot; does use &quot;polyamorous,&quot; but &quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20030508180124/http://www.lair.org/writings/polyamory/bouquet.html the original version] introduced the term &quot;poly-amorous&quot; in hyphenated form, which suggests that the author may not have viewed it as a word at the time. Later copies on the Internet were edited to remove the hyphen, after the word had become more well-known and established. The word &quot;polyamory&quot; does not appear in the article, and the predecessor word &quot;polygamy&quot; is used several times.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jennifer L. Wesp]] created the [[Usenet]] [[newsgroup]] alt.polyamory in May 1992,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.faqs.org/faqs/polyamory/faq/section-1.html Faqs.org]&lt;/ref&gt; and the Oxford English Dictionary cites the proposal to create that group as the first verified appearance of the word.&lt;ref&gt;[http://polyinthemedia.blogspot.com/2007/01/polyamory-enters-oxford-english.html &quot;Polyamory&quot; enters the ''Oxford English Dictionary,'' and tracking the word's origins]&lt;/ref&gt; The term [[polyfidelity]], now considered a subset of polyamory, was coined in the 1970s by members of the [[Kerista|Kerista commune]].  Naturally, such relationships existed long before the words for them came into use.

Most definitions center on the concepts of being open to, or engaging in, multiple loving relationships (of whatever form or configuration) wherein all parties are informed and consenting to the arrangement. However, no single definition of &quot;polyamory&quot; has universal acceptance; two areas of difference arise regarding the degree of commitment (such as in the practice of more casual sexual activities rather than long-term, loving partnerships) and whether it represents a viewpoint or a relational status quo (is a person who is open to the idea, but without partners at present, still &quot;polyamorous?&quot;). Similarly, an [[open relationship]] in which the committed partners agree to permit romantic or sexual relationships with other people, might be considered &quot;polyamorous&quot; under broader usages of the word, but excluded from some of the narrower usages, since polyamorous relationships can also be conducted as [[poly-fidelitous]] (&quot;closed,&quot; or faithful to the participants involved).

Members of the newsgroup alt.polyamory collaborated on a [[FAQ]] (frequently asked questions) post that was updated periodically, and included the group's definition of &quot;polyamory&quot;. The 1997 version,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.faqs.org/faqs/polyamory/faq/ Faqs.org]&lt;/ref&gt; which has been archived online, contains this definition:
{{quote|Polyamory means &quot;loving more than one&quot;.  This love may be sexual, emotional, spiritual, or any combination thereof, according to the desires and agreements of the individuals involved, but you needn't wear yourself out trying to figure out ways to fit fondness for apple pie, or filial piety, or a passion for the Saint Paul Saints baseball club into it. &quot;Polyamorous&quot; is also used as a descriptive term by people who are open to more than one relationship even if they are not currently involved in more than one. (Heck, some are involved in less than one.)  Some people think the definition is a bit loose, but it's got to be fairly roomy to fit the wide range of poly arrangements out there.|url=http://www.faqs.org/faqs/polyamory/faq/}}

In 1999, Zell-Ravenheart was asked by the editor of the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' to provide a definition of the term (which the dictionary had not yet recognized; the words &quot;polyamory, -ous, and -ist&quot; were added to the OED in 2006&lt;ref name=&quot;oed.com&quot;/&gt;). On their website, the Ravenhearts shared their submission to the OED, which follows:

{{quote|The practice, state or ability of having more than one sexual loving relationship at the same time, with the full knowledge and consent of all partners involved.|}}

The Ravenhearts then further explained their views on the above definition:

{{quote|This term was meant to be inclusive, and in that context, we have never intended to particularly exclude “swinging” per se, if practitioners thereof wished to adopt the term and include themselves. As far as we have understood, swinging specifically does not involve “cheating,” and it certainly does involve having “multiple lovers”! Moreover, we understand from speaking with a few swinging activists that many swingers are closely bonded with their various lovers, as best friends and regular partners.

The two essential ingredients of the concept of “polyamory” are “more than one;” and “loving.” That is, it is expected that the people in such relationships have a loving emotional bond, are involved in each other's lives multi-dimensionally, and care for each other. This term is not intended to apply to merely casual recreational sex, anonymous orgies, one-night stands, pick-ups, prostitution, “cheating,” serial monogamy, or the popular definition of swinging as “mate-swapping” parties.

Polyamory is about truthful communication with all concerned parties, loving intent, erotic meeting, and inclusivity (as opposed to the exclusivity of monogamy and monamory). On the basis of our own personal friendships with a few participants in the very large, diverse groundswell of human energy sometimes called the “Swinger’s Movement,” many—perhaps most—self-identified “swingers” do seem to fulfill our criteria of being polyamorous.

However, Ryam Nearing of [[Loving More]] says: “In all my talks with swingers it seems that the traditional (and most widespread) way of swinging is not polyamory as it is primarily sexual and specifically not relationship oriented. Some swingers and some locals allow for/choose more emotional connection, but they are the exception rather than the rule.”|Ravenhearts FAQ on Polyamory&lt;ref name=&quot;Web Archive of the Ravenhearts' Poly FAQ&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|author=The Ravenhearts |title=Frequently Asked Questions re: Polyamory |url=http://web.archive.org/web/20090225083604/http://www.mithrilstar.org/Polyamory-FAQ-Ravenhearts.htm |accessdate=2011-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The terms ''primary'' (or ''primary relationship(s)'') and ''secondary'' (or ''secondary relationship(s)'') are often used to indicate a hierarchy of different relationships or the place of each relationship in a person's life. Thus, a woman with a husband and an additional partner might refer to her husband as her &quot;primary,&quot; and a lover whom she only sees once a week as her &quot;secondary,&quot; in order to differentiate to the listener who is who. Some polyamorous people use such labels as a tool to manage multiple relationships, while others believe that all partners deserve equal standing and consideration and that a hierarchy is insulting to the people involved. Another model, sometimes referred to as an ''intimate network'', includes relationships that are of varying significance to the people involved, but are not explicitly labeled as &quot;primary&quot; or &quot;secondary.&quot; Within this model, a hierarchy may be fluid and vague, or nonexistent.

==Symbols of polyamory==

Although people who are polyamorous have adopted a number of symbols, none has universal recognition. The most common symbol is the red and white [[Heart (symbol)|heart]] ([[:wikt:♥|♥]]) combined with the blue [[infinity symbol]] ([[:wikt:∞|∞]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;ILIC&quot;/&gt; The colors often vary.

[[File:Polyamory-flag.svg|thumb|right|The Jim Evans poly pride flag.&lt;ref name=&quot;ILIC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Poly flag&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.isomedia.com/homes/jene/flag.html |title=Jim Evans' Polyamory Pride Flag |accessdate=2006-02-08 |last=Evans |first=Jim |date=1999-07-06 |work=ISOMEDIA - Business Solutions from Internet to eMedia |publisher=ISOMEDIA, INC. |pages=1 |quote=The poly pride flag consists of three equal horizontal colored stripes with a symbol in the center of the flag. The colors of the stripes, from top to bottom, are as follows: blue, representing the openness and honesty among all partners with which we conduct our multiple relationships; red, representing love and passion; and black, representing solidarity with those who, though they are open and honest with all participants of their relationships, must hide those relationships from the outside world due to societal pressures. The symbol in the center of the flag is a gold Greek lowercase letter '{{lang|el-Latn|pi}}', as the first letter of 'polyamory'. The letter's gold color represents the value that we place on the emotional attachment to others, be the relationship friendly or romantic in nature, as opposed to merely primarily physical relationships. This design is in the public domain. If you decide to use it, credit to Jim Evans would be nice, but is not required.}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The ''poly pride flag'' consists of three equal horizontal colored stripes with a symbol in the center of the flag. The colors of the stripes, from top to bottom, are as follows:
* Blue - The openness and honesty among all partners.
* Red - Love and passion.
* Black - Solidarity with those who must hide their relationships due to social pressures.
The symbol in the center of the flag is a gold Greek lowercase letter &quot;{{lang|el-Latn|''[[Pi (letter)|pi]]''}}&quot; ({{lang|el|[[wikt:π|π]]}}), as the first letter of &quot;polyamory&quot;. The letter's gold color represents the value that people who are polyamorous place on the emotional attachment to others, be the relationship friendly or romantic in nature, as opposed to merely primarily physical relationships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poly flag&quot;/&gt;

[[File:polyrib.gif|thumb|right|PAARC ribbon. The color scheme of the flag was adapted (with permission) for use in the ''Polyamory Awareness and Acceptance Ribbon Campaign''.]]

[[File:ILIC symbol.gif|thumb|right|The symbol of &quot;Infinite Love in Infinite Combinations&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ILIC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Poly flag&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.isomedia.com/homes/jene/flag.html |title=Jim Evans' Polyamory Pride Flag |accessdate=2006-02-08 |last=Evans |first=Jim |date=1999-07-06 |work=ISOMEDIA - Business Solutions from Internet to eMedia |publisher=ISOMEDIA, INC. |pages=1 |quote=The poly pride flag consists of three equal horizontal colored stripes with a symbol in the center of the flag. The colors of the stripes, from top to bottom, are as follows: blue, representing the openness and honesty among all partners with which we conduct our multiple relationships; red, representing love and passion; and black, representing solidarity with those who, though they are open and honest with all participants of their relationships, must hide those relationships from the outside world due to societal pressures. The symbol in the center of the flag is a gold Greek lowercase letter 'pi', as the first letter of 'polyamory'. The letter's gold color represents the value that we place on the emotional attachment to others, be the relationship friendly or romantic in nature, as opposed to merely primarily physical relationships. This design is in the public domain. If you decide to use it, credit to Jim Evans would be nice, but is not required.}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The symbol of ''ILIC (Infinite Love in Infinite Combinations)'' is a reference to the ''[[Star Trek]]'' ''kol-ut-shan'' or symbol of philosophy of [[Vulcan IDIC]] (Infinite Diversity in Infinite Combinations).&lt;ref name=&quot;ILIC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|people=[[Terry Windell]] (Director) [[Tim Russ]] (Actor: [[Tuvok]]) |date=1999-02-03 |title=&lt;!-- Do not move any apostrophes ('). --&gt; '''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'' &quot;[[Gravity (Star Trek: Voyager)|Gravity]]&quot;' |medium=[[Production company|Television production]] |publisher=[[Paramount Pictures]] |location=Los Angeles, California |quote=''kol-ut-shan''}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a variation on Pi-and-the-three-colors from the [[Polyamory#Symbols of polyamory|Polyamory Pride Flag]] by Jim Evans. Like the flag, the colors are: blue, representing the openness and honesty among all partners with which people who are polyamorous conduct their multiple relationships; red, representing love and passion; and black, representing solidarity with those who, though they are open and honest with all participants of their relationships, must hide those relationships from the outside world due to societal pressures. A gold Greek lowercase letter &quot;{{lang|el-Latn|''[[Pi (letter)|pi]]''}}&quot; ({{lang|el|[[:wikt:π|π]]}}), as the first letter of &quot;polyamory&quot;, represents the value that people who are polyamorous place on the emotional attachment to others, be the relationship friendly or romantic in nature, as opposed to merely primarily physical relationships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poly flag&quot;/&gt; The most common symbol that people who are polyamorous have adopted is the heart symbol combined with the [[infinity]] sign ([[:wikt:∞|∞]]) that the ILIC symbol also uses.&lt;ref name=&quot;ILIC&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Parrot polyamory mascot.gif|thumb|right|Ray Dillinger's ''Poly Parrot''.&lt;ref name=&quot;poly parrot&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.polyamory.org/ |title=alt.polyamory home page |accessdate=2007-10-09 |last=Dillinger |first=Ray |date=1997-06-08|quote=Parrot graphic by Ray Dillinger, placed in the public domain for use as a poly mascot.}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Another is the image of a [[parrot]], since &quot;Polly&quot; is a common name for these birds.&lt;ref name=&quot;poly parrot&quot;/&gt; PolyOz states in its polyamory glossary that &quot;The parrot is a common poly &quot;mascot&quot; or symbol. Punning on 'poly wanna X'&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;PolyOz&quot;&gt;PolyOz states in its [http://polyoz.scm-rpg.com.au/postnuke2/index.php?module=ContentExpress&amp;func=display&amp;ceid=8&amp;meid=-1 polyamory glossary] that &quot;The parrot is a common poly &quot;mascot&quot; or symbol. Punning on 'poly wanna X'&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; A 2003 article in ''[[The Guardian]]'' states &quot;Today America has more than 100 poly email lists and support groups. Their emblem, which marks the table when they meet in restaurants, is the parrot (because of their nickname Polly).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian&quot;&gt;A 2003 [http://www.guardian.co.uk/women/story/0,3604,1085003,00.html article] in ''[[The Guardian]]'' states &quot;Today America has more than 100 poly email lists and support groups. Their emblem, which marks the table when they meet in restaurants, is the parrot (because of their nickname Polly).&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Author Mystic Life describes this symbol an ironic reference to parrots' monogamy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spiritual&quot;&gt;Mystic Life (December 2003) in [http://www.spiritualpolyamory.com/ &quot;Spiritual Polyamory&quot;] ISBN 978-0-595-30541-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowley&quot;&gt;Rowley I(1997) &quot;Family Cacatuidae (Cockatoos)&quot; in ''[[Handbook of the Birds of the World]] Volume 4; Sandgrouse to Cuckoos'' (eds del Hoyo J, Elliott A, Sargatal J) Lynx Edicions:Barcelona. ISBN 84-87334-22-9&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Polymory Möbius Triangle.svg|thumb|right|Joreth InnKeeper's ''Purple Mobius''.&lt;ref name=&quot;purple mobius&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://sites.google.com/site/orlandopoly/symbol |title=OrlandoPoly What Is That Weird Purple Thing? |quote=Purple Mobius symbol placed in the public domain for an abstract symbol for polyamory}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The ''Purple Mobius symbol'' was created to provide an abstract symbol for the poly community, which had some disagreements over the use of the heart/infinity, the parrot, and the pi-flag. It was intended to be a neutral symbol that referenced all the civil and social rights groups that came before, by alluding to the color and shape of related movements, such as the Gay Rights movement, the lesbian/feminist movement, the bisexual community, and the BDSM community, as well as making a nodding reference to the heart/infinity symbol (the infinity symbol being another example of a Mobius Strip).&lt;ref name=&quot;purple mobius&quot;/&gt;

==Forms of polyamory==
{{Main|Non-monogamy}}
Forms of polyamory include:
* [[Polyfidelity]], which involves multiple romantic relationships with sexual contact restricted to only specific partners in the group (which may include all members of that group) (e.g. [[group marriage]]).
* Sub-relationships, which distinguish between [[primary and secondary (relationship)|&quot;primary&quot; and &quot;secondary&quot; relationships]] (e.g. most [[open marriage]]s). In 1906 [[H.G. Wells]] presented a defense of this sort of polyamory in a utopian novel entitled [[In the Days of the Comet]].
* Three people romantically involved, often called a &quot;triad relationship.&quot; (Commonly initiated by an established couple jointly dating a third person; however, there are many possible configurations.)
* Relationships between a couple and another couple ([[Foursome (group sex)|Quad]]).
* [[Polygamy]] ([[polygyny]] and [[polyandry]]), in which one person [[marriage|marries]] several spouses (who may or may not be married to, or have romantic relationships with, one another).
* Group relationships, sometimes referred to as tribes, and [[group marriage]], in which all consider themselves associated to one another, popularized to some extent by [[Robert A. Heinlein]] (in novels such as ''[[Stranger in a Strange Land]]'', ''[[Time Enough for Love]]'', ''[[Friday (novel)|Friday]]'', and ''[[The Moon Is a Harsh Mistress]]''). Also works by [[Robert Rimmer]], and [[Starhawk]] in her books ''[[The Fifth Sacred Thing]]'' (1993) and ''Walking to Mercury'' (1997). A domestic partnership consisting of four people who are all married to each other features in [[Vonda N. McIntyre]]'s ''Starfarers'' series.
* Networks of interconnecting relationships, where a particular person may have relationships of varying degrees of importance with various people.
* Mono/poly relationships, where one partner is monogamous but agrees to the other having outside relationships.
* So-called &quot;geometric&quot; arrangements, which are described by the number of people involved and their relationship connections. Examples include &quot;triads&quot; and &quot;quads&quot;, along with &quot;V&quot; (or &quot;Vee&quot;) and &quot;N&quot; geometries. (See: [[Terminology within polyamory]].)
* [[Open relationship]]s/[[open marriage]]s, where participants may have sexual liaisons with others not within their core group of partners. Some open relationships may be open only sexually, while exclusive emotionally.
* [[Swinging]]:  Traditionally there has been a cultural divide between the polyamorous and swinger communities, the former emphasizing the emotional aspects of plural relationships and the latter emphasizing the sexual activities of non-monogamy. It is possible for a person with polyamorous relationships to also engage in traditional [[swinging]] and other open relationships. Those in polyamorous relationships who take part in casual sex often see it as separate from the emotional bonds they share with their polyamorous partners.  However it is also possible for swingers to develop deep emotional attachments with those they have sex with, and thereby find themselves in polyamory.  Such swingers in their new polyamorous relationships may or may not choose to continue swinging with others.  Finally, both swingers and polyamorous people can engage in secret infidelities, but this is no better accepted by either communities than in monogamy.

==Cultural diversity within polyamory==

&quot;Polygamy&quot; is more often used to refer to codified forms of multiple marriage (especially those with a traditional/religious basis), while &quot;modern polyamory&quot; or &quot;egalitarian polyamory&quot; implies a relationship defined by negotiation between its members, rather than by cultural norms. Egalitarian polyamory is culturally rooted in such concepts as choice and individuality, rather than in religious traditions.

Egalitarian polyamory is more closely associated with values, subcultures and ideologies that favor individual freedoms and equality in sexual matters – most notably, those reflected by sexual freedom advocacy groups such as [[Woodhull Freedom Foundation &amp; Federation]], [[National Coalition for Sexual Freedom]] and [[American Civil Liberties Union]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acluutah.org/pluralmarriage.htm Acluutah.org]&lt;/ref&gt; However, polygamy advocacy groups and activists and egalitarian polyamory advocacy groups and activists can and do work together cooperatively. In addition, the two sub-communities have many common issues (poly parenting, dealing with jealousy, legal and social discrimination, etc.), the discussion and resolution of which are of equal interest to both sub-communities, regardless of any cultural differences that may exist. Moreover, there is considerable cultural diversity within both sub-communities. Religiously motivated polygamy has its [[Islamic]], [[Mormon fundamentalist]], [[Christian Plural Marriage]], [[Jewish]]&lt;ref&gt;Broward County Jewish Journal, Thursday, May 29, 2008, p. 16, Polygamy and the Right of Privacy, Rabbi Bruce S. Warshal, Publisher Emeritus: &quot;polygamy [...] happens to be legal under halachic rabbinic Judaism and appears throughout the bible&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and other varieties; similarly, some egalitarian polyamorists have cultural ties to [[Naturism]], [[Neopaganism|Neo-Pagans]],&lt;ref&gt;From PolyOz glossary on the book ''[[Stranger in a Strange Land]]'' which &quot;served as an inspiration to many poly folks before the term &quot;polyamory&quot; was even invented&amp;nbsp;... also inspired the Neopagan Church of All Worlds, which has been a long-term poly hotbed&quot; [http://polyoz.scm-rpg.com.au/postnuke2/index.php?module=ContentExpress&amp;func=display&amp;ceid=8&amp;meid=-1 Scm-rpg.com]&lt;/ref&gt; [[BDSM]], Modern [[Tantra]],&lt;ref&gt;[[OneTaste]]&lt;/ref&gt; and other special interest groups. For example, egalitarian polyamory and [[BDSM]] often face similar challenges (e.g. negotiating the ground rules for unconventional relationships, or the question of [[coming out]] to family and friends), and the [[cross-pollination]] of ideas takes place between the two.&lt;ref&gt;For instance, [[Dossie Easton]] and [[Janet Hardy]], co-authors of ''[[The Ethical Slut]]'', are equally well-known as authors on BDSM; in the introduction to ''The New Bottoming Book'', Hardy describes herself as &quot;a standard-issue Northern California bisexual polyamorous [[switch (sexuality)|switch]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal status==
[[File:Polyamory pride in San Francisco 2004.jpg‎|thumb|right|Start of polyamory contingent at [[San Francisco Pride]] 2004]]
In most countries, it is legal for three or more people to form and share a sexual relationship (subject sometimes to laws against [[homosexuality]]). However, no Western countries permit ''marriage'' among more than two people. Nor do they give strong and equal legal protection (e.g., of rights relating to children) to non-married partners – the legal regime is not comparable to that applied to married couples. Individuals involved in polyamorous relationships are considered by the law to be no different from people who live together, or &quot;date&quot;, under other circumstances.

In many jurisdictions where lesbian and gay couples can access [[civil unions]] or [[registered partnerships]], these are often intended as parallel institutions to that of heterosexual monogamous marriage. Accordingly, they include parallel entitlements, obligations, and limitations. Amongst the latter, as in the case of the New Zealand Civil Union Act 2005, there are parallel prohibitions on civil unions with more than one partner, which is considered bigamy, or dual marriage/civil union hybrids with more than one person. Both are banned under Sections 205-206 of the Crimes Act 1961. In jurisdictions where [[same-sex marriage]] proper exists, bigamous same-sex marriages fall under the same set of legal prohibitions as bigamous heterosexual marriages. As of yet, there is no case law applicable to these issues.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Webb ''et al.'' (eds) Butterworths Guide to Family Law in New Zealand: (13th Edition): Wellington: Lexis/Nexis: 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bigamy]] is the act of marrying one person while already being married to another, and is legally prohibited in most countries where monogamy is the cultural norm. Some bigamy statutes are broad enough to potentially encompass polyamorous relationships involving [[cohabitation]], even if none of the participants claim marriage to more than one partner. For instance, under Utah Code 76-7-101, &quot;A person is guilty of bigamy when, knowing he has a husband or wife or knowing the other person has a husband or wife, the person purports to marry another person ''or cohabits with another person''.&quot;

Having multiple non-marital partners, even if married to one, is legal in most U.S. jurisdictions; at most it constitutes grounds for [[divorce]] if the spouse is non-consenting, or feels that the interest in a further partner has destabilized the marriage. In jurisdictions where civil unions or registered partnerships are recognized, the same principle applies to divorce in those contexts. There are exceptions to this: in [[North Carolina]], a spouse can sue a third party for causing &quot;loss of affection&quot; in or &quot;criminal conversation&quot; ([[adultery]]) with their spouse,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aoc.state.nc.us/www/public/coa/opinions/2001/010003-1.htm RUBY DEATON PHARR, Plaintiff, v. JOYCE W. BECK, Defendant]&lt;/ref&gt; and more than twenty states in the US have laws against adultery&lt;ref&gt;[http://writ.news.findlaw.com/grossman/20031216.html Punishing Adultery in Virginia] by Joanna Grossman&lt;/ref&gt; although they are infrequently enforced. Some states were prompted to review their laws criminalizing consensual sexual activity in the wake of the Supreme Court's ruling in ''[[Lawrence v. Texas]]''. Some {{Citation needed|date=October 2010}} social conservatives hold that the reading of Justice Kennedy's opinion in ''Lawrence'' is that states may not constitutionally burden any private, consensual sexual activity between adults. Such a reading would throw laws against fornication, adultery, and even adult incest into question.

New Jersey's 2004 Domestic Partnership Act could in theory be used to legally connect more than two persons (albeit imperfectly), perhaps using a combination of marriage and [[domestic partnership]]. However, no case law in support of this theory yet exists.

At present, the extension to multiple-partner relationships of laws that use a criterion similar to that adopted in the [[United Kingdom|UK]], i.e., &quot;married ''or living together as married''&quot; remains largely untested. That is, it is not known whether these laws could treat some trios or larger groups as [[common-law marriage]]s.

If marriage is intended, most countries provide for both a religious marriage and a civil ceremony (sometimes combined). These recognize and formalize the relationship. Few Western countries give either religious or legal recognition – or permission – to marriages with three or more partners. While a recent case in the [[Netherlands]] was commonly read as demonstrating that Dutch law permitted multiple-partner [[civil union]]s,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brusselsjournal.com/node/301 First Trio &quot;Married&quot; in The Netherlands] by Paul Belien, Brussels Journal Online&lt;/ref&gt; this belief is mistaken. The relationship in question was a ''[[:nl:samenlevingscontract|samenlevingscontract]]'', or &quot;cohabitation contract&quot;, and not a registered partnership or marriage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.refdag.nl/artikel/1230743/&amp;bdquo%3BHuwelijk+wordt+steeds+verder+opgerekt&amp;rdquo%3B.html Dutch-language source]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/006/494pqobc.asp?pg=2 English-language source]&lt;/ref&gt; The Netherlands' law concerning registered partnerships provides that:
#A person may be involved in one only registered partnership with one other person whether of the same or of opposite sex at any one time.
#Persons who enter into a registered partnership may not at the same time be married.

When a relationship ends, non-consensual infidelity (&quot;[[infidelity|cheating]]&quot;) is often grounds for an unfavorable [[divorce]] settlement, and infidelity generally could easily be seized upon as a prejudicial issue by an antagonistic partner.

A detailed legal theory of polyamorous marriage is being developed.  The &quot;dyadic networks&quot; model&lt;ref&gt;Polyamory in the twenty-first century: love and intimacy with multiple partners (Google eBook) by Deborah Anapol, pp. 181-182 http://books.google.com/books?id=BkhLnjvweL8C&amp;pg=PA181&amp;lpg=PA181&amp;dq=%22dyadic+networks&lt;/ref&gt; calls for the revision of existing laws against bigamy to permit married persons to enter into additional marriages, provided that they have first given legal notice to their existing marital partner(s).

==Polyamory as a practice==
Separate from polyamory as a philosophical basis for relationship, are the practical ways in which people who live polyamorously arrange their lives and handle certain issues, as compared to those of a generally more socially acceptable monogamous arrangement.

===Values within polyamory===
{{Main|Values within polyamory}}

* '''Fidelity and loyalty:''' Many polyamorists define ''fidelity'' not as sexual exclusivity, but as faithfulness to the promises and agreements made about a relationship. A secret sexual relationship that violates those accords would be seen as a breach of fidelity. Polyamorists generally base definitions of ''commitment'' on considerations other than sexual exclusivity, e.g. &quot;trust and honesty&quot; or &quot;growing old together&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|first=Elaine |last=Cook |title=Commitment in Polyamorous Relationships |url=http://www.aphroweb.net/papers/thesis/index.htm |year=2005 |accessdate=2006-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Communication and negotiation:''' Because there is no &quot;standard model&quot; for polyamorous relationships, and reliance upon common expectations may not be realistic, polyamorists often advocate explicitly negotiating with all involved to establish the terms of their relationships, and often emphasize that this should be an ongoing process of honest communication and respect. Polyamorists will usually take a pragmatic approach to their relationships; many accept that sometimes they and their partners will make mistakes and fail to live up to these ideals, and that communication is important for repairing any breaches.&lt;ref name=&quot;polyoz_values&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;s.org&quot; /&gt;

* '''Trust, honesty, dignity, and respect:''' Most polyamorists emphasize respect, trust, and honesty for all partners.&lt;ref name=&quot;polyoz_values&quot;&gt;From PolyOz glossary: &quot;Not in the [linguistic roots of the term] but very important is the commitment to honesty with all partners, and openly negotiated ground rules.&quot; [http://polyoz.scm-rpg.com.au/postnuke2/index.php?module=ContentExpress&amp;func=display&amp;ceid=8&amp;meid=-1 Scm-rpg.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;s.org&quot;&gt;From [http://www.sexuality.org/book/ sexuality.org]: &quot;Two of the cultural cornerstones of the polyamory community are honesty and communication: it's expected that you and your existing long-term partner(s) will have talked over what you're comfortable with and what you aren't comfortable with, and that nobody is going around behind anyone else's back.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Ideally, a partner's partners are accepted as part of that person's life rather than merely tolerated, and usually a relationship that requires deception or a &quot;don't ask don't tell&quot; policy is seen as a less than ideal model.

* '''Boundaries and agreements:''' Poly relationships often involve negotiating agreements, and establishing specific boundaries, or &quot;ground rules&quot;; such agreements vary widely and may change over time, but could include, for example: consultation about new relationships; devising schedules that work for everyone; limits on physical displays of affection in public or among mixed company; and budgeting the amount of money a partner can spend on additional partners.

*'''Gender equality:''' Many polyamorists do not believe in different relationship &quot;rules&quot; based on gender, a point of contrast with some forms of religious non-monogamy which are often patriarchically based. Commonly, however, couples first expanding an existing monogamous relationship into a polyamorous one, may adhere to gender-specific boundaries until all parties are comfortable with the new dynamic, such as when a wife agrees not to engage sexually with another male at her husband's request, but may be allowed to have romantic and sexual relationships with women.  Such terms and boundaries are negotiable, and such [[symmetry|asymmetric]] degrees of freedom among the partners (who need not be of different genders) are more often due to individual differences and needs, and are usually understood to be temporary and within a negotiated time frame until further opening up of the relationship becomes practicable or easier for the parties to handle emotionally.

* '''Non-possessiveness:''' Many polyamorists view excessive restrictions on other deep relationships as less than desirable, as such restrictions can be used to replace trust with a framework of ownership and control. It is usually preferred or encouraged that a polyamorist strive to view their partners' other significant others (often referred to as OSOs) in terms of the gain to their partners' lives rather than a threat to their own (see [[compersion]]). Therefore, jealousy and possessiveness are generally viewed not so much as something to avoid or structure the relationships around, but as responses that should be explored, understood, and resolved within each individual, with compersion as a goal.

===Sharing of domestic burden===

Claimed benefits of a polyamorous relationship include the following:&lt;ref&gt;PolyamoryOnline ''[http://www.polyamoryonline.org/articles/polyamoury_101.html Polyamory 101]: Consensual Non-Monogamy for the 21st Century'' &quot;In a polyamourous relationship, this ['A burden shared is a burden lessened'] is doubly true. If you are having problems with one of the people in the relationship, often you can talk to another participant about it, with the added advantage of having a confidant with a good perspective on the relationship. When one person has problems, everyone else is there to help them through it. Child rearing benefits greatly in a polyamourous setting as well. Children are exposed to a wide range of viewpoints and experiences. To use a personal example, children raised in my Family&amp;nbsp;... are exposed to my experiences growing up in rural Illinois, two of our Family's childhoods in the city of Chicago, and my fiancee's childhood in South Carolina. Perhaps one day we will have a Family member from outside the United States, offering an entirely different perspective. This also makes it easier to supervise a child. When many people live in the same household, they can take turns supervising the children, offering the rest of the members of the household a chance to catch up on chores, do homework, or simply go out for a while. Try doing that in a two-parent household without paying for a babysitter. On a purely practical note, having ten incomes in a household is much more flexible than just two. If one of the family suffers a loss of income, the others can help to make up for it. It is much easier to get by after losing one tenth of household income than it is after losing one half. Expenses are also significantly reduced in a polyamourous household, as they are in any situation when multiple adults occupy the same house.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ability of parties to discuss issues with multiple partners has the potential to add mediation and stabilization to a relationship, and to reduce polarization of viewpoints.
* Emotional support and structure provided by other committed adults within the family unit.
* A wider range of experience, skills, resources, and perspectives that multiple adults bring to a family dynamic.
* The ability to share chores and child supervision, reducing domestic and child rearing pressure upon adults' time without needing to pay for outside child caregivers.
* Greatly reduced ''per capita'' cost of living.
* Increased financial stability; the loss of one income is not the entirety of the family income (if only one parent works), or half the family income (if both parents work), but may be far less.

===Specific issues affecting polyamorous relationships===

Polyamorists cite the human tendency towards [[jealousy]] and possessiveness as major hurdles in polyamory, and also as personal limitations to overcome:&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian1&quot; /&gt;
{{quote|Possessiveness can be a major stumbling block, and often it prevents what could be a successful polyamourous relationship from forming. When people are viewed, even inadvertently, as possessions, they become a commodity, a valuable one at that. Just as most people are reluctant to let go of what little money that they have, people are also reluctant to &quot;share&quot; their beloved. After all, what if [their beloved] finds someone else who is more attractive/intelligent/well-liked/successful/etc.. than [themselves], and decides to abandon the relationship in favor of the new lover? These sorts of feelings act as inferiority complexes inside of polyamorous relationships and must be resolved, completely, before a polyamorous relationship can be truly successful.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.polyamoryonline.org/poly101.html Poly 101]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

An editorial article on the polyamory website ''Polyamoryonline.org'' proposed in 2006 the following issues as being worthy of specific coverage and attention:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.polyamoryonline.org/ready.html A few insights (FAQ)]&lt;/ref&gt;
:* Helping children cope with &quot;being different.&quot;
:* &quot;[[Coming out]]&quot; as polyamorous (and explaining polyamory) to children.
:* Polyamorous parental interactions.
:* Polyamory social settings (involving children).
:* Legal (parenting) issues.
The author, herself part of a polyamorous relationship with two other adults, comments that:
{{quote|The kids started realizing that there were three adults in the house that they had to answer to. **Big Shock** Then came the onslaught of trying to 'befriend' a particular adult and get what they wanted from that one adult. Another big shock when they found that it didn't work and that we all communicated about wants or needs of any given child. After this was established, we sort of fell into our patterns of school, practices, just normal life in general. The kids all started realizing that there were three of us to care for them when they were sick, three of us to get scolded from, hugs from, tickles from; three of us to feed the small army of mouths and three of us to trust completely in. After trust was established, they asked more questions. Why do we have to live together? Why can't I have my own room?&amp;nbsp;... Why do you guys love each other? Why do I have to listen to them (non-biological parent)? We answered them as truthfully as we could and as much as was appropriate for their age. I found that it was more unnerving for me to think about how to approach a new kid and their parents than it ever was for the kids.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}}}

===Polyamory in a same-sex setting===

Gay psychotherapist [[Michael Shernoff]] wrote that non-monogamy is &quot;a well-accepted part of [[gay subculture]],&quot; although &quot;often viewed by some therapists as problematic,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Michael Shernoff]], [[Family Process (journal)|Family Process]], Vol.45 No.4, 2006 [http://www.familyprocess.org/Data/featured_articles/65_shernoff.pdf Familyprocess.org])&lt;/ref&gt; and that somewhere between 30%&lt;!-- ie 100% less 70%!!! --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;70% of men in male couples reported being in a monogamous relationship&quot; - Campbell, 2000 (cited by Michael Shernoff, Family Process, Vol.45 No.4, 2006 [http://www.familyprocess.org/Data/featured_articles/65_shernoff.pdf Familyprocess.org])&lt;/ref&gt; and 67%&lt;!-- ie 100% less &quot;approximately one third&quot;!!! --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;and that &quot;approximately one third of male couples are sexually exclusive&quot; - Bryant &amp; Demian, 1994; Wagner et al., 2000; Advocate Sex Poll, 2002; LaSala, 2004 (cited by Michael Shernoff, Family Process, Vol.45 No.4, 2006 [http://www.familyprocess.org/Data/featured_articles/65_shernoff.pdf Familyprocess.com])&lt;/ref&gt; of men in male couples reported being in a sexually non-monogamous relationship. According to Eli Coleman &amp; B. R. Simon Rosser (1996), &quot;although a majority of male couples are not sexually exclusive, they are in fact emotionally monogamous.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cited by Michael Shernoff, Family Process, Vol.45 No.4, 2006 [http://www.familyprocess.org/Data/featured_articles/65_shernoff.pdf Familyprocess.org])&lt;/ref&gt; Shernoff states that:

{{quote|One of the biggest differences between male couples and mixed-sex couples is that many, but by no means all, within the gay community have an easier acceptance of sexual nonexclusivity than does heterosexual society in general.&amp;nbsp;... Research confirms that nonmonogamy in and of itself does not create a problem for male couples when it has been openly negotiated.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Shernoff, Family Process, Vol.45 No.4, 2006 [http://www.familyprocess.org/Data/featured_articles/65_shernoff.pdf Familyprocess.org])&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In practice, most discussion of lesbian and gay polyamory occurs primarily within the context of relationship ethics. It should be noted that there is a broad spectrum of partner numerical and frequency profiles amongst lesbians and gay men, so that polyamorous ethical debates may be undertaken, but most legislative effort is expended on legal recognition of same-sex couples, whether through [[civil unions]], [[registered partnerships]] or [[same-sex marriage]] proper. As yet, there is no movement for lesbian/gay 'polyamorists rights' akin to that for same-sex marriage or alternative forms of legal relationship recognition.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example Marcia Munson and Judith Kiernan (eds) A Lesbian Polyamory Reader: New York: Haworth Press: 1999: ISBN 1-56023-120-3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Polyamory and parenting===

Many polyamorists have children, either within the relationship(s) or from previous relationships. Like other elements of polyamory, the way in which children are integrated into the family structure varies widely. Some possibilities are:

* Parents are primarily responsible for their own children (biological, adoptive, or step-), but other members of the relationship act as an [[extended family]], providing assistance in child-rearing.
* Adults raise children collectively, all taking equal responsibility for each child regardless of [[consanguinity]].
* Parents are wholly responsible for their own children, with other members of the relationship relating to the children as friends of the parents.
* Children treat parents' partners as a form of [[Stepfamily|stepparent]] or are told to think of them as aunts and uncles.

The choice of structures is affected by timing: an adult who has been present throughout a child's life is likely to have a more parental relationship with that child than one who enters a relationship with people who already have a teenage child. (The issues involved often parallel those of step-parenting.) The degree of logistical and emotional involvement between the members of the relationship is also important: a close-knit triad already living under one roof with shared finances is far more likely to take a collective approach to parenting than would a larger, loose-knit group with separate living arrangements:

{{quote|Some poly families are structured so that one parent can be home to care for the children while two or more other adults work outside the home and earn an income, thus providing a better standard of living for all concerned. More adult caretakers means more people available for child care, help with homework, and daily issues such as transportation to extracurricular activities. Children thrive on love. The more adults they have to love them who are part of the family, the happier and more well-adjusted they are. There is no evidence that growing up in a poly family is detrimental to the physical, psychological or moral well being of children. If parents are happy in their intimate relationships, it helps the family. Happy families are good for children.&lt;ref name=&quot;online&quot;&gt;[http://www.polyamoryonline.org/ready.html Polyamory Online].&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Whether children are fully informed of the nature of their parents' relationship varies, according to the above considerations and also to whether the parents are &quot;[[coming out|out]]&quot; to other adults.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

In one possible case indicative of the law related to parenting and polyamory in the United States, the Pennsylvania State Supreme Court in 2006 voted 5-1 that a father in a custody case had the right to teach his child (age 13) about polygamy (and hence possibly by implication about other multiple partner relationships), and that this right &quot;trumped&quot; the anti-bigamy and other laws which might apply and was not deemed inherently harmful to the child. (Note: this decision was made in the context of religious freedom, but religious freedom would not apply if there was harm to the child.)&lt;ref&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/data2/pennsylvaniastatecases/supreme/j-97-2004mo.pdf Shepp v. Shepp, J-97-2004], 2006, PA supreme court. The opinion stated that: the state's interest in enforcing the anti-bigamy law &quot;is not an interest of the 'highest order&quot;' that would trump a parent's right to tell a child about deeply held religious beliefs, and that a court may prohibit a parent from advocating religious beliefs that amount to a crime if doing so jeopardizes the child's physical or mental health or safety, or potentially creates significant social burdens, but that in this case it was not felt that discussing multiple partner relationships as a parents' preference or presenting or advocating them as desirable to the parent, was harmful.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Custody ramifications====

Parents involved in polyamorous relationships often keep it a secret because of the risk that it will be used by an ex-spouse, or other family member, as grounds to deprive them of custody of and/or access to their children. The fear is that it will be used in family disputes much as [[homosexuality]] has been used in the past.

In 1998, a [[Tennessee]] court granted guardianship of a child to her grandmother and step-grandfather after the child's mother [[April Divilbiss]] and partners [[outing|outed]] themselves as polyamorous on [[MTV]]. After contesting the decision for two years, Divilbiss eventually agreed to relinquish her daughter, acknowledging that she was unable to adequately care for her child and that this, rather than her polyamory, had been the grandparents' real motivation in seeking custody.&lt;ref name=&quot;society&quot;&gt;[http://www.polyamorysociety.org/Divilbiss_Families_Case_Ends.html Divilbiss Families Case Ends], Polyamory Society].&lt;/ref&gt; The Tennessee case is not necessarily normative for the entirety of the United States, since family law varies significantly from state to state. US state law is, of course, not normative for laws of other countries.

==Geographical and cultural differences==
Social views on polyamory vary by country and culture. For example, a 2003 article in ''The Guardian'' by Helena Echlin argues that &quot;British people are if anything more tolerant than in America which is perhaps why British polys are less in need of support groups&quot;, and quotes a UK source as stating: &quot;We have a tradition of people minding their own business here. People might disapprove, but they won't try to mess up your life. In America, they might call social services.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian Women&quot;&gt;ECHLIN, Helena. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/women/story/0,3604,1085003,00.html Women], The Guardian, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Philosophical aspects==
As with many non-traditional life choices, there is considerable active discussion about philosophical approaches to polyamory.

In 1929, ''[[Marriage and Morals]]'', written by the [[philosopher]], [[mathematician]], and [[Nobel Prize]] winner [[Bertrand Russell]], offered a strong precedent to the philosophy of polyamory. At the time of publication, Russell's questioning of the Victorian notions of morality regarding sex and marriage prompted vigorous protests and denunciations, but several intellectuals, led by [[John Dewey]], spoke out against this treatment.&lt;ref name=&quot;SexEdPioneers&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Pioneers of Sex Education |url=http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/ATLAS_EN/html/pioneers_of_sex_education.html |author=Haeberle, Erwin J. |year=1983 |accessdate=2008-02-17 |publisher=The Continuum Publishing Company}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Denied&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Appointment Denied: The Inquisition of Bertrand Russell |author=Leberstein, Stephen |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3860/is_200111/ai_n9008065 |publisher=Academe |date=November/December 2001 |accessdate=2008-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Echlin's article in ''The Guardian'', six reasons for choosing polyamory are identified: a drive towards female independence and equality driven by [[feminism]]; disillusionment with monogamy; a yearning for community; honesty and realism in respect of relational nature of human beings; human nature; and individual non-matching of the traditional monogamous stereotype. Jim Fleckenstein, director of the Institute for 21st-Century Relationships, is quoted as stating that the polyamory movement has been driven not only by science fiction, but also by feminism: &quot;Increased financial independence means that women can build relationships the way they want to.&quot; The disillusionment with monogamy is said to be &quot;because of widespread cheating and divorce&quot;. The longing for community is associated with a felt need for the richness of &quot;complex and deep relationships through extended networks&quot; in response to the replacement and fragmentation of the [[extended family]] by [[nuclear family|nuclear families]]. &quot;For many,&quot; Echlin writes, &quot;it is a hankering for community&amp;nbsp;... we have become increasingly alienated, partly because of the 20th century's replacement of the extended family with the nuclear family. As a result, many of us are striving to create complex and deep relationships through extended networks of multiple lovers and extended families&amp;nbsp;... Polys agree that some people are monogamous by nature. But some of us are not, and more and more are refusing to be shoehorned into monogamy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Guardian Women&quot; /&gt;

Others speak of creating an &quot;honest responsible and socially acceptable&quot; version of non-monogamy – &quot;since so many people are already non-monogamous, why not develop a non-monogamy that is honest, responsible and socially acceptable?&amp;nbsp;... It seems weird that having affairs is OK but being upfront about it is rocking the boat&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Women's Infidelity by Michelle Langley (ISBN 0-9767726-0-4) Straight talk about why women choose non-monogamy, 2005 [http://womensinfidelity.com Womensinfidelity.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

A sixth reason, a couple's response to a failure of monogamy, by reaching a consensus to accept the additional relationship, is identified by other authors.&lt;ref&gt;Polyamory The New Love without Limits by Dr Deborah Anapol (ISBN 1-880789-08-6) has a chapter called &quot;Making the transition to polyamorous relating&quot;, which deals with broken monogamous commitments from both perspectives.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==
Research into polyamory has been limited. A comprehensive government study of sexual attitudes, behaviors and relationships in [[Finland]] in 1992 (age 18-75, around 50% both genders) found that around 200 out of 2250 (8.9%) respondents &quot;agreed or strongly agreed&quot; with the statement ''&quot;I could maintain several sexual relationships at the same time&quot;'' and 8.2% indicated a relationship type &quot;that best suits&quot; at the present stage of life would involve multiple partners. By contrast, when asked about other relationships at the same time as a steady relationship, around 17% stated they had had other partners whilst in a steady relationship (50% no, 17% yes, 33% refused to answer).
[http://www.fsd.uta.fi/english/data/catalogue/FSD1243/cbF1243e.pdf] (PDF)

British artist Connie Rose was the first to create a film about polyamory consisting of interviews around the world including polamory's leading academics, authors and sex experts, including Dossie Easton (coauthor of ''[[The Ethical Slut]]'') and Christopher Ryan (coauthor of ''[[Sex at Dawn]]''). Rose's film ''Questioning Monogamy'' was exhibited in London 2011 as an eight foot installation for 12 people to lay in with ten screens.

The article, ''What Psychology Professionals Should Know About Polyamory'', based on a paper presented at the 8th Annual Diversity Conference in March 1999 in [[Albany, New York]] states the following:

{{quote|While openly polyamorous relationships are relatively rare (Rubin, 1982), there are indications that private polyamorous arrangements within relationships are actually quite common. Blumstein and Schwartz (1983, cited in Rubin &amp; Adams, 1986) noted that of 3,574 married couples in their sample, 15-28% had an understanding that allows nonmonogamy under some circumstances. The percentages are higher among cohabitating couples (28%), lesbian couples (29%) and gay male couples (65%) (p. 312).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.polyamory.org/~joe/polypaper.htm#Demographic What Psychology Professionals Should Know About Polyamory]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Polyamory in a clinical setting===
There is little research at present into the specific needs and requirements for handling polyamory in a clinical context.
A notable paper in this regard is ''Working with polyamorous clients in the clinical setting'' (Davidson, 2002),&lt;ref&gt;Paper delivered to the Society for the Scientific Study of Sexuality, Western Regional Conference, April 2002, and available online: Electronic Journal of Human Sexuality, Volume 5, April 16, 2002 [http://www.ejhs.org/volume5/polyoutline.html Ejhs.org]&lt;/ref&gt;
which addresses the following areas of inquiry:

# Why is it important that we talk about alternatives to monogamy now?
# How can therapists prepare to work with people who are exploring polyamory?
# What basic understandings about polyamory are needed?
# What key issues do therapists need to watch for in the course of working with polyamorous clients?

Its conclusions, summarized, were that &quot;Sweeping changes are occurring in the sexual and relational landscape&quot; (including &quot;dissatisfaction with limitations of serial monogamy, i.e. exchanging one partner for another in the hope of a better outcome&quot;);
that clinicians need to start by &quot;recognizing the array of possibilities that 'polyamory' encompasses&quot; and &quot;examine our culturally-based assumption that 'only monogamy is acceptable'&quot; and how this bias impacts on the practice of therapy; the need for self-education about polyamory, basic understandings about the &quot;rewards of the poly lifestyle&quot; and the common social and relationship challenges faced by those involved, and the &quot;shadow side&quot; of polyamory&quot;, the potential existing for coercion, strong emotions in opposition, and/or jealousy.

The paper also states that the configurations a therapist would be &quot;most likely to see in practice&quot; are individuals involved in primary-plus arrangements, monogamous couples wishing to explore non-monogamy for the first time, and &quot;poly singles.&quot;

A manual for psychotherapists who deal with polyamorous clients was published in September, 2009 by the ''National Coalition for Sexual Freedom'' titled ''What Psychotherapists Should Know About Polyamory''.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://ncsfreedom.org/images/stories/pdfs/KAP/2010_poly_web.pdf 2010_poly_web.pdf What Psychotherapists Should Know About Polyamory]''&lt;/ref&gt;

===The decision to explore polyamory===
Morin (1999) states that a couple has a very good chance of adjusting to nonexclusivity if at least some of the following conditions exist:&lt;ref name=&quot;familyprocess.org&quot;&gt;Cited by Michael Shernoff, Family Process, Vol.45 No.4, 2006, in the context of same-sex relationships [http://www.familyprocess.org/Data/featured_articles/65_shernoff.pdf Familyprocess.org]&lt;/ref&gt;
:* Both partners want their relationship to remain primary.
:* The couple has an established reservoir of good will.
:* There is a minimum of lingering resentments from past hurts and betrayals.
:* The partners are not polarized over monogamy/nonmonogamy.
:* The partners are feeling similarly powerful and autonomous.

Green &amp; Mitchell (2002) state that direct discussion of the following issues can provide the basis for honest and important conversations:&lt;ref name=&quot;familyprocess.org&quot;/&gt;
:* Openness versus secrecy
:* Volition and equality versus coercion and inequality
:* Clarity and specificity of agreements versus confusion/vagueness
:* Honoring keeping agreements versus violating them
:* How each partner views nonmonogamy.

According to Shernoff,&lt;ref&gt;Family Process, Vol.45 No.4, 2006, in the context of same-sex relationships [http://www.familyprocess.org/Data/featured_articles/65_shernoff.pdf Familyprocess.org]&lt;/ref&gt; if the matter is discussed with a third party, such as a therapist, the task of the therapist is to:

{{quote|Engage couples in conversations that let them decide for themselves whether sexual exclusivity or nonexclusivity is functional or dysfunctional for the relationship.}}

==Criticisms==
===Division of love===
In ''[[The Ethical Slut]]'', [[Dossie Easton]] and [[Janet Hardy]] (writing as 'Catherine Liszt') described an argument against polyamory which posits that when one's love is divided among multiple partners, the love is lessened. They referred to this as a &quot;starvation economy&quot; argument, because it treats love as a scarce commodity (like food or other resources) that can be given to one person only by taking it away from another. This is sometimes called a &quot;[[Thomas Malthus|Malthusian]] argument&quot;, after Malthus' writings on finite resources.

Many polyamorists, including Easton and Hardy, reject the idea that dividing love among multiple partners automatically lessens it. A commonly invoked argument uses an analogy with a parent who has two children—the parent does not love either of them any less because of the existence of the other.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|first=Derek |last=McCullough |coauthors=Hall, David S. |url=http://www.ejhs.org/volume6/polyamory.htm |title=Polyamory: What it is and what it isn't |journal=Electronic Journal of Human Sexuality |volume=6 |date=February 27, 2003 |accessdate=2006-07-10 |publisher=Institute for Advanced Study of Human Sexuality}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Heinlein expressed this in saying &quot;The more you love, the more you can love -- and the more intensely you love. Nor is there any limit on how many you can love. If a person had time enough, he could love all of that majority who are decent and just.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Heinlein, Robert. &quot;Intermission: Excerpts from the notebooks of Lazarus Long.&quot; ''in'' Time Enough For Love. New York: Penguin, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Perceived failure rates===
Polyamorous relationships are often criticised as &quot;not lasting&quot;, for example, Stanley Kurtz takes this as axiomatic when he says &quot;... legally recognized polyamory [would] be unstable&amp;nbsp;...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|first=Stanley |last=Kurtz |title=Polygamy Versus Democracy: You can't have both |url=http://www.weeklystandard.com/Utilities/printer_preview.asp?idArticle=12266 |work=Weekly Standard |date=June 5, 2006 |accessdate=006-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The problem of [[confirmation bias]] makes it impossible to accurately gauge the stability of polyamorous relationships without carefully conducted scientific investigation. The complex nature of polyamory presents difficulties in structuring such research. For instance, polyamorists may be reluctant to disclose their relationship status due to potential negative consequences, and researchers may be unfamiliar with the full range of polyamorous behaviours, leading to poorly framed questions that give misleading results.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|first=Gregory M. |last=Herek |coauthors=Douglas C. Kimmel, Hortensia Amaro, Gary B. Melton |title=Avoiding Heterosexual Bias in Psychological Research |publisher=American Psychological Association |url=http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/publications/research.html |month=September |year=1991 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060820040916/http://www.apa.org/pi/lgbc/publications/research.html |archivedate=20 August 2006 |accessdate=6 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While predating the term polyamory, some research has been done on the stability of some forms of what might be considered polyamorous relationships in the Netherlands. Weitzman&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite web|first=Geri D. |last=Weitzman |work=What Psychology Professionals Should Know About Polyamory |title=What is known about the psychological and social functioning of polyamorous individuals? |url=http://www.polyamoryonline.org/articles/psychological.html#top |date=March 12, 1999 |accessdate=2010-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; lists a study by Rubin and Adams in 1986 which found no differences in marital stability based on sexual exclusivity in married relationships.

==See also==
* ''[[Family: the web series]]''
* [[List of polyamorists]]
* [[Sociosexual orientation]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*Bennett, Jessica. [http://www.newsweek.com/id/209164 &quot;Only You. And You. And You&quot;], ''[[Newsweek]]'', July 29, 2009.
*Cook, Elaine. [http://www.ejhs.org/volume8/cook1.htm &quot;Commitment in Polyamory&quot;], ''[[Electronic Journal of Human Sexuality]]'', Volume 8, December 12, 2005.
*Davidson, Joy. [http://www.ejhs.org/volume5/polyoutline.html &quot;Working with Polyamorous Clients in the Clinical Setting&quot;], ''[[Electronic Journal of Human Sexuality]]'', Volume 5, April 16, 2002. Also delivered to the [[Society for the Scientific Study of Sexuality]], Western Regional Conference, April 2002.
*[[Elizabeth F. Emens|Emens, Elizabeth F.]] [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=506242 &quot;Monogamy's Law: Compulsory Monogamy and Polyamorous Existence&quot;], ''New York University Review of Law &amp; Social Change'', Vol. 29, p.&amp;nbsp;277, 2004. Analyzes social and legal perspectives on polyamory.
*McCullough, Derek; Hall, David S. [http://www.ejhs.org/volume6/polyamory.htm &quot;Polyamory - What it is and what it isn't&quot;], ''[[Electronic Journal of Human Sexuality]]'', Volume 6, February 27, 2003. Reviews some of the core beliefs, perspectives, practicalities, and references in polyamory.
*Newitz, Annalee. [http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg19125591.800 &quot;Love Unlimited: The Polyamorists&quot;], ''[[New Scientist]]'', 7 July 2006.
*Strassberg, Maura I. {{PDFlink|[https://culsnet.law.capital.edu/LawReview/BackIssues/31-3/Strassberg14.pdf &quot;The Challenge Of Post-Modern Polygamy: Considering Polyamory&quot;] |541&amp;nbsp;KB}}. Research analyzing monogamy, polygamy, polyfidelity and polyparenting and considers how polyfidelitous marriage might fit into Western culture within a Hegelian framework.
*Weitzman, Geri. [http://www.numenor.org/~gdw/psychologist/bipolycounseling.html &quot;Therapy with Clients Who Are Bisexual and Polyamorous&quot;], ''Journal of Bisexuality'', Volume 6, Issue 1/2, pp.&amp;nbsp;137–64.

==External links==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
{{Sister project links|commons=Category:Polyamory|v=no|n=no|s=no|b=no}}
;Polyamory-related media
*{{dmoz|Society/Relationships/Alternative_Lifestyles/Polyamory/}}

;Polyamory-related media coverage
* [http://polyinthemedia.blogspot.com/ Polyamory in the News] (2005–present)

;Research and articles
* [https://ncsfreedom.org/component/k2/item/470-sound-bites-for-the-polyamory-community.html National Coalition for Sexual Freedom Polyamory Sound Bites] Includes some data on frequency of nonmonogamy and psychiatric health of the polyamorous.
* [http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/library/haslam.html The Kenneth R. Haslam Collection on Polyamory] hosted at the [[Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, and Reproduction]] includes a wide variety of materials related to polyamory, along with research data.
* [http://www.kinseyinstitute.org/library/Pdf/Polyamory%20Bibliography.pdf Polyamory Bibliography] from the Kinsey Institute.


{{Close plural relationships}}
{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Sex}}
{{Human sexuality}}
{{Sexual identities}}
{{Bisexuality topics}}
{{LGBT|selected=identities|orientation=yes|state=collapsed|main=expanded}}
}}


&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Polyamory| ]]
[[Category:Love]]
[[Category:Intimate relationships]]
[[Category:Interpersonal relationships]]
[[Category:Sexual fidelity]]
[[Category:Sexuality and society]]
[[Category:Discrimination in the United States]]
[[Category:Article Feedback 5]]

&lt;!--Interwikis--&gt;
[[ca:Poliamor]]
[[cs:Polyamorie]]
[[da:Polyamory]]
[[de:Polyamory]]
[[es:Poliamor]]
[[eo:Pluramemo]]
[[fa:چندمهری]]
[[fr:Polyamour]]
[[gl:Poliamor]]
[[ko:비독점적 다자연애]]
[[hr:Višeljublje]]
[[it:Poliamore]]
[[he:פוליאמוריה]]
[[hu:Poliamoria]]
[[nl:Polyamorie]]
[[ja:ポリアモリー]]
[[no:Polyamori]]
[[pl:Poliamoria]]
[[pt:Poliamor]]
[[ro:Poliamor]]
[[ru:Полиамория]]
[[sk:Polyamoria]]
[[sl:Poliamorija]]
[[sr:Poliamorija]]
[[sh:Poliamorija]]
[[fi:Polyamoria]]
[[sv:Polyamori]]
[[tr:Poliamori]]
[[zh:多元之愛]]</text>
      <sha1>oylouuyp9tui1jw8wy285hnso0zhdrn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
