<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Polygamy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24475</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521059276</id>
      <parentid>521017517</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T14:51:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>64.215.250.7</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Forms of polygamy */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="76378">[[File:Toba chieftain 1892.jpg|thumb|right|240px|[[Toba people|Toba]] chieftain and his wives, 1892]]
'''Polygamy''' (from πολύς γάμος ''polys'' ''gamos'', translated literally in [[Greek language|Late Greek]] as &quot;often married&quot;)&lt;ref name=Zeitzen/&gt; is a marriage which includes more than two partners.&lt;ref name=Zeitzen&gt;{{cite book |last=Zeitzen |first=Miriam Koktvedgaard |title=Polygamy: a cross-cultural analysis |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WIzHjpTJgdQC&amp;pg=PA3 |publisher=Berg |page=3 |year=2008 |isbn=1-84520-220-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; When a man is married to more than one wife at a time, the relationship is called [[polygyny]], and there is no marriage bond between the wives; and when a woman is married to more than one husband at a time, it is called [[polyandry]], and there is no marriage bond between the husbands. If a marriage includes multiple husbands and wives, it can be called [[group marriage]].&lt;ref name=Zeitzen/&gt; The term is used in related ways in [[social anthropology]], [[sociobiology]], [[sociology]], as well as in popular speech. In social anthropology, polygamy is the practice of a person's making him/herself available for two or more spouses to mate with. In contrast, [[monogamy]] is a marriage consisting of only two parties. Like ''monogamy'', the term is often used in a ''[[de facto]]'' sense, applying regardless of whether the relationships are recognized by the [[state (polity)|state]] (see [[marriage (conflict)|marriage]] for a discussion on the extent to which states can and do recognize potentially and actually polygamous forms as valid). In [[sociobiology]] and [[zoology]], polygamy is used in a broad sense to mean any form of multiple [[mating]].
{{Close Relationships}}
{{Legal_recognition_of Polygamy}}
__TOC__

==Forms of polygamy==
Polygamy exists in three specific forms: [[polygyny]] - wherein a man has multiple simultaneous wives;&lt;ref&gt;''Webster's Third New International Dictionary, Unabridged'', s.v. 'polygyny'.&lt;/ref&gt; [[polyandry]] - wherein a woman has multiple simultaneous husbands; or [[group marriage]] - wherein the family unit consists of multiple husbands and multiple wives.

Historically, all three practices have been found, but polygyny is by far the most common.&lt;ref name=Atlas/&gt; Confusion arises when the broad term &quot;polygamy&quot; is used when a specific form of polygamy is being referred to. Additionally, different countries may or may not include all forms in their Polygamy laws.

===Polyandry===
{{Main|Polyandry}}
Polyandry is a practice wherein a woman has more than one husband at the same time. Fraternal polyandry was traditionally practiced among [[nomad]]ic [[Tibetan people|Tibetans]] in [[Nepal]], parts of [[China]] and part of northern India, in which two or more brothers are married to the same wife, with the wife having equal 'sexual access' to them. The Indian epic the [[Mahabharata]] includes the polyandrous marriage of [[Draupadi]] to the five [[Pandava]] brothers. Polyandry is believed to be more likely in societies with scarce environmental resources, as it is believed to limit human population growth and enhance child survival.&lt;ref name=Stone2006&gt;(Linda Stone, Kinship and Gender, 2006, Westview, 3rd ed, ch 6) [http://www.case.edu/affil/tibet/tibetanSociety/marriage.htm The Center for Research on Tibet] Papers on Tibetan Marriage and Polyandry. Accessed: October 1, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; It is a rare form of marriage that exists not only among poor families, but also the elite.&lt;ref&gt;Goldstein, Pahari and Tibetan Polyandry Revisited, Ethnology. 17(3): 325–327, 1978, from [http://www.case.edu/affil/tibet/tibetanSociety/marriage.htm The Center for Research on Tibet]. Accessed: October 1, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===Group marriage===
{{Main|Group marriage}}
Group marriage is a marriage wherein the family unit consists of more than two partners, any of whom share [[parent]]al responsibility for any children arising from the marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Constantine|first=Larry L.|title=Group Marriage;: A Study of Contemporary Multilateral Marriage|year=1974|publisher=Collier Books|isbn=978-0020759102}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Group marriage is a form of [[non-monogamy]] and [[polyamory]].

==Patterns of occurrence worldwide==
According to the ''Ethnographic Atlas Codebook'', of 1,231 societies noted, 186 were monogamous. 453 had occasional polygyny, 588 had more frequent polygyny, and 4 had polyandry.&lt;ref name=Atlas&gt;[http://eclectic.ss.uci.edu/~drwhite/worldcul/Codebook4EthnoAtlas.pdf ''Ethnographic Atlas Codebook''] derived from George P. Murdock’s ''Ethnographic Atlas'' recording the marital composition of 1231 societies from 1960 to 1980&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, even within societies which allow polygyny, the actual practice of polygyny occurs relatively rarely. There are exceptions: in [[Senegal]], for example, nearly 47 percent of marriages are multiple.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Diouf | first = Nafi | title = Polygamy hangs on in Africa | publisher = The Milwaukee Journal Sentinel | date = May 2, 2004 | url = http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4196/is_20040502/ai_n10968614 }}&lt;/ref&gt; To take on more than one wife often requires considerable resources: this may put polygamy beyond the means{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}} of the vast majority of people within those societies. Such appears the case in many traditional [[Islamic culture|Islamic societies]], and in [[Imperial era of Chinese history|Imperial China]]. Within polygynous societies, multiple wives often become a [[status symbol]] denoting wealth, power, and fame.

==Religion==

===Buddhism===
In [[Buddhism]],  marriage is not a [[sacrament]]. It is purely a [[secular]] affair and the monks do not participate in it, though in some sects priests and monks do marry. Hence it receives no religious sanction.&lt;ref name=&quot;access to insight&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/dewaraja/wheel280.html |title=Accesstoinsight.org |publisher=Accesstoinsight.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Forms of marriage consequently vary from country to country. It is said in the [[Parabhava Sutta]] that &quot;a man who is not satisfied with one woman and seeks out other women is on the path to decline&quot;. Other fragments in the Buddhist scripture can be found that seem to treat polygamy unfavorably, leading some authors to conclude that Buddhism generally does not approve of it&lt;ref name=&quot;ethics of buddhism&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=URZNk9noWJEC&amp;pg=PA101&amp;lpg=PA101&amp;dq=buddhism+ethics+polygamy&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ug6YVFGTGw&amp;sig=M_QRol9URCRV_1se6HaWOLR6KnA&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=hUweSvSsK5PFsgaY5sHNCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1 The Ethics of Buddhism], Shundō Tachibana, Routledge, 1992, ISBN 0-7007-0230-X, 9780700702305&lt;/ref&gt; or alternatively that it is a tolerated, but subordinate marital model.&lt;ref name=&quot;introduction to Buddhist ethics&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=URZNk9noWJEC&amp;pg=PA101&amp;lpg=PA101&amp;dq=buddhism+ethics+polygamy&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ug6YVFGTGw&amp;sig=M_QRol9URCRV_1se6HaWOLR6KnA&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=hUweSvSsK5PFsgaY5sHNCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1#PPA102,M1 An introduction to Buddhist ethics]: foundations, values, and issues, Brian Peter Harvey, Cambridge University Press, 2000, ISBN 0-521-55640-6, ISBN 978-0-521-55640-8&lt;/ref&gt;

Until 1935 polygyny was legally recognized in [[Thailand]]. In [[Burma]], polygyny was also frequent. It is still legally recognized but very rarely practiced in modern day and socially less acceptable.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} In [[Sri Lanka]], polyandry was practiced (though not widespread) till recent times.&lt;ref name=&quot;access to insight&quot; /&gt; When the Buddhist texts were translated into Chinese, the [[concubine]]s of others were added to the list of inappropriate partners. [[Polyandry in Tibet]] as well was common traditionally, as was polygyny, and having several wives or husbands was never regarded as having sex with inappropriate partners.&lt;ref name=&quot;berzin archives&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.berzinarchives.com/web/en/archives/approaching_buddhism/world_today/issues_buddhist_sexual_ethics.html |title=Berzinarchives.com |publisher=Berzinarchives.com |date=2010-10-07 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tibet is home to the largest and most flourishing polyandrous community in the world today. Most typically, fraternal polyandry is practiced, but sometimes father and son have a common wife, which is a unique family structure in the world. Other forms of marriage are also present, like group marriage and monogamous marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Polygamy: a cross cultural analysis&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=WIzHjpTJgdQC&amp;pg=PA35&amp;lpg=PA35&amp;dq=polygamy+buddhism&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=-dAqeWzeeX&amp;sig=l9o6_h8RN0VAn2OQphPc5CoOHZE&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=aUoeSu6aC8yNsAbB163RCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4 Polygamy: a cross-cultural analysis], Miriam Koktvedgaard Zeitze, Published by Berg Publishers, 2008, ISBN 1-84520-220-1, ISBN 978-1-84520-220-0 (as found at Google books)&lt;/ref&gt; Polyandry (especially fraternal polyandry) is also common among Buddhists in [[Bhutan]], [[Ladakh]], and other parts of the [[Indian subcontinent]].

===Celtic traditions===
The pre-Abrahamic [[Celtic paganism|Celtic pagans]] were known to practice polygamy, although the [[Celtic peoples]] wavered between it, [[monogamy]] and [[polyandry]] depending on the time period and area.&lt;ref&gt;Jean Markale, ''Women of the Celts'', page 36.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some areas this continued on even after Christianisation began, for instance the [[Brehon Laws]] of [[Gaelic]] [[Ireland]] explicitly allowed for polygamy,&lt;ref&gt;Jan Fries, ''Couldron of the Gods'', page 192.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Seán Duffy, ''Medieval Ireland, An Encyclopedia'', page 74.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt; especially amongst the noble class.&lt;ref&gt;Paul F State, ''A brief history of Ireland'', page 17.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some modern Celtic pagan religions accept the practice of polygamy to varying degrees,&lt;ref&gt;Fox, Martin and O'Ciarrai, Breandan. &quot;[http://ciarraide.org/sinnsreachd101.html  Céard is Sinnsreachd Ann? (What Is Sinnsreachd?)]&quot;, ''Tuath na Ciarraide'', March 7, 2007. Retrieved 
on July 27, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; though how widespread the practice is within these religions is unknown.

===Greeks &amp; Romans===

The Greeks and the Romans never practiced polygamy. The practice was thought to disrupt inheritance lines and thus was never sanctioned by the state.{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}}

===Christianity===
{{Main|Polygamy in Christianity}}
Saint [[Augustine of Hippo|Augustine]] saw a conflict with Old Testament polygyny. He refrained from judging the patriarchs, but did not deduce from their practice the ongoing acceptability of polygyny. On the contrary, he argued that the polygyny of the Fathers, which was tolerated by the Creator because of fertility, was a diversion from His original plan for human marriage. Augustine wrote: ''That the good purpose of marriage, however, is better promoted by one husband with one wife, than by a husband with several wives, is shown plainly enough by the very first union of a married pair, which was made by the Divine Being Himself.''&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume V/On Marriage and Concupiscence/Book I/Chapter 10|''On Marriage and Concupiscence'',I,10]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Augustine taught that the reason patriarchs had many wives was not because of fornication, but because they wanted more children. He supported his premise by showing that their marriages, in which husband was the head, were arranged according to the rules of good management: those who are ''in command'' (''quae principantur'') in their society were always singular, while ''subordinates'' (''subiecta'') were multiple. He gave two examples of such relationships: ''dominus-servus'' - master-servant (in older translation: ''slave'') and ''God-soul''. The Bible often equates worshipping multiple gods, i.e. idolatry to fornication.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Marcus|first=Joel|title=Idolatry In The New Testament|journal=Interpretation|year=2006|month=April|volume=60|issue=2|pages=152–164|url=http://int.sagepub.com/content/60/2/152.short|accessdate=5 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Augustine relates to that: ''On this account there is no True God of souls, save One: but one soul by means of many false gods may commit fornication, but not be made fruitful''.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume III/Moral Treatises of St. Augustin/On the Good of Marriage/Section 20|Augustine, ''On the Good of Marriage'', ch. 20]]; cf. [[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume V/On Marriage and Concupiscence/Book I/Chapter 10|''On Marriage and Concupiscence'',I,10]]&lt;/ref&gt;

As tribal populations grew, fertility was no longer a valid justification of polygamy: it ''was lawful among the ancient fathers: whether it be lawful now also, I would not hastily pronounce (utrum et nunc fas sit, non temere dixerim). For there is not now necessity of begetting children, as there then was, when, even when wives bear children, it was allowed, in order to a more numerous posterity, to marry other wives in addition, which now is certainly not lawful.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;St. Augustin [[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume III/Moral Treatises of St. Augustin/On the Good of Marriage/Section 17|''On the Good of Marriage'', ch.17]]; cf. [[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume V/On Marriage and Concupiscence/Book I/Chapter 9|''On Marriage and Concupiscence'',I,9.8]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Augustine saw marriage as sacrament-friendly covenant between one man and one woman, which may not be broken. It was the Creator who established monogamy: ''Therefore the first natural bond of human society is man and wife.''&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume III/Moral Treatises of St. Augustin/On the Good of Marriage/Section 1|''On the Good of Marriage'', ch.1]]&lt;/ref&gt; Such marriage was confirmed by the Saviour in the Gospel of Matthew (Mat 19,9) and by His presence at the wedding in Cana (John 2:2).&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume III/Moral Treatises of St. Augustin/On the Good of Marriage/Section 3|''On the Good of Marriage'', ch.3]]&lt;/ref&gt; In the Church—the City of God—marriage is a sacrament and may not and cannot be dissolved as long as the spouses live: ''But a marriage once for all entered upon in the City of our God, where, even from the first union of the two, the man and the woman, marriage bears a certain sacramental character, can in no way be dissolved but by the death of one of them.''.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume III/Moral Treatises of St. Augustin/On the Good of Marriage/Section 17|''On the Good of Marriage'', 17]]&lt;/ref&gt; In chapter 7, Augustine pointed out that the Roman Empire forbad polygamy, even if the reason of fertility would support it: ''For it is in a man’s power to put away a wife that is barren, and marry one of whom to have children. And yet it is not allowed; and now indeed in our times, and after the usage of Rome (nostris quidem iam temporibus ac more Romano), neither to marry in addition, so as to have more than one wife living''. Further on he notices that the Church's attitude goes much further than the secular law regarding monogamy: It forbids re-marrying, considering such to be a form of fornication: ''And yet, save in the City of our God, in His Holy Mount, the case is not such with the wife. But, that the laws of the Gentiles are otherwise, who is there that knows not'' .&lt;ref&gt;Augustine, [[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume III/Moral Treatises of St. Augustin/On the Good of Marriage/Section 7|''On the Good of Marriage'', ch. 7]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[New Testament]] does not specifically address the morality of polygamy. [[1 Timothy]], however, states that certain Church leaders should have but one wife: &quot;A ''bishop'' then must be blameless, the husband of one wife, vigilant, sober, of good behavior, given to hospitality, apt to teach&quot; (chapter 3, verse 2; see also verse 12 regarding deacons having only one wife).  Similar counsel is repeated in the first chapter of the [[Epistle of Titus]]; however, the redactor&lt;ref&gt;The Digital [[Nestle-Aland]] lists only one manuscript (P46) as source of the verse, while nine other manuscripts have no such verse, cf. http://nttranscripts.uni-muenster.de/AnaServer?NTtranscripts+0+start.anv&lt;/ref&gt; of 1 Corinthians (chapter 7, verse 2) writes, &quot;Nevertheless, to avoid fornication, let ''every'' man have his own wife, and let ''every'' woman have her own husband.&quot;  In modern times a minority of Roman Catholic theologians have argued that polygyny, though not ideal, can be a legitimate form of Christian marriage in certain regions, in particular Africa.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''The Ratzinger report: an exclusive interview on the state of the Church Pope Benedict XVI, Vittorio Messori&quot;'', p. 195, Ignatius Press, 1985, ISBN 0-89870-080-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''Morality: The Case for Polygamy&quot;,'' Time Magazine, May 10, 1968, [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,902227,00.html time.com] and &quot;''Christianity and the African imagination: essays in honour of [[Adrian Hastings]]''&quot;, edited by David Maxwell with Ingrid Lawrie, p. 345-346, Brill, 2002, ISBN 90-04-11668-0&lt;/ref&gt; The Roman Catholic Church teaches in its Catechism that &lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;polygamy is not in accord with the moral law. [Conjugal] communion is radically contradicted by polygamy; this, in fact, directly negates the plan of God which was revealed from the beginning, because it is contrary to the equal personal dignity of men and women who in matrimony give themselves with a love that is total and therefore unique and exclusive.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p3s2c2a6.htm Catholic Cathechism, para. 2387] April 05, 2009, Vatican website&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Periodically, Christian reform movements that have aimed at rebuilding Christian doctrine based on the Bible alone (''[[sola scriptura]]'') have at least temporarily accepted polygyny as a Biblical practice. For example, during the [[Protestant Reformation]], in a document referred to simply as ''&quot;Der Beichtrat&quot;'' (or ''&quot;The Confessional Advice&quot;'' ),&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=kqyauQISxFEC&amp;vid=0syFeDjkzVczX39npTyMsU2&amp;dq=Dr.+Martin+Luthers+Briefe%2C+Sendschreiben&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;jtp=238 Letter to Philip of Hesse], December 10, 1539, [[De Wette]]-Seidemann, 6:238–244&lt;/ref&gt; [[Martin Luther]] granted the [[Landgrave]] [[Philip of Hesse]], who, for many years, had been living &quot;constantly in a state of adultery and fornication,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ojwMAAAAIAAJ&amp;vid=OCLC24799826&amp;dq=%22The+Life+of+Luther+Written+by+Himself%22&amp;jtp=251 |title=The Life of Luther Written by Himself, p.251 |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; a dispensation to take a second wife. The double marriage was to be done in secret, however, to avoid public scandal.&lt;ref&gt;[[James Bowling Mozley]] ''Essays, Historical and Theological.'' 1:403–404 Excerpts from ''Der Beichtrat''. [http://books.google.com/books?vid=OCLC05173520&amp;id=ofwE7kEdx6QC&amp;pg=PA403&amp;dq=%22essays+historical+and+theological%22 books.google.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Some fifteen years earlier, in a letter to the Saxon Chancellor [[Gregor Brück]], Luther stated that he could not &quot;forbid a person to marry several wives, for it does not contradict Scripture.&quot; (&quot;''Ego sane fateor, me non posse prohibere, si quis plures velit uxores ducere, nec repugnat sacris literis.''&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;Letter to the Chancellor [[:de:Gregor Brück|Gregor Brück]], January 13, 1524, [[De Wette]] 2:459.&lt;!--this link does not work - [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;q=Ego+sane+fateor,+me+non+posse+prohibere]--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;On February 14, 1650, the parliament at Nürnberg decreed that, because so many men were killed during the Thirty Years’ War, the churches for the following ten years could not admit any man under the age of 60 into a monastery. Priests and ministers not bound by any monastery were allowed to marry. Lastly, the decree stated that every man was allowed to marry up to ten women. The men were admonished to behave honorably, provide for their wives properly, and prevent animosity among them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Larry O. Jensen, [http://www.familysearch.org/Eng/Search/Rg/images/Ger_BMD_RefDoc_HandbookGermanResearch.pdf A Genealogical Handbook of German Research] (Rev. Ed., 1980) p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Alfred X. Michiels, ''Secret History of the Austrian Government and of its Systematic Persecutions of Protestants'' (London: Chapman and Hall, 1859) p. 85 (copy at Google Books), the author stating that he is quoting from a copy of the legislation.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;William Walker Rockwell, ''Die Doppelehe des Landgrafen Philipp von Hessen'' (Marburg, 1904), p. 280, n. 2 (copy at Google Books), which reports the number of wives allowed was two.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Leonhard Theobald, “Der angebliche Bigamiebeschluß des fränkischen Kreistages” [“The So-called Bigamy Decision of the Franconian Kreistag”], ''Beitrage zur Bayerischen kirchengeschichte'' [Contributions to Bavarian Church History] 23 (1916 – bound volume dated 1917) Erlangen: 199–200 (Theobald reporting that the Franconian Kreistag did not hold session between 1645 and 1664, and that there is no record of such a law in the extant archives of Nürnberg, Ansbach, or Bamberg, Theobald believing that the editors of the Fränkisches Archiv must have misunderstood a draft of some other legislation from 1650).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alfred Altmann, &quot;Verein für Geschichte der Stadt Nürnburg,&quot; ''Jahresbericht über das 43 Vereinsjahr 1920'' [Annual Report for the 43rd Year 1920 of the Historical Society of the City of Nuremberg] (Nürnberg 1920): 13–15 (Altmann reporting a lecture he had given discussing the polygamy permission said to have been granted in Nuremberg in 1650, Altmann characterizing the Fränkisches Archiv as &quot;merely a popular journal, not an edition of state documents,&quot; and describing the tradition as &quot;a literary fantasy&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See Heinrich Christoph Büttner, Johann Heinrich Keerl, und Johann Bernhard Fischer. Fränkisches Archiv, herausgegeben. I Band. 1790. (at p. 155) (setting forth a 1790 printing of the legislation).&lt;/ref&gt;

The trend towards frequent divorce and remarriage is sometimes referred to as 'serial polygamy'.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''&lt;span dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Emblems of pluralism: cultural differences and the state&lt;/span&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?q=+bibliogroup:%22Cultural+lives+of+law%22&amp;as_brr=3&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;source=gbs_metadata_r&amp;cad=9 '', Cultural lives of law''][http://books.google.co.uk/books?q=+bibliogroup:%22Princeton+paperbacks%22&amp;as_brr=3&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;source=gbs_metadata_r&amp;cad=9 '', Princeton paperbacks''],''Carol Weisbrod, p. 53,  Princeton University Press, 2002, ISBN 0-691-08925-6&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, others may refer to this as '[[serial monogamy]]', since it is a series of monogamous relationships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Helen Fisher &quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Fisher|first=Helen|publisher=Ballantine Books|title=The First Sex|pages=271–72, 276|isbn=0-449-91260-4
|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first term highlights the multiplicity of marriages throughout the life-cycle, the second the non-simultaneous nature of these marriages.
&lt;!-- the link has no relevant material &amp; can't find any at site - [http://oregonstate.edu/dept/anthropology/glossary2.htm] --&gt;

In Sub-Saharan Africa, there has often been a tension between the Christian churches' insistence on monogamy and traditional polygamy. In some instances in recent times there have been moves for accommodation; in other instances, churches have resisted such moves strongly. African Independent Churches have sometimes referred to those parts of the Old Testament which describe polygamy in defending the practice.

====Roman Catholic Church====
The [[Roman Catholic Church]] clearly condemns polygamy; the ''[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]'' lists it in paragraph 2387 under the head &quot;Other offenses against the dignity of marriage&quot; and states that it &quot;is not in accord with the moral law.&quot; Also in paragraph 1645 under the head &quot;The Goods and Requirements of Conjugal Love&quot; states &quot;The unity of marriage, distinctly recognized by our Lord, is made clear in the equal personal dignity which must be accorded to husband and wife in mutual and unreserved affection. Polygamy is contrary to conjugal love which is undivided and exclusive.&quot;

The illegality of polygamy in certain areas creates, according to certain Bible passages, additional arguments against it. [[Paul of Tarsus]] writes &quot;submit to the authorities, not only because of possible punishment but also because of conscience&quot; (Romans 13:5), for &quot;the authorities that exist have been established by God.&quot; (Romans 13:1) [[St Peter]] concurs when he says to &quot;submit yourselves for the Lord's sake to every authority instituted among men: whether to the king, as the supreme authority, or to governors, who are sent by him to punish those who do wrong and to commend those who do right.&quot; (1 Peter 2:13,14) Pro-polygamists argue that, as long as polygamists currently do not obtain legal marriage licenses nor seek &quot;common law marriage status&quot; for additional spouses, no enforced laws are being broken any more than when monogamous couples who similarly co-habitate without a marriage license.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblicalpolygamy.com/exegesis/law-of-the-land/ &quot;Law of the Land&quot;] page at [http://www.biblicalpolygamy.com BiblicalPolygamy.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Mormonism====
{{LDSpolygamy}}
{{main|Mormonism and polygamy}}

The history of [[Mormonism|Mormon]] polygamy (specifically polygyny) began with [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]], who stated he received a revelation on July 17, 1831 that &quot;[[plural marriage]]&quot; should be practiced by some Mormon men who were specifically commanded to do so. This was later published in the [[Doctrine and Covenants]] by [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church).&lt;ref&gt;[http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132 Doctrine and Covenants 132] as found at lds.org&lt;/ref&gt; Despite Smith's revelation, the 1835 edition of the 101st Section of the Doctrine and Covenants, written after the doctrine of plural marriage began to be practiced, publicly condemned polygamy. This scripture was used by [[John Taylor (1808–1887)|John Taylor]] in 1850 to quash Mormon polygamy rumors in [[Liverpool, England]].&lt;ref&gt;Three nights public discussion between the Revds. C. W. Cleeve, James Robertson, and Philip Cater, and Elder John Taylor, Of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, At Boulogne-Sur-Mer, France. Chairman, Rev. K. Groves, M.A., Assisted By Charles Townley, LL.D., and Mr. Luddy. pp. 8–9&lt;/ref&gt; Polygamy was made illegal in the state of [[Illinois]]&lt;ref&gt;Greiner &amp; Sherman, Revised Laws of Illinois, 1833, pp. 198–199&lt;/ref&gt; during the 1839–44 [[Nauvoo, Illinois|Nauvoo]] era when several top Mormon leaders, including Smith,&lt;ref&gt;[[Todd Compton]], [http://content.lib.utah.edu/cdm4/document.php?CISOROOT=/dialogue&amp;CISOPTR=11460&amp;REC=12 &quot;A Trajectory of Plurality: An Overview of Joseph Smith's Thirty-three Plural Wives&quot;], ''[[Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought]]'', vol. 29, no. 2, pp. 1–38.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last= Smith |first= George D |title= Nauvoo Roots of Mormon Polygamy, 1841-46: A Preliminary Demographic Report |journal= Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought |volume= 27 |issue= 1 |date= Spring 1994 |url= http://content.lib.utah.edu/cdm4/document.php?CISOROOT=%2Fdialogue&amp;CISOPTR=15882&amp;REC=3&amp;CISOBOX=42 |accessdate= 2007-05-12 |postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brigham Young]] and [[Heber C. Kimball]], took plural wives. Mormon elders who publicly taught that all men were commanded to enter plural marriage were subject to harsh discipline.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.centerplace.org/history/ts/v5n03.htm Times and Seasons, vol. 5, p. 423], February 1, 1844&lt;/ref&gt; On June 7, 1844 the ''[[Nauvoo Expositor]]'' criticized Smith for plural marriage. After Joseph Smith's murder by a mob on June 27, 1844, the main body of Mormons left Nauvoo and followed Brigham Young to [[Utah]] where the practice of plural marriage continued.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mscbc.org/video/vid_lvp.htm Lifting the Veil of Polygamy] (2007, Main Street Church) A documentary concerning the history of Mormon polygamy and its modern manifestations.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1852 [[Brigham Young]], the second [[President of the Church|president of the LDS Church]] publicly acknowledged the practice of plural marriage through a sermon he gave. Additional sermons by top Mormon leaders on the virtues of polygamy followed.&lt;ref&gt;[[Journal of Discourses]] [http://journalofdiscourses.org/Vol_11/refJDvol11-19.html 11:128] Brigham Young - June 18, 1865 - &quot;Since the founding of the Roman empire monogamy has prevailed more extensively than in times previous to that. The founders of that ancient empire were robbers and women stealers, and made laws favoring monogamy in consequence of the scarcity of women among them, and hence this monogamic system which now prevails throughout Christendom, and which had been so fruitful a source of prostitution and whoredom throughout all the Christian monogamic cities of the Old and New World, until rottenness and decay are at the root of their institutions both national and religious.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Controversy followed when polygyny became a social cause, writers began to publish works condemning polygamy. The key plank of the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]'s 1856 [[Party platform|platform]] was &quot;to prohibit in the territories those twin relics of barbarism, polygamy and slavery&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ushistory.org/gop/convention_1856.htm GOP Convention of 1856 in Philadelphia] from the Independence Hall Association website&lt;/ref&gt; In 1862, [[37th United States Congress|Congress]] issued the [[Morrill Anti-Bigamy Act]] which clarified that the practice of polygamy was illegal in all [[Organized incorporated territories of the United States|US territories]]. The LDS Church believed that their religiously-based practice of plural marriage was protected by the [[United States Constitution]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/data/constitution/amendment01/05.html |title=Free Exercise Clause - First Amendment |publisher=Caselaw.lp.findlaw.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, the unanimous 1878 [[U.S. Supreme Court|Supreme Court]] decision ''[[Reynolds v. United States]]'' declared that polygamy was not protected by the Constitution, based on the longstanding legal principle that &quot;laws are made for the government of actions, and while they cannot interfere with mere religious belief and opinions, they may with practices.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=search&amp;court=US&amp;case=/us/98/145.html Reynolds v. United States] at [[findlaw.com]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Increasingly harsh anti-polygamy legislation in the US led some Mormons to emigrate to [[Canada]] and [[Mexico]]. In 1890, LDS Church president [[Wilford Woodruff]] issued a public declaration (the [[1890 Manifesto|Manifesto]]) announcing that the LDS Church had discontinued new plural marriages. [[Anti-Mormonism|Anti-Mormon sentiment]] waned, as did opposition to statehood for [[Utah]]. The [[Smoot Hearings]] in 1904, which documented that the LDS Church was still practicing polygamy spurred the LDS Church to issue a [[Second Manifesto]] again claiming that it had ceased performing new plural marriages. By 1910 the LDS Church [[excommunicate]]d those who entered into, or performed, new plural marriages. Even so, many plural husbands and wives continued to cohabit until their deaths in the 1940s and 1950s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.media.utah.edu/UHE/p/POLYGAMY.html Polygamy] entry in the Utah Historical Encyclopedia, [[University of Utah]], 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;  The last documented mainstream LDS polygamous marriage was Edward Eyring,{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} the grandfather of current LDS apostle [[Henry B. Eyring]]. One of the wives died in 1954, turning the marriage into a monogamous one.

Enforcement of the 1890 Manifesto caused various [[Schism (religion)|splinter groups]] to leave the LDS Church in order to continue the practice of plural marriage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://attorneygeneral.utah.gov/polygamy/The_Primer.pdf &quot;The Primer&quot;] - Helping Victims of Domestic Violence and Child Abuse in Polygamous Communities. A joint report from the offices of the Attorneys General of Arizona and Utah. (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; Polygamy among these groups persists today in [[Utah]] and neighboring states as well as in the spin-off colonies. Polygamist churches of Mormon origin are often referred to as &quot;[[Mormon fundamentalism|Mormon fundamentalist]]&quot; even though they are not a part of the LDS Church. Such fundamentalists often use a purported [[1886 revelation]] to [[John Taylor (1808–1887)|John Taylor]] as the basis for their authority to continue the practice of plural marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mormonfundamentalism.com/NEWFILES/1886RevelationNew.htm |title=An 1886 Revelation to John Taylor |publisher=Mormonfundamentalism.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Salt Lake Tribune]]'' stated in 2005 there were as many as 37,000 fundamentalists with less than half of them living in polygamous households.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.principlevoices.org/article.php?story=20050828124239994 &quot;LDS splinter groups growing&quot;] by Brooke Adams, August 9, 2005 - SLT Article ID: 10BF07C805DE5990&lt;!-- Note: this is a [[Wikipedia:Convenience_links|convenience link, as the original article is currently only viewable by subscription to the SLT archives, but article number provided for verifiability--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|So the fundamentalist Mormons who insist that polygamy is biblical are right, in a sense. If you're going to be a strict literalist, there's nothing wrong with polygamy.&lt;ref name=silver&gt;Alexandra Silver [http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,2027582,00.html What the Bible Has to Say About Sex] Time.com&lt;/ref&gt;|[[Michael Coogan]]|&quot;What the Bible Has to Say About Sex&quot; by Alexandra Silver}}

===Hinduism===
According [[Hindu Marriage Act]] Polygamy in any form is illegal.

Polygamy was practiced in many sections of [[Hindu]] society in ancient times. There was one example of [[polyandry]] in the ancient Hindu epic, [[Mahabharata]], [[Draupadi]] marries the five [[Pandava]] brothers. Regarding [[polygyny]], in [[Ramayana]], father of [[Rama|Ram]], King [[Dasharath]] has three wives, but Ram has pledged himself just one wife.

The Hindu god, Lord [[Krishna]], the 9th incarnation of the Hindu god [[Vishnu]] is supposed to have had 8 wives.  He formally married 16,100 girls whom he rescued from the prison of the Demon Narakasura, when they had nowhere to go to provide them a life and shelter at his kingdom in [[Dwarka]]. In the post-[[Vedic period]]s, polygamy declined in Hinduism, and is now considered immoral,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=V.Jayaram |url=http://www.hinduwebsite.com/hinduism/h_polygamy.asp |title=Hinduwebsite.com |publisher=Hinduwebsite.com |date=2007-01-09 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Marriage laws in India are dependent upon the religion of the subject in question. Although the [[Vedas]] and the Hindu religion itself do not outlaw polygamy, the terms under the [[Hindu Marriage Act]] has deemed polygamy to be illegal for Hindus, Jains, Buddhists, and Sikhs. Only Muslim men in India are allowed to have up to 4 wives, since they are governed under [[Sharia law]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sudhirlaw.com/Marriages.html Marriages-Divorces] section at general information website on Indian laws by Sudhir Shah and Associates&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===
{{Main|Polygamy in Islam}}
In Islam, [[polygyny]] is allowed, with the specific limitation that a man can have up to four wives at any one time. Prophet [[Muhammad]]  had eleven wives in his lifetime, and had 4 wives at a time. The [[Qur'an]] clearly states that men who choose this route must deal with their wives justly. If the husband fears that he cannot deal with his wives justly, then he should only marry one. The Qur'an does not give preference in marrying more than one wife but allows it to make it easier on a woman who has no support. Islamic scholars opinion that the husband must tell the first wife if he wants to marry another. A husband does not have to have permission from his first wife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamweb.net/ver2/fatwa/ShowFatwa.php?lang=A&amp;Id=18444&amp;Option=FatwaId |title=IslamWeb |publisher=IslamWeb |date=2002-02-07 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Women, on the other hand, are only allowed to marry one husband, although they are allowed to remarry after a divorce. Although many [[Muslim]] countries still retain traditional [[Sharia|Islamic law]] which permits polygamy, secular elements within some Muslim societies challenge its acceptability. Polygamy is prohibited by law in some Muslim-majority countries that have not adopted Islamic law for marital regulations, such as  [[Azerbaijan]], [[Tunisia]] and [[Turkey]].

Polygamy, and laws concerning polygamy, differ greatly throughout the Islamic world and form a very complex and diverse background from nation to nation. Whereas in some Muslim countries it may be fairly common, in most others it is often rare or non-existent. According to traditional Islamic law, a man may take up to four wives, and each of those wives must have her own property, assets, and [[dowry]]. Usually the wives have little to no contact with each other and lead separate, individual lives in their own houses, and sometimes in different cities, though they all share the same husband. Polygamy is an exception rather than the rule and is traditionally restricted to men who can manage things, and in some countries it is illegal for a man to marry multiple wives if he is unable to afford to take care of each of them properly.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

In the modern Islamic world, polygamy is mainly found in {{Citation needed|date=September 2007}} [[Saudi Arabia]], and West and East Africa; in Sudan it was encouraged by the president in 2001 to increase the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/1493309.stm |title=Omar Hassan al-Bashir, has urged Sudanese men to take more than one wife to increase the population |publisher=BBC News |date=2001-08-15 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the 22 member states of the [[Arab League]], [[Tunisia]] alone explicitly prohibits polygamy; however, it is generally frowned upon in many of the more secularized Arab states, such as [[Egypt]]. Few other countries including [[Libya]] and [[Morocco]] require the written permission of the first wife if her husband wishes to marry a second, third, or fourth wife.

===Judaism===
{{See also|Pilegesh}}
Multiple marriage was considered a realistic alternative in the case of famine, widowhood, or female infertility&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Freeman |first=Tzvi |url=http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/770990/jewish/Why-does-Torah-law-allow-polygamy.htm |title=Chabad.org |publisher=Chabad.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; like in the practice of [[levirate marriage]], wherein a man was required to marry and support his deceased brother's [[widow]], as mandated by {{Bibleverse||Deuteronomy|25:5–10}}. Despite its prevalence in the [[Hebrew bible]], scholars do not believe that polygyny was commonly practiced in the biblical era because it required a significant amount of wealth.&lt;ref&gt;Gene McAfee  [http://www.oxfordreference.com/views/ENTRY.html?subview=Main&amp;entry=t120.e0669 &quot;Sex&quot;]  The Oxford Companion to the Bible. Bruce M. Metzger and Michael D. Coogan, eds. Oxford University Press Inc. 1993. Oxford Reference Online. Oxford University Press. 19 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Michael Coogan]], in contrast, states that, ″Polygyny continued to be practised well into the biblical period, and it is attested among Jews as late as the second century CE.″&lt;ref name=coogan&gt;{{cite book|last=Coogan|first1=Michael|title=God and Sex. What the Bible Really Says|url=http://books.google.nl/books?id=2_gPKQEACAAJ&amp;dq=god+and+sex&amp;hl=nl&amp;ei=4fbCTaPKDpGXOrq88Z0I&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwAQ|accessdate=May 5, 2011|edition=1st|year=2010|month=October|publisher=Twelve. Hachette Book Group|location=New York, Boston|isbn=978-0-446-54525-9|page=78}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Torah]], Judaism's central text, includes a few specific regulations on the practice of polygamy, such as Exodus 21:10: ″If he take another wife for himself; her food, her clothing, and her duty of marriage, shall he not diminish″&lt;ref name=&quot;TJBEX2110&quot;&gt;''The Jerusalem Bible: The Holy Scriptures''.  Ed. Harold Fisch. Trans. Fisch.  Jerusalem: Koren Publishers Jerusalem LTD., 1980.  Print.&lt;/ref&gt;. {{Niv|Deut|21:15–17|Deuteronomy 21:15–17}}, states that a man must award the inheritance due to a first-born son to the son who was actually born first, even if he hates that son's mother and likes another wife more;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt0521.htm#15 Deuteronomy 21:15–17] from mechon-mamre.org&lt;/ref&gt; and {{Niv|Deut|17:17|Deuteronomy 17:17}} states that the king shall not have too many wives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chabad.org/library/article.asp?AID=9981&amp;showrashi=true Judaica Press Complete Tanach, Devarim - Chapter 17] from [[Chabad.org]]&lt;/ref&gt; The king's behavior is condemned by Prophet Samuel in {{kjv|1Samuel|1:8|1 Samuel 8}}.  (The understanding of the Jewish perspective on co-wives may also be derived from the Hebrew word for co-wife found in the [[Tanakh]], &quot;צרה&quot; [Tza'rah], which forms the same root as the Yiddush word, &quot;צרות&quot; [Tzoo'rus], meaning &quot;trouble&quot;.) It is important to note, as explained by Israeli lexicographer Vadim Cherny, that the Torah carefully distinguishes concubines and &quot;sub-standard&quot; wives with prefix &quot;to&quot; (lit. &quot;took to wives&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://vadimcherny.org/judaism/women_similar_wives.htm Women, similar to wives] from vadimcherny.org&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite these nuances to the biblical perspective on polygamy, many important figures had more than wife, such as in the instances of Esau (Gen 26:34; 28:6-9)&lt;ref name=&quot;TJBEX2110&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;, Jacob (Gen 29:15-28)&lt;ref name=&quot;TJBEX2110&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;, Elkanah (1 Samuel 1:1-8)&lt;ref name=&quot;TJBEX2110&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;, David (1 Samuel 25:39-44; 2 Samuel 3:2-5; 5:13-16)&lt;ref name=&quot;TJBEX2110&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;, and Solomon (1 Kings 11:1-3)&lt;ref name=&quot;TJBEX2110&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;.

The monogamy of the [[Roman Empire]] was the cause of two explanatory notes in the writings of [[Josephus]] describing how the polygamous marriages of [[Herod the Great|Herod]] were permitted under Jewish custom.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Jewish Family: Metaphor and Memory&quot;, [[David Charles Kraemer]], p21, Oxford University Press US, 1989, ISBN 0-19-505467-9&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- The following paragraph is copied almost verbatim from Encyclopedia Biblica
The [[Talmud]]ists formulate the rule that no Jew may have more than four wives; kings may have at the most eighteen. The ordinary Israelite at all times would doubtless have to be content with one secondary wife in addition to the principal wife, or at most with two wives. The last-named arrangement seems to receive the sanction of widely-diffused custom ({{niv|1Sam|1:2|1Sam. 1:2}}, {{niv|Deut|21:15|Deut. 21:15}}, {{niv|2Chron|24:3|2Chron. 24:3}}; cp the case of [[Jacob]]). When the first wife proved childless, polygamy was regarded as a necessity.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Marriage&quot;, ''[[Encyclopedia Biblica]]''&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

Rabbi Chaim Gruber speculates that the underlying reason why the Torah allows a man more than one wife at a time, while a woman is permitted only one husband at a time, is biological.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YP3a_AxQsHY 2 min. video of Rabbi Gruber discussing polygamy] from www.YouTube.com&lt;/ref&gt;:  No one could argue that a man has the ability to simultaneously father children with more than one woman.  However, it is improbable for a woman to become simultaneously pregnant from more than one man.  Therefore, as “marriage,” in strict or broad sense, means a joining together, as the genes of a man can simultaneously be joined together with the genes of multiple women via different conceptions, a man, Rabbi Gruber states, can be married to more than one woman at once.  A woman, however, is not naturally so joined to more than one man at a time.  This considered, the rabbi speculates that the intent of the allowance of polygamy is “not to say that monogamous marriage isn’t ideal,” but rather to create a social structure inclusive of this natural phenomenon; “…as a man may be linked to several women at once, it is better to consider these multiple relationships legit, than to criminalize them and put them outside the bounds of normality.  Doing so would wrongly shame many as ‘living in sin,’ and also unjustly condemn countless kids as ‘bastards’.”

The Rabbinical era that began with the destruction of the second temple in Jerusalem in 70 CE saw a continuation of some degree of legal acceptance for polygamy.  In the [[Talmud|Babylonian Talmud (BT)]], Kiddushin 7a, its states, &quot;[[Rabbah bar Nahmani|Raba]] said: [If a man declares,] ′Be thou betrothed to half of me,′ she is betrothed: ′half of thee be betrothed to me,′ she is not betrothed.″&lt;ref name=&quot;BTK7a&quot;&gt;''Babylonian Talmud: Kiddushin 7a''. halakhah.com, n.d.  7a.  Web.  25 Oct. 2012&lt;/ref&gt;  The BT during a discussion of [[Levirate marriage]] in Yevamot 65a appears to repeat the precedent found in Exodus 21:10: ″[[Rabbah bar Nahmani|Raba]] said: a man may marry wives in addition to the first wife; provided only that he possesses the means to maintain them.″&lt;ref name=&quot;BTY65a&quot;&gt;''Babylonian Talmud: Yevamot 65a''. halakhah.com, n.d.  5a.  Web.  25 Oct. 2012&lt;/ref&gt;  The Jewish Codices began a process of restricting polygamy in Judaism.  The [[Maimonides|Rambam's]] [[Mishneh Torah]], while maintaining the right to multiple spouses, and the requirement to provide fully for each as indicated in previously cited sources, went further: ″He may not, however, compel his wives to live in the same courtyard.  Instead, each one is entitled to her own household.″&lt;ref name=&quot;MTI143&quot;&gt;''Mishneh Torah: Laws of Matrimoney 14:3''. chabad.org, n.d.  Web.  25 Oct. 2012.  http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/682956/jewish/Mishneh-Torah.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  Finally, the most authoritative codex, the [[Shulchan Aruch]], builds on all of the previous works by adding further nuances: ″…but in any event, our sages have advised well not to marry more than four wives, in order that he can meet their conjugal needs at least once a month.  And in a place where it is customary to marry only one wife, he is not permitted to take another wife on top of his present wife.″&lt;ref name=&quot;SAEH19&quot;&gt;''Shulkhan Aruch: Even Ha'ezer 1:9'' en.wikisource.org, n.d.  Web 25 Oct. 2012.  http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Shulchan_Aruch/Even_ha-Ezer/1&lt;/ref&gt;  As can be seen, while the tradition of the Rabbinic period began with providing legal definition for the practice of polygamy (although this does not indicate the frequency with which polygamy in fact occurred) that corresponded to precedents in the tanakh, by the time of the Codices the Rabbis had greatly reduced or eliminated sanction of the practice.

Most notable in the Rabbinic period on the issue of polygamy, though more specifically for [[Ashkenazi Jews]], was the synod of [[Gershom ben Judah|Rabbeinu Gershom]].  ″About 1000 CE he called a synod which decided the following particulars: (1) prohibition of polygamy; (2) necessity of obtaining the consent of both parties to a divorce; (3) modification of the rules concerning those who became apostates under compulsion; (4) prohibition against opening correspondence addressed to another.″&lt;ref name&quot;WCGBJW&quot;&gt;Wikipedia contributors. &quot;Gershom ben Judah.&quot; Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia. Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia, 26 Apr. 2012. Web. 25 Oct. 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  These prohibitions remained in force for one thousand years.

In the modern day, polygamy is uncommon in [[Rabbinic Judaism]], especially among European Jews.  [[Ashkenazi Jews]] have continued to follow [[Rabbenu Gershom]]'s ban since the 11th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.faqs.org/faqs/judaism/FAQ/04-Observance/section-55.html Judaism and Polygamy:] &quot;Originally, Gershom's ban was limited in time to the year 1260,&quot; and a man &quot;could marry more than one wife if he obtained the special permission of 100 rabbis in 3 countries.&quot; From faqs.org&lt;/ref&gt; Some [[Sephardi]] and [[Mizrahi]] Jews (particularly those from [[North Africa]], [[Yemen]], [[Kurdistan]], and [[Iran]]) discontinued polygamy much more recently, as they emigrated to countries where it was forbidden. However polygamy still occurs in non-European Jewish communities that exist in countries where it is not forbidden, such as Jewish communities in Yemen and the Arab world. 

Among [[Karaite Jews]], who do not adhere to Rabbinic interpretations of the Torah, polygamy is almost non-existent today. Like other Jews, Karaites interpret {{Bibleverse||Leviticus|18:18}} to mean that a man can only take a second wife if his first wife gives her consent (Keter Torah on Leviticus, pp.&amp;nbsp;96–97) and Karaites interpret Exodus 21:10 to mean that a man can only take a second wife if he is capable of maintaining the same level of marital duties due to his first wife; the marital duties are 1) food, 2) clothing, and 3) sexual gratification. Because of these two biblical limitations and because most countries outlaw it, polygamy is considered highly impractical, and there are only a few known cases of it among Karaite Jews today.

[[Israel]], in accordance with Western ethics, has made polygamy illegal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Eglash |first=Ruth |url=http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1225199601867&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull |title=Israel 2008: State of Polygamy |publisher=Fr.jpost.com |date=2008-10-30 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Aburabia |first=Sarab |url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1027756.html |title=Victims of polygamy |publisher=Haaretz.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Provisions were instituted to allow for existing polygamous families immigrating from countries where the practice was legal. Furthermore, former chief rabbi [[Ovadia Yosef]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wwrn.org/article.php?idd=13900&amp;sec=40&amp;con=35 ''Polygamy's Practice Stirs Debate in Israel'']&lt;/ref&gt; has come out in favor of legalizing polygamy and the practice of [[pilegesh]] (concubine) by the Israeli government.

[[Tzvi Zohar]], a professor from the [[Bar-Ilan University]], recently suggested that based on the opinions of leading halachic authorities, the concept of concubines may serve as a practical [[Halacha|Halachic]] justification for premarital or non-marital cohabitation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Navon |first=Emmanuel |url=http://www.jpost.com/JewishWorld/JewishFeatures/Article.aspx?id=16328 |title=Kosher Sex Without Marriage, a Jerusalem Post article that discusses Jacob Emden's and Tzvi Zohar's views |publisher=Jpost.com |date=2006-03-16 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pilegeshpersonals.com/Pilegesh%20Tzvi%20Zohar.pdf |title=Tzvi Zohar's comprehensive academic research on the subject, Akdamot Journal for Jewish Thought 17, 2003, Beit Morasha Press (in Hebrew) |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Polygamy by country==
{{main|Legal status of polygamy}}
In countries that do not permit polygamy, the practice is considered [[bigamy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LawLibraryBigamy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://law.jrank.org/pages/2102/Sex-Offenses-Consensual-Bigamy.html |title=Sex Offenses: Consensual - Bigamy |work=Law Library - American Law and Legal Information |accessdate=2009-05-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In countries where polygamy is outlawed, consent from a prior spouse makes no difference to the validity of the second marriage and the second marriage is considered legally null and void. Laws usually do exist to protect the rights of an unsuspecting second spouse and any children from the otherwise invalid marriage.

===Africa===
Polygamy existed all over Africa as an aspect of culture or/and religion. Plural marriages have been more common than not in the [[history of Africa]]. Many African societies saw children as a form of wealth thus the more children a family had the more powerful it was. Thus polygamy was part of empire building. It was only during the colonial era that plural marriage was perceived as taboo. Esther Stanford, an African-focused lawyer, states that this decline was encouraged because the issues of property ownership conflicted with European colonial interest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.africanholocaust.net/news_ah/africanmarriageritual.html Polygamy in Africa] - Polygamy in Africa&lt;/ref&gt; Polygamy is very common in [[West Africa]]. However, the diffusion of Islam to this region has decreased the prevalence of polygamy in this region, due to restrictions on number of wives.&lt;ref&gt;See {{cite book  |title=World Religions and Social Evolution of the Old World Oikumene Civilizations: A Cross-cultural Perspective   |url=http://www.mellenpress.com/mellenpress.cfm?bookid=6102&amp;pc=9  |edition=First |last=Korotayev |first=Andrey  | authorlink=Andrey Korotayev |publisher=Edwin Mellen Press |location=Lewiston, New York |year=2004 |isbn=0-7734-6310-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.africanmarriage.info Polygamy and Marriage in Africa] - Polygamy in Africa&lt;/ref&gt;

====Kenya====
Polygamy is widespread in [[Kenya]], the most prominent individual being [[Akuku Danger]] who married over 100 wives.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc_ref&quot; &gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/661527.stm |title=Polygamist marries 100 times |publisher=BBC News |date=2000-02-29 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Nigeria====
After a BBC television interview with [[Mohammed Bello Abubakar]], articles were published in newspapers around the world about his 86 wives and 170 children, and he faced the death penalty under Sharia law if he did not divorce 82 of them.&lt;ref name=death&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/7574757.stm |title=Nigerian faces death for 86 wives |publisher=BBC News |date=2008-08-21 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====South Africa====
In [[South Africa]], traditionalists commonly practice polygamy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://allafrica.com/stories/200803170605.html South Africa Polygamy debate]&lt;/ref&gt; The president, [[Jacob Zuma]] is also openly in favor of plural marriages, being married to three wives himself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/8037900.stm Jacob Zuma's three first ladies], [[BBC]], May 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; He has a total of twenty-nine children with these and four previous wives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2010/01/04/2785364.htm Hundreds arrive in village for Zuma's fifth wedding] - [[ABC Online]], January 4, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sudan====
Sudanese President [[Omar Hassan al-Bashir]] has encouraged multiple marriages to increase the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/1493309.stm |title=Omar Hassan al-Bashir has urged Sudanese men to take more than one wife to increase the population |publisher=BBC News |date=2001-08-15 |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===East Asia===
The [[Chinese culture]] of [[Confucianism]] and thus the practice of polygamy spread from China to [[Japan]] and areas that are now [[Vietnam]]. Before their modernizations, East Asian countries permitted similar practices of polygamy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.demog.berkeley.edu/~ebenstei/litreview/Kang_04.pdf The Legacy Lingers On: Research Fellow, University of California, Berkeley]&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2011 opinion poll showed that most Malaysians and Indonesians youth opposed polygamy. The results were considered &quot;remarkable&quot; given that the youth were otherwise religiously conservative&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2011/07/12/poll-young-malaysia-indonesia-oppose-polygamy.html |title=Poll: Young in Malaysia, Indonesia oppose polygamy |publisher=Thejakartapost.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; (those surveyed advocated the [[hijab]] for women, and opposed premarital sex).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=France |first=Agence |url=http://news.ph.msn.com/regional/article.aspx?cp-documentid=5037881 |title=Most Malaysian youths reject polygamy: poll |publisher=News.ph.msn.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
====China====
Throughout the [[history of China]], it had been common for the rich and influential Chinese men to have several wives wife and various [[concubinage|concubines]], while poor commoners would have one wife.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} Polygamy in China is considered to be a by-product of the tradition of emphasis on procreation and the continuity of the father's family name.&lt;!-- this ref does not support the sentence it is attached to [http://www.exeas.org/resources/your-honor.html]--&gt;{{Citation needed|date=April 2007}} Although the establishment of the [[Republic of China]] made it explicitly unlawful for a man to have multiple spouses/concubines, such legislation were generally not enforced, especially among the societal elites who were most likely to live such lifestyles.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} The most serious changes occurred during and after the Communist Revolution, where traditions considered backward and feudal (such as concubinage, foot-binding, slavery, prostitution, etc.) were thoroughly outlawed and severely punished for.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} It is illegal in modern China to have more than one spouse for either sex.

====Hong Kong====
In [[Hong Kong]], polygamy was banned in October 1971.&lt;!-- these websites do not support the sentence it is cited for [http://www.immd.gov.hk/ehtml/bdmreg_4.htm][http://law.hku.hk/lmsf/Law%20on%20Marriage.pdf]--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Man-Lun Ng&quot;&gt;[http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/IES/hongkong.html#2 Hong Kong], article by Man-Lun Ng, M.D.; part of [http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/IES/ &quot;The International Encyclopedia of Sexuality&quot;] Volume I – IV 1997–2001, Edited by Robert T. Francoeur&lt;/ref&gt; Kevin Murphy of ''[[The International Herald Tribune]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;lang-smart&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author= Graeme Lang, Josephine Smart |title= Migration and the &quot;second wife&quot; in South China: Toward cross-border polygamy |journal= The International Migration Review |year= 2002 |volume= 36 |issue= 5 |pages= 546–569}}&lt;/ref&gt; reports the cross-border polygyny phenomenon between China and Hong Kong in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/1995/02/07/lunar.php Hong Kong Targets Its Two-Family Men], Kevin Murphy, International Herald Tribune, Tuesday, February 7, 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Asia===
Polygyny, permitted under [[Sharia|Islamic law]], is present amongst some Muslims in South Asia.

Polygamy is illegal in India for Hindus and other religious groups under the [[Hindu marriage Act]].  It remains legal for Muslims under the terms of [[The Muslim Personal Law (Shariat) Application Act]] of 1937, as interpreted by the [[All India Muslim Personal Law Board]].  .&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/news/sunday-toi/view-from-venus/Bigamy-An-issue-of-one-too-many/articleshow/5004493.cms | work=The Times of India | title=Bigamy: An issue of one too many | first=Divya | last=A | date=13 September 2009 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=Fn7GhTpJ4esC&amp;pg=PA148&amp;lpg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Communal Politics: Facts Versus Myths]''&quot;. [[Ram Puniyani]]. p.148. ISBN 0-7619-9667-2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=uDVHN6xkdiMC&amp;pg=PA78#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Mullahs on the Mainframe: Islam and Modernity Among the Daudi Bohras]''&quot;. Jonah Blank. p.78. ISBN 0-226-05676-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

Polygamy is generally quite rare in urban areas, and among the cosmopolitan middle classes.

===Thailand===
Until polygamy was outlawed by [[Vajiravudh|King Rama VI]], it was expected that wealthy or upper-class Thai men were historically recognized to maintain mansions consisting of multiple wives and their children in the same residence. Among the [[Chakri Dynasty|royalty]] and courtiers in the past, wives were classified as principal, secondary, and [[History of slavery#Southeast Asia|slave]]. Today, the tradition of minor wives still remains, but the practice is different from that of the past. Due to the expense involved, minor wives are mostly limited to the wealthy men. While a &quot;proper woman&quot; (Kulasatrii; [[Thai language|Thai]]: กุลสตรี) must remain faithful to her husband, there were no equivalent rules in history mandating fidelity in the &quot;virtuous man.&quot;

Regardless of the historical acceptance, male polygamy or [[plural marriage]] is no longer legally or socially acceptable in the contemporary Thai society. However, the practice of having &quot;minor wives&quot; (Mia-Noi: เมียน้อย) continues in modern days in secrecy from the &quot;primary wife&quot; (Mia-Luang: เมียหลวง).&lt;ref&gt;Interpersonal Heterosexual Behaviors of Thai People, [http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/IES/thailand.html#5 Extramarital Sex]&lt;/ref&gt; Almost all married Thai women today object to this practice, and indeed for many it has been grounds for divorce.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tillekeandgibbins.com/publications/pdf/rights_husband_wife.pdf The rights of husband and wife], Family Law in Thailand&lt;/ref&gt; Minor wives are viewed with contempt by the Thai society along the lines of being amoral women or home breakers.&lt;ref&gt;A research on [http://htc.anu.edu.au/pdfs/Knodel1.pdf Thai view of sexuality and sexual behavior] funded by the Rockefeller Foundation and conducted jointly by the Institute of Population Studies, Chulalongkorn University and Mahidol University, Bangkok, the Population Studies Center, University of Michigan and the Department of Sociology, University of Washington.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legalization==
===Nazi Germany===
In [[Nazi Germany]], there was an effort by [[Martin Bormann]] and [[Heinrich Himmler]] to introduce new legislation concerning plural marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;fest686&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Fest |first=Joachim C. |authorlink=Joachim Fest |title=Hitler |publisher=Verlagg Ulstein |year=1973|page=686|isbn=0-15-602754-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The argument ran that after the war, 3 to 4 million women would have to remain unmarried due to the great number of soldiers fallen in battle. In order to make it possible for these women to have children, a procedure for application and selection for suitable men (i.e. decorated war heroes) to enter a marital relationship with an additional woman was planned.&lt;ref name=&quot;fest686&quot;/&gt; The privileged position of the first wife was to be secured by awarding her the title ''[[Dominus (title)|Domina]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;fest686&quot;/&gt;

{{blockquote|The greatest fighter deserves the most beautiful woman ... If the German man is to be unreservedly ready to die as a soldier, he must have the freedom to love unreservedly. For struggle and love belong together. The [[Philistinism|philistine]] should be glad if he gets whatever is left|Adolf Hitler|&lt;ref name=&quot;fest686&quot;/&gt;}}

===United States===
[[David D. Friedman|David Friedman]] and [[Steve Sailer]] have argued that polygamy tends to benefit most women and disadvantage most men, under the assumption that most men and women do not practice it. The idea is firstly that many women would prefer half or one third of someone especially appealing to being the single spouse of someone that does not provide as much economic utility to them. Secondly, that the remaining women have a better market for finding a spouse themselves. Say that 20% of women are married to 10% of men, that leaves 90% of men to compete over the remaining 80% of women. Friedman uses this viewpoint to argue in favor of legalizing polygamy, while Sailer uses it to argue against legalizing it.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

In the US, the [[Libertarian Party (United States)|Libertarian Party]] supports complete decriminalization of polygamy as part of a general belief that the government should not regulate marriages.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azlp.org/platform.php#polygamy]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Individualist feminism]] and advocates such as [[Wendy McElroy]] also support the freedom for adults to voluntarily enter polygamous marriages.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

The [[American Civil Liberties Union]] of Utah is opposed to Utah's law against [[cohabitation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aclu.org/religion/frb/16163prs19990716.html ACLU of Utah to Join Polygamists in Bigamy Fight], 16 July 1999 press release.&lt;/ref&gt;

Those who advocate a [[Federal Marriage Amendment]] to the American Constitution to prohibit [[same-sex marriage]] generally word their proposed laws to also prohibit polygamy. Many proponents of [[same-sex marriage]] are also in favour of maintaining current statutory prohibitions against polygamy.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

Stanley Kurtz, a fellow at the Hudson Institute, lamented the modern arguments increasingly being made by various intellectuals who call for de-criminalizing polygamy. Kurtz concluded, ''&quot;Marriage, as its ultramodern critics would like to say, is indeed about choosing one's partner, and about freedom in a society that values freedom. But that's not the only thing it is about. As the Supreme Court justices who unanimously decided Reynolds in 1878 understood, marriage is also about sustaining the conditions in which freedom can thrive. Polygamy in all its forms is a recipe for social structures that inhibit and ultimately undermine social freedom and democracy. A hard-won lesson of Western history is that genuine democratic self-rule begins at the hearth of the monogamous family.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theweeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/012/266jhfgd.asp &quot;Polygamy vs. Democracy&quot;] The Weekly Standard, June 5, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Polygamy in fiction and popular culture==

===Science fiction, utopias, dystopias===
A number of writers have expressed their views on polygamy by writing about a fictional world in which it is the most common type of relationship. These worlds tend to be [[utopian]] or [[dystopian]] in nature.

For instance, [[Robert A. Heinlein]] uses this theme in a number of novels, such as ''[[Stranger in a Strange Land]]'', as well as his later works such as ''[[Time Enough for Love]]'', ''[[Number of the Beast]]'', and ''[[The Cat Who Walks Through Walls]].''

Conversely, [[Fritz Leiber]] explores polyandry in a 1951 story, ''Nice Girl with Five Husbands''.

Polygamy is practiced by the Fremen in [[Frank Herbert]]'s ''[[Dune (novel)|Dune]]'' as a means to pinpoint male infertility. It is socially accepted as long as the man provides for all wives equally. Cultures described within the [[Dune universe|Dune]] novel series have intentional similarities to Islamic, Arab, and other cultures – i.e. desert cultures.

Similarly, the [[Aiel]] society in [[Robert Jordan]]'s ''[[The Wheel of Time]]'' series practice a form of polygamy, in which multiple women may marry the same man; in that fictional culture, women are the ones who propose marriage. Among Aiel, sisters or very close friends who have adopted each other as sisters, will often marry the same man, so that he will not come between them. 

[[Ursula K. Le Guin]] describes a planet [[Planets of the Hainish Cycle#O|O]], where the cultural norm is a &quot;sedoretu&quot; or four-person marriage (a set combination of both genders and sexual orientations).

[[Dan Simmons]] describes a culture of three-person marriages (any gender ratio) in his book ''[[Endymion (Hyperion Cantos)|Endymion]]''.

In [[David Weber]]'s ''[[Honorverse|Honor Harrington]]'' series, the inhabitants of the planet [[Grayson (Honorverse)|Grayson]] practice polygamy ([[polygyny]]) due to the human colonists to the planet acquiring a genetic defect that gave rise to a large women-to-men birth ratio combined with a high [[infant mortality]]. [[Honor Harrington]] herself is married to [[Hamish Alexander]] as his second wife alongside [[Emily Alexander (Honorverse)|Emily Alexander]]. Their surname then becomes Alexander-Harrington.

[[Wen Spencer]]'s [[science fiction]] novel ''[http://www.wenspencer.com/abrothersprice.html A Brother's Price]'' describes a society where men are very rare and protected, and multiple sisters typically marry one man. In the novel Ruins of Isis, mention is made of a culture where a type of group marriage is performed-a group of 4 people minimum, two men, two women to start.

In the [[Star Trek]] television series ''[[Star Trek: Enterprise|Enterprise]]'', the ship's physician, [[Dr. Phlox]] (who is a Denobulan) has three wives, each of whom has three husbands of her own (including him). One of his wives seemed to be interested in having extramarital relations with a human, which Phlox himself did not oppose, and even encouraged.  Polygamy and open marriages are the societal norm on Denobula and many Denobulans have difficulty understanding how other alien races endure less-complicated couplings.  It has also been stated that the [[Andorian]] species enter into [[group marriage]]s (although whether this is due to societal custom or biological necessity has not been established onscreen, but left to [[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine relaunch]] original novels.)

In the [[Sci-Fi]] television series ''[[Babylon 5]]'' the Centauris allow for men to have more than one wife. In ''[[Star Wars]]'' [[Star Wars Expanded Universe|Expanded Universe]], it is explained that [[List of Star Wars races (A–E)#Cerean|Cereans]] (like [[Ki-Adi-Mundi]]) have a much higher birth-rate of girls than boys. Thus, every male Cerean must have one wife and multiple &quot;honor wives&quot;, to increase the chance of giving birth to another male. Jedi Cerean Ki-Adi-Mundi was allowed to marry multiple times, although Jedi were not supposed to marry at his time; but Ki-Adi-Mundi got a dispense of that norm.

===Prehistoric and historic fiction===
[[Jean M. Auel]] in the pre-historic ''[[Earth's Children]]'' series depicted several instances of &quot;co-mating,&quot; where a person could have more than one mate. Examples included the headwoman Tulie in the ''[[The Mammoth Hunters]]'', and a man who married twins in the ''[[The Shelters of Stone]]''. Also of note was Vincavec, the headman of the Mammoth Camp who wished to mate with the protagonist [[Ayla (Earth's Children)|Ayla]] and was willing to take her Promised, Ranec, implying a bisexual relationship as well.

In the [[Culture of China|Chinese]] ''[[Wuxia]]'' novel ''[[The Deer and the Cauldron]]'' by [[Hong Kong]] writer [[Jin Yong|Louis Cha]], set in the [[Qing Dynasty]] era during the reign of the [[Kangxi Emperor]], the protagonist [[Wei Xiaobao]] has seven wives. The novel has spawned numerous film and TV series adaptations since the 1960s.

===Contemporary setting===
Random House published [[David Ebershoff]]'s novel ''[[The 19th Wife]]'' in 2008. It is about [[Ann Eliza Young]], one of Brigham Young's wives, and the legacy of Mormon polygamy in the United States today. &quot;The Chosen One&quot; was written by Carol Lynch Williams. It was published in 2009, and is the story of a young girl named Kyra who runs away from her Christian polygamist Compound. ''[[A Home at the End of the World]]'' is a novel by [[Michael Cunningham]] about a polygamous family. It was later adapted into a film. Both explore issues of homosexuality and families. ''[[Big Love]]'' is an [[HBO]] series about a polygamous family in Utah in the first decade of the 21st century. In the series, [[Bill Henrickson]] has eight children (and one step-daughter) with his wives Barb, Nikki, Margene (and another child with Ana), who belong to a fundamentalist Mormon splinter group. ''Big Love'' explores the complex legal, moral, and religious issues associated with polygamy in Utah. Henrickson's three wives each have separate houses beside one another, with a shared backyard. By outward appearances, he lives with his primary wife, and has two &quot;friends&quot; living close by, while in reality taking turns sleeping at a different house each night. Henrickson effectively balances his work, the continuing demands of his wives, and his wives' relatives.

In September 2010 [[TLC (TV channel)|TLC]] premiered a reality television series entitled ''[[Sister Wives (TV series)|Sister Wives]]'', which deals with polygamy by a self-described fundamentalist Mormon family in modern day Utah.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesunion.com/entertainment/article/TLC-tackles-polygamy-with-Sister-Wives-673086.php Timesunion.com]{{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 13, 2011, the show's husband and his wives filed a complaint in United States District Court to challenge Utah's law against polygamy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Whitehurst |first=Lindsey |title='Sister Wives' polygamy lawsuit tackles privacy in Utah |work=[[The Salt Lake Tribune]] |date=July 13, 2011 |url=http://www.sltrib.com/sltrib/sports/52182460-78/turley-browns-family-privacy.html.csp |accessdate=July 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Hypergamy]]
*[[Marriage (conflict)#Polygamy]]
*[[More danico]]
*[[Polyandry]]
*[[Promiscuity]]
*[[Triad (relationship)]]

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book |author= Cairncross, John |title= After Polygamy Was Made a Sin: The Social History of Christian Polygamy |location= London | publisher=Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul |year= 1974 |url= http://www.patriarchpublishinghouse.com/3345.htm }}
* {{Cite book |author= Campbell, James |title= The History and Philosophy of Marriage |publisher= First published in Boston |year= 1869 }}
* {{cite book |author= Chapman, Samuel A. |title= Polygamy, Bigamy and Human Rights Law |publisher= Xlibris Corp |year= 2001 |isbn= 1-4010-1244-2 }}
* {{cite book |author= Hillman, Eugene |title= Polygamy Reconsidered: African Plural Marriage and the Christian Churches |location= New York |publisher= Orbis Books |isbn= 0-88344-391-0 |year= 1975 }}
* {{cite book |title= World Religions and Social Evolution of the Old World Oikumene Civilizations: A Cross-cultural Perspective |edition= First |last= Korotayev |first= Andrey |authorlink= Andrey Korotayev |publisher= Edwin Mellen Press |location= Lewiston, New York |year= 2004 |isbn= 0-7734-6310-0 }}
* {{cite book |author= Main Street Church |title= Lifting the Veil of Polygamy |publisher= Main Street Church |year= 2007; Video Documentary |url= http://www.mscbc.org/video/vid_lvp.htm }}
* {{cite book |author= Van Wagoner, Richard S. |authorlink=Richard S. Van Wagoner |url=  |title= Mormon Polygamy: A History |edition= 2nd |year= 1992 |location= Utah |publisher= Signature Books |isbn= 0-941214-79-6 }}
* {{cite book |first= E. O. |last= Wilson |authorlink= E. O. Wilson |title= Sociobiology: The New Synthesis |publisher= Harvard Univ Pr |year= 2000 |isbn= 0-674-00235-0 }}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Wikisource|Portal:Polygamy|Polygamy}}
{{Commons category-inline|Polygamy}}
* [http://signaturebookslibrary.org/?p=425 The Four Major Periods of Mormon Polygamy], essay by [[Todd M. Compton]], hosted by [[Signature Books]]
* [http://www.africanmarriage.info#polygamy Polygamy in Africa]
* [http://shamash.org/lists/scj-faq/HTML/faq/08-06.html History of Polygamy in Judaism]
* [http://www.life.com/image/first/in-gallery/49551/rare-life-with-polygamists-1944 LIFE With Polygamists, 1944] - slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''

{{Close plural relationships}}

[[Category:Greek loanwords]]
[[Category:Mating systems]]
[[Category:Polygamy| ]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]

&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;
[[af:Poligamie]]
[[ar:تعدد الزوجات]]
[[an:Poligamia]]
[[be:Палігамія]]
[[be-x-old:Палігамія]]
[[bg:Полигамия]]
[[br:Liespriediezh]]
[[ca:Poligàmia]]
[[cs:Polygamie]]
[[da:Polygami]]
[[de:Polygamie]]
[[et:Polügaamia]]
[[es:Poligamia]]
[[eo:Poligamio]]
[[eu:Poligamia]]
[[fa:چندهمسری]]
[[fr:Polygamie]]
[[gl:Poligamia]]
[[hr:Poligamija]]
[[id:Poligami]]
[[it:Poligamia]]
[[he:פוליגמיה]]
[[ka:პოლიგამია]]
[[sw:Mitara]]
[[mk:Многуженство]]
[[arz:بوليجاميه]]
[[ms:Poligami]]
[[nl:Polygamie]]
[[ja:複婚]]
[[no:Polygami]]
[[nn:Polygami]]
[[pl:Poligamia]]
[[pt:Poligamia]]
[[ro:Poligamie]]
[[ru:Полигамия]]
[[sah:Полигамия]]
[[simple:Polygamy]]
[[sk:Polygamia]]
[[sr:Полигамија]]
[[fi:Polygamia]]
[[sv:Polygami]]
[[ta:பலதுணை மணம்]]
[[te:బహుభార్యాత్వం]]
[[tr:Poligami]]
[[uk:Полігамія]]
[[ur:تعدد ازواج]]
[[zh:多配偶制]]</text>
      <sha1>3o1yd64ixbelnkw3u6hbmkdungp8mdk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
