<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Stalking</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25272420</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517846139</id>
      <parentid>517846088</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-15T02:07:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>XLinkBot</username>
        <id>6163802</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>BOT--Reverting link addition(s) by [[:en:Special:Contributions/OctoberReignz|OctoberReignz]] to revision 517066168 (http://www.youtube.com/user/BoohooUKTROLLwinning [\byoutube\.com])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39433">{{about||the stalking of deer|deer stalking|visiting near Chernobyl|Chernobyl stalking}}
{{pp-move-indef}}

'''Stalking''' is a term commonly used to refer to unwanted or obsessive [[attention]] by an individual or group toward another person. Stalking behaviors are related to [[harassment]] and [[intimidation]] and may include following the victim in person or monitoring them. The word ''stalking'' is used, with some differing meanings, in [[psychology]] and [[psychiatry]] and also in some legal [[jurisdiction]]s as a term for a [[criminal offense]].

According to a 2002 report by the [[National Center for Victims of Crime]], &quot;Virtually any unwanted contact between two people [that intends] to directly or indirectly communicates a threat or places the victim in fear can be considered stalking&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ncjrs.gov/ovc_archives/reports/help_series/pdftxt/stalkingvictimization.txt|title=Stalking Victimization|author=National Center for Victims of Crime|publisher=Office for Victims of Crime|date=February 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; although in practice the legal standard is usually somewhat more strict.

==Definitions==
The difficulties associated with precisely defining this term (or defining it at all) are well documented.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
| last1 = Sheridan | first1 = L. P.
| last2 = Blaauw | first2 = E.
| title = Characteristics of False Stalking Reports
| journal = Criminal Justice and Behavior
| volume = 31
| pages = 55–72
| at=56
| year = 2004
| doi = 10.1177/0093854803259235
| quote=Given that stalking may often constitute no more than the targeted repetition of ostensibly ordinary or routine behavior, stalking is inherently difficult to define.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Having been used since at least the 16th century to refer to a prowler or a poacher (''Oxford English Dictionary''), the term ''stalker'' started to be used by the media in the 20th century to describe people who pester and harass others, initially with specific reference to the harassment of celebrities by strangers who were described as being &quot;obsessed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;P. E. Mullen ''et al''. ''Stalkers and Their Victims'', 2nd edition. Cambridge University Press, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; This use of the word appears to have been coined by the [[tabloid press]] in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;Lawson-Cruttenden, 1996, Is there a law against stalking?, New Law Journal/6736 pp.418-420, cited here [http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6VH7-46DFRH8-1&amp;_user=121711&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000009978&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=121711&amp;md5=df75144342f08cd79977352a38757f6b]&lt;/ref&gt; Pathé and Mullen describe stalking as &quot;a constellation of behaviours in which an individual inflicts upon another repeated unwanted intrusions and communications&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1192/bjp.170.1.12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalking can be defined as the willful and repeated following, watching and/or harassing of another person. Unlike other crimes, which usually involve one act, stalking is a series of actions that occur over a period of time. 

Although stalking is illegal in most areas of the world, some of the actions that can contribute to stalking can be legal, such as gathering information, calling someone on the phone, sending gifts, emailing or instant messaging. They become illegal when they breach the legal definition of harassment e.g. an action such as sending a text is not usually illegal, but is illegal when frequently repeated to an unwilling recipient. In fact, United Kingdom law states the incident only has to happen twice when the stalker should be aware their behavior is unacceptable e.g. two phone calls to a stranger, two gifts following the victim then phoning them etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;harass_1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sexualharassmentsupport.org/Stalking.html|title=Stalking|publisher=sexualharassmentsupport.org|accessdate=2010-10-20}}{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Psychology and behaviors==
{{POV-section|date=August 2010}}
People characterized as stalkers may be accused of having a mistaken belief that another person loves them ([[erotomania]]), or that they need rescuing.&lt;ref name=&quot;harass_1&quot; {{dead link|date=August 2012}}/&gt; Stalking can sometimes consist of an accumulation of a series of actions which in themselves can be legal, such as calling on the phone, sending gifts, or sending emails.&lt;ref name=&quot;menace&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sociosite.org/cyberstalking_en.php|title=CyberStalking: menaced on the Internet|publisher=sociosite.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the United Kingdom, government research demonstrates that, despite media reports and research of vested interests, the [[Protection from Harassment Act 1997]] &quot;is rarely used for stalking as portrayed by the media since only a small minority of cases in the survey involved such behaviour&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;harass_3&quot; /&gt;

Stalkers may use threats and violence to frighten their victims. They may also engage in [[vandalism]] and property damage or make physical attacks that are mostly meant to frighten. Less common are sexual assaults.&lt;ref name=&quot;harass_1&quot; {{dead link|date=August 2012}}/&gt;

In the UK, for example, most stalkers are former partners and evidence indicates that the mentally ill stalking type of behaviour propagated in the media occurs in only a minority of cases of alleged stalking.&lt;ref name=&quot;harass_3&quot;/&gt; A UK Home Office research study on the use of the Protection from Harassment Act stated that &quot;The study found that the Protection from Harassment Act is being used to deal with a variety of behaviour such as domestic and inter-neighbour disputes. It is rarely used for stalking as portrayed by the media since only a small minority of cases in the survey involved such behaviour.&lt;ref name=&quot;harass_3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rds.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs/r130.pdf|title=The Protection from Harassment Act 1997 – An Evaluation of its Use and Effectiveness|author=Jessica Harris|publisher=Home Office Research, Development and Statistics Directorate|year=2000|ISSN=1364-6540|accessdate=2010-10-20}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Psychological effects on victims===
Disruptions in daily life necessary to escape the stalker, including changes in [[employment]], residence and phone numbers, may take a toll on the victim's well-being and lead to a sense of isolation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abrams&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Abrams KM and Robinson GE|title=Comprehensive Treatment of Stalking Victims: Practical Steps That Help Ensure Safety|journal=Psychiatric Times |volume=25 |issue=10 |date=September 1, 2008 |url=http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/paranoia/article/10168/1278421}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Lamber Royakkers, &lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Stalking is a form of mental assault, in which the perpetrator repeatedly, unwantedly, and disruptively breaks into the life-world of the victim, with whom they have no relationship (or no longer have). Moreover, the separated acts that make up the intrusion cannot by themselves cause the mental abuse, but do taken together (cumulative effect).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;menace&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Gender studies of stalkers===
According to one study, women often target other women, whereas men generally stalk women only.&lt;ref name=&quot;Women Who Stalk&quot;&gt;Rosemary Purcell, Michele Pathé, and Paul E. Mullen.  [http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/content/full/158/12/2056 A Study of Women Who Stalk. AJP 2001] Am J Psychiatry 158:2056-2060, December 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Types of Stalkers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sexualharassmentsupport.org/TypesofStalkers.html|title=Types of stalkers|publisher=sexualharassmentsupport.org|accessdate=2010-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, a January 2009 report from the [[United States Department of Justice|Department of Justice]] in the United States reports that &quot;Males were as likely to report being stalked by a male as a female offender. 43% of male stalking victims stated that the offender was female, while 41% of male victims stated that the offender was another male. Female victims of stalking were significantly more likely to be stalked by a male (67%) rather than a female (24%) offender.&quot; This report provides considerable data by gender and race about both stalking and harassment.&lt;ref name=&quot;StalkingVictimizationintheUnitedStates&quot;&gt;[http://www.ovw.usdoj.gov/docs/stalking-victimization.pdf &quot;Stalking Victimization in the United States&quot;], [[United States Department of Justice]]&lt;/ref&gt;  The data for this report were obtained via the 2006 Supplemental Victimization Survey (SVS), conducted by the U.S. Census Bureau for the U.S. Department of Justice.&lt;ref name=&quot;SUPPLEMENTALVICTIMIZATIONSURVEY&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=www.ovw.usdoj.gov/docs/stalking-victimization.pdf|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110828151246/http://bjs.ojp.usdoj.gov/content/pub/pdf/svs1_06.pdf|archivedate=2011-08-28|title=SUPPLEMENTAL VICTIMIZATION SURVEY (SVS)|publisher=United States Department of Justice}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Types of stalkers===
Psychologists often group individuals who stalk into two categories: [[psychotic]] and nonpsychotic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stalkers and Victims&quot;&gt;Mullen ''et al.''. ''Stalkers and Their Victims''. Cambridge University Press, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Stalkers may have pre-existing psychotic disorders such as [[delusional disorder]], [[schizoaffective disorder]], or [[schizophrenia]]. Most stalkers are nonpsychotic and may exhibit disorders or [[neuroses]] such as [[clinical depression|major depression]], [[adjustment disorder]], or [[Chemical dependency|substance dependence]], as well as a variety of [[Axis III|Axis II]] [[personality disorder]]s (such as [[Antisocial personality disorder|antisocial]], [[Borderline personality disorder|borderline]], [[Dependent personality disorder|dependent]], [[Narcissistic personality disorder|narcissistic]], or [[Paranoid personality disorder|paranoid]]). Some of the symptoms of &quot;obsessing&quot; over a person is part of [[obsessive compulsive personality disorder]]. The nonpsychotic stalkers' pursuit of victims can be influenced by various psychological factors, including [[anger]], hostility, [[Psychological projection|projection]] of [[blame]], [[wikt:obsession|obsession]], [[behavioral addiction|dependency]], [[Minimisation (psychology)|minimization]], [[denial]], and [[jealousy]]. Conversely, as is more commonly the case, the stalker has no antipathic feelings towards the victim, but simply a longing that cannot be fulfilled due to deficiencies either in their personality or their society's norms.&lt;ref name=&quot;A comparative study of psychotic and nonpsychotic stalking&quot;&gt;KK Kienlen, DL Birmingham, KB Solberg, JT O'Regan, and  Meloy JR. [http://www.jaapl.org/cgi/content/abstract/25/3/317 A comparative study of psychotic and nonpsychotic stalking] J Am Acad Psychiatry Law 25:3:317-334 (1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

In &quot;A Study of Stalkers&quot; Mullen ''et al.''. (2000)&lt;ref name=&quot;Study of Stalkers&quot;&gt;Paul E. Mullen, Michele Pathé, Rosemary Purcell, and Geoffrey W. Stuart.[http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/content/full/156/8/1244 A Study of Stalkers] Am J Psychiatry 156:1244-1249, August 1999&lt;/ref&gt; identified five types of stalkers:
* '''Rejected stalkers''' pursue their victims in order to reverse, correct, or avenge a rejection (e.g. divorce, separation, termination).
* '''Resentful stalkers''' pursue a vendetta because of a sense of grievance against the victims – motivated mainly by the desire to frighten and distress the victim.
* '''[[Obsessive love|Intimacy seekers]]''' seek to establish an intimate, loving relationship with their victim. To many of them the victim is a long-sought-after soul mate, and they were 'meant' to be together.
* '''Incompetent suitors''', despite poor social or courting skills, have a [[fixation (psychology)|fixation]], or in some cases, a sense of [[entitlement]] to an intimate relationship with those who have attracted their amorous interest. Their victims are most often already in a dating relationship with   someone else.
* '''Predatory stalkers''' spy on the victim in order to prepare and plan an attack – often sexual – on the victim.
The 2002 National Victim Association Academy defines an additional form of stalking: The '''vengeance/terrorist stalker'''. Both the vengeance stalker and terrorist stalker (the latter sometimes called the political stalker) ''do not'', in contrast with some of the aforementioned types of stalkers, seek a personal relationship with their victims but rather force them to emit a certain response favourable to the stalker. While the vengeance stalker's motive is &quot;to get even&quot; with the other person whom he/she perceives has done some wrong to them (e.g., an employee who believes is fired without justification from their job by their superior), the political stalker intends to accomplish a political agenda, also using [[threats]] and [[intimidation]] to force his/her target to refrain and/or become involved in some particular activity, regardless of the victim’s consent.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Victim Association Agency 2002 Chapter 22: Special topics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ncjrs.gov/ovc_archives/nvaa2002/chapter22_4.html 2002 National Victim Assistance Academy|title=National Victim Assistance Academy Textbook - Chapter 22 Special Topics - Section 4, Campus Crime and Victimization|date=June 2002|accessdate=2011-08-28|publisher=Office for Victims of Crime}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many stalkers {{Quantify|date=August 2010}} fit categories with [[paranoia disorder]]s. '''Intimacy-seeking stalkers''' often have delusional disorders involving erotomanic delusions. With rejected stalkers, the continual clinging to a relationship of an inadequate or dependent person couples with the entitlement of the narcissistic personality, and the persistent jealousy of the paranoid personality. In contrast, '''resentful stalkers''' demonstrate an almost “pure culture of [[persecution]],” with delusional disorders of the paranoid type, paranoid personalities, and [[paranoid schizophrenia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Study of Stalkers&quot;&gt;
Additionally, the very rarely seen Nathan Lally type stalker creeps up behind people munching on delicious Pita Chips and tries to nab them. Caution should be key when approaching this dangerous predator.&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the uncertainties in understanding the origins of stalking is that the concept is now widely understood in terms of specific behaviors&lt;ref&gt;as a US example, see January 2009 Special Report from the Department of Justice in the US titled [http://www.ncvc.org/src/AGP.Net/Components/DocumentViewer/Download.aspxnz?DocumentID=45862 &quot;Stalking Victimization in the United States&quot;], NCJ 224527&lt;/ref&gt; which are found to be offensive and/or illegal. As discussed above, these specific (apparently stalking) behaviors may have multiple motivations.

In addition, the personality characteristics that are often discussed as antecedent to stalking may also produce behavior that is not stalking as conventionally defined. Some research suggests there is a spectrum of what might be called &quot;obsessed following behavior.&quot; People who complain obsessively and for years, about a perceived wrong or wrong-doer, when no one else can perceive the injury—and people who cannot or will not &quot;let go&quot; of a person or a place or an idea—comprise a wider group of persons that may be problematic in ways that seem similar to stalking. Some of these people get extruded from their organizations—they may get hospitalized or fired or let go if their behavior is defined in terms of illegal stalking, but many others do good or even excellent work in their organizations and appear to have just one focus of tenacious obsession.&lt;ref&gt;(See Mary Rowe, &quot;People With Delusions or Quasi-Delusions Who ‘Won't Let Go’,&quot; Journal of the University and College Ombuds Association, Occasional Paper, Number 1, Fall 1994.)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cyberstalking===
{{main|Cyberstalking}}
Cyberstalking is the use of computers or other electronic technology to facilitate stalking. A booming “spy shop” industry has sprouted up to supply Hi-tech equipment such as computer hacking or monitoring software, hidden cameras, microphones, and [[GPS tracking unit]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/188274/gps_a_stalkers_best_friend.html|title=GPS: A Stalker's Best Friend|author=Leah Yamshon|publisher=PCWorld|date=Feb 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;. In Davis (2001), Lucks identified a separate category of stalkers who instead of a terrestrial means, prefer to perpetrate crimes against their targeted victims through electronic and online means.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, J.A. (2001). Stalking Crimes and Victim Protection, CRC Press.&lt;/ref&gt;.{{page needed|date=September 2012}}

===Stalking by groups===

According to a [[U.S. Department of Justice]] special report&lt;ref name=&quot;StalkingVictimizationintheUnitedStates&quot;/&gt; a significant number of people reporting stalking incidents claim that they had been stalked by more than one person, with 18.2% reporting that they were stalked by two people, 13.1% reporting that they had been stalked by three or more. The report did not break down these cases into numbers of victims who claimed to have been stalked by several people individually, and by people acting in concert. A question asked of respondents reporting three or more stalkers by polling personnel about whether the stalking was related to co-workers, members of a gang, fraternities, sororities, etc., did not have its responses indicated in the survey results as released by the DOJ.  The data for this report was obtained via the 2006 Supplemental Victimization Survey (SVS), conducted by the U.S. Census Bureau for the U.S. Department of Justice.&lt;ref name=&quot;SUPPLEMENTALVICTIMIZATIONSURVEY&quot;/&gt;

According to a United Kingdom study by Sheridan and Boon,&lt;ref&gt;Article: &quot;The Course and Nature of Stalking: A Victim Perspective&quot;,
Authors: Sheridan, Davies, Boon.
Source: ''Howard Journal of Criminal Justice'', Volume 40, Number 3, August 2001 , pp. 215-234.&lt;/ref&gt; in 5% of the cases they studied there was more than one stalker, and 40% of the victims said that friends or family of their stalker had also been involved. In 15% of cases, the victim was unaware of any reason for the harassment.

===False claims of stalking, gang stalking and delusions of persecution===
{{Also|False accusations}}
In 1999, Pathe, Mullen and Purcell wrote that popular interest in stalking was promoting false claims.&lt;ref&gt;M Pathe, PE Mullen, R Purcell; Stalking: false claims of victimisation; British Journal of Psychiatry 174: 170-172 (1999)[http://bjp.rcpsych.org/cgi/content/abstract/174/2/170]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, Sheridan and Blaauw said that they estimated that 11.5% of claims in a sample of 357 reported claims of stalking were false.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheridan and Blauuw 2004&quot;&gt;L. P. Sheridan, E. Blaauw; Characteristics of False Stalking Reports; Criminal Justice and Behavior, Vol. 31, No. 1, 55-72 (2004) {{DOI|10.1177/0093854803259235}} [http://cjb.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/31/1/55]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Sheridan and Blaauw, 70% of false stalking reports were made by people suffering from [[delusions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheridan and Blauuw 2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;After eight uncertain cases were excluded, the false reporting rate was judged to be 11.5%, with the majority of false victims suffering delusions (70%).&quot; [http://cjb.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/31/1/55]&lt;/ref&gt; Another study estimated the proportion of false reports that were due to delusions as 64%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1891/1559-4343.10.3.163}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Multiple news reports have described how groups of Internet users have cooperated to exchange detailed  [[conspiracy theories]] involving coordinated activities by large numbers of people called gang stalking, and the use of &quot;[[psychotronic]] weapons&quot; and other alleged [[mind control]] techniques. Descriptions include red and white cars following victims, vandalism of their homes, snickering by those around them. These are generally reported by external observers as being examples of [[belief system]]s, as opposed to reports of objective phenomena. Experts say Web sites that amplify reports of mind control and group stalking represent a dark side of social networking. They may reinforce the troubled thinking of the mentally ill and impede treatment. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/01/10/AR2007011001399.html|title=Mind Games|author=Sharon Weinberger|date=January 14, 2007|publisher=Washington Post|accessdate=2010-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/13/fashion/13psych.html?fta=y|title=Sharing Their Demons on the Web|author=Sarah Kershaw|date=November 12, 2008|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=2010-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Davis (2001), he reported &quot;very rare&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Davis, J.A. (2001). Stalking Crimes and Victim Protection, CRC Press , Page 378&lt;/ref&gt; instances of victimization that were alleged to be true but only falsified to gain attention, secondary or the specific purposes to exploit or manipulate others called &quot;Falsely Alleged Victimization Syndrome or FAVS.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, J.A. (2001). Stalking Crimes and Victim Protection, CRC Press , Page 376&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Epidemiology and prevalence==
===Australia===
According to a study conducted by Purcell, Pathé and Mullen (2002), 23% of the Australian population reported having been stalked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/120784248/abstract?
| title = The prevalence and nature of stalking in the Australian community
| accessdate =
| author =Rosemary Purcell
| authorlink =
| year = 2006
| month =
| format =
| work =
| pages =
| archiveurl =
| archivedate =
| quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Austria===
Stieger, Burger and Schild conducted a survey in Austria, revealing a lifetime prevalence of 11% (women: 17%, men: 3%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www1.icp2008.org/guest/AbstractView?ABSID=10152
| title = Lifetime prevalence and impact of stalking: Epidemiological data from Eastern Austria
| accessdate = 2008-01-17
| author = Christoph Burger
| last = Burger
| first = Christoph
| authorlink =
| coauthors = Anne Schild, Stefan Stieger
| date = 2008-08-27
| year =
| month =
| format =
| work =
| publisher = ICP2008
| pages =
| language = Englisch
| archiveurl =
| archivedate =
| quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://scielo.isciii.es/pdf/ejpen/v22n4/06.pdf
| title = Lifetime prevalence and impact of stalking: Epidemiological data from Eastern Austria
| accessdate = 2008-02-24
| author = Stefan Stieger
| last = Stieger
| first = Stefan
| authorlink =
| coauthors = Burger Christoph, Anne Schild
| date = 2008-10-14
| year =
| month =
| format =
| work =
| publisher = Eur. J. Psychiat. Vol. 22, N.° 4, (235-241)
| pages =
| archiveurl =
| archivedate =
| quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Further results include: 86% of stalking victims were female, 81% of the stalkers were male. Women were mainly stalked by men (88%) while men were almost equally stalked by men and women (60% male stalkers). 19% of the stalking victims reported that they were still being stalked at the time of study participation ([[point prevalence]] rate: 2%). To 70% of the victims, the stalker was known, being a prior intimate partner in 40%, a friend or acquaintance in 23% and a colleague at work in 13% of cases. As a consequence, 72% of the victims reported having changed their lifestyle. 52% of former and ongoing stalking victims reported suffering from a currently impaired ([[pathological]]) [[Mental health#Mental wellbeing|psychological well-being]]. There was no [[significant]]{{dn|date=July 2012}} difference between the incidence of stalking in rural and urban areas.

===England and Wales===
In 1998 Budd and Mattinson found a lifetime prevalence of 12% in England and Wales (16% female, 7% males).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.crimereduction.homeoffice.gov.uk/stalking.htm
| title = The extend and nature of stalking: findings from the 1998 British crime survey
| accessdate = 2006-12-12
| author = Tracey Budd
| last = Budd
| first = Tracey
| authorlink =
| coauthors = Joanna Mattinson,Andy Myhill
| year = 2000
| month =
| work =
| publisher = British Crime Survey
| pages =
| archiveurl =
| archivedate =
| quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2010/11 43% of stalking victims were found to be male and 57% female.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/publications/science-research-statistics/research-statistics/crime-research/hosb1011/hosb1011?view=Binary
| title = Crime in England and Wales 2010/11
| accessdate = 2012-03-29
| author = Rupert Chaplin
| last = Chaplin
| first = Rupert
| authorlink =
| coauthors = John Flatley, Kevin Smith
| year = 2011
| month = July
| work =
| publisher = The Home Office
| page = 66
| archiveurl =
| archivedate =
| quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a paper by staff from the [[Fixated Threat Assessment Centre]], a unit established to deal with people with fixations on public figures, 86% of a sample group of 100 people assessed by them appeared to them to suffer from [[psychotic illness]]; 57% of the sample group were subsequently admitted to hospital, and 26% treated in the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1080/14789941003596981}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A similar retrospective study published in 2009 in ''Psychological Medicine'' based on a sample of threats to the [[British Royal Family|Royal Family]] kept by the [[Metropolitan Police Service]] over a period of 15 years, suggested that 83.6% of the writers of these letters suffered from serious mental illness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|19335930}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
Dressing, Kuehner and Gass conducted a representative survey in [[Mannheim]], a middle-sized German city, and reported a lifetime prevalence of having been stalked of almost 12%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://bjp.rcpsych.org/cgi/content/abstract/187/2/168
| title = Lifetime prevalence and impact of stalking in a European population. Epidemiological data from a middle-sized German city
| accessdate = 2006-12-12
| author = Harald dressing
| last = Dressing
| first = Harald
| authorlink =
| coauthors = Kuehner, Gass
| year = 2005
| month =
| format =
| work =
| publisher = The British Journal of Psychiatry
| pages =
| archiveurl =
| archivedate =
| quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
Tjaden and Thoennes reported a lifetime prevalence (being stalked) of 8% in women and 2% in males (depending on how strict the definition) in the National violence against women survey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.ncjrs.gov/txtfiles/169592.txt
| title = Stalking in America: Findings from the National violence against women survey
| accessdate = 2006-12-12
| author = Patricia Tjaden
| last = Tjaden
| first = Patricia
| authorlink =
| coauthors = Nancy Thoennes
| year = 1998
| month =
| format =
| work =
| publisher = National Violence Against Women Survey
| pages =
| language = Englisch
| archiveurl =
| archivedate =
| quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Laws on harassment and stalking==
===Australia===
Every Australian state enacted laws prohibiting stalking during the 1990s, with Queensland being the first state to do so in 1994. The laws vary slightly from state to state, with Queensland's laws having the broadest scope, and South Australian laws the most restrictive. Punishments vary from a maximum of 10 years imprisonment in some states, to a fine for the lowest severity of stalking in others. Australian anti-stalking laws have some notable features. Unlike many US jurisdictions they do not require the victim to have felt fear or distress as a result of the behaviour, only that a reasonable person would have felt this way. In some states, the anti-stalking laws operate extra-territorially, meaning that an individual can be charged with stalking if either they or the victim are in the relevant state. Most Australian states provide the option of a [[restraining order]] in cases of stalking, breach of which is punishable as a criminal offence. There has been relatively little research into Australian court outcomes in stalking cases, although Freckelton (2001) found that in the state of [[Victoria, Australia|Victoria]], most stalkers received fines or community based dispositions.

===Canada===
Section 264 of the [[Criminal Code of Canada]], titled &quot;''criminal harassment''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/C-46/page-122.html#s-264 |title=Section 264 of the Criminal Code of Canada |publisher=Laws-lois.justice.gc.ca |date= |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; addresses acts which are termed &quot;stalking&quot; in many other jurisdictions. The provisions of the section came into force in August 1993 with the intent of further strengthening laws protecting women.&lt;ref name=&quot;264r&quot;&gt;[http://www.justice.gc.ca/en/ps/rs/rep/1996/wd96-7a.pdf Department of Justice of Canada - Review and Backgrounder on section 264]{{Dead link|date=January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a [[hybrid offence]], which may be punishable upon [[summary offence|summary conviction]] or as an [[indictable offence]], the latter of which may carry a prison term of up to ten years. Section 264 has withstood [[Charter of Rights and Freedoms|Charter]] challenges.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.justice.gc.ca/en/ps/fm/pub/harassment/part3a.html Department of Justice - Criminal Harassment]{{Dead link|date=January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Chief, Policing Services Program, for Statistics Canada has stated:

''&quot;... of the 10,756 incidents of criminal harassment reported to police in 2006, 1,429 of these involved more than one accused.&quot;
''

===Japan===
In 2000, [[Japan]] enacted a national law to combat this behaviour, after the [[murder of Shiori Ino]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20030612a2.html|title=Kin of stalking victim seek justice|publisher=[[The Japan Times]]|date=2003-06-12|accessdate=2008-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- Please supply legal issues in other countries, particularly non-common-law ones --&gt; Acts of stalking can be viewed as &quot;interfering [with] the [[tranquility]] of others' lives&quot; and are prohibited under [[misdemeanor|petty offence]] laws.

===Italy===
Following a series of high-profile incidents that came to public attention in the past years, a law was proposed in June 2008, and became effective in February 2009, making a criminal offence, punishable with imprisonment ranging from six months up to four years, any ''&quot;continuative harassing, threatening or persecuting behaviour which: (1) causes a state of anxiety and fear in the victim(s), or; (2) ingenerates within the victim(s) a motivated fear for his/her own safety or for the safety of relatives, {{Sic|kin|s}}, or others tied to the victim him/herself by an affective relationship, or; (3), forces the victim(s) to change his/her living habits&quot;''. If the perpetrator of the offense is a subject tied to the victim by kinship or that is or has been in the past involved in a relationship with the victim (i.e. current or former/divorced/split [[husband]]/[[wife]] or [[fiancée]]), and/or if the victim is a [[pregnant woman]] or a [[minor (law)|minor]], the sanction can be elevated up to six years of incarceration.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mentesociale.it/mentesociale/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;id=16&amp;Itemid=15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psicolab.net/index.asp?pid=idart&amp;cat=12&amp;scat=227&amp;arid=2473 psicolab.net]{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pariopportunita.gov.it/DefaultDesktop.aspx?doc=1924]{{Dead link|date=October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
There is no offence which is described in law as &quot;stalking&quot;. An attempt to create such an offence by the [[Stalking Bill 1996]] failed. It was felt that the proposed offence failed to distinguish between reasonable and unreasonable conduct.

In [[England and Wales]], &quot;[[Harassment in the United Kingdom|harassment]]&quot; was criminalised by the enactment of the [[Protection from Harassment Act 1997]], which came into force on June 16, 1997. It makes it a criminal offence, punishable by up to six months imprisonment, to pursue a course of conduct which amounts to harassment of another on two or more occasions. The court can also issue a restraining order, which carries a maximum punishment of five years imprisonment if breached. In [[England and Wales]], liability may arise in the event that the victim suffers either mental or physical harm as a result of being harassed (or slang term stalked) (see ''[[R. v. Constanza]]'').

Already before the enactment of the Act, the [[Malicious Communications Act 1988]] and the [[Telecommunications Act 1984]] (now the [[Communications Act 2003]]) criminalised indecent, offensive or threatening phone calls and the sending of an indecent, offensive or threatening letter, electronic communication or other article to another person.

In 2012, the Prime Minister [[David Cameron]] stated that the government intended to make another attempt to create a law aimed specifically at stalking behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-17294314|title=Stalking to be made specific criminal offence - Cameron|date=8 March 2012|publisher=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Scotland]], provision is made under the Protection from Harassment Act against stalking. It is not a criminal offence, however, but falls under the law of [[Delict (Scots law)|delict]]. Victims of stalking may sue for interdict against an alleged stalker, or a non-harassment order, breach of which is an offence.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

===United States===
The first state to criminalize stalking in the United States was [[California]] in 1990&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.privacyrights.org/fs/fs14-stk.htm |title=Are You Being Stalked? |publisher=Privacyrights.org |date=2011-06-06 |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to several high profile stalking cases in California, including the 1982 attempted murder of actress [[Theresa Saldana]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stalkingalert.com/articlesofinterest.htm |title=Stalking by Rhonda Saunders |publisher=Stalkingalert.com |date= |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; the 1988 massacre by [[Richard Farley]],&lt;ref name='bill analysis'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://info.sen.ca.gov/pub/93-94/bill/asm/ab_1151-1200/ab_1178_cfa_930426_112027_sen_comm |title=Bill Analysis by Bill Lockyer |date= |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; the 1989 murder of actress [[Rebecca Schaeffer]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.redorbit.com/news/health/110415/culture_of_patriarchy_in_law_violence_from_antiquity_to_modernity/index.html |title=Culture of Patriarchy in Law: Violence From Antiquity to Modernity |publisher=Redorbit.com |date=2004-12-11 |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and five [[Orange County, California|Orange County]] stalking murders also in 1989.&lt;ref name='bill analysis'/&gt;&lt;ref name='watson'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smartvoter.org/1998jun/ca/or/vote/watson_j/paper1.html |title=Judge John Watson profile |publisher=Smartvoter.org |date= |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first anti-stalking law in the United States, California Penal Code Section 646.9, was developed and proposed by Municipal Court Judge John Watson of [[Orange County, California|Orange County]]. Watson with U.S. Congressman [[Ed Royce]] introduced the law in 1990.&lt;ref name='watson'/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Nancy K.D. Lemon Battered Women's Justice Project |url=http://www.mincava.umn.edu/documents/bwjp/stalking/stalking.html |title=Domestic Violence Stalking by Nancy Lemon |publisher=Mincava.umn.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 1990, the [[Los Angeles Police Department]] (LAPD) began the United States' first [[Threat Management Unit]], founded by [[Los Angeles Police Department|LAPD]] Captain Robert Martin.

Within three years&lt;ref name='watson'/&gt; thereafter, every state in the [[United States]] followed suit to create the crime of stalking, under different names such as ''criminal harassment'' or ''criminal menace''. The [[Driver's Privacy Protection Act]] (DPPA) was enacted in 1994 in response to numerous cases of a driver's information being abused for criminal activity, examples such as the [[Theresa Saldana|Saldana]] and [[Rebecca Schaeffer|Schaeffer]] stalking cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.epic.org/privacy/drivers/ |title=DPPA and the Privacy of Your State Motor Vehicle Record |publisher=Epic.org |date= |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://judiciary.senate.gov/testimony.cfm?id=1437&amp;wit_id=4146 U.S. Senate Committee: Robert Douglas Testimony]{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The DPPA prohibits states from disclosing a driver's personal information without consent by State [[Department of Motor Vehicles]] (DMV). As of 2011, stalking is an offense under section 120a of the [[Uniform Code of Military Justice]] (UCMJ).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/10/usc_sec_10_00000920---a000-.html|title=United States Code: Title 10,920a. Art. 120a. Stalking -- LII / Legal Information Institute|accessdate=2011-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The law took effect on 1 October 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://militaryjusticeblog.blogspot.com/2007_05_01_archive.html |title=The New Article 120, UCMJ |publisher=Militaryjusticeblog.blogspot.com |date=2007-05-31 |accessdate=2012-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|4|
* [[Bunny boiler]]
* [[Courtship disorder]]
* [[Erotomania]]
* [[Gaslighting]]
* [[Obscene phone call]]
* [[Obsessive love]]
* [[Poison pen letter]]
* [[Querulant]]
* [[Secret admirer]]
* [[Surveillance]]
* [[Surveillance abuse]]
* [[Vexatious litigation]]
* [[Voyeurism]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* ''How To Stop A Stalker''. Proctor, Mike. Prometheus Books, 2000.
* [http://www.mincava.umn.edu/documents/stalkingannotatedbib/stalkingannotatedbib.html Minnesota Center Against Violence and Abuse Annotated Stalking Bibliography]
* ''The Psychology of Stalking''. Meloy, J. Reid. Academic Press, 2000.
* ''Stalkers and Their Victims'', 2nd edition. Mullen, Paul E., Pathe, Michele, Purcell, Rosemary. Cambridge University Press, 2009.
* ''Surviving a Stalker: Everything You Need to Know to Keep Yourself Safe''. Gross, Linda. Marlowe &amp; Company, 2000.
* [http://scielo.isciii.es/pdf/ejpen/v22n4/06.pdf Lifetime prevalence and impact of stalking: Epidemiological data from Eastern Austria]. Stefan Stieger; Christoph Burger; Anne Schild. ''European Journal of Psychiatry'' Vol. 22, N.° 4, (235-241), Zaragoza (ES) 2008, {{ISSN|0213-6163}}.
* [http://www.aic.gov.au/conferences/stalking/DennThom.pdf Is This Stalking? A Comparison Between Legal and Community Definitions of Stalking].{{dead link|date=August 2012}} Susan Dennison and Don Thomson, paper presented at the Stalking: Criminal Justice Responses Conference convened by the Australian Institute of Criminology in Sydney, 7–8 December 2000
* [http://www.ncvc.org/src/main.aspx?dbID=DB_Annotated_Stalking_Bibliography344 U.S. National Center for the Victims of Crime Annotated Stalking Bibliography]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}
* {{cite book|title=Stalking Crimes and Victim Protection|editor-last=Davis|editor-first=Joseph. A. |year=2001|isbn=0-8493-0811-9|publisher=CRC Press|unused_data=publisherCRC Press}}

==External links==
* {{DMOZ|Society/Crime/Prevention/Stalking/}}

{{abuse}}
{{Domestic violence}}
[[Category:Abuse]]
[[Category:Aggression]]
[[Category:Crimes]]
[[Category:Sex crimes]]
[[Category:Inchoate offenses]]

[[ca:Assetjament físic]]
[[cs:Stalking]]
[[da:Stalking]]
[[de:Stalking]]
[[es:Acoso físico]]
[[fr:Traque furtive]]
[[ko:스토킹]]
[[it:Stalking]]
[[he:הטרדה מאיימת]]
[[nl:Stalking]]
[[ja:ストーカー]]
[[no:Stalking]]
[[pl:Stalking]]
[[pt:Stalking]]
[[simple:Stalk]]
[[sk:Stalking]]
[[fi:Vaaniminen]]
[[sv:Förföljelsesyndrom]]
[[uk:Сталкінг]]</text>
      <sha1>ts0ir7m775fuuvafke4mqknhi47e2l4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
