<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Balto-Slavic languages</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>867145</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518122056</id>
      <parentid>517984451</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-16T13:54:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MacedonianBoy</username>
        <id>5678737</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22607">{{Infobox language family
|name=Balto-Slavic
|map=Balto Slavic countries.png
|mapcaption=Countries where the national language is:
{{legend|#008000|Eastern Slavic}}
{{legend|#7CDC87|Western Slavic}}
{{legend|#004040|Southern Slavic}}
{{legend|#F5BD43|Baltic}}
|region=[[Eastern Europe|Eastern]], [[Southern Europe|Southern]] and [[Northern Europe]]
|familycolor=Indo-European
|protoname=[[Proto-Balto-Slavic language|Proto-Balto-Slavic]]
|child1=[[Slavic languages|Slavic]]
|child2=[[Baltic languages|Baltic]]
}}
[[File:Slavic languages tree.svg|thumb|right|300px|Balto-Slavic languages.]]
The '''Balto-Slavic''' language group traditionally comprises the [[Baltic languages|Baltic]] and [[Slavic languages]], belonging to the [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European family]] of languages. Baltic and Slavic languages share several linguistic traits not found in any other Indo-European branch, which points to a period of common development. Most Indo-Europeanists classify Baltic and Slavic languages into a single branch, even though some details of the nature of their relationship remain in dispute in some circles, usually due to political controversies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Fortson|2010|p=414}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some linguists, however, have recently suggested that Balto-Slavic should be split into three equidistant nodes: Eastern Baltic, Western Baltic and Slavic.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Kortlandt |first=Frederik |author-link=Frederik Kortlandt |year=2009 |title=Baltica &amp; Balto-Slavica |page=5 |quote=Though Prussian is undoubtedly closer to the East Baltic languages than to Slavic, the characteristic features of the Baltic languages seem to be either retentions or results of parallel development and cultural interaction. Thus I assume that Balto-Slavic split into three identifiable branches, each of which followed its own course of development.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Etymological Dictionary of the Slavic Inherited Lexicon |first=Rick |last=Derksen |author-link=Rick Derksen |year=2008 |page=20 |quote=&quot;I am not convinced that it is justified to reconstruct a Proto-Baltic stage. The term Proto-Baltic is used for convenience’s sake.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Proto-Balto-Slavic language]] is reconstructable by the [[comparative method]], descending from [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] by means of well-defined [[sound law]]s, and out of which modern Slavic and Baltic languages descended. One particularly innovative dialect separated from the Balto-Slavic dialect continuum and became ancestral to the [[Proto-Slavic]] language, from which all Slavic languages descended.&lt;ref name=enc&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Young|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical dispute==

The nature of the relationship of the Balto-Slavic languages has been the subject of much discussion from the very beginning of historical Indo-European linguistics as a scientific discipline. A few are more intent on explaining the similarities between the two groups not in terms of a genetic relationship, but by language contact and dialectal closeness in the Proto-Indo-European period.
[[Image:Balto-Slavic theories.jpg|thumb|right|400px|Various schematic sketches of possible alternative Balto-Slavic language relationships; Van Wijk, 1923]]

Baltic and Slavic share more close [[phonology|phonological]], [[Lexical (semiotics)|lexical]], [[morphosyntactic]] and accentological similarities than do any other language groups within the Indo-European language family.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} The notable early Indo-Europeanist [[August Schleicher]] (1861) proposed a simple solution: From Proto-Indo-European descended Proto-Balto-Slavic, out of which Proto-Baltic and Proto-Slavic emerged. The Latvian linguist Jānis Endzelīns thought, however, that any similarities among Baltic and Slavic languages were a result of an intensive language contact, i.e., that they were not genetically related and that there was no common Proto-Balto-Slavic language. [[Antoine Meillet]] (1905, 1908, 1922, 1925, 1934), the distinguished French Indo-Europeanist, in reaction to a second simplified theory of Schleicher's, propounded a view according to which all similarities of Baltic and Slavic occurred accidentally, by independent parallel development, and that there was no Proto-Balto-Slavic language. In turn, the Polish linguist Rozwadowski suggests that the similarities among Baltic and Slavic languages are a result of not only genetic relationship, but also of later language contact. [[Thomas Olander]] corroborates the claim of genetic relationship in his research in the field of comparative Balto-Slavic [[accentology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Olander|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Even though some linguists still reject a genetic relationship, most scholars accept that Baltic and Slavic languages experienced a period of common development. {{Harvcoltxt|Beekes|1995|p=22}}, for example, states expressly that &quot;[t]he Baltic and Slavic languages were originally one language and so form one group&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Beekes|1995|22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gray and Atkinson's (2003) application of language-tree divergence analysis supports a genetic relationship between the Baltic and Slavic languages and dating the split of the family to about 1400 BCE. That this was found using a very different methodology than other studies lends some credence to the links between the two.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Gray|Atkinson|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern interpretation==
The Balto-Slavic languages are most often divided into Baltic and Slavic branches.&lt;ref&gt;James Clackson, ''Indo-European Linguistics, An Introduction'' (2007, Cambridge)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin W. Fortson IV, ''Indo-European Language and Culture, An Introduction'' (2nd ed, 2010, Wiley-Blackwell)&lt;/ref&gt; However, another division was proposed in the 1960s by [[Vyacheslav Vsevolodovich Ivanov|Vyacheslav Ivanov]] and [[Vladimir Toporov]]: that the Balto-Slavic proto-language split from the start into West Baltic, East Baltic and Proto-Slavic.&lt;ref&gt;[[Vyacheslav Vsevolodovich Ivanov|Иванов, В. B]]. &amp; [[Vladimir Toporov|Toпоров, B. H.]] 1958, ''On the Relations between Slavic and Baltic Languages'', 4th International Congress of Slavic Studies, Moscow&lt;/ref&gt; Thus Ivanov and Toporov questioned not only Balto-Slavic unity,{{Contradiction-inline|reason=If they accepted the existence of a Balto-Slavic proto-language, how can they question Balto-Slavic unity?|date=October 2012}} but also Baltic unity. In their framework, Proto-Slavic is a peripheral and innovative Balto-Slavic dialect which suddenly expanded, due to a conjunction of historical circumstances, and effectively erased all the other Balto-Slavic dialects, except in the marginal areas where [[Lithuanian language|Lithuanian]], [[Latvian language|Latvian]] and [[Old Prussian]] developed.  This model is supported by [[Glottochronology|glottochronologic]] studies by V.V.Kromer&lt;ref&gt;{{cite arXiv |last=Kromer |first=Victor V. |eprint=cs/0303007 |title=Glottochronology and problems of protolanguage reconstruction |year=2003 |class=cs.CL}}&lt;/ref&gt; although both of the most recent computer-generated family trees have a Baltic node parallel to the Slavic node.&lt;ref&gt;James Clackson, ''Indo-European Linguistics, An Introduction'' (2007, Cambridge)--the so-called &quot;Pennsylvania Tree&quot; (pg. 12) and the so-called &quot;New Zealand Tree&quot; (pg. 19)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Onomastics|Onomastic]] evidence shows that Baltic languages were once spoken in much wider territory than the one they cover today, all the way to [[Moscow]], and were later replaced by Slavic.

[[Image:Balto-Slavic lng.png|thumb|left|260px|Area of Balto-Slavic dialectic continuum (''purple'') with proposed material cultures correlating to speakers Balto-Slavic in Bronze Age (''white''). ''Red'' dots= archaic Slavic hydronyms]]

==Historical expansion==

The sudden expansion of Proto-Slavic in the sixth and the seventh century (around AD 600, uniform Proto-Slavic with no detectable dialectal differentiation was spoken from [[Thessaloniki]] in Greece to [[Novgorod]] in Russia) is according to some connected to the hypothesis that Proto-Slavic was in fact a ''[[Koiné language|koiné]]'' of the [[Eurasian Avars|Avar state]], i.e. the language of the administration and military rule of the Avar khaganate in Eastern Europe.&lt;ref&gt;cf. {{Harvcoltxt|Holzer|2002}} with references&lt;/ref&gt; It is well-known from historical sources that Slavs and Avars jointly attacked the Byzantine Empire and laid siege to Constantinople.&lt;ref&gt;Later historical sources, such as [[De Administrando Imperio]] by [[Constantine Porphyrogenitus]], often mix Avars and Slavs, after a few centuries making no clear distinction between them.&lt;/ref&gt; According to that interpretation, Avars were a thin layer of military aristocracy in that state/alliance, while the Slavs were a military caste – warriors (i.e. not a nation or ethnicity in the proper sense of that word). Their language – at first possibly only one local speech – once koinéized, became a ''lingua franca'' of the Avar state. This might explain how Proto-Slavic spread to the Balkans and the areas of the Danubian basin,&lt;ref&gt;Slavic languages were spoken till the year 800 all the way to line Trieste-Hamburg. Later they were pushed back to the east.&lt;/ref&gt; and would also explain why the Avars were assimilated so fast, leaving practically no linguistic traces, and that Proto-Slavic was so unusually uniform. However, such a theory fails to explain how Slavic spread to Eastern Europe, an area which had no historical links with the [[Eurasian Avars|Avar Khanate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Curta|2004}}: ''It is possible that the expansion of the Avar khanate during the second half of the eighth century coincided with the spread of... Slavic into the neighbouring areas of Bohemia, Moravia and southern Poland. (but) could hardly explain the spread of Slavic into Poland, Ukraine, Belarus and Russia, all regions that produced so far almost no archaeological evidence of Avar influence''&lt;/ref&gt;

That sudden expansion of Proto-Slavic erased most of the idioms of the Balto-Slavic dialect continuum, which left us today with only two branches: Baltic and Slavic (or East Baltic, West Baltic, and Slavic in the minority view). This secession of the Balto-Slavic dialect ancestral to Proto-Slavic is estimated on archaeological and glottochronological criteria to have occurred sometime in the period 1500–1000 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;cf. {{Harvcoltxt|Novotná|Blažek|2007}} with references. &quot;Classical glottochronology&quot; conducted by Czech Slavist M. Čejka in 1974 dates the Balto-Slavic split to -910±340 BCE, Sergei Starostin in 1994 dates it to 1210 BCE, and &quot;recalibrated glottochronology&quot; conducted by Novotná &amp; Blažek dates it to 1400–1340 BCE. This agrees well with Trziniec-Komarov culture, localized from Silesia to Central Ukraine and dated to the period 1500–1200 BCE.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Balto-Slavic isoglosses==
{{Indo-European topics}}
{{Technical|section|date=December 2010}}
The close relationship of the Baltic and Slavic languages is indicated by a series of exclusive [[isogloss]]es representing innovations not shared with any other branch of the Indo-European (IE) language family (especially in their phonology)&lt;ref name=enc/&gt; and by the fact that  the relative chronology of these innovations can be established, which is the most important criterion for establishing genetic relationship in historical linguistics.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} The most important of these isoglosses are:

* [[Winter's law]] (lengthening of vowels before Proto-Indo-European (PIE) voiced consonants, probably only in a closed syllable)
* [[Hirt's law]] (retraction of PIE accent to the preceding syllable closed by a laryngeal)
* identical reflexes of PIE syllabic [[sonorant]]s
* rise of the Balto-Slavic acute before PIE laryngeals in a closed syllable
* replacement of PIE genitive singular of thematic nouns with ablative
* ending for instrumental plural of *-miHs; e.g. Lith. ''[[wikt:sūnus#Lithuanian|sūnumìs]]'', [[Old Church Slavonic|OCS]] ''[[wikt:сꙑнъ#Old Church Slavonic|synъmi]]'' &quot;with sons&quot;
* formation of past tense with the ending *-ē (a type of Lithuanian preterite ''dãvė'' 'he gave', OCS imperfect ''bě'' 'he was')
* generalization of the PIE neuter *[[wikt:Appendix:Proto-Indo-European/tód|to-]] stem to the nominative singular of masculine and feminine demonstratives instead of PIE *[[wikt:Appendix:Proto-Indo-European/só|so-]], i.e. PIE demonstrative {{PIE|*só, *séh₂, *tód}} (&quot;this, that&quot;) became PBSl. *tos, *ta, *tod
* formation of so-called definite adjectives with a construction that includes adjective and a relative pronoun, e.g. Lith. ''geràsis'' 'the good' as opposed to ''[[wikt:geras#Lithuanian|gẽras]]'' 'good', OCS ''dobrъjь'' 'the good' as opposed to ''[[wikt:добръ#Old Church Slavonic|dobrъ]]'' 'good'
* usage of genitive to state the object of a negated verb, e.g. Russ. ''knigi (ja) ne čital'', Lith. ''knygos neskaičiau'' 'Book, haven't read'.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvcoltxt|Matasović|2008|pp=56–57}} ''&quot;Navedimo najvažnije baltoslavenske izoglose...Upotreba genitiva za izricanje objekta zanijekanog glagola&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt;

Common Balto-Slavic innovations include several other prominent, but non-exclusive, isoglosses, such as the [[Satemization]], [[Ruki sound law|Ruki]], change of PIE */o/ to PBSl. */a/ (shared with [[Germanic languages|Germanic]], [[Indo-Iranian languages|Indo-Iranian]] and [[Anatolian languages|Anatolian]] branch) and the loss of labialization in PIE labiovelars (shared with Indo-Iranian, Armenian and Tocharian). A number of these, however, fit only in the relative chronology of other otherwise exclusive Balto-Slavic isoglosses, which makes them specific Balto-Slavic innovation.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

Baltic and Slavic languages also show some correspondence in vocabulary; about 100 words are shared by Baltic and Slavic languages, either being a common innovation (i.e. not of PIE origin) or sharing the same semantic development from PIE root.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/50949/Baltic-languages |title=Baltic languages |authorlink=Vytautas Mažiulis |first=Vytautas |last=Mažiulis |accessdate=2008-10-10 |work=Britannica Online Encyclopedia}}&lt;/ref&gt;
For example:
* PBSl. {{PIE|*lḗjpā}} '[[tilia]]' &gt; Lith. ''[[wikt:liepa#Lithuanian|líepa]]'', Old Pr. ''līpa'', Latv. ''[[wikt:liepa#Latvian|liẽpa]]'', Latg. ''[[wikt:līpa#Latgalian|līpa]]''; PSl. *léjpā &gt; Common Slavic *lipa (OCS ''lipa'', Russ. ''[[wikt:липа#Russian|lipa]]'', Pol. ''[[wikt:lipa#Polish|lipa]]'')
* PBSl. {{PIE|*ránkā}} 'hand' &gt; Lith. ''[[wikt:ranka#Lithuanian|rankà]]'', Old Pr. ''rānkan'' ([[accusative case|A]] [[grammatical number|sg.]]), Latv. ''[[wikt:roka#Latvian|rùoka]]'', Latg. ''[[wikt:rūka#Latgalian|rūka]]''; PSl. *ránkā &gt; Common Slavic *{{unicode|[[wikt:Appendix:Proto-Slavic *rǫka|rǭkà]]}} (OCS ''[[wikt:рѫка#Old Church Slavonic|rǫka]]'', Russ. ''[[wikt:рука#Russian|ruká]]'', Pol. ''[[wikt:ręka#Polish|ręka]]'')
* PBSl. {{PIE|*galwā́}} 'head' &gt; Lith. ''[[wikt:galva#Lithuanian|galvà]]'', Old Pr. ''[[wikt:galwo#Old_Prussian|galwo]]'', Latv. ''[[wikt:galva#Latvian|galva]]'', Latg. ''[[wikt:golva#Latgalian|golva]]''; PSl. *{{unicode|galwā́}} &gt; Common Slavic *[[wikt:Appendix:Proto-Slavic *golva|golvà]] (OCS ''[[wikt:глава#Old Church Slavonic|glava]]'', Russ. ''[[wikt:голова#Russian|golová]]'', Pol. ''[[wikt:głowa#Polish|głowa]]'')

Among Balto-Slavic archaisms notable is the retention of [[Proto-Indo-European accent|free PIE accent]] (with many innovations).

==Proto-Balto-Slavic language==
{{Main|Proto-Balto-Slavic language}}
Proto-Balto-Slavic is a [[Linguistic reconstruction|reconstructed]] [[proto-language]] descending from [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] and out of which all later Baltic and Slavic languages and dialects descended.

==See also==
* [[Proto-Slavic]]
* [[Corded Ware culture]]
* [[International Workshop on Balto-Slavic Accentology]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* {{citation | author=Barschel; Kozianka; Weber (eds.) | title=Indogermanisch, Baltisch und Slawisch, Kolloquium in Zusammenarbeit mit der Indogermanischen Gesellschaft in Jena, September 1989 | location=[[Munich]] | publisher=Otto Sagner | year=1992 | isbn=3-87690-515-X |language=German}}
* {{citation| authorlink=Robert S. P. Beekes |first=Robert |last=Beekes | title=Comparative Indo-European Linguistics | location=[[Amsterdam]] | publisher=John Benjamins | year=1995 | id=ISBN 90-272-2151-0 (Europe), ISBN 1-55619-505-2 (U.S.)}}
* {{citation| last=Curta |first=Florin |title=The Slavic Lingua Franca. (Linguistic Notes of an Archaeologist Turned Historian) | url=http://florida.academia.edu/FlorinCurta/Papers/161557/The-Slavic-lingua-franca--Linguistic-notes-of-an-archaeologist-turned-historian- |journal=East Central Europe/L'Europe du Centre-Est |issue= 31 |year=2004 |pages=125–148}}
* {{citation |last=Fortson |first=Benjamin W. |title=Indo-European Language and Culture: An Introduction |location=Malden, Massachusetts |edition=2nd |publisher=Blackwell |year=2010 |isbn=978-1-4051-8896-8}}
* {{citation |doi=10.1038/nature02029 |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v426/n6965/abs/nature02029.html|first1=R.D. |last1=Gray |last2=Atkinson| first2=Q.D.  |title=Language-tree divergence times support the Anatolian theory of Indo-European origin |journal=Nature |volume=426 |issue=426 |pages=435−439 |year=2003 |bibcode=2003Natur.426..435G |pmid=14647380}}
* {{citation |year=2001 |authorlink=Georg Holzer |first=Georg |last=Holzer |language=German |title=Zur Lautgeschichte des baltisch-slavischen Areals |journal=Wiener slavistisches Jahrbuch |issue=47 |pages=33–50}}
* {{citation |url=http://www.uni-klu.ac.at/eeo/Urslawisch.pdf |contribution=Urslawisch |authorlink=Georg Holzer |first=Georg |last=Holzer |year=2002 |accessdate=2008-10-01 |title=Enzyklopädie des Europäischen Ostens |language=German |location=Klagenfurt |publisher=Wieser Verlag |format=PDF }}
*{{citation |year=2007 |authorlink=Georg Holzer |first=Georg |last=Holzer |title=Historische Grammatik des Kroatischen. Einleitung und Lautgeschichte der Standardsprache | location=[[Frankfurt am Main]] |publisher=Peter Lang |isbn=978-3-631-56119-5 |language=German }}
* {{citation |authorlink=Frederik Kortlandt |first=Frederik |last=Kortlandt |url=https://openaccess.leidenuniv.nl/dspace/bitstream/1887/1853/1/344_017.pdf |title=I.-E. palatovelars before resonants in Balto-Slavic |year=1978 |journal=Recent Developments in Historical Phonology |pages=237–243 |format=PDF }}
* {{citation |title=Baltica &amp; Balto-Slavica |first=Frederik |last=Kortlandt |year=2009 |isbn=978-90-420-2652-0 |location=Amsterdam-New York |publisher=Rodopi |author-link=Frederik Kortlandt }}
* {{citation |authorlink=Ranko Matasović |first=Ranko |last=Matasović |url=http://www.leidykla.vu.lt/inetleid/baltistic/40_2/straipsniai/str1.pdf |title=Toward a relative chronology of the earliest Baltic and Slavic sound changes |year=2005 |journal=[[Baltistica]] |volume=40/2 |format=PDF}}
* {{citation |authorlink=Ranko Matasović |first=Ranko |last=Matasović |language=Croatian |title=Poredbenopovijesna gramatika hrvatskoga jezika |location=[[Zagreb]] |publisher=[[Matica hrvatska]] |year=2008 |isbn=978-953-150-840-7 }}
* {{citation |first1=Petra |last1=Novotná |first2=Václav |last2=Blažek |title=Glottochronolgy and its application to the Balto-Slavic languages |journal=[[Baltistica]] |volume=XLII (2) |year=2007 |pages=185–210 |url=http://www.leidykla.eu/fileadmin/Baltistika/42-2/04_Blazeko.pdf |format=PDF}}
* {{citation |url=http://www.tommeltot.dk/files/olander-bsproblem.pdf |title=Det baltoslaviske problem – Accentologien |first=Tomas |last=Olander |author-link=Thomas Olander |year=2002 |language=Danish |format=pdf}} Thomas Olander's Ph.D. thesis on the existence of Balto-Slavic genetic node solely on the basis of accentological evidence
* {{citation |first=Thomas |last=Olander |author-link=Thomas Olander |year=2009 |title=Balto-Slavic Accentual Mobility |publisher=[[Mouton de Gruyter]] |location =Berlin &amp; New York |isbn=978-3-11-020397-4}}
* {{citation |authorlink=Christian Stang |first=Christian |last=Stang |title=Slavonic accentuation |location=[[Oslo]] |publisher=Universitetsforlaget |year=1957 |isbn=978-82-00-06078-9 }}
* {{citation | authorlink=Oswald Szemerényi |last=Szemerényi |first=Oswald | title=The problem of Balto-Slav unity | journal=Kratylos | year=1957 | volume=2 | pages=97–123}}
* {{citation|title=Balto-Slavic languages|journal=Concise encyclopedia of languages of the world| url=http://books.google.com/books?id=F2SRqDzB50wC&amp;pg=PA135|year=2009| last=Young |first=S |isbn=978-0-08-087774-7}}

==External links==
* [http://www.kortlandt.nl/publications/art218e.pdf Balto-Slavic Accentuation], by Kortlandt; a very idiosyncratic approach to Balto-Slavic accentuation
* {{Citation |url=http://www.kroraina.com/slav/bern_trub.htm |author=[[Oleg Trubachyov|Трубачев О.]], Бернштейн С. |chapter=Отрывки о балто-южнославянских изоглосах |title=Сравнительная грамматика славянских языков |year=2005 |location=Moscow |publisher=Наука |language=Russian}} (Bernstein and Trubachev on the Balto-South-Slavic isoglosses)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Balto-Slavic Languages}}
[[Category:Balto-Slavic languages]]

[[af:Balto-Slawies]]
[[ca:Llengües balto-eslaves]]
[[cs:Balto-slovanské jazyky]]
[[da:Baltoslaviske sprog]]
[[de:Balto-slawische Hypothese]]
[[dsb:Balto-słowjańske rěcy]]
[[es:Lenguas baltoeslavas]]
[[eo:Baltslava lingvaro]]
[[fr:Langues balto-slaves]]
[[glk:بالتؤ-ئسلاویکی زوانؤن]]
[[ko:발트슬라브어파]]
[[hy:Բալթիկ-սլավոնական լեզուներ]]
[[hr:Baltoslavenski jezici]]
[[it:Lingue balto-slave]]
[[he:שפות בלטו-סלאביות]]
[[ka:ბალტო-სლავური ენები]]
[[lv:Baltu-slāvu pirmvalodas hipotēze]]
[[lt:Baltų-slavų kalbos]]
[[hu:Balti-szláv nyelvek]]
[[mk:Балтословенски јазици]]
[[nl:Balto-Slavische talen]]
[[no:Baltoslaviske språk]]
[[oc:Lengas baltoeslavas]]
[[pl:Języki bałtosłowiańskie]]
[[pt:Línguas balto-eslávicas]]
[[ru:Балто-славянские языки]]
[[sr:Балто-словенски језици]]
[[sh:Balto-slavenski jezici]]
[[sv:Baltoslaviska språk]]
[[uk:Балто-слов'янська мовна спільність]]
[[yo:Àwọn èdè Balto-Slavic]]
[[bat-smg:Baltoslavu kalbas]]</text>
      <sha1>27wv96xbzynr9pv38iai7ppbjyignh9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
