<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>French language in Canada</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1385923</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520603791</id>
      <parentid>518168417</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T15:49:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>தமிழ்க்குரிசில்</username>
        <id>16955001</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* External links */ ta iw</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37713">'''[[French language|French]]''' is the mother '''[[language|tongue]]''' of about seven million '''[[Canada|Canadians]]''' (22.3% of the Canadian population, second to English at 58.4%).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www12.statcan.gc.ca/census-recensement/2006/dp-pd/hlt/97-555/T401-eng.cfm?Lang=E&amp;T=401&amp;GH=4&amp;SC=1&amp;S=99&amp;O=A Population by mother tongue and age groups, 2006 counts, for Canada, provinces and territories - 20% sample data], Statistics Canada. Includes multiple responses.&lt;/ref&gt; Most native French speakers in [[Canada]] live in [[Quebec]], where French is the majority and sole official language. About 80% of Quebec's population are native [[francophone]]s, and 95% of the population speak French as their first or second language. Additionally, about one million native francophones live in other provinces, forming a sizable minority in [[New Brunswick]], which is officially a bilingual province, where about one third of the population are francophone. There are also fairly large French-speaking communities in [[Manitoba]] and [[Ontario]], where francophones make up about five percent of the population, as well as significantly smaller communities in [[Alberta]], [[Nova Scotia]] and [[Saskatchewan]]. Many, but not all of these communities are supported by French-language institutions.

By the [[Official Languages Act (Canada)|Official Languages Act in 1969]], Canada recognized English and French as having equal status in the government of Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://laws.justice.gc.ca/eng/O-3.01/page-1.html|title=Official Languages Act - 1985, c. 31 (4th Supp.) |work=Act current to July 11th, 2010|publisher=Department of Justice|accessdate=2010-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; While French, with no specification as to dialect or variety, has the status of one of [[Canada]]'s two official languages at the [[Government of Canada|federal government level]], [[English language|English]] is the native language of the majority of Canadians. The federal government provides services and operates in both languages. French is the sole official language&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.olf.gouv.qc.ca/english/charter/index.html OLF]&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Quebec]] at the provincial level and is co-official with [[English language|English]] in [[New Brunswick]].  The provincial governments of [[Ontario]], [[New Brunswick]], and [[Manitoba]] are required to provide services in French where justified by the number of francophones (those whose mother tongue is French).  However, the [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] requires all provinces to provide primary and secondary education to their official-language minorities at public expense.  The French used in Canada is regulated by the [[Office québécois de la langue française|Office Québécois de la Langue Française]] (OQLF), previously known as the ''Office de la langue française'' (OLF).

==The evolution of the French language in Canada==
===Introduction===

In 1492, contact with the [[New World]] was initially made by [[Christopher Columbus]], an Italian navigator employed by the Spanish, followed in 1497 by [[John Cabot]], a Venetian navigator employed by the English. Their explorations kindled a desire among the European maritime powers to establish permanent colonies in the Americas.&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996)Tome 4, p.836&lt;/ref&gt;

===The 16th century===

In 1524, the Florentine navigator [[Giovanni da Verrazzano]], working for Italian bankers in France, explored the American coast from [[Spanish Florida|Florida]] to [[Cape Breton (Nova Scotia)|Cape Breton]]. In 1529, Verrazzano mapped a part of the coastal region of the North American continent under the name Nova Gallia ([[New France]]). In 1534, [[Francis I of France|Francis I]], king of France, sent [[Jacques Cartier]] to discover new lands. He discovered the [[Gulf of Saint Lawrence]], sealed an alliance with the local people and obtained passage to go further. During his second expedition (1535–1536), Cartier discovered the [[Saint Lawrence River]], a path into the heart of the continent. However, Cartier failed to establish a permanent colony in the area, and war in Europe kept France from further colonization through the end of the century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas Universalis 1996 p.57&quot;&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996), Tome 2, p.57&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996), Tome 5, p.23&lt;/ref&gt;

===The 17th century===

At the beginning of the 17th century, French settlements and private companies were established in the area which is now eastern Canada. In 1605 [[Samuel de Champlain]] founded [[Port Royal, Nova Scotia|Port Royal]] ([[Acadia]]) and in 1608 he founded [[Quebec City]].  In 1634 the foundation of Ville Marie, the settlement which would eventually become [[Montreal]], completed the occupation of the territory.

In 1634, Quebec contained two hundred settlers, who were principally involved in the fur trade. The trade was profit-making and the city was on the point of becoming more than a mere temporary trading post.

In 1635, [[Jesuits]] founded the secondary school of Quebec for the education of the children. Ten years later, in 1645, the Company of the Inhabitants was created, uniting the political and economic leaders of the colony. [[French language|French]] was the language of all the non-native people.

In 1685, the revocation of the [[Edict of Nantes]] by [[Louis XIV]] (1654–1715), which had legalized freedom of religion of the [[Reformed Church]], caused the emigration out of France of three hundred thousand [[Huguenots]] (French Calvinists), to other countries of Europe and to North America.&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996)Tome 4, p.837-838&lt;/ref&gt;

===The 18th century===

With the [[Treaty of Utrecht]] in 1713, the British began their domination of eastern North America, some territories formerly controlled by the French. The British took mainland [[Nova Scotia]] in 1713.  Present-day [[Maine]] fell to the British during [[Father Rale's War]], while present-day [[New Brunswick]] fell after [[Father Le Loutre's War]].   In 1755 the majority of the French-speaking inhabitants of [[Atlantic Canada]] were deported to the [[Thirteen Colonies]].  After 1758, they were deported to England and France. The [[Treaty of Paris (1763)]] completed the British takeover, removing France from Canadian territory, except for [[Saint-Pierre and Miquelon]] at the entrance of the Gulf of Saint Lawrence.

The French language was relegated to second rank as far as trade and state communications were concerned. Out of necessity, the educated class learned the [[English language]] and became progressively bilingual, but the great majority of the French-speaking inhabitants continued to speak only French, and their population increased. Anglicization of the French population failed, and it became obvious that coexistence was required. In 1774, [[Parliament of Great Britain|Parliament]] passed the [[Quebec Act]], restoring French civil laws and abrogating the [[Test Act]], which had been used to suppress Catholicism.&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996)Tome 4, p.838-839&lt;/ref&gt;

===The birth of Canada as a federal State===

In 1791, Parliament repealed the Quebec Act and gave the king authority to divide the Canadian colony into two new provinces: [[Upper Canada]], which later became Ontario, and [[Lower Canada]], which became Quebec.
 
In 1867, three colonies of British North America agreed to form a federal state which was named [[Canada]]. It was composed of four provinces: 
* [[Ontario]], formerly Upper Canada
* [[Quebec]], formerly Lower Canada
* [[Nova Scotia]]
* [[New Brunswick]], former Acadian territory

In Quebec, French became again the official language; until then it was the [[vernacular language]] but with no legal status.&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996)Tome 4, p.840-842&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996)Tome 19, p.397-404&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;BOURHIS Richard Y. et LEPICQ Dominique (1993), Québécois French and language issues in Québec, dans &quot;Trends in Romance Linguistics and Philology : Bilingualism and Linguistic Conflict in Romance&quot;, ed. par Rebecca Posner, John N. Green, Mouton De this is a joke  Gruyter, Berlin; New-York.[http://books.google.be/books?id=_8J7ilk0bAgC&amp;pg=PA453&amp;lpg=PA453&amp;dq=Trends+in+Romance+Linguistics+and+Philology+:+Bilingualism+and+Linguistic+Conflict+in+Romance%22,&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=sEsBiWTFKO&amp;sig=xyRs0bxWIs_uu_NyHLXzK7Ct-PM&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SYHCTazPHsWfOsbnqZ0I&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt;

==French dialects in Canada==
As a consequence of geographical seclusion and, due to the British Conquest, the French language in Canada presents three different but related dialects. They share certain features which distinguish them from European French. The name ''[[Canadian French]]'' is now usually viewed as an umbrella term for all of these varieties.

* [[Quebec French]] is spoken in [[Quebec]]. Closely related varieties descended from it are spoken by francophone communities in [[Ontario]], [[Western Canada]], [[Labrador]] and even in the [[New England]] region of the [[United States]], and differ primarily by their greater conservatism. The term ''Laurentian French'' has limited currency as an umbrella term for these varieties, and ''Quebec French'', somewhat confusingly, is also used. The term ''Canadian French'' was formerly used to refer to this dialect specifically,&lt;ref&gt;Francard and Latin, in ''Le régionalisme lexical'', write: &lt;blockquote&gt; Le français du Québec a rayonné en Ontario et dans l'ouest du Canada, de même qu'en Nouvelle-Angleterre. [...] Le français québécois et le français acadien peuvent être regroupés sous l'appellation plus large de ''français canadien''&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, laquelle englobe aussi le français ontarien et le français de l'Ouest canadien. Ces deux derniers possèdent des traits caractéristiques qui leur sont propres aujourd'hui dans l'ensemble canadien et qui s'expliquent surtout par un phénomène de conservatisme, mais il s'agit de variétés qui sont historiquement des prolongements du français québécois.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt; The footnote reads: &quot;Il faut noter ici que le terme de ''français canadien'' avait autrefois un sens plus restreint, désignant le français du Québec et les variétés qui s'y rattachent directement, d'où l'emploi à cette époque de ''canadianisme'' pour parler d'un trait caractéristique du français du Québec.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; (presumably because Canada and Acadia were distinct parts of New France, and even British North America until 1867), but is now not usually felt to exclude Acadian French.
* [[Acadian French]] is spoken by the [[Acadian]]s in the [[Canadian Maritimes]] and some parts of [[Quebec]] and [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]]. It is the ancestor of [[Cajun French]]. Acadian French shares many characteristics with Quebec French, however, differs in pronunciation.
*[[Chiac]] is a dialect originating primarily out of the Moncton/Shediac area of New Brunswick. It incorporates many English words, sayings, pronunciations and linguistic rules. Disputes have arisen surrounding the legitimacy of Chiac as a French dialect. Chiac has slowly advanced into other areas of Acadia among youth.
*[[Brayon French]] is spoken primarily in northwestern New Brunswick, parts of northern Maine, and the Bonaventure and Beauce-Appalaches regions of Quebec. It closely resembles traditional Quebec French in pronunciation but with a unique sound and incorporates a few Acadian words.
* [[Métis French]] or Métis, along with [[Michif]], is one of the traditional languages of the [[Métis people]], and is spoken in the [[Canadian Prairies|prairies]].
* [[Newfoundland French]] is spoken by a limited population in [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]]. It is an [[endangered language|endangered dialect]].
*[[Joual]] is spoken primarily by the working class of Montreal. It resembles but is not related to Brayon French.
*[[Magoua]] is spoken in the Trois-Rivières/Maskinonge region of Quebec. It is classified as a dialect of basilectal Quebec French. The name is thought to be derived from Algonquin origins.
*[[Chaouin]] is spoken just outside of the Trois-Rivières region of Quebec.

All of these dialects mix to varying degrees elements from regional languages and folk dialects spoken in France at the time of colonization. For instance, the origins of Quebec French lie in 17th- and 18th-century Parisian French influenced with folk dialects of the early [[French language|modern period]] and other [[Oïl languages|regional languages]] (such as [[Norman language|Norman]], [[Picard language|Picard]], and [[Poitevin (language)|Poitevin]]-[[Saintongeais]]) which French colonists brought to [[New France]]. The influence of these dialects on Acadian French is acknowledged to be stronger than on Quebec French. The three dialects can also be historically and geographically associated with three of the five former colonies of [[New France]], respectively [[Canada, New France|Canada]], [[Acadia]], and [[Colony of Newfoundland|Terre-Neuve (Newfoundland)]].

In addition, there is a [[mixed language]] known as [[Michif language|Michif]] which is based on [[Cree language|Cree]] and [[French language|French]]. It is spoken by [[Métis]] communities in [[Manitoba]] and [[Saskatchewan]] as well as adjacent areas of the United States.

Finally, more recent immigration (post-World War II) has brought francophone immigrants from around the world, and with them other [[French dialects]].

==The language across Canada==
=== Quebec ===
{{main|Quebec French}}
[[Image:Arret.jpg|right|thumb|A Quebec French stop sign.]]
[[Quebec]] is the only province whose sole official language is French. Today, 81.4 percent of Quebeckers are first language francophones.&lt;ref name=&quot;www12.statcan.ca&quot;&gt;[http://www12.statcan.ca/english/census01/products/analytic/companion/lang/provs.cfm Profile of languages in Canada: Provinces and territories&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]. ''Accessed 03 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt; About 95.0 percent of Quebecers speak French as either their first, second or even as their third language. However, many of the services the provincial government provides are available in English for the sizeable [[English-speaking Quebecker|anglophone]] population of the province (notably in [[Montreal]]). For native French speakers, [[Quebec French]] is noticeably different in pronunciation and vocabulary from the [[French language|French]] of [[France]], sometimes called ''Metropolitan French'', but they are easily mutually intelligible in their formal varieties, and after moderate exposure, in most of their informal ones as well. The differences are primarily due to changes that have occurred in Quebec French and [[Parisian French]] since the 18th century, when Britain gained possession of Canada.
Different regions of Quebec have their own varieties: [[Gaspé Peninsula]], [[Côte-Nord]], [[Quebec City]], [[Saguenay-Lac-Saint-Jean]], [[Outaouais (region)|Outaouais]], and [[Abitibi-Témiscamingue]] have differences in pronunciation as well as in vocabulary. For example, depending on one's region, the ordinary word for &quot;kettle&quot; can be ''bouilloire, bombe,'' or ''canard''.

In Quebec, the French language is of paramount importance. For example, the [[stop sign]]s are written '''''ARRÊT''''' (which means '''STOP''' in English), even if other French-speaking countries, like [[France]], use '''STOP'''. On a similar note, movies originally made in other languages than French (mostly movies originally made in English) are more literally named in Quebec than they are in France (e.g. The movie ''[[The Love Guru]]'' is called '''Love Gourou''' in France, but in Quebec it is called '''Le Gourou de l'amour'''). Also, [[French-speaking Quebecer|Québécois]] do not always use the same words as the French. Here are some examples:

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
! English !! Quebec French !! Metropolitan French
|-
| weekend || fin de semaine || week-end
|-
| parking || stationnement || parking 
|-
| e-mail || courriel || e-mail/mél
|-
| spam || pourriel || spam
|-
| (to) chat || clavarder || chater
|-
| podcasting || baladodiffusion || podcasting
|-
| beverage || breuvage || boisson
|-
| [[lunch]] || dîner || déjeuner
|-
| [[dinner]] || souper || dîner
|}

====The use of anglicisms====

The [[Quebec French]] has recourse to many [[anglicism]]s, which characterize it in comparison with other varieties of French{{fact|date=October 2012}}. 
The [[Quebec Office of the French Language]]’s &quot;Banque de dépannage linguistique&quot; distinguishes different kinds of anglicisms&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Office québécois de la langue française|title=Anglicismes|url=http://www.oqlf.gouv.qc.ca/francilettre/francilettreEX_20070914.html}}. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt;:
* The '''entire anglicisms''' are words or groups of [[loan words]] from the English Language. The form is often exactly the same as in English, e.g. : &quot;glamour&quot;, &quot;short&quot; and &quot;sweet&quot;, but sometimes there is a slightly adjustment to the French language, e.g.: &quot;drabe&quot;, which comes from the English word &quot;drab&quot;.
* The '''hybrid anglicisms''', which are new words, a combination of an English word to which a French element is added. This element (a suffix, for instance) sometimes replaces a similar element of the English word. &quot;Booster&quot; is an example of hybrid anglicism: it is made up of the English verb &quot;to boost&quot;, to which the French suffix  –er is added.
* Plenty of anglicisms are '''semantic anglicisms''': they are French words used in a sense which exists in English, but not in French. ''Ajourner'' in the sense of « to have a break », ''pathétique'' in the sense of &quot;miserable&quot; (pitiful), ''plancher'' in the sense of &quot;floor&quot; (level of a building) and ''préjudice'' in the sense of &quot;(unfavorable) opinion&quot;.
* The '''syntactic anglicisms''' concern the word order of a sentence and the use of prepositions and conjunctions. The expression &quot;un bon dix minutes&quot;, for instance, comes from the English language; in French, they rather say &quot;dix bonnes minutes&quot;. The use of the preposition &quot;pour&quot; after the verbs &quot;demander&quot; and &quot;chercher&quot; is also a syntactic anglicism.
* The '''morphological anglicisms''' are literal translations of the English forms. With this kind of loan words, every element comes from the French language, but what results from it as a whole reproduces, completely or partly, the image transmitted in English. ''Technicalité'', for instance, is formed under the English influence and doesn’t exist in French. ''À l'année longue'', ''appel conférence'' and ''prix de liste'' are other morphological examples of anglicisms.
* Finally, the '''sentencial anglicisms''' are loan set phrases or images peculiar to the English language. The expressions ''ajouter l'insulte à l'injure'' and ''sonner une cloche'' are sentencial  anglicisms.

The abundance of the anglicisms in Quebec French leads some people to speak of &quot;sabirisation&quot;, because of the mixture of both languages. [[Loi 101|Law 101]] could postpone the advance of the phenomenon or even prevent it.

In conclusion, according to the Robert Dubuc's article &quot;Régionalismes et communication&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Boisvert|first=Lionel|title=La lexicographie québécoise: bilan et perspectives|year=1986|publisher=Les presses de l'Université Laval|quote=il n’y a de salut hors de la maîtrise de ses moyens linguistiques dont le français commun constitue l’armature essentielle et efficace.}}[http://books.google.be/books?id=byAoAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=la+lexicographie+quebecoise&amp;dq=la+lexicographie+quebecoise&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=7YfCTY3GD8boOfuJ6Z0I&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA]. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt; for the French-speaking community of Quebec, « il n’y a de salut hors de la maîtrise de ses moyens linguistiques dont le français commun constitue l’armature essentielle et efficace. »

====Syntactic and semantic characteristics====

In general, the same norms as in common French are applied. Only certain words have a different gender.
From the semantic point of view, we note the use of the word &quot;pis&quot; for &quot;et&quot;, the word &quot;là&quot; to punctuate the end of a sentence or after a word, and finally the use of &quot;à&quot; instead of the possessive &quot;de&quot;, for instance, « la maison à Jacques ».

====The use of the 'tu' form====
Quebeckers frequently use the &quot;tu&quot; form. This use is often qualified as the imitation of the English-speaking use of &quot;you&quot;, which is the only pronoun referring to the second person, but only in spoken language. There is, however, a movement which is trying to reintroduce the respectful &quot;vous&quot;.{{fact|date=April 2012}}

====Conclusion====
Finally, the language of Quebec is not universal. Noteworthy differences exist when certain regions of Quebec are compared. This difference is tangible between country and urban regions, but they don’t prevent the understanding between regions.

===Atlantic Canada===

[[Image:The Acadians.png|thumb|left|150px|Present-day Acadian communities]]

====Historical review====
 
The colonists initially living in the present-day provinces of [[New Brunswick]] and [[Nova Scotia]] were principally constituted of [[Bretons]], [[Normans]], [[Basques]], and [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]]. Conquered by the English, they suffered [[Expulsion of the Acadians|massive deportations]] to the [[United States]] and [[France]]. Others went into exile to [[Canada (New France)|Canada]] or to nearby islands. Those who stayed were persecuted. At the end of the 18th century, more liberal measures granted new lands to those who had stayed, and measures were taken to promote the return of numerous exiled people from Canada and [[Miquelon]]. 
The number of Acadians rose rapidly, to the point of gaining representation in the [[Legislative Assembly]].
Progressively and with little conflict, the Acadians succeeded in recovering a place in their fatherland. 
This feeling of identity is also present in Louisiana due to the creation of the [[Council for the Development of French in Louisiana]] (CODFIL). The aim of this agency is to develop, to use, and to preserve the French language as it exists in Louisiana.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Landry|first=Nicolas|title=Histoire de l'Acadie|year=2001|publisher=Septentrion|location=Québec}}[http://books.google.be/books?id=SES4PQuGaooC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=histoire+de+l%27acadie&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=sI7CTaanD4SEOuHBtZ0I&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt;

====Origins of the dialect====

Linguists do not agree about the origin of the dialect. [[Acadian French]] is influenced by the ''[[langues d'oïl]]''. The dialect contains, among other features, the [[alveolar consonant|alveolar]] ''r'' and the pronunciation of the final syllable in the plural form of the verb in the third person. 
But Acadia is the only place outside [[Jersey]] (a [[Channel Islands|Channel Island]] close to mainland Normandy) where [[Jèrriais]] speakers can be found.&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis (1996), Thésaurus A-C, p.24&lt;/ref&gt;

====Some characteristics====

Commonly known as [[Acadian French]], the variety of French spoken in [[Atlantic Canada]] possesses features which are different from those of [[Quebec French]]. It is historically related to [[Cajun French]].
French is one of the official languages, with English, of the province of [[New Brunswick]]. Apart from [[Quebec]], this is the only other Canadian province that recognizes French as an official language. Approximately one-third of New Brunswickers are francophone,&lt;ref name=&quot;www12.statcan.ca&quot;/&gt; by far the largest [[Acadian]] population in Canada.
According to Albert Valdman in ''French and Creole in Louisiana'' (1997),&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.be/books?id=nJGvPwAACAAJ&amp;dq=dictionnaire+du+fran%C3%A7ais+acadien&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=XXjCTci3LIKWOvn5xZ0I&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA{{cite book|last=Valdman|first=Albert|title=French and Creole in Louisiana|year=1997|publisher=Premium Press|location=New-York}}]. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt; the characteristics of Acadian are being progressively weakened by the massive contact with Quebeckers. 
According to Pascal Poirier (1884: 63),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Poirier|first=Pascal|title=Nouvelles Soirées Canadiennes|year=1888}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Acadian pronunciation &quot;gets closer to the pronunciation in the vicinity of Tours and of the France Centre&quot;.
According to Raphaële Wiesmath’s work ''Le français acadien: analyse syntaxique d'un corpus oral recueilli au Nouveau-Brunswick, Canada'' (2006),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wiesmath|first=Raphaële|title=Le français acadien: analyse syntaxique d'un corpus oral recueilli au Nouveau-Brunswick, Canada|year=2006|publisher=l'Hamalthan}}[http://books.google.be/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=xwYbbUgbHeIC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA17&amp;dq=+WIESMATH+Rapha%C3%ABle+%282006%29,+Le+fran%C3%A7ais.&amp;ots=BJV8VOihY4&amp;sig=LtvUhwmsnX13CSrEOpxSiP0bO5s#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]. ''Assessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt; some characteristics of Acadian are &quot;''la désinence verbale –ont à la troisième personne du pluriel, la palatalisation de –k et de –g (quinze se prononcerait alors avec [ʧ] et gueule avec [ʤ] ) et «&amp;nbsp;l’ouisme&amp;nbsp;» (bonne&amp;nbsp;: [bun] )''.&quot; It would principally concern old persons’ oral  language.
Yves Cormier’s ''Dictionnaire du français acadien'' (ComiersAcad)&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.be/books?id=nJGvPwAACAAJ&amp;dq=dictionnaire+du+fran%C3%A7ais+acadien&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=XXjCTci3LIKWOvn5xZ0I&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA{{cite book|last=Cormier|first=Yves|title=Dictionnaire du français acadien|year=2009|publisher=Fides, Editions}}]. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt;  includes the majority of Acadian regionalisms. 
From a syntactic point of view, the main point is the use of ''je'' both for the first person singular and for the third plural; the same phenomenon takes place with ''i'' for the third persons. Acadian still differentiates the ''vous'' form  from the ''tu'' form.
Finally as all other varieties of French in Canada, English influenced the dialect and several words which are similar to the English language can be found. Those words are formerly French words used in the English language. 

The Acadian community is concentrated in primarily rural areas along the border with Quebec and the eastern coast of the province. Francophones in the [[Madawaska County, New Brunswick|Madawaska]] area may also be identified as [[Brayon]], although sociologists have disputed whether the Brayons represent a distinct francophone community, a subgroup of the Acadians or an extraprovincial community of Québécois.

The only major Acadian population centre is [[Moncton]], home to the main campus of the [[Université de Moncton]]. Francophones are, however, in the minority in Moncton.

In addition to New Brunswick, Acadian French has speakers in portions of mainland Quebec and in the Atlantic provinces of [[Nova Scotia]], [[Prince Edward Island]], and [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]]. In these provinces, the percentage of francophones is much smaller than in New Brunswick. In some communities, French is an [[endangered language]].

===Ontario===

Although French is the native language of just over half a million Canadians in [[Ontario]], francophone Ontarians represent only 4.4 percent of the province's population. They are concentrated primarily in the [[Eastern Ontario]] and [[Northeastern Ontario]] regions, near the border with [[Quebec]], although they are also present in smaller numbers throughout the province. Forty percent of [[Franco-Ontarian]]s no longer speak the language at home. However, [[Ottawa]] is the city which counts the biggest number of [[Franco-Ontarian]]s.
The Franco-Ontarians are originally from a first wave of immigration from [[France]], from a second wave from [[Quebec]]. The third wave comes from Quebec, but also from [[Haiti]], from [[Europe]], from [[Africa]], from [[Vietnam]], etc.
The province has no official language defined in law, although it is a largely English-speaking province. Ontario law requires that the provincial [[Legislative Assembly]] operate in both English and French (individuals can speak in the Assembly in the official language of their choice), and requires that all provincial statutes and bills be made available in both English and French. Furthermore, under the [[French Language Services Act]], individuals are entitled to communicate with the head or central office of any provincial government department or agency in French, as well as to receive all government services in French in 25 designated areas in the province, selected according to minority population criteria. The provincial government of [[Ontario]]'s website is bilingual. Residents of [[Ottawa]], [[Toronto]], [[Windsor, Ontario|Windsor]], [[Greater Sudbury|Sudbury]] and [[Timmins]] can receive services from their municipal government in the official language of their choice.
Also, there are several French speaking communities on Military bases in Ontario, such as the French speaking community at [[CFB Trenton]]. These communities are founded by French Canadians in the [[Canadian Forces]] who are stationed in Military residences together.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Statistiques Canada|title=Population dont le français est la langue parlée le plus souvent à la maison, Canada, Provinces, territoires et Canada moins le Québec, 1996 à 2006|url=www12.statcan.gc.ca|accessdate=3/05/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Block|first=David|title=Globalization and language teaching|year=2002|publisher=Taylor and Francis Group|author=Heller Monica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====The Franco-Ontarian====

The term [[Franco-Ontarian]] accepts two interpretations. According to the first one, it includes all French speakers of the Ontario, wherever they come from. According to second one, it includes all French Canadians born in Ontario, whatever their level of French is.&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996), Thésaurus K-M, p.2638&lt;/ref&gt;

The modern Franco-Ontarian language is close to the Quebec French with some rare exceptions of expressions and pronunciations. Once again, the influence of English can be noted, with a big recourse to tonic stresses, but nevertheless a French vocabulary is still used. 
According to Michel Laurier (1989),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Laurier|first=Michel|title=Le subjonctif dans le parler franco-ontarien : un mode en voie de disparition ?|year=1989|publisher=Université Carleton}}[http://books.google.be/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=EUzqrzHNwP0C&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA105&amp;dq=LAURIER+Michel+%281989%29,+Le+subjonctif+dans+le+parler+franco-ontarien+:+un+mode+en+voie+de+disparition+%3F,+Universit%C3%A9+Carleton.&amp;ots=uS3ckj-x1D&amp;sig=SlUKqZLFPB5CrvqM_-_hLDOpBgk#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt; the semantic and stylistic value of the use of the subjunctive is progressively disappearing.
In the article «Le français canadien parlé hors Québec : aperçu sociolinguistique » (1989),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Thomas|first=Alain|title=La variabilité en français ontarien|year=1989|publisher=Les presses de l'Université de Laval|location=Canada}}&lt;/ref&gt; Edward Berniak and Raymond Mougeon underline some characteristics: 
* the use of the possessive ''à''
* the transfer of rules from English to French, e.g., « J’ai vu un film sur/à la télévision » which comes from « I saw a film on television », or « Je vais à la maison/chez moi» coming from &quot; I'm going home &quot;
* the loaning of English conjunctions, for instance, &quot;so&quot; for ''ça fait que'' or ''alors''.

The use of French among Franco-Ontarians is in decline due to the omnipresence of the English language in a lot of fields.

===Newfoundland===
====Historical review====

The island is discovered by [[Jean Cabot]] in 1497. [[Newfoundland (island)|Newfoundland]] is annexed by [[England]] in 1583. It is the first British possession in [[North America]]. 
In 1610, the Frenchmen become established in the [[peninsula of Avalon]] and go to war against the Englishmen.
In 1713, the [[Treaty of Utrecht]] acknowledges the sovereignty of the Englishmen. 
The origin of [[Franco-Newfoundlanders]] is double: the first ones to arrive are especially of [[Breton people|Breton]] origin, attracted by the fishing possibilities. Then, from the 19th century, the Acadians who came from the [[Cape Breton Island]] and from the [[Magdalen Islands]], an archipelago of nine small islands belonging to Quebec,  become established. 
Up to the middle of the 20th century, Breton fishers, who had Breton as their mother tongue, but who had been educated in French came to settle. This Breton presence can explain differences between the Newfoundland French and the [[Acadian French]].
In the 1970s, the French language appears in the school of Cape St-George in the form of a bilingual education. 
In the 1980s, classes of French for native French speakers are organized there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlas Universalis 1996 p.57&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Atlas Universalis(1996), Tome 4, p.840-842&lt;/ref&gt;

====Characteristics of French of Newfoundland====
According to Patrice Brasseur’s articles « Les Représentations linguistiques des francophones de la péninsule de Port-au-Port » (2007)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brasseur|first=Patrice|title=Les Représentations linguistiques des francophones de la péninsule de Port-au-Port|journal=Glottopol, Revue de sociolinguistique en ligne|volume=9|pages=66–79}}[http://74.125.155.132/scholar?q=cache:vFNECI8gKpsJ:scholar.google.com/+brasseur+representations+linguistiques&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0,5]. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt;  and «Quelques aspects de la situation linguistique dans la communauté franco-terreneuvienne» (1995)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Brasseur|first=Patrice|title=Quelques aspects de la situation linguistique dans la communauté franco-terreneuvienne|journal=Etudes canadiennes/ Canadian Studies|year=1995|volume=39|pages=103–117}}[http://www.univ-avignon.fr/mini_site/group/222/1995.pdf]. ''Accessed 05 May 2011.''&lt;/ref&gt;  as well as according to the [[French Academy]], some characteristics of French in Newfoundland can be kept in mind:
* the [[affrication]] of [k], noted ''tch'' or, most often, ''ch'' (with the frequent examples of ''coeur'' and ''quinze'' and ''cuiller'' and ''cuisine''),
* the widespread use of English terms,
* the progressive extinction of the subjunctive form
* the use of septante, octante, and nonante

===Western Canada===
Manitoba also has a significant [[Franco-Manitoban]] community, centred especially in the [[St. Boniface, Manitoba|St. Boniface]] area of [[Winnipeg, Manitoba|Winnipeg]], but also in many surrounding villages. The provincial government of [[Manitoba]] boasts the only bilingual website of the Prairies; the Canadian constitution makes French an official language in Manitoba for the legislature and courts. Saskatchewan also has a [[Fransaskois]] community, as does Alberta with its [[Franco-Albertan]]s, and British Columbia hosts the [[Franco-Columbian]]s.

[[Michif]], a dialect of French originating in Western Canada, is a unique [[mixed language]] derived from [[Cree language|Cree]] and French. It is spoken by a small number of [[Metis (people)|Métis]] living mostly in [[Manitoba]] and in [[North Dakota]].

===Northern Canada===
French is an official language in each of the three northern territories: the [[Yukon]], the [[Northwest Territories]], and [[Nunavut]]. Francophones in the Yukon are called [[Franco-Yukonnais]], those from the Northwest Territories, [[Franco-Ténois]] (from the French acronym for the Northwest Territories, ''T.N.-O.''), and those in Nunavut, [[Franco-Nunavois]].

==French-speaking communities in Canada outside of Quebec==
* [[Franco-Ontarian]]s (or ''Ontarois'')
* [[Acadian]]s (in [[New Brunswick]], [[Nova Scotia]] and [[Prince Edward Island]]; also present in portions of [[Quebec]] and [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]])
* [[Franco-Manitoban]]s
* [[Fransaskois]] (in [[Saskatchewan]])
* [[Franco-Albertan]]s
* [[Franco-Columbian]]s
* Franco-Terreneuviens
* [[Franco-Ténois]] (in the [[Northwest Territories]])
* Franco-Yukon(n)ais (in the [[Yukon Territory|Yukon]])
* Franco-Nunavois (in [[Nunavut]])

==See also==
*[[Official bilingualism in Canada]]
*[[French in the United States]]
*[[French language]]
*[[French phonology]]
*[[Languages of Canada]]
*[[Quebec French lexicon]]
* [[Canadian French]]
* [[French Canadian]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1SEC820953 &quot;French language: Canadian French today&quot;] ''[[Canadian Encyclopedia|The Canadian Encyclopedia]]''. Toronto: Hurtig Publishers.
* [http://www.websters-online-dictionary.org/definition/French+Canadian-english/ Canadian French - English Dictionary] 	
* [http://www12.statcan.ca/english/census01/products/analytic/companion/lang/contents.cfm 2001 Census: Language] 	
* [http://www.oqlf.gouv.qc.ca/ Office québécois de la langue française] 	
* [http://www.granddictionnaire.com/ Grand dictionnaire terminologique] 	
* [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/philipsfo/hostie/glossaire/glossaire.html&amp;date=2009-10-26+00:33:22 Salon Québécois Internet's Largest Canadian French Glossary]

{{French dialects by continent}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:French Language In Canada}}
[[Category:French language|Canada]]
[[Category:Languages of Canada]]
[[Category:French dialects|Canada]]
[[Category:National dialects of French|Canada]]
[[Category:French Canada|Language]]

[[de:Französisch in Kanada]]
[[fr:Français canadien]]
[[ru:Французский язык в Канаде]]
[[ta:கனடாவில் பிரெஞ்சு மொழி]]</text>
      <sha1>r8wagqbneh97zr64jtpd88hczm8ev84</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
