<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Occitania</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1149357</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514549993</id>
      <parentid>505628126</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-25T21:22:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.131.231.33</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */ for accuracy ...</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18797">[[Image:Flag of Occitania (with star).svg|right|thumb|200px|A version of the flag frequently used by Occitan activists.]]
[[Image:Occitania blanck map.PNG|thumb|300px|[[Linguistic map]] of Occitania]]
'''Occitania''' ({{lang-oc|'''Occitània'''}}, {{IPA-oc|uksiˈtanjɔ|IPA}}, {{IPA-oc|ukʃiˈtanjɔ|}}, {{IPA-oc|usiˈtanjɔ|}}, {{IPA-oc|uksiˈtanja|}} &lt;small&gt;or&lt;/small&gt; {{IPA-oc|utsiˈtanjɔ|}}),&lt;ref&gt;Regional pronunciations: ''Occitània'' = {{IPA|[u(k)siˈtanjɔ, ukʃiˈtanjɔ, u(k)siˈtanja]}}. Note that the variant ''Occitania*'' = {{IPA|[utsitanˈi(j)ɔ]}} is considered incorrect, since it is influenced by French, according to [[:oc:Gramatica occitana segon los parlars lengadocians|Alibert's prescriptive grammar]] (p. viii) and to the prescriptions of the [[Conselh de la Lenga Occitana|Occitan Language Council]] ([http://www.revistadoc.org/file/Linguistica%20occitana%206%20CLO.pdf p. 101]).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;When speaking Occitan, Occitania can be easily referred to as  '''lo país''' , i.e. 'the country'.&lt;/ref&gt; also sometimes '''lo País d'Òc''', &quot;'''the Oc Country'''&quot;), is the [[historical region]] in southern Europe where [[Occitan language|Occitan]] was historically the main language spoken, and where it is sometimes still used, for the most part as a second language. This cultural area roughly encompasses the southern half of [[France]], as well as [[Monaco]] and smaller parts of [[Italy]] ([[Occitan Valleys]], [[Guardia Piemontese]]) and [[Spain]] ([[Aran Valley]]). Occitania has been recognized as a linguistic and cultural concept since the [[Middle Ages]], but has never been a legal nor a political entity under this name, although the territory was united in Roman times as the ''[[Septem Provinciae|Septem Provinciæ]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/04/The_Roman_Empire_ca_400_AD.png Map of the Roman Empire, ''ca''400 AD]&lt;/ref&gt; and the early Middle Ages (''Aquitanica'' or the [[Visigothic_Kingdom#Kingdom_of_Toulouse|Visigothic Kingdom of Toulouse]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/d/d7/Visigothic_Kingdom.png Map of the Visigothic Kingdom]&lt;/ref&gt;) before the French conquest started in the early 1200s.

Currently about a half million people out of 16 million in the area have a proficient knowledge of Occitan,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.minorityrights.org/1626/france/occitanspeakers.html ''World Directory of Minorities and Indigenous People'']&lt;/ref&gt; although the languages more usually spoken in the area are [[French language|French]], [[Italian language|Italian]], [[Catalan language|Catalan]] and [[Spanish language|Spanish]]. Since 2006, the Occitan language has been an official language of [[Catalonia]], which includes the [[Aran Valley]] where Occitan had gained official status in 1990.

Under later Roman rule (after 355), most of ''Occitania'' was known as ''Aquitania'',&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Pierre Juge (2001) ''Petit précis - Chronologie occitane - Histoire &amp; civilisation'', p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; itself part of [[Septem Provinciae|the Seven Provinces]] with a wider [[Provence]], while the northern provinces of what is now France were called ''Gallia'' ([[Gaul]]).  [[Gallia Aquitania]] (or ''Aquitanica'') is thus also a name used since medieval times for Occitania (i.e. [[Limousin (province)|Limousin]], [[Auvergne (province)|Auvergne]], [[Languedoc]] and [[Gascony]]), including [[Provence]] as well in the early 6th century. Thus the historic [[Duchy of Aquitaine]] must not be confused with the modern French region called [[Aquitaine]]: this is the main reason why the term ''Occitania'' was revived in the mid-19th century. The names &quot;Occitania&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Anglade, ''Grammaire de l'ancien provençal ou ancienne langue d'oc'', 1921, Part I, Chapter 1, p. 9: ''Le mot ''Langue d'Oc'' a d'abord désigné le ''pays'' où se parlait cette langue; c'était une expression géographique. Le pays de langue d'oc s'appelait en latin ''Occitania'' (formé sans doute sur ''Aquitania'')'' (&quot;The words ''Langue d'Oc'' first designated the ''country'' where the language was spoken: it was a geographical expression. The land of the langue d'oc was called ''Occitania'' in Latin (probably coined from ''Aquitania''&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Occitan language&quot; (''Occitana lingua'') appeared in Latin texts from as early as 1242-1254&lt;ref&gt;Frederic Mistral, ''Lo Tresor dóu Felibrige'' (1878-1886), vol. II, p. 1171: &quot;Les textes abondent qui montrent l'origine française ou ecclésiastique des expressions ''lingua occitana'' et ''Occitania''. Le pape Innocent IV (1242-1254), un des premiers parle de ''Occitania'' dans ses lettres; les commissaires de Philippe le Bel qui rédigèrent l'arrêt ''sanè'' des coûtumes de Toulouse se déclarent ''Ad partes linguae occitanae pro reformatione patriae designati'' et stipulent que leur règlement est valable ''in tota lingua occitaniae''.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; to 1290&lt;ref&gt;Robèrt LAFONT (1986) &quot;La nominacion indirècta dels païses&quot;, ''Revue des langues romanes'' nº2, tome XC, pp. 161-171&lt;/ref&gt; and during the following years of the early 14th century; texts exist in which the area is referred to indirectly as &quot;the country of the Occitan language&quot; (''Patria Linguae Occitanae''). This derives from the name [[Lenga d'òc]] that was used in Italian (''Lingua d'òc'') by [[Dante]] in the late 13th century. The somewhat uncommon ending of the term ''Occitania'' is most probably a [[portmanteau]] French clerks coined from ''òc'' {{IPA|[ɔk]}} and ''Aquitània'' {{IPA|[ɑkiˈtanjɑ]}}, thus blending the language and the land in just one concept.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.citizendium.org/wiki/Occitan_language#Name&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Occitan language|Occitan]]'' and ''Lenga d'òc'' both refer to the centuries-old set of [[Romance dialect]]s that use ''òc'' for &quot;yes&quot;.

==Geography==
Occitania includes the following regions:
* The southern half of [[France]]: [[Provence]], [[Drôme]]-[[Vivarais]], [[Auvergne (province)|Auvergne]], [[Limousin (province)|Limousin]], [[Guyenne]], [[Gascony]], southern [[Dauphiné]] and [[Languedoc]]. French is now the dominant language in this area, where Occitan is not recognized as an official language.
* The [[Occitan Valleys]] in the [[Italy|Italian Аlps]], where the Occitan language received legal status in 1999. These are fourteen [[Piedmont]]ese valleys in the provinces of [[Province of Cuneo|Cuneo]] and [[Province of Torino|Torino]], as well as in scattered mountain communities of the [[Liguria]] region ([[province of Imperia]]), and, unexpectedly, in one community ([[Guardia Piemontese]]) in the region of [[Calabria]] ([[province of Cosenza]]).
* The [[Aran valley]], in the [[Pyrenees]], in [[Catalonia]] ([[Spain]]) where Occitan has been an official language since 1990 (status granted by the partial autonomy of Aran Valley, then confirmed by the Catalan Statute)
* The Principality of [[Monaco]] (where Occitan is traditionally spoken besides [[Monégasque dialect|Monégasque]]).

[[Occitan language|Occitan]] or langue d'oc (''lenga d'òc'') is a [[Latin]]-based [[Romance language]] in the same way as [[Spanish language|Spanish]], [[Italian language|Italian]] or [[French language|French]]. There are six main regional varieties with easy intercomprehension among them: [[Provençal dialect|Provençal]] (including [[Niçard]] spoken in the vicinity of [[Nice]]), [[Vivaroalpenc]], [[Auvernhat]], [[Limousin language|Lemosin]], [[Gascon language|Gascon]] (including [[Béarnese dialect|Bearnés]] spoken in [[Béarn]]) and [[Lengadocian]]. All these varieties of the Occitan language are written and valid. '''Standard Occitan''' is a synthesis which respects soft regional adaptations. See also [[Northern Occitan]] and [[Southern Occitan]].

[[Catalan language|Catalan]] is a language very similar to Occitan and there are quite strong historical and cultural links between Occitania and [[Catalonia]].

==History==
{{tone|date=May 2012}}
Written texts in Occitan appeared in the 10th century: it was used at once in legal then literary, scientific and religious texts. The spoken [[dialects]] of Occitan are centuries older and appeared as soon as the 8th century, at least, revealed in [[toponym]]s or in Occitanized words left in [[Latin]] manuscripts, for instance.
[[Image:SpeakFrenchBeClean.jpg|thumb|400px|right|&quot;Speak French, Be Clean&quot; written across the wall of a Southern French school]]

Occitania was often politically united during the Early Middle Ages, under the [[visigoths|Visigothic Kingdom]] and several [[Merovingian]] and [[Carolingian]] sovereigns. In [[Thionville]], nine years before he died (805), [[Charlemagne]] vowed that his empire be partitioned into three autonomous territories according to nationalities and mother tongues: along with the Franco-German and Italian ones, was roughly what is now modern Occitania from the reunion of a broader Provence and Aquitaine.&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Pierre JUGE (2001) ''Petit précis - Chronologie occitane - Histoire &amp; civilisation'', p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; But things didn't go according to plan and at the division of the [[Frankish Empire]] (9th century), Occitania was split into different [[county|counties]], [[duchy|duchies]] and [[monarchy|kingdom]]s, bishops and [[abbot]]s, self-governing communes of its walled cities. Since then the country was never politically united again, though Occitania was united by a common culture which used to cross easily the political, constantly moving boundaries. Occitania suffered a tangle of varying loyalties to nominal sovereigns: from the 9th to the 13th centuries, the [[dukes of Aquitaine]], the [[counts of Foix]], the [[counts of Toulouse]] and the [[List of Aragonese monarchs|Aragonese kings]] rivalled in their attempts at controlling the various ''[[pays]]'' of Occitania.

[[Occitan literature]] was glorious and flourishing at that time: in the 12th and 13th centuries, the [[troubadour]]s invented courtly love (''fin'amor'') and the Lenga d'Òc spread throughout all European cultivated circles. Actually, the terms ''Lenga d'Òc, Occitan'', and ''Occitania'' appeared at the end of the 13th century.

But from the 13th to the 17th centuries, the [[French kings]] gradually conquered Occitania, sometimes by war and slaughtering the population, sometimes by annexation with subtle political intrigue. From the end of the 15th century, the nobility and bourgeoisie started learning French while the people stuck to Occitan (this process began from the 13th century in two northernmost regions, northern Limousin and Bourbonnais). In 1539, [[Francis I of France|Francis I]] issued the [[Ordinance of Villers-Cotterêts]] that imposed the use of French in administration. But despite measures such as this, a strong feeling of national identity against the French occupiers remained and [[Jean Racine]] wrote on a trip to [[Uzès]] in 1662: &quot;What they call France here is the land beyond the [[Loire (river)|Loire]], which to them is a foreign country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Frederic Mistral]], ''Lou Tresor dóu Felibrige ou Dictionnaire provençal-français embrassant les divers dialectes de la langue d'oc moderne'' (1878–1886), vol. I, p. 1182: &quot;Le poète Racine écrivait d'Uzès en 1662: «Nous appelons ici «la France» tout le pays qui est au-delà de la Loire. Celui-ci passe comme une province étrangère.»&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1789, the [[French Revolution|revolutionary]] committees tried to re-establish the autonomy of the &quot;Midi&quot; regions: they used the Occitan language but the [[Jacobin (politics)|Jacobin]] power neutralized them.

The 19th century witnessed a strong revival of the Occitan literature and the writer [[Frédéric Mistral]] was awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Literature]] in 1904.

But from 1881 onwards, children who spoke Occitan at school were punished in accordance with [[Political minister|minister]] [[Jules Ferry]]'s recommendations. That led to a deprecation of the language known as ''la [[vergonha]]'' (the shaming): the whole fourteen million inhabitants of the area spoke Occitan in 1914,&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Anglade, ''Grammaire de l'ancien provençal ou ancienne langue d'oc'', 1921: ''La Langue d'Oc est parlée actuellement par douze ou quatorze millions de Français'' (&quot;Occitan is now spoken by twelve or fourteen million French citizens&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt; but French gained the upper hand during the 20th century. The situation got worse with the media excluding the use of the langue d'oc. In spite of that decline, the Occitan language is still alive and gaining fresh impetus.

==Outer settlements==
Although not really a colony in a modern sense, there was an [[enclave]] in the [[County of Tripoli]]. [[Raymond IV of Toulouse]] founded it in 1102 during the [[Crusades]] north of [[Jerusalem]].
Most people of this county came from Occitania and [[Italy]] and so the Occitan language was spoken.

==Today==
{{Cleanup-rewrite|2=section|date=October 2010}}
There are 14 to 16 million inhabitants in Occitania today. According to the 1999 census, there are 610,000 native speakers and another million persons with some exposure to the language. Native speakers of Occitan are to be found mostly in the older generations. The [[Institut d'Estudis Occitans]] (IEO) has been modernizing the Occitan language since 1945, and the Conselh de la Lenga Occitana (CLO) since 1996. Nowadays Occitan is used in the most modern musical and literary styles such as rock 'n roll, folk rock ([[Lou Dalfin]]), rap ([[Fabulous Trobadors]]), reggae ([[Massilia Sound System]]) and heavy metal, detective stories or science-fiction. It is represented on the internet. Association schools (''[[Calandretas]]'') teach children in Occitan.

The Occitan political movement for self-government has existed since the beginning of the 20th century and particularly since post-war years ([[Partit Occitan]], [[Partit de la Nacion Occitana]], [[Anaram Au Patac]], [[Iniciativa Per Occitània]], [[Paratge]], etc.). The movement remains negligible in electoral and political terms. Nevertheless, Regional Elections in 2010 allowed the [[Partit Occitan]] to enter the Regional councils of Aquitaine, Auvergne, Midi-Pyrénées, and Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur.

Major demonstrations in [[Carcassonne]]  (2005 and 2009) and [[Béziers]] (2007) and the week-long ''Estivada'' festivals in [[Rodez]] (2006–2010) suggest that there is a revival of Occitan language and culture.  However, in France, Occitan is still not recognized as an official language, as [[Language policy in France|the status of French has been constitutionally protected since 1992]], and Occitan activists want the French government to adopt Occitan as the second official language for seven regions representing the South of France. {{Citation needed|date=December 2008}}

==Culture==
{{further2|[[Languedoc-Roussillon#Culture]]}}
{{see also|Occitan cuisine}}
The [[Romantic music]] composer [[Déodat de Séverac]] was born in the region, and, following his schooling in Paris, he returned to the region to compose.  He sought to incorporate the music indigenous to the area in his compositions.

==Notable people from Occitania==
{{columns
|col1width=27.0em
|col1=
*[[Eleanor of Aquitaine]]
*[[Jean Anouilh]]
*[[Emmanuelle Béart]]
*[[Henry IV of France]]
*[[Joan Bodon]]
*[[Pierre Bayle]]
*[[François Bayrou]]
*[[Bertrand de Born]]
*[[Pierre Bourdieu]]
*[[Georges Brassens]]
*[[Francis Cabrel]]
*[[Antoine Laumet de La Mothe, sieur de Cadillac]]
*[[Eric Cantona]]
*[[Paul Cézanne]]
*[[Jean-François Champollion]]
*[[Charles XIV John of Sweden|Charles XIV John of Sweden (Jean Bernadotte)]]
*[[Auguste Comte]]
|col2width=19.0em
|col2=
*[[Fernandel]]
*[[François Darlan]]
*[[Marcela Delpastre]]
*[[Gilbert du Motier, marquis de La Fayette|Lafayette]]
*[[Louis-Joseph de Montcalm]]
*[[Michel de Montaigne]]
*[[Gabriel Fauré]]
*[[Pierre de Fermat]]
*[[Valéry Giscard d'Estaing]]
*[[Daniel Goossens]]
*[[Jean Jaurès]]
*[[Yves Klein]]
*[[Robert Lafont]]
*[[Serge Lama]]
*[[Bernard Laporte]]
*[[François Mauriac]]
*[[Fleury Mesplet]]
|col3width=24.0em
|col3=
*[[Frédéric Mistral]]
*[[Nostradamus]]
*[[Georges Pompidou]]
*[[Claude Puel]]
*[[Richard I]]
*[[Ives Roqueta]]
*[[Max Roqueta]]
*[[Charles de Secondat, Baron de Montesquieu]]
*[[Déodat de Séverac]]
*[[Bernadette Soubirous]]
*[[Audrey Tautou]]
*[[Pierre Teilhard de Chardin]]
*[[Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec]]
*[[Paul Valéry]]
*[[Jean Parisot de la Valette]]
*[[Simone Veil]]
*[[Bernard de Ventadour]]
*[[Mans de Breish]]
}}

==See also==
{{Commons category|Occitània|Occitania}}
* [[Baìo]]
* [[Occitan conjugation]]
* [[Occitan cross]]
* [[Occitan cuisine]]
* [[Vergonha]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.occitania.fr/ occitania.fr]
* [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/guilhem_nou/CLO0.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+23:35:57  The Council of the Occitan Language (Conselh de la Lenga Occitana)]
* [http://occitanet.free.fr/en/index.html Occitanet - a guide to the language (English option)]
* [http://globegate.utm.edu/french/globegate_mirror/occit.html Troubadour &amp; Early Occitan Literature]
* [http://www.lexilogos.com/occitan_langue_dictionnaires.htm Guide to online Occitan dictionaries]
* [http://www.radio-occitania.com/ Radio Occitania]
* [http://occitan.paris.free.fr/ Informations webpage in occitan from Paris]
* [http://www.a-o-f.org/ Occitan Football Association]
* {{en icon}} {{fr icon}} {{oc icon}} [http://mtcn.free.fr/ Dances and traditional music used in the County of Nice]

&lt;!-- Interwikis found using http://vs.aka-online.de/globalwpsearch/ --&gt;

[[Category:Occitania| ]]
[[Category:Geographical, historical and cultural regions of France]]
[[Category:Geographical, historical and cultural regions of Italy]]
[[Category:Historical regions in Spain]]
[[Category:Geography of Catalonia]]
[[Category:French society]]
[[Category:Divided regions]]

[[ar:أوكسيطانيا]]
[[an:Occitania]]
[[frp:Occitania]]
[[ast:Occitania]]
[[zh-min-nan:Occitania]]
[[be:Аксітанія]]
[[be-x-old:Аксытанія]]
[[br:Okitania]]
[[ca:Occitània]]
[[cv:Окситани]]
[[cs:Okcitánie]]
[[de:Okzitanien]]
[[el:Οξιτανία]]
[[es:Occitania]]
[[eo:Okcitanio]]
[[eu:Okzitania]]
[[fa:اوکیتانیا]]
[[fr:Occitanie]]
[[fur:Ocitanie]]
[[gv:Yn Ocsitaan]]
[[gl:Occitania - Occitània]]
[[ko:오시타니아]]
[[hr:Oksitanija]]
[[io:Ocitania]]
[[id:Ositania]]
[[os:Окситани]]
[[it:Occitania]]
[[ku:Oksîtanya]]
[[lt:Oksitanija]]
[[lmo:Ucitània]]
[[nl:Occitanië]]
[[ja:オクシタニア]]
[[no:Oksitania]]
[[oc:Occitània]]
[[nds:Okzitanien]]
[[pl:Oksytania]]
[[pt:Occitânia]]
[[ro:Occitania]]
[[rm:Occitania]]
[[qu:Uqsitaniya]]
[[ru:Окситания]]
[[sk:Occitánia]]
[[ckb:ئوکسیتانیا]]
[[sh:Oksitanija]]
[[sv:Occitanien]]
[[ta:ஒக்சித்தானியா]]
[[tr:Oksitanya]]
[[uk:Окситанія]]
[[zh:歐西坦尼亞]]</text>
      <sha1>o8xvstmteih1qqpuyybctso2mobpw42</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
