<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Vergonha</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11737832</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520251614</id>
      <parentid>517340823</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T11:45:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gr8opinionater</username>
        <id>4847711</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32556">''La '''vergonha''''' ({{IPA-oc|berˈɣuɲɔ, veʀˈguɲɔ}}, meaning &quot;shame&quot;) is what [[Occitans]] call the effects of various policies of the [[government of France]] on its citizens whose mother tongue was a so-called ''[[patois]]'', specifically ''[[langue d'oc]]''&lt;ref&gt;''Patois: Any of various French or Occitan dialects spoken in France.'' [http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/patois Wiktionary]&lt;/ref&gt;. ''Vergonha'' is being made to reject and feel ashamed of one's (or one's parents') non-[[French language]] through official exclusion, humiliation at school and [[Social rejection|rejection]] from the [[Media (communication)|media]] as organized and sanctioned by French political leaders{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}, from [[Henri Grégoire]] onward. ''Vergonha'', which is still a taboo topic in France&lt;ref&gt;A clear sign of this ostracism and obscurantism is how all and any articles about or mentions of Vergonha and similar linguicidal policies elsewhere in France, have been systematically edited out or deleted from the French [[Wikipedia]]. This very article has counterparts in the Occitan, Catalan and Basque Wikipedias but not in the French one. http://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?search=vergonha&amp;title=Sp%C3%A9cial%3ARecherche&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Websites, blogs and [[YouTube]] channels referring to ''la Vergonha'' or linking to documents about it are known to be blocked by the French versions of [[Facebook]] and [[Wikipedia]]. One of them, [http://monoccitania.50webs.com/ MonOccitània], even advertises about the censorship it falls victim to.&lt;/ref&gt; where some still refuse to admit such discrimination ever existed, can be seen as the result of an attempted [[linguicide]]&lt;ref name=&quot;geocities.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.reocities.com/Athens/pantheon/8883/ Llengua Nacional, Catalan linguistic review], spring of 2002. Text available at http://fpl.forumactif.com/Forum-Occitan-f11/Le-patois-des-vieux-el-patues-dels-vells-p11914.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://oc.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vergonha_(ling%C3%BCicidi)&lt;/ref&gt;. As a matter of fact, native Occitan speakers, who in [[Demographics_of_France#Historical_population_of_metropolitan_France|1860]], before schooling was made compulsory in French ([[1882_in_France#Events|1882]]), represented more than 39%&lt;ref&gt;Louis de Baecker, ''Grammaire comparée des langues de la France'', 1860, p. 52: ''parlée dans le Midi de la France par quatorze millions d'habitants'' (&quot;spoken in the South of France by fourteen million inhabitants&quot;). [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k5846989r.f61.pagination.langEN.hl] + [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k5846989r.f63.langEN]&lt;/ref&gt; of the whole French population, as opposed to 52% of [[Francophone|francophones]] proper, went down to 26 to 36% in the 1920s&lt;ref&gt;Yann Gaussen, ''Du fédéralisme de Proudhon au Félibrige de Mistral'', 1927, p. 4: ''[...] défendre une langue, qui est aujourd'hui la mère de la nôtre, parlée encore par plus de dix millions d'individus [...]'' (&quot;protect a language, which is today the mother of ours, still spoken by more than ten million individuals&quot;). [http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k57104841.image.langEN.f6.pagination]&lt;/ref&gt;, with the figure free-falling to less than 7% in 1993&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Barbour &amp; Cathie Carmichael, ''Language and nationalism in Europe'', 2000, p. 62: Occitan is spoken in 31 ''départements'', but even the [[European Bureau for Lesser-Used Languages|EBLUL]] (1993: 15-16) is wary of statistics: 'There are no official data on the number of speakers. Of some 12 to 13 million inhabitants in the area, it is estimated 48 per cent understand Occitan, 28 per cent can speak it, about 9 per cent of the population use it on a daily basis, 13 per cent can read and 6 per cent can write the language.'&lt;/ref&gt;. 

==16th to 18th century==
Beginning in 1539 with Art. 111 of the [[Ordinance of Villers-Cotterêts]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/histoire/villers-cotterets.asp Ordinance of Villers-Cotterêt]&lt;/ref&gt;, non-French languages in France were reduced in stature when it became compulsory &quot;to deliver and execute all [legal] acts in the French language&quot; (''de prononcer et expedier tous actes en langaige françoys''). Originally meant as a way to eliminate [[Latin]] in official documents — few 16th-century French subjects were educated and familiar with Latin — it also stated that French and only French was legal in the kingdom (''en langage maternel françoys et non aultrement''). 

==Late 18th to late 19th century==
===Abbé Grégoire's &quot;Report on the necessity and means to annihilate the patois&quot;===
The deliberate process of eradicating non-French [[vernacular]]s in modern France and disparaging them as mere local and often strictly oral dialects was formalized with [[Abbé Grégoire]]'s ''Report on the necessity and means to annihilate the patois and to universalise the use of the French language'' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.languefrancaise.net/dossiers/dossiers.php?id_dossier=66 Abbé Grégoire's ''Report on the necessity and means to annihilate the patois and to universalize the use of the French language'']&lt;/ref&gt;, which he presented on June 4, 1794 to the [[National Convention]]; thereafter, all languages other than French were officially banned in the administration and schools for the sake of [[linguistics|linguistically]] uniting post-[[Bastille Day]] France. At the time, only one tenth of the population were fluent in French.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gwalarn.org/brezhoneg/istor/gregoire.html L'Abbé Grégoire en guerre contre les &quot;Patois&quot;, Hervé Luxardo, gwalarn.org]&lt;/ref&gt; In reference to &quot;patois&quot;, [[Jean Jaurès]] famously claimed that &quot;one names ''patois'' the language of a defeated nation&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://rleb07.free.fr/opinions/vecteur.html A new &quot;Common Vector&quot;, Robert L.E. Billon, April 2000, rleb07.free.fr]&lt;/ref&gt;. According to the ''[[Chambers Dictionary]]'', the origin of the term is disputed but could be a &quot;corruption of ''patrois'', from [[Vulgar Latin|LL]] ''patriensis'', a local inhabitant&quot;.

Four months earlier (January 27), [[Bertrand Barère de Vieuzac]], although an Occitan from [[Tarbes]] himself, claimed &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tlfq.ulaval.ca/axl/Europe/france-2politik_francais.htm L'aménagement linguistique dans le monde - La politique linguistique du français, www.tlfq.ulaval.ca]&lt;/ref&gt; before this same Convention that
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The monarchy had reasons to resemble the [[Tower of Babel]]; in [[democracy]], leaving the citizens to ignore the national language [that of Paris], unable to control the power, is betraying the motherland... For a free people, the tongue must be one and the same for everyone. [...] How much money have we not spent already for the translation of the laws of the first two [[National Assembly (French Revolution)|national assemblies]] in the various dialects of France! As if it were our duty to maintain those barbaric jargons and those coarse lingos that can only serve fanatics and [[Counter-revolutionary|counter-revolutionaries]] now!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===The end of traditional provinces===
This policy can be noted by the way France's internal borders were redrawn, creating 83 [[Departments of France|''départements'']]. The law was passed on December 22, 1789 and took effect the following year, on March 4, 1790. As a result, the centuries-old singularities of the various Occitan-speaking parts were overlooked and shaken in a deliberate effort by the newly-formed government to weaken and parcel out long-established feudal domains so that republican France would subdue traditional allegiances, as [[Antonin Perbòsc]] reveals in the Foreword to his ''Anthologie'':&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Georges Labouysse's ''Histoire de France: L'Imposture. Mensonges et manipulations de l'Histoire officielle'' p. 234. IEO Edicions&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
When the ''Constituante'' ([[National Constituent Assembly]]) created the ''départements'', their goal was clearly to erase the old geographical and historical distinction of the provinces; however this goal was not as perfectly met as some would have liked: in general, the ''départements'' were made up of pieces of existing provinces, quite seldom of the reunion of parts from different provinces. If one could criticize this territorial division for being too arbitrary and too geometric, what can be said of [[Tarn-et-Garonne]], born of a ''sénatus-consule'' (a law by the [[Senate of France]]) on November 2, 1808? Of course, one may think that the ''Centralisateur'' ([[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon Bonaparte]]) felt real pleasure showing he could do even better than the ''centralisateurs'' of the National Constituent Assembly. With fragments of [[Quercy]], [[Rouergue]], [[Agen]]ais, [[Lomagne]], [[Gascony]] and [[Languedoc]], creating a new unit so little vast and yet so diverse of soil, language and race, what a great idea! And maybe the audacious half-god had only one regret: coming a little too late to redesign according to this pattern all the provinces of old France...
&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

In the 20th century, the ''départements'' were grouped into ''[[Regions of France|régions]]'', to create a level of government between the departmental and national. While the ''régions'' were intended to replace the old provinces, they were not necessarily formed along the same boundaries. As the map shows, there were eleven Occitan-speaking enclaves in the pre-1789 state, such as the powerful lands of [[Languedoc]] and [[Gascony]], but they were divided into seven ''régions'' with no regard whatsoever for cultural and linguistic identities. This is how [[Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur]] was created out of portions of five Occitan provinces and three capitals were scrapped in favour of [[Marseille]]; and [[Auvergne (region)|Auvergne]] came to comprise both native and [[Langues d'oïl|Oïl-language]] entities. Meanwhile, the city of [[Nantes]] was administratively removed from [[Brittany]], of which it had been one of two traditional capitals (along with [[Rennes]]), and the city of [[Toulouse]] was not included in the ''région'' of [[Languedoc-Roussillon]], though it had historically been located in that province.

Many of the ''régions'' contain hyphenated names, reflecting the merging of multiple historically distinct areas.  This is true for four of the seven ''régions'' of Occitania: Languedoc-Roussillon, [[Midi-Pyrénées]], Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur and [[Rhône-Alpes]]. 
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;|center
|-
| [[Image:OccitanProvincesVsFrenchRegions.JPG|400px]]
| Traditional Occitan provinces:&lt;br /&gt;
1. [[Béarn]] ([[Pau, Pyrénées-Atlantiques|Pau]]) — 6,800&amp;nbsp;km² (est.) &lt;br /&gt;
2. [[Guyenne]] &amp; Gascony ([[Bordeaux]]) — 69,400&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
3. [[Limousin (province)|Limousin]] ([[Limoges]]) — 9,700&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
4. [[County of Marche]] ([[Guéret]]) — 7,600&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
5. [[Auvergne (province)|Auvergne]] ([[Riom]]) — 19,300&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
6. Languedoc (Toulouse) — 45,300&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
7. [[Dauphiné]] ([[Grenoble]]) — 8,500&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
8. County of [[Nice]] — 3,600&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
9. [[Provence]] ([[Aix-en-Provence]]) — 22,700&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
10. [[Comtat Venaissin]] ([[Carpentras]]) — 3,600&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
11. [[County of Foix]] ([[Foix]]) — 3,300&amp;nbsp;km² (est.)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Régions of France:&lt;br /&gt;
A. [[Aquitaine]] (Bordeaux) — 41,308&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
B. [[Limousin (region)|Limousin]] (Limoges) — 16,942&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
C. Auvergne ([[Clermont-Ferrand]]) — 26,013&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
D. Rhône-Alpes ([[Lyon]]) — 43,698&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
E. Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur (Marseille) — 31,400&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
F. Languedoc-Roussillon ([[Montpellier]]) — 27,376&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
G. Midi-Pyrénées (Toulouse) — 45,348&amp;nbsp;km²&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
- - -: Occitan / [[Franco-Provençal language|Franco-Provençal]] linguistic limit
|}

*Toulouse lost 76% of its territory of Languedoc
*Bordeaux lost a little more than half its territory of Gascony and Guyenne
*Limoges increased its administrative area by 43%
*Guéret, Pau, Foix, Riom, Aix-en-Provence, Grenoble, Carpentras (1791) and Nice (1860) lost their status as capitals
*Clermont-Ferrand, Montpellier and Marseille became capitals of Auvergne, Languedoc-Roussillon and Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur, respectively
*Languedoc was divided into five unequal parts, the largest of which forming Languedoc-Roussillon with the [[Catalan language|Catalan]]-speaking province of [[Roussillon]]
*The County of Marche, Béarn, the County of Foix and subsequently Comtat Venaissin and the County of Nice lost their autonomy
*Provence-Alpes-Côte d'Azur is made up of Provence and the County of Nice and bits and pieces of three other provinces
*The north of Languedoc and Comtat Venaissin and the western half of Dauphiné became linguistic minorities in the new Rhône-Alpes region 
*The Occitan provinces spread over a little less than 200,000&amp;nbsp;km²
*Gascony and Guyenne, Languedoc, Provence and Auvergne accounted for 78.4% of Occitania in terms of land area, with Gascony and Guyenne making up for over a third of the total surface and Languedoc almost a quarter

==Late 19th century - Policies and legacy of Jules Ferry==
===School discipline===
In the 1880s, [[Jules Ferry]] implemented a series of strict measures to further weaken ''regional'' languages in France, as shown in Bernard Poignant's 1998 report to [[Lionel Jospin]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chez.com/buan1/poignant.htm LANGUES ET CULTURES REGIONALES - Rapport de Monsieur Bernard Poignant - Maire de Quimper A Monsieur Lionel Jospin - Premier Ministre Le 1er juillet 1998, chez.com]&lt;/ref&gt;. These included children being given [[punishments]] by their teachers for speaking Occitan in a [[Toulouse]] school or [[Breton language|Breton]] in [[Brittany]]. Art. 30 of ''Loi d'éducation française'' (French Teaching Law, 1851) stated that: &quot;It is strictly forbidden to speak patois during classes or breaks.&quot; As [[Pêr-Jakez Helias]] (1914-1995), the author of the 1975 best-selling novel ''Le Cheval d'orgueil'' (The Horse of Pride), recalls in this interview &lt;ref&gt;http://217.147.194.129/cata.php?catalogueID=6250{{Dead link|date=May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;, 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Now I know, I learned that there was a government policy which goal was obviously to make France one and indivisible, and as a result regional languages had to disappear. But I didn't know it then and maybe the teachers of the [[French Third Republic|Third Republic]] did, though I asked some of them and they all denied it. Their own job was to teach us French. And consequently, while attending school, we were required to speak French. Whenever we used Breton instead, we weren't doing our share and so we deserved to be expelled. Period.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Image:SpeakFrenchBeClean.jpg|thumb|400px|right|&quot;Speak French, Be Clean&quot; written on the wall of the [[Ayguatébia-Talau]] school]]

Among other well-known humiliations was ''clogging'' young rebels, namely hanging a clog (''sabot'') around their necks as this young lady recalls her grandparents telling her:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.tripod.com/~SuuHialat/hialat3c.html Ecoles Diwan|title=Ecoles Diwan, la bosse du breton|last=de la Casinière|first=Nicolas|date=October 1, 1998|language=fr|accessdate=2008-06-28}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
My grandparents speak Breton too, though not with me. As children, they used to [[Rulering (punishment)|have their fingers smacked]] if they happened to say a word in Breton. Back then, the French of the Republic, one and indivisible, was to be heard in all schools and those who dared challenge this policy were humiliated with having to wear a clog around their necks or kneel down on a ruler under a sign that read: &quot;It is forbidden to spit on the ground and speak Breton&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bretagne.lalibreblogs.be/media/01/00/3d75e7dbef78f875f7cc337be5138241.jpg An example sign at bretagne.lalibreblogs.be]. The sign reads (in French): &quot;To all school pupils: It is forbidden 1. to speak Breton and spit on the ground; 2. to wet your fingers with your mouth to turn the pages of books and notebooks; 3. to insert the tip of a pen or penholder into your ear; 4. to clean your slates with your spit or directly with your tongue; 5. to hold pens, penholders, coins etc between your lips. Now do you want to know why these things are forbidden? Ask your teachers: they will give you the necessary explanations. And remember your duty is not just to obey these rules but to make sure everyone else applies them.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; That's the reason why some older folks won't transmit the language to their children: it brings trouble upon yourself...
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This practice was referred to as [[Symbole|le symbole]] by officials and &quot;la vache&quot; (the cow) by pupils, with offenders becoming &quot;vachards&quot;. Many objects were used, not just clogs: horseshoes, shingles, slates, wooden plates with a message, coins with a cross on them. The following are official instructions from a [[Finistère]] sub-prefect to teachers in 1845: &quot;And remember, Gents: you were given your position in order to kill the Breton language.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;France pp. 90-92&quot;&gt;Georges Labouysse in ''Histoire de France: L'Imposture. Mensonges et manipulations de l'Histoire officielle'' pp. 90-92. IEO Edicions&lt;/ref&gt; The prefect of [[Basses-Pyrénées]] in the French [[Northern Basque Country|Basque Country]] wrote in 1846: &quot;Our schools in the Basque Country are particularly meant to substitute the [[Basque language]] with French...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;France pp. 90-92&quot;/&gt;

Resorting to the practice of ''clogging'' is confirmed by the Autonomes de Solidarité Laïques website &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.autonome-solidarite.fr/?fas-usu=tribune&amp;type=politique&amp;id=1497 La neutralité politique, philosophique et religieuse et l’école, Autonomes de Solidarité Laïques website]&lt;/ref&gt;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
School has had a unifying role inasmuch as speaking the &quot;noble&quot; language [French] reduced the use of regional dialects and ''patois''. Let us mention the humiliation of children made to wear a clog around their necks for inadvertently speaking a word in the language of the people. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
As for signs, they were also found in [[Poitou]] schools &lt;ref&gt;[http://parlange.free.fr/pages/bas_poitevin.html Parlange : témoignages sur les patois du Bas-Poitou, parlange.free.fr]&lt;/ref&gt;:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
It seems as though Jules Ferry making school free and compulsory in 1881 materialized the work started four centuries earlier [with the [[Ordinance of Villers-Cotterêts]]]; the method of repression and humiliation that was undertaken bore fruit with, for instance, the famous signs in school reading: &quot;It is forbidden to spit on the ground and speak ''patois''.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The Conselh de Representacion Generala de la Joventut d'Òc (CRGJOC, General Representation Council of the Occitan Youth), through the Youth of European Nationalities website &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yeni.org/default.php?s=members&amp;p=members/membersitem.php&amp;id=204&amp;m=&amp;l=english Conselh de Representacion Generala de la Joventut d'Òc (CRGJOC) : Organization, at the Youth of European Nationalities Website]&lt;/ref&gt;, reports that
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Our language [Occitan] lost its name, becoming some &quot;''patois''&quot;, first at school and then in families through putting pressure on women in education (&quot;''Interdit de cracher par terre et de parler patois''&quot;) with the French Third Republic, [[Benito Mussolini|Mussolini]] and [[Francisco Franco|Franco]].
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The Confolentés Occitan (Occitan-speaking [[Limousin (province)|Limousin]]) website &lt;ref&gt;[http://ujan.free.fr/englOc2.htm Occitan : a short history, Confolentés Occitan website (ujan.free.fr)]&lt;/ref&gt; testifies of the methods used by French authorities over the past century or so:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
To help efface traditional regional identities, the Occitan language was not merely discouraged but actively suppressed. School pupils were punished well within living memory for speaking their native language on school premises.

The French administration managed to make the Occitan speakers think of their own language as a patois, i.e. as a corrupted form of French used only by the ignorant and uneducated. This alienating process is known as ''la vergonha'' (&quot;the shame&quot;).

Many older speakers of Occitan still believe that their native language is no more than a shameful patois. This is one reason why you rarely hear it in public — or anywhere outside of the neighbourhood or family circle.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the school of Camélas in [[Northern Catalonia]], a former pupil reports,&lt;ref&gt;''Quatre femmes en Roussillon'', TV show, 1st April 1973&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Everyone but the teacher's children spoke [[Catalan language|Catalan]] among themselves. We'd even get punished for that, because at the time, we all had to speak French. ''Be Clean, Speak French'' could be found written on the school's walls. And if you refused to speak French, they'd give you some sort of wooden sign to wear ''until death came'', as we said, which meant the last offender, in the evening, had twenty lines to copy. We'd speak French in the schoolyard, and for the first ten metres of the way back home, for as long as we thought the teacher would overhear us, and then we'd switch back to our own mother tongue, Catalan.

In those times, Catalan speakers were rather despised. My generation associated speaking Catalan with a disadvantage, with being less than the others, with running the risk of being left behind on the social ladder, in short with bringing trouble.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Abbé Grégoire's own terms were kept to designate the languages of France: while Breton referred to the dialect spoken in Brittany, the word ''patois'' encompassed all [[Romance languages|Romance]] ''dialects'' such as Occitan and [[Franco-Provençal]]. In his report, [[Corsican language|Corsican]] and [[Alsatian language|Alsatian]] were dismissed as &quot;highly degenerate&quot; (''très-dégénérés'') forms of [[Italian language|Italian]] and [[German language|German]], respectively. As a result, some people still call their non-French language ''patois'', encouraged by the fact they were never taught how to write it and made to think only French exists in the written form.

===Pressure on the church===
In 1902, in a speech before the ''[[Conseil général#Administrative role|Conseil Général]]'' of [[Morbihan]], Chief Education Officer Dantzer recommended that &quot;the Church give [[first communion]] only to French-speaking children&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;livre-blanc-et-noir-de-la-langue-bretonne&quot;&gt;[http://www.kervarker.org/fr/levr_27_period.html Livre blanc et noir de la langue bretonne, kervarker.org]&lt;/ref&gt;.

In the same year, prime minister [[Émile Combes]], himself an Occitan, told the prefects of Morbihan, [[Côtes-d'Armor|Côtes-du-Nord]] and [[Finistère]]&lt;ref name=&quot;livre-blanc-et-noir-de-la-langue-bretonne&quot; /&gt; that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Breton priests want to keep their flock in ignorance by refusing to promote education and using only the Breton language in religious teachings and [[catechism]]. The Bretons will only be part of the Republic the day they start speaking French.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Mid-20th century to the present==
As the doctor in [[Catalan language|Catalan]] [[philology]] and professor at the [[University of the Balearic Islands]] [[Jaume Corbera Pou]] argues&lt;ref name=&quot;geocities.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://dodeparaula.blogspot.com/search?q=patu%C3%A8s&lt;/ref&gt;,
&lt;blockquote&gt;
When at the mid-19th century, primary school is made compulsory all across the State, it is also made clear that only French will be taught, and the teachers will severely punish any pupil speaking in ''patois''. The aim of the French educational system will consequently not be to dignify the pupils' natural humanity, developing their culture and teaching them to write their language, but rather to humiliate them and morally degrade them for the simple fact of being what tradition and their nature made them. The self-proclaimed country of the &quot;[[Human rights]]&quot; will then ignore one of man's most fundamental rights, the right to be himself and speak the language of his nation. And with that attitude France, the &quot;grande France&quot; that calls itself the champion of liberty, will pass the 20th century, indifferent to the timid protest movements of the various linguistic communities it submitted and the literary prestige they may have given birth to.

[...]

France, that under [[Francisco Franco|Franco]]'s reign was seen here [in [[Catalonia]]] as the safe haven of freedom, has the miserable honour of being the State of [[Europe]] — and probably the world — that succeeded best in the diabolical task of destroying its own ethnic and linguistic patrimony and moreover, of destroying human family bonds: many parents and children, or grandparents and grandchildren, have different languages, and the latter feel ashamed of the first because they speak a despicable ''patois'', and no element of the grandparents' culture has been transmitted to the younger generation, as if they were born out of a completely new world. This is the French State that has just entered the 21st century, a country where stone monuments and natural landscapes are preserved and respected, but where many centuries of popular creation expressed in different tongues are on the brink of extinction. The &quot;gloire&quot; and the &quot;grandeur&quot; built on a genocide. [[liberté, égalité, fraternité|No liberty, no equality, no fraternity]]: just cultural extermination, this is the real motto of the French Republic.
&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

===Constitutional issues===
In 1972, [[Georges Pompidou]], the President of France and a native of an Occitan-speaking region, declared that &quot;there is no room for regional languages in a France whose fate is to mark Europe with its seal&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurominority.eu/documents/transferts/Audition%202-3%2007%2007%20discrimination%20linguistique-1.pdf Conséquences sociales, économiques et politiques de la discrimination linguistique. Audition au Parlement européen, groupe ALDE. La République française : non-droit au nom de l'égalité pour les locuteurs des langues régionales ou minoritaires Tangi Louarn, président d'EBLUL-France]&lt;/ref&gt;.

In a pre-election speech&lt;ref&gt;[http://pactedeslangues.com/spip.php?article1824 Le temps est venu d’un statut des langues et cultures de France, at pactedeslangues.com]&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Lorient]], on March 14, 1981, [[François Mitterrand]] asserted that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''The time has come to give the languages and cultures of France an official status. The time has come to open school doors wide for them, to create regional radio and TV stations to let them be broadcast, to ensure they play all the role they deserve in public life.''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
These declarations however were not followed by any effective measures.

In 1992, after some questioned the unconstitutional segregation of minority languages in France, Art. II of the 1958 [[French Constitution]] was revised so that &quot;the language of the Republic is French&quot; (''la langue de la République est le français''). This was achieved only months before the [[Council of Europe]] passed the [[European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://conventions.coe.int/treaty/en/Treaties/Html/148.htm European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages, Strasbourg, 5.XI.1992]&lt;/ref&gt;, which [[Jacques Chirac]] ignored &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.humanite.fr/popup_print.php3?id_article=291867 Langues régionales : Jospin saisit Chirac, www.humanite.fr, June 24, 1999]&lt;/ref&gt; despite [[Lionel Jospin]]'s plea for the [[Constitutional Council of France|Constitutional Council]] to amend Art. II and include all vernacular languages spoken on French soil. Yet again, non-French languages in France were denied official recognition and deemed too dangerous for the unity of the country&lt;ref&gt;Art. 1 of the French Constitution states that ''La France est une République indivisible, laïque, démocratique et sociale'', France is an indivisible, secular, democratic and social Republic.&lt;/ref&gt;, and [[Occitania|Occitans]], [[Basques]], [[Corsicans]], [[Catalan people|Catalans]], [[Bretons]], [[Alsace|Alsatians]], [[Savoyards]] and [[Flemings]] have still no explicit legal right to conduct public affairs in their regional languages within their home lands. The text was again refused&lt;ref&gt;[http://ouiaubreton.com/spip.php?article3466 Langues régionales : on verra plus tard, ouiaubreton.com]&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Union for a Popular Movement|majority]] deputies on January 18, 2008, after the [[Académie française]] voiced their absolute disapproval&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lepoint.fr/actualites-societe/2008-06-17/l-academie-francaise-contre-les-langues-regionales-dans-la/920/0/253644&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lavanguardia.es/lv24h/20080616/53482013513.html&lt;/ref&gt; of so-called regional languages, which recognition they perceive as &quot;an attack on French national identity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/jun/17/france | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Local language recognition angers French academy | first=Angelique | last=Chrisafis | date=June 17, 2008 | accessdate=May 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On the [[Union for a Popular Movement|UMP]] website&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.u-m-p.org/propositions/index.php?id=charte_europeene_des_langues_regionales Charte européenne des langues régionales, L'Abécédaire des propositions de Nicolas Sarkozy, UMP website]&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] denies any mistreatment of regional languages. In a pre-[[French presidential election, 2007|electoral]] speech in [[Besançon]] on March 13, 2007 he claimed:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
''If I'm elected, I won't be in favour of the European Charter for Regional Languages. I don't want a judge with a historical experience of the issue of minorities different from ours deciding tomorrow that a regional language must be considered as a language of the Republic just like French.''&lt;br&gt;''Because, beyond the text itself, there is a dynamic of interpretations and jurisprudence that can go very far. I am convinced that in France, the land of freedom, no minority is discriminated against and consequently it is not necessary to grant European judges the right to give their opinion on a matter that is consubstantial with our national identity and has absolutely nothing to do with the construction of [[European Union|Europe]].''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

His [[Socialist Party (France)|Socialist]] rival, [[Ségolène Royal]], on the contrary, declared herself ready to sign the Charter in a March 2007 speech &lt;ref&gt;[http://sego29.over-blog.org/article-5914843.html Charte des langues régionales : C'est OUI, sego29.over-blog.org]&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Northern Basque Country|Iparralde]] for the sake of cultural variety in France:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''Regional identities represent a tremendous asset for the future and I believe that understanding the link between the fundamental values that make the deep-rooted identity between France and the French nation in its diversity, in its authenticity, in its authentic traditions [...] makes the State work well.''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
*[[Minority language]]
*[[Regional language]]
*[[Separatism]]
*[[Language policy of France]]

===French language policy===
*[[Language policy in France]]
*[[Languages of France]]
*[[Jules Ferry]]

===Similar policies in other countries===
*[[Welsh Not]], English suppression of the [[Welsh language]].
*[[Dialect card]], suppression of [[Ryukyuan languages]] and dialects of the [[Tōhoku region]] in Japan.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.languefrancaise.net/dossiers/dossiers.php?id_dossier=66 Abbé Grégoire's ''Report on the necessity and means to annihilate the patois and to universalise the use of the French language'']
*[http://www.chez.com/buan1/poignant.htm Bernard Poignant's report]
*[http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/english/8ab.asp#TITLE%20I French Constitution]
*[http://conventions.coe.int/treaty/en/Treaties/Html/148.htm European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages]
*[http://www.yeni.org/default.php?s=members&amp;p=members/membersitem.php&amp;id=204&amp;m=&amp;l=english Youth of European Nationalities website]
*[http://www.aprene.org/spip.php?page=sommaire Aprene, Establiment d'Ensenhament Superior Occitan]

[[Category:Linguistic rights]]
[[Category:Occitan language]]
[[Category:Linguistic discrimination]]
[[Category:History of France]]

[[ca:Vergonha]]
[[es:Vergonha]]
[[eu:Vergonha]]
[[hr:Vergonha]]
[[oc:Vergonha (lingüicidi)]]
[[ru:Бергонья]]</text>
      <sha1>oc347xrc2yr3efxdqo2v5172s9vwp4c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
