<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Yiddish language</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34272</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520609812</id>
      <parentid>520585345</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T16:34:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Futhark</username>
        <id>172672</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv to title spelled exactly as it appears on the publication itself</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="65434">{{Distinguish|Hebrew language}}
{{Infobox language
|name=Yiddish
|nativename={{lang|yi|ייִדיש}} ''yidish''
|pronunciation={{IPA-yi|ˈjɪdɪʃ|}}
|states=[[Russia]], [[United States]], [[Israel]], [[Argentina]], [[Brazil]], [[United Kingdom]], [[Canada]], [[Ukraine]], [[Belarus]], [[Hungary]], [[Mexico]], [[Moldova]], [[Latvia]], [[Lithuania]], [[Belgium]], [[Germany]], [[Poland]],  [[Australia]], [[France]],  [[Sweden]], [[Austria]], and elsewhere
|speakers=1.8 million
|date=no date
|ref=&lt;ref name=Ethnologue&gt;[http://www.ethnologue.com/show_language.asp?code=ydd Yiddish, Eastern], on [[Ethnologue]]. Retrieved 11 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
|speakers2=11 million [[second language|L2]] speakers
|familycolor=Indo-European
|fam2=[[Germanic languages|Germanic]]
|fam3=[[West Germanic languages|West Germanic]]
|fam4=[[High German languages|High German]]
|script=uses a [[Yiddish orthography|Hebrew-based alphabet]]
|nation= {{flag|Jewish Autonomous Oblast}}, [[Russia]]
|minority={{BIH}}&lt;br /&gt;{{NED}}&lt;br /&gt;{{POL}}&lt;br /&gt;{{ROM}}&lt;br /&gt;{{SWE}}&lt;br /&gt;{{UKR}}
|agency=no formal bodies;&lt;br /&gt;[[YIVO]] de facto
|iso1=yi|iso2=yid
|iso3=yid
|lc1=ydd|ld1=Eastern Yiddish
|lc2=yih|ld2=Western Yiddish
|lingua=52-ACB-g = 52-ACB-ga (West) + 52-ACB-gb (East); totalling 11 varieties
}}

'''Yiddish''' ({{lang|yi|[[wikt:ייִדיש|ייִדיש]]}} ''yidish'' or {{lang|yi|[[wikt:אידיש|אידיש]]}} ''idish'', literally &quot;[[Jews|Jewish]]&quot;) is a [[High German languages|High German language]] of [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazi Jewish]] origin, spoken in many parts of the world. It developed as a fusion of [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] and [[Aramaic]] into German dialects with the infusion of [[Slavic languages|Slavic]] and traces of [[Romance languages]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=eyBQn7JrBVwC&amp;pg=PA72 ''Introduction to Old Yiddish literature'', p. 72], Baumgarten and Frakes, Oxford University Press, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishgen.org/databases/givennames/yiddial.htm &quot;Development of Yiddish over the ages&quot;], www.jewishgen.org&lt;/ref&gt; It is [[Yiddish orthography|written]] in the [[Hebrew alphabet]].

The language originated in the Ashkenazi culture that developed from about the 10th century in the [[Rhineland]] and then spread to [[Central Europe|Central]] and [[Eastern Europe]] and eventually to other continents. In the earliest surviving references to it, the language is called {{lang|yi|לשון־אַשכּנז}} (''loshn-ashknez'' = &quot;language of Ashkenaz&quot;) and {{lang|yi|טײַטש}} (''taytsh'', a variant of ''tiutsch'', the contemporary name for the language otherwise spoken in the region of origin, now called [[Middle High German]]). In common usage, the language is called {{lang|yi|מאַמע־לשון}} (''mame-loshn'', literally &quot;mother tongue&quot;), distinguishing it from [[Biblical Hebrew]] and [[Aramaic language|Aramaic]], which are collectively termed {{lang|yi|לשון־קודש}} (''loshn-koydesh'', &quot;holy tongue&quot;). The term &quot;Yiddish&quot; did not become the most frequently used designation in the literature of the language until the 18th century.

For a significant portion of its history, Yiddish was the primary spoken language of the Ashkenazi Jews and once spanned a broad [[dialect continuum]] from [[Western Yiddish]] to three major groups within [[Eastern Yiddish]], namely [[Litvish]], Poylish and Ukrainish. Eastern and Western Yiddish are most markedly distinguished by the extensive inclusion of words of [[Slavic languages|Slavic]] origin in the Eastern [[dialects]]. While [[Western Yiddish]] has few remaining speakers, Eastern dialects remain in wide use.

Yiddish is written and spoken in many [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jewish]] communities around the world, although there are also a number of Orthodox Jews who do not know Yiddish. It is a home language in most [[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidic]] communities, where it is the first language learned in childhood, used in schools and in many social settings. Yiddish is also the academic language of the study of the Talmud according to the tradition of the Lithuanian [[yeshiva]]s.

Yiddish is also used in the adjectival sense to designate attributes of Ashkenazic Jewish culture (for example, [[Jewish cooking#Jewish cuisine variations|Yiddish cooking]] and [[Klezmer|Yiddish music]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[Oscar Levant]] described  [[Cole Porter]]'s '[[My Heart Belongs to Daddy]]&quot; as &quot;one of the most [[Yiddish]] tunes ever written&quot; despite the fact that &quot;Cole Porter's genetic background was completely alien to any Jewishness.&quot; Oscar Levant,''[[The Unimportance of Being Oscar]]'', Pocket Books 1969 (reprint of G.P. Putnam 1968), p. 32. ISBN 0-671-77104-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In the 10th century, a distinctive Jewish culture formed in [[Central Europe]]. The culture came to be called ''Ashkenazi'', deriving its name from ''[[Ashkenaz]]'' ({{bibleverse||Genesis|10:3|HE}}), the medieval [[Hebrew name]] for the territory centred on what is now the westernmost part of [[Germany]]. Its geographic extent did not coincide with the German [[Christian]] principalities; Ashkenaz included [[Northern France]]. It also bordered on the area inhabited by the [[Sephardim]], or [[Spain|Spanish]] Jews, which ranged into [[Southern France]]. Ashkenazi culture later spread into [[Eastern Europe]].

The first language of [[European Jew]]s may have been [[Aramaic]],&lt;ref&gt;Katz, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; the vernacular of the Jews in [[Iudaea province|Roman-era Judea]] and ancient and early medieval [[Mesopotamia]]. The widespread use of Aramaic among the large non-Jewish [[Syria]]n trading population of the Roman provinces, including those in Europe, would have reinforced the use of Aramaic among Jews engaged in trade. In Roman times, many of the Jews living in [[Rome]] and [[Southern Italy]] appear to have been [[Greek language|Greek]]-speakers, and this is reflected in some Ashkenazi personal names (e.g., ''Kalonymus''). Much work needs to be done, though, to fully analyze the contributions of those languages to Yiddish.

Nothing is known about the [[vernacular]] of the earliest Jews in Germany, but several theories have been put forward. It is generally accepted that it was likely to have contained elements from other languages of the [[Near East]] and Europe, absorbed through dispersion. Since many settlers came via France and Italy, it is also likely that the Romance-based Jewish languages of those regions were represented. Traces remain in the contemporary Yiddish vocabulary: for example, {{lang|yi|בענטשן}} (''bentshn'', to bless), from the Latin ''{{lang|la|benedicere}}''; {{lang|yi|לייענען}} (''leyenen'', to read), from the Latin ''{{lang|la|legere}}''; and the personal names Anshl, cognate to Angel or Angelo; Bunim (probably from &quot;bon homme&quot;). Western Yiddish includes additional words of Latin derivation (but still very few): for example, ''orn'' (to pray), cf. Latin and Italian &quot;orare&quot;.

The Jewish community in the Rhineland would have encountered the myriad dialects from which standard [[German language|German]] would in time emerge many centuries later. They would have been speaking their own versions of these German dialects, mixed with linguistic elements that they themselves brought into the region. Perhaps the main point of difference was the use of the Hebrew alphabet for the recording of the Germanic vernacular, which may have been adopted either because of the community's familiarity with the alphabet or to prevent the non-Jewish population understanding the correspondence. In addition, there was probably widespread illiteracy in the non-Hebrew script, and the level of illiteracy in the non-Jewish communities was much higher.  Another point of difference was the use of Hebrew and Aramaic words. These words and terms were used because of their familiarity, but more so because in most cases there  were no equivalent terms in the vernacular which could express the Jewish concepts or describe the objects of cultural significance.

Apart from the obvious use of Hebrew words for specifically Jewish artifacts, it is very difficult to determine the extent to which the Yiddish spoken in any earlier period differed from the contemporary German. There is a rough consensus that by the 15th century Yiddish would have sounded distinctive to the average German ear, even when restricted to the Germanic component of its vocabulary.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

===Written evidence===
[[File:Machzor.jpg|thumb|The calligraphic segment in the Worms Mahzor.]]
It is not known when Yiddish came to be written down, but the oldest surviving literary document in Yiddish is a blessing in the Worms ''mahzor'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yivoencyclopedia.org/popups/viewmedia.aspx?id=1116 |title=Image |publisher=Yivoencyclopedia.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; a Hebrew prayer book from 1272 (with a scalable image online at the indicated reference; described extensively in [[#frakes2004|Frakes, 2004]] and [[#baumgarten2005|Baumgarten/Frakes, 2005]]):

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| &lt;small&gt;Yiddish&lt;/small&gt;
| {{lang|yi|גוּט טַק אִים בְּטַגְֿא שְ וַיר דִּיש מַחֲזֹור אִין בֵּיתֿ הַכְּנֶסֶתֿ טְרַגְֿא}}
|-
| &lt;small&gt;Transliterated&lt;/small&gt;
| ''gut tak im betage se vaer dis makhazor in beis hakneses trage''
|-
| &lt;small&gt;Translated&lt;/small&gt;
| May a good day come to him who carries this prayer book into the synagogue.
|}

This brief rhyme is decoratively embedded in a purely Hebrew text.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.milon.co.il/general/general.php?term=%D7%91%D7%93%D7%A2%D7%AA%D7%95 |title=בדעתו |publisher=Milon.co.il |date=2007-05-14 |accessdate=2010-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, it indicates that the Yiddish of that day was a more or less regular Middle High German written in the Hebrew alphabet into which Hebrew words&amp;nbsp;– {{lang|yi| מַחֲזֹור}}, [[Mahzor|''makhazor'']] (prayer book for the [[High Holidays|High Holy Days]]) and {{lang|yi| בֵּיתֿ הַכְּנֶסֶתֿ}}, ''beis hakneses'' ([[synagogue]])&amp;nbsp;– had been included. The [[Niqqud|pointing]] appears as though it might have been added by a second scribe, in which case it may need to be dated separately and may not be indicative of the pronunciation of the rhyme at the time of its initial annotation.

Over the course of the 14th and 15th centuries, songs and poems in Yiddish, and also [[macaronic]] pieces in Hebrew and German, began to appear. These were collected in the late 15th century by Menahem ben Naphtali Oldendorf.&lt;ref&gt;''Old Yiddish Literature from Its Origins to the Haskalah Period by Zinberg, Israel. KTAV, 1975. ISBN 0-87068-465-5.&lt;/ref&gt; During the same period, a tradition seems to have emerged of the Jewish community's adapting its own versions of German secular literature. The earliest Yiddish epic poem of this sort is the ''[[Dukus Horant]]'', which survives in the famous Cambridge Codex T.-S.10.K.22. This 14th-century manuscript was discovered in the [[Cairo Geniza|geniza of a Cairo synagogue]] in 1896, and also contains a collection of narrative poems on themes from the [[Hebrew Bible]] and the [[Haggadah]].

===Printing===
The advent of the [[printing press]] resulted in an increase in the amount of material produced and surviving from the 16th century and onwards. One particularly popular work was [[Elia Levita|Elia Levita's]] ''[[Bovo-Bukh]]'', composed around 1507–08 and printed in at least forty editions, beginning in 1541. Levita, the earliest named Yiddish author, may also have written ''Pariz un Viene'' ([[Paris]] and [[Vienna]]). Another Yiddish retelling of a chivalric romance, ''Vidvilt'' (often referred to as &quot;Widuwilt&quot; by Germanizing scholars), presumably also dates from the 15th century, although the manuscripts are from the 16th. It is also known as ''Kinig Artus Hof'', an adaptation of the Middle High German romance ''Wigalois'' by Wirnt von Gravenberg. Another significant writer is Avroham ben Schemuel Pikartei, who published a paraphrase on the [[Book of Job]] in 1557.

Women in the Ashkenazi community were traditionally not literate in Hebrew, but did read and write Yiddish. A body of literature therefore developed for which women were a primary audience. This included secular works, such as the ''Bovo-Bukh'', and religious writing specifically for women, such as the ''[[Tseno Ureno]]'' and the ''[[Tkhine]]s''. One of the best-known early woman authors was [[Glückel of Hameln]], whose memoirs are still in print.
[[File:Page from Yiddish-Hebrew-Latin-German dictionary by Elijah Levita.jpg|thumb|A page from the [http://cf.uba.uva.nl/nl/publicaties/treasures/page/p08.html ''Shemot Devarim''] (literally ''Names of Things''), a Yiddish-Hebrew-Latin-German dictionary and thesaurus, published by Elia Levita in 1542]]

The segmentation of the Yiddish readership, between women who read ''mame-loshn'' but not ''loshn-koydesh'', and men who read both, was significant enough that distinctive [[typeface]]s were used for each. The name commonly given to the semicursive form used exclusively for Yiddish was {{lang|yi|ווײַבערטײַטש}} (''vaybertaytsh'' = &quot;women's ''taytsh'',&quot; shown in the heading and fourth column in the adjacent illustration), with square Hebrew letters (shown in the third column) being reserved for text in that language and Aramaic. This distinction was retained in general typographic practice through to the early 19th century, with Yiddish books being set in ''vaybertaytsh'' (also termed {{lang|yi|מעשייט}} ''mesheyt'' or {{lang|yi|מאַשקעט}} ''mashket'' — the construction is uncertain).&lt;ref&gt;Max Weinreich, געשיכטע פֿון דער ייִדישער שפּראַך (New York: YIVO, 1973), vol. 1, p. 280, with explanation of symbol on p. xiv.&lt;/ref&gt;

An additional distinctive semicursive typeface was, and still is, used for rabbinical commentary on religious texts when Hebrew and Yiddish appear on the same page. This is commonly termed [[Rashi script]], from the name of the most renowned early author, whose commentary is usually printed using this script. (Rashi is also the typeface normally used when the Sefardi counterpart to Yiddish, [[Judaeo-Spanish|Ladino]], is printed in Hebrew script.)

==Secularization==
The Western Yiddish dialect—sometimes pejoratively labeled ''Mauscheldeutsch''&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last       = Bechtel
| first      = Delphine
| editor1-last  = Malkin
| editor1-first = Jeanette R.
| editor2-last  = Rokem
| editor2-first = Freddie
| title         = Jews and the making of modern German theatre
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=geJnnySQ4rUC
| accessdate    = 2011-10-28
| series    = Studies in theatre history and culture
| year      =  2010
| contribution = Yiddish Theatre and Its Impact on the German and Austrian Stage
| publisher = University of Iowa Press
| isbn      = 978-1-58729-868-4
| page     = 304
| quote         = [...] audiences heard on the stage a continuum of hybrid language-levels between Yiddish and German that was sometimes combined with the traditional use of Mauscheldeutsch (surviving forms of Western Yiddish).
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
(from ''Moischele-Deutsch'' or &quot;Moses German&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| first1 = Celia
| last1 = Applegate
| author1-link  = Celia Applegate
| first2 =  Pamela Maxine
| last2 = Potter
| title         = Music and German national identity
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=roHbXnBqE1wC
| accessdate    = 2011-10-28
| year      = 2001
| publisher = University of Chicago Press
| isbn      = 978-0-226-02131-7
| page     = 310
| quote         = [...] in 1787, over 10 percent of the Prague population was Jewish [...] which spoke German and, probably, ''Mauscheldeutsch'', a local Jewish-German dialect distinct from Yiddish (''Mauscheldeutsch'' = '''Moischele-Deutsch''' = 'Moses German').
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; - began to decline in the 18th century, as [[the Enlightenment]] and the ''[[Haskalah]]'' led to the view of Yiddish as a corrupt dialect. Owing to both assimilation to German and the incipient creation of [[Modern Hebrew]], Western Yiddish survived only as a language of &quot;intimate family circles or of closely knit trade groups&quot; ([[#liptzin1972|Liptzin 1972]]). Farther east, the response to this force took the opposite direction, with Yiddish becoming the cohesive force in a [[secular]] culture (see [[Yiddish Renaissance]]).

The late 19th and early 20th century are widely considered{{by whom|date=October 2011}} the Golden Age of secular Yiddish literature. This coincides with the development of Modern Hebrew as a spoken and literary language, from which some words were also absorbed into Yiddish. The three authors generally regarded{{by whom|date=October 2011}} as the founders of the modern Yiddish literary genre were born in the 19th century, but their work and significance continued to grow into the 20th. The first was Sholem Yankev Abramovitch, writing as [[Mendele Mocher Sforim]]. The second was Sholem Rabinovitsh, widely known as [[Sholem Aleichem]], whose stories about {{lang|yi|טבֿיה דער מילכיקער}} (''tevye der milkhiker'' = [[Tevye|Tevye the Dairyman]]) inspired the Broadway musical and film ''[[Fiddler on the Roof]]''. The third was [[I.L. Peretz|Isaac Leib Peretz]].

==20th century==
[[File:Yiddish WWI poster2.jpg|right|thumb|[[United States|American]] [[World War I]]-era poster in Yiddish. Translated caption: &quot;Food will win the war – You came here seeking freedom, now you must help to preserve it – We must supply the [[Allies of World War I|Allies]] with wheat – Let nothing go to waste&quot;. Colour lithograph, 1917. Digitally restored.]]
In the early 20th century, especially after Socialist [[October Revolution]] in Russia, Yiddish was emerging as a major Eastern European language. Its rich literature was more widely published than ever, [[Yiddish theatre]] and [[National Center for Jewish Film|Yiddish film]] were booming, and it for a time achieved status as one of the official languages of the [[Ukrainian People's Republic]], the [[Belarusian Soviet Socialist Republic|Belarusian]] and the short-lived [[Galician Soviet Socialist Republic|Galician SSR]], and the [[Jewish Autonomous Oblast]]. Educational autonomy for Jews in several countries (notably [[Poland]]) after [[World War I]] led to an increase in formal Yiddish-language education, more uniform orthography, and to the 1925 founding of the Yiddish Scientific Institute, [[YIVO]]. Yiddish emerged as the national language of a large Jewish community in Eastern Europe that rejected [[Zionism]] and sought Jewish cultural autonomy in Europe. It also contended with Modern Hebrew as a literary language among Zionists. In [[Vilna]] there was intense debate over which language should take primacy, [[Hebrew]] or Yiddish&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/exhibitions/vilna/before/hebrew_or_yiddish.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki Hebrew or Yiddish?] in the online exhibition [http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/exhibitions/vilna/index.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki The Jerusalem of Lithuania: The Story of the Jewish Community of Vilna] by [[Yad Vashem]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Yiddish changed significantly during the 20th century. [[Michael Wex]] writes, &quot;As increasing numbers of Yiddish speakers moved from the Slavic-speaking East to Western Europe and the Americas in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, they were so quick to jettison Slavic vocabulary that the most prominent Yiddish writers of the time—the founders of modern Yiddish literature, who were still living in Slavic-speaking countries—revised the printed editions of their oeuvres to eliminate obsolete and 'unnecessary' Slavisms.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[Born to Kvetch]]: Yiddish Language and Culture in All Its Moods |last=Wex |first=Michael|authorlink=Michael Wex |year=2005 |publisher=St. Martin's Press |page=29 |isbn=0-312-30741-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The vocabulary used in Israel absorbed many Modern Hebrew words, and there was a similar increase in the English component of Yiddish in the [[United States]] and, to a lesser extent, the [[United Kingdom]]. This has resulted in some difficulty in communication between Yiddish speakers from [[Israel]] and those from other countries.

===Numbers of speakers===
On the eve of [[World War II]], there were 11 to 13 million Yiddish speakers ([[#jacobs2005|Jacobs 2005]]). [[The Holocaust]], however, led to a dramatic, sudden decline in the use of Yiddish, as the extensive Jewish communities, both secular and religious, that used Yiddish in their day-to-day life were largely destroyed. Around five million people—85 percent of the Jews who died in the Holocaust—were speakers of Yiddish.&lt;ref&gt;[[Solomon Birnbaum|Solomo Birnbaum]], ''Grammatik der jiddischen Sprache'' (4., erg. Aufl., Hamburg: Buske, 1984), p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Although millions of Yiddish speakers survived the war (including nearly all Yiddish speakers in the Americas), further assimilation in countries such as the [[United States]] and the [[Soviet Union]], along with the strictly monolingual stance of the [[Zionist]] movement, led to a decline in the use of Eastern Yiddish. However, the number of speakers within the widely dispersed Orthodox (mainly Hasidic) communities is now increasing. Although used in various countries, Yiddish has attained official recognition as a minority language only in [[Moldova]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], the [[Netherlands]]  {{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} and [[Sweden]].

Reports of the number of current Yiddish speakers vary significantly. [[Ethnologue]] estimated in 2009 there were 1,762,320 speakers of Eastern Yiddish,&lt;ref name=Ethnologue/&gt; of which over one-third lived in the United States. In contrast, the [[Modern Language Association]] reports fewer than 200,000 in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mla.org/cgi-shl/docstudio/docs.pl?map_data_results Most spoken languages in the United States], Modern Language Association. Retrieved 17 October2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Western Yiddish, which had &quot;several tens of thousands of speakers&quot; on the eve of the Holocaust, is reported by Ethnologue to have had an &quot;ethnic population&quot; of slightly below 50,000 in 2000.&lt;ref name=Ethnologue-western&gt;[http://www.ethnologue.com/show_language.asp?code=yih Yiddish, Western], on Ethnologue. Retrieved 17 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Other estimates are also given, for example, of a worldwide Yiddish-speaking population of about two million in 1996 in a report by the [[Council of Europe]].&lt;ref&gt;Emanuelis Zingeris, [http://assembly.coe.int/Documents/WorkingDocs/doc96/EDOC7489.htm Yiddish culture], Council of Europe Committee on Culture and Education Doc. 7489, 12 February 1996. Retrieved 17 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Further [[demographics|demographic]] information about the recent status of what is treated as an Eastern-Western dialect continuum is provided in the YIVO ''Language and Cultural Atlas of Ashkenazic Jewry'' (Language and Cultural Atlas of Ashkenazic Jewry).

===Status as a language===
There has been frequent debate about the extent of the linguistic independence of Yiddish from the languages that it absorbed. There has been periodic assertion that Yiddish is a dialect of German, or even &quot;just broken German, more of a linguistic mishmash than a true language&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1996/10/29/science/scholars-debate-roots-of-yiddish-migration-of-jews.html?pagewanted=2 &quot;Scholars Debate Roots of Yiddish, Migration of Jews&quot;], George Johnson, ''New York Times'', October 29, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; Even when recognized as an autonomous language, it has sometimes been referred to as Judeo-German, along the lines of other Jewish languages like [[Judeo-Persian]] or [[Judeo-French]]. A widely cited summary of attitudes in the 1930s was published by [[Max Weinreich]], quoting a remark by an auditor of one of his lectures: {{lang|yi|אַ שפּראַך איז אַ דיאַלעקט מיט אַן אַרמיי און פֿלאָט}} ('' a shprakh iz a dialekt mit an armey un flot''—&quot;A language is a dialect with an army and navy&quot;, [http://www.bisso.com/ujg_archives/pix/armyNavyFull.jpg facsimile excerpt]  discussed in detail in a [[Language is a dialect with an army and navy|separate article]]). More recently, Prof. Paul Wexler, of Tel Aviv University in [[Israel]], has proposed that Eastern Yiddish should be classified as a Slavic language, formed by the [[relexification]] of Judeo-Slavic dialects by Judeo-German.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wexler&quot;&gt;{{en icon}} {{cite book |author=Paul Wexler |coauthors= |title=Two-tiered relexification in Yiddish: The Jews, Sorbs, Khazars and the Kiev-Polessian dialects |year=2002 |editor= |pages= |chapter= |chapterurl= |publisher=Mouton de Gruyter | location =Berlin |isbn=3-11-017258-5 |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Israel===
The national languages of Israel are Hebrew and Arabic. The rejection of Yiddish as an alternative reflected the conflict between religious and secular forces. Many in the larger, secular group wanted a new national language to foster a cohesive identity, while traditionally religious Jews desired that Hebrew be respected as a holy language reserved for prayer and religious study. In the early twentieth century, Zionist immigrants in [[Palestine]] tried to eradicate the use of Yiddish among their own population, and make its use socially unacceptable.

This conflict also reflected the opposing views among secular Jews worldwide, one side seeing Hebrew (and Zionism) and the other Yiddish (and [[internationalism (politics)|Internationalism]]) as the means of defining emerging Jewish nationalism. In the 1920s and 1930s, ''gdud meginéy hasafá'', &quot;the language defendants regiment&quot;, whose motto was ''ivrí, dabér ivrít'' &quot;Hebrew [i.e. Jew], speak Hebrew!&quot;, used to tear down signs written in &quot;foreign&quot; languages and disturb Yiddish theatre gatherings.&lt;ref&gt;Zuckermann, Ghil'ad (2009), [http://www.zuckermann.org/pdf/Hybridity_versus_Revivability.pdf Hybridity versus Revivability: Multiple Causation, Forms and Patterns]. In ''Journal of Language Contact'', Varia 2: 40-67, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to linguist [[Ghil'ad Zuckermann]], the members of this group in particular, and the Hebrew revival in general, did not succeed in uprooting Yiddish patterns (as well as the patterns of other European languages Jewish immigrants spoke) within what he calls &quot;Israeli&quot;, i.e. [[Modern Hebrew]]. Zuckermann believes that &quot;Israeli does include numerous Hebrew elements resulting from a conscious revival but also numerous pervasive linguistic features deriving from a subconscious survival of the revivalists’ mother tongues, e.g. Yiddish.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Zuckermann, Ghil'ad (2009), [http://www.zuckermann.org/pdf/Hybridity_versus_Revivability.pdf Hybridity versus Revivability: Multiple Causation, Forms and Patterns]. In ''Journal of Language Contact'', Varia 2: 40-67, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

In religious circles, it is the Ashkenazi [[Haredi Judaism|Haredi Jews]], particularly the Hasidic Jews and the Lithuanian [[yeshiva]] world (see [[Lithuanian Jews]]), who continue to teach, speak and use Yiddish, making it a language used regularly by hundreds of thousands of Haredi Jews today. The largest of these centers are in [[Bnei Brak]] and [[Jerusalem]]. 

There is a growing revival of interest in Yiddish culture among secular Israelis, with the flourishing of new proactive cultural organizations like YUNG YiDiSH, as well as [[Yiddish theater]] (usually with simultaneous translation to Hebrew and Russian) and young people are taking university courses in Yiddish, some achieving considerable fluency.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.columbia.edu/cu/news/03/09/yiddish_studies.html Yiddish Studies Thrives at Columbia After More than Fifty Years] – Columbia News.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Former Soviet Union===
In the Soviet Union during the 1920s, Yiddish was promoted as the language of the Jewish [[proletariat]]. It was one of the official languages of the [[Byelorussian SSR]], as well as several agricultural districts of the [[Galician SSR]]. A public educational system entirely based on the Yiddish language was established and comprised kindergartens, schools, and higher educational institutions (technical schools, [[rabfak]]s and other university departments). At the same time, Hebrew was considered a [[bourgeois]] language and its use was generally discouraged. The vast majority of the Yiddish-language cultural institutions were closed in the late 1930s along with cultural institutions of other ethnic minorities lacking administrative entities of their own. After the Second World War, growing [[anti-Semitism|anti-Semitic]] tendencies in Soviet politics drove Yiddish from most spheres. The last Yiddish-language schools, theaters and publications were closed by the end of the 1940s. It continued to be spoken widely for decades, nonetheless, in areas with compact Jewish populations (primarily in Moldova, Ukraine, and to a lesser extent Belarus).

In the former Soviet states, presently active Yiddish authors include Yoysef Burg ([[Chernivtsi]] 1912-2009) and [[Olexander Beyderman|Aleksander Beyderman]] (b. 1949, [[Odessa]]). Publication of an earlier Yiddish periodical ({{lang|yi|דער פֿרײַנד}} - der fraynd; lit. &quot;The Friend&quot;), was resumed in 2004 with {{lang|yi|דער נײַער פֿרײַנד}} (''der nayer fraynd''; lit. &quot;The New Friend&quot;, [[St. Petersburg]]).

====Jewish Autonomous Oblast of Russia====
[[File:RussiaJewish2007-07.png|thumb|The [[Jews and Judaism in the Jewish Autonomous Oblast|Jewish Autonomous Oblast]] in the Russian Federation]]
[[File:Birobidzhan Vokzal.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Birobidzhan]]'s train terminal square]] &lt;!-- See the talk page before restoring the claim that Yiddish is an official language--&gt;

{{Main|Jewish Autonomous Oblast|Birobidzhan|Jews and Judaism in the Jewish Autonomous Oblast}}

The Jewish Autonomous Oblast was formed in 1934 in the [[Russian Far East]], with its capital city in Birobidzhan and Yiddish as its official language. The intention was for the Soviet Jewish population to settle there. Jewish cultural life was revived in Birobidzhan much earlier than elsewhere in the Soviet Union. Yiddish theaters began opening in the 1970s. The newspaper {{lang|yi|דער ביראָבידזשאנער שטערן}} ([[Birobidzhaner Shtern|''Der Birobidzhaner Shtern'']]; lit: &quot;The Birobidzhan Star&quot;) includes a Yiddish section.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gazetaeao.ru/idish |title=Birobidzhaner Shtern in Yiddish |publisher=Gazetaeao.ru |date= |accessdate=2010-08-07}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the official status of the language was not retained by the Russian Federation, its cultural significance is still recognized and bolstered. The First Birobidzhan International Summer Program for Yiddish Language and Culture was launched in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rettig |first=Haviv |url=http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1176152810577 |title=Yiddish returns to Birobidzhan &amp;#124; Jewish Features &amp;#124; Jerusalem Post |publisher=Jpost.com |date=2007-04-17 |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Council of Europe===
Several countries which ratified the 1992 [[European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages]] have included Yiddish in the list of their recognized minority languages: the Netherlands (1996), Sweden (2000),  Poland (2009), Romania (2008), Bosnia and Herzegovina (2010). In 2005, Ukraine did not mention Yiddish as such, but &quot;the language(s) of the Jewish ethnic minority&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://conventions.coe.int/Treaty/Commun/ListeDeclarations.asp?NT=148&amp;CM=8&amp;DF=23/01/05&amp;CL=ENG&amp;VL=1 European Charter for Regional or Minority Languages. List of declarations made with respect to treaty No. 148], Status as of: 3/10/2011&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sweden====
[[File:Jidische.Folkschtime.jpg|thumb|Banner from the first issue of the ''Jidische Folkschtime'' (Yiddish People's Voice), published in Stockholm, 12 January 1917.]]
In June 1999, the Swedish Parliament enacted legislation giving Yiddish legal status&lt;ref&gt;{{sv icon}} [http://regeringen.se/download/f5c9eed7.pdf?major=1&amp;minor=2218&amp;cn=attachmentPublDuplicator_0_attachment Regeringens proposition 1998/99:143 Nationella minoriteter i Sverige], 10 June 1999. Retrieved 17 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; as one of the country's [[minority languages of Sweden|official minority languages]] (entering into effect in April 2000). The rights thereby conferred are not detailed, but additional legislation was enacted in June 2006 establishing a new governmental agency, The Swedish National Language Council,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sprakradet.se sprakradet.se]&lt;/ref&gt; the mandate of which instructs it to, &quot;collect, preserve, scientifically research, and spread material about the national minority languages&quot;, naming them all explicitly, including Yiddish. When announcing this action, the government made an additional statement about &quot;simultaneously commencing completely new initiatives for ... Yiddish [and the other minority languages]&quot;.

The Swedish government publishes documents in Yiddish, of which the most recent details the national action plan for human rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{yi icon}} [http://regeringen.se/download/098c9eb4.pdf?major=1&amp;minor=67638&amp;cn=attachmentPublDuplicator_0_attachment אַ נאַציאָנאַלער האַנדלונגס־פּלאַן פאַר די מענטשלעכע רעכט] A National Action Plan for Human Rights 2006–2009. Retrieved 4 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; An earlier one provides general information about national minority language policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{yi icon}} [http://www.manskligarattigheter.gov.se/dynamaster/file_archive/050216/24a99c86fd734f15c9f722b343cc152e/FaktaJu%5f0415ji.pdf נאַציאַנאַלע מינאָריטעטן און מינאָריטעט־שפּראַכן] National Minorities and Minority Languages. Retrieved 4 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 September 2007, it became possible to register Internet domains with Yiddish names in the national top-level domain [[.se|.SE]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.idg.se/2.1085/1.119665 |title=IDG: Jiddischdomänen är här |publisher=Idg.se |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
[[File:Yiddish language distribution in the United States.svg|thumb|300px|Yiddish distribution in the United States. {{legend|blue|More than 100,000 speakers}} {{legend|cyan|More than 10,000 speakers}}
{{legend|red|More than 5,000 speakers}}
{{legend|yellow|More than 1,000 speakers}}
{{legend|#cccccc|Fewer than 1,000 speakers}}]]
[[File:Women voter outreach 1935 English Yiddish.jpg|thumb|Women surrounded by posters in English and Yiddish supporting [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], [[Herbert H. Lehman]], and the [[American Labor Party]] teach other women how to vote, 1936.]]
At first, in the [[United States]] most Jews were of [[Sephardi Jews|Sephardic]] origin, and hence did not speak Yiddish. It was not until the mid to late 19th century, as first German, then Eastern European, Jews arrived in the nation, that Yiddish became dominant within the immigrant community.  This helped to bond Jews from many countries. {{lang|yi|פֿאָרווערטס}} (''forverts'' – [[The Forward|Yiddish Forward]]) was one of seven Yiddish daily newspapers in [[New York City]], and other Yiddish newspapers served as a forum for Jews of all European backgrounds. The ''Yiddish Forward'' still appears weekly and is available in an online edition.&lt;ref&gt;{{yi icon}} [http://yiddish.forward.com/ פֿאָרווערטס]: ''[[The Forward]]'' online.&lt;/ref&gt; It remains in wide distribution, together with {{lang|yi|דער אַלגעמיינער זשורנאַל}} (''der algemeyner zhurnal'' – [[Algemeiner Journal]]; ''algemeyner'' = general) a [[Lubavitcher]] newspaper which is also published weekly and appears online.&lt;ref&gt;{{yi icon}} [http://www.algemeiner.com/generic.asp?cat=4 דער אַלגעמיינער זשורנאַל]: ''Algemeiner Journal'' online&lt;/ref&gt; The widest-circulation Yiddish newspapers are probably the weekly issues {{lang|yi|[[Der Yid]]}} (דער איד = The Jew) and {{lang|yi|[[Der Blatt]]}} (דער בלאַט; ''blat'' = paper) and {{lang|yi|[[Di Tzeitung]]}} (די צייטונג; = the newspaper) . Several additional newspapers and magazines are in regular production, such as the monthly publications {{lang|yi|דער שטערן}} (Der Shtern; ''shtern'' = star) and {{lang|yi|דער בליק}} (Der Blick; ''blik'' = view). (The romanized titles cited in this paragraph are in the form given on the masthead of each publication and may be at some variance both with the literal Yiddish title and the [[Yiddish orthography#Transliteration|transliteration rules]] otherwise applied in this article.) Thriving Yiddish theater, especially in New York City, kept the language vital. Interest in [[klezmer]] music provided another bonding mechanism.

Most of the Jewish immigrants to the New York metropolitan area during the years of [[Ellis Island]] considered Yiddish their native language; however, native Yiddish speakers tended not to pass the language on to their children, who assimilated and spoke English. For example, [[Isaac Asimov]] states in his autobiography, ''[[In Memory Yet Green]],'' that Yiddish was his first and sole spoken language and remained so for about two years after he emigrated to the United States as a small child. By contrast, Asimov's younger siblings, born in the United States, never developed any degree of fluency in Yiddish.

Many &quot;Yiddishisms,&quot; like &quot;Italianisms&quot; and &quot;Spanishisms,&quot; entered the spoken [[New York dialect]], often used by Jews and non-Jews alike, unaware of the linguistic origin of the phrases. [[Yiddish words used in English]] were documented extensively by [[Leo Rosten]] in ''[[The Joys of Yiddish]]''; see also the [[list of English words of Yiddish origin]].

In 1976, the Canadian-born American author [[Saul Bellow]] received the [[Nobel Prize in literature]]. He was fluent in Yiddish, and translated several Yiddish poems and stories into English, including Isaac Bashevis Singer's &quot;Gimpel the Fool&quot;.

In 1978, the [[Poland|Polish]]-born Yiddish author [[Isaac Bashevis Singer]], a resident of the United States, received the [[Nobel Prize in literature]].

Legal scholars [[Eugene Volokh]] and [[Alex Kozinski]] argue that Yiddish is “supplanting Latin as the spice in American legal argot.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Volokh |first=Eugene |authorlink= |coauthors=Kozinski, Alex |year=1993 |month= |title=Lawsuit, Shmawsuit |journal=Yale Law Journal |volume=103 |issue=2 |pages=463–467 |doi=10.2307/797101|accessdate= |quote= |publisher=The Yale Law Journal Company, Inc. |postscript=. |jstor=797101 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Note: an updated version of the article appears on Professor Volokh's UCLA web page.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.ucla.edu/volokh/yiddish.htm |title=Judge Alex Kozinski &amp; Eugene Volokh, &quot;Lawsuit, Shmawsuit&quot; &lt;*&gt; |publisher=Law.ucla.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Present U.S. speaker population====
In the [[United States Census, 2000|2000 census]], 178,945 people in the United States reported speaking Yiddish at home. Of these speakers, 113,515 lived in [[New York]] (63.43% of American Yiddish speakers); 18,220 in [[Florida]] (10.18%); 9,145 in [[New Jersey]] (5.11%); and 8,950 in [[California]] (5.00%). The remaining states with speaker populations larger than 1,000 are [[Pennsylvania]] (5,445), [[Ohio]] (1,925), [[Michigan]] (1,945), [[Massachusetts]] (2,380), [[Maryland]] (2,125), [[Illinois]] (3,510), [[Connecticut]] (1,710), and [[Arizona]] (1,055). The population is largely elderly: 72,885 of the speakers were older than 65, 66,815 were between 18 and 64, and only 39,245 were age 17 or lower.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mla.org/map_data_states&amp;lang_id=609&amp;mode=lang_tops&amp;a=&amp;ea=&amp;order=r Language by State: Yiddish], [[Modern Language Association|MLA]] Language Map Data Center, based on U.S. Census data. Retrieved 25 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
In the six years since the [[United States Census, 2000|2000 census]], the 2006 [[American Community Survey]] reflected an estimated 15 percent decline of people speaking Yiddish at home in the U.S. to 152,515.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/DTTable?_bm=y&amp;-ds_name=ACS_2006_EST_G00_&amp;-_geoSkip=0&amp;-CONTEXT=dt&amp;-mt_name=ACS_2006_EST_G2000_C16001&amp;-redoLog=false&amp;-_skip=0&amp;-geo_id=01000US&amp;-_showChild=Y&amp;-format=&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-_toggle=ACS_2006_EST_G2000_C16001 |title=Detailed Tables – American FactFinder |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are a few predominantly [[Hasidic]] communities in the United States in which Yiddish remains the majority language. [[Kiryas Joel, New York]] is one such; in the 2000 census, nearly 90% of residents of Kiryas Joel reported speaking Yiddish at home.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mla.org/census_data_results&amp;state_id=36&amp;place_id=39853 Data center results] [[Modern Language Association]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
There are well over 30,000 Yiddish speakers in the United Kingdom, and several thousand children now have Yiddish as a first language. The largest group of Yiddish speakers in Britain reside in the [[Stamford Hill]] district of North London, but there are sizeable communities in [[Golders Green]], [[Stoke Newington]], [[Greater Manchester]] (in parts of [[Salford, Greater Manchester|Salford]]; mainly in the [[Broughton, Greater Manchester|Broughton]] and [[Kersal]] areas, North Manchester and in the north Manchester suburb of [[Prestwich]]) and [[Gateshead]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/faith/article1038349.ece Times on Yiddish in the UK]{{accessdate|2011-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Yiddish readership in the UK is mainly reliant upon imported material from the [[United States]] and [[Israel]] for newspapers, magazines and other periodicals. However, the London-based weekly ''[[The Jewish Tribune (UK)|Jewish Tribune]]'', has a small section in Yiddish called {{lang|yi|אידישע טריבונע}} ''Idishe Tribune''.

===Religious communities===
[[File:Brooklyn Posters 1.jpg|thumb|A typical poster-hung wall in Jewish [[Brooklyn]], New York]]

The major exception to the decline of spoken Yiddish can be found in [[Haredi Judaism|Haredi]] communities all over the world. In some of the more closely knit such communities Yiddish is spoken as a home and schooling language, especially in Hasidic, [[Litvish]] or [[Yeshivish]] communities such as [[Brooklyn]]'s [[Borough Park]], [[Williamsburg, Brooklyn|Williamsburg]] and [[Crown Heights, Brooklyn|Crown Heights]], and in the communities of [[Monsey, New York|Monsey]], [[Kiryas Joel, New York|Kiryas Joel]] and [[New Square, New York|New Square]] in [[New York State]] (over 88% of the population of Kiryas Joel is reported to speak Yiddish at home.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mla.org/census_data_results&amp;state_id=36&amp;place_id=39853 MLA Data Center Results: Kiryas Joel, New York], Modern Language Association. Retrieved 17 October 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;) Also in [[New Jersey]]  Yiddish is widely spoken mostly in [[Lakewood, NJ|Lakewood]] but also in smaller towns with [[yeshivos]] such as [[Passaic, NJ|Passaic]], [[Teaneck, NJ|Teaneck]] and elsewhere. Yiddish is also widely spoken in the [[Jewish Community of Antwerp|Antwerp Jewish community]] and in Haredi communities such as the ones in [[London]], [[Manchester]] and [[Montreal]]. Yiddish is also spoken in many communities throughout [[Israel]]. Among most Ashkenazi Haredim, Hebrew is generally reserved for prayer, while Yiddish is used for religious studies as well as a home and business language. In Israel, however, Haredim commonly speak Hebrew, with the notable exception of many Hasidic communities. However, some Haredim who use Modern Hebrew also understand Yiddish. There are some who send their children to schools in which the primary language of instruction is Yiddish. Members of movements such as [[Satmar (Hasidic dynasty)|Satmar]] Hasidism, who view the commonplace use of Hebrew as a form of Zionism, use Yiddish almost exclusively.

Hundreds of thousands of young children around the globe have been, and are still, taught to translate the texts of the [[Torah]] into Yiddish. This process is called {{lang|yi|טײַטשן}} (''taytshn'')—&quot;translating&quot; . Most Ashkenazi [[yeshiva]]s' highest level lectures in Talmud and [[Halakha]] are delivered in Yiddish by the [[rosh yeshiva]]s as well as ethical talks of [[mussar movement|mussar]]. Hasidic [[rebbe]]s generally use only Yiddish to converse with their followers and to deliver their various Torah talks, classes, and lectures. The linguistic style and vocabulary of Yiddish have influenced the manner in which many [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jews]] who attend yeshivas speak English. This usage is distinctive enough that it has been dubbed &quot;[[Yeshivish (dialect)|Yeshivish]]&quot;.

While Hebrew remains the language of [[Jewish prayer]], the Hasidim have mixed some Yiddish into their Hebrew, and are also responsible for a significant secondary religious literature written in Yiddish. For example, the tales about the [[Baal Shem Tov]] were written largely in Yiddish. As well as the Torah Talks of the late [[Lubavitch]] leaders are published in their original form, Yiddish. In addition, some prayers, such as the [[God of Abraham|Got fun Avrohom]], were composed and are recited in Yiddish.

Moreover, some Hasidic girls in the [[Diaspora]] are not taught Hebrew at all, and therefore do not understand either ancient or modern Hebrew. Even those who are taught parts of the [[Bible]] will still use prayer books with Yiddish translation and commentaries, as their comprehension of Hebrew is deficient.

===Modern Yiddish education===
[[File:Yiddishsign.JPG|thumb|A road sign in Yiddish (except for the word &quot;sidewalk&quot;) at an official construction site in the [[Monsey, New York|Monsey]] hamlet, a community with thousands of Yiddish speakers, in the [[Ramapo, New York|Town of Ramapo]], [[New York]].]]
There has been a resurgence in Yiddish learning in recent times among many from around the world with Jewish ancestry. The language which had lost many of its native speakers during WWII has been making somewhat of a comeback.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishsf.com/content/2-0-/module/displaystory/story_id/9529/edition_id/182/format/html/displaystory.html |title=Yiddish making a comeback, as theater group shows &amp;#124; j. the Jewish news weekly of Northern California |publisher=Jewishsf.com |date=1998-09-18 |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Poland, which traditionally had Yiddish speaking communities, a particular museum has begun to revive Yiddish education and culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2008/WORLD/europe/09/30/poland.jewish.revival/index.html |title=Poland's Jews alive and kicking |publisher=CNN.com |date=2008-10-06 |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Located in Kraków, the [[Galicia Jewish Museum]] offers classes in Yiddish Language Instruction and workshops on Yiddish Songs. The museum has taken steps to revive the culture through concerts and events held on site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.galiciajewishmuseum.org |title=Galicia Jewish Museum |publisher=Galicia Jewish Museum |date= |accessdate=2011-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
There are various Universities worldwide which now offer Yiddish programs based on the [[YIVO]] Yiddish standard. Many of these programs are held during the summer and are attended by Yiddish enthusiasts from around the world. One such school located within [[Vilnius University]] (Vilnius Yiddish Institute) was the first Yiddish center of higher learning to be established in post-Holocaust Eastern Europe. Vilnius Yiddish Institute is an integral part of the four-century-old Vilnius University. Published Yiddish scholar and researcher Dovid Katz is among the Faculty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Neosymmetria (www.neosymmetria.com) |url=http://www.judaicvilnius.com/en |title=Vilnius Yiddish Institute |publisher=Judaicvilnius.com |date=2009-10-01 |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other schools which offer Yiddish programs include [[Tel Aviv University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.h-net.org/announce/show.cgi?ID=165354 |title=Tel Aviv Yiddish Summer Program 2009 |publisher=H-net.org |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brandeis University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brandeis.edu/departments/nejs/undergraduate/minors/yiddish.html |title=Yiddish and East European Studies Minor |publisher=Brandeis.edu |date=2010-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Monash University]], [[Australian Centre for Jewish Civilisation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arts.monash.edu.au/jewish-civilisation/study-areas/yiddish-language-culture/ |title=Program in Yiddish language and Culture |publisher=arts.monash.edu.au|date=2011-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[University College London]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucl.ac.uk/hebrew-jewish/courses/courses.php |title=Courses – Department of Hebrew &amp; Jewish Studies – University College London |publisher=Ucl.ac.uk |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[University of Oxford]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.orinst.ox.ac.uk/hjs/yiddish.html|title=Studying Yiddish at Oxford|accessdate=2011-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[University of Maryland]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishstudies.umd.edu/courses/index.html|title=University of Maryland Meyerhoff Center for Jewish Studies|accessdate=2011-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[YIVO]], [[New York University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yivo.as.nyu.edu/page/home |title=Uriel Weinreich Program in Yiddsh Language, Literature, and Culture &gt; Home |publisher=Yivo.as.nyu.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hampshire College]] campus at Amherst&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yiddishsummer.org/internship-information.html |title=Summer Yiddish Internship 2010 |publisher=Yiddish Summer.org |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; (home of the [[National Yiddish Book Center]]), [[Binghamton University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.binghamton.edu/judaic-studies/courses.html |title=judaic studies |publisher= binghamton.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Harvard University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~nelc/yiddish.html |title=Yiddish Language and Literature |publisher=Fas.harvard.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stanford University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stanford.edu/class/hebrew/yiddish/ |title=Yiddish at Stanford |publisher=Stanford.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[University of Pennsylvania]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.upenn.edu/registrar/register/ydsh.html |title=Yiddish (Ydsh) |publisher=Upenn.edu |date=2003-02-28 |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Indiana University, Bloomington]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indiana.edu/~germanic/dutch/#yiddish |title=Dutch, Norwegian &amp; Yiddish &amp;#124; Germanic Studies, Indiana University Bloomington |publisher=Indiana.edu |date=2009-09-17 |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Ohio State University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://germanic.osu.edu/undergrad/yiddish/ylang.cfm |title=The Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures |publisher=Germanic.osu.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060901102915/http://germanic.osu.edu/undergrad/yiddish/ylang.cfm |archivedate = September 1, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[University of Düsseldorf]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.phil-fak.uni-duesseldorf.de/ijs/studium-und-lehre/ |title=Philosophische Fakultät der HHUD: Studium und Lehre |publisher=Phil-fak.uni-duesseldorf.de |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[University of Chicago]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://humanities.uchicago.edu/depts/german/06_courses/coursesYDDH.html |title=Department of Germanic Studies |publisher=Humanities.uchicago.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Columbia University]],&lt;ref&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.columbia.edu/cu/german/yiddish/index.html&lt;/nowiki&gt; {{Dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vassar College]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://silp.vassar.edu/yiddish.html |title=Vassar College SILP – Yiddish |publisher=Silp.vassar.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[University of Massachusetts Amherst|UMass Amherst]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umass.edu/ug_catalog/archive_2002/judaic/judaiccourses.html#yiddish |title=UMass Course Catalog: Judaic &amp; Near Eastern Studies Courses |publisher=Umass.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[McGill University]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mcgill.ca/jewishstudies/category/tags/yiddish |title=yiddish &amp;#124; Jewish Studies מדעי היהדות - McGill University |publisher=Mcgill.ca |date= |accessdate=2011-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[UCLA]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.germanic.ucla.edu/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=19&amp;Itemid=21 |title=Yiddish |publisher=Germanic.ucla.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Emory University]] in Atlanta, [[University of Virginia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.virginia.edu/jewishstudies/academics-yiddish-language.html |title=The Jewish Studies Program at the University of Virginia |publisher=Virginia.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-10-18}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[University of Manitoba]],&lt;ref&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;http://www.umanitoba.ca/faculties/arts.html&lt;/nowiki&gt; {{Dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[University of Sao Paulo]], in [[Brazil]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://sistemas2.usp.br/jupiterweb/listarGradeCurricular?codcg=8&amp;codcur=8051&amp;codhab=1404&amp;tipo=N Faculdade de Filosofia, Letras e Ciências Humanas] [[University of Sao Paulo]]&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite this growing popularity among many [[American Jews]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2000/may/22/news/cl-32637 |title=A Lasting Language – Los Angeles Times |publisher=Articles.latimes.com |date= 2000-05-22|accessdate=2009-10-18 | first=Mary | last=Rourke}}&lt;/ref&gt; finding opportunities for practical use of Yiddish is becoming increasingly difficult, and thus many students have trouble learning to speak the language.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forward.com/articles/6818/ |title=In Academia, Yiddish Is Seen, But Not Heard&amp;nbsp;– |publisher=Forward.com |date=2006-03-24 |accessdate=2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Internet community===
{{Expand section|date=May 2012}}
[[Google Translate]] includes Yiddish as one of its languages,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lowensohn |first=Josh |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-27076_3-10322250-248.html |title=Oy! Google Translate now speaks Yiddish &amp;#124; Apple Talk - CNET News |publisher=News.cnet.com |date=2009-08-31 |accessdate=2011-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://translate.google.com/?hl=en#yi%7Cen |title=Google Translate from Yiddish to English |publisher=Translate.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; as do Wikipedia and [[Facebook]].

==See also==
[[File:NewSquareElectionSign.JPG|thumb|A 2008 Election poster in front of a store in [[New Square, New York|Village of New Square]], Town of Ramapo, New York, entirely in Yiddish. The candidate names are transliterated into Yiddish.]]
* [[List of English words of Yiddish origin]]
* [[List of Yiddish language poets]]
* [[The Yiddish King Lear]]
* [[Yiddish dialects]]—as spoken in different regions of Europe.
* [[Yiddish literature]]
* [[Yiddish grammar]]—the structural detail of the language.
* [[Yiddish orthography]]—the written representation of the language.
* [[Yiddish phonology]]—the elements of the spoken language.
* [[Yiddish Renaissance]]
* [[Yiddish words used in English]]—definitions of Yiddish words used in a primarily English context.
* [[Yinglish]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite book |last=Baumgarten |first=Jean |editor=Jerold C. Frakes |title=Introduction to Old Yiddish Literature |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=2005 |isbn=0-19-927633-1 |postscript=.}}
*[[Solomon Birnbaum|Birnbaum, Solomon]], ''Yiddish – A Survey and a Grammar'', Toronto, 1979
*Dunphy, Graeme, &quot;The New Jewish Vernacular&quot;, in: Max Reinhart, ''Camden House History of German Literature'' vol 4: ''Early Modern German Literature 1350-1700'', 2007, ISBN 1-57113-247-3, 74-9.
*{{Cite book |last=Fishman |first=David E. |title=The Rise of Modern Yiddish Culture |publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press |location=Pittsburgh |year=2005 |isbn=0-8229-4272-0 |postscript=.}}
*[[Joshua Fishman|Fishman, Joshua A.]] (ed.), ''Never Say Die: A Thousand Years of Yiddish in Jewish Life and Letters'', Mouton Publishers, The Hague, 1981, ISBN 90-279-7978-2 (in Yiddish and English).
*{{Cite book |last=Frakes |first=Jerold C |title=Early Yiddish Texts 1100-1750 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=2004 |isbn=0-19-926614-X |postscript=.}}
*&lt;div id=&quot;lcaaj&quot;&gt;Herzog, Marvin, et al. ed., YIVO, ''The Language and Culture Atlas of Ashkenazic Jewry'', 3 vols., Max Niemeyer Verlag, Tübingen, 1992–2000, ISBN 3-484-73013-7.&lt;/div&gt;
*&lt;div id=&quot;jacobs2005&quot;&gt;Jacobs, Neil G. ''Yiddish: a Linguistic Introduction'', Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 2005, ISBN 0-521-77215-X.&lt;/div&gt;
*{{Cite book |last=Katz |first=Dovid |title=Grammar of the Yiddish Language |publisher=Duckworth |location= London |year=1987 |isbn=07156216929 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}} |postscript=.}}
*{{Cite book |last=Katz |first=Dovid |title=Words on Fire: The Unfinished Story of Yiddish |edition=2 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |year=2007 |isbn=04365037305 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}} |postscript=.}}
*{{Cite book |last=Kriwaczek |first=Paul |title=Yiddish Civilization: The Rise and Fall of a Forgotten Nation |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |location=London |year=2005 |isbn=0-297-82941-6 |postscript=.}}
*Lansky, Aaron, ''Outwitting History: How a Young Man Rescued a Million Books and Saved a Vanishing Civilisation'', Algonquin Books, Chapel Hill, 2004, ISBN 1-56512-429-4.
*&lt;div id=&quot;liptzin1972&quot;&gt;Liptzin, Sol, ''A History of Yiddish Literature'', Jonathan David Publishers, Middle Village, NY, 1972, ISBN 0-8246-0124-6.&lt;/div&gt;
*[[Leo Rosten|Rosten, Leo]], ''Joys of Yiddish'', Pocket, 2000, ISBN 0-7434-0651-2 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (2) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}
*Shandler, Jeffrey, ''Adventures in Yiddishland: Postvernacular Language and Culture'', University of California Press, Berkeley, 2006, ISBN 0-520-24416-8.
*Shmeruk, Chone, Prokim fun der yidisher literatur-geshikhte, Peretz, Tel-Aviv 1988.
*[[Uriel Weinreich|Weinreich, Uriel]]. ''College Yiddish: an Introduction to the Yiddish language and to Jewish Life and Culture'', 6th revised ed., YIVO Institute for Jewish Research, New York, 1999, ISBN 0-914512-26-9 (in Yiddish and English).
*Weinstein, Miriam, ''Yiddish: A Nation of Words'', Ballantine Books, New York, 2001, ISBN 0-345-44730-1.
*[[Michael Wex|Wex, Michael]], ''[[Born to Kvetch]]: Yiddish Language and Culture in All Its Moods'', St. Martin's Press, New York, 2005, ISBN 0-312-30741-1.
*Wexler, Paul, ''Two-Tiered Relexification in Yiddish: Jews, Sorbs, Khazars, and the Kiev-Polessian Dialect'', Berlin, New York, Mouton de Gruyter, 2002, ISBN 3-11-017258-5.
*Witriol, Joseph,(1974,unpublished) ''Mumme Loohshen: An Anatomy of Yiddish''  London, now available online at http://mummeloohshen.wordpress.com/ 
* Katz, Hirshe-Dovid, 1992. ''Code of Yiddish spelling ratified in 1992 by the programmes in Yiddish language and literature at Bar Ilan University, Oxford University Tel Aviv University, Vilnius University.'' Oxford: Oksforder Yidish Press in cooperation with the [[Oxford Centre for Postgraduate Hebrew Studies]]. (כלל–תקנות פון יידישן אויסלייג. 1992. אקספארד: אקספארדער צענטער פאר העכערע העברעאישע שטודיעס) ISBN 1-897744-01-3
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
===Periodicals===
*''YIVO Bleter'', pub. YIVO Institute for Jewish Research, NYC, [http://www.yivo.org/aboutyivo/timeline3.htm initial series] from 1931, [http://www.yivoinstitute.org/publications/index.php?tid=123&amp;aid=319 new series] since 1991.
*''Afn Shvel'', pub. League for Yiddish, NYC, since 1940; [http://www.leagueforyiddish.org/ishi.html אויפן שוועל], [http://docs.leagueforyiddish.org/undzer-perets-artikl.pdf sample article אונדזער פרץ – Our Peretz]
*''Lebns-fragn'', by-monthly for social issues, current affairs, and culture, Tel Aviv, since 1951; [http://lebnsfragn.com/about.html לעבנס-פראגן], [http://lebnsfragn.com/index.html current issue]
*''Yerusholaymer Almanakh'', periodical collection of Yiddish literature and culture, Jerusalem, since 1973; [http://yiddish-almanach.org/index.php/the-yerusholaymer-almanakh/ ירושלימער אלמאנאך], [http://yiddish-almanach.org/ new volume, contents and downloads]
*''Der Yiddisher Tam-Tam'', pub. Maison de la Culture Yiddish, Paris, since 1994, also available in [http://www.yiddishweb.com/tamtam.htm electronic format].
*''Yidishe Heftn'', pub. Le Cercle Bernard Lazare, Paris, since 1996, [http://mapage.noos.fr/bernardlazare/CahiersY.htm יידישע העפטן sample cover], [http://www.bernardlazare.org/ subscription info].
*''Gilgulim, naye shafungen'', new literary magazine, Paris, since 2008; [http://gilgulim.org/ גילגולים, נייע שאפונגען]

==External links==
{{InterWiki|code=yi}}
{{Wikibooks|Yiddish}}
{{Wikibooks|Yiddish for Yeshivah Bachurim}}
{{Wiktionary category}}
{{commonscat|Yiddish language}}
* [http://www.medienhilfe.org/page/index.php?rubrik=0029&amp;id=0061 www.medienhilfe.org] First overview about Yiddish media worldwide of Internationale Medienhilfe organization
* [http://jidysz.net/ ''yidish lebt'' project – open-source dictionary, spellchecker, keyboard for windows, and other stuff for yidish language]
* http://lib.cet.ac.il/pages/item.asp?item=12887 Israeli Government Portal: Yiddish
* [http://www.yiddishdictionary.co.il Free Yiddish Dictionary]
* [http://www.yiddishdictionaryonline.com/ On-line Yiddish dictionary]
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=dnMVAAAAYAAJ A Dictionary of the Yiddish Language] by [[Alexander Harkavy]], 1898 (from Google Books); [http://www.cs.uky.edu/~raphael/yiddish/harkavy/index.utf8.html 1910 edition (online), 6th edition]
* [http://www.verterbukh.org Verterbukh&amp;nbsp;– Yiddish Resources Online]
* [http://www.yiddishbookcenter.org Yiddish Book Center]
* [http://www.jewish-languages.org/yiddish.html Jewish Language Research Website: Yiddish]
* [http://www.sbs.com.au/yourlanguage/yiddish SBS Weekly Yiddish News (Australia)]
* [http://www.cs.engr.uky.edu/~raphael/yiddish/makeyiddish.html Yiddish Typewriter] – interconverts Yiddish text in Hebrew script with YIVO transliteration
* [http://yiddish-sources.com/ WWW Virtual Library History Central Catalogue – Yiddish Sources] Academic portal for Yiddish Studies, includes an online bibliography.
* [http://www.languagesandpeoples.com/Eng/Direct/Germanic/SglLgYiddishNewYork.htm 'Hover &amp; Hear' New York Yiddish pronunciations], and compare with equivalents in English and other Germanic languages.
* [http://yivo.org/ YIVO Institute for Jewish Research]
* [http://mummeloohshen.wordpress.com/ Mumme Loohshen: An Anatomy of Yiddish, Joseph Witriol]
* [http://www.heardutchhere.net/duhebrew.html Yiddish words in Dutch slang, with sound files]
{{Jewish languages}}
{{West Germanic languages}}
{{Germanic languages}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Yiddish Language}}
[[Category:Yiddish language| ]]
[[Category:Ashkenazi Jews topics]]
[[Category:Jewish languages]]
[[Category:Jews and Judaism in Germany]]
[[Category:German dialects]]
[[Category:High German languages]]
[[Category:Languages of Israel]]
[[Category:Languages of Poland]]
[[Category:Languages of Russia]]
[[Category:Languages of Ukraine]]
[[Category:Diaspora languages]]
[[Category:Subject–verb–object languages]]
[[Category:Verb-second languages]]

[[af:Jiddisj]]
[[als:Jiddisch]]
[[am:ዪዲሽኛ]]
[[ar:لغة يديشية]]
[[an:Yídix]]
[[az:İdiş dili]]
[[bjn:Bahasa Yiddish]]
[[zh-min-nan:Yidish-gí]]
[[ba:Идиш]]
[[be:Ідыш]]
[[be-x-old:Ідыш]]
[[bg:Идиш]]
[[bar:Jiddisch]]
[[br:Yideg]]
[[ca:Jiddisch]]
[[cv:Идиш]]
[[cs:Jidiš]]
[[cy:Iddew-Almaeneg]]
[[da:Jiddisch (sprog)]]
[[pdc:Yiddisch]]
[[de:Jiddisch]]
[[et:Jidiši keel]]
[[el:Γίντις]]
[[es:Yidis]]
[[eo:Jida lingvo]]
[[eu:Yiddish]]
[[fa:زبان ییدیش]]
[[hif:Yiddish bhasa]]
[[fo:Jiddiskt mál]]
[[fr:Yiddish]]
[[fy:Jiddysk]]
[[ga:An Ghiúdais]]
[[gd:Iùdais]]
[[gl:Lingua yiddish]]
[[ko:이디시어]]
[[hsb:Jidišćina]]
[[hr:Jidiš]]
[[io:Yiddisha linguo]]
[[id:Bahasa Yiddi]]
[[ie:Yiddic]]
[[it:Lingua yiddish]]
[[he:יידיש]]
[[jv:Basa Yiddish]]
[[ka:იდიში]]
[[kw:Yedhowek]]
[[kv:Идиш]]
[[ku:Zimanê yîdîş]]
[[lad:Idish]]
[[la:Lingua Iudaeogermanica]]
[[lv:Jidišs]]
[[lt:Jidiš]]
[[lij:Lengua yiddish]]
[[li:Jiddisch]]
[[hu:Jiddis nyelv]]
[[ml:യിദ്ദിഷ്]]
[[mr:यिडिश भाषा]]
[[arz:ييدى]]
[[ms:Bahasa Yiddish]]
[[nl:Jiddisch]]
[[nds-nl:Jiddisj]]
[[ja:イディッシュ語]]
[[no:Jiddisch]]
[[nn:Jiddisch]]
[[oc:Yiddish]]
[[mhr:Идиш йылме]]
[[pnb:یدش]]
[[nds:Jiddisch]]
[[pl:Jidysz]]
[[pt:Língua iídiche]]
[[crh:Yidiş tili]]
[[ro:Limba idiș]]
[[ru:Идиш]]
[[sco:Yiddish leid]]
[[scn:Lingua yiddish]]
[[simple:Yiddish]]
[[sk:Jidiš]]
[[sl:Jidiš]]
[[szl:Jidisz]]
[[sr:Јидиш]]
[[sh:Jidiš]]
[[fi:Jiddiš]]
[[sv:Jiddisch]]
[[tl:Wikang Yidis]]
[[ta:இத்திய மொழி]]
[[kab:Yidic]]
[[th:ภาษายิดดิช]]
[[tr:Yidiş]]
[[uk:Їдиш]]
[[vi:Tiếng Yiddish]]
[[yi:יידיש]]
[[zh:意第緒語]]</text>
      <sha1>1ex7sd7phy85lvtwdndf3pjz5ux0pk7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
