<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Coal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5987</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521068237</id>
      <parentid>521064009</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T16:00:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>2sc945</username>
        <id>12286615</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* World coal reserves */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="65469">{{pp-vandalism|expiry=25 April 2013|small=yes}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox rock
|name=Coal
|type=Sedimentary
|image=Coal anthracite.jpg 
|image_caption=Anthracite coal
|composition=carbon
|composition_secondary=hydrogen,&lt;br /&gt;sulfur,&lt;br /&gt;oxygen,&lt;br /&gt;nitrogen 
}}
'''Coal''' (from the Old English term ''col'', which has meant &quot;mineral of fossilized carbon&quot; since the 13th century)&lt;ref&gt;{{OEtymD|coal}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[combustible]] black or brownish-black [[sedimentary rock]] usually occurring in [[stratum|rock strata]] in layers or veins called '''coal beds&lt;!-- redirected term title--&gt;''' or '''coal seams'''. The harder forms, such as [[anthracite|anthracite coal]], can be regarded as [[metamorphic rock]] because of later exposure to elevated temperature and [[pressure]]. Coal is composed primarily of [[carbon]] along with variable quantities of other elements, chiefly  [[hydrogen]], [[sulfur]], [[oxygen]], and [[nitrogen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Blander|first=M|title=Calculations of the Influence of Additives on Coal Combustion Deposits|url=http://www.anl.gov/PCS/acsfuel/preprint%20archive/Files/Volumes/Vol34-2.pdf|publisher=Argonne National Laboratory|accessdate=17 December 2011|page=315}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Throughout history, coal has been a useful resource. It is primarily burned for the production of electricity and/or heat, and is also used for industrial purposes, such as refining metals. A [[fossil fuel]], coal forms when dead plant matter is converted into [[peat]], which in turn is converted into [[lignite]], then sub-bituminous coal, then bituminous coal, and lastly [[anthracite]]. This involves biological and geological processes that take place over a long period.

Coal is the largest source of energy for the [[Electricity generation|generation of electricity]] worldwide, as well as one of the largest worldwide [[anthropogenic]] sources of [[carbon dioxide]] releases. In 1999 world gross [[carbon dioxide emissions]] from coal usage were 8,666 million tonnes of carbon dioxide.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation| url  = http://www.eia.doe.gov/iea/carbon.html |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110523215823/http://www.eia.doe.gov/iea/carbon.html|title = International Energy Annual 2006| date =  2008| publisher =  [[Energy Information Administration]]| archivedate = 23 May 2011}}, see data tables&lt;/ref&gt;

Coal-fired electric power generation emits around 2,000 pounds of carbon dioxide for every megawatt-hour generated, which is almost double the carbon dioxide released by a natural gas-fired electric plant per megawatt-hour generated.  Because of this higher carbon efficiency of natural gas generation, as the fuel mix in the United States has changed to reduce coal and increase natural gas generation, carbon dioxide emissions have unexpectedly fallen. Those measured in the first quarter of 2012 were the lowest of any recorded for the first quarter of any year since 1992.&lt;ref&gt;Nuwer, Rachel (2012-08-17). [http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/08/17/a-20-year-low-in-u-s-carbon-emissions/ A 20-Year Low in U.S. Carbon Emissions]. blogs.nytimes.com&lt;/ref&gt;  

Coal is extracted from the ground by [[coal mining]], either underground by [[shaft mining]], or at ground level by [[open pit mining]] extraction.

The top hard and brown coal producers in 2010 (and 2009) were (in millions of tons): China 3,162 (2,971); United States 997 (985); India 571 (571); Australia 420 (399); Indonesia 336 (301); Russia 324 (297); South Africa 255 (247); Poland 134 (135); Kazakhstan 111 (101); and Colombia 74 (73).&lt;ref name=öljy&gt;*{{citation| title = 2010 Key World Energy Statistics| url = http://www.iea.org/textbase/nppdf/free/2010/key_stats_2010.pdf| publisher = IEA }}
*{{citation| title = 2011 Key World Energy Statistics| url = http://www.iea.org/textbase/nppdf/free/2011/key_world_energy_stats.pdf| publisher = IEA }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Coal bituminous.jpg|thumb|Bituminous coal]]

== Formation ==

[[File:Struktura chemiczna węgla kamiennego.svg|thumb|Example chemical structure of coal]]
About 300 million years ago, the earth had dense forests in low-lying wetland areas. Due to natural processes such as flooding, these forests were buried under the soil. As more and more soil deposited over them, they were compressed. The temperature also rose as they sank deeper and deeper. For the process to continue, the plant matter was protected from [[biodegradation]] and [[oxidization]], usually by mud or acidic water.  This trapped the carbon in immense [[peat bog]]s that were eventually covered and deeply buried by sediments. Under high pressure and high temperature, dead vegetation was slowly converted to coal. As coal contains mainly carbon, the conversion of dead vegetation into coal is called carbonization.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite book 
 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=_29tNNeQKeMC&amp;pg=PA18
 | title = Paleobotany: The biology and evolution of fossil plants
 | isbn = 978-0-12-373972-8
 | author1 = Taylor, Thomas N
 | author2 = Taylor, Edith L
 | author3 = Krings, Michael
 | year = 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The wide, shallow seas of the [[Carboniferous era]] provided ideal conditions for coal formation, although coal is known from most geological periods.  The exception is the coal gap in the [[Permian–Triassic extinction event]], where coal is rare.  Coal is known from [[Precambrian]] strata, which predate land plants — this coal is presumed to have originated from residues of algae.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tyler1957&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.1130/0016-7606(1957)68[1293:ACFPUH]2.0.CO;2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mancuso1981&quot;&gt;{{cite doi|10.2113/gsecongeo.76.4.951}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Types ==
[[File:Sydney Mines Point Aconi Seam 038.JPG|thumb|Coastal exposure of the Point Aconi Seam ]]
[[File:LateCarboniferousGlobal.jpg|thumb|Approximate position of [[continent]]s toward the end of the [[Carboniferous Period]]. The light blue represents shallow seas where many of today's coal deposits are found, as opposed to deeper waters which gave rise to oil-bearing rocks derived from marine species.]]
As geological processes apply [[pressure]] to dead [[biotic material]] over time, under suitable conditions it is transformed successively into:
* [[Peat]], considered to be a precursor of coal, has industrial importance as a fuel in some regions, for example, Ireland and Finland. In its dehydrated form, peat is a highly effective absorbent for fuel and oil spills on land and water. It is also used as a conditioner for soil to make it more able to retain and slowly release water.
* [[Lignite]], or brown coal, is the lowest rank of coal and used almost exclusively as fuel for electric power generation. [[jet (lignite)|Jet]], a compact form of lignite, is sometimes polished and has been used as an ornamental stone since the [[Upper Palaeolithic]].
* [[Sub-bituminous coal]], whose properties range from those of lignite to those of bituminous coal, is used primarily as fuel for steam-electric power generation and is an important source of light [[aromatic hydrocarbon]]s for the [[chemical synthesis]] industry.
* [[Bituminous coal]] is a dense sedimentary rock, usually black, but sometimes dark brown, often with well-defined bands of bright and dull material; it is used primarily as fuel in steam-electric power generation, with substantial quantities used for heat and power applications in manufacturing and to make [[coke (fuel)|coke]].
* &quot;Steam coal&quot; is a grade between bituminous coal and anthracite, once widely used as a fuel for [[steam locomotive]]s. In this specialized use, it is sometimes known as &quot;sea-coal&quot; in the US.&lt;ref&gt;[[Funk and Wagnalls]], quoted in {{cite book|title=[[Oxford English Dictionary]]|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1989|edition=2|chapter=sea-coal}}&lt;/ref&gt; Small steam coal (dry small steam nuts or DSSN) was used as a fuel for domestic [[water heating]].
* [[Anthracite]], the highest rank of coal, is a harder, glossy black coal used primarily for residential and commercial [[space heating]]. It may be divided further into metamorphically altered bituminous coal and &quot;petrified oil&quot;, as from the deposits in Pennsylvania.
* [[Graphite]], technically the highest rank, is difficult to ignite and is not commonly used as fuel — it is mostly used in pencils and, when powdered, as a [[lubricant]].

The classification of coal is generally based on the content of volatiles. However, the exact classification varies between countries. According to the German classification, coal is classified as follows:&lt;ref&gt;Eberhard Lindner; Chemie für Ingenieure; Lindner Verlag Karlsruhe, S. 258&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! German Classification
! English Designation
! Volatiles %
! C Carbon %
! H Hydrogen %
! O Oxygen %
! S Sulfur %
! Heat content kJ/kg
|-
|''Braunkohle
|Lignite
|45–65
|60–75
|6.0–5.8
|34-17
|0.5-3
|&lt;28,470
|-
|''Flammkohle
| Flame coal
|40-45
|75-82
|6.0-5.8
|&gt;9.8
|~1
|&lt;32,870
|-
|''Gasflammkohle
|Gas flame coal
|35-40
|82-85
|5.8-5.6
|9.8-7.3
|~1
|&lt;33,910
|-
|''Gaskohle
|Gas coal
|28-35
|85-87.5
|5.6-5.0
|7.3-4.5
|~1
|&lt;34,960
|-
|''Fettkohle
|Fat coal
|19-28
|87.5-89.5
|5.0-4.5
|4.5-3.2
|~1
|&lt;35,380
|-
|''Esskohle
|Forge coal
|14-19
|89.5-90.5
|4.5-4.0
|3.2-2.8
|~1
|&lt;35,380
|-
|''Magerkohle
|Nonbaking coal
|10-14
|90.5-91.5
|4.0-3.75
|2.8-3.5
|~1
|35,380
|-
|''Anthrazit
|Anthracite
|7-12
|&gt;91.5
|&lt;3.75
|&lt;2.5
|~1
|&lt;35,300
|-
|colspan=8| &lt;small&gt;Percent by weight&lt;/small&gt;
|}
The middle six grades in the table represent a progressive transition from the English-language sub-bituminous to bituminous coal, while the last class is an approximate equivalent to anthracite, but more inclusive (US anthracite has &lt; 6% volatiles).

[[Cannel coal]] (sometimes called &quot;candle coal&quot;) is a variety of fine-grained, high-rank coal with significant hydrogen content. It consists primarily of &quot;[[exinite]]&quot; [[maceral]]s, now termed &quot;liptinite&quot;.

===Hilt's law===
{{main|Hilt's law}}
[[Hilt's law]] is a geological term that states that, in a small area, the deeper the coal, the higher its rank (grade). The law holds true if the thermal gradient is entirely vertical, but metamorphism may cause lateral changes of rank, irrespective of depth.

==Early uses as fuel==
{{Further|History of coal mining}}
[[Image:Tiangong Kaiwu Coal Mining.gif|thumb|Chinese coal miners in an illustration of the ''Tiangong Kaiwu'' encyclopedia, published in 1637]]
Coal was used by the Chinese long before it was used in Europe; coal from the Fushun mine in northeastern China was used to smelt copper as early as 1000 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia Britannica http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/122863/coal&lt;/ref&gt; Marco Polo, the Italian who traveled to China in 13th century, described coal—which at that time was unknown to most Europeans—as “black stones...which burn like logs&quot;, and said coal was so plentiful, people could take three hot baths a week.&lt;ref&gt;http://factsanddetails.com/china.php?itemid=47&amp;catid=2&lt;/ref&gt; In Europe, the earliest reference to the use of coal as fuel is from the geological treatise ''On stones'' (Lap. 16) by the [[Greeks|Greek]] scientist [[Theophrastus]] (''circa'' 371–287 BC):&lt;ref name = &quot;Mattusch&quot;&gt;{{citation| first=Mattusch|last= Carol |year=2008| title = Metalworking and Tools| editorlink=John Peter Oleson|editor-last = Oleson| editor-first= John Peter| work = The Oxford Handbook of Engineering and Technology in the Classical World| publisher =  Oxford University Press| isbn= 978-0-19-518731-1| pages= 418–38 (432)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation| url= http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=qvTDGRMPU5kC|title = Greek Science of the Hellenistic Era: A Sourcebook| first = Georgia L.|last = Irby-Massie|first2 =  Paul T.| last2 = Keyser|publisher = Routledge| year = 2002 | at = 9.1 &quot;Theophrastos&quot;, p.228}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote| Among the materials that are dug because they are useful, those known as ''anthrakes'' [coals] are made of earth, and, once set on fire, they burn like charcoal. They are found in Liguria … and in Elis as one approaches Olympia by the mountain road; and they are used by those who work in metals.|Theophrastus, On Stones (16) ''translation''}}

[[Outcrop]] coal was used in [[Great Britain|Britain]] during the [[Bronze Age]] (3000–2000 BC), where it has been detected as forming part of the composition of [[funeral]] [[pyre]]s.&lt;ref name = &quot;Britannicacoal&quot;&gt;Britannica 2004: ''Coal mining: ancient use of outcropping coal''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Science and Civilisation in China |first2= Peter J |last2=Golas  |first=Joseph |last=Needham |pages = 186–91 | publisher =Cambridge University Press |year=1999 |isbn= 978-0-521-58000-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Roman Britain]], with the exception of two modern fields, &quot;the [[Mining in Roman Britain|Romans]] were exploiting coals in all the major coalfields in [[England]] and [[Wales]] by the end of the second century AD&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith 1997, 322–324&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Smith, A. H. V. |year=1997|title=Provenance of Coals from Roman Sites in England and Wales|journal=Britannia|volume=28|pages=297–324 (322–4)|jstor=526770|doi=10.2307/526770}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evidence of trade in coal (dated to about AD 200) has been found at [[Heronbridge Roman Site|roman settlement at Heronbridge]], near [[Chester]], and in the [[The Fens|Fenlands]] of [[East Anglia]], where coal from the [[English Midlands|Midlands]] was transported via the [[Car Dyke]] for use in drying grain.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last = Salway | first = Peter | year = 2001 | title = A History of Roman Britain | publisher = Oxford University Press }}&lt;/ref&gt; Coal cinders have been found in the hearths of [[Roman villa|villa]]s and [[Roman forts]], particularly in [[Northumberland]], dated to around AD 400. In the west of England, contemporary writers described the wonder of a permanent brazier of coal on the altar of [[Minerva]] at [[Aquae Sulis]] (modern day [[Bath, Somerset|Bath]]), although in fact easily accessible surface coal from what became the [[Somerset coalfield]] was in common use in quite lowly dwellings locally.&lt;ref&gt;Forbes, RJ (1966): ''Studies in Ancient Technology''. Brill Academic Publishers, Boston.&lt;/ref&gt; Evidence of coal's use for iron-working in the city during the Roman period has been found.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Cunliffe
 | first = Barry W.
 | authorlink = Barry Cunliffe
 | title = Roman Bath Discovered
 | publisher = Routledge
 | year = 1984
 | location = London
 | pages = 14–5, 194
 | isbn = 0-7102-0196-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Eschweiler]], [[Rhineland]], deposits of [[bituminous coal]] were used by the Romans for the smelting of [[iron ore]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith 1997, 322–324&quot;/&gt;

No evidence exists of the product being of great importance in Britain before the [[High Middle Ages]], after about AD 1000.&lt;ref name = &quot;TCC&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cantril|first=T. C.|title=Coal Mining|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, England|year= 1914 | pages = 3–10| oclc =156716838}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mineral]] coal came to be referred to as &quot;seacoal&quot; in the 13th century; the wharf where the material arrived in London was known as Seacoal Lane, so identified in a charter of [[Henry III of England|King Henry III]] granted in 1253.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Oxford English Dictionary]]|date=1 December 2010|publisher=Oxford University Press|chapter=coal, 5a}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, the name was given because much coal was found on the shore, having fallen from the exposed [[coal seam]]s on cliffs above or washed out of underwater coal outcrops,&lt;ref name = &quot;TCC&quot; /&gt; but by the time of [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]], it was understood to derive from the way it was carried to London by sea.&lt;ref&gt;[[John Caius]], quoted in Cantril (1914).&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1257–59, coal from [[Newcastle upon Tyne]] was shipped to London for the smiths and lime-burners building [[Westminster Abbey]].&lt;ref name = &quot;TCC&quot; /&gt; Seacoal Lane and Newcastle Lane, where coal was unloaded at wharves along the [[River Fleet]], are still in existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Trench|first= Richard |coauthors=Hillman, Ellis|title=London under London: a subterranean guide|publisher=John Murray|location=London|year=1993| edition= Second | page=33|isbn=0-7195-5288-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See [[Coal#Industrial processes|Industrial processes]] below for modern uses of the term.)

These easily accessible sources had largely become exhausted (or could not meet the growing demand) by the 13th century, when underground extraction by [[shaft mining]] or [[adit]]s was developed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannicacoal&quot; /&gt; The alternative name was &quot;pitcoal&quot;, because it came from mines. It was, however, the development of the [[Industrial Revolution]] that led to the large-scale use of coal, as the [[steam engine]] took over from the [[water wheel]]. In 1700, five-sixths of the world's coal was mined in Britain. Without coal, Britain would have run out of suitable sites for watermills by the 1830s.&lt;ref name = &quot;Wrigley&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| title = Continuity, Chance and Change: The Character of the Industrial Revolution in England| first = EA | last = Wrigley|isbn=0521396573|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year= 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1947, there were some 750,000 miners,&lt;ref name = &quot;BBC News&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/551544.stm | title = The fall of King Coal | work = BBC News | date = 6 December 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; but by 2004, this had shrunk to some 5,000 miners working in around 20 collieries.&lt;ref name = &quot;BBC Inside Out&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/insideout/eastmidlands/series5/miners_strike_coal.shtml |date=2 February 2004| title = The miners' strike revisited | publisher = BBC | periodical = Inside Out}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Uses today ==
[[Image:Grand Junction Trip 92007 098.JPG|thumb|[[Castle Gate Plant]] near [[Helper, Utah]], USA]]
[[File:Ashtabulacoalcars e2.jpg|thumb|Coal rail cars]]

===Coal as fuel===
{{Further|Electricity generation|Clean coal technology|Coal electricity|Global warming}}
Coal is primarily used as a [[solid fuel]] to produce electricity and heat through combustion. World coal consumption was about 7.25 billion [[tonnes]] in 2010&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eia.gov/cfapps/ipdbproject/iedindex3.cfm?tid=1&amp;pid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;cid=ww,&amp;syid=2000&amp;eyid=2011&amp;unit=TST World coal consumption 2000–2011] [[EIA]] statistics&lt;/ref&gt; (7.99 billion [[short ton]]s) and is expected to increase 48% to 9.05 billion tonnes (9.98 billion short tons) by 2030.&lt;ref&gt;EIA, World Energy Projections Plus (2009)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Coal power in China|China]] produced 3.47 billion tonnes (3.83 billion short tons) in 2011. [[India]] produced about 578 million tonnes (637.1 million short tons) in 2011. 68.7% of China's electricity comes from coal. The USA consumed about 13% of the world total in 2010, i.e. 951 million tonnes (1.05 billion short tons), using 93% of it for generation of electricity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eia.gov/coal/review/coal_consumption.cfm U.S. Coal Supply and Demand: 2010 Year in Review]. Eia.gov (2011-06-01). Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; 46% of total power generated in the USA was done using coal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eia.gov/coal/review/html/fig5.cfm Share of electric power sector net generation by energy source]. Eia.gov (2011-06-01). Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; 

When coal is used for [[electricity generation]], it is usually pulverized and then combusted (burned) in a [[furnace]] with a [[boiler]].&lt;ref name=&quot;World Coal&quot;/&gt; The furnace heat converts boiler water to [[steam]], which is then used to spin [[turbine]]s which turn [[electrical generator|generator]]s and create electricity. The [[thermodynamic efficiency]] of this process has been improved over time. Simple cycle steam turbines have topped out with some of the most advanced reaching about 35% thermodynamic efficiency for the entire process. Increasing the combustion temperature can boost this efficiency even further.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Fossil Power Generation | publisher = Siemens AG | url = http://w1.siemens.com/responsibility/en/environment/portfolio/fossil_power_generation.htm | accessdate =23 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Old coal power plants, especially &quot;[[grandfathered]]&quot; plants, are significantly less efficient and produce higher levels of [[waste heat]]. At least 40% of the world's electricity comes from coal,&lt;ref name=&quot;World Coal&quot;&gt;[http://www.worldcoal.org/coal/uses-of-coal/coal-electricity/ Total World Electricity Generation by Fuel (2006)]. Source: IEA 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldcoal.org/pages/content/index.asp?PageID=188 coal reserves, coal exploration – World Coal Association]. Worldcoal.org. Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2012, about one-third of the United States' electricity came from coal, down from approximately 49% in 2008.&lt;ref name=NYTKentucky /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.eia.doe.gov/cneaf/electricity/epa/figes1.html
|title=Figure ES 1. U.S. Electric Power Industry Net Generation
|work=Electric Power Annual with data for 2008
|publisher=U.S. Energy Information Administration
|date=21 January 2010
|accessdate=7 November 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2012 in the United States, use of coal to generate electricity was declining, as plentiful supplies of natural gas obtained by [[hydraulic fracturing]] of tight shale formations became available at low prices.&lt;ref name=NYTKentucky&gt;{{cite news|title=Even in Coal Country, the Fight for an Industry|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/05/30/business/energy-environment/even-in-kentucky-coal-industry-is-under-siege.html|accessdate=30 May 2012|newspaper=The New York Times|date=29 May 2012|author=Lipton, Eric}}&lt;/ref&gt; The emergence of the [[steam turbine|supercritical turbine]] concept envisions running a boiler at extremely high temperatures and pressures with projected efficiencies of 46%, with further theorized increases in temperature and pressure perhaps resulting in even higher efficiencies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Balancing economics and environmental friendliness – the challenge for supercritical coal-fired power plants with highest steam parameters in the future | coauthors=Jens Rosenkranz and Andreas Wichtmann|format=PDF|accessdate=23 October 2006|url=http://www.powergeneration.siemens.com/download/pool/PGE2005_BalancingEconomics.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Denmark, a net electric efficiency of &gt; 47% has been obtained at the coal-fired Nordjyllandsværket CHP Plant and an overall plant efficiency of up to 91% with cogeneration of electricity and district heating.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vattenfall.dk/da/file/NordjyllandUK080121_7841588.pdf Nordjyllandsværket]&lt;/ref&gt;  The multifuel-fired Avedøreværket CHP Plant just outside Copenhagen can achieve a net electric efficiency as high as 49%. The overall plant efficiency with cogeneration of electricity and district heating can reach as much as 94%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ipaper.ipapercms.dk/DONGENERGY/Internet/UK/ThermalPower/AVVbrochure2012UK/ Avedøreværket]&lt;/ref&gt;

An experimental way of coal combustion is in the form of [[coal-water slurry fuel]] (CWS), which was well-developed in Russia since the days of the [[Soviet Union]]. CWS significantly reduces emissions, improving the heating value of coal. Other ways to use coal are [[cogeneration|combined heat and power cogeneration]] and [[magnetohydrodynamic generator|an MHD topping cycle]].

The total known deposits recoverable by current technologies, including highly polluting, low-energy content types of coal (i.e., lignite, bituminous), is sufficient for many years.{{how many|date=May 2012}} However, consumption is increasing and [[peak coal|maximal production could be reached]] within decades (see [[Coal#World coal reserves|world coal reserves]], below).

===Coking coal and use of coke===
{{Main|Coke (fuel)}}
[[File:Coke Ovens Abercwmboi.jpg|right|thumb|Coke oven at a [[smokeless fuel]] plant in [[Wales]], [[United Kingdom]]]]
Coke is a solid carbonaceous residue derived from low-ash, low-sulfur bituminous coal from which the volatile constituents are driven off by baking in an oven without oxygen at temperatures as high as 1,000°C (1,832°F), so the fixed carbon and residual ash are fused together. Metallurgical coke is used as a fuel and as a [[reducing agent]] in smelting [[iron]] ore in a [[blast furnace]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.steelonthenet.com/cost-bof.html Blast furnace steelmaking cost model]. Steelonthenet.com. Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The result is [[pig iron]], and is too rich in dissolved carbon, so it must be treated further to make [[steel]]. The coking coal should be low in [[sulfur]] and [[phosphorus]], so they do not migrate to the metal. 

The coke must be [[Coke strength after reaction|strong enough]] to resist the weight of overburden in the blast furnace, which is why coking coal is so important in making steel using the conventional route. However, the alternative route is [[direct reduced iron]], where any carbonaceous fuel can be used to make sponge or pelletised iron. Coke from coal is grey, hard, and porous and has a heating value of 24.8 million Btu/ton (29.6 MJ/kg). Some cokemaking processes produce valuable byproducts, including [[coal tar]], [[ammonia]], light oils, and [[coal gas]].

[[Petroleum coke]] is the solid residue obtained in [[oil refining]], which resembles coke, but contains too many impurities to be useful in metallurgical applications.

===Gasification===
{{Main|Coal gasification|Underground coal gasification}}
Coal gasification can be used to produce [[syngas]], a mixture of [[carbon monoxide]] (CO) and hydrogen (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) gas. This syngas can then be converted into transportation fuels, such as gasoline and diesel, through the [[Fischer-Tropsch process]]. This technology is currently used by the [[Sasol]] chemical company of [[South Africa]] to make motor vehicle fuels from coal and natural gas. Alternatively, the hydrogen obtained from gasification can be used for various purposes, such as powering a [[hydrogen economy]], making ammonia, or upgrading fossil fuels.

During gasification, the coal is mixed with [[oxygen]] and [[steam]] while also being heated and pressurized. During the reaction, oxygen and water molecules [[oxidize]] the coal into carbon monoxide (CO), while also releasing [[hydrogen]] gas (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;). This process has been conducted in both underground coal mines and in the production of [[town gas]].

: C (''as Coal'') + O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O → H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + CO

If the refiner wants to produce gasoline, the syngas is collected at this state and routed into a Fischer-Tropsch reaction. If hydrogen is the desired end-product, however, the syngas is fed into the [[water gas shift reaction]], where more hydrogen is liberated.

: CO + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O → CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;

In the past, coal was converted to make coal gas ([[town gas]]), which was piped to customers to burn for illumination, heating, and cooking.

===Liquefaction===
{{Main|Coal liquefaction}}

Coal can also be converted into [[synthetic fuel]]s equivalent to [[gasoline]] or [[Diesel fuel|diesel]] by several different processes. In the direct liquefaction processes, the coal is either [[hydrogenation|hydrogenated]] or [[carbonization|carbonized]]. Hydrogenation processes are the [[Bergius process]],&lt;ref&gt;{{citation| first = Robert|last= Haul| title = Friedrich Bergius (1884–1949)| page =  62 |journal = Chemie in unserer Zeit| publisher =  VCH-Verlagsgesellschaft mbH| volume= 19|date= April 1985}}&lt;/ref&gt; the SRC-I and SRC-II (Solvent Refined Coal) processes and the NUS Corporation hydrogenation process.&lt;ref name=handbook2&gt;
{{Cite book
 | last =Speight | first = James G.
 | title = Synthetic Fuels Handbook: Properties, Process, and Performance
 | publisher = [[McGraw-Hill|McGraw-Hill Professional]]
 | pages = 9–10
 | year = 2008
 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=E3pgqnGgHjIC&amp;pg=PA9
 | isbn = 978-0-07-149023-8}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author= Lowe, Phillip A.; Schroeder, Wilburn C.; Liccardi, Anthony L.
 | title=Technical Economies, Synfuels and Coal Energy Symposium, Solid-Phase Catalytic Coal Liquefaction Process
 | publisher= [[American Society of Mechanical Engineers]]
 | year=1976
 | page=35}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In the process of low-temperature [[carbonization]], coal is coked at temperatures between 360 and 750°C (680 and 1,380°F). These temperatures optimize the production of coal tars richer in lighter hydrocarbons than normal coal tar. The coal tar is then further processed into fuels. Alternatively, coal can be converted into a gas first, and then into a liquid, by using the Fischer-Tropsch process. An overview of coal liquefaction and its future potential is available.&lt;ref&gt;Höök, M., Aleklett, K., 2009. A review on coal to liquid fuels and its coal consumption, International Journal of Energy Research, article in press [http://www.tsl.uu.se/uhdsg/Publications/CTL_Article.pdf Link]&lt;/ref&gt;

Coal liquefaction methods involve carbon dioxide ({{CO2}}) emissions in the conversion process. If coal liquefaction is done without employing either [[carbon capture and storage]] (CCS) technologies or biomass blending, the result is lifecycle greenhouse gas footprints that are generally greater than those released in the extraction and refinement of liquid fuel production from [[crude oil]]. If CCS technologies are employed, reductions of 5–12% can be achieved in [[Coal to liquids|Coal to Liquid (CTL)]] plants and up to a 75% reduction is achievable when co-gasifying coal with commercially demonstrated levels of biomass (30% biomass by weight) in coal/bomass-to-liquids plants.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
 | author= Tarka, Thomas J.; Wimer, John G.; Balash, Peter C.; Skone, Timothy J.; Kern, Kenneth C.; Vargas, Maria C.; Morreale, Bryan D.; White III, Charles W.; Gray, David
 | title=Affordable Low Carbon Diesel from Domestic Coal and Biomass
 | publisher= [[United States Department of Energy]], [[National Energy Technology Laboratory]]
 | year=2009
 | page=21}}
&lt;/ref&gt; For future [[synthetic fuel]] projects, [[carbon dioxide sequestration]] is proposed to avoid releasing {{CO2}} into the atmosphere. Sequestration adds to the cost of production. Currently, all US and at least one Chinese synthetic fuel projects,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Shenhua Group Starts China's First Coal-to-Fuel Plant | url=http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601072&amp;sid=a3SIXbVZ8JiE&amp;refer=energy | work=Bloomberg | date=6 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; include sequestration in their process designs.{{fact|date=October 2012}}

=== Refined coal ===
{{Main|Refined coal}}
Refined coal is the product of a coal-upgrading technology that removes moisture and certain pollutants from lower-rank coals such as sub-bituminous and lignite (brown) coals. It is one form of several precombustion treatments and processes for coal that alter coal's characteristics before it is burned. The goals of precombustion coal technologies are to increase efficiency and reduce emissions when the coal is burned. Depending on the situation, precombustion technology can be used in place of or as a supplement to postcombustion technologies to control emissions from coal-fueled boilers.

===Industrial processes {{anchor|Industrial processes}}===
Finely ground bituminous coal, known in this application as sea coal, is a constituent of [[foundry sand]]. While the molten metal is in the [[Molding (process)|mould]], the coal burns slowly, releasing [[Reducing agent|reducing gases]] at pressure, and so preventing the metal from penetrating the pores of the sand. It is also contained in 'mould wash', a paste or liquid with the same function applied to the mould before casting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rao|first=P. N.|title=Manufacturing technology: foundry, forming and welding|publisher=Tata McGraw-Hill|location=New Delhi|year=2007|edition=2|page=107|chapter=Moulding materials|isbn=978-0-07-463180-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sea coal can be mixed with the clay lining (the &quot;bod&quot;) used for the bottom of a [[cupola furnace]]. When heated, the coal decomposes and the bod becomes slightly friable, easing the process of breaking open holes for tapping the molten metal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kirk|first=Edward|title=Cupola Furnace – A Practical Treatise on the Construction and Management of Foundry Cupolas|publisher=Baird|location=Philadelphia, PA|year=1899|page=95|chapter=Cupola management|oclc=2884198}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural usage==
Coal is the [[List of U.S. state minerals, rocks, stones and gemstones|official state mineral]] of [[Kentucky]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kentucky mineral&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sos.ky.gov/kids/all/symbols/mineral.htm|title=Kentucky: Secretary of State – State Mineral|date=20 October 2009|accessdate=7 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the official state rock of [[Utah]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Utah rock&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pioneer.utah.gov/research/utah_symbols/rock.html|title=Utah State Rock – Coal|work=Pioneer: Utah's Online Library|publisher=Utah State Library Division|accessdate=7 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; both [[US state]]s have a historic link to coal mining.

Some cultures hold that children who misbehave will receive only a lump of coal from [[Santa Claus]] for Christmas in their [[christmas stocking]]s instead of presents.

It is also customary and considered lucky in Scotland and the North of England to give coal as a gift on New Year's Day. This occurs as part of [[First-Foot]]ing and represents warmth for the year to come.

==Coal as a traded commodity==
In North America, Central [[Appalachia]]n coal [[futures contract]]s are currently traded on the [[NYMEX|New York Mercantile Exchange]] (trading symbol ''QL''). The trading unit is {{convert|1550|ST|t}} per contract, and is quoted in U.S. dollars and cents per ton. Since coal is the principal fuel for generating electricity in the United States, coal futures contracts provide coal producers and the [[Electrical power industry|electric power industry]] an important tool for [[Hedge (finance)|hedging]] and [[risk management]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=NYMEX.com: Coal | url=http://web.archive.org/web/20080312083033/http://www.nymex.com/coa_fut_descri.aspx| accessdate=16 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to the NYMEX contract, the [[IntercontinentalExchange|IntercontinentalExchange (ICE)]] has European (Rotterdam) and South African (Richards Bay) coal futures available for trading. The trading unit for these contracts is {{convert|5000|t|ST}}, and are also quoted in U.S. dollars and cents per ton.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=ICE: Coal Futures | url=https://www.theice.com/coal.jhtml | accessdate=16 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The price of coal increased from around $30.00 per [[short ton]] in 2000 to around $150.00 per short ton as of September 2008. As of October 2008, the price per short ton had declined to $111.50. Prices further declined to $71.25 as of October 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eia.doe.gov/cneaf/coal/page/coalnews/coalmar.html ''Coal News and Markets (Archive)''] ''[[United States Department of Energy|Department of Energy]]'' – see Bloomberg for realtime prices&lt;/ref&gt;

==Environmental effects==
{{Main|Environmental effects of coal}}
[[File:Aerial view of ash slide site Dec 23 2008 TVA.gov 123002.jpg|thumb|Aerial photograph of Kingston Fossil Plant coal fly ash slurry spill site taken the day after the event]]
A number of adverse health,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lungusa.org/assets/documents/healthy-air/toxic-air-report.pdf Toxic Air: The Case for Cleaning Up Coal-fired Power Plants]. American Lung Association (March 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; and environmental effects of coal burning exist,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucsusa.org/clean_energy/coalvswind/c02c.html Environmental impacts of coal power: air pollution]. Union of Concerned Scientists&lt;/ref&gt; especially in [[power station]]s, and of [[coal mining]], including:

* Coal-fired power plants shortened nearly 24,000 lives a year in the United States, including 2,800 from [[lung cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/5174391/ &quot;Deadly power plants? Study Fuels Debate: Thousands of Early Deaths Tied To Emissions.&quot;] MSNBC (2004-09-06) Retrieved 5 November 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
* Generation of hundreds of millions of tons of waste products, including [[fly ash]], [[bottom ash]], and [[flue-gas desulfurization]] sludge, that contain [[mercury (element)|mercury]], [[uranium]], [[thorium]], [[arsenic]], and other [[heavy metals]]
* [[Acid rain]] from high sulfur coal
* Interference with [[groundwater]] and [[water table]] levels due to mining
* Contamination of land and waterways and destruction of homes from fly ash spills. such as the [[Kingston Fossil Plant coal fly ash slurry spill]]
* Impact of water use on flows of rivers and consequential impact on other land uses
* Dust nuisance
* Subsidence above tunnels, sometimes damaging infrastructure
* Uncontrollable [[coal seam fire]] which may burn for decades or centuries
* Coal-fired power plants without effective fly ash capture systems are one of the largest sources of human-caused [[background radiation]] exposure.
* Coal-fired power plants emit mercury, selenium, and arsenic, which are harmful to human health and the environment.&lt;ref&gt;World Coal Association [http://www.worldcoal.org/pages/content/index.asp?PageID=127 &quot;Environmental impact of Coal Use&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Release of carbon dioxide, a [[greenhouse gas]], causes [[climate change]] and [[global warming]], according to the [[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change|IPCC]] and the [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]]. Coal is the largest contributor to the human-made increase of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.columbia.edu/~jeh1/2007/IowaCoal_20071105.pdf Direct Testimony of James E. Hansen]. State of Iowa&lt;/ref&gt;

== Economic aspects ==
Coal (by liquefaction technology) is one of the [[backstop resources]] that could limit escalation of [[oil prices]] and mitigate the effects of transportation energy shortage that will occur under [[peak oil]]. This is contingent on liquefaction production capacity becoming large enough to satiate the very large and growing demand for petroleum. Estimates of the cost of producing liquid fuels from coal suggest that domestic U.S. production of fuel from coal becomes cost-competitive with oil priced at around $35 per barrel,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Diesel Fuel News: Ultra-clean fuels from coal liquefaction: China about to launch big projects – Brief Article | url=http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0CYH/is_15_6/ai_89924477 |accessdate=9 September 2005 | work=Diesel Fuel News | first=Jack | last=Peckham | year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the $35 being the break-even cost. With oil prices as low as around $40 per barrel in the U.S. as of December 2008, liquid coal lost some of its economic allure in the U.S., but will probably be re-vitalized, similar to [[oil sand]] projects, with an oil price around $70 per barrel.

In China, due to an increasing need for liquid energy in the transportation sector, coal liquefaction projects were given high priority even during periods of oil prices below $40 per barrel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Si Tingting and Li Jing | title=Coal-to-liquids project rescheduled to launch in early 2009 | url=http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/bizchina/2008-12/12/content_7300666.htm |date=12 December 2008 |accessdate=12 December 2008 |newspaper=China Daily}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is probably because China prefers not to be dependent on foreign oil, instead utilizing its enormous domestic coal reserves. As oil prices were increasing during the first half of 2009, the coal liquefaction projects in China were again boosted, and these projects are profitable with an oil barrel price of $40.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Sasol, Shenhua Group May Complete Coal-to-Fuel Plant by 2013 | url=http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&amp;sid=a.MSdPvb0Ep8|accessdate=10 January 2009 | work=Bloomberg | date=7 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

China is by far the largest producer of coal in the world.&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Energy Information Administration. (October 2008). [http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/international/coalproduction.html ''World Coal Production, Most Recent Estimates 1980–2007''].&lt;/ref&gt; It has now become the world's largest energy consumer&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703720504575376712353150310.html?mod=djemalertNEWS|title=China Becomes World's Biggest Energy Consumer|date=19 July 2010|publisher=Wall Street Journal|accessdate=19 July 2010 | first1=Spencer | last1=Swartz | first2=Shai | last2=Oster}}&lt;/ref&gt; but relies on coal to supply about 70% of its energy needs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ecoworld.com/home/articles2.cfm?tid=450|title=China’s Coal|last=Feller|first=Gordon|publisher=ECOworld|accessdate=19 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; An estimated 5 million people work in China's coal-mining industry.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1595235,00.html Where The Coal Is Stained With Blood]&quot;. ''TIME''. 2 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Energy density and carbon impact==
{{See also|Energy value of coal}}
The [[energy density]] of coal, i.e. its [[heating value]], is roughly 24 [[megajoule]]s per kilogram.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Fisher | first = Juliya | title = Energy Density of Coal | work = The Physics Factbook | url = http://hypertextbook.com/facts/2003/JuliyaFisher.shtml|year=2003|accessdate =25 August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; (approximately 6.7 [[kilowatt-hours]] per kg.) For a coal power plant with a 40% efficiency, it takes an estimated {{convert|325|kg|abbr=on}} of coal to power a 100-W lightbulb for one year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title = How much coal is required to run a 100-watt light bulb 24 hours a day for a year?
 | work = Howstuffworks
 | url = http://science.howstuffworks.com/question481.htm
 | accessdate =25 August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2006, the average efficiency of electricity-generating power stations was 31%; in 2002, coal represented about 23% of total global energy supply, an equivalent of 3.4 billion tonnes of coal, of which 2.8 billion tonnes were used for electricity generation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euractiv.com/energy/analysis-efficiency-coal-fired-power-stations-evolution-prospects/article-154672 Analysis: Efficiency of coal-fired power stations – evolution and prospects]. EurActiv. Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The US Energy Information Agency's 1999 report on CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions for energy generation quotes an emission factor of 0.963&amp;nbsp;kg CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/kWh for coal power, compared to  0.881&amp;nbsp;kg CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/kWh (oil), or 0.569&amp;nbsp;kg CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;/kWh (natural gas).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eia.doe.gov/cneaf/electricity/page/co2_report/co2report.html CO2 Carbon Dioxide Emissions from the Generation of Electric Power in the United States, DOE, EPA, 1999]. Eia.doe.gov. Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Underground fires==
{{Main|Coal seam fire}}
Thousands of coal fires are burning around the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Sino German Coal fire project | url=http://www.coalfire.caf.dlr.de/projectareas/world_wide_distribution_en.html | accessdate=9 September 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those burning underground can be difficult to locate and many cannot be extinguished. Fires can cause the ground above to subside, their combustion gases are dangerous to life, and breaking out to the surface can initiate surface [[wildfire]]s. Coal seams can be set on fire by [[spontaneous combustion]] or contact with a [[mine fire]] or surface fire. Lightning strikes are an important source of ignition, the coal continues to burn slowly back into the seam until oxygen (air) can no longer reach the flame front. A grass fire in a coal area can set dozens of coal seams on fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Committee on Resources-Index | url=http://resourcescommittee.house.gov/archives/108/testimony/johnmasterson.htm | accessdate=9 September 2005 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050825231038/http://resourcescommittee.house.gov/archives/108/testimony/johnmasterson.htm |archivedate = 25 August 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Snapshots 2003 |work=fire.blm.gov| url=http://web.archive.org/web/20060218013724/http://www.fire.blm.gov/textdocuments/6-27-03.pdf| accessdate=9 September 2005|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Coal fires in China burn an estimated 120 million tons of coal a year, emitting 360 million metric tons of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, amounting to 2–3% of the annual worldwide production of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; from [[fossil fuels]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=EHP 110-5, 2002: Forum | url=http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/docs/2002/110-5/forum.html | accessdate=9 September 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Overview about ITC's activities in China | url=http://www.itc.nl/personal/coalfire/activities/overview.html | accessdate=9 September 2005 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050616004903/http://www.itc.nl/personal/coalfire/activities/overview.html  |archivedate = 16 June 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Centralia, Pennsylvania]] (a [[Borough (Pennsylvania)|borough]] located in the [[Coal Region]] of the [[United States]]), an exposed vein of anthracite ignited in 1962 due to a trash fire in the borough landfill, located in an abandoned [[anthracite coal|anthracite]] [[Surface mining|strip mine]] pit. Attempts to extinguish the fire were unsuccessful, and it continues to burn underground to this day. The [[Australia]]n [[Burning Mountain]] was originally believed to be a volcano, but the smoke and ash comes from a coal fire that has been burning for some 6,000 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Fire in The Hole | url=http://www.smithsonianmag.com/travel/firehole.html | accessdate=5 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At Kuh i Malik in [[Yagnob Valley]], [[Tajikistan]], coal deposits have been burning for thousands of years, creating vast underground labyrinths full of unique minerals, some of them very beautiful. Local people once used this method to mine [[ammoniac]]. This place has been well-known since the time of [[Herodotus]], but European geographers misinterpreted the Ancient Greek descriptions as the evidence of active [[volcanism]] in [[Turkestan]] (up to the 19th century, when the Russian army invaded the area).{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

The reddish siltstone rock that caps many ridges and buttes in the [[Powder River Basin]] in [[Wyoming]] and in western [[North Dakota]] is called ''porcelanite'', which resembles the coal burning waste &quot;clinker&quot; or volcanic &quot;[[scoria]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=North Dakota's Clinker | url=http://www.state.nd.us/ndgs/ndnotes/ndn13_h.htm | accessdate=9 September 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clinker is rock that has been fused by the natural burning of coal. In the Powder River Basin approximately 27 to 54 billion tons of coal burned within the past three million years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=BLM-Environmental Education- The High Plains | url=http://www.blm.gov/education/high_plains/article.html |accessdate=9 September 2005 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050312133748/http://www.blm.gov/education/high_plains/article.html |archivedate = 12 March 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wild coal fires in the area were reported by the [[Lewis and Clark Expedition]] as well as explorers and settlers in the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Pyrophoricity (spontaneous combustion) of Powder River Basin coals: Considerations for coalbed methane development| url=http://www.wsgs.uwyo.edu/Coal/CR01-1.pdf | accessdate=9 September 2005|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050912063721/http://www.wsgs.uwyo.edu/Coal/CR01-1.pdf|archivedate = 12 September 2005|author=Lyman, Robert M. and Volkmer, John E.|date=March 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Production trends ==
[[File:Us coal regions 1996.png|thumb|Continental United States coal regions]]
[[File:2005coal.png|thumb|right|Coal output in 2005]]
[[File:Coal mine Wyoming.jpg|thumb|A coal mine in [[Wyoming]], [[United States]]. The United States has the world's largest coal reserves.]]

In 2006, [[China]] was the top producer of coal with 38% share followed by the [[United States]] and [[India]], according to the [[British Geological Survey]].

=== World coal reserves ===
The 948 billion short tons of recoverable coal reserves estimated by the Energy Information Administration are equal to about 4,196 BBOE (billion [[barrel of oil equivalent|barrels of oil equivalent]]).&lt;!-- (948,000*0.907186*4.879) --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=EIA International Energy Statistics : Coal : Recoverable Reserves | url=http://205.254.135.7/cfapps/ipdbproject/IEDIndex3.cfm?tid=1&amp;pid=7&amp;aid=6 | accessdate=31 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The amount of coal burned during 2007 was estimated at 7.075 billion short tons, or 133.179 quadrillion BTU's.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=EIA International Energy Statistics : Coal : Consumption | url=http://tonto.eia.doe.gov/cfapps/ipdbproject/IEDIndex3.cfm?tid=1&amp;pid=1&amp;aid=2 |accessdate=10 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is an average of 18.8 million BTU per short ton. In terms of heat content, this is about {{convert|57000000|oilbbl}} of oil equivalent per day.&lt;!-- 133179 trillion BTUs = 20820 MBoe, /365--&gt; By comparison in 2007, natural gas provided {{convert|51000000|oilbbl}} of oil equivalent per day, while oil provided {{convert|85800000|oilbbl|m3}} per day.

[[BP|British Petroleum]], in its 2007 report, estimated at 2006 end that there were 147 years [[reserves-to-production ratio]] based on ''proven'' coal reserves worldwide. This figure only includes reserves classified as &quot;proven&quot;; exploration drilling programs by mining companies, particularly in under-explored areas, are continually providing new reserves. In many cases, companies are aware of coal deposits that have not been sufficiently drilled to qualify as &quot;proven&quot;. However, some nations haven't updated their information and assume reserves remain at the same levels even with withdrawals. Speculative projections predict that global [[peak coal]] production may occur sometime around 2025 at 30 percent above current production, depending on future coal production rates.&lt;ref&gt;''Coal: Resources and Future Production'', 47 page report by Energy Watch group, 28 March 2007 (revised 10 July 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the three fossil fuels, coal has the most widely distributed reserves; coal is mined in over 100 countries, and on all continents except [[Antarctica]]. The largest reserves are found in the [[United States]], [[Russia]], [[China]], [[Australia]] and [[India]]. Note the table below.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;  style=&quot;margin:auto; text-align:right;&quot;
|+ '''Proved recoverable coal reserves at end-2008 (million tons (teragrams))'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldenergy.org/documents/ser_2010_report_1.pdf World Energy Council – Survey of Energy Resources 2010]. (PDF) . Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! style=&quot;width:120pt;&quot;|Country
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|Anthracite &amp; Bituminous
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|SubBituminous
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|Lignite
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|Total
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|Percentage of World Total
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|United States}}||108,501||98,618||30,176||237,295||22.6
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Russia}}||49,088||97,472||10,450||157,010||14.4
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|China}}||62,200||33,700||18,600||114,500||12.6
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Australia}}||37,100||2,100||37,200||76,500||8.9
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|India}}||56,100||0||4,500||60,600||7.0
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Germany}}||99||0||40,600||40,699||4.7
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Ukraine}}||15,351||16,577||1,945||33,873||3.9
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Kazakhstan}}||21,500||0||12,100||33,600||3.9
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|South Africa}}||30,156||0||0||30,156||3.5
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Serbia}}||9||361||13,400||13,770||1.6
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Colombia}}||6,366||380||0||6,746||0.8
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Canada}}||3,474||872||2,236||6,528||0.8
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Poland}}||4,338||0||1,371||5,709||0.7
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Indonesia}}||1,520||2,904||1,105||5,529||0.6
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Brazil}}||0||4,559||0||4,559||0.5
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Greece}}||0||0||3,020||3,020||0.4
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Bosnia and Herzegovina}}||484||0||2,369||2,853||0.3
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Mongolia}}||1,170||0||1,350||2,520||0.3
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Bulgaria}}||2||190||2,174||2,366||0.3
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Pakistan}}||0||166||1,904||2,070||0.3
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Turkey}}||529||0||1,814||2,343||0.3
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Uzbekistan}}||47||0||1,853||1,900||0.2
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Hungary}}||13||439||1,208||1,660||0.2
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Thailand}}||0||0||1,239||1,239||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Mexico}}||860||300||51||1,211||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Iran}}||1,203||0||0||1,203||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Czech Republic}}||192||0||908||1,100||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Kyrgyzstan}}||0||0||812||812||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Albania}}||0||0||794||794||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|North Korea}}||300||300||0||600||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|New Zealand}}||33||205||333-7,000||571–15,000&lt;ref&gt;Alan Sherwood and Jock Phillips. [http://www.TeAra.govt.nz/en/coal-and-coal-mining/2 Coal and coal mining – Coal resources], Te Ara – the Encyclopedia of New Zealand, updated 2009-03-02&lt;/ref&gt;||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Spain}}||200||300||30||530||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Laos}}||4||0||499||503||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Zimbabwe}}||502||0||0||502||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Argentina}}||0||0||500||500||0.1
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|All others||3,421||1,346||846||5,613||0.7
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
![[World]] Total ||404,762||260,789||195,387||860,938||100
|}

=== Major coal producers ===
{{See also|List of countries by coal production}}

The reserve life is an estimate based only on current production levels and proved reserves level for the countries shown, and makes no assumptions of future production or even current production trends. Countries with annual production higher than 100 million tonnes are shown. For comparison, data for the European Union is also shown.
Shares are based on data expressed in tonnes oil equivalent.
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;  style=&quot;margin:auto; text-align:right;&quot;
|+ '''Production of Coal by Country and year (million tonnes)'''
&lt;ref name=&quot;BPReview2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.bp.com/assets/bp_internet/globalbp/globalbp_uk_english/reports_and_publications/statistical_energy_review_2011/STAGING/local_assets/spreadsheets/statistical_review_of_world_energy_full_report_2012.xlsx | title = BP Statistical review of world energy 2012 | publisher = British Petroleum | format = XLS | accessdate =18 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! style=&quot;width:120pt;&quot;|Country
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2003
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2004
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2005
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2006
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2007
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2008
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2009
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2010
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2011
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|Share
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|Reserve Life (years)
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|China}}
| 1834.9
| 2122.6
| 2349.5
| 2528.6
| 2691.6
| 2802.0
| 2973.0
| 3235.0
| 3520.0
| 49.5%
| 35
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|United States}}
| 972.3
| 1008.9
| 1026.5
| 1054.8
| 1040.2
| 1063.0
| 975.2
| 983.7
| 992.8
| 14.1%
| 239
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|India}}
| 375.4
| 407.7
| 428.4
| 449.2
| 478.4
| 515.9
| 556.0
| 573.8
| 588.5
| 5.6%
| 103
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|''{{Flag|European Union}}''
| 637.2
| 627.6
| 607.4
| 595.1
| 592.3
| 563.6
| 538.4
| 535.7
| 576.1
| 4.2%
| 97
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Australia}}
| 350.4
| 364.3
| 375.4
| 382.2
| 392.7
| 399.2
| 413.2
| 424.0
| 415.5
| 5.8%
| 184
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Russia}}
| 276.7
| 281.7
| 298.3
| 309.9
| 313.5
| 328.6
| 301.3
| 321.6
| 333.5
| 4.0%
| 471
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Indonesia}}
| 114.3
| 132.4
| 152.7
| 193.8
| 216.9
| 240.2
| 256.2
| 275.2
| 324.9
| 5.1%
| 17
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|South Africa}}
| 237.9
| 243.4
| 244.4
| 244.8
| 247.7
| 252.6
| 250.6
| 254.3
| 255.1
| 3.6%
| 118
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Germany}}
| 204.9
| 207.8
| 202.8
| 197.1
| 201.9
| 192.4
| 183.7
| 182.3
| 188.6
| 1.1%
| 216
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Poland}}
| 163.8
| 162.4
| 159.5
| 156.1
| 145.9
| 144.0
| 135.2
| 133.2
| 139.2
| 1.4%
| 41
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Kazakhstan}}
| 84.9
| 86.9
| 86.6
| 96.2
| 97.8
| 111.1
| 100.9
| 110.9
| 115.9
| 1.5%
| 290
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! World Total
! 5,301.3
! 5,716.0
! 6,035.3
! 6,342.0
! 6,573.3
! 6,795.0
! 6,880.8
! 7,254.6
! 7,695.4
! 100%
! 112
|}

=== Major coal exporters ===
Countries with annual gross export higher than 10 million tonnes are shown. In terms of net export the largest exporters are still [[Australia]] (328.1 millions tonnes), [[Indonesia]] (316.2) and [[Russia]] (100.2).
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;  style=&quot;margin:auto; text-align:right;&quot;
|+ '''Exports of Coal by Country and year (million short tons)'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eia.doe.gov/oiaf/aeo/supplement/pdf/suptab_114.pdf Table 114. World Metallurgical Coal Flows By Importing Regions and Exporting Countries 1,2/ (million short tons)]. eia.doe.gov&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eia.doe.gov/oiaf/ieo/pdf/coal_tables.pdf World Coal Flows by Importing and Exporting Regions]. Eia.doe.gov. Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://tonto.eia.doe.gov/cfapps/ipdbproject/iedindex3.cfm?tid=1&amp;pid=1&amp;aid=4&amp;cid=&amp;syid=2003&amp;eyid=2008&amp;unit=TST EIA International Energy Annual]. Tonto.eia.doe.gov. Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! style=&quot;width:120pt;&quot;|Country
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2003
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2004
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2005
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2006
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2007
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2008
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2009
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2010
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|Share
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Australia}}
| 238.1
| 247.6
| 255.0
| 255.0
| 268.5
| 278.0
| 288.5
| 328.1
| 27.1%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Indonesia}}
| 107.8
| 131.4
| 142.0
| 192.2
| 221.9
| 228.2
| 261.4
| 316.2
| 26.1%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Russia}}
| 41.0
| 55.7
| 98.6
| 103.4
| 112.2
| 115.4
| 130.9
| 122.1
| 10.1%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|United States}}
| 43.0
| 48.0
| 51.7
| 51.2
| 60.6
| 83.5
| 60.4
| 83.2
| 6.9%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|South Africa}}
| 78.7
| 74.9
| 78.8
| 75.8
| 72.6
| 68.2
| 73.8
| 76.7
| 6.3%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Colombia}}
| 50.4
| 56.4
| 59.2
| 68.3
| 74.5
| 74.7
| 75.7
| 76.4
| 6.3%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Canada}}
| 27.7
| 28.8
| 31.2
| 31.2
| 33.4
| 36.5
| 31.9
| 36.9
| 3.0%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{flag|Kazakhstan}}
| 30.3
| 27.4
| 28.3
| 30.5
| 32.8
| 47.6
| 33.0
| 36.3
| 3.0%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{flag|Vietnam}}
| 6.9
| 11.7
| 19.8
| 23.5
| 35.1
| 21.3
| 28.2
| 24.7
| 2.0%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|China}}
| 103.4
| 95.5
| 93.1
| 85.6
| 75.4
| 68.8
| 25.2
| 22.7
| 1.9%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{flag|Mongolia}}
| 0.5
| 1.7
| 2.3
| 2.5
| 3.4
| 4.4
| 7.7
| 18.3
| 1.5%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{flag|Poland}}
| 28.0
| 27.5
| 26.5
| 25.4
| 20.1
| 16.1
| 14.6
| 18.1
| 1.5%
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! Total
! 713.9
! 764.0
! 936.0
! 1,000.6
! 1,073.4
! 1,087.3
! 1,090.8
! 1,212.8
! 100%
|}

=== Major coal importers ===
Countries with annual gross import higher than 20 million tonnes are shown. In terms of net import the largest importers are still [[Japan]] (206.0 millions tonnes), [[China]] (172.4) and [[South Korea]] (125.8).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eia.gov/cfapps/ipdbproject/iedindex3.cfm?tid=1&amp;pid=1&amp;aid=24&amp;cid=&amp;syid=2006&amp;eyid=2010&amp;unit=TST EIA International Energy Annual: Coal Overview 2010]. Eia.gov. Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;  style=&quot;margin:auto; text-align:right;&quot;
|+ '''Imports of Coal by Country and year (million short tons)'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://tonto.eia.doe.gov/cfapps/ipdbproject/iedindex3.cfm?tid=1&amp;pid=1&amp;aid=3&amp;cid=&amp;syid=2006&amp;eyid=2008&amp;unit=TST International Energy Annual]. Tonto.eia.doe.gov. Retrieved on 24 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! style=&quot;width:140pt;&quot;|Country
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2006
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2007
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2008
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2009
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|2010
! style=&quot;width:100pt;&quot;|Share
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Japan}}
| 199.7
| 209.0
| 206.0
| 182.1
| 206.7
| 17.5%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|China}}
| 42.0
| 56.2
| 44.5
| 151.9
| 195.1
| 16.6%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|South Korea}}
| 84.1
| 94.1
| 107.1
| 109.9
| 125.8
| 10.7%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|India}}
| 52.7
| 29.6
| 70.9
| 76.7
| 101.6
| 8.6%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Taiwan}}
| 69.1
| 72.5
| 70.9
| 64.6
| 71.1
| 6.0%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Germany}}
| 50.6
| 56.2
| 55.7
| 45.9
| 55.1
| 4.7%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Turkey}}
| 22.9
| 25.8
| 21.7
| 22.7
| 30.0
| 2.5%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|United Kingdom}}
| 56.8
| 48.9
| 49.2
| 42.2
| 29.3
| 2.5%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Italy}}
| 27.9
| 28.0
| 27.9
| 20.9
| 23.7
| 1.9%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Netherlands}}
| 25.7
| 29.3
| 23.5
| 22.1
| 22.8
| 1.9%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|Russia}}
| 28.8
| 26.3
| 34.6
| 26.8
| 21.8
| 1.9%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|France}}
| 24.1
| 22.1
| 24.9
| 18.3
| 20.8
| 1.8%
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|{{Flag|United States}}
| 40.3
| 38.8
| 37.8
| 23.1
| 20.6
| 1.8%
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! Total
! 991.8
! 1,056.5
! 1,063.2
! 1,039.8
! 1,178.1
! 100%
|}
{{Energy country lists|state=collapsed}}

== See also ==
{{Portal|Energy}}
{{div col|3}}
* [[Asphaltene]]
* [[Biochar]]
* [[Biobased economy|Biomass-coal]]
* [[Carbochemistry]]
* [[Clean coal]]
* [[Coal assay]]
* [[Coal dust]]
* [[Coal Measure]] (stratigraphic unit)
* [[Coal mining]]
* [[Coal phase out]]
* [[Coal-tar]]
* [[Coalbed methane]]
* [[Fluidized bed combustion]]
* [[Major coal producing regions]]
* [[Mountaintop removal mining]]
*[[Tonstein]]
* [[The Coal Question]]
* [[World Coal Association]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | last = Walter Licht| first = Thomas Dublin| year = 2005 | title = The Face of Decline: The Pennsylvania Anthracite Region in the Twentieth Century | publisher = Cornell University Press | isbn = 0-8014-8473-1 | oclc = 60558740}}
* {{cite book |last= Long|first= Priscilla |title= Where the Sun Never Shines: A History of America's Bloody Coal Industry |year= 1991 |publisher= Paragon House |location= New York, NY |isbn= 1-55778-465-5 |oclc= 25236866 }}
* {{cite book | last = Rottenberg | first = Dan | year = 2003 | title = In the Kingdom of Coal; An American Family and the Rock That Changed the World | publisher = Routledge | isbn = 0-415-93522-9 | oclc = 52348860}}
* {{cite journal | author=Robert H. Williams and Eric D. Larson | title=A comparison of direct and indirect liquefaction technologies for making fluid fuels from coal | journal=Energy for Sustainable Development | month=December | year=2003 | volume=VII | pages=103–129 | url= http://www.ieiglobal.org/ESDVol7No4/dclversussicl.pdf | format = PDF}}
* {{cite book |last= Outwater |first= Alice |title= Water: A Natural History |year= 1996 |publisher= Basic Books |location= New York, NY |isbn= 0-465-03780-1 |oclc= 37785911 }}
* {{cite book |last= Smith |first= Duane A. |title= Mining America: The Industry and the Environment, 1800–1980 |year= 1993 |month= May |publisher= University Press of Kansas |location= Lawrence, KS |isbn= 0-87081-306-4 |page= 210}}
* {{cite book |last = Freese |first = Barbara|title = Coal: A Human History|year = 2003|publisher=Penguin Books|isbn = 0-7382-0400-5 |oclc = 51449422}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|Coal}}
{{Wiktionary}}

* [http://www.coalonline.org/site/coalonline/content/home Coal Online – International Energy Agency]
* [http://tonto.eia.doe.gov/kids/energy.cfm?page=coal_home-basics Energy KIDS – Coal page] from U. S. [http://www.energy.gov Department of Energy].
* [http://www.euracoal.org/ European Association for Coal and Lignite]
* [http://www.worldcoal.org/ World Coal Association]

{{Coal}}
{{electricity generation}}

[[Category:Coal| ]]
[[Category:Coal mining]]
[[Category:Economic geology]]
[[Category:Fuels]]
[[Category:Sedimentary rocks]]
[[Category:Solid fuels]]
[[Category:Symbols of Kentucky]]
[[Category:Symbols of Utah]]

{{Link GA|ja}}

[[af:Steenkool]]
[[ar:فحم حجري]]
[[an:Carbón]]
[[as:কয়লা]]
[[ast:Carbón]]
[[ay:K'illima]]
[[az:Daş kömür]]
[[bn:কয়লা]]
[[bjn:Batu arang]]
[[zh-min-nan:Thô͘-thoàⁿ]]
[[be:Вугаль]]
[[be-x-old:Вугаль]]
[[bg:Каменни въглища]]
[[bs:Ugalj]]
[[br:Glaou]]
[[ca:Carbó]]
[[cs:Uhlí]]
[[cy:Glo]]
[[da:Kul (bjergart)]]
[[pdc:Kohl]]
[[de:Kohle]]
[[nv:Tsékǫʼ]]
[[et:Kivisüsi]]
[[el:Γαιάνθρακας (καύσιμο)]]
[[es:Carbón]]
[[eo:Terkarbo]]
[[eu:Harrikatz]]
[[fa:زغال‌ سنگ]]
[[fr:Charbon]]
[[fur:Cjarbon]]
[[ga:Gual]]
[[gd:Gual]]
[[gl:Carbón]]
[[ko:석탄]]
[[hy:Ածուխ]]
[[hi:कोयला]]
[[hr:Ugljen]]
[[io:Karbono]]
[[id:Batu bara]]
[[is:Kol]]
[[it:Carbone]]
[[he:פחם]]
[[jv:Batu bara]]
[[ka:ნახშირი (წიაღისეული)]]
[[kk:Көмір]]
[[sw:Makaa mawe]]
[[ht:Chabon]]
[[lbe:ХъуручӀ]]
[[la:Carbo]]
[[lv:Akmeņogles]]
[[lt:Akmens anglis]]
[[lmo:Carbun]]
[[hu:Kőszén]]
[[mk:Јаглен]]
[[ml:കൽക്കരി]]
[[mr:कोळसा]]
[[ms:Arang batu]]
[[mn:Нүүрс]]
[[my:ကျောက်မီးသွေး]]
[[nah:Teconalli]]
[[nl:Steenkool]]
[[ne:कोइला]]
[[new:ह्यंग्वा]]
[[ja:石炭]]
[[no:Kull]]
[[nn:Kol]]
[[nov:Karbone]]
[[oc:Carbon]]
[[pnb:کولہ]]
[[ps:ډبرين سکاره]]
[[pcd:Carbon]]
[[pl:Węgle kopalne]]
[[pt:Carvão mineral]]
[[ro:Cărbune]]
[[qu:K'illimsa]]
[[ru:Ископаемый уголь]]
[[sq:Qymyri]]
[[scn:Cravuni]]
[[simple:Coal]]
[[sk:Uhlie]]
[[sl:Premog]]
[[sr:Угаљ]]
[[sh:Ugljen]]
[[su:Batubara]]
[[fi:Kivihiili]]
[[sv:Kol (bränsle)]]
[[tl:Karbon (bato)]]
[[ta:நிலக்கரி]]
[[te:బొగ్గు]]
[[th:ถ่านหิน]]
[[tg:Ангишт]]
[[chy:Ho'ose]]
[[tr:Kömür]]
[[uk:Кам'яне вугілля]]
[[ur:کوئلہ]]
[[vec:Carbon]]
[[vi:Than đá]]
[[wa:Hoye]]
[[war:Uring]]
[[zh-yue:煤]]
[[zh:煤]]</text>
      <sha1>iugjifrkmq4j1a6b1b122p2c557doc6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
