<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Eco-terrorism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>303522</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514123100</id>
      <parentid>513339145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-23T05:48:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anderson76</username>
        <id>12896963</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25522">{{For|terrorist attacks directed against the environment|environmental terrorism}}
[[File:ELFMexico.jpg|thumb|right|240px|On March 23, 2009, The [[Earth Liberation Front]] claim the burning of a backhoe in [[Guadalajara, Jalisco]], [[Mexico]]. In one of many recent anonymous communiques, the ELF reported to ''[[Bite Back]]''; ''&quot;Maybe we have not collapsed the system of domination with these actions, but it begins with actions like these.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;elf2008&quot;&gt;[http://www.elfpressoffice.org/actions20062008.html Diary of Earth Liberation Actions 2006-2008], ''[[Earth Liberation Front Press Office]]'', 2006-2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.directaction.info/news_mar23_09.htm Earth-destroying machine burned], ''[[Bite Back]]'', March 23, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elfpressoffice.org/comm032209.html Earth Liberation Front Communique: 03.22.09], ''[[Earth Liberation Front Press Office]]'', March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;elf2009&quot;&gt;[http://www.elfpressoffice.org/actions2009.html Diary of Earth Liberation Actions 2009], ''[[Earth Liberation Front Press Office]]'', 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{terrorism}}
'''Eco-terrorism''' usually refers to acts of [[violence]] or [[sabotage]] committed in support of [[political ecology|ecological]], [[environmentalism|environmental]], or [[animal rights]] causes against persons or their property.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/ecoterrorism |publisher=Thefreedictionary.com |accessdate=2010-10-02
 |title=ecoterrorism - definition of ecoterrorism by the Free Online Dictionary, Thesaurus and Encyclopedia
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ecoterrorism
 |title=Ecoterrorism - Definition and More from the Free Merriam-Webster Dictionary |publisher=Merriam-webster.com
 |date=2010-08-13 |accessdate=2010-10-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eco-terrorism is defined by the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] as &quot;the use or threatened use of violence of a criminal nature against people or property by an environmentally oriented, subnational group for environmental-political reasons, or aimed at an audience beyond the target, often of a symbolic nature.&quot;&lt;ref name=CT/&gt;  The FBI has credited to eco-terrorism 300 million dollars in property damage from 2003 and 2008, and a majority of states within the USA have introduced laws aimed at these activities.&lt;ref name=BaldwinSW&gt;{{Citation
 |author=Brent Baldwin |publication-date=February 6, 2008 |title=Wade's War |periodical=Style Weekly
 |url=http://www.styleweekly.com/article.asp?idarticle=16293 |archivedate=March 24, 2008
 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080324141543/http://www.styleweekly.com/article.asp?idarticle=16293
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of this use of the term argue that it has been defined in order to vilify activists,&lt;ref name=smith&gt;REBECCA K. SMITH &quot;Ecoterrorism&quot;? A critical analysis of the vilification of radical environmental activists as terrorists. Published in Environmental Law 22 march 08 and reproduced http://legacy.lclark.edu/org/envtl/objects/38-2_Smith.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Videl&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2008/apr/03/greenbuilding.ethicalliving | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=The green scare | first=John | last=Vidal | date=April 3, 2008 | accessdate=May 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that the term would be more properly employed to describe the environmentally damaging activities of [[corporation]]s.&lt;ref name=Videl/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;“the real eco-terrorism is being committed every day by corporate America&quot; [[Paul Watson]] quoted in Eagan, SP. From spikes to bombs: the rise of eco-terrorism. Studies in conflict and terrorism 19 (1996): 1-18. Print. Page 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Indy&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=The Birth of a Buzz Word: Eco-Terrorism|url=http://www.indypendent.org/2007/09/15/the-birth-of-a-buzz-word-eco-terrorism/|accessdate=2 October 2010|newspaper=The Indypendent|date=September 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Application of the term ==
Eco-terrorism is a form of [[radical environmentalism]] that arose out of the same school of thought that brought about [[deep ecology]], [[ecofeminism]], [[social ecology]], and [[bioregionalism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;&gt;Long, Douglas. Ecoterrorism (Library in a Book). New York: Facts on File, 2004. Print. Page 19-22, 5, 5, 6, 6, 7, 154, 154, 48, 49-55.&lt;/ref&gt; Eco-terrorism is a controversial term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Komp |first=Catherine |url=http://newstandardnews.net/content/?action=show_item&amp;itemid=2779 |title=Vilified as ‘Terrorists,’ Eco-activists Face New Offensive by Business* - The NewStandard |publisher=Newstandardnews.net |date= |accessdate=2010-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eco-terrorism is closely related to [[civil disobedience]] and [[sabotage]] [[Ecotage|in the name of the environment]], and there is a debate on where to draw the lines between the three.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; Some of those who are labeled as eco-terrorists do not perpetrate violence against humans, but only against property. This has led to a debate that touches on whether or not to classify these actions as &quot;terrorist&quot;. In the United States, the FBI’s definition includes acts of violence against property, which makes most acts of sabotage fall in the realm of [[domestic terrorism]], even if they are not designed to induce terror, which is the dictionary definition of terrorism.

Sabotage involves destroying, or threatening to destroy, property, and in this case is also known as [[monkeywrenching]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; or [[ecotage]].&lt;ref&gt;Plows, A., Wall, D. &amp; Doherty, B., (2004) ‘Covert Repertoires: ecotage in the UK’ in Social Movement Studies, vol. 3, iss. 2, pp. 199 – 219&lt;/ref&gt; Many acts of sabotage involve the damage of equipment and unmanned facilities using [[arson]].

==Examples of tactics==
There are a wide variety of tactics that have been used by eco-terrorists and groups associated with eco-terrorism. Examples include:

* [[Tree spiking]] is a common tactic that was first used by members of EarthFirst! in 1984. Tree spiking involves hammering a small spike into the trunk of a tree that may be logged with the intention of damaging the chainsaw or mill blades and may seriously injure the logger. Only one case of serious injury has been widely reported.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt;

* [[Arson]] is a tactic most associated with recent activity in the [[Earth Liberation Front]] (ELF). The ELF has been attributed with arsons of sites such as housing developments, SUV dealerships, and chain stores.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt;

* [[Bombing]] is an extreme tactic used by eco-terrorists.  In 1982, [[Chaïm Nissim]], a radical ecologist militant with links to [[Carlos the Jackal]], fired five rockets at [[Superphénix]], then under construction.

==Groups accused of eco-terrorism==
Organizations accused of eco-terrorism are generally [[Grassroots|grassroots organizations]], do not have a hierarchal structure, and typically favor [[direct action]] approaches to their goals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eagan&quot;&gt;Eagan, SP. From spikes to bombs: the rise of eco-terrorism. Studies in conflict and terrorism/eco terrorism 19 (1996): 1-18. Print. Page 2&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Dr. Stefan Leader]] characterizes these groups, namely ELF, with having &quot;leaderless resistance&quot; which he describes as “a technique by which terrorist groups can carry out violent acts while reducing the risk of infiltration by law enforcement elements. The basic {{sic|principal}} of leaderless resistance is that there is no centralized authority or chain-of-command.”&lt;ref name = &quot;Leader&quot; &gt;Leader, Stefan H., and Peter Probst. THE EARTH LIBERATION FRONT AND ENVIRONMENTAL TERRORISM. Google. Web. 23 November 2009. http://google.com/scholar?q=cache:udk9yYLxD6QJ:scholar.google.com/+The+Earth+Liberation+front+and+Environmental+Terrorism&amp;hl=en.&lt;/ref&gt; Essentially this consists of independent cells which operate autonomously, sharing goals, but having no central leaders or formal organizational structure. Those who wish to join are typically encouraged to start their own cell, rather than seek out other members and jeopardize their secrecy.&lt;ref&gt;Leader &amp; Probst, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Organizations that have been accused of eco-terrorism in the United States include the [[Animal Liberation Front]] (ALF),&lt;ref name=CT&gt;{{Citation |author=James F. Jarboe |year=2002 |month=February
 |title=Testimony of James F. Jarboe, Domestic Terrorism Section Chief, Counterterrorism Division, FBI before the House Resources Committee, Subcommittee on Forests and Forest Health at February 12, 2002 &quot;The Threat of Eco-Terrorism&quot;
 |work=Congressional Testimony |publisher=[[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] |archivedate=March 11, 2008
 |url=http://www.fbi.gov/congress/congress02/jarboe021202.htm |accessdate=March 2008&lt;!-- inferred from Wikiblame search --&gt;
 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080311231725/http://www.fbi.gov/congress/congress02/jarboe021202.htm
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Earth Liberation Front]] (ELF),&lt;ref name=CT/&gt; [[Greenpeace]], the [[Sea Shepherd]] Conservation Society, People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals (PETA), [[Earth First!]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; The Coalition to Save the Preserves.&lt;ref name=&quot;FBI testimony&quot;/&gt; and the Hardesty Avengers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avengers&quot;&gt;Wyant, Dan. &quot;Spike Hunt is Battling a Deadline.&quot; ''The Register-Guard'' [Eugene, Oregon] 28 Oct. 1984. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2010 The FBI were criticized in [[US Justice Department]] reports for unjustified surveillance (and placement on the Terrorism Watchlist) between 2001 and 2006 of members of Animal Rights groups such as Greenpeace and PETA.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABCFBI&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=FBI Spied on PETA, Greenpeace, anti-war activists|url=http://abcnews.go.com/News/Blotter/fbi-spied-peta-greenpeace-anti-war-activists/story?id=11682844|accessdate=11 October 2010|newspaper=[[ABC News]]|date=September 20, 2010|author=Cloherty, Jack|author2=Ryan, Jason}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2002 testimony to the US Congress, an FBI official mentioned the actions of [[Sea Shepherd Conservation Society]] in the context of eco-terrorism.&lt;ref name=CT/&gt;  The Sea Shepherd Conservation Society intervenes against [[whaling]], seal hunting, and fishing operations with direct action tactics. In 1986, the group caused nearly 1.8 million dollars worth of damage to equipment used by whalers in Iceland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; In 1992, they sabotaged two Japanese ships that were drift-net fishing for squid by cutting their nets and throwing stink bombs on board the boats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eagan&quot;/&gt;

Inspired by Edward Abbey, Earth First! began in 1980. Although the group has been credited with becoming more mainstream, its use of [[tree spiking]] during campaigns has been associated with the origins of eco-terrorism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.boston.com/news/nation/washington/articles/2006/01/21/justice_dept_accuses_11_of_us_eco_terrorism/|title=Justice Dept. accuses 11 of US eco-terrorism|last=Savage|first=Charlie|date=January 21, 2006|work=The Boston Globe|accessdate=January 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, a jury found that FBI agents and Oakland police officers violated constitutional rights to free speech and protection from unlawful searches of two Earth First! organizers accused of a 1990 car bombing. Authorities alleged that the bomb was in the car of one of the accused when it accidentally detonated. The pair sued investigators, alleging false arrest, illegal search, slanderous statements and conspiracy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2002/06/12/MN87302.DTL|title= After 11 years, jury vindicates Earth First pair FBI, Oakland officers must pay $4.4 million for civil rights abuses |last=Zamora|first=Jim Hermon|date=June 12, 2002|work=San Francisco Chronicle|accessdate=January 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Earth Liberation Front, founded in 1992, joined with the Animal Liberation Front, which had its beginnings in England in 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; They have been connected primarily with arson but claim that they work to harm neither human nor animal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; A recent example of arson that was attributed to the ELF was in March 2008 concerning the &quot;torching of luxury homes in the swank Seattle suburb of Woodiness&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOX&quot;&gt;&quot;FBI: Eco-Terrorism Remains No. 1 Domestic Terror Threat - Local News | News Articles | National News | US News - FOXNews.com.&quot; Breaking News | Latest News | Current News - Fox News.com. 31 March 2008. Web. 23 Nov. 2009. http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,343768,00.html.&lt;/ref&gt; A banner was left at the scene that claimed the housing development was not green as advertised, and was signed ELF.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;&gt;Yardley, William. &quot;The New York Times Log In.&quot; ''The New York Times'' - Breaking News, World News &amp; Multimedia. 4 Mar. 2008. Web. 23 Nov. 2009. http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/04/us/04homes.html?_r=3.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2009 ELF claimed responsibility for the destruction of two radio towers in Seattle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Activists topple towers, claim dangers of AM radio waves|url=http://articles.cnn.com/2009-09-04/justice/washington.towers.terrorism_1_elf-radio-station-radio-waves?_s=PM:CRIME|publisher=CNN|accessdate=1 August 2012|date=4 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] in 2001 named the ELF as &quot;one of the most active extremist elements in the United States&quot;, and a &quot;terrorist threat&quot;,.&lt;ref name=CT/&gt; The [[Coalition to Save the Preserves]] was mentioned in FBI testimony as a group that was responsible for a series of arsons in Arizona. Using similar tactics to the ELF, they have caused more than $5 million in damages.&lt;ref name=&quot;FBI testimony&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Jarboe|first=James F.|title=Testimony of James F. Arbores, Domestic Terrorism Section Chief, Counter terrorism Division, FBI Before the House Resources Committee, Subcommittee on Forests and Forest Health|url=http://www.fbi.gov/congress/congress02/jarboe021202.htm|accessdate=2 October 2010|newspaper=Federal Bureau of Investigation|date=February 12, 2002}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Media reports have tied [[Theodore Kaczynski]], also known as the Una bomber, to environmental activists, and say that the 23 injuries and three deaths through letter-bombs were the acts of an independent Eco-terrorist. Among those making such accusations were ABC, ''The New York Times'', ''Time'' magazine, and ''USA Today''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=1360 |title=&quot;Exploding ABC's Uni bomber Hoax.&quot; Fairness and Accuracy in Media (FAIR), June 1996 |publisher=FAIR |date= |accessdate=2012-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of &quot;local&quot; organizations have also been indicted under US Federal laws related to Eco-terrorism. These include, among others, the group &quot;[[Stop Huntington Animal Cruelty]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usdoj.gov/usao/nj/press/files/shac0526_r.htm ]{{dead link|date=March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Hornebeagles.jpg|right|thumb|An [[Animal Liberation Front|ALF]] raid removing 82 beagles and 26 rabbits from [[Harlan (company)|Interfauna]] in Cambridge on [[Saint Patrick|St Patrick's Night]] 1990.&lt;ref name=Arkangel&gt;[http://www.directaction.info/barry/barry.htm &quot;The man, the activist&quot;], first published in ''[[Arkangel (magazine)|Arkangel]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;]] Another example is the Hardesty Avengers who spiked trees in the Hardesty Mountains in Willamette National Forest in 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avengers&quot;/&gt;

==Philosophy of eco-terrorism==
The thought behind eco-terrorism rises from the [[radical environmentalism]] movement, which gained popularity during the 1960s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; Ideas that arose from radical environmentalism are “based on the belief that capitalism, patriarchal society, and the Judeo-Christian tradition were responsible for the despoliation of nature”.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; Radical environmentalism is also characterized by the belief that human society is responsible for the depletion of the environment and, if current society is left unchecked, will lead to the ultimate complete degradation of the environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dunlap&quot;&gt;Dunlap. &quot;Deep Ecology and Radical Environmentalism.&quot; American environmentalism the U.S. environmental movement, 1970-1990. Philadelphia: Taylor &amp; Francis, 1992. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;

Like [[Deep ecology|deep ecologists]], eco-terrorists subscribe to the idea of [[biocentrism (ethics)|biocentrism]], which is described as “a belief that human beings are just an ordinary member of the biological community” and that all living things should have rights and deserve protection under the law.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eagan&quot;/&gt; Some eco-terrorists are motivated by other aspects of deep ecology, like the goal to return the environment to its &quot;natural&quot;, i.e., pre-industrial, state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leader&quot;/&gt;

Despite these generalizations, it should be noted that eco-terrorism encompasses a broad array of organizations, goals, and philosophies.

==Government response in the USA==
Spiking trees became a federal offense in the United States when it was added to the Drug Act in 1988.&lt;ref name=&quot;Code&quot;&gt;Office of the Law Revision Counsel. Web. 23 Nov. 2009. http://uscode.house.gov/download/pls/18C91.txt&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the [[Animal Enterprise Protection Act]] of 1992 it became a federal crime to “cause more than $10,000 in damage while engaged in “physical disruption to the functioning of an animal enterprise by intentionally stealing, damaging, or causing the loss of any property…used by the animal enterprise.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Long&quot;/&gt; In 2006, this was updated and renamed the [[Animal Enterprise Terrorism Act]] by the 109th congress.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bill&quot;&gt;Read The Bill: S. 3880 [109th] - GovTrack.us.&quot; GovTrack.us: Tracking the U.S. Congress. Web. 23 Nov. 2009. http://www.govtrack.us/congress/billtext.xpd?bill=s109-3880&lt;/ref&gt; The updated act included causing personal harm and the losses incurred on “secondary targets” as well as adding to the penalties for these crimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;FBI Main&quot;&gt;&quot;FBI Eco-Terrorism - Press Room - Headline Archives 06-30-08.&quot; FBI Federal Bureau of Investigation Homepage. Web. 23 Nov. 2009. http://www.fbi.gov/page2/june08/ecoterror_063008.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, a conservative Texas legislative reform group, the [[American Legislative Exchange Council]] (ALEC), proposed the &quot;Animal and Ecological Terrorism Act&quot; which defined an &quot;animal rights or ecological terrorist organization&quot; as &quot;two or more persons organized for the purpose of supporting any politically motivated activity intended to obstruct or deter any person from participating in an activity involving animals or an activity involving natural resources.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20051225091755/http://www.alec.org/news/press-releases/press-releases-2003/september/alec-offers-legislation-to-fight-domestic-terror-by-animal-rights-and-eco-extremist-groups.html ALEC - Animal and Ecological Terrorism Act]&lt;/ref&gt; The legislation was not enacted.

The FBI has stated that “since 2005…investigations have resulted in indictments against 30 individuals.” In 2006, an FBI case labeled ‘[[Operation Backfire (FBI)|Operation Backfire]]’ brought charges of domestic terrorism to eleven people associated with the ELF and ALF. “The indictment includes charges related to arson, conspiracy, use of destructive devices, and destruction of an energy facility.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Press Room&quot;&gt;&quot;Federal Bureau of Investigation - Press Room - Headline Archives - Eco-Terror Indictments.&quot; FBI Federal Bureau of Investigation Homepage. Web. 23 Nov. 2009. http://www.fbi.gov/page2/jan06/elf012006.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the Bush Justice Department, including the FBI, was recently criticized for improper investigations and prosecutions of left-leaning U.S. protest groups such as Greenpeace. The [[Washington Post]] reports that the &quot;FBI improperly opened and extended investigations of some U.S. activist groups and put members of an environmental advocacy organization on a terrorist watch list, even though they were planning nonviolent civil disobedience, the Justice Department said Monday.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/09/20/AR2010092003100.html?hpid=topnews |title=&quot;FBI probes were improper, Justice says&quot; Washington Post, Monday, September 20, 2010 |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |date= 21 September 2010|accessdate=2012-03-21 |first=Jerry |last=Markon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A report, filed by Inspector General Glenn A. Fine, found the FBI to be not guilty of the most serious charge—according to the Post, that &quot;agents targeted domestic groups based on their exercise of First Amendment rights.&quot; The investigation was conducted in response to allegations that the FBI had targeted groups on such grounds during the Bush Administration. The ''Post'' has more:

&quot;But the report cited what it called other &quot;troubling&quot; FBI practices in its monitoring of domestic groups in the years between the Sept. 11, 2001, terrorist attacks and 2006. In some cases, Fine said, agents began investigations of people affiliated with activist groups for &quot;factually weak&quot; reasons and &quot;without adequate basis&quot; and improperly kept information about activist groups in its files. Among the groups monitored were the Thomas Merton Center, a Pittsburgh peace group; People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals; and Greenpeace USA. Activists affiliated with Greenpeace were improperly put on a terrorist watch list, the report said.&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost.com&quot;/&gt;

In 2008, [[Eric McDavid]] was convicted of plotting to attack several targets including a fish hatchery, a dam, power stations, and cell phone towers. An undercover FBI agent exposed the plan. In addition to McDavid, two others were also convicted for aiding with the plot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters&quot;&gt;O-Callagahn, John. &quot;U.S. man jailed for 20 years for eco-bombing plot | U.S. | Reuters.&quot; Reuters.com - World News, Financial News, Breaking US &amp; International News. 8 May 2008. Web. 24 Nov. 2009. http://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSN0843592020080509&lt;/ref&gt; On March 6, 2008 Eric McDavid was sentenced to 20 years in prison for “conspiracy to damage or destroy property by fire and explosive.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Prison&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Scott|first=McGregor W.|title=Eco-terrorist given nearly twenty years in prison|url=http://google.com/search?q=cache%3AXHyL_l_5dikJ%3Asacramento.fbi.gov%2Fdojpressrel%2Fpressrel08%2Fsc050808.pdf+http%3A%2F%2Fsacramento.fbi.gov%2Fdojpressrel%2Fpressrel08%2Fsc050808.pdf&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us|work=United States Department of Justice|accessdate=2 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; United States Attorney McGregor Scott stated: “Today’s severe punishment of nearly 20 years in federal prison should serve as a cautionary tale to those who would conspire to commit life-threatening acts in the name of their extremist views.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Prison&quot;/&gt;

===Individuals accused of eco-terrorism===
*[[Eric McDavid]] – Convicted of conspiracy to commit what the FBI labeled an eco-terrorist plot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cbs13.com/local/eco.terrorist.Eric.2.483155.html |title=Man Convicted Of Plotting To Blow Up Nimbus Dam |publisher=cbs13.com |date=2007-09-27 |accessdate=2010-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Daniel G. McGowan|Daniel McGowan]] – Convicted of participation in an arson at a lumber company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Grigoriadis |first=Vanessa |url=http://nymag.com/news/intelligencer/33544/ |title=Daniel McGowan Becomes the First New Yorker Convicted of Ecoterrorism - New York Magazine |publisher=Nymag.com |date=2007-06-18 |accessdate=2010-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Discovery Communications headquarters hostage crisis|James Lee]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Background Report&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.start.umd.edu/start/announcements/Background_Report_Discovery_building.pdf|title=Background Report: Discovery Communications Building Hostage-Taking|publisher=Start|page=1|accessdate=4 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Tre Arrow]]
*[[Marie Mason]]
*[[Jeff Luers]]

==See also==
*[[Agro-terrorism]]
*[[Environmental Terrorism]]
*[[Ecotage]]
*[[Ecoterrorism in fiction]]
*[[Green Scare]]
*[[THERMCON]] – [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] operation against the &quot;Evan Mecham Eco-Terrorist International Conspiracy&quot; (EMETIC)
*[[Operation Backfire (FBI)|Operation Backfire]] – [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] operation
*[[Tree spiking]]
*[[Earth Liberation Prisoners Support Network]]

=== Ideologies ===
*[[Agro-terrorism]]
*[[Anarcho-primitivism]]
*[[Direct action]]
*[[Green anarchism]]
*[[Radical environmentalism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Gagliano Giuseppe, ''Il ritorno alla madre terra.L'utopia verde tra ecologia radicale e ecoterrorismo'' (Uniservice Press, 2010) ISBN 
* {{cite journal|last=Govern|first=Kevin|year=2009|title=Agroterrorism and Ecoterrorism: A Survey of Indo- American Approaches Under Law and Policy to Prevent and Defend Against the Potential Threats Ahead|journal=Fl. Coastal L. Rev.|volume=10|pages=223–261|url=https://www.fcsl.edu/sites/fcsl.edu/files/govern.pdf}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Eco-Terrorism}}
[[Category:Dysphemisms]]
[[Category:Eco-terrorism| ]]
[[Category:Green anarchism]]
[[Category:Political neologisms]]

[[be:Экатэрарызм]]
[[ceb:Ekoterorismo]]
[[cs:Ekoterorismus]]
[[de:Ökoterrorismus]]
[[et:Ökoterrorism]]
[[es:Ecoterrorismo]]
[[fr:Écoterrorisme]]
[[it:Ecoterrorismo]]
[[he:טרור אקולוגי]]
[[kk:Экологиялық терроризм]]
[[lt:Ekoterorizmas]]
[[ja:エコテロリズム]]
[[pl:Ekoterroryzm]]
[[pt:Ecoterrorismo]]
[[ru:Экологический терроризм]]
[[sk:Ekoterorizmus]]
[[sr:Екотероризам]]
[[sv:Ekoterrorism]]
[[tl:Ekoterorismo]]
[[uk:Екотероризм]]
[[zh:生態恐怖主義]]</text>
      <sha1>04977ea7cktfrnq70byrmwr6fjdbz2g</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
