<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Environmental vegetarianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2858505</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519471884</id>
      <parentid>519469177</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T22:39:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Citation needed}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15936">'''Environmental vegetarianism''' is the practice of [[vegetarianism]] or [[vegan]]ism based on the indications that animal production, particularly by [[Intensive farming|intensive agriculture]], is [[Natural environment|environmentally]] [[sustainable development|unsustainable]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/27/weekinreview/27bittman.html?_r=1&amp;scp=2&amp;sq=Rethinking+the+Meat-Guzzler&amp;st=nyt&amp;oref=slogin New York Time's Article: Rethinking the Meat-Guzzler]&lt;/ref&gt; The primary environmental concerns with animal products are [[pollution]] and the use of resources such as [[fossil fuel]]s, [[Water crisis|water]], and land.

==Environmental impact of meat production==
{{Main|Environmental impact of meat production}}[[Image:Sources of dietary energy-consumtion (%) 2001-2003 (FAO).svg|thumb|400px|right|The predictable increase in [[animal product]] proportions on the plates of people living in [[Developing country|developing countries]] will bring new challenges to global [[agriculture]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://faostat.fao.org/Portals/_Faostat/documents/pdf/sources_of_dietary_energy_consumption.pdf fao report]&lt;/ref&gt; ]]
[[Image:Hog confinement barn interior.jpg|thumb|right|Interior of a hog confinement barn or piggery]]
Industrial [[monoculture]] is harvesting large quantities of a single food species, such as maize, or cattle. Monoculture is commonly practiced in [[industrial agriculture]], which is more environmentally damaging than sustainable farming practices such as [[organic farming]], [[permaculture]], [[arable land|arable]], [[pastoral]], and rain-fed agriculture.&lt;ref&gt;Public health benefits of strategies to reduce greenhouse-gas emissions: food and agriculture http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0140673609617530&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a 2006 [[Food and Agriculture Organization]] report, industrialized agriculture contributes on a “massive scale” to climate change, air pollution, land degradation, energy use, [[Deforestation of the Amazon Rainforest|deforestation]], and [[biodiversity|biodiversity decline]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fao&quot;&gt;Livestock’s Long Shadow: environmental issues and options http://www.fao.org/docrep/010/a0701e/a0701e00.HTM&lt;/ref&gt; The FAO report estimates that the livestock (including poultry) sector (which provides draft animal power, leather, wool, milk, eggs, fertilizer, pharmaceuticals, etc., in addition to meat) contributes about 18 percent of global GHG ([[greenhouse gas]]) emissions expressed as 100-year CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; equivalents. This estimate was based on [[life cycle analysis]], including feed production, land use changes, etc., and used GWP ([[global warming potential]]) of  23 for methane and 296 for nitrous oxide, to convert emissions of these gases to 100-year CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; equivalents.  Some sources disagree with some of the figures used in arriving at the FAO estimate of 18 percent.  For example, the FAO report estimates that 37 percent of global anthropogenic methane emissions are attributable to the livestock sector, and a US [[NASA]] summary indicates about 30 percent.&lt;ref&gt;Augenbraun, H., E. Mathews and D. Sarma.  1997.  The global methane cycle.  http://icp.giss.nasa.gov/education/methane/intro/cycle.html&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the GWP multiplier used, such a difference between estimates will have a large effect on an estimate of GHG CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; equivalents contributed by the livestock sector.  Livestock sources (including enteric fermentation and manure) account for about 3.1 percent of US anthropogenic GHG emissions expressed as CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; equivalents.  This estimate is based on methodologies agreed to by the Conference of Parties of the UN [[FCCC]].&lt;ref&gt;EPA.   2011.  Inventory of U.S. greenhouse gas emissions and sinks:  1990-2009.  United States Environmental Protection Agency.  EPA 430-R-11-005.  459 pp.&lt;/ref&gt;  Data of a USDA study indicate that about 0.9 percent of energy use in the United States is accounted for by raising food-producing livestock and poultry. In this context, energy use includes energy from fossil, nuclear, hydroelectric, biomass, geothermal, technological solar, and wind sources. The estimated energy use in agricultural production includes embodied energy in purchased inputs.&lt;ref&gt;Canning, P., A. Charles, S. Huang, K. R. Polenske, and A Waters. 2010. Energy use in the U. S. food system. USDA Economic Research Service, ERR-94. 33 pp.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another agricultural effect is on land degradation. Much of the world's crops is used to feed animals.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian-un&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=UN urges global move to meat and dairy-free diet|last=Carus|first=Felicity|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=2010-06-02|accessdate=2011-10-26|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2010/jun/02/un-report-meat-free-diet}}&lt;/ref&gt; With 30 percent of the earth's land devoted to raising livestock,&lt;ref&gt;Livestock Grazing- Combats or Spreads Desertification? http://www.kkl.org.il/kkl/english/main_subject/curb%20global%20warming/livestock%20grazing-combats%20or%20spreads%20desertification.x&lt;/ref&gt; a major cutback is needed to keep up with growing population. A 2010 UN report explained that Western dietary preferences for meat would be unsustainable as the world population rose to the forecasted 9.1 billion by 2050.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian-un&quot;/&gt; Demand for meat is expected to double by this date; meat consumption is steadily rising in countries such as China that once followed more sustainable, vegetable-based diets.  Cattle are a known cause for soil erosion through trampling of the ground and [[overgrazing]].&lt;ref&gt;C.Michael Hogan. 2009. [http://www.eoearth.org/article/Overgrazing Overgrazing]. Encyclopedia of Earth. Sidney Draggan, topic ed.; Cutler J. Cleveland, ed., National council for Science and the Environment, Washington DC&lt;/ref&gt;

The environmental impacts of animal production vary{{clarify|date=October 2011}} with the method of production. A grazing-based production can limit soil erosion and also allow farmers to control pest problems with less pesticides through rotating crops with grass. In arid areas, however, it may catalyze a [[desertification]] process.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} The ability of soil to absorb water by infiltration is important for minimizing runoff and soil erosion. Researchers in Iowa reported that a soil under perennial pasture grasses grazed by livestock was able to absorb far more water than the same kind of soil under two annual crops: corn and soybeans.&lt;ref&gt;Bharati et al. 2002. Agroforestry Systems 56: 249-257&lt;/ref&gt; Corn and soybean crops commonly provide food for human consumption, biofuels, livestock feed, or some combination of these.

The FAO initiative concluded that &quot;the livestock sector emerges as one of the top two or three most significant contributors to the most serious environmental problems, at every scale from local to global.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fao&quot; /&gt;

==Related economic and social considerations==

Environmental vegetarianism can be compared with [[economic vegetarianism]]. An economic vegetarian is someone who practices vegetarianism either out of necessity or because of a conscious [[simple living]] strategy. Such a person  may base this belief on a philosophical viewpoint, such as the belief that the consumption of meat is economically unsound or that vegetarianism will help improve public health and curb [[starvation]]. According to the [[Worldwatch Institute]], &quot;massive reductions in meat consumption in [[industrial nation]]s will ease the health care burden while improving public health; declining livestock herds will take pressure off rangelands and grainlands, allowing the agricultural resource base to rejuvenate. As populations grow, lowering meat consumption worldwide will allow more efficient use of declining per capita land and water resources, while at the same time making grain more affordable to the world's chronically hungry.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.worldwatch.org/press/news/1998/07/02 United States Leads World Meat Stampede | Worldwatch Institute&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Environmental vegetarians call for a reduction of first world consumption of meat, especially in the US. According to the [[United Nations Population Fund]] &quot;Each U.S. citizen consumes an average of 260 lbs. of meat per year, the world's highest rate. That is about 1.5 times the industrial world average, three times the East Asian average, and 40 times the average in Bangladesh.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unfpa.org/6billion/ccmc/u.s.scorecard.html Day of 6 Billion: October 12 U.S. Scorecard&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, &quot;the [[ecological footprint]] of an average person in a high-income country is about six times bigger than that of someone in a low-income country, and many more times bigger than in the least-developed countries.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unfpa.org/swp/2004/english/ch3/ UNFPA State of World Population 2004&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[World Health Organization]] calls [[malnutrition]] &quot;the silent emergency&quot;, and says it is a factor in at least half of the 10.4 million child deaths which occur every year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/3559542.stm | work=BBC News | title=Hungry world 'must eat less meat' | date=August 16, 2004 | accessdate=May 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;trade-48538&quot;&gt;http://www.tradeobservatory.org/library.cfm?refID=48538&lt;/ref&gt;
Some argue{{who|date=October 2011}} that the adoption of a lacto-ovo vegetarian or entirely plant-based [[Veganism|vegan]] diet is best, but may not be totally necessary, because even modest reductions in meat consumption in industrialized societies would substantially reduce the burden on our natural resources. For developed countries, a CAST report estimates an average of 2.6 pounds of grain fed per pound of beef carcass meat produced. For developing countries, the estimate is 0.3 pounds per pound. (Some very dissimilar figures are sometimes seen; the CAST report discusses common sources of error and discrepancies among such figures.)&lt;ref&gt;Bradford, E. et al. 1999. Animal Agriculture and Global Food Supply. Council on Agricultural Science and Technology. 92 pp.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2007, US per capita beef consumption was 62.2 pounds per year, and US per capita meat (red meat plus fish plus poultry) consumption totaled 200.7 pounds, boneless trimmed weight basis.&lt;ref&gt;USDA.  2010. Agricultural Statistics 2010, Table 13-7&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2010 report from United Nations Environment Program's (UNEP) International Panel of Sustainable Resource Management, states that global shift towards a vegan diet is critical for mitigating global issues of hunger, fuel poverty and the worst impacts of climate change. The panel declared: &quot;Impacts from agriculture are expected to increase substantially due to population growth and increasing consumption of animal products. Unlike fossil fuels, it is difficult to look for alternatives: people have to eat. A substantial reduction of impacts would only be possible with a substantial worldwide diet change, away from animal products.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2010/jun/02/un-report-meat-free-diet UN urges global move to meat and dairy-free diet]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uneptie.org/scp/lifecycle/documents/Presentations/The%20Role%20of%20the%20International%20Panel%20on%20Sustainable%20Resource%20Management%20(Janet%20Salem).pdf The role of the International Panel for Sustainable Resource Management]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticisms==
A widely adopted vegetarian diet, in and of itself, may not be enough to make the US food system sustainable {{Citation needed|date=October 2012}}, unless greener agricultural practices, such as the adoption of [[renewable energy]], are also implemented. The support of alternative farming practices (e.g. well husbanded [[organic farming]], [[permaculture]], and [[Managed intensive grazing|rotational grazing]]) and the avoidance of certain plant commodities such as rice, also have a beneficial impact on environmental health and sustainable agriculture, though this would have little effect on animal welfare and rights{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}}. According to Cornell scientists, &quot;the heavy dependence on fossil energy suggests that the US food system, whether meat-based or plant-based, is not sustainable.&quot; but they also mention that: &quot;lactoovovegetarian diet is more sustainable than the average American meat-based diet. &quot; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ajcn.org/cgi/content/full/78/3/660S Sustainability of meat-based and plant-based diets and the environment - Pimentel and Pimentel 78 (3): 660S - American Journal of Clinical Nutrition&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some environmental activists claim that adopting a vegetarian diet may be a way of focusing on personal actions and righteous gestures rather than systemic change. Dave Riley, an [[Australia]]n environmentalist states that &quot;being meatless and guiltless seems seductively simple while environmental destruction rages around us,&quot; noting that animals can contribute to the food chain.  &quot;For instance, yams, which keep poorly, are stored inside pigs, and today's rotting apples attracting fruit flies are tomorrow's bacon,&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenleft.org.au/back/1993/110/110p13.htm Green Left - Issues: Does meat make the meal?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bill Mollison]] has inconsistently argued in his [[Permaculture]] Design Course that vegetarianism exacerbates [[soil erosion]]. This is because removing a plant from a field removes all the nutrients it obtained from the soil, while removing an animal leaves the field intact. On US farmland, much less soil erosion is associated with pastureland used for livestock grazing than with land used for production of crops.&lt;ref&gt;NRCS. 2009. Summary report 2007 national resources inventory. USDA Natural Resources Conservation Service. 123 pp.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert Hart (horticulturist)|Robert Hart]] has also developed [[forest gardening]], which has since been adopted as a common permaculture design element, as a sustainable plant-based food production system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Forest Gardening|author=Robert Hart|year=1996|page=45|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=N01940btQAQC&amp;lpg=PA97&amp;dq=forest%20gardening%20robert%20hart%20simple%20living&amp;pg=PA45#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
&lt;div style=&quot;column-count:2;-moz-column-count:2;-webkit-column-count:2&quot;&gt;
*''[[Devour the Earth]]''
*''[[Diet for a New America]]''
*[[Economic vegetarianism]]
*[[Entomophagy]] (another environmental approach for obtaining food)
*[[Environmentalism]]
*[[Ethics of vegetarianism]]
*[[In vitro meat]]
*''[[Livestock's Long Shadow]]''
*[[Stock-free agriculture]]
*[[Sustainable agriculture]]
*[[Sustainable food system]]
*[[Vegan organic gardening]]
&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.brook.com/veg/ Eco-Eating: Eating as if the Earth Matters (it does!)] Comprehensive source with ''many'' categories and links.
* [http://www.ivu.org/members/globalwarming.html Meat Eating and Global Warming] a list of articles making the vital connection between meat and climate change
* [http://www.bestfootforward.com/footprintlife.htm  Ecological footprint calculator] Two fields are dietary considerations.
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,2094651,00.html Dr. Ruth Fairchild of the UWIC's report on veganism and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;-emissions]
* [http://www.vegsoc.org/index.html The Vegetarian Society UK - information portal]
* [http://www.earthsave.org/environment/index.html EarthSave]
* [http://www.vegansociety.com/resources/environment.aspx Vegan Society - Environment]
{{Vegetarianism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Environmental Vegetarianism}}
[[Category:Vegetarianism]]
[[Category:Environmentalism]]
[[Category:Sustainable food system]]
[[Category:Environmental ethics]]

[[eo:Mediprotekta vegetarismo]]
[[fa:گیاه‌خواری زیست‌محیطی]]
[[pl:Wegetarianizm ekologiczny]]
[[ru:Экологическое вегетарианство]]</text>
      <sha1>lvcql14fycjzkpj3v0heat65iuiqiat</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
