<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Flood</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>50482</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521132077</id>
      <parentid>521131898</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T00:09:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2001:558:6045:A0:391F:B005:179D:8DD9</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 521131898 by [[Special:Contributions/Sydneyperez|Sydneyperez]] ([[User talk:Sydneyperez|talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26636">{{Other uses}}{{pp-move-indef}}
[[Image:Erschrecklichewasserfluth.jpg|thumb|Contemporary picture of the flood that struck the [[North Sea]] coast of Germany and Denmark in October 1634.]][[File:A Flood on Java 1865-1876 Raden Saleh.jpg|thumb|People seeking refuge from flood in [[Java]]. ca. 1865–1876.]]
[[File:Rapid Creek flooding 1.jpg|thumb|Flooding of a creek due to heavy monsoonal rain and high tide in [[Darwin, Northern Territory|Darwin]], [[Northern Territory]], [[Australia]].]]
[[File:Jeddah Flood - King Abdullah Street.jpg|thumb|[[Jeddah]] Flood, covering King Abdullah Street in [[Saudi Arabia]].]]
[[File:Flood102405.JPG|thumb|Flooding near [[Key West]], [[Florida]], [[United States]] from [[Hurricane Wilma]]'s [[storm surge]] in October 2005.]]
[[File:Trapped woman on a car roof during flash flooding in Toowoomba 2.jpg|thumb|[[Flash flood]]ing caused by heavy rain falling in a short amount of time.]]
[[File:BDF0.jpg|right|thumb|Dozens of villages were inundated when rain pushed the rivers of northwestern [[Bangladesh]] over their banks in early October 2005. The Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) on [[NASA]]’s Terra satellite captured the top image of the flooded Ghaghat and Atrai Rivers on October 12, 2005. The deep blue of the rivers is spread across the countryside in the flood image.]]

A '''flood''' is an overflow of  water that submerges land.&lt;ref&gt;MSN Encarta Dictionary. [http://encarta.msn.com/encnet/features/dictionary/DictionaryResults.aspx?refid=1861612277 Flood.] Retrieved on 2006-12-28. [http://www.webcitation.org/query?id=1257023547055729 Archived] 2009-10-31.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Union]] (EU) [[Floods Directive]] defines a flood as a  covering by water of land not normally covered by water.&lt;ref&gt;[http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2007:288:0027:0034:EN:PDF Directive 2007/60/EC Chapter 1 Article2]. eur-lex.europa.eu. Retrieved on 2012-06-12.&lt;/ref&gt; In the sense of &quot;flowing water&quot;, the word may also be applied to the inflow of the [[tide]].
Flooding may result from the volume of water within a body of water, such as a [[river]] or [[lake]], which overflows or breaks levees, with the result that some of the water escapes its usual boundaries,&lt;ref&gt;Glossary of Meteorology (June 2000). [http://amsglossary.allenpress.com/glossary/search?id=flood1 Flood.] Retrieved on 2009-01-09.&lt;/ref&gt; or may be due to accumulation of rainwater on saturated ground in an areal flood.

While the size of a lake or other body of water will vary with seasonal changes in precipitation and snow melt, it is not a significant flood unless such escapes of water endanger land areas used by man like a village, city or other inhabited area.

Floods can also occur in rivers, when flow exceeds the capacity of the river channel, particularly at bends or meanders. Floods often cause damage to homes and businesses if they are placed in natural flood plains of rivers.  While flood damage can be virtually eliminated by moving away from rivers and other bodies of water, since time out of mind, people have lived and worked by the water to seek sustenance and capitalize on the gains of cheap and easy travel and commerce by being near water. That humans continue to inhabit areas threatened by flood damage is evidence that the perceived value of living near the water exceeds the cost of repeated periodic flooding.

The word &quot;flood&quot; comes from the [[Old English language|Old English]] ''flod'', a word common to Germanic languages (compare German ''Flut'', Dutch ''vloed'' from the same root as is seen in ''flow, float''; also compare with Latin ''fluctus'', ''flumen''). [[Deluge myth]]s are [[Mythology|mythical]] stories of a great flood sent by a [[deity]] or deities to destroy [[civilization]] as an act of [[divine retribution]], and are featured in the mythology of many [[culture]]s.

==Principal types and causes==

===Areal===
*Floods often happen over flat or low-lying areas when the ground is saturated and water either cannot run off, or cannot run off quickly enough to stop accumulating. This may be later followed by a river flood as water moves away from the areal floodplain into local rivers and streams. 
*Floods can occur if water accumulates across an impermeable surface (e.g. from rainfall) and cannot rapidly dissipate (i.e. gentle orientation or low evaporation).
*A [[storm train|series of storms]] moving over the same area can cause areal [[flash flood]]ing.
*A [[muddy flood]] is produced by an accumulation of runoff generated on cropland. Sediments are then detached by runoff and carried as suspended matter or bed load. Muddy runoff is more likely detected when it reaches inhabited areas. Muddy floods are therefore a hill slope process, and confusion with mudflows produced by mass movements should be avoided.

===Riverine===
*'''Slow kinds:''' Runoff from sustained rainfall or rapid snow melt exceeding the capacity of a river's channel.  Causes include heavy rains from [[monsoon]]s, hurricanes and tropical depressions, foreign winds and warm rain affecting snow pack.  Unexpected drainage obstructions such as [[landslide]]s, [[ice]], or [[debris]] can cause slow flooding upstream of the obstruction.
*'''Fast kinds:''' include river [[flash floods]] resulting from convective precipitation (intense [[thunderstorm]]s) or sudden release from an upstream impoundment created behind a [[dam]], [[landslide]], or [[glacier]].
*[[Dam]]-building [[beaver]]s can flood low-lying urban and rural areas, often causing significant damage.

===Estuarine===
*Commonly caused by a combination of sea tidal surges caused by storm-force winds and high river stages due to heavy rain.

===Coastal===
*Caused by severe sea storms, or as a result of another hazard (e.g. [[tsunami]] or hurricane). A [[storm surge]], from either a [[tropical cyclone]] or an [[extratropical cyclone]], falls within this category.

===Catastrophic===
* Caused by a significant and unexpected event e.g. [[dam]] breakage, or as a result of another hazard (e.g. [[earthquake]] or volcanic eruption). See [[outburst flood]].

===Human-induced===
* Accidental damage by workmen to tunnels or pipes.

==Effects==

===Primary effects===
* Physical damage – damage to structures, including bridges, buildings, [[sewerage]] systems, [[roadway]]s, and [[canal]]s.

===Secondary effects===
*''Water supplies'' – [[water pollution|Contamination of water]]. Clean [[drinking water]]  will become scarce.
*''Diseases'' – Unhygienic conditions. Spread of [[water-borne diseases]].
*''Crops and food supplies'' – Shortage of food crops can be caused due to loss of entire harvest.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.southasianfloods.org&lt;/ref&gt;  However, lowlands near rivers depend upon river silt deposited by floods in order to add nutrients to the local soil.
*''Trees'' – Non-tolerant species can die from suffocation.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Bratkovich, Lisa Burban, et al., &quot;Flooding and its Effects on Trees&quot;, [[USDA Forest Service]], Northeastern Area State and Private Forestry, St. Paul, MN, September 1993, webpage: [http://www.na.fs.fed.us/spfo/pubs/n_resource/flood/cover.htm Na.fs.fed.us-flood-cover].&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Transport'' – Transport links destroyed, so hard to get emergency aid to those who need it.

===Tertiary and long-term effects===
* Economic – economic hardship due to temporary decline in tourism, rebuilding costs, food shortage leading to price increase, etc.
* Psychological – flooding can be highly traumatic for individuals, in particular where deaths, serious injuries and loss of property occurs.

==Control==
:{{Main|Flood control}}
[[File:Alicante(30-09-1997).JPG|thumb|upright|Autumn [[Mediterranean Sea|Mediterranean]] flooding in [[Alicante]] ([[Spain]]), 1997.]]
[[File:Povoden 2002 hlasna treban.jpg|thumb|right|The River Berounka, [[Czech Republic]], burst its banks in the [[2002 European floods]] and houses in the village of Hlásná Třebaň, [[Beroun District]], were inundated.]]
[[File:Flooderosion.jpg|thumb|right|alt=A river bank denuded of grass and other vegetation. Piles of deadwood line the high-water mark.|Debris and bank erosion left after the [[2009 Red River Flood]] in [[Winnipeg]], [[Manitoba]].]]
[[File:1936 Pittsburgh flood0007.jpg|thumb|right|[[Pittsburgh]] floods in 1936]]
[[File:Snoqualmie area flood.jpg|thumb|Flooding near [[Snoqualmie, Washington]], 2009.]]
[[File:Flood Dhaka Rezowan.jpg|thumb|right|Floods in [[Bangladesh]] 2009]]

In many countries across the world, rivers prone to floods are often carefully managed. Defenses such as [[levee]]s,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title=Levees and Other Raised Ground|author=Henry Petroski|publisher=American Scientist|year=2006|volume=94|issue=1|pages=7–11}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[bunding|bunds]], [[reservoir (water)|reservoirs]], and [[weir]]s are used to prevent rivers from bursting their banks. When these defenses fail, emergency measures such as sandbags or portable inflatable tubes are used. Coastal flooding has been addressed in Europe and the Americas with [[Coastal management|coastal defences]], such as [[sea wall]]s, [[beach nourishment]], and [[barrier island]]s.

===Europe===
Remembering the misery and destruction caused by the [[1910 Great Flood of Paris]], the French government built a series of reservoirs called Les Grands Lacs de Seine (or Great Lakes) which helps remove pressure from the [[Seine]] during floods, especially the regular winter flooding.&lt;ref&gt;See Jeffrey H. Jackson, ''Paris Under Water: How the City of Light Survived the Great Flood of 1910'' (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2010).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[London]] is protected from sea flooding by the [[Thames Barrier]], a huge mechanical barrier across the [[River Thames]], which is raised when the sea water level reaches a certain point.

[[Venice]] has a similar arrangement, although it is already unable to cope with very high tides; a new system of variable-height dikes is under construction. The defences of both London and Venice would be rendered inadequate if sea levels were to rise.

The [[Adige]] in Northern Italy was provided with an underground canal that allows to drain part of its flow into the [[Garda Lake]] (in the [[Po river|Po]] drainage basin), thus lessening the risk of estuarine floods. The underground canal has been used twice, in 1966 and 2000.

The largest and most elaborate [[flood control in the Netherlands|flood defences]] can be found in the [[Netherlands]], where they are referred to as [[Delta Works]] with the [[Oosterschelde]] dam as its crowning achievement. These works were built in response to the [[North Sea flood of 1953]] of the southwestern part of the Netherlands. The Dutch had already built one of the world's largest dams in the north of the country: the [[Afsluitdijk]] (closing occurred in 1932).

Currently the [[Saint Petersburg Dam|Saint Petersburg Flood Prevention Facility Complex]] is to be finished by 2008, in [[Russia]], to protect [[Saint Petersburg]] from [[storm surge]]s. It also has a main traffic function, as it completes a [[Beltway|ring road]] around Saint Petersburg.  Eleven dams extend for 25.4 kilometres and stand eight metres above water level.

In [[Austria]], flooding for over 150 years, has been controlled by various actions of the [[Vienna Danube regulation]], with dredging of the main [[Danube]] during 1870–75, and creation of the [[New Danube]] from 1972–1988.

In Northern Ireland flood risk management is provided by [[Rivers Agency]].

===North America===
Another elaborate system of floodway defences can be found in the Canadian province of [[Manitoba]]. The [[Red River of the North|Red River]] flows northward from the United States, passing through the city of [[Winnipeg]] (where it meets the [[Assiniboine River]]) and into [[Lake Winnipeg]]. As is the case with all north-flowing rivers in the temperate zone of the Northern Hemisphere, snowmelt in southern sections may cause river levels to rise before northern sections have had a chance to completely thaw. This can lead to devastating flooding, as occurred in Winnipeg during the [[1950 Red River Flood|spring of 1950]]. To protect the city from future floods, the Manitoba government undertook the construction of a massive system of diversions, dikes, and floodways (including the [[Red River Floodway]] and the [[Portage Diversion]]). The system kept Winnipeg safe during the [[1997 Red River Flood|1997 flood]] that devastated many communities upriver from Winnipeg, including [[Grand Forks, North Dakota]] and [[Ste. Agathe, Manitoba]]. It also kept Winnipeg safe during the [[2009 Red River Flood|2009 flood]].

In the U.S., the [[New Orleans Metropolitan Area]], 35% of which sits below sea level, is protected by hundreds of miles of levees and [[flood gate]]s. This system failed catastrophically, in numerous sections, during [[Hurricane Katrina]], in the city proper and in eastern sections of the Metro Area, resulting in the inundation of approximately 50% of the metropolitan area, ranging from a few centimetres to 8.2 metres (a few inches to 27 feet) in coastal communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;katreport&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=United States Department of Commerce| title=Hurricane Katrina Service Assessment Report|month=June|year=2006|accessdate=2006-07-14|format = PDF|url=http://www.weather.gov/om/assessments/pdfs/Katrina.pdf|authorlink= United States Department of Commerce}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In an act of successful flood prevention, the Federal Government of the United States offered to buy out flood-prone properties in the United States in order to prevent repeated disasters after the 1993 flood across the Midwest.  Several communities accepted and the government, in partnership with the state, bought 25,000 properties which they converted into [[wetland]]s.  These wetlands act as a sponge in storms and in 1995, when the floods returned, the government did not have to expend resources in those areas.&lt;ref name=time&gt;Amanda Ripley.
[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1229102,00.html &quot;Floods, Tornadoes, Hurricanes, Wildfires, Earthquakes... Why We Don't Prepare.&quot;] ''Time.'' August 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Asia===
In India, Bangladesh and China, flood [[diversion]] areas are rural areas that are deliberately flooded in emergencies in order to protect cities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/en/doc/2003-07/07/content_243670.htm &quot;China blows up seventh dike to divert flooding.&quot;] ''China Daily.'' 2003-07-07.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many have proposed that loss of vegetation ([[deforestation]]) will lead to a risk increase. With natural forest cover the flood duration should decrease. Reducing the rate of deforestation should improve the incidents and severity of floods.&lt;ref&gt;Bradshaw CJ, Sodhi NS, Peh SH, Brook BW. (2007). Global evidence that deforestation amplifies flood risk and severity in the developing. Also a flood has recently hit Pakistan which is said to be more devastating then the Tsunami of 2005 world. ''Global Change Biology'', 13: 2379–2395.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Africa===
In [[Egypt]], both the [[Aswan Dam]] (1902) and the [[Aswan High Dam]] (1976) have controlled various amounts of flooding along the [[Nile]] river.

===Clean-up safety===
Clean-up activities following floods often pose hazards to workers and volunteers involved in the effort. Potential dangers include: water polluted by mixing with and causing overflows from [[sanitary sewer]]s, [[electric shock|electrical hazards]], [[carbon monoxide]] exposure, [[musculoskeletal]] hazards, [[hyperthermia|heat]] or [[hypothermia|cold stress]], [[motor vehicle]]-related dangers, [[fire]], [[drowning]], and exposure to [[hazardous materials]].&lt;ref&gt;United States National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH). [http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/flood/ ''Storm and Flood Cleanup''.] Accessed 23 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Because flooded disaster sites are unstable, clean-up workers might encounter sharp jagged debris, biological hazards in the flood water, exposed electrical lines, blood or other body fluids, and animal and human remains. In planning for and reacting to flood disasters, managers provide workers with [[hard hats]], [[goggles]], heavy work gloves, [[life jackets]], and watertight boots with steel toes and insoles.&lt;ref&gt;NIOSH. [http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/docs/94-123/ ''NIOSH Warns of Hazards of Flood Cleanup Work''.] NIOSH Publication No. 94-123.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Benefits==
There are many disruptive effects of flooding on human settlements and economic activities. However, floods (in particular the more frequent/smaller floods) can also bring many benefits, such as recharging ground water, making soil more fertile and providing nutrients in which it is deficient. Flood waters provide much needed water resources in particular in arid and semi-arid regions where precipitation events can be very unevenly distributed throughout the year. Freshwater floods, particularly play an important role in maintaining ecosystems in river corridors and are a key factor in maintaining floodplain biodiversity.&lt;ref&gt;WMO/GWP Associated Programme on Flood Management [http://www.apfm.info/pdf/ifm_environmental_aspects.pdf &quot;Environmental Aspects of Integrated Flood Management.&quot;] WMO, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Flooding adds a lot of nutrients to lakes and rivers which leads to improved fisheries for a few years, also because of the suitability of a floodplain for spawning (little predation and a lot of nutrients).&lt;ref&gt;[http://kops.ub.uni-konstanz.de/volltexte/2009/7515/pdf/2008_Wantzen_etal_An_extension_of_the_floodpulse.pdf Extension of the Flood Pulse Concept]. Kops.ub.uni-konstanz.de. Retrieved on 2012-06-12.&lt;/ref&gt; Fish like the [[weather fish]] make use of floods to reach new habitats. Together with fish also birds profit from the boost in production caused by flooding.&lt;ref&gt;[http://africa.ipsterraviva.net/2010/10/15/birdlife-soars-above-botswanas-floodplains/ Birdlife soars above Botswana's floodplains]. Africa.ipsterraviva.net (2010-10-15). Retrieved on 2012-06-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

Periodic flooding was essential to the well-being of ancient communities along the [[Tigris-Euphrates]] Rivers, the [[Nile]] River, the [[Indus]] River, the [[Ganges]] and the [[Yellow River]], among others. The viability for hydrological based renewable sources of energy is higher in flood prone regions.

==Computer modelling==
While flood modelling is a fairly recent practice, attempts to understand and manage the mechanisms at work in floodplains have been made for at least six millennia.&lt;ref&gt;Dyhouse, G. &quot;Flood modelling Using HEC-RAS (First Edition).&quot; Haestad Press, Waterbury (USA), 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; The recent development in computational flood modelling has enabled engineers to step away from the tried and tested &quot;hold or break&quot; approach and its tendency to promote overly engineered structures. Various computational flood models have been developed in recent years; either 1D models (flood levels measured in the channel) and 2D models (variable flood depth measured across the extent of the floodplain). [[HEC-RAS]],&lt;ref&gt;United States Army Corps of Engineers. Davis, CA. [http://www.hec.usace.army.mil Hydrologic Engineering Center.]&lt;/ref&gt; the Hydraulic Engineering Centre model, is currently among the most popular if only because it is available free of charge. Other models such as TUFLOW&lt;ref&gt;BMT WBM Pty Ltd., Brisbane, Queensland. [http://www.tuflow.com/ &quot;TUFLOW Flood and Tide Simulation Software.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; combine 1D and 2D components to derive flood depth across the river channel and floodplain. To date the focus has primarily been on mapping tidal and fluvial flood events, but the 2007 flood events in the UK have shifted the emphasis there onto the impact of surface water flooding.&lt;ref&gt;Cabinet Office, UK. [http://archive.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/pittreview/thepittreview.html &quot;Pitt Review: Lessons learned from the 2007 floods.&quot;] June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Deadliest floods==
{{Main|List of deadliest floods}}
Below is a list of the deadliest floods worldwide, showing events with death tolls at or above 100,000 individuals.
{| class=&quot;sortable wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:95%;&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#ccc;&quot;
! style=&quot;width:20%;&quot;|Death toll !! style=&quot;width:40%;&quot;|Event !! style=&quot;width:20%;&quot;|Location !! style=&quot;width:20%;&quot;|Date
|-
||2,500,000–3,700,000&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nbc10.com/news/4030540/detail.html Worst Natural Disasters In History]. Nbc10.com (2012-06-07). Retrieved on 2012-06-12.&lt;/ref&gt; || [[1931 China floods]] || [[China]] || 1931
|-
||900,000–2,000,000 || [[1887 Yellow River (Huang He) flood]] || [[China]] || 1887
|-
||500,000–700,000 || [[1938 Yellow River (Huang He) flood]] || [[China]] || 1938
|-
||231,000 || [[Banqiao Dam]] failure, result of [[Typhoon Nina (1975)|Typhoon Nina]]. Approximately 86,000 people died from flooding and another 145,000 died during subsequent disease. || [[China]] || 1975
|-
||230,000 || [[2004 Indian Ocean earthquake|Indian Ocean tsunami]] || [[Indonesia]] || 2004
|-
||145,000 || [[1935 Yangtze river flood]] || [[China]] || 1935
|-
||100,000+ || [[St. Felix's Flood]], storm surge || [[Netherlands]] || 1530
|-
||100,000 || [[Hanoi]] and [[Red River Delta]] flood || [[North Vietnam]] || 1971
|-
||100,000 || [[1911 Yangtze river flood]] || [[China]] || 1911
|}

==See also==
{{portalbox|Environment|Ecology}}
{{colbegin}}
*[[Chicago Flood]], man-made flood under downtown Chicago
*[[Disaster preparedness]]
*[[Flood control in the Netherlands]]
*[[Flood pulse concept]]
*[[Flood risk assessment|Flood Risk Assessment]]
*[[Floods directive]]
*[[Floods in Australia]]
*[[Floods in the Netherlands]]
*[[Floods in the United States]]
*[[List of floods]]
*[[SMS (hydrology software)]]
*[[Storm tides of the North Sea]]
{{colend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*O'Connor, Jim E. and John E. Costa. (2004). ''The World's Largest Floods, Past and Present: Their Causes and Magnitudes'' [Circular 1254]. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of the Interior, U.S. Geological Survey.
*Thompson, M.T. (1964). ''Historical Floods in New England '' [Geological Survey Water-Supply Paper 1779-M]. Washington, D.C.: United States Government Printing Office.
* Powell, W. Gabe. 2009. Identifying Land Use/Land Cover (LULC) Using National Agriculture Imagery Program (NAIP) Data as a Hydrologic Model Input for Local Flood Plain Management. Applied Research Project. [http://ecommons.txstate.edu/arp/296/ Texas State University – San Marcos.]

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{Wikinews}}
{{External links|date=January 2011}}
*[http://www.parisunderwater.com Website on the Great Flood of Paris in 1910]
*[http://www.cdc.gov/healthywater/emergency/flood/index.html U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Healthy Water – Flood Water Exposure] Health risks, cleanup of flood waters, and links to flood resources
*[http://www.awra.org American Water Resources Association]
*[http://www.apfm.info/ Associated Programme on Flood Management] from [[World Meteorological Organization]]
*[http://www.dartmouth.edu/~floods/ Dartmouth Flood Observatory]
*[http://www.floodrisk.net Decision tree to choose an uncertainty method for hydrological and hydraulic modelling], Choosing an uncertainty analysis for flood modeling.
*[http://www.deltaworks.org DeltaWorks.Org] Flood protecting dams and barriers project in the Netherlands
*[http://natgeoadventure.tv/Post.aspx?Id=24521 Video: Monsoon flooding, in Phnom Penh, Cambodia]
*[[n:Europe floods 2006|Europe floods 2006]]
*[http://www.floodrisk.org.uk/ Flood Risk Management Research Consortium]
*[http://www.ifi-home.info/ International Flood Initiative]
*[http://floodmaster.de International teaching module &quot;Integrated Flood Risk Management of Extreme Events&quot; (Floodmaster)]
*[http://www.planetark.com/dailynewsstory.cfm/newsid/44023/story.htm Predictions Off for Global Warming Flood Risk – Study].
*[http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?chanID=sa004&amp;articleID=000E6686-677C-134D-A77C83414B7F0000 Protecting against the Next Katrina] – Scientific American Magazine (October 2005)
*[[Appropedia:Category:Flood control|Related articles]] at Appropedia, a wiki for non-Wikipedia (projects &amp; practical &quot;how to&quot;) content.
*[http://www.safecoast.org/ Safecoast] Knowledge exchange on coastal flooding and climate change in the North Sea region
*[http://www.economics.noaa.gov/?goal=weather&amp;file=events/precip/ Social &amp; Economic Benefits/Costs of Heavy Rain &amp; Flooding] NOAA Economics
*[http://www.riversagencyni.gov.uk/ Riversagencyni.gov.uk], [[Rivers Agency]] of [[Northern Ireland]]
*[http://cecar.unu.edu/ UN-CECAR] research and courses on flood disaster risk management and climate change adaptation

{{Natural disasters}}
{{Disasters}}

[[Category:Basic meteorological concepts and phenomena]]
[[Category:Weather]]
[[Category:Flood| ]]
[[Category:Weather hazards]]
[[Category:Water]]
[[Category:Water waves]]
[[Category:Hydrology]]

{{Link FA|sl}}

[[af:Oorstroming]]
[[ar:فيضان]]
[[an:Inundación]]
[[ast:Inundación]]
[[az:Daşqın]]
[[bn:বন্যা]]
[[bjn:Baah]]
[[zh-min-nan:Toā-chúi]]
[[be:Паводка]]
[[be-x-old:Паводка]]
[[bg:Наводнение]]
[[bs:Poplava]]
[[br:Dour-beuz]]
[[ca:Inundació]]
[[cs:Povodeň]]
[[cy:Llifogydd]]
[[da:Oversvømmelse]]
[[de:Hochwasser]]
[[et:Üleujutus]]
[[el:Πλημμύρα]]
[[es:Inundación]]
[[eo:Inundo]]
[[eu:Uholde]]
[[fa:سیل]]
[[fr:Inondation]]
[[fy:Oerstreaming]]
[[ga:Tuile]]
[[gl:Inundación]]
[[gan:水澇]]
[[gu:પૂર]]
[[ko:홍수]]
[[hy:Ջրհեղեղ]]
[[hi:बाढ़]]
[[hr:Poplava]]
[[io:Diluvio]]
[[id:Banjir]]
[[is:Flóð]]
[[it:Inondazione]]
[[he:שיטפון]]
[[kn:ಪ್ರವಾಹ]]
[[ka:წყალდიდობა]]
[[kk:Сел]]
[[sw:Mafuriko]]
[[ht:Inondasyon]]
[[ku:Lehî]]
[[la:Inundatio]]
[[lv:Plūdi]]
[[lt:Potvynis (stichinė nelaimė)]]
[[hu:Árvíz]]
[[mk:Поплава]]
[[mg:Tondra-drano]]
[[ml:വെള്ളപ്പൊക്കം]]
[[mr:पूर]]
[[ms:Banjir]]
[[mn:Үер]]
[[my:ရေကြီးခြင်း]]
[[nl:Overstroming]]
[[ne:बाढी]]
[[ja:洪水]]
[[frr:Huuchweeder]]
[[no:Flom]]
[[nn:Flaum]]
[[oc:Inondacion]]
[[pnb:ہڑ]]
[[pl:Powódź]]
[[pt:Inundação]]
[[ro:Inundație]]
[[qu:Nuyuy]]
[[rue:Повінь]]
[[ru:Наводнение]]
[[sa:प्लावन]]
[[scn:Allavinamentu]]
[[si:ගංවතුර]]
[[simple:Flood]]
[[sk:Povodeň]]
[[sl:Poplava]]
[[sr:Поплава]]
[[sh:Poplava]]
[[su:Caah]]
[[fi:Tulva]]
[[sv:Översvämning]]
[[tl:Baha]]
[[ta:வெள்ளம்]]
[[te:వరద]]
[[th:น้ำท่วม]]
[[tr:Sel]]
[[uk:Повідь]]
[[ur:سیلاب]]
[[vi:Lụt]]
[[fiu-vro:Üleujotus]]
[[wa:Grossès aiwes]]
[[war:Bahâ]]
[[zh-yue:水浸]]
[[zh:洪灾]]</text>
      <sha1>4o1z49l55slavc0mfxm0hzi24j5fcn1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
