<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hydraulic fracturing in the United States</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8798949</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519813432</id>
      <parentid>519811502</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T19:31:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vsmith</username>
        <id>84417</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/68.63.141.43|68.63.141.43]] ([[User talk:68.63.141.43|talk]]) to last version by Smm201`0</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="105682">{{POV|date=August 2012}}
{{cleanup |reason= that the article is poorly organized and poorly written|date=August 2012}}
[[Hydraulic fracturing]], a process of utilizing pressurized water, chemical additives, and physical proppants to fracture rock layers and release [[petroleum]], [[natural gas]], or other substances so that they can be extracted, has been used in the United State for over 60 years, and over a million wells have been drilled over that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 03Aug2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/04/us/04natgas.html |title=A Tainted Water Well, and Concern There May be More |first=Ian |last = Urbina |date=3 August 2011 |newspaper=The New York Times |accessdate=22 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Environmental safety and health concerns about hydraulic fracturing emerged over 25 years ago, and are still being debated at the state and federal levels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 03Aug2011&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
*{{cite interview
 | last        = Fox
 | first       = Josh
 | interviewer = Ira Flatow
 | title       = New Film Investigates 'Fracking' For Natural Gas
 | program     = Science Friday
 | callsign    = [[WAMU]]
 | city        = [[Washington, D.C.]]
 | date        = June 18, 2010
 | accessdate  = June 21, 2010
 | url         = http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=127932770
}}
*{{cite news
 | title = Gulf oil spill worsens -- but what about the safety of gas fracking?
 | author = Margot Roosevelt
 | url = http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/greenspace/2010/06/gulf-oil-spill-bp-hydraulic-fracturing-gas-fracking-.html
 | newspaper = LA Times
 | date = June 18, 2010
 | accessdate = June 21, 2010
 }}
*{{cite news
 | title = EPA Announces a Schedule of Public Meetings on Hydraulic Fracturing Research Study
 | url = http://yosemite.epa.gov/opa/admpress.nsf/0/5ab7fab1665a0d698525774600606afe?OpenDocument
 | agency = [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]]
 | date = June 21, 2010
 | accessdate = June 21, 2010
 }}
*{{cite web
 | title = FracTracker’s Mapping Tool
 | url= http://www.fractracker.org/maps/
 | date = March 17, 2011
 | accessdate = October 06, 2012
 }}
*{{cite news
 | title = APNewsBreak: EPA theorizes fracking-pollution link
 | url = http://news.yahoo.com/apnewsbreak-epa-theorizes-fracking-pollution-211055287.html
 | agency = [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]]
 | date = December 8, 2011
 | accessdate = December 9, 2011
 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

{{TOC limit|3}}

==History==
Fracturing as a method to stimulate shallow, hard rock oil wells dates back to the 1860s. It was applied by oil producers in [[Pennsylvania]], [[New York]], [[Kentucky]], and [[West Virginia]] by using liquid and later also solidified [[nitroglycerin]]. Later, the same method was applied to water and natural gas wells.&lt;ref name=&quot;Montgomery&quot;/&gt;  The first industrial use of hydraulic fracturing was as early as 1903, according to T.L. Watson.&lt;ref&gt;Watson, T.L., Granites of the southeastern Atlantic states, U.S. Geological Survey Bulletin 426, 1910.&lt;/ref&gt; Before that date, hydraulic fracturing was used at Mt. Airy [[Quarry]], near [[Mount Airy, North Carolina|Mt Airy]], [[North Carolina]] where it was (and still is) used to separate granite blocks from bedrock.{{citation needed|date=August 2012}}

The idea to use acid as a nonexplosive fluid for well stimulation was introduced in the 1930s. Due to [[acid etching]], fractures would not close completely and therefore productivity was enhanced. The same phenomenon was discovered with water injection and [[squeeze cementing]] operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Montgomery&quot;/&gt;

The relationship between well performance and treatment pressures was studied by Floyd Farris of [[Stanolind Oil and Gas Corporation]]. This study became a basis of the first hydraulic fracturing experiment, which was conducted in 1947 at the [[Hugoton gas field]] in [[Grant County, Kansas|Grant County]] of southwestern [[Kansas]] by Stanolind.&lt;ref name=&quot;Montgomery&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Charlez&quot;/&gt;  For the well treatment {{convert|1000|USgal}} of gelled gasoline and sand from the [[Arkansas River]] was injected into the gas-producing limestone formation at {{convert|2400|ft}}. The experiment was not very successful as deliverability of the well did not change appreciably.  The process was further described by J.B. Clark of Stanolind in his paper published in 1948. A patent on this process was issued in 1949 and an exclusive license was granted to the Halliburton Oil Well Cementing Company. On March 17, 1949, Halliburton performed the first two commercial hydraulic fracturing treatments in [[Stephens County, Oklahoma]], and [[Archer County, Texas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Montgomery&quot;/&gt;  Since then, hydraulic fracturing has been used to stimulate approximately a million oil and gas wells.&lt;ref name=&quot;UT Study&quot;/&gt;

In the 1970s the United States government initiated the [[Eastern Gas Shales Project]], a set of dozens of public-private hydro-fracturing pilot demonstration projects. During the same period, the [[Gas Research Institute]], a gas industry research consortium, received approval for research and funding from the [[Federal Energy Regulatory Commission]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gri&quot;/&gt; In 1977, the [[United States Department of Energy|Department of Energy]] pioneered massive hydraulic fracturing in tight sandstone formations. In 1997, based on earlier techniques used by Union Pacific Resources, now part of [[Anadarko Petroleum Corporation]], Mitchell Energy, now part of [[Devon Energy]], developed the hydraulic fracturing technique known as &quot;slickwater fracturing&quot; that made the shale gas extraction economical.&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoZV-10&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SPE-20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoZV-9&quot;/&gt;

Between 2005 and 2010 the shale-gas industry in the United States grew by 45% a year. As a proportion of the country's overall gas production, shale gas increased from 4% in 2005 to 24% in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url= http://www.economist.com/node/21556242 |title= Shale of the century |journal= The Economist |issue= 2 June 2012 |accessdate= 2 June 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economic Impact==
Proponents of hydraulic fracturing tout its potential to make the United States the  world's largest oil producer and make it an energy leader.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fortson 11Sep2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.thesundaytimes.co.uk/sto/business/Industry/article773144.ece |title=America to be No 1 oil producer |author=Danny Fortson |date=11 September 2011 |newspaper=[[The Sunday Times]] |accessdate=4 March 2012 |quote=Goldman Sachs, the investment bank, has predicted that US production will hit 10.9m barrels a day by 2017, a one-third rise over its current level of 8.3m barrels a day. .&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. Jeffrey Currie, Goldman's head of commodities, said the reversal of fortune for America was a combination of &quot;technological innovation, as shale technologies developed in gas were applied to oil, and a surge of investment into the US oil industry&quot;.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents say that hydraulic fracturing would give the [[United States energy independence]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bloomberg 07.02.2012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-02-07/americans-gaining-energy-independence-with-u-s-as-top-producer.html |title=Americans Gaining Energy Independence With U.S. as Top Producer |author=Rich Miller, Asjylyn Loder and Jim Polson |date=7 February 2012 |agency=Bloomberg |accessdate=21 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Globally, gas use is expected to rise by more than 50% compared to 2010 levels, and account for over 25% of world energy demand in 2035.&lt;ref name=&quot;WEO 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.iea.org/weo/docs/weo2011/WEO2011_GoldenAgeofGasReport.pdf |title=World Energy Outlook 2011: Are We Entering a Golden Age of Gas? |date=9 November 2011 |publisher=International Energy Agency |accessdate=3 March 2012 |quote=Based on the assumptions of the GAS Scenario, from 2010 gas use will rise by more than 50% and account for over 25% of world energy demand in 2035—surely a prospect to designate the Golden Age of Gas.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anticipated demand and higher prices abroad have motivated non-US companies to buy shares in invest in US gas and oil companies,&lt;ref name=&quot;Chinese buy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.businessweek.com/news/2012-01-04/sinopec-group-to-buy-stakes-in-devon-energy-oil-projects.html |title=Sinopec Group to Buy Stakes in Devon Energy Oil Projects |author=Polson, Jim, &amp; Haas, Benjamin |date=4 February |publisher=Bloomberg Businessweek |accessdate=4 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Intl buy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-01-09/shale-bubble-inflates-on-near-record-prices-for-untested-fields.html |title= U.S. Shale Bubble Inflates After Near-Record Prices for Untested Fields|author=Carroll, Joe &amp; Polson, Jim |date=9 January |publisher=Bloomberg Businessweek |accessdate=4 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in some cases buy them, and their shale plays, outright&lt;ref name=&quot;Statoil buys&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2011/10/17/norways-statoil-to-acquire-brigham-exploration-for-4-4-billion/ |title=Norway’s Statoil to Acquire Brigham Exploration for $4.4 Billion |author=Scott, Mark |date=17 October 2011 |work=Dealb%k |publisher=New York Times |accessdate=4 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; leading to greater international control of US gas resources. Oil and natural gas companies have recently sought to build a new pipeline through Pennsylvania and Maryland&lt;ref name=&quot;PAMDpipeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/02/07/usa-lng-exports-idUSL2E8D771D20120207 |title=Sierra Club opposes Maryland LNG export terminal |author=Rascoe, Ayesha |date=7 February |publisher=Reuters |accessdate=5 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; to new liquid natural gas export terminals in Maryland,&lt;ref name=&quot;USSecurity&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/ericagies/2012/02/24/push-to-export-natural-gas-could-threaten-u-s-energy-security/ |title=Push to Export Natural Gas Could Threaten U.S. Energy Security |author=Gies, Erica |date=24 February |work=Green Tech | publisher=Forbes |accessdate=4 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order to increase profits by exporting gas to Europe and Asia (e.g., China and Korea). Such a move could potentially threaten national security.&lt;ref name=&quot;USSecurity&quot; /&gt; 

Some geologists say that the well productivity estimates are inflated and minimize the impact of the reduced productivity of wells after the first year or two.&lt;ref name=&quot;Geosoc yield&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://geology.com/royalty/production-decline.shtml |title=Production Decline of a Natural Gas Well Over Time |date=3 January 2012 |work=Geology.com | publisher=The Geology Society of America |accessdate=4 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A June, 2011 [[New York Times]] investigation of industrial emails and internal documents found that the financial benefits of unconventional shale gas extraction may be less than previously thought, due to companies intentionally overstating the productivity of their wells and the size of their reserves. The same article said, &quot;Many people within the industry remain confident.&quot; [[T. Boone Pickens]] said that he was not worried about shale companies and that be believed they would make good money if prices rise. Pickens also said that technological advances, such as the repeated hydrofracking of wells, was making production cheaper. Companies that specialize in shale gas have diversified into lucrative products such as [[propoane]] and [[butaine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Urbina|first=Ian|title=Insiders Sound an Alarm Amid a Natural Gas Rush|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/26/us/26gas.html?pagewanted=1&amp;sq=marcellus&amp;st=cse&amp;scp=12|accessdate=28 June 2011|newspaper=New York Times|date=25 June 2011}}; {{cite news|last=Urbina|first=Ian|title=S.E.C. Shift Leads to Worries of Overestimation of Reserves|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/27/us/27gasside.html?_r=2&amp;pagewanted=1|accessdate=28 June 2011|newspaper=New York Times|date=27 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lower natural gas prices in the US have reduced incentives to investigate renewable sources of energy, perpetuating dependence on gas and oil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bloomberg 16.02.2012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-02-16/energy-independence-offers-u-s-golden-chance-to-develop-renewables-view.html |title=Energy Independence Gives Opening for Renewables |author=Editorial |date=16 February 2012 |agency=Bloomberg |accessdate=21 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the interim, rather than pass the savings from lower natural gas prices on to US consumers, companies are reducing production to reduce supply and inflate natural gas prices in the US.&lt;ref name=&quot;gasprices03082012&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/03/07/us-natgas-cuts-idUSTRE8261G820120307 |title=Show, don't tell: U.S. natural gas traders question cuts. North American natural gas producers face one big problem as they pledge to cut production to bolster prices: skeptical traders. |author=McAllister, Edward |date=7 March 2012 |publisher=Reuters |accessdate=8 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More locally, economic impacts of hydraulic fracturing include payments to property owners, an increase in jobs, and an increase in business. The EPA states that it is unclear on a local level how and for how long hydraulic fracturing affects a community economically. It is hypothesized that hydraulic fracturing may not provide jobs to local communities due to the specialized nature of hydraulic fracturing tasks. Also, communities’ local resources could potentially be taxed due to the increase in industry traffic or if an accident occurs.&lt;ref name=&quot;hydraulic fracturing study plan draft 2011&quot; /&gt; Concerns have also been raised regarding the terms and clarity of the leases energy companies are signing with landowners, as well as the manner in which they are sold and the tactics used by companies in implementing them.&lt;ref name=&quot;UrbinaCMcG 01Dec2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/02/us/drilling-down-fighting-over-oil-and-gas-well-leases.html |title=Learning Too Late of the Perils in Gas Well Leases |author=Ian Urbina and Jo Craven McGinty |date=1 December 2011 |newspaper=The New York Times |accessdate=23 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

'''Real estate and mortgage industries'''
Another question has been the effect the leases can have on mortgages, with some lenders becoming reluctant to loan money &quot;for a piece of land that ends up storing the equivalent of an Olympic-size swimming pool filled with toxic wastewater from drilling&quot; or making mortgages conditional on not signing a drilling contract.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 19Oct2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/20/us/rush-to-drill-for-gas-creates-mortgage-conflicts.html |title=Rush to Drill for Natural Gas Creates Conflicts With Mortgages |author=Ian Urbina |date=19 October 2011 |newspaper=The New York Times |accessdate=23 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 24Nov2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/25/us/officials-push-for-clarity-on-oil-and-gas-leases.html |title=Officials Push for Clarity on Oil and Gas Leases |author=Ian Urbina |date=24 November 2011 |newspaper=The New York Times |accessdate=23 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Insurance industry''' [[Nationwide Insurance]], issued a statement that its policies do not cover hydraulic fracturing related damage. The company said that it issued the memo because their research led them to decide that the financial exposure created by such coverage was too great. The company will not cover damages to land involved in hydraulic fracturing operations, damages resulting from hauling water, pipe, and lumber to and from drill sites, and damages resulting from the use of bulldozers, dump trucks and other vehicles used in conjunction with hydraulic fracturing.&lt;ref name=&quot;EschJul122012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.pressconnects.com/viewart/20120713/NEWS01/207130323/U-S-insurer-won-t-cover-gas-drill-fracking-exposure?odyssey=tab|mostpopular|text|FRONTPAGE |title=U.S. insurer won't cover gas drill fracking exposure |author=Mary Esch and Rik Stevens|date=13 July 2012 |agency=Associated Press |accessdate=14 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Company representatives said that they have historically not insured the oil and gas business, but added that they were uncomfortable with hydraulic fracturing's unique risks and could not provide coverage at a reasonable price.&lt;ref name=&quot;WilliamsJul142012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dispatch.com/content/stories/business/2012/07/14/insurers-deny-drilling-claims.html |title=Insurers deny drilling claims Nationwide continues policy of not covering policyholders for damage from ‘fracking’ |author=Mark Williams|date=14 July 2012 |publisher=The Columbus Dispatch |accessdate=14 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jeffrey Hanneman, the director of environmental practice for [[Aon Risk Solutions]], said the decision would be unlikely to signal a wider trend. Hanneman said that while some insurance companies have been reluctant to offer coverage to tracking and related activities, there have been no substantial claims except for rare claims against companies owning or operating wells. Mike Elmendorf, head of the [[Associated General Contractors of New York State]] said that AGCNY members did not welcome Nationwide's decision, and that it was hard to understand, anti-job creation, and had no factual basis. Simon Lomax, the research director for [[Energy In Depth]], a petroleum industry group, has called the decision reckless and uninformed.&lt;ref name=&quot;EschJul122012&quot; /&gt;

'''Health care industry'''
[[Geisinger Health System]], a physician-led health care system, serves many patients who live in the Pennsylvania towns where Marcellus Shale gas drilling (hydraulic fracturing) is occurring. Geisinger has 2.6 million patients, many hospitals and clinics in the area, and an insurance program. It has archives that include historical health care data for the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Geisinger&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://carbonwaters.org/2012/05/pa-health-care-company-seeks-gas-drilling-facts/ |title=Pa. health care company seeks gas drilling facts : Carbon County Groundwater Guardians |publisher=Carbonwaters.org |date=2012-05-20 |accessdate=2012-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company is concerned about future health costs that might be incurred due to the practice of hydraulic fracturing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Geisinger&quot; /&gt; In addition to drinking water quality concerns, in 2012 OSHA and NIOSH released a warning about worker exposure to crystalline [[silica]], which is related to [[silicosis]],&lt;ref name=&quot;OSHA hazard&quot;&gt;{{cite document |url=http://www.osha.gov/dts/hazardalerts/hydraulic_frac_hazard_alert.html |title=OSHA/NIOSH Hazard Alert. Worker Exposure to Silica during Hydraulic Fracturing |author=OSHA/NIOSH |date=2012 |publisher=United States Department of Labor, Occupational Safety and Health Administration|accessdate=08 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a 2012 OSH article outlined the risk of worker radiation exposure.&lt;ref name=&quot;OSH radiation&quot;&gt;{{cite document |url=http://ohsonline.com/articles/2012/10/01/radiation-sources-in-natural-gas-well-activities.aspx?admgarea=ht.HandProtection |title=Radiation Sources in Natural Gas Well Activities. More attention and monitoring of occupational radiation exposure in the natural gas industry are warranted |author=Gayle Nicoll |date=01 October 2012 |publisher=Occupational Health and Safety|accessdate=06 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Geisinger is currently conducting a study of the health impact of hydraulic fracturing using its database's capacity to examine links between drilling and health by dates and locations, as well as identify control populations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Geisinger&quot; /&gt;

==Environmental and health impact==
{{Main|Environmental impact of hydraulic fracturing in the United States}}
[[File:HydroFrac.png|thumb|400px|Schematic depiction of hydraulic fracturing for shale gas, showing potential [[environmental effect]]s.]]

There are [[Environment (biophysical)|environment]]al concerns, including contamination of [[ground water]], risks to [[air quality]], the potential migration of gases and hydraulic fracturing chemicals to the surface, the potential mishandling of waste, and the health effects of these, like cancer.&lt;ref name=&quot;house1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://democrats.energycommerce.house.gov/sites/default/files/documents/Hydraulic%20Fracturing%20Report%204.18.11.pdf |publisher=Committee on Energy and Commerce U.S. House of Representatives |title=Chemicals Used in Hydraulic Fracturing |date=April 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HeatOnGas&quot;/&gt; There is already evidence of environmental contamination,&lt;ref name=&quot;UT Study&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Fact-Based Regulation for Environmental Protection in Shale Gas Development|url=http://energy.utexas.edu/images/ei_shale_gas_regulation120215.pdf|accessdate=29 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://switchboard.nrdc.org/blogs/amall/incidents_where_hydraulic_frac.html |publisher=U.S. NRDC |title=Incidents where hydraulic fracturing is a suspected cause of drinking water contamination |date=December 2011 |accessdate=23 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 03Mar2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/04/us/04gas.html |title=Pressure Limits Efforts to Police Drilling for Gas |author=Ian Urbina |date=3 March 2011 |newspaper=The New York Times |accessdate=23 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SciAm 30.03.2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=shale-gas-and-hydraulic-fracturing |title=What the Frack? Natural Gas from Subterranean Shale Promises U.S. Energy Independence--With Environmental Costs |author=[http://e360.yale.edu/author/David_Biello/13/ David Biello] |date=30 March 2010 |work=[[Scientific American]] |accessdate=21 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.commondreams.org/view/2012/02/06 |title=Fracking Perils: A Dangerous Misstep on the Road to U.S. Energy Independence |author=Daphne Wysham |date=6 February 2012 |publisher=[[Common Dreams NewsCenter|Common Dreams]] |accessdate=22 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it has been predicted that exposure to chemicals in hydraulic fracturing fluid will increase as gas wells using this technology proliferate.&lt;ref name=&quot;HeatOnGas&quot;&gt;{{cite article|last=Brown |first=Valerie J. |title=Industry Issues: Putting the Heat on Gas |date=February 2007 |journal=Environmental Health Perspectives |publisher=US National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences |issue=115(2) |http=http://ehp03.niehs.nih.gov/article/browseIssue.action?issue=info:doi/10.1289/issue.ehp.v115.i02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some hydraulic fracturing companies have taken steps to protect groundwater and comply with state regulations, including filing completion reports with the appropriate state agencies and submitting to inspections before, during, and after drilling takes place, but are reluctant to release information about proprietary substances in the fluid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornellvet03092012&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;http://www.hydraulicfracturing.com/FAQs/Pages/information.aspx&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

===EPA hydraulic fracturing study===
In 2010 Congress requested that the EPA undertake a new, broader study of hydraulic fracturing.  The report is slated for release in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;Burdeau, Cain. &quot;EPA to Study 'Fracking' Gas Drilling Method.&quot; ''Associated Press''. 18 March 2010. http://abcnews.go.com/Business/wireStory?id=10141059&lt;/ref&gt; The purpose of the EPA study regarding Hydraulic Fracturing is to examine the effects of hydraulic fracturing on the water supply, specifically for human consumption. The research aims to examine the full scope of the water pathway as it moves through the hydraulic fracturing process, including water that is used for the construction of the wells, the fracturing mixture, and subsequent removal and disposal. Fundamental research questions include:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eesi.org/transatlantic-perspectives-shale-gas-development-21-jun-2011 |last=Environmental and Energy Study Institute |title=Transatlantic Perspectives on Shale Gas Development}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*How might large volume water withdrawals from ground and surface water impact drinking water resources?
*What are the possible impacts of releases of flowback and produced water on drinking water resources?
*What are the possible impacts of inadequate treatment of hydraulic fracturing wastewaters on drinking water resources?
The Scientific Advisory Board reviewed the study plan in early March 2011. In June 2011, the EPA announced the locations of its five retrospective case studies, which will examine existing hydrofracking sites for evidence of drinking water contamination. They are:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://water.epa.gov/type/groundwater/uic/class2/hydraulicfracturing/case_studies.cfm |last=U.S. EPA |title=Case Study Locations for Hydraulic Fracturing Study}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Bakken formation|Bakken Shale]] - Kildeer, and Dunn Counties, North Dakota
*[[Barnett Shale]] - Wise and Denton Counties, Texas
*[[Marcellus Formation|Marcellus Shale]] - Bradford and Susquehanna Counties, Pennsylvania
*[[Marcellus Formation|Marcellus Shale]] - Washington County, Pennsylvania
*[[Raton Basin]] - Las Animas County, Colorado
Research should be completed by the end of 2012, and the EPA's Hydraulic Fracturing Report is expected to be completed in 2014.

Industry forces applied pressure to exclude the study of tracer isotopes from the study. Although the study's Science Advisory Board (SAB) pushed EPA to conduct toxicity tests, some members of the chartered SAB suggested that the EPA narrow its planned toxicity testing of chemicals used in the hydraulic fracturing because of the limited resources and time frame.&lt;ref name=&quot;EPA study tracers&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=DiCosmo |first=Bridget |url=http://insideepa.com/201107052369131/EPA-Daily-News/Daily-News/sab-pushes-to-advise-epa-to-conduct-toxicity-tests-in-fracking-study/menu-id-95.html |title=SAB Pushes To Advise EPA To Conduct Toxicity Tests In Fracking Study   |quote=But some members of the chartered SAB are suggesting that the fracking panel revise its recommendation that the agency scale back its planned toxicity testing of chemicals used in the hydraulic fracturing, or fracking, process, because of the limited resources and time frame...Chesapeake Energy supported the draft recommendation, saying that “an in-depth study of toxicity, the development of new analytical methods and tracers are not practical given the budget and schedule limitation of the study.”|date=15 May 2012 |work=InsideEPA |publisher=US Environmental Protection Agency |accessdate=2012-05-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Chesapeake Energy agreed,&lt;ref name=&quot;Chesapeake&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://insideepa.com/iwpfile.html?file=jul2011%2Fepa2011_1273b.pdf |title=Letter from Chesapeake Energy to EPA |last=Satterfield |first=John |date=30 June 2011 |work=InsideEPA |publisher=US Environmental Protection Agency |accessdate=2012-05-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; stating “an in-depth study of toxicity, the development of new analytical methods and tracers are not practical given the budget and schedule limitation of the study.”&lt;ref name=&quot;EPA study tracers&quot; /&gt; Thus, despite concerns about the elevated levels of [[iodine-131]] (a radioactive tracer used in hydraulic fracturing) in drinking water in Philadelphia and Pittsburgh, downstream from hydraulic fracturing sites,&lt;ref name=&quot;EPA radiation&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/jeffmcmahon/2011/04/10/epa-new-radiation-highs-in-little-rock-milk-philadelphia-drinking-water/ |title=EPA: New Radiation Highs in Little Rock Milk, Philadelphia Drinking Water |author=Jeff McMahon |date=10 April 2011 |publisher=Forbes |accessdate=22 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.epa.gov/japan011/rert/radnet-sampling-data.html#water|title=Japanese Nuclear Emergency: Radiation Monitoring  |date=30 June 2011 |publisher=EPA |accessdate=23 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carbon County&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://carbonwaters.org/2011/07/cancer-patients-urine-suspected-in-wissahickon-iodine-131-levels/ |title=Cancer patients’ urine suspected in Wissahickon iodine-131 levels |author=Sandy Bauers |date=21 July 2011 |publisher=Philadelphia inquirer, Carbon County Groundwater Guardians |accessdate=25 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; iodine-131 is not listed among the chemicals to be monitored in the draft plan for the study. Other known radioactive tracers used in hydraulic fracturing&lt;ref name=&quot;No5635712&quot;&gt;[http://ip.com/patent/US5635712] Scott III, George L. (03-June-1997) US Patent No. 5635712: Method for monitoring the hydraulic fracturing of a subterranean formation. US Patent Publications.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;US4415805&quot;&gt;[http://ip.com/patent/US4415805] Fertl; Walter H. (15-Nov-1983)  US Patent No. US4415805: Method and apparatus for evaluating multiple stage fracturing or earth formations surrounding a borehole. US Patent Publications.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;US5441110&quot;&gt;[http://ip.com/patent/US5441110] Scott III, George L. (15-Aug-1995)  US Patent No. US5441110: System and method for monitoring fracture growth during hydraulic fracture treatment. US Patent Publications.&lt;/ref&gt; but not listed as chemicals to be studied include isotopes of gold, xenon, rubidium, iridium, scandium, and krypton.[http://www.shalegas.energy.gov/resources/HFStudyPlanDraft_SAB_020711.pdf]

The EPA Hydraulic Fracturing Draft Study Plan can be found here.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Environmental Protection Agencey (EPA)|title=Hydraulic Fracturing|url=http://www.epa.gov/hfstudy/|work=EPA's Draft Hydraulic Fracturing Study Plan|accessdate=6 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Water quality studies===

=====1987=====

'''Kaiser Exploration and Mining Company incident''' In 1987, an [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|Environmental Protection Agency]] (EPA) report was published that indicated fracture fluid invasion into a well in [[West Virginia]]. The well, drilled by Kaiser Exploration and Mining Company, was found to have induced fractures that allowed fracture fluid to contaminate groundwater. The [[Petroleum Institute]] agreed that hydraulic fracturing had caused the drinking water contamination, and the EPA held it up as an example of the hazards created by the technique.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 03Aug2011&quot;/&gt;

=====2004=====
In the United States, a 2004 [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|Environmental Protection Agency]] (EPA) study concluded that the process was safe and didn't warrant further study, because there was &quot;no unequivocal evidence&quot; of health risks, and the fluids were neither necessarily hazardous nor able to travel far underground.  That study, however, was not intended as a general study of hydraulic fracturing, but only of its use in [[coalbed methane]] deposits, and the study did not consider impacts above ground.&lt;ref name=businessweek /&gt; The EPA report did find uncertainties in knowledge of how fracturing fluid migrates through rocks, and upon its release service companies voluntarily agreed to stop using diesel fuel as a component of fracturing fluid in coalbed methane walls due to public concerns of its potential as a source of [[benzene]] contamination.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.epa.gov/ogwdw/uic/pdfs/cbmstudy_attach_uic_final_fact_sheet.pdf |title=Evaluation of Impacts to Underground Sources of Drinking Water by Hydraulic Fracturing of Coalbed Methane Reservoirs; National Study Final Report |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Environmental group [[Riverkeeper]] presented a report to the EPA of over 100 cases of contamination.&lt;ref name=RubinkamEsch2010/&gt; It has published a report of various environmental impacts using reports from federal and state regulators.&lt;ref name=Riverkeeper2010&gt;Michaels C, Simpson JL, Wegner W. (2010). [http://cleanwaternotdirtydrilling.org/library/doc_download/28-fractured-communities-case-studies-of-the-environmental-impacts-of-gas-drilling Fractured Communities: Case Studies of the Environmental Impacts of Gas Drilling]. Riverkeeper.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====2008=====
The increased use of hydraulic fracturing prompted more speculation about its environmental dangers.  A 2008 investigation of benzene contamination in Colorado and Wyoming led some EPA officials to suggest hydraulic fracturing as a culprit. One of the authors of the 2004 EPA report states that it has been misconstrued by the gas-drilling industry.&lt;ref name=businessweek&gt;An example of the composition of a typical fracturing fluid can be found in [http://www.energyindepth.org/frac-fluid.pdf Typical Solution Used in Hydraulic Fracturing], [http://www.energyindepth.org energyindepth.org]. A more complete listing of chemicals used in fracturing fluid, which includes kerosene, benzene, tolulene, xylene, formaldehyde to name a few, may be found in [http://www.dec.ny.gov/docs/materials_minerals_pdf/ogdsgeischap5.pdf Chapter 5 Natural Gas Development Activities And High‐Volume Hydraulic Fracturing].{{Clarify|date=June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====2010=====
'''State Investigation - Pennsylvania''' The investigation was initiated after a water well exploded on New Year's Day in 2009.  The state investigation revealed that Cabot Oil &amp; Gas Company &quot;had allowed combustible gas to escape into the region's groundwater supplies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Rubinkam, [http://www.pressconnects.com/article/20100415/NEWS11/4150364/Pa.-regulators-shut-down-Cabot-drilling Pa. regulators shut down Cabot drilling], April 15, 2010, pressconnects.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lustgarten|first=Abrahm|title=Pa. Residents Sue Gas Driller for Contamination, Health Concerns|accessdate=2 June 2011|newspaper=Pro Publica|date=20 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arsenic, barium, DEHP, glycol compounds, manganese, phenol, methane, and sodium were found in unacceptable levels in the wells.&lt;ref name=&quot;EPA Dimock letter 2012&quot;&gt;{{cite report|url=http://www.epaosc.org/sites/7555/files/dimock-action-memo-01-19-12%5B1%5D.pdf |author=Fetzer, Richard M. |date=19 January 2012 |title=Action Memorandum - Request for funding for a Removal Action at the Dimock Residential Groundwater Site|accessdate=27 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2010, the state of Pennsylvania banned [[Cabot Oil &amp; Gas]] Corp. from further drilling in the entire state until it plugs wells believed to be the source of contamination of the drinking water of 14 homes in [[Dimock Township, Susquehanna County, Pennsylvania|Dimock Township, Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Legere&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Legere|first=Laura|title=Gas company slapped with drilling ban and fine|url=http://thetimes-tribune.com/news/gas-company-slapped-with-drilling-ban-and-fine-1.731625#axzz1LnTyIdBb|publisher=The Times Tribune|accessdate=8 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cabot Oil &amp; Gas was also required to financially compensate residents and provide alternative sources of water until mitigation systems were installed in affected wells.&lt;ref name=&quot;EPA Dimock letter 2012&quot; /&gt;

'''United States Environmental Protection Agency investigation - Wyoming''' Complaints about water quality from residents near a gas field in [[Pavillion, Wyoming]] prompted an EPA groundwater investigation, which reported detections of methane and other chemicals, some used or produced in fracking, and some at dangerous levels.&lt;ref name=&quot;EPAPav&quot;&gt;{{cite press release |title= EPA Releases Draft Findings of Pavillion, Wyoming Ground Water Investigation for Public Comment and Independent Scientific Review |url=http://yosemite.epa.gov/opa/admpress.nsf/1e5ab1124055f3b28525781f0042ed40/ef35bd26a80d6ce3852579600065c94e |date=8 December 2011 |accessdate=27 February 2012|publisher= [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; A draft report stated that the impact to ground water could be explained by fracking.&lt;ref name=&quot;EPA Pavillion Dec2011&quot;&gt;{{cite report|title=Investigation of Ground Water Contamination near Pavillion, Wyoming. Draft |first1=Dominic C. |last1=DiGiulio |first2= Richard T. |last2=Wilkin |first3= Carlyle |last3= Miller | first4=Gregory |last4 = Oberley |publisher = [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]] |url=http://www.epa.gov/region8/superfund/wy/pavillion/EPA_ReportOnPavillion_Dec-8-2011.pdf | month = December | year = 2011 | format = PDF |accessdate=23 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Phillips 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://stateimpact.npr.org/pennsylvania/2011/12/08/epa-blames-fracking-for-wyoming-groundwater-contamination/ |title=EPA Blames Fracking for Wyoming Groundwater Contamination |author=Susan Phillips |date=8 December 2011 |work=StateImpact Penn­syl­va­nia |publisher=WITF, WHYY &amp; NPR |accessdate=6 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report said that ground water contamination of the nature found in Pavilion is &quot;typically infeasible or too expensive to remediate or restore (GAO 1989).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EPA Pavillion Dec2011&quot;/&gt;

=====2011=====
'''Congressional Study''' A 2011 study by Congressional Democrats found that, in the process of hydraulic fracturing, &quot;oil and gas companies injected hundreds of millions of gallons of hazardous or carcinogenic chemicals into wells in more than 13 states from 2005 to 2009,&quot; according to the [[New York Times]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Urbina|first=Ian|title=Chemicals Were Injected Into Wells, Report Says|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/17/science/earth/17gas.html?ref=health|accessdate=2 May 2011|newspaper=New York Times|date=2011-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Congressional study had identified 750 different chemicals in that fluid; 29 of which are considered to be known or possible hazards or carcinogens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=CHEMICALS USED IN HYDRAULIC FRACTURING|url=http://democrats.energycommerce.house.gov/sites/default/files/documents/Hydraulic%20Fracturing%20Report%204.18.11.pdf|publisher=US House of Representatives|accessdate=14 December 2011|month=April|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A 2011 investigation by the New York Times based on various leaked EPA documents found that hydraulic fracturing had resulted in significant increases of radioactive material including radium and carcinogens including benzene in major rivers and watersheds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Documents: Natural Gas's Toxic Waste|url=http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2011/02/27/us/natural-gas-documents-1.html#document/p416/a9943|accessdate=2 May 2011|newspaper=New York Times|date=2011-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; At one site the amount of benzene discharged into the [[Allegheny River]] after treatment was 28 times accepted levels for drinking water.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina&quot;/&gt;

'''Duke University Study''' A study published in May 2011 by researchers at Duke University found that &quot;levels of flammable methane gas in drinking water wells increased to dangerous levels when those water supplies were close to natural gas wells.&quot;  Water samples from 68 private water wells in the states of Pennsylvania and New York were tested and some were found to have extremely high concentrations of methane: 64 milligrams of methane per liter of drinking water, compared with a normal level of one milligram or lower. The study found that, on average, methane concentrations 17 times above normal in samples taken from water wells near shale gas drilling sites employing hydraulic fracturing. According to one of the authors of the study, &quot;That sort of concentration is up at a level where people worry about an explosion hazard.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2011/05/02/1100682108 |title=Methane contamination of drinking water accompanying gas-well drilling and hydraulic fracturing |publisher=Pnas.org |date=2011-05-09 |accessdate=2011-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-13333473 | work=BBC News | title=Shale gas drilling 'contaminates drinking water' | date=9 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The average concentration of methane in the water wells near drilling sites lies within a range that, according to the U.S. Department of the Interior, is dangerous and requires urgent &quot;hazard mitigation&quot; action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lustgarten|first=Abraham|title=Scientific Study Links Flammable Drinking Water to Fracking|url=http://www.propublica.org/article/scientific-study-links-flammable-drinking-water-to-fracking|work=Propublica|accessdate=10 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Osborn SG, Vengosh A, Warner NR, Jackson, B|year=2011|title=Methane contamination of drinking water accompanying gas-well drilling and hydraulic fracturing|url=http://www.biology.duke.edu/jackson/pnas2011.html| journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, U.S.A.,|volume=108|issue=20|pages=8172–8176| doi=10.1073/pnas.1100682108|accessdate=2011-05-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; They found that the type of gas detected at high levels in the water was the same type of gas that energy companies were extracting from thousands of feet underground, strongly implying that the gas may be seeping underground through natural or man-made faults and fractures, or coming from cracks in the well structure itself &quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lustgarten|first=Abrahm|title=Scientific Study Links Flammable Drinking Water to Fracking|url=http://www.propublica.org/article/scientific-study-links-flammable-drinking-water-to-fracking|publisher=propublica|accessdate=11 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study concluded that fracking has seriously contaminated shallow groundwater supplies in northeast Pennsylvania with flammable methane.  The study does not discuss how pervasive such contamination might be in other areas where drilling for shale gas has taken place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url =  http://news.sciencemag.org/sciencenow/2011/05/study-high-tech-gas-drilling-is-.html?ref=hp | journal = Science Now | title =  Study: High-Tech Gas Drilling Is Fouling Drinking Water | author = Richard A. Kerr | date = 13 May 2011 | page = 775 | volume = 332 | accessdate = 2011-06-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Though the study found thermogenic groundwater methane concentrations were higher near active drilling sites compared to neighboring nonextracting sites, no traces of hydraulic fracturing fluids were detected in any of the analyzed groundwater samples.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2011/05/02/1100682108 |title=Methane contamination of drinking water accompanying gas-well drilling and hydraulic fracturing |publisher=Pnas.org |date=2011-05-09 |accessdate=2012-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

'''SUNY Study''' According to a study performed by a lecturer at the State University of New York, Oneonta, nearly two percent of fracked gas wells have the potential to cause groundwater contamination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holzman, David C.&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Holzman|first=David|title=Methane Found in Well Water Near Fracking Sites|url=http://ehp03.niehs.nih.gov/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1289%2Fehp.119-a289|publisher=Environmental Health Perspectives|accessdate=14 Feb 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Colorado School of Public Health''' [[Colorado School of Public Health]] (Garfield county, Colorado) released a second draft report of the Battlement Mesa Health Impact Assessment on March 1, 2011 for public comment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Colorado School of Public Health|title=Battlement Mesa HIA/EHMS|url=http://www.garfield-county.com/public-health/battlement-mesa-health-impact-assessment-draft2.aspx|publisher=Garfield County|accessdate=11 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''University of Michigan-Ann Arbor''' In May 2011 the [[University of Michigan-Ann Arbor]] began studying the effects of natural gas fracking on the Great Lakes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.umich.edu/newsandinfo/releases/Pages/seagrant.aspx |title=MLaw Receives Grant from National Sea Grant Law Center |publisher=Law.umich.edu |date=2011-05-17 |accessdate=2011-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====2012=====

'''University of Texas Study'''  The UT study found that all steps in the process except the actual injection of the fluid (which proponents artificially separated from the rest of the process and designated &quot;hydraulic fracturing&quot;) have resulted in environmental contamination.&lt;ref name=&quot;UT Study&quot;/&gt;  The radioactivity of the injected fluid itself was not assessed in the University of Texas study.&lt;ref name=&quot;UT Study&quot; /&gt;  The other stages or &quot;phases of the shale gas development life cycle&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;UT Study&quot; /&gt; into which hydraulic fracturing has been divided in various reports are (1) drill pad construction and operation, (2) the construction, integrity, and performance of the wellbores, (3) the flowback of the fluid back towards the surface, (4) blowouts and spills, (5) integrity of other pipelines involved and (6) the disposal of the flowback, including waste water and other waste products.&lt;ref name=&quot;fuelfix&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Fact-Based Regulation for Environmental Protection in Shale Gas Development|url=http://fuelfix.com/blog/2012/02/16/ut-study-fracturing-itself-not-connected-to-water-pollution/ |title=Fracturing ‘has no direct’ link to water pollution, UT study finds    |author=Vaughan, Vicki |date= 16 February 2012  |accessdate=3 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vancouversun&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Fracking does not contaminate groundwater: study released in Vancouver|url=http://www.vancouversun.com/news/Fracking+does+contaminate+groundwater+study+released+Vancouver/6165532/story.html |author=Munro, Margaret |date= 17 February 2012  |accessdate=3 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; These stages were all reported to be sources of contamination in the University of Texas study.&lt;ref name=&quot;UT Study&quot; /&gt;  The study concluded that if hydraulic fracturing is to be conducted in an environmentally safe manner, these issues need to be addressed first.&lt;ref name=&quot;UT Study&quot; /&gt; It is to the university's credit that the distortion seemed only to be the focus on the injection stage. There are extensive links between UT and the oil &amp; gas industry, with the giving of fossil-fuel behemoth [[Royal Dutch Shell]] to the university currently standing at more than $24.8 million, $4m alone having been handed over for 2012.&lt;ref name=&quot;UTweb 14Feb2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.utexas.edu/news/2012/02/14/shell_oil_invests/ |title=Shell Oil Company Invests Nearly $4 Million in The University of Texas at Austin |date=14 February 2012 |publisher=UT Austin website |accessdate=5 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HBJ 15Feb2012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bizjournals.com/houston/news/2012/02/15/shell-oil-invests-39m-in-ut.html |title=Shell Oil invests $3.9M in UT |author=Sandra Zaragoza |date=15 February 2012 |newspaper=Houston Business Journal |accessdate=5 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2011, Shell has partnered Texas in a program called [http://www.beg.utexas.edu/sutur/index.php Shell-UT Unconventional Research], and the university has a similar research program in place with [[Exxon Mobil]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Clanton 13Sep2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.chron.com/business/energy/article/Shell-UT-to-study-better-shale-production-methods-2167340.php |title=Shell, UT to study better shale production methods |author=Brett Clanton |date=13 September 2011 |newspaper=Houston Chronicle |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Halliburton]], the largest supplier of fracking services in the United States, has also given millions of dollars to the university.&lt;ref name=&quot;UTweb 28Feb2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.utexas.edu/news/2007/02/28/support/ |title=Halliburton Gives $90,000 in Grants to The University of Texas at Austin |date=28 February 2007 |publisher=UT Austin website |accessdate=5 March 2012 |quote=Energy services company Halliburton has contributed $90,000 to support academic programs at The University of Texas at Austin, bringing the company's total university giving to nearly $7 million.}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Statoil]] announced a $5m research agreement (part of which will focus on oil shale) with UT's Bureau of Economic Geology in September 2011, whose program director, Ian Duncan, was the senior contributor for the parts of the Texas study to do with the environmental impacts of shale gas development.&lt;ref name=&quot;UT Study&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Statoil buys&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAS 19Sep2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.statesman.com/business/norway-based-energy-company-ut-agree-on-5-1867592.html |title=Norway-based energy company, UT agree on $5 million research program |author=Barry Harrell |date=19 September 2011 |newspaper=The Austin American-Statesman |accessdate=5 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Cornell Study''' A 2012 study out of Cornell's College of Veterinary Medicine by Robert Oswald, a professor of molecular medicine at Cornell's College of Veterinary Medicine, and veterinarian Michelle Bamberger, DVM, soon to be published in 'New Solutions: A Journal of Environmental and Occupational Health Policy,' suggests that hydraulic fracking is sickening and killing cows, horses, goats, llamas, chickens, dogs, cats, fish and other wildlife, as well as humans. The study covered cases in Colorado, Louisiana, New York, Ohio, Pennsylvania and Texas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornellvet03092012&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.news.cornell.edu/stories/March12/FrackingAnimals.html|title=Study suggests hydrofracking is killing farm animals, pets |author=Ramanuja, Krishna  |date=7 March 2012 |work=Cornell Chronicle Online |publisher=Cornell University|accessdate=9 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case studies include reports of sick animals, stunted growth, and dead animals after exposure to hydraulic fracturing spills from dumping of the fluid into streams and from workers slitting the lining of a wastewater impoundment (evaporation ponds) so that it would drain and be able to accept more waste. The researchers stated that it was difficult to assess health impact because of the industry's strategic lobbying efforts that resulted in legislation allowing them to keep the proprietary chemicals in the fluid secret, protecting them from being held legally responsible for contamination. Bamberger stated that if you don't know what chemicals are, you can't conduct pre-drilling tests and establish a baseline to prove that chemicals found postdrilling are from hydraulic fracturing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornellvet03092012&quot; /&gt; The researchers recommended requiring disclosure of all hydraulic fracturing fluids, that nondisclosure agreements not be allowed when public health is at risk, testing animals raised near hydraulic fracturing sites and animal products (milk, cheese, etc.) from animal raised near hydraulic fracturing sites prior to selling them to market, monitoring of water, soil and air more closely, and testing the air, water, soil and animals prior to drilling and at regular intervals thereafter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornellvet03092012&quot;/&gt;

'''Meyers Aquifer study in ''Ground Water'''''
An article by Tom Myers, a researcher from Reno, Nevada, in the journal ''Ground Water''&lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers study&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Potential Contaminant Pathways from Hydraulically Fractured Shale to Aquifers |author=Meyers, T. |date=17 April 2012 |journal=Ground Water (National Ground Water Association) | doi=10.1111/j.1745-6584.2012.00933.x |publisher=Wiley|accessdate=4 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that hydraulic fracturing fluids under pressure can migrate upward through available crevices and reach shallow drinking-water aquifers in as little as three years. Myers is an independent consultant who has worked for conservation groups and governments. Myers was hired by Catskill Mountainkeeper, a New York-based environmental group that opposes fracking, and The Park Foundation in Ithaca, which offers a variety of grants. Terry Engelder, professor of geosciences at The Pennsylvania State University in University Park, said that the computer models used by Myers contain errors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aquifer study&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-05-03/fracking-fluids-may-migrate-to-aquifers-researcher-says.html |title=Fracking Fluids May Migrate to Aquifers, Researcher Says |author=Efstathiou, Jim  |date=3 May 2012 |publisher=Bloomberg|accessdate=4 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''U.S. Geological Survey and EPA retest Pavillion, Wyoming''' In 2012 the U.S. Geological Survey tested one of two EPA monitoring wells near Pavillion, Wyoming, and found evidence of methane, ethane, diesel compounds and phenol, which the EPA had also identified in its 2011 report.&lt;ref name=&quot;AP 09272012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=New Data, but Not Much New in Wyo. Fracking Study |author=Mead Gruver |url=http://abcnews.go.com/US/wireStory/data-wyo-frack-site-await-interpretation-17335835#.UGfJflFWQyo|publisher=Associated Press|date=27 September 2012 |accessdate=30 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rob Jackson, an environmental scientist at Duke University, described the methane, ethane, and propane concentrations as very high, consistent with fossil fuel rather than natural sources.&lt;ref name=&quot;bswk 09272012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Diesel in Water Near Fracking Confirms EPA Tests Wyoming Disputes |author=Mark Drajem |url=http://www.businessweek.com/news/2012-09-26/diesel-compounds-found-in-water-near-wyoming-fracking-site |publisher=Bloomberg News|date=27 September 2012 |accessdate=28 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, the EPA retested water in Pavillion, and briefed the homeowners, but has not yet released the results to the public. Pavillion resident John Fenton reported that the EPA told him the recent test results were consistent with previous results, and that the EPA recommended that they don't cook with or drink their water.&lt;ref name=&quot;bswk 09272012&quot; /&gt;

===Well blowouts and spills of fracturing fluids===	 
A well blowout in [[Clearfield County, Pennsylvania]] on June 3, 2010, sent more than 35,000 gallons of hydraulic fracturing fluids into the air and onto the surrounding landscape in a forested area. Campers were evacuated and the company [[EOG Resources]] and the well completion company C.C. Forbes have been ordered to cease all operations in the state of Pennsylvania pending investigation. The [[Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection]] has called this a &quot;serious incident&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.riverreporter.com/issues/10-06-10/news-explosions.html Gas eruption fallout], The River Reporter, June 10–16, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anya Litvak, [http://pittsburgh.bizjournals.com/pittsburgh/stories/2010/06/07/daily32.html Marcellus Shale well blowout prompts second DEP suspension], Pittsburgh business Times, June 9, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Natural gas drilling and seismic events===
Injection of fluid into subsurface [[geological]] structures, such as [[fault (geology)|fault]]s and fractures, reduces the effective normal stress acting across these structures.  If sufficient [[shear stress]] is present, the structure may slip in shear and generate [[seismic]] events over a range of magnitudes; it is possible that natural gas drilling may have caused earthquakes in North Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Casselman|first=Ben|title=Wastewater Disposal Well May Have Caused Texas Earthquakes|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB125020088034530363.html|accessdate=8 May 2011|newspaper=Wall Street Journal|date=13 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Subsidence is not directly caused by hydraulic fracturing but may occur after considerable production of oil or ground water. [[Subsidence]] occurs over reservoirs whether they have been subject to hydraulic fracturing or not because it is a result of producing fluids from the reservoir and lowering the reservoir pore pressure. The subsidence process can be associated with some seismicity.  Reports of minor [[tremor]]s of no greater than 2.8 on the [[Richter magnitude scale|Richter scale]] were reported on June 2, 2009 in [[Cleburne, Texas]], the first in the town's 140-year history.&lt;ref name=associatepress&gt;{{cite news | title = Drilling Might Be Culprit Behind Texas Earthquakes | agency = Associated Press | date = June v12, 2009 | url = http://www.newsvine.com/_news/2009/06/12/2923921-drilling-might-be-culprit-behind-texas-earthquakes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fracking connected to deep well waste water disposal has been banned in [[Arkansas]] due to the risk of contaminating [[aquifer]]s if the [[earthquake]]s it induced continued.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Fracking Disposal Wells Linked to Earthquakes, Banned in Arkansas |url=http://planetsave.com/2011/09/16/fracking-disposal-wells-linked-to-earthquakes-banned-in-arkansas/|date=16 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Geological Survey is working on ways to head off quakes from wastewater wells.&lt;ref name=&quot;nprFracking&quot;&gt;Joyce, Christopher, [http://www.npr.org/2012/01/05/144694550/man-made-quakes-blame-fracking-and-drilling How Fracking Wastewater Is Tied To Quakes], National Public Radio, 2012-01-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air and health===
Many particulates and chemicals can be released into the atmosphere during the process of hydraulic fracturing, such as sulfuric oxide, nitrous oxides, volatile organic compounds (VOC), benzene, toluene, diesel fuel, hydrogen sulfide which can have serious health implications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Oil and Gas Air Pollution|url=http://www.earthworksaction.org /oilgasairpollution.cfm|publisher=Earthworks|accessdate=11 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study conducted between August 2011 and July 2012 as part of Earthworks’ Oil &amp; Gas Accountability Project (OGAP) found chemical contaminants in the air and water of rural communities affected by the Shale extraction process in central New York and Pennsylvania. The study found disproportionately high numbers of adverse health effects in children and adults in those communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;IPS 10212012&quot; /&gt; 

A potential hazard that is commonly overlooked is the venting of bulk sand silos directly to atmosphere.  When they are being filled, or emptied during the fracture job, a fine cloud of silica particulate will be vented directly into atmosphere.  This dust has the potential to travel many kilometers on the wind directly into populated areas.  While the immediate personnel are wearing personal protective equipment, other people in the area of a well fracture can potentially be exposed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Oil and Gas Air Pollution|url=http://www.earthworksaction.org/oilgasairpollution.cfm|publisher=Earthworks|accessdate=8 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Workplace safety==
The EPA states in their Hydraulic Fracturing Study Plan (2011) that the exposure to hydraulic fracturing chemicals in an occupational setting needs to be examined to determine the acute and chronic effects on health. The exposure risks such as “transport, mixing, delivery, and potential accidents” have not been properly assessed (p.&amp;nbsp;57).&lt;ref name=&quot;hydraulic fracturing study plan draft 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Hydraulic Fracturing Study Plan Draft 2011|url=http://water.epa.gov/type/groundwater/uic/class2/hydraulicfracturing/upload/HFStudyPlanDraft_SAB_020711.pdf|work=Environmental Protection Agency's Hydraulic Fracturing Study Plan Draft 2011|publisher=Environmental Protection Agency|accessdate=3 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hydraulic fracturing also affects individuals in close proximity to the activity, like the case previously discussed about the nurse who became ill after exposure from treating a hydraulic fracturing worker (Frankowski, 2008).&lt;ref name=&quot;hydraulic fracturing study plan draft 2011&quot;/&gt;

== Lawsuits ==
In September 2010, a lawsuit was filed in Pennsylvania alleging that [[Southwestern Energy Company]] contaminated aquifers through a defective cement casing in the well.&lt;ref name=RubinkamEsch2010&gt;Rubinkam M, Esch M. (Sept 10, 2010). [http://www.mnn.com/earth-matters/energy/stories/lawsuit-gas-drilling-fluid-ruined-pennsylavania-water-wells Lawsuit: Gas drilling fluid ruined Pennsylvania{{sic|hide=y}} water wells]. AP.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2011, Northeast Natural Energy sued the town of [[Morgantown, West Virginia]], for its ban on hydraulic fracturing in the Marcellus Shale within a mile of the town's borders. The ban had been initiated to protect the municipal water supply as well as the town's inhabitants, in the absence at the state level of regulations specific to hydraulic fracturing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Associated Press|title=Company sues W.Va town over drilling ban|url=http://www.businessweek.com/ap/financialnews/D9O4DT700.htm|accessdate=28 June 2011|newspaper=Bloomberg Businessweek|date=27 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; There have been other cases as well.  After court cases concerning contamination from hydraulic fracturing are settled, the documents are sealed, and information regarding contamination is not available to researchers or the general public. While the American Petroleum Institute deny that this practice has hidden problems with gas drilling, others believe it has and could lead to unnecessary risks to public safety and health.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 03Aug2011&quot;/&gt;

==Regulation==
The amount of proposed regulatory legislation related to hydraulic fracturing has dramatically increased within state legislatures since 2005. This is in part due to the fact hydraulic fracturing has started in areas in which residents are unfamiliar with natural gas operations. The majority of the proposed bills specifically address one aspect of natural gas drilling, for example wastewater treatment, though some are more comprehensive and consider multiple regulatory concerns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Pless|first=Jacquelyn|title=Fracking Update: What States Are Doing to Ensure Safe Natural Gas Extraction|url=http://www.ncsl.org/issues-research/energyhome/fracking-update-what-states-are-doing-to-ensure-s.aspx|accessdate=21 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Federal versus state regulation debate===
There is discussion regarding whether control of hydraulic fracturing should be at the state or federal level.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 07052012&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mlive 10192012&quot; /&gt; Advocates of state level control of energy sources (e.g., oil, gas, wind and solar), argue that a state approach allows each state to create regulations and review processes that fit the states' particular geology, ecology and citizen concerns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mlive 10192012&quot; /&gt; Critics say that this would create a patchwork of inconsistent regulations.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 07052012&quot; /&gt; They also note that the components and consequences of energy development (e.g., emissions, commerce, wastewater, earthquakes, and radiation) may cross states lines, and argue that regulations need to consider the overall impact on all states. This would require regulation at the federal level. Local and state governments may also lack resources to initiate and defend against corporate legal action related to hydraulic fracturing.&lt;ref name=&quot;TimesUnion&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OilGasJournal&quot; /&gt; 

Those supporting federal regulation think that it will provide more consistent, uniform standards.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 07052012&quot; /&gt; They say that there is a need for national environment and public health standards, including those related to water and air pollution (e.g., public disclosure of chemicals used in hydraulic fracturing, protection of drinking water sources, and control of air pollutants).&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 07052012&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mlive 10192012&quot; /&gt; An compromise approach called, &quot;cooperative federalism&quot; has been proposed for hydraulic fracturing. This approach has been used for coal since 1977. In this approach, the federal government sets baseline standards rather than detailed specifications, which allows states more flexibility in how they meet the standards. It would require the government to remove the regulatory exemptions for hydraulic fracturing (e.g., the [[Energy Policy Act of 2005]], which exempted oil and gas producers from certain requirements of the Safe Drinking Water Act), and develop a comprehensive set of regulations for the industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 07052012&quot; /&gt;

===Federal===
On August 7, 1997, the [[Eleventh Circuit Court]] ordered the United States Environmental Protection Agency to reevaluate its stance on hydraulic fracturing based on a lawsuit brought by the Legal Environmental Assistance Foundation. Up until that decision, the EPA deemed that hydraulic fracturing did not fall under the rules in the [[Safe Drinking Water Act]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Did the 11th Ciurcuit Crack &quot;Frac&quot;? – Hydraulic Fracturing after the Court’s Landmark LEAF Decision |url=https://litigation-essentials.lexisnexis.com/webcd/app?action=DocumentDisplay&amp;crawlid=1&amp;doctype=cite&amp;docid=18+Va.+Envtl.+L.J.+507&amp;srctype=smi&amp;srcid=3B15&amp;key=9eb6c4315bb9758fd3d5ea7bfce873d1 |journal= Virginia Environmental Law Journal 
|volume=18 |issue= 4  |year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the impact of this decision was localized to Alabama, it forced the EPA to evaluate its oversight responsibility under the Safe Drinking Water Act for hydraulic fracturing. In 2004, the EPA released a study that concluded the threat to drinking water from hydraulic fracturing was “minimal” and the [[Energy Policy Act of 2005]] exempted fractured wells from being re-classified as [[injection well]]s, which would place them under federal regulation under the Safe Drinking Water Act.&lt;ref name=businessweek&gt;{{cite news 
| title = Does Natural-Gas Drilling Endanger Water Supplies? 
| work = [[BusinessWeek]] 
| date = November 11, 2008 
| url = http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/08_47/b4109000334640.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was originally intended to regulate disposal wells. The [[Energy Policy Act of 2005]] did not exempt fracturing wells when diesel fuel is used as a component in the fracturing fluid. Some US house representatives have petitioned the EPA to take a broad interpretation of the definition of &quot;diesel fuel&quot; in order to increase the agency's regulatory power over hydraulic fracturing. They argue that the intent of the current limitation is not to prevent the use of a small subset of diesel compounds, but rather a safety measure to decrease the probability of accidental groundwater contamination with toxic BTEX chemicals (benzene, toluene, ethylbenzene and xylenes) that are present in diesel compounds&lt;ref&gt;[http://democrats.energycommerce.house.gov/sites/default/files/documents/Letter_08.08.11_DieselEPA_1.pdf Letter from Representatives Henry A. Waxman, Edward J. Markey, Diana DeGette, and Rush Holt to EPA Administrator Lisa Jackson, 8 August 2011 ]&lt;/ref&gt;
Congress has been urged to repeal the 2005 regulatory exemption under the Energy Policy Act of 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mulkern&quot;&gt;{{cite news 
| title = Industry campaign targets 'hydraulic fracturing' bill 
| newspaper = The New York Times 
| date = May 7, 2009 
| url = http://www.nytimes.com/gwire/2009/05/07/07greenwire-industry-campaign-targets-hydraulic-fracturing-10572.html 
| first1=Anne C. 
| last1=Mulkern 
| accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Fracturing Responsibility and Awareness of Chemicals Act|FRAC Act]], introduced in June 2009, would eliminate the exemption and might allow producing wells to be reclassified as injection wells placing them under federal jurisdiction in states without approved UIC programs.

====Fracturing Responsibility and Awareness of Chemicals Act====
Congress has been urged to repeal the 2005 regulatory exemption under the Energy Policy Act of 2005 by supporting The [[Fracturing Responsibility and Awareness of Chemicals Act|FRAC Act]], introduced in June 2009, but has so far refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mulkern&quot;/&gt; In June 2009 two identical bills named the [[Fracturing Responsibility and Awareness of Chemicals Act]] were introduced to both the United States House and the Senate.  The House bill was introduced by representatives [[Diana DeGette]], D-Colo., [[Maurice Hinchey]] D-N.Y., and [[Jared Polis]], D-Colo.  The Senate version was introduced by senators [[Bob Casey, Jr.|Bob Casey]], D-Pa., and [[Chuck Schumer]], D-N.Y.  These bills are designed to amend the Safe Drinking Water Act. This would allow the Environmental Protection Agency to regulate hydraulic fracturing that occurs in states which have not taken primacy in UIC regulation. The bill required the energy industry to reveal what chemicals are being used in the sand-water mixture. The [[111th United States Congress]] adjourned on January 3, 2011, without taking any significant action on the FRAC Act. The FRAC Act was re-introduced in both houses of the [[112th United States Congress]]. In the Senate, Sen. [[Bob Casey, Jr.|Bob Casey]] (D-PA) introduced S. 587 on March 15, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=s112-587 H.R. 1084: S. 587: FRAC Act]&lt;/ref&gt; In the House, Rep. [[Diana DeGette]] (D-CO) introduced H.R. 1084 on March 24, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=h112-1084 H.R. 1084: Fracturing Responsibility and Awareness of Chemicals Act of 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; As of March 2012 Congress had not yet passed either of The [[Fracturing Responsibility and Awareness of Chemicals Act|FRAC Act]] bills.&lt;ref name=&quot;H.R. 1084&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=h112-1084 |title=H.R. 1084: Fracturing Responsibility and Awareness of Chemicals Act of 2011 |publisher=GovTrack.us |accessdate=9 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;S. 587: FRAC Act&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=s112-587|title=S. 587: FRAC Act |publisher=GovTrack.us |accessdate=9 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The oil and gas industry contributes heavily to campaign funds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Open Secrets&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.opensecrets.org/industries/summary.php?cycle=2012&amp;ind=E01 |title=Oil &amp; Gas: Money to Congress |publisher=OpenSecrets.org |accessdate=9 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; [http://www.opensecrets.org/industries/summary.php?cycle=2012&amp;ind=E01]

====Disclosure of additives====
{{see also|Radionuclides associated with hydraulic fracturing}}
{{see also|List of additives for hydraulic fracturing}}
In April 2011, the Ground Water Protection Council, in conjunction with the industry, began releasing well-by-well lists of hydraulic fracturing chemicals at [http://www.FracFocus.org].&lt;ref name=&quot;bizjournals.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url=http://www.bizjournals.com/pittsburgh/blog/energy/2011/04/a-new-home-for-marcellus-shale-frac.html 
| first=Anya 
| last=Litvak 
| title=A new home for Marcellus Shale frac water 
| date=April 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Disclosure is still on a voluntary basis; companies are still not required to provide information about their hydraulic fracturing techniques and fluids that they consider to be proprietary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/07/12/fracking-water-killed-trees-study-finds/ |title=Fracking Water Killed Trees, Study Finds |author=Mireya Navarro |date=12 July 2011 |work=Green |publisher=The New York Times |accessdate=22 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lists do not include all substances used; a complete listing of the specific chemical formulation of additives used in hydraulic fracturing operations is still not currently made available to landowners, neighbors, local officials, or health care providers, let alone the general public. This practice is under scrutiny.&lt;ref&gt;Fracking Regulations; http://www.caslab.com/Fracking-Regulations/&lt;/ref&gt; Two studies released in 2009, one by the [[United States Department of Energy|U.S. Department of Energy]] and the other released by the Ground Water Protection Council, address hydraulic fracturing safety concerns. Chemicals which can be used in the fracturing fluid include [[kerosene]], [[benzene]], [[toluene]], [[xylene]], and [[formaldehyde]].&lt;ref name=chemicals&gt;[http://www.dec.ny.gov/docs/materials_minerals_pdf/ogdsgeischap5.pdf Chapter 5 Natural Gas Development Activities And High‐Volume Hydraulic Fracturing].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;chemicals&quot;/&gt;

''Notable omissions.'' Lists provided by companies do not include many radioactive tracers used in hydraulic fracturing, such as [[Antimony-121]], [[Antimony-122]], [[Antimony-123]], [[Antimony-124]],  [[Antimony-125]], [[Antimony-126]], [[Antimony-127]], [[Chromium-51]], [[Cobalt-57]], [[Cobalt-58]], [[Cobalt-60]], [[Gold-198]], [[Iodine-127]], [[Iodine-128]], [[Iodine-129]], [[Iodine-130]], [[Iodine-131]] (one of the most commonly named in patents of the process, with a half life of 8.04 days), [[Iridium-192]], [[Iron-59]], [[Krypton-85]], [[Lanthanum-140]], [[Potassium-39]] (activated to [[Potassium-40]]), [[Potassium-41]] (activated to [[Potassium-42]]), [[Potassium-43]], [[Rubidium-86]], [[Scandium-45]], [[Scandium-46]], [[Scandium-47]], [[Scandium-48]], [[Silver-110]], [[Strontium-85]], [[Xenon-133]],  [[Zinc-65]], and [[Zirconium-95]]. Several are typically combined and injected together. Their half lives range from 40.2 hours ([[Lanthanum-140]]) to 5.27 years ([[Cobalt-60]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;No5635712&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;US4415805&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;US5441110&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ep0340956a1&quot;&gt;[http://ip.com/patent/ep0340956a1] Gadeken, Larry L., Halliburton Company (08-Nov-1989)  Patent EP0340956A1: Radioactive well logging method.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== State and local ===
In the US, some states have introduced legislation that limits the ability of municipalities to use zoning to protect citizens from exposure to pollutants from hydraulic fracturing by protecting residential areas. For instance, in Pennsylvania, the new Marcellus Shale Law (House Bill 1950)&lt;ref name=&quot;PA zoning bill&quot;/&gt; requires all municipalities to allow Marcellus Shale well drilling in all zoning districts, including residential, and allow water and wastewater pits in all zoning district, including residential. Compressor stations must be allowed in industrial and agricultural zoning districts, and gas processing plants allowed in industrial zoning districts. Municipalities are no longer permitted to limit the hours of operation of gas related activities. Gas pipelines must be allowed in all zoning districts.&lt;ref name=&quot;PA zoning bill&quot; /&gt; Similar laws have been created in Ohio,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohio2004bill&quot;/&gt; and New York,&lt;ref name=natlawreview/&gt; Colorado, and Texas are battling over related legislation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tavernise12142011&quot;/&gt; Pennsylvania's Marcellus Shale Law (House Bill 1950) also contains a provision that allows doctors in Pennsylvania access to the list of chemicals in hydraulic fracturing fluid in emergency situations only, and forbids them from ever discussing this information with their patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;PA Dr access bill&quot;/&gt;

==== California ====
In May 2012 the California Senate defeated a bill, introduced by state Sen. Fran Pavley (D-Agoura Hills), requiring drillers to notify local property owners and water authorities in advance that hydraulic fracturing was going to occur, and requiring the testing of groundwater  before and after the hydraulic fracturing to determine whether contamination had occurred. Pavley said that this monitoring and reporting approach would help to address citizens' concerns. The state Senate defeated the bill in a bipartisan 18-17 vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;CA Pavley bill&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-hiltzik-20120608,0,1622100.column|title=Let's close the information gap about fracking. The oil and gas industry wants to withhold information even from regulators about the exact formulation of the fluids injected into the ground during fracking, calling them trade secrets.|last=Hiltzik |first=Michael |date=9 June 2012 |publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]] |accessdate=9 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Maryland ====
Gov. Martin O'Malley has issued a hold on applications to drill in western Maryland until the completion of a three-year study of hydraulic fracturing's environmental impacts, thus creating a &quot;de facto moratorium&quot; on Hydraulic fracturing. Del. Heather Mizeur plans to introduce a bill formally banning hydraulic fracturing in Maryland until state officials can determine whether it can be done without harming drinking water or the environment. The gas industry has refused to fund the three-year study and opposed a bill sponsored by Mizeur to fund the study with fees on gas drilling leases. The industry has objected to paying for any studies unless it receives guarantees that it will eventually be able to drill for gas.&lt;ref name=&quot;MD Ban 09162012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.baltimoresun.com/features/green/blog/bal-bmg-legislative-fracking-ban-in-maryland-proposed-20120912,0,6855106.story|title=Greens urge 'fracking' ban in Maryland. Lawmaker vows to bar controversial gas drilling until impact studies done|last=Wheeler |first=Tim |date=12 September 2012 June 2012 |publisher=[[Baltimore Sun]] |accessdate=30 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====New York====
The New York City watershed includes a large area of the [[Marcellus shale]] formation.  The NYC Dept. of Environmental Protection's position: &quot;While DEP is mindful of the potential economic opportunity that this represents for the State, hydraulic fracturing poses an unacceptable threat to the unfiltered water supply of nine million New Yorkers and cannot safely be permitted with the New York City watershed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyc.gov/html/dep/html/news/natural_gas_drilling_dep.shtml] NYC DEP, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

=====State Level=====
The New York State assembly voted 93 to 43, Nov. 30, 2010, to place a moratorium or freeze on hydraulic fracturing to give the state more time to undertake safety and environmental concerns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Navarro|first=Mireya
|title=N.Y. Assembly Approves Fracking Moratorium
|url=http://green.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/11/30/n-y-assembly-approves-fracking-moratorium/?scp=1&amp;sq=approves%20fracking%20moratorium&amp;st=Search
|newspaper=The New York Times Company
|date=30 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2012, the Cuomo administration decided to wait until it completes a review of the potential public health effects of hydraulic fracturing before it allows high-volume hydraulic fracturing in New York. State legislators, medical societies and health experts pressed Joseph Martens, commissioner of the State Department of Environmental Conservation, for an independent review of the health impacts of hydraulic fracturing by medical experts before any regulations are made final and drilling is allowed to start. Martens rejected commissioning an outside study. Instead, he appointed the health commissioner, Dr. Nirav Shah, to assess the department’s analysis of the health effects closely and said Shah could consult qualified outside experts for his review.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Navarro|first=Mireya
|title=New York State Plans Health Review as It Weighs Gas Drilling |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/21/nyregion/new-york-states-decision-on-hydrofracking-will-await-health-review.html?_r=0 |newspaper=The New York Times Company |date=20 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Municipal Level=====
At the municipal level, some towns and cities in central New York state have moved to regulate drilling by hydraulic fracturing and its attendant effects, either by banning it within municipal limits, maintaining the option to do so in the future, or banning wastewater from the drilling process from municipal water treatment plants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Barnes|first=Shawnee
|title=Town of Ithaca bans gas drilling
|url=http://www.theithacajournal.com/article/20110712/NEWS01/107120348/Town-Ithaca-bans-gas-drilling?odyssey=mod%7Cmostview
|accessdate=14 July 2011
|newspaper=Ithaca Journal
|date=12 July 2011}}; {{cite news|last=Munzer|first=Aaron
|title=Ulysses residents at hearing back proposed fracking ban
|url=http://www.theithacajournal.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=2011106300382
|accessdate=14 July 2011
|newspaper=Ithaca Journal
|date=30 June 2011}}; {{cite news|last=Martin|first=Alyson
|title=Caroline rejects move to stay out of hydrofracking
|url=http://www.theithacajournal.com/article/20110713/NEWS01/107130371/Caroline-rejects-move-stay-out-hydrofracking?odyssey=tab%7Ctopnews%7Ctext%7CFRONTPAGE
|accessdate=14 July 2011
|newspaper=Ithaca Journal
|date=13 July 2011}}; {{cite news|author=AP
|title=Auburn to ban wastewater from gas drillers
|url=http://www.theithacajournal.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=2011107080327
|accessdate=14 July 2011
|newspaper=Ithaca Journal
|date=8 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Niagara Falls.''' [[Niagara Falls]]' City Council approved an ordinance that prohibits natural gas extraction in [[Niagara Falls]], as well as the &quot;storage, transfer, treatment or disposal of natural gas exploration and production wastes.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Niagra03062012&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Niagara Falls: Drilling Wastewater Won't Be Treated Here |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/03/07/niagara-falls-drilling-wastewater_n_1325136.html |agency=Associated Press |publisher=Huffington Post |date=6 March 2012 |accessdate=8 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Elected officials there said that they didn't want their citizens, who experienced the [[Love Canal]] toxic waste crisis firsthand, to be guinea pigs for hydraulic fracturing, the new technology used in gas drilling operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Niagra03062012&quot; /&gt; City council member, Glenn Choolokian said, “We won’t let the temptation of millions of dollars in reward for out-of-town companies, corporations and individuals to be the driving force that puts the health and lives of our children and families at risk from the dangers of hydraulic fracturing and its toxic water. I will not take part in bringing another Love Canal to the City of Niagara Falls.”“Our once great city and all the families of Niagara Falls have been through so much over the years. With Love Canal alive in our memories we aren’t going to allow another environmental tragedy to happen in our city, not today, not ever,” said Glenn Choolokian.&lt;ref name=&quot;Niagra03062012&quot; /&gt; Council Chairman Sam Fruscione said he was against selling out future generations of children for corporate greed. Rita Yelda of Food and Water Watch, pointed out that pollutants don't only affect Niagara's citizens, but those in communities downstream as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Niagra03062012&quot; /&gt;

====Ohio====
On 24 May 2012, House of Representatives of Ohio passed Senate Bill 315&lt;ref name=&quot;OH Senate Bill 315&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.legislature.state.oh.us/BillText129/129_SB_315_PS_N.html
 | title = Ohio Senate Bill 315
 | date = 24 May 2012
 | accessdate = 9 June 2012}}
&lt;/ref&gt; regulating oil and gas drilling, including hydraulic fracturing. According to [[Upstream (newspaper)|Upstream Online]], the bill says companies should to test water within {{convert|1500|ft}} of proposed drill sites and to report the fluids and chemicals used while drilling and fracking, except for those considered proprietary. Companies would also be required to track wastewater injected into disposal wells.&lt;ref name=upstream250512&gt;
{{cite news
 | url = http://www.upstreamonline.com/live/article1248215.ece
 | title = Ohio passes drilling regulation bill
 | newspaper = [[Upstream (newspaper)|Upstream Online]]
 | publisher = [[NHST Media Group]]
 | date = 25 May 2012
 | accessdate = 28 May 2012}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
According to John Funk of [[The Plain Dealer]], the bill does not require complete disclosure of all chemicals used during drilling and hydraulic fracturing, and only requires any disclosure of chemicals after the well is already drilled. Proprietary formulas are protected. The Ohio Department of Natural Resources is allowed up to 60 days after drilling to post the chemicals on its web site. Opponents had wanted the bill to require chemicals to be disclosed before drilling so that citizens could have their wells tested for baseline levels of contaminants. The Ohio Senate also removed the requirement for disclosure of drilling lubricants in the space below the local water table but above its final depth. The bill denies the public the right to appeal a drilling permit, and permits do not require public notices. The bill allows doctors to reveal the formulate only to the patient, family and other doctors involved solely for the purpose of treatment, not legal or other proceedings.&lt;ref name=PlainDealer24052012&gt;
{{cite news
 | url = http://www.cleveland.com/business/index.ssf/2012/05/post_99.html
 | title = Ohio lawmakers race to finish shale gas regulations despite complaints from environmentalists
 | author = John Funk
 | newspaper = [[Cleveland Plain Dealer]]
 | publisher = [[Cleveland Plain Dealer]]
 | date = 24 May 2012
 | accessdate = 9 June 2012}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=PlainDealer20052012&gt;
{{cite news
 | url = http://ohiocitizen.org/?cat=92&amp;paged=2
 | title = Gov. John Kasich’s proposed fracking law is riddled with loopholes, say environmental groups
 | author = John Funk
 | newspaper = [[Cleveland Plain Dealer]]
 | publisher = [[Cleveland Plain Dealer]]
 | date = 20 May 2012
 | accessdate = 9 June 2012}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pennsylvania====
''Marcellus Shale Drilling Permits'' The Marcellus Center at Pennsylvania State University reports that the number of permits issued for wells has increased from 122 in 2007 to 3249 in 2011. The Marcellus Center has posted an animated map of the proliferation of [http://marcellus.psu.edu/images/permit_animation.gif Marcellus Shale Drilling Permits in Pennsylvania]. 

''The Marcellus Shale Law (House Bill 1950)''&lt;ref name=&quot;PA House bill 1950&quot;&gt;[http://www.legis.state.pa.us/CFDOCS/Legis/PN/Public/btCheck.cfm?txtType=PDF&amp;sessYr=2011&amp;sessInd=0&amp;billBody=H&amp;billTyp=B&amp;billNbr=1950&amp;pn=3048 Pennsylvania House bill 1950]&lt;/ref&gt; was signed on February 14, 2012, by Governor [[Tom Corbett]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PA zoning bill&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.coshoctontribune.com/usatoday/article/38716263?odyssey=mod|newswell|text|Frontpage|s |title=Local zoning provisions in Pa.'s gas drilling law |work=USA Today |agency=Associated Press |date=3 March 2012 |accessdate=23 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite warnings from the EPA about the safety of wastewater,&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt/EPA study&quot;&gt;{{cite paper|title=Contaminant Characterization of Effluent from Pennsylvania Brine Treatment Inc., Josephine Facility:Implications for Disposal of Oil and Gas Flowback Fluids from Brine Treatment Pollutants |author=Conrad D. Volz, Kyle Ferrar, Drew Michanowicz, Charles Christen, Shannon Kearney, Matt Kelso, and Samantha Malone |work=EPA Hydraulic Fracturing Study Technical Workshop 3, Fate and Transport |date=March 28‐29, 2011 |url=http://www.epa.gov/hfstudy/contaminantcharacterizationofeffluent.pdf |accessdate=17 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; the law changes the zoning laws applicable to Marcellus Shale Well Drilling. The law was slated to take effect in April, 2012, but legal challenges from a growing group of Pennsylvania municipalities and organizations led Commonwealth Senior Judge Keith Quigley to order that the implementation of parts of Act 13 be delayed for 120 days.&lt;ref name=&quot;VOXXI07202012&quot;&gt;{{cite paper|title=Fracking regulations, a legal battle in Pennsylvania|author=Susana G. Baumann |publisher=VOXXI News |date=20 July 2012 |url=http://www.voxxi.com/fracking-regulations-pennsylvania/ |accessdate=21 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of its provisions are that all municipalities ''must'' now allow Marcellus Shale well drilling (in all zoning districts, including residential and may not limit hours of operation), water and wastewater pits (in all zoning district, including residential), compressor stations (in industrial and agricultural zoning districts and may not limit hours of operation), gas processing plants (in industrial zoning districts and cannot limit hours of operation), and gas pipelines (in all zoning districts, including residential).&lt;ref name=&quot;PA zoning bill&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PA House bill 1950&quot; /&gt; The law helps pave the way for a new pipeline across Pennsylvania to export terminals in Maryland. 

The Marcellus Shale Law (House Bill 1950) also contains a provision that allows doctors in Pennsylvania access to the list of chemicals in hydraulic fracturing fluid in emergency situations, but forbids them from discussing this information with their patients. This provision was added during the last revisions of the bill.&lt;ref name=&quot;PA Dr access bill&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://motherjones.com/environment/2012/03/fracking-doctors-gag-pennsylvania |title=For Pennsylvania's Doctors, a Gag Order on Fracking Chemicals. A new provision could forbid the state’s doctors from sharing information with patients exposed to toxic fracking solutions. |work=Mother Jones |author=Sheppard, Kate |date=23 March 2012 |accessdate=23 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, the bill reads that, &quot;(11) If a health professional determines that a medical emergency exists and the specific identity and amount of any chemicals claimed to be a trade secret or confidential proprietary information are necessary for emergency treatment, the vendor, service provider or operator shall immediately disclose the information to the health professional upon a verbal acknowledgment by the health professional that the information may not be used for purposes other than the health needs asserted and that the 'health professional shall maintain the information as confidential.' The vendor, service provider or operator may request, and the health professional shall provide upon request, a written statement of need and a confidentiality agreement from the health professional as soon as circumstances permit, in conformance with regulations promulgated under this chapter.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PA House bill 1950&quot; /&gt; The bill also says that vendors, service providers, and operators cannot be held responsible for inaccuracy
in information that is provided to them, nor do they have to reveal the identities of chemicals that are not disclosed to them, that were not intentionally added to the hydraulic fracturing fluid, that are accidentally present in trace amounts, or are a product of a chemical reaction or process that occurs within the fluid.&lt;ref name=&quot;PA House bill 1950&quot; /&gt;

''Export of Pennsylvania Natural Gas'' Companies have sought and received permission from the [[US Department of Energy]] (DOE)&lt;ref name=&quot;CovePtLusbyMD&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dom.com/business/gas-transmission/cove-point/lng-exports.jsp |title=LNG Exports Dominion Receives DOE Authorization to Export LNG |date=October 2011 |publisher=[[Dominion]] |accessdate=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; to export gas to Europe and Asia (e.g., China and Korea),&lt;ref name=&quot;USSecurity&quot;/&gt; They have asked for permission to build a new pipeline through Pennsylvania and Maryland&lt;ref name=&quot;PAMDpipeline&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;1B pipeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/1b-natural-gas-pipeline-proposed-for-pa-would-connect-to-baltimore-dc-areas/2012/03/02/gIQAhdgImR_story.html |title=$1B natural gas pipeline proposed for Pa., would connect to Baltimore, DC areas |date=2 March 2012 |publisher=Associate Press |accessdate=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pipeline2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2006-04-19/news/0604190067_1_pipeline-sparrows-point-dundalk |title=Firm to hold meetings on LNG pipeline plan|author=Barnhardt, Laura |date=19 April 2006 |publisher=Baltimore Sun |accessdate=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pipeline07282011&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/07/28/us-marcellus-bradford-idUSTRE76R6Q720110728 |title=Analysis: U.S. shale gas sector girds for next battle: pipeline |author=Prezioso, Jeanine  |date=28 July 2011 |publisher=Reuters |accessdate=6 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; to transport liquid natural gas (LNG) to new export terminals in [[Maryland]] to facilitate the export of natural gas and oil.&lt;ref name=&quot;USSecurity&quot; /&gt; Possible terminal locations include [[Sparrows Point, Maryland|Sparrow's Point]], ([[Baltimore]])&lt;ref name=&quot;ToSparrowsPt&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2008-08-12/news/0808110222_1_pipeline |title=Information sessions on LNG pipeline Federal officials to meet with property owners about route (correction)|author=Barnhardt, Laura |date=12 August 2008 |publisher=Baltimore Sun |accessdate=4 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Lusby]],&lt;ref name=&quot;CovePtLusbyMD&quot; /&gt; Maryland.&lt;ref name=&quot;USSecurity&quot;/&gt;

The [[US Environmental Protection Agency]] is taking over the investigation of hydraulic fracturing in Pennsylvania, which is currently under the administration of pro-drilling Governor [[Tom Corbett]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/pennsylvania-dep-secretary-defends-states-ability-to-regulate-hydraulic-fracturing-134054278.html | title=Pennsylvania DEP Secretary Defends States' Ability to Regulate Hydraulic Fracturing | date=November 17, 2011 | publisher=PR Newswire}}&lt;/ref&gt;  ''The New York Times'' reported that regulations are lax in Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 26Feb2011&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/27/us/27gas.html |title=Regulation Lax as Gas Wells' Tainted Water Hits Rivers |author=Ian Urbina |date=26 February 2011 |newspaper=The New York Times |accessdate=22 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The oil and gas industry is generally left to police itself in the case of accidents. Unannounced inspections are not made by regulators: the companies report their own spills, and create their own remediation plans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 26Feb2011&quot;/&gt; A recent review of the state-approved plans found them to appear to be in violation of the law.&lt;ref name=&quot;Urbina 26Feb2011&quot;/&gt; There are signs of [[regulatory capture]]. Corbett received over a million dollars in campaign contributions from the oil and gas industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYRB 08.03.2012&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.nybooks.com/articles/archives/2012/mar/08/why-not-frack/ |title=Why Not Frack? |author=Bill McKibben |authorlink=Bill McKibben |date=8 March 2012 |journal=[[The New York Review of Books]] |volume=59 |issue=4 |accessdate=21 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Don Hopey|title=Corbett repeals policy on gas drilling in parks|url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11055/1127614-455.stm|accessdate=March 7, 2012 |newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette|date=February 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ronald Krancer, father of 2012 Pennsylvania DEP Secretary Michael Krancer, donated $25,000 to the State Republican Committee the day before his son was confirmed as the new Department of Environmental Protection Secretary. In addition, Michael Krancer's father  contributed $150,000 to Governor Corbett's campaign, tens of thousands to GOP [[Bob Asher]]'s political action committee and at least $125,000 to the state Republican Party since 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11188/1158769-178.stm | title=Dad's donation riles state Democrats: Father of DEP secretary gave $25,000 to GOP on the eve of his confirmation by Pennsylvania Senate |author=Olson, Laura (Post-Gazette Harrisburg Bureau) | date=July 7, 2011 |newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette |accessdate=March 7, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Vermont====

While there has been no hydraulic fracking in the state, the Vermont House of Representatives passed a moratorium on hydraulic fracturing in February 2012, and on May 17, 2012 Governor Peter Shumlin (Democrat) signed the law making Vermont the first state to ban hydraulic fracturing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2012/05/17/vermont-becomes-first-state-to-ban-fracking/ |title=Vermont becomes first state to ban fracking |publisher=Fox News |date= |accessdate=2012-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Vermont ban 2&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://articles.cnn.com/2012-05-17/us/us_vermont-fracking_1_fracking-shale-natural-gas?_s=PM:US | title=Vermont first state to ban fracking |author=CNN Wire Staff | date=May 17, 2012 |publisher=CNN |accessdate=June 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On Friday, May 4, 2012, the Vermont legislature voted 103-36 to ban hydraulic fracturing in the state. The bill also requires the state's regulations be revised to prohibit injection well operators from accepting oil and natural gas drilling waste water from out of state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vermont ban&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.platts.com/RSSFeedDetailedNews/RSSFeed/NaturalGas/6264761 | title=Vermont legislature votes 103-36 to ban hydraulic fracturing |author=White, Rodney | date=May 4, 2012 |newspaper=Washington (Platts) |accessdate=May 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Wyoming====
On June 8, 2010 the Wyoming Oil and Gas Conservation Commission voted to require full disclosure of the hydraulic fracturing fluids used in natural gas exploration.&lt;ref&gt;David O. Williams, [http://coloradoindependent.com/55018/wyoming-oil-and-gas-regulators-approve-new-rules-for-frack-fluid-disclosureWyoming oil and gas regulators approve new rules for frack fluid disclosure], June 8, 2010, The Colorado Independent.&lt;/ref&gt; This may aid in tracking pollutants that have migrated from hydraulically fractured gas wells.&lt;ref&gt;[http://trib.com/news/state-and-regional/article_069139a4-5b9b-51c3-a599-a38f788e8ff4.html Wyoming approves 'fracking' disclosure rules ], June 9, 2010, trib.com&lt;/ref&gt;

==Media and public relations==
{{POV|Section|date=April 2012}}
The opposition against fracking activities in local townships has led companies to adopt a variety of public relations measures to assuage fears about fracking, including the admitted use of &quot;mil­i­tary tac­tics to counter drilling oppo­nents&quot;. At a conference where public relations measures were discussed, a senior executive at [[Anadarko Petroleum]] was recorded on tape saying, ''&quot;Download the US Army / Marine Corps Counterinsurgency Manual, because we are dealing with an insurgency&quot;'', while referring to fracking opponents. Matt Pitzarella, spokesman for the most important fracking company in Pennsylvania, [[Range Resources]], also told other conference attendees that Range employed [[psychological warfare]] operations veterans. According to Pitzarella, the experience learnt in the Middle East has been valuable to Range Resources in Pennsylvania, when dealing with emotionally-charged township meetings and advising townships on zoning and local ordinances dealing with fracking.&lt;ref name=psyops&gt;{{cite news|last=Javers|first=Eamon|title=Oil Executive: Military-Style 'Psy Ops' Experience Applied|url=http://www.cnbc.com/id/45208498|newspaper=[[CNBC]]|date=8 Nov 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Phillips|first=Susan|title=‘We’re Dealing with an Insurgency,’ says Energy Company Exec of Fracking Foes|url=http://stateimpact.npr.org/pennsylvania/2011/11/09/were-dealing-with-an-insurgency-says-energy-company-exec-of-fracking-foes/|newspaper=[[National Public Radio]]|date=9 Nov 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, in a February 2012 campaign speech, Rick Santorum, a [[Rick Santorum presidential campaign, 2012|candidate for]] the [[Republican Party presidential primaries, 2012|2012 Republican Party presidential nomination]], referred to those objecting to hydraulic fracturing as environmental [[terrorists]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com/2012/02/09/santorum-takes-on-environmental-terror/ |title=Santorum takes on 'environmental terror' |author=Adam Aigner-Treworgy |publisher=CNN |accessdate=24 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Energy in the United States]]
*[[Shale gas in the United States]]
*''[[Gasland]]'' - a 2010 documentary by [[Josh Fox]] exploring environmental impact of hydraulic fracturing in the United States

==Notes==
:a. {{note_label|a|a|none}} Also spelled &quot;fraccing&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.appea.com.au/images/stories/Policy_CSG/APPEA_Fraccing_chemicals_-_FINAL.pdf &quot;Chemicals that may be used in Australian CSG fraccing fluid&quot;] [[Petroleum industry in Western Australia|Australian Petroleum Ptoduction &amp; Exploration Association Limited]]&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;fracing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://stocks.investopedia.com/stock-analysis/2010/Will-The-EPA-Crack-Down-On-Fracking-HAL-APC-NBL-COG-EOG-CHK-UPL-XOM0712.aspx &quot;Will The EPA Crack Down On 'Fracking'?&quot;], Investopedia&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hydraulicfracturing.com |title=HydraulicFracturing.com |publisher=HydraulicFracturing.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;TimesUnion&quot;&gt;{{cite news |http://blog.timesunion.com/capitol/archives/142499/gas-drilling-firm-threatens-to-sue-over-potential-frack-bans/ |title=Gas drilling firm threatens to sue over potential frack bans |first =Rick | last =  Karlin  |date=31 July 2012 |accessdate=19 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;IPS 10212012&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |first1=Sarah |last1=McHaney|url=http://www.ipsnews.net/2012/10/shale-gas-extraction-brings-local-health-impacts/ |title=Shale Gas Extraction Brings Local Health Impacts |date=21 October 2012 |newspaper = IPS News |publisher= [[Inter Press Service]] |accessdate=2012-10-21|}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;OilGasJournal&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.mlive.com/politics/index.ssf/2012/10/yes_or_no_obama_romney_answer_1.html
|title=Trends emerge on hydraulic fracturing litigation |first =Barclay | last =  Nicholson |first2=Kadian |last2=Blanson |date=05 December 2012 |accessdate=19 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mlive 10192012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.mlive.com/politics/index.ssf/2012/10/yes_or_no_obama_romney_answer_1.html
|title=Yes or No? Obama, Romney answer 'fracking' question |first =David | last = Eggert |date=19 October 2012 |  |accessdate=19 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 07052012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/06/opinion/the-wise-way-to-regulate-hydraulic-fracturing.html?_r=0|title=The Wise Way to Regulate Gas Drilling|first =Jody | last = Freeman |date=05 July 2012| work = [[New York Times]] |accessdate=19 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Montgomery&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Montgomery|first1=Carl T.|last2=Smith|first2=Michael B.|date=2010-12-105|title= Hydraulic fracturing. History of an enduring technology |journal=JPT Online |publisher=[[Society of Petroleum Engineers]] |format=PDF |pages=26–41|url=http://jgs.geoscienceworld.org/cgi/content/abstract/131/6/653|accessdate=13 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Charlez&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Charlez |first=Philippe A. |year=1997 |title=Rock Mechanics: Petroleum Applications |location=Paris |publisher=Editions Technip |url =http://books.google.com/books?id=NigwG_BYRsYC&amp;pg=PA239| page = 239| accessdate = 2012-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=gri&gt;{{cite book |title= A review of the management of the Gas Research Institute |author= [[United States National Research Council]], Committee to Review the Gas Research Institute's Research, Development and Demonstration Program, [[Gas Research Institute]] |publisher= National Academies |page = ? |year= 1989}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoZV-10&quot;&gt;[http://thebreakthrough.org/blog/2012/03/shale_gas_fracking_history_and.shtml &quot;US Government Role in Shale Gas Fracking: An Overview&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SPE-20&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= SPE production &amp; operations | volume = 20 |year= 2005 | publisher = [[Society of Petroleum Engineers]]| page = 87 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AutoZV-9&quot;&gt;[http://thebreakthrough.org/blog/2011/12/interview_with_dan_steward_for.shtml The Breakthrough Institute. Interview with Dan Steward, former Mitchell Energy Vice President. December 2011.]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=natlawreview&gt;{{cite web |title= Recent Court Decisions May Affect Hydraulic Fracturing in New York and Ohio|url= http://www.natlawreview.com/article/recent-court-decisions-may-affect-hydraulic-fracturing-new-york-and-ohio|publisher= McDermott Will &amp; Emery|work=The [[National Law Review]]|date=2012-04-01|accessdate=2012-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Ohio2004bill&gt;{{cite news|last=Suddes |first=Thomasn|title='Fracking' debate exposes weaknesses in Ohio Statehouse – term limits and the death of home rule |url=http://www.cleveland.com/opinion/index.ssf/2012/01/fracking_debate_exposes_weakne.html |newspaper=[[The Plain Dealer]]|date=14 Jan 2012|accessdate=26 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=Tavernise12142011&gt;{{cite news|last=Tavernise |first=Sabrina|title=As Gas Drilling Spreads, Towns Stand Ground Over Control Applied |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/12/15/us/towns-fighting-to-stand-ground-against-gas-drillers.html?pagewanted=all |newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=14 Dec 2011|accessdate=26 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Further reading==
*''Under the Surface: Fracking, Fortunes, and the Fate of the Marcellus Shale'' by Tom Wilber. ([[Cornell University Press]], May 2012) ISBN 978-0-8014-5016-7

==External links==
{{external links|date=August 2012}}
*[http://www.epa.gov/safewater/uic/wells_hydrofrac.html EPA: Hydraulic fracturing (United States)]
*[http://www.democracynow.org/2010/9/14/as_regulators_weigh_drilling_in_marcellus EPA Opens Public Hearings on Health and Environmental Impact of Hydraulic Fracturing]&amp;nbsp;— video report by ''[[Democracy Now!]]''
*[http://www.fractracker.org/ FracTracker: Maps, data, and articles from news, government, industry, and academic sources.]
*[http://www.globalresearch.ca/index.php?context=va&amp;aid=22667 Global Research (Canada)]
*[http://www.nyc.gov/html/dep/html/news/natural_gas_drilling.shtml NYC Department of Environmental Protection: Natural Gas Drilling In Marcellus Shale]
*[http://savethewatertable.org/ SavetheWaterTable.org]&amp;nbsp;— Organization dedicated to saving the aquifer in the face of fracking
*[http://shaleshock.org/ Shale Shock] Upstate New York organization dedicated to education, outreach, and organizing resistance against drilling in the Marcellus Shale.
*[http://www.perf.com/uploads/news/papers_and_publications/papers/ATCE%20Paper%202008.pdf Treatment of Fracture Stimulated Wells] Publication discussing the process of testing and treating fracture stimulated wells.

===News links===
*[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2010/11/12/60minutes/main7048737.shtml?tag=currentVideoInfo;segmentTitle Energy: The Pros and Cons of Shale Gas Drilling] a [[60 Minutes]] report on fracing by CBS News, featuring [[Chesapeake Energy]], originally broadcast on November 14, 2010
*{{Cite news| issn = 0362-4331| last = Kaplan| first = Thomas| title = Hydrofracking Debate Spurs Huge Spending by Industry| work = The New York Times| accessdate = 2011-11-28| date = 2011-11-25| url = http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/26/nyregion/hydrofracking-debate-spurs-huge-spending-by-industry.html}}
*[http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=4477 Natural Gas and the News; Most messages on fracking ‘brought to you by our sponsors’] from [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]] February 2012
*[http://www.pressconnects.com/marcellusshale Pressconnects.com Marcellus Shale]&amp;nbsp;— Newspaper website covering Hydraulic fracturing &amp; Marcellus Shale
*{{Cite news| last = Saefong| first = Myra P.| title =Shale gas gives rise to era of energy independence| work = [[MarketWatch]]| accessdate = 2011-12-04| date = 2011-12-02| url = http://www.marketwatch.com/story/shale-gas-gives-rise-to-era-of-energy-independence-2011-12-02}}


[[Category:Hydraulic fracturing by country|United States]]
[[Category:Mining in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>24lo0e3e87ovca7xxpzxqsf1olwzyir</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
