<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mercury poisoning</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>344287</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520483849</id>
      <parentid>519789307</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T20:37:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>64.88.191.182</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Organic mercury compounds */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="62912">{{Merge from |Mad hatter disease|discuss=Talk:Mercury poisoning#Merge discussion |date=May 2012}}
{{Infobox disease
 | Name            = Mercury poisoning
 | Image           = Hg_Mercury.jpg
 | Caption         = [[Chemical element|Elemental]] [[Mercury (element)|mercury]]
 | DiseasesDB      = 8057
 | ICD10           = {{ICD10|T|56|1|t|51}}
 | ICD9            = {{ICD9|985.0}}
 | ICDO            = 
 | OMIM            = 
 | MedlinePlus     = 002476
 | eMedicineSubj   = emerg
 | eMedicineTopic  = 813
 | MeshID          = D008630
}}
Mercury poisoning (also known as hydrargyria or '''mercurialism''') is a disease caused by exposure to [[mercury (element)|mercury]] or its [[chemical compound|compounds]]. Mercury (chemical symbol Hg) is a [[Heavy metal (chemistry)|heavy metal]] occurring in several forms, all of which can produce toxic effects in high enough doses. Its zero [[oxidation state]] [[Mercury (element)|Hg]]&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; exists as vapor or as liquid metal, its mercurous state Hg&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; exists as [[inorganic]] salts, and its mercuric state Hg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; may form either inorganic salts or [[organomercury]] compounds; the three groups vary in effects. Toxic effects include damage to the brain, kidney, and lungs.&lt;ref name=Clifton/&gt; Mercury poisoning can result in several diseases, including acrodynia (pink disease),&lt;ref name=&quot;geir&quot;/&gt; Hunter-Russell syndrome, and [[Minamata disease]].&lt;ref name=Davidson/&gt;

Symptoms typically include sensory impairment (vision, hearing, speech), disturbed sensation and a lack of coordination. The type and degree of symptoms exhibited depend upon the individual toxin, the dose, and the method and duration of exposure.

==Signs and symptoms==
Common symptoms of mercury poisoning include [[peripheral neuropathy]] (presenting as [[paresthesia]] or [[itching]], burning or [[pain]]), skin discoloration (pink cheeks, fingertips and toes), swelling, and [[desquamation]] (shedding of skin).

Mercury irreversibly inhibits selenium-dependent enzymes (see below) and may also inactivate [[S-adenosyl-methionine]], which is necessary for catecholamine [[catabolism]] by [[catechol-o-methyl transferase]]. Due to the body's inability to degrade catecholamines (e.g. [[epinephrine]]), a person suffering from mercury poisoning may experience profuse sweating, [[tachycardia]] (persistently faster-than-normal heart beat), increased salivation, and [[hypertension]] (high blood pressure).

Affected children may show red [[cheek]]s, [[human nose|nose]] and lips, loss of [[hair]], [[teeth]], and [[nail (anatomy)|nails]], transient rashes, [[hypotonia]] (muscle weakness), and increased sensitivity to light. Other symptoms may include [[kidney]] dysfunction (e.g. [[Fanconi syndrome]]) or neuropsychiatric symptoms such as emotional [[Labile affect|lability]], [[memory]] impairment, and / or [[insomnia]].

Thus, the clinical presentation may resemble [[pheochromocytoma]] or [[Kawasaki disease]].

An example of [[desquamation]] (skin peeling) of the hand of a child with severe mercury poisoning acquired by handling elemental mercury is [http://adc.bmj.com/content/vol86/issue6/images/large/90015199.f1.jpeg this photograph] in Horowitz, ''et al.'' (2002).&lt;ref name=siblings&gt;{{cite journal | author = Horowitz Y, Greenberg D, Ling G, Lifshitz M | year = 2002 | title = Acrodynia: a case report of two siblings | url = | journal = Arch Dis Child | volume = 86 | issue = 6| page = 453 | pmid = 12023189 | pmc = 1762992 | doi=10.1136/adc.86.6.453}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Causes===
The [[Mercury in fish|consumption of fish]] is by far the most significant source of ingestion-related mercury exposure in humans and animals, although plants and livestock also contain mercury due to [[bioaccumulation]] of mercury from soil, water and atmosphere, and due to [[biomagnification]] by ingesting other mercury-containing organisms.&lt;ref name=EPAMercuryStudyIII&gt;{{Cite book| author = [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]]| title =Mercury Study Report to Congress| publisher =United States Environmental Protection Agency| date =December 1997| location =[[Washington, D.C.]]| volume =3| url =http://www.epa.gov/ttn/oarpg/t3/reports/volume3.pdf| format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Exposure to mercury can occur from breathing contaminated air,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|name=ATSDR Mercury ToxFAQ
  | title =ToxFAQs: Mercury
  | publisher =[[Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry]]
  | date =1999-04
  | url =http://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/tfacts46.html#bookmark04
  | accessdate =2007-07-25  }}&lt;/ref&gt; from eating foods that have acquired mercury residues during processing,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Dufault R, LeBlanc B, Schnoll R ''et al.'' |title= Mercury from chlor-alkali plants: measured concentrations in food product sugar |journal= Environ Health |volume=8 |issue= 1 |pages=2 |year=2009 |pmid=19171026 |pmc=2637263 |doi=10.1186/1476-069X-8-2 |url=http://ehjournal.net/content/8/1/2 |laysummary=http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/587466 |laydate=2009-01-27 |laysource= Medscape Today}}&lt;/ref&gt; from exposure to mercury vapor in mercury amalgam dental restorations,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Levy M. |title= Dental Amalgam: toxicological evaluation and health risk assessment |journal= J Cdn Dent Assoc |volume=61 |pages= 667–8, 671–4 |year=1995}}&lt;/ref&gt; and from improper use or disposal of mercury and mercury-containing objects, for example, after spills of elemental mercury or improper disposal of [[fluorescent lamp]]s.&lt;ref name=Pediatrics&gt;{{cite journal |author= Goldman LR, Shannon MW; American Academy of Pediatrics: Committee on Environmental Health | title = Technical report: mercury in the environment: implications for pediatricians | journal =Pediatrics| volume =108| issue =1| pages =197–205| date =2001-07| url =http://aappolicy.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/pediatrics;108/1/197| accessdate =2007-07-25| doi =10.1542/peds.108.1.197| pmid =11433078  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Consumption of whale and dolphin meat, as is the practice in [[Japan]], is a source of high levels of mercury poisoning.  Tetsuya Endo, a professor at the Health Sciences [[University of Hokkaido]], has tested [[whale meat]] purchased in the whaling town of Taiji and found mercury levels more than 20 times the acceptable Japanese standard.&lt;ref name=Hokkaido&gt;url = http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20090923f2.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Human-generated sources, such as coal plants, emit about half of atmospheric mercury, with natural sources such as [[volcano]]es responsible for the remainder. An estimated two-thirds of human-generated mercury comes from stationary combustion, mostly of [[coal]]. Other important human-generated sources include [[Gold mining|gold production]], [[nonferrous metal]] production, [[cement]] production, [[waste disposal]], human [[crematoria]], [[caustic soda]] production, [[pig iron]] and [[steel]] production, mercury production (mostly for batteries), and biomass burning.&lt;ref name=Pacyna&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Atmos Environ |year=2006 |volume=40 |issue=22 |pages=4048–63 |title= Global anthropogenic mercury emission inventory for 2000 |author= Pacyna EG, Pacyna JM, Steenhuisen F, Wilson S |doi=10.1016/j.atmosenv.2006.03.041}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Small independent gold-mining operation workers are at higher risk of mercury poisoning because of crude processing methods.  Such is the danger for the [[galamsey]] in Ghana and similar workers known as ''[[orpailleur|orpailleurs]]'' in neighboring [[francophone]] countries.  While no official government estimates of the labor force have been made, observers believe 20,000-50,000 work as galamseys in Ghana, a figure including many women, who work as porters.

Mercury and many of its chemical compounds, especially [[organomercury]] compounds, can also be readily absorbed through direct contact with bare, or in some cases (such as dimethylmercury) insufficiently protected, skin. Mercury and its compounds are commonly used in chemical laboratories, hospitals, dental clinics, and facilities involved in the production of items such as fluorescent light bulbs, batteries, and explosives.&lt;ref name=EPAMercuryStudyIV&gt;{{Cite book
  | author = [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]]
  | title =Mercury Study Report to Congress
  | publisher =United States Environmental Protection Agency
  | date =December 1997
  | location =[[Washington, D.C.]]
  | volume =4
  | url =http://www.epa.gov/ttn/oarpg/t3/reports/volume4.pdf
  | format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mechanism==
Mercury is highly reactive with [[Selenium_in_biology|selenium]], an essential dietary element required by about 25 genetically distinct enzyme types (selenoenzymes).&lt;ref name=&quot;Reeves and Hoffman&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Reeves|first=M.A.|coauthors=Hoffman, P.R.|title=The human selenoproteome: recent insights into functions and regulation.|journal=Cell Mol Life Sci.|year=2009|volume=66|issue=15|pages=2457–2478|pmid=19399585|doi=10.1007/s00018-009-0032-4|pmc=2866081}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among their numerous functions, selenoenzymes prevent and reverse oxidative damage in the brain and endocrine organs. The molecular mechanism of mercury toxicity involves its unique ability to irreversibly inhibit activities of selenoenzymes, such as thioredoxin reductase (IC50 = 9 nM).&lt;ref name=Carvalho-Holmgren&gt;{{cite journal|last=Carvalho|first=C.M.L.|coauthors=Hashemy, S.I., Lu, J., Holmgren A.|title=Inhibition of the human thioredoxin system: A molecular mechanism of mercury toxicity.|journal=Journal of Biological Chemistry.|year=2008|volume=283|issue=18|pages=11913–11923}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although it has many additional functions, thioredoxin reductase restores vitamins C and E, as well as a number of other important antioxidant molecules, back into their reduced forms, enabling them to counteract oxidative damage within body cells.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Linster|first=C.L.|coauthors=Van Schaftingen, E.|title=Vitamin C: Biosynthesis, recycling and degradation in mammals.|journal=FEBS Journal|year=2007|volume=274|pages=1–22|pmid=17222174|doi=10.1111/j.1742-4658.2006.05607.x|issue=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Since the rate of oxygen consumption is particularly high in brain tissues, production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) is accentuated in these vital cells, making them particularly vulnerable to oxidative damage and especially dependent upon the antioxidant protection provided by selenoenzymes.  High mercury exposures deplete the amount of cellular selenium available for the biosynthesis of thioredoxin reductase and other selenoenzymes that prevent and reverse oxidative damage,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Ralston|first=Nicholas V.C.|coauthors=Raymond, Laura J.|title=Dietary selenium's protective effects against methylmercury toxicity.|journal=Toxicology|year=2010|volume=278|pages=112–123}}&lt;/ref&gt; which, if the depletion is severe and long lasting, results in brain cell dysfunctions that can ultimately cause death.

High exposures to mercury in its various forms are particularly toxic to [[fetus]]es and infants. Women who have been exposed to mercury in substantial excess of dietary selenium intakes during pregnancy are at risk of giving birth to children with serious [[Minamata disease|birth defects]]. Mercury exposures in excess of dietary selenium intakes in young children can have severe neurological consequences, preventing nerve sheaths from forming properly. Mercury inhibits the formation of [[myelin]].

According to some evidence, mercury poisoning may predispose to [[Young's syndrome]] (men with [[bronchiectasis]] and [[low sperm count]]).&lt;ref name=hendry&gt;{{cite journal | author = Hendry WF, A'Hern FPA, Cole PJ | year = 1993 | title = Was Young's syndrome caused by mercury exposure in childhood? | url = | journal = [[BMJ]] | volume = 307 | issue = 6919| pages = 1579–82 | pmid = 8292944 | pmc = 1697782 | doi=10.1136/bmj.307.6919.1579}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of differences in tissue distributions, mercury poisoning's effects will differ depending on whether it has been caused by exposure to elemental mercury, inorganic mercury compounds (as salts), or organomercury compounds.

===Elemental mercury===
[[Mercury (element)|Quicksilver]] (liquid metallic mercury) is poorly absorbed by ingestion and skin contact. It is hazardous due to its potential to release mercury vapor. Animal data indicate less than 0.01% of ingested mercury is absorbed through the intact [[gastrointestinal tract]], though it may not be true for individuals suffering from [[ileus]]. Cases of systemic toxicity from accidental swallowing are rare, and attempted suicide via intravenous injection does not appear to result in systemic toxicity.&lt;ref name=Clarkson-Magos/&gt; Though not studied quantitatively, the physical properties of liquid elemental mercury limit its absorption through intact skin and in light of its very low absorption rate from the gastrointestinal tract, skin absorption would not be high.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATSDR&quot;&gt;ATSDR. 1999. Toxicological Profile for Mercury. Atlanta, GA:Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry. http://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxprofiles/tp46.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  Some mercury vapor is absorbed dermally, but uptake by this route is only about 1% of that by inhalation.&lt;ref name=&quot;hursh1989&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.1080/00039896.1989.9934385|author=Hursh JB, Clarkson TW, Miles E, Goldsmith LA | title=Percutaneous absorption of mercury vapor by man | journal=Arch.
Environ. Health | volume=44 | issue=2 | pages=120–127 | year=1989 | pmid=2494955}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In humans, approximately 80% of inhaled mercury vapor is absorbed via the [[respiratory tract]], where it enters the [[circulatory system]] and is distributed throughout the body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Cherian MG, Hursh JG, Clarkson TW | year = 1978 | title = Radioactive mercury distribution in biological fluids and excretion in human subjects after inhalation of mercury vapor | url = | journal = Archives of Environmental Health | volume = 33 | issue = | pages = 190–214 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Chronic exposure by inhalation, even at low concentrations in the range 0.7–42 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, has been shown in [[case control studies]] to cause effects such as tremors, impaired cognitive skills, and sleep disturbance in workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ngim&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Ngim CH, Foo SC, Boey KW, and Keyaratnam J | title=Chronic neurobehavioral effects of elemental mercury in dentists | journal=British Journal of Industrial Medicine | volume=49 | pages=782–790 | year=1992|pmid=1463679|issue=11|pmc=1039326}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;liang&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Liang YX, Sun RK, Chen ZQ, and Li LH | title=Psychological effects of low exposure to mercury vapor: Application of computer-administered neurobehavioral evaluation system | journal=Environmental Research | volume=60 | pages=320–327 | doi=10.1006/enrs.1993.1040 | year=1993|pmid=8472661|issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Acute inhalation of high concentrations causes a wide variety of cognitive, personality, sensory, and motor disturbances. The most prominent symptoms include [[tremors]] (initially affecting the hands and sometimes spreading to other parts of the body), [[emotional lability]] (characterized by irritability, excessive shyness, confidence loss, and nervousness), [[insomnia]], [[memory loss]], neuromuscular changes (weakness, muscle atrophy, muscle twitching), headaches, [[polyneuropathy]] (paresthesia, stocking-glove sensory loss, hyperactive tendon reflexes, slowed sensory and motor nerve conduction velocities), and performance deficits in tests of cognitive function.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATSDR&quot; /&gt;

===Inorganic mercury compounds===
Mercury occurs inorganically as salts such as [[mercury(II) chloride]]. Mercury salts affect primarily the gastrointestinal tract and the [[kidney]]s, and can cause severe kidney damage; however, as they cannot cross the [[blood–brain barrier]] easily, mercury salts inflict little neurological damage without continuous or heavy exposure.&lt;ref name=Hypertension&gt;{{cite journal
  | author =Langford NJ, Ferner RE
  | title =Toxicity of mercury
  | journal =Journal of Human Hypertension
  | volume =13
  | issue =10
  | pages =651–6
  | year =1999
  | url =http://www.nature.com/jhh/journal/v13/n10/pdf/1000896a.pdf
  | accessdate =2007-07-31
  | doi =10.1038/sj.jhh.1000896|format=PDF
  | pmid =10516733}}&lt;/ref&gt; As two [[oxidation state]]s of mercury form salts (Hg&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt; and Hg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;), mercury salts occur in both mercury(I) (or mercurous) and mercury(II) (mercuric) forms. Mercury(II) salts are usually more toxic than their mercury(I) counterparts because their [[solubility]] in water is greater; thus, they are more readily absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract.&lt;ref name=Hypertension/&gt;

====Mercuric cyanide====
[[Mercuric cyanide]] (also known as Mercury (II) cyanide), Hg(CN)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, is a particularly toxic mercury compound. If ingested, both life-threatening mercury and [[cyanide poisoning]] can occur. Hg(CN)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; can enter the body via inhalation, [[ingestion]], or passage through the [[skin]]. Inhalation of mercuric cyanide [[irritation|irritates]] the [[throat]] and air passages.  Heating or contact of Hg(CN)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; with acid or acid mist releases toxic mercury and cyanide vapors that can cause [[bronchitis]] with cough and phlegm and/or [[Human lung|lung]] tissue irritation. Contact with [[Human eye|eye]]s can cause [[burn]]s and brown stains in the eyes, and long-time exposure can affect the [[peripheral vision]]. Contact with skin can cause skin [[allergy]], irritation, and gray skin color.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercuric&quot;&gt;&quot;Mercuric Cyanide.&quot;  '''1987'''.  http://www.gulflink.osd.mil/m256/m256_refs/n17en111/164.htm (accessed April 2, 2009).&lt;/ref&gt;

Chronic exposure to trace amounts of the compound can lead to mercury buildup in the body over time; it may take months or even years for the body to eliminate excess mercury.  Overexposure to mercuric cyanide can lead to [[Nephrotoxicity|kidney damage]] and/or mercury poisoning, leading to 'shakes' (ex: shaky handwriting), [[irritability]], sore [[gingiva|gums]], increased [[saliva]], metallic taste, loss of [[appetite]], [[memory]] loss, [[Personality type|personality]] changes, and [[brain damage]]. Exposure to large doses at one time can lead to sudden death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercuric&quot; /&gt;

Mercuric cyanide has not been tested on its ability to cause [[reproduction|reproductive]] damage. Although inorganic mercury compounds (such as Hg(CN)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) have not been shown to be human [[teratology|teratogens]], they should be handled with care, as they are known to damage developing [[embryo]]s and decrease [[fertility]] in men and women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercuric&quot; /&gt;

According to one study, two people exhibited symptoms of cyanide poisoning within hours after ingesting mercuric cyanide or [[mercury oxycyanide]], Hg(CN)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;•HgO, in [[suicide]] attempts. The toxicity of Hg(CN)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is commonly assumed to arise almost exclusively from mercury poisoning; however, the patient who ingested mercury oxycyanide died after five hours of cyanide poisoning before any mercury poisoning symptoms were observed. The patient who ingested Hg(CN)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; initially showed symptoms of acute cyanide poisoning, which were brought under control, and later showed signs of mercury poisoning before recovering. The degree to which cyanide poisoning occurs is thought to be related to whether cyanide ions are released in the [[stomach]], which depends on factors such as the amount ingested, stomach acidity, and volume of stomach contents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benaissa&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1007/BF01700673 | author = Benaissa M.L., Hantson P., Bismuth C., Baud F.J. | year = 1995 | title = Mercury oxycyanide and mercuric cyanide poisoning: two cases.| url = | journal = Intensive Care Med. | volume = 21 | issue = 12| pages = 1051–1053 | pmid = 8750135 }}&lt;/ref&gt;   Given that Hg(CN)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; molecules remain undissociated in pure water and in [[base (chemistry)|basic]] solutions,&lt;ref name=&quot;Aylett&quot;&gt;Aylett, B.J.  &quot;Mercury (II) Pseudohalides: Cyanide, Thiocyanate, Selenocyanate, Azide, Fulminate.&quot;  ''Comprehensive Inorganic Chemistry'' 3:304-306.  J.C. Bailar, H.J. Emeléus, Sir Ronald Nyholm, and A.F. Trotman-Dickenson, ed.  Oxford: Pergamon Press, '''1973'''; distributed by Compendium Publishers (Elmsford, NY), p. 304.&lt;/ref&gt; it makes sense that dissociation would increase with increasing acidity. High stomach acidity thus helps cyanide ions to become more [[bioavailability|bioavailable]], increasing the likelihood of cyanide poisoning.

Mercury cyanide was used in two murders in New York in 1898. The perpetrator, Roland B. Molineux, sent poisoned medicines to his victims through the [[United States Postal Service|US mail]]. The first victim, Henry Barnett, died of mercury poisoning 12 days after taking the poison. The second victim, Catherine Adams, died of cyanide poisoning within 30 minutes of taking the poison. As in the suicide cases, the difference between the two cases may be attributed to differences in the acidities of the solutions containing the poison, or to differences in the acidities of the victims' stomachs.&lt;ref&gt;Emsley, John.  ''The Elements of Murder.''  Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2005.  ISBN 0-19-280599-1&lt;/ref&gt;

The drug n-acetyl penicillamine has been used to treat mercury poisoning with limited success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercuric&quot;/&gt;

===Organic mercury compounds===
Compounds of mercury tend to be much more toxic than the elemental form, and organic compounds of mercury are often extremely toxic and have been implicated in causing [[brain damage|brain]] and [[hepatitis|liver damage]]. The most dangerous mercury compound, [[dimethylmercury]], is so toxic that even a few [[microliter]]s spilled on the skin, or even a latex glove, can cause death, as in the case of [[Karen Wetterhahn]].&lt;ref name=bris/&gt;&lt;ref name=osha/&gt;

==== Methylmercury ====
{{Main|Mercury in fish}}
[[Methylmercury]] is the major source of organic mercury for all individuals.&lt;ref name=Clifton/&gt; It works its way up the [[food chain]] through [[bioaccumulation]] in the environment, reaching high concentrations among populations of some species. Larger species of fish, such as [[tuna]] or [[swordfish]], are usually of greater concern than smaller species. The US [[Food and Drug Administration|FDA]] and the [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]] advise women of child-bearing age, nursing mothers, and young children to completely avoid [[swordfish]], [[shark]], [[king mackerel]] and [[tilefish]] from the Gulf of Mexico, (golden tilefish from the mid- and North-Atlantic present no risk{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}) to limit consumption of [[albacore|albacore (&quot;white&quot;) tuna]] to no more than {{convert|6|oz|g|lk=on|abbr=on}} per week, and of all other fish and shellfish to no more than {{convert|12|oz|g|abbr=on}} per week.&lt;ref name=&quot;fda2004&quot;&gt;[http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyNET.exe/300065VC.TXT?ZyActionD=ZyDocument&amp;Client=EPA&amp;Index=2000+Thru+2005&amp;Docs=&amp;Query=&amp;Time=&amp;EndTime=&amp;SearchMethod=1&amp;TocRestrict=n&amp;Toc=&amp;TocEntry=&amp;QField=&amp;QFieldYear=&amp;QFieldMonth=&amp;QFieldDay=&amp;IntQFieldOp=0&amp;ExtQFieldOp=0&amp;XmlQuery=&amp;File=D%3A\zyfiles\Index%20Data\00thru05\Txt\00000008\300065VC.txt&amp;User=ANONYMOUS&amp;Password=anonymous&amp;SortMethod=h|-&amp;MaximumDocuments=1&amp;FuzzyDegree=0&amp;ImageQuality=r75g8/r75g8/x150y150g16/i425&amp;Display=p|f&amp;DefSeekPage=x&amp;SearchBack=ZyActionL&amp;Back=ZyActionS&amp;BackDesc=Results%20page&amp;MaximumPages=1&amp;ZyEntry=1&amp;SeekPage=x&amp;ZyPURL What you need to know about mercury in fish and shellfish - Advice for women who might become pregnant women who are pregnant nursing mothers young children.] U.S. [[Food and Drug Administration|FDA]] and U.S. [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|EPA]] Advisory EPA-823-F-04-009, March 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; A 2006 review&lt;!--, conducted by Dr. Dariush Mozaffarian and Dr. Eric B. Rimm,--&gt; of the risks and benefits of fish consumption found, for adults, the benefits of one to two servings of fish per week outweigh the risks, even (except for a few fish species) for women of childbearing age, and that avoidance of fish consumption could result in significant excess [[coronary heart disease]] deaths and suboptimal [[neural development]] in children.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mozaffarian D, Rimm EB 2006 1885–99&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |journal=JAMA |year=2006 |volume=296 |issue=15 |pages=1885–99 |title= Fish intake, contaminants, and human health: evaluating the risks and the benefits |author= Mozaffarian D, Rimm EB |url=http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/296/15/1885 |pmid=17047219 |doi=10.1001/jama.296.15.1885}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- (Dr. Rimm has reported in the past that he has received payment or honoraria for presentations about food and diets from both the Culinary Institute of America and the International Chefs Association, among others.)--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mozaffarian D, Rimm EB 2006 1885–99&quot;/&gt;

The period between exposure to methylmercury and the appearance of symptoms in adult poisoning cases is long. The longest recorded latent period is five months after a single exposure, in the Dartmouth case (see [[#History|History]]); other latent periods in the range of weeks to months have also been reported. No explanation for this long latent period is known. When the first symptom appears, typically [[paresthesia]] (a tingling or numbness in the skin), it is followed rapidly by more severe effects, sometimes ending in [[coma]] and death. The toxic damage appears to be determined by the peak value of mercury, not the length of the exposure.&lt;ref name=Clarkson-Magos/&gt;

==== Ethylmercury ====
[[Ethylmercury]] is a breakdown product of the antibacteriological agent ethylmercurithiosalicylate, which has been used as a topical antiseptic and a vaccine preservative (further discussed under [[#Thiomersal|Thiomersal]] below). Its characteristics have not been studied as extensively as those of methylmercury. It is cleared from the blood much more rapidly, with a half-life of seven to 10 days, and it is metabolized much more quickly than methylmercury. It is presumed not to have methylmercury's ability to cross the [[blood–brain barrier]] via a transporter, but instead relies on simple diffusion to enter the brain.&lt;ref name=Clifton/&gt;

==== Other sources ====
Other exposure sources of organic mercury include phenylmercuric acetate and phenylmercuric nitrate. These were used in indoor latex paints for their antimildew properties, but were removed in 1990 because of cases of toxicity.&lt;ref name=Clifton/&gt;

==Diagnosis==

Diagnosis of elemental or inorganic mercury poisoning involves determining the history of exposure, physical findings, and an elevated [[body burden]] of mercury. Although whole-blood mercury concentrations are typically less than 6&amp;nbsp;μg/L, diets rich in fish can result in blood mercury concentrations higher than 200&amp;nbsp;μg/L; it is not that useful to measure these levels for suspected cases of elemental or inorganic poisoning because of mercury's short half-life in the blood. If the exposure is chronic, urine levels can be obtained; 24-hour collections are more reliable than spot collections. It is difficult or impossible to interpret urine samples of patients undergoing [[chelation therapy]], as the therapy itself increases mercury levels in the samples.&lt;ref name=Ibrahim/&gt;

Diagnosis of organic mercury poisoning differs in that whole-blood or hair analysis is more reliable than urinary mercury levels.&lt;ref name=Ibrahim&gt;{{cite journal |author= Ibrahim D, Froberg B, Wolf A, Rusyniak DE |title= Heavy metal poisoning: clinical presentations and pathophysiology |journal= Clin Lab Med |volume=26 |issue=1 |pages=67–97, viii |year=2006 |pmid=16567226 |doi=10.1016/j.cll.2006.02.003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prevention==

Mercury poisoning can be prevented (or minimized) by eliminating or reducing exposure to mercury and mercury compounds. To that end, many governments and private groups have made efforts to regulate heavily the use of mercury, or to issue advisories about its use.
For example, the export from the [[European Union]] of mercury and some mercury compounds has been prohibited since 2010-03-15.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/expert/infopress_page/064-29478-140-05-21-911-20080520IPR29477-19-05-2008-2008-false/default_en.htm |title= Export-ban of mercury and mercury compounds from the EU by 2011 |publisher= European Parliament |date=2008-05-21 |accessdate=2008-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The variability among regulations and advisories is at times confusing for the lay person as well as scientists.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxprofiles/tp46-c7.pdf ATSDR - Mercury - Regulations and Advisories]&lt;/ref&gt;
!Country
!Regulating agency
!Regulated activity
!Medium
!Type of mercury compound
!Type of limit
!Limit
|-
|US
|[[Occupational Safety and Health Administration]]
|occupational exposure
|air
|elemental mercury
|Ceiling (not to exceed)
|0.1&amp;nbsp;mg/m³
|-
|US
|Occupational Safety and Health Administration
|occupational exposure
|air
|organic mercury
|Ceiling (not to exceed)
|0.05&amp;nbsp;mg/m³
|-
|US
|Food and Drug Administration
|eating
|sea food
|methylmercury
|Maximum allowable concentration
|1 [[Parts per million|ppm]] (1&amp;nbsp;mg/L)
|-
|US
|[[United States Environmental Protection Agency|Environmental Protection Agency]]
|drinking
|water
|inorganic mercury
|Maximum contaminant level
|2 ppb (0.002&amp;nbsp;mg/L)
|}

The [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]] (EPA) issued recommendations in 2004 regarding exposure to [[mercury in fish]] and shellfish.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.epa.gov/waterscience/fish/advice/ What You Need to Know about Mercury in Fish and Shellfish]&lt;/ref&gt;  The EPA also developed the &quot;Fish Kids&quot; awareness campaign for children and young adults &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.epa.gov/waterscience/fish/kids/ EPA Fish Kids Flash-based Movie]&lt;/ref&gt; on account of the greater impact of mercury exposure to that population.

==Treatment==
Identifying and removing the source of the mercury is crucial. Decontamination requires removal of clothes, washing skin with soap and water, and flushing the eyes with saline solution as needed. Inorganic ingestion such as [[mercuric chloride]] should be approached as the ingestion of any other serious [[Corrosive substance|caustic]]. Immediate [[chelation therapy]] is the [[standard of care]] for a patient showing symptoms of severe mercury poisoning or the laboratory evidence of a large total mercury load.&lt;ref name=Clifton/&gt;

[[Chelation therapy]] for acute inorganic mercury poisoning can be done with [[2,3-Dimercaptosuccinic acid|DMSA]], [[2,3-dimercapto-1-propanesulfonic acid]] (DMPS), [[D-penicillamine]] (DPCN), or [[dimercaprol]] (BAL).&lt;ref name=Clifton/&gt; Only DMSA is FDA-approved for use in children for treating mercury poisoning. However, several studies found no clear clinical benefit from DMSA treatment for poisoning due to mercury vapor.&lt;ref name=Risher&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Neurotoxicology |year=2005 |volume=26 |issue=4 |pages=691–9 |title= Mercury exposure: evaluation and intervention the inappropriate use of chelating agents in the diagnosis and treatment of putative mercury poisoning |author= Risher JF, Amler SN |doi=10.1016/j.neuro.2005.05.004 |pmid=16009427}}&lt;/ref&gt; No chelator for methylmercury or ethylmercury is approved by the FDA; DMSA is the most frequently used for severe methylmercury poisoning, as it is given orally, has fewer side-effects, and has been found to be superior to BAL, DPCN, and DMPS.&lt;ref name=Clifton/&gt; [[Alpha-lipoic acid]] (ALA) has been shown to be protective against acute mercury poisoning in several mammalian species when it is given soon after exposure; correct dosage is required, as inappropriate dosages increase toxicity. Although it has been hypothesized that frequent low dosages of ALA may have potential as a mercury chelator, studies in rats have been contradictory.&lt;ref name=Rooney/&gt; [[Glutathione]] and [[N-acetylcysteine]] (NAC) are recommended by some physicians, but have been shown to increase mercury concentrations in the kidneys and the brain.&lt;ref name=Rooney&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Toxicology |year=2007 |volume=234 |issue=3 |pages=145–56 |title= The role of thiols, dithiols, nutritional factors and interacting ligands in the toxicology of mercury |author= Rooney JP |doi=10.1016/j.tox.2007.02.016 |pmid=17408840}}&lt;/ref&gt; Experimental findings have demonstrated an interaction between [[selenium]] and methylmercury, but epidemiological studies have found little evidence that selenium helps to protect against the adverse effects of methylmercury.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Tohoku J Exp Med |year=2002 |volume=196 |issue=2 |pages=71–7 |title= Modification of mercury toxicity by selenium: practical importance? |author= Watanabe C |doi=10.1620/tjem.196.71 |pmid=12498318 |url=http://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/article/tjem/196/2/71/_pdf |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Even if the patient has no symptoms or documented history of mercury exposure, a minority of physicians (predominantly those in [[alternative medicine]]) use chelation to &quot;rid&quot; the body of mercury, which they believe to cause [[neurological]] and other disorders. A common practice is to challenge the patient's body with a chelation agent, collect urine samples, and then use laboratory reports to diagnose the patient with toxic levels of mercury; often no pre-chelation urine sample is collected for comparison. The patient is then advised to undergo further chelation.&lt;ref name=Risher/&gt; No scientific data supports the claim that the mercury in vaccines causes autism&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Can J Neurol Sci |year=2006 |volume=33 |issue=4 |pages=341–6 |title= Immunizations and autism: a review of the literature |author= Doja A, Roberts W |pmid=17168158}}&lt;/ref&gt; or its symptoms,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal= N Engl J Med |volume=357 |issue=13 |pages=1281–92 |year=2007 |title= Early thimerosal exposure and neuropsychological outcomes at 7 to 10 years |author= Thompson WW, Price C, Goodson B ''et al.'' |pmid=17898097 |url=http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/357/13/1281 |doi= 10.1056/NEJMoa071434}}&lt;/ref&gt; and there is no scientific support for chelation therapy as a treatment for autism.&lt;ref name=Weber&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Pediatr Clin North Am |year=2007 |volume=54 |issue=6 |pages=983–1006 |title= Complementary and alternative medical therapies for attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder and autism |author= Weber W, Newmark S |doi=10.1016/j.pcl.2007.09.006 |pmid=18061787}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chelation therapy can be hazardous if administered incorrectly. In August 2005, an incorrect form of EDTA used for chelation therapy resulted in [[hypocalcemia]], causing [[cardiac arrest]] that killed a five-year-old autistic boy.&lt;ref name=hypocalcemia&gt;Hazards of chelation therapy:
*{{cite journal |journal=Pediatrics |year=2006 |volume=118 |issue=2 |pages=e534–6 |title= Deaths resulting from hypocalcemia after administration of edetate disodium: 2003–2005 |author= Brown MJ, Willis T, Omalu B, Leiker R |doi=10.1542/peds.2006-0858 |pmid=16882789 |url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/118/2/e534}}
*{{cite journal |author= Baxter AJ, Krenzelok EP |title= Pediatric fatality secondary to EDTA chelation |journal= Clin Toxicol |volume=46 |issue=10 |pages=1083–4 |year=2008 |pmid=18949650 |doi=10.1080/15563650701261488}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prognosis==
Many of the toxic effects of mercury are partially or wholly reversible, either through specific therapy or through natural elimination of the metal after exposure has been discontinued.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.neonatology.org/pdf/pinkdisease.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;  However, heavy or prolonged exposure can do irreversible damage, in particular in fetuses, infants, and young children. [[Young's syndrome]] is believed to be a long term consequence of early childhood mercury poisoning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Hendry WF, A'Hern RP, Cole PJ |title=Was Young's syndrome caused by exposure to mercury in childhood? |journal=BMJ |volume=307 |issue=6919 |pages=1579–82 |year=1993 |pmid=8292944 |pmc=1697782 |doi=10.1136/bmj.307.6919.1579 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mercuric chloride]] may cause cancer as it has caused increases in several types of tumors in rats and mice, while methyl mercury has caused kidney tumors in male rats. The EPA has classified mercuric chloride and methyl mercury as possible human carcinogens (ATSDR, EPA)

===Detection in biological fluids===
Mercury may be measured in blood or urine to confirm a diagnosis of poisoning in hospitalized victims or to assist in the forensic investigation in a case of fatal overdosage. Some analytical techniques are capable of distinguishing organic from inorganic forms of the metal. The concentrations in both fluids tend to reach high levels early after exposure to inorganic forms, while lower but very persistent levels are observed following exposure to elemental or organic mercury. Chelation therapy can cause a transient elevation of urine mercury levels.&lt;ref&gt;R. Baselt, ''Disposition of Toxic Drugs and Chemicals in Man'', 8th edition, Biomedical Publications, Foster City, CA, 2008, pp. 923-927.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

* The first emperor of unified China, [[Qin Shi Huang]], it is reported, died of ingesting mercury pills that were intended to give him eternal life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Zhao HL, Zhu X, Sui Y |title= The short-lived Chinese emperors |journal= J Am Geriatr Soc |volume=54 |issue=8 |pages=1295–6 |year=2006 |pmid=16914004 |doi=10.1111/j.1532-5415.2006.00821.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The phrase ''[[mad as a hatter]]'' is likely a reference to mercury poisoning, as mercury-based compounds were once used in the manufacture of [[Felt|felt hats]] in the 18th and 19th century. (The [[Mad Hatter]] character of ''[[Alice in Wonderland]]'' was, it is presumed, inspired by an eccentric furniture dealer named [[Theophilus Carter]]. Carter was  not a victim of [[mad hatter disease]] although [[Lewis Carroll]] would have been familiar with the phenomenon of dementia that occurred among hatters.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Br Med J (Clin Res Ed) |year=1983 |volume=287 |issue=6409 |pages=1961 |title= Did the Mad Hatter have mercury poisoning? |author= Waldron HA |pmid=6418283 |pmc=1550196 |doi= 10.1136/bmj.287.6409.1961}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1810, two British ships, [[HMS Triumph (1764)|HMS ''Triumph'']] and HMS ''Phipps'', salvaged a large load of elemental mercury from a wrecked Spanish vessel near Cadiz, Spain. The bladders containing the mercury soon ruptured. The element spread about the ships in liquid and vapor forms.  The sailors presented with neurologic compromises: tremor, paralysis, and excessive salivation as well as tooth loss, skin problems, and pulmonary complaints.  In 1823 William Burnet, MD published a report on the effects of Mercurial vapor.&lt;ref&gt;An Account of the Effect of Mercurial Vapors on the Crew of His Majesty's Ship Triumph, in the year 1810. By Wm. Burnet, M.D. one of the Medical Commissioners of the Navy, formerly Physician and Inspector of Hospitals to the Mediterranean Fleet.&lt;/ref&gt;  The ''Triumph''’s [[Ship's surgeon|surgeon]], Henry Plowman, had concluded that the ailments had arisen from inhaling the mercurialized atmosphere.  His treatment was to order the lower deck gun ports to be opened, when it was safe to do so; sleeping on the orlop was forbidden; and no men slept in the lower deck if they were at all symptomatic. Windsails were set to channel fresh air into the lower decks day and night.&lt;ref&gt;Michael J. Doherty MD: The Quicksilver Prize: Mercury vapor poisoning aboard HMS Triumph and HMS Phipps (2003).&lt;/ref&gt;
* For years, including the early part of his presidency, [[Abraham Lincoln]] took a common medicine of his time called &quot;[[blue mass]],&quot; which contained significant amounts of mercury.
* On September 5, 1920, silent movie actress [[Olive Thomas]] ingested mercury capsules dissolved in an alcoholic solution at the Hotel Ritz in Paris. There is still controversy over whether it was suicide, or whether she consumed the external preparation by mistake. Her husband, [[Jack Pickford]] (the brother of [[Mary Pickford]]), had [[syphilis]], and the mercury was used as a treatment of the venereal disease at the time. She died a few days later at the American Hospital in Neuilly.
* An early scientific study of mercury poisoning was in 1923–6 by the German inorganic chemist, [[Alfred Stock]], who himself became poisoned, together with his colleagues, by breathing mercury vapor that was being released by his laboratory equipment—[[diffusion pump]]s, [[float valve]]s, and [[manometer]]s—all of which contained mercury, and also from mercury that had been accidentally spilt and remained in cracks in the [[linoleum]] floor covering. He published a number of papers on mercury poisoning, founded a committee in Berlin to study cases of possible mercury poisoning, and introduced the term ''micromercurialism''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Stock A |title=Die Gefaehrlichkeit des Quecksilberdampfes |journal=Zeitschrift für angewandte Chemie |pages=461–466 |issue= 15 |volume=39 |year=1926 |doi=10.1002/ange.19260391502 |authorlink= Alfred Stock}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The term ''Hunter-Russell syndrome'' derives from a study of mercury poisoning among workers in a seed packing factory in [[Norwich]], England in the late 1930s who breathed [[methylmercury]] that was being used as a seed disinfectant and preservative.&lt;ref name=&quot;hunterwalker&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | title=Poisoning by methylmercury compounds | author=Hunter D, Bomford RR, Russell DS | journal=Quart. J. Med. | volume=9 | pages=193–213 | year=1940}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Outbreaks of [[methylmercury]] poisoning occurred in several places in Japan during the 1950s due to industrial discharges of mercury into rivers and coastal waters. The best-known instances were in [[Minamata, Kumamoto|Minamata]] and [[Niigata Prefecture|Niigata]]. In Minamata alone, more than 600 people died due to what became known as [[Minamata disease]]. More than 21,000 people filed claims with the Japanese government, of which almost 3000 became certified as having the disease. In 22 documented cases, pregnant women who consumed contaminated fish showed mild or no symptoms but gave birth to infants with severe developmental disabilities.&lt;ref name=Davidson&gt;{{cite journal |author= Davidson PW, Myers GJ, Weiss B |title= Mercury exposure and child development outcomes |journal=Pediatrics |volume=113 |issue= 4 Suppl |pages=1023–9 |year=2004 |pmid=15060195  |url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/113/Supplement_3/1023.full |doi=10.1542/peds.113.4.S1.1023}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Widespread mercury poisoning occurred in rural [[Iraq]] in 1971-1972, when grain treated with a methylmercury-based [[fungicide]] that was intended for planting only was used by the rural population to make bread, causing at least 6530 cases of mercury poisoning and at least 459 deaths (see [[Basra poison grain disaster]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;basraincident&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| url=http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=5002117801| title=Technology out of Control| author= Engler R | journal=The Nation| volume=240| month=April 27| year=1985}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On August 14, 1996, [[Karen Wetterhahn]], a chemistry professor working at [[Dartmouth College]], spilled a small amount of [[dimethylmercury]] on her latex glove. She began experiencing the symptoms of mercury poisoning five months later and, despite aggressive [[chelation therapy]], died a few months later from [[Encephalopathy|brain malfunction]] due to mercury intoxication.&lt;ref name=bris&gt;[http://www.chm.bris.ac.uk/motm/dimethylmercury/dmmh.htm The Karen Wetterhahn story] - University of Bristol web page documenting her death, retrieved December 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=osha&gt;[http://www.osha.gov/dts/hib/hib_data/hib19980309.html OSHA update following Karen Wetterhahn's death]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In April 2000, Alan Chmurny attempted to kill a former employee, Marta Bradley, by pouring mercury into the [[ventilation (architecture)|ventilation]] system of her car.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Mad Scientist': On Court TV, Fatal Chemistry|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/01/25/AR2007012502091.html|publisher=[[The Washington Post]]|author= Vargas JA |date=2007-01-26|accessdate=2007-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On March 19, 2008, Tony Winnett, 55, inhaled mercury vapors while trying to extract gold from computer parts (by using liquid mercury to separate gold from the rest of the alloy), and died ten days later. His Oklahoma residence became so contaminated that it had to be gutted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= Swearengin M |title= Man dies from mercury poisoning after trying to extract gold |work= Durant Daily Democrat |&lt;!-- after 14 days, convenience link goes to registration page: url=http://www.durantdemocrat.com/articles/2008/04/01/news/doc47f14876d8777987127925.txt  summary still available: url=http://www.durantdemocrat.com/shared-content/search/index.php?search=go&amp;o=0&amp;q=mercury&amp;d1=3-31-2008&amp;d2=5-4-2008&amp;section%5B%5D=news+or+breaking_news&amp;s=relevance&amp;r=Subject%2CAuthor%2CContent&amp;l=20 --&gt; | date=2008-04-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=(Associated Press) | title=Colbert man dies from mercury poisoning | publisher=''Tulsa World'' | date=2008-04-01 | url=http://www.tulsaworld.com/news/article.aspx?articleID=20080401_12_80377 |  accessdate=2008-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In December 2008, actor [[Jeremy Piven]] was diagnosed with [[hydrargyria]] resulting from eating sushi twice a day for twenty years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Jeremy Piven Explains His Mystery Ailment|url=http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20252763,00.html |work=[[People (magazine)|People]] |author=Tiffany McGee|date=2009-01-15|accessdate=2009-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Actress [[Daphne Zuniga]] was diagnosed with mercury poisoning after eating sushi four times a week.
* In India, a study by non-profit [[Centre_for_Science_and_Environment|Centre for Science and Environment]] has found that in country's energy capital, Singrauli&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.downtoearth.org.in/content/india-s-minamata?page=0,0 Down To Earth: India's Minimata]&lt;/ref&gt;, mercury is slowly entering people's homes, food, water and even blood. 
=== Infantile acrodynia ===
Infantile acrodynia (also known as &quot;calomel disease&quot;, &quot;erythredemic polyneuropathy&quot;, and &quot;pink disease&quot;) is a type of mercury poisoning in children characterized by pain and pink discoloration of the hands and feet.&lt;ref name=Andrews&gt;{{cite book |author= James WD, Berger TG, Elston DM |title= Andrews' diseases of the skin: clinical dermatology |publisher=Saunders |year=2006 |isbn=0-7216-2921-0 |edition=10th |page=134}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word is derived from the [[Greek language|Greek]], where άκρο means ''end'' (as in: upper [[Limb (anatomy)|extremity]]) and οδυνη means ''pain''. Also known as pink disease, Swift disease, Feer disease, Selter disease, erythroderma, erythroderma polyneuritis, dermatopolyneuritis, trophodermatoneurosis, erythema arthricum epidemicum,&lt;ref&gt;The name ''erythema arthricum epidemicum'' more commonly describes [[Haverhill fever]] (rat-bite fever).&lt;/ref&gt; vegetative neurosis, and vegetative encephalitis.&lt;ref name=&quot;geir&quot;/&gt; These terms describe different aspects of the syndrome.  Acrodynia was relatively commonplace among children in the first half of the 20th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;pink&quot;/&gt; At first, the cause of the acrodynia [[epidemic]] among infants and young children was unknown;&lt;ref name='family-doctor-1935'&gt;{{cite book | last = No Given Author or Editor. | title = Everybody's Family Doctor | publisher = Odhams Press LTD | year = 1935 | location = London, UK | pages = 16 }}&lt;/ref&gt; however, mercury poisoning, primarily from [[calomel]] in teething powders, began to be widely accepted as its cause in the 1950s and 60s.&lt;ref name=&quot;geir&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pink&quot;/&gt; The prevalence of acrodynia decreased greatly after calomel was excluded from most teething powders in 1954.&lt;ref name=geir&gt;{{cite journal | author = Bjørklund G | year = 1995 | title = 
Mercury and Acrodynia | url = http://www.orthomolecular.org/library/jom/1995/pdf/1995-v10n0304-p145.pdf | journal = Journal of Orthomolecular Medicine | volume = 10 | issue = 3 &amp; 4 | pages = 145–146 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pink&gt;{{cite journal |title= The rise and fall of pink disease |author= Dally A |journal= Soc Hist Med |year=1997 |volume=10 |issue=2 |pages=291–304 |doi=10.1093/shm/10.2.291 |pmid=11619497}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Acrodynia is difficult to diagnose, &quot;it is most often postulated that the etiology of this syndrome is an idiosyncratic hypersensitivity reaction to mercury because of the lack of correlation with mercury levels, many of the symptoms resemble recognized mercury poisoning.&quot;&lt;ref name=Ford&gt;{{cite book |author= Ford M, Delaney KA, Ling L, Erickson T |title=Clinical Toxicology |publisher=Saunders |year=2000 |isbn=0-7216-5485-1 |edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Medical procedures===
Because elemental mercury often passes through the GI tract without being absorbed, it was used medically for various purposes until the dangers of mercury poisoning became known. For example, elemental mercury was used to mechanically clear intestinal obstructions (due to its great weight and fluidity), and it was a key ingredient in various medicines throughout history, such as [[blue mass]].  The toxic effects often were either not noticed at all or so subtle or generic that they were attributed to other causes and were not recognized as poisoning caused by mercury. While the usage of mercury in medicine has declined, mercury-containing compounds are still used medically in vaccines and dental amalgam, both of which have been the subject of controversy regarding their potential for mercury poisoning.

====Thiomersal====
{{Details|Thiomersal controversy}}

In 1999, the [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention|Centers for Disease Control]] (CDC) and the [[American Academy of Pediatrics]] (AAP) asked vaccine makers to remove the [[organomercury]] compound [[thiomersal]] (spelled &quot;thimerosal&quot; in the US) from vaccines as quickly as possible, and thiomersal has been phased out of US and European vaccines, except for some preparations of [[influenza vaccine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Offit&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |journal=N Engl J Med |year=2007 |volume=357 |issue=13 |pages=1278–9 |title=Thimerosal and vaccines—a cautionary tale |author=[[Paul Offit|Offit PA]] |doi=10.1056/NEJMp078187 |pmid=17898096 |url=http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/357/13/1278}}&lt;/ref&gt; The CDC and the AAP followed the [[precautionary principle]], which assumes that there is no harm in exercising caution even if it later turns out to be unwarranted, but their 1999 action sparked confusion and controversy that has diverted attention and resources away from efforts to determine the causes of autism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Offit&quot; /&gt; Since 2000, the thiomersal in child vaccines has been alleged to contribute to [[autism]], and thousands of parents in the United States have pursued legal compensation from a federal fund.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sugarman&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |journal=N Engl J Med |year=2007 |volume=357 |issue=13 |pages=1275–7 |title=Cases in vaccine court—legal battles over vaccines and autism |author=Sugarman SD |pmid=17898095 |url=http://content.nejm.org/cgi/content/full/357/13/1275 |doi=10.1056/NEJMp078168}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2004 [[Institute of Medicine]] (IOM) committee favored rejecting any causal relationship between thiomersal-containing vaccines and autism.&lt;ref name=&quot;ISRC&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Immunization Safety Review Committee |title=Immunization Safety Review: Vaccines and Autism |publisher=The National Academies Press |year=2004 |isbn=0-309-09237-X |url=http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=10997 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Autism incidence rates increased steadily even after thiomersal was removed from childhood vaccines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gerber&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gerber|first=Jeffrey S.|coauthors=Paul A. Offit|title=Vaccines and Autism: A Tale of Shifting Hypotheses|journal=Clinical Infectious Diseases|url=http://cid.oxfordjournals.org/content/48/4/456.full|year=2009|volume=48|issue=4|pages=456-451|doi=10.1086/596476|pmid=19128068}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently there is no accepted scientific evidence that exposure to thiomersal is a factor in causing autism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Can J Neurol Sci |year=2006 |volume=33 |issue=4 |pages=341–6 |title=Immunizations and autism: a review of the literature |author=Doja A, Roberts W |pmid=17168158}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Dental amalgam====
{{Details|Dental amalgam controversy}}

[[Amalgam (dentistry)|Dental amalgam]], an alloy of about 50 percent elemental mercury, was first introduced in France in the early 19th century.&lt;ref name='Ferracane_2001'&gt;{{cite book |author= Ferracane JL |title= Materials in Dentistry: Principles and Applications |edition=2nd |publisher= Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins |year=2001 |page=3 |isbn=0-7817-2733-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chosen for its cost-effective durability, this amalgam is a source of low-level exposure to mercury vapour, and an enormous amount of controversy. Although the vast majority of patients with amalgam fillings are exposed to levels believed to be too low to pose any risk to health, many patients (i.e., those in the upper 99.9 percentile) exhibit urine test results that are comparable to those at the maximum allowable legal limits for workplace (occupational) safety.&lt;ref&gt;L. Barregard.(2005) Occupational and Environmental Medicine, June 1, 2005. no. 62 pg. 352-353. Mercury From Dental Amalgam: Looking Beyond the Average. http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1741026/pdf/v062p00352.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Occupational Safety and Health Guideline for Mercury, OSHA, US Department of Labor http://www.osha.gov/SLTC/healthguidelines/mercuryvapor/recognition.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Diana Echeverria, et al. (1998) The FASEB Journal
vol. 12, no. 11, pg. 971-980.  Neurobehavioral Effects from Exposure to Dental Amalgam (Hg0): new distinctions between recent exposure and Hg body burden. http://www.fasebj.org/content/12/11/971.full retrieved:19/10/2011.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- NOTE: It shouldn't be overlooked that (1) renal function is widely thought to be the first thing to go in low-level long-term mercury exposure and (2) when renal function is lost urine mercury levels may become uncoupled from blood mercury levels. --&gt; Nonetheless, in the United States the [[National Institutes of Health]] has stated that amalgam fillings pose no personal health risk, and that replacement by non-amalgam fillings is not indicated.&lt;ref name=Clifton&gt;{{cite journal |journal= Pediatr Clin North Am |year=2007 |volume=54 |issue=2 |pages=237–69, viii |title= Mercury exposure and public health |author= Clifton JC 2nd |doi=10.1016/j.pcl.2007.02.005 |pmid=17448359}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Norway]], amalgam fillings are banned due to concerns over public health and environmental pollution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Edlich RF, Cochran AA, Cross CL, Wack CA, Long WB, Newkirk AT |title=Legislation and informed consent brochures for dental patients receiving amalgam restorations |journal=Int J Toxicol |volume=27 |issue=4 |pages=313–6 |year=2008 |pmid=18821394 |doi=10.1080/10915810802366851 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Maths Berlin, Professor Emeritus of Environmental Medicine and chair of the 1991 World Health Organization Task Group on Environmental Health Criteria for Inorganic Mercury, published {{medical citation needed|date=December 2011}} an overview and assessment of the scientific literature published between November 1997 and 2002 as part of a special investigation for the Swedish Government on amalgam-related health issues. The report concluded: &quot;With reference to the fact that mercury is a multipotent toxin with effects on several levels of the biochemical dynamics of the cell, amalgam must be considered to be an unsuitable material for dental restoration.&quot;

===Cosmetics===

Some [[skin whitening]] products contain the toxic chemical mercury(II) chloride as the active ingredient. When applied, the chemical readily absorbs through the skin into the bloodstream.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whitening skin can be deadly&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Whitening skin can be deadly |author= Counter SA |publisher=The Boston Globe|url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/health_science/articles/2003/12/16/whitening_skin_can_be_deadly/|date=December 16, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of [[mercury (element)|mercury]] in cosmetics is illegal in the United States. However, cosmetics containing mercury are often illegally imported. Following a certified case of mercury poisoning resulting from the use of an imported skin whitening product, the United States [[Food and Drug Administration (United States)|Food and Drug Administration]] warned against the use of such products.&lt;ref name=&quot;FDA Proposes Hydroquinone Ban&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=FDA Proposes Hydroquinone Ban|url=http://www.medicinenet.com/script/main/art.asp?articlekey=64167}}FDA bans hydroquinone in skin whitening products&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYC HEALTH DEPT&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|title=NYC Health Dept. Warns Against Use of &quot;Skin-lightening&quot; Creams Containing Mercury or Similar Products Which Do Not List Ingredients|date=January 27, 2005|url=http://www.nyc.gov/html/doh/html/pr/pr008-05.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; Symptoms of mercury poisoning have resulted from the use of various mercury-containing cosmetic products.&lt;ref name=Clarkson-Magos&gt;{{cite journal |title=The toxicology of mercury and its chemical compounds |author= Clarkson TW, Magos L |journal= Crit Rev Toxicol |year=2006 |volume=36 |issue=8 |pages=609–62 |doi=10.1080/10408440600845619 |pmid=16973445}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercury exposure in children: a review&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Mercury exposure in children: a review|author= Counter SA, Buchanan LH |url=http://www.state.nj.us/health/eoh/cehsweb/kiddiekollege/documents/counter04_mercuryexpochildren.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|title=Dynamics of Mercury Pollution on Regional and Global Scales
|author= Mahaffey KR
|url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/w245027uu23r4381/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of skin whitening products is especially popular amongst Asian women.&lt;ref name=&quot;synovate&quot;&gt;In a survey, 28% of Koreans and 50% of Philippians say that they use skin whitening products.{{Cite web
|title=Skin lightening in Asia? A bright future?
|url=http://www.synovate.com/knowledge/infact/issues/200406/}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Hong Kong in 2002, two products were discovered to contain between 9,000 to 60,000 times the recommended dose.&lt;ref name=&quot;SKIN DEEP: Dying to be white&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
|title=SKIN DEEP: Dying to be white
|author= Bray M
|publisher=CNN
|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2002/WORLD/asiapcf/east/05/13/asia.whitening/
| date=2002-05-15
| accessdate=2010-05-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fluorescent lamps===

[[Fluorescent lamp]]s contain mercury released when bulbs are broken. Mercury in bulbs is typically present as either elemental mercury liquid, vapor, or both, since the liquid evaporates at ambient temperature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Aucott M, McLinden M, Winka M |title=Release of mercury from broken fluorescent bulbs |journal=J Air Waste Manag Assoc |volume=53 |issue=2 |pages=143–51 |year=2003 |pmid=12617289 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When broken indoors, bulbs may emit sufficient mercury vapor to present health concerns, and the [[U.S. Environmental Protection Agency]] recommends evacuating and airing out a room for at least 15 minutes after breaking a fluorescent light bulb.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Spills, disposal and site cleanup |url=http://epa.gov/hg/spills/ |accessdate=2009-06-30 |date=2009-07-13 |publisher=U.S. Environmental Protection Agency }}&lt;/ref&gt; Breakage of multiple bulbs presents a greater concern. A 1987 report described a 23-month-old toddler who suffered [[Anorexia (symptom)|anorexia]], weight loss, irritability, profuse sweating, and peeling and redness of fingers and toes. This case of acrodynia was traced to exposure of mercury from a carton of 8-foot fluorescent light bulbs that had broken in a potting shed adjacent to the main nursery. The glass was cleaned up and discarded, but the child often used the area for play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Pediatrics |year=1987 |volume=79 |issue=5 |pages=786–9 |title= Acrodynia: exposure to mercury from fluorescent light bulbs |author= Tunnessen WW Jr, McMahon KJ, Baser M |pmid=3575038}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Assassination===
Mercury has been used at various times to assassinate people. In 2008, Russian lawyer [[Karinna Moskalenko]] claimed to have been poisoned by mercury left in her car,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2008-10-15-1112115214_x.htm ''Russian lawyer suspects mercury poisoning''], USA Today.com&lt;/ref&gt; while in 2010 journalists [[Viktor Kalashnikov]] and [[Marina Kalashnikova]] accused Russia's FSB of trying to poison them.&lt;ref name=Tel&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/germany/8227644/German-inquiry-into-poisoning-of-Russian-dissidents.html ''German inquiry into 'poisoning' of Russian dissidents''], Telegraph&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[Diagnosis Mercury: Money, Politics and Poison]]''
* [[Erethism]]
* [[Got Mercury?]]
* [[Lead poisoning]]
* [[Mercury vacuum]]
* [[Mercury-containing and Rechargeable Battery Management Act]]
* [[Methylmercury]]
* [[Minamata disease]]
* [[Niigata Minamata disease]]
* [[Ontario Minamata disease]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
&lt;!--==========================({{NoMoreLinks}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =========================({{NoMoreLinks}})=============================--&gt;
* {{dmoz|Health/Occupational_Health_and_Safety/Hazardous_Substances/Mercury|Hazardous Substances: Mercury}}
* {{dmoz|Science/Environment/Environmental_Health/Toxic_Substances/Mercury|Toxic Substances: Mercury}}

{{Poisoning and toxicity|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mercury Poisoning}}
[[Category:Mercury poisoning| ]]
[[Category:Drug eruptions]]

[[da:Kviksølvforgiftning]]
[[de:Quecksilbervergiftung]]
[[es:Envenenamiento por mercurio]]
[[eo:Hidrarga veneniĝo]]
[[fr:Intoxication au mercure]]
[[ko:수은 중독]]
[[it:Avvelenamento da mercurio]]
[[nl:Kwikvergiftiging]]
[[ja:水銀中毒]]
[[pl:Rtęcica]]
[[ru:Отравления ртутью]]
[[sl:Zastrupitev z živim srebrom]]
[[fi:Elohopeamyrkytys]]
[[uk:Отруєння ртуттю]]
[[zh:汞中毒]]</text>
      <sha1>6s5q4e4y0smn093qb4f4ntedrvmzxih</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
