<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Weather modification</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>265307</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519224793</id>
      <parentid>517386557</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-22T16:18:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>149.241.204.68</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Cloud seeding */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22275">[[Image:Dszpics1.jpg|thumb|325px|right|A [[tornado]] in central [[Oklahoma]]. Weather modification researchers aspire to eliminate or control dangerous types of weather such as this.]]

'''Weather modification''' is the act of intentionally manipulating or altering the [[weather]].  The most common form of weather modification is [[cloud seeding]] to increase rain or snow, usually for the purpose of increasing the local [[water supply]].&lt;ref name=&quot;azwater&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://ag.arizona.edu/azwater/arroyo/061wthr.html | title=Weather Modification:  A Water Resource Strategy to be Researched, Tested Before Tried | publisher=University of Arizona | accessdate=April 17, 2012 | author=Gelt, Joe}}&lt;/ref&gt; Weather modification can also have the goal of preventing damaging weather, such as [[hail]] or [[hurricanes]], from occurring; or of provoking damaging weather against an enemy or rival, as a tactic of military or economic warfare.  Weather modification in warfare has been banned by the [[United Nations]].

==History==
[[Image:Witches add ingredients to a cauldron.JPG|thumb|[[Witchcraft|Witch]]es concoct a [[Potion|brew]] to summon a [[hail]]storm.]]

[[Magic (paranormal)|Magical]] and [[religion|religious]] practices to control the weather are attested in a variety of cultures. In ancient [[India]] it is said that yajna or vedic rituals of chanting manthras and offering were performed by [[rishis]] to bring sudden bursts of rain fall in rain starved regions. Some [[indigenous peoples of the Americas|American Indians]] like some Europeans had rituals which they believed could induce rain. The [[Finns|Finnish people]], on the other hand, were believed by others to be able to control weather. As a result, [[Viking]]s refused to take Finns on their oceangoing raids. Remnants of this superstition lasted into the twentieth century, with some ship crews being reluctant to accept Finnish sailors. The early modern era saw people observe that during battles the firing of [[cannon]]s and other firearms often initiated precipitation.
In [[Greek mythology]], [[Iphigenia]] was offered as a [[human sacrifice]] to appease the wrath of the goddess [[Artemis]], who had becalmed the [[Achaeans (Homer)|Achaean]] fleet at [[Avlida|Aulis]] at the beginning of the [[Trojan War]].  In [[Homer]]'s ''[[Odyssey]]'', [[Aeolus]], keeper of the winds, bestowed [[Odysseus]] and his crew with a gift of the four winds in a bag.  However, the sailors opened the bag while Odysseus slept, looking for booty, and as a result were blown off course by the resulting gale.&lt;ref&gt;Homer, ''[[s:The Odyssey/Book X|The Odyssey]]'', book 10.&lt;/ref&gt;  In ancient Rome, the ''[[lapis manalis]]'' was a sacred stone kept outside the [[Servian Wall|walls of Rome]] in a temple of [[Mars (mythology)|Mars]].  When Rome suffered from [[drought]], the stone was dragged into the city.&lt;ref&gt;Sir [[James George Frazer|James Frazer]], ''[[The Golden Bough]]'', ch. 5 (abridged edition), &quot;The Magical Control of Rain&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[North Berwick witch trials|Berwick witches]] of [[Scotland]] were found guilty of using [[black magic]] to summon storms to murder [[James I of England|King James VI of Scotland]] by seeking to sink the ship upon which he travelled.&lt;ref&gt;[[Christopher Smout]], ''A History of the Scottish People 1560-1830'', pp. 184-192&lt;/ref&gt;  Scandinavian witches allegedly claimed to sell the [[wind]] in bags or magically confined into wooden staves; they sold the bags to seamen who could release them when becalmed.&lt;ref&gt;[[Adam of Bremen]] and [[Ole Worm]] are quoted as maintaining this in Grillot de Givry's ''Witchcraft, Magic and Alchemy'' (Frederick Publications, 1954).&lt;/ref&gt;  In various towns of [[Navarre]], [[prayer]]s petitioned [[Saint Peter]] to grant rain in time of drought.  If the rain was not forthcoming, the statue of St Peter was removed from the church and tossed into a river.&lt;ref&gt;Frazer, ''supra''.&lt;/ref&gt;

The theoretical efficacy of von Neumann's proposal remains to be examined. [[Wilhelm Reich]] performed [[cloudbuster|cloudbusting]] experiments in the 1950s to 1960s, the results of which are controversial and not widely accepted by mainstream science.

Dr Walter Russell wrote of weather control in Atomic Suicide 1956.&quot;--give him complete power to cause rains, wherever he desires, on deserts or meadows and to dissipate cyclones while forming.&quot;page xxvii

In January, 2011, several newspapers and magazines, including the UK's ''Sunday Times'' and ''Arabian Business'', reported that scientists backed by the government of Abu Dhabi, the capital of the [[United Arab Emirates]], had created over 50 artificial rainstorms between July and August 2010 near Al Ain, a city which lies close to the country's border with [[Oman]] and is the second-largest city in the Abu Dhabi Emirate. The artificial rainstorms were said to have sometimes caused hail, gales and thunderstorms, baffling local residents.&lt;ref&gt;Leigh, Karen. [http://www.arabianbusiness.com/abu-dhabi-backed-scientists-create-fake-rainstorms-in-11m-project-371038.html], &quot;Arabian Business&quot;, January 3, 2011. Retrieved 2011-01-8.&lt;/ref&gt; The scientists reportedly used ionizers to create the rainstorms, and although the results are disputed, the large number of times it is recorded to have rained right after the ionizers were switched on during a usually dry season is encouraging to those who support the experiment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-1343470/Have-scientists-discovered-create-downpours-desert.html], &quot;Daily Mail&quot;, January 3, 2011. Retrieved 2011-01-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Cloud Seeding.svg|thumb|left|300px|Cloud seeding]]

==Cloud seeding==
{{main|Cloud Seeding}}
Cloud seeding is a common technique to enhance precipitation. Evidence on its safety is strong, but there are still doubts about its effectiveness. Cloud seeding entails spraying small particles (like silver iodide) onto clouds in order to affect their development, usually with the goal of increasing precipitation. Cloud seeding only works to the extent that there is already water vapor present in the air.  Critics generally contend that claimed successes occur in conditions which were going to lead to rain anyway. It is used in a variety of drought-prone countries, including the [[United States]], the [[People's Republic of China]], [[India]], and [[Russia]]. In the People's Republic of China there is a perceived dependency upon it in dry regions, and there is a strong suspicion it is used to &quot;wash the air&quot; in dry and heavily polluted places, such as [[Beijing]]. In mountainous areas of the United States such as the Rocky Mountains and Sierra Nevada,&lt;ref&gt;Hunter, Steven M. (U.S. Bureau of Reclamation). 2007. Optimizing Cloud Seeding for Water and Energy in California. California Energy Commission, PIER Energy‐Related Environmental Research Program. CEC‐500‐2007‐008. http://www.energy.ca.gov/2007publications/CEC-500-2007-008/CEC-500-2007-008.PDF&lt;/ref&gt; cloud seeding has been employed since the 1950s.{{clr}}

[[File:Project stormfury hypothesis.gif|thumb|right|250px|[[Project Stormfury]]]]

==Storm prevention==
[[File:International congress on hail shooting.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Hail cannon]]s at an international congress on hail shooting held in 1901]]
[[Project Stormfury]] was an attempt to weaken [[tropical cyclone]]s by flying aircraft into storms and seeding the [[eye (cyclone)|eyewall]] with silver iodide. The project was run by the [[federal government of the United States|United States Government]] from 1962 to 1983.  A similar project using soot was run in 1958, with inconclusive results.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsci1&quot; /&gt; Various methods have been proposed to reduce the harmful effects of hurricanes.  Moshe Alamaro of the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://alamaro.home.comcast.net/Alamaro-bio.htm |title=Moshe Alamaro's brief bio |publisher=Alamaro.home.comcast.net |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; proposed using barges with upward-pointing jet engines to trigger smaller storms to disrupt the progress of an incoming hurricane; critics doubt the jets would be powerful enough to make any noticeable difference.&lt;ref name=&quot;newsci1&quot;&gt;http://environment.newscientist.com/article/dn7995.html - Alamaro proposal and energy critique&lt;/ref&gt;

Alexandre Chorin of the [[University of California, Berkeley]], proposed dropping large amounts of environmentally friendly oils on the sea surface to prevent droplet formation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn7726 |title=Chorin proposal |publisher=Newscientist.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Experiments by Kerry Emanuel&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wind.mit.edu/~emanuel/home.html |title=Kerry Emanuel's Homepage |publisher=Wind.mit.edu |date=2002-05-15 |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; of MIT in 2002 suggested that hurricane-force winds would disrupt the oil slick, making it ineffective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://environment.newscientist.com/article/dn7995.html |title=Could humans tackle hurricanes? - earth - 14 September 2005 - New Scientist Environment |publisher=Environment.newscientist.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other scientists disputed the factual basis of the theoretical mechanism assumed by this approach.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article.ns?id=dn7726 |title=Oil on troubled waters may stop hurricanes - earth - 25 July 2005 |publisher=New Scientist |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Florida company Dyn-O-Mat proposes the use of a product it has developed, called Dyn-O-Gel, to reduce the strength of hurricanes. The substance is a [[polymer]] in powder form which reportedly has the ability to absorb 1,500 times its own weight in water.  The theory is that the polymer is dropped into clouds to remove their moisture and force the storm to use more energy to move the heavier water drops, thus helping to dissipate the storm.  When the gel reaches the ocean surface, it is reportedly dissolved.  The company has tested the substance on a thunderstorm, but there has not been any scientific consensus established as to its effectiveness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nashuatelegraph.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20051022/OPINION04/110220166/-1/news Anti-hurricane invention worth pursuing.]  Murdock, Deroy.  Scripps Howard News Service.  22 Oct 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hail cannon]]s have been used by some farmers since the 19th century in an attempt to ward off [[hail]], but there is no reliable scientific evidence to confirm their effectiveness. Another new anti-hurricane technology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=WIPO |url=http://www.wipo.int/pctdb/en/wo.jsp?IA=WO2006085830&amp;DISPLAY=STATUS |title=(WO/2006/085830) A METHOD OF AND A DEVICE FOR THE REDUCTION OF TROPICAL CYCLONES DESTRUCTIVE FORCE |publisher=Wipo.int |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a method for the reduction of tropical cyclones’ destructive force - pumping sea water into and diffusing it in the wind at the bottom of such tropical cyclone in its eyewall.

==Hurricane modification==
Various ideas for manipulating [[Tropical cyclone|hurricanes]] have been suggested.  One TV show&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/doczone/hurricane.html|title=How to stop a hurricane|publisher=CBC|accessdate=2009-05-06|deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=August 2012|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; explored various ideas such as:
*Using lasers to discharge [[lightning]] in storms which are likely to become hurricanes
*Pouring [[liquid nitrogen]] onto the sea to deprive the hurricane of [[Internal energy|heat energy]].
*Creating [[soot]] to absorb sunlight and change [[Temperature|air temperature]] and hence [[Convection|convection currents]] in the outer wall.

==Weather modification and law ==

===US and Canada agreement===
In 1975, the US and Canada entered into an agreement under the auspices of the United Nations for the exchange of information on weather modification activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://untreaty.un.org/unts/1_60000/27/20/00052955.pdf |title=Agreement Relating to the Exchange of Information on Weather Modification Activities |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1977 UN Environmental Modification Convention===
{{Main|Environmental Modification Convention}}
Weather modification, particularly hostile [[weather warfare]], was addressed by the &quot;United Nations General Assembly Resolution 31/72, TIAS 9614 Convention&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fas.org/nuke/control/enmod/text/environ2.htm |title=Environmental Modification Convention |publisher=Fas.org |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; on the Prohibition of Military or Any Other Hostile Use of Environmental Modification Techniques&quot; was adopted. The Convention was: Signed in Geneva May 18, 1977; Entered into force October 5, 1978; Ratification by U.S. President December 13, 1979; U.S. ratification deposited at New York January 17, 1980.&lt;ref name='dos'&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=Convention on the Prohibition of Military or Any Other Hostile Use of Environmental Modification Techniques | date= | publisher=[[United States Department of State]] | url =http://www.state.gov/t/ac/trt/4783.htm | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2007-09-28 | language = |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070914081350/http://www.state.gov/t/ac/trt/4783.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===US National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration===
In the US, the [[National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration]] keeps records of weather modification projects on behalf of the Secretary of Commerce, under authority of Public Law 92-205, 15 USC § 330B, enacted in 1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cornell&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/15/chapter-9A | title=15 USC CHAPTER 9A - WEATHER MODIFICATION ACTIVITIES OR ATTEMPTS; REPORTING REQUIREMENT | accessdate=April 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Proposed US Legislation===

'''2005 U.S. Senate Bill 517 and U.S. House Bill 2995'''
U.S. Senate Bill 517&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=s109-517 S. 517 [109th&amp;#93;: Weather Modification Research and Development Policy Authorization Act of 2005, proposed by [[U.S. Senator]] [[Kay Bailey Hutchison]] of [[Texas]] and then [[U.S. Representative]] (later Senator) [[Mark Udall]] of [[Colorado]] (GovTrack.us)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and U.S. House Bill 2995&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=h109-2995 |title=H.R. 2995 [109th&amp;#93;: Weather Modification Research and Technology Transfer Authorization Act of 2005 |publisher=GovTrack.us |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; were two bills proposed in 2005 that would have expanded experimental weather modification, to establish a [[Weather Modification Operations and Research Board]], and implemented a national weather modification policy.  Neither were made into law. Former [[Texas State Senate|Texas State Senator]] [[John N. Leedom]] was the key [[lobbyist]] on behalf of the weather modification bills.

'''2007 U.S. Senate Bill 1807 &amp; U.S. House Bill 3445'''
Senate Bill 1807 and House Bill 3445, identical bills introduced July 17, 2007, proposed to establish a Weather Mitigation Advisory and Research Board to fund weather modification research  &lt;ref&gt;[http://tlp.law.pitt.edu/SP_DiLorenzo_Weather%20Modification.htm ]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=s110-1807 |title=S. 1807 [110th&amp;#93;: Weather Mitigation Research and Development Policy Authorization Act of 2007 |publisher=GovTrack.us |date= |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Future aspirations ==
Climatologists have simulated hurricane control based on selective heating and cooling (or prevention of evaporation).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?articleID=000593AE-704B-1151-B57F83414B7F0000  Hoffman, R, &quot;Controlling Hurricanes,&quot; ''Scientific American,'' Oct 2004].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Futurist]] [[John Smart (futurist)|John Smart]] has discussed the potential for weather control via space-based solar power networks. One proposal involves the gentle heating via microwave of portions of large hurricanes. Such chaotic systems may be susceptible to &quot;side steering&quot; with a few degrees of increased temperature/pressure at critical points. A sufficient network might keep the largest and most potentially damaging hurricanes from landfall, at the request of host nations. Blizzards, [[monsoons]], and other extreme weather are also potential candidates for space-based amelioration.{{Citation needed|date=April 2007}} If large-scale weather control were to become feasible, potential negative implications may include:
* Unintended side effects, especially given the chaotic nature of weather development {{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
* Damage to existing ecosystems {{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
* Health risks to humans {{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
* Equipment malfunction or accidents {{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
* Malevolent control or use as a weapon {{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
* ELF hot spots causing slightly accelerated ionospheric depletion by solar wind &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=how-planets-lose-their-atmospheres  Kevin J. Zahnle, &quot;Our Planet's Leaky Atmosphere,&quot; ''Scientific American,'' May 2009].&lt;/ref&gt;{{failed verification|date=July 2012}}

For the [[2008 Olympics]], China had 30 airplanes, 4,000 rocket launchers, and 7,000 anti-aircraft guns to stop rain. Each system would shoot various chemicals into any threatening clouds to shrink rain drops before they reach the stadium.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/world/la-fg-rain31jan31,0,39372.story Demick, Barbara, &quot;China plans to halt rain for Olympics,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' January 2008].&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Weather Modification Operations and Research Board]]
* [[Global warming]]
* [[Geoengineering]]
* [[Weather forecasting]]
* [[Hail cannon]]
* [[Operation Popeye]]
* [[Beijing Weather Modification Office]]
* [[Project Cumulus]]
* [[Alberta Hail Project]]
* [[Chemtrail conspiracy theory]]
* [[Fog Investigation and Dispersal Operation]] (FIDO)

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.weathermodification.org/related_sites.htm Weather Modification Association] Perhaps the largest commercial overhead organization for weather modification research and application.
*[http://commerce.senate.gov/pdf/defelice.pdf The Testimony of Dr. Tom DeFelice] (Past President, Weather Modification Association) in support of [[Weather Modification Operations and Research Board]]
*[http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=s109-517 109th Congress S. 517: Weather Modification Research and Technology Transfer Authorization Act of 2005]
*[http://data.opi.state.mt.us/bills/2005/billhtml/HB0399.htm Article] Montana restricts spraying to a window of months and requires materials and employee lists
*&quot;[http://commerce.senate.gov/public/index.cfm?FuseAction=PressReleases.Detail&amp;PressRelease_Id=248556 The Weather Modification Operations and Research Board (passed Oct.2005) - in corporate cooperation with BAE Systems (HAARP apparatus &amp; facility owner) and Raytheon Corporation (HAARP patent owner)]
*&quot;[http://www.publicaffairs.noaa.gov/releases2005/aug05/noaa05-098.html NOAA’S National Weather Service Awards $300 Million AWIPS Contract to Raytheon]&quot;
*[http://www.weathermodification.org Weathermodification.org]
*[http://www.naiwmc.org North American Interstate Weather Modification Council]
*[http://www.iceflares.com Iceflares.com]
*[http://www.failedsuccess.com/index.php?/weblog/more/arch_weather_story The Gateway Arch as a weather control device]
*[http://www.sciam.com/article.cfm?chanID=sa006&amp;articleID=000593AE-704B-1151-B57F83414B7F0000 Scientific American Magazine (October 2004 Issue) Controlling Hurricanes]
* [http://www.history.com/shows.do?episodeId=464914&amp;action=detail That's Impossible: Weather Warfare], History Channel

==Patents==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;
;Original
* Process for weather control, H. M. Brandau, {{US patent|2756097}}
* Weather control by artificial means, Heinz W. Kasemir, {{US patent|3284005}}
* Cloud formation and subsequent moisture precipitation, {{US patent|3409220}}
* System and method for irradiation of planet surface areas, Aurthur G. Buckingham, {{US patent|3564253}}
* Weather modification method, Knollenberg, {{US patent|3613992}}
* Combustible compositions for generating aerosols, particularly suitable for cloud modification and weather control and aerosolization process, [[Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche]], {{US patent|3630950}}
* Method and apparatus for altering a region in the Earth's atmosphere, ionosphere, and/or magnetosphere, J. Eastlund{{Who|date=August 2011}}, {{US patent|4686605}}
* Method and composition for precipitation of atmospheric water, Slavko Mentus, {{US patent|5360162}}
* Use of artificial satellites in earth orbits adaptively to modify the effect that solar radiation would otherwise have on earth's weather, Franklin Y. K. Chen, {{US patent|5762298}}
* Weather modification by artificial satellites, Franklin Y. K. Chen, {{US patent|5984239}}
* Method of and a device for the reduction of tropical cyclones destructive force, Jozef Solc, [http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;p=1&amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsearch-bool.html&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;co1=AND&amp;d=PTXT&amp;s1=Solc&amp;s2=hurricane&amp;OS=Solc+AND+hurricane&amp;RS=Solc+AND+hurricane U.S. Patent 7,798,419]

;Reissue
* Combustible compositions for generating aerosols, particularly suitable for cloud modification and weather control and aerosolization process, Consiglio Nazionale delle Richerche, {{US patent|RE29142}}
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Global warming}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Weather modification}}
[[Category:Geoengineering]]
[[Category:Weather modification]]

[[bn:আবহাওয়া নিয়ন্ত্রণ]]
[[de:Wetterbeeinflussung]]
[[es:Manipulación del clima]]
[[fr:Modification du temps]]
[[he:שינוי מזג אוויר]]
[[lt:Orų valdymas]]
[[nl:Weerbeïnvloeding]]
[[ja:気象制御]]
[[pl:Modyfikacja pogody]]
[[pt:Manipulação do clima]]
[[ru:Активное воздействие на гидрометеорологические процессы]]</text>
      <sha1>lnpv4xo27rcl9yb6buejpxwoyod55vm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
