<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Amish</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19346935</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520711350</id>
      <parentid>520388602</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T06:51:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Richwales</username>
        <id>151693</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Language */ typo fix</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="59981">{{About|Old Order Amish, but also refers to other Amish sects}}
{{pp-protected|expiry=2013-04-19T04:41:58Z|small=yes}}{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2012}}&lt;!-- primarily U.S. article--&gt;
{{Infobox Religious group | group    = Amish
| image    = [[File:Lancaster County Amish 03.jpg|200px| alt=An Amish family in a horse-drawn square buggy passes a farmhouse, barn and granary; more farms and forest in the distance.]]
| poptime  = 249,000 &lt;br&gt;(Old Order Amish)&lt;ref name=&quot;Amish Population Growth: Numbers Increasing, Heading West&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/07/29/amish-population-growth-n_n_663323.html|title= Amish Population Growth: Numbers Increasing, Heading West | last =Scolforo | first = Mark | date= July 28, 2010| work= The Huffington Post| accessdate= July 29, 2010| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20100730110138/http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/07/29/amish-population-growth-n_n_663323.html| archivedate= July 30, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| popplace = United States (notably [[Ohio]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[Indiana]] and New York)&lt;br /&gt;Canada (notably [[Ontario]])
| founder  = [[Jakob Ammann]] | rels     = [[Anabaptist]] | scrips   = [[The Bible]]
| langs    = [[Pennsylvania German language|Pennsylvania German]], [[Swiss German]], English}}
The '''Amish''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|ɑː|m|ɪ|ʃ}} {{respell |Ah|mish}}; [[Pennsylvania German language|Pennsylvania Dutch]]: ''Amisch'', German: ''Amische''), sometimes referred to as [[Amish Mennonite]]s, are a group of traditionalist Christian church fellowships that form a subgroup of the [[Mennonite]] churches. The Amish are known for [[simple living]], [[plain dress]], and reluctance to adopt many [[modern conveniences|conveniences of modern technology]]. The history of the Amish church began with a [[schism (religion)|schism]] in Switzerland within a group of Swiss and [[Alsace|Alsatian]] [[Anabaptist]]s in 1693 led by [[Jakob Ammann]].{{Sfn | Kraybill | 2001 | pp = 7–8}}  Those who followed Ammann became known as Amish.{{Sfn | Kraybill | 2001 | p = 8}}

In the early 18th century, many Amish and Mennonites emigrated to [[Pennsylvania]] for a variety of reasons. Today, the most traditional descendants of the Amish continue to speak [[Pennsylvania German language|Pennsylvania German]], also known as [[Pennsylvania Dutch]]. However, a dialect of [[Swiss German]] predominates in some Old Order Amish communities, especially in the American state of [[Indiana]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gameo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Berne, Indiana, Old Order Amish Settlement |url= http://www.gameo.org/encyclopedia/contents/B4762.html|author=Zook, Noah and Samuel L Yoder|year=1998|accessdate= April 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2000, over 165,000 Old Order Amish live in the United States and approximately 1500 live in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/amish.htm |title=The Amish: history, beliefs, practices, etc |publisher=Religious tolerance |accessdate= November 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 study suggested their numbers have increased to 227,000,&lt;ref name=&quot;Scolforo&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Amish population nearly doubles in 16 years|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2008-08-20-3770622862_x.htm| last = Scolforo | first = Mark | date= August 20, 2008 | accessdate=February 3, 2011|newspaper= USA Today|agency= Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2010 a study suggested their population had grown by 10% in the past two years to 249,000, with increasing movement to the West.&lt;ref name = &quot;Amish Population Growth: Numbers Increasing, Heading West&quot;/&gt;

Amish church membership begins with [[Believer's baptism|baptism]], usually between the ages of 16 and 25. It is a requirement for marriage, and once a person has affiliated with the church, he or she may marry only within the faith.  Church districts average between 20 and 40 families, and worship services are held every other Sunday in a member's home. The district is led by a bishop and several ministers and deacons.{{Sfn | Kraybill | 1994 | p = [http://books.google.com/books?id=OYNYKYsulbQC&amp;pg=PA3#v=snippet&amp;f=false  3]}}  The rules of the church, the ''[[Ordnung]]'', must be observed by every member. These rules cover most aspects of day-to-day living, and include prohibitions or limitations on the use of power-line electricity, telephones, and automobiles, as well as regulations on clothing. Many Amish church members may not buy insurance or accept government assistance such as [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]]. As [[Anabaptist]]s, Amish church members practice [[nonresistance]] and will not perform any type of military service. 

Members who do not conform to these expectations and who cannot be convinced to [[repentance|repent]] are excommunicated. In addition to excommunication, members may be [[Shunning|shunned]],&lt;ref name=PBSAE&gt;{{cite web|url=http://video.pbs.org/video/2200745636/|title=American Experience: The Amish|publisher=PBS|date=February 27, 2012|accessdaste=October 18, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; a practice that limits social contacts to shame the wayward member into returning to the church. Almost 90% of Amish teenagers choose to be baptized and join the church.&lt;ref name=PBSAE/&gt;  During adolescence ''[[rumspringa]]'' (&quot;running around&quot;) in some communities, nonconforming behavior that would result in the shunning of an adult who had made the permanent commitment of baptism, may meet with a degree of forbearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://channel.nationalgeographic.com/series/inside/3660/amish-rumspringa|title=Amisch Teenagers Experience the World|publisher=National Geographic Television}}{{failed verification|date=February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amish church groups seek to maintain a degree of separation from the non-Amish (English) world. There is generally a heavy emphasis on church and family relationships. They typically operate their own [[one-room school]]s and discontinue formal education at grade eight (age 13/14).&lt;ref name=PBSAE/&gt; They value rural life, manual labor and humility.

==History==
[[File:Amish cover.jpg|right|thumb|alt=Cover of &quot;Little Known Facts About The Amish and the Mennonites. A study of the Social customs and Habits of Pennsylvania's Plain People. By Ammon Monroe Aurand, Jr. Aurand Press. 1938. |Cover ''The Amish and the Mennonites'', 1938]]
[[File:amish cemetery.gif|thumb|alt=Cemetery filled many small plain headstones with simple inscriptions, and two large bare trees. |An old Amish cemetery in [[Lancaster County, Pennsylvania]], 1941.]]
The Amish [[Mennonite]] movement descends from the 16th century fellowship known as the [[Swiss Brethren]].{{sfn|Hostetler|1993|p=25}} The Swiss Brethren were [[Anabaptist]]s, and are often viewed as having been a part of the [[Radical Reformation]]. &quot;Anabaptist&quot; means &quot;one who baptizes again&quot; – a reference to those who had been baptized as infants, but later adopted a belief in &quot;believer's baptism&quot;, and then let themselves again be baptized as adults. These Swiss Brethren trace their origins to [[Felix Manz]] (ca. 1498–1527) and [[Conrad Grebel]] (ca. 1498–1526), who had broken from reformer [[Huldrych Zwingli]].{{sfn|Hostetler|1993|p=27}}

The Amish movement takes its name from [[Jakob Ammann]] (c. 1656–1730), a Swiss Mennonite leader. Ammann believed Mennonites, the peaceful Anabaptists of the [[Low Countries]] and Germany, were drifting away from the teachings of [[Menno Simons]] and the 1632 Mennonite [[Dordrecht Confession of Faith]]. Ammann favored stronger church discipline, including a more rigid application of [[shunning]], the social exclusion of excommunicated members. Swiss Anabaptists, who were scattered by persecution throughout the [[Alsace]] and the [[Electorate of the Palatinate]], never practiced strict shunning as had some lowland Anabaptists.{{Citation needed | date = February 2009}}  Ammann insisted upon this practice, even to the point of expecting spouses to refuse to eat with each other, until the banned spouse repented.{{Sfn | Smith | Krahn | 1981 | pp = 68–69, 84–85}}  This type of strict literalism, on this issue, as well as others, brought about a division among the Mennonites of Southern Germany, the Alsace and Switzerland in 1693, and led to withdrawal of those who sided with Ammann.

Swiss Anabaptism developed, from this point, in two parallel streams. Those following Ammann became known as ''Amish'' or ''Amish Mennonite''. The others eventually formed the basis of the [[Swiss Mennonite Conference]]. Because of this common heritage, Amish and Mennonites retain many similarities. Those who leave the Amish fold tend to join various congregations of [[Conservative Mennonites]].{{Sfn | Smith | Krahn | 1981 | pp = 212–4}}{{Sfn | Kraybill| 2000| pp = 63–4}}

Amish Mennonites began migrating to [[Pennsylvania]] in the 18th century as part of a larger migration from the [[Palatinate (region)|Palatinate]] and neighboring areas. This migration was a reaction to religious wars, poverty, and [[religious persecution]] on the Continent.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}} The first Amish immigrants went to [[Berks County, Pennsylvania]], but later moved, motivated by land issues and by security concerns tied to the [[French and Indian War]].{{Citation needed| date=September 2009}} Many eventually settled in [[Lancaster County, Pennsylvania]]. Other groups later settled in, or spread to [[Alabama]], [[Delaware]], [[Illinois]], [[Indiana]], [[Iowa]], [[Kansas]], [[Kentucky]], [[Michigan]], [[Minnesota]], [[Mississippi]], [[Missouri]], [[Montana]], [[Nebraska]], New York, [[Ohio]], [[Maryland]], [[Tennessee]], [[Wisconsin]], [[Maine]], and [[Ontario, Canada]].

The Amish congregations remaining in Europe slowly merged with the [[Mennonites]]. The last Amish congregation to merge was the Ixheim Amish congregation, which merged with the neighboring Mennonite Church in 1937. Some Mennonite congregations, including most in Alsace, are descended directly from former Amish congregations.{{Sfn | Nolt | 1992}}{{Rp | needed = yes |date=February 2012}}

Most Amish communities that were established in North America did not ultimately retain their Amish identity. The original major split that resulted in the loss of identity occurred in the 1860s. During that decade ''Dienerversammlungen'' (ministerial conferences) were held in [[Wayne County, Ohio]], concerning how the Amish should deal with the pressures of modern society. The meetings themselves were a progressive idea; for bishops to assemble to discuss uniformity was an unprecedented notion in the Amish church.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}} By the first several meetings, the more traditionally minded bishops agreed to [[boycott]] the conferences. The more progressive members, comprising approximately two thirds of the group, retained the name [[Amish Mennonite]]. Many of these eventually united with the [[Mennonite Church]], and other Mennonite denominations, especially in the early 20th century. The more traditionally minded groups became known as the Old Order Amish.{{Sfn | Kraybill | 2000 | p = 67}}

== Religious practices ==
{{Main|Amish religious practices}}
[[File:De Ausbund 329.jpg|right|thumb|alt=A page of ornate old German text. See description.|A scan of the historical document ''Diß Lied haben die sieben Brüder im Gefängnüß zu Gmünd gemacht '']]
[[File:DSCN4624 holmescountyamishbuggy e.jpg|right|thumb|alt=See description.|Amish couple in horse-driven buggy in rural [[Holmes County, Ohio]], September 2004)]]

Two key concepts for understanding Amish practices are their rejection of ''Hochmut'' (pride, arrogance, haughtiness) and the high value they place on ''Demut'' (humility) and ''[[Ordnung#Gelassenheit|Gelassenheit]]'' (calmness, composure, placidity), often translated as &quot;submission&quot; or &quot;letting-be&quot;. Gelassenheit is perhaps better understood as a reluctance to be forward, to be self-promoting, or to assert oneself. The Amish's willingness to submit to the &quot;Will of Jesus&quot;, expressed through group norms, is at odds with the individualism so central to the wider American culture. The Amish anti-individualist orientation is the motive for rejecting labor-saving technologies that might make one less dependent on community. Modern innovations like electricity might spark a competition for status goods, or photographs might cultivate personal vanity.

== Way of life ==
{{Main|Amish way of life}}

Amish lifestyle is dictated by the Ordnung&lt;ref name=PBSAE/&gt; (German, meaning: order), which differs slightly from community to community, and, within a community, from district to district. What is acceptable in one community may not be acceptable in another. No summary of Amish lifestyle and culture can be totally adequate, because there are few generalities that are true for all Amish. Groups may separate over matters such as the width of a hat-brim, the color of buggies, or other issues.{{Citation needed|date=October 2012}}

Bearing children, raising them, and socializing with neighbors and relatives are the greatest functions of the Amish family. All Amish believe large families are a blessing from God.

===Language===
{{Main|Pennsylvania German language}}
The Amish speak in Pennsylvania Dutch and refer to non-Amish as &quot;English&quot;.&lt;ref name=PBSAE/&gt; According to one scholar, &quot;today, almost all Amish are functionally bilingual in Pennsylvania Dutch and English; however, domains of usage are sharply separated. Pennsylvania Dutch dominates in most in-group settings, such as the dinner table and preaching in church services. In contrast, English is used for most reading and writing. English is also the medium of instruction in schools and is used in business transactions and often, out of politeness, in situations involving interactions with non-Amish. Finally, the Amish read prayers and sing in [[Standard German]], or [[Upper German|High German]] (Hoch Deitsch)&lt;!-- this is not a misake. The quote write is in low German and so it is written as such here--&gt; at church services. The distinctive use of three different languages serves as a powerful conveyor of Amish identity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hurst |first1=Charles E. |last2=McConnell |first2=David L. |title=An Amish Paradox: Diversity and Change in the World's Largest Amish Community |year=2010 |publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press |isbn=0-8018-9398-4 |pages=15–16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although &quot;the English language is being used in more and more situations,&quot; Pennsylvania Dutch is &quot;one of a handful of minority languages in the United States that is neither endangered nor supported by continual arrivals of immigrants.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hurst |first1=Charles E. |last2=McConnell |first2=David L. |title=An Amish Paradox: Diversity and Change in the World's Largest Amish Community |year=2010 |publisher=The Johns Hopkins University Press |isbn=0-8018-9398-4 |page=15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Population and distribution==
[[File:AmishFamilyNiagaraFalls.jpg|thumb|left|alt= |Amish family shopping near [[Niagara Falls, Ontario]]]]
:''See also [[List of U.S. states by Amish population]]''
{{Historical populations
|footnote= '''US Populations'''&lt;br /&gt;
sources: 221,000 in 2008;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scolforo&quot;/&gt; 249,000 in 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amish Population Growth: Numbers Increasing, Heading West&quot;/&gt;
|1920|5000
|1928|7000
|1936|9000
|1944|13000
|1952|19000
|1960|28000
|1968|39000
|1976|57000
|1984|84000
|1992|125000
|2000|166000
|2008|221000
|2010|249000
}}

Because members usually get baptized no earlier than 18 and children are not counted in local congregation numbers, it is difficult to put an exact figure on the number of Amish.  Rough estimates from various studies have placed their numbers at 125,000 in 1992; 166,000 in 2000; and 221,000 in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/PDF/Statistics/Population_Change_Summary_1992_2008.pdf | title = Amish Population Change Summary 1992–2008 | format = PDF | publisher = Young Center for Anabaptist and Pietist Studies, Elizabethtown College | accessdate = July 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Thus, from 1992 to 2008, population growth among the Amish in North America was 84% (3.6% per year).  During that time they established 184 new settlements and moved into six new states.&lt;ref name= &quot;Trends&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/Population_Trends_1992_2008.asp|title= Population Trends 1992–2008 | publisher= Young Center for Anabaptist and Pietist Studies, Elizabethtown College| accessdate= July 8, 2009 | archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090606152522/http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/Population_Trends_1992_2008.asp | archivedate= June 6, 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2000, approximately 165,620 Old Order Amish resided in the United States, of whom 73,609 were church members.{{Sfn | Kraybill | 2000}}{{Rp | needed = yes|date=October 2012}}  The Amish are among the fastest-growing populations in the world, with an average of seven children per family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1 = Julia A |last1 = Ericksen | last2 = Ericksen | first2 = Eugene P | last3 = Hostetler | first3 = John A | last4 = Huntington | first4 = Gertrude E |title=Fertility Patterns and Trends among the Old Order Amish |journal= Population Studies |issue=33 |month=July | year=1979 |issn=00324728 |oclc=39648293 |pages=255–76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are Old Order communities in 27 U.S. states and the Canadian province of [[Ontario]]; [[Ohio]] has the largest population (55,000), followed by [[Pennsylvania]] (51,000) and [[Indiana]] (38,000).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/Population_by_State_2008.asp |title=Amish Population by State (2008) |publisher=Young Center for Anabaptist and Pietist Studies, Elizabethtown College|accessdate=July 8, 2009| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20090629043711/http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/Population_by_State_2008.asp| archivedate= June 29, 2009 | deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest Amish settlements are in [[Holmes County, Ohio|Holmes County]] in central Ohio, [[Lancaster County, Pennsylvania|Lancaster County]] in south-central Pennsylvania, and [[Elkhart County, Indiana|Elkhart]] and [[LaGrange County, Indiana|LaGrange]] counties in northeast Indiana.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/Largest_Settlements_2008.asp |title=The Twelve Largest Amish Settlements | year = 2008 |publisher= Young Center for Anabaptist and Pietist Studies, Elizabethtown College|accessdate= July 8, 2009| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20090606152447/http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/Largest_Settlements_2008.asp | archivedate= June 6, 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl = no}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest concentration of Amish west of the [[Mississippi River]] is in [[Missouri]], with other settlements in eastern [[Iowa]] and [[Southeast Minnesota]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/Population_by_State_2009.asp| title = Amish Population by State | year = 2009 | publisher =Young Center for Anabaptist and Pietist Studies, Elizabethtown College|accessdate=February 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there is a population of approximately 10,000 Old Order Amish in West Central Wisconsin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url =http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/18/national/18manure.html |title=Amish May Be Good Neighbors, but Not Their Horses | work=The New York Times | first=Alexei |last=Barrionuevo|date=October 18, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of rapid population growth in Amish communities, new settlements are formed to obtain sufficient farmland. Other reasons for new settlements include locating in isolated areas that support their lifestyle, moving to areas with cultures conducive to their way of life, maintaining proximity to family or other Amish groups, and sometimes to resolve church or leadership conflicts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trends&quot;/&gt;

A small [[Beachy Amish]] congregation associated with [[Weavertown Amish Mennonite Church]] exists in the Republic of Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Michael |last=Clifford |url= https://www.tribune.ie/archive/article/2000/aug/06/at-ease-with-the-alternative-amish-way/ |title=At ease with the alternative Amish way |work=Sunday Tribune |location=Ireland |date=August 6, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ethnicity==
The Amish largely share a German or [[Swiss (people)|Swiss]]-[[Ethnic German|German]] ancestry. They generally use the term &quot;Amish&quot; only for members of their faith community, and not as an ethnic designation. Those who choose to affiliate with the church, or young children raised in Amish homes, but too young to yet be church members, are considered to be Amish. Certain [[Mennonite]] churches have a high number of people who were formerly from Amish congregations. Although more Amish immigrated to America in the 19th century than during the 18th century, most of today's Amish descend from 18th-century immigrants. The latter tended to emphasize tradition to a greater extent, and were perhaps more likely to maintain a separate Amish identity.{{Sfn | Nolt | 1992 | p = 104}}  There are a number of Amish Mennonite church groups that had never in their history been associated with the Old Order Amish.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} The former Western Ontario Mennonite Conference (WOMC) was made up almost entirely of former Amish Mennonites who reunited with the Mennonite Church in Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gameo.org/encyclopedia/contents/W4781ME.html | last = Gingerich | first = Orland|title=Western Ontario Mennonite Conference|publisher=Global Anabaptist Mennonite Encyclopedia Online|year=1990|accessdate=July 5, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Orland Gingerich's book ''The Amish of Canada'' devotes the vast majority of its pages not to the Beachy or Old Order Amish, but to congregations in the former WOMC.

==Health==
Amish populations have higher incidences of particular [[genetic disorder]]s, including [[dwarfism]] ([[Ellis–van Creveld syndrome]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url = http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v24/n3/full/ng0300_203.html | title = Ellis-van Creveld syndrome and the Amish |journal=[[Nature Genetics]] |year=2000 |accessdate=July 2, 2008 |volume= 24 |issue= 3 |doi= 10.1038/73389 |archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080517090345/http://www.nature.com/ng/journal/v24/n3/full/ng0300_203.html |archivedate= May 17, 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; and various [[metabolic disorders]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1002/ajmg.c.20002 |url= http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/104542765/abstract | last1 =Morton |first1=D. Holmes |last2=Morton |first2=Caroline S. |last3=Strauss |first3=Kevin A. |last4=Robinson |first4=Donna L. |last5=Puffenberger |pmid= 12888982 |first5= Erik G |last6= Hendrickson |first6= Christine | last7 = Kelley | first7 = Richard I. |title= Pediatric medicine and the genetic disorders of the Amish and Mennonite people of Pennsylvania | journal= [[American Journal of Medical Genetics]] | page= 5 | issue= 1 | volume= 121C | date = June 27, 2003 | quote = Regional hospitals and midwives routinely send whole-blood filter paper neonatal screens for tandem mass spectrometry and other modern analytical methods to detect 14 of the metabolic disorders found in these populations… | accessdate = July 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as an unusual distribution of blood types.{{Sfn | Hostetler | 1993 | p = 330}}  Amish represent a collection of different [[deme (biology)|demes]] or genetically closed communities.{{Sfn | Hostetler | 1993 | p = 328}}  Since almost all Amish descend from about 200 18th-century founders, genetic disorders that come out due to inbreeding exist in more isolated districts (an example of the [[founder effect]]). Some of these disorders are quite rare, or unique, and are serious enough to increase the mortality rate among Amish children. The majority of Amish accept these as &quot;Gottes Wille&quot; (God's will); they reject use of preventive genetic tests prior to marriage and genetic testing of unborn children to discover genetic disorders.  However, Amish are willing to participate in studies of genetic diseases.  Their extensive family histories are useful to researchers investigating diseases such as [[Alzheimer's]], [[Parkinson's]], and [[macular degeneration]].

[[File:Amish farm morristown new york.jpg|thumb|alt=An Amish woman and three children, on a path to a house and six wooden farm buildings, past some farm equipment.|An Amish farm near Morristown in New York State.]]
While the Amish are at an increased risk for a number of genetic disorders, researchers at The Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center—Arthur G. James Cancer Hospital and Richard J. Solove Research Institute (OSUCCC-James) have found their tendencies for clean living can lead to a healthier life. Overall cancer rates in the Amish population are 60 percent of the age-adjusted rate for Ohio and 56 percent of the national rate. The incidence of tobacco-related cancers in the Amish adults is 37 percent of the rate for Ohio adults, and the incidence of non-tobacco-related cancer is 72 percent. The Amish have protection against many types of cancer both through their lifestyle—there is very little tobacco or alcohol use and limited sexual partners—and through genes that may reduce their susceptibility to cancer. Dr. Judith Westman, director of human genetics at OSUCCC-James, conducted the study.  The findings were reported in a recent issue of the journal ''Cancer Causes &amp; Control''. Even skin cancer rates are lower for Amish, despite the fact many Amish make their living working outdoors where they are exposed to sunlight and UV rays. They are typically covered and dressed to work in the sun by wearing wide-brimmed hats and long sleeves to protect their skin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |oldurl=http://medicalcenter.osu.edu/viewer/Pages/index.aspx?NewsId=5307 |url= http://www.internalmedicine.osu.edu/genetics/article.cfm?id=5307 |title=Amish Have Lower Rates of Cancer, Ohio State Study Shows |date=January 1, 2010 |publisher=Ohio State University Medical Center |accessdate=January 6, 2010 |location=Columbus, OH}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Amish are conscious of the advantages of [[exogamy]]. A common bloodline in one community will often be absent in another, and genetic disorders can be avoided by choosing spouses from unrelated communities. For example, the founding families of the Lancaster County Amish are unrelated to the founders of the [[Perth County, Ontario]] Amish community. Because of a [[inbreeding|smaller gene pool]], some groups have increased incidences of certain inheritable conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.genomenewsnetwork.org/articles/2004/07/23/sids.php |title=Genomics in Amish Country | last =Ruder | first = Katherine ‘Kate’ |date=July 23, 2004 |publisher=Genome News Network}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Old Order Amish do not typically carry private commercial health insurance. About two-thirds of the Amish in Lancaster County participate in Church Aid, an informal self-insurance plan for helping members with catastrophic medical expenses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/10/05/AR2006100501360.html |title=Amish Reluctantly Accept Donations |last=Rubinkam |first=Michael |work=The Washington Post |date=October 5, 2006 |accessdate=March 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; A handful of American hospitals, starting in the mid-1990s, created special outreach programs to assist the Amish. The first of these programs was instituted at the Susquehanna Health System in central Pennsylvania by James Huebert. This program has earned national media attention in the United States, and has spread to several surrounding hospitals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.dailyitem.com/archive/2004/0618/local/stories/04local.htm |work=The Daily Item |title=Doctors make house calls in barn |date=June 18, 2004|first=Bevin |last=Milavsky |archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20040619061900/http://www.dailyitem.com/archive/2004/0618/local/stories/04local.htm | archivedate= June 19, 2004 |accessdate= March 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.imt.ie/lifestyle/2007/08/a_culture_vastly_different_fro.html | title = A culture vastly different from the rest of America | newspaper = The Irish Medical Times | date = August 3, 2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Treating genetic problems is the mission of [[Clinic for Special Children]] in [[Strasburg, Pennsylvania]], which has developed effective treatments for such problems as [[maple syrup urine disease]], a previously fatal disease. The clinic is embraced by most Amish, ending the need for parents to leave the community to receive proper care for their children, an action that might result in shunning.

DDC Clinic for Special Needs Children, located in [[Middlefield, Ohio]], has been treating special-needs children with inherited or metabolic disorders since May 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ddcclinic.org/ |title=DDC Clinic for Special Needs Children |date=October 7, 2011 |accessdate=November 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The DDC Clinic provides treatment, research, and educational services to Amish and non-Amish children and their families.

Although not forbidden or thought of as immoral, most Amish do not practice any form of [[birth control]], hence their large families. They are against abortion and also find &quot;artificial insemination, genetics, eugenics, and stem cell research&quot; to be &quot;inconsistent with Amish values and beliefs&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Transcultural concepts in nursing care | first=Margaret M. |last=Andrews |first2=Joyceen S. |last2=Boyle |url= http://books.google.com/?id=Tq-rL8VcQBQC&amp;pg=PA455&amp;lpg=PA455&amp;dq=abortion+amish | publisher=Lippincott | year=2002 | accessdate=January 19, 2008 | page=455 |isbn=978-0-7817-3680-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''People's Helpers'' is an Amish-organized network of mental health caregivers who help families dealing with mental illness and recommend professional counselors.{{Sfn | Kraybill | 2001 | p = 105}}  Suicide rates for the Amish of Lancaster County were 5.5 per 100,000 in 1980, about half that of the general population and a third the rate of the non-religious population.{{Refn|group=lower-alpha|The overall suicide rate in 1980 in the USA was 12.5 per 100,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Kraybill|others=et al|title=Suicide Patterns in a Religious Subculture: The Old Order Amish|journal=International Journal of Moral and Social Studies|volume=1|month=Autumn|year=1986}}.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Amish life in the modern world==
{{Main|Amish life in the modern world}}
[[File:Traditional Amish buggy.jpg|thumb|alt=Horsedrawn grey buggy in multilane auto traffic, with rearview mirrors, directional signals, lights, and reflectors|Traditional Amish buggy]]

As time has passed, the Amish have felt pressures from the modern world. Issues such as taxation, education, law and its enforcement, and occasional discrimination and hostility, are areas of difficulty.

The Amish way of life in general has increasingly diverged from that of modern society. On occasion, this has resulted in sporadic discrimination and hostility from their neighbors, such as throwing of stones or other objects at Amish horse-drawn carriages on the roads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Iseman|first=David|title=Trumbull probes attack on woman, Amish buggy|newspaper=[[The Vindicator]]|date=May 18, 1988|page=1|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=1uBRAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=GoUMAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5866,396113&amp;hl=en|accessdate=July 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Stone Amish|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=-15ZAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=gUgNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6383,209217&amp;dq=amish+stoning+-fulham+-muslim&amp;hl=en|accessdate=July 12, 2011|newspaper=[[Painesville Telegraph]]|date=September 12, 1949|page=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=State Police Arrest 25 Boys in Rural Areas|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=q8Q_AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=z1cMAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=amish%20stoning%20-fulham%20-muslim&amp;pg=2772%2C3130040|accessdate=July 12, 2011|newspaper=[[The Vindicator]]|date=October 25, 1958}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Amish do not usually educate their children past the [[eighth grade]], believing that the basic knowledge offered up to that point is sufficient to prepare one for the Amish lifestyle. Almost no Amish go to high school and college. In many communities, the Amish operate their own schools, which are typically [[one-room schoolhouse]]s with teachers (young unmarried women) from the Amish community. On May 19, 1972, Jonas Yoder and Wallace Miller of the Old Order Amish, and Adin Yutzy of the Conservative Amish Mennonite Church, were each fined $5 for refusing to send their children, aged 14 and 15, to high school. In ''[[Wisconsin v. Yoder]]'', the Wisconsin Supreme Court overturned the conviction,&lt;ref&gt;''Wisconsin v. Yoder'', 182 N.W.2d 539 (Wis. 1971).&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[U.S. Supreme Court]] affirmed this, finding the benefits of universal education do not justify a violation of the [[Free Exercise Clause]] of the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]].&lt;ref&gt;''Wisconsin v. Yoder'', 406 U.S. 205, 32 L.Ed.2d 15, 92 S.Ct. 1526 (1972).&lt;/ref&gt;

Like other citizens, Amish pay sales and property taxes.  However, Amish buggies, bicyclists, and pedestrians use public highways, but need not pay either motor vehicle registration fees or motor fuel taxes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Rumble strips removed after the Amish say they're dangerous |url=http://www.wwmt.com/articles/rumble-1366086-joseph-0in.html |accessdate=2011-11-24 |quote=Dobberteen is one of a growing number of people in St. Joseph County who believes that the Amish shouldn't have a say in what happens with a state road. 'Some people are saying, &quot;Well jeeze, you know the Amish people don't pay taxes for that, why are we filling them in&quot; what do you think about that? We pay our taxes,' said Dobberteen. Roads are paid for largely with gas tax and vehicle registration fees, which the Amish have no reason to pay. |newspaper=[[WWMT]] television news|date=August 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under their beliefs and traditions, the Amish do not agree with the idea of social security benefits and have a religious objection to insurance.  On this basis, the United States [[Internal Revenue Service]] agreed in 1961 that they did not need to pay [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]] related taxes.  In 1965, this policy was codified into law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode26/usc_sec_26_00001402----000-.html |title=U.S. Code collection |publisher=Law.cornell.edu |date= |accessdate=September 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Self-employed individuals in certain sects do not pay into, nor receive benefits from, United States Social Security.  This exemption applies to members of a religious group that is conscientiously opposed to accepting benefits of any private or public insurance, provides a reasonable level of living for its dependent members and has existed continuously since December 31, 1950.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/f4029.pdf |format=PDF |title= Application for Exemption From Social Security and Medicare Taxes and Waiver of Benefits |publisher=[[Internal Revenue Service]] |year=2006 |accessdate=July 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The U.S. Supreme Court in 1982 clarified that Amish employers are not exempt, but only those Amish individuals who are self-employed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=U.S. v. Lee, 102 S. Ct. 1051 (1982) |url=http://www.ssa.gov/OP_Home/rulings/oasi/45/SSR82-44-oasi-45.html |accessdate=2011-11-24 |quote=On appeal, the Supreme Court noted that the exemption provided by 26 U.S.C. 1402(g) is available only to self-employed individuals and does not apply to employers or employees. As to the constitutional claim, the court held that, since accommodating the Amish beliefs under the circumstances would unduly interfere with the fulfillment of the overriding governmental interest in assuring mandatory and continuous participation in and contribution to the Social Security system, the limitation on religious liberty involved here was justified. Consequently, in reversing the district court, the Supreme Court held that, unless Congress provides otherwise, the tax imposed on employers to support the Social Security system must be uniformly applicable to all. |date=August 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Publishing===
The Old Order Amish support an unofficial publishing house known as [[Pathway Publishing Company]] in Lagrange, Indiana, and Aylmer, Ontario.  Pathway publishes a number of school text books, general reading books, and periodicals.

==Subgroups of Amish==
{{main|Subgroups of Amish}}
Over the years, the Amish churches have divided many times over doctrinal disputes.  The &quot;Old Order&quot; Amish, a conservative faction that withdrew from fellowship with the wider body of Amish in the 1860s, are those that have most emphasized traditional practices and beliefs. There are as many as eight different subgroups of Amish with most belonging, in ascending order of conservatism, to the Beachy Amish, New Order, Old Order, or Swartzentruber Amish sects.

===Conflicts===
Conflicts between subgroups of Amish have resulted in instances of &quot;beard cutting&quot; attacks on members of the Amish community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-16522281 |title=Amish men plead 'not guilty' to hair-cutting attacks |publisher=BBC News |date=January 11, 2012 |accessdate=February 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-15700838 |title=Amish son cuts off father's beard and hair |publisher=BBC News |date=November 11, 2011 |accessdate=February 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Due to the cloistered nature of Amish lifestyle, they are often reluctant to bring complaints to local police&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-15231033 |title=Four arrested over hair and beard attacks on Ohio Amish |publisher=BBC News |date=October 9, 2011 |accessdate=February 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; who describe the attacks as &quot;very rare&quot;. In September, 2012, a group of 16 Amish men and women from Bergholz, Ohio, were convicted on Federal hate-crime and conspiracy charges, including Samuel Mullet Sr., who did not participate in the five hair- and beard-cutting attacks but was tried as the leader of the campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Jury Convicts Amish Group of Hate Crimes |author=Erik Eckholm |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/21/us/jury-convicts-amish-group-of-hate-crimes.html |newspaper=NY Times |date=September 20, 2012 |accessdate=September 20, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Similar groups==
[[Old Order Mennonite]]s, [[Conservative Mennonites]], [[Hutterite]]s, and [[Old German Baptist Brethren]] are distinct from the Amish. They all emigrated from Europe, but they arrived with different dialects, separate cultures, and diverse religious traditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etown.edu/YoungCenter.aspx?topic=About+Anabaptists+and+Pietists |title=Elizabethtown College — Young Center |publisher=Etown |accessdate=November 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Particularly, the Hutterites live communally&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/277694/Hutterites|title=Hutterites|work=Britannica Online|publisher=Encyclopaedia Britannica|accessdate=November 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are generally accepting of modern technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/hutterites.html|title= Hutterites|last= Laverdure|first= Paul|year= 2006|work= Encyclopedia of Saskatchewan|publisher= Canadian Plains Research Center | accessdate = November 9, 2008| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20081013223110/http://esask.uregina.ca/entry/hutterites.html| archivedate= October 13, 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Testimony of Simplicity|Plain Quakers]] are similar in manner and lifestyle, but unrelated to the Amish.{{sfn |Hamm|2003|p=101}} Early Quakers were influenced, to some degree, by the [[Anabaptists]]. Most modern Quakers have since abandoned their traditional dress.{{sfn|Hamm|2003|pp=103–5}}

==Portrayal in popular entertainment==
&lt;!-- please do not add individual episodes of series or minor mentions or references; this section has a tendency to get out of hand --&gt;

===Film===

====Topical====
[[Peter Weir]]'s 1985 drama ''[[Witness (1985 film)|Witness]]'' is set and filmed in the Amish community of Lancaster County, Pennsylvania. ''[[Harvest of Fire]]'' is a 1996 [[Hallmark Hall of Fame]] made-for-TV movie about an FBI agent's investigation of cases of suspected arson in an Amish farming community. The 2002 documentary ''[[Devil's Playground (2002 film)|Devil's Playground]]'' follows a group of Amish teenagers during [[rumspringa]], and it portrays their personal dilemma with both the &quot;English&quot; world and the decision on whether or not to be baptized as adult members of the church.

In ''[[Kingpin (film)|Kingpin]]'', a former bowling champion coaches a young Amish man in winning a bowling tournament to win enough money to save his family's farm.

[[Michael Landon, Jr.]]'s 2007 film ''[[Saving Sarah Cain]]'', based on the novel ''The Redemption of Sarah Cain'' by [[Beverly Lewis]], shows the removal of young Amish children to the big city and realizing the life they can have with both the Amish and English world. Producer [[Larry A. Thompson|Larry Thompson's]] 2010 Lifetime Original Movie.

''The Heritage of Lancaster County'', another series by [[Beverly Lewis]], is the inspiration for a trio of movies on the Hallmark Channel beginning with ''The Shunning''.  It follows Katie Lapp, a young Amish woman with ties to the English world and her struggle to find where she belongs.

''[[Amish Grace]]'' portrayed the events surrounding an [[Amish school shooting]] in Nickel Mines, Pennsylvania.

====Episodical====
In the comedy ''[[Sex Drive (film)|Sex Drive]]'', the three main characters hitchhike with an Amish man, played by [[Seth Green]], who takes them to his home. There they find a party during rumspringa, where the character Lance meets his future love interest in the film. In the [[George Romero]] film ''Diary of the Dead'', a deaf Amish man appears and helps the main survivors before killing himself after being infected.

''[[For Richer or Poorer]]'' is a 1997 comedy film starring [[Tim Allen]] and [[Kirstie Alley]], who find themselves hiding in a small Amish community in Pennsylvania.

===Literature===

====Modern novels====
*[[Beverly Lewis]], the &quot;Queen of Amish Fiction&quot;, has an extensive series of Amish romantic fiction.
*[[W. Dale Cramer]] won a [[Christy Award]] for ''Levi's Will'', a novel based on his father's life after leaving the Amish as a teenager.  He wrote a series, ''The Daughters of Caleb Bender'', based once again on the history of his family, this time with his great-grandfather.  It follows a small group of Amish fleeing persecution in America in the 1920s and settling in Mexico.
*[[Leslie Gould]] is writing a series of books based on [[William Shakespeare]]'s plays set in the Amish world.  The first book, ''Courting Cate'', is based on [[The Taming of the Shrew]].
*''Almost Amish'' is a novel by [[Kathryn Cushman]] about two modern families trying to live Amish for a reality TV show.
*[[Paul Levinson]]'s 1999 [[Locus Award]]–winning novel ''[[Phil D'Amato#The Novels|The Silk Code]]'' portrays Amish farmers involved in a science-fiction mystery about biotechnology and mysterious deaths
*[[Jodi Picoult]]'s 2000 novel (and 2004 TV movie) ''[[Plain Truth]]'' deal with a crime concerning the death of a newborn infant on an Amish farm.
*[[Lurlene McDaniel]]'s 2002 ''The Angels Trilogy''.
*Paul Gaus's Ohio Amish Mystery series, set among the Amish community in Holmes County, Ohio.
*[[Richard Montanari]]'s Philadelphia crime series features a homicide detective named Joshua Bontrager who grew up Amish.

====Older novels====
[[Helen Reimensnyder Martin]]'s 1905 novel ''Sabina, a Story of the Amish'', similar to her 1904 novel ''Tillie, a Mennonite Maid'', so harshly depicted its subjects as to provoke cries of misrepresentation. [[Anna Balmer Myers]]' 1920 novel ''Patchwork: a Story of &quot;the Plain People&quot;'', like her 1921 novel ''Amanda: A Daughter of the Mennonites'', are generally regarded as gentle correctives to the work of Martin. Ruth Lininger Dobson's 1937 novel ''Straw in the Wind'', written while a student at the [[University of Michigan]] and receiving the school's [[Hopwood Award]], so negatively depicted the Amish of Indiana that [[Joseph Yoder]] was motivated to correct the severe stereotypes with a more accurate book about the Amish way of life. In 1940, he wrote the gentler ''Rosanna of the Amish'', a story of his mother's life (and his own). He later wrote a sequel, ''Rosanna's Boys'' (1948), as well as other books presenting and recording what he regarded as a truer picture of Amish culture.

====Children's literature====
*[[Marguerite de Angeli]]'s 1936 children's story ''[[Henner's Lydia]]'' portrays a tender Amish family. The author sketched many of the illustrations at the site of the [[Little Red Schoolhouse (Pennsylvania)|Little Red Schoolhouse]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://www.wikimapia.org/#y=40146077&amp;x=-75948315&amp;z=14&amp;l=0&amp;m=h&amp;v=2 | contribution = Little red schoolhouse | title = Wikimapia}}.&lt;/ref&gt; still standing at the intersection of [[Pennsylvania Route 23]] and Red Schoolhouse Road, just west of Morgantown, Pennsylvania. Today the building is the Amish Mennonite Information Center. The Lancaster County landscape, portrayed in the end papers of the book, can be recognized throughout the area. De Angeli's illustrations of a nearby bank barn were sketched just hours before the barn was destroyed by fire. She incorporated the incident in her 1944 [[Caldecott Medal|Caldecott Honor]] book ''Yonie Wondernose'', a story about a curious Amish boy, younger brother to the Lydia of ''Henner's Lydia''.
*Another popular children's book, ''[[Plain Girl]]'' by [[Virginia Sorensen]], was published in 1956, and is still in print.
*[[Beverly Lewis]], known for her numerous award-winning Amish novels, has also written several picture books and chapter books for children.

===Theatre===
* The 1955 Broadway musical show, ''[[Plain and Fancy]],'' is an early stage-play portrayal of the Amish people.  Set in Lancaster County, it tells of a couple from New York who encounter the quaint Amish lifestyle when they arrive to sell off some property. This show depicted &quot;shunning&quot; and &quot;barn-raising&quot; to the American audience for the first time.
*''[[Quiet in the Land]],'' a Canadian play concerning Amish struggles during World War I (1917–[[1918|18]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url        = http://www.dramatists.com/cgi-bin/db/single.asp?index=0&amp;key=1172
 | title      = Quiet in the Land | first     = Anne | last = Chislett
 | publisher  = Dramatists Play Service | accessdate = 2012-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''The Confession'' is a musical based on [[Beverly Lewis]]'s best-selling ''The Heritage of Lancaster County'' series.

===Television===

In 1988 [[NBC]] aired a family drama, ''[[Aaron's Way]]'', about an Amish family who moved to California and had to adjust to a non-Amish lifestyle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.tvguide.com/News/Merlin-Olsen-Dies-1016163.aspx |title = Football Hall of Famer and Actor Merlin Olsen Dies at 69|work=TV Guide|date=Mar 11, 2010| first =Joyce | last = Eng|accessdate=Sep 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp; Numerous other TV shows have presented episodes with Amish characters or storylines, including ''[[Family Guy]]'', ''[[The Simpsons]]'', and ''[[Grey's Anatomy]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Igou, Brad. [http://www.amishnews.com/amisharticles/amishinmedia.htm &quot;The Amish in the Media&quot;]. ''Amish County News''. 2001/2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In the summer of 2004, a controversial reality-television program called ''[[Amish in the City]]'' aired on [[UPN]]. Amish teenagers were exposed to non-Amish culture by living together with &quot;English&quot; teens and, at the time of the show, had yet to decide if they wanted to be baptized into the Amish church.

In 2009, [[BBC2]] in the UK  aired ''Trouble in Amish Paradise'', a one-hour documentary about Ephraim and Amanda Stoltzfus and their desire to adhere to Evangelical Christianity whilst remaining Amish in culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00ht3z6 |title=Trouble in Amish Paradise |publisher=BBC TV |date=February 2009 |accessdate=February 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by a second programme, ''Leaving Amish Paradise'', in 2011, documenting the transition of the couple and two of their friends to non Amish society after their excommunication from the Amish church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/tvandradio/8386430/Leaving-Amish-Paradise-BBC-Two-review.html |title=Leaving Amish Paradise|last=Deacon|first=Michael|date=Mar 16, 2011|work=The Telegraph|publisher=Telegraph Media Group |accessdate=August 4, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the UK's [[Channel 4]] aired a series of documentaries entitled ''Amish: World's Squarest Teenagers'' where a group of Amish teenagers were taken to the UK in a cultural exchange to live with British teenagers during rumspringa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.channel4.com/programmes/amish-worlds-squarest-teenagers/ |title=Amish: World's Squarest Teenagers|last=Anon|year=2010|work=Channel 4 TV listings|publisher= Channel 4|accessdate= August 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/tv-and-radio/2010/jul/24/charlie-brooker-screen-burn |title=Charlie Brooker's Screen burn: Amish: The World's Squarest Teenagers|last=Brooker|first=Charlie|date= July 24, 2010|work= The Guardian|publisher= Guardian News and Media |accessdate= August 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; A follow-up series, ''Living with the Amish'', aired in 2012, where British teenagers were taken to live for a few weeks in various Amish communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.channel4.com/programmes/living-with-the-amish/episode-guide/series-1/episode-1 | title= Living with the Amish| work= TV listings| publisher= Channel 4 |accessdate= August 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/tv-and-radio/2011/nov/27/living-with-the-amish-review |title=Rewind TV: Living With the Amish; When Bankers Were Good; The Cafe; The Young Apprentice | format = review|last=Ferguson|first=Euan|date=November 27, 2011|work=Observer TV reviews|publisher= Guardian News and Media | accessdate =August 3, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2012, the [[National Geographic Channel]] debuted the documentary reality series ''[[Amish: Out of Order]]'', about the lives of former Amish who have left the community.

In September 2012, [[TLC]] began airing the reality television series, [[Breaking Amish]] which follows a group of Amish and Mennonite youths as they leave their communities to experience the outside world in New York City. Not long after the show began airing, controversy arose concerning evidence that appears to indicate the cast members had actually been living outside the Amish community for some time, leaving the viewers to believe that much of the show is staged or scripted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2206755/Breaking-Amish-Is-TLC-fake.html|title=Is Breaking Amish for real? Just two episodes in and already viewers are asking whether it's really all that authentic | work = Daily Mail | edition = online |date=22 September 2012|publisher=Associated Newspapers | location = [[United Kingdom|UK]] |accessdate=3 Oct 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[PBS]] had broadcast a [[The Amish (documentary)|documentary about the Amish]] in February 2012.&lt;ref name=PBSAE/&gt;

===Music===
[[&quot;Weird Al&quot; Yankovic]]'s 1996 parody &quot;[[Amish Paradise]]&quot; and the accompanying music video were an affectionate send-up of [[Coolio]]'s earlier rap song &quot;[[Gangsta's Paradise (song)|Gangsta's Paradise]]&quot;, with Yankovic and former ''[[The Brady Bunch]]'' actress [[Florence Henderson]] in Amish garb, and lyrics reflecting Amish themes.

==See also==
{{Portal|Anabaptism}}
* [[Amish furniture]]
* [[Amish music]]
* [[Amish school shooting]]
* [[Barn raising]]
* [[Beverly Lewis]]
* [[Christian views on poverty and wealth]]
* [[Fancy Dutch]]
* [[Martyrs Mirror]]
* [[Northkill Amish Settlement]]
* ''[[Ordnung]]''
* [[Plain people]]
* [[Simple living]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=lower-alpha|colwidth = 64em}}

==References==
{{Reflist| colwidth = 32em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{Citation |last=Hamm |first=Thomas D |title=Amish Society |edition= 4th |publisher=Columbia University Press |year=2003 |isbn=0-231-12362-0 |allpages=293}}.
* {{Citation |last=Hostetler |first=John |authorlink=John A. Hostetler |title=Amish Society |edition= 4th |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |year=1993 |isbn=978-0-8018-4442-3 |location=Baltimore, Maryland; London}}.
* {{Citation | last = Kraybill | first = Donald B | editor-first = Marc A | editor-last = Olshan | title = The Amish Struggle with Modernity | place = Hanover, NH | publisher = University Press of New England | eyar = 1994 | allpages = 304}}.
* {{Citation | last =Kraybill | first = Donald B |authorlink=Donald Kraybill | title = The Anabaptist Escalator}}.
* {{Citation | last =Kraybill | first = Donald B |authorlink=Donald Kraybill | author-mask = 3 |title=Anabaptist World USA |publisher=Herald Press |year=2001 | origyear = 2000 |isbn=0-8361-9163-3}}.
* {{Citation |title=The Riddle of Amish Culture |last=Kraybill |first=Donald B |authorlink=Donald Kraybill | author-mask = 3 |edition= revised |year=2001 |isbn=0-8018-6772-X}}.
* {{Citation | last = Nolt | first = SM | title = A History of the Amish | place = Intercourse | publisher = Good Books | year = 1992}}.
* {{Citation |last1 =Smith |first1 =C Henry |title=Smith's Story of the Mennonites |year=1981 |publisher=Faith and Life Press |location=Newton, Kansas |isbn=0-87303-069-9| pages=249–356 | edition =revised &amp; expanded | first2 = Cornelius | last2 = Krahn}}.
* {{Citation | title = Amish America | contribution = Swiss Amish | publisher = Type pad | url= http://amishamerica.typepad.com/amish_america/swiss_amish/ | accessdate= March 26, 2009| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20090302035944/http://amishamerica.typepad.com/amish_america/swiss_amish/| archivedate= March 2, 2009 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}.

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* ''Die Botschaft'' (Lancaster, PA 17608-0807; 717-392-1321). Magazine for Old Order Amish published by non-Amish; only Amish may place advertisements.
* [http://www.thebudgetnewspaper.com/ ''The Budget''] (P.O. Box 249, Sugarcreek, OH 44681; 330-852-4634). Weekly newspaper by and for Amish.
* ''The Diary'' (P.O. Box 98, Gordonville, PA 17529). Monthly newsmagazine by and for Old Order Amish.
*Beachy, Leroy. ''Unser Leit ... The Story of the Amish''. Millersburg, OH: Goodly Heritage Books, 2011. 996 pp.&amp;nbsp;ISBN 0-9832397-0-3
*DeWalt, Mark W. ''Amish Education in the United States and Canada''. Rowman and Littlefield Education, 2006. 224 pp.
*Garret, Ottie A and Ruth Irene Garret. ''True Stories of the X-Amish: Banned, Excommunicated and Shunned'', Horse Cave, KY: Neu Leben, 1998.
*Garret, Ruth Irene. ''Crossing Over: One Woman's Escape from Amish Life'', Thomas More, 1998.
*Good, Merle and Phyllis. ''20 Most Asked Questions about the Amish and Mennonites''. Intercourse, PA: Good Books, 1979.
*Hostetler, John A. ed. ''Amish Roots: A Treasury of History, Wisdom, and Lore''. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1989. 319 pp.
* Igou, Brad. ''The Amish in Their Own Words: Amish Writings from 25 Years of Family Life'', Scottdale, PA: Herald Press, 1999. 400 pp.
*Johnson-Weiner, Karen M. ''Train Up a Child: Old Order Amish and Mennonite Schools''. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2006. 304 pp.
*Keim, Albert. ''Compulsory Education and the Amish: The Right Not to be Modern''. Beacon Press, 1976. 211 pp.
*Kraybill, Donald B. ''The Amish of Lancaster County''. Mechanicsburg, PA: Stackpole Books, 2008.
*Kraybill, Donald B. ed. ''The Amish and the State''. Foreword by Martin E. Marty. 2nd ed.: Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2003. 351 pp.
*Kraybill, Donald B. and Carl D. Bowman. ''On the Backroad to Heaven: Old Order Hutterites, Mennonites, Amish, and Brethren''. Baltimore, Johns Hopkins University Press, 2002. 330pp.
*Kraybill, Donald B. and Steven M. Nolt. ''Amish Enterprise: From Plows to Profits''. 2nd ed. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2004. 286 pp.
*Kraybill, Donald B., Steven M. Nolt and David L. Weaver-Zercher. ''Amish Grace: How Forgiveness Transcended Tragedy''. New York: Jossey-Bass, 2006. 256 pp.
*Luthy, David. ''Amish Settlements That Failed, 1840–1960''. LaGrange, IN: Pathway Publishers, 1991. 555pp.
*Nolt, Steven M. ''A history of the Amish''. Rev. and updated ed.: Intercourse, Pa.: Good Books, 2003. 379 pp.
*Nolt, Steven M. and Thomas J. Myers. ''Plain Diversity: Amish Cultures and Identities''. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2007. 256 pp.
*Schachtman, Tom. ''Rumspringa: To be or not to be Amish''. New York: North Point Press, 2006. 286 pp.
*Schlabach, Theron F. ''Peace, Faith, Nation: Mennonites and Amish in Nineteenth-Century America''. Scottdale, PA: Herald Press, 1988. 415 pp.
*Schmidt, Kimberly D., Diane Zimmerman Umble, and Steven D. Reschly, eds. ''Strangers at Home: Amish and Mennonite Women in History''. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2002. 416 pp.
*Scott, Stephen. ''The Amish Wedding and Other Special Occasions of the Old Order Communities''. Intercourse, PA: Good Books, 1988. 128pp.
*Stevick, Richard A. ''Growing Up Amish: the Teenage Years''. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2007. 320 pp.
*Umble, Diane Zimmerman. ''Holding the Line: the Telephone in Old Order Mennonite and Amish Life''. Johns Hopkins University Press, 2000. 192 pp.
*Umble, Diane Zimmerman and David L. Weaver-Zercher, eds. ''The Amish and the Media''. Johns Hopkins University Press, 2008. 288 pp.
* Weaver-Zercher, David L. ''The Amish in the American Imagination''. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2001. 280 pp.
* Yoder, Harvey. ''The Happening: Nickel Mines School Tragedy''. Berlin, OH: TGS International, 2007. 173 pp.

{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Amish}}
* [http://www.gameo.org/encyclopedia/contents/A4574ME.html &quot;Amish&quot;] in the ''Global Anabaptist Mennonite Encyclopedia Online''
* [http://www2.etown.edu/amishstudies/Index.asp &quot;Amish Studies&quot;] at Young Center for Anabaptist &amp; Pietist Studies at [[Elizabethtown College]]
* [http://missourifolkloresociety.truman.edu/Amish.htm &quot;The Amish&quot;]  from the Missouri Folklore Society
* [http://www.orrar.net/amish/bdamishmovement.htm Background Dynamics of the Amish Movement]

[[Category:American people of Swiss descent]]
[[Category:Amish|*]]
[[Category:Christianity in Indiana]]
[[Category:Christianity in Ohio]]
[[Category:Christianity in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Christianity in Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Ethnic groups in North America]]
[[Category:History of Lancaster, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Germanic peoples]]
[[Category:German-American history]]
[[Category:German diaspora]]
[[Category:Ohio culture]]
[[Category:Peace churches]]
[[Category:Pennsylvania culture]]
[[Category:Religion in Lancaster, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1693]]
[[Category:Simple living]]
[[Category:Christian organizations established in the 17th century]]
[[Category:American people of German descent|*]]

{{Link FA|yi}}
&lt;!-- Interwikis --&gt;
[[als:Amische]]
[[ar:أميش]]
[[zh-min-nan:Amisch]]
[[bg:Амиши]]
[[ca:Amish]]
[[cs:Amišové]]
[[cy:Amisch]]
[[da:Amish]]
[[pdc:Amisch]]
[[de:Amische]]
[[et:Amišid]]
[[es:Amish]]
[[eo:Amiŝismo]]
[[eu:Amish]]
[[fa:آمیش]]
[[fr:Amish]]
[[fy:Amish]]
[[ga:Amanaigh]]
[[ko:아미시파]]
[[hr:Amiši]]
[[id:Amish]]
[[it:Amish]]
[[he:אמיש]]
[[kn:ಅಮಿಶ್]]
[[ka:ამიშები]]
[[mrj:Амишвлӓ]]
[[lt:Amišai]]
[[hu:Amisok]]
[[nl:Amish]]
[[ja:アーミッシュ]]
[[no:Amish]]
[[nds:Amisch]]
[[pl:Amisze]]
[[pt:Amish]]
[[ro:Amish]]
[[ru:Амиши]]
[[sq:Amish]]
[[simple:Amish]]
[[sk:Amiši]]
[[sl:Amiši]]
[[sr:Амиши]]
[[sh:Amiši]]
[[fi:Amissit]]
[[sv:Amish]]
[[tr:Amiş]]
[[uk:Аміші]]
[[yi:אמיש]]
[[zh:阿米什人]]</text>
      <sha1>netg7fdg70z21gnl75y06nr1i586pdj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
