<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anti-clericalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>571440</id>
    <revision>
      <id>512346019</id>
      <parentid>512343221</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-14T07:34:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Fact}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38589">{{refimprove|date=December 2011}}

'''Anti-clericalism''' is a historical movement that opposes the [[clergy]] for reasons including their actual or alleged power and influence in all aspects of public and political life and their involvement in the everyday life of the citizen, their privileges, or their enforcement of orthodoxy.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopædia Britannica, ''Anticlericalism'' (2007 Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.)&lt;/ref&gt;  Not all anti-clericals are irreligious or anti-religious, some anti-clericals have been religious and have opposed clergy on the basis of institutional issues and/or disagreements in religious interpretation, such as during the [[Protestant Reformation]].

Anti-clericalism in one form or another has existed through most of [[History of Christianity|Christian history]]. Some philosophers of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]], including [[Voltaire]], attacked the Catholic Church, its leadership and priests claiming moral corruption of many of its clergy.

== France ==
=== Revolution ===
The [[French Revolution]], particularly in its [[Jacobin]] period, initiated one of the most violent episodes of anti-clericalism in pre-modern Europe; the new revolutionary authorities suppressed the church; destroyed, desecrated and expropriated monasteries; exiled 30,000 priests and killed hundreds more.&lt;ref name=&quot;StoryChr&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Collins|first= Michael|others= Mathew A Price|title=The Story of Christianity|year=1999|publisher= Dorling Kindersley |isbn=978-0-7513-0467-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; As part of a [[Dechristianization of France during the French Revolution|campaign to de-Christianize France]] in October 1793 the Christian calendar was outlawed, replaced with one reckoning from the date of the Revolution, and then an atheist [[Cult of Reason]] was inaugurated, all churches not devoted to that cult being closed.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;Helmstadter, Richard J., [http://books.google.com/books?id=aw_1aaE0Fb4C&amp;dq Freedom and religion in the nineteenth century] p. 251, 1997 Stanford Univ. Press.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1794, the atheistic cult was replaced with a deistic [[Cult of the Supreme Being]].&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; When anticlericalism became a clear goal of French revolutionaries, [[counter-revolutionaries]] seeking to restore tradition and the Ancien Régime took up arms, particularly in the [[War in the Vendée]] (1793 to 1796).

When [[Pope Pius VI]] took sides against the revolution in the [[First Coalition]] (1792–1797), [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] invaded [[Italy]] (1796).&lt;ref name=&quot;SandS&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Duffy|first= Eamon|others= |title=Saints and Sinners, a History of the Popes|year=1997|publisher= [[Yale University Press]] in association with S4C |isbn=|id=Library of Congress Catalog card number 97-60897}}
&lt;/ref&gt; French troops imprisoned the Pope in 1797, and he died after six weeks of captivity.&lt;ref name=&quot;SandS&quot;/&gt;
After a change of heart, Napoleon then re-established the Catholic Church in France with the signing of the [[Concordat of 1801]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SandS&quot;/&gt;
Many anti-clerical policies continued. When Napoleonic armies entered a territory, monasteries were often sacked and church property secularized.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=M3m1CfZj8ZAC&amp;pg=PA131&amp;lpg=PA131&amp;dq=napoleon+sacked+monasteries+closed+secularized&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=XmGqU5d6LT&amp;sig=ac2RlTNNh6gcD_U90vSJ_lCnzeE&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=K98vT5ueM4zkggfCsP37Dw&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=napoleon%20sacked%20monasteries%20closed%20secularized&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=ZS3nAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA412&amp;lpg=PA412&amp;dq=napoleon+sacked+monasteries+closed+secularized&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=oFPjMTHcxw&amp;sig=PU_gWjv16zvshLlpylXNSgdq-vQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=K98vT5ueM4zkggfCsP37Dw&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=napoleon%20sacked%20monasteries%20closed%20secularized&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=XRtWxK42KMgC&amp;pg=PA281&amp;lpg=PA281&amp;dq=napoleon+sacked+monasteries+closed+secularized&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=K9lykl9zkB&amp;sig=RyIp6kcSjEzFs8TI_8__1Rw-_fQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=K98vT5ueM4zkggfCsP37Dw&amp;ved=0CEMQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=napoleon%20sacked%20monasteries%20closed%20secularized&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gordon.edu/lettersfromeurope/agneshoward]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Third Republic ===
A further phase of anti-clericalism occurred in the context of the French [[French Third Republic|Third Republic]] and its dissensions with the Catholic Church. Prior to the [[1905 French law on the Separation of the Churches and the State]], the Catholic Church enjoyed preferential treatment from the French state (formally along with the Jewish, [[Lutheran]] and [[Calvinist]] minority religions, but in practice with much more influence than those). During the 19th century, public schools employed priests as teachers, and religion was taught in schools (teachers were also obliged to lead the class to [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]]). In 1881–1882 [[Jules Ferry]]'s government passed the [[Jules Ferry laws]], establishing free education (1881) and mandatory and lay education (1882), giving the basis of French [[public education]]. The [[French Third Republic|Third Republic]] (1871–1940), dominated the nation until the [[16 May 1877 crisis]] by the Catholic [[Legitimists]] who dreamed of a return to the ''[[Ancien Régime]]''.

In 1880 and 1882 [[Benedictine]] teaching monks were effectively exiled. This was not completed until 1901.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.st-benoit-du-lac.com/histoire1/history1.html]. Retrieved November 29, 2008.
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
[http://books.google.com/books?id=Wk1KzHS1IagC&amp;pg=PA495&amp;lpg=PA495&amp;dq=-wikipedia+benedictines+expelled+from+france+1901&amp;source=web&amp;ots=7RydgvaUmY&amp;sig=e6nAEj6HiM6GS-WrGt1w1Fp3dpI&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=result]. Retrieved November 29, 2008.
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02443a.htm CATHOLIC ENCYCLOPEDIA: The Benedictine Order]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.ryde.shalfleet.net/wootton_and_quarr.htm Wootton and Fishbourne]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.citeaux.net/assisi2005/delivrance-eng.htm RGM 2005 OCSO]&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1905 law on separation of state and church was enacted with strength and vigor by the government of [[Radical Party (France)|Radical-Socialist]] [[Émile Combes]]. Most Catholic schools and educational foundations were closed  — except in [[Alsace-Lorraine]] which belonged at that time to Germany.

In the [[Affaire Des Fiches]] in France in 1904–1905, it was discovered that the anticlerical War Minister under [[Émile Combes]], General [[Louis André]], was determining promotions based on the French [[Catholicism and Freemasonry|Masonic]] Grand Orient's huge card index on public officials, detailing which were Catholic and who attended Mass, with a view to preventing their promotions.&lt;ref&gt;Larkin, Church and State after the Dreyfus Affair, pp. 138–41: `Freemasonry in France’, Austral Light 6, 1905, pp. 164–72, 241–50.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Republicanism|Republicans]]' anti-clericalism softened after the First World War as the Catholic right-wing began to accept [[secularism]]. However, the theme of subsidized [[education in France|private schools in France]], which are overwhelmingly Catholic but whose teachers draw pay from the state, remains a sensitive issue in [[Politics of France|French politics]].

== Austria (Austro-Hungarian Empire) ==
Emperor [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor|Joseph II]] opposed what he called “contemplative” religious institutions — reclusive Catholic institutions that he perceived as doing nothing positive for the community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08508b.htm Catholic Encyclopedia]. Retrieved March 19, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; His policy towards them are included in what is called [[Josephinism]].

Joseph decreed that Austrian bishops could not communicate directly with the [[Roman Curia|Curia]]. More than 500 of 1,188 monasteries in Austro-Slav lands (and a hundred more in Hungary) were dissolved, and 60 million florins taken by the state. This wealth was used to create 1,700 new parishes and welfare institutions.&lt;ref&gt;Okey, 44&lt;/ref&gt;

The education of priests was taken from the Church as well. Joseph established six state-run “General Seminaries.” In 1783, a Marriage Patent treated marriage as a civil contract rather than a religious institution.&lt;ref&gt;Berenger, 102&lt;/ref&gt;

Catholic Historians have claimed that there was an alliance between Joseph and anti-clerical Freemasons.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In Germany and Austria, Freemasonry during the eighteenth century was a powerful ally of the so-called party, of &quot;[[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]]&quot; (Aufklaerung), and of Josephinism&quot; from {{Cite Catholic Encyclopedia|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm|title=Masonry (Freemasonry)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Italy ==
Anti-clericalism in [[Italy]] is connected with reaction against the absolutism of the [[Papal States]], overthrown in 1870. For a long time, the [[Pope]] required Catholics not to participate in the public life of the [[Italy|Kingdom of Italy]] that had invaded the Papal States to complete the unification of Italy, leaving the pope confined in the [[Vatican City|Vatican]]. Some politicians that had played important roles in this process, such as [[Camillo Benso, conte di Cavour]], were known to be hostile to the temporal and political power of the Church.

The hostility between the [[Holy See]] and the kingdom was finally settled by fascist [[dictator]] [[Benito Mussolini]], who sought an agreement with the Church to gain its support: the [[Lateran Treaty]] was finalised in 1929.

After World War II, anti-clericalism was embodied by the [[Italian Communist Party|Italian Communist]] and [[Italian Socialist Party|Italian Socialist]] parties, in opposition to the Vatican-endorsed party [[Christian Democracy (Italy)|Christian Democracy]].

The revision of the Lateran treaties during the 1980s by the Socialist [[Prime Minister of Italy]] [[Bettino Craxi]], removed the status of &quot;official religion&quot; of the Catholic Church, but still granted a series of provisions in favour of the Church, such as the [[eight per thousand]] law, the teaching of religion in schools, and other privileges.

Recently, the Catholic Church has been taking a more aggressive stance in [[Politics of Italy|Italian politics]], in particular through [[cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[Camillo Ruini]], who often makes his voice heard commenting the political debate and indicating the official line of the Church on various matters. This interventionism has increased with the papacy of [[Benedict XVI]]. Anti-clericalism, however, is not the official stance of most parties (with the exception of the [[Italian Radicals]], who, however identify as [[laicist]]), as most party leaders consider it an electoral disadvantage to openly contradict the Church: since the demise of the Christian Democracy as a single party, Catholic votes are often swinging between the right and the left wing, and are considered to be decisive to win an election.

== Poland ==
[[Palikot's Movement]], is an anti-clerical party founded in 2011 by politician [[Janusz Palikot]]. Palikot's Movement won 10% of the national vote at the [[Polish parliamentary election, 2011]]. This was an unprecedented result for an anti-church party in Poland, where Catholicism is believed to be deeply rooted.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

== Latin America ==
{{Main|Anti-clericalism in Latin America}}

Of the population of Latin America, about 71% acknowledge allegiance to the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser, Barbara J., [http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/0503707.htm In Latin America, Catholics down, church's credibility up, poll says] Catholic News Service June 23, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fewer Catholics in Latin America&quot;&gt;Oppenheimer, Andres [http://legacy.signonsandiego.com/uniontrib/20050517/news_lz1e17oppenh.html Fewer Catholics in Latin America] San Diego Tribune May 15, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, about 43% of the world's Catholics inhabit the ‘Latin’ countries of South, Central and North America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fewer Catholics in Latin America&quot;/&gt;

The slowness to embrace religious freedom in Latin America is related to its colonial heritage and to its post-colonial history. The Aztec and the Inca both made substantial use of religion to support their authority and power. This pre-existing role of religion in pre-Columbian culture made it relatively easy for the Spanish conquistadors to replace native religious structures with those of a Catholicism that was closely linked to the Spanish throne.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Paul E. |last=Sigmund |year=1996 |publisher=Emory University School of Law |journal=Emory International Law Review |title=Religious Human Rights in the World Today: A Report on the 1994 Atlanta Conference: Legal Perspectives on Religious Human Rights: Religious Human Rights in Latin America}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anti-clericalism was a common feature of 19th-century liberalism in Latin America. This anti-clericalism was often purportedly based on the idea that the clergy (especially the prelates who ran the administrative offices of the Church) were hindering social progress in areas such as public education and economic development.

Beginning in the 1820s, a succession of liberal regimes came to power in Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;Stacy, ''Mexico and the United States'' (2003), p. 139&lt;/ref&gt; Some members of these liberal regimes sought to imitate the Spain of the 1830s (and revolutionary France of a half-century earlier) in expropriating the wealth of the Catholic Church, and in imitating the eighteenth-century benevolent despots in restricting or prohibiting the religious orders. As a result, a number of these liberal regimes expropriated Church property and tried to bring education, marriage and burial under secular authority. The confiscation of Church properties and changes in the scope of religious liberties (in general, increasing the rights of non-Catholics and non-observant Catholics, while licensing or prohibiting the orders) generally accompanied secularist, and later, Marxist-leaning, governmental reforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Norman172&quot;&gt;Norman, ''The Roman Catholic Church an Illustrated History'' (2007), pp. 167–72&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mexico ===
The Mexican Constitution of 1824 had required the Republic to prohibit the exercise of any religion other than the Roman Catholic and Apostolic faith.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tarlton.law.utexas.edu/constitutions/text/1824index.html Federal Constitution of the United Mexican States (1824)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Reform War ====
{{Main|Reform War}}

Starting in 1855, President [[Benito Juárez]] issued decrees nationalizing church property, separating church and state, and suppressing religious orders. Church properties were confiscated and basic civil and political rights were denied to religious orders and the clergy.

==== Cristero War ====
{{Main|Cristero War}}
[[File:Miguel Pro.gif|thumb|left |[[Miguel Pro]], arms spread in the form of a cross, was executed by the anti-clerical regime in Mexico in 1927]]

More severe laws called [[Calles Law]] during the rule of [[atheist]]&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|title=Mexico's New Politics
|author=David A. Shirk
|page = 58
|year=2005
|publisher=[[Lynne Rienner Publishers]]
|isbn=1-58826-270-7
|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WOBRb0wKpocC&amp;pg=PA58&amp;lpg=PA58&amp;dq
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Plutarco Elías Calles]] eventually led to the [[Cristero War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Chadwick264&quot;&gt;Chadwick, ''A History of Christianity'' (1995), pp. 264–5&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the [[Mexican Revolution]] of 1910, the new Mexican Constitution of 1917 contained further anti-clerical provisions. Article 3 called for secular education in the schools and prohibited the Church from engaging in primary education; Article 5 outlawed monastic orders; Article 24 forbade public worship outside the confines of churches; and Article 27 placed restrictions on the right of religious organizations to hold property. Most offensively to Catholics{{fact|date=September 2012}}, Article 130 deprived clergy members of basic political rights. Many of these laws were resisted, leading to the [[Cristero War|Cristero Rebellion]] of 1927–1929. The suppression of the Church included the closing of many churches and the killing of priests. The persecution was most severe in Tabasco under the [[atheist]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Godman, &quot;Graham Greene's Vatican Dossier&quot; ''The Atlantic Monthly'' 288.1 (July/August 2001): 85.
&lt;/ref&gt; governor [[Tomás Garrido Canabal]].

The war had a profound effect on the Church. Between 1926 and 1934 at least 40 priests were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blood-Drenched Altars&quot;&gt;Van Hove, Brian [http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT Blood-Drenched Altars] Faith &amp; Reason 1994
&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1926 and 1934, over 3,000 priests were exiled or assassinated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scheina&quot;&gt;Scheina, ''Latin America's Wars: The Age of the Caudillo'' (2003), p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Van Hove | first =Brian | title =Blood Drenched Altars | publisher =EWTN | year =1994 | url =http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT Blood-Drenched Altars |accessdate=2008-03-09}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Where 4,500 priests served the people before the rebellion, in 1934 there were only 334 priests licensed by the government to serve fifteen million people, the rest having been eliminated by emigration, expulsion and assassination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blood-Drenched Altars&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scheina, Robert L. p. 33&quot;&gt;
Scheina, Robert L. [http://books.google.com/books?id=8aWQ_7oKJfkC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;lpg=PA33&amp;dq=cristero+war+priests+killed&amp;source=web&amp;ots=YNDpLM2ukb&amp;sig=YWccvtnJKnSpaI15bTHCOX3zoyc#PPA33,M1 Latin America's Wars: The Age of the Caudillo, 1791–1899] p. 33 (2003 Brassey's) ISBN 978-1-57488-452-4
&lt;/ref&gt; It appears that ten states were left without any priests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scheina, Robert L. p. 33&quot;/&gt;

=== Ecuador ===
This issue was one of the bases for the lasting dispute between Conservatives, who represented primarily the interests of the [[Geography of Ecuador#La Sierra (the highlands)|Sierra]] and the church, and the Liberals, who represented those of the Costa and anticlericalism. Tensions came to a head in 1875 when the conservative President [[Gabriel García Moreno]], after being elected to his third term, was allegedly assassinated by anticlerical Freemasons.&lt;ref&gt;Berthe, P. Augustine, translated from French by Mary Elizabeth
Herbert [http://books.google.com/books?id=Akr838XsIO0C&amp;dq Garcia Moreno, President of Ecuador, 1821–1875] p. 297-300, 1889 Burns and Oates&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Burke, Edmund [http://books.google.com/books?id=wD89Lnx_S_gC&amp;d Annual Register: A Review of Public Events at Home and Abroad, for the year 1875] p.323 1876 Rivingtons&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Colombia ===
{{See|La Violencia}}

Colombia enacted anticlerical legislation and its enforcement during more than three decades (1849–84).

[[La Violencia]] refers to an era of civil conflict in various areas of the [[Colombia]]n countryside between supporters of the [[Colombian Liberal Party]] and the [[Colombian Conservative Party]], a conflict which took place roughly from 1948 to 1958.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author= Stokes, Doug| url= http://bailey83221.livejournal.com/54324.html| title= America's Other War : Terrorizing Colombia| publisher= Zed Books| year= 2005| isbn=978-1-84277-547-9}} p. 68, ''Both Livingstone and Stokes quote a figure of 200,000 dead between 1948–1953 (Livingstone) and &quot;a decade war&quot; (Stokes)''&lt;br /&gt;*{{cite journal
|first =Camilo A.
|last =Azcarate
|authorlink =
|coauthors =
|year =1999
|month =March
|title = Psychosocial Dynamics of the Armed Conflict in Colombia
|journal =Online Journal of Peace and Conflict Resolution
|volume =
|issue =
|pages =
|url =http://www.trinstitute.org/ojpcr/2_1columbia.htm
}} ''Azcarate quotes a figure of 300,000 dead between 1948–1959''&lt;br /&gt;*{{cite journal
|first =Pedro Ruz
|last =Gutiérrez
|authorlink =
|coauthors =
|year =1999
|month =October 31
|title =Bullets, Bloodshed And Ballots;For Generations, Violence Has Defined Colombia's Turbulent Political History
|journal =Orlando Sentinel (Florida)
|volume =
|issue =
|pages =G1
|url =http://bailey83221.livejournal.com/77682.html
}}''Political violence is not new to that South American nation of 38 million people. In the past 100 years, more than 500,000 Colombians have died in it. From the &quot;War of the Thousand Days,&quot; a civil war at the turn of the century that left 100,000 dead, to a partisan clash between 1948 and 1966 that claimed nearly 300,000...''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|first =Charles
|last =Bergquist
|authorlink =
|coauthors = David J. Robinson
|year = 1997–2005
|url = http://ca.encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761564636_10/Colombia.html
|title = Colombia
|work = Microsoft Encarta Online Encyclopedia 2005
|publisher = Microsoft Corporation
|accessdate = April 16, 2006
|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5kwsWoGia|archivedate=2009-10-31}}''On April 9, 1948, Gaitán was assassinated outside his law offices in downtown Bogotá. The assassination marked the start of a decade of bloodshed, called ''La Violencia'' (the violence), which took the lives of an estimated 180,000 Colombians before it subsided in 1958.''&lt;/ref&gt;

Across the country, militants attacked churches, convents, and monasteries, killing priests and looking for arms, since the conspiracy theory maintained that the religious had guns, and this despite the fact that not a single serviceable weapon was located in the raids.&lt;ref&gt;Williford p.218&lt;/ref&gt;

When their party came to power in 1930, anticlerical Liberals pushed for legislation to end Church influence in public schools. These Liberals held that the Church and its intellectual backwardness were responsible for a lack of spiritual and material progress in Colombia. Liberal-controlled local, departmental and national governments ended contracts with religious communities who operated schools in government-owned buildings, and set up secular schools in their place. These actions were sometimes violent, and were met by a strong opposition from clerics, Conservatives, and even a good number of more moderate Liberals.

=== Argentina ===
The original [[Argentine Constitution of 1853]] provided that all Argentine presidents must be Catholic and stated that the duty of the Argentine congress was to convert the Indians to Catholicism. All of these provisions have been eliminated with the exception of the mandate to &quot;sustain&quot; Catholicism.

Liberal anti-clericalists of the 1880s established a new pattern of church-state relations in which the official constitutional status of the Church was preserved while the state assumed control of many functions formerly the province of the Church. Conservative Catholics, asserting their role as definers of national values and morality, responded in part by joining in the rightist religio-political movement known as Catholic Nationalism which formed successive opposition parties. This began a prolonged period of conflict between church and state that persisted until the 1940s when the Church enjoyed a restoration of its former status under the presidency of Colonel [[Juan Perón]]. Perón claimed that Peronism was the &quot;true embodiment of Catholic social teaching&quot; – indeed, more the embodiment of Catholicism than the Catholic Church itself.

In 1954, Argentina saw extensive destruction of churches, denunciations of clergy and confiscation of Catholic schools as Perón attempted to extend state control over national institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Norman167&quot;&gt;Norman, ''The Roman Catholic Church an Illustrated History'' (2007), pp. 167–8&lt;/ref&gt;

The renewed rupture in church-state relations was completed when Perón was [[Excommunication|excommunicated]]. However, in 1955, he was overthrown by a military general who was a leading member of the Catholic Nationalist movement.

In 1983, the civilian president, [[Raúl Alfonsín]], attempted to restore a liberal democratic state. Alfonsín's opposition to the church-military alliance, conjoined with his strongly secular emphasis contravening traditional Catholic positions, incited opposition that served to curtail his agenda.

=== Venezuela ===
In Venezuela, the government of [[Antonio Guzmán Blanco]] virtually crushed the institutional life of the church, even attempting to legalize the marriage of priests. These anticlerical policies remained in force for decades afterward.

=== Cuba ===
Cuba, under atheist [[Fidel Castro]], succeeded in reducing the Church's ability to work by deporting the archbishop and 150 Spanish priests, discriminating against Catholics in public life and education and refusing to accept them as members of the Communist Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chadwick266&quot;/&gt; The subsequent flight of 300,000 people from the island also helped to diminish the Church there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chadwick266&quot;&gt;Chadwick, ''A History of Christianity'' (1995), p. 266&lt;/ref&gt;

== Portugal ==
A first wave of anti-clericalism occurred in 1834 when under the government of [[Pedro I of Brazil|Dom Pedro]] all convents and monasteries in Portugal were abolished, simultaneously closing some of Portugal's primary educational establishments.

The fall of the Monarchy in the [[5 October 1910 revolution|Republican revolution of 1910]] led to another wave of anti-clerical activity. Most church property was put under State control, and the church was not allowed to inherit property. The revolution and the republic which took a [[Separation of church and state#Friendly and hostile separation|&quot;hostile&quot; approach to the issue of church and state separation]], like that of the [[Dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution|French Revolution]], the [[Spanish Constitution of 1931]] and the [[Mexican Constitution of 1917]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite book| ref=harv
| last=Maier | first=Hans
| others=trans. Jodi Bruhn
| year=2004
| url= http://books.google.com/?id=Wozo1W7giZQC&amp;dq
| title=Totalitarianism and Political Religions
| isbn=0-7146-8529-1
| page=[http://books.google.com/books?id=Wozo1W7giZQC&amp;pg=PA106 106]
| publisher=Routledge
}}&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the anticlerical revolution, the bishops were driven from their dioceses, the property of clerics was seized by the state, wearing of the [[cassock]] was banned, all minor [[seminaries]] were closed and all but five major seminaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Church in the Modern Age&quot;&gt;Jedin, Hubert, Gabriel Adriányi, John Dolan, [http://books.google.com/books?id=LjLQwToInS4C&amp;dq The Church in the Modern Age], p. 612, Continuum International Publishing Group, 1981&lt;/ref&gt; A law of February 22, 1918 permitted only two seminaries in the country, but they had not been given their property back.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Church in the Modern Age&quot;/&gt;  [[Religious orders]] were expelled from the country, including 31 orders comprising members in 164 houses (in 1917 some orders were permitted to form agaain).&lt;ref name=&quot;The Church in the Modern Age&quot;/&gt;  Religious education was prohibited in both primary and secondary school.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Church in the Modern Age&quot;/&gt; Religious oaths and church taxes were also abolished.

== Spain ==
The first instance of anti-clerical violence due to political conflict in 19th century Spain occurred during the [[Trienio Liberal]] (Spanish Civil War of 1820–1823). During riots in [[Catalonia]], 20 clergymen were killed by members of the liberal movement in retaliation for the Church's siding with absolutist supporters of [[Ferdinand VII]].

In 1836 following the [[First Carlist War]], the [[Ecclesiastical Confiscations of Mendizábal]] ({{lang-es|Desamortización}}) promulgated by [[Juan Álvarez Mendizábal]], prime minister of the new regime abolished the major Spanish Convents and Monasteries.&lt;ref&gt;Germán Rueda Hernánz, ''La desamortización en España: un balance, 1766-1924,'' Arco Libros. 1997. ISBN 978-84-7635-270-0&lt;/ref&gt;

Many years later the [[Radical Republican Party]] leader [[Alejandro Lerroux]] would distinguish himself by his inflammatory pieces of opinion.

=== Second Republic and Civil War (1931-1939) ===
{{Main|Red Terror (Spain)}}
{{See|Martyrs of the Spanish Civil War}}

The [[Second Spanish Republic|Republican government]] which came to power in Spain in 1931 was based on secular principles. In the first years some laws were passed secularising education, prohibiting religious education in the schools, and expelling the [[Jesuits]] from the country. On [[Pentecost]] 1932, Pope Pius XI protested against these measures and demanded [[restitution]]. He asked the Catholics of Spain to fight with all legal means against the injustices. June 3, 1933 he issued the encyclical [[Dilectissima Nobis]], in which he described the expropriation of all Church buildings, episcopal residences, parish houses, seminaries and monasteries.

By law, they were now property of the Spanish State, to which the Church had to pay rent and taxes in order to continuously use these properties. &quot;Thus the Catholic Church is compelled to pay taxes on what was violently taken from her&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dilectissima Nobis, 9–10&lt;/ref&gt; Religious vestments, liturgical instruments, statues, pictures, vases, gems and other valuable objects were expropriated as well.&lt;ref&gt;Dilectissima Nobis, 12&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Spanish Civil War|Civil War]] in Spain started in 1936, during which thousands of churches were destroyed, thirteen bishops and some 7,000 clergy and religious Spaniards were assassinated.&lt;ref&gt;Franzen 397&lt;/ref&gt; Catholics largely supported Franco and the Nationalist forces in the Spanish Civil War of 1936–1939.

Anti-clerical assaults during what has been termed by the Nationalists [[Red Terror (Spain)|Red Terror]] included sacking and burning monasteries and churches and killing 6,832 priests,&lt;ref name=&quot;cueva355&quot;&gt;{{Harvard citation no brackets|de la Cueva|1998|p=355}}&lt;/ref&gt; including 13 bishops, 4,184 diocesan priests, 2,365 members of male religious orders, among them 259 Claretians, 226 Franciscans, 204 Piarists, 176 Brothers of Mary, 165 Christian Brothers, 155 Augustinians, 132 Dominicans, and 114 Jesuits.

13&amp;nbsp;bishops were killed from the dioceses of [[Sigüenza]], [[Lleida]], [[Cuenca, Spain|Cuenca]], [[Barbastro]] [[Segorbe]], [[Jaén, Spain|Jaén]], [[Ciudad Real]], [[Almería]], [[Guadix]], [[Barcelona]], [[Teruel]] and the auxiliary of [[Tarragona]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedin 617&quot;/&gt; Aware of the dangers, they all decided to remain in their cities. ''I cannot go, only here is my responsibility, whatever may happen,'' said the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Cuenca|Bishop of Cuenca]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedin 617&quot;/&gt; In addition 4,172&amp;nbsp;diocesan priests, 2,364&amp;nbsp;monks and friars, among them 259&amp;nbsp; Clarentians, 226&amp;nbsp;[[Franciscan]]s, 204&amp;nbsp;[[Piarists]], 176&amp;nbsp;Brothers of Mary, 165&amp;nbsp;[[Congregation of Christian Brothers|Christian Brothers]], 155&amp;nbsp;[[Augustinians]], 132&amp;nbsp;[[Dominican Order|Dominicans]], and 114&amp;nbsp;[[Jesuit]]s were killed.&lt;ref name=beevor /&gt; In some dioceses, a number of secular priests were killed:

* In [[Barbastro]] 123 of 140 priests were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedin 617&quot;/&gt; about 88&amp;nbsp;percent of the secular clergy were murdered, 66&amp;nbsp;percent
* In [[Lleida]], 270 of 410 priests were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedin 617&quot;/&gt; about 62&amp;nbsp;percent
* In [[Tortosa]], 44&amp;nbsp;percent of the secular priests were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;cueva355&quot; /&gt;
* In [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]] 286 of 600 priests priests were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedin 617&quot;/&gt;
* In the dioceses of [[Málaga]], [[Minorca]] and [[Segorbe]], about half of the priests were killed&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cueva355&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedin 617&quot;/&gt;
* In [[Madrid]] 4,000 priests priests were murdered.

One source records that 283 nuns were killed, some of whom were badly tortured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jedin 617&quot;&gt;Jedin 617&lt;/ref&gt; There are accounts of Catholic faithful being forced to swallow rosary beads, thrown down mine shafts and priests being forced to dig their own graves before being buried alive.&lt;ref name=beevor&gt;Beevor, Antony ''The Battle for Spain'' (Penguin 2006).&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic Church has [[canonize]]d several [[martyrs of the Spanish Civil War]] and [[beatification|beatified]] hundreds more.

== Canada ==
Anti-clerical waves have been seen in [[Quebec]] since 1960. The [[Quiet Revolution]] is characterised essentially by an opening toward socialism.

== United States ==
Although anti-clericalism is more often spoke of regarding the history or current politics of Latin countries where the Catholic Church was established and the clergy had privileges, [[Philip Jenkins]] in his [[The New Anti-Catholicism: The Last Acceptable Prejudice]] notes that the U.S., despite the lack of Catholic establishment, has always had anti-clericals.&lt;ref&gt;Jenkins, Philip, [http://books.google.com/books?id=cVwthOtTiI4C The New Anti-Catholicism: The Last Acceptable Prejudice], p. 10, Oxford University Press US, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

== Certain branches of Freemasonry ==
{{Main|Anticlericalism and Freemasonry}}

According to the 1917 Catholic Encyclopedia, Freemasonry was historically viewed by the Catholic Church as a principal source of anti-Clericalism,&lt;ref name=&quot;cathencmason1&quot;&gt;&quot;From the official documents of French Masonry contained principally in the official &quot;Bulletin&quot; and &quot;Compte-rendu&quot; of the Grand Orient it has been proved that all the anti-clerical measures passed in the French Parliament were decreed beforehand in the Masonic lodges and executed under the direction of the Grand Orient, whose avowed aim is to control everything and everybody in France.&quot; From the 1917 Catholic Encyclopedia article [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Freemasonry] citing ''&quot;Que personne ne bougera plus en France en dehors de nous&quot;, &quot;Bull. Gr. Or.&quot;, 1890, 500 sq.''&lt;/ref&gt; – especially in, but not limited to,&lt;ref name=&quot;cathencmason2&quot;&gt;&quot;But in spite of the failure of the official transactions, there are a great many German and not a few American Masons, who evidently favour at least the chief anti-clerical aims of the Grand Orient party.&quot; From the 1917 Catholic Encyclopedia article [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09771a.htm Freemasonry]&lt;/ref&gt; historically Catholic countries.

== Communism ==
Most Communist governments have been officially anti-clerical, abolishing religious holidays, teaching [[atheism]] in schools, closing monasteries, church social and educational institutions and many churches.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uscirf.gov/images/AR2008/annual%20report%202008-entire%20document.pdf 2008 Annual Report] of the United States Commission on International Religious Freedom&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Soviet Union]], anti-clericalism was expressed through the state; in the first five years alone after the Bolshevik revolution, 28 bishops and 1,200 priests were executed.&lt;ref name=Ostling&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ostling |first=Richard |title=Cross meets Kremlin |journal=TIME Magazine |date=June 24, 2001 |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,150718,00.html |accessdate=2007-07-03 | work=Time| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20070813173443/http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,150718,00.html| archivedate= 13 August 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Anticlericalism in the Islamic world ==
=== Iran ===
As of the late 1990s and early 2000s anticlericalism was reported to be significant in the Islamic Republic of [[Iran]]. Demonstrators have used slogans such as &quot;The clerics live like kings while we live in poverty!&quot; One report claims &quot;Working-class Iranian lamented clerical wealth in the face of their own poverty,&quot; and &quot;stories about Swiss bank accounts of leading clerics circulated on [[Tehran]]'s rumor mill.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Molavi, Afshin, ''The Soul of Iran'', Norton, (2005), p.163&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Iran, although an Islamic state, imbued with religion and religious symbolism, is an increasingly anti-clerical country. In a sense it resembles some Roman Catholic countries where religion is taken for granted, without public display, and with ambiguous feelings towards the clergy. Iranians tend to mock their mullahs, making mild jokes about them ...&lt;ref name=&quot;Economist 16, January 2003&quot;&gt;''Economist'' 16, January 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The sentiment there differs from Western anticlericalism in that it is/was associated not with [[Irreligion|irreligious]] beliefs but with dissatisfaction with theocratic rule there, the perceived misrule of [[Supreme Leader of Iran|Islamic clerics]] (particularly [[History of the Islamic Republic of Iran#Economy and human development|economic dissatisfaction]]) who rule under the principle of [[Hokumat-e Islami : Velayat-e faqih (book by Khomeini)|velayat-e faqih]].

== See also ==
* [[Age of Enlightenment]]
* [[Agnosticism]]
* [[Antitheism]]
* [[Atheism]]
* [[Clericalism]]
* [[Cristero War]]
* [[Dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution]]
* [[Denis Diderot]]
* [[Freedom of thought]]
* [[Freethought]]
* [[Inquisition]]
* [[John Dewey]]
* [[Laïcité]]
* [[La Violencia]]
* [[Red Terror (Spain)]]
* [[Reign of Terror]]
* [[Relations between the Catholic Church and the State]]
* [[Secularism]]
* [[Secular state]]
* [[Separation of church and state]]
* [[Theocracy]]
* [[Thomas Jefferson]]
* [[Thomas Paine]]
* [[Voltaire]]

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Age of Enlightenment}}
{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{Criticism of religion}}
{{Religious persecution|right}}
{{Catholic}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Anti-Clericalism}}
[[Category:Agnosticism]]
[[Category:Anticlericalism| ]]
[[Category:Anti-Catholicism]]
[[Category:Anti-Christianity]]
[[Category:Antitheism]]
[[Category:Atheism]]
[[Category:18th-century philosophy]]
[[Category:Enlightenment philosophy]]
[[Category:Freethought]]
[[Category:History of ideas]]
[[Category:History of philosophy]]
[[Category:Liberalism]]
[[Category:Persecution of Christians]]
[[Category:Political ideologies]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Religion and society]]
[[Category:Republicanism]]
[[Category:History of Roman Catholicism]]
[[Category:Secularism]]
[[Category:Separation of church and state]]
[[Category:Age of Enlightenment]]

[[ar:العداء لرجال الدين]]
[[bg:Антиклерикализъм]]
[[ca:Anticlericalisme]]
[[cs:Antiklerikalismus]]
[[da:Anti-klerikalisme]]
[[de:Antiklerikalismus]]
[[es:Anticlericalismo]]
[[eu:Antiklerikalismo]]
[[fr:Anticléricalisme]]
[[gl:Anticlericalismo]]
[[ko:반 교권주의]]
[[it:Anticlericalismo]]
[[la:Anticlericalismus]]
[[lb:Antiklerikalismus]]
[[nl:Antiklerikalisme]]
[[ja:反教権主義]]
[[no:Anti-klerikalisme]]
[[pl:Antyklerykalizm]]
[[pt:Anticlericalismo]]
[[ru:Антиклерикализм]]
[[sk:Antiklerikalizmus]]
[[sl:Antiklerikalizem]]
[[sv:Antiklerikalism]]
[[tr:Anti-klerikalizm]]
[[uk:Антиклерикалізм]]</text>
      <sha1>8r05540rorbbwi84wv2ze0u0vflygrl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
