<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Biblical literalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2100861</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517132521</id>
      <parentid>510010714</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-11T04:22:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hibernian</username>
        <id>557233</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10797">{{Bible related}}
'''Biblical literalism''' (also called '''Biblicism''' or '''Biblical fundamentalism''') is the interpretation or translation of the explicit and primary sense of words in the [[Bible]].&lt;ref&gt;''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'' Houghton Mifflin; 4 edition (September 14, 2000) defines literalism as &quot;1.  Adherence to the explicit sense of a given text or doctrine. 2. Literal portrayal; realism.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Baker Book House | isbn = 0-8010-3413-2 | last = Elwell | first = Walter A. | title = Evangelical Dictionary of Theology | location = Grand Rapids, Mich. | year = 1984 }} p. 643&lt;/ref&gt; A literal Biblical interpretation is associated with the [[Christian fundamentalism|fundamentalist]] and [[Evangelicalism|evangelical]] [[hermeneutics|hermeneutical]] approach to scripture&amp;mdash;the [[historical-grammatical method]]&amp;mdash;and is used extensively by [[Conservatism|conservative]] [[Christians]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;se=gglsc&amp;d=97803346 ''Beyond Biblical Literalism and Inerrancy: Conservative Protestants and the Hermeneutic Interpretation of Scripture''], John Bartkowski, Sociology of Religion, 57, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; in contrast to the [[historical-critical method]] of [[liberal Christianity|liberal Christians]]. The essence of this approach focuses upon the author's intent as the primary meaning of the text.&lt;ref name=elwell&gt;''Elwell Evangelical Dictionary'', Walter A. Elwell,   Baker Publishing Group, May 1996,  ISBN 0-8010-2049-2&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Literal interpretation]] does place emphasis upon the referential aspect of the words or terms in the text. It does not, however, mean a complete denial of literary aspects, genre, or figures of speech within the text (e.g., parable, allegory, simile, or metaphor).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | edition = Rev. and expanded | publisher = Moody Press | isbn = 0-8024-2187-3 | page = 224 | last = Ryrie | first = Charles Caldwell | title = Dispensationalism | location = Chicago | year = 1995 }} p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; Also literalism does not necessarily lead to total and complete agreement upon one single interpretation for any given passage. 

There are two kinds of literal interpretation, letterism and the more common historical-grammatical method. Letterism attempts to uncover the meaning of the text through a strict emphasis upon a mechanical, wooden literalism of words. This approach often obscures the literary aspects and consequently the primary meaning of the text.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Baker Book House | isbn = 0-8010-7600-5 | last = Ramm | first = Bernard | title = Protestant Biblical Interpretation | year = 1970 }} p.48&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Historical-grammatical method|historical grammatical method]] is a [[Biblical hermeneutics|hermeneutic]] technique that strives to uncover the meaning of the text by taking into account not just the grammatical words, but also the syntactical aspects, the cultural and historical background, and the literary genre. 

Fundamentalists and evangelicals sometimes refer to themselves as &quot;literalists&quot; or Biblical literalists. Sociologists also use the term in reference to conservative Christian beliefs which include not just literalism but also inerrancy. Often the term ''Biblical literalism'' is used as a pejorative to describe or ridicule the interpretative approaches of fundamentalist or evangelical Christians.&lt;ref&gt;Laurence Wood, 'Theology as History and Hermeneutics', (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;George Regas, 'Take Another Look At Your Good Book', Los Angeles Times, February 3, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dhyanchand Carr, 'Christian Council of Asia: Partnership in Mission, Conference on World Mission and the Role of Korean Churches, November 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

== Clarity of scripture ==
The vast majority of evangelical and fundamentalist Christians hold that [[Clarity of scripture|scripture is clear]], that the basic meaning and teachings of scripture may be understood by the average person. It refers to the product (teachings of scripture) rather than the process of interpretation itself ([[exegesis]]). [[Martin Luther]] distinguished between external and internal aspects within the clarity of scripture. External clarity concerns the principles of hermeneutics (including grammatical aspects) and guidance into understanding through the process of interpretation. The internal clarity concerns [[light (theology)|illumination]] of the believer—that is, guidance into understanding by the Holy Spirit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = InterVarsity Press | isbn = 0-8308-2826-5 | last = Osborne | first = Grant R | title = The Hermeneutical Spiral: A Comprehensive Introduction to Biblical Interpretation | year = 2006 }} p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;

So clarity of scripture does not mean that no interpretation principles are necessary, or that there is no cultural gap between scripture and today. Instead exegesis and interpretation principles are utilized as part of the process to close the cultural gap in striving to understand. What the clarity of scripture does deny is that the Bible is a code to decipher, or that it cannot be understood apart from complex academic analysis as is typical in the [[historical-critical method]] of interpretation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | publisher = Victor Books | isbn = 0-89693-819-0 | page = 324 | last = Zuck | first = Roy B | title = Basic Bible Interpretation | location = Wheaton, Ill | year = 1991 }}  p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

Biblical literalists believe that, unless a passage is clearly intended as allegory, poetry, or some other genre, the Bible should be interpreted as literal statements by the author.  Who may appropriately decide when a passage is allegorical or literal, however, is not defined. Fundamentalists typically treat as simple history, according to its plain sense, such passages as the [[Genesis creation narrative|Genesis account of creation]], the [[Flood myth|deluge]] and [[Noah's ark]], and the unnaturally long life-spans of the patriarchs given in [[genealogies of Genesis]], as well as the strict historicity of the narrative accounts of [[Ancient Israel]], the [[supernatural]] interventions of [[God]] in history, and [[Miracles of Jesus|Jesus' miracles]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cslewisinstitute.org/pages/resources/publications/knowingDoing/2004/Miracles.pdf#search=%22miracles%20C.S.Lewis%22 ''Lewis on Miracles''], Art Lindsley, Knowing &amp; Doing; A Teaching Quarterly for Discipleship of Heart and Mind: 
C.S. LEWIS INSTITUTE, Fall 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icr.org/pdf/imp/imp-395.pdf#search=%22Genesis%20Flood%20Whitcomb%22  ''The History and Impact of the Book, The Genesis Flood''], John C. Whitcomb, Impact, Number 395, May 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
Literalism does not question that parables, metaphors and allegory exist in the Bible, but rather relies on contextual interpretations based on the author's intention.&lt;ref name=Chicago&gt;[http://www.bible-researcher.com/chicago2.html ''Chicago Statement on Biblical Hermeneutics With commentary by Norman L. Geisler''], Reproduced from ''Explaining Hermeneutics: A Commentary on the Chicago Statement on Biblical Hermeneutics'', Oakland, California: International Council on Biblical Inerrancy, 1983.&lt;/ref&gt;

As a part of ''[[Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy]],''&lt;ref name=Chicago2&gt;[http://www.spurgeon.org/~phil/creeds/chicago.htm ''The Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy''] (1997)&lt;/ref&gt; conservative Christian scholarship affirms the following:

{{quotation|WE AFFIRM the necessity of interpreting the Bible according to its literal, or normal, sense. The literal sense is the grammatical-historical sense, that is, the meaning which the writer expressed. Interpretation according to the literal sense will take account of all figures of speech and literary forms found in the text.

WE DENY  the legitimacy of any approach to Scripture that attributes to it meaning which the literal sense does not support.}}

Noted inerrantist [[Norman Geisler]] in his commentary on the ''Chicago Statement on Biblical Hermeneutics'' states:

{{quotation|
The literal sense of Scripture is strongly affirmed here. To be sure the English word literal carries some problematic connotations with it. Hence the words normal and grammatical-historical are used to explain what is meant. The literal sense is also designated by the more descriptive title grammatical-historical sense. This means the correct interpretation is the one which discovers the meaning of the text in its grammatical forms and in the historical, cultural context in which the text is expressed.&lt;ref name=Chicago/&gt;}}

== Criticism ==

Steve Falkenberg, professor of religious psychology at [[Eastern Kentucky University]], says,
{{quote|I've never met anyone who actually believes the Bible is literally true. I know a bunch of people who say they believe the Bible is literally true but nobody is actually a literalist. Taken literally, the Bible says [[Flat earth|the earth is flat]] and sitting on pillars and cannot move ([[Psalms|Ps]] 93:1, Ps 96:10, [[Books of Samuel|1 Sam]] 2:8, [[Book of Job|Job]] 9:6). It says that great sea monsters are set to guard the edge of the sea (Job 41, Ps 104:26)... &lt;ref&gt;Falkenberg, Steve [http://web.archive.org/web/20080615062211/http://www.newreformation.org/literalism.htm ''Biblical Literalism''], ''New Reformation'', 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Conrad Hyers]], professor of comparative religion at [[Gustavus Adolphus College]] in [[St. Peter, Minnesota]], criticized biblical literalism as
{{quote|a mentality [that] manifests itself [not] only in conservative churches, private-school enclaves, television programs of the evangelical right, and a considerable amount of Christian bookstore material; one often finds a literalist understanding of Bible and faith being assumed by those who have no religious inclinations, or who are avowedly antireligious in sentiment. Even in educated circles the possibility of more sophisticated theologies... is easily obscured by burning [[straw man|straw effigies]] of biblical literalism.&lt;ref&gt;Hyers, Conrad  [http://www.religion-online.org/showarticle.asp?title=1332 &quot;Biblical Literalism: Constricting the Cosmic Dance&quot;], ''Christian Century'', August 4–11, 1982, p. 823.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==See also==
* [[Biblical inerrancy]]
* [[Science and the Bible]]
* [[Textual criticism#Application of textual criticism to religious documents|Application of textual criticism to religious documents]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Bible|Literalism]]
[[Category:Christian theology of the Bible]]
[[Category:Christianity-related controversies]]
[[Category:Christian fundamentalism]]
[[Category:Revelation]]
[[Category:Religion and science]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[da:Biblicisme]]
[[de:Biblizismus]]
[[es:Literalismo bíblico]]
[[pt:Literalismo bíblico]]
[[sv:Bokstavstro]]
[[zh:聖經直譯主義]]</text>
      <sha1>eduepyu3oyjpi8e5mbu3d52cnjxwfpb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
