<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Catholicism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4559718</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521050893</id>
      <parentid>521048744</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T13:42:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marauder40</username>
        <id>7651504</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Undid revision 521048744 by [[Special:Contributions/173.9.10.73|173.9.10.73]] ([[User talk:173.9.10.73|talk]]) rvv</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="53668">{{hatnote|This article is about religious beliefs held by several Christian denominations. For the Christians in union with the Bishop of Rome, see [[Catholic Church]]}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{Christianity}}
'''Catholicism''' is a broad term for the body of the [[Catholic]] [[faith]], its [[Theology|theologies]] and [[doctrine]]s, its [[Catholic liturgy|liturgical]], [[Ethics|ethical]], spiritual, and behavioral characteristics, as well as a [[religious]] people as a whole.&lt;ref name=&quot;McBrien&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=McBrien|first=Richard P.|title=Catholicism|publisher=HarperCollins|year=1994|pages=3–19|isbn=978-0-06-065405-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For McBrien, the &quot;broad term&quot; refers exclusively and specifically to that &quot;Communion of Catholic Churches&quot; in communion with the Bishop of Rome. Richard McBrien, ''The Church: The Evolution of Catholicism'' (New York: HarperOne, 2008), 6, 281-82, and 356. In its [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_28051992_communionis-notio_en.html Letter on Some Aspects of the Church Understood as Communion] the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] stressed that the idea of the universal church as a communion of churches must not be presented as meaning that &quot;every [[particular Church]] is a subject complete in itself, and that the universal church is the result of a ''reciprocal recognition'' on the part of the particular Churches&quot;. It insisted that &quot;the universal Church cannot be conceived as the sum of the particular Churches, or as a federation of particular Churches&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; 

For many the term usually refers to Christians and churches, [[Latin Church|western]] and [[Eastern Catholic Churches|eastern]], in [[full communion]] with the [[Holy See]], known alternatively as the [[Catholic Church]] or as the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;ref&gt;McBrien, Catholicism, 19-20.&lt;/ref&gt; However, many others use the term to refer to other churches with historical continuity from the first millennium.

In the sense of indicating historical continuity of faith and practice, the term &quot;catholicism&quot; is at times employed to mark a contrast to [[Protestantism]], which tends to look solely to the Bible as interpreted on the principles of the 16th-century [[Protestant Reformation]] as its ultimate standard.&lt;ref&gt;The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3), article ''Catholic'', p. 308&lt;/ref&gt; It was thus used by the [[Oxford Movement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Connor|first=Charles Patrick|title=Classic Catholic Converts|publisher=Ignatius Press|year=2001|isbn=978-0-89870-787-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

According to [[Richard McBrien]], Catholicism is distinguished from other forms of [[Christianity]] in its particular understanding and commitment to [[Sacred Tradition|tradition]], the [[Sacraments of the Catholic Church|sacraments]], the mediation between God, [[Communion (Christian)|communion]], and the [[See of Rome]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McBrien&quot;/&gt; According to Orthodox leaders like Bishop [[Kallistos Ware]], the [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox Church]] has these things as well, though the [[Primacy of the Roman Pontiff|primacy of the See of Rome]] is only [[honorific]], showing non-jurisdictional respect for the [[Bishop of Rome]] as the &quot;[[first among equals]]&quot; and &quot;[[Patriarch]] of the West&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Timothy Ware, ''The Orthodox Church'' (Oxford: Penguin Books, 1993), 214–217.&lt;/ref&gt; Catholicism, according to McBrien's paradigm, includes a [[Monasticism|monastic]] life, [[religious institute]]s, a religious appreciation of the arts, a communal understanding of sin and redemption, and missionary activity.&lt;ref&gt;In his book, ''Catholicism'', he notes (on page 19) that his book was &quot;written in the midst of yet another major crisis in the history of the Roman Catholic Church....&quot; Never once does he indicate in his book that Catholicism refers to churches not in communion with the See of Rome. McBrien, 19–20.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of the term ''Catholic''==
{{main|History of the term Catholic}}
The earliest recorded evidence of the use of the term ''Catholic Church'' is the ''[[Letter to the Smyrnaeans]]'' that [[Ignatius of Antioch]] wrote in about 107 to Christians in Smyrna. Exhorting Christians to remain closely united with their [[bishop]], he wrote: &quot;Wherever the bishop shall appear, there let the multitude [of the people] also be; even as, wherever [[Jesus Christ]] is, there is the Catholic Church.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smyrnaeans 8&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.v.vii.viii.html|title=Chapter VIII.—Let nothing be done without the bishop|publisher=Christian Classics Ethereal Library|accessdate=21 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Angle|first=Paul T.|title=The Mysterious Origins of Christianity|publisher=Wheatmark, Inc.|year=2007|isbn=978-1-58736-821-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Numerous other early writers including [[Cyril of Jerusalem]] (c. 315–386), [[Augustine of Hippo]] (354–430) and others further developed the use of the term &quot;catholic&quot; in relation to Christianity.

==Divergent interpretations==
Many individual Christians and [[Christian denominations]] consider themselves &quot;catholic&quot; on the basis, in particular, of [[Apostolic Succession]]. They fall into five groups:
# The Catholic Church, also known as the Roman Catholic Church, considers [[full communion]] with the [[Bishop]] of [[Diocese of Rome|Rome]] an essential element of Catholicism. Its constituent [[particular Church]]es ([[Latin Rite|Western]] and [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern]]) have distinct and separate jurisdictions, while still being &quot;in union with Rome.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Richard McBrien, ''Catholicism'' (Minneapolis, MN: Winston Press, 1981), 680.&lt;/ref&gt;
# Those, like the [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]] and [[Oriental Orthodoxy|Oriental Orthodox]], that claim unbroken [[Apostolic Succession]] from the early Church and identify themselves as ''the'' Catholic Church. The Eastern Orthodox, but not the Oriental, see themselves (along with the [[See of Rome]]) as part of a patriarchal first-millennium structure that developed in the East into the theory of the [[pentarchy|five patriarchal sees]], but not in the West, which preferred the theory of the three [[Saint Peter|Petrine]] sees of Rome, Alexandria and Antioch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myriobiblos.gr/texts/english/milton1_21.html |title=Milton V. Anastos, '&amp;#39;Aspects of the Mind of Byzantium (Political Theory, Theology, and Ecclesiastical Relations with the See of Rome)'&amp;#39;, Ashgate Publications, Variorum Collected Studies Series, 2001. ISBN 0-86078-840-7) |publisher=Myriobiblos.gr |date= |accessdate=2011-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.homolaicus.com/storia/medioevo/pentarchia/pentarchia.htm |title=L'idea di pentarchia nella cristianità |publisher=Homolaicus.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=PCPCU-fr&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/general-docs/rc_pc_chrstuni_doc_20060322_patriarca-occidente_fr.html |title=Pontifical Council for Promoting Christian Unity, press release on the suppression of the title &quot;Patriarch of the West&quot; in the 2006 Annuario Pontificio |publisher=Vatican.va |date= |accessdate=2011-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=PCPCU-en&gt;{{cite web|author=Catholic Online |url=http://www.catholic.org/international/international_story.php?id=19144 |title=Vatican explains why pope no longer &quot;patriarch of the West&quot; |publisher=Catholic.org |date=2006-03-22 |accessdate=2011-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The title, &quot;[[Patriarch of the West]]&quot;, was rarely used by the popes until the 16th and 17th centuries, and was included in the [[Annuario Pontificio]] from 1863 to 2005, being dropped in the following year as never very clear, and having become over history &quot;obsolete and practically unusable&quot;.&lt;ref name=PCPCU-fr/&gt;&lt;ref name=PCPCU-en/&gt;
# Those, like the [[Old Catholic Church|Old Catholic]], [[Anglican]], and some [[Lutheran]] and other denominations, that claim unbroken [[Apostolic Succession]] from the early Church, and see themselves as a constituent part of the Church.
# Those who claim to be spiritual descendants of the [[Twelve Apostles|Apostles]] but have no discernible institutional descent from the historic Church, and normally do not refer to themselves as catholic.
# Those who have acknowledged a break in Apostolic Succession, but have restored it in order to be in full [[Communion (Christian)|communion]] with bodies that have maintained the practice. Examples in this category include the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]] and the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in Canada]] ''vis-à-vis'' their Anglican and Old Catholic counterparts.

For some confessions listed under category 3, the self-affirmation refers to the belief in the ultimate unity of the universal church under one [[God]] and one [[soteriology|Saviour]], rather than in one visibly unified institution (as with category 1, above). In this usage, &quot;catholic&quot; is sometimes written with a lower-case &quot;c&quot;. The Western [[Apostles' Creed]] and the [[Nicene Creed]], stating &quot;I believe in ... one holy catholic ... church&quot;, are recited in worship services. Among some denominations in category 3, &quot;Christian&quot; is substituted for &quot;catholic&quot; in order to denote the doctrine that the Christian Church is, at least ideally, undivided.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lcms.org/pages/internal.asp?NavID=3355|title=Apostles' Creed|publisher=The Lutheran Church--Missouri Synod|accessdate=21 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wels.net/cgi-bin/site.pl?2617&amp;collectionID=711&amp;contentID=4334&amp;shortcutID=2077#nicene|title=Nicene Creed|publisher=Wisconsin Evangelical Lutheran Synod|accessdate=21 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=February 2010}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilflutheran.org/page11.html|title=Texts of the Three Chief Symbols are taken from the Book of Concord, Tappert edition|publisher=The International Lutheran Fellowship|accessdate=21 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Catholic Church use===
The [[Catholic Church]] considers Protestant and Anglican Christians who are not in communion with the See of Rome to be &quot;non-Catholics&quot;. It does not consider their churches to be genuine churches and so uses the term &quot;ecclesial communities&quot; to refer to them. It considers a &quot;valid episcopate&quot; and Eucharist as necessary prerequsites for being a church. Because the Roman Catholic Church does not consider these church bodies to have valid episcopal orders capable of celebrating a valid Eucharist, it does not classify them as churches &quot;in the proper sense&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fowler&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Fowler|first=Jeaneane D.|title=World Religions|publisher=Sussex Academic Press|year=1997|isbn=978-1-898723-48-6|page=82}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The ecclesial communities which have not preserved the valid Episcopate and the genuine and integral substance of the Eucharistic mystery are not Churches in the proper sense; however, those who are baptized in these communities are, by Baptism, incorporated in Christ and thus are in a certain communion, albeit imperfect, with the Church&quot; ([http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20000806_dominus-iesus_en.html [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]], Declaration ''[[Dominus Iesus]]'',] 17).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;(The expression ''[[Sister Churches (ecclesiology)|sister Churches]]'') has been applied improperly by some to the relationship between the Catholic Church on the one hand, and the Anglican Communion and non-catholic ecclesial communities on the other. ... it must also be borne in mind that the expression ''sister Churches'' in the proper sense, as attested by the common Tradition of East and West, may only be used for those ecclesial communities that have preserved a valid episcopate and Eucharist&quot; ([http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20000630_chiese-sorelle_en.html Note on the expression &quot;sister Churches&quot;] issued by the Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith on 30 June 2000).&lt;/ref&gt; Those churches not in communion with the [[Holy See]] which consider themselves to be &quot;Catholic&quot; define the word as meaning an adherence to the ancient Catholic beliefs and practices, absent any more recent addition of a requirement for union with the [[Holy See]].

====Latin and Eastern Catholic Churches====
{{Main|Catholic Church}}
The [[Latin Rite|Latin]] and [[Eastern Catholic Churches]] together form the &quot;Catholic Church&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;McBrien, ''The Church'', 356. McBrien also says they form the &quot;Communion of Catholic Churches&quot;, a name not used by the Church itself, which has pointed out the ambiguity of this term in a 1992 [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_28051992_communionis-notio_en.html letter from the Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith &quot;on some aspects of the Church understood as communion&quot;], 8.&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;Roman Catholic Church&quot;,&lt;ref name=Advanced&gt;&quot;The Catholic Church is also called the Roman Church to emphasize that the centre of unity, which is an essential for the Universal Church, is in the [[Diocese of Rome|Roman See]]&quot; ([http://books.google.com/books?id=7MQbg9j_sboC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=An+Advanced+Catechism+Of+Catholic+Faith+And+Practice#v=onepage&amp;q=Roman%20Catholic&amp;f=false Thomas J. O'Brien, An Advanced Catechism of Catholic Faith and Practice, Kessinger Publishers, 2005, ISBN 1-4179-8447-3], page 70)&lt;/ref&gt; the world's largest single religious body and the largest [[Christian church]], comprising over half of all Christians (1.1&amp;nbsp;billion Christians of 2.1&amp;nbsp;billion) and nearly one-sixth of the [[world population|world's population]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Zenit&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =Number of Catholics and Priests Rises | publisher =Zenit News Agency | date =12 February 2007 | url =http://www.zenit.org/article-18894?l=english |accessdate=21 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =CIA World Factbook | publisher =United States Government Central Intelligence Agency | year =2008 | url =https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/xx.html#People |accessdate=22 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mapping the Global Muslim Population: A Report on the Size and Distribution of the World's Muslim Population: Main Page, Pew Research Center. There are 1.5&amp;nbsp;billion Muslims, nearly a billion of whom are Sunnite (nearly 90% of Muslim population), thus the latter forming the second largest single religious body.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Todd Johnson, David Barrett, and Peter Crossing, &quot;Christianity 2010: A View from the New Atlas of Global Christianity&quot;, ''[[International Bulletin of Missionary Research]]'', Vol., 34, No.1, January 2010, pps.29-36&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard McBrien]] would put the proportion even higher, extending it to those who are in communion with the Bishop of Rome only in &quot;degrees&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Richard McBrien, ''The Church: The Evolution of Catholicism'', 6. ISBN 978-0-06-124521-3 McBrien says this: Vatican II &quot;council implicitly set aside the category of membership and replaced it with degrees.&quot; &quot;...it is not a matter of either/or—either one is in communion with the Bishop of Rome, or one is not. As in a family, there are degrees of relationships: parents, siblings, aunts, uncles, cousins, nephews, nieces, in-laws. In many cultures, the notion of family is broader than blood and legal relationships.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; It comprises 23 component &quot;[[particular church]]es&quot; (also called &quot;rites&quot; in the Second Vatican Council's Decree on the Eastern Catholic Churches),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_decree_19641121_orientalium-ecclesiarum_en.html ''Orientalium Ecclesiarum''], 2&lt;/ref&gt; all of which acknowledge a primacy of jurisdiction of the [[Bishop of Rome]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_P17.HTM |title=Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches, canon 43 |publisher=Intratext.com |date=2007-05-04 |accessdate=2011-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are in [[full communion|full]] [[communion (Christian)|communion]] with the [[Holy See]] and each other.

These particular churches or component parts are the [[Latin Rite|Latin Rite or Western Church]] (which uses a number of different [[Latin liturgical rites|liturgical rites]], of which the [[Roman Rite]] is the best known) and 22 [[Eastern Catholic Churches]]. Of the latter particular churches, 14 use the [[Byzantine Rite|Byzantine liturgical rite]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Annuario Pontificio]], 2012 edition, pages 1140–1141 (ISBN 978-88-209-8722-0).&lt;/ref&gt; Within the Church as a whole, each &quot;particular Church&quot;, whether Eastern or Western, is of equal dignity.&lt;ref&gt;''Orientalium Ecclesiarum'', 3&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, in its official documents, the Church, though made up of several particular Churches, &quot;continues to refer to itself as the 'Catholic Church{{'&quot;}}&lt;ref&gt;Thomas P. Rausch, S.J., ''Catholicism in the Third Millennium'' (Collegeville: The Liturgical Press), xii.&lt;/ref&gt; or, less frequently but consistently, as the 'Roman Catholic Church', owing to its essential&lt;ref name=Advanced/&gt; link with the Bishop of Rome.&lt;ref&gt;For example, in [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xii/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-xii_enc_12081950_humani-generis_en.html his encyclical ''Humani Generis''], 27-28 [[Pope Pius XII]] decried the error of those who denied that they were bound by &quot;the doctrine, explained in Our Encyclical Letter of a few years ago, and based on the Sources of Revelation, which teaches that the Mystical Body of Christ and the Roman Catholic Church are one and the same thing&quot;; and in [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xi/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-xi_enc_31121929_divini-illius-magistri_en.html his ''Divini Illius Magistri''] Pope Pius XI wrote: &quot;In the City of God, the Holy Roman Catholic Church, a good citizen and an upright man are absolutely one and the same thing.&quot; On other occasions too, both when signing agreements with other Churches (e.g. [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/anc-orient-ch-docs/rc_pc_christuni_doc_19711025_syrian-church_en.html that with Patriarch Mar Ignatius Yacoub III of the Syrian Orthodox Church)] and in giving talks to various groups (e.g. [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/speeches/2006/may/documents/hf_ben-xvi_spe_20060525_incontro-ecumenico_en.html Benedict XVI in Warsaw], the Popes refer to the Church that they head as the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;/ref&gt;

McBrien, in his book ''Catholicism'', disagrees with the Church's usage of referring to itself as &quot;Roman Catholic&quot;, saying: &quot;But is 'Catholic' synonymous with 'Roman Catholic'? And is it accurate to refer to the Roman Catholic Church as simply the 'Roman Church'? The answer to both questions is no. The adjective 'Roman' applies more properly to the diocese, or see, of Rome than to the worldwide Communion of Catholic Churches that is in union with the Bishop of Rome. Indeed, it strikes some Catholics as contradictory to call the Church 'Catholic' and 'Roman' at one and the same time. Eastern-rite Catholics, of whom there are more than twenty million, also find the adjective 'Roman' objectionable. In addition to the Latin, or Roman, tradition, there are seven non-Latin, non-Roman ecclesial traditions: Armenian, Byzantine, Coptic, Ethiopian, East Syrian (Chaldean), West Syrian, and Maronite. Each to the Churches with these non-Latin traditions is as Catholic as the Roman Catholic Church. Thus, not all Catholics are Roman Catholic.&quot; Thus &quot;to be Catholic—whether Roman or non-Roman—in the ecclesiological sense is to be in full communion with the Bishop of Rome and as such to be an integral part of the Catholic Communion of Churches.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Richard McBrien, ''The Church'', 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

In spite of McBrien's affirmation that, on an official level, what he calls the &quot;Communion of Catholic Churches&quot; always refers to itself as &quot;The Catholic Church&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;McBrien, ''The Church'', 351-371&lt;/ref&gt; the term &quot;Roman Catholic Church&quot; is in fact, as seen above, used by Popes and departments of the Holy See. The Latin-Rite Archdiocese of Detroit lists eight Eastern (Catholic) Churches, each with its own bishop, as having one or more parishes in what is also the territory of the Latin archdiocese, yet each is designated as being in &quot;full communion with the Roman Church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aodonline.org/AODOnline/Parish+Information+6911/Parish+Locator+7701/ParishLocator.asp?ParishLocatorPageType=EasternRite |title=Archdiocese of Detroit listing of Eastern Churches |publisher=Aodonline.org |date= |accessdate=2012-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other traditions===
{{Denominations of the United States}}
Within Western Christianity, the churches of the [[Anglican Communion]], [[Continuing Anglicanism]], the [[Old Catholic]]s, the [[Liberal Catholic Church]], the [[Apostolic Catholic Church]] (ACC), the Aglipayans ([[Philippine Independent Church]]), the [[African Orthodox Church]], the [[Polish National Catholic Church]] of America, and many [[Independent Catholic Churches]], which emerged directly or indirectly from and have beliefs and practices largely similar to [[Latin Rite]] Catholicism, regard themselves as &quot;Catholic&quot; without [[full communion|full]] [[communion (Christian)|communion]] with the Bishop of Rome, whose claimed status and authority they generally reject. The [[Chinese Patriotic Catholic Association]], a division of the [[People's Republic of China]]'s Religious Affairs Bureau exercising state supervision over mainland China's Catholics, holds a similar position, while attempting, as with Buddhism and Protestantism, to indoctrinate and mobilize for Communist Party objectives.&lt;ref&gt;Simon Scott Plummer, &quot;China's Growing Faiths&quot; in ''The Tablet'', March 2007. Based on a review of ''Religious Experience in Contemporary China'' by Kinzhong Yao and Paul Badham (University of Wales Press).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anglicanism===
{{Main|Anglicanism}}
Introductory works on Anglicanism, such as ''The Study of Anglicanism'', typically refer to the character of the Anglican tradition as &quot;Catholic and Reformed&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Fahlbusch|first=Erwin|coauthors=Geoffrey William Bromiley|others=David B. Barrett|title=The Encyclopedia of Christianity|publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing|year=2005|pages=269, 494|isbn=978-0-8028-2416-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is in keeping with the understanding of Anglicanism articulated in the [[Elizabethan Settlement]] of 1559 and in the works of the earliest standard Anglican divines such as [[Richard Hooker (theologian)|Richard Hooker]] and [[Lancelot Andrewes]]. Yet different strains in Anglicanism, dating back to the [[English Reformation]], have emphasized either the Reformed, Catholic, or &quot;Reformed Catholic&quot; nature of the tradition.

Anglican theology and ecclesiology has thus come to be typically expressed in three distinct, yet sometimes overlapping manifestations: [[Anglo-Catholicism]] (often called &quot;[[high church]]&quot;), [[Evangelicalism]] (often called &quot;[[low church]]&quot;), and [[Latitudinarianism]] (&quot;[[broad church]]&quot;), whose beliefs and practices fall somewhere between the two. Though all elements within the [[Anglican Communion]] recite the same creeds, Evangelical Anglicans generally regard the word ''catholic'' in the ideal sense given above. In contrast, Anglo-Catholics regard the communion as a component of the whole Catholic Church, in spiritual and historical union with the Roman Catholic, Old Catholic and several Eastern churches. Broad Church Anglicans tend to maintain a mediating view, or consider the matter one of ''[[adiaphora]]''. These Anglicans, for example, have agreed in the [[Porvoo Agreement]] to interchangeable ministries and full eucharistic communion with Lutherans.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Anglican-Lutheran agreement signed&quot;, ''The Christian Century'', 13 November 1996, 1005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Two Churches Now Share a Cleric&quot;, ''New York Times'', 20 October 1996, 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Catholic nature or strain of the Anglican tradition is expressed doctrinally, ecumenically (chiefly through organisations such as the [[Anglican Roman Catholic International Commission]]), ecclesiologically (through its [[Episcopal polity|episcopal governance]] and maintenance of the [[historical episcopate]]), and in liturgy and piety. Anglicans (except [[neo-evangelical]]s) maintain belief in the [[Sacraments of the Catholic Church|Seven Sacraments]]. Many Anglo-Catholics practice [[Blessed Virgin Mary|Marian devotion]], recite the [[rosary]] and the [[angelus]], practice [[Eucharistic adoration]], and seek the intercession of [[saint]]s. In terms of liturgy, most Anglicans use candles on the altar and many churches use incense and [[sanctus bell]]s in the Eucharist, which is often referred to by the Latin-derived word &quot;Mass&quot; used in the first prayer book and in the American Prayer Book of 1979. In numerous churches the Eucharist is celebrated facing the altar (often with a [[Church tabernacle|tabernacle]]) by a priest assisted by a [[deacon]] and [[subdeacon]]. Some Anglicans believe in the [[Real Presence]] of Christ in the Eucharist. However different Eucharistic rites or orders contain different, if not necessarily contradictory, understandings of salvation. For this reason, no single strain or manifestation of Anglicanism can speak for the whole, even in ecumenical statements (as issued, for example, by the Anglican - Roman Catholic International Commission).&lt;ref&gt;Rowan A. Greer, &quot;Anglicanism as an ongoing argument&quot;, ''The Witness'', May 1998, 23.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matt Cresswell, &quot;Anglican conservatives say 'second reformation' is already under way&quot;, ''The Tablet'', 28 June 2008, 32.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Philip Jenkins, &quot;Defender of the Faith&quot;, ''The Atlantic Monthly'', November 2003, 46-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

The growth of Anglo-Catholicism is strongly associated with the [[Oxford Movement]] of the 19th century. Two of its leading lights, [[John Henry Newman]] and [[Henry Edward Manning]], both priests, ended up joining the Roman Catholic Church, becoming [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinals]]. Others, like [[John Keble]], [[Edward Bouverie Pusey]], and [[Charles Gore]] became influential figures in Anglicanism. The current [[Archbishop of Canterbury]], [[Rowan Williams]], is a patron of the Anglican organisation, [[Affirming Catholicism]], a more liberal movement within Catholic Anglicanism. Conservative Catholic groups also exist within the tradition, such as [[Forward in Faith]]. There are about 80&amp;nbsp;million Anglicans in the Anglican Communion, comprising 3.6% of global Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barrett&quot;&gt;David Barrett, &quot;Christian World Communities: Five Overviews of Global Christianity, AD 1800-2025&quot;, in ''[[International Bulletin of Missionary Research]]'', January 2009, Vol. 33, No 1, pp. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protestantism===

There are Catholic groups among the traditional [[Protestant]] churches. For example, the 20th century &quot;[[High Church Lutheranism]]&quot; movement developed an [[Evangelical Catholic]]ity, combining [[justification by faith]] with Catholic doctrine on sacraments, in some cases also restoring lacking [[Apostolic Succession]], especially in Germany. Certain Lutheran churches, incluiding the [[Church of Sweden]] and several small American churches of recent origin — such as the [[Lutheran Orthodox Church]] and the [[Anglo-Lutheran Catholic Church]]- consider themselves to be Catholic.

In [[Reformed churches]] there is a [[Scottish Church Society|Scoto-Catholic]] grouping within the [[Presbyterian]] [[Church of Scotland]]. Such groups point to their churches' continuing adherence to the &quot;Catholic&quot; doctrine of the early Church Councils. The [[Articles Declaratory of the Constitution of the Church of Scotland]] of 1921 defines that church legally as &quot;part of the Holy Catholic or Universal Church&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia&quot; /&gt;

==Brief organizational history of the Church==
{{main|History of the Catholic Church}}
[[File:Rome basilica st peter 011c.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Ancient statue of [[Saint Peter]] in the Basilica dedicated to him in the [[Vatican City|Vatican]].]]
According to the theory of [[Pentarchy]], the early Catholic Church came to be organised under the three [[patriarch]]s of [[Rome]], [[Alexandria]] and [[Antioch]], to which later were added the patriarchs of [[Constantinople]] and [[Jerusalem in Christianity|Jerusalem]]. The [[Bishop of Rome]] was at that time recognized as first among them, as is stated, for instance, in canon 3 of the [[First Council of Constantinople]] (381)—many interpret &quot;first&quot; as meaning here [[first among equals]]—and doctrinal or procedural disputes were often referred to Rome, as when, on appeal by St Athanasius against the decision of the [[First Synod of Tyre|Council of Tyre (335)]], [[Pope Julius I]], who spoke of such appeals as customary, annulled the action of that council and restored Athanasius and Marcellus of Ancyra to their sees.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Catholic Encyclopedia (1913)/Pope St. Julius I|Catholic Encyclopedia, ''Pope St. Julius I'']]&lt;/ref&gt; The Bishop of Rome was also considered to have the right to convene ecumenical councils. When the Imperial capital moved to Constantinople, Rome's influence was sometimes challenged. Nonetheless, Rome claimed special authority because of its connection to [[Saint Peter]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Radeck|first=Francisco|coauthors=Dominic Radecki|title=Tumultuous Times|publisher=St. Joseph's Media|year=2004|isbn=978-0-9715061-0-7|page=79}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/_P2A.HTM#RC|title=The Hierarchical Constitution of the Church - 880-881|publisher=The Vatican|accessdate=21 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Paul of Tarsus|Saint Paul]], who, all agreed, were martyred and buried in Rome, and because the Bishop of Rome saw himself as the successor of Saint Peter.

The 431 [[First Council of Ephesus|Council of Ephesus]], the Third [[Ecumenical Council]], was chiefly concerned with [[Nestorianism]], which emphasised the distinction between the humanity and divinity of Jesus and taught that, in giving birth to Jesus Christ, the Virgin Mary could not be spoken of as giving birth to God. This Council rejected Nestorianism and affirmed that, as humanity and divinity are inseparable in the one person of Jesus Christ, his mother, the Virgin Mary, is thus [[Theotokos]], God-bearer, Mother of God. The first great rupture in the Church followed this Council. Those who refused to accept the Council's ruling were largely [[Iran|Persian]] and are represented today by the [[Assyrian Church of the East]] and related Churches, which, however, do not now hold a &quot;Nestorian&quot; theology. They are often called Ancient Oriental Churches.

The next major break was after the [[Council of Chalcedon]] (451). This Council repudiated [[Monophysitism|Eutychian Monophysitism]] which stated that the divine nature completely subsumed the human nature in Christ. This Council declared that Christ, though one person, exhibited two natures &quot;without confusion, without change, without division, without separation&quot; and thus is both fully God and fully human. The Alexandrian Church rejected the terms adopted by this Council, and the Christian Churches that follow the tradition of non-acceptance of the Council—they are not Monophysite in doctrine—are referred to as Pre-Chalcedonian or [[Oriental Orthodoxy#Oriental Orthodox Communion|Oriental Orthodox]] Churches.

The next great rift within Christianity was in the 11th century. Longstanding doctrinal disputes, as well as conflicts between methods of Church government, and the evolution of separate rites and practices, precipitated a split in 1054 that divided the Church, this time between a &quot;West&quot; and an &quot;East&quot;. [[England]], [[France]], the [[Holy Roman Empire]], [[Poland]], [[Bohemia]], [[Slovakia]], [[Scandinavia]], the [[Baltic countries]], and Western [[Europe]] in general were in the Western camp, and [[Greece]], [[Romania]], [[Russia]] and many other Slavic lands, [[Anatolia]], and the Christians in [[Syria]] and [[Egypt]] who accepted the Council of Chalcedon made up the Eastern camp. This division between the [[Western Church]] and the [[Eastern Church]] is called the [[East-West Schism]].

The fourth major division in the Church occurred in the 16th century with the [[Protestant Reformation]], after which many parts of the [[Western Church]] either entirely rejected the teachings and structure of the Western Church at that time and became known as &quot;[[Reformed]]&quot; or &quot;[[Protestantism|Protestant]]&quot;, or else repudiated papal authority and the teaching office in the Western Church for the authority of a civil ruler in religious matters (e.g., in [[Anglicanism]] and parts of the [[Lutheranism|Lutheran Church]]).

A much less extensive rupture occurred when, after the Roman Catholic Church's [[First Vatican Council]], in which it officially proclaimed the dogma of [[papal infallibility]], small clusters of Catholics in the Netherlands and in German-speaking countries formed the [[Old Catholic Church|Old-Catholic (Altkatholische) Church]].

==Distinctive beliefs and practices==
Due to the divergent interpretations of the word &quot;Catholicism&quot;, any listing of beliefs and practices that distinguish Catholicism from other forms of Christianity must be preceded by an indication of the sense employed. If Catholicism is understood as the [[Roman Catholic Church]] understands it, identification of beliefs is relatively easy, though preferred expressions of the beliefs vary, especially between the [[Latin Rite|Latin Church]], the Eastern Catholic Churches of [[Byzantine Rite|Greek tradition]], and the other Eastern Catholic Churches. Liturgical and canonical practices vary between all these [[particular Church]]es constituting the Roman and Eastern Catholic Churches (or, as Richard McBrien calls them, the &quot;Communion of Catholic Churches&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Mc Brien, ''The Church'', 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the understanding of another Church that identifies Catholicism with itself, such as the Eastern Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox Churches, clear identification of certain beliefs may sometimes be more difficult, because of the lack of a central authority like that of the Roman and Eastern Catholic Churches. On the other hand, practices are more uniform, as indicated, for instance, in the single liturgical rite employed, in various languages, within the Eastern Orthodox Church, in contrast to the variety of liturgical rites in the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. In all these cases the beliefs and practices of Catholicism would be identical with the beliefs and practices of the Church in question.

If Catholicism is extended to cover all who consider themselves spiritual descendants of the Apostles, a search for beliefs and practices that distinguish it from other forms of Christianity would be meaningless.

If Catholicism is understood in the sense given to the word by those who use it to distinguish their position from a Calvinistic or Puritan form of [[Protestantism]]   it is then meaningful to attempt to draw up a list of common characteristic beliefs and practices of Catholicism not commonly held by those merely claiming spiritual descent. Catholicism could include the Roman Catholic Church, the various Churches of Eastern Christianity, the Old Catholic Church, Anglicanism, and at least some of the &quot;independent Catholic Churches&quot; and, again in this interpretation, the beliefs and practices of Catholicism include:

* Direct and continuous organizational descent from the original church founded by Jesus{{bibleref2c|Matthew|16:18}}, who, according to tradition, designated the Apostle [[St. Peter|Peter]] as its first leader.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;And I tell you, you are Peter [Πετρός, meaning 'rock'], and on this rock I will build my church, and the gates of [[Hades]] will not prevail against it.&quot; (Mt 16:18)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Belief that Jesus Christ is Divine, a doctrine officially clarified in the [[First Council of Nicea]] and expressed in the [[Nicene Creed]].
* [[Transubstantiation]], the belief that the elements in the Eucharist become really, truly, the body, blood, soul and divinity of Christ at consecration, resulting in the Real Presence of Christ, and that, because Christ himself is present in the sacrament, he is to be honoured in it with the worship known as [[Eucharistic adoration]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P44.HTM |title=Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1418 |publisher=Vatican.va |date= |accessdate=2011-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Possession of the &quot;threefold ordained ministry&quot; of [[Bishop]]s, [[Priest]]s and [[Deacon]]s.
* All ministers are ordained by, and subject to, Bishops, who pass down sacramental authority by the &quot;laying-on of hands&quot;, having themselves been ordained in a direct line of succession from the Apostles (see [[Apostolic Succession]]).
* Belief that the Church is the vessel and deposit of the fullness of the teachings of Jesus and the Apostles from which the Scriptures were formed. This teaching is preserved in both written [[scripture]] and in unwritten [[tradition]], neither being independent of the other.
* A belief in the necessity and efficacy of sacraments.
* The use of [[crucifix|sacred images]], candles, vestments and music, and often incense and water, in worship.
* [[Veneration]] of [[Mary, the mother of Jesus]] as the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]] or [[Theotokos]] (i.e., &quot;God-bearer&quot; or &quot;Mother of God&quot;), and veneration of the saints.
* A distinction between ''adoration'' (''[[latria]]'') for God, and ''veneration'' (''[[dulia]]'') for saints. The term ''[[hyperdulia]]'' is used for a special veneration accorded to the Virgin Mary among the saints.
* The use of [[prayer for the dead]].
* The acceptance of [[canonization]]s.
* Requests to the departed saints for intercessory prayers.

===Sacraments or sacred mysteries===
{{Main|Catholic sacraments}}
{{Main|Sacred mysteries}}
{{Main|Anglican sacraments}}
Churches in the Catholic tradition administer seven [[sacrament]]s or &quot;sacred mysteries&quot;: [[Baptism]], [[Confirmation (Christian sacrament)|Confirmation]] or [[Chrismation]], [[Eucharist]], [[Penance#Sacramental penance|Penance]], [[Anointing of the Sick]], [[Holy Orders]], and [[Christian views of marriage|Matrimony]]. In some Catholic churches this number is regarded as a convention only.

In Catholicism, a sacrament is considered to be an efficacious visible sign of God's invisible [[Divine grace|grace]]. While the word ''mystery'' is used not only of these [[rite]]s, but also with other meanings with reference to revelations of and about God and to God's mystical interaction with creation, the word ''[[sacrament]]'' (Latin: ''a solemn pledge''), the usual term in the West, refers specifically to these rites.

* [[Baptism]] - the first sacrament of Christian initiation, the basis for all the other sacraments. Churches in the Catholic tradition consider baptism conferred in most Christian denominations &quot;in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit&quot; (cf. {{bibleref|Matthew|28:19}}) to be valid, since the effect is produced through the sacrament, independently of the faith of the minister, though not of the minister's intention. This is not necessarily the case in other churches. As stated in the [[Nicene Creed]], Baptism is &quot;for the forgiveness of sins&quot;, not only personal sins, but also of [[original sin]], which it remits even in infants who have committed no actual sins. Expressed positively, forgiveness of sins means bestowal of the sanctifying grace by which the baptized person shares the life of God. The initiate &quot;puts on Christ&quot; (Galatians 3:27), and is &quot;buried with him in baptism ... also raised with him through faith in the working of God&quot; (Colossians 2:12).

* [[Confirmation (sacrament)|Confirmation]] or [[Chrismation]] - the second sacrament of Christian initiation, the means by which the gift of the Holy Spirit conferred in baptism is &quot;strengthened and deepened&quot; (see, for example, ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p2s2c1a2.htm §1303]) by a sealing. In the Western tradition it is usually a separate rite from baptism, bestowed, following a period of education called [[catechism|catechesis]], on those who have at least reached the [[age of reason (canon law)|age of discretion]] (about 7)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P32.HTM |title=Code of Canon Law, canon 891 |publisher=Intratext.com |date=2007-05-04 |accessdate=2011-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and sometimes postponed until an age when the person is considered capable of making a mature independent profession of faith. It is considered to be of a nature distinct from the anointing with [[chrism]] (also called myrrh) that is usually part of the rite of baptism and that is not seen as a separate sacrament. In the Eastern tradition it is usually conferred in conjunction with baptism, as its completion, but is sometimes administered separately to converts or those who return to Orthodoxy. Some theologies consider this to be the outward sign of the inner &quot;Baptism of the Holy Spirit&quot;, the special gifts (or ''charismata'') of which may remain latent or become manifest over time according to God's will. Its &quot;originating&quot; minister is a validly consecrated bishop; if a priest (a &quot;presbyter&quot;) confers the sacrament (as is permitted in some Catholic churches) the link with the higher order is indicated by the use of chrism blessed by a bishop. (In an [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], this is customarily, although not necessarily, done by the primate of the local [[autocephalous]] church.)

* [[Eucharist]] - the sacrament (the third of Christian initiation) by which the faithful receive their ultimate &quot;daily bread&quot;, or &quot;bread for the journey&quot;, by partaking of and in the Body and Blood of [[Jesus]] Christ and being participants in Christ's one eternal sacrifice. The bread and wine used in the rite are, according to Catholic faith, in the mystical action of the Holy Spirit, transformed to be Christ's Body and Blood—his [[Real Presence]]. This transformation is interpreted by some as [[transubstantiation]] or [[metousiosis]], by others as [[consubstantiation]] or [[Sacramental Union]].

* [[Penance]] (also called [[Confession (religion)|Confession]] and Reconciliation) - the first of the two sacraments of healing. It is also called the sacrament of conversion, of forgiveness, and of absolution. It is the sacrament of spiritual healing of a baptized person from the distancing from God involved in actual sins committed. It involves the penitent's contrition for sin (without which the rite does not have its effect), confession (which in highly exceptional circumstances can take the form of a corporate general confession) to a minister who has the faculty to exercise the power to absolve the penitent,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P3F.HTM|title=Chapter II : The Minister of the Sacrament of Penance |publisher=IntraText|accessdate=21 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and absolution by the minister. In some traditions (such as the Roman Catholic), the rite involves a fourth element – satisfaction – which is defined as signs of repentance imposed by the minister. In early Christian centuries, the fourth element was quite onerous and generally preceded absolution, but now it usually involves a simple task (in some traditions called a &quot;penance&quot;) for the penitent to perform, to make some reparation and as a medicinal means of strengthening against further sinning.

* [[Anointing of the Sick]] (or Unction) - the second sacrament of healing. In it those who are suffering an illness are anointed by a priest with oil consecrated by a bishop specifically for that purpose. In past centuries, when such a restrictive interpretation was customary, the sacrament came to be known as &quot;Extreme Unction&quot;, i.e. &quot;Final Anointing&quot;, as it still is among [[traditionalist Catholics]]. It was then conferred only as one of the &quot;Last Rites&quot;. The other &quot;Last Rites&quot; are Penance (if the dying person is physically unable to confess, at least absolution, conditional on the existence of contrition, is given), and the Eucharist, which, when administered to the dying, is known as &quot;Viaticum&quot;, a word whose original meaning in [[Latin (language)|Latin]] was &quot;provision for a journey&quot;.

* [[Holy Orders]] - the sacrament which integrates someone into the Holy Orders of bishops, priests (presbyters), and deacons, the threefold order of &quot;administrators of the mysteries of God&quot; (1 Corinthians 4:1), giving the person the mission to teach, sanctify, and govern. Only a bishop may administer this sacrament, as only a bishop holds the fullness of the Apostolic Ministry. Ordination as a bishop makes one a member of the body that has succeeded to that of the Apostles. Ordination as a priest configures a person to Christ the Head of the Church and the one essential Priest, empowering that person, as the bishops' assistant and vicar, to preside at the celebration of divine worship, and in particular to confect the sacrament of the Eucharist, acting &quot;in persona Christi&quot; (in the person of Christ). Ordination as a deacon configures the person to Christ the Servant of All, placing the deacon at the service of the Church, especially in the fields of the ministry of the Word, service in divine worship, pastoral guidance and charity. Deacons may later be further ordained to the priesthood, but only if they do not have a wife. In some traditions (such as those of the Roman Catholic Church), while married men may be ordained, ordained men may not marry. In others (such as the Anglican), [[clerical marriage]] is permitted, as is the [[ordination of women]].&lt;ref&gt;In regard to the ordination of women to the episcopacy, one cannot underestimate the chasm that is currently developing between the Eastern Orthodox, Oriental and Roman Catholic Chuches, on the one hand, and the Lutheran, Anglican and Independent Catholic Churches, on the other hand. Cardinal Walter Kasper, President of the Pontifical Council for Promoting Christian Unity, for example, noted this when he addressed some Anglican bishops in 2006. Quoting St Cyprian of Carthage (d. 258), he said the episcopate is one, which means that &quot;each part of it is held by each one for the whole&quot;; that bishops were instruments of unity not only within the contemporary Church, but also across time, within the universal Church. This being the case, he continued, &quot;the decision for the ordination of women to the Episcopal office ... must not in any way involve a conflict between the majority and the minority.&quot; Such a decision should be made &quot;with the consensus of the ancient Churches of the East and West.&quot; To do otherwise &quot;would spell the end&quot; to any kind of unity. James Roberts, &quot;Women bishops 'would spell the end of unity hopes'&quot; in ''[[The Tablet]]'', 10 June 2006, 34.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, some sectors of Anglicanism &quot;in isolation of the whole&quot; have approved the [[ordination of homosexuals|ordination of openly active homosexuals]] to the priesthood and episcopacy, in spite of the support that Rowan Williams, the Archbishop of Canterbury, voiced for the Anglican Church's teaching on homosexuality, which he said the Church &quot;could not change simply because of a shift in society's attitude&quot;, noting also that those churches blessing same-sex unions and consecrating openingly gay bishops would not be able &quot;to take part as a whole in ecumenical and interfaith dialogue.&quot; Thus in ecumenical matters, only if the Roman Catholic as well as Orthodox churches come to an understanding with first tier or primary bishops of the Anglican Communion can those churches (representing 95% of global Catholicism) implement an agreement with second tier or secondary Anglican bishops and their respective Anglican communities.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rowan Williams predicts schism over homosexuality&quot; (''The Tablet'' 1 August 2009, 33).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The [[Russian Orthodox Church]], which because of the episcopal ordination of [[Gene Robinson]] severed its dialogue with the United States Episcopal Church, while declaring itself open to &quot;contacts and cooperation with those American Episcopalians who remain faithful to the gospel’s moral teaching&quot;, stated that it was willing to restore relations with those Episcopal dioceses that refused to recognize the election of [[Katharine Jefferts Schori]] as their Church's presiding bishop ([http://www.interfax-religion.com/?act=documents&amp;div=89 Letter of Metropolitan Kirill of Smolensk and Kaliningrad)].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stan Chu Ilo, &quot;An African view on ordaining Gene Robinson&quot;, ''The National Catholic Reporter'', 12 December 2003, 26.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matthew Moore, &quot;Archbishop of Canterbury foresees a 'two-tier' church to avoid gay schism&quot;, ''The Telegraph.co.uk'', 27 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Christian views of marriage|Holy Matrimony]] (or Marriage) - is the sacrament of joining a man and a woman (according to the churches' doctrines) for mutual help and love (the unitive purpose), consecrating them for their particular mission of building up the Church and the world, and providing grace for accomplishing that mission. Western tradition sees the sacrament as conferred by the canonically expressed mutual consent of the partners in marriage; Eastern and some recent Western theologians not in communion with the see of Rome view the blessing by a priest as constituting the sacramental action.

==See also==
{{Portal| Catholicism }}
* [[Four Marks of the Church]]
* [[Order (religious)|Religious Orders]]
* [[Anglican Catholic Church]]
* [[Anglican Church in North America]]
* [[Arianism]]
* [[Evangelical Catholic]]
* [[Global Anglican Future Conference]]
* [[Neo-Lutheranism]]
* [[Porvoo Agreement]]
* [[Apostolic Constitution]] [[Anglicanorum Coetibus]]
* [[Traditionalist Catholic]]
* [[Criticism of the Catholic Church]]
* [[Anti-Catholicism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* ''Without Roots: The West, Relativism, Christianity, Islam'' by Pope Benedict XVI, formerly Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger (Basic Books, 0465006345, 2006).
* ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'' English translation (Libreria Editrice Vaticana, 2000). ISBN 1-57455-110-8
* H. W. Crocker III, ''Triumph—The Power and the Glory of the Catholic Church: A 2,000-Year History'' (Prima Publishing, 2001). ISBN 0-7615-2924-1
* Leo J. Trese, ''The Faith Explained'' Third Edition (Fides/Claretian, 2001). ISBN 1-889334-29-4
* Eamon Duffy, ''Saints and Sinners: A History of the Popes'' (Yale Nota Bene, 2002). ISBN 0-300-09165-6
* K. O. Johnson, ''Why Do Catholics Do That?'' (Ballantine, 1994). ISBN 0-345-39726-6
* [[Ludwig von Pastor]], ''History of the Popes from the Close of the Middle Ages''; Drawn from the [[Vatican Secret Archives|Secret Archives of the Vatican]] and other original sources, 40 vols. St. Louis, B.Herder 1898
* ''Basic Catechism'' Seventh Revised Edition (Pauline Books &amp; Media, 1999). ISBN 0-8198-0623-4
* Peter Lynch, ''The Church's Story: A History of Pastoral Care and Vision'' (Pauline Books &amp; Media, 2005). ISBN 0-8198-1575-6
* [[Robert Ekelund|Robert B. Ekelund Jr.]] and [[Robert Tollison|Robert D. Tollison]], [http://www.themontrealreview.com/2009/Economic-Origins-of-Roman-Christianity.php ''Economic Origins of Roman Christianity''] (University Of Chicago Press, 2011)
* Robert Kugelmann, [http://www.themontrealreview.com/2009/Psychology-and-Catholicism.php ''Psychology and Catholicism: Contested Boundaries''] (Cambridge University Press, 2011)

==External links==
{{commons category|Catholicism}}
* [http://www.ecupatriarchate.org/ Ecumenical Patriarchate of Constantinople]
* [http://www.newadvent.org A library of public domain Catholic writings]

{{Christianityfooter}}
{{catholicism}}

[[Category:Ecclesiology]]
[[Category:Catholicism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic Church]]
[[Category:Christian theology]]

[[ace:Katolik]]
[[als:Katholizismus]]
[[ar:كاثوليكية]]
[[an:Catolicismo]]
[[frp:Catolicismo]]
[[az:Katolisizm]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kong-kàu]]
[[map-bms:Katolik]]
[[ba:Католицизм]]
[[be:Каталіцызм]]
[[be-x-old:Каталіцтва]]
[[br:Katoligiezh]]
[[ca:Catolicisme]]
[[cs:Katolictví]]
[[cy:Catholigiaeth]]
[[da:Katolicisme]]
[[de:Katholizismus]]
[[et:Katoliiklus]]
[[es:Catolicismo]]
[[eo:Katolikismo]]
[[eu:Katolizismo]]
[[fa:کاتولیسیزم]]
[[fr:Catholicisme]]
[[fy:Katolisisme]]
[[ko:가톨릭주의]]
[[hy:Կաթոլիկություն]]
[[hi:कैथोलिक धर्म]]
[[hr:Katoličanstvo]]
[[io:Katolikismo]]
[[id:Katolik]]
[[ia:Catholicismo]]
[[os:Католикон дин]]
[[it:Cattolicità]]
[[he:נצרות קתולית]]
[[jv:Katulik]]
[[ka:კათოლიციზმი]]
[[kk:Католицизм]]
[[ky:Католицизм]]
[[lv:Katolicisms]]
[[lb:Katholizismus]]
[[lt:Katalikybė]]
[[ln:Mumpɛ́]]
[[hu:Katolicizmus]]
[[mg:Katolisisma]]
[[mr:कॅथलिक धर्म]]
[[xmf:კათოლიციზმი]]
[[mwl:Catolicismo]]
[[mn:Католик]]
[[nl:Katholicisme]]
[[ja:カトリシズム]]
[[no:Katolisisme]]
[[nrm:Catholicisme]]
[[mhr:Католицизм]]
[[pl:Katolicyzm]]
[[pt:Catolicismo]]
[[crh:Katoliklik]]
[[ru:Католицизм]]
[[sco:Catholicism]]
[[simple:Catholicism]]
[[sk:Katolicizmus]]
[[sl:Katolištvo]]
[[sr:Католицизам]]
[[sh:Katoličanstvo]]
[[fi:Katolisuus]]
[[sv:Katolicitet]]
[[tl:Katolisismo]]
[[th:คาทอลิก]]
[[tr:Katolik]]
[[uk:Католицтво]]
[[ug:Katolik dini]]
[[vi:Công giáo]]
[[wa:Catolicisse]]
[[war:Katolisismo]]
[[yi:קאטאליציזם]]
[[zh-yue:天主敎]]
[[bat-smg:Katalėkībė]]
[[zh:天主教]]</text>
      <sha1>cf635qwe9kec4c4rzud0kovqi2yrgxc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
