<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Christian Coalition of America</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>196570</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521067971</id>
      <parentid>521067831</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T15:58:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MrX</username>
        <id>10539714</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/98.91.28.169|98.91.28.169]] ([[User talk:98.91.28.169|talk]]): Reverting inexplicable content blanking. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15215">{{dablink|For other organizations with similar names, see [[Christian Coalition]].}}
{{Infobox non-profit
| name            = Christian Coalition of America
| image           = [[File:Christian Coalition of America Logo.png|135px]]
| caption         = Christian Coalition of America Logo
| founder         = [[Pat Robertson|Marion Gordon &quot;Pat&quot; Robertson]]
| type            = non-profit 501(c)4 organization
| location        = [[Washington, D.C.]]
| coordinates     = 
| origins         =
| founded_date    = {{Start date|1989}}
| key_people      =
| area_served     = 
| products        = 
| services        =
| focus           = 
| mission         =
| method          =
| revenue         = 
| endowment       = 
| num_volunteers  = 
| num_employees   =
| num_members     =
| subsid          = 
| owner           = 
| motto           = 
| former name     =
| homepage        = {{URL|http://www.cc.org/}}
| dissolved       = 
| footnotes       = 
}}
The '''Christian Coalition of America''' ('''CCA'''), a 501(c)(4) organization, is the successor to the original Christian Coalition created in 1989 by religious broadcaster and former presidential candidate [[Pat Robertson|Marion Gordon &quot;Pat&quot; Robertson]],&lt;ref&gt;Joel D. Vaughan, &quot;The Rise and Fall of the Christian Coalition,&quot; Eugene, OR:  Wipf &amp; Stock, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and is a [[United States|US]] [[Christian]]  [[advocacy group]], which includes [[Fundamentalist Christianity|Christian fundamentalists]], [[Neo-evangelicalism|neo-evangelicals]] and conservative [[Charismatic movement|charismatics]]. While labeling itself &lt;ref&gt;Don Hodel speech, Christian Coalition Road to Victory '97, Atlanta, GA, September 13, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; as the Christian Coalition, the organization represents certain viewpoints among numbers of Christians in the United States, but Christians with other beliefs disagree with the organization's ideas. The CCA's values are consistent with those of the [[Christian right]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://content.usatoday.com/topics/topic/Christian%20Coalition%20of%20America | work=USA Today}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early Years ==
===Formation===
Following a well-funded but failed bid for the [[President of the United States|U.S. presidency]] in 1988, religious broadcaster and political commentator Pat Robertson used the remainder of his campaign resources to jump-start the creation of a voter mobilization effort dubbed the Christian Coalition. ''Americans for Robertson'' accumulated a mailing list of several million conservative Christians interested in politics. This mailing list formed the foundation for the new organization.

The coalition had four original directors, including Robertson himself, Robertson's son, Gordon Robertson, Dick Weinhold, head of the [[Texas]] organization, and [[Billy McCormack (Louisiana pastor)|Billy McCormack]], pastor of the University Worship Center in [[Shreveport, Louisiana|Shreveport]], [[Louisiana]]. McCormack had headed the Louisiana division of ''Americans for Robertson'' in 1988&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.justicetalking.org/ShowPage.aspx?ShowID=469|title=Pulpits and Politics: The Role of Religion in Elections, September 27, 2004|publisher=justicetalking.org|accessdate=June 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was also the vice president of the coalition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://demo.openlogicsys.com/cc/blog/we%C3%A2%E2%82%AC%E2%84%A2ve_come_long_way_baby_race_relations|title=We've Come a Long Way, Baby, in Race Relations, March 16, 2008|publisher=demo.openlogicsys.com|accessdate=June 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After its founding, the CCA allowed a [[grace period]] to operate as a [[501(c)|501(c)(4) tax-exempt organization]] before the [[Internal Revenue Service|IRS]] made its final determination. Forty-nine state chapters were also created as independent corporations within their states, including the Christian Coalition of Texas. A handful, including the Christian Coalition of Texas, successfully obtained non-profit status as a 501(c)(4) tax-exempt organization, while the national group's application remained pending and unresolved.

===Voter guides===
In 1990, the national Christian Coalition, Inc., headquartered in [[Chesapeake, Virginia]], began producing non-partisan voter guides which it distributed to conservative Christian churches. 40&amp;nbsp;million guides were distributed in the 1992 and 1996 presidential election years. Complaints that the voter guides were actually partisan led to the denial of the Christian Coalition, Inc.'s tax-exempt status in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/politics/daily/june99/christian11.htm | work=The Washington Post | date=June 12, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that same year, the Coalition prevailed in its five year defense of lawsuit brought by the Federal Election Commission.&lt;ref&gt;Vaughan, p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ralph E. Reed, Jr.|Ralph Reed]], a University of Georgia Ph.D. candidate and hotel waiter whom Robertson had met at an inaugural dinner for George H. W. Bush in January 1989, took control of day-to-day operations of the coalition in 1989 as its founding executive director. He remained in the post until August 1997 when he left to enter [[Partisan (political)|partisan]] political consulting, founding his new firm Century Strategies, based near Atlanta, Georgia.&lt;ref&gt;E. J. Dionne, &quot;The Religious Right Loses Its Most Skilled Tactician,&quot; (Norfolk) Virginian Pilot, April 24, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political involvement===
Robertson served as the organization's president from its founding until June 1997, when President [[Ronald Reagan|Reagan]]'s Cabinet Secretary [[Donald P. Hodel]] was named president of the CCA, and former U. S. Representative [[Randy Tate]] (R-WA) was named executive director.&lt;ref&gt;Vaughan, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Baker and Laurie Goodstein, &quot;Christian Coalition Rearranges Top Posts,&quot; Washington Post, June 12, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon announcement of Hodel becoming president of the CCA, he expressed a desire to serve the grassroots activists that made up the Coalition:  &quot;...I am here. Not only because I felt God's call on me but that I knew of God's call on you.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=September 2012}}&lt;!--needs cite because it was obviously missing a word and I had to guess what the word was. I guessed 'on' --&gt;

Washington insider and president of [[Americans for Tax Reform]], [[Grover Norquist]], an old Reed ally, said of the appointments: &quot;What you've got is Reagan and [[Newt Gingrich|Gingrich]]. Hodel is a Reagan Republican and Tate is a Gingrich Republican.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Baker and Goodstein.&lt;/ref&gt;

The CCA was ranked by ''[[Fortune (magazine)|Fortune]]'' magazine as the 7th most powerful political organization in America late in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey H. Birnbaum, &quot;Washington's Power 25,&quot; FORTUNE, December 8, 1997, pp. 144-158.&lt;/ref&gt;

After a disagreement with Robertson, Hodel left in January 1999&lt;ref&gt;Ralph Z. Hallow, &quot;Christian Coalition President Resigns,&quot; Washington Times, February 10, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; and Tate soon followed. Robertson re-assumed the presidency, and later turned it and the chairmanship over to the group's Executive Vice President and former State Chairman of South Carolina, Roberta Combs, when he officially left the Coalition in late 2001. &lt;ref&gt;Vaughan, pp. 151 - 163.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Recent Years ==
In 2000, the CCA moved from its long-standing headquarters in Chesapeake, Virginia, to a large office on Capitol Hill in [[Washington, D.C.]]. Roberta Combs, the current president and CEO, is a founding state director and has been the only woman on the board of directors for the CCA in the history of the organization. Since then, Combs installed members of her family as high-ranking officials in the group, including her daughter Michele Ammons and her son-in-law Tracy Ammons. Michele Ammons later divorced Tracy Ammons, leading to Tracy's departure.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2004/dec/02/20041202-111826-4444r/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/04/09/AR2006040901063_2.html | work=The Washington Post | first1=Alan | last1=Cooperman | first2=Thomas B. | last2=Edsall | title=Christian Coalition Shrinks as Debt Grows | date=April 10, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Combs canceled a direct-mail fund-raising campaign run by fund-raiser [[Bill Sidebottom]] of Interact Response Communications aimed at fighting child pornography after a U.S. Supreme Court ruling.{{clarify|date=September 2012}} The cancellation of the campaign in the middle of its run led to nearly a dozen lawsuits by creditors and the bankruptcy of its fund-raising company. Without a fund-raising company supporting it, the Christian Coalition went into sharp decline financially.

In March 2001, the CCA was sued U.S. District Court by its African-American employees, who alleged racial discrimination by Roberta Combs.&lt;ref&gt;See Washington Post, &quot;10 Blacks Allege Bias at Christian Coalition,&quot; March 31, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; The Washington D.C. District Court issued an injunction against the CCA and the case was later settled with money paid to the African-American plaintiffs.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thelutheran.org/article/article.cfm?article_id=4634&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/intelligence-report/browse-all-issues/2007/spring/face-right&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtontimes.com&quot;&gt;http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2005/oct/13/20051013-121940-9083r/?page=all&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.washingtontimes.com/national/default-200135222537.htm/&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2002, Roberta Combs down-sized the staff and moved the organization's offices from Washington, D.C., to a suburb of [[Charleston, South Carolina]]. The Christian Coalition was later sued for $1,890 by the moving company it used to transport itself to South Carolina because the Christian Coalition failed to pay it in full. The Christian Coalition lost in court in Richmond, Virginia, and finally paid the movers.&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtontimes.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2006/jan/19/20060119-105804-6857r/&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, the Christian Coalition's longtime law firm, Huff, Poole &amp; Mahoney PC of Virginia Beach, said it was owed $69,729. Global Direct, a fundraising firm in Oklahoma, sued for $87,000 in expenses.&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost.com&quot;/&gt;

In the years since Robertson and Reed left the group, the Coalition's influence has greatly declined under Combs. The Coalition saw a loss in revenue from a high of $26.5 million in 1996 to $1.3 million in 2004.  The organization's 2004 income tax return, (which for non-profits is made publicly available), showed the Christian Coalition to be technically bankrupt, with debts exceeding income and a negative net worth. The once prosperous group now owes more than $2 million in debt and is now under siege by lawsuits from creditors and is also struggling to hold on to state chapters.&lt;ref name=&quot;cephas-library.com&quot;/&gt;

In 2005, the Coalition finally concluded a settlement agreement with the [[Internal Revenue Service]], ending its long-running battle with that agency regarding its [[tax exempt status]].&lt;ref name=&quot;washpost06&quot;&gt;{{cite news
  | last =Cooperman
  | first =Alan
  | coauthors =Thomas B. Edsall
  | title =Christian Coalition Shrinks as Debt Grows
  | publisher =[[The Washington Post]]
  | date =2006-04-10
  | url =http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/04/09/AR2006040901063.html
  | accessdate =2007-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, the IRS has now recognized the Coalition as a 501(c)(4) tax-exempt organization, the first time in the agency's history that it has granted a letter of exemption to a group that stated in its application that it would distribute voter guides directly in churches. The consent decree enforces limitations on the terminology that may be used in the Coalition's voter guides.&lt;ref name=&quot;washpost06&quot; /&gt;

In late 2005, the Washington Post reported that the Christian Coalition was unable to pay its office postage bill to [[Pitney Bowes]], and that the Christian Coalition had not paid its new lawyers in Virginia Beach and that the law firm had also sued the Christian Coalition for its legal bills. Attempts to collect the law firm's fees in Virginia and South Carolina returned no funds of the Christian Coalition at various banks.&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtontimes.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://archive.frontpagemag.com/readArticle.aspx?ARTID=7488&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2006, the Christian Coalition of Iowa renamed itself the Iowa Christian Alliance. In splitting from the national group, the Iowa Christian Alliance cited &quot;the current problems facing the Christian Coalition of America&quot; in announcing that it had no ties to the national organization. In August 2006, the Christian Coalition of Alabama split from the national group. It later renamed itself Christian Action Alabama.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/04/09/AR2006040901063.html | work=The Washington Post | first1=Alan | last1=Cooperman | first2=Thomas B. | last2=Edsall | title=Christian Coalition Shrinks as Debt Grows | date=April 10, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cephas-library.com&quot;&gt;http://www.cephas-library.com/church_n_state/churchnstate_christian_coalition_shrinks_as_debt_grows.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2007/11/a-rebuke-of-robertson-from-iowas-powerful-christian-alliance/50934/&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2006, the president-elect of the CCA resigned his post, citing a difference in philosophy over which issues the conservative Christian organization should embrace.  [[Rev. Joel C. Hunter]], currently the senior pastor of the Northland Church in Longwood, Florida, was to assume the presidency in January. But Hunter said the Coalition's leaders resisted his calls to expand their issue base, saying the organization wouldn't allow him to expand its agenda beyond opposing abortion and same-sex marriage. Hunter also said he wanted to focus on rebuilding the Coalition's once powerful grassroots, an appeal he says board members rejected. &quot;After initial willingness to consider these changes, the board of the CCA decided, 'that is fine, but that is not who we are,'&quot; Hunter said. Combs still remains as the Coalition's president.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/28/us/28pastor.html?ref=joelchunter | work=The New York Times | first=Neela | last=Banerjee | title=Pastor Chosen to Lead Christian Coalition Steps Down in Dispute Over Agenda | date=November 28, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.cc.org/ Christian Coalition of America]

[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:Political party factions in the United States]]
[[Category:Political organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Organizations that oppose same-sex marriage]]
[[Category:Christian organizations based in the United States]]
[[Category:501(c)(4) nonprofit organizations]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1989]]
[[Category:Organizations based in Washington, D.C.]]

[[de:Christian Coalition of America]]
[[fa:ائتلاف مسیحیان برای آمریکا]]
[[fr:Christian Coalition of America]]
[[pl:Chrześcijańska Koalicja Ameryki]]
[[ru:Христианская коалиция Америки]]</text>
      <sha1>15j8qoe8tuxwfedr1r3vzefynkwgayc</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
