<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Cult</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1008588</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519470871</id>
      <parentid>519470207</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T22:31:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Florian Blaschke</username>
        <id>84755</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Stigmatization and discrimination */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52494">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2010}}
:''This article gives a general cultural account of &quot;cult&quot;. For its usage in the original sense of &quot;veneration&quot; or &quot;religious practice&quot;, see [[Cult (religious practice)]]. For its use in a scientific, sociological context see [[New religious movement]].  For other uses, see [[Cult (disambiguation)]].''

The word '''cult''' in current popular usage usually refers to a [[new religious movement]] or other group whose beliefs or practices are considered abnormal or bizarre.&lt;ref&gt;[[OED]], citing ''American Journal of Sociology'' 85 (1980), p. 1377: &quot;Cults[...], like other deviant social movements, tend to recruit people with a grievance, people who suffer from a some variety of deprivation.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The word originally denoted a system of ritual practices. The word was first used in the early 17th century denoting homage paid to a divinity and borrowed via the French ''culte'' from [[Latin]] ''cultus'' &quot;worship&quot;, from the adjective ''cultus'' &quot;inhabited, cultivated, worshipped&quot;, derived from the verb ''colere'' &quot;care, cultivate&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

In the 1930s cults became the object of sociological study in the context of the study of religious behavior.  They have been criticized by mainstream Christians for their unorthodox beliefs. In the 1970s the [[anticult movement]] arose, partly motivated by acts of violence and other crimes committed by members of some cults (notably the [[Manson Family]] and [[People's Temple]]). Some of the claims of the anti-cult movement have been disputed by other scholars, leading to further controversies.

Government reaction to cults has led to controversy. Cults have also been featured in popular culture.

==Origin==
===Origins in sociology===
{{Main|Sociological classifications of religious movements}}
The concept of &quot;cult&quot; was introduced into [[Sociology|sociological]] classification in 1932 by American sociologist [[Howard P. Becker]] as an expansion of German theologian [[Ernst Troeltsch]]'s [[Sociological_classifications_of_religious_movements#Sociological_Church-Sect_typology|church-sect typology]].  Troeltsch's aim was to distinguish between three main types of religious behavior: churchly, [[Sectarianism|sectarian]] and [[Mysticism|mystical]].  Becker created four categories out of Troeltsch's first two by splitting ''church'' into &quot;[[Christian Church|ecclesia]]&quot; and &quot;[[Religious denomination|denomination]]&quot;, and ''sect'' into &quot;[[sect]]&quot; and &quot;cult&quot;.&lt;ref name =SwatosEncy&gt;{{cite book |chapter = Church-Sect Theory |last = Swatos Jr. | first = William H. |year = 1998 |pages= 90–93 | title= Encyclopedia of Religion and Society |editors = William H. Swatos Jr. (Ed.) | publisher = AltaMira | location = Walnut Creek, CA | isbn =978-0-7619-8956-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Like Troeltsch's &quot;mystical religion&quot;, Becker's cults were small religious groups lacking in organization and emphasizing the private nature of personal beliefs.&lt;ref name =CampbellEncy&gt;{{cite book |chapter = Cult |last = Campbell. | first = Colin |year = 1998 |pages= 122–123 | title= Encyclopedia of Religion and Society |editors = William H. Swatos Jr. (Ed.) | publisher = AltaMira | location = Walnut Creek, CA | isbn =978-0-7619-8956-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Later formulations built on these characteristics while placing an additional emphasis on cults as [[deviant]] religious groups &quot;deriving their inspiration from outside of the predominant religious culture&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Richardson93|Richardson]], 1993 p. 349&lt;/ref&gt; This deviation is often thought to lead to a high degree of tension between the group and the more mainstream culture surrounding it, a characteristic shared with religious sects.&lt;ref&gt;[[#StarkBainbridge|Stark and Bainbridge]], 1987 p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologists still maintain that unlike sects, which are products of religious [[schism (religion)|schism]] and therefore maintain a continuity with [[tradition]]al beliefs and practices, &quot;cults&quot; arise spontaneously around novel beliefs and practices.&lt;ref&gt;[[#StarkBainbridge|Stark and Bainbridge]], 1987 p. 124&lt;/ref&gt;

===Popularizing the word: Anti-cult movements and their impact===
{{Main|Anti-cult movement|Christian countercult movement}} 

In the 1940s, the long held opposition by some established Christian denominations to non-Christian religions or/and supposedly [[heresy|heretical]], or counterfeit, pseudo-Christian sects crystallized into a more organized &quot;[[Christian countercult movement]]&quot; in the United States (using a doctrinal definition comparing the essential doctrines of established, Bible-based Christianity with the other groups deemed heretical).  For those belonging to the movement, all religious groups claiming to be Christian, but deemed outside of Christian [[orthodoxy]], were considered &quot;cults&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cowan2003|Cowan]], 2003&lt;/ref&gt;  

As more foreign religious traditions found their way into the United States, the religious movements they brought with them attracted even fiercer resistance.  This was especially true for movements incorporating [[mysticism|mystical]] or exotic new beliefs and those with [[charisma]]tic, authoritarian leaders. They widened their scope to also critique (from a Bible-based, traditional Christian perspective) world religions and the occult, including the eclectic New Age Movement.

In the early 1970s, a secular opposition movement to &quot;cult&quot; groups had taken shape.  The organizations that formed the secular &quot;[[Anti-cult movement]]&quot; (ACM) often acted on behalf of relatives of &quot;cult&quot; [[religious conversion|converts]] who did not believe their loved ones could have altered their lives so drastically by their own free will.  A few [[psychologist]]s and sociologists working in this field lent credibility to their disbelief by suggesting that &quot;[[brainwashing]] techniques&quot; were used to maintain the loyalty of &quot;cult&quot; members.&lt;ref name=&quot;refRichardsonIntrovigne&quot;&gt;[[#RichardsonIntrovigne|Richardson and Introvigne]], 2001&lt;/ref&gt;  The belief that cults &quot;brainwashed&quot; their members became a unifying theme among cult critics and in the more extreme corners of the Anti-cult movement techniques like the sometimes forceful &quot;[[deprogramming]]&quot; of &quot;cult members&quot; becoming standard practice.&lt;ref name =ShupeEncy&gt;{{cite book |chapter = Anti-Cult Movement |last = Shupe | first = Anson |year = 1998 |page= 27| title= Encyclopedia of Religion and Society |editors = William H. Swatos Jr. (Ed.) | publisher = AltaMira | location = Walnut Creek, CA | isbn =978-0-7619-8956-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the meantime, a handful of high profile crimes were committed by groups identified as cults, or by the groups' leaders.  The mass suicides committed by members of the [[People's Temple]] in [[Jonestown]], Guyana, and the [[Charles_Manson#The_Manson_Family|Manson Family]] [[Charles_Manson#Family_crimes|murders]] are perhaps the most prominent examples in American [[popular culture]]. The publicity of these crimes, as amplified by the Anti-cult movement, influenced the popular perception of new religious movements{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}. 

In the mass media, and among average citizens, &quot;cult&quot; gained an increasingly negative connotation, becoming associated with things like [[kidnapping]], [[brainwashing]], [[psychological abuse]], [[sexual abuse]] and other [[crime|criminal activity]], and [[mass suicide]]. While most of these negative qualities usually have real documented precedents in the activities of a very small minority of new religious groups, mass culture often extends them to any religious group viewed as culturally deviant, however peaceful or law abiding it may be.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.2307/3512241|title=Cults and Sects and Doomsday Groups, Oh My: Media Treatment of Religion on the Eve of the Millennium|author=Hill, Harvey, John Hickman and Joel McLendon|journal=Review of Religious Research|volume=43|issue=1|year=2001|pages= 24–38|jstor=3512241}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.2307/3711011|author=van Driel, Barend and J. Richardson|year=1988|title=Cult versus sect: Categorization of new religions in American print media|journal=Sociological Analysis|volume=49|issue=2|pages=171–183|jstor=3711011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|doi=10.2307/3511972|title=Definitions of Cult: From Sociological-Technical to Popular-Negative|author= Richardson, James T.|journal=Review of Religious Research|volume=34|issue=4|year=1993|pages=348–356|
publisher=Religious Research Association, Inc.|jstor=3511972}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1980s, psychologists and sociologists started to abandon theories like brainwashing and [[mind-control]]. While scholars may believe that various less dramatic [[coercion|coercive]] psychological mechanisms could influence group members, they came to see conversion to new religious movements principally as an act of a rational choice.&lt;ref name=Ayella&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1177/0002764290033005005 | author = Ayella, Marybeth | year = 1990 | title = They Must Be Crazy: Some of the Difficluties in Researching 'Cults'| journal = American Behavioral Scientist | volume = 33 | issue = 5 | pages = 562–577}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Cowan2003|Cowan]], 2003 ix&lt;/ref&gt; 

==== &quot;New religious movements&quot; ====
Most sociologists and scholars of religion also began to reject the word &quot;cult&quot; altogether because of its negative connotations in mass culture. Some began to advocate the use of new terms like &quot;new religious movement&quot;, &quot;alternative religion&quot; or &quot;novel religion&quot; to describe most of the groups that had come to be referred to as &quot;cults&quot;,&lt;ref name=Goldman&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1111/j.1468-5906.2006.00007.x | author = Goldman, Marion | year = 2006 | title = Review Essay: Cults, New Religions, and the Spiritual Landscape: A Review of Four Collections | journal = Journal of the Scientific Study of Religion | volume = 45 | issue = 1 | pages = 87–96}}&lt;/ref&gt; yet none of these terms have had much success in popular culture or in the media. Other scholars have pushed to redeem the word as one fit for neutral academic discourse,&lt;ref name = Bainbridge1996&gt;{{cite book | author=Bainbridge, William Sims | title= The Sociology of Religious Movements  | publisher=Routledge | location=New York | year=1997 | page=24 |isbn=0-415-91202-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; while researchers aligned with the Anti-cult movement have attempted to reduce the negative connotations being associated with all such groups by classifying only some as &quot;[[destructive cults]]&quot;.

==The study of cults==

While most scholars no longer refer to any new religious movements as cults, some sociologists still favor retaining the word as it was used in church-sect [[Typology (theology)|typologies]]. For this value-neutral use of the word, please refer to [[new religious movements]]. Other scholars and non-academic researchers who use the word do so from explicitly critical perspectives which focus on the relationship between cult groups and the individual people who join them.  

These perspectives share the assumption that some form of coercive persuasion or [[mind control]] is used to recruit and maintain members by suppressing their ability to reason, think critically, and make choices in their own best interest.  However, most social scientists believe that mind control theories have no scientific merit in relation to religious movements.

===Mind control===
{{Main|Mind control}}
{{POV-section|date=August 2012}}
Studies have identified a number of key steps in coercive persuasion:&lt;ref&gt;Galanter, 1989; Mithers, 1994; Ofshe &amp; Watters, 1994; Singer, Temerlin, &amp; Langone, 1990; Zimbardo &amp; leipper, 1991&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=Uy1gmwcAgg4C&amp;pg=PA46&amp;lpg=PA46&amp;dq=coercive+persuasion,+psychology&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=XAdQttkc02&amp;sig=SPrlMB_4ggub6N49xR6RTgHk3wI&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=zB0YStrjFsyYtgf0tJDsDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6#PPA46,M1 Cordón, ''Popular Psychology'' 46–47]&lt;/ref&gt;
# People are put in physically or emotionally distressing situations;
# Their problems are reduced to one simple explanation, which is repeatedly emphasized;
# They receive what seems to be unconditional love, acceptance, and attention from a charismatic leader or group;
# They get a new identity based on the group;
# They are subject to entrapment (isolation from friends, relatives and the mainstream culture) and their access to information is severely controlled.&lt;ref&gt;Psychology 101, Carole Wade et al., 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

This view is disputed by scholars such as James Gene&lt;ref&gt;Gene G. James, ''Brainwashing: The Myth and the Actuality''  [[Fordham University]] Quarterly, Volume LXI, June 1986&lt;/ref&gt; and Bette Nove Evans.&lt;ref&gt;Novit Evas, Bette ''Interpreting the Free Exercise of Religion: The Constitution and American Pluralism'', () pp.&amp;nbsp;91–3, UNC Press, ISBN 0-8078-4674-0&lt;/ref&gt; ''Society for the Scientific Study of Religion''&lt;ref&gt;Council meeting on 7 November 1990 [http://rra.hartsem.edu/sssr/SSSR/BUSINESS/90.html (Online)]&lt;/ref&gt; stated in 1990 that there was not sufficient research to permit a consensus on the matter and that &quot;one should not automatically equate the techniques involved in the process of physical coercion and control with those of nonphysical coercion and control&quot;.

===Potential for harm===
[[File:Thugs Strangling Traveller.jpg|thumb|250px|The [[Thuggee]] were a secret cult of assassins.]]
In the opinion of [[Benjamin Zablacki]], a professor of Sociology at [[Rutgers University]], groups that have been characterized as cults are at high risk of becoming abusive to members. He states that this is in part due to members' adulation of [[charismatic authority|charismatic]] leaders contributing to the leaders becoming corrupted by power. Zablocki defines a cult as an ideological organization held together by charismatic relationships and the demand of total commitment.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Zablocki, Benjamin [http://www.rci.rutgers.edu/~zablocki/] Paper presented to a conference, ''Cults: Theory and Treatment Issues'', 31 May 1997 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to Barrett, the most common accusation made against groups referred to as cults is [[sexual abuse]] (see [[Cult#Criticism by former members|some allegations made by former members]]). According to [[Reender Kranenborg|Kranenborg]], some groups are risky when they advise their members not to use regular medical care.&lt;ref name = &quot;Kranenborg-1996&quot;&gt;Kranenborg, Reender Dr. (Dutch language) ''Sekten... gevaarlijk of niet?/Cults... dangerous or not?'' published in the magazine ''Religieuze bewegingen in Nederland/Religious movements in the Netherlands'' nr. 31 ''Sekten II'' by the [[Vrije Universiteit|Free university Amsterdam]] (1996) ISSN 0169-7374 ISBN 90-5383-426-5&lt;/ref&gt; Certain cults have been accused of severely abusing children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Why Cults Terrorize and Kill Children|author=Demause, Lloyd|journal=The Journal of Psychohistory|volume=21|issue=4|year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Psychological dynamics of cult joiners===

[[Michael Langone]], executive director of the [[International Cultic Studies Association]], gives three different models for conversion. Under Langone's deliberative model, people are said to join cults primarily because of how they view a particular group. Langone notes that this view is most favored among sociologists and religious scholars. Under the &quot;psychodynamic model&quot;, popular with some mental health professionals, individuals choose to join for fulfillment of subconscious psychological needs. Finally, the &quot;thought reform model&quot; states that people do not join because of their own psychological needs, but because of the group's influence through forms of [[psychological manipulation]]. Langone claims that those mental health experts who have more direct experience with large numbers of cultists tend to favor this latter view.&lt;ref&gt;[[Michael Langone|Langone, Michael]], ''&quot;Clinical Update on Cults&quot;'', Psychiatric Times July 1996 Vol. XIII Issue 7 [http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/p960714.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some scholars favor one particular view, or combined elements of each. According to [[Marc Galanter]], Professor of Psychiatry at [[NYU]],&lt;ref&gt;Galanter, Marc (Editor), (1989), ''Cults and new religious movements: a report of the committee on psychiatry and religion of the [[American Psychiatric Association]]'', ISBN 0-89042-212-5&lt;/ref&gt; typical reasons why people join cults include a search for community and a spiritual quest. Sociologists [[Rodney Stark|Stark]] and [[William Sims Bainbridge|Bainbridge]], in discussing the process by which individuals join new religious groups, have even questioned the utility of the concept of ''conversion'', suggesting that ''affiliation'' is a more useful concept.&lt;ref&gt;Bader, Chris &amp; A. Demaris,  ''A test of the Stark-Bainbridge theory of affiliation with religious cults and sects.''  Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion, 35, 285-303. (1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1960s  sociologist [[John Lofland (sociologist)|John Lofland]] lived with [[Unification Church]] [[missionary]] [[Young Oon Kim]] and a small group of American church members in [[California]] and studied their activities in trying to promote their beliefs and win new members.  Lofland noted that most of their efforts were ineffective and that most of the people who joined did so because of personal relationships with other members, often family relationships.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hirr.hartsem.edu/ency/conversion.htm Conversion], [http://hirr.hartsem.edu/ency/Unification.htm Unification Church], ''Encyclopedia of Religion and Society'', Hartford Institute for Religion Research, [[Hartford Seminary]]&lt;/ref&gt;  Lofland published his findings in 1964 as a doctorial thesis entitled: &quot;The World Savers: A Field Study of Cult Processes&quot;, and in 1966 in book form by [[Prentice-Hall]] as ''[[Doomsday Cult: A Study of Conversion, Proselytization, and Maintenance of Faith]]''.  It is considered to be one of the most important and widely cited studies of the process of religious conversion.&lt;ref&gt;''Introduction to New and Alternative Religions in America: African diaspora traditions and other American innovations'', Volume 5 of Introduction to New and Alternative Religions in America, W. Michael Ashcraft, Greenwood Publishing Group, 2006
ISBN 0-275-98717-5, ISBN 978-0-275-98717-6,  page 180&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Exploring New Religions'',
Issues in contemporary religion, George D. Chryssides, Continuum International Publishing Group, 2001
ISBN 0-8264-5959-5, ISBN 978-0-8264-5959-6  page 1&lt;/ref&gt;

===Leaving===
There are several ways people leave a cult:&lt;ref&gt;Duhaime, Jean ([[Université de Montréal]]), ''Les Témoigagnes de Convertis et d'ex-Adeptes'' (English: ''The testimonies of converts and former followers'', an article which appeared in the book ''New Religions in a Postmodern World'' edited by Mikael Rothstein and Reender Kranenborg, RENNER Studies in New religions, [[Aarhus University]] press, 2003, ISBN 87-7288-748-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Giambalvo-PostCult&quot;&gt;[http://www.csj.org/infoserv_articles/giambalvo_carol_postcult_problems.htm Giambalvo, Carol, ''Post-cult problems'']&lt;/ref&gt;  Popular authors Conway and Siegelman conducted a survey and published it in the book ''Snapping'' regarding after-cult effects and deprogramming and concluded that people deprogrammed had fewer problems than people not deprogrammed. The [[BBC]] writes that, &quot;in a survey done by Jill Mytton on 200 former cult members most of them reported problems adjusting to society and about a third would benefit from some counseling&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/755588.stm BBC News 20 May 2000: Sect leavers have mental problems]&lt;/ref&gt;

Ronald Burks, in a study comparing Group Psychological Abuse Scale (GPA) and Neurological Impairment Scale (NIS) scores in 132 former members of cults and cultic relationships, found a positive correlation between intensity of reform environment as measured by the GPA and cognitive impairment as measured by the NIS. Additional findings were a reduced earning potential in view of the education level that corroborates earlier studies of cult critics  (Martin 1993; Singer &amp; Ofshe, 1990; West &amp; Martin, 1994) and significant levels of depression and dissociation agreeing with Conway &amp; Siegelman, (1982), Lewis &amp; Bromley, (1987) and Martin, et al. (1992).&lt;ref&gt;[http://oak.cats.ohiou.edu/~rb267689/#_Toc2952976 Burks, Ronald, ''Cognitive Impairment in Thought Reform Environments'']&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologists Bromley and Hadden note a lack of empirical support for claimed consequences of having been a member of a &quot;cult&quot; or &quot;sect&quot;, and substantial empirical evidence against it. These include the fact that the overwhelming proportion of people who get involved in NRMs leave, most short of two years; the overwhelming proportion of people who leave do so of their own volition; and that two-thirds (67%) felt &quot;wiser for the experience&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hadden, J and Bromley, D eds. (1993), ''The Handbook of Cults and Sects in America.'' Greenwich, CT: JAI Press, Inc., pp. 75–97.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to F. Derks and J. van der Lans, there is no uniform [[post-cult trauma]]. While psychological and social problems upon resignation are not uncommon, their character and intensity are greatly dependent on the personal history and on the traits of the ex-member, and on the reasons for and way of resignation.&lt;ref&gt;F. Derks and the professor of [[psychology of religion]] [[Jan van der Lans]] ''The post-cult syndrome: Fact or Fiction?'', paper presented at conference of Psychologists of Religion, [[Radboud University Nijmegen|Catholic University Nijmegen]], 1981, also appeared in Dutch language as ''Post-cult-syndroom; feit of fictie?'', published in the magazine ''Religieuze bewegingen in Nederland/Religious movements in the Netherlands'' nr. 6 pages 58–75 published by the [[Vrije Universiteit|Free university Amsterdam]] (1983)&lt;/ref&gt;

The report of the &quot;Swedish Government's Commission on New Religious Movements&quot; (1998) states that the great majority of members of new religious movements derive positive experiences from their subscription to ideas or [[doctrine]]s which correspond to their personal needs, and that withdrawal from these movements is usually quite undramatic, as these people leave feeling enriched by a predominantly positive experience. Although the report describes that there are a small number of withdrawals that require support (100 out of 50,000+ people), the report did not recommend that any special resources be established for their rehabilitation, as these cases are very rare.&lt;ref&gt;''Report of the Swedish Government's Commission on New Religious Movements (1998)'', 1.6 The need for support  [http://www.regeringen.se/info_rosenbad/departement/social/sou98_113/s98_113.pdf (Swedish)],[http://www.cesnur.org/testi/swedish.htm English translation] &lt;br /&gt;The great majority of members of the new religious movements derive positive experience from their membership. They have subscribed to an idea or doctrine which corresponds to their personal needs. Membership is of limited duration in most cases. After two years, the majority have left the movement. This withdrawal is usually quite undramatic, and the people withdrawing feel enriched by a predominantly positive experience. The Commission does not recommend that special resources be established for the rehabilitation of withdraws. The cases are too few in number and the problem picture too manifold for this: each individual can be expected to need help from several different care providers or facilitators.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:120 American pastors in front of the Moon's official residence in Cheongpyeong.jpg|thumb|250px|American pastors  of [[Sun Myung Moon|Moon]]'s [[Unification Church]] in front of the Moon's official residence in [[Cheongpyeong]].]]
[[Stuart A. Wright]] explores the distinction between the apostate narrative and the role of the apostate, asserting that the former follows a predictable pattern, in which the apostate utilizes a &quot;[[captivity narrative]]&quot; that emphasizes manipulation, entrapment and being victims of &quot;sinister cult practices&quot;. These narratives provide a rationale for a &quot;hostage-rescue&quot; motif, in which cults are likened to POW camps and deprogramming as heroic hostage rescue efforts. He also makes a distinction between &quot;leavetakers&quot; and &quot;[[Apostasy|apostates]]&quot;, asserting that despite the popular literature and lurid media accounts of stories of &quot;rescued or recovering 'ex-cultists'&quot;, empirical studies of defectors from NRMs &quot;generally indicate favorable, sympathetic or at the very least mixed responses toward their former group&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, Stuart, A., ''Exploring Factors that Shatpe the Apostate Role'', in Bromley, David G., ''The Politics of Religious Apostasy'', pp. 95–114, Praeger Publishers, 1998. ISBN 0-275-95508-7&lt;/ref&gt;

===According to the anti-cult movement===
Secular cult opponents like those belonging to the [[anti-cult movement]] tend to define a &quot;cult&quot; as a group that tends to manipulate, exploit, and control its members. Specific factors in cult behavior are said to include manipulative and authoritarian [[mind control]] over members, communal and totalistic organization, aggressive proselytizing, systematic programs of indoctrination, and perpetuation in middle-class communities.&lt;ref&gt;T. Robbins and D. Anthony (1982:283, quoted in Richardson 1993:351) (&quot;...certain manipulative and authoritarian groups which allegedly employ mind control and pose a threat to mental health are universally labeled cults. These groups are usually 1) authoritarian in their leadership; 2)communal and totalistic in their organization; 3) aggressive in their proselytizing; 4) systematic in their programs of indoctrination; 5)relatively new and unfamiliar in the United States; 6)middle class in their clientele&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;

While acknowledging the issue of multiple definitions of the word,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csj.org/infoserv_articles/langone_michael_term_cult_definitional_ambiquity.htm The Definitional Ambiguity of &quot;Cult&quot; and ICSA’s Mission]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Langone]] states that: &quot;Cults are groups that often exploit members psychologically and/or financially, typically by making members comply with leadership's demands through certain types of [[psychological manipulation]], popularly called ''mind control'', and through the inculcation of deep-seated anxious dependency on the group and its leaders.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;William Chambers, Michael Langone, Arthur Dole &amp; James Grice, ''The Group Psychological Abuse Scale: A Measure of the Varieties of Cultic Abuse'', ''Cultic Studies Journal'', 11(1), 1994. The definition of a cult given above is based on a study of 308 former members of 101 groups.&lt;/ref&gt;  A similar definition is given by [[Louis Jolyon West]]:

{{quote|A cult is a group or movement exhibiting a great or excessive devotion or dedication to some person, idea or thing and employing unethically manipulative techniques of persuasion and control (e.g. isolation from former friends and family, debilitation, use of special methods to heighten suggestibility and subservience, powerful group pressures, information management, suspension of individuality or critical judgment, promotion of total dependency on the group and fear of [consequences of] leaving it, etc.) designed to advance the goals of the group's leaders to the actual or possible detriment of members, their families, or the community.&lt;ref&gt;[[Louis Jolyon West|West, L. J.]], &amp; Langone, M. D. (1985). ''Cultism: A conference for scholars and policy makers. Summary of proceedings of the Wingspread conference on cultism, 9–11 September''. Weston, MA: American Family Foundation.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In each, the focus tends to be on the specific tactics of conversion, the negative impact on individual members, and the difficulty in leaving once [[indoctrination]] has occurred.&lt;ref&gt;A discussion and list of ACM (anti-cult movement) groups can be found at [http://www.religioustolerance.org/acm.htm http://www.religioustolerance.org/acm.htm].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism by former members==
:''See also: [[Apostasy#Other religious movements|Apostasy: Other religious movements]] and [[Anti-cult movement#Former members|Anti-cult movement: Former members]]''

The role of former members, or &quot;apostates&quot;, has been widely studied by social scientists. At times, these individuals become outspoken public critics of the groups they leave.  Their motivations, the roles they play in the anti-cult movement, the validity of their testimony, and the kinds of narratives they construct, are controversial.  Some scholars like [[David G. Bromley]], [[Anson Shupe]], and [[Brian R. Wilson]] have challenged the validity of the testimonies presented by critical former members.  Wilson discusses the use of the [[atrocity story]] that is rehearsed by the apostate to explain how, by manipulation, [[coercion]], or [[Deception|deceit]], he was recruited to a group that he now condemns.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Bryan R. ''Apostates and New Religious Movements'', Oxford, England, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; The hostile ex-members would invariably shade the truth and blow out of proportion minor incidents, turning them into major incidents.&lt;ref&gt;Melton, Gordon J., ''Brainwashing and the Cults: The Rise and Fall of a Theory'', 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

==Stigmatization and discrimination==
[[File:Anti-Aum Shinrikyo protest.JPG|thumb|250px|Anti-[[Aum Shinrikyo]] protest in Japan.]]
Because of the increasingly pejorative use of the words &quot;cult&quot; and &quot;cult leader&quot; since the cult debate of the 1970s, some academics, in addition to groups referred to as cults, argue that these are words to be avoided.&lt;ref&gt;''Pilgrims of Love: The Anthropology of a Global Sufi Cult. By Pnina Werbner. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2003. xvi, 348 pp''  &quot;...the excessive use of &quot;cult&quot; is also potentially misleading. With its pejorative connotations&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Definitions of Cult: From Sociological-Technical to Popular-Negative, James T. Richardson, Review of Religious Research, Vol. 34, No. 4 (Jun. 1993), pp. 348–356'' &quot;the word cult is useless, and should be avoided because of the confusion between the historic meaning of the word and current pejorative use&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Catherine Wessinger]] ([[Loyola University New Orleans]]) has stated that the word &quot;cult&quot; represents just as much prejudice and antagonism as racial slurs or derogatory words for women and homosexuals.&lt;ref name=Wessinger /&gt; She has argued that it is important for people to become aware of the bigotry conveyed by the word, drawing attention to the way it dehumanises the group's members and their children.&lt;ref name=Wessinger&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Wessinger
  | first = Catherine Lowman
  | authorlink = Catherine Wessinger
  | coauthors =
  | title = How the Millennium Comes Violently
  | publisher = Seven Bridges Press
  | year = 2000
  | location = New York, NY/London, UK
  | url =
  | doi =
  | isbn = 1-889119-24-5
  | page = 4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Labeling a group as subhuman, she says, becomes a justification for violence against it.&lt;ref name=Wessinger /&gt; 

At the same time, she adds, labeling a group a &quot;cult&quot; makes people feel safe, because the &quot;violence associated with religion is split off from conventional religions, projected onto others, and imagined to involve only aberrant groups.&quot;&lt;ref name=Wessinger /&gt; This fails to take into account that child abuse, sexual abuse, financial extortion and warfare have also been committed by believers of mainstream religions, but the pejorative &quot;cult&quot; stereotype makes it easier to avoid confronting this uncomfortable fact.&lt;ref name=Wessinger /&gt;

The concept of &quot;cult&quot; as a [[Pejorative|slur]] was legally tested in the United Kingdom when a protester refused to put down a sign that read, &quot;Scientology is not a religion, it is a dangerous cult&quot;, citing a 1984 high court judgment describing the organization as a cult. The London police issued a summons to the protester for violating the Public Order Act by displaying a &quot;threatening, abusive or insulting&quot; sign. The Crown Prosecution Service ruled that the word &quot;cult&quot; on a sign, &quot;...is not abusive or insulting and there is no offensiveness, as opposed to criticism, neither in the idea expressed nor in the mode of expression.&quot; There was no action taken against the protester, and police would allow future such demonstrations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/may/23/religion Schoolboy avoids prosecution for branding Scientology a 'cult'] Daily Mail, 23 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt; In Scotland, an official of the [[Politics of Edinburgh#The City of Edinburgh Council|Edinburgh City Council]] told inquiring regular protesters, &quot;I understand that some of the signs you use may display the word 'cult' and there is no objection to this.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.scotsman.com/latestnews/Protesters-celebrate-city39s-39cult39-stance.4121704.jp Protesters celebrate city's 'cult' stance] – Edinburgh Evening News, 27 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Sociologist Amy Ryan has argued for the need to differentiate those groups that may be dangerous from groups that are more benign.&lt;ref&gt;Amy Ryan: ''New Religions and the Anti-Cult Movement: Online Resource Guide in Social Sciences'' (2000) [http://rand.pratt.edu/~giannini/newreligions.html#Definitions]&lt;/ref&gt; Ryan notes the sharp differences between definition from cult opponents, who tend to focus on negative characteristics, and those of sociologists, who aim to create definitions that are value-free. The movements themselves may have different definitions of religion as well. [[George Chryssides]] also cites a need to develop better definitions to allow for common ground in the debate.

These definitions have political and ethical impact beyond just scholarly debate. In ''Defining Religion in American Law'', Bruce J. Casino presents the issue as crucial to international human rights laws. Limiting the definition of religion may interfere with freedom of religion, while too broad a definition may give some dangerous or abusive groups &quot;a limitless excuse for avoiding all unwanted legal obligations&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Casino-DefiningReligion&quot;&gt;[http://www.religiousfreedom.com/articles/casino.htm Casino. Bruce J., ''Defining Religion in American Law'', 1999]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some authors in the cult opposition dislike the word cult to the extent it implies that there is a continuum with a large gray area separating &quot;cult&quot; from &quot;noncult&quot; which they do not see.&lt;ref name = &quot;Casino-DefiningReligion&quot;/&gt; Other authors, e.g. [[Steven Hassan]], differentiate by using words and terms like &quot;[[Destructive cult]]&quot;, or &quot;Cult&quot; (totalitarian type) vs. &quot;benign cult&quot;.

==Doomsday cults==
[[File:Jonestown Memorial Service Pictures.jpg|thumb|250px|Pictures of those that died in [[Jonestown]] in 1978.]]
An additional commonly used subcategory of cult movements are the [[doomsday cults]], characterized by the central role played by [[eschatology]] in these groups' belief systems. Although most religions adhere to some beliefs about the eventual [[End time|end of the world]] as we know it, in doomsday cults, these tend to take the form of concrete prophesies and predictions of specific catastrophic events being imminent, or in some cases, even expected to occur on a particular calendar date.  

This category of religious movements includes some well-known cases of extremely destructive behavior by adherents in anticipation of the end of times, such as the mass suicide by members of the [[Peoples Temple]] in 1978, the [[Branch Davidians]] in 1993 and the [[Heaven's Gate (religious group)|Heaven's Gate]] in 1997, although many examples are known of doomsday cults that do not become nearly as destructive.  This latter class of doomsday cults are of theoretical interest to the scholarly study of cults, because of the often paradoxical response of adherents to the failure of doomsday prophesies to be confirmed.  

Social psychologist [[Leon Festinger]] and his collaborators performed a detailed case study of one such group in 1954, subsequently documented in &quot;[[When Prophecy Fails]]&quot;.  The members of a small, obscure [[UFO cult]] in question were very quick to amend their world-view so as to rationalize the unexpected outcome without losing their conviction about the validity of the underlying belief system, despite the obvious evidence to the contrary. The authors explained this phenomenon within the framework of the [[cognitive dissonance]] theory, which states that people are in general motivated to adjust their beliefs so as to be consistent with their behavior, in order to avoid the painful experience of a dissonance between the two.  

On this account, the more committed one is at the behavioral level to their beliefs being true, the more driven one is to reduce the tension created by dis-confirming evidence.  An important implication of this theory is that common, universal psychological factors contribute to the persistence of what otherwise appear to be bizarre and even absurd sets of beliefs.

==Government policy==
{{See|List of groups referred to as cults or sects in government documents}}
[[Image:Fraserport.pdf|thumb|upright|United States Congressional investigation of the [[Unification Church]], 1977-1978.]]
The difference between the negative and the neutral definition of the word cult has also had political implications. In the 1970s, the scientific status of the &quot;brainwashing theory&quot; became a central topic in U.S. court cases where the theory was instrumental in justifying the use of the forceful &quot;deprogramming&quot; of cult members.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis, 2004&quot;&gt;[[#Lewis2004|Lewis]], 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Davis1996&gt;Davis, Dena S. 1996 &quot;Joining a Cult: Religious Choice or Psychological Aberration&quot; Journal of Law and Health.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, sociologists critical of these theories assisted advocates of [[religious freedom]] in defending the legitimacy of new religious movements in court. While the official response to new religious groups has been mixed across the globe, some governments aligned more with the critics of these groups to the extent of distinguishing between &quot;legitimate&quot; religion and &quot;dangerous&quot;, &quot;unwanted&quot; cults in [[public policy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;refRichardsonIntrovigne&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Edelman&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1525/nr.2003.6.2.312 | author = Edelman, Bryan and Richardson, James T. | year = 2003 | title = Falun Gong and the Law: Development of Legal Social Control in China | journal = Nova Religio | volume = 6 | issue = 2 | pages = 312–331}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

France and Belgium have taken policy positions which accept &quot;brainwashing&quot; theories uncritically, while other European nations, like Sweden and Italy, are cautious about brainwashing and have adopted more neutral responses to new religions.&lt;ref&gt;[[#RichardsonIntrovigne|Richardson and Introvigne]], 2001 pp. 144–146&lt;/ref&gt;  Scholars have suggested that outrage following the mass murder/suicides perpetuated by the [[Order of the Solar Temple|Solar Temple]]&lt;ref name=&quot;refRichardsonIntrovigne&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Robbins2002&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1111/0021-8294.00047 | author = Robbins, Thomas | year = 2002 | title = Combating 'Cults' and 'Brainwashing' in the United States and Europe: A Comment on Richardson and Introvigne's Report | journal = Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion | volume = 40 | issue = 2 | pages = 169–76}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the more latent xenophobic and anti-American attitudes have contributed significantly to the extremity of European anti-cult positions.&lt;ref name=Beckford1998&gt;{{cite journal | author = Beckford, James A. | year = 1998 | title = 'Cult' Controversies in Three European Countries | journal = Journal of Oriental Studies | volume = 8 | pages = 174–84}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1949, the People's Republic of China has been classifying dissenting groups as ''xiéjiào''（邪教.）&lt;ref name=Irons&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1525/nr.2003.6.2.244 | author = Irons, Edward | year = 2003 | title = Falun Gong and the Sectarian Religion Paradigm | journal = Nova Religio | volume = 6 | issue = 2 | pages = 244–62}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the Chinese language, the word xiéjiào translates to &quot;Evil Religion&quot; [邪 (xié) = Evil   教 (jiào)= Religion]. The word xiéjiào as a whole is used to describe what is known in the Western world as a cult.&lt;ref&gt;Google Translate&lt;/ref&gt;  In recent years, the Chinese government has allied with Western anti-cult scholars in order to lend legitimacy to its crackdown on practitioners of [[Falun Gong]]. In 2009, Rabbi Binyamin Kluger and Raphael Aron, director of the Cult Counseling Australia, spoke at a four-day conference in southern China on cult-fighting strategies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/130012&lt;/ref&gt;  Aron is a ''[[Chabad|Lubavitch Jew]]'', a group which might be considered a cult in that its members believe their former [[rabbi]] to be the [[Messiah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/29/nyregion/messiah-fervor-for-late-rabbi-divides-many-lubavitchers.html | work=The New York Times | title=Messiah Fervor for Late Rabbi Divides Many Lubavitchers | first=Jim | last=Yardley | date=29 June 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==== Discussion ====
Sociologists critical to this negative politicized use of the word &quot;cult&quot; argue that it may adversely impact the religious freedoms of group members.&lt;ref name=Davis1996 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Richardson, 1993&quot;&gt;[[#Richardson93|Richardson]], 1993&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name =Barker2002&gt;{{cite book |chapter = Watching for Violence: A comparative Analysis of the Roles of Five Types of Cult-watching Groups |last = Barker | first = Eileen |year = 2002 |pages=  | title= Cults, Religion and Violence |editors = David G. Bromley and J. Gordon Melton (Eds.) | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | isbn =052166898}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;T. Jeremy Gunn, [http://www.law.harvard.edu/students/orgs/hrj/iss16/gunn.shtml#fn33 The Complexity of Religion and the Definition of “Religion” in International Law]&lt;/ref&gt;

In many countries, there exists a [[separation of church and state]] and [[freedom of religion]]. Governments of some of these countries, concerned with possible abuses by groups they deem cults, have taken restrictive measures against some of their activities. Critics of such measures claim that the [[counter-cult movement]] and the anti-cult movement have succeeded in influencing governments in transferring the public's abhorrence of doomsday cults and make the generalization that it is directed against all small or new religious movements without discrimination. The critique is countered by stressing that the measures are directed not against any religious beliefs, but specifically against groups whom they see as inimical to the public order due to their [[totalitarianism]], violations of the fundamental liberties, inordinate emphasis on finances, and/or disregard for appropriate medical care.&lt;ref name = &quot;Kent-Brainwashing&quot;&gt;[[Stephen A. Kent|Kent, Stephen A.]] ''Brainwashing in Scientology's Rehabilitation Project Force (RPF)'', 1997 [http://www.lermanet2.com/scientology/gulags/BrainwashinginScientology'sRehabilitationProjectForce.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

The application of the labels &quot;cult&quot; or &quot;sect&quot; to religious movements in government documents signifies the popular and negative use of the term &quot;cult&quot; in [[English (language)|English]] and a functionally similar use of words translated as &quot;sect&quot; in several European languages.&lt;ref name = &quot;Richardson01&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = [[James T. Richardson|Richardson, James T.]] and [[Massimo Introvigne|Introvigne, Massimo]] | year = 2001 | title = 'Brainwashing' Theories in European Parliamentary and Administrative Reports on 'Cults' and 'Sects'  | journal = Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion | volume = 40 | issue = 2 | pages = 143–168 | doi=10.1111/0021-8294.00046}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Robbins02&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = [[Thomas Robbins (sociologist)|Robbins, Thomas]] | year = 2002 | title = Combating 'Cults' and 'Brainwashing' in the United States and Europe: A Comment on Richardson and Introvigne's Report | journal = Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion | volume = 40 | issue = 2 | pages = 169–76 | doi=10.1111/0021-8294.00047}}&lt;/ref&gt;  While these documents utilize similar terminology they do not necessarily include the same groups nor is their assessment of these groups based on agreed criteria.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richardson01&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Robbins02&quot; /&gt; Other governments and world bodies also report on new religious movements but do not use these terms to describe the groups.&lt;ref name = &quot;Richardson01&quot; /&gt; (see: [[List of groups referred to as cults or sects in government documents]])

==In literature and popular culture==
{{Main|Cults and new religious movements in literature and popular culture}}
Cults have been a subject or theme in [[literature]] and [[popular culture]] since ancient times. There were many references to them in the 20th century.

== See also ==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;
* [[Cult suicide]]
* [[Cybersectarianism]]
* [[List of groups referred to as cults in government documents]]
* [[Religious conversion#Other religions and sects|Religious conversion]]
&lt;/Div&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*&lt;cite id = Cowan2003&gt;{{cite book | author=Cowan, Douglas E. | title= Bearing False Witness? An Introduction ot the Christian Countercult | publisher=Praeger | location=Westport, CT | year=2003 |isbn=978-0-275-97459-6}}
*&lt;cite id = Lewis2004&gt;{{Cite book | author= [[James R. Lewis (scholar)|Lewis, James R.]] | year = 2004 | title = The Oxford handbook of New Religious Movements | publisher=Oxford University Press US | isbn=0-19-514986-6}}
*&lt;cite id = Richardson93&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.2307/3511972 | author = [[James T. Richardson|Richardson, James T.]] | year = 1993 | title = Definitions of Cult: From Sociological-Technical to Popular-Negative | journal = Review of Religious Research | volume = 34 | issue = 4 | pages = 348–356 | jstor = 3511972}}
*&lt;cite id = RichardsonIntrovigne&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1111/0021-8294.00046 | author = Richardson, James T. and [[Massimo Introvigne|Introvigne, Massimo]] | year = 2001 | title = 'Brainwashing' Theories in European Parliamentary and Administrative Reports on 'Cults' and 'Sects'  | journal = Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion | volume = 40 | issue = 2 | pages = 143–168}}
*&lt;cite id = StarkBainbridge&gt;{{cite book | author=[[Rodney Stark|Stark, Rodney]] and [[William Sims Bainbridge|Bainbridge, William Sims]] | title= The Future of Religion: Secularization, Revival and Cult Formation | publisher=University of California Press | location=Berkley, CA | year=1987 |isbn=978-0-520-05731-9}}

==Bibliography==
;Books
{{refbegin}}
* [[Eileen Barker|Barker, E.]] (1989) ''New Religious Movements: A Practical Introduction'', London, HMSO
* Bromley, David et al.: ''Cults, Religion, and Violence'', 2002, ISBN 0-521-66898-0
* Enroth, Ronald. (1992)  ''[[Churches that Abuse]]'', Zondervan, ISBN 0-310-53290-6 [http://www.apologeticsindex.org/716-churches-that-abuse-online-book Full text online]
* Esquerre, Arnaud: ''La manipulation mentale. Sociologie des sectes en France'', Fayard, Paris, 2009.
* Hassan, Steve: ''Combatting Cult Mind Control'', Park Street Press, 1990, ISBN 978-0-89281-311-7
* Hassan, Steve: ''Releasing the Bonds: Empowering People to Think for Themselves'', 2000, ISBN 978-0-9670688-0-0, Freedom of Mind Press
* House, Wayne: ''Charts of Cults, Sects, and Religious Movements'', 2000, ISBN 0-310-38551-2
* Kramer, Joel and Alstad, Diane: ''The Guru Papers: Masks of Authoritarian Power'', 1993.
* Lalich, Janja: ''Bounded Choice: True Believers and Charismatic Cults'', 2004, ISBN 0-520-24018-9
* Landau Tobias, Madeleine et al. : ''Captive Hearts, Captive Minds'', 1994, ISBN 0-89793-144-0
* [[James R. Lewis (scholar)|Lewis, James R.]] ''The Oxford Handbook of New Religious Movements'' [[Oxford University Press]], 2004
* [[James R. Lewis (scholar)|Lewis, James R.]] ''Odd Gods: New Religions and the Cult Controversy'',  [[Prometheus Books]], 2001
* Martin, Walter et al.: ''[[The Kingdom of the Cults]]'', 2003, ISBN 0-7642-2821-8
* [[J. Gordon Melton|Melton, Gordon]]: ''Encyclopedic Handbook of Cults in America'', 1992 [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0815311400 (Search inside]), ISBN 0-8153-1140-0
* Oakes, Len: ''Prophetic Charisma: The Psychology of Revolutionary Religious Personalities'', 1997, ISBN 0-8156-0398-3 
* [[Margaret Singer|Singer, Margaret Thaler]]: ''Cults in Our Midst: The Continuing Fight Against Their Hidden Menace'', 1992, ISBN 0-7879-6741-6 
* Tourish, Dennis: '''On the Edge: Political Cults Right and Left'', 2000, ISBN 0-7656-0639-9
* Williams, Miriam: (1998) ''Heaven's Harlots: My Fifteen Years As a Sacred Prostitute in the Children of God Cult ''. William Morrow &amp; Co. ISBN 978-0-688-15504-9.
* [[Colin Wilson|Wilson, Colin]] ''Rogue Messiahs: Tales of Self-Proclaimed Saviors'', 2000, [[Hampton Roads Publishing Company]]. ISBN 978-1-57174-175-2
* Zablocki, Benjamin et al.: ''Misunderstanding Cults: Searching for Objectivity in a Controversial Field'', 2001, ISBN 0-8020-8188-6
{{refend}}

;Articles
{{refbegin}}
*Szubin, Jensen, Gregg (FBI) : Interacting with &quot;cults&quot; : a policing model [http://www.icsahome.com/infoserv_articles/szubin_adam_policing_model.htm]
* Hardin, John W.: Defining a Cult – The Borderline Between Christian and Counterfeit: Article defining a cult by its attributes from a Biblical Christian perspective.[http://www.gideonsword.net/WordPress/]
* Langone, Michael: Cults: Questions and Answers [http://www.csj.org/infoserv_articles/langone_michael_cultsqa.htm]
* [[Robert Jay Lifton|Lifton, Robert Jay]]: ''Cult Formation'',  ''The Harvard Mental Health Letter'', February 1991 [http://www.csj.org/infoserv_articles/lifton_robert.htm]
* Moyers. Jim: ''Psychological Issues of Former Members of Restrictive Religious Groups'' [http://home.earthlink.net/%7Ejcmmsm/article/index.html]
* Richmond, Lee J. :''When Spirituality Goes Awry: Students in Cults'', Professional School Counseling, June 2004 [http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0KOC/is_5_7/ai_n6121244]
* Robbins, T. and D. Anthony, 1982. &quot;Deprogramming, brainwashing and the medicalization of deviant religious groups&quot; ''Social Problems'' '''29''' pp 283–97.
* Shaw, Daniel: ''Traumatic abuse in cults'' [http://members.aol.com/shawdan/essay.htm]
* [[James Richardson (sociologist)|James T. Richardson]]: &quot;Definitions of Cult: From Sociological-Technical to Popular-Negative&quot; ''Review of Religious Research'' '''34'''.4 (June 1993), pp.&amp;nbsp;348–356.
* Rosedale, Herbert et al.: ''On Using the Term &quot;Cult&quot;'' [http://www.csj.org/infoserv_articles/langone_michael_term_cult.htm]
* Van Hoey, Sara: ''Cults in Court'' The Los Angeles Lawyer, February 1991 [http://www.csj.org/infoserv_articles/van_hoey_sara_cults_in_court.htm]
* [[Philip Zimbardo|Zimbardo, Philip]]: ''What messages are behind today's cults?'', American Psychological Association Monitor, May 1997 [http://www.csj.org/infoserv_articles/zimbardo_philip_messeges.htm]
* Aronoff, Jodi; Lynn, Steven Jay; Malinosky, Peter.  ''Are cultic environments psychologically harmful?'', ''Clinical Psychology Review'', 2000, Vol. 20 #1 pp.&amp;nbsp;91–111
* [[Mikael Rothstein|Rothstein, Mikael]], ''[[Hagiography]] and Text in the  [[Aetherius Society]]: Aspects of the Social Construction of a Religious Leader'', an article which appeared in the book ''New Religions in a Postmodern World'' edited by Mikael Rothstein and Reender Kranenborg, RENNER Studies in New religions, [[Aarhus University]] press, ISBN 87-7288-748-6
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{wikisource|Category:Cults}}
{{commons|Cults}}

* [http://www.cesnur.org/ CESNUR] See [[CESNUR]] (the works of some scholars in the area of new religious movements [[New religious movement|NRMs]])
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/ Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance] – articles and essays about religious groups and related subjects.
* [http://religiousmovements.lib.virginia.edu University of Virginia Religious Movements Homepage] – Website featuring the opinions and collected papers of the late sociologist [[Jeffrey Hadden]], regarding new religious movements, now edited by [[Douglas E. Cowan]]

{{New Religious Movements, Cults, and Sects}}
{{Conformity}}

[[Category:Cults| ]]
	
[[de:Sekte]]
[[es:Secta]]
[[et:Kultus]]
[[fr:Secte]]
[[ko:컬트]]
[[ia:Culto]]
[[he:כת]]
[[it:Setta]]
[[lb:Sekt]]
[[ms:Organisasi ajaran sesat]]
[[ja:カルト]]
[[pl:Sekta destrukcyjna]]
[[pt:Seita]]
[[ru:Тоталитарная секта]]
[[sl:Kult]]
[[sr:Секта]]
[[fi:Kultti]]
[[zh:邪教]]</text>
      <sha1>k2zkaoouesksapq3zfwxngoj7bdrhra</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
