<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dorje Shugden controversy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1635659</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519443205</id>
      <parentid>501913936</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T19:32:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pol098</username>
        <id>169132</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:NCCL]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="74743">{{Primary sources|date=October 2009}}
{{See|Dorje Shugden|}}
{{Tibetan Buddhism}} 
A controversy arose in the late 1970s&lt;ref name=&quot;dalailama.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.dalailama.com/page.150.htm ''The Shuk-den affair: Origins of a Controversy (Part II)''] by [[Geshe]] Georges Dreyfus, retrieved 2009-10-18.&lt;/ref&gt; when the [[14th Dalai Lama|Fourteenth Dalai Lama]] started to speak out against the [[propitiation]] of [[Dorje Shugden]], which has intensified since 1996&lt;ref&gt;von Brück, Michael (2001). &quot;Canonicity and Divine Interference&quot; in Dalmia, V., Malinar, A., &amp; Christof, M. (2001). ''Charisma and Canon: Essays on the Religious History of the Indian Subcontinent''. New Delhi: Oxford University Press. p. 331&lt;/ref&gt; when he issued an &quot;explicit ban&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Dalai Lama, direct quote in Chhaya, Mayank (2007). ''Dalai Lama: Man, Monk, Mystic''. New York: Doubleday. p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Waterhouse, Helen (2001). ''Representing western Buddhism: a United Kingdom focus''. quoted in Beckerlegge, G. (2001). ''From sacred text to internet. Religion today'', v. 1. Aldershot, Hants, England: Ashgate. p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Partridge, C. H. (2004). ''New religions: A guide : New Religious Movements, Sects, and Alternative spiritualities''. New York: Oxford University Press. p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Curren, Erik D. 2006. ''Buddha's Not Smiling: Uncovering Corruption at the Heart of Tibetan Buddhism Today''. Staunton, VA: Alaya Press. p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; suppressing the practice within the Tibetan exile community.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Richard, &amp; Mitchell, Jon (2003). ''Human Rights in Global Perspective: Anthropological Studies of Rights, Claims and Entitlements''. London: Routledge. p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Dorje Shugden]] is a [[Dharma Protector]] of the Sakya and Gelug traditions, who has been worshipped for over three hundred years.&lt;ref&gt;Dalai Lama (1996-06-16). ''His Holiness the Dalai Lama's Address to the Buddhist Society''. The Middle Way. November 1996. Vol. 7, No. 3. p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt; However, this Dharma Protector's precise nature as either an ''enlightened being'' or a ''worldly being'' has been the subject of debate among some adherents of Tibetan Buddhism since his appearance in the 17th century.

==Overview of the controversy==

The practice of [[Dorje Shugden]] (i.e. different forms of [[Buddhist devotion|worship]] and specific [[Vajrayana#Deity_yoga|meditation techniques]]) began at the time of the Fifth [[Dalai Lama]] [[Lobsang Gyatso]] (1617–1682 AD).&lt;ref&gt;rdo rje shugs ldan rtsal gyi gsol kha 'phrin las 'dod 'jo/Petition to Dorje Shugden Tsel: Granting all Desired Activities by Morchen Kunga Lhundrub&lt;/ref&gt; Those who have followed the practice of Dorje Shugden most recently in the 20th and 21st centuries include the majority of the most famous [[Gelug]] teachers, including [[Pabongka Rinpoche]], [[Ling Rinpoche]] (senior tutor of the current, [[14th Dalai Lama]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;Chryssides, George 1999 p. 239&quot;&gt;Chryssides, George (1999). ''Exploring New Religions''. London: Cassell. p. 239.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Trijang Rinpoche]] (junior tutor of the Dalai Lama), [[Zong Rinpoche]], Gangchen Rinpoche, Gonsar Rinpoche, [[Dagom Rinpoche]], [[Lama Yeshe]], [[Geshe Kelsang Gyatso]], [[Lama Zopa]], Kundeling Rinpoche, Domo Geshe Rinpoche, and [[Trijang Chocktrul Rinpoche]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://wisdombuddhadorjeshugden.org/dorjeshugden05.php#6 Talk to monks at Trijang Labrang by the Dalai Lama]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=October 2009}}

Trijang Rinpoche, the [[Guru#Guru_in_Buddhism|root Guru]] of the 14th Dalai Lama,&lt;ref name=&quot;Dalai Lama p. 26&quot;&gt;Dalai Lama, ''Union of Bliss and Emptiness'', p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; introduced the Dorje Shugden practice to the Dalai Lama in 1959 prior to the [[History_of_Tibet#Rule_of_the_Chinese_Communist_government|Chinese takeover]]. The Dalai Lama carried out the practice in private as well as encouraging it in [[Tibetan_monasteries#Kadam.2FGeluk|Gelug monasteries]].&lt;ref&gt;Waterhouse, Helen (1997). ''Buddhism in Bath: Adaptation and Authority''. University of Leeds, Department of Theology and Religious Studies. p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt; Some twenty years later, the Dalai Lama got involved in a &quot;bitter dispute&quot; with his teacher&lt;ref name=&quot;Dreyfus, Georges B. J. 2003 p. 301&quot;&gt;Dreyfus, Georges B. J. (2003). ''The Sound of Two Hands Clapping: The Education of a Tibetan Buddhist Monk''. Berkeley, Calif: University of California Press, p. 301.&lt;/ref&gt; by stating that the practice is in conflict with the state protector [[Nechung Oracle|Pehar]] and with the main protective goddess of the Gelug tradition and the Tibetan people, [[Palden Lhamo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kay, David 2004 p. 49&quot;&gt;Kay, David (2004). ''Tibetan and Zen Buddhism in Britain: Transplantation, Development and Adaptation''. RoutledgeCurzon critical studies in Buddhism. London: RoutledgeCurzon. p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; He also stated that the practice was in conflict with his eclectic religious approach as well as his political responsibilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;/&gt;

In 1976, after the publication of Zemey Rinpoche's ''The Yellow Book''—a text which contained tales of Dorje Shugden punishing those who do not follow the lineage of the [[Gelugpa]] sect exclusively and instead also listen to [[Nyingma]] teachings—the Dalai Lama, a Gelugpa himself, began to speak out against the use of the deity as an institutional protector.&lt;ref name=Mills&gt;Mills, Martin A, Human Rights in Global Perspective, [[Routledge]] ISBN 0-415-30410-5, page 56&lt;/ref&gt; He stated that individuals should decide for themselves if they wanted to practice it privately.&lt;ref name=Mills/&gt; From March 1996 onwards, the Dalai Lama decided to move more forcefully on this issue,&lt;ref name=Mills/&gt; which &quot;is to be seen in connection with his interest in finding common ground in the main schools of Tibetan Buddhism so as to overcome precisely those exclusivist tendencies that Shugden is said to protect.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;von Brück, Michael (2001). ''Canonicity and Divine Interference: The Tulkus and the Shugden-Controversy''. Quoted in Dalmia, Vasudha; Malinar, Angelika; &amp; Christof, Martin (2001). ''Charisma and Canon: Essays on the Religious History of the Indian Subcontinent''. New Delhi: Oxford University Press. p. 343.&lt;/ref&gt; By doing this, he responded &quot;to growing pressure - particularly from other schools of Tibetan Buddhism such as the Nyingmapa, who threatened withdrawal of their support in the Exiled Government project.&quot;&lt;ref name=Mills/&gt; The [[Tenzin Gyatso, 14th Dalai Lama|Dalai Lama]] stated during a Buddhist Tantric initiation that Shugden was 'an evil spirit' whose actions were detrimental to the 'cause of Tibet'.&lt;ref name=Mills/&gt; The Dalai Lama concluded that henceforth he would not give Tantric initiations to worshippers of Shugden,&lt;ref name=Mills/&gt; since &quot;the unbridgeable divergence of their respective positions would inevitably undermine the sacred guru-student relationship, and thus compromise his role as a teacher (and by extension his health).&quot;&lt;ref name=Mills/&gt; This introduces a contradiction on the Dalai Lama's part, as von Brück explains:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Many of the present Lamas of the Gelukpa tradition have received their teachings from [[Trijang Rinpoche]] or [[Zong Rinpoche]]. In those cases where he is the 'root Lama' (rtsa ba'i bla ma) who has handed down all three aspects of the tradition (oral transmission of texts, commentaries, the empowerments), the relationship to him is absolutely binding. This is an essential part of Vajrayana practice. Otherwise, according to Tantric tradition he might be regarded as a person who has broken the Tantric vow (dam-nyams) and this would concern the Dalai Lama himself as having been initiated by Shugden practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brück, Michael 2001 p. 345&quot;&gt;von Brück, Michael (2001). ''Canonicity and Divine Interference: The Tulkus and the Shugden-Controversy''. Quoted in Dalmia, Vasudha; Malinar, Angelika; &amp; Christof, Martin (2001). ''Charisma and Canon: Essays on the Religious History of the Indian Subcontinent''. New Delhi: Oxford University Press. p. 345.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

According to von Brück, after examining Dorje Shugden based on three methodological devices&amp;mdash;historical evidence, political reason, and spiritual insight&amp;mdash;the Dalai Lama changed his view and now considers Dorje Shugden to be a worldly spirit. Von Brück concludes: &quot;However, in spite of these arguments, opposition against this interpretation of the Dalai Lama and the exile government is still strong on two grounds: the truthfulness and commitments to one's root teacher, and religious freedom.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brück, Michael 2001 p. 345&quot;/&gt;

According to news reports by France 24 and Al Jazeera, the words and actions of the Dalai Lama constitute a ban on the practice.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.france24.com/en/20080808-dalai-lama-demons-india-buddhism-dorje-shugden ''The Dalai Lama's Demons''], France 24 (2008-08-08). retrieved 2009-10-24.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/peopleandpower/2008/09/200893014344405483.html ''The Dalai Lama: The devil within''], Al Jazeera's People &amp; Power, 2008-09-30, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt; Others allege that such &quot;[[Ishta-deva (Buddhism)|Deity]] discrimination&quot; is illegal according to both the [[Constitution of India]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buddhistchannel.tv/index.php?id=8,7040,0,0,1,0 ''Will the Dalai Lama return to Tibet?''] by Meindert Gorter (2008-10-29). New Statesman. retrieved 2009-10-23.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]],&lt;ref name=&quot;cesnur.org&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080430021801/http://www.cesnur.org/testi/fr99/gkg2.htm ''Open Letter to H.H. the Dalai Lama''], Geshe Kelsang Gyatso, 1997-12-09, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[Constitution of Tibet]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
All religious denominations are equal before the law. Every Tibetan shall have the right to freedom of thought, conscience and religion. These religious rights include the freedom to manifest one's belief, to receive initiation into religious traditions, practice with matters relating to religious commitment, such as preaching and worship of any religion, either alone or in community with others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/t100000_.html ''The Charter of Tibetans in-Exile''], Article 10, retrieved 2010-02-14.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Arguments for and against the practice==
===Views of the 14th Dalai Lama===
{{See|Dorje Shugden|}}
The [[14th Dalai Lama]] is asking people who want to take Tantric initiation from him to let go of the practice of Dorje Shugden,&lt;ref name=&quot;fpmt.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.fpmt.org/organization/announcements/shugden/HHDLZurich05.pdf ''Talk Given by His Holiness the Dalai Lama in Zurich''] (2005-08-12), FPMT official website. p. 1. retrieved 2009-10-23.&lt;/ref&gt; giving three main reasons:&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;&gt;[http://www.dalailama.com/page.132.htm ''His Holiness the Dalai Lama's Advice Concerning Dolgyal (Shugden)''], HH the Dalai Lama official website, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.phayul.com/news/article.aspx?id=21437&amp;article=His+Holiness+the+Dalai+Lama's+Advice+Concerning+Dolgyal+(Shugden) ''His Holiness the Dalai Lama's Advice Concerning Dolgyal (Shugden)''], 2008-05-31, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|
#The Dalai Lama identifies Dorje Shugden as a &quot;spirit&quot;, and claims that the tradition of propitiation associated with Shugden elevates this spirit to being equal or superior to the Buddha.&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;/&gt;  He states that encouraging the worship of Dorje Shugden could contribute to reducing Tibetan Buddhism to a form of superstitious spirit worship.&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;/&gt;
#The Dalai Lama states that there is an &quot;acknowledged link&quot; between worship of Dorje Shugden and sectarianism between the various Tibetan Buddhist schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;/&gt;  The Dalai Lama believes non-sectarianism is &quot;his most important commitment&quot;, and that the worship of Dorje Shugden may be a barrier to this commitment to non-sectarianism.&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;/&gt;
#The Dalai Lama says that Dorje Shugden has a long history of antagonistic attitude to the Dalai Lamas and the Tibetan Government they have headed since the time of the [[5th Dalai Lama]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;/&gt;  He identifies the 5th and 13th Dalai Lamas as having specifically spoken out against Dorje Shugden as a threat &quot;to the welfare of beings in general and the Tibetan government headed by the Dalai Lamas in particular&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;/&gt;  He states that in light of the current difficult situation endured by the Tibetan people, it is particularly important to resist the worship of Dorje Shugden as a potentially divisive practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;dlpg132&quot;/&gt;}}

The Dalai Lama stated conclusively, &quot;I have explained the reasons why I am against the veneration of Shugden and given my sources in a very detailed manner.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fpmt.org&quot;/&gt; The [[Foundation for the Preservation of the Mahayana Tradition]] (FPMT) explains the official advice of the Dalai Lama based on the three points above:

{{cquote|
The Dalai Lama has strongly urged his followers to consider carefully the problems of Dolgyal practice on the basis of these three reasons and to act accordingly. He has stated that, as a Buddhist leader with a special concern for the Tibetan people, it is his responsibility to speak out against the damaging consequences of this kind of spirit worship. Whether or not his advice is heeded, the Dalai Lama has made clear, is a matter for the individual. However, since he personally feels strongly about how negative this practice is, he has requested those who continue to propitiate Dolgyal not to attend his formal religious teachings, which traditionally require the establishment of a teacher-disciple relationship.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fpmt.org/organization/announcements/shugden/#zurich ''Collection of Advice Regarding Shugden (Dholgyal)''] by the FPMT official website. retrieved 2009-10-24.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Replies from Shugden practitioners===

Responding to the above three points, some members of the [[Western Shugden Society]] (a campaigning group established in 2008) replied:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wisdombuddhadorjeshugden.blogspot.com/2008/08/dalai-lamas-reasons-for-ban-of-dorje.html ''Dalai Lama's Reasons for the Ban of Dorje Shugden ''], Wisdom Buddha Dorje Shugden blog, 2008-08-05, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=October 2009}}
{{cquote|
#The practice of Dorje Shugden is not spirit worship because Dorje Shugden is viewed as the embodiment of [[Manjushri]], the Buddha of Wisdom and because Dorje Shugden practitioners practice the complete [[Dharma]] of [[Buddha]] [[Shakyamuni]]. Moreover, if the Dalai Lama's reason were true, it would mean that the teachings he is giving himself are non-Buddhist as many of these come from his teachers who were faithful Dorje Shugden practitioners.
#There is no evidence to support the claim that they are promoting sectarianism. All they are requesting is the freedom to practice the tradition without being ostracized. For example, regarding the Dalai Lama's public teachings, even &quot;declared non-Buddhists are permitted to attend even his most esoteric Buddhist rituals,&quot; but Buddhist Dorje Shugden practitioners are excluded.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shugdensociety.info/pdfs/BernisResearch.pdf ''Condemned to Silence: A Tibetan Identity Crisis''] by Ursula Bernis, p. 56 (Eulogy - page 22), retrieved 2009-10-24.&lt;/ref&gt;
#If another political leader were to say someone's spiritual practice was affecting the government headed by that leader and so should be stopped, this would be considered dictatorial and unacceptable. In the same way, it is not correct to say that those who pray to [[Dorje Shugden]] for the protection of their [[Dharma]] realizations in any way is detrimental to the government headed by the Dalai Lama.}}

Pro-Dorje Shugden Lamas such as Geshe Kelsang Gyatso have asked the Dalai Lama to present valid reasons supporting his claims and, in the absence of any response, have continued to engage in the practice.&lt;ref&gt;Geshe Kelsang Gyatso, [http://web.archive.org/web/20080430021801/http://www.cesnur.org/testi/fr99/gkg2.htm ''Open Letter to H.H. the Dalai Lama''], 09 December 1997&lt;/ref&gt; They continue to rely on teachers such as Trijang Rinpoche, who taught that Dorje Shugden is a Buddha. [[Trijang Rinpoche]], the junior tutor and &quot;root guru&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dalai Lama, ''The Gelug/Kagyü tradition of Mahamudra''. Ithaca, N.Y.: Snow Lion Publications (1997), p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt; of the current Dalai Lama, is seen by the [[FPMT]] and others as &quot;One of the foremost Tibetan Buddhist masters of our time&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fpmt.org/teachers/hhtrijang.asp ''His Holiness Kyabje Trijang Rinpoche''] by the FPMT. retrieved 2008-12-07&lt;/ref&gt; Remarking on this debate in his text on Dorje Shugden Trijang Rinpoche stated:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Yet all this talk is nothing but babbling speculation. Why? Because this great guardian of the [[Dharma|teachings]] is well known to be the precious supreme emanation from [[Drepung]] monastery's upper house, Dragpa Gyaltsen, arising in a wrathful aspect. The proof is unmistaken. Tulku Dragpa Gyaltsen, as is taught in the lineage, was the final birth in a reincarnation lineage that included the [[Mahasiddha]] Birwawa, the great [[Kashmir]]i [[Pandit]] Shakya Shri, the omniscient [[Buton Rinchen Drub|Buton]], Duldzin Dragpa Gyaltsen, Panchen Sonam Dragpa, and so forth; this is proven by valid scriptural quotation and reasoning. These great beings, from a definitive point of view, were already fully enlightened, and even to common appearances, every one of them was a holy being that attained high states of realization. What worse [[karma]] could there be than denying this and asserting that he was born in the [[preta]] (spirit) realm?&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dorjeshugden.com/articles/musicdelighting.pdf ''Music Delighting the Ocean of Protectors''] by Trijang Rinpoche (circa 1967), p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

McCune comments, &quot;As we see, the Shukden issue is far more complex than it appears at its surface. Both sides offer seemingly convincing arguments in favor of their respective points of view.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McCune, Lindsay G. (2007) (PDF). [http://etd.lib.fsu.edu/theses/available/etd-04092007-003235/unrestricted/lgm_thesis.pdf ''Tales of Intrigue from Tibet's Holy City: The Historical Underpinnings of a Modern Buddhist Crisis'']. Florida State University. p. 44. Retrieved 2009-10-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
=== 1970s - The Yellow Book===

{{cquote|Retrospectively, we can say that the whole affair started from this book and the Dalai Lama's reaction to it. Prior to its publication, there was no controversy concerning Shuk-den.&lt;ref&gt;''The Shuk-Den Affair: Origins of a Controversy'' (1998) by Georges Dreyfus. Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies. Vol., 21, no. 2 [1998]:227-270. retrieved 2009-03-06.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The controversy surfaced within the Tibetan exile community during the 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kay, David 2004 p. 49&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dreyfus, Georges B. J. (2003). ''The Sound of Two Hands Clapping: The Education of a Tibetan Buddhist Monk''. Berkeley, Calif: University of California Press, p. 300.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated9&gt;Mills, Martin A, Human Rights in Global Perspective, Routelidge ISBN 0-415-30410-5, page 56&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, Zemey Rinpoche published the ''Yellow Book'', which included cautionary tales passed down by Pabongkha Rinpoche and [[Trijang Rinpoche]] of 23 members of the Gelugpa sect who also practiced Nyingma teachings and were supposedly &quot;killed&quot; by Shugden.&lt;ref name=autogenerated9 /&gt;

The ''Yellow Book'' (so called because of the color of its cover) was actually entitled ''Thunder of the Stirring Black Cloud: The Oral Transmission of the Intelligent Father''. It was written by Dzeme Tulku Lobsang Palden (1927–1996) of Ganden Shartse College and published in 1974 by Chophel Legden in Delhi. This book claims to be a record of stories told to the Dzeme Rinpoche by his guru, Trijang Rinpoche, about how Dorje Shugden punished various Geluk and Nyingma lamas and others who &quot;corrupted the pure Geluk teachings,&quot; mainly by studying Nyingma teachings. According to Mumford, Dorje Shugden is &quot;extremely popular, but held in awe and feared among Tibetans because he is highly punitive.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mumford 1989:125-126&lt;/ref&gt;

Georges Dreyfus remarks that the sectarian elements of the ''Yellow Book'' were not unusual and do not &quot;justify or explain the Dalai Lama's strong reaction.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dalailama.com&quot;/&gt; Instead, he traces back the conflict more on the exclusive/inclusive approach and maintain that to understand the Dalai Lama's point of view one has to consider the complex ritual basis for the institution of the Dalai Lamas, which was developed by the Great Fifth and rests upon &quot;an eclectic religious basis in which elements associated with the Nyingma tradition combine with an overall Gelug orientation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dreyfus 1998: 269&lt;/ref&gt; This involves the promotion and practices of the Nyingma school. Kay reminds us that &quot;when traditions come into conflict, religious and philosophical differences are often markers of disputes that are primarily economic, material and political in nature.&lt;ref&gt;Kay, David (2004). ''Tibetan and Zen Buddhism in Britain: Transplantation, Development and Adaptation''. RoutledgeCurzon critical studies in Buddhism. London: RoutledgeCurzon. p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 14th Dalai Lama started to encourage the devotion to [[Padmasambhava]], for the supposed purpose of unifying the Tibetans,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shugdensociety.info/HHsWordsEN.html ''H.H. the Dalai Lama's Words in the Mirror of Reality''], Dorje Shugden Devotee's Charitable &amp; Religious Society , retrieved 2009-10-04.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=October 2009}} and &quot;to protect Tibetans from danger&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dreyfus 1998: 262&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Paul Williams (British professor)|Paul Williams]] states that &quot;The Dalai Lama is trying to modernize the Tibetans' political vision and trying to undermine the factionalism. He has the dilemma of the liberal: do you tolerate the intolerant?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Guardian, London, 6 July 1996, Shadow boxing on the path to Nirvana by Madeleine Bunting&lt;/ref&gt; Georges Dreyfus disagrees with such an interpretation:&lt;ref&gt;Dreyfus, Georges B. J. (2003). ''The Sound of Two Hands Clapping: The Education of a Tibetan Buddhist Monk''. Berkeley, Calif: University of California Press, p. 304.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
[I]n this dispute the Dalai Lama's position does not stem from his Buddhist modernism and from a desire to develop a modern nationalism, but from his commitment to another protector, [[Nechung]], who is said to resent Shukden. Thus, this dispute is not between followers of a traditional popular cult and a modernist reformer who tries to discredit this cult by appealing to modern criteria of rationality. Rather, it is between two traditional or clan-based interpretations of the Geluk tradition, that of Shukden's followers who want to set the Geluk tradition apart from others, and the Dalai Lama's more eclectic vision. The fact that the former may be more exclusivistic and that the latter may be more open does not entail that they can be interpreted adequately through the traditional/modern opposition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thlib.org/collections/texts/jiats/#jiats=/01/dreyfus/b3/#ixzz0T1qwKncA ''Are We Prisoners of Shangrila? Orientalism, Nationalism, and the Study of Tibet''] by Georges Dreyfus, JIATS, no. 1 (October 2005), THL #T1218, 21, section 3: ''The Shukden Affair and Buddhist Modernism'', retrieved 2009-10-04.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Various Shugden supporters assert that there was no factionalism before the ban, and that it is the Dalai Lama who is being intolerant and adhering to a theocratic model of government&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.citybeat.com/cincinnati/article-15996-freedom-celebration.html ''Tibet Fest Supports Endangered Tradition''] by Gregory Flannery (2008-09-18). [[Cincinnati CityBeat]]. retrieved 2009-10-23.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=October 2009}} by banning their 400-year old religious practice.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wisdombuddhadorjeshugden.org Why is the Dalai Lama suppressing religious freedom?]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=October 2009}}

=== 1996-1998 ===

In March 1996, responding to increasing political pressure (especially from the Nyingma school, who threatened to withdraw from the [[Tibetan Government in Exile|TGIE]]), the Dalai Lama announced that Dorje Shugden was &quot;an evil spirit&quot; detrimental to the cause of a free Tibet,&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Richard. ''Human Rights in Global Perspective'', Routelidge, p. 56, ISBN 0-415-30410-5&lt;/ref&gt; and so he began to request that those who worshiped Shugden no longer attend tantric initiations from him,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 192&quot;&gt;Lopez, Donald (1998). ''Prisoners of Shangri-La: Tibetan Buddhism and the West''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt; which &quot;effectively placed them outside the fold of the exiled Tibetan polity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Richard. ''Human Rights in Global Perspective'', Routelidge, p. 60, ISBN 0-415-30410-5&lt;/ref&gt; At one Tantric initiation, the Dalai Lama said:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
If any among you here are determined to continue propitiating Dolgyal, it would be better for you to stay away from this empowerment, get up and leave this place. It is improper for you to continue to sit here. It will not benefit you. On the contrary it will have the effect of reducing the life span of Gyalwa Rinpoche [the Dalai Lama], which is not good. However, if there are any among you who hope that Gyalwa Rinpoche will soon die, then you can stay.&lt;ref&gt;Dalai Lama, direct quote in Chhaya, Mayank (2007). ''Dalai Lama: Man, Monk, Mystic''. New York: Doubleday. p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In remarks to members of the Cholsum Congress on March 4, 1996, the Dalai Lama expressed satisfaction that the Congress had passed a resolution addressing the worship of Dorje Shugden, implying that Tibetan Buddhists ignoring his restrictions might hasten his own death, since &quot;then there would not be any point in my continuing to live silently as a disappointed man.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 192&quot;/&gt; The Dalai Lama's official position is that:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Propitiating Dolgyal does great harm to the cause of Tibet. It also imperils the life of the Dalai Lama. Therefore, it is totally inappropriate for the great monasteries of the Gelug tradition, the Upper and Lower Tantric Monasteries and all other affiliated monasteries which are national institutions ever to propitiate Dolgyal. The public should be thoroughly informed so that they can gain a clear appreciation of the situation themselves. However, everyone is completely free to say: &quot;If the cause of Tibet and the Dalai Lama’s life are undermined so be it. We have religious freedom. We are a democracy. We are free to do as we please. We will not change our tradition of propitiating Dolgyal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dalai Lama, direct quote in Chhaya, Mayank (2007). ''Dalai Lama: Man, Monk, Mystic''. New York: Doubleday. p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Although the TGIE said that individuals must be free &quot;to decide as they like,&quot; it asked that monks in the refugee community sign an agreement in support of the ban, in particular requesting the names of any monks at Sera monastery who continued to worship Dorje Shugden.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 192&quot;/&gt; According to Chandler, &quot;Individual monks are required to render fingerprints and signatures that demonstrate their pledge to uphold the Dalai Lama's position.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gradworks.umi.com&quot;&gt;Chandler, Jeannie M. [http://gradworks.umi.com/33/67/3367332.html ''Hunting the Guru: Lineage, Culture, and Conflict in the Development of Tibetan Buddhism in America''] (2009), p. 212&lt;/ref&gt; House to house searches were conducted by the TGIE, &quot;demanding that people sign a declaration&quot; that they had abandoned the practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chryssides, George 1999 p. 239&quot;/&gt; The TGIE passed a resolution forbidding governmental and monastic institutions from propitiating Dorje Shugden:&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 192&quot;/&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
In sum, the departments, their branches and subsidiaries, monasteries and their branches that are functioning under the administrative control of the Tibetan Government-in-Exile should be strictly instructed, in accordance with the rules and regulations, not to indulge in the propitiation of Shugden. We would like to clarify that if individual citizens propitiate Shugden, it will harm the common interest of Tibet, the life of His Holiness the Dalai Lama and strengthen the spirits that are against the religion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dalailama.com/messages/dolgyal-shugden/atpd-resolutions The Assembly of Tibetan People's Deputies' Resolutions - Resolutions Passed Unanimously in June 1996. (Parliament in Exile)], accessed 2010-0522.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Previously confined primarily to the Tibetan exile community, the dispute over Dorje Shugden developed international dimensions that same year, when the British-based [[New Kadampa Tradition]] (NKT) began to publicly oppose the Dalai Lama's position.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 193&quot;&gt;Lopez, Donald (1998). ''Prisoners of Shangri-La: Tibetan Buddhism and the West''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt; Geshe Kelsang Gyatso, founder of the New Kadampa Tradition, was a devotee of Shugden, and the nephew of a man who had previously served as a medium for Shugden in Tibetan refugee communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 193&quot;/&gt; Unlike other Gelug teachers, some of whom privately worshiped Shugden but did not teach the practice to their Western students, Gyatso made Shugden practices central to the teachings he imparted to non-Tibetan students in England and abroad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 193&quot;/&gt;

When the Dalai Lama visited England later in the summer of 1996, members of the New Kadampa tradition staged pickets outside venues where the Dalai Lama was speaking, holding placards accusing the Dalai Lama of repressing religious freedom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 193&quot;/&gt; At the time, the NKT was the largest Buddhist organization in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 194&quot;&gt;Lopez, Donald (1998). ''Prisoners of Shangri-La: Tibetan Buddhism and the West''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; Gyatso also founded the Shugden Supporters Community (SSC), which distributed press releases to news outlets covering the Dalai Lama's trip to England.&lt;ref&gt;Lopez, Donald (1998). ''Prisoners of Shangri-La: Tibetan Buddhism and the West''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. pp. 193-194.&lt;/ref&gt; The SSC also initiated a letter-writing campaign to petition the British Home Secretary to revoke the Dalai Lama's visa.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 195&quot;&gt;Lopez, Donald (1998). ''Prisoners of Shangri-La: Tibetan Buddhism and the West''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1996, Sera Je monastery in India formally expelled Kelsang Gyatso, citing his opposition to the Dalai Lama.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 195&quot;/&gt;

The NKT claimed that the Dalai Lama's remarks had inspired the harassment of Dorje Shugden worshippers among the Tibetan exile community in India.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsweekApril281997&quot;/&gt; Martin Mills, a lecturer in Religious Studies at the [[University of Aberdeen]], observed while in India that those who did not worship Dorje Shugden seemed to feel that they should &quot;endeavor to eradicate its practice amongst their peers, neighbors and co-workers ''as an act of loyalty to the Dalai Lama''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Richard. ''Human Rights in Global Perspective'', Routelidge, p. 61, emphasis in original, ISBN 0-415-30410-5&lt;/ref&gt;  The alleged abuses included searches of the homes and temples of Shugden devotees, and the destruction of images of Dorje Shugden.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsweekApril281997&quot;/&gt; In 1996, the TGIE began a campaign to &quot;subdue Dorje Shugden propitiation amongst government employees and Gelug monasteries.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kay, David. N. (2004). ''Tibetan and Zen Buddhism in Britain: Transplantation, Development and Adaptation''. RoutledgeCurzon critical studies in Buddhism. London: RoutledgeCurzon. p. 104&lt;/ref&gt; Speaking to the press in England, the SSC therefore stated that Shugden worshippers had been dismissed from their jobs and expelled from monasteries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 194&quot;/&gt;

The numerous denials on the part of TGIE officials between 1996 and 1998 of any kind of &quot;ban&quot; on Dorje Shugden practice were &quot;clearly&quot; and &quot;in all probability simply disingenuous,&quot; according to Martin Mills.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Richard. ''Human Rights in Global Perspective'', Routelidge, pp. 60, 61, ISBN 0-415-30410-5&lt;/ref&gt; Chandler adds that &quot;despite the government's insistence that the Dalai Lama's decree does not constitute a &quot;ban,&quot; it is important to note that those who choose to worship Shugden against the wishes of the Dalai Lama and mainstream Tibetan society become virtual outcasts.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gradworks.umi.com&quot;/&gt;

A Swiss TV documentary made in 1997 paints an even grimmer picture. The documentary shows evidence of violence and even death threats towards Dorje Shugden practitioners with [[wanted posters]] of Dorje Shugden adherents being posted in Dharamsala, encouraging violence towards practitioners.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n5sOm-uQH9Y ''Dalai Lama / Dorje Shugden''] (Part 2 of 3, 2:36-3:00), SF1 - Swiss Public Television, 1998-01-05, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n5sOm-uQH9Y ''Dalai Lama / Dorje Shugden''] (Part 3 of 3, 0:01-0:40), SF1 - Swiss Public Television, 1998-01-05, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt; After protests from viewers and especially the Tibetan exile community in Switzerland, the channel broadcast another documentary in which it painted a more balanced picture, retracting some of the statements and impressions left by the first documentary (e.g. the existence of wanted posters).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tibetonline.tv/videos/57/shugden-issue-on-swiss-tv Video]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Sara Chamberlain in the New Internationalist, in 1996 the Dalai Lama announced that worship of Dorje Shugden was banned and explained that the Tibetan state oracle, [[Nechung]], had advised him that the deity was a threat to his personal safety and the future of Tibet.&lt;ref&gt;Deity banned, Outrage as Dalai Lama denounces Dorje Shugden &quot;http://www.newint.org/issue304/update.htm&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=October 2009}} The Dalai Lama stated in 1996: &quot;All final decisions have been concluded only through divination.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://wisdombuddhadorjeshugden.org/dalailamaspeech.pdf Address delivered by the Dalai Lama at the preparatory session of Tamdrin Yangsang and Sangdrub empowerments, March 21 1996, page 4]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=October 2009}} Thus, the belief that Dorje Shugden is a threat to the Dalai Lama and to Tibet is directly attributable to an [[oracle]] in a trance.&lt;ref name=&quot;newint.org&quot;/&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=October 2009}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Chryssides, George 1999 p. 239&quot;/&gt;

Yet the 14th Dalai Lama has gone on record saying that oracles have &quot;nothing to do with Buddhism...they should be looked upon as a manifestation of popular superstition.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Grunfeld, ''The Making of Modern Tibet'', 28.&lt;/ref&gt; He was also quoted in 1971 saying: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;
This has nothing to do with Buddhism.  The oracles are absolutely without importance.  They are only small tree-spirits.  They do not belong to the three treasures of Buddhism.  Relations with them are of no help for our next incarnation.  They should be looked upon as manifestations of popular superstition which is deleterious to the health of human beings.&lt;ref&gt;Prince Peter of Greece and Denmark, &quot;Tibetan Oracles,&quot; in ''Himalayan Anthropology, The Indo-Tibetan Interface'' by James F. Fisher (The Hague: Mouton Publishers, 1978), 287&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Nechung oracle has a history of false prophecies, including the repeated prophecy that Tibet would gain independence within a few years&lt;ref&gt;Prince Peter of Greece and Denmark, quoted in Norbu, ''Shadow Tibet'', 290-1&lt;/ref&gt; and also contributed toward the bungling surrounding the recognition of the reincarnation of the Panchen Lama.&lt;ref&gt;Tibet in Exile, http://dorjeshugden.com/articles/TibetinExile.pdf (accessed September 15, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;

The Nechung oracle is not the only means by which the Dalai Lama makes his decisions.  He openly admits that he uses dough-balls,&lt;ref&gt;Dorjee Tseten, &quot;Tibetan Art of Divination,&quot; ''The Government of Tibet in Exile website (Tibetan Bulletin, March–April 1995),&quot; http://www.tibet.com/Buddhism/divination.html (accessed September 22, 2009).&lt;/ref&gt; dice and dreams to help make important decisions.  He is also quoted as saying:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I conducted a dough-ball examination and dice divination, which were so convincing that since 1975 I have completely stopped this practice [of Dorje Shugden].  I have not even had a portentous dream to make me wonder if the deity is vexed.&lt;ref&gt;Fourteenth Dalai Lama, ''Talk at Sera Monastery'', 1980.  The Dalai Lama also mentions making decisions by using oracles, dream and divination by dough-balls in ''A Talk Concerning Shugden Practice'', July 13, 1978, from ''An Anthology of Talks Given by His Holiness The Dalai Lama Concerning Reliance Upon the Dharma Protectors'' (LTWA, Dharamsala).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In India, some protests and opposition were organised by the Dorje Shugden Religious and Charitable Society with the support of the SSC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.friendsoftibet.org/databank/indiageneral/indiag1.html ''Allegations of Religious Persecution''] by Dorje Shugden Devotees Charitable and Religious Society and Shugden Supporters Community (Delhi), 1996-06-19, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=October 2009}} In, 1996 the SSC attempted to obtain a statement from [[Amnesty International|Amnesty International (AI)]] that the TGIE (specifically the [[14th Dalai Lama]]) had violated [[human rights]]. However, the AI replied that the SSC's allegations were as yet unsubstantiated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lopez, Donald 1998 p. 194&quot;/&gt; Two years later, the AI stated in an official press release that complaints by Shugden practitioners fell outside its purview of &quot;grave violations of fundamental human rights&quot; (such as torture, the death penalty, extrajudicial executions, arbitrary detention or imprisonment, or unfair trials), adding that &quot;while recognizing that a spiritual debate can be contentious, [we] cannot become involved in debate on spiritual issues.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Amnesty International's position on alleged abuses against worshippers of Tibetan deity Dorje Shugden'', AI Index 17/14/98, 1998-06, quoted in [http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1824531,00.html ''The Dalai Lama's Buddhist Foes''] by David Van Biema (2008-07-18), retrieved 2009-10-31.&lt;/ref&gt; In itself, the nuanced statement neither asserted nor denied the validity of the claims made against the TGIE, just that they were not actionable according to AI's mandate.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, Richard. ''Human Rights in Global Perspective'', Routelidge, p. 57, ISBN 0-415-30410-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, Jeannie M. [http://gradworks.umi.com/33/67/3367332.html ''Hunting the Guru: Lineage, Culture, and Conflict in the Development of Tibetan Buddhism in America''] (2009), p. 211&lt;/ref&gt; While the AI report effectively exonerated the TGIE of human rights abuses, Jane Ardley comments that the Dalai Lama ''was'' at fault for using his political authority to infringe upon others' religious freedom,&lt;ref&gt;Ardley, Jane (2002). ''The Tibetan Independence Movement: Political, Religious and Gandhian Perspectives''. London: RoutledgeCurzon. p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; saying that &quot;While the Dalai Lama's stated concern,&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, Jeannie M. [http://gradworks.umi.com/33/67/3367332.html ''Hunting the Guru: Lineage, Culture, and Conflict in the Development of Tibetan Buddhism in America''] (2009), p. 207&lt;/ref&gt; that worship of the deity threatened the Tibetan struggle, is entirely valid from a political perspective, this was not cause enough to ban it as a religious practice... The Dalai Lama used his political authority to deal with what was and should have remained a purely religious issue.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ardley, Jane (2002). ''The Tibetan Independence Movement: Political, Religious and Gandhian Perspectives''. London: RoutledgeCurzon. pp. 175, 176.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2008-present ===
The Dalai Lama has recently stated: &quot;I have meditated and considered (my decision to put aside the Shugden) at length in my soul and spirit before coming to the right decision” and continued: &quot;People have killed, lied, fought each other and set things alight in the name of this deity. These monks must be expelled from all monasteries. If they are not happy, you can tell them that the Dalai Lama himself asked that this be done, and it is very urgent&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.france24.com/en/20080808-dalai-lama-demons-india-buddhism-dorje-shugden ''The Dalai Lama's Demons''] (4:24-4:41), France 24 (2008-08-08). retrieved 2009-10-24.&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Recently monasteries have fearlessly expelled Shugden monks where needed. I fully support their actions. I praise them. If monasteries find taking action hard, tell them the Dalai Lama is responsible for this.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/peopleandpower/2008/09/200893014344405483.html ''The Dalai Lama: The Devil Within''] (3:33-3:49), Al Jazeera's People &amp; Power, 2008-09-30, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

The opening address of the fifth session of the [[Tibetan Parliament in Exile]] (TPiE), which began on March 4, 2008, was delivered by Karma Chophel. According to the official website of the TGIE, he lauded the bold initiative of Tibetan monastic communities in their resolve to end the Dolgyal (Shugden) worship, following the long life offering to the Dalai Lama held at [[Drepung monastery]] in south India in February. &quot;This session will present motions to strengthen the present resolution adopted by the TPiE against the propitiation of Shugden,&quot; he added.&lt;ref&gt;Opening address of the fifth session of the Tibetan Parliament in Exile (TPiE), March 4, 2008, by Karma Chophel&lt;/ref&gt;

Critics of the ban on the practice of Dorje Shugden say that it has caused a large rift in the Tibetan community and is increasing disharmony in the Tibetan diaspora.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.france24.com/en/20080808-dalai-lama-demons-india-buddhism-dorje-shugden ''The Dalai Lama's Demons''] (4:41-5:25)), France 24 (2008-08-08). retrieved 2009-10-24.&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 22, 2008, the newly-founded [[Western Shugden Society]] (WSS) began a campaign directed at the 14th [[Dalai Lama]], picketing the venues where he was to appear around the world&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Dalai Lama in Oxford |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/oxford/content/articles/2008/05/30/dalai_lama.shtml |newspaper=BBC News |date=May 30, 2008 |accessdate=July 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and claiming that he is &quot;banning them from practicing their own lineage of Buddhism&quot;. The WSS claims that the Dalai Lama and the TGIE have not responded to any of their attempts to dialogue on the subject and supporters say that the TGIE have simply discredited the opposition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dorjeshugdenblog.wordpress.com/2008/10/04/reasoning-from-madness-the-dalai-lamas-campaign-against-human-rights/ ''Mixing Religion and Politics: The Dalai Lama's ban on Dorje Shugden Prayer''], Investigating the campaign against Dorje Shugden blog, 2008-10-04, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=October 2009}}

Sara Chamberlain reported that the TGIE will not employ those worshipping Dorje Shugden, keeping a [[blacklist]] of those who do.&lt;ref name=&quot;newint.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.newint.org/issue304/update.htm ''Deity Banned: Outrage as Dalai Lama Denounces Dorje Shugden''] by Sara Chamberlain, The New Internationalist (vol. 304, 1998), retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=October 2009}} The TGIE is also accused of labeling Shugden supporters as &quot;terrorists,&quot; as reported by [[Al Jazeera]]: &quot;In the Tibetan refugee camps, Shugden worshippers have been turned away from jobs, shops and schools. Posters with the message 'no Shugden followers allowed' cover hospital and shop fronts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/peopleandpower/2008/09/200893014344405483.html ''The Dalai Lama: The Devil Within], Al Jazeera's People &amp; Power, retrieved 2009-10-23.&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of perceived religious discrimination, the founder of Kundeling Monastery, Lobsang Yeshe, who lives in [[South India]], has filed a complaint against the Dalai Lama at the [[High Courts of India|Indian High Court]] on the grounds of [[religious persecution]]. The prosecuting lawyer, Shree Sanjay Jain, argues that when the Dalai Lama excommunicates Dorje Shugden worshippers from Buddhist society, &quot;then it is discrimination of the worst kind.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/peopleandpower/2008/09/200893014344405483.html ''The Dalai Lama: The Devil Within''] (9:35-9:55), Al Jazeera's People &amp; Power, 2008-09-30, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

The TGIE accuses Lobsang Yeshe of being paid by the Chinese and state that he has visited China at least twice. He however denies working for the Chinese, but does confirm that he has Chinese friends and he praises the Chinese &quot;for what they are doing in Tibet,&quot; claiming that if Tibetans who followed Dorje Shugden had to live under the Dalai Lama in Tibet, they &quot;would have possibly been [[Crucifixion|crucified]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.france24.com/en/20080808-dalai-lama-demons-india-buddhism-dorje-shugden ''The Dalai Lama's Demons''] (9:41-10:19)), France 24 (2008-08-08). retrieved 2009-10-24.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Views on the conflict ==
=== According to the Dalai Lama and the Tibetan government in exile ===
According to the Dolgyal Research Committee, instituted by the Tibetan government in exile (TGIE), prominent opponents to the practice have included not only the 5th, 13th and current Dalai Lamas but also the 5th and 8th [[Panchen Lamas]], [[Dzongsar Khyentse Chokyi Lodro]], the 14th and 16th [[Karmapa]]s among others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tibet.com/dholgyal/shugden-history.html ''A Brief History Of Opposition To Shugden''] edited and compiled by The Dolgyal Research Committee. retrieved 2008-12-07&lt;/ref&gt;

=== According to Shugden supporters ===
The claims of the Dalai Lama and the Tibetan government in exile (TGIE) are denied by the followers of Dorje Shugden. They claim, that for example, in 1921 the 13th Dalai Lama's biography refers to Dorje Shugden as an enlightened Protector (jam mgon bstan srung pa) and explains that the 13th Dalai Lama subsequently restored the Potala and Ganden stupas as an offering to him.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} According to Shugden adherents, the Fifth Dalai Lama started off in opposition but then changed his mind.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shugdensociety.info/praise5DalaiLamaEN.html ''Prayer to the protector Dorje Shugden''] by the Fifth Dalai Lama.&lt;/ref&gt; As further evidence of their view they state the example of Phelgye Ling monastery that was transformed to a Gelug monastery by the 5th Dalai Lama, who gave the monastery a statue (about 20&amp;nbsp;cm high) of Dorje Shugden riding on a black horse, which still exists in the monastery in [[Kathmandu]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dorjeshugden.com/index.htm ''Dorje Shugden and Dalai Lama - Spreading Dharma Together''] (about mid-way down the page). retrieved 2008-12-07.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Trijang Rinpoche]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Furthermore, from the definitive point of view, that these holy beings were already fully enlightened innumerable ages ago, is clear if one examines the accounts of their lives, and if one were to say that a fully enlightened being could take birth as an ordinary gyalpo or tsen spirit, then one would be asserting that degeneration is possible from the state of full enlightenment or that someone could be both fully enlightened and an ordinary preta at the same time. Or else, one would have to say that the accounts of those great beings' lives are worthless. A mountain of absurd consequences, previously non-existent distorted ideas, would have to be accepted.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dorjeshugden.com/articles/musicdelighting.pdf ''Music Delighting the Ocean of Protectors'' (1967)] by Kyabje Trijang Dorje Chang. p. 9. retrieved 2008-12-07&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This view is also held by other [[Gelug]] Lamas past and present who are or were considered great masters, including:  Kyabje [[Pabongka Rinpoche]] (root Guru of many highly regarded [[Gelug]] Lamas of the early 20th century), Kyabje [[Trijang Rinpoche]] (junior tutor of the 14th Dalai Lama). Among those who practised Shugden in the Gelug school were not only the Dalai Lama but also Geshe Rabten, Kyabje Zong Rinpoche, Lama Yeshe (founder of the [[FPMT]]), Geshe [[Kelsang Gyatso]] (founder of the [[NKT]]) and Tomo Geshe Rinpoche.&lt;ref&gt;Lopez, Donald (1998). ''Prisoners of Shangri-La: Tibetan Buddhism and the West''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt; It is also said that some of the [[Panchen Lama]]s (e.g. the 9th and 10th) practised Shugden,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dorjeshugden.com/gallery03.htm H.H. the previous Panchen Lama and H.E. Gangchen Rinpoche]&lt;/ref&gt; as does the current Chinese-appointed [[Panchen Lama]], Gyenkyen Norbu&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dorjeshugden.com/panchenshugden.htm Panchen and Shugden]&lt;/ref&gt; (the current Panchen Lama as recognized by the Dalai Lama and most Tibetans, Gedun Choekyi Nyima, has been a prisoner of the People's Republic of China for fifteen years; he is the world's youngest political prisoner). Trijang Rinpoche claims that the view that Dorje Shugden is an emanation of Manjushri has also been held by the [[Fifth Dalai Lama]] and the [[11th Dalai Lama|Eleventh Dalai Lama]]. According to Trijang Rinpoche, the [[11th Dalai Lama|Eleventh Dalai Lama]] &quot;enthroned Gyalchen Dorje Shugden as the principal protector of the Yellow Hat teachings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dorjeshugden.com/articles/musicdelighting.pdf ''Music Delighting the Ocean of Protectors'' (1967)] by Kyabje Trijang Dorje Chang. pp. 123-124. retrieved 2008-12-07&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Views of non-Gelugpa Tibetan Buddhists ===
Dorje Shugden has traditionally been regarded as a protector especially of the [[Gelugpa]] tradition. The other schools of Tibetan Buddhism have therefore usually not worshipped him or even, in the historical context of (political) rivalry, have seen him as a potential threat.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

Sakya Trizin, head of the Sakya lineage of Tibetan Buddhism, notes that at one time followers of his school did make offerings to Shugden but that, in this context, Shugden was regarded as a worldly deity. He also mentions two Lamas of pre-occupation Tibet, Dorjechang Jamyang Khyentse Chokyi Lodro and Ngor Kangchen Dorjechang, who limited the practice in their monasteries,&lt;ref&gt;[http://dalailama.com/page.157.htm ''Dorjee Shugden, The Spirit and the Controversy'' (??:?? -  ??:??)] by the [[TGIE]]. 2000-12-06, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt; confirming the existence of the practice within that tradition up to that time.

[[Tai Situpa|Palpung Tai Situ Rinpoche]], one of the most important Lamas in the [[Karma Kagyu]] tradition has said that the practice of Shugden &quot;causes fear.&quot; He adds the practice is considered to create obstacles to spiritual practice.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dalailama.com/page.157.htm ''Dorjee Shugden, The Spirit and the Controversy'' (21:24 - 21:49)] by the [[TGIE]]. 2000-12-06, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

While traditionally, the relationship between Shugden and the Nyingma is one of enmity, there is some evidence of latter day Nyingma&lt;ref&gt;Mumford, S. (1989). ''Himalayan dialogue: Tibetan lamas and Gurung shamans in Nepal''. New directions in anthropological writing. Madison, Wis: University of Wisconsin Press. p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt; practitioners in Nepal having received and propitiated Dorje Shugden via a patriarchal rather than politico-institutional lineage.  Mumford writes based on his anthropological studies in Nepal in the late 1970s:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Tibetans in Kathmandu regard Shugs-ldan as a guardian honored by those who adhere to the Gelug sect, while members of the Nyingma sect think of Shug-ldan as an enemy, sent against them by the rival sect. But in the villages these sectarian differences are not well understood. In Gyasumdo the lamas are Nyingmapa, yet most of them honor Shugs-ldan as a lineage guardian picked up in Tibet in the past by their patriline.&lt;ref&gt;Mumford, Stan. ''Himalayan dialogue: Tibetan lamas and Gurung shamans in Nepal'', p. 135.  Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Chogyal Namkhai Norbu]] claims that Shugden can cause devotees to become &quot;nervous, confused and upset.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Namkhai Norbu Rinpoche, Provocations of the Gyalpo, Dzogchen Community Italy: 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Minling Trichen Rinpoche, late head of the Nyingma tradition,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rigpawiki.org/index.php?title=Minling_Trichen_Rinpoche ''Minling Trichen Rinpoche''] at Rigpa Wiki, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt; said that &quot;Shugden is a ghost. We Nyingma practitioner do not follow him. We propagate only those protectors that were bound by [[Padmasambhava]]. Shugden came after Padmasambhava.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://dalailama.com/page.157.htm ''Dorjee Shugden, The Spirit and the Controversy'' (36:56 - 37:16)] by the [[TGIE]]. 2000-12-06, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

== Claims of violence/discrimination ==
===  Claims of violence/discrimination against Shugden practitioners ===
David Van Biema reports: &quot;Addressing charges of shunning, threats and even physical abuse against Shugdenites, American Dalai Lama adviser John Ackerly admits that 'there have been cases of [[harassment]],' all condemned by the High Lama.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,988311,00.html ''Monks vs. Monks''] by David Van Biema, ''Time'', 11 May 1998, retrieved 2009-05-22.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dorje Shugden worshippers say the ban and its implementation are in direct conflict with the proposed constitution of a free [[Tibet]], laid down by the Dalai Lama in 1963, which states that all religious denominations are equal before the law, and every Tibetan shall have the right to freedom of thought, conscience and religion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wisdombuddhadorjeshugden.org/dorjeshugden08.php Tibetan Government in Exile Constitution, Article 17]&lt;/ref&gt; But when Dorje Shugden worshippers challenged the ban on these grounds, the TGIE responded: &quot;Concepts like [[democracy]] and [[freedom of religion]] are empty when it comes to the well-being of the Dalai Lama and the common cause of Tibet.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;newint.org&quot;/&gt; [[Lama Zopa]] of the [[FPMT]] explains that the main reason he stopped the practice of Dorje Shugden himself and among his students was to support the Dalai Lama's political efforts on behalf of Tibet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fpmt.org/organization/announcements/shugden/ILTKtalk-Thirdedit.pdf ''His Holiness the Dalai Lama and Shugden''] by Lama Zopa Rinpoche, pp. 3, 6&lt;/ref&gt; Brendan O'Neill argues that the extreme [[Personality cult|idolization]] of the Dalai Lama by his followers only serves to undermine democracy in a future free Tibet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/mar/06/theproblemwithtibet ''The problem with Tibet''] by Brendan O'Neill, The Guardian, 2008-03-06, retrieved 2008-12-06&lt;/ref&gt; Ursula Bernis commented that second-guessing any pronouncement made by the Dalai Lama is &quot;sacrilege among religious Tibetans.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dalai Lama, Lamrim teachings given 1996-03-19, quoted in [http://www.shugdensociety.info/pdfs/BernisResearch.pdf ''Condemned to Silence: A Tibetan Identity Crisis''] by Ursula Bernis, p. 55 (Eulogy - page 21), retrieved 2008-12-06&lt;/ref&gt;

The Dalai Lama claims that Dorje Shugden conflicts with government-approved Dharma Protectors,&lt;ref&gt;Dalai Lama, Lamrim teachings given 1996-03-19, quoted in [http://www.shugdensociety.info/pdfs/BernisResearch.pdf ''Condemned to Silence: A Tibetan Identity Crisis''] by Ursula Bernis, p. 54 (Eulogy - page 20), retrieved 2008-12-06&lt;/ref&gt; so [[Al Jazeera]] asked one of the Tibetan government's [[Member of Parliament|Members of Parliament]], Tsultrim Tenzin, whether there had been any parliamentary debate about Dorje Shugden. He replied that there had been no debate simply because there was no opposition, adding &quot;We do not have any doubt about Dalai Lama's decisions. We do not think he is a human being. He's a supreme human being and he is god, he is [[Avalokiteshvara]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/peopleandpower/2008/09/200893014344405483.html ''The Dalai Lama: The Devil Within''] (5:20-5:47), Al Jazeera's People &amp; Power, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

According to PK Dey, a human-rights lawyer from Delhi, Dorje Shugden worshippers are suffering harassment from the Dalai Lama's followers and his government, citing door-to-door searches and [[wanted posters]] as examples.&lt;ref name=&quot;newint.org&quot;/&gt;  In 1998, Dey stated that he had gathered 300 statements from Tibetans living throughout India who claimed to have been subject to harassment or attack because of their worship of Dorje Shugden.&lt;ref name=&quot;spiked-online.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.spiked-online.com/index.php?/site/article/5170/ ''Is the Dalai Lama a &quot;religious dictator&quot;?''] by Brendan O'Neill, 2008-05-20, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

Shugden practitioners claim that they have been subjected to violence while protesting the ban, both in the 1990s and in the present-day.&lt;ref name=&quot;WSS-news-reponsetoletter&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
  | title = Response to letter from the Australian Sangha Association
  | publisher = [[Western Shugden Society]]
  | date = 2008-08-11
  | url = http://www.westernshugdensociety.org/en/news/response-to-letter-from-the-australian-sangha-association
  | accessdate = 2008-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; They state that in 1996, outside a monastery in southern India, a group of pro Dalai Lama supporters (including monks) surrounded hundreds of monks who had gathered to demonstrate against the Dalai Lama's ban on Dorje Shugden and threw stones and bricks.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} Chryssides reported that &quot;it is certainly true that, in July 1997, 200 of the Dalai Lama's followers physically attacked Shugden supporters.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Chryssides, George (1999). ''Exploring New Religions''. London: Cassell. p. 240.&lt;/ref&gt;

Deccan Herald reported on Monday, September 11, 2000: &lt;blockquote&gt;
Three police officers and more than 30 persons were injured in stone pelting incident in Lama camp of Tibetan settlement, Mundgod on Sunday morning. More than 2000 Lamas including 200 women who are said to be the followers of Dalai Lama took out procession under the leadership of Prema Tsering and tried to destroy Shugden temple and started pelting stones on Shugden devotees. Police personnel resorted to lathi charge and later bursted teargass shells.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070929124754/http://www.tibet-internal.com/ What is wrong with Tibetan society? Click on &quot;Eye Witness Report&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On July 17, 2008, a large mob of Dalai Lama supporters, who had been attending one of the Dalai Lama's teachings at the [[Radio City Music Hall]] in New York, clashed with Shugden protestors after the event, spitting, screaming, and throwing money at them, indicating that they believed that the Shugden protestors were paid by the Chinese government. The New York riot police led the protestors away to safety.&lt;ref name=&quot;nypost&quot;&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/seven/07182008/news/regionalnews/midtown_clash_over_dalai_120434.htm ''Midtown Clash over Dalai''] by Pilar Conci and Jamie Schram, New York Post, 2008-07-18, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Dalai Lama's Buddhist Foes |author=David Van Biema |url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1824531,00.html |newspaper=Time.com |date=July 18, 2008 |accessdate=July 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jamphel Yeshe, the President of the Dorje Shugden Society, stated that information about he and his family were posted on &quot;wanted posters&quot; in Tibetan communities in India and Nepal.&lt;ref name=&quot;yesheinterview&quot;&gt;[http://www.wisdombuddhadorjeshugden.org/interview4.php ''An Interview with Jamphel Yeshe''], Wisdom Buddha Dorje Shugden website, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;  Yeshe said in an interview that these posters had resulted in threats being made against himself and his family.&lt;ref name=&quot;yesheinterview&quot;/&gt;

Wanted posters described people believed to be Shugden leaders as the &quot;top ten enemies of the state&quot;. The posters were put up in monasteries, settlements and in [[Dharamsala, Himachal Pradesh|Dharamsala]] by the TGIE. In Clementown, India, &quot;the house of a family of Shugden worshippers was stoned and then firebombed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;newint.org&quot;/&gt;

Shugden supporters say that in July 2008, wanted posters of several monks involved in the WSS protests appeared in Queens, New York.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wisdombuddhadorjeshugden.blogspot.com/2008/08/conversation-with-tibetan-western.html ''Wanted Posters of Tibetan Western Shugden Society supporters''], Wisdom Buddha Dorje Shugden blog, 2008-08-06, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=April 2009}} [[Al Jazeera]] reported about public shunning via posters of Dorje Shugden practitioners displayed in public, adding &quot;No Shugden worshipper has ever been charged or investigated for terrorism, and yet the monks that continue to worship Shugden remain victims of a campaign of name and shame.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/peopleandpower/2008/09/200893014344405483.html ''The Dalai Lama: The Devil Within''] (7:02-7:11), Al Jazeera's People &amp; Power, 2008-09-30, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt; Dorje Shugden practitioners have also received other warning and death threats since the 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n5sOm-uQH9Y ''Dalai Lama / Dorje Shugden''] (Part 1 of 3, 7:17-8:05), SF1 - Swiss Public Television, 1998-01-05, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2008, [[Radio Free Asia]] reported that some Tibetan monks had been convicted by the Chinese government for fire-bombing the residence of a Dorje Shugden practitioner, the Shugden deity being &quot;regarded with suspicion by those loyal to the Dalai Lama.&quot;&lt;ref name=rfa&gt;[http://www.rfa.org/english/news/tibet/tibetans-10022008095355.html ''Tibetans Jailed For Blasts''] by Lobsang Choephel, Radio Free Asia, 2008-10-02, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

The Tibetan exile government began saying in 2009 that the Dorje Shugden issue is not even religious, that it is entirely political.  Samdhong Tulku claimed that Shugden practitioners are tools being used by the Chinese government and is quoted as saying &quot;...it is not a question of religion; it falls under the situation of politics only.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sandhong Rinpoche, Radio Free Asia (Tibetan Service), Washington D.C., August 30, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Claims of violence/discrimination against non-Shugden practitioners ===
A year after the Dalai Lama's 1996 banning of the practice, [[Lobsang Gyatso (monk)|Gen Lobsang Gyatso]] was murdered in Dharmasala, along with two of his students.&lt;ref&gt;Lopez, Donald (1998). ''Prisoners of Shangri-La: Tibetan Buddhism and the West''. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. pp. 195-196.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lobsang Gyatso had been a vocal supporter of the Dalai Lama's position on the worship of Dorje Shugden since the 1970s. In 1978, he wrote a book apparently criticizing the Dalai Lama’s teacher, Trijang Rinpoche, for his propagation of the Shugden cult, calling him a &quot;knotless heretic teacher—that is, a heretic disguised as a Buddhist monk.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dreyfus, Georges B. J. 2003 p. 301&quot;/&gt; According to Lobsang Gyatso's biographer, Gareth Sparham, many Geshes and Lamas were outraged about his criticism:

&lt;blockquote&gt;

How could a nobody like Lobsang Gyatso, who was neither from an aristocratic family nor the head of a Tibetan region, indeed not even a full graduate of a religious university, dare to criticize in print an important establishment figure? Georges Dreyfus at the time remarked that in pre-1959 Gen-la would have been killed outright for his temerity. Many in the Tibetan community ostracized Gen-la, even though the Dalai Lama had already by that time begun speaking publicly against the Shugden cult. Even the Dalai Lama appeared to distance himself from Gen-la. &quot;He is headstrong and his lack of sensitivity is making trouble,&quot; seemed to be his attitude towards Gen-la at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Gareth Sparham (1998). ''Memoirs of a Tibetan Lama''. Ithaca, N.Y.: Snow Lion Publications, p. 321.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Georges Dreyfus adds that &quot;Despite being hurt by the polemical attack, Tri-jang Rin-po-che made it clear that violence was out of the question. Gradually, tempers cooled down and the incident was forgotten—or so it seemed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dreyfus, Georges B. J. (2003). ''The Sound of Two Hands Clapping: The Education of a Tibetan Buddhist Monk''. Berkeley, Calif: University of California Press, p. 303.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the murder, Indian police interviewed several men they identified as worshippers of Dorje Shugden,&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsweekApril281997&quot;/&gt; but, given the lack of any evidence, could not formally charge anyone.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}} Though no arrest was made,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tricycle.com/two-sides-of-the-same-god ''Two Sides of the Same God''] by Donald Lopez. Tricycle: The Buddhist Review, p. 68. Retrieved 2009-04-10&lt;/ref&gt; many within the CTA assumed that it had been carried out by supporters of Dorje Shugden. The ''Seattle Times'' reported that: &quot;The two men suspected of stabbing their victims are believed to have fled India. Five others, all linked to the Dorje Shugden Society in New Delhi, were questioned for months about a possible conspiracy. No one has been charged.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=19970821&amp;slug=2555891 ''Dalai Lama Fighting Ghost In Religious Dispute''] by Arthur Max, ''Seattle Times'', 21 August 1997, retrieved 2009-05-22.&lt;/ref&gt;

Geshe [[Kelsang Gyatso]] denied the involvement of any of his followers in the murder, and condemned the killings.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsweekApril281997&quot;&gt;Clifton, Tony. [http://www.cesnur.org/press/Newsweek.htm ''Did an obscure Tibetan sect murder three monks close to the Dalai Lama?'']. Newsweek. 1997-04-28.  Retrieved 2009-04-10.&lt;/ref&gt; The Tibetan government in exile maintains that the murder of [[Lobsang Gyatso (monk)|Lobsang Gyatso]] was carried out by followers of Dorje Shugden.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tibet.com/dholgyal/CTA-book/chapter-5-2.html ''Two More Shugden Activists Identified as Murderers''], [[The Tribune]], 1997-11-29, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation broken|date=November 2009}}

In June 2007, the Times stated that Interpol had issued a [[INTERPOL notice|Red notice]] to China for extraditing two of the alleged killers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/asia/article1968987.ece ''Interpol on trail of Buddhist killers''] by Jane Macartney, [[The Times]], 2007-06-22, retrieved 2008-12-04&lt;/ref&gt;

==Court case concludes==
On 5 April 2010, Justice S. Muralidhar dismissed the writ petition filed by the Dorje Shugden Devotees’ Charitable and Religious Society against the Central Tibetan Administration and the Dalai Lama. The major reason cited for denying jurisdiction was location:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The government of India pointed out that this court has no territorial jurisdiction over a dispute. As they are located in Dharamshala, the state government is to investigate the allegations against the Dalai Lama and Tibetan government in exile. Indian government does not recognize the so-called Tibetan government in exile. It is further stated that worshippers of Dorje Shugden have a right to freedom of religion as enshrined under Article 25 of the Constitution.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The court noted that the Shugden Society's harassment and maltreatment accusations had not yet been lodged in a formal complaint to the local police authorities. According to the website of the Central Tibetan Administration, Justice Muralidhar's decision had the effect of &quot;Closing the doors on the possibility of similar complaints in the future,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tibet.net/en/index.php?id=1526&amp;articletype=flash&amp;rmenuid=morenews&amp;tab=1 Delhi High Court Dismisses Dorjee Shugden Devotees’ Charges] 2010-04-10, retrieved 2010-04-29.&lt;/ref&gt; omitting the fact that &quot;It is however clarified that the dismissal of this petition will not preclude any individual member or members of the Dorje Shugden Society to seek appropriate remedies as may be available to them in law&quot; before the police in Karnataka and its state government.

==See also==

*[[Theocracy]]
*[[sectarianism]]
*[[Feud]]
*[[Religious segregation]]
*[[Sectarian violence]]
*[[Sect]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==

*{{Cite journal
  | first = Paul
  | last = Mooney
  | authorlink =
  | title = Beyond Belief: Manipulating Tibetan Buddhism
  | publisher = Post Magazine, South China Morning Post
  | date = 2011-09-04
  | url = http://www.scmp.com/portal/site/SCMP/menuitem.1d923702d0f3d4b2b5326b10cba0a0a0/?vgnextoid=186c72c387422310VgnVCM100000360a0a0aRCRD&amp;vgnextfmt=mag&amp;issue=20110904&amp;ss=Post+Magazine&amp;s=Magazines#Top
  | accessdate = 2011-09-27}}

*{{Cite journal
  | first = Ursula
  | last = Bernis
  | authorlink =
  | title = Condemned to Silence: A Tibetan Identity Crisis (1996-1999)
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url = http://www.shugdensociety.info/pdfs/BernisResearch.pdf
  | format = PDF
  | accessdate = 2009-10-25}}

*{{Cite book
| last = Shugden Society
| first = Western
| title = A Great Deception
| url = http://www.agreatdeception.com
| date = January 2010
| isbn = 978-0-9563918-0-3}}

*{{Cite book
  | last = Curren
  | first = Erik
  | title = Buddha's Not Smiling: Uncovering Corruption at the Heart of Tibetan Buddhism Today
  | pages = 15–20, 299
  | publisher = Alaya Press
  | place = Staunton, Virginia
  | year = 2006
  | isbn = 978-0-9772253-0-9}}

*{{Cite journal
  | last = Dreyfus
  | first = Georges
  | title = The Shuk-Den Affair: Origins of a Controversy
  | journal = Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies
  | volume = 21
  | issue = 2
  | pages = 227–270
  | publisher = Peeters Publishers
  | place = Leuven
  | year = 1998
  | issn = 0193-600X}}

*{{Cite book
  | last = Kay
  | first = David
  | title = Tibetan and Zen Buddhism in Britain: Transplantation, Development and Adaptation
  | publisher = Routlge Curzon
  | place = London
  | year = 2004
  | isbn = 978-0-415-29765-3}}

*{{Cite book
  | last = Lopez
  | first = Donald
  | title = Prisoners of Shangri-La: Tibetan Buddhism and the West
  | publisher = University of Chicago Press
  | place = Chicago &amp; London
  | year = 1998
  | pages = 188–196
  | isbn = 978-0-226-49310-7}}

*{{Cite journal
  | first = Lindsay G.
  | last = McCune
  | authorlink =
  | title = Tales of Intrigue from Tibet's Holy City: The Historical Underpinnings of a Modern Buddhist Crisis
  | publisher =  Florida State University
  | year = 2007
  | url = http://etd.lib.fsu.edu/theses/available/etd-04092007-003235/unrestricted/lgm_thesis.pdf
  | format = PDF
  | accessdate = 2009-05-26}}

*{{Cite book
  | first = Martin A.
  | last = Mills
  | author-link =
  | editor-last = Von Richard
  | editor-first = Wilson
  | editor2-last = Mitchell
  | editor2-first = Jon P.
  | contribution = This Turbulent Priest: Contesting religious rights and the state in the Tibetan Shugden controversy
  | contribution-url = http://books.google.com/books?id=mczjYa-0KvYC&amp;pg=PA54&amp;dq=This+Turbulent+Priest&amp;ei=KO8aSqH5CpmYyAS5ipTjBg
  | title = Human Rights in Global Perspective: Anthropological Studies of Rights, Claims and Entitlements
  | year = 2003
  | pages = 54–70
  | place =
  | publisher = Routlege
  | isbn = 978-0-415-30410-8}}

*{{Cite journal
  | first = Michael
  | last = Nau
  | title = Killing for the Dharma: An Analysis of the Shugden Deity and Violence in Tibetan Buddhism
  | publisher =  Miami University
  | place =
  | year = 2007
  | url = http://www.ohiolink.edu/etd/send-pdf.cgi/Nau%20Michael.pdf?acc_num=muhonors1178300733
  | format = PDF
  | accessdate = 2009-05-26}}

*{{Cite book
  | author = René de Nebesky-Wojkowitz
  | authorlink = René Nebesky-Wojkowitz
  | title = Oracles and demons of Tibet: the cult and iconography of the Tibetan protective deities
  | publisher = Mouton
  | year = 1956
  | location = The Hauge}}

*{{Cite book
  | author = Tenpai Gyaltsen Dhongthog
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors = Lucjan Shila (translator)
  | title = The Earth Shaking Thunder of True Word. A refutation of attacks on the advice of H.H. the Dalai Lama regarding the propitiation of guardian deities.
  | publisher = Sapan Institute
  | year = 2000
  | location = Shoreline, Washington
  | isbn =
  | lccn= 2002298068}}

==External links==

&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;
&lt;!--| DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF |--&gt;
&lt;!--| LINKS. If you think that your link might be useful, do not add it here, |--&gt;
&lt;!--| but put it on this article's discussion page first or submit your link  |--&gt;
&lt;!--| to the appropriate category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org)|--&gt;
&lt;!--| and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.             |--&gt;
&lt;!--|                                                                         |--&gt;
&lt;!--|           Links that have not been verified WILL BE DELETED.            |--&gt;
&lt;!--|  See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details    |--&gt;
&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;

===Supporters of Dorje Shugden===
*[http://www.dorjeshugden.com Dorje Shugden &amp; The Dalai Lama Spreading Dharma Together]
*[http://www.westernshugdensociety.org/ Official Western Shugden Society website]
*[http://wisdombuddhadorjeshugden.org/ Why is the Dalai Lama Suppressing Religious Freedom?]
*[http://www.shugdensociety.info/ Dorje Shugden Charitable Society (Delhi)]
*[http://www.dorjeshugdenhistory.org Dorje Shugden History] by Trinley Kalsang

===Critics of Dorje Shugden===
*[http://www.dalailama.com/page.132.htm Official Website of the Dalai Lama] - Advice Concerning Dolgyal (Shugden)
*[http://www.tibetonline.tv/shugden_issues.html Official Web TV Station of the Central Tibetan Administration] - includes [[BBC]] documentary &quot;An Unholy Row&quot; and Second Shugden Documentary filmed by Swiss TV in 1998
*[http://www.fpmt.org/organization/announcements/shugden/ Collection of Advice Regarding Shugden] by the [[FPMT]]
*[http://www.tibet.com/dholgyal/index.html The Central Tibetan Administration on Controversy Surrounding Dorjee Shugden Practice]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dorje Shugden Controversy}}
[[Category:Politics of Tibet]]
[[Category:Tibetan Buddhism]]
[[Category:Buddhism-related controversies]]

[[fr:Controverse Dordjé Shougdèn]]
[[nl:Dorje Shugden-controverse]]
[[pt:Controvérsia de Dorje Shugden]]
[[zh:多傑雄登爭議]]</text>
      <sha1>luydyxgbyx2avuiay71dhn46r3ddm21</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
