<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hate group</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>437067</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516581979</id>
      <parentid>516579452</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-08T05:01:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SummerPhD</username>
        <id>1606041</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/75.110.23.42|75.110.23.42]] ([[User talk:75.110.23.42|talk]]): -POV. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14802">{{Globalize/US|date=February 2011}}
{{Discrimination sidebar}}

A '''hate group''' is an organized group or movement that advocates and practices [[hatred]], [[hostility]], or [[violence]] towards members of a race, ethnicity, religion, gender, sexual orientation or other designated sector of society. According to the United States [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI), hate groups' &quot;primary purpose is to promote animosity, hostility, and malice against persons belonging to a race, religion, disability, sexual orientation, or ethnicity/national origin which differs from that of the members of the organization.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hate Crime Data Collection Guidelines&quot;, ''Uniform Crime Reporting: Summary Reporting System: National Incident-Based Reporting System'', U.S. Department of Justice: Federal Bureau of Investigation, Criminal Justice Information Services Division, Revised October 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Southern Poverty Law Center]]'s (SPLC) definition of a &quot;hate group&quot; includes those having beliefs or practices that attack or malign an entire class of people, typically for their immutable characteristics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/hate-map Hate Map] - SPLC&lt;/ref&gt;

In the US, two main organizations that monitor intolerance and hate groups are the [[Anti-Defamation League]] (ADL)&lt;ref name=&quot;titleADL: Fighting Anti-Semitism, Bigotry and Extremism&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/ |title=ADL: Fighting Anti-Semitism, Bigotry and Extremism |accessdate=2008-04-13 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the SPLC.&lt;ref name=&quot;titleSPLCenter.org...forwarding to index.jsp&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.splcenter.org/ |title=SPLCenter.org...forwarding to index.jsp |accessdate=2008-04-13 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hate groups are also tracked by the FBI.&lt;ref name=jessup/&gt; The ADL and the SPLC maintain a list of what they deem to be hate groups, supremacist groups and [[anti-Semitism|anti-Semitic]], anti-government or extremist groups that have committed [[hate crime]]s. However, at least for the SPLC, inclusion of a group in the list &quot;does not imply a group advocates or engages in violence or other criminal activity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.splcenter.org/get-informed/hate-map| title=Hate Map| accessdate=2010-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the SPLC, from 2000 to 2008, hate group activity saw a 50 percent increase in the US, with a total of 926 active groups.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Katel |first=Peter |date=2009-05-08 |title=Hate Groups |volume=19 |issue=18 |pages=421–448 |publisher=[[CQ Researcher]]}}  See &quot;The Year in Hate&quot; Southern Poverty Law Center, February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The FBI does not publish a list of hate groups, and &quot;[I]nvestigations are conducted only when a threat or advocacy of force is made; when the group has the apparent ability to carry out the proclaimed act; and when the act would constitute a potential violation of federal law.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Frequently Asked Questions&quot;, [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]], accessed  April 7, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Violence and hate crimes==
{{See|Hate crime}}
The California Association for Human Relations Organizations (CAHRO) asserts that hate groups such as the [[Ku Klux Klan]] (KKK) and [[White Aryan Resistance]] (WAR) preach violence against racial, religious, sexual and other minorities in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cahro.org/2011/08/freedom-from-fear-ending-californias-hate-violence-epidemic/&lt;/ref&gt; Joseph E. Agne argues that hate-motivated violence is a result of the successes of the civil rights movement, and asserts that the KKK has resurfaced and new hate groups have formed.&lt;ref&gt;http://gbgm-umc.org/advance/Church-Burnings/hategrup.html#consult&lt;/ref&gt; Agne argues that it is a mistake to underestimate the strength of the hate-violence movement, its [[apologist]]s and its silent partners.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gbgm-umc.org/advance/Church-Burnings/hategrup.html#consult The Church's Response to Hate-Group Violence&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the US, crimes that &quot;manifest evidence of prejudice based on race, religion, sexual orientation, or ethnicity, including the crimes of murder and nonnegligent manslaughter; forcible rape; robbery; aggravated assault; burglary; larceny-theft; motor vehicle theft; arson; simple assault; intimidation; and destruction, damage or vandalism of property&quot;, 
directed at the government, an individual, a business, or institution, involving hate groups and hate crimes, may be investigated as acts of domestic terrorism.&lt;ref&gt;The Uniform Crime Reporting (UCR) Program - Data Quality Guidelines for Statistics - APPENDIX III—A BRIEF HISTORY OF THE HATE CRIME PROGRAM [http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/guidelines/guidelines.htm#hatecrimehistory]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Federal Bureau of Investigation - Civil Rights - Hate Crime Overview - The FBI’s Role [http://www.fbi.gov/hq/cid/civilrights/overview.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fbi.gov/ucr/hc2006/index.html Hate Crime Statistics, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;1999 Developing Hate Crime Questions for the National Crime Victim Survey (NCVS) Pg. 1 [http://66.102.1.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:vynjDEZksWEJ:https://www.amstat.org/sections/srms/Proceedings/papers/1999_181.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hate speech==
{{See|Hate speech}}
Counterterrorism expert Ehud Sprinzak argues that verbal violence is &quot;the use of extreme language against an individual or a group that either implies a direct threat that physical force will be used against them, or is seen as an indirect call for others to use it.&quot; Sprinzak argues that verbal violence is often a substitute for real violence, and that the verbalization of hate has the potential to incite people who are incapable of distinguishing between real and verbal violence to engage in actual violence.&lt;ref&gt;Sprinzak, Ehud, ''Brother against Brother: Violence and Extremism in Israeli Politics from Altalena to the Rabin Assassination'' (New York: The Free Press, 1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian [[Daniel Goldhagen]], discussing [[Anti-semitism|antisemitic]] hate groups, argues that we should view verbal violence as &quot;an assault in its own right, having been intended to produce profound damage—emotional, psychological, and social—to the dignity and honor of the Jews. The wounds that people suffer by ... such vituperation ... can be as bad as ... [a] beating.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Goldhagen, Daniel Jonah, ''Hitler’s Willing Executioners: Ordinary Germans the Holocaust'' (Knopf, 1996), p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the mid-1990s, the popularity of the Interne] brought new international exposure to many organizations, including groups with beliefs such as [[white supremacy]], [[neo-Nazism]], [[homophobia]], [[Holocaust denial]] or [[Islamophobia]]. Several white supremacist groups have founded websites dedicated to attacking their perceived enemies. In 1996, the [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]] of Los Angeles asked Internet access providers to adopt a code of ethics that would prevent extremists from publishing their ideas online. In 1996, the [[European Commission]] formed the Consultative Commission on Racism and Xenophobia (CRAX), a pan-European group which was tasked to &quot;investigate and, using legal means, stamp out the current wave of racism on the Internet.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Newsbytes News Network (31 January 1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious hate groups==
{{see also|List of organizations designated by the Southern Poverty Law Center as anti-gay hate groups‎}}
The [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] has designated several Christian groups as hate groups, including [[American Family Association]], [[Family Research Council]], [[Abiding Truth Ministries]], [[American Vision]], [[Chalcedon Foundation]], [[Dove World Outreach Center]] and [[Traditional Values Coalition]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SPLC-18-List&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Waddington|first=Lynda|title=Groups that Helped Oust Iowa Judges Earn 'Hate Group' Designation; SPLC Adds American Family Association, Family Research Council to List|url=http://iowaindependent.com/47947/groups-that-helped-oust-iowa-judges-earn-hate-group-designation|accessdate=25 November 2010|newspaper=[[American Independent News Network|Iowa Independent]]|date=23 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPo hate&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Thompson|first=Krissah|title='Hate group' designation angers same-sex marriage opponents|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/11/24/AR2010112405573.html|accessdate=25 November 2010|newspaper=Washington Post|date=24 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The SPLC classes [[Nation of Islam]] (NOI) as a hate group under the category &quot;black separatist&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/map/type.jsp?DT=3 SPLC - Active U.S. Hate Groups in 2008: Black Separatist]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=jessup&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=1IL-RQcFjRsC&amp;pg=PA165&amp;vq=hate+organizations&amp;dq=%22Hate+organizations%22&amp;source=gbs_search_s&amp;sig=ACfU3U3UPapDLm3h82CpppP_PmUVMLvKEg Jessup, Michael &quot;The Sword of Truth in the Sea of Lies: The Theology of Hate&quot;, in Priest, Robert J. and Alvaro L. Nieves, eds., ''This Side of Heaven'' (Oxford University Press US, 2006) ISBN 0-19-531056-X, Google Print, pp.165-66]&lt;/ref&gt; The NOI preaches that a black scientist named [[Yakub (Nation of Islam)|Yakub]] created the white race, a &quot;race of devils&quot;, on the Greek island of [[Patmos]]. The NOI, unlike traditional [[Muslim]] groups, does not accept white members and is not regarded as a legitimate branch of Islam by mainstream Muslims.

The [[white supremacy|white supremacist]] [[Creativity Movement]] (formerly World Church of the Creator), led by [[Matthew F. Hale]], is associated with violence and bigotry. [[Aryan Nations]] is another religion-based white supremacist hate group.

[[Westboro Baptist Church]] is considered a hate group for its provocative stance against homosexuality and [[United States|America]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.splcenter.org/intel/intelreport/article.jsp?aid=627 The year in hate 2005], [[Southern Poverty Law Center]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Internet hate groups==
Traditionally, hate groups recruited members and spread extremist messages by word of mouth, or through the distribution of flyers and pamphlets. In contrast, the Internet allows members from all over the world to engage in real-time conversations.&lt;ref&gt;Meddaugh and Kay (2009)&lt;/ref&gt; The Internet has been a boon for hate groups in terms of promotion, recruitment and expanding their base to include younger audiences.&lt;ref&gt;Schafer and Navarro (2002); Williamson and Pierson (2003)&lt;/ref&gt; An Internet hate group does not have to be a part of a traditional faction such as the [[Ku Klux Klan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibiblio.org/nmediac/summer2012/Articles/obama_facebook.htm Moody, M., &quot;New Media-Same Stereotypes: An Analysis of Social Media Depictions of President Barack Obama and Michelle Obama&quot;, ''The Journal of New Media &amp; Culture'' (2012).]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]] (SWC), in its 2009 ''iReport'', identified more than 10,000 problematic hate and terrorist websites and other Internet postings. The report includes hate websites, social networks, blogs, newsgroups, YouTube and other video sites. The findings illustrate that as the Internet continues to grow, extremists find new ways to seek validation for their hateful agendas and to recruit members. 

[[Facebook]] hate page/group creators choose their target, set up a site, and then recruit members&lt;ref&gt;Perry and Olsson (2009)&lt;/ref&gt; Anyone can create a Facebook group and invite followers to post comments, add pictures and participate in discussion boards. A Facebook page is similar, except one must ‘like’ the page to become a member. Because of the ease of creating and joining such groups, many so-called hate groups exist only in cyberspace&lt;ref&gt;Meddaugh and Kay (2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Psychopathology of hate groups==
According to a 2003 FBI Law Enforcement bulletin, a hate group, if unimpeded, passes through seven successive stages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title =2003 [[FBI]] Law Enforcement bulletin
| url =http://www.fbi.gov/stats-services/publications/law-enforcement-bulletin/2003-pdfs/mar03leb.pdf/at_download/file
| year =2003
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the first four stages, hate groups vocalize their beliefs and in the last three stages, they act on their beliefs. The report points to a transition period that exists between verbal violence and acting that violence out, separating hardcore haters from rhetorical haters. Thus, [[hate speech]] is seen as a prerequisite of [[hate crime]]s, and as a [[condition of possibility|condition of their possibility]].

==See also==
* [[List of organizations designated by the Southern Poverty Law Center as hate groups]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Schafer,John R. MA &amp; Navarro. Joe, MA . ''The seven-stage hate model: The psychopathology of hate groups''. [[FBI]] Law Enforcement Bulletin, March 2003
* [[Dorothy E. Denning|Denning, Dorothy E.]], and Peter J. Denning. ''Internet Besieged: Countering Cyberspace Scofflaws.'' New York: ACM Press (1998)
* Perry, Barbara - ''‘Button-Down Terror’: The Metamorphosis of the Hate Movement.'' Sociological Focus Vol. 33 (No. 2, May 2000): 113.
* Jessup, Michael ''The Sword of Truth in the Sea of Lies: The Theology of Hate'', [http://books.google.com/books?id=1IL-RQcFjRsC&amp;pg=PA165&amp;vq=hate+organizations&amp;dq=%22Hate+organizations%22&amp;source=gbs_search_s&amp;sig=ACfU3U3UPapDLm3h82CpppP_PmUVMLvKEg Google Print, p.165-p.166], in Robert J. Priest, Alvaro L. Nieves (ed.), ''This Side of Heaven'', Oxford University Press US, 2006, ISBN 0-19-531056-X
*J. Wayne Dudley, ''&quot;Hate&quot; Organizations of the 1940s: The Columbians, Inc.'', Phylon, Vol. 42, No. 3 (3rd Qtr., 1981), pp.&amp;nbsp;262–274 ([http://www.jstor.org/pss/274923 JSTOR])

==External links==
* {{dmoz|Society/Issues/Race-Ethnic-Religious_Relations/Hate/Hate_Groups|Hate Groups}}
* [http://www.adl.org/poisoning_web/introduction.asp ''Poisoning the Web: Hatred Online, Internet Bigotry, Extremism and Violence'' - The Anti-defamation League]
* [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/hatewatch/ Hatewatch]
* [http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/issues/online_hate/index.cfm ''Online Hate'' - The Media Awareness Network]
* [http://www.media-awareness.ca/english/issues/online_hate/deconst_online_hate.cfm ''Deconstructing Hate Sites'']
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/rcip//sbh.html Survivor bashing - bias motivated hate crimes]
* [http://www.wickedness.net/Evil/Evil%208/chaturvedi%20paper.pdf Hate Communities in Cyber Space; Manjeet Chaturvedi,Ishan, Ishita]
* [http://64.233.179.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:bouJkou0NsIJ:www.simson.net/ref/leaderless/berlet_when_hate_went_online.pdf+KKK+SEXISM &quot;When Hate went Online&quot;]
* [http://www.splcenter.org/intel/map/hate.jsp Active U.S. Hate Groups] - a map at The Southern Poverty Law Center

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Discrimination}}
{{Racism topics|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hate Group}}
[[Category:Hatred]]

[[la:Grex exosus]]
[[no:Hatgruppe]]
[[simple:Hate group]]
[[fi:Viharyhmä]]
[[zh:仇恨團體]]</text>
      <sha1>pzp04oaui6hm7ryfkz376e1cp2mncsb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
