<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Judas Iscariot</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>59172</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519785147</id>
      <parentid>519783735</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T16:29:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>McGeddon</username>
        <id>455421</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/83.180.226.73|83.180.226.73]] ([[User talk:83.180.226.73|talk]]) identified as [[WP:VAND|vandalism]] to last revision by Darthjarek. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48797">{{about|the biblical figure|the band|Judas Iscariot (band)}}
[[Image:The-Last-Supper-large.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Judas Iscariot (right), retiring from the [[Last Supper]], painting by [[Carl Bloch]], late 19th century ]]

'''Judas Iscariot''' ({{lang-he|יהודה איש־קריות}}, ''[[Judah|Yehuda]]'', {{unicode|Yəhûḏāh ʾÎš-qrayyôṯ}}) was, according to the [[New Testament]], one of the [[Twelve Apostles]] of [[Jesus Christ]]. 

He is infamously known for his [[Kiss of Judas|kiss and betrayal of Jesus]] to the hands of the chief [[Sanhedrin]] priests in exchange for a payment of [[Thirty pieces of silver|30 pieces of silver]], after which he subsequently hanged himself out of remorse and guilt. &lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse||Matthew|26:14|16}}, {{Bibleverse||Matthew|26:47|56}}, {{Bibleverse||Mark|14:10|11}}, {{Bibleverse||Mark|14:42|52}}, {{Bibleverse||Luke|22:1|5}}, {{Bibleverse||Luke|22:47|53}}, {{Bibleverse||John|13:18|30}}, {{Bibleverse||John|18:1|11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Etymology==
In the [[Greek language|Greek]] [[New Testament]], Judas is called Ιούδας Ισκάριωθ  and Ισκαριώτης . &quot;Judas&quot; (spelled &quot;Ioudas&quot; in ancient Greek and &quot;Iudas&quot; in Latin, pronounced ''yudas'' in both) is the Greek form of the common name [[Judah (biblical figure)|Judah]] (יהודה, Y&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;hûdâh, Hebrew for &quot;God is praised&quot;). The Greek spelling underlies other names in the New Testament that are traditionally rendered differently in English: [[Judah]] and [[Jude (disambiguation)|Jude]].

The significance of &quot;Iscariot&quot; is uncertain. There are several major theories on etymology:
*One popular explanation derives ''Iscariot'' from [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] איש־קריות, ''Îš-Qrîyôth'', or &quot;man of [[Kerioth]]&quot;. The Gospel of John refers to Judas as &quot;son of Simon Iscariot&quot; (although the biblical text only refers to him as &quot;''the son'' of Simon&quot; (Jn 6:71, Jn 13:26, King James Version)),&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|6:71}} and {{bibleverse||John|13:26}}&lt;/ref&gt; implying it was not Judas, but his father, who came from there.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Bauckham, ''Jesus and the Eyewitnesses: The Gospels as Eyewitness Testimony'', Eerdmans (2006), p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt; Some speculate that ''Kerioth'' refers to a region in [[Judea]], but it is also the name of two known Judean towns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://net.bible.org/bible.php?book=Mat&amp;chapter=10#n11 New English Translation Bible, n. 11 in Matthew 11].&lt;/ref&gt;
*A second theory is that &quot;Iscariot&quot; identifies Judas as a member of the ''[[sicarii]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Bastiaan van Iersel, ''Mark: A Reader-Response Commentary'', Continuum International (1998), p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt; These were a cadre of assassins among Jewish rebels intent on driving the Romans out of Judea. However, some historians maintain the ''sicarii'' arose in the 40s or 50s of the 1st century, in which case Judas could not have been a member.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, Raymond E. (1994). ''The Death of the Messiah: From Gethsemane to the Grave: A Commentary on the Passion Narratives in the Four Gospels v.1 ''pp. 688–92. New York: Doubleday/The Anchor Bible Reference Library. ISBN 0-385-49448-3; Meier, John P. [[John P. Meier#A Marginal Jew: Rethinking the Historical Jesus|''A Marginal Jew: Rethinking the Historical Jesus'']] (2001). v. 3, p. 210. New York: Doubleday/The Anchor Bible Reference Library. ISBN 0-385-46993-4.&lt;/ref&gt;
*A third possibility advanced by Ernst Wilhelm Hengstenberg is that Iscariot means &quot;the liar&quot; or &quot;the false one,&quot; perhaps from the Hebrew [[File:HebrewIscariot-1.jpg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;search.ebscohost.com&quot;&gt;Joan E. Taylor, &quot;The name 'Iskarioth' (Iscariot),&quot; pages 367–383 in ''[[Journal of Biblical Literature]]'' 129 no 2 (Sum 2010), 369. Online:  http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=rfh&amp;AN=ATLA0001790392&amp;site=ehost-live&amp;scope=site.  Accessed 2011-03-12.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Fourth, some have proposed that the word derives from an Aramaic word meaning &quot;red color,&quot; from the root [[File:HebrewIscariot-2.jpg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;search.ebscohost.com&quot;/&gt;
*Fifth, the word derives from one of the Aramaic roots [[File:HebrewIscariot-3.jpg]] or [[File:HebrewIscariot-4.jpg]].  This would mean &quot;to deliver,&quot; based on the LXX rendering of Isaiah 19:4a—a theory advanced by J. Alfred Morin.&lt;ref&gt;Joan E. Taylor, &quot;The name 'Iskarioth' (Iscariot),&quot; pages 367–383 in ''[[Journal of Biblical Literature]]'' 129 no 2 (Sum 2010), 370. Online:  http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=rfh&amp;AN=ATLA0001790392&amp;site=ehost-live&amp;scope=site.  Accessed 2011-03-12.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Finally, the epithet could be associated with the manner of Judas' death, i.e., hanging.  This would mean Iscariot derives from a kind of Greek-Aramaic hybrid:  [[File:HebrewIscariot-5.jpg]], ''Iskarioutha'', &quot;chokiness&quot; or &quot;constriction.&quot;  This might indicate that the epithet be applied posthumously by the remaining disciples, but Joan E. Taylor has argued that it was a descriptive name given to Judas by Jesus, since other disciples such as Simon Peter/Cephas (''Kephas'' = &quot;rock&quot;) were also given such names.&lt;ref&gt;Joan E. Taylor, &quot;The name 'Iskarioth' (Iscariot),&quot; pages 367–383 in ''[[Journal of Biblical Literature]]'' 129 no 2 (Sum 2010), 379–383. Online:  http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=rfh&amp;AN=ATLA0001790392&amp;site=ehost-live&amp;scope=site.  Accessed 2011-03-12.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biblical narrative==
[[File:Gustave Doré - The Holy Bible - Plate CXLI, The Judas Kiss.jpg|thumb|&quot;The Judas Kiss&quot; (1866) by [[Gustave Doré]].|250px]]
Judas is mentioned in the [[synoptic gospels]], the [[Gospel of John]] and at the beginning of [[Acts of the Apostles]].

Mark states that the chief priests were looking for a sly way to [[Arrest of Jesus|arrest Jesus]]. They decided not to do so during the feast since they were afraid that people would riot; instead, they chose the night before the feast to arrest him. In the [[Gospel of Luke]], [[demonic possession|Satan enters]] Judas at this time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luke&quot; /&gt;

According to the account in the Gospel of John, Judas carried the disciples' money bag.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|12:6|131}}&lt;/ref&gt; He betrayed Jesus for a bribe of &quot;[[thirty pieces of silver]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matthew|26:14|131}}&lt;/ref&gt; by identifying him with a kiss — &quot;the [[kiss of Judas]]&quot; — to arresting soldiers of the High Priest [[Caiaphas]], who then turned Jesus over to [[Pontius Pilate]]'s soldiers.

===Death===
There are a few descriptions of the death of Judas, two of which are included in the modern [[Biblical canon]]:
*Matthew 27:3–10 says that Judas returned the money to the [[priest]]s and committed [[suicide]] by hanging himself. They used it to buy the [[potter's field]]. The Gospel account presents this as a fulfillment of prophecy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Matthew|27:9–10|NASB}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The ''[[Acts of the Apostles]]'' says that Judas used the money to buy a field, but fell headfirst, and ''burst asunder in the midst, and all his bowels gushed out''. This field is called [[Akeldama]] or ''Field of Blood''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=acts%201:18 Acts 1:18].&lt;/ref&gt;
*The non-canonical ''[[Gospel of Judas]]'' says Judas had a vision of the disciples stoning and persecuting him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalgeographic.com/lostgospel/pdf/GospelofJudas.pdf Gospel of Judas 44–45].&lt;/ref&gt;
*Another account was preserved by the early Christian leader, [[Papias of Hierapolis|Papias]]: &quot;Judas walked about in this world a sad example of impiety; for his body having swollen to such an extent that he could not pass where a chariot could pass easily, he was crushed by the chariot, so that his bowels gushed out.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.vii.ii.iii.html (Papias ''Fragment'' 3, 1742–1744)].&lt;/ref&gt;

The existence of conflicting accounts of the death of Judas caused problems for scholars who saw them as threatening the reliability of Scripture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arie W. Zwiep page 109&quot; /&gt; This problem was one of the points causing [[C. S. Lewis]], for example, to reject the view &quot;that every statement in Scripture must be historical truth&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;letter to Clyde S. Kilby, 7 May 1959, quoted in Michael J. Christensen, ''C. S. Lewis on Scripture'', Abingdon, 1979, Appendix A.&lt;/ref&gt; Various attempts at [[Gospel harmony|harmonization]] have been suggested, such as that of [[Augustine]] that Judas hanged himself in the field, and the rope eventually snapped and the fall burst his body open,&lt;ref name=&quot;Arie W. Zwiep page 109&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christnotes.org/dictionary.php?dict=ebd&amp;q=Judas|title=Easton’s Bible Dictionary: Judas|publisher=christnotes.org|accessdate=2007-06-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; or that the accounts of Acts and Matthew refer to two different transactions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.levendwater.org/companion/append161.html|title=The purchase of &quot;the potter's field&quot;, Appendix 161 of the Companion Bible|accessdate=2008-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some modern scholars tend to reject these approaches&lt;ref&gt;Raymond E. Brown, ''An Introduction to the New Testament'', p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Charles Talbert, ''Reading Acts: A Literary and Theological Commentary'', Smyth &amp; Helwys (2005) p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frederick Dale Bruner, Matthew: A Commentary, Eerdmans (2004), p. 703.&lt;/ref&gt; stating that the Matthew account is a [[midrashic]] exposition that allows the author to present the event as a fulfillment of prophetic passages from the Old Testament. They argue that the author adds imaginative details such as the thirty pieces of silver, and the fact that Judas hangs himself, to an earlier tradition about Judas' death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://academic.shu.edu/btb/vol35/06Reed.pdf|title=&quot;Saving Judas&quot;—A social Scientific Approach to Judas’s Suicide in Matthew 27:3–10|author=Reed, David A.|publisher=Biblical Theology Bulletin|year=2005|accessdate=2007-06-26|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070629151614/http://academic.shu.edu/btb/vol35/06Reed.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Matthew's reference to the death as fulfilment of a prophecy &quot;spoken through Jeremiah the prophet&quot; caused controversy, since it paraphrases a story from the [[Book of Zechariah]] &lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Zechariah|11:12–13|NASB|Zechariah 11:12–13}}&lt;/ref&gt; which refers to the return of a payment of [[thirty pieces of silver]].&lt;ref&gt;Vincent P. Branick, ''Understanding the New Testament and Its Message'', (Paulist Press, 1998), pp. 126–128.&lt;/ref&gt; Some writers, such as [[Jerome]] and [[John Calvin]] concluded that this was an obvious error.&lt;ref&gt;Frederick Dale Bruner, ''Matthew: A Commentary'' (Eerdmans, 2004), p. 710; Jerome, ''Epistolae'' 57.7: &quot;This passage is not found in Jeremiah but in Zechariah, in quite different words and a different order&quot; [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf206.v.LVII.html]; John Calvin, ''Commentary on a Harmony of the Evangelists, Matthew, Mark and Luke'', 3:177: &quot;The passage itself plainly shows that the name of Jeremiah has been put down by mistake, instead of Zechariah, for in Jeremiah we find nothing of this sort, nor any thing that even approaches to it.&quot; [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom33.ii.xxxvi.html].&lt;/ref&gt; Some modern writers suggest that the Gospel writer may have had a passage from Jeremiah in mind,&lt;ref&gt;Donald Senior, ''The Passion of Jesus in the Gospel of Matthew'' (Liturgical Press, 1985), pp. 107–108; Anthony Cane, ''The Place of Judas Iscariot in Christology'' (Ashgate Publishing, 2005), p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; such as chapters {{bibleref2|Jeremiah|18:1–4|NASB|18:1–4}} and {{bibleref2|Jeremiah|19:1–13|NASB|19:1–13}} which refers to a potter's jar and a burial place, and chapter {{bibleref2|Jeremiah|32:6–15|NASB|32:6–15}} which refers to a burial place and an earthenware jar.&lt;ref&gt;See also Maarten JJ Menken, [http://www.bsw.org/project/biblica/bibl83/Comm10.html 'The Old Testament Quotation in Matthew 27,9–10'], ''[[Biblica (journal)|Biblica]]'' '''83''' (2002): 9–10.&lt;/ref&gt;
Randel Helms wrote, &quot; That Matthew 27v9 thinks the passage he is quoting comes from Jeremiah shows that he has departed from his usual practice -especially when using Mark - of checking the accuracy of his source's Old Testament reference. Matthew's source has blended Jeremiah's buying of a field and placing the deed in a pot with Zechariah's casting of thirty pieces of silver down in the temple and the purchase of the Potter's Field. The story of Judas's actions after the betrayal is one of the most revealing examples of the early Christians' fictional and imaginative use of the Old Testament as a book about Jesus. &quot;&lt;ref&gt;p116 of chapter vi, ' The Passion Narrative ' from &quot; Gospel fictions &quot; by [[ Randel Helms ]], published 1988 by Prometheus Books&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theology==
===Betrayal of Jesus===
There are several explanations as to why Judas betrayed Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Dictionary of Jesus and the Gospels|author=Joel B. Green, Scot McKnight, I. Howard Marshall|year=1992|page=406|isbn=978-0-8308-1777-1|publisher=InterVaristy Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; A prevalent explanation is that Judas betrayed Jesus for 30 pieces of silver ({{bibleverse||Matthew|26:14–16|niv}}). One of Judas's main weaknesses seemed to be money ({{bibleverse||John|12:4–6|niv}}). A possibility is that Judas expected Jesus to overthrow Roman rule of Israel. In this view, Judas is a disillusioned disciple betraying Jesus not so much because he loved money, but because he loved his country and thought Jesus had failed it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Dictionary of Jesus and the Gospels|author=Joel B. Green, Scot McKnight, I. Howard Marshall|year=1992|page=407|isbn=978-0-8308-1777-1|publisher=InterVaristy Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to {{bibleverse||Luke|22:3–6|niv}} and {{bibleverse||John|13:27|niv}}, Satan entered into him and called him to do it.

The Gospels suggest that Jesus foresaw ({{bibleverse||John|6:64|niv}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|26:25|niv}}) and allowed Judas's betrayal ({{bibleverse||John|13:27–28|niv}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.ca&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=yUmI4US6rOUC&amp;pg=PA7 |title=Judas and the choice of Matthias: a study on context and concern of Acts 1:15–26, Arie W. Zwiep |publisher=Books.google.ca |date= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One explanation is that Jesus allowed the betrayal because it would allow God's plan to be fulfilled.  Another is that regardless of the betrayal, Jesus was ultimately destined for crucifixion.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.religioustolerance.org/gospj3.htm Did Judas betray Jesus]'' Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance, April 2006&lt;/ref&gt;  In April 2006, a Coptic papyrus manuscript titled the [[Gospel of Judas]] from 200 AD was translated, suggesting that Jesus told Judas to betray him,&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews.com&quot;&gt;Associated Press, [http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,190826,00.html &quot;Ancient Manuscript Suggests Jesus Asked Judas to Betray Him,&quot;] Fox News Thursday, 6&amp;nbsp;April 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; although some scholars question the translation.&lt;ref name=&quot;erudit.org&quot;&gt;[[André Gagné]], &quot;[http://www.erudit.org/revue/ltp/2007/v63/n2/016791ar.pdf A Critical Note on the Meaning of APOPHASIS in Gospel of Judas 33:1].&quot; ''Laval théologique et philosophique'' 63 (2007): 377–83.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=April D. |last=Deconick |title=Gospel Truth |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/01/opinion/01deconink.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin |work=New York Times |date=December 1, 2007 |accessdate=2007-12-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Origen]] knew of a tradition according to which the greater circle of disciples betrayed Jesus, but does not attribute this to Judas in particular, and Origen did not deem Judas to be thoroughly corrupt (Matt., tract. xxxv).

Judas is the subject of philosophical writings, including ''[[Problem of Evil|The Problem of Natural Evil]]'' by [[Bertrand Russell]] and &quot;[[Three Versions of Judas]]&quot;, a short story by [[Jorge Luis Borges]]. They allege various problematic ideological contradictions with the discrepancy between Judas's actions and his eternal punishment.  [[John S. Feinberg]] argues that if Jesus foresees Judas's betrayal, then the betrayal is not an act of [[free will]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Predestination &amp; free will: four views of divine sovereignty &amp; human freedom |author=John S. Feinberg, David Basinger |year=2001 |page=91 |isbn=978-0-8254-3489-1|publisher=Kregel Publications}}&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore should not be punishable. Conversely, it is argued that just because the betrayal was foretold, it does not prevent Judas from exercising his own free will in this matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Exploring the gospel of John: an expository commentary |author=John Phillips |year=1986 |page=254 |isbn=978-0-87784-567-6 |publisher=InterVaristy Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other scholars argue that Judas acted in obedience to God's will.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=QRP1wF2b2V8C&amp;pg=PA407 |title=Authenticating the activities of Jesus, Bruce Chilton, Craig A. Evans |publisher=Books.google.ca |date= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The gospels suggest that Judas is apparently bound up with the fulfillment of God's purposes ({{bibleverse||John|13:18|niv}}, {{bibleverse||John|17:12|niv}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|26:23–25|niv}}, {{bibleverse||Luke|22:21–22|niv}}, {{bibleverse||Matt|27:9–10|niv}}, {{bibleverse||Acts|1:16|niv}}, {{bibleverse||Acts|1:20|niv}}),&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.ca&quot;/&gt; yet ''woe is upon him'', and he would ''have been better unborn'' ({{bibleverse||Matthew|26:23–25|niv}}). The difficulty inherent in the saying is its paradoxicality: if Judas had not been born, the Son of Man will apparently no longer go &quot;''as it is written of him''.&quot; The consequence of this apologetic approach is that Judas's actions come to be seen as necessary and unavoidable, yet leading to condemnation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=P2hx1FCnNEYC&amp;pg=PA33 |title=The place of Judas Iscariot in christology, Anthony Cane |publisher=Books.google.ca |date= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Erasmus]] believed that Judas was free to change his intention, but [[Martin Luther]] argued in rebuttal that Judas's will was immutable. [[John Calvin]] states that Judas was predestined to damnation, but writes on the question of Judas's guilt: &quot;''surely in Judas' betrayal, it will be no more right, because God himself willed that his son be delivered up and delivered him up to death, to ascribe the guilt of the crime to God than to transfer the credit for redemption to Judas.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=7R0IGTSvIVIC&amp;pg=PA419 |title=A Dictionary of biblical tradition in English literature, David L. Jeffrey |publisher=Books.google.ca |date= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is speculated that Judas's damnation, which seems possible from the Gospels' text, may not stem from his betrayal of Christ, but from the despair which caused him to subsequently commit suicide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=7R0IGTSvIVIC&amp;pg=PA418 |title=A Dictionary of biblical tradition in English literature, David L. Jeffrey |publisher=Books.google.ca |date= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; This position is not without its problems since Judas was already damned by Jesus even before he committed suicide (see {{bibleverse||John|17:12}}), but it does avoid the paradox of Judas's predestined act setting in motion both the salvation of all mankind and his own damnation. The damnation of Judas is not a universal conclusion, and some have argued that there is no indication that Judas was condemned with eternal punishment.  Others argue Judas had the free will to accept or reject Christ anytime before his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tentmaker.org/Dew/Dew3/D3-JudasIscariot.html |title=Judas Iscariot-In Heaven or in Hell? |publisher=Tentmaker.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Adam Clarke]] writes: &quot;''he [Judas] committed a heinous act of sin...but he repented ({{bibleverse||Matthew|27:3–5|niv}}) and did what he could to undo his wicked act: he had committed the sin unto death, i.e. a sin that involves the death of the body; but who can say, (if mercy was offered to Christ's murderers? ({{bibleverse||Luke|23:34|niv}})...) that the  same mercy could not be extended to wretched Judas?...''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=AC0-AAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA653 |title=The New Testament of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ: the text ... Volume 1, Adam Clarke |publisher=|date= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Giotto - Scrovegni - -31- - Kiss of Judas.jpg|thumb|''The Kiss of Judas'', by [[Giotto di Bondone]]]]

===Modern interpretations===

Most Christians still consider Judas a traitor. Indeed the term ''Judas'' has entered many languages as a [[synonym]] for ''betrayer''.

American philosopher [[Will Durant]] argues that the early Church would never create material that only embarrassed the followers of Jesus, or weakened its position with opponents (in this case, a traitor apostle).&lt;ref&gt;
Durant, Will. ''Christ and Caesar''. Simon &amp; Schuster, 1972, p. 557.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some&lt;ref&gt;Dirk Grützmacher : ''The &quot;Betrayal&quot; of Judas Iscariot : a study into the origins of Christianity and post-temple Judaism'', Edinburgh 1998 (Thesis (M.Phil) --University of Edinburgh, 1999).&lt;/ref&gt; have embraced the alternative notion that Judas was merely the negotiator in a prearranged prisoner exchange (following the [[Jesus and the Money Changers|money-changer riot]] in the Temple) that gave Jesus to the Roman authorities by mutual agreement, and that Judas's later portrayal as &quot;traitor&quot; was a historical distortion.

In his book ''[[The Passover Plot]]'' the British [[theology|theologian]] [[Hugh J. Schonfield]] argues that the crucifixion of Christ was a conscious re-enactment of Biblical [[prophecy]] and Judas acted with Jesus' full knowledge and consent in &quot;betraying&quot; his master to the authorities.

Theologian Aaron Saari contends in his work ''The Many Deaths of Judas Iscariot'' that Judas Iscariot was the literary invention of the Markan community. As Judas does not appear in the Epistles of Paul, nor in the [[Q Gospel]], Saari argues that the language indicates a split between Pauline Christians, who saw no reason for the establishment of an organized Church, and the followers of Peter. Saari contends that the denigration of Judas in Matthew and Luke-Acts has a direct correlation to the elevation of Peter.&lt;ref&gt;Saari, Aaron Maurice. ''The Many Deaths of Judas Iscariot: A Meditation on Suicide'' London: Routledge, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Further evidence of the absence of the Judas story in the earliest Christian documents is drawn on the basis of {{bibleverse||Matthew|19:28|niv}} and {{bibleverse||Luke|22:28–30|niv}}. Here Jesus tells his disciples that they will “sit on the twelve thrones judging the twelve tribes of Israel.” No exception is made for Judas even though Jesus was aware of his impending act of betrayal. The answer may lie in the fact that the source of these verses could be the hypothetical [[Q document]] (QS 62). Q is thought to predate the gospels and would be one of the earliest Christian documents. Given that possibility, the betrayal story could have been invented by the writer of Mark.&lt;ref&gt;Cable L W ''[http://www.inu.net/skeptic/judas.htm Judas Iscariot, Betrayer or Enabler, Fact or Fiction?]'' in [http://www.inu.net/skeptic/ Sceptics Corner] essay collection&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=Hhv_lx9wSXIC&amp;pg=PA390 Q 22:28,30 By Paul Hoffmann, Stefan H. Brandenburger, Christoph Heil, Ulrike Brauner, International Q Project, Thomas].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=c9K_6NN3llcC&amp;pg=PA186 Jesus, apocalyptic prophet of the new millennium By Bart D. Ehrman].&lt;/ref&gt;
The book ''The Sins of the Scripture'', by [[John Shelby Spong]], investigates the possibility that early [[Christian]]s compiled the Judas story from three [[Old Testament]] [[Jew]]ish betrayal stories. He writes, &quot;...the act of betrayal by a member of the twelve disciples is not found in the earliest Christian writings. Judas is first placed into the Christian story by the [[Gospel of Mark]] ([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=mark%203:19 3:19]), who wrote in the early years of the eighth decade of the Common Era.&quot; He points out that some of the Gospels, after the Crucifixion, refer to the number of Disciples as &quot;Twelve&quot;, as if Judas were still among them. He compares the three conflicting descriptions of Judas's death — hanging, leaping into a pit, and disemboweling — with three Old Testament betrayals followed by similar suicides.

Spong's conclusion is that early [[Authors of the Bible|Bible authors]], after the [[First Jewish-Roman War]], sought to distance themselves from [[Ancient Rome|Rome]]'s enemies. They augmented the [[Gospels]] with a story of a disciple, personified in Judas as the Jewish state, who either betrayed or handed over Jesus to his Roman crucifiers. Spong identifies this augmentation with the origin of modern [[Anti-Semitism]].

Jewish scholar [[Hyam Maccoby]], suggests that in the New Testament, the name &quot;Judas&quot; was constructed as an attack on the Judaeans or on the Judaean religious establishment held responsible for executing Christ.&lt;ref&gt;Hyam Maccoby, Antisemitism And Modernity, Routledge 2006, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; The English word &quot;[[Jew]]&quot; is derived from the [[Latin]] ''Iudaeus'', which, like the [[Greek language|Greek]] Ιουδαίος (''[[Ioudaios]]''), could also mean &quot;Judaean&quot;.

==Role in apocrypha==
Judas has been a figure of great interest to esoteric groups, such as many [[Gnostic]] sects. [[Irenaeus]] records the beliefs of one Gnostic sect, the [[Cainite]]s, who believed that Judas was an instrument of the [[Sophia (wisdom)|Sophia]], Divine Wisdom, thus earning the hatred of the [[Demiurge]]. In the [[Hebrew Bible]], the book of [[Book of Zechariah|Zechariah]], the one who casts [[thirty pieces of silver]], as Judas does in the Gospels, is a servant of God. His betrayal of Jesus thus was a victory over the materialist world. The Cainites later split into two groups, disagreeing over the ultimate significance of Jesus in their cosmology.

===Gospel of Judas===
{{Main|Gospel of Judas}}
During the 1970s, a [[Coptic language|Coptic]] [[papyrus]] [[codex]] (book) was discovered near Beni Masah, [[Egypt]] which appeared to be a 3rd- or 4th-century-AD copy of a 2nd-century original,&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www9.nationalgeographic.com/lostgospel/timeline.html Timeline of early Christianity]'' at ''National Geographic''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/4882420.stm Judas 'helped Jesus save mankind']'' BBC News, 7 May 2006  (following ''National Geographic'' publication)&lt;/ref&gt; describing the story of [[Historical Jesus|Jesus]]'s death from the viewpoint of Judas. At its conclusion, the text identifies itself as &quot;the Gospel of Judas&quot; (''Euangelion Ioudas'').

The discovery was given dramatic international exposure in April 2006 when the US ''National Geographic'' magazine (for its May edition) published a feature article entitled ''The Gospel of Judas'' with images of the fragile codex and analytical commentary by relevant experts and interested observers (but not a comprehensive translation). The article's introduction stated: &quot;An ancient text lost for 1,700 years says Christ's betrayer was his truest disciple&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cockburn A ''[http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/2006/05/judas-gospel/cockburn-text.html The Gospel of Judas]'' ''National Geographic'' (USA) May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The article points to some evidence that the original document was extant in the 2nd century: &quot;Around A.D. 180, [[Irenaeus]], Bishop of Lyon in what was then Roman Gaul, wrote a massive treatise called ''[[On the Detection and Overthrow of the So-Called Gnosis|Against Heresies]]'' [in which he attacked] a 'fictitious history,' which 'they style the Gospel of Judas.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cockburn A [http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/2006/05/judas-gospel/cockburn-text/3 at page 3]&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the magazine's edition was circulated, other news media gave exposure to the story, abridging and selectively reporting it.&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews.com&quot;/&gt;

In December 2007, a ''[[The New York Times|New York Times]]'' [[op-ed]] article by [[April DeConick]] asserted that the [[National Geographic Society|''National Geographic'']]'s translation is badly flawed: For example, in one instance the ''National Geographic'' transcription refers to Judas as a &quot;daimon&quot;, which the society’s experts have translated as &quot;spirit&quot;. However, the universally accepted word for &quot;spirit&quot; is &quot;pneuma&quot; — in Gnostic literature &quot;daimon&quot; is always taken to mean &quot;demon&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Deconick A D ''[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/01/opinion/01deconink.html Gospel Truth]'' ''New York Times'' 1 December 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Geographic Society]] responded that &quot;Virtually all issues April D. DeConick raises about translation choices are addressed in footnotes in both the popular and critical editions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://press.nationalgeographic.com/pressroom/index.jsp?pageID=pressReleases_detail&amp;siteID=1&amp;cid=1196944434958 Statement from National Geographic in Response to April DeConick's New York Times Op-Ed &quot;Gospel Truth&quot;]''&lt;/ref&gt; In a later review of the issues and relevant publications, critic [[Joan Acocella]] questioned whether ulterior intentions had not begun to supersede historical analysis, e.g., whether publication of ''The Gospel of Judas'' could be an attempt to roll back ancient anti-semitic imputations. She concluded that the ongoing clash between scriptural fundamentalism and attempts at revision were childish because of the unreliability of the sources. Therefore, she argued, &quot;People interpret, and cheat. The answer is not to fix the Bible but to fix ourselves.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Acocella J ''[http://www.newyorker.com/arts/critics/atlarge/2009/08/03/090803crat_atlarge_acocella?currentPage=all Betrayal: Should we hate Judas Iscariot?]'' ''The New Yorker'' 3&amp;nbsp;August 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Other scholars have questioned the initial translation and interpretation of the ''Gospel of Judas'' by the National Geographic team of experts.&lt;ref name=&quot;erudit.org&quot;/&gt;

===Gospel of Barnabas===
According to medieval copies (the earliest copies from the 15th century) of the [[Gospel of Barnabas]] it was Judas, not Jesus, who was crucified on the cross. This work states that Judas's appearance was transformed to that of Jesus', when the former, out of betrayal, led the Roman soldiers to arrest Jesus who by then was ascended to the heavens. This transformation of appearance was so identical that the masses, followers of Christ, and even the Mother of Jesus, Mary, initially thought that the one arrested and crucified was Jesus himself. The gospel then mentions that after three days since burial, Judas's body was stolen from his grave, and then the rumors spread of Jesus being risen from the dead. When Jesus was informed in the third heaven about what happened, he prayed to God to be sent back to the earth, and descended and gathered his mother, disciples, and followers, and told them the truth of what happened.  He then ascended back to the heavens, and will come back at the end of times as a just king.

==Representations and symbolism==
The term ''Judas'' has entered many languages as a synonym for ''betrayer'', and Judas has become the archetype of the traitor in Western art and literature. Judas is given some role in virtually all literature telling the [[Passion (Christianity)|Passion]] story, and appears in a number of modern novels and movies.

In the [[Eastern Orthodox]] hymns of [[Holy Wednesday]] (the Wednesday before [[Easter|Pascha]]), Judas is contrasted with the woman who anointed Jesus with expensive [[perfume]] and washed his feet with her tears. According to the [[Gospel of John]], Judas protested at this apparent extravagance, suggesting that the money spent on it should have been given to the poor. After this, Judas went to the chief priests and offered to betray Jesus for money. The hymns of Holy Wednesday contrast these two figures, encouraging believers to avoid the example of the fallen disciple and instead to imitate Mary's example of repentance. Also, Wednesday is observed as a day of fasting from meat, dairy products, and olive oil throughout the year in memory of the betrayal of Judas. The prayers of preparation for receiving the [[Eucharist]] also make mention of Judas's betrayal: &quot;I will not reveal your mysteries to your enemies, neither like Judas will I betray you with a kiss, but like the thief on the cross I will confess you.&quot;

[[File:Beso de Judas.png|thumb|A red-haired Judas betrays Jesus with [[kiss of Judas|a kiss]] in a Spanish ''[[paso]]'' figure.]]
Judas Iscariot is often represented with [[red hair]] in [[Spanish culture]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DRAE&quot;&gt;[http://buscon.rae.es/draeI/SrvltObtenerHtml?LEMA=pelo&amp;SUPIND=0&amp;CAREXT=10000&amp;NEDIC=No#pelo_de_cofre,_o_pelo_de_Judas. pelo de Judas] (&quot;Judas hair&quot;) in the ''[[Diccionario de la Real Academia Española]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eclectic&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=WX3QAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=judas%20hair&amp;pg=PA314#v=onepage&amp;q=judas%20hair&amp;f=false Page 314] of article ''Red Hair'' from ''[[Bentley's Miscellany]]'', July 1851. ''[[The eclectic magazine of foreign literature, science, and art]]'', Volumen 2; Volumen 23, [[Leavitt, Trow, &amp; Co.]], 1851.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanco&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=O5UMAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=judas%20hair&amp;pg=PA256#v=onepage&amp;q=judas%20hair&amp;f=false Page 256] of ''[[Letters from Spain]]'', [[Joseph Blanco White]], [[H. Colburn]], 1825.&lt;/ref&gt;
and by [[William Shakespeare]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanco&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Glossary&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=EWcPAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=judas%20hair&amp;pg=PA473#v=onepage&amp;q=judas%20hair&amp;f=false Judas colour] in page 473 of ''A glossary: or, Collection of words, phrases, names, and allusions to customs, proverbs, etc., which have been thought to require illustration, in the words of English authors, particularly [[Shakespeare]], and his contemporaries,'' Volumen 1. [[Robert Nares]], [[James Orchard Halliwell-Phillipps]], [[Thomas Wright (antiquarian)|Thomas Wright]]. [[J.R. Smith]], 1859&lt;/ref&gt; The practice is comparable to the Renaissance portrayal of Jews with red hair, which was then regarded as a negative trait and which may have been used to correlate Judas Iscariot with contemporary Jews.&lt;ref&gt;''Judas's Red Hair and The Jews'', ''Journal of Jewish Art (9)'', 1982, Melinnkoff R.M&lt;/ref&gt;

==Art and literature==
Judas has become the archetype of the betrayer in Western culture, with some role in virtually all literature telling the [[Passion (Christianity)|Passion]] story.
* Judas is the subject of one of the oldest surviving English ballads, which dates from the 13th century. [[Judas (ballad)|In the ballad]], the blame for the betrayal of Christ is placed on his sister.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jstor.org/stable/456954&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Dante Alighieri|Dante]]'s ''[[Inferno (Dante)|Inferno]]'', he is condemned to the lowest circle of [[Hell]], the Ninth Circle for Traitors, also known as [[Cocytus]], where he is one of three sinners deemed evil enough that they are doomed to be chewed for eternity in the mouths of the triple-headed [[Satan]] (the others being [[Marcus Junius Brutus the Younger|Brutus]] and [[Gaius Cassius Longinus|Cassius]], the assassins of [[Julius Caesar]]).&lt;ref&gt;http://danteworlds.laits.utexas.edu/circle9.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* In art, one of the most famous depictions of Judas Iscariot and his kiss of betrayal of Jesus is [[The Taking of Christ (Caravaggio)|The Taking of Christ]] by Italian Baroque artist, [[Caravaggio]], done in 1602.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nga.gov/exhibitions/caravbr-2.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* In ''Memoirs of Judas'' (1867) by [[Ferdinando Petruccelli della Gattina]], he is seen as a  leader of the Jewish revolt against the rule of Romans.&lt;ref&gt;Baldassare Labanca, ''Gesù Cristo nella letteratura contemporanea, straniera e italiana'', Fratelli Bocca, 1903, p.240&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Edward Elgar]]'s [[oratorio]], ''[[The Apostles (Elgar)|The Apostles]]'', depicts Judas as wanting to force Jesus to declare his divinity and establish the kingdom on earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;{{Citation
|author=|editorn-last=Adams|editorn-first=Byron|title=Edward Elgar and His World|url=http://www.amazon.com/Edward-Elgar-World-Music-Festival/dp/0691134464/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1330012535&amp;sr=8-1|format=book|year=2007|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-0-691-13446-8|pages=140–141}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Autun cathédrale chapiteau pendaison de Judas.jpg|thumb|Cathédrale Saint-Lazare, [[Autun]]. Judas hangs himself]]
* In ''Trial of Christ in Seven Stages'' (1909) by [[John Brayshaw Kaye]], the author did not accept the idea that Judas intended to betray Christ, and the poem is a defence of Judas, in which he adds his own vision to the biblical account of the story of the trial before the [[Sanhedrin]] and [[Caiaphas]].&lt;ref name=mag&gt;''The Magazine of poetry, Volume 2, Issues 1–4'' (1890) Charles Wells Moulton, Buffalo, New York [http://books.google.com/books?id=EdgKAAAAYAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s]&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 1954, Jose Limon choreographed &quot;The Traitor,&quot; a depiction of the betrayal of Jesus by Judas, and also commentary on the naming of names in McCarthy's House Un-American Activity Hearings.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.limon.org/News/newsletter07.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*In [[Mikhail Bulgakov]]'s novel ''[[The Master and Margarita]]'', Judas is paid by the high priest of Judaea to testify against Jesus, who had been inciting trouble among the people of Jerusalem. After authorizing the crucifixion, Pilate suffers an agony of regret and turns his anger on Judas, ordering him assassinated. The story-within-a-story appears as a counter-revolutionary novel in the context of Moscow in the 1920s–1930s.&lt;ref&gt;http://rt.com/all-about-russia/literature/mikhail-bulgakov/the-master-and-margarita/how-the-procurator-tried-to-save-judas-of-karioth/&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Three Versions of Judas|Tres versiones de Judas]]'' ([[English language|English]] title: '&quot;Three Versions of Judas&quot;') is a short story by Argentine writer and poet [[Jorge Luis Borges]]. It was included in Borges' anthology, ''[[Ficciones]]'', published in 1944, and revolves around the main character's doubts about the canonical story of Judas who instead creates three alternative versions.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.equinoxpub.com/equinox/books/showbook.asp?bkid=430&amp;keyword=&lt;/ref&gt;
* The film ''[[King of Kings (1961 film)|King of Kings]]'' presents Judas betraying Jesus as a means to force an attack on the Romans, rather than Jesus' death: &quot;I will force his hand! When he feels the Roman sword at his throat he will smite them down with the wave of one arm.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.filmscoremonthly.com/notes/king_of_kings2.html | work=Film Score Monthly | first=George | last=Komar | title=FSM: King of Kings (Miklós Rózsa) | accessdate=2012-Apr-09 | quote = So he betrays Jesus in order to force Jesus’ hand to use his miraculous powers to defeat the Romans.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Andrew Lloyd Webber]]'s musical ''[[Jesus Christ Superstar]]'', Judas is portrayed as a [[tragic hero]] who believed that Jesus was not the son of God, but rather just a man. Since he feared that if Jesus' following grew too large then the Romans would attack and kill the Jews, he betrayed Jesus to [[Caiaphas]] and [[Annas]] to prevent a bloodbath.
* [[Taylor Caldwell]]'s 1978 novel ''I, Judas'' portrays Judas as a much misunderstood political person who conspires with the Zealots for the sake of Jewish liberation and who is persuaded that an appearance before the Sanhedrin will offer Jesus an opportunity to prove himself.  This view of Judas Iscariot is also featured in the miniseries ''[[Jesus of Nazareth (miniseries)|Jesus of Nazareth]]''
* In [[Martin Scorsese]]'s film ''[[The Last Temptation of Christ (film)|The Last Temptation of Christ]],'' based on the novel by [[Nikos Kazantzakis]], Judas Iscariot's only motivation in betraying Jesus to the Romans was to help him accomplish his mission by mutual agreement, making Judas the catalyst for the event later interpreted as bringing about humanity's salvation.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.decentfilms.com/articles/lasttemptation&lt;/ref&gt; This view of Judas Iscariot is reflected in the recently discovered [[Gospel of Judas]] and was also featured in [[Robert Graves]]'s novel ''[[King Jesus]]'', [[Michael Moorcock]]'s novel ''[[Behold the Man (novel)|Behold the Man]]'', [[Morley Callaghan]]'s novel ''[[A Time for Judas]]'', [[José Saramago]]'s novel ''[[The Gospel According to Jesus Christ]]'', [[Éric-Emmanuel Schmitt]]'s novel ''[[The Gospel According to Pilate]]'' and in [[Gerald Messadié]]'s novel ''Judas le bien-aimé''.
* In the short story ''[[The Way of Cross and Dragon]]'' by [[George R.R. Martin]], a cult in the distant future has risen up and made a saint of Judas Iscariot.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.epubbud.com/book.php?g=DDMLB4TL&lt;/ref&gt;
* In ''[[The Last Days of Judas Iscariot]]'', a critically acclaimed play by Stephen Adly Guirgis, Judas is given a trial in Purgatory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://theater.nytimes.com/mem/theater/treview.html?res=9B06E0DB133DF930A35750C0A9639C8B63 | work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Leon Rosselson]] song &quot;Stand Up for Judas&quot; presents Judas in a positive light, as a revolutionary who wanted justice in this world, not the next.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dickgaughan.co.uk/songs/texts/judas.html&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--- Not sure this is a great reference, but it needs to be one that has the lyrics ---&gt;
* In [[Dracula 2000]], it is suggested that the legendary vampire is actually Judas Iscariot, who, after his betrayal of Christ, hanged himself at dawn the day after he handed Christ over to the Roman authorities, to embrace death but was cursed by God for his actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9B05EFD91738F930A15751C1A9669C8B63 | work=The New York Times | first=Stephen | last=Holden | title=FILM REVIEW; Those Wacky, Drooling, Foaming, Biting Undead | date=2000-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; This version attempts to explain why vampires in folklore have aversions to Christian relics (for betraying Christ), stakes (for the spikes that were used to nail Christ's hands and feet to the cross), silver (for the 30 silver he accepted) and sunlight (for hanging himself at dawn).
* In the TV movie ''[[Judas (film)|Judas]]'', Judas sincerely took Jesus as the future King of Israel, but when Jesus refused to take real action to depose the Romans became disappointed and finally betrayed the man he thought would lead them to victory.
* In [[C. K. Stead]]'s novel ''My Name Was Judas,'' Judas, who was then known as Idas of Sidon, recounts the story of Jesus and recalled by him some forty years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2006/nov/18/featuresreviews.guardianreview27 | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Jenny | last=Diski | title=Review: My Name Was Judas by CK Stead | date=2006-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The American recording artist [[Lady Gaga]] explained that her song &quot;[[Judas (song)|Judas]]&quot; (2011) is a metaphor and an analogy about forgiveness and betrayal and things that haunt you in your life.&lt;ref name=&quot;msnca&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://entertainment.ca.msn.com/music/features/pop-culture-as-religion-lady-gaga-explains-the-controversial-biblical-imagery-in-her-upcoming-music-video-judas|title=Pop culture as religion: Lady Gaga explains the controversial biblical imagery in her upcoming music video &quot;Judas&quot;|last=Ritchie|first=Kevin|date=2011-04-26|accessdate=2011-04-27|publisher=[[MSN]]. [[Microsoft]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zPkl7xyU|archivedate=2011-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the short story &quot;Kakekomi uttae&quot; (Heed My Plea) by [[Osamu Dazai]], Judas narrates the story of his betrayal to Jesus.
* The character of William Barrow in ''The Judas Chronicles'' series by [[Aiden James]] is in reality Judas, cursed to walk the earth as a cursed immortal and now an archivist for the Smithsonian Institute and part-time operative for the CIA.
* In the TNT film [[The Librarian: Curse of the Judas Chalice]] Flynn Carsen must find the Judas Chalice, which is revealed to be a vampiric Holy Grail made out of the 30 pieces of silver given to Judas—the world's first vampire.

==See also==
{{portal|Christianity}}
* [[Gospel of Judas]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;Luke&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Luke%2022:3&amp;version=31
|title=BibleGateway.com – Passage Lookup: Luke 22:3
|publisher=[[BibleGateway]]
|accessdate=2008-06-21}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Arie W. Zwiep page 109&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Zwiep
|first=Arie W
|title=Judas and the choice of Matthias: a study on context and concern of Acts 1:15–26
|page=109
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==External links==
&lt;!-- Wikipedia is NOT a link depository. Considering all the commercial links on this site before (and the POV status that has ''still'' not been removed), links added to this entry will be watched RATHER CLOSELY. --&gt;
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
{{Commons category|Judas Iscariot}}
*[http://www.hellandjustice.com/romans_josephus.htm The Prophecy of Judas in Psalm 41 Video]
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08539a.htm Judas Iscariot: Catholic Encyclopedia article published 1910]
*[http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=671&amp;letter=J Jewish Encyclopedia: Judas Iscariot]
*[http://www.lieberknecht.de/~diss/papers/p_judas.htm &quot;Death and Retribution: Medieval Visions of the End of Judas the Traitor&quot; – 1997 lecture by Dr Otfried Lieberknecht]
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/01/opinion/01deconink.html?ex=1354251600&amp;en=4aa1c48adc771d13&amp;ei=5090 Gospel Truth]
{{Apostles}}
{{New Testament people}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Iscariot, Judas
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Biblical apostle
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Iscariot, Judas}}
[[Category:Ancient people who committed suicide]]
[[Category:Christianity and antisemitism]]
[[Category:Twelve Apostles]]
[[Category:1st-century deaths]]
[[Category:Suicides by hanging]]
[[Category:Judas Iscariot| ]]
[[Category:Biblical apostles]]

[[ar:يهوذا الإسخريوطي]]
[[an:Chudas Escariot]]
[[arc:ܝܗܘܕܐ ܣܟܪܝܘܛܐ]]
[[bg:Юда Искариотски]]
[[bo:ཡུ་དཱ་དབྱི་སི་ཀར།]]
[[br:Judaz Iskariot]]
[[ca:Judes Iscariot]]
[[cs:Jidáš Iškariotský]]
[[da:Judas Iskariot]]
[[de:Judas Ischariot]]
[[et:Juudas Iskariot]]
[[el:Ιούδας Ισκαριώτης]]
[[es:Judas Iscariote]]
[[eo:Judaso Iskarioto]]
[[eu:Juda Iskariote]]
[[fa:یهودا اسخریوطی]]
[[fr:Judas Iscariote]]
[[gl:Xudas Iscariote]]
[[ko:이스가리옷 유다]]
[[hy:Հուդա Իսկարիովտացի]]
[[hi:जूडस इस्कैरियट]]
[[hr:Juda Iškariotski]]
[[ilo:Judas Iscariote]]
[[id:Yudas Iskariot]]
[[it:Giuda Iscariota]]
[[he:יהודה איש קריות]]
[[jv:Yudas Iskariot]]
[[ka:იუდა ისკარიოტელი]]
[[sw:Yuda Iskarioti]]
[[la:Iudas Iscariot]]
[[lv:Jūda Iskariots]]
[[lt:Judas Iskariotas]]
[[hu:Iskarióti Júdás]]
[[ml:യൂദാസ് സ്കറിയോത്ത]]
[[ms:Judas Iscariot]]
[[nl:Judas Iskariot]]
[[ja:イスカリオテのユダ]]
[[no:Judas Iskariot]]
[[nn:Judas Iskariot]]
[[oc:Judàs Escariòt]]
[[nds:Judas Ischariot]]
[[pl:Judasz Iskariota]]
[[pt:Judas Iscariotes]]
[[ro:Iuda Iscarioteanul]]
[[ru:Иуда Искариот]]
[[simple:Judas Iscariot]]
[[sk:Judáš Iškariotský]]
[[sl:Juda Iškarijot]]
[[sr:Јуда Искариотски]]
[[sh:Juda Iskariotski]]
[[fi:Juudas Iskariot]]
[[sv:Judas Iskariot]]
[[ta:யூதாசு இஸ்காரியோத்து]]
[[tl:Hudas Iskariote]]
[[te:జుడాస్ ఇస్కారియట్]]
[[th:ยูดาส อิสคาริโอท]]
[[tr:Yehuda (havari)]]
[[uk:Юда Іскаріот]]
[[vi:Giuđa Ítcariốt]]
[[wa:Djuda Iscariote]]
[[zh:加略人猶大]]</text>
      <sha1>6u9ck2u9pl07mro0cz66bu8105c4etf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
