<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Last Supper</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30667</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519379676</id>
      <parentid>519375097</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T12:41:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marauder40</username>
        <id>7651504</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rvv</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41879">{{Other uses2|The Last Supper}}
[[File:Última Cena - Da Vinci 5.jpg|thumb|400px|right|
Depictions of the [[Last Supper in Christian art]] have been undertaken by artistic masters for centuries, [[The Last Supper (Leonardo da Vinci)|Leonardo da Vinci's late 1490s mural painting]] in [[Milan]], [[Italy]], being perhaps the best known example.&lt;ref name=Zuffi /&gt;]]

The '''Last Supper''' is the final meal that, according to [[Christianity|Christian]] belief, [[Jesus]] shared with his [[Apostles]] in [[Jerusalem]] before [[Crucifixion of Jesus|his crucifixion]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Last Supper. The final meal of Christ with His Apostles on the night before the Crucifixion.&quot;, Cross, F. L., &amp; Livingstone, E. A. (2005). The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (3rd ed. rev.) (958). Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; The Last Supper is commemorated by Christians especially on [[Maundy Thursday]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=1UWp5pi1SdUC&amp;pg=PA64&amp;dq=maundy+thursday+evening+jewish&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=mz57T9XcJOHv0gHhqISbBg&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=maundy%20thursday%20evening%20jewish&amp;f=false|title = Worship and Festivals|publisher=[[Heinemann (publisher)|Heinemann]]|author=Gwyneth Windsor, John Hughes|quote=On the Thursday, which is known as Maundy Thursday, Christians remember the Last Supper which Jesus had with His disciples. It was the Jewish Feast of the Passover, and the meal which they had together was the traditional ''Seder'' meal, eaten that evening by the Jews everywhere.|date=21 November 1990|accessdate =11 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, The Last Supper provides the scriptural basis for the [[Eucharist]], also known as &quot;Holy Communion&quot; or &quot;The Lord's Supper&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=edXChxGzxgoC&amp;pg=PA34&amp;dq=Last+Supper+Communion+Christians&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=JER7T6rtOYyL0QHx0OSpBg&amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Last%20Supper%20Communion%20Christians&amp;f=false|title = Inside Christianity|publisher=Lorenz Educational Press|author=Walter Hazen|quote=The Anglican Church in England uses the term Holy Communion. In the Roman Catholic Church, both terms are used. Most Protestant churches refer to the sacrament simply as communion or The Lord's Supper. Communion reenacts the Last Supper that Jesus ate with His disciples before He was arrested and crucified.|date=1 September 2002|accessdate =3 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[First Epistle to the Corinthians]] is the earliest known mention of the Last Supper. The four [[canonical Gospel]]s all state that the Last Supper took place towards the end of the week, after Jesus' [[triumphal entry into Jerusalem]] and that Jesus and his disciples shared a meal shortly before Jesus was crucified at the end of that week.&lt;ref name=CEvans465 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Fahlbusch52 /&gt; During the meal [[Jesus predicts his betrayal]] by one of the disciples present, and foretells that, before next morning, [[Apostle Peter|Peter]] will [[Denial of Peter|deny knowing him]].&lt;ref name=CEvans465 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Fahlbusch52 /&gt; 

The three [[Synoptic Gospel]]s and the First Epistle to the Corinthians include the account of the institution of the [[Eucharist]] in which Jesus takes bread, breaks it and gives it to the disciples, saying: &quot;This is my body which is given for you&quot;.&lt;ref name=CEvans465 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Fahlbusch52 /&gt; The Gospel of John does not include this episode, but tells of Jesus [[washing the feet of the Apostles]], giving [[The New Commandment|the new commandment]] &quot;to love one another as I have loved you&quot;, and has a detailed [[farewell discourse]] by Jesus, calling the Apostles who follow his teachings &quot;friends and not servants&quot;, as he prepares them for his departure.&lt;ref name=ODCC/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Gospel according to John'' by Colin G. Kruse 2004 ISBN 0-8028-2771-3 page 103&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholars have looked to the Last Supper as the source of early Christian Eucharist traditions.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The custom of placing the eucharist at the heart of the worship and fellowship of the Church may have been inspired not only by the disciples’ memory of the Last Supper with Jesus but also by the memory of their fellowship meals with Him during both His days on earth and the forty days of His risen appearances.&quot;, Bromiley, G. W. (1988; 2002). Vol. 3: The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia, Revised (164). Wm. B. Eerdmans.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Christian Worship 2005&quot;&gt;The Oxford History of Christian Worship. Oxford University Press, USA. 2005. ISBN 0-19-513886-4&lt;/ref&gt; Others see the account of the Last Supper as derived from 1st-century eucharistic practice&lt;ref name=&quot;Christian Worship 2005&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;ActJIntro&quot;&gt;[[Robert W. Funk|Funk, Robert W.]] and the [[Jesus Seminar]]. ''The acts of Jesus: the search for the authentic deeds of Jesus.'' HarperSanFrancisco. 1998. Introduction, p. 1-40&lt;/ref&gt; as described by Paul in the mid-50s.
{{Gospel Jesus}}

==The name and its usage==
The term &quot;Last Supper&quot; does not appear in the [[New Testament]].&lt;ref&gt;''An Episcopal dictionary of the church'' by Donald S. Armentrout, Robert Boak Slocum 2005 ISBN 0-89869-211-3 page 292&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fitzmyer1378 &gt;''The Gospel according to Luke: introduction, translation, and notes, Volume 28, Part 1'' by Joseph A. Fitzmyer 1995 ISBN 0-385-00515-6 page 1378&lt;/ref&gt; However, traditionally, many Christians refer to the New Testament accounts of the last meal Jesus shared with his disciples as the Last Supper.&lt;ref name=Fitzmyer1378 /&gt; The Last Supper was likely a retelling of the events of the last meal of Jesus among the [[Early Christianity|early Christian community]], and became a ritual which recounted that meal.&lt;ref&gt;''''The church according to the New Testament'' by Daniel J. Harrington 2001 ISBN 1-58051-111-2 page 49&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anglican]]s and [[Presbyterian]]s use the term &quot;Lord's Supper&quot;, stating that the term &quot;last&quot; suggests this was one of several meals and not ''the'' meal.&lt;ref&gt;''The Companion to the Book of Common Worship'' by Peter C. Bower 2003 ISBN 0-664-50232-6 pages 115-116&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Liturgical year: the worship of God'' Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.) 1992 ISBN 978-0-664-25350-9 page 37&lt;/ref&gt; The term &quot;Lord's Supper&quot; refers both to the biblical event and the act of [[Eucharist]]ic celebration within [[liturgy]]. Many Protestants also use the term Lord's Supper.&lt;ref name=Bard493 &gt;''Humanists and Reformers: A History of the Renaissance and Reformation'' by Bard Thompson 1996 ISBN 978-0-8028-6348-5 pages 493-494&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Eastern Orthodox]] use the term &quot;Mystical Supper&quot; which refers both to the biblical event and the act of Eucharistic celebration within liturgy.&lt;ref&gt;''The Orthodox Church'' by John Anthony McGuckin 2010 ISBN 978-1-4443-3731-0 pages 297 and 293&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scriptural basis==
The last meal that Jesus shared with his disciples is described in all four [[canonical Gospel]]s, namely in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Matthew#26:17|Matthew 26:17-30]], [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Mark#14:12|Mark 14:12-26]], [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Luke#22:7|Luke 22:7-39]] and [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#13:1|John 13:1-17:26]]. This meal later became known as the Last Supper.&lt;ref name=Fahlbusch52 &gt;''The Encyclopedia of Christianity, Volume 4'' by Erwin Fahlbusch, 2005 ISBN 978-0-8028-2416-5 pages 52-56&lt;/ref&gt; 

Paul's [[First Epistle to the Corinthians]] ([[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/1 Corinthians#11:23|11:23-26]]), which was likely written before the Gospels, includes a reference to the Last Supper but emphasizes the theological basis rather than giving a detailed description of the event or its background.&lt;ref name=Fahlbusch52 /&gt;&lt;ref name=CEvans465 &gt;The Bible Knowledge Background Commentary'' by Craig A. Evans 2003 ISBN 0-7814-3868-3 pages 465-477&lt;/ref&gt;

===Background and setting===
The overall narrative that is shared in all Gospel accounts that leads to the Last Supper is that after the [[Triumphal entry into Jerusalem]] early in the week, and encounters with various people and the Jewish elders, Jesus and his disciples share a meal towards the end of the week. After the meal Jesus is betrayed, arrested, tried and then [[Crucifixion of Jesus|crucified]].&lt;ref name=CEvans465 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Fahlbusch52 /&gt;

Key events in the meal are the preparation of the disciples for the departure of Jesus, the predictions about the impending betrayal of Jesus, and the foretelling of the upcoming denial of Jesus by [[Apostle Peter]].&lt;ref name=Fahlbusch52 /&gt;&lt;ref name=CEvans465 /&gt;

===Prediction of Judas' betrayal===
{{Main|Jesus predicts his betrayal}}
In [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Matthew#26:24|Matthew 26:24-25]], [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Mark#14:18|Mark 14:18-21]], [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Luke#22:21|Luke 22:21-23]] and [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#13:21|John 13:21-30]] during the meal, Jesus predicted that one of [[Twelve Apostles|his Apostles]] would betray him.&lt;ref name=Cox182 &gt;Steven L. Cox, Kendell H Easley, 2007 ''Harmony of the Gospels'' ISBN 0-8054-9444-8 page 182&lt;/ref&gt; Jesus is described as reiterating, despite each Apostle's assertion that he would not betray Jesus, that the betrayer would be one of those who were present, and saying that there would be ''woe to the man who betrays the [[Son of man (Christianity)|Son of man]]! It would be better for him if he had not been born.''&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref|Mark|14:20-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Matthew#26:23|Matthew 26:23-25]] and [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#13:26|John 13:26-27]] [[Judas]] is specifically identified as the traitor. In the Gospel of John, when asked about the traitor Jesus states: &quot;He it is, for whom I shall dip the sop, and give it him. So when he had dipped the sop, he taketh and giveth it to Judas, the son of Simon Iscariot.&quot;&lt;ref name=CEvans465 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Fahlbusch52 /&gt;

===Institution of the Eucharist===
{{Main|Eucharist}}

The Eucharist, which &quot;is recorded as celebrated by the early Christian community at [[Jerusalem in Christianity|Jerusalem]] and by St. Paul on his visit to Troas&quot;, is held to have been instituted by Christ.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Acts|20:7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ODCC&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church / editors, F. L. Cross &amp; E. A. Livingstone 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3, article ''Eucharist''&lt;/ref&gt;

The institution of the Lord's Supper is recorded in the three Synoptic Gospels and in Paul's first epistle to the Corinthians. The words of institution differ slightly in each account, reflecting a Marcan tradition (upon which Matthew is based) and a Pauline tradition (upon which Luke is based).&lt;ref name=&quot;NBD&quot;&gt;&quot;Lord's Supper, The&quot; in ''New Bible Dictionary'', 3rd edition; IVP, 1996; page 697&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Luke 22:19b-20 is a disputed text, which does not appear in some of the early manuscripts of Luke. Some scholars therefore believe that it is an [[Interpolation (manuscripts)|interpolation]], while others have argued that it is original.&lt;ref name=&quot;NBD&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|author=Craig Blomberg|title=Jesus and the Gospels|year=1997|publisher=Apollos|pages=333}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A comparison of the accounts given in the Gospels and 1 Corinthians is shown in the table below, with text from the [[American Standard Version|ASV]]. The disputed text from Luke 22:19b-20 is in italics.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! &lt;small&gt;[[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Mark#14:22|Mark 14:22-24]]&lt;/small&gt;
| And as they were eating, he took bread, and when he had blessed, he brake it, and gave to them, and said, ‘Take ye: this is my body.’
| And he took a cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave to them: and they all drank of it. And he said unto them, ‘This is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many.’
|-
! &lt;small&gt;[[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Matthew#26:26|Matthew 26:26-28]]&lt;/small&gt;
| And as they were eating, Jesus took bread, and blessed, and brake it; and he gave to the disciples, and said, ‘Take, eat; this is my body.’
| And he took a cup, and gave thanks, and gave to them, saying, ‘Drink ye all of it; for this is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many unto remission of sins.’
|-
! &lt;small&gt;[[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/1 Corinthians#11:23|1 Corinthians 11:23-25]]&lt;/small&gt;
| For I received of the Lord that which also I delivered unto you, that the Lord Jesus in the night in which he was betrayed took bread; and when he had given thanks, he brake it, and said, ‘This is my body, which is for you: this do in remembrance of me.’
| In like manner also the cup, after supper, saying, ‘This cup is the new covenant in my blood: this do, as often as ye drink it, in remembrance of me.’
|-
! &lt;small&gt;[[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Luke#22:19|Luke 22:19-20]]&lt;/small&gt;
| And he took bread, and when he had given thanks, he brake it, and gave to them, saying, ‘This is my body ''which is given for you: this do in remembrance of me.’''
| ''And the cup in like manner after supper, saying, ‘This cup is the new covenant in my blood, even that which is poured out for you.’''
|}

Jesus' actions in sharing the bread and wine have been linked with Isaiah 53:12,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Isaiah|53:12}}&lt;/ref&gt; which refers to a blood sacrifice that, as recounted in Exodus 24:8,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|24:8}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moses]] offered in order to seal a covenant with God: scholars often interpret the description of Jesus' action as asking his disciples to consider themselves part of a sacrifice, where Jesus is the one due to physically undergo it .&lt;ref&gt;(Brown et al. 626)&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the Gospel of John does not include a description of the bread and wine ritual during the Last Supper, most scholars agree that [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#6:58|John 6:58-59]] (the [[Bread of Life Discourse]]) has a Eucharistic nature and resonates with the &quot;words of institution&quot; used in the Synoptic Gospels and the Pauline writings on the Last Supper.&lt;ref&gt;''Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible'' 2000 ISBN 90-5356-503-5 page 792&lt;/ref&gt;

===Prediction of Peter's denial===
{{Main|Denial of Peter}}
In [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Matthew#26:33|Matthew 26:33-35]], [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Mark#14:29|Mark 14:29-31]], [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Luke#22:33|Luke 22:33-34]] and [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#13:36|John 13:36-38]] Jesus predicts that Peter will deny knowledge of him, stating that [[Denial of Peter|Peter will disown him]] three times before the [[rooster]] crows the next morning. The three [[Synoptic Gospel]]s mention that after the [[arrest of Jesus]] Peter denied knowing him three times, but after the third denial, heard the rooster crow and recalled the prediction as Jesus turned to look at him. Peter then began to cry bitterly.&lt;ref&gt;''Peter: apostle for the whole church'' by Pheme Perkins 2000 ISBN 0-567-08743-3 page 85&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Gospel according to Matthew, Volume 1'' by Johann Peter Lange 1865 Published by Charles Scribner Co, NY page 499&lt;/ref&gt;

===Elements unique to the Gospel of John===
{{See also|Washing the feet of the Apostles|The New Commandment|Farewell discourse}}
[[File:Christ Taking Leave of the Apostles.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Jesus giving the ''[[Farewell Discourse]]'' to his eleven remaining disciples, from the [[Maestà (Duccio)|Maesta]] by [[Duccio]], 1308-1311.]]
In John, Jesus has his last supper and is executed not on the day Nisan 15 (the first night of Passover) but on Nisan 14, when the Passover lambs were slaughtered. Presumably the author preferred this date because it associated Jesus as the [[Lamb of God]] with the sacrificial lambs of Passover.&lt;ref&gt;Sanders, E. P. The historical figure of , 1993. p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;

[[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#13|John 13]] includes the account of the [[washing the feet of the Apostles]] by Jesus before the meal.&lt;ref name =&quot;Harris John&quot;&gt;[[Stephen L Harris|Harris, Stephen L.]], Understanding the Bible. Palo Alto: Mayfield. 1985. &quot;John&quot; p. 302-310&lt;/ref&gt; In this episode, Apostle Peter objects and does not want to allow Jesus to wash his feet, but Jesus answers him, &quot;If I wash thee not, thou hast no part with me.&quot; after which Peter agrees.

In the Gospel of John, after the departure of [[Judas iscariot|Judas]] from the Last Supper, Jesus tells his remaining eleven disciples ([[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#13:33|13:33]]) that he will be with them for only a short time, then gives them a [[The New Commandment|New Commandment]], stating:&lt;ref name=AndreasK149 &gt;''Encountering John: The Gospel in Historical, Literary, and Theological Perspective'' by Andreas J. Kostenberger 2002 ISBN 0801026032 pages 149-151&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Yarbrough215 /&gt; &quot;A new commandment I give unto you, That ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye also love one another. By this shall all ''men'' know that ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another.&quot; in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#13:34|John 13:34-35]]. Two similar statements also appear later in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#15:12|John 15:12]]: &quot;This is my commandment, that ye love one another, even as I have loved you.&quot; and [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#15:17|John 15:17]]: &quot;These things I command you, that ye may love one another.&quot;&lt;ref name=Yarbrough215 &gt;''1, 2, and 3 John'' by Robert W. Yarbrough 2008 ISBN 0801026873 Baker Academic Press page 215&lt;/ref&gt;

At the Last Supper in the Gospel of John, Jesus gives an extended [[sermon]] to his disciples.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|14-16|KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; This discourse  resemble farewell speeches called testaments, in which a father or religious leader, often on the deathbed, leaves instructions for his children or followers.&lt;ref name=&quot;5G&quot;&gt;[[Robert W. Funk|Funk, Robert W.]], Roy W. Hoover, and the Jesus Seminar. ''The five gospels.'' HarperSanFrancisco. 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; 

This sermon is referred to as the [[Farewell discourse]] of Jesus, and has historically been considered a source of Christian [[doctrine]], particularly on the subject of [[Christology]]. [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#17:1|John 17:1-26]] is generally known as the ''Farewell Prayer'' or the ''High Priestly Prayer'', given that it is an intercession for the coming Church.&lt;ref name=Herman546 &gt;''The Gospel according to John'' by [[Herman Nicolaas Ridderbos|Herman Ridderbos]] 1997 ISBN 978-0-8028-0453-2 ''The Farewell Prayer'': pages 546-576&lt;/ref&gt; The prayer begins with Jesus' petition for his glorification by the Father, given that completion of his work and continues to an intercession for the success of the works of his disciples and the community of his followers.&lt;ref name=Herman546 /&gt;

==Time and place==
===Date===
{{See also|Chronology of Jesus|Crucifixion darkness and eclipse}}
In the New Testament, the date of the Last Supper is very close to the date of the [[crucifixion of Jesus]] (hence its name). Scholarly estimates for the date of the crucifixion generally fall in the range AD 30-36.&lt;ref&gt;Jesus &amp; the Rise of Early Christianity: A History of New Testament Times by Paul Barnett 2002 ISBN 0-8308-2699-8 pages 19-21&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Paul's early period: chronology, mission strategy, theology'' by [[Rainer Riesner]] 1997 ISBN 978-0-8028-4166-7 page 19-27 (page 27 has a table of various scholarly estimates)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Cradle, the Cross, and the Crown: An Introduction to the New Testament'' by Andreas J. Köstenberger, L. Scott Kellum 2009 ISBN 978-0-8054-4365-3 pages 77-79&lt;/ref&gt; Physicist [[Colin Humphreys]] rules out the year 36 on astronomical grounds,&lt;ref&gt;Colin J. Humphreys, ''The Mystery of the Last Supper'' Cambridge University Press 2011 ISBN 978-0-521-73200-0, p. 63 [http://books.google.com/books?id=BEy1BZRRAPQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Mystery+of+the+Last+Supper:+Reconstructing+the+Final+Days+of+Jesus%27%27+by+Colin+J.+Humphreys&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=2RPFTdmRKNOKhQeCo5X-Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22April%201%22&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt; and adduces other grounds for holding that the crucifixion of Jesus occurred in the afternoon of Friday 3 April 33 and that this was 14 [[Nisan]] in the official Jewish calendar that year.&lt;ref&gt;Humphreys 2011, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Last-supper-from-Kremikovtsi.jpg|thumb|16th century [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] [[fresco]] from [[Kremikovtsi]]]]
The Gospels say that Jesus died on a [[Good Friday|Friday]] and that his body was left in the tomb for the whole of the next day, which was a  Sabbath (Saturday).&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse||Mark|15:42|ESV}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Mark|16:1-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Synoptic Gospels]] present as a Passover meal&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matthew|26:17}}; {{bibleverse||Mark|14:1-2}}; {{bibleverse||Luke|22:1-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Last Supper, the meal that they seem to present as held on the evening before the crucifixion (although in no Gospel is it unequivocally said that this meal took place on the night before Jesus died).&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=cgEmAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22Annie+Jaubert%22+%22Last+Supper%22&amp;dq=%22Annie+Jaubert%22+%22Last+Supper%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=olHFTefZGYiyhAeq09z_Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwCDhG Jacob Neusner, ''Judaism and Christianity in the First Century (Taylor and Francis 1991 ISBN 978-0-8240-8174-4), vol. 3, part 1, p. 333]&lt;/ref&gt; This would mean that the Passover feast (15 Nisan) began at sunset on what now would commonly be called Thursday evening and lasted until sunset on Friday (the Jewish calendar reckons a date as beginning at sunset, not at midnight). On the contrary, the [[Gospel of John]] presents the feast as beginning on the evening ''following'' the afternoon death of Jesus. This would mean that the Friday of the crucifixion was the day of preparation for the feast (14 Nisan), not the feast itself. Various attempts to reconcile these two accounts have been made, some of which are indicated in the [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14341a.htm article on the Last Supper] by Francis Mershman in the 1912 [[Catholic Encyclopedia]].

In the 1950s Annie Jaubert argued that, while in the year of Jesus' death the official lunar calendar had Passover begin on a Friday evening, a 364-day year was also used, for instance by the [[Qumran]] community, and that Jesus celebrated the Passover on the date given in that calendar, which always had the feast begin on Tuesday evening.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholiceducation.org/articles/religion/re1049.htm Pope Benedict XVI, The Dating of the Last Supper], extract from [http://books.google.com/books?id=cbzkRUa2j18C&amp;pg=PR17&amp;dq=benedict+xvi+jesus+of+nazareth&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=zl_FTdS3E8iYhQfOra31Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Jaubert&amp;f=false ''Jesus of Nazareth'' (Catholic Truth Society and Ignatius Press 2011 ISBN 978-1-85082-707-5{{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (5) does not correspond to calculated 8.}}), pp. 106-115]&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, Humphreys, who holds that the &quot;[[Palm Sunday]]&quot; entry of Jesus into Jerusalem occurred on Monday, not Sunday, argued that the Last Supper took place on the evening of Wednesday 1 April 33.&lt;ref&gt;Humphreys 2011, pp. 164 and 168&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=humphreys &gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/135477/20110418/colin-humphreys-last-supper-challenge-biblical-calendar-jewish-calendar-final-days-of-jesus-good-fri.htm |author=Staff Reporter |title=Last Supper was on Wednesday, not Thursday, challenges Cambridge professor Colin Humphreys.| publisher=[[International Business Times]] |date=18 April 2011 |accessdate=18 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; If the Last Supper was on Tuesday (Jaubert) or Wednesday (Humphreys), this would allow more time than in the traditional view (Last Supper on Thursday) for interrogation of Jesus and [[Pilate's Court|his presentation to Pilate]] before he was crucified on Friday.

===Location===
{{main|Cenacle}}
[[File:Cenacle on Mount Zion.jpg|thumb|180px|left|The [[Cenacle]] on [[Mount Zion]], claimed to be the location of the Last Supper and [[Pentecost]].]]

According to later tradition, the Last Supper took place in what is called today The [[Cenacle|Room of the Last Supper]] on [[Mount Zion]], just outside of the walls of the [[Old City (Jerusalem)|Old City]] of [[Jerusalem]], and is traditionally known as ''The Upper Room''. This is based on the account in the [[Synoptic Gospels]] that states that Jesus had instructed a pair of unnamed disciples to go to &quot;the city&quot; to meet &quot;a man carrying a jar of water&quot;, who would lead them to a house, where they would find &quot;a large upper room furnished and ready&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Mark|14:13-15|ESV}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this upper room they &quot;prepare the Passover&quot;.

No more specific indication of the location is given in the New Testament, and the &quot;city&quot; referred to may be a [[suburb]] of Jerusalem, such as Bethany, rather than Jerusalem itself. The traditional location is in an area that, according to [[archaeology]], had a large [[Essenes|Essene]] community, a point made by scholars who suspect a link between Jesus and the group (Kilgallen 265).

Saint Mark's Syrian Orthodox Church in Jerusalem is another possible site for the room in which the Last Supper was held, and contains a Christian stone inscription testifying to early reverence for that spot. Certainly the room they have is older than that of the current coenaculum (crusader - 12th century) and as the room is now underground the relative altitude is correct (the streets of 1st century Jerusalem were at least twelve feet (3.6 metres) lower than those of today, so any true building of that time would have even its upper storey currently under the earth). They also have a revered Icon of the Virgin Mary, reputedly painted from life by St Luke.

[[Bargil Pixner]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Pixner&quot;&gt;Bargil Pixner, ''The Church of the Apostles found on Mount Zion'', [[Biblical Archaeology Review]] 16.3 May/June 1990 [http://www.centuryone.org/apostles.html]&lt;/ref&gt; claims the original [[Church of the Apostles]] is located under the current structure of the [[Cenacle]] on [[Mount Zion]].

==Theology of the Last Supper==
[[File:Duccio di Buoninsegna 029.jpg|thumb|180px|The ''[[Washing the feet of the Apostles|Washing of Feet]]'' and the Supper, from the [[Maestà (Duccio)|Maesta]] by [[Duccio]], 1308-1311. Peter often displays amazement in feet washing depictions, as in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#13:8|John 13:8]].]]
St. [[Thomas Aquinas]] viewed [[God the Father|The Father]], Christ, and the [[Holy Spirit (Christianity)|Holy Spirit]] as teachers and masters who provide lessons, at times by example. For Aquinas the Last Supper and the Cross form the summit of the teaching that wisdom flows from intrinsic grace, rather than external power.&lt;ref name=Dauphinais /&gt; For Aquinas, at the Last Supper Christ taught by example, showing the value of humility (as reflected in John's foot washing narrative) and self-sacrifice, rather than by exhibiting external, miraculous powers.&lt;ref name=Dauphinais &gt;''Reading John with St. Thomas Aquinas'' by Michael Dauphinais, Matthew Levering 2005 ISBN page xix&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Wawrykow &gt;''A-Z of Thomas Aquinas'' by Joseph Peter Wawrykow 2005 ISBN 0-334-04012-4 pages 124-125&lt;/ref&gt;  

And Aquinas stated that based on [[wikisource:Bible (NKJV)/John#15:15|John 15:15]] (in the [[Farewell discourse]]) in which Jesus said: &quot;No longer do I call you servants; .... but I have called you friends&quot; those who follow the path Christ, and partake in the Sacrament of the Eucharist, become his friends, as those gathered at the table of the Last Supper.&lt;ref&gt;''The ethics of Aquinas'' by Stephen J. Pope 2002 ISBN 0-87840-888-6 page 22&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dauphinais /&gt;&lt;ref name=Wawrykow /&gt; For Aquinas, at the Last Supper Christ made the promise to be present in the [[Sacrament]] of the [[Eucharist]], and be with those who partake in it, as he was with those at the Last Supper.&lt;ref&gt;''The Westminster handbook to Thomas Aquinas'' by Joseph Peter Wawrykow 2005 ISBN 978-0-664-22469-1 page 124&lt;/ref&gt;

Given that [[John Calvin]] believed only in the two sacraments of Baptism and the &quot;Lord's Supper&quot; (i.e. Eucharist), his analysis of the Gospel accounts of the Last Supper were an important part of his entire theology.&lt;ref name=Calv66 &gt;''Reformed worship'' by Howard L. Rice, James C. Huffstutler 2001 ISBN 0-664-50147-8 pages 66-68&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Calv62 &gt;''Calvin's Passion for the Church and the Holy Spirit'' by David S. Chen 2008 ISBN 978-1-60647-346-7 pages 62-68&lt;/ref&gt; Calvin related the Synoptic Gospel accounts of the Last Supper with the [[Bread of Life Discourse]] in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#6:35|John 6:35]] that states: &quot;I am the bread of life. He who comes to me will never go hungry.&quot;&lt;ref name=Calv62 /&gt;

Calvin also believed that the acts of Jesus at the Last Supper should be followed as an example, stating that just as in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/1 Corinthians#11:24|1 Corinthians 11:24]] Jesus gave thanks to the Father before breaking the bread, those who go to the &quot;Lord's Table&quot; to receive the sacrament of the Eucharist must give thanks for the &quot;boundless love of God&quot; and celebrate the sacrament with both joy and thanksgiving.&lt;ref name=Calv62 /&gt;

==Remembrances==
{{main|Maundy Thursday}}
{{See also|Agape feast}}
[[Image:Simon ushakov last supper 1685.jpg|thumb|left|[[Simon Ushakov]]'s [[icon]] of the ''Mystical Supper''.]]

The institution of the Eucharist at the Last Supper is remembered by Roman Catholics as one of the [[Luminous Mysteries]] of the [[Rosary]], the First Station of the [[Scriptural Way of the Cross]] and by most Christians as the &quot;inauguration of the [[New Covenant (theology)|New Covenant]]&quot;, mentioned by the prophet [[Jeremiah]], fulfilled at the last supper when Jesus &quot;took bread, and after blessing it broke it and gave it to them, and said, 'Take; this is my body.' And he took a cup, and when he had given thanks he gave it to them, and they all drank of it. And he said to them, 'This is my blood of the covenant, which is poured out for many.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref|Mark|14:22-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref|Matthew|26:26-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref|Luke|22:19-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other Christian groups consider the Bread and Wine remembrance to be a change to the [[Passover (Christian Holy Day)|Passover]] ceremony, as Jesus Christ has become &quot;our Passover, sacrificed for us&quot; (I Corinthians 5:7), and hold that partaking of the Passover Communion (or fellowship) is now the sign of the New Covenant, when properly understood by the practicing believer.

These meals evolved into more formal worship services and became codified as the [[Eucharist (Catholic Church)|Mass]] in the Catholic Church, and as the [[Divine Liturgy]] in the Eastern Orthodox Church; at these liturgies, Catholics and Eastern Orthodox celebrate the Sacrament of the Eucharist. The name &quot;Eucharist&quot; is from the Greek word ''εὐχαριστία'' (eucharistia) which means &quot;thanksgiving&quot;.

[[Early Christianity]] observed a ritual meal known as the &quot;[[agape feast]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Agape]]'' is one of the four main [[Greek words for love]] (''[[The Four Loves]]'' by [[C. S. Lewis]]). It refers to the ''idealised'' or high-level unconditional love rather than ''lust'', ''friendship'',  or ''affection'' (as in ''parental affection''). Though Christians interpret ''Agape'' as meaning a ''divine'' form of love beyond human forms, in modern Greek the term is used in the sense of &quot;I love you&quot; (''romantic love'').&lt;/ref&gt; These &quot;love feasts&quot; were apparently a full meal, with each participant bringing food, and with the meal eaten in a common room. They were held on Sundays, which became known as the [[Lord's Day]], to recall the resurrection, the appearance of Christ to the disciples on the road to Emmaus, the appearance to Thomas and the Pentecost which all took place on Sundays after the Passion.

==Possible parallels==
Raymond Brown has argued that during the Jewish [[Passover Seder]], the first cup of wine is drunk before the eating of the (unleavened) bread, but here it occurs after. This may indicate that the event was not the first [[Passover]] Seder (which occurs on [[Nisan]] 15), and hence more in line with John's chronology which places it on [[Quartodeciman|Nisan 14]], although the meal could easily have been altered during the Last Supper for symbolic or religious purposes.  Among Christian denominations, the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] holds that this Eucharistic meal was not the Passover Seder, but a separate meal.&lt;ref&gt;Brown et al. page 626&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Presbyterian Church]] documents also specifically rejects the Seder arguments and state that given that no Jewish Seder texts exist earlier than the 9th century, it is historically implausible to attempt a reconstruction of the Seder to create a parallel to the Last Supper, and that the Gospel accounts clearly indicate that the purpose of the Last Supper was not the annual repetition of the [[The Exodus|Exodus]].&lt;ref name=Presbyterian37 &gt;''Liturgical year: the worship of God'' by Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.), 1992 ISBN 978-0-664-25350-9 page 37&lt;/ref&gt;

The fifth chapter in Quran, ''[[Al-Ma'ida]]'' (the table) contains a reference to a meal (Sura 5:113) with a table sent down from God to [[Jesus in Islam|ʿĪsá]] (i.e. Jesus) and the apostles (Hawariyyin). However, there is nothing in Sura 5:113 to indicate that Jesus was celebrating that meal regarding his impending death. Thus although, Sura 5:113 refers to &quot;a meal&quot;, there is no indication that it is the Last Supper.&lt;ref&gt;''Christology in dialogue with Muslims'' by Ivor Mark Beaumont 2005 ISBN 1-870345-46-0 page 145&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historicity==
Some scholars consider the Lord's supper to have derived not from Jesus' last supper with the disciples but rather from the [[gentile]] tradition of memorial dinners for the dead.&lt;ref name = &quot;ActJMark&quot;&gt;[[Robert W. Funk|Funk, Robert W.]] and the [[Jesus Seminar]]. ''The acts of Jesus: the search for the authentic deeds of Jesus.'' HarperSanFrancisco. 1998. &quot;Mark,&quot; p. 51-161&lt;/ref&gt; In this view, the Last Supper is a tradition associated mainly with the gentile churches that Paul established, rather than with the earlier, Jewish congregations.&lt;ref name=&quot;ActJMark&quot;/&gt;

Luke is the only Gospel in which Jesus tells his disciples to repeat the ritual of bread and wine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vermes&quot;&gt;Vermes, Geza. The authentic gospel of Jesus. London, Penguin Books. 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Bart D. Ehrman states that these particular lines do not appear in certain ancient manuscripts and might not be original to the text.&lt;ref name=&quot;MisJ&quot;&gt;[[Bart D. Ehrman|Ehrman, Bart D.]]. [[Misquoting Jesus]]: The Story Behind 
Who Changed the Bible and Why. HarperCollins, 2005. ISBN 978-0-06-073817-4&lt;/ref&gt;

However, many early [[Church Fathers]] have attested to the belief that at the Last Supper, Christ made the promise to be present in the Sacrament of the Eucharist, with attestations dating back to the first century AD.&lt;ref name=JTM&gt;{{cite web|last=The Martyr|first=Justin|title=The First Apology|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0126.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Irenaeus&gt;{{cite web|last=of Lyons|first=Irenaeus|title=Against Heresies|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0103.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Clement&gt;{{cite web|last=of Alexandria|first=Clement|title=The Paedagogus (Book I)|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/02091.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=IgnatiusS&gt;{{cite web|last=of Antioch|first=Ignatius|title=The Epistle of Ignatius to the Smyrnaeans|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0109.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=IgnatiusE&gt;{{cite web|last=of Antioch|first=Ignatius|title=The Epistle of Ignatius to the Ephesians|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0104.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=IgnatiusR&gt;{{cite web|last=of Antioch|first=Ignatius|title=The Epistle of Ignatius to the Romans|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0107.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Tertullian&gt;{{cite web|last=Tertullian|title=On the Resurrection of the Flesh|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0316.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AugustineEP&gt;{{cite web|last=Augustine|title=Exposition on Psalm 33 (mistakenly labelled 34)|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/1801034.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The teaching was also affirmed by many councils throughout the Church's history.&lt;ref name=Nicaea&gt;{{cite web|title=First Council of Nicæa (A.D. 325)|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3801.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ephesus&gt;{{cite web|title=Council of Ephesus (A.D. 431)|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3810.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Artistic depictions==
{{Main|Last Supper in Christian art}}
[[File:BouveretLastSupper.jpg|thumb|240px|The Last Supper, by [[Pascal Dagnan-Bouveret|Bouveret]], 19th century.]]
The Last Supper has been a popular subject in [[Christian art]].&lt;ref name=Zuffi /&gt; Depictions of the Last Supper in Christian art date back to [[early Christianity]] and can be seen in the [[Catacombs of Rome]]. [[Byzantine]] artists frequently focused on the Apostles receiving Communion, rather than the reclining figures having a meal. By the [[Renaissance]], the Last Supper was a favorite topic in Italian art.&lt;ref name=McNamee &gt;''Vested angels: eucharistic allusions in early Netherlandish paintings'' by Maurice B. McNamee 1998 ISBN 978-90-429-0007-3 pages 22-32&lt;/ref&gt;

There are three major themes in the depictions of the last supper. The first theme is the dramatic and dynamic depiction of Jesus' [[Jesus predicts his betrayal|announcement of his betrayal]]. The second theme is the moment of the institution of the tradition of the [[Eucharist]]. The depictions here are generally solemn and mystical. The third major theme is the [[Farewell discourse|farewell of Jesus to his disciples]], in which [[Judas Iscariot]] is no longer present, having left the supper. The depictions here are generally melancholy, as Jesus prepares his disciples for his departure.&lt;ref name=Zuffi &gt;''Gospel figures in art'' by Stefano Zuffi 2003 ISBN 978-0-89236-727-6 pages 254-259&lt;/ref&gt; There are also other, less frequently depicted scenes, such as the washing of the feet of the disciples.&lt;ref name=Zuffi2&gt;''Gospel figures in art'' by Stefano Zuffi 2003 ISBN 978-0-89236-727-6 pages 252&lt;/ref&gt;

Well known examples include [[The Last Supper (Leonardo da Vinci)|Leonardo da Vinci's depiction]], which is considered the first work of [[High Renaissance]] art due to its high level of harmony,&lt;ref name=Buser &gt;''Experiencing art around us'' by Thomas Buser 2005 ISBN 978-0-534-64114-6 pages 382-383&lt;/ref&gt; [[Last Supper (Tintoretto)|Tintoretto's depiction]] which is unusual in that it includes secondary characters carrying or taking the dishes from the table&lt;ref&gt;''Tintoretto: Tradition and Identity'' by Tom Nichols 2004 ISBN 1-86189-120-2 page 234&lt;/ref&gt; and [[The Sacrament of the Last Supper|Salvadore Dali's depiction]] combines the typical Christian themes with modern approaches of [[Surrealism]].&lt;ref&gt;''The mathematics of harmony'' by Alexey Stakhov, Scott Olsen 2009 ISBN 978-981-277-582-5 pages 177-178 &lt;/ref&gt;


&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Comunione degli apostoli, cella 35.jpg|''Communion of the Apostles'', by [[Fra Angelico]], with [[donor portrait]], 1440-41
File:Domenico ghirlandaio, cenacolo di ognissanti 01.jpg|[[Domenico Ghirlandaio]], 1480, depicting Judas separately
File:Juan de Juanes 003.jpg|The first Eucharist, depicted by [[Juan de Juanes]], mid-late 16th century
File:Valentin de Boulogne, Last Supper.jpg|[[Valentin de Boulogne]], 1625-1626 
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{commons category|Last Supper}}
* [[Bread of Life Discourse]]
* [[Chronology of Jesus]]
* [[Eucharist]]
* [[Farewell discourse]]
* [[Life of Jesus in the New Testament]]
* [[New Covenant (theology)]]

==Citations==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*Brown, Raymond E. ''An Introduction to the New Testament'' Doubleday 1997 ISBN 0-385-24767-2
*Brown, Raymond E. et al. ''The New Jerome Biblical Commentary'' Prentice Hall 1990 ISBN 0-13-614934-0
*Bultmann, Rudolf ''The Gospel of John'' Blackwell 1971
*Kilgallen, John J. ''A Brief Commentary on the Gospel of Mark'' Paulist Press 1989 ISBN 0-8091-3059-9
*Linders, Barnabas ''The Gospel of John'' Marshall Morgan and Scott 1972

==External links==
* [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/331170/Last-Supper &quot;Last Supper&quot;] on Encyclopædia Britannica Online.
*{{CathEncy|wstitle=The Last Supper}}

{{Easter}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Last Supper, The}}
[[Category:New Testament words and phrases]]
[[Category:Doctrines and teachings of Jesus]]
[[Category:Gospel episodes]]
[[Category:Luminous Mysteries]]
[[Category:Sacraments]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[ar:العشاء الأخير]]
[[arc:ܚܫܡܝܬܐ ܐܚܪܝܬܐ]]
[[az:Sonuncu şam yeməyi]]
[[bcl:An Ultimong Pamanggi]]
[[bg:Тайната вечеря]]
[[br:Koan Diwezhañ]]
[[ca:Sant Sopar]]
[[cs:Poslední večeře]]
[[cy:Swper Olaf]]
[[da:Den sidste nadver]]
[[de:Abendmahl Jesu]]
[[el:Μυστικός δείπνος]]
[[es:La Última Cena]]
[[eo:Lasta Vespermanĝo]]
[[eu:Jesusen Azken Afaria]]
[[fa:شام آخر]]
[[fr:Cène]]
[[ga:An Suipéar Déanach]]
[[gl:A Última Cea]]
[[ko:최후의 만찬]]
[[hr:Posljednja večera]]
[[id:Perjamuan Malam]]
[[is:Síðasta kvöldmáltíðin]]
[[it:Ultima Cena]]
[[he:הסעודה האחרונה (אירוע)]]
[[jv:Bujana Ndalu]]
[[la:Ultima Cena]]
[[hu:Az utolsó vacsora]]
[[mk:Тајна вечера]]
[[ml:തിരുവത്താഴം]]
[[ms:Santapan Terakhir]]
[[nl:Het Laatste Avondmaal (Jezus)]]
[[ja:最後の晩餐]]
[[nn:Den siste nattverden]]
[[pl:Ostatnia Wieczerza]]
[[pt:Última Ceia]]
[[ro:Cina cea de Taină (biblie)]]
[[ru:Тайная вечеря]]
[[sl:Zadnja večerja]]
[[sr:Тајна вечера]]
[[sh:Posljednja večera]]
[[sv:Jesu sista måltid]]
[[tl:Huling Hapunan]]
[[th:อาหารค่ำมื้อสุดท้าย]]
[[tr:Son Akşam Yemeği]]
[[uk:Тайна вечеря]]
[[vi:Tiệc Ly]]
[[yo:Ónjẹ Alẹ́ Olúwa]]
[[zh:最后的晚餐]]</text>
      <sha1>chboqx4mj9awskg8ubs184p4dk7tt7v</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
