<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mormonism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21023</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519500105</id>
      <parentid>519494448</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T02:33:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot</username>
        <id>14488899</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Adding protection templates) (bot</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="50984">{{pp-protected|expiry=2012-11-14T01:48:00Z|small=yes}}{{About|the Mormon religion|the Mormon people|Mormons|the Mormon church|The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|other uses|Mormon (disambiguation)}}
[[File:Book of Mormon 1830 edition reprint.jpg|thumb|right|120px|Reprint of the first edition of the [[Book of Mormon]] (1830)]]
'''Mormonism''' is the predominant religious tradition of the [[Latter Day Saint movement]]. This movement was founded by [[Joseph Smith|Joseph Smith, Jr.]], in the 1820s as a form of [[Christian primitivism]]. During the 1830s and 1840s, Mormonism gradually distinguished itself from traditional [[Protestantism]].  ''Mormonism'' today represents the new, non-Protestant faith taught by Smith in the 1840s. After Smith's death, most Mormons followed [[Brigham Young]] west, calling themselves the [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church). Other branches of Mormonism include [[Mormon fundamentalism]], which seeks to maintain practices and doctrines such as [[polygamy]] that were discontinued by the LDS Church, and various other small independent denominations.&lt;ref&gt;The second-largest [[Latter Day Saint movement|Latter Day Saint]] denomination, the [[Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]], since 2001 called &quot;Community of Christ&quot;, does not describe itself as Mormon, but instead follows a [[Trinitarianism|Trinitarian]] [[Restorationism (Christian primitivism)|Christian restorationist]] theology, and also considers itself [[Restoration (Latter-day Saints)|Restorationist]] in terms of Latter-day Saint doctrine. In reference to Latter Day Saint denominations like the Community of Christ, the ''[[AP Stylebook]]'' states, &quot;The term Mormon is not properly applied to the other Latter Day Saints churches that resulted from the split after [Joseph] Smith's death.&quot; {{cite web |url=http://newsroom.lds.org/style-guide |title=Style Guide – The Name of the Church |author= |date= |work= |publisher=LDS Newsroom |accessdate=November 11, 2011}} However, the term Mormon is often used to refer to adherents of [[Mormon fundamentalism]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Mormon (word)|word ''Mormon'']] is derived from the [[Book of Mormon]], one of the faith's [[religious text]]s. Based on the name of that book, early followers of founder [[Joseph Smith|Joseph Smith, Jr.]] were called ''Mormons'', and their faith was called ''Mormonism''. The term was initially considered pejorative,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/ldsterm.htm Terms used in the LDS Restorationist movement] ReligiousTolerance.org&lt;/ref&gt; but is no longer considered so by Mormons (although other terms such as Latter-day Saint, or LDS, are generally preferred).&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.lds.org/general-conference/2011/10/the-importance-of-a-name?lang=eng |title=The Importance of a Name |author=M. Russell Ballard |date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mormonism shares a common set of beliefs with the rest of the Latter Day Saint movement, including use of, and belief in, the [[Bible]], as well as other [[religious texts]] including the [[Book of Mormon]] and [[Doctrine and Covenants]]. It also accepts the [[Pearl of Great Price (Mormonism)|Pearl of Great Price]] as part of its scriptural canon, and has a history of teaching [[Celestial marriage|eternal marriage]], [[Exaltation (LDS Church)|eternal progression]], and [[plural marriage]] (although the LDS Church had abandoned that practice by the early 20th century). [[Culture of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|Cultural Mormonism]] includes a lifestyle promoted by the Mormon institutions, and includes [[cultural Mormon]]s who identify with the culture, but not necessarily the theology.

==Brief history==
{{See also|History of the Latter Day Saint movement|History of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints}}
[[Image:Joseph Smith first vision stained glass.jpg|left|upright|thumb|A stained glass window showing [[Joseph Smith]]'s [[First Vision]].]]
Mormonism, originated in the 1820s in western [[New York]] during a period of religious excitement known as the [[Second Great Awakening]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=1}}; {{Harvtxt|Shipps|1985|p=36}}; {{Harvtxt|Remini|2002|p=1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Founded by [[Joseph Smith|Joseph Smith, Jr.]], the faith drew its first converts while Smith was dictating the text of the Book of Mormon. This book described itself as a chronicle of early [[indigenous peoples of the Americas]], portraying them as believing [[Israelite]]s, who had a belief in Christ many hundred years before his birth. Smith dictated the book of 584 pages over a period of about three months&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; saying that he translated it from an ancient language &quot;by the gift and power of God&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;History of the Church 1:315; {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=21}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During production of this work in mid-1829, Smith, his close associate [[Oliver Cowdery]], and other early followers began [[baptism|baptizing]] new converts into a [[Restorationism (Christian primitivism)|Christian primitivist]] church, formally organized in 1830 as the [[Church of Christ (Latter Day Saints)|Church of Christ]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Remini|2002|pp=63, 79}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smith was seen by his followers as a modern-day [[prophet]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Smith later wrote that he had seen a vision of God the Father and Jesus Christ in spring 1820 in answer to his question of which [[Christian denomination|denomination]] he should join.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes called the &quot;[[First Vision]]&quot;, Smith's vision of God the Father and Jesus Christ as two separate beings was reportedly the basis for the difference in doctrine between Mormonism's view of the nature of God and that of orthodox Christianity. Smith further said that in answer to his prayer the Lord instructed him to join none of the existing churches because they were all wrong.&lt;ref&gt;Smith's 1838 written account of this vision was later canonized in a book called the &quot;[[Pearl of Great Price (Mormonism)|The Pearl of Great Price]].&quot; (See: [[Joseph Smith—History]] 1:19)&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1820s Smith reported having several [[angel]]ic visitations, and by 1830 Smith said that he had been instructed that God would use him to re-establish the true Christian church and that the Book of Mormon would be the means of establishing correct doctrine for the restored church.

The church grew steadily, but from the beginning in 1830, its members were persecuted. To avoid persecution from New York residents, the members moved to [[Kirtland, Ohio]] and hoped to establish a permanent [[New Jerusalem]] or [[Zion (Latter Day Saints)|City of Zion]] in [[Jackson County, Missouri]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, they were expelled from Jackson County in 1833 and forced to flee Kirtland in early 1838. In Missouri, [[Mormon War (1838)|violent conflicts]] with other Missourians resulted in the governor of Missouri issuing an &quot;[[Missouri Executive Order 44|extermination order]],&quot; expelling Latter Day Saints from Missouri.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Remini|2002|p=135}}&lt;/ref&gt; The displaced Mormons fled to [[Illinois]] and settled the city of [[Nauvoo, Illinois]], where they were able to live with a degree of peace and prosperity for a few years.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; However tensions between Mormons and non-Mormons again escalated to the point that in 1844, Smith was [[death of Joseph Smith, Jr.|killed]] by a mob, precipitating a [[Succession crisis (Latter Day Saints)|succession crisis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|pp=12–14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The largest group of Mormons, or [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]], accepted [[Brigham Young]] as the new prophet/leader and emigrated to what became the [[Utah Territory]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=13}}&lt;/ref&gt; There the church began the open practice of [[plural marriage]], a form of [[polygyny]] which Smith had instituted in Nauvoo. Plural marriage became the faith's most sensational characteristic during the 19th century, but vigorous opposition by the [[United States Congress]] threatened the church's existence as a legal [[institution]]. In his [[1890 Manifesto]], church president [[Wilford Woodruff]] announced the official end of plural marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=2}}; {{cite web |url=http://lds.org/scriptures/dc-testament/od/1?lang=eng |title=Official Declaration 1 |publisher=lds.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the formal abolition of plural marriage in 1890, several smaller groups of Mormons broke with the LDS Church forming several denominations of [[Mormon fundamentalism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the LDS Church has become a proponent of [[monogamy]] and [[patriotism]], has extended its reach internationally by a vigorous [[missionary (LDS Church)|missionary]] program, and has grown in size to 14 million members. The church is becoming a part of the American and international mainstream.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Mauss|1994|p=22}}. &quot;With the consistent encouragement of church leaders, Mormons became models of patriotic, law-abiding citizenship, sometimes seeming to &quot;out-American&quot; all other Americans. Their participation in the full spectrum of national, social, political, economic, and cultural life has been thorough and sincere&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; However, it consciously and intentionally retains its identity as a &quot;peculiar people&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The term &quot;peculiar people&quot; is consciously borrowed from [http://lds.org/scriptures/nt/1-pet/2.9?lang=eng#8 1 Peter 2:9], and can be interpreted as &quot;special&quot; or &quot;different,&quot; though Mormons have certainly been viewed as &quot;peculiar&quot; in the modern sense as well. {{Harvtxt|Mauss|1994|p=60}}; See also: [http://lds.org/ensign/1995/05/children-of-the-covenant?lang=eng&amp;query=peculiar Children of the Covenant], Russell M. Nelson, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; set apart from the world by what it believes is its unique relationship with God.

==Theology==

===Restoration===
[[File:Priesthood Restoration Crocheron.jpg|thumb||upright=0.8|A depiction of [[Joseph Smith]] and [[Oliver Cowdery]] receiving [[Priesthood (Latter Day Saints)|priesthood]] authority from [[John the Baptist]]]]
Mormonism describes itself as falling within world [[Christianity]], but as a distinct restored [[Dispensation_(period)#Latter_Day_Saint_dispensations|dispensation]]; it characterizes itself as the only true form of the Christian religion since the time of a [[Great Apostasy#The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|Great Apostasy]] that began not long after the [[ascension of Jesus Christ]].&lt;ref name = PMG35&gt;{{Citation |author= Missionary Department of the LDS Church |authorlink= The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints |title= Preach My Gospel |publisher= [[LDS Church]], Inc |year= 2004 |pages= 35 |url= http://lds.org/languages/additionalmanuals/preachgospel/PreachMyGospel___06_03-1_TheRestoration__36617_eng_006.pdf |isbn= 0402366174 }} Mormons believe the Great Apostasy had been foretold by Paul, who knew that the Lord would not come again “except there come a falling away first” (see 2 Thessalonians 2:3)&lt;/ref&gt; According to Mormons this Apostasy involved the corruption of the pure, original Christian doctrine with [[Greek philosophy|Greek]] and other philosophies,&lt;ref name = GA2&gt;{{Citation |last= Talmage |first= James E. |authorlink= James E. Talmage |title= The Great Apostasy |publisher= The Deseret News |year= 1909 |pages= 64–65 |url= http://www.archive.org/stream/greatapostasycon00atalm#page/68/mode/2up |isbn= 0875798438}}&lt;/ref&gt; and followers dividing into different ideological groups.&lt;ref name = MARV1&gt;{{Citation |last= Richards |first= LeGrand |authorlink= LeGrand Richards |title= A Marvelous Work and a Wonder |publisher= Deseret Book Company |year= 1976 |pages= 24 |url= http://books.google.com/?id=udFopREPKMgC&amp;lpg=PR2&amp;dq=a%20marvelous%20work%20and%20a%20wonder&amp;pg=PA25#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |isbn= 0877471614}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Additionally, Mormons claim the [[martyr]]dom of the [[Apostle (Christian)|Apostles]] 
led to the loss of [[Priesthood (Latter Day Saints)|Priesthood authority]] to administer the Church and its ordinances.&lt;ref name = GA1&gt;{{Citation | last = Talmage | first = James E. | authorlink = James E. Talmage | title = The Great Apostasy | publisher = The Deseret News | year = 1909 | pages = 68 | url =http://www.archive.org/stream/greatapostasycon00atalm#page/68/mode/2up | isbn = 0875798438}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Eyring&gt;{{Citation |last= Eyring |first= Henry B. |author-link= Henry B. Eyring |title= The True and Living Church |url= http://lds.org/ensign/2008/05/the-true-and-living-church?lang=eng |journal= Ensign |publisher= LDS Church |pages= 20–24 |date= May 2008 |year= 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mormons believe that God re-established the [[Early Christianity|early Christian]] Church as found in the [[New Testament]] through Joseph Smith.&lt;ref&gt;Smith's restoration differed significantly from other ''restorationist'' movements of the era (for instance, that of Alexander Campbell). Instead of using Bible analysis, Smith claimed to write and interpret scripture as the biblical prophets did. {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, Mormons believe that angels such as [[Saint Peter|Peter]], [[James, son of Zebedee|James]], [[John the Apostle|John]], and [[John the Baptist]] appeared to Joseph Smith and others and bestowed various [[Priesthood (Latter Day Saints)|Priesthood]] authorities on them.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://scriptures.lds.org/en/js_h/1/69-72#69 JSH 1:69,72] and [http://scriptures.lds.org/en/dc/84 Doctrine and Covenants 84:19-21]&lt;/ref&gt; Mormons thus believe that their Church is the &quot;only true and living church&quot; because divine authority was restored to it through Smith. In addition, Mormons believe that Smith and his legitimate successors are modern prophets who receive revelation from God to guide the church. They maintain that other religions have a portion of the truth and are guided by the [[Light of Christ]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith |page=316 |author=Joseph Fielding Smith |year=1993|ref=harv}} (&quot;Have the Presbyterians any truth? Yes. Have the Baptists, Methodists, etc., any truth? Yes. They all have a little truth mixed with error. We should gather all the good and true principles in the world and treasure them up, or we shall not come out true 'Mormons'.&quot;); {{Cite book |title=Religions of the World: A Latter-day Saint View |last1=Palmer |last2=Keller |last3=Choi |last4=Toronto |publisher=Brigham Young University |year=1997}} (Mormons take an [[Inclusivism|inclusivist]] position that their religion is correct and true but that other religions have genuine value).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cosmology===
For many Mormons, Joseph Smith's cosmology is the most attractive part of the restoration.&lt;ref&gt;Smith's cosmology is laid out mostly in Smith's later revelations and sermons, but particularly the Book of Abraham, the Book of Moses, and the King Follett discourse. {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|pp=64–71}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Mormon cosmology]] presents a unique view of God and the universe, and places a high importance on human agency. In Mormonism, life on earth is just a short part of an eternal existence. Mormons believe that in the beginning all people existed as [[spirit]]s or &quot;intelligences,&quot; independent of God.&lt;ref&gt;Mormons differ among themselves about the form of man in the beginning...but Smith's intention was to assert that some essence of human personality has always existed. {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=72}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In this state, God came among the intelligences and offered [[Plan of salvation|a plan]] whereby they could progress and &quot;have a privilege to advance like himself.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;See King Follett discourse and {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=73}}&lt;/ref&gt; The spirits were free to accept or reject this plan, and a third of them, led by [[Satan]] rejected it.&lt;ref&gt;According to the Book of Moses, Lucifer offered an alternate plan that would guarantee the salvation of ''all'' spirits, however, at the cost of their agency, essentially forcing them to be saved. God's plan allowed spirits the freedom of choice, but left room for some to fall out of his presence into darkness. {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=73}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rest accepted the plan, coming to earth and receiving bodies with an understanding that they would experience sin and suffering.

In Mormonism, the central part of God's plan is the [[Atonement in Christianity|atonement]] of Jesus Christ.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=77}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mormons believe that one purpose of earthly life is to learn to choose good over evil. In this process, people inevitably make mistakes, becoming unworthy to return to the presence of God. Mormons believe that Jesus paid for the sins of the world, and that all people can be saved through his atonement.&lt;ref&gt;Nineteenth century Mormonism defined itself against Calvinistic religions that asserted humans' incapacity and utter dependence on the grace of God. Early Mormon preachers emphasized good works and moral obligation; however in the late twentieth century, Mormons pulled back from an &quot;entrenched aversion&quot; to the doctrines of grace, and today have an attitude of trusting in the grace of Christ while trying their best to do good works. {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mormons accept Christ's atonement through faith, repentance, formal covenants or ordinances such as baptism, and consistently trying to live a Christ-like life.

===Ordinances===
In Mormonism, an [[Ordinance (Latter Day Saints)|ordinance]] is a religious [[ritual]] of special significance, often involving the formation of a [[Covenant (Latter Day Saints)|covenant]] with God.&lt;ref&gt;The ordinance is generally a physical act signifying a spiritual commitment, or a covenant. Failure to honor that commitment results in the ordinance having no effect. However, sincere repentance can restore the blessings associated with the ordinance.&lt;/ref&gt; Ordinances are performed by the authority of the [[Priesthood (Mormonism)|priesthood]] and in the name of [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]]. The term has a meaning roughly similar to that of the term &quot;[[sacrament]]&quot; in other Christian denominations.

[[File:LDS Baptism Panama.JPG|thumb|left|An eight-year-old girl being baptized in Cerro Punta, Panama]]
Saving ordinances (or ordinances viewed as necessary for salvation) include: [[Baptism (Latter Day Saints)|baptism]] by [[immersion baptism|immersion]] after the [[age of accountability]] (normally age 8); [[Confirmation (Latter Day Saints)|confirmation]] and reception of the [[Baptism with the Holy Spirit|gift of the Holy Ghost]], performed by laying hands on the head of a newly baptized member; ordination to the [[Aaronic priesthood (LDS Church)|Aaronic]] and [[Melchizedek priesthood]]s for males; an [[Endowment (Latter Day Saints)|endowment]] (including [[washing and anointing]]) received in [[Temple (LDS Church)|temples]]; and [[Celestial marriage|marriage]] (or [[Sealing (Latter Day Saints)|sealing]]) to a spouse.&lt;ref&gt;''True to the Faith: A Gospel Reference'', 2004, LDS Church. &quot;[http://library.lds.org/nxt/gateway.dll/Curriculum/home%20and%20family.htm/true%20to%20the%20faith%20a%20gospel%20reference.htm/ordinances.htm?f=templates$fn=document-frame.htm$3.0#JD_36863Ord Ordinances],&quot; p. 109&lt;/ref&gt;
Mormons renew their baptismal covenants through weekly participation in the Lord's supper (commonly called [[Sacrament (Latter Day Saints)|sacrament]]).&lt;ref&gt;Strictly speaking, this is a non-saving ordinance because a person could be saved without ever having participated in the sacrament. However, individuals who have been baptized are expected to regularly participate in the sacrament and most Latter-day Saints would probably believe that a person who avoided doing so would not be a serious candidate for exaltation&lt;/ref&gt;

Mormons also perform other ordinances, which include [[naming and blessing children]], giving [[priesthood blessing]]s and [[patriarchal blessings]], [[Anointing of the Sick|anointing and blessing the sick]], participating in [[Prayer circle (Mormonism)|prayer circles]], and setting apart  individuals who are called to church positions.

In Mormonism, the saving ordinances are seen as necessary for salvation, but they are not sufficient in and of themselves. For example, baptism is required for [[Exaltation (Mormonism)|exaltation]], but simply having been baptized does not guarantee any eternal reward. The baptized person is expected to be obedient to God's commandments, to repent of any sinful conduct subsequent to baptism, and to receive the other saving ordinances.

Because Mormons believe that everyone must receive certain ordinances to be saved, Mormons perform ordinances on behalf of deceased persons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|pp=60&amp;ndash;61}}&lt;/ref&gt; These ordinances are performed vicariously or by &quot;proxy&quot; on behalf of the dead. In accordance with their belief in each individual's &quot;free agency&quot;, living or dead, Mormons believe that the deceased may accept or reject the offered ordinance in the [[spirit world (Latter Day Saints)|spirit world]], just as all spirits decided to accept or reject God's plan originally. In addition, these &quot;conditional&quot; ordinances on behalf of the dead are performed only when a deceased person's genealogical information has been submitted to a temple and correctly processed there before the ordinance ritual is performed. Only ordinances for salvation are performed on behalf of deceased persons. {{nowrap|''See also: [[Baptism for the dead]].''}}

===Scripture===
[[File:Latter-day Saint Scripture Quadruple Combination.jpg|thumb|upright=0.80|The Latter Day Saint scriptural [[Biblical canon|canon]]]]

Mormons believe in the Old and New Testaments, and the LDS Church uses the [[Authorized King James Version|King James Bible]] as its official scriptural text of the [[Christian biblical canons|Bible]]. While Mormons believe in the general accuracy of the modern day text of the Bible, they also believe that it is incomplete and that errors have been introduced.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Encyclopedia of Mormonism]]'', Macmillan 1992, pp. 106-107; Matthews, Robert J., ''A Bible! A Bible'', Bookcraft, 1990, p. 13; {{Citation|title=Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith|publisher=Deseret Book|year=1976|pages=9–10,327}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Mormon theology, many lost truths are restored in the [[Book of Mormon]], which Mormons hold to be divine scripture and equal in authority to the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Encyclopedia of Mormonism]]'', Macmillan 1992, pp. 111&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Mormon scriptural canon also includes a collection of revelations and writings contained in the [[Doctrine and Covenants]] and the [[Pearl of Great Price (Mormonism)|Pearl of Great Price]]. These books, as well as the [[Joseph Smith Translation of the Bible]], have varying degrees of acceptance as divine scripture among different denominations of the Latter Day Saint movement.

===Revelation===
In Mormonism, [[continuous revelation]] is the principle that God or his divine agents still continue to communicate to mankind.  This communication can be manifest in many ways: influences of the [[Holy Ghost]] (the principal form in which this principle is manifest), visions, visitations of divine beings, and others. Joseph Smith used the example of the Lord's revelations to Moses in [[Deuteronomy]] to explain the importance of continuous revelation.

{{quote|text=&quot;God said, 'Thou shalt not murder' at another time He said, 'Thou shalt utterly destroy.' This is the principle on which the government of heaven is conducted&amp;ndash;by revelation adapted to the circumstances in which the children of the kingdom are placed. Whatever God commands is right, no matter what it is, although we may not see the reason thereof till long after the events transpire.&quot;|sign=[[Joseph Smith]]|source=[[Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith (book)|''Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith'']], pp.&amp;nbsp;256&amp;ndash;7.}}

Mormons believe that Smith and subsequent church leaders could speak scripture &quot;when moved upon by the Holy Ghost.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;personalrev&quot;&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=26}} See also: Doctrine and Covenants 68:4&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, many Mormons believe that ancient prophets in other regions of the world received revelations that resulted in additional scriptures that have been lost and may, one day, be forthcoming. In Mormonism, revelation isn't limited to church members alone. For instance, Latter Day Saints believe that the [[United States Constitution]] is a divinely inspired document.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://lds.org/ensign/1992/02/the-divinely-inspired-constitution?lang=eng |title=The Divinely Inspired Constitution |author=Dallin H. Oaks |date=Feb. 1992 |publisher=''[[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''See'' D&amp;C 101:77–80&lt;/ref&gt;

Mormons are encouraged to develop a personal relationship with the Holy Ghost and receive personal revelation for their own direction and that of their family.&lt;ref name=personalrev/&gt; The Latter Day Saint concept of revelation includes the belief that revelation from God is available to all those who earnestly seek it with the intent of doing good. It also teaches that everyone is entitled to ''personal'' revelation with respect to his or her [[stewardship]] (leadership responsibility). Thus, parents may receive inspiration from God in raising their families, individuals can receive divine inspiration to help them meet personal challenges, church officers may receive revelation for those whom they serve.

The important consequence of this is that each person may receive confirmation that particular doctrines taught by a prophet are true, as well as gain divine insight in using those truths for their own benefit and eternal progress. In the church, personal revelation is expected and encouraged, and many converts believe that personal revelation from God was instrumental in their conversion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Continuing Revelation | work=Mormon.org | url=http://www.mormon.org/learn/0,8672,1084-1,00.html | accessdate=August 5, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Relation to Mainstream Christianity===
{{See also|Mormonism and Christianity}}
According to [[Bruce McConkie]], a [[general authority]] of the LDS Church, &quot;Mormonism is indistinguishable from Christianity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bruce R. McConkie, ''[[Mormon Doctrine (book)|Mormon Doctrine]]'', p.&amp;nbsp;513.&lt;/ref&gt; In many ways, however, the religion differs from Christian orthodoxy as held by [[Catholicism|Catholic]], [[Orthodox Christianity|Orthodox]], and [[Protestantism|Protestant]] Christianity. To those for whom Christianity is defined by that orthodoxy, Mormonism's differences place it outside the umbrella of Christianity altogether.&lt;ref&gt;For example, a 2007 poll conducted by the Pew Research Center found that one in three Americans surveyed do not consider Mormons to be Christian. See for example [http://www.religionnewsblog.com/19478/religion-poll-2 ReligionNewsblog.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It is sometimes said that Mormonism is to Christianity as Christianity is to Judaism. Both Mormonism and Christianity established themselves by reinterpreting a preceding faith. Christianity built on Judaism but emphasized the death and resurrection of Jesus Christ; Mormonism began with Christianity but accepted new revelation through a modern prophet.&quot; {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Christus statue temple square salt lake city.jpg|thumb|Mormons see {{nowrap|[[Jesus|Jesus Christ]]}} as the premier figure of their religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=8}} (&quot;As the name of the church&amp;nbsp;... suggests, Jesus Christ is the premier figure. Smith does not even play the role of the last and culminating prophet, as Muhammad does in Islam&quot;); {{cite web |url=http://newsroom.lds.org/article/what-mormons-believe-about-jesus-christ |title=What Mormons Believe About Jesus Christ |author= |date= |work= |publisher=LDS Newsroom |accessdate=November 11, 2011}}; In a [http://www.pewforum.org/Christian/Mormon/mormons-in-america-executive-summary.aspx#beliefs 2011 Pew Survey] a thousand Mormons were asked to volunteer the one word that best describes Mormons. The most common response from those surveyed was “Christian” or “Christ-centered&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Since its beginnings, the faith has proclaimed itself to be Christ's Church [[Restorationism (Christian primitivism)|restored]] with its original authority, structure and power; maintaining that existing denominations believed incorrect doctrines and were not acknowledged of God as his church and kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;Teaching that existing denominations &quot;were believing in incorrect doctrines, and that none of them was acknowledged by God as his church and kingdom&quot; {{Harvnb|Smith|1842a|p=707}} and &quot;all their creeds were an abomination in his sight.&quot; {{Harvnb|Smith|1842c|p=748}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the religion quickly gained a large following of Christian seekers, in the 1830s, many American Christians came to view the church's early doctrines and practices&lt;ref&gt;The most publicized of these doctrines and practices included abolitionism, [[plural marriage]] and the church's [[theodemocracy|theocratic aspirations]] (both now discontinued by the mainstream faith).&lt;/ref&gt; as politically and culturally [[subversion (politics)|subversive]], as well as doctrinally heretical, abominable, and condemnable. This discord led to a series of sometimes-deadly conflicts between Mormons and others who saw themselves as orthodox Christians.&lt;ref&gt;For more information on historical conflicts, see [[History of the Latter Day Saint movement]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Although such violence declined over the twentieth century, the religion's unique doctrinal views and practices still generate criticism, sometimes vehemently so. These gives rise to efforts by Mormons and opposing types of Christians to proselytize each other.

Mormons believe in [[Jesus Christ]] as the literal firstborn [[Son of God]] and [[Messiah]], his [[Crucifixion of Jesus|crucifixion]] as a conclusion of a [[sin offering]], and subsequent [[Resurrection of Jesus|resurrection]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsroom.lds.org/article/what-mormons-believe-about-jesus-christ What Mormons Believe About Jesus Christ—LDS Newsroom]&lt;/ref&gt; However, Latter-day Saints (LDS) reject the ecumenical creeds and definition of the [[Trinity]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://scriptures.lds.org/en/js_h/1/18-19#18 Joseph Smith History 1:18-19]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith (book)|Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith]]'', selected by [[Joseph Fielding Smith]], Salt Lake City: Smith, Deseret Book, 1976, p. 370.&lt;/ref&gt; (In contrast, the second largest Latter Day Saint denomination, the [[Community of Christ]], is Trinitarian and [[monotheistic]].) Mormons hold that the New Testament prophesied both the [[Great Apostasy|apostasy]] from the teachings of Christ and his apostles as well as the [[Restorationism (Christian primitivism)|restoration]] of all things prior to the second coming of Christ.&lt;ref&gt;See, for instance, [http://scriptures.lds.org/en/2_thes/2/2-3#2 Thessalonians 2:2-3] and [http://scriptures.lds.org/en/acts/3/19-21#19 Acts 3:19-21]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some notable differences with mainstream Christianity include: A belief that Jesus began his [[Atonement in Christianity|atonement]] in the garden of Gethsemane and continued it to his crucifixion, rather than the orthodox belief that the crucifixion alone was the physical atonement;&lt;ref&gt;Bruce R. McConkie, “The Purifying Power of Gethsemane,” Ensign, May 1985, 9.&lt;/ref&gt; and an afterlife with three [[degrees of glory]], with [[hell]] (often called [[Spirit world (Latter Day Saints)#Spirit prison|spirit prison]]) being a temporary repository for the wicked between death and the resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;Mormon scriptures speak of hell in two ways. The first is another name for [[Spirit world (Latter Day Saints)#Spirit prison|spirit prison]], a place for the spirits of people who have &quot;died in their sins.&quot; The second is a more permanent place called [[Outer Darkness]], reserved for the Devil, his angels, and those who have committed the unpardonable sin. ''True to the Faith: A Gospel Reference'', 2004, LDS Church. &quot;[http://library.lds.org/nxt/gateway.dll/Curriculum/home%20and%20family.htm/true%20to%20the%20faith%20a%20gospel%20reference.htm/hell.htm?f=templates$fn=document-frame.htm$3.0#JD_36863Hel Hell],&quot; p. 81; See also: [[Christian views on Hell#Latter-day Saints|Christian views on Hell (Latter-day Saints)]]&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, Mormons don't believe in creation [[ex nihilo]], believing that matter is eternal, and creation involved God organizing existing matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=71}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Much of the Mormon belief system is oriented geographically around the North and South American continents. Mormons believe the people of the Book of Mormon lived in the western hemisphere, that Christ appeared in the western hemisphere after his death and resurrection, that the true faith was restored in upstate New York by Joseph Smith, that the [[Garden of Eden]] was located in North America, and that the [[New Jerusalem]] would be built in Missouri. For this and other reasons, including a belief by many Mormons in [[American exceptionalism]], [[Molly Worthen]] speculates that this may be why [[Leo Tolstoy]] described Mormonism as the &quot;quintessential 'American religion'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Molly Worthen|Worthen, Molly]], &quot;[http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2011/06/13/the_missionary_position The Missionary Position]&quot;, ''[[Foreign Policy Magazine|Foreign Policy]]'', 13 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Relation to Judaism===
{{See also|Mormonism and Judaism}}
Although Mormons do not claim to be part of [[Judaism]], Mormon theology claims to situate Mormonism within the context of Judaism to an extent that goes beyond what most other Christian denominations claim. The faith incorporates many [[Old Testament]] ideas into its theology, and the beliefs of Mormons sometimes parallel those of Judaism and certain elements of Jewish culture. In the earliest days of Mormonism, Joseph Smith taught that the [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas]] were members of some of the [[Lost Tribes of Israel]]. Later, he taught that Mormons were Israelites, and that they may learn of their tribal affiliation within the twelve Israelite tribes. Members of the LDS Church receive [[Patriarchal blessing]]s which declare the recipient's lineage within one of the tribes of Israel. The lineage is either through true blood-line or adoption. The LDS Church teaches that if one is not a direct descendant of one of the twelve tribes, upon baptism he or she is adopted into one of the tribes. Patriarchal blessings also include personal information which is revealed through a patriarch by the power of the priesthood.

The Mormon affinity for Judaism is expressed by the many references to Judaism in the Mormon liturgy.  For example, Smith named the largest Mormon settlement he founded ''[[Nauvoo, Illinois|Nauvoo]]'', which means &quot;to be beautiful&quot; in [[Hebrew]].  Brigham Young named a tributary of the [[Great Salt Lake]] the &quot;[[Jordan River (Utah)|Jordan River]]&quot;. The LDS Church created a writing scheme called the [[Deseret Alphabet]], which was based, in part, on Hebrew. Currently, the LDS Church has a [[BYU Jerusalem Center|Jerusalem Center]] in [[Israel]], where students focus their study on Near Eastern history, culture, language, and the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ce.byu.edu/jc/ BYU Jerusalem Center for Near Eastern Studies]&lt;/ref&gt;

There has been some controversy involving Jewish groups who see the actions of some elements of Mormonism as offensive. In the 1990s, Jewish groups vocally opposed the LDS practice of [[baptism for the dead]] on behalf of Jewish victims of [[the Holocaust]] and Jews in general. According to LDS Church [[general authority]] Monte J. Brough, &quot;Mormons who baptized 380,000 Holocaust victims posthumously were motivated by love and compassion and did not understand their gesture might offend Jews...they did not realize that what they intended as a 'Christian act of service' was 'misguided and insensitive'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Pyle, Richard. {{cite web|title=Mormons, Jews sign agreement on baptizing Holocaust victims.|url=http://www.jewishgen.org/InfoFiles/ldsagree.html|accessdate=2007-01-04}} AP Newswire, May 5, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt;  Mormons believe that when the dead are baptized through proxy, they have the option of accepting or rejecting the ordinance.

===Relation to Islam===
{{Main|Mormonism and Islam}}
Since its origins in the 19th century, Mormonism has been compared to [[Islam]], often by detractors of one religion or the other.&lt;ref name=&quot;mohammed&quot;&gt;[http://www.saintswithouthalos.com/w/1838_tbmoh.phtml Thomas Marsh and Orson Hyde Affidavit], for example; see also [http://www.pbs.org/americanprophet/prologue.html PBS's American Prophet: Prologue] and Todd J. Harris,  [http://contentdm.lib.byu.edu/ETD/image/etd2067.pdf A Comparison of Muhammad and Joseph Smith in the Prophetic Pattern], a thesis submitted for a Master of Arts degree at Brigham Young University in 2007, footnotes on pages 1 and 2.&lt;/ref&gt;  For instance, [[Joseph Smith]] was referred to as &quot;the modern [[Muhammad|Mahomet]]&quot; by the ''[[New York Herald]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/americanprophet/prologue.html PBS's American Prophet: Prologue].&lt;/ref&gt; shortly after his [[Death of Joseph Smith, Jr.|murder]] in June 1844.  This epithet repeated a comparison that had been made from Smith's earliest career,&lt;ref name=&quot;mohammed&quot;/&gt; one that was not intended at the time to be complimentary.  Comparison of the Mormon and Muslim prophets still occurs today, sometimes for derogatory or [[polemical]] reasons&lt;ref&gt;See, for example:[http://www.inplainsite.org/html/smith_and_muhammed.html Joseph Smith and Muhammad: The Similarities], and Eric Johnson,[http://www.utlm.org/booklist/titles/josephsmithandmuhammad_xb183.htm Joseph Smith and Muhammad], a book published by the &quot;Mormonism Research Ministry&quot; and offered for sale by the anti-Mormon &quot;[http://www.utlm.org/ Utah Lighthouse Ministries]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; but also for more scholarly (and neutral) purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;mohammed&quot;/&gt;  While Mormonism and Islam certainly have many similarities, there are also significant, fundamental differences between the two religions.  [[Mormon]]–[[Muslim]] relations have been historically cordial,&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2008/apr/02/local/me-morlims2 U.S. Muslims and Mormons share deepening ties]&lt;/ref&gt; seldom involving [[Islamophobia]] or [[Anti-Mormonism]]; recent years have seen increasing [[dialogue]] between adherents of the two faiths, and cooperation in [[charity (practice)|charitable endeavors]], especially in the [[Middle East|Middle]] and [[Far East]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://worldmuslimcongress.blogspot.com/2008/04/mormons-muslims.html World Muslim Congress: Mormons and Muslims]; [http://bycommonconsent.com/2007/09/10/mormon-muslim-interfaith-ramadan-dinner-in-washington-dc-area/ Mormon-Muslim Interfaith Ramadan Dinner].&lt;/ref&gt;

Islam and Mormonism both originate in the [[Abrahamic religions|Abrahamic tradition]]s. Both believe that Christianity as originally established by Jesus Christ was a true religion, but that it subsequently became deformed to the point that it was beyond simple reformation. Hence, each religion sees its founder (Muhammad for Islam, and Joseph Smith for Mormonism) as being a true [[prophet]] of God, called to re-establish the true faith. In addition, both prophets received visits from an [[angel]], leading to additional books of [[scripture]]. Both religions share a high emphasis on family life, charitable giving, chastity, abstention from alcohol, and a special reverence for, though not worship of, their founding prophet. Before the [[1890 Manifesto]] against plural marriage, Mormonism and Islam also shared in the belief in and practice of plural marriage, a practice now held in common by Islam and various branches of Mormon fundamentalism.

The religions differ significantly in their views on God. Islam insists upon the complete [[Tawheed|oneness]] and uniqueness of [[God]] ([[Allah]]), while Mormonism asserts that the [[Godhead (Latter Day Saints)|Godhead]] is made up of three distinct &quot;personages.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://eom.byu.edu/index.php/Godhead Encyclopedia of Mormonism], entry: &quot;Godhead&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
Mormonism sees [[Jesus Christ]] as the promised [[Messiah]] and the literal [[Son of God]], while Islam insists that the title &quot;Messiah&quot; means that Jesus (or &quot;[[Jesus in Islam|Isa]]&quot;) was a prophet sent to establish the true faith, not that he was the Son of God or a divine being.  Despite opposition from other [[Christian denominations]], Mormonism identifies itself as a Christian religion, the &quot;restoration&quot; of primitive Christianity. Islam does not refer to itself as &quot;Christian&quot;, asserting that Jesus and all true followers of Christ's teachings were (and are) Muslims–a term that means ''submitters to God''–not Christians as the term is used today.&lt;ref&gt;[http://islam-voice.net/jesus-was-muslim.html Jesus Was Muslim], from the [http://islam-voice.net/ Islam-Voice] website.&lt;/ref&gt; Islam proclaims that its [[Prophets of Islam|prophet]] [[Muhammad]] was the &quot;seal of the prophets&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Holy Qur'an, Surah 33, verse 40.&lt;/ref&gt; and that no further prophets would come after him. Mormons, though honoring Joseph Smith as the first prophet in modern times, see him as just one in a long line of prophets, with Jesus Christ being the premier figure of the religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=8}} (&quot;In the Mormon view, many prophets preceded Smith and many will follow.&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theological divisions==
Mormon theology includes three main movements. By far the largest of these is &quot;mainstream Mormonism&quot;, defined by the leadership of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church). The two broad movements outside mainstream Mormonism are [[Mormon fundamentalism]], and liberal reformist Mormonism.

===Mainstream Mormon theology===
{{See also|Beliefs and practices of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints}}
Mainstream Mormonism is defined by the leadership of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church) which identifies itself as Christian.&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, Stephanie (May 1998).[http://www.lds.org/new-era/1998/05/are-mormons-christians?lang=eng Are Mormons Christians?].''Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints.''&lt;/ref&gt;  Members of the LDS Church consider their top leaders to be [[prophet]]s and [[Apostle (Latter Day Saints)|Apostle]]s, and are encouraged to accept their positions on matters of theology, while seeking confirmation of them through personal study of the Book of Mormon and the Bible. Personal prayer is encouraged as well.  The LDS Church is by far the largest branch of Mormonism.  It has continuously existed since the [[Succession crisis (Latter Day Saints)|succession crisis]] of 1844 that split the [[Latter Day Saint movement]] after the death of founder [[Joseph Smith|Joseph Smith, Jr.]]

Presently, the LDS Church seeks to distance itself from other branches of Mormonism, particularly those that practice polygamy.&lt;ref&gt;The LDS Church encourages journalists not to use the word ''Mormon'' in reference to organizations or people that practice polygamy {{cite web |url=http://newsroom.lds.org/style-guide |title=Style Guide &amp;mdash; LDS Newsroom |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=November 11, 2011}}; The church repudiates polygamist groups and excommunicates their members if discovered {{Harvtxt|Bushman|2008|p=91}}; {{Cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/25396937/ns/us_news-faith/t/mormons-seek-distance-polygamist-sects |title=Mormons seek distance from polygamous sects |year=2008 |publisher=msnbc.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The church maintains a degree of orthodoxy by excommunicating or disciplining its members who take positions or engage in practices viewed as apostasy.  For example, the LDS Church excommunicates members who practice polygamy or who adopt the beliefs and practices of Mormon fundamentalism.

===Mormon fundamentalism===
{{Main|Mormon fundamentalism}}
One way Mormon fundamentalism distinguishes itself from mainstream Mormonism is through the practice of [[plural marriage]]. Fundamentalists initially broke from the LDS Church after that doctrine was discontinued around the beginning of the 20th century.  Mormon fundamentalism teaches that plural marriage is a requirement for [[Exaltation (Latter Day Saints)|exaltation]] (the highest degree of salvation), which will allow them to live as gods and goddesses in the afterlife.  Mainstream Mormons, by contrast, believe that a single [[Celestial marriage]] is necessary for exaltation.

In distinction with the LDS Church, Mormon fundamentalists also often believe in a number of other doctrines taught and practiced by [[Brigham Young]] in the 19th century, which the LDS Church has either abandoned, repudiated, or put in abeyance. These include:
*the [[law of consecration]] also known as the [[United Order]] (put in abeyance by the LDS Church in the 19th century);
*the [[Adam–God theory|Adam–God teachings]] taught by Brigham Young and other early leaders of the LDS Church (repudiated by the LDS Church in the mid-20th century);
*the principle of [[blood atonement]] (repudiated by the LDS Church in the mid-20th century); and
*the [[Black people and Mormonism|exclusion of black men]] from the [[Priesthood (Latter Day Saints)|priesthood]] (abandoned by the LDS Church in 1978).

Mormon fundamentalists believe that these principles were wrongly abandoned or changed by the LDS Church, in large part due to the desire of its leadership and members to assimilate into mainstream American society and avoid the persecutions and conflict that had characterized the church throughout its early years. Others believe that it was a necessity at some point for &quot;a restoration of all things&quot; to be a truly restored Church.

===Liberal reformist theology===
{{see also|Bickertonite}}
Some LDS Church members have worked towards a liberal reform of the church. Others have left the LDS Church but consider themselves to be [[cultural Mormon]]s. Others have formed new religions (most of them now defunct). For instance, the [[Godbeites]] broke from the LDS Church in the late 19th century on the basis of both political and religious liberalism, and in 1985 the [[Restoration Church of Jesus Christ]] broke from the LDS Church as an [[LGBT]]-friendly denomination.

==See also==
{{Portal|Latter-day Saints}}
*[[Black people and early Mormonism]]
*[[Criticism of the Latter Day Saint movement]]
*[[List of articles about Mormonism]]
*[[The Joseph Smith Papers]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{Citation
|last = Bloom
|first = Harold
|author-link = Harold Bloom
|title = The American Religion: The Emergence of  the Post-Christian  Nation
|publisher = [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]
|publication-place = New York
|edition = 1st
|year = 1992
|isbn = 9780671679972
}}.
*{{Citation
|last = Brooke
|given = John L.
|title = The Refiner's Fire: The Making of Mormon Cosmology, 1644–1844
|year = 1994
|publisher = Cambridge University Press
|publication-place = Cambridge
}}.
*{{Citation
|last = Bushman
|first = Richard Lyman
|authorlink = Richard Bushman
|title = Mormonism: A Very Short Introduction
|year = 2008
|place = New York
|publisher = Oxford University Press
|isbn = 978-0-19-531030-6
}}.
*{{Citation
|title = Mormons and Mormonism: an introduction to an American world religion
|first = Eric Alden
|last = Eliason
|publisher = University of Illinois Press
|year = 2001
}}.
*{{Citation
|last = McMurrin
|first = Sterling M.
|authorlink = Sterling M. McMurrin
|title = The Theological Foundations of the Mormon Religion
|publisher = [[Signature Books]]
|publication-place = Salt Lake City
|year = 1965
|isbn = 156085135X
}}.
*{{Citation
|last1 = Ostling
|first1 = Richard
|last2 = Ostling
|first2 = Joan K.
|author1-link = Richard and Joan Ostling
|author2-link = Richard and Joan Ostling
|title = Mormon America: The Power and the Promise
|publisher = HarperOne
|publication-place = New York
|year = 2007
|isbn = 978-0-06-143295-8
}}.
*{{Citation
|last = Shipps
|first = Jan
|title = Mormonism: The Story of a New Religious Tradition
|year = 1985
|publisher = University of Illinois Press
|publication-place = Chicago
|isbn = 0-252-01417-0
}}.
*{{Citation
 | last=Remini
 | given=Robert V.
 | author-link=Robert V. Remini
 | title=Joseph Smith: A Penguin Life
 | year=2002
 | publisher=Penguin Group
 | publication-place=New York
 | isbn=0-670-03083-X
 }}.
*{{Citation
|first1 = Rodney
|last1 = Stark
|first2 = Reid Larkin
|last2 = Neilson
|title = The rise of Mormonism
|publisher = Columbia University Press
|year = 2005
|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=IN4QeS38Qk0C
|isbn = 9780231136341
}}.
*{{Citation
|last1 = Toscano
|first1 = Margaret
|last2 = Toscano
|first2 = Paul
|year = 1990
|title = Strangers in Paradox: Explorations in Mormon Theology
|publisher = Signature Books
|publication-place = Salt Lake City
|url = http://signaturebookslibrary.org/?p=3813
}}.
*{{Citation
|last = White
|first = O. Kendall, Jr.
|title = The Transformation of Mormon Theology
|journal = [[Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought]]
|volume = 5
|issue = 2
|year = 1970
|pages = 9–24
|url = https://dialoguejournal.com/wp-content/uploads/sbi/articles/Dialogue_V05N02_11.pdf
}}.
*{{Citation
|last = White
|first = O. Kendall, Jr.
|title = Mormon Neo-Orthodoxy: A Crisis Theology
|year = 1987
|publisher = [[Signature Books]]
|publication-place = Salt Lake City
|url = http://www.signaturebookslibrary.org/theology/preface.htm#preface
|isbn = 0941214-524
}}.
*{{Citation
|last = Widmer
|first = Kurt
|title = Mormonism and the Nature of God: A Theological Evolution, 1830–1915
|publication-place = Jefferson, N.C.
|publisher = McFarland
|year = 2000
}}.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary category|type=Mormonism|category=Mormonism}}
{{Sister project links |wikt=no |commons=Mormonism |b=no |n=no |q=Mormonism |s=Mormonism |v=no |species=no }}
*[http://www.pbs.org/mormons/ PBS: ''Frontline'' + ''American Experience'': Mormons]—PBS special on Mormon belief
*[http://www.patheos.com/Library/Mormonism.html/  Patheos + Mormonism]—Patheos.com. Mormonism Origins, Mormonism History, Mormonism Beliefs
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/mormon/index.shtml &quot;Religions: Mormonism&quot;] &amp;ndash; [[BBC]]

{{LDS|hide|hide|hide|hide|hide|show}}

[[Category:Mormonism| ]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saint terms]]
[[Category:Mormon studies]]
[[Category:Nontrinitarian denominations]]
[[Category:Christian new religious movements]]

[[bcl:Mormonismo]]
[[bg:Мормонизъм]]
[[ca:Mormonisme]]
[[cy:Mormoniaeth]]
[[de:Mormonentum]]
[[et:Mormoonid]]
[[eo:Mormonismo]]
[[id:Mormonisme]]
[[ia:Mormonismo]]
[[it:Mormonismo]]
[[hu:Mormonizmus]]
[[arz:مورمون]]
[[mn:Мормоны шашин]]
[[ja:モルモン教]]
[[ru:Мормонизм]]
[[simple:Mormonism]]
[[sl:Mormonizem]]
[[sv:Mormonism]]
[[ta:மொர்மனியம்]]
[[tr:Mormonluk]]
[[uk:Мормонізм]]
[[zh:摩爾門教]]</text>
      <sha1>d91a4lt9o9bm6qfhwzqe7dxrjxi18ka</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
