<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ole Nydahl</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>643015</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521118317</id>
      <parentid>521118054</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T22:16:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yworo</username>
        <id>9813438</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>lc headings</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25754">{{infobox person
|image =Portrait of Lama Ole Nydahl 2010.jpg
|caption=Nydahl 2010
|honorific_prefix=Lama
|name=Ole Nydahl
|birth_date={{Birth date and age|1941|03|19}}
|birth_place=[[Copenhagen]], Denmark
|nationality=Danish
|religion=[[Vajrayana|Vajrayana Buddhism]]
|denomination=[[Karma Kagyu]]
|organization=[[Diamond Way Buddhism]]
|title=[[Lama]]
}}
'''Ole Nydahl''' (born March 19, 1941) is a Danish [[Lama]] in the [[Karma Kagyu]] school of [[Tibetan Buddhism]]. Since the early 1970s, Nydahl has toured the world giving lectures and meditation courses. With his wife, Hannah Nydahl, he founded [[Diamond Way Buddhism]], a worldwide Karma Kagyu Buddhist organization of lay practitioners.

Nydahl is the author of nine books in English, including ''The Way Things Are'', ''Entering the Diamond Way'', and ''Riding the Tiger''.

==Early life and education==
Ole Nydahl was born in [[Copenhagen]] and grew up in [[Denmark]]. In the early 1960s, he served briefly in the [[Royal Danish Army|Danish Army]],&lt;ref name=ENTER&gt;{{cite book |last=Nydahl |first=Ole |title=Entering The Diamond Way, Tibetan Buddhism Meets the West |publisher=Blue Dolphin Publishing |year=1999 |isbn=978-0-931892-03-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; then studied philosophy, English, and German at the [[University of Copenhagen]], where he completed the [[examen philosophicum]] with the best possible grade.&lt;ref name=ENTER/&gt; He began but did not finish a doctoral thesis on [[Aldous Huxley]]’s ''[[Doors of Perception]]''.&lt;ref name = SCHERER&gt;{{Cite journal
  | last = Scherer
  | first = Burkhard
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = Interpreting the Diamond Way: Contemporary Convert Buddhism in Transition
  | journal = Journal of Global Buddhism
  | volume = 10
  | issue =
  | pages =
  | publisher =
  | location =
  | year = 2009
  | url = http://www.globalbuddhism.org/10/scherer09.htm
  | doi =
  | id =
  | accessdate = 24 September 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a young man, Nydahl was involved in boxing, race car driving and also travelled overland from Denmark to Nepal several times. As described in his book &quot;Entering the Diamond Way&quot;, his travels were financed through smuggling, for which he was once arrested and detained in Denmark.

==Involvement with Buddhism==
===Buddhist education===
In 1968, Nydahl and his wife Hannah travelled to Nepal on their honeymoon. Ole and Hannah Nydahl's first Buddhist teacher was the [[Drukpa Kagyu]] master [[Lopon Tsechu Rinpoche]].&lt;ref name=ENTER /&gt; In December 1969, the Nydahls met [[Rangjung Rigpe Dorje]], the [[16th Karmapa]].&lt;ref name=SHA83&gt;{{cite book |author=Shamar Rinpoche |chapter=Official letter from Shamar Rinpoche |year=1983 |editor=Nydahl, Ole |title=Riding the Tiger: Twenty Years on the Road: Risks and Joys of Bringing Tibetan Buddhism to the West |publisher=Blue Dolphin Publishing, 1992 |isbn=978-0-931892-67-7}} Letter available online at [http://www.lama-ole-nydahl.de/dokumente/shamarpa.htm].&lt;/ref&gt; They were among the first Western students of the Karmapa and grew close to him.&lt;ref name=NOSMILE&gt;{{cite book |last=Curren |first=Erik D. |year=2008 |title=Buddha's Not Smiling: Uncovering the Corruption at the Heart of Tibetan Buddhism Today |publisher=Alaya Press |isbn=0-9772253-0-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Nydahls also became students of [[Mipham Chokyi Lodro]], the fourteenth [[Shamarpa]]. From the Karmapa, the Nydahls learned about [[Vajrayana]] Buddhism and [[mahamudra]]. From the Shamarpa, they took the [[Bodhisattva vows]] and learned about [[Gampopa]]'s ''Jewel Ornament of Liberation''. They have received teachings and [[Empowerment (Tibetan Buddhism)|empowerments]] from various Tibetan lamas, including the [[Dalai Lama]].&lt;ref name=TIGER&gt;{{cite book |last=Nydahl |first=Ole |year=1992 |title=Riding The Tiger, Twenty Years on the Road: The Risks and Joys of Bringing Tibetan Buddhism to the West |publisher=Blue Dolphin Publishing |isbn=978-0-931892-67-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1972, Ole Nydahl was appointed a Buddhist teacher by the Karmapa&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Dorje|first=Rangjung Rigpe|title=H.H. the 16th Karmapa|url=http://www.lama-ole-nydahl.org/documents/k_letter_01.pdf|publisher=Diamond Way Buddhist Network|accessdate=27 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and was sent back to Europe in order to promote Buddhism in the West. In 1983, the Shamarpa named Nydahl a Buddhist master.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Shamar|first=Kunzig|title=Rinpoche|url=http://www.lama-ole-nydahl.org/documents/shamarpa.htm|publisher=Diamond Way Buddhist Network|accessdate=27 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1995, Khenpo Chödrak Thenpel Rinpoche named Nydahl a lama on behalf of the Buddhist Institutes of the Gyalwa Karmapa.&lt;ref name=&quot;SCHERER&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=SHA83/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Khenpo Chödrak Thenpel Rinpoche |url=http://www.lama-ole-nydahl.de/dokumente/kenpo_choedrak.htm |title=Certificate issued by the Buddhist Institutes of the Gyalwa Karmapa regarding Lama Ole Nydahl |date=December 3, 1995 |work=Lama-Ole-Nydahl.de |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nydahl has been criticised for never going on a three-year retreat, which is a prerequisite for use of the title 'lama' in some traditions of Buddhism.&lt;ref name=&quot;SCHERER&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=BORUP/&gt; However, the use of the word [[Lama]] as a term of address (vs. as a title) is a more individual matter, like the term of address 'Rinpoche'. Many of the early Buddhist teachers in the Karma Kagyu tradition used the word 'Lama' as a term of address, including [[Marpa]] and [[Milarepa]], in their songs to their teachers, who had not gone on three year retreats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Chang|first=Garma C.C.|title=The Hundred Thousand Songs of Milarepa|year=2010|publisher=Kessinger Publishing|location=LLC|isbn=978-1161603187}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sixteenth Karmapa also stated that, &quot;if someone has a greater wisdom and capacity for penetrating the teaching, then even without doing a three-year retreat, it is possible for one to experience definite understanding and realization.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=16th Karmapa |first=Rangjung Rigpei Dorje |coauthors=Ngodup Tsering Burkhar (tr.) |title=On Confidence in the Dharma: An Interview |url=http://www.kagyu.org/kagyulineage/buddhism/int/int02.php |year=1980 |work=Kagyu.org |publisher=Karma Triyana Dharmachakra |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nydahl was expressly confirmed as a lama by the Shamarpa in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Shamar|first=Kunzig|title=Rinpoche|url=http://www.lama-ole-nydahl.org/documents/ole_shamar_letter.pdf|accessdate=27 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Teaching===
{{multiple image
|direction=vertical
|width=220
|image1=|caption1=Lama Ole Nydahl, London 2005
|image2=Olenydahlblessing.jpg|caption2=Ole Nydahl, London, August 2007.
}}
Upon returning to Europe, Hannah and Ole Nydahl began to teach Buddhism and organize meditation centers, first in their native Denmark, then in Germany and other countries. The centers belong to the Karma Kagyu [[lineage (Buddhism)|lineage]] and operate under Ole Nydahl's practical guidance. In the early 90s, Diamond Way Buddhism was founded as a way to protect established centers during the [[Karmapa controversy]].&lt;ref name=NOSMILE/&gt;

{{As of|2012|2}}, there were 629 Diamond Way centers throughout the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Diamond Way Buddhism Worldwide |url=http://www.diamondway-buddhism.org/ |work=Diamondway-Buddhism.org |publisher=Diamond Way Buddhism Network |accessdate=February 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most are in Europe, Russia, or the United States. 

Ole Nydahl regularly travels between them during the year giving lectures and meditation courses. His courses cover topics such as mahamudra and [[phowa]]. He has traveled almost constantly for the last 40 years, teaching in a new city nearly every day.&lt;ref name=TIGER/&gt; His teaching activity was described and commended by the Shamarpa in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Shamar|first=Kunzig|title=Rinpoche|url=http://www.lama-ole-nydahl.org/documents/shamar%20_rinpoche_lama_ole_nydahl.pdf																					 					1|publisher=Diamond Way Buddhist Network|accessdate=5 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Together with his students, Nydahl has created Buddhist centers that provide access to Vajrayana meditation methods without requiring an understanding of [[Standard Tibetan|Tibetan language]] or [[Tibetan culture|culture]]. In the Diamond Way centers, the meditations and names of the various Buddha forms have been translated into Western languages. Ole Nydahl believes{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} it essential for people to understand and read the meditations in their own language in order for Buddhism to become truly rooted in the West. 

Diamond Way centers are run entirely by volunteers; the organization does not maintain any paid staff. The organizational structure is intended to be democratic and to function on the basis of idealism and friendship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Diamond Way Buddhism Worldwide&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.diamondway-buddhism.org/default.asp?col=03&amp;t=meditation.htm |title=Diamond Way Buddhism Worldwide |work=DiamondWay-Buddhism.org |publisher=Diamond Way Buddhism Network |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Buddhism Today, the Diamond Way Buddhist magazine,  &quot;hierarchical systems will not sell with independent people in the West. Nobody wants a distant teacher on a pedestal or a big organization standing on their shoulders and telling them what to think.&quot;&lt;ref name=FoB&gt;{{cite journal |last=Nydahl |first=Ole |title=Meditation in Diamond Way Buddhism |url=http://www.futureofbuddhism.com/budlamateach.htm |journal=Buddhism Today: The Diamond Way Magazine |volume=5 |year=1998 |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Students in Diamond Way Centers practice the [[ngöndro]] given by [[Wangchuk Dorje, 9th Karmapa Lama]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Refuge and the Enlightened Attitude|year=2006|publisher=Diamond Way Buddhist Centers USA|location=San Francisco, CA|author=9th Gyalwa Karmapa, Wangchuk Dorje|coauthors=Ulrich Kragh, Hannah Nydahl, Jim Rheingans, Frank Muller-Witte (translation)|editor=Anthony Hopson|format=Limited edition booklet}}&lt;/ref&gt; which are a set of four foundational practices that are intended to prepare the mind for enlightenment, a meditation on the Buddha Loving Eyes ([[Avalokiteśvara]] in Sanskrit, Chenrezig in Tibetan) and several forms of guru yoga or meditation on the lama (as given by the [[16th Karmapa]]). &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Dorje|first=Rangjung Rigpe|title=H.H. 16th Gyalwa Karmapa|url=http://www.namsebangdzo.com/product_p/9881.htm|work=Audio Recording 1977|publisher=Namse Bangdzo|accessdate=August 19, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Diamond Way Buddhism Worldwide&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Diamond Way Meditation Practices|url=http://www.buddhism.org.uk/buddhism/diamond-way-meditation/|publisher=Diamond Way Buddhist Network|accessdate=27 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a newsletter dated July 9, 2010, Nydahl responded to questions about the types of practices taught in Diamond Way Centers by stating &quot;I never taught anything I was not asked to pass on by the great Sixteenth Karmapa and that its basis was always the Guru Yogas of the Karmapas. Nothing else is practiced in our now 650 Diamond Way centers world-wide where my students meditate side by side.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |work=Newsletter of Diamond Way Centres |volume=39 |number=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Jørn Borup, a professor of religion at [[Aarhus University]], says that Ole Nydahl is &quot;the most lasting influence on the Buddhist practice scene in Denmark&quot; and &quot;has in many ways been the icon of living [[Buddhism in Denmark]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=BORUP&gt;{{cite journal |title=Critical Note: Buddhism in Denmark |url=http://www.globalbuddhism.org/9/borup08.htm |journal=Journal of Global Buddhism |first=Jørn |last=Borup |year=2008 |issn=1527-6457 |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The total number of Nydahl's adherents is unknown, but can be estimated conservatively to include 15,000 to 70,000 students and casual sympathizers world wide.&lt;ref name=&quot;SCHERER&quot;/&gt; In Germany alone, the German Buddhist Union, (Deutsche Buddhistische Union) estimates that about 20,000 persons regularly visit the Diamond Way centers and groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;SCHERER&quot;/&gt;

===Role in the Karmapa controversy===
{{Main|Karmapa controversy}}

When a great Tibetan lama dies, it is tradition in [[Tibetan Buddhism]] to find the next [[reincarnation]] to continue the work. When the Sixteenth Karmapa died in 1981, two potential successors were found, [[Trinley Thaye Dorje]] and [[Ogyen Trinley Dorje]], causing a major split in the Karma Kagyu. Nydahl, along with the Fourteenth Shamarpa, who was one of only four lineage-holders appointed to recognize the incarnation of the Karmapa at that time, supported Trinley Thaye Dorje. It was largely because of the work of Hannah and Ole Nydahl that most European Karma Kagyu centers chose to support Trinley Thaye Dorje.&lt;ref name=NOSMILE/&gt;&lt;ref name=BORUP/&gt; As a result, 629 of the centers supporting Trinley Thaye Dorje are affiliated with Diamond Way Buddhism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.diamondway-buddhism.org/default.asp?col=01 |title=Diamond Way Buddhism Worldwide |work=DiamondWay-Buddhism.org |publisher=Diamond Way Buddhism Network |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The other candidate, Ogyen Trinley Dorje, was recognized by [[Tenzin Gyatso, 14th Dalai Lama]]. The Dalai Lama confirmed Ogyen Trinley Dorje as the Karmapa after he had been requested to do so by two of the other lineage-holders, Tai Situ Rinpoche and [[Gyaltsap Rinpoche]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  |first = Ken
  |last = Holmes
  |title = Karmapa
  |publisher = Altea Publishing
  |year = 1995
  |isbn = 0-9524555-4-4
}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the supporters of Trinley Thaye Dorje say that the Dalai Lama is not entitled to do so, and has never done so before.&lt;ref name=NOSMILE/&gt;

The argument that Ogyen Trinley Dorje is the Karmapa is based in part on a letter presented by [[Pema Tönyö Nyinje]], 12th Tai Situpa. The supporters of Ogyen Trinley claim it was written by the Sixteenth Karmapa in order to predict the identity of his future rebirth.&lt;ref name=&quot;NOSMILE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RR&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Rogues in Robes: An Inside Chronicle of a Recent Chinese-Tibetan Intrigue in the Karma Kagyu Lineage of Diamond Way Buddhism |first=Tomek |last=Lehnert |publisher=Blue Dolphin Publishing |year=2000 |isbn=1-57733-026-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nydahl, the Shamarpa, and Topgala requested that the letter's authenticity be tested.&lt;ref name=&quot;RR&quot;/&gt; They believe that the letter was written not by the Sixteenth Karmapa but by the Situpa himself. They have requested that the letter be verified by independent experts including [[Questioned document examination|forensic document examiners]]. Tai Situ has thus far refused to allow this claiming it would be a violation of a sacred object.

Due to his role in the Karmapa controversy, Nydahl has been heavily criticized by the supporters of Ogyen Trinley Dorje, such as the authors [[Mick Brown (journalist)|Mick Brown]] and Lea Terhune, a student of Tai Situpa.&lt;ref name=&quot;RR&quot;/&gt; In connection to this, some blame Nydahl for causing the 1992 split of the Karma Kagyu, although there is no evidence of this, and accuse him of breaking the [[samaya]]s to his teachers, which is deprecated in [[Vajrayana]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NOSMILE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RR&quot;/&gt;

=== Dispute with German Buddhist Union ===
There is a greater concentration of Diamond Way centers in Germany compared to elsewhere in Europe. Between late 1999 and April 2000 there was a [[:de:Ole Nydahl#Rezeption und Kritik|public dispute]] between the [[:de:Deutsche Buddhistische Union|German Buddhist Union]] and the German branch of [[:de:Diamantweg|Diamond Way]], which is a member organisation of the Union. Due to of Nydahl's [[#Opinions of Islam|attitude towards Islam]], his political statements, his manner of expressing and presenting himself, and his [[#Personal life|relationships with women]], there were calls for the expulsion of Nydahl's organisation from the Union.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Peljor |first=Tenzin |url= http://info-buddhismus.de/lama_ole_nydahl.html |title= Lama Ole Nydahl - Diamantweg Buddhismus |date=20 April 2007 |work=Tibetischer Buddhismus |publisher=www.info-buddhismus.de |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dispute was resolved at a meeting between the two organizations on 4 October 2000; although differences were clear, they agreed to learn from the past and cooperate in the future. The conversation was described as &quot;a first step&quot; that &quot;should eliminate misunderstandings, and lead to clarity and cooperation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.buddhismus-heute.de/archive.issue__32.position__1.de.html |journal=Buddhismus Heute |number=32 |year=2001 |last= Zemlicka |first=Martina |title=Ein Interview mit Lama Ole Nydahl |publisher=Buddhistischen Dachverband Diamantweg der Karma Kagü Linie e. V.  |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The German branch of Diamond Way ''(Buddhistischer Dachverband Diamantweg)'' remains a member of the German Buddhist Union.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Deutsche Buddhistische Union e.V. (DBU) – Buddhismus in Deutschland: DBU-Mitgliedsgemeinschaften |url=http://www.dharma.de/dbu/frameset.php?content=http://www.dharma.de/dbu/dbu_gemeinschaften.php |work=Buddhismus in Deutschland |publisher=''Deutsche Buddhistische Union'' (German Buddhist Union) |accessdate=February 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Academic reception ===
Burkhard Scherer, a pupil of both Nydahl and Thaye Dorje,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Burkhard Scherer |url=http://www.randomhouse.de/Autor/Burkhard_Scherer/p156968.rhd?per=156968 |work=Randomhouse.de |publisher=Verlagsgruppe Random House |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; takes a historical-critical approach of Tibetan Buddhist Studies. He writes that: 

{{quote|Lay practitioners, both patrons and tantric adepts, played a decisive role in the process of assimilation that formed Tibetan Buddhism(s).  In the same way, lay people are now playing a key role during the westernization of Tibetan Buddhism(s). The [[Mahāsiddha]] / crazy yogi heritage and the medieval Tibetan doctrinal debate about teaching the [[Mahamudra|Great Seal]] outside of the [[Vajrayana|Tantra]] prove to be highly relevant historical precedents in the interpretation of unconventional modern/contemporary yogic/lay teachers such as the late [[Chogyam Trungpa]] and Ole Nydahl.&lt;ref name=&quot;SCHERER&quot; /&gt;}}

He regrets that Nydahl continues to be ignored by Tibet scholars  and argues that prevailing negative criticism from a position of suspicion by sociologists and students of [[New Religious Movements]] should be counterbalanced by positive criticism from a position of trust by Tibet scholars.

{{quote|... the little recent academic attention Nydahl has drawn so far come, interestingly, from European sociologists of religions who specialize in New Religious Movements and Contemporary Religions/Buddhism(s).The neglect of Modern Tibetan Buddhist movements by classically trained Tibetologists is deplorable; the historical-critical methodology of Tibetan Studies can complement sociology and anthropology and add greatly to the discourses about authenticity and legitimization of movements such as Nydahl's ''Diamond Way''.&lt;ref name=&quot;SCHERER&quot; /&gt;}}

Martin Baumann, a professor of religion at the [[University of Lucerne]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unilu.ch/eng/martin-baumann_242594.html |title= Martin Baumann |work=Unilu.ch |publisher=Universität Luzern |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; remarked in a newspaper interview &quot;when I listen to his [Nydahl's] alarmingly superficial formulations in his talks I can understand his critics who say that he is presenting a watered-down 'instant Buddhism', a sort of 'Buddhism light' for the West.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Baumann |first=Martin |title= Eine Art 'Buddhismus Light'? |newspaper= Neue Luzerner Zeitung |date=4 November 2004 |number=255 |page=11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Political views ==
Nydahl is a strong proponent of human rights, and of women's rights in particular.  He also has a critical view of [[Islam]]. He has called [[Allah]] a &quot;terrible god&quot;,&lt;ref name=WWIRE&gt;{{cite web |last=Graham |first=Matt |url=http://www.wweek.com/portland/blog-5866-lama_ole_nydahl_controversial_unconventional_lama_.html |title=Lama Ole Nydahl, Controversial, Unconventional Lama, Speaks Tonight |work=Williamette Week |date=November 25, 2008 |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has characterized Muslim beliefs as antithetical to freedom of speech and women's rights:

{{quote|I seriously hope, you know, that we're not losing the freedom of expression right now, that we're not losing the ability to say what we think even if we step on the toes of some gentlemen from the Near East&amp;nbsp;… who like to beat their wives or stone them or whatever else they do, right?&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube |id=2Y9fwIl1jCM |title=The Freedom To Choose - Lama Ole Nydahl}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Nydahl says that he does not make political comments in his capacity as a lama, but as a &quot;responsible, thinking human being&quot;, and that no one can make such statements from a Buddhist perspective because [[Buddha Shakyamuni]] did not comment on religious ideas founded centuries after his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Hedegaard |first=Lars |url=http://www.sappho.dk/Den%20loebende/nydahl-english.html |title=The Buddha meets Holger Danske |publisher=[[Free Press Society]] |work=Sappho |location=Denmark |date=6 April 2007 |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also distinguishes the &quot;mainstream Muslims&quot; that he disapproves of from [[Sufi]]s and [[Bahá'í]]s.&lt;ref name=WWIRE/&gt;

An online interview with Nydahl also featured the following statement: &quot;Judaism and Christianity are fine. Islam, I warn against. I know the Koran, I know the life story of Mohammad and I think we cannot use that in our society today.&quot;&lt;ref name=WWIRE/&gt;

== Personal life ==
Nydahl is not a monk and so has not taken vows of celibacy. Jørn Borup, Associate Professor of Religion at Aarhus University, notes that Nydahl &quot;certainly isn't afraid to say that he likes the ladies, primarily his wife, who is now deceased, but also other women. This brings him into conflict with not just Islam but also, sometimes, with old-fashioned Buddhism...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Rasmussen |first=Hans Henrik |work=Information |title=Buddhas Kirger |date=18 June 2009 |url=http://www.information.dk/195037 |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Yet several well-known [[Vajrayana]] Buddhist lamas were married: [[Marpa]] the translator is said to have had nine wives;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Quintman |first=Andrew |title=Marpa Chokyi Lodro |url=http://www.treasuryoflives.org/biographies/view/Marpa-Chokyi-Lodro/4354 |work=The Treasury of Lives: Biographies of Tibetan Buddhist Masters |date=September 2010 |publisher=Shelley &amp; Donald Rubin Foundation |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; others had romantic relationships, including the [[6th Dalai Lama]], and the teacher who brought Buddhism to Tibet, [[Padmasambhava]], who had five Tantric consorts who were also his students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Camphausen |first=Rufus C. |title=The Five Consorts |work=Yoniversum.nl |publisher=The Yoniverse |url=http://www.yoniversum.nl/dakini/padma5.html |accessdate=February 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When asked about it, Nydahl has said: &quot;There’s no teacher-student relationship involved in that, [...] They’re Diamond Way Buddhists, but they’re not my students in that moment. They’re equal partners.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Orso |first=Joe |work=La Crosse Tribune |date=November 15, 2009 |title=Joe Orso: Lama Ole: Buddhist teacher or charlatan |url=http://lacrossetribune.com/news/local/article_bc6ed916-d197-11de-85b7-001cc4c002e0.html |accessdate=February 17, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bibliography==
Ole Nydahl has written several books in English, German and Danish, which have been translated into several other European languages.

Most popular English titles:
* ''Ngondro: The Four Foundational Practices of Tibetan Buddhism''. Blue Dolphin Publishing (1990). ISBN 978-0-931892-23-3
* ''Riding the Tiger: Twenty Years on the Road - Risks and Joys of Bringing Tibetan Buddhism to the West''. Blue Dolphin Publishing (1992). ISBN 978-0-931892-67-7
* ''Entering the Diamond Way: Tibetan Buddhism meets the West''. Blue Dolphin Publishing (1999). ISBN 978-0-931892-03-5
* ''The Great Seal: Limitless Space and Joy - The Mahamudra View of Diamond Way Buddhism''. Fire Wheel Publishing (2004). ISBN 0-9752954-0-3
* ''The Way Things Are: A living Approach to Buddhism for today's world.'' O Books (2008). ISBN 978-1-84694-042-2
* ''Buddha and Love: Timeless Wisdom for Modern Relationships.'' Brio Books (2012). ISBN 978-1937061845

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* {{official website|http://www.lama-ole-nydahl.org/}}
* {{Commons-inline|Ole Nydahl}}

{{Modern Dharmic writers}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Nydahl, Ole
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1941-03-19
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Copenhagen, Denmark
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Nydahl, Ole}}
[[Category:1941 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Danish non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Danish religious leaders]]
[[Category:Karma Kagyu Lamas]]
[[Category:People from Copenhagen]]
[[Category:Tibetan Buddhism writers]]
[[Category:Tibetan Buddhists from Denmark]]
[[Category:Converts to Buddhism]]

[[bg:Оле Нидал]]
[[cs:Ole Nydahl]]
[[da:Ole Nydahl]]
[[de:Ole Nydahl]]
[[et:Ole Nydahl]]
[[es:Ole Nydahl]]
[[fr:Ole Nydahl]]
[[it:Ole Nydahl]]
[[he:אולה נידהל]]
[[lt:Ole Nydahl]]
[[hu:Láma Ole Nydahl]]
[[nl:Ole Nydahl]]
[[pl:Ole Nydahl]]
[[ru:Нидал, Оле]]
[[simple:Ole Nydahl]]
[[sk:Ole Nydahl]]
[[fi:Ole Nydahl]]
[[sv:Ole Nydahl]]
[[tr:Ole Nydahl]]
[[uk:Оле Нідал]]
[[zh:欧雷·尼达尔]]</text>
      <sha1>bnkxf6pmpv4vy9rn7qeh8swj2t2af9i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
