<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Reincarnation research</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7484080</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519558814</id>
      <parentid>519111028</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T12:13:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rubinbot</username>
        <id>7661631</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.5.4) (Robot: Modifying [[ru:Исследования реинкарнаций]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45449">'''Reincarnation research''' is a branch of [[parapsychology]] concerning [[reincarnation]], specifically the study of &quot;cases of the reincarnation type&quot;, that is, cases in which a young child &quot;spontaneously makes remarks about a previous life he would have led before his birth&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |title=Three Cases of the Reincarnation Type in the Netherlands |author=Rivas, Titus |journal=Journal of Scientic Exploration |volume=17 |number=3 |date=2003 |pages=527-532 |url=http://www.scientificexploration.org/journal/jse_17_3_rivas.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; about a person with whom the child identifies himself.&lt;ref name=MHK/&gt; [[Psychiatrist]] [[Ian Stevenson]], from the [[University of Virginia School of Medicine]], investigated many reports of young children who claimed to remember a past life. He conducted more than 2,500 [[case study|case studies]] over a period of 40 years and published twelve books, including ''[[Twenty Cases Suggestive of Reincarnation]]'' and ''[[Where Reincarnation and Biology Intersect]]''. Stevenson retired in 2002, and psychiatrist [[Jim B. Tucker]] took over his work and wrote ''[[Life Before Life]]''. Other people who have undertaken research on reincarnation include [[Satwant Pasricha]], [[Godwin Samararatne]], Antonia Mills, and [[Erlendur Haraldsson]]. Research methods have involved analysis of childhood memories, corresponding birthmarks, and psychological/cultural characteristics. No line of research has conclusively demonstrated the existence of reincarnation.  Skeptics and the scientific community in general consider reincarnation research to be [[pseudoscientific]].&lt;ref name=kurtsPS&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kurtz P. |title=Two Sources of Unreason in Democratic Society: The paranormal and religion |journal=Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences |volume=775 |pages=493–504 |year=2006 |doi=10.1111/j.1749-6632.1996.tb23166.x |url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119242621/abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;isbn9781405181235&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Smith, Jonathan C |title=Pseudoscience and Extraordinary Claims of the Paranormal: A Critical Thinker's Toolkit |publisher=Wiley Blackwell |location=New York |year=2009 |page=241 |isbn=978-1-4051-8123-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some parapsychologists advocate developing protocols to guide, sort, compare, and evaluate cases studies.&lt;ref name=edelnet/&gt;

==Background==
[[Reincarnation]] is the religious or philosophical concept that the [[Soul (spirit)|soul]] or [[spirit]], after biological [[death]], begins a new life in a new body that may be human, animal or spiritual depending on the moral quality of the previous life's actions. This doctrine is a central tenet of the [[Indian religions]]&lt;ref&gt;The [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] concept of [[Rebirth (Buddhism)|rebirth]] is also often referred to as reincarnation.see Charles Taliaferro, Paul Draper, Philip L. Quinn, ''A Companion to Philosophy of Religion''. John Wiley and Sons, 2010, page 640, [http://books.google.com/books?id=SSCx-67Tk6cC&amp;pg=PA640&amp;dq=reincarnation+and+rebirth&amp;cd=8#v=onepage&amp;q=reincarnation%20and%20rebirth&amp;f=false Google Books].&lt;/ref&gt; and is a belief that was held by such historic figures as [[Pythagoras]], [[Plato]] and [[Socrates]]. Reincarnation is a central doctrine of the [[Kabbalah]] and is accepted by [[Hasidim]] and other (although not all) adherents of [[Orthodox Judaism]]. It is also a common belief of pagan religions such as [[Druidism]], [[Spiritism]], [[Theosophy]], and [[Eckankar]] and is found in many tribal societies around the world, in places such as Siberia, West Africa, North America, and Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Gananath Obeyesekere, ''Imagining Karma: Ethical Transformation in Amerindian, Buddhist, and Greek Rebirth''. University of California Press, 2002, page 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent decades, many Europeans and North Americans have developed an interest in reincarnation.&lt;ref name=&quot;hi.is&quot;&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.hi.is/~erlendur/english/Nordic_Psychology_erlhar06.pdf Popular psychology, belief in life after death and reincarnation in the Nordic countries, Western and Eastern Europe]|54.8&amp;nbsp;KB}}&lt;/ref&gt; Feature films, such as ''[[Kundun]]'', ''[[What Dreams May Come (film)|What Dreams May Come]]'' and ''[[Birth (film)|Birth]]'', contemporary books by authors such as [[Carol Bowman]] and [[Vicki Mackenzie]], as well as popular songs, regularly mention reincarnation.

==Researchers==
Several researchers are examining cases of early childhood past life memories and birthmarks at the [[University of Virginia]] Division of Perceptual Studies in the School of Medicine. Two of the best known researchers at Virginia are the psychiatrists Jim B. Tucker (Bonner-Lowry Associate Professor of Personality Studies) and Ian Stevenson (Professor of psychiatry and head of the Division of Perceptual Studies until his retirement in 2002) and between them they have published many books and dozens of research papers in peer-reviewed journals.&lt;ref&gt;University of Virginia, Division of Perceptual Studies, [http://www.medicine.virginia.edu/clinical/departments/psychiatry/sections/cspp/dops/publications-page#Reincar-articles Books and Articles by Division Staff]&lt;/ref&gt;

Other people who have undertaken research on reincarnation include [[Satwant Pasricha]], Antonia Mills, [[Godwin Samararatne]], [[Erlendur Haraldsson]] and H. H. Jürgen Keil. Pasricha is the head of the Department of Clinical Psychology at the [[NIMHANS|National Institute of Mental Health and Neurosciences]] in India.&lt;ref&gt;K. Sekar, et al., [http://stg1.kar.nic.in/nimhans/dis_man/man_tsu1.pdf Tsunami: Psychosocial care for individuals &amp; families]{{dead link|date=September 2012}}, January 2005, p. 7. Accessed 2009-01-27.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, she wrote the book ''Can the Mind Survive Beyond Death?: Reincarnation Research''.&lt;ref&gt;Satwant Pasricha (2008). ''Can the Mind Survive Beyond Death?: Reincarnation Research'', 184 pages.&lt;/ref&gt; Mills is an [[anthropology|anthropologist]] and professor of First Nation Studies at [[University of Northern British Columbia]], specializing in [[First Nations]] peoples' reincarnation beliefs and cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=University of Northern British Columbia: First Nations Studies Faculty |url=http://www.unbc.ca/firstnations/faculty.html |accessdate=2012-08-26 |quote=First Nations ... reincarnation beliefs and cases are [among] her current research interests.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1994, she co-edited (with Richard Slobodin) ''Amerindian Rebirth: Reincarnation Belief Among North American Indians and Inuit''. Haraldsson is Professor Emeritus of [[psychology]] at the Faculty of [[social science]] at the [[University of Iceland]].

Mills, Haraldsson and Keil conducted independent replication studies of Stevenson's reincarnation research from 1987 to 1994&lt;ref name=MHK/&gt; and subsequently continued independent research in the field.

==Methods==
===Children's memories===
Ian Stevenson, a Canadian [[biochemist]] and [[professor]] of [[psychiatry]], investigated many reports of young children who claimed to remember a past life with events that occurred during a previous life, ultimately conducting more than 2,500 [[case study|case studies]] over the course of his lifetime and publishing twelve books. Stevenson undertook reincarnation research throughout the world, including North and South America, Europe, Africa and Asia.&lt;ref name = Cordon&gt;{{cite book |author=Cordón LA |title=Popular psychology: an encyclopedia |publisher= [[Greenwood Publishing Group|Greenwood Press]] |location=Westport, Conn |year=2005 |pages= 183–5|isbn=0-313-32457-3 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Stevenson, childhood memories ostensibly related to reincarnation normally occur between the ages of three and seven years then fade shortly afterwards. He compared the memories with reports of people known to the deceased, attempting to do so before any contact between the child and the deceased's family had occurred.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker 2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Tucker, Jim |title=Life before life: a scientific investigation of children's memories of previous lives |publisher=St. Martin's Press |location=New York |year=2005 |pages= |isbn=0-312-32137-6 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stevenson found that the vast majority of cases investigated involved people who had met some sort of violent or untimely death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker 2005&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cadoret, Remi 2005&quot;/&gt;

===Corresponding birthmarks===
Some 35 percent of the subjects examined by Stevenson had birthmarks or birth defects. Stevenson reported that in the majority of these cases &quot;the subject's marks or defects correspond to injuries or illness experienced by the deceased person who the subject remembers; and medical documents have confirmed this correspondence in more than forty cases&quot;.&lt;ref name=jh&gt;Jane Henry (2005). [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=EaIhapm-4UgC&amp;pg=PP5&amp;lpg=PP5&amp;dq=%22Parapsychology:+Research+on+Exceptional+Experiences%22+%22Jane+Henry%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=tReXJKfiIh&amp;sig=IIE8o603PaUPxN2RT21gedmeoP8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=k_VKSpL6HIvkNduOrJsB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1 Parapsychology: research on exceptional experiences] Routledge, p. 224.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the birthmarks are not just small discolourations. They are &quot;often unusual in shape or size and are often puckered or raised rather than simply being flat. Some can be quite dramatic and unusual in appearance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Tucker, 2005, p.10&lt;/ref&gt; Stevenson believed that the existence of birth marks and deformities on children, when they occurred at the location of fatal wounds in the deceased, provided the best evidence for reincarnation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cadoret, Remi 2005&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | last = Cadoret | first = R | url = http://ajp.psychiatryonline.org/cgi/content/full/162/4/823 | title = Book Forum: Ethics, Values, and Religion - European Cases of the Reincarnation Type | volume = 162 | issue = 4 | pages = 823–4 | journal = The American Journal of Psychiatry | year = 2005 | doi = 10.1176/appi.ajp.162.4.823}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he subsequently wrote ''[[Reincarnation and Biology|Reincarnation and Biology: A Contribution to the Etiology of Birthmarks and Birth Defects]]''.&lt;ref name=NYT/&gt;

===Psychological and cultural characteristics===
Erlendur Haraldsson and colleagues conducted several studies of the personality, abilities and psychological characteristics of children who claim memories of a previous life, comparing them with paired children who did not.&lt;ref name=Haraldsson1995/&gt;&lt;ref name=Haraldsson-Fowler/&gt;&lt;ref name=Haraldsson2003&gt;Haraldsson, Erlendur (2003). Children who speak of past-life experiences: Is there a psychological explanation? ''Psychology and Psychotherapy: Theory, Research and Practice'', ''76'', 55-67. [https://notendur.hi.is/erlendur/english/cort/explain.pdf Reprint]&lt;/ref&gt; The objective of these studies was to determine the role certain psychological characteristics the children might have as possible explanations for their past-life memories, such as, fantasy, suggestibility, social isolation, dissociation and attention seeking. In a study of 23 children pairs in Sri Lanka, those claiming memories of a previous life had greater verbal skills and better memory than their peers, performed much better in school, and were more socially active, but were not more suggestible.&lt;ref name=Haraldsson1995/&gt; In a further study of 27 children pairs in Sri Lanka, one evaluation checklist revealed that the target children exhibited more behavioral problems, including oppositional traits, and obsessional and perfectionistic characteristics, and a dissociation instrument showed them to have dissociative tendencies such as rapid changes in personality and frequent daydreaming.&lt;ref name=Haraldsson-Fowler/&gt; In a later study of 30 children pairs from Lebanon, children claiming memories of a previous life tested higher for daydreaming, attention seeking and dissociation but not for suggestibility and social isolation. The level of dissociation was much lower than cases of multiple personality and was not clinically relevant. There was some evidence of [[post-traumatic stress disorder]]-like symptoms; eighty percent of the children spoke of memories of a violent death, mostly from accidents but also war-related deaths and murders. It is possible the repeated appearance of this imagery serves as a stressor.&lt;ref name=Haraldsson2003/&gt;

Antonia Mills reported an on-going longitudinal study of Hindu and Muslim children who reported memories of a previous life, both with and without a shift in religion, from Hindu to Muslim or vice versa.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Antonia (2006). Back from Death: Young Adults in Northern India Who as Children Were Said to Remember a Previous Life, with or without a Shift in Religion (Hindu to Moslem or Vice Versa). ''Anthropology and Humanism'', Volume 31, Issue 2, 141–156.&lt;/ref&gt; The objective is to evaluate the later effect of the children's experience as young adults, how it impacts their attitude toward efforts at Hindu—Muslim reconciliation, their integration in their communities, and whether they score higher on dissociative and psychic experience scales than those who have no such memories. These cases of a shift in religion are very rare. Reincarnation is accepted as a reality by Hindus, yet most of the reported cases entail someone who died violently and came back quickly. Muslims do not formally accept reincarnation as a possibility, yet they report about as many cases of children remembering a life in the &quot;other&quot; religion as do the Hindus.

===Independent replication===
Mills, Haraldsson and Keil conducted independent studies of Stevenson and his colleague's cases&lt;ref name=MHK/&gt; and added several previously unpublished cases.&lt;ref name=Mills1989&gt;Mills, A. (1989). Three cases suggestive of reincarnation in northern India: A replication study. ''Journal of Scientific Exploration'', ''3'', 133-184.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Haraldsson, E. (1991). Children claiming past-life memories: Four cases in Sri Lanka. ''Journal of Scientific Exploration'', ''5'', 233-261.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Keil&gt;Keil, H. H. J. (1991). New cases in Burma, Thailand and Turkey: A limited field study replication of some aspects of Ian Stevenson's research. ''Journal of Scientific Exploration'', ''5'', 29-59.&lt;/ref&gt; Their replications included 60 cases in Burma, Thailand and Turkey by Keil,&lt;ref name=Keil/&gt; 25 cases in Sri Lanka by Haraldsson,&lt;ref name=MHK/&gt; and 38 cases in northern India by Mills.&lt;ref name=Mills1989/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mills, A. (1990a). Moslem cases of the reincarnation type in northern India: A test of the hypothesis of imposed identification. Part I: Analysis of 26 cases. ''Journal of Scientific Exploration'', ''4'', 171-188.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mills, A. (1990b). Moslem cases of the reincarnation type in northern India: A test of the hypothesis of imposed identification. Part II: Reports of three cases. ''Journal of Scientific Exploration'', ''4'', 189-201.&lt;/ref&gt; Mills, Haraldsson and Keil concluded that in some of the cases the children had no normal way of knowing about the person with whom they identified themselves. They noted problem areas requiring further study.&lt;ref name=MHK/&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The investigations of three independent researchers into reported claims of reincarnation in five cultures in which such cases are reported suggests that some children who identify themselves with a person about whom they have no way of knowing. In these cases, the children apparently exhibit knowledge and behavior appropriate to that person. Although cultural belief in the possibility of reincarnation fosters such cases, and more research needs to be done on the social construction of cases, belief itself does not appear to account for the totality of the child's statements and behavior.&lt;ref name=MHK/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In further research, Antonia Mills, an anthropologist specializing in [[First Nations]] studies, published studies of reincarnation cases among First Nations peoples, including cases involving birthmarks.&lt;ref&gt;Mills, A. (1994). Rebirth and Identity: Three Gitksan cases of pierced-ear birthmarks. In Antonia Mills and Richard Slobodin (Eds.), ''Amerindian Rebrith: Reincarnation belief among North American Indians and Inuit'' (pp. 211-241), Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mills, A. (1988). A Preliminary Investigation of Cases of Reincarnation among the Beaver and Gitksan Indians, ''Anthropologica'', Vol. 30, No. 1, p. 23-59.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mills, A. C. (1988). A comparison of Wet'suwet'en cases of the reincarnation type with Gitksan and Beaver, ''Journal of Anthropological Research'', Vol. 44, No. 4, pp. 385-415.&lt;/ref&gt; In a summary of her work,&lt;ref name=Mills1994&gt;Mills, Antonia (1994). Making a scientific investigation of ethnographic cases suggestive of reincarnation. In David E. Young and Jean-Guy Goulet, ''Being Changed by Cross-cultural Encounters: The anthropology of extraordinary experience'' (pp. 237-270). Peterborough, Ontario: Broadview Press, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; Mills concluded that the numerous cases of the reincarnation type require an explanation for which reincarnation appears to be the most compelling. However, it is impossible to eliminate other possible sources of the child's knowledge. [[Cryptomnesia]] or [[amnesia]] as the source of the information may be present in some cases but are unlikely to account for most of them. Other paranormal means of communication such as [[extrasensory perception]] (ESP) may account for some elements of some cases, but the evidence for telepathic or other types of ESP indicate that they alone could not account for the level of knowledge and the personal characteristics shown in these cases. Mills suggested three criteria be used as guidelines to evaluate whether reported cases of reincarnation are indicative of more than cultural construction and wishful thinking:&lt;ref name=Mills1994/&gt;

# '''Statements made by the child based on knowledge the child could not have learned through normal means''' such as the name of the previous personality and the mode of death, and speaking from the point of view of the previous personality including recognition of people, objects and places.
# '''The presence of skills and interests in the child which it cannot be expected to have acquired in the current life''' such as speaking a language unknown to the current family and community, the ability to play a musical instrument, or abnormal philias or phobias.
# '''Specific birthmarks or birth defects which correspond to wounds or marks on the previous personality''', comparing them to photographs, medical records or autopsies of the previous personality. In cases where the mother witnessed the marks or wounds on the previous personality, one cannot eliminate the possibility that the mother's awareness had an impact on the creation of the birthmark.

===Reviews===
''[[Old Souls|Old Souls: Scientific Evidence From Children Who Remember Previous Lives]]'' is a [[non-fiction]] book by journalist [[Tom Shroder]]. An editor at the ''Washington Post'', Shroder traveled extensively with Ian Stevenson, as he conducted [[past life]] and reincarnation research in [[Lebanon]], [[India]] and the [[American South]].&lt;ref name=Herald-Tribune&gt;[http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=fh4cAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=530EAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4574,4095009 &quot;Searching out Old Souls&quot;], by Karen R. Long, ''[[Sarasota Herald-Tribune]]'', August 19, 1999, page 5E. Online at [[Google News]]. Retrieved June 15, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; While Stevenson wrote extensively on his reincarnation studies, his work earned limited circulation outside [[academia]]. At the outset, Shroder sees his role not only as observer, but also as skeptic. But as his journey with Stevenson progresses, Shroder finds it increasingly difficult to reject the possibility of past lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;john&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://weeklywire.com/ww/01-10-00/alibi_bookreview.html |title= Little Johnny Just Isn't Himself Today |author=Kenny, Thane |date=January 10, 2000 |work=Weekly Wire }}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Life Before Life]]: A Scientific Investigation of Children's Memories of Previous Lives'' is a 2005 book written by psychiatrist [[Jim B. Tucker]], which presents an overview of more than 40 years of reincarnation research at the [[University of Virginia School of Medicine]].&lt;ref name=but&gt;Butziger, R. &quot;A Scientific Look at Reincarnation&quot;, ''PsycCRITIQUES'', 51(22), May 31, 2006, p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Life Before Life'' has been translated into ten languages&lt;ref&gt;[http://cedarcreekinst.org/html/board_members.html Cedar Creek Institute Board Members: Jim B. Tucker]&lt;/ref&gt; and the foreword to the book is written by [[Ian Stevenson]].&lt;ref name=tuck&gt;Jim B. Tucker (2005). ''[http://books.google.com.au/books?id=dhTJzv_K5A0C&amp;dq=%22life+before+life%22+book&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=y9N6kXkuge&amp;sig=veonzeQNCneMQOSldwrXOyBAcN8&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=D5B9TP7SOIGgvQP9oKXJAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwBg Life Before Life: A scientific Investigation of Children's Memories of Previous Lives]'', St. Martin's Press, New York, 256pp. ISBN 0-312-32137-6.&lt;/ref&gt;  Psychiatrist Jim Tucker took over Stevenson's work on his retirement in 2002. Tucker recognizes that none of the cases examined are perfect, and &quot;faulty memory by informants&quot; is seen to be the &quot;best normal explanation for many of the cases&quot; reviewed in the book.&lt;ref name=two&gt;Jim B. Tucker (2005). ''Life Before Life: A scientific Investigation of Children's Memories of Previous Lives'', St. Martin's Press, New York, pp. 205-209.&lt;/ref&gt; Tucker discusses this, referring to several relevant studies which have been done, and argues that there is no support for the conclusion that informants must be remembering statements or events incorrectly.&lt;ref name=two/&gt; Tucker basically agrees with Ian Stevenson who said &quot;reincarnation is the best — even though not the only — explanation for the stronger cases we have investigated&quot;.&lt;ref name=three&gt;Jim B. Tucker (2005). ''Life Before Life: A scientific Investigation of Children's Memories of Previous Lives'', St. Martin's Press, New York, p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Paul Edwards (philosopher)|Paul Edwards]], a philosopher and skeptic, has analyzed many of accounts of reincarnation, and called them [[anecdotal evidence|anecdotal]].&lt;ref name=skepticreport.com&gt;Rockley, Richard. [http://www.skepticreport.com/newage/stevensonbook.htm Book Review: Children who remember previous lives]{{dead link|date=September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; while also suggesting that claims of evidence for reincarnation originate from [[selective thinking]] and from the [[false memory syndrome|false memories]] that often result from one's own belief system and basic fears, and thus cannot be counted as [[empirical evidence]].

===Research protocols===
In 2000, Jim Tucker demonstrated the way in which the University of Virginia has used the ‘strength-of-case scale’ (SOCS) to sort and classify about 800 cases. The SOCS uses four criteria to evaluate a reincarnation case:
(1) whether it involves birthmarks/defects that correspond to the
supposed previous life;
(2) the strength of the statements made about the previous life;
(3) the relevant behaviours exhibited, as they relate to the previous life; and
(4) an evaluation of a possible connection between the child
reporting a previous life and the supposed previous life.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker, Jim B. (2000). A Scale to Measure the Strength of Children’s Claims of Previous Lives: Methodology and Initial Findings. ''Journal of Scientific Exploration'', Vol. 14, No. 4, 571–581. [http://www.scientificexploration.org/journal/jse_14_4_tucker.pdf Reprint]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=edelnet/&gt;

Antonia Mills used the SOCS scale to re-evaluate the case of Ajendra Singh Chauhan,&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Antonia (2004). Inferences from the Case of Ajendra Singh Chauhan: The Effect of Parental Questioning, of Meeting the &quot;Previous Life&quot; Family, an Aborted Attempt to Quantify Probabilities, and the Impact on His Life as a Young Adult. ''Journal of Scientific Exploration'', Vol. 18, No. 4, 609–641. [http://www.scientificexploration.org/journal/jse_18_4_mills.pdf Reprint]&lt;/ref&gt; then assessing what the score would have been had Ajendra’s father not suspected that his son's statements represented a case of reincarnation and had not asked him questions. Ajendra made 12 statements spontaneously without questioning and a further 15 statements in response to his father's questions. The Ajendra case would have had a SOCS score of 0 and would not have been &quot;solved&quot;, had the father not asked questions. As a result of the father's questions, the case was solved and most of Ajendra's statements were verified with a total SOCS score of 31, ranking high on the SOCS scale. This result shows how important parental questioning can be in eliciting the information necessary for solving a case. The case demonstrated the importance of having a written record of the child’s statements before the case is solved, to prevent possible cultural elaboration. In this case, after-the-fact embroidery was checked and was found less accurate, as it has been found in other cases, than the child’s initial statements.

Jonathan Edelmann and William Bernet say that the SOCS is an important tool for studying reincarnation.  But an ideal research protocol would have the sort of evidence and employ the research methods able to “give substantive weight to a reincarnation hypothesis, even for those who have physicalism as a metaphysical bias and are therefore highly sceptical of reincarnation case studies”.&lt;ref name=edelnet/&gt; Edelmann and Bernet go on to say:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
In order to have an ideal protocol for reincarnation research, the standards, acceptable practices, and methods should be carefully outlined and reviewed by professionals in fields as varied as psychology,
psychiatry, parapsychology, forensic science, and anthropology. The group must hold varying degrees of sympathy and skepticism for the belief in reincarnation so as to add as much objectivity and balance to the discussion as possible.&lt;ref name=edelnet&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.imprint.co.uk/pdf/Edelman.pdf |title=Setting Criteria for Ideal Reincarnation Research |author=Jonathan Edelmann and William Bernet |date= 2007 |work=[[Journal of Consciousness Studies]], 14, No. 12 |page=92–101 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Antonia Mills and Steven Lynn&lt;ref name=Mills-Lynn&gt;Mills, Antonia, and Lynn, Steven Jay (2000). Past-life experiences, in Cardeña, Etzel; Lynn, Steven Jay; and Krippner, Stanley (Eds). ''[[Varieties of Anomalous Experience]]: Examining the scientific evidence'', (pp. 283-313). Washington, DC: American Psychological Association, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; noted a number of methodological issues in reincarnation research:
* '''The need for independent replication of Stevenson and his associates' work.''' A number of replications have been carried out by independent researchers, for example Mills, Haraldsson and Keil,&lt;ref name=MHK&gt;Mills, A., Haraldsson, E., and Keil, H. H. J. (1994). Replication studies of cases suggestive of reincarnation by three independent investigators. ''Journal of the American Society for Psychical Research, ''88'', 207-219. [https://notendur.hi.is/erlendur/english/cort/Replication_Studies_of_Cases.pdf Reprint].&lt;/ref&gt; who augmented Stevenson's work with methods such as (1) video-recording children who visit the village and home of a previous personality for the first time,&lt;ref&gt;Mills, Antonia (2003). Are Children with Imaginary Playmates and Children Said to Remember Previous Lives Cross-Culturally Comparable Categories? ''Transcultural Psychiatry'', vol. 40, no. 1, 62-90.&lt;/ref&gt; and (2) assessing the psychological characteristics of children who appear to remember and act on the basis of experiences from a previous life.&lt;ref name=Haraldsson1995&gt;Haraldsson, E. (1995). Personality and Abilities of Children Claiming Previous-Life Memories, ''Journal of Nervous &amp; Mental Disease'', 183(7), 445-451.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Haraldsson-Fowler&gt;Haraldsson, Erlendur, Patrick Fowler &amp; Vimala  Periyannanpillai (2000).  Psychological Characteristics of Children Who Speak of a Previous Life: A Further Field Study in Sri Lanka. ''Transcultural Psychiatry'', ''37'', 525-544. [https://notendur.hi.is/~erlendur/english/cort/transcult.pdf Reprint]&lt;/ref&gt; 
* '''Interviewer effects.''' An interviewer's communications may cause young children to incorporate misinformation into their accounts and repeat it as actual experience. Thus, researchers' and others' expectations, communications and suggestions may shape a child's past-life report. It would therefore be worthwhile to study the role of investigator effects in studies of children's past-life memory reports.
* '''Difficulties with probability assessments.''' It is difficult to assess whether a child's statements regarding a past life exceed chance probability. Each case is unique and needs its own assessment of probabilities. For example, how does one verify the correctness of a detailed statement (e.g., how many people had two water buffaloes in the village decades earlier) or how much weight does one give to incorrect or invalid statements (e.g., statements that are self-contradictory)? Stevenson assessed the chance probability to be very low of having one or more birthmarks on the same regions of the body as the injuries to the previous personality, for example with bullet entry and exit wounds and the corresponding birthmarks. However, the assessment of birthmarks is very complex and collaboration with geneticists would be useful. Also, when a case is &quot;solved&quot; on the basis of corresponding bodily markings, the accuracy of the child's statements needs to be evaluated, noting whether socializers imparted knowledge to the child consistent with the reincarnation interpretation.

==Conclusions and criticism==
Antonia Mills and Steven Lynn&lt;ref name=Mills-Lynn/&gt; discussed three explanations that have been offered by various researchers for spontaneous childhood past-life experiences: 

* The '''reincarnation hypothesis''', which holds that the reported experiences are veridical. 
* The '''ESP hypothesis''', which holds that the reported experiences are transmitted telepathically or through extrasensory perception. 
* The '''sociocognitive hypothesis''', which holds that the experiences are a cultural construction and interpretation of behavior. 

A fourth explanation, that the experiences are the result of deliberately fraudulent or unconsciously motivated self-deception driven by a need for notoriety, self-aggrandizement or confirmation of a belief in reincarnation, was felt by Mills and Lynn to be neither a satisfactory nor plausible explanation for many of the most impressive and thoroughly investigated cases.&lt;ref name=Mills-Lynn/&gt;

Stevenson never claimed that he had proved the existence of reincarnation, and cautiously referred to his cases as being &quot;of the reincarnation type&quot; or &quot;suggestive of reincarnation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Harvey J. Irwin (2004). [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=jB88qA7C9oYC&amp;pg=PA218&amp;lpg=PA218&amp;dq=stevenson+edwards+reincarnation&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=L63PNxxajw&amp;sig=oqfdC3Bjov9Hqm-nJ8aXZUx8HQ4&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=MwtzTJScBY_svQOvq8DtDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwCTgU#v=onepage&amp;q=stevenson%20edwards%20reincarnation&amp;f=false An introduction to parapsychology] McFarland, p. 218.&lt;/ref&gt; He concluded that &quot;reincarnation is the best — even though not the only — explanation for the stronger cases we have investigated&quot;.&lt;ref name=three&gt;[[Jim B. Tucker]] (2005). ''[[Life Before Life]]: A scientific Investigation of Children's Memories of Previous Lives'', St. Martin's Press, New York, p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt; Jim Tucker recognizes that this may seem to be an &quot;astounding statement&quot; —- that &quot;memories, emotions and physical injuries can sometimes carry over from one life to the next&quot;.&lt;ref name=three/&gt; However, he argues that this is no more astounding than many currently accepted ideas in physics seemed to be when they were originally proposed.&lt;ref name=three/&gt;

Research on reincarnation has received a mixed response. His methodology was criticized for providing no conclusive evidence for the existence of past lives.&lt;ref name=Edelmann&gt;{{cite journal| title = Setting Criteria for Ideal Reincarnation Research | url = http://www.imprint.co.uk/pdf/Edelman.pdf | year = 2007 | journal = Journal of Consciousness Studies | page = 92 | volume = 14 | issue = 12 | last1 = Edelmann | first1 = J. | last2 = Bernet | first2 = W.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a book review criticizing one of Stevensons' books, the reviewer raised the concern that many of Stevenson's examples were gathered in cultures with pre-existing belief in reincarnation.&lt;ref name=rock&gt;{{cite web | last = Rockley | first = R | url = http://skepticreport.com/sr/?p=482 | title = Book Review: Children who remember previous lives, A question of reincarnation, Ian Stevenson | date = 2002-11-01 | accessdate = 2010-03-01 | publisher = Skeptic Report }}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to address this type of concern, Stevenson wrote ''[[European Cases of the Reincarnation Type]]'' (2003) which presented 40 cases he examined in Europe.&lt;ref name=kf&gt;K. Farcnik. European Cases of the Reincarnation Type, ''[[Journal of Psychosomatic Research]]'', Volume 57, Issue 5, November 2004, 505-506.&lt;/ref&gt; Stevenson's obituary in the ''[[New York Times]]'' stated: &quot;Spurned by most academic scientists, Dr. Stevenson was to his supporters a misunderstood genius, bravely pushing the boundaries of science. To his detractors, he was earnest, dogged but ultimately misguided, led astray by gullibility, wishful thinking and a tendency to see science where others saw superstition&quot;.&lt;ref name=NYT&gt;{{cite news |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DD153EF93BA25751C0A9619C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all |title=Ian Pretyman Stevenson, 88; Studied Claims of Past Lives |publisher=New York Times |author=Margalit Fox |date=February 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, the ''[[British Medical Journal|BMJ]]'' said that Stevenson was a &quot;psychiatrist who researched reincarnation with scientific rigour&quot;.&lt;ref name=BMJ&gt;Janice Hopkins Tanne. [http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/extract/334/7595/700 Obituaries: Ian Pretyman Stevenson], ''British Medical Journal''. April 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Deducing from this research the conclusion that reincarnation is a proven fact has been listed as an example of [[pseudoscience]] by [[scientific skepticism|skeptics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kurtz P. |title=Two Sources of Unreason in Democratic Society: The paranormal and religion |journal= [[Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences]] |volume=775 |issue=1 Phagocytes |pages=493–504 |year=2006 |doi=10.1111/j.1749-6632.1996.tb23166.x |url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119242621/abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carl Sagan#Personal life and beliefs|Carl Sagan]] and [[Arthur C. Clarke#Views on paranormal phenomena|Arthur C. Clarke]] felt that reincarnation research work fell short of providing proof of reincarnation (which they both viewed as unlikely). Nevertheless, they felt that further research was warranted. In ''[[The Demon-Haunted World]]'' (1996), Sagan wrote that claims about reincarnation may have some experimental support, however dubious and inconclusive. He said &quot;at the time of writing, there are three claims in the ESP field that deserve serious study&quot;, the third being &quot;young children sometimes report details of a previous life, which upon checking turn out to be accurate and which they could not have known about in any other way than reincarnation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/02/10/AR2007021001393.html | work=The Washington Post | first=Tom | last=Shroder | title=Ian Stevenson; Sought To Document Memories Of Past Lives in Children | date=2007-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sagan, Carl. ''The Demon-Haunted World'', Random House, 1997, p. 302; also see Butziger, R. (2006). &quot;A Scientific Look at Reincarnation&quot;, ''PsycCRITIQUES'', 51(22), May 31, 2006, p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt; Sagan further stated he picked the three examples not because he thought them valid, but as examples of contentions that might be true.&lt;ref&gt;Quoting directly from ''The Demon-Haunted World'', Random House, 1997, p. 302 | | &quot;I pick these claims not because I think they're likely to be valid (I don't), but as examples of contentions that might be true. The last three have at least some, although still dubious, experimental support. Of course, I could be wrong.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Clarke observed that Stevenson had produced a number of studies that were &quot;hard to explain&quot; conventionally, then noted that accepting reincarnation raised the question of the means for personality transfer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Council for Secular Humanism |url=http://www.secularhumanism.org/library/fi/clarke_19_2.html |title=A Chat With Arthur C. Clarke |publisher=Secularhumanism.org |date=2004-02-13 |accessdate=2010-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  To date no physical process by which a personality could survive death and travel to another body has been identified,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Beyerstein | first = B | url = http://www.csicop.org/si/show/a_cogent_consideration_of_the_case_for_karma_and_reincarnation/ | title = A Cogent Consideration of the Case for Karma (and Reincarnation) | accessdate = 2010-03-01 | year = 1999 | volume = 23 | issue = 1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which researchers such as Stevenson and Tucker recognize as a limitation.&lt;ref name=&quot;document&quot;&gt;Shroder, Tom. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/02/10/AR2007021001393.html?nav=hcmodule Ian Stevenson; Sought To Document Memories Of Past Lives in Children] ''The Washington Post'', 11 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Skeptic [[Sam Harris (author)|Sam Harris]] said of Stevenson &quot;either he is a victim of truly elaborate fraud, or something interesting is going on.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=AlterNet / By John Gorenfeld |url=http://www.alternet.org/story/46196/ |title=Sam Harris's Faith in Eastern Spirituality and Muslim Torture |publisher=AlterNet |date=2007-01-05 |accessdate=2010-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Carl Wickland]]
*[[List of parapsychology topics]]
*[[Near-death experience]]
*[[Society for Psychical Research]]
*[[Spiritism]]
*[[Xenoglossy]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*Chakri, C.T.K (1978), “Reincarnation research: Method and Interpretation”, in ''Signet Handbook of parapsychology'', edited by Martin Ebon, New York: New American Library, 313-324.
*[[Paul Edwards (philosopher)|Edwards, Paul]]. (2001). ''Reincarnation: A Critical Examination'', ISBN 1-57392-921-2
*[[Erlendur Haraldsson|Haraldsson, Erlendur]], [[Godwin Samararatne]]: Children who speak of memories of a previous life as a Buddhist monk. Three new cases. In: ''[[Journal of the Society for Psychical Research]].'' 63 (1999), S. 268-291. {{ISSN|0037-1475}}; [http://www.hi.is/~erlendur/english/cort/monks.pdf PDF (1,8 MB)]
*Erlendur Haraldsson (2003). Children who speak of past-life experiences: Is there a psychological explanation? ''Psychology and Psychotherapy: Theory Research and Practice''. 76, 1, 55-67.
*Erlendur Haraldsson, Patrick Fowler &amp; Vimala Periyannanpillai (2000). Psychological Characteristics of Children Who Speak of a Previous Life: A Further Field Study in ''Sri Lanka Transcultural Psychiatry'', 37, 525-544.
*Erlendur Haraldsson (1995). Personality and abilities of children claiming previous-life memories. ''Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease'' 183(7), 445-451. 
*Erlendur Haraldsson (1995). Reinkarnation. In G. L. Eberlein (Ed.) ''Kleine Lexikon der Parawissenschaften''. München: C. H. Beckschen Verlagsbuchhandlung, 157-164. 
*Keil H.H.J., and Tucker J.B. (2000). &quot;An unusual birthmark case thought to be linked to a person who had previously died', ''Psychological Reports'', 87:1067-1074.
* Mills, Antonia, and Richard Slobodin (Eds.), ''Amerindian Rebrith: Reincarnation belief among North American Indians and Inuit''. Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1994.
* Mills, A., Haraldsson, E., and Keil, H. H. J. (1994). Replication studies of cases suggestive of reincarnation by three independent investigators. ''Journal of the American Society for Psychical Research'', ''88'', 207-219. [https://notendur.hi.is/erlendur/english/cort/Replication_Studies_of_Cases.pdf Reprint].
*Mills, Antonia, and Lynn, Steven Jay (2000). Past-life experiences. In [[Etzel Cardeña|Cardeña, Etzel]]; Lynn, Steven Jay; and [[Stanley Krippner|Krippner, Stanley]] (Eds). ''[[Varieties of Anomalous Experience]]: Examining the scientific evidence'', (pp. 283-313). Washington, DC, US: American Psychological Association, 2000.
*Pasricha, S.K., Keil, J., Tucker, J.B. and I. Stevenson, (2005). &quot;Some Bodily Malformations Attributed to Previous Lives&quot;, ''[[Journal of Scientific Exploration]]'', 19(3):359-383.
*Satwant Pasricha (2008). ''Can the Mind Survive Beyond Death?: Reincarnation Research'', 184 pages.
*Ramster, Peter. (1990). ''In Search of Lives Past'', ISBN 0-646-00021-7
*Rivas, Titus. (2003). [http://www.scientificexploration.org/journal/jse_17_3_rivas.pdf &quot;Three Cases of the Reincarnation Type in the Netherlands&quot;,] ''Journal of Scientific Exploration,'' 17(3): 527-532.
*Roach, Mary. (2005). ''Spook: Science Tackles the Afterlife.'' ISBN 0-393-05962-6
*Stevenson, Ian (1974). ''Twenty Cases Suggestive of Reincarnation,'' second (revised and enlarged) edition, University of Virginia Press, ISBN 978-0-8139-0872-4
*Stevenson, Ian. (1993).[http://www.childpastlives.org/library_articles/birthmark.htm &quot;Birthmarks and Birth Defects Corresponding to Wounds on Deceased Persons&quot;,] ''Journal of Scientific Exploration'', 7:403-410.
*Stevenson, Ian. (1997). ''Reincarnation and Biology: A Contribution to the Etiology of Birthmarks and Birth Defects'' ISBN 0-275-95283-5
*Stevenson, Ian. (1997). ''Where Reincarnation and Biology Intersect''. Praeger Publishers, ISBN 0-275-95282-7 . (A short and non-technical version of the scientific two-volumes work above, for the general reader)
*Stevenson, Ian. (2000). ''Children Who Remember Previous Lives: A Question of Reincarnation, revised edition'' (This is a text aimed mainly at an undergraduate audience.) ISBN 0-7864-0913-4
*Stevenson, Ian, Godwin Samararatne: Three new cases of the reincarnation type in Sri Lanka with written records made before verification. In: ''[[Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease]].'' 176 (1988), S. 741. {{ISSN|0022-3018}}
*Stevenson, Ian, Godwin Samararatne. Three new cases of the reincarnation type in Sri Lanka with written records made before verification. In: ''Journal of Scientific Exploration.'' 2 (1988), S. 217-238. {{ISSN|0892-3310}} ([http://www.scientificexploration.org/jse/abstracts/v2n2a6.php Abstract]{{dead link|date=September 2012}}, [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://br.geocities.com/existem_espiritos/reencarnacao_1988.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+01:41:44  Portuguese translation])
*Stevenson, Ian, Satwant Pasricha, Godwin Samararatne: Deception and self-deception in cases of the reincarnation type. Seven illustrative cases in Asia. In: ''Journal of the American Society for Psychical Research.'' 82 (1988), S. 1-31. {{ISSN|0003-1070}}
*Tucker, Jim B. (2005). ''Life Before Life: A Scientific Investigation of Children's Memories of Previous Lives'', ISBN 0-312-32137-6
*Tucker J.B. (2000). &quot;A scale to measure the strength of children's claims of previous lives: methodology and initial findings&quot;, ''[[Journal of Scientific Exploration]]'', 14(4):571-581.
*Van Lommel, Pim. (2001). &quot;Near-death experience in survivors of cardiac arrest: a prospective study in the Netherlands&quot;, ''The Lancet,'' 358: 2039-45.
*Williams-Cook, Emily, Bruce Greyson, and Ian Stevenson. (1998). [http://sedna.no.sapo.pt/death_scresearch/pdf_docs/12.3_cook_greyson_stevenson.pdf &quot;Do Any Near-Death Experiences Provide Evidence for the Survival of Human Personality after Death? Relevant Features and Illustrative Case Reports&quot;] ''Journal of Scientific Exploration,'' 12(3): 377-406.
* Williams Cook, Emily, [[Pasricha Satwant|Satwant Pasricha]], Godwin Samararatne, U Win Maung, Ian Stevenson: Review and analysis of &quot;unsolved&quot; cases of the reincarnation type. I. Introduction and illustrative case reports. In: ''Journal of the American Society for Psychical Research.'' 77 (1983), S. 45-62. {{ISSN|0003-1070}}
* Williams Cook, Emily, Satwant Pasricha, Godwin Samararatne, U Win Maung, Ian Stevenson: Review and analysis of &quot;unsolved&quot; cases of the reincarnation type. II. Comparison of features of solved and unsolved cases. In: ''Journal of the American Society for Psychical Research.'' 77 (1983), S. 115-135. {{ISSN|0003-1070}}

==External links==
*[http://www.healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/personalitystudies/ Division of Perceptual Studies, University of Virginia School of Medicine]
* [http://csicop.org/ Committee for Skeptical Inquiry] Organization formed in 1976 to promote [[scientific skepticism]] and encourage the critical investigation of paranormal claims and parapsychology.
* [http://www.parapsych.org/index.html Parapsychological Association] An organization of scientists and scholars engaged in the study of psychic phenomena, affiliated with the [[American Association for the Advancement of Science]] in 1969.

{{Reincarnation research}}
{{Death}}
{{Parapsychology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reincarnation research}}
[[Category:Reincarnation research| ]]
[[Category:Afterlife]]
[[Category:Parapsychology]]
[[Category:Pseudoscience]]

[[de:Reinkarnationsforschung]]
[[ru:Исследования реинкарнаций]]
[[simple:Reincarnation research]]</text>
      <sha1>4vu43kabtto3pasbeg3sz5h8jehtatn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
