<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Religion and sexuality</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43243</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514338448</id>
      <parentid>512787697</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-24T15:50:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>94.113.164.22</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>interwiki</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58715">{{Other uses}}
{{Cleanup-rewrite|date=March 2011}}{{Refimprove|date=June 2009}}
Most world '''religions''' have sought to address the moral issues that arise from people's '''sexuality''' in society and in human interactions. Each major religion has developed [[moral code]]s covering issues of [[human sexuality|sexuality]], [[morality]], [[ethics]] etc. These moral codes seek to regulate the situations which can give rise to sexual interest and to influence people's [[human sexual activities|sexual activities]] and practices.

Sexual morality has varied greatly over time and between cultures. A society's [[sexual norm]]s—standards of sexual conduct—can be linked to [[religion|religious]] beliefs, or social and environmental conditions, or all of these. Sexuality and reproduction are fundamental elements in human interaction and society worldwide. Furthermore, &quot;sexual restrictions&quot; is one of the universals of culture peculiar to all human societies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://everything2.com/index.pl?node_id=1744457 accessed September 16, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, most religions have seen a need to address the question of a &quot;proper&quot; role for sexuality in human interactions. Different religions have different codes of sexual morality, which regulate [[Human sexual activity|sexual activity]] or assign normative values to certain sexually charged actions or thoughts.

==Overview==
The views of religions and religious believers range widely, from giving sex and sexuality a rather negative connotation, to the belief that sex is the highest expression of the divine. Views on sexuality may not even be shared among adherents of a particular sector. Some religions distinguish between sexual activities that are practiced for biological reproduction (sometimes allowed only when in formal marital status and at a [[age of consent|certain age]]), and other activities practiced for sexual pleasure, as [[morality|immoral]].

==Hebrew bible/Old Testament==

While there was no prohibition against premarital sex,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Coogan|first=Michael|title=God and Sex. What the Bible Really Says|url=http://books.google.nl/books?id=2_gPKQEACAAJ&amp;dq=god+and+sex&amp;hl=nl&amp;ei=4fbCTaPKDpGXOrq88Z0I&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwAQ|page=103|edition=1st|year=2010|month=October|publisher=Twelve. Hachette Book Group|location=New York, Boston|isbn=978-0-446-54525-9|oclc=505927356|quote=Because it was addressed to men, it does not explicitly prohibit women from having sex with married men, or, for that matter, prohibit married men from having sex with unmarried women, including prostitutes.}}&lt;/ref&gt; children resulting from such liaisons were considered fatherless (&quot;orphans&quot;) and therefore could not inherit property.&lt;ref name=coogan&gt;[http://www.summitstonehill.com/se/the-summit/opinion/5-questions-with-professor-michael-d-coogan-1.1716380 5 Questions with Professor Michael D. Coogan] The Summit, October 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The following summarises laws and penalties from the three major codes:

===Deuteronomistic code===
''([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy%2022&amp;version=NIV Deuteronomistic code, Deuteronomy 12-26])''

* Conquest: Regulations on taking wives from women captured during war ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|21:10-14|KJV|}})
* Bigamy: Birth-rights of the sons of multiple wives to be respected ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|21:15–17|KJV}})
* Transvestism: Banned for both men and women, no penalty mentioned ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|22:5|KJV}})
* Pre-marital sex: A girl accused of not being a virgin at the time of marriage is to be stoned to death; however, if the accusation is false, the man who brings the accusation is to be punished with a fine ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|22:13–21|KJV}})
* Adultery (defined as a man sleeping with another man's wife): Death penalty for both partners ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|22:22|KJV}})
* Sex with a betrothed virgin inside a town: Death by stoning for the man, and for the woman as well if she consented ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|22:23–24|KJV}})
* Sex with a betrothed virgin in the countryside (consensual sex or rape): Death penalty for the man, no penalty for the girl ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|25:27|KJV}})
* Sex with a virgin who is not yet betrothed: The man must pay a fine to the father of the girl and marry her. He may never divorce her, but she is not forbidden from divorcing him ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|22:28–29|KJV}})
* Marriage: Men are forbidden from marrying their father's wife ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|22:30|KJV}})
* Wet dreams: A man who has a wet dream while on military service is defiled, and is to observe appropriate ritual to restore his purity ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|23:9–11|KJV}})
* Prohibition on remarriage after divorce: A man may not remarry a wife he has previously divorced if she remarries someone else then becomes single again ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|24:1–4|KJV}})
* Compulsory remarriage of a dead brother's widow: A man must marry his dead brother's widow if the brother has no son; a penalty of social disgrace is imposed on a man who refuses his obligation ({{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|25:5–10|KJV}})

===Covenant code===
''([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Exodus+22&amp;version=NIV Covenant code, Exodus 21–23])''

*Sale and purchase of girls: A man who has purchased another man's daughter to be his concubine or to marry his son, must respect her rights (Exodus 21:7–11)
*Pre-marital sex: A man who has sex with an unbetrothed virgin must pay bride-price and marry the girl (Exodus 22:16–17)
*Bestiality: Death penalty (Exodus 22:19)

===Holiness code===
''([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Leviticus%2017&amp;version=NIV Holiness code, Leviticus 17–26])''
* Incest: Men are forbidden to have sex with relatives, including their mother, father's wife, sister, daughter of father's wife if born to the father, father's sister, mother's sister, father's brother's wife, son's wife, or brother's wife (Leviticus 18:6–16)
* Relatives of a woman: A man is forbidden to have sex with the daughter of a woman he has had sex with, or with her son's daughter or daughter's daughter (Leviticus 18:17)
* Wife's sister: A man is forbidden to take his wife's sister as a second wife while she is still living (Leviticus 18:18)
* Menstruating women: Forbidden (Leviticus 18)
* Neighbor's wife: Forbidden (Leviticus 20)
* Male homosexuality: Sex with a man &quot;as with a woman&quot; forbidden, punishable by death for both participating men (Leviticus 18:22 and Leviticus 20:13)
* Bestiality: Forbidden for both men and women (Leviticus 18:23)

==Modern practice==
Judaism and most Christian religions teach [[chastity]] whether married or not. They also teach heterosexual [[monogamy]]. [[List of Christian denominational positions on homosexuality|Churches representing a minority]] of Christians permit monogamy with homosexuals.&lt;ref name=brunne/&gt;

===Judaism===
{{Main|Prohibition of extracting semen in vain (Judaism)|Tzniut|Niddah|Yichud|Negiah|Jewish views of homosexuality|Adultery#Rabbinic Judaism|Judaism and sexuality}}

In the perspective of traditional [[Judaism]], sex and reproduction are the holiest of acts one can do, the act through which one can imitate God, &quot;The Creator&quot;, and in order to preserve its sanctity there are many boundaries and guidelines. Within the boundaries, there are virtually no outright strictures, and it is in fact obligatory. It prohibits sexual relations outside of heterosexual marriage, maintains biblical strictures on relations within marriage including observance of [[Niddah]], a prohibition on relations for a period including the menstrual period, and [[Tzniut]], requirements of modest dress and behavior. Traditional Judaism views adultery, incest, and male/female homosexual acts as grave sins. See [[Jewish views of homosexuality]]. Judaism permits relatively free divorce, with [[Orthodox Judaism]] and [[Conservative Judaism]] requiring a [[get (divorce document)|religious divorce]] ceremony for a divorce to be religiously recognized. More modern branches of Judaism have adapted perspectives more consistent with contemporary general secular culture.

====Orthodox====
{{Main|Tzniut}}

There are several levels to the observance of physical and personal modesty (''tzniut'') according to [[Orthodox Judaism]] as derived from various sources in ''[[halakha]]''. Observance of these rules varies from aspirational to mandatory to routine across the spectrum of Orthodox stricture and observance.

* A prohibition on dwelling on lascivious or immoral thoughts.
* A prohibition on staring at members of the opposite sex, particularly at the reproductive anatomy.
* A requirement to keep most of one's body clothed in respectable clothing.
* A requirement to avoid the company of uncouth individuals and avoid frequenting places where an atmosphere of levity and depravity prevails.
* A prohibition on looking at pictures or scenes that will be sexually arousing.
* A prohibition on touching a person of the opposite sex, especially in a lingering arousing manner. See [[Negiah]].
* A prohibition on wearing the clothing of a member of the opposite sex.
* A prohibition on looking at animals copulating.
* A prohibition on erotically [[hug]]ging (''chibuk'') or [[kiss]]ing (''nishuk'') one's spouse in public,
* A prohibition on sexual contact or touching between spouses when the wife is a ''[[niddah]]'' (&quot;menstruant&quot;) or has not immersed in a [[mikvah]] following the niddah period.
* A prohibition on seclusion with a person of the opposite sex who is not a spouse or close relative (''[[Yichud]]'')
* A requirement that men and women be separated during prayer, dancing, and on certain other occasions ([[Mechitza]])
* A prohibition on ''hotza'at zera levatala''—&quot;secreting semen in vain&quot; by men. There is no equivalent prohibition for women since there is no secretion. However, masturbation by women is considered to be a lewd act and is thus included in the general commandment &quot;And you shall be holy&quot;.
* A prohibition on sex between men, or with any type of animal, or with a corpse.

Orthodox Judaism also maintains a strong prohibition on interfaith sexual relations and marriage.

Orthodox Jews tend to have a lower intermarriage rate than their Conservative and Reform counterparts. The 1990 [[National Jewish Population Survey]] indicated that of all the Jewish denominations, Orthodox Jews alone had a lower intermarriage rate in the 18-39 age category (3%) vs. the 40+ category (10%), compared with 37% vs. 10% for Conservative Jews, 53% vs. 10% for Reform Jews, and 72% vs. 39% for secular Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | title =Frequently Asked Questions on Intermarriage | work = | publisher =Joint Commission on Response to Intermarriage | date =   | url =http://www.uscj.org/intmar/ | accessdate = 2006-02-03 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20051211100314/http://www.uscj.org/intmar/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2005-12-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs]] report showed that Orthodox Judaism had doubled among synagogue-affiliated Jews in the United States, from 10% in 1990 to 21.8% in 2001, and that most of this growth was in the stricter [[Haredi Judaism]] as opposed to [[Modern Orthodox Judaism]]. It speculated that this trend may have been related to a general trend towards greater religious and social traditionalism, as well as due to earlier marriage and higher birth rates in Orthodox families consistent with more traditional sexual behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Waxman | first =Chaim I | title =Winners and Losers in Denominational Memberships in the United States | publisher =Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs | date = | url =http://www.jcpa.org/cjc/cjc-waxman-f05.htm | accessdate = 2007-02-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Orthodox Judaism, alone of all the Jewish denominations, retains relatively mild traditional disabilities on divorce, including a Biblical prohibition on a [[Kohen]] (priestly descendant of [[Aaron]]) marrying a divorcee or a woman who has engaged in certain types of sexual misconduct. These strictures, while observed, are generally regarded as matters of personal status rather than morality. An Orthodox [[get (divorce document)|bill of divorce]] is required for a divorce to be recognized.

====Conservative====

[[Conservative Judaism]], consistent with its general view that [[Halakha]] (Jewish law) is a binding guide to Jewish life but subject to periodic revision by the Rabbinate, has lifted a number of strictures observed by [[Orthodox Judaism]]. In particular, in December 2006, Conservative Judaism's [[Committee on Jewish Law and Standards]] adopted [[responsum|responsa]] presenting diametrically opposed views on the issue of homosexuality. It adopted an opinion restricting a prior prohibition on homosexual conduct to male-male anal sex only, which it declared to be the only Biblical prohibition, declaring all other prohibitions (e.g. male-male oral sex or lesbian sex) rabbinic, and lifting all rabbinic restrictions based on its interpretation of the Talmudic principle of [[Kevod HaBriyot]] (&quot;human dignity&quot;). While declining to develop a form of religious gay marriage, it permitted blessing lesbian and gay unions and ordaining openly lesbian and gay rabbis who agree not to engage in male-male anal sex.&lt;ref name = &quot;rabbinevins-gayjews&quot;&gt;[http://www.rabbinevins.org/HHH%20Dorff%20Nevins%20Reisner%20Final2.pdf Elliott N. Dorff, Daniel Evans, and Avram Reisner. ''Homosexuality, Human Dignity, and Halakha.'' Committee on Jewish Law and Standards, Rabbinical Assembly, December 6, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; It is also a traditionalist opinion, upholding all traditional prohibitions on homosexual activity, also adopted as a majority opinion,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rabbinicalassembly.org/docs/Roth_Final.pdf Rabbi Joel Roth, Homosexuality Revisited, Committee on Jewish Law and Standards, Rabbinical Assembly, December 6, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The approach permits individual rabbis, congregations, and rabbinical schools to set their own policy on homosexual conduct. It reflects a profound change from a prior blanket prohibition on male homosexual practices. It acknowledges a sharp divergence of views on sexual matters within Conservative Judaism, such that there is no single Conservative Jewish approach to matters of sexuality. Conservative Judaism currently straddles the divide between liberal and traditional opinion on sexual matters within contemporary American society, permitting both views.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forward.com/articles/conservative-panel-votes-to-permit-gay-rabbis/ Conservative Panel Votes To Permit Gay Rabbis ''Jewish Daily Forward'', December 7, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;

Conservative Judaism has maintained on its books a variety requirements and prohibitions, including a requirement that married women observe the laws of [[Niddah]] (refraining from sex during and shortly after their [[menstrual period]] and immersing in a [[Mikvah]] prior to resuming relations) and a general prohibition on non-marital heterosexual conduct. On the same day as the [[Committee on Jewish Law and Standards|CJLS]] released its homosexuality responsa, it released multiple opinions on the subject of Niddah including a responsum lifting certain traditional restrictions on husband-wife contact during the niddah period while maintaining a prohibition on sexual relations. The permissive responsum on homosexuality used the Conservative movement's approach to Niddah as an analogy for construing the Biblical prohibition against male homosexual conduct narrowly and lifting restrictions it deemed Rabbinic in nature. The responsum indicated it would be making a practical analogy between an approach in which male homosexual couples would be on their honor to refrain from certain acts and its approach to Niddah:

:We expect homosexual students to observe the rulings of this responsum in the same way that we expect heterosexual students to observe the [[Committee on Jewish Law and Standards|CJLS]] rulings on niddah. We also expect that interview committees, administrators, faculty and fellow students will respect the privacy and dignity of gay and lesbian students in the same way that they respect the privacy and dignity of heterosexual students.

The responsum enjoined young people not to be &quot;promiscuous&quot; and to prepare themselves for &quot;traditional marriage&quot; if possible, while not explicitly lifting or re-enforcing any express strictures on non-marital heterosexual conduct.&lt;ref name = &quot;rabbinevins-gayjews&quot;/&gt;

Even before this responsum, strictures on pre-marital sex had been substantially ignored, even in official circles. For example, when the [[Jewish Theological Seminary of America]] proposed enforcing a policy against non-marital cohabitation by rabbinical students in the 1990s, protests by cohabiting rabbinical students resulted in a complete rescission of the policy.

Conservative Judaism formally prohibits [[interfaith]] marriage and its standards currently indicate it will expel a Rabbi who performs an interfaith marriage. It maintains a variety of formal strictures including a prohibition on making birth announcements in synagogue bulletins for children on non-Jewish mothers and accepting non-Jewish individuals as synagogue members. However, interfaith marriage is relatively widespread among the Conservative laity, and the Conservative movement has recently adapted a policy of being more welcoming of interfaith couples in the hopes of interesting their children in Judaism.

Conservative Judaism, which was for much of the 20th century the largest Jewish denomination in the United States declined sharply in synagogue membership in the United States the 1990s, from 51% of synagogue memberships in 1990 to 33.1% in 2001, with most of the loss going to Orthodox Judaism and most of the rest to Reform. The fracturing in American society of opinion between increasingly liberal and increasingly traditionalist viewpoints on sexual and other issues, as well as the gap between official opinion and general lay practice vis-a-vis the more traditionalist and liberal denominations, may have contributed to the decline.&lt;ref name = &quot;icpa-waxman&quot;&gt;[http://www.jcpa.org/cjc/cjc-waxman-f05.htm Chaim Waxman, Winners and Losers in Denominational Memberships in the United States. Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Reform, Reconstructionist and Humanistic====

[[Reform Judaism]], [[Humanistic Judaism]] and [[Reconstructionist Judaism]] do not observe or require traditional sexuality rules and have welcomed non married and homosexual couples and endorsed homosexual commitment ceremonies and marriages.

Reform and Reconstructionist Judaism are more tolerant of interfaith marriage, and many rabbis in both communities will perform one. Humanistic Judaism permits interfaith marriage. Reform, Reconstructionist and Humanistic Judaism also do not require a religious divorce ceremony separate from a civil divorce.

It has been speculated that the more tolerant attitudes of Reform, Reconstructionist and Humanistic Judaism towards both sexual diversity and interfaith marriage may have contributed to the rise in their popularity during the 1990s, from about 33% of affiliated households to 38%, making it pass Conservative Judaism as the largest Jewish denomination in the United States.&lt;ref name = &quot;icpa-waxman&quot;/&gt;

===Christianity===
{{See also|Biblical law in Christianity|Homosexuality and Christianity}}

==== Historical background ====
In early and ascetic Christianity, with expectation of an imminent [[Armageddon]], sex (procreation of children) was not highly emphasized, and was considered by some &quot;evil&quot;, while celibacy and virginity were highly praised.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=lxczAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=jzIHAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6938,5650941&amp;dq=&amp;hl=en Sex Exploitation Is Big Business To Americans] Lodi News Sentinel, retrieved 12 June 2012&lt;/ref&gt; [[Paul of Tarsus]] wrote in [[First Epistle to the Corinthians|1 Corinthians]] that &quot;It is good for [the unmarried] to stay unmarried, but if they cannot control themselves, they should marry, for it is better to marry than to burn with passion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Corinthians%207 1 Corinthians 7:8-9]&lt;/ref&gt; Some have suggested that Paul's treatment of sex was influenced by his conviction that the [[Christian eschatology|end of the world]] was imminent.  Under this view, Paul, believing that the world would soon end, took it as a corollary that all earthly concerns,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Corinthians%207 1 Corinthians 7:29-31]&lt;/ref&gt; including sex, should hold little interest for Christians.&lt;ref&gt;Brundage (1987), pp.59-61&lt;/ref&gt; Paul's letters show far greater concern with sexual issues than the gospel writers attributed to Jesus, since Paul was building Christian communities over decades and responding to various issues that arose.

Paul did, however, support marriage, and sex within marriage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Corinthians%207 1 Corinthians 7:2]&lt;/ref&gt; He recognized that for married couples, sex is helpful in protecting them with respect to their temptations&lt;ref name=&quot;1 Corinthians 7:5&quot;&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Corinthians%207 1 Corinthians 7:5]&lt;/ref&gt; and he recommends ongoing sexual relations between spouses,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Corinthians%207 1 Corinthians 7:3]&lt;/ref&gt; even if their religious observances may prompt them to abstain for a time.&lt;ref name=&quot;1 Corinthians 7:5&quot;/&gt; Importantly, Paul’s view of sex is also that it is actually unnecessary for those with certain “gifts”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Corinthians%207 1 Corinthians 7:7]&lt;/ref&gt; (presumably [[Celibacy#Christianity|&quot;celibacy&quot;]]).

From the beginning of the thirteenth century, the Catholic Church formally recognized [[Fruit of the Holy Spirit|marriage between a freely consenting, baptized man and woman]] as a [[sacrament]]—an outward sign communicating a special gift of God's love. The [[Council of Florence]] in 1438 gave this definition, following earlier Church statements in 1208, and declared that sexual union was a special participation in the union of Christ in the Church.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09707a.htm&lt;/ref&gt; However the [[Puritans]], while highly valuing the institution, viewed marriage as a &quot;civil&quot;, rather than a &quot;religious&quot; matter, being &quot;under the jurisdiction of the civil courts&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feige, Diana 1995 P109&quot;&gt;Feige, Diana, and Franz G M. Feige. &quot;Love, Marriage, and Family in Puritan Society.&quot; Dialogue &amp; Alliance 9, no. 1 (March 1, 1995): 96-114. ATLA Religion Database with ATLASerials, EBSCOhost (accessed December 3, 2010). P109&lt;/ref&gt; This is because they found no biblical precedent for clergy performing marriage ceremonies. Further, marriage was said to be for the &quot;relief of [[concupiscence]]&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Feige, Diana 1995 P109&quot;/&gt; as well as any spiritual purpose.

During the [[Protestant Reformation]], [[Martin Luther]] and [[John Calvin]] denied the [[Sacrament of marriage|sacramentality of marriage]].

This unanimity was broken at the [[Lambeth Conferences#Seventh Conference (1930)|1930 Lambeth Conference]], the quadrennial meeting of the worldwide [[Anglican]] Communion—creating divisions in that denomination.

Sex before marriage was not a taboo in the Anglican Church until the &quot;Hardwicke Marriage Act of 1753, which for the first time stipulated that everyone in England and Wales had to be married in their parish church&quot; [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/2296151.stm]  Prior to that time, &quot;marriage began at the time of betrothal, when couples would live and sleep together... The process begun at the time of the Hardwicke Act continued throughout the 1800s, with stigma beginning to attach to illegitimacy&quot;  [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/2296151.stm].

After World War II, divergence in Protestant teaching on sexuality accelerated. Today, [[progressive Christianity|progressive Christians]] in a wide number of denominations advocate that the teachings against [[premarital sex]], [[Christian views on divorce|divorce]], and [[Christianity and homosexuality|homosexuality]] have been either misread throughout previous centuries or that they [[Abrogation of Old Covenant laws|applied to ancient, and not current, circumstances]]. [[Fundamentalist Christians]] tend to hold onto the idea that based on passages in the Bible that condemn men laying with men and [[porneia]] that homosexuality and premarital sex are sinful. However, some conservative Protestant Christians have downplayed the importance of Bible verses that condemn remarriage after divorce as [[adultery]].{{fact|cite is to biblical passage, not to statement about conservative protestants|date=May 2012}}({{bibleverse||Matthew|5:31-32|KJV|}})

&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew%205:31-32 Matthew 5:31-32]&lt;/ref&gt;

Scriptures in the [[New Testament]] dealing with sexuality are extensive. Subjects include: the [[Apostolic Decree]] ({{bibleverse||Acts|15}}), sexual immorality, divine love ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|13|KJV}}), mutual self-giving ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|7|KJV}}), bodily membership between Christ and between husband and wife ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|6:15-20|KJV}}) and honor versus dishonor of adultery.({{bibleverse||Hebrews|13:4|KJV}})
Even with the large number of Bible passages that address issues of sexuality, [[Biblical hermeneutics|interpretation]] of these verses can vary. The issue of premarital sex is good example of how the same verse can be viewed in different ways. In modern [[English language|English]], ''fornication'' typically refers to voluntary [[sexual intercourse]] between persons not married to each other. Given that modern definition, a verse that condemns fornication (such as {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|6:9|KJV}} which is often cited by various denominations as biblical opposition to pre-marital sex) would appear to be clear. However, in the New Testament, ''fornication'' is the word used to translate the [[Koine Greek]] word ''porneia'' into English. In Ancient Greek, the word ''porneia'' meant &quot;illicit sex&quot; or &quot;illegal sex&quot;. [[Early Christianity|Early Christians]] interpreted this word to encompass activities such as: [[adultery]], [[incest]], and [[bestiality]]. Modern [[evangelical Christians]] tend to prefer the definition of [[premarital sex]], or will even choose to broaden the term to also include activities such as [[homosexuality]], [[prostitution]], [[masturbation]] and [[pornography]], while [[Progressive Christianity|progressive Christians]] tend to limit the interpretation of the word to illegal sexual activities such as incest, bestiality, and [[pedophilia]].

====Protestantism and Anglicanism====

In most [[Lutheran]], [[Reformed]] and [[United Church of Christ|United]] churches of the [[Evangelical Church in Germany|EKD]] in Germany and in the Netherlands and Switzerland view homosexuality as a violation of the [[Ten_Commandments#Division_according_to_different_religions|7th commandment]]. In these Lutheran, United and Reformed churches ([[Martin Luther|Luther]]/[[John Calvin|Calvin]]) gay ministers are not permitted in ministry and gay couples are not allowed in their churches.

Inside the Lutheran [[Church of Sweden]], the Bishop of Stockholm, [[Eva Brunne]] is a [[lesbian]].&lt;ref name=brunne&gt;Rev. Mary Frances Schjonberg [http://www.episcopalchurch.org/81808_116555_ENG_HTM.htm SWEDEN: Lesbian priest ordained as Lutheran bishop of Stockholm] Episcopal News Service.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Anglican church there is a large discussion over the blessing of gay couples and over tolerance of homosexuality. In some dioceses, Anglican (Episcopal) churches in Canada and the USA permit openly gay priests in ministry and allow same-sex blessings, which has drawn much criticism from other parts of the Anglican Communion. Anglican churches in parts of Africa are extremely conservative in their attitude towards homosexuality. Gay priests in most Anglican churches must be celibate if they wish to continue their work as priests.

While the [[Unity Church]] at one point in its history offered prayers for the healing of homosexuality, the church has consistently ordained openly gay ministers, beginning with [[Ernest C. Wilson]], who was ordained as a minister by founder [[Charles Fillmore (Unity Church)|Charles Fillmore]], who sent him to a church in [[Hollywood, California]] on learning of his orientation.

Most evangelical churches, such as [[Southern Baptists]], for example, interpret the Bible to say that homosexuality is a sin. Although Leviticus calls for the killing of anyone who commits a homosexual act, evangelicals believe that this was part of the Mosaic law. They point out that in the new testament, {{bibleverse||Romans|1:27|KJV}}, while it is still a sin, sinners have a chance for forgiveness. The theme of Leviticus, death, is not echoed in this reading.

====Catholic====
{{Main|Catholicism and sexuality}}
{{See also|Theology of the Body}}

The Catholic Church affirms the sanctity of human life, from conception to natural death. The Church believes the human being has been created in the &quot;image and likeness of God&quot;, and that human life should not be weighed against other values such as economy, convenience, personal preferences, or social engineering. Therefore, the Church opposes activities that they believe harmful or devalue divinely created life, including [[euthanasia]], [[eugenics]], [[death penalty]] and [[abortion]].

The Church preaches that [[Manichaeism]] is a [[heresy]]. Therefore, the Church does not preach that sex is sinful or an impairment to a grace-filled life. &quot;And God saw every thing that he had made, and, behold, it was very good.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|1:31}}&lt;/ref&gt; then the human body and sex must likewise be good. The Catechism teaches that &quot;the flesh is the hinge of salvation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', [http://www.usccb.org/catechism/text/pt1sect2chpt3art11.htm#1015 1015]&lt;/ref&gt;

However the Church does refer to sexual intercourse outside of marriage is contrary to its purpose. The &quot;conjugal act&quot; aims at a deeply personal unity, a unity that, beyond union in one flesh, leads to forming one heart and soul&quot; (Catechism [http://www.usccb.org/catechism/text/pt3sect2chpt2art6.htm#1643 1643]) since the marriage bond is to be a sign of the love between God and humanity (Catechism [http://www.usccb.org/catechism/text/pt3sect2chpt2art6.htm#1617 1617]).

[[Pope John Paul II]]'s first major teaching was on the [[Theology of the Body]]. Over the course of five years he elucidated a vision of sex that was not only positive and affirming but was about redemption, not condemnation. He taught that by understanding God's plan for physical love we could understand &quot;the meaning of the whole of existence, the meaning of life.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=General Audience, 6 |url=http://www.ewtn.com/library/PAPALDOC/jp2tb45.htm |author=Pope John Paul II |date=29 October 1980 |publisher=L'Osservatore Romano |accessdate=2006-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; He taught that human beings were created by a loving God for a purpose: to be loving persons who freely choose to love, to give themselves as persons who express their self-giving through their bodies. Thus, sexual intercourse between husband and wife is a [[symbol]] of their total mutual self-donation.

For John Paul II, &quot;The body, and it alone, is capable of making visible what is invisible: the spiritual and divine.&quot; He says there is no other more perfect [[image]] of the unity and communion of God in mutual love than the sexual act of a married couple, whereby they give themselves in a total way—exclusively to one another, and up to end of their lives, and in a fruitfully generous way by participating in the [[Insemination|creation]] of new human beings. Through this perspective, he understands the immorality of extra marital sex. It falsifies the language of the human body, a language of total love worthy of persons by using the body for selfish ends, thus treating persons and things and objects, rather than dealing with embodied persons with the reverence and love that incarnate spirits deserve. John Paul II stresses that there is great [[beauty]] in sexual love when done in [[harmony]] with the human values of freely chosen total commitment and self-giving. For him, this sexual love is a form of [[worship]], an experience of the [[sacred]].&lt;ref&gt;Theology of Marriage and Celibacy, Boston, St. Paul Books and Media 1986&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.catholiceducation.org/articles/sexuality/se0055.htmlhttp://www.catholic.org/saints/saint.php?saint_id=5603 |author=Christopher West| work=Catholic Education Resource Center | title=John Paul II's Theology of the Body | accessdate=2009-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]'' indicates that sexual relationships in marriage as ''a way of imitating in the flesh the Creator's generosity and fecundity'' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p3s2c2a6.htm#2335&lt;/ref&gt; and lists [[fornication]] as one of the &quot;Offenses Against Chastity&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p3s2c2a6.htm#2352&lt;/ref&gt; and calls it &quot;an intrinsically and gravely disordered action&quot; because &quot;use of the sexual faculty, for whatever reason, outside of marriage is essentially contrary to its purpose.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Persona Humana:Declaration on Certain Questions Concerning Sexual Ethics, Section IX
  | work = Sacred Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith
  |date=December 29, 1975
  | url = http://www.newadvent.org/library/docs_df75se.htm
  | accessdate = 2006-08-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===
{{Main|Islamic sexual jurisprudence}}
{{See also|Homosexuality and Islam}}

Few modern Muslim countries have legal systems based fully on Islamic law (called ''shariah''), and an increasing number of Muslims do not look to shariah but to the Quran itself for moral guidance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jivraj&amp;de Jong, p.2&quot;&gt;Jivraj&amp;de Jong, p.2&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Islam]] encourages [[marriage]] as a form of religious practice, and considers it as the best form that regulates the sexual relationship of human beings.

[[Qur'an]]ic verses made it legal for Muslim men to marry women from other Abrahamic religions (i.e. Jews and Christians), provided that the women are faithful (adherent) to their own religious beliefs. Contemporary scholars have upheld this ruling.

A Muslim woman, on the other hand, is only allowed to marry a Muslim man, one of the reasons being, to marry a non-Muslim man would mean that the children would grow up as non-Muslims. A marriage contract between a Muslim woman and a non-Muslim man is traditionally considered illegal and void, and hence legally an [[adulterous]] affair. Another reason is to insure that the woman's legal rights are fully recognized in a marriage contract.

The Qur'an states the following conditions for men with regard to marriage:

&lt;!---I suspect that surahs need to have quotes don't they?---&gt;
4:22 And marry not women whom your fathers married save for what is past: it is shameful and odious—indeed an abominable custom.

4:23 Prohibited to you (For marriage) are: Your mothers, daughters, sisters; father's sisters, Mother's sisters; brother's daughters, sister's daughters; foster-mothers, foster-sisters; your wives' mothers; your stepdaughters under your guardianship, born of your wives to whom ye have gone in,- no prohibition if ye have not gone in; (Those who have been) wives of your sons proceeding from your loins; and two sisters in wedlock at one and the same time save for what is past; for God is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful.

4:24 Also (prohibited are) women already married. Thus hath God ordained (Prohibitions) against you: Except for these, all others are lawful, provided ye seek (them in marriage) with gifts from your property: desiring chastity, not lust, seeing that ye derive benefit from them, give them their dowers (at least) as prescribed; but if, after a dower is prescribed, agree mutually (to vary it), there is no blame on you. And God is All-Knowing, All-Wise.

4:25 If any of you have not the means wherewith to wed free believing women, they may wed believing girls from among those whom your right hands possess. And God hath full knowledge about your faith. Ye are one from another: wed them with the leave of their owners, and give them their dowers, according to what is reasonable. They should be chaste, not lustful, nor taking paramours: when they are taken in wedlock, if they fall into shame, their punishment is half that for free women. This (permission) is for those among you who fear sin; but it is better for you that ye practice self-restraint. And God is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful.

4:26 Allah doth wish to make clear to you and to show you the ordinances of those before you; and (He doth wish to) turn to you (In Mercy): And God is All-Knowing, All-Wise.{{cn|not clear this is a surah quote|date=May 2012}}

Most forms of sexual contact within a marriage are allowed. Sex is considered a pleasurable, even spiritual activity, and a duty. At least one [[hadith]] explicitly states that for a married couple to have sex is a good deed rewarded by God. Another hadith suggests that a man should not leave the proverbial bed until the woman is satisfied, a reference many say points to [[orgasm]].

[[Adultery]] warrants severe punishment. [[Pre-marital sex]] is also considered sinful, albeit less severe. All [[shari'a]] laws regulating sexual conduct apply to both men and women equally, apart from those concerning [[menstruation]].

Forbidden sexual contact includes genital contact with a woman while she is [[menstruating]]. In such case, other sexual contact (such as kissing and any sexual activity that does not include vaginal contact) is explicitly allowed. Temporary marriage (''[[Mut'a]]'', marriage designated for a preset period of time) is not allowed by the majority [[Sunni]] schools, but is allowed by [[Shia]] schools. Debate continues on its validity.

There are dissenting views on the topic of [[masturbation]]. While some scholars consider it unlawful and thus prohibited according to Islamic doctrine, others (such as those of the Hanbali doctrine) believe that those who masturbate out of fear of committing fornication or fear for their bodies have done nothing wrong and are not punished if (and only if) they are unable to marry. According to some [[hadith]]s however, men are encouraged to fast in order to avoid fornication and tempting oneself with sexual thoughts or conversations with opposite sex outside marriage is strongly discouraged.

The [[Quran]] clearly disapproves of [[sodomy]], but only one passage, sura 4:16, can be interpreted as taking a particular legal position towards such activities: &quot;As for the two of you who are guilty thereof, punish them both; and if they repent and improve, then let them be. Lo, Allah is relenting, merciful.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sura 4:16, quoted in Wafer, p.88&lt;/ref&gt; The [[hadith]] (reports of Muhammad's sayings and deeds from those close to him in his lifetime) are inconsistent, some reporting that &quot;inverts&quot; were common in the Prophet's own tribe and that he was much amused by their wit, while others recommend the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;Wafer, p.89&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic law, or ''[[shariah]]'', distinguishes between ''liwat'' (penetrative male-male sexual activity) and non-penetrative male same-sex activity, the second being considered only a minor sin requiring chastisement.&lt;ref&gt;Habib, p.287&lt;/ref&gt; Homosexual sodomy attracts the same penalties as adultery or fornication (flogging or death), although the exact punishment varies with schools and scholars.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jivraj&amp;de Jong, p.2&quot;/&gt;

The position regarding male/female anal intercourse is not clear-cut in Shia Islam. The majority of Shiite interpreters hold that (l) anal intercourse, while strongly disliked, is not ''haram'' (forbidden) provided the wife agrees, and (2), if the wife does not agree, then it is preferable to refrain: &quot;Woman is a means of your pleasure, therefore do not harm her.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.al-islam.org/m_morals/chap3b.htm Al-Islam.org]&lt;/ref&gt; Sunni Muslim disagree with that interpretation.

===Bahá'í faith===
In the [[Bahá'í Faith]], sexual relationships are permitted only between a husband and wife. [[Bahá'u'lláh]], the founder of the Bahá'í Faith in his book of laws, the [[Kitáb-i-Aqdas]], forbid extramarital sexual intercourse.&lt;ref name=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author = Universal House of Justice |year = 1992 |title = The Kitáb-i-Aqdas |publisher = Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location = Wilmette, Illinois, USA |isbn = 0-85398-999-0 |url = http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/b/KA/ka-53.html | page = 191}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kiq&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author = Bahá'u'lláh |authorlink = Bahá'u'lláh |origyear = 1873 |year = 1992 |title = The Kitáb-i-Aqdas |publisher = Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location = Wilmette, Illinois, USA |isbn = 0-85398-999-0 | page = 26 |url = http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/b/KA/ka-4.html#gr19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Baha'i understanding of sex is that [[chastity]] should be practised by both sexes before marriage because it is commendable ethically and that it leads to a happy and successful marital life. The Bahá'í Faith recognizes the value of the sex impulse, but that its proper use is within the institution of [[Bahá'í marriage|marriage]]; Baha'is do not believe in the suppression of the sex impulse but in its regulation and control.&lt;ref name=&quot;log&quot;&gt;Letter written on behalf of [[Shoghi Effendi]] September 5, 1938. Published in {{cite book |author = Compilations |editor = Hornby, Helen (Ed.) |year = 1983 |title = Lights of Guidance: A Bahá'í Reference File |publisher = Bahá'í Publishing Trust, New Delhi, India |isbn = 81-85091-46-3 |url = http://bahai-library.com/hornby_lights_guidance | page = 344}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Unitarian Universalism==

While Unitarianism and Universalism are terms used to express Christian theological ideas, since the 1950s it has changed to be less focused on Scripture and the traditions of Christianity and started to draw from a wider range of sources.

Unitarian Universalists have advocated for many decades for [[same-sex marriage]]. The Canadian Unitarian Council was given Intervenor status to argue in support of same-sex marriage in the debates before legalisation in [[Same-sex marriage in Canada|2005]].

The [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] and the [[United Church of Christ]] partnered to create [[Our Whole Lives]], a comprehensive sexuality curricula that has modules from Kindergarten/Grade 1 through adult. This program is an abstinence-based program that focuses on comprehensive [[sexual education]] (as opposed to the abstinence-only programs often taught in the United States).

Unitarian Universalism advocates freedom for people to choose which sexual acts are [[moral relativism|morally]] and personally permissible, and to express one's sexual orientation and gender openly.

The Reverend [[Debra Haffner]], a Unitarian Universalist minister, is co-founder and director of [[the Religious Institute on Sexual Morality, Justice, and Healing]], a multi-faith organization promoting sexual health, education and justice in faith communities.  The Institute has become a major progressive voice on sexuality issues, and Reverend Haffner completed an assessment of sexual health and responsibility within the UUA.

==Hinduism==
{{See also|Homosexuality and Hinduism}}

In [[Hinduism]], views of sexual morality differ widely depending on the tendence. [[Hindu scriptures]] themselves are often vague about sexuality. There are temples depicting sexual activity openly (examples include temple complexes at [[Ajanta]] and [[Ellora]], and at [[Khajuraho]], which has a group of medieval Hindu and Jain temples, with their erotic sculpture), and sexual imagery is not sacrilege, but sexual self-restraint (as well as in other aspects of life) are considered essential to a Hindu's well being and [[dharmic]]/[[karmic]] duties. Sexual variance was seen as a creative expression and was not expressly discouraged: it was also encouraged as part of a human soul's need to experience/comprehend the multifariousness that the world has to offer; but it is deemed, as with any other worldly act, impermanent and imperfect compared to the bliss of [[moksha]]. However, celibacy, sexual regulation and sexual abstinence was recommended for those who would like a quicker, less complicated and proven path to liberation. Note that any act of sex between consenting adults is not inherently sinful: being attached to sex might merely delay your 'liberation'; in that sense sex is as much an impedance as amassing wealth, anger, attachment to one's kin or any other worldly pursuits, including intellectual pursuits.

Religiously speaking, Hindus begin life at the [[Brahmacharya]] or &quot;student&quot; stage, in which they are directed to chastely advance themselves educationally and spiritually to prepare themselves for a life of furthering their [[dharma]] (societal, occupational, parental, etc. duties) and [[karma]] (right earthly actions); only once they reach the [[Grihastya]] or &quot;householder&quot; stage can they seek [[kama]] (physical pleasure) and [[artha]] (worldly achievement, material prosperity) through their vocations.

Among more traditional elements of Hindu society, such concepts as pre-marital sex are still [[anathema]].

The ''[[Kama Sutra]]'' (Discourse on Kāma) by Vatsayana, widely believed to be just a manual for sexual congress, offers an insight into sexual mores, ethics and societal rules that were prevalent at that time (ca. 5 CE). Shrungara Ras (Romance, one of the nine rasas or emotions). A drama in Sanskrit, [[Shakuntalam]] by Kalidasa, cited as one of the best examples of Shrungara Ras, talks of the love story of [[Dushyanta]] and [[Shakuntala]].

==Buddhism==

{{Main|Sexuality and Buddhism}}
{{See also|Homosexuality and Buddhism}}

Buddhism does not go into details regarding what is right and what is wrong within the [[wiktionary:mundane|mundane]] activities of life. Details of accepted or unaccepted human sexual conduct is not specifically mentioned in any of the religious scriptures. The most common formulation of Buddhist ethics are the [[The Five Precepts|Five Precepts]] and the [[Noble Eightfold Path|Eightfold Path]], which say that one should neither be attached to nor crave sensual pleasure. These precepts take the form of voluntary, personal undertakings, not divine mandate or instruction. The third of the Five Precepts is &quot;To refrain from committing sexual misconduct.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =Higgins
  | first =Winton
  | title =Buddhist Sexual Ethics
  | work =
  | publisher =BuddhaNet Magazine
  | date =
  | url =http://www.buddhanet.net/winton_s.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-01-15 }}
&lt;/ref&gt; However, the &quot;sexual misconduct&quot; is such a broad term, and is subjected to interpretation relative to the social norms of the followers. In fact, Buddhism in its fundamental form, does not define what is right and what is wrong in absolute terms for [[Laity|lay followers]]. Therefore the interpretation of what kinds of sexual activity is acceptable for a [[layperson]], is not a religious matter as far as Buddhism is concerned.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

[[Sangha|Buddhist monks and nuns]] of most traditions are expected to refrain from all sexual activity and the [[Sakyamuni Buddha|Buddha]] is said to have admonished his followers to avoid unchastity &quot;as if it were a pit of burning cinders.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Saddhatissa | first =Hammalawa | authorlink = | coauthors = | title =Buddhist Ethics: The Path to Nirvana | publisher =Wisdom Pubns; New Ed edition |date=December 1987 | location = | page =88 | url =
  | doi = | isbn = 0-86171-053-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Neopaganism==
Most [[Neopaganism|Neopagan]] religions have the theme of fertility (both physical and creative/spiritual) as central to their practices, and as such encourage what they view as a healthy sex life, consensual sex between adults, regardless of gender or age.

[[Wicca]], like other religions, has adherents with a broad spectrum of views ranging from conservative to liberal. It is a largely nondogmatic religion and has no prohibitions against sexual intercourse outside of marriage or relationships between members of the same sex. The religion's ethics are largely summed up by the [[Wiccan Rede]]: &quot;An it harm none, do as thou wilt&quot;, which is interpreted by many as allowing and endorsing responsible sexual relationships of all varieties.  Specifically in the Wiccan tradition of modern witchcraft, one of the widely accepted pieces of [[Craft]] liturgy, the Charge of the Goddess instructs that &quot;...all acts of love and pleasure are [the Goddess'] rituals&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Alternative Sexuality | publisher =Tangled Moon Coven |date=2006-08-08 | url =http://www.tangledmoon.org/sexuality.htm | accessdate = 2006-12-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; giving validity to all forms of sexual activity for Wiccan practitioners.

In the Gardnerian and Alexandrian forms of Wicca, the &quot;[[Great Rite]]&quot; is a sex ritual much like the [[hieros gamos]], performed by a priest and priestess who are believed to embody the Wiccan God and Goddess. The Great Rite is almost always performed figuratively using the athame and chalice as symbols of the penis and vagina. The literal form of the ritual is always performed by consenting adults, by a couple who are already lovers and in private. The Great Rite is not seen as an opportunity for casual sex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title =Sex, Wicca and the Great Rite | journal =The Blade &amp; Chalice | volume = Spring 1993 | issue = 3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most Neopagan religions generally accept same-sex relationships as equal to heterosexual ones; notable exceptions include the early writings of [[Gerald Gardener]], which are sometimes cited as [[homophobia|homophobic]], and some [[Neopagan reconstructionism|reconstructionists]] regard same-sex relationships as second to heterosexuality.  Homophobia is considerably most-common amongst [[Germanic Neopaganism]],{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}} though some are outspoken advocates of civil rights for same-sex-loving persons, and as homosexual or bisexual, themselves.

==Satanism==
[[LaVeyan Satanism]] is critical of Abrahamic sexual mores, considering them narrow, restrictive and hypocritical. Satanists are pluralists, accepting gays, lesbians, bisexuals, BDSM, transgendered people, and asexuals. Sex is viewed as an indulgence, but one that should only be freely entered into with consent. [[LaVeyan Satanism#The Eleven Satanic Rules of the Earth|The Eleven Satanic Rules of the Earth]] only give two instructions regarding sex: &quot;Do not make sexual advances unless you are given the mating signal&quot; and &quot;Do not harm little children&quot;, though the latter is much broader and encompasses physical and other abuse. This has always been consistent part of CoS policy since its inception in 1966, as Peter H. Gillmore wrote in an essay on [[same sex marriage]]:

{{quotation| Finally, since certain people try to suggest that our attitude on sexuality is “anything goes” despite our stated base principle of “responsibility to the responsible,” we must reiterate another fundamental dictate: The Church of Satan’s philosophy strictly forbids sexual activity with children as well as with non-human animals.|Magister Peter H. Gilmore&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.churchofsatan.com/Pages/FoundingFamily.html &quot;Founding Family: 'Morality' versus Same-Sex Marriage&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Spread to non-adherents==
Many cultures attempt to codify their prescriptions concerning individual sexual behaviors. Such codifications are frequently enacted as laws, extending their application beyond the culture to other cultures under the purview of the laws, including dissenters.

Most of the Islamic world has strict rules enforced with sometimes violent punishments to enforce [[Sharia|Islamic moral codes]], including sexual morality on their citizens, and impose it on non-Muslims living within their societies. The same was true of various European Christian regimes at some stages in history, and some contemporary Christians support restrictions on the private expression of [[human sexuality|sexuality]] outside of marriage, ranging from prohibitions of [[prostitution]] to restrictions on [[oral sex]] and [[sodomy]].&lt;!--[[Haredi Judaism|Haredi Jews]] in [[Israel]] use various verbal and print media (newspapers, books, radio shows, websites, etc.) to try to encourage other [[Jew]]s to follow the [[halakha|Jewish laws]] of sexuality.--&gt;


==See also==
{{multicol}}
* [[Asceticism]]
* [[Child sexuality]]
* [[Christian views on contraception]]
* [[Erotic plasticity]]
* [[Incest]]
* [[List of topics in sexual ethics]]
* [[Nazar ill'al-murd]]
* [[Pederasty in ancient Greece#In myth and religion|Pederasty in ancient Greece]]
* [[Polygamy#Patterns of occurrence across religions|Polygamy: Polygamy and religion]]
* [[The Religious Institute on Sexual Morality, Justice, and Healing]]
* [[Seven Laws of Noah]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Sex magic]]
* [[Sexual revolution]]
* [[Sexual abstinence]]
* [[Sexual ethics]]
* [[Sexual misconduct]]
* [[Sexual norm]]
* [[Sodomy law]]
* [[Song of Solomon]]
* [[Unification Church views of sexuality]]
* [[Victimless crime]]
* [[Judaism and sexuality]]
{{multicol-break}}
{{Portal|Religion|Sexuality}}
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
;Buddhism
* Bernard Faure. ''The Red Thread: Buddhist Approaches to Sexuality''. ISBN 0-691-05998-5.
* Philip T. Sudo. ''Zen Sex: The Way of Making Love''. ISBN 0-06-075799-X.

;Judaism
*[[Shmuley Boteach]]. ''Kosher Sex: A Recipe for Passion and Intimacy''. ISBN 0-385-49466-1.
*Michael Gold. ''Does God Belong in the Bedroom?'' ISBN 0-8276-0421-1.

;Critical perspectives
* {{Cite book|last=Gravatt|first=Sandra L|title=An Introduction to the Hebrew Bible: A Thematic Approach|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=y0PtOdR5pxkC&amp;pg=PA110&amp;dq=sexuality+and+the+Hebrew+bible#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=2008|isbn=978-0-664-23030-2}}
* {{Cite book|last=Brundage|first=James A|title=Law, Sex, and Christian Society in Medieval Europe|url=http://books.google.com.kh/books?id=SiGe-Zf0nTIC&amp;dq=Law,+Sex,+and+Christian+Society+in+Medieval+Europe&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|publisher=University of Chicago Press|year=1987|isbn=978-0-226-07784-0}}
* Demosthenes Savramis. ''The Satanizing of Woman: Religion Versus Sexuality''. ISBN 0-385-04485-2.

;Christianity
*[[Miguel A. De La Torre]]. ''A Lily Among the Thorns: Imagining a New Christian Sexuality''. ISBN 978-0-7879-8146-4.
*Jan Kern. ''Seduced By Sex: Saved By Love''. ISBN 0-7847-2158-2{{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (2) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}.
*[[Andreas J. Köstenberger]]. ''God, Marriage, and Family: Rebuilding the Biblical Foundation''. ISBN 978-1-58134-580-3.

;Islam
* {{Cite book|last=Dialmy|first=Abdessamad|title=Which Sex Education for Young Muslims?|publisher=World Congress of Muslim Philanthropists|year=2010|url=http://xa.yimg.com/kq/groups/14368256/413849807/name/Which}}
* {{Cite book|last=Habib|first=Samar|title=Islam and Homosexuality, vol.2|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=PqRq1bBbT54C&amp;pg=PA287&amp;lpg=PA287&amp;dq=liwat+is+regarded+as+a+temptation#v=onepage&amp;q=liwat%20is%20regarded%20as%20a%20temptation&amp;f=false|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=1997|isbn=978-0-313-37904-8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Jahangir|first=Junaid bin|chapter=Implied Cases for Muslim Same-Sex Unions|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=PqRq1bBbT54C&amp;pg=PR3&amp;dq=Islam+and+homosexuality,+Volume+2#v=onepage&amp;q=Islam%20and%20homosexuality%2C%20Volume%202&amp;f=false|editor=Samar Habib|title=Islam and homosexuality, Volume 2|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2010|isbn=978-0-313-37904-8}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Schmitt|first1=Arno|last2=Sofer|first2=Jehoeda|title=Sexuality and Eroticism among Males in Muslim Societies|publisher=Haworth Press|year=1992|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=Kw_BVSVmNsUC&amp;dq=Sexuality+and+eroticism+among+males+in+Moslem+societies&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|isbn=978-1-56024-047-1}}
* {{Cite book|last=Schmitt|first=Arno|title=Liwat im Fiqh: Männliche Homosexualität?|publisher=Journal of Arabic and Islamic Studies|date=Volume IV, 2001–2002|url=http://www.uib.no/jais/content4.htm}}
* {{Cite book|last1=Van Jivraj|first1=Suhraiya|last2=de Jong|first2=Anisa|title=Muslim Moral Instruction on Homosexuality|publisher=Yoesuf Foundation Conference on Islam in the West and Homosexuality – Strategies for Action|year=2001|url=http://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:KjIohrD0R-AJ:www.safraproject.org/Reports/Muslim_Moral_Instruction_on_Homosexuality.pdf+Islam,+Homosexuality+and+Migration&amp;hl=km&amp;gl=kh&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESi8Wm3zisCleP-UN8czw5a7tpJLFe2ekZJF6ccbenXhff2ub-0SP0uu-fIfZvZBmHiuZ6vVJfYvaxtkKcxiMSQV-p_WTdlSR_wOVD0XVZznB9RJgtgWUUEOQNlfd8jgYiPqL4U0&amp;sig=AHIEtbTAKkG0EQImULQIOH5QsnBAyVuR_w}}
* {{Cite book|last=Wafer|first=Jim|chapter=Mohammad and Male Homosexuality|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=hQuHFPKp8L0C&amp;pg=PA87&amp;lpg=PA87&amp;dq=Muhammad+and+male+homosexuality#v=onepage&amp;q=Muhammad%20and%20male%20homosexuality&amp;f=false|editor=Stephen O. Murray &amp; Will Roscoe|title=Islamic Homosexualities: Culture, History and Literature|publisher=New York University Press|year=1997|isbn=978-0-8147-7468-7}}

== Further reading ==
* [[John Boswell (historian)|John Boswell]], ''Christianity, Social Tolerance and Homosexuality: Gay People in Western Europe from the Beginning of the Christian Era to the Fourteenth Century'', University Of Chicago Press, 1st ed. 1980 ISBN 0-226-06710-6, paperback Nov. 2005 ISBN 0-226-06711-4
* [[Dag Øistein Endsjø]], [[Sex and Religion (book)|''Sex and Religion: Teachings and Taboos in the History of World Faiths'']], Reaktion Books 2011. ISBN 978-1-86189-815-9
* [[Mathew Kuefler]] (editor), ''The Boswell Thesis: Essays on Christianity, Social Tolerance, and Homosexuality'', University Of Chicago Press, Nov. 2005 ISBN 0-226-45741-9
* [[Eckhart Tolle]], ''The Power of Now: A Guide to Spiritual Enlightenment'', New World Library, 1st ed. 1999, paperback 2004 ISBN 1-57731-480-8

{{Religion topics}}
{{Sex}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Religion And Sexuality}}
[[Category:Sexuality and religion| ]]
[[Category:Religious views|Sexuality]]

[[ar:الجنس و الدين]]
[[cs:Náboženství a sexualita]]
[[es:Religión y sexualidad]]</text>
      <sha1>0kpvhjdqugbq5ufrp8pu6fqapuqlijy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
