<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Universalism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31902</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520246531</id>
      <parentid>519360800</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T10:48:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gregbard</username>
        <id>1193764</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removing link(s) to &quot;Stephen Palmquist&quot;: redlink. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30486">{{About|1=Universalism in religion and theology|2=other uses of the word|3=Universalism (disambiguation)}}
{{universalism}}

'''Universalism''', in its primary sense, refers to religious, theological, and philosophical concepts with [[Universal (metaphysics)|universal]] application or applicability. [[Religion]] in this context is defined as a set of beliefs concerning the cause, nature, and purpose of the [[universe]], especially when considered as the creation of a superhuman agency or agencies, usually involving devotional and ritual observances, and often containing a [[moral]] code governing the conduct of human affairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=religion|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Religion|work=Dictionary.com, LLC|publisher=Dictionary.com, LLC|accessdate=29 June 2012|author=Staff|year=2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Universalism is a term used to identify particular doctrines considering all people in their formation. Universalism in the religious context claims that religion or religious man (sic) is a universal quality. This can be contrasted with nonuniversalist religions.

In its secondary sense, a community that calls itself '''Universalist''' may emphasize the [[Cultural universal|universal principles of most religions]] and accept other religions in an inclusive manner, believing in a universal reconciliation between humanity and the divine. For example, some forms of [[Abrahamic religions]] happened to claim the universal value of their doctrine and moral principles, and feel inclusive.&lt;ref name='Schaff-Herzog'/&gt;

A belief in one common truth is also another important tenet. The living truth is seen as more far-reaching than national, cultural, or religious boundaries.

==Christianity==
{{Main|Christian Universalism}}
{{See also|Universal Reconciliation|Trinitarian Universalism}}
{{religious text primary|date=February 2012}}
{{refimprove section|date=February 2012}}
{{Copy edit-section|date=February 2012}}

In [[Christianity]], Universalism can refer to the beliefs that all humans either may or will be saved through [[Jesus Christ]] and eventually come to harmony in [[Kingdom of God|God's kingdom]]. This salvation is expressed as offered both to the Jew, and also to the [[Gentile]] ({{Bibleverse||Romans|1:16|ESV}}, {{Bibleverse||Romans|9:24-25|ESV}}, {{Bibleverse||Revelation|7:9|ESV}}). It is opposed to the doctrines of [[reprobation]] and [[Predestination (Calvinism)#Double predestination|double-predestination]] in [[Calvinism]].

The Greek term ''[[apokatastasis]]'' came to be related by some to the beliefs of [[Christian Universalism]], but in early Patristic usage is distinct. Additionally the term [[Catholic]] is derived from the Greek word ''katholikos'', which means universal. The Catholic Church is universal in the sense that it embraces individuals &quot;from every race, nation, language, and people&quot;, but does not teach universal salvation.

[[Universalist]] writers such as [[George T. Knight (Universalist)|George T. Knight]] have claimed that Universalism was a widely held view among theologians in [[Early Christianity]]&lt;ref name='Schaff-Herzog'&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/encyc12/Page_96.html [[George T. Knight (Universalist)|George T. Knight]] The Schaff-Herzog Encyclopedia of Religious Knowledge, 1953, vol. 12, p. 96; retrieved 30/04/09]&lt;/ref&gt; However, some examples, such as [[Origen]] and [[Clement of Alexandria]], used by Knight and other Universalist writers are contested by writers such as Crouzel{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}, Root{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}, Norris{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}, and Itter{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}.

Christian Universalist ideas are first undisputedly documented in 17th-century England and 18th-century Europe and America. [[Gerrard Winstanley]] (1648), [[Richard Coppin]] (1652), [[Jane Leade]] (1697), and then [[George de Benneville]] in America, taught that God would grant all human beings salvation. Those in America teaching this became known as the [[Universalist Church of America|Universalists]].&lt;ref&gt;Unitarian Universalism: A Research Guide By: Neal Wyatt ; Tierney V Dwyer ; Tierney V Dwyer
Format: Article Year: 2008 Published in: Reference &amp; User Services Quarterly SpringDF2008, Vol. 47 Issue 3, p210-214 5p 10949054 ][F;[]G=PY[GPGOPFG[A][]P[H[FDC Database: Academic Search Premier&lt;/ref&gt;

Some prevalent verses within the Christian Universalist Argument are:
# 1 Corinthians 15:22&lt;ref name=&quot;Tent&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The Fate of the Wicked|url=http://www.tentmaker.org/tracts/TheFateOfTheWicked.html|work=tentmaker.org|publisher=Tentmaker|accessdate=29 June 2012|author=Tentmaker|year=Unknown}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
#* &quot;For as in Adam '''ALL''' die, so in Christ '''ALL''' will be made alive.&quot; (NIV; Emphasis Added)
#* &quot;For as in Adam '''ALL''' die, so also in Christ shall '''ALL''' be made alive&quot; (ESV; Emphasis Added)
# Romans 5:18-19 (The &quot;one trespass&quot; and the &quot;one man's disobedience&quot; refer to Adam's sin, while the &quot;act of righteousness&quot; and the &quot;one man's obedience&quot; refer to Jesus' voluntary death on the cross).
#* &quot;Consequently, just as the result of one trespass was condemnation for all men, so also the result of one act of righteousness was justification that brings '''life for all men'''. For just as through the disobedience of the one man '''the many''' were made sinners, so also through the obedience of the one man '''the many will be made righteous'''.&quot; (NIV; Emphasis Added)
#* &quot;Therefore, as one trespass led to condemnation for all men, so one act of righteousness leads to justification and '''life for all men'''. For as by the one man's disobedience '''the many''' were made sinners, so by the one man's obedience '''the many will be made righteous'''.&quot; (ESV; Emphasis added)
# 2 Peter 3:9 (Goes to the character of God, in that He want's everyone to be saved. If He can do anything He wants and He wants everyone to be saved, why wouldn’t He save them?)
#* &quot;'''The Lord''' is not slow in keeping his promise, as some understand slowness. He is patient with you, '''not wanting anyone to perish, but everyone to come to repentance'''.&quot; (NIV; Emphasis Added)
#* &quot;'''The Lord''' is not slow to fulfill his promise as some count slowness, but is patient toward you, '''not wishing that any should perish, but that all should reach repentance'''.&quot; (ESV; Emphasis Added)
# 1 Timothy 2:3-6&lt;ref name=&quot;Tent&quot; /&gt; (Verses 3 &amp; 4 go to the Character of God. Verses 5 &amp; 6 explicitly state that Jesus paid the ransom for &quot;All men&quot;)
#* &quot;This is good, and pleases God our Savior, who '''wants all men to be saved''' and to come to a knowledge of the truth. For there is one God and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus, who gave himself as a ransom for '''ALL''' men--the testimony given in its proper time.&quot; (NIV; Emphasis Added)
#* &quot;This is good, and it is pleasing in the sight of God our Savior, who '''desires all people to be saved''' and to come to the knowledge of the truth. For there is one God, and there is one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus, who gave himself as a ransom for '''ALL''', which is the testimony given at the proper time.&quot; (ESV; Emphasis Added)
# 1 John 2:2
#* &quot;He is the atoning sacrifice for our sins, and not only for ours but also for the sins of the whole world.&quot; (NIV)
#* &quot;He is the propitiation for our sins, and not for ours only but also for the sins of the whole world.&quot; (ESV)
#  1 Timothy 4:10&lt;ref name=&quot;Tent&quot; /&gt; (This means that He is the savior of those who believe, but He is ALSO the savior of those who do NOT believe. How can He be the savior of those who do NOT believe, unless he saves them?)
#* &quot;(and for this we labor and strive), that we have put our hope in the living God, who is the '''Savior of all men, and especially of those who believe'''.&quot; (NIV; Emphasis Added)
#* &quot;For to this end we toil and strive, because we have our hope set on the living God, who is the '''Savior of all people, especially of those who believe'''.&quot; (ESV; Emphasis Added)
# Romans 11:32&lt;ref name=&quot;Tent&quot; /&gt; (Mercy on all, not mercy on some)
#* &quot;For God has bound all men over to disobedience so that he may have mercy on them all.&quot; (NIV)
#* &quot;For God has consigned all to disobedience, that he may have mercy on all.&quot; (ESV)
# 1 John 4:14&lt;ref name=&quot;Tent&quot; /&gt; (&quot;The world&quot;. Not &quot;Part of the world&quot;) 
#* &quot;And we have seen and testify that the Father has sent his Son to be the Savior of the world.&quot; (NIV)
#* &quot;And we have seen and testify that the Father has sent his Son to be the Savior of the world.&quot; (ESV)

Another key point within the Christian Universalist Argument is the understanding that mistranslations exist within many modern English translations. One of the biggest of such translation errors being that of the Greek word αιών (Lit. aion). This Greek word is the origin from which the modern English word &quot;eon&quot; is derived (synonymous with age). However, this word is often translated &quot;eternal&quot; as in the case of eternal punishment/torment and eternal life. In his tetralogy called &quot;Word Studies in the New Testament&quot;, the 19th century theologian Marvin R. Vincent wrote:

'''Aion, transliterated aeon, is a period of longer or shorter duration, having a beginning and an end, and complete in itself. Aristotle (peri ouravou, i. 9,15) says: &quot;The period which includes the whole time of one's life is called the aeon of each one.&quot; Hence it often means the life of a man, as in Homer, where one's life (aion) is said to leave him or to consume away (Iliad v. 685; Odyssey v. 160). It is not, however, limited to human life; it signifies any period in the course of events, as the period or age before Christ; the period of the millenium; the mythological period before the beginnings of history... The adjective aionios in like manner carries the idea of time. Neither the noun nor the adjective, in themselves, carry the sense of endless or everlasting. They may acquire that sense by their connotation, as, on the other hand, aidios, which means everlasting, has its meaning limited to a given point of time in Jude 6. Aionios means enduring through or pertaining to a period of time. Both the noun and the adjective are applied to limited periods... Words which are habitually applied to things temporal or material cannot carry in themselves the sense of endlessness. Even when applied to God, we are not forced to render aionios everlasting. Of course the life of God is endless; but the question is whether, in describing God as aionios, it was intended to describe the duration of his being, or whether some different and larger idea was not contemplated.'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Vincent|first=Marvin|title=Note on Olethron Aionion (eternal destruction)|url=http://www.auburn.edu/~allenkc/vincent.html|work=Word Studies in the New Testament|accessdate=18 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hinduism==
{{expand section|date=February 2012}}
Hinduism embraces universalism by conceiving the whole world as a single family that deifies the one truth, and therefore it accepts all forms of beliefs and dismisses labels of distinct religions which would imply a division of identity.&lt;ref&gt;(Rigveda 1:164:46) “Ekam sat vipra bahudha vadanti” - Truth is one; sages call it many names&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;(Maha Upanishad: Chapter 6, Verse 72) &quot;Vasudhaiva kutumbakam&quot; - The entire world is a one big family&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Badlani| first = Hiro| title = Hinduism: Path of the Ancient Wisdom| publisher = [[iUniverse]]| year = 2008| page = 303| url = http://books.google.com/?id=8NrQhyxH-GgC| isbn = 978-0-595-70183-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hindu]] Universalism denotes the ideology that all religions are true and therefore worthy of toleration and respect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=What Is Hinduism?: Modern Adventures Into a Profound Global Faith|year=2007|publisher=Himalayan Academy Publications|isbn=1934145009, 9781934145005|pages=416|url=What Is Hinduism?: Modern Adventures Into a Profound Global Faith|author=Editors of Hinduism Today}}&lt;/ref&gt; Veneration for all other religions was articulated by [[Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi|Gandhi]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;After long study and experience, I have come to the conclusion that [1] all religions are true; [2] all religions have some error in them; [3] all religions are almost as dear to me as my own Hinduism, in as much as all human beings should be as dear to one as one's own close relatives. My own veneration for other faiths is the same as that for my own faith; therefore no thought of conversion is possible.&quot; (M. K. Gandhi, ''All Men Are Brothers: Life and Thoughts of Mahatma Gandhi as told in his own words'', Paris, UNESCO 1958, p 60.)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Sikhism==
{{refimprove section|date=February 2012}}
{{expand section|date=February 2012}}
In [[Sikhism]], all the religions of the world are compared to rivers flowing into a single ocean. Although the Sikh Gurus did not agree with the practices of [[fasting]], [[idolatry]] and [[Religious pilgrimage|pilgrimage]] during their times, they stressed that [[Religious tolerance|all religions should be tolerated]] and [[Latitudinarianism|considered on equal footing]]. The Sikh [[Scripture]], the [[Guru Granth Sahib]], contains the writings of not just the Sikh [[Sikh Gurus|Guru]] themselves, but the writings of several [[Hindu saints|Hindu]] and [[Wali|Muslim]] [[saints]], known as the ''[[Bhagat]]s''. Although Sikhism does not teach that men are created in [[Image of God|God's image]], it states that the essence of the One is to be found throughout all of its creation. As was said by [[Yogi]] [[Bhajan]], the man who is credited with having brought Sikhism to the [[Western world|West]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;If you can't see [[God in Sikhism|God]] in all, you can't see God at all&quot;. (Sri Singh Sahib, Yogi Bhajan){{page needed|date=February 2012}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The First Sikh Guru, [[Guru Nanak]] said himself:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;There is no Hindu, there is no Muslim&quot;.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

By this, Guru Nanak meant that there is no distinction between religion in God's eyes, whether [[polytheist]], [[monotheist]], [[pantheist]], or even [[atheist]], all that one needs to gain salvation is purity of heart, tolerance of all beings, compassion and kindness. Unlike many of the major world religions, Sikhism does not have [[proselytism|missionaries]], instead it believes men have [[Religious freedom|the freedom to find]] their own path to [[salvation]].

==Judaism==
{{Main|Jewish views of religious pluralism}}
{{See also|Noahidism}}

Judaism teaches that [[God]] chose the Jewish people to be in a [[Jews as a chosen people|unique covenant with God]], and one of their beliefs is that Jewish people were charged by the [[Torah]] with a specific mission&amp;nbsp;— to be a light unto the nations, and to exemplify the covenant with God as described in the Torah to other nations. Not explicitly a Universalist theology, this view, however, does ''not'' preclude a belief that [[God]] also has a relationship with other peoples&amp;mdash;rather, Judaism holds that God had entered into a covenant with all humanity as [[Noachide]]s, and that Jews and non-Jews alike have a relationship with God, as well as being universal in the sense that it is open to all mankind.&lt;ref&gt;Covenant-Jewish Universalism and Particularism
By: David Polish
Format: Article
Year: 1985
Published in: Judaism Summer85, Vol. 34 Issue 3, p284 17p 00225762
Database: Academic Search Premier
&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Jewish Spiritual Leaders Institute (JSLI)]] believes in a more inclusive version of Jewish Universalism, believing that &quot;God equally chose all nations to be lights unto the world, and we have much to learn and share with each other. We can only accomplish &quot;[[Tikkun Olam]]&quot; by our unconditional acceptance of each other's peaceful doctrines.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jewish Universalism|url=http://www.jsli.net/jewish-universalism|work=Jewish Spiritual Leaders Institute|publisher=Google Inc|accessdate=29 June 2012|author=Staff|year=Unknown}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islam==
{{See|Ummah|Divisions of the world in Islam|People of the Book|Dhimmi|Jizya|Dawah|Jihad|}}
[[Islam]] recognizes to a certain extent the validity of the [[Abrahamic religions]], the [[Qur'an]] identifying [[Jew]]s, [[Christians]], and &quot;Sabi'un&quot; or &quot;baptists&quot; (usually taken as a reference to the [[Mandeans]]) as &quot;[[people of the book]]&quot; (''[[ahl al-kitab]]''). Later Islamic theologians expanded this definition to include Zoroastrians, and later even Hindus, as the early Islamic empire brought many people professing these religions under its dominion, but the Qur'an explicitly identifies only Jews, Christians, and Sabians as People of the Book.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Crone|first=Patricia|title=God's Rule: Government and Islam: Six Centuries of Medieval Islamic Political Thought|year=2005|publisher=Columbia University Press|isbn=978-0-231-13291-6|pages=472}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lapidus|first=Ira M.|title=A History of Islamic Societies|year=2002|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, England, UK|isbn=978-0-521-77933-3|pages=1000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Karsh 2007 304&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Karsh|first=Efraim|title=Islamic Imperialism: A History|year=2007|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=978-0-300-12263-3|pages=304}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Views of Muslims range along a continuum, from the most inclusive teaching common among [[Liberal Islam|liberal Muslims]] summed up in Surah 2:62,256&lt;ref&gt;1. S. A. Rahman, Punishment of Apostasy in Islam, Institute of Islamic Culture, Lahore, 1972&lt;/ref&gt; - &quot;Verily! Those who believe and those who are Jews and Christians, and Sabians, whoever believes in Allah and the Last Day and do righteous good deeds shall have their reward with their Lord, on them shall be no fear, nor shall they grieve...let there be no compulsion in religion&quot; - that all monotheistic religions or people of the book have a chance of salvation, to the most exclusive teaching common amongst [[Salafi]]s and [[Wahhabi]]s, and supported by several works of medieval Islamic theology and by traditions (''[[hadith]]'') which are considered correct (''[[sahih]]'') by Sunni Muslims, for the most part are summed up in Surah 9:5,29: &quot;Then, when the sacred months have passed, slay the idolaters [''[[mushrikun]]''] wherever ye find them, and take them, and besiege them, and lay in wait in every stratagem of war. But if they repent and establish worship and pay the ''[[jizya]]'', then leave their way free. Lo! Allah is Forgiving, Merciful...Fight against such of those who have been given the Scripture [i.e. people of the book] as believe not in Allah nor the Last Day, and forbid not that which Allah hath forbidden by His messenger, and follow not the Religion of Truth, until they pay the ''jizya'' readily, being brought low [in submission].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;All quotations of the Koran taken from the USC Center for Muslim-Jewish Engagement (formerly the USC Muslim Students' Association) Compendium of Muslim Texts: http://www.cmje.org/religious-texts/home/, [[Yusuf Ali]] or [[AJ Arberry]] translations.&lt;/ref&gt;

The interpretation of all of these passages are hotly contested amongst various schools of thought, traditionalist and reform-minded, and branches of Islam, from the reforming [[Qur'an only|Qur'anists]] and [[Ahmadiyya]] to the ultra-traditionalist [[Salafi]], as is the doctrine of abrogation (''[[naskh]]'') which is used to determine which verses take precedent, based on reconstructed chronology, with later verses superseding earlier ones. The traditional chronology places Surah 9 as the last or second-to-last surah revealed, thus, in traditional exegesis, it gains a large power of abrogation, and verses 9:5,29,73 are held to have abrogated 2:256&lt;ref name=&quot;Ibn Kathir 2000 6608&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Ibn Kathir|first=Ismail (1301-1373)|title=Tafsir al-Qur'an al-Aziz (Tafsir Ibn Kathir)|year=2000|publisher=Maktaba Darussalam|location=Riyadh, Saudi Arabia|isbn=978-1-59144-020-8|pages=6608|edition=English Abridged|editor=Sheikh Safiur-Rahman Al-Mubarakpuri|language=English and Arabic}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ahadith also play a major role in this, and different schools of thought assign different weightings and rulings of authenticity to different hadith, with the [[madhhab|four schools]] of Sunni thought accepting the [[Six major hadith collections|Six Authentic Collections]], generally along with the [[Muwatta Imam Malik]]. Depending on the level of acceptance of rejection of certain traditions, the interpretation of the Koran can be changed immensely, from the Qur'anists and Ahmadiyya who reject the ahadith, to the Salafi, or ''ahl al-hadith'', who hold the entirety of the traditional collections in great reverence.

Traditional Islam&lt;ref name=&quot;Ibn Kathir 2000 6608&quot;/&gt;{{cn|date=June 2012}}&lt;ref name=khalil&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.islamway.com/bindex.php?section=article&amp;id=211 |title=Ahmed Khalil: &quot;Dar Al-Islam And Dar Al-Harb: Its Definition and Significance&quot; |publisher=English.islamway.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; views the world as bipartite, consisting of the [[Dar al-Islam|House of Islam]], that is, where people live under the Islamic law - the [[Shariah]]{{cn|date=June 2012}}&lt;ref name=&quot;khalil&quot;/&gt; - and the [[Dar al-Harb|House of War]], that is, where the people do not live under Islamic law, which must be proselytized (see ''[[da'wah]]''){{cn|date=June 2012}}&lt;ref name=&quot;khalil&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ye'or|first=Bat|title=The Dhimmi: Jews and Christians Under Islam|year=1985|publisher=Farleign Dickinson University Press|pages=444|url=978-0838632628}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ye'or|first=Bat|title=The Decline of Eastern Christianity Under Islam: From Jihad to Dhimmitude: 7th-20th Centuries|publisher=Farleigh Dickinson University Press|isbn=978-0-8386-3688-6|pages=522}}&lt;/ref&gt; using whatever resources available, including, in some traditionalist and conservative interpretations,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Ibn Kathir's Tafsir al-Qur'an al-Aziz&lt;/ref&gt; the use of violence, as [[Jihad fi sabil Allah|holy struggle in the path of Allah]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Karsh 2007 304&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sayyid Qutb ''Milestones''&lt;/ref&gt; to either convert its inhabitants to Islam, or to rule them under the Shariah (cf. [[dhimmi]]);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Durie|first=Mark|title=The Third Choice: Islam, Dhimmitude and Freedom|year=2010|publisher=Deror Books|isbn=978-0-9807223-1-4|pages=288}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ye'or|first=Bat|title=Islam and Dhimmitude: Where Civilizations Collide|year=2001|publisher=Farleigh Dickinson University Press|isbn=978-0-8386-3942-9|pages=528}}&lt;/ref&gt;  since the abolition of the [[Caliphate]], there has been debate about the proper role of divisions of the world in Islam, and whether the traditional bipartite division is sufficient to meet the needs of the ''[[ummah]]'' (world community of Muslims) and world moving in to the future.

The [[Ash'ari]] school of [[Sunni]] [[aqidah]] (theology) holds that those who had never heard of the message of Islam, by virtue of isolation, can still be saved by the grace of Allah, similar to [[Karl Rahner]]'s concept of the [[Anonymous Christian]]. [[Sufi]]s generally hold to a much more inclusivist and tolerant view of other faiths and religious systems than traditional Sunni and Shi'a Islam.

==Zoroastrianism and Manicheanism==
{{main|Zoroastrianism|Manicheanism}}
Some forms of Zoroastrian and Manichean belief were universalistic in application to all races, but not universalist in the sense of [[universal salvation]].&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Porter Berkey ''The formation of Islam: religion and society in the Near East'' 2003 p28 &quot;This is not to say that there was no universalist dimension to Zoroastrian religious life; but what universalism there was derived directly, and to a greater degree than in the case of Rome and Christianity, from the explicit connection between religion and the state.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bahá'í Faith==
{{expand section|date=February 2012}}
In [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]] belief, [[God in the Bahá'í Faith|a single God]] has sent all the historic founders of the world religions in a process of [[Progressive revelation (Bahá'í)|progressive revelation]]. The major world religions are seen as divine in origin and are continuous in their purpose. In this view, there is unity among the founders of world religions, but each revelation brings a more advanced set of teachings in human history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Paradise and Paradigm: Key Symbols in Persian Christianity and the Bahá'í Faith | location = Albany | publisher = State University of New York Press | year = 1999 | page = 292 | last = Buck | first = Christopher}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within this universal view, the [[Bahá'í Faith and the unity of humanity|unity of humanity]] is one of the central teachings of the [[Bahá'í Faith]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockman&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Sourcebook of the World's Religions | editor-first= Joel |last = Beversluis | isbn = 1-57731-121-3 | publisher = New World Library | year = 2000 | first = Robert | last = Stockman | chapter = The Baha'i Faith | page = 7}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bahá'í teachings]] state that since all humans have been created in the image of God, God does not make any distinction between people regardless of [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[Human skin colour|colour]] or [[religion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith138&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Smith | first = Peter | year = 2008 | title = An Introduction to the Baha'i Faith | publisher = Cambridge University Press | place = Cambridge | isbn=0-521-86251-5 | page = 138}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, because all humans have been created equal, they all require equal opportunities and treatment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockman&quot;/&gt; Thus the Bahá'í view promotes the unity of humanity, and that people's vision should be world-embracing and that people should love the whole world rather than just their nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith138&quot;/&gt; The teaching, however, does not equal unity with uniformity, but instead the Bahá'í writings advocate for the principle of ''unity in diversity'' where the variety in the human race is valued.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith139&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Smith | first = Peter | year = 2008 | title = An Introduction to the Baha'i Faith | publisher = Cambridge University Press | place = Cambridge | isbn=0-521-86251-5 | page = 139}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Yi Guan Dao==
{{Main|I-Kuan Tao}}
{{unreferenced section|date=February 2012}}

Yi Guan Dao (loosely translated as &quot;Universal Taoism&quot;, &quot;the pervasive truth&quot;, or &quot;the consistent path&quot;) incorporates elements from Confucianism, Taoism, and Chinese Buddhism, and recognizes the validity of non-Chinese religious traditions such as Christianity and Islam as well. For this reason it is often classified as a syncretistic sect, along with other similar religions in the Way of Former Heaven (Xian Tian Dao) family.

==New Thought==
{{Main|New Thought}}
{{unreferenced section|date=February 2012}}

[[Unity Church|Unity]], [[Religious Science]], [[Divine Science]] are denominations within the [[New Thought]] movement. Each teaches that there is a common thread of truth at the heart of all religions. New Thought is an ever-evolving belief system which will incorporate ''Truth'' where ever it is found, hence the name ''New Thought''. ''All is God, But God transcends all''.

==Non-religious Universalism==

Universalism is not only a set of values, but a world view. To which any can prescribe if they observe and believe in the universality of the human experience, and that of all sentient life - and work to uphold the principles, ethics, and actions which safeguard these fundamental things.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Unitarian Universalism|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/atheism/types/unitarianuniversalism.shtml|publisher=BBC|accessdate=4 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Indeed many Universalists may be attracted to the logic of universally applicable principles, rather than any belief or dogma. Human unity, solidarity, and the perceived need for a sustainable and socially conscious global order are among the tendencies of non-religious Universalist thought.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Unitarian Universalism|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/u-u.htm|accessdate=4 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Religion}}

* [[Ananda Marga]]
* Christianity:
** [[Christian Universalism]]
** [[Liberal Catholic Church]]
** [[Primitive Baptist Universalist]]
** [[Religious Society of Friends]]
** [[Schwarzenau Brethren]]
** [[Swedenborgianism]] ([[The New Church]])
** [[Trinitarian Universalism]]
** [[Universalist Church of America]]
** [[Universal reconciliation]]
* [[Comparative religion]]
* [[Ecumenism]]
* [[George MacDonald]]
* [[Mahatma Gandhi Foundation]]
* [[Post-theism]]
* [[New Thought]]
* [[Omnism]]
* [[Perennial philosophy]]
* [[Religious pluralism]]
* [[Subud]]
* [[Unitarian Universalism]]
* [[Universal Sufism]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15181a.htm ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' article on Universalists as a Protestant denomination]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01599a.htm ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' article on Apocatastasis/apokatastatis]
* E Casara, ed., ''Universalism in America'' (1984)

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last= Ankerl |first= Guy |title= Global communication without universal civilization |year= 2000 |series= INU societal research |volume= Vol.1: Coexisting contemporary civilizations : Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western |publisher= INU Press |location= Geneva |isbn= 2-88155-004-5 |pages= }}
*Palmquist, Stephen, &quot;Christianity as the Universal Religion&quot;, Chapter Eight in Stephen Palmquist, [http://www.hkbu.edu.hk/~ppp/ksp2 Kant's Critical Religion] (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2000).

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Religion topics}}
{{Unitarian, Universalist and Unitarian Universalist topics}}

[[Category:Universalism| ]]
[[Category:Christian theological movements]]
[[Category:Christian soteriology]]
[[Category:Religious pluralism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Philosophical theories]]

[[ar:كونية]]
[[bg:Универсализъм]]
[[cs:Univerzalismus]]
[[da:Universalisme (teologi)]]
[[de:Universalismus (Religionswissenschaft)]]
[[el:Ουνιβερσαλισμός]]
[[es:Universalismo]]
[[ga:An tUilíochas]]
[[ko:보편주의]]
[[id:Universalisme]]
[[ia:Universalismo]]
[[it:Universalismo]]
[[he:אוניברסליזם]]
[[nl:Universalisme (theologie)]]
[[no:Universalisme]]
[[pl:Uniwersalizm]]
[[pt:Universalismo]]
[[ru:Универсализм]]
[[fi:Universalismi]]
[[zh:普世主义]]</text>
      <sha1>fyjq3eyikvf2pv9ys62lxldpsouqucw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
