<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf2</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Prison</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19008450</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520998946</id>
      <parentid>520904267</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T03:15:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>203.105.90.38</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 515408409 by [[Special:Contributions/Shorty23sin|Shorty23sin]] ([[User talk:Shorty23sin|talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27928">{{Redirect2|Jail|Gaol}}
{{Other uses}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Refimprove|date=October 2012}}
{{Globalize/US|date=January 2012|discuss=Talk:Prison#Globalize}}
A '''prison''' (from [[Old French]] ''prisoun'')&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=prison&amp;searchmode=none Online Etymology Dictionary], retrieved on 2009-10-12.&lt;/ref&gt; is a place in which people are physically confined and usually deprived of a range of personal [[Freedom (political)|freedoms]]. '''[[Imprisonment]]''' or '''[[incarceration]]''' is a legal [[punishment|penalty]] that may be imposed by the [[State (polity)|state]] for the commission of a [[crime]]. Other terms used are penitentiary, correctional facility, remand centre, detention centre, and jail or gaol. In some legal systems some of these terms have distinct meanings.

A criminal [[suspect]] who has been charged with or is likely to be charged with criminal [[Offense (law)|offense]] may be held ''on [[Detention of suspects|remand]]'' in prison if he or she is denied or unable to meet conditions of [[bail]], or is unable or unwilling to post bail. A criminal [[defendant]] may also be held in prison while awaiting [[trial (law)|trial]] or a trial [[verdict]]. If found guilty, a defendant will be [[conviction (law)|convicted]] and may receive a custodial [[sentence (law)|sentence]] requiring imprisonment.

As well as convicted or suspected criminals, prisons may be used for [[internment]] of those not charged with a crime. Prisons may also be used as a tool of [[political repression]] to detain [[political prisoner]]s, [[prisoner of conscience|prisoners of conscience]], and &quot;[[enemy of the state|enemies of the state]]&quot;, particularly by [[authoritarianism|authoritarian]] regimes. In times of [[war]] or conflict, [[prisoner of war|prisoners of war]] may also be detained in prisons. A prison system is the organizational arrangement of the provision and operation of prisons.

==History==
[[File:HuntsvilleUnitHuntsvilleTX.jpg|thumb|The [[Huntsville Unit]] (also known as &quot;The Walls&quot;) of the [[Texas Department of Criminal Justice]] in [[Huntsville, Texas]].&lt;br&gt; Texas' execution chamber is located in this unit]]For most of history, imprisoning has not been a punishment in itself, but rather a way to confine criminals until [[corporal punishment|corporal]] or [[capital punishment]] was administered. There were prisons used for detention in [[Jerusalem]] in [[Old Testament]] times, and the Bible details the imprisonment of Joseph in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle=Prisons}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dungeon]]s were used to hold prisoners; those who were not killed or left to die there often became [[galley slave]]s or faced [[penal transportation]]s. In other cases [[debtor]]s were often thrown into [[debtor's prison]]s, until they paid their jailers enough money in exchange for a limited degree of freedom.

Only in the 19th century, beginning in Britain, did prisons as known today become commonplace. The modern prison system was born in [[London]], influenced by the [[utilitarianism]] of [[Jeremy Bentham]]. Bentham's [[panopticon]] introduced the principle of observation and control that underpins the design of the modern prison. The notion of prisoners being incarcerated as part of their punishment and not simply as a holding state until trial or hanging, was at the time revolutionary. This is when prisons had begun to be used as criminal rehabilitation centers.

[[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|Britain]] practiced [[penal transportation]] of [[convict]]ed [[criminal]]s to [[penal colonies]] in the British Empire, in [[the Americas]] from the 1610s through the [[American Revolution]] in the 1770s and in [[Australia]] between 1788 and 1868. [[France]] sent criminals to [[tropical]] penal colonies including [[Louisiana]] in the early 18th century.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, Alan. ''American Colonies''. Penguin: London(2001).&lt;/ref&gt; Penal colonies in [[French Guiana]] operated until 1951 (in particular, infamous ''Île du Diable'' ([[Devil's Island]])). [[Katorga]] prisons were established in the 17th century in [[Tsardom of Russia]] in underpopulated areas of [[Siberia]] and the [[Russian Far East]] that had few towns or food sources. Since these times, Siberia gained its fearful connotation of punishment.

==Design and facilities==
[[File:Fence of Prison-BPO.jpg|thumb|[[Barbed tape]] is a feature of prisons.]]
[[File:Cela.jpg|thumb|A modern [[jail cell]].]]

Male and female prisoners are typically kept in separate locations or separate prisons altogether.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hmprisonservice.gov.uk/assets/documents/10003BB3womens_prisons_int_review_final_report.pdf International Profile of Women's Prisons] (144p), International Centre for Prison Studies, April 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Prison accommodation, especially modern prisons in the [[developed world]], are often divided into wings. A building holding more than one wing is known as a &quot;hall&quot;. Many prisons are divided into two sections, one containing prisoners before trial and the other containing convicted prisoners.

===Facilities===
Amongst the facilities that prisons may have are:
* A ''main entrance'', which may be known as the '[[sally port]]' or 'gatelodge' (stemming from old [[castle]] nomenclature)
* A religious facility, which will often house [[chaplain]]cy offices and facilities for [[psychotherapy|counselling]] of individuals or groups
* An '[[prison education|education facility]]', often including a [[library]], providing [[adult education]] or [[continuing education]] opportunities
* A ''[[gym]]'' or an ''exercise [[Yard (land)|yard]]'', a fenced, usually open-air-area which prisoners may use for recreational and exercise purposes
* A ''healthcare facility'' or ''[[hospital]]''
* A ''segregation unit'' (also called a 'block' or 'isolation cell'), used to separate unruly, dangerous, or vulnerable prisoners from the general population, also sometimes used as punishment (see [[solitary confinement]])
* A section of ''vulnerable prisoners'' (VPs), or ''protective custody'' (PC) units, used to accommodate prisoners classified as vulnerable, such as sex offenders, former [[police officer]]s, [[informants]] and those that have gotten into debt or trouble with other prisoners
* A section of ''safe cells'', used to keep prisoners under [[constant visual observation]], for example when considered at risk of [[suicide]]
* A ''visiting area'', where prisoners may be allowed restricted contact with relatives, friends, lawyers, or other people
* A ''death row'' in some prisons, a section for prisoners awaiting execution
* A ''staff accommodation'' area, where staff and prison officers live in the prison, typical of historical prisons
* A ''service/facilities area'' housing support facilities like [[kitchen]]s
* Industrial or agricultural plants operated with convict labour
* A ''recreational area'' containing items such as a TV and pool table

===Prison design===
[[Image:Pentonvilleiso19.jpg|thumb|An isometric drawing of [[Pentonville (HM Prison)|Pentonville prison]], from an 1844 report by [[Joshua Jebb]], [[Royal Engineers]].&lt;ref&gt;Report of the Surveyor-General of Prisons, London, 1844 reproduced in Mayhew, Criminal Prisons of London, London, 1862&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Prisons are normally surrounded by fencing, walls, earthworks, geographical features, or other barriers to prevent escape. Multiple barriers, [[concertina wire]], [[electric fence|electrified fencing]], secured and defensible main gates, armed guard towers, lighting, motion sensors, [[police dog|dogs]] and roving patrols may all also be present depending on the level of security. Remotely controlled doors, [[closed-circuit television|CCTV]] monitoring, alarms, cages, restraints, nonlethal and lethal weapons, riot-control gear and physical segregation of units and prisoners may all also be present within a prison to monitor and control the movement and activity of prisoners within the facility.

Modern prison designs have sought to increasingly restrict and control the movement of prisoners throughout the facility while permitting a maximal degree of direct monitoring by a smaller prison staff. As compared to traditional large landing-cellblock designs which were inherited from the 19th century and which permitted only intermittent observation of prisoners, many newer prisons are designed in a decentralized &quot;podular&quot; layout.

Smaller, separate and self-contained housing units known as &quot;pods&quot; or &quot;modules&quot; are designed to hold between sixteen and fifty prisoners each and are arranged around exercise yards or support facilities in a decentralized &quot;campus&quot; pattern. A small number of prison officers, sometimes a single officer, is assigned to supervise each pod. The pods contain tiers of cells arranged around a central control station or desk from which a single officer can monitor all of the cells and the entire pod, control cell doors and communicate with the rest of the prison. Pods may be designed for high-security &quot;indirect-supervision&quot;, in which officers in segregated and sealed control booths monitor smaller numbers of prisoners confined to their cells.

An alternative is &quot;direct-supervision&quot;, in which officers work within the pod and directly interact with and supervise prisoners, who may spend the day outside their cells in a central &quot;dayroom&quot; on the floor of the pod. Movement in or out of the pod to and from exercise yards, work assignments or medical appointments can be restricted to individual pods at designated times and is generally centrally controlled. Goods and services, such as meals, laundry, [[Commissary#Metonymic use|commissary]], educational materials, religious services and medical care can increasingly be brought to individual pods or cells as well.

Despite these design innovations, overcrowding at many prisons, particularly in the U.S., has resulted in a contrary trend, as many prisons are forced to house large numbers of prisoners, often hundreds at a time, in gymnasiums or other large buildings that have been converted into massive open dormitories.
Lower-security prisons are often designed with less restrictive features, confining prisoners at night in smaller locked dormitories or even cottage or cabin-like housing while permitting them freer movement around the grounds to work or activities during the day.

==Security levels==
The levels of security within a prison system are categorized differently around the world, but tend to follow a distinct pattern. Most developed countries divide prisons into separate security classes depending on the inmate population and the security needed to keep them under control. Accordingly, most developed countries have classes ranging from the most secure, which typically hold violent prisoners and those judged most likely to escape, to the least, which are most often used to house non-violent offenders or those for whom more stringent security is deemed unnecessary. Below are some different examples of prison classifications from around the world.

===England and Wales===
{{Main|Prisoner security categories in the United Kingdom}}
In [[England]] and [[Wales]], prisoners are assigned security classes when they are sentenced. Thus prisons are given security classifications depending on the prisoners they are designed to hold. Therefore, prisons classified as &quot;A&quot; would typically house prisoners assigned the &quot;A&quot; category during sentencing, and be designed with the level of security necessary for that class. The categories of prisoners in descending order are:
* '''Category A''': prisoners are those whose escape would be highly dangerous to the public or national security.
* '''Category B''': prisoners are those who do not require maximum security, but for whom escape needs to be made very difficult.
* '''Category C''': prisoners are those who cannot be trusted in open conditions but who are unlikely to try to escape.
* '''Category D''': prisoners are those who can be reasonably trusted not to try to escape, and are given the privilege of an open prison. Prisoners at 'D Cat' (as it is commonly known) prisons, are, subject to approval, given ROTL (Release On Temporary Licence) to work in the community or to go on 'home leave' once they have passed their FLED (Full Licence Eligibility Dates), which is usually a quarter of the way through the sentence.

The British prison system is also divided into &quot;Open&quot; and &quot;Closed&quot; prisons. Categories A-C are considered &quot;Closed&quot; prisons as prisoners cannot be trusted to interact with society, while category D prisons are generally &quot;Open&quot;, meaning that prisoners with a good record and who are approved can be allowed limited function in society such as home-leave or a nominal employment.

===United States===
{{Main|Incarceration in the United States}}
In the [[United States]], &quot;jail&quot; and &quot;prison&quot; refer to separate levels of incarceration; generally speaking, jails are [[County (United States)|county]] or city administrated institutions which house both inmates awaiting trial on the local level and convicted [[misdemeanor|misdemeanants]] serving a term of one year or less, while prisons are [[state government|state]] or [[US Federal government|federal]] facilities housing convicted [[felony|felons]] serving a term of more than one year. On the federal level, this terminology has been largely superseded by a more complex five-tier system implemented by the [[Federal Bureau of Prisons]] that ranges from low security &quot;Prison Camps&quot; to medium security &quot;Correctional Institutions&quot; and finally maximum security &quot;Penitentiaries&quot;. Federal prisons can also house pre-trial inmates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=BOP Information|url=http://www.bop.gov/inmate_locator/index.jsp|publisher=Bop.gov|accessdate=2012-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[file:Supermax prison, Florence Colorado.jpg|thumb|[[ADX Florence]] is presently the only facility housing [[supermax]] units operating in the [[Federal Bureau of Prisons]].]]
[[File:Alderson Federal Prison Camp entrance.jpg|thumb|[[Federal Prison Camp, Alderson]], a minimum security U.S. federal prison for women in Alderson, West Virginia]] The exact classification systems differ between county, state, and federal systems. Some common types of prisons include:
* '''[[Supermax]]''': As the name implies, the custody level goes beyond Maximum by segregating &quot;the worst of the worst&quot; in a prison system, such as terrorists deemed a threat to national security and inmates from other prisons who have a history of violent or other disruptive behavior in prison or are suspected of gang affiliation. This level is also used for non-terrorists who have been deemed too dangerous or too high-profile to ever be in a normal prison. These inmates have individual cells and are kept in [[solitary confinement|lockdown]] for 23 hours per day. Meals are served through &quot;chuck holes&quot; in the cell door, and each inmate is permitted out of their cell for one hour of exercise per day, alone. They are normally permitted no contact with other inmates and are under constant surveillance via [[closed-circuit television]] cameras.
* '''[[Administrative detention|Administrative]]''': Administrative security is a classification of prisons or detention centers that are for a specific purpose, such as housing mentally ill offenders. These range in levels of security from Minimum to Administrative Maximum Security (ADMAX), as in the case of [[ADX Florence]] in Florence, Colorado.
* '''Maximum''': A custody level in which both design and construction as well as inmate classification reflect the need to provide maximum external and internal control and supervision of inmates primarily through the use of high security perimeters and extensive use of internal physical barriers and check points. Inmates accorded this status present serious escape risks or pose serious threats to themselves, to other inmates, to staff, or the orderly running of the institution. Supervision of inmates is direct and constant.
* '''High''': The &quot;Middle Ground&quot; for violent crimes, High security institutions have highly-secured perimeters (featuring walls or reinforced fences), multiple- and single-occupant cell housing, the highest staff-to-inmate ratio, and close control of inmate movement.
* '''Medium''': A custody level in which design and construction as well as inmate classification reflect the need to provide secure external and internal control and supervision of inmates. Inmates accorded to this status may present a moderate escape risk or may pose a threat to other inmates, staff, or the orderly running of the institution. Supervision remains constant and direct. Through an inmate's willingness to comply with institutional rules and regulations, increased job and program opportunities exist.
* ''' Close Security''': Close Security prisons are institutions which house inmates too dangerous for Low Security, but who did not commit a crime worthy of incarceration in a Medium Security Facility. These prisons are rare, as most inmates fall into either &quot;Medium&quot; or &quot;Low&quot; Security Classifications. These facilities are often located in separate areas of a Low or Medium security Prison.
* '''Low''': A custody level in which both the design and construction as well as inmate classification reflect the goal of returning to the inmate a greater sense of personal responsibility and autonomy while still providing for supervision and monitoring of behavior and activity. Inmates within this security level are not considered a serious risk to the safety of staff, inmates or to the public. Program participation is mandated and geared toward their potential reintegration into the community. Additional access to the community is limited and under constant direct staff supervision
* '''Minimum''': The lowest level of security to which an inmate can be assigned directly. This type of prison is typically a &quot;[[Prison farm|prison farm]]&quot;, or other work-oriented facility, and most often houses petty or &quot;[[White collar criminal|White-collar criminals.]]&quot;
* '''Pre-release.''' A custody level in which both design and construction as well as inmate classification reflect the goal of restoring to the inmate maximum responsibility and control of their own behavior and actions prior to their release. Direct supervision of these inmates is not required, but intermittent observation may be appropriate under certain conditions. Inmates within this level may be permitted to access the community unescorted to participate in programming, including but not limited to work release or educational release.

==Special types of prison==
===Juvenile===
{{Main|Youth detention center}}
Prisons for [[Minor (law)|juveniles]] (people under 17 or 18, depending on the jurisdiction) are known as young offender facilities or similar designation and hold minors who have been remanded into custody or serving sentence. Many countries have their own [[age of criminal responsibility]] in which children are deemed legally responsible for their actions for a crime. Countries such as Canada may try to sentence a juvenile as an adult, but have them serve their sentence in a juvenile facility until they reach the age of majority, at which time they would be transferred to an adult facility.

===Military===
[[File:USDB2002.jpg|thumb|The [[United States Disciplinary Barracks]] in [[Fort Leavenworth, Kansas]] is a [[military prison]].]]
{{Main|Military prison}}
Prisons form part of military systems, and are used variously to house prisoners of war, [[unlawful combatant]]s, those whose freedom is deemed a national security risk by military or civilian authorities, and members of the [[military]] found guilty of a serious crime.

===Political===
{{Main|Political prisoner}}
Certain countries maintain or have in the past had a system of political prisons; arguably the [[gulag]]s associated with [[Stalinism]] are best known.

===Psychiatric===
{{Main|Psychiatric hospital}}
Some [[Psychiatry|psychiatric]] facilities have characteristics of prisons, particularly when confining patients who have committed a crime and are considered dangerous. In addition, many prisons have psychiatric units dedicated to housing offenders diagnosed with a wide variety of [[mental disorder]]s.

==Population statistics==
{{See also|List of countries by incarceration rate}}
As of 2006, it is estimated that at least 9.25&amp;nbsp;million people are currently imprisoned worldwide.&lt;ref name=Walmsley&gt;{{cite web|title=World Prison Population List (Seventh Edition)|url=http://www.kcl.ac.uk/depsta/law/research/icps/downloads/world-prison-pop-seventh.pdf|author=Walmsley, Roy|month=October|year=2006|accessdate=2007-12-15|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is probable that this number is much higher, in view of general under-reporting and a lack of data from various countries, especially [[Authoritarianism|authoritarian]] regimes.

The United States currently has the world's largest prison population. There are over 2 million people in American prisons or jails, up from 744,000 in 1985.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://money.cnn.com/magazines/business2/business2_archive/2006/12/01/8394995/index.htm Inside America's $37 billion prison economy]&quot;. CNNMoney. March 15 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

If observers of prisons can agree upon one fact, it is that American prisons are overcrowded at the moment. In the United States, as of 2009, California had 158,000 inmates in prisons that were designed to hold 84,000. The result was that almost 14,000 inmates were sleeping in very tight spaces, or in hallways or on floors. Prisons all over the nation are overcrowded, and people are being incarcerated at an increasing rate, whereas the new prisons cannot be built fast enough.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Engdahl |first= Sylvia |title=Prisons |publisher= Farmington Hills: Greenhaven Press |year=2010 |isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Portal|Criminal justice}}
==See also==
* [[Prisons by country]]
{{col-start}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Anton Praetorius]] (early prison reformer)
* [[Community service]]
* [[Corrections]]
* [[Department of Corrections]]
* [[gaol fever|Gaol Fever]] (An illness commonly found in pre-industrial age prisons)
* [[Howard League for Penal Reform]] (oldest prison reform organisation in the world)
* [[Incarceration of women]]
* [[Inmate telephone system]]
* [[Jailhouse lawyer]]
* [[John Howard (prison reformer)]]
* [[Juvenile delinquency]]
* [[Kishka (prison cell)]]
* [[List of countries by incarceration rate]]
* [[Mental illness|Mental Illness in prison]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1646652 |title=Mental Illness in Prison: Inmate Rehabilitation &amp; Correctional Officers in Crisis by SpearIt :: SSRN |publisher=Papers.ssrn.com |date= |accessdate=2012-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Penal labour]]
* [[Penology]]
* [[Prison abolition movement]]
* [[Prison Act]]
* [[Prison discipline]]
* [[Prison education]]
* [[Prison escape]]
* [[Prison food]]
* [[Prison gang]]
* [[Prison officer]]
* [[Prison rape]]
* [[Prison reform]]
* [[Prison religion]]
* [[Prison sexuality]] (homosexuality and abuse in prisons)
* [[Prison uniform]]
* [[Prisoner]]
* [[Prisoner's dilemma]]
* [[Prisoners' rights]]
* [[Punishment]]
* [[Rehabilitation (penology)]]
* [[Stanford prison experiment]]
* [[Yardbird]]
* Types of imprisonment
** [[False imprisonment]]
** [[House arrest]]
** [[Life imprisonment]]
** [[Protective custody]]
** [[Detention of suspects|Remand]]
** [[Separate system]]
** [[Solitary confinement]]
{{col-break}}
* Types of prisons
** [[Boot camp (correctional)|Boot camp]]
** [[Borstal]]
** [[Death Row]]
** [[Federal prison]]
** [[Immigration detention]]
** [[Mental hospital]]
** [[Military prison]]
** [[Panopticon]]
** [[Penal colony]]
** [[Political prison]]
** [[Private prisons]]
** [[Roundhouse (lock-up)|Roundhouse]]
** [[Supermax]]
** [[Village lock-up]]
** [[Youth detention center]]
* Specific prisons
** [[List of prisons]]
* Prison-related crime
** [[Gassing (prison slang)|Gassing]]
* Game
** ''[[Prison Architect]]''
** ''[[Prison Tycoon]]''
** ''[[Prison Tycoon 2: Maximum Security]]'' (also known as ''Prison Tycoon II'')
* Song
** &quot;[[Black Steel in the Hour of Chaos]]&quot;, Public Enemy song
** &quot;[[Folsom Prison Blues]]&quot;, Johhny Cash song
** &quot;[[Jailbreak (AC/DC song)|Jailbreak]]&quot;, AC/DC song
** &quot;[[Jailbreak (Thin Lizzy song)|Jailbreak]]&quot;, Thin Lizzy song
** [[Jailhouse Rock (song)|&quot;Jailhouse Rock&quot;]], Elvis Presley song
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Carlson, Peter M.; Garrett, Judith Simon, [http://books.google.com/books?id=sY7nRteCGEkC&amp;printsec=frontcover ''Prison and Jail Administration: Practice and Theory''], [[Jones and Bartlett Publishers]], 1999.
* Diiulio, John J., [http://books.google.com/books?id=s6AsM5Y_MUIC&amp;printsec=frontcover ''Governing Prisons: A Comparative Study of Correctional Management''], [[Simon and Schuster]], 1990. ISBN 0-02-907883-0.
* Harnsberger, R. Scott. A Guide to Sources of Texas Criminal Justice Statistics [North Texas Crime and Criminal Justice Series, no.6]. Denton: University of North Texas Press, 2011. ISBN 978-1-57441-308-3
* James (Jim) Bruton, ''Big House: Life Inside a Supermax Security Prison'', Voyageur Press (July 2004), hardcover, 192 pages, ISBN 0-89658-039-3.
* [[Michel Foucault]], ''[[Discipline and Punish|Discipline and Punish: The Birth of the Prison]]'', New York: [[Random House]] 1975.
* Ted Conover. ''Newjack: Guarding Sing Sing''. Knopf, 2001. Trade paperback, 352 pages, ISBN 0-375-72662-4.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|prison|jail|gaol|penitentiary}}
{{Commons category|Prisons}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://edutube.org/interactive/prison-population-capita Interactive world map showing number of prisoners per 100,000 citizens]
* [http://sites.google.com/site/australianprisons/ Australian Prisons]
* [http://www.free-writer.ru/pages/prisonen.html Russian Prisons photostory]
* [http://www.touropia.com/historic-prisons/ Historic Prisons]
* [http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/documentsonline/prison.asp Victorian Prisoners' Photograph Albums from Wandsworth prison on The National Archives' website.]
* [http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs2/r188.pdf World Prison Population List (fourth edition)] UK [[Home Office]], 2003. {{ISSN|1473-8406}}.
* [http://www.sccjr.ac.uk/pubs/User-Views-of-Punishment-The-comparative-experience-of-short-term-prison-sentences-and-communitybased-punishments/284 User Views of Punishment: The comparative experience of short term prison sentences and community-based punishments] Research Report by [http://www.sccjr.ac.uk The Scottish Centre for Crime and Justice Research]

{{Incarceration}}

[[Category:Penology]]
[[Category:Prisons| ]]
[[Category:Total institutions]]

[[ar:سجن]]
[[an:Garchola]]
[[arc:ܚܒܘܫܝܐ]]
[[ay:Mutüwi]]
[[az:Həbsxana]]
[[bn:কারাগার]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kaⁿ-ga̍k]]
[[be:Турма]]
[[be-x-old:Турма]]
[[bg:Затвор]]
[[bs:Zatvor]]
[[br:Toull-bac'h]]
[[ca:Presó]]
[[cs:Věznice]]
[[cy:Carchar]]
[[da:Fængsel]]
[[de:Gefängnis]]
[[et:Vangla]]
[[es:Prisión]]
[[eo:Malliberejo]]
[[eu:Espetxe]]
[[fa:زندان]]
[[fo:Fongsul]]
[[fr:Prison]]
[[fy:Finzenis]]
[[gl:Centro penitenciario]]
[[gan:牢監]]
[[ko:교도소]]
[[hi:थाना]]
[[hr:Zatvor]]
[[io:Karcero]]
[[id:Penjara]]
[[is:Fangelsi]]
[[it:Prigione]]
[[he:בית סוהר]]
[[jv:Pakunjaran]]
[[kk:Абақты]]
[[ku:Girtîgeh]]
[[la:Carcer]]
[[lv:Cietums]]
[[lt:Kalėjimas]]
[[hu:Börtönbüntetés]]
[[mk:Затвор]]
[[mt:Ħabs]]
[[mr:तुरुंग]]
[[ms:Penjara]]
[[nl:Gevangenis]]
[[ne:थाना]]
[[ja:刑務所]]
[[no:Fengsel]]
[[nn:Fengsel]]
[[pl:Więziennictwo]]
[[pt:Prisão]]
[[ro:Închisoare]]
[[qu:Samk'ay wasi]]
[[ru:Тюрьма]]
[[sco:Preeson]]
[[scn:Carciareri]]
[[simple:Prison]]
[[sk:Väznica]]
[[sl:Zapor]]
[[sr:Затвор]]
[[sh:Zatvor]]
[[fi:Vankila]]
[[sv:Fängelse]]
[[te:కారాగారము]]
[[tr:Cezaevi]]
[[uk:В'язниця]]
[[vi:Nhà tù]]
[[wa:Prijhon]]
[[war:Prisuhan]]
[[yi:טורמע]]
[[zh:監獄]]</text>
      <sha1>0y666l2udz94m3ojf7q54vc2kye82ci</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
