<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ancient music</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1502321</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522291956</id>
      <parentid>522232006</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T06:03:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Termininja</username>
        <id>8164021</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14892">{{more footnotes|date=September 2011}}
{{Musiceras}}
'''Ancient music''' is music that developed in literate cultures, replacing [[prehistoric music]].

Ancient music refers to the various musical systems that were developed across various geographical regions such as Mesopotamia, Egypt, Persia, India, China, Greece and Rome. Ancient music is designated by the characterization of the basic audible tones and scales. It may have been [[transmitted]] through oral or written [[systems]].

==Mesopotamia==
{{main|Music of ancient Mesopotamia}}
Anne Draffkorn Kilmer from the [[University of California]] at Berkeley published in 1986 her [[decipherment]] of [[cuneiform]] [[Clay tablet|tablet]] from [[Nippur]] dated to about 2000 BCE, demonstrating that it represents fragmentary instructions for performing music and that the music was composed in harmonies of thirds, and that it was also written using a [[diatonic scale]] (Kilmer 1986). The notation in that tablet was not as developed as the notation in the later cuneiform tablet dated to about 1250 BCE (Kilmer 1965). Although the interpretation of the notation system is still controversial, it is clear that the notation indicates the names of strings on a [[lyre]], the tuning of which is described in other tablets (West 1994). These tablets represent the earliest recorded melodies, though fragmentary, from anywhere in the world  (West 1994).

===The harps of Ur===
{{Main|Lyres of Ur}}
In 1929, [[Leonard Woolley]] discovered pieces of four [[harp]]s while excavating in the ruins of the ancient city of [[Ur]] located in what was [[Ancient Mesopotamia]] and is contemporary [[Iraq]]. Some fragments are at the [[University of Pennsylvania]], some in the [[British Museum]] in [[London]], and some in [[Baghdad]]. They have been dated to [[27th century BCE|2,750 BCE]]. Various reconstructions have been attempted, but none were totally satisfactory. Depending on various definitions, they could be classed as [[lyre]]s rather than harps. The most famous is the bull-headed harp, held in Baghdad. The second [[Iraqi War]] led to the destruction of the bull-head lyre,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.liv.ac.uk/news/press_releases/2005/07/lyre_of_ur.htm Ancient Iraqi harp reproduced by Liverpool engineers - University of Liverpool&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and attempts are being made to play a replica of it as part of a touring [[orchestra]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Harps from Assyria and Egypt===
[[Assurbanipal]] (705 - 681 BCE) was king of [[Assyria]]. At his capital at [[Nineveh]] is a [[bas-relief]] showing the fall of the [[Judea]]n city of [[Lachish]]. In the procession is the [[Elamite]] court orchestra, containing seven lyre-players and possibly a [[hammer-dulcimer]] player. The lyres appear to have seven strings. Harps are shown in [[mural]]s from the time [[Ramesses III]] of Egypt, about 1200 BCE. &quot;The Tomb of the Harpists&quot; contains a bas-relief with two blind musicians. [[James Bruce]] described it in 1768 and it is sometimes known as Bruce's Tomb.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Hurrian music===
{{main|Hurrian songs}}

Among the [[Hurrian]] texts from [[Ugarit]] are some of the oldest known instances of written music, dating from c.1400 BCE and including one substantially complete song. A reconstruction of this hymn is presented at the [http://128.97.6.202/urkeshpublic/music.htm Urkesh webpage].

==Ancient India==
{{main|Music in ancient India}}
{{see also|Ancient Tamil music|Origins and history of Carnatic music}}
Musical instruments, such as the seven-holed [[flute]] and various types of stringed instruments have been recovered from the [[Indus valley civilization]] archaeological sites.

The [[Samaveda]] consists of a collection (samhita) of hymns, portions of hymns, and detached verses, all but 75 taken from the [[Rigveda]], to be sung, using specifically indicated melodies called ''[[Samagana]]'', by [[Udgatar]] priests at sacrifices in which the juice of the [[Soma]] plant, clarified and mixed with milk and other ingredients, is offered in libation to various deities. In ancient India, [[Patha#Styles_of_memorization|memorization]] of the sacred ''[[Veda]]s'' included up to eleven forms of recitation of the same text. 

The [[Natya Shastra|Nātya Shastra]] is an [[History of India|ancient Indian]] treatise on the [[performing arts]], encompassing [[Indian theatre|theatre]], [[Indian classical dance|dance]] and [[Indian classical music|music]]. It was written at an uncertain date in classical [[India]] (between 200 BCE and 200 CE). The Natya Shastra is based upon the much older [[Natya Veda]] which contained 36000 slokas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last = Ghosh |first = Manomohan |title = Natyasastra |year = 2002 |isbn =81-7080-076-5| page = 2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately there are no surviving copies of the Natya Veda. There are scholars who believe that it may have been written by various authors at different times. The most authoritative commentary on the ''Natya Shastra'' is ''[[Abhinavabharati]]'' by [[Abhinava Gupta]].

While much of the discussion of music in the Natyashastra focuses on musical instruments, it also emphasizes several theoretical aspects that remained fundamental to [[Music of India|Indian music]]: 

# Establishment of ''Shadja'' as the first, defining note of the scale or [[grama]].
# Two Principles of Consonance: The first principle states that there exists a fundamental note in the musical scale which is Avinashi (अविनाशी) and Avilopi (अविलोपी) that is, the note is ever-present and unchanging.  The second principle, often treated as ''law'', states that there exists a natural consonance between notes; the best between Shadja and Tar Shadja, the next best between Shadja and Pancham.
# The Natyashastra also suggests the notion of [[musical mode]]s or [[jati]]s which are the origin of the notion of the modern melodic structures known as [[raga]]s.  Their role in invoking emotions are emphasized; thus compositions emphasizing the notes [[gandhara]] or [[rishabha]] are said to be related to tragedy (''karuna rasa'') whereas [[rishabha]] is to be emphasized for evoking heroism (''vIra rasa'').

Jatis are elaborated in greater detail in the text [[Dattilam]], composed around the same time as the Natyashastra. 

The Natyashastra also suggests several aspects of musical performance, particularly its application to vocal, instrumental and orchestral compositions.  It also deals with the [[Rasa (aesthetics)|rasas]] and [[bhava]]s that may be evoked by music.

== Ancient Srilankan Ravanahatha ==

&lt;ref&gt;http://zomobo.net/ravanhatta&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ravanahatha]] is a crude violin made of coconut shell and bamboo And goat skin , with a natural fibre serving as the string. Goat and sheep gut and coconut wood are also used.Having been the first stringed instrument to be played with a bow, it is recognised as the world's first violin.
[[Ravanahatha]] or Ravana's hand is mentioned in the ancient Indian epic '[[Ramayana]]'.The soulful music emanating from the Ravanahatha is believed to have moved Hindu god Shiva, of whom Ravana was an ardent devotee.
'The instrument was picked by Hanuman and flown to north India, where it is still played in Rajasthan and in the Agra area of Uttar Pradesh and is known as [[Ravanahatha]],
[[File:The Ancient Instrument Ravanahatha.jpg|thumb|Sri lankan [[Ravanahatha]]]]
From India, the [[Ravanahatha]] travelled westwards to the Middle East and Europe, where in the 9th century, it came to be called the ravanastrom, according to the website library thinkquest.org.
From the 11th century onwards, the bowed instrument underwent many changes before it took the shape of the modern violin in Italy in the 16th century.

,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.india-forums.com/news/srilanka/76066-sri-lankan-revives-ravana-musical-instrument-feature.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://sundaytimes.lk/090524/Magazine/sundaytimesmagazine_00.html&lt;/ref&gt;[[Dinesh Subasinghe]]  a star on the Sri Lankan music horizon, has a new and daring passion - to popularise [[Ravanahatha]]  a violin-like instrument that Lanka king Ravana had devised and played about 5,000 years ago.The [[Ravanahatha]] sounds like the north Indian instruments Sarangi and Esraj. Its plaintive and melancholic sound touches an emotional chord ,' , 

The melancholic sound of [[Ravanahatha]] might be a reflection of the character of Ravana, a tragic hero who the author of the 'Ramayana' demonised, conveniently ignoring his abilities as a scholar, musician and technologist.
The ravanahatha's birth itself is believed to have taken place under traumatic circumstances. According to legend, Ravana's mother Kaikasi, an ardent devotee of Shiva, was eager to go and live in the god's abode on Mount Kailash in the Himalayas. Ravana opposed the plan vehemently, but to please his mother he promised to bring Mount Kailash itself to Sri Lanka.
As Ravana was lifting the mountain, an angry Shiva trapped his 10 heads and 20 arms. Writhing in pain, Ravana prayed for mercy. When Shiva let him off, Ravana decided to sing his praise and instantly made an accompanying instrument using one of his heads, an arm and some of his hair. The soulful music emanating from Ravana's instrument is said to have moved Shiva, who bestowed immortality on him.
Though crude and utterly simple, the [[Ravanahatha]] has proved to be a very versatile instrument.

&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buzzle.com/articles/coconut-uses.html&lt;/ref&gt;[[Dinesh Subasinghe]] brought some changes in to this ancient instrument,he brought a unique style and technique to play it like a Sarangi, in year 2007 for the first time he introduced this instrument to electronic media in srilanka and in to the recording music industry and [[Dinesh Subasinghe]] launched the first audio album from thia Ancient Instrument [[Ravanahatha]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thaindian.com/newsportal/uncategorized/sri-lankan-revives-ravanas-musical-instrument_10018913.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indodutchconnect.com/articles/stringing-a-new-tune_500.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancient China==
{{main|Guqin history}}
[[Image:Jiu Xiao Huan Pei.jpg|thumb|300px|A famous [[Tang Dynasty]] qin, &quot;Jiu Xiao Huan Pei&quot; 《九霄環佩》.]]
The history of the [[Guqin]], an ancient Chinese musical instrument, is a long one. It is mentioned in Chinese writings dating back nearly 3,000 years, and it is the most prestigious of all Chinese musical instruments. Chinese legend says the qin originally had five strings, but then two were added around 1000 BCE.

==Ancient Persia==
Little is known of the music during the ancient Persian period except for the fact that various instruments, such as [[lute]]s and [[flute]]s, were created and played. Instruments such as the &quot;[[barbat (lute)|barbat]]&quot; (a precursor of the lute, the modern form commonly referred to as [[oud]] or ud in Arabic countries and in Turkey) are said to have originated in this period, probably around 800 BCE.

==Ancient Greece==
{{main|Music of ancient Greece}}
[[File:Banquet scene Louvre G135.jpg|thumb|[[Symposium]] scene, c. 490 BCE]]
Ancient Greek musicians developed their own robust system of musical notation. The system was not widely used among Greek musicians, but nonetheless a modest corpus of notated music remains from [[Ancient Greek music|Ancient Greece]] and [[Ancient Roman music|Rome]]. The [[Epic poetry|epic]]s of [[Homer]] were originally sung with instrumental accompaniment, but no notated melodies from Homer are known. Several complete songs exist in ancient Greek musical notation. The [[Seikilos epitaph]] is the oldest surviving example of a complete musical composition, including musical notation, from anywhere in the world.{{Contradiction-inline|date=January 2012}}&lt;!--The section above, on Hurrian music, refers (if vaguely) to one complete, considerably earlier piece.--&gt; Three complete [[hymn]]s by [[Mesomedes]] of [[Crete]] (2nd century CE) exist in manuscript. In addition, many fragments of Greek music are extant, including fragments from [[tragedy]], among them a [[Greek chorus|choral song]] by [[Euripides]] for his ''[[Orestes (play)|Orestes]]'' and an instrumental [[intermezzo]] from [[Sophocles]]' ''[[Ajax (play)|Ajax]]''. Romans did not have their own system of musical notation, but a few Romans apparently learned the Greek system. {{Citation needed|date=July 2012}} A line from [[Terence]]'s ''[[Hecyra]]'' was set to music and possibly notated by his composer [[Flaccus (composer)|Flaccus]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

It has always been known that some ancient music was not strictly monophonic.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} Some fragments of Greek music, such as the ''Orestes'' fragment, clearly call for more than one note to be sounded at the same time. Greek sources occasionally refer to the technique of playing more than one note at the same time. In addition, double pipes, such as used by the Greeks and Persians, and ancient bagpipes, as well as a review of ancient drawings on vases and walls, etc., and ancient writings (such as in Aristotle, ''Problems,'' Book XIX.12) which described musical techniques of the time, all indicate harmony existed. One pipe in the aulos pairs (double flutes) may have served as a [[Drone (music)|drone]] or &quot;keynote,&quot; while the other played melodic passages.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Ancient Rome==
 {{main|Music of ancient Rome}}

==See also==
* [[Persian traditional music]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Kilmer, Anne Draffkorn, 'The Strings of Musical Instruments: their Names, Numbers, and Significance', ''Studies in Honor of Benno Landsberger'' = ''Assyriological Studies'' xvi (1965), 261–68.
* Kilmer, Anne Draffkorn, and Miguel Civil. 'Old Babylonian Musical Instructions Relating to Hymnody', ''Journal of Cuneiform Studies'', xxxviii (1986), 94–98.
* West, M. L., 'The Babylonian Musical Notation and the Hurrian Melodic Texts', ''Music &amp; Letters'', lxxv, no. 2 (May 1994), 161–79.

==External links==
* [http://nay-nava.blogfa.com/ Nay-Nava the encyclopedia of Persian music instruments]
* [http://www.ancientinstruments.co.uk Reconstructed bone flutes, sound sample and playing instructions.]
* [http://www.musicarchaeology.org/ International Study Group on Music Archaeology]
* [http://www.musica-romana.de/ Musica Romana: Ensemble for ancient music]
* [http://www.myspace.com/daemonianymphemyspace Ancient Greek music on original instruments : Daimonia Nymphe]

{{Ancient music}}
{{Music topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ancient Music}}
[[Category:Ancient music| ]]

{{Link FA|nl}}

[[bg:Древна музика]]
[[ca:Música de l'antiguitat]]
[[de:Musik der Antike]]
[[et:Vanaaja muusika]]
[[es:Música en la Antigüedad]]
[[hr:Starovjekovna glazba]]
[[ko:고대의 서양 고전 음악]]
[[nl:Muziek in de Oudheid]]
[[ja:古代の音楽]]
[[sh:Antička muzika]]
[[fi:Antiikin musiikki]]
[[sv:Antikens musik]]</text>
      <sha1>iw1oai425gfeoiujrmgeghnxlefv1sk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
