<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ancient warfare</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>962433</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518635250</id>
      <parentid>516575874</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-19T03:53:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ravenswing</username>
        <id>270405</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Important ancient battles */  No independent evidence of the historicity of this battle</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="50612">{{About|ancient warfare|the magazine with the same title|Ancient Warfare (magazine)}}
{{History of war}}

'''Ancient warfare''' is [[war]] as conducted from the beginnings of [[recorded history]] to the end of the [[ancient period]]. In [[Europe]] and the [[Near East]], the end of antiquity is often equated with the [[Roman Empire|fall of Rome]] in 476, and the wars of the Eastern Roman Empire [[Byzantium]] in its South Western Asian and North African borders and the beginnings of the [[Muslim conquests]] in the 7th century. In [[China]], it can also be seen as ending with the growing role of mounted warriors needed to counter the ever-growing threat from the north in the 5th century and the beginning of the [[Tang Dynasty]] in 618. In [[Indian subcontinent|India]], the ancient period ends with the decline of the [[Gupta Empire]] (6th century) and the beginning [[Muslim conquest in the Indian subcontinent|Islamic conquests]] from the 8th century. In [[Japan]], the ancient period can be taken to end with the rise of [[feudalism]] in the [[Kamakura period]] in the 12-13th century.

The difference between [[Prehistoric warfare|prehistoric]] and ancient warfare is less one of technology than of organization. The development of first [[city-state]]s, and then [[empire]]s, allowed warfare to change dramatically. Beginning in [[Mesopotamia]], states produced sufficient agricultural surplus so that full-time ruling elites and military commanders could emerge. While the bulk of military forces were still farmers, the society could support having them campaigning rather than working the land for a portion of each year. Thus, organized armies developed for the first time.

These new armies could help states grow in size and became increasingly centralized. Early ancient armies continued to primarily use [[bow and arrow|bows]] and [[spear]]s, the same weapons that had been developed in prehistoric times for hunting. Early armies in [[Egypt]] and [[China]] followed a similar pattern of using massed infantry armed with bows and spears. 

No clear line can be drawn between ancient and [[medieval warfare]]. The characteristic properties of medieval warfare, notably [[heavy cavalry]] and [[Medieval siege weaponry|siege engines]] such as the [[trebuchet]] were first introduced in [[Late Antiquity]]. The main division within the ancient period is rather at the beginning [[Iron Age]] with the introduction of [[cavalry]] (resulting in the decline of [[chariot warfare]]), of [[naval warfare]] ([[Sea Peoples]]), and of course the development of an industry  based on [[ferrous metallurgy]] which allowed for the mass production of metal weapons and thus the equipment of large standing armies.
The first military power to profit from these innovations was the [[Neo-Assyrian Empire]], which achieved a [[List of largest empires#Ancient empires|hitherto unseen]] extent of centralized control, the first &quot;[[world power]]&quot; to extend over the entire [[Fertile Crescent]] ([[Mesopotamia]], the [[Levant]] and [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]]).

== Chariots ==
{{main|Chariot}}
As states grew in size, speed of movement became crucial because central power could not hold if rebellions could not be suppressed rapidly. The first solution to this was the [[chariot]] which became used in the [[Middle East]] from around 1800 BC. First pulled by [[oxen]] and [[donkey]]s, they allowed rapid traversing of the relatively flat lands of the Middle East. The chariots were light enough that they could easily be floated across rivers. Improvements in the ability to train [[horse]]s soon allowed them to be used to pull chariots, possibly as early as 2100 BC,&lt;ref&gt;Kuznetsov, P.F., 2006, “The emergence of Bronze Age chariots in eastern Europe,” ''Antiquity'' 80:638-645&lt;/ref&gt; and their greater speed and power made chariots even more efficient. The major drawback of the use of chariots is similar to one of its advantages, the fact that it is light. The lack of armor causes it to be extremely vulnerable to spears, pikes, etc.

The power of the chariot as a device both of transportation and of battle became the central weapon of the peoples of the [[Ancient Near East]] in the [[2nd millennium BC]]. The typical chariot was worked by two men: one would be a bowman and fire at the enemy forces, while the other would control the vehicle. Over time, chariots carrying up to five warriors were developed. The effectiveness of these vehicles is still somewhat in doubt. In [[China]], [[Chariot (Ancient China)|chariot]]s became the central weapon of the [[Shang dynasty]], allowing them to unify a great area.

Although chariots have been compared to modern-day [[tanks]] in the role they played on the battlefield, i.e., shock attacks, this is disputed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lloyd|first=Alan B.|title=A Companion to Ancient Egyp|year=2010|publisher=Wiley Blackwell|isbn=978-1-4051-5598-4|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=RK2pLin2sPAC&amp;pg=PA438&amp;dq=egyptian+chariots+tanks&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=DAcxT83fJdTb8QOA4Zn8Bg&amp;ved=0CFcQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=%20%20chariots%20tanks&amp;f=false|page=438}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Drews|first=Robert|title=The end of the Bronze Age: changes in warfare and the catastrophe ca. 1200 B.C.|year=new edition 1995|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-0-691-02591-9|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=bFpK6aXEWN8C&amp;pg=PA121&amp;dq=egyptian+chariots+tanks&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=DAcxT83fJdTb8QOA4Zn8Bg&amp;ved=0CFEQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%20%20tank&amp;f=false|page=221}}&lt;/ref&gt; with scholars pointing out that chariots were vulnerable and fragile, required a level terrain while tanks are all-terrain vehicles, and thus not suitable for use in the way modern tanks have been used as a physical shock force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Littauer|first=M.A.|title=Wheeled vehicles and ridden animals in the ancient Near East|year=1979|publisher=Brill|isbn=978-90-04-05953-5|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=TcoUAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA98&amp;dq=ancient+near+east+chariots++tanks&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=PxQxT9elGcer8APCp4WPBw&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=ancient%20near%20east%20chariots%20%20tanks&amp;f=false|coauthors=J. H. Crouwel|page=98}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gaebel|first=Robert E.|title=Cavalry operations in the ancient Greek world|publisher=University of Oklahoma Press|isbn=978-0-8061-3444-4|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=6z6foPWT3_oC&amp;pg=PA40&amp;dq=ancient+near+east+chariots++tanks&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=PxQxT9elGcer8APCp4WPBw&amp;ved=0CE8Q6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=ancient%20near%20east%20chariots%20%20tanks&amp;f=false|page=40}}&lt;/ref&gt; The chief advantage of the chariot was the tactical mobility they provided to bowmen. Because tightly packed infantry were the formation of choice, in order for ancient generals to maintain [[Command and Control (Military)|command and control]] during the battle as well as for mutual protection, a force of chariots could stand off at long range and rain arrows down on the infantrymen's heads. Because of their speed, any attempts to charge the chariots could be easily evaded. If, on the other hand, an infantry unit spread out to minimize the damage from arrows, they would lose the benefit of mutual protection and the charioteers could easily overrun them.

From a tactical standpoint this put any force facing chariots on the horns of dilemma, making chariots indispensable to armies of the day. Chariots, however, were complicated pieces of hardware that required specialized craftsmen to maintain them. Such services, therefore, made chariots expensive to own. When chariots were owned by individuals within a society, it tended to give rise to a warrior class of specialists and a [[feudal system]] (an example of which can be seen in [[Homer]]'s [[The Iliad]]). Where chariots were publicly owned, they helped in the maintenance and establishment of a strong central government, e.g., the [[New Kingdom|New Egyptian Kingdom]]. Chariot usage peaked in the [[Battle of Kadesh]] in 1274 BC, which was probably the largest chariot battle ever fought, involving perhaps 5,000 chariots.

== Naval warfare ==
{{main|Naval warfare}}
The first dateable recorded sea battle occurred about 1210 BC: [[Suppiluliuma II]], king of the [[Hittites]], defeated a fleet from [[Cyprus]], and burned their ships at sea.

The [[Persian Wars]] were the first to feature large-scale naval operations: not only sophisticated fleet engagements with dozens of [[trireme]]s on each side, but combined land–sea operations. Ships in the ancient world could operate only on the relatively quiet waters of seas and rivers; the oceans were off limits. Navies were almost always used as auxiliaries to land forces, often essential to bringing them supplies. They would rarely strike out on their own. With only limited-range weapons, naval galleys would often attempt to ram their opponents with their reinforced bow to cause damage or sink the enemy warships which often caused the two ships to become joined together, and initiated a boarding battle. Only occasionally was a decisive naval battle fought, such as the [[Battle of Lade]] in which a Persian navy destroyed the Greek navy.
 
The [[Punic Wars]] led to innovation on the high seas. Rome previously had hardly touched naval warfare, being only concerned with the Italian peninsula, while Carthage was a trading civilization, and so had developed a large fleet. Only by examining the ruins of Carthaginian ships did the Romans come to build an effective navy. Moreover, they developed an implement called the [[Corvus (weapon)|corvus]] which was a way of dropping a gangplank onto an enemy ship, this gave the Romans an enormous advantage as their superiority in close-quarters combat could come into play as legionnaires boarded the Carthaginian ships and slaughtered the crews with ease.

== Tactics and weapons ==

=== Strategy ===
Ancient strategy focused broadly on the twin goals of convincing the enemy that continued war was more costly than submitting, and of making the most gain from war as possible. 

Forcing the enemy to submit generally consisted of defeating their army in the field. Once the enemy force was routed, the threat of siege, civilian deaths, and the like often forced the enemy to the bargaining table. However, this goal could be accomplished by other means. Burning enemy fields would force the choice of surrendering or fighting a [[pitched battle]]. Waiting an enemy out until their army had to disband due to the beginning of the harvest season or running out of payment for mercenaries presented an enemy with a similar choice. The exceptional conflicts of the ancient world were when these rules of warfare were violated. The Spartan and Athenian refusal to accept surrender after many years of war and near bankruptcy in the [[Peloponnesian War]] is one such exceptional example, as is the Roman refusal to surrender after the [[Battle of Cannae]].

A more personal goal in war was simple profit. This profit was often monetary, as was the case with the raiding culture of the Gallic tribes. But the profit could be political, as great leaders in war were often rewarded with government office after their success. These strategies often contradict modern common sense as they conflict with what would be best for the states involved in the war.

=== Tactics ===
{{Main|Military Tactics}}
Effective tactics varied greatly, depending on:
# The army's size
# Unit types
# Terrain
# The Weather
# Positional advantage
# Skill level
# Individual battle experience
# Individual morale
# Armament (quantity and quality)

=== Weapons ===
{{main|List of ancient weapons}}
Ancient weapons included the [[spear]], the [[atlatl]] with light javelin or similar projectile, the [[bow (weapon)|bow]] and arrow, the [[Sling (weapon)|sling]]; [[polearm]]s such as the [[spear]], [[falx]] and [[pilum|javelin]]; hand-to-hand weapons such as [[sword]]s, [[spear]]s, [[Club (weapon)|clubs]], [[Mace (club)|maces]], [[axe]]s, and [[knife|knives]]. [[Catapult]]s, [[siege tower]]s, and [[battering ram]]s were used during [[siege]]s.

=== Sieges ===
{{main|Siege}}
[[File:Ramesseum siege of Dapur.jpg|thumb|The Egyptian [[siege of Dapur]] in the 13th century BC, from [[Ramesseum]], [[Thebes, Egypt|Thebes]].]]

Siege warfare of the [[ancient Near East]] took place behind walls built of mud bricks, stone, wood or a combination of these materials depending on local availability. The earliest representations of siege warfare date to the [[Protodynastic Period of Egypt]], c.3000 BC, while the first siege equipment is known from Egyptian tomb reliefs of the 24th century BC showing wheeled siege ladders. [[Assyria]]n palace reliefs of the 9th to 7th centuries BC display sieges of several Near Eastern cities. Though a simple battering ram had come into use in the previous millennium, the Assyrians improved siege warfare. The most common practise of siege warfare was, however, to lay siege and wait for the surrender of the enemies inside. Due to the problem of logistics, long lasting sieges involving anything but a minor force could seldom be maintained.

== By culture ==

=== Ancient Near East ===

==== Mesopotamia ====
{{main|Military history of the Assyrian Empire|Military history of Iraq}}

==== Egypt ====
{{main|Military history of Egypt}}
Throughout most of its history, [[ancient Egypt]] was unified under one government. The main military concern for the nation was to keep enemies out. The arid plains and deserts surrounding Egypt were inhabited by nomadic tribes who occasionally tried to raid or settle in the fertile [[Nile]] river valley. The [[Egyptians]] built fortresses and outposts along the borders east and west of the Nile Delta, in the Eastern Desert, and in [[Nubia]] to the south. Small garrisons could prevent minor incursions, but if a large force was detected a message was sent for the main army corps. Most Egyptian cities lacked city walls and other defenses.

The first Egyptian soldiers carried a simple armament consisting of a spear with a copper spearhead and a large wooden shield covered by leather hides. A stone mace was also carried in the Archaic period, though later this weapon was probably only in ceremonial use, and was replaced with the bronze battle axe. The spearmen were supported by archers carrying a composite bow and arrows with arrowheads made of flint or copper. No armour was used during the 3rd and early 2nd Millennium BC. The major advance in weapons technology and warfare began around 1600 BC when the Egyptians fought and defeated the [[Hyksos]] people, who ruled Lower Egypt at the time. It was during this period the horse and chariot were introduced into Egypt. Other new technologies included the [[sickle sword]], body [[armour]] and improved bronze casting. In the [[New Kingdom]], the Egyptian military changed from levy troops into a firm organization of professional soldiers. Conquests of foreign territories, like Nubia, required a permanent force to be garrisoned abroad. The Egyptians were mostly used to slowly defeating a much weaker enemy, town by town, until beaten into submission. The preferred tactic was to subdue a weaker city or kingdom one at a time resulting in surrender of each fraction until complete domination was achieved. The encounter with other powerful Near Eastern kingdoms like [[Mitanni]], the [[Hittites]], and later the [[Assyria]]ns and [[Babylonians]], made it necessary for the Egyptians to conduct campaigns far from home. The next leap forwards came in the Late Period (712-332 BC), when mounted troops and weapons made of iron came into use. After the conquest by [[Alexander the Great]], Egypt was heavily Hellenized and the main military force became the infantry [[Phalanx formation|phalanx]]. The ancient Egyptians were not great innovators in weapons technology, and most weapons technology innovation came from Western Asia and the Greek world.

These soldiers were paid with a plot of land for the provision of their families. After fulfilment of their service, the veterans were allowed retirement to these estates. Generals could become quite influential at the court, but unlike other feudal states, the Egyptian military was completely controlled by the king. Foreign mercenaries were also recruited; first Nubians ([[Medjay]]), and later also Libyans and Sherdens in the New Kingdom. By the Persian period Greek mercenaries entered service into the armies of the rebellious pharaohs. The Jewish mercenaries at [[Elephantine]] served the Persian overlords of Egypt in the 5th century BC. Although,  they might also have served the Egyptian Pharaohs of the 6th century BC.

As far as had been seen from the royal propaganda of the time, the king or the crown prince personally headed the Egyptian troops into battle. The army could number tens of thousands of soldiers, so the smaller battalions consisting of 250 men, led by an officer, may have been the key of command. The tactics involved a massive strike by archery followed by an infantry and/or chariotry attacking the broken enemy lines. The enemies could,  however, try to surprise the large Egyptian force with ambushes and by blocking the road as the Egyptian campaign records informs us.

Within the [[Nile]] valley itself, ships and barges were important military elements. Ships were vital for providing supplies for the troops. The Nile river had no fords so barges had to be used for river crossings. Dominating the river often proved necessary for prosecuting sieges, like the Egyptian conquest of the [[Hyksos]] capital [[Avaris]]. Egypt had no navy to fight naval battles at sea before the Late Period. However, a battle involving ships took place at the Egyptian coast in the 12th century BC between [[Ramesses III]] and seafaring raiders.

==== Persia ====
{{main|Military history of Iran}}
Ancient Persia first emerged as a major military power under [[Cyrus the Great]]. Its form of warfare was based on massed infantry in light armor to pin the enemy force whilst cavalry dealt the killing blow. Cavalry was used in huge numbers but it is not known whether they were heavily armored or not. Most Greek sources claim the Persians wore no armor, but we do have an example from Herodotus which claims that an unhorsed cavalryman wore a gold cuirass under his red robes. Chariots were used in the early days but during the later days of the [[Persian Empire]] they were surpassed by horsemen. During the Persian Empire's height, they even possessed [[War elephants]] from North Africa and distant India. The elite of the Persian Army were the famous [[Persian Immortals]], a 10,000 strong unit of professional soldiers armed with a spear, a sword and a bow. Archers also formed a major component of the Persian Army.

Persian tactics primarily had four stages involving archers, infantry and cavalry. The archers, which wielded longbows, would fire waves of arrows before the battle, attempting to cut the enemy numbers down prior battle. The cavalry would then attempt to run into the enemy and sever communications between generals and soldiers. Infantry would then proceed to attack the disorientated soldiers, subsequently weakened from the previous attacks.

=== India ===
{{Main|Military history of India}}
During the [[Vedic civilization|Vedic period]] ([[floruit|fl.]] 3500-1500 BC), the ''[[Vedas]]'' and other associated texts contain references to warfare. The earliest allusions to a specific battle are those to the  [[Battle of the Ten Kings]] in [[Mandala 7]] of the [[Rigveda]].

The two great ancient epics of [[India]], ''[[Ramayana]]'' and ''[[Mahabharata]]'' (c. 1000-500 BC) are centered on conflicts and refer to military formations, theories of warfare and esoteric weaponry. [[Valmiki]]'s ''Ramayana'' describes [[Ayodhya]]'s military as defensive rather than aggressive. The city, it says, was strongly fortified and was surrounded by a deep moat. ''Ramayana'' describes Ayodhya in the following words: &quot;The city abounded in warriors undefeated in battle, fearless and chinskilled in the use of arms, resembling lions guarding their mountain caves&quot;. ''Mahabharata'' describes various military techniques, including the ''[[Chakravyuha]]''.

The world's first recorded military application of [[war elephant]]s is in the Mahabharatha.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Asian Elephant: Ecology and Management|author=R. Sukumar|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1993}}&lt;/ref&gt; From India, war elephants were taken to the [[Persian Empire]] where they were used in several campaigns. The Persian king [[Darius III]] employed about 50 Indian elephants in the [[Battle of Gaugamela]] (331 BC) fought against Alexander the Great. In the [[Battle of the Hydaspes River]], the Indian king [[King Porus|Porus]], who ruled in [[Punjab, Pakistan|Punjab]], with his smaller army of 200 war elephants, 2000 cavalry and 20,000 infantry, presented great difficulty for Alexander the Great's larger army of 4000 cavalry and 50,000 infantry, though Porus was eventually defeated. At this time, the [[Magadha|Magadha Empire]] further east in [[North India|northern]] and [[East India|eastern]] India had an army of 6000 war elephants, 80,000 cavalry, 200,000 infantry and 8000 armed chariots. Had Alexander the Great decided to continue his campaign in India, he may very well have been vanquished by the much more powerful, more able and more technologically advanced army, but it is more likely he would have adopted the weapons and techniques of such a foe to augment and improve his own forces and strategic aimss, as he had done throughout his career.

[[Chanakya]] (c. 350-275 BC) was a professor of [[political science]] at [[Takshashila University]], and later the [[Prime Minister]] of emperor [[Chandragupta Maurya]], the founder of the [[Maurya Empire]]. Chanakya wrote the ''[[Arthashastra]]'', which covered various topics on ancient Indian warfare in great detail, including various techniques and strategies relating to war. These included the earliest uses of [[espionage]] and [[assassination]]s. These techniques and strategies were employed by Chandragupta Maurya, who was a student of Chanakya, and later by [[Ashoka|Ashoka the Great]] (304-232 BC).

Chandragupta Maurya conquered the Magadha Empire and expanded to all of northern India, establishing the Maurya Empire, which extended from the [[Arabian Sea]] to the [[Bay of Bengal]]. In 305 BC, Chandragupta defeated [[Seleucus I Nicator]], who ruled the [[Seleucid Empire]] and controlled most of the territories conquered by Alexander the Great. Seleucus eventually lost his territories in Southern Asia, including southern [[Afghanistan]], to Chandragupta. Seleucus exchanged territory west of the Indus for 500 war elephants and offered his daughter to Chandragupta. In this matrimonial alliance the enmity turned into friendship, and Seleucus' dispatched an ambassador, [[Megasthenes]], to the Mauryan court at [[Pataliputra]]. As a result of this treaty, the Maurya Empire was recognized as a great power by the [[Hellenistic civilization|Hellenistic World]], and the kings of [[Egypt]] and [[Syria]] sent their own ambassadors to his court. According to Megasthenes, Chandragupta Maurya built an army consisting of 30,000 cavalry, 9000 war elephants, and 600,000 infantry, which was the largest army known in the ancient world. Ashoka the Great went on to expand the Maurya Empire to almost all of [[South Asia]], along with much of Afghanistan and parts of [[Iran|Persia]]. Ashoka eventually gave up on warfare after converting to [[Buddhism]].

=== China ===
{{main|Military history of China (pre-1911)}}
Ancient China during the [[Shang Dynasty]] was a Bronze Age society based on [[chariot]] armies. Archaeological study of Shang sites at [[Anyang]] have revealed extensive examples of chariots and bronze weapons. The overthrow of the Shang by the [[Zhou Dynasty|Zhou]] saw the creation of a feudal social order, resting militarily on a class of aristocratic chariot warriors (士). 

In the [[Spring and Autumn Period]], warfare increased exponentially. ''Zuo zhuan'' describes the wars and battles among the feudal lords during the period. Warfare continued to be stylised and ceremonial even as it grew more violent and decisive. The concept of military hegemon (霸) and his &quot;way of force&quot; (霸道) came to dominate Chinese society. Sun Tzu created a book that still applies to today's modern armies.

Formations of the army can be clearly seen from the Terracotta Army of [[Qin Shi Huang]], the first Emperor in the history of China to be successful in unification of different warring states. Light infantry acting as shock troops lead the army, followed by heavy infantry as the main body of the army. Wide usage of cavalry and chariots behind the heavy infantry also gave the Qin army an edge in battles against the other warring states. 

Warfare became more intense, ruthless and much more decisive during the [[Warring States Period]], in which great social and political change was accompanied by the end of the system of chariot warfare and the adoption of mass infantry armies. Cavalry was also introduced from the northern frontier, despite the cultural challenge it posed for robe-wearing Chinese men. Chinese river valley civilizations would adopt nomadic &quot;[[pants]]&quot; for their cavalry units and soldiers.

=== Iron Age Europe ===

==== Ancient Greece ====
{{main|Military history of Greece|Ancient Greek warfare}}
Infantry did almost all of the fighting in Greek battles. The Greeks did not have any notable cavalry tradition except the Thessalians.&lt;ref&gt;Cavalry Operations in the Ancient Greek World by Robert E. Gaebel,ISBN 0-8061-3444-5,2004,Page 59,&quot;... It is perhaps unlikely that by 500 cavalry played an important military role anywhere south of Thessaly, where cavalry traditionally dominated, but there can be little doubt that there were aristocratic cavalrymen on the battlefields in some ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hoplites]], Greek infantry, fought with a long spear and a large shield, the [[hoplon]] also called [[aspis]]. Light infantry (psiloi) [[peltasts]], served as skirmishers.

Despite the fact that most Greek cities were well fortified (with the notable exception of [[Sparta]]) and Greek siege technology was not up to the task of breaching these fortifications by force, most land battles were pitched ones fought on flat-open ground. This was because of the limited period of service Greek soldiers could offer before they needed to return to their farms; hence, a decisive battle was needed to settle matters at hand. To draw out a city's defenders, its fields would be threatened with destruction, threatening the defenders with starvation in the winter if they did not surrender or accept battle. 

This pattern of warfare was broken during the [[Peloponnesian War]], when [[Athens]]' command of the sea allowed the city to ignore the destruction of the Athenian crops by [[Sparta]] and her allies by shipping grain into the city from the [[Crimea]]. This led to a warfare style in which both sides were forced to engage in repeated raids over several years without reaching a settlement. It also made sea battle a vital part of warfare. Greek naval battles were fought between [[triremes]]—long  and speedy rowing ships which engaged the enemy by ramming and boarding actions.

==== Hellenistic Era ====
{{Main|Ancient Macedonian army|Hellenistic armies}}
During the time of [[Philip II of Macedon]] and [[Alexander the Great]], the [[Ancient Macedonians|Macedonians]] were regarded as the most complete well co-ordinated [[military]] force in the known world. Although they are best known for the achievements of [[Alexander the Great]], his father [[Philip II of Macedon]] created and designed the fighting force Alexander used in his conquests.Before this time and for centuries their military prowess was nowhere near that the [[sarissa]] [[Phalanx formation|phalanx]] offered.

However prior to the improvements made by [[Philip II of Macedon]] army fought in the traditional manner of the Greeks that of the [[hoplite]] [[Phalanx formation|phalanx]].

Philip provided his [[Macedon]]ian soldiers in the [[Phalanx formation|phalanx]] with [[sarissa]], a [[spear]] which was 4–6 meters in length. The sarissa, when held upright by the rear [[Rank (formation)|rank]]s of the phalanx (there were usually eight ranks), helped hide maneuvers behind the phalanx from the view of the enemy. When held horizontal by the front ranks of the phalanx, enemies could be run through from far away.The [[hoplite]] type troops were not abandoned,&lt;ref&gt;Macedonian Warrior Alexander's elite infantryman,page 41,ISBN 978-1-84176-950-9,2006&lt;/ref&gt; but were no longer the core of the army.

In 358 BC he met the [[Illyrians]] in battle with his reorganized Macedonian phalanx, and utterly defeated them. The Illyrians fled in panic, leaving the majority of their 9,000-strong army dead. The [[Ancient Macedonian military|Macedonian army]] invaded [[Illyria]] and conquered the southern Illyrian tribes.

After the defeat of the [[Illyrians]], [[Macedon]]'s policy became increasingly aggressive. [[Paionia|Paeonia]] was already forcefully integrated into [[Macedon]] under [[Philip II of Macedon|Philip]]'s rule. In 357 BC Philip broke the treaty with [[Athens]] and attacked [[Amphipolis]] which promised to surrender to the [[Athenians]] in exchange for the fortified town of [[Pydna]], a promise he didn't keep. The city fell back in the hands of [[Macedon]]ia after an intense [[siege]]. Then he secured possession over the [[Gold mining|gold mines]] of nearby [[Mount Pangaeus]], which would enable him to finance his future wars. 

In 356 the Macedonian army advanced further eastward and captured the town of [[Crenides]] (near modern [[Drama, Greece|Drama]]) which was in the hands of the [[Thracians]], and which Philip renamed after himself to [[Philippi]]. The Macedonian eastern border with [[Thrace]] was now secured at the river [[Nestus]] (Mesta).

[[Philip II of Macedon|Philip]] next marched against his southern enemies. In [[Thessaly]] he defeated his enemies and by 352, he was firmly in control of this region. The Macedonian [[army]] advanced as far as the pass of [[Thermopylae]] which divides [[Greece]] in two parts, but it did not attempt to take it because it was strongly guarded by a joint force of [[Athenians]], [[Sparta]]ns, and [[Achaea (ancient region)|Achaeans]].

Having secured the bordering regions of [[Macedon]], [[Philip II of Macedon|Philip]] assembled a large Macedonian army and marched deep into Thrace for a long conquering campaign. By 339 after defeating the Thracians in series of battles, most of [[Thrace]] was firmly in Macedonian hands save the most eastern [[Greece|Greek]] coastal cities of [[Byzantium]] and [[Perinthus]] who successfully withstood the long and difficult sieges. But both [[Byzantium]] and [[Perinthus]] would have surely fell had it not been for the help they received from the various Greek city-states, and the [[Persian Empire|Persian]] king himself, who now viewed the rise of [[Macedon]]ia and its eastern expansion with concern. Ironically, the Greeks invited and sided with the [[Persian people|Persians]] against the Macedonians, although Persia had been the nation hated the most by [[Greece]] for more than a century. The memory of the [[Persian Empire|Persian]] invasion of [[Greece]] some 150 years ago was still alive, but the current politics for the Macedonians had put it aside.

Much greater would be the conquests of his son, [[Alexander the Great]], who would add to the phalanx a powerful [[cavalry]],  led by his elite [[Companion Cavalry|Companions]], and flexible, innovative formations and tactics.  He advanced [[Greece|Greek]] style of combat, and was able to muster large bodies of men for long periods of time for his campaigns against [[Persian Empire|Persia]].

==== Roman Empire ====
{{main|Military History of Rome|Roman infantry tactics, strategy and battle formations}}
The [[Roman army]] was the world's first professional army. It had its origins in the citizen army of the [[Roman Republic|Republic]], which was staffed by citizens serving mandatory duty for Rome. The reforms of [[Gaius Marius|Marius]] around 100 BC turned the army into a professional structure, still largely filled by citizens, but citizens who served continuously for 20 years before being discharged.

The Romans were also noted for making use of auxiliary troops, non-Romans who served with the legions and filled roles that the traditional Roman military could not fill effectively, such as light skirmish troops and heavy cavalry. Later in the Empire, these auxiliary troops, along with foreign mercenaries, became the core of the Roman military. By the late Empire, tribes such as the [[Visigoths]] were bribed to serve as mercenaries.

The Roman navy was traditionally considered less important, although it remained vital for the transportation of supplies and troops, also during the great purge of pirates from the Mediterranean sea by Pompey the Great in the 1st century BC. Most of Rome's battles occurred on land, especially when the Empire was at its height and all the land around the [[Mediterranean]] was controlled by Rome.

But there were notable exceptions. The [[First Punic War]], a pivotal war between Rome and Carthage in the 3rd century BC, was largely a naval conflict. And the naval [[Battle of Actium]] established the Roman empire under [[Augustus]].

==== Balkans ====
{{Main|Illyrian warfare}}
[[File:IllyrianwarriorsMaybeScordisci.gif|thumb|[[Scordisci]] warriors of the 2nd century BC]]
The Illyrian king [[Bardyllis]] turned part of south [[Illyria]] into a formidable local power in the 4th century BC. He managed to become king of the [[Dardanians (Balkans)|Dardanians]]&lt;ref&gt;Borza, Eugene N. In the Shadow of Olympus: The Emergence of Macedon, 1990, p. 180, ISBN 0-691-00880-9. Amyntas had barely seized the throne in 394/3 when he found his kingdom under attack by a powerful Illyrian force, probably led by Bardylis, king of the Dardanii.&lt;/ref&gt; and include other tribes under his rule. However their power was weakened by bitter rivalries and jealousy.The army was composed by [[peltast]]s with a variety of weapons. 
 {{Main|Thracian warfare}}
The [[Thracians]] fought as [[peltast]]s using [[javelins]] and crescent or round wicker shields.Missile weapons were favored but close combat weaponry was carried by the Thracians as well.These close combat weapons varied from the dreaded [[Rhomphaia]] &amp; [[Falx]]
to [[spear]]s and swords.Thracians shunned armor and greaves and fought as light as possible favoring mobility above all other traits and had excellent horsemen.&lt;ref&gt;The Cambridge Ancient History, Volume 3, Part 2: The Assyrian and Babylonian Empires and Other States of the Near East, from the Eighth to the Sixth Centuries BC (Hardcover)
by John Boardman (Editor), I. E. S. Edwards (Editor), E. Sollberger (Editor), N. G. L. Hammond (Editor),1992,ISBN 0-521-22717-8,page XVI,&quot;Very different from the Phoenicians were the Scythians and the Thracians who had no interest or skill in seafaring but excelled in raiding and horsemanship&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Main|Dacian warfare}}
The [[Dacians|Dacian]] tribes, located on modern-day [[Romania]] and [[Moldova]] were part of the greater [[Thracians|Thracian]] family of peoples. They established a highly [[militarized]] society and, during the periods when the tribes were united under one [[Monarch|king]] (82-44 BC, 86-106) posed a major threat to the [[Roman province]]s of Lower [[Danube]]. Dacia was conquered and transformed into a Roman province in 106 after a long, hard [[Trajan's Dacian Wars|war]].

==== Celtic ====
{{main|Celtic warfare}}
{{further|Gallic Wars|Gaelic warfare}}

[[Endemic warfare|Tribal warfare]] appears to have been a regular feature of [[Celts|Celtic societies]]. While epic literature depicts this as more of a sport focused on raids and hunting rather than organised territorial conquest, the historical record is more of tribes using warfare to exert political control and harass rivals, for economic advantage, and in some instances to conquer territory.

The Celts were described by classical writers such as  [[Strabo]], [[Livy]], [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], and [[Florus]] as fighting like &quot;wild beasts&quot;, and as hordes. [[Dionysius of Halicarnassus|Dionysius]] said that their &quot;manner of fighting, being in large measure that of wild beasts and frenzied, was an erratic procedure, quite lacking in [[military science]]. Thus, at one moment they would raise their swords aloft and smite after the manner of [[Boar|wild boars]], throwing the whole weight of their bodies into the blow like hewers of wood or men digging with mattocks, and again they would deliver crosswise blows aimed at no target, as if they intended to cut to pieces the entire bodies of their adversaries, protective armour and all&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dionysius of Halicarnassus,  ''Roman Antiquities''
p259 Excerpts from Book XIV&lt;/ref&gt; Such descriptions have been challenged by contemporary historians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book 
|author=Ellis, Peter Berresford
|title= ''The Celts: A History''
|pages= 60–3 
|publisher=Caroll &amp; Graf 
|year= 1998
|isbn= 0-7867-1211-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Germanic ====
[[File:Praying Germanic man 1890.jpg|right|thumb|Roman bronze figurine depicting a Germanic man adorned with a [[Suebian knot]] engaged in prayer. (Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris)]]
{{further|Germanic Wars|Gothic warfare|Anglo-Saxon warfare|Migration period spear}}
Historical records of the [[Germanic peoples|Germanic tribes]] in [[Germania]] east of the [[Rhine]] and west of the [[Danube]] do not begin until quite late in the ancient period, so only the period after 100 BC can be examined. What is clear is that the Germanic idea of warfare was quite different from the pitched battles fought by [[Rome]] and [[Greece]]. Instead the Germanic tribes focused on raids.

The purpose of these was generally not to gain territory, but rather to capture resources and secure prestige. These raids were conducted by [[irregular military|irregular troops]], often formed along family or village lines, in groups of 10 to about 1,000. Leaders of unusual personal magnetism could gather more soldiers for longer periods, but there was no systematic method of gathering and training men, so the death of a charismatic leader could mean the destruction of an army. Armies also often consisted of more than 50 percent noncombatants, as displaced people would travel with large groups of soldiers, the elderly, women, and children.

Large bodies of troops, while figuring prominently in the history books, were the exception rather than the rule of ancient warfare. Thus a typical [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] force might consist of 100 men with the sole goal of raiding a nearby Germanic or foreign village. According to [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] sources, when the [[Germanic Tribes]] did fight pitched battles, the infantry often adopted wedge formations, each wedge being led by a clan head.

Though often defeated by the [[Roman Empire|Romans]], the Germanic tribes were remembered in Roman records as fierce combatants, whose main downfall was that they failed to unite successfully into one fighting force, under one [[Command (military formation)|command]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tacitus&quot;&gt;Tacitus, The Annals [[s:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 2#45|2.45]]&lt;/ref&gt;  After the three [[Roman legion]]s were ambushed and destroyed by an alliance of Germanic tribes headed by [[Arminius]] at the [[Battle of the Teutoburg Forest]] in 9 AD, the Roman Empire made no further concentrated attempts at conquering Germania beyond the Rhine. Prolonged warfare against the Romans accustomed the Germanic tribes to improved tactics such as the use of reserves, military discipline and centralised command.&lt;ref &lt;ref name=&quot;Tacitus&quot;/&gt; Germanic tribes would eventually overwhelm and conquer the ancient world, giving rise to modern Europe and medieval warfare. For an analysis of Germanic tactics versus the Roman empire see [[Roman infantry tactics|tactical problems in facing the Gauls and the Germanic tribes]]

=== Japanese ===
{{main|Military history of Japan}}
Horses and bows were very important in Japan, and were used in warfare from very early times, as shown in statues and artifacts found in tombs of early chieftains. Samurai eventually became very skilled in using the horse. Because their main weapon at this time was the bow and arrow, early samurai exploits were spoken of in Japanese war tales as the “Way of the Horse and Bow.” Horse and bow combined was a battlefield advantage to the early samurai. A bunch of arrows made of mainly wood with poison tipped points were worn on a warrior’s right side so he could quickly take out an arrow and fire it as he continued to gallop on his horse. 

Although they weren’t as important as the bow, swords of various sizes and types were also part of a samurai’s armory in the early days. They were mostly for fighting close up with an enemy. Many different kinds of spears were used also. The naginata, one of them, was a curved blade fixed to the end of a pole several feet long. This was known as a 'woman’s spear' because samurai girls were taught to use it from an early age. A device called the kumade that looks like a long-handled garden rake was used to grab the clothing or helmet of enemy horsemen and to take them off their horse. 

Common samurai archers had armor made of lamellae pieces laced together with colorful cords. The lightweight armor allowed for greater freedom of movement and was light, so it was easier on the horse, which could even move faster. The knights of Europe though, wore a lot of armor, and eventually they wore an entire ‘metal’ suit, which gave them a lot of trouble in movement, and was much heavier than what the samurai wore-plus, it is therefore clear that heavy armor had its advantages and disadvantages.

The early [[Yamato period]] had seen a continual engagement in the Korean Peninsula until Japan finally withdrew, along with the remaining forces of the [[Baekje]] Kingdom. Several battles occurred in these periods as the [[Emperor of Japan|Emperor's]] succession gained importance. By the [[Nara period]], [[Honshū]] was completely under the control of the [[Yamato (people)|Yamato]] clan. Near the end of the [[Heian period]], [[samurai]] became a powerful political force, thus starting the feudal period.

== Important ancient wars ==
* [[Ionian Revolt]]
:The Ionian Revolt was a series of conflicts between the [[Ionia]] and the [[Persian Empire]] that began 499 BC and lasted until 493 BC. The revolt begins because of Athens offensive attack to city of Sardis and massacring the Persian citizens by burning down the city. This revolt had a major role in starting the Greco-Persian wars.
* [[Greco-Persian Wars]]
:The Greco-Persian Wars were a series of conflicts between the [[Ancient Greece|Greek City-States]] and the [[Persian Empire]] that began around 500 BC and lasted until 448 BC.
* [[Peloponnesian War]]
:The Peloponnesian War was begun in 431 BC between the [[Athenian Empire]] and the [[Peloponnesian League]] which included [[Sparta]] and [[Corinth, Greece|Corinth]]. The war was documented by [[Thucydides]], an Athenian general, in his work ''[[The History of The Peloponnesian War]]''. The war lasted 27 years, with a brief truce in the middle.
* [[Punic Wars]]
:The Punic Wars were a series of three wars fought between [[Rome]] and the city of [[Carthage]] (a [[Phoenicia]]n descendant). They are known as the &quot;Punic&quot; Wars because Rome's name for Carthaginians was ''Punici'' (older ''Poeni'', due to their Phoenician ancestry).
#The [[First Punic War]] was primarily a naval war fought between 264 BC and 241 BC.
#The [[Second Punic War]] is famous for [[Hannibal]]'s crossing of the [[Alps]] and was fought between 218 BC and 202 BC.
#The [[Third Punic War]] resulted in the destruction of Carthage and was fought between 149 BC and 146 BC.

* [[Kalinga War]] ([[265 BC|265]]-264 BC) was a war fought between the [[Mauryan Empire]] under [[Ashoka the Great]] and the state of [[Kalinga (India)|Kalinga]], a feudal [[republic]] located on the coast of the present-day [[India]]n state of [[Orissa]]. Ashoka's response to the Kalinga War is recorded in the [[Edicts of Ashoka]]. According to some of these (Rock Edict XIII and Minor Rock Edict I), the Kalinga War prompted Ashoka, already a non-engaged Buddhist, to devote the rest of his life to [[Ahimsa]] (non-violence) and to Dhamma-Vijaya (victory through [[Dhamma]]).

* [[Roman-Persian Wars]]
:The Roman-Persian Wars were a series of conflicts between the [[Roman Empire]] and [[Persian Empire]] that began between the [[Roman Republic]] and [[Parthia]] in 92 BC and lasted until the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]] and [[Sassanid Empire]] in 627 AD. This series of conflicts became the longest war between two entities in all of history, until it eventually came to an end with the [[Arab]] [[Muslim conquests]] of the 7th century.

== Important ancient battles ==
{{columns-list|3|
* [[Battle of Megiddo (15th century BC)|Battle of Megiddo]], c. 1457 BC
* [[Battle of the Ten Kings]], c. [[14th century BC|1400 BC]]
* [[Battle of Kadesh]], 1274 BC
* [[Battle of Muye]], 1046 BC
* [[Battle of Megiddo (609 BC)|Battle of Megiddo]], 609 BC
* [[Battle of Carchemish]], 605 BC
* [[Battle of Pteria]], 547 BC
* [[Battle of Thymbra]], 546 BC
* [[Battle of Lade]], 546 BC
* [[Battle of Marathon]], 490 BC
* [[Battle of Thermopylae]], 480 BC
* [[Battle of Artemisium]], 480 BC
* [[Battle of Salamis]], 480 BC
* [[Battle of Plataea]], 479 BC
* [[Battle of Mycale]], 479 BC
* [[Battle of Cunaxa]], 401 BC
* [[Battle of the Allia]], 387 BC
* [[Battle of Chaeronea (338 BC)|Battle of Chaeronea]], 338 BC
* [[Battle of Issus]], 333 BC
* [[Battle of Gaugamela]], 331 BC
* [[Battle of the Persian Gate]], 330 BC
* [[Battle of the Hydaspes River]], 326 BC
* [[Battle of Paraitacene]], 317 BC
* [[Battle of Gabiene]], 316 BC
* [[Battle of Ipsus]], 301 BC
* [[Battle of Corupedium]], 281 BC
* [[Siege of Saguntum]], 218 BC
* [[Battle of Ticinus]], 218 BC
* [[Battle of the Trebia]], 218 BC
* [[Battle of Lake Trasimene]], 217 BC
* [[Battle of Ager Falernus]], 217 BC
* [[Battle of Raphia]], 217 BC
* [[Battle of Geronium]], 217 BC
* [[Battle of Cannae]], 216 BC
* [[Battle of the Metaurus]], 207 BC
* [[Battle of Jingxing|Battle of Tao River]], 204 BC
* [[Battle of Wei River]], 204 BC
* [[Battle of Gaixia]], 202 BC
* [[Battle of Zama]], 202 BC
* [[Battle of Pydna]], 168 BC
* [[Battle of Cynoscephalae]], 197 BC
* [[Battle of Magnesia]], 190 BC
* [[Battle of Aquae Sextiae]], 102 BC
* [[Battle of Vercellae]], 101 BC
* [[Battle of Tigranocerta]], 69 BC
* [[Battle of Vosges (58 BC)|Battle of Vosges]], 58 BC
* [[Battle of Carrhae]], 53 BC
* [[Battle of Gergovia]], 52 BC
* [[Battle of Alesia]], 52 BC
* [[Battle of Pharsalus]], 48 BC
* [[Battle of Munda]], 45 BC
* [[Battle of Actium]], 31 BC
* [[Battle of the Teutoburg Forest]], [[9|AD 9]]
* [[Battle of Ikh Bayan]], 89
* [[Battle of Red Cliffs]], 208
* [[Battle of Edessa]], 259
* [[Battle of Adrianople]], 378
* [[Battle of Fei River]], 383
* [[Battle of Chalons]], 451
* [[Sack of Rome (455)|Sack of Rome]], 455
}}

== Unit types ==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Infantry]]
** [[Archery]]
** [[Slingman]]
** [[Peltast]]
** [[Hoplite]]
** [[Persian Immortals|Persian Immortal]]
** [[Phalanx formation|Phalanx]]
*** [[Macedonian phalanx]]
** [[Roman legion|Legion]]
*** [[Legionary]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Cavalry]]
** [[Cataphract]]
** [[Clibanarii]]
** [[Horse archer]]
** [[Chariot]]
** [[War elephant]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Artillery]] and [[siege engines]]
** [[Catapult]]
** [[Onager (siege weapon)|Onager]]
** [[Ballista]]
** [[Scorpio (Dart-thrower)|Scorpio]]
** [[Siege tower]]
** [[Battering ram]]
{{col-end}}

== See also ==
* [[Ancient Mediterranean piracy]]
* [[Horses in warfare]]
* [[Women in warfare]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Literature ==
#Anglim, Simon, and Phyllis G. Jestice. ''Fighting Techniques of the Ancient World (3000 B.C. to 500 A.D.): Equipment, Combat Skills, and Tactics''. Dunne Books: 2003. ISBN 0-312-30932-5.
#Bradford, Alfred S. ''With Arrow, Sword, and Spear: A History of Warfare in the Ancient World.'' Praeger Publishing: 2001. ISBN 0-275-95259-2.
#Connolly, Peter. ''Greece and Rome at War''. Greenhill Books: 1998. ISBN 1-85367-303-X.
#Gabriel, Richard A. ''The Great Armies of Antiquity''. Praeger Publishing: 2002. ISBN 0-275-97809-5
#Gichon, Mordechai, and Chaim Herzog. ''Battles of the Bible''. Greenhill Books: 2002. ISBN 1-85367-477-X.
#Goldsworthy, Adrian. ''The Complete Roman Army''. Thames &amp; Hudson: 2003. ISBN 0-500-05124-0.
#Keegan, John. ''A History of Warfare''. Vintage: 1993. ISBN 0-679-73082-6.
#Kern, Paul Bentley. ''Ancient Siege Warfare''. Indiana University Press: 1999. ISBN 0-253-33546-9.
#Leblanc, Steven A. ''Prehistoric Warfare in the American Southwest''. University of Utah Press: 1999. ISBN 0-87480-581-3.
#Mayor, Adrienne. ''Greek Fire, Poison Arrows &amp; Scorpion Bombs: Biological and Chemical Warfare in the Ancient World''. Overlook Press: 2003. ISBN 1-58567-348-X.
#Peers, Chris J. ''Ancient Chinese Armies 1500–200 BC''. [[Osprey Publishing]]: 1990. ISBN 0-85045-942-7.
#Peers, Chris J., and Michael Perry. ''Imperial Chinese Armies : 200 BC–589 AD''. [[Osprey Publishing]]: 1995. ISBN 1-85532-514-4.
#Sabin, Philip. ''Lost Battles: Reconstructing The Great Clashes of the Ancient World''. [[Hambledon Continuum]]: 2007. ISBN 1-84725-187-0.
#Van Creveld, Martin. &quot;Technology and War: From 2000 B.C. to the Present&quot;. Free Press: 1991. ISBN 0-02-933153-6.
#Warry, John Gibson, and John Warry. ''Warfare in the Classical World: An Illustrated Encyclopedia of Weapons, Warriors and Warfare in the Ancient Civilisations of Greece and Rome''. University of Oklahoma Press: 1999.

== External links ==
* [http://www.hinduwisdom.info/War_in_Ancient_India.htm War in Ancient India]
* [http://www.redstoneprojects.com/trebuchetstore/sling.html Evolution of Sling Weapons]
* [http://bsa.biblio.univ-lille3.fr/polemos.htm War in ancient Greece : a bibliography]
* [http://www.worldmuseumofman.org Ancient and Prehistoric Weapons and Tools]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ancient Warfare}}
[[Category:Warfare of the Ancient era]]

[[cs:Starověké vojenství]]
[[it:Guerra antica]]
[[no:Krigføring i oldtiden]]
[[pt:Guerra e armamento da Antiguidade]]
[[ro:Războiul în Antichitate]]
[[ru:Древние войны]]
[[tr:Antik çağda savaş]]
[[vi:Chiến tranh thời cổ đại]]</text>
      <sha1>fw99lwxe374dk113azbb7usjmd3kazm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
