<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Baroque music</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23275904</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521394482</id>
      <parentid>520874248</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T19:02:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>74.130.134.232</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* After 1760 */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44671">{{more footnotes|date=August 2012}}
[[File:Ceskystage.jpg|thumb|265px|Private baroque theatre in [[Český Krumlov]].]]
[[File:Pannini, Giovanni Paolo_-_Musical Fête_-_1747.png|thumb|265px|[[Teatro Argentina]] ([[Giovanni Paolo Panini|Panini]], 1747, [[Musée du Louvre]]).]]

'''Baroque music''' is the style of [[Classical music|Western music]] extending approximately from [[Dates of classical music eras|1600 to 1750]].{{sfn|Palisca|2001|loc=“Baroque”}} This era follows the [[Renaissance music|Renaissance]] and was followed in turn by the [[Classical period (music)|Classical era]]. The word &quot;[[baroque]]&quot; comes from the Portuguese word ''barroco'', meaning &quot;misshapen pearl&quot;{{sfn|Mackay|Romanec|2007}}, a negative description of the ornate and heavily ornamented music of this period; later, the name came to be applied also to its [[baroque architecture|architecture]].

Baroque music forms a major portion of the classical music canon, being widely studied, performed, and listened to. Composers of the baroque era include [[Johann Sebastian Bach]], [[George Frideric Handel]], [[Alessandro Scarlatti]], [[Antonio Vivaldi]], [[Georg Philipp Telemann]], [[Jean-Baptiste Lully]], [[Arcangelo Corelli]], [[François Couperin]], [[Denis Gaultier]], [[Claudio Monteverdi]], [[Jean-Philippe Rameau]] and [[Henry Purcell]].

The baroque period saw the creation of [[functional tonality]]. During the period, composers and performers used more elaborate musical ornamentation, made changes in musical notation, and developed new instrumental playing techniques. Baroque music expanded the size, range, and complexity of instrumental performance, and also established [[opera]] as a musical genre. Many musical terms and concepts from this era are still in use today.

== Etymology ==

{{History of European art music}}

=== History of European art music ===

The term &quot;Baroque&quot; is generally used by music historians to describe a broad range of styles from a wide geographic region, mostly in Europe, composed over a period of approximately 150 years.{{sfn|Palisca|2001|loc=“Baroque”}}

Although it was long thought that the word as a critical term was first applied to architecture, in fact it appears earlier in reference to music, in an anonymous, satirical review of the première in October 1733 of Rameau’s ''Hippolyte et Aricie,'' printed in the ''Mercure de France'' in May 1734. The critic implied that the novelty in this opera was &quot;du barocque,&quot; complaining that the music lacked coherent melody, was filled with unremitting dissonances, constantly changed key and meter, and speedily ran through every compositional device.{{sfn|Palisca|2001|loc=“Baroque”}}

The systematic application by historians of the term &quot;baroque&quot; to music of this period is a relatively recent development. In 1919, [[Curt Sachs]] became the first to apply the five characteristics of [[Heinrich Wölfflin]]’s theory of the Baroque systematically to music.{{sfn|Sachs|1919|pp=7–15}} In English the term acquired currency only in the 1940s, in the writings of Lang and Bukofzer.{{sfn|Palisca|2001|loc=“Baroque”}}

As late as 1960 there was still considerable dispute in academic circles, particularly in France and Britain, whether it was meaningful to lump together music as diverse as that of [[Jacopo Peri]], [[Domenico Scarlatti]], and [[J.S. Bach]] under a single rubric. Nevertheless, the term has become widely used and accepted for this broad range of music.{{sfn|Palisca|2001|loc=“Baroque”}} It may be helpful to distinguish the Baroque from both the preceding (Renaissance) and following ([[Classical music|Classical]]) periods of musical history.

== History ==
=== Early baroque music (1600–1654) ===

{{details|Transition from Renaissance to Baroque in instrumental music}}
[[File:Jacopo Peri 1.jpg|200px|thumb|Jacopo Peri]]

The [[Florentine Camerata]] was a group of humanists, musicians, poets and intellectuals in late Renaissance Florence who gathered under the patronage of Count [[Giovanni de' Bardi]] to discuss and guide trends in the arts, especially music and drama. In reference to music, their ideals were based on their perception of Classical (especially [[Ancient Greece|ancient Greek]]) musical drama, in which discourse and oration was viewed with much importance.{{sfn|Nuti|2007|p=14}} As such, they rejected the use by their contemporaries of polyphony and instrumental music, and discussed such ancient Greek music devices as [[monody]], which consisted of a solo singing accompanied by a kithara.{{sfn|Wallechinsky|2007|p=445}} The early realizations of these ideas, including [[Jacopo Peri]]'s ''[[Dafne]]'' and ''[[Euridice (Peri)|L'Euridice]]'', marked the beginning of opera,{{sfn|Chua|2001|p=26}} which in turn can be considered to have marked the catalyst of Baroque music.{{sfn|Wainwright|Holman|2005|p=4}}

Concerning music theory, the more widespread use of [[figured bass]] (also known as &quot;thorough bass&quot;) represents the developing importance of [[harmony]] as the linear underpinnings of polyphony.{{sfn|Clarke|1898|pp=147–148}}
Harmony is the end result of [[counterpoint]], and figured bass is a visual representation of those harmonies commonly employed in musical performance.{{sfn|Haagmans|1916|p=vi}} Composers began concerning themselves with harmonic progressions,{{sfn|York|1909|p=109}} and also employed the [[tritone]], perceived as an unstable interval,{{sfn|Donington|1974|p=156}} to create dissonance. Investment in harmony had also existed among certain composers in the Renaissance, notably [[Carlo Gesualdo]];{{sfn|Watkins|1991|p=103}} However, the use of harmony directed towards tonality, rather than modality, marks the shift from the Renaissance into the Baroque period.{{sfn|Norton|1984|p=24}} This led to the idea that chords, rather than notes, could provide a sense of closure, which is one of the fundamental ideas of what came to be known as [[tonality]].

[[File:Claudio Monteverdi.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Claudio Monteverdi in 1640 by [[Bernardo Strozzi]]]]

Italy formed one of the cornerstones of the new style, as the papacy—besieged by [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]] but with coffers fattened by the immense revenues flowing in from [[Habsburg]] conquest—searched for artistic means to promote faith in the Roman Catholic Church. One of the most important musical centers was [[Venice]], which had both secular and sacred patronage available.{{Or|date=March 2012}}

[[Giovanni Gabrieli]] became one of the important transitional figures in the emergence of the new style, although his work is largely considered to be in the &quot;High Renaissance&quot; manner. However, his innovations were foundational to the new style. Among these are instrumentation (labeling instruments specifically for specific tasks) and the use of dynamics.{{Or|date=March 2012}}

The demands of religion were also to make the text of sacred works clearer, and hence there was pressure to move away from the densely layered polyphony of the Renaissance, to lines which put the words front and center, or had a more limited range of imitation. This created the demand for a more intricate weaving of the vocal line against backdrop, or homophony.{{Or|date=March 2012}}

Claudio Monteverdi became the most visible of a generation of composers who felt that there was a secular means to this &quot;modern&quot; approach to harmony and text, and in 1607 his opera ''[[L'Orfeo]]'' became the landmark which demonstrated the array of effects and techniques that were associated with this new school, called ''seconda pratica'', to distinguish it from the older style or ''[[prima pratica]]''. Monteverdi was a master of both, producing precisely styled madrigals that extended the forms of [[Luca Marenzio]] and [[Giaches de Wert]]. But it is his pieces in the new style which became the most influential. These included features which are recognizable even to the end of the baroque period, including use of idiomatic writing, virtuoso flourishes, and the use of new techniques.{{Or|date=March 2012}}

This musical language proved to be international, as [[Heinrich Schütz]], a German composer who studied in Venice under both Gabrieli and later Monteverdi, used it to the liturgical needs of the [[John George II, Elector of Saxony|Elector of Saxony]] and served as the choir master in [[Dresden]].{{Or|date=March 2012}}

=== Middle baroque music (1654–1707) ===

{{unreferenced section|date=March 2012}}
[[File:Louis XIV of France.jpg|thumb|215px|King Louis XIV by [[Hyacinthe Rigaud]] (1701)]]

The rise of the centralized court is one of the economic and political features of what is often labelled the [[Absolutism (European history)|Age of Absolutism]], personified by [[Louis XIV]] of France. The style of palace, and the court system of manners and arts which he fostered, became the model for the rest of Europe. The realities of rising church and state patronage created the demand for organized public music, as the increasing availability of instruments created the demand for [[chamber music]]. This included the availability of keyboard instruments.

The middle Baroque is separated from the early Baroque by the coming of systematic thinking to the new style and a gradual institutionalization of the forms and norms, particularly in opera. As with literature, the [[printing press]] and trade created an expanded international audience for works and greater cross-pollination between national centres of musical activity.

The middle Baroque, in music theory, is identified by the increasingly harmonic focus of musical practice and the creation of formal systems of teaching. Music was an art, and it came to be seen as one that should be taught in an orderly manner. This culminated in the later work of [[Johann Fux]] in systematizing counterpoint.

One pre-eminent example of a court style composer is [[Jean-Baptiste Lully]]. His career rose dramatically when he collaborated with [[Molière]] on a series of comédie-ballets, that is, plays with dancing. He used this success to become the sole composer of operas for the king, using not just innovative musical ideas such as the [[Tragédie en musique|tragédie lyrique]], but patents from the king which prevented others from having operas staged. Lully's instinct for providing the material that his monarch desired has been pointed out by almost every biographer, including his rapid shift to church music when the mood at court became more devout. His 13 completed lyric tragedies are based on libretti that focus on the conflicts between the public and private life of the monarch.

[[File:arcangelo corelli.jpg|thumb|200px|left|upright|Arcangelo Corelli]]

Musically, he explored contrast between stately and fully orchestrated sections, and simple recitatives and airs. In no small part, it was his skill in assembling and practicing musicians into an orchestra which was essential to his success and influence. Observers noted the precision and intonation, this in an age where there was no standard for tuning instruments. One essential element was the increased focus on the [[inner voices]] of the harmony and the relationship to the soloist. He also established the string-dominated norm for orchestras.

Arcangelo Corelli is remembered as influential for his achievements on the other side of musical technique— as a violinist who organized violin technique and pedagogy— and in purely instrumental music, particularly his advocacy and development of the [[concerto grosso]]. Whereas Lully was ensconced at court, Corelli was one of the first composers to publish widely and have his music performed all over Europe. As with Lully's stylization and organization of the opera, the concerto grosso is built on strong contrasts— sections alternate between those played by the full orchestra, and those played by a smaller group. Dynamics were &quot;terraced&quot;, that is with a sharp transition from loud to soft and back again. Fast sections and slow sections were juxtaposed against each other. Numbered among his students is Antonio Vivaldi, who later composed hundreds of works based on the principles in Corelli's [[trio sonata]]s and concerti.

[[File:Henry Purcell by John Closterman.jpg|thumb|225px|Henry Purcell by [[John Closterman]]]]

In England the middle Baroque produced a cometary genius in Henry Purcell, who, despite dying at age 36, produced a profusion of music and was widely recognized in his lifetime. He was familiar with the innovations of Corelli and other Italian style composers; however, his patrons were different, and his musical output was prodigious. Rather than being a painstaking craftsman, Purcell was a fluid composer who was able to shift from simple anthems and useful music such as marches, to grandly scored vocal music and music for the stage. His catalogue runs to over 800 works. He was also one of the first great keyboard composers, whose work still has influence and presence.

In contrast to these composers, [[Dieterich Buxtehude]] was not a creature of court but instead was an organist and entrepreneurial presenter of music. Rather than publishing, he relied on performance for his income, and rather than royal patronage, he shuttled between vocal settings for sacred music, and organ music that he performed. His output is not as fabulous or diverse, because he was not constantly being called upon for music to meet an occasion. Buxtehude's employment of contrast was between the free, often improvisatory sections, and more strict sections worked out contrapuntally. This procedure would be highly influential on later composers such as Bach, who took the contrast between free and strict to greater heights.

=== Late baroque music (1680–1750) ===

{{unreferenced section|date=March 2012}}
[[File:Attribué à Joseph Aved, Portrait de Jean-Philippe Rameau (vers 1728) - 001.jpg|230px|thumb|left|Jean-Philippe Rameau, by [[Jacques André Joseph Aved]], 1728]]

The dividing line between middle and late Baroque is a matter of some debate. Dates for the beginning of &quot;late&quot; baroque style range from 1680 to 1720. In no small part this is because there was not one synchronized transition; different national styles experienced changes at different rates and at different times. Italy is generally regarded as the first country to move to the late baroque style. The important dividing line in most histories of baroque music is the full absorption of tonality as a structuring principle of music. This was particularly evident in the wake of theoretical work by Jean-Philippe Rameau, who replaced Lully as the important French opera composer. At the same time, through the work of [[Johann Fux]], the Renaissance style of polyphony was made the basis for the study of counterpoint. The combination of modal counterpoint with tonal logic of cadences created the sense that there were two styles of composition— the homophonic dominated by vertical considerations and the polyphonic dominated by imitation and contrapuntal considerations.

The forms which had begun to be established in the previous era flourished and were given wider range of diversity; concerto, suite, sonata, concerto grosso, oratorio, opera and ballet all saw a proliferation of national styles and structures. The overall form of pieces was generally simple, with repeated binary forms (AABB), simple three part forms (ABC), and rondeau forms being common. These schematics in turn influenced later composers.

[[File:Vivaldi.jpg|thumb|210px|Antonio Vivaldi]]

Antonio Vivaldi is a figure who was forgotten in concert music making for much of the 19th century, only to be revived in the 20th century. Born in Venice in 1678, he began as an ordained priest of the Catholic Church but ceased to say [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]] by 1703. Around the same time he was appointed ''maestro di violino'' at a Venetian girls' orphanage with which he had a professional relationship until nearly the end of his life. Vivaldi's reputation came not from having an orchestra or court appointment, but from his published works, including trio sonatas, violin sonatas and concerti. They were published in [[Amsterdam]] and circulated widely through Europe.

It is in these instrumental genres of baroque sonata and baroque concerto, which were still evolving, that Vivaldi's most important contributions were made. He settled on certain patterns, such as a fast-slow-fast three-movement plan for works, and the use of [[ritornello]] in the fast movements, and explored the possibilities in hundreds of works— 550 concerti alone. He also used programmatic titles for works, such as his famous &quot;[[The Four Seasons (Vivaldi)|The Four Seasons]]&quot; violin concerti. Vivaldi's career reflects a growing possibility for a composer to be able to support himself by his publications, tour to promote his own works, and have an independent existence.

[[Domenico Scarlatti]] was one of the leading keyboard virtuosi of his day, who took the road of being a royal court musician, first in [[Portugal]] and then, starting in 1733, in [[Madrid]], Spain, where he spent the rest of his life. His father, Alessandro Scarlatti, was a member of the [[Neapolitan School]] of opera and has been credited with being among its most skilled members. Domenico also wrote operas and church music, but it is the publication of his keyboard works, which spread more widely after his death, which have secured him a lasting place of reputation. Many of these works were written for his own playing but others for his royal patrons. As with his father, his fortunes were closely tied to his ability to secure, and keep, royal favour.

[[File:Retrato de Handel.jpg|250px|left|thumb|George Frideric Handel by [[Philip Mercier]]]]

Perhaps the most famous composer to be associated with royal patronage was George Frideric Handel, who was born in Germany, studied for three years in Italy, and went to London in 1711, which was his base of operations for a long and profitable career that included independently produced operas and commissions for nobility. He was constantly searching for successful commercial formulas, in opera, and then in oratorios in English. A continuous worker, Handel borrowed from others and often recycled his own material. He was also known for reworking pieces such as the famous ''[[Messiah (Handel)|Messiah]]'', which premiered in 1742, for available singers and musicians. Even as his economic circumstances rose and fell with his productions, his reputation, based on published keyboard works, ceremonial music, constant stagings of operas and oratorios and concerti grossi, grew tremendously.

By the time of his death, he was regarded as the leading composer in Europe and was studied by later classical-era musicians. Handel, because of his very public ambitions, rested a great deal of his output on melodic resource combined with a rich performance tradition of improvisation and counterpoint. The practice of [[ornament (music)|ornamentation]] in the Baroque style was at a very high level of development under his direction. He travelled all over Europe to engage singers and learn the music of other composers, and thus he had among the widest acquaintance of other styles of any composer.

[[File:Johann Sebastian Bach.jpg|thumb|230px|Johann Sebastian Bach by [[Elias Gottlob Haussmann]], 1748]]

Johann Sebastian Bach has, over time, come to be seen as the towering figure of Baroque music, with what [[Béla Bartók]] described as &quot;a religion&quot; surrounding him. During the baroque period, he was better known as a teacher, administrator and performer than composer, being less famous than either Handel or Georg Philipp Telemann. Born in [[Eisenach]] in 1685 to a musical family, he received an extensive early education and was considered to have an excellent [[boy soprano]] voice. He held a variety of posts as an organist, rapidly gaining in fame for his virtuosity and ability. In 1723 he settled at the post which he was associated with for virtually the rest of his life: cantor and director of music for [[Leipzig]]. His varied experience allowed him to become the town's leader of music both secular and sacred, teacher of its musicians, and leading musical figure. He began his term in Leipzig by composing a [[Bach cantata|church cantata]] for every Sunday and holiday of the [[List of Bach cantatas by liturgical function|Liturgical year]], resulting in annual cycles of cantatas, namely his second cycle of [[Chorale cantata (Bach)|Chorale cantata]]s. About 200 sacred cantatas are extant.

Bach created the grand scale works ''[[St John Passion]]'', the ''[[St Matthew Passion]]'', the ''[[Christmas Oratorio]]'', spanning six feast days, and the ''[[Mass in B minor]]''. Bach's musical innovations plumbed the depths and the outer limits of the Baroque homophonic and polyphonic forms. He was a virtual catalogue of every contrapuntal device possible and every acceptable means of creating webs of harmony with the chorale. As a result, his works in the form of the fugue coupled with [[prelude (music)|preludes]] and toccatas for organ, and the baroque concerto forms, have become fundamental in both performance and theoretical technique. Virtually every instrument and ensemble of the age— except for the theatre genres— is represented copiously in his output. Bach's teachings became prominent in the classical and romantic eras as composers rediscovered the harmonic and melodic subtleties of his works.

[[File:Telemann 4.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Georg Philipp Telemann (1681–1767), hand-colored [[aquatint]] by Valentin Daniel Preisler, after a lost painting by Louis Michael Schneider, 1750.]]

Georg Philipp Telemann was the most famous instrumental composer of his time, and massively prolific— even by the standards of an age where composers had to produce large volumes of music. His two most important positions – director of music in [[Frankfurt]] in 1712 and in 1721 director of music of the Johanneum in [[Hamburg]] – required him to compose vocal and instrumental music for secular and sacred contexts. He composed two complete cantata cycles for Sunday services, as well as sacred oratorios. Telemann also founded a periodical that published new music, much of it by Telemann. This dissemination of music made him a composer with an international audience, as evidenced by his successful trip to Paris in 1731. Some of his finest works were in the 1750s and 1760s, when the Baroque style was being replaced by simpler styles but were popular at the time and afterwards. Among these late works are ''[[Der Tod Jesu]]'' (The Death of Jesus) 1755, &quot;Die Donner-Ode&quot; (The Ode of Thunder) 1756, &quot;Die Auferstehung und Himmelfahrt Jesu&quot; (The Resurrection and Ascension of Jesus) 1760 and &quot;Der Tag des Gerichts&quot; (The Day of Judgement) 1762.

== Influence on later music ==
=== Transition to the Classical era (1740–1780) ===

{{unreferenced section|date=March 2012}}
[[File:Adolph Menzel_-_Flötenkonzert Friedrichs des Großen in Sanssouci_-_Google Art Project.jpg|350px|thumb|''The Flute Concert of Sanssouci'' by [[Adolph von Menzel]], 1852, depicts [[Frederick the Great]] playing the flute as Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach accompanies on the keyboard. The audience includes Bach's colleagues as well as nobles.]]

The phase between the late Baroque and the [[Classical music era#Beginnings of the Classical style (1730–1760)|early Classical era]], with its broad mixture of competing ideas and attempts to unify the different demands of taste, economics and &quot;worldview&quot;, goes by many names. It is sometimes called &quot;[[Galant]]&quot;, &quot;[[Rococo]]&quot;, or &quot;pre-Classical&quot;, or at other times, &quot;early Classical&quot;. It is a period where composers still working in the Baroque style were still successful, if sometimes thought of as being more of the past than the present—Bach, Handel and Telemann all composed well beyond the point at which the homophonic style is clearly in the ascendant. Musical culture was caught at a crossroads: the masters of the older style had the technique, but the public hungered for the new. This is one of the reasons [[Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach]] was held in such high regard: he understood the older forms quite well and knew how to present them in new garb, with an enhanced variety of form; he went far in overhauling the older forms from the Baroque.

The practice of the baroque era was the standard against which new [[Musical composition|composition]] was measured, and there came to be a division between sacred works, which held more closely to the Baroque style from secular or &quot;profane&quot; works, which were in the new style.

[[File:Thomas Augustine Arne.png|thumb|200px|left|Thomas Arne]]

Especially in the Catholic countries of central Europe, the baroque style continued to be represented in sacred music through the end of the eighteenth century, in much the way that the ''stile antico'' of the Renaissance continued to live in the sacred music of the early 17th century. The masses and oratorios of [[Joseph Haydn]] and [[Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart]], while Classical in their orchestration and ornamentation, have many Baroque features in their underlying contrapuntal and harmonic structure. The decline of the baroque saw various attempts to mix old and new techniques, and many composers who continued to hew to the older forms well into the 1780s. Many cities in Germany continued to maintain performance practices from the Baroque into the 1790s, including Leipzig, where J.S. Bach worked to the end of his life.

In England, the enduring popularity of Handel ensured the success of [[Charles Avison]], [[William Boyce (composer)|William Boyce]], and [[Thomas Arne]]—among other accomplished imitators—well into the 1780s, who competed alongside Mozart and Bach. In Continental Europe, however, it was considered an old-fashioned way of writing and was a requisite for graduation from the burgeoning number of [[music school|conservatories]] of music, and otherwise reserved only for use in sacred works.

=== After 1760 ===

{{section OR|date=March 2012}}
[[File:Fritz Kreisler 1.jpg|thumb|250px|alt=Fritz Kreisler|Violinist and composer Fritz Kreisler attributed many discovered works to lesser known Baroque composers.]]

Because baroque music was the basis for pedagogy, it retained a stylistic influence even after it had ceased to be the style of composing or of music making. Even as Baroque practice fell out of use, it continued to be part of musical notation. In the early 19th century, scores by baroque masters were printed in complete edition, and this led to a renewed interest in the &quot;strict style&quot; of counterpoint, as it was then called. With [[Felix Mendelssohn]]'s revival of Bach's choral music, the baroque style became an influence through the 19th century as a paragon of academic and formal purity.

In the 20th century, Baroque was named as a period, and its music began to be studied.

There are several instances of contemporary pieces being published as &quot;rediscovered&quot; Baroque masterworks. Some examples of this include a viola concerto written by [[Henri Casadesus]] but attributed to [[Johann Christian Bach]], as well as several pieces attributed by [[Fritz Kreisler]] to lesser-known figures of the Baroque such as [[Gaetano Pugnani]] and [[Giovanni Battista Martini|Padre Martini]]. [[Alessandro Parisotti]] attributed his aria for voice and piano, &quot;Se tu m'ami&quot;, to [[Giovanni Battista Pergolesi|Pergolesi]].

Various works have been labelled &quot;neo-baroque&quot; for a focus on imitative polyphony, including the works of [[Giacinto Scelsi]], [[Paul Hindemith]], [[Paul Creston]] and [[Bohuslav Martinů]], even though they are not in the baroque style proper. Musicologists attempted to complete various works from the Baroque, most notably Bach's ‘’[[The Art of Fugue]]’’. Composer Peter Schickele [[parody|parodies]] classical and baroque styles under the pen name [[PDQ Bach]].

Baroque performance practice had a renewed influence with the rise of &quot;Authentic&quot; or [[Historically informed performance]] in the late 20th century. Texts by [[Johann Joachim Quantz]] and [[Leopold Mozart]] among others, formed the basis for performances which attempted to recover some of the aspects of baroque sound world, including one-on-a-part performance of works by Bach, use of gut strings rather than metal, reconstructed [[harpsichord]]s, use of older playing techniques and styles. Several popular ensembles adopted some or all of these techniques, including the [[Anonymous 4]], the [[Academy of Ancient Music]], Boston's [[Handel and Haydn Society]], [[William Christie (musician)|William Christie]]'s [[Les Arts Florissants (ensemble)|Les Arts Florissants]], [[Sigiswald Kuijken]]'s [[La Petite Bande]] and others.

== Timeline of Baroque composers ==

{{see also|List of Baroque composers}}
{{Timeline Classical Composers Baroque}}

== Baroque instruments ==

[[File:Baschenis_-_Musical Instruments.jpg|thumb|250px|Baroque instruments including hurdy gurdy, harpsichord, bass viol, lute, violin, and guitar.]]
[[File:Harpsichord VitalJulianFrey.jpg|thumb|250px|A double-manual harpsichord after Jean-Claude Goujon (1749).]]
{{see also|List of period instruments}}

=== Strings ===

* [[Violino piccolo]]
* [[Baroque violin|Violin]]
* [[Viol]]
* [[Viola]]
* [[Viola d'amore]]
* [[Viola pomposa]]
* [[Tenor violin]]
* [[Cello]]
* [[Contrabass]]
* [[Lute]]
* [[Theorbo]]
* [[Archlute]]
* [[Angélique (instrument)|Angélique]]
* [[Mandolin]]
* [[Baroque guitar|Guitar]]
* [[Harp]]
* [[Hurdy gurdy]]

=== Woodwinds ===

* [[Baroque flute]]
* [[Chalumeau]]
* Cortol (also known as Cortholt, Curtall, [[Oboe]] family)
* [[Dulcian]]
* [[Musette de cour]]
* [[Baroque oboe]]
* [[Rackett]]
* [[Recorder]]

=== Brasses ===

* [[Baroque trumpet]]
* [[Cornett]]
* [[Natural horn|Horn]]
* [[Serpent (instrument)|Serpent]]
* [[Sackbut]]

=== Keyboards ===

* [[Clavichord]]
* [[Tangent piano]]
* [[Fortepiano]] – early version of piano
* [[Harpsichord]]
* [[organ (music)|Organ]]

== Styles and forms ==
=== The Baroque suite === 

The Baroque suite often consists of the following movements:

* [[French overture|Overture]] – The Baroque suite often began with a French overture (&quot;Ouverture&quot; in French), which was followed by a succession of dances of different types.
* [[Allemande]] – Often the first dance of an instrumental [[suite (music)|suite]], the allemande was a very popular dance that had its origins in the German [[Renaissance]] era, when it was more often called the [[almain]]. The allemande was played at a moderate [[tempo]] and could start on any beat of the bar.{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}{{sfn|Estrella|2012}}
* [[Courante]] – The courante is a lively, French dance in [[triple meter]]. The Italian version is called the corrente.{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}{{sfn|Estrella|2012}}
* [[Sarabande]] – The sarabande, a Spanish dance, is one of the slowest of the baroque dances. It is also in triple meter and can start on any beat of the bar, although there is an emphasis on the second beat, creating the characteristic 'halting', or iambic rhythm of the sarabande.{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}{{sfn|Estrella|2012}}
* [[Gigue]] – The gigue is an upbeat and lively baroque dance in compound meter, typically the concluding movement of an instrumental suite. The gigue can start on any beat of the bar and is easily recognized by its rhythmic feel. The gigue originated in the [[British Isles]]. Its counterpart in folk music is the [[jig]].{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}{{sfn|Estrella|2012}}

These four dance types make up the majority of 17th century suites; later suites interpolate additional movements between the sarabande and gigue:

* [[Gavotte]] – The gavotte can be identified by a variety of features; it is in 4/4 time and always starts on the third beat of the bar, although this may sound like the first beat in some cases, as the first and third beats are the strong beats in quadruple time. The gavotte is played at a moderate tempo, although in some cases it may be played faster.{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}
* [[Bourrée]] – The bourrée is similar to the gavotte as it is in 2/2 time although it starts on the second half of the last beat of the bar, creating a different feel to the dance. The bourrée is commonly played at a moderate tempo, although for some composers, such as Handel, it can be taken at a much faster tempo.{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}
* [[Minuet]] – The minuet is perhaps the best-known of the baroque dances in triple meter. It can start on any beat of the bar. In some suites there may be a Minuet I and II, played in succession, with the Minuet I repeated.{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}
* [[Passepied]] – The passepied is a fast dance in binary form and triple meter that originated as a court dance in [[Brittany]].{{sfn|Little|2001|loc= “Passepied”}} Examples can be found in later suites such as those of Bach and Handel.{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}
* [[Rigaudon]] – The rigaudon is a lively French dance in duple meter, similar to the bourrée, but rhythmically simpler. It originated as a family of closely related southern-French folk dances, traditionally associated with the provinces of Vavarais, [[Languedoc]], [[Dauphiné]], and [[Provence]].{{sfn|Little|2001|loc= “Rigaudon”}}{{sfn|Kenyon|1997}}

=== Other features ===

* ''[[Basso continuo]]'' – a kind of continuous accompaniment notated with a new music notation system, [[figured bass]], usually for a sustaining bass instrument and a keyboard instrument.
* The [[concerto]] and [[concerto grosso]]
* [[Monody]] – music for one melodic voice with [[accompaniment]], characteristic of the early 17th century, especially in Italy{{sfn|Dorak|2008}}
* [[Homophony]] – music with one melodic voice and rhythmically similar accompaniment (this and monody are contrasted with the typical Renaissance [[texture (music)|texture]], [[polyphony]]){{sfn|Root|2012|loc=&quot;Homophony”}}
* Dramatic musical forms like opera, ''[[dramma per musica]]''{{sfn|Dorak|2008}}{{sfn|Shotwell|2002}}
* Combined instrumental-vocal forms, such as the [[oratorio]] and [[cantata]]{{sfn|Shotwell|2002}}
* New instrumental techniques, like ''[[tremolo]]'' and ''[[pizzicato]]''{{sfn|Shotwell|2002}}
* Clear and linear [[melody]]{{cn|date=August 2012}}
* [[Notes inégales]] – a technique of playing pairs of notes of equal written length (typically eighth notes) with a &quot;[[Swung note|swung]]&quot; rhythm, alternating longer and shorter values in pairs, the degree of inequality varying according to context. Particularly characteristic of French performance practice.{{cn|date=August 2012}}
* The [[aria]]{{sfn|Dorak|2008}}
* The ''[[ritornello]]'' aria – repeated short instrumental interruptions of vocal passages.{{sfn|Root|2012|loc=&quot;Ritornello”}}
* The [[concertato]] style – contrast in sound between orchestra and solo-instruments or small groups of instruments.{{sfn|Root|2012|loc=&quot;Concertato”}}
* Precise instrumental scoring (in the Renaissance, exact instrumentation for ensemble playing was rarely indicated){{cn|date=August 2012}}
* Virtuosic instrumental and vocal writing, with appreciation for virtuosity as such{{cn|date=August 2012}}
* Extensive [[Ornament (music)|Ornamentation]]{{sfn|Roseman|2008}}
* Development to modern Western tonality ([[major scale|major]] and [[minor scale]]s){{cn|date=August 2012}}
* [[Cadenza]] (an extended virtuosic section for the soloist usually near the end of a movement of a concerto).{{cn|date=August 2012}}

== Genres ==
=== Vocal ===

* Opera
** [[Zarzuela]]
** [[Opera seria]]
** [[Opera comique]]
** [[Opera-ballet]]
* [[Masque]]
* [[Oratorio]]
* [[Passion (music)]]
* [[Cantata]]
* [[Mass (music)]]
* [[Anthem]]
* [[Monody]]
* [[Chorale]]

=== Instrumental ===

* [[Chorale composition]]
* [[Concerto grosso]]
* [[Fugue (music)|Fugue]]
* [[Suite (music)|Suite]]
** [[Allemande]]
** [[Courante]]
** [[Sarabande]]
** [[Gigue]]
** [[Gavotte]]
** [[Minuet]]
* [[Sonata (music)|Sonata]]
** [[Sonata da camera]]
** [[Sonata da chiesa]]
** [[Trio sonata]]
* [[Partita]]
* [[Canzona]]
* [[Sinfonia]]
* [[Fantasia (music)|Fantasia]]
* [[Ricercar]]
* [[Toccata]]
* [[Prelude (music)|Prelude]]
* [[Chaconne]]
* [[Passacaglia]]
* [[Chorale prelude]]
* [[Stylus fantasticus]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|colwidth = 25em}}

== References ==

{{refbegin}}

* {{cite book | last = Clarke | first = Hugh Archibald | year = 1898 | title = A System of Harmony | publisher = T. Presser| location = Philadelphia |isbn=978-1248379462 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Chua | first = Daniel K. L. | chapter = Vincenzo Galilei, modernity, and the division of nature | title = Music theory and natural order from the Renaissance to the early twentieth century | editor-first = Suzannah | editor-last = Clark | year = 2001 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=wSYm0cUW6PMC | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Donington | first = Robert | year = 1974 | title = A Performer's Guide to Baroque Music |isbn=978-0571097975|publisher=C. Scribner's Sons | location =  New York | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | last = Dorak | first = Tevrik | url = http://www.dorak.info/music/baroque.html | title = Baroque Music | publisher = Dorak.info | year = 2008 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | last = Estrella | first = Espie | url= http://musiced.about.com/od/historyofmusic/a/baroquesuite.htm | title = The Suite: Baroque Dance Suite | publisher = About.com | year = 2012 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Haagmans | first = Dirk | year = 1916 | title = Scales, Intervals, Harmony |isbn=978-1437062021 |publisher=J. Fischer &amp; Bro. | location = University of Michigan | ref = harv }}
*{{cite web | last = Root| first = Deane L.|year = 2012| title = Grove Music Online | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]] |url = http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/public/|ref = harv}}
* {{cite journal | last = Kenyon | first = Stephen | year = 1997 | title = The Baroque Suite | publisher = Jacaranda Music | url = http://www.jacaranda-music.com/baroque.html | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Little | first = Meredith Ellis | year = 2001 | title = The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians | publisher = Grove's Dictionaries | location = New York | isbn= 978-1-56159-239-5 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web | last1 = Mackay | first1 = Alison | last2 = Romanec | first2 = Craig | date = 22 October 2007 | url = http://www.tafelmusik.org/sites/all/themes/tafelmusik/downloads/Baroque_Guide.pdf | title = Baroque Guide | publisher = Tafelmusik | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Norton | first = Richard | year = 1984 | title = Tonality in Western Culture: A Critical and Historical Perspective | isbn=978-0271003597|publisher=Pennsylvania State University Press | location = University Park | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Nuti | first = Giulia | year = 2007 | title = The performance of Italian basso continuo: style in keyboard accompaniment in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries | publisher = Ashgate Publishing | location = Aldershot, England | isbn = 978-0-7546-0567-6 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book| last = Palisca | first = Claude V. | year = 2001 | title = The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians | publisher = Macmillan Publishers | location = London | isbn = 978-1-56159-239-5 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web|last = Roseman |first = Ronald |year=2008|url = http://www.musebaroque.fr/Articles/Baroque_ornamentation.htm |title = Baroque Ornamentation | publisher = Muse Baroque | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Sachs | first1 = Curt | authorlink1 = Curt Sachs | title = Barockmusik | trans_title = Baroque Music | series = Jahrbuch der Musikbibliothek Peters | volume = 26 | year = 1919 | publisher = Edition Peters | location = Leipzig | language = Deutsch | ref = harv }}
* {{cite web| last = Shotwell| first = Clay | url= http://www.aug.edu/~cshotwel/4350.Baroquetraits.html |title = Music of the Baroque Era | publisher = Augusta State University | year = 2002| ref= harv }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Wainwright | first1 = Jonathan | last2 = Holman | first2 = Peter | year = 2005 | title = From Renaissance to Baroque: Change in Instruments and Instrumental Music in the Seventeenth Century | url = http://books.google.com/?id=2uXTdwWxppwC |isbn=978-0754604037|publisher=Ashgate Publishing | location = Aldershot, England | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Wallechinsky | first = David | year = 2007 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=938irIZnmGsC | title = The Knowledge Book: Everything You Need to Know to Get by in the 21st century | location = Washington, DC | publisher = National Geographic Books | isbn = 978-1-4262-0124-0 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Watkins | first = Glenn | year = 1991 | title = Gesualdo: The Man and His Music | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford | isbn = 978-0-19-816197-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = York | first = Francis L. | year = 1909 | title = Harmony Simplified: A Practical Introduction to Composition | publisher = Oliver Ditson and Company | location = Boston| isbn = 978-1-176-33956-9 | ref = harv }}

== Further reading ==
* Christensen, Thomas Street, and Peter Dejans. ''Towards Tonality Aspects of Baroque Music Theory''. Leuven: Leuven University Press, 2007. ISBN 978-90-5867-587-3
* Cyr, Mary. ''Essays on the Performance of Baroque Music Opera and Chamber Music in France and England''. Variorum collected studies series, 899. Aldershot, Hants, England: Ashgate, 2008. ISBN 978-0-7546-5926-6
* Foreman, Edward. ''A Bel Canto Method, or, How to Sing Italian Baroque Music Correctly Based on the Primary Sources''. Twentieth century masterworks on singing, v. 12. Minneapolis, Minn: Pro Musica Press, 2006. ISBN 978-1-887117-18-0
* Schubert, Peter, and Christoph Neidhöfer. ''Baroque Counterpoint''. Upper Saddle River, NJ: Pearson Prentice Hall, 2006. ISBN 978-0-13-183442-2
* Schulenberg, David. ''Music of the Baroque''. New York: Oxford UP, 2001. ISBN 978-0-19-512232-9
* Stauffer, George B. ''The World of Baroque Music New Perspectives''. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2006. ISBN 978-0-253-34798-5
* Strunk, Oliver.''Source Readings in Music History. From Classical Antiquity to the Romantic Era''. London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1952.

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.barockmusic.com Barock Music (webradio)]
* [http://www.pandora.com/stations/3ef0ec647572b75a1d03771f434593efe7c5e7241f96d370 Pandora Radio: Baroque Period] (not available outside the U.S.)
* [http://www.saladelcembalo.org/ Handel's Harpsichord Room&amp;nbsp;– free recordings of harpsichord music of the Baroque era]
* [http://plato.acadiau.ca/courses/musi/callon/2233/ch-comp.htm Renaissance &amp; Baroque Music Chronology]: Composers
* [http://www.orpheon.org/ Orpheon Foundation] in Vienna, Austria
* {{IMSLP|id=Baroque_composers|cname=various baroque composers}}
* [http://etd.lib.fsu.edu/theses/available/etd-11172003-033041/unrestricted/02_smp_fire1.pdf Music, Affect and Fire]: Thesis on Affect Theory with Fire as the special topic
* [http://www.essentialhumanities.net/mus5.php Overview of Baroque Music]
* [http://www.rism.info Répertoire International des Sources Musicales (RISM)], a free, searchable database of worldwide locations for music manuscripts up to ca. 1800

{{music topics}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Baroque Music}}
[[Category:Baroque music| ]]
[[Category:Age of Enlightenment]]

{{Link FA|fi}}
{{Link GA|ru}}

[[af:Barokmusiek]]
[[ar:عصر الباروك]]
[[az:Barokko (musiqi)]]
[[ca:Música barroca]]
[[cs:Barokní hudba]]
[[da:Barokmusik]]
[[de:Barockmusik]]
[[et:Barokkmuusika]]
[[el:Μπαρόκ μουσική]]
[[es:Música del Barroco]]
[[eo:Baroka muziko]]
[[fa:موسیقی دوره باروک]]
[[fr:Musique baroque]]
[[fy:Barokmuzyk]]
[[gl:Música barroca]]
[[ko:바로크 음악]]
[[hr:Barokna glazba]]
[[id:Musik Barok]]
[[it:Musica barocca]]
[[he:המוזיקה הקלאסית בתקופת הבארוק]]
[[la:Aetas Baroca (musica)]]
[[lt:Baroko muzika]]
[[hu:Barokk zene]]
[[mk:Барокна музика]]
[[ms:Muzik era barok]]
[[mwl:Música barroca]]
[[nl:Barokmuziek]]
[[ja:バロック音楽]]
[[no:Barokkmusikk]]
[[nn:Barokkmusikk]]
[[pl:Muzyka barokowa]]
[[pt:Música barroca]]
[[ru:Музыка эпохи барокко]]
[[sq:Muzika barok]]
[[scn:Mùsica barocca]]
[[simple:Baroque music]]
[[sk:Baroková hudba]]
[[sl:Baročna glasba]]
[[sr:Барокна музика]]
[[sh:Barokna muzika]]
[[fi:Barokkimusiikki]]
[[sv:Barockens musik]]
[[tl:Tugtuging Barok]]
[[th:ดนตรียุคบาโรก]]
[[tr:Barok müzik]]
[[uk:Барокова музика]]
[[yi:באראק מוזיק]]
[[zh:巴洛克音乐]]</text>
      <sha1>c1sl2275cb7naxx8r2mk4s3czpuic6m</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
