<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bourbon Restoration</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>62244</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522261357</id>
      <parentid>520770165</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T00:51:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.178.108.229</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58045">{{for|the restoration of the Bourbon dynasty following the First Spanish Republic|Spain under the Restoration}}
{{POV|date=December 2011}}
{{Infobox former country
|native_name = &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''Royaume de France''&lt;/span&gt;
|conventional_long_name = Kingdom of France
|common_name = France
|continent = Europe
|region    =
|country   = France
|era       =
|status    =
|status_text=
|religion  = [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]]&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Furet|1995|p=271}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|empire    =
|government_type = [[Constitutional monarchy]]
|event_start = [[Louis XVIII of France#Bourbon Restoration|Restoration]] 
|life_span   = 1814–1815&lt;br /&gt;1815–1830
|year_start  = 1814
|date_start  = 6 April
|event_end   = [[July Revolution]]
|year_end    = 1830
|date_end    = 26 July
|event1      = [[Treaty of Paris (1814)|Treaty of Paris]]
|date_event1 = 30 May 1814
|event2      = [[Charter of 1814|Constitution adopted]]
|date_event2 = 4 June 1814
|event3      = [[Hundred Days]]
|date_event3 = 20 Mar – 7 Jul 1815
|event4      = [[Hundred Thousand Sons of Saint Louis|Invasion of Spain]]
|date_event4 = 6 April 1823
|event_pre   =
|date_pre    =

|p1          = First French Empire
|flag_p1     = flag of France.svg
|s1          = July Monarchy
|flag_s1     = flag of France.svg

|flag        =
|flag_type   =
|image_flag  = Pavillon royal de France.svg
|symbol       =
|symbol_type  = Royal Coat of arms
|image_coat   = Coat of Arms of the Bourbon Restoration (1815-30).svg
|image_map    = France 1815.jpg
|image_map_caption  = The Kingdom of France in 1815.
|capital          = [[Paris]]
|national_motto   = ''Montjoie Saint Denis!''&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&quot;Mount joy Saint Denis!&quot;
|national_anthem  = ''[[Le Retour des Princes Français à Paris]]''&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&quot;The Return of the French Princes to Paris&quot;&lt;small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;center&gt;[[File:Hymne De La Monarchie Francaise.ogg]]&lt;/center&gt;
|common_languages = [[French language|French]]
|currency         = [[French franc]]
|leader1      = &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis XVIII of France|Louis XVIII]]&lt;/span&gt;
|year_leader1 = 1814–1824
|leader2      = &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Charles X of France|Charles X]]&lt;/span&gt;
|year_leader2 = 1824–1830
|leader3      = &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis XIX of France|Louis XIX]]&lt;/span&gt;
|year_leader3 = 1830
|leader4      = &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Henry, Count of Chambord|Henry V]]&lt;/span&gt;
|year_leader4 = 1830
|title_leader = [[List of French monarchs|King]]
|title_deputy = [[List of Prime Ministers of France#Presidents of the Council of Ministers|President of the Council of Ministers]]
|deputy1      = [[Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Périgord|Charles de Bénévent]] &lt;small&gt;(first)&lt;/small&gt;
|year_deputy1 = 1815
|deputy2      = [[Jules, 3rd Duke of Polignac|Jules de Polignac]] &lt;small&gt;(last)&lt;/small&gt;
|year_deputy2 = 1829–1830
|legislature  = [[Parliament of France|Parliament]]
|house1       = [[Chambre des pairs|Chamber of Peers]]
|house2       = [[Chamber of Deputies of France|Chamber of Deputies]]
}}

{{History of France}}
The '''Bourbon Restoration''' is the name given to the period following the successive events of the [[French Revolution]] (1789–1799), the end of the [[French First Republic|First Republic]] (1792–1804), and then the forcible end of the [[First French Empire|First French Empire under Napoleon]] (1804–1814/1815)&amp;nbsp;– when a [[War of the Sixth Coalition|coalition of European powers]] restored by arms the monarchy to the heirs of the [[House of Bourbon]], who once again became possessors of the '''Kingdom of France'''. The Bourbon Restoration existed from (about) 6 April 1814 until the popular uprisings of the [[July Revolution]] of 1830, excepting the interval of the &quot;[[Hundred Days]]&quot;,&lt;ref group=lower-alpha name=nb/&gt; less than a full year into the Restoration, when the Bourbon monarchy had again made themselves so unpopular with the general population of France that the family was again forced to flee [[Paris]] and [[France]] for [[Ghent]], ahead of exploding civil disorders and collapsing civil authority.

At the beginning of the Hundred Days, deposed Emperor [[Napoleon|Napoleon I]] returned triumphantly to Paris from [[Elba]]. He was greeted with great acclaim and joy by French crowds lining the roads. Coming from far away with advance news spreading of his approach all along the way, crowds swelled his army overnight at his back, growing at every step, even by aggregating the very troops sent to arrest him by the monarchy on several occasions. With the flight of the king, after reaching Paris, he re-announced and reclaimed his dignities as Emperor. The European Great Powers were nowhere near as welcoming, and they quickly mobilized armies once more. This resulted in Napoleon's decisive defeat in 1815 at the [[Battle of Waterloo]].

There is little evidence that the Bourbon regime took away any lesson in the aftermath, and became increasingly annoying to the Parisian populace, and around France in general. The pre-revolution problems soon returned with court behavior driving home new hatreds between the upper and lower classes.

The new Bourbon regime was, however, a [[constitutional monarchy]], unlike the ''[[Ancien Régime in France|Ancien Régime]]'', which was absolute, so it had some limits on its abilities to govern. The period was characterized by a sharp conservative reaction, and consequent minor but consistent occurrences of civil unrest and disturbances.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davies|2002|pp=47–54}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also saw the re-establishment of the Roman Catholic Church as a power in French politics.&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 296&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical overview==
The Armies of the [[War of the Sixth Coalition|Sixth Coalition]] restored [[Louis XVIII]], called the ''[[Pretender#French pretenders|Bourbon pretender]]'' by historiographers, especially by those unfavorable to the restoration of the monarchy, to the throne of France in April 1814. A constitution, the [[Charter of 1814]], was drafted, presenting all Frenchmen equal before the law,&lt;ref&gt;The Charter of 1814, Public Law of the French: Article 1&lt;/ref&gt; but retaining substantial prerogative for the king and nobility.

Louis XVIII was the supreme head of the state. He commanded the land and sea forces, declared war, made treaties of peace, alliance and commerce, appointed to all places of public administration, and made the necessary regulations and ordinances for the execution of the laws and the security of the state.&lt;ref&gt;The Charter of 1814, Form of the Government of the King: Article 14&lt;/ref&gt; Louis was more liberal than his successor [[Charles X]], choosing many centrist cabinets.&lt;ref&gt;Price, p 93&lt;/ref&gt;

Louis XVIII died in September 1824. He was succeeded by his brother, Charles. Charles X pursued a more conservative form of governance than Louis. His ultra-reactionary laws included the [[Anti-Sacrilege Act]] (1825–1830), which saw his popularity plummet. The king and his ministers attempted to manipulate the outcome of a general election in 1830, through their [[July Ordinances]]. The ordinances sparked a revolution against Charles's ''coup'' attempt; by 2 August 1830, Charles had fled Paris and abdicated in favour of his grandson [[Henry, Count of Chambord|Henri, duc de Bordeaux]]. Henri's theoretical reign was ended on 9 August when the [[Chamber of Deputies of France|Chamber of Deputies]] declared [[Louis Philippe I|Louis Philippe d'Orléans]], who was currently ruling France as regent, [[King of the French]], thus ushering in the [[July Monarchy]].

== Louis XVIII, 1814–1824 ==
===First Restoration (1814)===
{{See also|Louis XVIII of France#Bourbon Restoration}}
[[File:Louis XVIII2.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Portrait of Louis XVIII 1755-1824 in coronation robes'', by [[François Gérard]]]]
[[File:Louis XVIII relevant la France.jpg|thumb|left|upright|''Allégorie du retour des Bourbons le 24 avril 1814 : Louis XVIII relevant la France de ses ruines'', by [[Louis-Philippe Crépin]]]]
Louis XVIII's restoration to the throne in 1814 was effected largely through the support of Napoleon's former foreign minister, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Périgord|Talleyrand]]&lt;/span&gt;, who convinced the victorious Allied Powers of the desirability of a &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bourbon&lt;/span&gt; Restoration.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Tombs|1996|p=329}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Allies had initially split on the best candidate for the throne: Britain favoured the Bourbons, the Austrians considered a regency for Napoleon's son, [[Napoleon II|François Bonaparte]], and the Russians were open to either the [[Dukes of Orléans|duc d'Orléans]], [[Louis Philippe I|Louis Philippe]], or [[Charles XIV John of Sweden|Jean-Baptiste Bernadotte]], Napoleon's former [[Marshal of France|Marshal]], who was in line for the Swedish throne. Napoleon was offered to keep the throne in February 1814, on the condition that France returned to its 1792 frontiers, but he refused.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 329&lt;/ref&gt; The feasibility of the Restoration was in doubt, but the allure of peace to a war-weary French public, and demonstrations of support for the Bourbons in Paris, [[Bordeaux]], [[Marseille]], and [[Lyon]]s, helped assure the Allies.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 330, 331&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis&lt;/span&gt;, in accordance with the [[Declaration of Saint-Ouen]],&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 271&lt;/ref&gt; granted a written constitution, the [[Charter of 1814]], which guaranteed a [[bicameral legislature]] with a hereditary/appointive [[Chamber of Peers (France)|Chamber of Peers]] and an elected [[Chamber of Deputies of France|Chamber of Deputies]] – their role was consultative (except on taxation), as only the King had the power to propose or sanction laws, and appoint or recall ministers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Furet, p. 272&quot;&gt;Furet, p. 272&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Suffrage|franchise]] was limited to men with considerable property holdings, and around 1% of people could vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;Furet, p. 272&quot;/&gt; Many of the legal, administrative, and economic reforms of the revolutionary period were left intact; the [[Napoleonic Code]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Furet, p. 272&quot;/&gt;, which guaranteed legal equality and civil liberties, the peasants' ''[[biens nationaux]]'', and the new system of dividing the country into &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[departments of France|départments]]''&lt;/span&gt; were not undone by the new king. Relations between church and state remained regulated by the [[Concordat of 1801]]. However, in spite of the fact that the Charter was a condition of the Restoration, the preamble declared it to be a 'concession and grant', given 'by the free exercise of our royal authority'.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 332&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:La famille royale et les alliées s'occupant du bonheur de l'Europe from NPG.jpg|thumb|upright|Popular colored etching, verging on caricature, published by Décrouant, early 19th century: ''La famille royale et les alliées s'occupant du bonheur de l'Europe'' (''The Royal Family and the Allies concerned with the Happiness of Europe'')]]
After a first sentimental flush of popularity, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis&lt;/span&gt;' gestures towards reversing the results of the [[French Revolution]] quickly lost him support among the disenfranchised majority. Symbolic acts, such as the replacement of the [[Flag of France|tricolore]] with the [[White flag#Ancien Régime in France|white flag]], the titling of Louis as the 'XVIII' (as successor to [[Louis XVII of France|Louis XVII]], who never ruled) and as 'King of France' rather than 'King of the French', and the monarchy's recognition of the anniversaries of the deaths of [[Louis XVI]] and [[Marie Antoinette]] were significant. A more tangible source of antagonism was the pressure applied to possessors of ''biens nationaux'' by the Catholic Church and returning ''[[émigré]]s'' to give back their lands.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 332, 333&lt;/ref&gt; Other groups bearing ill sentiment towards Louis included the army, non-Catholics, and workers hit by a post-war slump and British imports.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 333&quot;&gt;Tombs, p. 333&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second Restoration (1815)===
Napoleon's emissaries informed him of this brewing discontent,&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 333&quot;/&gt; and, on 20 March 1815, he returned to Paris from [[Elba]]. On his [[Route Napoléon]], most troops sent to stop his march, including some that were nominally royalist, felt more inclined to join the former Emperor than to stop him.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ingram|1998|p=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; Louis was forced to flee Paris to [[Ghent]] on 19 March,&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 334&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 278&lt;/ref&gt; but returned after the [[Battle of Waterloo]] ended Napoleon's rule of the [[Hundred Days]]. In Louis' absence, a small revolt in the traditionally pro-royalist [[Vendée]] was put down, but there were otherwise few subversive acts favouring the Restoration, even though Napoleon's popularity began to flag.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|pp=32, 33}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Talleyrand floatingwiththetide0001.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Périgord]], who served under several regimes, depicted &quot;floating with the tide&quot;]]
Talleyrand was again influential in seeing that the Bourbons reigned, as was [[Joseph Fouché|Fouché]],&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 335&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 279&lt;/ref&gt; Napoleon's minister of police during the Hundred Days. This Second Restoration saw the beginning of the [[Second White Terror]], largely in the south, when supporters of the monarchy sought revenge against those who had supported Napoleon's return, killing 200–300 and forcing thousands to flee. The perpetrators were often known as the ''[[:fr:Verdets (royalistes)|Verdets]]'' because of their green cockets, which was the colour of the comte d'Artois – this being the title of Charles X at the time, who was associated with the hardline [[ultra-royalist]]s, or Ultras. After a period in which local authorities were powerless to stop the violence, the King and his ministers sent out their own officials to restore order.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 336&quot;&gt;Tombs, p. 336&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Treaty of Paris (1815)|Second Treaty of Paris]] was signed on 20 November 1815, which had more punitive terms than the [[Treaty of Paris (1814)|First]]. France was ordered to pay 700 million francs in indemnities, and the country's borders were reduced to their 1790 level. After the [[Battle of Waterloo]], France was occupied by 1.2&amp;nbsp;million foreign soldiers; occupation continued until 1818, by around 200,000 Allies, and France was made to pay the costs of their accommodation and rations, on top of the reparations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 337&quot;&gt;Tombs, p. 337&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Philological-Society-161&gt;Staff. ''[[The European Magazine, and London Review]]'', Philological Society (Great Britain), January 1918 [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=mOwRAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA161 p. 161]&lt;/ref&gt; The promise of tax cuts, prominent in 1814, failed to actualize because of these payments. The legacy of this, and the White Terror, left Louis with a formidable opposition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 337&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Élie, comte Decazes.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Élie, duc Decazes|Élie, 1st comte Decazes]], remained loyal to the Bourbons during the Hundred Days and was the most powerful minister from 1818 to 1820]]
&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis&lt;/span&gt;' chief ministers were at first moderate,&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 336&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Tuer Bury|2003|p=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; including &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Talleyrand&lt;/span&gt;, the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Armand-Emmanuel de Vignerot du Plessis, Duc de Richelieu|Duc de Richelieu]]&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Élie, duc Decazes]]&lt;/span&gt;; &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis&lt;/span&gt; himself followed a cautious policy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Furet, p. 281&quot;&gt;Furet, p. 281&lt;/ref&gt;  The &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[chambre introuvable]]''&lt;/span&gt;, [[French legislative election, 1815|elected in 1815]] and given the nickname &quot;unobtainable&quot; by Louis, due to the overwhelming ultra-royalist majority, threw out the Talleyrand-Fouché government and sought to legitimize the White Terror, passing trial against enemies of the state, sacking 50,000–80,000 civil service members, and dismissing 15,000 army officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 337&quot;/&gt; &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Richelieu&lt;/span&gt;, an ''émigré'' who had left in October 1789, who &quot;had had nothing at all to do with the new France&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Furet, p. 281&quot;/&gt; was appointed [[Prime Minister of France|Prime Minister]]. The ''chambre introuvable'', meanwhile, continued to aggressively uphold the place of the monarchy and the church, and called for more commemorations for historical royal figures.&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 282. This included blocking the budget over plans to guarantee bonds on the sale of 400,000 hectares of forest previously owned by the church, reintroducing prohibition of divorce (Alexander, p. 37, 38), demanding the death penalty for individuals found with the tricolore (Alexander, p. 37, 38), and attempting to hand civil registers back to the church (Alexander, p. 37, 38).&lt;/ref&gt; Over the course of the parliamentary term, the ultra-royalists increasingly began to fuse their brand of politics with state ceremony, much to Louis' chagrin.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; Decazes, perhaps the most moderate minister, moved to stop the politicization of the [[National Guard (France)|National Guard]] (many ''Verdets'' had been drafted in) by banning political demonstrations by the militia in July 1816.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, p. 54, 58&lt;/ref&gt;

Owing to contrasting standpoints of the chamber and the King, the ultra-royalists began to assert the Chamber of Deputies' rights. This resulted in a concession from the government that the chamber had the right to approve state expenditure, granted after the ultra-royalists attempted to obstruct the 1816 budget. However, they were unable to gain a guarantee from the King that his cabinets would represent the majority in parliament.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1816, the chamber was dissolved by Louis for its reactionary measures, and electoral manipulation resulted in a more liberal [[French legislative election, 1816|chamber in 1816]]. Richelieu served until 29 December 1818, followed by [[Jean-Joseph, Marquis Dessolles]] until 19 November 1819, and then Decazes (in reality the dominant minister from 1818 to 1820)&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 338&quot;&gt;Tombs, p. 338&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 289&lt;/ref&gt; until 20 February 1820. This was the era in which the ''[[Doctrinaires]]'' dominated policy. The following year, the government changed the electoral laws, resorting to [[gerrymandering]], and altering the franchise to allow some rich men of trade and industry to vote,&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 289, 290&lt;/ref&gt; in an attempt to prevent the ultras of winning a majority in future elections. Press censorship was clarified and relaxed, some positions in the military hierarchy were made open to competition, and mutual schools were set up that encroached on the Catholic monopoly of public primary education.&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 290&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt; Decazes purged a number of ultra-royalist [[Prefect (France)|prefects]] and sub-prefects, and in by-elections, an unusually high proportion of [[Bonapartists]] and republicans were elected, some of whom were backed by ultras resorting to [[tactical voting]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 338&quot;/&gt; The ultras were strongly critical of the practice of giving civil service employment or promotions to deputies, as the government continued to consolidate its position.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:François-René de Chateaubriand by Anne-Louis Girodet de Roucy Trioson.jpg|thumb|upright|[[François-René de Chateaubriand]], a [[Romanticism|Romantic]] writer who sat in the [[Chamber of Peers (France)|Chamber of Peers]]]]
By 1820, the opposition liberals, who with the ultras made up half the chamber, proved unmanageable, and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Decazes&lt;/span&gt; and the king were looking for ways to revise the electoral laws again, to ensure a more tractable conservative majority. The assassination of the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Charles Ferdinand, Duke of Berry|Duc de Berry]]&lt;/span&gt;, the ultrareactionary son of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis&lt;/span&gt;' ultrareactionary brother and heir-presumptive, the future &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Charles X of France|Charles X]]&lt;/span&gt;, by a Bonapartist in February 1820, triggered &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Decazes&lt;/span&gt;' fall from power and the triumph of the Ultras.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 339&quot;&gt;Tombs, p. 339&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Richelieu&lt;/span&gt; returned to power for a short interval, from 1820 to 1821. The press was more strongly censored, detention without trial was reintroduced, and ''Doctrinaire'' leaders, such as [[François Guizot]], were banned from teaching at the [[École Normale Supérieure]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 339&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 291&lt;/ref&gt; Under Richelieu, the franchise was changed to give the wealthiest electors a double vote, in time for the [[French legislative election, 1820|November 1820 election]]. After a resounding victory, a new Ultra ministry was formed, headed by &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean-Baptiste de Villèle]]&lt;/span&gt;, a leading Ultra who served for six years. The ultras found themselves back in power in favourable circumstances: Berry's wife, the [[Princess Caroline of Naples and Sicily|duchesse de Berry]], gave birth to &quot;miracle child&quot;, [[Henry, Count of Chambord|Henri]], seven months after the duc's death; [[Napoleon]] died on [[Saint Helena]] in 1821, and his son, the [[Napoleon II|duc de Reichstadt]], remained interned in Austrian hands. Literary figures, most notably [[François-René de Chateaubriand|Chateaubriand]], but also [[Victor Hugo|Hugo]], [[Alphonse de Lamartine|Lamartine]], [[Alfred de Vigny|Vigny]], and [[Charles Nodier|Nodier]], rallied to the ultras' cause. Both Hugo and Lamartine later became republicans, whilst Nodier was formerly.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 340&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 295&lt;/ref&gt; Soon, however, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Villèle&lt;/span&gt; proved himself to be nearly as cautious as his master, and, so long as &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis&lt;/span&gt; lived, overtly reactionary policies were kept to a minimum.

[[File:Cruikshank - Old Bumblehead.png|thumb|left|upright|Caricature of Louis preparing for the Spanish expedition, by [[George Cruikshank]]]]
{{Anchor|Spanish Intervention of 1823}}&lt;!-- This anchor is a target of links. Please do not remove it. --&gt;
The ultras broadened their support, and put a stop to growing military dissent in 1823, when intervention in [[Spain]], in favour of Spanish Bourbon King [[Ferdinand VII of Spain|Ferdinand VII]], and against the [[Trienio Liberal|Liberal Spanish Government]], fomented popular patriotic fervour. Despite British backing for the military action, the intervention was widely seen as an attempt to win back influence in Spain, which had been lost to the British under Napoleon. The French army, called the [[Hundred Thousand Sons of Saint Louis]], was led by the [[Louis Antoine, Duke of Angoulême|duc d'Angoulême]], the comte d'Artois's son. The French troops marched to [[Madrid]] and then to [[Cadiz]], ousting the Liberals with little fighting (April to September 1823), and would remain in Spain for five years. Support for the ultras was further strengthened by doling out favours in a similar fashion to the 1816 chamber, and fears over the ''charbonnerie'', the French equivalent of the ''[[carbonari]]''. In the [[French legislative election, 1824|1824 election]], another large majority was secured.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 340, 341; Crawley, p. 681&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis XVIII&lt;/span&gt; died on 16 September 1824, and was succeeded by his brother, the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;comte d'Artois&lt;/span&gt;, who took the title of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Charles X of France|Charles X]]&lt;/span&gt;.

== &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt;, 1824–1830 ==
[[File:François Pascal Simon Gérard 006.JPG|thumb|upright|&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Charles X of France|Charles X]]&lt;/span&gt;, by François Gérard]]
The ascension to the throne of Charles X, the leader of the [[ultra-royalist]] faction, coincided with the ultras' control of power in the Chamber of Deputies; thus, the ministry of the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean-Baptiste de Villèle|comte de Villèle]]&lt;/span&gt; was able to continue, and the last &quot;restraint&quot; (i.e., Louis) on the ultra-royalists was removed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 341&quot;&gt;Tombs, p. 341&lt;/ref&gt; As the country underwent a [[Christian revival]] in the post-[[French Revolution|Revolutionary]] years, the ultras saw fit to upraise the status of the Roman Catholic Church once more.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 341&quot;/&gt; The [[Concordat of 11 June 1817]] was set to replace the [[Concordat of 1801]], but, despite being signed, it was never validated. The &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Villèle&lt;/span&gt; government, under pressure from the ''[[:fr:Chevaliers de la Foi|Chevaliers de la Foi]]'', which many deputies were members of, voted on the [[Anti-Sacrilege Act]] in January 1825, which punished by death the theft of [[Sacramental bread|consecrated hosts]] as [[parricide]]. The law was unenforceable and only enacted for symbolic purposes, though the act's passing caused a considerable uproar, particularly among the ''[[Doctrinaires]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 341, 342&quot;&gt;Tombs, p. 341, 342&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Coronation_of_Charles_X_of_France_by_François_Gérard,_circa_1827.jpg|left|thumb|''Coronation of Charles X of France'', by François Gérard]]
On 29 May 1825, Charles received his coronation in [[Reims]], in an opulent and spectacular ceremony that was reminiscent of the royal pomp of the [[Coronation of the French monarch|coronations]] of the ''[[Ancien Régime in France|Ancien Régime]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 301, 302&lt;/ref&gt; Some innovations were included, upon request by Villèle: though Charles was hostile towards the 1814 Charter, commitment to the 'constitutional charter' was affirmed, and four of Napoleon's generals were in attendance. The [[Reims Cathedral]] was decorated to portray the union of Altar and Throne, and [[Charles Percier]], the architect, adorned the building with [[Gothic Revival architecture|Neo-Gothic]] décor, in a style that evoked the [[Middle Ages]], rather than the Roman-influenced &quot;[[Empire style]]&quot; that he was renowned for. Charles was anointed with the sacred oil brought from heaven by a dove in 496; he prostrated himself before the [[altar]]; and received the ring, sceptre, hand of justice and then the crown. Charles even touched some people ill with [[scrofula]],&lt;ref&gt;This practice, common among monarchs in France and England, was written about by [[Annales School]] historian [[Marc Bloch]] in ''Les Rois Thaumaturges'' (1924), later translated as ''The Royal Touch'' (1990)&lt;/ref&gt; and some were reported to have recovered. Hugo, Lamartine, and [[Gioachino Rossini|Rossini]] lauded over the ceremony, while critics saw cause for alarm, and [[Pierre-Jean de Béranger|Béranger]] notoriously mocked the King in a song, titled &quot;The Coronation of King Charles the Simple&quot;. Others went as far as to accuse Charles of being a crypto-[[Jesuit]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 341, 342&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Furet, p. 300–303&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Davies, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt;

In the months preceding the ceremony, the chambers approved legislation that paid an indemnity to ''émigrés'', who had suffered by the confiscation of their lands during the Revolution, and the requirement that all children would inherit an equal share of land; thus, ending the law of [[primogeniture]]. Although this law had been engineered by Louis, Charles was influential in seeing that it was passed. A bill to finance this compensation, by converting government debt (the ''rente'') from 5% to 3% [[Government bond|bond]]s, which would save the state 30 million [[French franc|franc]]s a year in interest payments, was also put before the chambers. Villèle's government argued that ''rentiers'' had seen their returns grow disproportionately, compared to their original investment, and that the redistribution was just and would reconcile ''émigrés'' to post-Revolutionary France; whereas, the opposition accused the ultras of taking money from small investors for disloyal nobles. The bill was eventually defeated in the Peers, where there was still a liberal contingent sitting, mainly appointees of Decazes. When the bill to reimburse ''émigrés'' went through in April, at a cost to the state of approximately 988 million francs (''le milliard des émigrés''), it was financed by government bonds at a value of 600&amp;nbsp;million francs, at an interest rate of 3%. Around 18&amp;nbsp;million francs were paid to the ''émigrés'' per year.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 342, 343&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Price, p. 116, 117&lt;/ref&gt;

The state's payments were slower than expected, as the market value of the bonds fell; a quarter of those reimbursed received only 250 francs a year. Ironically, the main beneficiaries were perhaps the owners of ''[[biens nationaux]]'', numbering around one million, as their property had been guaranteed as one of the conditions for the act's passing, which subsequently led to a rise in the value of their land.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 343&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1826, Villèle introduced a bill reestablishing the law of primogeniture; at least, it would be automatic for owners of large estates, unless they chose otherwise. The liberal Peers and press rebelled, as did some dissident ultras, such as Chateaubriand. The forcefulness of this criticism prompted the government to introduce a bill to restrict the press in December, having largely withdrawn censorship in 1824;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Apostle of Liberty: Life of La Fayette|author=Maurice de La Fuye, Émile Albert Babeau|year=1956|chapter=Truth beyond the Atlantic, Error on his Side|page=281|publisher=T. Yoseloff}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tuer Bury, p. 34&quot;&gt;Tuer Bury, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; this, however, only aggravated the ultras' opponents more, and the bill was withdrawn.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 344, 345&lt;/ref&gt;

The &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Villèle&lt;/span&gt; cabinet faced increasing pressure in 1827 from the liberal press, including the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[Journal des débats]]''&lt;/span&gt;, which hosted &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[François-René de Chateaubriand|Chateaubriand]]&lt;/span&gt;'s articles. Chateaubriand, the most prominent of the anti-Villèle ultras, had combined with others opposed to press censorship laws (a new law had reimposed it on 24 July 1827) to form the ''Société des amis de la liberté de la presse''; [[Claude Antoine Gabriel, duc de Choiseul-Stainville|Choiseul-Stainville]], [[Narcisse-Achille de Salvandy|Salvandy]] and [[Abel-François Villemain|Villemain]] were among the contributors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Election of 1827 in France|author=Sherman Kent|publisher=[[Harvard University Press]]|year=1975|isbn=0-674-24321-8|pages=81–83}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another influential society was the ''Société, [[Aide-toi, le ciel t'aidera]]'', which worked within the confines of legislation, banning the unauthorized assemblage of more than 20 members. The group, emboldened by the rising tide of opposition, was of a more liberal composition (it was associated with ''[[Le Globe]]'') and included members such as [[François Guizot|Guizot]], [[Charles de Rémusat|Rémusat]], and [[Odilon Barrot|Barrot]].&lt;ref&gt;Kent, p. 84–89&lt;/ref&gt; Pamphlets were sent out which evaded the censorship laws, and the group provided organizational assistance to liberal candidates against pro-government state officials in the [[French legislative election, 1827|November 1827 election]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 345&quot;&gt;Tombs, p. 345&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 1827, the King and Villèle were confronted by an unruly [[National Guard (France)|National Guard]]. The garrison which Charles reviewed, under orders to express deference to the king but disapproval of his government, instead shouted derogatory anti-Jesuit remarks at his devoutly Catholic niece, [[Marie Thérèse of France|Marie Thérèse, Madame la Dauphine]]. Villèle suffered worse treatment, as liberal officers led troops to protest at his office. In response, the Guard was disbanded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tombs, p. 345&quot;/&gt; Pamphlets continued to be proliferated, which included accusations in September that Charles, on a trip to the northern ''départments'', was holed up in [[Saint-Omer]], was colluding with the [[Pope]] and planned to reinstate the [[tithe]], and had suspended the Charter under the protection of a loyal garrison army.&lt;ref&gt;Kent, p. 111&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time of the election, the moderate royalists (constitutionalists) were also beginning to turn against Charles, as was the business community, in part due to a financial crisis in 1825, that was blamed on the government's passing of the law of indemnification.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 344&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kent, p. 107–110&lt;/ref&gt; Hugo and a number of other writers, dissatisfied with the reality of life under Charles X, also began to criticize the regime.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 346, 347&lt;/ref&gt; In preparation for the 30 September registration cut-off for the election, opposition committees worked furiously to get as many voters as possible signed up, countering the actions of ''préfects'', who began removing certain voters who had failed to provide up-to-date documents since the 1824 election. 18,000 voters were added to the 60,000 on the first list; despite préfect attempts to register those who met the franchise and were supporters of the government, this can mainly be attributed to opposition activity.&lt;ref&gt;Kent, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; Organization was mainly divided behind Chateaubriand's Friends and the ''Aide-toi''; the ''Aide-toi'' backed liberals, ''constitutionnels'', and the ''contre-opposition'' (constitutional monarchists).&lt;ref&gt;Kent, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;

The new chamber did not result in a clear majority for any side. &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Villèle&lt;/span&gt;'s successor, the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jean Baptiste Gay, vicomte de Martignac|vicomte de Martignac]]&lt;/span&gt;, who began his term in January 1828, tried to steer a middle course, appeasing liberals by loosening press controls, expelling Jesuits, modifying electoral registration, and restricting the formation of Catholic schools.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 348&lt;/ref&gt; Charles, unhappy with the new government, surrounded himself with men from the ''[[Chevaliers de la Foi]]'' and other ultras, such as the [[Jules, 3rd Duke of Polignac|Prince de Polignac]] and [[François Régis de La Bourdonnaye|La Bourdonnaye]]. Martignac was deposed when his government lost a bill on local government. Charles and his advisers believed a new government could be formed with the support of the Villèle, Chateaubriand, and Decazes monarchist factions, but chose a chief minister, Polignac, in November 1829 who was repellant to the liberals and, worse, Chateaubriand. Though Charles remained nonchalant, the deadlock led some royalists to call for a ''coup'', and prominent liberals for a tax strike.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 348, 349&lt;/ref&gt;

At the opening of the session in March 1830, the King delivered a speech that contained veiled threats to the opposition; in response, 221 deputies (an absolute majority) condemned the government, and Charles subsequently [[legislative session#Procedure in Commonwealth realms|prorogue]]d and then dissolved parliament. Charles retained a belief that he was popular amongst the unenfranchised mass of the people, and he and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Polignac&lt;/span&gt; chose to pursue an ambitious foreign policy of colonialism and expansionism, with the assistance of Russia. France had intervened in the Mediterranean a number of times after Villèle's resignation, and expeditions were now sent to Greece and [[Madagascar]]. Polignac also initiated French colonization in [[Algeria]]; victory was announced over the [[Dey of Algiers]] in early June. Plans were drawn up to invade Belgium, which was shortly to undergo its [[Belgian Revolution|own revolution]]. However, foreign policy did not prove sufficient to divert attention from domestic problems.&lt;ref&gt;Tombs, p. 349, 350&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tuer Bury, p. 39, 42&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Eugène Delacroix - La liberté guidant le peuple.jpg|thumb|upright|The July Revolution of 1830 led to the abdication of Charles X and the end of the Bourbon Restoration]]
Charles's dissolution of the chamber of deputies, his ''[[July Ordinances]]'', which set up rigid control of the press, and his restriction of [[suffrage]] resulted in the [[July Revolution]] of 1830. The major cause of the regime's downfall, however, was that, while it managed to keep the support of the aristocracy, the Catholic Church and even much of the peasantry, the ultras' cause was deeply unpopular outside of parliament and with those who did not hold the franchise,&lt;ref name=&quot;Tuer Bury, p. 34&quot;/&gt; especially the industrial workers and the bourgeoisie.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hudson|1973|pp=182, 183}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Charles abdicated in favor of his grandson, the [[Comte de Chambord]], and left for England. However, the liberal, bourgeois-controlled Chamber of Deputies refused to confirm the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Comte de Chambord&lt;/span&gt; as &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Henri V&lt;/span&gt;. In a vote largely boycotted by conservative deputies, the body declared the French throne vacant, and elevated [[Louis Philippe I|Louis-Philippe, Duke of Orléans]], to power.

== The Fall of the ''Restoration'', 1827–1830 ==
[[File:Coat of Arms of the Bourbon Restoration (1815-30).svg|thumb|left|upright|[[National Emblem of France|Coat of Arms of France]], used during the Restoration]]
There is still considerable debate among historians as to the actual cause of the downfall of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt;. What is generally conceded, though, is that between 1820 and 1830, a series of economic downturns, combined with the rise of a liberal opposition within the Chamber of Deputies, ultimately felled the conservative Bourbons.&lt;ref&gt;Pilbeam (1999), p. 40, 41&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1827 and 1830, France faced an economic downturn, industrial and agricultural, that was possibly worse than the one that sparked the [[French Revolution|Revolution of 1789]]. A series of progressively worsening grain harvests in the late 1820s pushed up the prices on various [[staple food]]s and [[cash crop]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Tuer Bury, p. 38&lt;/ref&gt; In response, the rural peasantry throughout France lobbied for the relaxation of protective tariffs on grain, in order to lower prices and ease their economic situation. However, Charles X, bowing to pressure from wealthier landowners, kept the tariffs in place. He did so based upon the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bourbon&lt;/span&gt; response to the &quot;[[Year Without a Summer]]&quot; in 1816, during which &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis XVIII&lt;/span&gt; relaxed tariffs during a series of famines, caused a downturn in prices, and incurred the ire of wealthy landowners, who were the traditional source of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Bourbon&lt;/span&gt; legitimacy. Thus, peasants throughout France, between 1827 and 1830, faced a period of relative economic hardship and rising prices.

At the same time, international pressures, combined with weakened purchasing power from the provinces, led to decreased economic activity in urban centers. This industrial downturn contributed to the rising poverty levels among Parisian artisans. Thus, by 1830, multiple demographics had suffered from the economic policies of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt;.

While the French economy faltered, a series of elections brought a relatively powerful liberal bloc into the Chamber of Deputies. The 17-strong liberal bloc of 1824 grew to 180 in 1827, and 274 in 1830. This liberal majority grew increasingly dissatisfied with the policies of the centrist &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Martignac]]&lt;/span&gt; and the ultra-royalist &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jules, 3rd Duke of Polignac|Polignac]]&lt;/span&gt;, seeking to protect the limited protections of the Charter of 1814. They sought both the expansion of the franchise, and more liberal economic policies. They also demanded the right, as the majority bloc, to appoint the Prime Minister and the Cabinet.

Also, the growth of the liberal bloc within the Chamber of Deputies corresponded roughly with the rise of a liberal press within France. Generally centered around Paris, this press provided a counterpoint to the government's journalistic services, and to the newspapers of the right. It grew increasingly important in conveying political opinions and the political situation to the Parisian public, and can thus be seen as a crucial link between the rise of the liberals and the increasingly agitated and economically suffering French masses.

By 1830, the Restoration government of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt; faced difficulties on all sides. The new liberal majority clearly had no intention of budging in the face of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Polignac&lt;/span&gt;'s aggressive policies. The rise of a liberal press within Paris, that outsold the official government newspaper, indicated a general shift in Parisian politics towards the left. And yet, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles&lt;/span&gt;' base of power was certainly toward the right of the political spectrum, as were his own views. He simply could not yield to the growing demands from within the Chamber of Deputies. The situation would soon come to a head.
{{Governments_of France}}

== The Four Ordinances ==
{{Main|July Ordinances|July Revolution}}

Technically, the Charter of 1814 had made France a constitutional monarchy. While the King retained extensive power over policy-making, as well as the sole power of the Executive, he was, nonetheless, reliant upon the Parliament to accept and pass his legal decrees. The Charter also fixed the method of election of the Deputies, their rights within the Chamber of Deputies, and the rights of the majority bloc. Thus, in 1830, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt; faced a significant problem. He could not overstep his constitutional bounds, and yet, he could not preserve his policies with a liberal majority within the Chamber of Deputies. Stark action was required.

A final no-confidence vote by the liberals, in March 1830, spurred the king into action, and he set about to alter the Charter of 1814 by decree. These decrees, known as the &quot;Four Ordinances&quot;, or the &quot;Ordinances of Saint-Cloud&quot;, were:

#Dissolution of the Chamber of Deputies
#Restriction of the Press Laws
#Restriction of the franchise to only the wealthiest within France
#Immediate new elections based upon the new electorate

Word spread quickly of the king's intent. On 10 July 1830, before the king had even made his declarations, a group of wealthy, liberal journalists and newspaper proprietors, led by &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Adolphe Thiers]]&lt;/span&gt;, met in Paris to decide upon a strategy to counter &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt;. It was decided then, nearly three weeks before the Revolution, that in the event of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles&lt;/span&gt;' expected proclamations, the journalistic establishment of Paris would publish vitriolic criticisms of the king's policies in an attempt to mobilize the masses. Thus, when &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt; made his declarations on the 25 July 1830, the liberal journalism machine mobilized, publishing articles and complaints decrying the despotism of the king's actions.

The urban mobs of Paris also mobilized, driven by patriotic fervor and economic hardship, assembling barricades and attacking the infrastructure of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt;. Within days, the situation escalated beyond the ability of the monarchy to control it. As the Crown moved to shut down liberal periodicals, the radical Parisian masses defended those publications. They also launched attacks against pro-Bourbon presses, and paralyzed the coercive apparatus of the monarchy. Seizing the opportunity, the liberals in Parliament began drafting resolutions, complaints, and censures against the king.

The king finally abdicated on 30 July 1830. Twenty minutes later, his son, [[Louis Antoine, Duke of Angoulême]], who had nominally succeeded as Louis XIX, also abdicated, having lasted what is believed to be the shortest reign on record. The Crown nominally then fell upon the son of Louis Antoine's younger brother, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Charles X&lt;/span&gt;'s grandson, who became &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Henri V&lt;/span&gt;, with Louis-Phillippe, Duc d'Orléans, as Lieutenant-General of the realm. However, the newly-empowered Chamber of Deputies declared the throne vacant, and on 9 August, elevated &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis-Philippe&lt;/span&gt;, to the throne. Thus, the [[July Monarchy]] began.

== &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis-Philippe&lt;/span&gt; and the House of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Orléans&lt;/span&gt; ==
&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Louis-Philippe&lt;/span&gt; ascended the throne on the strength of the [[July Revolution]] of 1830, and ruled, not as &quot;King of France&quot; but as &quot;King of the French&quot;, marking the shift to [[national sovereignty]]. The [[Orléanist]]s remained in power until 1848. Following the ousting of the last king to rule France during the [[February 1848 Revolution]], the [[French Second Republic|Second Republic]] was formed with the election of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Napoleon III|Louis-Napoléon Bonaparte]]&lt;/span&gt; as President (1848–1852). In the [[French coup of 1851]], Napoleon declared himself Emperor [[Napoleon III]] of the [[Second French Empire|Second Empire]], which lasted from 1852 to 1870.

== Political parties under Restoration ==
[[Political party|Political parties]] saw substantial changes of alignment and membership under the Restoration. The Chamber of Deputies oscillated between repressive ''ultra-royalist'' phases and progressive ''liberal'' phases. Opponents of the monarchy were absent from the political scene, because of the repression of the ''[[Second White Terror|White Terror]]''. Individuals of influence who had different visions of the French [[constitutional monarchy]] clashed.

All parties remained fearful of the common people, whom [[Adolphe Thiers]] later referred to by the term &quot;cheap multitude&quot;. Their political sights were set on a favoritism of class. Political changes in the Chamber were due to abuse by the majority tendency, involving a dissolution and then an inversion of the majority, or critical events; for example, the assassination of the [[Charles Ferdinand, Duke of Berry|Duc de Berry]] in 1820.

Disputes were a power struggle between the powerful (royalty against deputies) rather than a fight between royalty and populism. Although the deputies claimed to defend the interests of the people, most had an important fear of common people, of innovations, of socialism and even of simple measures, such as the extension of [[voting rights]].

The principal political parties during the Restoration were:

=== &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Constitutionnels&lt;/span&gt; ===
&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Constitutionnels]]&lt;/span&gt; were mostly rich and educated middle-class men: lawyers, senior officials of the Empire, and academics. They feared the triumph of the aristocracy, as much as that of the democrats. They accepted the charter, because it guaranteed freedom and civil equality and created a barrier to the popular masses who were considered unable, because of their ignorance, to be involved in the management of public affairs. Important personalities were [[Pierre Paul Royer-Collard]], [[François Guizot]], and the count of &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Serre&lt;/span&gt;. Their newspapers were ''[[Le Courrier Français]]'' and ''[[Le Censeur]]''.

=== &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;Doctrinaires&lt;/span&gt; ===
&lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Doctrinaires]]&lt;/span&gt; promoted a return to a moderate monarchy and were opposed to the extremists in the early period of the Restoration. The most prominent ''Doctrinaire'' newspaper was ''[[:fr:Le Courrier français|Le Courrier français]]''.

=== Independents ===
Independents were mostly [[lower middle class]]: doctors and lawyers, bourgeoisie, men of law, and, in rural constituencies, traders of national goods. They rejected the charter, considering it too conservative. They rejected the treaties of 1815, the white flag and the pre-eminence of clergy and of [[nobility]]. Important personalities were parliamentary monarchist &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Benjamin Constant]]&lt;/span&gt;, officer of the Empire &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Maximilien Sebastien Foy]]&lt;/span&gt;, republican lawyer &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jacques-Antoine Manuel]]&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Gilbert du Motier, marquis de Lafayette]]&lt;/span&gt;. Their newspapers were &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[La Minerve (French newspaper)|La Minerve]]''&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[Le Constitutionnel]]''&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[Le Globe]]''&lt;/span&gt;.

=== Liberal royalists ===
[[Liberalism|Liberals]] appeared as a party in the last years of the Restoration. Liberal royalists preached movement towards more liberty and openness. They wished to lower the taxable quota to support the middle-class as a whole, to the detriment of the aristocracy. Liberals had profited from the emergence of a new middle-class elite, due to the [[Industrial Revolution]], which upset the aristocratic order.

=== Republicans ===
Facing the representatives of the middle class, the [[republicanism|Republican]]s, then situated on the extreme left, addressed the miserable world of the worker. Workers were not represented, nor listened to. Their demonstrations were repressed or diverted, causing, at most, a reinforcement of [[parliamentarism]], which did not mean democratic evolution, only wider taxation. For some, such as &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis Auguste Blanqui|Blanqui]]&lt;/span&gt;, revolution seemed the only solution. [[Louis-Antoine Garnier-Pagès|Garnier-Pagès]], and [[Louis-Eugène Cavaignac|Louis-Eugène]] and [[Éléonore-Louis Godefroi Cavaignac]] considered themselves to be Republicans, while [[Étienne Cabet|Cabet]] and [[François-Vincent Raspail|Raspail]] were active as socialists. [[Claude Henri de Rouvroy, comte de Saint-Simon|Saint-Simon]] was also active during this period, and made direct appeals to Louis XVIII before his death in 1825.&lt;ref&gt;Kirkup, T., ''A History of Socialism'' (London: Adam and Charles Black, 1892), p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Ultra-royalists ===
[[Ultra-royalist]]s wished for a return to the &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Ancien Régime in France|''Ancien Régime'']]&lt;/span&gt;, such as before 1789, with a view toward [[Political absolutism|absolutism]]: domination by the nobility and &quot;other devoted Christians&quot;. They were anti-Republican, anti-[[Democratic]], and preached ''Government on High'', by a marked noble elite. They tolerated &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''vote censitaire''&lt;/span&gt;: a form of democracy limited to taxpayers. [[Ultra-royalist]]s were interested in preserving aristocracy and promoting [[Political absolutism|absolutism]]. They found the [[Charter of 1814]] to be too revolutionary. The ultra-royalists wanted a return to [[absolute monarchy]], the re-establishment of privileges, and a king: &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Charles X of France|Charles X]]&lt;/span&gt;.

Prominent ultra-royalists theorists were &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Louis de Bonald]]&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Joseph de Maistre]]&lt;/span&gt;. Their parliamentary leaders were &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[:fr:François Régis de La Bourdonnaye|François Régis de La Bourdonnaye]]&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;comte de La Bretèche&lt;/span&gt; and, in 1829, &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Jules, 3rd Duke of Polignac|Jules de Polignac]]&lt;/span&gt;. Their main newspapers were &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[La Quotidienne]]''&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;''[[La Gazette]]''&lt;/span&gt;; other royalist papers included the ''Drapeau Blanc'', named after the Bourbon white flag, and the ''[[Oriflamme]]'', named after the battle standard of France.

===Popular culture===
The French Historical film [[Jacquou le Croquant]] directed by [[Laurent Boutonnat]], starring [[Gaspard Ulliel]] and [[Marie-Jos%C3%A9e_Croze|Marie-Josée Croze]] is based on the background of Bourbon Restoration.

== See also ==
{{Div col|2}}
* &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Pierre Louis Jean Casimir de Blacas]]&lt;/span&gt;
* &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;[[Mathieu de Montmorency]]&lt;/span&gt;
* [[French Empire mantel clock]]
* [[French monarchs family tree]]
* [[France in the long nineteenth century]]
{{Div col end}}

===Literature===
* ''[[Les Misérables]]'', [[Victor Hugo]]'s novel which is set in the 20 years after Napoleon's Hundred Days
* ''[[The Red and the Black]]'', [[Stendhal]]'s novel set in the final years of the regime
* ''[[La Comédie humaine]]'', a sequence of almost 100 novels and plays by [[Honoré de Balzac]], set during the Restoration and the July Monarchy

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=lower-alpha|refs=
&lt;ref name=nb&gt;20 March-8 July 1815, 111 days except in the common acceptable period title in [[historiography]], bestowed by committee of historians as a common term.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Reflist|2}}

== References ==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last=Alexander |first=Robert |title=Re-Writing the French Revolutionary Tradition: Liberal Opposition and the Fall of the Bourbon Monarchy |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |year=2003 |isbn=0-521-80122-2}}
*{{cite book |last=Tuer Bury |first=John Patrick |title=France, 1814–1940 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |year=2003 |isbn=0-415-31600-6}}
*{{cite book |last=Collingham |first=Hugh A. C. |title=The July Monarchy: A Political History of France, 1830–1848 |location=London |publisher=Longman |year=1988 |isbn=0-582-02186-3}}
*{{cite book |last=Crawley |first=C. W. |year=1969 |title=The New Cambridge Modern History. Volume IX: War and Peace in an Age of Upheaval, 1793–1830 |location=Cambridge |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn= 978-0-521-04547-6}}
*{{cite book |last=Davies |first=Peter |title=The Extreme Right in France, 1789 to the Present: From De Maistre to Le Pen |publisher=Routledge |year=2002 |isbn=0-415-23982-6}}
*{{cite book  | last = Furet | first = François  | title = Revolutionary France: 1770–1880  | publisher= Wiley Blackwell | year = 1995  | isbn = 0-631-19808-3 }}
*{{cite book |last=Hudson |first=Nora Eileen |title=Ultra-Royalism and the French Restoration  |publisher=Octagon Press |year=1973| isbn=0-374-94027-4}}
*{{cite book  | last = Ingram | first = Philip  | title = Napoleon and Europe  | publisher=[[Nelson Thornes]]  | year = 1998  | isbn = 0-7487-3954-8 }}
*{{cite book |last=Pilbeam |first=Pamela |editor=Martin S. Alexander |title=French History Since Napoleon |publisher=Arnold | year= 1999 | isbn =0-340-67731-7}}
*{{cite journal |last=Pilbeam |first=Pamela |title=The Economic Crisis of 1827–32 and the 1830 Revolution in Provincial France |journal=[[The Historical Journal]] |volume=32 |issue=2 |month=June |year=1989}}
*{{cite book |last=Price |first=Munro. |title=The Perilous Crown: France between Revolutions |location=Great Britain |publisher=Pan |year=2008 |isbn=978-0-330-42638-1}}
*{{cite book |last=Rader |first=Daniel L. |title=The Journalists and the July Revolution in France |location=The Hague |publisher=Martinus Nijhoff |year=1973 |isbn=90-247-1552-0}}
*{{cite book  | last = Tombs | first = Robert  | title = France 1814–1914  | publisher=[[Longman]]  | year = 1996  | location = London  | isbn = 0-582-49314-5 }}
{{Refend}}

== Further reading ==
{{Commonscat|Restauration period}}
* {{cite journal
 | author1 =
 De Bertier De Sauvigny, G
 | quotes =
 | last = &lt;span lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;G. de Bertier de Sauvigny&lt;/span&gt;
 | authorlink =
 | year = 1981
 | month = Spring
 | title = The Bourbon Restoration: One Century of French Historiography
 | journal=[[French Historical Studies]]
 | volume = 12
 | issue = 1
 | pages = 41–67
 | issn =
 | pmid =
 | doi =
 10.2307/286306| id =
 | format =
 | laysummary =
 | laysource =
 | laydate =
 | quote =
 | jstor =
 286306
 }}
* {{cite journal
 | quotes =
 | last = Kroen
 | first = Sheryl T.
 | coauthors =
 | year = 1998
 | month = Winter
 | title = Revolutionizing Religious Politics during the Restoration
 | journal=[[French Historical Studies]]
 | volume = 21
 | issue = 1
 | pages = 27–53
 | issn =
 | pmid =
 | doi = 10.2307/286925
 | id =
 | format =
 | laysummary =
 | laysource =
 | laydate =
 | quote =
 | publisher=Duke University Press
 | jstor =
 286925
 }}
* {{cite journal
 | quotes =
 | last = Newman
 | first = Edgar Leon
 | coauthors =
 | year = 1974
 | month = March
 | title = The Blouse and the Frock Coat: The Alliance of the Common People of Paris with the Liberal Leadership and the Middle Class during the Last Years of the Bourbon Restoration
 | journal=[[The Journal of Modern History]]
 | volume = 46
 | issue = 1
 | pages = 26–59
 | issn =
 | pmid =
 | doi = 10.1086/241164
 | id =
 | url =
 | format =
 | laysummary =
 | laysource =
 | laydate =
 | quote =
 }}
* {{cite journal
 | quotes =
 | last = Pilbeam
 | first = Pamela
 | authorlink = Pamela Pilbeam
 | coauthors =
 | year = 1982
 | month = June
 | title = The Growth of Liberalism and the Crisis of the Bourbon Restoration, 1827–1830
 | journal=[[The Historical Journal]]
 | volume = 25
 | issue = 2
 | pages = 351–366
 | issn =
 | pmid =
 | doi =
 10.1017/S0018246X00011596| id =
 | url =
 | format =
 | laysummary =
 | laysource =
 | laydate =
 | quote =
 }}

{{House of Bourbon (France)}}
{{France topics}}

{{coord|48|49|N|2|29|E|source:eswiki_type:country|display=title}}

[[Category:19th century in France]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1814]]
[[Category:1830 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Bourbon Restoration| ]]
[[Category:States and territories disestablished in the 1830s]]
[[Category:1814 establishments in France]]

[[ar:استعادة بوربون]]
[[bg:Реставрация на Бурбоните]]
[[ca:Restauració francesa]]
[[cs:Restaurace Bourbonů]]
[[de:Restauration (Frankreich)]]
[[et:Bourbonide restauratsioon]]
[[el:Παλινόρθωση των Βουρβόνων]]
[[es:Restauración borbónica en Francia]]
[[eu:Borboien berrezarkuntza (Frantzia)]]
[[fa:بازگشت بوربون‌ها به سلطنت فرانسه]]
[[fr:Restauration (histoire de France)]]
[[gl:Restauración Francesa]]
[[ko:부르봉 왕정복고]]
[[it:Restaurazione francese]]
[[he:הרסטורציה]]
[[ka:ბურბონთა რესტავრაცია]]
[[nl:Restauratie (Frankrijk)]]
[[ja:フランス復古王政]]
[[no:Restaurasjonen i Frankrike]]
[[pl:Restauracja Burbonów]]
[[pt:Restauração francesa]]
[[ro:Restaurația franceză]]
[[ru:Реставрация Бурбонов]]
[[simple:Bourbon Restoration]]
[[sk:Reštaurácia (Francúzsko)]]
[[sr:Бурбонска рестаурација]]
[[sh:Burbonska restauracija]]
[[sv:Bourbonska restaurationen]]
[[tr:Restorasyon (Fransa)]]
[[uk:Реставрація Бурбонів]]
[[vi:Bourbon phục hoàng]]
[[zh:波旁复辟]]</text>
      <sha1>14lskldv7vcmn5xo2gqqq8oluz30g2c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
