<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Carolingian Renaissance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>118560</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520625108</id>
      <parentid>520625098</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T18:26:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/69.253.61.222|69.253.61.222]] to version by Gumruch. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1304713) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14228">[[File:Minuscule caroline.jpg|thumb|[[Carolingian minuscule]], one of the products of the Carolingian Renaissance.]]
The '''Carolingian Renaissance''' was as a period of intellectual and cultural revival in the [[Carolingian Empire]] occurring from the late eighth century to the ninth century, as the first of three [[medieval renaissances]]. It occurred mostly during the reigns of the [[Carolingian]] rulers [[Charlemagne]] and [[Louis the Pious]]. It was supported by the scholars of the [[Carolingian dynasty|Carolingian court]], notably [[Alcuin|Alcuin of York]]&lt;ref&gt;G.W. Trompf, &quot;The concept of the Carolingian Renaissance&quot;, ''Journal of the History of Ideas'', 1973:3ff.&lt;/ref&gt; For moral betterment the Carolingian renaissance reached for models drawn from the example of the Christian Roman Empire of the 4th century. During this period there was an increase of [[literature]], [[writing]], the [[art]]s, [[architecture]], [[jurisprudence]], [[liturgical]] reforms and [[Religious text|scriptural]] studies. Charlemagne's ''[[Admonitio Generalis|Admonitio generalis]]'' (789) and his ''[[De litteris colendis|Epistola de litteris colendis]]'' served as manifestos. The effects of this cultural revival, however, were largely limited to a small group of court ''[[intellectual|literati]]'': &quot;it had a spectacular effect on education and culture in [[Francia]], a debatable effect on artistic endeavors, and an unmeasurable effect on what mattered most to the Carolingians, the moral regeneration of society,&quot; John Contreni observes.&lt;ref&gt;John G. Contreni, &quot;The Carolingian Renaissance&quot;, in Warren T. Treadgold, ed. ''Renaissances before the Renaissance: cultural revivals of late antiquity and the Middle Ages'' 1984:59; see also Janet L. Nelson, &quot;On the limits of the Carolingian renaissance&quot; in her ''Politics and Ritual in Early Medieval Europe'', 1986.&lt;/ref&gt; Beyond their efforts to write better Latin, to copy and preserve patristic and classical texts and to develop a more legible, classicizing script, the [[Carolingian minuscule]] that [[Renaissance humanism|Renaissance humanists]] took to be Roman and employed as [[humanist minuscule]], from which has developed early modern [[Italic script]], the secular and ecclesiastical leaders of the Carolingian Renaissance for the first time in centuries applied rational ideas to social issues, providing a common language and writing style that allowed for communication across most of Europe.

[[Sir Kenneth Clark]] was of the view that by means of the Carolingian Renaissance, Western civilization survived by the skin of its teeth.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, ''Civilization''.&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the term ''renaissance'' to describe this period is contested&lt;ref&gt;Notably by [[Lynn Thorndike]], as in his &quot;Renaissance or Prenaissance?&quot; in ''Journal of the History of Ideas'', '''4''' (1943:65ff)&lt;/ref&gt; due to the majority of changes brought about by this period being confined almost entirely to the [[clergy]], and due to the period lacking the wide-ranging social movements of the later [[Italian Renaissance]].&lt;ref name=Scott30&gt;Scott pg 30&lt;/ref&gt; Instead of being a rebirth of new cultural movements, the period was more an attempt to recreate the previous culture of the [[Roman Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;Cantor pg 190&lt;/ref&gt; The Carolingian Renaissance in retrospect also has some of the character of a false dawn, in that its cultural gains were largely dissipated within a couple of generations, a perception voiced by [[Walahfrid Strabo]] (died 849), in his introduction to [[Einhard]]'s ''Life of Charlemagne'',&lt;ref&gt;Einhard's use of the Roman historian [[Suetonius]] as a model for the new genre of [[biography]] is itself a marker for the Carolingian Renaissance; see M. Innes, &quot;The classical tradition in the Carolingian Renaissance: Ninth-century encounters with Suetonius&quot;, ''International Journal of the Classical Tradition'', 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; summing up the generation of renewal:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''Charlemagne was able to offer the cultureless and, I might say,  almost completely unenlightened territory of the realm which God had entrusted to him, a new enthusiasm for all human knowledge. In its earlier state of barbarousness, his kingdom had been hardly touched at all by any such zeal, but now it opened its eyes to God's illumination.  In our own time the thirst for knowledge is disappearing again: the light of wisdom is less and less sought after and is now becoming rare again in most men's minds.''&lt;ref&gt;[[Lewis Thorpe]], tr., Einhard and Notker the Stammerer, ''Two Lives of Charlemagne'', 1969:49f.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Scholarly efforts==
{{see also|Carolingian minuscule|Medieval Latin}}
The lack of literate persons in eighth century western Europe caused problems for the Carolingian rulers by severely limiting the number of people capable of serving as court scribes. Of even greater concern to the very pious rulers was the fact that not all parish priests possessed the skill to read the [[Vulgate Bible]]. An additional problem was that the [[vulgar Latin]] of the later [[Western Roman Empire]] had begun to diverge into the regional dialects, the precursors to today's [[Romance languages]], that were becoming mutually unintelligible and preventing scholars from one part of Europe being able to communicate with persons from another part of Europe.

[[Image:Raban-Maur Alcuin Otgar.jpg|thumb|left|[[Alcuin]] (pictured center),  was one of the leading scholars of the Carolingian Renaissance.]]

To address these problems, [[Charlemagne]] ordered the creation of schools.  A major part of his program of reform was to attract many of the leading scholars of his day to his court.   Among the first called to court were [[Italians]]:  [[Peter of Pisa]], who from 776 to about 790 instructed Charlemagne in Latin, and from 776 to 787 [[Paulinus of Aquileia]], whom Charlemagne nominated as [[patriarch of Aquileia]] in 787. The [[Lombards|Lombard]] [[Paul the Deacon]] was brought to court in 782 and remained until 787, when Charles nominated him [[abbot]] of [[Montecassino]]. [[Theodulf of Orléans]] was a [[Spain|Spanish]] [[Visigoths|Goth]] who served at court from 782 to 797 when nominated as [[bishop of Orléans]]. Theodulf had been in friendly competition over the standardization of the [[Vulgate]] with the chief among the Charlemagne's scholars, [[Alcuin of York]].  Alcuin was a [[Northumbria]]n [[monk]] and [[deacon]] who served as head of the Palace School from 782 to 796, except for the years 790 to 793 when he returned to [[England]].  After 796, he continued his scholarly work as abbot of St. Martin's Monastery in [[Tours]].&lt;ref name=Scott30/&gt; Among those to follow Alcuin across the Channel to the Frankish court was [[Joseph Scottus]], an Irishman who left some original biblical commentary and acrostic experiments. After this first generation of non-Frankish scholars, their [[Franks|Frankish]] pupils, such as [[Angilbert]], would make their own mark.  

The later courts of [[Louis the Pious]] and [[Charles the Bald]] had similar groups of scholars.  Among the most important was [[John Scotus Eriugena]].

One of the primary efforts was the creation of a standardized curriculum  for use at the recently created schools.  Alcuin led this effort and was responsible for the writing of textbooks, creation of word lists, and establishing the [[trivium (education)|trivium]] and [[quadrivium]] as the basis for education.&lt;ref&gt;Cantor pg 189&lt;/ref&gt;

Another contribution from this period was the development of [[Carolingian minuscule]], a &quot;book-hand&quot; first used at the monasteries of [[Corbie]] and Tours that introduced the use of lower case letters.  A standardized version of Latin was also developed that allowed for the coining of new words while retaining the grammatical rules of [[Classical Latin]]. This [[Medieval Latin]] became the common language of scholarship and allowed administrators and travelers to make themselves understood across Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Chambers pg 204-205&lt;/ref&gt;

==Carolingian art==
[[Image:Karolingischer Buchmaler um 820 001.jpg|thumb|Aachen Gospels (c. 820), an example of Carolingian [[Illuminated manuscript|illumination]].]]
{{main|Carolingian art}}
Carolingian art spans the roughly 100-year period from about 800–900. Although brief, it was an influential period. Northern Europe embraced classical Mediterranean Roman art forms for the first time, setting the stage for the rise of [[Romanesque art]] and eventually [[Gothic art]] in the West. [[Illuminated manuscript]]s, [[metalwork]], small-scale [[sculpture]], [[mosaic]]s and [[fresco]]s survive from the period.

[[Image:St gall plan.jpg|thumb|left|upright|A copy of the [[Plan of Saint Gall]]]]

==Carolingian architecture==
{{main|Carolingian architecture}}
Carolingian architecture is the style of North European architecture promoted by Charlemagne. The period of architecture spans the late eighth and ninth centuries until the reign of [[Otto I, Holy Roman Emperor|Otto I]] in 936, and was a conscious attempt to create a [[Roman architecture|Roman]] Renaissance, emulating [[Roman architecture|Roman]], [[Early Christian art and architecture|Early Christian]] and [[Byzantine architecture]], with its own innovation, resulting in having a unique character. Its architecture was the most salient Carolingian art to a society that never saw an illuminated manuscript and rarely handled one of the new coins. &quot;The little more than eight decades between 768 to 855 alone saw the construction of 27 new cathedrals, 417 monasteries, and 100 royal residences&quot;, John Contreni calculates.&lt;ref&gt;Contreni 1984:63.&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Carolingian music==
{{main|Charlemagne and church music}}
In Western culture, there had been an unbroken tradition in musical practice and theory from the earliest written records of the [[Sumerians]] (c. 2500 BC) through the [[Babylonians]] and [[Persia]]ns down to [[ancient Greece]] and [[ancient Rome|Rome]]. However, the [[Germanic migrations]] of the 5th century brought about a break with this tradition. Most in western Europe for the next few centuries did not understand the [[Greek language]], and thus the works of [[Boethius]], who saw what was happening and translated ancient Greek treatises into [[Latin]], became the foundation of learning during this period. The advent of scholarly reforms by Charlemagne, who was particularly interested in music, began a period of intense activity in the monasteries of the writing and copying of treatises in [[music theory]] – the [[Musica enchiriadis]] is one of the earliest and most interesting of these. Charlemagne sought to unify the practice of church music by eliminating regional stylistic differences. There is evidence that the earliest Western [[musical notation]], in the form of [[neume]]s ''in camp aperto'' (without [[Staff (music)|staff]]-lines), was created at [[Metz]] around 800, as a result of Charlemagne's desire for [[Franks|Frank]]ish church musicians to retain the performance nuances used by the Roman singers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0003-0139(200321)56%3A1%3C43%3AADCCMP%3E2.0.CO%3B2-%23 James Grier ''Ademar de Chabannes, Carolingian Musical Practices, and &quot;Nota Romana&quot;''], Journal of the American Musicological Society, Vol. 56, No. 1 (Spring, 2003), pp. 43-98, retrieved July 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  Western musical practice and theory of today can be traced in an unbroken line from this time to the present, thus it had its beginnings with Charlemagne.

==Economic and legal reforms==
Charlemagne was faced with a variety of currencies at the start of his reign. To correct problems these various currencies caused, he standardized a system based on a pound of [[silver]] (''[[Livre tournois]]'').  ''[[Denier (coin)|Denier]]s'' were minted with a value of 240 deniers to a pound of silver.  A second value, the ''solidus'', was also created as an accounting device with a value of twelve deniers or one twentieth of a pound of silver.  The solidus was not minted but was instead used to record values such as a &quot;solidus of grain&quot; which was equal to the amount of grain that twelve deniers could purchase.&lt;ref&gt;Scott pg 40&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
*{{cite book |last=Cantor | first= Norman F. |author-link=Norman Cantor | year = 1993 | title = The Civilization of the Middle Ages: a completely revised and expanded edition of Medieval history, the life and death of a civilization | publisher = [[HarperCollins]] | isbn = 0-06-017033-6}}
*{{cite book | author = Mortimer Chambers | coauthors = Raymond Grew, David Herlihy, Theodore K. Rabb, Isser Woloch | year = 1983 | title = The Western Experience: To 1715 | edition = 3rd edition | publisher = [[Alfred A. Knopf]] | location = New York | isbn = 0-394-33085-4}}
*{{cite book | author = Martin Scott | year = 1964 | title = Medieval Europe | publisher = Dorset Press | location = New York | isbn = 0-88029-115-X}}

===Footnotes===
{{reflist}}
[[Category:Carolingian Latin literature|*]]
[[Category:Carolingian period|Renaissance]]
[[Category:Medieval art]]
[[Category:Christianity of the Middle Ages]]

{{Link FA|fr}}

[[bg:Каролингски Ренесанс]]
[[ca:Renaixement carolingi]]
[[cs:Karolínská renesance]]
[[da:Karolingisk renæssance]]
[[de:Karolingische Renaissance]]
[[et:Karolingide renessanss]]
[[el:Καρολίγγεια αναγέννηση]]
[[es:Renacimiento carolingio]]
[[eo:Karolida Renesanco]]
[[fr:Renaissance carolingienne]]
[[fy:Karolingyske Renêssânse]]
[[gl:Renacemento carolinxio]]
[[hr:Karolinška renesansa]]
[[it:Rinascita carolingia]]
[[lv:Karolingu renesanse]]
[[lt:Karolingų Renesansas]]
[[nl:Karolingische renaissance]]
[[ja:カロリング朝ルネサンス]]
[[no:Den karolingiske renessanse]]
[[nn:Den karolingiske renessansen]]
[[pl:Renesans karoliński]]
[[pt:Renascença carolíngia]]
[[ru:Каролингское возрождение]]
[[sk:Karolínska renesancia]]
[[sr:Каролиншка ренесанса]]
[[sh:Karolinška renesansa]]
[[fi:Karolinginen renessanssi]]
[[sv:Karolingisk renässans]]
[[th:สมัยฟื้นฟูศิลปวิทยาการอแล็งเฌียง]]
[[uk:Каролінзьке Відродження]]
[[vls:Karolingische renaissance]]
[[zh:卡洛林文艺复兴]]</text>
      <sha1>evpp6cdwxnswxtcqdxff0o72rey5p6n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
