<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of transport</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1203727</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519027307</id>
      <parentid>519026803</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-21T14:50:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DVdm</username>
        <id>262666</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/122.161.219.163|122.161.219.163]] ([[User talk:122.161.219.163|talk]]) to last revision by ClueBot NG ([[WP:HG|HG]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13206">[[File:Bangkok traffic by g-hat.jpg|thumb|right|A busy street crowded with [[vehicle]]s in [[Bangkok]]. As the population of Earth increases, so does the strain on transport]]
{{Transport}}
The '''history of [[transport]]''' evolved with the development of human culture. Long distance walking tracks developed as trade routes in [[paleolithic]] times. For most of human history the only forms of transport apart from walking were using domesticated animals or transport in small boats.

==Road transport==
{{Main|History of road transport}}
The first earth tracks were created by humans carrying goods and often followed [[Game (food)|game]] [[trail]]s.  Tracks  would be naturally created at points of high traffic density.  As animals were domesticated, [[horse]]s, [[ox]]en and [[donkey]]s became an element in track-creation.  With the growth of trade, tracks were often flattened or widened to accommodate animal traffic. Later, the [[travois]], a frame used to drag loads, was developed.  Animal-drawn [[wheel]]ed vehicles probably developed in [[Sumer]] in the [[Ancient Near East]] in the 4th or 5th millennium BC and spread to [[Europe]] and [[India]] in the 4th millennium BC and [[China]] in about 1200 BC.  The [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] had a significant need for good roads to extend and maintain their [[Roman Empire|empire]] and developed [[Roman roads]].

In the [[Industrial Revolution]], [[John Loudon McAdam]] (1756–1836) designed the first modern highways, using inexpensive paving material of soil and stone aggregate ([[macadam]]), and he embanked roads a few feet higher than the surrounding terrain to cause water to drain away from the surface.  With the development of [[automobile|motor transport]] there was an increased need for hard-topped roads to reduce [[washaway]]s, bogging and dust on both urban and rural roads, originally using [[cobblestone]]s and wooden paving in major western cities and in the early 20th century tar-bound macadam ([[tarmac]]) and concrete paving were extended into the countryside.

The modern history of road transport also involves the development of new vehicles such as new models of [[horse-drawn vehicles]], [[History of the bicycle|bicycles]], [[History of the automobile|motor cars]], motor trucks and [[History of the electric vehicle|electric vehicles]].

== Maritime transport ==
{{Main|Maritime history}}
In the stone ages primitive boats developed to permit navigation of rivers and for fishing in rivers and off the coast.  It has been argued that boats suitable for a significant sea crossing was necessary for [[Prehistory of Australia|people to reach Australia]] an estimated 40,000-45,000 years ago.  With the development of [[civilization]], bigger vessels were developed both for trade and war.  In the [[Mediterranean]], [[galley]]s were developed about 3000 BC.  Galleys were eventually rendered obsolete by ocean-going [[sailing ship]]s, such as the Arabic [[caravel]] in the 13th century, the Chinese [[treasure ship]] in the early 15th century, and the Mediterranean [[man-of-war]] in the late 15th century. In the [[Industrial Revolution]], the first [[steamboat]]s and later [[Diesel engine|diesel]]-powered ships were developed.  Eventually [[History of submarines|submarines]] were developed mainly for military purposes.

Meanwhile specialised craft were developed for river and canal transport.  [[Canal]]s were developed in [[Mesopotamia]] c. 4000 BC. The [[Indus Valley Civilization]] in [[Pakistan]] and [[North India]] (from c. 2600 BC) had the first canal [[irrigation]] system in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title =Civlisations - case studies
  | publisher =[[Oracle Thinkquest]] 
  | url =http://library.thinkquest.org/C0110225/civilisations.htm
  | accessdate =2007-01-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The longest canal of ancient times was the [[Grand Canal of China]]. It is {{convert|1794|km|mi|sp=us}} long and was built to carry the [[Emperor Yang of Sui|Emperor Yang Guang]] between [[Beijing]] and [[Hangzhou]]. The project began in 605, although the oldest sections of the canal may have existed since c. 486 BC.  Canals were developed in the [[Middle Ages]] in [[Europe]] in [[Venice]] and the [[Netherlands]].  [[Pierre-Paul Riquet]] began to organise the construction of the 240&amp;nbsp;km-long [[Canal du Midi]] in [[France]] in 1665 and it was opened in 1681.  In the Industrial Revolution, inland canals were built in [[History of the British canal system England]] and later the [[United States]] before the development of [[railway]]s.  Specialised craft were also developed for [[fishing]] and later [[whaling]].  

Maritime history also deals with the development of [[navigation]], [[oceanography]], [[cartography]] and [[hydrography]].

==Rail transport==
{{Main|History of rail transport}}
The history of rail transportation dates back nearly 500 years, and includes systems with man or horse power and [[track (rail transport)|rails]] of wood (or occasionally stone).  This was usually for moving [[coal]] from the mine down to a river, from where it could continue by boat, with a flanged wheel running on a rail.  The use of [[cast iron]] plates as rails began in the 1760s, and was followed by systems ([[plateway]]s) where the flange was part of the rail.  However, with the introduction of rolled [[wrought iron]] rails, these became obsolete.  

Modern rail transport systems first appeared in [[England]] in the 1820s.  These systems, which made use of the [[steam locomotive]], were the first practical form of mechanized land transport, and they remained the primary form of mechanized land transport for the next 100 years.

The history of rail transport also includes the [[history of rapid transit]] and arguably [[monorail history]].

==Aviation==
{{Main|Aviation history}}
Humanity's desire to [[flight|fly]] likely dates to the first time man observed birds, an observation illustrated in the legendary stories of [[Daedalus]] and [[Icarus]] in [[Greek mythology]], and the [[Vimana]]s in [[Indian epic poetry|Indian mythology]]. Much of the focus of early research was on imitating birds, but through [[trial and error]], [[balloon (aircraft)|balloons]], [[airship]]s, [[glider aircraft|glider]]s and eventually powered [[fixed-wing aircraft|aircraft]] and other types of flying machines were invented.

Kites were the first form of man-made flying objects,&lt;ref name=&quot;wings-tom&quot; /&gt; and early records suggest that kites were around before 200 B.C. in China.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Brown|first=Brian |title=Chinese Nights Entertainments  |publisher=Brentano's|year=1922|oclc=843525}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Leonardo da Vinci]]'s dream of flight found expression in several designs, but he did not attempt to demonstrate flight by literally constructing them.

During the 17th and 18th century, when scientists began analysing the Earth's atmosphere, gases such as [[hydrogen]] were discovered which in turn led to the invention of hydrogen balloons.&lt;ref name=&quot;wings-tom&quot;&gt;{{Citation | last = Crouch | first = Tom | title = Wings: A History of Aviation from Kites to the Space Age | publisher = W.W. Norton &amp; Co | location = New York | year = 2004 | isbn = 0-393-32620-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Various theories in [[mechanics]] by physicists during the same period of time—notably [[fluid dynamics]] and [[Newton's laws of motion]]—led to the foundation of modern [[aerodynamics]]. Tethered balloons filled with hot air were used in the first half of the 19th century and saw considerable action in several mid-century wars, most notably the [[American Civil War]], where balloons provided observation during the [[Siege of Petersburg]].

[[Image:SpitfireIX611a.jpg|thumb|left|Pilots of [[No. 611 Squadron RAF|611 ''West Lancashire'' Squadron]] lend a hand pushing an early Spitfire Mark IXb, [[RAF Biggin Hill|Biggin Hill]], late 1942.]]
Apart from some scattered reference in ancient and medieval records, resting on slender evidence and in need of interpretation, the earliest clearly verifiable human flight took place in [[Paris]] in 1783, when [[Jean-François Pilâtre de Rozier]] and [[François Laurent d'Arlandes]] went {{convert|5|mi|km}} in a [[hot air balloon]] invented by the [[Montgolfier brothers]]. The [[Wright brothers]] made the first sustained, controlled and powered heavier-than-air flight on December 17, 1903, in their revolutionary aircraft, the [[Wright Flyer]].

[[World War II]] saw a drastic increase in the pace of aircraft development and production. All countries involved in the war stepped up development and production of aircraft and flight based weapon delivery systems, such as the first long range bomber.

After the war ended, commercial aviation grew rapidly, used mostly ex-military aircraft to transport people and cargo. This growth was accelerated by the glut of heavy and super-heavy bomber airframes like the [[B-29]] and [[Avro Lancaster|Lancaster]] that could be converted into commercial aircraft. The first commercial jet airliner to fly was the [[de Havilland Comet|British De Havilland Comet.]]  This marked the beginning of the [[Jet Age]], a period of relatively cheap and fast international travel.

In the beginning of the 21st century, subsonic military aviation focused on eliminating the pilot in favor of remotely operated or completely autonomous vehicles. Several unmanned aerial vehicles or UAVs have been developed. In April 2001 the unmanned aircraft [[Global Hawk]] flew from Edwards AFB in the US to Australia non-stop and unrefuelled. This is the longest point-to-point flight ever undertaken by an unmanned aircraft, and took 23 hours and 23 minutes. In October 2003 the first totally autonomous flight across the Atlantic by a computer-controlled model aircraft occurred. Major disruptions to air travel in the 21st Century included the closing of U.S. airspace following the [[September 11 attacks]], and the closing of northern European airspace after the [[2010 eruptions of Eyjafjallajökull]].

==Spaceflight==
{{Main|Spaceflight}}
{{see also|Space Age}}

The realistic dream of spaceflight dated back to [[Konstantin Tsiolkovsky]], however Tsiolkovsky wrote in Russian, and this was not widely influential outside Russia.  Spaceflight became an engineering possibility with the work of [[Robert H. Goddard]]'s publication in 1919 of his paper '[[Robert H. Goddard#A Method of Reaching Extreme Altitudes|A Method of Reaching Extreme Altitudes]]'; where his application of the [[de Laval nozzle]] to [[liquid-propellant rocket]]s gave sufficient power that interplanetary travel became possible. This paper was highly influential on [[Hermann Oberth]] and [[Wernher von Braun]], later key players in spaceflight.

The first [[human spaceflight]] was achieved with the [[Soviet space program]]'s [[Vostok 1]] mission in 1961. The lead architects behind the mission were [[Sergei Korolev]] and [[Kerim Kerimov]], with [[Yuri Gagarin]] being the first [[astronaut]]. Kerimov later went on to launch the first [[space dock]]s ([[Kosmos 186 and Kosmos 188]]) in 1967 and the first [[space station]]s ([[Salyut]] and [[Mir]] series) from 1971 to 1991.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Bond, [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20030407/ai_n12692130 Obituary: Lt-Gen Kerim Kerimov], ''[[The Independent]]'', 7 April 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Betty Blair (1995), &quot;Behind Soviet Aeronauts&quot;, ''[[Azerbaijan International]]'' '''3''' (3).&lt;/ref&gt; The first spaceflight to the [[Moon]] was achieved with [[NASA]]'s [[Apollo 11]] mission in 1969, with [[Neil Armstrong]] and [[Buzz Aldrin]] being the first astronauts on the Moon. The history of transportation is largely one of technological innovation. Advances in technology have allowed people to travel farther, explore more territory, and expand their influence over larger and larger areas. Even in ancient times, new tools such as foot coverings, skis, and snowshoes lengthened the distances that could be traveled. As new inventions and discoveries were applied to transportation problems, travel time decreased while the ability to move more and larger loads increased. Innovation continues today, and transportation researchers are working to find new ways to reduce costs and increase transportation efficiency.

==See also==
{{portal|Transport}}
* [[Medieval transport]]
* [[Timeline of artificial satellites and space probes]]
* [[Timeline of aviation]]
* [[Timeline of diving technology]]
* [[Timeline of jet power]]
* [[Timeline of transportation technology]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Casson, Lionel. 1984. ''Ancient Trade and Society.'' Detroit: Wayne State University Press.
*[[Martin van Creveld|Creveld van, Martin]], 1977. ''Supplying War: Logistics from Wallenstein to Patton.'' Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
*Farooque, Abdul K.M. 1977. ''Roads and Communications in Mughal India.'' Delhi: Idarah-I Adabiyat-I Delli.


{{History of technology|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Transport}}
[[Category:History of technology|Transport]]
[[Category:History of transport| ]]
[[Category:Transport]]

[[ar:تاريخ النقل]]
[[ca:Història del transport]]
[[de:Geschichte des Verkehrs]]
[[hr:Povijest prijevoza]]
[[hu:A közlekedés története]]
[[zh:運輸史]]</text>
      <sha1>15m8oawnt0r06a12k46ewl1lzc6tdy7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
