<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Cyprus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>50621</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521275625</id>
      <parentid>520932965</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T23:30:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ec.Domnowall</username>
        <id>11002219</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Ancient history */ internal link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30515">{{History of Cyprus}}
Human habitation of Cyprus dates back to the [[Paleolithic]] era. Cyprus's geographic position has caused Cyprus to be influenced by differing Eastern Mediterranean civilisations over the millennia.

==Prehistory==
{{main|Cyprus (Prehistory)}}

[[File:Khirokitia4.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Khirokitia]] archeological site.]]
Cyprus was [[human settlement|settled]] by humans in the [[Paleolithic]] period (known as the stone age) who coexisted with various dwarf animal species, such as [[Cyprus Dwarf Elephant|dwarf elephants]] (''Elephas cypriotes'') and [[Cyprus Dwarf Hippopotamus|pygmy hippos]] (''Hippopotamus minor'') well into the [[Holocene]]. There are claims of an association of this [[fauna]] with [[Artifact (archaeology)|artifacts]] of [[Epipalaeolithic]] foragers at [[Aetokremnos]] near Limassol on the southern coast of Cyprus. The first undisputed settlement occurred in the 9th (or perhaps 10th) millennium BC from the [[Levant]]. The first [[settler]]s were agriculturalists of the so-called PPNB ([[Pre-Pottery Neolithic B|pre-pottery Neolithic B]]) era, but did not yet produce [[pottery]] ([[aceramic]] [[Neolithic]]). 

The dog, sheep, goats and possibly [[cattle]] and pigs were introduced, as well as numerous wild animals such as [[fox]]es (''Vulpes vulpes'') and [[Persian fallow deer]] (''Dama mesopotamica'') that were previously unknown on the island. The PPNB settlers built round houses with floors made of [[terrazzo]] of burned lime (e.g. [[Kastros]], [[Shillourokambos]]) and cultivated [[einkorn]] and [[emmer]]. Pigs, sheep, goat and cattle were kept but remained, for the most part, behaviourally wild. Evidence of cattle such as that attested at Shillourokambos is rare, and when they apparently died out in the course of the 8th millennium they were not re-introduced until the ceramic Neolithic.

In the 6th millennium BC, the aceramic [[Khirokitia]] culture was characterised by [[roundhouse (dwelling)|roundhouses]], stone vessels and an economy based on sheep, goats and pigs. Cattle were unknown, and Persian [[fallow deer]] were hunted. This was followed by the ceramic [[Sotira]] phase. The [[Eneolithic]] era is characterised by stone [[figurine]]s with spread arms.

Water wells discovered by archaeologists in western Cyprus are believed to be among the oldest in the world, dated at 9,000 to 10,500 years old, putting them in the [[Stone Age]]. They are said to show the sophistication of early settlers, and their heightened appreciation for the environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8118318.stm |title=Stone Age wells found in Cyprus |publisher=BBC News |date=2009-06-25 |accessdate=2009-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, the remains of an 8-month-old cat were discovered buried with its human owner at a Neolithic archeological site in Cyprus.&lt;ref&gt;Wade, Nicholas, &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/29/health/29iht-29cat.6404420.html?_r=1 Study Traces Cat's Ancestry to Middle East]&quot;, ''[[The New York Times]]'', June 29, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The grave is estimated to be 9,500 years old, predating Egyptian civilization and pushing back the earliest known feline-human association significantly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Marsha|last=Walton |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Ancient burial looks like human and pet cat |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2004/TECH/science/04/08/cats.cyprus/index.html |work= |publisher=CNN|date= April 9, 2004|accessdate=2007-11-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Bronze Age ===
In the [[Bronze Age]] the first cities, such as [[Enkomi]], were built. Systematic copper mining began, and this resource was widely traded. [[Mycenaean Greece|Mycenaean Greeks]] were undoubtedly inhabiting Cyprus from the late stage of the Bronze Age, while the island's Greek name is already attested from the 15th century B.C. in the [[Linear B]] script.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Strange|first=John|title=Caphtor : Keftiu : a new investigation|year=1980|publisher=Brill|location=Leiden|isbn=978-90-04-06256-6|pages=167|url=http://books.google.gr/books?id=c9QUAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA154&amp;dq=cyprus+mycenaeans&amp;hl=el&amp;ei=L2J2ToWdEoOg-waylLSeAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFcQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=cyprus%20mycenaeans&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Cypriot syllabary|Cypriot syllabic script]] was first used in early phases of the late Bronze Age (LCIB) and continued in use for ca. 500 years into the  to LC IIIB, maybe up to the second half of the eleventh century BC. Most scholars believe it was used for a native Cypriot language ([[Eteocypriot]]) that survived until the 4th century BC, but the actual proofs for this are scant, as the tablets still have not been completely deciphered.

The LCIIC (1300-1200 BC) was a time of local prosperity. Cities such as Enkomi were rebuilt on a rectangular grid plan, where the town gates correspond to the grid axes and numerous grand buildings front the street system or newly founded.
Great official buildings constructed from [[ashlar]] masonry point to increased social hierarchisation and control. Some of these buildings contain facilities for processing and storing [[olive oil]], such as [[Maroni]]-Vournes and Building X at [[Kalavassos]]-Ayios Dhimitrios. A Sanctuary with a horned altar constructed from [[ashlar]] masonry has been found at Myrtou-Pigadhes, other temples have been located at Enkomi, [[Kition]] and  [[Kouklia]] (Palaepaphos). Both the regular layout of the cities and the new masonry techniques find their closest parallels in Syria, especially in [[Ugarit]] (modern Ras Shamra).
Rectangular corbelled tombs point to close contacts with Syria and Palestine as well.

The practice of writing spread and tablets in the [[Cypriot syllabary|Cypriot syllabic script]] have been found at [[Ras Shamra]] which was the Phoenician city of Ugarit. Ugaritic texts from Ras Shamra and Enkomi mention Ya, the Assyrian name of Cyprus, that thus seems to have been in use already in the late Bronze Age.

Copper ingots shaped like oxhides have been recovered from shipwrecks such as at [[Ulu Burun]], Iria and [[Cape Gelidonya]] which attest to the widespread metal trade. Weights in the shape of animals found in Enkomi and Kalavassos follow the Syro-Palestinian, Mesopotamian, Hittite and Aegean standards and thus attest to the wide ranging trade as well.

[[File:Base ring vessel.jpg|thumb|Base ring vessel of Late Bronze Age]]
Late Bronze Age Cyprus was a part of the [[Hittite Empire|Hittite empire]] but was a client state and as such was not invaded but rather merely part of the empire by association and governed by the ruling kings of Ugarit.&lt;ref name=&quot;TTW1&quot;&gt;Thomas, Carol G. &amp; Conant, C.: ''The Trojan War'', pages 121-122. Greenwood Publishing Group, 2005. ISBN 0-313-32526-X, 9780313325267.&lt;/ref&gt; As such Cyprus was essentially &quot;left alone with little intervention in Cypriot affairs&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;TTW1&quot; /&gt; However, during the reign of [[Tudhaliya I|Tudhaliya]], the island was briefly invaded by the Hittites for either reasons of securing the copper resource or as a way of preventing piracy. Shortly afterwards the island was reconquered by his son around 1200 BCE.

In the later phase of the [[late Bronze Age]] (LCIIIA, 1200-1100 BC) great amounts of 'Mycenean' IIIC:1b pottery were produced locally. New architectural features include [[cyclopean walls]], found on the Greek mainland, as well and a certain type of rectangular stepped capitals, endemic on Cyprus. Chamber tombs are given up in favour of shaft graves. Large amounts of IIIC:1b pottery are found in Palestine during this period as well. While this was formerly interpreted as evidence of an invasion ('[[Sea Peoples]]'), this is seen more and more as an indigenous development, triggered by increasing trade relations with Cyprus and [[Crete]].  Evidence of early trade with Crete is found in archaeological recovery on Cyprus of pottery from [[Kydonia|Cydonia]], a powerful urban center of ancient Crete.&lt;ref&gt;C. Michael Hogan, [http://www.themodernantiquarian.com/site/10881/cydonia.html#fieldnotes C. Michael Hogan, ''Cydonia'', The Modern Antiquarian, Jan. 23, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Achaean Greeks were living in Cyprus from the 14th century, most of them inhabited the island after the Trojan war. Achaeans were colonizing Cyprus from 1210-1000 BC.
Dorian Greeks come at 1100 BC and unlike the Greek mainland they settle in Cyprus peacefully.

Another wave of Greek settlement is believed to have taken place in the following century (LCIIIB, 1100-1050), indicated, among other things, by a new type of graves (long dromoi) and Mycenean influences in pottery decoration.

Most authors claim that the Cypriot city kingdoms, first described in written sources in the 8th century BC were already founded in the 11th century BC. Other scholars see a slow process of increasing social complexity between the 12th and the 8th centuries, based on a network of chiefdoms. In the 8th century (geometric period) the number of settlements increases sharply and monumental tombs, like the 'Royal' tombs of [[Salamis, Cyprus|Salamis]] appear for the first time. This could be a better indication for the appearance of the Cypriot kingdoms.

=== Iron Age ===
The [[Iron Age]] follows the Submycenian period (1125-1050 BC) or [[Late Bronze Age]] and is divided into the:
* Geometric 1050-700
* Archaic 700-525

Foundations myths documented by classical authors connect the foundation of numerous Cypriot towns with immigrant Greek heroes in the wake of the [[Trojan war]]. For example, [[Teucer]], brother of [[Aias]] was supposed to have founded [[Salamis, Cyprus|Salamis]], and the Arcadian [[Agapenor]] of Tegea to have replaced the native ruler Kinyras and to have founded [[Paphos]]. Some scholars see this a memory of a Greek colonisation already in the 11th century. In the 11th century tomb 49 from Palaepaphos-Skales three bronze [[obelisk|obeloi]] with inscriptions in Cypriot syllabic script have been found, one of which bears the name of Opheltas. This is first indication of the use of Greek language on the island.

Cremation as a burial rite is seen as a Greek introduction as well. The first cremation burial in Bronze vessels has been found at Kourion-Kaloriziki, tomb 40, dated to the first half of the 11th century (LCIIIB). The shaft grave contained two bronze rod tripod stands, the remains of a shield and a golden sceptre as well. Formerly seen as the Royal grave of first Argive founders of Kourion, it is now interpreted as the tomb of a native Cypriote or a Phoenician prince. The cloisonné enamelling of the sceptre head with the two falcons surmounting it has no parallels in the Aegean, but shows a strong Egyptian influence.

In the 8th century, several Phoenician colonies were founded, like Kart-Hadasht ('New Town'), present day [[Larnaca]] and [[Salamis, Cyprus|Salamis]]. The oldest cemetery of Salamis has indeed produced children's burials in Canaanite jars, clear indication of Phoenician presence already in the LCIIIB 11th century. Similar jar burials have been found in cemeteries in Kourion-Kaloriziki and Palaepaphos-Skales near Kouklia. In Skales, many Levantine imports and Cypriote imitations of Levantine forms have been found and point to a Phoenician expansion even before the end of the 11th century.

==Ancient history==
{{Main|Ancient history of Cyprus}}
{{Main|Roman Cyprus}}

[[Image:Kourion theatre southeast 2010.jpg|thumb|250px|An ancient Roman theatre in [[Kourion]].]]
The first written source shows Cyprus under [[Assyria]]n rule. A [[stela]] found 1845 in [[Kition (ancient state)|Kition]] commemorates the victory of king [[Sargon II]] (721-705 BC) in 709 over the seven kings in the land of Ia', in the district of Iadnana or Atnana. The former is supposedly the Assyrian name of the island, while some authors take the latter to mean Greece (the Islands of the Danaoi). There are other inscriptions referring to Ia' in Sargon's palace at [[Khorsabad]].
The ten kingdoms listed by an inscription of [[Esarhaddon]] in 673/2 BC have been identified as [[Salamis, Cyprus|Salamis]], [[Kition]], [[Amathus]], [[Kourion]], [[Paphos]] and [[Soli, Cyprus|Soli]] on the coast and [[Tamassos]], [[Ledra]], [[Idalium]] and [[Chytri]] in the interior.

Cyprus gained independence for some time around 669 but was conquered by Egypt under [[Amasis II|Amasis]] (570-526/525). The island was conquered by the Persians around 545 BC. A Persian palace has been excavated in the territory of [[Marion, Cyprus|Marion]] on the North coast near Soli. The inhabitants took part in the Ionian rising. At the beginning of the 4th century BC, Euagoras I, King of Salamis, took control of the whole island and tried to gain independence from Persia. Another uprising took place in 350 but was crushed by [[Artaxerxes III of Persia|Artaxerxes]] in 344.

During the siege of [[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]], the Cypriot Kings went over to [[Alexander the Great]]. In 321 four Cypriot kings sided with [[Ptolemy I]] Soter and defended the island against [[Antigonus I Monophthalmus|Antigonos]]. Ptolemy lost Cyprus to [[Demetrios Poliorketes]] in 306 and 294 BC, but after that it remained under [[Ptolemaic dynasty|Ptolemaic]] rule till 58 BC. It was ruled by a governor from Egypt and sometimes formed a minor Ptolemaic kingdom during the power-struggles of the 2nd and 1st centuries. Strong commercial relationships with [[Athens]] and [[Alexandria]], two of the most important commercial centres of antiquity, developed.

Full [[Hellenisation]] only took place under Ptolemaic rule. Phoenician and native Cypriot traits disappeared, together with the old [[Cypriot syllabic script]]. A number of cities were founded during this time, e.g. [[Arsinoe (Southwest Cyprus)|Arsinoe]] that was founded between old and new [[Paphos]] by [[Ptolemy II]].

Cyprus became a Roman province in 58 BC, according to [[Strabo]] because [[Publius Clodius Pulcher]] held a grudge against [[Ptolemy of Cyprus|Ptolemy]] and sent [[Cato the Younger|Marcus Cato]] to conquer the island after he had become [[tribune]]. [[Marc Anthony]] gave the island to [[Cleopatra VII]] of Egypt and her sister [[Arsinoe IV of Egypt|Arsinoe IV]], but it became a Roman province again after his defeat at the [[Battle of Actium]] (31 BC) in 30 BC. Since 22 BC it was a senatorial province, after the reforms of [[Diocletian]] it was placed under the Consularis Oriens. The island suffered great losses during the Jewish rising of 115/116 AD. Several earthquakes led to the destruction of Salamis at the beginning of the 4th century, at the same time drought and famine hit the island.

Christianisation:
The apostle [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]] is reported to have converted the people of Cyprus to Christianity. The Levit Barnabas, a Cypriot,  travels to Cyprus and Anatolia with Paul (Apg. 12, 13). During the 5th century AD, the [[church of Cyprus]] achieved its independence from the [[Patriarch of Antioch]] at the [[First Council of Ephesus|Council of Ephesus]] in 431.

==Middle Ages to High Middle Ages and Byzantine Renaissance==
{{main|Cyprus in the Middle Ages}}

[[File:Yeroskipou 2010-05-04.jpg|thumb|250px|Ayia Paraskevi Byzantine church in [[Yeroskipou]].]]
After the division of the Roman Empire into an eastern half and a western half, Cyprus came under the rule of [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantium]]. At that time, its [[bishop]], while still subject to the [[One Holy Catholic and Apostolic Church|Church]], was made [[autocephalous]] by the [[First Council of Ephesus|Council of Ephesus]].

The [[Arabs]] invaded Cyprus in force in the 650s, but in 688, the emperor [[Justinian II]] and the [[caliph]] [[Abd al-Malik ibn Marwan|Abd al-Malik]] reached an unprecedented agreement. For the next 300 years, Cyprus was ruled jointly by both the Arabs and the Byzantines as a [[condominium (international law)|condominium]], despite the nearly constant warfare between the two parties on the mainland. The Byzantines recovered control over the island for short periods thereafter, but the ''status quo'' was always restored.

This period lasted until the year 965, when [[Niketas Chalkoutzes]] conquered the island for a resurgent Byzantium. In 1185, the last Byzantine governor of Cyprus, [[Isaac Comnenus of Cyprus]] from a minor line of the Imperial house, rose in rebellion and attempted to seize the throne. His attempted coup was unsuccessful, but Comnenos was able to retain control of the island.

Byzantine actions against Comnenos failed because he enjoyed the support of [[William II of Sicily]]. The Emperor had an agreement with the [[sultan]] of Egypt to close Cypriot harbours to the Crusaders. Isaac Comnenos was displaced by [[Richard I of England|Richard I Plantagenet]] in 1192 and kept prisoner till his death in 1194 or 1195.

In the 12th century A.D. the island became a target of the [[crusades|crusaders]]. [[Richard I of England|Richard the Lionheart]] landed in [[Limassol]] on 1 June 1191 in search of his sister and his bride [[Berengaria of Navarre|Berengaria]], whose ship had become separated from the fleet in a storm. Richard married Berengaria in Limassol on 12 May 1192. She was crowned as Queen of England by [[John Fitzluke]], [[Bishop of Évreux]]. The crusader fleet continued to St. Jean d'Acre (Syria) on 5 June.

The army of [[Richard I of England|Richard the Lionheart]] continued to occupy Cyprus and raised taxes. He sold the island to the  [[Knights Templar]]. Soon after that, the [[Franks]] (Lusignans) occupied the island, establishing the [[Kingdom of Cyprus]]. They declared Latin the official language, later replacing it with French; much later, Greek was recognised as a second official language. In 1196, the Latin Church was established, and the Orthodox Cypriot Church experienced a series of religious persecutions. [[Maronites]] settled on Cyprus during the crusades and still maintain some villages in the North.

==Late Middle Ages and Renaissance==
{{main|Kingdom of Cyprus}}
[[File:Ancient old Nicosia Aqueduct Republic of Cyprus.jpg|thumb|250px|The [[Old Nicosia aqueduct]].]]
[[File:LalaMustafaPasaMosque.jpg|thumb|250px|Saint Nicholas Cathedral in [[Famagusta]], where the Kings of Cyprus where also crowned as Kings of Jerusalem.]]
[[File:Hadjigeorgakis Kornesios Mansion in Nicosia Republic of Cyprus.jpg|thumb|left|[[Hadjigeorgakis Kornesios Mansion]].]]
Amalric I of Cyprus, received the royal crown and title from Henry VI, Holy Roman Emperor. A small minority Roman Catholic population of the island was mainly confined to some coastal cities, such as Famagusta, as well as inland Nicosia, the traditional capital. Roman Catholics kept the reins of power and control, while the Greek inhabitants lived in the countryside; this was much the same as the arrangement in the Kingdom of Jerusalem. The independent Eastern Orthodox Church of Cyprus, with its own archbishop and subject to no patriarch, was allowed to remain on the island, but the Latin Church largely displaced it in stature and holding property.

After the death of Amalric of Lusignan, the Kingdom continually passed to a series of young boys who grew up as king. The Ibelin family, which had held much power in Jerusalem prior its downfall, acted as regents during these early years. In 1229 one of the Ibelin regents was forced out of power by Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor, who brought the struggle between the Guelphs and Ghibellines to the island. 

Frederick's supporters were defeated in this struggle by 1233, although it lasted longer in the Kingdom of Jerusalem and in the Holy Roman Empire. Frederick's Hohenstaufen descendants continued to rule as kings of Jerusalem until 1268 when Hugh III of Cyprus claimed the title and its territory of Acre for himself upon the death of Conrad III of Jerusalem, thus uniting the two kingdoms. The territory in Palestine was finally lost while Henry II was king in 1291, but the kings of Cyprus continued to claim the title.

Like Jerusalem, Cyprus had a Haute Cour (High Court), although it was less powerful than it had been in Jerusalem. The island was richer and more feudal than Jerusalem, so the king had more personal wealth and could afford to ignore the Haute Cour. The most important vassal family was the multi-branch House of Ibelin. However, the king was often in conflict with the Italian merchants, especially because Cyprus had become the centre of European trade with Africa and Asia after the fall of Acre in 1291.

The kingdom eventually came to be dominated more and more in the 14th century by the Genoese merchants. Cyprus therefore sided with the Avignon Papacy in the [[Western Schism]], in the hope that the French would be able to drive out the Italians. The Mameluks then made the kingdom a tributary state in 1426; the remaining monarchs gradually lost almost all independence, until 1489 when the last Queen, Catherine Cornaro, was forced to sell the island to Venice.  [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]]s started raiding Cyprus immediately afterwards, and [[Ottoman–Venetian War (1570–1573)|captured it in 1571]].
{{wide image|Nicosia Venetian walls the Venetians ruled Cyprus from 1489 to 1571.JPG|600px|[[Venetican walls of Nicosia]].}}

== Ottoman Cyprus ==
{{main|Ottoman Cyprus}}

===Beginnings of Enosis===
During the [[Greek War of Independence]] the Greek people fought for independence from the Ottoman Empire who ruled them. A number of Greek Cypriots rebelled on Cyprus, in return the Ottoman rulers of Cyprus tried to keep control by using draconian means of suppression. 486 Greek Cypriots were executed on 9 July 1821, accused of conspiring with the rebelling Greeks, including four Bishops and numerous prominent citizens—all beheaded in the central square of Nicosia, while Archbishop Kyprianos was hanged. Actions during the short period that followed caused a strengthening of that Greek Cypriot desire to become part of Greece, known as ''Enosis'' (&quot;Union&quot;).

Many Cypriots again sought the incorporation of Cyprus into Greece when Greece became independent in 1830,{{citation needed|date=August 2012}} but it remained part of the Ottoman Empire. The [[Russo-Turkish War (1877–1878)|Russo-Turkish War]] ended the Ottoman control of Cyprus in 1878 when Cyprus was left under the control of the United Kingdom; with its conditions set out in the [[Cyprus Convention]], although sovereignty of the island continued to belong to the [[Ottoman Empire]] until the Kingdom annexed the island unilaterally in 1914, when it declared war against the Ottomans at the First World War.

Under British rule the island began to enjoy a period of increased free-speech, something which allowed further development of the Greek Cypriots' ideas of Enosis.

==Modern era==
{{main|Modern history of Cyprus}}
[[File:Cypriot demonstration 1930.jpg|thumb|250px|Cypriot demonstrations for [[Enosis]] (Union) with [[Greece]].]]
[[File:Statue of Liberty Nicosia Cyprus.JPG|thumb|250px|Statue of Liberty symbolising the independence of Cyprus.]]
In 1878, as the result of the [[Cyprus Convention]], the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]] took over the government of Cyprus as a protectorate from the [[Ottoman Empire]].  In 1914, at the beginning of [[World War I]], Cyprus was annexed by the United Kingdom.  In 1925, following the [[dissolution of the Ottoman Empire]], Cyprus was made a [[Crown Colony]].  Between 1955-59 [[EOKA]] was created by Greek Cypriots and led by [[George Grivas]] to perform [[enosis]] (union of the island with Greece). However the EOKA campaign did not result union with Greece but rather an independent republic, The Republic of Cyprus, in 1960.

In 1960, the mostly Muslim Turkish Cypriots were only 18% of the Cypriot population {{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}. However, the 1960 constitution carried major imbalances in the favour of Turkish Cypriots regarding state affairs, such as the vice-president being Turkish Cypriot, 30% of parliament being Turkish Cypriot, etc. Archbishop Makarios would be the [[President of Cyprus|President]] and [[Dr Fazil Kucuk]] would become Vice President. One of the articles in the constitution was the creation of separate local municipalities so that Greek and Turkish Cypriots could manage their own municipalities in the big towns. 

Internal conflicts turned into full-fledged armed fighting between the two communities on the island which prompted the United Nations to send [[United Nations Peacekeeping Force in Cyprus|peacekeeping forces]] in 1964; these forces are still in place today. In 1974 Greek Cypriots performed [[1974 Cypriot coup d'état|a military coup]] with the support of military junta in Greece. Turkey used the coup as a pretext to [[Turkish invasion of Cyprus|invade]] the northern portion of the island. Turkish forces remained after a cease-fire, resulting in the [[Taksim (politics)|partition]] of the island; an objective of Turkey since 1955.&lt;ref name=danopoulos&gt;Danopoulos, Constantine Panos. ''Civil-military relations, nation building, and national identity: comparative perspectives'' (2004), Greenwood Publishing Group. p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; The intercommunal violence and subsequent [[Turkish invasion of Cyprus|Turkish invasion]] led to the [[Cypriot refugees|displacement]] of hundreds of thousands of Cypriots.&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Rose Johnston, Susan Slyomovics. ''Waging War, Making Peace: Reparations and Human Rights'' (2009), American Anthropological Association Reparations Task Force, [http://books.google.com.tr/books?id=jOU9_BQU9SYC&amp;pg=PA211&amp;dq=%22in+turn,+some+of+the+approximately%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=PA7XT_W2Ncm3hAfroPjlAw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=%22in%20turn%2C%20some%20of%20the%20approximately%22&amp;f=false p. 211].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Morelli, Vincent. ''Cyprus: Reunification Proving Elusive'' (2011), DIANE Publishing, [http://books.google.com.tr/books?id=dyWwReoc81oC&amp;pg=PA10&amp;dq=%22it+was+estimated+that+over+150,000%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=qw7XT9uaGIy7hAf5gPnPAw&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22it%20was%20estimated%20that%20over%20150%2C000%22&amp;f=false p. 10].&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[de facto]] state of Northern Cyprus was proclaimed in 1975 under the name &quot;Turkish Federated State of Northern Cyprus&quot;. The name was changed to its present form on 15 November 1983. The only country to formally recognise The &quot;[[Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus]]&quot; is [[Turkey]]. Hundreds of thousands of Turkish settlers have been granted right to illegally reside in the 'TRNC' and allowed to reside on Greek Cypriot land and property in order to change the island's demographic in favour of the Turkish Cypriots. The international community considers the North as occupied territory of the Republic of Cyprus and Turkey has repeatedly violated numerous UN Resolutions calling on it to withdraw its occupation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.int/cyprus/resolut.htm UN Resolutions on Cyprus]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002 UN Secretary General Kofi Annan started a new round of negotiations for the unification of the island. In 2004 after long negotiations between both sides a plan for unification of the island emerged. The resulting plan was supported by UN, EU and the US. The nationalists in both sides campaigned for the rejection of the plan but Turkish side accepted the plan while Greek side rejected it.

After Cyprus became a member of the European Union in 2004, it adopted the [[Euro (currency)|Euro]] as its currency on January 1, 2008, replacing the previously used [[Cypriot Pound]]; whilst the illegally occupied areas continued to use the Turkish Lira and on January 1, 2008 the [[New Turkish Lira]].

==See also==
*[[Kingdom of Cyprus]]
*[[Timeline of Cypriot history]]

'''General:'''
*[[History of Europe]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
#History, general
#* C. D. Cobham, ''Excerpta Cypria: materials for a history of Cyprus'' (Cambridge 1908). Nice Collection of written sources.
#* D. Hunt, ''Footprints in Cyprus'' (London, Trigraph 1990).
#Prehistory
#* Vassos Karageorghis, ''Cyprus'' (1969). Includes bibliography.
#* Veronica Tatton-Brown, ''Cyprus BC: 7000 years of history'' (London, British Museum 1979).
#* Stuart Swiny, ''Earliest Prehistory of Cyprus'' (American School of Oriental Research 2001) ISBN 0-89757-051-0
#* J. M. Webb/D. Frankel, &quot;Characterising the Philia facies. Material culture, chronology and the origins of the Bronze Age in Cyprus&quot; in ''American Journal of archaeology'' 103, 1999, 3-43.
#* S. Gitin/A. Mazar/E. Stern (eds.), ''Mediterranean peoples in transition, thirteenth to early 10th century BC'' (Jerusalem, Israel exploration Society 1998). Late Bronze Age and transition to the Iron Age.
#* J. D. Muhly, &quot;The role of the Sea People in Cyprus during the LCIII period. In: Vassos Karageorghis and J. D.  Muhly (eds), ''Cyprus at the close of the Bronze Age'' (Nicosia 1984), 39-55. End of Bronze Age
#Classical Period, Sources
#*[[Herodotus]], &quot;The Histories&quot;
#*[[Isocrates]], &quot;Nicocles&quot;
#*[[Diodorus Siculus]], &quot;Bibliothiki&quot; (Library)
#*[[Arrian]], &quot;The Campaigns of Alexander the Great&quot;
#Mediavial Age
#*Angel Nicolaou-Konnari (Ed): ''Cyprus. Society and culture (1191 - 1374)''; Leiden : Brill, 2005. - XVI, 403 S., ISBN 90-04-14767-5
#History, 20th century
#* C. Spyridiakis, ''The education policy of the English government in Cyprus'' (1878–1954).
#* C. Spyridiakis, ''A brief history of Cyprus''.
#Mythology
#* ''[[Bibliotheca (Pseudo-Apollodorus)|Bibliotheca]]''
#*[[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]], &quot;Description of Greece&quot;
#*[[Ovid]], &quot;Metamorphosis&quot;

==External links==
*[http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/docs/books/gutenberg/etext03/cyprs10.txt &quot;Cyprus, as I Saw it in 1879&quot;] by [[Samuel Baker|Samuel W. Baker]].
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/flash/0,5860,1199973,00.html Cyprus - an island divided] - Interactive guide from ''[[The Guardian]]''

{{European history by country}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Cyprus}}
[[Category:History of Cyprus| ]]
[[Category:History of the Mediterranean]]
[[Category:History of Western Asia]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;
[[ar:تاريخ قبرص]]
[[be:Гісторыя Кіпра]]
[[ca:Història de Xipre]]
[[de:Geschichte Zyperns]]
[[el:Ιστορία της Κύπρου]]
[[es:Historia de Chipre]]
[[fr:Histoire de Chypre]]
[[hr:Povijest Cipra]]
[[io:Historio di Chipro]]
[[it:Storia di Cipro]]
[[li:Historie va Cyprus]]
[[mk:Историја на Кипар]]
[[ms:Sejarah Cyprus]]
[[nl:Geschiedenis van Cyprus]]
[[pl:Historia Cypru]]
[[pt:História do Chipre]]
[[ru:История Кипра]]
[[fi:Kyproksen historia]]
[[sv:Cyperns historia]]
[[tr:Kıbrıs Cumhuriyeti#Tarih]]
[[uk:Історія Кіпру]]</text>
      <sha1>d6y7afi12uh7kera7t47dzikjv8mnws</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
