<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of the Falkland Islands</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10689</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519589057</id>
      <parentid>513778535</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T15:53:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Neshmick</username>
        <id>16228686</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Luis Vernet's enterprise */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="83360">[[Image:Falkland Islands map shaded relief-en.svg|thumb|right|350px|Map of the modern Falkland Islands.]]

The '''history of the Falkland Islands''' ({{lang-es|Islas Malvinas}}) goes back at least five hundred years, with active exploration and colonisation only taking place in the 18th century. Nonetheless, the islands have been a matter of controversy, as they have been claimed by the French, British, Spaniards and Argentines at various points.

== Pre-European discovery ==
[[Image:FalklandIslandFox2.jpg|right|thumb|The extinct [[Falkland Island fox|warrah]] is sometimes taken as evidence of pre-European discovery.]]

While [[Amerindian]]s from [[Patagonia]] could have visited the Falklands,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| author = G. Hattersley-Smith
| year = 1983
| month = June
| title = Fuegian Indians in the Falkland Islands
| journal = Polar Record
| volume = 21
| issue = 135
| pages = 605–606
| publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]]
| doi = 10.1017/S003224740002204X
| accessdate = 1 February 2012
| url = http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract;jsessionid=C6D4151001DCF6AE8937B936C8FDCC62.journals?fromPage=online&amp;aid=5400340
| quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the islands were uninhabited when discovered by Europeans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.everyculture.com/Cr-Ga/Falkland-Islands.html |title=Culture of Falkland Islands – history, people, clothing, beliefs, food, life, immigrants, population, religion |accessdate=17 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Recent discoveries of arrowheads in [[Lafonia]] (on the southern half of [[East Falkland]]) as well as the remains of a [[wood]]en [[canoe]] provide evidence that suggests the [[Yaghan]] people of [[Tierra del Fuego]] may have made the journey to the islands. It is not known if these are evidence of one-way journeys, but there is no known evidence of pre-Columbian buildings or structures. However, it remains ambiguous whether the discovery predates arrival of Europeans because of the presence of a Patagonian Missionary Society mission station on Keppel Island, founded in 1856.  Yahgan Indians were at this station from 1856 to 1898 and may be the source of the discovered artifacts.

The presence of the [[Falkland Islands Wolf|Warrah]] has often been cited as evidence of pre-European occupation of the islands.  However,  in 2009, this hypothesis was disproved when DNA analysis identified the Falkland Island wolf's closest living relative as the [[Maned Wolf]] (''Chrysocyon brachyurus'')—an unusually long-legged, fox-like South American canid, from which it separated about 6.7 million years ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;'Httpwwwsciencedailycomreleaseshtm'&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/11/091102121449.htm | title = New Clues To Extinct Falklands Wolf Mystery | accessdate = 2011-09-03 | date = 2009-11-03 | work = EurekAlert | publisher = Science Daily}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It would seem that the lineages of the Maned Wolf and the Falkland Islands Wolf separated in North America; canids did not appear in South America until roughly 3 million years ago in a [[zoogeography|paleozoogeographical]] event called the [[Great American Biotic Interchange]], in which the continents of North and South America were newly connected by the formation of the [[Isthmus of Panama]].  This means is it likely that the Warrah arrived in the islands long before humans.

The islands had no native trees when discovered but there is some ambiguous evidence of past forestation, that may be due to wood being transported by oceanic currents from Patagonia. All modern trees have been introduced by Europeans.

==European discovery==
[[File:Richard Hawkins.jpg|right|thumb|200px|upright|[[Richard Hawkins]]]]

An [[archipelago]] in the region of the Falkland Islands appeared on Portuguese [[map]]s from the early 16th century. However, it is unlikely that they were sighted by [[Ferdinand Magellan]] or [[Estêvão Gomes]] of the ''San Antonio'', one of the captains in the expedition of Magellan. None of the chroniclers aboard mentions any such discovery. All say that the San Antonio returned to Spain up the coast of South America, and there is no positive evidence to support the discovery of the Falklands. 

Though definite proof is lacking, there is evidence that the islands were first discovered by an unrecorded Portuguese expedition before Magellan set sail. The evidence is found in two early maps, one made by the Portuguese [[cartographer]] [[Pedro Reinel]] in about 1522, the very first map to show the Falklands, the other a French copy of a Portuguese map bought in Lisbon by [[André Thévet]] (1516-1590), a [[Franciscan]] [[friar]] and prolific writer on many subjects; this copy is now in the manuscript of a large unpublished work by Thevet in the [[Bibliothèque nationale de France]] in Paris. These two maps of Portuguese origin suggest that it was Portuguese navigators who first saw and mapped the Falklands. It is not unusual that no written record of their expedition survives; voyages of discovery in those days were often national or commercial secrets, and unless a journal survived, they are completely unknown today.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.falklandshistory.org/gettingitright.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Hawkesworth-Byron-Map.PNG|thumb|300px|left|1773 Map by J. Hawkesworth and J. Byron showing Hawkins' discovery]]
When [[England|English]] explorer [[John Davis (English explorer)|John Davis]], commander of the ''[[Desire (ship)|Desire]]'', one of the ships belonging to [[Thomas Cavendish]]'s second expedition to the [[New World]], separated from Cavendish off the coast of what is now southern [[Argentina]], he decided to make for the [[Strait of Magellan]] in order to find Cavendish. On 9 August 1592 a severe storm battered his ship, and Davis drifted under bare masts, taking refuge &quot;among certain Isles never before discovered.&quot; Consequently, for a time the Falklands were known as &quot;Davis Land&quot; or &quot;Davis' Land.&quot;

In 1594, they were visited by English commander [[Richard Hawkins]], who, combining his own name with that of [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I, the &quot;Virgin Queen&quot;]], gave the islands the name of &quot;Hawkins' Maidenland.&quot;

In 1600, [[Sebald de Weert]], a [[Netherlands|Dutchman]], visited them and called them the Sebald Islands (in Spanish, &quot;Islas Sebaldinas&quot; or &quot;Sebaldes&quot;), a name which they bore on some Dutch maps into the 19th century.

[[File:French map of South America, c. 1710.jpg|thumb|French map, c. 1710, illustrating the fragmentary knowledge about the islands of the South Atlantic at the time. 'Anycan' is most probably a corruption of Hawkin's]] 

English Captain [[John Strong (mariner)|John Strong]], commander of the ''Welfare'', sailed between the two principal islands in 1690 and called the passage &quot;Falkland Channel&quot; (now [[Falkland Sound]]), after [[Anthony Cary, 5th Viscount Falkland]] (1659–1694), who as Commissioner of the [[Admiralty]] had financed the expedition and later became First Lord of the Admiralty. From this body of water the island group later took its collective name.

== Early colonisation ==

[[France]] established a colony at [[Port St. Louis]], on [[East Falkland]]'s [[Berkeley Sound]] coast in 1764. The [[French language|French]] name ''Îles Malouines'' was given to the islands – ''malouin'' being the adjective for the [[Brittany|Breton]] [[seaport|port]] of [[Saint-Malo]]. The [[Spanish language|Spanish]] name ''Islas Malvinas'' is a translation of the [[French language|French]] name of ''Îles Malouines''.

[[Image:John Byron-Joshua Reynolds-1759 .jpg|right|thumb|upright|John Byron, by [[Joshua Reynolds]], 1759.]]

In 1765, Capt. [[John Byron]], who was unaware of the French presence in the east, explored [[Saunders Island (Falkland Islands)|Saunders Island]], in the west, named the harbour [[Port Egmont]], and claimed this and other islands for [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Britain]] on the grounds of prior discovery. The next year [[Captain (naval)|Captain]] [[John MacBride (Royal Navy officer)|John MacBride]] established a British settlement at Port Egmont. These events were nearly the cause of a war between Britain and Spain, both countries having sent armed fleets to contest [[sovereignty]] of the strategically important islands. In 1766, France agreed to leave, and Spain agreed to reimburse [[Louis Antoine de Bougainville|Louis de Bougainville]], who had established a settlement at his own expense. The Spaniards assumed control in 1767 and renamed Port St. Louis as ''[[Puerto Soledad]]''.

Meanwhile, the British presence in the west continued, until interrupted by Spain during the [[Falkland Crisis (1770)|Falkland Crisis]] from 10 July 1770 to 22 January 1771. As a result of economic pressures stemming from the upcoming [[American War of Independence]], Britain unilaterally chose to withdraw from many overseas settlements in 1774.&lt;ref name=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;[http://www.falklands.info/history/timeline.html] Falkland Islands Timeline: A Chronology of events in the history of the Falkland Islands, Accessed 2007-10-02&lt;/ref&gt;  On 20 May 1776 the British forces under the command of Lt. Clayton formally took their leave of Port Egmont, while leaving a plaque asserting Britain's continuing sovereignty over the islands.&lt;ref name=&quot;briefhistory2&quot;&gt;[http://www.falklands.info/history/history2.html A brief history of the Falkland Islands Part 2 - Fort St. Louis and Port Egmont.], Accessed 2007-07-19&lt;/ref&gt;

Spain ruled the Islands from [[Buenos Aires]] until 1811, withdrawing due to the pressures of the [[Peninsular war]] against Bonapartist rule at home and the moves [[South American wars of independence|toward independence]] by her South American colonies. Like Britain earlier, Spain left behind a plaque proclaiming her sovereignty.

== Inter-colonial period ==

Following the departure of the Spanish settlers, the [[Falkland Islands]] became the domain of whalers and sealers who used the islands to shelter from the worst of the South Atlantic weather. By merit of their location, the Falkland Islands have often been the last refuge for ships damaged at sea. Most numerous among those using the islands were British and American [[seal hunting|sealers]], where typically between 40 and 50 ships were engaged in exploiting [[fur seal]]s. This represents an itinerant population of up to 1,000 sailors, which outnumbered any permanent population by an order of magnitude.

===The ''Isabella'' incident===

On 8 February 1813 the British ship ''Isabella'', a ship of 193 tons and a crew of fourteen, was wrecked off the coast of [[Speedwell Island|Eagle Island]] (now known as Speedwell Island). Captain George Higton and five other men volunteered to make the hazardous voyage to the [[Río de la Plata|River Plate]] in one of the ship's longboats. Braving the South Atlantic in a boat little more than {{convert|18|ft|m|abbr=on|adj=mid|long}}, they made landfall a month later. The British gun brig ''Nancy'' was sent to rescue the survivors.&lt;ref&gt;''Australian Shipwrecks - vol 1 1622-1850'', [[Charles Bateson]], AH and AW Reed, Sydney, 1972, ISBN 0-589-07112-2 p48&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 April [[Charles Barnard|Captain Charles Barnard]] of the American [[Seal hunting|sealer]] ''Nanina'' was sailing off the shore of [[Speedwell Island|Eagle Island]], with a discovery boat deployed looking for seals. Having seen smoke and heard gunshots the previous day, he was alert to the possibility of survivors of a ship wreck. This suspicion was heightened, when the crew of the discovery boat came aboard and informed the captain they had come across a new moccasin as well as the partially butchered remains of a seal. At dinner that evening, the crew observed a man approaching the ship who was shortly joined by eight to ten others. Both Barnard and the survivors from the ''Isabella'' had harboured concern the other party was Spanish and were relieved to discover their respective nationalities.

Barnard dined with the ''Isabella'' survivors that evening and finding that the British party were unaware of the [[War of 1812]] informed the survivors that technically they were at war with each other. Nevertheless Barnard promised to rescue the British party and set about preparations for the voyage to the River Plate. Realising that they had insufficient stores for the voyage he set about hunting wild pigs and otherwise acquiring additional food. However, while Barnard was gathering supplies, the British took the opportunity to seize the ''Nanina'' and departed leaving Barnard and three of his crew marooned. Shortly thereafter the ''Nanina'' encountered the British ship ''Nancy'' under Lt D'Aranda who had sailed from the River Plate in order to rescue the survivors of the ''Isabella''. Lt D'Aranda took the ''Nanina'' as a prize.

Barnard and his party survived for eighteen months marooned on the islands until rescued by the British ships ''{{lang|und|Indispensible}}''&lt;!--That was the name of the ship, please don't change--&gt; and ''Asp'' in November 1814. The British admiral in [[Rio de Janeiro]] had requested their masters to divert to the area to look for him.&lt;ref name = &quot;MerchantsMagazine&quot;&gt;Hunt, Freeman, ''The Merchants Magazine and Commercial Review'', New York, 1842&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1829, Barnard published an account of his survival entitled ''A Narrative of the Sufferings and Adventures of Capt Charles H. Barnard''.&lt;ref&gt;Barnard, Charles H., ''A narrative of the sufferings and adventures of Capt. Charles H. Barnard.'', Wesleyan University Press, 1979, ISBN 0-8195-5031-0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.co.uk/books?id=JbUBAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=Captain+Charles+Barnard] Barnard, Charles H., ''A narrative of the sufferings and adventures of Capt. Charles H. Barnard.''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Argentine colonisation attempts ==
[[Image:Jewett .Col.D.contemporary.jpeg|thumb|right|upright|Colonel Jewett]]

In March 1820, the ''[[Heroína (ship)|Heroína]]'', a privately owned frigate that was operated as a [[privateer]] under a license issued by the United Provinces of the River Plate, under the command of American Colonel [[David Jewett]], set sail looking to capture Spanish ships as prizes. After seven months, most of her crew were incapacitated by scurvy and disease. Jewett executed six of his crew for an attempted mutiny. He was unable to find any Spanish prizes but did manage to capture a Portuguese ship named ''Carlota''. As Argentina and Portugal were not at war, Jewett was considered to have committed piracy. A storm resulted in severe damage to the ''Heroína'' and sank the prize ''Carlota'' forcing Jewett to put into [[Puerto Soledad]] for repairs in October 1820.

Captain Jewett chose to rest and recover in the islands, seeking assistance from the British explorer [[James Weddell]]. Weddell reported only 30 seamen and 40 soldiers fit for duty out of a crew of 200, and how Jewett slept with pistols over his head following the mutiny. On 6 November 1820, Jewett raised the flag of the [[United Provinces of the River Plate]] (a predecessor of modern-day [[Argentina]]) and claimed possession of the islands. Weddell reported the letter he received from Jewett as:&lt;ref name=&quot;&quot;Weddell&quot;&gt;Weddell, James, ''A Voyage Towards the South Pole'', London, Longman, Rees, Orme, Brown and Green, 1827&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;''Sir, I have the honor of informing you that I have arrived in this port with a commission from the Supreme Government of the United Provinces of the Rio de la Plata to take possession of these islands on behalf of the country to which they belong by Natural Law. While carrying out this mission I want to do so with all the courtesy and respect all friendly nations; one of the objectives of my mission is to prevent the destruction of resources necessary for all ships passing by and forced to cast anchor here, as well as to help them to obtain the necessary supplies, with minimum expenses and inconvenience. Since your presence here is not in competition with these purposes and in the belief that a personal meeting will be fruitful for both of us, I invite you to come aboard, where you'll be welcomed to stay as long as you wish; I would also greatly appreciate your extending this invitation to any other British subject found in the vicinity; I am, respectfully yours.'' Signed, Jewett, Colonel of the Navy of the United Provinces of South America and commander of the frigate ''[[Heroína (ship)|Heroína]]''.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Many modern authors report this letter as the declaration issued by [[David Jewett|Jewett]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Destefani&quot;&gt;Laurio H. Destéfani, ''The Malvinas, the South Georgias and the South Sandwich Islands, the conflict with Britain'', Buenos Aires, 1982&lt;/ref&gt; Weddell did not believe that Jewett was acting with the interests of the United Provinces of the River Plate in mind, rather Jewett had merely put into the harbour in order to obtain refreshments for his crew, and that the assumption of possession was chiefly intended for the purpose of securing an exclusive claim to the wreck of the French ship ''Uranie''  that had foundered at the entrance of [[Berkeley Sound]] a few months prior. Weddell left the islands on 20 November 1820 noting that Jewett had not completed repairs to the ''Heroína''.

Finally Jewett seized an American-flagged ship named ''Rampart'', committing piracy for a second time. Jewett sent a long report to Buenos Aires dated 1 February 1821 in which he described his journey. He did not, however, make any mention whatsoever of his claim over the Falklands. News of Jewett's claim over the Falklands was reported first in the ''Salem Gazette'', a Massachusetts newspaper and then reprinted in the ''Times'' of London. The Spanish newspaper ''Cadiz'' then reported the story and it was only when this report reached Buenos Aires, as a foreign news story, was it published in the Buenos Aires ''Argos'' on 10 November 1821. More than a year after the event. The Argentine government itself made no announcements. This was probably because Jewett had made no report of his 'acquisition' and so they were completely unaware that it had taken place.

Jewett departed from the Falkland Islands in April 1821. In total he had spent no more than six months on the island, entirely at Port Luis. In 1822, Jewett was accused of piracy by a Portuguese court, but by that time he was in Brazil.


===Luis Vernet's enterprise===
[[File:Vernet Luis Portrait.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Luis Vernet]]]]

In 1823, the United Provinces of the River Plate granted [[fishing]] rights to Jorge Pacheco and [[Luis Vernet]]. Travelling to the islands in 1824, the first expedition failed almost as soon as it landed, and Pacheco chose not to continue with the venture. Vernet persisted, but the second attempt, delayed until winter 1826 by a [[Brazil]]ian blockade, was also unsuccessful. The expedition intended to exploit the [[feral]] cattle on the islands but the [[Swamp|boggy]] conditions meant the [[gaucho]]s could not catch cattle in their traditional way. Vernet was by now aware of conflicting British claims to the islands and sought permission from the British [[consulate]] before departing for the islands.

In 1828, the United Provinces government granted Vernet all of [[East Falkland]] including all its resources, and exempted him from taxation if a colony could be established within three years. He took settlers, including British Captain Matthew Brisbane (who had sailed to the islands earlier with [[James Weddell|Weddell]]), and before leaving once again sought permission from the British Consulate in Buenos Aires. The British asked for a report for the British government on the islands, and Vernet asked for British protection should they return.&lt;ref name=&quot;briefhistory3&quot;&gt;[http://www.falklands.info/history/history3.html A brief history of the Falkland Islands Part 3 - Louis Vernet: The Great Entrepreneur], Accessed 2007-07-19&lt;/ref&gt;

On 10 June 1829, Vernet was designated as 'civil and military commandant' of the islands (no Governor was ever appointed) and granted a monopoly on [[seal hunting]] rights. A protest was lodged by the British Consulate in [[Buenos Aires]]. By 1831, the colony was successful enough to be advertising for new colonists, although the ''Lexington'''s report suggests that the conditions on the islands were quite miserable.&lt;!--Commenting out as this should be sourced from an external site if there is information not contained in the other reference: &lt;ref&gt;[[User:Apcbg/Duncan-Woodbury|Report by Silas Duncan, Commander U.S.S. Lexington, sent to Navy Secretary Levi Woodbury, on 4 April 1832]]&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ussduncan.org/silas_page13.htm Commander Silas Duncan and the Falkland Island Affair, Accessed 2007-10-02]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Charles Darwin]]'s visit in 1833 confirmed the squalid conditions in the settlement, although Captain [[Matthew Brisbane]] (Vernet's deputy) later claimed that this was the result of the ''[[USS Lexington (1825)|Lexington]]'' raid.&lt;ref name=&quot;brisbanefitzroy&quot;&gt;[http://darwin-online.org.uk/content/frameset?itemID=F10.2&amp;viewtype=text&amp;pageseq=326&amp;keywords=brisbane Fitzroy, R., ''VOYAGES OF THE ADVENTURE AND BEAGLE. VOLUME II.''], Accessed 2007-10-02&lt;/ref&gt;

===USS ''Lexington'' raid===

In 1831, Vernet attempted to assert his monopoly on [[seal hunting]] rights. This led him to capture the American ships ''Harriet'', ''Superior'' and ''Breakwater''. As a reprisal, the [[United States]] consul in Buenos Aires sent Captain [[Silas Duncan]] of the [[USS Lexington (1825)|USS ''Lexington'']] to recover the confiscated property. After finding what he considered proof that at least four American fishing ships had been captured, plundered, and even outfitted for war, Duncan took seven prisoners aboard the ''Lexington'' and charged them with [[piracy]].

Also taken on board, Duncan reported, &quot;''were the whole of the (Falklands') population consisting of about forty persons, with the exception of some 'gauchos', or cowboys who were encamped in the interior.''&quot; The group, principally [[Germany|German]] citizens from [[Buenos Aires]], &quot;''appeared greatly rejoiced at the opportunity thus presented of removing with their families from a desolate region where the climate is always cold and cheerless and the soil extremely unproductive''&quot;. However, about 24 people did remain on the island, mainly gauchos and several [[Charrúa people|Charrúa]] [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Indians]], who continued to trade on Vernet's account.

Measures were taken against the settlement, the log of the ''Lexington'' reports destruction of arms and a powder store, while settlers remaining later said that there was great damage to private property.&lt;ref&gt;FitzRoy, R. 1839. [http://darwin-online.org.uk/content/frameset?viewtype=text&amp;itemID=F10.2&amp;pageseq=326 Narrative of the surveying voyages of His Majesty's Ships Adventure and Beagle. Proceedings of the second expedition, 1831-36. Chapter XVIII.]&lt;/ref&gt;  Towards the end of his life, Luis Vernet authorised his sons to claim on his behalf for his losses stemming from the raid.  In the case lodged against the US Government for compensation, rejected by the US Government of [[Grover Cleveland|President Cleveland]] in 1885, [[Luis Vernet#Vernet's role in the dispute over the Falkland Islands|Vernet]] stated that the settlement was destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tatham pp. 544&quot;&gt;{{cite book|chapter = Luis Vernet| last = Peter Pepper| first = Graham Pascoe|editor=David Tatham|title=The Dictionary of Falklands Biography (Including South Georgia): From Discovery Up to 1981|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0D0VNAAACAAJ|accessdate=15 August 2011|date=1 June 2008|publisher=D. Tatham|isbn=978-0-9558985-0-1|page=544}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Attempted establishment of a penal colony===

In the aftermath of the ''Lexington'' incident, [[Major]] [[Esteban Mestivier]] was commissioned by the [[Buenos Aires]] government to set up a [[penal colony]]. He arrived at his destination on 15 November 1832 but his soldiers [[mutiny|mutinied]] and killed him. [[Lieutenant Colonel|Lt. Col.]] [[José María Pinedo]] quelled the rebellion and took charge of the settlement.

== British return ==
{{main|Re-establishment of British rule on the Falklands (1833)}}
[[Image:HMS Beagle by Conrad Martens.jpg|thumb|right|A watercolour by [[HMS Beagle|HMS ''Beagle'']]'s [[technical drawing|draughtsman]], [[Conrad Martens]]. Painted during the survey of [[Tierra del Fuego]], it depicts the ''Beagle'' being hailed by native Fuegians. The ''Beagle'' visited the Falklands in 1834, and a Fuegian &quot;mission&quot; was later planted on [[Keppel Island]] in the west of the Falklands]]

The Argentinian assertions of sovereignty provided the spur for Britain to send a naval task force in order to finally and permanently return to the islands.

On 3 January 1833, Captain James Onslow, of the brig-sloop [[HMS Clio (1807)|HMS ''Clio'']], arrived at Vernet's settlement at Port Louis to request that the flag of the United Provinces of the River Plate be replaced with the British one, and for the administration to leave the islands. While Lt. Col. José María Pinedo, commander of the schooner ''Sarandí'', wanted to resist, his numerical disadvantage was obvious, particularly as a large number of his crew were British mercenaries who were unwilling to fight their own countrymen. Such a situation was not unusual in the newly independent states in Latin America, where land forces were strong, but navies were frequently quite undermanned. As such he protested verbally, but departed without a fight on 5 January. Argentina claims that Vernet's colony was also expelled at this time, though sources from time appear to dispute this, suggesting that the colonists were encouraged to remain initially under the authority of Vernet's storekeeper, [[William Dickson (Falklands)|William Dickson]] and later his deputy, Matthew Brisbane.&lt;ref name=&quot;briefhistory3&quot; /&gt;

Initial British plans for the Islands were based upon the continuation of Vernet's settlement at Port Louis. An Argentine immigrant of Irish origin, William Dickson, was appointed as the British representative and provided with a flagpole and flag to be flown whenever ships were in harbour.&lt;ref name=&quot;briefhistory3&quot;/&gt; In March 1833, Vernet's Deputy, Matthew Brisbane returned and presented his papers to Captain Fitzroy of HMS ''Beagle'', which coincidentally happened to be in harbour at the time. Fitzroy encouraged Brisbane to continue with Vernet's enterprise with the proviso that whilst private enterprise was encouraged, Argentine assertions of sovereignty would not be welcome.&lt;ref name=&quot;brisbanefitzroy&quot;/&gt;

Brisbane reasserted his authority over Vernet's settlement and recommenced the practice of paying employees in promissory notes. Due to Vernet's reduced status, the promissory notes were devalued, which meant that the employees received fewer goods at Vernet's stores for their wages. After months of freedom following the ''Lexington'' raid this accentuated dissatisfaction with the leadership of the settlement. In August 1833, under the leadership of [[Antonio Rivero]], a gang of Creole and Indian gauchos ran amok in the settlement. Armed with muskets obtained from American sealers, the gang killed five members of Vernet's settlement including both Dickson and Brisbane. Shortly afterward the survivors fled Port Louis, seeking refuge on Turf Island in [[Berkeley Sound]] until rescued by the British sealer 'Hopeful' in October 1833.&lt;ref name=&quot;briefhistory3&quot;/&gt;

Lt Henry Smith was installed as the first British resident in January 1834. One of his first actions was to pursue and arrest Rivero's gang for the murders committed the previous August. The gang was sent for trial in London but due to a quirk of the British Legal system could not be tried as the Crown Court did not have jurisdiction over the Falkland Islands. In the British colonial system, colonies had their own, distinct governments, finances, and judicial systems.&lt;ref&gt;[http://encyclopedia.farlex.com/British+colonies] British colonies - Hutchinson encyclopedia article about British colonies&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Karsten, Peter, ''Between Law and Custom, &quot;High&quot; and &quot;Low&quot; Legal Cultures in the Lands of the British Diaspora - The United States, Canada, Australia and New Zealand, 1600-1900''&lt;/ref&gt;  Rivero was not tried and sentenced because the British local government and local judiciary had not yet been installed in 1834; these were created later, by the 1841 British [[Letters Patent]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Destefani&quot;/&gt;  Subsequently, Rivero has acquired the status of a folk hero in Argentina, where he is portrayed as leading a rebellion against British rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Destefani&quot;/&gt;  Ironically it was the actions of Rivero that were responsible for the ultimate demise of Vernet's enterprise on the Falklands.

[[Charles Darwin]] revisited the Falklands in 1834; [[Darwin, Falkland Islands|Darwin]] and [[Fitzroy, Falkland Islands|Fitzroy]] both take their names from this visit.

After the arrest of Rivero, Smith set about restoring the settlement at Port Louis, repairing the damage done by the ''Lexington'' raid and renaming it 'Anson's Harbour'. Lt Lowcay succeeded Smith in April 1838, followed by Lt Robinson in September 1839 and Lt Tyssen in December 1839.&lt;ref name=&quot;briefhistory3&quot;/&gt;

Vernet later attempted to return to the Islands but was refused permission to return. The British Crown reneged on promises and refused to recognise rights granted by Captain Onslow at the time of the reoccupation. Eventually, after travelling to London, Vernet received paltry compensation for horses shipped to Port Louis many years before.&lt;ref name=&quot;briefhistory3&quot;/&gt;  G.T. Whittington obtained a concession of {{convert|6400|acre|km2|0}} from Vernet that he later exploited with the formation of the Falkland Islands Commercial Fishery and Agricultural Association.&lt;ref name=&quot;UBA1&quot;&gt;[http://www.cpel.uba.ar/filargenta/correo/malv0020.htm] Islas del Atlántico Sur, Islas Malvinas, Historia, Ocupación Inglesa: Port Stanley, Accessed 2007-10-02&lt;/ref&gt;

== British colonisation ==
{{see also|Origins of Falkland Islanders}}
[[Image:Lord john russell.jpg|thumb|left|upright|'''John Russell, 1st Earl Russell''', [[Order of the Garter|KG]], [[Order of St Michael and St George|GCMG]], [[Privy Council of the United Kingdom|PC]] (18 August 1792{{spaced ndash}}28 May 1878).]]

Following their [[Re-establishment of British rule on the Falklands (1833)|return]] to the Falkland Islands and the failure of Vernet's settlement, the British had largely maintained [[Port Louis, Falkland Islands|Port Louis]] as a military outpost. Pressure to develop the islands as a colony began to mount as the result of a campaign mounted by British merchant G.T. Whittington. Whittington formed the Falkland Islands Commercial Fishery and Agricultural Association and (based on information indirectly obtained from Vernet) published a pamphlet entitled &quot;The Falkland Islands&quot;. Later a petition signed by London merchants was presented to the [[Whig Government 1835-1841|British Government]] demanding the convening of a public meeting to discuss the future development of the Falkland Islands. Whittington petitioned the [[Secretary of State for War and the Colonies|Colonial Secretary]],  [[John Russell, 1st Earl Russell|Lord Russell]], proposing that his association be allowed to colonise the islands. In May 1840, the British Government made the decision to colonise the Falkland Islands.

Unaware of the decision by the [[Whig Government 1835-1841|British Government]] to colonise the islands, Whittington grew impatient and decided to take action of his own initiative. Obtaining two ships, he sent his brother, J. B. Whittington, on a mission to land stores and settlers at [[Port Louis, Falkland Islands|Port Louis]]. On arrival he presented his claim to land that his brother had bought from Vernet.&lt;ref name=&quot;UBA1&quot;/&gt;  Lt. Tyssen was taken aback by Whittington's arrival, indicating that he had no authority to allow this; however, he was unable to prevent the party from landing. Whittington constructed a large house for his party, and using a salting house built by Vernet established a fish-salting business.&lt;ref name = &quot;briefhistory4&quot;&gt;[http://www.falklands.info/history/history4.html] A Brief History of the Falkland Islands, Part 4 - The British Colonial Era, Accessed 2007-10-02&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1836, [[East Falkland]] was surveyed by Admiral George Grey, and further in 1837 by Lowcay. Admiral George Grey, conducting the geographic survey in November 1836 had the following to say about their first view of East Falkland -

:''We anchored a little after sunset off a creek called '[[Johnson's Harbour]]'. The day having been cloudy with occasional showers, these islands at all times dreary enough, looked particularly so on our first view of them, the shores of [[Berkeley Sound|sound]], steep, with bare hills intersected with ravines rising from them, these hills without a tree and the clouds hanging low, gave them exactly the appearance of the [[Cheviots]] or a [[Scotland|Scotch]] moor on a winter's day and considering we were in the May of these latitudes, the first impression of the climate was not favourable, the weather however, was not called, the thermometer was 63 degrees &amp;#91;Fahrenheit (17°C)] which is [[Howick, Northumberland|Howick]] mid-summer temperature.''

=== Establishment of Port Stanley ===
{{main|Stanley, Falkland Islands}}
[[Image:Stamp Falkland Islands 1891 0.5p.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Halfpenny postage stamp, issued 1891.]]

The [[Whig Government 1835-1841|British Government]] continued with its plans to colonise the [[Falkland Islands]], appointing [[Richard Moody|Lt Richard Moody]] as the first [[Governor of the Falkland Islands|Lieutenant Governor]] of the Islands. He was transported to the Falkland Islands aboard the ship ''Hebe'', arriving in [[Port Louis, Falkland Islands|Anson's Harbour]] in October 1841. He was accompanied by twelve sappers and miners and their families, together with Whittington's colonists this brought the population of Anson's Harbour to approximately 50.

In 1842, Lieutenant Governor [[Richard Moody|Moody]] was instructed by [[Edward Smith-Stanley, 14th Earl of Derby|Lord Stanley]] the British [[Secretary of State for War and the Colonies]] to report on the potential of the [[Port William, Falkland Islands|Port William]] area as the site of the new capital. Moody assigned the task of surveying the area to [[James Clark Ross|Captain Ross]], leader of the [[List of Antarctic expeditions|Antarctic Expedition]]. Captain Ross delivered his report in 1843, concluding that Port William afforded a good deep-water anchorage for naval vessels, and that the southern shores of [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Port Jackson]] was a suitable location for the proposed settlement. Not everyone was enthused with the selection of the location of the new capital, J. B. Whittington famously remarked that &quot;''Of all the miserable bog holes, I believe that Mr Moody has selected one of the worst for the site of his town.''&quot;

Construction of the new settlement started in July 1843, and in July 1845 (at [[Richard Moody|Governor Moody's]]) suggestion the new capital of the islands was officially named [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Port Stanley]] after [[Edward Smith-Stanley, 14th Earl of Derby|Lord Stanley]]. The structure of the Colonial Government was established in 1845 with the formation of the Legislative Council and [[Executive Council of the Falkland Islands|Executive Council]] and work on the construction of [[Government House (Falkland Islands)|Government House]] commenced.. The following year, the first officers appointed to the Colonial Government took their posts, by this time a number of residences, a large storage shed, carpenter's shop and blacksmiths shop had been completed and the Government Dockyard laid-out.

With the establishment of the deep-water anchorage and improvements in port facilities, Stanley saw a dramatic increase in the number of visiting ships in the 1840s in part due to the [[California Gold Rush]]. A boom in ship provisioning and ship-repair resulted, aided by the notoriously bad weather in the South Atlantic and around [[Cape Horn]]. Stanley and the Falkland Islands are famous as the repository of many wrecks of 19th century ships that reached the islands to be condemned as unseaworthy and were often employed as floating warehouses by local merchants.

At one point in the 19th century, Stanley became one of the world's busiest ports. However, the ship-repair trade began to slacken off in 1876 with the establishment of the [[Plimsoll line]], which saw the elimination of the so-called [[coffin ship (insurance)|coffin ships]] and unseaworthy vessels that might otherwise have ended up in Stanley for repair. With the introduction of increasingly reliable iron [[Steamboat|steamships]] in the 1890s the trade declined further and was no longer viable following the opening of the [[Panama Canal]] in 1914. Port Stanley continued to be a busy port supporting whaling and sealing activities in the early part of the 20th century, British warships (and garrisons) in the [[World War I|First]] and [[World War II|Second World War]] and the [[fishing]] and [[cruise ship]] industries in the latter half of the century.

[[File:WhaleboneArchCathedral.JPG|thumb|left|upright|Christ Church Cathedral and Whalebone Arch.]]

[[Government House (Falkland Islands)|Government House]] opened as the offices of the [[Governor of the Falkland Islands|Lieutenant Governor]] in 1847.  [[Government House (Falkland Islands)|Government House]] continued to develop with various additions, formally becoming the Governor's residence in 1859 when [[Governor of the Falkland Islands|Governor Moore]] took residence. Government House remains the residence of the Governor.

Many of the colonists begin to move from [[Port Louis, Falkland Islands|Ansons' Harbour]] to [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Port Stanley]]. As the new town expanded the population grew rapidly reaching 200 by 1849. The population was further expanded by the arrival of 30 married [[Chelsea pensioner|Chelsea Pensioners]] and their families. The Chelsea Pensioners were to form the permanent garrison and police force taking over from the Royal Sappers and Miners Regiment who had garrisoned the early colony.

The Exchange Building opened in 1854, part of the building was later used as a church. 1854 also saw the establishment of Marmont Row, including the Eagle Inn now known as the [[Falkland Islands Holdings|Upland Goose Hotel]]. In 1887 Jubilee Villas were built to celebrate the [[Golden Jubilee]] of [[Victoria of the United Kingdom|Queen Victoria]]. Jubilee Villas are a row of brick built houses that follow a traditional British pattern, positioned on Ross road near the waterfront they became an iconic image during the [[Falklands War]].

[[Peat]] is common on the islands and has traditionally been exploited as a fuel. Uncontrolled exploitation of this natural resource lead to [[Landslide|peat slips]] in 1878 and 1886. The 1878 peat slip resulted in the destruction of several houses, whilst the 1886 peat slip resulted in the deaths of two women and the destruction of the Exchange Building.

[[Christ Church Cathedral (Falkland Islands)|Christ Church Cathedral]] was consecrated in 1892 and completed in 1903. It received its famous [[Baleen|whalebone]] arch, constructed from the jaws of two [[Blue Whale]]s in 1933 to commemorate the [[Centennial|centenary]] of continuous British administration. Also consecrated in 1892 was the Tabernacle United Free Church, constructed from an imported timber kit.

=== Development of agriculture and the Camp ===
{{further|Camp (Falkland Islands)}}
[[Image:Sapper-Hill-Corral.jpg|thumb|right|One of the remaining historic [[corral]]s at Sapper Hill, near Stanley.]]

A few years after the British had established themselves in the islands, a number of new British settlements were started. Initially many of these settlements were established in order to exploit the [[feral]] cattle on the islands. Following the introduction of the [[Cheviot sheep|Cheviot]] breed of sheep to the islands in 1852, sheep farming became the dominant form of agriculture on the Islands.

[[Salvador Settlement]] was one of the earliest, being started in the 1830s, by a [[Gibraltarian people|Gibraltarian]] immigrant (hence its other name of &quot;Gibraltar Settlement&quot;), and it is still run by his descendants, the Pitalugas.

Vernet furnished Samuel Fisher Lafone, a British merchant operating from [[Montevideo]], with details of the Falklands Islands including a map. Sensing that the exploitation of feral cattle on the islands would be a lucrative venture, in 1846 he negotiated a contract with the British Government that gave him exclusive rights to this resource. Until 1846 [[Richard Moody|Moody]] had allotted feral cattle to new settlers and the new agreement not only prevented this but made Stanley dependent upon Lafone for supplies of [[Beef]].

[[Cattle]] were concentrated in the southern part of [[East Falkland]], an area that became known as [[Lafonia]]. Lafone was an absentee landlord and never actually set foot on the islands. His activities were not monitored by the British and rather than introducing more British settlers as he promised, he brought large numbers of Spanish and Indian gauchos to hunt cattle. In 1846, they established [[Hope Place]] on the south shores of [[Brenton Loch]] and in 1849 a sod wall (the Boca wall) was built across the isthmus at [[Darwin, Falkland Islands|Darwin]] to control the movement of cattle.
[[Image:Falkland-Islands-Company.JPG|thumb|left|Falkland Islands Company's historical building in Stanley]]
Lafone continued to develop his business interests and in 1849 looked to establish a joint stock company with his [[London]] creditors. The company was launched as the ''The Royal Falkland Land, Cattle, Seal and Fishery Company'' in 1850 but soon thereafter was incorporated under Royal Charter as the [[Falkland Islands Holdings|''The Falkland Islands Company Limited''.]]  Lafone became a director and his brother-in-law J.P. Dale the company's first manager in the Islands. By 1852, the feral cattle had been hunted virtually to extinction by gauchos and the company switched to sheep farming with the introduction of the [[Cheviot sheep|Cheviot]] breed of sheep. Hope Place proved to be an unsuitable location and the operation moved to [[Darwin, Falkland Islands|Darwin]]. In 1860, the Lafone Beef contract was terminated but the Falkland Islands Company was given a grant to [[Lafonia]]. Ownership of the remaining cattle outside of Lafonia reverted to the Government and hunting cattle without permission was banned.

In the second half of the 19th century, [[Darwin, Falkland Islands|Darwin]], [[Goose Green]], [[Fox Bay]] and [[Port Howard]] were established. Port Howard was founded by James Lovegrove Waldron, and his brother in 1866; the Waldron brothers later left for [[Patagonia]], but left the farm under local management.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wigglesworth&quot;&gt;Wigglesworth, Angela. (1992) ''Falkland People''. Pub. Peter Owen. ISBN 0-7206-0850-3&lt;/ref&gt;

Darwin was initially the haunt of ''[[gaucho]]s'', and cattle farmers, but sheep farming came to dominate the area, and Scottish shepherds were brought in. A few years later, the first large tallow works in the islands (though not the first) was set up by the FIC in 1874. It handled 15,891 sheep in 1880.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ian_Strange&quot;/&gt;

From the 1880s, until 1972, Darwin and [[Fox Bay]] had their own separate medical officers. Nowadays, most medical care is based in Stanley.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ian_Strange&quot;/&gt;

=== Exploitation of maritime resources ===

The [[Falkland Islands]] were used as a base for [[Whaler|whaling ships]] hunting the [[Southern Right Whale]] and [[Sperm Whale]] from the 1770s until British authority was established over the islands and surrounding seas.  [[Whaling]] was briefly revived with the establishment of a whaling station on [[New Island]] from 1909 to 1917 until whaling operations moved to [[South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands|South Georgia]].

[[Fur Seal|Fur seals]] had long been exploited for their pelts but numbers entered a drastic decline in the early 19th century. As a result seal hunting died off, although continuing at a low level. In order to conserve stocks, a ban on the hunting of fur seals during summers months was enacted in 1881 but it was not until 1921 that hunting was banned entirely.

[[Elephant seal]]s were exploited for oil but like the fur seals their numbers declined drastically in the mid-1850s. Sealers instead turned their attention to the [[South American Sea Lion]] resulting in a dramatic decline in their numbers that made sealing uneconomic. Attempts to revive the trade, including a sealing station at [[Port Albermarle]], were unsuccessful.

Even penguins were exploited for oil. [[Southern Rockhopper Penguin|Rockhopper]] and [[Gentoo penguin|Gentoo]] [[penguin]]s were rendered down in [[Try pot|trypots]] from 1860 until the 1880s.

== Twentieth century ==

===Establishment of communications===
Although the first telephone lines were installed by the Falkland Islands Company in the 1880s, the Falkland Islands Government was slow to embrace telephony. It was not until 1897 that a telephone line was installed between [[Cape Pembroke]] lighthouse and the police station. The islands isolation was broken in 1911 when Marconi installed a wireless telegraphy station that enabled telegrams to be sent to mainland Uruguay.&lt;ref name = &quot;CableWireless&quot;&gt;[http://www.cwfi.co.fk/history.html] Cable &amp; Wireless, The Falkland Islands, Our History&lt;/ref&gt;

A line was laid between Darwin and Stanley, with the ship ''Consort'' landing poles on the coast. Construction commenced in 1906 and was finished in 1907 (a length of nearly {{convert|50|mi|disp=or}}). The line was initially only for business but the public could make calls occasionally.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ian_Strange&quot;/&gt;  Lines continued to be laid to most of the major settlements in the islands, with the Falkland Islands police responsible for their maintenance till 1927. Communications among the settlements relied on the telephone network until radio telephones were introduced in the 1950s, although the telephone network continued until 1982.&lt;ref name =&quot;CableWireless&quot;/&gt;  Telecommunications improved dramatically after the [[Falklands War]], when an earth station was installed to allow direct dialling for the first time. In 1997, an Internet service was launched and by 2002 nearly 90% of Falkland homes had Internet access.&lt;ref name =&quot;CableWireless&quot;/&gt;

===Economic development===
[[Image:Ajaxbayview.jpg|right|thumb|The freezer plant at [[Ajax Bay]]. Most of the workers' cottages were moved to Stanley]]

A canning factory was opened in 1911 at Goose Green and was initially extremely successful. It absorbed a large proportion of surplus sheep but during the postwar slump suffered a serious loss and closed down in 1921.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ian_Strange&quot;/&gt;

Despite this setback, a mere year later, the settlement grew after it became the base for the [[Falkland Islands Company]]'s [[sheep farm]] in [[Lafonia]] in 1922, with improved sheep handling and wool shed being built.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ian_Strange&quot;/&gt; In 1927, the settlement's huge sheep shearing shed was built, which is claimed to be the world's largest, with a capacity of five thousand sheep.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wigglesworth&quot; /&gt; In 1979, 100,598 sheep were shorn at Goose Green&lt;ref name = &quot;Ian_Strange&quot;/&gt;

The mid 20th century saw a number of abortive attempts to diversify the islands' economy away from large scale sheep ranching.

In the period just after the Second World War, [[Port Albemarle]] in the south west of [[West Falkland]], was enlarged during the post-WWII period by the [[Colonial Development Company]] and included its own power station, jetty, [[Nissen hut]]s etc. - this was an attempt to revive the old sealing industry which had flourished during the 19th century. However, the project proved to be a &quot;white elephant&quot;, not least because seal numbers had declined massively.
[[Image:Shovel-Falklands.jpg|thumb|Islanders shovelling [[peat]] (1950s)]]
Similarly, [[Ajax Bay]] on [[Falkland Sound]], was developed by the [[Colonial Development Corporation]] in the 1950s, which was also responsible for developing Port Albemarle. It was mainly a refrigeration plant, and was supposed to freeze Falkland [[mutton]], but this was found to be economically unviable, despite the huge expense incurred. Many of the pre-fabricated houses here were moved to [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Stanley]]. The site later became a British field hospital during the landings of [[Operation Sutton]].

The seas around the Falkland Islands were not well policed prior to the Falklands War, and many foreign boats fished off the islands, despite protests that potential revenue was being lost. Fishing licences were only later to be introduced.

===Education===
In 1956, J.L. Waldron Ltd built a school at Port Howard, possibly inspired by the &quot;gift&quot; of the FIC at Darwin, a few years earlier.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ian_Strange&quot;&gt;Strange, Ian, ''The Falkland Islands'', 1983&lt;/ref&gt;

Up until the 1970s, Goose Green was the site of a boarding school, run by the state. [[Camp (Falklands)|&quot;Camp&quot;]] children boarded here, and there were 40 spaces. The boarding school was later transferred to Stanley, although the recent emphasis has been on locally based education. The school itself became an Argentine HQ, and was burnt down. A new (day) school has been built for local children.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wigglesworth&quot; /&gt;

===First World War===
[[Image:HMS Canopus news mimic.jpg|left|thumb|left|HMS ''Canopus''. Canopus Hill in the [[Falkland Islands]] commemorates her role in the [[Battle of the Falkland Islands]].]]
[[Image:Falklandschlacht.jpg|right|thumb|The '''[[Battle of the Falkland Islands]]''', 8 December 1914. The German [[armoured cruiser]]s under Admiral von Spee that had been raiding British sealanes were sunk by a British [[battlecruiser]] task force.]]
{{main|Battle of the Falkland Islands}}

Port Stanley became an important coaling station for the [[Royal Navy]]. This led to ships based there being involved in major naval engagements in both the [[World War I|First]] and [[Second World War]]s.

The strategic significance of the [[Falkland Islands]] was confirmed by the [[Battle of the Falkland Islands|second major naval engagement]] of the [[World War I|First World War]]. [[Admiral]] [[Graf Maximilian von Spee]]'s [[German East Asia Squadron]] called at the islands on its trip from the [[Pacific Ocean]] back to [[Germany]], intending to destroy the [[Royal Navy]] radio relay station and coaling depot there. Unknown to Spee, a British [[Squadron (naval)|squadron]], including two [[battlecruiser]]s considerably more powerful than his forces, had been sent to hunt down his squadron and happened to be in the harbour coaling. In the one-sided battle which followed, most of Spee's squadron was sunk. [[Canopus Hill]], south of Stanley, is named after [[HMS Canopus (1897)|HMS ''Canopus'']], which had fired the first shot in the battle.

===Second World War===
{{main|Battle of the River Plate}}

In December, 1939 a British [[Squadron (naval)|naval squadron]] comprising [[HMS Ajax (22)|HMS ''Ajax'']], [[HMS Achilles (70)|HMS ''Achilles'']] and [[HMS Exeter (68)|HMS ''Exeter'']] engaged the German [[Deutschland class cruiser|Pocket Battleship]] [[German pocket battleship Admiral Graf Spee|''Admiral Graf Spee'']]. Despite being outgunned by the {{convert|11|in|mm|0|sing=on}} guns of the ''Graf Spee'', the British squadron aggressively engaged ''Graf Spee'' inflicting major damage. The {{convert|8|in|mm|0|sing=on}} guns of ''Exeter'' were a more significant threat than the {{convert|6|in|mm|0|sing=on}} guns of ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' and inflicted more serious damage to the ''Graf Spee''. As a result the ''Graf Spee'' concentrated fire upon the ''Exeter'' inflicting some 40 direct hits and causing major damage. On the 16 December, ''Exeter'' limped into [[Stanley Harbour]], with 60 of the 600 crew dead and 49 wounded. The crew had to be boarded out in Stanley as ''Exeter'' was too badly damaged. The [[County class cruiser|County class]] heavy cruiser [[HMS Cumberland (C57)|HMS ''Cumberland'']], which had been self-refitting in the [[Falkland Islands]] at the time of the battle, steamed to join ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' at the mouth of the [[Río de la Plata|River Plate]]. Convinced by British [[propaganda]] and false intelligence that a major naval task force awaited his ship and short of ammunition, Captain [[Hans Langsdorff|Langsdorf]] of the ''Graf Spee'' chose instead to [[Scuttling|scuttle]] the ship rather than face the [[Royal Navy]].

===Argentine incursions===

A series of incidents in the 1960s marked the intensification of Argentine sovereignty claims.

The first of these took place in 1964, when a light plane piloted by Miguel Fitzgerald touched down on the racecourse at [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Stanley]]. Leaping from the aircraft, he handed a letter claiming sovereignty to a bemused [[Falkland Islanders|islander]] before flying off again. The stunt was timed to coincide with Argentine diplomatic efforts at the UN Decolonisation Committee.

[[Image:MiguelLFitzergersald.jpg|left|thumb|upright|Miguel L. Fitzgerald flew to the [[Falkland Islands]] in [[light aircraft]] in 1964 and 1968.  (Originally published by ''Crónica'', 9 September 1964.)]]

The more serious incident took place in 1966.
An [[Aerolíneas Argentinas]] [[Douglas DC-4|DC-4]] on an internal flight to Santa Cruz with 35 passengers was hijacked and flown to the Falkland Islands. A group of ardent Argentine nationalists, styling themselves 'Condors', forced the pilot to fly to Stanley. The head of the operation was Dardo Cabo (aged 25 at the time), who walked into the command cabin with a pistol and ordered pilot Ernesto Fernandez Garcia to turn the plane on course one-zero-five.&lt;ref name=briefhistory_150yrs&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.falklands.info/history/history2.html
|title = Falkland Islands Defence Force: 150 years of Voluntary Service
|author = Peter Biggs
|date = November 2004
|publisher = A brief history of the Falkland Islands
|accessdate = 2010-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;   On arrival, they attempted to land at the racecourse but hit telegraph poles and the undercarriage sank into the mud. Islanders, assuming that the plane was in trouble, rushed to assist but found themselves taken hostage by the terrorists (included in the group of four was a young police sergeant, [[Terry Peck]], who became a local hero in the [[Falklands War]]). Les Gleadell, acting Governor of the Falkland Islands, ordered that the DC-4 be surrounded.&lt;ref name=briefhistory_150yrs/&gt; He received three of the invaders, who announced that they had as much right as anyone to be there and in reply were firmly told that they should disarm and give up. The result of this meeting was an agreement that seven men, including Peck and Captain Ian Martin, commanding a four-man Royal Marines detachment, should be exchanged for the hostages aboard the aircraft. The 26 passengers were then allowed to disembark and sent to lodge with local families, as the island had no hotel. One of the passengers was Admiral Jose Guzmán, the Governor of Tierra del Fuego (which theoretically included the Falklands); on being taken past the governor's residence, he laughingly commented: &quot;Mi casa&quot;. After a bitterly cold night in the aircraft, which contained only brandy, wine, orange juice and a few biscuits, the kidnappers still refused to surrender to the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/politics-obituaries/5819646/Les-Gleadell.html | work=The Daily Telegraph | location=London | title=Les Gleadell | date=13 July 2009 | accessdate=4 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
After 24 hours, the terrorists surrendered and were detained in an annex to St Mary's Church. Wishing to avoid a prolonged incident, the British Government chose to repatriate the terrorists to Argentina, where they received only nominal prison sentences and were treated as heroes (a plaque was later unveiled in [[Buenos Aires]] honouring their escapade). The significance of this event was later shown when in 2009 it was reported in Merco Press&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.mercopress.com/2009/07/22/pensions-for-argentine-members-of-failed-attempt-to-capture-the-falklands-i Pensions for Argentine members of failed attempt to capture the Falklands in 1966] ''The Peronist government of the Argentine province of Buenos Aires will grant a special pension to the nationalist group of 18 civilians who in 1966 took command of a commercial flight to Rio Gallegos and had it re-routed to the Falkland Islands with the purpose of taking over the Malvinas for Argentina.''&lt;/ref&gt; that a monthly pension, equivalent to the basic salary of provincial government staff, would be awarded to the remaining terrorists or the descendants of those who had already died. This incident was timed to coincide with the start of the autumn session of the United Nations.

On October of the same year a group of Argentine [[Tactical Divers Group|naval special forces]] conducted covert landings from the submarine [[USS Lamprey (SS-372)|ARA ''Santiago del Estero'']]. The 12-man team, which landed some {{convert|40|km|mi|0}} from Stanley, was led by Juan Jose Lombardo who later, as Chief of Naval Operations, planned the [[1982 invasion of the Falkland Islands]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clarin.com/diario/96/03/31/malvinas.html#prof Malvinas: los secretos de la guerra {{es}}]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:ARA-Stgo.jpg|left|thumb|The locally upgraded [[Balao class|''Balao'' class]] submarine ARA ''Santiago del Estero'' (S-12), Argentine Naval Base at [[Mar del Plata]], ''circa'' 1969]]
In November 1968, Miguel Fitzgerald was hired by the Argentine press to attempt a reprise of his 1964 landing. Accompanied by one of the 1966 hijackers, he flew to Stanley but on arrival found he could not land at the racecourse due to obstacles placed following the hijacking. The plane was forced to crash land on Eliza Cove Road, but the two occupants were unharmed. The stunt was intended to coincide with the visit of [[Alun Jones, Baron Chalfont|Lord Chalfont]] to the islands.

The latter incident proved counter-productive to the Argentine sovereignty push, as Lord Chalfont had been talking to a public meeting at the time of the plane's arrival. The islanders made it plain to Lord Chalfont that they rejected a Memorandum of Agreement negotiated between Britain and Argentina that August which stated that Britain was prepared to discuss sovereignty provided the islanders' wishes were respected. This spurred the formation of the Falkland Islands Committee by London barrister Bill Hunter-Christie and others. The Emergency Committee, as it became known, proved to be an effective lobbying organisation, constantly undermining Foreign Office initiatives on sovereignty negotiations. In December 1968, the lobbying effort managed to force the British Government to state that the islanders' wishes would be paramount.

===Growing links with Argentina===

Partly as the result of diplomatic pressure, economic and political links with [[Argentina]] increased in the 1960s and 70s. These became severed after the end of the Falklands War, but before the War they were not entirely negative, and some islanders sent their children to boarding schools in Argentina.

Realising that any talks on the sovereignty issue would be derailed if it did not meet with the islanders' wishes, the British and Argentine Governments enacted a series of measures designed to encourage dependence on Argentina. In 1971, following secret talks between the two Governments (and without consulting the islanders), the communications agreement was signed. The thrust of the agreement was the establishment of direct air and sea links between the islands and Argentina, together with agreements on postal and telephony services. Following the agreement the subsidised shipping link with [[Montevideo]] ended, a passenger and cargo ship service to the mainland (that would ameliorate any dependence on Argentina) was promised by the British but never provided.

[[LADE|''Líneas Aéreas del Estado'' (LADE)]], the airline operated by the [[Argentine Air Force|Argentine Air Force (''Fuerza Aérea Argentina'' or FAA)]], began an air link to the islands. Initially this service operated [[amphibious aircraft]] between [[Comodoro Rivadavia]] and Stanley using [[HU-16 Albatross|Grumman HU-16 Albatross]] aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;&quot;&gt;[http://web.sion.com/s.alaimo/malvinas.html] Commemorative Stamps of first flights&lt;/ref&gt;  The inauguration of the service was commemorated by a series of stamps issued by both the Argentine and Falkland Island postal services. In 1972, a temporary airstrip was constructed by Argentina near [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Stanley]]. Britain constructed a small permanent airstrip in 1976 suitable only for short haul flights.

As part of the agreement, islanders had to travel via Argentina and were forced to carry Argentine Identity Cards issued in [[Buenos Aires]]. The ''Tarjeta Provisoria'' or &quot;white card&quot; as they were known were hated by the islanders, who felt they were a ''[[de facto]]'' Argentine [[passport]], since only islanders were required to use them and not other temporary residents of the islands. Tensions were raised further with the agreement that male [[Falkland Islander]]s would not have to undertake conscription into the [[Argentine Army]], since this carried the implication that [[Falkland Islander]]s were Argentine citizens.

[[LADE]] set up an office in [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Stanley]] and mail was routed through Argentina. Medical treatments unavailable in the islands were provided in Argentina and scholarships were made available for study in [[Buenos Aires]], [[Córdoba, Argentina|Córdoba]] and other Argentine cities.  [[Spanish language]] teachers were provided by Argentina.  [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office|Foreign Office]] officials in [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Stanley]] were instructed to do everything possible to foster good relations between the Islands and Argentina.

The islands became more dependent upon Argentina, when the British and Argentine governments agreed that the islands would be supplied with petrol, diesel and oil by [[Yacimientos Petrolíferos Fiscales|YPF]], the Argentine national oil and gas company.

[[Image:James Callaghan.JPG|right|thumb|upright|[[Prime Minister]] [[James Callaghan|Jim Callaghan]] sent a naval task force in response to Argentine pressure in 1976.]]

Despite these tensions relationships between the islanders and the Argentines operating the new services in the islands were cordial. Although there was apprehension, politics were generally avoided and on a one-to-one basis there was never any real hostility.

On the international level, relations began to sour in 1975 when Argentine delegates at the London meeting of the International Parliamentary Union condemned Britain's &quot;act of international piracy&quot; in establishing a colony in the Falkland Islands. Diplomatic relations between Britain and Argentina were broken but resumed in 1976.

In October 1975, the British Government tasked [[Edward Shackleton, Baron Shackleton|Lord Shackleton]] (son of the Antarctic explorer [[Ernest Shackleton|Sir Ernest Shackleton]]) with an economic survey of the [[Falkland Islands]]. The Argentine Government reacted furiously and refused permission for [[Edward Shackleton, Baron Shackleton|Lord Shackleton]] to travel via Argentina. Later the ship transporting Shackleton to the islands, the [[RRS Shackleton|RRS ''Shackleton'']], was fired upon by the Argentine [[destroyer]] [[USS Cowell (DD-547)|ARA ''Almirante Storni'']].

In 1976, after a military ''[[military junta|junta]]'' took control of the country, Argentina covertly established a [[Corbeta Uruguay|military base]] on [[Southern Thule]]. It was discovered by the [[British Antarctic Survey]] ship [[RRS Bransfield|RRS ''Bransfield'']] in 1977. The British protested but restricted their response to a diplomatic protest. Backing up the diplomatic efforts, the British Prime Minister [[James Callaghan|Jim Callaghan]] sent a naval task force consisting of surface ships and a [[Submarine|nuclear submarine]]. Nevertheless Argentine aircraft and warships harassed ships fishing in Falkland waters.

[[Edward Shackleton, Baron Shackleton|Lord Shackleton]]'s report was delivered in 1977 and documented the economic stagnation in the islands. It nevertheless concluded that the islands made a net contribution to the British economy and had economic potential for development. Recommendations included oil exploration, exploitation of the fisheries, extension of the Stanley runway, the creation of a development agency, the expansion of the road network, expansion of the facilities at Stanley harbour and the breakdown of absentee landlord owned farms into family units. The report was largely ignored at the time, as it was felt that acting upon it would sour relations with Argentina. A reprise of the report by [[Edward Shackleton, Baron Shackleton|Lord Shackleton]] in 1982 following the [[Falklands War]] became the blueprint for subsequent economic development of the islands.

===Falklands War===
[[Image:FotoOficialGaltieri.jpg|right|thumb|upright| General [[Galtieri]], Argentina's leader during the Falklands War.]]
{{main|Events leading to the Falklands War|1982 invasion of the Falkland Islands|Occupation of the Falkland Islands|Falklands War}}

[[Argentina]] invaded the islands on 2 April 1982, using special forces, which landed at [[Mullet Creek]] and advanced on Government House in Stanley, with a secondary force coming in from [[Yorke Bay]]. They encountered little opposition, there being only a small force of fifty-seven British marines and eleven sailors, in addition to the [[Falkland Islands Defence Force]] (who were later sent to [[Fox Bay]]). There was only one Argentine fatality. The event garnered international attention at a level which the islands had never experienced before, and made them a household name in the UK.

For a brief period, the Falkland Islands found themselves under Argentine control. This included Spanish-language signage, and attempts to make the islanders drive on the right (although few roads in the Falklands at the time actually had two lanes). In many parts of the [[Camp (Falkland Islands)|Camp]], such as [[Goose Green]] and [[Pebble Island]], the islanders found themselves under [[house arrest]].

The British responded with an expeditionary force that landed seven weeks later and, after fierce fighting, forced the Argentine garrison to surrender on 14 June 1982. The war proved to be an anomaly in a number of different respects, not least that it proved that small arms still had a role to play. It also had major consequences for the ''Junta'', which was toppled soon afterwards.

[[Margaret Thatcher]]'s general political legacy remains controversial and divisive within the UK and within the context of the Falklands her government's withdrawal of HMS ''Endurance'' is a stated contributing factor to the causes of the conflict because it gave the wrong signals about the UK attitude towards maintaining its possession.   However, within the Falklands, she is considered a heroine because of the determination of her response to the Argentine invasion.  The islands celebrate ''Margaret Thatcher Day'' on every 10 January, and named a street ''Thatcher Drive'' after her, in Stanley.

== Post-war ==
[[File:Kirchner-UN General Assembly (2007).jpg|right|thumb|President [[Néstor Kirchner]] continued to pursue Argentine claims to the islands. His wife [[Cristina Fernández]] is the incumbent.]]

Following the war, Britain focused on improving its facilities on the islands. It increased its military presence significantly, building a large base at [[RAF Mount Pleasant]] and its port at [[Mare Harbour]]. It also invested heavily in improving facilities in [[Stanley, Falkland Islands|Stanley]] and transportation and infrastructure around the islands, [[tarmac]]king the Stanley - Mount Pleasant road and many roads within Stanley.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/south-america/falkland-islands
|title = Falkland Islands (British Overseas Territory)
|published = [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]]
|year = 2011
|accessdate = 22 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The population has risen due to the growth of Stanley, but has declined in ''[[Camp (Falkland Islands)|Camp]]'' (the countryside). 
Since November 2008, a regular [[ferry]] service has linked [[East Falkland|East]] and [[West Falkland|West]], carrying cars, passengers and cargo serviced by the ''MV Concordia Bay'', a 42.45&amp;nbsp;m twin-screw shallow draft (2.59&amp;nbsp;m) landing craft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.holyheadtowing.co.uk/vessels/concordia-bay/
|title = Concordia Bay
|publisher = Holyhead Towing Company Ltd
|year = 2010
|accessdate = 2010-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A major change to the way the Falkland Islands are governed was introduced by the 1985 constitution. Under the 1985 constitution the Falkland Islands Government (FIG) became a parliamentary representative democratic dependency, with the governor as head of government and representative of the [[Monarchy of the United Kingdom|Queen]]. Members of the FIG are democratically elected; the Governor is purely a figurehead with no [[Executive (government)|executive powers]]. Effectively under this constitution, the Falkland Islands are self-governing with the exception of foreign policy, although the FIG represents itself at the [[United Nations Special Committee on Decolonisation]] as the British Government no longer attends.

Links with Argentina became severed during the post-war period, with laws being introduced to forbid Argentine citizens from buying land. An alternative trading partner was found in [[Chile]], and over the years, the islands found themselves with closer links to that country, with flights being introduced to [[Punta Arenas, Chile|Punta Arenas]], in the far south of [[Patagonia]]n Chile, near [[Tierra del Fuego]]. In recent years, Argentines have been allowed to visit the islands again, often to visit the military cemeteries where their friends and loved ones are buried.

[[Image:Falklands-Minefield.JPG|thumb|War legacy: An Argentine minefield at Port William.]]

Mines continue to be a persistent problem, and though some areas have been cleared, massive [[minefield]]s are still to be found on both the main islands and elsewhere, particularly in the areas immediately around Stanley. Because [[peat]] moves over time, the mines themselves have shifted location.

As well as the military build-up, the UK also passed the [[British Nationality (Falkland Islands) Act 1983]] which granted full [[British nationality law|British citizenship]] to the islanders. High-profile British dignitaries also visited to show British commitment to the islands, including [[Margaret Thatcher]], the [[Charles, Prince of Wales|Prince of Wales]] and [[Princess Alexandra, The Honourable Lady Ogilvy|Princess Alexandra]]. In 1985, the Falkland Islands Dependency was split into the Falkland Islands proper and a new separate territory of [[South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands]].

Relations between the UK and Argentina remained hostile following 1982, and diplomatic relations were not restored until 1989. Although the [[United Nations General Assembly]] passed a resolution calling for the UK and Argentina to return to negotiations over the Islands' future,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/37/a37r009.htm A/RES/37/9. Question of the Falkland Islands (Malvinas)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the UK ruled out any further talks over the Islands' sovereignty. The UK also maintained an arms [[embargo]] against Argentina that was initiated during the 1982 war, which forced Argentine armed forces, a traditional UK buyer, switch to other markets.

&lt;!--Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:203301 queen and menem shake hands300.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Queen Elizabeth II]] greets [[Carlos Menem]] at [[Buckingham Palace]], [[London]] in October 1998.]]--&gt;
Relations between the [[English settlement in Argentina|UK and Argentina]] improved further in the 1990s. In 1998, [[Carlos Menem]], the [[President of Argentina]] visited London, where he reaffirmed his country's claims to the Islands, although he stated that Argentina would use only peaceful means for their recovery. In 2001, [[Tony Blair]], [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom]] visited Argentina where he stated that he hoped the UK and Argentina could resolve their differences that led to the 1982 war. However, no talks on sovereignty took place during the visit. His reception in Argentina was more welcoming than that of [[Diana, Princess of Wales]] in 1995, who was heckled by the mother of an Argentine soldier killed in the war.

===Increased British military presence and new bases===
{{main|RAF Mount Pleasant|Mare Harbour}}

After the war ended, the British still faced the problem of potential Argentine aggression in the future, so an aircraft carrier had to remain on station to guard the islands with its [[Squadron (aviation)|squadron]] of Sea Harriers until the local airfield was prepared for jet aircraft. [[HMS Hermes (R12)|HMS ''Hermes'']] was the first to take guard duty, whilst [[HMS Invincible (R05)|HMS ''Invincible'']] went north to change a gearbox that had broken while departing the mainland UK, the Argentines claimed the aircraft carrier was hit on 30 May, and needed repairs.  ''Invincible'' then returned to relieve ''Hermes'' which urgently needed to return to the UK to have its boilers cleaned. ''Invincible'' returned until the ship was relieved by [[HMS Illustrious (R06)|HMS ''Illustrious'']], which was quickly rushed south and commissioned during the journey. Once the Port Stanley runway was available for jets, ''Illustrious'' was relieved by several RAF [[F-4 Phantom|Phantoms]].

The British government later decided to construct a new RAF base as the centrepiece of plans to considerably strengthen the island's defences. This was intended to deter any future Argentine attempts to take the islands by force again. It was a massive undertaking, requiring the construction of the world's longest corridor, a half-mile long, linking barracks, messes and recreational and the welfare areas of the base.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?view=DETAILS&amp;grid=&amp;xml=/news/2006/07/22/db2202.xml Obituary of former commander, British Forces, Falkland Islands, Brig. David Nicholls.]&lt;/ref&gt; The base is occasionally referred to by its residents as the [[Death Star]] because of its vast size, and sometimes confusing layout.

[[Image:Mount-Pleasant.JPG|thumb|RAF Mount Pleasant]]

[[RAF Mount Pleasant|Mount Pleasant]], to the west of Stanley, was chosen as the site for the new base. The airfield was opened by [[Prince Andrew, Duke of York|The Duke of York]] in 1985, and became fully operational in 1986.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.falklands.gov.fk/3.htm Falkland Islands Government]&lt;/ref&gt;

Using the [[IATA airport code]] '''MPN''', [[RAF Mount Pleasant]] also acts as the Falkland Islands' only international airport, in addition to its military role. Flights open to civilian passengers are operated twice-weekly.&lt;ref name=FITB&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.visitorfalklands.com/content/view/186/175/ | title= Getting Here (By Air) | publisher= Falklands Islands Tourist Board | accessdate= 2009-01-05}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
These flights are currently operated by a civilian airline on behalf of the Royal Air Force, and fly to and from [[RAF Brize Norton]] in [[Oxfordshire]], UK with a refuelling stop at [[RAF Ascension Island]] in the south-central [[Atlantic Ocean]]. Chilean airline [[LAN Airlines]] also operate weekly flights from [[Santiago, Chile|Santiago]].&lt;ref name=FITB/&gt;

In May 2005, some English [[Tabloid press|tabloid newspapers]] reported that Argentina might be considering another invasion of the Islands. The ''[[Sunday Express]]'' carried the frontpage headline, &quot;Falklands Invasion Alert&quot; on its 22 May edition, citing an increase in Argentine military activity near the Islands, as well as a reported increase in the British garrison, including a Royal Navy ship allegedly carrying tactical [[nuclear weapon]]s (the last Royal Navy tactical nuclear weapons were withdrawn in the late 1990s). The only nuclear armed RN vessels in service at the time were the four [[Vanguard class submarine]]s, which were armed with [[Trident missile]]s. Two days later, ''India Daily'' published speculation that the islands could be a nuclear flashpoint in the future if Argentina were to gain a nuclear arsenal, citing the findings of an unnamed international [[thinktank]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indiadaily.com/editorial/2849.asp Indiadaily.com - Falkland Islands can become a nuclear flashpoint in South/Central America&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; There was no official comment on the stories by the British or Argentine governments, and other writers have denounced the stories as &quot;nonsense&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.falkland-malvinas.com/Detalle.asp?NUM=5698 Mercopress&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; - any such invasion would meet with a considerably larger Falklands based British force than in 1982.

===Attempts at diversifying the economy===
[[Image:Port-William.JPG|left|thumb|A squid trawler, and a cruise ship in [[Port William, Falkland Islands|Port William]] representing two trends in recent economic development]]

Before the Falklands war, sheep-farming was the Falkland Islands' only industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;browne20020317&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2002/mar/17/uk.falklands?INTCMP=ILCNETTXT3487 | title=Falkland Islands millionaires reap the war dividend | work=The Observer | date=2002-03-17 | accessdate=July 15, 2012 | author=Browne, Anthony}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fishing has become the largest part of the economy since two species of squid popular with consumers were discovered in substantial numbers near the Falklands in the late 1980s.&lt;ref name=&quot;herbert20070118&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/this-britain/wanted-holiday-rep-to-sell-joys-of-falklands-tourism-432581.html | title=Wanted: holiday rep to sell joys of Falklands tourism | work=The Independent | date=2007-01-18 | accessdate=August 10, 2012 | author=Herbert, Ian}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 September 2011 Rockhopper Exploration announced plans are under way for oil production to commence in 2016, through the use of [[Floating production storage and offloading|Floating production storage and offloading (FPSO)]] technology, replicating the methodology used on the [[Foinaven]] field off the [[Shetland Islands]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.rockhopperexploration.co.uk/pdf/cap_markets/RKH_CapMark_Section_04Development.pdf
|title = Capital Markets Presentation - Development
|publisher = Rockhopper Exploration plc
|date = 14 September 2011
|accessdate = 2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The production site will require approximately 110 people working offshore and another 40 working onshore.&lt;ref&gt;Rockhopper presentation - page 130&lt;/ref&gt; The oil is expected to trade at {{nobreak|90 - 105%}} of the Brent crude price.&lt;ref&gt;Rockhopper presentation - page 151&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the small businesses attempted at [[Fox Bay]] have included a market garden, a salmon farm and a knitting mill with &quot;Warrah Knitwear&quot;.

[[Tourism]] is the second-largest part of the economy.{{r|herbert20070118}} The war brought the islands newfound fame, and tourists came both to see the islands' wildlife and go on war tours. Cruise ships often visit, frequently as a tie-in to [[Tourism in Antarctica|Antarctica]].{{r|browne20020317}} Nonetheless, the remoteness of the [[archipelago]], and the lack of direct flights to major cities, have made the islands an expensive holiday destination, and as a result mass tourism has not really begun.

===Conservation===
In line with the increasing global interest in [[Environmentalism|environmental issues]], some nature reserves have been set up around the islands, although there are no national parks. In the 1990s, two of the [[Jason Islands]], [[Steeple Jason Island]] and [[Grand Jason Island]], were bought by [[New York]] philanthropist [[Michael Steinhardt]], who later donated them to the [[Bronx Zoo]]-based [[Wildlife Conservation Society]]. He also gave them [[US dollar|US$]]425,000 to build a conservation station named after himself and his wife Judy.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

Likewise in [[Sea Lion Island]], in 1990, the Clifton family who had owned the island sold it to the Falkland Island Development Company. They had planted 60,000 stands of [[tussac grass]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Wigglesworth&quot; /&gt; which was considered important as much of the tussac grass on the two main islands had been depredated by grazing. A similar trend may be seen on [[Bleaker Island]], where the farm &quot;went organic&quot; in 1999.{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}}

==See also==
* [[Origins of Falkland Islanders]]
* [[Puerto Soledad]]
* [[History of South Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands]]
* [[Timeline of the history of the Falkland Islands]]
* [[Sovereignty of the Falkland Islands]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://history.falklands.info Falkland Islands History] ''Early history adapted from the ninth edition of an encyclopedia (1879) and other sources.''
*[http://www.falklands.info/history/timeline.html Falklands Islands History - timeline]
*[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/report/1987/CRD.htm 1987 American report] by Richard D. Chenette, Lieutenant Commander, USN, laying out the history and background of the disputed claims
*[http://www.history.horizon.co.fk/chronology.html The History of the Falkland Islands - Chronology]
*[http://www.ussduncan.org/silas_page13.htm Silas Duncan and the Falkland Islands' Incident]
* [http://www.cema.edu.ar/ceieg/arg-rree/historia_indice00.htm Historia de las Relaciones Exteriores Argentinas, Obra dirigida por Carlos Escudé y Andrés Cisneros, desarrollada y publicada bajo los auspicious del Consejo Argentino para las Relaciones Internacionales (CARI), GEL/Nuevohacer (Buenos Aires), 2000.]
* [http://www.historyofnations.net/southamerica/falklandislands.html History of Falkland Islands]
* Graham Pascoe and Peter Pepper. [http://www.falklandshistory.org/gettingitright.pdf Getting it right: The real history of the Falklands/Malvinas.] May 2008.

{{Navboxes
|list =
{{Falkland Islands topics}}
{{History of South America}}
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of The Falkland Islands}}
[[Category:History of the Falkland Islands| ]]
[[Category:British colonization of the Americas]]
[[Category:French colonization of the Americas]]
[[Category:Spanish colonization of the Americas]]

{{Link GA|no}}

[[de:Geschichte der Falklandinseln]]
[[es:Historia de las islas Malvinas]]
[[fr:Histoire des îles Malouines]]
[[no:Falklandsøyenes historie]]</text>
      <sha1>0zxv3qc0jvtjnxkstqgyi6ulqlqq31h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
