<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Papua New Guinea</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23401</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520482666</id>
      <parentid>514119269</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T20:30:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[io:Historio di Papua-Nova-Guinea]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22660">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{Refimprove|date=February 2007}}
{{History of Papua New Guinea}}
The '''[[prehistory]] of [[Papua New Guinea]]''' can be traced back to about 60,000 years ago when people first migrated towards the [[Australia (continent)|Australian continent]]. The written history began when [[Europe]]an navigators first sighted [[New Guinea]] in the early part of the 16th century.

==Archaeology==
Archeological evidence indicates that humans arrived on New Guinea perhaps 60,000 years ago, although this is under debate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.anthro.utah.edu/PDFs/Papers/JAS%3DOC%26A.pdf|title=Dating the colonization of Sahul (Pleistocene Australia–New Guinea): a review of recent research|author=J.F. O’Connella, J. Allen|journal=Journal of Archaeological Science|volume=31 (2004)|pages=835–853|date=9 November 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Peopling of Sahul: mtDNA Variation in Aboriginal Australian and Papua New Guinean Populations|author=Alan J. Redd1, Mark Stoneking|url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0002929707623349|journal=AJHG – The American Journal of Human Genetics|volume=65|issue=3|date=September 1999|pages=808–828|doi=10.1086/302533}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They came probably by sea from Southeast Asia during an Ice Age period when the sea was lower and distances between islands shorter. Although the first arrivals were hunters and gatherers, early evidence shows that people managed the forest environment to provide food. There also are indications of [[neolithic]] gardening having been practiced at [[Kuk (New Guinea)|Kuk]] at the same time that agriculture was developing in Mesopotamia and Egypt. Today's staples—sweet potatoes and pigs—were later arrivals, but shellfish and fish have long been mainstays of coastal dwellers' diets. Recent archaeological research suggests that 50,000 years ago, people may have occupied sites in the highlands at altitudes of up to 2000 metres, rather than being restricted to warmer coastal areas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2010/09/30/us-australia-png-humans-idUSTRE68T4X620100930
|publisher=Reuters
|date=30 September 2010
|accessdate=2011-06-21 
|title=Early humans lived in PNG highlands 50,000 years ago
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==European contact==
When Europeans first arrived, inhabitants of New Guinea and nearby islands – while still relying on bone, wood, and stone tools – had a productive agricultural system. They traded along the coast, mainly in pottery, shell ornaments and foodstuffs, and in the interior, where forest products were exchanged for shells and other sea products.

The first Europeans to sight New Guinea were probably the [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] and [[Spanish people|Spanish]] navigators sailing in the South Pacific in the early part of the 16th century. In 1526–27, the Portuguese explorer [[Jorge de Menezes]] accidentally came upon the principal island and is credited with naming it '''Papua''', a [[Malay language|Malay]] word for the frizzled quality of [[Melanesia]]n hair. The term '''New Guinea''' was applied to the island in 1545 by a Spaniard, [[Yñigo Ortiz de Retez]], because of a resemblance between the islands' inhabitants and those found on the [[Guinea|African Guinea]] coast.

Although [[Europe]]an navigators visited the islands and explored their coastlines thereafter, little was known of the inhabitants by Europeans until the 1870s, when [[Russian people|Russian]] anthropologist [[Nicholai Miklukho-Maklai]] made a number of expeditions to New Guinea, spending several years living among native tribes, and described their way of life in a comprehensive treatise.

[[Image:British flag raised on new guinea annexed by queensland.jpg|thumb|British flag raised by Queensland 1883]]

==Territory of Papua==
{{main| Territory of Papua}}

In 1883, the [[Queensland|Colony of Queensland]] purported to annex the southern half of eastern New Guinea. On 6 November 1884, a British protectorate was proclaimed over the southern coast of New Guinea and its adjacent islands. The protectorate, called '''British New Guinea''', was annexed outright on 4 September 1888. The possession was placed under the authority of the Commonwealth of Australia in 1902. Following the passage of the [[Papua Act, 1905]], British New Guinea became the '''Territory of Papua''', and formal Australian administration began in 1906, although Papua remained ''de jure'' a British possession until the independence of Papua New Guinea in 1975. Papua was administered under the ''Papua Act'' until it was invaded by the [[Empire of Japan]] in 1941, and civil administration suspended. During the [[Pacific War]], Papua was governed by an Australian military administration from Port Moresby, where General [[Douglas MacArthur]] occasionally made his headquarters.

[[Image:German new guinea flag.svg|thumb|left|Flag under German control of New Guinea.]]

==German New Guinea==
{{main|German New Guinea}}

With Europe's growing desire for [[coconut oil]], [[Godeffroy's of Hamburg]], the largest trading firm in the Pacific, began trading for [[Copra plantations in New Guinea|copra in the New Guinea Islands]]. In 1884, the [[German Empire]] formally took possession of the northeast quarter of the island and put its administration in the hands of a chartered trading company formed for the purpose, the ''[[German New Guinea Company]]''. In the charter granted to this company by the German Imperial Government in May 1885, it was given the power to exercise sovereign rights over the territory and other &quot;unoccupied&quot; lands in the name of the government, and the ability to &quot;negotiate&quot; directly with the native inhabitants. Relationships with foreign powers were retained as the preserve of the German government. The ''Neu Guinea Kompanie'' paid for the local governmental institutions directly, in return for the concessions which had been awarded to it.

In 1899, the German imperial government assumed direct control of the territory, thereafter known as '''German New Guinea'''. In 1914, Australian troops occupied German New Guinea, and it remained under Australian military control through [[World War I]] until 1921.

==Territory of New Guinea==
{{main|Territory of New Guinea}}
The Commonwealth of Australia assumed a mandate from the [[League of Nations]] for governing the former German territory of New Guinea in 1920. It was administered under this mandate until the [[Japan]]ese invasion in December 1941 brought about the suspension of Australian civil administration. Much of the Territory of New Guinea, including the islands of [[Bougainville Island|Bougainville]] and [[New Britain]], was occupied by Japanese forces before being recaptured by Australian and American forces during the final months of the war (see [[New Guinea campaign]]).

==Exploration of Mandated Territory of New Guinea==
===Akmana Expedition 1929–1930===

‘The exploration of Papua–New Guinea has been a continuing process. Even today [April 1971] new groups of people occasionally are still contacted. Not until recent years has New Guinea’s exploration been planned; much of it has been the work of miners, labour recruiters, missionaries, adventurers, with different objects in mind. Many of these people have been doers, not recorders of facts, with the result that our knowledge of the territory’s exploration has not kept pace with the exploration itself.’&lt;ref&gt;Stuart Inder, Editor &quot;Pacific Islands Monthly&quot; April 1971 p. 40 Introduction&lt;/ref&gt;

An exception is the record of the Akmana Gold Prospecting Company’s Field Party which carried out two expeditions from September to December 1929 and from mid February to the end of June 1930.&lt;ref&gt;Ernest Alfred Shepherd, 'Akmana: A new name in the continuing story of New Guinea exploration' &quot;Pacific Islands Monthly&quot; April 1971 pp. 41–9&lt;/ref&gt; They journeyed on the &quot;Banyandah&quot;, a cruiser of {{convert|38|ft|m|0}} from Madang up the coast to the mouth of the Sepik River, travelling along that river to Marienberg and Moim, then along the Karosameri River to the Karrawaddi River and on to the Arrabundio River and Yemas, after which it was necessary to transport their stores and equipment by pinnace, canoe and ultimately on foot to their Mountain Base on the upper Arrabundio River.

During their first expedition the Akmana Field Party prospected the tributaries of the Arrabundio and then trekked across a spur of the Central Mountain Range to sample the Upper Karrawaddi River. Retracing their steps to the Arrabundio they then headed out across another spur of the Central Mountain Range to the Junction of the Yuat River with the Jimmi and Baiyer Rivers, again without finding gold in sufficient quantity. Returning to Madang at the end of December 1929, several of the party went back to Sydney to obtain instructions from the Akmana Gold Prospecting Company.

In mid February 1930 the second expedition quickly returned to their Mountain Base and on across the mountains to the junction of the Yuat with the Baiyer and Jimmi Rivers. They prospected south along the Baiyer River to its junction with the Maramuni and Tarua Rivers, where they established a palisaded forward camp naming the place ‘Akmana Junction.’ From this base they prospected along the Maramuni River and its tributaries, again without success. Finally they prospected the Tarua River south past the tributary which flows to Waipai, once more without success and on the advice of mining engineer Seale, it was decided there was nothing to justify further exploration. They had not progressed to any country on the southern watershed through which the early explorers and prospectors travelled to the Hagan Range and Wabag. The party returned to Madang, sailing for Sydney on 3 July 1930.

After leading the first expedition, Sam Freeman did not return and Reg Beazley became party leader of the second expedition, with Pontey Seale mining engineer, Bill MacGregor and Beazley prospectors and recruiters, and Ernie Shepherd in charge of transport and supplies, prospecting when opportunity arose. They had all served overseas during World War I with the AIF on the western front, in Egypt and the Levant and had previously been to New Guinea. In 1926 Freeman was near Marienberg with Ormildah drilling for oil; Shepherd was with Dr. Wade and R.J. Winters on their geological survey of an oil lease of {{convert|10000|sqmi|km2|sigfig=2}} in the Bogia and Nubio to Ramu region and up the Sepik River to Kubka {{convert|60|mi|km|sigfig=2}} above Ambunto. Beazley was drilling test sites for oil with Matahower in the lower Sepik and he and McGregor recruited labour on the Sepik and explored grass country to Wee Wak. Beazley also prospected the Arrabundio for gold and on his promising report to Freeman, Akmana Gold Prospecting Coy was floated in 1928.

The Akmana Gold Prospecting Field Party made contact with many peoples they called: grass country people, head hunters, pygmies, wig–men, Kanakas, Poomani. These contacts were often with the help of Drybow/Dribu, a leader and spokesman of the wig–men, a most intelligent man of goodwill, with a quiet authority that brought forth friendly cooperation. ‘We made a peaceful entry into this new country, establishing a reputation for fair trade and decent behaviour ... but gold was our interest and we had traced the rivers and tributaries as far as practicable where conditions and results justified the effort and found nothing worthwhile. In the many years since, there have been quite a few reports of prospecting parties in the area. But nothing of note has been reported: So we did not leave much behind, it seems.’&lt;ref&gt;Ernest Alfred Shepherd, “Akmana: A new name in the continuing story of New Guinea exploration” Pacific Islands Monthly April 1971 p. 49&lt;/ref&gt;

‘Members of the Akmana party donated wigs they had brought back to various museums. Two of them went to The [[Australian Museum]], Sydney (from Beazley and Shepherd). Current records at the Australian Museum show that Beazley’s wig, described as “a cap composed of human hair from the headwaters of the U–at River, Central Mountains, Mandated Territory of NG”, was lodged on 31 January 1930, presumably on his quick visit to Sydney after the first expedition. Shepherd presented another wig to Father Kirschbaum, who wanted to send it to Germany. The wigs at The Australian Museum were later confused with some brought out of the Highlands 10 years afterwards by Jim Taylor during his Hagen–Sepik patrol, and wrongly attributed to him when put on display. Seale presented two wigs to the National Museum Canberra in 1930.’&lt;ref&gt;Ernest Alfred Shepherd, “Akmana: A new name in the continuing story of New Guinea exploration” Pacific Islands Monthly April 1971 p.49&lt;/ref&gt;

==World War Two==
[[File:Australian troops at Milne Bay.jpg|thumb|200px|Australian troops at Milne Bay, Papua.The Australian garrison was the first to inflict defeat on the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] during [[World War II]] at the [[Battle of Milne Bay]] of Aug–Sep 1942.]]
[[File:Buna.jpg|thumb|200px|An Australian soldier, Private George &quot;Dick&quot; Whittington, is aided by Papuan orderly Raphael Oimbari, near Buna on 25 December 1942.]] 

{{Main|New Guinea Campaign}}

Shortly after the start of the [[Pacific War]], the island of New Guinea was invaded by the [[Japan]]ese. Most of [[West Papua (region)|West Papua]], at that time known as [[Dutch New Guinea]], was occupied, as were large parts of the [[Territory of New Guinea]] (the former [[German New Guinea]], which was also under Australian rule after [[World War I]]), but Papua was protected to a large extent by its southern location and the near-impassable [[Owen Stanley Ranges]] to the north.

The [[New Guinea campaign]] opened with the battles for New Britain and New Ireland in the [[Territory of New Guinea]] in 1942. [[Rabaul]], the capital of the Territory was [[Battle of Rabaul (1942)|overwhelmed on 22–23 January]] and was established as a major Japanese base from whence they landed on mainland New Guinea and advanced towards Port Moresby and Australia.&lt;ref&gt;http://ajrp.awm.gov.au/ajrp/remember.nsf/Web-Printer/C6FD73CC5C579789CA256AC000135979?OpenDocument&lt;/ref&gt; Having had their initial effort to capture Port Moresby by a seaborne invasion disrupted by the [[U.S. Navy]] in the [[Battle of the Coral Sea]], the Japanese attempted a landward invasion from the north via the [[Kokoda Trail]]. From July 1942, a few Australian reserve battalions, many of them very young and untrained, fought a stubborn rearguard action against a Japanese advance along the [[Kokoda Track]], towards Port Moresby, over the rugged Owen Stanley Ranges.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.awm.gov.au/units/event_291.asp&lt;/ref&gt; Local Papuans, called [[Fuzzy Wuzzy Angels]] by the Australians, assisted and escorted injured Australian troops down the Kokoda trail. The militia, worn out and severely depleted by casualties, were relieved in late August by regular troops from the Second Australian Imperial Force, returning from action in the [[Mediterranean theater]]. 

The Japanese were driven back. The bitter [[Battle of Buna-Gona]] followed in which Australian and United States forces attacked the main Japanese beachheads in New Guinea, at Buna, Sanananda and Gona. Facing tropical disease, difficult terrain and well constructed Japanese defences, the allies only secured victory with heavy casualties.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.awm.gov.au/units/event_340.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

In early September 1942 Japanese marines attacked a strategic [[Royal Australian Air Force]] base at Milne Bay, near the eastern tip of Papua. They were beaten back by the Australian Army, and the [[Battle of Milne Bay]] is remembered as the first outright defeat on Japanese land forces during World War II.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.awm.gov.au/units/event_345.asp&lt;/ref&gt; The offensives in Papua and New Guinea of 1943–44 were the single largest series of connected operations ever mounted by the Australian armed forces.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.awm.gov.au/wartime/23/new-guinea-offensive/&lt;/ref&gt; The Supreme Commander of operations was the United States General [[Douglas Macarthur]], with Australian General [[Thomas Blamey]] taking a direct role in planning and operations being  essentially directed by staff at New Guinea Force headquarters in Port Moresby.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.awm.gov.au/wartime/23/new-guinea-offensive/&lt;/ref&gt; Bitter fighting continued in New Guinea between the largely Australian force and the Japanese [[Eighteenth Army (Japan)|18th Army]] based in New Guinea until the [[Japanese surrender]] in 1945.

The New Guinea campaign was a major campaign of the Pacific War. In all, some 200,000 Japanese soldiers, sailors and airmen died during the campaign against approximately 7,000 Australian and 7,000 American service personnel.&lt;ref&gt;http://ajrp.awm.gov.au/ajrp/remember.nsf/Web-Printer/58EBD6D993E15CE8CA256D05002671FD?OpenDocument&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Territory of Papua and New Guinea==
Following the surrender of the Japanese in 1945, civil administration of Papua as well as New Guinea was restored, and under the [[Papua New Guinea Provisional Administration Act]], (1945–46), Papua and New Guinea were combined in an administrative union.

The [[Papua and New Guinea Act 1949]] formally approved the placing of New Guinea under the [[United Nations Trusteeship Council|international trusteeship system]] and confirmed the administrative union under the title of '''The Territory of Papua and New Guinea'''. The act provided for a Legislative Council (established in 1951), a judicial organization, a public service, and a system of local government. A [[House of Assembly]] replaced the Legislative Council in 1963, and the first House of Assembly opened on 8 June 1964. In 1972, the name of the territory was changed to '''Papua New Guinea'''.
Australia's change of policy towards Papua New Guinea largely commenced with the invitation from the Australian Government to the World Bank to send a mission to the Territory to advise on measures to be taken towards its economic development and political preparation.  The mission's report, The Economic Development of the Territory of Papua New Guinea, published in 1964, set out the framework upon which much of later economic policy, up to and beyond independence, proceeded.

==Independence==
Elections in 1972 resulted in the formation of a ministry headed by Chief Minister [[Michael Somare]], who pledged to lead the country to self-government and then to independence. Papua New Guinea became self-governing on 1 December 1973 and achieved independence on 16 September 1975. The 1977 national elections confirmed Michael Somare as Prime Minister at the head of a coalition led by the [[Pangu Party]]. However, his government lost a [[vote of confidence]] in 1980 and was replaced by a new cabinet headed by [[Sir Julius Chan]] as prime minister. The 1982 elections increased Pangu's plurality, and parliament again chose Somare as prime minister. In November 1985, the Somare government lost another vote of no confidence, and the parliamentary majority elected [[Paias Wingti]], at the head of a five-party coalition, as prime minister. A coalition, headed by Wingti, was victorious in very close elections in July 1987. In July 1988, a no-confidence vote toppled Wingti and brought to power [[Rabbie Namaliu]], who a few weeks earlier had replaced Somare as leader of the Pangu Party.

Such reversals of fortune and a revolving-door succession of prime ministers continue to characterize Papua New Guinea's national politics. A plethora of political parties, coalition governments, shifting party loyalties and motions of no confidence in the leadership all lend an air of instability to political proceedings.

Under legislation intended to enhance stability, new governments remain immune from no-confidence votes for the first 18 months of their incumbency.

A nine-year [[secession]]ist revolt on the island of [[Bougainville Island|Bougainville]] claimed some 20,000 lives. The rebellion began in early 1989, active hostilities ended with a truce in October 1997 and a permanent ceasefire was signed in April 1998. A peace agreement between the Government and ex-combatants was signed in August 2001. A regional peace-monitoring force and a [[UN]] observer mission monitors the government and provincial leaders who have established an interim administration and are working toward complete surrender of weapons, the election of a provincial government and an eventual referendum on independence.

Although close relations have been maintained since peaceful independence and Australia remains the largest bilateral aid donor to Papua New Guinea, relations with Australia have recently shown signs of strain.  While on a state visit in March 2005, Prime Minister Somare was asked to submit to a security check and remove his shoes upon arriving at the airport in [[Brisbane]].  Despite demands from the PNG government that Australia apologize, the latter refused.  Additionally, problems have arisen with regard to Australia's latest aid package for the country.  Valued at [[Australian dollar|A$]]760 million, the program was to tackle crime and corruption in PNG by sending 200 Australian police to Port Moresby and installing 40 Australian officials within the national bureaucracy.  However, after the first detachment of police arrived, Papua New Guinea's high court ruled that the arrangement was unconstitutional, and the police returned home.  A new arrangement, by which only 30 officers will serve as a training force for the local force has been described by the Australian foreign minister as &quot;second-best&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.economist.com/displayStory.cfm?Story_ID=S'(X%20.Q!_*!%40!-%0A |title=Thirty Years On |work=[[The Economist]] |date=25 August 2005}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==&lt;!-- ArchaeolOceania37:92 --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2797.htm U.S. State Department Background Note: Papua New Guinea]
* [http://www.historyofnations.net/oceania/papuanewguinea.html History of Papua New Guinea]

{{History of Oceania}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Papua New Guinea}}
[[Category:History of Papua New Guinea| ]]

[[ca:Història de Papua Nova Guinea]]
[[es:Historia de Papúa Nueva Guinea]]
[[fr:Histoire de la Papouasie-Nouvelle-Guinée]]
[[io:Historio di Papua-Nova-Guinea]]
[[it:Storia di Papua Nuova Guinea]]
[[tpi:Histori long Papua Niugini]]
[[pt:História de Papua-Nova Guiné]]
[[ru:История Папуа — Новой Гвинеи]]</text>
      <sha1>3dvkx28lzibvk7spf2mzbhj7vwss7pv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
