<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Historical revisionism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13293</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520834821</id>
      <parentid>518846151</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T01:34:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Poyani</username>
        <id>4283254</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Vietnam War */  NPOV</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35172">{{for|the denial and distortion of well-established historical facts|Historical revisionism (negationism)}}

In [[historiography]], '''historical revisionism''' is the reinterpretation of orthodox views on evidence, motivations, and decision-making processes surrounding a historical event.  Though the word ''revisionism'' is sometimes used in a negative way, constant revision of history is part of the normal scholarly process of writing [[history]].

==Scholarly process==
[[Pulitzer Prize]] winning [[historian]] [[James M. McPherson|James McPherson]], writing for the [[American Historical Association]], described the importance of revisionism:

{{quote|The 14,000 members of this Association, however, know that revision is the lifeblood of historical scholarship. History is a continuing dialogue between the present and the past. Interpretations of the past are subject to change in response to new evidence, new questions asked of the evidence, new perspectives gained by the passage of time. There is no single, eternal, and immutable &quot;truth&quot; about past events and their meaning. The unending quest of historians for understanding the past—that is, &quot;revisionism&quot;—is what makes history vital and meaningful. Without revisionism, we might be stuck with the images of [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]] after the [[American Civil War]] that were conveyed by [[D. W. Griffith]]'s ''[[The Birth of a Nation]]'' and [[Claude Bowers]]'s ''The Tragic Era''. Were the [[Gilded Age]] entrepreneurs &quot;[[Captain of industry|Captains of Industry]]&quot; or &quot;[[Robber baron (industrialist)|Robber Barons]]&quot;? Without revisionist historians who have done research in new sources and asked new and nuanced questions, we would remain mired in one or another of these stereotypes. [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] decisions often reflect a &quot;revisionist&quot; interpretation of history as well as of the Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historians.org/perspectives/issues/2003/0309/0309pre1.cfm Revisionist Historians&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Those historians who work within the existing establishment and who have a body of existing work from which they claim authority, often have the most to gain by maintaining the ''status quo''. This can be called an accepted [[paradigm]], which in some circles or societies takes the form of a denunciative stance towards revisionism of any kind. However, the historian and philosopher of science, [[Thomas Kuhn]], pointed out that in contrast to the sciences, in which there tends to be (except in times of [[paradigm shift]]) a single reigning paradigm, the social sciences are characterized by a &quot;tradition of claims, counterclaims, and debates over fundamentals.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last= Kuhn | first= Thomas N. |authorlink= Thomas Kuhn |editor1-last= Lakatos |editor1-first= Imre |editor2-last= Musgrave |editor2-first= Alan |editor1-link= Imre Lakatos |editor2-link= Alan Musgrave |title= Criticism and the Growth of Knowledge |edition= second |origyear= 1970 |year= 1972 |publisher= Cambridge University Press |location= Cambridge |isbn= 0-521-09623-5 |page= 6 |chapter= Logic of Discovery or Psychology of Research }}&lt;/ref&gt; Historian David Williams describes the resistance to the advocates of a more inclusive United States history that would include the roles of women, African Americans, and the labor movement:

{{quote|These and other scholarly voices called for a more comprehensive treatment of American history, stressing that the mass of Americans, not simply the power elites, made history. Yet it was mainly white males of the power elite who had the means to attend college, become professional historians, and shape a view of history that served their own class, race, and gender interests at the expense of those not so fortunate&amp;nbsp;— and quite literally to paper over aspects of history they found uncomfortable. “One is astonished in the study of history,” wrote [[W. E. B. Du Bois|Du Bois]] in 1935, “at the recurrence of the idea that evil must be forgotten, distorted, skimmed over. ... The difficulty, of course, with this philosophy is that history loses its value as an incentive and an example; it paints perfect men and noble nations, but it does not tell the truth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Williams, David. ''A People’s History of the Civil War: Struggles for the Meaning of Freedom.''(2005) pp.10–11&lt;/ref&gt;}}

After World War II “a new and more broadly based generation of scholars”, as the result of the [[G.I. Bill]], the nationwide expansion of state universities and community colleges, and the [[feminist movement]], [[civil rights movement]], and [[American Indian Movement]], expanded the scope of American history.&lt;ref&gt;Williams p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;

If there were a universally accepted view of history that never changed, there would be no need to research it further. Many historians who write revisionist exposés are motivated by a genuine desire to educate and to correct history. Many great discoveries have come as a result of the research of men and women who have been curious enough to revisit certain historical events and explore them again in depth from a new perspective. Historian [[Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr.]], in contrasting the United States with the [[Soviet Union]] during the [[Cold War]], wrote:

{{quote|But others, especially in the United States ... represent what American historians call “revisionism”&amp;nbsp;— that is a readiness to challenge official explanations. No one should be surprised by this phenomenon. Every war in American history has been followed in due course by skeptical reassessments of supposedly sacred assumptions ... for revisionism is an essential part of the process by which history, through the posing of new problems and the investigation of new possibilities, enlarges its perspectives and enriches its insights.&lt;ref&gt;Schlesinger, Arthur M. Jr. ''The Cycles of American History.''(1986) p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Revisionist historians contest the mainstream or traditional view of historical events, they raise views at odds with traditionalists, which must be freshly judged. Revisionist history is often practiced by those who are in the minority, such as feminist historians, ethnic minority historians, those working outside of mainstream academia in smaller and less known universities, or the youngest scholars, essentially historians who have the most to gain and the least to lose in challenging the status quo. In the friction between the mainstream of accepted beliefs and the new perspectives of historical revisionism, received historical ideas are either changed, solidified, or clarified. If over a period of time the revisionist ideas become the new establishment ''status quo'' a [[paradigm shift]] is said to have occurred. Historian [[Forrest McDonald]] is often critical of the turn that revisionism has taken but he nevertheless admits that the turmoil of the 1960s in the United States changed the way history was written. He wrote:

{{quote|The result, as far as the study of history was concerned, was an awakened interest in subjects that historians had previously slighted. Indian history, black history, women’s history, family history, and a host of specializations arose. These expanded horizons enriched our understanding of the American past, but they also resulted in works of special pleading, trivialization, and downright falsification.&lt;ref&gt;McDonald, Forest. ''Recovering the Past: A Historian’s Memoir.'' (2004) p. 114&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Historians, like all people, are inexorably influenced by the ''[[zeitgeist]]'' (the spirit of the times). Historian [[C. Vann Woodward]] sees this as a positive influence. Speaking of the changes that occurred after the end of World War II, he wrote:

{{quote|These events have come with a concentration and violence for which the term &quot;revolution&quot; is usually reserved. It is a revolution, or perhaps a set of revolutions for which we have not yet found a name. My thesis is that these developments will and should raise new questions about the past and affect our reading of large areas of history, and my belief is that future revisions may be extensive enough to justify calling the coming age of historiography an age of reinterpretation. The first illustration [the absence from United States’ history of external threats due to its geographic isolation] happens to come mainly from American history, but this should not obscure the broader scope of the revolution, which has no national limitations.&lt;ref&gt;Woodward, C. Vann. ''The Future of the Past.'' (1989). p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Developments in other academic areas, and cultural and political fashions, all help to shape the currently accepted model and outlines of history (the accepted [[historiography|historiographical]] paradigm). For example, philosopher [[Karl Popper]] echoed Woodward’s sentiments regarding revisionism when he noted that “each generation has its own troubles and problems, and therefore its own interests and its own point of view” and:

{{quote|It follows that each generation has a right to look upon and re-interpret history in its own way. ... After all, we study history because we are interested in it, and perhaps because we wish to learn something about our problems. But history can serve neither of these two purpose if, under the influence of an inapplicable idea of objectivity, we hesitate to present historical problems from our point of view. And we should not think that our point of view, if consciously and critically applied to the problem, will be inferior to that of a writer who naively believes ... that he has reached a level of objectivity permitting him to present “the events of the past as they actually did happen.”&lt;ref&gt;Novick, Peter. ''That Noble Dream: The Objectivity Question and the American Historical profession. '' (1988) p. 395&lt;/ref&gt;}}

As time passes and these influences change so do most historians views on the explanation of historical events. The old consensus may no longer be considered by most historians to explain how and why certain events in the past occurred, and so the accepted model is revised to fit in with the current agreed-upon version of events. For example, historian John Hope Franklin in 1986 described four specific stages in the historiography of African American that were based on different consensus models.&lt;ref&gt;[African-American History: Origins, Development, and Current State of the Field | Joe W. Trotter | [[Organization of American Historians]] Magazine of History&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Revisionism vs. denial===
[[Deborah Lipstadt]] (1993), [[Michael Shermer]], and Alex Grobman (2000), authors of critical studies of [[Holocaust denial]], make a distinction between revisionism and [[Denialism|denial]]. Revisionism, in their view, entails a refinement of existing knowledge about a historical event, not a denial of the event itself, a refinement that comes through the examination of new empirical evidence or a reexamination or reinterpretation of existing evidence. Legitimate historical revisionism acknowledges a 'certain body of irrefutable evidence' or a 'convergence of evidence' that suggest that an event&amp;nbsp;— like the black plague, American slavery, or the Holocaust&amp;nbsp;— did occur.&lt;ref&gt;(Lipstadt 1993:21; Shermer &amp; Grobman 200:34&lt;/ref&gt; Denial, on the other hand, rejects the entire foundation of historical evidence....&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ronald J. Berger. ''Fathoming the Holocaust: A Social Problems Approach'', Aldine Transaction, 2002, ISBN 0-202-30670-4, p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influences==
Some of the influences on historians, which may change over time are:

[[File:Dachau_execution_coalyard_1945-04-29.jpg|thumb|300px|While U.S. newspapers reported the liberation of Dachau prisoners by American soldiers, they neglected to mention the execution of German Nazi S.S. soldiers who surrendered the camp. It would be many years later until the [[Dachau massacre]] was widely known by historians.]]

*'''Access to new data:''' Much historical data has been lost. Even [[archives]] have to make decisions based on space and interest on what original material to obtain or keep. At times documents are discovered or publicized that give new views of well established events. Archived material may be sealed by Governments for many years, either to hide political scandals, or to protect information vital for national security. When these archives are opened, they can alter the historical perspective on an event. For example with the released of the [[Ultra (cryptography)|ULTRA]] archives in the 1970s under the British 30 years rule, a lot of the Allied high command tactical decision making process was re-evaluated, particularly the [[Battle of the Atlantic]]. &lt;!-- Before the release of the ULTRA archives, there was much debate over whether Field Marshal [[Bernard Montgomery]] could have known that [[Arnhem]] was heavily garrisoned. With the release of the archives, which indicated that they were, the balance of the evidence swung in the direction of his detractors.--&gt; The release of the ULTRA archives also forced a re-evaluation of the [[History of computing hardware|history of the electronic computer]].&lt;ref&gt;In 1972, before the release of official documents about ULTRA, [[Herman Goldstine]] wrote in ''The Computer from Pascal to von Neuman'' page 321 that: ''&quot;Britain had such vitality that it could immediately after the war embark on so many well-conceived and well-executed projects in the computer field&quot;''. In 1976 after the archive were opened [[Brian Randell]] wrote in ''The COLOSSUS'' on page 87 that: ''&quot;the COLOSSUS project was an important source of this vitality, one that has been largely unappreciated, as has the significance of its places in the chronology of the invention of the digital computer&quot;''.&lt;/ref&gt; When American soldiers entered the [[Dachau concentration camp]] on April 29, 1945 to obtain the surrender of the retreating Nazis, the [[Dachau massacre|massacre of German S.S. guards]] was not reported by American newspaper reporters who were embedded with the American troops. When the &quot;I.G. Report&quot; of the Army's &quot;Investigation of Alleged Mistreatment of German Guards at Dachau&quot; was released in 1991, it became obvious that the massacre had actually occurred and had been suppressed by General Patton.&lt;ref name=Humanitas&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.humanitas-international.org/archive/dachau-liberation/|title=Dachau Concentration Camp Liberation (A Documentary)|author=R.H. Perez|publisher=Humanitas International|year=2002|accessdate=January 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Developments in other fields of science:''' [[DNA]] analysis has had an impact in various areas of history either confirming established historical theories or presenting new evidence that undermines the current established historical explanation. Professor [[Andrew Sherratt]], a British prehistorian, was responsible for introducing the work of anthropological writings on the consumption of currently legal and illegal drugs and how to use these papers to explain certain aspects of prehistoric societies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/people/obituaries/article349471.ece Obituary of Andrew Sherratt] in [[The Independent]] 6 March 2006&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carbon dating]], the examination of [[ice core]]s and [[tree rings]], [[palynology]], [[Scanning electron microscope|SEM analysis]] of early metal samples, and measuring [[oxygen isotopes]] in bones, have all provided new data in the last few decades with which to argue new hypotheses. Extracting [[ancient DNA]] allows scientists to argue whether or not humans are partly descended from [[Neanderthals]].
* '''Language:''' For example as more sources in other languages become available historians may review their theories in light of the new sources. The revision of the meaning of the [[#The &quot;Dark Ages&quot;|Dark Ages]] are an example of this.
* '''Nationalism:''' For example when reading schoolbook history in Europe, it is possible to read about an event from completely different perspectives. In the [[Battle of Waterloo]] most British, French, Dutch and German schoolbooks slant the battle to emphasise the importance of the contribution of their nations. Sometimes the name of an event is used to convey political or a national perspective. For example the same conflict between two English speaking countries is known by two different names, for example, the &quot;[[American War of Independence]]&quot; and the &quot;[[American Revolutionary War]]&quot;. As perceptions of nationalism change so do those areas of history that are driven by such ideas.
* '''Culture:''' For example as regionalism has become more prominent in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] some historians have been suggesting that the [[English Civil War]] is too Anglo-centric and that to understand the war, events that had previously been dismissed as on the periphery should be given greater prominence; to emphasise this, revisionist historians have suggested that the English Civil War becomes just one of a number of interlocking conflicts known as [[Wars of the Three Kingdoms]].
* '''Ideology:''' For example during the 1940s it became fashionable to see the English Civil War from a Marxist school of thought. In the words of [[Christopher Hill (historian)|Christopher Hill]], &quot;the Civil War was a class war.&quot; In the post [[World War II]] years the influence of Marxist interpretation waned in British academia and by the 1970s this view came under attack by a new school of revisionists and it has been largely overturned as a major mainstream explanation of the middle 17th century conflict in [[Kingdom of England|England]], [[Kingdom of Scotland|Scotland]], and [[Kingdom of Ireland|Ireland]].
*'''Historical causation:''' Issues of [[causality|causation]] in history are often revised with new research: for example by the middle of the twentieth century the status quo was to see the [[French Revolution]] as the result of the triumphant rise of a new [[middle class]]. Research in the 1960s prompted by revisionist historians like [[Alfred Cobban]] and [[Francois Furet]] revealed the social situation as much more complex and the question of what caused the Revolution is now a closely debated one.

==Examples==
These are examples of historical revisionist ideas.

===The &quot;Dark Ages&quot;===
As non-[[Latin]] texts such as [[Welsh language|Welsh]], [[Gaelic languages|Gaelic]] and the [[Old Norse|Norse]] [[saga]]s have been analysed and added to the canon of knowledge about the period and a lot more [[archaeological]] evidence has come to light, the period traditionally known as the [[Dark Ages (historiography)|Dark Ages]] has narrowed to the point where many historians no longer believe that such a term is useful. Moreover, the term &quot;dark&quot; implies less of a void of culture and law, but more a lack of many [[source text]]s in mainland [[Europe]]. Many modern scholars who study the era tend to avoid the term altogether for its [[negative connotation]]s, finding it misleading and inaccurate for any part of the Middle Ages.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Snyder|first=Christopher A.|author-link=Christopher Snyder|year=1998|contribution=|contribution-url=|title=An Age of Tyrants: Britain and the Britons A.D. 400&amp;ndash;600|publisher=Pennsylvania State University Press|publication-date=1998|publication-place=University Park|pages=xiii&amp;ndash;xiv|isbn=0-271-01780-5|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}, for example. This work contains over 100 pages of footnoted citations to source material and bibliographic references (pp. 263&amp;ndash;387). In explaining his approach to writing the work, he refers to the &quot;so-called Dark Ages&quot;, noting that &quot;Historians and archaeologists have never liked the label Dark Ages ... there are numerous indicators that these centuries were neither &quot;dark&quot; nor &quot;barbarous&quot; in comparison with other eras.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dmas&gt;[[William Chester Jordan|Jordan, Chester William]] (2004). ''[[Dictionary of the Middle Ages]]'', Supplement 1. Verdun, Kathleen, &quot;Medievalism&quot; pp. 389–397. Sections 'Victorian Medievalism', 'Nineteenth-Century Europe', 'Medievalism in America 1500–1900', 'The 20th Century'. Same volume, [[Paul Freedman|Freedman, Paul]], &quot;Medieval Studies&quot;, pp. 383–389.&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Feudalism&quot;===
The concept of [[feudalism]] has been questioned. Revisionist scholars led by historian [[Elizabeth A. R. Brown]] have [[Feudalism#Feudalism revisionism|rejected the term]].

===Agincourt===
For centuries, historians thought the [[Battle of Agincourt]] was an engagement in which the English army, though overwhelmingly outnumbered four to one by the [[France|French]] army, pulled off a stunning victory&amp;mdash;a version especially popularised by [[Shakespeare]]'s play [[Henry V (play)|Henry V]]. However, recent research by Professor [[Anne Curry]] using the original enrollment records, has brought into question this interpretation. Though her research is not finished,&lt;ref&gt;Page 288. Matthew Strickland ''The Great Warbow''. Pub Sutton, 2005, ISBN 0-7509-3167-1&lt;/ref&gt; she has published her initial findings,&lt;ref&gt;[[Anne Curry]]. ''Agincourt: A New History'', Pub Tempus, 2005, ISBN 0-7524-2828-4&lt;/ref&gt; that the French only outnumbered the English and Welsh 12,000 to 8,000. If true, the numbers may have been exaggerated for patriotic reasons by the English.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Brooks ''[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/printFriendly/0,,1-523-1632547,00.html Henry V’s payroll cuts Agincourt myth down to size]'' May 29, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

===Alchemy===
Science historians are taking a new look at [[alchemy]]. Traditionally there was little room in the history of science for alchemy, which famously tried to convert [[lead]] into [[gold]] ([[Lead(II) oxide|lead oxide]] has a yellow colour), and it has been seen as closer to magic or mysticism than science. However there has been a revival of scholarship on the field and historians are finding reasons to give at least some alchemy a new interpretation. Alchemists, some historians are now saying, contributed to the emergence of modern chemistry as a science.&lt;ref&gt;John Noble Wilford, [http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/01/science/01alch.html &quot;Transforming the Alchemists&quot;], [[New York Times]], August 1, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===New World discovery===
In recounting the [[European colonization of the Americas]], some history books of the past paid little attention to the [[indigenous peoples of the Americas]], usually mentioning them only in passing and making no attempt to understand the events from their point of view. This was reflected in the description of [[Christopher Columbus]] having discovered America. The portrayal of these events has since been revised, and much present scholarship examines the impact of European exploration and colonization on indigenous peoples (''see'' [[Postcolonialism]]).

===French attack formations in the Napoleonic wars===
The military historian James R. Arnold argues that:
{{quote|The writings of Sir [[Charles Oman]] and Sir [[John Fortescue (military historian)|John Fortescue]] dominated subsequent English-language Napoleonic history. Their views [that the French infantry used [[heavy column]]s to attack lines of infantry] became very much the [[received wisdom]]. ... By 1998 a new paradigm seemed to have set in with the publication of two books devoted to Napoleonic battle tactics. Both claimed that the French fought in line at [[Battle of Maida|Maida]] and both fully explored French tactical variety. The 2002 publication of ''The Battle of Maida 1806: Fifteen Minutes of Glory'', appeared to have brought the issue of column versus line to a satisfactory conclusion: &quot;The contemporary sources are...the best evidence and their conclusion is clear: General Compère's brigade formed into line to attack Kempt's Light Battalion.&quot; The decisive action at Maida took place in less than fifteen minutes. It had taken 72 years to rectify a great historian's error about what transpired during those minutes.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, James R. &quot;''[http://www.napoleon-series.org/military/organization/maida/c_maida.html A Reappraisal of Column Versus Line in the Peninsular War Oman and Historiography]''&quot;, [[The Napoleon Series]], August 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James R. Arnold, &quot;A Reappraisal of Column Versus Line in the Napoleonic Wars&quot; [[Journal of the Society for Army Historical Research]] LX no. 244 (Winter 1982): pp. 196–208.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Military leadership during the First World War===
The military leadership of the [[British Army]] during the [[First World War]] was frequently condemned as poor by historians and politicians for decades after the war ended. Common charges were that the generals commanding the army were blind to the realities of [[trench warfare]], ignorant of the conditions of their men and were unable to learn from their mistakes, thus causing enormous numbers of casualties ('[[lions led by donkeys]]').&lt;ref&gt;Lions Led By Donkeys
*Thompson, P.A. ''[http://www.churchillbooks.com/detail.cfm?item_num=38200&amp;is_mil_book=1 Lions Led By Donkeys: Showing How Victory In The Great War Was Achieved By Those Who Made the Fewest Mistakes] T. Werner Laurie, Ltd. 1st English Edition.1927
*Bournes, John. [http://www.firstworldwar.bham.ac.uk/donkey/index.htm Lions Led By Donkeys], Centre for First World War Studies, [[University of Birmingham]].&lt;/ref&gt; However, during the 1960s historians such as [[John Terraine]] began to challenge this interpretation. In recent years as new documents have come forth and the distance of time has allowed for more objective analysis, historians such as [[Gary D. Sheffield]] and [[Richard Holmes (military historian)|Richard Holmes]] observe that the military leadership of the British Army on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] had to cope with many problems that they could not control such as a lack of adequate military [[communication]]s, which was not known before. Furthermore, military leadership improved throughout the war culminating in the [[Hundred Days Offensive]] advance to victory in 1918. Some historians, even revisionists, still criticise the British High Command severely, but they are less inclined to portray the war in a simplistic manner with brave troops being led by foolish officers.

There has been a similar movement regarding the French Army during the war with contributions by historians such as [[Anthony Clayton]]. Revisionists are far more likely to view commanders such as French General [[Ferdinand Foch]], British General [[Douglas Haig]] and other figures, such as American General Pershing, in a sympathetic light.

===Reconstruction in U.S.===
Revisionist historians of [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction after the U.S. Civil War]] rejected the dominant [[Dunning School]] that found the blacks were tools of evil [[Carpetbaggers]], and instead stressed economic greed on the part of northern businessmen.&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Weisberger, &quot;The Dark and Bloody Ground of Reconstruction Historiography,&quot; ''The Journal of Southern History,'' Vol. 25, No. 4 (Nov., 1959), pp. 427–447 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2954450 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, in recent years a &quot;[[neoabolitionist]]&quot; revisionism has become standard, that uses the moral standards of the 19th century abolitionists to criticize racial policies. &quot;Foner's book represents the mature and settled Revisionist perspective,&quot; historian Michael Perman has concluded regarding [[Eric Foner]]'s ''Reconstruction: America's Unfinished Revolution, 1863–1877'' (1988)&lt;ref&gt;Michael Perman, &quot;Review: Eric Foner's Reconstruction: A Finished Revolution,&quot; ''Reviews in American History,'' Vol. 17, No. 1 (Mar., 1989), pp. 73–78 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2703129 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

===German guilt in causing World War I===
In reaction to the orthodox interpretation enshrined in the [[Versailles Treaty]] (which declared that Germany was guilty of starting World War I), the self-described &quot;revisionist&quot; historians of the 1920s rejected the orthodox view and presented a complex causation in which several other countries were equally guilty. Intense debate continues among scholars, see [[Causes of World War I]].&lt;ref&gt;See Selig Adler, &quot;The War-Guilt Question and American Disillusionment, 1918–1928,&quot; ''Journal of Modern History,'' Vol. 23, No. 1 (Mar., 1951), pp. 1–28 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1871365 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Guilt for causing World War II===
The orthodox interpretation blamed Hitler and Nazi Germany, and Imperial Japan, for causing the war (see [[Causes of World War II]]). Revisionist historians of World War II, notably [[Charles A. Beard]], said the U.S. was partly to blame because it pressed the Japanese too hard in 1940–41 and rejected compromises.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Flagg Bemis, &quot;First Gun of a Revisionist Historiography for the Second World War,&quot; ''Journal of Modern History,'' Vol. 19, No. 1 (Mar., 1947), pp. 55–59 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1875652 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; British historian [[A. J. P. Taylor]] ignited a firestorm when he argued that Hitler was a rather ordinary diplomat and did not deliberately set out to cause a war.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon Martel, ed. ''The Origins of the Second World War Reconsidered: A.J.P. Taylor and the Historians.'' (2nd ed. 1999).&lt;/ref&gt;

The American conservative, [[Patrick Buchanan]],&lt;ref&gt;Patrick J. Buchanan: Churchill, Hitler and the Unnecessary War: How Britain Lost Its Empire and the West Lost the World&lt;/ref&gt; argued that the British-French guarantee to Poland in 1939 encouraged Poland not to seek a compromise over Danzig, though Britain and France were in no position to come to Poland's aid, and Hitler was offering the Poles an alliance in return. He argues that they thereby turned a minor border dispute into a catastrophic world conflict, and handed East Europe, including Poland, to Stalin.

===American Business and the &quot;Robber Barons&quot;===
The role of American business and the alleged [[Robber baron (industrialist)|&quot;robber barons&quot;]] began to be revised in the 1930s.  Termed &quot;business revisionism&quot; by [[Gabriel Kolko]], historians such as [[Allan Nevins]], and, later, [[Alfred D. Chandler]] emphasized the positive contributions of individuals who were previously pictured as villains.&lt;ref&gt;Kolko, Gabriel. &quot;The Premises of Business Revisionism&quot; in ''The Business History Review'', Vol. 33, No. 3 (Autumn, 1959), p. 334&lt;/ref&gt; Peter Novick writes, &quot;The argument that whatever the moral delinquencies of the robber barons, these were far outweighed by their decisive contributions to American military {and industrial} prowess, was frequently invoked by Allan Nevins.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Novick,Peter. ''That Noble Dream: The Objectivity Question and the American Historical profession.'' (1988) p. 342. Novick describes Nevins as &quot;the best known voice of what came to be called &quot;business history revisionism.&quot; (p. 343)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cold War===
In the [[Historiography of the Cold War]] a debate exists between historians advocating an &quot;orthodox&quot; and &quot;revisionist&quot; interpretation of [[Soviet history]] and other aspects of the [[cold war]] such as the [[Vietnam War]].

====Vietnam War====
''[[America in Vietnam]]'' by [[Guenter Lewy]] is an example of historical revisionism which substantially differs from the popular view of America's role in the [[Vietnam War]]. Lewy's work was the first of a body of work by other historians which form the revisionist school with respect to the behavior and role of the United States in the Vietnam War. Other reinterpretations which attempt to offer alternative explanations for American behavior include those by [[Norman Podhoretz]],&lt;ref name=&quot;tri&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| first = Ian
| last = Horwood
| authorlink =
| coauthors =
| year =
| month =
| title = Book review: Triumph Forsaken: The Vietnam War, 1954–1965
| journal = Institute of Historical Research
| volume =
| issue =
| pages =
| id =
| url = http://www.history.ac.uk/reviews/paper/horwood.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mark Moyar,&lt;ref&gt;''Triumph Forsaken: The Vietnam War, 1954&amp;ndash;1965'' (2006) ISBN 0-521-86911-0&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Michael Lind]].&lt;ref&gt;''Vietnam: The Necessary War'' (1999)&lt;/ref&gt; ''America in Vietnam'' attracted both criticism and support of Lewy for belonging to the &quot;revisionist&quot; school on Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;tri&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| first = Ian
| last = Horwood
| authorlink =
| coauthors =
| year =
| month =
| title = Book review: Triumph Forsaken: The Vietnam War, 1954–1965
| journal = Institute of Historical Research
| volume =
| issue =
| pages =
| id =
| url = http://www.history.ac.uk/reviews/paper/horwood.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;reverse&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| first = Robert A.
| last = Divine
| authorlink =
| coauthors =
| year = 1979
| month = September
| title = Review: Revisionism in Reverse
| journal = Reviews in American History
| volume = 7
| issue = 3
| pages = 433–438
| id =
| doi = 10.2307/2701181
| last2 = Lewy
| first2 = Guenter
| last3 = Millett
| first3 = Allan R.
| jstor=2701181
}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Lewy:&lt;blockquote&gt;It is the reasoned conclusion of this study... that the sense of guilt created by the Vietnam war in the minds of many Americans is not warranted and that the charges of ''officially, condoned'' illegal and grossly immoral conduct are without substance. Indeed, detailed examination of battlefield practices reveals that the loss of civilian life in Vietnam was less great than in World War II and Korea and that concern with minimizing the ravages of the war was strong. To measure and compare the devastation and loss of human life caused by different war will be objectionable to those who repudiate all resort to military force as an instrument of foreign policy and may be construed as callousness. Yet as long as wars do take place at all it remains a moral duty to seek to reduce the agony caused by war, and the fulfillment of this obligation should not be disdained.&lt;ref&gt;Guenter Lewy, ''America in Vietnam'', p. VII.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
*[[Afrocentrism]]
*[[Biblical criticism]]
* [[Black Legend]]
* [[Denialism]]
* [[Historical revisionism (negationism)]]
* [[The Inquisition myth]]
* [[New Historians]]&amp;nbsp;— An on-going historical revisionism debate dealing with the early period of the [[Arab-Israeli Conflict]].
* [[Pseudohistory]]
* [[Korean Air Lines Flight 007 alternate theories]]
* [[Selective omission]] - biaises to taboo some elements of a [[collective memory]] 
* [[Japanese textbook controversy]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Historical Revisionism}}
[[Category:Historical revisionism| ]]
[[Category:Historiography|Revisionism]]
[[Category:Theories of history]]

[[be:Гістарычны рэвізіянізм]]
[[ca:Revisionisme històric]]
[[da:Revisionisme (historie)]]
[[de:Geschichtsrevisionismus]]
[[es:Revisionismo histórico]]
[[gl:Revisionismo histórico]]
[[ko:역사수정주의]]
[[it:Revisionismo storiografico]]
[[nl:Historisch revisionisme]]
[[ja:歴史修正主義]]
[[no:Historisk revisjonisme]]
[[pt:Revisionismo histórico]]
[[ru:Исторический ревизионизм]]
[[sh:Historijski revizionizam]]
[[fi:Historiallinen revisionismi]]
[[sv:Historierevisionism]]
[[uk:Історичний ревізіонізм]]
[[zh:历史修正主义]]</text>
      <sha1>78w9tgyptyftl7onkk83utcsbklmiwp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
