<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Laos</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17753</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520248538</id>
      <parentid>520247174</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T11:10:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TYelliot</username>
        <id>13096125</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14498">{{History of Laos}}
The official '''History of Laos''' as introduced in government textbooks, is conventionally traced to the establishment of the kingdom of [[Lan Xang]] by [[Fa Ngum]] in 1353. This is a relatively conservative date to begin the history of the nation, providing a contrast to the course taken by [[Thailand|Thai]] historiography (which reaches back implausibly far into proto-history).  By the 14th century, when this &quot;official history&quot; begins, the speakers of early [[Tai languages|Lao-related languages]] had probably developed a reasonable base of population among the prior inhabitants of (what is now) Laos over the prior century or two. The borders of the modern state of Laos were established by the French colonial government in the late 19th and early 20th centuries. 

==Early history==
{{main|history of Laos to 1945}}
[[Image:Map-of-southeast-asia_1400_CE.png|thumb|left|180px| Southeast Asia c.1400 CE, showing [[Lan Xang]] kingdom in teal, Khmer Empire in red, [[Ayutthaya Kingdom|Ayutthaya]] Kingdom in violet, [[Sukhothai kingdom]] in orange, [[Champa]] in yellow, Kingdom of [[Lanna]] in purple, [[Dai Viet]] in blue.]]

The earliest Laos legal document (and the earliest sociological evidence about the existence of the Lao people) is known as &quot;the laws of [[Khun Borom]]&quot; (also spelled &quot;Khun Bulom&quot;), still preserved in manuscript form.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seasite.niu.edu/lao/laoliterature/Lao_traditional_literature/khun_borom.htm Traditional Lao Literature&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

This set of [[wikt:memoriter|memoriter]] laws is composed in a type of indigenous [[blank verse]], and reflects the state of proto-Lao society as early as the 9th century, possibly prior to their adoption of [[Theravada]] Buddhism, and prior to (or coeval with) their southward migration into the territory now comprising modern Laos (from North-Western Vietnam).

While some Lao people regard Borom/Bulom as a subject of myth only{{fact|date=February 2011}}, Western scholars regard him as an historical figure, albeit there is very little factually known about him aside from the fact of his bare existence and the description of a very primitive kingdom in his laws.

In general terms, these ancient laws describe an agrarian society in which life revolves around [[subsistence agriculture]] with domesticated water-buffaloes (the [[gayal]]). The strict punishments set down for stealing or killing a neighbor's elephant reflect that these were (evidently) an expensive and important possession of the time.

===Human settlement===
{{main|Khmuic peoples}}
Human settlement in the region is known to date back many centuries BC. The most famous evidence of the region's pre-history consists of the huge stone mortuary jars found on the north-central [[Xiangkhoang Plateau]], which have given the area the name [[Plain of Jars]]. Little is known about the society which created the jars, which date from the first century BC. 

The known history of the region follows from the [[Tai peoples|Tai]] migration. In the 13th century, [[Tai people]] constructed their first states, drawing together different tribal communities under rulers claiming quasi-divine authority and kingly status. 

The earlier inhabitation of the land by peoples such as the [[Mon people|Mon]] kingdom of [[Dvaravati]] and Proto-[[Khmer people|Khmer]] peoples was given a great deal of emphasis in the histories of Laos written during the French colonial period.  However, post-colonial historiography has instead sought to represent all peoples of Laos as equally &quot;indigenous&quot;, relating the early history in terms of a complex interaction with the (admittedly more ancient) [[Cambodia]]n kingdoms to the south, and praising the Proto-Khmer as Lao [[nationalists]] for their heroism and modern struggles against the French and Americans (see, e.&amp;nbsp;g., the [[Ong Keo|Ong Keo Rebellion]] starting circa 1902).

Both French colonial history and post-colonial ([[Communist]]) history sought to reverse the obvious [[racism]] of earlier, popular accounts that when the Lao migrated into the country, they simply conquered and enslaved the native inhabitants (viz., primarily Proto-Khmer people, described in such a context with the derogatory term &quot;Kha-That&quot;. See [[Khmu people]] and [[Lan_Xang#McCarthy.27s_account_of_1894|McCarthy's account of Lan Xang's origins]]). This traditional view has almost no factual basis, but remains a commonly heard pseudo-history, and a special concern for teachers to address (or redress) in the classroom.  [[Vatthana Pholsena]] provides a survey of the historiography on this point in ''Post-War Laos'', 2006, Silkworm Books.

=== Unitary States=== 
{{main|Mandala (Southeast Asian history)}}
It is generally assumed that, as late as the 16th century, [[King Photisarath]] helped establish [[Theravada]] Buddhism as the predominant religion of the country. However, this aspect of official history may now have to change given recent archaeological discoveries in Cambodia and Vietnam, showing intact [[Pali]] inscriptions as early as the 9th century. (See: [[JPTS]], Vol. XXIII, 1997: Peter Skilling, &quot;New Paali Inscriptions from Southeast Asia&quot;)

While there can be no doubt that [[animism]] and fragments of [[Shiva]]-worship were popular in ancient Laos, evidence increasingly indicates a long, gradual process leading to the ascendancy of Buddhism (rather than a single king converting the country). The reverse also did occur, as with the historical layers of statuary and inscriptions at [[Wat Phu Champassak]]; the oldest are in [[Sanskrit]], and worship Shiva, while the later evidence is Buddhist, subsequently reverting to animism (with the most recent statues simply depicting giant elephants and lizards, with no references to the organized religions of India, and neither Sanskrit nor [[Pali]] text).

It is significant to note that all of these official histories exclude the (possible and actual) influence of [[Religion in China|Chinese religion]] in the region. In fact, the ancient [[Lao calendar]] and [[Thai lunar calendar|Thai calendar]] are both of Chinese origin (adapted from the &quot;Heavenly [[Stem Branch Calendar]]&quot;), and do not reflect Indian cosmology.  These calendars were both part of the royal religion (preserved in [[epigraphy]]) and, apparently, part of popular religion (fortune telling) for centuries.


==Before full independence in 1953==
In the 17th century Lan Xang entered a period of decline and the late 18th century Siam (now [[Thailand]]) established control over much of what is now Laos. The region was divided into three dependent states centered on [[Luang Prabang]] in the north, [[Vientiane]] in the center, and [[Kingdom of Champasak|Champassak]] in the south. The Vientiane Lao rebelled in 1828 but were defeated, and the area was incorporated into Siam. Following its occupation of [[Vietnam]], [[France]] absorbed [[Laos]] into [[French Indochina]] via treaties with Siam in 1893 and 1904. 

During [[World War II]], the [[Japan]]ese occupied French Indochina. When Japan surrendered, Lao nationalists declared Laos independent, but by early 1946, French troops had reoccupied the country and conferred limited autonomy on Laos. During the [[Indochina War|First Indochina War]], the [[Indochinese Communist Party]] formed the [[Pathet Lao]] resistance organization committed to Lao independence. Laos gained full independence on 22 October 1953.

==The period of the Kingdom of Laos==
Elections were held in 1955, and the first coalition government, led by Prince [[Souvanna Phouma]], was formed in 1957. The coalition government collapsed in 1958 under pressure from the [[United States]]. In 1960 Captain [[Kong Le]] staged a coup when the cabinet was away at the royal capital of Luang Prabang and demanded reformation of a neutralist government. The second coalition government, once again led by Souvanna Phouma, was not successful in holding power. Rightist forces under General [[Phoumi Nosavan]] drove out the neutralist government from power later that same year. 

A second Geneva conference, held in 1961-62, provided for the independence and [[International Agreement on the Neutrality of Laos|neutrality of Laos]], but the agreement was subverted by both the United States and North Vietnam and the war soon resumed. The government and army of Laos were generally neutral during the conflict. The United States and North Vietnam subverted the agreement by forming private proxy armies. Growing American and North Vietnamese military presence in the country increasingly drew Laos into the [[Second Indochina War]] (1954-1975). For nearly a decade, eastern Laos was subjected to the heaviest bombing in the history of warfare [http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2003-12-11-laos-bombs_x.htm], as the U.S. sought to destroy the [[Ho Chi Minh Trail]] that passed through Laos. The country was also repeatedly invaded by Vietnam.

Shortly after the [[Paris Peace Accords]] led to the withdrawal of U.S. forces from Vietnam, a ceasefire between the Pathet Lao and the government led to a new coalition government. However, North Vietnam never really withdrew from Laos and the Pathet Lao remained little more than a proxy army for Vietnamese interests. After the fall of South Vietnam to communist forces in April 1975, the Pathet Lao with the backing of North Vietnam were able to take total power with little resistance. On December 2, 1975, the king was forced to abdicate his throne and the Lao People's Democratic Republic was established.

===Conflict===

The Military Regions Laos was divided into five military regions:

Military Region I at Luang Prabang was dominated by the royal family and the former commander in Chief of the Royal Laos Army, General Oune Rathikul. The region commander was Brigadier General Tiao Say~vong, a half brother of the king. The region was located in northwest Laos and covered four provinces: Phong Saly,Houa Khong, Sayaboury and Luang Prabang.
 
Military Region II, in the northeastern section of Laos, was under Major General Vang P.ao, the Meo guertilla war hero of Laos. It covered two provinces: Houa Phan (Samneua), and Xieng Khouang. The headquarters was at Long Cheng, northwest of the Plain of Jars.
 
Military Region III in central Laos was headquartered at Savannakhet and covered two provinces; Khammouane(Thakitek) and Savannakhet. This region was commanded by General Bounpon and later by Brigadier General Nouphet Dao Heuang, in July 1971. The real power in this region was the Insixiengmay family led by Minister Leuam Insixiengmay, Vice Premier and Minister of Education.( his wife is elder sister of Mom bouanphan who is a wife of Chao Boun oum na champasack)

Military Region IV, with headquarters at Pakse, included the six provinces of southern Laos: Saravane, Attopeu, Champassak, Sedone,Khong Sedone, and Sithandone (Khong Island). It was dominated by the Nachampassak family led by Prince Boun Oum Nachampassak. The commander of Military Region IV was Major General Phasouk S. Rassaphak, a member of the Champassak family. He commanded this area for almost a decade and a half until finally replaced by the author, Brigadier General Soutchay Vongsavanh, in July 1971.

Military Region V contained Borikhane and Vientiane Provinces, the capital province of Laos, was headquartered at Chinaimo Army Camp and was led by Major General Kouprasith Abhay until he was replaced by Brigadier General Thongligh Chokbeng Boun in July 1971.

==The period of the Communist government/contemporary period==
{{main|History of Laos since 1945}}
The new communist government led by [[Kaysone Phomvihane]] imposed centralized economic decision-making and incarcerated many members of the previous government and military in &quot;re-education camps&quot; which also included the Hmongs. While nominally independent, the communist government was for many years effectively little more than a puppet regime run from Vietnam. The government's policies prompted about 10 percent of the Lao population to leave the country. Laos depended heavily on Soviet aid channeled through Vietnam up until the Soviet collapse in 1991. In the 1990s the communist party gave up centralised management of the economy but still has a monopoly of political power.

==See also==
*[[Dai people]]
*[[Dong Son culture]]
*[[History of Asia]]
*[[History of Cambodia]]
*[[History of Isan]]
*[[History of Southeast Asia]]
*[[History of Laos to 1945]]
*[[History of Laos since 1945]]
*[[History of Vietnam]]
*[[Khmuic peoples]]
*[[Lao People's Revolutionary Party]]
*[[List of Presidents of Laos]]
*[[List of monarchs of Laos]]
*[[North Vietnamese invasion of Laos]]
*[[Peopling of Laos]]
*[[Politics of Laos]]
*[[Prime Minister of Laos]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.laomanuscripts.net Digital Library of Lao Manuscripts - an online library of historical Lao manuscripts and related background information]
* [http://www.historyofnations.net/asia/laos.html History of Laos]
* [http://www.laos-travel-guide.com/history-of-laos.html Laos Travel Guide History of Laos]
* {{cite web
|url= http://countrystudies.us/laos
|title= Laos: A Country Study
|date= 1994
|accessdate= August 8, 2011
|author= Andrea Matles Savada, ed.
|work=  [[Library of Congress Country Studies]]
|publisher= [[United States Government Printing Office|GPO]] for the [[Library of Congress]]
}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.royalark.net/Laos/laos2.htm|title= Laos
|author= Christopher Buyers |date=  August 2001 &amp;ndash; October 2009
|format= |work=  The Khun Lo Dynasty Genealogy &amp;c. |publisher=  The Royal Ark
|accessdate=  March 3, 2012 |quote=  All materials contained in this site are the subject of copyright. Many items are in use under licence. Therefore, on no account may copies be made of text, photographs, graphics or any other materials, without the express written consent of the site owner.&lt;!-- On 3/3/2012 4:58 AM, Christopher Buyers wrote: A link to my website is fine. --&gt;}}
{{History of Asia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Laos}}
[[Category:History of Laos| ]]
{{Link GA|ja}}

[[ar:تاريخ لاوس]]
[[cy:Hanes Laos]]
[[es:Historia de Laos]]
[[eu:Laosko historia]]
[[fr:Histoire du Laos]]
[[ko:라오스의 역사]]
[[io:Historio di Laos]]
[[id:Sejarah Laos]]
[[it:Storia del Laos]]
[[he:היסטוריה של לאוס]]
[[ja:ラオスの歴史]]
[[pt:História do Laos]]
[[ru:История Лаоса]]
[[sv:Laos historia]]
[[vi:Lịch sử Lào]]
[[zh:老挝历史]]</text>
      <sha1>6zeukf40imo48ue6pwdcfrmk0hv8tk7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
