<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Liberia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17792</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521591554</id>
      <parentid>521591377</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T00:12:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sue Rangell</username>
        <id>3799777</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/168.12.253.66|168.12.253.66]] ([[User talk:168.12.253.66|talk]]) to last revision by 76.127.181.131 ([[WP:HG|HG]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="59145">{{Liberia}}
'''[[Liberia]]''' was established by citizens of the [[United States]] as a [[colony]] for former [[African-American]] [[slaves]]. It is one of only two sovereign states in the world that were started by citizens of a political power as a colony for former slaves of the same political power: [[Sierra Leone]] was begun as a colony for resettlement of [[Black Loyalists]] and poor blacks from England for the same purpose by [[United Kingdom|Britain]].

==Early times (pre&amp;ndash;1821)==
[[File:Map of West Coast of Africa 1830.png|thumb|Map of Liberia circa 1830]]
Historians believe that many of the [[indigenous peoples]] of Liberia migrated there from the north and east between the 12th and 16th centuries AD. Portuguese explorers established contacts with people of the land later known as &quot;Liberia&quot; as early as 1461.  They named the area ''Costa da Pimenta'' ([[Pepper Coast]]) because of the abundance of [[Aframomum melegueta|melegueta pepper]]. In 1602 the Dutch established a trading post at Grand Cape Mount but destroyed it a year later. In 1663, the British installed trading posts on the Pepper Coast. No further known settlements by non-African colonists occurred along the Grain Coast (an alternative name) until the arrival in 1821 of free blacks from the United States.

==Colonization (1821–1847)==
{{main|American Colonization Society}}
From around 1800, in the [[United States]], people agreed to slavery were planning ways to alleviate the problem. Some abolitionists and slaveholders collaborated on the idea to set up a colony in Africa for former [[African-American]] slaves. Between 1821 and 1847, by a combination of purchase and conquest, American ‘Societies’ developed the colony ‘Liberia.’ On July 26, 1847, it declared its independence. 

===First ideas of colonization===
As early as the period of the [[American Revolution]], many white members of American society thought that African Americans could not succeed in living in ‘their’ society as free people. Some considered blacks physically and mentally inferior to whites, and others believed that the racism and societal polarization resulting from slavery were insurmountable obstacles for integration of the races. The young politician [[Thomas Jefferson]] was among those who proposed colonization in Africa; relocating free blacks outside the new nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Schwarz|first=Benjamin|year=1997|month=March|title=What (Thomas) Jefferson Helps to Explain|journal=[[The Atlantic|The Atlantic Monthly]]|volume=279}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Growing numbers of free blacks===
After 1783 the ranks of [[free black]]s expanded markedly, due both to manumission of the enslaved in the South during the first two decades after the [[American Revolutionary War|Revolutionary War]], attributable both to slaveholders inspired by its ideals and to others inspired to manumission by Quaker, Methodist and Baptist preachers active in those years.  The Northeast states abolished slavery following the war, generally on a graduated basis where it was still economically viable, as in the mid-Atlantic states. 

In 1800 and 1802, slave rebellions occurred (see [[Gabriel Prosser#Gabriel's Rebellion|Gabriel’s rebellion]]) in Virginia, and were brutally suppressed by slaveholders.  Some planters feared that free blacks would encourage slaves to run away or revolt. From 1782-1810, the number and percentage of free blacks in the [[Upper South]] increased from less than one percent to 13.5%.   In the nation as a whole, the number of free people of color also increased. In 1790, there were 59,467 free blacks, out of a total U.S. population of almost four million and a total black U.S. population of 800,000. By 1800, there were 108,378 free blacks in a population of 7.2 million.
These factors significantly influenced the popularity of the concept of colonization as a ‘solution’ to the ‘problem’ of free blacks.

===Sierra Leone===
[[File:Paul Cuffee4.jpg|right|thumb|Paul Cuffee in 1812.]]
In 1787, Britain had started to resettle the Black Poor of London in the colony of [[Freetown]] in modern-day [[Sierra Leone]], many of whom were [[Black Loyalists]] who had been freed in exchange for their services during the American Revolution. The Crown also offered resettlement to former slaves from Nova Scotia. The wealthy African-American shipowner [[Paul Cuffee]] thought this was a worthwhile exercise, and with support from certain members of Congress and British officials conveyed 38 American Blacks to Freetown in 1816 at his own expense. Despite such voyages ceasing with his death in 1817, his private initiative served to arouse public interest.

===Cape Mesurado===
In this same period, on the initiative of the Virginian politician [[Charles F. Mercer]] and the Presbyterian minister [[Robert Finley]] from New Jersey, in 1816 the [[American Colonization Society]] (ACS) was established in Washington D.C. by American politicians, senators and religious leaders from a variety of orientations.  They united on the project of ‘colonizing’ free blacks out of the U.S., to Africa. 

From January 1820, the ACS sent ships from New York to West Africa.  The first had 88 free black emigrants and three white ACS agents on board, who intended to seek an appropriate area to ground a settlement. After several attempts and hardships, ACS representatives in December 1821 succeeded, perhaps with some threat of force (see  [[American Colonization Society#Second ship: the Nautilus|American Colonization Society]]), to buy [[Cape Mesurado]], a 36-mile long strip of land near current day [[Monrovia]], from the indigenous ruler King Peter. 

From the beginning, the colonists were attacked by indigenous peoples, such as the [[Mandinka people|Malinké]] tribes.  In addition, they suffered from diseases, the harsh climate, lack of food and medicine, and poor housing conditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Schick |first=Tom W. |title=Behold the Promised Land: A History of Afro-American Settler Society in Nineteenth-Century Liberia |location=Baltimore |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Expansion===
Up until 1835, five more colonies were started by American Societies other than the ACS, and one by the U.S. government, all on the same West African coast. The first colony on Cape Mesurado was extended, along the coast as well as inland, sometimes by use of force.  In 1824 it was named Liberia, with the capital of Monrovia. By 1842, four of the other American colonies were incorporated into Liberia, and one was destroyed by indigenous people. The colonists of African-American descent became known as [[Americo-Liberian]]s. Not only were many racially mixed and of European descent, but their education, religion and culture made them distinct from the indigenous peoples, with whom they did not identify.

===Handing over command to Americo-Liberians===
[[File:Joseph Jenkins Roberts 2.jpg|thumb|thumb|200px|right| [[Joseph Jenkins Roberts]], governor and first president. Daguerreotype taken probably between 1840 and 1850.]] 
The maturing colony was gradually given more self-governance. In 1839, it was renamed the Commonwealth of Liberia; 1841 saw the Commonwealth's first black Governor, [[J.J. Roberts]]. By the 1840s, the ACS was effectively bankrupt; Liberia had become a financial  burden for it. In 1846, the ACS directed the Americo-Liberians to proclaim their independence. In 1847, Roberts proclaimed the colony the free and independent republic of Liberia. It then counted some 3000 settlers. A Constitution was drawn up along the lines of the United States’, denying voting rights to the indigenous Liberians.

==Americo-Liberian Rule (1847–1980)==
Between 1847 and 1980, the state of Liberia was governed by the small minority of African-American colonists and their offspring, together called [[Americo-Liberian]]s, suppressing the large indigenous majority of 95% of the Liberian population. The history of Liberia in this period can be described as four major, intertwined and interacting developments: 

# Relations between Americo-Liberians and the indigenous peoples
# Relations between the U.S. and Liberia
# Relations between non-U.S. foreign powers and Liberia
# Liberian economy, industry and natural resources

===Relations between Americo-Liberians and the indigenous peoples===
Relations between colonists and natives were contentious from the founding of Liberia, and eventually led to the overthrow of the Americo-Liberian regime in 1980.

====Resistance====
The original inhabitants of the area resented the American settlements and their territorial expansions.  They engaged in resistance in all imaginable forms from the inception of colonization until at least 1980.

====Americo-Liberian domination and suppression====
[[File:Map of Liberian Republic 1856.jpg|thumb|left|Map of Liberia c. 1856]]
The Americo-Liberians had been cut off from their African cultural inheritance by the conditions of [[slavery]], and were entirely acculturated to contemporary Euro-America society.  They were of mixed African and European ancestry and therefore generally lighter-skinned than the indigenous blacks.  Crucially, they had absorbed beliefs in the religious superiority of Protestant Christianity, the cultural superiority of [[European civilization]], and the aesthetic superiority of European skin color and hair texture.

They created a social and material facsimile of American society in Liberia, maintaining their English-speaking, Americanized way of life, and building churches and houses resembling those of the Southern U.S.
 
The Americo-Liberians never constituted more than five percent of the population of Liberia, yet they controlled key resources that allowed them to dominate the local native peoples: access to the ocean, modern technical skills, literacy and higher levels of [[education]], and valuable relationships with many American institutions, including the American government.

Ironically, one aspect of American society that the Americo-Liberians recreated was a cultural and racial caste system—however, in this case with themselves at the top instead of the bottom.  To them, their society must have seemed radically different from the USA because it rejected the ubiquitous Western belief in immutable racial hierarchy, which had led the colonists to despair of life in the USA. They, on the other hand, believed in racial equality, and therefore in the potential of all people to become 'civilized' through evangelization and education. Like many white missionaries before and after them, they were frustrated by the natives' lack of interest in becoming 'civilized.'

Some local people assimilated into Americo-Liberian society, often by marriage.  Some entire coastal tribes became Protestants and learned English. But most indigenous Africans kept to their traditional languages and religions. Before long, the Americo-Liberian ruling elite was living rather prosperously, sending their children to America for (often racially segregated) high school and college education, and keeping the indigenous peoples excluded from all political and economic leadership.

====Native insurgencies====
The Americo-Liberian settlers in 1878 organized their political power in the [[True Whig Party]], which permitted no organized political opposition. Until 1980, the Americo-Liberians firmly held onto their position of authority, meeting with unremitting uprising, rebellion and riots from the native peoples. The United States would, at least until 1915, take sides with the ruling Americo-Liberians in these struggles (see [[#(B.) Relations between the U.S. and Liberia|Relations between the U.S. and Liberia]]); European powers would, in the 19th century, stir up internal unrest in Liberia (see [[#Relations between non-U.S. foreign powers and Liberia|military threats]]). 

1856: war with [[Grebo (ethnic group)|Grebo]] and [[Kru people|Kru]] peoples, leading to the last American African colony, [[Republic of Maryland]], joining Liberia. It was annexed into Liberia as Maryland County in 1857.&lt;ref name=statesman&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Liberia.htm |work=World Statesmen.org|title=Liberia|accessdate= July 3, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=afric&gt;{{cite book|title=On Afric's Shore: A History of Maryland in Liberia, 1834-1857|publisher= Maryland Historical Society|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; (See [[Stephen Allen Benson|1856-64, Presidency Benson]].) 

1864: uprisings of inland and coastal tribes ([[Stephen Allen Benson|Presidency Benson]])

1875-76:  war in [[Cape Palmas]] (see [[James Spriggs Payne|1876-78, Presidency Payne-II]])

circa 1886: an uprising ([[Hilary R. W. Johnson|Presidency Johnson]])

mid 1880s until late 1890s: some tribes stay at war (see [[William D. Coleman (politician)|1896-1900, Presidency Coleman]])

1893: Grebo tribe attacked settlement of [[Harper, Liberia|Harper]] ([[Joseph James Cheeseman|Presidency Cheeseman]])

1900: bloody battle ([[William D. Coleman (politician)|Presidency Coleman]])

1915: rebellion of the Kru ([[Daniel Edward Howard|Presidency Howard]])

1912-20: internal wars ([[Daniel Edward Howard|Presidency Howard]])

====Admonishment from the League of Nations====
After 1927, the [[League of Nations]] investigated accusations that the Liberian government recruited and sold indigenous people as contract labor or slaves. In its 1930 report the League admonished the Liberian government for ‘systematically and for years fostering and encouraging a policy of gross intimidation and suppression’, “in order to suppress the native, prevent him from realizing his powers and limitations and prevent him from asserting himself in any way whatever, for the benefit of the dominant and colonizing race, although originally the same African stock as themselves”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Report of the International Commission of Inquiry into The Existence of Slavery and Forced Labor in the Republic of Liberia |publisher=U.S. Government Printing Office |location=Washington year=1931}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[Charles D. B. King|Presidency Charles King 1920-1930]]). President King hastily resigned.

====Social tensions 1940–1980====
[[File:Tubman&amp;Tolbert commemorative wrap 1968.jpg|thumb|President Tubman and Vice President Tolbert on a commemorative wrap celebrating the sixth term. 1968]]
During [[World War II]] thousands of indigenous Liberians came from the nation's interior to the coastal regions in search of jobs.  The Liberian Government had long opposed this kind of migration, but was no longer able to restrain it.

In the decades after 1945, the Liberian government received hundreds of millions of dollars of unrestricted foreign investment, which destabilized the Liberian economy. Liberian Government revenue rose enormously, but was being grossly embezzled by government officials. Growing economic disparities caused increased hostility between indigenous groups and Americo-Liberians.

The social tensions led President Tubman to enfranchise the indigenous Liberians either in 1951 or 1963 (accounts differ). Regardless of the date, this was enfranchisement in name only, since Tubman continued to repress political opposition, and to rig elections.

President Tolbert (1971–80) continued to suppress opposition harshly. Dissatisfaction over governmental plans to raise the price of rice in 1979 led to protest demonstrations in the streets of Monrovia. Tolbert ordered his troops to fire on the demonstrators, and seventy people were killed. Rioting ensued throughout Liberia, finally leading to a military coup d'état in April 1980.

===Relations between the U.S. and Liberia===
During their 133 years in power (1847–1980), the Americo-Liberian ruling class had a complicated relationship with the U.S.

====U.S. assists Americo-Liberians====
The United States had a long history of intervening in Liberia's internal affairs, occasionally sending naval vessels to help the Americo-Liberian (freed slave) ruling minority put down insurrections by indigenous tribes (in 1821, 1843, 1876, 1910, and 1915). By 1909, Liberia faced serious external threats to its sovereignty from the European colonial powers over unpaid foreign loans and annexation of its borderlands.http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/ops/liberia.htm

President William Howard Taft devoted a considerable portion of his First Annual Message to Congress (December 7, 1909) to the Liberian question, noting the close historical ties between the two countries that gave an opening for a wider intervention: 

&quot;It will be remembered that the interest of the United States in the Republic of Liberia springs from the historical fact of the foundation of the Republic by the colonization of American citizens of the African race. In an early treaty with Liberia there is a provision under which the United States may be called upon for advice or assistance. Pursuant to this provision and in the spirit of the moral relationship of the United States to Liberia, that Republic last year asked this Government to lend assistance in the solution of certain of their national problems, and hence the Commission was sent&quot; across the ocean on two cruisers.http://www.unz.org/Pub/LiteraryDigest-1909dec25-01167

In 1912 the U.S. arranged a 40-year international loan of $ 1.7 million, against which Liberia had to agree to four Western powers (America, Britain, France and Germany) controlling Liberian Government revenues for the next 14 years, until 1926. American administration of the border police also stabilized the frontier with Sierra Leone and checked French ambitions to annex more Liberian territory. The American navy also established a coaling station in Liberia, cementing its presence. When World War I started, Liberia declared war on Germany and expelled its resident German merchants, who constituted the country's largest investors and trading partners – Liberia suffered economically as a result.http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/ops/grebo2.htm

[[File:Roosevelt and Barclay.gif|thumb|right|President [[Edwin Barclay]] (right) and U.S. President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] during World War II, January 1943]]  
In 1926, the Liberian government gave a concession to the American [[rubber]] company [[Charles D. B. King#Firestone Rubber Company|Firestone]] to start the world’s largest rubber plantation at [[Harbel]], Liberia. At the same time, Firestone arranged a $5 million private loan to Liberia. In the 1930s Liberia was again virtually bankrupt, and, after some American pressure, agreed to an assistance plan from the [[League of Nations]].  As part of this plan, two key officials of the League were placed in positions to ´advise´ the Liberian government.

====War involvement====
In [[Edwin Barclay#World War II|World War II]], Liberia signed a Defence Pact with the U.S. in 1942, and assured the Americans and their allies of all the supply of natural rubber (a strategic commodity in wartime) that they needed. It also allowed the U.S. to use its territory for military bases, and as a bridgehead for American transports of soldiers and war supplies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=William R. |last=Stanley |title=Trans-South Atlantic air link in World War II|journal=GeoJournal|doi=10.1007/BF00806430|volume=33|month=August | year=1994|url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/luq322hw03n72p13/|accessdate=2007-06-23 |doi_brokendate=2008-06-24|issue=4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. subsidized the construction of airports (Roberts Field), the [[Freeport of Monrovia]], and roads into the interior of Liberia.

====Cold War, foreign investment, exploitation====
[[File:Carter and Tolbert.gif|thumb|250px|left|President Tolbert and U.S. President [[Jimmy Carter]] (in car, left) in [[Monrovia]], 1978]] 
After World War II, the U.S. positioned Liberia to resist the expansion of [[U.S.S.R.|Soviet]] influence in Africa during the [[Cold War]].  Liberian president [[William Tubman|Tubman]] was agreeable to this policy.  Between 1946 and 1960 Liberia received from some $500 million in unrestricted foreign investment, mainly from the U.S. From 1962 to 1980, the U.S. donated $280 million in aid to Liberia. In the 1970s under president [[Tolbert]], Liberia strove for a more non-aligned and independent posture, and established diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union, China, Cuba and Eastern bloc countries.  It also severed ties with Israel during the [[Yom Kippur War]] in 1973, but kept supporting the U.S. on the [[Vietnam War]].

===Relations between non-U.S. foreign powers and Liberia===
====Dubious commerce, military threats====
From the founding of Liberia, Europeans had commercial contacts with the nation. During the period 1856-64 European merchants consistently evaded Liberian import and export duties, in which they were supported by their own governments. This practice started or aggravated the financial tightness of the new state. By 1870 Liberia had sunk into financial crisis, which dragged on into the 1930s. Several times the Liberian government borrowed money from English banks on severe terms, and even from local German merchants. In 1912 the U.S. intervened into Liberia’s dire financial situation (see [[#(B.) Relations between the U.S. and Liberia|Relations between the U.S. and Liberia]]). 

Between 1878 and 1919 Britain, France and Germany, busy extending their own colonial territories in the region, threatened Liberia militarily, and France and Britain forced Liberia to cede parts of its territory to them (1883, 1885, 1892, 1903, 1919). Only after 1892 were Liberia's borders officially negotiated with these European powers.&lt;ref name=statesman/&gt;  
The British (in 1875) and French (in 1886) are also alleged to have fuelled internal Liberian uprisings and wars.{{citation needed|date=October 2010}}
From 1878 onwards Liberian presidents regularly called for more foreign trade and more foreign investment in Liberia.

====Two World Wars====
Between 1910 and 1943 Germany was Liberia’s major trading partner. 
In [[Daniel Edward Howard#World War I|World War I]], Liberia nevertheless tended to support the Allies, partly because it was French and British colonial territories that surrounded Liberia but also because Allied control of the Atlantic sea lanes made continued trade with Germany unviable. As a result Germany withdrew business from Liberia, causing Liberian customs revenue to decrease significantly. 
In the 1930s Dutch, Danish, German and Polish investors signed agreements for economic activities. 
In the [[Edwin Barclay#World War II|Second World War]], the U.S. pressured Liberia to side with the Allies, and to expel all German citizens and business representatives in 1944. This would have again significantly disturbed the Liberian economy, but America had already in 1942 begun investing substantially in Liberia, in projects related to America’s war effort.

====Large scale investments====
Between 1945 and 1980, the posture of Western European states towards Liberia was largely that of the U.S.. Americo-Liberian rulers received hundreds of millions of dollars in unrestricted foreign investment, mainly from the U.S., but also from Western Europe. Many Western politicians courted president Tubman. 

Liberian rulers also built up ties with the [[Soviet bloc]] and other powers, striving for an independent position in world politics, as far as their strong bonds with the [[Western world]] allowed them to.

===Liberian economy, industry and natural resources===
The Liberian economy between 1847 and 1980 expanded from primitive agriculture, through large scale rubber industry, to exploitation of mineral resources and rendering services.

====Agriculture====
From its foundation, Liberia had flourishing trade contacts in West Africa, and soon started trading with Europeans. Primary export products were coffee, rice, palm oil, palm kernels, [[piassava]], sugarcane and (hardwood) timber. Shipbuilding was important, until it declined in the 1870s with the competition from steamships. Also in the 1870s competition from Brazilian coffee and European sugar beets caused a decline in Liberian exports. 
Liberia then tried to modernize its largely agricultural economy. President [[Anthony W. Gardiner|Gardiner]] (1878–83) called for increases of foreign trade and investment. President  [[William D. Coleman (politician)|Coleman]] (1896–1900) considered the future of Liberia to depend on exploitation of the resources of Liberia’s interior. President [[Garreston W. Gibson|Gibson]] (1900–04) granted rights to [[Union Mining Company]] to investigate the hinterland for minerals. 
During [[Daniel Edward Howard#World War I|World War I]], Germany, at that time Liberia’s major trading partner, withdrew from the country, causing Liberian customs revenue to decrease. Additionally a German submarine blockade of Liberia caused trade with Britain, France and the U.S. to decrease to negligible amounts.

====Natural resources====
[[File:Latex dripping.JPG|thumb|200px|right|Latex being collected from a [[rubber tapping|tapped]] [[Pará rubber tree|rubber tree]]]] 
In 1926, [[Charles D. B. King#Firestone Rubber Company|Firestone]], an American rubber company, started the worlds largest rubber plantation in Liberia. This industry created 25,000 jobs, and rubber quickly became the backbone of the Liberian economy; in the 1950s, rubber accounted for 40 percent of the national budget. 
In the 1930s, Liberia signed concession agreements with Dutch, Danish, German and Polish investors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Fred p.m. van der Kraaij|title=The Open Door Policy of Liberia. An Economic history of Modern Liberia|publisher=Bremen|year=1983|chapter= Chapter 2, The origins of the Closed Door Policies and Open Door Policies 1847-1947|pages=12–46}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
In [[Edwin Barclay#World War II|World War II]], rubber was strategically important, and Liberia assured the U.S. and its allies of all the natural rubber they needed. Also, Liberia allowed the U.S. to use its territory as a bridgehead for transports of soldiers and war supplies, to construct military bases, airports, the Freeport of Monrovia, roads to the interior, etc. The American military presence boosted the Liberian economy; thousands of laborers descended from the interior to the coastal region. The country’s huge iron ore deposits were made accessible to commerce.

Between 1946 and 1960, the Liberian government attracted $500 million in foreign investment, mainly American, partly also from [[multinational corporation]]s. By 1971, this amounted to more than $1 billion. Exports of iron, timber and rubber rose strongly. In 1971, Liberia had the world’s largest rubber industry, and was the third largest exporter of iron ore. 
Other mineral deposits also generated state income.  From 1948 [[Flag of convenience|Ship registrations]] became another large new source of state revenue.  From 1962 until 1980, the U.S. donated $280 million in aid to Liberia, in exchange for which Liberia offered its land free of rent for U.S. government facilities.

Throughout the 1970s the price of rubber in the world commodities market was depressed, putting pressure on Liberian state finances.

==Samuel Doe and the People’s Redemption Council (1980–1989)==
{{main|Samuel Doe}}

After a bloody overthrow of the Americo-Liberian régime by indigenous Liberians in 1980, a ‘Redemption Council’ took control of Liberia. Internal unrest, opposition to the new military regime, and governmental repression steadily grew, until in 1989 Liberia sank into outright [[tribalism|tribal]] and [[civil war]].

===Coup d’état; relations with U.S.===
[[Samuel Doe|Samuel Kanyon Doe]] (1951–1990) was a member of the small ethnic group of the [[Krahn]], a master sergeant in the Liberian army, and trained by [[U.S. Army Special Forces]]{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}. On April 12, 1980, Doe led a bloody ''[[coup d'état]]'' against president [[William R. Tolbert, Jr.|Tolbert]], in which Tolbert and twenty-six of his supporters were murdered; ten days later thirteen of Tolbert’s Cabinet members were publicly executed. Thus ended 133 years of [[Americo-Liberian]] political domination over Liberia. Doe established a military regime called the [[People's Redemption Council]] (PRC). 
Many people welcomed Doe's takeover as a shift favouring the majority of the population that had been excluded from power. Immediately following the coup, the PRC tolerated a relatively free press. 

Doe quickly established good relations with the [[United States]], especially after U.S. President [[Ronald Reagan]] took office in 1981. Reagan increased financial aid for Liberia, from the $20 million it had been in 1979, to $75 million, and later $95 million per year. Liberia became again an important [[Cold War]] ally of the U.S.. Liberia served to protect important U.S. facilities and investments, and to counter the perceived spread of Soviet influence in Africa. Doe closed the [[Libya]]n mission in Monrovia and even severed diplomatic relations with the [[Soviet Union]]. He agreed to a modification of the mutual defence pact with the U.S. granting staging rights on 24-hour notice at Liberia's sea- and airports for the [[United States Rapid Deployment Forces|U.S. Rapid Deployment Forces]]. 
Under Doe, Liberian ports were opened to [[United States|American]], [[Canada|Canadian]], and [[Europe]]an ships, which brought in considerable foreign investment from shipping firms and earned Liberia a reputation as a [[tax haven]].

===Fear of counter-coup; repression===
Doe overcame seven coup attempts between 1981 and 1985. In August 1981 he had [[Thomas Weh Syen]] and four other PRC members arrested and executed for allegedly conspiring against him. Then Doe’s government declared an amnesty for all political prisoners and exiles, and released sixty political prisoners. 
Soon there were more internal rifts in the PRC. Doe became paranoid about the possibility of a counter-coup, and his government grew increasingly corrupt and repressive, banning political opposition, shutting down newspapers and jailing reporters. He began to systematically eliminate PRC members who challenged his authority, and to place people of his own ethnic Krahn background in key positions, which intensified popular anger. 
Meanwhile, the economy deteriorated precipitously. Popular support for Doe's government evaporated.

===1985 presidential election===
A draft constitution providing for a multiparty republic had been issued in 1983 and was approved by referendum in 1984. After the referendum, Doe staged a [[Liberia elections, 1985|presidential election]] on October 15, 1985. Nine political parties sought to challenge Doe's National Democratic Party of Liberia (NDPL), but only three were allowed to take part. Prior to the election, more than fifty of Doe's opponents were murdered. Doe was ‘elected’ with 51% of the vote, but the election was heavily rigged. Foreign observers declared the elections fraudulent, and most of the elected opposition candidates refused to take their seats. 
U.S. Assistant Secretary of State for Africa [[Chester Crocker]] testified before Congress that the election was imperfect but that at least it was a step toward democracy. He further justified his support for the election results with the claim that, in any case, all African elections were known to be rigged at that time.

===Repression escalates into tribal warfare===
''(see also [[First Liberian Civil War]])'' 

In November 1985 [[Thomas Quiwonkpa]], Doe’s former second-in-command, with an estimated 500 to 600 people, failed in an attempt to seize power; all were killed. Doe was sworn in as President on January 6, 1986. Doe then initiated crackdowns against certain tribes, such as the [[Gio Tribe|Gio]] (or Dan) and [[Mano people|Mano]], in the north, where most of the coup plotters came from. This government's mistreatment of certain ethnic groups resulted in divisions and violence among indigenous populations, who until then had coexisted relatively peacefully. 
In the late 1980s, as fiscal austerity took hold in the United States and the perceived threat of Communism declined with the waning of the Cold War, the U.S. became disenchanted with Doe's government and began cutting off critical foreign aid to Liberia. This, together with the popular opposition, made Doe’s position precarious. 

Nonetheless, the [[Krahn]] tribe of president Doe attacked tribes in [[Nimba County]] in the north; some northerners fled to bordering [[Côte d’Ivoire]] (Ivory Coast). In the late 1980s, [[Charles Taylor (Liberia)|Charles Taylor]] assembled rebels from Gio and Mano tribes in Ivory Coast into a militia, invaded Nimba County in 1989, and by 1990 a full-blown tribal war was taking place.

==First Liberian Civil War (1989–1996)==
''(See also: [[First Liberian Civil War]] and [[Charles Taylor (Liberia)|Charles Taylor]])''

In the late 1980s opposition from abroad to [[Samuel Doe|Doe]]’s regime led to economic collapse. Doe had already been repressing and crushing internal opposition for some time, when in November 1985 another coup attempt against him failed. Doe retaliated against tribes such as the [[Gio Tribe|Gio]] (or Dan) and [[Mano people|Mano]] in the north, where most of the coup plotters had come from. Perhaps as a sequel to these governmental retaliations, perhaps as another circumscription of these same events: Doe’s [[Krahn]] tribe began attacking other tribes, particularly in [[Nimba County]] in the northeast of Liberia, bordering on [[Côte d’Ivoire]] (Ivory Coast) and on [[Guinea]]. Some Liberian northerners fled brutal treatment from the Liberian army into the Ivory Coast.

===Charles Taylor and the NPFL 1980-’89===
[[Charles Taylor (Liberia)|Charles Taylor]], born 1948, is son to a [[Gola people|Gola]] mother and either an [[Americo-Liberian]] or an [[Afro-Trinidadian]] father.  Taylor was a student at Bentley College in Waltham, Massachusetts, U.S.A., from 1972 to 1977, earning a degree in economics. After the 1980 ''coup d’état'' he served some time in Doe’s government until he was sacked in 1983 on accusation of embezzling government funds. He fled Liberia, was arrested in 1984 in Massachusetts on a Liberian warrant for extradition, and jailed in Massachusetts; escaped from jail in 1985, and probably fled to [[Libya]]. 
Some time later, while in the Ivory Coast, Taylor assembled a group of rebels into the [[National Patriotic Front of Liberia]] (NPFL), mostly from the [[Gio Tribe|Gio]] and [[Mano people|Mano]] tribes.

===War===
December 1989, NPFL invaded Nimba County in Liberia. Thousands of Gio and Mano joined them, Liberians of other ethnic background as well. The Liberian army (AFL) counterattacked, and retaliated against the whole population of the region. Mid 1990, a war was raging between Krahn on one side, and Gio and Mano on the other. On both sides, thousands of civilians were massacred.

===1990-1991===
By the middle of 1990, Taylor controlled much of the country, and by June laid siege to Monrovia. In July, [[Yormie Johnson]] split off from NPFL and formed the [[Independent National Patriotic Front of Liberia]] (INPFL), based on the Gio tribe. Both NPFL and INPFL continued siege on Monrovia. Bloodshed was all over. 

In August 1990, the [[Economic Community of West African States]] (ECOWAS), an organisation of West African states, created a military intervention force called [[Economic Community of West African States Monitoring Group]] (ECOMOG) of 4,000 troops, to restore order. President Doe and Yormie Johnson (INPFL) agreed to this intervention, Taylor didn’t. 
On 9 September, President Doe paid a visit to the barely established headquarters of ECOMOG in the Free Port of Monrovia, was at the ECOMOG headquarters attacked by INPFL, taken to the INPFL’s Caldwell base, tortured and killed. 

November 1990, ECOWAS agreed with some principal Liberian players but without Charles Taylor, on an Interim Government of National Unity (IGNU) under President [[Amos Sawyer|Dr. Amos Sawyer]]. Sawyer established his authority over most of Monrovia, with the help of a paramilitary police force, the 'Black Berets', under [[Brownie Samukai]], while the rest of the country was in the hands of the various warring factions. 

June 1991, former Liberain army fighters formed rebel group [[United Liberation Movement of Liberia for Democracy]] (ULIMO), entered western Liberia in September ’91, and gained territories from the NPFL.

===1993-1996===
1993, ECOWAS brokered a peace agreement in [[Cotonou]], [[Benin]]. On 22 September 1993, the [[United Nations]] established the [[United Nations Observer Mission in Liberia]] (UNOMIL) to support ECOMOG in implementing the Cotonou agreement. March 1994, the ‘interim government’ of [[Amos Sawyer|Sawyer]] was succeeded by a ''Council of State'' collective presidency of six members headed by [[David D. Kpormakpor]]. May 1994, renewed armed hostilities broke out and held on. Somewhere 1994, ULIMO broke into two militias: ULIMO-J, a Krahn faction led by [[Roosevelt Johnson]] and ULIMO-K, a Mandigo-based faction under [[Alhaji G.V. Kromah]]. September ’94, factional leaders agreed to the Akosombo peace agreement in Ghana, but to little consequence. October ‘94, the UN reduced its number of UNOMIL observers to about 90 because of the lack of will of combatants to honour peace agreements. December ’94, factions and parties signed the Accra agreement, but fighting continued. August 1995, factions signed an agreement largely brokered by [[Jerry Rawlings]], Ghanaian President; Charles Taylor agreed. September ’95, [[David D. Kpormakpor|Kpormakpor]]’s ''Council of State'' is succeeded by one under civilian [[Wilton G. S. Sankawulo]] and with the factional heads Charles Taylor, Alhaji Kromah and [[George Boley]] in it. April 1996, followers of Taylor and Kromah assaulted the headquarters of Roosevelt Johnson in Monrovia, and the peace accord collapsed. In August ’96, a new ceasefire is reached in [[Abuja]], [[Nigeria]]. 3 September 1996, [[Ruth Perry]] followed [[Wilton G. S. Sankawulo|Sankawulo]] as chairwoman of the ''Council of State'', with the same three militia leaders in it.

==Second Liberian Civil War (1997–2003)==
''(See also: [[First Liberian Civil War]], [[Charles Taylor (Liberia)|Charles Taylor]] and [[Second Liberian Civil War]]) ''

===Elections 1997===
[[Charles Taylor (Liberia)|Charles Taylor]] won the 1997 presidential elections with 75.33 percent of the vote, while the runner-up, [[Unity Party (Liberia)|Unity Party]] leader [[Ellen Johnson Sirleaf]], received a mere 9.58 percent of the vote. Accordingly, Taylor's [[National Patriotic Party]] gained 21 of a possible 26 seats in the Senate, and 49 of a possible 64 seats in the House of Representatives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kieh, Jr.|first=George Klay|title=Warlords, Politicians and the Post-First Civil War Election in Liberia|journal=African and Asian Studies|year=2011|volume=10|page=97}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The election was judged free and fair by some observers although it was charged that Taylor had employed widespread intimidation to achieve victory at the polls.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}

===1997-1999===
Bloodshed in Liberia did slow considerably, but it did not end. Violence kept flaring up. During his entire reign, Taylor had to fight insurgencies against his government. Suspicions were, Taylor continued to assist rebel forces in neighbouring countries, like [[Sierra Leone]], trading weapons for diamonds.

===1999-2003===
Some ULIMO forces reformed themselves as the [[Liberians United for Reconciliation and Democracy]] (LURD), backed by the government of neighbouring [[Guinea]]. In 1999, they emerged in northern Liberia, in April 2000 they started fighting in [[Lofa County]] in northernmost Liberia. By the spring of 2001 they were posing a major threat to the Taylor government. Liberia was now engaged in a complex three-way conflict with Sierra Leone and the Guinea Republic. 

Meanwhile, the [[United Nations Security Council]] in March 2001 ([[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1343|Resolution 1343]])&lt;ref name=&quot;UNSC resolutions 2001&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=UNSC Resolution 1343|work=UN Security Council|url=http://www.un.org/Docs/scres/2001/sc2001.htm|accessdate=2008-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;  concluded that Liberia and Charles Taylor played roles in the civil war in Sierra Leone, and therefore: 
* banned all arms sales to, and diamonds sales from Liberia; and
* banned high Liberian Government members to travel to UN-states.

By the beginning of 2002, Sierra Leone and Guinea were supporting the LURD, while Taylor was supporting opposition factions in both countries. By supporting Sierra Leonean rebels, Taylor also drew the enmity of the British and Americans. 

Other elements of the former ULIMO-factions formed another new rebel group, the [[Movement for Democracy in Liberia]] (MODEL). Early 2003, MODEL emerged in the south of Liberia.

===Women of Liberia===
{{Main|Women of Liberia Mass Action for Peace}}
[[File:LiberianWomen.jpg|right|thumb|320px|[[Women of Liberia Mass Action for Peace]]]]
In 2002, the women in Liberia were tired of seeing their country torn apart. Organized by social worker [[Leymah Gbowee]], women started gathering and praying in a fish market to protest the violence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.odemagazine.com/blogs/readers_blog/9001/leymah_gbowee_peace_warrior_for_liberia 2009|title= eymah_gbowee_peace_warrior_for_liberia 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; They organized the Women in Peacebuilding Network (WIPNET), and issued a statement of intent: &quot;In the past we were silent, but after being killed, raped, dehumanized, and infected with diseases, and watching our children and families destroyed, war has taught us that the future lies in saying NO to violence and YES to peace! We will not relent until peace prevails.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myhero.com/go/hero.asp?hero=womens_peace_movement_liberia_08|title= Womens peace movement of liberia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Joined by Liberian Muslim Women's Organization,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unmultimedia.org/radio/english/detail/64653.html|title= United Nations Radio}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christian and Muslim women joined forces to create [[Women of Liberia Mass Action for Peace]]. They wore white, to symbolize peace. They staged silent [[nonviolence]] protests and forced a meeting with President [[Charles Taylor (Liberia)|Charles Taylor]] and extracted a promise from him to attend peace talks in [[Ghana]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanprogress.org/events/2008/11/inf/GboweeLeymah.html |title=Bio of Gbowee Leymah}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2003, a delegation of Liberian women went to [[Ghana]] to continue to apply pressure on the warring factions during the peace process. They staged a [[sit in]] outside of the Presidential Palace, blocking all the doors and windows and preventing anyone from leaving the peace talks without a resolution. [[Women of Liberia Mass Action for Peace]] became a political force against violence and against their government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.guideposts.com/blog/life-faith-liberia-peace-movement-women|title= Guideposts review}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their actions brought about an agreement during the stalled peace talks. As a result, the women were able to achieve peace in [[Liberia]] after a 14-year civil war and later helped bring to power the country's first female head of state, [[Ellen Johnson Sirleaf]].

===Another UN embargo, and arrest warrant against Taylor===
[[File:Buduburam-refugee-camp.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Buduburam]] [[refugee camp]] west of [[Accra]], [[Ghana]], home in 2005 to more than 40,000 refugees from Liberia]]
On March 7, 2003, the war tribunal [[Special Court for Sierra Leone]] (SCSL) decided to summon Charles Taylor and charge him with [[war crime]]s and [[crimes against humanity]], but they kept this decision and this charge secret until June that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;NRC 5-6-2003&quot;&gt;{{cite news| newspaper=NRC Handelsblad|language=Dutch|location= Nederlands |date= 5 June 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

May 6, 2003, the UN Security Council ([[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1478|Resolution 1478]]) decided to an embargo also on Liberian “round logs and timber products”.&lt;ref name=&quot;UNSC resolutions 2003&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=UNSC Resolution 1478|work=UN Security Council|url=http://www.un.org/Docs/sc/unsc_resolutions03.html|accessdate=2008-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

By mid-2003, LURD controlled the northern third of the country and was threatening the capital, MODEL was active in the south, and Taylor's government controlled only a third of the country: Monrovia and central Liberia. 

On June 4, 2003, ECOWAS organized peace talks in [[Accra]], [[Ghana]], among the Government of Liberia, civil society, and the rebel groups  LURD and MODEL. On the opening ceremony, in Taylor’s presence, the SCSL revealed their charge against Taylor which they had kept secret since March, and also issued an international arrest warrant for Taylor.&lt;ref name=&quot;NRC 5-6-2003&quot;/&gt; The SCSL indicted Taylor for “bearing the greatest responsibility” for atrocities in Sierra Leone since November 1996. The Ghanaian authorities did not attempt to arrest Taylor, declaring they could not round up a president they themselves had invited as a guest for peace talks.&lt;ref name=&quot;NRC 5-6-2003&quot;/&gt; The same day, Taylor returned to Liberia.

===Pressure of rebels, Presidents, and UN: Taylor resigns===
June 2003, LURD began a siege of Monrovia. July 9, the Nigerian President offered Taylor safe [[exile]] in his country, if Taylor stayed out of Liberian politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2003/WORLD/africa/07/09/liberia/ | title=Nigeria would shield Taylor from trial|publisher=cnn.com|date=2003-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in July, American President [[George W. Bush|Bush]] stated twice that Taylor “must leave Liberia”. Taylor insisted that he would resign only if American [[peacekeeping]] troops were deployed to Liberia. 
1 August 2003, the Security Council, ([[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1497|Resolution 1497]]) decided on a multinational force in Liberia, to be followed-on by a United Nations stabilization force. 
ECOWAS sent troops under the banner of '[[ECOMIL]]' to Liberia.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimesnigeria&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first=Felicity | last=Barringer | coauthors= | title= Nigeria Readies Peace Force for Liberia; Battles Go On | date=2003-07-24 | publisher= | url =http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D6153FF937A15754C0A9659C8B63 | newspaper =The New York Times | pages = | accessdate = 2008-01-18 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;  These troops started to arrive in Liberia probably as of 15 August. The U.S. provided logistical support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2003/WORLD/africa/07/07/liberia/ | title=Liberia's Taylor not ready to leave| date=2003-07-07|publisher=cnn.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; President Taylor resigned, and flew into exile in [[Nigeria]]. Vice-President [[Moses Blah]] replaced Taylor as interim-President. 
A ECOWAS-ECOMIL force of 1000 Nigerian troops was airlifted into Liberia on August 15, to halt the occupation of [[Monrovia]] by rebel forces. Meanwhile, U.S. stationed a [[Marine Expeditionary Unit]] with 2300 Marines offshore Liberia.

==Peace agreement and transitional government (2003–2005)==
[[File:Gyude Bryant.jpg|thumb|150px|right|[[Gyude Bryant]]]] 
On August 18, 2003, the Liberian Government, the rebels, political parties, and leaders from civil society signed a peace agreement that laid the framework for a two-year National Transitional Government of Liberia. August 21, they selected businessman [[Charles Gyude Bryant]] as Chair of the National Transitional Government of Liberia (NTGL), effective on October 14. These changes paved the way for the ECOWAS peacekeeping mission to expand into a 3,600-strong force, constituted by [[Benin]], [[Gambia]], [[Ghana]], [[Guinea-Bissau]], [[Mali]], [[Nigeria]], [[Senegal]] and [[Togo]]. 

On October 1, 2003, [[UNMIL]] took over the peacekeeping duties from ECOWAS. Some 3,500 West African troops were provisionally ‘re-hatted’ as United Nations peacekeepers. The UN Secretary-General commended the African Governments who have contributed to UNMIL, as well as the United States for its support to the regional force. October 14, 2003, Blah handed power to [[Gyude Bryant|Charles Gyude Bryant]]. 

Fighting initially continued in parts of the country, and tensions between the factions did not immediately vanish. 
But fighters were being disarmed; in June 2004, a program to reintegrate the fighters into society began; the economy recovered somewhat in 2004; by year's end, the funds for the re-integration program proved inadequate; also by the end of 2004, more than 100,000 Liberian fighters had been disarmed, and the disarmament program was ended. In light of the progress made, President Bryant requested an end to the UN embargo on Liberian diamonds (since March 2001) and timber (since May 2003), but the Security Council postponed such a move until the peace was more secure. 
Because of a supposed ‘fundamentally broken system of governance that contributed to 23 years of conflict in Liberia’, and failures of the Transitional Government in curbing corruption, the Liberian government and the [[International Contact Group on Liberia]] signed onto the anti-corruption program [[GEMAP]], starting September 2005.

==Ellen Johnson Sirleaf elected president (2005)==
{{main|Liberian elections, 2005|Ellen Johnson Sirleaf}} 
 [[File:Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf3.jpg|thumb|200px|left|[[Ellen Johnson Sirleaf]]]] 
The transitional government prepared for fair and peaceful democratic elections on October 11, 2005, with UNMIL troops safeguarding the peace. Twenty three candidates stood for the presidential election, with [[George Weah]], internationally famous footballer, [[UNICEF]] Goodwill Ambassador and member of the [[Kru people|Kru]] ethnic group, and [[Ellen Johnson Sirleaf]], a former [[World Bank]] economist and finance minister,  [[Harvard]]-trained economist and of mixed [[Americo-Liberian]] and indigenous descent. 
In the first round, no candidate took the required majority, Weah won this round with 28% of the vote. A run-off between the top two vote getters, Weah and Ellen Johnson Sirleaf, was necessary. 

The second round of elections took place on November 8, 2005. Ellen Johnson Sirleaf won this runoff decisively. Both the general election and runoff were marked by peace and order, with thousands of Liberians waiting patiently in the Liberian heat to cast their ballots. 
Sirleaf claimed victory of this round, winning 59 per cent of the vote. However, Weah alleged electoral fraud, despite international observers declaring the election to be free and fair. Although Weah was still threatening to take his claims to the Supreme Court if no evidence of fraud was found, Johnson-Sirleaf was declared winner on November 23, 2005, and took office on January 16, 2006.
{{clear}}

==Recent events (2006–present)==
===Allegations of labor rights abuses by Firestone===
{{main|Labor conditions at Firestone Plantation in Liberia}}
In November 2005, the [[International Labor Rights Fund]] filed an Alien Tort Claims Act (ATCA) case against [[Bridgestone]], the parent company of Firestone, alleging “forced labor, the modern equivalent of slavery”, on the [[Firestone Tire and Rubber Company|Firestone]] Plantation in [[Harbel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Claim against Firestone&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Firestone Claim|work=socialfunds.com|url=http://www.socialfunds.com/news/article.cgi/1897.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In May 2006, the [[United Nations Mission in Liberia]] (UNMIL) released a report: “Human Rights in Liberia’s Rubber Plantations: Tapping into the Future” which detailed the results of its investigation into the conditions on the Firestone plantation in Liberia.

===Extradition and trial of Charles Taylor, arrest of Bryant===
Under international pressure, President [[Ellen Johnson Sirleaf|Sirleaf]] requested in March 2006 that [[Nigeria]] extradite Charles Taylor, who was then brought before an international tribunal in [[Sierra Leone]] to face charges of [[crimes against humanity]], arising from events during the Sierra Leone civil war (his trial was later transferred to [[The Hague]] for security purposes). In June, 2006, the United Nations ended its embargo on Liberian timber (effective since May 2003), but continued its diamond embargo (effective since March 2001) until an effective certificate of origin program was established, a decision that was reaffirmed in October 2006. 

In March 2007, former interim president [[Gyude Bryant|Bryant]] was arrested and charged with having embezzled government funds while in office. In August 2007, the [[Supreme Court of Liberia]] allowed the criminal prosecution for this to proceed in the lower courts.&lt;ref name=Bryant&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.monstersandcritics.com/news/africa/news/article_1348020.php|title=Liberia's Supreme Court endorses ex-leader's trial|work=Africa News|date=August 27, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court ruled that Bryant was not entitled to immunity as the head of state under the Constitution as he was not elected to the position and he was not acting in accordance with law when he allegedly stole USD $1.3 million in property from the government.&lt;ref name=Bryant/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The Inquirer|title=Liberia; Corruption Case Against Bryant to Be Decided This Week|date= August 8, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2008-2009===
In July 2008, the Legislature reintroduced the [[death penalty]] into Liberian law, with President Sirleaf signing the bill into law.&lt;ref name=death&gt;{{Cite news|newspaper=The Analyst|title=Liberia; Death Penalty Under Fire|publisher=Africa News|date=August 7, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The law allowed for executions for convictions of armed robbery, rape, terrorism, and hijacking.&lt;ref name=death/&gt;

Some parts of the country were declared disaster zones due to a plague of [[caterpillar]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=100276266 |title=Liberia Overwhelmed By Plague of Caterpillars}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[American Colonization Society]]
*[[History of Africa]]
*[[History of West Africa]]
*[[President of Liberia]]
*[[Politics of Liberia]]
*[[Lott Carey]], of [[Richmond, Virginia]], the first American [[missionary]] to Liberia
*[[Republic of Maryland]]
*[[Pray the Devil Back to Hell]]
*[[Women of Liberia Mass Action for Peace]]

==References==
{{StateDept|url=http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/6618.htm}}
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last= Boley|first= G.E. Saigbe |title= Liberia: The Rise and Fall of the First Republic|location=New York|publisher= MacMillan Publishers|year=1983}}
*{{cite book|last = Cassell|first= C. Abayomi |title= Liberia: The History of the First African Republic|location= New York|publisher= Fountainhead Publishers', Inc.|year=1970}}
*{{cite book|last1 = Dunn|first1= Elwood D.|last2= Holsoe|first2=Svend E. |title= Historical Dictionary of Liberia|series= African Historical Dictionaries Series|location=Metuchen|publisher= Scarecrow Press|year= 1985}}
*{{cite book|last = Johnston|first= Harry |title= Liberia|location= London|publisher= Hutchinson|year= 1906}}
*{{cite book|last = Liebenow|first= J. Gus |title= Liberia: the Quest for Democracy|location= Bloomington|publisher= Indiana University Press|year= 1987}}
*{{cite book|editor-last = Nelson|editor-first=Harold D. |title= Liberia: A Country Study|location= Washington D.C.|publisher= U.S. Government Printing Office|year= 1985}}
*{{cite book|last = Shick|first= Tom W. |title= Behold the Promised Land: The History of Afro-American Settler Society in Nineteenth-Century Liberia|location= Baltimore|publisher= The Johns Hopkins University Press|year= 1980}}
*{{cite book|last = Smith|first= James Wesley |title= Sojourners in Search of Freedom: The Settlement of Liberia of Black Americans|location= Lanham|publisher= University Press of America|year=1987}}
*{{cite book|last = Staudenraus|first= P.J. |title= The African Colonization Movement, 1816 - 1865|location= New York| origyear = Columbia University Press, 1961|publisher= Octagon Books|year= 1980}}

==External links==
* [http://thelouvertureproject.org/index.php?title=The_Struggle_for_the_Recognition_of_Haiti_and_Liberia_as_Independent_Republics The Struggle for the Recognition of Haiti and Liberia as Independent Republics] - From Haitian history Wiki
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09216a.htm Liberia] - Entry on Liberia from the 1907 '''Catholic Encyclopedia'''
*Article Liberia, from Catholic Encyclopedia, 1910 edition, from EB 1911
*[http://www.historyofnations.net/africa/liberia.html History of Liberia] - Offers a history of Liberia from 1461 to the present.
*[http://www.liberian.org The Liberian Post] - Extensive background information with links and photos.
*[http://library.lawschool.cornell.edu/WhatWeHave/SpecialCollections/LiberianLaw/index.cfm Liberian Law] - Cornell Law Library - contains digitized documents dealing with the creation of the nation of Liberia and the laws enacted at its foundation, as well as extensive links for further research
*[http://rulers.org/rull.html Rulers]
*[http://kaery.ellone-loire.net/obsidian/westafr.html#Liberia West Africa]
*[http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/african/afam002.html U.S. Library of Congress exhibition, based on materials deposited by the ACS.]
*[http://www.africawithin.com/tour/liberia/hist_gov1.htm A View of Liberian History and Government]: a critical view of the ACS
*[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/li.html CIA World Factbook : Liberia]
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/country_profiles/1043500.stm BBC Country Profile : Liberia]
*[http://www.uiowa.edu/~africart/toc/countries/Liberia.html Art and Life in Africa : Liberia]
*[http://timelines.ws/countries/LIBERIA.HTML Timeline Liberia]
*[http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/gmdhtml/libhtml/liberia.html History of Liberia: a Timeline, from Library of Congress]
*[http://www.politicalresources.net/liberia.htm Political Resources on the Net: Liberia]
*[http://www.hri.ca/fortherecord2002/vol2/liberia.htm For the Record: Liberia, from UN Human Rights System]
*{{gutenberg|no=22118|name=Official Report of the Niger Valley Exploring Party}} by [[Martin Delany]]

{{Liberia topics}}
{{History of Africa}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Liberia}}
[[Category:History of Liberia| ]]

[[ar:تاريخ ليبيريا]]
[[ca:Història de Libèria]]
[[de:Geschichte Liberias]]
[[es:Historia de Liberia]]
[[fr:Histoire du Liberia]]
[[ko:라이베리아의 역사]]
[[io:Historio di Liberia]]
[[it:Storia della Liberia]]
[[he:היסטוריה של ליבריה]]
[[lt:Liberijos istorija]]
[[mk:Историја на Либерија]]
[[pl:Historia Liberii]]
[[pt:História da Libéria]]
[[ru:История Либерии]]
[[fi:Liberian historia]]
[[uk:Історія Ліберії]]
[[vec:Storia de la Liberia]]
[[yo:Ìtàn ilẹ̀ Làìbéríà]]
[[zh:利比里亚历史]]</text>
      <sha1>g8s9lrtpg4tvohius15ha0t345smxzk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
