<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Uganda</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>56921</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519496282</id>
      <parentid>516443957</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T02:05:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[io:Historio di Uganda]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9337">{{refimprove|date=May 2011}}
{{History of Uganda}}
The '''history of Uganda''' comprises the history of the [[Geography of Uganda|territory of present-day Uganda]] in [[East Africa]] and the peoples inhabiting the region.

== Early history of Uganda ==
{{See|Early history of Uganda}}

== Uganda Protectorate (1894-1962) ==
{{See|Uganda Protectorate}}

==Early independent Uganda (1962-71)==
{{main|History of Uganda (1962–71)}}
Britain granted independence to Uganda in 1962, and the first elections were held on 1 March 1961. [[Benedicto Kiwanuka]] of the Democratic Party became the first Chief Minister. Uganda became a republic the following year, maintaining its [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] membership. 

In succeeding years, supporters of a centralized state vied with those in favor of a loose federation and a strong role for tribally-based local kingdoms. Political maneuvering climaxed in February 1966, when Prime Minister [[Milton Obote]] suspended the constitution and assumed all government powers, removing the positions of president and vice president. In September 1967, a new constitution proclaimed Uganda a republic, gave the president even greater powers, and abolished the traditional kingdoms.

== Uganda under Idi Amin (1971–79)==
{{main|History of Uganda (1971–79)}}
On 25 January 1971, Obote's government was ousted in a [[1971 Ugandan coup d'état|military coup]] led by armed forces commander [[Idi Amin Dada]]. Amin declared himself 'president,' dissolved the parliament, and amended the constitution to give himself absolute power. 

Idi Amin's six-year rule produced economic decline, social disintegration, and massive human rights violations. The [[Acholi people|Acholi]] and [[Langi people|Langi]] ethnic groups were particular objects of Amin's political persecution because they had supported Obote and made up a large part of the army. In 1978, the [[International Commission of Jurists]] estimated that more than 100,000 Ugandans had been murdered during Amin's reign of terror; some authorities place the figure as high as 300,000—a statistic cited at the end of the 2006 movie [[The Last King of Scotland]], which chronicled part of Amin's dictatorship.

A border altercation involving Ugandan exiles who had a camp close to the Ugandan border of Mutukula resulted into an attack by the Uganda army into Tanzania.  In October 1978, Tanzanian armed forces repulsed an incursion by Amin's troops into Tanzanian territory. The Tanzanian army, backed by [[Uganda]]n exiles, waged [[Ugandan–Tanzanian War|a war of liberation against Amin's troops]] and the [[Libya]]n soldiers sent to help him. On 11 April 1979 [[Kampala]] was captured and Amin fled with his remaining forces to [[Libya]].

==Uganda since 1979==
{{main|History of Uganda (1979–present)}}
After Amin' removal, the Uganda National Liberation Front formed an interim government with [[Yusuf Lule]] as president and [[Jeremiah Lucas Opira]] as the Secretary General of the UNLF. This government adopted a ministerial system of administration and created a quasi-parliamentary organ known as the National Consultative Commission (NCC). The NCC and the Lule cabinet reflected widely differing political views. In June 1979, following a dispute over the extent of presidential powers, the NCC replaced Lule with [[Godfrey Binaisa]]. In a continuing dispute over the powers of the interim presidency, Binaisa was removed in May 1980. Thereafter, Uganda was ruled by a military commission chaired by [[Paulo Muwanga]]. The December 1980 elections returned the UPC to power under the leadership of [[Milton Obote|President Milton Obote]], with Muwanga serving as vice president. Under Obote, the security forces had one of the world's worst human rights records. In their efforts to stamp out an insurgency led by [[Yoweri Museveni]]'s [[National Resistance Army]] (NRA), they laid waste to a substantial section of the country, especially in the Luwero area north of Kampala. 

Obote ruled until 27 July 1985, when an army brigade, composed mostly of ethnic Acholi troops and commanded by Lt. Gen. [[Bazilio Olara-Okello]], took Kampala and proclaimed a military government. Obote fled to exile in [[Zambia]]. The new regime, headed by former defense force commander Gen. [[Tito Okello]] (no relation to Lt. Gen. Olara-Okello), opened negotiations with Museveni's insurgent forces and pledged to improve respect for human rights, end tribal rivalry, and conduct free and fair elections. In the meantime, massive human rights violations continued as the Okello government carried out a brutal counterinsurgency in an attempt to destroy the NRA's support. 

[[Image:Acholiland, Uganda.png|thumb|right|300px|[[Acholiland]] in the north.]]
Negotiations between the Okello government and the NRA were conducted in [[Nairobi]] in the fall of 1985, with Kenyan President [[Daniel arap Moi]] seeking a cease-fire and a coalition government in Uganda. Although agreeing in late 1985 to a cease-fire, the NRA continued fighting, and seized Kampala and the country in late January 1986, forcing Okello's forces to flee north into [[Sudan]]. Museveni's forces organized a government with Museveni as president. 

Since assuming power, the government dominated by the political grouping created by Museveni and his followers, the [[National Resistance Movement]] (NRM or the &quot;Movement&quot;), has largely put an end to the human rights abuses of earlier governments, initiated substantial political liberalization and general press freedom, and instituted broad economic reforms after consultation with the International Monetary Fund (IMF), World Bank, and donor governments. 

In northern areas such as [[Acholiland]], there has been armed resistance against the government since 1986.  [[Acholi people|Acholi]] based rebel groups include the [[Uganda People's Democratic Army]] and the [[Holy Spirit Movement]].  Currently, the only remaining rebel group is the  [[Lord's Resistance Army]] headed by [[Joseph Kony]], which has carried out widespread abduction of children to serve as soldiers or sex slaves.

In 1996, Uganda was a key supporter of the overthrow of [[Zaire]]an President [[Mobutu Sese Seko]] in the [[First Congo War]] in favor of rebel leader [[Laurent-Désiré Kabila]].  Between 1998 and 2003, the Ugandan army was involved in the [[Second Congo War]] in the renamed [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] and the government continues to support rebel groups such as the [[Movement for the Liberation of Congo]] and some factions of the [[Rally for Congolese Democracy]].

In August 2005, Parliament voted to change the constitution to lift presidential term limits, allowing Museveni to run for a third term if he wishes to do so. In a [[Uganda multiparty referendum, 2005|referendum in July, 2005]], 92.5% supported restoring multiparty politics, thereby scrapping the no-party or &quot;movement&quot; system. [[Kizza Besigye]], Museveni's political rival, returned from exile in October 2005, and was a presidential candidate for the 2006 elections. In the same month, Milton Obote died in South Africa.  Museveni won the February 2006 presidential election.

In 2009, the [[Anti-Homosexuality Bill]] was proposed and under consideration.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc1&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/8308912.stm BBC News: Uganda MP urges death for gay sex]&lt;/ref&gt; It was proposed on 13 October 2009 by [[Member of Parliament]] [[David Bahati]] and would, if enacted, broaden the criminalization of homosexuality in Uganda, including introducing the death penalty for people who have previous convictions, who are [[HIV]]-positive, or who engage in sexual acts with those under 18,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.pinknews.co.uk/2009/10/15/ugandan-mp-proposes-that-gays-should-be-executed/|title= Ugandan MP proposes that gays should be executed|publisher= Pink News|first= Jessica|last= Geen|date= 15 October 2009|accessdate= 21 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; introducing [[extradition]] for those engaging in same-sex sexual relations outside Uganda, and penalising individuals, companies, media organizations, or NGOs who support [[LGBT]] rights.

==See also==
*[[Buganda]]
*[[History of Africa]]
*[[Luo (family of ethnic groups)|Luo History]]
*[[Politics of Uganda]]
*[[President of Uganda]]
*[[Prime Minister of Uganda]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*{{loc}} - [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/ugtoc.html Uganda]
*U.S. State Department [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2963.htm#history Background Note: Uganda]
*[http://www.africa.upenn.edu/NEH/uethnic.htm East Africa Living Encyclopedia], African Studies Center, University of Pennsylvania
*[http://www.bunyoro-kitara.com/history2.htm#The%20Babiito Origins of Bunyoro-Kitara Kings], Bunyoro-Kitara website
*{{cite|author=Phyllis Martin and Patrick O'Meara|title=Africa. 3rd edition|publisher=Indiana University Press|date=August 1995}}


{{Africa topic|History of}}
{{Uganda topics}}

[[Category:History of Uganda| ]]

[[de:Geschichte Ugandas]]
[[es:Historia de Uganda]]
[[fr:Histoire de l'Ouganda]]
[[io:Historio di Uganda]]
[[it:Storia dell'Uganda]]
[[he:היסטוריה של אוגנדה]]
[[pt:História de Uganda]]
[[ru:История Уганды]]
[[sv:Ugandas historia]]
[[uk:Історія Уганди]]
[[vec:Storia de l'Uganda]]
[[yo:Ìtàn ilẹ̀ Ùgándà]]</text>
      <sha1>jof12ud1adt75evje8z19l77cvajo75</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
