<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Historiography</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13276</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521902250</id>
      <parentid>521882585</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T22:57:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BG19bot</username>
        <id>14508071</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fix #86.  External link with two brackets.  Do [[Wikipedia:GENFIXES|general fixes]] and cleanup if needed using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8512)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="46058">{{see also|Historian}}

'''Historiography''' refers either to the study of the methodology and development of &quot;[[history]]&quot; (as a discipline), or to a body of historical work on a specialized topic. Scholars discuss historiography topically&amp;nbsp;– such as the &quot;historiography of [[Catholicism]]&quot;, the &quot;[[historiography of early Islam]]&quot;, or the &quot;[[Chinese historiography|historiography of China]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– as well as specific approaches and [[genre]]s, such as [[political history]] and [[social history]]. Beginning in the nineteenth century, with the ascent of [[academic history]], a corpus of historiographic literature developed.

The research interests of historians change over time, and in recent decades there has been a shift away from traditional diplomatic, economic and political history toward newer approaches, especially social and cultural studies. From 1975 to 1995, the proportion of professors of history in American universities identifying with social history rose from 31% to 41%, while the proportion of political historians fell from 40% to 30%.&lt;ref&gt;Diplomatic dropped from 5% to 3%, economic history from 7% to 5%, and cultural history grew from 14% to 16%. Based on full-time professors in U.S. history departments. Stephen H. Haber, David M. Kennedy, and Stephen D. Krasner, &quot;Brothers under the Skin: Diplomatic History and International Relations,&quot; ''International Security,'' Vol. 22, No. 1 (Summer, 1997), pp. 34–43 at p. 42 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2539326 online at JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;  In the history departments of British universities in 2007, of the 5,723 faculty members, 1,644 (29%)  identified themselves with [[social history]] while [[political history]] came next with 1,425 (25%).&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.history.ac.uk/ihr/Resources/Teachers/a27.html &quot;Teachers of History in the Universities of the UK 2007 – listed by research interest&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Jacob de Wit - Allegorie op het schrijven van de geschiedenis 1754.jpg|thumb|200px|Allegory on writing history by [[Jacob de Wit]] (1754). An almost naked [[Truth]] keeps an eye on the writer of history. [[Pallas Athena|Wisdom]] gives advice; with [[Ptolemy&amp;nbsp;I Soter]], a master in [[objectivity]] in his book on [[Alexander the Great]], below in profile.]]

In the [[early modern period]], the term ''historiography'' tended to be used in a more basic sense, to mean simply &quot;the writing of history&quot;. ''Historiographer'' therefore meant &quot;[[historian]]&quot;, and it is in this sense that certain [[Official history|official historians]] were given the title &quot;Historiographer Royal&quot;, in [[Rikshistoriograf|Sweden]] (from 1618), [[Historiographer Royal (England)|England]] (from 1660), and [[Historiographer Royal|Scotland]] (from 1681). The Scottish post is still in existence.

==Defining historiography==
Furay and Salevouris (1988) define historiography as &quot;the study of the way history has been and is written — the history of historical writing... When you study 'historiography' you do not study the events of the past directly, but the changing interpretations of those events in the works of individual historians.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;(''The Methods and Skills of History: A Practical Guide'', 1988, p. 223, ISBN 0-88295-982-4)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Narrative===
According to [[Lawrence Stone]], narrative has traditionally been the main rhetorical device used by historians. In 1979, at a time when the new [[Social History]] was demanding a social-science model of analysis, Stone detected a move back toward the narrative. Stone defined narrative as follows: it is organized chronologically; it is focused on a single coherent story; it is descriptive rather than analytical; it is concerned with people not abstract circumstances; and it deals with the particular and specific rather than the collective and statistical. He reported that, &quot;More and more of the 'new historians' are now trying to discover what was going on inside people's heads in the past, and what it was like to live in the past, questions which inevitably lead back to the use of narrative.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence Stone, &quot;The Revival of Narrative: Reflections on a New Old History,&quot; ''Past and Present'' 85 (Nov 1979) pp 3-24, quote on p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians committed to a social science approach, however, have criticized the narrowness of narrative and its preference for anecdote over analysis, and its use of clever examples rather than statistically verified empirical regularities.&lt;ref&gt;J. Morgan Kousser, “The Revivalism of Narrative: A Response to Recent Criticisms of Quantitative History,” ''Social Science History'' vol 8, no. 2 (Spring 1984): 133–49; Eric H. Monkkonen, “The Dangers of Synthesis,” ''American Historical Review'' 91, no. 5 (December 1986): 1146–57.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Topics studied==
Some of the common topics in historiography are:
#Reliability of the sources used, in terms of authorship, credibility of the author, and the authenticity or corruption of the text.  (See also [[source criticism]]).
#Historiographical tradition or framework. Every historian uses one (or more) historiographical traditions, for example [[Marxist]], [[Annales School]], &quot;total history&quot;, or [[political history]].
#[[morality|Moral]] issues, guilt assignment, and praise assignment
#[[historical revisionism|Revisionism]] versus [[Orthodoxy|orthodox]] interpretations
#Historical [[metanarratives]]

==The history of written history==
Understanding the past appears to be a universal human need, and the telling of history has emerged independently in civilisations around the world. What constitutes history is a philosophical question (see [[philosophy of history]]). The earliest [[Chronology|chronologies]] date back to [[Mesopotamia]] and [[ancient Egypt]], though no historical writers in these early civilizations were known by name. For the purposes of this article, history is taken to mean written history recorded in a narrative format for the purpose of informing future generations about events. Some experts have advised against the tendency to extrapolate trends for historical patterns that do not align with expectations about the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://marketing.wharton.upenn.edu/ideas/pdf/armstrong2/causal.pdf | title = Causal Forces: Structuring Knowledge for Time-series Extrapolation | author = J. Scott Armstrong and Fred Collopy | journal = Journal of Forecasting | volume = 12 | pages = 103–115 | year = 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hellenic world===
[[File:Thucydides Manuscript.jpg|thumb|upright|Reproduction of part of a tenth-century copy of [[Thucydides]]'s ''[[History of the Peloponnesian War]]''.]]

{{main|Greek historiography}}

The earliest known systematic historical thought emerged in [[ancient Greece]], a development which would be an important influence on the writing of history elsewhere around [[History of the Mediterranean region|the Mediterranean]] region. [[Greeks|Greek]] historians greatly contributed to the development of historical methodology. The earliest known critical historical works were ''[[Histories (Herodotus)|The Histories]]'', composed by [[Herodotus|Herodotus of Halicarnassus]] (484 BC–c.&amp;nbsp;425 BC) who later became known as the &quot;father of history&quot; (Cicero). Herodotus attempted to distinguish between more and less reliable accounts, and personally conducted research by travelling extensively, giving written accounts of various [[Mediterranean Basin|Mediterranean]] cultures. Although Herodotus' overall emphasis lay on the actions and characters of men, he also attributed an important role to divinity in the determination of historical events.

The generation following Herodotus witnessed a spate of local histories of the individual city-states (''[[polis|poleis]]''), written by the first of the [[Local history|local historians]] who employed the written archives of city and sanctuary. [[Dionysius of Halicarnassus]] characterized these historians as the forerunners of Thucydides,&lt;ref&gt;Dionysius, ''On Thucydides'', 5.&lt;/ref&gt; and these local histories continued to be written into Late Antiquity, as long as the city-states survived. Two early figures stand out: [[Hippias of Elis]], who produced the lists of winners in the Olympic Games that provided the basic chronological framework as long as the pagan classical tradition lasted, and [[Hellanicus of Lesbos]], who compiled more than two dozen histories from civic records, all of them now lost.

[[Thucydides]] largely eliminated divine causality in his account of the war between Athens and Sparta, establishing a rationalistic element which set a precedent for subsequent Western historical writings. He was also the first to distinguish between cause and immediate origins of an event, while his successor [[Xenophon]] (c.&amp;nbsp;431–355&amp;nbsp;BC) introduced autobiographical elements and character studies in his [[Anabasis (Xenophon)|Anabasis]].

The proverbial [[Philippic]] attacks of the Athenian orator [[Demosthenes]] (384–322&amp;nbsp;BC) on [[Philip&amp;nbsp;II of Macedon]] marked the height of ancient political agitation. The now lost history of Alexander's campaigns by the [[diadoch]] [[Ptolemy&amp;nbsp;I]] (367–283&amp;nbsp;BC) may represent the first historical work composed by a ruler. [[Polybius]] (c.&amp;nbsp;203–120 BC) wrote on the rise of Rome to world prominence, and attempted to harmonize the Greek and Roman points of view.

The [[Chaldea]]n priest [[Berossus]] (fl. 3rd century){{Clarify|date=September 2009}}&lt;!--AD or BC?--&gt; composed a Greek-language ''History of [[Babylonia]]'' for the [[Seleucid]] king [[Antiochus&amp;nbsp;I]], combining [[Hellenistic]] methods of historiography and [[Mesopotamia]]n accounts to form a unique composite. Reports exist of other near-eastern histories, such as that of the Phoenician historian [[Sanchuniathon]]; but he is considered semi-legendary and writings attributed to him are fragmentary, known only through the later historians [[Philo of Byblos]] and [[Eusebius]], who asserted that he wrote before even the [[Trojan war]].

===Roman world===
{{Main|Roman historiography}}

The Romans adopted the Greek tradition, writing at first in Greek, but eventually chronicling their history in a freshly non-Greek language.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} While early Roman works were still written in Greek, the ''Origines'', composed by the Roman statesman [[Cato the Elder]] (234–149 BC), was written in Latin, in a conscious effort to counteract Greek cultural influence. It marked the beginning of Latin historical writings. Hailed for its lucid style, [[Julius Caesar]]'s (100 BC–44 BC) ''[[Commentarii de Bello Gallico|Bellum Gallicum]]'' exemplifies autobiographical war coverage. The politician and orator [[Cicero]] (106–43 BC) introduced rhetorical elements in his political writings.

[[Strabo]] (63 BC–c.&amp;nbsp;AD 24) was an important exponent of the Greco-Roman tradition of combining geography with history, presenting a descriptive history of peoples and places known to his era. [[Livy]] (59 BC–AD&amp;nbsp;17) records the rise of [[Roman Empire|Rome]] from [[city-state]] to [[empire]]. His speculation about what would have happened if [[Alexander the Great]] had marched against Rome represents the first known instance of [[alternate history]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mcadams.posc.mu.edu/txt/ah/Livy/Livy09.html |title=Livy's History of Rome: Book 9 |publisher=Mcadams.posc.mu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Biography, although popular throughout antiquity, was introduced as a branch of history by the works of [[Plutarch]] (c.&amp;nbsp;46–127) and [[Suetonius]] (c.&amp;nbsp;69–after 130) who described the deeds and characters of ancient personalities, stressing their human side. [[Tacitus]] (c.&amp;nbsp;56–c.&amp;nbsp;117) denounces Roman immorality by praising [[Germanic peoples|German]] virtues, elaborating on the [[topos]] of the [[Noble savage]].

===China===
[[File:Shiji.jpg|upright|thumb|First page of the ''[[Shiji]]''.]]
{{Main|Chinese historiography}}

In [[China]], the ''[[Classic of History]]'' is one of the [[Five Classics]] of [[Chinese classic texts]] and one of the earliest narratives of China.  The ''[[Spring and Autumn Annals]]'', the official chronicle of the State of Lu covering the period from 722 BC to 481 BC, is among the earliest surviving Chinese historical texts to be arranged on [[Annals|annalistic]] principles. It is traditionally attributed to [[Confucius]]. The ''[[Zuo Zhuan]]'', attributed to [[Zuo Qiuming]] in the 5th&amp;nbsp;century BC, is the earliest Chinese work of narrative history and covers the period from 722 BC to 468&amp;nbsp;BC. ''[[Zhan Guo Ce]]'' was a renowned ancient Chinese historical compilation of sporadic materials on the [[Warring States Period]] compiled between the 3rd and 1st centuries BC.

[[Sima Qian]] (around 100 BC) was the first in China to lay the groundwork for professional historical writing. His written work was the ''[[Shiji]]'' (''[[Records of the Grand Historian]]''), a monumental lifelong achievement in literature. Its scope extends as far back as the 16th century BC, and it includes many treatises on specific subjects and individual biographies of prominent people, and also explores the lives and deeds of commoners, both contemporary and those of previous eras. His work influenced every subsequent author of history in China, including the prestigious Ban family of the [[Eastern Han Dynasty]] era.

Traditional Chinese historiography describes history in terms of dynastic cycles. In this view, each new dynasty is founded by a morally righteous founder. Over time, the dynasty becomes morally corrupt and dissolute. Eventually, the dynasty becomes so weak as to allow its replacement by a new dynasty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jörn Rüsen|title=Time and History: The Variety of Cultures|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=SvGyzu-nLaUC&amp;pg=PA54|year=2007|publisher=Berghahn Books|isbn=978-1-84545-349-7|pages=54–55}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christendom===
{{See also|Christendom}}

Christian historiography began early, perhaps as early as [[Luke-Acts]], which is the [[primary source]] for the [[Apostolic Age]], though its [[Historical reliability of the Acts of the Apostles|historical reliability is disputed]]. In the [[Early Christianity|first Christian centuries]], the [[Development of the New Testament canon|New Testament canon was developed]]. The [[Early centers of Christianity|growth of Christianity]] and its enhanced status in the Roman Empire after [[Constantine I and Christianity|Constantine&amp;nbsp;I]] (see [[State church of the Roman Empire]]) led to the development of a distinct Christian historiography, influenced by both [[Christian theology]] and the nature of the [[Christian Bible]], encompassing new areas of study and views of history.  The central role of the Bible in Christianity is reflected in the preference of Christian historians for written sources, compared to the classical historians' preference for oral sources and is also reflected in the inclusion of politically unimportant people. Christian historians also focused on development of religion and society.  This can be seen in the extensive inclusion of written sources in the ''[[Church History (Eusebius)|Ecclesiastical History]]'' written by [[Eusebius of Caesarea]] around 324 and in the subjects it covers.&lt;ref name = &quot;sxixkf&quot;&gt;[http://www.cuw.edu/Academics/programs/history/historiography.html ''Historiography''], Concordia University Wisconsin , retrieved on 2 November 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Christian theology]] considered time as linear, progressing according to divine plan.  As God's plan encompassed everyone, Christian histories in this period had a universal approach. For example, Christian writers often included summaries of important historical events prior to the period covered by the work.&lt;ref&gt;Warren, John (1998). ''The past and its presenters: an introduction to issues in historiography'', Hodder &amp; Stoughton, ISBN 0-340-67934-4, pp. 67–68.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Beda Petersburgiensis f3v.jpg|right|upright|thumb|A page of [[Bede]]'s ''Ecclesiastical History of the English People'']]

Writing history was popular among Christian monks and clergy in the [[Middle Ages]]. They wrote about the history of Jesus Christ, that of the Church and that of their patrons, the dynastic history of the local rulers.  In the [[early medieval|Early Middle Ages]] historical writing often took the form of [[annals]] or [[chronicle]]s recording events year by year, but this style tended to hamper the analysis of events and causes.&lt;ref&gt;Warren, John (1998). ''The past and its presenters: an introduction to issues in historiography'', Hodder &amp; Stoughton, ISBN 0-340-67934-4, pp. 78–79.&lt;/ref&gt; An example of this type of writing is the [[Anglo-Saxon Chronicle]]s, which were the work of several different writers: it was started during the reign of [[Alfred the Great]] in the late 9th&amp;nbsp;century, but one copy was still being updated in 1154.  Some writers in the period did construct a more [[narrative]] form of history. These included [[Gregory of Tours]], and more successfully [[Bede]] who wrote both [[secular]] and [[ecclesiastical]] history and is known for writing the ''[[Ecclesiastical History of the English People]]''.&lt;ref name = &quot;sxixkf&quot;/&gt;

During the [[Renaissance]], history was written about states or nations. The study of history changed during the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] and [[Romanticism]]. [[Voltaire]] described the history of certain ages that he considered important, rather than describing events in chronological order. History became an independent discipline. It was not called ''philosophia historiae'' anymore, but merely history (''historia'').

===Islamic world===
{{Main|Historiography of early Islam|Muqaddimah}}
{{See also|Muslim historians|Prophetic biography|Biographical evaluation|Science of hadith}}

[[Muslim]] historical writings first began to develop in the 7th century, with the reconstruction of the Prophet [[Muhammad]]'s life in the centuries following his death. With numerous conflicting narratives regarding Muhammad and his [[Sahaba|companions]] from various sources, it was necessary to verify which sources were more reliable. In order to evaluate these sources, various methodologies were developed, such as the &quot;[[Ilm ar-Rijal|science of biography]]&quot;, &quot;[[science of hadith]]&quot; and &quot;[[Isnad]]&quot; (chain of transmission). These methodologies were later applied to other historical figures in the [[Islamic Golden Age|Islamic civilization]]. Famous historians in this tradition include [[Urwah ibn Zubayr|Urwah]] (d.&amp;nbsp;712), [[Wahb ibn Munabbih]] (d.&amp;nbsp;728), [[Ibn Ishaq]] (d.&amp;nbsp;761), [[al-Waqidi]] (745–822), [[Ibn Hisham]] (d.&amp;nbsp;834), [[Muhammad al-Bukhari]] (810–870) and [[Ibn Hajar Asqalani|Ibn Hajar]] (1372–1449).

Historians of the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic world]] also developed an interest in [[world history]]. The historian [[Muhammad ibn Jarir al-Tabari]] (838–923) is known for writing a detailed and comprehensive chronicle of [[History of the Mediterranean region|Mediterranean]] and [[History of the Middle East|Middle Eastern]] history in his ''[[History of the Prophets and Kings]]'' in 915. Until the 10th&amp;nbsp;century, history most often meant political and military history, but this was not so with [[Persian people|Persian]] historian [[Abu-Rayhan Biruni|Biruni]] (973–1048). In his ''Kitab fi Tahqiq ma l'il-Hind'' (''Researches on India'') he did not record political and military history in any detail, but wrote more on [[History of India|India]]'s [[Culture of India|cultural]], [[History of Indian science and technology|scientific]], social and [[Religion in India|religious]] history. He expanded on his idea of history in another work, ''The Chronology of the Ancient Nations''.&lt;ref&gt;M. S. Khan (1976). &quot;al-Biruni and the Political History of India&quot;, ''Oriens'' '''25''', pp. 86–115.&lt;/ref&gt; Biruni is considered the father of [[Indology]] for his detailed studies on [[History of India|Indian history]].&lt;ref&gt;Zafarul-Islam Khan, [http://milligazette.com/Archives/15-1-2000/Art5.htm At The {{sic|Threshhold}} Of A New Millennium – II], ''The Milli Gazette''.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sociology in medieval Islam#Archeology|Archaeology in the Middle East]] began with the study of the [[ancient Near East]] by Muslim historians in the medieval [[Muslim world|Islamic world]] who developed an interest in learning about pre-Islamic cultures. In particular, they most often concentrated on the archaeology and history of [[pre-Islamic Arabia]], [[Mesopotamia]] and [[ancient Egypt]]. In [[Egyptology]], the first known attempts at deciphering [[Egyptian hieroglyphs]] were made in [[History of Arab Egypt|Islamic Egypt]] by [[Dhul-Nun al-Misri]] and [[Ibn Wahshiyya]] in the 9th century, who were able to at least partly understand what was written in the ancient Egyptian hieroglyphs, by relating them to the contemporary [[Coptic language]] used by [[Copt]]ic priests in their time.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} Muslim historians such as Abu al-Hassan al-Hamadani of [[Yemen]] (d. 945), [[Abd al-Latif al-Baghdadi (medieval writer)|Abdul Latif al-Baghdadi]] (1162–1231) and Al-Idrisi of [[Egypt]] (d. 1251) developed elaborate archaeological [[Scientific method|methods]] which they employed in their excavations and research of ancient archaeological sites.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Egyptology: The Missing Millennium : Ancient Egypt in Medieval Arabic Writings|first=Okasha|last=El Daly|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2004|isbn=1-84472-063-2|pages=45–7|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Ibn Khaldoun.jpg|thumb|Tunisian statue of [[Ibn Khaldun]], pioneer of historiography, [[cultural history]], and the [[philosophy of history]].]]

Islamic historical writing eventually culminated in the works of the [[Arab]] Muslim historian and historiographer [[Ibn Khaldun]] (1332–1406), who published his historiographical studies in the ''[[Muqaddimah]]'' (translated as ''Prolegomena'') and ''Kitab al-I'bar'' (''Book of Advice'').&lt;ref&gt;S. Ahmed (1999). ''A Dictionary of Muslim Names''. C. Hurst &amp; Co. Publishers. ISBN 1-85065-356-9.&lt;/ref&gt; Among many other things, his ''Muqaddimah'' laid the groundwork for the observation of the roles of the state, in history,&lt;ref name=Mowlana&gt;H. Mowlana (2001). &quot;Information in the Arab World&quot;, ''Cooperation South Journal'' '''1'''.&lt;/ref&gt; and he discussed the rise and fall of [[civilization]]s. He also developed a method for the study of history, and is thus considered to be the founder of Arab historiography,&lt;ref name=&quot;Salahuddin Ahmed 1999&quot;&gt;Salahuddin Ahmed (1999). ''A Dictionary of Muslim Names''. C. Hurst &amp; Co. Publishers. ISBN 1-85065-356-9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Enan&gt;{{Cite book|title=Ibn Khaldun: His Life and Works|first=Muhammed Abdullah|last=Enan|publisher=[[The Other Press]]|year=2007|isbn=983-9541-53-6|page=v|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gates&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Spread of Ibn Khaldun's Ideas on Climate and Culture|author=Warren E. Gates|journal=[[Journal of the History of Ideas]]|volume=28|issue=3|date=July–September 1967|pages=415–422 [415]|publisher=[[University of Pennsylvania Press]]|jstor=2708627|doi=10.2307/2708627|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; or the &quot;father of the [[philosophy of history]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=Akhtar&gt;Dr. S. W. Akhtar (1997). &quot;The Islamic Concept of Knowledge&quot;, ''Al-Tawhid: A Quarterly Journal of Islamic Thought &amp; Culture'' '''12''' (3).&lt;/ref&gt; In the preface to the ''Muqaddimah'', Ibn Khaldun warned of seven mistakes that he thought historians often committed. In this criticism, he approached the past as strange and in need of interpretation. The originality of Ibn Khaldun was to claim that the cultural differences of another age must govern the evaluation of relevant historical material, to distinguish the principles according to which it might be possible to attempt the evaluation, and lastly, to consider the need for experience, in addition to rational principles, in order to assess a culture of the past. Ibn Khaldun often criticized &quot;idle superstition and uncritical acceptance of historical data.&quot; As a result, he introduced a method to the study of history, which was considered something &quot;new to his age&quot;, and he often referred to it as his &quot;new science&quot;, now associated with historiography.&lt;ref&gt;Ibn Khaldun, Franz Rosenthal, N. J. Dawood (1967), ''The Muqaddimah: An Introduction to History'', p. x, [[Princeton University Press]], ISBN 0-691-01754-9.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Muqaddimah'' is also the earliest known work to critically examine [[military history]], criticizing certain accounts of historical battles that appear to be exaggerated, and takes [[military logistics]] into account when questioning the exaggerated sizes of historical armies reported in earlier sources.&lt;ref&gt;Ibn Khaldun, [[Franz Rosenthal]], N. J. Dawood (1967), ''The Muqaddimah: An Introduction to History'', pp. 11–2, [[Princeton University Press]], ISBN 0-691-01754-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern era===
Modern historiography emerged in 19th century German universities, where [[Leopold von Ranke]] revolutionized historiography with his seminars and critical approach; he emphasized politics and diplomacy, dropping the social and cultural themes Voltaire had highlighted.&lt;ref&gt;E. Sreedharan, ''A textbook of historiography, 500&amp;nbsp;BC to AD&amp;nbsp;2000'' (2004) p 185&lt;/ref&gt;  Sources had to be hard, not speculations and rationalizations. His credo was to write history the way it was. He insisted on primary sources with proven authenticity. [[Hegel]] and [[Karl Marx|Marx]] introduced the concept of spirit and dialectical materialism, respectively, into the study of world historical development. Former historians had focused on cyclical events of the rise and decline of rulers and nations. Process of [[nationalization of history]], as part of [[Romantic nationalism|national revival]]s in 19th century, resulted with separation of &quot;one's own&quot; history from common [[universal history]] by such way of perceiving, understanding and treating the past that constructed history as history of a nation.&lt;ref name = &quot;laboratory&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
| url         = http://books.google.com/?id=f52rawP96lYC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;lpg=PA39&amp;dq=%22nationalisation+of+history%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22nationalisation%20of%20history%22&amp;f=false
| title       = A Laboratory of Transnational History Ukraine and recent Ukrainian historiography
| accessdate  = October 18, 2010
| author      = Georgiy Kasianov, Philipp Terr
| pages       = 7
| quote       = This essay deals with, what I call, &quot;nationalized history&quot;, meaning a way of perceiving, understanding and treating the past that requires separation of &quot;one's own&quot; history from &quot;common&quot; history and its construction as history of a nation.
| isbn         = 978-1-84545-621-4
| date         = 2010-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; A new discipline, [[sociology]], emerged in the late 19th century and analyzed and compared these perspectives on a larger scale.

The French [[Annales School]] radically changed the focus of historical research in France during the 20th century. [[Fernand Braudel]] wanted history to become more scientific and less subjective, and demanded more quantitative evidence. Furthermore, he introduced a socio-economic and geographic framework to historical questions. Other French historians, like [[Philippe Ariès]] and [[Michel Foucault]], described the history of everyday topics such as death and sexuality. Carlo Ginzburg and Natalie Zemon Davis pioneered the genre of historical writing sometimes known as &quot;microhistory,&quot; which attempted to understand the mentalities and decisions of individuals - mostly peasants - within their limited milieu using contracts, court documents and oral histories.

====Foundation of important historical journals====
The historical journal, a forum where academic historians could exchange ideas and publish newly discovered information, came into being in the 19th century. The early journals were similar to those for the physical sciences, and were seen as a means for history to become more professional. Journals also helped historians to establish various historiographical approaches, the most notable example of which was ''Annales. Économies. Sociétés. Civilisations.'', a publication instrumental in establishing the [[Annales School]].

Some historical journals are as follows:

*1840 ''[[Historisk tidsskrift (Denmark)]]''
*1859 ''[[Historische Zeitschrift]]'' (Germany)
*1866 ''Archivum historicum'', later ''Historiallinen arkisto'' (Finland, published in Finnish)
*1867 ''Századok'' (Hungary)
*1871 ''[[Historisk tidsskrift (Norway)]]''
*1876 ''Revue Historique'' (France)
*1881 ''[[Svenska Historiska Föreningen|Historisk tidskrift]]'' (Sweden)
*1886 ''[[English Historical Review]]'' (England)
*1892 ''[[William and Mary Quarterly]]'' (USA)
*1894 ''Ons Hémecht'' (Luxembourg)
*1895 ''[[American Historical Review]]'' (USA)
*1914 ''[[Mississippi Valley Historical Review]]'' (renamed in 1964 the ''[[Journal of American History]]'') (USA)	
*1916 ''[[The Journal of Negro History]]''
*1916 ''Historisk Tidskrift för Finland'' (Finland, published in Swedish)
*1918 ''Hispanic American historical review''
*1928 ''[[Scandia (journal)|Scandia]]'' (Sweden)
*1929 ''[[Annales School|Annales. Économies. Sociétés. Civilisations]]''
*1941 ''[[The Journal of Economic History]]''
*1952 ''[[Past &amp; Present|Past &amp; present: a journal of historical studies]]'' (Great Britain)
*1953 ''Vierteljahrshefte für Zeitgeschichte'' (Germany)	
*1956 ''Journal of the Historical Society of Nigeria'' (Nigeria)	
*1960 ''Journal of African History'' (Cambridge)		
*1960 ''[[Technology and Culture|Technology and culture: the international quarterly of the Society for the History of Technology]]'' (USA)
*1967 ''[[The Journal of Social History]]''
*1969 ''[[Journal of Interdisciplinary History]]''
*1975 ''Geschichte und Gesellschaft. Zeitschrift für historische Sozialwissenschaft'' (Germany)
*1976 ''Journal of Family History''
*1978 ''[[The Public Historian]]''
*1982 ''Storia della Storiografia — History of Historiography — Histoire de l'Historiographie — Geschichte der Geschichtsschreibung''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cisi.unito.it/stor/home.htm |title=Unito.it |publisher=Cisi.unito.it |date= |accessdate=2010-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1982 ''[[Subaltern Studies]]'' ([[Oxford University Press]])	
*1986 ''Zeitschrift für Sozialgeschichte des 20. und 21. Jahrhunderts'', new title since 2003: ''[http://www.stiftung-sozialgeschichte.de/ Sozial.Geschichte. Zeitschrift für historische Analyse des 20. und 21. Jahrhunderts]'' (Germany)
*1990 ''Gender and history''
*1990 ''[[Journal of World History]]''
*1990 ''L'Homme. Zeitschrift für feministische Geschichtswissenschaft''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.univie.ac.at/Geschichte/LHOMME/ |title=Univie.ac.at |publisher=Univie.ac.at |date= |accessdate=2010-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Austria)	
*1990 ''Österreichische Zeitschrift für Geschichtswissenschaften'' (ÖZG)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.univie.ac.at/Wirtschaftsgeschichte/OeZG/ |title=Univie.ac.at |publisher=Univie.ac.at |date= |accessdate=2010-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1992 ''Women's History Review''
*1993 ''Historische Anthropologie''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historische-anthropologie.uni-goettingen.de/ |title=Uni-Goettingen.de |publisher=Historische-anthropologie.uni-goettingen.de |date=2010-01-09 |accessdate=2010-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Approaches to history==
How a historian approaches historical events is one of the most important decisions within historiography. It is commonly recognised by historians that, in themselves, individual historical facts dealing with names, dates and places are not particularly meaningful. Such facts will only become useful when assembled with other historical evidence, and the process of assembling this evidence is understood as a particular historiographical approach.

The most influential historiographical approaches are:

* [[Comparative history]]
* [[Cultural history]]
* [[Diplomatic history]]
* [[Economic history]]
* [[Environmental history]], a relatively new field
* [[Ethnohistory]]
* [[Family history]]
* [[Feminist history]]
* [[History of Religion]] and [[Church history|Church History]]; the history of theology is usually handled under [[Theology]]
* [[Intellectual History]] and [[History of ideas]]
* [[Labor history (discipline)|Labor history]]
* [[History of Latin America|Latin American History]]
* [[Local History]] and  [[Microhistory]]
* [[Marxist historiography]] and [[Historical materialism]]
* [[Military history]], including naval and air
* [[Oral history]]
* [[Political history]]
* [[Public history]], especially museums and historic preservation
* [[Quantitative history]], [[Cliometrics]] (in economic history); [[Prosopography]] using statistics to study biographies
* [[Shared historical authority]]
* [[Social history]] and [[People's history|History from below]]; along with the French version the [[Annales School]] and the German [[Bielefeld School]]
* [[Women's history]] and [[Gender history]]
* [[World history]] and [[Universal history]]

Scholars typically specialize in a particular theme and region. see:
* [[Dark Ages (historiography)]]
* [[Historiography of the British Empire]]
* [[Historiography of the causes of World War I]]
* [[Historiography of China]]
* [[Historiography of the Cold War]]
* [[Historiography of the Crusades]]
* [[Historiography of early Islam]]
* [[Historiography of feudalism#Historiography|Historiography of feudalism]]
* [[Historiography and nationalism]]
* [[Historiography of the French Revolution]]
* [[Historiography of science]]
* [[Historiography of Switzerland]]
* [[Historiography of the United States]]
* [[Historiography of World War II]]
* [[Soviet historiography]]

===Related fields===
Important related fields include:

* [[Antiquarian]]ism
* [[Genealogy]]
* [[Numismatics]]
* [[Paleography]]
* [[Philosophy of history]]
* [[Pseudohistory]], that is, false history

==See also==
* [[Auxiliary sciences of history]]
* [[Annales School]]
*[[Atlantic history]]
* [[Bielefeld School]]
* [[Historical method]]
** [[Primary source]] — documents, correspondence, diaries
*** [[Secondary source]] — interpretations, written history
**** [[Tertiary source]] — textbooks and encyclopedias
* [[v:Topic:Historiography|Historiography at Wikiversity]], where it is part of the [[v:School:History|School of History]]
* [[List of historians]]
** [[List of historians by area of study]]
* [[Popular history]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==

===Theory ===
* Joyce Appleby, Lynn Hunt &amp; Margaret Jacob, ''Telling the Truth About History''. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1994.
* Michael Bentley, ''Modern Historiography: An Introduction'', 1999 ISBN 0-415-20267-1
* [[Marc Bloch]], ''The Historian's Craft'' [1940]
* [[Peter Burke]], ''History and Social Theory'', Polity Press, Oxford, 1992
* [[David Cannadine]] (editor), ''What is History Now'', Palgrave Macmillan, 2002
* [[E. H. Carr]], ''[[What is History?]]'' 1961, ISBN 0-394-70391-X
* [[R.G. Collingwood]], ''The Idea of History'', 1936, ISBN 0-19-285306-6
* [[Geoffrey Elton]], ''The Practice of History'', 1969, ISBN 0-631-22980-9
* [[Richard J. Evans]] ''In Defence of History'', 1997, ISBN 1-86207-104-7
* [[David Hackett Fischer]], ''Historians' Fallacies: Towards a Logic of Historical Thought'', Harper &amp; Row, 1970
* Gardiner, Juliet (ed) ''What is History Today...?'' London: MacMillan Education Ltd., 1988.
* [[Lionel Gossman]]. “Towards a Rational Historiography.” American Philosophical Society, 1989. ISBN 1-4223-8196-X. {{cite book|url=http://dianepub.wordpress.com/2010/06/30/lionel-gossman-towards-a-rational-historiography-american-philosophical-society-transaction-73-5-isbn-142237467x/ |title=Lionel Gossman’s Towards a Rational Historiography - American Philosophical Society Transaction 73-5| isbn= 1-4223-7467-X|publisher=Dianepub.wordpress.com |year=2010}}
* Harlaftis, Gelina, ed. ''The New Ways of History: Developments in Historiography''  (I.B. Tauris, 2010) 260 pages; trends in historiography since 1990
* Keith Jenkins, ed. ''The Postmodern History Reader'' (2006)
* [[Keith Jenkins]], ''Rethinking History'', 1991, ISBN 0-415-30443-1
* [[Arthur Marwick]], ''The Nature of History'', London: Macmillan, 1970, ISBN 0-333-10941-4
* [[Arthur Marwick]], ''The New Nature of History: knowledge, evidence, language'', Basingstoke: Palgrave, 2001, ISBN 0-333-96447-0
* [[Alun Munslow]]. ''The Routledge Companion to Historical Studies'' (2000)
* Revel, Jacques, and Lynn Hunt, eds. ''Histories: French Constructions of the Past,'' (1995). 654pp; 65 essays by French historians
* Roger Spalding &amp; Christopher Parker, ''Historiography: An Introduction'', 2008, ISBN 0-7190-7285-9
* [[John Tosh]], ''The Pursuit of History'', 2002, ISBN 0-582-77254-0
* Aviezer Tucker, ed. ''A Companion to the Philosophy of History and Historiography'' Malden: Blackwell, 2009
* Hayden White, ''The Fiction of Narrative: Essays on History, Literature, and Theory, 1957–2007'', Johns Hopkins, 2010. Ed. Robert Doran

===Guides to scholarship===
* Allison, William Henry. ''A guide to historical literature'' (1931) comprehensive bibliography for scholarship to 1930. [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=acls;cc=acls;view=toc;idno=heb06297.0001.001 online edition]
* Loades, David, ed. ''Reader's Guide to British History'' (Routledge; 2 vol 2003) 1760pp; highly detailed guide to British historiography  [http://books.google.com/books?id=AYEYAQAAIAAJ excerpt and text search]
* [[Mary Beth Norton|Norton, Mary Beth]], ed. ''The American Historical Association's guide to historical literature'' (Oxford University Press, 1995) [http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.06298 vol 1 online], [http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.06298 vol 2 online]
* Parish, Peter, ed. ''Reader's Guide to American History'' (Routledge, 1997),  880 pp; detailed guide to historiography of American topics [http://books.google.com/books?id=DnQTAXf4NuIC excerpt and text search]

===Histories of historical writing===
* Barnes, Harry Elmer. ''A history of historical writing'' (1962)
* Barraclough, Geoffrey. ''History: Main Trends of Research in the Social and Human Sciences,'' (1978)
* Bentley, Michael. ed., ''Companion to Historiography'', Routledge, 1997, ISBN 0415285577: 39 chapters by experts
* Breisach, Ernst. ''Historiography: Ancient, Medieval and Modern'', 3rd edition, 2007, ISBN 0-226-07278-9
* Budd, Adam, ed. ''The Modern Historiography Reader: Western Sources.'' London: Routledge, 2009.
* Cohen, H. Floris ''The Scientific Revolution: A Historiographical Inquiry'', Chicago, 1994, ISBN 0-226-11280-2
* Conrad, Sebastian. ''The Quest for the Lost Nation: Writing History in Germany and Japan in the American Century'' (2010)
* Gilderhus, Mark T. ''History an Historiographical Introduction'', 2002, ISBN 0-13-044824-9
* Iggers, Georg G. ''Historiography in the 20th Century: From Scientific Objectivity to the Postmodern Challenge'' (2005)
* Kramer, Lloyd, and Sarah Maza, eds. ''A Companion to Western Historical Thought'' Blackwell 2006. 520pp; ISBN 978-1-4051-4961-7.
* [[Arnaldo Momigliano|Momigliano, Arnaldo]]. ''The Classical Foundation of Modern Historiography'', 1990, ISBN 978-0-226-07283-8
* Rahman, M. M. ed. ''Encyclopaedia of Historiography'' (2006) [http://books.google.com/books?id=1BhtHVHgnwAC&amp;dq=historiography+%22joseph+priestly%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=0&amp;as_miny_is=&amp;as_maxm_is=0&amp;as_maxy_is=&amp;as_brr=0&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Excerpt and text search]
* [[Daniel Woolf|Woolf, Daniel]], ed. ''A Global Encyclopedia of Historical Writing'' (2 vol. 1998)
* [[Daniel Woolf|Woolf, Daniel]]. &quot;Historiography&quot;, in ''New Dictionary of the History of Ideas'', ed. M.C. Horowitz, (2005), vol. I.
* [[Daniel Woolf|Woolf, Daniel]]. ''A Global History of History'' (Cambridge University Press, 2011)
* [[Daniel Woolf|Woolf, Daniel]], ed. ''The Oxford History of Historical Writing''. 5 vols. (Oxford University Press, 2011–12).

===Feminist historiography===
* Bonnie G. Smith, ''The Gender of History: Men, Women, and Historical Practice'', [[Harvard University Press]] 2000
* [[Gerda Lerner]],  ''The Majority Finds its Past: Placing Women in History'', New York: [[Oxford University Press]] 1979
* Judith M. Bennett, ''History Matters: Patriarchy and the Challenge of Feminism'', [[University of Pennsylvania Press]], 2006
* Julie Des Jardins, ''Women and the Historical Enterprise in America'', [[University of North Carolina Press]], 2002
* [[Mary Ritter Beard]], ''Woman as force in history: A study in traditions and realities''
* Mary Spongberg, ''Writing women's history since the Renaissance'', [[Palgrave Macmillan]], 2002
Indian Historiography
*Vivek Kumar Srivastava,Pandit Nehru and his View of History, Mainstream, VOL XLIX, No 48, November 19, 2011

===Thematic and teaching===
* Carlebach, Elishiva, et al. eds. ''Jewish History and Jewish Memory: Essays in Honor of Yosef Hayim Yerushalmi'' (1998) [http://www.amazon.com/Jewish-History-Memory-Yerushalmi-Institute/dp/0874518717/ excerpt and text search]
* Charlton, Thomas L. ''History of Oral History: Foundations and Methodology'' (2007)
* Cohen, Paul. ''Discovering History in China: American Historical Writing on the Recent Chinese Past''. New York, London:: Columbia University Press, Studies of the East Asian Institute,  1984. 237p.  Reprinted: 2010, with a New Introduction by the Author. ISBN 023152546X. [http://www.worldcat.org/title/discovering-history-in-china-american-historical-writing-on-the-recent-chinese-past/oclc/456728837/viewport]
* Darcy, R. and Richard C. Rohrs, ''A Guide to Quantitative History'' (1995)
* Dawidowicz, Lucy S. ''The Holocaust and Historians''. (1981).
* Ernest, John. ''Liberation Historiography: African American Writers and the Challenge of History, 1794–1861''. (2004)
* Evans, Ronald W. ''The Hope for American School Reform: The Cold War Pursuit of Inquiry Learning in Social Studies''(Palgrave Macmillan; 2011) 265 pages
* Farrell, Frank. ''Themes in Australian History: Questions, Issues and Interpretation in an Evolving Historiography'' (1990)
* [[Pat Hudson|Hudson, Pat]]. ''History by Numbers: An Introduction to Quantitative Approaches'' (2002)
* Keita, Maghan. ''Race and the Writing of History''. Oxford UP (2000)
* Leavy, Patricia. ''Oral History: Understanding Qualitative Research'' (2011) [http://www.amazon.com/Oral-History-Understanding-Qualitative-Research/dp/0195395093/ excerpt and text search]
* Loewen, James W. ''Lies My Teacher Told Me: Everything Your American History Textbook Got Wrong'', (1996)
* [[Marc Ferro]], ''Cinema and History'' (1988)
* Parish, Peter J., ed/ ''Reader's Guide to American History'' (1997), historiographical overview of 600 topics
* [[Peter Novick]], ''That Noble Dream: The &quot;Objectivity Question&quot; and the American Historical Profession'' (1988), ISBN 0-521-34328-3
* Ritchie, Donald A. ''The Oxford Handbook of Oral History'' (2010) [http://www.amazon.com/Oxford-Handbook-Oral-History-Handbooks/dp/019533955X/ excerpt and text search]
* Tessa Morris-Suzuki, ''The Past Within Us: Media, Memory, History'' (2005), ISBN 1-85984-513-4

===Journals===
* [http://www.cromohs.unifi.it/index.html Cromohs — cyber review of modern historiography]
* ''History and Theory''
* [http://www.cisi.unito.it/stor/home.htm History of Historiography]

==External links==
* [http://www-open2-net-vip2.open.ac.uk/history/natureofhistory/index.html BBC Historiography Guide]
* [http://www.historiographyinternational.org/ International Commission for the History and Theory of Historiography]
* [http://www.galilean-library.org/int18.html Philosophy of History] introduced at The Galilean Library
* [http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/page/189/postcolonial-empires.htm 'Postcolonial Historiographies' group at Cambridge University], Includes online reading &amp; video archive
* [http://www.galilean-library.org/tucker.html Scientific Historiography], explained in an interview with Aviezer Tucker at the Galilean Library
* [http://www.activehistory.co.uk/historiography/index.htm Series of accessible, interactive online lectures]
* [http://www.cusd.chico.k12.ca.us/~bsilva/ib/histo.html Summary of key historiographical schools]
* [http://www.culturahistorica.es/welcome.html Web Portal on Historiography and Historical Culture]

[[Category:Articles with inconsistent citation formats]]
[[Category:Historiography|*]]
[[Category:Philosophy of history]]
[[Category:Historical eras| ]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

{{Link FA|es}}
[[ast:Historiografía]]
[[bn:ইতিহাস লিখনধারা]]
[[be:Гістарыяграфія]]
[[bg:Историография]]
[[ca:Historiografia]]
[[cs:Historiografie]]
[[cy:Hanesyddiaeth]]
[[de:Geschichtsschreibung]]
[[el:Ιστοριογραφία]]
[[es:Historiografía]]
[[eo:Historiografio]]
[[eu:Historiografia]]
[[fa:تاریخ‌نگاری]]
[[fr:Historiographie]]
[[gl:Historiografía]]
[[ko:역사학]]
[[hr:Historiografija]]
[[id:Historiografi]]
[[is:Sagnaritun]]
[[it:Storiografia]]
[[he:היסטוריוגרפיה]]
[[ka:ისტორიოგრაფია]]
[[lb:Historiographie]]
[[lt:Istoriografija]]
[[hu:Historiográfia]]
[[arz:التأريخ]]
[[mwl:Storiografie]]
[[nl:Geschiedschrijving]]
[[ja:歴史学]]
[[nap:Storiografia]]
[[no:Historiografi]]
[[oc:Istoriografia]]
[[pl:Historiografia]]
[[pt:Historiografia]]
[[ro:Istoriografie]]
[[ru:Историография]]
[[simple:Historiography]]
[[sk:Historiografia (dejepisectvo)]]
[[sh:Historiografija]]
[[fi:Historiografia]]
[[sv:Historiografi]]
[[tl:Historyograpiya]]
[[tr:Historiyografi]]
[[uk:Історіографія]]
[[vec:Storiografia]]
[[vo:Jenotemipenav]]
[[zh:歷史學]]</text>
      <sha1>0t73wowrtphquuz3rhnzd93kqvyllpz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
