<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Libya</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13812</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522406933</id>
      <parentid>521718669</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T00:31:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>77.211.36.61</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="43950">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{History of Libya}}
The '''History of [[Libya]]''' includes the history of its rich mix of ethnic groups added to the indigenous [[Berber people|Berber]] tribes. Berbers, the bulk of Libya's population, have been present throughout the entire history of the country. For most of its history, Libya has been subjected to varying degrees of foreign control, from Europe, Asia, and Africa. The modern history of independent Libya began in 1951.

The history of Libya comprises six distinct periods: Ancient Libya, the Roman era, the Islamic era, Ottoman rule, Italian rule, and the Modern era.

==Berber Pre-Roman Libya==
[[Image:Herodotus world map-en.svg|thumb|300px|Map of the world according to Herodotus]]
:''See also [[History of Ancient Libya|Ancient Libya]] (Tripolitania and Cyrenaica) ''

Archaeological evidence indicates that from at least the thirtieth millennium BC.&lt;ref name=EARLYHISTORY&gt;Helen Chapin Metz(1987). &quot;[http://countrystudies.us/libya/4.htm) Libya: Early History]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Libya's coastal plain shared in a [[Neolithic]] culture, skilled in the domestication of cattle and cultivation of crops, that was common to the whole Mediterranean [[littoral]]. To the south, in what is now the [[Sahara Desert]], nomadic hunters and herders roamed a large, well-watered savanna that was abundant in game and provided pastures for their livestock. Their culture flourished until the region began to [[desiccate|dry out]] after 2000 BC. Scattering before the encroaching desert and invading horsemen, the savanna people migrated into [[the Sudan]] or were absorbed by the [[Berber people|Berbers]].&lt;ref name=EARLYHISTORY&gt;Nelson &amp; Nyrop (1987). &quot;[http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+ly0013) Libya: Early History]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

The origin of the [[Berbers]] is a partial mystery. Archaeological and linguistic evidence strongly suggests southwestern Asia as the point from which the ancestors of the Berbers may have begun their migration into North Africa early in the third millennium BC. Over the succeeding centuries they extended their range from Egypt to the [[Niger Basin]]. Caucasians of predominantly Mediterranean stock, the Berbers present a broad range of physical types and speak a variety of mutually unintelligible Berber dialects that belong to the Berber family of the Afro-Asiatic language family. They rarely developed a sense of a ''full Berber nationhood'', as we understand it today. They have historically identified themselves in terms of their tribes, clans, or kingdoms. Collectively, Berbers referred to themselves simply as ''imazighen'', to which has been attributed the meaning &quot;free men&quot;.&lt;ref name=EARLYHISTORY/&gt;

Inscriptions found in Egypt dating from the [[Old Kingdom]] (ca. 2700–2200 BC) are the earliest known recorded testimony of the Berber migration and also the earliest written documentation of Libyan history. At least as early as this period, troublesome Berber tribes, one of which was identified in Egyptian records as the Levu (or &quot;Libyans&quot;), were raiding eastward as far as the [[Nile Delta]] and attempting to settle there. During the [[Middle Kingdom of Egypt|Middle Kingdom]] (ca. 2200-1700 BC) the Egyptian pharaohs succeeded in imposing their overlordship on these eastern Berbers and extracted tribute from them. Many Berbers served in the army of the pharaohs, and some rose to positions of importance in the Egyptian state. One such Berber officer seized control of Egypt in about 950 BC and, as [[Sheshonk I]], ruled as pharaoh. His successors of the twenty-second and twenty-third dynasties are also believed to have been Berbers.&lt;ref name=EARLYHISTORY/&gt;

To the [[Ancient Greeks]], Libya was one of the three known [[continent]]s along with [[Asia]] and [[Europe]]. In this sense, Libya was the whole known African continent to the west of the [[Nile]] Valley and extended south of Egypt.  Herodotus described the inhabitants of Libya as two peoples: The Libyans in northern Africa and the ''[[Ethiopia]]ns'' in the south. According to Herodotus, Libya began where ancient Egypt ended, and extended to [[Cape Spartel]], south of [[Tangier]] on the [[Atlantic coast]]. Both the Greeks and the [[Phoenicia]]ns colonized North African soil, and [[Punic|Punic civilization]] emerged, although its central city of [[Carthage]] was not in present-day Libya but in neighboring [[Tunisia]].

The territory of modern Libya had separate histories until Roman times, as Tripoli and Cyrenaica.

[[Cyrenaica]] was Greek before it was Roman. It was also known as [[Cyrenaica|Pentapolis]], the &quot;five cities&quot; being [[Cyrene, Libya|Cyrene]] (near the village of Shahhat) with its port of Apollonia ([[Susa, Libya|Susa]]), Arsinoe ([[Taucheira]]), Berenice ([[Benghazi]]) and Barca ([[Marj, Libya|Marj]]).  From the oldest and most famous of the [[Greek colonies]] the fertile coastal plain took the name of Cyrenaica.

==Berber Roman Libya==
[[File:Leptis Magna Arch of Septimus Severus.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Arch of [[Septimius Severus]] in [[Leptis Magna]].]]
{{main|Roman Libya}}

The Romans conquered [[Tripolitania]] (the region around Tripoli) in 106 BC. [[Ptolemy Apion]], the last Greek ruler, bequeathed Cyrenaica to Rome, which formally annexed the region in 74 BC and joined it to Crete as a Roman province. By 64 BC, [[Julius Caesar|Julius Caesar's]] legions had established their occupation, and the [[Roman Empire|Romans]] had thus unified all three regions of Libya (Tripolitania, [[Cyrenaica]] and northern [[Fezzan]]) in one single new province called ''Africa proconsularis'' (later Cyrenaica was separated administratively).
[[File:Roman Republic-44BC.png|thumb|left|200px|Libya united under [[Roman Republic]] rule (green area in North Africa)]]

As a Roman province, Libya was prosperous, and reached a golden age in the 2nd century AD, when the city of [[Leptis Magna]] rivalled Carthage and Alexandria in prominence. For more than 400 years, Tripolitania and Cyrenaica were wealthy Roman provinces and part of a cosmopolitan state whose citizens shared a common language, legal system, and Roman identity. Roman ruins like those of [[Leptis Magna]], extant in present-day Libya, attest to the vitality of the region, where populous cities and even smaller towns enjoyed the amenities of urban life - the forum, markets, public entertainments, and baths - found in every corner of the Roman Empire. Merchants and artisans from many parts of the Roman world established themselves in coastal Libya and the province was greatly &quot;[[Romanization (cultural)|Romanized]]&quot;, according to [[Theodore Mommsen]]. But the character of the cities of Tripolitania remained partially Punic and, in Cyrenaica, Greek. The predominant religion was [[Christianity]], but there was even a huge [[Jewish]] community (mainly in Cyrenaica).

Tripolitania was a major exporter of olive oil (produced there with the ''Centenaria'' farm system, protected by the [[Limes Tripolitanus]]), as well as a centre for the gold and slaves conveyed to the coast by the [[Garamentes]], while Cyrenaica remained an important source of wines, drugs, and horses.

As part of his reorganization of the empire in 300 AD, the Emperor [[Diocletian]] separated the administration of Crete from Cyrenaica and in the latter formed the new provinces of &quot;Upper Libya&quot; and &quot;Lower Libya&quot;, using the term Libya for the first time as an administrative designation. With the definitive partition of the empire in 395 AD, the Libyans of Cirenaica were assigned to the eastern empire; Tripolitania was attached to the [[Western Roman empire]].

==The Islamic Period==

===Early Islamic rule===
:''See also [[History of Islamic Tripolitania and Cyrenaica|Islamic Tripolitania and Cyrenaica]]''
[[Image:Aghlabids Dynasty 800 - 909 (AD).PNG|thumb|300px|Aghlabids dynasty at the beginning of IX century.]]
In 647 an army of 40,000 [[Arab]]s, led by [[Abdullah ibn Saad]] had come to take Libya from the Byzantines and Berbers. Tripoli was taken from the Byzantine rule, followed by [[Sbeitla|Sufetula]], a city {{convert|240|km|mi}} south of [[Carthage]], where the [[Exarch Gregory]] was killed.
Following the revolt, Gennadius fled to Damascus and asked for aid from [[Muawiyah]], to whom he had paid tribute for years. The caliph sent a sizable force with Gennadius to spread Islam and expand the Arab empire in Africa in 665. Even though the deposed exarch died after reaching [[Alexandria]], the Arabs marched on. The Byzantines dispatched an army to reinforce Africa, but its commander [[Nicephorus the Patrician]] lost a battle with the Arabs and reembarked. [[Uqba ibn Nafi]] and [[Abu Muhajir al Dinar]] did much to spread Islam and Arab rule. In the following centuries most of the Berbers converted to Islam, although after the Arab rule receded permanently from North Africa.

In 750 the [[Abbasid dynasty]] overthrew the [[Umayyad]] caliph and shifted the capital to [[Baghdad]], with emirs retaining nominal control over the Libyan coast on behalf of the far-distant caliph. In 800 Caliph [[Harun ar-Rashid]] appointed [[Ibrahim ibn al-Aghlab]] as his governor. The [[Aghlabids]] dynasty effectively became independent of the Baghdad caliphs, who continued to retain spiritual authority. The Aghlabid emirs took their custodianship of Libya seriously, repairing Roman [[irrigation]] systems, restoring order and bringing a measure of prosperity to the region.

However, this prosperity was followed by economic and political collapse&lt;ref name=&quot;Morony, Michael G. 2003 p. 245&quot;&gt;Morony, Michael G. (2003) ''Manufacturing and Labour'' Ashgate, Aldershot, Hant, England, p. 245, note 77, ISBN 0-86078-707-9&lt;/ref&gt; and then the Hilalian invasion of 1050-1052.  Groups of [[bedouin]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiss&quot;&gt;Weiss, Bernard G. and  Green, Arnold H.(1987) ''A Survey of Arab History'' American University in Cairo Press, Cairo, p. 129, ISBN 977-424-180-0&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pastoralism|pastoralists]] from [[Upper Egypt]], left the degraded grasslands on the upper [[Nile]] and headed westward into Libya, destroying the fields and gardens of the inhabitants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ballais, Jean-Louis 2000 p. 133&quot;&gt;Ballais, Jean-Louis (2000) &quot;Chapter 7: Conquests and land degradation in the eastern Maghreb&quot; p. 133  ''In'' Barker, Graeme and Gilbertson, David (2000) ''The Archaeology of Drylands: Living at the Margin'' Routledge, London, Volume 1, Part III - Sahara and Sahel,  pp. 125-136, ISBN 978-0-415-23001-8&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ibn Khaldun]] compared the invasion to a swarm of locusts.&lt;ref name=&quot;OCLC 9462004&quot;&gt;Bovill, E. W. (1958) ''The Golden Trade of the Moors'' Oxford University Press, London, pp. 58-59 [http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/9462004 OCLC 9462004]&lt;/ref&gt; The leading tribe of these bedouin were the [[Banu Hilal]], hence the name Hilalian invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weiss&quot;/&gt;

===Libya under the Ottomans (1551-1911) ===
:''See also [[History of Ottoman Libya|Ottoman Rule]] (15th–1912)''
[[File:Guillaume Delisle North West Africa 1707.jpg|thumb|1707 map by [[Guillaume Delisle]] showing northwest Africa, including the Barbary Coast]]
By the beginning of the 16th century the Libyan coast had minimal central authority and its harbours were havens for pirates. Habsburg Spain occupied Tripoli in 1510, but the Spaniards were more concerned with controlling the port than with the inconveniences of administering a colony. In 1538 Tripoli was reconquered by a pirate king called Khair ad-Din (known more evocatively as [[Hayreddin Barbarossa|Barbarossa]], or Red Beard) and the coast became renowned as the [[Barbary Coast]].

When the Ottomans arrived to occupy Tripoli in 1551, they saw little reason to rein in the pirates, preferring instead to profit from the booty. It would be more than two centuries before the pirates' control of the region was challenged.

Under the Ottomans, the Maghreb was divided into three provinces, Algiers, Tripoli and Tunis. After 1565, administrative authority in a [[pasha]] appointed by the [[sultan]] in Constantinople. The sultan provided the pasha with a corps of [[janissaries]], which was in turn divided into a number of companies under the command of a junior officer or [[bey]]. The janissaries quickly became the dominant force in Ottoman Libya.

In 1711, [[Ahmed Karamanli]], an Ottoman cavalry officer, seized power and founded the [[Karamanli dynasty|Karamanli]] dynasty, which would last 124 years. The [[Libyan Civil War of 1791–1795]] occurred in those years.

[[File:Burning of the uss philadelphia.jpg|220px|thumb|right|The burning frigate [[USS Philadelphia (1799)|''Philadelphia'']] in the harbor of Tripoli, 16 February 1804, by [[Edward Moran]], painted 1897.]]
In May 1801, Pasha [[Yusuf Karamanli]] demanded from the United States an increase in the tribute (then $83,000) which the US government had paid since 1796 for the protection of US commerce from piracy by Ottoman tribes along the North African coast. The increased tribute demand was refused, a United States of America naval force blockaded Tripoli, and the [[First Barbary War]] continued on until 3 June 1805 resulting in the repatriation of 300 US sailors and the first time the US flag had been raised in victory on foreign soil.

The [[Second Barbary War]] (1815, also known as the Algerine or Algerian War) was the second of two wars fought between the United States of America, England, and The Netherlands loosely allied against the Ottoman Empire's North African regencies of Algiers, Tripoli, and Tunis, known collectively as the [[Barbary Coast|Barbary States]]. The treaty negotiated by England's envoy after a nine-hour bombardment of Algiers resulted in a treaty on 24 September 1816. 1,083 Christian slaves and the British Consul were freed and the US ransom money of $10,000 was repaid by the Ottoman pasha. As the general European wars abated during this time, the European and American navies were able to focus on countering the Barbary pirates and the pirate threat soon faded.

In 1814, the government of [[Mahmud II|Sultan Mahmud II]] took advantage of local disturbances to reassert their direct authority and held it until the final collapse of the Ottoman Empire. As decentralized Ottoman power had resulted in the virtual independence of Egypt as well as Tripoli, the coast and desert lying between them relapsed to anarchy, even after direct Ottoman control was resumed in Tripoli. Over a 75 year period the Ottoman Turks provided 33 governors and Libya remained part of the empire — although at times virtually autonomous — until [[Italy]] invaded it in 1911 in the [[Italo-Turkish War]], as the Ottoman Empire was collapsing.

== Italian rule (1911-1943) ==
[[File:Territorial growth of Libya during the Italian period.jpg|thumb|Territorial growth of Italian Libya: Territory ceded by Ottoman Empire 1912 (dark-green) but effectively Italy controlled only five ports (black), territories ceced by France and Britain 1919 and 1926 (light-green), territories ceced by France and Britain 1934/35 (red)]]
:''See also [[Italo-Turkish War]] and [[History of Libya as Italian Colony|Italian Colony]] (1911–1947)''
The Italian rule in Libya started with the Italian conquest of coastal Tripolitania and Cyrenaica from the Ottomans in 1911.

It lasted more than thirty years until February 1943, when western Tripolitania was conquered by the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] in the [[North African Campaign]].

Officially Italy renounced to Libya in 1947, in the Peace Treaty after [[World War II]].

The colony expanded after concessions from the British colony of [[Anglo-Egyptian Sudan|Sudan]] and a territorial agreement with [[Kingdom of Egypt|Egypt]]. The [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Kingdom of Italy]] at the 1919 Paris &quot;Conference of Peace&quot; received nothing from [[Germany|German]] colonies, but as a compensation [[Great Britain]] gave it the [[Oltre Giuba]] and France agreed to give some Saharan territories to the Italian Libya.

After prolonged discussions through the 1920s, it was not until 1935 that the Mussolini-Laval agreement was reached and Italy received the [[Aouzou strip]] that was added to Libya (but this agreement was not ratified later by [[France]]).

Probably the most important legacy of the Italian rule -according to historians like Chapin Metz- is the political creation of &quot;Libya&quot; with the unification of [[Tripolitania]], [[Cyrenaica]] and [[Fezzan]] in 1934, done by Governor [[Italo Balbo]]. He promoted a huge colonization of Italians in Libya: total native [[Italian settlers in Libya|Italian population for Libya]] was 110,575 out of a total population of 915,440 in 1939 &lt;ref&gt;General Staff War Office 1939, 165/b&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Italo-Turkish War and Italian Libya ===
The attempted Italian colonization of the Ottoman provinces of [[Tripolitania]] and [[Cyrenaica]] was never wholly successful, at least initially. On 3 October 1911 [[Italo-Turkish War|the Italians attacked Tripoli]], claiming somewhat disingenuously to be liberating Libya from Ottoman rule. Despite a major revolt by the [[Libya]]ns, the Ottoman sultan ceded Libya to the Italians by signing the 1912 [[Treaty of Lausanne]].
[[Image:Italo-Turkish War peace treaty chromolithograph.jpg|thumb|1912 Italian-American chromolithograph showing a fanciful depiction of the Italian-Turkish Peace treaty. Titled, 'LA PACE ITALO-TURCA'.]]

After the withdrawal of the Ottoman army the Italians could easily extend their occupation of the country, seizing East Tripolitania,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marieni-saredo.it/6.1%20LIBIA.htm Photos and data about the Italian conquest of Libya (in Italian)]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ghadames]], the Djebel and [[Fezzan]] with [[Murzuk]] during 1913.&lt;ref name=be206&gt;Bertarelli (1929), p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt; The outbreak of the First World War with the necessity to bring back the troops to Italy, the proclamation of the [[Jihad|Holy War]] by the Ottomans, the uprising of the Libyans in Tripolitania and Fezzan and the partisan war led by the Senussi in Cyrenaica &lt;ref name=be419&gt;Bertarelli (1929), p. 419.&lt;/ref&gt; forced the Italians to abandon all the occupied territory and to entrench themselves in Tripoli, Derna and the coast of Cyrenaica.&lt;ref name=be206/&gt;  Only in the late 1920s were the Italians able to take control of all Libya. Meanwhile 150,000 Italians settled in Libya between 1920 and 1940, greatly developing [[Italian Libya]] in all areas.

At the [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|1919 Paris Peace Conference]], the [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Kingdom of Italy]] did not receive any part of the [[Germany|German]] colonies.  Instead, France agreed to give some Saharan territories to the Italian Libya, and the [[Oltre Giuba]] in Somalia was given to Italy by [[Great Britain]].  After many discussions during the 1920s, in 1935 the Mussolini-Laval agreement was made and Italy received the [[Aouzou strip]], which was united to the newly created ''Italian colony of Libya''.

On 25 October 1920 the Italian government recognized [[Idris I of Libya|Sheikh Sidi Idris]] the hereditary head of the nomadic [[Senussi]], with wide authority in [[Kufra]] and other oases, as Emir of Cyrenaica, a new title extended by the British at the close of World War I. The emir would eventually become king of the free Libyan state.

=== Libya under fascism ===
{{Main|Italian Libya}}
Fighting intensified after the accession to power in Italy of the [[dictator]] [[Benito Mussolini]]. [[King Idris|Idris]] (later King of Libya) fled to [[Egypt]] in 1922. From 1922 to 1928, Italian forces under General [[Pietro Badoglio]] waged a [[punitive pacification]] campaign. Badoglio's successor in the field, [[Marshal]] [[Rodolfo Graziani]], accepted the commission from Mussolini on the condition that he was allowed to crush [[Libyan resistance]] unencumbered by the restraints of either Italian or [[international law]]. Mussolini reportedly agreed immediately and Graziani intensified the oppression. Some [[Libyans]] continued to defend themselves, with the strongest voices of dissent coming from the Cyrenaica. [[Omar Mukhtar]], a Senussi [[sheikh]], became the leader of the uprising.

After a much-disputed truce on 3 January 1928, the Italian policy in Libya reached the level of full scale war, including deportation and concentration of the people of the [[Jebel Akhdar, Libya|Jebel Akhdar]] to deny the rebels the support of the local population.
After [[Omar Mukhtar|Al-Mukhtar]]'s capture 15 September 1931 and his execution in Benghazi, the resistance petered out. Limited resistance to the Italian occupation crystallized round the person of [[Idris of Libya|Sheik Idris]], the Emir of Cyrenaica.
[[File:Fiat Train Passing in to Cyrenaica.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Italian &quot;Littorina&quot; train in Cyrenaica]]
By 1934, Libya was fully pacified and the new Italian governor [[Italo Balbo]] started a policy of integration between the Arabs and the Italians. Indeed in 1939, laws were passed that allowed Muslims to be permitted to join the [[National Fascist Party]] and in particular the [[Muslim Association of the Lictor]] (''Associazione Musulmana del Littorio''), and the 1939 reforms allowed the creation of Libyan military units within the Italian army.&lt;ref&gt;Sarti, p196.&lt;/ref&gt;
As a consequence during WWII there was a strong support for Italy between many Muslim Libyans, who enrolled in the Italian Army &lt;ref&gt;[http://xoomer.virgilio.it/ramius/Militaria/colonie_italiane-libia.html  30000 Libyans fought for Italy in WWII]&lt;/ref&gt;

The governor Balbo (after the creation of &quot;Libya&quot; in 1934, with the unification of Tripolitania, Cyrenaica and Fezzan in a single country) developed Italian Libya from 1934 to 1940, creating a huge infrastructure (from 4,000&amp;nbsp;km of roads to 400&amp;nbsp;km of narrow gauge [[Italian Libya Railways|railways]] to new industries and to dozen of new agricultural villages).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fedoa.unina.it/1881/01/Santoianni_Progettazione_Architettonica.pdf  Chapter Libya (in Italian)]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Libyan economy nearly &quot;boomed&quot;, mainly in the agricultural sector. Even some manufacturing activities were developed, mostly related to the food industry. Building construction increased in a huge way. Furthermore, the Italians made modern medical care available for the first time in Libya and improved sanitary conditions in the towns.

Howard Christie wrote that ''The Italians started numerous and diverse businesses in Tripolitania and Cirenaica. These included an explosives factory, railway workshops, Fiat Motor works, various food processing plants, electrical engineering workshops, ironworks, water plants, agricultural machinery factories, breweries, distilleries, biscuit factories, a tobacco factory, tanneries, bakeries, lime, brick and cement works, Esparto grass industry, mechanical saw mills, and the Petrolibya Society (Trye 1998). Italian investment in her colony was to take advantage of new colonists and to make it more self-sufficient. Total native Italian population for Libya was 110,575 out of a total population of 915,440 in 1940 (General Staff War Office 1939, 165/b).''&lt;ref&gt;[http://cgsc.cdmhost.com/cgi-bin/showfile.exe?CISOROOT=/p4013coll2&amp;CISOPTR=597&amp;filename=591.pdf. Economic development of Italian Libya]&lt;/ref&gt;

Governor Balbo promoted the construction of many new villages &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airl.it/photogallery/varie/varie_06.php Photo of a new Village]&lt;/ref&gt; for many thousands of [[Italian settlers in Libya|Italian colonists]] in the coastal areas of Italian Libya. He promoted even the creation of new villages for the Arabs.

On 13 September 1940, [[Via Balbia|Mussolini's highway]] was used for the invasion of [[Egypt]] by Italian forces stationed in Libya.
Counterattacks of British Allied forces from Egypt, commanded by [[Wavell]] and their successful two-month campaign in ([[Tobruk]], [[Benghazi]], [[El Agheila]]), and the counteroffensives under [[Erwin Rommel|Rommel]] in 1940-43, all took place during [[World War II]]. In November 1942, the Allied forces retook Cyrenaica; by February 1943, the last German and Italian soldiers were driven from Libya.

== Towards independence (1943-1951)==
In the early post-war period, Tripolitania and Cyrenaica remained under [[United Kingdom|British]] administration, while the [[France|French]] controlled Fezzan. In 1945, Idris returned from exile in [[Cairo]] but declined to resume permanent residence in Cyrenaica until the removal in 1947 of some aspects of foreign control. Under the terms of the 1947 peace treaty with the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]], Italy, which hoped to maintain the colony of [[Tripolitania]], (and France, which wanted the [[Fezzan]]), relinquished all claims to Libya. Libya so remained united.

Severe anti-Jewish violence erupted in Libya following the liberation of North Africa by Allied troops. From 5–7 November 1945, more than 140 Jews (including 36 children) were killed and hundreds injured in a [[1945 Tripoli pogrom|pogrom in Tripoli]]. Five synagogues in Tripoli and four in provincial towns were destroyed, and over 1,000 Jewish residences and commercial buildings were plundered in Tripoli alone.&lt;ref name=Selent&gt;Selent, pp. 20-21&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Shields&gt;Shields, Jacqueline.&quot;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/History/jewref.html Jewish Refugees from Arab Countries]&quot; in [[Jewish Virtual Library]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stillman, 2003, p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1948, anti-Jewish rioters in Libya killed another 12 Jews and destroyed 280 Jewish homes.&lt;ref name=Shields/&gt; The fear and insecurity which arose from these anti-Jewish attacks and the [[Declaration of the Establishment of the State of Israel|founding of the state of Israel]] led many Jews to [[Jewish exodus from Arab and Muslim lands|flee Libya]]. From 1948 to 1951, 30,972 Libyan Jews [[Jewish exodus from Arab and Muslim lands|moved to Israel]].&lt;ref name=berkeley&gt;[http://sunsite.berkeley.edu/JewsofLibya/LibyanJews/thejews.html History of the Jewish Community in Libya]&quot;. Retrieved 1 July 2006&lt;/ref&gt; By 1970s, the rest of Libyan Jews (some 7,000) were evacuated to Italy.

On 21 November 1949 the [[UN General Assembly]] passed a resolution stating that Libya should become independent before 1 January 1952.&lt;ref&gt;http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/RESOLUTION/GEN/NR0/051/08/IMG/NR005108.pdf?OpenElement&lt;/ref&gt; [[Idris I of Libya|Idris]] represented Libya in the subsequent UN negotiations.  The transition to independence was overseen by the Dutch UN commissioner [[Adriaan Pelt]] who was appointed on 10 December 1949.

==Independent Libya  ==

[[Image:LA CATTEDRALE DI TRIPOLI 1960.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Italian legacies: [[Tripoli Cathedral]] (now largely rebuilt as Mosque) and the former [[FIAT]] centre (Meydan al Gaza'ir) during the 1960s.]]

=== Kingdom of Libya (1951-1969) ===
{{main|Kingdom of Libya}}
[[Idris I of Libya|Idris as-Senussi]], the [[Emir]] of Tripolitania and Cyrenaica and the leader of the [[Senussi]] Muslim Sufi order, represented Libya in the UN negotiations, and on 24 December 1951, Libya declared its independence with representatives from Cyrenaica, Tripolitania and Fezzan declaring a [[Political union|union]] with the country being called the United Kingdom of Libya, and Idris as-Senussi being offered the crown. In accordance with the constitution the new country had a [[federal government]] with the three states of Cyrenaica, Tripolitania and Fezzan having [[autonomy]]. The kingdom also had three capital cities: [[Tripoli]], [[Benghazi]] and [[Bayda, Libya|Bayda]]. Two years after independence, on 28 March 1953, Libya joined the [[Arab League]].

When Libya declared its independence on 24 December 1951 it was the first country to achieve independence through the United Nations and the third former European colony in [[Africa]] to gain independence after Egypt (1922) and Abyssinia (1941). The Kingdom of Libya was proclaimed a constitutional and a hereditary [[monarchy]] and Idris was proclaimed king. Previously, the USSR had sought a Mandate over Libya following the end of World War II.&lt;ref&gt;''Stalin: Court of the Red Czar'', Simon S. Montefiore, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

Following independence Libya faced a number of problems. There were no colleges in the country and just sixteen college graduates. Also the country had just three lawyers with not a single [[Libyan]] [[physician]], [[engineer]], [[Surveying|surveyor]] or [[pharmacist]] in the kingdom. It was also estimated that only 250,000 Libyans were literate and that 5% of the population was blind, with eye diseases such as [[trachoma]] widespread. In light of these Britain provided a number of [[civil servant]]s to staff the government.

In April 1955, oil exploration started in the kingdom with its first oil fields being discovered in 1959. The first exports began in 1963 with the discovery of oil helping to transform the Libyan economy, although imposing a [[resource curse]] on Libya. Although oil drastically improved Libya's finances, popular resentment grew as wealth was increasingly concentrated in the hands of the elite.

On 25 April 1963, the federal system of government was abolished and in line with this the name of the country was changed to the ''Kingdom of Libya'' to reflect the constitutional changes.

As was the case with other African nations following independence, the remaining [[Italian settlers in Libya]] held many of the best jobs, owned the best farmland and ran the most successful businesses.

The monarchy came to an end on 1 September 1969 when a group of military officers led by [[Muammar Gaddafi]] staged a coup d’état against King Idris while he was in [[Turkey]] for medical treatment. The revolutionaries arrested the army chief of staff and the head of security in the kingdom. After hearing about the coup, King Idris dismissed it as &quot;unimportant&quot; while it was initially reported (falsely) that the Crown Prince [[Hasan as-Senussi]] had announced his support for the new regime.

The coup pre-empted King Idris' instrument of abdication dated 4 August 1969 to take effect 2 September 1969 in favour of the Crown Prince, who had been appointed regent following the king's departure for Turkey. Following the overthrow of the monarchy the country was renamed the ''Libyan Arab Republic''.

===Libya under Gaddafi (1969-2011) ===
{{main|History of Libya under Gaddafi}}
{{further|Politics of Libya}}
[[File:Nasser Gaddafi 1969.jpg|thumb|left|Gaddafi (left) with Egyptian President [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]] in 1969]]

On 1 September 1969 a small group of military officers led by then 27-year-old army officer [[Muammar Gaddafi]] staged a coup d'état against King Idris, who was exiled to Egypt. The new regime, headed by the [[Libyan Revolutionary Command Council|Revolutionary Command Council]] (RCC), abolished the monarchy and proclaimed the new [[Libyan Arab Republic]]. The new RCC's motto became &quot;freedom, socialism, and unity&quot;. It pledged itself to remedy &quot;backwardness&quot;, take an active role in the [[Palestinian Arab]] cause, promote Arab unity, and encourage domestic policies based on social justice, non-exploitation, and an equitable distribution of wealth.

The new government negotiated with the Americans to evacuate the base from Libya. The [[Wheelus Air Base]] agreement had just two more years to run, and in December 1969, the US agreed to vacate the facility by June 1970.

In 1977, Gaddafi renamed the state to ''[[Jamahiriya]]'', a neologism translating to &quot;state of the masses&quot;. Gaddafi styled himself &quot;Leader and Guide of the Revolution of Libya&quot;. Gaddafi also styled himself as an advocate of [[Pan-Africanism]], and was active in the establishment of the [[African Union]] in 2001. He used to give himself titles such as &quot;King of Kings&quot;, &quot;leader of the Arab leaders&quot; and &quot;imam of the Muslims&quot; (at the 2009 Arab League Summit).

Gaddafi stepped down as General Secretary of the General People's Committee in 1977, being succeeded by [[Abdul Ati al-Obeidi]]. However, he remained in [[autocrat]]ic control of the country as de facto [[military dictatorship|dictator]], as he retained full control over the [[Armed forces of the Libyan Arab Jamahiriya|Libyan Armed Forces]].

Gaddafi undertook a number of military adventures during the 1970s to 1980s, including the [[Chadian–Libyan conflict]], the [[Libyan–Egyptian War]] and the [[Gulf of Sidra incident (1981)|first Gulf of Sidra incident]].
He introduced the [[Islamic Legion]] in 1972, a Libyan-sponsored pan-Arab paramilitary force by means of which Gaddafi aspired to establish a &quot;Great Islamic State of the Sahel&quot;.
His open endorsement of terrorism led to the [[Reagan administration]] declaring Libya a &quot;state sponsor of terrorism&quot; on 29 December 1979, and eventually culminated in the [[1986 Bombing of Libya|1986 US Bombing of Libya]].

The 1986 bombing of Libya was a turning-point in Gaddafi's approach to the [[foreign relations of Libya]].
Gaddafi stopped endorsing terrorist attacks on western countries, and while his behaviour remained extremely erratic, occasionally provoking international incidents such as the [[HIV trial in Libya]] and the [[Switzerland-Libya conflict|Swiss-Libyan diplomatic crisis]], Gaddafi managed to improve his image in the west and by the early 2000s had mostly benign relations with western democracies.

===Libyan civil war===
{{main|Libyan civil war}}

In February 2011, [[Libyan civil war|anti-government mass protests]] sprang up against Gaddafi in Benghazi, [[Bayda, Libya|Bayda]] and [[Zintan]], in the context of the wider [[Arab Spring]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title=Libyan Police Stations Torched|date=16 February 2011|work=Al Jazeera |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/02/20112167051422444.html |accessdate=26 March 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5wYDLZMdr |archivedate=16 February 2011 |deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 February, demonstrators took control of [[Benghazi]], the second largest city in Libya, with some support from police and military units. In reaction the government sent elite troops, which were resisted by Benghazi's inhabitants and mutineering members of the military.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Bloodshed as tensions rise in Libya|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12513941 | work=BBC News | date=19 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Benghazi, during the course of four separate protests that took place on 20 February, more than 200 people have died.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-12520366|title=Libya: Anti-Gaddafi protests spread to Tripoli|newspaper=[[BBC News]]|date=20 February 2011|accessdate=20 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''New York Times'' reported that &quot;the crackdown in Libya has proven the bloodiest of the recent government actions.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT2_20&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|first=David D.|last=Kirkpatrick|title=Libyan Forces Again Fire on Residents at Funerals|date=20 February 2011|newspaper=[[New York Times]]|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/21/world/africa/21libya.html?pagewanted=2&amp;hp |accessdate=20 February 2011|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 10 March, [[France]] became the first nation to recognise the ''National Transitional Council'' of the anti-government rebels as the sole representative of Libya.  An Élysée source also announced that France plans to send an ambassador to Benghazi. Nations who recognize the Council as the government of Libya may not have to go through the process of obtaining UN security council's approval to establish a &quot;No-fly zone&quot; if the Council requests one, as this could count as a &quot;friendly request&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work = Ha’aretz| url = http://www.haaretz.com/news/international/france-grants-official-recognition-to-rebel-libyan-national-council-1.348338?localLinksEnabled=false | title = France grants official recognition to rebel Libyan national council}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 March, the [[United Nations Security Council]] passed [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1973|Resolution 1973]] with a 10–0 vote and five abstentions. The resolution sanctioned the establishment a [[no-fly zone]] and the use of &quot;all means necessary&quot; to protect civilians within Libya.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=37808|title=Security Council authorizes ‘all necessary measures’ to protect civilians in Libya|publisher=United Nations-DPI/NMD - UN News Service Section|date=17 March 2011|accessdate=30 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly afterwards, Libyan [[Minister of Foreign Affairs (Libya)|Foreign Minister]] [[Moussa Koussa]] stated that &quot;Libya has decided an immediate ceasefire and an immediate halt to all military operations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-12787739 | work=BBC News | title=Libya: Pro-Gaddafi forces 'to observe ceasefire' | date=18 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, attacks against insurgent strongholds appear to have continued despite this claim.

[[File:Arrott libya tripoli gadhafi effigy 480 29aug2011.jpg|thumb|250px|right|An effigy of Muammar Gaddafi hangs from a scaffold in Tripoli's Martyrs' Square, Libya. 29 August 2011]]

On 19 March, the first Allied act to secure the no-fly zone began when French military jets entered Libyan airspace on a [[reconnaissance]] mission heralding attacks on enemy targets.&lt;ref name=libyarate1/&gt; Allied military action to enforce the ceasefire commenced the same day when a French aircraft opened fire and destroyed a vehicle on the ground. French jets also destroyed five tanks belonging to the Gaddafi government.&lt;ref name=libyarate1&gt;{{cite news|author=Jonathan Marcus |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-12795971 |title='French military jets open fire in Libya' |work=BBC |date=19 March 2011 |accessdate=20 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The United States and United Kingdom launched attacks on over 20 &quot;integrated air defense systems&quot; using more than 110 [[Tomahawk cruise missiles]] during operations [[Operation Odyssey Dawn|Odyssey Dawn]] and [[Operation Ellamy|Ellamy]].&lt;ref name=bbc&gt;{{cite news|title=Coalition launches Libya attacks|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-12796972|accessdate=20 March 2011|newspaper=BBC|date=19 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 June, the [[International Criminal Court]] issued an arrest warrant for Gaddafi, alleging that Gaddafi had been personally involved in planning and implementing &quot;a policy of widespread and systematic attacks against civilians and demonstrators and dissidents&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Ian Black and David Smith in Tripoli |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jun/27/muammar-gaddafi-arrest-warrant-hague |title=War crimes court issues Gaddafi arrest warrant|work=The Guardian |date=27 June 2011 |accessdate=20 August 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 22 August, rebel fighters had entered Tripoli and taken [[Martyrs' Square, Tripoli|Martyrs' Square]].&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/middle-east/libyan-rebels-converging-on-tripoli/2011/08/21/gIQAbF3RUJ_story.html?hpid=z1 | work=The Washington Post | first=William | last=Wan | date=22 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, Gaddafi asserted that he was still in Libya and would not concede power to the rebels.&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost.com&quot;/&gt;

On 20 October, NTC forces captured Sirte, and in the process captured and [[Death of Muammar Gaddafi|killed]] Muammar Gaddafi.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/10/20111020111520869621.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transition===
{{Main|Aftermath of the Libyan civil war}}
After the [[Libyan civil war]], the [[National Transitional Council]] (NTC) has been responsible for the transition of the administration of the governing of Libya. The &quot;liberation&quot; of Libya was celebrated on 23 October 2011. Then Jibril announced that consultations were under way to form an interim government within one month, followed by elections for a constitutional assembly within eight months and parliamentary and presidential elections to be held within a year after that. He stepped down as expected the same day and was succeeded by [[Ali Tarhouni]]. 

On 24 November, Tarhouni was replaced by [[Abdurrahim El-Keib]]. El-Keib formed a [[cabinet of Libya|provisional government]], filling it with independent or CNT politicians, including women.

After the fall of Gaddhafi, Libya has been faced with internal struggles. A protest started against the new regime of NTC.{{Clarify|date=February 2012}} The loyalists of Gaddhafi rebelled and fought with the new Libyan army.{{Clarify|date=February 2012}}

Because the [[Libyan Constitutional Declaration|Constitutional Declaration]] allowed a multi-party system, the political parties, like [[Democratic Party (Libya)|Democratic Party]], [[Party of Reform and Development]], [[National Gathering for Freedom, Justice and Development]] appeared. The Islamist movement started. For stop it, CNT government deny the parties based on religion, tribal and ethnic bases.

On 7 July 2012, Libyans voted in their first parliamentary elections since the end of the dictatorship of Moammar Gadhafi. The election, in which more than 100 political parties have registered, will form an interim 200-member national assembly. This will replace the unelected National Transitional Council, name a prime minister, and form a committee to draft a constitution. The vote was postponed several times to resolve logistical and technical problems, and to give more time to register to vote, and to vetting candidates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Epatko|first=Larisa|title=In Libya, Expectations High as Parliamentary Vote Approaches|publisher=PBS NewsHour|accessdate=7/5/2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Arab Spring]]
*[[History of North Africa]]
*[[History of the Jews in Libya]]
*[[List of heads of state of Libya]]
*[[Military history of Libya]]
*[[Politics of Libya]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==

*{{cite book |last=Bruce St John|first= Ronald|title= Historical dictionary of Libya|publisher= Scarecrow Press|location= Lanham, Md.|year=2006|isbn=0-8108-5303-5}}
*{{cite book |last=Chapin Metz|first=Hellen|title=Libya: A Country Study|publisher=GPO for the Library of Congress|location=Washington|year=1987}}
*{{cite book |last=Nelson |first=Harold D. |coauthors=Nyrop, Richard F. |url=http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/lytoc.html |title=Libya: A Country Study |series=[[Library of Congress Country Studies]] |publisher=United States Government Printing Office |location=Washington, D.C. |year=1987 |oclc=5676518}}
*{{cite book |last=Wright|first=John L.|title=Nations of the Modern World: Libya|publisher=Ernest Benn Ltd|year=1969}}
*{{cite book |last=Bertarelli |first=L.V. |title=Guida d'Italia, Vol. XVII |publisher=Consociazione Turistica Italiana|location=Milano |year=1929|language=Italian}}
* Tuccimei, Ercole (1999). ''La Banca d'Italia in Africa'', Foreword by Arnaldo Mauri, Laterza, Bari.

==External links==
*[http://www.libyaconnected.com/Tourism.html History of Libya | Libya Connected]
*[http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552588 Libya in Crisis: Modern History of Libya] from the [https://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552494/browse?type=title Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives]

{{Libya topics}}
{{History of Africa}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Libya}}
[[Category:History of North Africa]]
[[Category:History of Libya| ]]

{{Link FA|sv}}
{{Link GA|sv}}
&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;
[[ar:تاريخ ليبيا]]
[[az:Liviya tarixi]]
[[bg:История на Либия]]
[[ca:Història de Líbia]]
[[de:Geschichte Libyens]]
[[es:Historia de Libia]]
[[eu:Libiako historia]]
[[fa:تاریخ لیبی]]
[[fr:Histoire de la Libye]]
[[io:Historio di Libia]]
[[it:Storia della Libia]]
[[he:היסטוריה של לוב]]
[[lt:Libijos istorija]]
[[mk:Историја на Либија]]
[[mg:Tantaran'i Libia]]
[[nl:Geschiedenis van Libië]]
[[ja:リビアの歴史]]
[[pt:História da Líbia]]
[[ro:Istoria Libiei]]
[[ru:История Ливии]]
[[fi:Libyan historia]]
[[sv:Libyens historia]]
[[uk:Історія Лівії]]
[[vec:Storia de la Libia]]
[[yo:Ìtàn ilẹ̀ Líbyà]]</text>
      <sha1>5ime8a2vjw9bxieng2aobvlw2qmr4zr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
