<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Japan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25890428</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521452355</id>
      <parentid>520954505</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T02:29:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hmains</username>
        <id>508734</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>copyedit, refine cat, and AWB general fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8414)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="112655">{{History of Japan}}
{{Culture of Japan}}
The '''history of Japan''' encompasses the history of the [[Geography of Japan|islands of Japan]] and the [[Japanese people]], spanning the [[Japanese Paleolithic|ancient history of the region]] to the [[Heisei period|modern history of Japan]] as a nation state. Following the last [[ice age]], around 12,000 BC, the rich ecosystem of the [[Japanese archipelago]] fostered human development. The earliest-known pottery found in Japan belongs to the [[Jōmon period]]. The first known written reference to Japan is in the brief information given in ''[[Twenty-Four Histories]]'' in the 1st century AD. The main cultural and religious influences came from China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jacques Gernet|title=A History of Chinese Civilization|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jqb7L-pKCV8C&amp;pg=PA290|year=1996|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=290}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The first permanent  capital was founded at [[Nara, Nara|Nara]] in 710, which became a center of [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] art, religion and culture. The current imperial family emerged about 700, but until 1868 (with few exceptions) had high prestige but little power. By 1550 or so political power was subdivided into several hundred local units, or &quot;domains&quot; controlled by local &quot;daimyō&quot; (lords), each with his own force of [[samurai]] warriors. [[Tokugawa Ieyasu]] came to power in 1600, gave land to his supporters, set up his &quot;bakufu&quot; (military government) at Edo (modern [[Tokyo]]). The &quot;Tokugawa period&quot; was prosperous and peaceful and Japan terminated the Christian missions and cut off almost all contact with the outside world. 

In the 1860s the [[Meiji period]] began, and the new national leadership systematically ended [[feudalism]] and transformed an isolated, underdeveloped [[island country]] into a [[great power|world power]] that closely followed Western models. Democracy was problematic, because Japan's powerful military was semi-independent and overruled—or assassinated—civilians in the 1920s and 1930s. The military moved into [[China]] starting in 1931 and declared all-out war on China in 1937. Japan controlled the coast and major cities and set up puppet regimes, but was unable to defeat China. Its [[attack on Pearl Harbor]] in December 1941 led to war with the [[United States]] and its [[allies of World War II|allies]].  After a series of naval victories by mid-1942, Japan's military forces were overextended and its industrial base was unable to provide the needed ships, armaments and oil. Even with his navy sunk and his main cities destroyed by air, the [[Hirohito|Emperor Shōwa]] held out until August 1945 when two atomic bombs and a Soviet invasion forced a [[surrender of Japan|surrender]]. 

[[Occupation of Japan|Occupied by the U.S.]] after the war and stripped of its entire [[Empire of Japan|Empire]], Japan was transformed into a peaceful and democratic nation. After 1950 it enjoyed [[Japanese post-war economic miracle|very high economic growth rates]], and became a world economic powerhouse, especially in engineering, automobiles and electronics. Since the 1990s economic stagnation has been a major issue, with an [[2011 Tōhoku earthquake and tsunami|earthquake and tsunami in 2011]] causing massive economic dislocations and loss of the [[nuclear power]] supply.

==Japanese prehistory==

===Paleolithic Age===
[[File:JapanesePolishedStoneAxes.JPG|thumb|left|180px|Polished stone axes, excavated at Hinatabayashi B site, [[Shinano, Nagano|Shinano city]], [[Nagano Prefecture|Nagano]]. Pre-Jōmon period, 30,000 BC. [[Tokyo National Museum]]]]
{{Main|Japanese Paleolithic}}
The [[Japanese Paleolithic]] age covers a lengthy period starting as early as 50,000 BC and ending sometime around 12,000 BC, at the end of the last [[ice age]]. Artifacts claimed to be older than ca. 38,000 BC are not generally accepted, and most historians therefore believe that the Japanese Paleolithic started after 40,000 years ago.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.t-net.ne.jp/~keally/palaeol.html Japanese Palaeolithic Period], Charles T. Keally&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Japanese archipelago]] would become disconnected from the mainland continent after the last ice age, around 11,000 BC. After a [[Japanese paleolithic hoax|hoax]] by an amateur researcher, [[Shinichi Fujimura]], had been exposed,&lt;ref&gt;[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20001107a9.html Archaeology center sorry for fake finds]. Japan Times. November 7, 2000. Retrieved on 2011-10-29.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Lower Paleolithic|Lower]] and [[Middle Paleolithic]] evidence reported by Fujimura and his associates has been rejected after thorough reinvestigation.

As a result of the fallout over the hoax, now only some [[Upper Paleolithic]] evidence (not associated with Fujimura) can possibly be considered as having been well established.

==Ancient Japan==

===Jōmon period===
[[File:MiddleJomonVessel.JPG|thumb|left|200px|A Middle Jōmon vessel (3000–2000 BC)]]
{{Main|Jōmon period}}
The [[Jōmon period]] lasted from about 14,000 until 300 BC. The first signs of civilization and stable living patterns appeared around 14,000 BC with the Jōmon culture, characterized by a [[Mesolithic]] to [[Neolithic]] semi-sedentary [[hunter-gatherer]] lifestyle of wood [[stilt house]] and pit dwellings and a rudimentary form of [[agriculture]].

[[Weaving]] was still unknown at the time and clothes were often made of furs. The Jōmon people started to make clay vessels, decorated with patterns made by impressing the wet clay with braided or unbraided cord and sticks. Based on [[Radiocarbon dating|radio-carbon]] dating, some of the  surviving examples of pottery  can be found in Japan along with daggers, jade, combs made of shells, and various other household items dated to the 11th millennium&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The earliest known pottery comes from Japan, and is dated to about 10,600 BC. China and Indo-China followed shortly afterward&quot; (&quot;Past Worlds&quot; The Times Atlas of Archeology. p. 100, 1995).&lt;/ref&gt;

The most recent finds, in 1998, have been at the [[Odai Yamamoto I site]], where fragments of a single vessel are dated to 14,500 BC (ca 16,500 [[Before Present|BP]]); this places them as or among the earliest pottery currently known in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Ancient Jomon of Japan (Case Studies in Early Societies) |author=Habu Junko |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-521-77213-6 |pages=34–42}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pref.aomori.lg.jp/bunka/culture/oodaiyamamoto.html |title=大平山元Ｉ遺跡 －日本最古の土器出土－ |trans_title=Ōdaiyamamoto Ichi Site – Excavation of Japan's Earliest Earthenware |language=Japanese |publisher=[[Aomori Prefecture]] |accessdate=12 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;World&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.world-archaeology.com/features/jomon-pottery-japan/ |title=Jomon pottery, Japan |author=Kaner, S. |work=[[Current World Archaeology]] |publisher=[[Current Publishing (UK)|Current Publishing]] |year=2003 |issue=1 |accessdate=12 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Among older discoveries, calibrated radiocarbon measures of carbonized material from pottery artifacts: Fukui Cave {{nowrap|12500 ± 350 BP}} and {{nowrap|12500 ± 500 BP}} (Kamaki &amp; Serizawa 1967), Kamikuroiwa [[rock shelter]] 12, 165 ± 350 years BP in Shikoku.&lt;ref&gt;(Esaka ''et al.'' 1967), from &quot;Prehistoric Japan&quot;, Keiji Imamura, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; although the specific dating is disputed.

Elaborate pottery figurines known as [[dogū]] are found from the Late Jōmon period.

===Yayoi period===
{{Main|Yayoi period}}
[[File:DotakuBronzeBellLateYayoi3rdCenturyCE.jpg|thumb|A Yayoi period [[Dōtaku]], 3rd century&amp;nbsp;AD]]
The [[Yayoi period]] lasted from about 400 or 300 BC until 250 AD. This period followed the Jōmon period and completely supplanted it. This period is named after Yayoi town, the subsection of [[Bunkyō, Tokyo]], where archaeological investigations uncovered its first recognized traces.

The start of the Yayoi period marked the influx of new practices such as weaving, rice farming, and iron and bronze making. Bronze and iron appear to have been simultaneously introduced into Yayoi Japan. Iron was mainly used for agricultural and other tools, whereas, bronze was used for ritual and ceremonial artifacts. Some casting of bronze and iron began in Japan by about 100&amp;nbsp;BC, but the raw materials for both metals were introduced from the Asian continent.  The Yayoi period brought [[Shamanism]] and divination by oracles to Shinto, in order to guarantee good crops.,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John Whitney Hall, ed., |title=The Cambridge History of Japan: Ancient Japan|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=A3_6lp8IOK8C&amp;pg=PA334|year=1993|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=334}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Japan first appeared in written records in 57 AD with the following mention in China's [[Book of the Later Han]]:&lt;ref&gt;後漢書, ''樂浪海外有東鯷人 分爲二十餘國''&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Across the ocean from [[Lelang Commandery|Lelang]] are the people of [[Wa (Japan)|Wa]]. Formed from more than one hundred tribes, they come and pay tribute frequently.&quot; The book also recorded that [[Suishō]], the king of Wa, presented slaves to the [[Emperor An of Han]] in&amp;nbsp;107. The ''[[Records of Three Kingdoms|Sanguo Zhi]]'', written in the 3rd century, noted that the country was the unification of some 30 small tribes or states and ruled by a shaman queen named [[Himiko (queen)|Himiko]] of [[Yamataikoku]].

During the [[Han Dynasty|Han]] and [[Cao Wei|Wei]] dynasties, Chinese travelers to [[Kyūshū]] recorded its inhabitants who claimed that they were the descendants of the Grand Count (Tàibó) of the [[Wu (state)|Wu]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}} The inhabitants also show traits of the pre-[[wiktionary:sinicize|sinicized]] Wu people with tattooing, teeth-pulling, and baby-carrying. The ''Sanguo Zhi'' records the physical descriptions which are similar to ones on ''[[haniwa]]'' statues, such as men wearing braided hair and tattoos and women wearing large, single-pieced clothing.

The [[Yoshinogari site]] in Kyūshū is the most famous archaeological site of the Yayoi period and reveals a large settlement continuously inhabited for several hundred years. Archaeological excavation has shown the most ancient parts to be from around 400&amp;nbsp;BC. It appears that the inhabitants had frequent communication and trade relations with the mainland. Today, some reconstructed buildings stand in the park on the archaeological site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Peter G. Stone|author2=Philippe G. Planel|title=The Constructed Past: Experimental Archaeology, Education and the Public|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=456jNSMNwrcC&amp;pg=PA66|year=1999|publisher=Psychology Press|page=66}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kofun period===
[[File:NintokuTomb.jpg|thumb|left|Daisenryō Kofun, [[Osaka Prefecture|Osaka]], 5th century.]]
{{Main|Kofun period}}
The [[Kofun period]] began around 250 AD, is named after the large [[tumulus]] burial mounds (''[[kofun]]'') that started appearing around that time.

The Kofun period (the ''&quot;Kofun-Jidai&quot;'') saw the establishment of strong military states, each of them concentrated around powerful clans (or ''[[zoku]]''). The establishment of the dominant Yamato [[polity]] was centered in the provinces of [[Yamato Province|Yamato]] and [[Kawachi Province|Kawachi]] from the 3rd century AD till the 7th century, establishing the origin of the [[List of Japanese monarchs|Japanese imperial lineage]]. And so the polity, by suppressing the clans and acquiring agricultural lands, maintained a strong influence in the western part of Japan.

Japan started to send [[List of tributaries of Imperial China|tributes to Imperial China]] in the 5th century. In the Chinese history records, the polity was called Wa, and its [[Five kings of Wa|five kings]] were recorded. Based upon the Chinese model, they developed a central administration and an imperial court system, with its society being organized into various occupation groups. Close relationships between the [[Three Kingdoms of Korea]] and Japan began during the middle of this period, around the end of the 4th century.

==Classical Japan==

===Asuka period===
[[File:Takamat1.jpg|thumb|200px|Mural painting on the wall of the [[Takamatsuzuka Tomb]], [[Asuka, Nara|Asuka]], [[Nara Prefecture|Nara]], 8th century]]
{{Main|Asuka period}}
During the [[Asuka period]] (538 to 710), the proto-Japanese Yamato polity gradually became a clearly centralized state, defining and applying a code of governing laws, such as the [[Taika Reforms]] and [[Taihō Code]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HOJ&quot;&gt;Mason, R.H.P and Caiger, J.G, A History of Japan, Revised Edition, Tuttle Publishing, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Also during the same period, the Japanese developed strong economic ties with the Paikche or [[Baekje kingdom|Baekje]] people, who lived on the southwestern coast of the Korean Peninsula. Good relations with the Baekje had begun in 391 when a Japanese expedition saved the King of Baekje and the Baekje people from their traditional enemies—the [[Koguryo]] people—who lived in the northern part of the Korean Peninsula.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Indeed, Buddhism was introduced to Japan in 538 by [[Baekje kingdom|Baekje]] people, to whom Japan continued to provide military support.&lt;ref&gt;See ''[[Nihon Shoki]]'', volumes 19, Story of Kinmei. [http://applepig.idv.tw/kuon/furu/text/syoki/syoki19_2.htm#sk19_11]&quot;''[[Nihon Shoki]]''&lt;/ref&gt;
In Japan, however, Buddhism was promoted largely by the ruling class for their own purposes{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}. Accordingly, in the early stages, Buddhism was not a popular religion with the common people of Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; However, the introduction of [[Buddhism in Japan|Buddhism]] led to a discontinuing of the practice of burying deceased people in large kofuns. 
 
[[Prince Shōtoku]] came to power in Japan as Regent to Empress Suiko in 594. Empress Suiko had come to the throne as the niece of the previous Emperor—Sujun (588–593)--who had been assassinated in 593. Empress Suiko had also been married to a prior Emperor—Bidatsu (572–585), but she was the first female ruler of Japan since the legendary matriarchal times.&lt;ref name=&quot;George Sansom p. 50&quot;&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

As Regent to Empress Suiko, Prince Shotoku devoted his efforts to the spread of Buddhism and [[Culture of China|Chinese culture]] in Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;George Sansom p. 50&quot;/&gt; He is also credited with bringing relative peace to Japan through the proclamation of the [[Seventeen-article constitution]], a [[Confucian]] style document that focused on the kinds of morals and virtues that were to be expected of government officials and the [[Emperor of Japan|emperor's]] subjects. Buddhism would become a permanent part of Japanese culture.

A letter brought to the [[Emperor of China]] by an [[Imperial embassies to China|emissary]] from Japan in 607 stated that the &quot;Emperor of the Land where the Sun rises (Japan) sends a letter to the Emperor of the land where Sun sets (China)&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[Book of Sui]] (隋書 東夷伝 第81巻列伝46): &quot;日出处天子至书日没处天子无恙&quot; [http://www.guoxue.com/shibu/24shi/suisu/sui_081.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; thereby implying an equal footing with China which angered the Chinese emperor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=general editors|title=The Cambridge history of Japan|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, UK|year=1988|pages=182–183|isbn=0-521-22352-0|oclc=|doi=|author-separator=,|author2=John W. Hall...|display-authors=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nara period===
[[File:NaraTodaijiDaibutsu0212.jpg|thumb|left|200px|The Great [[Buddharupa|Buddha]] at [[Nara, Nara|Nara]], 752 AD.]]
{{Main|Nara period}}
The [[Nara period]] of the 8th century marked the emergence of a strong Japanese state and is often portrayed as a golden age. In 710, the capital city of Japan was moved from Asuka to Nara.&lt;ref name=&quot;George Sansom p. 82&quot;&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt; Hall (1966) concludes that &quot;Japan had been transformed from a loose federation of uji in the fifth century to an empire on the order of Imperial China in the eighth century. A new theory of state and a new structure of government supported the Japanese sovereign in the style and with the powers of an absolute monarch.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John W. Hall, ''Government and Local Power in Japan, 500–1700: A Study Based on Bizen Province'' (Princeton University Press, 1966) p 63.&lt;/ref&gt; Traditional, political, and economic practices were now organized through a rationally structured government apparatus that legally defined functions and precedents. Lands were surveyed and registered with the state. A powerful new aristocracy emerged.  This aristocracy controlled the state and was supported by taxes that were efficiently collected. The government built great public works, including government offices, temples, roads, and irrigation systems. A new system of land tenure and taxation, which was designed to widely spread land ownership  throughout the rural population, was introduced. Such allotments tended to be about one acre. However, they could be as small as one-tenth of an acre. However, lots for slaves were about two-thirds the size of the allotments to free men. Allotments were reviewed every five years when the census was conducted.&lt;ref name=s83&gt;Sansom (1958) pp. 83–84.&lt;/ref&gt;

There was a cultural flowering during this period.&lt;ref name=&quot;George Sansom p. 82&quot;/&gt; Soon, dramatic new cultural manifestations characterized the Nara period, which lasted four centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Hall (1966) p 64&lt;/ref&gt;

Following an imperial [[Wiktionary:rescript|rescript]] by [[Empress Gemmei]], the capital was moved to [[Heijō Palace|Heijō-kyō]], present-day [[Nara, Nara|Nara]], in 710. The city was modeled on [[Chang'an]] (now [[Xi'an]]), the capital of the Chinese [[Tang Dynasty]].

During the Nara Period, political development was marked by a struggle between the [[Imperial House of Japan|imperial family]] and the Buddhist clergy,&lt;ref name=s83/&gt; as well as between the imperial family and the regents—the [[Fujiwara clan]]. Japan did enjoy peaceful relations with their traditional foes—the [[Silla]] people—who occupied the southeast coast of the Korean Peninsula. Japan also established formal relationships with the Tang dynasty of China.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 128&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 784, the capital was again moved to [[Nagaoka-kyō]] to escape the Buddhist priests; in 794, it was moved to [[Heian-kyō]], present-day [[Kyoto|Kyōto]]. The capital was to remain in Kyoto until 1868.&lt;ref name=&quot;George Sansom p. 99&quot;&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; In the religious town of Kyoto, Buddhism and Shinto began to form a syncretic system.&lt;ref&gt;Elmer M. Brown, ed. ''The Cambridge history of Japan: Ancient Japan: Volume 1'' (1993) p. 356 ISBN 0-521-22352-0&lt;/ref&gt;

Historical writing in Japan culminated in the early 8th century with the massive chronicles, the ''[[Kojiki]]'' (''The Record of Ancient Matters'', 712) and the ''[[Nihon Shoki]]'' (''Chronicles of Japan'', 720). These chronicles give a legendary account of Japan's beginnings, today known as the [[Japanese mythology]]. According to the myths contained in these chronicles, Japan was founded in 660&amp;nbsp;BC by the ancestral [[Emperor Jimmu]], a direct descendant of the [[Shinto|Shintō]] deity, [[Amaterasu]] (Sun Goddess). The myths recorded that Jimmu started a line of emperors that remains to this day. Historians assume that the myths partly describe historical facts, but the first emperor who actually existed was [[Emperor Ōjin]], though the date of his reign is uncertain. Since the Nara period, actual political power has not been in the hands of the emperor but has, instead, been exercised at different times by the court nobility, warlords, the military, and, more recently, the [[Prime Minister of Japan]].

===Heian period===
{{Main|Heian period}}
[[File:西寺復元模型.jpg|thumb|left|Miniature model of [[Heian-kyō]]]]
The [[Heian period]], lasting from 794 to 1185, is the final period of classical Japanese history. It is considered the peak of the Japanese imperial court and noted for its [[Japanese art|art]], especially its [[Japanese poetry|poetry]] and [[Japanese literature|literature]]. In the early 11th century, [[Murasaki Shikibu|Lady Shikibu Murasaki]] wrote Japan's (and one of the world's) oldest surviving novels, ''[[The Tale of Genji]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 150.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Man'yōshū]]&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) pp. 92–96.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Kokin Wakashū]],&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) pp. 130–131.&lt;/ref&gt; the oldest existing collections of Japanese poetry, were compiled during this period.

Strong differences from mainland Asian cultures emerged (such as an indigenous writing system, the [[kana]]). Due to the decline of the Tang Dynasty,&lt;ref&gt;Fairbank, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; Chinese influence had reached its peak, and then effectively ended, with the last imperially sanctioned mission to Tang China in 838, although trade expeditions and Buddhist pilgrimages to China continued.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/heia/hd_heia.htm Heian Period],&quot; Metropolitan Museum of Art.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Genji emaki TAKEKAWA.jpg|thumb|A handscroll painting dated circa 1130, illustrating a scene from the &quot;Bamboo River&quot; chapter of the ''[[Tale of Genji]]'']]
Political power in the imperial court was in the hands of powerful aristocratic families (''[[kuge]]''), especially the [[Fujiwara clan]], who ruled under the titles [[Sesshō and Kampaku]] (imperial regents). The Fujiwara clan obtained almost complete control over the imperial family. However, the Fugiwara Regents who advised the Imperial Court were content to derive their authority from imperial line. This meant that the Fujiwara authority could always be challenged by a vigorous emperor. Fujiwara domination of the Court during the time from 858 until about 1160 led to this period being called &quot;the Fujiwara Period.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;transformation351&quot;&gt;Fairbank, p. 351.&lt;/ref&gt; The Fujiwara clan gained this ascendancy because of their matrimonial links with the imperial family.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, because of the number of emperors that were born to Fujiwara mothers, the Fujiwara Regents became so closely identified with the imperial family, that people saw no difference between the &quot;direct rule&quot; by the imperial family and the rule of the Fujiwara Regents.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 212.&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, when dissatisfaction with the government arose resulting in the [[Hogen Rebellion]] (1156–1158), the [[Heiji Rebellion]] (1160) and the [[Gempei War]] (1180–1185), the target of the dissatisfaction was the Fujiwara Regents, as well as the Imperial family. The [[Gempei War]] ended in 1185 with the naval battle of Dan-no-ura in which the Minamoto clan defeated the Taira clan.  In 1192, the Court appointed [[Yoritomo]] of the Minamoto clan to a number of high positions in government. These positions were consolidated and Yoritomo became the first person to be designated the ''Seii-tai-shogun'' or &quot;Shogun.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;transformation363&quot;&gt;Fairbank, p. 363.&lt;/ref&gt; Yoritomo then defeated the Fujiwara clan in a military campaign in the north of Japan. This spelled the end of the Fujiwara Period and the end of Fujiwara influence over the government. 

The end of the period saw the rise of various military clans. The four most powerful clans were the [[Minamoto clan]], the [[Taira clan]], the [[Fujiwara clan]], and the [[Tachibana clan (kuge)|Tachibana clan]]. Towards the end of the 12th century, conflicts between these clans turned into civil war, such as the [[Hōgen Rebellion|Hōgen]] (1156–1158). The Hogen Rebellion was of cardinal importance to Japan, since it was the turning point that led to the first stages of the development of feudalism in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) pp. 210–211.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Heiji Rebellion]] of 1160 also occurred during this period&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 257.&lt;/ref&gt; and the uprising was followed by the [[Genpei War]], from which emerged a society led by [[samurai]] clans under the political rule of the [[shogun|shōgun]]—the beginnings of feudalism in Japan. 

[[File:Byodo-in Uji01pbs2640.jpg|thumb|[[Byōdō-in]] (1053) is a temple of [[Pure Land Buddhism]]. It was registered to the UNESCO World Heritage Site.]]
Buddhism began to spread during the Heian Period. However, Buddhism was split between two sects—the [[Tendai]] sect which had been brought to Japan from China by [[Saichō]] (767–822) and the [[Shingon Buddhism|Shingon]] sect which had been introduced from China by [[Kūkai]] (774–835). Whereas, the Tendai sect tended to be a monastic form of Buddhism which established isolated monasteries or temples on the tops of mountains,&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; the Shingon variation of Buddhism was a less philosophical and more practical and more popular version of the religion.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pure Land Buddhism]] ([[Jōdo-shū]], [[Jōdo Shinshū]]) was a form of Buddhism which was much simpler than either the Tendai or Shingon versions of Buddhism. Pure Land Buddhism became very popular in Japan during a time of degeneration and trouble in the latter half of the 11th century.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 224.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Feudal Japan (1185–1868)==
The &quot;[[Feudalism|feudal]]&quot; period of Japanese history, dominated by the powerful regional families ([[daimyo|daimyō]]) and the military rule of warlords (shōgun), stretched from 1185 to 1868. The emperor remained but was mostly kept to a ''[[de jure]]'' figurehead ruling position, and the power of merchants was weak. This time is usually divided into periods following the reigning family of the shōgun.

===Kamakura period===
{{Main|Kamakura period}}
The [[Kamakura period]], 1185 to 1333, is a period that marks the governance of the [[Kamakura shogunate]] and the transition to the Japanese &quot;medieval&quot; era, a nearly 700-year period in which the emperor, the court, and the traditional central government were left intact but largely relegated to ceremonial functions. Civil, military, and judicial matters were controlled by the ''bushi'' (samurai) class, the most powerful of whom was the ''[[de facto]]'' national ruler, the shōgun. This period in Japan differed from the old ''[[shōen]]'' system in its pervasive military emphasis.

In 1185, [[Minamoto no Yoritomo]] and his younger brother, [[Minamoto no Yoshitsune|Yoshitsune]] defeated the rival [[Taira clan]] at the naval battle of Dan-no-ura.&lt;ref&gt;Fairbank, p. 362.&lt;/ref&gt; The outcome of the Battle of Dan-no-ura meant the rise of the warrior or samurai class. Under the feudal structure that was arising in Japan, the samurai owed military service and loyalty to the emperor. The Samurai, in turn required loyalty and work from the peasants who rented land from them and served them. On occasion the samurai would conduct warfare against each other, which caused disruption to the society. In 1192, Yoritomo was appointed ''Seii Tai-Shōgun'' by the emperor.&lt;ref name=&quot;transformation363&quot;/&gt; The shogun was expected to run the day-to-day affairs of the government on behalf of the emperor and to keep the samurai in line. During this time the Imperial Court remained in their capital of Kyoto. Society at Kyoto was regarded as more refined and cultured than the rest of the country.&lt;ref name=s421&gt;Sansom (1958) p. 421.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Yoritomo established his base of power called the [[Bakufu]] in the seaside town of [[Kamakura, Kanagawa|Kamakura]].&lt;ref name=&quot;transformation363&quot;/&gt; Yoritomo became the first in a line of shōguns who ruled from Kamakura. Thus, the period of time from 1185 until 1334 became known as the period of the Kamakura Shogunate. Society in the military or samurai capital of Kamakura was regarded as rough and ignorant by comparison with the refined society at Kyoto.&lt;ref name=s421/&gt; However, Yoritomo wished to free his government from the pernicious influence of the bureaucracy in Kyoto and, thus remained in Kamakura. The Kamakura Shogunate based itself on the interests of this rising class rather than on the bureaucracy at Kyoto. Accordingly, the preference of Kamakura as the capital of the shogunate fit this new warrior class. 

Yoritomo was married to Hōjō Masako of the Hōjō clan, herself a Sensei (teacher) in [[kyujutsu]] (the art of the bow) and [[kenjutsu]] (the art of the sword), and she contributed much to his ascent and organizing the Bafuku. However, after Yoritomo's death, another warrior clan, the [[Hōjō clan|Hōjō]], came to rule as ''[[shikken]]'' (regents) for the shōgun.

[[File:Mokoshuraiekotoba.jpg|thumb|260px|Japanese [[samurai]] boarding Mongol ships in 1281]]
A traumatic event of the period was the [[Mongol invasions of Japan]] in 1274 and in 1281. Massive Mongol forces with superior naval technology and weaponry attempted a full-scale invasion of the Japanese islands in both 1274 and in 1281. However, a famous [[typhoon]] referred to as ''[[Kamikaze (typhoon)|kamikaze]]'' (translating as ''divine wind'' in Japanese) is credited with devastating both Mongol invasion forces and saving Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Rossabi |first=Morris |title=Khubilai Khan: his life and times |publisher=University of California Press |year=1988 |page=207 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sJd-OqqnUBwC&amp;pg=PA207&amp;dq=KAMIKAZE#v=onepage&amp;q=KAMIKAZE&amp;f=false |isbn=0-520-06740-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Japanese were successful in stopping the Mongols, the invasion attempt had devastating domestic repercussions, leading to the extinction of the Kamakura shogunate. For two decades after the second failed Mongol invasion of Japan, the Japanese remained fearful of a third Mongol attempt. (Indeed, Japan could not rest assured of peace until the death of Kublai Khan in 1294.) Consequently, the shogun required the various samurai spend money lavishly on armed forces in order to remain in a high state of readiness for the expected third attack by the Mongols. This vast expenditure of money had a ruinous effect on the economy of Japan. The Kamakura Shogunate could perhaps have survived the strain of the continual military readiness and the resultant bad economy if that had been the only problem. However, upon the death of Emperor Go-Saga in 1272, there arose a bitter dispute over succession to the throne within the imperial family.

===Kemmu Restoration===
{{Main|Kemmu Restoration}}
In 1333, the Kamakura shogunate was overthrown in a [[coup d'état]] known as the [[Kemmu Restoration]], led by [[Emperor Go-Daigo]] and his followers ([[Ashikaga Takauji]], [[Nitta Yoshisada]], and [[Kusunoki Masashige]]). Emperor Go-Daigo had come to the throne in 1318. From the beginning, Go-Daigo had made it clear that he was not going to abdicate and become a &quot;cloistered emperor&quot; and that he was intending to rule Japan from his palace in Kyoto, independent of the Kamakura Shogunate.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; Go-Daigo and his supporters went to war against the Kamakura Shogunate, the Imperial House was restored to political influence, and the government was now civilian one, replacing the military government of the Kamakura Shogunate. However, this did not last. The warrior class throughout Japan was in tumult.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated35&quot;&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Go-Daigo was not a gifted leader, tending, instead, to alienate people.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated35&quot;/&gt; One of those that was alienated by Go-Daigo, was his former supporter, Ashikaga Takauji. Ashikaga Takauji found that he had support from other regional warlords in Japan. In early 1335, Ashikaga left Kyoto and moved to Kamakura.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; Ashikaga, then began assuming powers that had not been given him by the Emperor. This brought Ashikaga Takauji in direct conflict with the governmental officials in Kyoto, including his old allies, Nitta Yoshisada and Kusunoki Masashige. However, by assuming shogun-like powers, Ashikaga appeared to be standing up for the warrior class against the civilian authority that seemed intent on destroying the power of the warriors. Accordingly, Ashikaga Takauji was joined in Kamakura by a number of other regional warlords. On November 17, 1335, Ashikaga Tadayoshi, brother of Takauji, issued a call (in the name of his brother Takauji) asking the warriors throughout the country to &quot;assemble your clansmen and hasten to join me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; Dissatisfaction with Go-Daigo was so strong that a majority of the warriors in Japan answered this call.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; 

After initial defeats on the main island of [[Honshu]], Ashikaga and his troops retreated to the southern island of [[Kyushu]], where he immediately won over most of the regional warlords to his side and defeated the few who remained loyal to Go-Daigo. With all of the island of Kyushu in his hands, Ashikaga Takauji invaded the main island of Honshu again and, in 1336, at the decisive [[Battle of Minatogawa]], or the Battle of Minato River, defeated the armed forces of Nitta Yoshisada and Kusunoki Masanori and the other loyalist forces of Go-Daigo. The victorious warrior-class forces gathered around the town of Kamakura became known as the &quot;Northern Court.&quot; The Loyalist forces may have been defeated but they survived to fight on. They formed the &quot;Southern Court&quot; and upon the death of Go-Daigo in the late summer of 1339, they rallied around the person of Prince Kazuhito who was enthroned as [[Emperor Kōgon]]. Prince Kazuhito was from a younger line of descendents in the Imperial family and, thus, his supporters were supporters of the &quot;junior line.&quot; On September 20, 1336, the Ashikaga coalition of samurai opposed to Go-Daigo enthroned [[Prince Yutahito]] as [[Emperor Kōmyo]].&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; Prince Yutahito was from the &quot;senior line&quot; of descendents in the Imperial family. Accordingly, the civil war between the warriors led by the Ashikaga clan—the Northern Court on the one hand and the &quot;Loyalist&quot; Southern Court on the other hand, became a civil war of imperial succession between followers of the &quot;senior&quot; and &quot;junior&quot; lines of succession in the Imperial family. The warriors and the Ashikaga clan captured Kyoto and proceeded to move their forces from Kamakura to Kyoto. Meanwhile, the Southern Court deposed from their capital in Kyoto, now established themselves in Yoshino. 
 
The Ashikaga Shogunate was never able to control and centralize the government over the entire country. Rather they ruled because of a narrow and shifting majority of warlords who supported them. There were always some warlords that acted independently of either the Northern Court or the Southern Court. Later, during the war of succession, these independent warlords enthroned a third emperor—Emperor Suko. So the civil war of succession became a three-cornered affair. The prestige of the throne declined as the civil war continued. This had the effect of bolstering the idea that the Imperial family should be removed from politics and strengthened the need for a shogun to be appointed to run the government on a day-to-day basis. 
 
In 1338, Ashikaga Takauji was officially appointed as Shogun by the new Emperor. He was the first of a line of Ashikaga shoguns. The attempted restoration of independent power of the throne—the Kemmu Restoration—was at an end and the period of the Ashikaga Shogunate had begun.

The civil war of succession to the throne was finally settled. As part of the settlement, all three &quot;emperors&quot; abdicated on April 6, 1352.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Ashikaga died in 1358 and Ashikaga Yoshiakira succeeded him as Shogun.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1368, however, the ascendancy of the Ashikaga Shogunate was so complete that Ashikaga Yoshimitsu was able to rule Japan without reference to the emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) pp. 141–142.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1392, the Southern Court and the Northern Court were finally merged under an agreement that placed Emperor Kogon, of the Southern Court and the junior line, on the throne and pledged that the throne would, henceforth, alternate between candidates of the Northern Court and the Southern Court. This agreement was, however, never implemented.

===Muromachi period===
[[File:Kinkakuji 2004-09-21.jpg|thumb|right|[[Kinkaku-ji]], Kyoto. 1397, in [[Kitayama period]]]]
{{Main|Muromachi period|Nanboku-chō period|Higashiyama period}}
During the [[Muromachi period]], the [[Ashikaga shogunate]] ruled for 237 years from 1336 to 1573. It was established by Ashikaga Takauji who seized political power from Emperor Go-Daigo. A majority of the warrior class supported the Ashikaga clan in the succession war. After taking Kyoto from Emperor Go-Daigo, the Ashikaga clan made Kyoto, the capital of the Ashikaga Shogunate in late 1336.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt; This became the new capital of the Northern Court. Go-Daigo, then, moved to the town of [[Yoshino, Nara|Yoshino]] and established the new capital of the Southern Court there. This ended the attempted restoration of the powers of the throne—the Kemmu restoration. The early years (1336 to 1392) of the Muromachi period are known as the [[Nanboku-chō period|Nanboku-chō (Northern and Southern court) period]] because the imperial court was split in two. In 1392, the Northern court and the southern Court were finally merged and Emperor Kogon was placed on the throne. There was an agreement that, heretofore, succession to the throne would alternate between candidates of the Northern court and candidates of the Southern Court. However, this agreement was never acted upon. 

Rule of the Ashikaga Bakufu looked a lot like the rule of the Kamakura Bakufu, as the Ashikaga clan made few changes in the offices and councils of the prior government.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) pp. 143–144.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Ashikaga Shogunate dominated the Imperial throne more than the Kamakura Shogunate ever did. Nonetheless, the Ashikaga Shogunate was never able to centralize its power over the regional warlords as much as the prior Kamakura government. The Ashikaga Shogunate was based on a coalition of a loose majority of the various regional warlords across the country. As a consequence, the Ashikaga Shogunate was unable to do anything about the problem of the pirates who were operating off their own shores, despite repeated requests to do so by both Korea&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) pp. 178–179&lt;/ref&gt; and Ming dynasty China.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt; Warlord clans, like the [[Kotsuna]] clan and the Kiyomori branch of the Taira clan, that lived along the coast of the [[Seto Inland Sea|Inland Sea]], made money from the pirates and supported them.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) p. 177.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1368, the [[Ming Dynasty]] replaced the [[Yuan Dynasty]] of the [[Mongols]] in China. Japanese trade with China had been frozen since the second and final attempt by Mongol China to invade Japan in 1281. Now a new trade relationship began with the new Ming rulers in China. Part of the new trade with China was the coming to Japan of Zen Buddhist monks. During the Ashikaga Shogunate Zen Buddhism came to have a great influence with the ruling class in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Sansom (1961) pp. 157–158.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Muromachi period ended in 1573 when the 15th and last shōgun, [[Ashikaga Yoshiaki]], was driven out of the capital in Kyoto by [[Oda Nobunaga]].

In the viewpoint of a cultural history, [[Kitayama period]] (end of 14th – first half of 15th century&lt;ref name=&quot;Japanese About Muromachi Culture&quot;&gt;[http://www.isu.edu.tw/upload/84203/17/files/dept_17_lv_3_13436.pdf (Japanese) About Muromachi Culture]. (PDF) . Retrieved on 2011-10-29.&lt;/ref&gt;) and [[Higashiyama period]] (second half of 15th – first half of 16th century&lt;ref name=&quot;Japanese About Muromachi Culture&quot;/&gt;) exist in Muromachi period.

===Sengoku period===
[[File:Osaka Castle 02bs3200.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Osaka Castle]]]]
[[File:HasekuraWithShipDetail.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Hasekura Tsunenaga]] and [[Japanese warship San Juan Bautista|San Juan Bautista]]]]
{{Main|Sengoku period}}
{{See also|Nanban trade|Kirishitan}}
The later years of the Muromachi period, 1467 to 1573, are also known as the [[Sengoku period]] (Period of Warring Kingdoms), a time of intense internal warfare, and correspond with the period of the first contacts with the West—the arrival of [[Portugal|Portuguese]] &quot;[[Nanban trade|Nanban]]&quot; traders.

In 1543, a Portuguese ship, blown off its course to China, landed on [[Tanegashima|Tanegashima Island]]. Firearms introduced by the Portuguese would bring the major innovation of the Sengoku period, culminating in the [[Battle of Nagashino]] where reportedly 3,000 [[arquebus]]es (the actual number is believed to be around 2,000) cut down charging ranks of samurai. During the following years, traders from Portugal, the [[Netherlands]], [[England]], and [[Spain]] arrived, as did [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]], [[Dominican Order|Dominican]], and [[Franciscan]] missionaries.

===Azuchi-Momoyama period===
{{Main|Azuchi-Momoyama period}}
The [[Azuchi-Momoyama period]] runs from approximately 1568 to 1603. The period, regarded as the late Warring Kingdoms period, marks the military reunification and stabilization of the country under a single political ruler, first by the campaigns of [[Oda Nobunaga]] (1534–1582) who almost united Japan. Nobunaga decided to reduce the power of the Buddhist priests, and gave protection to Christianity. He slaughtered many Buddhist priests and captured their fortified temples. He was killed in a revolt in 1582.&lt;ref&gt;John Whitney Hall, ed. ''The Cambridge History of Japan, Vol. 4: Early Modern Japan'' (1991) [http://www.amazon.com/Cambridge-History-Japan-Vol-Modern/dp/0521223555/ table of contents]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Frare crucificat.jpg|thumb|130px|Drawing about Catholic monks executed on 5 February 1597.]]
Unification was finally achieved by one of Nobunaga's generals, [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]]. 

After having united Japan, [[Japanese invasions of Korea (1592–1598)|Hideyoshi invaded Korea]] in an attempt to conquer Korea and points beyond. However, after two unsuccessful campaigns towards the allied forces of Korea and China and his death, his forces returned to Japan in 1598. Following his death, Japan experienced a short period of succession conflict. [[Tokugawa Ieyasu]], one of the regents for Hideyoshi's young heir, emerged victorious at the [[Battle of Sekigahara]] and seized political power.

===Christian missions===
{{main|History of Roman Catholicism in Japan}}
Catholic Jesuit missionaries led by [[Francis Xavier]] (1506–1552) arrived in 1549 and were welcomed in Kyoto.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Richmond Ellis, &quot;The Best Thus Far Discovered”: The Japanese in the Letters of St. Francisco Xavier,&quot; ''Hispanic Review,'' Vol. 71 No. 2 (Spring 2003), pp. 155–169 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3247185 in jstor]&lt;/ref&gt; Their proselytizing was most successful in Kyushu, with about 100,000 to 200,000 converts, including many daimyo.&lt;ref&gt;Otis Cary, [http://books.google.com/books?id=ldtBAAAAIAAJ ''A History of Christianity in Japan: Roman Catholic and Greek Orthodox missions''] (1909) pp. 13–241&lt;/ref&gt; In 1587, Hideyoshi reversed course and decided the Christian presence was divisive and might present the Europeans with an opportunity to disrupt Japan. The Christians missionaries were seen as a threat; the Portuguese merchants were allowed to continue their operations. The edict was not immediately enforced but restrictions grew tighter in the next three decades until a full-scale government persecution destroyed the Christian community by the 1620s. The Jesuits were expelled, churches and schools were torn down, and the daimyo were forbidden to become Christians. Converts who did not reject Christianity were killed. Many Christians went underground, becoming {{nihongo|[[Kakure Kirishitan|hidden Christians]]|隠れキリシタン|kakure kirishitan}}, but their communities died out. Not until the 1870s was Christianity re-established in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Jurgis Ellisonas, [http://books.google.com/books?id=6RBXXJixf-sC&amp;pg=PA301 &quot;Christianity and the daimyo,&quot;] in Hall, ed. ''The Cambridge History of Japan: Early modern Japan'' Cambridge University Press, 1991, pp. 301–72 ISBN 0-521-22355-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;George Elison, ''Deus Destroyed: The Image of Christianity in Early Modern Japan'' (1988) University of Michigan ISBN 0-674-19962-6&lt;/ref&gt;

==Edo (&quot;Tokugawa&quot;) period (1603–1868)==
{{Main|Edo period}}
[[File:Map of Japan appears in the Cihannuma.jpg|thumb|Map of Japan appears in the Cihannuma]]
[[File:Tokugawa Ieyasu2.JPG|thumb||200px|[[Tokugawa Ieyasu]], first [[shogun]] of the [[Tokugawa shogunate]]]]
The Edo or Tokugawa era saw power centralized in the hands of a hereditary shogunate that took control of religion, regulated the entire economy, subordinated the nobility, and set up uniform systems of taxation, government spending and bureaucracies. It avoided international involvement and wars, established a national judiciary and suppressed protest and criticism. The Tokugawa era brought peace, and that brought prosperity to a nation of 31 million.

===Economy===
About 80% of the people were rice farmers.&lt;ref&gt;Susan B. Hanley and Kozo Yamamura, ''Economic and demographic change in preindustrial Japan, 1600–1868'' (1977) pp. 69–90 ISBN 0-691-10055-1&lt;/ref&gt; Rice production increased steadily, but population remained stable, so prosperity increased. Rice paddies grew from 1.6 million chō in 1600 to 3 million by 1720.&lt;ref&gt;One chō, or chobu, equals 2.5 acres.&lt;/ref&gt; Improved technology helped farmers control the all-important flow of irrigation to their paddies. The daimyos operated several hundred castle towns, which became loci of domestic trade. Large-scale rice markets developed, centered on Edo and Osaka.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Conrad D. Totman|title=A history of Japan|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=UJLtPR_gMtsC&amp;pg=PA225|year=2000|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-21447-2|chapter=ch. 11}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the cities and towns, guilds of merchants and artisans met the growing demand for goods and services. The merchants, while low in status, prospered, especially those with official patronage. Merchants invented credit instruments to transfer money, currency came into common use, and the strengthening credit market encouraged entrepreneurship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Tetsuji Okazaki|title=The role of the merchant coalition in pre-modern Japanese economic development: an historical institutional analysis|journal=Explorations in Economic History|year=2005|volume= 42 |issue =2|pages=184–201|url=http://www2.e.u-tokyo.ac.jp/cemano/research/DP/documents/coe-f-33.pdf|doi=10.1016/j.eeh.2004.06.005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The samurai, forbidden to engage in farming or business but allowed to borrow money, borrowed too much. One scholar observed that the entire military class was living &quot;as in an inn, that is, consuming now and paying later&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKayHill1992&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=John P. McKay|author2=Bennett D. Hill|author3=John Buckler|title=A History of World Societies: Since 1500|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=9ux63MLJzdAC|accessdate=2012-06-08|year=1992|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company|isbn=978-0-395-47295-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bakufu and daimyos raised taxes on farmers, but did not tax business, so they too fell into debt. By 1750 rising taxes incited peasant unrest and even revolt. The nation had to deal somehow with samurai impoverishment and treasury deficits. The financial troubles of the samurai undermined their loyalties to the system, and the empty treasury threatened the whole system of government. One solution was reactionary—with prohibitions on spending for luxuries. Other solutions were modernizing, with the goal of increasing agrarian productivity. The eighth Tokugawa shogun, [[Tokugawa Yoshimune]] (in office 1716–1745) had considerable success, though much of his work had to be done again between 1787 and 1793 by the shogun's chief councilor [[Matsudaira Sadanobu]] (1759–1829). Other shoguns debased the coinage to pay debts, which caused inflation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Herman Ooms|title=Charismatic bureaucrat: a political biography of Matsudaira Sadanobu, 1758–1829|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5yArAAAAIAAJ|year=1975|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|isbn=978-0-226-63031-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

By 1800 the commercialization of the economy grew rapidly, bringing more and more remote villages into the national economy. Rich farmers appeared who switched from rice to high-profit commercial crops and engaged in local money-lending, trade, and small-scale manufacturing. Some wealthy merchants sought higher social status by using money to marry into the samurai class.

A few domains, notably [[Chōshū Domain|Chōshū]] and [[Satsuma Domain|Satsuma]], used innovative methods to restore their finances, but most sunk further into debt. The financial crisis provoked a reactionary solution near the end of the &quot;[[Tenpō Reforms]]&quot; (1830–1843) promulgated by the chief counselor [[Mizuno Tadakuni]]. He raised taxes, denounced luxuries and tried to impede the growth of business; he failed and it appeared to many that the continued existence of the entire Tokugawa system was in jeopardy.&lt;ref&gt;James L. McClain, ''Japan: A Modern History'' (2001) pp. 128–29 ISBN 0-393-04156-5&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social structure===
Japanese society had an elaborate social structure, in which everyone knew their place and level of prestige. At the top were the emperor and the court nobility, invincible in prestige but weak in power. Next came the &quot;bushi&quot; of shogun, daimyo and layers of feudal lords whose rank was indicated by their closeness to the Tokugawa. They had power. The &quot;daimyo&quot; comprised about 250 local lords of local &quot;han&quot; with annual outputs of 50,000 or more bushels of rice. The upper strata was much given to elaborate and expensive rituals, including elegant architecture, landscaped gardens, Noh drama, patronage of the arts, and the tea ceremony.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Conrad D. Totman|title=A history of Japan|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=UJLtPR_gMtsC&amp;pg=PA225|year=2000|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|isbn=978-0-631-21447-2|pages=225–230}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Samurai====
{{main|Samurai}}
Next in the social structure were the 400,000 warriors, called &quot;samurai&quot;, whose ranks ranged in numerous grades and degrees. A few upper samurai were eligible for high office; most were foot soldiers (ashigaru) with minor duties. The samurai were affiliated with senior lords in a well-established chain of command. The shogun had 17,000 samurai retainers; the daimyo each had hundreds. Most lived in modest homes near their lord's headquarters, and lived off hereditary rights to collect rents and stipends. Together these high status groups comprised Japan's ruling class making up about 6% of the total population.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan Clements, ''A Brief History of the Samurai'', Running Press (2010) ISBN 0-7624-3850-9&lt;/ref&gt;

====Lower orders====
The lower social orders were divided into two main segments—the peasants—80% of the population—whose high prestige as producers was undercut by their burden as the chief source of taxes. They were illiterate and lived in villages controlled by appointed officials who kept the peace and collected taxes. Peasants and villagers frequently engaged in unlawful and disruptive protests, especially after 1780.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Anne Walthall|title=Peasant uprisings in Japan: a critical anthology of peasant histories|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mXiwI_oZfyoC|year=1991|publisher=University of Chicago Press|isbn=978-0-226-87234-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Merchants and artisans====
Near the bottom of the prestige scale—but much higher up in terms of income and life style—were the merchants and artisans of the towns and cities. They had no political power, and even rich merchants found it difficult to rise in the world in a society in which place and standing were fixed at birth.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Sheldon, ''The rise of the merchant class in Tokugawa Japan, 1600–1868'' (1973)&lt;/ref&gt; Finally came the entertainers, prostitutes, day laborers and servants, and the thieves, beggars and hereditary outcasts. They were tightly controlled by local officials and were not allowed to mingle with higher status people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Gerald Groemer|title=The Creation of the Edo Outcaste Order|jstor=3591967|journal=Journal of Japanese Studies|year=2001|volume=27|issue= 2|pages=263–83|doi=10.2307/3591967}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Literacy====
Literacy was highly prized, albeit made difficult by the writing system. Wood block printing had been standard for centuries; after 1500 Japanese printers experimented with movable type, but reverted to the wood blocks. By the 1780s Japan was publishing 3000 books a year (compared with 400 in Russia). By the 1850s the major new trend was the translation of western scientific and geographical books, which reached a wide audience. By 1860 about 40% of the men and 10% of the women were literate in rural areas, with much higher rates in the cities, such as 80% in Edo (Tokyo).&lt;ref&gt;Cyril E. Black ''et al.'', ''The Modernization of Japan and Russia: A Comparative Study'' Free Press (1975) pp. 106–9 ISBN 0-02-906850-9&lt;/ref&gt; Universal compulsory education only began in 1871.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Richard Rubinger|title=Popular literacy in early modern Japan|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mYkLNEczmogC&amp;pg=PA139|year=2007|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|isbn=978-0-8248-3124-0|pages=139–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Government===
[[File:Tokugawa Yoshimune.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Tokugawa Yoshimune]] the Shogun 1716–1745]]
During the [[Edo period]], also called the '''Tokugawa period,''' the administration of the country was shared by over two hundred [[daimyō]] in a federation governed by the [[Tokugawa shogunate]]. The [[Tokugawa clan]], leader of the victorious eastern army in the Battle of Sekigahara, was the most powerful of them and for fifteen generations monopolized the title of ''Sei-i Taishōgun'' (often shortened to ''shōgun''). With their headquarters at [[Edo]] (present-day [[Tokyo]]), the Tokugawa commanded the allegiance of the other daimyō, who in turn ruled their [[Han (administrative division)|domains]] with a rather high degree of autonomy.

The Tokugawa shogunate carried out a number of significant policies. They placed the samurai class above the commoners: the agriculturists, artisans, and merchants. They enacted sumptuary laws limiting hairstyle, dress, and accessories. They organized commoners into groups of five and held all responsible for the acts of each individual. To prevent daimyō from rebelling, the shōguns required them to maintain lavish residences in Edo and live at these residences on a rotating schedule; carry out expensive processions to and from their domains; contribute to the upkeep of shrines, temples, and roads; and seek permission before repairing their castles.

This 265-year span was called &quot;A peaceful state&quot;. Cultural achievement was high during this period, and many artistic developments took place. Most significant among them were the ''[[ukiyo-e]]'' form of wood-block print and the ''[[kabuki]]'' and ''[[bunraku]]'' theaters. Also, many of the most famous works for the ''[[koto (musical instrument)|koto]]'' and ''[[shakuhachi]]'' date from this time period.

===''Sakoku''—seclusion from the outside world===
{{Sync|Sakoku}}
{{Main|Sakoku}}
[[File:First Japanese treatise on Western anatomy.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Japan's first treatise on Western anatomy, published in 1774, an example of [[Rangaku]].]]
During the early part of the 17th century, the shogunate suspected that foreign traders and missionaries were actually forerunners of a military conquest by European powers. Christianity had spread in Japan, especially among peasants, and the shogunate suspected the loyalty of Christian peasants towards their daimyō, severely persecuting them. This led to a revolt by persecuted peasants and Christians in 1637 known as the [[Shimabara Rebellion]] which saw 30,000 Christians, [[rōnin]], and peasants facing a massive samurai army of more than 100,000 sent from Edo. The rebellion was crushed at a high cost to the shōgun's army.

After the eradication of the rebels at Shimabara, the shogunate placed foreigners under progressively tighter restrictions. It monopolized foreign policy and expelled traders, missionaries, and foreigners with the exception of the Dutch and Chinese merchants who were restricted to the man-made island of [[Dejima]] in [[Nagasaki, Nagasaki|Nagasaki]] Bay and several small trading outposts outside the country. However, during this period of isolation (''[[Sakoku]]'') that began in 1635, Japan was much less cut off from the rest of the world than is commonly assumed, and some acquisition of western knowledge occurred under the [[Rangaku]] system. Russian encroachments from the north led the shogunate to extend direct rule to Hokkaidō, [[Sakhalin]] and the [[Kuril Islands|Kuriles]] in 1807, but the policy of exclusion continued.

===End of seclusion===
[[File:1853Yokohama 01.jpg|thumb|200px|Landing of Commodore Perry, officers &amp; men of the squadron, to meet the Imperial commissioners at [[Yokohama]] July 14, 1853. Lithograph by Sarony &amp; Co., 1855, after W. Heine]]
{{Main|Bakumatsu}}
The policy of isolation lasted for more than 200 years. In 1844, [[William II of the Netherlands|William&amp;nbsp;II of the Netherlands]] sent a message urging Japan to open its doors which was rejected by the Japanese.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oranda-cg.or.jp/english/relations.html &quot;A 400 Year History of Dutch-Japanese Relations&quot;] The Consulate General of the Netherlands at Osaka-Kobe&lt;/ref&gt; On July&amp;nbsp;8, 1853, Commodore [[Matthew C. Perry|Matthew Perry]] of the [[United States Navy]] with four [[warship]]s—the [[USS Mississippi (1841)|''Mississippi'']], [[USS Plymouth (1844)|''Plymouth'']], [[USS Saratoga (1842)|''Saratoga'']], and [[USS Susquehanna (1850)|''Susquehanna'']]—steamed into the bay in [[Yokohama]] and displayed the threatening power of his ships' cannons during a Christian burial which the Japanese observed. He requested that Japan open to trade with the West. These ships became known as the ''kurofune'', the [[Black Ships]].

The following year at the [[Convention of Kanagawa]] on March&amp;nbsp;31, 1854, Perry returned with seven ships and demanded that the shōgun sign the Treaty of Peace and Amity, establishing formal diplomatic relations between Japan and the [[United States]]. Within five years, Japan had signed similar treaties with other Western countries. The [[Treaty of Amity and Commerce (United States-Japan)|Harris Treaty]] was signed with the United States on July&amp;nbsp;29, 1858. These treaties were unequal, having been forced on Japan through [[gunboat diplomacy]], and were interpreted by the Japanese as a sign of Western [[imperialism]] taking hold of the rest of the Asian continent. Among other measures, they gave the Western nations unequivocal control of tariffs on imports and the right of [[extraterritoriality]] to all of their visiting nationals. They would remain a sticking point in Japan's relations with the West up to around the start of the 20th century.

==Empire of Japan (1868–1945)==
{{Main|Empire of Japan}}
Beginning in 1868, Japan undertook political, economic, and cultural transformations emerging as a unified and centralized state, the [[Empire of Japan]] (also Imperial Japan or Prewar Japan). This 77-year period, which lasted until 1945, was a time of rapid economic growth. Japan became an imperial power, colonizing [[Korea under Japanese rule|Korea]] and [[Taiwan under Japanese rule|Taiwan]]. Starting in 1931 it began the takeover of Manchuria and China, in defiance of the League of Nations and the United States. Escalating tension with the U.S.--and western control of Japan's vital oil supplies—led to World War II. Japan launched multiple successful attacks on the U.S. as well as British and Dutch territories in 1941–42. After a series of great naval battles, the Americans sank the Japanese fleet and largely destroyed 50 of its largest cities through air raids, including nuclear attacks on Hiroshima and Nagasaki. Japan surrendered in late summer 1945, gave up its overseas holdings in Korea, China, Taiwan and elsewhere, and was occupied and transformed into a demilitarized democratic nation by the U.S.

===Meiji Restoration===
[[File:Satsuma-samurai-during-boshin-war-period.jpg|thumb|200px|Samurai of the Satsuma clan, during the [[Boshin War]] period. Colored photograph by [[Felice Beato]].]]
{{Main|Meiji Restoration|Meiji period}}
Renewed contact with the West precipitated a profound alteration of Japanese society. Importantly, within the context of Japan's subsequent aggressive militarism, the signing of the treaties was viewed as profoundly humiliating and a source of national shame. The Tokugawa shōgun was forced to resign, and soon after the [[Boshin War]] of 1868, the emperor was restored to power, beginning a period of fierce nationalism and intense socio-economic restructuring known as the [[Meiji Restoration]]. The Tokugawa system was abolished, the military was modernized, and numerous Western institutions were adopted–including a Western legal system and quasi-parliamentary constitutional government as outlined in the [[Meiji Constitution]]. This constitution was modeled on the constitution of the [[German Empire]]. While many aspects of the Meiji Restoration were adopted directly from Western institutions, others, such as the dissolution of the feudal system and removal of the shogunate, were processes that had begun long before the arrival of Perry. Nonetheless, Perry's intervention is widely viewed as a pivotal moment in Japanese history.

[[File:Meiji tenno1.jpg|150px|left|thumb|Emperor Meiji, the 122nd emperor of Japan.]]

===Economic modernization===
{{Main|Economic history of Japan}}
Japan's [[industrial revolution]] began about 1870 as  national leaders decided to catch up with the West. The government built railroads, improved roads, and inaugurated a land reform program to prepare the country for further development. Modern industry first appeared in textiles, including cotton and especially silk, which was based in home workshops in rural areas.&lt;ref&gt;G.C. Allen, ''Short Economic History of Modern Japan'' (1972)&lt;/ref&gt;  the government inaugurated a new Western-based education system for all young people, sent thousands of students to the United States and Europe, and hired more than 3,000 Westerners to teach modern science, mathematics, technology, and foreign languages in Japan ([[Foreign government advisors in Meiji Japan|O-yatoi gaikokujin]]). 

In 1871 a group of Japanese politicians known as the [[Iwakura Mission]] toured Europe and the USA to learn western ways. The result was a deliberate state-led industrialisation policy to enable Japan to quickly catch up. The [[Bank of Japan]], founded in 1877, used taxes to fund model steel and textile factories. Education was expanded and Japanese students were sent to study in the West.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Ian Hill Nish|title=The Iwakura Mission in America and Europe: A New Assessment|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=rFntG3WUvR4C|year=1998|publisher=Psychology Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wars with China and Russia===
{{Main|Foreign relations of Meiji Japan}}
Japanese intellectuals of the late-[[Meiji period]] espoused the concept of a &quot;line of advantage&quot;, an idea that would help to justify Japanese foreign policy around the start of the 20th century. According to this principle, embodied in the slogan ''[[fukoku kyōhei]]'', Japan would be vulnerable to aggressive Western imperialism unless it extended a line of advantage beyond its borders which would help to repel foreign incursions and strengthen the Japanese economy. Emphasis was especially placed on Japan's &quot;preeminent interests&quot; in the Korean Peninsula, once famously described as a &quot;dagger pointed at the heart of Japan&quot;. It was tensions over Korea and [[Manchuria]], respectively, that led Japan to become involved in the first [[Sino-Japanese War (1894–1895)|Sino-Japanese War]] with China in 1894–1895 and the [[Russo-Japanese War]] with Russia in 1904–1905.

The war with China made Japan the world's first Eastern, modern imperial power, and the war with Russia proved that a Western power could be defeated by an Eastern state. The aftermath of these two wars left Japan the dominant power in the [[Far East]] with a sphere of influence extending over southern Manchuria and Korea, which was formally annexed as part of the Japanese Empire in 1910. Japan had also gained half of Sakhalin Island from Russia. The results of these wars established Japan's dominant interest in Korea, while giving it the [[Pescadores Islands]], Formosa (now [[Taiwan]]), and the [[Liaodong Peninsula]] in Manchuria, which was eventually retroceded in the &quot;humiliating&quot; [[Triple Intervention]].

Over the next decade, Japan would flaunt its growing prowess, including a very significant contribution to the [[Eight-Nation Alliance]] formed to quell China's [[Boxer Rebellion]]. Many Japanese, however, believed their new empire was still regarded as inferior by the Western powers, and they sought a means of cementing their international standing. This set the climate for growing tensions with Russia, which would continually intrude into Japan's &quot;line of advantage&quot; during this time.

Russian pressure from the north appeared again after [[Mikhail Nikolayevich Muravyov|Muraviev]] had gained [[Outer Manchuria]] at [[Treaty of Aigun|Aigun]] (1858) and [[Convention of Peking|Peking]] (1860). This led to heavy Russian pressure on Sakhalin which the Japanese eventually yielded in exchange for the Kuril islands (1875). The [[Ryukyu Islands]] were similarly secured in 1879, establishing the borders within which Japan would &quot;enter the World&quot;. In 1898, the last of the [[Unequal Treaties|unequal treaties]] with Western powers was removed, signaling Japan's new status among the nations of the world. In a few decades by reforming and modernizing social, educational, economic, military, political and industrial systems, the [[Emperor Meiji]]'s &quot;controlled revolution&quot; had transformed a feudal and isolated state into a world power. Significantly, the impetus for this change was the belief that Japan had to compete with the West both industrially and militarily to achieve equality.

===Anglo-Japanese Alliance===
{{Main|Anglo-Japanese Alliance}}
The [[Anglo-Japanese Alliance]] treaty was signed with Britain in 1902. It was renewed in 1905 and 1911 before its demise in 1921 and its termination in 1923. It was a military alliance between the two countries that threatened Russia and Germany. Due to this alliance, Japan entered World War I on the side of Great Britain. Japan seized German bases in China and the pacific. The Treaty facilitated cultural and technological exchange between the two countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Phillips Payson O'Brien|title=The Anglo-Japanese Alliance, 1902–1922|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=UYtuBMCsrDwC|year=2004|publisher=Psychology Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War I===
{{Main|Japan during World War I}}
[[File:Marunouchi London Street 1920s.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Early Modern Japan, [[Marunouchi]], Tokyo 1920]]
Japan entered [[World War I|World War&amp;nbsp;I]] on the Allied side and declared war on the [[Central Powers]]. Though Japan's role was limited largely to seizing German colonial outposts in East Asia and the Pacific, it took advantage of the opportunity to expand its influence in Asia and its territorial holdings in the Pacific. Acting virtually independently of the civil government, the Japanese navy seized Germany's [[Micronesia]]n colonies. It also attacked and occupied the German coaling port of [[Qingdao]] in the Chinese [[Shandong]] peninsula.

Japan went to the [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|peace conference at Versailles]] in 1919 as one of the great military and industrial powers of the world and received official recognition as one of the &quot;Big Five&quot; of the new international order. It joined the [[League of Nations]] and received a mandate over Pacific islands north of the Equator formerly held by Germany. Japan was also involved in the post-war Allied intervention in Russia, occupying Russian (Outer) Manchuria and also north Sakhalin (which held Japan's limited oil reserves). It was the last Allied power to withdraw from the interventions against Soviet Russia (doing so in 1925).

The post–World War I era brought Japan unprecedented prosperity.

===Fascism in Japan===
{{Main|Statism in Shōwa Japan}}
During the 1910s and 1920s, Japan progressed towards democracy movements known as '[[Taishō period|Taishō]] Democracy'. However, parliamentary government was not rooted deeply enough to withstand the economic and political pressures of the late 1920s and 1930s during the Depression period, and its state became increasingly militarized. This was due to the increasing powers of military leaders and was similar to the actions some European nations were taking leading up to World War&amp;nbsp;II. These shifts in power were made possible by the ambiguity and imprecision of the Meiji Constitution, particularly its measure that the legislative body was answerable to the Emperor and not the people. The Kodoha, a militarist faction, even attempted a [[coup d'état]] known as the [[February 26 Incident|February&amp;nbsp;26 Incident]], which was crushed after three days by Hirohito, the [[Emperor Shōwa]].&lt;ref&gt;Bix, pp. 127–204&lt;/ref&gt;

Party politics came under increasing fire because it was believed they were divisive to the nation and promoted self-interest where unity was needed. As a result, the major parties voted to dissolve themselves and were absorbed into a single party, the [[Imperial Rule Assistance Association]] (IRAA), which also absorbed many prefectural organizations such as women's clubs and neighborhood associations. However, this umbrella organization did not have a cohesive political agenda and factional in-fighting persisted throughout its existence, meaning Japan did not devolve into a totalitarian state. The IRAA has been likened to a sponge, in that it could soak everything up, but there is little one could do with it afterwards. Its creation was precipitated by a series of domestic crises, including the advent of the [[Great Depression]] in the 1930s and the actions of extremists such as the members of the [[Cherry Blossom Society]], who enacted the [[May 15 Incident|May&amp;nbsp;15 Incident]].&lt;ref&gt;Bix, p. 243&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second Sino-Japanese War===
{{Main|Germany–Japan relations|Second Sino-Japanese war|Pacific War|Greater East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere|Home front during World War II#Japan}}
[[File:Yamato during Trial Service.jpg|thumb|left|200px|The [[Imperial Japanese Navy]]'s [[Japanese battleship Yamato|''Yamato'']], the heaviest battleship in history, 1941]]
Under the pretext of the [[Mukden Incident|Manchurian Incident]], Lieutenant Colonel [[Kanji Ishiwara]] invaded Inner (Chinese) Manchuria in 1931, an action the Japanese government ratified with the creation of the puppet state of [[Manchukuo]] under the last Chinese emperor, [[Henry Pu Yi|Pu Yi]]. As a result of international condemnation of the incident, Japan resigned from the League of Nations in 1933. After several more similar incidents fueled by an expansionist military, the second [[Sino-Japanese War (1937–1945)|Sino-Japanese War]] began in 1937 after the [[Marco Polo Bridge Incident]].M&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Gordon, David M|url= http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/journal_of_military_history/v070/70.1gordon.html |title=The China–Japan War, 1931–1945|journal=Journal of Military History|year=2006|volume=70|issue=1|pages=137–82}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1937–45, Emperor Hirohito was supreme commander of the [[Imperial General Headquarters]], by which the military decisions were made. After joining the [[Anti-Comintern Pact]] in 1936, Japan formed the Axis Pact with Germany and Italy on September&amp;nbsp;27, 1940. Many Japanese politicians believed war with the Occident to be inevitable due to inherent cultural differences and [[Western imperialism]]. [[Japanese imperialism]] was then justified by the revival of the traditional concept of [[hakko ichiu]], the divine right of the emperor to unite and rule the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Johanna Margarete Menz Meskill|author2=Thomas Nowotny|title=Nazi Germany and Imperial Japan: The Hollow Diplomatic Alliance|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sHayjGiGQycC&amp;pg=PT12|year=2012|publisher=Aldine Transaction|page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Japan was defeated by Soviet Union in 1938 in large-scale but localized battles at [[Battle of Lake Khasan]] and in 1939 in the [[Battle of Khalkhin Gol]]. The Army no longer wanted to fight the Soviets, so the [[Soviet–Japanese Neutrality Pact]] was signed in 1941.&lt;ref&gt;Alvin D. Coox, ''Nomonhan: Japan Against Russia, 1939'' (1990)&lt;/ref&gt; The treaty held until August 1945 when the Soviets invaded Manchuria and Korea.

===World War II===
{{main|Home front during World War II#Japan}}
Tensions were mounting with the U.S. as a result of public outcry over Japanese aggression and reports of atrocities in China, such as the infamous [[Nanjing Massacre]]. The U.S. strongly supported China with money, airmen, supplies and threats against Japan. In retaliation to the invasion of [[French Indochina]] the U.S. began an embargo on such goods as petroleum products and scrap iron. On July&amp;nbsp;25, 1941, all Japanese assets in the US were frozen. Because Japan's military might, especially the Navy, was dependent on their dwindling oil reserves, this action had the contrary effect of increasing Japan's dependence on and hunger for new acquisitions.

Many civil leaders of Japan, including Prime Minister [[Konoe Fumimaro]], believed a war with America would end in defeat, but felt the concessions demanded by the U.S. would almost certainly relegate Japan from the ranks of the World Powers, leaving it prey to Western collusion. Civil leaders offered political compromises in the form of the &quot;Amau Doctrine,&quot; dubbed the &quot;Japanese [[Monroe Doctrine]]&quot; that would have given the Japanese free rein with regard to war with China. These offers were flatly rejected by the U.S.; the military leaders instead vied for quick military action.&lt;ref&gt;Dorothy Borg, ''The United States and the Far Eastern crisis of 1933–1938'' (1964) ch 2&lt;/ref&gt;

Most military leaders such as [[Osami Nagano]], [[Prince Kan'in Kotohito|Kotohito Kan'in]], [[Hajime Sugiyama]] and [[Hideki Tōjō]] believed that war with the Occident was inevitable. They finally convinced the Emperor to sanction on November 1941 an attack plan against U.S., Great Britain and the Netherlands. However, there were dissenters in the ranks about the wisdom of that option, most notably Admiral [[Yamamoto Isoroku]] and [[Prince Takamatsu]]. They pointedly warned that at the beginning of hostilities with the US, the Empire would have the advantage for six months, after which Japan's defeat in a prolonged war with an enemy with a much larger economy would be almost certain.

[[File:Carrier shokaku.jpg|thumb|200px|Planes from the [[Japanese aircraft carrier Shokaku]] preparing the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]]]]
The Americans were expecting an attack in the [[Philippines]] and sent bombers to deter Japan. On Yamamoto's advice, Japan made the decision to attack the main American fleet at [[Pearl Harbor]] in Hawaii. American strategists believed that Japan would never be so bold as to attack so close to its home base, and the US was taken completely by surprise.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon W. Prange, Donald M. Goldstein and Katherine V. Dillon, ''At Dawn We Slept: The Untold Story of Pearl Harbor'' (1982)&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[attack on Pearl Harbor]], initially appeared to be a major success that knocked out the American battle fleet—but it missed the aircraft carriers that were at sea and ignored vital shore facilities whose destruction could have crippled US Pacific operations. Ultimately, the attack proved a long-term strategic disaster that actually inflicted relatively little significant long-term damage while provoking the United States to seek revenge. At the same time as the Pearl Harbor attack, the Japanese army attacked British Hong Kong and [[Japanese Occupation of Hong Kong|occupied]] it for nearly four years.&lt;ref&gt;Oliver Lindsay, ''The Battle for Hong Kong, 1941–1945: Hostage to Fortune'' (2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

While [[Nazi Germany]] was in the middle of its ''[[Blitzkrieg]]'' through Europe, Japan was following suit in Asia. The Japanese Army invaded and captured most of the coastal Chinese cities such as Shanghai. Japan took over [[French Indochina]] (Vietnam, Laos, Cambodia), [[British Malaya]] (Brunei, Malaysia, Singapore) as well as the [[Dutch East Indies]] (Indonesia) while [[Thailand]] entered into an alliance with Japan. Japanese forces overwhelmed the British in Burma (thus cutting off supplies to China) and reached the borders of India and Australia. Its air raids devastated Darwin, Australia. Japan had soon established an empire stretching over much of the Pacific.

[[File:Atomic cloud over Hiroshima.jpg|thumb|200px|[[atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki|Atomic cloud over Hiroshima]], 1945]]
However as Admiral Yamamoto warned, Japan's six-month window of military advantage following Pearl Harbor ended with the Japanese Navy's offensive ability being crippled at the hands of the American Navy in the [[Battle of Midway]], which established a significant American military advantage. The war became one of mass production and logistics, the U.S. funding a far stronger navy with more numerous warplanes, and a superior communications and logistics system. The Japanese had stretched too far and were unable to supply its forward bases—many soldiers died of starvation. American submarines destroyed the Japanese tankers, causing a severe shortage of fuel oil for ships and aviation gasoline. Japan built warplanes in large quantity but the quality plunged, and the performance of poorly trained pilots spiraled downward.&lt;ref&gt;Eric M Bergerud, ''Fire In The Sky: The Air War In The South Pacific'' (2001)&lt;/ref&gt; The Navy lost a series of major battles, from Midway (1942) to the Philippine Sea (1944) and Leyte Gulf (1945), which put American long-range B-29 bombers in range. A series of massive raids burned out much of Tokyo and other major industrial cities beginning in March 1945 while [[Operation Starvation]] seriously disrupted the nation's vital internal shipping lanes. Regardless of how the war was becoming hopeless, the circle around the Emperor held fast and refused to open negotiations. Finally in August, two atomic bombs and the Soviet invasion of Manchuria demonstrated the cause was futile, and Hirohito authorized a surrender whereby he kept his throne.&lt;ref&gt;Bix, pp. 487–32&lt;/ref&gt;

Total Japanese military fatalities between 1937 and 1945 were 2.1 million; most came in the last year of the war. Starvation or malnutrition-re­lated illness accounted for roughly 80 percent of Japanese military deaths in the Philippines, and 50 percent of military fatalities in China. The aerial bombing of a total of 65 Japanese cities appears to have taken a minimum of 400,000 and possibly closer to 600,000 civilian lives (over 100,000 in Tokyo alone, over 200,000 in Hiroshima and Nagasaki combined, and 80,000–150,000 civilian deaths in the battle of Okina­wa). Civilian death among settlers who died attempting to re­turn to Japan from Manchuria in the winter of 1945 were probably around 100,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=John Dower|title=Lessons from Iwo Jima|journal=Perspectives|year=2007|volume= 45|issue=6|pages=54–56|url=http://www.historians.org/perspectives/issues/2007/0709/index.cfm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modernizing society==

===Childhood transformed===
Childhood as a distinct phase of life was apparent in the early modern period, when social and economic changes brought increased attention to children, the growth of schooling and child-centered rituals. A modern concept of childhood emerged in Japan after 1850 as part of its engagement with the West. Meiji era leaders decided the nation-state had the primary role in mobilizing individuals – and children – in service of the state. The Western-style school was introduced as the agent to reach that goal. By the 1890s, schools were generating new sensibilities regarding childhood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Brian Platt|title=Japanese Childhood, Modern Childhood: The Nation-State, the School, and 19th-Century Globalization|doi=10.1353/jsh.2005.0073|journal=Journal of Social History|year= 2005|volume= 38 |issue= 4|pages=965–985}}&lt;/ref&gt; After 1890 Japan had numerous reformers, child experts, magazine editors, and well-educated mothers who bought into the new sensibility. They taught the upper middle class a model of childhood that included children having their own space where they read children's books, played with educational toys and, especially, devoted enormous time to school homework. These ideas rapidly disseminated through all social classes &lt;ref&gt;Kathleen S. Uno, ''Passages to Modernity: Motherhood, Childhood, and Social Reform in Early Twentieth Century Japan'' (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mark Jones, ''Children as Treasures: Childhood and the Middle Class in Early Twentieth Century Japan'' (2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Postwar Japan (1945–present)==
{{Main|Postwar Japan}}
After the collapse of the [[Empire of Japan]], Japan was transformed into a democratic state with a revised democratic [[constitution|Constitution of Japan]]. During the postwar period, Japan became an economic power state. This period is characterized by the US-Japan Alliance such as the [[United States Forces Japan]].

===Occupation of Japan===
[[File:macarthur hirohito.jpg|thumb|200px|General [[Douglas MacArthur]] and Emperor [[Hirohito]]]]
{{Main|Occupation of Japan}}
Japan had never been occupied by a foreign power, and the arrival of the Americans with strong ideas about transforming Japan into a peaceful democracy had a major long-term impact.  Japan came under the firm direction of American General [[Douglas MacArthur]], The main American objective was to turn Japan into a peaceful nation and to establish democratic self-government. The occupation transformed the Japanese government into an engine of production, wealth redistribution, and social reform.  Political reforms included a freely elected Japanese Diet (legislature) and universal adult suffrage.  The Occupation emphasized land reform so that tenant farmers became owners of their rice paddies,  and stimulated the formation of powerful labor unions that gave workers a say in industrial democracy.  The great zaibatsu business conglomerates were broken up, consumer culture was encouraged, education was radically reformed and democratized, and the Shinto-basis of emperor worship was ended. Historian John Dower says the &quot;visible hand&quot; of [[New Deal]]-inspired state leadership, while keeping a capitalist economy, was welcomed by a battered and humiliated Japanese society that was eager to find a peaceful route forward into prosperity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John W. Dower|title=Cultures of War: Pearl Harbor/Hiroshima/9-11/Iraq|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=SC4X1muvigYC&amp;pg=PA409|year=2011|publisher=W. W. Norton |page=409}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The reforms were implemented by Japanese officials under indirect American control, so that no Japanese institutions were directly controlled by Americans.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The American Occupation of Japan, 1945–1952,&quot; in Columbia University, East Asian Curriculum Project, ''Contemporary Japan: A Teaching Workbook'' [http://afe.easia.columbia.edu/japan/japanworkbook/modernhist/occupation.html online]&lt;/ref&gt;  While Emperor Hirohito was allowed to retain his throne as a symbol of national unity, actual power was held by complex interlocking networks of elites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Mark E. Caprio and Yoneyuki Sugita|title=Democracy in Occupied Japan: The U.S. Occupation and Japanese Politics and Society|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=pqxMC9mkfLkC&amp;pg=PA21|year=2007|publisher=Routledge}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Empire of Japan]] was dissolved.  Japan was stripped of its overseas possessions and retained only the home islands and Okinawa. Manchukuo was dissolved, and Manchuria and Formosa were returned to China. Korea was occupied and divided by the U.S. and the Soviet Union. The U.S. became the sole administering authority of the Ryukyu, Bonin, and Volcano Islands, while the USSR took southern Sakhalin and the Kurile islands. Japan vehemently rejects Soviet control of the Kuriles, and diplomatic tension over the issue continued into the 21st century.  Shutting down the empire meant that Japanese settlers and officials had leave. In all Japanese repatriation centers handled over 7 million expatriates returning to Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Lori Watt|title=When Empire Comes Home: Repatriation and Reintegration in Postwar Japan|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_F3AN6x6AQ8C&amp;pg=PA71|year=2010|publisher=Harvard U.P.|pages=65–72}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[International Military Tribunal for the Far East]] (Tokyo Trial), an international [[war crime]]s tribunal, was held, in which seven politicians were executed. [[Hirohito|Emperor Hirohito]] was not convicted, but instead was turned into a figurehead emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Yuma Totani, ''The Tokyo War Crimes Trial: The Pursuit of Justice in the Wake of World War II'' (Harvard East Asian Monographs, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richard H. Minear, ''Victor's Justice: The Tokyo War Crimes Trial'' (1971)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Shigeru Yoshida]] (1878–1967) played the central role as prime minister between 1946 and 1954 (with one interruption). His goal was rapid rebuilding Japan and cooperation with the American Occupation. He led Japan to adopt the “[[Yoshida Doctrine]]”, based on three tenets: economic growth as the primary national objective, no involvement in international political-strategic issues, and the provision of military bases to the United States. The Yoshida Doctrine proved immensely successful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John W. Dower|title=Embracing defeat: Japan in the wake of World War II|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hae0dC_NaiUC|year=2000|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|pages=323–325}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bix, pp. 583–585.&lt;/ref&gt;

The historiography before 1980 was celebratory, and focused on the success of the American occupation in transforming Japan in terms of democracy and freedom. Since the 1980s historians more often stress the limitations of the occupation's reforms and argue that they partly reflected prewar and wartime Japanese innovations.&lt;ref&gt;Juha Saunavaara. &quot;Review of Aldous, Christopher; Suzuki, Akihito, ''Reforming Public Health in Occupied Japan, 1945–52: Alien Prescriptions?''&quot; H-US-Japan, H-Net Reviews. June, 2012.
[https://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.php?id=36083 online]&lt;/ref&gt;

Dower explains the factors that promoted the success of the American occupation: 
:&quot;Discipline, moral legitimacy, well-defined and well-articulated objectives, a clear chain of command, tolerance and flexibility in policy formulation and implementation, confidence in the ability of the state to act constructively, the ability to operate abroad free of partisan politics back home, and the existence of a stable, resilient, sophisticated civil society on the receiving end of occupation policies—these political and civic virtues helped make it possible to move decisively during the brief window of a few years when defeated Japan itself was in flux and most receptive to radical change.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John W. Dower|title=Cultures of War: Pearl Harbor/Hiroshima/9-11/Iraq|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=SC4X1muvigYC&amp;pg=PA338|year=2011|publisher=W. W. Norton |page=338}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Peace treaty===
Entering the [[Cold War]] with the [[Korean War]], Japan came to be seen as an important ally of the US government. Political, economic, and social reforms were introduced, such as an elected Japanese Diet (legislature) and expanded suffrage. The country's constitution took effect on May&amp;nbsp;3, 1947. The United States and 45 other Allied nations signed the [[Treaty of San Francisco|Treaty of Peace with Japan]] in September 1951. The [[United States Senate|U.S. Senate]] ratified the treaty on March&amp;nbsp;20, 1952, and under the terms of the treaty, Japan regained full sovereignty on April&amp;nbsp;28, 1952.

Under the terms of the peace treaty and later agreements, the United States maintains naval bases at Sasebo, Okinawa and at Yokosuka. A portion of the U.S. Pacific Fleet, including one aircraft carrier (currently [[USS George Washington (CVN-73)]]), is based at Yokosuka. This arrangement is partially intended to provide for the defense of Japan, as the treaty and the new Japanese constitution imposed during the occupation severely restrict the size and purposes of [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]] in the modern period.

===Cold War===
{{Main|Post-occupation Japan}}
After a series of realignment of political parties, the conservative [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party]] (LDP) and the leftist [[Social Democratic Party (Japan)|Social Democratic Party]] (SDP) were formed in 1955. The political map in Japan had been largely unaltered until early 1990s and LDP had been the largest political party in the national politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Roger W. Bowen|title=Japan's Dysfunctional Democracy: The Liberal Democratic Party and Structural Corruption|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=U_6iRfaYELsC&amp;pg=PA111|year=2003|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|page=111}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn19970813a7.html Parties and politicians jockey for power], [[Japan Times]], August 13, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; LDP politicians and government [[bureaucrats]] focused on economic policy. From the 1950s to the 1980s, Japan experienced its rapid development into a major economic power, through a process often referred to as the [[Japanese post-war economic miracle]].

Japan's biggest postwar political crisis took place in 1960 over the revision of the [[Japan-United States Mutual Security Assistance Pact]]. The new Treaty of Mutual Cooperation and Security, which renewed the United States role as military protector of Japan, was pushed through the Diet by LDP Prime Minister [[Eisaku Sato]] through the Diet in 1960 against the strong opposition of minority parties. Opponents on the left responded with massive street protests and political upheaval occurred, and the cabinet resigned a month after the Diet's ratification of the treaty. Thereafter, political turmoil subsided. Japanese views of the United States, after years of mass protests over nuclear armaments and the mutual defense pact, improved by 1972 with the reversion of United States-occupied [[Okinawa]] to Japanese sovereignty and the winding down of the [[Vietnam War]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Robert A. Scalapino|title=The Foreign Policy of Modern Japan|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=uOnddOYJ3jEC&amp;pg=PA43|year=1977|publisher=University of California Press|page=43}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Japan had reestablished relations with the [[Republic of China]] after World War II, and cordial relations were maintained with the nationalist government when it was relocated to [[Taiwan]], a policy that won Japan the enmity of the People's Republic of China, which was established in 1949. After the general warming of relations between China and Western countries, especially the United States, which shocked Japan with its sudden rapprochement with Beijing in 1971, Tokyo established relations with Beijing in 1972. Close cooperation in the economic sphere followed. Japan's relations with the [[Soviet Union]] continued to be problematic after the war, but a Joint Declaration between Japan and the USSR ending the state of war and reestablishing diplomatic relations was signed October&amp;nbsp;19, 1956.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mofa.go.jp/region/europe/russia/territory/edition92/preface.html Compendium of Documents]. Mofa.go.jp. Retrieved on 2011-10-29.&lt;/ref&gt; The main object of dispute was the Soviet occupation of what Japan calls its [[Kuril Islands dispute|Northern Territories]], the two most southerly islands in the [[Kurils]] ([[Iturup|Etorofu]] and [[Kunashir Island|Kunashiri]]) and [[Shikotan]] and the [[Khabomai|Habomai Islands]], which were seized by the Soviet Union in the closing days of World War&amp;nbsp;II.

===Economic growth===
Throughout the postwar period, Japan's economy continued to boom, with results far outstripping expectations.&lt;ref&gt;James L. McClain, ''Japan: A Modern History'' (2002) pp. 562–98&lt;/ref&gt;  Given a massive boost by the [[Korean War]], in which it acted as a major supplier to the UN force, Japan's economy embarked on a prolonged period of extremely rapid growth, led by the manufacturing sectors. Japan emerged as a significant power in many economic spheres, including steel working, car manufacturing and the manufacturing of [[Electronics|electronic]] goods. Japan rapidly caught up with the West in foreign trade, [[Gross national product|GNP]], and general [[quality of life]]. These achievements were underscored by the 1964 [[1964 Summer Olympics|Tokyo Olympic Games]] and the [[Expo '70|Osaka International Exposition]] in 1970. The high economic growth and political tranquility of the mid to late 1960s were tempered by the quadrupling of oil prices by the [[OPEC]] in 1973. Almost completely dependent on imports for petroleum, Japan experienced its first recession since World War&amp;nbsp;II. Another serious problem was Japan's growing trade surplus, which reached record heights during [[Nakasone]]'s first term. The United States pressured Japan to remedy the imbalance, demanding that Tokyo raise the value of the yen and open its markets further to facilitate more imports from the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Hans Brinckmann, and Ysbrand Rogge. ''Showa Japan: The Post-War Golden Age and Its Troubled Legacy'' (2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

===After the Cold War===
{{Main|Heisei period}}
Japan after the Cold War is also called as the [[Heisei period]], which starts from the year of the [[Revolutions of 1989|Revolutions of Eastern Europe]]. 1989 marked one of the most rapid economic growth spurts in Japanese history. With a strong [[yen]] and a favorable exchange rate with the dollar, the [[Bank of Japan]] kept interest rates low, sparking an investment boom that drove Tokyo property values up sixty percent within the year. Shortly before New Year's Day, the [[Nikkei 225|Nikkei&amp;nbsp;225]] reached its record high of 39,000. By 1991, it had fallen to 15,000, signifying the end of Japan's famed [[bubble economy]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/watkins/bubble.htm The Bubble Economy of Japan], [[San José State University]] Department of Economics&lt;/ref&gt; Unemployment ran reasonably high, but not at crisis levels. Rather than suffer large-scale unemployment and lay-offs, Japan's labor market suffered in more subtle, yet no less profound effects that were nonetheless difficult to gauge statistically. During the prosperous times, jobs were seen as long term even to the point of being lifelong. In contrast, Japan during the lost decade saw a marked increase in temporary and part-time work which only promised employment for short periods and marginal benefits. This also created a generational gap, as those who had entered the labor market prior to the lost decade usually retained their employment and benefits, and were effectively insulated from the economic slowdown, whereas younger workers who entered the market a few years later suffered the brunt of its effects.

In a series of financial scandals of the LDP, a coalition led by [[Morihiro Hosokawa]] took power in 1993. Hosokawa succeeded to legislate a new [[Plurality voting system|plurality voting]] election law instead of the stalemated [[Single non-transferable vote|multi-member constituency election system]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0004-4687(199407)34%3A7%3C589%3AERIJHI%3E2.0.CO%3B2-6 Electoral Reform in Japan: How It was Enacted and Changes It May Bring], Raymond V. Christensen, [[Asian Survey]], Vol. 34, No. 7, 1994&lt;/ref&gt; However, the coalition collapsed the next year as parties had gathered to simply overthrow LDP and lacked a unified position on almost every social issue. The LDP returned to the government in 1996, when it helped to elect Social Democrat [[Tomiichi Murayama]] as prime minister.

The [[Great Hanshin earthquake]] hit [[Kobe]] on January&amp;nbsp;17, 1995. 6,000 people were killed and 44,000 were injured. 250,000 houses were destroyed or burned in a fire. The amount of damage totaled more than ten trillion yen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kobe-jma.go.jp/shiryou/higaijishin/higaijishin.htm 兵庫県の主な被害地震], Kobe Marine Observatory&lt;/ref&gt; In March of the same year the doomsday [[cult]] [[Aum Shinrikyo]] [[Sarin gas attack on the Tokyo subway|attacked]] on the [[Tokyo subway]] system with [[sarin]] gas, killing 12 and injuring hundreds more. An investigation later revealed that the cult was responsible for dozens of murders that occurred prior to the gas attacks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cfr.org/publication/9238/ Aum Shinrikyo (Japan, cultists)], Council on Foreign Relations&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Junichiro Koizumi]] was president of the LDP and Prime Minister of Japan from April 2001 to September 2006. Koizumi enjoyed high approval ratings. He was known as an economic reformer and he privatized the national postal system. Koizumi also had an active involvement in the [[War on Terrorism]], sending 1,000 soldiers of the [[Japan Self-Defense Forces]] to help in Iraq's reconstruction after the [[Iraq War]], the biggest overseas troop deployment since World War&amp;nbsp;II.

The ruling coalition is formed by the liberal [[Democratic Party of Japan]] (DPJ), the [[leftist]] [[Social Democratic Party (Japan)|Social Democratic Party]] and the conservative [[People's New Party]]. The opposition is formed by the [[Liberal conservatism|liberal conservative]] [[Liberal Democratic Party (Japan)|Liberal Democratic Party]] (LDP). Other parties are the [[New Komeito Party]], a [[Sōka Gakkai]] party and the [[Japanese Communist Party]]. On 2&amp;nbsp;June 2010 Prime Minister [[Yukio Hatoyama]] resigned from his position as leader of the DPJ, citing the failure to fulfill his campaign promise of removing a U.S. base from the island of Okinawa as his main reason for stepping down.

On March 11, 2011, Japan suffered the [[2011 Tōhoku earthquake and tsunami|strongest earthquake]] in its recorded history, affecting the north-east area of Honshū. The magnitude 9.0&lt;ref name=&quot;USGS9.0&quot;&gt;[http://earthquake.usgs.gov/earthquakes/eqinthenews/2011/usc0001xgp/neic_c0001xgp_wmt.php USGS analysis as of 2011-03-12]. Earthquake.usgs.gov (2011-06-23). Retrieved on 2011-10-29.&lt;/ref&gt; quake was aggravated by a tsunami and also caused numerous fires and damaged several nuclear reactors. [[Fukushima Daiichi nuclear disaster|Damage to Fukushima Nuclear Plant]] led to [[Nuclear meltdown|meltdown]] of three reactors and release of radioactive material, in the largest nuclear accident since the 1986 [[Chernobyl disaster]].

==Periodization==
One commonly accepted [[periodization]] of Japanese history:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- style=&quot;border-bottom:3px solid; background:#ffefef;&quot;
! Dates !! Period !! Period !! Subperiod !! Main government
|-
| 30,000–10,000 BC
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |[[Japanese Paleolithic]]
| &amp;nbsp;
| unknown
|-
| 10,000–300 BC
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | Ancient Japan
| [[Jōmon period|Jōmon]]
| &amp;nbsp;
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | local clans
|-
| 900 BC – 250 AD (overlaps)
| [[Yayoi period|Yayoi]]
| &amp;nbsp;
|-
| c. 250–538 AD
| [[Kofun period|Kofun]]
|
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | &amp;nbsp; [[Yamato people|Yamato clans]]
|-
| 538–710 AD
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | Classical Japan
| [[Asuka period|Asuka]]
|
|-
| 710–794
| [[Nara period|Nara]]
| &amp;nbsp;
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Emperor of Japan]]
|-
| 794–1185
| [[Heian period|Heian]]
| &amp;nbsp;
|-
| 1185–1333
| rowspan=&quot;6&quot; | Feudal Japan
| [[Kamakura period|Kamakura]]
| &amp;nbsp;
| [[Kamakura shogunate]]
|-
| 1333–1336
| [[Kemmu Restoration]]
| &amp;nbsp;
| [[Emperor of Japan]]
|-
| 1336–1392
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Muromachi period|Muromachi]]
| [[Nanboku-cho]]
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Ashikaga shogunate]]
|-
| 1392–1467
| &amp;nbsp;
|-
| 1467–1573
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Sengoku period]]
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Ashikaga shogunate]], [[daimyō]]s, [[Oda Nobunaga]], [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]]
|-
| 1573–1603
| [[Azuchi-Momoyama period|Azuchi-Momoyama]]
|-
| 1603–1868
| Early Modern Japan
| [[Edo period|Edo]]
| &amp;nbsp;
| [[Tokugawa shogunate]]
|-
| 1868–1912
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | Modern Japan
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Empire of Japan|Prewar]]
| [[Meiji period|Meiji]]
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Emperor of Japan]]
|-
| 1912–1926
| [[Taishō period|Taishō]]
|-
| 1926–1945
| [[Shōwa period|Prewar Shōwa]]
|-
| 1945–1952
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | Contemporary Japan
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Postwar Japan|Postwar]]
| [[Occupation of Japan|Occupied Japan]] (Postwar Shōwa)
| [[Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers]]
|-
| 1952–1989
| [[Post-occupation Japan|Post-occupation]] (Postwar Shōwa)
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Parliamentary democracy
|-
| 1989–present
| [[Heisei period|Heisei]]
|}

&lt;!--:[[Jōmon period|Jōmon]] (prehistory – circa 300 BC)
:[[Yayoi period|Yayoi]] (circa 300 BC – 250 AD)
:[[Yamato period|Yamato]] (circa 250–710 AD)
:*[[Kofun period|Kofun]] (circa. 250 – ca. 538 AD)
:*[[Asuka period|Asuka]] (538–710)
:[[Nara period|Nara]] (710–794)
:[[Heian period|Heian]] (794–1185)
:[[Kamakura period|Kamakura]] (see also [[Kamakura Shogunate]]) (1185–1333)
:[[Kenmu restoration]] (1333–1336)
:[[Muromachi period|Muromachi]] (also called [[Ashikaga Shogunate|Ashikaga]]) (1388–1573)
:*[[Nanboku-chō period|Nanboku-chō]] (1336–1392)
:*early part of the [[Sengoku period]] (1392–1573)
:[[Azuchi-Momoyama period]] (1573–1603)
:*latter part of the [[Sengoku period]] (1573–1603)
:[[Edo period|Edo]] (also called Tokugawa) (1600–1867)
:[[Meiji period|Meiji]] (1867–1912)
:[[Taishō period|Taishō]] (1912–1926)
:[[Shōwa period|Shōwa]] (1926–1989)
:*[[Japanese expansionism|Expansionism]] (1926–1945)
:*[[Occupied Japan]] (1945–1952)
:*[[Post-Occupation Japan|Post-occupation]] (1952–1989)
:[[Heisei|Contemporary]] (1989–present)

--&gt;

==Regnal years==
{{Main|Japanese era name}}

[[Regnal year]]s (''[[Japanese era name|Gengō]]'') in Japan

:Regnal years are commonly used in Japan as an alternative to the [[Gregorian calendar]]. For example, in censuses, birthdays are written using regnal years. Dates of newspapers and official documents are also written using regnal years.
:Regnal years are changed upon the enthronement of each new [[Emperor of Japan|Tennō]] since [[Emperor Meiji|Meiji]] until the [[Constitution of Japan|Postwar Constitution]] was enacted (1868–1947).
:But, in 1979, the ''Regnal Years Law'' was enacted, regnal years are changed upon the enthronement of each new Tennō once more.
:Until [[Keio]], regnal years were changed on a whim.

;Regnal years since 1800
*[[Kansei]] (1789–1801)
*[[Kyōwa]] (1801–1804)
*[[Bunka]] (1804–1818)
*[[Bunsei]] (1818–1830)
*[[Tenpō]] (1830–1844)
*[[Kōka]] (1844–1848)
*[[Kaei]] (1848–1854)
*[[Ansei]] (1854–1860)
*[[Man'en]] (1860–1861)
*[[Bunkyū]] (1861–1864)
*[[Genji]] (1864–1865)
*[[Keiō]] (1865–1867)
*[[Meiji period|Meiji]] (1868–1912)
*[[Taishō period|Taishō]] (1912–1926)
*[[Shōwa period|Shōwa]] (December 25, 1926 – January 7, 1989)
*[[Heisei]] (January 8, 1989–present)

;For example :
*1820 was the 3rd year of Bunsei.
*1855 was the 2nd year of Ansei.
*1900 was the 33rd year of Meiji.
*1945 was the 20th year of Shōwa.
*2000 was the 12th year of Heisei.
*1848 was the 5th year of Kōka through March 31, but on April 1, it became the 1st year(''Gan-nen'') of Kaei.
*1989 was the 64th year of Shōwa through to January 7, but on January 8, it became the 1st year(''Gan-nen'') of Heisei.

===Other eras===
*During the [[Empire of Japan|pre–World War II period]], '''[[Jimmu]] era ([[Kōki]])''' is also used in common that the year of enthronement of first Tennō (''Jimmu-Tennō'') is defined as First Year. (= 660 BC)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 | last = Nihon Kokugo Daijiten Dai Nihan Henshū Iin Kai
 | title = [[Nihon Kokugo Daijiten]]: Volume 5
 | publisher = [[Shogakukan|Shōgakukan]]
 | date = 2001-2002
 | location = Tōkyō
 | language = Japanese
 | isbn = 4-09-521005-2
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 | last = Matsumura
 | first = Akira
 | title = [[Daijirin]] (Third Edition)
 | publisher = [[Sanseido|Sanseidō]]
 | year = 2006
 | location = Tōkyō
 | language = Japanese
 | isbn = 4-385-13905-9
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;factbook&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ja.html
 | title = CIA – The World Factbook – Japan
 | publisher = [[The World Factbook]]
 | date = 2008-04-15
 | accessdate = 2008-04-23
 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, 2010 is 2670 Jimmu era.

*During the [[Postwar Japan|post–World War II period]], '''postwar era (sengo)''' has been used as a private era,{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} which starts from 1946 (1945 being the 0th postwar year). It is seen in media and books. For example, 2010 is 65 postwar.

==See also==
{{Portal|Ancient Japan}}
*[[Timeline of Japanese history]]
*[[History of Asia]]
**[[History of East Asia]]
* [[List of Emperors of Japan]]
* [[List of Prime Ministers of Japan]]
* [[Politics of Japan]]
* [[Rikkokushi]], six imperially commissioned Japanese national histories
* [[1980s in Japan]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
* {{loc}} – [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/jptoc.html Japan]

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book|author=Bix, Herbert P. |title=Hirohito and the making of modern Japan|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=zjmVltzm1kYC|date=4 September 2001|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-093130-8}}
*Fairbank, John K.; Reischauer, Edwin O. and Craig, Albert M. ''East Asia: Tradition and Transformation'' (Houghton Mifflin Publishing Co.: Boston, 1978)
*{{cite book|author=Sansom, George Bailey|title=A History of Japan to 1334|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=t2c4t4yw21gC|date=1 June 1958|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-0523-3}}
*{{cite book|author=Sansom, George Bailey|title=A History of Japan, 1334–1615|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0syC6L77dpAC|year=1961|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-0525-7}}

==Further reading==
* Allinson, Gary D. ''The Columbia Guide to Modern Japanese History.'' (1999). 259 pp. [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0231111444 excerpt and text search]
* Allinson, Gary D. ''Japan's Postwar History.'' (2nd ed 2004). 208 pp. [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0801489121 excerpt and text search]
* [[William G. Beasley|Beasley, William G.]] [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=10327723 ''The Modern History of Japan''] (1963)
* Clement, Ernest Wilson. [http://books.google.com/books?id=mOoTAAAAIAAJ ''A Short History of Japan''] (1915)
* [[Louis Cullen|Cullen, Louis M.]] [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=106045491 ''A History of Japan, 1582–1941: Internal and External Worlds''] (2003)
* Edgerton, Robert B. ''Warriors of the Rising Sun: A History of the Japanese Military.'' (1999). 384 pp. [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0813336007 excerpt and text search]
* [[Andrew Gordon (historian)|Gordon, Andrew]]. [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=103548936 ''A Modern History of Japan: From Tokugawa Times to the Present''] (2003) ISBN 0-19-511061-7
* [[John Whitney Hall|Hall John Whitney]]. ''Japan: From Prehistory to Modern Times.'' 1970.
* Hane, Mikiso. [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=57239340 ''Modern Japan: A Historical Survey''] (2nd ed 1992)
* Huffman, James L., ed. ''Modern Japan: An Encyclopedia of History, Culture, and Nationalism.'' (1998).
* Hunter Janet. ''Concise Dictionary of Modern Japanese History.'' 1984.
* [[Marius Jansen|Jansen, Marius B.]] ''The Making of Modern Japan'' (2002) ISBN 0-674-00991-6
* McClain, James L. ''Japan: A Modern History.'' (2001) ISBN 0-393-97720-X
* Perez, Louis G. [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=93932879 ''The History of Japan''] (1998)
* Perkins, Dorothy. ''Encyclopedia of Japan: Japanese History and Culture, from Abacus to Zori.'' (1991).
* [[Edwin O. Reischauer|Reischauer, Edwin O.]] ''Japan: The Story of a Nation.'' 1990.
* Stockwin, J. A. A. [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=107546295# ''Dictionary of the Modern Politics of Japan.''] (2003).
* Tipton, Elise. ''Modern Japan: A Social and Political History'' (2002) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0415185378/ excerpt and text search]

==External links==
{{Commons category|History of Japan}}
*[http://www.ames.cam.ac.uk/jbib/bibtitle.html Bibliography of Japanese History up to 1912], University of Cambridge.
*[http://www.samurai-archives.com/ Samurai Archives Japanese History Page], a great amount of text about Japanese history
*[http://www.openhistory.org/jhdp/ The Japanese History Documentation Project] by Christopher Spackman. This is published under the terms of the [[GNU Free Documentation License|GFDL]], so it should be usable as a resource for Wikipedia.
*[http://www4.ncsu.edu/~fljpm/chron/jc01.outline.html Outline Chronology of Japanese Cultural History]
*[http://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/index_ne.html National Museum of Japanese History]
*[http://www.sengokudaimyo.com/ SengokuDaimyo.com], the website of Samurai author and historian [[Anthony J. Bryant]]
*[http://www.uri.edu/artsci/his/mua/project_journals/aj/aj_intro.shtml Japanese History through Edo Period Art]
*[http://www.asiaquarterly.com/content/view/124/40/ Yamada Sho (2002). Politics and Personality: Japan's Worst Archaeology Scandal], ''Harvard Asia Quarterly'' Vol. VI, No. 3. In-depth commentary on the extensive fraud that took place in archeology in Japan over a 20-year period.
*[http://miko.org/~uraki/kuon/furu/furu_index1.htm 古事記~往古之追慕~](Big5 Chinese) Many online Japanese historical texts, e.g. the [[Rikkokushi]], Dainihonshi and more.
*{{ja icon}}[http://kodaishi-db.hp.infoseek.co.jp/ 日本古代史料本文データ] Downloadable lzh compressed files of Japanese historical texts.
*{{ja icon}}[http://www001.upp.so-net.ne.jp/dassai/ 古代史獺祭] Many online historical texts from Japanese, Chinese, Korean related to history of Japan.
*{{ja icon}}[http://www.j-texts.com/ J－Texts (日本文学電子図書館)] Many Japan historical literature texts
*[http://www.hi.u-tokyo.ac.jp/index.html Historiographical Institute – The University of Tokyo (東京大学史料編纂所)]
*[http://www2.u-netsurf.ne.jp/~kojin/e-wajinden.html English translation of the ''Wei Zhi'']

{{Japan topics}}
{{History of Asia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Japan}}
[[Category:History of Japan| ]]

{{Link FA|ca}}
{{Link FA|es}}
{{Link FA|fi}}
{{Link FA|vi}}
[[ar:تاريخ اليابان]]
[[bg:История на Япония]]
[[ca:Història del Japó]]
[[cs:Dějiny Japonska]]
[[da:Japans historie]]
[[de:Geschichte Japans]]
[[et:Jaapani ajalugu]]
[[el:Ιαπωνική ιστορία]]
[[es:Historia de Japón]]
[[eo:Historio de Japanio]]
[[eu:Japoniako historia]]
[[fa:تاریخ ژاپن]]
[[fr:Histoire du Japon]]
[[fy:Skiednis fan Japan]]
[[gl:Historia do Xapón]]
[[gan:日本嗰歷史]]
[[ko:일본의 역사]]
[[hy:Ճապոնիայի պատմություն]]
[[hi:जापान का इतिहास]]
[[hr:Povijest Japana]]
[[io:Historio di Japonia]]
[[id:Sejarah Jepang]]
[[is:Saga Japans]]
[[it:Storia del Giappone]]
[[he:היסטוריה של יפן]]
[[jv:Sajarah Jepang]]
[[ka:იაპონიის ისტორია]]
[[la:Historia Iaponiae]]
[[lv:Japānas vēsture]]
[[lt:Japonijos istorija]]
[[hu:Japán történelme]]
[[mk:Историја на Јапонија]]
[[mwl:Stória de l Japon]]
[[my:ဂျပန်သမိုင်း]]
[[nl:Geschiedenis van Japan]]
[[ja:日本の歴史]]
[[no:Japans historie]]
[[pl:Historia Japonii]]
[[pt:História do Japão]]
[[ro:Istoria Japoniei]]
[[ru:История Японии]]
[[sq:Historia e Japonisë]]
[[simple:History of Japan]]
[[sk:Dejiny Japonska]]
[[sl:Zgodovina Japonske]]
[[sr:Класични Јапан]]
[[sh:Historija Japana]]
[[su:Sajarah Jepang]]
[[fi:Japanin historia]]
[[sv:Japans historia]]
[[th:ประวัติศาสตร์ญี่ปุ่น]]
[[uk:Історія Японії]]
[[vi:Lịch sử Nhật Bản]]
[[zh-yue:日本史]]
[[zh:日本历史]]</text>
      <sha1>g4bkells12w7n27rxwuce9fnrikt7kx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
