<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of American Samoa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4143460</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520659992</id>
      <parentid>520659981</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T22:39:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/206.80.31.55|206.80.31.55]] to version by Allens. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1305223) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6379">{{Unreferenced|date=August 2007}}
{{wikiatlas|American Samoa}}
[[File:Olosega Native village 1896.jpg|thumb|right|[[Ofu-Olosega|Olosega]] native village 1896]]
Originally inhabited as early as 850 AD, '''Samoa''' was not reached by [[Europe]]an explorers until the 18th century. By the 20th and 21st century, the islands were incorporated into [[Samoa]] (Western Samoa, Independent Samoa) and [[American Samoa]] (Eastern Samoa).

== Early occupation by Polynesian people ==
The pre-Western history of Eastern Samoa (now [[American Samoa]]) is inextricably bound with the history of Western Samoa (now independent [[Samoa]]).

The islands of Tutuila and Aunu'u were politically connected to 'Upolu island in what is now independent Samoa. It can be said that all the Samoa islands are politically connected today through the [[faamatai]] chiefly system and through family connections that are as strong as ever. This system of the faamatai and the customs of [[faasamoa]] originated with two of the most famous early chiefs of Samoa, who were both women and related, [[Nafanua]] and [[Salamasina]].

== Initial European discovery ==
Early Western contact included a battle in the 18th century between French explorers and islanders in Tutuila, for which the Samoans were blamed in the West, giving them a reputation for ferocity. Early 19th century Rarotongan missionaries to the Samoa islands were followed by a group of Western missionaries led by [[John Williams (missionary)]] of the (Congregationalist) London Missionary Society in the 1830s, officially bringing Christianity to Samoa. Less than a hundred years later, the [[Samoan Congregationalist Church]] became the first independent indigenous church of the South Pacific.

== Division of the Samoan archipelago ==
International rivalries in the later half of the 19th century were settled by an 1899 [[Treaty of Berlin, 1899|Treaty of Berlin]] in which Germany and the U.S. divided the Samoan [[archipelago]]. The U.S. formally occupied its portion—a smaller group of eastern islands with the noted harbor of [[Pago Pago, American Samoa|Pago Pago]]—the following year. The western islands are now the independent state of [[Samoa]].

== Colonization by the United States and conflicts with native Samoans ==
'''American Samoa''' is the result of the [[Second Samoan Civil War]] and an agreement made between [[Germany]], the [[United States]], and the [[United Kingdom]] in the [[Tripartite Convention]] of 1899.

After the U.S. took possession of American Samoa, the [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] built a [[coal]]ing station on Pago Pago Bay for its Pacific Squadron and appointed a local Secretary. Several chiefs of the island of [[Tutuila]] swore allegiance, and ceded the island, to the United States in the [[Treaty of Cession of Tutuila]] of 1900. The last sovereign of {{Unicode|Manuʻa}}, the {{Unicode|[[Tui Manua Elisala|Tui Manuʻa Elisara]]}}, was forced to sign the [[Treaty of Cession of Manuʻa]] of 1904 following a series of US Naval trials, known as the &quot;Trial of the Ipu&quot;, in Pago Pago, {{Unicode|Taʻu}}, and aboard a Pacific Squadron gunboat. The treaties where ratified by the United States in the [[Ratification Act of 1929]].

After World War I, during the time of the [[Mau movement]] in Western Samoa (then a New Zealand protectorate), there was a corresponding American Samoa Mau movement, led by Samuel Sailele Ripley, who was from Leone village and was a WWI war veteran. After meetings in America, he was prevented from disembarking from the ship that brought him home to American Samoa and was not allowed to return. The American Samoa Mau movement having been suppressed by the US Navy, in 1930 the US Congress sent a committee to investigate the status of American Samoa, led by Americans who had had a part in the overthrow of the Hawaiian Kingdom.

During World War II, U.S. Marines in American Samoa outnumbered the local population, having a huge cultural influence. Young Samoan men from the age of 14 and above were combat trained by US military personnel. As in WWI, American Samoans served in WWII as combatants, medical personnel, code personnel, ship repairs, etc.

== Current status of the territory and attempts of incorporation in the United States ==
After the war, Organic Act 4500, a U.S. [[United States Department of the Interior|Department of Interior]]-sponsored attempt to incorporate American Samoa, was defeated in Congress, primarily through the efforts of American Samoan chiefs, led by [[Tuiasosopo Mariota]]. These chiefs' efforts led to the creation of a local legislature, the [[American Samoa Fono|American Samoa ''Fono'']] which meets in the village of [[Fagatogo]], the territory's ''[[de facto]]'' and ''[[de jure]]'' capital.

In time, the Navy-appointed governor was replaced by a locally elected one. Although technically considered &quot;unorganized&quot; in that the [[Congress of the United States|U.S. Congress]] has not passed an [[Organic Act]] for the territory, American Samoa is self-governing under a constitution that became effective on July 1, 1967. The U.S. Territory of American Samoa is on the [[United Nations list of Non-Self-Governing Territories]], a listing which is disputed by territorial government officials.

The islands have been reluctant to separate from the USA in any manner. The [[maritime boundary|maritime boundaries]] of [[American Samoa]] with [[New Zealand]] ([[Tokelau]], the [[Cook Islands]], and [[Niue]]) have been determined in a series of treaties.  Maritime boundaries with [[Tonga]] and [[Samoa]] have yet to be agreed upon.

== Economy of American Samoa ==
Employment on the island basically falls into three relatively equally-sized categories of approximately 5,000 workers each: the public sector, the two tuna canneries, and the rest of the private sector. There are only a few federal employees in American Samoa and no active military personnel (there is an [[Army Reserve]] unit, however); the overwhelming majority of public sector employees work for the American Samoa Government. The two tuna canneries ([[StarKist]] and [[Samoa Packing]]) export several hundred million dollars worth of canned tuna to the United States.

== See also ==
{{Commons category}}
* [[Outline of American Samoa]]


{{U.S. political divisions histories}}
{{History of Oceania}}

[[Category:History of American Samoa| ]]</text>
      <sha1>563vdegqfiofer6xu96x58lpe4nlg94</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
