<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Greece</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>565594</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520188682</id>
      <parentid>520033899</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T00:21:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xqbot</username>
        <id>8066546</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[hr:Povijest Grčke]], [[tr:Yunanistan tarihi]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="61425">{{hatnote|This article covers the Greek civilization.  For the Greek language as a whole, see [[Greek language]].  For the Classical Greek language, see [[Ancient Greek]]. For the history of the modern republic, see [[History of modern Greece]].}}
{{Refimprove|date=August 2010}}
{{lead rewrite|date=September 2012}}

{{History of Greece}}
{{Culture of Greece}}

The '''history of Greece''' encompasses the history of the territory of the modern state of Greece, as well as that of the [[Greeks|Greek people]] and the areas they ruled historically. The scope of Greek habitation and rule has varied much through the ages, and, as a result, the history of Greece is similarly elastic in what it includes. Each era has its own related sphere of interest.

The first [[Proto-Greek language|(proto-) Greek-speaking]] tribes, known later as [[Mycenaean Greece|Mycenaeans]], are generally thought to have arrived in the Greek mainland between the late 3rd and the first half of the [[2nd millennium BC]] – probably between 1900 and 1600 BC.{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=77 &amp; 113}} When the Mycenaeans invaded, the area was inhabited by various non-Greek-speaking, indigenous pre-Greek people, who practiced agriculture as they had done since the [[Sesklo|7th millennium BC]].{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=13}}

At its geographical peak, Greek civilization spread from Greece to [[Egypt]] and to the [[Hindu Kush]] mountains in [[Afghanistan]]. Since then, Greek minorities have remained in former Greek territories (e.g., [[Turkey]], [[Albania]], [[Italy]], and [[Libya]], [[Levant]], [[Armenia]], [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], etc.), and Greek [[emigrants]] have assimilated into differing societies across the globe (e.g., [[North America]], [[Australia]], [[Northern Europe]], [[South Africa]], etc.). Nowadays most Greeks live in the modern state of Greece (independent since 1821) and [[Cyprus]].

==Prehistoric Greece==
{{main|Prehistoric Balkans}}
{{see also|Dimini|Sesklo|Dispilio}}

===Neolithic===
{{main|Neolithic Europe}}
The [[Neolithic Revolution]] reached Europe by way of Greece and the Balkans, beginning in the 7th millennium BC.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}} Some Neolithic communities in southeastern Europe, such as [[Sesklo]] in Greece, were living in heavily fortified settlements of 3,000-4,000 people. The Greek Neolithic era ended with the arrival of the [[Bronze Age]] from Anatolia and the Near East, by the end of the 28th century BC (early [[Helladic period]]).

In about 1900 BC, [[Proto-Indo-Europeans]] overran the Greek peninsula from the north and east.{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=77}} These Indo-Europeans, known as [[Mycenaeans]], introduced the Greek language to present-day Greece.{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=101}}

===Bronze Age===
{{main|Helladic period|Aegean Bronze Age}}

====Cycladic and Minoan civilization====
{{main|Minoan Civilization|Cycladic civilization}}

One of the earliest civilizations to appear around Greece was the [[Minoan civilization]] in [[Crete]], which lasted from about 2700 ([[Early Minoan]]) BC to 1450 BC, and the [[Early Helladic]] period on the Greek mainland from ca. 2800 BC to 2100 BC.

Little specific information is known about the Minoans (even the name is a modern appellation, from [[Minos]], the legendary king of [[Crete]]).{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=101}} They have been characterized as a [[Old European culture|pre-Indo-European]] people, apparently the linguistic ancestors of the [[Eteo-Cretan]] speakers of [[Classical Antiquity]], their language being encoded in the undeciphered [[Linear A]] script. They were primarily a mercantile people engaged in overseas trade, taking advantage of their land's rich natural resources. [[Timber]] was then an abundant natural resource that was commercially exploited and exported to nearby lands such as [[Cyprus]], [[Syria]], [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]] and the [[Aegean Islands]].{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=101}} During the [[Early Bronze Age]] (3300 BC through 2100 BC), the Minoan Civilization on the island of Crete held great promise for the future.{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=108}}

The Mycenaean Greeks invaded Crete and adopted much of the Minoan culture they found on Crete.{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=107}} The Minoan civilization which preceded the Mycenaean civilization on Crete was revealed to the modern world by Sir [[Arthur Evans]] in 1900, when he purchased and then began excavating a site at [[Knossus]].{{sfn|Roebuck|1966|p=108}}

====Mycenaean civilization====
{{main|Mycenaean Greece}}
[[File:Proto Greek Area reconstruction.png|thumb|350px|[[Proto-Greek language|Proto-Greek]] linguistic area according to linguist [[Vladimir I. Georgiev|V. I. Georgiev]].]]
The [[Proto-Greeks]] are [[1900 BCE Near East mass migration|assumed to have arrived]] in the [[Greek peninsula]] during the late 3rd to early 2nd millennium BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bryce|2006|p=91}}; {{harvnb|Cadogan|Langdon Caskey|1986|p=125}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[1900 BCE Near East mass migration|migration]] of the [[Ionians]] and [[Aeolians]] resulted in [[Mycenaean Greece]] by the 16th century BC.&lt;ref name=Brit1&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |year=2008 |title = The Greeks |encyclopedia= Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher= Encyclopædia Britannica Inc. |location=US |id=Online Edition }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Chadwick |first=John |authorlink=John Chadwick |title=The Mycenaean world  |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=RMj7M_tGaNMC&amp;dq |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |year=1976 |pages=1–3 |isbn=0-521-29037-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The transition from pre-Greek to Greek culture appears to have been rather gradual. Some archaeologists have pointed to evidence that there was a significant amount of continuity of prehistoric economic, architectural, and social structures, suggesting that the transition between the Neolithic, Helladic and early Greek cultures  may have continued without major rifts in social texture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Runnels |first1=Curtis Neil |last2=Murray |first2=Priscilla |title=Greece before history: an archaeological companion and guide |publisher=Stanford University Press |location=Stanford, Calif |year=2001 |page=64 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=rg4rTjo0OCQC&amp;dq |isbn=0-8047-4050-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On Crete, however, the Mycenean invasion of around 1400 BC spelled the end of the [[Minoan civilization]]. [[Mycenaean Greece]] is the [[Late Helladic]] Bronze Age civilization of [[Ancient Greece]]. It lasted from the arrival of the Greeks in the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]] around 1600 BC to the collapse of their Bronze Age civilization around 1100 BC. It is the historical setting of the [[Epic poetry|epic]]s of [[Homer]] and of most [[Greek mythology]]. The Mycenaean period takes its name from the archaeological site [[Mycenae]] in the northeastern [[Argolid]], in the [[Peloponnesos]] of southern Greece. [[Athens]], [[Pylos]], [[Thebes (Greece)|Thebes]], and [[Tiryns]] are also important Mycenaean sites.

Mycenaean civilization was dominated by a warrior [[aristocracy]]. Around 1400 BC the [[Mycenaeans]] extended their control to [[Crete]], center of the [[Minoan civilization]], and adopted a form of the Minoan script called [[Linear A]] to write their early form of [[Greek language|Greek]]. The Mycenaean era script is called [[Linear B]].

The Mycenaeans buried their nobles in [[beehive tombs]] (''tholoi''), large circular burial chambers with a high vaulted roof and straight entry passage lined with stone. They often buried daggers or some other form of military equipment with the deceased. The nobility were often buried with gold masks, tiaras, armour, and jeweled weapons. Mycenaeans were buried in a sitting position, and some of the nobility underwent [[mummy|mummification]].

Around 1100 BC the Mycenaean civilization collapsed. Numerous cities were sacked and the region entered what historians see as a [[Greek dark ages|dark age]]. During this period Greece experienced a decline in [[population]] and [[literacy]].  The Greeks themselves have traditionally blamed this decline on an [[Dorian invasion|invasion]] by another wave of Greek people, the [[Dorians]], although there is scant archaeological evidence for this view.

===Early Iron Age===
{{main|Greek Dark Ages}}
{{further|Protogeometric art}}
The ''Greek Dark Ages'' (ca. 1100 BC–800 BC) refers to the period of Greek history from the presumed [[Dorian invasion]] and end of the [[Mycenaean civilization]] in the 11th century BC to the rise of the first [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] [[city-state]]s in the 9th century BC and the epics of [[Homer]] and earliest writings in [[Greek alphabet|alphabetic]] [[Greek language|Greek]] in the 8th century BC.

The collapse of the Mycenaean coincided with the fall of several other large empires in the near east, most notably the [[Hittites|Hittite]] and the [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptian]]. The cause may be attributed to an invasion of the [[sea people]] wielding iron weapons. When the Dorians came down into Greece they also were equipped with superior iron weapons, easily dispersing the already weakened Mycenaeans. The period that follows these events is collectively known as the Greek Dark Ages.

Kings ruled throughout this period until eventually they were replaced with an aristocracy, then still later, in some areas, an aristocracy within an aristocracy—an elite of the elite. Warfare shifted from a focus on cavalry to a great emphasis on infantry. Due to its cheapness of production and local availability, iron replaced bronze as the metal of choice in the manufacturing of tools and weapons. Slowly equality grew among the different sects of people, leading to the dethronement of the various Kings and the rise of the family.

At the end of this period of stagnation, the Greek civilization was engulfed in a renaissance that spread the Greek world as far as the [[Black Sea]] and [[Spain]]. Writing was relearned from the [[Phoenicians]], eventually spreading north into [[Italy]] and the [[Gauls]].

==Ancient Greece==
{{Unreferenced section|date=August 2010}}
{{main|Ancient Greece}}
[[File:Plato Pio-Clementino Inv305 n2.jpg|thumb|&quot;The safest general characterisation of the European philosophical tradition is that it consists of a series of footnotes to [[Plato]].&quot; ([[Alfred North Whitehead]], ''[[Process and Reality]]'', 1929).]]

There are no fixed or universally agreed dates for the beginning or the end of the Ancient/Classical Greek period. In common usage it refers to all Greek history before the [[Roman Empire]], but historians use the term more precisely. Some writers include the periods of the [[Minoan civilization|Minoan]] and [[History of Mycenaean Greece|Mycenaean]] civilizations, while others argue that these civilizations were so different from later Greek cultures that they should be classed separately. Traditionally, the Ancient Greek period was taken to begin with the date of the first [[Olympic Games]] in 776 BC, but most historians now extend the term back to about 1000 BC.

The traditional date for the end of the Ancient Greek period is the death of [[Alexander the Great]] in 323 BC. The period that follows  is classed as [[History of Hellenistic Greece|Hellenistic]]. Not everyone treats the Ancient and Hellenic periods as distinct, however, and some writers treat the Ancient Greek civilization as a continuum running until the advent of [[Christianity]] in the 3rd century AD.

Ancient Greece is considered by most historians to be the foundational culture of [[Western world|Western Civilization]]. Greek culture was a powerful influence in the [[Roman Empire]], which carried a version of it to many parts of [[Europe]]. Ancient Greek civilization has been immensely influential on the language, politics, educational systems, philosophy, art and architecture of the modern world, particularly during the [[Renaissance]] in Western Europe and again during various [[Classicism|neo-Classical]] revivals in 18th and 19th century Europe and the [[Americas]].

===Archaic Greece===
{{main|Archaic Greece}}
{{further|Orientalizing Period|Geometric Art}}
In the 8th century BC, Greece began to emerge from the Dark Ages which followed the fall of the Mycenaean civilization. Literacy had been lost and [[Linear B|Mycenaean script]] forgotten, but the Greeks adopted the [[Phoenician alphabet]], modifying it to create the [[Greek alphabet]]. From about the 9th century BC, written records begin to appear.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Hall Jonathan M. |title=A history of the archaic Greek world, ca. 1200-479 BCE|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|year=2007| isbn= 978-0-631-22667-3 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WGNH-oxXiAUC&amp;dq=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Greece was divided into many small self-governing communities, a pattern largely dictated by Greek geography, where every island, valley and plain is cut off from its neighbours by the sea or mountain ranges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| authorlink=Raphael Sealey | first=Raphael | last=Sealey | title=A history of the Greek city states, ca. 700–338 B.C. | publisher=[[University of California Press]] | year=1976 | isbn= 978-0-631-22667-3 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kAvbhZrv4gUC&amp;dq= | pages= 10–11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Archaic period can be understood as the [[Orientalizing period]], when Greece was at the fringe, but not under the sway, of the budding [[Neo-Assyrian Empire]]. Greece adopted significant amounts of cultural elements from the Orient, in art as well as in religion and mythology. Archaeologically, Archaic Greece is marked by [[Geometric pottery]].

===Classical Greece===
{{main|Classical Greece}}
{{further|Classical Athens}}
[[File:3393 - Athens - Stoà of Attalus - Herodotus - Photo by Giovanni Dall'Orto, Nov 9 2009.jpg|thumb|[[Herodotus]] (5th century BC), one of the earliest nameable historians whose work survives.]]
[[File:Jacques-Louis David 004 Thermopylae.jpg|thumb|''[[Leonidas]] at [[Thermopylae]]'' by [[Jacques-Louis David]].]]

The basic unit of politics in Ancient Greece was the [[polis]], sometimes translated as [[city-state]]. &quot;Politics&quot; literally means &quot;the things of the polis&quot;. Each city was independent, at least in theory.  Some cities might be subordinate to others (a colony traditionally deferred to its mother city), some might have had governments wholly dependent upon others (the [[Thirty Tyrants]] in [[Athens]] was imposed by [[Sparta]] following the [[Peloponnesian War]]), but the titularly supreme power in each city was located within that city. This meant that when Greece went to war (e.g., against the [[Persian Empire]]), it took the form of an alliance going to war. It also gave ample opportunity for wars within Greece between different cities.

Two major wars shaped the Classical Greek world. The [[Greco-Persian Wars|Persian Wars]] (500–448 BC) are recounted in [[Herodotus]]'s ''[[The Histories of Herodotus|Histories]]''. [[Ionia]]n Greek cities [[Ionian Revolt|revolted]] from the [[Persian Empire]] and were supported by some of the mainland cities, eventually led by [[History of Athens|Athens]]. The notable battles of this war include [[Battle of Marathon|Marathon]], [[Battle of Thermopylae|Thermopylae]], [[Battle of Salamis|Salamis]], and [[Battle of Plataea|Plataea]].)

To prosecute the war and then to defend Greece from further Persian attack, Athens founded the [[Delian League]] in 477 BC. Initially, each city in the League would contribute ships and soldiers to a common army, but in time Athens allowed (and then compelled) the smaller cities to contribute funds so that it could supply their quota of ships. Secession from the League could be punished. Following military reversals against the Persians, the treasury was moved from [[Delos]] to Athens, further strengthening the latter's control over the League. The Delian League was eventually referred to pejoratively as the Athenian Empire.

In 458 BC, while the Persian Wars were still ongoing, war broke out between the Delian League and the [[Peloponnesian League]], comprising [[Sparta]] and its allies. After some inconclusive fighting, the two sides signed a peace in 447 BC. That peace, it was stipulated, was to last thirty years: instead it held only until 431 BC, with the onset of the [[Peloponnesian War]]. Our main sources concerning this war are [[Thucydides]]'s ''[[History of the Peloponnesian War]]'' and [[Xenophon]]'s ''[[Hellenica (Xenophon)|Hellenica]]''.

The war began over a dispute between [[Corcyra]] and [[Epidamnus]]; the latter was a minor enough city that Thucydides has to tell his reader where it is. [[Corinth]] intervened on the Epidamnian side. Fearful lest Corinth capture the Corcyran navy (second only to the Athenian in size), Athens intervened. It prevented Corinth from landing on Corcyra at the [[Battle of Sybota]], laid siege to [[Battle of Potidaea|Potidaea]], and forbade all commerce with Corinth's closely situated ally, [[Megara]] (the [[Megarian decree]]).

There was disagreement among the Greeks as to which party violated the treaty between the Delian and Peloponnesian Leagues, as Athens was technically defending a new ally. The Corinthians turned to Sparta for aid. Fearing the growing might&lt;!-- OK here: don't correct it--&gt; of Athens, and witnessing Athens' willingness to use it against the Megarians (the embargo would have ruined them), Sparta declared the treaty to have been violated and the Peloponnesian War began in earnest.

The first stage of the war (known as the Archidamian War for the Spartan king, [[Archidamus II]]) lasted until 421 BC with the signing of the [[Peace of Nicias]]. The Athenian general [[Pericles]] recommended that his city fight a defensive war, avoiding battle against the superior land forces led by Sparta, and importing everything needful by maintaining its powerful navy. Athens would simply outlast Sparta, whose citizens feared to be out of their city for long lest the [[helots]] revolt. 

This strategy required that Athens endure regular [[siege]]s, and in 430 BC it was visited with an awful [[Plague of Athens|plague that killed about a quarter of its people]], including Pericles. With Pericles gone, less conservative elements gained power in the city and Athens went on the offensive. It captured 300–400 Spartan [[hoplite]]s at the [[Battle of Pylos]]. This represented a significant fraction of the Spartan fighting force which the latter decided it could not afford to lose. Meanwhile, Athens had suffered humiliating defeats at [[Battle of Delium|Delium]] and [[Battle of Amphipolis|Amphipolis]]. The Peace of Nicias concluded with Sparta recovering its hostages and Athens recovering the city of [[Amphipolis]].

[[File:Map athenian empire 431 BC-en.svg|thumb|350px|Map of the [[Delian League]] (&quot;Athenian Empire&quot;) in 431 B.C., just prior to the [[Peloponnesian War]].]]
Those who signed the Peace of Nicias in 421 BC swore to uphold it for fifty years.  The second stage of the Peloponnesian War began in 415 BC when Athens embarked on the [[Sicilian Expedition]] to support an ally ([[Segesta]]) attacked by [[Syracuse, Italy|Syracuse]] and to conquer [[Sicily]]. Initially, Sparta was reluctant, but [[Alcibiades]], the Athenian general who had argued for the Sicilian Expedition, defected to the Spartan cause upon being accused of grossly impious acts and convinced them that they could not allow Athens to subjugate Syracuse. The campaign ended in disaster for the Athenians.

Athens' Ionian possessions rebelled with the support of Sparta, as advised by Alcibiades.  In 411 BC, an oligarchical revolt in Athens held out the chance for peace, but the Athenian navy, which remained committed to the democracy, refused to accept the change and continued fighting in Athens' name. The navy recalled Alcibiades (who had been forced to abandon the Spartan cause after reputedly seducing the wife of [[Agis II]], a Spartan king) and made him its head. The oligarchy in Athens collapsed and Alcibiades reconquered what had been lost.

In 407 BC, Alcibiades was replaced following a minor naval defeat at the [[Battle of Notium]].  The Spartan general [[Lysander]], having fortified his city's naval power, won victory after victory.  Following the [[Battle of Arginusae]], which Athens won but was prevented by bad weather from rescuing some of its sailors, Athens executed or exiled eight of its top naval commanders.  Lysander followed with a crushing blow at the [[Battle of Aegospotami]] in 405 BC which almost destroyed the Athenian fleet. Athens surrendered one year later, ending the Peloponnesian War.

The war had left devastation in its wake. Discontent with the [[Spartan hegemony]] that followed (including the fact that it ceded [[Ionia]] and [[Cyprus]] to the [[Persian Empire]] at the conclusion of the [[Corinthian War]] (395–387 BC); see [[Treaty of Antalcidas]]) induced the [[Thebes, Greece|Thebans]] to attack.  Their general, [[Epaminondas]], crushed Sparta at the [[Battle of Leuctra]] in 371 BC, inaugurating a period of Theban dominance in Greece. In 346 BC, unable to prevail in its ten-year war with [[Phocis]], Thebes called upon [[Philip II of Macedon]] for aid. [[Macedon]] quickly forced the city states into being united by the [[League of Corinth]] which led to the conquering of the Persian Empire and the Hellenistic Age had begun.

===Hellenistic Greece===
{{main|Hellenistic Greece}}
[[File:DemetriosPolyorchetes.jpg|thumb|Coin showing [[Demetrius I Poliorcetes]].]]
The Hellenistic period of Greek history begins with the death of [[Alexander the Great]] in 323 BC and ends with the [[annexation]] of the Greek peninsula and islands by [[Roman Republic|Rome]] in 146 BC. Although the establishment of Roman rule did not break the continuity of Hellenistic society and culture, which remained essentially unchanged until the advent of [[Christianity]], it did mark the end of Greek political independence. 

During the Hellenistic period the importance of &quot;Greece proper&quot; (that is, the territory of modern Greece) within the Greek-speaking world declined sharply. The great centres of Hellenistic culture were [[Alexandria]] and [[Antioch]], capitals of [[Ptolemaic Egypt]] and [[Seleucid Empire|Seleucid Syria]]. (See [[Hellenistic civilization]] for the history of Greek culture outside Greece in this period.)

Athens and her allies revolted against [[Macedon]] upon hearing that Alexander had died, but were defeated within a year in the [[Lamian War]]. Meanwhile, a struggle for power broke out among Alexander's generals, which resulted in the break-up of his empire and the establishment of a number of new kingdoms (see the [[Wars of the Diadochi]]). [[Ptolemy I Soter|Ptolemy]] was left with [[Egypt]], [[Seleucus I Nicator|Seleucus]] with the [[Levant]], [[Mesopotamia]], and points east. Control of Greece, [[Thrace]], and [[Anatolia]] was contested, but by 298 BC the [[Antigonid dynasty]] had supplanted the [[Antipatrid dynasty|Antipatrid]].

Macedonian control of the city-states was intermittent, with a number of revolts.  [[Athens]], [[Rhodes]], [[Pergamum]] and other Greek states retained substantial independence, and joined the [[Aetolian League]] as a means of defending it and restoring democracy in their states, where as they saw Macedon as a tyrannical kingdom because of the fact they had not adopted democracy. The [[Achaean League]], while nominally subject to the [[Ptolemaic dynasty|Ptolemies]] was in effect independent, and controlled most of southern Greece. [[Sparta]] also remained independent, but generally refused to join any league.

In 267 BC, [[Ptolemy II]] persuaded the Greek cities to revolt against Macedon, in what became the [[Chremonidean War]], after the Athenian leader [[Chremonides]]. The cities were defeated and Athens lost her independence and her democratic institutions. This marked the end of Athens as a political actor, although it remained the largest, wealthiest and most cultivated city in Greece. In 225 BC Macedon defeated the Egyptian fleet at [[Kos|Cos]] and brought the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]] islands, except Rhodes, under its rule as well.

[[Sparta]] remained hostile to the Achaeans, and in 227 BC invaded [[Achaea]] and seized control of the League. The remaining Acheans preferred distant Macedon to nearby Sparta, and allied with the former. In 222 BC the Macedonian army defeated the Spartans and annexed their city—the first time Sparta had ever been occupied by a different state.

[[File:Diadochen1.png|thumb|300px|The major [[Hellenistic civilization|Hellenistic]] realms included the [[Diadochi|Diadoch kingdoms]]:
{{legend|#787CAD|Kingdom of [[Ptolemy I Soter]]}}
{{legend|#50A249|Kingdom of [[Cassander]]}}
{{legend|#C38833|Kingdom of [[Lysimachus]]}}
{{legend|#C3B933|Kingdom of [[Seleucus I Nicator]]}}
{{legend|#AF3662|[[Epirus]]}}
Also shown on the map:
{{legend|#85AB54|[[Greek colonies]]}}
{{legend|#A361BD|[[Carthage]] (non-Greek)}}
{{legend|#70A9BE|[[Ancient Rome|Rome]] (non-Greek)}}
The orange areas were often in dispute after 281 BC. The [[kingdom of Pergamon]] occupied some of this area. Not shown: [[Indo-Greeks]].]]

[[Philip V of Macedon]] was the last Greek ruler with both the talent and the opportunity to unite Greece and preserve its independence against the ever-increasing power of [[Roman Republic|Rome]]. Under his auspices, the [[Peace of Naupactus]] (217 BC) brought conflict between Macedon and the Greek leagues to an end, and at this time he controlled all of Greece except Athens, Rhodes and Pergamum.

In 215 BC, however, Philip formed an alliance with Rome's enemy [[Carthage]]. Rome promptly lured the Achaean cities away from their nominal loyalty to Philip, and formed alliances with Rhodes and Pergamum, now the strongest power in [[Asia Minor]]. The [[First Macedonian War]] broke out in 212 BC, and ended inconclusively in 205 BC, but Macedon was now marked as an enemy of Rome.

In 202 BC, Rome defeated Carthage, and was free to turn her attention eastwards. In 198 BC, the [[Second Macedonian War]] broke out because Rome saw Macedon as a potential ally of the [[Seleucid Empire]], the greatest power in the east. Philip's allies in Greece deserted him and in 197 BC he was decisively defeated at the [[Battle of Cynoscephalae]] by the Roman proconsul [[Titus Quinctius Flaminius]].

Luckily for the Greeks, Flaminius was a moderate man and an admirer of Greek culture. Philip had to surrender his fleet and become a Roman ally, but was otherwise spared. At the [[Isthmian Games]] in 196 BC, Flaminius declared all the Greek cities free, although Roman garrisons were placed at Corinth and [[Chalcis]]. But the freedom promised by Rome was an illusion. All the cities except Rhodes were enrolled in a new League which Rome ultimately controlled, and aristocratic constitutions were favoured and actively promoted.

===Roman Greece===
{{main|Roman Greece}}
Militarily, Greece itself declined to the point that the [[Roman Republic|Romans]] conquered the land (168 BC onwards), though Greek culture would in turn conquer Roman life. Although the period of Roman rule in Greece is conventionally dated as starting from the sacking of [[Corinth]] by the Roman [[Lucius Mummius]] in 146 BC, Macedonia had already come under Roman control with the defeat of its king, [[Perseus of Macedon|Perseus]], by the Roman [[Aemilius Paullus]] at [[Pydna]] in 168 BC. 

The Romans divided the region into four smaller republics, and in 146 BC Macedonia officially became a province, with its capital at [[Thessalonica]]. The rest of the Greek [[city-states]] gradually and eventually paid homage to Rome ending their ''de jure'' autonomy as well. The Romans left local administration to the [[Greeks]] without making any attempt to abolish traditional political patterns. The [[agora]] in [[Athens]] continued to be the centre of civic and political life.

[[Caracalla]]'s decree in AD 212, the [[Constitutio Antoniniana]], extended citizenship outside [[Italy]] to all free adult men in the entire [[Roman Empire]], effectively raising provincial populations to equal status with the city of [[Rome]] itself. The importance of this decree is historical, not political. It set the basis for integration where the economic and judicial mechanisms of the state could be applied throughout the Mediterranean as was once done from Latium into all Italy. In practice of course, integration did not take place uniformly. Societies already integrated with Rome, such as Greece, were favored by this decree, in comparison with those far away, too poor or just too alien such as Britain, Palestine or Egypt.

Caracalla's decree did not set in motion the processes that led to the transfer of power from Italy and the West to Greece and the East, but rather accelerated them, setting the foundations for the millennium-long rise of Greece, in the form of the [[Eastern Roman Empire]], as a major power in [[Europe]] and the [[Mediterranean]] in the [[Middle Ages]].

==Byzantine Empire (4th century - 1453)==
{{main|Byzantine Empire|Byzantine Greece}}
[[File:Ravenna, san vitale, teodora e il suo seguito (prima metà del VI secolo).jpg|thumb|260px|[[Empress Theodora]] and her retinue (mosaic from [[Basilica of San Vitale]], [[Ravenna]], 6th century).]]
[[File:Greekfire-madridskylitzes1.jpg|thumb|260px|Depiction of the [[Greek fire]] by [[John Skylitzes]]' [[Madrid Skylitzes|Chronicle]] (late 11th century).]]

The history of the East Roman or Byzantine Empire is described by [[Byzantinist]] August Heisenberg as the history of &quot;the Christianized Roman empire of the Greek nation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Winnifrith |first =Tom | last2 =Murray | first2=Penelope | title=Greece Old and New | publisher = Macmillan | year=1983 | ISBN= 0-333-27836-4 | page=113}}. &quot;For August Heisenberg the Byzantine empire was 'the Christianised Roman empire of the Greek nation'.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The division of the empire into East and West and the subsequent collapse of the [[Western Roman Empire]] were developments that constantly accentuated the position of the Greeks in the empire and eventually allowed them to become identified with it altogether. The leading role of [[Constantinople]] began when [[Constantine the Great]] turned [[Byzantium]] into the new capital of the Roman Empire, from then on to be known as [[Constantinople]], placing the city at the center of Hellenism a beacon for the [[Greeks]] that lasted to the modern era.

The figures of [[Constantine the Great]] and [[Justinian I|Justinian]] dominated during 324–610. Assimilating the Roman tradition, the emperors sought to offer the basis for later developments and for the formation of the Byzantine Empire. Efforts to secure the borders of the Empire and to restore the Roman territories marked the early centuries. At the same time, the definitive formation and establishment of the [[Orthodox Christianity|Orthodox]] doctrine, but also a series of conflicts resulting from heresies that developed within the boundaries of the empire marked the early period of Byzantine history.

In the first period of the middle Byzantine era (610–867) the empire was attacked both by old enemies ([[Persian Empire|Persians]], [[Lombards]], [[Eurasian Avars|Avars]] and [[Slavs]]) as well as by new ones, appearing for the first time in history ([[Arabs]], [[Bulgars]]). The main characteristic of this period was that the enemy attacks were not localized to the border areas of the state but they were extended deep beyond, even threatening the capital itself. At the same time, these attacks lost their periodical and temporary character and became permanent settlements that transformed into new states, hostile to Byzantium. Those states were referred by the Byzantines as ''[[Sclavinia]]s''.

Changes were also observed in the internal structure of the empire which was dictated by both external and internal conditions. The predominance of the small free farmers, the expansion of the military estates and the development of the system of [[theme (Byzantine administrative unit)|theme]]s, brought to completion developments that had started in the previous period. Changes were noted also in the sector of administration: the administration and society had become immiscibly [[Greeks|Greek]], while the restoration of Orthodoxy after the [[iconoclasm|iconoclast]] movement, allowed the successful resumption of missionary action among neighboring peoples and their placement within the sphere of Byzantine cultural influence. During this period the state was geographically reduced and economically damaged, since it lost wealth-producing regions; however, it obtained greater lingual, dogmatic and cultural homogeneity.

From the late 8th century, the Empire began to recover from the devastating impact of successive invasions, and the reconquest of Greece began. Greeks from [[Sicily]] and [[Asia Minor]] were brought in as settlers. The [[Slavs]] were either driven out or assimilated and the Sclavinias were eliminated. By the middle of the 9th century, Greece was Greek again, and the cities began to recover due to improved security and the restoration of effective central control.

===Economic prosperity===
[[File:Palaiologos-Dynasty.svg|thumb|150px|Imperial flag during the [[Palaiologos]] dynasty. The four ''Bs'', or ''pyrekvola'', represent the initials of the family's motto.]]

When the Byzantine Empire was rescued from a period of crisis by the resolute leadership of the three [[Komnenos|Komnenoi]] emperors [[Alexios I Komnenos|Alexios]], [[John II Komnenos|John]] and [[Manuel I Komnenos|Manuel]] in the 12th century, Greece prospered. Recent research has revealed that this period was a time of significant growth in the rural economy, with rising population levels and extensive tracts of new agricultural land being brought into production. The widespread construction of new rural churches is a strong indication that prosperity was being generated even in remote areas.

A steady increase in population led to a higher population density, and there is good evidence that the demographic increase was accompanied by the revival of towns. According to Alan Harvey in his book ‘’Economic expansion in the Byzantine Empire 900-1200’’, towns expanded significantly in the twelfth century. Archaeological evidence shows an increase in the size of urban settlements, together with a ‘notable upsurge’ in new towns.  Archaeological evidence tells us that many of the medieval towns, including [[Athens]], [[Thessaloniki]], [[Thebes, Greece|Thebes]] and [[Corinth]], experienced a period of rapid and sustained growth, starting in the 11th century and continuing until the end of the 12th century.

The growth of the towns attracted the [[Venice|Venetians]], and this interest in trade appears to have further increased economic prosperity in Greece. Certainly, the Venetians and others were active traders in the ports of the [[Holy Land]], and they made a living out of shipping goods between the [[Crusader states|Crusader]] Kingdoms of [[Outremer]] and the West while also trading extensively with Byzantium and [[Egypt]].

===Artistic revival===
[[File:Madonna costantinopolitana, fine XI, inizio XII secolo 02.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Mosaic of [[Virgin Mary]] (11th century).]]

The 11th and 12th centuries are said to be the Golden Age of [[Byzantine art]] in Greece. Many of the most important Byzantine churches in and around Athens, for example, were built during these two centuries, and this reflects the growth of urbanisation in Greece during this period. There was also a revival in the mosaic art with artists showing great interest in depicting natural landscapes with wild animals and scenes from the hunt. Mosaics became more realistic and vivid, with an increased emphasis on depicting three-dimensional forms. With its love of luxury and passion for color, the art of this age delighted in the production of masterpieces that spread the fame of Byzantium throughout the Christian world.

Beautiful [[Byzantine silk|silks from the work-shops of Constantinople]] also portrayed in dazzling color animals—lions, elephants, eagles, and griffins—confronting each other, or representing Emperors gorgeously arrayed on horseback or engaged in the chase. The eyes of many patrons were attracted and the economy of Greece grew. In the provinces, regional schools of Architecture began producing many distinctive styles that drew on a range of cultural influences. All this suggests that there was an increased demand for art, with more people having access to the necessary wealth to commission and pay for such work.

Yet the marvelous expansion of Byzantine art during this period, one of the most remarkable facts in the history of the empire, did not stop there. From the tenth to the 12th century Byzantium was the main source of inspiration for the West. By their style, arrangement, and iconography the mosaics of St. Mark's at Venice and of the cathedral at Torcello clearly show their Byzantine origin. Similarly those of the Palatine Chapel, the Martorana at Palermo, and the cathedral of Cefalu, together with the vast decoration of the cathedral at Monreale, prove the influence of Byzantium οn the Norman Court of Sicily in the 12th century.

Hispano-Moorish art was unquestionably derived from the Byzantine. Romanesque art owes much to the East, from which it borrowed not only its decorative forms but the plan of some of its buildings, as is proved, for instance, by the domed churches of south-western France. Princes of Kiev, Venetian doges, abbots of [[Monte Cassino]], merchants of Amalfi, and the Norman kings of Sicily all looked to Byzantium for artists or works of art. Such was the influence of Byzantine art in the 12th century, that Russia, Venice, southern Italy and Sicily all virtually became provincial centers dedicated to its production.

===The Fourth Crusade===
{{main|Fourth Crusade|Frankokratia}}
[[File:LatinEmpire2.png|thumb|350px|The division of the [[Byzantine Empire]] after the [[Fourth Crusade]].]]

The year 1204 marks the beginning of the late Byzantine period, when probably the most important event for the Empire occurred. [[Constantinople]] was lost for the Greek people for the first time, and the empire was conquered by [[Latin]] crusaders and would be replaced by a new [[Latin Empire|Latin]] one, for 57 years. In addition, the period of Latin occupation decisively influenced the empire's internal development, as elements of feudality entered aspects of Byzantine life.

In 1261 the Greek empire was divided between the former Greek Byzantine [[Comnenos]] dynasty members (Epirus) and [[Palaiologos]] dynasty (the last dynasty until the fall of Constantinople). After the gradual weakening of the structures of the Greek Byzantine state and the reduction of its land from [[Ottoman Empire|Turkish]] invasions, came the fall of the Greek Byzantine Empire, at the hands of the [[Ottomans]], in 1453, when the Byzantine period is considered to have ended.

It must be pointed out that the term &quot;Byzantine&quot; is a contemporary one established by historians. People used to call the Empire from the 10th century on the Greek Empire as well as Romeo-Greek before that time; that's why Greeks sometimes call themselves Romioi, in a colloquial form. The Romeo term was used sometimes because of the legal tradition left in many aspects of the political administration of the Empire. It must also be added that many empires all around Europe had used this term, along with the Greek Byzantines, like the [[Carolingians]], or the Heiliges Römisches Reich (Latin Sacrum Romanum Imperium) of the [[Germans]] who looked at themselves as the legitimate heirs of the Roman Empire.

==Ottoman rule (15th century - 1821)==
{{main|Ottoman Greece|Greek War of Independence}}
[[File:Navarino.jpg|thumb|220px|The [[Battle of Navarino]], on October 1827, marked the effective end of Ottoman rule in Greece.]]
When the [[Ottomans]] arrived, two Greek migrations occurred. The first migration entailed the Greek [[intelligentsia]] migrating to Western Europe and influencing the advent of the Renaissance. The second migration entailed Greeks leaving the plains of the Greek peninsula and resettling in the mountains.&lt;ref&gt;Vacalopoulos, p. 45. ''The Greeks never lost their desire to escape from the heavy hand of the Turks, bad government, the impressment of their children, the increasingly heavy taxation, and the sundry caprices of the conqueror. Indeed, anyone studying the last two centuries of Byzantine rule cannot help being struck by the propensity of the Greeks to flee misfortune. The routes they chiefly took were: first, to the predominantly Greek territories, which were either still free or Frankish-controlled (that is to say, the Venetian fortresses in the Despotate of Morea, as well as in the Aegean and Ionian Islands) or else to Italy and the West generally; second, to remote mountain districts in the interior where the conqueror's yoke was not yet felt.''&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[millet system]] contributed to the ethnic cohesion of Orthodox Greeks by segregating the various peoples within the Ottoman Empire based on religion.

The Greeks living in the plains during Ottoman domination were either Christians who dealt with the burdens of foreign rule or Crypto-Christians (Greek Muslims who were secret practitioners of the Greek Orthodox faith). Some Greeks became [[Crypto-Christians]] to avoid heavy taxes and at the same time express their identity by maintaining their ties to the Greek Orthodox Church. However, Greeks who converted to [[Islam]] and were not Crypto-Christians were deemed Turks in the eyes of Orthodox Greeks, even if they didn't adopt Turkish language.

The Ottomans ruled Greece until the early 19th century.

==Modern Greek state (1821-)==
{{main|History of Modern Greece}}
[[File:Greekhistory.GIF|thumb|Territorial evolution of [[Kingdom of Greece]] until 1947.]]

In the early months of 1821, the Greeks [[Greek War of Independence|declared their independence]] but did not achieve it until 1829. The Great Powers first shared the same view concerning the necessity of preserving the ''status quo'' of the [[Ottoman Empire]], but soon changed their stance. Scores of non-Greeks volunteered to fight for the cause, including [[Lord Byron]]. 

On 20 October 1827, a combined British, French and Russian naval force destroyed the Ottoman and Egyptian armada. The Russian minister of foreign affairs, [[Ioannis Kapodistrias]], himself a Greek, returned home as President of the new [[First Hellenic Republic|Republic]]. After his assassination the European powers helped turn Greece into a monarchy; the first King, [[Otto of Greece|Otto]], came from [[Bavaria]] and the second, [[George I of Greece|George I]], from [[Denmark]].

During the 19th and early 20th centuries Greece sought to enlarge its boundaries to include the ethnic Greek population of the Ottoman Empire. The [[Ionian Islands]] were returned by Britain upon the arrival of the new King [[George I of Greece|George I]] in 1863 and [[Thessaly]] was ceded by the Ottomans. As a result of the [[Balkan Wars]] of 1912-13 [[Epirus (region)|Epirus]], southern [[Macedonia (region)|Macedonia]], [[Crete]] and the [[Aegean Islands]] were annexed into the [[Kingdom of Greece]]. Another enlargement followed in 1947, when Greece annexed the Dodecanese Islands from Italy.

===World War I and Greco-Turkish War===
[[File:Greece in the Treaty of Sèvres.jpg|thumb|Map of Greater Greece after the [[Treaty of Sèvres]], when the ''[[Megali Idea]]'' seemed close to fulfillment, featuring [[Eleftherios Venizelos]].]]
[[File:Greek Cavalry Asia Minor 1921.jpg|thumb|Greek cavalry attacking during the [[Greco-Turkish War (1919–1922)]].]]

In [[World War I]], Greece sided with the [[Triple Entente|Entente]] powers against [[Ottoman Empire]] and the other [[Central Powers]]. In the war's aftermath, the Great Powers awarded parts of [[Asia Minor]] to Greece, including the city of [[Smyrna]] (known as [[İzmir]] today) which had a Greek population of significant size.

However, the Turkish nationalists, led by [[Kemal Atatürk|Mustafa Kemal Atatürk]], overthrew the Ottoman government, organised a military assault on the Greek troops and defeated them. Immediately afterwards, over one million native Greeks of Turkey had to leave for Greece as a [[population exchange between Greece and Turkey]].

===World War II===
[[File:GreecefightsonBig.jpg|thumb|left|180px|American 1942 poster, during the [[World War II|WW2]], in support of Greece.]]

Despite the country's numerically small and ill-equipped armed forces, Greece made a decisive contribution to the [[Allies|Allied]] efforts in [[World War II]]. At the start of the war Greece sided with the Allies and refused to give in to Italian demands. [[Italy]] invaded Greece by way of [[Albania]] on 28 October 1940, but Greek troops repelled the invaders after a bitter struggle (see [[Greco-Italian War]]). This marked the first Allied victory in the war.

Primarily to secure his strategic southern flank, German dictator [[Adolf Hitler]] reluctantly stepped in and launched the [[Battle of Greece]].  Troops from [[Germany]], [[Bulgaria]], and [[Italy]] successfully invaded Greece, through [[Yugoslavia]], overcoming Greek, British, [[Australian]], and [[New Zealand]] units.

On 20 May 1941, the Germans attempted to [[Battle of Crete|seize Crete]] with a large attack by [[paratroop]]s—with the aim of reducing the threat of a counter-offensive by Allied forces in [[Egypt]]—but faced heavy resistance. The Greek campaign might have delayed German military plans against Soviet Union, and it is argued that had the German invasion of the [[Soviet Union]] started on 20 May 1941 instead of 22 June 1941, the Nazi assault against the Soviet Union might have succeeded. The heavy losses of German paratroopers led the Germans to launch no further large-scale air-invasions.

During the years of [[Axis occupation of Greece|Occupation of Greece by Nazi Germany]], thousands of Greeks died in direct combat, in concentration camps, or of starvation. The occupiers murdered the greater part of the [[Jewish]] community despite efforts by the [[Church of Greece|Greek Orthodox]] Church and many other [[Christian]] Greeks to shelter the Jews. The economy of Greece was devastated.

When the Soviet Army began its drive across [[Romania]] in August 1944, the German Army in Greece began withdrawing north and northwestward from Greece into [[Yugoslavia]] and [[Albania]] to avoid being cut off in Greece. Hence, the German occupation of Greece ended in October 1944. The Resistance [[ELAS]] seized control of Athens on 12 October 1944. British troops had already landed on 4 October in [[Patras]], and entered Athens at 14 October 1944.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Churchill|first=S.W.|title=The Second World War (Volume 6)|year=1953|page=285}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Greek Civil War===
The [[Greek Civil War]] ({{lang-el|Eμφύλιος πόλεμος ''Emfílios pólemos''}}), was fought between 1944 and 1949 in [[Greece]] between the Governmental forces of Greece supported by the [[United Kingdom]] at first, and later by the [[United States|USA]], and the [[Democratic Army of Greece]]; the military branch of the Greek communist party. According to some analysts, it represented the first example of a post-[[World War II|war]] West interference in the political situation of a foreign country.&lt;ref name= Noam&amp;Chomsky&gt;{{cite book|last=Chomsky|first=Noam|title=World Orders, Old And New|publisher=Pluto Press London|year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; The victory of the British—and later US-supported government forces led to Greece's membership in [[NATO]] and helped to define the ideological balance of power in the [[Aegean Sea|Aegean]] for the entire [[Cold War]].

The civil war consisted on one side of the armed forces of the postwar non-Marxist Greek administrations, and on the other, communist-led forces, and key members of the former [[resistance movement|resistance]] organization ([[National People's Liberation Army (Greece)|ELAS]]), the leadership of which was controlled by the [[Communist Party of Greece]] (KKE).

The first phase of the civil war occurred in 1942-1944. Marxist and non-Marxist resistance groups fought each other in a fratricidal conflict to establish the leadership of the Greek resistance movement. In the second phase (1944) the ascendant communists, in military control of most of Greece, confronted the returning Greek [[government in exile]], which had been formed under Western Allied auspices in [[Cairo]] and originally included six KKE-affiliated ministers. In the third phase (commonly called the &quot;Third Round&quot; by the Communists) (1946–1949), guerrilla forces controlled by KKE fought against the internationally recognized Greek Government which was formed after elections boycotted by KKE. Although the involvement of KKE in the uprisings was universally known, the party remained legal until 1948, continuing to coordinate attacks from its [[Athens]] offices until [[proscription]].

The civil war left Greece with a legacy of political polarization; as a result, Greece also entered into alliance with the United States and joined NATO, while relationships with its Communist northern neighbours, both pro-Soviet and neutral, became strained.

===Postwar recovery===
In the 1950s and 1960s, Greece developed rapidly, initially with the help of the U.S. [[Marshall Plan]]'s grants and loans, and later through growth in the [[tourism]] sector. New attention was given to [[women's rights]], and in 1952 [[women's suffrage|suffrage for women]] was guaranteed in the Constitution, full Constitutional equality following, and [[Lina Tsaldari]] becoming the first female minister that decade. 

In 1967, the Greek military seized power in a [[coup d'état]], overthrew the centre right government of [[Panagiotis Kanellopoulos]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Richard Clogg|title=A Concise History of Greece|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=H5pyUIY4THYC&amp;pg=PA159|year=2002|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=159}}&lt;/ref&gt; It established the [[Greek military junta of 1967-1974]] which became known as the ''Régime of the Colonels''.  In 1973, the régime abolished the [[Kings of Greece|Greek monarchy]]. In 1974, dictator [[George Papadopoulos|Papadopoulos]] denied help to the U.S. After a second coup that year, Colonel [[Dimitrios Ioannides|Ioannides]] was appointed as the new head-of-state.

Ioannides was responsible for the 1974 coup against President [[Makarios]] of [[Cyprus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Barry Bartmann|title=De Facto States: The Quest For Soverignty|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=uIbah-giC0EC&amp;pg=PA167|year=2003|publisher=Psychology Press|page=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; The coup became the pretext for the first wave of the [[Turkish invasion of Cyprus]] in 1974 (see [[Greco-Turkish relations]]). The Cyprus events and the outcry following a bloody suppression of [[Athens Polytechnic uprising]] in Athens led to the implosion of the military régime. An exiled politician, [[Konstantinos Karamanlis]], returned and became interim prime minister on July 23, 1974&lt;ref name=&quot;NATO Update 1974&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nato.int/docu/update/70-79/1974e.htm | title = NATO Update 1974| date = 26 October 2001 | publisher = NATO: North Atlantic Treaty Organization}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later gained re-election for two further terms at the head of the conservative [[Nea Dimokratia]] party. On August 21, 1971, Greek forces withdrew from the integrated military structure of NATO in protest at the Turkish occupation of northern Cyprus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Dr Fo Moustakis|title=The Greek-Turkish Relationship and NATO|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YAJ91tgEE_MC&amp;pg=PA33|year= 2003|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|page=33}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Restoration of democracy===
In 1975, a referendum voted 69%-31% to confirm the deposition of King [[Constantine II of Greece|Constantine II]]. A democratic republican constitution came into force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Geoffrey Pridham|title=Securing Democracy: Political Parties and Democratic Consolidation in Southern Europe|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=u2L2Fq5I404C&amp;pg=PA182|year=1990|publisher=Psychology Press|page=182}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another previously exiled politician, [[Andreas Papandreou]] also returned and founded the [[socialist]] [[Panhellenic Socialist Movement]] (PASOK) party, which won the elections in 1981 and dominated the country's political course for almost two decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Harry Coccossis|author2=Yannis Psycharis|title=Regional Analysis and Policy: The Greek Experience|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=x9TG0Q0xKJYC&amp;pg=PA45|year= 2008|publisher=Springer|page=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the restoration of democracy, the stability and economic prosperity of Greece have grown remarkably. Greece rejoined [[NATO]] in 1980. Greece joined the [[European Union]] in 1981 and adopted the [[euro]] as its currency in 2001. New infrastructure, funds from the EU and growing revenues from tourism, shipping, services, light industry and the telecommunications industry have brought Greeks an unprecedented standard of living. Tensions continue to exist between Greece and [[Turkey]] over Cyprus and the [[Aegean dispute|delimitation of borders]] in the [[Aegean Sea]] but relations have considerably thawed following successive earthquakes—first in Turkey and then in Greece—and an outpouring of sympathy and generous assistance by ordinary Greeks and Turks (see [[Greek-Turkish earthquake diplomacy|Earthquake Diplomacy]]).

===Economic crisis of 2009-2012===
{{main|Greek government-debt crisis}}
From late 2009, fears of a [[sovereign debt crisis]] developed among investors concerning Greece's ability to meet its debt obligations due to strong increase in [[government debt]] levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSLDE61F0W720100216 |title= Peripheral euro zone government bond spreads widen |agency=Reuters |author=George Matlock |date=16 February 2010 |accessdate=28 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/node/16009099 | title=Acropolis now | work=The Economist | date= 29 April 2010 |accessdate=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This led to a crisis of confidence, indicated by a widening of [[bond (finance)|bond]] [[yield spread]]s and risk insurance on [[credit default swap]]s compared to other countries, most importantly Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.financialmirror.com/News/Cyprus_and_World_News/20151 |title=Greek/German bond yield spread more than 1,000 bps |publisher=Financialmirror.com |date=28 April 2010 |accessdate=5 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/7d25573c-1ccc-11df-8d8e-00144feab49a.html |title=Gilt yields rise amid UK debt concerns |work=Financial Times  |date=18 February 2010 |accessdate=15 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Downgrading of Greek government debt to [[junk bonds]] created alarm in financial markets. On 2 May 2010, the Eurozone countries and the [[International Monetary Fund]] agreed on a {{Nowrap|€110 billion}} loan for Greece, conditional on the implementation of harsh austerity measures. 

In October 2011, Eurozone leaders also agreed on a proposal to write off 50% of Greek debt owed to private creditors, increasing the EFSF to about €1 trillion and requiring European banks to achieve 9% capitalization to reduce the risk of [[Financial contagion|contagion]] to other countries. These austerity measures have proved extremely unpopular with the Greek public, precipitating demonstrations and civil unrest. There are widespread fears that a Greek default on its debt would have global repercussions, endangering the economies of many other countries in the European Union, threatening the stability of the European currency, the euro, and possibly plunging the world into another recession. It has been speculated that the crisis will force Greece to abandon the euro and bring back its former currency, the drachma.

==See also==

* [[Intermediate Region]]
* [[History of Crete]]
* [[History of the Cyclades]]
* [[History of Thessaly]]
* [[History of Athens]]
* [[History of the Greek language]]
* [[Timeline of Ancient Greece]]
* [[Timeline of modern Greek history]]

'''Lists:'''
* [[List of ancient Greeks]]
* [[List of ancient Greek cities]]
* [[List of Kings of Greece]]
* [[List of Presidents of Greece]]
* [[List of Prime Ministers of Greece]]

'''General''':
* [[History of the Balkans]]
* [[History of Europe]]

==Further reading==
*{{cite book | last = Boardman |first= John | last2= et al. | title = The Oxford History of Greece &amp; the Hellenistic World | year = 2002}}
*{{Cite book | last=Brewer | first= David |title = Greece: The Hidden Centuries: Turkish Rule from the Fall of Constantinople to Greek Independence | publisher = I.B. Tauris | year= 2010 | pages=308}}
* {{cite book |last=Burn | first=A.R. |title = The Penguin History of Greece | year = 1966}}
*{{cite book | last = Cartledge | first=Paul |title=The Cambridge Illustrated History of Ancient Greece | year =2002}}
* {{cite book | author= [[John Chadwick|Chadwick, John]]| title=The Mycenaean World | publisher=[[Cambridge University Press|Cambridge UP]] | year=1976 | isbn=0-521-29037-6}}
*{{Cite book | last=Demand | first=Nancy H. |title =A History of Ancient Greece in Its Mediterranean Context | year=2006}}
*{{cite book | last=Grant | first= Michael | title =A Social History of Greece and Rome | year=1993}}
*{{Cite book | last= Koliopoulos |first=John S. |first2=Thanos M. | last2=Veremis | title = Modern Greece: A History since 1821 | year=2009}}
*{{cite book | last=Pomeroy | first=Sarah B. |last2=et al. |title = A Brief History of Ancient Greece: Politics, Society and Culture | year=2009}}
*{{Cite book | last = Woodhouse | first=C. M. | title = Modern Greece: A Short History | year=2000}}

==References==
* {{cite book | author= [[John Chadwick|Chadwick, John]]| title=The Mycenaean World | publisher=[[Cambridge University Press|Cambridge UP]] | year=1976 | isbn=0-521-29037-6}}
* {{cite book | author= Mountjoy, P.A. | title=Mycenaean Decorated Pottery: A Guide to Identification | publisher=Studies in Mediterranean Archaeology 73. [[Göteborg]]: Paul Åströms Forlag | year=1986 | isbn=91-86098-32-2}}
* {{cite book | author=Mylonas, George E. | title=Mycenae and the Mycenaean Age | publisher=[[Princeton University Press|Princeton UP]] | year=1966 | isbn=0-691-03523-7}}
* {{Cite encyclopedia | last = Podzuweit | first = Christian | year=1982 | title = Die mykenische Welt und [[Troy|Troja]] | editor-first= B. | editor-last=Hänsel | work = Südosteuropa zwischen 1600 und 1000 v. Chr. | pages=65–88}}
* {{cite book | first=Carl |last=Roebuck | title=The World of Ancient Times | publisher = Charles Scribner's Sons | location=New York | year=1966}}
* {{cite book | author= Taylour, Lord William| title=The Mycenaeans | publisher=Revised edition (1990). London: [[Thames &amp; Hudson]] | year=1964 | isbn=0-500-27586-6}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | authorlink = Joachim Latacz | first = Joachim | last = Latacz | title = Between [[Troy]] and [[Homer]]. The so-called Dark Ages in Greece | encyclopedia = Storia, Poesia e Pensiero nel Mondo antico. Studi in Onore di M. Gigante | location = [[Rome]] | year=1994}}
*{{cite book | last = Vacalopoulos | first=Apostolis | title = The Greek Nation, 1453-1669 | publisher = Rutgers University Press | year = 1976}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|History of Greece}}
* [http://projectsx.dartmouth.edu/classics/history/bronze_age/index.html Jeremy B. Rutter, &quot;The Prehistoric Archaeology of the Aegean&quot;]: chronology, history, bibliography
* [http://eudocs.lib.byu.edu/index.php/History_of_Greece:_Primary_Documents History of Greece: Primary Documents]
* [http://www.ahistoryofgreece.com/ A short history of Greece]

{{History of Europe}}
{{European history by country}}
{{Greece topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Greece}}
[[Category:History of Greece| ]]

{{Link GA|cs}}
{{Link GA|zh}}

[[ar:تاريخ اليونان]]
[[bn:গ্রিসের ইতিহাস]]
[[be:Гісторыя Грэцыі]]
[[bg:История на Гърция]]
[[ca:Història de Grècia]]
[[cs:Dějiny Řecka]]
[[cy:Hanes Groeg]]
[[de:Geschichte Griechenlands]]
[[el:Ελληνική ιστορία]]
[[es:Historia de Grecia]]
[[eu:Greziako historia]]
[[fr:Histoire de la Grèce]]
[[ko:그리스의 역사]]
[[hi:यूनान का इतिहास]]
[[hr:Povijest Grčke]]
[[io:Historio di Grekia]]
[[ia:Historia de Grecia]]
[[it:Storia della Grecia]]
[[he:היסטוריה של יוון]]
[[ka:საბერძნეთის ისტორია]]
[[la:Historia Graeca]]
[[lt:Graikijos istorija]]
[[li:Historie vaan Griekeland]]
[[jbo:xelso citri]]
[[hu:Görögország történelme]]
[[mk:Историја на Грција]]
[[ms:Sejarah Greece]]
[[nl:Geschiedenis van Griekenland]]
[[ja:ギリシャの歴史]]
[[no:Hellas’ historie]]
[[pl:Historia Grecji]]
[[pt:História da Grécia]]
[[ro:Istoria Greciei]]
[[ru:История Греции]]
[[sq:Historia e Greqisë]]
[[sk:Dejiny Grécka]]
[[sl:Zgodovina Grčije]]
[[sh:Historija Grčke]]
[[fi:Kreikan historia]]
[[sv:Greklands historia]]
[[th:ประวัติศาสตร์กรีซ]]
[[tr:Yunanistan tarihi]]
[[uk:Історія Греції]]
[[vi:Lịch sử Hy Lạp]]
[[yi:היסטאריע פון גריכנלאנד]]
[[zh:希腊历史]]</text>
      <sha1>c0fn0b7az7bp7hmadt5ff5mgwsyieka</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
