<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Luxembourg</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17830</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522358047</id>
      <parentid>522357164</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T17:42:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjensen</username>
        <id>313197</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Further reading */ add cite</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34064">{{Refimprove|date=August 2009}}
{{History of the Low Countries}}
The '''history of Luxembourg''' is inherently entwined with the histories of surrounding countries, peoples, and ruling dynasties.  Over time, the territory of [[Luxembourg]] has been eroded, whilst its ownership has changed repeatedly, and its political independence has grown gradually.
''
Although recorded Luxembourgian history dates back to [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] times, the history of Luxembourg proper is considered to begin in 963.  Over the following five centuries, the powerful [[House of Luxembourg]] emerged. Its extinction put an end to Luxembourgian independence.  After a brief spell of [[Duchy of Burgundy|Burgundian]] rule, Luxembourg fell into the hands of the [[Habsburg]]s in 1477.

After the [[Eighty Years' War]], Luxembourg became a part of the [[Southern Netherlands]], which passed to the Austrian line of the Habsburg dynasty in 1713.  After occupation by [[Revolutionary France]], the 1815 [[Treaty of Paris, 1815|Treaty of Paris]] transformed Luxembourg into a [[Grand Duchy]] in [[personal union]] with the [[United Kingdom of the Netherlands|Netherlands]].  The treaty also resulted in the second [[Partitions of Luxembourg|partition of Luxembourg]], the first being in 1658 and the third in 1839.  Although these treaties greatly reduced Luxembourg's territory, they increased Luxembourg's independence, which was confirmed after the [[Luxembourg Crisis]] in 1867.

In the following decades, Luxembourg fell further into Germany's [[sphere of influence]], particularly after the creation of a separate ruling house in 1890.  Luxembourg was occupied by Germany [[German occupation of Luxembourg in World War I|from 1914 until 1918]] and again [[German occupation of Luxembourg in World War II|from 1940 until 1944]].  Since the [[World War II|Second World War]], Luxembourg has become one of the world's richest countries, buoyed by a booming [[financial services]] sector, political stability, and [[European integration]].

==Ancient Luxembourg (before 963)==
{{See also|Celtic Luxembourg}}

In the territory now covered by the [[Grand Duchy of Luxembourg]], there is evidence of primitive inhabitants right back to the Paleolithic or old stone age over 35,000 years ago. The oldest artifacts from this period are decorated bones found at Oetrange.[2]

However, the first real evidence of civilization is from the Neolithic or 5th millennium BC when houses began to appear. Traces have been found in the south of Luxembourg at Grevenmacher, Diekirch, Aspelt and Weiler-la-Tour. The dwellings were made of a combination of tree trunks for the basic structure, mud-clad wickerwork walls, and roofs of thatched reeds or straw.[3] Pottery from this period has been found near Remerschen.[4]

While there is not much evidence of communities in Luxembourg at the beginning of the Bronze Age, a number of sites dating back to the period between the 13th and the 8th century BC provide evidence of dwellings and reveal artifacts such as pottery, knives and jewelry. These include Nospelt, Dalheim, Mompach and Remerschen.

The [[Celts]] inhabited what is now Luxembourg from roughly 600 BC until 100 AD. The Celts inhabited large areas of Europe from the [[Danube]] to the [[Rhine]] and [[Rhône]] during this time. It was around 100 BC that the [[Treveri]], one of the [[Celtic tribes]], entered a period of prosperity. They constructed a number of fortified settlements or [[oppida]] near the [[Moselle valley]] in what is now southern Luxembourg, western Germany and eastern France.[1]

The Celtic civilization reached its height in the 1st century BC, prior to the Roman conquest in 54 BC. Most of the evidence from that period has been discovered in tombs, many closely associated with Titelberg, a 50 ha site which reveals much about the dwellings and handicrafts of the period.

The first known reference to the territory in modern Luxembourg was by [[Julius Caesar]] in his ''[[Commentarii de Bello Gallico|Commentaries on the Gallic War]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09465a.htm |title=Luxembourg |accessdate=2006-07-30 |year=1913 |publisher=Catholic Encyclopaedia }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Celtic tribe in what is now Luxembourg during and after the [[La Tène period]] was known as the [[Treveri]]. By and large, the Treveri were more co-operative with the Romans, who completed their occupation in 53 BC under Julius Caesar, than most [[Gallic tribes]]. Two 1st-century AD revolts did not permanently damage their cordial relations with Rome, and the Treveri adapted readily to Roman civilization.

==Medieval Luxembourg (963 – 1477)==
[[Image:Early settlements in LuxbrgCity-english.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Early settlements in the area of present-day Luxembourg City before the 10th century with the church Saint-Saveur, today St.Micheal, built in 987]]

The history of Luxembourg properly began with the construction of Luxembourg Castle in the [[Middle Ages]].  It was Siegfried I, [[Earldom|Count]] of [[Ardennes]] who traded some of his ancestral lands with the monks of the [[Abbey of St. Maximin]] in [[Trier]] in 963 for an ancient, supposedly [[Ancient Rome|Roman]], fort named ''Lucilinburhuc''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/04/17/whos-afraid-of-greater-luxembourg/ | work=The New York Times | first=Frank | last=Jacobs | title=Who's Afraid of Greater Luxembourg? | date=17 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Modern historians explain the etymology of the word with ''Letze'', meaning fortification which might have referred to either the remains of a Roman watchtower or to a primitive refuge of the early Middle Ages.

Around this fort a town gradually developed, which became the centre of a small but important state of great strategic value to France, Germany and the Netherlands. Luxembourg's fortress, located on a rocky outcrop known as the [[Bock (Luxembourg)|Bock]], was steadily enlarged and strengthened over the years by successive owners, among others the [[Bourbons]], [[Habsburg]]s and [[Hohenzollern]]s, which made it one of the strongest fortresses on the European continent.  Its formidable defences and strategic location caused it to become known as the ‘[[Gibraltar]] of the North’.

The [[House of Luxembourg|Luxembourgish dynasty]] provided several [[Holy Roman Emperor]]s, Kings of [[Bohemia]], and [[Archbishop]]s of [[Trier]] and [[Mainz]]. From the [[Early Middle Ages]] to the [[Renaissance]], Luxembourg bore multiple names, depending on the author. These include ''Lucilinburhuc'', ''Lutzburg'', ''Lützelburg'', ''Luccelemburc'', ''Lichtburg'', among others.

Luxembourg remained an independent [[fief]] (county) of the [[Holy Roman Empire]] until 1354, when the emperor [[Charles IV, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles IV]] elevated it to the status of a [[duchy]].  At that time the Luxembourg family held the Crown of [[Bohemia]], but the duchy was usually possessed as [[appanage]] by a separate branch of the family. In 1437 the imperial Luxembourg family became extinct in the male line.  At that time, the duchy and castle were held by the Bohemian princess [[Elisabeth of Gorlitz, Duchess of Luxembourg]], a cadet granddaughter of emperor Charles IV. Elisabeth was childless, and in 1440 made a treaty with her powerful neighbour [[Philip III, Duke of Burgundy]] that Philip would administer the duchy and inherit it after the Duchess Elisabeth's death. Elisabeth died in 1451, but Philip accelerated things by expelling Elisabeth in 1443. The heirs of the main Luxembourg dynasty were not happy with the arrangement the Burgundians had made, and managed at times to wrest the possession from Burgundy. The [[Habsburg]] prince [[Ladislas the Posthumous]], king of Bohemia and Hungary (d. 1457), held the title in the 1450s. After his death, his brother-in-law [[William of Thuringia]] (1425 to 1482) held (or at least claimed) it from 1457 to 1469. In 1467, [[Elizabeth of Austria (1436–1505)|Elisabeth, Queen of Poland]], the last surviving sister of Ladislas, renounced her right in favour of Burgundy by treaty and some concessions, since the possession was next to impossible to hold against Burgundian actions. After being captured by [[Philip the Good|Philip]] of [[Duchy of Burgundy|Burgundy]] in 1443 and ultimately from 1467 to 1469, the duchy became one of the [[Seventeen Provinces]] of the Netherlands. With the marriage of [[Mary of Burgundy]] in 1477 all the Netherlands provinces, including Luxembourg, came under Habsburg rule in the person of her husband Maximilian, and later their son [[Philip the Handsome]].

==Habsburg (1477–1795) and French (1795-1815) rule==
[[Image:Luxembourg New Arms.svg|150px|right|thumb|[[Coat of arms]] of the Counts, Dukes and Grand Dukes of Luxembourg]]In these centuries the electors of Brandenburg, later kings of Prussia ([[Prussia|Borussia]]), advanced their claim to the Luxembourg patrimony as heirs-general to William of Thuringia and his wife Anna of Bohemia, the disputed dukes of Luxembourg of the 1460s – Anna was the eldest daughter of the last Luxembourg heiress. From 1609 onwards, they had a territorial base in the vicinity, the [[Duchy of Cleves]], the starting-point of the future [[Prussian Rhineland]]. This Brandenburger claim ultimately produced some results when some districts of Luxembourg were united with Prussia in 1813.

The first Hohenzollern claimant to descend from both Anna and her younger sister Elisabeth, was [[John George, Elector of Brandenburg]] (1525–98), his maternal grandmother having been [[Barbara Jagiellon]]. In the late 18th century, the younger line of [[Orange-Nassau]] (the princes who held sway in the neighbouring Dutch oligarchy) also became related to the Brandenburgers.

In 1598, the then possessor, [[Philip II of Spain]], bequeathed Luxembourg and the other Low Countries to his daughter the Infanta [[Isabella Clara Eugenia]] and her husband [[Albert VII, Archduke of Austria]]. Albert was an heir and descendant of [[Elisabeth of Austria (d. 1505)]], queen of Poland, the youngest granddaughter of [[Sigismund of Luxembourg]], the Holy Roman Emperor. Thus, Luxembourg returned to the heirs of the old Luxembourg dynasty – at least those of the line of Elisabeth. The Low Countries were a separate political entity during the couple's reign. After Albert's childless death in 1621, Luxembourg passed to his great-nephew and heir [[Philip IV of Spain]], who through his paternal grandmother Anna of Austria, queen of Spain, Albert's sister, was the primogenitural heir to the Queen Elisabeth of Poland.

[[Siege of Luxembourg (1684)|Luxembourg was invaded]] by [[Louis XIV of France]] (husband of Maria Theresa, daughter of Philip IV) in 1684, an action that caused alarm among France's neighbours and resulted in the formation of the [[League of Augsburg]] in 1686. In the ensuing [[War of the Grand Alliance]], France was forced to give up the duchy, which was returned to the Habsburgs by the [[Treaty of Ryswick]] in 1697. During this period of French rule, the defences of the fortress were strengthened by the famous [[siege]] engineer [[Vauban]]. The French king's great-grandson Louis (1710–74) was, from 1712, the first heir-general of Albert VII. Albert VII was a descendant of Anna of Bohemia and William of Thuringia, having that blood through his mother's Danish great-great-grandmother, but was not the heir-general of that line. Louis was the first real claimant of Luxembourg to descend from both sisters, the daughters of [[Elisabeth of Bohemia (1409–1442)|Elisabeth of Bohemia]], the last Luxembourg empress.

Habsburg rule was confirmed in 1715 by the [[Treaty of Utrecht (1713)|Treaty of Utrecht]], and Luxembourg was integrated into the [[Southern Netherlands|Austrian Netherlands]]. Emperor Joseph and his successor Emperor Charles VI were descendants of Spanish kings who were heirs of Albert VII. Joseph and Charles VI were also descendants of Anna of Bohemia and William of Thuringia, having that blood through their mother, although they were heirs-general of neither line. Charles was the first ruler of Luxembourg to descend from both sisters, daughters of [[Elisabeth of Bohemia (1409–1442)|Elisabeth of Bohemia]], the last Luxembourg empress.

Austrian rulers were more or less ready to exchange Luxembourg and other territories in the Low Countries. Their purpose was to round out and enlarge their power base, which in geographical terms was centered around Vienna. Thus, Bavarian candidate(s) emerged to take over the Duchy of Luxembourg, but this plan led to nothing permanent. Emperor [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor|Joseph II]] however made a preliminary pact to make a neighbour of Luxembourg, [[Charles Theodore, Elector Palatine]], as Duke of Luxembourg and king in the Low Countries, in exchange of his possessions in Bavaria and Franconia. However, this scheme was aborted due to [[Prussia]]'s opposition. Charles Theodore, who would thus have become Duke of Luxembourg, was genealogically a junior descendant of both Anna and Elisabeth, but main heir of neither.

During the [[War of the First Coalition]], Luxembourg was conquered and annexed by [[Revolutionary France]], becoming part of the ''[[Départements of France|département]]'' of the [[Forêts]]&lt;ref&gt;Literally 'woods', in reference to the [[Ardennes]].&lt;/ref&gt; in 1795.  The annexation was formalised at [[Treaty of Campo Formio|Campo Formio]] in 1797. In 1798 Luxembourgish peasants rebelled against the French but the Rebellion was rapidly oppressed.This short Rebellion is called the [[Peasants' War (1798)|Peasant's War]].

==Developing independence (1815–1890)==
[[Image:LuxembourgPartitionsMap english.png|thumb|left|250px|The three Partitions of Luxembourg]]
Luxembourg remained more or less under French rule until the [[Treaty of Paris (1815)|defeat]] of [[Napoleon]] in 1815, when the [[Congress of Vienna]] gave formal autonomy to Luxembourg. The Prussians had already in 1813 managed to wrest lands from Luxembourg, to strengthen the Prussian-possessed [[Duchy of Julich]]. The Bourbons of France held a strong claim to Luxembourg, the Emperor of Austria on the other hand had controlled the duchy until the revolutionary forces had joined it to the French republic (he reportedly was not enthusiastic about regaining Luxembourg and the Low Countries, being more interested in the Balkans). The King of Prussia held the claim of the senior heiress, Anna. An additional claimant emerged, [[William VI, Prince of Orange]] who now ruled the Netherlands, and whose mother and wife were descendants of the Prussian royal family and thus also descendants of both daughters of the last Luxembourg heiress. Prussia and Orange-Nassau made the following exchange deal: Prussia received the [[Principality of Orange-Nassau]], which included the ancestral lands of Nassau in Central Germany; the Prince of Orange in turn received Luxembourg.

Luxembourg, somewhat diminished in size (as the medieval lands had been slightly reduced by the French and Prussian heirs), was augmented in another way through the elevation to the status of [[grand duchy]] and placed under the rule of [[William I of the Netherlands]]. This was the first time that the duchy had a monarch who had no claim to inheritance of the medieval patrimony (as lineages through his mother and wife had a better entitled claimant, the Prussian king himself). However, Luxembourg's military value to [[Prussia]] prevented it from becoming a part of the Dutch kingdom. The fortress, ancestral seat of the medieval Luxembourgers, was taken over by Prussian forces, following Napoleon's defeat, and Luxembourg became a member of the [[German Confederation]] with Prussia responsible for its defense.

In July 1819 a contemporary from Britain visited Luxembourg: his journal offers some insights.   [[Norwich Duff]] writes that &quot;Luxembourg is considered one of the strongest fortifications in Europe, and … it appears so. It is situated in [[Netherlands|Holland]] (then as now used by English speakers as shorthand for the Netherlands) but by treaty is [[Fortified town|garrisoned]] by Prussians and 5,000 of their troops occupy it under a [[William I, Elector of Hesse|Prince of Hesse]]. The civil government is under the Dutch and the [[taxes|duties]] collected by them.   The town is not very large but the streets are broader than [in] the French towns and clean ands the houses are good.... [I] got the cheapest of [[public bathing|hot baths]] here at the principal house I ever had in my life: one franc.&quot;

Much of the Luxembourgish population joined the [[Belgian revolution]] against [[United Kingdom of the Netherlands|Dutch]] rule. Except for the fortress and its immediate vicinity Luxembourg was considered a province of the new Belgian state from 1830 to 1839. By the [[Treaty of London, 1839|Treaty of London]] in 1839 the status of the grand duchy was confirmed as sovereign and in personal union to the king of the Netherlands. In turn, the predominantly French speaking part of the duchy was ceded to Belgium as the [[Luxembourg (province of Belgium)|province de Luxembourg]]. This loss left the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg a predominantly German state, although French cultural influence remained strong. The loss of Belgian markets also caused painful economic problems for the state. Recognizing this, the grand duke integrated it into the German ''[[Zollverein]]'' in 1842. Nevertheless, Luxembourg remained an underdeveloped agrarian country for most of the century. As a result of this about one in five of the inhabitants [[Luxembourg American|emigrated]] to the United States between 1841 and 1891.

===Crisis of 1867===
{{Main|Luxembourg Crisis}}
It was not until 1867 that Luxembourg's independence was formally ratified, after a turbulent period which even included a brief time of civil unrest against plans to annex Luxembourg to Belgium, Germany or France. The [[Luxembourg crisis|crisis]] of 1867 almost resulted in war between France and Prussia over the status of Luxembourg. It involved competition between France and Prussia over control of Luxembourg, which had become free of German control when the German Confederation was abolished at the end of the [[Seven Weeks War]] in 1866. 

William III, king of the Netherlands, which still had sovereignty over Luxembourg, was willing to sell the grand duchy to France's Emperor [[Napoleon III]] in order to retain Limbourg but backed out when Prussian chancellor [[Otto von Bismarck]] expressed opposition. The growing tension brought about a conference in London from March to May 1867 in which the British served as mediators between the two rivals. Bismarck manipulated public opinion, resulting in the denial of sale to France and the continued suzerainty of Holland, a member of the customs union with close ties to Prussia.  The issue was resolved by the second [[Treaty of London, 1867|Treaty of London]] which guaranteed the perpetual independence and [[Neutral country|neutrality]] of the state. The fortress walls were pulled down and the Prussian garrison was withdrawn.&lt;ref&gt;Frédéric Laux, &quot;Bismarck et l'affaire du Luxembourg de 1867 a la Lumiere des Archives Britanniques,&quot; [Bismarck and the Luxembourg Affair of 1867 in Light of British Archives] ''Revue d'histoire diplomatique'' 2001 115(3): 183-202&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herbert Maks, &quot;Zur Interdependenz Innen- Und Aussenpolitischer Faktoren in Bismarcks Politik in Der Luxemburgischen Frage 1866/67,&quot; [&quot;The Interdependence of Domestic and Foreign Factors in Bismarck's Policies on the Luxembourg Question, 1866-67] ''Francia'' Part 3 19./20. 1997 24(3): 91-115.&lt;/ref&gt;

Famous visitors to Luxembourg in the 18th and 19th centuries included the German poet [[Johann Wolfgang von Goethe]], the French writers [[Emile Zola]] and [[Victor Hugo]], the composer [[Franz Liszt]], and the English painter [[Joseph Mallord William Turner]].

==Separation and the World Wars (1890–1945)==
Luxembourg remained a possession of the kings of the Netherlands until the death of [[William III of the Netherlands|William III]] in 1890, when the grand duchy passed to the House of Nassau-Weilburg due to a Nassau inheritance pact of 1783.

===First World War===
World War I affected Luxembourg at a time when the nation-building process was far from complete. The small grand duchy (about 260,000 inhabitants in 1914) opted for an ambiguous policy between 1914 and 1918. With the country occupied by Germans troops, the government, led by Paul Eyschen, chose to remain neutral. This strategy had been elaborated with the approval of [[Marie-Adélaïde, Grand Duchess of Luxembourg]]. Although continuity prevailed on the political level, the war caused social upheaval, which laid the foundation for the first [[trades union]] in Luxembourg.

===Interwar period===
The end of the occupation in November 1918 squared with a time of uncertainty on the international and national levels. The victorious Allies disapproved of the choices made by the local élites, and some Belgian politicians even demanded the (re)integration of the country into a greater Belgium. Within Luxembourg a strong minority asked for the creation of a republic. In the end, the grand duchy remained a monarchy but was led by a new head of state, [[Charlotte, Grand Duchess of Luxembourg|Charlotte]]. In 1921 it entered into an economic and monetary union with Belgium, the Union Économique Belgo-Luxembourgeoise (UEBL). During most of the 20th century, however, Germany remained its most important economic partner.

The introduction of [[universal suffrage]] for men and women favored the Rechtspartei (party of the Right), which played the dominant role in the government throughout the 20th century, with the exception of 1925–26 and 1974–79, when the two other important parties, the [[Liberal League (Luxembourg)|Liberal]] and the [[Social Democratic Party (Luxembourg)|Social-Democratic]] parties, formed a coalition. The success of the resulting party was due partly to the support of the church — the population was more than 90 percent Catholic — and of its newspaper, the ''Luxemburger Wort''.

On the international level, the interwar period was characterized by an attempt to put Luxembourg on the map. Especially under Joseph Bech, head of the Department of Foreign Affairs, the country participated more actively in several international organizations, in order to ensure its autonomy. On December 16, 1920, Luxemburg became a member of the [[League of Nations]]. On the economic level in the 1920s and the 1930s, the agricultural sector declined in favor of industry, but even more so for the service sector. The proportion of the active population in this last sector rose from 18 percent in 1907 to 31 percent in 1935.

In the 1930s the internal situation deteriorated, as Luxembourgish politics were influenced by European left- and right-wing politics. The government tried to counter [[communist]]-led unrest in the industrial areas and continued friendly policies towards [[Nazi Germany]], which led to much criticism. The attempts to quell unrest peaked with the ''[[Maulkuerfgesetz]]'', the &quot;muzzle&quot; Law, which was an attempt to outlaw the [[Communist Party of Luxembourg|Communist Party]]. The law was turned down in a 1937 referendum.

===Second World War===
Upon the outbreak of the [[Second World War]] in September 1939, the government of Luxembourg observed its neutrality and issued an official proclamation to that effect on September 6, 1939.&lt;ref&gt;Government of the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg, ''Luxembourg and the German Invasion: Before and After'' (London and New York, 1942) p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; On May 10, 1940, the Luxembourgish government and monarchy was swept away into exile by the German invasion of that date. The German invasion, made up of the [[1st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|1st]], [[2nd Panzer Division|2nd]], and [[10th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|10th Panzer Divisions]] began at 04:35. They did not encounter any significant resistance save for some bridges destroyed and some land mines, since the majority of the Luxembourgish Volunteer Corps stayed in their barracks. Luxembourgish police resisted the German troops, however, to little avail; the capital city was occupied before noon. Total Luxembourgish casualties amounted to 75 police and soldiers captured, six police wounded, and one soldier wounded.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alistair Horne|Horne, Alistair]], ''To Lose a Battle'', p.258-264&lt;/ref&gt; The Luxembourg royal family and their entourage received visas from [[Aristides de Sousa Mendes]] in Bordeaux. They crossed into Portugal and subsequently traveled to the United States in two groups: on the USS Trenton from Lisbon to Baltimore in July 1940, and on the Pan American airliner Yankee Clipper in October 1940. Throughout the war, Grand Duchess Charlotte broadcast via on [[BBC]] to Luxembourg to give hope to the people.  

The state was [[German occupation of Luxembourg in World War II|placed under military occupation until August 1942, when it was formally annexed]] by the [[Third Reich]] as part of the ''[[Gau (German)|Gau]]'' ''Moselland''. Luxembourgers were declared to be German citizens and 13,000 were called up for military service.  2,848 Luxembourgers eventually died fighting in the German army.  

Luxembourgish opposition to this annexation took the form of passive resistance at first, as in the ''[[Spéngelskrich]]'' (lit. &quot;War of the Pins&quot;), and by the refusal to speak German.  As French was forbidden, many Luxembourgers resorted to resuscitating old Luxembourgish words, which led to a renaissance of the language.  Other measures included [[deportation]], [[forced labour]], [[forced conscription]] and, more drastically, [[internment]], deportation to [[concentration camps]] and execution.  

The latter measure was applied after the so-called [[Luxembourgian general strike of 1942|general strike]] from 1 September to 3 September 1942, which paralyzed the administration, agriculture, industry and education as response to the declaration of [[forced conscription]] by the German administration on 30 August 1942.  It was violently suppressed: 21 strikers were executed and hundreds more deported to [[concentration camps]].  The then civilian administrator of Luxembourg, [[Gauleiter]] [[Gustav Simon]] had declared conscription necessary to support the German war effort.  It was to remain one of the few mass strikes against the German war machinery in Western Europe.

U.S. forces liberated most of the country in September 1944, they entered the capital city on 10 September 1944. During the [[Ardennes Offensive]] ([[Battle of the Bulge]]) German troops took back most of northern Luxembourg for a few weeks.  The Germans were finally expelled in January 1945. Altogether, of a pre-war population of 293,000, 5,259 Luxembourgers lost their lives during the hostilities.

==Modern history (since 1945)==
After [[World War II]] Luxembourg abandoned its politics of [[Neutral country|neutrality]], when it became a founding member of the [[NATO|North Atlantic Treaty Organization]] (1949) and the [[United Nations]].  It is a signatory of the [[Treaty of Rome]], and constituted a monetary union with Belgium ([[Benelux Customs Union]] in 1948), and an economic union with Belgium and the Netherlands, the so-called [[BeNeLux]].

Between 1945 and 2005, the economic structure of Luxembourg changed significantly. The crisis of the metallurgy sector, which began in the mid-1970s and lasted till the late 1980s, nearly pushed the country into economic recession, given the monolithic dominance of that sector. The Tripartite Coordination Committee, consisting of members of the government, management representatives, and trade union leaders, succeeded in preventing major social unrest during those years, thus creating the myth of a “Luxembourg model” characterized by social peace. Although in the early years of the 21st century Luxembourg enjoyed one of the highest GNP per capita in the world, this was mainly due to the strength of its financial sector, which gained importance at the end of the 1960s. Thirty-five years later, one-third of the tax proceeds originated from that sector. The harmonization of the tax system across Europe could, however, seriously undermine the financial situation of the grand duchy.

Luxembourg has been one of the strongest advocates of the [[European Union]] in the tradition of [[Robert Schuman]]. In 1957, Luxembourg became one of the six founding countries of the [[European Economic Community]] (later the European Union) and in 1999 it joined the [[euro]] currency area.

Encouraged by the contacts established with the Dutch and Belgian governments in exile, Luxembourg pursued a policy of presence in international organizations. It was one of the six founding members of the European Coal and Steel Community (ECSC) in 1952 and of the European Economic Community (EEC) in 1957. In the context of the Cold War, Luxembourg clearly opted for the West by joining the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) in 1949, thus renouncing its traditional neutrality, which had determined its international policy since the founding of the state. Engagement in European construction was rarely questioned subsequently, either by politicians or by the greater population. Despite its small proportions, Luxembourg often played an intermediary role between larger countries. This role of mediator, especially between the two large and often bellicose nations of Germany and France, was considered one of the main characteristics of national identity, allowing the Luxembourger not to have to choose between one of these two neighbours. The country also hosted a large number of European institutions such as the European Court of Justice. Luxembourg’s small size  no longer seemed to be a challenge to the existence of the country, and the creation of the Banque Centrale du Luxembourg (1998) and of the University of Luxembourg (2003) was evidence of the continuing desire to become a “real” nation. The decision in 1985 to declare Lëtzebuergesch (Luxembourgian) the national language was also a step in the affirmation of the country’s independence. In fact, the linguistic situation in Luxembourg was characterized by trilinguilism: Lëtzebuergesch was the spoken vernacular language, German the written language, in which Luxembourgers were most fluent, and French the language of official letters and law.

In 1985, the country became victim to a mysterious bombing spree, which was targeted mostly at electrical masts and other installations.

In 1995 Luxembourg provided the President of the [[European Commission]], former Prime Minister [[Jacques Santer]] who later had to resign over corruption accusations against other commission members.

The current Prime Minister, [[Jean-Claude Juncker]] follows this European tradition. On 10 September 2004, Mr Juncker became the semi-permanent President of the group of finance ministers from the 12 countries that share the euro, a role dubbed &quot;Mr Euro&quot;.

The present sovereign is Grand Duke [[Henri, Grand Duke of Luxembourg|Henri]]. Henri's father, [[Jean, Grand Duke of Luxembourg|Jean]], succeeded his mother, Charlotte, on 12 November 1964. Jean's eldest son, Prince Henri, was appointed &quot;Lieutenant Représentant&quot; (Hereditary Grand Duke) on 4 March 1998. On 24 December 1999, Prime Minister Juncker announced Grand Duke Jean's decision to abdicate the throne on 7 October 2000, in favour of Prince Henri who assumed the title and constitutional duties of Grand Duke.

On 10 July 2005, after threats of resignation by Prime Minister Juncker, the proposed European Constitution was approved by 56.52% of voters.

==See also==
* [[County, Duchy and Grand Duchy of _Luxembourg#County (963–1353)|County of Luxenbourg]]
* [[History of Belgium]]
* [[History of Europe]]
* [[History of European Union]]
* [[History of France]]
* [[History of Germany]]
* [[History of the Netherlands]]
* [[Luxembourg]]
* [[List of monarchs of Luxembourg]]
* [[List of Prime Ministers of Luxembourg]]
* [[Politics of Luxembourg]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}
==Further reading==
*Arblaster, Paul. ''A History of the Low Countries'' (Palgrave Essential Histories) (2005)
*  Blom, J.C.H. ''History of the Low Countries'' (2006)
* de Vries, Johan. &quot;Benelux, 1920-1970,&quot; in C. M. Cipolla, ed. ''The Fontana Economic History of Europe: Contemporary Economics Part One'' (1976) pp 1-71
* Kossmann, E. H. ''The Low Countries 1780–1940'' (1978)

==External links==
{{commons category|History of Luxembourg}}
* [http://www.igd-leo.lu/igd-leo/emigration/emigrationus.html Luxembourg emigration in the 19th century] - Offers reasons why people left Luxembourg in the 19th century.
* [http://eudocs.lib.byu.edu/index.php/History_of_Luxembourg:_Primary_Documents History of Luxembourg: Primary Documents]
* [http://www.historyofnations.net/europe/luxembourg.html History of Luxembourg] – History of Luxembourg from 53 BC to the present.
* [http://www.hoeckmann.de/deutschland/luxemburgkarte.htm Historical Map of Luxembourg 1789]
* [http://www.nat-military-museum.lu National Museum of Military History]

{{History of Europe}}
{{European history by country}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Luxembourg}}
[[Category:History of Luxembourg| ]]

{{Link GA|no}}

[[bg:История на Люксембург]]
[[cs:Dějiny Lucemburska]]
[[de:Geschichte Luxemburgs]]
[[es:Historia de Luxemburgo]]
[[fr:Histoire du Luxembourg]]
[[gl:Historia de Luxemburgo]]
[[hr:Povijest Luksemburga]]
[[io:Historio di Luxemburgia]]
[[it:Storia del Lussemburgo]]
[[he:היסטוריה של לוקסמבורג]]
[[mk:Историја на Луксембург]]
[[nl:Geschiedenis van Luxemburg]]
[[ja:ルクセンブルクの歴史]]
[[no:Luxembourgs historie]]
[[pl:Historia Luksemburga]]
[[pt:História de Luxemburgo]]
[[ru:История Люксембурга]]
[[tr:Lüksemburg tarihi]]
[[uk:Історія Люксембургу]]
[[zh:卢森堡历史]]</text>
      <sha1>0zfmr9xvnqorw76diivpeoxqn40ou95</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
