<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of medicine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14194</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522199422</id>
      <parentid>522199266</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T16:54:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjensen</username>
        <id>313197</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Renaissance to Early Modern period */ add cite</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="65801">All human societies have [[medicine|medical]] beliefs that provide explanations for [[childbirth|birth]], [[death]], and [[disease]]. Throughout history, illness has been attributed to [[witchcraft]], [[demons]], [[astrology|astral influence]], or the will of the [[deity|gods]]. These ideas still retain some power, with [[faith healing]] and [[shrine]]s still used in some places, although the rise of scientific medicine over the past millennium has altered or replaced mysticism in most cases.

The ancient Egyptians had a [[Ancient Egyptian medicine|system of medicine]] that was very advanced for its time and influenced later medical traditions. The Egyptians and Babylonians both introduced the concepts of [[diagnosis]], [[prognosis]], and [[medical examination]]. The [[Hippocratic Oath]], still taken by doctors today, was written in Greece in the 5th century BCE. In the medieval era, surgical practices inherited from the ancient masters were improved and then systematized in [[Rogerius (physician)|Rogerius's]] ''The Practice of Surgery''. During the Renaissance, understanding of anatomy improved, and the invention of the microscope would later lead to the [[germ theory of disease]]. These advancements, along with developments in chemistry, genetics, and lab technology (such as the [[x-ray]]) led to [[modern medicine]].

[[Image:HippocraticOath.jpg|thumb|The ''[[Hippocratic Corpus]]'', is a collection of around seventy early medical works from [[ancient Greece]] strongly associated with the ancient Greek physician [[Hippocrates]] and his teachings.]]

== Prehistoric medicine ==
{{Further|Prehistoric medicine}}
Although there is no record to establish when plants were first used for medicinal purposes ([[herbalist|herbalism]]), the use of plants as healing agents is an ancient practice. Over time through emulation of the behavior of fauna a medicinal knowledge base developed and was passed between generations. As tribal culture specialized specific castes, [[Shaman]]s and [[apothecary|apothecaries]] performed the 'niche occupation' of healing.

== Antiquity ==

=== Egypt ===
{{Further|Ancient Egyptian medicine}}
[[File:Hieroglyphic-brain.jpg|thumb|right|240px|The [[Edwin Smith Surgical Papyrus]], written in the 17th century BC, contains the earliest recorded reference to the brain]]

[[Ancient Egypt]] developed a large, varied and fruitful medical tradition. [[Herodotus]] described the Egyptians as &quot;the healthiest of all men, next to the Libyans&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | title = [[Histories (Herodotus)|The Histories]] | author = [[Herodotus]] | chapter = Chapter 77, Book II | language = [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0126&amp;layout=&amp;loc=2.77.3 English translation]}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to the dry climate and the notable [[public health system]] that they possessed. According to him, &quot;[t]he practice of medicine is so specialized among them that each physician is a healer of one disease and no more.&quot;  Although Egyptian medicine, to a good extent, dealt with the supernatural,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Nunn, John F. | title = Ancient Egyptian Medicine | publisher = University of Oklahoma Press | year = 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; it eventually developed a practical use in the fields of anatomy, public health, and clinical diagnostics.

Medical information in the [[Edwin Smith Papyrus]]&lt;ref&gt;J. H. Breasted, ''The Edwin Smith Surgical Papyrus'', University of Chicago Press, 1930&lt;/ref&gt; may date to a time as early as 3000&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref&gt;James Henry Breasted, &quot;The Edwin Smith Surgical Papyrus: published in facsimile and hieroglyphic transliteration with translation and commentary in two volumes&quot;. (University of Chicago Oriental Institute publications, v. 3-4. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1991),9.&lt;/ref&gt;  The earliest known [[surgery]] was performed in [[History of ancient Egypt|Egypt]] around 2750&amp;nbsp;BC. [[Imhotep]] in the [[Third dynasty of Egypt|3rd dynasty]] is sometimes credited with being the founder of ancient Egyptian medicine and with being the original author of the ''Edwin Smith Papyrus'', detailing cures, ailments and [[anatomical]] observations. The ''Edwin Smith Papyrus'' is regarded as a copy of several earlier works and was written c. 1600&amp;nbsp;BC. It is an ancient textbook on surgery almost completely devoid of magical thinking and describes in exquisite detail the ''examination, diagnosis, treatment,'' and ''prognosis'' of numerous ailments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article?tocId=9032043&amp;query=Edwin%20Smith%20papyrus&amp;ct= |title=Edwin Smith papyrus - Britannica Online Encyclopedia |publisher=Britannica.com |date= |accessdate=2012-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Conversely, the [[Ebers papyrus]]&lt;ref&gt;P. W. Bryan, ''The Papyrus Ebers'', Geoffrey Bles: London, 1930&lt;/ref&gt; (c.&amp;nbsp;[[16th century BC|1550&amp;nbsp;BC]]) is full of incantations and foul applications meant to turn away disease-causing demons, and other superstition. The Ebers papyrus also provides our earliest possible documentation of ancient awareness of [[tumor]]s, but ancient medical terminology being badly understood, ''cases Ebers 546 and 547''{{Vague|date=November 2009}} for instance may refer to simple swellings.

The  [[Kahun Gynaecological Papyrus]]&lt;ref&gt;Griffith, F. Ll. ''The Petrie Papyri: Hieratic Papyri from Kahun and Gurob''&lt;/ref&gt; treats women's complaints, including problems with conception. Thirty four cases detailing diagnosis and treatment survive, some of them fragmentarily.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reshafim.org.il/ad/egypt/timelines/topics/kahunpapyrus.htm |title=The Kahun Gynaecological Papyrus |publisher=Reshafim.org.il |date= |accessdate=2012-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dating to 1800&amp;nbsp;BC, it is the oldest surviving medical text of any kind.

Medical institutions, referred to as ''Houses of Life'' are known to have been established in ancient Egypt as early as the [[First dynasty of Egypt|1st Dynasty]].{{fact|date=November 2012}}

The earliest known physician is also credited to [[History of ancient Egypt|ancient Egypt]]: [[Hesy-Ra]], “Chief of Dentists and Physicians” for King [[Djoser]] in the 27th century&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref&gt;[[Helaine Selin]], Hugh Shapiro, eds., ''Medicine Across Cultures: History and Practice of Medicine in Non-Western Cultures,'' Springer 2003, p.35&lt;/ref&gt; Also, the earliest known woman physician, [[Peseshet]], practiced in [[Ancient Egypt]] at the time of the [[Fourth dynasty of Egypt|4th dynasty]]. Her title was “Lady Overseer of the Lady Physicians.” In addition to her supervisory role, Peseshet trained midwives at an ancient Egyptian medical school in [[Sais]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

=== Mesopotamia and Levant ===
{{Further|Babylonian Medicine}}

The oldest Babylonian texts on [[medicine]] date back to the [[Old Babylonian]] period in the first half of the [[2nd millennium BC|2nd&amp;nbsp;millennium&amp;nbsp;BC]]. The most extensive Babylonian medical text, however, is the ''Diagnostic Handbook'' written by the ''ummânū'', or chief scholar, [[Esagil-kin-apli]] of [[Borsippa]],&lt;ref name=Stol-99/&gt; during the reign of the Babylonian king [[Adad-apla-iddina]] (1069-1046&amp;nbsp;BC).&lt;ref&gt;Marten Stol (1993), ''Epilepsy in Babylonia'', p. 55, [[Brill Publishers]], ISBN 90-72371-63-1.&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with contemporary [[ancient Egyptian medicine]], the Babylonians introduced the concepts of [[medical diagnosis|diagnosis]], [[prognosis]], [[physical examination]], and [[medical prescription]]s. In addition, the ''Diagnostic Handbook'' introduced the methods of [[therapy]] and [[etiology]] and the use of [[empiricism]], [[logic]] and [[rationality]] in diagnosis, prognosis and therapy. The text contains a list of medical [[symptom]]s and often detailed empirical [[observation]]s along with logical rules used in combining observed symptoms on the body of a [[patient]] with its diagnosis and prognosis.&lt;ref&gt;H. F. J. Horstmanshoff, Marten Stol, Cornelis Tilburg (2004), ''Magic and Rationality in Ancient Near Eastern and Graeco-Roman Medicine'', p. 97-98, [[Brill Publishers]], ISBN 90-04-13666-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Diagnostic Handbook'' was based on a logical set of [[axiom]]s and assumptions, including the modern view that through the examination and [[inspection]] of the symptoms of a patient, it is possible to determine the patient's [[disease]], its aetiology and future development, and the chances of the patient's recovery. The symptoms and diseases of a patient were treated through therapeutic means such as [[bandage]]s, [[Cream (pharmaceutical)|creams]] and [[pill (pharmacy)|pills]].&lt;ref name=Stol-99&gt;H. F. J. Horstmanshoff, Marten Stol, Cornelis Tilburg (2004), ''Magic and Rationality in Ancient Near Eastern and Graeco-Roman Medicine'', p. 99, [[Brill Publishers]], ISBN 90-04-13666-5.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of our knowledge of ancient [[Hebrew medicine]] during the [[1st millennium BC|1st&amp;nbsp;millennium&amp;nbsp;BC]] comes from the [[Torah]], i.e.&amp;nbsp;the Five Books of [[Moses]], which contain various health related laws and rituals, such as isolating infected people (Leviticus 13:45-46), washing after handling a dead body (Numbers 19:11-19) and burying excrement away from camp (Deuteronomy 23:12-13). While the observance of these statutes would have and do lead to several health benefits, Jewish belief commands that these rituals and prohibitions be kept purely to fulfill the will of God with no ulterior motive. Max Neuberger, writing in his &quot;History of Medicine&quot; says
:''&quot;The commands concern prophylaxis and suppression of epidemics, suppression of venereal disease and prostitution, care of the skin, baths, food, housing and clothing, regulation of labour, sexual life, discipline of the people,&amp;nbsp; etc. Many of these commands, such as Sabbath rest, circumcision, laws concerning food (interdiction of blood and pork), measures concerning menstruating and lying-in women and those suffering from gonorrhea, isolation of [[lepers]], and hygiene of the camp, are, in view of the conditions of the climate, surprisingly rational.&quot;'' (Neuburger: History of Medicine, Oxford University Press, 1910, Vol.&amp;nbsp;I,&amp;nbsp;p.&amp;nbsp;38).

=== India ===
{{Main|Ayurveda|Unani}}

The [[Atharvaveda]], a sacred text of [[Hinduism]] dating from the [[Iron Age India|Early Iron Age]], is the first Indian text dealing with medicine, like the medicine of the Ancient Near East based on concepts of the [[exorcism]] of demons and [[magical thinking|magic]]. The Atharvaveda also contain  prescriptions of herbs for various ailments. The use of herbs to treat ailments would later form a large part of [[Ayurveda]].

In the first millennium BCE, there emerges in post-Vedic India the traditional medicine system known as [[Ayurveda]], meaning the &quot;complete knowledge for long life&quot;. Its two most famous texts belong to the schools of [[Charaka]], born c. 600 BCE, and [[Sushruta]], born 600 BCE. While these writings display some limited continuities with the earlier medical ideas known from the  [[Vedas]], historians{{Who|date=April 2010}} have been able to demonstrate direct historical connections between early Ayurveda and the early literature of the [[Shramana|Buddhists and Jains]].
The earliest foundations of Ayurveda were built on a synthesis of traditional herbal practices  together with a massive addition of theoretical conceptualizations, new [[nosology|nosologies]] and new therapies dating from about 400 BCE onwards, and coming out of the communities of thinkers who included the Buddha and others.&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth G. Zysk, ''Asceticism and Healing in Ancient India: Medicine in the Buddhist Monastery,'' Oxford University Press, rev. ed. (1998) ISBN 0-19-505956-5&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the compendium of [[Charaka]], the [[Charaka Samhita|Charakasamhitā]], health and disease are not predetermined and life may be prolonged by human effort. The compendium of [[Sushruta|Suśruta]], the [[Sushruta Samhita|Suśrutasamhitā]] defines the purpose of medicine to cure the diseases of the sick, protect the healthy, and to prolong life. Both these ancient compendia include details of the examination, diagnosis, treatment, and prognosis of numerous ailments.  The [[Sushruta Samhita|Suśrutasamhitā]] is notable for describing procedures on various forms of [[surgery]], including [[rhinoplasty]], the repair of torn ear lobes, perineal [[lithotomy]], cataract surgery, and several other excisions and other surgical procedures. Most remarkable is Sushruta's penchant for scientific classification:
His medical treatise consists of 184 chapters, 1,120 conditions are listed, including injuries and illnesses relating to ageing and mental illness. The Sushruta Samhita describe 125 surgical instrument, 300 surgical procedures and classifies human surgery in 8 categories &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ispub.com/ostia/index.php?xmlFilePath=journals/ijps/vol4n2/sushruta.xml |title=Sushruta: The first Plastic Surgeon in 600 B.C. |publisher=ISPUB |date= |accessdate=2012-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ayurvedic classics mention eight branches of medicine: kāyācikitsā ([[internal medicine]]), śalyacikitsā ([[surgery]] including [[Human anatomy|anatomy]]), śālākyacikitsā ([[Human eye|eye]], [[ear]], [[human nose|nose]], and [[throat]] diseases), kaumārabhṛtya ([[pediatrics]]), bhūtavidyā (spirit medicine), and agada tantra ([[toxicology]]), rasāyana
(science of rejuvenation), and vājīkaraṇa (aphrodisiacs, mainly for men).
Apart from learning these, the student of Āyurveda was expected to know ten arts that were indispensable in the preparation and application of his medicines: distillation, operative skills, cooking, horticulture, metallurgy, sugar manufacture, pharmacy, analysis and separation of minerals, compounding of metals, and preparation of [[alkalis]].  The teaching of various subjects was done during the instruction of relevant clinical subjects.  For example, teaching of anatomy was a part of the teaching of surgery, [[embryology]] was a part of training in pediatrics and [[obstetrics]], and the knowledge of [[physiology]] and [[pathology]] was interwoven in the teaching of all the clinical disciplines.
The normal length of the student's training appears to have been seven years.  But the physician was to continue to learn.&lt;ref&gt;Dominik Wujastyk, ed., ''The Roots of Ayurveda,'' Penguin (2003) ISBN 0-14-044824-1&lt;/ref&gt;

As an alternative form of medicine in India, [[Unani medicine]] got deep roots and royal patronage during medieval times. It progressed during Indian [[sultanate]] and [[Mughal Empire|mughal]] periods. Unani medicine is very close to Ayurveda. Both are based on theory of the presence of the elements (in Unani, they are considered to be fire, water, earth and air) in the human body. According to followers of Unani medicine, these elements are present in different fluids and their balance leads to health and their imbalance leads to illness.&lt;ref&gt;Arab Medicine during the Ages by Hakim Syed Zillur Rahman, Studies in History of Medicine and Science, IHMMR, New Delhi, Vol. XIV, No. 1-2, 1996, p. 1-39&lt;/ref&gt;

=== China ===
{{Main|Medicine in China|Traditional Chinese medicine}}

China also developed a large body of traditional medicine. Much of the philosophy of [[traditional Chinese medicine]] derived from empirical observations of disease and illness by [[Taoist]] physicians and reflects the classical Chinese belief that individual human experiences express causative principles effective in the environment at all scales. These causative principles, whether material, essential, or mystical, correlate as the expression of the natural order of the universe.

The foundational text of Chinese medicine is the [[Huangdi Neijing|Huangdi neijing]], or ''Yellow Emperor's Inner Canon'', which is composed of two books: the [[Suwen]] 素問 (&quot;Basic Questions&quot;) and the [[Lingshu]] 靈樞 (&quot;Divine Pivot&quot;). Although the ''Neijing'' has long been attributed to the mythical [[Yellow Emperor]] (twenty-7th century BC), Chinese scholars started doubting this attribution as early as the 11th century and now usually date the ''Neijing'' to the late [[Warring States Period|Warring States period]] (5th century-221 BC).&lt;ref&gt;Unschuld (2003), 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Because the medical [[Mawangdui Silk Texts|&quot;silk manuscripts&quot;]] dating from around 200 BC that were excavated in the 1970s from the tomb of a [[Han Dynasty|Han-dynasty]] noble in [[Mawangdui]] are undoubtedly ancestors of the received ''Neijing'', scholars like [[Nathan Sivin]] now argue that the ''Neijing'' was first compiled in the 1st century BC.&lt;ref&gt;Sivin (1993).&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Han dynasty, [[Zhang Zhongjing]], who was mayor of [[Changsha]] near the end of the 2nd century AD, wrote a [[Shang Han Lun|''Treatise on Cold Damage'']], which contains the earliest known reference to the ''[[Neijing Suwen]]''. The [[Jin Dynasty (265–420)|Jin Dynasty]] practitioner and advocate of [[acupuncture]] and [[moxibustion]], [[Huangfu Mi]] (215-282), also quotes the [[Yellow Emperor]] in his ''Jiayi jing'', c. 265.  During the [[Tang Dynasty]], Wang Bing claimed to have located a copy of the originals of the ''Suwen'', which he expanded and edited substantially.  This work was revisited by an imperial commission during the 11th century, and the result is our best extant representation of the foundational roots of traditional Chinese medicine.

[[Traditional Chinese Medicine]] that is based on the use of herbal medicine, acupuncture, massage and other forms of therapy has been practiced in China for thousands of years.  However, Western Medicine was introduced to China in the 19th Century, mainly by medical missionaries sent from various Christian mission organizations, such as the [[London Missionary Society]] (Britain), the [[Methodism|Methodist]] Church (Britain) and the [[Presbyterian Church in the United States|Presbyterian Church (USA)]].  [[Benjamin Hobson]] (1816-1873), a medical missionary sent by the [[London Missionary Society]] in 1839, set up a highly successful Wai Ai Clinic (惠愛醫館) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.ifeng.com/article/46027.html |title=回眸：当年传教士进羊城_MW悦读室之岭南话廊_凤凰网博报- 博采众家之言 报闻公民心声-凤凰网 |publisher=Blog.ifeng.com |date= |accessdate=2012-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mall.cnki.net/magazine/Article/GDSI199901009.htm |title=合信的《全体新论》与广东士林-《广东史志》1999年01期-中国知网 |publisher=Mall.cnki.net |date=2012-02-03 |accessdate=2012-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Guangzhou, China. The [[Hong Kong College of Medicine for Chinese]] (香港華人西醫書院) was founded in 1887 by the [[London Missionary Society]], with its first graduate (in 1892) being [[Sun Yat-sen]] (孫中山).  Sun later led the [[Chinese Revolution (1911)]], which changed China from an empire to a republic. The [[Hong Kong College of Medicine for Chinese]] was the forerunner of the School of Medicine of the [[University of Hong Kong]], which started in 1911.

Due to the social custom that men and women should not be near to one another, the women of China were reluctant to be treated by male doctors of Western Medicine.  This resulted in a tremendous need for female doctors of Western Medicine in China.  Thus, female medical missionary Dr. Mary H. Fulton (1854-1927) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Inasmuch |url=http://www.amazon.com/Inasmuch-Mary-H-Fulton/dp/1140341804 |title=Inasmuch: Mary H. Fulton, The United Study of Forring: 9781140341802: Amazon.com: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date=2010-04-06 |accessdate=2012-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; was sent by the Foreign Missions Board of the Presbyterian Church (USA) to found the first medical college for women in China.  Known as the Hackett Medical College for Women (夏葛女子醫學院),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hkbu.edu.hk/~libimage/theses/abstracts/b15564174a.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cqvip.com/qk/83891A/200203/6479902.html |title=中国近代第一所女子医学院－－夏葛医学院-【维普网】-仓储式在线作品出版平台-www.cqvip.com |publisher=Cqvip.com |date= |accessdate=2012-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; this College was located in Guangzhou, China, and was enabled by a large donation from Mr. Edward A.K. Hackett (1851-1916) of Indiana, USA.  The College was dedicated in 1902 and offered a four-year curriculum.  By 1915, there were more than 60 students, mostly in residence. Most students became Christians, due to the influence of Dr. Fulton.   The College was officially recognized, with its diplomas marked with the official stamp of the Guangdong provincial government.  The College was aimed at the spreading of Christianity and modern medicine and the elevation of Chinese women's social status.  The David Gregg Hospital for Women and Children (also known as Yuji Hospital 柔濟醫院) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books/about/A_crusade_of_compassion_for_the_healing.html?id=UpkNAAAAYAAJ |title=A crusade of compassion for the healing of the nations: a study of medical ... - Belle Jane Allen, Caroline Atwater Mason - Google Boeken |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.qq.com/a/20100411/001143.htm |title=柔济医院的实验室_新闻_腾讯网 |publisher=News.qq.com |date=2012-01-17 |accessdate=2012-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; was affiliated with this College.   The graduates of this College included CHAU Lee-sun (周理信, 1890-1979) and WONG Yuen-hing (黃婉卿), both of whom graduated in the late 1910s &lt;ref&gt;Rebecca Chan Chung, [[Deborah Chung]] and Cecilia Ng Wong, &quot;Piloted to Serve&quot;, 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.facebook.com/PilotedToServe |title=Piloted to Serve |publisher=Facebook |date= |accessdate=2012-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and then practiced medicine in the hospitals in Guangdong province.

=== Greek and Roman medicine ===
{{Main|Medicine in ancient Greece|Medicine in ancient Rome|Medical community of ancient Rome|Byzantine medicine}}
The first known Greek medical school opened in [[Cnidus]] in 700 BC. [[Alcmaeon]], author of the first anatomical work, worked at this school, and it was here that the practice of observing patients was established.  As was the case elsewhere, the ancient Greeks developed a humoral medicine system where treatment sought to restore the balance of [[Classical element|humours]] within the body.

Temples dedicated to the healer-god [[Asclepius]], known as ''[[Asclepeion|Asclepieia]]'' ({{lang-grc|Ἀσκληπιεῖα}}, sing. {{lang|grc|Ἀσκληπιεῖον}}, '''Asclepieion''), functioned as centers of medical advice, prognosis, and healing.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Risse |first=G. B. |title=Mending bodies, saving souls: a history of hospitals |publisher= Oxford University Press |year=1990 |page= 56 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=htLTvdz5HDEC&amp;pg=PA56&amp;dq=History+of+Hospital%2BAsclepieion&amp;lr=lang_en&amp;as_brr=0&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=History%20of%20Hospital%2BAsclepieion&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; At these shrines, patients would enter a dream-like state of induced sleep known as ''enkoimesis'' ({{lang|grc|ἐγκοίμησις}}) not unlike anesthesia, in which they either received guidance from the deity [[Sleep temple|in a dream]] or were cured by surgery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Askitopoulou, H. 2002 p.11-17&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Askitopoulou, H., Konsolaki, E., Ramoutsaki, I., Anastassaki, E. |title=Surgical cures by sleep induction as the Asclepieion of Epidaurus. |work=The history of anesthesia: proceedings of the Fifth International Symposium, by José Carlos Diz, Avelino Franco, Douglas R. Bacon, J. Rupreht, Julián Alvarez. Elsevier Science B.V., International Congress Series 1242 |year=2002 |pages=11–17 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=TM-8NIDPowoC&amp;pg=PA11&amp;dq=History+of+Hospital%2BAsclepieion&amp;lr=lang_en&amp;as_brr=0&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=History%20of%20Hospital%2BAsclepieion&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asclepeia provided carefully controlled spaces conducive to healing and fulfilled several of the requirements of institutions created for healing.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;  In the Asclepieion of [[Epidaurus]], three large marble boards dated to 350 BC preserve the names, case histories, complaints, and cures of about 70 patients who came to the temple with a problem and shed it there.  Some of the surgical cures listed, such as the opening of an abdominal abscess or the removal of traumatic foreign material, are realistic enough to have taken place, but with the patient in a state of enkoimesis induced with the help of soporific substances such as opium.&lt;ref name=&quot;Askitopoulou, H. 2002 p.11-17&quot;/&gt;

A towering figure in the history of medicine was the physician [[Hippocrates]] of [[Kos]] (c. 460 – c. 370 BC), considered the &quot;father of modern medicine.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.medicinaantiqua.org.uk/sa_hippint.html Hippocrates: The &quot;Greek Miracle&quot; in Medicine]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.geocities.com/trepanationz/hippocrates/ |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080228084033/http://www.geocities.com/trepanationz/hippocrates/ |archivedate=2008-02-28 |title=The Father of Modern Medicine: Hippocrates |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2008-02-28 |accessdate=2012-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Hippocratic Corpus]] is a collection of around seventy early medical works from ancient Greece strongly associated with Hippocrates and his students.  Most famously, Hippocrates invented the [[Hippocratic Oath]] for physicians, which is still relevant and in use today.

[[Hippocrates]] and his followers were first to describe many diseases and medical conditions. He is given credit for the first description of [[Nail clubbing|clubbing]] of the fingers, an important diagnostic sign in chronic suppurative lung disease, [[lung cancer]] and [[Cyanotic heart defect|cyanotic heart disease]]. For this reason, clubbed fingers are sometimes referred to as &quot;Hippocratic fingers&quot;.&lt;ref name=schwartz&gt;{{Harvnb|Schwartz|Richards|Goyal|2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hippocrates was also the first physician to describe [[Hippocratic face]] in ''Prognosis''. [[Shakespeare]] famously alludes to this description when writing of [[Falstaff]]'s death in Act II, Scene iii. of ''[[Henry V (play)|Henry V]]''.&lt;ref name=sing40&gt;{{Harvnb|Singer|Underwood|1962|p=40}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=margotta70&gt;{{Harvnb|Margotta|1968|p=70}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hippocrates began to categorize illnesses as [[Acute (medical)|acute]], [[Chronic (medicine)|chronic]], [[Endemic (epidemiology)|endemic]] and [[epidemic]], and use terms such as, &quot;exacerbation, [[relapse]], resolution, crisis, [[paroxysm]], peak, and [[convalescence]].&quot;&lt;ref name=garrison97&gt;{{Harvnb|Garrison|1966|p=97}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mart90&gt;{{Harvnb|Martí-Ibáñez|1961|p=90}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another of Hippocrates's major contributions may be found in his descriptions of the symptomatology, physical findings, surgical treatment and prognosis of [[Empyema|thoracic empyema]], i.e. [[suppuration]] of the lining of the chest cavity. His teachings remain relevant to present-day students of [[Pulmonology|pulmonary medicine]] and surgery.&lt;ref name = major/&gt;{{Page needed|date=January 2011}} Hippocrates was the first documented [[Cardiothoracic Surgery|chest surgeon]] and his findings are still valid.&lt;ref name=major&gt;{{Harvnb|Major|1965}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=January 2011}}[[Image:Kos Asklepeion.jpg|thumb|right|300px|View of the ''Askleipion'' of [[Kos]], the best preserved instance of an Asklepieion.]]
[[File:Heraklas Plinthios Brokhos Jaw Sling.jpg|thumb|right|The ''Plinthios Brokhos'' as described by Greek physician [[Heraklas]], a sling for binding a [[Bone fracture|fractured]] [[Human mandible|jaw]].  These writings were preserved in one of [[Oribasius]]' collections.&lt;ref name=&quot;cldquipu&quot;&gt;{{cite book  | last = Day  | first = Cyrus L.  | title = Quipus and Witches' Knots  | publisher = University of Kansas Press  | year = 1967  | location = Lawrence, Kansas  | pages = 86–89, 124–126 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

[[Herophilos|Herophilus of Chalcedon]], working at the medical school of [[Alexandria]] placed intelligence in the brain, and connected the nervous system to motion and sensation. Herophilus also distinguished between [[vein]]s and [[artery|arteries]], noting that the latter [[pulse]] while the former do not.  He and his contemporary, [[Erasistratus|Erasistratus of Chios]], researched the role of veins and [[nerve]]s, mapping their courses across the body.  Erasistratus connected the increased complexity of the surface of the human brain compared to other animals to its superior [[intelligence]]. He sometimes employed [[experiment]]s to further his research, at one time repeatedly weighing a caged bird, and noting its weight loss between feeding times.  In [[Erasistratus]]' physiology, air enters the body, is then drawn by the lungs into the heart, where it is transformed into vital spirit, and is then pumped by the arteries throughout the body. Some of this vital spirit reaches the [[Human brain|brain]], where it is transformed into animal spirit, which is then distributed by the nerves.&lt;ref&gt;Mason, ''A History of the Sciences'', p 57&lt;/ref&gt;

The Greek [[Galen]] was one of the greatest surgeons of the ancient world and performed many audacious operations—including brain and eye [[surgery|surgeries]]— that were not tried again for almost two millennia. Later, in medieval Europe, Galen's writings on anatomy became the mainstay of the medieval physician's university curriculum along; but they suffered greatly from stasis and intellectual stagnation. In the 1530s, however, Belgian anatomist and physician [[Andreas Vesalius]] took on a project to translate many of Galen's Greek texts into Latin.  Vesalius's most famous work, ''[[De humani corporis fabrica]]'', was greatly influenced by Galenic writing and form.&lt;ref&gt;Dear, Peter. ''Revolutionizing the Sciences: European Knowledge and Its Ambitions, 1500-1700.'' Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press (2001), 37-39.&lt;/ref&gt; The works of [[Galen]] and [[Avicenna]], especially ''The Canon of Medicine'' which incorporated the teachings of both, were translated into [[Latin]], and the ''Canon'' remained the most authoritative text on anatomy in European medical education until the 16th century.

The [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] invented numerous [[surgical instruments]], including the first instruments unique to women,&lt;ref name=Rome&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/library/wdc-lib/historical/artifacts/roman_surgical/ |title=Surgical Instruments from Ancient Rome |publisher=Healthsystem.virginia.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the surgical uses of [[forceps]], [[scalpel]]s, [[Cautery#History|cautery]], [[Scissors|cross-bladed scissors]], the [[surgical needle]], the [[Sound (medical instrument)|sound]], and [[Speculum (medical)|speculas]].&lt;ref name=Surgery&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7137224.stm Roman period surgery set on show], [[BBC]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Chirurgia&gt;[[William Alexander Greenhill]], [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Chirurgia.html Chirurgia]&lt;/ref&gt; Romans also performed [[cataract surgery]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/7194352.stm The Romans carried out cataract ops], [[BBC]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Medieval medicine was an evolving mixture of the [[science|scientific]] and the spiritual like [[Unani]]. In the early [[Middle Ages]], following the fall of the [[Roman Empire]], standard medical knowledge was based chiefly upon surviving Greek and Roman texts, preserved in monasteries and elsewhere. Ideas about the origin and cure of [[disease]] were not, however, purely [[secular]], but were also based on a [[spirituality|spiritual]] world view, in which factors such as destiny, sin, and astral influences played as great a part as any physical cause.

[[Oribasius]] was the greatest [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] compiler of medical knowledge. Several of his works, along with many other [[Byzantine medicine|Byzantine physicians]], were translated into Latin, and eventually, during the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] and [[Age of Reason]], into English and French. The last great Byzantine Physician was [[John Actuarius]], who lived in the early 14th century in [[Constantinople]].

== Middle Ages ==

=== Hebrew medicine===
{{Expand section|date=April 2012}}
The [[Hebrew medicine|Hebrew contribution]] to the development of modern medicine started in the [[Byzantine Era]], with the physician [[Asaph the Jew]], and has since been tremendous.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/judaica/ejud_0002_0013_0_13493.html |title=Medicine |work=Encyclopaedia Judaica |year=2008 |first=Samuel |last=Vaisrub |first2=Michael |last2=A. Denman |first3=Yaakov |last3=Naparstek |first4=Dan |last4=Gilon |publisher=The Gale Group}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Islamic Middle Ages ===
{{Main|Medicine in medieval Islam|Ancient Iranian Medicine}}
{{Further|Bimaristan|Ophthalmology in medieval Islam|Unani}}
[[Image:Cheshm manuscript.jpg|right|thumb|An [[Arabic]] manuscript, dated 1200, titled ''Anatomy of the Eye'', authored by al-Mutadibih.]]

Persia's position at the crossroads of the East and the West frequently placed it in the midst of developments in both ancient Greek and Indian medicine. The first generation of Persian physicians trained at the [[Academy of Jundishapur]]. This evolved into the medieval Islamic [[Bimaristan]] hospitals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Micheau|first=Françoise|contribution=The Scientific Institutions in the Medieval Near East|pages=991–2|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}, in {{Harv|Morelon|Rashed|1996|pp=985–1007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Barrett&gt;Peter Barrett (2004), ''Science and Theology Since Copernicus: The Search for Understanding'', p. 18, [[Continuum International Publishing Group]], ISBN 0-567-08969-X.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Islamic Golden Age|Islamic civilization]] rose to primacy in medical science as Muslim [[physician]]s contributed significantly to the field of medicine, including [[anatomy]], [[ophthalmology]], [[pharmacology]], [[pharmacy]], [[physiology]], [[surgery]], and the [[pharmaceutical sciences]]. The Arabs were influenced by, and further developed Greek, Roman and Indian medical practices. [[Galen]], [[Hippocrates]], [[Sushruta]] and [[Charaka]] were pre-eminent authorities.&lt;ref name=Amber&gt;Amber Haque (2004), &quot;Psychology from Islamic Perspective: Contributions of Early Muslim Scholars and Challenges to Contemporary Muslim Psychologists&quot;, ''Journal of Religion and Health'' '''43''' (4): 357-377 [361]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify source|date=April 2011}} The translation of 129 works of ancient Greek physician [[Galen]] into [[Arabic language|Arabic]] by [[Hunayn ibn Ishaq]] and his assistants, and in particular Galen's insistence on a rational systematic approach to medicine, set the template for [[Islamic medicine]], which rapidly spread throughout the [[Abbasid Caliphate|Arab Empire]]. Muslim physicians set up some of the earliest dedicated [[hospital]]s, which later spread to Europe during the [[Crusade]]s, inspired by the hospitals in the Middle East.&lt;ref name=Sarton&gt;[[George Sarton]], ''Introduction to the History of Science''.&lt;br /&gt;([[cf.]] Dr. A. Zahoor and Dr. Z. Haq (1997), [http://www.cyberistan.org/islamic/Introl1.html Quotations From Famous Historians of Science], Cyberistan.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Al-Kindi]] wrote ''[[De Gradibus]]'', in which he demonstrated the application of mathematics to medicine, particularly in the field of pharmacology. This includes the development of a mathematical scale to quantify the strength of [[drug]]s, and a system that would allow a doctor to determine in advance the most critical days of a patient's illness.&lt;ref&gt;Felix Klein-Frank (2001), ''Al-Kindi'', in [[Oliver Leaman]] and [[Hossein Nasr]], ''History of Islamic Philosophy'', p. 172. [[Routledge]], London.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Abu al-Qasim al-Zahrawi]] (Abulcasis), who some have called the [[father of modern surgery]],&lt;ref&gt;A. Martin-Araguz, C. Bustamante-Martinez, Ajo V. Fernandez-Armayor, J. M. Moreno-Martinez (2002). &quot;Neuroscience in al-Andalus and its influence on medieval scholastic medicine&quot;, ''Revista de neurología'' '''34''' (9), p. 877-892.&lt;/ref&gt; wrote the ''Kitab [[al-Tasrif]]'' (1000), a 30-volume medical [[encyclopedia]] which was taught at Muslim and European [[medical school]]s until the 17th century. He used numerous [[surgical instruments]], including some that are unique to women.&lt;ref name=Rome/&gt;&lt;ref name=Saad&gt;Bashar Saad, Hassan Azaizeh, Omar Said (October 2005). &quot;[http://ecam.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/2/4/475 Tradition and Perspectives of Arab Herbal Medicine: A Review]&quot;, ''Evidence-based Complementary and Alternative Medicine'' '''2''' (4), p. 475-479 [476]. [[Oxford University Press]].&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Avicenna]], considered among the most influential medical scholars in history,&lt;ref name=Sarton/&gt; wrote ''[[The Canon of Medicine]]'' (1025) and ''[[The Book of Healing]]'' (1027), which remained standard textbooks in both Muslim and European [[University|universities]] until the 17th century. Avicenna's contributions include the distinction of [[mediastinitis]] from [[pleurisy]] and careful descriptions of [[human skin|skin]] troubles, [[sexually transmitted disease]]s, and [[Nervous system|nervous]] [[ailment]]s,&lt;ref name=Sarton/&gt; as well the use of [[ice]] to treat [[fever]]s, and the separation of [[medicine]] from [[pharmacology]], which was important to the development of the [[pharmaceutical sciences]].&lt;ref name=Saad/&gt;

In 1242 [[Ibn al-Nafis]] gave the first description of [[pulmonary circulation]] and [[coronary circulation]].&lt;ref&gt;Husain F. Nagamia (2003), &quot;Ibn al-Nafīs: A Biographical Sketch of the Discoverer of Pulmonary and Coronary Circulation&quot;, ''Journal of the International Society for the History of Islamic Medicine'' '''1''', p. 22–28.
&lt;/ref&gt; He also described the earliest concept of [[metabolism]],&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Abu Shadi Al-Roubi (1982), &quot;Ibn Al-Nafis as a philosopher&quot;, ''Symposium on Ibn al-Nafis'', Second International Conference on Islamic Medicine: Islamic Medical Organization, Kuwait ([[cf.]] [http://www.islamset.com/isc/nafis/drroubi.html Ibn al-Nafis As a Philosopher], ''Encyclopedia of Islamic World'').&lt;/ref&gt; and developed new systems of [[physiology]] to replace the [[Avicenna|Avicennian]] and [[Galen]]ic systems, while discrediting many of their erroneous theories on the [[humorism|four humours]], [[Pulse|pulsation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Nahyan A. G. Fancy |year=2006 |title=Pulmonary Transit and Bodily Resurrection: The Interaction of Medicine, Philosophy and Religion in the Works of Ibn al-Nafīs (died 1288) |pages= 3 &amp; 6 Electronic Theses and Dissertations |publisher=University of Notre Dame |url=http://etd.nd.edu/ETD-db/theses/available/etd-11292006-152615}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[bone]]s, [[muscle]]s, [[intestine]]s, [[Sensory system|sensory organs]], [[Bile|bilious]] [[Canal (anatomy)|canals]], [[esophagus]], [[stomach]], etc.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Sulaiman Oataya (1982), &quot;Ibn ul Nafis has dissected the human body&quot;, ''Symposium on Ibn al-Nafis'', Second International Conference on Islamic Medicine: Islamic Medical Organization, Kuwait ([[cf.]] [http://www.islamset.com/isc/nafis/index.html Ibn ul-Nafis has Dissected the Human Body], ''Encyclopedia of Islamic World'').&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Tashrih al-badan'' (''Anatomy of the body'') of [[Mansur ibn Ilyas]] (c. 1390) contained comprehensive diagrams of the body's structural, [[Nervous system|nervous]] and [[circulatory system]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hakim Syed Zillur Rahman]]. ''Tarikh llm Tashrih'' [An extensive Book in [[Urdu language|Urdu]] on History of anatomy] (1967), Tibbi Academy, [[Delhi]], Second revised edition 2009 (ISBN 978-81-906070-), [[Ibn Sina Academy of Medieval Medicine and Sciences]], [[Aligarh]]&lt;/ref&gt; Other medical innovations first introduced by Muslim physicians include the discovery of the [[immune system]], the use of [[animal testing]], and the combination of medicine with other [[science]]s (including [[agriculture]], [[botany]], [[chemistry]], and [[pharmacology]]),&lt;ref name=Saad/&gt; the first [[Pharmacy|drugstores]] in [[Baghdad]] (754), the distinction between medicine and pharmacy by the 12th century, and the discovery of at least 2,000 medicinal and [[chemical substance]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Information taken from the abstract of {{Cite journal | issn = 0350-199X | volume = 51 | issue = 1–2 | pages = 47–50 | last = Hadzović | first = S | title = [Pharmacy and the great contribution of Arab-Islamic science to its development]  (Article in Croatian) | journal = Medicinski arhiv | year = 1997 | pmid = 9324574 | ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Christian Middle Ages ===
{{Further|Medieval medicine}}
[[File:Physician setting a dislocated arm.jpg|thumb|250px|Physician setting a dislocated arm (1450)]]
[[Image:The Anatomy Lesson.jpg|right|thumb|250px|&quot;[[Anatomy Lesson of Dr. Nicolaes Tulp]]&quot; by [[Rembrandt van Rijn]], 1632.]]

In western Europe, with the collapse of Roman imperial authority, medicine became localised; folk-medicine supplemented what remained of the medical knowledge of antiquity. Medical knowledge was preserved and practised in many [[christian monasticism|monastic]] institutions, which often had a [[hospital]] attached. Organised professional medicine re-emerged, with the foundation of the medical college ([[Schola Medica Salernitana]]) of [[Salerno]] in Italy in the 11th century, which in co-operation with the monastery of [[Monte Cassino]], translated many [[Byzantine]] and Arabic works. In the 12th century universities were founded in Italy and elsewhere, which soon developed schools of medicine.

Gradually the reliance on the masters of the ancient world was augmented by the results of individual observation and experience. Surgical practice improved greatly during the medieval period. [[Rogerius (physician)|Rogerius Salernitanus]] composed his ''Chirurgia,'' which became the foundation for modern Western surgical manuals up to the modern time.

== Renaissance to Early Modern period ==
With the Renaissance came an increase in experimental investigation, principally in the field of dissection and body examination, thus advancing our knowledge of human anatomy.&lt;ref&gt;Nancy G. Siraisi,  &quot; Medicine, 1450–1620, and the History of Science,&quot; ''Isis'' (2012) 103#3 pp 491-514  DOI: 10.1086/667970&lt;/ref&gt; The development of modern neurology began in the 16th century with [[Andreas Vesalius|Vesalius]], who described the anatomy of the brain and other organs; he had little knowledge of the brain's function, thinking that it resided mainly in the ventricles. Over his lifetime he corrected over 200 of [[Galen]]'s mistakes. Understanding of medical sciences and diagnosis improved, but with little direct benefit to health care. Few effective drugs existed, beyond [[opium]] and [[quinine]]. Folklore cures and potentially poisonous metal-based compounds were popular treatments.
Independently from [[Ibn al-Nafis]], [[Michael Servetus]] rediscovered the [[pulmonary circulation]], but this discovery did not reach the public cause it was written down for the first time in the &quot;Manuscript of Paris&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://michaelservetusresearch.com/ENGLISH/works.html Michael Servetus Research] Website with a graphical study on the Manuscript of Paris by Servetus&lt;/ref&gt; in 1546, and later published in the theological work which he paid with his life in 1553. Later this was perfected by [[Renaldus Columbus]] and [[Andrea Cesalpino]]. Later [[William Harvey]] provided a refined and complete description of the [[circulatory system]]. The most useful tomes in medicine used both by students and expert physicians were [[Materia Medica]] and [[Pharmacopoeia]].

== 19th century: Rise of modern medicine ==
The practice of medicine changed in the face of rapid advances in science, as well as new approaches by physicians. Hospital doctors began much more systematic analysis of patients' symptoms in diagnosis.&lt;ref&gt;Mary Fissell, &quot;The Disappearance of the Patient's Narrative and the Invention of Hospital Medicine,&quot; in ''British Medicine in an Age of Reform'' ed. by Roger French and Andrew Wear, (1991).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Technical advances===
Among the more powerful new techniques were anaesthesia, and the development of both antiseptic and aseptic operating theatres.&lt;ref&gt;Guenter B. Risse, ''Mending Bodies, Saving Souls: A History of Hospitals'' (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

Actual cures were developed for certain endemic infectious diseases. However the decline in many of the most lethal diseases was more due to improvements in public health and nutrition than to medicine. It was not until the 20th century that the application of the [[scientific method]] to medical research began to produce multiple important developments in medicine, with great advances in [[pharmacology]] and surgery.

Medicine was revolutionized in the 19th century and beyond by advances in chemistry and laboratory techniques and equipment, old ideas of infectious disease [[epidemiology]] were replaced with [[bacteriology]] and [[virology]].
[[Bacteria]] and [[microorganisms]] were first observed with a [[microscope]] by [[Antonie van Leeuwenhoek]] in 1676, initiating the scientific field [[microbiology]].&lt;ref name=Brock&gt;{{cite book | author = Madigan M, Martinko J (editors) | title = Brock Biology of Microorganisms | edition = 11th | publisher = Prentice Hall | year = 2006 | isbn = 0-13-144329-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ignaz Semmelweis]] (1818–1865) in 1847 dramatically reduced the death rate of new mothers from [[childbed fever]] by the simple expedient of requiring physicians to [[hand washing|clean their hands]] before attending to women in [[childbirth]]. His discovery pre-dated the [[germ theory of disease]]. However, his discoveries were not appreciated by his contemporaries and came into general use only with discoveries of British surgeon [[Joseph Lister, 1st Baron Lister|Joseph Lister]], who in 1865 proved the principles of [[antisepsis]] in the treatment of wounds; However, medical conservatism on new breakthroughs in pre-existing science prevented them from being generally well received during the 19th century.

Semmelweis's work was supported by the discoveries made by [[Louis Pasteur]]. Linking microorganisms with disease, Pasteur brought about a revolution in medicine. He also invented with [[Claude Bernard]] (1813–1878) the process of [[pasteurization]] still in use today. His experiments confirmed the germ theory. Claude Bernard aimed at establishing [[scientific method]] in medicine; he published ''An Introduction to the Study of Experimental Medicine'' in 1865. Beside this, Pasteur, along with [[Robert Koch]] (who was awarded the [[Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine|Nobel Prize]] in 1905), founded bacteriology. Koch was also famous for the discovery of the [[Mycobacterium tuberculosis|tubercle bacillus]] (1882) and the [[Vibrio cholerae|cholera bacillus]] (1883) and for his development of [[Koch's postulates]].

The participation of women in medical care (beyond serving as [[midwives]], sitters and cleaning women) was brought about by [[Florence Nightingale]]. Nightingale showed a previously male dominated profession the elemental role of nursing in order to lessen the aggravation of patient mortality which resulted from lack of hygiene and nutrition. Nightingale set up the St Thomas hospital, post-Crimea, in 1852. The International Red Cross began operations in numerous countries in the late 19th century, promoting nursing as an ideal profession for middle class women.&lt;ref&gt;Brian Abel-Smith, ''A History of the Nursing Profession'' (1960)&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Elizabeth Blackwell (doctor)|Elizabeth Blackwell]] (1821–1910) became the first woman to formally study, and subsequently practice, medicine in the United States.

===U.S. Civil War===
In the [[American Civil War]] (1861–65), as was typical of the 19th century, more soldiers died of disease than in battle, and even larger numbers were temporarily incapacitated by wounds, disease and accidents.&lt;ref&gt;George Worthington   Adams, ''Doctors in Blue: The Medical History of the Union Army in the Civil War'' (1996), [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0807121053/  excerpt and text search]; Glenna R.  Schroeder-Lein, ''The Encyclopedia of Civil War Medicine'' (2012) [http://www.amazon.com/Encyclopedia-Civil-War-Medicine/dp/0765621304/  excerpt and text search].&lt;/ref&gt;  Conditions were poor in the [[Confederate States of America|Confederacy]], where doctors and medical supplies were in short supply.&lt;ref&gt;H.H. Cunningham, ''Doctors in Gray: The Confederate Medical Service'' (1993) [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0807118567/ excerpt and text search]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Union responded by building army hospitals in every state. The hygiene of the camps was poor, especially at the beginning of the war when men who had seldom been far from home were brought together for training with thousands of strangers. First came epidemics of the childhood diseases of chicken pox, mumps, whooping cough, and, especially, measles. Operations in the South meant a dangerous and new disease environment, bringing diarrhea, dysentery, typhoid fever, and malaria. There were no antibiotics, so the surgeons prescribed coffee, whiskey, and quinine. Harsh weather, bad water, inadequate shelter in winter quarters, poor policing of camps, and dirty camp hospitals took their toll.&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth Link, &quot;Potomac Fever: The Hazards of Camp Life,&quot; ''Vermont History,'' (1983) 51#2 pp 69-88&lt;/ref&gt;  This was a common scenario in wars from time immemorial, and conditions faced by the Confederate army were even worse. What was different in the Union was the emergence of skilled, well-funded medical organizers who rook proactive action, especially in the much enlarged United States Army Medical Department,&lt;ref&gt;Mary C. Gillett, ''The Army Medical Department, 1818-1865'' (1987)&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[United States Sanitary Commission]], a new private agency.&lt;ref&gt;William Quentin Maxwell, ''Lincoln's Fifth Wheel: The Political History of the U.S. Sanitary Commission'' (1956)&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous other new agencies also targeted the medical and morale needs of soldiers, including the [[United States Christian Commission]] as well as smaller private agencies such as the Women's Central Association of Relief for Sick and Wounded in the Army (WCAR) founded in 1861 by [[Henry Whitney Bellows]], and [[Dorothea Dix]].  Systematic funding appeals raised public consciousness, as well as millions of dollars. Many thousands of volunteers worked in the hospitals and rest homes, most famously poet [[Walt Whitman]]. [[Frederick Law Olmstead]], a famous landscape architect, was the highly efficient executive director of the Sanitary Commission.&lt;ref&gt;Justin Martin,  ''Genius of Place: The Life of Frederick Law Olmsted'' (2011) pp 178-230&lt;/ref&gt;

States could use their own tax money to support their troops as Ohio did. Following the unexpected carnage at the battle of Shiloh in April 1862, the Ohio state government sent 3 steamboats to the scene as floating hospitals with doctors, nurses and medical supplies. The state fleet expanded to eleven hospital ships.  The state also set up 12 local offices in main transportation nodes to help Ohio soldiers moving back and forth.&lt;ref&gt;Eugene E. Roseboom, ''The Civil War Era, 1850-1873'' (1944) p 396&lt;/ref&gt;  The U.S. Army learned many lessons and in 1886, it established the Hospital Corps.  The Sanitary Commission collected enormous amounts of statistical data, and opened up the problems of storing information for fast access and mechanically searching for data patterns.&lt;ref&gt;James H. Cassedy, &quot;Numbering the North's Medical Events: Humanitarianism and Science in Civil War Statistics,&quot; ''Bulletin of the History of Medicine,'' Summer 1992, Vol. 66 Issue 2, pp 210-233&lt;/ref&gt; The pioneer was [[John Shaw Billings]] (1838-1913). A senior surgeon in the war, Billings built two of the world's most important libraries, [[Library of the Surgeon General's Office]] (now the [[National Library of Medicine]] and the [[New York Public Library]]; he also figured out how to mechanically analyze data by turning it into numbers and punching onto the computer punch card as developed by his student [[Herman Hollerith]].

== World Wars ==
[[File:Ww2-53.jpg|thumb|American [[combat surgery]] during the [[Pacific War]], 1943. Major wars have stressed the need for qualified medical treatment and hygiene.]]
The 20th century witnessed a shift from a master-apprentice paradigm of teaching of clinical medicine to a more &quot;democratic&quot; system of medical schools. With the advent of the [[evidence-based medicine]] and great advances of information technology the process of change is likely to evolve further, with greater development of international projects such as the [[Human genome project]].

During the 20th century, large-scale wars were attended with [[medic]]s and [[mobile hospital]] units which developed advanced techniques for healing massive injuries and controlling infections rampant in battlefield conditions. Thousands of scarred troops provided the need for improved [[prosthetic limb]]s and expanded techniques in plastic surgery or [[reconstructive surgery]]. Those practices were combined to broaden [[cosmetic surgery]] and other forms of [[elective surgery]].

During the [[First World War]], [[Alexis Carrel]] and [[Henry Drysdale Dakin|Henry Dakin]] developed the [[Carrel-Dakin method]] of treating wounds with an irrigation, Dakin's solution, a [[germicide]] which helped prevent [[gangrene]].

The Great War spurred the usage of [[Wilhelm Röntgen|Roentgen]]'s [[X-ray]], and the [[electrocardiograph]], for the [[monitoring (medicine)|monitoring]] of internal bodily functions.  This was followed in the inter-war period by the development of the first anti-bacterial agents such as the [[sulpha]] antibiotics.  The Second World War saw the introduction of widespread and effective [[antimicrobial therapy]] with the development and mass production of [[penicillin]] antibiotics, made possible by the pressures of the war and the collaboration of British scientists with the American pharmaceutical industry.

The [[1918 flu pandemic]] killed at least 50 million people around the world, and has become an important case study in [[epidemiology]], see [[Spanish flu research]].

[[Human subject research]], and killing of patients with disabilities, were at its height during the mid-20th century, with [[Nazi human experimentation]] and [[Aktion T4]] during [[the Holocaust]] as the most significant example, followed up by the [[Doctors' Trial]]. Principles of [[medical ethics]], such as the [[Nuremberg Code]], have been introduced to prevent atrocities.

During and just after World War II, [[DDT]] was used as [[insecticide]] to combat [[insect vector]]s carrying [[malaria]] and [[typhus]].

===Psychiatric reform===
{{Further|History of psychiatry}}
[[Lunatic asylum]]s began to appear in the [[Industrial Era]]. [[Emil Kraepelin]] (1856–1926) introduced new medical categories of [[mental illness]], which eventually came into [[psychiatry|psychiatric]] usage despite their basis in behavior rather than [[Biopsychiatry controversy|pathology or etiology]]. In the 1920s [[surrealism|surrealist]] opposition to psychiatry was expressed in a number of surrealist publications.  In the 1930s several controversial medical practices were introduced including inducing seizures (by [[electroshock]], [[insulin]] or other drugs) or cutting parts of the brain apart ([[leucotomy]] or [[lobotomy]]). Both came into widespread use by psychiatry, but there were grave concerns and much opposition on grounds of basic morality, harmful effects, or misuse. In the 1950s new [[psychiatric drugs]], notably the antipsychotic [[chlorpromazine]], were designed in laboratories and slowly came into preferred use. Although often accepted as an advance in some ways, there was some opposition, due to serious adverse effects such as [[tardive dyskinesia]]. Patients often opposed psychiatry and refused or stopped taking the drugs when not subject to psychiatric control. There was also increasing opposition to the use of psychiatric hospitals, and attempts to move people back into the community on a collaborative [[World Network of Users and Survivors of Psychiatry|user-led group]] approach (&quot;therapeutic communities&quot;) not controlled by psychiatry. Campaigns against [[masturbation]] were done in the [[Victorian era]] and elsewhere. [[Lobotomy]] was used until the 1970s to treat [[schizophrenia]]. This was denounced by the [[anti-psychiatric]] movement in the 1960s and later.

==Post-World War II==
[[File:Fighting smallpox in Niger, 1969.jpg|thumb|[[Smallpox]] vaccination in Niger, 1969. A decade later, this was the first infectious disease to be eradicated.]]
[[File:Life expectancy in some Southern African countries 1958 to 2003.png|thumb|Most countries have seen a tremendous increase in life expectancy since 1945. However, in southern Africa, the [[HIV]] epidemic beginning around 1990 has eroded national health.]]
[[File:Infant with cochlear implant.jpg|left|thumb|A [[cochlear implant]] is a common kind of [[neural prosthesis]], a device replacing part of the [[human nervous system]].]]
The [[World Health Organization]] was founded in 1948 as a [[United Nations]] agency to improve [[global health]]. In most of the world, [[life expectancy]] has improved since then, and was about 67 years as of 2010, and well above 80 years in some countries. [[Eradication of infectious diseases]] is an international effort, and several new [[vaccine]]s have been developed during the post-war years, against infections such as [[measles]], [[mumps]], several strains of [[influenza]] and [[human papilloma virus]]. The long-known vaccine against [[Smallpox]] finally eradicated the disease in the 1970s, and [[Rinderpest]] was wiped out in 2011. [[Eradication of polio]] is underway. [[Tissue culture]] is important for development of vaccines.

As infectious diseases have become less lethal, and the most common [[cause of death|causes of death]] in developed countries are now [[tumor]]s and [[cardiovascular disease]]s, these conditions have received increased attention in medical research. [[Tobacco smoking]] as a cause of [[lung cancer]] was first researched in the 1920s, but was not widely supported by publications until the 1950s. [[Cancer treatment]] has been developed with [[radiotherapy]] and [[chemotherapy]].

[[Oral rehydration therapy]] has been extensively used since the 1970s to treat [[cholera]] and other diarrhea-inducing infections.

[[Hormonal contraception]] was introduced in the 1950s, and was associated with the [[sexual revolution]], with normalization of [[abortion]] and [[homosexuality]]. [[Family planning]] has been applied around the world, and has promoted a [[demographic transition]] in most of the world. With threatening [[sexually transmitted infections]], not least [[HIV]], use of [[barrier contraception]] has become imperative. The struggle against HIV has provided no cure, but improved [[antiretroviral]] treatments, and in the late 2000s (decade), male [[circumcision]] was proved to diminish infection risk.

[[Medical radiography|X-ray imaging]] was the first kind of [[medical imaging]], and later [[ultrasonic imaging]], [[CT scanning]], [[MR scanning]] and other imaging methods became available.

[[Genetics]] have advanced with the discovery of the [[DNA]] molecule, [[genetic mapping]] and [[gene therapy]].

[[Stem cell]] research took off in the 2000s (decade), with [[stem cell therapy]] as a promising method.

[[Evidence-based medicine]] is a modern concept, not introduced to literature until the 1990s.

[[Prosthetic]]s have improved. In 1958, [[Arne Larsson]] in Sweden became the first patient to depend on an [[artificial cardiac pacemaker]]. He died in 2001, having outlived its inventor, the surgeon, and 26 pacemakers. Lightweight materials as well as [[neural prosthetic]]s emerged in the end of the 20th century.

===Modern surgery===
[[Cardiac surgery]] was revolutionized in the late 1940s, as open-heart surgery was introduced.

In 1954 [[Joseph Murray]], [[J. Hartwell Harrison, M.D.]] and others accomplished the first [[kidney transplantation]]. [[organ transplant|Transplantation]]s of other organs, such as heart, liver and pancreas, were also introduced during the latter 20th century. The first partial [[face transplant]] was performed in 2005, and the first full one in 2010. By the end of the 20th century, [[microtechnology]] had been used to create tiny robotic devices to assist [[microsurgery]] using micro-video and [[fiber optics|fiber-optic]] cameras to view internal tissues during surgery with minimally invasive practices.&lt;ref&gt;Murray, Joseph E., &quot;The First Successful Organ Transplants in Man&quot;, Nobel Lect., 1990, Nobelprize.org., Web, July 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Laparoscopic surgery]] was broadly introduced in the 1990s. [[Natural orifice surgery]] has followed.

{{-}}

== See also ==
* [[Centers for Disease Control and Prevention timeline]]
* [[History of pathology]]
* [[History of pharmacy]]
* [[History of surgery]]
* [[Timeline of medicine]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Bibliography ==
* Berridge, Virginia. &quot;Health and Medicine&quot; in ''The Cambridge Social History of Britain, 1750-1950, vol. 3, Social Agencies and Institutions,'' edited by F M.L. Thompson, (1990).
* Porter, Roy, and Dorothy Porter. ''In Sickness and in Health: The British Experience, 1650-1850'' (1988).
* {{cite book | title = The Greatest Benefit to Mankind: A Medical History of Humanity from Antiquity to the Present | last = [[Roy Porter|Porter]] | first =  Roy | year = 1997 | publisher = Harper Collins | isbn = 0-00-215173-1 }}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Rousseau |editor1-first=George S. |year=2003 |title=Framing and Imagining Disease in Cultural History |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=Basingstoke |isbn=1-4039-1292-0 }} With Miranda Gill, David Haycock and [[Malte Herwig]].
*Siraisi,  Nancy G. &quot; Medicine, 1450–1620, and the History of Science,&quot; ''Isis'' (2012) 103#3 pp 491-514  DOI: 10.1086/667970
* Sivin, Nathan (1993). &quot;''Huang-ti nei-ching'' 黃帝內經.&quot; In ''Early Chinese Texts: A Bibliographical Guide'', ed. by Michael Loewe: 196-215. Institute for East Asian Studies, University of California, Berkeley.
* Unschuld, Paul U. ''Huang Di Nei Jing Su Wen: Nature, Knowledge, Imagery in an Ancient Chinese Medical Text''. (2003).
* Warner, John Harley, and Janet A. Tighe, eds. ''Major Problems in the History of American Medicine and Public Health'' (2006), 560pp; readings in primary and secondary sources [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0395954355/ excerpt and text search]
* Weatherall, Miles. ''In Search of a Cure: A History of Pharmaceutical Discovery'' (1990), emphasis on antibiotics.
* Wohl, Anthony S. ''Endangered Lives: Public Health in Victorian Britain'' (1983).

== External links ==
{{commons category}}
* [http://www.histmed.org/ American Association for the History of Medicine],
* [http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/broughttolife Science Museum's History of Medicine Website]
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=History of Medicine}}
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=Anatomy}}
* [http://www.nlm.nih.gov/hmd/ History of Medicine], [[United States National Library of Medicine]]
* [http://wwwcf.nlm.nih.gov/hmddirectory/index.cfm/ Directory of History of Medicine Collections]
* [http://www.imageofsurgery.com/Surgery_history_art.htm  The history of medicine and surgery as portrayed by various artists]
* [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=325&amp;letter=M&amp;search=medicine Medicine @ JewishEncyclopedia.com]
* [http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/vatican/medicine.html Exhibition of the Vatican Library's Medical Holdings @ The Library of Congress]
* [http://www.infobritain.co.uk/History_Of_Medicine.htm Info Britain - History of medicine in the UK]
* [http://library.wellcome.ac.uk/index.html Wellcome Library History of Medicine]
* [http://clendening.kumc.edu/dc/index.html Digital Clendening Library at the University of Kansas Medical Center]
* [http://www.lib.unc.edu/dc/mackinney/index.html &quot;MacKinney Collection of Medieval Medical Illustrations&quot;]
* [http://www.countway.harvard.edu/menuNavigation/historicalResources.html The Center for the History of Medicine, Countway Library, Harvard Medical School (includes the Warren Anatomical Museum)]
* [http://www.medicalheritage.org/ Medical Heritage Library] digital curation collaborative
* [http://history.lshtm.ac.uk/ Centre for History in Public Health, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine]
* [http://phisick.com/article/the-practice-of-phisick/ &quot;The Practice of Phisick&quot;] article phisick.com 13 November 2011
* [http://michaelservetusresearch.com/ENGLISH/works.html Michael Servetus Research] Website with  a graphical study on the Manuscript of Paris by Michael Servetus (1546)

{{History of medicine}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Medicine}}
[[Category:History of medicine| ]]

{{Link FA|es}}

[[ast:Historia de la medicina]]
[[bg:История на медицината]]
[[ca:Història de la medicina]]
[[de:Medizingeschichte]]
[[es:Historia de la medicina]]
[[eu:Medikuntzaren historiaren kronologia]]
[[fa:تاریخ پزشکی]]
[[fr:Histoire de la médecine]]
[[ko:의학사]]
[[hi:आयुर्विज्ञान का इतिहास]]
[[hr:Povijest medicine]]
[[it:Storia della medicina]]
[[nl:Geschiedenis van de geneeskunde]]
[[ja:医学史]]
[[no:Medisinens historie]]
[[pl:Historia medycyny]]
[[pt:História da medicina]]
[[ro:Istoria medicinii]]
[[ru:История медицины]]
[[sk:Dejiny medicíny]]
[[sr:Istorija medicine]]
[[sh:Istorija medicine]]
[[fi:Lääketieteen historia]]
[[sv:Medicinhistoria]]
[[ta:மருத்துவத்துறையின் வரலாறு]]
[[uk:Історія медицини]]
[[zh:医学史]]</text>
      <sha1>hxvn3wljifqzbersurtbgblbdp71m11</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
