<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Cambodia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5428</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521069742</id>
      <parentid>520995519</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T16:12:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheTimesAreAChanging</username>
        <id>13216755</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* People's Republic of Kampuchea (1979–1993) */ Removed, because I cannot trust the permanently blocked user to provide the full source.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42702">{{Refimprove|date=November 2008}}
{{lead missing|date=August 2012}}
{{History of Cambodia}}

== Prehistory and early history ==
{{main|Early history of Cambodia}}
[[Image:AncientKhmerScript.jpg|thumb|left|Ancient [[Khmer script]]]]
[[Carbon 14 dating]] of a cave at [[Laang Spean]] in northwest [[Cambodia]] reveals people who made pots were living in Cambodia as early as 4200 [[Before the Common Era|BCE]] &lt;!--(Before the Common Era)--&gt;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chandlerp13&quot;&gt;David Chandler, ''A History of Cambodia'' (Westview Publishers: Boulder Colorado, 2008) p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; Further archaeological evidence indicates that other parts of the region now called [[Cambodia]] were inhabited from around 2000-1000 BCE by a [[Neolithic]] culture. Skulls and human bones found at Samrong Sen date from 1500 BCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chandlerp13&quot;/&gt; These people may have migrated from South Eastern China to the Indochinese Peninsula. Scholars trace the first cultivation of rice and the first bronze making in Southeast Asia to these people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chandlerp13&quot;/&gt; By the 1st century CE, the inhabitants had developed relatively stable, organized societies and spoke languages very much related to the Cambodian or Khmer of the present day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chandlerp13&quot;/&gt; The culture and technical skills of these people &lt;!-- of the 1st century in the CE --&gt;in the 1st century CE&lt;!--O'k?--&gt; far surpassed the primitive stage. The most advanced groups lived along the coast and in the lower Mekong River valley and delta regions in houses constructed on stilts where they cultivated rice, fished and kept domesticated animals. Recent research has unlocked the discovery of artificial circular [[earthworks (archeology)|earthworks]] dating to Cambodia's [[Neolithic]] era.[http://muse.jhu.edu/demo/asian_perspectives/v039/39.1albrecht.pdf *]

The [[Khmer people]] were among the first inhabitants of South East Asia. They were also among the first in [[South East Asia]] to adopt religious ideas and political institutions from [[Indian subcontinent|India]] and to establish centralized kingdoms comprising large territories. The earliest known kingdom in the area, [[Kingdom of Funan|Funan]], flourished from around the first to the 6th century. This was succeeded by [[Chenla]], which controlled large parts of modern [[Cambodia]], [[Vietnam]], [[Laos]], and [[Thailand]].

==Funan Kingdom==
{{Main|Kingdom of Funan}}
[[Image:FunanMap001.jpg|thumb|150px|Map of Funan at around 3rd century]]
The [[Kingdom of Funan|Funan]]ese Empire rose to eminence from its affluent and powerful home city of [[Oc Eo]] (in nowadays [[Vietnam]]), known in the [[Roman Empire]] as [[Kattigara]], meaning the Renowned City. Contacts with the distant Roman Empire are evidenced by the fact that Roman coins have been found at archeological sites dating from the 2nd and 3rd centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chandlerp19&quot;&gt;David Chandler, ''A History of Camboida,'' p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; However, most of the foreign trade of the Funan Empire was carried on much closer to home with [[India]], especially the [[Bengal]] area of India. Trade with India commenced well before 500 BCE (before the widespread use of [[Sanskrit]] as a language in India).&lt;ref&gt;Percival Spear, ''India: A Modern History'' (University of Michigan Press: Ann Arbor, 1961) p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; With the Indian trade came the Indianization of the culture of Funan and the religion of Hinduism. Hinduism produced a [[syncretism]] phenomenon with other previous religions and beliefs already present in the Khmer culture. Funan and its succeeding societies which occupied this section of Southeast Asia would remain mainly Hindu in religion for about 900 years. Some cultural features and customs of Hinduism continue to exist within the current society. 

The empire reached its greatest extent under the rule of Fan Shih-man in the early 3rd century, extending as far south as [[Malaysia]] and as far west as [[Burma]]. The Funanese established a strong system of mercantilism and commercial monopolies that would become a pattern for empires in the region. Exports from the Funan Empire were largely forest products and precious metals—including accessories such as gold elephants, ivory, rhinoceros horn, kingfisher feathers, wild spices like cardamom, lacquer hides and aromatic wood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chandlerp19&quot;/&gt; Fan Shih-man expanded the fleet and improved the Funanese bureaucracy, creating a quasi-feudal pattern that left local customs and identities largely intact, particularly in the empire's farther reaches.

==Chenla Kingdom==
{{Main|Chenla}}
The Khmers, vassals of Funan, had reached the [[Mekong River]] from the northern [[Menam River]] via the [[Mun River]] Valley. [[Chenla]], their first independent state developed out of Funanese influence.

Ancient Chinese records mention two kings, [[Shrutavarman]] and [[Shreshthavarman]] who ruled at the capital [[Shreshthapura]] located in modern day southern Laos. The immense influence on the identity of Cambodia to come was wrought by the Khmer Kingdom of [[Bhavapura]], in the modern day Cambodian city of [[Kampong Thom City|Kompong Thom]]. Its legacy was its most important sovereign, [[Ishanavarman]] who completely conquered the kingdom of Funan during 612-628. He chose his new capital at the [[Sambor Prei Kuk]], naming it Ishanapura.

After the death of [[Jayavarman I]] in 681, turmoil came upon the kingdom and at the start of the 8th century, the kingdom broke up into many principalities. [[Pushkaraksha]], the ruler of [[Shambhupura]] announced himself as king of the entire [[Kambuja]]. Chinese chronicles proclaim that in the 8th century, Chenla was split into land Chenla and water Chenla. During this time, [[Shambhuvarman]] son of Pushkaraksha controlled most of water Chenla until the 8th century which the [[Malayans]] and [[Javanese people|Javanese]] dominated over many Khmer principalities.

==Khmer Empire==
{{Main|Khmer Empire}}
[[Image:Angkor Wat.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Angkor Wat]]]]
[[Image:Map-of-southeast-asia 900 CE.png|thumb|200px|Map of South-east Asia circa 900 CE, showing the [[Khmer Empire]] in red, [[Champa]] in yellow and [[Haripunjaya]] in light Green plus additional surrounding states.]]

The golden age of Khmer civilization, however, was the period from the 9th to the 13th centuries, when Khmer Empire, which gave Kampuchea, or Cambodia, its name, ruled large territories from its capital in the region of Angkor in western Cambodia.

Legend has it that in 802 CE, [[Jayavarman II]], king of the Khmers, first came to the Kuhlen hills, the future site of Angkor Wat.&lt;ref&gt;David Chandler, ''A History of Cambodia'' (Westview Publishers: Boulder Colorado, 2008) p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, under [[Jayavarman VII of Kambuja|Jayavarman VII]] (1181–ca. 1218), Khmer reached its zenith of political power and cultural creativity. Jayavarman VII gained power and territory in a series of successful wars. Khmer conquests were almost unstoppable as they raided home cities of powerful seafaring Chams. However, territorial expansion stopped after a defeat by [[Dai Viet]]. The battle also witnessed Suryavarman II's death. Following Jayavarman VII's death, Khmer experienced a gradual decline. Important factors were the aggressiveness of neighboring peoples (especially the [[Thai people|Thai, or Siamese]]), chronic interdynastic strife, and the gradual deterioration of the complex irrigation system that had ensured rice surpluses. The [[Angkor]]ian monarchy survived until 1431, when the Thai captured [[Angkor Thom]] and the Cambodian king fled to the southern part of the country

==Dark ages of Cambodia==
{{Main|Dark ages of Cambodia}}
The 15th to the 19th centuries were a period of continued decline and territorial loss. Cambodia enjoyed a brief period of prosperity during the 16th century because its kings, who built their capitals in the region southeast of the [[Tonle Sap]] along the [[Mekong River]], promoted trade with other parts of Asia. This was the period when [[Spain|Spanish]] and [[Portugal|Portuguese]] adventurers and missionaries first visited the country. However, the Thai conquest of the new capital at [[Lovek]] in 1594 marked a downturn in the country's fortunes and Cambodia. Becoming a pawn in power struggles between its two increasingly powerful neighbors, Siam and Vietnam. Cambodia remained a protectorate of Siam. Vietnam's settlement of the [[Mekong Delta]] led to its annexation of that area at the end of the 17th century. Vietnam employed a strategy similar to those of North American pilgrims and pioneers: settle and claim. Such foreign encroachments continued through the first half of the 19th century. A successful invasion by Vietnam further limited Thai protectorship in Cambodia and established the kingdom under full Vietnamese suzerainty.

==French colonial period (1863–1953)==
{{Main|French protectorate of Cambodia|French Indochina}}
[[Image:Indochine française (1913).jpg|thumb|right|200px|French Indochina in 1913.]]
In 1863, [[Norodom of Cambodia|King Norodom]] signed an agreement with the [[France|French]] to establish a protectorate over his kingdom. The state gradually came under French colonial rule.

[[File:King Norodom.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Norodom of Cambodia]]]]
During [[World War II]], the 1940 - 1941 [[Franco-Thai War]] left the [[French Indochina|French Indochinese]] colonial authorities in a position of weakness. The Vichy government signed an agreement with Japan to allow the Japanese military transit through French Indochina.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.net4war.com/e-revue/dossiers/2gm/indochine-sgm/indochine-sgm-01.htm Jean-Philippe Liardet, ''L'Indochine française pendant la Seconde Guerre mondiale''; Les accords de septembre 1940]&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile the [[Thailand|Thai]] government, under the pro-Japanese leadership of Field Marshal [[Plaek Phibunsongkhram]], took advantage of its position and invaded Cambodia's western provinces.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.net4war.com/e-revue/dossiers/2gm/indochine-sgm/indochine-sgm-02.htm Jean-Philippe Liardet, ''L'Indochine française pendant la Seconde Guerre mondiale''; La guerre contre le Siam, 1940-41]&lt;/ref&gt;

Cambodia's situation at the end of the war was chaotic. The [[Free French]], under General [[Charles de Gaulle]], were determined to recover Indochina, though they offered Cambodia and the other Inchochinese protectorates a carefully circumscribed measure of self-government. Convinced that they had a &quot;[[civilizing mission]]&quot;, they envisioned Indochina's participation in a French Union of former colonies that shared the common experience of French culture.

==Administration of Sihanouk (1953–1970)==
{{Main|Japanese occupation of Cambodia|Kingdom of Cambodia (1953–1970)}}
On 9 March 1945, during the [[Japanese occupation of Cambodia]], young king [[Norodom Sihanouk]] proclaimed an independent Kingdom of Kampuchea, following a formal request by the Japanese. Shortly thereafter the Japanese government nominally ratified the independence of Cambodia and established a consulate in Phnom Penh.&lt;ref&gt;Keat Gin Ooi ''Southeast Asia: a historical encyclopedia''&lt;/ref&gt; The new government did away with the [[Latin alphabet|romanization]] of the [[Khmer language]] that the French colonial administration was beginning to enforce and officially reinstated the [[Khmer script]]. This measure taken by the short-lived governmental authority would be popular and long-lasting, for since then no government in Cambodia has tried to romanize the Khmer language again.&lt;ref&gt;David P. Chandler, ''A History of Cambodia'', Silkworm 1993&lt;/ref&gt;
After Allied military units entered Cambodia, the Japanese military forces present in the country were disarmed and repatriated. The French were able to reimpose the colonial administration in Phnom Penh in October the same year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.country-data.com/frd/cs/cambodia/kh_appnb.html Cambodia, Appendix B - Major Political and Military Organizations]&lt;/ref&gt;

Sihanouk's &quot;royal crusade for independence&quot; resulted in grudging French acquiescence to his demands for a transfer of sovereignty. A partial agreement was struck in October 1953. Sihanouk then declared that independence had been achieved and returned in triumph to [[Phnom Penh]]. As a result of the Geneva Conference on Indochina, Cambodia was able to bring about the withdrawal of the [[Viet Minh]] troops from its territory and to withstand any residual impingement upon its sovereignty by external powers.

Neutrality was the central element of Cambodian foreign policy during the 1950s and 1960s. By the mid-1960s, parts of Cambodia's eastern provinces were serving as bases for North Vietnamese Army and [[Viet Cong]] (NVA/VC) forces operating against South Vietnam, and the port of [[Sihanoukville]] was being used to supply them. As NVA/VC activity grew, the United States and [[South Vietnam]] became concerned, and in 1969, the United States began a 14 month long series of bombing raids targeted at NVA/VC elements, contributing to destabilization. The United States claims that the bombing campaign took place no further than ten, and later twenty miles (32&amp;nbsp;km) inside the Cambodian border, areas where the Cambodian population had been evicted by the NVA.&lt;ref&gt;Davidson, Phillip B. ''Vietnam at War: The History 1946–1975''. 1988. P. 593&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--Cite supports entire paragraph--&gt; Prince Sihanouk, fearing that the conflict between communist North Vietnam and South Vietnam might spill over to Cambodia, publicly opposed the idea of a bombing campaign by the United States along the Vietnam-Cambodia border and inside Cambodian territory. However [[Peter Rodman]] claimed, &quot;Prince Sihanouk complained bitterly to us about these North Vietnamese bases in his country and invited us to attack them&quot;. In December 1967 Washington Post journalist Stanley Karnow was told by Sihanouk that if the US wanted to bomb the Vietnamese communist sanctuaries, he would not object, unless Cambodians were killed.&lt;ref&gt;Washington Post, December 29, 1967&lt;/ref&gt; The same message was conveyed to US President Johnson's emissary Chester Bowles in January 1968.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen J. Morris &quot;Why Vietnam Invaded Cambodia.&quot;. (Stanford University Press. 1999). p. 44&lt;/ref&gt; So the US had no real motivation to overthrow Sihanouk. However Prince Sihanouk wanted Cambodia to stay out of the North Vietnam-South Vietnam conflict and was very critical of the United States government and its allies (the South Vietnamese government).  Prince Sihanouk, facing internal struggles of his own, due to the rise of the Khmer Rouge, did not want Cambodia to be involved in the conflict. Sihanouk wanted the United States and its allies (South Vietnam) to keep the war away from the Cambodian border.  Sihanouk did not allow the United States to use Cambodian air space and airports for military purposes. This upset the United States greatly and contributed to there view that of Prince Sihanouk as a North Vietnamese sympathizer and a thorn on the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{worldhistory|quote=P. 1012|section=4084}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, declassified documents indicate that, as late as March 1970, the Nixon administration was hoping to garner &quot;friendly relations&quot; with Sihanouk.

Throughout the 1960s, domestic Cambodian politics became polarized. Opposition to the government grew within the middle class and leftists including Paris-educated leaders like [[Son Sen]], [[Ieng Sary]], and Saloth Sar (later known as [[Pol Pot]]), who led an [[insurgency]] under the clandestine Communist Party of Kampuchea (CPK). Sihanouk called these insurgents the [[Khmer Rouge]], literally the &quot;Red Khmer.&quot; But the 1966 national assembly elections showed a significant swing to the right, and General [[Lon Nol]] formed a new government, which lasted until 1967. During 1968 and 1969, the insurgency worsened. However members of the government and army, who resented Sihanouk's ruling style as well as his tilt away from the United States, did have a motivation to overthrow him.

==Khmer Republic and the War (1970–1975)==
[[File:Asien Bd1.jpg|350px|thumb|Map of [[Asia]] in 1890]]
{{Main|Cambodian Civil War|Khmer Republic}}
{{Refimprove section|date=January 2010}}
While visiting Beijing in 1970 Sihanouk was [[Cambodian coup of 1970|ousted by a military coup]] led by Prime Minister General [[Lon Nol]] and Prince Sisowath [[Sirik Matak]] in the early hours of March 18, 1970.&lt;ref&gt;Philip Short, ''Pol Pot: Anatomy of a Nightmare'' p. 197.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
&quot;Prince Sihanouk was deposed in a right-wing coup in 1970 led by Lt-Gen Lon Nol&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/133533.stm]&lt;/ref&gt;
Despite Sihanouk's allegations, there is no evidence that this coup was planned by the United States [[Central Intelligence Agency]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Shortp196&quot;&gt;Philip Short, ''Pol Pot: Anatomy of a Nightmare'' (Henry Holt &amp; Co.: New York, 2004) p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, as early as March 12, 1970, the CIA Station Chief told Washington that based on communications from Sirik Matak, Lon Nol's cousin, that &quot;the (Cambodian) army was ready for a coup&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Philip Short, ''Pol Pot: Anatomy of a Nightmare'' (Henry Holt &amp; Co.: New York, 2004) p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt; Lon Nol assumed power after the military coup and immediately allied Cambodia with the United States. Son Ngoc Thanh, an opponent of Pol Pot, announced his support for the new government. On October 9, the Cambodian monarchy was abolished, and the country was renamed the Khmer Republic. The new regime immediately demanded that the Vietnamese communists leave Cambodia.

Hanoi rejected the new republic's request for the withdrawal of NVA troops. In response, the United States moved to provide material assistance to the new government's armed forces, which were engaged against both CPK insurgents and NVA forces.The North Vietnamese and Viet Cong forces, desperate to retain their sanctuaries and supply lines from North Vietnam, immediately launched armed attacks on the new government. The king urged his followers to help in overthrowing this government, hastening the onset of [[Cambodian Civil War|civil war]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SIHNK&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Sihanouk | first = Norodom | authorlink = Norodom Sihanouk | title = My War with the CIA, The Memoirs of Prince Norodom Sihanouk as related to Wilfred Burchett | publisher=Pantheon Books | year = 1973| isbn = 0394485432}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 1970, US President Nixon announced to the American public that US and South Vietnamese ground forces had entered Cambodia in a campaign aimed at destroying NVA base areas in Cambodia (see [[Cambodian Incursion]]).&lt;ref&gt;Philip Short, ''Pol Pot: Anatomy of a Nightmare'' (Henry Holt &amp; Co.: New York, 2004) p. 204.&lt;/ref&gt; The US had already been bombing Vietnamese positions in Cambodia for well over a year by that point.

Although a considerable quantity of equipment was seized or destroyed by US and South Vietnamese forces, containment of North Vietnamese forces proved elusive. The North Vietnamese moved deeper into Cambodia to avoid US and South Vietnamese raids. NVA units overran many Cambodian army positions while the CPK expanded their small-scale attacks on lines of communication.

The Khmer Republic's leadership was plagued by disunity among its three principal figures: Lon Nol, Sihanouk's cousin [[Sirik Matak]], and National Assembly leader [[In Tam]]. Lon Nol remained in power in part because none of the others were prepared to take his place. In 1972, a constitution was adopted, a parliament elected, and Lon Nol became president. But disunity, the problems of transforming a 30,000-man army into a national combat force of more than 200,000 men, and spreading corruption weakened the civilian administration and army.

The Communist insurgency inside Cambodia continued to grow, aided by supplies and military support from North Vietnam. [[Pol Pot]] and [[Ieng Sary]] asserted their dominance over the Vietnamese-trained communists, many of whom were purged. At the same time, the [[Communist Party of Kampuchea]] forces became stronger and more independent of their Vietnamese patrons. By 1973, the CPK were fighting battles against government forces with little or no North Vietnamese troop support, and they controlled nearly 60% of Cambodia's territory and 25% of its population.

The government made three unsuccessful attempts to enter into negotiations with the insurgents, but by 1974, the CPK were operating openly as divisions, and some of the NVA combat forces had moved into South Vietnam. Lon Nol's control was reduced to small enclaves around the cities and main transportation routes. More than 2 million refugees from the war lived in [[Phnom Penh]] and other cities.

On New Year's Day 1975, Communist troops launched an offensive which, in 117 days of the hardest fighting of the war, collapsed the Khmer Republic. Simultaneous attacks around the perimeter of Phnom Penh pinned down Republican forces, while other CPK units overran fire bases controlling the vital lower Mekong resupply route. A US-funded airlift of ammunition and rice ended when Congress refused additional aid for Cambodia. The Lon Nol government in Phnom Penh surrendered on April 17, 1975, just five (5) days after the US mission evacuated Cambodia.&lt;ref&gt;Philip Short, ''Pol Pot: Anatomy of a Nightmare'' p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

The relationship between the massive carpet bombing of Cambodia by the United States and the growth of the Khmer Rouge, in terms of recruitment and popular support, has been a matter of interest to historians. Some historians have cited the U.S. intervention and bombing campaign (spanning 1965–1973) as a significant factor leading to increased support of the Khmer Rouge among the Cambodian peasantry. However, Pol Pot biographer David Chandler argues that the bombing &quot;had the effect the Americans wanted – it broke the Communist encirclement of Phnom Penh&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, David 2000, ''Brother Number One: A Political Biography of Pol Pot'', Revised Edition, Chiang Mai, Thailand: Silkworm Books, pp. 96–7.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Peter Rodman]] and [[Michael Lind]] claimed that the US intervention saved Cambodia from collapse in 1970 and 1973.&lt;ref name=&quot;Returning to Cambodia&quot;&gt;Rodman, Peter, [http://www.brookings.edu/opinions/2007/0823iraq_rodman.aspx Returning to Cambodia], Brookings Institute, August 23, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lind, Michael, ''Vietnam: The Necessary War: A Reinterpretation of America's Most Disastrous Military Conflict'', Free Press, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;  Craig Etcheson agreed that it was &quot;untenable&quot; to assert that US intervention caused the Khmer Rouge victory while acknowledging that it may have played a small role in boosting recruitment for the insurgents.&lt;ref&gt;Etcheson, Craig, ''The Rise and Demise of Democratic Kampuchea'', Westview Press, 1984, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt;  [[William Shawcross]], however, wrote that the US bombing and ground incursion plunged Cambodia into the chaos Sihanouk had worked for years to avoid.&lt;ref&gt;Shawcross, William, ''Sideshow'', Isaacs, Hardy, &amp; Brown, pp. 92–100, 106–112.&lt;/ref&gt;  

Historians [[Ben Kiernan]] and Taylor Owen argued:{{quote|[F]rom October 4, 1965, to August 15, 1973, the United States dropped far more ordnance on Cambodia than was previously believed: 2,756,941 tons' worth, dropped in 230,516 sorties on 113,716 sites. Just over 10 percent of this bombing was indiscriminate, with 3,580 of the sites listed as having &quot;unknown&quot; targets and another 8,238 sites having no target listed at all.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. &quot;The total payload dropped during these years to be nearly five times greater than the generally accepted figure. To put the revised total of 2,756,941 tons into perspective, the Allies dropped just over 2 million tons of bombs during all of World War II, including the bombs that struck Hiroshima and Nagasaki: 15,000 and 20,000 tons, respectively. Cambodia may well be the most heavily bombed country in history.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. [T]he bombing forced the Vietnamese Communists deeper and deeper into Cambodia, bringing them into greater contact with Khmer Rouge insurgents&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. [and] drove ordinary Cambodians into the arms of the Khmer Rouge, a group that seemed initially to have slim prospects of revolutionary success.&quot;&lt;ref name=KiernanOwen_2006&gt;{{cite journal|author=Ben Kiernan|authorlink=Ben Kiernan|coauthor=Taylor Owen|title=Bombs over Cambodia|journal=The Walrus|date=October 2006|url=http://www.yale.edu/cgp/Walrus_CambodiaBombing_OCT06.pdf|accessdate=29 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Rodman, however, disagreed with this view:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;When Congress, in the summer of 1973, legislated an end to U.S. military action in, over, or off the shores of Indochina, the only U.S. military activity then going on was air support of a friendly Cambodian government and army desperately defending their country against a North Vietnamese and Khmer Rouge onslaught...What destabilized Cambodia was North Vietnam's occupation of chunks of Cambodian territory from 1965 onwards for use as military bases from which to launch attacks on U.S. and South Vietnamese forces in South Vietnam. Cambodia's ruler Prince Sihanouk complained bitterly to us about these North Vietnamese bases in his country and invited us to attack them (which we did from the air in 1969–70). Next came a North Vietnamese attempt to overrun the entire country in March–April 1970, to which U.S. and South Vietnamese forces responded by a limited ground incursion at the end of April...The outcome in Indochina was not foreordained. Congress had the last word, however, between 1973 and 1975.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Returning to Cambodia&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Vietnamese intervention in Cambodia, launched at the request of the Khmer Rouge,&lt;ref&gt;Dmitry Mosyakov, &quot;The Khmer Rouge and the Vietnamese Communists: A History of Their Relations as Told in the Soviet Archives,&quot; in Susan E. Cook, ed., Genocide in Cambodia and Rwanda (Yale Genocide Studies Program Monograph Series No. 1, 2004), p54ff. Available online at: www.yale.edu/gsp/publications/Mosyakov.doc &quot;In April–May 1970, many North Vietnamese forces entered Cambodia in response to the call for help addressed to Vietnam not by Pol Pot, but by his deputy Nuon Chea. Nguyen Co Thach recalls: &quot;Nuon Chea has asked for help and we have liberated five provinces of Cambodia in ten days.&quot;&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; has also been cited as a major factor in their eventual victory, including by Shawcross.&lt;ref&gt;Shawcross, William and Peter Rodman,[http://www.brookings.edu/research/opinions/2007/06/07iraq-rodman Defeat's Killing Fields], Brookings Institute, June 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  Vietnam later admitted that it played &quot;a decisive role&quot; in their seizure of power.&lt;ref&gt;''The Economist'', February 26, 1983; ''Washington Post'', April 23, 1985.&lt;/ref&gt; China &quot;armed and trained&quot; the Khmer Rouge during the civil war and continued to aid them years afterward.&lt;ref&gt;Bezlova, Antoaneta, [http://www.atimes.com/atimes/China/KB21Ad01.html China haunted by Khmer Rouge links], ''Asia Times'', Feb 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Democratic Kampuchea (Khmer Rouge Era) (1975–1979)==
{{refimprove section|date=November 2008}}
{{Main|Democratic Kampuchea|Khmer Rouge rule of Cambodia}}
[[File:Flag of Democratic Kampuchea.svg|thumb|200px|Flag of [[Democratic Kampuchea]]]]
[[File:CPKbanner.svg|thumb|200px|Flag of the [[Communist Party of Kampuchea]]]]
Immediately after its victory, the CPK ordered the evacuation of all cities and towns, sending the entire urban population into the countryside to work as farmers, as the CPK was trying to reshape society into a model that Pol Pot had conceived.

The new government sought to completely restructure Cambodian society. Remnants of the old society were abolished and religion, particularly [[Buddhism]] and [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholicism]], was suppressed. Agriculture was collectivized, and the surviving part of the industrial base was abandoned or placed under state control. Cambodia had neither a currency nor a banking system.

Democratic Kampuchea's relations with [[Vietnam]] and [[Thailand]] worsened rapidly as a result of border clashes and ideological differences. While communist, the CPK was fiercely nationalistic, and most of its members who had lived in Vietnam were purged. Democratic Kampuchea established close ties with the [[People's Republic of China]], and the Cambodian-Vietnamese conflict became part of the Sino-[[Soviet Union|Soviet]] rivalry, with Moscow backing Vietnam. Border clashes worsened when the Democratic Kampuchea military attacked villages in Vietnam. The regime broke off relations with Hanoi in December 1977, protesting Vietnam's alleged attempt to create an Indochina Federation. In mid-1978, Vietnamese forces invaded Cambodia, advancing about {{convert|30|mi|km}} before the arrival of the rainy season.

The reasons for Chinese support of the CPK was to prevent a pan-Indochina movement, and maintain Chinese military superiority in the region. The Soviet Union supported a strong Vietnam to maintain a second front against China in case of hostilities and to prevent further Chinese expansion. Since Stalin's death, relations between Mao-controlled China and the Soviet Union had been lukewarm at best. In February to March 1979, China and Vietnam would fight the brief [[Sino-Vietnamese War]] over the issue.

In December 1978, Vietnam announced formation of the [[Kampuchean United Front for National Salvation]] (KUFNS) under [[Heng Samrin]], a former DK division commander. It was composed of Khmer Communists who had remained in Vietnam after 1975 and officials from the eastern sector&amp;mdash;like Heng Samrin and Hun Sen&amp;mdash;who had fled to Vietnam from Cambodia in 1978. In late December 1978, Vietnamese forces launched a full invasion of Cambodia, capturing Phnom Penh on January 7, 1979 and driving the remnants of Democratic Kampuchea's army westward toward Thailand.

Within the CPK, the Paris-educated leadership&amp;mdash;[[Pol Pot]], [[Ieng Sary]], [[Nuon Chea]], and [[Son Sen]]&amp;mdash;were in control. A new constitution in January 1976 established Democratic Kampuchea as a Communist People's Republic, and a 250-member Assembly of the Representatives of the People of Kampuchea (PRA) was selected in March to choose the collective leadership of a State Presidium, the chairman of which became the head of state.

Prince Sihanouk resigned as head of state on April 4. On April 14, after its first session, the PRA announced that [[Khieu Samphan]] would chair the State Presidium for a 5-year term. It also picked a 15-member cabinet headed by Pol Pot as prime minister. Prince Sihanouk was put under virtual house arrest.

===Social and cultural implications of the regime===
Thousands starved or died of disease during the evacuation and its aftermath. Many of those forced to evacuate the cities were resettled in newly created villages, which lacked food, agricultural implements, and medical care. Many who lived in cities had lost the skills necessary for survival in an agrarian environment. Thousands starved before the first harvest. Hunger and malnutrition&amp;mdash;bordering on starvation&amp;mdash;were constant during those years. Most military and civilian leaders of the former regime who failed to disguise their pasts were executed.
Some of the ethnicities in Cambodia, such as the [[Cham people|Cham]] suffered specific and targeted and violent persecutions. To the point of some international source referring to it as the &quot;Cham genocide&quot;. Entire families and towns were targeted and attacked with the goal of significantly diminishing their numbers and eventually eliminated them.[http://diacritics.org/2010/democratic-kampucheas-genocide-of-the-cham] 
Life in 'Democratic Kampuchea' was strict and brutal. In many areas of the country people were rounded up and executed for speaking a foreign language, wearing glasses, scavenging for food, and even crying for dead loved ones. Former businessmen and bureaucrats were hunted down and killed along with their entire families; the Khmer Rouge feared that they held beliefs that could lead them to oppose their regime. A few Khmer Rouge loyalists were even killed for failing to find enough 'counter-revolutionaries' to execute.

Modern research has located 20,000 mass graves from the Khmer Rouge era all over Cambodia. Various studies have estimated the death toll at between 740,000 and 3,000,000, most commonly between 1.4&amp;nbsp;million and 2.2&amp;nbsp;million, with perhaps half of those deaths being due to executions, and the rest from starvation and disease.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mekong.net_deaths&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Sharp|first=Bruce|title=Counting Hell: The Death Toll of the Khmer Rouge Regime in Cambodia|date = April 1, 2005|url = http://www.mekong.net/cambodia/deaths.htm|accessdate =July 5, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Department of State|U.S. State Department]]-funded Yale Cambodian Genocide Project estimates approximately 1.7 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cambodian Genocide Project&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yale.edu/cgp/ |title=Cambodian Genocide Program &amp;#124; Yale University |publisher=Yale.edu |date=July 18, 2007 |accessdate=July 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[R. J. Rummel]], an analyst of historical political killings, gives a figure of 2 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/SOD.CHAP4.HTM |title=Rummel, RJ, &quot;Statistics of Cambodian Democide: Estimates, Calculations, And Sources.&quot; |publisher=Hawaii.edu |accessdate=July 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A UN investigation reported 2–3 million dead, while UNICEF estimated 3 million had been killed.&lt;ref&gt;William Shawcross, ''The Quality of Mercy: Cambodia, Holocaust, and Modern Conscience'' (Touchstone, 1985), pp. 115–6.&lt;/ref&gt;  Demographic analysis by Patrick Heuveline suggests that between 1.17 and 3.42 million Cambodians were killed,&lt;ref name=&quot;Heuveline, Patrick 2001&quot;&gt;Heuveline, Patrick (2001). &quot;The Demographic Analysis of Mortality in Cambodia.&quot; In Forced Migration and Mortality, eds. Holly E. Reed and Charles B. Keely. Washington, D.C.: National Academy Press.&lt;/ref&gt; while Marek Sliwinski estimates that 1.8 million is a conservative figure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marek Sliwinski 1995&quot;&gt;Marek Sliwinski, ''Le Génocide Khmer Rouge: Une Analyse Démographique'' (L'Harmattan, 1995).&lt;/ref&gt;   Researcher Craig Etcheson of the Documentation Center of Cambodia suggests that the death toll was between 2 and 2.5 million, with a &quot;most likely&quot; figure of 2.2 million. After 5 years of researching grave sites, he concluded that &quot;these mass graves contain the remains of 1,386,734 victims of execution&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mekong.net_deaths&quot; /&gt;

==People's Republic of Kampuchea (1979–1993)==
{{Main|Cambodia under Vietnamese occupation (1979–1989)}}
On January 10, 1979, after the [[Vietnam|Vietnamese army]] and the [[KUFNS]] invaded Cambodia, the new [[People's Republic of Kampuchea]] (PRK) was established with Heng Samrin as head of state. [[Pol Pot]]'s [[Khmer Rouge]] forces retreated rapidly to the [[Thailand|Thai]] border. The Khmer Rouge and the PRK began a costly struggle that played into the hands of the larger powers [[China]], the [[United States]] and the [[Soviet Union]]. A civil war was imposed on impoverished Cambodia that displaced 600,000 Cambodians to refugee camps along the border between Thailand and Cambodia.&lt;ref&gt;David P. Chandler, A history of Cambodia, Westview Press; Allen &amp; Unwin, Boulder, Sydney, 1992&lt;/ref&gt;  The new regime killed tens of thousands of people.&lt;ref&gt;Craig Etcheson, ''After the Killing Fields'' (Praeger, 2005), pp24, 27.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Modern Cambodia#Peace efforts and the free elections|Peace efforts]] began in Paris in 1989 under the [[People's Republic of Kampuchea#Transition: State of Cambodia (1989 - 1993)|State of Cambodia]], culminating two years later in October 1991 in a comprehensive peace settlement. The [[United Nations]] was given a mandate to enforce a ceasefire, and deal with refugees and disarmament known as the [[United Nations Transitional Authority in Cambodia]] (UNTAC).&lt;ref name=&quot;USDOS3&quot;&gt;US Department of State. [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2732.htm Country Profile of Cambodia.]. Retrieved July 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ben Kiernan]] claimed that the US offered support to the Khmer Rouge after the Vietnamese invasion.&lt;ref name = &quot;Kiernan 30&quot;&gt;{{citation |separator= . |last= Kiernan |first= Ben |authorlink= Ben Kiernan |month= April |year= 2005 |chapter= The Cambodian Genocide and Imperial Culture |chapterurl= http://www.yale.edu/cgp/KiernanCambodia30thAnniversaryEssay.doc |title= 90 Years of Denial |publisher= ''[[Aztag (daily)|Aztag Daily]]'' (Beirut) &amp; ''[[Armenian Weekly]]'' (Boston) |pages= 20–21 |accessdate= 15 September 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other sources have disputed these claims,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DA163FF931A15757C0A96E958260 | work=The New York Times | title=Pol Pot's Evil Had Many Faces; China Acted Alone | date=April 22, 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nate Thayer, “Cambodia: Misperceptions and Peace,” Washington Quarterly, Spring 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen J. Morris, “Vietnam’s Vietnam,” Atlantic Monthly, January 1985, “ABC Flacks For Hanoi,” Wall Street Journal, April 26, 1990&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;“Skeletons in the Closet,” The New Republic, June 4, 1990&lt;/ref&gt; and described &quot;extensive fighting&quot; between the US-backed forces of the [[Khmer People's National Liberation Front]] and the Khmer Rouge.&lt;ref&gt;Far Eastern Economic Review, December 22, 1988.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern Cambodia (1993-present)==
{{Main|Modern Cambodia|l1=Modern Cambodia (1990&amp;ndash;present)}}
On October 23, 1991, the Paris Conference reconvened to sign a comprehensive settlement giving the UN full authority to supervise a cease-fire, repatriate the displaced Khmer along the border with Thailand, disarm and demobilize the factional armies, and prepare the country for free and fair elections. Prince Sihanouk, President of the Supreme National Council of Cambodia (SNC), and other members of the SNC returned to Phnom Penh in November 1991, to begin the resettlement process in Cambodia. The UN Advance Mission for Cambodia (UNAMIC) was deployed at the same time to maintain liaison among the factions and begin demining operations to expedite the repatriation of approximately 370,000 Cambodians from Thailand.

On March 16, 1992, the [[United Nations Transitional Authority in Cambodia|UN Transitional Authority in Cambodia]] (UNTAC) arrived in Cambodia to begin implementation of the UN Settlement Plan. The UN High Commissioner for Refugees began fullscale repatriation in March 1992. UNTAC grew into a 22,000-strong civilian and military peacekeeping force to conduct free and fair elections for a constituent assembly.

Over 4 million Cambodians (about 90% of eligible voters) participated in the May 1993 elections, although the Khmer Rouge or [[Party of Democratic Kampuchea]] (PDK), whose forces were never actually disarmed or demobilized, barred some people from participating. [[Norodom Ranariddh|Prince Ranariddh]]'s royalist [[Funcinpec|FUNCINPEC Party]] was the top vote recipient with 45.5% of the vote, followed by Hun Sen's [[Cambodian People's Party]] and the [[Buddhist Liberal Democratic Party]], respectively. FUNCINPEC then entered into a coalition with the other parties that had participated in the election. The parties represented in the 120-member assembly proceeded to draft and approve a new constitution, which was promulgated September 24, 1993. It established a multiparty liberal democracy in the framework of a constitutional monarchy, with the former Prince Sihanouk elevated to King. Prince Ranariddh and Hun Sen became First and Second Prime Ministers, respectively, in the Royal Cambodian Government (RGC). The constitution provides for a wide range of internationally recognized human rights.

On October 4, 2004, the Cambodian National Assembly ratified an agreement with the United Nations on the establishment of a tribunal to try senior leaders responsible for the atrocities committed by the Khmer Rouge. Donor countries have pledged the $43 million international share of the three-year tribunal budget, while the Cambodian government’s share of the budget is $13.3 million. The tribunal started trials of senior Khmer Rouge leaders in 2008.  Cambodia is also recovering from the land mines which were used heavily by the Khmer Rouge and Vietnamese; it will take approximately a decade to remove most of the land mines from Cambodia.

==See also==
{{portal|Cambodia}}
{{Wikipedia books|Cambodia}}
*[[Economic history of Cambodia]]
*[[History of Buddhism in Cambodia]]
*[[History of Asia]]
*[[Khmer Rouge]]
*[[List of kings of Cambodia]]
*[[List of Prime Ministers of Cambodia]]
*[[Military history of Cambodia]]
*[[Politics of Cambodia]]
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/133533.stm BBC article]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
*{{loc}} - [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/khtoc.html Cambodia]
*{{StateDept}} - [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2732.htm]

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|Cambodia}}
*State Department [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2732.htm#history Background Note: Cambodia]
*[http://www.un.org/Depts/dpko/dpko/co_mission/untacbackgr1.html Summary of UNTAC mission]
*[http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552701 History of Cambodian Civil War] from the [http://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552494 Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives]
*[http://countrystudies.us/cambodia/15.htm Cambodia under Sihanouk,1954-70]
*[http://siteresources.worldbank.org/DEC/Resources/DEWALQUE.PGS351-368.pdf Selective Mortality During the Khmer Rouge Period in Cambodia]
*[http://www.virginialawreview.org/content/pdfs/90/893.pdf Crossroads in Cambodia: The United Nation´s responsibility to withdrawn involvement from the establishment of a Cambodian Tribunal to prosecute the Khmer Rouge]
{{Cambodia topics}}
{{History of Asia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Cambodia}}
[[Category:History of Cambodia| ]]

[[ar:تاريخ كمبوديا]]
[[bg:История на Камбоджа]]
[[de:Geschichte Kambodschas]]
[[es:Historia de Camboya]]
[[eu:Kanbodiako historia]]
[[fr:Histoire du Cambodge]]
[[ko:캄보디아의 역사]]
[[io:Historio di Kambodja]]
[[it:Storia della Cambogia]]
[[he:היסטוריה של קמבודיה]]
[[lt:Kambodžos istorija]]
[[mk:Историја на Камбоџа]]
[[mr:कंबोडियाचा इतिहास]]
[[ja:カンボジアの歴史]]
[[no:Kambodsjas historie]]
[[km:ប្រវត្តិសាស្ត្រខ្មែរ]]
[[pt:História do Camboja]]
[[ru:История Камбоджи]]
[[fi:Kambodžan historia]]
[[sv:Kambodjas historia]]
[[th:ประวัติศาสตร์กัมพูชา]]
[[uk:Історія Камбоджі]]
[[vi:Lịch sử Campuchia]]
[[zh:柬埔寨历史]]</text>
      <sha1>sqy8781gckrc2n873pcjdvopzg5e0nv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
