<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Hong Kong</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1146443</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521019889</id>
      <parentid>520975638</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T07:59:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjensen</username>
        <id>313197</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/177.84.192.190|177.84.192.190]] ([[User talk:177.84.192.190|talk]]) to last version by Bodriscoll</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35760">{{History of Hong Kong}}
[[Hong Kong]] began as a coastal island geographically located off the southern coast of [[China]]. While pockets of settlements had taken place in the region                                              with archaeological findings dating back thousands of years, regular written records were not made until the engagement of [[History of China#Qin Dynasty: The Beginning of Imperial China|Imperial China]] and the [[British Colony]] in the territory. Starting out as a fishing village, salt production site and trading ground, it later evolved into a military port of strategic importance and eventually an international [[Financial Centre|financial centre]] that has the world's 6th highest [[Measures of national income and output#Gross National Product|GDP (PPP) per capita]], supporting 33% of the foreign capital flows into China.&lt;ref&gt;CIA gov. &quot;[https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/rankorder/2004rank.html CIA].&quot; ''HK GDP 2004.'' Retrieved on 6 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prehistoric era==
{{Main|Prehistoric Hong Kong}}
Archaeological findings suggesting human activity in Hong Kong date back over 30,000 years. Stone tools of the pre-historic people during the old stone age have been excavated in [[Sai Kung]] in [[Wong Tei Tung]]. The stone tools found in Sai Kung were perhaps from a stone tool making ground. Religious carvings on outlying islands and coastal areas have also been found, possibly related to [[Che people]] in [[Neolithic]]. The latest findings dating from the [[Paleolithic]] suggest that [[Wong Tei Tung]] (黃地峒) is one of the most ancient settlements in Hong Kong.

==Imperial China era (221 BC – 1911)==
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2008}}&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:CastlePeakMonastery.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The [[facade]] of the [[Tsing Shan Monastery]]]] --&gt;
{{Main|History of Hong Kong under Imperial China}}
{{seealso|Nanyue}}
The territory was incorporated into China during the [[Qin Dynasty]] (221 BC - 206 BC), and the area was firmly consolidated under [[Nanyue]] (203 BC - 111 BC.) Archaeological evidence indicates that the population increased since the [[Han Dynasty]] (206 BC - 220). In the 1950s, the [[Lei Cheng Uk Han Tomb Museum|tomb at Lei Cheng Uk]] from the [[Eastern Han Dynasty]] (25 – 220) was excavated and archaeologists began to investigate the possibility that salt production flourished in Hong Kong around 2000 years ago, although conclusive evidence has not been found.

[[Tai Po Hoi]], the sea of Tai Po, was a major [[pearl hunting]] harbour in China from the Han Dynasty through the [[Ming Dynasty]] (1368 to 1644), with activities peaking during the [[Southern Han]] (917 to 971).

During the [[Tang Dynasty]], the Guangdong region flourished as an international trading center. The ''Tuen Mun'' region in what is now Hong Kong's [[New Territories]] served as a port, naval base, salt production centre and later, base for the exploitation of pearls. [[Lantau Island]] was also a [[salt]] production centre, where the salt smugglers riots broke out against the government.

In 1276 during the [[Mongol]] invasion, the [[Southern Song Dynasty]] court moved to [[Fujian]], then to Lantau Island and later to today's [[Sung Wong Toi|Kowloon City]]. [[Emperor Bing of Song|Emperor Huaizong of Song]], the last Song Dynasty emperor, was enthroned at [[Mui Wo]] on Lantau Island on May 10, 1278 at the age of 8. This event is commemorated by the [[Sung Wong Toi]] in Kowloon. After his defeat at the [[Battle of Yamen]] on March 19, 1279, the child emperor committed suicide by drowning with his officials at Mount Ya (modern [[Yamen (town)|Yamen Town]] in Guangdong). [[Tung Chung]] valley, named after a hero who gave up his life for the emperor, is believed to have been one of the locations for his court. [[Hau Wong]], an official of the emperor is still worshipped in Hong Kong today.

During the Mongol period, Hong Kong saw its first population boom as Chinese refugees entered the area. The main reason for them to enter Hong Kong was because of [[wars]] and [[famines]], and some groups even went there to find jobs. Five [[Chinese clan|clans]] of [[Hou|Hau]] (侯), [[Tang Clan|Tang]] (鄧), [[Peng (surname)|Pang]] (彭) and [[Liao|Liu]] (廖) and [[Wen|Man]] (文) were [[Punti]] (Locals, 本地人) from [[Guangdong]], Fujian and [[Jiangxi]] in China. Despite the immigration and light development of agriculture, the area was hilly and relatively barren. People had to rely on salt, pearl and fishery trades to produce income. Some clans built [[walled villages of Hong Kong|walled villages]] to protect themselves from the threat of bandits, rival clans and wild animals. The famous Chinese [[pirate]] [[Cheung Po Tsai]] was legendary in Hong Kong.

The last dynasty in China, [[Qing Dynasty]], was also the last to come in contact with Hong Kong. As a military outpost and trading port, the Hong Kong territory  later gained the attention of the world.

==Colonial Hong Kong era (1800s – 1930s)==
{{Main|History of Hong Kong (1800s–1930s)|British Hong Kong}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:55%; float:left&quot;
! Date
! Treaty
! Result
|-valign=top
| 20 January 1841 || [[Convention of Chuenpee]] || Preliminary cession of [[Hong Kong Island]] to the United Kingdom
|-valign=top
| 29 August 1842 || [[Treaty of Nanjing]] || Cession of [[Hong Kong Island]], founded as a crown colony of the United Kingdom
|-valign=top
| 18 October 1860 || [[Convention of Beijing]] || Cession of [[Kowloon]] (south of [[Boundary Street]])
|-valign=top
| 1 July 1898 || [[Convention for the Extension of Hong Kong Territory|Second Convention of Beijing]] || Lease of the [[New Territories]] (including [[New Kowloon]])
|}
[[Image:Situationskärtchen von Kanton, Makao, Hongkong.jpg|thumb|right|140px|1888 German map of Hong Kong, [[Macau]], and [[Guangzhou|Canton (Guangzhou)]]]]
[[Image:Treaty of Peking1887.jpg|thumb|140px|left|The [[Treaty of Peking]]]]
By the early 19th century, the British Empire trade was heavily dependent upon the importation of tea from China. While the British exported to China luxury items like clocks and watches, there remained an overwhelming imbalance in trade. China developed a strong demand for silver, which was a difficult commodity  for the British to come by in large quantities. The counterbalance of trade came with exports of opium to China, opium being legal in Britain and grown in significant quantities in the UK, &lt;ref&gt; International Substance Abuse library &quot;http://www.drugtext.org/library/books/opiumpeople/opiuminthefens.html&quot; Retrieved on 26 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; and later in far greater quantities in India.

A Chinese commissioner [[Lin Zexu]] voiced to [[Queen Victoria]] the Qing state's opposition to the opium trade. It resulted in the [[First Opium War]], which led to British victories over China and the cession of Hong Kong to the United Kingdom via the enactment of the new treaties in 1842.

Christian missionaries founded numerous schools and churches in Hong Kong.  St. Stephen’s Anglican Church located in West Point was founded by the Church Missionary Society ([[Church Mission Society]])(CMS) in 1865. [[Ying Wa Girls' School]] (英華女學校) located in Mid-levels was founded by the [[London Missionary Society]] in 1900.  The [[Hong Kong College of Medicine for Chinese]] (香港華人西醫書院) was founded  by the [[London Missionary Society]] in 1887, with its first graduate (in 1892) being [[Sun Yat-sen]] (孫中山).  The [[Hong Kong College of Medicine for Chinese]] was the forerunner of the School of Medicine of the [[University of Hong Kong]], which started in 1911. 

Along with fellow students [[Yeung Hok-ling]], [[Chan Siu-bak]] and [[Yau Lit]], [[Sun Yat-sen]] started to promote the thought of overthrowing the Qing Government while he studied in the [[Hong Kong College of Medicine for Chinese]] (香港華人西醫書院).  The four students were known by the Qing Government as the [[Four Bandits]]. Sun attended To Tsai Church (道濟會堂, founded by the [[London Missionary Society]] in 1888) while he studied in this College.  Later Sun led the [[Chinese Revolution (1911)]], which changed China from an empire to a republic. 

In April 1899, the residents of [[Kam Tin]] (錦田) rebelled against the rule of the British colonial government. They defended themselves in [[Kat Hing Wai]] (吉慶圍), a walled village. After several unsuccessful attacks by the British troops, the iron gate was blasted open. The gate was then shipped to London for exhibition. Under the demand of the [[Tang Clan|Tang]] (鄧) clan in 1924, the gate was eventually returned in 1925 by the 16th governor, [[Reginald Edward Stubbs|Sir Reginald Stubbs]] (司徒拔爵士).

After the territorial settlements, the achievements of the era set the foundation for the culture and commerce in modern Hong Kong for years to come. The territory's commerce and industry transitioned in numerous ways: [[Hong Kong and China Gas Company]] to the [[Hongkong Electric|first electric company]]; [[Rickshaws]] transited to [[History of bus transport in Hong Kong|bus]], [[Hongkong and Yaumati Ferry|ferries]], [[Peak Tram|trams]] and [[Imperial Airways|airline]],&lt;ref&gt;Wiltshire, Trea. [First published 1987] (republished &amp; reduced 2003). Old Hong Kong - Volume One. Central, Hong Kong: Text Form Asia books Ltd. ISBN Volume One 962-7283-59-2&lt;/ref&gt; there was no shortage of improvements. Every industry went through major transformation and growth. Other vital establishments included changes in philosophy, starting with a western-style education with [[Frederick Stewart (colonial administrator)|Frederick Stewart]],&lt;ref&gt;Bickley, Gillian. [1997](1997). The Golden Needle: The Biography of Frederick Stewart (1836-1889). Hong Kong. ISBN 962-8027-08-5&lt;/ref&gt; which was a critical step in separating Hong Kong from mainland China during the political turmoil associated with the falling [[Qing dynasty]]. The monumental start of the financial powerhouse industry of the far east began with the [[The Hongkong and Shanghai Banking Corporation|first large scale bank]].&lt;ref&gt;
Lim, Patricia. [2002] (2002). Discovering Hong Hong's Cultural Heritage. Central, Hong Kong: Oxford University Press. ISBN Volume One 0-19-592723-0
&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same period there was the onslaught of the [[Third plague pandemic|Third Pandemic]] of [[Bubonic Plague]], which provided the pretext for [[racial segregation|racial zoning]] with the creation of [[Peak Reservation Ordinance]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Wordie
 | first = Jason
 | authorlink = 
 | coauthors =
 | title = Streets: Exploring Hong Kong Island
 | publisher = [[Hong Kong University Press]]
 | year = 2002
 | location = Hong Kong
 | pages =74–75
 | url =
 | doi =
 | id = 
 | isbn = 962-209-563-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and recognising the importance of the [[Tung Wah Hospital|first hospital]]. On the outbreak of World War I in 1914, fear of a possible attack on the colony led to an exodus of 60,000 Chinese. Statistically Hong Kong's population continued to boom in the following decades from 530,000 in 1916 to 725,000 in 1925. Nonetheless the crisis in mainland China in the 1920s and 1930s left Hong Kong vulnerable to a strategic invasion from [[Imperial Japan]].

==Japanese occupation era (1940s)==

{{Main|Battle of Hong Kong|Japanese Occupation of Hong Kong}}

Hong Kong was occupied by Japan from 23 December 1941 to 15 August 1945. The period, called '3 years and 8 months' halted the economy. The British, Canadians, Indians and the Hong Kong Volunteer Defence Forces resisted the Japanese invasion commanded by [[Sakai Takashi]] which started on 8 December 1941, eight hours after the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]]. Japan achieved air superiority on the first day of battle and the defensive forces were outnumbered. The British and the Indians retreated from the [[Gin Drinker's Line]] and consequently from [[Kowloon]] under heavy aerial bombardment and artillery barrage. Fierce fighting continued on [[Hong Kong Island]]; the only [[Reservoirs in Hong Kong|reservoir]] was lost. Canadian [[Winnipeg Grenadiers]] fought at the crucial [[Wong Nai Chong Gap]], which was the passage between the north and the secluded southern parts of the island.

On 25 December 1941 – which has gone down in history as ''Black Christmas'' to local people – British colonial officials headed by the [[Governor of Hong Kong]], [[Mark Aitchison Young]], surrendered in person at the Japanese headquarters on the third floor of the [[The Peninsula Hong Kong|Peninsula Hotel]]. [[Isogai Rensuke]] became the first Japanese governor of Hong Kong.

During the Japanese occupation, [[hyper-inflation]] and food rationing became the norm of daily lives. It became unlawful to own [[Hong Kong Dollar]]s, which were replaced by the [[Japanese Military Yen]], a currency without reserves issued by the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] administration. Some estimated that as many as 10,000 women were raped after Hong Kong's capture and a large number of suspected dissidents were executed.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} Philip Snow, a prominent historian of the period, said that the Japanese cut rations for civilians to conserve food for soldiers, usually to starvation levels and deported many to famine- and disease-ridden areas of the [[mainland China|mainland]]. Most of the repatriated had come to Hong Kong just a few years earlier to flee the terror of the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] in mainland China.

By the end of the war in 1945, Hong Kong had been liberated by joint British and Chinese troops. The population of Hong Kong had shrunk to 600,000; less than half of the pre-war population of 1.6 million due to scarcity of food and emigration. The [[Chinese Revolution (1949)|communist revolution in China]] in 1949 led to another population boom in Hong Kong. Thousands of [[refugee]]s emigrated from mainland China to Hong Kong, and made it an important [[entrepôt]] until the United Nations ordered a [[trade embargo]] on mainland China due to the [[Korean War]]. More refugees came during the [[Great Leap Forward]].

==Modern Hong Kong==

===Modern Hong Kong under British rule (1950s – 1997)===
===1950s===
[[Image:Hk1950.jpg|thumb|300px|Hong Kong, 1950s]]
{{Main|1950s in Hong Kong}}
Skills and capital brought by refugees of Mainland China, especially from Shanghai, along with a vast pool of cheap labour helped revive the economy. At the same time, many foreign firms relocated their offices from Shanghai to Hong Kong. Enjoying unprecedented growth, Hong Kong transformed from a territory of [[entrepôt|entrepôt trade]] to one of industry and manufacturing. The early industrial centres, where many of the workers spent the majority of their days, turned out anything that could be produced with small space from [[buttons]], [[artificial flowers]], [[umbrellas]], [[textile]], [[enamelware]], [[footwear]] to [[plastics]].

Large squatter camps developed throughout the territory providing homes for the massive and growing number of immigrants. The camps, however, posed a fire and health hazard, leading to disasters like the [[Shek Kip Mei]] fire. Governor [[Alexander Grantham]] responded with a &quot;multi storey buildings&quot; plan as a standard. It was the beginning of the high rise buildings. Conditions in public housing were very basic with several families sharing communal cooking facilities. Other aspects of life changed as traditional [[Cantonese opera]] gave way to [[cinema of Hong Kong|big screen cinemas]]. [[Tourism in Hong Kong|The tourism industry]] began to formalise. [[North Point]] was known as ''&quot;Little Shanghai&quot;'' (小上海), since in the minds of many, it has already become the replacement for the surrendered Shanghai in China.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wordie&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= Streets: Exploring Hong Kong Island|last= Wordie|first= Jason|authorlink= |coauthors= |year= 2002|publisher= [[Hong Kong University Press]]|location= Hong Kong|isbn= 962-209-563-1|page= |pages= |url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1960s===
[[Image:Hk1960c.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Hong Kong, 1960s]]
{{Main|1960s in Hong Kong}}
The manufacturing industry opened a new decade employing large sections of the population. The period is considered a turning point for Hong Kong's economy. The construction business was also revamped with new detailed guidelines for the first time since World War II. While Hong Kong started out with a low [[Gross Domestic Product|GDP]], it used the textile industry as the foundation to boost the economy. China's [[cultural revolution]] put Hong Kong on a new political stage. Events like the [[Hong Kong 1967 riots|1967 riot]] filled the streets with [[Improvised explosive device|home-made bombs]] and chaos. Bomb disposal experts from the police and the [[British military]] defused as many as 8,000 home-made bombs. One in every eight bombs was genuine.&lt;ref&gt;Wiltshire, Trea. [First published 1987] (republished &amp; reduced 2003). Old Hong Kong - Volume Three. Central, Hong Kong: Text Form Asia books Ltd. Page 12. ISBN Volume Three 962-7283-61-4&lt;/ref&gt;

Family values and Chinese tradition were challenged like never before as people spent more time in the factories than at home. Other features of the period included water shortages, long working hours coupled with extremely low wages. The [[H3N2|Hong Kong Flu]] of 1968 infected 15% of the population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starling&quot;&gt;Starling, Arthur. [2006] (2006) Plague, SARS, and the Story of Medicine in Hong Kong. HK University Press. ISBN 962-209-805-3&lt;/ref&gt; Amidst all the struggle, &quot;Made in Hong Kong&quot; went from a label that marked cheap low-grade products to a label that marked high-quality products.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley, Roger. [1997] (1997). Hong Kong: The Road to 1997 By Roger Buckley. Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-46979-1&lt;/ref&gt;

===1970s===
[[Image:Hong Kong 1978.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Hong Kong, 1970s]]
{{Main|1970s in Hong Kong}}

The rights of women and men to have equal pay and equal benefits for equal work were openly denied by the [[British Hong Kong]] Government up to the early 1970s. Leslie Wah-Leung Chung (鍾華亮, 1917-2009), President of the Hong Kong Chinese Civil Servants’ Association 香港政府華員會 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hkccsa.org/ Hong Kong Chinese Civil Servant's Association&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; (1965-68), contributed to the establishment of equal pay for men and women, including the right for married women to be permanent employees. Before this, the job status of a woman changed from permanent employee to temporary employee once she was married, thus losing the pension benefit.  Some of them even lost their jobs.  Since nurses were mostly women, this improvement of the rights of married women meant much to the Nursing profession. &lt;ref&gt;[http://m.torontosun.com/2012/04/06/celebrating-two-lives-well-lived Toronto SUN&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ottawasun.com/videos/celebrating-two-lives-well-lived/1550780688001 Celebrating two lives well lived : Featured OTT : Videos&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.torontosun.com/2012/04/07/life-love-and-service-recalled Life, love and service | Toronto &amp; GTA | News | Toronto Sun&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.singtao.ca/toronto/2012-04-08/city1333873203d3799095.html 曾參與二戰及香港保衛戰華裔夫婦.加美軍方墓前致最高敬意_星島日報_加拿大多倫多中文新聞網。 Canada Toronto Chinese newspaper&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://epapertor.worldjournal.com/showtor.html?apJi+mgEEOB3Bg1Fmi3TsQ==,MMV3f+xDb0CKYCyOu+WesQ== 世界日報電子報 - World Journal ePaper&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mingpaotor.com/htm/News/20120408/tfc1.htm 明報新聞網海外版 - 加東版(多倫多) - Canada Toronto Chinese Newspaper - 社區新聞&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt; Rebecca Chan Chung, Deborah Chung and Cecilia Ng Wong, &quot;Piloted to Serve&quot;, 2012 &lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[https://www.facebook.com/PilotedToServe Piloted to Serve | Facebook&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1970s saw the extension of [[Education in Hong Kong|government subsidised education]] from six years to nine years and the setup of Hong Kong's [[Country parks and conservation in Hong Kong|country parks system]].

The opening of the mainland Chinese market and rising salaries drove many manufacturers north. Hong Kong consolidated its position as a commercial and tourism centre in the South-East Asia region. High [[life expectancy]], literacy, per-capita income and other socioeconomic measures attest to Hong Kong's achievements over the last four decades of the 20th Century. Higher income also led to the introduction of the first [[private housing estates]] with [[Taikoo Shing]]. The period saw a boom in residential high rises, many of the people's homes became part of Hong Kong's skyline and scenery.

In 1974, [[MacLehose of Beoch|Murray McLehose]] founded [[Independent Commission Against Corruption of Hong Kong|ICAC]], the Independent Commission Against Corruption, in order to combat corruption within the [[Hong Kong Police Force|police force]]. The extent of corruption was so widespread that a mass police petition took place resisting prosecutions. Despite early opposition to the ICAC by the police force, Hong Kong was successful in its anti-corruption efforts, eventually becoming one of the [[Index of perception of corruption|least corrupt societies in the world]].

===1980s===
[[Image:hk1989a.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Hong Kong, 1980s]]
{{Main|1980s in Hong Kong}}
In 1982, the British Prime Minister, [[Margaret Thatcher]], hoped that the increasing openness of the PRC government and the [[Economic reform in the People's Republic of China|economic reform]] in the mainland would allow the continuation of British rule. The resulting meeting led to the signing of [[Sino-British Joint Declaration]] and the proposal of the [[One country, two systems]] concept by [[Deng Xiaoping]]. Political news dominated the media, while [[Economy of Hong Kong|real estate]] took a major upswing. The financial world was also rattled by panics, leading to waves of policy changes and [[Black Saturday (1983)|Black Saturday]]. Meanwhile Hong Kong was now recognised as one of the wealthiest representatives of the far east. At the same time, the warnings of the 1997 [[Transfer of the sovereignty of Hong Kong|handover]] raised [[emigration]] statistics to historic highs. Many left Hong Kong for the United States, Canada, the United Kingdom, Australia, and any other destination without any communist influence.

[[Cinema of Hong Kong|Hong Kong's Cinema]] enjoyed one paramount run that put it on the international map. Some of the biggest names included [[Jackie Chan]] and [[Chow Yun-fat]]. The music world also saw a new group of [[cantopop]] stars like [[Anita Mui]] and [[Leslie Cheung]]. But everything seemed to be overshadowed by an uncertainty of the future.

===1990s===
[[Image:HK1996t.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Hong Kong, 1990s]]
{{Main|1990s in Hong Kong|Transfer of the sovereignty of Hong Kong}}
On 4 April 1990, the [[Hong Kong Basic Law]] was officially accepted as the mini-constitution of the Hong Kong SAR after the handover. The pro-Beijing bloc welcomed the Basic Law, calling it the most democratic legal system to ever exist in the PRC. The pro-democratic bloc criticised it as not democratic enough. In July 1992, [[Chris Patten]] was appointed as the last British [[Governor of Hong Kong]]. Patten had been Chairman of the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] in the UK until he lost his parliamentary seat in the [[United Kingdom general election, 1992|general election]] earlier that year. Relations with the PRC government in Beijing became increasingly strained, as Patten introduced democratic reforms that increased the number of elected members in the [[Legislative Council of Hong Kong|Legislative Council]]. This caused considerable annoyance to the PRC, which saw this as a breach of the Basic Law. On 1 July 1997 Hong Kong was handed over to the People's Republic of China by the United Kingdom. The old Legislative Council, elected under Chris Patten's reforms, was replaced by the Provisional Legislative Council elected by a selection committee whose members were appointed by the PRC government. [[Tung Chee Hwa]], elected in December by a selection committee with members appointed by the PRC government, assumed duty as the first [[Chief Executive of Hong Kong]].

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! width=50% | Unchanged after 1997
! width=50% | Changed after 1997
|-valign=top
|
# The long-held British practice of no general elections by HK citizens remains unchanged.
# English is still taught in all schools. However, many schools teach in Mandarin in parallel with [[Cantonese]] and English.
# The border with the mainland continues to be patrolled as before.
# Hong Kong remains an individual member of various international organizations, such as the [[IOC]], [[APEC]] and [[WTO]].
# Hong Kong continues to negotiate and maintain its own aviation bilateral treaties with foreign countries and territories. Flights between Hong Kong and China mainland are treated as international flights (or more commonly known as inter-territorial flights in China mainland).
# Hong Kong SAR passport holders have easier access to countries in Europe and North America, while mainland citizens do not. Citizens in mainland China can apply for a visa to Hong Kong only from the PRC Government. Many former colonial citizens can still use [[British National (Overseas)]] and [[British citizen]] passports after 1997. (''Main article: [[British nationality law and Hong Kong]]'')
# It continues to have more political freedoms than the mainland China, including [[freedom of the press]].
# Motor vehicles in Hong Kong, unlike those in mainland China, continue to [[Driving on the left |drive on the left]].
# Electrical plugs ([[BS1363]]), TV transmissions ([[PAL|PAL-I]]) and many other technical standards from the United Kingdom are still utilised in Hong Kong. However, telephone companies ceased installing [[British Standard]] [[BS 6312]] telephone sockets in Hong Kong. HK also adopts the digital TV standard devised in mainland China. (''Main article: [[Technical standards in colonial Hong Kong]]'')
# Hong Kong retains a separate [[country calling code|international dialling code]] (+852) and [[Hong Kong telephone numbering plan|telephone numbering plan]] from that of the [[China telephone numbering plan|mainland]]. Calls between Hong Kong and the mainland still require international dialling.
# The former British military drill, marching and words of command in English continues in all disciplinary services including all civil organizations. The [[People's Liberation Army|PLA]] soldiers of the Chinese Garrison in Hong Kong have their own drills and Mandarin words of command.
# Hong Kong still uses the British date format.
# All statues of British monarchs like Queen Victoria and King George remain.
# Road names like &quot;Queen's Road&quot;, &quot;King's Road&quot; remain.
||
# The Chief Executive of Hong Kong is now [[Elections in Hong Kong|elected]] by a selection committee with 1200 members, who mainly are elected from among professional sectors and pro-Chinese business in Hong Kong.
# All public offices now fly the [[Flag of the People's Republic of China|flags of the PRC]] and the [[flag of Hong Kong|Hong Kong SAR]]. The [[Union Flag]] now flies only outside the [[British Consulate-General, Hong Kong|British Consulate-General]] and other British premises.
# [[Elizabeth II]]'s portrait disappeared from [[Hong Kong dollar|banknotes]], [[postage stamps]] and public offices. As of 2009, some pre-1997 coins and banknotes are still legal tenders and are in circulation.
# The 'Royal' title was dropped from almost all organizations that had been granted it, with the exception of the [[Royal Hong Kong Yacht Club]].
# Legal references to the 'Crown' were replaced by references to the 'State', and barristers who had been appointed [[Queen's Counsel]] were now to be known as [[Senior Counsel]].
# A local [[Orders, decorations, and medals of Hong Kong|honours system]] was introduced to replace the [[Orders, decorations, and medals of the United Kingdom|British honours system]], with the [[Grand Bauhinia Medal]] replacing the [[Order of the British Empire]].
# [[Public holidays in Hong Kong|Public holidays]] changed, with the [[Queen's Birthday|Queen's Official Birthday]] and other British-inspired occasions being replaced by PRC National Day and Hong Kong SAR Establishment Day.
# Many of the red British style [[pillar box]]es were removed from the streets of Hong Kong and replaced by green [[Hongkong Post]] boxes in the Singapore style. A few examples remain, but have been repainted.
# British citizens (without the right of abode) are no longer able to work in Hong Kong for one year without a visa; the policy was changed on 1 April 1997.
# Secondary schools must teach in Cantonese, unless approved by the Department of Education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Culture Shock! Hong Kong |last1=Wei |first1=Betty |last2=Li |first2=Elizabeth |year=2008 |publisher=Marshall Cavendish Editions |location=New York |isbn=978-0-7614-5482-3 |page=44}}&lt;/ref&gt; Secondary education will move away from the English model of five years secondary schooling plus two years of university matriculation to the Chinese model of three years of junior secondary plus another three years of senior secondary. University education extends from three years to four.
|-
|}

===Modern Hong Kong under China (post-1997 – present)===
[[Image:Hongkong Evening Skyline.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Hong Kong, 2000s]]

===2000s===
{{Main|2000s in Hong Kong}}
The new millennium signalled a series of events. A sizeable portion of the population that was previously against the handover found itself living with the adjustments. [[Hong Kong Basic Law Article 23|Article 23]] became a controversy, and led to marches in different parts of Hong Kong with as many as 750,000 people out of a population of approximately 6,800,000 at the time. The government also dealt with the [[Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome|SARS outbreak]] in 2003. A further health crisis, the [[Global spread of H5N1|Bird Flu Pandemic]] (H5N1) gained momentum from the late 90s, and led to the disposal of millions of chickens and other poultry. The slaughter put Hong Kong at the centre of global attention. At the same time, the economy tried to adjust fiscally. Within a short time, the political climate heated up and the Chief Executive position was challenged culturally, politically and managerially. [[Hong Kong Disneyland]] was also launched during this period.

Hong Kong's skyline has continued to evolve, with two new skyscrapers dominating. The 415 meter (1,362 foot) tall, 88 storey [[Two International Finance Centre]], completed in 2003, previously Hong Kong's tallest building, has been eclipsed by the 484 meter (1,588 foot) tall, 118 storey [[International Commerce Centre]] in West Kowloon, which was topped-out in 2010 and remains the tallest skyscraper in Hong Kong. Nine additional skyscrapers over 250 meters (825&amp;nbsp;feet) have also been completed during this time.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.emporis.com/en/wm/ci/bu/sk/li/?id=101300&amp;bt=2&amp;ht=3&amp;sro=0&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
[[Image:Flag of Hong Kong.svg|thumb|right|200px|[[Flag of Hong Kong]]]]
{{Portal|Hong Kong}}
* [[History of Colonial Hong Kong (1800s–1930s)]]
* [[History of China]] ([[Timeline of Chinese history|timeline]])
* [[History of the People's Republic of China]]
* [[British Empire]]
* [[British nationality law and Hong Kong]]
* [[Secretary of State for War and the Colonies]] (1801–1854)
* [[Secretary of State for the Colonies]] (1768–1782 and 1854–1966)
* [[Secretary of State for Commonwealth Affairs]] (1966–1968)
* [[Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs]] (since 1968)
* [[Governor of Hong Kong]]
* [[Declared monuments of Hong Kong]]
* [[Heritage conservation in Hong Kong]]
* [[Museums in Hong Kong]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* Butenhoff, Linda. ''Social movements and political reform in Hong Kong,'' Westport:  Praeger 1999, ISBN 0-275-96293-8
* Carroll, John M. ''A Concise History of Hong Kong'' (2007) 
* Clayton, Adam. ''Hong Kong since 1945: An Economic and Social History'' (2003)
* {{cite book|title=Forts and Pirates – A History of Hong Kong|first=Adam Yuen-chung|last=Lui|publisher=Hong Kong History Society|year=1990|isbn=962-7489-01-8|page=114}}
* {{cite book|first=Shuyong|last=Liu|first2=Wenjiong|last2=Wang|first3=Mingyu|last3=Chang|title=An Outline History of Hong Kong|publisher=Foreign Languages Press|year=1997|page=291|isbn=978-7-119-01946-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Ngo|first=Tak-Wing|title=Hong Kong's History: State and Society Under Colonial Rule|publisher=Routledge|date=1 August 1999|page=205|isbn=978-0-415-20868-0}}
* Snow, Philip. ''The Fall of Hong Kong: Britain, China, and the Japanese Occupation (2004) [http://www.amazon.com/Fall-Hong-Kong-Japanese-Occupation/dp/0300103735/  excerpt and text search]
* {{cite book|last=Tsang|first=Steve|title=A Modern History of Hong Kong|publisher=I. B. Tauris|year2007|isbn=978-1-84511-419-0}} [http://www.amazon.com/Modern-History-Hong-Kong/dp/1845114191/ excerpt and text search]
* {{cite book|last=Welsh|first=Frank|title=A Borrowed place: the history of Hong Kong|page=624|publisher=Kodansha International|year=1993|isbn=978-1-56836-002-7}}
{{refend}}
===Primary sources===
* {{cite book|last=Endacott|first=G. B|title=An Eastern Entrepot;: A Collection of Documents Illustrating the History of Hong Kong|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationary Office|year=1964|page=293|asin=B0007J07G6 }}
* {{cite book|last=Tsang|first=Steve|title=Government and Politics: A Documentary History of Hong Kong|publisher=Hong Kong University Press|year=1995|page=312|isbn=962-209-392-2}}

==External links==
{{wikibooks|History of Hong Kong}}
* [http://www.lcsd.gov.hk/CE/Museum/History/en/index.php Hong Kong Museum of History website]
* [http://www.asiasociety.org/speeches/wong.html A speech script on history of Hong Kong]
* [http://www.hku.hk/hkprehis/biblio2.htm Bibliography of Hong Kong Archaeology on the University of Hong Kong website]
* [http://www.stanfordprojects.co.uk/index.html &quot;Story of the Stanford family and the effect of the fall of Hong Kong in 1941.&quot;]
* [http://sunzi1.lib.hku.hk/bldho/ Basic Law Drafting History Online] -University of Hong Kong Libraries, Digital Initiatives
* [http://xml.lib.hku.hk/gsdl/db/oelawhk/search.shtml/ Historical Laws of Hong Kong Online] - University of Hong Kong Libraries, Digital Initiatives
* Sidney C. H. Cheung, [http://www.asa2000.anthropology.ac.uk/cheung/cheung.html Martyrs, Mystery and Memory Behind the Colonial Shift] - Anti-British resistance movement in 1899
* [http://www.howardscott.net/6/ImagesOf_HongKong_2002_2004/index.html Dr Howard M Scott &quot;Images of Hong Kong - Journal&quot;]
* [http://www.archive.org/details/cu31924071143832 Historical and statistical abstract of the colony of Hongkong (1907)]

{{History of Asia}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Hong Kong}}
[[Category:History of Hong Kong| ]]

{{Link GA|zh}}

[[de:Geschichte Hongkongs]]
[[es:Historia de Hong Kong]]
[[fr:Histoire de Hong Kong]]
[[gl:Historia urbana de Hong Kong]]
[[ko:홍콩의 역사]]
[[he:היסטוריה של הונג קונג]]
[[hu:Hongkong történelme]]
[[ms:Sejarah Hong Kong]]
[[ja:香港の歴史]]
[[ta:ஹொங்கொங் வரலாறு]]
[[vi:Lịch sử Hồng Kông]]
[[zh-yue:香港史]]
[[zh:香港歷史]]</text>
      <sha1>58ej6lbqvm0sfiv7x2y4j1h02rgqlrq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
