<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of colonialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7351463</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519552192</id>
      <parentid>509348420</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T11:21:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John of Reading</username>
        <id>11308236</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Typo/[[WP:AWB/GF|general]] fixing, replaced: de-jure → de jure using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42939">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}
[[File:Colonisation2.gif|thumb|400px|Territories colonized by the European powers and the United States since 1492]]
The historical phenomenon of [[colonisation]] is one that stretches around the globe and across time, including such disparate peoples as the [[Hittites]], the [[Incas]] and the [[British Empire|British]].  European colonialism, or [[imperialism]], began in the 15th century with the &quot;[[Age of Discovery]]&quot;, led by [[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese]] and [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] exploration of the [[Americas]], and the coasts of Africa, the Middle East, India, and [[East Asia]]. During the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, England, France and Holland established their own overseas empires, in direct competition with each other. The end of the eighteenth and early 19th century saw the first era of [[decolonization]] when most of the European colonies in the Americas gained their independence from their respective [[metropole]]s. Spain and Portugal were irreversibly weakened after the loss of their [[New World]] colonies, but the [[Kingdom of Great Britain]] (after the union of England, Wales, and Scotland), France and Holland turned their attention to the Old World, particularly South Africa, India and [[South East Asia]], where coastal enclaves had already been established. The industrialization of the nineteenth century led to what has been termed the era of [[New Imperialism]], when the pace of colonization rapidly accelerated, the height of which was the [[Scramble for Africa]], in which Belgium was a major and Germany a lesser participant. During the twentieth century, the overseas colonies of the losers of World War I were distributed amongst the victors as [[League of Nations mandate|mandates]], but it was not until the end of World War II that the second phase of decolonization began in earnest. In 1999 Portugal returned the last of Europe's colonies in Asia, [[Macau]], to China, ending an era that had lasted six hundred years.

== Portuguese and Spanish exploration and colonization ==
[[Image:ElminaCastle1668.jpg|thumb|[[Elmina Castle]], Ghana, one in a chain of about 50 fortified [[factory (trading post)|factories]] to enforce Portuguese trade rule along the coast. View from the sea in 1668.]]
[[Image:Spanish Empire Anachronous 0.PNG|thumb|The combined Spanish and Portuguese empires during the [[Iberian Union]] (1580-1640)]]
{{Main|Portuguese Empire|Portugal in the Age of Discovery|Spanish colonization of the Americas}}
European colonisation of both [[Eastern Hemisphere|Eastern]] and [[Western Hemisphere]]s has its roots in Portuguese exploration. There were financial and religious motives behind this exploration. By finding the source of the lucrative [[spice trade]], the Portuguese could reap its profits for themselves. They would also be able to probe the existence of the fabled Christian kingdom of [[Prester John]], with a view to encircling the [[Islamic]] [[Ottoman Empire]]. The first foothold outside of Europe was gained with the conquest of [[Ceuta]] in 1415. During the 15th century Portuguese sailors discovered the Atlantic islands of [[Madeira]], [[Azores]], and [[Cape Verde]], which were duly populated, and pressed progressively further along the west African coast until [[Bartolomeu Dias]] demonstrated it was possible to sail around Africa by rounding the [[Cape of Good Hope]] in 1488, paving the way for [[Vasco da Gama]] to reach India in 1498.

Portuguese successes led to Spanish financing of a mission by [[Christopher Columbus]] in 1492 to explore an alternative route to Asia, by sailing west. When Columbus eventually made landfall in what are now called the [[Bahamas]] he believed he had reached the coast of Japan, but had in fact &quot;discovered&quot; the peripheral islands of a new continent, the Americas.

After Columbus' return to Europe, competing Spanish and Portuguese claims to undiscovered lands were settled in 1494 with the [[Treaty of Tordesillas]], which divided the world outside of Europe in an exclusive duopoly between the Iberian kingdoms along a north-south meridian 370 leagues west of [[Cape Verde]]. Technically this meant that all of the Americas were open to Spanish colonization, but when [[Pedro Álvares Cabral]]'s voyage to India was blown off course and landfall made on the Brazilian coast, this accident of navigation and an inability at the time to accurately measure [[longitude]] meant that Brazil ended up within the Portuguese half.

The boundaries specified by the Treaty of Tordesillas were put to the test a second time when [[Ferdinand Magellan]], a Portuguese explorer sailing under the Spanish flag reached the Philippines in 1521. The two by now global empires, which had set out from opposing directions, had finally met on the other side of the world.

During the 16th century the Portuguese continued to press both eastwards and westwards into the Oceans. Towards Asia they made the first direct contact between Europeans and the peoples inhabiting present day countries such as [[Mozambique]], [[Madagascar]], [[Sri Lanka]], [[Malaysia]], [[Indonesia]], [[East Timor]] (1512), China, and finally Japan). In the opposite direction, the Portuguese colonized the huge territory that eventually became Brasil, and the Spanish [[conquistadores]] established the vast Viceroyalties of [[New Spain]] and [[Viceroyalty of Peru|Peru]], and later of [[Viceroyalty of the Río de la Plata|Río de la Plata]] (Argentina) and [[Viceroyalty of New Granada|New Granada]] (Colombia). In Asia, the Portuguese encountered ancient and well populated societies, and established a seaborne empire consisting of armed coastal trading posts along their trade routes (such as [[Goa]], [[Malacca]] and [[Macau]]), so they had relatively little cultural impact on the societies they forced their way into trading with. In the Western Hemisphere, the European colonization involved the emigration of large numbers of settlers, soldiers and administrators intent on owning land and exploiting the apparently primitive (as perceived by Old World standards) [[indigenous peoples of the Americas]]. The result was that the colonization of the New World was catastrophic: native peoples were no match for European technology, ruthlessness, or their diseases which decimated the [[Population history of American indigenous peoples|indigenous population]].

Spanish treatment of the indigenous populations provoked a fierce debate, the [[Valladolid Controversy]], over whether Indians possessed souls and if so, whether they were entitled to the basic rights of mankind. [[Bartolomé de Las Casas]], author of ''[[A Short Account of the Destruction of the Indies]]'', championed the cause of the native peoples, and was opposed by [[Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda|Sepúlveda]], who claimed [[Amerindians]] were &quot;natural slaves&quot;.

The [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic Church]] played a large role in Spanish and Portuguese overseas activities. The [[Dominican Order|Dominicans]], [[Jesuits]], and [[Franciscans]], notably [[Francis Xavier]] in Asia and [[Junípero Serra]] in North America, were particularly active in this endeavour. Many buildings erected by the Jesuits still stand, such as the [[Cathedral of Saint Paul in Macau]] and the [[La Santisima Trinidad de Paraná|Santisima Trinidad de Paraná]] in [[Paraguay]], the latter an example of the [[Jesuit Reductions]]. The Dominican and Franciscan buildings of [[Spanish missions in California|California's missions]] and [[Spanish missions in New Mexico|New Mexico's missions]] stand restored, such as [[Mission Santa Barbara]] in [[Santa Barbara, California]] and [[San Francisco de Asis Mission Church]] in [[Ranchos de Taos, New Mexico]].

[[File:Colonization of the Americas 1750.PNG|thumb|200px|Map indicating the territories colonized by the European powers over the Americas in 1750, (mainly Spain, Portugal and France at the time.]]
As characteristically happens in any colonialism, European or not, previous or subsequent, both Spain and Portugal profited handsomely from their new found overseas colonies: the Spanish from gold and silver from mines such as [[Potosí]] and [[Zacatecas, Zacatecas|Zacateca]] in [[New Spain]], the Portuguese from the huge markups they enjoyed as trade intermediaries, particarlarly during the [[Namban]] [[Japanese history|Japan]] trade period. The influx of precious metals to the Spanish monarchy's coffers allowed it to finance costly [[religious war]]s in Europe which ultimately proved its undoing: the supply of metals was not infinite and the large inflow caused inflation and debt.

===Northern European challenges to the Iberian hegemony===
It was not long before the exclusivity of Iberian claims to the Americas was challenged by other up and coming European powers, primarily the Netherlands, France and England: the view taken by the rulers of these nations is epitomized by the quotation attributed to [[Francis I of France]] demanding to be shown the clause in Adam's will excluding his authority from the New World.

This challenge initially took the form of piratical attacks (such as those by [[Francis Drake]]) on Spanish treasure fleets or coastal settlements, but later the Northern European countries began establishing settlements of their own, primarily in areas that were outside of Spanish interests, such as what is now the eastern seaboard of the U.S. and Canada, or islands in the Caribbean, such as [[Aruba]], [[Martinique]] and [[Barbados]], that had been abandoned by the Spanish in favour of the mainland and larger islands.

Whereas Spanish colonialism was based on the religious conversion and exploitation of local populations via [[encomienda]]s (many Spaniards emigrated to the Americas to elevate their social status, and were not interested in manual labour), Northern European colonialism was bolstered by those emigrating for religious reasons (for example, the [[Mayflower]] voyage). The motive for emigration was not to become an aristocrat or to spread one's faith but to start a new society afresh, structured according to the colonists wishes. The most populous emigration of the seventeenth century was that of the English, who after a series of wars with the Dutch and French came to dominate the [[British North America|eastern coast of the present day U.S. and Canada]].

However, the English, French and Dutch were no more averse to making a profit than the Spanish and Portuguese, and whilst their areas of settlement in the Americas proved to be devoid of the precious metals found by the Spanish, trade in other commodities and products that could be sold at massive profit in Europe provided another reason for crossing the Atlantic, in particular furs from Canada, tobacco and cotton grown in [[Virginia]] and sugar in the islands of the Caribbean and Brazil. Due to the massive depletion of indigenous labour, plantation owners had to look elsewhere for manpower for these labour-intensive crops. They turned to the centuries old slave trade of west Africa and began transporting Africans across the Atlantic on a massive scale – historians estimate that the [[Atlantic slave trade]] brought between 10 and 12 million African (mostly black skinned) slaves to the New World. The islands of the Caribbean soon came to be populated by slaves of African descent, ruled over by a white minority of plantation owners interested in making a fortune and then returning to their home country to spend it.

===Role of companies in early colonialism===
From its very outset, Western colonialism was operated as a joint public-private venture. Columbus' voyages to the Americas were partially funded by Italian investors, but whereas the Spanish state maintained a tight reign on trade with its colonies (by law, the colonies could only trade with one designated port in the mother country and treasure was brought back in special [[Spanish treasure fleet|convoys]]), the English, French and Dutch granted what were effectively trade [[monopolies]] to [[Joint stock company|joint-stock companies]] such as the [[British East India Company|East India Companies]] and the [[Hudson's Bay Company]]. [[Russian Empire|Imperial Russia]] had no State sponsored expeditions or colonization in the Americas, but did charter the first Russian joint-stock commercial enterprise, the [[Russian America Company]], which did sponsor those activities in its territories.

===European colonies in India===
[[Image:Clive.jpg|thumb|[[Lord Clive]] meeting with [[Mir Jafar]] at the [[Battle of Plassey]] in 1757, painted by [[Francis Hayman]]]]
{{Main|European colonies in India}}

In May 1498, the [[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese]] set foot in [[Kozhikode]] in [[Kerala]]. Rivalry among reigning European powers saw the entry of the [[Dutch Empire|Dutch]], [[Colonial empire of the Kingdom of England|English]], [[French India|French]], [[Danish India|Danish]] and others. The kingdoms of [[History of India|India]] were gradually taken over by the Europeans and indirectly controlled by puppet rulers. In 1600, Queen [[Elizabeth I]] accorded a [[charter]], forming the [[East India Company]] to trade with India and eastern Asia. The English landed in India in [[Surat]] in 1612. By the nineteenth century, they had assumed [[British India|direct]] and [[Princely states|indirect]] control over most of India.

==Independence in the Americas (1770–1820)==

During the five decades following 1770, Britain, France, Spain and Portugal lost many of their possessions in the Americas.

===Britain and the Thirteen Colonies===

{{Main|Thirteen Colonies|American Revolutionary War|United States Declaration of Independence}}

After the conclusion of the [[Seven Years' War]] in 1763, Britain had emerged as the world's dominant power, but found itself mired in debt and struggling to finance the Navy and Army necessary to maintain a global empire. The [[Parliament of Great Britain|British Parliament]]'s attempt to raise taxes from North American colonists raised fears among the Americans that their rights as &quot;Englishmen&quot;, and particularly their rights of self-government, were in danger. A series of disputes with Parliament over taxation led first to informal [[committees of correspondence]] among the colonies, then to coordinated protest and resistance. A [[standing army]] was formed by the [[Thirteen Colonies|United Colonies]], and [[United States Declaration of Independence|independence was declared]]  by the Second [[Continental Congress]] on 4 July 1776. The [[American War of Independence]] continued until 1783, when the [[Treaty of Paris (1783)|Treaty of Paris]] was signed. Britain recognised the sovereignty of the United States over the territory bounded by the British possessions to the North, [[Florida]] to the South, and the Mississippi River to the west.

===France and the Haitian Revolution (1791–1804)===
The [[Haïtian Revolution]], a slave revolt led by [[Toussaint L'Ouverture]] in the French colony of '''[[Saint-Domingue]]''', established [[Haïti]] as a free, black [[republic]], the first of its kind. Haiti became the second independent nation that was a former European colony in the [[Western Hemisphere]] after the United States. Africans and people of African ancestry freed themselves from slavery and colonization by taking advantage of the conflict among whites over how to implement the reforms of the [[French Revolution]] in this slave society. Although independence was declared in 1804, it was not until 1825 that it was formally recognized by [[King Charles X of France]].

===Spain and the Wars of Independence in Latin America===
[[Image:Independence in the Americas c.1830.png|thumb|Independent republics in the Americas, c. 1830.]]
{{Main|Spanish American wars of independence|Latin American revolutions}}
The gradual decline of Spain as an imperial power throughout the 17th century was hastened by the [[War of the Spanish Succession]] (1701–14), as a result of which it lost its European imperial possessions. The death knell for the Spanish Empire in the Americas was Napoleon's invasion of the Iberian peninsula in 1808. With the installation of his brother [[Joseph Bonaparte|Joseph]] on the Spanish throne, the main tie between the metropole and its American colonies, the Spanish monarchy, had been cut, leading the colonists to question their continued subordination to a declining and distant country.

With an eye on the events of the American Revolution forty years earlier, revolutionary leaders began bloody wars of independence against Spain, whose armies were ultimately unable to maintain control. By 1831, Spain had been ejected from the mainland of the American continent, leaving a collection of independent republics that stretched from Chile and Argentina in the south to Mexico in the north. Spain's colonial possessions were reduced to [[Cuba]], [[Puerto Rico]], the Philippines and a number of small islands in the Pacific, all of which she was to lose to the United States in the 1889 [[Spanish-American War]] or sell to Germany shortly thereafter.

===Portugal and Brazil===
Brazil was the only country in Latin America to gain its independence without bloodshed. The invasion of Portugal by [[Napoleon]] in 1808 had forced King [[João VI]] to escape to Brazil and establish his court in Rio de Janeiro. For thirteen years, Portugal was ruled from Brazil (the only instance of such a reversal of roles between colony and metropole) until his return to Portugal in 1821. His son, [[Pedro I of Brazil|Dom Pedro]], was left in charge of Brazil and in 1822 he declared independence from Portugal and himself the Emperor of Brazil. Unlike Spain's former colonies which had abandoned the monarchy in favour of republicanism, Brazil therefore retained its links with its monarchy, the [[House of Braganza]].

==India==
{{Main|Colonial India}}
[[Vasco da Gama]]'s maritime success to discover for Europeans a new sea route to India in 1498 paved the way for direct Indo-European commerce.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1497degama.html| title = Vasco da Gama: Round Africa to India, 1497–1498 CE| accessdate = 7 May 2007| month = June | year = 1998 | work = Internet Modern History Sourcebook| publisher = Paul Halsall }} From: Oliver J. Thatcher, ed., The Library of Original Sources (Milwaukee: University Research Extension Co., 1907), Vol. V: 9th to 16th Centuries, pp. 26–40.&lt;/ref&gt; The Portuguese soon set up trading-posts in [[Goa]], [[Daman District, India|Daman]], [[Diu, India|Diu]] and [[Bombay]]. The next to arrive were the [[Netherland|Dutch]], the [[British Empire|British]]—who set up a trading-post in the west-coast port of [[Surat]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.indianchild.com/history_of_india.htm| title = Indian History – Important events: History of India. An overview| accessdate = 7 May 2007| work = History of India| publisher = Indianchild.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 1619—and the French. The internal conflicts among Indian Kingdoms gave opportunities to the European traders to gradually establish political influence and appropriate lands. Although these continental European powers were to control various regions of southern and eastern India during the ensuing century, they would eventually lose all their territories in India to the British islanders, with the exception of the French outposts of [[Pondicherry]] and [[Chandernagore]], the Dutch port in [[Travancore]], and the Portuguese colonies of [[Goa]], [[Daman, Daman and Diu|Daman]], and [[Diu, India|Diu]].

===The British raj===
{{Main|British Raj}}
[[File:BritishIndianEmpireandEnvirons2.jpg|thumb|left|The [[British Indian Empire]] and surrounding countries in 1909]]
The [[East India Company|English East India Company]] had been given permission by the Mughal emperor Jahangir in 1617 to trade in India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/india/1617englandindies.html| title = The Great Moghul Jahangir: Letter to James I, King of England, 1617 A.D.| accessdate = 7 May 2007| month = June | year = 1998
| work = Indian History Sourcebook: England, India, and The East Indies, 1617 CE| publisher = Internet Indian History Sourcebook, Paul Halsall}} From: [[James Harvey Robinson]], ed., Readings in European History, 2 Vols. (Boston: Ginn and Co., 1904–1906), Vol. II: From the opening of the Protestant Revolt to the Present Day, pp. 333–335.&lt;/ref&gt; Gradually the Company's increasing influence led the ''[[de jure]]'' Mughal emperor [[Farrukh Siyar]] to grant them ''dastaks'' or permits for duty free trade in [[Bengal]] in 1717.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.calcuttaweb.com/history.shtml| title =  KOLKATA (CALCUTTA) : HISTORY | accessdate = 7 May 2007| publisher = Calcuttaweb.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Nawab of Bengal]] [[Siraj Ud Daulah]], the ''[[de facto]]'' ruler of the Bengal province, opposed British attempts to use these permits. This led to the [[Battle of Plassey]] in 1757, in which the [[Presidency armies|armies]] of the East India Company, led by [[Robert Clive]], defeated the Nawab's forces. This was the first political foothold with territorial implications that the British had acquired in India. Clive was appointed by the Company as its first Governor of Bengal in 1757.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.historyofwar.org/articles/people_cliveofindia.html| title = Robert Clive, Baron Clive, 'Clive of India', 1725–1774| accessdate = 7 May 2007| last = Rickard| first = J.| date = 1 November 2000| work = Military History Encyclopedia on the Web| publisher = historyofwar.org
}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was combined with British victories over the French at [[Siege of Madras|Madras]], [[Battle of Wandiwash|Wandiwash]] and [[Siege of Pondicherry|Pondicherry]] that, along with wider [[Great Britain in the Seven Years War|British successes during the Seven Years War]], reduced French influence in India. After the [[Battle of Buxar]] in 1764, the Company acquired the civil rights of administration in Bengal from the Mughal Emperor [[Shah Alam II]]; it marked the beginning of its formal rule, which was to engulf eventually most of India and extinguish the Moghul rule and dynasty itself in less than a century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.lse.ac.uk/collections/economicHistory/GEHN/GEHN%20PDF/Transformation%20from%20a%20Pre-Colonial%20-%20Om%20Prakash.pdf
| title = The Transformation from a Pre-Colonial to a Colonial Order: The Case of India
| accessdate = 7 May 2007| last = Prakash| first = Om| format = PDF| work = Global Economic History Network | publisher = Economic History Department, [[London School of Economics]]| pages = 3–40}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The East India Company monopolized the trade of Bengal. They introduced a land taxation system called the [[Permanent Settlement]] which introduced a [[feudalism|feudal]]-like structurea (See ''[[Zamindar]]'') in Bengal. By the 1850s, the East India Company controlled most of the Indian sub-continent, which included present-day [[Pakistan]] and [[Bangladesh]]. Their policy was sometimes summed up as [[Divide and Rule]], taking advantage of the enmity festering between various princely states and social and religious groups.

The first major movement against the British Company's high handed rule resulted in the [[Indian Rebellion of 1857]], also known as the &quot;Indian Mutiny&quot; or &quot;Sepoy Mutiny&quot; or the &quot;First War of Independence&quot;. After a year of turmoil, and reinforcement of the East India Company's troops with British soldiers, the Company overcame the rebellion. The nominal leader of the uprising, the last Mughal emperor [[Bahadur Shah Zafar]], was exiled to Burma, his children were beheaded and the Moghul line abolished. In the aftermath all power was transferred from the East India Company to the [[British Crown]], which began to administer most of India as a colony; the Company's lands were controlled directly and the rest through the rulers of what it called the [[Princely states]]. There were 565 princely states when the Indian subcontinent gained independence from Britain in August 1947.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/1762146.stm Kashmir: The origins of the dispute], BBC News, 16 January 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[British Raj]], [[famine in India|famines in India]], often attributed to failed government policies, were some of the worst ever recorded, including the [[Great Famine of 1876–78]], in which 6.1 million to 10.3 million people died&lt;ref name=mikedavis&gt;Davis, Mike. Late Victorian Holocausts. 1. Verso, 2000. ISBN 1-85984-739-0 pg 7&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Indian famine of 1899–1900]], in which 1.25 to 10 million people died.&lt;ref name=mikedavis&gt;Davis, Mike. Late Victorian Holocausts. 1. Verso, 2000. ISBN 1-85984-739-0 pg 173&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Third plague pandemic|Third Plague Pandemic]] started in China in the middle of the 19th century, spreading plague to all inhabited
continents and killing 10 million people in India alone.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.who.int/vaccine_research/diseases/zoonotic/en/index4.html Plague]. World Health Organization.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite persistent diseases and famines, however, the population of the [[Indian subcontinent]], which stood at about 125 million in 1750, had reached 389 million by 1941.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.petersoninstitute.org/publications/chapters_preview/98/1iie2806.pdf Reintegrating India with the World Economy]. ''Peterson Institute for International Economics.''&lt;/ref&gt;

==New Imperialism (1870–1914)==
{{Main|The Second European colonization wave (19th-20th century)}}
[[File:Imperialism2.png|thumb|right|Empires of the world in 1910]]

The policy and ideology of European colonial expansion between the 1870s and the outbreak of World War I in 1914 are often characterised as the &quot;New Imperialism&quot;. The period is distinguished by an unprecedented pursuit of what has been termed &quot;empire for empire's sake&quot;, aggressive competition for overseas territorial acquisitions and the emergence in colonising countries of doctrines of racial superiority which denied the fitness of subjugated peoples for self-government.

During this period, Europe's powers added nearly 8,880,000 square miles (23,000,000&amp;nbsp;km²) to their overseas colonial possessions. As it was mostly unoccupied by the Western powers as late as the 1880s, Africa became the primary target of the &quot;new&quot; imperialist expansion (known as [[The Scramble for Africa]]), although conquest took place also in other areas — notably south-east Asia and the East Asian seaboard, where Japan joined the European powers' scramble for territory.

The [[Berlin Conference]] (1884–1885) mediated the imperial competition among Britain, France and Germany, defining &quot;effective occupation&quot; as the criterion for international recognition of colonial claims and codifying the imposition of [[direct rule]], accomplished usually through armed force.

A decade later, rival imperialisms would collide in the 1898 [[Fashoda Incident]], during which war between France and Britain was barely avoided. This fear led to new alliances, and in 1904 the ''[[Entente Cordiale]]'' was signed between both powers. Imperialistic rivalry between the European powers was a main cause of the triggering of World War I in 1914.

In Germany, rising [[pan-germanism]] was coupled to imperialism in the ''[[Alldeutsche Verband]]'' (&quot;Pangermanic League&quot;), which argued that Britain's world power position gave the British unfair advantages on international markets, thus limiting Germany's economic growth and threatening its security.

===The scramble for Africa===
[[Image:Colonial Africa 1913 map.svg|thumb|European territories in Africa, 1914, following the [[Scramble for Africa]].]]
{{Main|Scramble for Africa}}

Many European statesmen and industrialists wanted to accelerate the [[Scramble for Africa]], securing colonies before they strictly needed them. The champion of [[Realpolitik]], [[Otto von Bismarck|Bismarck]] thus pushed a [[Weltpolitik]] vision (&quot;World Politic&quot;), which considered the colonization as a necessity for the emerging German power. German colonies in [[Togo]]land, [[Samoa]], [[South-West Africa]] and [[New Guinea]] had corporate commercial roots, while the equivalent German-dominated areas in [[East Africa]] and China owed more to political motives. The British also took an interest in Africa, using the East Africa company to take over Kenya and Uganda. The British crown formally took over in 1895 and renamed the area the East Africa Protectorate.

[[Leopold II of Belgium]] personally owned the [[Congo Free State]] from 1885 to 1908, while the [[Dutch colonial empire|Dutch]] had the [[Dutch East Indies]].

In the same manner, [[Italian Empire|Italy]] tried to conquer its &quot;[[place in the sun]]&quot;, acquiring [[Somaliland]] in 1899-90, [[Eritrea]] and 1899, and, taking advantage of the &quot;[[Sick man of Europe]]&quot;, the [[Ottoman Empire]], also conquered [[Tripolitania]] and [[Cyrenaica]] (modern [[Libya]]) with the 1911 [[Italo-Turkish War|Treaty of Lausanne]]. The conquest of [[Ethiopia]], which had remained the last African independent territory, had to wait till the [[Second Italo-Abyssinian War]] in 1935–36 (the [[First Italo–Ethiopian War]] in 1895–96 had ended in defeat for Italy).

The [[Portuguese colonial empire|Portuguese]] and [[Spanish colonial empire]] were smaller, mostly legacies of past colonization. Most of their colonies had acquired independence during the [[Latin American wars of independence|Latin American revolutions]] at the beginning of the nineteenth century.

===Imperialism in Asia===
{{Main|Imperialism in Asia}}

In Asia, the [[Great Game]], which lasted from 1813 to 1907, opposed the British Empire against [[Imperial Russia]] for supremacy in [[central Asia]]. [[History of China|China]] was opened to Western influence starting with the [[First Opium War|First]] and [[Second Opium War]]s (1839–1842; 1856–1860). After the visits of [[Matthew Perry (naval officer)|Commodore Matthew Perry]] in 1852–1854, Japan opened itself to the Western world during the [[Meiji Era]] (1868–1912).

The above basically concerns India and China.

But other or the same forms of Imperialism, that should not be overlooked, were in action in Burma, Indonesia (Netherlands East Indies), Malaya and the Philippines.

{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

==Inter-War Period (1918–1939)==
{{Further|Aftermath of World War I|League of Nations Mandate}}

The colonial map was redrawn following the defeat of Germany and the [[Ottoman Empire]] after the [[first World War]] (1914–18). Colonies from the defeated empires were transferred to the newly founded [[League of Nations]], which itself redistributed it to the victorious powers as [[League of Nations Mandate|&quot;mandates&quot;]].

The secret 1916 [[Sykes-Picot Agreement]] partitioned the Middle East between Britain and France, and the 1917 [[Balfour Declaration, 1917|Balfour Declaration]] promised to the international [[Zionism|Zionist]] movement their support in creating a Jewish homeland in Palestine, later to become the state of [[Israel]]. French mandates included [[French mandate of Syria|Syria]] and [[French mandate of Lebanon|Lebanon]], whilst the British were handed [[British mandate of Iraq|Iraq]] and [[British mandate of Palestine|Palestine]]. The bulk of the Arabian peninsula became the independent Kingdom of [[Saudi Arabia]] in 1922. The discovery of the world's largest easily accessible crude oil deposits led to an influx of Western [[oil companies]] that dominated the region's economies until the 1970s, and making the emirs of the oil states immensely rich, enabling them to consolidate their hold on power and giving them a stake in preserving Western hegemony over the region.

During the 1920 and 1930s [[Iraq]], [[Syria]] and [[Egypt]] moved towards independence, although the British and French did not formally depart the region until they were forced to do so after World War II.

===Japanese imperialism===
{{Main|Japanese imperialism|Imperialism in Asia}}

After being closed for centuries to Western influence, Japan opened itself to the West during the [[Meiji Era]] (1868–1912), characterized by swift modernization and borrowings from European culture (in law, science, etc.) This, in turn, helped make Japan the modern power that it is now, which was symbolized as soon as the 1904–1905 [[Russo-Japanese War]]: this war marked the first victory of an Asian people against a European imperial power, and led to widespread fears among European populations (first appearance of the &quot;[[Yellow Peril]]&quot;). During the first part of the twentieth century, while China was still victim of various European imperialisms, Japan became an imperialist power, conquering what it called a &quot;[[Greater East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere]]&quot;.

Japan's encroachment on Korea began with the [[Japan–Korea Treaty of 1876]] with the [[Joseon Dynasty]] of Korea, increased with the 1895 assassination of [[Empress Myeongseong]] and the 1905 [[Japan–Korea Treaty of 1905]], and was completed with the illicit 1910 [[Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty]]. In 1910, Korea was formally annexed to the [[Japanese Empire]]. The [[Korea under Japanese rule|Japanese colonization of Korea]] was particularly brutal, even by twentieth century standards. This brutal colonization included the use of Korean &quot;[[comfort women]]&quot; who were forced to serve as sex slaves in Japanese Army brothels.

In 1931 Japanese army units based in [[Manchuria]] seized control of the region; full-scale war with China followed in 1937, drawing Japan toward an overambitious bid for Asian hegemony (Greater East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere), which ultimately led to defeat and the loss of all its overseas territories after World War II (see Japanese expansionism and Japanese nationalism). As in Korea, the Japanese treatment of the Chinese people was particularly brutal as exemplified by the Nanjing Massacre.
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

==Decolonization (1945–97)==
[[Image:Africa independence dates.svg|thumb|Dates of [[Decolonization of Africa|independence of African countries]].]]
{{Main|Decolonization}}

Anticolonialist movements had begun to gain momentum after the close of World War I, which had seen colonial troops fight alongside those of the metropole, and U.S. President [[Woodrow Wilson]]'s speech on the [[Fourteen Points]]. However, it was not until the end of World War II that they fully mobilised. British Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]] and U.S. President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]'s 1941 [[Atlantic Charter]] declared that the signatories would &quot;respect the right of all peoples to choose the form of government under which they will live&quot;. Though Churchill subsequently claimed this applied only to those countries under Nazi occupation, rather than the British Empire, the words were not so easily retracted: for example, the legislative assembly of Britain's most important colony, India, passed a resolution stating that the Charter should apply to it too.

To nationalist movements, it was hypocritical and morally indefensible for colonial governments to expect their colonies to fight side by side with them in a struggle against the racist ideologies of [[Nazism]] and [[fascism]], yet at the same time expect to return to the white supremacy of the status [[History of the Southern United States#Antebellum Era .281781.E2.80.931860.29|ante bellum]], once hostilities had ceased. Moreover, Roosevelt and the American public were firmly of the mind that they were not, as ''[[Life magazine]]'' put it in 1942, &quot;fighting ... to hold the British Empire together&quot;.

In 1945, the United Nations (UN) was founded when 50 nations signed the [[Charter of the United Nations|UN Charter]], which included a statement of its basis in the respect for the principle of equal rights and self-determination of peoples. In 1952, demographer [[Alfred Sauvy]] coined the term &quot;[[Third World]]&quot; in reference to the French [[Third Estate]]. The expression distinguished nations that aligned themselves with neither the [[Western World|West]] nor with the [[Soviet Bloc]] during the [[Cold War]]. In the following decades, decolonization would strengthen this group which began to be represented at the United Nations. The Third World's first international move was the [[Bandung Conference|1955 Bandung Conference]], led by [[Jawaharlal Nehru]] for [[History of India|India]], [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]] for [[History of Egypt|Egypt]] and [[Josip Broz Tito]] for [[History of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]. The Conference, which gathered 29 countries representing over half the world's population, led to the creation of the [[Non-Aligned Movement]] in 1961.

Although the U.S. had first opposed itself to colonial powers, in particular during the 1956 [[Suez crisis]] between Egypt, France, the UK and Israel, the Cold War concerns about Soviet influence in the Third World caused it to downplay its advocacy of popular sovereignty and decolonization. France thus had a free hand in the [[First Indochina War]] (1946–54) and in the [[Algerian war of independence]] (1954–62), where [[torture]] techniques were heavily employed (the Algerian war would become a military model of [[counter-insurgency]] [[military tactics|tactics]], and has been studied ever since in military schools throughout the world). Furthermore, attempts such as [[Mossadegh]]'s [[nationalisation]] of the petroil in [[History of Iran|Iran]] were blocked by the U.S., who supported a coup in 1953 order to impose Shah  [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]] (the covert operation was named [[Operation Ajax]]). The next year, when [[History of Guatemala|Guatemala's]] president [[Jacobo Arbenz Guzmán|Arbenz]] tried to nationalise the [[United Fruit]], the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] overthrew him and replaced him by a military ''[[Military dictatorship|junta]]'' in [[Operation PBSuccess]].

In spite of these [[national sovereignty|interferences in other states]], decolonization itself was a seemingly unstoppable process. In 1960, after several [[wars of national liberation]], the UN had reached 99 members states: the [[decolonization of Africa]] was almost complete. In 1980, the UN had 154 member states, and in 1990, after [[Namibia]]'s independence, 159 states&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Growth in United Nations Membership, 1945–2005|publisher=United Nations | year=2000 | accessdate = 2006 | url=http://www.un.org/Overview/growth.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; But what could be seen retrospectively as a gigantic and quiet wave representing the ''[[Zeitgeist]]'' (&quot;Spirit of Times&quot;) overthrowing the domination of European colonialist powers was in fact the product of the struggle of the colonized people, whom many paid it with their lives.

In effect, although the anticolonialist struggle didn't lead in all cases to wars such as the Algerian War (1954–62), it was nevertheless bloody. Many anticolonialist leaders were assassinated in more or less obscure circumstances in the 1960s, whether by foreign powers or internal enemies, sometimes supported by foreign powers who more or less openly supported [[dictatorships]] (for example, France and its ties with the ''[[Françafrique]]''). The most famous names shouldn't dissimulate others less-known leaders, but a quick enumeration of [[Decolonization#Assassinated anticolonialist leaders|slain anti-imperialist leaders]] would include [[Patrice Lumumba]], the first Prime minister of the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]] assassinated in 1961; [[Sylvanus Olympio]], the first [[List of Presidents of Togo|president of Togo]], assassinated in 1963 (quickly replaced by [[Gnassingbé Eyadéma]], who would rule Togo until his death in 2005); [[Mehdi Ben Barka]], leader of the Moroccan opposition, who was preparing the [[Tricontinental Conference]] which was supposed to gather in [[La Habana]] in 1966 national liberation movements (not states) from all continents in order to organize the anti-imperialist struggle (kidnapped in Paris); [[Eduardo Mondlane]], the leader of the [[Mozambique|Mozambiquan]] [[FRELIMO]], allegedly assassinated by ''Aginter Press'', the Portuguese branch of [[Gladio]]&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.isn.ethz.ch/php/documents/collection_gladio/chronology.htm ISN Zurich Institute] hosted by [[ETH Zurich]] University&lt;/ref&gt; — [[NATO]]'s [[anti-communist]] paramilitary organization during the Cold War — [[Amilcar Cabral]], [[Oscar Romero]], the prelate archbishop of [[San Salvador]] and a proponent of [[Liberation Theology]], or [[Dulcie September]], [[African National Congress]] (ANC) activist murdered in Paris in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;See [[Decolonization#Assassinated anticolonialist leaders|Assassinated anticolonialist leaders]] subsection in the [[Decolonization]] article for a more complete list&lt;/ref&gt;

===Role of the USSR and China===
The [[Soviet Union]] was a main supporter of decolonization movements. While the [[Non-Aligned Movement]], created in 1961 following the [[Bandung Conference|Bandung 1955 Conference]], was supposedly neutral, the &quot;Third World&quot; being opposed to both the &quot;First&quot; and the &quot;Second&quot; Worlds, [[geopolitics|geopolitical]] concerns, as well as the refusal of the U.S. to support decolonization movements against its NATO European allies, led the national liberation movements to look increasingly toward the East. However, [[History of China|China's]] appearance on the world scene, under the leadership of [[Mao Zedong]], created a rupture between the Soviet Union and independentists movements. Globally, the non-aligned movement, led by [[Jawaharlal Nehru]] (India), [[Josip Broz Tito]] (Yugoslavia) and [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]] (Egypt) tried to create a block of nations powerful enough to be dependent on neither the U.S. nor the Soviet Union, but finally tilted towards the U.S.S.R, while smaller liberation movements, both by strategic necessity and ideological choice, were supported either by Moscow or by Peking. The Cuban government, led by [[Fidel Castro]] after the [[Cuban revolution]] of 1959, was at first neutral before turning itself towards Moscow. Cuba also sponsored liberation movements in Angola and Mozambique. Few liberation movements were totally independent from foreign aid.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{cite book
| last                  = Scott
| first                 = Barbara Gail
| title                 = Viking Colonialism: Contact and Interaction Between Viking/Medieval Norway and the Northern Isles 
| url                   = http://books.google.com/books?id=2aZqPwAACAAJ
| accessdate            = 2012-08-26
| year                  = 1993
| publisher             = University of Minnesota
}}

{{Colonial Empires}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Colonialism}}
[[Category:History of colonialism|*]]
[[Category:Colonialism]]

[[fa:تاریخ استعمار]]
[[hi:उपनिवेशवाद का इतिहास]]
[[ms:Sejarah kolonialisme]]
[[simple:History of colonialism]]</text>
      <sha1>rqdjmp6gfwayzyl7k36ntxayfc8mxtp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
