<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Yemen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34245</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520852495</id>
      <parentid>519628295</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T04:38:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kembangraps</username>
        <id>6513045</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48099">{{History of Yemen}}
[[Image:Panel Almaqah Louvre DAO18.jpg|thumb|upright|Sabaean inscription addressed to the moon-god [[Almaqah]], mentioning five South [[Arabia]]n gods, two reigning sovereigns and two governors, 7th century BCE.]]
[[Yemen]] is one of the oldest centers of [[civilization]] in the [[Near East]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/ht/04/wap/ht04wap.htm Arabian Peninsula, 1000 B.C.–1 A.D. | Timeline of Art History | The Metropolitan Museum of Art&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Its relatively fertile land and adequate rainfall in a moister climate helped sustain a stable population, a feature recognized by the ancient Greek geographer [[Ptolemy]], who described Yemen as ''Eudaimon Arabia'' (better known in its Latin translation, ''[[Arabia Felix]]'') meaning &quot;fortunate Arabia&quot; or ''Happy Arabia''.

The [[Nomadic]] Semites from the Yemeni desert regions ([[Rub' al Khali]] and [[Sayhad]]) migrated to the North, settling [[Akkadian Empire|Akkad]], later penetrating [[Mesopotamia]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/MESO/AKKAD.HTM The Akkadians]&lt;/ref&gt; eventually conquering [[Sumer]] by 2300 BCE, and assimilating the [[Amorites]] of Syria.

Some scholars{{Who|date=May 2008}} believe that Yemen remains the only region in the world that is exclusively [[Semitic]], meaning that Yemen historically did not have any non–Semitic-speaking people. Yemeni Semites derived their [[South Arabian alphabet|Musnad]] script by the 12th to 8th centuries BCE, which explains why most historians date all of the ancient Yemeni kingdoms to the 12th to 8th centuries BCE.

Between the 12th century BCE and the 6th century CE, it was dominated by six successive civilizations which rivaled each other, or were allied with each other and controlled the lucrative [[spice trade]]: [[M'ain]], [[Qataban]], [[Hadhramaut]], [[Awsan]], [[Sheba|Saba]] and [[Himyarite]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/ht/03/wap/ht03wap.htm Arabian Peninsula, 2000–1000 B.C. | Timeline of Art History | The Metropolitan Museum of Art&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Arab conquests|Islam arrived]] in 630{{citation needed|date=April 2012}} CE, and Yemen became part of the Muslim realm and was mostly [[Arabic language|Arabized]].

==Prehistory==
[[Image:griffon hadhramaut.jpg|thumb|upright|A Griffon from the royal palace at Shabwa, the capital city of [[Hadhramaut]]]]
{{Main|Ancient history of Yemen}}

According to Arab tradition, the [[Semites]] of South Arabia integrated into Qahtan lineage 40 generations before the [[Qahtanite|Qahtani]] Yemeni tribe of [[Jurhum]] adopted [[Ishmael|Ismail]] and 80 generations before Adnan was born, in the 23rd century BCE. After the fall of the Northern Semitic cultures, [[Qahtan]] revived the Semitic influence in the North through the famous [[Kahlan]] ([[Azd]] and [[Lakhm]]) and other Yemenite tribes migration into the North during the 3rd century CE after the first destruction of the [[Marib]] Dam.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://www.thearabhistory.com The Arab History Enyclopedia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Horn of Africa]]'s first Semitic nation, [[Dʿmt]], was a Yemeni settlement.

The [[Qahtanite|Qahtani]] Semites remained dominant in Yemen from 2300 BCE to 800 BCE, but little is known about this era because the Semites of the South were separated by the vast Arabian desert from Mesopotamian Semites and they lacked any type of script to record their history. However, it is known that they actively traded along the Red Sea coasts. This led to contact with the [[Phoenicians]] and from them, the Southern Semites adopted their writing script in 800 BCE and began recording their history.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt;

The Tihama Semitic culture lasted from 1500-1200 BCE. During the late 2nd millennium BCE, a cultural Semitic complex arose in the [[Tihama]] region of Yemen and spread to northern [[Ethiopia]] and [[Eritrea]] (specifically the [[Tigray Region]], central Eritrea, and coastal areas like [[Adulis]]). The Semites of Yemen began settling the Ethiopian highlands. These settlements would reach their climax by the 8th century BCE, eventually giving rise to the [[Dʿmt]] and [[Aksum]] kingdoms&lt;ref&gt;Fattovich, Rodolfo &quot;The Near East and eastern Africa: their interaction&quot;, in Vogel, J.O. ed., &quot;Encyclopedia of precolonial Africa.&quot; AltaMira Press, Walnut Creek, 1997, pps.479–484.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Kingdoms==
[[Image:Bar'an temple 1986-1.jpg|thumb|Ruins of Mahram Bilqis temple near [[Ma'rib]]]]

During the rule of the [[Sabaeans]], 8th century BCE to 275 CE, trade and agriculture flourished generating much wealth and prosperity. The Sabaean kingdom is located in what is now the Aseer region in southwestern Yemen, and its capital, Ma'rib, is located near what is now Yemen's modern capital, [[Sana'a]].&lt;ref&gt;http://web.archive.org/web/20071112054008/http://www.iraqandiraqis.com/Arab+history.htm&lt;/ref&gt; According to tradition, the eldest son of [[Noah]], [[Shem]], founded the city of Ma'rib.  

During Sabaean rule, Yemen was called &quot;Arabia Felix&quot; by the Romans who were impressed by its wealth and prosperity. The success of the Kingdom was based on the cultivation and trade of spices and aromatics including frankincense and myrrh. These were exported to the Mediterranean, India, and Abyssinia where they were greatly prized by many cultures, using camels on routes through Arabia, and to India by sea. 

During the 8th and 7th century BCE, there was a close contact of cultures between the Kingdom of [[Dʿmt]] in northern Ethiopia and Eritrea and Saba'. Though the civilization was indigenous and the royal inscriptions were written in a sort of proto-[[Ethiopian Semitic languages|Ethiosemitic]], there were also some Sabaean immigrants in the kingdom as evidenced by a few of the Dʿmt inscriptions.&lt;ref&gt;Sima, Alexander. &quot;Dʿmt&quot; in Siegbert von Uhlig, ed., ''Encyclopaedia Aethiopica: D-Ha'' (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2005), pp.185.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Munro-Hay, Stuart. ''Aksum: A Civilization of Late Antiquity,'' (Edinburgh: University Press, 1991), pp.58.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Agriculture in Yemen thrived during this time due to an advanced irrigation system which consisted of large water tunnels in mountains, and dams. The most impressive dam, known as the dam of Ma'rib was built ca. 700 BCE, provided irrigation for about {{convert|25000|acre|km2}} of land&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everyculture.com/To-Z/Yemen.html Culture of Yemen - History and ethnic relations, Urbanism, architecture, and the use of space&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and stood for over a millennium, finally collapsing in CE 570 after centuries of neglect.

The Sabaean kingdom, with its capital at [[Ma'rib]] where the remains of a large temple can still be seen, thrived for almost 14 centuries. Some have argued that this kingdom was the [[Sheba]] described in the [[Old Testament]].
[[Image:BronzeManNashqum.jpg|upright|thumb|&quot;Bronze man&quot; found in [[Al Bayda', Yemen|Al Bayda']] (ancient Nashqum); 6th-5th century BCE. [[Louvre Museum]].]]
[[Image:qataban lion bronze.jpg|thumb|left|Bronze lion with a rider made by the [[Qatabanians]] circa 75-50 BCE.]]
The first known inscriptions of the Kingdom of [[Hadramaut]] are from the 8th century BCE. It was first referenced by an outside civilization in an [[Sabaean language|Old Sabaic]] inscription of Karab'il Watar from the early 7th century BCE, in which the King of Hadramaut, Yada''il, is mentioned as being one of his allies. When the Minaeans took control of the caravan routes in the 4th century BCE, however, Hadramaut became one of its confederates, probably because of commercial interests. It later became independent and was invaded by the growing kingdom of [[Himyar]] toward the end of the first century BC, but it was able to repel the attack. Hadramaut annexed Qataban in the second half of the 2nd century AD, reaching its greatest size. During this period, Hadramaut was continuously at war with Himyar and Saba', and the [[Sabaeans|Sabaean]] king Sha'irum Awtar was even able to take its capital, Shabwa, in 225. During this period the [[Kingdom of Aksum]] began to interfere in South Arabian affairs. King [[GDRT]] of Aksum acted by dispatching troops under his son, BYGT, sending them from the western coast to occupy [[Zafar, Yemen|Zafar]], the Himyarite capital, as well as from the southern coast against Hadramaut as Sabaean allies. The kingdom of Hadramaut was eventually conquered by the Himyarite king Shammar Yuhar'ish around 300 CE, unifying all of the South Arabian kingdoms.&lt;ref&gt;Müller, Walter W. &quot;Ḥaḍramawt&quot;, ''Encyclopaedia: D-Ha'', pp.965-6.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ancient Kingdom of [[Awsan]] with a capital at Hagar Yahirr in the wadi Markha to the south of the wadi Bayhan is now marked by a [[tell]] or artificial mound, which is locally named [[Hagar Asfal]]. Once it was one of the most important small kingdoms of South Arabia. 

The city, which has its origin in 800 BC, seems to have been destroyed in the 7th century BCE by the king and [[mukarrib]] of [[Sabaeans|Saba]] [[Karib'il Watar]], according to a Sabaean text that reports the victory in terms that attest to its significance for the Sabaeans.

[[Qataban]], which lasted from the 4th century BCE to 200 CE, was one of the ancient Yemeni kingdoms which thrived in the Baihan valley. Like the other Southern Arabian kingdoms it gained great wealth from the trade of frankincense and myrrh incense which were burned at altars. The capital of Qataban was named Timna and was located on the trade route which passed through the other kingdoms of Hadramaut, Saba and Ma'in. The chief deity of the Qatabanians was Amm, or &quot;Uncle&quot; and the people called themselves the &quot;children of Amm&quot;.

===Kingdom of Ma'in===
{{main|Minaean}}
During '''Minaean''' rule the capital was at Karna (now known as [[Sadah]]). Their other important city was Yathill (now known as Baraqish). Other parts of modern Yemen include [[Qataban]] and the coastal string of watering stations known as the [[Hadhramaut]]. Though Saba' dominated in the earlier period of South Arabian history, Minaic inscriptions are of the same time period as the first Sabaic inscriptions. Note, however, that they pre-date the appearance of the Minaeans themselves, and, hence, are called now more appropriately as &quot;Madhabic&quot; rather than &quot;Minaic&quot;. The Minaean Kingdom was centered in northwestern Yemen, with most of its cities laying along the [[Wadi Madhab]]. Minaic inscriptions have been found far afield of the Kingdom of Ma'in, as far away as [[al-'Ula]] in northwestern [[Saudi Arabia]] and even on the island of [[Delos]] and in [[Egypt]]. It was the first of the South Arabian kingdoms to end, and the Minaic language died around 100 CE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nebes&quot;&gt;Nebes, Norbert. &quot;Epigraphic South Arabian&quot;, ''Encyclopaedia: D-Ha''pp.334; Leonid Kogan and [[Andrey Korotayev]]: Sayhadic Languages (Epigraphic South Arabian) // Semitic Languages. London: Routledge, 1997, p. 157-183.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kingdom of Himyar===
[[Image:Statue Ammaalay Louvre AO20282.jpg|thumb|upright 0.7|Statue of [[Ammaalay]], 1st century BC, Yemen ]]
{{main|Himyar}}
The '''Himyarites''' had united Southwestern Arabia, controlling the [[Red Sea]] as well as the coasts of the [[Gulf of Aden]]. From their capital city, the Himyarite Kings launched successful military campaigns, and had stretched its domain at times as far east as the [[Persian Gulf]] and as far north to the Arabian Desert. 

During the 3rd century CE, the South Arabian kingdoms were in continuous conflict with one another. [[GDRT]] of Aksum began to interfere in South Arabian affairs, signing an alliance with Saba', and a Himyarite text notes that Hadramaut and Qataban were also all allied against the kingdom. As a result of this, the [[Kingdom of Aksum]] was able to capture the Himyarite capital of [[Zafar, Yemen|Zafar]] in the first quarter of the 3rd century. However, the alliances did not last, and Sha'ir Awtar of Saba' unexpectedly turned on Hadramaut, allying again with Aksum and taking its capital in 225. Himyar then allied with Saba' and invaded the newly taken Aksumite territories, retaking Zafar, which had been under the control of GDRT's son BYGT, and pushing Aksum back into the [[Tihamah|Tihama]].&lt;ref&gt;Sima, Alexander. &quot;GDR(T)&quot;, ''Encyclopaedia: D-Ha'', pp.718-9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Munro-Hay, ''Aksum'', pp.72.&lt;/ref&gt;

They established their capital at [[Zafar, Yemen|Zafar]] (now just a small village in the [[Ibb]] region) and gradually absorbed the Sabaean kingdom. They traded from the port of [[al-Muza]] on the Red Sea. [[Dhu Nuwas]], a Himyarite king, changed the state religion to [[Judaism]] in the beginning of the 6th century and began to massacre the Christians. Outraged, [[Kaleb of Axum|Kaleb]], the Christian King of [[Kingdom of Aksum|Aksum]] with the encouragement of the Byzantine Emperor [[Justin I]] invaded and annexed Yemen.  About fifty years later, [[Sayf ibn Dhi Yazan]] asked for help from the Persians, so the Persians sent all of their criminals as an army to Yemen.  One way to help get rid of the criminals in jail, and help their new ally [[Sayf ibn Dhi Yazan]].

===Kingdom of Aksum===
{{main|Kingdom of Aksum}}
[[File:Stela aksum.jpg|thumb|upright|Aksum obelisk, symbol of the Aksumite civilization]]
Around 517/8, a [[Judaism|Jewish]] king called [[Dhu Nuwas|Yusuf Asar Yathar]] (also known as Dhu Nuwas) usurped the kingship of Himyar from [[Ma'adkarib Ya'fur]]. Interestingly, [[Zacharias Rhetor|Pseudo-Zacharias]] of [[Mytilene]] (fl. late 6th century) says that Yusuf became king because the previous king had died in winter, when the Aksumites could not cross the [[Red Sea]] and appoint another king. Ma'adkarib Ya'fur's long title puts its truthfulness in doubt, however.&lt;ref&gt;Munro-Hay, Stuart. ''Aksum'', p.80.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon gaining power, Yusuf attacked the Aksumite garrison in [[Zafar, Yemen|Zafar]], the Himyarite capital, killing many and destroying the church there.&lt;ref&gt;Mentioned in an inscription dated to 633 of the Himyarite era, or 518 CE.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aksum81&quot;&gt;Munro-Hay, Stuart. ''Aksum'', p.81.&lt;/ref&gt; The Christian King [[Kaleb of Axum]] learned of Dhu Nuwas's persecutions of Christians and Aksumites, and, according to [[Procopius]], was further encouraged by his ally and fellow Christian [[Justin I]] of Byzantium, who requested [[Kingdom of Aksum|Aksum's]] help to cut off [[silk]] supplies as part of his economic war against the [[Sassanid Empire|Persians]].&lt;ref&gt;Munro-Hay, Stuart. ''Aksum'', p.54.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kaleb sent a fleet across the Red Sea and was able to defeat Dhu Nuwas, who was killed in battle according to an inscription from Husn al-Ghurab, while later Arab tradition has him riding his horse into the sea.&lt;ref&gt;Alessandro de Maigret, Arabia Felix, translated by Rebecca Thompson (London: Stacey International, 2002), p. 251&lt;/ref&gt; Kaleb installed a native [[Himyar]]ite viceroy, [[Sumyafa' Ashwa']], who ruled until 525, when he was deposed by the Aksumite general (or soldier and former slave&lt;ref name=&quot;Sima&quot;&gt;Sima, Alexander, &quot;Abraha&quot; in ''Encyclopaedia: D-Ha'', p.42.&lt;/ref&gt;) [[Abraha]] with the support of disgruntled [[Ethiopia]]n soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aksum81&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A contemporary inscription refers to Sumyafa' Ashwa' as &quot;viceroy for the kings of Aksum. Munro-Hay, Stuart &quot;Arabia&quot; in ''Encyclopaedia: D-Ha'', p.297.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the later Arabic sources, Kaleb retaliated by sending a force of 3,000 men under a relative, but the troops defected and killed their leader, and a second attempt at reigning in the rebellious Abraha also failed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aksum82&quot;&gt;Munro-Hay, Stuart. ''Aksum'', p.82.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Munro-Hay, Stuart &quot;Arabia&quot; in ''Encyclopaedia: D-Ha'', p.297.&lt;/ref&gt; Later Ethiopian sources state that Kaleb abdicated to live out his years in a monastery and sent his crown to be hung in the [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]] in [[Jerusalem]]. While uncertain, it seems to be supported by the die-links between his coins and those of his successor, [[Alla Amidas]]. An inscription of Sumyafa' Ashwa' also mentions two kings (''nagaśt'') of Aksum, indicating that the two may have co-ruled for a while before Kaleb abdicated in favor of Alla Amidas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aksum82&quot; /&gt; 

Procopius notes that Abraha later submitted to Kaleb's successor, as supported by the former's inscription in 543 stating Aksum before the territories directly under his control. During his reign, Abraha repaired the [[Marib Dam]] in 543, and received embassies from Persia and Byzantium, including a request to free some bishops who had been imprisoned at [[Nisbis]] (according to [[John of Epheseus]]'s [[Life of Simeon]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Aksum82&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Munro-Hay, Stuart &quot;Arabia&quot; in ''Encyclopaedia: D-Ha'', pp.297-8.&lt;/ref&gt; Abraha ruled until at least 547, sometime after which he was succeeded by his son, Aksum. Aksum (called &quot;Yaksum&quot; in Arabic sources) was perplexingly referred to as &quot;of [[Ma'afir]]&quot; (''ḏū maʻāfir''), the southwestern coast of Yemen, in Abraha's Marib dam inscription, and was succeeded by his brother, Masruq. Aksumite control in Yemen ended in 570 with the invasion of the elder Sassanid general [[Vahriz]] who, according to later legends, famously killed Masruq with his well-aimed arrow.&lt;ref&gt;Munro-Hay, Stuart &quot;Arabia&quot; in ''Encyclopaedia: D-Ha'', p.298.&lt;/ref&gt;

Later Arabic sources also say that [[Abraha]] constructed a great Church called [[al-Qulays]] at [[Sana'a]] in order to divert pilgrimage from the [[Kaaba]] and have him die in the [[Year of the Elephant]] (570) after returning from a failed attack on Mecca.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sima&quot; /&gt; The exact chronology of the early wars are uncertain, as a 525 inscription mentions the death of a King of Himyar, which could refer either to the Himyarite viceory of Aksum, Sumyafa' Ashwa', or to Yusuf Asar Yathar. The later Arabic histories also mention a conflict between [[Abraha]] and another Aksumite general named Aryat occurring in 525 as leading to the rebellion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aksum81&quot; /&gt;

==Sassanid period==
{{main|Sassanid}}
[[File:Sassanid Empire 620.png|thumb|left|The Sassanid Empire at its greatest extent, under king [[Khosrau II]]]]
The [[Persian Empire|Persian]] king [[Khosrau I]], sent troops under the command of [[Vahriz]], who helped [[Sayf ibn Dhi Yazan]] to drive the Ethiopian [[Kingdom of Aksum|Aksumites]] out of Yemen. Southern Arabia became a Persian dominion under a Yemenite vassal and thus came within the sphere of influence of the [[Sassanid Empire]]. Later another army was sent to Yemen, and in 597/8 Southern Arabia became a province of the Sassanid Empire under a Persian [[satrap]]. It was a Persian province by name but after the Persians assassinated Dhi Yazan, Yemen divided into a number of autonomous kingdoms.

This development was a consequence of the expansionary policy pursued by the Sassanian king [[Khosrau II Parviz]] (590-628), whose aim was to secure Persian border areas such as Yemen. Following the death of Khosrau II in 628, then the Persian governor in Southern Arabia, [[Badhan (Persian Governor)|Badhan]], converted to Islam and Yemen followed the new religion.

==Medieval history==
{{main|Islamic history of Yemen|Imams of Yemen}}
[[Image:Age of Caliphs.png|thumb|right|The Age of the Caliphs]]

Islam came to Yemen around 630, during the Islamic prophet [[Muhammad]]'s lifetime. At that time the Persian governor [[Badhan (Persian Governor)|Badhan]] was ruling. Thereafter Yemen was ruled as part of Arab-Islamic caliphates, and Yemen became a province in the [[Rashidun Caliphate|Islamic empire]].

Yemeni textiles, long recognized for their fine quality, maintained their reputation and were exported for use by the [[Abbasid]] elite, including the [[caliph]]s themselves. The products of Sana'a and [[Aden]] are especially important in the East-West textile trade.

The former [[North Yemen]] came under control of [[Imamah (Shi'a doctrine)|Imams]] of various dynasties usually of the [[Zaidi]] sect, who established a [[theocratic]] political structure that survived until modern times.  In 897, a Zaidi ruler, [[al-Hadi ila'l-Haqq Yahya|Yahya al-Hadi ila'l Haqq]], founded a line of Imams, whose [[Shia Islam|Shiite]] dynasty survived until the second half of the 20th century. 

Nevertheless, Yemen's medieval history is a tangled chronicle of contesting local Imams. The [[Fatimid]]s of [[Egypt]] helped the [[Isma'ili]]s maintain dominance in the 11th century through the [[Sulayhid dynasty]] founded and brought to peak by [[Ali al-Sulayhi]] between 1047-1063. [[Turan-Shah]] annexed Yemen to the [[Ayyubid dynasty|Ayyubid Empire]] of [[Saladin]] in 1173. The [[Rasulid]] dynasty ruled Yemen, with [[Zabid]] as its capital, from about 1230 to the 15th century. In 1516, the [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)|Mamluk]]s of Egypt annexed Yemen; but in the following year, the Mamluk governor surrendered to the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottomans]], and Turkish armies subsequently overran the country. They were challenged by the Zaidi Imam, [[al-Mansur al-Qasim|Qasim the Great]] (r.1597&amp;ndash;1620), and were expelled from the interior around 1630. From then until the 19th century, the Ottomans retained control only of isolated coastal areas, while the highlands generally were ruled by the Zaidi Imams.

==Ottoman influence==
As the [[Zaidi]] [[Imamate]] collapsed in the 19th century due to internal division, the Ottomans moved south along the west coast of Arabia back into northern Yemen in the 1830s, and eventually even took [[San'a']] making it the Yemeni district capital in 1872.  The Ottomans were aided by the adoption of [[Crimean War]] modern weapons. 

[[United Kingdom|British]] interests in the area which would later become South Yemen, began to grow when in 1832, [[British East India Company]] forces captured the port of [[Aden]], to provide a [[coal]]ing station for ships en route to [[India]]. The British interest in reducing [[pirate]] attacks on British merchants lead to their creating a protectorate over the town of Aden in 1839, and adding the surrounding lands over the following years.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, R. Lambert (1859) ''A history of Arabia Felix or Yemen : from the commencement of the Christian era to the present time, including an account of the British settlement of Aden'' Education Society's Press, Byculla, [[India]] (variously reprinted)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;ʻAmrī, Muḥsin ibn Aḥmad Ḥarrāzī; Ḥusayn ʻAbd Allāh (1986) ''Fatrat al-fawḍá wa-ʻawdat al-Atrāk ilá Ṣanʻāʼ : al-sifr al-thānī min tārīkh al-Ḥarrāzī (Riyāḍ al-rayāḥīn) 1276-1289 H/1859-1872 M'' Dār al-Fikr, Dimashq 9الحرازي، محسن ابن أجمد. تحقيق ودراسة حسين عبد الله العمري. عمري، حسين عبد الله. ''فترة الفوضى وعودة الأتراك الى صنعاء : السفر الثاني من تاريخ الحرازي (رياض الرياحين) ٦٧٢١-٩٨٢١ ه/٩٥٨١-٢٧٨١ م'' دار الفكر ؛ دار الحكمة اليمانية،&lt;/ref&gt;  
The [[colony]] gained much [[politics|political]] and [[strategy|strategic]] importance after the opening of the [[Suez Canal]] in 1869 and the increased traffic on the Red Sea route to India

The Ottomans and the British eventually established a [[de facto]] border between north and south Yemen, which was formalized in a treaty in 1904. However the interior boundaries were never clearly established.  However the presence of the Ottomans, and to a lesser extent the British, allowed the Zaydi Imamate to rebuild against a common enemy.  Guerrilla warfare and banditry erupted into the  rebellion of the Zaydi tribes in 1905.

Starting in the latter decades of the 19th century and continuing into the 20th century, Britain signed agreements with local rulers of traditional polities that, together, became known as the '''[[Aden Protectorate]]'''. The area was divided into numerous sultanates, emirates, and sheikhdoms, and was divided for administrative purposes into the East Aden Protectorate and the West Aden Protectorate. The eastern protectorate consisted of the three Hadhramaut states ([[Qu'aiti]] State of Shihr and [[Al Mukalla|Mukalla]], [[Kathiri]] State of [[Seiyun]], [[Mahra Sultanate|Mahra]] State of [[Qishn]] and [[Socotra]]) with the remaining states comprising the west.

Ottoman suzerainty was reestablished in northern Yemen in the late 19th century but its control was largely confined to cities, and the [[Zaiddiyah|Zaidi]] [[Imamah (Shi'a doctrine)|imam]]'s rule over [[Upper Yemen]] was formally recognized. Turkish forces withdrew in 1918, and Imam [[Yahya Muhammad Hamid ed-Din|Yahya Muhammad]] strengthened his control over northern Yemen creating the [[Mutawakkilite Kingdom of Yemen]].

==Modern history==

===Mutawakkilite kingdom and southern protectorates===
[[Image:Sanaa.JPG|thumb|left|upright|The old city of [[Sana'a|Sanaa]]]]
{{main|Modern history of Yemen|Mutawakkilite Kingdom of Yemen|Yemen Arab Republic}}

The [[Mutawakkilite Kingdom of Yemen]] engaged in hostilities with the House of Saud, feuding over Asir. The conflict escalated into a full fledged [[Saudi-Yemeni War|war]] in 1934, though resulted in no territorial changes.

Aden was ruled as part of [[British India]] until 1937, when the city of Aden became the [[Colony of Aden]], a [[crown colony]] in its own right. The Aden [[hinterland]] and [[Hadhramaut]] to the east formed the remainder of what would become South Yemen and were not administered directly by Aden but were tied to Britain by treaties of protection. [[Economic development]] was largely centred in Aden, and while the city flourished partly due to the discovery of [[crude oil]] on the [[Arabian Peninsula]] in the 1930s, the states of the Aden Protectorate stagnated.

Yemen became a member of the [[Arab League]] in 1945  and the [[United Nations]] in 1947. 

Imam Yahya died during an unsuccessful coup attempt in 1948 and was succeeded by his son Ahmad. [[Ahmad bin Yahya]]'s reign was marked by growing economic and political reforms, renewed friction with the [[United Kingdom]] over the British presence in the south, and growing pressures to support the Arab [[nationalist]] objectives of Egyptian President [[Gamal Abdul Nasser]]. He died in September 1962.

Encouraged by the rhetoric of [[Gamal Abdel Nasser|President Nasser]] of [[Egypt]] against British colonial rule in the [[Middle East]], pressure for the British to leave South Yemen grew. Following Nasser's creation of the [[United Arab Republic]], attempts to incorporate Yemen in turn threatened Aden and the Protectorate. To counter this, the British attempted to unite the various states under its protection and, on 11 February 1959, six of the West Aden Protectorate states formed the [[Federation of Arab Emirates of the South]] to which nine other states were subsequently added.

Shortly after assuming power in 1962, Ahmad's son, the Crown Prince [[Muhammad al-Badr]] was deposed by coup forces, who took control of [[Sana'a|Sanaa]] and created the [[Yemen Arab Republic]] (YAR). Egypt assisted the YAR with troops and supplies to combat forces loyal to the Kingdom. [[Saudi Arabia]] and [[Jordan]] supported Badr's royalist forces to oppose the newly formed republic starting the [[North Yemen Civil War]]. Conflict continued periodically until 1967 when Egyptian troops were withdrawn. 

During the 1960s, the British sought to incorporate all of the [[Aden Protectorate]] territories into the Federation. On 18 January 1963, the Colony of Aden was incorporated against the wishes of much of the city's populace as the State of Aden and the Federation was renamed the [[Federation of South Arabia]].  Several more states subsequently joined the Federation and the remaining states that declined to join, mainly in Hadhramaut, formed the '''[[Protectorate of South Arabia]]'''. 

In 1963 fighting between Egyptian forces and British-led [[Saudi Arabia|Saudi]]-financed [[guerrilla warfare|guerrilla]]s in the [[Yemen Arab Republic]] spread to South Arabia with the formation of the [[National Liberation Front (Yemen)|National Liberation Front]] (NLF), who hoped to force the British out of South Arabia.  Hostilities started with a grenade attack by the NLF against the British High Commissioner on 10 December 1963, killing one person and injuring fifty, and a [[state of emergency]] was declared, becoming known as the [[Aden Emergency]].

In January 1964, the British moved into the [[Radfan]] hills in the border region to confront Egyptian-backed guerrillas, later reinforced by the NLF.  By October they had largely been suppressed, and the NLF switched to grenade attacks against off-duty [[military]] personnel and [[police]] officers elsewhere in the Aden Colony. 

In 1964, the new British government under [[Harold Wilson]] announced their intention to hand over power to the Federation of South Arabia in 1968, but that the British military would remain.  In 1964, there were around 280 guerrilla attacks and over 500 in 1965.  In 1966  the British Government announced that all British forces would be withdrawn at independence.  In response, the security situation deteriorated with the creation of the [[socialism|socialist]] [[Front for the Liberation of Occupied South Yemen]] (FLOSY) which started to attack the NLF in a bid for power, as well as attacking the British.

In January 1967, there were mass riots by NLF and FLOSY supporters in the old Arab quarter of Aden town, which continued until mid February, despite the intervention of British troops.  During the period there were many attacks on the troops, and an Aden Airlines [[Douglas DC-3]] plane was destroyed in the air with no survivors.  At the same time, the members of FLOSY and the NLF were also killing each other in large numbers.

The [[Yellow Fleet|temporary closure]] of the [[Suez Canal]] in 1967 effectively negated the last reason that British had kept hold of the colonies in Yemen, and, in the face of uncontrollable violence, they began to withdraw. 

On 20 June 1967, there was a mutiny in the Federation of South Arabia Army, which also spread to the police.  Order was restored by the British, mainly due to the efforts of the 1st Battalion [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders]], under the command of Lt-Col. [[Colin Campbell Mitchell]].

Nevertheless, deadly guerrilla attacks particularly by the NLF soon resumed against British forces once again, with the British being defeated and driven from Aden by the end of November 1967, earlier than had been planned by British Prime Minister [[Harold Wilson]] and without an agreement on the succeeding governance. Their enemies, the NLF, managed to seize power, with Aden itself under NLF control. The [[Royal Marines]], who had been the first British troops to occupy Aden in 1839, were the last to leave.  The Federation of South Arabia collapsed and Southern Yemen became independent as the [[People's Republic of South Yemen]].  The NLF, with the support of the [[army]], attained total control of the new state after defeating the FLOSY and the states of the former Federation in a drawn out campaign of [[terrorism|terror]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}

Most of the opposing leaders reconciled by 1968, in the aftermath of a final royalist siege of San'a'.  In 1970, Saudi Arabia recognized the Yemen Arab Republic and a ceasefire was effected.

A radical (Marxist) wing of the NLF gained power in South Yemen in June 1969.

===South and North Yemen===
The NLF changed the name of South Yemen on 1 December 1970 to the [[People's Democratic Republic of Yemen]] (PDRY). In the PDRY, all political parties were amalgamated into the [[Yemeni Socialist Party]] (YSP), which became the only legal party. The PDRY established close ties with the [[Soviet Union]], [[People's Republic of China]], [[Cuba]], and radical [[Palestinians]].

The major communist powers assisted in the building of the PDRY's armed forces. Strong support from Moscow resulted in Soviet naval forces gaining access to naval facilities in South Yemen.

Unlike [[East Germany|East]] and [[West Germany]], the two Yemens remained relatively friendly, though relations were often strained. In 1972 it was declared unification would eventually occur.{{citation needed|date=December 2011}}

However, in October 1972 fighting erupted between the North Yemen and the South Yemen; North Yemen supplied by Saudi Arabia and South Yemen by the USSR. Fighting was short-lived and the conflict led to the October 28, 1972 Cairo Agreement, which set forth a plan to unify the two countries.&lt;ref&gt;'''[http://www.scribd.com/doc/51196986/CIA-Study-on-Yemeni-Unification CIA Study on Yemeni Unification]'''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gause, Gregory, '''[http://books.google.com/books?id=0yUzV-g2X2QC&amp;pg=PA98&amp;dq=%22arab+league%22+yemen+1972&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=KOGMTZC3HaaB0QH-3ry2Cw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22arab%20league%22%20yemen%201972&amp;f=false Saudi-Yemeni relations: domestic structures and foreign influence]''', Columbia University Press, 1990, page 98&lt;/ref&gt;

Fighting broke out again in February and March 1979, with South Yemen allegedly supplying aid to rebels in the north through the [[National Democratic Front (Yemen)|National Democratic Front]] and crossing the border.&lt;ref&gt;Hermann, Richard, '''[http://books.google.com/books?id=fvx_mozejjgC&amp;pg=PA241&amp;dq=yemen+1979&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=DeOMTYijCcaw0QHzg7C8Cw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEgQ6AEwBjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=yemen&amp;f=false Perceptions and behavior in Soviet foreign policy]''', University of Pittsburgh Pre, 1985, page 152&lt;/ref&gt; Southern forces made it as far as the city of [[Taizz]] before withdrawing.&lt;ref&gt;Hoagland, Edward, '''[http://books.google.com/books?id=vd97al2M3o4C&amp;pg=PA218&amp;dq=taizz+1979&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Ze-MTcOdBaiQ0QHknuCrCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CE0Q6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Balancing Acts]''',Globe Pequot, 1999, page 218&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;'''[http://www.jstor.org/stable/3011111?seq=1 Interview with ''Al-Hamdani'']''' Middle East Research and Information Reports, February 1985&lt;/ref&gt; This conflict was also short-lived.&lt;ref&gt;Burrowes, Robert, '''[http://books.google.com/books?id=x3CtaL2yEnkC&amp;pg=PA187&amp;dq=yemen+unification&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=CJ-MTZ7uM8Ga0QHMlvTCCw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=yemen%20unification&amp;f=false Middle East dilemma: the politics and economics of Arab integration]''', Columbia University Press, 1999, pages 187 to 210&lt;/ref&gt;

The war was only stopped by an [[Arab League]] intervention. The goal of unity was reaffirmed by the northern and southern heads of state during a summit meeting in [[Kuwait]] in March 1979. 

What the PDRY government failed to tell the YAR government was that it wished to be the dominant power in any unification, and left wing rebels in North Yemen began to receive extensive funding and arms from South Yemen.

In 1980, PDRY president [[Abdul Fattah Ismail]] resigned and went into [[exile]]. His successor, [[Ali Nasir Muhammad]], took a less interventionist stance toward both North Yemen and neighbouring [[Oman]]. On January 13, 1986, a violent [[South Yemen Civil War|struggle]], known as [[South Yemen Civil War]] began in Aden between Ali Nasir's supporters and supporters of the returned Ismail, who wanted power back. Fighting lasted for more than a [[month]] and resulted in thousands of casualties, Ali Nasir's [[:wikt:ouster|ouster]], and Ismail's [[death]]. Some 60,000 people, including the deposed Ali Nasir, [[emigration|fled]] to the YAR.

Efforts toward unification proceeded from 1988. ''See also: [[Aden]], [[Aden Protectorate]], [[Federation of South Arabia]], [[Hadhramaut]], and the [[People's Democratic Republic of Yemen]]''

Although the governments of the PDRY and the YAR declared that they approved a future union in 1972, little progress was made toward unification, and relations were often strained.

In May 1988, the YAR and PDRY governments came to an understanding that considerably reduced tensions including agreement to renew discussions concerning unification, to establish a joint oil exploration area along their undefined border, to demilitarize the border, and to allow Yemenis unrestricted border passage on the basis of only a national identification card.

In November 1989, the leaders of the YAR ([[Ali Abdullah Saleh]]) and the PDRY ([[Ali Salim al-Baidh]]) agreed on a draft unity constitution originally drawn up in 1981.

===Unified Yemen===

====Unification====
{{further2|[[Yemenite reunification]]}}
The [[Republic of Yemen]] (ROY) was declared on 22 May 1990 with Saleh becoming President and al-Baidh Vice President.  For the first time in centuries, much of [[Greater Yemen]] was politically united. A 30-month transitional period for completing the [[Yemenite reunification|unification of the two political and economic systems]] was set. A presidential council was jointly elected by the 26-member YAR advisory council and the 17-member PDRY presidium. The presidential council appointed a Prime Minister, who formed a Cabinet. There was also a 301-seat provisional unified [[Assembly of Representatives of Yemen|parliament]], consisting of 159 members from the north, 111 members from the south, and 31 independent members appointed by the chairman of the council.

A unity constitution was agreed upon in May 1990 and ratified by the populace in May 1991. It affirmed Yemen's commitment to free elections, a multiparty political system, the right to own private property, equality under the law, and respect of basic human rights. Parliamentary elections were held on 27 April 1993. International groups assisted in the organization of the elections and observed actual balloting. The resulting Parliament included 143 GPC, 69 YSP, 63 Islaah (Yemeni grouping for reform, a party composed of various tribal and religious groups), six Baathis, three Nasserists, two Al Haq, and 15 independents. The head of Islaah, Paramount [[Hashid Sheik Abdallah Bin Husayn Al-Ahmar]], is the speaker of Parliament. 

In late 1991 through early 1992, deteriorating economic conditions led to significant domestic unrest, including several riots. Legislative elections were nonetheless held in early 1993, and in May the two former ruling parties, the GPC and the YSP, merged to create a single political party with an overall majority in the new [[House of Representatives of Yemen|House of Representatives]]. In August Vice President al Baydh exiled himself voluntarily to [[Aden]], and the country’s general security situation deteriorated as political rivals settled scores and tribal elements took advantage of the widespread unrest. In January 1994, representatives of the main political parties signed a document of pledge and accord in [[Amman]], [[Jordan]], that was designed to resolve the ongoing crisis. Despite this, clashes intensified until [[civil war]] broke out in early May 1994.

====1994 Civil War====
{{main|1994 civil war in Yemen}}
Almost all of the actual fighting in the 1994 civil war occurred in the southern part of the country despite air and missile attacks against cities and major installations in the north. Southerners sought support from neighboring states and received billions of dollars of equipment and financial assistance, mostly from [[Saudi Arabia]], which felt threatened by a united Yemen. The [[United States]] strongly supported Yemeni unity, but repeatedly called for a cease-fire and a return to the negotiating table. Various attempts, including by a UN special envoy, were unsuccessful to effect a cease-fire. 

Southern leaders declared secession and the establishment of the '''[[Democratic Republic of Yemen]]''' (DRY) on 21 May 1994, but the DRY was not recognized by the international community. Ali Nasir Muhammad supporters greatly assisted military operations against the secessionists and Aden was captured on 7 July 1994. Other resistance quickly collapsed and thousands of southern leaders and military went into exile. Early during the fighting, President Ali Abdallah Salih announced a general [[amnesty]] which applied to everyone except a list of 16 persons. Most southerners returned to Yemen after a short exile. 

An armed opposition was announced from Saudi Arabia, but no significant incidents within Yemen materialized. The government prepared legal cases against four southern leaders--[[Ali Salim al-Baidh]], [[Haydar Abu Bakr Al-Attas]], [[Abd Al-Rahman Ali Al-Jifri]], and [[Salih Munassar Al-Siyali]] -- for misappropriation of official funds. Others on the list of 16 were told informally they could return to take advantage of the amnesty, but most remained outside Yemen. Although many of Ali Nasir Muhammad's followers were appointed to senior governmental positions (including Vice President, Chief of Staff, and Governor of Aden), Ali Nasir Muhammad himself remained abroad in [[Syria]].

In the aftermath of the civil war, YSP leaders within Yemen reorganized the party and elected a new politburo in July 1994. However, the party remained disheartened and without its former influence. Islaah held a party convention in September 1994. The GPC did the same in June 1995. 

In 1994, [[Constitutional amendment|amendment]]s to the unity constitution eliminated the presidential council. President [[Ali Abdallah Saleh]] was elected by Parliament on 1 October 1994 to a 5-year term. The constitution provides that henceforth the President will be elected by popular vote from at least two candidates selected by the legislature. Yemen held its first direct presidential elections in September 1999, electing President Ali Abdallah Salih to a 5-year term in what were generally considered free and fair elections. Yemen held its second multiparty parliamentary elections in April 1997.

In 1994, amendments to the unity constitution eliminated the presidential council. On October 1, 1994, Parliament elected President Ali Abdullah Saleh to a 5-year term. In April 1997, Yemen held its second multiparty parliamentary elections. The country held its first direct presidential elections in September 1999, electing President Ali Abdullah Saleh to a 5-year term in what were generally considered credible elections.
 
Constitutional amendments adopted in the summer of 2000 extended the presidential term by 2 years, creating a 7-year presidential term. The constitution provides that henceforth the president will be elected by popular vote from at least two candidates selected by the legislature. The amendments also extended the parliamentary term of office to a 6-year term, with the next elections supposed to take place in 2012. On February 20, 2001, a new constitutional amendment created a bicameral legislature consisting of a Shura Council (111 seats; members appointed by the president) and a House of Representatives (301 seats; members elected by popular vote). In April 2003, the third multiparty parliamentary elections were held with improvements in voter registration for both men and women and in a generally free and fair atmosphere. Two women were elected. In September 2006, citizens re-elected President Saleh to a second term in a generally open and competitive election, although there were multiple problems with the voting process and use of state resources on behalf of the ruling party.

====Destabilization and insurgency campaigns====
{{update-section|date=June 2012}}
{{Further|Sa'dah conflict|South Yemen insurgency|Yemeni al-Qaeda crackdown|2011 Yemeni uprising}}
In the 2000s the government has been fighting numerous rebel groups, such as the one led by [[Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi|Hussein al-Houthi]]'s [[Zaydi]] movement [[Shabab al-Muomineen|Shabab al-Mu'mineen]], &quot;The Young Believers&quot;. In 2009, armed insurgency also resumed in southern Yemen, led by [[South Yemen Movement]] successors. 

[[File:Yemen protest2.jpg|thumb|Protesters in Sana'a on 3 February.]]
The [[2011 Yemeni protests]] followed the initial stages of the [[Arab Spring]] and began simultaneously with the [[2011 Egyptian revolution|Egyptian Revolution]]. The protests were initially against unemployment, economic conditions and corruption, as well as against the government's proposals to modify the [[constitution of Yemen]]. The protestors' demands then escalated to calls for President [[Ali Abdullah Saleh]] to resign.

The situation however quickly deteriorated into a widescale [[2011 Yemeni uprising|uprising]], with various insurgency campaigns consolidating into an armed tribal struggles, both between the armed opposition and terror groups vs. the government and among themselves. Despite the assassination attempt on Saleh, and the eventually signed Saudi brockered agreement on Saleh's resignation the conflict kept inflicting casualties nationwide in late 2011.

==See also==
{{div col|3}}
*[[History of Asia]]
*[[History of the Middle East]]
*[[List of Kings of Yemen]]
*[[List of Presidents of Yemen]]
*[[Politics of Yemen]]
*[[South Arabia]]
*[[South Yemen]]
*[[Timeline of Yemeni history]]
*[[Yemin Shou]]
*[[Yemen]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*Original text from [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/35836.htm U.S. State Dept. Country Study]
*(1): DAUM, W. (ed.): ''Yemen. 3000 years of art and civilisation in Arabia Felix''., Innsbruck / Frankfurt am Main / Amsterdam [1988]. pp.&amp;nbsp;53–4.
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20060823035154/http://www.utcyemen.com/UTC_history.htm  History of Yemen]
*[http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/ht/04/wap/ht04wap.htm   Timeline of Art History of Arabia including Yemen (The Metropolitan Museum of Art). ]
*[http://www.saudiaramcoworld.com/issue/197802/a.dam.at.marib.htm A Dam at Marib]
*[http://www.derjemen.de/50368995620f4a811/503689956210fe324/534321971b0a80538/index.php Das Fenster zum Jemen (German)]
*[http://www.i3mainz.fh-mainz.de/dipl/d5_10/Geschichte.htm Geschichte des Jemen (German)]
*[http://www.al-bab.com/yemen/hist/hist.htm History of Yemen]

==Further reading==
*Alessandro de Maigret. ''Arabia Felix'', translated Rebecca Thompson. London: Stacey International, 2002. ISBN 1-900988-07-0
*[[Andrey Korotayev]]. ''Ancient Yemen''. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1995. ISBN 0-19-922237-1 [http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0199222371].

==External links==
*[http://www.terra.es/personal7/jqvaraderey/190523ar.gif Map of Arabia (1905-1923) including Yemen]
*[http://www.saudiaramcoworld.com/issue/197802/a.dam.at.marib.htm A Dam at Marib]
*Original text from [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5302.htm#history U.S. State Dept. Country Study] http://web.archive.org/web/20040913083237/http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/5302.htm
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20080212020702/http://www.al-bab.com/yemen/hist/hist.htm History of Yemen]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20040902081629/http://www.geocities.com/baja/dunes/3147/ Yemenite Virtual Museum] - excellent site with many pictures.
*[http://www.saudiaramcoworld.com/issue/197802/a.dam.at.marib.htm A Dam at Marib]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20071029022940/http://derjemen.de/50368995620f4a811/503689956210fe324/534321971b0a80538/index.php Das Fenster zum Jemen (German)]
*[http://www.i3mainz.fh-mainz.de/dipl/d5_10/Geschichte.htm Geschichte des Jemen (German)]
*[http://www.nationsencyclopedia.com/Asia-and-Oceania/Yemen-HISTORY.html Encyclopedia of the Nations, Asia and Oceania, Yemen]
*[http://cliodynamics.ru/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=324&amp;Itemid=70 Social History of Yemen]

{{History of Asia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Yemen}}
[[Category:History of Yemen| ]]

[[ar:تاريخ اليمن]]
[[bn:ইয়েমেন#ইতিহাস]]
[[bg:История на Йемен]]
[[ca:Història del Iemen]]
[[cs:Dějiny Jemenu]]
[[de:Geschichte des Jemen]]
[[es:Historia de Yemen]]
[[fr:Histoire du Yémen]]
[[hr:Povijest Jemena]]
[[io:Historio di Yemen]]
[[it:Storia dello Yemen]]
[[he:היסטוריה של תימן]]
[[lt:Jemeno istorija]]
[[ms:Sejarah Yaman]]
[[nl:Geschiedenis van Jemen]]
[[pt:História do Iémen]]
[[ru:История Йемена]]
[[sq:Historia e Jemenit]]
[[sh:Historija Jemena]]
[[sv:Jemens historia]]
[[uk:Історія Ємену]]</text>
      <sha1>lkj8uqxnsksqko6nt9gfe9r7jmy4dtk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
