<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of road transport</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8979498</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520777536</id>
      <parentid>520457237</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T17:53:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SchreiberBike</username>
        <id>5839411</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fix centuries to match [[WP:CENTURY]] and eliminate duplicated text.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26194">The '''history of [[road transport]]''' started with the development of tracks by humans and their beasts of burden.

== Early roads ==
The first forms of road transport were [[horse]]s, [[ox]]en or even humans carrying goods over tracks that often followed [[Game (food)|game]] [[trail]]s, such as the [[Natchez Trace]].&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p5&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Stone Age]] humans did not need constructed tracks in open country. The first improved trails would have been at [[ford (crossing)|ford]]s, [[mountain pass]]es and through swamps.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p7&lt;/ref&gt; The first improvements would have consisted largely of clearing trees and big stones from the path. As commerce increased, the tracks were often flattened or widened to accommodate human and animal traffic. Some of these dirt [[Animal tracks|tracks]] were developed into fairly extensive networks, allowing [[communication]]s, [[trade]] and [[governance]] over wide areas. The [[Inca|Incan Empire]] in [[South America]] and the [[Iroquois|Iroquois Confederation]] in [[North America]], neither of which had the wheel, are examples of effective use of such [[Trail|paths]].

The first goods transport was on human backs and heads, but the use of pack animals, including [[donkey]]s and [[horse]]s, developed during the Stone Age. The first vehicle is believed to have been the [[travois]], a frame used to drag loads, which probably developed in [[Eurasia]] after the first use of bullocks ([[castrated]] [[cattle]]) for pulling [[plough]]s. In about 5000 BC, [[sled]]s developed, which are more difficult to build than travois, but are easier to propel over smooth surfaces. Pack animals, ridden horses and bullocks dragging travois or sleds require wider paths and higher clearances than people on foot and improved tracks were required.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p25&lt;/ref&gt; As a result by about 5000 BC roads, including [[the Ridgeway]], developed along ridges in [[England]] to avoid crossing rivers and bogging.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p9&lt;/ref&gt; In central Germany, such [[ridgeway (track)|ridgeways]] remained the predominant form of long-distance road till the mid 18th century.&lt;ref&gt;Landau, Georg: Beiträge zur Geschichte der alten Heer- und Handelsstraßen in Deutschland, Kassel, Bärenreiter, 1958&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Harappan roads ===
Street paving has been found from the first human settlements around 4000 BC in cities of the [[Indus Valley Civilization]] on the [[Indian subcontinent]], such as [[Harrapa]] and [[Mohenjo-daro]].

=== Wheeled transport ===
[[Wheel]]s appear to have been developed in ancient [[Sumer]] in [[Mesopotamia]] around 5000 BC, perhaps originally for the making of pottery. Their original transport use may have been as attachments to travois or sleds to reduce resistance. It has been argued that [[Timber|logs]] were used as [[Cylindrical|rollers]] under sleds prior to the development of wheels, but there is no archeological evidence for this.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p27&lt;/ref&gt; Most early wheels appear to have been attached to fixed axles, which would have required regular lubrication by animal fats or vegetable oils or separation by leather to be effective.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lay 1992, p28&quot;&gt;Lay (1992), p28&lt;/ref&gt; The first simple two-wheel carts, apparently developed from travois, appear to have been used in Mesopotamia and northern [[Iran]] in about 3000 BC and two-wheel [[chariot]]s appeared in about 2800 BC. They were hauled by [[onager]]s, related to [[donkey]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lay 1992, p28&quot;/&gt; 

Heavy four-wheeled wagons developed about 2500 BC, which were only suitable for oxen-haulage, and therefore were only used where crops were cultivated, particularly Mesopotamia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lay 1992, p28&quot;/&gt; Two-wheeled chariots with [[spoke]]d wheels appear to have been developed around 2000 BC by the [[Andronovo culture]] in southern [[Siberia]] and [[Central Asia]]. At much the same time the first primitive [[Horse tack|harness]] enabling horse-haulage was invented.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lay 1992, p28&quot;/&gt; 

Wheeled-transport created the need for better roads. Generally natural materials cannot be both soft enough to form well-graded surfaces and strong enough to bear wheeled vehicles, especially when wet, and stay intact. In urban areas it began to be worthwhile to build stone-paved streets and, in fact, the first paved streets appear to have been built in [[Ur]] in 4000 BC. [[Corduroy road]]s were built in [[Glastonbury]], [[England]] in 3300 BC&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p51&lt;/ref&gt; and brick-paved roads were built in the [[Indus Valley Civilization]] on the [[Indian subcontinent]] from around the same time. Improvements in [[metallurgy]] meant that by 2000 BC stone-cutting tools were generally available in the Middle East and [[Greece]] allowing local streets to be paved.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p43&lt;/ref&gt; Notably, in about 2000 BC, the [[Minoan civilization|Minoans]] built a 50&amp;nbsp;km paved road from [[Knossos]] in north [[Crete]] through the mountains to [[Gortyn]] and [[Lebena]], a port on the south coast of the island, which had side drains, a 200&amp;nbsp;mm thick pavement of [[sandstone]] blocks bound with [[clay]]-[[gypsum]] [[Mortar (masonry)|mortar]], covered by a layer of [[basalt]]ic [[flagstone]]s and had separate [[Shoulder (road)|shoulders]]. This road could be considered superior to any [[Roman road]].&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p44&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Royal Road ===
In 500 BC, [[Darius I the Great]] started an extensive road system for [[Persia]] ([[Iran]]), including the famous [[Royal Road]] which was one of the finest highways of its time. The road was used even after the Roman times. Because of the road's superior quality, mail couriers could travel {{convert|2,699|km}} in seven days.

[[Image:Greek street - III century BC - Porta Rosa - Velia - Italy.JPG|right|300 px|thumb|Greek street - 4th or 3rd century BC - The Porta Rosa was the main street of [[Elea]]. It connects the northern quarter with the southern quarter. The street is five meters wide and has an incline of 18% in the steepest part.  It is paved with limestone blocks and on one side there is a small gutter for drainage.]]

=== Roman roads ===
{{main|Roman roads}}
With the advent of the [[Roman Empire]], there was a need for armies to be able to travel quickly from one area to another, and the roads that existed were often muddy, which greatly delayed the movement of large masses of troops. To solve this problem, the Romans built great roads. These '[[Roman roads]]' used deep roadbeds of crushed stone as an underlying layer to ensure that they kept dry, as the water would flow out from the crushed stone, instead of becoming mud in clay soils. The [[Roman legion|legions]] made good time on these roads and some are still used millennia later.

On the more heavily traveled routes, there were additional layers that included six sided capstones, or pavers, that reduced the dust and reduced the [[drag (physics)|drag]] from [[wheel]]s. The pavers allowed the Roman [[chariot]]s to travel very quickly, ensuring good communication with the Roman provinces. Farm roads were often paved first on the way into town, to keep produce clean. Early forms of [[spring (device)|springs]] and shocks to reduce the bumps were incorporated in horse drawn transport, as the original pavers were sometimes not perfectly aligned.

Roman roads deteriorated in [[Middle Ages|medieval Europe]] because of lack of resources and skills to maintain them, but many continued to be used. The alignments are still partially used today, for instance, parts of [[England]]'s [[A1 road (Great Britain)|A1]].

=== Early tar-paved roads ===
In the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic world]], many roads were built throughout the [[Caliphate|Arab Empire]]. The most sophisticated roads were those of the [[Baghdad]], [[Iraq]], which were paved with [[tar]] in the 8th century. Tar was derived from [[petroleum]], accessed from [[oil field]]s in the region, through the chemical process of [[destructive distillation]].&lt;ref name=Ajram&gt;{{cite book|author=Dr. Kasem Ajram|title=The Miracle of Islam Science|edition=2nd Edition|publisher=Knowledge House Publishers|year=1992|id=ISBN 0-911119-43-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{anchor|New construction methods in the 18th and 19th centuries}}
== New construction methods in the 18th and 19th centuries ==
As states developed and became richer, especially with the [[Renaissance]], new roads and bridges began to be built, often based on Roman designs. Although there were attempts to rediscover Roman methods, there was little useful innovation in road building before the 18th century.

Between 1725 and 1737 General [[George Wade]] constructed {{convert|250|mi|km}} of road and 40 bridges to improve [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Britain]]'s control of the [[Scottish Highlands]], using Roman road designs with large stones at the bottom and gravel on top, with a typical overall depth of two metres. They were so poorly aligned and steep, according to [[Thomas Telford]], &quot;as to be unfit for the purposes of civil life&quot; and also rough and poorly drained.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lay 1992, p72&quot;&gt;Lay (1992), p72&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Toll roads ===
==== England and Wales ====
{{main|turnpike trust}}

As traffic increased in England, roads deteriorated.  [[Toll road]]s were built by ''Turnpike Trusts'', especially between 1730-1770.  It has been claimed that as a result the time taken between London, to York, Manchester or Exeter was cut by two-thirds between 1720 and 1780.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last =Huxford
  | first =Robert 
  | title =How old is that route?
  | publisher =[[Institution of Civil Engineers]]
  | date = 3 September 2003
  | url =http://www.ice.org.uk/downloads//BS-History_of_Routes.pdf
  | format =pdf
  | accessdate = 2007-01-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Metcalf (civil engineer)|Blind Jack Metcalf]] (1717–1810) built about {{convert|300|km|mi|abbr=on}} of [[turnpike trust|turnpike road]] between 1753 and 1810, mainly in [[Lancashire]], [[Derbyshire]], [[Cheshire]] and [[Yorkshire]].  He understood the importance of good drainage and surfaced his roads with &quot;a compact layer of small, broken stones with sharp edges&quot;, rather than the naturally rounded stones traditionally used in European road building.  British turnpike builders began to realise the importance of selecting clean stones for surfacing, and excluding vegetable material and clay to make better lasting roads.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lay 1992, p72&quot;/&gt;

==== United States of America ====
[[Image:Highways USA 1825.png|thumb|Highways in the USA circa 1825]]
Turnpikes were also later built in the [[United States]].  They were usually built by private companies under a government franchise. They typically paralleled or replaced routes already with some volume of commerce, hoping the improved road would divert enough traffic to make the enterprise profitable. [[Plank road]]s were particularly attractive as they greatly reduced rolling resistance and mitigated the problem of getting mired in mud. Another improvement, better grading to lessen the steepness of the worst stretches, allowed draft animals to haul heavier loads.

Water transport on rivers and [[canals]] carried many farm goods from the frontier U.S. (between the Appalachian mountains and Mississippi River) in the early 19th century, but the shorter route over the mountains had advantages.  Successful farms created a demand for imported and manufactured goods from the Atlantic coast.  The commercial interests of the East were quick to see the possibilities of this new market.  An eager rivalry sprung up between the merchants of New York, Philadelphia, and Baltimore.  Everywhere ways and means of cheaper transportation were discussed.  In this subject the western farmer was vitally interested, for freight charges added nearly one third to the cost of merchandise transported over the mountains.  The cotton planter of the Seaboard States, also, feeling the competition of the Southwest, where riverways were abundant and easily navigable, saw the need of better roads to tidewater, in order to lessen the cost of marketing his produce.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson (1915), p254-255&lt;/ref&gt;

The popular demand for better roads was not recent.  All the states had encouraged, directly or indirectly, the building of turnpikes and bridges.  Between 1793 and 1812, Pennsylvania had chartered fifty-five turnpike companies, and other states had been scarcely less ready to grant articles of incorporation to stock companies.  Private enterprise had, indeed, done much to improve communication along the seaboard.  As the system became interconnected, turnpikes and bridges had shortened the journey from Boston to Washington by [[stagecoach]] to four and a quarter days by the year 1815.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson (1915), p255&lt;/ref&gt;  While having power over coastal trade and defense issues, the federal power over domestic &quot;[[internal improvements]]&quot;, away from the coasts and among the states, did not gain political consensus.  Federal assistance for &quot;internal improvements&quot; evolved slowly and haphazardly—the product of contentious congressional factions and an executive branch generally concerned with avoiding unconstitutional federal intrusions into state affairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;CoE-Trans&quot;/&gt;

In [[Federalist]] President [[John Adams]]' first message to Congress, he advocated not only the construction of roads and canals on a national basis but also the establishment of [[observatory|observatories]] and a national university.  Later, in 1806 [[Democratic-Republican]] President Jefferson also had recommended many internal improvements for Congress to consider, including the creation of necessary amendments to the Constitution to allow themselves such powers.  Adams did not share Jefferson's view of the limitations of the Constitution.  In much alarm Jefferson suggested to Madison the desirability of having Virginia adopt a new set of resolutions, bottomed on those of 1798, and directed against the acts for internal improvements.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Johnson|1915|pp=319–320}}&lt;/ref&gt;    

The magnitude of the transportation problem was such, however, that neither individual states nor private corporations seemed able to meet the demands of an expanding internal trade.  As early as 1807, [[Albert Gallatin]] had advocated the construction of a great system of internal waterways to connect East and West, at an estimated cost of $20,000,000.  But the only contribution of the national government to internal improvements during the Jeffersonian era was an appropriation in 1806 of two percent of the net proceeds of the sales of public lands in Ohio for the construction of a national road, with the consent of the states through which it should pass.  By 1818 the road was open to traffic from [[Cumberland, Maryland]], to Wheeling, West Virginia.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson (1915), p256&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1816, with the experiences of the war before him, no well-informed statesman could shut his eyes to the national aspects of the problem.  Even President Madison invited the attention of Congress to the need of establishing &quot;a comprehensive system of roads and canals&quot;.  Soon after Congress met, it took under consideration a bill drafted by Calhoun which proposed an appropriation of $1,500,000 for internal improvements.  Because this appropriation was to be met by the moneys paid by the National Bank to the government, the bill was commonly referred to as the &quot;Bonus Bill&quot;.  But on the day before he left office, President Madison vetoed the bill because it was unconstitutional.  The policy of internal improvements by federal aid was thus wrecked on the constitutional scruples of a member of the Virginia dynasty.  Nevertheless, road and canal construction soon began, with private businesses and state and local governments funding much of the work.  Having less regard for consistency, the House of Representatives recorded its conviction, by close votes, that Congress could appropriate money to construct roads and canals, but had not the power to construct them.  As yet the only direct aid of the national government to internal improvements consisted of various appropriations, amounting to about $1,500,000 for the [[Cumberland Road]].&lt;ref&gt;Johnson (1915), p257-258&lt;/ref&gt;

As the country recovered from financial depression following the [[Panic of 1819]], the question of internal improvements again forged to the front.  In 1822, a bill to authorize the collection of tolls on the Cumberland Road had been vetoed by the President.  In an elaborate essay Monroe set forth his views on the constitutional aspects of a policy of internal improvements.  Congress might appropriate money, he admitted, but it might not undertake the actual construction of national works nor assume jurisdiction over them.  For the moment the drift toward a larger participation of the national government in internal improvements was stayed.  

The situation would change dramatically two years later however, with the [[Judicial Branch]] of government weighing in on related constitutional questions and ruling on them with some finality.  In March 1824 the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] ruled on [[Gibbons v. Ogden]], in what would become [[List of landmark court decisions in the United States|a landmark decision]]; the Court held that the power to regulate interstate commerce was granted to [[United States Congress|Congress]] by the [[Commerce Clause]] of the [[United States Constitution]].  The Court went on to conclude that Congressional power over commerce should extend to the regulation of all aspects of it, overriding state law to the contrary.  

In the debate that followed, no one pleaded more eloquently for a larger conception of the functions of the national government than Speaker of the House [[Henry Clay]], the foremost proponent of the '[[American System]]'.  He called the attention of his hearers to provisions made for coast surveys and lighthouses on the Atlantic seaboard and deplored the neglect of the interior of the country.  Of the other presidential candidates, Senator and war-hero [[Andrew Jackson]] voted for the General Survey Act, as did Secretary of State John Quincy Adams, who left no doubt in the public mind that he did not reflect the narrow views of his New England region on this issue.  [[William H. Crawford]] felt the constitutional scruples which were everywhere being voiced in the South, and followed the old expedient of advocating a constitutional amendment to sanction national internal improvements.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Johnson|1915|pp=309–310}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly thereafter, Congress passed two important laws that would set a new course concerning federal involvement in &quot;internal improvements&quot;.   In April Congress passed the [[General Survey Act]], which authorized the president to have surveys made of routes for roads and canals &quot;of national importance, in a commercial or military point of view, or necessary for the transportation of public mail;&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CoE-Trans&quot;&gt;[http://www.usace.army.mil/History/Documents/Brief/03-transportation/transport.html Improving Transportation], [[United States Army Corps of Engineers]] (USACE)&lt;/ref&gt;  this is sometimes refereed to as the first &quot;Roads and Canals&quot; Act.&lt;ref name=&quot;CARivDev&quot;/&gt;  It authorized the survey of waterways to designate those &quot;capable of sloop navigation.&quot;  The second act, &quot;An Act to Improve the Navigation of the Ohio and Mississippi Rivers,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CARivDev&quot;&gt;[http://www.caria.org/iwns_timeline.html Timeline: Development of US Inland Waterways System], Coosa-Alabama River Improvement Association, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt; was passed in May; it appropriated $75,000 to improve navigation on the Ohio and Mississippi rivers by removing sandbars, snags, and other obstacles; the second act is often called the first [[River and Harbor Act|rivers and harbors legislation]].  The president assigned responsibility for the road, canal and waterway surveys as well as the navigation improvements to the Corps of Engineers.  This legislation marked the beginning of the USACE's continuous involvement in domestic civil works.&lt;ref name=&quot;CoE-Trans&quot;/&gt; 

Some political differences did remain; in March, 1826, the Virginia general assembly declared that all the principles of their earlier resolutions applied &quot;will full force against the powers assumed by Congress&quot; in passing acts to further internal improvements and to protect manufacturers.  That the John Quincy Adams administration would meet with opposition in Congress was a foregone conclusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Johnson|1915|pp=319–320}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Trésaguet's work in France ===
In France, [[Pierre-Marie-Jérôme Trésaguet]] is widely credited with establishing the first [[scientific method|scientific approach]] to [[road building]] about the year 1764. He wrote a memorandum on his method in 1775, which became general practice in France.  It involved a layer of large rocks, covered by a layer of smaller gravel.  The lower layer improved on Roman practice in that it was based on the understanding that the purpose of this layer (the sub-base or [[base course]]) is to transfer the weight of the road and its traffic to the ground, while protecting the ground from deformation by spreading the weight evenly.  Therefore, the sub-base did not have to be a self-supporting structure.  The upper running surface provided a smooth surface for vehicles, while protecting the large stones of the sub-base.  Trésaguet understood the importance of drainage by providing deep side ditches, but he insisted on building his roads in trenches, so that they could be accessed from the sides, which undermined this principle.  Well-maintained surfaces and drains protect the integrity of the sub-base and Trésaguet introduced a system of continuous maintenance, where a roadman was allocated a section of road to be kept up to a standard.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p73-74&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Developments in Britain ===
==== Telford ====
[[Thomas Telford]] (1757–1834) a [[Scottish people|Scottish]] surveyor and engineer also made substantial advances in the engineering of new roads and the construction of bridges.  Under his supervision 1,500&amp;nbsp;km of roads and 1,000 bridges were built in [[Scotland]] between 1802 and 1822.  He elaborated on the Trésaguet method by a more complex and costly system of stonework in the subgrade, but his main improvement over Trésaguet was the raising of his roads above the natural level to improve drainage or the drainage of the area around the road.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p75&lt;/ref&gt;  

==== McAdam ====
[[John Loudon McAdam]] (1756–1836), another [[Scottish people|Scottish]] engineer, designed the first modern roads. He developed an inexpensive paving material of soil and stone aggregate (known as [[macadam]]).  He had noticed in his observations that [[Coach (vehicle)|coaches]] with narrow, iron-tyred wheels and moving at relatively high speed were causing significant damage to roads, but that areas of small broken stones were most resistant to damage, while the areas that had large surface stones degraded fastest.  His solution was to create roads with three layers of stones laid on a crowned [[subgrade]] with side ditches for drainage. The first two layers consisted of angular hand-broken [[Aggregate (composite)|aggregate]], maximum size 3 inches (75&amp;nbsp;mm), to a total depth of about 8&amp;nbsp;inches (200&amp;nbsp;mm). The third layer was about 2&amp;nbsp;inches (50&amp;nbsp;mm) thick with a maximum aggregate size of 1&amp;nbsp;inch (25&amp;nbsp;mm). Each layer would be compacted with a heavy [[Road roller|roller]], causing the angular stones to lock together with their neighbours.  It is possible that his initial decision not to use the heavy layer of base stones used by Telford in his subgrade reflected lack of suitable stones, but McAdam quickly saw they were not necessary.  In practice, his roads proved to be twice as strong as Telford's roads.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p77&lt;/ref&gt;  He also insisted on raising the roads to ensure good drainage and flat crowned surfaces, rather than ridges built into the road to encourage drainage.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p78&lt;/ref&gt;    

McAdam was adamantly opposed to the filling of the voids between his small cut stones with smaller material, possibly as a reaction against the use of poor materials, including soil and vegetable matter, on roads in the past.  Nevertheless, in practice road builders began to introduce filler materials such as smaller stones, sand and clay, and it was observed that these roads were stronger as a result.  Macadam roads were being built widely in the United States and Australia in the 1820s and in Europe in the 1830s and 1840s.&lt;ref&gt;Lay (1992), p83&lt;/ref&gt;

== Development of modern paved roads ==
Various systems had been developed over centuries to reduce [[washaway]]s, bogging and dust in cities, including [[cobblestone]]s and wooden paving.  Tar-bound macadam ([[tarmac]]) was applied to macadam roads towards the end of the 19th century in cities such as [[Paris]].  In the early 20th century tarmac and concrete paving were extended into the countryside.

Incidentally, bicyclists were among the early campaigners on what was called the [[Good Roads Movement]].  Bicycling was an extremely popular recreation among the middle and upper classes in the late 19th century and was more fun on paved roads.

== See also ==
* [[Auto trail]]s in the United States
* [[Caravanserai]]
* [[Dromography]]
* [[Trade route]]
* [[Horses in the Middle Ages]]

== References ==
* {{cite book
  | last =Johnson
  | first =Allen
  | authorlink =Allen Johnson (teacher)
  | title =Union and Democracy
  | publisher =Houghton Mifflin Company
  | year =1915
  | location =Cambridge, Massachusetts
}}
* {{cite book
  | last =Lay
  | first =M G 
  | authorlink =
  | title = Ways of the World
  | publisher =Primavera Press
  | year =1992
  | location =Sydney 
  | pages =401
  | id = ISBN 1-875368-05-1  }}

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://curbstone.com/_macadam.htm Macadam - Road Building in America]
* [http://www.vehiclerecovery.org/history/index.htm UK Vehicle Recovery History]

{{DEFAULTSORT:History of road transport}}
[[Category:Road transport|Road transport]]
[[Category:History of road transport| ]]
[[Category:Pavements|Road transport]]
[[Category:History of transport]]</text>
      <sha1>licegag8ei3yv9vi7qi1xauhq2ujfny</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
