<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of rail transport</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>211919</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516155556</id>
      <parentid>516155226</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-05T14:37:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>156.110.24.142</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reversed apparent vandalism.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="55103">{{trainstopics}}
{{stack begin|clear=true}}
[[File:HorseRailway-1-.jpg|thumbnail|250px|right|Horse drawn railway coach, late 18th century]]
[[File:Railwayneteurope1896.JPG|thumb|250px|right|Density of the railway net in Europe 1896]]
{{stack end}}
The '''history of rail transport''' dates back nearly 500 years and includes systems with man or horse power and [[rail tracks|rails]] of wood or stone.  Modern [[rail transport]] systems first appeared in England in the 1820s.  These systems, which made use of the [[steam locomotive]], were the first practical forms of mechanized land transport, and they remained the primary form of mechanized land transport for the next 100 years.

==Wagonways and tramways==

===Earliest traces===
The earliest evidence of a [[wagonway]], a predecessor of the railway, found so far was the 6 to 8.5&amp;nbsp;km long ''[[Diolkos]]'' wagonway, which transported boats across the [[Isthmus of Corinth]] in Greece since around 600 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot; Verdelis, Nikolaos (1957), 526&quot;&gt;Verdelis, Nikolaos: &quot;Le diolkos de L'Isthme&quot;, ''Bulletin de Correspondance Hellénique'', Vol. 81 (1957), pp. 526–529 (526)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cook, R. M. (1979), 152&quot;&gt;Cook, R. M.: &quot;Archaic Greek Trade: Three Conjectures 1. The Diolkos&quot;, ''The Journal of Hellenic Studies'', Vol. 99 (1979), pp. 152–155 (152)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Drijvers, J.W. (1992), 75&quot;&gt;Drijvers, J.W.: &quot;Strabo VIII 2,1 (C335): Porthmeia and the Diolkos&quot;, ''Mnemosyne'', Vol. 45 (1992), pp. 75–76 (75)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Raepsaet, G. &amp; Tolley, M. (1993), 256&quot;&gt;[[Georges Raepsaet|Raepsaet, G.]] &amp; Tolley, M.: &quot;Le Diolkos de l’Isthme à Corinthe: son tracé, son fonctionnement&quot;, ''Bulletin de Correspondance Hellénique'', Vol. 117 (1993), pp. 233–261 (256)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis, M. J. T. (2001), 11&quot;&gt;Lewis, M. J. T., [http://www.sciencenews.gr/docs/diolkos.pdf &quot;Railways in the Greek and Roman world&quot;], in Guy, A. / Rees, J. (eds), ''Early Railways. A Selection of Papers from the First International Early Railways Conference'' (2001), pp. 8–19 (11)&lt;/ref&gt; Wheeled vehicles pulled by men and animals ran in grooves in [[limestone]], which provided the track element, preventing the wagons from leaving the intended route. The Diolkos was in use for over 650 years, until at least the 1st century AD.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis, M. J. T. (2001), 11&quot;/&gt;  The first horse-drawn wagonways also appeared in ancient [[Greece]], with others to be found on [[Malta]] and various parts of the [[Roman Empire]], using cut-stone tracks.

Railways began reappearing in Europe after the [[Dark Ages (historiography)|Dark Ages]]. The earliest known record of a railway in Europe from this period is a stained-glass window in the [[Freiburg Minster|Minster of Freiburg im Breisgau]] dating from around 1350.&lt;ref name=GrandExperiment&gt;{{cite book |last=Hylton |first=Stuart |title=The Grand Experiment: The Birth of the Railway Age 1820–1845 |publisher=Ian Allan Publishing |year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1515, [[Matthäus Lang|Cardinal Matthäus Lang]] wrote a description of the [[Reisszug]], a [[funicular|funicular railway]] at the [[Hohensalzburg Castle]] in Austria. The line originally used wooden rails and a [[hemp]] haulage rope, and was operated by human or animal power, through a [[treadwheel]]. The line still exists, albeit in updated form, and is probably the oldest railway still to operate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first = Reinhard | last = Kriechbaum | url = http://www.die-tagespost.de/Archiv/titel_anzeige.asp?ID=8916 | title = Die große Reise auf den Berg | work = der Tagespost | date = 2004-05-15 | accessdate = 2009-04-22 | language = German}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fm1&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.funimag.com/funimag10/RESZUG01.HTM | title = Der Reiszug – Part 1 – Presentation | publisher = Funimag | accessdate = 2009-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early wagonways===
{{Main|Wagonways}}
[[File:Leitnagel Hund (Mining cart).png|thumbnail|250px|right|[[Minecart]] shown in ''[[De Re Metallica]]'' (1556). The guide pin fits in a groove between two wooden planks.]]
Wagonways (or ''''tramways'''') are thought to have developed in Germany in the 1550s to facilitate the transport of ore tubs to and from mines, utilising primitive wooden rails. Such an operation was illustrated in 1556 by [[Georgius Agricola]] (Image right).&lt;ref&gt;Georgius Agricola (trans Hoover), ''[[De re metallica]]'' (1913), p. 156&lt;/ref&gt;  These used  &quot;Hund&quot; carts with unflanged wheels running on wooden planks and a vertical pin on the truck fitting into the gap between the planks, to keep it going the right way.&lt;ref&gt;The miners called the wagons ''Hund'' — &quot;dog&quot; — from the noise they made on the tracks. {{cite book|last=Lee|first=Charles E|title=The Evolution of Railways|edition=2|year=1943|publisher=Railway Gazette|location=London|page=16|oclc=1591369}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Such a transport system was used by German miners at [[Caldbeck]], [[Cumbria]], perhaps from the 1560s.&lt;ref&gt;Warren Allison, Samuel Murphy, and Richard Smith, 'An Early Railway in the German Mines of Caldbeck' in G. Boyes (ed.), ''Early Railways 4: Papers from the 4th International Early Railways Conference 2008'' (Six Martlets, Sudbury, 2010), 52–69.&lt;/ref&gt;
The first true railway is now suggested to have been a [[Funicular|funicular railway]] made at [[Broseley]] in [[Shropshire]] at some time before 1605.  This carried coal for James Clifford from his mines down to the [[river Severn]] to be loaded on to barges and carried to riverside towns.&lt;ref&gt;Peter King, ‘The First Shropshire Railways’ in G. Boyes (ed.), ''Early Railways 4: Papers from the 4th International Early Railways Conference 2008'' (Six Martlets, Sudbury, 2010), 70–84.&lt;/ref&gt;  Though the first documentary record of this is later, its construction probably preceded the [[Wollaton Waggonway|Wollaton Wagonway]], completed in 1604, hitherto regarded as the earliest British installation.  This ran from [[Strelley, Nottingham|Strelley]] to [[Wollaton]] near [[Nottingham]].  Another early [[wagonway]] is noted onwards.  [[Huntingdon Beaumont]] (who was concerned with mining at [[Strelley]]) also laid down broad wooden rails near [[Newcastle upon Tyne]], on which a single horse could haul fifty or sixty [[bushel]]s (130–150&amp;nbsp;kg) of coal.&lt;ref&gt;M. J. T. Lewis, ''Early Wooden railways''.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 18th century, such wagonways and tramways existed in a number of areas. Ralph Allen, for example, constructed a tramway to transport stone from a local quarry to supply the needs of the builders of the Georgian terraces of [[Bath, Somerset|Bath]]. The [[Battle of Prestonpans]], in the [[Jacobite Rebellion]], was fought astride a wagonway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ransom|first=Philip|title=The archaeology of railways|publisher=World's Work|location=Tadworth, England|year=1981|page=268|isbn=978-0-437-14401-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This type of transport spread rapidly through the whole [[Tyneside]] coal-field, and the greatest number of lines were to be found in the coalfield near [[Newcastle upon Tyne]].  Their function in most cases was to facilitate the transport of coal in [[chaldron]] wagons from the coalpits to a [[staithe]] (a wooden pier) on the river bank, whence coal could be shipped to London by [[collier brigs]]. The wagonways were engineered so that trains of coal wagons could descend to the staithe by gravity, being braked by a brakesman who would &quot;sprag&quot; the wheels by jamming them. Wagonways on less steep gradients could be retarded by allowing the wheels to bind on curves. As the work became more wearing on the horses, a vehicle known as a [[dandy wagon]] was introduced, in which the horse could rest on downhill stretches.

===Rails===
Because a stiff wheel rolling on a rigid rail requires less energy per ton-mile moved than road transport (with a highly compliant wheel on an uneven surface), railroads are highly suitable for the movement of dense, bulk goods such as coal and other minerals. This was incentive to focus a great deal of inventiveness upon the possible configurations and shapes of wheels and rails. In the late 1760s, the [[Coalbrookdale]] Company began to fix plates of [[cast iron]] to the upper surface of the wooden rails.  These (and earlier railways) had [[flange]]d wheels as on modern railways, but another system was introduced, in which unflanged wheels ran on L-shaped metal plates – these became known as plateways.  [[John Curr]], a Sheffield colliery manager, invented this flanged rail, though the exact date of this is disputed. The plate rail was taken up by [[Benjamin Outram]] for wagonways serving his canals, manufacturing them at his [[Butterley Company|Butterley ironworks]]. Meanwhile [[William Jessop]], a [[civil engineer]], had used a form of edge rail successfully for an extension to the [[Charnwood Forest Canal]] at [[Nanpantan]], [[Loughborough]], [[Leicestershire]] in 1789. Jessop became a partner in the Butterley Company in 1790.  The flanged wheel eventually proved its superiority due to its performance on curves, and the composite iron/wood rail was replaced by all metal rail, with its vastly superior stiffness, durability, and safety.

The introduction of the [[Bessemer process]] for making cheap steel led to the era of great expansion of railways that began in the late 1860s.  Steel rails lasted several times longer than iron.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wells1891&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|title=Recent Economic Changes and Their Effect on Production and Distribution of Wealth and Well-Being of Society
|last=Wells
 |first=David A.
|authorlink=
|coauthors=
|year=1891 |publisher= D. Appleton and Co.|location= New York|isbn= 0-543-72474-3 |pages= |url= http://books.google.com/?id=2V3qF4MWh_wC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=RECENT+ECONOMIC+CHANGES+AND+THEIR+EFFECT+ON+DISTRIBUTION+OF+WEALTH+AND+WELL+BEING+OF+SOCIETY+WELLS#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Grubler1990&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
 | last1 = Grübler
 | first1 = Arnulf
 | author1-link =
 | title = The Rise and Fall of Infrastructures: Dynamics of Evolution and Technological Change in Transport
 | year = 1990
|publisher=Physica-Verlag
|location= Heidelberg and New York
|isbn=
|pages=
 | url = http://www.iiasa.ac.at/Admin/PUB/Documents/XB-90-704.pdf
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Railroads and American Economic Growth: Essays in Econometric History |last=Fogel |first=Robert W.|authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1964 |publisher=The John Hopkins Press |location=Baltimore and London |isbn= 0-8018-1148-1 |pages= |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Steam power introduced===
[[James Watt]], a Scottish inventor and mechanical engineer, was responsible for improvements to the [[steam engine]] of [[Thomas Newcomen]], hitherto used to pump water out of mines. Watt developed a [[reciprocating engine]], capable of powering a wheel. Although the Watt engine powered cotton mills and a variety of machinery, it was a large [[stationary engine]]. It could not be otherwise; the state of boiler technology necessitated the use of low pressure steam acting upon a vacuum in the cylinder, and this mode of operation needed a separate [[Condenser (heat transfer)|condenser]] and an [[air pump]]. Nevertheless, as the construction of boilers improved, he investigated the use of high pressure steam acting directly upon a piston. This raised the possibility of a smaller engine, that might be used to power a vehicle, and he actually patented a design for  a [[steam locomotive]] in 1784.  His employee [[William Murdoch]] produced a working model of a self-propelled steam carriage in that year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Gordon
  | first =W.J.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Our Home Railways, volume one
  | publisher =Frederick Warne and Co
  | year =1910
  | location =London
  | pages =7–9
  | url =
  | doi =
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:TrevithicksEngine.jpg|thumb|250px|A replica of Trevithick's engine at the [[National Waterfront Museum]], Swansea]]
The first working model of a steam rail locomotive was designed and constructed by [[John Fitch (inventor)|John Fitch]] in the United States in 1794.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nps.gov/history/history/online_books/steamtown/shs2.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;  The first full scale working railway [[steam locomotive]] was built in the United Kingdom in 1804  by [[Richard Trevithick]], an English engineer born in [[Cornwall]]. (The story goes that it was constructed to satisfy a bet by [[Samuel Homfray]], the local iron master.) This used high pressure steam to drive the engine by one power stroke. (The transmission system employed a large fly-wheel to even out the action of the piston rod.) On 21 February 1804 the world's first railway journey took place as Trevithick's unnamed [[steam locomotive]] hauled a train along the [[Rail transport|tramway]] of the [[Penydarren]] ironworks, near [[Merthyr Tydfil]] in [[South Wales]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.museumwales.ac.uk/en/rhagor/article/trevithic_loco/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title       = Steam train anniversary begins
| url         = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/3509961.stm
| publisher   = BBC
| accessdate  = 2009-06-13
| quote       = A south Wales town has begun months of celebrations to mark the 200th anniversary of the invention of the steam locomotive. Merthyr Tydfil was the location where, on 21 February 1804, Richard Trevithick took the world into the railway age when he set one of his high-pressure steam engines on a local iron master's tram rails
| date=21 February 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Trevithick later demonstrated a locomotive operating upon a piece of circular rail track in Bloomsbury, London, the &quot;Catch-Me-Who-Can&quot;, but never got beyond the experimental stage with railway locomotives, not least because his engines were too heavy for the cast-iron plateway track then in use. Despite his inventive talents, Richard Trevithick died in poverty, with his achievement being largely unrecognized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Pictorial Encyclopedia of Railways |author=Hamilton Ellis |publisher=The Hamlyn Publishing Group |year=1968 |page=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The impact of the [[Napoleonic Wars]] resulted in (amongst other things) a dramatic rise in the price of fodder. This was the imperative that made the [[locomotive]] an economic proposition, if it could be perfected.

The first commercially successful steam locomotive was [[Matthew Murray]]'s [[rack railway|rack]] locomotive ''[[The Salamanca|Salamanca]]'' built for the [[narrow gauge railway|narrow gauge]] [[Middleton Railway]] in 1812. This twin cylinder locomotive was not heavy enough to break the [[wagonway|edge-rails]] track, and solved the problem of [[Rail adhesion|adhesion]] by a [[cog-wheel]] utilising teeth cast on the side of one of the rails. It was the first [[rack railway]].

This was followed in 1813 by the ''[[Puffing Billy (locomotive)|Puffing Billy]]'' built by [[Blackett of Wylam|Christopher Blackett]] and [[William Hedley]] for the Wylam Colliery Railway, the first successful locomotive running by [[Rail adhesion|adhesion]] only. This was accomplished by the distribution of weight by a number of wheels. Puffing Billy is now on display in the [[Science Museum (London)|Science Museum]] in London, the oldest locomotive in existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Pictorial Encyclopedia of Railways |author=Hamilton Ellis |publisher=The Hamlyn Publishing Group |year=1968 |pages=20–22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1814 [[George Stephenson]], inspired by the early locomotives of Trevithick, Murray and Hedley, persuaded the manager of the [[Killingworth]] [[Coal mining|colliery]] where he worked to allow him to build a [[Steam engine|steam-powered]] machine.  He built the ''[[Blücher (locomotive)|Blücher]]'', one of the first successful [[flange]]d-wheel adhesion locomotives. Stephenson played a pivotal role in the development and widespread adoption of the steam locomotive. His designs considerably improved on the work of the earlier pioneers. In 1825 he built the ''[[Locomotion No 1|Locomotion]]'' for the [[Stockton and Darlington Railway]] in the north east of England, which was the first public steam railway in the world. Such success led to Stephenson establishing his company as the pre-eminent builder of steam locomotives used on railways in the United Kingdom, United States and much of Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Pictorial Encyclopedia of Railways |author=Hamilton Ellis |publisher=The Hamlyn Publishing Group |year=1968 |pages=24–30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Britain==
{{Main|History of rail transport in Great Britain}}
As the colliery and quarry tramways and wagonways grew longer, the possibility of using the technology for the public conveyance of goods suggested itself. On 26 July 1803, Jessop opened the [[Surrey Iron Railway]] in south London – arguably, the world's first public railway, albeit a horse-drawn one. It was not a railway in the modern sense of the word, as it functioned like a [[turnpike road]]. There were no official services, as anyone could bring a vehicle on the railway by paying a toll.

In 1812, [[Oliver Evans]], an American engineer and inventor, published his vision of what steam railways could become, with cities and towns linked by a network of long distance railways plied by speedy locomotives, greatly reducing the time required for personal travel and for transport of goods. Evans specified that there should be separate sets of parallel tracks for trains going in different directions. Unfortunately, conditions in the infant United States did not enable his vision to take hold.

This vision had its counterpart in Britain, where it proved to be far more influential. [[William James (railway promoter)|William James]], a rich and influential surveyor and land agent, was inspired by the development of the steam locomotive to suggest a national network of railways. It seems likely &lt;ref name=Macnair&gt;{{cite book|author=Macnair, Miles|title=William James (1771–1837): the man who discovered George Stephenson|publisher=[[Railway and Canal Historical Society]]|location=Oxford|year=2007|isbn=978-0-901461-54-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 1808 James attended the demonstration running of [[Richard Trevithick]]’s [[steam locomotive]] ''[[Catch me who can]]'' in London; certainly at this time he began to consider the long-term development of this means of transport. He was responsible for proposing a number of projects that later came to fruition, and he is credited with carrying out a survey of the [[Liverpool and Manchester Railway]]. Unfortunately, he became bankrupt and his schemes were taken over by George Stephenson and others. However, he is credited by many historians with the title of &quot;Father of the Railway&quot;.&lt;ref name=Macnair&gt;{{cite book|author=Miles Macnair|title=William James (1771–1837): the man who discovered George Stephenson|publisher=[[Railway and Canal Historical Society]]|location=Oxford|year=2007|isbn=978-0-901461-54-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was not until 1825 that the success of the [[Stockton and Darlington Railway]] proved that the railways could be made as useful to the general shipping public as to the colliery owner.  This railway broke new ground by using rails made of [[rolling mill|rolled]] [[wrought iron]], produced at [[Bedlington Ironworks]] in [[Northumberland]].&lt;ref&gt;A. Pacey, ''Technology in World Civilisation'' (MIT Press, Cambridge, Mass. 1990), 135.&lt;/ref&gt;  Such rails were stronger. This railway linked the town of [[Darlington]] with the port of [[Stockton-on-Tees]], and was intended to enable local collieries (which were connected to the line by short branches) to transport their coal to the docks. As this would constitute the bulk of the traffic, the company took the important step of offering to haul the colliery wagons or chaldrons by locomotive power, something that required a scheduled or timetabled service of trains. However, the line also functioned as a toll railway, where private horse drawn wagons could be operated upon it. This curious hybrid of a system (which also included, at one stage, a horse drawn passenger wagon) could not last, and within a few years, traffic was restricted to timetabled trains. (However, the tradition of private owned wagons continued on railways in Britain until the 1960s.)

The success of the Stockton and Darlington encouraged the rich investors of the rapidly industrialising [[North West of England]] to embark upon a project to link the rich cotton manufacturing town of [[Manchester]] with the thriving port of [[Liverpool]]. The [[Liverpool and Manchester Railway]] was the first modern railway, in that both the goods and passenger traffic was operated by scheduled or timetabled locomotive hauled trains. At the time of its construction, there was still a serious doubt that locomotives could maintain a regular service over the distance involved. A widely reported competition was held in 1829 called the [[Rainhill Trials]], to find the most suitable [[steam engine]] to haul the [[train]]s. A number of locomotives were entered, including [[Novelty (locomotive)|Novelty]], [[Perseverance (steam locomotive)|Perseverance]], and [[Sans Pareil]]. The winner was [[Stephenson's Rocket]], which had superior steaming qualities as a consequence of the installation of a [[Fire-tube boiler|multi-tubular boiler]] (suggested by [[Henry Booth]], a director of the railway company).

[[File:Planet replica.jpg|thumb|250px|A replica of the ''Planet'', which ran on the [[Liverpool and Manchester Railway]] from 1830]]
The promoters were mainly interested in goods traffic, but after the line opened on 15 September 1830, they found to their amazement that passenger traffic was just as remunerative. The success of the Liverpool and Manchester railway influenced the development of railways elsewhere in Britain and abroad. The company hosted many visiting deputations from other railway projects, and many railwaymen received their early training and experience upon this line.

It must be remembered that the Liverpool and Manchester line was still a short one ({{convert|35|mi|km|0}}), linking two towns within an English [[shire county]]. The world's first trunk line can be said to be the [[Grand Junction Railway]], opening in 1837, and linking a midpoint on the Liverpool and Manchester Railway with [[Birmingham]], by way of [[Crewe]], [[Stafford]], and [[Wolverhampton]].

===Further development===

The earliest locomotives in revenue service were small four-wheeled locos similar to the Rocket. However, the inclined cylinders caused the engine to rock, so they first became horizontal and then, in his &quot;Planet&quot; design, were mounted inside the frames. While this improved stability, the &quot;crank axles&quot; were extremely prone to breakage. Greater speed was achieved by larger driving wheels at expense of a tendency for wheel slip when starting. Greater tractive effort was obtained by smaller wheels coupled together, but speed was limited by the fragility of the cast iron connecting rods. Hence, from the beginning, there was a distinction between the light fast passenger loco and the slower more powerful goods engine. [[Edward Bury and Company|Edward Bury]], in particular, refined this design and the so-called [[Bury Bar Frame locomotive|&quot;Bury Pattern&quot;]] was popular for a number of years, particularly on the [[London and Birmingham Railway|London and Birmingham]].

Meanwhile, by 1840, Stephenson had produced larger, more stable, engines in the form of the [[2-2-2]] [[Patentee locomotive|&quot;Patentee&quot;]] and six-coupled goods engines. Locomotives were travelling longer distances and being worked more extensively. The [[North Midland Railway]] expressed their concern to [[Robert Stephenson]] who was, at that time, their general manager, about the effect of heat on their fireboxes. After some experiments, he patented his so-called [[Long Boiler locomotive|Long Boiler design]]. These became a new standard and similar designs were produced by other manufacturers, particularly [[Sharp Brothers]] whose engines became known affectionately as &quot;Sharpies&quot;.

The longer wheelbase for the longer boiler produced problems in cornering. For his six-coupled engines, Stephenson removed the flanges from the centre pair of wheels. For his express engines, he shifted the trailing wheel to the front in the [[4-2-0]] formation, as in his &quot;Great A.&quot; There were other  problems. One was that  the firebox was restricted in size, or had to be mounted behind the wheels.  The other problem was that for improved stability most engineers believed that the centre of gravity should be kept low.

The most extreme outcome of this was the [[Crampton locomotive]] which mounted the driving wheels behind the firebox and could be made very large in diameter. These achieved the hitherto unheard of speed of {{convert|70|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}} but were very prone to wheelslip. With their long wheelbase, they were unsuccessful on [[Great Britain|Britain]]'s winding tracks, but became popular in the USA and France, where the popular expression became to &quot;prendre le Crampton&quot;.

John Gray of the [[London and Brighton Railway]] disbelieved the necessity for a low centre of gravity and produced a series of locos that were much admired by [[David Joy (engineer)|David Joy]] who developed the design at the firm of [[E. B. Wilson and Company]] to produce the [[2-2-2]] [[Jenny Lind locomotive]], one of the most successful passenger locomotives of its day. Meanwhile the Stephenson [[0-6-0]] Long Boiler locomotive with inside cylinders became the archetypical goods engine.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right; text-align:right;&quot;
|+ Growth of British railways&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyhome.co.uk/peel/railways/expans.htm |title=The Peel Web: Railway expansion|accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
! Year !! Total miles
|-
| 1830
| 98
|-
| 1835
| 338
|-
| 1840
| 1,498
|-
| 1845
| 2,441
|-
| 1850
| 6,621
|-
| 1855
| 8,280
|-
| 1860
| 10,433
|}

===Expanding network===
Railways quickly became essential to the swift movement of goods and labour that was needed for [[industrialization]]. In the beginning, [[canal]]s were in competition with the railways, but the railways quickly gained ground as [[Steam engine|steam]] and rail technology improved, and railways were built in places where canals were not practical.

By the 1850s, many steam-powered railways had reached the fringes of built-up London. But the new lines were not permitted to demolish enough property to penetrate the City or the West End, so passengers had to disembark at [[Paddington]], [[Euston railway station|Euston]], [[London King's Cross railway station|Kings Cross]], [[Fenchurch Street]], [[Charing Cross]], [[Waterloo Station|Waterloo]] or [[Victoria station (London)|Victoria]] and then make their own way via [[hackney carriage]] or on foot into the centre, thereby massively increasing [[Traffic congestion|congestion]] in the city. A [[Metropolitan Line|Metropolitan Railway]] was built under the ground to connect several of these separate railway terminals, and thus became the world's first &quot;Metro.&quot;

===British Empire===

====Canada====
See [[Grand Trunk Railway of Canada]]

In [[History of Canada|Canada]], the national government strongly supported railway construction for political goals. First it wanted to knit the far-flung provinces together, and second, it wanted to maximize trade inside Canada and minimize trade with the United States, to avoid becoming an economic satellite. The [[Grand Trunk Railway]] of Canada linked Toronto and Montreal in 1853, then opened a line to Portland, Maine (which was ice-free), and lines to Michigan and Chicago. By 1870 it was the longest railway in the world.  The Intercolonial line, finished in 1876, linked the Maritimes to [[Quebec]] and [[Ontario]], tying them to the new Confederation.

[[File:Grand Trunk Railway Station, Montreal.jpg|thumb|Grand Trunk's [[Bonaventure Station]], Montreal, 1900s]]
{{main|Intercolonial Railway}}
Anglo entrepreneurs in [[Montreal]] sought direct lines into the U.S. and shunned connections with the Maritimes, with a goal of competing with American railroad lines heading west to the Pacific. [[Joseph Howe]], [[Charles Tupper]], and other Nova Scotia leaders used the rhetoric of a &quot;civilizing mission&quot; centered on their British heritage, because Atlantic-centered railway projects promised to make Halifax the eastern terminus of an intercolonial railway system tied to London. [[Leonard Tilley]], New Brunswick's most ardent railway promoter, championed the cause of &quot;economic progress,&quot; stressing that Atlantic Canadians needed to pursue the most cost-effective transportation connections possible if they wanted to expand their influence beyond local markets. Advocating an intercolonial connection to Canada, and a western extension into larger American markets in Maine and beyond, New Brunswick entrepreneurs promoted ties to the United States first, connections with Halifax second, and routes into central Canada last.  Thus metropolitan rivalries between Montreal, Halifax, and Saint John led Canada to build more railway lines per capita than any other industrializing nation, even though it lacked capital resources, and had too little freight and passenger traffic to allow the systems to turn a profit.&lt;ref&gt;A.A. den Otter, ''The Philosophy of Railways: The Transcontinental Railway Idea in British North America'' (1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

Den Otter (1997) challenges popular assumptions that Canada built transcontinental railways because it feared the annexationist schemes of aggressive Americans. Instead Canada overbuilt railroads because it hoped to compete with, even overtake Americans in the race for continental riches. It downplayed the more realistic Maritimes-based London-oriented connections and turned to utopian prospects for the farmlands and minerals of the west.  The result was closer ties between north and south, symbolized by the Grand Trunk's expansion into the American Midwest. These economic links promoted trade, commerce, and the flow of ideas between the two countries, integrating Canada into a North American economy and culture by 1880. About 700,000 Canadians migrated to the U.S. in the late 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;Den Otten (1997); Bill Waiser, ''Saskatchewan: A New History'' (2005) p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadian Pacific, paralleling the American border, opened a vital link to British Canada, and stimulated settlement of the Prairies. The CP was affiliated with [[James J. Hill]]'s American railways, and opened even more connections to the South. The connections were two-way, as thousands of American moved to the Prairies after their own frontier had closed.

Two additional transcontinental lines were built to the west coast—three in all—but that was far more than the traffic would bear, making the system simply too expensive. One after another, the federal government was forced to take over the lines and cover their deficits. In 1923 the government merged the Grand Trunk, Grand Trunk Pacific, Canadian Northern and National Transcontinental lines into the new the Canadian National Railways system. Since most of the equipment was imported from Britain or the U.S., and most of the products carried were from farms, mines or forests, there was little stimulation to domestic manufacturing. On the other hand, the railways were essential to the growth of the wheat regions in the Prairies, and to the expansion of coal mining, lumbering, and paper making. Improvements to the St. Lawrence waterway system continued apace, and many short lines were built to river ports.&lt;ref&gt;M. L. Bladen, Construction of Railways in Canada to the Year 1885,&quot; ''Contributions to Canadian Economics'' Vol. 5 (1932), pp. 43–60; [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0383-6258%281932%295%3C43%3ACORICT%3E2.0.CO%3B2-V in JSTOR]; Bladen, &quot;Construction of Railways in Canada Part II: From 1885 to 1931,&quot; ''Contributions to Canadian Economics'' Vol. 7 (1934), pp. 61–107; [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0383-6258%281934%297%3C61%3ACORICP%3E2.0.CO%3B2-R in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

====India====
{{Main|History of rail transport in India}}
[[File:India railways1909a.jpg|550px|thumb|left|The 1909 Map of [[Indian Railways]], when India had the fourth largest railway network in the world.]]

[[History of India|India]] provides an example of the British Empire pouring its money and expertise into a very well built system designed for military reasons (after the Mutiny of 1857), and with the hope that it would stimulate industry. The system was overbuilt and much too elaborate and expensive for the small amount of freight traffic it carried. However, it did capture the imagination of the Indians, who saw their railways as the symbol of an industrial modernity—but one that was not realized until a century or so later.

The British built a superb system in India. However, Christensen (1996) looks at of colonial purpose, local needs, capital, service, and private-versus-public interests. He concludes that making the railways a creature of the state hindered success because railway expenses had to go through the same time-consuming and political budgeting process as did all other state expenses. Railway costs could therefore not be tailored to the timely needs of the railways or their passengers.&lt;ref&gt;R. O. Christensen, &quot;The State and Indian Railway Performance, 1870–1920&quot; in Terri Gourvish, ed. ''Railways'' vol 1 (1996)&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 1940s, India had the fourth longest railway network in the world. Yet the country's industrialization was delayed until after independence in 1947 by British colonial policy. Until the 1930s, both the Indian government and the private railway companies hired only European supervisors, civil engineers, and even operating personnel, such as engine (locomotive) drivers. The government's &quot;Stores Policy&quot; required that bids on railway matériel be presented to the India Office in London, making it almost impossible for enterprises based in India to compete for orders. Likewise, the railway companies purchased most of their matériel in Britain, rather than in India. Although the railway maintenance workshops in India could have manufactured and repaired locomotives, the railways imported a majority of them from Britain, and the others from Germany, Belgium, and the United States. The Tata company built a steel mill in India before World War I but could not obtain orders for rails until the 1920s and 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;Ian J. Kerr, ''Engines of Change: The Railroads that Made India'' (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pakistan====
{{Main|History of rail transport in Pakistan}}
[[Pakistan]] has a rich railway heritage spanning almost 200 years which it owes the [[British Empire|British]]. It was in 1847 when the first railway was imagined but it was not until 1861 when it came into existence in the form of the railway built from [[Karachi]] to [[Kotri]]. Pakistan has stayed true to this rich heritage because since [[Pakistan Railways|rail transport]] is possibly the most popular mode of non-independent transport in Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pakrail.com/history.php Pakistan railways History]&lt;/ref&gt;

==France==
{{Main|History of rail transport in France}}
In France, railways became a national medium for the modernization of backward regions, and a leading advocate of this approach was the poet-politician [[Alphonse de Lamartine]]. One writer hoped that railways might improve the lot of &quot;populations two or three centuries behind their fellows&quot; and eliminate &quot;the savage instincts born of isolation and misery.&quot; Consequently, France built a centralized system that radiated from Paris (plus lines that cut east to west in the south). This design was intended to achieve political and cultural goals rather than maximize efficiency. After some consolidation, six companies controlled monopolies of their regions, subject to close control by the government in terms of fares, finances, and even minute technical details. The central government department of Ponts et Chaussées [bridges and roads] brought in British engineers and workers, handled much of the construction work, provided engineering expertise and planning, land acquisition, and construction of permanent infrastructure such as the track bed, bridges and tunnels. It also subsidized militarily necessary lines along the German border, which was considered necessary for the national defense. Private operating companies provided management, hired labor, laid the tracks, and built and operated stations. They purchased and maintained the rolling stock—6,000 locomotives were in operation in 1880, which averaged 51,600 passengers a year or 21,200 tons of freight. Much of the equipment was imported from Britain and therefore did not stimulate machinery makers.

[[File:France1860railways.png|thumb|upright=1.8|Development of the network up to 1860]]

Although starting the whole system at once was politically expedient, it delayed completion, and forced even more reliance on temporary experts brought in from Britain. Financing was also a problem. The solution was a narrow base of funding through the Rothschilds and the closed circles of the Bourse in Paris, so France did not develop the same kind of national stock exchange that flourished in London and New York. The system did help modernize the parts of rural France it reached, but it did not help create local industrial centers. Critics such as [[Emile Zola]] complained that it never overcame the corruption of the political system, but rather contributed to it. The railways probably helped the industrial revolution in France by facilitating a national market for raw materials, wines, cheeses, and imported manufactured products. Yet the goals set by the French for their railway system were moralistic, political, and military rather than economic. As a result, the freight trains were shorter and less heavily loaded than those in such rapidly industrializing nations such as Britain, Belgium or Germany. Other infrastructure needs in rural France, such as better roads and canals, were neglected because of the expense of the railways, so it seems likely that there were net negative effects in areas not served by the trains.&lt;ref&gt;Patrick O’Brien, ''Railways and the Economic Development of Western Europe, 1830–1914'' (1983)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Russia==
{{Further|History of rail transport in Russia|Rail transport in Russia|Russian Railways}}

Russia was in need of big transportation systems and geographically suited to railroads, with long flat stretches of land and comparatively simple land acquisition.  It was hampered, however, by its outmoded political situation and a shortage of capital. [[Yefim Alekseyevich Cherepanov|Yefim and Miron Cherepanovs]], Russian factory engineers, actually invented and built successful working locomotives for a mine tramway between 1832 and 1835, but their inventiveness was not pursued. Foreign initiative and capital were required. The first major public railroad was the [[Saint Petersburg]]-[[Tsarskoye Selo]] Railway, proposed and built by a [[Bohemia]]n engineer, František Antonín Gerstner the son of [[František Josef Gerstner]], in 1836.

==United States 1830–1890==
{{Further|History of rail transport in the United States}}
In 1830, there were only {{convert|39.8|mi|km}} of documented railroad track laid in the United States (there is ample historical evidence that a more correct figure would be a little over {{convert|75|mi|km}} due to a failure to count special purpose railroads hauling only coal and granite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Henry V. Poor |title= Railroads and Canals of the United States of America |pages=85,415}}&lt;/ref&gt;). After this, railroad lines grew rapidly. Ten years later, in 1840, the railways had grown to {{convert|2755.18|mi|km}}. Two decades after that, the number had reached {{convert|28919.79|mi|km}}, and 20 years after that, the number had tripled once more to {{convert|87801.42|mi|km}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=United States Census Bureau |title= Report on the Agencies of Transportation in the United States at Tenth Census 1880 |pages=308–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; colspan=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot; face=&quot;Arial&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;       RAILROAD ACCUMULATED MILEAGE BY REGION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;       1830&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;       1840&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;       1850&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;       1860&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;       1870&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;       1880&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;       1890&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;ME,NH,VT,MA,RI,CT&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;29.80&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;513.34&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;       2,595.57&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;       3,644.24&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;       4,326.73&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;       5,888.09&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;       6,718.19&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;NY,PA,OH,MI,IN,MD,DE,NJ,DC&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;1,483.76&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;3,740.36&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;11,927.21&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;18,291.93&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;28,154.73&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;40,825.60&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;VA,WV,KY,TN,MS,AL,GA,FL,NC,SC&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;10.00&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;737.33&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;2,082.07&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;7,907.79&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;10,609.60&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;14,458.33&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;27,833.15&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;IL,IA,WI,MO,MN&lt;br /&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;46.48&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;4,951.47&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;11,030.85&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;22,212.98&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;35,579.80&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;LA,AR &amp; OK (Indian) Territory&lt;br /&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;20.75&lt;br /&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;107.00&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;250.23&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;331.23&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;1,621.11&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;5,153.91&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;(Terr.)ND/SD,NM,WY,MT,ID,UT,AZ,WA&lt;br /&gt;(States)NE,KS,TX,CO,CA,NV,OR&lt;br /&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;238.85&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;4,577.99&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;15,466.18&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;47,451.47&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;         TOTAL USA&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;39.80&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;2,755.18&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;8,571.48&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;28,919.79&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;49,168.33&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;87,801.42&lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;163,562.12&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=United States Census Bureau |title= Report on Transportation Business in the United States at the Eleventh Census 1890 |page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1869, the symbolically important [[Transcontinental railroad#United States|transcontinental railroad]] was completed in the United States with the driving of a golden spike (near the city of [[Ogden, Utah|Ogden]]).

==Diesel and electric engines==

===Electric railways revolutionize urban transport ===
Prior to the development of electric railways, most overland transport aside from the railways had consisted primarily of horse powered vehicles. Placing a [[horse car]] on rails had enabled a horse to move twice as many people, and so street railways were born. The world's first electric tram line opened in Lichterfelde near Berlin, Germany, in 1881. It was built by Werner von Siemens (see [[Gross-Lichterfelde Tramway]]). Seven years later, in January 1888, [[Richmond, Virginia]] served as American proving grounds for [[streetcar|electric railways]] as [[Frank J. Sprague|Frank Sprague]] built an electric streetcar system there. By the 1890s, electric power became practical and more widespread, allowing extensive underground railways. Large cities such as London, New York, and Paris built [[Subway (rail)|subway]] systems. When electric propulsion became practical, most street railways were electrified. These then became known as &quot;streetcars,&quot; &quot;trolleys,&quot; &quot;trams&quot; and &quot;Strassenbahn.&quot; They can be found around the world.

In many countries, these electric street railways grew beyond the metropolitan areas to connect with other urban centers. In the USA, &quot;electric interurban&quot; railroad networks connected most urban areas in the states of Illinois, Indiana, Ohio, Pennsylvania and New York.  In Southern California, the [[Pacific Electric Railway]] connected most cities in Los Angeles and Orange Counties, and the [[Inland Empire (California)|Inland Empire]].  There were similar systems in Europe.  One of the more notable rail systems connected every town and city in Belgium. One of the more notable tramway systems in Asia is the [[Hong Kong Tramways]], which started operation in 1904 and run exclusively on double-decker trams.

The remnants of these systems still exist, and in many places they have been modernized to become part of the urban &quot;rapid transit&quot; system in their respective areas. In the past thirty years increasing numbers of cities have restored electric rail service by building &quot;light rail&quot; systems to replace the tram system they removed during the mid-20th century.

===Diesel power===
[[Diesel-electric transmission|Diesel-electric]] locomotives could be described as electric locomotives with an on-board generator powered by a diesel engine.  The first diesel locomotives were low-powered machines, [[diesel-mechanical]] types used in switching yards.  Diesel and electric locomotives are cleaner, more efficient, and require less maintenance than steam locomotives. They also required less specialized skills in operation and their introduction diminished the power of railway unions in the United States (one of the earliest countries to adopt diesel power on a wide scale).  After working through technical difficulties in the early 1900s, diesel locomotives became mainstream after World War II.  By the 1970s, diesel and electric power had replaced steam power on most of the world's railroads.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grubler1990&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
 | last1 = Grübler
 | first1 = Arnulf
 | author1-link =
 | title = The Rise and Fall of Infrastructures: Dynamics of Evolution and Technological Change in Transport
 | year = 1990
|publisher=Physica-Verlag
|location= Heidelberg and New York
|isbn=
|page=124
 | url = http://www.iiasa.ac.at/Admin/PUB/Documents/XB-90-704.pdf
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 20th century, [[road transport]] and air travel replaced railroads for most long-distance passenger travel in the United States, but railroads remain important for hauling freight in the United States, and for passenger transport in many other countries.

===High-speed rail===
Starting with the opening of the first [[Shinkansen]] line between Tokyo and [[Osaka]] in 1964, [[high-speed rail]] transport, functioning at speeds up and above 300&amp;nbsp;km/h, has been built in Spain, France, Germany, Italy, the People's Republic of China, Taiwan, the United Kingdom, South Korea, Scandinavia, Belgium and the Netherlands. The construction of many of these lines has resulted in the dramatic decline of short haul flights and automotive traffic between connected cities, such as the London-Paris-Brussels corridor, Madrid-Barcelona, as well as many other major lines.

== See also ==
{{portal|Trains}}
* [[Matthias W. Baldwin|Matthias William Baldwin]] (1795–1866), manufacturer
* [[John Blenkinsop]] (1783–1831), inventor
* [[George Bradshaw]], originator of the railway timetable
* [[Thomas Gray (1788–1848)|Thomas Gray]], railway advocate, published 1st ed. of ''Observations on a General Iron Railway'', 1820.
* [[:Category:Rail transport timelines]]
* [[Historical sizes of railroads]] in North America
* [[Land speed record for railed vehicles]]
* [[Oldest railroads in North America]]
* [[Permanent way: historical development]]
* [[Timeline of railway history]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==Bibliography==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|author=Skelton, Oscar D.|title=The Railway Builders|publisher=Glasgow, Brook, &amp; Company, Toronto|year=1916}}
* Leland H. Jenks, &quot;Railroads as an Economic Force in American Development,&quot; ''The Journal of Economic History'', Vol. 4, No. 1 (May, 1944), 1–20.
*{{Cite journal | last1=Smith | first=R S.| title=Huntingdon Beaumont Adventurer in Coal Mines | journal=Renaissance and Modern Studies| year=1957 | page=115 to 153 }}.
*{{Cite journal | last1=Smith | first=R S. | title=England's First Rails : A reconsideration | journal=Renaissance and Modern Studies| year=1960 | page=119 to 134 }}.
*{{Cite document | surname= Lewis | given=M J T | title=Early Wooden Railways | publisher=Routledge Keegan Paul (out of print) | place=London, England | year=1970 }}.
* Rainer Fremdling, &quot;Railways and German Economic Growth: A Leading Sector Analysis with a Comparison to the United States and Great Britain,&quot; ''The Journal of Economic History'', Vol. 37, No. 3. (Sep., 1977), pp.&amp;nbsp;583–604.
* O . S. Nock, ed. ''Encyclopedia of Railways'' (London, 1977), worldwide coverage, heavily illustrated
* Hadfield, C. and Skempton, A. W. ''William Jessop, Engineer'' (Newton Abbot 1979)
* Misa, Thomas J. ''A Nation of Steel: The Making of Modern America, 1865–1925'' (1995) [http://www.umn.edu/~tmisa/NOS/1.1_intro.html chapter 1 'Dominance of Rails' online]
* Patrick O’Brien. ''Railways and the Economic Development of Western Europe, 1830–1914'' (1983)
* Omrani, Bijan [http://books.google.com/books?id=I7USQgAACAAJ&amp;dq=omrani+asia+overland&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=pL43Tq-1I5SyhAeGzdmoAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA Asia Overland: Tales of Travel on the Trans-Siberian and Silk Road] Odyssey Publications, 2010 ISBN 962-217-811-1
*{{Cite document | surname=Smith | given= R S | title=Early Coal Mining Around Nottingham 1500 – 1650 | publisher=University of Nottingham (out of print) | year=1989 }}.
* John Stover, ''American Railways'' (2nd ed 1997)
* [[Jack Simmons (historian)|Jack Simmons]] and Gordon Biddle (editors). ''The Oxford Companion to British Railway History: From 1603 to the 1990s'' (2nd ed 1999)
* John Stover, ''The Routledge Historical Atlas of the American Railroads'' (2001)
* Lewis, M. J. T., [http://www.sciencenews.gr/docs/diolkos.pdf &quot;Railways in the Greek and Roman world&quot;], in Guy, A. / Rees, J. (eds), ''Early Railways. A Selection of Papers from the First International Early Railways Conference'' (2001), pp.&amp;nbsp;8–19 (10–15)
* {{Cite conference | author=M J T Lewis | title=Reflections on 1604 | booktitle=Early Railways 3 (Subscription print run issued in 2006) | year=2004 | pages=8–22}}
* Riley, C. J.  ''The Encyclopedia of Trains &amp; Locomotives'' (2002).
*{{Cite journal | last1=New | first=J R.    | title=400 years of English railways – Huntingdon Beaumont and the early years | journal=Backtrack |volume=18 |issue=11 (Nov) | year=2004 | page=660 to 665 }}.
*{{Cite journal | last1=Jenks | first=Leyland  | title=Railroads as an Economic Force in American Development | journal=The Journal of Economic History  |volume=4 |issue=1 (May) | year=1944 | page=1 to 20 }}.
* {{Cite journal |last=Keys |first=C. M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1914 |month=August  |title=Redrawing The Railroad Map Of The World |journal=[[World's Work|The World's Work: A History of Our Time]] |volume=XLIV |issue=2 |pages=414–425  |url=http://books.google.com/?id=zegeQtMn9JsC&amp;pg=PA414 |accessdate=2009-08-04 }} Includes maps of major rail lines on all continents c. 1914
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
* [http://ndpbeta.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/5385284 How the Railroad is Modernising Asia], The Advertiser, Adelaide, S. Australia, 22 March 1913. N.B.: The article is of approx. 1,500 words, covering approx. a dozen Asian countries.
* {{Cite journal |last=Clarke |first=Thomas Curtis |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1888 |month=June |title=The Building of a Railway |journal=Scribner's Magazine |volume=III |issue=6 |pages=642–670  |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=VdFEmTaneHwC&amp;pg=PA642|accessdate= }} Includes numerous c. 1880 diagrams and illustrations.

==External links==
* [http://tigger.uic.edu/~rjensen/railroad.htm  WWW Guide to &quot;Railroad History&quot;]
* [http://americanhistory.si.edu/archives/d8523.htm John H. White, Jr. Reference Collection, 1880s–1990]  Archives Center, National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution.
* [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=LCCNa13002565&amp;id=VdKN4UZ57qAC&amp;dq=railways+africa&amp;pg=PA4&amp;printsec=4&amp;lpg=PA4 ''Foreign Railways of the World: Containing in One Volume, the Names of Officers, Length, Capital,...'' (1884)]
* Waggonway Research Circle: [http://www.waggonways.fsnet.co.uk/woll_wag_leaflet_a4.pdf The Wollaton Wagonway of 1604. The World’s First Overland Railway], August 2005

{{Africa in topic|History of rail transport in}}
{{Asia in topic|History of rail transport in}}
{{Central America in topic|History of rail transport in}}
{{History of rail transport in Europe}}
{{North America in topic|History of rail transport in}}
{{History of rail transport in Oceania}}
{{South America in topic|History of rail transport in}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Rail Transport}}
[[Category:Rail transport]]
[[Category:History of rail transport| ]]

[[de:Geschichte der Eisenbahn]]
[[fr:Histoire des chemins de fer]]
[[hu:A vasút története]]
[[nl:Mijlpalen in de spoorweggeschiedenis]]
[[ja:鉄道の歴史]]
[[pl:Historia kolei]]
[[ru:История железных дорог]]
[[sv:Järnvägshistoria]]</text>
      <sha1>fjuo0tum21i40tawkwq8p5ju2el7l75</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
