<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>History of Ukraine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>84795</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519178463</id>
      <parentid>517231559</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-22T10:24:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DixonDBot</username>
        <id>10330367</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[io:Historio di Ukrainia]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="66706">&lt;!-- Merge tag removed and notes added on the talk page - please do not re-apply until discussion is finished --&gt;
{{History of Ukraine}}

The territory of [[Ukraine]] was a key center of [[Early East Slavs|East Slavic culture]] in the [[Middle Ages]], before being divided between a variety of powers. However, the '''history of Ukraine''' dates back many thousands of years. The territory has been settled continuously since at least 5000 BC and is a candidate [[Proto-Indo-European Urheimat hypotheses|site of the origins]] of the [[Proto-Indo-European language|Proto-Indo-European]] language family. The horse was first domesticated on the territory of Ukraine.&lt;ref&gt;Matossian ''Shaping World History'' p. 43&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://imh.org/legacy-of-the-horse/what-we-theorize-when-and-where-did-domestication-occur/ |title=What We Theorize – When and Where Did Domestication Occur |accessdate=2010-12-12 |format= |work=International Museum of the Horse }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cbc.ca&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Horsey-aeology, Binary Black Holes, Tracking Red Tides, Fish Re-evolution, Walk Like a Man, Fact or Fiction |url=http://www.cbc.ca/quirks/episode/2009/03/07/horsey-aeology-binary-black-holes-tracking-red-tides-fish-re-evolution-walk-like-a-man-fact-or-ficti/|work=Quirks and Quarks Podcast with Bob Macdonald |publisher= CBC Radio |date=2009-03-07|accessdate=2010-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prehistory==
{{see also|Ukrainian stone stela}}
[[File:Slavic peoples 6th century historical map.jpg|thumb|175px|Territory of Slavic peoples (6th century)]]
Settlement in Ukraine by members of the ''[[homo]]'' genus has been documented into distant prehistory. The [[Neanderthal]]s are associated with the Molodova archaeological sites (43,000-45,000 BC) which include a mammoth bone dwelling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/science/science-news/8963177/Neanderthals-built-homes-with-mammoth-bones.html | title = Neanderthals built homes with mammoth bones | work = Telegraph.co.uk | first = Richard | last = Gray | date = December 18, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://archaeology.about.com/od/mterms/g/molodova.htm Molodova I and V (Ukraine)]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gravettian]] settlements dating to 32,000 BCE have been unearthed and studied in the Buran-Kaya cave site of the [[Crimean Mountains]].&lt;ref name=orig&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.plosone.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0020834 | title = The Oldest Anatomically Modern Humans from Far Southeast Europe: Direct Dating, Culture and Behavior | first1 = Sandrine | last1= Prat | first2= Stéphane C. | last2= Péan | first3= Laurent | last3= Crépin | first4 =Dorothée G. |last4= Drucker | first5 =Simon J. | last5= Puaud | first6 =Hélène | last6=Valladas | first7= Martina |last7 =Lázničková-Galetová | first8 =Johannes | last8 =van der Plicht | first9= Alexander | last9= Yanevich |date = 17 June 2011 | publisher = plosone | accessdate = 21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bbc&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/science-environment-13846262 | title = Early human fossils unearthed in Ukraine | first = Jennifer | last = Carpenter |date = 20 June 2011 | publisher = [[BBC]] | accessdate = 21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The late [[Neolithic]] [[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture|Cucuteni-Trypillian Culture]] flourished from about 4500–3000&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bank.gov.ua/ENGL/Macro/index.htm|title=Trypillian Civilization 5,508 – 2,750 BC|accessdate=2007-12-16|work=The Trypillia-USA-Project|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071021232506/http://bank.gov.ua/Engl/Macro/index.htm &lt;!--Added by H3llBot--&gt;|archivedate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Copper Age]] people of the [[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture|Cucuteni-Trypillian Culture]] resided in the western part, and the [[Sredny Stog culture|Sredny Stog Culture]] further east, succeeded by the early [[Bronze Age]] [[Yamna]] (&quot;[[Kurgan hypothesis|Kurgan]]&quot;) culture of the steppes, and by the [[Catacomb culture]] in the 3rd millennium BC.

During the [[Iron Age]], these were followed by the [[Dacians]] as well as [[pastoral nomads|nomadic peoples]] like the [[Cimmerians]], [[Scythians]] and [[Sarmatians]]. The [[Scythia]]n Kingdom existed here from 750–250&amp;nbsp;BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB-Scyth&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9066426|title=Scythian|accessdate=2007-09-12|work=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with [[Ancient Greece|ancient Greek]] colonies founded in the 6th century BC on the northeastern shore of the [[Black Sea]], the colonies of [[Tyras]], [[Olbia, Ukraine|Olbia]], [[Hermonassa]], continued as [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] and [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] cities until the 6th century.

In the 3rd century AD, the [[Goths]] arrived in the lands of Ukraine around 250–375&amp;nbsp;AD, which they called [[Oium]], corresponding to the archaeological [[Chernyakhov culture]].&lt;ref name=&quot;history of ukraine27&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Paul Robert|last=Magocsi|year=1996|title=A History of Ukraine|publisher=[[University of Toronto Press]]|location=[[Toronto]]|isbn=0-8020-0830-5|page=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Ostrogoths]] stayed in the area but came under the sway of the [[Huns]] from the 370s. North of the Ostrogothic kingdom was the [[Kiev culture]], flourishing from the 2nd–5th centuries, when it was overrun by the [[Huns]]. After they helped defeat the Huns at the [[battle of Nedao]] in 454, the Ostrogoths were allowed to settle in [[Pannonia]].

With the power vacuum created with the end of Hunnic and Gothic rule, [[Slavic tribes]], possibly emerging from the remnants of the Kiev culture, began to expand over much of the territory that is now Ukraine during the 5th century, and beyond to the Balkans from the 6th century.

In the 7th century, the territory of modern Ukraine was the core of the state of the [[Bulgars]] (often referred to as [[Old Great Bulgaria]]) with its capital city of [[Phanagoria]]. At the end of the 7th century, most Bulgar tribes migrated in several directions and the remains of their state were absorbed by the [[Khazars]], a semi-[[nomad|nomadic people]] from [[Central Asia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;history of ukraine27&quot;/&gt; 

The Khazars founded the [[Khazars|Khazar kingdom]] in the southeastern part of today's [[Europe]], near the [[Caspian Sea]] and the [[Caucasus (geographic region)|Caucasus]]. The kingdom included western [[Kazakhstan]], and parts of eastern Ukraine, [[Azerbaijan]], southern [[Russia]], and [[Crimea]]. Around 800&amp;nbsp;AD, the kingdom converted to [[Judaism]].

==Kievan Rus'==
[[File:001 Kievan Rus' Kyivan Rus' Ukraine map 1220 1240.jpg|thumb|175px|Historical map of [[Kievan Rus']] and territory of [[Ukraine]]: last 20 years of the state (1220–1240).]]
{{Main|Kievan Rus'}}
As [[Mykhailo Hrushevskyi|Hrushevsky]] states, the city of Kiev was established during the time when area around the mid- and low-Dnipro was the part of the [[Khazar]] state. He derived that information  from local legends because no written chronicles from that period are left. The main reasons for that might be the fact that during the Christianization of the Kievan Rus and later occupation of [[Ukraine]], all earlier religious and historical publications of that land were destroyed. In 882, Kiev was conquered from the [[Khazars]] by the [[Varangian]] noble [[Oleg of Kiev|Oleg]] who started the long period of rule of the [[Rurikid]] princes. During this time, several Slavic tribes were native to Ukraine, including the [[Polans (eastern)|Polans]], the [[Drevlyans]], the [[Severians]], the [[Ulichs]], the [[Tiverians]], the [[White Croats]] and the [[Dulebes]]. Situated on lucrative trade routes, Kiev among the Polanians quickly prospered as the center of the powerful Slavic state of [[Kievan Rus]].

In CE 941, the prince of Kiev invaded the Byzantine Empire but his fleet was destroyed due to the Byzantine Greek fire.

In the 11th century, [[Kievan Rus']] was, geographically, the largest state in Europe, becoming known in the rest of Europe as [[Ruthenia]] (the Latin name for Rus'), especially for western principalities of Rus' after the Mongol invasion. The name &quot;Ukraine&quot;, meaning &quot;in-land&quot; or &quot;native-land&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[:uk:Україна (назва)|Україна (назва)]]&lt;/ref&gt; usually interpreted as &quot;border-land&quot;, first appears in historical documents of 12th century&lt;ref&gt;[[Name of Ukraine]]&lt;/ref&gt; and then on history maps of the 16th century period.&lt;ref&gt;[[:uk:Історія України#Історичні назви українських територій|Історичні назви українських територій]]&lt;/ref&gt; The meaning of this term seems to have been synonymous with the land of Rus' propria—the principalities of [[Kiev]], [[Chernihiv]] and [[Pereiaslav-Khmel'nyts'kyi|Pereyaslav]]. The term, &quot;Greater Rus'&quot; was used to apply to all the lands ruled by Kiev, including those that were not just Slavic, but also [[Uralic languages|Uralic]] in the north-east portions of the state.  Local regional subdivisions of Rus' appeared in the Slavic heartland, including, &quot;Belarus'&quot; (White Ruthenia), &quot;Chorna Rus'&quot; (Black Ruthenia) and &quot;Cherven' Rus'&quot; (Red Ruthenia) in northwestern and western Ukraine.

Although Christianity had made headway into the territory of Ukraine before the first ecumenical council, the [[First Council of Nicaea|Council of Nicaea]] (325) (particularly along the Black Sea coast) and, in western Ukraine during the time of empire of [[Great Moravia]], the formal governmental acceptance of Christianity in Rus' occurred at in 988. The major cause of the [[Christianization of Kievan Rus']] was the Grand-Duke, [[Vladimir the Great]] (''Volodymyr''). His Christian interest was midwifed by his grandmother, [[Princess Olga]]. Later, an enduring part of the East-Slavic legal tradition was set down by the Kievan ruler, [[Yaroslav I the Wise|Yaroslav I]], who promulgated the [[Russkaya Pravda]] (Truth of Rus') which endured through the Lithuanian period of Rus'.

Conflict among the various principalities of Rus', in spite of the efforts of Grand Prince [[Vladimir Monomakh]], led to decline, beginning in the 12th century. In Rus' propria, the Kiev region, the nascent Rus' principalities of [[Halych-Volhynia|Halych and Volynia]] extended their rule. In the north, the name of Moscow appeared in the historical record in the principality of [[Suzdal]], which gave rise to the nation of Russia. In the north-west, the principality of Polotsk increasingly asserted the autonomy of [[Belarus']]. Kiev was sacked by Vladimir principality (1169) in the power struggle between princes and later by [[Cumans]] and [[Mongol Empire|Mongol]] raiders in the 12th and 13th centuries, respectively. Subsequently, all principalities of present-day Ukraine acknowledged dependence upon the Mongols (1239–1240). In 1240,
the Mongols sacked Kiev, and many people fled to other countries.

Five years after the fall of Kiev, Papal envoy [[Giovanni da Pian del Carpine|Giovanni di Plano Carpini]] wrote:

:&quot;''They destroyed cities and castles and killed men and Kiev, which is the greatest Russian city they besieged; and when they had besieged it a long while they took it and killed the people of the city. So when we went through that country we found countless human skulls and bones from the dead scattered over the field. Indeed it had been a very great and populous city and now is reduced almost to nothing. In fact there are hardly two hundred houses there now and the people are held in the strictest servitude.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home.swipnet.se/roland/mongols.html |title=Ukrainian Tribal Divisions and Ethnographic Groups |publisher=Home.swipnet.se |date= |accessdate=2011-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Galicia-Volhynia==
[[File:Kingdom of Galicia Volhynia Rus' Ukraine 1245 1349.jpg|thumb|175px|The Galician–Volhynian Kingdom in the 13th–14th centuries]]
{{Main|Galicia-Volhynia}}
A [[successor state]] to Kievan Rus' on part of the territory of today's Ukraine was the principality of [[Galicia-Volhynia]].
Previously, [[Vladimir the Great]] had established the cities of [[Halych]] and  [[Volodymyr-Volynskyi|Ladomir]] (later Volodimer) as regional capitals for the western Ukrainian heartland. This new, more exclusively Ukrainian predecessor state was based upon the [[Dulebe]], [[Tiverian]] and [[White Croat]] tribes. The state was ruled by the descendants of [[Yaroslav the Wise]] and [[Vladimir Monomakh]]. For a brief period, the country was ruled by a Hungarian nobleman. Battles with the neighboring states of Poland and Lithuania also occurred, as well as internecine warfare with the independent Ruthenian principality of [[Chernigov]] to the east. The nation reached its peak with the extension of rule to neighboring [[Wallachia]]/[[Bessarabia]], all the way to the shores of the Black Sea.

During this period (around 1200–1400), each principality was independent of the other for a period of time. The state of Halych-Volynia eventually became a vassal to the Mongolian Empire, but efforts to gain European support for opposition to the Mongols continued. This period marked the first &quot;King of Rus'&quot;; previously, the rulers of Rus' were termed, &quot;[[Grand Duke]]s&quot; or &quot;Princes.&quot;

==14th Century==
{{see also|Golden Horde}}
During the 14th century, [[Poland]] and [[Lithuania]] fought wars against the Mongol invaders, and eventually most of Ukraine passed to the rule of Poland and Lithuania. More particularly, the lands of Volynia in the north and north-west passed to the rule of Lithuanian princes, while the south-west passed to the control of Poland ([[Galicia (Central Europe)|Galicia]]) and Hungary ([[Carpathian Ruthenia|Zakarpattya]]).

Most of Ukraine bordered parts of Lithuania, and some say that the name, &quot;Ukraine&quot; comes from the local word for &quot;border,&quot; although the name &quot;Ukraine&quot; was also used centuries earlier. Lithuania took control of the state of [[Volynia]] in northern and northwestern Ukraine, including the region around Kiev (Rus'), and the rulers of Lithuania then adopted the title of ruler of Rus'. Poland took control of the region of Galicia. Following [[Polish–Lithuanian Union|the union between Poland and Lithuania]], [[Poles]], [[German people|Germans]], [[Lithuanians]] and [[Jew]]s migrated to the region.

==Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth==
[[File:Rzeczpospolita2nar.png|thumb|right|175x|Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth.
{{legend|hotpink|Kingdom of Poland}}]]
After the [[Union of Lublin]] in 1569 and the formation of the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] Ukraine fell under Polish administration, becoming part of the [[Crown of the Kingdom of Poland]]. The period immediately following the creation of the Commonwealth saw a huge revitalisation in colonisation efforts. Many new cities and villages were founded. New schools spread the ideas of the [[Renaissance]]; Polish peasants arrived in great numbers and quickly became mixed with the local population; during this time, most of Ukrainian nobles became [[polonisation|polonised]] and converted to [[Catholicism]], and while most Ruthenian-speaking peasants remained within the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], social tension rose.

Ruthenian peasants (Ukrainians and some from other nations) who fled efforts to force them into [[serfdom]] came to be known as [[Cossacks]] and earned a reputation for their fierce martial spirit. Some Cossacks were hired by the Commonwealth (became 'register Cossacks') as soldiers to protect the southeastern borders of Poland from [[Tatars]] or took part in campaigns abroad (like [[Petro Konashevych-Sahaidachny]] in the battle of [[Khotyn]] 1621). Cossack units were also active in wars between the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] and [[Tsardom of Russia]].

==Cossack era==
[[File:Location of Cossack Hetmanate.png|thumb|The Hetmanate in 1654 (against the backdrop of contemporary Ukraine)]]
{{See also|History of Cossacks}}
The 1648 Ukrainian [[Cossack]] (''Kozak'') rebellion and war of independence ([[Khmelnytsky Uprising]]), which started an era known as the [[Ruin (Ukrainian history)|Ruin]] (in [[Polish history]] as [[The Deluge (Polish history)|The Deluge]]), undermined the foundations and stability of the Commonwealth. The nascent Cossack state, the [[Cossack Hetmanate]],&lt;ref name=Serhy/&gt; usually viewed as precursor of Ukraine,&lt;ref name=Serhy&gt;''Ukraine: Birth of a Modern Nation'' by [[Serhy Yekelchyk]], [[Oxford University Press]] (2007), ISBN 978-0-19-530546-3&lt;/ref&gt; found itself in a three-sided military and diplomatic rivalry with the [[Ottoman Turks]], who controlled the Tatars to the south, the Commonwealth of Poland and Lithuania, and the rising [[Russia]] to the East.

The reconstituted Ukrainian state, having recently fought a bitter war with Poland, sought a treaty of protection with Russia in 1654.&lt;ref name=Serhy/&gt; This agreement was known as the [[Treaty of Pereyaslav]].&lt;ref name=Serhy/&gt; Commonwealth authorities then sought compromise with the Ukrainian Cossack state by signing the [[Treaty of Hadiach]] in 1658, but — after [[Russo-Polish War (1654-1667)|thirteen years of incessant warfare]] — the agreement was later superseded by 1667 Polish-Russian [[Treaty of Andrusovo]], which divided Ukrainian territory between the Commonwealth and Russia. Under Russia, the Cossacks initially retained official autonomy in the [[Cossack Hetmanate|Hetmanate]].&lt;ref name=Serhy/&gt; For a time, they also maintained a semi-independent republic in [[Zaporozhia]], and a colony on the Russian frontier in [[Sloboda Ukraine]].

==Russian Empire and Austro-Hungary==
[[File:Gubernias de Ucrania - ENG.png|thumb|right|175px|Administrative divisions of Russian Empire superimposed on map of Ukraine]]
{{See also|Partitions of Poland|Little Russia}}
Tsarist rule over central Ukraine gradually replaced 'protection' over the subsequent decades. After the [[Partitions of Poland]] in 1772, 1793 and 1795, [[Galicia (Central Europe)|the extreme west]] of Ukraine fell under the control of the [[Austrians]], with the rest as part of the Russian Empire. As a result of [[Russo-Turkish Wars]] the [[Ottoman Empire]]'s control receded from south-central Ukraine, while the rule of [[Hungary]] over the Transcarpathian region continued. Ukrainian writers and intellectuals were inspired by the nationalistic spirit stirring other European peoples existing under other imperial governments and became determined to revive the [[Culture of Ukraine|Ukrainian linguistic and cultural traditions]] and re-establish a Ukrainian nation-state, a movement that became known as [[Ukrainophilia|Ukrainophilism]].

Russia, fearing separatism, imposed strict limits on attempts to elevate the [[Ukrainian language]] and culture, even banning its use and study. This led to an exodus of a number of Ukrainian intellectuals into Western Ukraine. However, many Ukrainians accepted their fate in the [[Russian Empire]] and some were to achieve a great success there. Many Russian writers, composers, painters and architects of the 19th century were of Ukrainian descent. Probably the most notable were [[Nikolai Gogol]], one of the greatest writers in the history of [[Russian literature]], and [[Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky]], one of the greatest composers in the history of [[Music of Russia|Russian music]], whose father came of Ukrainian Cossack stock. 

[[File:Древний Фастов 14.jpg|thumb|left|Railway station of [[Fastiv]] before 1917, in tsarist Russia]]
The fate of the Ukrainians was far different under the [[Austrian Empire]] where they found themselves in the pawn position of the Russian-Austrian power struggle for the Central and Southern Europe. Unlike in Russia, most of the elite that ruled Galicia were of Austrian or Polish descent, with the Ruthenians being almost exclusively kept in peasantry. During the 19th century, [[Ukrainian Russophiles|Russophilia]] was a common occurrence among the Slavic population, but the mass exodus of Ukrainian intellectuals escaping from Russian repression in Eastern Ukraine, as well as the intervention of Austrian authorities, caused the movement to be replaced by [[Ukrainophilia]], which would then cross-over into the Russian Empire. With the start of [[World War I]], all those supporting Russia were rounded up and massacred by the Austrian forces at [[Talerhof]].

==First World War, the revolutions and aftermath==
{{Main|Ukraine in World War I|Ukraine after the Russian Revolution}}
{{See also|Ukrainian War of Independence}}

When World War I and series of revolutions across the Europe including the [[October Revolution]] in Russia shattered many existing empires such as the [[Austrian Empire|Austrian]] and [[Imperial Russia|Russian]] ones, while people of Ukraine were caught in the middle. Between 1917 and 1918, several separate Ukrainian republics manifested independence, the [[anarchist]] [[Free Territory]], the [[Ukrainian People's Republic]], the [[West Ukrainian People's Republic]], and numerous [[Ukrainian SSR|Bolshevik revkoms]].

As the area of Ukraine fell into warfare and anarchy, it was also fought over by [[German Army|German]] and [[Austro-Hungarian Army|Austrian forces]], the [[Red Army]] of [[Bolshevik Russia]], the [[White Forces]] of [[General Denikin]], the [[Polish Army]], [[anarchist]]s led by [[Nestor Makhno]]. [[Kiev]] itself was occupied by many different armies. The city was captured by the Bolsheviks on 9 February 1918, by the Germans on 2 March 1918, by the Bolsheviks a second time on 5 February 1919, by the White Army on 31 August 1919, by Bolsheviks for a third time on 15 December 1919, by the Polish Army on 6 
May 1920,  and finally by the Bolsheviks for the fourth time on 12 June 1920.

The defeat in the [[Polish-Ukrainian War]] and then the failure of the [[Józef Piłsudski|Piłsudski]]'s and [[Symon Petlura|Petliura]]'s ''[[Treaty of Warsaw (1920)|Warsaw agreement of 1920]]'' to oust the Bolsheviks during the [[Kiev Offensive|Kiev Operation]] led almost to the occupation of Poland itself. In course of the new [[Polish-Soviet War]] purpose of which changed from the 1920 led to the signing of the [[Peace of Riga]] in March 1921, and after which the part of [[Ukraine]] west of [[Zbruch river|Zbruch]] had been incorporated into [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]], and the east became part of the Soviet Union as the [[Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic]].

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Skoropadsky - before 1917.jpg|[[Pavlo Skoropadskyi]]
File:ZUNR coa.svg|Coat of arms of the [[West Ukrainian People's Republic]]
File:Alex K Ukrainska Derzhava.svg|Coat of arms of the [[Ukrainian State]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=={{anchor|interwar}} Interbellum==&lt;!-- Do not change anchor name, a link with articles. WP:ANCHOR --&gt;

===Soviet Ukraine===
[[File:Flag of Ukrainian SSR.svg|thumb|300px|[[Flag of the Ukrainian SSR|Flag of Soviet Ukraine]]]]
{{see also|Ukrainian_Soviet_Socialist_Republic#interbellum|label 1=Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic, Interwar years: 1922–1939}}
The Ukrainian national idea lived on during the inter-war years and was even spread to a large territory with traditionally mixed population in the east and south that became part of the Ukrainian [[Republics of the Soviet Union|Soviet republic]]. The [[Ukrainian culture]] even enjoyed a revival due to Bolshevik concessions in the early Soviet years (until early-1930s) known as the policy of [[Korenization]] (&quot;indigenisation&quot;). In these years, an impressive [[Ukrainization]] program was implemented throughout the republic. The rapidly developed Ukrainian language based education system dramatically raised the literacy of the Ukrainophone rural population. Simultaneously, the newly-literate ethnic Ukrainians migrated to the cities, which became rapidly largely Ukrainianised—in both population and in education. Similarly expansive was an increase in Ukrainian language publishing and overall eruption of Ukrainian cultural life.

At the same time, the usage of Ukrainian was continuously encouraged in the workplace and in the government affairs as the recruitment of indigenous cadre was implemented as part of the korenisation policies. While initially, the party and government apparatus was mostly Russian-speaking, by the end of 1920s the ethnic Ukrainians composed over one half of the membership in the Ukrainian communist party, the number strengthened by accession of [[Borotbists]], a formerly indigenously Ukrainian &quot;independentist&quot; and non-Bolshevik communist party.

Despite the ongoing [[Soviet Union]]-wide antireligious campaign, the Ukrainian national [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Orthodox]] church was created called the [[Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church]] (UAOC). The Bolshevik government initially saw the national church as a tool in their goal to suppress the [[Russian Orthodox Church]] always viewed with the great suspicion by the regime for its being the cornerstone of pre-revolutionary [[Russian Empire]] and the initially strong opposition it took towards the regime change. Therefore, the government tolerated the new Ukrainian national church for some time and the UAOC gained a wide following among the Ukrainian peasantry.
[[File:DneproGES.jpg|thumb|left|A 1934 photo of the [[DnieproGES]] hydropower plant, a heavyweight of Soviet industrialization in Ukraine.]]

The change in the Soviet economic policies towards the fast-pace [[History of the Soviet Union (1927-1953)#Industrialisation in practice|industrialisation]] was marked by the 1928 introduction of [[Joseph Stalin]]'s first [[piatiletka]] (a five-year plan). The industrialisation brought about a dramatic economic and social transformation in traditionally agricultural Ukraine. In the first piatiletkas the industrial output of Ukraine quadrupled as the republic underwent a record industrial development. The massive influx of the rural population to the industrial centres increased the urban population from 19% to 34%.

However, the industrialisation had a heavy cost for the peasantry, demographically a backbone of the Ukrainian nation. To satisfy the state's need for increased food supplies and finance industrialisation, Stalin instituted a [[Collectivisation in the USSR|program of collectivisation]] of agriculture, which profoundly affected Ukraine, often referred to as the &quot;breadbasket of the USSR&quot;. In the late 1920s and early 1930s, the state combined the peasants' lands and animals into collective farms. Starting in 1929, a policy of enforcement was applied, using regular troops and secret police to confiscate lands and materials where necessary.

Many resisted, and a desperate struggle by the peasantry against the authorities ensued. Some slaughtered their livestock rather than turn it over to the collectives. Wealthier peasants were labeled &quot;[[kulak]]s&quot;, enemies of the state. Tens of thousands were executed and about 100,000 families were deported to Siberia and Kazakhstan.

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Holodomor Famine map.jpg|thumb|Rate of population decline in Ukraine and some regions of the USSR as a result of the [[Holodomor]]&lt;br&gt;Note: The map was created according to the data of the localities affected by the Holomodor and extrapolated to the post-WW2 administrative divisions. For example, in the [[Moldavian SSR]], only [[Transnistria]] have been affected by the Holodomor. In the Odessa Oblast, the [[Bugeac]] was not affected by the Holodomor.]] --&gt;

Forced collectivisation had a devastating effect on agricultural productivity. Despite this, in 1932 the Soviet government increased Ukraine's production quotas by 44%, ensuring that they could not be met. Soviet law required that the members of a collective farm would receive no grain until government quotas were satisfied. The authorities in many instances exacted such high levels of procurement from collective farms that starvation became widespread.

The precise number of Ukrainians murdered by Stalin's custom-made famine and firing squads remains unknown to this day. The KGB's archives, and recent work by Russian historians, show at least seven million died. Ukrainian historians put the figure at nine million, or higher. Twenty-five percent of Ukraine's population was exterminated in what is known as the ''[[Holodomor]]'' or ''[[Holodomor|Ukrainian Holocaust]]''.

The Soviet Union suppressed information about this genocide, and as late as the 1980s admitted only that there was some hardship because of kulak sabotage and bad weather. Today, its existence is accepted.{{By whom|date=July 2009}} Non-Soviets maintain that the famine was an avoidable, deliberate act of genocide.

The times of industrialisation and collectivisation also brought about a wide campaign against &quot;nationalist deviation&quot; which in Ukraine translated into an assault on the national political and cultural elite. The first wave of purges between 1929 and 1934 targeted the revolutionary generation of the party that in Ukraine included many supporters of [[Ukrainization]]. [[Great Purge|The next 1936–1938 wave of political purges]] eliminated much of the new political generation that replaced those that perished in the first wave and halved the membership of the Ukrainian communist party. The purged Ukrainian political leadership was largely replaced by the cadre sent from [[Russian SFSR|Russia]] that was also largely &quot;rotated&quot; by Stalin's purges. As the policies of Ukrainisation were halted (1931) and replaced by massive [[Russification]] approximately four-fifths of the Ukrainian cultural elite, intellectuals, writers, artists and clergy, had been &quot;eliminated&quot;, executed or imprisoned, in the following decade.&lt;ref name=Britannica&gt;Encyclopædia Britannica, [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-30078/Ukraine Ukraine] article, page 51.&lt;/ref&gt; Mass arrests of the hierarchy and clergy of the [[Ukrainian Autocephalous Orthodox Church]] culminated in the liquidation of the church in 1930.

===Galicia and Volhynia under Polish rule===
[[File:PBW March 1919.png|thumb|right|The breaking of the [[Battle of Lwów (1918)|siege of Lviv]] by Poles (November 1919) and the Polish border at the [[Zbruch River]] by the wars end, with eastern Galicia (shown in blue) under the Polish control.]]
{{Main|History of Poland (1918–1939)}}
{{See also|Treaty of Warsaw (1920)}}

Following the end of World War I, the eastern part of the former Austrian province of [[Galicia (eastern Europe)|Galicia]], as well as [[Volhynia]], which had belonged to the [[Russian Empire]], became the area of a [[Polish-Ukrainian War]]. The Ukrainians claimed these lands because they made up the majority of population there (except for cities, such as [[Lviv]]), while the Poles saw these provinces as [[Kresy|Eastern Borderlands]], a [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth|historical part of their country]]. The war was won by the Poles, and their rule over these disputed lands was cemented after another [[Treaty of Riga|Polish victory]], in the [[Polish-Soviet War]].

In the interbellum period, eastern Galicia was divided into three [[voivodeship|administrative units]] — [[Lwów Voivodeship]], [[Stanisławów Voivodeship]], and [[Tarnopol Voivodeship]], while in Volhynia, [[Wołyń Voivodeship (1921–1939)|Wołyń Voivodeship]] was created. Ukrainian majority of these lands was repressed by the Polish authorities, and the conflict escalated in the 1930s, also due to terrorist actions of the [[Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists]]. The tensions were further exacerbated by arrival of thousands of [[osadnik]]s, or Polish settlers, who were granted land, especially in Volhynia.

Polish rule over the provinces ended in 1939, following [[Polish September Campaign|Nazi and Soviet attack]]. After [[Battle of Lvov (1939)|Battle of Lwow]], units of the [[Red Army]] entered regional capital, Lviv, and following [[Elections to the People's Assemblies of Western Ukraine and Western Belarus]], both eastern Galicia and Volhynia were annexed by the [[Soviet Union]].

===Bukovina under Romanian rule===
{{Main|Bukovina}}
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

===Transcarpathia under Czechoslovakia and Hungary===
{{Main|Carpathian Ruthenia|Carpatho-Ukraine}}
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

==World War II==
[[File:Ukrainian SSR 1940.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Ukrainian SSR in 1940, after the Soviet invasions of [[Soviet invasion of Poland (1939)|Poland]] and [[Soviet occupation of Bessarabia and Northern Bukovina|Romania]] and before the [[Operation Barbarossa|German invasion of Soviet Union]].]]

Following the [[Ribbentrop-Molotov pact]], in September 1939, German and Soviet troops [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|divided the territory of Poland]], including [[Galicia (Central Europe)|Galicia]] with its Ukrainian population. Next, after [[Battle of France|France surrendered]] to Germany, [[Romania]] ceded [[Bessarabia]] and northern [[Bukovina]] to [[June 1940 Soviet Ultimatum|Soviet demands]]. The Ukrainian SSR incorporated northern and southern districts of Bessarabia, the northern Bukovina, and additionally the Soviet-occupied [[Hertsa region]], but ceded the western part of the [[Moldavian ASSR]] to the newly-created [[Moldavian SSR]]. All these territorial gains were internationally recognized by the [[Paris Peace Treaties, 1947]].

When [[Nazi Germany]] with [[Axis forces|its allies]] [[Operation Barbarossa|invaded the Soviet Union]] in 1941, many Ukrainians and Polish people, particularly in the west where they had experienced two years of harsh Soviet rule, initially regarded the Nazis as liberators. Some Ukrainian activist of the national movement hoped for a momentum to establish an independent state of Ukraine. German policies initially gave some encouragement to such hopes through the vague promises of sovereign 'Greater Ukraine' as the Germans were trying to take advantage of anti-Soviet, anti-Ukrainian, anti-Polish, and anti-Jewish sentiments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Luciuk| first=Lubomyr Y.|title=Searching for place: Ukrainian displaced persons, Canada, and the migration of memory|publisher=University of Toronto Press|year=2000|page=125|isbn=0-8020-4245-7|url=  http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN080208088X&amp;id=6srpcaGeuvcC&amp;pg=PA125&amp;lpg=PA125&amp;dq=ukrainians+under+germans&amp;sig=OTTMYCLmt0qe9mtdMFqPUPVKRYM#v=onepage&amp;q=ukrainians%20under%20germans&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; A local Ukrainian auxiliary police was formed as well as Ukrainian SS division, [[14th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS Galicia (1st Ukrainian)]]. However, after the initial period of a limited tolerance, the German policies soon abruptly changed and the Ukrainian national movement was brutally crushed.

Most Ukrainians, however, utterly resisted the Nazi onslaught from its start and a [[Soviet partisans|partisan movement]] immediately spread over the occupied territory. Some elements of the Ukrainian nationalist underground formed a [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army]] that fought both Soviet and Nazi forces. In some western regions of Ukraine, the Ukrainian Insurgent Army survived underground and continued the resistance against the Soviet authorities well into the 1950s, though many Ukrainian civilians were murdered in this conflict by both sides.

The Nazi administrators of conquered Soviet territories made little attempt to exploit the population's possible dissatisfaction with Soviet political and economic policies. Instead, the Nazis preserved the collective-farm system, systematically carried out genocidal policies against Jews, and deported many Ukrainians to forced labour in Germany. In their active resistance to Nazi Germany, the Ukrainians comprised a significant share of the Red Army and its leadership as well as the underground and resistance movements.
Total civilian losses during the War and German occupation in Ukraine are estimated at seven million, including over a million Jews shot and killed by the ''[[Einsatzgruppen]]''.

Many civilians fell victim to atrocities, forced labor, and even massacres of whole villages in reprisal for attacks against Nazi forces. Of the estimated eleven million Soviet troops who fell in battle against the Nazis, about 25% (2.7 million) were ethnic Ukrainians. Moreover, Ukraine saw some of the biggest battles of the war starting with the [[Battle of Kiev (1941)|encirclement of Kiev]] (the city itself fell to the Germans on 19 September 1941 and was later acclaimed as a ''[[Hero City]]'') where more than 660,000 Soviet troops were taken captive, to the fierce defence of [[Odessa]], and on to the victorious storming across the [[Dnieper river]].

Kiev was recaptured by the Soviet Red Army on 6 November 1943.

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Stamp Russia occ Ukraine 1941 12pf.jpg|German occupation of Ukraine stamp of 1941
File:Cherkaschyna deportation 1942.jpg|Ukrainians [[OST-Arbeiter|being deported]] to [[Nazi Germany]] for forced labor, 1942
File:ZaporizhiaCombat.jpg|Battle of the dam in Zaporizhia, 1943
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Post-war==
{{see also|Ukrainian_Soviet_Socialist_Republic#postwar|label 1=Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic, Post-war years: 1945–1953}}
After World War II some amendments to the Constitution of the [[Ukrainian SSR]] were accepted, which allowed it to act as a separate subject of [[international law]] in some cases and to a certain extent, remaining a part of the Soviet Union at the same time. In particular, these amendments allowed the Ukrainian SSR to become one of founding members of the [[United Nations]] (UN) together with the Soviet Union and the [[Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic|Byelorussian SSR]]. This was part of a deal with the [[United States]] to ensure a degree of balance in the [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]], which, the USSR opined, was unbalanced in favor of the Western Bloc. In its capacity as a member of the UN, the Ukrainian SSR was [[List of members of the United Nations Security Council|an elected member]] of the [[United Nations Security Council]] in 1948–1949 and 1984–1985.

Over the next decades, the Ukrainian republic not only surpassed pre-war levels of industry and production but also was the spearhead of Soviet power. Ukraine became the centre of Soviet [[arms industry]] and high-tech research. The republic was also turned into a Soviet military outpost in the [[cold war]], a territory crowded by military bases packed with the most up-to-date weapons systems.

Such an important role resulted in a major influence of the local elite. Many members of the Soviet leadership came from Ukraine, most notably [[Nikita Khrushchev]] and [[Leonid Brezhnev]] a Soviet leader from 1964 to 1982, as well as many prominent Soviet sportsmen, scientists and artists. In 1954, the [[Russians|Russian]]-populated oblast of [[Crimea]] was transferred from the Russian to the Ukrainian Soviet Republic.

However, the relatively underdeveloped industrial branches such as [[coal mining|coal]]- and [[iron ore]] mining, [[metallurgy]], [[chemical industry|chemical]] and [[energy industry]] dominated the republic's economy. Once a [[Cossack]] steppe, the southern oblasts of [[Dnipropetrovsk Oblast|Dnipropetrovsk]] and [[Zaporizhzhia Oblast|Zaporizhzhia]] were turned into a highly industrialised area with rapidly increasing impact on its environment and public health. A pursuit to energy production sufficient for growing industry led to the gigantic nature-remastering: turning the [[Dnieper River]] into a regulated system of large reservoirs.

The products of the rapidly developed [[high-tech]] industry in Ukraine were largely directed for military consumption, similarly to much of the [[Economy of the Soviet Union|Soviet economy]], and the supply and quality of [[consumer goods]] remained low compared even to the neighboring countries of the [[Eastern bloc]]. A state-regulated system of production and consumption lead to gradual decrease of quality of life and growing &quot;shadowisation&quot; of retail infrastructure as well as of corruption.
&lt;!--To be continued---&gt;

The town of [[Pripyat, Ukraine]] was the site of the [[Chernobyl disaster]], which occurred on April 26, 1986 when a nuclear plant exploded. The fallout contaminated large areas of northern Ukraine and even parts of [[Belarus]]. This spurred on a local independence movement called the [[People's Movement of Ukraine|Rukh]] that helped expedite the break-up of the Soviet Union during the late 1980s.

==Independence==

=== Kravchuk and Kuchma rule (1991–2004) ===
On January 21, 1990, over 300,000 Ukrainians&lt;ref name=&quot;subtelny-576&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Ukraine: A History|author=Subtelny, Orest|publisher=[[University of Toronto Press]]|year= 2000|isbn=0-8020-8390-0|page=576|authorlink= Orest Subtelny}}&lt;/ref&gt; organised a human chain for Ukrainian independence between [[Kiev]] and [[Lviv]], in [[Act Zluky|memory of the 1919 unification]] of the [[Ukrainian People's Republic]] and the [[West Ukrainian National Republic]]. Citizens came out to the streets and highways, forming live chains by holding hands in support of unity. 

Ukraine officially declared itself an independent state on August 24, 1991, when the communist Supreme Soviet (parliament) of Ukraine proclaimed that Ukraine will no longer follow the laws of USSR and only the laws of the Ukrainian SSR, de facto declaring Ukraine's independence from the Soviet Union. On December 1, Ukrainian voters overwhelmingly approved a referendum formalising independence from the Soviet Union. Over 90% of Ukrainian citizens voted for independence, with majorities in every region, including 56% in [[Crimea]], which had a 75% ethnic Russian population. The Soviet Union formally ceased to exist on December 26, when the presidents of Ukraine, Belarus and Russia (the founding members of the USSR) met in [[Belovezh Pushcha]] to formally dissolve the Union in accordance with the Soviet Constitution. And with this Ukraine's independence was formalized de jure and recognised by the international community.

The first nation to recognize Ukraine's independence was Canada, which has the largest ethnic Ukrainian minority in the West. 

The history of Ukraine between 1991 and 2004 was marked by the presidencies of [[Leonid Kravchuk]] and [[Leonid Kuchma]]. This was a time of transition for Ukraine. While it had attained nominal independence from Russia, its presidents maintained close ties with their neighbours.

On June 1, 1996, Ukraine became a non-nuclear nation when it sent the last of its 1,900 strategic nuclear warheads it had inherited from the Soviet Union to Russia for dismantling.;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/0773520872 Power versus Prudence: Why Nations Forgo Nuclear Weapons] by [[T. V. Paul]], [[McGill-Queen's University Press]], 2000, ISBN 978-0-7735-2087-5, page 117&lt;/ref&gt; Ukraine had committed to this by signing the [[Budapest Memorandum on Security Assurances]] in January 1994.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/1574885855 Tactical Nuclear Weapons: Emergent Threats in an Evolving Security Environment] by Brian Alexander, [[Brassey's US]], 2003, ISBN 978-1-57488-585-9, page 139&lt;/ref&gt;

The country adopted its constitution on June 28.

The [[Cassette Scandal]] of 2000 was one of the turning points in post-independence history of the country.

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Leonid Kravchuk.jpg|[[Leonid Kravchuk]] in 1992
File:Ukraine.LeonidKuchma.01 cropped.jpg|[[Leonid Kuchma]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Orange Revolution (2004)===
[[File:Joesjtsjenko Marion Kiev 2004.jpg|thumb|Protesters at [[Maidan Nezalezhnosti|Independence Square]] on the first day of the Orange Revolution.]]
{{main|Orange Revolution}}
In 2004, Leonid Kuchma announced that he would not run for re-election. Two major candidates emerged in the [[Ukrainian presidential election, 2004|2004 presidential election]]. [[Viktor Yanukovych]], the incumbent Prime Minister, supported by both Kuchma and by the Russian Federation, wanted closer ties with Russia. The main opposition candidate, [[Viktor Yushchenko]], called for Ukraine to turn its attention westward and eventually join the EU. In the runoff election, Yanukovych officially won by a narrow margin, but Yushchenko and his supporters cried foul, alleging that vote rigging and intimidation cost him many votes, especially in eastern Ukraine. A political crisis erupted after the opposition started massive street [[Orange Revolution|protests in Kiev and other cities]], and the [[Supreme Court of Ukraine]] ordered the election results null and void. A second runoff found [[Viktor Yushchenko]] the winner. Five days later, [[Viktor Yanukovych]] resigned from office and his cabinet was dismissed on January 5, 2005.

===Since the Orange Revolution===
In March 2006, the [[Verkhovna Rada]] [[Ukrainian parliamentary election, 2006|elections]] took place and three months later the official government was formed by the &quot;[[Anti-Crisis Coalition]]&quot; among the ''[[Party of Regions]]'', ''[[Communist Party of Ukraine|Communist]]'', and ''[[Socialist Party of Ukraine|Socialist]]'' parties. The latter party switched from the &quot;Orange Coalition&quot; with ''[[Our Ukraine Bloc/Our Ukraine–People's Self-Defense Bloc|Our Ukraine]]'', and the ''[[Yulia Tymoshenko Bloc]]''. The new coalition nominated Viktor Yanukovych for the post of Prime Minister. Yanukovych once again became Prime Minister, while the leader of the Socialist Party, [[Oleksander Moroz]], managed to secure the position of chairman of parliament, which is believed by many to have been the reason for his leaving the Orange Coalition, where he had not been considered for this position.

On April 2, 2007, President Yushchenko dissolved the Verkhovna Rada because members of his party were defecting to the opposition.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Lee Myers Published: May 31, 2007, [http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/05/31/america/kiev.php Confusion, chaos and comedy in Ukrainian politics] International Herald Tribune&lt;/ref&gt; His opponents called the move unconstitutional. When they took the matter to the [[Constitutional Court of Ukraine|Constitutional Court]], Yushchenko dismissed 3 of the court's 18 judges, accusing them of corruption.

During the Yushchenko term, relations between Russia and Ukraine often appeared strained as Yushchenko looked towards improved relations with the European Union and less toward Russia. In 2005, a highly-publicized [[Russia-Ukraine gas dispute|dispute over natural gas prices]] took place, involving Russian state-owned gas supplier Gazprom, and indirectly involving many European countries which depend on natural gas supplied by Russia through the Ukrainian pipeline. A compromise was reached in January 2006, and in early 2010 a further agreement was signed locking the price of Russian gas at $100 per 1,000 cubic meters in an exclusive arrangement.

By the time of the presidential election of 2009, Yushchenko and Tymoshenko — allies during the Orange Revolution — had become bitter enemies. Tymoshenko ran for president against both Yushchenko and Viktor Yanukovych, creating a three-way race. Yushchenko, whose popularity had plummeted, refused to close ranks and support Tymoshenko, thus dividing the anti-Yanukovych vote. Many pro-Orange voters stayed home.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1963613,00.html Ukraine's New President: Is the Orange Revolution Over?], [[Time.com]] (11 February 2010)&lt;/ref&gt; Yanukovych received 48% of the vote and Yushchenko less than 6%, an amount which, if thrown to Tymoshenko, who received 45%, would have prevented Yanukovych from gaining the presidency; since no candidate obtained an absolute majority in the first round of voting the two highest polling candidates contested in a run-off second ballot which Yanukovych won.

During Yanukovych's term he has been accused of [[Freedom of the press in Ukraine#Latest developments|tightening of press restrictions]] and a renewed effort in the parliament to limit freedom of assembly.&lt;ref&gt;Appleseed Democracy Documentary interview with Ukrainian MP Andriy Schevchenko 6 July 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Umland&gt;[http://www.opendemocracy.net/od-russia/andreas-umland/ukraine-right-wing-politics-is-genie-out-of-bottle Ukraine right-wing politics: is the genie out of the bottle?], [[openDemocracy.net]] (January 3, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-12171740 Ukraine viewpoint: Novelist Andrey Kurkov], [[BBC News]] (January 13, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-12042561 Ukraine ex-PM Tymoshenko charged with misusing funds], [[BBC News]] (December 20, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osw.waw.pl/en/publikacje/osw-commentary/2010-09-29/party-regions-monopolises-power-ukraine#_ftn5 The Party of Regions monopolises power in Ukraine], [[Centre for Eastern Studies]] (September 29, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-12219712 Ukraine launches battle against corruption], [[BBC News]] (January 18, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-11549381 Ukrainians' long wait for prosperity], [[BBC News]] (October 18, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://pulitzercenter.org/blog/news-points/ukraine-press-censorship-journalists-uncertain-future Ukraine:Journalists Face Uncertain Future], [[Pulitzer Center on Crisis Reporting]] (October 27, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.turkishweekly.net/news/108194/yanukovych-tells-u-k-39-s-cameron-no-fears-for-ukraine-39-s-democracy.html Yanukovych Tells U.K's Cameron No Fears for Ukraine's Democracy], [[Turkish Weekly]] (October 6, 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.partyofregions.org.ua/eng/pr-east-west/4d394880be20c/ Yulia Kovalevska:Only some bankrupt politicians try to use the Day of Unification with the aim of self-PR], [[Party of Regions]] official website (January 21, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.president.gov.ua/en/news/19116.html President: Ukraine must fulfill its commitments to Council of Europe], [[president.gov.ua]] (January 13, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.interfax.com.ua/eng/main/69573/ Our Ukraine comes to defense of Tymoshenko, Lutsenko, Didenko, Makarenko in statement], [[Interfax-Ukraine]] (May 25, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; One frequently-cited example of Yankukovych's alleged attempts to centralize power is the August 2011 arrest of Yulia Tymoshenko.&lt;ref&gt;http://ukraine.usembassy.gov/government-statement-tymoshenko.html  [[US Embassy, Kiev]], (September 24, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-14459446 [[BBC News]], (September 24, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; Other high-profile political opponents also came under criminal investigation since.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kyivpost.com/news/politics/detail/112105/, [[Kyiv Post]] (September 24, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,736745,00.html, [[Der Spiegel]] (September 24, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kyivpost.com/news/politics/detail/79199/ [[Kyiv Post]] (September 24, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kyivpost.com/news/nation/detail/112081/ [[Kyiv Post]] (September 24, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; On 11 October 2011, a Ukrainian court sentenced Tymoshenko to seven years in prison after she was found guilty of abuse of office when brokering the [[2009 Russia–Ukraine gas dispute|2009 gas deal with Russia]].&lt;ref name=BBCOct2011&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-15250742 Ukraine ex-PM Yulia Tymoshenko jailed over gas deal], BBC News (11 October 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; The conviction is seen as &quot;justice being applied selectively under political motivation&quot; by the [[European Union]] and other international organizations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euronews.net/2011/10/11/eu-feels-let-down-by-ukraine-over-tymoshenko/ EU feels let down by Ukraine over Tymoshenko], [[Euronews]] (11 October 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Viktor Yuschenko.jpg|[[Viktor Yushchenko]] with [[chloracne]] from [[2,3,7,8-Tetrachlorodibenzodioxin|TCDD]] [[Polychlorinated dibenzodioxins|dioxin]] poisoning (2006).
File:Yulia Tymoshenko, 2010.JPG|[[Yulia Tymoshenko]] (2010)
File:Viktor Yanukovych 27 April 2010-1.jpeg|[[Viktor Yanukovych]] (2010)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Historiography of Ukraine==
The scholarly study of Ukraine's history emerged from romantic impulses in the late 19th century. The outstanding leaders were Volodymyr Antonovych (1834–1908), based in Kiev, and his student Michael Hrushevsky (1866–1934).&lt;ref&gt;Serhii Plokhy, ''Unmaking Imperial Russia: Mykhailo Hrushevsky and the Writing of Ukrainian History'' (2005)&lt;/ref&gt; For the first time full-scale scholarly studies based on archival sources, modern research techniques, and modern historical theories became possible. However, the demands of government officials—especially Soviet, but also Czarists and Polish—made it difficult to disseminate ideas that ran counter to the central government. Therefore exile schools of historians emerged in central Europe and Canada after 1920.&lt;ref&gt;KubijovyČ, ed. ''Ukraine: A Concise Encyclopedia'' (1963) 1:559-74&lt;/ref&gt;

Strikingly different interpretations of the medieval state of Kievan Rus' appear in the four schools of historiography within Ukraine: Russophile, Sovietophile, Eastern Slavic, and Ukrainophile. The Sovietophile and Russophile schools have become marginalized in independent Ukraine, with the Ukrainophile school being dominant in the early 21st century. The Ukrainophile school promotes an identity that is mutually exclusive of Russia. It has come to dominate the nation's educational system, security forces, and national symbols and monuments, although it has been dismissed as nationalist by Western historians. The East Slavic school, an eclectic compromise between Ukrainophiles and Russophilism, has a weaker ideological and symbolic base, although it is preferred by Ukraine's centrist former elites.&lt;ref&gt;Taras Kuzio, &quot;National Identity and History Writing in Ukraine,&quot; ''Nationalities Papers'' 2006 34(4): 407–427, online in [[EBSCO]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Many historians in recent years have sought alternatives to national histories, and Ukrainian history invited approaches that looked beyond a national paradigm. Multiethnic history recognizes the numerous peoples in Ukraine; transnational history portrays Ukraine as a border zone for various empires; and area studies categorizes Ukraine as part of Eurasia, or more often as part of East-Central Europe. Plokhy (2007) argues that looking beyond the country's national history has made possible a richer understanding of Ukraine, its people, and the surrounding regions.&lt;ref&gt;Serhii Plokhy, &quot;Beyond Nationality&quot; ''Ab Imperio'' 2007 (4): 25–46,&lt;/ref&gt;

After 1991, historical memory was a powerful tool in the political mobilization and legitimation of the post-Soviet Ukrainian state, as well as the division of selectively used memory along the lines of the political division of Ukrainian society. Ukraine did not experience the restorationist paradigm typical of some other post-Soviet nations, including the Baltic states, although the multifaceted history of independence, the Orthodox Church in Ukraine, Soviet-era repressions, mass famine, and World War II collaboration were used to provide a different constitutive frame for the new Ukrainian nation. The politics of identity (which includes the production of history textbooks and the authorization of commemorative practices) has remained fragmented and tailored to reflect the ideological anxieties and concerns of individual regions of Ukraine.&lt;ref&gt;See Andryi Portnov, &quot;Exercises with history Ukrainian style (notes on public aspects of history's functioning in post-Soviet Ukraine),&quot; ''Ab Imperio'' 2007 (3): 93–138, in Ukrainian&lt;/ref&gt;

===Historical maps of Ukraine===
The Ukrainian state has occupied a number of territories since its initial foundation. Most of these territories have been located within [[Eastern Europe]], however, as depicted in the maps in the gallery below, has also at times extended well into [[Eurasia]] and southeastern Europe.
At times there has also been a distinct lack of a Ukrainian state, as its territories were on a number of occasions, annexed by its more powerful neighbours.
&lt;center&gt;
{| class=&quot;collapsible collapsed&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #ddd; float:center; margin:5px 5px 0 0;&quot;
|-
!style=&quot;background:#f5f5f5; padding:5px;&quot;|&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 10px 0 20px;&quot;&gt;Historical Maps of Ukraine and its Predecessors&lt;/span&gt;
|-
|{{Gallery
|width=135
|lines=2
|File:Slavic peoples 6th century historical map.jpg|Territory of Slavic peoples (6th century).
|File:East Slavic tribes peoples 8th 9th century.jpg|European territory inahibted by East Slavic tribes in 8th and 9th century.
|File:Kievan Rus' Kyivan Rus' early formation 862 912.jpg|Early formation of [[Kievan Rus']] (862–912): Territory of rulers Askold, Dyr and Oleh of Novgorod.
|File:Kievan Rus' historical map 980 1054.jpg|Gallery of Historical map of Kievan Rus' at its zenith (980–1054).
|File:001 Kievan Rus' Kyivan Rus' Ukraine map 1220 1240.jpg|Historical map of Kievan Rus' and territory of Ukraine: last 20 years of the state (1220–1240).
|File:Kingdom of Galicia Volhynia Rus' Ukraine 1245 1349.jpg|The [[Kingdom of Galicia–Volhynia]] or Kingdom of Halych-Volynia (1245–1349).
|File:Grand Duchy of Lithuania Rus and Samogitia 1434.jpg|Historical map of [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]], Rus' (Ukraine) and Samogitia until 1434.
|File:Ukrainian Cossack state Zaporizhian Host 1649 1653.jpg|Historical map of [[Cossack Hetmanate]], also known as Hetmanate of Zaporizhian Host or Ukrainian Cossack state (1649–1653).
|File:Polish Lithuanian Ruthenian Commonwealth 1658 historical map.jpg|[[Polish–Lithuanian–Ruthenian Commonwealth]] or Commonwealth of Three Nations (1658).
|File:007 Ukrainian Cossack Hetmanate and Russian Empire 1751.jpg|Historical map of Ukrainian Cossack Hetmanate and territory of Zaporozhian Cossacks under rule of [[Russian Empire]] (1751).
|File:Ukrainian National Republic map 1917 1920.jpg|Historical map of Ukrainian National Republic or [[Ukrainian People's Republic]] (1917–1920).
}}
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==Bibliography==
*''Encyclopedia of Ukraine'' (University of Toronto Press, 1984–93) 5 vol; from [http://www.utoronto.ca/cius/webfiles/eu.htm Canadian Institute of Ukrainian Studies], partly online
*''Ukraine: A Concise Encyclopedia.'' ed by Volodymyr E. KubijovyČ; University of Toronto Press. 1963; 1188pp [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=58069636 online at [[Questia]]]
*Kohut, Zenon E.; Nebesio, Bohdan Y.; and Yurkevich, Myroslav. ''Historical Dictionary of Ukraine.'' (2005). 854 pp.
*Aslund, Anders, and Michael McFaul.''Revolution in Orange: The Origins of Ukraine's Democratic Breakthrough'' (2006)
*Brandon, Ray, and Wendy Lower, eds. ''The Shoah in Ukraine: History, Testimony, Memorialization.'' (2008). 378 pp. [http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.php?id=24078 online review]
*[[Karel C. Berkhoff|Berkhoff, Karel C.]] ''Harvest of Despair: Life and Death in Ukraine Under Nazi Rule.'' (2004). 448 pp.
*D'Anieri, Paul, et al. ''Politics and Society in Ukraine'' (1999) [http://www.questia.com/read/85964038?title=Politics%20and%20Society%20in%20Ukraine online edition]
*Dimarov, Anatoliy et al. ''A Hunger Most Cruel: The Human Face of the 1932–1933 Terror-Famine in Soviet Ukraine'' (2002) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/096838997X excerpt and text search]
*Gross, Jan T. ''Revolution from Abroad: The Soviet Conquest of Poland's Western Ukraine and Western Belorussia'' (1988).
*[[Mykhailo Hrushevsky]]. ''A History of Ukraine'' (1986)
*[[Mykhailo Hrushevsky]]. ''History of Ukraine-Rus''' in 9 volumes. [http://www.utoronto.ca/cius/bios/hrushevskybio.htm Selected volumes translated into English]. Available online in Ukrainian as [http://litopys.org.ua/hrushrus/iur.htm &quot;Історія України-Руси&quot;].
*[[Askold Krushelnycky]]. ''An Orange Revolution: A Personal Journey Through Ukrainian History.'' (2006). ISBN 0-436-20623-4. 320 pages.
*Kutaisov, Aleksandr. ''[http://www.archive.org/details/ukrainaby00kutauoft Ukraina]'' (1918).
*Kubicek, Paul. ''The History of Ukraine'' (2008) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0313349207 excerpt and text search]
*Kuzio, Taras. ''Ukraine: State and Nation Building'' (1998) [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=102997170 online edition]
*Luckyj, George S. ''Literary Politics in the Soviet Ukraine, 1917–1934'' (1990). [http://www.questia.com/read/14448562?title=Literary%20Politics%20in%20the%20Soviet%20Ukraine%2c%201917-1934 online edition]
*Lower, Wendy. ''Nazi Empire-Building and the Holocaust in Ukraine.'' U. of North Carolina Press, 2005. 307 pp.
*[[Paul Robert Magocsi]]. ''A History of Ukraine.'' Toronto: University of Toronto Press (1996) ISBN 0-8020-0830-5.
*Plokhy, Serhii. ''The Cossacks and Religion in Early Modern Ukraine'' (2001) [http://www.questia.com/read/115305507?title=The%20Cossacks%20and%20Religion%20in%20Early%20Modern%20Ukraine online edition]
*Redlich, Shimon. ''Together and Apart in Brzezany: Poles, Jews, and Ukrainians, 1919–1945.'' Indiana U. Press, 2002. 202 pp.
*Reid, Anna. ''Borderland: A Journey Through the History of Ukraine'' (2003) [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=96969196 online edition]
*{{cite book|first=Orest|last=Subtelny|title=Ukraine: A History|location=Toronto |publisher=University of Toronto Press|year=2009|isbn=0-8020-8390-0|authorlink=Orest Subtelny}} A Ukrainian translation navailable [http://www.infoukes.com/ukremb/history/SUBTELNY/title.htm online].
* Velychenko, Stephen, &quot;Nationalizing and Denationalizing the Past. Ukraine and Russia in Comparative Context,&quot; Ab Imperio no 1 (2007). http://abimperio.net/cgi-bin/aishow.pl?state=showa&amp;idart=1846&amp;idlang=1&amp;Code=
*Wanner, Catherine. ''Burden of Dreams: History and Identity in Post-Soviet Ukraine'' (1998) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0271030011 excerpt and text search]
*[[Andrew Wilson (historian)|Andrew Wilson]]. ''The Ukrainians: Unexpected Nation.'' Yale University Press; 2nd edition (2002) ISBN 0-300-09309-8.
*[[Alexandre Wolkonsky]]. [http://www.archive.org/details/TheUkraineQuestionTheHistoricTruthVersusTheSeparatistPropaganda The Ukraine Question : The historic truth versus the separatist propaganda.] 1920.
*[[Yekelchyk, Serhy]] (2007). ''Ukraine: Birth of a Modern Nation''. Oxford University Press. ISBN 978-0-19-530545-6.
*Zabarko, Boris, ed. ''Holocaust in the Ukraine.'' Vallentine Mitchell, 2005. 394 pp.
*[http://connexion.oclc.org/WebZ/XPathfinderQuery?sessionid=0:term=5134:xid=LCP Abridged History of Ukraine] at [http://www.loc.gov/rr/international/european/ukraine/ua.html Portals of the World: Ukraine] project by the [[Library of Congress]]

===Historiography and memory===
* Kasianov, Georgiy, and Philipp Ther, eds. ''Laboratory of Transnational History: Ukraine and Recent Ukrainian Historiography'' (Central European University Press 2009) [http://www.questia.com/read/118787789/a-laboratory-of-transnational-history-ukraine-and online edition]
* Velychenko, Stephen, ''National history as cultural process : a survey of the interpretations of Ukraine's past in Polish, Russian, and Ukrainian historical writing from the earliest times to 1914'' (Edmonton, 1992)
* Velychenko, Stephen, ''Shaping identity in Eastern Europe and Russia : Soviet-Russian and Polish accounts of Ukrainian history, 1914-1991'' (London, 1993)

===Primary sources in English===
*Luckyj, George S. ''Towards an Intellectual History of Ukraine: An Anthology of Ukrainian Thought from 1710 to 1995.'' (1996)

===Ukrainian===
*''Essays on History on Ukraine''
**Volume 1 by Natalia Yakovenko, [http://www.vesna.org.ua/txt/yakovenkon/znaid/index.html ''&quot;From the Earliest Times until the End of the 18th Century&quot;'']
**Volume 2: {{cite book|author=Ярослав Грицак (Yaroslav Hrytsak)|title=Формування модерної української нації XIX-XX ст. (Formation of the Modern Ukrainian Nation in the late 19th–20th centuries)|location=[[Kiev]]|publisher=Генеза (Heneza)|year=1996|isbn=966-504-150-9}}. Available [http://www.vesna.org.ua/txt/grytsakj/formuv/index.html online].
*[[Mykhailo Hrushevsky]]. ''Illustrated History of Ukraine'' (1913). Available [http://www.vesna.org.ua/txt/grushevs/istukr/index.html online]
*I. Krypiakevych. [http://www.vesna.org.ua/txt/krypyakevych/istukr/index.html &quot;History of Ukraine]
*''[http://www.vesna.org.ua/txt/dov/istukr/index.html Handbook on the History of Ukraine]''
*&quot;[http://www.wumag.kiev.ua/index2.php?param=pgs20031/4 Ukraine: Briefly about Her Past and Present]&quot;, in ''Welcome to Ukraine'', 2003, 1.
*Polons'ka-Vasylenko, Natalia. ''History of Ukraine'' in two volumes. Available [http://www.vesna.org.ua/txt/polonska/istukr/index.html online].
*[[Alexander F. Tsvirkun]] History of Ukraine.7 class electronic textbooks. Kiev., 2005 (co-authored with [[Valentin A.Savelii]])
*[[Alexander F. Tsvirkun]] E-learning course. History of Ukraine. [[Journal Auditorium]], Kiev 2010

==See also==
{{Portal|Ukraine}}
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Crimean Khanate]]
* [[Dissolution of the Soviet Union]]
* [[History of Christianity in Ukraine]]
* [[History of Belarus]]
* [[History of Germany]]
* [[History of Lithuania]]
* [[History of Poland]]
* [[History of Russia]]
* [[History of Turkey]]
* [[History of the Soviet Union]]
** [[History of the Soviet Union (1927–1953)]]
** [[History of the Soviet Union (1953–1964)]]
** [[History of the Soviet Union (1964–1982)]]
** [[History of the Soviet Union (1982–1991)]]
* [[Kievan Rus]]
* [[List of Ukrainian rulers]]
* [[Politics of Ukraine]]
* [[Ruthenia]]
* [[Ukrainian language]]

{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.day.kiev.ua/131109/ Ukrainian history overview] published in ''[[Den']]''.
*[http://www.holocaustbybullets.com/ The Holocaust by bullets, the Jewish victims of the Einsatzgruppen in Eastern Europe] Yahad In Unum

{{Ukraine topics}}
{{History of Europe}}
{{European history by country}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Ukraine}}
[[Category:History of Ukraine| ]]
[[Category:Ukrainian studies]]
[[Category:History of Austria-Hungary|Ukraine]]

{{Link FA|hr}}

[[bg:История на Украйна]]
[[ca:Història d'Ucraïna]]
[[cs:Dějiny Ukrajiny]]
[[cy:Hanes Wcráin]]
[[de:Geschichte der Ukraine]]
[[et:Ukraina ajalugu]]
[[es:Historia de Ucrania]]
[[eo:Historio de Ukrainio]]
[[fr:Histoire de l'Ukraine]]
[[ko:우크라이나의 역사]]
[[hr:Povijest Ukrajine]]
[[io:Historio di Ukrainia]]
[[he:היסטוריה של אוקראינה]]
[[la:Historia Ucrainae]]
[[lt:Ukrainos istorija]]
[[hu:Ukrajna történelme]]
[[mk:Историја на Украина]]
[[nl:Geschiedenis van Oekraïne]]
[[ja:ウクライナの歴史]]
[[no:Ukrainas historie]]
[[pl:Historia Ukrainy]]
[[pt:História da Ucrânia]]
[[ro:Istoria Ucrainei]]
[[ru:История Украины]]
[[sk:Dejiny Ukrajiny]]
[[sr:Историја Украјине]]
[[fi:Ukrainan historia]]
[[sv:Ukrainas historia]]
[[tr:Ukrayna tarihi]]
[[uk:Історія України]]
[[zh:烏克蘭歷史]]</text>
      <sha1>hi19o4lvng1brikhm5y9z98r8eju2iq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
