<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hundred Years' War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19038039</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521499987</id>
      <parentid>521388261</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T11:58:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Alanscottwalker</username>
        <id>7131173</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Background */ ce</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="62010">{{pp-semi-vandalism|small=yes|expiry=December 19, 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Hundred Years' War
|image = [[File:Hundred Years' War montage.jpg|300px|Hundred Years' War]]
|caption = Clockwise, from top left: [[John of Bohemia]] at the [[Battle of Crécy]],&lt;br /&gt;{{nowrap|English and Franco-Castilian fleets at the [[Battle of La Rochelle]],}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Henry V of England|Henry V]] and the English army at the [[Battle of Agincourt]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Joan of Arc]] rallies French forces at the [[Siege of Orléans]]
|date = 1337–1453
|place = [[France]], the [[Low Countries]], [[England]], [[Spain]]
|result = French victory&lt;br /&gt;House of Valois maintained throne of France
|territory = England lost all continental territory except for the [[Pale of Calais]]
|
|combatant1={{flagicon image|Pavillon royal de la France.svg|size=22px}} [[Kingdom of France|France]]
|combatant2={{flagicon image|Royal Standard of England (1406-1603).svg|size=22px}} [[Kingdom of England|England]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon image|Ancient Flag of Burgundy.svg|size=22px}} [[Duchy of Burgundy|Burgundy]]
|strength1 =
|strength2 =
|casualties1 =
|casualties2 =
|notes =
}}
{{Campaignbox Hundred Years' War}}
{{Campaignbox Edwardian War}}
{{Campaignbox Caroline War}}
{{Campaignbox Lancastrian War}}
The '''Hundred Years' War''' was a series of conflicts waged from 1337 to 1453 between the Kingdom of England and the Kingdom of France and their various allies for control of the French throne. It was the result of a [[dynasty|dynastic]] disagreement dating back to [[William the Conqueror]] who became King of England in 1066, while remaining [[Duke of Normandy]].  As dukes of Normandy, the English kings owed [[Homage (feudal)|homage]] to the King of France. In 1337 [[Edward III of England]] refused to pay homage to [[Philip VI of France]], which resulted in the French king confiscating Edward's lands in [[Aquitaine]].
 
Edward responded by declaring that he, not Philip, was the rightful king of France - a claim dating back to 1328 when Charles IV of France had died without a male heir. A claim for the succession had been made for Edward through the right of his mother Isabella, daughter of Philip IV. But it had been the son of Philip IV’s younger brother, Charles of Valois, who had been made king. The establishment of a legal succession to the French crown was central to the war and there were succeeding generations of English and French claimants. 

The war is commonly divided into three or four phases, separated by various unsuccessful truces: the [[Hundred Years' War (1337–1360)|Edwardian Era War (1337–1360)]],&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.edwardianera.org/edwardian-era-war.html The Edwardian Era War'']''/&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Hundred Years' War (1369–1389)|Caroline War (1369–1389)]], and the [[Hundred Years' War (1415–1453)|Lancastrian War (1415–1453)]], which saw the slow decline of Plantagenet fortunes after the appearance of Joan of Arc (1412–1431). Several other contemporary European conflicts were directly related to this conflict: the [[Breton War of Succession]], the [[Castilian Civil War]]; the [[War of the Two Peters]]; and the [[1383-1385 Crisis]]. The term &quot;Hundred Years' War&quot; was a later term invented by historians to describe the series of events.

The war owes its historical significance to a number of factors. Although primarily a dynastic conflict, the war gave impetus to ideas of both French and English [[nationalism]]. Militarily, it saw the introduction of new weapons and tactics which eroded the older system of [[feudal]] armies dominated by [[heavy cavalry]] in Western Europe. The first [[standing army|standing armies]] in Western Europe since the time of the [[Western Roman Empire]] were introduced for the war, thus changing the role of the [[peasantry]]. For all this, as well as for its long duration, it is often viewed as one of the most significant conflicts in the history of [[medieval warfare]]. In France, civil wars, deadly [[List of epidemics|epidemics]], [[famine]]s and marauding [[mercenary]] armies turned to banditry reduced the population by about one-half.

==Background==
{{see also|The Anarchy}}
[[File:Hommage of Edward I to Philippe le Bel.jpg|thumb|180px|Homage of [[Edward I of England]] (kneeling) to Philip IV (seated) - 1286. As [[Duke of Aquitaine]], Edward was also a vassal to the French king.]]
The [[Anglo-Norman]] dynasty that had ruled England since the [[Norman Conquest]] of 1066, was brought to an end by an alliance between [[Geoffrey Plantagenet, Count of Anjou|Geoffrey of Anjou]] and [[Robert, 1st Earl of Gloucester|Robert of Gloucester]].  Geoffrey and [[Empress Matilda]]'s son [[Henry II of England|Henry]] (great-grandson of [[William the Conqueror]]) became the first of the [[Angevins|Angevin]] kings of England in 1154 as King Henry II.&lt;ref name=bartlett22&gt;Bartlett. England under the Norman and Angevine kings. p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; The King of England, in what is now known as the [[Angevin Empire]], directly ruled more territory on the continent than did the King of France himself. A potential difficulty was that as dukes on the continent, the English kings also owed homage to the King of France, however as the dukes had large amounts of autonomy from the 11th century onwards it was not really a problem in practice.&lt;ref name=bartlett17&gt;Bartlett. England under the Norman and Angevine kings. p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John of England]] inherited the Angevin domains from [[Richard I of England|King Richard I]]. However, [[Philip II of France]] acted decisively to exploit the weaknesses of King John, both legally and militarily, and by 1204 had succeeded in wresting control of most of the ancient continental possessions. The subsequent [[Battle of Bouvines]] (1214), along with the [[Saintonge War]] (1242) and finally the [[War of Saint-Sardos]] (1324), reduced England's holdings on the continent to a few small provinces in Gascony, and the complete loss of Normandy.&lt;ref name=ehistory&gt;Gormley. [http://ehistory.osu.edu/osu/archive/hundredyearswar.cfm?CFID=12106913&amp;CFTOKEN=48989585&amp;jsessionid=463076a37003e50bfe0063343a5d3c64687b The Hundred Years War: Overview] Ohio State University&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dynastic turmoil: 1314–1328===
&lt;!-- This section is linked from Edward III of England --&gt;
{{see also|Absolute cognatic primogeniture|British claims to the French throne}}
When Philip IV died in 1314, his eldest son Louis X inherited the throne. Louis X died in 1316, leaving a daughter ([[Joan II of Navarre]]) and a pregnant wife. The wife produced a son, John I, who died in infancy. Philip IV's second-eldest son, [[Philip V of France|Philip, Count of Poitiers]], sought the throne for himself to the exclusion of his niece (Louis X's daughter). This was opposed by several of the nobility, such as [[Odo IV, Duke of Burgundy]] (Joan II of Navarre's maternal uncle), [[Charles of Valois]] (Philip's uncle) and Charles, Count of La Marche (Philip's brother). However, Philip was able to negotiate them into silence; Philip's uncle and brother may have realized that this would bring them closer to the throne, while the Duke of Burgundy married Philip's eldest daughter, [[Joan III, Countess of Burgundy]]. Up until that time, all [[Fee (feudal tenure)|fiefs]] in France passed by cognatic primogeniture, a  system of inheritance whereby the oldest child inherited irrespective of gender. Philip had to provide justification why the French throne should pass in a different manner. For this, Philip exalted the throne of France to be equal to that of the [[Holy Roman Emperor]] and the [[Papacy]] — an office that could be entrusted to men only.  The principle that a woman could not reign in France was confirmed when Philip himself died leaving only daughters, and the next brother, Charles the Fair (Charles IV), succeeded unchallenged.&lt;ref name=orton872&gt;Previte-Orton. The Shorter Cambridge Medieval History. p. 872&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Favier. La Guerre de Cent Ans. p.37. The concept of [[Salic law]], which completely precluded women from inheriting, would be invoked only much later — in the 1350s — when a Benedictine from the Abbey of St. Denis, who kept the official chronicle of the kingdom, invoked that law to strengthen the position of the King of France in his propaganda fight against Edward III of England.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
{{chart/start}}
{{chart | | AAA | |AAA='''[[Philip III of France]]'''&lt;br&gt;r. 1270-1285}}
{{chart | | |)|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|.| | }}
{{chart | | AAA | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | FFF | |AAA='''[[Philip IV of France]]'''&lt;br&gt;r. 1285-1314|FFF=Charles of Valois&lt;br&gt;d. 1325}}
{{chart | | |)|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|v|-|-|-|.| | | | | | | |!| | }}
{{chart | | AAA | | BBB | | CCC | | DDD |y| EEE | | FFF | |AAA='''[[Louis X of France]]'''&lt;br&gt;r. 1314-1316|BBB='''Philip V of France'''&lt;br&gt;r. 1316-1322|CCC='''Charles IV of France'''&lt;br&gt;r. 1322-1328|DDD=[[Isabella of France]]|EEE=[[Edward II of England]]|FFF='''Philip VI of France'''&lt;br&gt;r. 1328-1350}}
{{chart | | |!| | | |!| | | | | | | | | |!| | | }}
{{chart | | AAA | | BBB | | | | | | | | EEE | | | | | | | |AAA=Joan II of Navarre&lt;br&gt;b. 1312|BBB=Joan III, Countess of Burgundy&lt;br&gt;b. 1308|EEE=Edward III of England&lt;br&gt;b. 1312}}
{{chart | | |!| | | |!| | | }}
{{chart | | AAA | | BBB | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | | |AAA=[[Charles II of Navarre|Charles of Évreux]]&lt;br&gt;b. 1332|BBB=[[Philip II, Count of Auvergne|Philip of Burgundy]]&lt;br&gt;b. 1323}}
{{chart/end}}
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Charles IV died in 1328, also only leaving daughters; the  nearest male in line to the throne was Edward III of England.&lt;ref name=orton872 /&gt; The French nobility, however, balked at the prospect of being ruled by the king of England. Edward had inherited his right through his mother Isabella, the sister of the dead king; but the question arose of whether she should be able to transmit a right that she did not possess.  An assembly of the French aristocracy decided the nearest heir through male ancestry was Charles IV's first cousin, Philip, Count of Valois, and that he should be crowned Philip VI.&lt;ref name=orton872 /&gt;

==Beginning of the war: 1337–1360==
{{Campaignbox Edwardian War}}
{{Main|Hundred Years' War (1337–1360)}}
{{See also|War of the Breton Succession|Auld Alliance|}} 
In the 11th century, Gascony had been incorporated into Aquitaine (''also'' Guyenne or Guienne) and formed with it the province of Guyenne and Gascony (''French:'' Guyenne-et-Gascogne). The English kings became dukes of Aquitaine; after Henry II married [[Eleanor of Aquitaine]] in 1152, the lands were held in vassalage to the French crown. By the 13th century the terms Aquitaine, Guyenne and Gascony were virtually synonymous.&lt;ref name=harris8&gt;Harris. Valois Guyenne. p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=prestwich298&gt;Prestwich. Edward I. p. 298&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of Edward III's reign, the only part of Aquitaine that remained in English hands was the duchy of Gascony.  The term Gascony came to be used for the territory held by the English in south west France, although they still used the title Duke of Aquitaine.&lt;ref name=prestwich298 /&gt;&lt;ref name=prestwich292&gt;Prestwich. Plantagenet England. pp. 292-293&lt;/ref&gt;

For the first 10 years of Edward III's reign,  Gascony had been a major point of friction. The English argued that, as Charles IV had not acted in a proper way towards his tenant holding fealty towards him, then the English should be able to hold the duchy free of any French [[suzerainty]]. However, this line of argument could not be maintained by the English, so in 1329 Edward III paid homage to the new French king, Philip VI. Despite this concession the French continued to put pressure on the English administration in Gascony.&lt;ref name=prestwich304&gt;Prestwich. Plantagenet England. p. 394&lt;/ref&gt;

Gascony was not the only factor behind the Hundred Years' War. One of Edward's influential advisers was [[Robert III of Artois]]. Robert was an exile from the French court, having fallen out with Philip VI over an inheritance claim. He urged Edward to start a war to reclaim the Kingdom of France and was able to provide extensive intelligence on the French court to the English.&lt;ref name=prestwich306&gt;Prestwich. Plantagenet England p. 306&lt;/ref&gt;

The kings of England had been trying to subjugate the Scots for some time. In 1295 there was a treaty between France and Scotland, during the reign of Philip the Fair. Charles IV formally [[Treaty of Corbeil (1326)|renewed the treaty]] in 1326, undertaking that if England invaded Scotland then France would take steps to support Scotland. Similarly the Scots would support the French, in the event that England attacked France.  Thus, Edward could not succeed in his plans for Scotland, while they could count on French support.&lt;ref name=prestwich304&gt;Prestwich. Plantagenet England pp. 304-305&lt;/ref&gt;

Philip VI had assembled a large naval fleet off Marseilles as part of an ambitious plan for a crusade to the Holy Land. However the plan was abandoned, and the fleet including elements of the Scottish navy moved to the [[English Channel]] off Normandy in 1336, threatening England.&lt;ref name=prestwich306&gt;Prestwich. Plantagenet England. p. 306&lt;/ref&gt; To deal with this crisis Edward proposed that the English raise two armies, one to deal with the Scots at a &quot;suitable time&quot;, the other to proceed at once to Gascony. At the same time ambassadors were to be sent to France with a proposed treaty for the French king.&lt;ref name=sumption180&gt;Sumption. The Hundred Years war. p. 180&lt;/ref&gt;

At the end of April 1337 Philip was invited to meet the delegation from England, but refused. The [[arrière-ban]], literally a call to arms, was proclaimed throughout France starting on 30 April 1337.&lt;ref name=sumption184&gt;Sumption. The Hundred Years War. p. 184&lt;/ref&gt; Then, in May 1337, Philip met with his Great Council in Paris.  It was agreed that the duchy of Aquitaine, effectively Gascony, should be taken back into the King's hands on the grounds that Edward III was in breach of his obligations as vassal; also that he had sheltered the Kings 'mortal enemy' Robert d'Artois, and other unspecified reasons.&lt;ref name=sumption184&gt;Sumption. The Hundred Years War.&lt;/ref&gt; Edward responded to the confiscation of Aquitaine by  challenging Philip’s right to the French throne. When Charles VI had died there had been a claim for the succession of the French throne by Edward, through the right of his mother Isabella (Charles IV’s sister), daughter of Philip IV. Any claim was seen to be invalidated by Edward's homage to Philip VI in 1329. However Edward now revived his claim, and in 1340 formally assumed the title 'King of France and the French Royal Arms'.&lt;ref name=prestwich307&gt;Prestwich. Plantagenet England. pp. 307-312&lt;/ref&gt; On 26 January 1340, Edward III formally received homage from Guy, the half brother of the Count of [[County of Flanders|Flanders]]. The civic authorities of Ghent, Ypres and Bruges proclaimed Edward as King of France. Edward's purpose was to strengthen his alliances with the Low Countries. His supporters would be able to claim that they were loyal to the &quot;true&quot; king of France and not rebels against Philip.&lt;ref name=prestwich307 /&gt; In February 1340, Edward returned to England to try and raise more funds and also deal with political difficulties.&lt;ref name=prestwich307 /&gt;
[[File:BattleofSluys.jpeg|thumb|left|Battle of Sluys from a [[Froissart of Louis of Gruuthuse (BnF Fr 2643-6)|manuscript]] of [[Froissart's Chronicles]], Bruge, c.1470]]

Edward III had commanded that his [[Lord Chancellor|Chancellor]] should sit on the [[woolsack]] in council as a symbol of the pre-eminence of the wool trade.&lt;ref name=&quot;friar480&quot;&gt;Friar. The Sutton Companion to local history. pp. 480-481&lt;/ref&gt; At the time there was about 110,000 sheep in [[History of Sussex#wool|Sussex]] alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;darby160&quot;&gt;Darby. A new historical geography of England before 1600. p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; The great medieval English monasteries produced large surpluses of wool, which were sold to Europe, and successive governments were able to make large amounts of money from taxation of the trade.&lt;ref name=&quot;friar480&quot;/&gt; France's sea power led to economic disruptions, with England having to cut down on the wool trade to Flanders and the wine trade from Gascony. Edward, with his fleet, sailed from England on 22 June 1340 and arrived, the next day, off the Zwyn estuary. The French fleet could be seen in a defensive formation off the port of Sluys. The English fleet apparently tricked the French into believing they were withdrawing. However, when the wind turned in the late afternoon, the English fleet attacked with the wind and sun behind them. The French fleet was almost completely destroyed in what became known as the [[Battle of Sluys]].&lt;ref name=prestwich307 /&gt; After this, England was able to dominate the English Channel for the rest of the war, preventing French [[invasions]].&lt;ref name=prestwich307 /&gt; At this point, Edward's funds ran out and the war probably would have come to an end, were it not for the death of the [[John III, Duke of Brittany|Duke of Brittany]] precipitating a succession dispute between the Duke's half brother [[John IV, Duke of Brittany|John of Montfort]] and [[Charles I, Duke of Brittany|Charles of Blois]], nephew of Philip VI.&lt;ref name=rogers88&gt;Rogers. The Oxford Encyclopedia of Medieval Warfare. pp. 88-89&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Crécy jean froissard.jpg|thumb|200px|Battle of Crécy, 1346]]
In 1341, conflict over the succession to the Duchy of Brittany began the Breton War of Succession, in which Edward backed John of Montfort, and Philip backed Charles of Blois. Action for the next few years focussed around a back and forth struggle in Brittany, with the city of [[Vannes]] changing hands several times, as well as further campaigns in Gascony with mixed success for both sides.&lt;ref name=rogers88 /&gt; 

In July 1346, Edward mounted a major invasion across the Channel, landing in the [[Cotentin]]. The English army captured [[Caen]] in just one day, surprising the French who had expected the city to hold out much longer. Philip gathered a large army to oppose Edward, who chose to march northward toward the Low Countries, pillaging as he went, rather than attempting to take and hold territory. Finding himself unable to outmanoeuvre Philip, Edward positioned his forces for battle, and Philip's army attacked. The Battle of Crécy was a complete disaster for the French, largely credited to the [[English longbow]]men and the French king, who allowed his army to attack before they were ready.&lt;ref name=prestwich318&gt;Prestwich. Plantagenet England. pp. 318-319&lt;/ref&gt; Philip  appealed to his Scottish allies to help with a diversionary attack on England.  King [[David II of Scotland]] responded by invading northern England, but he was captured and his army defeated at the [[Battle of Neville's Cross]], on 17 October 1346.  This greatly reduced the threat from Scotland.&lt;ref name=rogers88 /&gt;&lt;ref name=rogers55&gt;Rogers. The Oxford Encyclopedia of Medieval Warfare. pp. 55-45&lt;/ref&gt; In France, Edward was able to proceed north unopposed and besieged the city of [[Calais]] on the English Channel, capturing it in 1347. This became an important strategic asset for the English. It allowed them to keep troops in France safely.&lt;ref name=prestwich318 /&gt; Calais would remain under English control until the successful French siege in 1558.&lt;ref name=grummitt1&gt;Grummitt.The Calais Garrison. p. 1&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1348, the [[Black Death]] began to ravage Europe.&lt;ref name=birsall3&gt;Birdsall. The Chronicles of Jean de Venette. Introduction pp. 3-5.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1356, after it had passed and England was able to recover financially, Edward's son and namesake, the [[Prince of Wales]], known as the [[Edward, the Black Prince|Black Prince]], invaded France from Gascony, winning a great victory in the [[Battle of Poitiers (1356)|Battle of Poitiers]].&lt;ref name=rogers88 /&gt; John II of France (known as John the Good) was captured on the field of battle and eventually taken to England. In his absence John's son the [[Dauphin of France|Dauphin]] (later to become [[Charles V of France]]) took over as [[Regency (government)|regent]].&lt;ref name=guignebert304&gt;Guignebert. A Short History of the French People. Vol 1. pp.304-307&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Edward III counting the dead on the battlefield of Crécy.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Edward III]] counting the dead on the battlefield of Crécy]]
After the Battle of Poiters, chaos ruled in town and country, many of the French nobles and mercenaries went on the rampage. A contemporary report said:
&lt;blockquote&gt; 
&quot;... all went ill with the kingdom and the State was undone. Thieves and robbers rose up everywhere in the land. The Nobles despised and hated all others and took no thought for usefulness and profit of lord and men. They subjected and despoiled the peasants and the men of the villages. In no wise did they defend their country from its enemies; rather did they trample it underfoot, robbing and pillaging the peasants' goods...&quot;  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;From the Chronicles of Jean de Venette&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=birsall66&gt;Birdsall. The Chronicles of Jean de Venette. p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Then, in 1358, according to the French medieval chronicler [[Jean Froissart]], as there was no leadership in the countryside, people revolted against the French nobility, who they accused of shaming the realm. The revolt became known as the [[Jacquerie]].&lt;ref name=froissartclxxxii&gt;Froissart. The Chronicles of Froissart. Chap. CLXXXII pp. 136-137&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=birdsall1347&gt;Birdsall. The Chronicles of Jean de Venette. Chapters. 1347-1356&lt;/ref&gt; 

Edward invaded France, for the third and last time, hoping to capitalise on the discontent and seize the throne. The Dauphin's strategy was that of non-engagement with the English army in the field. However Edward wanted to be crowned King of France, and chose the cathedral city of Reims as the place of his coronation (Reims being traditionally where the Kings of France were crowned).&lt;ref name=prestwich326&gt;Prestwich. Plantagenet England. p. 326&lt;/ref&gt; However, the citizens of Reims were able to build and reinforce the defences of the city before Edward and his army arrived.&lt;ref  name=patourel189&gt;Le Patourel.  Feudal Empires. p. 189&lt;/ref&gt; Edward besieged the city for five weeks, the defences held out and there was no coronation.&lt;ref name=prestwich326 /&gt; Edward moved on to Paris, but retreated after a few skirmishes in the suburbs. The French made contact with him and forced him to negotiate.&lt;ref  name=patourel32&gt;Le Patourel.  Feudal Empires. p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; Edward III, of England and John II, of France, negotiated the [[Treaty of Brétigny]] which was signed in 1360. The treaty gave Edward enlarged sovereignty  over Aquitaine, in return for abandoning his claim to the throne of France.&lt;ref  name=patourel20&gt;Le Patourel.  Feudal Empires. p. 20&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=wsbretigny&gt;{{ws|[[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Brétigny]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==First peace: 1360–1369==
{{Main|Treaty of Brétigny}}
John II had been held captive in England, the Treaty of Brétigny set his ransom at 3&amp;nbsp;million&amp;nbsp;crowns. John's son [[Louis I of Anjou|Louis of Anjou]] stood in as a replacement hostage at English held Calais, while John returned to France to try and raise funds to pay off the ransom. When  Louis escaped in 1362 John gave himself up and returned to captivity in England.&lt;ref name=&quot;guignebert304&quot;/&gt;

The French crown had been at odds with Navarre since 1354 and in 1363 the Navaresse used John II's captivity in London and the political weakness of the dauphine to try and seize power.&lt;ref name=wagner102&gt;Wagner. Encyclopedia of the Hundred Years War. pp. 102-103&lt;/ref&gt; Although there was no formal treaty in place, Edward III supported the Navaresse moves particularly as there was a prospect that he might get control over the northern and western provinces as a consequence. With this in mind Edward deliberately slowed the peace negotiations.&lt;ref name=Ormrod&gt;Ormrod. Edward III. p. 384&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1364 John II died in London, while still in honorable captivity. Charles V succeeded him as king of France.&lt;ref name=guignebert304 /&gt;&lt;ref name=britannica1&gt;Britannica. [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/78946/Treaty-of-Bretigny Treaty of Brétigny]. Retrieved 21 September 2012&lt;/ref&gt; On 6 May 1364, one month after the dauphine's accession and three days before his coronation as Charles V, the Navaresse suffered a crushing defeat at the [[Battle of Cocherel]].&lt;ref name=wagner86&gt;Wagner. Encyclopedia of the Hundred Years War. p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Treaty of Brétigny had made Edward renounce his claim to the French crown. At the same time, it greatly expanded his territory in Aquitaine and confirmed his conquest of Calais. The ratified version, the Treaty of Calais, had one small difference: the exchange of renunciations would happen ''after'' the territorial exchanges, not immediately, as had been stated in the Treaty of Brétigny.&lt;ref name=guignebert304 /&gt;

==French ascendancy under Charles V: 1369–1389==
{{Campaignbox Caroline War}}
{{Main|Hundred Years' War (1369–1389)}}
{{See also|Castilian Civil War}}
[[File:Du Guesclin Dinan.jpg|thumb|Statue of Du Guesclin in [[Dinan]]]]
In 1366 there was a civil war of succession  in [[Crown of Castile#Ascension of the Trastámara dynasty|Castile]] the  ruler, [[Peter of Castile]]'s forces, was pitched against those of  his half brother [[Henry II of Castile|Henry of Trastámara]]. The English crown supported Peter and the French Henry.  The French forces were led by [[Bertrand du Guesclin]], a Breton, who rose from relatively humble beginnings to prominence as one of France's war leaders. Charles V provided a force of 12,000, with du Guesclin at their head, to support Trastámara in his invasion of Castile.&lt;ref name=curry69&gt;Curry. The Hundred Years War. pp. 69-70&lt;/ref&gt;
Peter appealed to the Black Prince, for help, but none was forthcoming so Peter had to escape to exile in Aquitaine. The  Black Prince had previously agreed that he would support Peter's claims but being concerned about the terms of the treaty of Brétigny he assisted Peter as a representative of  Aquitaine, not England and led an Anglo-Gascon army into Castille. Peter was restored to power after Henry du Trastámara's army was defeated at the [[Battle of Najera]].&lt;ref name=wagner78&gt;Wagner. Encyclopedia of the Hundred Years War. p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the Castilians had agreed to fund the Black Prince for his help, none was forthcoming, the prince was also was suffering from ill health so returned with his army to Aquitaine. Then to pay off the debts  incurred during the campaign in Castille,  the prince instituted a [[hearth tax]] in Aquitaine. Arnaud-Amaniieu VIII, lord of [[Albret]] had fought on the Black Prince's side during the war.  Albret, who already had become discontented by the influx of English administrators into the enlarged Aquitaine,  refused to allow the tax to be collected in his lordship. He then joined a group of Gascon lords  who appealed to Charles V for support in their refusal to pay the tax. Charles V summoned one Gascon lord and also the Black Prince to hear the case in his ''Parlement'' in Paris. The Black Prince's answer was that he would go to Paris with sixty thousand men behind him. War broke out again, and Edward III resumed the title of King of France.&lt;ref name=wagner122&gt;Wagner. Encyclopedia of the Hundred Years War. p. 122&lt;/ref&gt; 
Charles V declared that all the English possessions in France were forfeited, and before the end of 1369 all Aquitaine was in full revolt.&lt;ref name=wagner122 /&gt;
&lt;ref name=wagner3&gt;Wagner. Encyclopedia of the Hundred Years War. pp. 3-4&lt;/ref&gt;

With the Black Prince gone from Castille, Henry du Trastámara led a second invasion  that ended with Peter's death at the [[Battle of Montiel]] in March 1369. The new Castilian regime then went on to provide naval support to French campaigns against Aquitaine and England.&lt;ref name=wagner78 /&gt;

With his health continuing to deteriorate the Black Prince returned home to England in January 1371, where by now his father Edward III was elderly and also in poor health. The prince's illness was debilitating and limited what he could do. He died on the 8 June 1376.&lt;ref name=dnbbarber&gt;{{Cite web|last=Barber|first=Richard|title= Edward , prince of Wales and of Aquitaine (1330–1376)'' in '' Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn. Subscription Required|year=2008|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/8523|accessdate= 3 Oct 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Edward III only just outlived his son and died the following year 21 June 1377;&lt;ref name=dnbomrod&gt;{{Cite web|last=Omrod|first=W. M|title=Edward III (1312–1377)'' in '' Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn. Subscription Required|year=2008|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/8519 |accessdate= 3 Oct 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; he was succeeded by the Black Prince's second son [[Richard II of England|Richard II]] who was still a child.&lt;ref name=dnbtuck&gt;{{Cite web|last=Tuck|first=Richard|title=Richard II (1367–1400'' in '' Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn. Subscription Required|year=2008|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/23499 |accessdate= 3 Oct 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The treaty at Brétigny had seen Edward III and England with enlarged holdings in France, however a small professional French army under the leadership of du Guesclin pushed the English back and by the time of Charles V's death in 1380, the English only held Calais.&lt;ref name=vauchez283&gt;Francoise Autrand. Charles V King of France ''in'' Vauchéz. Encyclopedia of the Middle Ages. Volume 1. pp. 283-284&lt;/ref&gt;

It was usual to appoint a [[regent]] in the case of a child monarch, but no regent was appointed for Richard II who nominally exercised all the power of kingship from the date of his accession in 1377.&lt;ref name=dnbtuck /&gt; However, between 1377 and 1380  Richard's government was in the hands of a series of councils. The political community preferred this to a regency led by the king's uncle, [[John of Gaunt, 1st Duke of Lancaster|John of Gaunt]], yet Gaunt remained highly influential.&lt;ref name=dnbtuck /&gt; 

Richard had to face many challenges during his reign including the [[Peasants' Revolt]] led by [[Wat Tyler]] in 1381, an Anglo-Scottish war in 1384-1385, then  a group of noblemen known as the [[Lords Appellant]] took over government between 1387 and 1389. His attempts to raise taxes to pay for his Scottish adventure and also the cost for the protection of Calais against the French made him increasingly unpopular.&lt;ref name=dnbtuck /&gt;

==Second peace: 1389–1415==
{{See also|Civil war between the Armagnacs and the Burgundians}}

In 1399, after John of Gaunt died,  Richard II disinherited Gaunt's son, [[Henry IV of England|Henry of Bolingbroke]], who had previously been exiled. Bolingbroke returned to England in June 1399 and with his supporters managed to depose Richard; he then had himself crowned Henry IV.&lt;ref name=dnbtuck /&gt; One of the causes of Richard's unpopularity had been his reluctance to continue the war in France. Henry was aware of this, and planned to resume hostilities. However this did not happen, as he was plagued with financial problems, declining health and was kept busy putting down rebellions.&lt;ref name=mortimer353&gt;Mortimer. The Fears of Henry IV. p. 353&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=curry77&gt;Curry. The Hundred Year War. pp. 77-82&lt;/ref&gt;

In Scotland, the change in regime in England prompted a fresh series of border raids which were countered by an invasion in 1402 and the defeat of a Scottish army at the [[Battle of Homildon Hill]].&lt;ref name=mortimer253&gt;Mortimer. The Fears of Henry IV. pp. 253-254&lt;/ref&gt; A dispute over the spoils of this action between Henry and  [[Henry Percy, 1st Earl of Northumberland]] resulted in a long and bloody struggle between the two for control of northern England, which was resolved only with the almost complete destruction of the [[House of Percy|Percy family]] by 1408.&lt;ref name=mortimer263&gt;Mortimer. The Fears of Henry IV. pp. 263-264&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dnbbean&gt;{{Cite web|last=Bean|first=J.M.W|title= Percy, Henry, first earl of Northumberland (1341–1408)'' in '' Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn. Subscription Required|year=2008|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/index/21/101021932|accessdate= 8 Oct 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In Wales, [[Owain Glyndŵr]] was declared prince of Wales on 16 September 1400, he was acknowledged as the leader of the most serious and widespread rebellion against English authority in Wales since the conquest of 1282–3. The rebellion was not finally put down until 1415 and actually resulted in Welsh semi-independence for a number of years.&lt;ref name=dnbsmith&gt;{{Cite web|last=Smith|first=Llinos|title= Glyn Dŵr , Owain (c.1359–c.1416)'' in '' Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn. Subscription Required|year=2008|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/index/10/101010816|accessdate=8 Oct 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

In the meantime [[Charles VI of France]] was descending into madness, and an open conflict for power began between his cousin [[John the Fearless]], and his brother, [[Louis of Valois, Duke of Orléans|Louis of Orléans]]. After Louis's assassination, the [[Armagnac (party)|Armagnac]] family took political power in opposition to John. By 1410, both sides were bidding for the help of English forces in a civil war.&lt;ref name=curry77 /&gt;

Throughout this period, England was also faced with repeated raids by [[pirates]], which heavily damaged trade and the navy. There is some evidence that Henry IV used state-legalised piracy as a form of warfare in the English channel. He used these privateering campaigns to put pressure on enemies without the risk of open war.&lt;ref name=hattendorf76&gt;Ian Friel. The English and War at Sea. c.1200-c1500 ''in'' Hattendorf. War at Sea. pp. 76-77&lt;/ref&gt; The French responded in kind and French pirates operating under Scottish protection, raided many English coastal towns.&lt;ref name=nolan424&gt;Nolan. The Age of Wars of Religion. p. 424&lt;/ref&gt;

The domestic and dynastic difficulties faced by  England and France in this period quieted the war for a decade.&lt;ref name=nolan424 /&gt;

Henry IV of England died in 1413 and was replaced by his eldest son Henry V. Because of Charles VI of France's mental illness, his power was exercised by royal princes whose rivalries continued to cause deep divisions in France. Henry V was well aware of these divisions and hoped to exploit them.  In 1414 while he held court at Leicester, he received ambassadors from Burgandy.&lt;ref name=dnballmand&gt;{{Cite web|last=Allmand|first=C.T|title= Henry V (1386-1422)'' in '' Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn. Subscription Required|year=2008|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/index/12/101012952|accessdate= 8 Oct 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Henry accredited envoys to visit the French king and make clear his territorial claims in France; he also demanded the hand of Charles VI's youngest daughter [[Catherine of Valois]]. These demands not being met by the French Henry prepared for war.&lt;ref name=dnballmand /&gt;

==Resumption of the war under Henry V: 1415–1429==
{{Campaignbox Lancastrian War}}
{{Main|Hundred Years' War (1415–1453)}}
In August 1415 Henry V sailed from England and landed with a force of about 10,500 fighting men and laid siege to [[Harfleur]],  the city resisted for longer than expected, but finally surrendered on 22 September 1415. Because of the unexpected delay most of the campaign season was gone. So rather than march on Paris directly, he elected to make a raiding expedition across France toward English-occupied Calais. In a campaign reminiscent of [[Crécy]], he found himself outmanoeuvred and low on supplies, and had to make a stand against a much larger French army at the Battle of Agincourt, north of the [[Somme]]. Despite the problems and having a smaller force, his victory was near-total; the French defeat was catastrophic, with the loss of many of the Armagnac leaders. About 40% of the French nobility was lost at Agincourt.&lt;ref name=&quot;population&quot;/&gt; Henry apparently concerned that so many prisoners were a security risk, as there were more French prisoners than the entire English army, he ordered their killing.&lt;ref name=dnballmand /&gt;[[File:Agincourt miniature.JPG|thumb|left|Fifteenth-century miniature depicting the Battle of Agincourt]]

Henry retook much of Normandy, including Caen in 1417 and [[Rouen]] on January 19, 1419, making Normandy English for the first time in two centuries. A formal alliance was made with the Duchy of Burgundy, who had taken Paris, after the assassination of Duke John the Fearless in 1419. In 1420, Henry met with king Charles VI, they signed the [[Treaty of Troyes]], by which Henry finally would get to marry Charles' daughter Catherine of Valois and Henry's heirs would inherit the throne of France. The Dauphin, [[Charles VII of France|Charles VII]], was declared illegitimate. Henry formally entered Paris later that year and the agreement was ratified by the [[French States-General|Estates-General]].&lt;ref name=dnballmand /&gt;

On 22 March 1421 Henry V's progress, in his French campaign, experienced an unexpected reverse. Henry had left his brother and heir presumptive Thomas, duke of Clarence in charge while he returned to England. Clarence engaged a Franco-Scottish force led by [[John Stewart, Earl of Buchan]] at the [[battle of Baugé]]. It seem that Clarence  attacked before his army were fully assembled. He was killed and the English defeated in the ensuing battle.&lt;ref name=dnballmand /&gt;&lt;ref name=wagner44&gt;Wagner. Encyclopedia of the hundred Years War. p.44&lt;/ref&gt;

Henry returned to France and landed at Calais on 10 June 1421. From Calais he went onto Paris then visiting Chartres and Gâtinais before returning to Paris. From there he decided to attack the dauphin held town of [[Meaux]]. It turned out to be more difficult to overcome than first thought, the siege began about 6 October 1421 and the town held on for seven months before finally falling on  11 May 1422.&lt;ref name=dnballmand /&gt; 

At the end of May Henry was joined by his queen  and together with the French court, they went to rest at Senlis. While there it became apparent that he was ill(possibly dysentery) and when he set out to the Upper Loire it was evident that he would not be able to make it so was diverted to the royal castle at Vincennes, near Paris where he died  31 August 1422.&lt;ref name=dnballmand /&gt; The elderly and insane Charles VI of France died, two months later, on 21 October 1422.&lt;ref name=dnbgriffiths /&gt;  Henry left an only child, his nine month old son, [[Henry VI of England|Henry]], later to become Henry VI.&lt;ref name=dnbgriffiths /&gt;

On his deathbed, Henry V had given the duke of Bedford the responsibility of English France (as Henry VI was only an infant). So the war in France continued under Bedford's generalship, and several battles were won. The English won a decisive victory at the [[Battle of Verneuil]], (17 August 1424). At the battle of Baugé Clarence had rushed into  battle without the support of the English archers. At Verneuil the archers were used to devastating effect against the Franco-Scottish army. The effect of the battle was to virtually destroy the dauphin's field army and to eliminate the Scots as a significant military force for the rest of the war.&lt;ref name=dnbgriffiths /&gt;&lt;ref name=wagner307&gt;Wagner. Encyclopedia of the Hundred Years War. pp. 307-308&lt;/ref&gt; 

Joan of Arc's appearance sparked a revival of French spirits and the tide began to turn  against the English.&lt;ref name=dnbgriffiths /&gt;

In 1428, the English laid [[siege]] to Orléans. Their force was insufficient to fully [[investment (military)|invest]] the city.  Then in 1429, Joan of Arc convinced the Dauphin to send her to the siege, saying she had received visions from [[God]] telling her to drive out the English. She raised the morale of the local troops and they attacked the English [[Redoubt]]s, forcing the English to lift the siege. Inspired by Joan, the French took several English strong points on the Loire.&lt;ref name=davis76&gt;Davis. Besieged: 100 Great Sieges from Jericho to Sarajevo. pp. 76-80&lt;/ref&gt; 

Shortly afterwards, a French army  broke through the English archers at [[Battle of Patay|Patay]] defeating an  army commanded by John Fastolf and [[John Talbot, 1st Earl of Shrewsbury]]. This victory opened the way for the Dauphin to march to [[Reims]] for his coronation as Charles VII (16 July 1429).&lt;ref name=davis76 /&gt;

Joan changed the way that the French forces engaged with the English in battle. Her tactics were not to engage prepared English lines, with a full frontal assault, as had been the traditional way.&lt;ref name=davis76 /&gt;

==French victory: 1429–1453==
[[File:Hundred years war.gif|thumb|300px|Hundred Years' War evolution. French territory: yellow; English: grey; Burgundian: dark grey.]]
Henry VI was eventually crowned king of England, at Westminster Abbey on 5 November 1429 and king of France at Notre-Dame, in Paris, on 16 December 1431.&lt;ref name=dnbgriffiths &gt;{{Cite web|last=Griffiths|first=R.A|title=Henry VI (1421–1471) ''in'' Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, 2004; online edn, Sept 2010; Subscription required|publisher= Oxford University Press|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/index/12/101012953/|accessdate=9 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Siege orleans.jpg|thumb|210px|left|The first Western image of a battle with cannon: the [[Siege of Orleans]] in 1429.]]
Joan was captured by the Burgundians in 1430, Charles refused to pay her ransom so she was sold to the English, they tried her as a witch, Joan was found guilty and executed by being burned at the stake on 30 May 1431.&lt;ref name=davis76 /&gt;

After Joan of Arc's death the fortunes of war turned remorselessly against the English.&lt;ref name=lee145&gt;Lee. This Sceptred Isle. pp. 145-147&lt;/ref&gt;
Most of Henry's royal advisers were against making peace with the French.&lt;ref name=dnbgriffiths /&gt; There were different factions, the duke of  Bedford wanted to defend Normandy, the duke of Gloucester was committed to just Calais whereas Cardinal Beaufort was inclined to peace. Negotiations were stalled. It seems that at the congress of [[Treaty of Arras (1435)|Arras]], in the summer of 1435, where the duke of Beaufort was mediator, the English were unrealistic in their demands.  A few days after the congress ended in September, Philip III, duke of Burgundy deserted to Charles VII, signing the Treaty of Arras that returned Paris to the King of France. This was a major blow to English sovereignty in France.&lt;ref name=dnbgriffiths /&gt; Then the duke of Bedford died 14 September 1435 and was replaced by a lesser man.&lt;ref name=lee145 /&gt;

Burgundy's allegiance remained fickle, but their focus on expanding their domains into the Low Countries left them little energy to intervene in France.&lt;ref name=sumption562&gt;Sumption. Hundred Years War. p.562&lt;/ref&gt;  The long truces that marked the war also gave Charles time to reorganise his army and government, replacing his feudal levies with a more modern professional army that could put its superior numbers to good use, and centralising the French state. A castle that once could only be captured after a prolonged siege would now fall after a few days from bombardment by cannons with the French artillery having the reputation as the best in the world.&lt;ref name=lee145 /&gt;

By 1449, the French had retaken Rouen, and in 1450 the [[Count of Clermont]] and Arthur de Richemont, Earl of Richmond, of the Montfort family (the future [[Arthur III, Duke of Brittany]]) caught an English army attempting to relieve Caen at the [[Battle of Formigny]] and defeated it, the English army having been attacked from the flank and rear by Richemont's force just as they were on the verge of beating Clermont's army.&lt;ref name=nicole26&gt;Nicole. The Fall of English France 1449-53. pp.26-35&lt;/ref&gt; 

After Charles VII's successful campaign in retaking Normandy in 1450, he concentrated his efforts on Gascony the last province held by the English. Bordeaux, the capital of Gascony, was besieged and surrendered to the French on 30 June 1451. Largely due to the English sympathies of the Gascon people this was reversed  when John Talbot, earl of Shrewsbury and his army retook the city on 23 October 1452. However, the English were defeated at the [[Battle of Castillon]]  17 July 1453. Talbot had been  persuaded to engage the French army at Castillon near to Bordeaux.  During the  battle the French appeared to retreat towards their camp.  The French camp at Castillon had been laid out by  Charles VII's ordinance officer [[Jean Bureau]] and this was instrumental in the French success as when the French cannon opened fire, from their positions in the camp, the English took severe casualties including the death of both Talbot and his son.&lt;ref name=wagner79&gt;Wagner. Encyclopedia of the Hundred Years War. p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; 

After three hundred years, English rule in Gascony was over as was the hundred year war. The Battle of Castillon is considered the last battle of the Hundred Years' War.&lt;ref name=wagner79 /&gt;  The English were in no position to carry on the war as they faced several years of unrest at home, culminating in a civil war known as the Wars of the Roses that started in 1455.&lt;ref name=lee145 /&gt;

==Significance==
[[File:Vigiles du roi Charles VII 32.jpg|thumb|right|The Battle of Formigny (1450)]]
The Hundred Years' War was a time of military evolution. Weapons, tactics, army structure, and the societal meaning of war all changed, partly in response to the demands of the war, partly through advancement in technology, and partly through lessons that [[warfare]] taught.

Before the Hundred Years' War, heavy cavalry was considered the most powerful unit in an army, but by the war's end, this belief had shifted. The heavy horse was increasingly negated by the use of the longbow (and, later, another long-distance weapon: firearms) and fixed defensive positions of men-at-arms — tactics which helped lead to English victories at Crécy and Agincourt. Learning from the Scots, the English began using lightly armoured mounted troops — later called [[dragoons]] — who would dismount in order to fight battles. By the end of the Hundred Years' War, this meant a fading of the expensively outfitted, highly trained heavy cavalry, and the eventual end of the armoured [[knight]] as a military force and the [[nobility]] as a political one.&lt;ref name=&quot;RolandPreston1991&quot;&gt;Preston. Men in arms: a history of warfare and its interrelationships with Western society. p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;

The war also stimulated nationalistic sentiment. It devastated France as a land, but it also awakened French nationalism. The Hundred Years' War accelerated the process of transforming France from a feudal monarchy to a centralized state. The conflict became one of not just English and French kings but one between the [[English people|English]] and [[French people|French]] peoples. There were constant rumours in England that the French meant to invade and destroy the English language. National feeling that emerged out of such rumours unified both France and England further. The Hundred Years War basically confirmed the fall of the [[French language]] in England, which had served as the language of the ruling classes and commerce there from the time of the Norman conquest until 1362.&lt;ref name=holmes61&gt;Holmes. History of the French Language. p. 61&lt;/ref&gt;

==Timeline==
&lt;center&gt;[[File:TimeLine100YearsWar (cropped).png|600px]]&lt;/center&gt;
{{clear}}

===Battles===
{{further|List of Hundred Years' War battles}}

==Important figures==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+England
|King Edward III
|1327–1377
|Edward II's son
|-
|King Richard II
|1377–1399
|Edward III's grandson
|-
|King Henry IV
|1399–1413
|Edward III's grandson
|-
|King Henry V
|1413–1422
|Henry IV's son
|-
|King Henry VI
|1422–1461
|Henry V's son
|-
|Edward, the Black Prince
|1330–1376
|Edward III's son
|-
|John of Gaunt, 1st Duke of Lancaster
|1340–1399
|Edward III's son
|-
|[[John of Lancaster, 1st Duke of Bedford]]
|1389–1435
|Henry IV's son
|-
|[[Henry of Grosmont, 1st Duke of Lancaster]]
|1306–1361
|Knight
|-
|John Talbot, 1st Earl of Shrewsbury
|1384–1453
|Knight
|-
|[[Richard Plantagenet, 3rd Duke of York]]
|1411–1460
|Knight
|-
|[[Sir John Fastolf]]
|1378?–1459
|Knight
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ France
|King Philip VI
|1328–1350
|
|-
|[[John II of France|King John II]]
|1350–1364
|Philip VI's son
|-
|King Charles V
|1364–1380
|John II's son
|-
|Louis I of Anjou
|1380–1382
|John II's son
|-
|King Charles VI
|1380–1422
|Charles V's son
|-
|King Charles VII
|1422–1461
|Charles VI's son
|-
|Joan of Arc
|1412–1431
|Commander
|-
|[[Jean de Dunois]]
|1403–1468
|Knight
|-
|[[Gilles de Rais]]
|1404–1440
|Knight
|-
|Bertrand du Guesclin
|1320–1380
|Knight
|-
|Jean Bureau
|13??–1463
|Knight
|-
|[[La Hire]]
|1390–1443
|Knight
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Burgundy
|[[Philip the Bold, Duke of Burgundy]]
|1363–1404
|Son of John II of France
|-
|[[John the Fearless, Duke of Burgundy]]
|1404–1419
|Son of Philip the Bold
|-
|[[Philip the Good, Duke of Burgundy]]
|1419–1467
|Son of John the Fearless
|}

==Memory and impact==
[[File:Bubonic plague map.PNG|thumb|The spread of the Black Death (with modern borders).]]
Lowe (1997) argues that opposition to the war helped to shape England's early modern political culture. Although anti-war and pro-peace spokesmen generally failed to influence outcomes at the time, they had a long-term impact. England showed decreasing enthusiasm for a conflict deemed not in the national interest, yielding only losses in return for the economic burdens it imposed. In comparing this English cost-benefit analysis with French attitudes, given that both countries suffered from weak leaders and undisciplined soldiers, Lowe notes that the French understood that warfare was necessary to expel the foreigners occupying their homeland. Furthermore French kings found alternative ways to finance the war - sales taxes, debasing the coinage - and were less dependent than the English on tax levies passed by national legislatures. English anti-war critics thus had more to work with than the French.&lt;ref&gt;Lowe. Imagining Peace: A History of Early English Pacifist Ideas, 1340-1560&lt;/ref&gt;

Bubonic [[Plague (disease)|Plague]] and warfare depleted the overall population of Europe in the 14th and 15th centuries. France, for example, had a population of about 17 million, which by the end of the Hundred Years War had declined by about one-half.&lt;ref name=&quot;population&quot;&gt;Turchin.[http://books.google.com/books?id=mUoCrTUo-eEC&amp;pg=PA179&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Historical dynamics: why states rise and fall]. pp.179–180&lt;/ref&gt; Some regions were affected much more than others. [[Normandy]] lost three-quarters of its population during the war. In the Paris region, the population between 1328 and 1470 was reduced by at least two-thirds.&lt;ref&gt;Ladurie.[http://books.google.com/books?id=VT9rIMQFt2MC&amp;pg=PA32&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The French peasantry, 1450-1660]. p.32&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Timeline of the Hundred Years' War]]
* [[French military history]]
* [[British military history]]
* [[Anglo-French relations]]
* [[Medieval demography]]
* [[Second Hundred Years' War]]- this is the name given by some historians to the near-continuous series of conflicts between Britain and France from 1688–1815, beginning with the [[Glorious Revolution]] and ending with the [[Battle of Waterloo]].

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==	
* {{Cite book|last=Bartlett|first=Robert|title=England Under the Norman and Angevin Kings 1075 -1225|year=2000|editor=J.M.Roberts|publisher=OUP|location=London|isbn=978-0-19-925101-8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Curry|first=Anne|title=The Hundred Years War 1337-1453|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford|year=2002|isbn=1-84176-269-5}}
* {{Cite book|last=Darby|first=H. C.|title=The British islands and their vegetation|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1976 New edition|location=Cambridge, England|isbn= 0-521-29144-5}}
*{{Cite book|last=Davis|first=Paul K|title=Besieged: 100 Great Sieges from Jericho to Sarajevo 2nd. Ed|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Santa Barbara CA|isbn=0-19-521930-9|year=2003}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com|title=Encyclopædia Britannica Online|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica|accessdate=21 September 2012}}
* {{Cite book|last= Favier|first= Jean|title=La Guerre de Cent Ans|publisher= Fayard|year= 1980|isbn=978-2-213-00898-1|location=Paris}}
* {{Cite book|last=Friar|first=Stephen|title=The Sutton Companion to Local History|publisher=Sutton|year=2004|location=Sparkford, England|isbn=0-7509-2723-2}}
* {{Cite book|last=Froissart|first=Jean|editor=Macaulay; George Campbell|coauthor=John Bourchier Tr.; Lord Berners Tr.|title=The Chronicles of Froissart|publisher=Macmillan and Son|location=London|year=1895|url=http://archive.org/stream/chroniclesfrois00macagoog#page/n176/mode/2up|accessdate=24 September 2012}}
* {{cite web|last=Gormley|first=Larry|url=http://ehistory.osu.edu/osu/archive/hundredyearswar.cfm?CFID=12106913&amp;CFTOKEN=48989585&amp;jsessionid=463076a37003e50bfe0063343a5d3c64687b|title=eHistory:The Hundred Years War: Overview|publisher=Ohio State University|year=2007|accessdate=20 September 2012}}
* {{Cite book|last=Grummitt|first=David|title=The Calais Garrison: War and Military Service in England, 1436-1558|publisher=The Boydell Press|location=Woodbridge|year=2008|isbn=978-1-84383-398-7}}
* {{Cite book|first=Charles|last=Guignebert|title= A Short History of the French People. Vol 1.|coauthor=F. G. Richmond Tr.| publisher=Macmilan Company|location =New York|year=1930|url= http://www.questia.com/read/98573239}}
* {{Cite book|last=Harris|first=Robin|title=Studies in History 71: Valois Guyenne|publisher=Boydell Press|location=Woodbridge, Surrey|year=1994|isbn=0-86193-226-9}}
* {{Cite encyclopedia|editor1-last=Hattendorf|editor1-first=John B|editor2-last=Unger|editor2-first=Richard W|title=War at Sea in the Middle Ages and the Renaissance|publisher=The Boydell Press|location=Woodbridge|year=2003|isbn=0-85115-903-6}}
* {{Cite book|first1=Urban T|last1=Holmes, Jr|first2= Alexander H|last2= Schutz|title= A History of the French Language, Revised ed|location=Columbus, OH|publisher= Harold L. Hedrick|url=http://www.questia.com/read/82238646|year=1948}}
* {{Cite book|last=Lee|first=Cristopher|title=This Sceptred Isle:55BC-1901|publisher=Penguin Books|isbn=0-140-26133-8|location=London|year=1998}}
* {{Cite book|first=Emmanuel Le Roy|last= Ladurie|coauthor=Alan Sheridan Tr.|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=VT9rIMQFt2MC&amp;pg=PA32&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|title= The French peasantry, 1450-1660|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley and LA|year=1987|isbn= 0-520-05523-3}}
* {{Cite book|last=Lowe|first=Ben|title=Imagining Peace: History of Early English Pacifist Ideas |publisher=Pennsylvania State University Press|location=University Park PA|year=1997|isbn=0271016892}}
* {{Cite book|first=Ian|last=Mortimer|title=The Fears of Henry IV: the Life of England's Self-Made King|publisher=Jonathan Cape|location=London|year=2008|isbn=978-1-844-13529-5}}
* {{Cite book|last=Nicolle|first=David|title=The Fall of English France 1449-53|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Colchester, Essex|year=2012|isbn=978-1-84908-616-5}}
* {{Cite book|last=Ormrod|first=W Mark|title=Edward III|publisher=Yale University Press|location=London|year=2001|isbn=978-0-30-011910-7}}
* {{Cite book|last=Le Patourel|first=John|editor-last=Jones|editor-first=Michael|title=Feudal Empires:Norman and Plantagenet|publisher=Hambledon Continuum|year=1984|location=London|isbn=0-907628-22-2|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=aGlLTOOeBG0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=treaty+of+br%C3%A9tigny&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=gT0ExAQS42&amp;sig=EnglcrqXyhO7etEuonGwmC8D9gQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=HyNiUP6vOqWr0QWfvYCQAw&amp;ved=0CFcQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=paris&amp;f=false|accessdate=26 September 2012}}
* {{Cite book|last=Preston|first=Richard|coauthors=Sydney F. Wise, Herman O. Werner|title= Men in arms: a history of warfare and its interrelationships with Western society. 5th Edition|year=1991|location=Beverley MA|publisher=Wadsworth Publishing Co Inc|isbn=0-03-033428-4 }}
* {{Cite book|last=Prestwich|first=Michael|title=English Monarchs: Edward I|authorlink=Michael Prestwich|publisher=University of California|location=Berkeley and LA|year=1988|isbn=0-520-06266-3}}
* {{Cite book|last=Prestwich|first=Michael|title=Plantagenet England|editor=J.M.Roberts|publisher=OUP|location=Oxford|year=2005|isbn=978-0-19-922687-0}}
* {{Cite encyclopedia|last=Previte-Orton|first=C.W|title=The shorter Cambridge Medieval History 2|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|year=1978|isbn=0-521-20963-3}}
* {{Cite encyclopedia|editor-last=Rogers|editor-first=Clifford J|title=The Oxford Encyclopedia of Medieval Warfare and Military Technology. Vol. 1|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=2010|isbn=978-0-19-533403-6}}
* {{Cite book|last=Sumption|first=Jonathan|title=The Hundred Years War I: Trial by Battle|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|location = Philidelphia|year=1991|isbn=0-8122-1655-5}}	
* {{Cite book|last=Turchin|first=Peter|title=Historical dynamics: why states rise and fall|publisher= Princeton University|year=2003|location=Princeton|isbn=0-691-11669-5}}
* {{Cite encyclopedia|editor-last=Vauchéz|editor-first=Andre|title=Encyclopedia of the Middle ages. Volume 1|publisher=James Clark|location=Cambridge|year=2000|isbn=1-57958-282-6}}
* {{Cite book|last=de Venette|first=Jean|editor1-last=Newall|editor1-first=Richard A|title=The Chronicle of Jean de Venette. Translated by Jean Birdsall|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=1953|location=New York}}
* {{Cite encyclopedia|last=Wagner|first=John A|title=Encyclopedia of the Hundred Years War|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport CT|year=2006|isbn=0-313-32736-x}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Hundred Years' War}}
* [http://www.jeanne-darc.dk/ Jeanne d'Arc. Online University research project.]
* [http://www.lebrelblanco.com/15.htm The Hundred Years War and the History of Navarre]
* [http://www.maisonstclaire.org/timeline/timeline.html Timeline of the Hundred Years War]
* [http://www.maidofheaven.com/joanofarc_long_biography.asp Extensive website about Joan of Arc]
* [http://www.vlib.us/medieval/lectures/hundred_years_war.html The Hundred Years' War (1336–1565) by Dr. Lynn H. Nelson], University of Kansas Emeritus
* [http://www.hyw.com The Hundred Years' War information and game]
* [http://www.yecompaynyeofcheualrye.com/ The Company Of Chivalry: Re-enactment Society at the time of the 100 Years War]
* Jean Froissart, [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/froissart1.html &quot;On The Hundred Years War (1337–1453)&quot;] from the [[Internet Medieval Sourcebook]]
{{Hundred Years' War}}

[[Category:Hundred Years' War| ]]
[[Category:14th century in France]]
[[Category:15th century in France]]
[[Category:Anglo-French Wars]]
[[Category:Late Middle Ages]]
[[Category:Warfare of the Middle Ages]]

{{Link GA|eo}}
{{Link FA|fr}}
{{Link FA|hr}}

[[af:Honderdjarige Oorlog]]
[[ar:حرب المئة عام]]
[[an:Guerra d'os Cient Anyos]]
[[az:Yüzillik müharibə]]
[[zh-min-nan:Pah-nî Chiàn-cheng]]
[[be:Стогадовая вайна]]
[[be-x-old:Стогадовая вайна]]
[[bg:Стогодишна война]]
[[bs:Stogodišnji rat]]
[[br:Brezel Kant Vloaz]]
[[ca:Guerra dels Cent Anys]]
[[cs:Stoletá válka]]
[[cy:Y Rhyfel Can Mlynedd]]
[[da:Hundredårskrigen]]
[[de:Hundertjähriger Krieg]]
[[et:Saja-aastane sõda]]
[[el:Εκατονταετής πόλεμος]]
[[es:Guerra de los Cien Años]]
[[eo:Centjara milito]]
[[eu:Ehun Urteko Gerra]]
[[fa:جنگ صدساله]]
[[hif:Hundred Years War]]
[[fr:Guerre de Cent Ans]]
[[fy:Hûndertjierrige oarloch]]
[[ga:Cogadh Céad Bliain]]
[[gl:Guerra dos Cen Anos]]
[[ko:백년 전쟁]]
[[hy:Հարյուրամյա պատերազմ]]
[[hi:शतवर्षीय युद्ध]]
[[hr:Stogodišnji rat]]
[[io:Cent-yara milito]]
[[ilo:Gubat ti Sangagasut a Tawtawen]]
[[id:Perang Seratus Tahun]]
[[is:Hundrað ára stríðið]]
[[it:Guerra dei cent'anni]]
[[he:מלחמת מאה השנים]]
[[ka:ასწლიანი ომი]]
[[kk:Жүзжылдық соғыс]]
[[sw:Vita ya miaka 100]]
[[la:Bellum Centum Annorum]]
[[lv:Simtgadu karš]]
[[lb:Honnertjärege Krich]]
[[lt:Šimtametis karas]]
[[hu:Százéves háború]]
[[mk:Стогодишна војна]]
[[ml:നൂറ്റാണ്ടു യുദ്ധം]]
[[mr:शंभर वर्षांचे युद्ध]]
[[xmf:ოშწანიანი ლჷმა]]
[[arz:حرب الميت سنه]]
[[ms:Perang Seratus Tahun]]
[[nl:Honderdjarige Oorlog]]
[[ja:百年戦争]]
[[no:Hundreårskrigen]]
[[nn:Hundreårskrigen]]
[[nrm:Gùerre dé Chent Auns]]
[[oc:Guèrra de Cent Ans]]
[[pnb:سو سالہ لڑائی]]
[[pl:Wojna stuletnia]]
[[pt:Guerra dos Cem Anos]]
[[ro:Războiul de 100 de Ani]]
[[ru:Столетняя война]]
[[simple:Hundred Years' War]]
[[sk:Storočná vojna]]
[[sl:Stoletna vojna]]
[[sr:Стогодишњи рат]]
[[sh:Stogodišnji rat]]
[[fi:Satavuotinen sota]]
[[sv:Hundraårskriget]]
[[ta:நூறாண்டுப் போர்]]
[[th:สงครามร้อยปี]]
[[tr:Yüz Yıl Savaşı]]
[[tk:Ýüzýyllyk uruş]]
[[uk:Столітня війна]]
[[ur:جنگ سو سالہ]]
[[za:Baknienz cancwng]]
[[vi:Chiến tranh Trăm Năm]]
[[vls:Ounderdjoarigen ôorlog]]
[[war:Uskagatos ka Tuig nga Gyera]]
[[yi:הונדערט-יעריגע מלחמה]]
[[zh-yue:百年戰爭]]
[[diq:Herbê Seserre]]
[[bat-smg:Šėmtametė vaina]]
[[zh:百年战争]]</text>
      <sha1>fp8m0156onmrfo5ma240dxd5rz1oxg3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
