<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Imperialism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15316</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522395860</id>
      <parentid>522242771</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T22:49:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>70.77.72.64</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31844">{{for|the tract by Lenin|Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism}}
{{seealso|Empire|Hegemony}}

'''Imperialism''', as defined by the ''People of Human Geography'', is &quot;the creation and/or maintenance of an unequal economic, cultural, and territorial relationship, usually between states and often in the form of an empire, based on domination and subordination.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Johnston, Ronald John (2000). ''[http://books.google.ca/books?id=0-GxowMfwlkC&amp;pg=375 The Dictionary of Human Geography]'' (4th ed.). Wiley-Blackwell. p. 375. ISBN 0-631-20561-6&lt;/ref&gt; Lewis Samuel Feuer identifies two major subtypes of imperialism; the first is &quot;regressive imperialism&quot; identified with pure conquest, unequivocal exploitation, extermination or reductions of undesired peoples, and settlement of desired peoples into those territories, an example being [[Nazi Germany]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis Samuel Feuer 1989. P. 4&quot;&gt;Lewis Samuel Feuer. Imperialism and the Anti-Imperialist Mind. Transaction Publishers, 1989. P. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; The second type identified by Feurer is &quot;progressive imperialism&quot; that is founded upon a [[Cosmopolitanism|cosmopolitan]] view of [[humanity]], that promotes the spread of [[civilization]] to allegedly &quot;backward&quot; societies to elevate living standards and culture in conquered territories, and allowance of a conquered people to assimilate into the imperial society, examples being the [[Roman Empire]] and [[British Empire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lewis Samuel Feuer 1989. P. 4&quot;/&gt;

Imperialism always involves the massive export of capital to foreign countries for the purpose of exploiting and dominating both their labor forces and their markets. Imperialism, the highest stage of capitalism, represents the stage at which a country's consumers cannot buy all the products that have been produced, and additional markets must be sought after. The dominant feature of imperialism is the repatriation of invested capital.

[[Image:Punch Rhodes Colossus.png|thumb|right|180px|[[Cecil Rhodes]] and the [[Cape-Cairo railway]] project. Rhodes founded the [[De Beers Mining Company]], owned the [[British South Africa Company]] and had his name given to what became the state of [[Rhodesia]]. He liked to &quot;paint the map [[British Empire|British]] red&quot; and declared: &quot;all of these stars ... these vast worlds that remain out of reach. If I could, I would annex other planets.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[S. Gertrude Millin]], ''Rhodes'', London: 1933, p.138.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The term as such primarily has been applied to Western political and economic dominance in the 19th and 20th centuries. Some writers, such as [[Edward Said]], use the term more broadly to describe any system of domination and subordination organized with an imperial center and a periphery. According to the Marxist historian, Walter Rodney, imperialism meant capitalist expansion. It meant that European (and North American and Japanese) capitalists were forced by the internal logic of their competitive system to seek abroad in less developed countries opportunities to control raw material, to find markets, and to find profitable fields of investment.

It's generally accepted that modern day [[colonialism]] is an expression of imperialism and cannot exist without the latter. The extent to which &quot;informal&quot; imperialism with no formal colonies is properly described as such remains a controversial topic among historians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bush2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Barbara Bush|title=Imperialism And Postcolonialism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6qmJrjHcBkkC&amp;pg=PA46|accessdate=28 September 2012|year=2006|publisher=Pearson Longman|isbn=978-0-582-50583-4|pages=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==

Imperialism has been found in the histories of [[Japan]], the [[Assyrian Empire]], the [[History of China|Chinese Empire]], the [[Roman Empire]], [[Ancient Greece|Greece]], the [[Byzantine Empire]], the [[Persian Empire]], the [[Ottoman Empire]], ancient [[Egypt]], and [[India]]. Imperialism was a basic component to the conquests of [[Genghis Khan]] during the [[Mongol Empire]], and other war-lords. Historically recognized [[List of Muslim empires and dynasties|Muslim empires]] number in the dozens. Sub-Saharan Africa has also had dozens of empires that pre-date the European colonial era, for example the [[Ethiopian Empire]], [[Oyo Empire]], [[Asante Union]], [[Luba Empire]], [[Lunda Empire]] and [[Mutapa Empire]]. The Americas during the pre-Columbian era also had large empires in [[Mesoamerica]], such as the [[Aztec civilization|Aztec]] and the [[Inca civilization|Inca]], [[United Kingdom|Britain]], [[United States]], [[France]], the [[Netherlands]], [[Portugal]], and [[Kingdom of Spain|Spain]] in [[Africa]], [[Asia]], and the [[Americas]]. Imperialism not only describes colonial and territorial policies, but also economic and military dominance and influence.

Although normally used to imply forcible imposition of a more powerful foreign government's control on a weaker country, or over conquered territory that was previously without a unified government, &quot;imperialism&quot; is sometimes also used to describe loose or indirect political or economic influence or control of weak states by more powerful ones.&lt;ref name=IESS&gt;&quot;Imperialism.&quot; 'International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences'', 2nd edition.&lt;/ref&gt; If the dominant country's influence is felt in social and cultural circles, such as &quot;foreign&quot; music being popular with young people, it may be described as [[cultural imperialism]].

&quot;Imperialism has been subject to moral censure by its critics, and thus the term is frequently used in international propaganda as a pejorative for expansionist and aggressive foreign policy.&quot;&lt;ref name=IESS /&gt;

==Colonialism vs imperialism==

[[File:The British Empire.png|thumb|right|300px|Territories that were once part of the [[British Empire]].]]
The term 'imperialism' should not be confused with ‘colonialism’ as it often is.  [[Robert J. C. Young|Robert Young]] writes that imperialism operates from the center, it is a state policy, and is developed for ideological as well as financial reasons whereas colonialism is nothing more than development for settlement or commercial intentions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gilmartin, Mary 2008. pg.116&quot;&gt;Gilmartin, Mary. Gallaher, C. et al., 2008. Key Concepts in Political Geography, Sage Publications Ltd. : Imperialism/Colonialism. pg.116&lt;/ref&gt;

==Age of Imperialism==

The Age of Imperialism was a time period beginning around 1870 when modern, relatively developed nations were taking over less developed areas, colonizing them, or influencing them in order to expand their own power. Although imperialist practices have existed for thousands of years, the term &quot;Age of Imperialism&quot; generally refers to the activities of nations such as the [[British Empire|United Kingdom]], [[French colonial empire|France]], [[German Empire|Germany]], [[Italian Empire|Italy]], [[Empire of Japan|Japan]] and the [[American imperialism|United States]] in the early 18th through the middle 20th centuries, e.g., the &quot;[[The Great Game]]&quot; in Persian lands, the &quot;[[Scramble for Africa]]&quot; and the &quot;[[Open Door Policy]]&quot; in China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:QigcXabehRwJ:mclane.fresno.k12.ca.us/wilson98/mwh/C/MH11C045.PDF+%22age+of+imperialism%22&amp;hl=en&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEEShoA0WBotar1_hzLNv-9Xgbr0KhmGgiHvs6VZK5ODaRsecbPWTVIeZ8PJCovszsXYeJcDWdlca9YDUjAlQGB1uVY9tyy7HUUhtkBi0qMsJSi2Uqd78Dt1vLEEpeqOVRpg-yIY6V&amp;sig=AHIEtbQdQ4H9pgU4AKtL7ZDIlzqVjYPUxA| title=The Age of Imperialism, 1850–1914| publisher=Google docs| accessdate=December 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://porter.umdl.umich.edu/p/philamer/| title=The United States and its Territories: 1870–1925 The Age of Imperialism| publisher=University of Michigan| accessdate=February 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Colonial Africa 1913 map.svg|thumb|right|260px|The [[scramble for Africa]].]]
The ideas of imperialism put forward by historians [[John Andrew Gallagher|John Gallagher]] and [[Ronald Robinson]] during the 19th century. [[Colonial empire|European imperialism]] were influential, and they rejected the notion that &quot;imperialism&quot; required formal, legal control by one government over another country. &quot;In their view, historians have been mesmerized by formal empire and maps of the world with regions colored red. The bulk of British emigration, trade, and capital went to areas outside the formal British Empire. A key to the thought of Robinson and Gallagher is the idea of empire 'informally if possible and formally if necessary.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Louis, Wm. Roger. (1976) ''Imperialism'' page 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

Europe’s expansion into territorial imperialism had much to do with the great economic benefit from collecting resources from colonies, in combination with assuming political control often by military means. Most notably, the “British exploited the political weakness of the [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] state, and, while military activity was important at various times, the economic and administrative incorporation of local elites was also of crucial significance”. Although a substantial number of colonies had been designed or subject to provide economic profit (mostly through the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries), Fieldhouse suggests that in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries in places such as Africa and Asia, this idea is not necessarily valid&lt;ref&gt;Painter, J. &amp; Jeffrey, A., 2009. Political Geography 2nd ed., Sage. pg.183-184&lt;/ref&gt;:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Modern empires were not artificially constructed economic machines. The second expansion of Europe was a complex historical process in which political, social and emotional forces in Europe and on the periphery were more influential than calculated imperialism. Individual colonies might serve an economic purpose; collectively no empire had any definable function, economic or otherwise. Empires represented only a particular phase in the ever-changing relationship of Europe with the rest of the world: analogies with industrial systems or investment in real estate were simply misleading.&lt;ref&gt;Painter, J. &amp; Jeffrey, A., 2009. Political Geography 2nd ed., Sage. pg.184&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

During this time, European merchants had the ability to “roam the high seas and appropriate surpluses from around the world (sometimes peaceably, sometimes violently) and to concentrate them in Europe.”&lt;ref&gt;Harvey, D., 2006. Spaces of Global Capitalism: A Theory of Uneven Geographical Development, Verso. pg. 91&lt;/ref&gt;

European expansion accelerated greatly in the 19th century. To obtain raw materials, Europe began importing them from other countries. Europeans sought raw materials such as dyes, cotton, vegetable oils, and metal ores from overseas. Europe was being transformed into the manufacturing center of the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adas 2008 54-58&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Adas |first=Michael |title=Turbulent Passage A Global History of the Twentieth Century |year=2008 |publisher=Pearson Education, Inc. |isbn=0-205-64571-2 |pages=54–58 |edition=Fourth Edition |coauthors=Peter N. Stearns}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Communication became much more advanced during the European expansion. The invention of railroads and telegraphs made it easier to communicate with other countries. Railroads assisted in transporting goods and in supplying large armies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adas 2008 54-58&quot;/&gt;

Along with advancements in communication, Europe also continued to develop its military technology. European chemists made deadly explosives that could be used in combat, and with the advancement of machinery they were able to create lighter, cheaper guns. The guns were also much faster and more accurate. By the late 19th century (1880s) the machine gun had become an effective battlefield weapon. This technology gave European armies an advantage over their opponents, as armies in less developed countries were still fighting with arrows, swords, and leather shields.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adas 2008 54-58&quot;/&gt;

==Germany==

From their original homelands in Scandinavia and the far north of Europe, Germanic tribes expanded throughout northern and western Europe in the middle period of classical antiquity, and southern Europe in late antiquity, conquering Celtic and other peoples and forming in 800 the [[Holy Roman Empire]], the first German Empire. However unlike China, there was no real systemic continuity from the western Roman Empire to its German successor which famously was &quot;not holy, not Roman, and not an empire&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;attributed to [[Voltaire]]&lt;/ref&gt; and numerous small states existed in variously autonomous confederation. Although by 1000 Germanic conquest of central, western, and southern Europe west of and including Italy was complete, excluding only Muslim Iberia, there was no process equivalent to Han [[sinification]], and &quot;Germany&quot; remained largely a conceptual term referring to an amorphous area of central Europe.

Not a maritime power, and not a nation-state, as it became one, Germany's participation in Western imperialism was negligible until the late 19th century and the participation of Austria was primarily as a result of [[Habsburg]] control of the First Empire, the [[Spanish throne]], and other royal houses. After the defeat of Napoleon, who caused the dissolution of that first German Empire, Prussia, and the German states continued to stand aloof from imperialism, preferring to manipulate the European system through polices such as those of [[Metternich]]. After Prussia unified the other states into the [[second German Empire]], its long-time leader [[Otto von Bismarck]] (1862–90) had long opposed colonial acquisitions, arguing that the burden of obtaining, maintaining and defending such possessions would outweigh any potential benefit. He felt that colonies did not pay for themselves, that the German bureaucratic system would not work well in the easy-going tropics, and the diplomatic disputes over colonies would distract Germany from its central interest, Europe itself.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Pakenham, ''The Scramble for Africa: White Man's Conquest of the Dark Continent from 1876-1912'' (1992) ch 12&lt;/ref&gt;  However, in 1883-84 he suddenly reversed himself and overnight built a colonial empire in Africa and the South Pacific, and then lost interest in imperialism. Historians have debated exactly why he made this sudden and short-lived move.&lt;ref&gt;Paul M. Kennedy, ''The Rise of the Anglo-German Antagonism, 1860-1914'' (1988) ch 10&lt;/ref&gt;  He was aware that public opinion had started to demand colonies for reasons of German prestige.&lt;ref&gt;Hans-Ulrich Wehler, &quot;Bismarck's Imperialism 1862–1890,&quot; ''Past &amp; Present'', (1970) 48: 119–55 [http://past.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/48/1/119.pdf online]&lt;/ref&gt; Bismarck was influenced by Hamburg merchants and traders, his neighbors at Friedrichsruh. The establishment of the [[German colonial empire]] proceeded smoothly, starting with [[German New Guinea]] in 1884.&lt;ref&gt;Hartmut Pogge von Strandmann, &quot;Domestic Origins of Germany's Colonial Expansion under Bismarck&quot; ''Past &amp; Present'' (1969) 42:140–159 [http://past.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/42/1/140.pdf online]; Crankshaw, pp. 395–7&lt;/ref&gt;

After the collapse of the short-lived [[Third Reich]], and the failure of its attempt to create a [[lebensraum|great land empire]] in Eurasia, Germany was split between Western and Soviet [[sphere of influence|spheres of influence]] until [[Perestroika]] and the collapse of the Soviet Union.

==Tsarist and Soviet Russian imperialism==

{{seealso|Criticism of communist party rule|Soviet Empire}}
[[File:Soviet empire 1960.png|thumb|right|200px|The maximum territorial extent of countries in the world under Soviet influence, after the [[Cuban Revolution]] of 1959 and before the official [[Sino-Soviet split]] of 1961.]]

As Germanic tribes conquered western Europe, Slavic peoples gradually expanded their control over eastern Europe and northern Eurasia, and in the form of the [[Russian Empire|Romanov Empire]] extended that control to the Pacific forming a common border with the [[Qing Empire]].

[[Bolshevik]] leaders had effectively reestablished a polity with roughly the same jurisdiction as that empire by 1921, but with an internationalist ideology: Lenin in particular asserted the right to self-determination for national minorities within the new territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url=http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1913/crnq/index.htm| author=V.I. Lenin| title=Critical Remarks on the National Question| publisher= Prosveshcheniye| year=1913}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in 1923, the policy of &quot;Indigenization&quot; [korenizatsiia] was intended to support non-Russians develop their national cultures within a socialist framework. Never formally revoked, it stopped being implemented after 1932.  After World War II, the Soviet Union installed socialist regimes modelled on those it had installed in 1919–20 in the old [[Tsarist Empire|Tsarist empire]] in areas its forces occupied in Eastern Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005506| title=The Soviet Union and Europe after 1945| publisher=The U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum| accessdate=December 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union and People's Republic of China supported post–World War II anti-colonial national-liberation movements to advance their own interests but were not always successful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url=http://books.google.com/books?id=qFTHBoRvQbsC&amp;pg=PA138#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false| author=Melvin E. Page| title=Colonialism: an international social, cultural, and political encyclopedia| publisher=ABC-CLIO| year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Trotsky, and others believed that the revolution could only succeed in Russia as part of a [[world revolution]], which was in fact shortly after the Russian Revolution spreading in the defeated [[central powers]] of Europe. Lenin wrote extensively on the matter and famously declared that [[Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism|Imperialism was the highest stage of]] [[capitalism]]. However after Lenin's death, [[Joseph Stalin]] established [[Socialism in one country]] for the Soviet Union, creating the model for subsequent inward looking Stalinist states and purging the early Internationalist elements.  The internationalist tendencies of the early revolution would be abandoned until they returned in a [[client state]] form in the competition with the United States in the [[Cold War]].

[[Image:McKinley Destroys Imperialism Straw Man.jpg|thumb|&quot;[[William McKinley|President McKinley]] fires a cannon into the Imperialist [[Strawman]]&quot;. Cartoon by [[William Allen Rogers|W. A. Rogers]] in ''[[Harper's Weekly]]'', September 22, 1900.]]
Though the Soviet Union declared itself [[anti-imperialism|anti-imperialist]], critics argue that it exhibited tendencies common to historic empires. Some scholars hold that the Soviet Union was a hybrid entity containing elements common to both multinational empires and nation states. It has also been argued that the USSR practiced [[colonialism]] as did other imperial powers and was carrying on the old Russian tradition of expansion and control.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |jstor=20031013 |pages=135–144 |last1=Caroe |first1=O. |title=Soviet Colonialism in Central Asia |volume=32 |issue=1 |journal=Foreign Affairs |year=1953}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States as &quot;the world's policeman&quot;==

{{main|American imperialism}}
The early United States expressed its opposition to Imperialism, at least that distinct from its own [[Manifest Destiny]], in policies such as the [[Monroe Doctrine]]. Beginning in the late 19th and early 20th century however, policies such as [[Woodrow Wilson]]'s mission to &quot;make the world safe for democracy&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/ww18.htm Text of Original address (mtholyoke.edu)]&lt;/ref&gt; were often backed by military force, but more often effected from behind the scenes, consistent with the general notion of hegemony and imperium of historical empires.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.cfr.org/publication/7190/in_modern_imperialism_us_needs_to_walk_softly.html| author=Max Boot| title=In Modern Imperialism, U.S. Needs to Walk Softly| publisher=Council on Foreign Relations| date=July 15, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/specials/article5047143.ece| author=Oliver Kamm| title=America is still the world's policeman| publisher=The Times| date=October 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1898 Americans who opposed imperialism created the [[American Anti-Imperialist League|Anti-Imperialist League]] to oppose the US annexation of the Philippines and Cuba. A year later a war erupted in the Philippines causing business, labor and government leaders in the US to condemn America's occupation in the Philippines. They also denounced them for causing the deaths of many Filipinos.&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=QKgraWbb7yoC&amp;pg=PA1075#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;

After the second world war the United States became identified with Western interests generally in a [[cold war|global conflict]] of spheres of influence with the Soviet Union. After the collapse of the Soviet Union, the United States did not diminish its global ability to project force, remaining &quot;the sole superpower&quot; and what has been called a &quot;[[Polarity in international relations|unipolar]]&quot; situation of domination by it globally came into force.

Since the end of the previous century [[Battlespace]] domination has been an open and variously reported policy of the U.S. Department of defense and U.S. Administrations stated and restated in various Quadrennial Reports, force posture statements, etc. in execution of its role as sole remaining superpower.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defense.gov/qdr/archive/ Quadrennial Review 1997]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defense.gov/qdr/archive/20060206qdr1.html 2006 QDR]&lt;/ref&gt; The 2010 QDR indicates a change in perspective and it is unclear how the policy of the first decade of the 21st century would be sustained through the [[late 2000s recession|anticipated fiscal environment]] of the second.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defense.gov/qdr/ Current QDR (2012)]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, the United States had 737 military bases in foreign countries, according to official sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.alternet.org/story/47998| author=Chalmers Johnson| title=737 U.S. Military Bases = Global Empire| publisher=AlterNet| date=February 19, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[List of countries by military expenditures|As of 2010]] US Military spending is about 43% of the world total.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/blogs/democracyinamerica/2011/12/defence-spending ''Always more, or else''] Economist Article December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Only a handful of countries spent a larger portion of GDP on military in 2010 and of these only Israel, Saudi Arabia, and the United Arab Emirates spent more than US$10 billion.

== Justification ==

A controversial aspect of imperialism is the imperial power’s defense and justification of such actions. Most controversial of all is the justification of imperialism done on rational grounds. [[J. A. Hobson]] identifies this justification: “It is desirable that the earth should be peopled, governed, and developed, as far as possible, by the races which can do this work best, i.e. by the races of highest 'social efficiency'.”&lt;ref&gt;Hobson, J. A. &quot;Imperialism: a study.&quot; Cosimo, Inc., 2005. pg. 154&lt;/ref&gt; This is clearly the racial argument, which pays heed to other ideas such as the “[[The White Man's Burden|White Man’s Burden]]” prevalent at the turn of the twentieth century.

[[Technology|Technological]] and [[economic efficiency]] were often improved in territories subjected to imperialism through the building of roads and introduction of innovations. However, the majority of the rewards of such infrastructure improvements are usually shipped to the imperial state or utilized by the local administration. Similarly, the rapid adoption of the [[scientific method]] throughout the world was partly a side effect of the [[British Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=L5wdAAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PA243&amp;ots=Krjpr-iAPF&amp;dq=scientific%20revolution%20british%20imperialism&amp;pg=PA243#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;

The principles of imperialism are often deeply connected to the policies and practices of British Imperialism &quot;during the last generation, and proceeds rather by diagnosis than by historical description.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hobson, J. A. &quot;Imperialism: a study.&quot; Cosimo, Inc., 2005. pg. V&lt;/ref&gt; British Imperialist strategy often but not always used the concept of ''terra nullius'' (Latin expression which stems from [[Roman law]] meaning ‘empty land’). The country of [[Australia]] serves as a case study in relation to British imperialism. British settlement and colonial rule of the island continent of Australia in the eighteenth century was premised on ''terra nullius'', for its settlers considered it unused by its sparse inhabitants.

This form of imperialism can also be seen in British Columbia, Canada. In the 1840s, the territory of British Columbia was divided into two regions, one space for the native population, and the other for non-natives. The indigenous peoples were often forcibly removed from their homes onto reserves. These actions were “justified by a dominant belief among British colonial officials that land occupied by Native people was not being used efficiently and productively.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Gilmartin, Mary 2008. pg.116&quot;/&gt;

== See also ==
{{columns |colwidth=19em
|col1 =
* [[Colonialism]]
* [[Cultural imperialism]]
* [[Empire]]
* [[Feudalism]]
* [[Globalization]]
* [[Hegemony]]
* [[Leninism#Imperialism|Imperialism in Leninist theory]]
* [[Imperium]]
* [[Imperialism (video game)]]
* [[John A. Hobson]]
* [[List of empires]]
|col2 =
* [[List of largest empires]]
* [[Neocolonialism]]
* [[New Imperialism]]
* [[Oil imperialism theories]]
* [[Old Imperialism]]
* [[Scientific imperialism]]
* [[Super-imperialism]]
* [[Theories of New Imperialism]]
* [[Ultra-imperialism]]
* [[Uneven and combined development]]
}}

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== Further reading ==
* Guy Ankerl, ''Coexisting Contemporary Civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharatai, Chinese, and Western,'' Geneva, INU PRESS, 2000, ISBN 2-88155-004-5.
* Robert Bickers/Christian Henriot, ''New Frontiers: Imperialism's New Communities in East Asia, 1842–1953'', Manchester, Manchester University Press, 2000, ISBN 0-7190-5604-7
* [[Barbara Bush]], ''Imperialism and Postcolonialism (History: Concepts,Theories and Practice),'' Longmans, 2006, ISBN 0-582-50583-6
* John Darwin (author)'', After Tamerlane: The Rise and Fall of Global Empires, 1400–2000,'' Penguin Books, 2008, ISBN 0-14-101022-3
* [[Niall Ferguson]], ''Empire: How Britain Made the Modern World,'' Penguin Books, 2004, ISBN 0-14-100754-0
* [[Michael Hardt]] and [[Toni Negri]], ''Empire,'' [[Harvard University Press]], 2000, ISBN 0-674-00671-2
* [[E.J. Hobsbawm]], ''The Age of Empire, 1875–1914,'' Abacus Books, 1989, ISBN 0-349-10598-7
* [[E. J. Hobsbawm]], ''On Empire: America, War, and Global Supremacy,'' Pantheon Books, 2008, ISBN 0-375-42537-3
* [[J. A. Hobson]], ''Imperialism: A Study,'' Cosimo Classics, 2005, ISBN 1-59605-250-3
* [[Michael Hudson (economist)|Michael Hudson]], ''Super Imperialism: The Origin and Fundamentals of U.S. World Dominance,'' Pluto Press, 2003, ISBN 0-7453-1989-0
* [[V. I. Lenin]], ''[[Imperialism: The Highest Stage of Capitalism]],'' International Publishers, New York, 1997, ISBN 0-7178-0098-9
* [[Rosa Luxemburg]], ''[[The Accumulation of Capital: A Contribution to an Economic Explanation of Imperialism]]''
* Petringa, Maria, ''Brazza, A Life for Africa'', Bloomington, IN: AuthorHouse, 2006. ISBN 978-1-4259-1198-0
* [[Edward Said]], ''Culture and Imperialism,'' Vintage Books, 1998, ISBN 0-09-996750-2
* Simon C. Smith, ''British Imperialism 1750–1970,'' Cambridge University Press, 1998, ISBN 0-521-59930-X
* Stuchtey, Benedikt, [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-20101025319 ''Colonialism and Imperialism, 1450-1950''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2011, retrieved: July 13, 2011.
* Leo Blanken, ''[http://www.themontrealreview.com/2009/Rational-Empires-Institutional-Incentives-and-Imperial-Expansion.php Rational Empires: Institutional Incentives and Imperial Expansion],'' University Of Chicago Press, 2012, ISBN 0-226-05674-0

== External links ==
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/hobson/1902/imperialism/index.htm J.A Hobson, Imperialism a Study] 1902.
* [http://www.mises.org/story/2383 The Paradox of Imperialism] by [[Hans-Hermann Hoppe]]. November 2006.
* [http://www.polyarchy.org/documents/imperialism.html Imperialism] Quotations
* [http://www.panarchy.org/schumpeter/imperialism.html State, Imperialism and Capitalism] by [[Joseph Schumpeter]]
* [http://www.panarchy.org/taylor/imperialism.1952.html Economic Imperialism] by A.J.P.Taylor
* [http://www.bartelby.org/65/im/imperial.html Imperialism Entry in the Columbia Encyclopedia (Bartleby)]
* [http://www.polis.cam.ac.uk/contacts/staff/eperreausaussine/imperialism.pdf] Imperialism by Emile Perreau-Saussine
* [http://dostoevskiansmiles.blogspot.com/2008/10/nation-state-core-and-periphery-brief.html The Nation-State, Core and Periphery: A Brief sketch of Imperialism in the 20th century.]
* [http://www.sam.gov.tr/perceptions/volume12/winter/winter-004-PERCEPTION(mehmetakifokur)%5B4%5D.pdf Mehmet Akif Okur, Rethinking Empire After 9/11: Towards A New Ontological Image of World Order, Perceptions, Journal of International Affairs, Volume XII, Winter 2007, pp.61–93]
* [http://www.michaelparenti.org/Imperialism101.html Imperialism 101, Against Empire By Michael Parenti Published by City Lights Books, 1995, ISBN 0-87286-298-4, ISBN 978-0-87286-298-2, 217 pages]

{{Marxist &amp; Communist phraseology}}
{{Empires}}

[[Category:Economic theories]]
[[Category:History of colonialism]]
[[Category:Marxist theory]]
[[Category:Imperialism| ]]
[[Category:Political economy]]
[[Category:Political systems]]
[[Category:Political theories]]

[[ar:إمبريالية]]
[[an:Imperialismo]]
[[ast:Imperialismu]]
[[zh-min-nan:Tè-kok-chú-gī]]
[[be:Імперыялізм]]
[[be-x-old:Імпэрыялізм]]
[[bg:Империализъм]]
[[bar:Imperialismus]]
[[bs:Imperijalizam]]
[[br:Impalaerouriezh]]
[[ca:Imperialisme]]
[[cs:Imperialismus]]
[[cy:Imperialaeth]]
[[da:Imperialisme]]
[[de:Imperialismus]]
[[et:Imperialism]]
[[el:Ιμπεριαλισμός]]
[[es:Imperialismo]]
[[eo:Imperiismo]]
[[eu:Inperialismo]]
[[fa:امپریالیسم]]
[[hif:Samrajwaad]]
[[fr:Impérialisme]]
[[fy:Ymperialisme]]
[[gl:Imperialismo]]
[[ko:제국주의]]
[[hi:साम्राज्यवाद]]
[[hr:Imperijalizam]]
[[id:Imperialisme]]
[[is:Heimsvaldastefna]]
[[it:Imperialismo]]
[[he:אימפריאליזם]]
[[krc:Империализм]]
[[ka:იმპერიალიზმი]]
[[sw:Ubeberu]]
[[la:Imperialismus]]
[[lv:Imperiālisms]]
[[lt:Imperializmas]]
[[hu:Imperializmus]]
[[mk:Империјализам]]
[[ml:സാമ്രാജ്യത്വം]]
[[ms:Imperialisme]]
[[mwl:Amperialismo]]
[[nl:Imperialisme]]
[[ne:साम्राज्यवाद]]
[[ja:帝国主義]]
[[no:Imperialisme]]
[[nn:Imperialisme]]
[[nrm:Împérialisme]]
[[oc:Imperialisme]]
[[pnb:امپیریلزم]]
[[pl:Imperializm]]
[[pt:Imperialismo]]
[[ro:Imperialism]]
[[rue:Імперіалізм]]
[[ru:Империализм]]
[[sah:Империализм]]
[[scn:Mpirialismu]]
[[simple:Imperialism]]
[[sk:Imperializmus]]
[[sl:Imperializem]]
[[sr:Империјализам]]
[[sh:Imperijalizam]]
[[fi:Imperialismi]]
[[sv:Imperialism]]
[[tl:Imperyalismo]]
[[ta:பேரரசுவாதம்]]
[[th:ลัทธิจักรวรรดินิยม]]
[[tr:Emperyalizm]]
[[uk:Імперіалізм]]
[[ur:سامراجیت]]
[[vi:Chủ nghĩa đế quốc]]
[[fiu-vro:Imperialism]]
[[war:Imperyalismó]]
[[bat-smg:Imperēlėzmos]]
[[zh:帝国主义]]</text>
      <sha1>8jembjiz68mft7efmma1hsznc3mc83k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
