<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>55023</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517549068</id>
      <parentid>514748871</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-13T10:06:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HammerFilmFan</username>
        <id>12478971</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Fall of Jin */ removed tag - the statement is concise and clear</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24404">{{About|the Jurchen Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)|other Chinese dynasties whose names are also rendered &quot;Jin&quot; in [[pinyin]]|Jin Dynasty (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox Former Country
|native_name            = [[File:Amba-an Ancu-un.png|65px]]&lt;br&gt;大金
|conventional_long_name = Great Jin
|common_name            = Jin Dynasty, 1115–1234
|
|continent              = Asia
|region                 = China
|country                = China
|era                    =
|status                 = Empire
|status_text            =
|empire                 =
|government_type        = Monarchy
|
|
|year_start             = 1115
|year_end               = 1234
|
|year_exile_start       =
|year_exile_end         =
|
|event_start            = Established
|date_start             = January 28,
|event_end              = Fall of [[Runan County|Caizhou]]
|date_end               = February 9,
|
|event1                 = Ended [[Liao Dynasty|Liao]]'s rule
|date_event1            = 1125
|event2                 = Captured [[Kaifeng|Bianliang]]
|date_event2            = January 9, 1127
|event3                 =
|date_event3            =
|event4                 =
|date_event4            =
|
|event_pre              =
|date_pre               =
|event_post             = |date_post              =
|
|p1                     = Liao Dynasty
|p2                     = Song Dynasty
|s1                     = Mongol Empire
|
|image_flag             =
|flag                   =
|flag_type              =
|
|image_coat             =
|symbol                 =
|symbol_type            =
|
|image_map              = Sung Dynasty 1141.png
|image_map_caption      = Jin Dynasty (blue) circa 1141
|
|capital                = [[Huining Fu|Huining]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1122–1153)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Zhongdu]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1153–1214)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Kaifeng]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1214–1233)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Runan County|Caizhou]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1233–1234)&lt;/small&gt;
|capital_exile          =
|latd= |latm= |latNS= |longd= |longm= |longEW=
|
|national_motto         =
|national_anthem        =
|common_languages       =
|religion               = [[Buddhism]], [[Daoism]], [[Confucianism]], [[Chinese folk religion]]
|currency               = [[Chinese coin]], [[Chinese cash]]
|
|leader1                = [[Wanyan Aguda|Emperor Taizu]]
|leader2                = [[Emperor Modi of Jin|Emperor Modi]]
|year_leader1           = 1115–1123
|year_leader2           = 1234
|title_leader           = [[Jin_Dynasty,_1115–1234#Rise_of_the_Manchus|Emperor]]
|stat_year1             = 1126 est.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Turchin|first1=Peter|last2=Adams|first2=Jonathan M.|last3=Hall|first3=Thomas D | title = East-West Orientation of Historical Empires | journal = Journal of world-systems research|date=December 2006|volume=12|issue=2|pages=219–229|url=http://jwsr.ucr.edu/archive/vol12/number2/pdf/jwsr-v12n2-tah.pdf|accessdate=12 August 2010 |issn= 1076–156x}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|stat_area1             = 2300000
|stat_pop1              =
|stat_year2             = 1142 est.
|stat_area2             = 3000000
|stat_pop2              =
|stat_year3             =
|stat_area3             =
|stat_pop3              =
|stat_year4             =
|stat_area4             =
|stat_pop4              =
|stat_year5             =
|stat_area5             =
|stat_pop5              =
|footnotes              =
}}
{{History of China}}

The '''Jīn Dynasty''' ([[Jurchen language|Jurchen]]: Anchun Gurun; {{zh|c=金朝|p=Jīn Cháo|w=Chin Dynasty}}, {{IPA-cmn|tɕîn tʂʰɑ̌ʊ̯|IPA}}); [[Manchu language|Manchu]]: Aisin Gurun; [[Khitan language]]: Nik, Niku;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.surag.net/viewArticle.do?method=viewArticle&amp;id= 关于契丹小字中的 “金”]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apu.ac.jp/~yoshim/ginnhei.pdf 天朝万顺(岁)”臆解可以休矣]&lt;/ref&gt; {{lang-mn|Altan Ulus}}; 1115–1234), also known as the ''Jurchen Dynasty'' or ''Jurched Dynasty'', was founded by the [[Wanyan]] (完顏 Wányán) [[clan]] of the [[Jurchens]], the ancestors of the [[Manchus]] who established the [[Qing Dynasty]] some 500 years later. The name is sometimes written as ''Jinn'' to differentiate it from an earlier [[Jin Dynasty (265–420)|Jìn Dynasty]] of [[China]] whose name is identically [[Pinyin|spelled using the Latin alphabet]].

==History==
[[Image:Premongol.png|thumb|left|Map of [[Asia]] and parts of [[Europe]] and [[Africa]] circa 1200]]
The Jin Dynasty was founded in what would become northern [[Manchuria]] by the [[Jurchen people|Jurchen]] tribal chieftain [[Wanyan Aguda]] (完顏阿骨打) in 1115. The Jurchens' early rival was the [[Liao Dynasty]], which had held sway over [[Northern and southern China|northern China]], including [[Manchuria]] and part of the [[Mongol]] region for several centuries.  In 1121, the Jurchens entered into the [[Alliance on the Sea]] with the [[Song Dynasty]] and agreed to jointly invade the Liao.  While the Song armies faltered, the Jurchens succeeded in [[Western Liao|driving the Liao to Central Asia]].
In 1125, after the death of Aguda, the Jin broke the alliance with the Song and invaded North China.  On January 9, 1127, Jin forces [[Jingkang Incident|ransacked]] [[Kaifeng]], capital of the [[Northern Song Dynasty]], capturing both [[Emperor Qinzong of Song China|Emperor Qinzong]] and his father, [[Emperor Huizong of Song China|Emperor Huizong]], who had abdicated in panic in the face of Jin forces. Following the fall of Kaifeng, the succeeding [[Southern Song Dynasty]] continued to fight the Jin for over a decade, eventually signing the [[Treaty of Shaoxing]] in 1141, which called for the cession of all Song land north of the [[Huai River]] to the Jin and the execution of Song General [[Yue Fei]] in return for peace.

===The migration south===
[[File:Jade ornament grapes jin dynasty shanghai museum 2004 07 22.jpg|thumb|left|[[Jade]] ornament with flower design, Jin Dynasty, [[Shanghai Museum]].]]
After taking over [[Northern and southern China|Northern China]], the Jin Dynasty became increasingly Sinicized. About three million people, half of them [[Jurchens]], migrated south into northern China over two decades, and this minority governed about thirty million people. The Jurchens were given land grants and organized society into 1,000 households  - ''meng'an'') and 100 households  - ''mouke''). Many married Hans, although the ban on Jurchen nobles marrying Hans was not lifted until 1191. After Jin [[Emperor Taizong of Jin|Emperor Tàizōng]]  died in 1135, the next three Jin emperors were grandsons of [[Wanyan Aguda|Wányán Āgǔdǎ]] by three different princes. Young Jin [[Emperor Xizong of Jin|Emperor Xīzōng]]  (r. 1135–1149) studied the classics and wrote Chinese poetry. He adopted Han cultural traditions, but the Jurchen nobles had the top positions.

[[File:China 11b.jpg|thumb|right|Jin Dynasty, Sourthen Song Dynasty, Western Xia Dynasty and Dali Dynasty 1142.]]
Later in life, Emperor Xīzōng became an alcoholic and executed many officials for criticizing him. He also had Jurchen leaders who opposed him murdered, even those in his own Wanyan family clan. In 1149 he was murdered by a cabal of relatives and nobles, who made his cousin Wányán Liàng  the next Jin emperor. Because of the brutality of both his domestic and foreign policy, Wanyan Liang was posthumously demoted from the position of emperor. Consequently, historians have commonly referred to him by the [[posthumous name]] of [[Emperor Hailingwang of Jin|King Hǎilíng]].&lt;ref name=&quot;multiref1&quot;&gt;[http://www.san.beck.org/AB3-China.html#9 Ethics of China 7 BC To 1279 by Sanderson Beck&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rebellions in the north===
Having usurped the throne,  [[Emperor Hailingwang of Jin|Wanyan Liang]] embarked on the program of legitimizing his rule as an emperor of China. In 1153, he moved the empire's main capital from [[Huining Fu]] in northern Manchuria (south of present-day [[Harbin]]) to the former Liao capital, Yanjing (now [[Beijing]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;multiref1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=tao44&gt;Tao (1976), p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;
Four years later, in 1157, to emphasize the permanence of the move, he razed the nobles’ residences in Huining.&lt;ref name=&quot;multiref1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=tao44/&gt;
Hǎilíng also reconstructed the former Song capital, Bianjing (now [[Kaifeng]]), which had been sacked in 1127, making it the Jin's southern capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;multiref1&quot;/&gt;

Prince Hǎilíng also tried to suppress dissent by killing Jurchen nobles, executing 155 princes.&lt;ref name=&quot;multiref1&quot;/&gt;

To fulfill his dream of becoming the ruler of all China, Prince Hǎilíng attacked the [[Southern Song]] in 1161. Meanwhile, two simultaneous rebellions erupted in [[Manchuria]]: one of [[Jurchen people|Jurchen]] nobles, led by Hǎilíng's cousin, soon-to-be crowned [[Emperor Shizong of Jin|Wányán Yōng]] (完顏雍), and the other of [[Khitan people|Khitan]] tribesmen. Hǎilíng had to withdraw Jin troops from southern China to quell the uprisings. The Jin were defeated in the [[Battle of Caishi]] and [[Battle of Tangdao]]. With a depleted military force, Prince Hǎilíng failed to make headway in his attempted invasion of the [[Southern Song]]. Finally he was assassinated by his own generals in December of 1161, due to his defeats. His son and heir was also assassinated in the capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;multiref1&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Luohan.jpg|thumb|left|A [[marble]] statue of a [[Buddhist]] monk, 1180 AD, Jin Dynasty.]]
Although crowned in October,  Wányán Yōng was not officially recognized as Jin [[Emperor Shizong of Jin|Emperor Shìzōng]] (世宗) until the murder of Prince Hǎilíng's heir.&lt;ref name=&quot;multiref1&quot;/&gt; The Khitan uprising was not suppressed until 1164; their horses were confiscated so that the rebels had to take up farming. Other Khitan and [[Kumo Xi|Xi]] cavalry units had been incorporated into the Jin army. Because these internal uprisings had severely weakened the Jin's capacity to confront the Southern Song militarily, the Jin court under Emperor Shizong began negotiating for peace. The [[Treaty of Lóngxīng]] (隆興和議) was signed in 1164 and ushered over 40 years of peace between the two empires.

[[Image:Wood Bodhisattva 2.jpg|thumb|left|200px|A wooden [[Bodhisattva]] statue, Jin Dynasty, [[Shanghai Museum]].]]
In the early 1180s Emperor Shìzōng instituted a restructuring of 200 ''meng'an'' units to remove tax abuses and help Jurchens. Communal farming was encouraged. The Jin empire prospered and had a large surplus of grain in reserve. Although learned in Chinese classics, Shizong was also known as a promoter of [[Jurchen language]] and culture; during his reign, a number of Chinese classics were translated into Jurchen, the Imperial Jurchen Academy was founded, and the [[Imperial examination]]s started to be offered in the Jurchen language.&lt;ref name=tao69&gt;Tao (1976), Chapter 6. &quot;The Jurchen Movement for Revival&quot;, Pages 69-83.&lt;/ref&gt; Shizong's reign (1161–1189) was remembered by the posterity as the time of comparative peace and prosperity, and the emperor himself was compared to the legendary [[Yao (ruler)|Yao]] and [[Shun (Chinese leader)|Shun]]&lt;ref name=tao69/&gt;

Shìzōng's grandson, [[Emperor Zhāngzōng]] (章宗) (r. 1189–1208) venerated Jurchen values, but he also immersed himself in Chinese culture and married an ethnic Han woman. The ''[[Taihe Code of law]]'' was promulgated in 1201 and was based mostly on the [[Tang Code]]. In 1207 the Song tried to invade, but the Jin forces effectively repulsed them. In the peace agreement the Song had to pay higher annual indemnities and behead [[Han Tuozhou|Hán Tūozhòu]] (韩侂胄), the leader of their war party.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chinaknowledge.de/History/Song/song-event.html Chinese History - Song Dynasty 宋 event history (www.chinaknowledge.de)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fall of Jin===
{{Main|Mongol-Jin War}}
{{History of Manchuria}}
Starting from the early 13th century the Jin Dynasty began to feel the pressure of [[Mongol]]s from the north. [[Genghis Khan]] first led the Mongols into [[Western Xia]] territory in 1205 and ravaged them four years later. In 1211 about 50,000 Mongols on horses invaded the Jin Empire and began absorbing Khitan and Jurchen rebels. The Jin army had a half million men with 150,000 cavalry but abandoned the “western capital” [[Datong]] (see also [[Badger's Mount Campaign]]). The next year the Mongols went north and looted the Jin &quot;eastern capital&quot;, and in 1213 they besieged the &quot;central capital&quot;, [[Zhongdu]] (Beijing). In 1214 the Jin made a humiliating treaty but retained the capital. That summer, Jin [[Emperor Xuānzōng]] (宣宗) abandoned the central capital and moved the government to the &quot;southern capital&quot; of Kaifeng, making it the official seat of Jin Dynasty power. In 1216 a war faction persuaded Xuānzōng to attack the Song, but in 1219 they were defeated at the same place by the [[Yangtze River]], where Prince Hǎilíng had been defeated in 1161. The Jin now faced a two front war which they could not afford. Furthermore, the Jin [[Emperor Āizōng]] (哀宗) won a succession struggle against his brother and then quickly ended the war and went back to the capital. He made peace with the [[Tanguts]], who had been allied with the Mongols. Genghis Khan died in 1227 while his armies were conquering the [[Western Xia Dynasty]]. His son [[Ögedei Khan]] invaded the Jin Empire in 1232 with assistance from the [[Southern Song]]. The Jurchens tried to resist; but when Kaifeng was attacked, Āizōng fled south. An allied army of Song and Mongols looted the capital in 1233, and the next year Āizōng committed suicide to avoid being captured, ending the Jin dynasty in 1234.&lt;ref name=&quot;multiref1&quot;/&gt; The territory of the Jin was to be divided between the Mongols and the Song. However, due to lingering territorial disputes, the Song and the Mongols eventually went to war with one another over these territories.

[[Image:Chenglingpagodazhengding.jpg|thumb|left|200px|The Chengling Pagoda of [[Zhengding]], [[Hebei]] province, built between 1161 and 1189 AD.]]

In ''Empire of The Steppes'', [[René Grousset]] reports that the Mongols were always amazed at the valor of the Jin warriors, who held out until seven years after the death of [[Genghis Khan]].

==The Jin military==

Contemporary Chinese writers ascribed Jurchen success in overwhelming the Liao and Northern Song mainly to their cavalry. Already during [[Wanyan Aguda|Aguda]]'s rebellion against the Liao, all Jurchen fighters were mounted. It was said that the Jurchen cavalry tactics were a carryover from their hunting skills.&lt;ref name=tao21&gt;Tao (1976),  Chapter 2. &quot;The Rise of the Chin Dynasty&quot;, Pages 21-24.&lt;/ref&gt;
Jurchen horsemen were provided with heavy armor; on occasions, they would use a team of horses attached to each other with chains (拐子马, ''guaizi ma'')&lt;ref name=tao21/&gt;

As the Liao Empire fell apart and the Song retreated beyond the [[Yangtze]], the army of the new Jin Dynasty absorbed many soldiers who formerly fought for the Liao or Song.&lt;ref name=tao21/&gt; The new Jin empire adopted many of the Song's weapons, including various machines for [[siege warfare]] and [[artillery]]. In fact, the Jin use of cannons, grenades, and even rockets to defend besieged [[Kaifeng]] against the Mongols in 1233 is considered the first ever battle in human history in which gunpowder was used effectively, even though it failed to prevent the eventual Jin defeat.&lt;ref name=tao21/&gt;

On the other hand, Jin Empire was not particularly good at naval warfare. Both in 1129–30 and in 1161 Jin forces were defeated by the [[Southern Song Dynasty|Southern Song]] navies when trying to cross the Yangtze River into the core [[Southern Song Dynasty|Southern Song]] territory (see [[Battle of Tangdao]] and [[Battle of Caishi]]), even though for the latter campaign the Jin had equipped a large navy of their own, using Chinese shipbuildiers and even Chinese captains who had defected from the Southern Song.&lt;ref name=tao21/&gt;

In 1130 the Jin army reached Hangzhou and Ningbo in southern China. But heavy Chinese resistance and the geography of the area halted the Jin advance, and they were forced retreat and withdraw, and they had not been able to escape the Song navy when trying to return until they were directed by a Chinese defector who helped them escape in [[Zhenjiang|Chenkiang]]. Southern China was then cleared of the Jurchen forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |accessdate=14 December 2011|quote=The emperor Kao-tsung had taken flight to Ningpo (then known as Mingchow) and later to the port of Wenchow, south of Chekiang. From Nanking the Kin general Wu-chu hastened in pursuit and captured Hangchow and Ningpo (end of 1129 and beginning of 1130. However, the Kin army, consisting entirely of cavalry, had ventured too far into this China of the south with its flooded lands, intersecting rivers, paddy fields and canals, and dense population which harassed and encircled it. We-chu, leader of the Kin troops, sought to return north but was halted by the Yangtze, now wide as a sea and patrolled by Chinese flotillas. At last a traitor showed him how he might cross the river near Chenkiang, east of Nanking (1130).|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=CHzGvqRbV_IC&amp;pg=PA137&amp;dq=The+emperor+Kao-tsung+had+taken+flight+to+Ningpo+(then+known+as+Mingchow)+and+later+to+the+port+of+Wenchow,+south+of+Chekiang.+From+Nanking+the+Kin+general+Wu-chu+hastened+in+pursuit+and+captured+Hangchow+and+Ningpo+(end+of+1129+and+beginning+of+1130.+However,+the+Kin+army,+consisting+entirely+of+cavalry,+had+ventured+too+far+into+this+China+of+the+south+with+its+flooded+lands,+intersecting+rivers,+paddy+fields+and+canals,+and+dense+population+which+harassed+and+encircled+it.+We-chu,+leader+of+the+Kin+troops,+sought+to+return+north&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Wk8ST_fpIsHd0QGV5OzHAw&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20emperor%20Kao-tsung%20had%20taken%20flight%20to%20Ningpo%20(then%20known%20as%20Mingchow)%20and%20later%20to%20the%20port%20of%20Wenchow%2C%20south%20of%20Chekiang.%20From%20Nanking%20the%20Kin%20general%20Wu-chu%20hastened%20in%20pursuit%20and%20captured%20Hangchow%20and%20Ningpo%20(end%20of%201129%20and%20beginning%20of%201130.%20However%2C%20the%20Kin%20army%2C%20consisting%20entirely%20of%20cavalry%2C%20had%20ventured%20too%20far%20into%20this%20China%20of%20the%20south%20with%20its%20flooded%20lands%2C%20intersecting%20rivers%2C%20paddy%20fields%20and%20canals%2C%20and%20dense%20population%20which%20harassed%20and%20encircled%20it.%20We-chu%2C%20leader%20of%20the%20Kin%20troops%2C%20sought%20to%20return%20north&amp;f=false|title=The Empire of the Steppes: A History of Central Asia|author=René Grousset|editor=|edition=reprint, illustrated|volume=|series=|year=1970|location=|publisher=Rutgers University Press|language=|isbn=0-8135-1304-9|page=137|pages=|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |accessdate=14 December 2011|quote=Nanking and Hangchow were taken by assault in 1129 and in 1130 the Jürchen ventured as far as Ning-po, in the north-eastern tip of Chekiang.|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jqb7L-pKCV8C&amp;q=ning+po#v=snippet&amp;q=ventured%20ning%20po%20north-eastern%20Chekiang&amp;f=false|title=A history of Chinese civilization|author=Jacques Gernet|editor=|edition=2, illustrated, revised|volume=|series=|year=1996|location= |publisher=Cambridge University Press|language=|isbn=0-521-49781-7|page=357|pages=|}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
===Rise of the Manchus===
{{Expand section|date=October 2009}}
After thirty years of struggle, the Jurchen chief [[Nurhaci]] (努爾哈赤) combined the three Jurchen tribes and founded the [[Qing Dynasty|Later Jin Dynasty]] (1616–1636). Nurhaci's eighth son and heir, [[Huang Taiji|Huáng Tàijí]] (皇太極), later changed the name of his people from [[Jurchen people|Jurchen]] to [[Manchu people|Manchu]] in 1635. The next year, he changed the name of the Later Jin to [[Qing Dynasty|Qing]] in 1636.

== List of Jin Dynasty Emperors ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;auto&quot;
|+'''Sovereigns of Jin Dynasty 1115–1234'''
|-
!Temple Name&lt;br&gt;[[Miao Hao]]&lt;br&gt;廟號&lt;br&gt;miàohào
!Posthumous Name&lt;br&gt;[[Shi Hao]]&lt;br&gt;諡號&lt;br&gt;shìhào
!Birth Name&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;姓名&lt;br&gt;xìngmíng
!Years of&lt;br&gt;Reign
!Era Name&lt;br&gt;[[Nian Hao]]&lt;br&gt;年號&lt;br&gt;niánhào&lt;br&gt;and Years
|-
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; | ''Convention: &quot;Jin&quot; + temple name or posthumous name''
|-
|[[Emperor Taizu of Jin|Tàizǔ]]&lt;br&gt;太祖
|(1)
|Wányán Āgǔdǎ&lt;br&gt;完顏阿骨打&lt;br&gt;''or''&lt;br&gt;Wányán Min&lt;br&gt;完顏旻
|1115–1123
|
Shōuguó (收國, 1115–1116)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Tiānfǔ (天輔, 1117–1123)
|-
|[[Emperor Taizong of Jin|Tàizōng]]&lt;br&gt;太宗
|(1)
|Wányán Wúqǐmǎi&lt;br&gt;完顏吳乞買&lt;br&gt;''or''&lt;br&gt;Wányán Shèng&lt;br&gt;完顏晟
|1123–1135
|Tiānhuì (天會, 1123–1135)
|-
|[[Emperor Xizong of Jin|Xīzōng]]&lt;br&gt;熙宗
|(1)
|Wányán Hélá&lt;br&gt;完顏合剌&lt;br&gt;''or''&lt;br&gt;Wányán Dǎn&lt;br&gt;完顏亶
|1135–1149
|
Tiānhuì (天會, 1135–1138)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Tiānjuàn (天眷, 1138–1141)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Huángtǒng (皇統, 1141–1149)
|-
|(2)
|[[Emperor Hailingwang of Jin|Hǎilíngwáng]]&lt;br&gt;海陵王&lt;br&gt;
|Wányán Dígǔnǎi &lt;br&gt;完顏迪古乃&lt;br&gt;''or''&lt;br&gt;Wányán Liàng&lt;br&gt;完顏亮
|1149–1161
|
Tiāndé (天德, 1149–1153)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Zhènyuán (貞元, 1153–1156)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Zhènglóng (正隆, 1156–1161)
|-
|[[Emperor Shizong of Jin|Shìzōng]]&lt;br&gt;世宗
|(1)
|Wányán Wūlù &lt;br&gt;完顏烏祿&lt;br&gt;''or''&lt;br&gt;Wányán Yōng&lt;br&gt;完顏雍
|1161–1189
|Dàdìng (大定, 1161–1189)
|-
|[[Emperor Zhangzong of Jin|Zhāngzōng]]&lt;br&gt;章宗
|(1)
|Wányán Jǐng&lt;br&gt;完顏璟
|1189–1208
|Míngchāng (明昌, 1190–1196)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Chéng'ān (承安, 1196–1200)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Tàihé (泰和, 1200–1208)
|-
|(2)
|[[Emperor Weishaowang of Jin|Wèishàowáng]]&lt;br&gt;衛紹王&lt;br&gt;''or''&lt;br&gt;Wèiwáng&lt;br&gt;衛王
|Wányán Yǒngjì&lt;br&gt;完顏永濟
|1208–1213
|Dà'ān&lt;br&gt;大安 &lt;br&gt;1209-1212&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Chóngqìng&lt;br&gt;崇慶&lt;br&gt;1212-1213&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Zhìníng&lt;br&gt;至寧&lt;br&gt;1213
|-
|[[Emperor Xuanzong of Jin|Xuānzōng]]&lt;br&gt;宣宗
|(1)
|Wányán Xún&lt;br&gt;完顏珣
|1213–1224
|Zhēnyòu&lt;br&gt;貞祐&lt;br&gt;1213-1217&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Xīngdìng&lt;br&gt;興定&lt;br&gt;1217-1222&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Yuánguāng&lt;br&gt;元光&lt;br&gt;1222-1224
|-
|[[Emperor Aizong of Jin|Āizōng]]&lt;br&gt;哀宗
|(1)
|Wányán Shǒuxù&lt;br&gt;完顏守緒
|1224–1234
|Zhèngdà&lt;br&gt;正大&lt;br&gt;1224-1232&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Kāixīng&lt;br&gt;開興&lt;br&gt;1232&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
Tiānxīng&lt;br&gt;天興&lt;br&gt;1232-1234
|-
|(2)&lt;br&gt;
|[[Emperor Modi of Jin|Mòdì]]&lt;br&gt;末帝
|Wányán Chénglín&lt;br&gt;完顏承麟
|1234
|(2)
|}

(1) Quite long and thus not used when referring to this sovereign.&lt;br&gt;
(2) Did not exist

==See also==
*[[Puxian Wannu]]
*[[Chinese_emperors_family_tree_(middle)#Jin_Dynasty|Jurchen Jin emperors family tree]]
*[[Korean-Jurchen wars]]

==Literature==
* [[Jing-shen Tao]], &quot;The Jurchen in Twelfth-Century China&quot;. University of Washington Press, 1976, ISBN 0-295-95514-7.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)}}
*[http://www.uglychinese.org/jurchen.htm Jin-Song relations]

{{S-start}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Dynasties in Chinese history]]|before=[[Liao Dynasty]]|after=[[Mongol Empire]]|years=1115-1234}}
{{s-end}}

[[Category:States and territories established in 1115]]
[[Category:Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)|*]]
[[Category:1234 disestablishments]]
[[Category:12th century in China]]
[[Category:13th century in China]]

{{Link GA|zh}}
{{Link FA|zh}}

[[ar:أسرة جين]]
[[cs:Říše Ťin (1115-1234)]]
[[da:Jin-dynastiet (1115-1234)]]
[[de:Jin-Dynastie (1125–1234)]]
[[es:Dinastía Jin (1115-1234)]]
[[fa:دودمان کین (۱۲۳۴–۱۱۱۵)]]
[[fr:Dynastie Jin (1115-1234)]]
[[ko:금나라]]
[[hi:जिन राजवंश (१११५–१२३४)]]
[[id:Dinasti Jin (1115-1234)]]
[[it:Dinastia Jīn]]
[[kk:Цзинь әулеті (1115 — 1234)]]
[[hu:Csin-dinasztia (1115–1234)]]
[[ms:Dinasti Jin, 1115–1234]]
[[mn:Алтан улс]]
[[nl:Jin-dynastie (1115-1234)]]
[[ja:金 (王朝)]]
[[no:Jin-dynastiet (1115–1234)]]
[[oc:Dinastia Jin (1115-1234)]]
[[pl:Dynastia Jin (1115-1234)]]
[[pt:Dinastia Jin (1115-1234)]]
[[ru:Династия Цзинь (1115—1234)]]
[[simple:Jin Dynasty]]
[[fi:Jin-dynastia]]
[[sv:Jindynastin (jurchen)]]
[[th:ราชวงศ์จิน]]
[[tr:Kin Hanedanı (1115-1234)]]
[[uk:Династія Цзінь]]
[[vi:Nhà Kim]]
[[zh-classical:金朝]]
[[wuu:金国]]
[[zh-yue:金朝]]
[[zh:金朝]]</text>
      <sha1>orrhpgcpm5gyxc9si0l33rk0xqylqdy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
