<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Liberal Wars</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>183729</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520200411</id>
      <parentid>512004800</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T02:09:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cristiano Tomás</username>
        <id>12157539</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10916">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Liberal Wars
| partof   = 
| campaign = 
| image    = [[File:Battle of Ferreira Bridge.jpg|300px]]
| caption  = [[Battle of Ponte Ferreira|Battle of Ferreira Bridge]], 23 July 1832
| date     = 1828 to 1834
| place    = Portugal
| result   = Liberal victory, [[Concession of Evoramonte]]:
*Constitutional monarchy is restored.
*Dom Miguel renounces all his claims to the throne and goes into exile.
| combatant1  = [[File:Flag Portugal (1830).svg|25px|border]] [[Maria II of Portugal|Portugal supporting Maria II]]&lt;br /&gt;
'''Supported by:'''
*{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]
*{{flagicon|France}} [[July Monarchy|France]] (from 1830)
*{{flagicon|Spain|1785}} [[Spain]] (from 1834)
| combatant2  = [[File:Flag Portugal (1707).svg|25px|border]] [[Miguelites|Portugal supporting Miguel I]]
'''Supported by:'''
*{{flagicon|Spain|1785}} [[Spain]] (until 1833)
| commander1  = [[File:Flag Portugal (1830).svg|25px|border]] [[Pedro I of Brazil|Dom Pedro]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag Portugal (1830).svg|25px|border]] [[António José Severim de Noronha, 1st Duke of Terceira|Duke of Terceira]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag Portugal (1830).svg|25px|border]] [[João Carlos Saldanha de Oliveira Daun, 1st Duke of Saldanha|Marshal Saldanha]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag Portugal (1830).svg|25px|border]] [[Charles Napier]] 
| commander2  = [[File:Flag Portugal (1707).svg|25px|border]] [[Miguel of Portugal|Dom Miguel]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag Portugal (1707).svg|25px|border]] [[Luís Vaz Pereira Pinto Guedes|Viscount of Montalegre]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag Portugal (1707).svg|25px|border]] [[Manuel Gregório de Sousa Pereira de Sampaio, 1st Viscount of Santa Marta|Viscount of Santa Marta]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Flag Portugal (1707).svg|25px|border]]Manuel António Marreiros
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Liberal Wars}}
}}
The '''Liberal Wars''', also known as the '''Portuguese Civil War''', the '''War of the Two Brothers''', or '''Miguelite War''', was a war between progressive constitutionalists and [[authoritarian]] absolutists in [[Portugal]] over royal succession that lasted from 1828 to 1834. Embroiled parties included [[Kingdom of Portugal|Portugal]], Portuguese rebels, the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]], [[July Monarchy|France]], the [[Catholic Church]] and [[Spain]].

==Roots of the conflict==
[[File:Liberal Wars.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Great Britain holds the crown of Miguel on his head, who is supported by France while an upset Pedro crosses his arms]]
The death of King [[John VI of Portugal|João VI]] in 1826 created a dispute over royal succession. While Dom [[Pedro I of Brazil|Pedro]], the Emperor of Brazil, was the king's oldest son, his younger brother [[Miguel of Portugal|Miguel]] contended that Pedro had forfeited his claim to the throne by declaring Brazilian independence. Pedro briefly assumed the title of [[Dom (title)|Dom]] Pedro IV of Portugal. Neither the Portuguese nor the Brazilians wanted a unified monarchy; consequently, Pedro abdicated the Portuguese crown in favor of his daughter, [[Dona]] [[Maria da Glória of Portugal|Maria da Glória]], a child of seven, on the condition that when of age she would marry Miguel. In April 1826, as part of the succession settlement, Pedro revised the [[constitution]] granted in 1822, the first constitution of Portugal, and left the throne to Maria, with his sister [[Isabella Maria of Portugal|Isabella Maria]] as [[regent]].

==A new constitution==
In the Portuguese Constitutional Charter, Pedro attempted to reconcile absolutists and liberals by allowing both factions a role in the government. Unlike the Constitution of 1822, this new document established four branches of government. The [[Legislature]] was divided into two chambers. The upper chamber, the [[Chamber of Peers (Portugal)|Chamber of Peers]], was composed of life and hereditary peers and clergy appointed by the king. The lower chamber, the Chamber of Deputies, was composed of 111 deputies elected to four-year terms by the indirect vote of local assemblies, which in turn were elected by a limited suffrage of male tax-paying property owners. Judicial power was exercised by the courts; executive power by the ministers of the government; and moderative power by the king, who held an absolute veto over all legislation.

==Discontent==
[[File:Batalha da Praia da Vitória.jpg|thumb|left|300px|[[Battle of Praia Bay]], 11 August 1829]]
The absolutist party of the landowners and the [[Roman Catholicism in Portugal|Church]], however, were not satisfied with this compromise, and they continued to regard Miguel as the legitimate successor to the throne on the grounds that according to the Portuguese succession rules (approved by the [[Portuguese Cortes|Cortes]] after the [[Portuguese Restoration War|1640 Restoration]]), Pedro had lost the right to the Portuguese crown, and therefore to choose a successor, when he took possession of a foreign crown ([[Brazil]]). They were alarmed by the liberal reforms that had been initiated in Spain by the detested Revolutionary French (reforms which the Portuguese feudal aristocracy had been spared) and took heart at the recent restoration of the autocratic [[Ferdinand VII of Spain|Ferdinand VII]] in Spain (1823) who was eradicating all the Napoleonic innovations. In February 1828, Miguel returned to Portugal, ostensibly to take the oath of allegiance to the Charter and assume the regency. He was immediately proclaimed king by his supporters, who pressed him to return to absolutism. A month after his return, Miguel dissolved the Chamber of Deputies and the Chamber of Peers and, in May, summoned the traditional Cortes of the three estates of the realm to proclaim his accession to absolute power. The Cortes of 1828 assented to Miguel's wish, proclaiming him king as [[Miguel I of Portugal]] and nullifying the Constitutional Charter.

==Rebellion==
[[File:Landing of liberal forces in Oporto.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Landing of the liberal forces in Pampelido, north of [[Porto]], 8 July 1832]]
[[File:BatalhaCaboS.Vicente.jpg|thumb|left|300px|[[Battle of Cape St. Vincent (1833)|Battle of Cape St. Vincent]], 5 July 1833]]
This alleged usurpation did not go unchallenged by the Liberals. On May 18, the garrison in [[Porto]], the center of Portuguese progressives, declared its loyalty to Pedro, to Maria da Glória, and the Constitutional Charter. The rebellion against the absolutists spread to other cities. Miguel suppressed these rebellions, and many thousands of Liberals were either arrested or fled to Spain and Britain. There followed five years of repression.

Meanwhile, in [[Brazil]], relations between Pedro and Brazil's agricultural magnates had become strained. In April 1831, Pedro abdicated in Brazil in favor of his son, [[Peter II of Brazil|Pedro II]], and sailed for [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|Britain]]. He organized a military expedition there and then went to [[Terceira island]] in the [[Azores]], which was in the hands of the Liberals, to set up a government in exile. The government of Miguel blockaded the island, but the blockading squadron was attacked by a French squadron during the run-up to the [[Battle of the Tagus]], where several Miguelist ships were captured. In July 1832, with the backing of Liberals in Spain and [[England]], an expedition led by Dom Pedro landed near Porto, which the Miguelites abandoned and where, after military activities including the [[Battle of Ponte Ferreira]], Pedro and his associates were besieged by Miguelite forces for nearly a year. To protect British interests, a naval squadron under Commander [[William Glascock]] in [[HMS Orestes|HMS ''Orestes'']] was stationed in the [[Douro]], where it came under fire from both sides.

In June 1833, the Liberals, still encircled at Porto, sent to the [[Algarve]] a force commanded by the [[António José Severim de Noronha, 1st Duke of Terceira|Duke of Terceira]] supported by a naval squadron commanded by [[Charles Napier (naval officer)|Charles Napier]], using the alias 'Carlos de Ponza'. The Duke of Terceira landed at [[Faro, Portugal|Faro]] and marched north through the [[Alentejo]] to capture Lisbon on July 24. Meanwhile Napier's squadron encountered the absolutists' fleet near [[Cape Saint Vincent]] (''Cabo São Vicente'') and decisively defeated it at the fourth [[Battle of Cape St. Vincent (1833)|Battle of Cape St. Vincent]]. The Liberals were able to occupy Lisbon, where Pedro moved from Porto and repulsed a Miguelite siege. A stalemate of nine months ensued. Towards the end of 1833, Maria da Glória was proclaimed queen, and Dom Pedro was made regent. His first act was to confiscate the property of all who had served under Dom Miguel. He also suppressed all religious houses and confiscated their property, an act that suspended friendly relations with Rome for nearly eight years, until mid-1841. The absolutists controlled the rural areas, where they were supported by the aristocracy, and by a peasantry that was galvanized by the Church. The Liberals occupied Portugal's major cities, Lisbon and Porto, where they commanded a sizable following among the middle classes. Operations against the [[Miguelites]] began again in earnest in early 1834. Meanwhile, the Liberal army had suffered a sound defeat at [[Alcácer do Sal]], which proved that, despite the Duke of Terceira's recent march from Faro to Lisbon, the south was still loyal to the Miguelites.

==Peace==
The [[Battle of Asseiceira]], fought on May 16, 1834, was the last and decisive engagement of the Portuguese Civil War.  The Migueliste army was still formidable (about 18,000 men), but on May 24, 1834, at [[Evoramonte]], a peace was declared under a concession by which [[Miguel I of Portugal|Dom Miguel]] formally renounced all claims to the throne of [[Portugal]], was guaranteed an annual pension, and was definitively exiled. [[Pedro IV of Portugal|Dom Pedro]] restored the Constitutional Charter, but he died September 24, 1834.

Maria da Glória resumed her interrupted reign as [[Maria II of Portugal]].

==References==
*{{loc}}

{{Portuguese Monarchy Topics}}
{{Portugal topics}}

[[Category:1820s conflicts]]
[[Category:1830s conflicts]]
[[Category:Wars involving France]]
[[Category:Wars involving Portugal]]
[[Category:Wars involving Spain]]
[[Category:Wars involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Wars of succession]]
[[Category:19th century in Portugal]]
[[Category:Civil wars involving the states and peoples of Europe]]
[[Category:Liberalism in Portugal]]
[[Category:Liberal Wars]]

[[de:Miguelistenkrieg]]
[[es:Guerras Liberales]]
[[fr:Guerre civile portugaise]]
[[it:Guerre Liberali]]
[[ja:ポルトガル内戦]]
[[pt:Guerra Civil Portuguesa]]
[[ru:Мигелистские войны]]
[[sv:Liberala krigen]]</text>
      <sha1>n93g7e9sejldsh2met13tvr6pwa97x8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
