<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Meiji Restoration</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27751221</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522051162</id>
      <parentid>520405905</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T19:36:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BD2412</username>
        <id>196446</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>per [[WP:INTDABLINK]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25569">{{History of Japan|MeijiJoukyou.jpg|Image explanation = The Meiji Emperor,&lt;br&gt; moving from [[Kyoto]] to [[Tokyo]], end of 1868.}}
The {{Nihongo|'''Meiji Restoration'''|明治維新|Meiji Ishin}}, also known as the ''Meiji Ishin'', ''Revolution'', ''Reform'' or ''Renewal'', was a chain of events that restored imperial rule to Japan in 1868 under [[Emperor Meiji]]. The goals of the restored government were expressed by the new emperor in the [[Charter Oath]]. The Restoration led to enormous changes in Japan's political and social structure, and spanned both the late [[Edo period]] (often called [[Late Tokugawa shogunate]]) and the beginning of the [[Meiji period]]. The period spanned from 1868 to 1912 and was responsible for the emergence of Japan as a modernised nation in the early twentieth century.

==Alliances and allegiances==
The formation in 1866 of the [[Satchō Alliance|Satsuma-Chōshū Alliance]] between [[Saigō Takamori]], the leader of the [[Satsuma domain]], and [[Kido Takayoshi]], the leader of the [[Chōshū Domain|Chōshū]] domain, built the foundation of the Meiji restoration.  These two leaders supported the [[Emperor Kōmei]] ([[Emperor Meiji]]'s father) and were brought together by [[Sakamoto Ryōma]] for the purpose of challenging the ruling [[Tokugawa Shogunate]] (''bakufu'') and restoring the Emperor to power. On February 3, 1867, Emperor Meiji ascended the throne after Emperor Kōmei's death on January 30, 1867. This period also saw Japan change from being a [[feudal]] society to having a market economy and left the Japanese with a lingering Western influence.

==End of the Shogunate==
{{Main|Bakumatsu}}
The Tokugawa Shogunate came to its official end on November 9, 1867, when [[Tokugawa Yoshinobu]], the 15th Tokugawa Shogun, &quot;put his prerogatives at the Emperor's disposal&quot; and resigned 10 days later. This was effectively the &quot;restoration&quot; (''Taisei Hōkan'') of imperial rule – although Yoshinobu still had significant influence and it was not until January 3, the following year, with the young emperor's edict that the restoration fully occurred.&lt;ref&gt;''One can date the &quot;restoration&quot; of imperial rule from the edict of 3 January 1868.'' Jansen (2000), p.334.&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly thereafter in January 1868, the [[Boshin War]] (War of the Year of the Dragon) started with the [[Battle of Toba-Fushimi]] in which Chōshū and [[Satsuma Domain|Satsuma]]'s forces defeated the ex-shogun's army. This forced (or allowed) Emperor Meiji to strip Yoshinobu of all power, setting the stage for official restoration. On January 3, 1868, the Emperor made a formal declaration of the restoration of his power:

{{quote|The Emperor of Japan announces to the sovereigns of all foreign countries and to their subjects that permission has been granted to the [[Shogun]] Tokugawa Yoshinobu to return the governing power in accordance with his own request. We shall henceforward exercise supreme authority in all the internal and external affairs of the country. Consequently the title of Emperor must be substituted for that of [[Taikun]], in which the treaties have been made. Officers are being appointed by us to the conduct of foreign affairs. It is desirable that the representatives of the treaty powers recognize this announcement.|January 3, 1868 &lt;br&gt;[[Mutsuhito]]|&lt;ref&gt;Quoted and translated in &quot;A Diplomat In Japan&quot;, [[Sir Ernest Satow]], p.353, ISBN 978-1-933330-16-7&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Some shogunate forces escaped to [[Hokkaidō]], where they attempted to set up a breakaway [[Republic of Ezo]]; however, forces loyal to the Emperor ended this attempt in May 1869 with the [[Battle of Hakodate]] in Hokkaidō. The defeat of the armies of the former shogun (led by [[Enomoto Takeaki]] and [[Hijikata Toshizō]]) marked the final end of the Tokugawa Shogunate, with the Emperor's power fully restored.

The growth of vassals later held inherited lands and provided military service and homage to their lords after the defeat of the armies. The Bakuhan Taisei split feudal power between the shogunate in Edo and provincial domains throughout Japan. Provinces had a degree of sovereignty and were allowed an independent administration of the Han in exchange for loyalty to the Shogun, who was responsible for foreign relations and national security. The shogun and lords were all daimyo: feudal lords with their own bureaucracies, policies, and territories. The Shogun also administered the most powerful han, the hereditary fief of the House of Tokugawa. Each level of government administered its own system of taxation.

== Motives ==
[[File:Teenager Meiji Emperor with foreign representatives 1868 1870.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|left|A teenaged [[Meiji Emperor]] with foreign representatives at the end of the [[Boshin War]], 1868-1870.]]
There were many causes to the Meiji Restoration. The Japanese knew that they were behind the rest of the world when American [[Commodore (United States)|Commodore]] [[Matthew C. Perry]] came to Japan to try to issue a treaty that would open up Japanese ports to trade. Perry came to Japan in [[Black Ships|large warships]] with armament and technology that far outclassed those of Japan at the time. The leaders of the Meiji Restoration, as this revolution came to be known, acted in the name of restoring imperial rule in order to strengthen Japan against the threat represented by the colonial powers of the day. The word &quot;Meiji&quot; means &quot;enlightened rule&quot; and the goal was to combine &quot;western advances&quot; with the traditional, &quot;eastern&quot; values.&lt;ref&gt;Hunt, Lynn, Thomas R. Martin, Barbara H. Rosenwein, R. Po-chia Hsia et al.. The Making of the West, Peoples and Cultures. Vol. C. 3rd ed. Boston: Bedford/ St. Martin's, 2009. 712-13.&lt;/ref&gt; The main leaders of this were: [[Itō Hirobumi]], [[Matsukata Masayoshi]], [[Kido Takayoshi]], [[Itagaki Taisuke]], [[Yamagata Aritomo]], [[Mori Arinori]], [[Ōkubo Toshimichi]], and [[Yamaguchi Naoyoshi]].  Under the leadership of [[Mori Arinori]], a group of prominent Japanese intellectuals went on to form the [[Meirokusha|Meiji Six Society]] in 1873 in order to continue to &quot;promote civilization and enlightenment&quot; through western ethics and ideas. However, during the restoration, political power simply moved from the [[Tokugawa Shogunate]] to an [[oligarchy]] consisting of these leaders, mostly from the [[Satsuma Province]] ([[Ōkubo Toshimichi]] and [[Saigō Takamori]]), and [[Chōshū Province]] ([[Itō Hirobumi]], [[Yamagata Aritomo]], and Kido Takayoshi). This reflected their belief in the more traditional practice of imperial rule, whereby the [[Tenno|Emperor of Japan]] serves solely as the spiritual authority of the nation and his ministers govern the nation in his name.

== Effects ==
{{Main|Meiji Period|Government of Meiji Japan|Meiji Constitution|Abolition of the han system}}
[[File:The New fighting the Old in early Meiji Japan circa 1870.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|Allegory of the New fighting the Old in early Meiji Japan, circa 1870.]]
The Meiji Restoration accelerated [[industrialization]] in Japan, which led to its rise as a military power by the year 1905, under the slogan of {{Nihongo|&quot;Enrich the country, strengthen the military&quot;|富国強兵|[[fukoku kyōhei]]}}.

The [[Meiji oligarchy]] that formed the government under the rule of the Emperor first introduced measures to consolidate their power against the remnants of the Edo period government, the shogunate, [[daimyo]], and the [[samurai]] class.

In 1868, all Tokugawa lands were seized and placed under &quot;imperial control&quot;, thus placing them under the prerogative of the new Meiji government. In 1869, the daimyo of the [[Tosa Domain|Tosa]], [[Hizen Domain|Hizen]], Satsuma and [[Chōshū domain]]s, who were pushing most fiercely against the shogunate, were persuaded to 'return their domains to the Emperor'. Other daimyo were subsequently persuaded to do so, thus creating, arguably for the first time, a central government in Japan which exercised direct power through the entire 'realm' ([[Tianxia#Japan|天下]]).

Finally, in 1871, the daimyo, past and present, were summoned before the Emperor, where it was declared that [[abolition of the han system|all domains were now to be returned to the Emperor]]. The roughly 300 domains (han) were turned into prefectures, each under the control of a state-appointed governor. By 1888, several prefectures had been merged in several steps to reduce their number to 75. The daimyo were promised 1/10 of their fiefs' income as private income. Later, their debts and payments of samurai stipends were to be taken over by the state.

The oligarchs also endeavoured to abolish the [[four divisions of society]].

[[File:Tokyo hoheikosho.jpg|thumb|The [[Tokyo]] [[Koishikawa Arsenal]] was established in 1871.]]
Throughout Japan at the time, the samurai numbered 1.9 million.  (For comparison, this was more than 10 times the size of the French privileged class before the 1789 [[French Revolution]].  Moreover, the samurai in Japan were not merely the lords, but also their higher retainers—people who actually worked.) With each samurai being paid fixed stipends, their upkeep presented a tremendous financial burden, which may have prompted the oligarchs to action. Whatever their true intentions, the oligarchs embarked on another slow and deliberate process to abolish the samurai class. First, in 1873, it was announced that the samurai stipends were to be taxed on a rolling basis. Later, in 1874, the samurai were given the option to convert their stipends into government bonds. Finally, in 1876, this commutation was made compulsory.

To reform the military, the government instituted nationwide conscription in 1873, mandating that every male would serve in the armed forces upon turning 21 for four years; followed by three more years in the reserves. One of the primary differences between the samurai and peasant class was the right to bear arms; this ancient privilege was suddenly extended to every male in the nation. Furthermore, samurai were no longer allowed to walk about town bearing a sword or weapon to show their status as in former times.

This led to a series of riots from disgruntled samurai. One of the major riots was the one led by Saigō Takamori, the [[Satsuma Rebellion]], which eventually turned into a civil war. This rebellion was, however, put down swiftly by the newly formed [[Imperial Japanese Army]], trained in Western tactics and weapons, even though the core of the new army was the Tokyo police force, which was largely composed of former samurai. This sent a strong message to the dissenting samurai that their time was indeed up. There were fewer subsequent samurai uprisings and the distinction became all but a name as the samurai joined the new society. The ideal of samurai military spirit lived on in romanticized form and was often used as propaganda during the early 20th century wars of the [[Empire of Japan]].

However, it is equally true that the majority of samurai were content despite having their status abolished. Many found employment in the government bureaucracy, which resembled an elite class in its own right. The samurai, being better educated than most of the population, became teachers, gun makers, government officials, or military officers. While the formal title of samurai was abolished, the elitist spirit that characterized the samurai class lived on.

The oligarchs also embarked on a series of [[Land Tax Reform (Japan 1873)|land reforms]]. In particular, they legitimized the tenancy system which had been going on during the Tokugawa period. Despite the [[bakufu]]'s best efforts to freeze the four classes of society in place, during their rule villagers had begun to lease land out to other farmers, becoming rich in the process. This greatly disrupted the clearly defined class system which the bakufu had envisaged, partly leading to their eventual downfall.

The military of Japan was also strengthened, and they showed themselves as a growing world power by winning both the [[First Sino-Japanese War|Sino-Japanese war]], and the [[Russo-Japanese war]]. The victory against Russia was the more shocking as it was the first time since the Mongol invasion of Europe that an Asian nation had obtained a major victory against a European power.

Besides drastic changes to the social structure of Japan, in an attempt to create a strong centralized state defining its national identity, the government established a dominant national dialect that replaced local and regional dialects called hyojungo, which was based on patterns of the Tokyo’s samurai classes that has eventually become the norm in the realms of education, media, government and business.&lt;ref&gt;Bestor, Theodore C. &quot;Japan.&quot; Countries and Their Cultures. Eds. Melvin
Ember and Carol Ember. Vol. 2. New York: Macmillan Reference USA, 2001. 1140-1158. 4 vols. Gale Virtual Reference Library. Gale. Pepperdine University SCELC. 23 November 2009 &lt;http://find.galegroup.com.lib.pepperdine.edu/gvrl/infomark.do?&amp;contentSet=EBKS&amp;type=retrieve&amp;tabID=T001&amp;prodId=GVRL&amp;docId=CX3401700121&amp;source=gale&amp;userGroupName=pepp12906&amp;version=1.0&gt;.
&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Industrial growth ===
The rapid industrialization and modernization of Japan both allowed and required a massive increase in production and infrastructure. Japan built industries such as shipyards, iron smelters, and spinning mills, which were then sold to well-connected entrepreneurs. Consequently, domestic companies became consumers of Western technology and applied it to produce items that would be sold cheaply in the international market. With this, industrial zones grew enormously, and there was massive migration to industrializing centers from the countryside. Industrialization additionally went hand in hand with the development of a national railway system and modern communications.&lt;ref&gt;Yamamura, Kozo. &quot;Success Iligotten? The Role of Meiji Militarism in Japan's Technological
Progress.&quot; The Journal of Economic History 37.1 (1977). Web.
&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:0; text-align:left;&quot;
|+Raw silk production and export from Japan
! Year(s)
! Production/exports, annual average (tons){{ambiguous|date=November 2011}}&lt;!-- metric, short or long --&gt;
|-
| 1868–1872 || 1026/646
|-
| 1883 || 1682/1347
|-
| 1889–1893 || 640
|-
| 1899–1903 || 7103/4098
|-
| 1909–1914 || 12460/9462
|}

With industrialization came the demand for coal. There was dramatic rise in production, as shown in the table below.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:0; text-align:left;&quot;
|+Coal production
!rowspan=2| Year
!colspan=3| Coal production 
|-
!(millions of&lt;br/&gt;metric tons)
!(millions of&lt;br/&gt;long tons)
!(millions of&lt;br/&gt;short tons)
|-
| 1875 
| {{convert|0.6|t|LT ST|disp=table}}
|-
| 1885 
| {{convert|1.2|t|LT ST|disp=table}}
|-
| 1895 
| {{convert|5|t|LT ST|disp=table}}
|-
| 1905 
| {{convert|13|t|LT ST|disp=table}}
|-
| 1913 
| {{convert|21.3|t|LT ST|disp=table}}
|}

Coal was needed for two things: steamships and railroads. The growth of these sectors is shown below.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:0; text-align:left;&quot;
|+Size of the merchant fleet
! Year
! Number of steamships
|-
| 1873 || 26
|-
| 1894 || 169
|-
| 1904 || 797
|-
| 1913 || 1514
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:0; text-align:left;&quot;
|+Length of train track
!rowspan=2| Year
!colspan=2| Track
|-
! (mi)
! (km)
|-
| 1872 
| {{convert|18|mi|km|disp=table}}
|-
| 1883 
| {{convert|240|mi|km|disp=table}}
|-
| 1887 
| {{convert|640|mi|km|disp=table}}
|-
| 1894 
| {{convert|2100|mi|km|disp=table}}
|-
| 1904 
| {{convert|4700|mi|km|disp=table}}
|-
| 1914 
| {{convert|7100|mi|km|disp=table}}
|}

== Controversy in semantics ==
{{Multiple issues|section=y|refimprove=August 2007|cleanup=November 2007}}
Ongoing debate continues between historians as to the historical legitimacy of the name &quot;restoration&quot;, as opposed to a &quot;coup&quot; or &quot;revolution&quot;. There are reasons to call it all three.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = De Bary
  | first = William Theodore
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors = Donald Keene, George Tanabe, Paul Varley
  | title = Sources of Japanese Tradition
  | publisher = Columbia University Press
  | year = 2001
  | location = New York
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn = 0-231-12984-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Advocates of the term &quot;coup&quot; would point out the fact that there was a change in only the regime, with the fighting confined to the elite, which managed to avoid being spread to the rest of society and that there was a shared sense of national mission and class values. However, this term only refers to the political leaders—not commoners. More importantly, it also does not represent the wider historical context of the period, and the various ideological struggles of the time in addition to the subsequent radical changes of society.

The direct challenge to the legitimacy of the [[Tokugawa Regime]] in 1868 identifies this event as a revolution. This term also implies an anticipation of subsequent radical changes and indicates that the regime was toppled through the combination of concerns and actions of different groups. This term is problematic because it gives the false impression that rebels had unified or coherent plans for the future and it does not account for the relatively peaceful transition or how much actually stayed the same within the country.

The events of 1868 can be viewed in terms of a restoration because the opposition made claims that the Tokugawa Shogunate had usurped the power to govern from the Emperor. This claim as well as the strictly isolationist sentiments of the times is an accurate representation of the event, in some ways. The word restoration implies a focus on the elite ideological debates but does not address the regional and religious tensions of the period. It also undervalues the strategic nature of restorationist claims and gives a false impression of unity among the rebelling houses. The most detrimental implication of this term is that it offers no concrete explanation of how ordinary people came to accept the legitimacy of direct imperial rule.

== See also ==
* [[Bakumatsu]]
* [[Land Tax Reform (Japan 1873)]]
* [[Lists of incumbents]]
* [[Meiji-era leaders]]
* [[Modernization of Japanese Military 1868–1931]]
* [[Meiji Constitution]]
* [[Restoration (disambiguation)|Restoration]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* {{Cite book
  | last =Akamatsu
  | first =Paul
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Meiji 1868: Revolution and Counter-Revolution in Japan
  | publisher =Harper &amp; Row
  | year =1972
  | location =New York
  | page = 1247
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}
* {{Cite book
  | last =[[William G. Beasley|Beasley, William G.]]
  | first =.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =The Meiji Restoration
  | publisher =Stanford University Press
  | year =1972
  | location =Stanford
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}
* {{Cite book
  | last = Beasley, William G.
  | first = 
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = The Rise of Modern Japan: Political, Economic and Social Change Since 1850
  | publisher = St. Martin's Press
  | year = 1995
  | location = New York
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}
* {{Cite book
  | last =[[Albert M. Craig|Craig, Albert M.]]
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Chōshū in the Meiji Restoration
  | publisher =Harvard University Press
  | year =1961
  | location =Cambridge
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}
* {{Cite book
  | last =[[Marius Jansen|Jansen, Marius B.]]
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =Gilbert Rozman, eds.
  | title =Japan in Transition: From Tokugawa to Meiji
  | publisher =[[Princeton University Press]]
  | year =1986
  | location =Princeton
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}
* {{Cite book
  | last =Jansen, Marius B.
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =The Making of Modern Japan
  | publisher =Harvard University Press
  | year =2000
  | location =Cambridge
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}
*{{Cite book
  | last =Murphey
  | first =Rhoads
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =East Asia: A New History
  | publisher =Addison Wesley Longman
  | year =1997
  | location =New York
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}
*{{Cite book
  | last =[[Ernest Mason Satow|Satow, Ernest Mason]]
  | first = 
  | authorlink = 
  | coauthors =
  | title =A Diplomat in Japan
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | location =
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =4-925080-28-8
}}
* {{Cite book
  | last =Wall
  | first =Rachel F.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Japan's Century: An Interpretation of Japanese History since the Eighteen-fifties
  | publisher =The Historical Association
  | year =1971
  | location =London
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =
}}
* [[John Breen (scholar)|Breen, John]], 'The Imperial Oath of April 1868: ritual, power and politics in Restoration Japan', Monumenta Nipponica,51,4 (1996)
* Francisco Barberan &amp; [[Rafael Domingo Osle]], Codigo civil japones. Estudio preliminar, traduccion y notas (2 ed. Thomsons Aranzadi, 2006).
* Harry D. Harootunian, Toward Restoration (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1970), &quot;Introduction&quot;, pp 1 – 46; on Yoshida: chapter IV &quot;The Culture of Action – Yoshida Shōin&quot;, pp 184 – 219.
* Najita Tetsuo, The Intellectual Foundations of Modern Japanese Politics (Chicago &amp; London: University of Chicago Press), chapter 3: &quot;Restorationism in Late Tokugawa&quot;, pp 43 – 68.
* H. Van Straelen, Yoshida Shōin, Forerunner of the Meiji Restoration: A Biographical Study (Leiden: E. J. Brill, 1952).
* David M. Earl, Emperor and Nation in Japan (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1972), on Yoshida: &quot;Attitude toward the Emperor/Nation&quot;, pp 161 – 192. Also pp.&amp;nbsp;82 – 105.
* Marius B Jansen, Sakamoto Ryōma and the Meiji Restoration (New York: Columbia University Press, 1994) especially chapter VIII: &quot;Restoration&quot;, pp 312 – 346.
* W. G. Beasley, The Meiji Restoration (Stanford, California: Stanford University Press, 1972), especially chapter VI: &quot;Dissenting Samurai&quot;, pp 140 – 171.
* Conrad Totman, &quot;From Reformism to Transformism, bakufu Policy 1853–1868&quot;, in: T. Najita &amp; V. J. Koshmann, Conflict in Modern Japanese History (New Jersay: Princeton University Press, 1988), pp.&amp;nbsp;62 – 80.
* Jansen, Marius B.: The Meiji Restoration, in: Jansen, Marius B. (ed.): The Cambridge history of Japan, Volume 5: The nineteenth century (New York: Cambridge UP, 1989), pp.&amp;nbsp;308–366.

*In addition, the anime &quot;Rurouni Kenshin&quot; directly deals with the aftermath of the revolution, and presents a good example of the times.

== External links ==
* [http://www.housing.com/categories/homes/japanese-meiji-period-architecture-1868-1912.html Japanese Meiji Period Architecture (1868-1912)]
* [http://aboutjapan.japansociety.org/content.cfm/the_meiji_restoration_era_1868-1889 Essay on The Meiji Restoration Era, 1868-1889] on the About Japan, A Teacher's Resource website

{{JapanEmpireNavbox}}

[[Category:Meiji Restoration| ]]
[[Category:19th century in Japan]]
[[Category:History of Japan]]
[[Category:Japanese governmental reforms]]

[[ar:استعراش مييجي]]
[[an:Restauración Meichi]]
[[ast:Restauración Meiji]]
[[zh-min-nan:Meizi Î-sin]]
[[be:Рэстаўрацыя Мэйдзі]]
[[be-x-old:Рэстаўрацыя Мэйдзі]]
[[bg:Реставрация Мейджи]]
[[bs:Revolucija Meiji]]
[[br:Adsav Meiji]]
[[ca:Restauració Meiji]]
[[cs:Reformy Meidži]]
[[cy:Adferiad y Meiji]]
[[da:Meiji-restaurationen]]
[[de:Meiji-Restauration]]
[[et:Meiji restauratsioon]]
[[el:Μεταρρύθμιση Μεΐτζι]]
[[es:Restauración Meiji]]
[[eo:Mejĝi-reformo]]
[[eu:Meiji berrezarkuntza]]
[[fa:اصلاحات میجی]]
[[hif:Meiji Restoration]]
[[fr:Restauration de Meiji]]
[[gl:Restauración Meixi]]
[[gan:明治維新]]
[[ko:메이지 유신]]
[[hi:मेइजी पुनर्स्थापन]]
[[hr:Revolucija Meiji]]
[[id:Restorasi Meiji]]
[[is:Meiji-endurreisnin]]
[[it:Rinnovamento Meiji]]
[[he:תקופת מייג'י#הרקע, העלייה לשלטון והרסטורציה]]
[[krc:Мэйдзи реставрация]]
[[ka:მეიძის რესტავრაცია]]
[[kk:Мэйдзи жаңғыртуы]]
[[la:Restauratio Meiji dicta]]
[[lv:Meidzi restaurācija]]
[[lt:Meidži restauracija]]
[[hu:Meidzsi-restauráció]]
[[ml:മീജി പുനരുദ്ധരിക്കൽ]]
[[ms:Pemulihan Meiji]]
[[nl:Meiji-restauratie]]
[[ja:明治維新]]
[[no:Meijirestaurasjonen]]
[[nn:Meijirestaurasjonen]]
[[oc:Restauracion Meiji]]
[[pnb:میجی مڑ آنا]]
[[nds:Meiji-Restauration]]
[[pl:Restauracja Meiji]]
[[pt:Restauração Meiji]]
[[ro:Restauraţia Meiji]]
[[ru:Реставрация Мэйдзи]]
[[simple:Meiji Restoration]]
[[sk:Meidži išin]]
[[sl:Obnova Meidži]]
[[sr:Revolucija Meidži]]
[[sh:Meiji revolucija]]
[[fi:Meiji-restauraatio]]
[[sv:Meijirestaurationen]]
[[tl:Pagpapanumbalik ng Meiji]]
[[ta:மெய்சி மீள்விப்பு]]
[[th:การคืนสู่ราชบัลลังก์ของจักรพรรดิเมจิ]]
[[tr:Meiji Restorasyonu]]
[[uk:Реставрація Мейджі]]
[[ur:بحالی مییجی]]
[[za:Mingzci veizsaen]]
[[vi:Minh Trị Duy tân]]
[[fiu-vro:Meiji restaurats'uun]]
[[war:Restorasyon Meiji]]
[[zh-yue:明治維新]]
[[bat-smg:Meidžė Restauracėjė]]
[[zh:明治维新]]</text>
      <sha1>o9gxymhpp33sdottz6jm4w0w2tu2edp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
