<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mesolithic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20568</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521467003</id>
      <parentid>520625370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T04:49:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.98.1.233</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Ceramic Mesolithic */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18158">[[File:OpgravingStevoort.jpg|thumb|225px|Mesolithic microliths]]
{{Mesolithic|233}}
The '''Mesolithic''' ([[Greek language|Greek]]: ''mesos'' &quot;middle&quot;, ''lithos'' &quot;stone&quot;) is an archaeological concept used to refer to specific groups of [[archaeological culture]]s defined as falling between the [[Paleolithic]] and the [[Neolithic]].
The term developed as a catch-all to refer to material that did not fit into the other categories of [[prehistory]] and after the development of [[radiocarbon dating]] the arbitrary nature of its definition has become apparent. 

The term is used to refer to different time spans in different parts of [[Eurasia]]. It was first used to refer to post-[[Holocene]] but pre-[[agricultural]] material in [[northwest Europe]] about 10,000 to 5000&amp;nbsp;BCE but is also applied to material from [[the Levant]] (about 20,000 to 9500&amp;nbsp;BCE); in [[Japan]] the [[Jōmon period]] (about 14,000 to 400&amp;nbsp;BCE) is sometimes called Mesolithic and it is also applied to some cultures from the [[Indian sub-continent]] (100,000 to 30,000&amp;nbsp;BCE). The term &quot;[[Epipaleolithic]]&quot; is often used for areas outside [[northern Europe]] but was also the preferred synonym used by French archaeologists until the 1960s.

==History of the concept==
The three -lithics are subdivisions of the [[Stone Age]] in the [[three-age system]] developed since classical times and given a modern archaeological meaning by [[Christian Jürgensen Thomsen]], a Danish archaeologist, in the early 19th century. Subdivisions of &quot;earlier&quot; and &quot;later&quot; were added to the Stone Age by Thomsen and especially his junior colleague and employee [[Jens Jacob Asmussen Worsaae]]. [[John Lubbock, 1st Baron Avebury|John Lubbock]] kept these divisions in his work ''Pre-historic Times'' in 1865 and introduced the terms [[Paleolithic]] (&quot;Old Stone Age&quot;) and [[Neolithic]] (&quot;New Stone Age&quot;) for them. He saw no need for an intermediate category.

When Hodder Westropp introduced the Mesolithic in 1866 as a technology intermediate between Paleolithic and Neolithic, a storm of controversy immediately arose around it. A British school led by [[John Evans]] denied any need for an intermediate. The ages blended together like the colors of a rainbow, he said. A European school led by [[Louis Laurent Gabriel de Mortillet]] asserted that there was a gap between the earlier and later. Edouard Piette claimed to have filled the gap with his discovery of the [[Azilian]] Culture. Knut Sterjna offered an alternative in the [[Epipaleolithic]], a continuation of the use of Paleolithic technology. By the time of [[Vere Gordon Childe]]'s work, ''The Dawn of Europe'' (1947), which affirms the Mesolithic, sufficient data had been collected to determine that the Mesolithic was in fact necessary and was indeed a transition and intermediary between the Paleolithic and the Neolithic.
&lt;ref&gt;Linder, F., 1997. ''Social differentiering i mesolitiska jägar-samlarsamhällen.'' Institutionen för arkeologi och antik historia, Uppsala universitet. Uppsala.&lt;/ref&gt;

The start and end dates of the Mesolithic vary by geographical region. Childe's recycled view prevails that the term generally covers the period between the end of the [[Pleistocene]] and the start of the Neolithic. The times of these events vary greatly; moreover, the various Mesolithics within the span might be as short as roughly a thousand years or as long as roughly 15,000 years depending on the circumstances. If the Mesolithic is more similar to the Paleolithic it is called the Epipaleolithic. The Paleolithic was an age of purely hunting and gathering while in the Neolithic domestication of plants and animals had occurred. Some Mesolithic people continued with intensive hunting. Others were practising the initial stages of domestication. Some Mesolithic settlements were villages of huts. Others were walled cities. The type of tool remains the diagnostic factor. The Mesolithic featured composite devices manufactured with Mode V chipped [[stone tool]]s. The Paleolithic had utilized Modes I-IV and the Neolithic mainly abandoned the modes in favor of polished, not chipped, stone tools.

Due to the innovation of a three-stage system for African archaeology by John Hilary Goodman and Clarence van Riet Lowe of South Africa in the early 20th century, translations of &quot;Old,&quot; &quot;Middle,&quot; and &quot;New Stone Age&quot; can no longer be used for Paleolithic, Mesolithic and Neolithic. In African archaeology, which applies only from the [[Sahara]] southward, Lower Paleolithic is replaced by &quot;Early Stone Age,&quot; Middle Paleolithic is replaced by &quot;Middle Stone Age&quot; and Upper Paleolithic by &quot;Later Stone Age.&quot; The Mesolithic and Neolithic are not recognized.

==Current terminology==
The term &quot;Mesolithic&quot; is in competition with another term, &quot;[[Epipaleolithic]]&quot;, which means the &quot;final Upper Palaeolithic industries occurring at the end of the [[last Ice Age|final glaciation]] which appear to merge technologically into the Mesolithic&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bahn, Paul, ''The Penguin Archaeology Guide'',  Penguin, London, pp. 141. ISBN 0-14-051448-1&lt;/ref&gt;

In the archaeology of [[northern Europe]], for example for archaeological sites in Great Britain, Germany, Scandinavia, Ukraine, and Russia, the term &quot;Mesolithic&quot; is almost always used. In the archaeology of other areas, the term &quot;Epipaleolithic&quot; may be preferred by most authors, or there may be divergences between authors over which term to use or what meaning to assign to each.

* Some authors use the term &quot;Epipaleolithic&quot; for those cultures that are late developments of [[hunter-gatherer]] traditions but not in transition toward [[agriculture]], reserving the term &quot;Mesolithic&quot; for those cultures, like the [[Natufian culture]], that are transitional between hunter-gatherer and agricultural practices.

* Other authors use the term Mesolithic for a variety of Late Paleolithic cultures subsequent to the end of the [[last glacial period]] whether they are transitional towards agriculture or not.

A Spanish scholar, Alfonso Moure, says in this regard:&lt;ref&gt;A. Moure ''El Origen del Hombre'', 1999. ISBN 84-7679-127-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;In the terminology of prehistoric archeology, the most widespread trend is to use the term 'Epipaleolithic' for the industrial complexes of post-glacial hunter-gatherer groups. Conversely, those that are in course of transition toward artificial food production are assigned to the 'Mesolithic.'&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==The Levant==
There are two designated periods:

'''Mesolithic 1''' (Kebara culture; 20–18,000&amp;nbsp;BCE to 12,150&amp;nbsp;BCE) followed the [[Aurignacian]] or Levantine Upper Paleolithic throughout the [[Levant]]. By the end of the Aurignacian, gradual changes took place in stone industries. Small stone tools called [[microlith]]s and retouched bladelets can be found for the first time. The microliths of this culture period differ greatly from the Aurignacian artifacts. This period is more properly called Epipaleolithic.

By 20,000 to 18,000&amp;nbsp;BCE the climate and environment had changed, starting a period of transition. The Levant became more arid and the forest vegetation retreated, to be replaced by steppe. The cool and dry period ended at the beginning of Mesolithic 1. The hunter-gatherers of the Aurignacian would have had to modify their way of living and their pattern of settlement to adapt to the changing conditions. The crystallization of these new patterns resulted in Mesolithic 1. New types of settlements and new stone industries developed.

The inhabitants of a small Mesolithic 1 site in the Levant left little more than their chipped stone tools behind. The industry was of small tools made of bladelets struck off single-platform cores. Besides bladelets, [[burin]]s and end-[[Scraper (archaeology)|scraper]]s were found. A few bone tools and some ground stone have also been found. These so-called Mesolithic sites of Asia are far less numerous than those of the Neolithic and the archeological remains are very poor.

The second period, '''Mesolithic 2''', is also called the [[Natufian culture]]. The change from Mesolithic 1 to Natufian culture can be dated more closely. The latest date from a Mesolithic 1 site in the Levant is 12,150&amp;nbsp;BCE. The earliest date from a Natufian site is 11,140&amp;nbsp;BCE.{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}} This period is characterized by the early rise of agriculture that would later emerge into the [[Neolithic]] period. 

Natufian culture is commonly split into two subperiods: [[Early Natufian]] (12,500–10,800&amp;nbsp;BCE) (Christopher Delage gives a. 13000 - 11500 [[Before Present|BP]] uncalibrated, equivalent to ca. 13,700 to 11,500&amp;nbsp;BCE)&lt;ref&gt; Delage, Christopher, ''The Last Hunter-gatherers in the Near East'', British Archaeological Reports (1 June 2004), ISBN 1-84171-389-2 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (2) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Late Natufian]] (10,800–9500&amp;nbsp;BCE). The Late Natufian most likely occurred in tandem with the [[Younger Dryas]]. [[Radiocarbon dating]] places the Natufian culture between 12,500 and 9500&amp;nbsp;BCE, just before the end of the [[Pleistocene]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Munro2003&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| last = Munro | first = Natalie D. | authorlink = | coauthors = | year = 2003 | month = | title = Small game, the Younger Dryas, and the transition to agriculture in the southern Levant | journal = Mitteilungen der Gesellschaft für Urgeschichte | volume = 12 | url = http://www.anth.uconn.edu/faculty/munro/assets/Mitteilungen.pdf| pages = 47&amp;ndash;71 |format=PDF| accessdate = | quote = }}&lt;/ref&gt; This period is characterised by the beginning of agriculture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
|last=Bar-Yosef
|first=Ofer
|year=1998
|title=The Natufian Culture in the Levant, Threshold to the Origins of Agriculture
|journal=Evolutionary Anthropology
|volume=6
|issue=5
|pages=159–177
|url=http://www.columbia.edu/itc/anthropology/v1007/baryo.pdf
|format=PDF|doi=10.1002/(SICI)1520-6505(1998)6:5&lt;159::AID-EVAN4&gt;3.0.CO;2-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest known battle occurred during the Mesolithic period at a site in Egypt known as [[Cemetery 117]].

==Europe==
[[File:Sépulture de Teviec Global.jpg|right|thumb|Two skeletons of women aged between 25 and 35 years, dated between 6740 and 5680 BP, both of whom died a violent death. Found at [[Téviec]], [[France]] in 1938.]]
The Mesolithic began with the [[Holocene]] warm period around 11,660&amp;nbsp;[[Before Present|BP]] and ended with [[Neolithic Revolution|the introduction of farming]], the date of which varied in each geographical region. Regions that experienced greater environmental effects as the [[last glacial period]] ended have a much more apparent Mesolithic era, lasting millennia. In northern Europe, for example, societies were able to live well on rich food supplies from the marshlands created by the warmer climate. Such conditions produced distinctive human behaviors that are preserved in the material record, such as the [[Maglemosian]] and [[Azilian]] cultures. Such conditions also delayed the coming of the Neolithic until as late as 5000-4000&amp;nbsp;BC in northern Europe.

As the &quot;[[Neolithic]] package&quot; (including farming, herding, polished stone axes, [[Longhouse|timber longhouse]]s and pottery) spread into Europe, the Mesolithic way of life was marginalized and eventually disappeared. Mesolithic adaptations such as sedentism, population size and use of plant foods are cited as evidence of the transition to agriculture.&lt;ref&gt;T.Douglas Price, ''Europe's first farmers'' (Cambridge University Press 2000), page 5.&lt;/ref&gt; However in north-Eastern Europe, the hunting and fishing lifestyle continued into the [[Medieval]] period in regions less suited to agriculture.

==Ceramic Mesolithic==
In North-Eastern Europe, Siberia, and certain southern European and North African sites, a &quot;ceramic Mesolithic&quot; can be distinguished between 7000-3850&amp;nbsp;BCE. Russian archaeologists prefer to describe such pottery-making cultures as Neolithic, even though farming is absent. This pottery-making Mesolithic culture can be found peripheral to the sedentary Neolithic cultures. It created a distinctive type of pottery, with  point or knob base and flared rims, manufactured by methods not used by the Neolithic farmers. Though each area of Mesolithic ceramic developed an individual style, common features suggest a single point of origin.&lt;ref&gt;De Roevers, p.162-163&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest manifestation of this type of pottery may be in the region around Lake Baikal in Siberia. It appears in the Elshan or Yelshanka or [[Samara culture]] on the Volga in Russia c. 7000&amp;nbsp;BCE,&lt;ref&gt;D. W. Anthony, Pontic-Caspian Mesolithic and Early Neolithic societies at the time of the Black Sea Flood: a small audience and small effects, in V. Yanko-Hombach, A.A. Gilbert, N. Panin and P. M. Dolukhanov (eds.), ''The Black Sea Flood Question: changes in coastline, climate and human settlement'' (2007), pp. 245-370 (361); D. W. Anthony, ''[[The Horse, The Wheel and Language]]'' (2007), pp.148-9, p. 480, note 19.&lt;/ref&gt;  and from there spread via the [[Dnieper-Donets culture]] to the [[Narva culture]] of the Eastern Baltic. Spreading westward along the coastline it is found in the [[Ertebølle culture]] of Denmark and Ellerbek of Northern Germany, and the related [[Swifterbant culture]] of the Low Countries.&lt;ref&gt;Detlef Gronenborn, Beyond the models: Neolithisation in Central Europe, ''Proceedings of the British Academy'', vol. 144 (2007), pp. 73-98 (87).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mesolithic cultures==
''Periodization: [[Mesolithic#In the Levant|The Levant]]: 20,000 to 9500&amp;nbsp;BCE; [[Mesolithic#In Europe|Europe]]: 9660 to 5000&amp;nbsp;BCE; [[Jōmon period|Elsewhere]]: 10,000 to 400&amp;nbsp;BCE''
*[[Azilian|Azilian culture]]
*[[Prehistory of Southeastern Europe|Balkan mesolithic cultures]]
*[[Capsian culture]]
*[[Fosna-Hensbacka culture]]
*[[Harifian|Harifian culture]]
*[[Kebaran|Kebaran culture]]
*[[Jōmon period|Jōmon cultures]]
*[[Jeulmun pottery period|Jeulmun culture]]
*[[Komsa culture]]
*[[Kongemose culture]]
*[[Kunda culture]]
*[[Lepenski Vir|Lepenski Vir culture]]
*[[Maglemosian culture]]
*[[Natufian culture]]
*[[Neman culture]]
*[[Nøstvet and Lihult cultures]]
*[[Sauveterrian|Sauveterrian culture]]
*[[Tardenoisian|Tardenoisian culture]]
*[[Zarzian culture]]

==Mesolithic sites==
Some notable Mesolithic sites:
*[[Lepenski Vir]], Serbia — 7000&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Star Carr]], England — 8700&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Pulli settlement]], Estonia — 9000&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Franchthi cave]], Greece — 20,000–3000&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Cramond]], Scotland — 8500&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Mount Sandel Mesolithic site|Mount Sandel]], Ireland — 7010&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Howick house]], England — 7000&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Newbury, Berkshire|Newbury]], England
*[[Swifterbant culture]], The Netherlands
*[[Aveline's Hole]], Somerset, England — 8000&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Ngwenya Mine]], Swaziland - 42,000&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Nanzhuangtou]] bog, China - 8500-7700&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Rock Shelters of Bhimbetka]], India - 100,000-30,000&amp;nbsp;BCE
*[[Shigir Idol]], Russia - 7500&amp;nbsp;BCE

==See also==
*[[10th millennium BC]]
*[[7th millennium BC]]
*[[8th millennium BC]]
*[[9th millennium BC]]
*[[Holocene]]
*[[Jōmon period]]

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==Further reading==
*Dragoslav Srejovic ''Europe's First Monumental Sculpture: New Discoveries at Lepenski Vir.'' (1972) ISBN 0-500-39009-6

==External links==
{{Commons category|Mesolithic}}
*[http://www.yurope.com/people/nena/Vir/ Official Lepenski Vir Site in Serbian]
*[http://www.york.ac.uk/depts/arch/Mesolithic/index.htm Mesolithic Miscellany — Newsletter and Information on the European Mesolithic]
* 20th Century Mesolithic Sites in Mandla (Madhya Pradesh), India, discovered by Dr. Babul Roy: [http://highland.trf.or.th/News1/SEAnews/SEAnewletter/SEAN15$.pdf], [http://www.insulators.info/clubs/bric/aug03.htm], and [http://www.prehistory.wetpaint.com ]
*[http://www.anthropark.wz.cz/aagalery.htm Picture Gallery of the Paleolithic (reconstructional palaeoethnology)],  Libor Balák at the Czech Academy of Sciences, the Institute of Archaeology in Brno, The Center for Paleolithic and Paleoethnological Research
*[http://ads.ahds.ac.uk/catalogue/library/cba/rr20.cfm  Gazetteer of Mesolithic sites in England and Wales with a gazetteer of Upper Palaeolithic sites in England and Wales.] Wymer JJ and CJ Bonsall, 1977  [[Council for British Archaeology]] Research Report No 20
*[http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/925 UNESCO World Heritaga Site in India - Rock Shelters of Bhimbetka]
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Holocene]]
[[Category:Mesolithic| ]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[ast:Mesolíticu]]
[[az:Mezolit]]
[[bn:মেসোলিথিক]]
[[ba:Мезолит]]
[[be:Мезаліт]]
[[be-x-old:Мэзаліт]]
[[bg:Мезолит]]
[[br:Krennoadvezh ar maen]]
[[ca:Mesolític]]
[[cs:Mezolit]]
[[cy:Oes Ganol y Cerrig]]
[[da:Ældre stenalder]]
[[de:Mittelsteinzeit]]
[[et:Mesoliitikum]]
[[el:Μεσολιθική περίοδος]]
[[es:Mesolítico]]
[[eu:Mesolito]]
[[fa:میان‌سنگی]]
[[fr:Mésolithique]]
[[fy:Mesolitikum]]
[[gl:Mesolítico]]
[[ko:중석기 시대]]
[[hy:Միջին քարի դար]]
[[hi:मध्यपाषाण काल]]
[[hr:Srednje kameno doba]]
[[id:Mesolitikum]]
[[it:Mesolitico]]
[[he:תקופת האבן התיכונה]]
[[jv:Mesolitikum]]
[[ka:მეზოლითი]]
[[kk:Мезолит]]
[[ky:Мезолит]]
[[la:Mesolithicum]]
[[lv:Mezolīts]]
[[lt:Mezolitas]]
[[hu:Középső kőkorszak]]
[[mk:Мезолит]]
[[ms:Zaman Mesolitik]]
[[mn:Мезолит]]
[[nl:Mesolithicum]]
[[ja:中石器時代]]
[[no:Mesolitikum]]
[[nn:Mellomsteinalderen]]
[[oc:Mesolitic]]
[[pl:Mezolit]]
[[pt:Mesolítico]]
[[ro:Mezolitic]]
[[ru:Мезолит]]
[[sq:Mezoliti]]
[[simple:Mesolithic]]
[[sk:Mezolit]]
[[sl:Mezolitik]]
[[sr:Мезолит]]
[[sh:Mezolit]]
[[su:Mesolitikum]]
[[fi:Mesoliittinen kausi]]
[[sv:Mesolitikum]]
[[ta:இடைக் கற்காலம்]]
[[tt:Мезолит]]
[[tg:Мезолит]]
[[tr:Orta Taş Çağı]]
[[uk:Мезоліт]]
[[ur:وسطی زمانہ پتھر]]
[[vi:Thời đại đồ đá giữa]]
[[vls:Mesolithicum]]
[[zh:中石器時代]]</text>
      <sha1>0q77a9yop737yslicg8ra0ouio9eva8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
