<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Military history</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25595604</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521672461</id>
      <parentid>520467350</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T14:25:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Stefanomione</username>
        <id>186638</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rename category</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="54121">{{About|the field of study|television channel of the same name|Military History (TV channel)}}

{{War}}
'''Military history''' is a [[humanities]] [[List of academic disciplines|discipline]] within the scope of [[History|general historical]] recording of [[War|armed conflict]] in the [[Human history|history of humanity]], and its impact on the societies, their cultures, economies and changing [[Politics|intra]] and [[international relations]]hips.

Professional historians normally focus on military affairs that had a major impact on the societies involved as well as the aftermath of conflicts, while amateur historians and hobbyists often take a larger interest in the details of battles, equipment and uniforms in use.

The essential subjects of military history study are the causes of war, the social and cultural foundations, [[Doctrine#Military usage|military doctrine on each side]], the logistics, leadership, technology, [[strategy]], and [[military tactics|tactics]] used, and how these changed over time.

As an applied field, military history has been studied at academies and service schools because the [[Command and control (military)|military command]] seeks to not repeat past mistakes, and improve upon its current performance by instilling an ability in commanders to perceive historical parallels during a battle, so as to capitalize on the lessons learned from the past.

The discipline of military history is dynamic, changing with development as much of the subject area as the societies and organisations that make use of it.&lt;ref&gt;Cowley, Parker, p.xiii&lt;/ref&gt; The dynamic nature of the discipline of military history is largely related to the rapidity of change the military forces, and the art and science of managing them, as well as the frenetic pace of [[Technological evolution|technological development]] that had taken place during the period known as the [[Industrial Revolution]], and more recently in the [[Nuclear proliferation|nuclear]] and [[information age]]s.

An important recent concept is the [[Revolution in Military Affairs]] (RMA) which attempts to explain how warfare has been shaped by emerging technologies, such as gunpowder. It highlights the short outbursts of rapid change followed by periods of relative stability.

==Historiography of military history==
[[Historiography]] is the study of the history and method of the discipline of history or the study of a specialised topic. In this case, military history with an eye to gaining an accurate assessment of conflicts using all available sources. For this reason military history is periodised, creating overlaying boundaries of study and analysis in which descriptions of battles by leaders may be unreliable due to the inclination to minimize mention of failure and exaggerate success. Military historians use Historiographical analysis in an effort to allow an unbiased, contemporary view of records.&lt;ref&gt;Morillo, Pevkovic, pp.4-5&lt;/ref&gt;

One military historian, Jeremy Black, in a recent work mentioned some problems 21st century military historians face as an inheritance of their predecessors: Eurocentricity, a technological bias, a focus on leading military powers and dominant military systems, the separation of land from sea and recently air conflicts, the focus on state-to-state conflict, a lack of focus on political &quot;tasking&quot; in how forces are used.&lt;ref name=&quot;p.ix, Black&quot;&gt;Black, p.ix&lt;/ref&gt;

If these challenges were not sufficient for the military historians, the limits of method are complicated by the lack of records, either destroyed or never recorded for its value as a [[military secret]] that may prevent some salient facts from being reported at all; scholars still do not know the exact nature of [[Greek fire]] for instance. Despite these limits, wars are some of the most studied and detailed periods of human history.

Military historians have often [[Comparative history|compared]] organization, tactical and strategic ideas, leadership, and national support of the militaries of different nations.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Kennedy, ''The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers: Economic Change and Military Conflict from 1500 to 2000'' (Random House, 1987)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early historians==
The documentation of military history begins with the confrontation between Sumer (current [[Iraq]]) and Elam (current [[Iran]]) c. 2700 BCE near the modern [[Basra]], and includes such enduring records as the [[Hebrew Bible]]. Other prominent records in military history are the [[Trojan War]] in [[Homer]]'s ''[[Iliad]]'' (though its [[historicity of the Iliad|historicity]] has been challenged), ''[[Histories (Herodotus)|The Histories]]'' by [[Herodotus]] (484 BC - 425 BC) who is often called the &quot;father of history&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/tasmania/stories/s999564.htm &quot;Herodotus: the father of history&quot;], Warburton&lt;/ref&gt; Next was [[Thucydides]] whose impartiality, despite being an [[Athens|Athenian]], allowed him to take advantage of his exile to research the war from different perspectives by carefully examining documents and interviewing eyewitnesses.&lt;ref&gt;Farah, Karls, pp. 137-138&lt;/ref&gt; An approach centered around the analysis of a leader was taken by [[Xenophon]] (430 BC - 355 BC) in ''[[Anabasis (Xenophon)|Anabasis]]'', recording the expedition of [[Cyrus the Younger]] into [[Anatolia]].

The records of the Roman [[Julius Caesar]] (100 BC - 44 BC) enable a comparative approach for [[Military campaign|campaign]]s such as ''[[Commentarii de Bello Gallico]]'' and ''[[Commentarii de Bello Civili]]''.

==Technological evolution==
{{rquote|right|The nature of warfare ''never'' changes, only its superficial manifestations. [[Joshua]] and [[David]], [[Hector]] and [[Achilles]] would recognize the combat that our soldiers and Marines have waged in the alleys of Somalia and Iraq. The uniforms evolve, bronze gives way to titanium, arrows may be replaced by laser-guided bombs, but the heart of the matter is still killing your enemies until any survivors surrender and do your will.|[[Ralph Peters]]&lt;ref&gt;Peters, Ralph. ''New Glory: Expanding America's Supremacy'', 2005. p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[Image:Ramses II at Kadesh.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Relief of [[Ramses II]] located in [[Abu Simbel]] fighting at the [[Battle of Kadesh]] on a [[chariot]].]]

New weapons development can dramatically alter the face of war.

[[Chariot]]s, pulled by animals like the [[onager]], [[ox]], [[donkey]], and later the [[horse]], originated around 2000 BC. The chariot was an effective, fast weapon; while one man controlled the maneuvering of the chariot, a second bowman could shoot arrows at enemy soldiers. These became crucial to the maintenance of several governments, including the [[New Egyptian Kingdom]] and the [[Shang Dynasty]] and the nation states of early to mid [[Zhou dynasty]].

Some of the military unit types and technologies which were developed in the ancient world are:

*[[Sling (weapon)|Slinger]]
*[[Hoplite]]
*[[Auxiliaries (Roman military)|Auxiliaries]]
*[[Infantry]]
*[[Crossbowmen]]
*[[Chariots]]
*[[Cavalry]]

For settled agrarian civilizations, the [[infantry]] would become the core of military action. The infantry started as opposing armed groups of soldiers underneath commanders. The [[Ancient Greece|Greeks]] and early Romans used rigid, heavily armed [[phalanx formation|phalanxes]]. The Macedonians and Hellenistic states would adopt phalanx formations with [[sarissa]] pikemen. The [[Roman Army|Romans]] would later adopt more flexible maniples from their neighbors which made them extremely successful in the field of battle. The kingdoms of the [[Warring States]] in East Asia also adopted infantry combat, a transition from chariot warfare from centuries earlier.

[[Cavalry]] would become an important tool. In the [[Sicilian Expedition]], led by [[Athens]] in an attempt to subdue [[Syracuse, Italy|Syracuse]], the well-trained Syracusan cavalry became crucial to the success of the Syracusans. [[Macedon]]ian [[Alexander the Great]] effectively deployed his cavalry forces to secure victories. In battles such as the [[Battle of Cannae]] of the [[Second Punic War]], and the [[Battle of Carrhae]] of the [[Roman-Persian Wars]], the importance of the cavalry would be repeated.

There were also [[horse archer]]s, who had the ability to shoot on horseback&amp;nbsp;– the [[Parthians]], [[Scythians]], [[Mongols]], and other various steppe people were especially fearsome with this tactic. By the 3rd-4th century CE, heavily armored cavalry became widely adopted by the [[Eastern Roman Empire]], [[Sassanids]], [[Eastern Han Dynasty]] and [[Three Kingdoms]], etc.

Even in the First World War, cavalry was still considered important; the British mobilized 165,000 horses, the Austrians 600,000, the Germans 715,000, and the Russians more than a million.&lt;ref name=Keegan&gt;Keegan, p.73&lt;/ref&gt;

The early [[Indo-Iranians]] developed the use of [[chariot]]s in warfare. The [[scythed chariot]] was later invented in India and soon adopted by the Persian Empire.

[[War elephant]]s were often deployed for fighting in ancient warfare. They were first used in India and later adopted by both the [[Persia]]ns and Alexander the Great against one another. War elephants were also used in the [[Battle of the Hydaspes River]], and by [[Hannibal Barca|Hannibal]] in the Second Punic War against the Romans.(The effectiveness of war elephants in a battle is a matter of debate)

There were also organizational changes, made possible by better training and intercommunication. [[Combined arms]] was the concept of using infantry, cavalry, and [[artillery]] in a coordinated way.

[[Image:Trireme.jpg|250px|right|thumb|A [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] [[trireme]]]]
[[Naval warfare]] was often crucial to military success. Early navies used sailing ships without cannons; often the goal was to ram the enemy ships and cause them to sink.

There was human oar power, often using slaves, built up to ramming speed. [[Galley]]s were used in the [[3000 BC|3rd millennium BC]] by the [[Crete|Cretan]]s. The [[Ancient Greece|Greek]]s later advanced these ships.

In 1210 BC, the first recorded naval battle was fought between [[Suppiluliuma II]], king of the [[Hittites]], and [[Cyprus]], which was defeated. In the [[Persian Wars]], the navy became of increasing importance.

[[Trireme]]s were involved in more complicated sea-land operations. [[Themistocles]] helped to build up a stronger Greek navy, composed of 310 ships, and defeated the Persians at the [[Battle of Salamis]], ending the Persian invasion of Greece.&lt;ref&gt;Moerbeek, Martijn (January 21, 1998). [http://monolith.dnsalias.org/~marsares/warfare/battle/salamis.html &quot;The battle of Salamis, 480 BC&quot;] Accessed May 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[First Punic War]], the war between [[Carthage]] and Rome started with an advantage to Carthage because of their naval experience. A Roman fleet was built in 261 BC, with the addition of the [[Corvus (weapon)|corvus]] that allowed Roman soldiers on board the ships to board the enemy ships. The bridge would prove effective at the [[Battle of Mylae]], resulting in a Roman victory.

The [[Vikings]], in the 8th century AD, invented a ship propelled by oars with a dragon decorating the prow, hence called the [[Drekar|Drakkar]]. The 12th century CE [[Song Dynasty]] invented ships with watertight bulk head compartments while the 2nd century BCE [[Han Dynasty]] invented rudders and sculled oars for their warships.

[[Fortification]]s are important in warfare. Early [[hill-fort]]s were used to protect inhabitants in the [[Iron Age]]. They were primitive forts surrounded by ditches filled with water.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timeref.com/casterly.htm &quot;The Medieval Castle&quot;]. Accessed May 16, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Forts were then built out of mud bricks, stones, wood, and other available materials. Romans used rectangular fortresses built out of wood and stone. As long as there have been fortifications, there have been contraptions to break in, dating back to the times of [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] and earlier. [[Siege]] warfare is often necessary to capture forts.

Some of the military unit types and technologies which were used in the medieval period are:
*[[Artillery]]
*[[Cataphract]]
*[[Condottieri]]
*[[Fyrd]]
*[[Rashidun army|Rashidun]]
*[[Mobile guard]]
*[[Mamluk]]
*[[Janissary]]
*[[Knight]] (see also: [[Chivalry]])
*[[Crossbow]]
*[[Pikeman]]
*[[Samurai]]
*[[Sipahi]]

[[Bow (weapon)|Bows]] and [[Arrow (weapon)|arrows]] were often used by combatants. Egyptians shot arrows from chariots effectively. The [[crossbow]] was developed around 500 BC in China, and was used a lot in the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref&gt;Selby, Stephen (2001). [http://www.atarn.org/chinese/bjng_xbow/bjng_xbow.htm &quot;A Crossbow Mechanism with Some Unique Features from Shandong, China&quot;]. Accessed on May 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The English/Welsh [[longbow]] from the 12th century also became important in the Middle Ages. It helped to give the English a large early advantage in the [[Hundred Years' War]], even though the English were eventually defeated. The [[Battle of Crécy]] and the [[Battle of Agincourt]] are excellent examples of how to destroy an enemy using a longbow. It dominated battlefields for over a century.

[[Image:Cannon pic.jpg|250px|right|thumb|A small [[English Civil War]]-era cannon]]
In the 10th century, the invention of gunpowder led to many new weapons that were improved over time. [[Blackpowder]] was used in China since the 4th century, but it was not used as a weapon until the 11th century.

Until the mid-15th century, guns were held in one hand, while the [[explosive charge]] was ignited by the other hand. Then came the [[matchlock]], which was used widely until around the 1720s. [[Leonardo da Vinci]] made drawings of the [[wheel lock]] which made its own sparks. Eventually, the matchlock was replaced by the [[flintlock]].

[[Cannon]]s were first used in Europe in the early 14th century, and played a vital role in the [[Hundred Years' War]]. The first cannons were simply welded metal bars in the form of a cylinder, and the first cannonballs were made of stone. By 1346, at the Battle of Crécy, the cannon had been used; at the [[Battle of Agincourt]] they would be used again.&lt;ref&gt;Calvert, J.B. (February 19, 2006) [http://www.du.edu/~jcalvert/tech/cannon.htm &quot;Cannons and Gunpowder&quot;]. Accessed on May 18, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

At the beginning of the 16th century, the first European [[fire ship]]s were used. Ships were filled with flammable materials, set on fire, and sent to enemy lines. This tactic was successfully used by [[Francis Drake]] to scatter the [[Spanish Armada]] at the Battle of [[Gravelines]],&lt;ref&gt;Jorge. [http://www.tudorplace.com.ar/Documents/defeat_of_the_armada.htm The &quot;Invincible&quot; Armada]. Accessed on May 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and would later be used by the Chinese, Russians, Greeks, and several other countries in naval battles.

[[Naval mines]] were invented in the 17th century, though they were not used in great numbers until the [[American Civil War]]. They were used heavily in the [[First World War|First]] and Second World Wars.

The first navigable [[submarine]] was built in 1624 by [[Cornelius Drebbel]], it could cruise at a depth of 15 feet (5&amp;nbsp;m). However, the first military submarine was constructed in 1885 by [[Isaac Peral]].

The [[American Turtle|''Turtle'']] was developed by [[David Bushnell]] during the [[American Revolution]]. [[Robert Fulton]] then improved the submarine design by creating the [[Nautilus (submarine)|''Nautilus'']].&lt;ref&gt;[http://submarinehistory.homestead.com/EarlyUnderwaterwarfare.html &quot;Early Underwater Warfare&quot;]. California Center for Military History. Accessed on May 18, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:155fire.jpg|200px|right|thumb|A 155&amp;nbsp;mm [[M198 howitzer]] firing a shell.]]
The [[Howitzer]], a type of [[field artillery]], was developed in 17th century to fire high [[trajectory]] explosive shells at targets that could not be reached by flat trajectory projectiles.

Bayonets also became of wide usage to infantry soldiers. [[Bayonet]] is named after [[Bayonne]], France where it was first manufactured in the 16th century. It is used often in infantry charges to fight in hand-to-hand combat. General [[Jean Martinet]] introduced the bayonet to the French army. They were used a lot in the [[American Civil War]], and continued to be used in modern wars like the [[Invasion of Iraq]].

[[Balloon (aircraft)|Balloon]]s were first used in warfare at the end of the 18th century. It was first introduced in Paris of 1783; the first balloon traveled over 5&amp;nbsp;miles (8&amp;nbsp;km). Previously military [[Reconnaissance|scouts]] could only see from high points on the ground, or from the mast of a ship. Now they could be high in the sky, signalling to troops on the ground. This made it much more difficult for troop movements to go unobserved.

At the end of the 18th century, iron-cased [[artillery rocket]]s were successfully used militarily in India against the British by [[Tipu Sultan]] of the [[Kingdom of Mysore]] during the [[Anglo-Mysore Wars]]. Rockets were generally inaccurate at that time, though [[William Hale (British inventor)|William Hale]], in 1844, was able to develop a better rocket. The new rocket no longer needed the [[rocket stick]], and had a higher accuracy.

In the 1860s there were a series of advancements in [[rifle]]s. The first [[repeating rifle]] was designed in 1860 by a company bought out by [[Winchester Repeating Arms Company|Winchester]], which made new and improved versions. [[Springfield rifle]]s arrived in the mid-19th century also. [[Machine gun]]s arrived in the middle of the 19th century. [[Automatic rifle]]s and [[light machine gun]]s first arrived at the beginning of the 20th century.

Also in the 1860s came the first boats that would later be known as [[torpedo boat]]s. These were first used in the American Civil War, but generally were not successful. Several [[Confederate States of America|Confederates]] used [[spar torpedo]]es, which were bombs on long poles designed to attach to boats. In the later part of the 19th century, the self-propelled [[torpedo]] was developed. The [[HNoMS Rap (1873)|HNoMS Rap]] was the world's first torpedo boat.

At the start of the World Wars, various nations had developed weapons that were a surprise to their adversaries, leading to a need to learn from this, and alter how to combat them. [[Flame thrower]]s were first used in the First World War. The French were the first to introduce the [[Armored car (military)|armored car]] in 1902. Then in 1918, the British produced the first [[Armoured personnel carrier|armored troop carrier]]. Many early [[tank]]s were proof of concept but impractical until further development. In World War I, the British and French held a crucial advantage due to their superiority in tanks; the Germans had only a few dozen A&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;V tanks, as well as 170 captured tanks. The British and French both had several hundred each. The French tanks included the 13 ton [[Schneider-Creusot]], with a 75&amp;nbsp;mm gun, and the British had the [[Mark I tank#Mark IV|Mark IV]] and [[Mark I tank#Mark V series|Mark V]] tanks.&lt;ref&gt;Keegan, p.410&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 17, 1903, the [[Wright Brothers]] performed the first controlled, powered, heavier-than-air flight; it went 39 meters (120&amp;nbsp;ft). In 1907, the first [[helicopter]] flew, but it wasn't practical for usage. [[World War I Aviation|Aviation]] became important in World War I, in which several [[Flying ace|aces]] gained fame. In 1911 an aircraft took off from a [[warship]] for the first time. It was a [[Cruiser (warship)|cruiser]]. [[Takeoff]]s were soon perfected, but deck landings on a cruiser were another matter.  This led to the development of an [[aircraft carrier]] with a decent unobstructed flight deck.

[[Chemical warfare]] exploded into the public consciousness in World War I but may have been used in earlier wars without as much human attention. The Germans used gas-filled shells at the [[Battle of Bolimov]] on January 3, 1915. These were not lethal, however. In April 1915, the Germans developed a chlorine gas that was highly lethal, and used it to great effect at the [[Second Battle of Ypres]].&lt;ref&gt;Keegan, pp.197-199&lt;/ref&gt;

World War II gave rise to even more technology. The worth of the aircraft carrier was proved in the battles between the United States and Japan like the [[Battle of Midway]]. [[Radar]] was independently invented by the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] and [[Axis Powers|Axis powers]]. It used [[radio wave]]s to detect objects. [[Molotov cocktail]]s were invented by General Franco in the Spanish Civil War, directing the Nationalists to use them against Soviet tanks in the assault on Toledo. The [[atomic bomb]] was developed by the [[Manhattan Project]] and [[Atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki|dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki]] in 1945, ultimately ending World War II.

During the [[Cold War]], even though fighting did not actually occur, the superpowers&amp;nbsp;– the United States and the USSR&amp;nbsp;– engaged in a [[Nuclear arms race|race]] to develop and increase the level of technology available for military purposes. In the [[space race]], both nations attempted to launch human beings into space to the moon. Other technological advances centered around intelligence (like the [[spy satellite]]) and missiles ([[ballistic missile]]s, [[cruise missile]]s). [[Nuclear submarine]], invented in 1955. This meant submarines no longer had to surface as often, and could run more quietly. They evolved into becoming underwater missile platforms. Cruise missiles were invented in Nazi Germany during World War II in the form of the V-1.

==Periods of military history==
The influence of technology on military history, and evident Eurocentrism are nowhere more pronounced than in the attempt by the military historians to divide their subject area into more manageable [[Periodization|periods]] of analysis. While general discipline of history subdivides history into Ancient history (Classical antiquity), Middle Ages (Europe, 4th century - 15th century), Early modern period (Europe, 14th century - 18th century), Modern era (Europe, 18th century - 20th century), and the Post-Modern (USA, 1949–present), the periodisation below stresses technological change in its emphasis, particularly the crucial dramatic change during the Gunpowder warfare period.

Periodisation is not uniformly applied through time and space, affirming the claims of Eurocentrism from regional historians. For example what might be described as [[ancient warfare]] is still practised in a number of parts of the world. Other eras that are distinct in European history, such as the era of [[medieval warfare]], may have little relevance in East Asia.

===Ancient warfare===
{{details|Ancient warfare}}

Much of what we know of [[ancient history]] is the history of militaries: their conquests, their movements, and their technological innovations. There are many reasons for this. Kingdoms and empires, the central units of control in the ancient world, could only be maintained through military force. Due to limited agricultural ability, there were relatively few areas that could support large communities, so fighting was common.

[[Weapon]]s and [[armor]], designed to be sturdy, tended to last longer than other artifacts, and thus a great deal of surviving artifacts recovered tend to fall in this category as they are more likely to survive. Weapons and armor were also mass-produced to a scale that makes them quite plentiful throughout history, and thus more likely to be found in archaeological digs.

Such items were also considered signs of prosperity or virtue, and thus were likely to placed in tombs and monuments to prominent warriors. And writing, when it existed, was often used for kings to boast of military conquests or victories.

Writing, when used by the common man, also tended to record such events, as major battles and conquests constituted major events that many would have considered worthy of recording either in an epic such as the [[Homeric]] writings pertaining to the Trojan War, or even personal writings. Indeed the earliest stories center around warfare, as war was both a common and dramatic aspect of life; the witnessing of a major battle involving many thousands of soldiers would be quite a spectacle, even today, and thus considered worthy both of being recorded in song and art, but also in realistic histories, as well as being a central element in a fictional work.

Lastly, as [[nation states]] evolved and empires grew, the increased need for order and efficiency lead to an increase in the number of records and writings. Officials and armies would have good reason for keeping detailed records and accounts involving any and all things concerning a matter such as warfare that in the words of [[Sun Tzu]] was &quot;a matter of vital importance to the state&quot;. For all these reasons, military history comprises a large part of ancient history.

Notable militaries in the ancient world included the [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptian]]s, [[Babylon]]ians, [[Persian Empire|Persians]], Ancient [[Ancient Greece|Greeks]] (notably the [[Sparta]]ns and [[Macedon]]ians), [[Military history of India|Indians]] (notably the [[Magadha]]s, [[Gangaridai]]s, [[Gandhara]]s and [[Cholas]]), Early Imperial [[History of China|Chinese]] (notably the [[Qin (state)|Qin]] and [[Han (state)|Han]] Dynasties), [[Xiongnu]] Confederation, Ancient [[Ancient Rome|Romans]], and [[Carthage|Carthaginians]].

The [[fertile crescent]] of [[Mesopotamia]] was the center of several prehistoric conquests. Mesopotamia was conquered by the [[Sumer]]ians, [[Akkadian Empire|Akkadians]], [[Babylonia]]ns, [[Assyria]]ns and Persians. [[Iran]]ians were the first nation to introduce [[cavalry]] into their army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Suren-Pahlav&quot;&gt;Suren-Pahlav S., ''General Surena; The Hero of Carrhae''&lt;!-- link blocked by spam filter: http://www.cais-soas.com/CAIS/History/ashkanian/surena.htm ; accessed Jan 16, 2007 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Egypt]] began growing as an ancient power, but eventually fell to the [[Libya]]ns, [[Nubia]]ns, Assyrians, Persians, Greeks, Romans, [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantines]] and [[Arab]]s.

The earliest recorded battle in [[History of India|India]] was the [[Battle of the Ten Kings]]. The [[Indian epic poetry|Indian epics]] ''[[Mahabharata]]'' and ''[[Ramayana]]'' are centered around conflicts and refer to military formations, theories of warfare and esoteric weaponry. [[Chanakya]]'s ''[[Arthashastra]]'' contains a detailed study on ancient warfare, including topics on [[espionage]] and [[war elephant]]s.

[[Alexander the Great]] invaded Northwestern India and defeated [[King Porus]] in the [[Battle of the Hydaspes River]]. The same region was soon re conquered by [[Chandragupta Maurya]] after defeating the Macedonians and [[Seleucid Empire|Seleucids]]. He also went on to conquer the [[Nanda Dynasty|Nanda Empire]] and unify Northern India. Most of Southern Asia was unified under his grandson [[Ashoka|Ashoka the Great]] after the [[Kalinga War]], though the empire collapsed not long after his reign.

In China, the [[Shang Dynasty]] and [[Zhou Dynasty]] had risen and collapsed. This led to a [[Warring States Period]], in which several states continued to fight with each other over territory. Philosopher-strategists such as [[Confucius]] and [[Sun Tzu]] wrote various manuscripts on ancient warfare (as well as international diplomacy).

The Warring States era philosopher [[Mozi]] ([[Micius]]) and his [[Mohist]] followers invented various siege weapons and siegecraft, including the Cloud Ladder (a four-wheeled, extendable ramp) to scale fortified walls during a siege of an enemy city. The warring states were first unified by [[Qin Shi Huang]] after a series of military conquests, creating the first empire in China.

His [[Qin Dynasty|empire]] was succeeded by the [[Han Dynasty]], which expanded into Central Asia, Northern China/Manchuria, Southern China, and present day Korea and Vietnam. The Han came into conflict with settled people such as the proto-Korean Gojoseons, and proto-Vietnamese Nanyue. They also came into conflict with the [[Xiongnu]] ([[Huns]]), [[Yuezhi]], and other steppe civilizations.

The Han defeated and drove the Xiongnus west, securing the city-states along the silk route that continued into the [[Parthia]]n Empire. After the decline of central imperial authority, the Han Dynasty collapsed into an era of civil war and continuous warfare during the [[Three Kingdoms]] period in the 3rd century CE.

The [[Achaemenid Empire|Achaemenid]] Persian Empire was founded by [[Cyrus the Great]] after conquering the [[Medes|Median Empire]], [[Neo-Babylonian Empire]], [[Lydia]] and [[Asia Minor]]. His successor [[Cambyses II of Persia|Cambyses]] went onto conquer the [[Egyptian Empire]], much of Central Asia, and parts of Greece, India and Libya. The empire later fell to Alexander the Great after defeating [[Darius III of Persia|Darius III]]. After being ruled by the Seleucid dynasty, the Persian Empire was subsequently ruled by the Parthian and [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid]] dynasties, which were the [[Roman Empire]]'s greatest rivals during the [[Roman-Persian Wars]].

In Greece, several [[city-state]]s rose to power, including [[Athens]] and [[Sparta]]. The Greeks successfully stopped two Persian invasions, the first at the [[Battle of Marathon]], where the Persians were led by [[Darius I of Persia|Darius the Great]], and the second at  the [[Battle of Salamis]], a naval battle where the Greek ships were deployed by orders of [[Themistocles]] and the Persians were under [[Xerxes I]], and the land engagement of the [[Battle of Plataea]].

The [[Peloponnesian War]] then erupted between the two Greek powers Athens and Sparta. Athens built a long wall to protect its inhabitants, but the wall helped to facilitate the spread of a plague that killed about 30,000 Athenians, including [[Pericles]]. After a disastrous campaign against [[Syracuse, Italy|Syracuse]], the Athenian navy was decisively defeated by [[Lysander]] at the [[Battle of Aegospotami]].

The [[Ancient Macedonians|Macedonians]], underneath [[Philip II of Macedon]] and Alexander the Great, invaded Persia and won several major victories, establishing Macedonia as a major power. However, following Alexander's death at an early age, the empire quickly fell apart.

Meanwhile, Rome was gaining power, following a rebellion against the [[Etruscans]]. During the three [[Punic Wars]], the Romans defeated the neighboring power of Carthage. The [[First Punic War]] centered around [[naval warfare]]. The [[Second Punic War]] started with [[Hannibal Barca|Hannibal]]'s invasion of Italy by crossing the [[Alps]]. He famously won the encirclement at the [[Battle of Cannae]]. However, after [[Scipio Africanus|Scipio]] invaded Carthage, Hannibal was forced to follow and was defeated at the [[Battle of Zama]], ending the role of Carthage as a power.

After defeating Carthage the Romans went on to become the Mediterranean's dominant power, successfully campaigning in Greece, ([[Aemilius Paulus]] decisive victory over Macedonia at the [[Battle of Pydna]]), in the Middle East ([[Lucius Licinius Lucullus]], [[Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus]]), in [[Gaul]] ([[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]]) and defeating several [[Germanic tribe]]s ([[Gaius Marius]], [[Germanicus]]). While Roman armies suffered several major losses, their large population and ability (and will) to replace battlefield casualties, their training, organization, tactical and technical superiority  enabled Rome to stay a predominant military force for several centuries, utilizing well trained and maneuverable armies to routinely overcome the much larger &quot;tribal&quot; armies of their foes (see Battles of [[Battle of Aquae Sextiae|Aquae Sextiae]], [[Battle of Vercellae|Vercellae]], [[Battle of Tigranocerta|Tigranocerta]], [[Battle of Alesia|Alesia]]).

In 54 BCE the Roman triumvir [[Marcus Licinius Crassus]] took the offensive against the [[Parthian Empire]] in the east. In a decisive battle at [[Battle of Carrhae|Carrhae]] Romans were defeated and the golden [[Aquila (Roman)|Aquilae]] (legionary battle standards) were taken as trophies to [[Ctesiphon]]. The battle was one of the worst defeats suffered by the Roman Republic in its entire history.

While successfully dealing with foreign opponents, Rome experienced numerous civil wars, notably the power struggles of Roman generals such as Marius and [[Sulla]] during the end of the Republic. Caesar was also notable for his role in the civil war against the other member of the Triumvirate (Pompey) and against the Roman Senate.

The successors of Caesar&amp;nbsp;— Octavian and Mark Anthony, also fought a civil war with Caesar's assassins (Senators Brutus, Cassius, etc.). Octavian and Mark Anthony eventually fought another civil war between themselves to determine the sole ruler of Rome. Octavian emerged victorious and Rome was turned into an empire with a huge standing army of professional soldiers.

By the time of [[Marcus Aurelius]], the Romans had expanded to the Atlantic Ocean in the west and to [[Mesopotamia]] in the east and controlled Northern Africa and Central Europe up to the [[Black Sea]]. However, Aurelius marked the end of the [[Nerva–Antonine dynasty#Five Good Emperors|Five Good Emperors]], and Rome quickly fell into decline.

The [[Hun]]s, [[Goths]], and other barbaric groups invaded Rome, which continued to suffer from [[inflation]] and other internal strifes. Despite the attempts of [[Diocletian]], [[Constantine I (emperor)|Constantine I]], and [[Theodosius I]], western Rome collapsed and was eventually conquered in 476. The [[Byzantium|Byzantine empire]] continued to prosper, however.

===Medieval warfare===
{{details|Medieval warfare}}

When [[stirrups]] came into use some time during the [[Dark Ages (historiography)|Dark Ages]] militaries were forever changed. This invention coupled with technological, cultural, and social developments had forced a dramatic transformation in the character of warfare from [[Classical antiquity|antiquity]], changing military tactics and the role of [[cavalry]] and [[artillery]].

Similar patterns of warfare existed in other parts of the world. In China around the 5th century armies moved from massed infantry to cavalry based forces, copying the [[steppe]] [[nomad]]s. The Middle East and North Africa used similar, if often more advanced, technologies than Europe.

In Japan the Medieval warfare period is considered by many to have stretched into the 19th century. In Africa along the [[Sahel]] and [[Sudan (region)|Sudan]] states like the [[Kingdom of Sennar]] and [[Fulani Empire]] employed Medieval tactics and weapons well after they had been supplanted in Europe.

In the [[Medieval]] period, [[feudalism]] was firmly implanted, and there existed many landlords in Europe. Landlords often owned castles to protect their territory.

The Islamic [[Caliphate|Arab Empire]] began rapidly expanding throughout the Middle East, North Africa, and Central Asia, initially led by [[Khalid ibn al-Walid]], and later under the [[Umayyads]].  While their attempts to invade Europe by way of the Balkans were [[Siege of Constantinople (717–718)|defeated]] by [[Byzantium]] and [[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgaria]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Wikisource:Great Battles of Bulgaria]]&lt;/ref&gt; the Arabs expanded to the [[Iberian Peninsula]] in the west and the [[Indus River|Indus Valley]] in the east. The [[Abassid]]s then took over the Arab Empire, though the Umayyads remained in control of [[Al-Andalus|Islamic Spain]].

At the [[Battle of Tours]], the [[Franks]] under [[Charles Martel]] stopped short a Muslim invasion. The Abassids defeated the [[Tang Dynasty|Tang]] Chinese army at the [[Battle of Talas]], but were later defeated by the [[Seljuk Turk]]s and the [[Mongol Empire|Mongols]] centuries later, until the Arab Empire eventually came to an end after the [[Battle of Baghdad (1258)|Battle of Baghdad]] in 1258.

In China, the [[Sui Dynasty]] had risen and conquered the Chen Dynasty of the south. They invaded Vietnam (northern Vietnam had been in Chinese control since the Han Dynasty), fighting the troops of [[Champa]], who had cavalry mounted on elephants. After decades of economic turmoil and a failed invasion of Korea, the Sui collapsed and was followed by the Tang Dynasty, who fought with various [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] groups, the [[Tibetan people|Tibetans]] of [[Lhasa]], the [[Tanguts]], the [[Khitans]], and collapsed due to political fragmentation of powerful regional military governors (jiedushi). The innovative [[Song Dynasty]] followed next, inventing new weapons of war that employed the use of [[Greek Fire]] and [[gunpowder]] (see section below) against enemies such as the [[Jurchens]].

The [[Mongol]]s under [[Genghis Khan]], [[Ögedei Khan]], [[Möngke Khan]], and [[Kublai Khan]] conquered most of Eurasia. They took over China, Persia, Turkestan, and Russia. After Kublai Khan took power and created the [[Yuan Dynasty]], the divisions of the empire ceased to cooperate with each other, and the Mongol Empire was only nominally united.

In New Zealand, prior to European discovery, oral histories, legends and [[whakapapa]] include many stories of battles and wars. [[Māori people|Māori]] warriors were held in high esteem. One group of [[Polynesians]] migrated to the [[Chatham Islands]], where they developed the largely pacifist [[Moriori]] culture. Their pacifism left the Moriori unable to defend themselves when the islands were invaded by mainland Māori in the 1830s.

They proceeded to massacre the Moriori and enslave the survivors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.teara.govt.nz/NewZealanders/MaoriNewZealanders/Moriori/4/en &quot;Moriori - The impact of new arrivals&quot;] ''Te Ara Encyclopedia of New Zealand''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newzealandatoz.com/index.php?pageid=607&amp;PHPSESSID=1c2fab7979e45ccc7c3e7336e8636142 &quot;Chatham Islands&quot;] ''New Zealand A to Z''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Warrior]] culture also developed in the isolated [[Hawaiian Islands]]. During the 1780s and 1790s the chiefs and alii were constantly fighting for power. After a series of battles the Hawaiian Islands were united for the first time under a single ruler who would become known as [[Kamehameha I]].

===Gunpowder warfare===
{{details|Gunpowder warfare}}

After [[gunpowder]] weapons were first developed in [[Song Dynasty]] China (see also [[Technology of Song Dynasty]]), the technology later spread west to the [[Ottoman Empire]], from where it spread to the [[Safavid Empire]] of Persia and the [[Mughal Empire]] of India. The [[arquebus]] was later adopted by European armies during the [[Italian Wars]] of the early 16th century.

This all brought an end to the dominance of armored cavalry on the battlefield. The simultaneous decline of the feudal system&amp;nbsp;— and the absorption of the medieval city-states into larger states&amp;nbsp;— allowed the creation of professional standing armies to replace the [[Feudalism|feudal levies]] and mercenaries that had been the standard military component of the Middle Ages.

In Africa, [[Ahmad ibn Ibrihim al-Ghazi]], was the first African commander to use gunpowder on the continent in the [[Ethiopian–Adal War]], that lasted for fourteen years (1529–1543)

The period spanning between the 1648 [[Peace of Westphalia]] and the 1789 [[French Revolution]] is also known as ''[[Kabinettskriege]]'' (Princes' warfare) as wars were mainly carried out by imperial or monarchics states, decided by cabinets and limited in scope and in their aims. They also involved quickly shifting alliances, and mainly used mercenaries. 

Over the course of the 18th-19th centuries all military arms and services underwent significant developments that included a more mobile [[field artillery]], the transition from use of battalion [[infantry drill]] in [[close order formation|close order]] to open order formations and the transfer of emphasis from the use of [[bayonets]] to the rifle that replaced the musket, and virtual replacement of all types of cavalry with the universal [[dragoons]], or [[mounted infantry]].

===Industrial warfare===
{{details|Industrial warfare}}

As weapons—particularly small arms—became easier to use, countries began to abandon a complete reliance on professional soldiers in favor of [[conscription]].  Technological advances became increasingly important; while the armies of the previous period had usually had similar weapons, the industrial age saw encounters such as the [[Battle of Sadowa]], in which possession of a more advanced technology played a decisive role in the outcome.

Conscription was employed in industrial warfare to increase the number of soldiers that were available for combat. This was used by [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] in the [[Napoleonic Wars]].

[[Total war]] was used in industrial warfare, the objective being to prevent the opposing nation to engage in war. [[William Tecumseh Sherman]]'s &quot;March to the Sea&quot; and [[Philip Sheridan]]'s burning of the [[Shenandoah Valley]] are examples of total warfare.

===Modern warfare===
{{details|Modern warfare}}

In modern times, war has evolved from an activity steeped in tradition to a [[scientific enterprise]] where success is valued above methods. The notion of [[total war]] is the extreme of this trend.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} Militaries have developed technological advances rivaling the scientific accomplishments of any other field of study.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

However, it should be noted that modern militaries benefit in the development of these technologies under the funding of the [[public]], the leadership of [[Central government|national governments]], and often in cooperation with large [[civilian]] groups, such as the [[General Dynamics]] and [[Lockheed Martin]] corporations, in the United States. And as for &quot;total war&quot;, it may be argued that it is not an exclusive practice of modern militaries, but in the tradition of [[Ethnic war|genocidal conflict]] that marks even tribal warfare to this day.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

What distinguishes modern military organizations from those previous is not their willingness to prevail in conflict by any method, but rather the technological variety of tools and methods available to modern battlefield commanders, from [[submarine]]s to [[satellite]]s, from knives to [[nuclear warheads]].

Some of the military unit types and technologies which were developed in modern times are:

*[[Ammunition]]
*[[Armory (military)|Armory]]
*[[Conscription]]
*[[Grenade Launcher|Grenadier]]
*[[Sapping|Sappers]] and [[Mining (military)|Miners]]
*[[marine (armed services)|Marine]]
*[[Military aviation|Aviation]]
*[[Rifleman]]
*[[Special Forces]]
*[[Naval Combatant]]
*[[Global Information Grid]]
*[[Active Electronically Scanned Array]]
*[[Network-centric warfare]]
*[[Supercomputer]]
*[[Space warfare]]
*[[Cyberwar]]

World War I was sparked by the assassination of [[Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria|Archduke Franz Ferdinand]], leading to the mobilization of Austria and [[Serbia]]. The [[Germany|Germans]] joined the Austrians to form the Central powers; the French, British, and Russians formed the Allied powers. Following the [[First Battle of the Marne|Battle of the Marne]] and the outflanking attempt of both nations in the &quot;[[Race to the Sea]]&quot;, [[trench warfare]] ensued, leaving the war in a great deadlock.

Major operations by the Germans at the [[Battle of Verdun]] and by the British and the French at the [[Battle of the Somme]] were carried out, and new technology like tanks and chlorine gas were used. Following the [[United States of America|USA's]] entrance into the war, the Germans and their allies were eventually defeated.

World War II ensued after Germany's invasion of Poland, forcing Britain and France to declare war. Germany quickly defeated France and Belgium, later aided by Italy. A hasty evacuation occurred at [[Dunkirk]] to save the Allied army from complete destruction. The Germans then attacked [[USSR]] and marched to take over the [[Soviet]] resources, but were thwarted.

Meanwhile, Japan, who had [[Second Sino-Japanese War|already been at war]] with the Chinese since 1937, had launched a surprise attack on [[Pearl Harbor]], leading the United States to join the Allied powers. In Europe, the Allies opened three fronts: in the west, after securing [[Normandy]]; in the east, aiding the Soviet Union; and in the south, through Italy. Germany eventually surrendered, upon which the Allies turned and focused troops to do [[Leapfrogging (strategy)|island hopping]]. The dropping of the [[atom bomb]]s on [[Hiroshima]] and [[Nagasaki, Nagasaki|Nagasaki]] led to the surrender of Japan and the end of the Second World War.

Worsening relationships between wartime Allies developed into the [[Cold War]], reaching a climax during the [[Cuban Missile Crisis]] at the same time as the [[Sino-Indian War]]. Hostilities never actually occurred, though the US-backed UN forces did engage against the [[communist]] states in the [[Korean War]] and the [[Vietnam War]].

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
*[[Army history]]
*[[Ancient Greek warfare]]
*War
*[[Military science]]
*[[Historical reenactment]]
*[[Maritime history]]
*[[Naval history]]
*[[Roman warfare]]

{{Col-2}}
{{Portal|Military History|War|History}}
*[[Military history of ancient Rome]]
*[[Military history of Africa]]
*[[Military history of Asia]]
*[[Military history of Europe]]
*[[Military history of Oceania]]
*[[Military history of North America]]
*[[Military history of South America]]
{{Col-end}}

==References and footnotes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* Archer, I. John R. Ferris, Holger H. Herwig, and Timothy H. E. Travers. ''World History of Warfare'' (2nd ed. 2008) 638pp
* Barnett, Correlli, Shelford Bidwell, Brian Bond, and John Terraine. ''Old Battles and New Defences: Can We Learn from Military History?'' (1986). [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=15086871# online edition]
* Black, Jeremy. &quot;Determinisms and Other Issues&quot;, ''Journal of Military History'', 68 (Oct. 2004), 1217–32. in [[Project MUSE]]
* Black, Jeremy.  ''Rethinking Military History'' (2004) [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=108014389 online edition]
* Black, Jeremy.  ''Warfare in the Western World, 1775-1882'' (2001) 240pp.
* Black, Jeremy.  ''Warfare in the Western World, 1882-1975'' (2002), 256pp
* Bucholz, Arden. &quot;Hans Delbruck and Modern Military History.&quot; ''The Historian'' vol 55#3 (1993) pp 517+.
*Chambers II, John Whiteclay. &quot;The New Military History: Myth and Reality&quot;, ''Journal of Military History'', 55 (July 1991), 395–406
*  Chambers, John Whiteclay, ed.  ''The Oxford Companion to American Military History'' (2000)  online at OUP
* Charters, David A., Marc Milner, and J. Brent Wilson. eds. ''Military History and the Military Profession'', (1992)
* Citino, Robert M. &quot;Military Histories Old and New: A Reintroduction&quot;, ''The American Historical Review'' Vol. 112, no. 4 (October 2007), pp.&amp;nbsp;1070–1090  [http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/resolve?AHRahr.112.4.1070PDF online version]
*  Cowley, Robert, and Geoffrey Parker, eds. ''The Reader's Companion to Military History'' (2001)  excellent coverage by scholars. [http://web.archive.org/web/20040807042512/college.hmco.com/history/readerscomp/mil/html/mh_000105_entries.htm Complete text online free of 1996 edition]
* Dear, I. C. B.,  and M. R. D. Foot, eds. ''Oxford Companion to World War II'' (2005; 2nd ed. 2010) online at OUP
* Doughty, Robert, Ira Gruber, Roy Flint, and Mark Grimsley. ''Warfare In The Western World'' (2 vol 1996), comprehensive textbook
* Dupuy, R. Ernest and Trevor N. Dupuy. ''The Encyclopedia of Military History: From 3500 B.C. to the Present'' (1977), 1465pp; comprehensive discussion focused on wars and battles

* Echevarria, Antulio J. ''Imagining Future War: The West's Technological Revolution and Visions of Wars to Come, 1880-1914'' (2007)
* Grimsley, Mark. &quot;Why Military History Sucks&quot;, Nov. 1996, War Historian.org, online at [http://www.warhistorian.org/why_military_history_sucks.php]
* Holmes, Richard, ed. ''The Oxford Companion to Military History'' (2001) 1071pp; online at OUP
* Jones, Archer, 2001, ''The Art of War in the Western World'', University of Illinois Press. ISBN 978-0-252-06966-6
* {{cite book |last= Keegan |first= John| title= The First World War |year= 1999 |edition= 9th |publisher= Random House |location= New York |isbn= 0-375-40052-4}}
* Kohn, George C. ''Dictionary of Wars'' (3rd ed. 2006) 704pp; very useful summary across world history
* Karsten, Peter. ed., ''Encyclopedia of War and American Society'' (3 vols., 2005).
* Karsten, Peter. &quot;The 'New' American Military History: A Map of the Territory, Explored and Unexplored&quot;, ''American Quarterly'', 36 #3, (1984), 389–418 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1988340 in JSTOR]
* Kohn, Richard H. &quot;The Social History of the American Soldier: A Review and Prospectus for Research&quot;, ''American Historical Review'', 86 (June 1981), 553–67. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1860370 in JSTOR]
* Lee, Wayne E. &quot;Mind and Matter—Cultural Analysis in American Military History: A Look at the State of the Field&quot;, ''Journal of American History'', 93 (March 2007), 1116–42. Fulltext: [[History Cooperative]] and [[Ebsco]]
*Littauer,  M. A., and J. H. Crouwel, ''The origin of the true chariot'', ''Antiquity'', (1996) Volume 70,  Number 270, pp.&amp;nbsp;934–939
* Lynn, John A. ''Battle: A Cultural History of Combat and Culture'' (2003).
* Lynn, John A. &quot;Rally Once Again: The Embattled Future of Academic Military History&quot;, ''Journal of Military History'', 61 (Oct. 1997), 777–89.
* Mearsheimer, John J.  ''Liddell Hart and the Weight of History.'' (1988). 234 pp.
* Messenger, Charles, ed. ''Reader's Guide to Military History'' (Routledge,  2001), 948 pp; detailed guide  to the historiography of 500 topics
* Morillo, Stephen. ''What is Military History'' (2006)
* Moyar, Mark. &quot;The Current State of Military History&quot;, ''The Historical Journal'' (2007), 50: 225-240 online at [[Cambridge Journals Online|CJO]]
* Murray, Williamson and Richard Hart Sinnreich, eds. ''The past as prologue: the importance of history to the military profession'' (2006).
* Noe, Kenneth W., George C. Rable and Carol Reardon. &quot;Battle Histories: Reflections on Civil War Military Studies&quot;  ''Civil War History'' 53#3 2007. pp 229+. [http://www.questia.com/read/5022722823?title=Battle%20Histories%3a%20Reflections%20on%20Civil%20War%20Military%20Studies online edition]
* Parker, Geoffrey, ed. ''The Cambridge Illustrated History of Warfare'' (2008), good overview
* Porch, Douglas. &quot;Writing History in the &quot;End of History&quot; Era - Reflections on Historians and the GWOT&quot; ''Journal of Military History'' 2006 70(4): 1065-1079. Issn: 0899-3718 Fulltext: [[Ebsco]], on war on terror, 2001–present
* Reardon, Carol. ''Soldiers and Scholars: The U.S. Army and the Uses of Military History, 1865-1920.'' U. Press of Kansas 1990. 270 pp.&amp;nbsp;ISBN 978-0-7006-0466-1.
* Reid, Brian Holden. &quot;American Military History: the Need for Comparative Analysis.&quot; ''Journal of American History'' 2007 93(4): 1154-1157. Issn: 0021-8723 Fulltext: [[History Cooperative]] and [[Ebsco]]
* Reid, Brian Holden, and Joseph G. Dawson III, eds., &quot;Special Issue: The Vistas of American Military History, 1800–1898&quot;, ''American Nineteenth Century History'', 7 (June 2006), 139–321.
* Spector, Ronald H. &quot;Teetering on the Brink of Respectability.&quot; ''Journal of American History'' 2007 93(4): 1158-1160. Issn: 0021-8723 Fulltext: [[History Cooperative]] and [[Ebsco]]
* Spiller, Roger. &quot;Military History and its Fictions.&quot; ''Journal of Military History'' 2006 70(4): 1081-1097. Issn: 0899-3718 Fulltext: [[Ebsco]]
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Military history}}
* [http://www.brill.nl/ibmh ''International Bibliography of Military History''] of the International Commission of Military History
* [http://www.brill.nl/jcmh ''Journal of Chinese Military History'']
*[http://www.smh-hq.org/ Society for Military History]
* [http://www.smh-hq.org/jmh/jmh.html  ''Journal of Military History'']
* [http://www.americanhistoryprojects.com/downloads/mil-2012.html &quot;Web Sources for Military History&quot;]
* [http://www.smh-hq.org/gradguide/gradguide/degree.html Graduate programs in military history]
*[http://www.malc.eu/history/general.warfare.index.html List of Wars World History Database]
*[http://www.historyofwar.org Military History Encyclopedia]
*[http://www.civilization.ca/cwm/explore/military-history Military History - The Canadian War Museum]

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Navboxes
|title=Military History by continent
|state=collapsed
|list1=
{{North America in topic|Military history of}}
{{South America in topic|Military history of}}
{{Military history of Europe}}
{{Asia in topic|Military history of}}
{{Africa in topic|Military history of}}
{{Oceania in topic|Military history of}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Military History}}
[[Category:Military history| ]]
[[Category:Military science|History]]
[[Category:War|History]]
[[Category:Works about the military| ]]

[[ar:تاريخ عسكري]]
[[ca:Història militar]]
[[da:Militærhistorie]]
[[de:Militärgeschichte]]
[[es:Historia militar]]
[[fr:Histoire militaire]]
[[ko:전쟁사]]
[[hi:सैनिक इतिहास]]
[[hr:Vojna povijest]]
[[id:Sejarah militer]]
[[it:Storia militare]]
[[he:היסטוריה צבאית]]
[[ka:სამხედრო ისტორია]]
[[kk:Әскери тарих]]
[[lt:Karo istorija]]
[[ms:Sejarah ketenteraan]]
[[nl:Militaire geschiedenis]]
[[ja:軍事史]]
[[no:Militærhistorie]]
[[pl:Historia wojskowości]]
[[pt:História militar]]
[[ru:Военная история]]
[[simple:Military history]]
[[sl:Vojna zgodovina]]
[[fi:Sodankäynnin historia]]
[[sv:Militärhistoria]]
[[tl:Kasaysayang militar]]
[[th:ประวัติศาสตร์การทหาร]]
[[tr:Askerî tarih]]
[[uk:Військова історія]]
[[zh:軍事史]]</text>
      <sha1>rkd7higqs6tcmrv0p5836thyj1mt0es</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
