<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Modern history</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>885795</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522154944</id>
      <parentid>522154928</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T10:17:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/27.99.25.191|27.99.25.191]] to version by Yobot. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1325056) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="140283">{{Redirect4|Modern|Modern Age}}
&lt;!--
*****
NOTE: The following is a brief summary of the modern age. It covers the key points of the modern era. The key points of each topic have been 'main articled' to other pages where possible; edit individual section of a topic if there is an issue with a section's length.--&gt;

{{Human history}}
'''Modern history''', or the '''modern era''', describes the historical [[timeline]] after the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref&gt;Intrinsic to the English language, &quot;modern&quot; denotes (in reference to history) a period that is opposed to either ancient or medieval—modern history comprising the history of the world since the close of the Middle Ages.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=LaNDmZBcNGQC&amp;pg=PA3814 ''The Century Dictionary and Cyclopedia'', Page 3814]&lt;/ref&gt; Modern history can be further broken down into the ''[[early modern period]]'' and the ''late modern period'' after the [[French Revolution]] and the [[Industrial Revolution]]. ''[[Contemporary history]]'' describes the span of historic events that are immediately relevant to the present time. 

The modern era began approximately in the 16th century.&lt;ref&gt;Dunan, Marcel. ''Larousse Encyclopedia of Modern History, From 1500 to the Present Day''. New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1964.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bartlebyModern&quot; /&gt;  Many major events caused [[Europe]] to change around the turn of the 15th to 16th century, starting with the [[Fall of Constantinople]] in 1453, the fall of [[Muslim Spain]] and the discovery of the [[Americas]] in 1492, and [[Martin Luther]]'s [[Protestant Reformation]] in 1517. In [[England]] the modern period is often dated to the start of the [[Tudor period]] with the victory of [[Henry VII of England|Henry VII]] over [[Richard III of England|Richard III]] at the [[Battle of Bosworth]] in 1485.&lt;ref&gt;Helen Miller, Aubrey Newman. ''Early modern British history, 1485-1760: a select bibliography'', [[Historical Association]], 1970&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.libraries.rutgers.edu/rul/rr_gateway/research_guides/history/texts_by_period.shtml#emp ''Early Modern Period (1485-1800)''], Sites Organized by Period, [[Rutgers University]] Libraries&lt;/ref&gt; [[Early modern Europe]]an history is usually seen to span from the turn of the 14th to 15th century, through the [[Age of Reason]] and the [[Age of Enlightenment]] in the 17th and 18th centuries, until the beginning of the [[Industrial Revolution]] in the late 18th century.

{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

==The study of modern history==
Some events, though born out of context not entirely new, show a new way of perceiving the world. The concept of modernity interprets the general meaning of these events and seeks explanations for major developments.

===Source text===
{{Main|Historical method|Source text}}
The fundamental difficulty of studying modern history is the fact that a plethora of it has been documented up to the present day. It is imperative to consider the reliability of the information obtained from these records.
{{further2|[[Historiography]]|[[Philosophy of history]]}}

===Terminology and usage===

====Pre-Modern====
&lt;!-- &quot;Pre-Modern&quot; redirects here; if changing the title, please change the redirects --&gt;In the Pre-Modern era, many people's sense of self and purpose was often expressed via a [[faith]] in some form of [[deity]], be that in a single [[god]] or in many [[gods]].&lt;ref&gt;Tirosh-Samuelson, H. (2003). ''Happiness in premodern Judaism: Virtue, knowledge, and well-being''. Monographs of the Hebrew Union College, no. 29. Cincinnati, Ohio: Hebrew Union College Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Pre-modern cultures have not been thought of creating a sense of distinct individuality,&lt;ref&gt;''Nation, civil society and social movements: essays in political sociology'' by T. K. Oommen. Page 236.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Premodern Japan: a historical survey'' by Mikiso Hane&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Griffin, D. R. (1990). ''Sacred interconnections: Postmodern spirituality, political economy, and art''. SUNY series in constructive postmodern thought. Albany: State University of New York Press.&lt;/ref&gt; though. Religious officials, who often held positions of power, were the spiritual intermediaries to the common person. It was only through these intermediaries that the general masses had access to the [[Divinity|divine]]. [[Tradition]] was [[sacred]] to ancient cultures and was unchanging and the [[social order]] of [[ceremony]] and [[morals]] in a culture could be strictly enforced.&lt;ref&gt;Maine, H. S., &amp; Dwight, T. W. (1888). ''Ancient law: Its connection with the early history of society and its relation to modern ideas''. New York: H. Holt and Co.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boylan, P. (1922). ''Thoth, the Hermes of Egypt: A study of some aspects of theological thought in ancient Egypt''. London: H. Milford, Oxford university press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fordyce, J. (1888). ''The new social order''. London: Kegan Paul, Trench &amp; Co.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=3w_6bStksAsC ''Lectures on the Early History of Institutions'']&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See also|Ancient history|Medieval history}}

====Modern====
In contrast to the pre-modern era, Western civilization made a [[#Western transformations|gradual transition]] from ''premodernity'' to [[modernity]] when [[scientific method]]s were developed which led many to believe that the use of science would lead to all knowledge, thus throwing back the shroud of [[mythology|myth]] under which pre-modern peoples lived. New information about the world was discovered via [[empirical observation]],&lt;ref&gt;Baird, F. E., &amp; Kaufmann, W. A. (2008). ''Philosophic classics: From Plato to Derrida''. Upper Saddle River, N.J: Pearson/Prentice Hall.&lt;/ref&gt; versus the historic use of [[reason]] and [[innate knowledge]].

The term &quot;modern&quot; was coined shortly before 1585 to describe the beginning of a new era.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartlebyModern&quot;&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/61/28/M0362800.html modern. The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition. 2000&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Renaissance|European Renaissance]] (about 1420–1630) is an important transition period beginning between the [[Late Middle Ages]] and Early Modern Times, which started in Italy.

The term &quot;Early Modern&quot; was introduced in the English language in the 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;''New Dictionary of the History of ideas'', Volume 5, Detroit 2005. Modernism and Modern&lt;/ref&gt; to distinguish the time between what we call Middle Ages and time of the late Enlightenment (1800) (when the meaning of the term Modern Ages was developing its contemporary form). It is important to note that these terms stem from European History. In usage in other parts of the world, such as in Asia, and in Muslim countries, the terms are applied in a very different way, but often in the context with their contact with European culture in the [[Age of Discoveries]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nlm.nih.gov/exhibition/islamic_medical/islamic_14.html ''Islamic Culture and the Medical Arts: Late Medieval and Early Modern Medicine''&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Postmodern and contemporary====
&quot;[[Postmodernism]]&quot;, coined 1949,&lt;!--m-w.com, see below, don't {{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}this--&gt; on the other hand, would describe rather a movement in art than a period of history, and is usually applied to arts, but not to any events of the very recent history.&lt;ref&gt;[http://m-w.com/dictionary/postmodern postmodern - Definition from the Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; This changed when [[postmodernity]] was coined to describe the major changes in the 1950s and 1960s in economy, society, culture, and philosophy. Sometimes distinct from the modern periods themselves, the terms &quot;[[modernity]]&quot; and &quot;[[modernism]]&quot; refer to a new way of thinking, distinct from medieval thinking. &quot;''[[Contemporary history|Contemporary]]''&quot; is applied to more recent events because it means &quot;belonging to the same period&quot; and &quot;current&quot;.

==Modern era==

===Significant developments===
The modern period has been a period of significant development in the fields of [[science]], [[politics]], [[warfare]], and [[technology]]. It has also been an [[age of discovery]] and [[globalization]]. During this time, the [[power (international)|European powers]] and later their colonies, began a political, economic, and cultural [[colonization]] of the rest of the world.

By the late 19th and 20th centuries, [[modernist]] art, politics, science and culture has come to dominate not only [[Western Europe]] and [[North America]], but almost every civilized area on the globe, including movements thought of as opposed to the west and globalization. The modern era is closely associated with the development of [[individualism]],&lt;ref name=&quot;NCEref&quot;&gt;''National, cultural, and ethnic identities: harmony beyond conflict'' by Jaroslav Hroch, David Hollan&lt;/ref&gt; [[capitalism]],&lt;ref&gt;''Capitalism and modernity: the great debate'' by Jack Goody&lt;/ref&gt; [[urbanization]]&lt;ref name=&quot;NCEref&quot; /&gt; and a belief in the possibilities of technological and political [[Progress (history)|progress]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=m9Ha1fmAXk4C ''Progress and its discontents''] American Academy of Arts and Sciences. &quot;[http://books.google.com/books?id=ov86j30F96EC&amp;pg=PA297 Technology and politics].&quot; Western Center&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''A companion to the philosophy of technology'' by Jan-Kyrre Berg Olsen, Stig Andur Pedersen, Vincent F. Hendricks&lt;/ref&gt;

The brutal wars and other problems of this era, many of which come from the effects of rapid change, and the connected loss of strength of traditional religious and ethical norms, have led to many reactions against modern development.&lt;ref&gt;''Marx, Durkheim, Weber: formations of modern social thought'' by Kenneth L. Morrison. Page 294.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;William Schweiker, ''The Blackwell companion to religious ethics''. 2005. Page 454. (cf., &quot;In modernity, however, much of economic activity and theory seemed to be entirely cut off from religious and ethical norms, at least in traditional terms. Many see modern economic developments as entirely secular.&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt; Optimism and belief in constant progress has been most recently criticized by [[postmodernism]] while the dominance of Western Europe and [[Anglo-America]] over other continents has been criticized by [[postcolonialism|postcolonial theory]].

===Modern as post-medieval===
One common use of the term is to describe the condition of Western history since the mid-15th century, or roughly the European development of [[movable type]]&lt;ref&gt;''Early European History'' by [[Henry Kitchell Webster]]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[printing press]].&lt;ref&gt;''The European Reformations'' by Carter Lindberg&lt;/ref&gt; In this context the &quot;modern&quot; society is said to develop over many periods, and to be influenced by important events which represent breaks in the continuity.&lt;ref&gt;''The new Cambridge modern history: Companion volume'' by Peter Burke&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Plains Indian History and Culture: Essays on Continuity and Change'' by John C. Ewers&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Weber, irrationality, and social order'' by Alan Sica&lt;/ref&gt;

====Early modern period====
{{Main|Early modern period}}
The modern era includes the early period, sometimes called the early modern period, which lasted from c.  1500 to around c.  1800 (most often 1815). Particular facets of early modernity include:
*The [[Renaissance]]
*[[Protestant reformation|The Reformation]] and [[Counter Reformation]].
*The [[Age of Discovery]]
*Rise of [[capitalism]]

Important events in the early modern period include:
*The invention of the [[printing press]]
*The [[English Civil War]]

{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin:0 0 1em 1em; width:222px; text-align:left; clear:right;&quot;
|&lt;div style=&quot;background:#f8eaba; text-align:center;&quot;&gt; Modern Age characteristics&lt;/div&gt;
The concept of the modern world as distinct from an ancient or medieval world rests on a sense that the modern world is not just another [[era]] in history, but rather the result of a new type of change. This is usually conceived of as progress driven by deliberate human efforts to better their situation.

Advances in all areas of human activity—[[politics]], [[industry]], [[society]], [[economics]], [[commerce]], [[transport]], [[communication]],  [[mechanization]], [[automation]], [[science]], [[medicine]], [[technology]], and [[culture]]—appear to have transformed an ''Old World'' into the ''Modern'' or ''New World''.&lt;ref name=&quot;GrosvenorModern&quot;&gt;''Contemporary history of the world'' by Edwin Augustus Grosvenor&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MicheletAndSimpson&quot;&gt;''A summary of modern history'' by Jules Michelet, Mary Charlotte Mair Simpson&lt;/ref&gt; In each case, the identification of the old Revolutionary change can be used to demarcate the old and old-fashioned from the modern.&lt;ref name=&quot;GrosvenorModern&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MicheletAndSimpson&quot; /&gt;

Portions of the Modern world altered its relationship with the [[Bible|Biblical]] [[value system]], revalued the [[monarchy|monarchical]] government system, and abolished the [[feudalism|feudal]] economic system, with new [[democratic]] and [[Liberalism|liberal]] ideas in the areas of [[politics]], [[science]], [[psychology]], [[sociology]], and [[economics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GrosvenorModern&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MicheletAndSimpson&quot; /&gt;
|}
This combination of epoch events totally changed thinking and thought in the early modern period, and so their dates serve as well as any to separate the old from the new modes.&lt;ref name=&quot;GrosvenorModern&quot; /&gt; Particular ways to categorize early modernity include:
*[[Age of Reason|The Age of Reason]]
*[[The Enlightenment]]
*[[Romanticism|the Romantic]] era
*[[Victorianism|the Victorian]] era

As an [[Age of Revolution]]s dawned, beginning with those revolts in [[American Revolution|America]] and [[French Revolution|France]], political changes were then pushed forward in other countries partly as a result of upheavals of the [[Napoleonic Wars]] and their impact on thought and thinking, from concepts from nationalism to organizing armies.&lt;ref&gt;Crawley, C. W. (1965). [[Cambridge Modern History|The new Cambridge modern history]]. Volume 9., ''War and peace in an age of upheaval 1793-1830''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Goldman, E. O., &amp; Eliason, L. C. (2003). The diffusion of military technology and ideas. Stanford, Calif: Stanford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boot, M. (2006). ''War made new: Technology, warfare, and the course of history, 1500 to today''. New York: Gotham Books.&lt;/ref&gt;

The early period ended in a time of political and economic change as a result of [[mechanization]] in society, the [[American Revolution]], the first [[French Revolution]]; other factors included the redrawing of the map of Europe by the [[wikisource:Final Act of the Congress of Vienna|Final Act]] of the [[Congress of Vienna]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last= Bloy
  | first = Marjie
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = The Congress of Vienna, 1 November 1814 – 8 June 1815
  | work =
  | publisher = The Victorian Web
  | date = 30 April 2002
  | url = http://www.victorianweb.org/history/forpol/vienna.html
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2009-01-09}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and the peace established by [[Treaty of Paris (1815)|Second Treaty of Paris]] which ended the Napoleonic Wars.&lt;ref&gt;Hazen, Charles Downer (1910). ''Europe since 1815''. American historical series, H. Holt and Company.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Late modern period====
As a result of the [[Industrial Revolution]] and the earlier political revolutions, the worldviews of [[Modernism]] emerged. The industrialization of many nations was initiated with the industrialization of Britain. Particular facets of the late modernity period include:
*Increasing role of [[science]] and [[technology]]
*Mass [[literacy]] and proliferation of [[mass media]]
*Spread of [[social movements]]
*Institution of [[representative democracy]]
*[[Individualism]]
*[[Industrialization]]
*[[Urbanization]]

Other important events in the development of the Late modern period include:
*The [[Revolutions of 1848]]
*The [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]]
*[[The First World War]] and the [[Second World War]]

Our most recent era{{mdash}}Modern Times{{mdash}}begins with the end of these revolutions in the 19th century,&lt;ref&gt;Duruy, V., &amp; Grosvenor, E. A. (1894). ''History of modern times: From the fall of Constantinople to the French revolution''. New York: H. Holt and company.&lt;/ref&gt; and includes the World Wars era&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, P. (2001). ''Modern times: The world from the twenties to the nineties''. New York: HarperPerennial.&lt;/ref&gt; (encompassing [[World War I]] and [[World War II]]) and the emergence of [[socialism|socialist countries]] that lead to the [[Cold War]]. The ''contemporary era'' follows shortly afterward with the explosion of research and increase of knowledge known as the [[Information Age]] in the latter 20th and the early 21st century. Today's [[Postmodernism|Postmodern]] era is seen in widespread [[Digitality]].&lt;ref&gt;Martín Lister, ''New media: a critical introduction''. Psychology Press, 2003. Page 14&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early modern period==
{{Main|Early modern period}}
[[Image:Waldseemuller map 2.jpg|thumb|center|550px|[[Waldseemüller map]] with joint sheets, 1507]]
{{clear left}}
The early modern period is a term used by historians to refer to the period from approximately 1500 to 1800. follows the Late Middle Ages period, and is marked by the first European colonies, the rise of strong centralized governments, and the beginnings of recognizable nation states that are the direct antecedents of today's states.

In Africa and the Ottoman Empire, the Muslim expansion took place in North and East Africa. In West Africa, various native nations existed. The Indian Empires and civilizations of Southeast Asia were a vital link in the spice trade. On the Indian subcontinent, the Great Mughal Empire existed. The archipelagic empires, the Sultanate of Malacca and later the Sultanate of Johor, controlled the southern areas.

Concerning the Asia, various Chinese dynasties and Japanese shogunates controlled the Asian sphere. In Japan, the Edo period from 1600 to 1868 is also sometimes referred to as the early modern period. And in Korea, from the rising of Joseon Dynasty to the enthronement of King Gojong is referred to as the early modern period. In the Americas, Native Americans had built a large and varied civilization, including the Aztec Empire and alliance, the Inca civilization, the Mayan Empire and cities, and the Chibcha Confederation. In the west, the European kingdoms and movements were in a movement of reformation and expansion. Russia reached the Pacific coast in 1647 and consolidated its control over the [[Russian Far East]] in the 19th century.

Later religious trends of the period saw the end of the expansion of Muslims and the Muslim world. Christians and Christendom saw the end of the Crusades and end of religious unity under the Roman Catholic Church. It was during this time that the Inquisitions and Protestant reformations took place.

[[Image:colonisation2.gif|thumb|center|550px|World Colonization of 1492 (Early Modern World), 1550, 1660 (Age of Enlightenment), 1754 (Age of Revolution), 1822 (Industrial revolution), 1885 (European Hegemony), 1914 (World War I era), 1938 (World War II era), 1959 (Cold War era), 1974 (Recent history), and 2008 (Contemporary era).]]
During the early modern period, an age of discovery and trade was undertaken by the European nations. European powers went on a colonial expansion and took possession throughout the world. There was a conquest of the Americas and exploitation of its resources. Various European powers set up colonies in North America and Latin America.

Toward the end of the early period, Europe was dominated by the evolving system of mercantile capitalism in its trade and the New Economy. European states and politics had the characteristic of Absolutism. The French power and English revolutions dominated the political scene. There eventually evolved an international balance of power that held sway a great conflagration until years later.

The end date of the early modern period is usually associated with the Industrial Revolution, which began in Britain in about 1750. Another significant date is 1789, the beginning of the French Revolution, which drastically transformed the state of European politics and ushered in the Prince Edward Era and modern Europe.

===Eastern foundations===
{{main|Qing Dynasty|Mughal Empire|Maratha Empire|Tokugawa shogunate}}

In China, urbanization increased as the population grew and as the division of labor grew more complex. Large urban centers, such as [[Nanjing]] and [[Beijing]], also contributed to the growth of private industry. In particular, small-scale industries grew up, often specializing in paper, silk, cotton, and porcelain goods. For the most part, however, relatively small urban centers with markets proliferated around the country. Town markets mainly traded food, with some necessary manufactures such as pins or oil. Despite the [[xenophobia]] and intellectual introspection characteristic of the increasingly popular new school of [[neo-Confucianism]], China under the early Ming Dynasty was not isolated. Foreign trade and other contacts with the outside world, particularly Japan, increased considerably. Chinese merchants explored all of the [[Indian Ocean]], reaching East Africa with the voyages of [[Zheng He]].

The Qing Dynasty (1644&amp;ndash;1911) was founded after the defeat of the [[Ming Dynasty|Ming]], the last [[Han Chinese]] [[dynasty]], by the [[Manchus]]. The Manchus were formerly known as the ''[[Jurchen people|Jurchen]]''. When Beijing was captured by [[Li Zicheng]]'s peasant rebels in 1644, the last Ming Emperor [[Chongzhen]] committed suicide. The Manchu then allied with Ming Dynasty general [[Wu Sangui]] and seized control of [[Beijing]], which became the new capital of the Qing dynasty. The Manchus adopted the Confucian norms of traditional Chinese government in their rule of [[China proper]].

In Japan following the [[Sengoku Period]] of &quot;warring states&quot;, central government had been largely reestablished by [[Oda Nobunaga]] and [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]] during the [[Azuchi-Momoyama period]]. After the [[Battle of Sekigahara]] in 1600, central authority fell to [[Tokugawa Ieyasu]] who completed this process and received the title of ''[[shogun]]'' in 1603. In order to become shogun, one traditionally was a descendant of the ancient [[Minamoto clan]].

[[Edo society|Society in the Japanese &quot;Tokugawa period&quot;]], unlike the shogunates before it, was supposedly based on the strict class [[hierarchy]] originally established by [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]]. The [[daimyo]], or lords, were at the top, followed by the [[warrior]]-caste of [[samurai]], with the [[farmer]]s, [[artisans]], and [[merchant|trader]]s ranking below. In some parts of the country, particularly smaller regions, ''daimyo'' and ''samurai'' were more or less identical, since ''daimyo'' might be trained as ''samurai'', and ''samurai'' might act as local lords.  Otherwise, the largely inflexible nature of this [[social stratification]] system unleashed disruptive forces over time. [[Taxes]] on the [[peasantry]] were set at fixed amounts which did not account for [[inflation]] or other changes in [[monetary]] value. As a result, the tax revenues collected by the samurai landowners were worth less and less over time. This often led to numerous confrontations between noble but impoverished samurai and well-to-do peasants, ranging from simple local disturbances to much bigger [[rebellion]]s. None, however, proved compelling enough to seriously challenge the established order until the arrival of foreign powers.

On the [[Indian subcontinent]], the Mughal Empire ruled most of India in the early 18th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/southasia/History/Mughals/mughals.html &quot;The Mughal Empire&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;classic period&quot; ended with the death and defeat of Emperor [[Aurangzeb]] in 1707 by the rising [[Hindu]] Maratha Empire,&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Mughal Empire (1500s, 1600s)|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/mughalempire_1.shtml|work=bbc.co.uk|publisher=BBC|accessdate=18 October 2010|location=London|at=Section 5: Aurangzeb}}&lt;/ref&gt; although the dynasty continued for another 150 years. During this period, the Empire was marked by a highly centralized administration connecting the different regions. All the significant monuments of the Mughals, their most visible legacy, date to this period which was characterised by the expansion of Persian cultural influence in the Indian subcontinent, with brilliant literary, artistic, and architectural results. The Maratha Empire was located in the south west of present-day India and expanded greatly under the rule of the [[Peshwa]]s, the prime ministers of the Maratha empire. In 1761, the Maratha army lost the [[Third Battle of Panipat]] which halted imperial expansion and the empire was then divided into a confederacy of Maratha states.

===Western transformations===
&lt;!-- linked to by the above section &quot;Premodern&quot;; if you change the section title, please change the link ... also linked to the 'Late modern period' redirect--&gt;

====Tsardom of Russia====
{{Main|Tsardom of Russia}}
Russia experienced territorial growth through the 17th century, which was the age of [[Cossacks]]. Cossacks were warriors organized into military communities, resembling [[pirates]] and [[pioneers of the New World]]. In 1648, the peasants of [[Ukraine]] joined the [[Zaporozhian Cossacks]] in rebellion against Poland-Lithuania during the [[Khmelnytsky Uprising]], because of the social and religious oppression they suffered under Polish rule. In 1654 the Ukrainian leader, [[Bohdan Khmelnytsky]], offered to place Ukraine under the protection of the Russian Tsar, [[Aleksey I]]. Aleksey's acceptance of this offer led to another [[Russo-Polish War (1654–1667)]]. Finally, Ukraine was split along the river [[Dnieper]], leaving the western part (or [[Right-bank Ukraine]]) under Polish rule and eastern part ([[Left-bank Ukraine]] and [[Kiev]]) under Russian. Later, in 1670–71 the [[Don Cossacks]] led by [[Stenka Razin]] initiated a major uprising in the Volga region, but the Tsar's troops were successful in defeating the rebels. In the east, the rapid Russian exploration and colonisation of the huge territories of Siberia was led mostly by Cossacks hunting for valuable [[fur]]s and [[ivory]]. [[Russian explorers]] pushed eastward primarily along the [[Siberian river routes]], and by the mid-17th century there were Russian settlements in the Eastern Siberia, on the [[Chukchi Peninsula]], along the [[Amur River]], and on the Pacific coast. In 1648 the [[Bering Strait]] between Asia and North America was passed for the first time by [[Fedot Popov]] and [[Semyon Dezhnyov]].

====Reason and Enlightenment====
{{Further|Great Divergence}}
Traditionally, the European intellectual transformation of and after the Renaissance bridged the Middle Ages and the Modern era. The [[Age of Reason]] in the Western world is generally regarded as being the start of [[modern philosophy]],&lt;ref&gt;For example, ''[[Conversations on the Plurality of Worlds]]'' offered an explanation of the heliocentric model of the Universe.&lt;/ref&gt; and a departure from the medieval approach, especially [[Scholasticism]]. Early 17th century philosophy is often called the Age of Rationalism and is considered to succeed Renaissance philosophy and precede the Age of Enlightenment, but some consider it as the earliest part of the Enlightenment era in philosophy, extending that era to two centuries. The 18th century saw the beginning of [[secularization]] in Europe, rising to notability in the wake of the [[French Revolution]].

The [[Age of Enlightenment]] is a term used to describe a time in [[Western philosophy]] and cultural life centered upon the 18th century, in which reason was advocated as the primary source and legitimacy for authority. Developing more or less simultaneously in many parts of Europe and America. Developing during the Enlightenment era, [[Renaissance humanism]] was an intellectual movement spread across Europe. The basic training of the humanist was to speak well and write (typically, in the form of a letter). The term ''umanista'' comes from the latter part of the 15th century. The people were associated with the ''[[studia humanitatis]]'', a novel curriculum that was competing with the ''[[quadrivium]]'' and [[scholastic logic]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Paul Oskar Kristeller]], ''Humanism'', pp. 113-4, in Charles B. Schmitt, [[Quentin Skinner]] (editors), ''The Cambridge History of Renaissance Philosophy'' (1990).&lt;/ref&gt;

Renaissance humanism took a close study of the Latin and Greek classical texts, and was antagonistic to the values of [[scholasticism]] with its emphasis on the accumulated commentaries; and humanists were involved in the sciences, philosophies, arts and poetry of classical antiquity. They self-consciously imitated [[classical Latin]] and deprecated the use of [[medieval Latin]]. By analogy with the perceived decline of Latin, they applied the principle of ''[[ad fontes]]'', or back to the sources, across broad areas of learning.

The [[quarrel of the Ancients and the Moderns]] was a [[literature|literary]] and artistic quarrel that heated up in the early 1690s and shook the [[Académie française]]. It opposed two sides, the Ancients (''Anciens'') who constrain choice of subjects to those drawn from the literature of [[Classical antiquity|Antiquity]] and the Moderns (''Modernes''), who supported the merits of the authors of the century of [[Louis XIV of France|Louis XIV]]. [[Bernard le Bovier de Fontenelle|Fontenelle]] quickly followed with his ''Digression sur les anciens et les modernes'' (1688), in which he took the Modern side, pressing the argument that modern scholarship allowed modern man to surpass the ancients in knowledge.

====Scientific Revolution====
{{Main|Scientific Revolution}}
The Scientific Revolution was a period when European ideas in [[classical physics]], [[classical astronomy|astronomy]], [[classical biology|biology]], [[classical human anatomy|human anatomy]], [[classical chemistry|chemistry]], and other [[classical science]]s were rejected and led to doctrines supplanting those that had prevailed from [[Ancient Greece]] to the Middle Ages which would lead to a transition to [[modern science]]. This period saw a fundamental transformation in scientific ideas across [[physics]], [[astronomy]], and [[biology]], in institutions supporting [[scientific investigation]], and in the more [[worldview|widely held picture of the universe]]. Individuals started to question all manners of things and it was this questioning that led to the Scientific Revolution, which in turn formed the foundations of contemporary sciences and the establishment of several modern scientific fields.

{{See also|History of electromagnetism|Science in the Age of Enlightenment}}

====American wars and revolution====
The [[French and Indian Wars]] were a series of conflicts in North America that represented the actions there that accompanied the European dynastic wars. In Quebec, the wars are generally referred to as the Intercolonial Wars. While some conflicts involved Spanish and Dutch forces, all pitted Great Britain, its colonies and American Indian allies on one side and France, its colonies and Indian allies on the other.

The expanding French and British colonies were contending for control of the western, or interior, territories. Whenever the European countries went to war, there were actions within and by these colonies although the dates of the conflict did not necessarily exactly coincide with those of the larger conflicts.

[[Image:Declaration independence.jpg|thumb|[[John Trumbull]]'s ''[[Trumbull's Declaration of Independence|Declaration of Independence]]'', showing the five-man committee in charge of drafting the Declaration in 1776 as it presents its work to the [[Second Continental Congress]] in [[Philadelphia]]]]
Beginning in the Age of Revolution, the [[American Revolution]] and the ensuing political upheaval during the last half of the 18th century saw the Thirteen Colonies of North America overthrow the governance of the Parliament of Great Britain, and then reject the British monarchy itself to become the sovereign United States of America. In this period the colonies first rejected the authority of the Parliament to govern them without representation, and formed self-governing independent states. The Second Continental Congress then joined together against the British to defend that self-governance in the armed conflict from 1775 to 1783 known as the American Revolutionary War (also called American War of Independence).

The American Revolution begun with fighting at Lexington and Concord. On July 4, 1776, they issued the Declaration of Independence, which proclaimed their independence from Great Britain and their formation of a cooperative union. In June 1776, [[Benjamin Franklin]] was appointed a member of the Committee of Five that drafted the [[Declaration of Independence]]. Although he was temporarily disabled by gout and unable to attend most meetings of the Committee, Franklin made several small changes to the draft sent to him by [[Thomas Jefferson]].

The rebellious states defeated Great Britain in the [[American Revolutionary War]], the first successful colonial war of independence. While the states had already rejected the governance of Parliament, through the Declaration the new United States now rejected the legitimacy of the monarchy to demand allegiance. The war raged for seven years, with effective American victory, followed by formal British abandonment of any claims to the United States with the Treaty of Paris.

[[File:North America 1797 - U.S. Bureau of the Census, 1909.jpg|thumb|right|North America 1797]]
The [[Philadelphia Convention]] set up the current United States; the [[United States Constitution]] ratification the following year made the states part of a single republic with a limited central government. The [[Bill of Rights]], comprising ten constitutional amendments guaranteeing many fundamental civil rights and freedoms, was ratified in 1791.

====The French Revolutions====
{{Main|French Revolution}}
Toward the middle and latter stages of the Age of Revolution, the French political and social revolutions and radical change saw the French governmental structure, previously an absolute monarchy with feudal privileges for the aristocracy and Catholic clergy transform, change to forms based on Enlightenment principles of citizenship and inalienable rights. The first revolution led to government by the [[National Assembly (French Revolution)|National Assembly]], the second by the [[Legislative Assembly (France)|Legislative Assembly]], and the third by the [[French Directory|Directory]].

The changes were accompanied by violent turmoil which included the trial and execution of the king, vast bloodshed and repression during the Reign of Terror, and warfare involving every other major European power. Subsequent events that can be traced to the Revolution include the Napoleonic Wars, two separate restorations of the monarchy, and two additional revolutions as modern France took shape. In the following century, France would be governed at one point or another as a republic, constitutional monarchy, and two different empires.

=====National and Legislative Assembly=====
{{Main|National Assembly (French Revolution)|Legislative Assembly (France)}}
During the French Revolution, the National Assembly, which existed from June 17 to July 9 of 1789, was a transitional body between the Estates-General and the National Constituent Assembly.

The Legislative Assembly was the legislature of France from October 1, 1791 to September 1792. It provided the focus of political debate and revolutionary law-making between the periods of the National Constituent Assembly and of the National Convention.

=====The Directory and Napoleonic Era=====
{{Main|French Directory|Napoleonic Era}}
The Executive Directory was a body of five Directors that held executive power in France following the Convention and preceding the Consulate. The period of this regime (2 November 1795 until 10 November 1799), commonly known as the Directory (or Directoire) era, constitutes the second to last stage of the French Revolution.

The Napoleonic Era is a period in the [[History of France]] and Europe. It is generally classified as the fourth stage of the French Revolution. The Napoleonic Era begins roughly with [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon]]'s [[coup d'état]], overthrowing the Directory and ends at the [[Hundred Days]] and his defeat at [[Waterloo, Belgium|Waterloo]] (November 9, 1799 – June 28, 1815).  The congress of Vienna soon set out to restore Europe to pre-French revolution days.

====Italian unification====
[[Italian unification]] was the political and social movement that annexed different states of the [[Italian peninsula]] into the single state of Italy in the 19th century. There is a lack of consensus on the exact dates for the beginning and the end of this period, but many scholars agree that the process began with the end of Napoleonic rule and the [[Congress of Vienna]] in 1815, and approximately ended with the [[Franco-Prussian War]] in 1871, though the last ''[[Italia irredenta|città irredente]]'' did not join the [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Kingdom of Italy]] until after World War I.

====Eastern colonization====
The development of [[New Imperialism]] saw the conquest of nearly all eastern hemisphere territories by colonial powers. The [[Company rule in India|commercial colonization of India]] commenced in 1757, after the [[Battle of Plassey]], when the [[Nawab of Bengal]] surrendered his dominions to the British East India Company,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bose|Jalal|2003|p=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 1765, when the Company was granted the ''diwani'', or the right to collect revenue, in [[Bengal]] and [[Bihar]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Brown|1994|p=46}}, {{Harvnb|Peers|2006|p=30}}&lt;/ref&gt; or in 1772, when the Company established a capital in [[Calcutta]], appointed its first [[Governor-General of India|Governor-General]], [[Warren Hastings]], and became directly involved in governance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Metcalf|Metcalf|p=56}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Maratha Empire|Maratha states]], following the [[Anglo-Maratha wars]], eventually lost to the [[British East India Company]] in 1818. The rule lasted until 1858, when, after the [[Indian rebellion of 1857]] and consequent of the [[Government of India Act 1858]], the [[India Office|British government]] assumed the task of directly administering India in the new [[British Raj]]. In 1819 [[Stamford Raffles]] established [[Singapore]] as a key trading post for Britain in their rivalry with the Dutch. However, their rivalry cooled in 1824 when an [[Anglo-Dutch Treaty of 1824|Anglo-Dutch treaty]] demarcated their respective interests in Southeast Asia. From the 1850s onwards, the pace of colonization shifted to a significantly higher gear.

The [[Dutch East India Company]] (1800) and [[British East India Company]] (1858) were dissolved by their respective governments, who took over the direct administration of the colonies. Only [[Thailand]] was spared the experience of foreign rule, although, Thailand itself was also greatly affected by the power politics of the Western powers. Colonial rule had a profound effect on Southeast Asia. While the colonial powers profited much from the region's vast resources and large market, colonial rule did develop the region to a varying extent.&lt;ref&gt;Commercial agriculture, mining and an export based economy developed rapidly during this period.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Decolonization of the Americas ====
{{Main|Decolonization of the Americas|Spanish American wars of independence}}

Decolonization of the Americas refers to the process by which the countries in the Americas gained their independence from European rule. Decolonization began with a series of revolutions in the late 18th and early-to-mid-19th centuries. The Spanish American wars of independence were the numerous wars against Spanish rule in Spanish America that took place during the early 19th century, from 1808 until 1829, directly related to the Napoleonic French invasion of Spain. The conflict started with short-lived governing juntas established in Chuquisaca and Quito opposing the composition of the Supreme Central Junta of Seville.

{| style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;  class=&quot;toccolours&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#f8eaba; text-align:center;&quot;|
&lt;center&gt;
; Decolonization of the Americas
&lt;/center&gt;
|-
|
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Americas independence map.PNG|Countries in the Americas by date of independence. Note that the United States did not complete its continental territorial expansion until 1867
File:Hisparevol.gif|''Development of Spanish American Independence''
File:Spanish Empire - 1824.jpg|Map of territories that became independent during those wars (blue).
&lt;/gallery&gt;
|}

When the Central Junta fell to the French, numerous new Juntas appeared all across the Americas, eventually resulting in a chain of newly independent countries stretching from Argentina and Chile in the south, to Mexico in the north. After the death of the king Ferdinand VII, in 1833, only Cuba and Puerto Rico remained under Spanish rule, until the Spanish–American War in 1898. Unlike the Spanish, the Portuguese did not divide their colonial territory in America. The captaincies they created were subdued to a centralized administration in Salvador (later relocated to Rio de Janeiro) which reported directly to the Portuguese Crown until its independence in 1822, becoming the [[Empire of Brazil]].

{{See also|Latin American wars of independence|Timeline of the Spanish American wars of independence}}

==Modern Age==
''Late modern period''

===Industrial revolutions===
{{Main|Industrial Revolution|Second Industrial Revolution}}
[[Image:Maquina vapor Watt ETSIIM.jpg|thumb|A [[Watt steam engine]]. The development of the [[steam engine]] started the Industrial Revolution in [[United Kingdom|Great Britain]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Watt steam engine]] image: located in the lobby of into the Superior Technical School of Industrial Engineers of a the UPM ([[Madrid]])&lt;/ref&gt; The steam engine was created to pump water from coal mines, enabling them to be deepened beyond [[groundwater]] levels.]] The date of the [[Industrial Revolution]] is not exact. [[Eric Hobsbawm]] held that it 'broke out' in the 1780s and was not fully felt until the 1830s or 1840s,&lt;ref&gt;Eric Hobsbawm, ''The Age of Revolution: Europe 1789–1848'', Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.  ISBN 0-349-10484-0&lt;/ref&gt; while [[T.S. Ashton]] held that it occurred roughly between 1760 and 1830 (in effect the reigns of [[George III of the United Kingdom|George III]], The [[English Regency|Regency]], and [[George IV of the United Kingdom|George IV]]).&lt;ref&gt;Joseph E Inikori.  [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0521010799&amp;id=y7rhKYWhCyIC&amp;pg=PA102&amp;lpg=PA102&amp;sig=zOPr9UkQv258KyhCkuFM0abERnI  ''Africans and the Industrial Revolution in England''], Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-01079-9.&lt;/ref&gt; The great changes of centuries before the 19th were more connected with ideas, religion or military conquest, and technological advance had only made small changes in the material wealth of ordinary people.

The first Industrial Revolution merged into the [[Second Industrial Revolution]] around 1850, when technological and economic progress gained momentum with the development of steam-powered ships and railways, and later in the 19th century with the [[internal combustion engine]] and [[electric power]] generation. The Second Industrial Revolution was a phase of the Industrial Revolution; sometimes labeled as the separate Technical Revolution. From a technological and a social point of view there is no clean break between the two. Major innovations during the period occurred in the chemical, electrical, petroleum, and steel industries. Specific advancements included the introduction of oil fired steam turbine and internal combustion driven steel ships, the development of the airplane, the practical commercialization of the automobile, mass production of consumer goods, the perfection of canning, mechanical refrigeration and other food preservation techniques, and the invention of the telephone.

====Industrialization====
[[Industrialization]] is the process of social and economic change whereby a human group is transformed from a pre-industrial society into an industrial one. It is a subdivision of a more general [[modernization|modernization process]], where [[social change]] and [[economic development]] are closely related with [[innovation|technological innovation]], particularly with the development of large-scale energy and metallurgy production. It is the extensive organization of an economy for the purpose of manufacturing. Industrialization also introduces a form of philosophical change, where people obtain a different attitude towards their [[nature|perception of nature]].

====Revolution in manufacture and power====
An [[economic system|economy]] based on [[manual labour]] was replaced by one dominated by industry and the manufacture of machinery.  It began with the mechanization of the [[textile]] industries and the development of [[iron]]-making techniques, and trade expansion was enabled by the introduction of [[canal]]s, improved roads, and then [[rail transport|railways]].

The introduction of [[steam engine|steam power]] (fuelled primarily by [[coal]]) and powered machinery (mainly in [[textile manufacturing]]) underpinned the dramatic increases in production capacity.&lt;ref&gt;Business and Economics.  [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0195115899&amp;id=CX9kBaVx4JkC&amp;pg=PA98&amp;lpg=PA98&amp;sig=V0eO27c7koD8rrIV2EKv6-guB5s  ''Leading Issues in Economic Development''], Oxford University Press US. ISBN 0-19-511589-9.&lt;/ref&gt;  The development of all-metal [[machine tool]]s in the first two decades of the 19th century facilitated the manufacture of more production machines for manufacturing in other industries.

The modern [[petroleum industry]] started in 1846 with the discovery of the process of refining [[kerosene]] from [[coal]] by [[Nova Scotia]]n [[Abraham Pineo Gesner]]. [[Ignacy Łukasiewicz]] improved Gesner's method to develop a means of refining kerosene from the more readily available &quot;rock oil&quot; (&quot;petr-oleum&quot;) [[seep]]s in 1852 and the first rock oil mine was built in [[Bóbrka, Krosno County|Bóbrka]], near [[Krosno]] in [[Galicia (Central Europe)|Galicia]] in the following year. In 1854, [[Benjamin Silliman]], a science professor at [[Yale University]] in [[New Haven, Connecticut|New Haven]], was the first to fractionate petroleum by distillation. These discoveries rapidly spread around the world.

====Notable engineers====
Engineering achievements of the revolution ranged from electrification to developments in materials science. The advancements made a great contribution to the quality of life. In the first revolution, [[Lewis Paul]] was the original inventor of roller spinning, the basis of the water frame for spinning cotton in a cotton mill. [[Matthew Boulton]] and [[James Watt]]'s improvements to the steam engine were fundamental to the changes brought by the Industrial Revolution in both the Kingdom of Great Britain and the world.

[[Image:Teslathinker.jpg|thumb|right|Nikola Tesla, with [[Roger Joseph Boscovich|Ruđer Bošković]]'s book ''Theoria Philosophiae Naturalis'', sits in front of the spiral coil of his high-frequency transformer at East Houston Street, New York.]]
In the latter part of the second revolution, [[Thomas Alva Edison]] developed many devices that greatly influenced life around the world  and is often credited with the creation of the first industrial research laboratory. In 1882, Edison switched on the world's first large-scale [[electrical supply network]] that provided 110 volts direct current to fifty-nine customers in lower Manhattan. Also toward the end of the second industrial revolution, [[Nikola Tesla]] made many contributions in the field of [[electricity]] and [[magnetism]] in the late 19th and early 20th centuries. Much of Tesla's early work in electrical engineering and many of his discoveries were of importance. Tesla's patents and theoretical work formed the basis of modern [[alternating current electric power]] systems, including the [[polyphase system]]s [[power distribution]] and the [[alternating current motor]], with which he helped usher in the Second Industrial Revolution. In 1887, Tesla filed a number of patents related to a competing form of power distribution known as alternating current. In the following years a bitter rivalry between Tesla and Edison, known as the &quot;[[War of Currents]]&quot;, took place over the preferred method of distribution. After Tesla's demonstration of [[wireless communication]] (radio) in 1894 and after being the victor in the &quot;War of Currents&quot;, he was widely respected as one of the greatest electrical engineers who worked in America.

====Social effects and classes====
The Industrial Revolutions were major [[technology|technological]], [[socioeconomics|socioeconomic]], and [[culture|cultural]] changes in late 18th and early 19th centuries that began in Britain and spread throughout the world. The effects spread throughout [[Western Europe]] and North America during the 19th century, eventually affecting the majority of the world. The impact of this change on [[society]] was enormous and is often compared to the [[Neolithic revolution]], when mankind developed [[agriculture]] and gave up its [[nomad|nomadic lifestyle]].&lt;ref&gt;Russell Brown, Lester. [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN1853839043&amp;id=5aCyfUsHM6kC&amp;pg=PA93&amp;lpg=PA93&amp;sig=1dsUat9P_-9dWWVRMpPt1udT8DQ ''Eco-Economy''], James &amp; James, Earthscan. ISBN 1-85383-904-3.&lt;/ref&gt;
It has been argued that [[Gross Domestic Product|GDP]] per capita was much more stable and progressed at a much slower rate until the industrial revolution and the emergence of the modern [[capitalism|capitalist]] economy, and that it has since increased rapidly in capitalist countries.&lt;ref&gt;Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis [http://www.minneapolisfed.org/pubs/region/04-05/essay.cfm  essay] retrieved March 11, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Mid-19th century European revolts =====
The [[Revolutions of 1848|European Revolutions of 1848]], known in some countries as the Spring of Nations or the Year of Revolution, were a series of political upheavals throughout the European continent. Described as a revolutionary wave, the period of unrest began in France and then, further propelled by the French Revolution of 1848, soon spread to the rest of Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Cayley, E. S. (1856). ''The European revolutions of 1848''. London: Smith, Elder &amp; Co. Vol. I and II.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harding, S. B., &amp; Hart, A. B. (1918). ''New medieval and modern history''. New York: American book company.&lt;/ref&gt; Although most of the revolutions were quickly put down, there was a significant amount of violence in many areas, with tens of thousands of people tortured and killed. While the immediate political effects of the revolutions were reversed, the long-term reverberations of the events were far-reaching.

=====Industrial age reformism=====
Industrial age [[reform movement]]s began the gradual change of society rather with episodes of rapid fundamental changes. The reformists' ideas were often grounded in liberalism, although they also possessed aspects of utopian, socialist or religious concepts. The Radical movement campaigned for electoral reform, a reform of the Poor Laws, free trade, educational reform, postal reform, prison reform, and public sanitation.

Following the Enlightenment's ideas, the reformers looked to the [[Scientific Revolution]] and industrial progress to solve the social problems which arose with the Industrial Revolution. Newton's natural philosophy combined a mathematics of axiomatic proof with the mechanics of physical observation, yielding a coherent system of verifiable predictions and replacing a previous reliance on revelation and inspired truth. Applied to public life, this approach yielded several successful campaigns for changes in social policy.

====Imperial Russia====
{{Main|Russian Empire}}

Under [[Peter I of Russia|Peter I]] (''the Great''), Russia was proclaimed an Empire in 1721 and became recognized as a world power. Ruling from 1682 to 1725, Peter defeated Sweden in the [[Great Northern War]], forcing it to cede West [[Karelia]] and [[Ingria]] (two regions lost by Russia in the [[Time of Troubles]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Solovyov, S.|title=History of Russia from the Earliest Times|publisher=AST|year=2001|volume=9, ch.1|url=http://militera.lib.ru/common/solovyev1/09_01.html|isbn=5-17-002142-9|accessdate=27 December  2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[Governorate of Estonia|Estland]] and [[Livland]], securing Russia's access to the sea and sea trade.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Solovyov, S.|title=History of Russia from the Earliest Times|publisher=AST|year=2001|volume=15, ch.1|url=http://militera.lib.ru/common/solovyev1/15_01.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the [[Baltic Sea]] Peter founded a new capital called [[Saint Petersburg]], later known as Russia's ''Window to Europe''. [[Peter the Great's reforms]] brought considerable Western European cultural influences to Russia. [[Catherine the Great|Catherine II]] (''the Great''), who ruled in 1762–96, extended Russian political control over the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth and incorporated most of its territories into Russia during the [[Partitions of Poland]], pushing the Russian frontier westward into Central Europe. In the south, after successful [[Russo-Turkish Wars]] against the [[Ottoman Empire]], Catherine advanced Russia's boundary to the Black Sea, defeating the [[Crimean khanate]].

===European Hegemony and the 19th century===
[[File:World head of states in 1889.jpg|400px|thumb|alt=Painting of a group of standing and seated heads of state in a variety of national uniforms and formal dress|&quot;The World's Sovereigns&quot;, 1889.]]
{{Main|19th century}}

Historians sometimes define the 19th century [[List of time periods|historical era]] stretching from 1815 (the [[Congress of Vienna]]) to 1914 (the outbreak of the [[World War I|First World War]]); alternatively, [[Eric Hobsbawm]] defined the [[The long 19th century|&quot;Long Nineteenth Century&quot;]] as spanning the years 1789 to 1914. During this time, the fall of the [[Spanish Armada]] enabled the rise of the [[British Empire]].

====Imperialism and empires====
{{Main|Imperialism}}
During the 19th century, the [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]], [[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese]], and [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] empires began to crumble and the [[Holy Roman Empire|Holy Roman]] and [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] empires ceased. Following the [[Napoleonic Wars]], the [[British Empire]] became the world's leading power, controlling one quarter of the World's population and one third of the land area. It enforced a [[Pax Britannica]], encouraged trade, and battled rampant piracy.

Electricity, steel, and petroleum  enabled Germany to become [[Power (international)|great international power]] that [[New Imperialism|raced to create empires of its own]]. The [[Meiji Restoration]] was a chain of events that led to enormous changes in Japan's political and social structure that was taking a firm hold at the beginning of the [[Meiji Era]] which coincided the opening of Japan by the arrival of the [[Black Ships]] of [[Commodore (USN)|Commodore]] [[Matthew C. Perry|Matthew Perry]] and made [[Imperial Japan]] a [[great power]]. However, [[Imperial Russia|Russia]] and [[Qing Dynasty]] China failed to keep pace with the other world powers which led to massive social unrest in both empires. The Qing Dynasty's military power weakened during the 19th century, and faced with international pressure, massive [[rebellion]]s and defeats in wars, the dynasty declined after the mid-19th century. European powers controlled parts of Oceania, with French [[New Caledonia]] from 1853 and [[French Polynesia]] from 1889; the Germans established colonies in [[German New Guinea|New Guinea]] in 1884, and [[German Samoa|Samoa]] in 1900. The United States expanded into the Pacific with Hawaii becoming a [[Territory of Hawaii|U.S. territory]] from 1898. Disagreements between the US, Germany and UK over Samoa led to the [[Tripartite Convention (1899)|Tripartite Convention of 1899]].

{{See also|Chronology of colonialism}}

====British Victorian era====
{{Main|British Empire|Victorian era}}

[[File:Flag of the United Kingdom.svg|thumb|National flag of the United Kingdom.]]
The Victorian era of the United Kingdom was the period of Queen Victoria's reign from June 1837 to January 1901. This was a long period of prosperity for the British people, as profits gained from the overseas British Empire, as well as from industrial improvements at home, allowed a large, educated middle class to develop. Some scholars would extend the beginning of the period—as defined by a variety of sensibilities and political games that have come to be associated with the Victorians—back five years to the passage of the Reform Act 1832.

[[File:British Empire 1897.jpg|thumb|The British Empire in 1897, marked in the traditional colour for imperial British dominions on maps]]
In Britain's &quot;imperial century&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;For more, see [[Pax Britannica]].&lt;/ref&gt; Victory over Napoleon left Britain without any serious international rival, other than Russia in central Asia. Unchallenged at sea, Britain adopted the role of global policeman, a state of affairs later known as the ''[[Pax Britannica]]'', and a foreign policy of &quot;[[splendid isolation]]&quot;. Alongside the formal control it exerted over its own colonies, Britain's dominant position in world trade meant that it effectively controlled the economies of many nominally independent countries, such as China, [[Argentina]] and [[Thailand|Siam]], which has been generally characterized as &quot;[[informal empire]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Edwards, B. T. (2004). ''Informal empire: Mexico and Central America in Victorian culture''. Minneapolis, Minn: Univ. of Minnesota Press&lt;/ref&gt; Of note during this time was the [[Anglo-Zulu War]], which was fought in 1879 between the British Empire and the [[Zulu Empire]].

British imperial strength was underpinned by the [[Steamboat|steamship]] and the [[Telegraphy|telegraph]], new technologies invented in the second half of the 19th century, allowing it to control and defend the Empire. By 1902, the British Empire was linked together by a network of telegraph cables, the so-called [[All Red Line]]. Growing until 1922, around {{convert|13000000|sqmi|km2}} of territory and roughly 458 million people were added to the British Empire.&lt;ref&gt;Maddison, Angus (2001). ''The World Economy: A Millennial Perspective''. Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development. ISBN 92-64-18654-9. pp. 98, 242.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson, Niall (2004). ''Colossus: The Price of America's Empire''. Penguin. ISBN 1-59420-013-0. p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; The British established colonies in Australia in 1788, New Zealand in 1840 and [[Colonial Fiji|Fiji]] in 1872, with much of [[Oceania]] becoming part of the British Empire.

====French governments and conflicts====
The [[Bourbon Restoration]] followed the ousting of Napoleon I of France in 1814. The Allies restored the Bourbon Dynasty to the French throne. The ensuing period is called the Restoration, following French usage, and is characterized by a sharp conservative reaction and the re-establishment of the Roman Catholic Church as a power in French politics. The [[July Monarchy]] was a period of liberal constitutional monarchy in France under King Louis-Philippe starting with the July Revolution (or Three Glorious Days) of 1830 and ending with the Revolution of 1848. The [[Second French Empire|Second Empire]] was the Imperial Bonapartist regime of Napoleon III from 1852 to 1870, between the Second Republic and the Third Republic, in France.

[[Image:BismarckundNapoleonIII.jpg|thumb|[[Napoleon III of France|Napoleon III]] and [[Otto von Bismarck|Bismarck]] after the [[Battle of Sedan]]]]
The [[Franco-Prussian War]] was a conflict between France and Prussia, while Prussia was backed up by the North German Confederation, of which it was a member, and the South German states of Baden, Württemberg and Bavaria. The complete Prussian and German victory brought about the final unification of Germany under King Wilhelm I of Prussia. It also marked the downfall of Napoleon III and the end of the Second French Empire, which was replaced by the Third Republic. As part of the settlement, almost all of the territory of Alsace-Lorraine was taken by Prussia to become a part of Germany, which it would retain until the end of World War I.

The [[French Third Republic]] was the republican government of France between the end of the Second French Empire following the defeat of Louis-Napoléon in the Franco-Prussian war in 1870 and the Vichy Regime after the invasion of France by the German Third Reich in 1940. The Third Republic endured seventy years, making it the most long-lasting regime in France since the collapse of the Ancien Régime in the French Revolution of 1789.

====Slavery and abolition====
[[Slavery]] was greatly reduced around the world in the 19th century. Following a successful [[Haitian Revolution|slave revolt in Haiti]], Britain forced the [[Barbary pirates]] to halt their practice of kidnapping and enslaving Europeans, [[Slavery Abolition Act|banned slavery throughout its domain]], and charged its navy with ending the global [[slave trade]]. Slavery was then abolished in [[Emancipation reform of 1861 in Russia|Russia]], [[Emancipation Proclamation|America]], and [[Lei Áurea|Brazil]] (see [[Abolitionism]]).

====African colonization====
Following the abolition of the slave trade, and propelled by economic exploitation, the [[Scramble for Africa]] was initiated formally at the [[Berlin West Africa Conference]] in 1884–1885.  All the major European powers laid claim to the areas of Africa where they could exhibit a sphere of influence over the area.  These claims did not have to have any substantial land holdings or treaties to be legitimate. The French gained major ground in  West Africa, the British in East Africa, and the [[Portugal|Portuguese]] and Spanish at various points throughout the continent, while [[Leopold II of Belgium|King Leopold]] was able to retain his personal fiefdom, [[Belgian Congo|Congo]].

====Meiji Japan====
Around the end of the 19th century and into the 20th century, the [[Meiji era]] was a marked by the reign of the [[Emperor Meiji|Meiji Emperor]]. During this time, Japan started its modernization and rose to world power status. This [[Japanese era name|era name]] means &quot;Enlightened Rule&quot;. It was not until the beginning of the Meiji Era that the Japanese government began taking modernization seriously. Japan expanded its military production base by opening arsenals in various locations. The hyobusho (war office) was replaced with a War Department and a Naval Department.  The [[samurai]] class suffered great disappointment the following years.

Laws were instituted that required every able-bodied male Japanese citizen, regardless of class, to serve a mandatory term of three years with the first reserves and two additional years with the second reserves. This action, the deathblow for the samurai warriors and their [[daimyo]] feudal lords, initially met resistance from both the peasant and warrior alike. The peasant class interpreted the term for military service, ketsu-eki (blood tax) literally, and attempted to avoid service by any means necessary. The Japanese government began modelling their ground forces after the French military.  The French government contributed greatly to the training of Japanese officers.  Many were employed at the military academy in Kyoto, and many more still were feverishly translating French field manuals for use in the Japanese ranks.

After the death of the Meiji Emperor, the [[Emperor Taishō|Taishō Emperor]] took the throne, thus beginning the [[Taishō period]]. A key foreign observer of the remarkable and rapid changes in [[culture of Japan|Japanese society]] in this period was [[Ernest Mason Satow]].

===United States egress===
{{Main|History of the United States (1865–1918)}}

====Antebellum expansion====
The [[Antebellum Age]] was the a period of increasing sectionalism that led up to the American Civil War. The Antebellum Age was a time of great transition because of the industrial revolution in America. It also was a time of growth in slavery in the American South. In a sense, the Antebellum Period is often considered to have begun with the Kansas-Nebraska Act of 1854, though it is sometimes stipulated to extend back as early as 1812.

[[Image:Westward the Course of Empire.jpg|thumb|American westward expansion is idealized in [[Emanuel Leutze]]'s famous painting ''Westward the Course of Empire Takes its Way'' (1861). ]]
&quot;[[Manifest Destiny]]&quot; was the territorial expansion of the United States from 1812 to 1860. Manifest Destiny incorporated the  belief that the United States was destined, even divinely ordained, to expand across the North American continent, from the Atlantic seaboard to the Pacific Ocean. This era, from the end of the War of 1812 to the beginning of the American Civil War, has been called the &quot;Age of Manifest Destiny.&quot; During this time, the United States expanded to the Pacific Ocean—&quot;from sea to shining sea&quot;—largely defining the borders of the contiguous United States as they are today.
{{See also|American Old West|Territorial changes of the United States}}

====US Civil War and Reconstruction====

{{Main|American Civil War|Reconstruction era of the United States}}
The American Civil War was a [[civil war]] in the United States of America. Eleven [[Slave state|Southern slave states]] declared their [[secession]] from the U.S. and formed the [[Confederate States of America|Confederate States of America (the Confederacy)]]. Led by [[Jefferson Davis]], they fought against the [[Union (American Civil War)|U.S. federal government (the Union)]], which was supported by all the free states and the five [[Border states (American Civil War)|border slave states]] in the north.

Northern leaders agreed that victory would require more than the end of fighting. It had to encompass the two [[strategy|strategies]]: secession had to be totally repudiated and all forms of slavery had to be eliminated. They disagreed sharply on the [[military tactics]] and [[political tactics]] for these goals. They also disagreed on the degree of federal control, that should be imposed on the South and the process by which Southern states should be reintegrated into the Union. The Reconstruction Era in United States history existed in the [[Post-Civil War Reconstruction|post-Civil War era]] in the entire United States between 1865 and 1877.

====The Gilded Age and legacy====
{{Main|Gilded Age}}
During the Gilded Age, there was substantial growth in population in the United States and extravagant displays of wealth and excess of America's upper-class during the post-Civil War and post-Reconstruction era, in the late 19th century. The wealth polarization derived primarily from industrial and population expansion. The businessmen of the Second Industrial Revolution created industrial towns and cities in the Northeast with new factories, and contributed to the creation of an ethnically diverse industrial [[working class]] which produced the wealth owned by rising super-rich [[Robber baron (industrialist)|industrialists and financiers called the &quot;robber barons&quot;]]. An example is the company of [[John D. Rockefeller]], who was an important figure in shaping the new oil industry. Using highly effective tactics and aggressive practices, later widely criticized, [[Standard Oil]] absorbed or destroyed most of its competition.

The creation of a modern industrial economy took place. With the creation of a [[Infrastructure|transportation and communication infrastructure]], the [[corporation]] became the dominant form of [[business organization]] and a [[Management|managerial revolution]] transformed [[business|business operation]]s. In 1890, [[Congress of the United States|Congress]] passed the [[Sherman Antitrust Act]]—the source of all American anti-monopoly laws. The law forbade every contract, scheme, deal, or conspiracy to restrain trade, though the phrase &quot;restraint of trade&quot; remained subjective. By the beginning of the 20th century, per capita income and [[industrial production]] in the United States exceeded that of any other country except Britain. Long hours and hazardous working conditions led many workers to attempt to form [[labor union]]s despite strong opposition from industrialists and the courts. But the courts did protect the marketplace, declaring the Standard Oil group to be an &quot;unreasonable&quot; [[monopoly]] under the Sherman Antitrust Act in 1911. It ordered Standard to break up into 34 independent companies with different boards of directors.&lt;ref&gt;See generally ''Standard Oil Co. of New Jersey v. United States'', 221 U.S. 1 (1911).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transitions and Enlightenment negation===
Around the start of the 20th century, Enlightenment philosophy was challenged in various quarters. After the use of [[classical physics]] since the end of the scientific revolution, ''[[modern physics]]'' arose with the advent of quantum physics;&lt;ref&gt;F.K Richtmyer, E.H Kennard, T. Lauristen (1955). &quot;Introduction&quot;. ''Introduction to Modern Physics'' (5th edition ed.). New York: McGraw-Hill Book Company. p. 1. LCCN 55-6862.&lt;/ref&gt; substituting [[mathematical physics|mathematics studies]] for [[experimental physics|experimental studies]] and examining [[equation]]s to build a [[theoretical structure]].&lt;ref&gt;Nikola Tesla, &quot;Radio Power Will Revolutionize the World&quot; in ''Modern Mechanics and Inventions'' (July 1934) (ed., &quot;Today's scientists have substituted mathematics for experiments, and they wander off through equation after equation, and eventually build a structure [...].&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The concepts derived are at times [[abstraction]]s from [[nature]] for baselines or reference states. These can be ''unattainable'' in practice, such as [[free space]] (electromagnetism) and [[absolute zero]] (temperature).&lt;/ref&gt; The [[old quantum theory]] was a collection of results which predate modern [[quantum mechanics]], but were never complete or self-consistent.&lt;ref name=&quot;HaarQM&quot; /&gt; The collection of [[heuristic]] prescriptions for quantum mechanics were the first corrections to [[classical mechanics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;HaarQM&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last = ter Haar|first =D.|title =The Old Quantum Theory|publisher=Pergamon Press|year=1967|page = 206}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Matrix mechanics]] and wave mechanics supplanted other studies to end the era of the old-quantum theory.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the various number of [[aether theories]] in classical physics which supposed a &quot;[[classical elements|fifth element]]&quot;, such as the [[Luminiferous aether]],&lt;ref&gt;a substance in early physics considered to be the medium through which light propagates.&lt;/ref&gt; was nullified by the [[Michelson-Morley experiment]] in an attempt to detect the motion of earth through the aether. In biology, [[Darwinism]] gained acceptance and exposed [[adaptation]] in the theory of [[natural selection]]. The fields of [[modern geology|geology]], [[modern astronomy|astronomy]] and [[modern psychology|psychology]] also made strides and gained new insights. In [[modern medicine|medicine]], there were advances of [[medical theory]] and [[medical treatment|treatment]]s.

[[Image:Xinhai Revolution in Shanghai.jpg|thumb|right|Xinhai Revolution in Shanghai; Chen Qimei organized Shanghainese civilians to start the uprising and was successful. The picture above is Nanjing Road after the uprising, hung with the [[Five Races Under One Union]] Flags then used by the revolutionaries.]]
Another philosophical trend was Chinese philosophy began to integrate concepts of Western philosophy, as steps toward modernization. By the time of the [[Xinhai Revolution]] in 1911, there were many calls, such as the [[May Fourth Movement]], to completely abolish the old imperial institutions and practices of China. There have been attempts to incorporate [[democracy]], [[republicanism]], and [[industrialism]] into Chinese philosophy, notably by [[Sun Yat-Sen]] (''Sūn yì xiān'', in one Mandarin form of the name) at the beginning of the 20th century. [[Mao Zedong]] (''Máo zé dōng'') added [[Marxism-Leninism]] thought. When the [[Communist Party of China]] [[Chinese Civil War|took over]] power, previous schools of thought, excepting notably [[Legalism (Chinese philosophy)|Legalism]], were denounced as backward, and later even purged during the [[Cultural Revolution]].

Developed from earlier [[secular]] traditions, modern [[Humanism]] [[ethics|ethical philosophies]] affirm the dignity and worth of all people, based on the ability to determine right and wrong by appealing to universal human qualities, particularly [[rationalism|rationality]], without resorting to the supernatural or alleged divine authority from religious texts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title=Compact Oxford English Dictionary| publisher=Oxford University Press| year=2007| quote=humanism ''n.'' 1 a rationalistic system of thought attaching prime importance to human rather than divine or supernatural matters. 2 a Renaissance cultural movement that turned away from medieval scholastic-ism and revived interest in ancient Greek and Roman thought.| publication-date = 2007}} Typically, abridgments of this definition omit all senses except #1, such as in the [http://dictionary.cambridge.org/define.asp?key=38402&amp;dict=CALD ''Cambridge Advanced Learner's Dictionary''], [http://www.thefreedictionary.com/humanism ''Collins Essential English Dictionary''], and {{cite book | title = Webster's Concise Dictionary  | publisher = RHR Press  | year = 2001  | location = New York  | page = 177}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title=Collins Concise Dictionary| publisher=HarperCollins| year=1999| quote=The rejection of religion in favour of a belief in the advancement of humanity by its own efforts. |publication-date = 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; For [[liberal humanism|liberal humanists]] such as [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseau]] or [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]], the universal law of [[reason]] guided the way towards total emancipation from any kind of tyranny. These ideas were challenged. The [[young Marx|young Karl Marx]] criticized the project of political emancipation (embodied in the form of [[human rights]]), asserting it to be symptomatic of the very dehumanization it is supposed to oppose. For [[Friedrich Nietzsche]], humanism was nothing more than a secular version of [[theism]]. In his ''[[Genealogy of Morals]]'', he argues that human rights exist as a means for the weak to collectively constrain the strong. On this view, such rights do not facilitate emancipation of life, but rather deny it. In the 20th century, the notion that human beings are rationally autonomous was challenged by the concept that humans were driven by unconscious irrational desires.

====Notable persons====
[[Sigmund Freud]] is renowned for his redefinition of [[sexual desire]] as the primary motivational energy of human life, as well as his therapeutic techniques, including the use of [[free association (psychology)|free association]], his [[transference|theory of transference]] in the therapeutic relationship, and the [[Dream interpretation|interpretation of dreams]] as sources of insight into [[unconscious desire]]s.

[[Albert Einstein]] is known for his theories of [[special relativity]] and [[general relativity]]. He also made important contributions to [[statistical mechanics]], especially his mathematical treatment of [[Brownian motion]], his resolution of the [[Einstein solid|paradox of specific heats]], and his connection of [[Fluctuation dissipation theorem|fluctuations and dissipation]]. Despite his reservations about its interpretation, Einstein also made contributions to quantum mechanics and, indirectly, [[quantum field theory]], primarily through his theoretical studies of the [[photon]].

====Social Darwinism====
At the end of the 19th century, [[Social Darwinism]] was promoted and included the various ideologies based on a concept that competition among all individuals, groups, nations, or ideas was a &quot;natural&quot; framework for social evolution in human societies. In this view, society's advancement is dependent on the &quot;[[survival of the fittest]]&quot;, the term was in fact coined by [[Herbert Spencer]] and referred to in &quot;[[The Gospel of Wealth]]&quot; theory written by [[Andrew Carnegie]].

====Marxist society====
[[Image:communist-manifesto.png|thumb|The Communist Manifesto]]
[[Karl Marx]] summarized his approach to history and politics in the opening line of the first chapter of [[The Communist Manifesto]] (1848). He wrote:
:''The history of all hitherto existing society is the history of [[class struggle]]s.''&lt;ref&gt;In the 1888 English edition of the Communist Manifest, [[Friedrich Engels]] added a footnote with the commentary: &quot;That is, all written history. In 1847, the prehistory of society, the social organization existing previous to recorded history, was all but unknown. Since then Haxthausen discovered common ownership of land In Russia, Maurer concluded it to be the social foundation from which all Teutonic races started in history, and by and by village communities were found to be, or to have been, the primitive form of society everywhere from India to Ireland. The Inner organization of this primitive Communistic society was laid bare, In its typical form, by Morgan's work on the true nature of the gens and Its relation to the tribe. With the dissolution of these primaeval communities society begins to be differentiated into separate and finally antagonistic classes. I have attempte to retrace this process of dissolution in &quot;''[[Der Ursprung der Familie, des Privateigenthums und des Staats]]''&quot;&quot;, from Marx, Karl, Friedrich Engels, Leon Trotsky, and Karl Marx. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=dEyEzazZKwIC&amp;pg=PA46 The Communist Manifesto and Its Relevance for Today]''. Chippendale, N.S.W.: Resistance Books, 1998. p. 46, see also ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=p7s0oTEWB_MC&amp;pg=PA204 Cornelius Castoriadis, Political and Social Writings]''. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1993. p. 204&lt;/ref&gt;
The ''Manifesto'' went through a number of editions from 1872 to 1890; notable new prefaces were written by Marx and Engels for the 1872 German edition, the 1882 Russian edition, the 1883 German edition, and the 1888 English edition. In general, [[Marxism]] identified five (and one transitional) successive stages of development in Western Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Marx makes no claim to have produced a master key to history. Historical materialism is not &quot;an historico-philosophic theory of the marche generale imposed by fate upon every people, whatever the historic circumstances in which it finds itself&quot;. (Marx, Karl, Letter to editor of the Russian paper ''Otetchestvennye Zapiskym'', 1877) His ideas, he explains, are based on a concrete study of the actual conditions that pertained in Europe.&lt;/ref&gt;
# ''[[Primitive Communism]]:'' as seen in cooperative tribal societies.
# ''[[Slave]] Society:'' which develops when the tribe becomes a city-state. Aristocracy is born.
# ''[[Feudalism]]:'' aristocracy is the ruling class. Merchants develop into capitalists.
# ''[[Capitalism]]:'' capitalists are the ruling class, who create and employ the true working class.
# ''[[Dictatorship of the proletariat]]:'' workers gain class consciousness, [[Proletarian revolution|overthrow]] the capitalists and take control over the [[Socialist state|state]].
# ''[[Communism]]:'' a classless and stateless society.

===European decline and the 20th century===
{{Main|20th century}}
Major political developments saw the former [[British Empire]] lose most of its remaining political power over [[British Commonwealth|commonwealth]] countries.&lt;ref&gt;Most notably by dividing the British crown into several sovereignties by the [[Statute of Westminster 1931|Statute of Westminster]], the [[patriation]] of constitutions by the [[Canada Act 1982]] and the [[Australia Act 1986]], and by the independence of countries such as India, Pakistan, South Africa, and [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], along with the 1997 [[return of Hong Kong]] to the [[People's Republic of China]].&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Trans-Siberian Railway]], crossing Asia by train, was complete by 1916. Other events include the [[Israeli–Palestinian conflict]], two world wars, and the [[Cold War]].

====Australian Constitution====
In 1901, the [[Federation of Australia]] was the process by which the six separate British [[self-governing colony|self-governing colonies]] of [[New South Wales]], [[Queensland]], [[South Australia]], [[Tasmania]], [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] and [[Western Australia]] formed one nation. They kept the systems of government that they had developed as separate colonies but also would have a federal government that was responsible for matters concerning the whole nation. When the [[Constitution of Australia]] came into force, the colonies collectively became [[States and territories of Australia|states]] of the [[Australia|Commonwealth of Australia]].

====Eastern warlords====
The last days of the [[Qing Dynasty]] were marked by civil unrest and foreign invasions. Responding to these civil failures and discontent, the Qing Imperial Court did attempt to reform the government in various ways, such as the decision to draft a constitution in 1906, the establishment of provincial legislatures in 1909, and the preparation for a national parliament in 1910. However, many of these measures were opposed by the conservatives of the Qing Court, and many reformers were either imprisoned or executed outright. The failures of the Imperial Court to enact such reforming measures of political liberalization and modernization caused the reformists to steer toward the road of revolution.

In 1912, the Republic of China was established and was inaugurated in [[Nanjing]] as the first [[President of the Republic of China|Provisional President]]. But power in [[Beijing]] already had passed to [[Yuan Shikai]], who had effective control of the [[Beiyang Army]], the most powerful military force in China at the time. To prevent [[civil war]] and possible foreign intervention from undermining the infant republic, leaders agreed to Army's demand that China be united under a Beijing government. On March 10, in Beijing, Shikai was sworn in as the second Provisional President of the Republic of China.

After the early 20th century revolutions, shifting alliances of [[Warlord era (China)|China's regional warlords fought for control]] of the Beijing government.  Despite the fact that various warlords gained control of the government in Beijing during the warlord era, this did not constitute a new era of control or governance, because other warlords did not acknowledge the transitory governments in this period and were a law unto themselves.  These military-dominated governments were collectively known as the [[Beiyang government]].  The warlord era is ends around in 1927.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph, W. A. (2010). ''Politics in China: An introduction''. Oxford: Oxford University Press. Page 423.&lt;/ref&gt;

====World Wars era====
{{see also|Timeline of modern history|Timeline of World War I|Timeline of World War II}}

=====start of the 20th century=====
Begun  at the [[Battle of Port Arthur]], the [[Russo-Japanese War]] establishes the [[Empire of Japan]] as a world power. The Russians were in constant pursuit of a [[warm water port]] on the Pacific Ocean, for their navy as well as for maritime trade. The Manchurian Campaign of the [[Russian Empire]] was fought against the Japanese over [[Manchuria]] and [[Korea]]. The major theatres of operations were Southern Manchuria, specifically the area around the [[Liaodong Peninsula]] and [[Mukden]], and the seas around Korea, Japan, and the [[Yellow Sea]]. The resulting campaigns, in which the fledgling Japanese military consistently attained victory over the Russian forces arrayed against them, were unexpected by world observers. These victories, as time transpired, would dramatically transform the distribution of power in East Asia, resulting in a reassessment of Japan's recent entry onto the world stage. The embarrassing string of defeats increased Russian popular dissatisfaction with the inefficient and corrupt Tsarist government.

The [[Russian Revolution of 1905]] was a wave of mass political unrest through vast areas of the [[Russian Empire]]. Some of it was directed against the government, while some was undirected.  It included [[terrorism]], worker strikes, peasant unrests, and military mutinies.  It led to the establishment of the limited constitutional monarchy, the establishment of [[State Duma of the Russian Empire]], the [[multi-party system]] and [[Russian Constitution of 1906]].

In China, the Qing Dynasty was overthrown following the [[Xinhai Revolution]]. The  ''Xinhai Revolution'' began with the [[Wuchang Uprising]] on October 10, 1911 and ended with the abdication of [[Emperor Puyi]] on February 12, 1912. The primary parties to the conflict were the Imperial forces of the [[Qing Dynasty]] (1644–1911), and the revolutionary forces of the [[Tongmenghui|Chinese Revolutionary Alliance]] (Tongmenghui).

=====Edwardian Britain=====
The [[Edwardian era]] in the United Kingdom is the period spanning the reign of [[Edward VII of the United Kingdom|King Edward VII]] up to the end of the First World War, including the years surrounding the sinking of the [[RMS Titanic|RMS ''Titanic'']]. In the early years of the period, the [[Second Boer War]] in South Africa split the country into anti- and pro-war factions. The imperial policies of the Conservatives eventually proved unpopular and in the [[United Kingdom general election, 1906|general election of 1906]] the Liberals won a huge landslide. The Liberal government was unable to proceed with all of its radical programme without the support of the [[House of Lords]], which was largely Conservative. Conflict between the two Houses of Parliament over the [[People's Budget]] led to a reduction in the power of the peers in 1910. The [[United Kingdom general election, January 1910|general election in January that year]] returned a [[hung parliament]] with the balance of power held by [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] and [[Nationalist Party (Ireland)|Irish Nationalist]] members.

=====World War I=====
{{Main|World War I}}
The [[causes of World War I]] included many factors, including the conflicts and antagonisms of the four decades leading up to the war. The [[Triple Entente]] was the name given to the loose alignment between the [[British Empire|United Kingdom]], [[French Third Republic|France]], and [[Russian Empire|Russia]] after the signing of the [[Anglo-Russian Entente]] in 1907.  The alignment of the three powers, supplemented by various agreements with [[Empire of Japan|Japan]], the United States, and [[Spain under the Restoration|Spain]], constituted a powerful counterweight to the [[Triple Alliance (1882)|Triple Alliance]] of [[German Empire|Germany]], [[Austria-Hungary]], and [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italy]], the third having concluded an additional secret agreement with France effectively nullifying her Alliance commitments.  Militarism, alliances, imperialism, and nationalism played major roles in the conflict. The immediate origins of the war lay in the decisions taken by statesmen and generals during the [[July crisis]] of 1914, the spark (or casus belli) for which was the assassination of [[Archduke Franz Ferdinand]] of Austria.

However, the crisis did not exist in a void; it came after a long series of diplomatic clashes between the Great Powers over European and colonial issues in the decade prior to 1914 which had left tensions high. The diplomatic clashes can be traced to changes in the balance of power in Europe since 1870.  An example is the [[Baghdad Railway]] which was planned to connect the [[Ottoman Empire]] cities of [[Konya]] and [[Baghdad]] with a line through modern-day Turkey, Syria and Iraq. The railway became a source of international disputes during the years immediately preceding World War I. Although it has been argued that they were resolved in 1914 before the war began, it has also been argued that the railroad was a cause of the First World War.&lt;ref&gt;([[Morris Jastrow, Jr.|Jastrow]] 1917)&lt;/ref&gt; Fundamentally the war was sparked by tensions over territory in the [[Balkans]]. Austria-Hungary competed with Serbia and Russia for territory and influence in the region and they pulled the rest of the great powers into the conflict through their various alliances and treaties. The [[Balkan Wars]] were two wars in South-eastern Europe in 1912–1913 in the course of which the Balkan League (Bulgaria, Montenegro, Greece, and Serbia) first captured Ottoman-held remaining part of Thessaly, Macedonia, Epirus, Albania and most of Thrace and then fell out over the division of the spoils, with incorporation of Romania this time.

[[Image:World War 1.gif|thumb||600px|center|Various periods of World War I; 1914.07.28 (Tsar Nicholas II of Russia orders a partial mobilization against Austria-Hungary), 1914.08.01 (Germany declares war on Russia), 1914.08.03 (Germany declares war on Russia's ally France), 1914.08.04 (Britain declares war on Germany), 1914.12 (British and German [[Christmas truce]]), 1915.12 (French and German Christmas truce), 1916.12 ([[Battle of Magdhaba]]), 1917.12 (British troops take Jerusalem from the Ottoman Empire), and 1918.11.11 (World War I ends: Germany signs an armistice agreement with the Allies).
----
Allies and Central Powers in the First World War&lt;br&gt;{{color box|#088A08}}{{color box|#01DF01}} Allied powers and areas&lt;br&gt;{{color box|#FE9A2E}}{{color box|#F7BE81}} Central powers and colonies or occupied territory&lt;br&gt;{{color box|#BDBDBD}} Neutral countries]]
The First World War began in 1914 and lasted to the final [[Armistice with Germany (Compiègne)|Armistice]] in 1918. The [[Allies of World War I|Allied Powers]], led by the [[Britain in World War I|British Empire]], [[French Third Republic|France]], Russia until March 1918, Japan and the United States after 1917, defeated the [[Central Powers]], led by the [[German Empire]], [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]] and the [[Ottoman Empire]]. The war caused the disintegration of four empires—the Austro-Hungarian, German, Ottoman, and Russian ones—as well as radical change in the European and Middle Eastern maps. The Allied powers before 1917 are sometimes referred to as the [[Triple Entente]], and the Central Powers are sometimes referred to as the [[Triple Alliance (1882)|Triple Alliance]].

Much of the fighting in World War I took place along the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]], within a system of opposing manned trenches and fortifications (separated by a &quot;[[No man's land]]&quot;) running from the [[North Sea]] to the border of Switzerland. On the [[Eastern Front (World War I)|Eastern Front]], the vast eastern plains and limited rail network prevented a trench warfare stalemate from developing, although the scale of the conflict was just as large.  Hostilities also occurred on and under the sea and—for the first time—from the air. More than 9 million soldiers died on the various battlefields, and nearly that many more in the participating countries' home fronts on account of food shortages and [[genocide]] committed under the cover of various civil wars and internal conflicts. Notably, more people died of the worldwide [[Spanish flu|influenza outbreak]] at the end of the war and shortly after than died in the hostilities.  The unsanitary conditions engendered by the war, severe overcrowding in barracks, wartime propaganda interfering with public health warnings, and migration of so many soldiers around the world helped the outbreak become a [[pandemic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Barry|first=John M.|authorlink=John M. Barry|title=The Great Influenza: The Epic Story of the Greatest Plague in History|publisher=Viking Penguin|year=2004|isbn=0-670-89473-7|series=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ultimately, World War I created a decisive break with the old [[New World Order (political)|world order]] that had emerged after the [[Napoleonic Wars]], which was modified by the mid-19th century's nationalistic revolutions. The results of World War I would be important factors in the development of World War II approximately 20 years later. More immediate to the time, the ''[[partitioning of the Ottoman Empire]]'' was a political event that redrew the political boundaries of the Middle East. The huge conglomeration of territories and peoples formerly ruled by the Sultan of the Ottoman Empire was divided into several new nations.&lt;ref&gt;Roderic H. Davison; Review &quot;From Paris to Sèvres: The Partition of the Ottoman Empire at the Peace Conference of 1919-1920. by Paul C. Helmreich&quot; in ''[[Slavic Review]]'', Vol. 34, No. 1 (March , 1975), pp. 186-187&lt;/ref&gt; The partitioning brought the creation of the modern [[Arab world]] and the [[Republic of Turkey]]. The [[League of Nations]] granted France mandates over [[French Mandate of Syria|Syria]] and [[French Mandate of Lebanon|Lebanon]] and granted the United Kingdom mandates over [[British Mandate of Mesopotamia|Mesopotamia]] and [[British Mandate of Palestine|Palestine]] (which was later divided into two regions: [[Palestine]] and [[Transjordan]]). Parts of the Ottoman Empire on the [[Arabian Peninsula]] became parts of what are today [[Saudi Arabia]] and [[Yemen]].

=====Revolutions and war=====
{{Main|Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Civil War}}
[[File:Flag of the Soviet Union.svg|thumb|right|National flag of the Soviet Union.]]
The Russian Revolution is the series of revolutions in Russia in 1917, which destroyed the [[Tsarist autocracy]] and led to the creation of the Soviet Union. Following the abdication of [[Nicholas II of Russia]], the [[Russian Provisional Government]] was established. In October 1917, a [[October Revolution|''red'' faction revolution]] occurred in which the [[Red Guards (Russia)|Red Guard]], armed groups of workers and deserting soldiers directed by the Bolshevik Party, seized control of [[Saint Petersburg]] (then known as [[Petrograd]]) and began an immediate armed takeover of cities and villages throughout the former [[Russian Empire]].

Another action in 1917 that is of note was the armistice signed between Russia and the Central Powers at [[Brest-Litovsk]].&lt;ref&gt;Evan Mawdsley (2008) ''The Russian Civil War'': 42&lt;/ref&gt; As a condition for peace, the treaty by the [[Central Powers]] conceded huge portions of the former Russian Empire to [[German Empire|Imperial Germany]] and the Ottoman Empire, greatly upsetting [[nationalist]]s and [[Conservatism|conservative]]s. The Bolsheviks made peace with the [[German Empire]] and the [[Central Powers]], as they had promised the Russian people prior to the Revolution. Vladimir Lenin's decision has been attributed to his sponsorship by the foreign office of [[Wilhelm II, German Emperor]], offered by the latter in hopes that with a revolution, Russia would withdraw from World War I. This suspicion was bolstered by the German Foreign Ministry's sponsorship of Lenin's return to [[Saint Petersburg|Petrograd]].  The [[Triple Entente|Western Allies]], expressed their dismay at the Bolsheviks, upset at:
# the withdrawal of Russia from the war effort,
# worried about a possible Russo-German alliance, and
# galvanized by the prospect of the Bolsheviks making good their threats to assume no responsibility for, and so default on, Imperial Russia's massive [[External debt|foreign loans]].&lt;ref&gt;the legal notion of [[Odious debt]] had not yet been formulated&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, there was a concern, shared by many [[Central Powers]] as well, that the socialist revolutionary ideas would spread to the West. Hence, many of these countries expressed their support for the Whites, including the provision of troops and supplies. [[Winston Churchill]] declared that Bolshevism must be &quot;strangled in its cradle&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.winstonchurchill.org/i4a/pages/index.cfm?pageid=282 Cover Story: Churchill's Greatness.] Interview with Jeffrey Wallin. (The Churchill Centre)&lt;/ref&gt;

The Russian Civil War was a multi-party war that occurred within the former [[Russian Empire]] after the [[Russian provisional government]] collapsed and the [[Soviet republic (system of government)|Soviets]] under the domination of the [[Bolshevik]] party assumed power, first in [[Saint Petersburg|Petrograd (St. Petersburg)]] and then in other places. In the wake of the [[October Revolution]], the old Russian Imperial Army had been demobilized; the volunteer-based Red Guard was the Bolsheviks' main military force, augmented by an armed military component of the [[Cheka]], the Bolshevik state security apparatus. There was an instituted mandatory conscription of the rural peasantry into the Red Army.&lt;ref&gt;Read, Christopher, ''From Tsar to Soviets'', Oxford University Press (1996), p. 237: By 1920, 77% of the Red Army's enlisted ranks were composed of peasant conscripts.&lt;/ref&gt;  Opposition of rural Russians to Red Army conscription units was overcome by taking hostages and shooting them when necessary in order to force compliance.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, Beryl, ''The Russian Revolution 1917-1921'', Blackwell Publishing Ltd. (1987), ISBN 978-0-631-15083-1: Typically, men of conscriptible age (17-40) in a village would vanish when Red Army draft units approached.  The taking of hostages and a few exemplary executions usually brought the men back.&lt;/ref&gt;  Former Tsarist officers were utilized as &quot;military specialists&quot; (''voenspetsy''),&lt;ref&gt;Overy, R.J., ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia'', W.W. Norton &amp; Company (2004), ISBN 978-0-393-02030-4, p. 446: By the end of the civil war, one-third of all Red Army officers were ex-Tsarist ''voenspetsy''.&lt;/ref&gt; sometimes taking their families hostage in order to ensure loyalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Williams, Beryl 1921&quot;&gt;Williams, Beryl, ''The Russian Revolution 1917-1921'', Blackwell Publishing Ltd. (1987), ISBN 978-0-631-15083-1&lt;/ref&gt; At the start of the war, three-fourths of the Red Army officer corps was composed of former Tsarist officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Williams, Beryl 1921&quot;/&gt;  By its end, 83% of all Red Army divisional and corps commanders were ex-Tsarist soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Overy, R.J., ''The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia'', W.W. Norton &amp; Company (2004), ISBN 978-0-393-02030-4, p. 446:&lt;/ref&gt;

The principal fighting occurred between the [[Bolshevik]] [[Red Army]] and the forces of the [[White Movement|White Army]]. Many foreign armies warred against the Red Army, notably the [[Allied intervention in the Russian Civil War|Allied Forces]], yet many volunteer foreigners fought in both sides of the Russian Civil War. Other nationalist and regional political groups also participated in the war, including the Ukrainian nationalist [[Green armies|Green Army]], the Ukrainian anarchist [[Revolutionary Insurrectionary Army of Ukraine|Black Army]] and [[Black Guards]], and warlords such as [[Ungern von Sternberg]]. The most intense fighting took place from 1918 to 1920. Major military operations ended on 25 October 1922 when the Red Army occupied [[Vladivostok]], previously held by the [[Provisional Priamur Government]]. The last enclave of the White Forces was the [[Ayano-Maysky District]] on the Pacific coast. The majority of the fighting ended in 1920 with the defeat of General [[Pyotr Wrangel]] in the [[Crimea]], but a notable resistance in certain areas continued until 1923 (e.g., [[Kronstadt Uprising]], [[Tambov Rebellion]], [[Basmachi Revolt]], and the final resistance of the [[White movement]] in the [[Russian Far East|Far East]]).

In 1917, China declared war on Germany in the hope of recovering its lost province, then under Japanese control. The [[New Culture Movement]] occupied the period from 1917 to 1923. Chinese representatives refused to sign the [[Treaty of Versailles]], due to intense pressure from the student protesters and public opinion alike.

The May Fourth Movement helped to rekindle the then-fading cause of republican revolution. In 1917 [[Sun Yat-sen]] had become commander-in-chief of a rival military government in [[Guangzhou]] in collaboration with southern warlords. Sun efforts to obtain aid from the Western democracies were ignored, however, and in 1920 he turned to the Soviet Union, which had recently achieved its own revolution. The Soviets sought to befriend the Chinese revolutionists by offering scathing attacks on Western imperialism. But for political expediency, the Soviet leadership initiated a dual policy of support for both Sun and the newly established [[Chinese Communist Party]] (CCP).

[[File:Naval Jack of the Republic of China.svg|thumb|right|The [[flag of the Kuomintang]], one canton of the [[flag of the Republic of China]].]]
The policy of working with the [[Kuomintang]] and [[Chiang Kai-shek]] had been recommended by the [[Netherlands|Dutch]] Communist [[Henk Sneevliet]], chosen in 1923 to be the [[Comintern]] representative in China due to his revolutionary experience in the [[Dutch Indies]], where he had a major role in founding the [[Partai Komunis Indonesia]] (PKI) - and who felt that the Chinese party was too small and weak to undertake a major effort on its own (see [[Henk Sneevliet#Working for the Comintern|Henk Sneevliet's work for the Comintern]]).

In early 1927, the Kuomintang-CCP rivalry led to a split in the revolutionary ranks. The CCP and the left wing of the Kuomintang had decided to move the seat of the Nationalist government from Guangzhou to [[Wuhan]]. But [[Chiang Kai-shek]], whose Northern Expedition was proving successful, set his forces to destroying the Shanghai CCP apparatus and established an anti-Communist government at Nanjing in [[April 12 Incident|April 1927 - bloody events]].

=====The 1920s and the Depression=====
{{Main|Interwar period|Roaring Twenties|Great Depression}}
The interwar period was the period between the end of the First World War and the beginning of the Second World War. This period was marked by turmoil in much of the world, as Europe struggled to recover from the devastation of the First World War.

In North America, especially the first half of this period, people experienced considerable prosperity in the Roaring Twenties. The social and societal upheaval known as the Roaring Twenties began in North America and spread to Europe in the [[aftermath of World War I]]. The ''Roaring Twenties'', often called &quot;[[Jazz Age|The Jazz Age]]&quot;, saw an exposition of social, artistic, and cultural dynamism. '[[Normalcy]]' returned to politics, [[jazz music]] blossomed, the [[flapper]] redefined modern womanhood, [[Art Deco]] peaked. The spirit of the Roaring Twenties was marked by a general feeling of discontinuity associated with modernity, a break with traditions. Everything seemed to be feasible through modern technology. New technologies, especially automobiles, movies and radio proliferated 'modernity' to a large part of the population. The 1920s saw the general favor of practicality, in architecture as well as in daily life. The 1920s was further distinguished by several inventions and discoveries, extensive industrial growth and the rise in consumer demand and aspirations, and significant changes in [[lifestyle (sociology)|lifestyle]].

[[Image:EUROPE 1929-1938 POLITICAL MAP.svg|thumb|right|300px|Europe between 1920 and 1938.]]
Europe spent these years rebuilding and coming to terms with the vast human cost of the conflict. The economy of the United States became increasingly intertwined with that of Europe. In Germany, the [[Weimar Republic]] gave way to episodes of political and economic turmoil, which culminated with the German [[hyperinflation]] of 1923 and the failed [[Beer Hall Putsch]] of that same year. When Germany could no longer afford war payments, Wall Street invested heavily in European debts to keep the European economy afloat as a large consumer market for American mass produced goods. By the middle of the decade, [[economic development]] soared in Europe, and the Roaring Twenties broke out in Germany, Britain and France, the second half of the decade becoming known as the &quot;[[Golden Twenties]]&quot;. In France and francophone Canada, they were also called the &quot;''années folles''&quot; (&quot;Crazy Years&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Hakim | first = Joy | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = War, Peace, and All That Jazz | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 1995 | location = New York | pages = 41–46 | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = 0-19-509514-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Worldwide prosperity changed dramatically with the onset of the [[Great Depression]] in 1929. The [[Wall Street Crash of 1929]] served to punctuate the end of the previous era, as ''The Great Depression'' set in. The ''Great Depression'' was a worldwide economic [[Recession|downturn]] starting in most places in 1929 and ending at different times in the 1930s or early 1940s for different countries.&lt;ref name=CRomer1&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/243118/Great-Depression &quot;Great Depression&quot;], ''Encyclopædia Britannica''&lt;/ref&gt; It was the largest and most important [[Depression (economics)|economic depression]] in the 20th century, and is used in the 21st century as an example of how far the world's economy can fall.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Duhigg, &quot;Depression, You Say? Check Those Safety Nets&quot;, ''New York Times'', March 23, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The depression had devastating effects in virtually every country, rich or poor. International trade plunged by half to two-thirds, as did personal income, tax revenue, prices and profits. [[Cities in the Great Depression|Cities all around the world]] were hit hard, especially those dependent on [[heavy industry]]. Construction was virtually halted in many countries. Farming and rural areas suffered as crop prices fell by roughly 60 percent.&lt;ref name=&quot;USBLS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bls.gov/data/|title=Commodity Data|publisher=US Bureau of Labor Statistics|accessdate=2008-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author= Cochrane, Willard W.|title=Farm Prices, Myth and Reality|year=1958|page=15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|journal=[[League of Nations]]|title=World Economic Survey 1932–33|page=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; Facing plummeting demand with few alternate sources of jobs, areas dependent on [[Primary sector of economic activity|primary sector industries]] suffered the most.

The Great Depression ended at different times in different countries with the [[Home front during World War II|effect lasting into the next era]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/learn/features/timeline/depwwii/depwar.html Great Depression and World War II]. ''The Library of Congress''.&lt;/ref&gt; America's Great Depression ended in 1941 with America's entry into World War II.&lt;ref&gt;[http://useconomy.about.com/od/grossdomesticproduct/p/1929_Depression.htm What Ended the Great Depression of 1929?]. ''Source: The Federal Reserve Board web site, &quot;Remarks by Governor Ben Bernanke at the H. Parket Willis Lecture in Economic Policy&quot;, March 2, 2004, FDR Library Web Site.''&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of countries set up relief programs, and most underwent some sort of political upheaval, pushing them to the left or right. In some world states, the desperate citizens turned toward nationalist [[Demagogy|demagogues]]—the most infamous being [[Adolf Hitler]]—setting the stage for the next era of war. The convulsion brought on by the worldwide depression resulted in the rise of [[Nazism]]. In Asia, Japan became an ever more assertive power, especially with regards to China.

=====Nanjing period=====
{{Main|Nanjing decade}}

[[Image:Sino-german cooperation.png|thumb|220px|[[Sino-German cooperation (1911–1941)|With help from Germany]], Chinese industry and military was improved just prior to the war against Japan.]]
The &quot;Nanjing Decade&quot; of 1928-37 was one of consolidation and accomplishment under the leadership of the Nationalists, with a mixed but generally positive record in the economy, social progress, development of [[democracy in China|democracy]], and cultural creativity. Some of the harsh aspects of foreign concessions and privileges in China were moderated through diplomacy.
{{See also|Sino-German cooperation|National Resources Commission|Chinese Civil War}}

=====The League and crises=====
The interwar period was also marked by a radical change in the international order, away from the [[balance of power in international relations|balance of power]] that had dominated pre–World War I Europe. One main institution that was meant to bring stability was the [[League of Nations]], which was created after the First World War with the intention of maintaining world security and peace and encouraging economic growth between member countries. The League was undermined by the bellicosity of [[Nazi Germany]], [[Imperial Japan]], the Soviet Union, and [[Benito Mussolini|Mussolini's]] Italy, and by the non-participation of the United States, leading many to question its effectiveness and legitimacy.

A series of international crises strained the League to its limits, the earliest being the [[Japanese invasion of Manchuria|invasion of Manchuria]] by Japan and the [[Abyssinian crisis]] of 1935/36 in which Italy invaded [[Ethiopian Empire|Abyssinia]], one of the only free African nations at that time. The League tried to enforce economic sanctions upon Italy, but to no avail. The incident highlighted French and British weakness, exemplified by their reluctance to alienate Italy and lose her as their ally. The limited actions taken by the Western powers pushed Mussolini's Italy towards alliance with Hitler's Germany anyway. The Abyssinian war showed Hitler how weak the League was and encouraged the remilitarization of the Rhineland in flagrant disregard of the Treaty of Versailles. This was the first in a series of provocative acts culminating in the [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|invasion of Poland]] in September 1939 and the beginning of the Second World War.

Few Chinese had any illusions about Japanese designs on China. Hungry for raw materials and pressed by a growing population, Japan initiated the seizure of [[Manchuria]] in September 1931 and established ex-Qing emperor [[Puyi]] as head of the [[puppet state]] of [[Manchukuo]] in 1932. During the [[Sino-Japanese War (1937-1945)]], the loss of Manchuria, and its vast potential for industrial development and war industries, was a blow to the Kuomintang economy. The [[League of Nations]], established at the end of World War I, was unable to act in the face of the Japanese defiance. After 1940, conflicts between the Kuomintang and Communists became more frequent in the [[Free China (Second Sino-Japanese War)|areas not under Japanese control]]. The Communists expanded their influence wherever opportunities presented themselves through mass organizations, administrative reforms, and the land- and tax-reform measures favoring the peasants—while the Kuomintang attempted to neutralize the spread of Communist influence.

=====Tripartite Pact=====
The [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] had seen tensions rise between Imperial Japan and the United States; events such as the [[Panay incident]] and the [[Nanking Massacre]] turned American public opinion against Japan. With the occupation of [[French Indochina]] in the years of 1940–41, and with the continuing war in China, the United States placed embargoes on Japan of strategic materials such as scrap metal and oil, which were vitally needed for the war effort. The Japanese were faced with the option of either withdrawing from China and losing face or seizing and securing new sources of raw materials in the resource-rich, European-controlled colonies of [[South East Asia]]—specifically [[British Malaya]] and the [[Dutch East Indies]] (modern-day [[Indonesia]]). In 1940, Imperial Japan signed the [[Tripartite Pact]] with Nazi Germany and Fascist Italy.

=====World War II=====
{{Main|World War II}}
The Second World War was a global military conflict that took place in 1939–1945. It was the largest and deadliest war in history, culminating in [[the Holocaust]] and ending with the dropping of the [[atom bomb]].

[[File:Flag of Germany 1933.svg|thumb|right|National flag of the [[Third Reich]] ([[Nazi Germany]]).]]
Even though Japan had been fighting in China since 1937, the conventional view is that the war began on September 1, 1939, when [[Nazi Germany]] invaded Poland, the [[Drang nach Osten]]. Within two days the United Kingdom and France declared war on Germany, even though the fighting was confined to Poland. Pursuant to a then-secret provision of its non-aggression [[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact]], the Soviet Union joined with Germany on September 17, 1939, to conquer Poland and to divide Eastern Europe.

The [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] were initially made up of Poland, the United Kingdom, France, Australia, Canada, New Zealand, South Africa, as well as [[Commonwealth of Nations|British Commonwealth]] countries which were controlled directly by the UK, such as the [[British Raj|Indian Empire]]. All of these countries declared war on Germany in September 1939.

Following the lull in fighting, known as the &quot;[[Phoney War]]&quot;, Germany invaded western Europe in May 1940. Six weeks later, France, in the mean time attacked by Italy as well, surrendered to Germany, which then tried unsuccessfully to conquer Britain. On September 27, Germany, Italy, and Japan signed a mutual defense agreement, the [[Tripartite Pact]], and were known as the [[Axis Powers]].

Nine months later, on June 22, 1941, Germany launched a massive invasion of the Soviet Union, which promptly joined the Allies. Germany was now engaged in fighting a war on two fronts. This proved to be a mistake by Germany - Germany had not successfully carried out the invasion of Britain and the war turned against of the Axis.

[[Image:Naval Ensign of Japan.svg|right|thumb|[[Rising sun flag|Ensign of the Imperial Japanese Navy]]]]
On  December 7, 1941, [[Attack on Pearl Harbor|Japan attacked the United States at Pearl Harbor]], bringing it too into the war on the Allied side. China also joined the Allies, as eventually did most of the rest of the world. China was in turmoil at the time, and attacked Japanese armies through guerilla-type warfare. By the beginning of 1942, the major combatants were aligned as follows: the British Commonwealth, the United States, and the Soviet Union were fighting Germany and Italy; and the British Commonwealth, China, and the United States were fighting Japan. From then through August 1945, battles raged across all of Europe, in the [[North Atlantic Ocean]], across North Africa, throughout [[Southeast Asia]], throughout China, across the Pacific Ocean and in the air over Japan.

Italy surrendered in September 1943 and split in a northern Germany-occupied [[puppet state]] and in an Allies-friendly state in the South; Germany surrendered in May 1945. Following the [[atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]], [[surrender of Japan|Japan surrendered]], marking the end of the war on September 2, 1945.

It is possible that around 62 million people [[World War II casualties|died in the war]]; estimates vary greatly. About 60% of all casualties were civilians, who died as a result of disease, starvation, [[genocide]] (in particular, the [[Holocaust]]), and aerial bombing. The former Soviet Union and China suffered the most casualties. Estimates place deaths in the Soviet Union at around 23 million, while China suffered about 10 million. No country lost a greater portion of its population than Poland: approximately 5.6 million, or 16%, of its pre-war population of 34.8 million died.

The Holocaust (which roughly means &quot;burnt whole&quot;) was the deliberate and systematic murder of millions of Jews and other &quot;unwanted&quot; during World War II by the Nazi regime in Germany. Several differing views exist regarding whether it was intended to occur from the war's beginning, or if the plans for it came about later.  Regardless, persecution of Jews extended well before the war even started, such as in the ''[[Kristallnacht]]'' (Night of Broken Glass).  The Nazis used propaganda to great effect to stir up anti-Semitic feelings within ordinary Germans.

After World War II, Europe was informally split into Western and Soviet [[Sphere of influence|spheres of influence]]. [[Western Europe]] later aligned as [[NATO|North Atlantic Treaty Organization]] (NATO) and [[Eastern Europe]] as the [[Warsaw Pact]]. There was a shift in power from Western Europe and the [[British Empire]] to the two new superpowers, the United States and the Soviet Union. These two rivals would later face off in the [[Cold War]]. In Asia, the defeat of Japan led to its [[democratization]]. [[Chinese Civil War|China's civil war]] continued through and after the war, resulting eventually in the establishment of the [[People's Republic of China]]. The former colonies of the European powers began their road to independence.

====Post-1945 world====
[[Image:The Earth seen from Apollo 17.jpg|thumb|The Earth seen from Apollo 17. The second half of the 20th century saw an increase of interest in both [[space exploration]] and the [[environmental movement]].]]
The mid-20th century is distinguished from most of human history in that its most significant changes were directly or indirectly economic and technological in nature. Economic development was the force behind vast changes in everyday life, to a degree which was unprecedented in human history.

Over the course of the 20th century, the world's per-capita [[gross domestic product]] grew by a factor of five,&lt;ref&gt;J. Bradford DeLong, [http://www.j-bradford-delong.net/TCEH/2000/TCEH_2.html ''Cornucopia: Increasing Wealth in the Twentieth Century'']. 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; much more than all earlier centuries combined (including the 19th with its Industrial Revolution). Many economists make the case that this understates the magnitude of growth, as many of the goods and services consumed at the end of the 20th century, such as improved medicine (causing world life expectancy to increase by more than two decades) and communications technologies, were not available at any price at its beginning.  However, the gulf between the world's rich and poor grew wider,&lt;ref&gt;Morrison, Wayne. ''Theoretical criminology: from modernity to post-modernism''. Page 53.&lt;/ref&gt; and the majority of the global population remained in the poor side of the divide.&lt;ref&gt;Millennium Ecosystem Assessment (Program). ''Ecosystems and Human Well-Being''. The Millennium Ecosystem Assessment series. Washington, D.C.: Island Press, 2005. Page 12&lt;/ref&gt;

Still, advancing technology and medicine has had a great impact even in the [[Global South]]. Large-scale industry and more centralized [[Mass media|media]] made brutal dictatorships possible on an unprecedented scale in the middle of the century, leading to wars that were also unprecedented. However, the increased communications contributed to [[democratization]]. Technological developments included the development of airplanes and [[space exploration]], [[nuclear technology]], advancement in [[genetics]], and the dawning of the [[Information Age]].

=====American Peace=====
{{Main|Pax Americana}}
[[File:Flag of the United States.svg|thumb|right|National flag of the United States.]]
Pax Americana is an appellation applied to the historical concept of relative liberal peace in the Western world, resulting from the preponderance of power enjoyed by the United States of America starting around the start of the 20th century. Although the term finds its primary utility in the latter half of the 20th century, it has been used in various places and eras. Its modern connotations concern the peace established after the end of World War II in 1945.
{{details|American Century}}

=====Cold War era=====
{{Main|Cold War}}
The Cold War began in the mid-1940s and lasted into the early 1990s. Throughout this period, the conflict was expressed through military coalitions, espionage, weapons development, invasions, propaganda, and competitive technological development. The conflict included costly defense spending, a massive [[Conventional weapon|conventional]] and [[Nuclear weapon|nuclear]] [[arms race]], and numerous [[proxy war]]s; the two [[superpower]]s never fought one another directly.

[[Image:NATO vs Warsaw (1949-1990).png|654px|thumb|center|Borders of [[NATO]] (blue) and Warsaw Pact (red) states during the Cold war era.]]

The Soviet Union created the [[Eastern Bloc]] of countries that it occupied, annexing some as [[Soviet Socialist Republics]] and maintaining others as satellite states that would later form the [[Warsaw Pact]].  The United States and various western European countries began a policy of &quot;[[containment]]&quot; of [[communism]] and forged myriad alliances to this end, including [[NATO]].  Several of these western countries also coordinated efforts regarding the rebuilding of western Europe, including western Germany, which the Soviets opposed.  In other regions of the world, such as Latin America and [[Southeast Asia]], the Soviet Union fostered [[communist revolution]]ary movements, which the United States and many of its allies opposed and, in some cases, attempted to &quot;[[rollback|roll back]]&quot;.  Many countries were prompted to align themselves with the nations that would later form either NATO or the Warsaw Pact, though other movements would also emerge.

The Cold War saw periods of both heightened tension and relative calm. International crises arose, such as the [[Berlin Blockade]] (1948–1949), the [[Korean War]] (1950–1953), the [[Berlin Crisis of 1961]], the [[Vietnam War]] (1959–1975), the [[Cuban Missile Crisis]] (1962), the [[Soviet war in Afghanistan]] (1979–1989) and [[Able Archer 83|NATO exercises in November 1983]].  There were also periods of reduced tension as both sides sought [[détente]]. Direct military attacks on adversaries were deterred by the potential for [[mutual assured destruction]] using deliverable [[nuclear weapon]]s. In the Cold War era, the [[Generation of Love]] and the rise of [[computer]]s changed society in very different, complex ways, including higher social and local mobility.

{| style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;
|-
|[[File:Europe 1988.png|thumb|333px|European [[trade bloc]]s as of the late 1980s. EEC member states are marked in blue, [[EFTA]] &amp;ndash; green, and Comecon &amp;ndash; red.]]
|[[File:Cold War Map 1980.svg|thumb|333px|East and West in 1980, as defined by the Cold War. The Cold War had divided Europe politically into East and West, with the Iron Curtain splitting [[Central Europe]].]]
|}

The Cold War drew to a close in the late 1980s and the early 1990s.  The United States under President [[Ronald Reagan]] increased diplomatic, military, and economic pressure on the Soviet Union, which was already suffering from [[Brezhnev stagnation|severe economic stagnation]]. In the second half of the 1980s, newly appointed Soviet leader [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] introduced the ''[[perestroika]]'' and ''[[glasnost]]'' reforms. [[History of the Soviet Union (1985–1991)|The Soviet Union collapsed]] in 1991, leaving the United States as the dominant military power, though Russia retained much of the massive Soviet nuclear arsenal.

=====Latin America polarization=====
In Latin America in the 1970s, leftists acquired a significant political influence which prompted the right-wing, ecclesiastical authorities and a large portion of the individual country's upper class to support coup d'états to avoid what they perceived as a communist threat. This was further fueled by Cuban and United States intervention which led to a political polarization. Most South American countries were in some periods ruled by [[military dictatorship]]s that were supported by the United States of America. Around the 1970s, the regimes of the [[Southern Cone]] collaborated in [[Operation Condor]] killing many [[leftist]] dissidents, including some [[urban guerrilla]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.el-universal.com.mx/editoriales/34023.html | author = Victor Flores Olea | title = Editoriales - El Universal - 10 de abril 2006 : Operacion Condor | work=[[El Universal (Mexico)|El Universal]] | location=Mexico | accessdate = 2009-03-24 | language=Spanish) }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, by the early 1990s all countries had restored their democracies.

=====Space Age=====
[[Image:Hubble ultra deep field high rez edit1.jpg|thumb|right|275px|This high-resolution image of the Hubble Ultra Deep Field includes galaxies of various ages, sizes, shapes, and colors. The smallest, reddest galaxies, are some of the most distant galaxies to have been imaged by an optical telescope]]
The [[Space Age]] is a period encompassing the activities related to the [[Space Race]], [[space exploration]], space technology, and the cultural developments influenced by these events. The Space Age began with the development of several technologies that culminated with the launch of [[Sputnik 1]] by the Soviet Union. This was the world's first artificial satellite, orbiting the Earth in 98.1 minutes and weighing in at 83&amp;nbsp;kg. The launch of Sputnik 1 ushered a new era of political, scientific and technological achievements that became known as the Space Age. The Space Age was characterized by rapid development of new technology in a close race mostly between the United States and the Soviet Union. The Space Age reached its peak with the [[Apollo program]] which captured the imagination of much of the world's population. The landing of [[Apollo 11]] was an event watched by over 500 million people around the world and is widely recognized as one of the defining moments of the 20th century. Since then and with the end of the space race due to the [[dissolution of the Soviet Union]], public attention has largely moved to other areas.

===Contemporary era===
{{Main|Contemporary history}}
In the Contemporary era, there were various socio-technological trends, among the challenges and problems the modern world faces is climate change. Regarding the 21st century and the late modern world, the Information age and computers were forefront in use, not completely ubiquitous but often present in daily life. The development of Eastern powers was of note, with China and India becoming more powerful. In the Eurasian theater, the European Union and Russian Federation were two forces recently developed. A concern for Western world, if not the whole world, was the late modern form of terrorism and the warfare that has resulted from the contemporary terrorist acts.

==Modern history education and schools==
The [[humanities]] are academic disciplines which study the [[human condition]], using methods that are primarily [[Analytic induction|analytic]], critical, or speculative, as distinguished from the mainly [[empirical]] approaches of the [[natural science|natural]] and [[social sciences]]. Although many of the subjects of modern history coincide with that of standard history, the subject is taught independently by various systems of education in the world.

===British education===
Students can choose the subject at university. The material covered includes from the mid-18th century, to analysis of the present day. Virtually all colleges and sixth forms that do teach modern history do it alongside standard history; very few teach the subject exclusively.

===Universities===
At the [[University of Oxford]] 'Modern History' has a somewhat different meaning. The contrast is not with the Middle Ages but with Antiquity. The earliest period that can be studied in the [[Final Honour School]] of Modern History begins in 285.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.ox.ac.uk/currentunder/honours/history/general/1index.htm history.ox.ac.uk]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
&lt;!--
**Note**
Below are items that do not fall neatly into the parent article.
If you can, please incorporated them in a smooth fashion or leave them here.
Also, please add more if notable and they have not been covered in the parent article text.
********
--&gt;
{{too many see alsos|date=May 2012}}
;Religious: [[Irreligion]], [[Atheism]], [[Ancestor worship]], [[Muslim]]s and the [[Muslim world]], [[Christian]]s and [[Christendom]], [[Huguenots]], [[Puritan]]s, [[Church Missionary Society]], [[Robert College]], [[Pietist]], [[London Missionary Society]], [[Society of Jesus]] ([[Jesuits]]), [[European wars of religion]]

;People and groups: [[Andreas Karlstadt]], [[Anne Boleyn]], [[Menocchio]], [[Descartes]], [[Goethe]], [[Voltaire]], [[Nostradamus]],  [[Isaac Newton]], [[Fugger]], [[Charles VII, Holy Roman Emperor]], [[Boers]], [[Congress of Berlin]], [[Lenin]], [[Yamagata Aritomo]], [[Tojo Hideki]], [[Balkan League]], [[Tutsi]], [[William Paley]], [[Whig (British political faction)|British Whig Party]] and the [[Radical Whigs]], [[Whig Party (United States)|US Whig Party]], [[John Stuart Mill]], [[John Partridge (artist)|John Partridge]], [[Sir Frederick Pollock, 3rd Baronet|Sir Frederick Pollock]], [[William Ashley (economic historian)|William Ashley]], [[American Historical Association]], [[John Adams]], [[Andrew Jackson]] and [[Jacksonian Democracy]], [[United States Republican party]], [[Joseph Galloway]], [[Frederick Jackson Turner]], [[American Anti-Slavery Society]], [[A. P. Herbert]], [[Rosa Parks]], [[Jackie Robinson]], [[Institute of Contemporary History]]{{Disambiguation needed|date=June 2011}}

;Companies and businesses: [[Laissez-faire]], [[Marconi Company]], [[Electric Vehicle Company]], [[Henry Ford]] and the [[Ford Motor Company]], [[AT&amp;T Corporation]], [[Bechtel]], [[Asahi Shimbun]], [[Daily Mail]]

;Areas and histories: [[List of World Map changes]], [[Duchy of Warsaw]], [[Bohemia]], [[Cape Colony]], [[Transvaal Colony|Transvaal]], [[History of the Netherlands]], [[History of Iran]], [[History of Korea]], [[History of Manchuria]], [[History of Vladivostok]], [[History of Pakistan]], [[History of Saudi Arabia]], [[History of Kuwait]], [[History of Cambodia]], [[Kansas-Nebraska Act]], [[History of New York City]], [[Moabit]], [[Willingboro Township, New Jersey|Levittown]]

;Culture and society: [[Iconoclasm]], [[Le Corbusier]], [[Apsley House]], [[Yosano Akiko]], [[Romanticist]], [[Television]] and [[Cable television]], [[History of modern literature]], [[Symbolism (arts)|Symbolist]], The [[Beatles]], [[Rodgers and Hammerstein]], [[I Love Lucy]], [[Mass Observation]]

;Legal:[[letter of credence]], [[prisoner of war]], [[laws of war]], [[exequatur]], [[extradition]], [[right of asylum]], [[jus soli]], [[jus sanguinis]], [[exterritoriality]]

;Other: [[Modernity]], [[Postmodernity]], [[Romanticism]], [[Free silver]], [[political consciousness]], [[Sophisms]], [[Fire of London]], [[Tower of London]], [[utilitarian]], [[Uitlanders]], [[Pan-Slavism]], [[Sinn Féin]], [[UNESCO]], [[Women's suffrage]], The [[Nobel Prize|Nobel]] and the [[Nobel Peace Prize|Peace Prize]], [[Origin of Species]], [[human evolution]], [[Social evolution]], [[Bakelite]], [[Transistor]]s, [[Infidelity]], [[Penicillin]], [[Ethanol]], [[Gasoline]], [[Fuel Cell]], [[Automobile]], [[personal computers]], [[mobile phone]], [[Falklands War]]

;Modernism Framework: [[Modern history#Pre-Modern|Premodernity]], [[Modernism]], [[Postmodernism]]

;[[Western Philosophy]]:  [[Classicism (philosophy)|Classicism]], [[Modernity]], [[Postmodernity]]

==Further reading==
&lt;!-- Books are listed by date; most recent first, oldest last --&gt;
;21st century sources

* Boyd, Andrew, Joshua Comenetz. [http://books.google.com/books?id=P1dly1ikblUC ''An atlas of world affairs'']. Routledge, 2007. ISBN 0-415-39169-5
* Black, Edwin. [http://books.google.com/books?id=IghvdDUumdIC ''Internal Combustion: How Corporations and Governments Addicted the World to Oil and Derailed the Alternatives'']. New York: St. Martin's Press, 2006.
* Briggs, Asa, and Peter Burke. [http://books.google.com/books?id=kIhzo0ze7vsC ''A Social History of the Media: From Gutenberg to the Internet'']. Cambridge: Polity, 2002.
* Barzun, Jacques. [http://books.google.com/books?id=UfdSZQf8UjkC ''From Dawn to Decadence: 500 Years of Western Cultural Life : 1500 to the Present'']. New York: HarperCollins, 2001.

;20th century sources

* Burke, Peter. [http://books.google.com/books?id=fbGuxIsGjwsC ''A Social History of Knowledge: From Gutenberg to Diderot'']. Cambridge, UK: Polity, 2000.
* CBS News. [http://books.google.com/books?id=wO3qlZr7s3MC ''People of the century'']. Simon and Schuster, 1999. ISBN 0-684-87093-2
* Wang, Ke-wen. [http://books.google.com/books?id=j5irhLHE6gUC ''Modern China: an encyclopedia of history, culture, and nationalism'']. Taylor &amp; Francis, 1998. ISBN 0-8153-0720-9
* Huffman, James L. [http://books.google.com/books?id=pXe0zF1jd14C ''Modern Japan: an encyclopedia of history, culture, and nationalism'']. Taylor &amp; Francis, 1998. ISBN 0-8153-2525-8
* Schlesinger, Arthur M. [http://books.google.com/books?id=W8d1AAAAMAAJ ''New Viewpoints in American History'']. New York: Macmillan, 1922.
* Bakeless, John Edwin. [http://books.google.com/books?id=5wgAAAAAYAAJ ''The Economic Causes of Modern War; A Study of the Period: 1878-1918'']. New York: Printed for the Department of political science of Williams college, by Moffat, Yard and Co, 1921
* Day, Clive. [http://books.google.com/books?id=NO5AAAAAIAAJ ''A History of Commerce'']. New York [etc.]: Longmans, Green, and Co, 1921.
* Moore, Edward Caldwell. [http://books.google.com/books?id=F-ATAAAAYAAJ ''The Spread of Christianity in the Modern World'']. Chicago, Ill: University of Chicago Press, 1919.
* Muir, Ramsay. [http://books.google.com/books?id=7mQMAAAAYAAJ ''The Expansion of Europe; The Culmination of Modern History'']. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1917.
* Palat, Madhavan K., [http://www.palgrave.com/products/Title.aspx?pid=262964 Social Identities in Revolutionary Russia], ed. (Macmillan, Palgrave, UK, and St Martin’s Press, New York, 2001).
* Palat, Madhavan K., [http://www.unesco.org/culture/asia/html_eng/volume6.htm History of Civilizations of Central Asia, ed. , vol. 6, Towards the Contemporary Period: From The Mid-Nineteenth Century To The End Of The Twentieth Century], UNESCO, Paris 2005.
* Robinson, James Harvey, and Charles Austin Beard. [http://books.google.com/books?id=9TcNAAAAIAAJ ''Readings in Modern European History; A Collection of Extracts from the Sources Chosen with the Purpose of Illustrating Some of the Chief Phases of Development of Europe During the Last Two Hundred Years'']. Boston: Ginn &amp; Co, 1908.
* McCarthy, Michael J. F. [http://books.google.com/books?id=tiMMAAAAYAAJ ''The Coming Power; A Contemporary History of the Far East'', 1898-1905]. London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1905.
* Kidd, Benjamin. [http://books.google.com/books?id=PzkoAAAAYAAJ ''Principles of Western Civilisation'']. London: Macmillan and Co., Limited, 1902.
* Acton, John Emerich Edward Dalberg Acton, Adolphus William Ward, G. W. Prothero, Stanley Mordaunt Leathes, and E. A. Benians. ''[[The Cambridge Modern History]]''. New York: Macmillan Co, 1902
* Wilson, George Grafton, and George Fox Tucker. [http://books.google.com/books?id=1Tm3AAAAIAAJ ''International Law'']. New York: Silver, Burdett and co, 1901.

;19th century sources

* Stubbs, William. [http://books.google.com/books?id=TE4MAAAAYAAJ ''Seventeen Lectures on the Study of Medieval and Modern History and Kindred Subjects; Delivered at Oxford, Under Statutory Obligation in the Years 1867-1884; with Two Addresses Given at Oxford and Reading'']. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1900.
* Duruy, Victor, and Edwin A. Grosvenor. [http://books.google.com/books?id=WGIMAAAAYAAJ ''History of Modern Times, From the Fall of Constantinople to the French Revolution'']. New York: H. Holt and company, 1894.
* Fredet, Peter. [http://books.google.com/books?id=wWsqAAAAYAAJ ''Modern History; From the Coming of Christ and Change of the Roman Republic into an Empire, to the Year of Our Lord 1888'']. Baltimore: J. Murphy &amp; Co, 1888.
* Thalheimer, M. E. [http://books.google.com/books?id=A8sXAAAAIAAJ ''An Outline of General History: For the Use of Schools'']. Cincinnati: Van Antwerp, Bragg &amp; Co, 1883.
* Lord, John. [http://books.google.com/books?id=-aEOAAAAYAAJ ''A Modern History, From the Time of Luther to the Fall of Napoleon'']. Philadelphia: C. Desilver &amp; Sons [etc.], 1877.
* Michelet, Jules, and M. C. M. Simpson. [http://books.google.com/books?id=0mAMAAAAYAAJ ''A Summary of Modern History'']. London: Macmillan, 1875.
* Timbs, John. [http://books.google.com/books?id=RJgBAAAAQAAJ ''Predictions Realized in Modern Times.: Now First Collected by Horace Welby'']. London: Kent and Co. Paternoster Row, 1862.
* Post, Truman M. [http://books.google.com/books?id=NMINAAAAYAAJ ''The Skeptical Era in Modern History; Or, The Infidelity of the Eighteenth Century, the Product of Spiritual Despotism'']. New York: C. Scribner, 1856.
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=XIUDAAAAQAAJ ''Modern history'']. Chambers W. and R., ltd. 1856.
* Michelet, Jules, and Alonzo Potter. [http://books.google.com/books?id=-atJAAAAIAAJ ''Modern History'']. New York: Harper &amp; Brothers, 82 Cliff-St, 1846.
* Goodrich, Samuel G. [http://books.google.com/books?id=wqsfAAAAMAAJ ''Famous Men of Modern Times'']. Boston: Bradbury, Soden &amp; Co, 1843.
* [http://books.google.com/books?id=JJ11AAAAIAAJ ''General History of the World: Abridged'']. Huddersfield: Brook and Lancaster, 1802.

==References==
;General information
''Books''
* Earle, Edward Mead. [http://books.google.com/books?id=YncMAAAAYAAJ ''An Outline of Modern History; A Syllabus with Map Studies'']. New York: Macmillan Co, 1921.
* Grosvenor, Edwin A. [http://books.google.com/books?id=DVQPAAAAYAAJ ''Contemporary History of the World'']. New York and Boston: T.Y. Crowell &amp; Co, 1899.
* Taylor, William Cooke, Charles Duke Yonge, and G. W. Cox. [http://books.google.com/books?id=bjQYAAAAYAAJ ''The Student's Manual of Modern History; Containing the Rise and Progress of the Principal European Nations, Their Political History, and the Changes in Their Social Condition; with a History of the Colonies Founded by Europeans'']. 1880.
* {{Cite book
|last=Bryant
|first=Arthur
|title=The age of elegance
|url=http://www.worldcat.org/title/age-of-elegance-1812-1822/oclc/14763324
|accessdate=2010-04-29
|volume=2
|year='''1950'''
|publisher= New York and Boston
|page=54
}} [[ISSN|ISSN 1476-3324]]

''Websites''
*[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/modsbook.html Internet Modern History Sourcebook], fordham.edu
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://jch.sagepub.com/ ''Journal of Contemporary History'']. SAGE Publications. ISSN 1461-7250  (Print ISSN 0022-0094)
*[http://www.ohiou.edu/conhist/ Contemporary History Institute (CHI)]. ohiou.edu (ed., Analyzes the contemporary period in world affairs—the period from World War II to the present—from an interdisciplinary historical perspective.)
*[http://afe.easia.columbia.edu/chinawh/index.html ''China and Europe, 1500–2000 and Beyond: What is Modern?'']. [[Columbia University]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Modern History}}
[[Category:Modern history| ]]
[[Category:Historical eras]]
[[Category:Modernism]]
[[Category:Historiography]]
[[Category:Postmodern theory]]

[[als:Neuzeit]]
[[cs:Novověk]]
[[da:Nyere tid (historisk periode)]]
[[de:Neuzeit]]
[[et:Uusaeg]]
[[eo:Moderna epoko]]
[[hr:Novi vijek]]
[[id:Zaman modern]]
[[hu:Újkor]]
[[nl:Nieuwe Tijd]]
[[nds:Nutiet]]
[[simple:Modern history]]
[[sk:Novovek]]
[[sl:Novi vek]]
[[sr:Нови вијек]]
[[fi:Uusi aika]]
[[sv:Modern tid]]
[[uk:Нова історія]]
[[yi:נייע צייט]]
[[zh:現代史]]</text>
      <sha1>tecus8cohf7xv1pkfi7i4frs0eg259v</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
