<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mongol Empire</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>240146</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522435823</id>
      <parentid>522389064</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T05:15:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjensen</username>
        <id>313197</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/96.255.247.52|96.255.247.52]] ([[User talk:96.255.247.52|talk]]) to last version by Adashiel</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="95275">{{Infobox Former Country
|native_name=Ikh Mongol Uls
|conventional_long_name=Mongol Empire
|common_name=Mongol Empire
|gf|image_map = Mongol Empire map.gif
|image_caption=Expansion of the Mongol Empire
|continent=Eurasia
|country=Mongolia
|status=Empire
|government_type=[[Elective monarchy]]
|image_flag = White Sulde of the Mongol Empire.jpg
|flag = Flag of the Mongols
|flag_type = Modern reconstruction of the Nine Base White Banners
|title_leader=[[Great Khan]]
|leader1=Genghis Khan
|year_leader1=1206–1227
|leader2=Ögedei Khan
|year_leader2=1229–1241
|leader3=Güyük Khan
|year_leader3=1246–1248
|leader4=Möngke Khan
|year_leader4=1251–1259
|leader5=Kublai Khan
|year_leader5=1260–1294
|leader6=[[Toghan Temür]] Khan
|year_leader6=1333–1370
|legislature  = ''[[Kurultai]]''
|national_motto =
|stat_area1_km = 24000000
|religion = [[Tengrism]], later [[Buddhism]], [[Islam]], [[Christianity]], and [[Religion in the Mongol Empire|others]]
|currency = [[Coin]]s (such as [[dirham]]s), [[Sukhe]], [[banknote|paper money]] (paper currency backed by silk or silver ingots, and the Yuan's [[Chao (currency)|Chao]])
|capital=[[Avarga]]&lt;br&gt;[[Karakorum]]&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot;&gt;The actual foundation of this city did not occur until 1220, and served as the capital of the Mongol Empire as least until 1259.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Khanbaliq|Dadu]]&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot;&gt;After the death of [[Möngke Khan]] in 1259, there was no single major city in the empire, with [[Khanbaliq|Dadu]] being the capital of the [[Yuan Dynasty]] from 1272 to 1368.&lt;/ref&gt; (modern [[Beijing]])
|year_start=1206
|event_start=[[Genghis Khan]] unified the tribes and proclaimed the Great Mongol State
|event1=Death of [[Genghis Khan]]
|date_event1=1227
|event2=Pax Mongolica
|date_event2=1210–1350
|event3=Fragmentation of the empire
|date_event3=1260–1264
|year_end=1368
|event_end=Fall of [[Yuan Dynasty]], marking the empire's final dissolution
|p1          = Khamag Mongol
|s1          = Chagatai Khanate
|s2          = Golden Horde
|s3          = Ilkhanate
|s4          = Yuan Dynasty
|s5          = Northern Yuan
|today                  = {{Collapsible list |titlestyle=font-weight:normal; background:transparent; text-align:left;|title=Countries today|
{{flag|Afghanistan}}|{{flag|Armenia}}|{{flag|Azerbaijan}}|{{flag|Belarus}}|{{flag|China}}|{{flag|Georgia}}|{{flag|India}}|{{flag|Iran}}|{{flag|Iraq}}|{{flag|Kazakhstan}}|{{flag|Kyrgyzstan}}|{{flag|Laos}}|{{flag|Moldova}}|{{flag|Mongolia}}|{{flag|Myanmar}}||{{flag|North Korea}}|{{flag|Pakistan}}|{{flag|Poland}}|{{flag|Romania}}|{{flag|Russia}}|{{flag|South Korea}}|{{flag|Syria}}|{{flag|Tajikistan}}|{{flag|Turkey}}|{{flag|Turkmenistan}}|{{flag|Ukraine}}|{{flag|Uzbekistan}}|{{flag|Vietnam}}
}}
}}
The '''Mongol Empire''' ([[Mongolian language|Mongolian]]:{{Audio|Mongoliinezentguren.ogg|listen}} ''Mongol-yn Ezent Güren''; [[Mongolian Cyrillic alphabet|Cyrillic]]: Монголын эзэнт гүрэн) existed during the 13th and 14th centuries A.D., and was the [[List of largest empires#Contiguous|largest contiguous land empire]] in human history.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in the Central Asian steppes, it eventually stretched from Eastern Europe to the [[Sea of Japan]], covering large parts of [[Siberia]] in the north and extending southward into Southeast Asia, the [[Indian subcontinent]], the [[Iranian plateau]], and the Middle East. At its greatest extent it spanned {{convert|9700|km|mi|abbr=on}}, covered an area of {{convert|24000000|km2|sqmi|-5|abbr=on}},&lt;ref&gt;Finlay. ''Pilgrim Art''. p.151.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/102315/history-of-Central-Asia/73543/Creation-of-the-Mongol-empire&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;«Mongolia se encomienda a Gengis Jan» {{es icon}}. ''El País'' 18.08.2007 (2007). Consultado el 19/06/2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Turchin, Thomas D. Hall and Jonathan M. Adams, &quot;[http://jwsr.ucr.edu/archive/vol12/number2/pdf/jwsr-v12n2-tah.pdf East-West Orientation of Historical Empires]&quot;. ''Journal of World-Systems Research'' Vol. 12 (no. 2). pp. 219-229 (2006).&lt;/ref&gt; 16% of the Earth's total land area, and held sway over a population of 100 million.

The Mongol Empire emerged from the unification of [[Mongols|Mongol]] and [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] tribes of historical [[Mongolia]] under the leadership of [[Genghis Khan]]. Genghis Khan was proclaimed ruler of all Mongols in 1206. The empire grew rapidly under his rule and then under the rule of his descendants, who sent [[Mongol invasions|invasions]] in every direction.&lt;ref&gt;Diamond. ''Guns, Germs, and Steel''. p. 367.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Mongols and Russia'', by [[George Vernadsky]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Mongol World Empire, 1206-1370'', by John Andrew Boyle&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The History of China'', by David Curtis Wright. p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Early Civilization of China'', by Yong Yap Cotterell, Arthur Cotterell. p. 223.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Mongols and Mamluks: The Mamluk-Ilkhanid War, 1260&amp;ndash;1281'' by Reuven Amitai-Preiss&lt;/ref&gt; The vast transcontinental empire which connected the [[eastern world|east]] with the [[western world|west]] with an enforced ''[[Pax Mongolica]]'' allowed trade, technologies, commodities and ideologies to be disseminated and exchanged across [[Eurasia]].&lt;ref&gt;Gregory G.Guzman &quot;Were the barbarians a negative or positive factor in ancient and medieval history?&quot;, ''The Historian'' 50 (1988), 568-70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allsen. ''Culture and Conquest''. p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt;

The empire began to split as a result of wars over succession, as the grandchildren of Genghis Khan disputed whether the royal line should follow from Genghis's son and initial heir [[Ögedei Khan|Ögedei]], or one of his other sons such as [[Tolui]], [[Chagatai Khan|Chagatai]], or [[Jochi]]. The Toluids prevailed after a bloody purge of Ögedeid and Chagataid factions, but disputes continued even among the descendants of Tolui. When one Great Khan died, rival ''[[kurultai]]'' councils would simultaneously elect different successors, such as the brothers [[Ariq Böke]] and [[Kublai Khan|Kublai]], they were both elected and then not only had to defy each other, but also deal with challenges from descendants of other of Genghis's sons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucalgary.ca/applied_history/tutor/islam/mongols/goldenHorde.html |title=The Islamic World to 1600: The Golden Horde|publisher=University of Calgary|year=1998|accessdate=December 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Biran. ''Qaidu and the Rise of the Independent Mongol State in Central Asia''. The Curzon Press, 1997, ISBN 0-7007-0631-3&lt;/ref&gt; Kublai successfully took power, but civil war ensued, as Kublai sought, unsuccessfully, to regain control of the [[Chagatai khans|Chagatayid]] and [[House of Ögedei|Ögedeid families]]. 

By the time of Kublai's death in 1294, the Mongol Empire had fractured into four separate khanates or empires, each pursuing its own separate interests and objectives: the [[Golden Horde]] khanate in the northwest, the [[Chagatai Khanate]] in the west, the [[Ilkhanate]] in the southwest, and the [[Yuan Dynasty]] based in modern-day [[Beijing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;China p413&quot;&gt;''The Cambridge History of China: Alien Regimes and Border States''. p. 413.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1304, the three western khanates briefly accepted the nominal suzerainty of the Yuan Dynasty,&lt;ref&gt;Jackson. ''Mongols and the West''. p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allsen. ''Culture and Conquest'. pp. xiii, 235.&lt;/ref&gt; but when it was overthrown by the [[Han Chinese]] [[Ming Dynasty]] in 1368, the Mongol Empire finally dissolved.

==Name==
What is referred to in English as the Mongol Empire was called the ''Ikh mongol uls'' (Great Mongolian Nation).&lt;ref&gt;Sanders. p. 300.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1240s, Genghis's descendant [[Güyük Khan]] wrote a letter to [[Pope Innocent IV]] which used the preamble, &quot;Dalai (great/oceanic) Khagan of the great Mongol state (ulus)&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Saunders. ''History of the Mongol conquests''. p. 225.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the succession war between [[Kublai Khan]] and his brother [[Ariq Böke]], Ariq limited Kublai's real power to the eastern part of the empire, Kublai officially issued an imperial [[edict]] on December 18, 1271 to name the country &quot;Great Yuan&quot; (''Dai Yuan'', or ''Dai On Ulus'') to establish the [[Yuan Dynasty]]. Some sources state that the full Mongolian name was ''Dai Ön Yehe Monggul Ulus''.&lt;ref&gt;Rybatzki. p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Pre-empire context===
{{Main|Mongols before Genghis Khan}}
[[File:YuanEmperorAlbumGenghisPortrait.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Painting of Genghis Khan|[[Genghis Khan]]'s picture at the [[National Palace Museum]] in [[Taipei, Taiwan]].]]
The area around [[Mongolia]], [[Manchuria]], and parts of [[North China]] had been controlled by the [[Liao Dynasty]] since the 10th century. In 1125, the [[Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)|Jin Dynasty]] founded by the [[Jurchens]] overthrew the Liao Dynasty, and attempted to gain control over former Liao territory in Mongolia. The Jin Dynasty rulers, known as the Golden Kings, successfully resisted in the 1130s the [[Khamag Mongol]] confederation, ruled at the time by [[Khabul Khan]], great grandfather of Temujin (Genghis Khan). The [[Mongolian plateau]] was occupied mainly by five powerful tribal confederations (''khanlig''): [[Kereit]], Khamag Mongol, [[Naimans|Naiman]], [[Merkit|Mergid]] and [[Tatar confederation|Tatar]]. The Jin emperors, following a policy of [[divide and rule]], encouraged disputes among the tribes, especially between the Tatars and Mongols, in order to keep the nomadic tribes distracted by their own battles, and thereby away from themselves. Khabul's successor was [[Ambaghai|Ambaghai Khan]], who was betrayed by the Tatars, handed to the Jurchen and executed. The Mongols retaliated by raiding the frontier, resulting in a failed Jurchen counter-attack in 1143. In 1147, the Jin somewhat changed their policy, signing a peace treaty with the Mongols and withdrawing a score of forts. The Mongols then resumed attacks on the Tatars to avenge the death of their late khan, opening a long period of active hostilities. The Jin and Tatar armies defeated the Mongols in 1161.&lt;ref&gt;Barfield. p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genghis Khan===
{{History of the Mongols}}
{{Main|Khamag Mongol|Genghis Khan}}
[[File:PremongolEurasia.png|thumb|left|alt=Map of Eurasia showing the different states|[[Eurasia]] on the eve of the Mongol invasions, ''c.'' 1200.]]
Known during his childhood as Temujin, Genghis Khan was the son of a Mongol chieftain. He suffered a difficult childhood, and when his young wife [[Börte]] was kidnapped by a rival tribe, Temujin united the nomadic, previously ever-rivaling Mongol-Turkic tribes under his rule through political manipulation and military might. His most powerful allies were his father's friend, Kereyd chieftain [[Wang Khan]] Toghoril, and Temujin's childhood [[anda (Mongol)|''anda'']] (blood brother) [[Jamukha]] of the Jadran clan. With their help, Temujin defeated the Merkit tribe, rescued his wife Börte, and then went on to defeat the Naimans and Tatars.&lt;ref name=morgan-49&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. pp. 49–73.&lt;/ref&gt;

Temujin forbade looting and raping of his enemies without permission, and implemented a policy of sharing spoils with the Mongol warriors and their families, instead of giving all to the aristocrats.&lt;ref&gt;Riasanovsky. ''Fundamental Principles of Mongol law''. p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt; He thus held the Khan title. These policies brought him into conflict with his uncles, who were also legitimate heirs to the throne, they regarded Temujin not as leader but merely an insolent usurper. This controversy spread to his generals and other associates, and some Mongols who had previously been allies with him broke their allegiance. War ensued, but Temujin and the forces still loyal to him prevailed, and from 1203–1205 destroyed all the remaining rival tribes and brought them under his sway. In 1206, Temujin was crowned as the [[Khaghan]] of the ''Yekhe Mongol Ulus'' (Great Mongol Nation) at a ''[[Kurultai]]'' (general assembly/council). It was there that he assumed the title of &quot;Genghis Khan&quot;  (universal leader) instead of one of the old tribal titles such as Gur Khan or Tayang Khan, and marked the start of the Mongol Empire.&lt;ref name=morgan-49/&gt;

===Early organization===
Genghis Khan innovated many ways of organizing his army, dividing it into decimal subsections of arbans (10 people), zuuns (100), myangans (1000) and [[tumen]]s (10,000). The ''[[Kheshig]]'' or the [[Imperial Guard]] was founded and divided into day (''[[khorchin]]'', ''[[torghuds]]'') and night guards (''[[khevtuul]]'').&lt;ref&gt;Ratchnevsky. p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt; He rewarded those who had been loyal to him and placed them in high positions, placing them as heads of army units and households, even though many of his allies had been from very low-rank clans. Compared to the units he gave to his loyal companions, those assigned to his own family members were quite few. He proclaimed a new law of the empire, ''Ikh Zasag'' or ''[[Yassa]]'', and codified everything related to the everyday life and political affairs of the nomads at the time. He forbade the selling of women, theft of other's properties, fighting between the Mongols, and the hunting of animals during the breeding season.&lt;ref&gt;''Secret history''. p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt;

He appointed his adopted brother Shigi-Khuthugh supreme judge (''jarughachi''), ordering him to keep records of the empire. In addition to laws regarding family, food and army, Genghis also decreed religious freedom and supported domestic and international trade. He exempted the poor and the clergy from taxation.&lt;ref&gt;Vladimortsov. p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, [[Muslim]]s, [[Buddhist]]s and [[Christian]]s from Manchuria, North China, India and Persia joined Genghis Khan long before his foreign conquests. He also encouraged literacy, adopting the [[Uyghur script]] which would form the [[Mongolian script|Uyghur-Mongolian script]] of the empire, and he ordered the [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] Tatatunga, who had previously served the khan of Naimans, to instruct his sons.&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;

Genghis quickly came into conflict with the Jin Dynasty of the Jurchens and the [[Western Xia]] of the [[Tanguts]] in northern China. Towards the West, under the provocation of the Muslim [[Caliphate]] [[Khwarezmid Empire]], he moved into [[Central Asia]] as well, devastating [[Transoxiana]] and the eastern [[Persian Empire|Persia]], then raiding into [[Kievan Rus']] (a [[predecessor state]] of Russia, [[Belarus]] and [[Ukraine]]) and the [[Caucasus]].&lt;ref name=morgan-49/&gt;

Before his death, Genghis Khan divided his empire among his sons and immediate family, making the Mongol Empire the joint property of the entire imperial family who, along with the Mongol aristocracy, constituted the ruling class.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. pp. 99–101.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Expansion under Ögedei===
{{main|Mongol conquests}}
As previously stated the Mongol Empire started in Central Asia, with the unification of [[Mongol]] and [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] tribes.  Under the leadership of Genghis Khan, the empire expanded westwards across Asia into the Middle East, [[Rus' (region)|Rus]], and Europe; southward into India and China; and eastward as far as the [[Korean Peninsula]], and into Southeast Asia.&lt;ref name=morgan-49/&gt;

[[File:YuanEmperorAlbumOgedeiPortrait.jpg|thumb||alt=Painting of Ögedei Khan|[[Ögedei Khan]], Genghis Khan's son and successor.]]
Genghis Khan died in 1227, by which point the Mongol Empire ruled from the Pacific Ocean to the [[Caspian Sea]] – an empire twice the size of the [[Roman Empire]] and Muslim [[Caliphate]]. Genghis had stated that his heir should be his third son, the charismatic [[Ögedei Khan|Ögedei]]. The regency was originally held by Ögedei's younger brother [[Tolui]], until Ögedei's formal election at the ''kurultai'' in 1229.&lt;ref&gt;Man. ''Genghis Khan''. p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt;

Among his first actions, Ögedei sent troops to subjugate the [[Bashkirs]], [[Bulgars]], and other nations in the Kipchak-controlled steppes.&lt;ref&gt;Saunders. p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; In the east, Ögedei's armies re-established Mongol authority in Manchuria, crushing the [[Puxian Wannu|Eastern Xia]] regime and [[Water Tatars]]. In 1230, the Great Khan personally led his army in the campaign against the [[Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)|Jin Dynasty]] (China). Ögedei's general [[Subutai]] captured Emperor [[Emperor Aizong of Jin|Wanyan Shouxu]]'s capital, [[Kaifeng]] in 1232.&lt;ref&gt;Atwood. p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1234, three armies commanded by Ögedei's sons Kochu and Koten, as well as the [[Tangut people|Tangut]] general Chagan, invaded southern China. With the assistance of the [[Song Dynasty]], the Mongols finished off the Jin in 1234.&lt;ref&gt;Rossabi. p. 221.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Atwood. p. 509.&lt;/ref&gt; In the West, Ögedei's general [[Chormaqan]] destroyed [[Jalal ad-Din Mingburnu]], the last [[shah]] of the [[Khwarazmian dynasty|Khwarizmian Empire]]. The small kingdoms in Southern Persia voluntarily accepted Mongol supremacy.&lt;ref&gt;May. ''Chormaqan''. p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amitai. ''The Mamluk-Ilkhanid war''&lt;/ref&gt; In East Asia, there were [[Mongol invasions of Korea|a number of Mongolian campaigns into Goryeo Korea]], but Ögedei's attempt to annex the [[Korean Peninsula]] met with little success. The king of [[Goryeo]], [[Gojong of Goryeo|Gojong]], surrendered but revolted and massacred Mongol ''[[darughachi]]s'' (overseers), and then moved his imperial court from [[Gaeseong]] to [[Ganghwa Island]].&lt;ref&gt;Grousset. p. 259.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the empire grew, Ögedei established a Mongol capital at [[Karakorum]] in northwestern Mongolia.&lt;ref&gt;Burgan. p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Sacking of Suzdal by Batu Khan.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Painting of a battle scene|Sacking of [[Suzdal]] by [[Batu Khan]] in February, 1238: a [[Miniature (illuminated manuscript)|miniature]] from the 16th century chronicle.]]
Meanwhile, in an offensive action against the Song Dynasty, Mongol armies captured Siyang-yang, the [[Yangtze River|Yangtze]] and [[Sichuan]], but did not secure their control over the conquered sites. The Song generals were able to recapture Siyang-yang from the Mongols in 1239. After the sudden death of Ögedei's son Kochu in Chinese territory, the Mongols withdrew from southern China, although Kochu's brother Prince Koten invaded [[Tibet]] right after their withdrawal.&lt;ref name=morgan-49/&gt;

Another grandson of Genghis Khan, [[Batu Khan]], overran the countries of the [[Volga Bulgaria|Bulgars]], the [[Alans]], the Kypchaks, Bashkirs, [[Mordvin]]s, [[Chuvash people|Chuvash]], and other nations of the southern Russian steppe. By 1237, the Mongols began encroaching upon their first Russian principality, [[Ryazan]]. After a 3 day-siege using heavy attacks, the Mongols captured the city and massacred its inhabitants, then proceeded to destroy the army of the Grand principality of [[Vladimir]] at [[Battle of the Sit River|the Sit River]]. The Mongols captured the [[Alania]] capital, [[Maghas]], in 1238. By 1240, all [[Kievan Rus'|Rus]]’ lands including [[Kiev]] [[Mongol invasion of Rus|had fallen to the Asian invaders]] except for a few northern cities. Mongol troops under Chormaqan in Persia [[Mongol invasions of Georgia and Armenia|connected his invasion]] of [[Transcaucasia]] with the invasion of Batu and Subutai, forced the [[Georgia (country)|Georgian]] and [[Armenia]]n nobles to surrender as well.&lt;ref&gt;Timothy May. ''Chormaqan''. p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the military successes, strife continued within the Mongol ranks. Batu's relations with [[Güyük]], Ögedei's eldest son, and [[Büri]], the beloved grandson of [[Chagatai Khan]], remained tense, and worsened during Batu's victory banquet in southern Russia, nevertheless Güyük and Buri couldn´t do anything to harm Batu's position as long as his uncle Ögedei was still alive. Meanwhile, Ögedei continued with [[Mongol invasions of India|Mongol invasions into the Indian subcontinent]], temporarily investing [[Uchch]], [[Lahore]] and [[Multan]] of the [[Delhi Sultanate]] and stationing a Mongol overseer in [[Kashmir]],&lt;ref&gt;Jackson. ''Delhi Sultanate''. p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt; though the invasions into India eventually failed and were forced to drive back. In northeastern Asia, Ögedei agreed to settle conflicts with [[Goryeo]] by making it a client state and sent Mongolian princesses to wed Goryeo princes. He then reinforced his ''keshig'' with the Koreans through both diplomacy and military force.&lt;ref&gt;Bor. p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Atwood. p. 297.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Henthorn. ''Korea, the Mongol invasions''.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Legnica.JPG|260px|thumb|alt=Painting of a battle scene with mounted warriors on either side|The [[Battle of Legnica|battle of Liegnitz]], 1241. From a medieval manuscript of the [[Hedwig of Poland|Hedwig]] legend.]]
The [[Mongol invasion of Europe|advance into Europe]] continued with Mongol invasions of Poland, Hungary and [[Transylvania]]. When the western flank of the Mongols plundered Polish cities, a European alliance between the [[Poles]], the [[Moravia]]ns, and the Christian military orders of the [[Hospitallers]], [[Teutonic Knights]] and the [[Knights Templar|Templars]] assembled sufficient forces to halt, although briefly, the Mongol advance [[Battle of Legnica|at Legnica]]. The [[Kingdom of Hungary|Hungarian]] army, their [[Croats|Croatian allies]] and the Templar Knights were beaten by Mongols at the banks of [[battle of Mohi|Sajo River]] on April 11, 1241. After their victories over European Knights at [[Legnica]] and [[Muhi]], Mongol armies quickly advanced across [[Bohemia]], [[Serbia]], [[Babenberg]] Austria and into the [[Holy Roman Empire]],&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 157.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Howorth. pp. 55-62.&lt;/ref&gt; but before Batu's forces could continue into [[Vienna]] and northern [[Albania]], news of Ögedei's death in December 1241 brought a halt to the invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weatherford. p. 158&quot;&gt;Weatherford. p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matthew Paris. ''English history'' (trans. by J.A.Giles). p. 348.&lt;/ref&gt; As was customary in Mongol military tradition, all princes of Genghis's line had to attend the ''kurultai'' to elect a successor. Batu and his western Mongol army withdrew from Central Europe the next year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan. p. 104&quot;&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. p. 104.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-Ögedei power struggles===
[[File:YuanEmperorAlbumGüyükPortrait1.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Painting of Güyük Khan|[[Güyük Khan]], Ögedei Khan's son and successor.]]
Following the Great Khan Ögedei's death in 1241, and before the next ''kurultai'', Ögedei's widow [[Töregene]] took over the empire. She persecuted her husband's Khitan and Muslim officials, giving high positions to her own allies instead. She built palaces, cathedrals and social structures on an imperial scale, supporting religion and education. She was able to win over most Mongol aristocrats to support Ögedei's son [[Güyük Khan|Güyük]]. But Batu, ruler of the [[Golden Horde]], refused to come to the ''kurultai'', claiming he was ill and the Mongolian climate was too harsh for him. The resulting stalemate lasted more than four years, and further destabilized the unity of the empire.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson. ''Mongols and the West''. p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Genghis Khan's youngest brother [[Temüge]] threatened Töregene to seize the throne, Güyük came to Karakorum to try and secure his position.&lt;ref&gt;The Academy of Russian science and the academy of Mongolian science ''Tataro-Mongols in Europe and Asia''. p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; Batu eventually agreed to send his brothers and generals to the ''kurultai'' which Töregene convened in 1246. Güyük by this time was ill and alcoholic, but his campaigns in Manchuria and Europe gave him the kind of stature necessary for a Great Khan. He was duly elected at a ceremony attended by Mongols and foreign dignitaries from both within and without the empire—leaders of vassal nations, and representatives from Rome and other entities, who came to the ''kurultai'' to show their respects and negotiate diplomacy.&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Man. ''Kublai Khan''. p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Guyuk khan's Stamp 1246.jpg|right|thumb|250px|alt=White paper with vertical lines of red Mongolian text|Seal from [[Güyük Khan]]'s letter to [[Pope Innocent IV]], 1246.]]
Güyük took steps to reduce corruption, announcing that he would continue the policies of his father Ögedei, not Töregene. He punished Töregene's supporters, except governor [[Arghun the Elder]]. He also replaced young [[Qara Hülëgü]], the khan of the [[Chagatai Khanate]], with his favorite cousin [[Yesü Möngke]] to assert his newly conferred powers. He restored his father's officials to their former positions and was surrounded by the Uyghur, [[Naimans|Naiman]] and Central Asian officials, favoring [[Han Chinese]] commanders who helped his father's conquest of Northern China. He continued military operations in Korea, advanced into Song China in the south and Iraq in the west, and ordered an empire-wide census. Güyük also divided the Sultanate of Rum between [[Kaykaus II|Izz-ad-Din Kaykawus]] and [[Kilij Arslan IV|Rukn ad-Din Kilij Arslan]], though Kaykawus disagreed with this decision.&lt;ref name=atwood-255&gt;Atwood. p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Turtle-Karakorum.jpg|left|thumb|250px|alt=Photograph of a field with a large stone tortoise|[[Bixi (tortoise)|Stone Turtle]] at Karakorum.]]
Not all parts of the empire respected Güyük's election. The [[Hashshashin]]s, former Mongol allies whose Grand Master Hasan Jalalud-Din had offered his submission to Genghis Khan in 1221, angered Güyük by refusing to submit, instead murdering Mongol generals in Persia. Güyük appointed his best friend's father [[Eljigidei]] as chief commander of the troops in Persia, and gave them the task of both reducing the strongholds of the [[Assassins]] a Muslim mouvement, and conquering the [[Abbasids]] in the center of the Islamic world, [[Iran]] and [[Iraq]].&lt;ref name=atwood-255/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;D. Bayarsaikhan. ''Ezen khaaniig Ismailiinhan horooson uu'' (Did the Ismailis kill the Great Khan){{Better source|date=February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1248, Güyük raised more troops and suddenly marched westwards from the Mongol capital of Karakorum. The reasoning was unclear: some sources wrote that he sought to recuperate his personal property Emyl; others suggested that he might have been moving to join Eljigidei to conduct a full-scale conquest of the Middle East, or possibly to make a surprise attack on his rival cousin Batu Khan in Russia. Suspicious of Güyük's motives, [[Sorghaghtani Beki]], the widow of Genghis's son Tolui, secretly warned her nephew Batu of Güyük's approach. Batu had himself been traveling eastwards at the time, possibly to pay homage, or perhaps with other plans in mind. Before the forces of Batu and Güyük met though, Güyük, sick and worn out by travel, died en route at Qum-Senggir in Eastern Turkestan, possibly a victim of poison.&lt;ref&gt;Atwood. p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;

Güyük's widow [[Oghul Qaimish]] stepped forward to take control of the empire, but she lacked the skills of her mother-in-law Töregene, and her young sons Khoja and Naku and other princes challenged her authority. To decide on a new Great Khan, Batu called a ''kurultai'' on his own territory in 1250. As it was far from the Mongolian heartland, members of the Ögedeid and Chagataid families refused to attend. The ''kurultai'' offered the throne to Batu, but he rejected it, claiming he had no interest in the position. He instead nominated Möngke, a grandson of Genghis of his son Tolui lineage. Möngke was leading a Mongol army in Russia, Northern Caucasus and Hungary. The pro-Tolui faction rose up and supported Batu's choice, and Möngke was elected, though given the ''kurultai's'' limited attendance and location, it was of questionable validity. Batu sent Möngke under the protection of his brothers, [[Berke]] and Tukhtemur, and his son [[Sartaq]] to assemble a more formal ''kurultai'' at Kodoe Aral in the heartland. The supporters of Möngke invited Oghul Qaimish and other main Ögedeid and Chagataid princes to attend the ''kurultai'', but they refused each time. The Ögedeid and Chagataid princes refused to accept a descendant of Genghis's son Tolui as leader, demanding that only descendants of Genghis's son Ögedei could be Great Khan.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Toluid reformation===
[[File:YuanEmperorAlbumMöngkePortrait.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Painting of Möngke Khan|[[Möngke Khan]], Genghis Khan's grandson.]]
When Möngke's mother Sorghaghtani and their cousin [[Berke]] organized a second ''kurultai'' on July 1, 1251, the assembled throng proclaimed Möngke Great Khan of the Mongol Empire. This marked a major shift in the leadership of the empire, transferring power from the descendants of Genghis's son Ögedei to the descendants of Genghis's son Tolui. The decision was acknowledged by a few of the Ögedeid and Chagataid princes, such as Möngke's cousin [[Kadan]] and the deposed khan Qara Hülëgü, but one of the other legitimate heirs, Ögedei's grandson Shiremun, sought to topple Möngke. Shiremun moved with his own forces towards the emperor's nomadic palace with a plan for an armed attack, but Möngke was alerted by his falconer of the plan. Möngke ordered an investigation of the plot, which led to a series of major trials all across the empire. Many members of the Mongol elite were found guilty and put to death, with estimates ranging from 77–300, though princes of Genghis's royal line were often exiled rather than executed. Möngke eliminated the Ögedeid and the Chagatai families' estates and shared the western part of the empire with his ally [[Batu Khan]]. After the bloody purge, Möngke ordered a general amnesty for prisoners and captives, but ever after, the power of the Great Khan's throne remained firmly with the descendants of Genghis's son Tolui.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. pp. 103–104.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Kharkorum silver tree1.jpg|thumb|250px|alt=Photograph of a large red-roofed Mongolian building, with an elaborate metallic tree in front of it, about 30 feet tall|The Silver Tree Fountain of Karakorum (modern recreation).]]
Möngke was a serious man who followed the laws of his ancestors and avoided alcoholism. He was tolerant of outside religions and artistic styles, which led to the building of foreign merchants' quarters, [[Buddhist monasteries]], [[mosques]], and [[Christian churches]] in the Mongol capital. As construction projects continued, Karakorum was adorned with Chinese, European and [[Persian architecture]]. One famous example was a large silver tree with cleverly designed pipes which dispensed various drinks. The tree, topped by a triumphant angel, was crafted by [[Guillaume Boucher]], a Parisian goldsmith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=European captives and craftsmen among the Mongols, 1231-1255|author=Guzman, Gregory G.|journal=[[The Historian (journal)|The Historian]]|volume=72|issue=1|pages=122–150|date=Spring 2010|doi=10.1111/j.1540-6563.2009.00259.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Hulagu 1.jpg|left|thumb|250px||alt=Stylized line drawing of Hulagu, seated and drinking from a bowl|[[Hulagu]], Genghis Khan's grandson and founder of the [[Il-Khanate]]. From a medieval Persian manuscript.]]
Although he had a strong Chinese contingent, Möngke relied heavily on Muslim and Mongol administrators, and launched a series of economic reforms to make government expenses more predictable. His court limited government spending and prohibited nobles and troops from abusing civilians or issuing edicts without authorization. He commuted the contribution system into a fixed poll tax which was collected by imperial agents and forwarded to units in need. His court also tried to lighten the tax burden on commoners by reducing tax rates. Along with the reform of the [[tax system]], he reinforced the guards at the postal relays and centralized control of monetary affairs. Möngke also ordered an empire-wide census in 1252 which took several years to complete, not being finished until [[Novgorod]] in the far northwest was counted in 1258.&lt;ref&gt;Allsen. ''Mongol Imperialism''. p. 280.&lt;/ref&gt;

In another move to consolidate his power, Möngke assigned his brothers [[Hulagu]] and [[Kublai]] to rule Persia and Mongol-held China. In the southern part of the empire, he continued his predecessors' struggle against the [[Song Dynasty]]. In order to outflank the Song from three directions, Möngke dispatched Mongol armies under his brother Kublai to [[Yunnan]], and under his uncle Iyeku to subdue Korea and pressure the Song from that direction as well. Kublai conquered the [[Dali Kingdom]] in 1253, and Möngke's general Qoridai stabilized his control over Tibet, inducing leading monasteries to submit to Mongol rule. Subutai's son, Uryankhadai, reduced neighboring peoples of Yunnan to submission and beat the [[Trần Dynasty]] in northern [[Vietnam]] into temporary submission in 1258.&lt;ref name=atwood-255/&gt;

After stabilizing the empire's finances, Möngke once again sought to expand its borders. At ''kurultais'' in Karakorum in 1253 and 1258 he approved new invasions of the Middle East and [[South Central China|south China]]. Möngke put Hulagu in overall charge of military and civil affairs in Persia, and appointed Chagataids and Jochids to join Hulagu's army. The Muslims from [[Qazvin]] denounced the menace of the [[Nizari]] [[Ismailis]], a heretical sect of [[Shiites]]. The Mongol Naiman commander [[Kitbuqa]] began to assault several Ismaili fortresses in 1253, before Hulagu deliberately advanced in 1256. Ismaili Grand Master [[Rukn ud-Din]] surrendered in 1257 and was executed. All of the Ismaili strongholds in Persia were destroyed by Hulagu's army in 1257 though Girdukh held out until 1271.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bagdad1258.jpg|250px|thumb|250px|alt=Colorful medieval depiction of a siege, showing the city of Baghdad surrounded by walls, and the Mongol army outside|[[Siege of Baghdad (1258)|Fall of Baghdad in 1258]], an event often considered as the single most catastrophic event in the history of Islam.]]
The center of the Islamic Empire at the time was Baghdad, which had held power for 500 years but was suffering internal divisions. When its caliph [[al-Mustasim]] refused to submit to the Mongols, [[Battle of Baghdad (1258)|Baghdad was besieged and captured]] by the Mongols in 1258, an event considered as one of the most catastrophic events in the history of Islam, and sometimes  compared to the rupture of the [[Kaaba]]. With the destruction of the Abbasid Caliphate, Hulagu had an open route to Syria and moved against the other Muslim powers in the region. His army advanced towards [[Ayyubid]]-ruled Syria, capturing small local states en route. The sultan [[Al-Nasir Yusuf]] of the Ayyubids refused to show himself before Hulagu; however, he had accepted Mongol supremacy two decades earlier. When Hulagu headed further west, the [[Lesser Armenia|Armenians]] from [[Cilicia]], the [[Seljuks]] from [[Rum]] and the Christian realms of [[Antioch]] and [[Tripoli]] submitted to Mongol authority, joining the Mongols in their assault against the Muslims. While some cities surrendered without resisting, others such as Mayafarriqin fought back; their populations were massacred and the cities were sacked.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. pp. 132–135.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, in the northwestern portion of the empire, Batu's successor and younger brother [[Berke]] sent punitive expeditions to Ukraine, Belarus, [[Lithuania]] and Poland. Dissension began brewing between the northwestern and southwestern sections of the Mongol Empire, as Batu suspected that Hulagu's invasion of Western Asia would result in the elimination of Batu's own predominance there.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. pp. 127–128.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Disintegration===
[[File:MongolEmpire.jpg|thumb|alt=Map of Asia|The Mongol Empire after the death of [[Möngke Khan]] (r. 1251–59).]]

====Dispute over succession====
In the southern part of the empire, Möngke Khan himself led his army to complete the conquest of China. Military operations were generally successful, but prolonged, so the forces did not withdraw to the north as was customary when the weather turned hot. Disease ravaged the Mongol forces with bloody epidemics, and Möngke died there on August 11, 1259. This event began a new chapter of history for the Mongols, as again a decision needed to be made on a new Great Khan. Mongol armies across the empire withdrew from their campaigns to once again convene for a new ''kurultai''.&lt;ref&gt;Lane. p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

Möngke's brother Hulagu broke off his successful military advance into Syria, withdrawing the bulk of his forces to [[Mughan]] and leaving only a small contingent under his general [[Kitbuqa]]. The opposing forces in the region, the Christian Crusaders and Muslim Mamluks, both recognizing that the Mongols were the greater threat, took advantage of the weakened state of the Mongol army and engaged in an unusual passive truce with each other. In 1260, the Mamluks advanced from Egypt, being allowed to camp and resupply near the Christian stronghold of [[Acre, Israel|Acre]], and engaged Kitbuqa's forces just north of Galilee, at the [[Battle of Ain Jalut]]. The Mongols were defeated, and Kitbuqa executed. This pivotal battle marked the western limit for Mongol expansion, as the Mongols were never again able to make any serious military advances farther than Syria.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a separate part of the empire, another brother of Hulagu and Möngke, Kublai, heard of the Great Khan's death at the [[Huai River|Huai]] in China.  Rather than returning to the capital though, he continued his advance into the [[Wuchang District|Wuchang]] area of China, near the [[Yangtze River]]. Their younger brother [[Ariq Böke|Ariqboke]] took advantage of the absence of Hulagu and Kublai, and used his position at the capital to win the title of Great Khan for himself, with representatives of all the family branches proclaimed him as the leader at the ''kurultai'' in Karakorum.  When Kublai learned of this, he summoned his own ''kurultai'' at [[Kaiping]], where virtually all the senior princes and great noyans resident in North China and Manchuria supported his own candidacy over that of Ariqboke.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morgan. p. 104&quot;/&gt;

====Civil war====
{{see also|Berke–Hulagu war}}
[[File:YuanEmperorAlbumKhubilaiPortrait.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Yellowed painting of the head and shoulders of a plump middle-aged Asian man.  He is wearing a white robe and a white cap with black trim.  He has a long black moustache and a forked beard.|[[Kublai Khan]], Genghis Khan's grandson and founder of the [[Yuan Dynasty]]. Painting from 1294.]]Battles ensued between the armies of Kublai and those of his brother Ariqboke, which included forces still loyal to Möngke's previous administration.  Kublai's army easily eliminated Ariqboke's supporters, and seized control of the civil administration in southern Mongolia. Further challenges took place from their cousins, the Chagataids. Kublai sent Abishka, a Chagataid prince loyal to him, to take charge of Chagatai's realm.  But Ariqboke captured and then executed Abishka, having his own man [[Alghu]] crowned there instead. Kublai's new administration blockaded Ariqboke in Mongolia to cut off food supplies, causing a famine. Karakorum fell quickly to Kublai, but Ariqboke rallied and re-took the capital in 1261.&lt;ref&gt;Wassaf. p. 12.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jackson. ''Mongols and the West''. p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barthold. ''Turkestan''. p. 488.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the southwestern Ilkhanate, Hulagu was loyal to his brother Kublai, but clashes with their cousin Berke, the ruler of the Golden Horde in the northwestern part of the empire, began in 1262. The suspicious deaths of Jochid princes in Hulagu's service, unequal distribution of war booties and Hulagu's massacres of the Muslims increased the anger of Berke, who considered supporting a rebellion of the Georgian Kingdom against Hulagu's rule in 1259–1260.&lt;ref&gt;L. N.Gumilev, A. Kruchki. ''Black legend''&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}} Berke also forged an alliance with the Egyptian Mamluks against Hulagu, and supported Kublai's rival claimant, Ariqboke.&lt;ref name=barthold&gt;Barthold. ''Turkestan down to the Mongol invasion''. p. 446.&lt;/ref&gt; Hulagu died on February 8, 1264. Berke sought to take advantage of this and invade Hulagu's realm, but died himself along the way, and a few months later, Alghu Khan of the Chagatai Khanate died as well. Kublai named Hulagu's son [[Abaqa Khan|Abaqa]] as a new Ilkhan, and Abaqa sought foreign alliances, such as attempting to form a [[Franco-Mongol alliance]] with the Europeans against the Egyptian Mamluks.  To lead the Golden Horde, Kublai nominated Batu's grandson [[Möngke Temür]].&lt;ref&gt;Prawdin. ''Mongol Empire and its legacy''. p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt; Ariqboqe surrendered to Kublai at [[Shangdu]] on August 21, 1264.&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:VoyagesOfRabbanBarSauma.jpg|thumb|270px|left|alt=Map of Asia, Europe, and the northern part of Africa, with a red dotted line showing a journey starting from the far eastern side of Asia, heading all the way westward across the continent, through the Middle East, into the Mediterranean, and visiting the capitals of Europe.|[[Rabban Bar Sauma]], the ambassador of [[Great Khan]] [[Kublai]] and Ilkhan [[Arghun]], travelled from Dadu in the East, to Rome, Paris and [[Bordeaux]] in the West, meeting with the major rulers of the period in 1287–1288.]]
In the south, after [[Battle of Xiangyang|the fall of Xiangyang]] in 1273, the Mongols sought the final conquest of the Song Dynasty in South China. In 1271, Kublai renamed the new Mongol regime in China as the [[Yuan Dynasty]], and sought to [[sinicize]] his image as [[Emperor of China]] in order to win the control of the millions of Chinese. Kublai moved his headquarters to [[Khanbaliq|Dadu]], the genesis for what later became the modern city of [[Beijing]], although his establishment of a capital there was a controversial move to many Mongols who accused him of being too closely tied to [[Chinese culture]].&lt;ref&gt;Man. ''Kublai Khan''. p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sh.Tseyen-Oidov – Ibid. p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; But the Mongols were eventually successful in their campaigns against China, and the Chinese [[Southern Song|Song imperial family]] surrendered to the Yuan in 1276, making the Mongols the first non-Chinese people to conquer all of China. Kublai used his base to build a powerful empire, creating an academy, offices, trade ports and canals, and sponsoring arts and science. Mongol records list 20,166 public schools created during his reign.&lt;ref name=man/&gt;

Having achieved actual or nominal dominion over much of Eurasia, and having seen his successful conquest of China, Kublai was in a position to look beyond China. However, his costly invasions of [[Burma]], [[Vietnam|Annam]], [[Sakhalin]] and [[Champa]] secured only the vassal status of those countries. [[Mongol invasion of Japan|Mongol invasions of Japan]] (1274 and 1280) and [[Mongol invasion of Java|Java]] (1293) failed.&lt;ref name=man&gt;Man. ''Kublai Khan''. p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nogai and [[Köchü|Konchi]], the khan of the [[White Horde]], established friendly relations with the Yuan Dynasty and the Ilkhanate. Political disagreement between contending branches of the family over the office of Great Khan continued, but the economic and commercial success of the Mongol Empire continued despite the squabbling.&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vernadsky. ''The Mongols and Russia''. pp. 344–366.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Henryk Samsonowicz, Maria Bogucka. ''A Republic of Nobles''. p. 179.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political struggles===
[[File:Emperor Chengzong of Yuan China.png|thumb|right|alt=Painting of Emperor Temür|[[Temür Khan]]，Kublai Khan's grandson and Khagan (Emperor) of the Yuan Dynasty. 14th century image.]]
Major changes occurred in the Mongol Empire in the late 1200s. Kublai Khan, after having conquered all of China and established the Yuan Dynasty, died in 1294, and was succeeded by his grandson [[Temür Khan]], who continued Kublai's policies. The [[Ilkhanate]] remained loyal to the Yuan court but endured its own power struggle, in part because of a dispute with the growing Islamic factions within the southwestern part of the empire. When [[Ghazan]] took the throne of the Ilkhanate in 1295, he formally accepted Islam as his own religion, marking a turning point in Mongol history after which Mongol Persia became more and more Islamic. Despite this though, Ghazan continued to strengthen ties with Temür Khan and the Yuan Dynasty in the east. It was politically useful to advertise the Great Khan's authority in the Ilkhanate, because the [[Golden Horde]] in Russia had long made claims on nearby Georgia.&lt;ref&gt;Prawdin. {{Page needed|date=February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within four years, Ghazan began sending tributes to the Yuan court, appealed to other khans to accept Temür Khan as their overlord, and oversaw an extensive program of cultural and scientific interaction between the Ilkhanate and the Yuan Dynasty in the following decades.&lt;ref&gt;Allsen. ''Culture and Conquest''. pp. 32–35.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ghazan's faith may have been Islamic, but he continued his ancestors’ war with the Egyptian Mamluks, and consulted with his old Mongolian advisers in his native tongue. He defeated the Mamluk army at the [[Battle of Wadi al-Khazandar]] in 1299, but was only briefly able to occupy Syria, due to distracting raids from the [[Chagatai Khanate]], under its ''de facto'' ruler [[Kaidu]], who was at war with both the Ilkhans and the Yuan Dynasty.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} Struggling for influence within the Golden Horde, Kaidu sponsored his own candidate Kobeleg against [[Bayan (khan)|Bayan]] (r. 1299–1304), the khan of the White Horde. Bayan, after receiving military support from the Mongols in Russia, requested assistance from both the Great Khan Temür and the Ilkhanate to organize a unified attack against Kaidu's forces. Temür was amenable, and enlarged counterattacks against Kaidu a year later. After a bloody battle with Temür's armies near [[Zawkhan River]] in 1301, the old valiant Kaidu died, and was succeeded by [[Duwa]].&lt;ref&gt;René Grousset. ''The Empire of the Steppes''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Atwood. p. 445.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Temür Chabar Toqta Öldjeïtu.jpeg|thumb|left|The four khans Temür (Yuan), Chapar ([[House of Ögedei]]), [[Toqta]] (Golden Horde), and Öljaitü (Ilkhanate).&lt;ref&gt;Bibliothèque nationale de France. Département des Manuscrits. Division occidentale. Nouvelle acquisition française 886, fol. 37v&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In spite of his conflicts with Kaidu and Duwa, Yuan emperor Temür established a tributary relationship with the war-like [[Shan people|Shan]] brothers after his series of military operations against [[Thailand]] from 1297 to 1303. This was to mark the end of the southern expansion of the Mongols. Some Mongols sought to decrease internal strife, and unify under Temür. Duwa initiated a peace proposal and persuaded the Ögedeids that &quot;Let we Mongols stop shedding blood of each other. It is better to surrender to Khagan Temür&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;d.Ohson. ''History of the Mongols. p.II''. p. 355.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sh.Tseyen-Oidov. ''Genghis bogdoos Ligden khutagt khurtel (khaad)''. p. 81.{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1304, all khanates approved a peace treaty, and accepted Temür's supremacy.&lt;ref&gt;Vernadsky – ''The Mongols and Russia''. p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Oljeitu's letter to Philipp the Fair&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J. J. Saunders ''The History of the Mongol conquests''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Howorth. p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt;

Duwa was challenged by Kaidu's son Chapar, but with the assistance of Temür, Duwa defeated the Ögedeids. [[Tokhta]] of the Golden Horde, also seeking a general peace, sent 20,000 men to buttress the Yuan frontier.&lt;ref&gt;Atwood. p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt; After Tokhta's death in 1312 though, he was succeeded by [[Ozbeg]] (r. 1313–41), who seized the throne of the Golden Horde and persecuted non-Muslim Mongols. The Yuan's influence on the Horde was largely reversed and border clashes between Mongol states resumed. [[Ayurbarwada Buyantu Khan, Emperor Renzong of Yuan|Ayurbawda Khan]]'s envoys backed Tokhta's son against Ozbeg.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

In the Chagatai Khanate, [[Esen Buqa I]] (r. 1309-1318) was enthroned as khan after suppressing a sudden rebellion by Ögedei's descendants and driving Chapar into exile. The Yuan and Ilkhanid armies eventually attacked the Chagatai Khanate. [[File:Mikhailtver.jpg|thumb|right|230px|alt=Painting of a medieval court scene|Ozbeg Khan (1313-1341) judging the case of [[Mikhail of Tver]]. By [[Vasily Vereshchagin]].]] Realizing economic benefits and the Genghisid legacy, Ozbeg reopened friendly relations with the Yuan in 1326, and strengthened ties with the Muslim world as well, building mosques and other elaborate places such as baths.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

By the second decade of the 14th century, Mongol invasions had further decreased. In 1323, [[Abu Sa'id (Ilkhanid dynasty)|Abu Said Khan]] (r. 1316-35) of the Ilkhanate signed a peace treaty with Egypt. At his request, the Yuan court awarded his custodian [[Chupan]] the title of commander-in-chief of all Mongol khanates. But Chupan's reputation could not save his life in 1327.&lt;ref&gt;Allsen. ''Culture and Conquest''. p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; A new civil war erupted in the Yuan Dynasty in 1327-1328, with Chagatai khan [[Eljigidey]] (r. 1326–29) supporting [[Kusala]], the Yuan [[Khagan Khayisan]]'s son, as Great Khan.  Kusala was elected on August 30, 1329. Fearing Chagataid influence on the Yuan, [[Tugh Temür]]'s (1304–1332) [[Kypchak]] commander poisoned him, and took power for himself. In order to be accepted by other khanates as the sovereign of Mongol world, Tugh Temür, who had a good knowledge of Chinese language and history and was also a creditable poet, calligrapher, and painter, sent Genghisid princes and descendants of other notable Mongol generals to the Chagatai Khanate, Ilkhan Abu Said and Ozbeg. In response to the  emissaries, they all agreed to send tribute each year.&lt;ref&gt;Franke. pp. 541-550.&lt;/ref&gt; Tugh Temür also gave lavish presents and an imperial seal to Eljigidey to mollify his anger. The Kypchak and the Alans became even more powerful at the court of the Yuan than had been seen since Temür's reign. [[Pope John XXII]] was presented a memorandum from the eastern church describing their [[Pax Mongolica]]: &quot;...Khagan is one of the greatest monarchs and all lords of the state, e.g. the king of Almaligh (Chagatai Khanate), emperor Abu Said and Uzbek Khan, are his subjects, saluting his holiness to pay their respects. These 3 monarchs send their overlord leopards, camels, falcons as well as precious jewelries every year. ... They acknowledge him as their absolute  supreme lord.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Vernadsky. p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;

With the relative stability (''[[Pax Mongolica]]'') brought to the region by the Mongol conquests, international trade and cultural exchanges flourished between Asia and Europe. The communications between the Yuan Dynasty in China and Ilkhanate in Persia further encouraged the trade and commerce between the east and the west. Patterns of Yuan royal textiles could be found on the opposite side of the empire adorning Armenian decorations; trees and vegetables were transplanted across the empire; and technological innovations spread from Mongol dominions towards the West.&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===Fall===
[[File:Mongolia 1500 AD.jpg|thumb|right|300px|alt=Map of Asia|The Tumens of Mongolia Proper and relict states of the Mongol Empire by 1500.]]
With the death of Ilkhan [[Abu Sa'id (Ilkhanid dynasty)|Abu Said Bahatur]] in 1335, the Mongol rule in Persia fell into political anarchy. A year later his successor was killed by an Oirat governor and the Ilkhanate was divided between the Suldus, the [[Jalayir]], [[Jöchi Khasar|Qasarid]] [[Togha Temür]] (d. 1353) and Persian warlords. Taking advantage of the chaos, the Georgians pushed the Mongols out of their own territory, and the Uyghur commander [[Ghiyath al-Din Eretna|Eretna]] established an independent state ([[Ertenids]]) in [[Anatolia]] in 1336. Following the downfall of their Mongol masters, the all-time loyal vassal, the Armenian Kingdom of Cilicia, received escalating threats from the Mamluks, and were eventually overrun.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Along with the dissolution of the Mongol Ilkhanate in Persia, Mongol rulers in China and the [[Chagatai Khanate]] were also in turmoil. Plagues such as the [[Black Death]], which certainly started in the Mongol dominions and then spread to Europe, added to the confusion. Disease devastated all the khanates, cutting off commercial ties and killing off millions.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. pp. 117–118.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the 14th century, it may have taken 70–100 million lives in Africa, Asia and Europe.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

[[File:YuanEmperorAlbumToghunTemürPortrait.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Painting of Emperor Toghan Temür Khan|[[Toghan Temür]] Khan，Khagan (Emperor) of the Yuan Dynasty.]]
As the power of the Mongols declined, chaos erupted everywhere as non-Mongol leaders struggled for their own influence. The [[Golden Horde]] lost all of its western dominions (including modern [[Belarus]] and [[Ukraine]]) to Poland and [[Lithuania]] from 1342 to 1369. Muslim and non-Muslim princes in the Chagatai Khanate warred with each other from 1331–1343, and the Chagatai Khanate disintegrated when non-Genghisid warlords set up their own puppet khans in [[Transoxiana]] and [[Moghulistan]]. [[Janibeg]] Khan (r. 1342–1357) briefly reasserted Jochid dominance over the Chaghataids to restore their former glory. Demanding submission from an offshoot of the Ilkhanate in [[Azerbaijan]], he boasted that &quot;today three uluses are under my control&quot;. However, rival families of the Jochids began fighting for the throne of the Golden Horde after the assassination of his successor [[Berdibek]] Khan in 1359. The last Yuan ruler [[Toghan Temür]] (r. 1333–70) was powerless to regulate those troubles because the empire had nearly reached its end. His court's unbacked currency had entered a [[hyperinflation]]ary spiral and [[Red Turban Rebellion|the Han-Chinese people revolted]] due to the Yuan's harsh restrictions. In the 1350s [[Gongmin of Goryeo]] successfully pushed Mongolian garrisons back and exterminated the family of Toghan Temür Khan's empress while [[Tai Situ Changchub Gyaltsen]] managed to eliminate the Mongol influence in Tibet.&lt;ref&gt;Prawdin. p. 379.&lt;/ref&gt;

Increasingly isolated from their subjects, the Mongols quickly lost most of China to the rebellious [[Ming Dynasty|Ming forces]] in 1368 and fled to their homeland Mongolia. After the overthrow of the [[Yuan Dynasty]], the Golden Horde lost touch with Mongolia and China, while the two main parts of the Chagatai Khanate were defeated by [[Timur]] (Tamerlane) (1336–1405). The Golden Horde broke into smaller Turkic-hordes that declined steadily in power through four long centuries. Among them, the khanate's shadow [[Great Horde]] survived until 1502, when one of its successors, the [[Crimean Khanate]], sacked Sarai. The Yuan remnants, known as [[Northern Yuan Dynasty|Northern Yuan]], continued to rule Mongolia until 1635 when the semi-nomadic [[Manchus]] from [[Manchuria]] defeated them. The [[Khalkha]] under the [[Genghisids]] and their former subjects, the [[Dzungars|Oirat Mongols]], lost their independence to the [[Qing Dynasty]] in 1691 and 1755 respectively, and the remnants of the Crimean Khanate were annexed by the [[Russian Empire]] in 1783.&lt;ref&gt;Halperin. p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military setup==
{{Main|Mongol military tactics and organization}}
{{Campaignbox Mongol invasions}}
The number of troops mustered by the Mongols is the subject of some scholarly debate,&lt;ref&gt;Sverdrup. p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt; but was at least 105,000 in 1206.&lt;ref&gt;Sverdrup. p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mongol military organization was simple but effective, based on the [[decimal]] system. The army was built up from squads of ten men each, called an ''arbat''; ten ''arbat''s constituted a company of one hundred, called a ''zuut''; ten ''zuut''s made a regiment of one thousand called ''myanghan'' and ten ''myanghan''s would then constitute a division of ten thousand (''tumen''). The Mongols were most famous for their horse archers, but troops armed with lances were equally skilled, and the Mongols recruited other military talents from the cities they conquered. With experienced Chinese engineers and bombardier corps who were experts in building [[trebuchet]]s, [[Battle of Xiangyang|Xuanfeng]] catapults and other machines, the Mongols could lay siege to fortified positions, sometimes building machinery on the spot using available local resources.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. pp. 80–81.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:MongolArcher.jpg|thumb|220px|left|alt=Painting of Mongol archers on horseback|With the help of their [[mounted archer]]s, the [[Mongols]] conquered most of [[Eurasia]].]]
Forces under the command of the Mongol Empire were trained, organized, and equipped for mobility and speed. Mongol soldiers were more lightly armored than many of the armies they faced, but able to make up for it with maneuverability. Each Mongol warrior would usually travel with multiple horses, allowing him to quickly switch to a fresh mount as needed. In addition, soldiers of the Mongol army functioned independently of supply lines, considerably speeding up army movement. Skillful use of couriers enabled these armies to maintain contact with each other and their leadership. Discipline was inculcated during a ''nerge'' (traditional hunt), as reported by [[Ata al-Mulk Juvayni|Juvayni]]. These hunts were distinctive from hunts in other cultures where they were the equivalent to small unit actions. Mongol forces would spread out in a line, surround an entire region, and then drive all of the [[game]] within that area together. The goal was to let none of the animals escape and slaughter them all.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. pp. 74–75&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Mōko Shūrai Ekotoba 2.jpg|thumb|right|250px|alt=Painting of a medieval battle scene between warriors on horseback|Samurai warriors face Mongols, during the [[Mongol invasions of Japan]]. From [[Takezaki Suenaga]]'s [[Moko Shurai Ekotoba]].]]

Another advantage of the Mongols was their ability to traverse large distances even in unusual cold winters; for instance, frozen rivers led them like highways to large urban centers on their banks. In addition to siege engineering, the Mongols were also adept at river-work, crossing the river [[Sajó]] in spring flood conditions with thirty thousand cavalry soldiers in a single night during the [[battle of Mohi]] (April, 1241) to defeat the Hungarian king [[Béla IV]]. Similarly, in the attack against the Muslim [[Muhammad II of Khwarezm|Khwarezmshah]], a flotilla of barges was used to prevent escape on the river.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Traditionally known for their prowess with ground forces, the Mongols rarely used [[navy|naval]] power, with a few exceptions. In the 1260s and 1270s they used seapower while conquering the [[Song Dynasty]] of China, though they were unable to mount successful seaborne campaigns against Japan. Around the Eastern Mediterranean, their campaigns were almost exclusively land-based, with the seas being controlled by the Crusader and Mamluk forces.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''Mongols and the Eastern Mediterranean''&lt;/ref&gt;

All military campaigns were preceded by careful planning, reconnaissance and gathering of sensitive information relating to enemy territories and forces. The success, organization and mobility of the Mongol armies permitted them to fight on several fronts at once. All adult males up to the age of 60 were eligible for conscription into the army, a source of honor in their tribal warrior tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Morgan. ''The Mongols''. p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Society==
{{Main|Society of the Mongol Empire}}

===Law and governance===
[[File:DiezAlbumsArmedRiders I.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Mongol]] [[Mongol_Army#Cavalry|cavalry]] pursuing their enemy.]] 
{{See also|Organization of the Mongol Empire under Genghis Khan}}
The Mongol Empire was governed by a code of law devised by Genghis, called ''[[Yassa]]'', meaning &quot;order&quot; or &quot;decree&quot;. A particular canon of this code was that those of rank shared much of the same hardship as the common man. It also imposed severe penalties – e.g., the death penalty was decreed if one mounted soldier following another did not pick up something dropped from the mount in front. Penalties were also decreed for rape and to some extent for murder. On the whole, the tight discipline made the Mongol Empire extremely safe and well-run; European travelers were amazed by the organization and strict discipline of the people within the Mongol Empire.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Under ''Yassa'', chiefs and generals were selected based on [[meritocracy|merit]]. [[freedom of religion|Religious tolerance]] was guaranteed, and thievery and vandalizing of civilian property was strictly forbidden.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

The empire was governed by a non-democratic [[parliament]]ary-style central assembly, called ''[[Kurultai]]'', in which the Mongol chiefs met with the Great Khan to discuss domestic and foreign policies. ''Kurultais'' were also convened for the selection of each new Great Khan.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Genghis was very tolerant of other religions, and never persecuted people on religious grounds. This was associated with their culture and progressive thought (Roger Bacon). Some historian of the 20th century thought that it was a good military strategy, the occasion in which he was at war with Sultan Muhammad of Khwarezm, other Islamic leaders did not join the fight against Genghis — it was instead seen as a non-holy war between two individuals.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Throughout the empire, trade routes and an extensive postal system (''yam'') were created. Many merchants, messengers and travelers from China, the Middle East and Europe used the system. Genghis Khan also created a national seal, encouraged the use of a written alphabet in Mongolia, and exempted teachers, lawyers, and artists from taxes, although taxes were heavy on all other subjects of the empire.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

At the same time, any resistance to Mongol rule was met with massive collective punishment. Cities were destroyed and their inhabitants slaughtered if they defied Mongol orders.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

===Religions===
[[File:GhazanConversionToIslam.JPG|thumb|200px|alt=Painting of a stylized building, showing Ghazan kneeling and accepting conversion|[[Persian miniature]] showing [[Ghazan]]'s conversion from Buddhism to [[Islam]].]]
{{main|Religion in the Mongol Empire}}
Mongols were highly tolerant of most religions, to the extent of sponsoring several at the same time. At the time of Genghis Khan, virtually every religion had found converts, from [[Buddhism]] to [[Christianity]] and [[Manichaeism]] to [[Islam]]. To avoid strife, Genghis Khan set up an institution that ensured complete religious freedom, though he himself was a [[shamanism|shamanist]]. Under his administration, all religious leaders were exempt from taxation, and from public service.&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Initially there were few formal places of worship, because of the nomadic lifestyle. However, under [[Ögedei Khan|Ögedei]] (1186&amp;ndash;1241), several building projects were undertaken in the Mongol capital of [[Karakorum]]. Along with palaces, Ögedei built houses of worship for the Buddhist, Muslim, Christian, and [[Taoism|Taoist]] followers. The dominant religions at that time were [[Shamanism]], [[Tengrism]] and [[Buddhism]], although Ögedei's wife was a Nestorian Christian.&lt;ref&gt;Weatherford. p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, three of the four principal khanates embraced [[Islam]].&lt;ref&gt;Ezzati. ''The spread of Islam: the contributing factors. p. 274.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bukharaev. ''Islam in Russia: the four seasons''. p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Arts and literature===
The oldest surviving literary work in the [[Mongolian language]] is ''[[The Secret History of the Mongols]]'', which was written for the royal family sometime after Genghis Khan's death in 1227. It is the most significant native account of Genghis's life and genealogy, covering his origins and childhood, through to the establishment of the Mongol Empire and the reign of his son, Ögedei. Another classic from the empire is the ''[[Jami' al-tawarikh]]'', or &quot;Universal History&quot;. It was commissioned in the early 14th century by the Ilkhan [[Abaqa Khan]], as a way of documenting the entire world's history, to help establish the Mongols' own cultural legacy. With hundreds of illustrated pages, it was effectively one of the first written histories of the world.

The Mongols also appreciated the visual arts, though their taste in portraiture was strictly focused on portraits of their horses, rather than of people.

===Mail system===
{{main|Ortoo}}
[[File:OljeituToPhilippeLeBel1305.jpg|250px|thumb|alt=A partially unrolled scroll, opened from left to right to show a portion of the scroll with widely spaced vertical lines in the Mongol language. Imprinted over two of the lines is an official-looking square red stamp with an intricate design.|1305 letter (a roll measuring {{convert|302|by|50|cm|ft}}) from the Ilkhan Mongol [[Öljaitü]] to King [[Philip IV of France]].]]
The Mongol Empire had an ingenious and efficient mail system for the time, often referred to by scholars as the [[Yam (route)|Yam]], which had lavishly furnished and well guarded relay posts known as ''örtöö'' setup all over the Mongol Empire. The ''yam'' system would be replicated later in the United States, in the form of the [[Pony Express]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Chambers&quot;&gt;Chambers, James. ''The Devil's Horsemen'' Atheneum, 1979, ISBN 0-689-10942-3&lt;/ref&gt; A messenger would typically travel {{convert|25|mi|km}} from one station to the next, either receiving a fresh, rested horse, or relaying the mail to the next rider to ensure the speediest possible delivery. The Mongol riders regularly covered {{convert|125|mi|km|-1}} per day, better than the fastest record set by the Pony Express some 600 years later.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Genghis and his successor [[Ögedei]] built a wide system of roadways, one of which carved the [[Altai Range]]. After his enthronement, Ögedei further organized the road system, ordering the Chagatai Khanate and Golden Horde to link up roads in western parts of the Mongol Empire.&lt;ref&gt;''Secret history of the Mongols''&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} In order to reduce pressure on households, he set up relay stations with attached households every {{convert|25|mi|km}}. Anyone with [[paiza]] was allowed to stop there for re-mounts and specified rations, while those carrying military identities used the Yam even without a [[paiza]]. When the Great Khan died in [[Karakorum]], news reached the Mongol forces under [[Batu Khan]] in Central Europe within 4–6 weeks thanks to the Yam.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weatherford. p. 158&quot;/&gt;

[[Kublai Khan]], the founder of the [[Yuan Dynasty]], built special relays for high officials, as well as ordinary relays which had hostels. During Kublai's reign, the Yuan communication system consisted of some 1,400 postal stations, which used 50,000 horses, 8,400 oxen, 6,700 mules, 4,000 carts, and 6,000 boats.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} In [[Manchuria]] and southern [[Siberia]], the Mongols still used [[dogsled]] relays for the yam. In the Ilkhanate, Ghazan restored the declining relay system in the Middle East on a restricted scale. He constructed some hostels and decreed that only imperial envoys could receive a stipend. The Jochids of the [[Golden Horde]] financed their relay system by a special yam tax.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

==Silk Road==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Silk Road]] --&gt;
{{Main|Silk Road}}
{{see also|Pax Mongolica}}
[[File:Lugou-Bridge-east-end-relief-3577.jpg|thumb|alt=Photograph of a park in Beijing, showing a stone relief carving of a Mongol caravan|A small caravan arriving to Beijing from the west - a modern relief near [[Marco Polo Bridge]].]]
The Mongols had a strong history of supporting merchants and trade. Genghis Khan had encouraged foreign merchants early in his career, even before uniting the Mongols. Merchants provided him with information about neighboring cultures, served as diplomats and official traders for the Mongols, and were essential for many needed goods, since the Mongols produced little of their own. Mongols sometimes provided capital for merchants and sent them far afield, in an ''ortoq'' (merchant partner) arrangement. As the empire grew, any merchants or ambassadors with proper documentation and authorization received protection and sanctuary as they traveled through Mongol realms. Well-traveled and relatively well-maintained roads linked lands from the Mediterranean basin to China, greatly increasing overland trade and resulting in some dramatic stories of those who travelled through what would come be known as the famed Silk Road. [[Marco Polo]] is a famous western explorer who traveled east along the Silk Road, and the Chinese Mongol monk [[Rabban Bar Sauma]] made a comparably epic journey along the Road who ventured from his home of [[Khanbaliq]] (Beijing) to as far as Europe. And European missionaries, like [[William of Rubruck]], also traveled to the Mongol court to convert believers to their cause, or went as papal envoys (sent on behalf of the pope) to correspond with Mongol rulers in an attempt to secure a [[Franco-Mongol alliance]]. It was rare, however, for anyone to journey the full length of Silk Road. Instead, merchants moved products like a bucket brigade, goods being traded from one middleman to another, moving from China all the way to the West; the goods moved over such long distances reached extravagant prices.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

After Genghis, the merchant partner business continued to flourish under his successors Ögedei and Güyük. Merchants brought clothing, food, information, and other provisions to the imperial palaces, and in return the Great Khans gave the merchants tax exemptions, and allowed them to use the official relay stations of the Mongol Empire. Merchants also served as tax farmers in China, Russia and Iran. If the merchants were attacked by bandits, losses were made up from the imperial treasury.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Policies changed under the Great Khan [[Möngke Khan|Möngke]]. Because of money laundering and overtaxing, he attempted to limit abuses and sent imperial investigators to supervise the ''ortoq'' businesses. He decreed all merchants must pay commercial and property taxes, and he paid off all drafts drawn by high ranking Mongol elites from the merchants. This policy continued in the [[Yuan Dynasty]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

The fall of the Mongol Empire in the 14th century led to the collapse of the political, cultural, and economic unity along the Silk Road. Turkic tribes seized the western end of the Silk Road trade routes from the decaying Byzantine Empire, and sowed the seeds of a Turkic culture that would later crystallize into the [[Ottoman Empire]] under the [[Sunni]] faith. In the East, the native Chinese overthrew the Yuan Dynasty in 1368, launching their own [[Ming Dynasty]] and pursuing a policy of economic isolationism.&lt;ref name=&quot;footsteps&quot;&gt;Guoli Liu ''Chinese foreign policy in transition''. p. 364&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
{{see also|History of Mongolia}}

The Mongol Empire had a lasting impact, unifying large regions, some of which (such as eastern and western Russia and the western parts of China) remain unified today, albeit under different rulership. The Mongols, except the main population, might have been assimilated into local populations after the fall of the empire, and some of these descendants adopted local [[religion]]s — for example, the eastern khanates largely adopted [[Buddhism]], and the western khanates adopted [[Islam]], largely under [[Sufi]] influence.&lt;ref&gt;Foltz. pp. 105–106.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to some{{specify|date=February 2012}} interpretations, Genghis Khan's conquests caused wholesale destruction on an unprecedented scale in certain geographical regions, and therefore led to some changes in the demographics of Asia, such as the mass migration of the Iranian tribes of Central Asia into modern-day Iran. The [[Islamic world]] was also subject to massive changes as a result of Mongol invasions. The population of the Iranian plateau suffered from widespread disease and famine, resulting in the deaths of up to three-quarters of its population, possibly 10 to 15 million people. Historian Steven Ward estimates that Iran's population did not again reach its pre-Mongol levels until the mid-20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = R. Ward
  | first = Steven
  | title = Immortal: a military history of Iran and its armed forces
  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=8eUTLaaVOOQC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false
  | publisher = Georgetown University Press
  | year = 2009
  | page = 39
  | isbn = 1-58901-258-5}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Mongols-map.png|thumb|300px|right|alt=Map of Asia|This map shows the boundary of 13th century Mongol Empire compared to today's Mongols in [[Mongolia]], Russia, the [[Central Asia]]n States and China.]]
Non-military achievements of the Mongol Empire included the introduction of a writing system, a Mongol alphabet based on the [[Uyghur language|Uighur]] characters, that is still used today in [[Inner Mongolia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last1 = Hahn | first1 = Reinhard F. | title = Spoken Uyghur | year = 1991 | publisher = University of Washington Press | location = London and Seattle | isbn = 978-0-295-98651-7 | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the other long-term consequences of the Mongol Empire include:
* Moscow rose to prominence during the [[Timeline of the Tataro-Mongol Yoke in Russia|Mongol-Tatar yoke]], some time after Russian rulers were accorded the status of tax collectors for the Mongols. The fact that the Russians collected tribute and taxes for the Mongols meant that the Mongols themselves would rarely visit the lands that they owned. The Russians eventually gained military power, and their ruler [[Ivan III of Russia|Ivan III]] overthrew the Mongols completely to form the [[Moscow principality|Russian Tsardom]]. After the [[Great stand on the Ugra river]] proved the Mongols vulnerable, this led to the independence of the Grand Duke of Moscow.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}
* Europe's knowledge of the known world was immensely expanded by the information brought back by ambassadors and merchants. When [[Christopher Columbus|Columbus]] sailed in 1492, his missions were to reach [[Cathay]], the land of the Grand Khan in China, and give him a letter from the monarchs [[Ferdinand II of Aragon]] and [[Isabella I of Castile]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}
* Some research studies indicate that the [[Black Death]] which devastated Europe in the late 1340s may have traveled from China to Europe along the trade routes of the Mongol Empire. In 1347, the [[Republic of Genoa|Genoese]] possessor of [[Feodosiya|Caffa]], a great trade emporium on the [[Crimea]]n peninsula, came under siege by an army of Mongol warriors under the command of [[Janibeg]]. After a protracted siege during which the Mongol army was reportedly withering from the disease, they decided to use the infected corpses as a [[biological weapon]]. The corpses were catapulted over the city walls, infecting the inhabitants.&lt;ref&gt;Svat Soucek. ''A History of Inner Asia''. Cambridge University Press, 2000. ISBN 0-521-65704-0. P. 116.&lt;/ref&gt; The Genoese traders fled, transferring the plague via their ships into the south of Europe, whence it rapidly spread. The total number of deaths worldwide from the pandemic is estimated at 75 million people, with an estimated 20 million deaths in Europe alone. There are claims{{By whom|date=July 2012}} of lesser casualties in the Mongol Empire due to superior hygiene and Oriental medicine.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}[[File:Meczennicy Sandomierscy.jpg|thumb|170px|Dominican martyrs killed by Mongols during the [[Mongol invasion of Poland]] in 1260.]]
* Western researcher [[R. J. Rummel]] estimated that 30 million people were killed under the rule of the Mongol Empire. The population of China fell by half in fifty years of Mongol rule. Before the Mongol invasion, the territories of the Chinese dynasties reportedly had approximately 120 million inhabitants; after the conquest was completed in 1279, the 1300 census reported roughly 60 million people. While it is tempting to attribute this major decline solely to Mongol ferocity, scholars today have mixed opinions regarding this subject. Scholars such as Frederick W. Mote argue that the wide drop in numbers reflects an administrative failure to record rather than a ''de facto'' decrease, whilst others such as Timothy Brook argue that the Mongols reduced much of the south Chinese population, and very debatably of the Han Chinese population to an invisible status through cancellation of right to passports and denial of right to direct land ownership. This meant that the Chinese had to depend and be cared for chiefly by Mongols and Tartars, which also involved recruitment into the Mongol army. When possibly resisted by Muslim women in the aftermath of the Tangut princess episode, this is reported to have led to close to an infraction in the trafficking in women. Forbidden in the Jasa/Zasaq, women were distributed freely after what has been alleged in footnotes to Igor de Rachewitz edition of the Niuca Mongqol-un Tovcha´an to have been ordered tantamount sexual abuse, with two casualties alleged out of four thousand. Other historians such as William McNeill and David Morgan argue that the Bubonic Plague was the main factor behind the demographic decline during this period.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}
[[File:MongolsInHungary1285.jpg|thumb|200px|left|The [[Mongol invasion of Hungary]] in 1285. The dismounted Mongols, with captured women, are on the left, the Hungarians, with one saved woman, on the right.]] All conditions in the Mongol empire for women were mitigated by women´s right to divorce, and their discouragement of foot-binding, however Chinese Nationalist women continued to bind their feet. They had the right to divorce, discouraged by Confucianism, but encouraged by the Mongols as the Jasa specially ordained commerce to be for women. Women warriors existed such as Chatulun, and as were reported by an abbot, and women were sometimes in commanding roles as well during the mass executions following the end of pages.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}
*David Nicole states in ''The Mongol Warlords'', &quot;terror and mass extermination of anyone opposing them was a well tested Mongol tactic.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mongol Conquests&quot;&gt;[http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat0.htm#Mongol Mongol Conquests]&lt;/ref&gt; About half of the Russian population may have died during the invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;parallelsixty.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.parallelsixty.com/history-russia.shtml History of Russia, Early Slavs history, Kievan Rus, Mongol invasion]&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Colin McEvedy]] (''Atlas of World Population History, 1978'') estimates the population of Russia-in-Europe dropped from 7.5 million prior to the invasion to 7 million afterwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mongol Conquests&quot;/&gt; Historians estimate that up to half of Hungary's two million population at that time were victims of the [[Mongol invasion of Europe|Mongol invasion]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-34789/Hungary The Mongol invasion: the last Arpad kings]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rogerius of Apulia|Rogerius]], a monk who survived the Mongol invasion of Hungary, pointed out not only the genocidal element of the occupation, but also that the Mongols especially &quot;found pleasure&quot; in humiliating women. The fact is that the Mongols initially at least were not given to violent sexual abuse of women but liked to engage in such acts while physically clasping them in a kind of embrace.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=NilW70Yol74C&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false ''Life after death: approaches to a cultural and social history of Europe during the 1940s and 1950s'']. Richard Bessel, Dirk Schumann (2003). Cambridge University Press. p.143. ISBN 978-0-521-00922-5&lt;/ref&gt;
* One of the more successful tactics employed by the Mongols was to wipe out urban populations that refused to surrender. For example, after the conquest of [[Konye-Urgench|Urgench]], each Mongol warrior – in an army group that might have consisted of two [[tumen]]s (units of 10,000) – was required to execute 24 people. In the [[Mongol invasion of Rus]], almost all major cities were destroyed. If they chose to submit, the people were spared, war prisoners sometimes became part of the Mongol army to aid in future conquests.&lt;ref&gt;The Story of the Mongols Whom We Call the Tartars= Historia Mongalorum Quo s Nos Tartaros Appellamus: Friar Giovanni Di Plano Carpini's Account of His Embassy to the Court of the Mongol Khan by Da Pian Del Carpine Giovanni and Erik Hildinger (Branden BooksApril 1996 ISBN 978-0-8283-2017-7)&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to intimidation tactics, the rapid expansion of the empire was facilitated by military hardiness (especially during bitterly cold winters), military skill, meritocracy, and discipline.

[[File:Location of Mongolia.svg|thumb|350px|alt=Outline map of Asia, showing a red outline of the current location of Mongolia|[[Mongolia]] today.]]
The influence of the Mongol Empire may prove to be even more direct — Zerjal et al. [2003]&lt;ref&gt;Zerjal, Xue, Bertolle, Wells, Bao, Zhu, Qamar, Ayub, Mohyuddin, Fu, Li, Yuldasheva, Ruzibakiev, Xu, Shu, Du, Yang, Hurles, Robinson, Gerelsaikhan, Dashnyam, Mehdi, Tyler-Smith (2003). &quot;The Genetic Legacy of the Mongols&quot;. ''American Journal of Human Genetics'' (72): 717–721.&lt;/ref&gt; identify a [[List of genetic results derived from historical figures|Y-chromosomal lineage]] present in about 8% of the men in a large region of Asia (or about 0.5% of the men in the world). The paper suggests that the pattern of variation within the lineage is consistent with a hypothesis that it originated in Mongolia about 1,000 years ago. Such a spread would be too rapid to have occurred by [[diffusion]], and must therefore be the result of [[selection]]. The authors propose that the lineage is carried by likely male line descendants of Genghis Khan, and that it has spread through social selection.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

In addition to the khanates and other descendants, the [[Mughal Empire|Mughal]] royal family of South Asia are also descended from Genghis Khan: [[Babur]]'s mother was a descendant — whereas his father was directly descended from [[Timur]] (Tamerlane). The word ''&quot;Mughol&quot;'' is an Arabic word for Mongol.

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Sources==
* {{cite book|author=Allsen, Thomas T.| title=Mongol Imperialism: The Policies of the Grand Qan Möngke in China, Russia, and the Islamic Lands, 1251-1259|isbn=978-0-520-05527-6{{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (6) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}|year=1987|publisher=University of California Press}}
* {{cite book|author=Allsen, Thomas T.|title=Culture and conquest in Mongol Eurasia|year=2004|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-60270-9}}
* {{Cite book|author=Amitai-Preiss, Reuven|title=Mongols and Mamluks: The Mamluk-Ilkhanid War, 1260–1281|year=1995|location=Cambridge, UK; New York, USA|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-46226-6}}
* {{Cite book|author=Atwood, Christopher P.|title=Encyclopedia of Mongolia and the Mongol Empire|year=2004|location=New York, USA|publisher=Facts on File, Inc.|isbn=0-8160-4671-9}}
* {{cite book|author=Barfield, Thomas Jefferson|year=1992|publisher=Blackwell|isbn=978-1-55786-324-9|title=The perilous frontier: nomadic empires and China}}
*{{Cite book| publisher = Infobase Publishing| isbn = 978-1-4381-0318-1| last = Burgan| first = Michael| title = Empire of the Mongols| year = 2005|location=New York, USA}}
* {{cite book|author=Diamond, Jared|authorlink=Jared Diamond|year=1997|title=Guns, Germs, and Steel: The Fates of Human Societies|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Co.|location=New York, USA|isbn=0-393-6131-0}}
* {{cite book|author=Finlay, Robert|title=The Pilgrim Art: Cultures of Porcelain in World History|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley, California, USA|year=2010|isbn=978-0-520-24468-9}}
* {{cite book |author=Foltz, Richard C.| authorlink=Richard Foltz |title=Religions of the Silk Road: Overland Trade and Cultural Exchange from Antiquity to the Fifteenth Century |location=New York, USA|publisher=St. Martin's Press|year=1999|isbn=0-312-23338-8 }}
* {{cite book|author=Franke, Herbert|editors=Twitchett, Denis; Fairbank, John King|title=Alien Regimes and Border States, 907-1368|volume=6|work=The Cambridge History of China|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, UK; New York, USA|year=1994|isbn=978-0-521-24331-5}}
* {{Cite book|author=Grousset, Rene|authorlink=René Grousset |title=The Empire of the Steppes: a History of Central Asia (translated from French by Naomi Walford). |location=New Brunswick, New Jersey, USA|publisher=Rutgers University Press|year=1970}}
* {{cite book|author=Halperin, Charles J.|title=Russia and the Golden Horde: The Mongol Impact on Medieval Russian History|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=1985|isbn=0-253-20445-3|location=Bloomington, Indiana, USA}}
* {{cite book|author=Howorth, Henry H.|title=History of the Mongols from the 9th to the 19th Century: Part I: The Mongols Proper and the Kalmuks|location=New York, USA|publisher=Burt Frankin|year=1965 (reprint of London edition, 1876)}}
* {{cite journal|author=Jackson, Peter|title=The dissolution of the Mongol Empire | journal=[[Central Asiatic Journal]]|volume=XXXII|year=1978|pages=208–351}}
* {{cite book|last= Jackson| first=Peter |title=The Delhi Sultanate: A Political and Military History|year=2003|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge, UK; New York, USA|isbn=0-521-54329-0}}
* {{Cite book|author=Jackson, Peter|authorlink=Peter Jackson (historian)|location=Harlow, UK; New York, USA|title=The Mongols and the West: 1221-1410|year=2005|publisher=Longman|isbn=978-0-582-36896-5}}
* {{cite book|author=Lane, George|title=Daily life in the Mongol empire|year=2006|isbn=978-0-313-33226-5|publisher=Greenwood Press|location=Westport, Connecticut, USA}}
* {{cite book|author=Man, John|title=Genghis Khan: Life, death and resurrection|isbn=978-0-312-36624-7|year=2004|publisher=Thomas Dunne Books|location=New York, USA}}
* {{cite book|author=Man, John|title=Kublai Khan: from Xanadu to superpower|publisher=Bantam Books|year=2007|isbn=978-0-553-81718-8}}
* {{cite journal|author=Morgan, David|authorlink=David Morgan (historian)|title=The Mongols and the Eastern Mediterranean: Latins and Greeks in the Eastern Mediterranean after 1204|editors=Arbel, B.; et al.|journal=[[Mediterranean Historical Review]]|volume=4| issue=1| month=June | year=1989 | page=204| doi=10.1080/09518968908569567| issn=0951-8967| publisher=Routledge| location=Tel Aviv, Illinois, USA}}
* {{cite book|author=Morgan, David|title=The Mongols|edition=2nd|year=2007|publisher=Blackwell Publishing|location=Malden, Massachusetts, USA;  Oxford, UK; Carlton, Victoria, Australia|isbn=978-1-4051-3539-9}}
*{{Cite book|author=Prawdin, Michael (pseudonym for Charol, Michael)|authorlink=Michael Prawdin|date=1940/1961|publisher=Collier-Macmillan Canada|title=Mongol Empire|isbn=1-4128-0519-8|location=New Brunswick, New Jersey, USA}}
* {{cite book|author=Ratchnevsky, Paul|editor=Haining, Thomas Nivison (translator)|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|year=1993|isbn=8780631189497{{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (7) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}{{Please check ISBN|reason=13 digit ISBN should start with  978 or 979.}}|title=Genghis Khan: his life and legacy}}
* {{cite book|author=Rossabi, Morris|title=China among equals: the Middle Kingdom and its neighbors, 10th-14th centuries|publisher=University of California Press|year=1983|isbn=0-520-04383-9|location=Berkeley, California, USA}}
* {{Cite book| publisher = Scarecrow Press| isbn = 978-0-8108-6191-6| last = Sanders| first = Alan J. K.| title = Historical dictionary of Mongolia| year = 2010|location=Lanham, Maryland, USA}}
*{{Cite book| publisher = University of Pennsylvania Press|isbn = 978-0-8122-1766-7| last = Saunders| first = John Joseph| title = The history of the Mongol conquests| year= 2001|location=Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA}}
* {{cite book|author=Rybatzki, Volker|title=The early mongols: language, culture and history|isbn=97880933070578{{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}}|year=2009|publisher=Indiana University}}
* {{Cite book| publisher = Boydell &amp; Brewer| isbn = 978-1-84383-596-7| editors = Rogers, Clifford J.; [[Kelly DeVries|DeVries, Kelly]]; France, John| title = [[Journal of Medieval Military History]]|location=Woodbridge, Suffolk, UK| volume =8| date = November 2010|chapter=Numbers in Mongol Warfare|author=Sverdrup, Carl|url=http://books.google.com/?id=4jHEwSc2gEMC&amp;pg=PA109&amp;dq=devries+mongols#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
* {{cite book|author=Vladimortsov, Boris|title=The life of Chingis Khan|publisher=B. Blom|year=1969}}
* {{cite book|author=Weatherford, Jack|year=2004|title=Genghis Khan and the Making of the Modern World|location=New York, USA|publisher=Three Rivers Press|isbn=0-609-80964-4}}

==Further reading==
* Brent, Peter. ''The Mongol Empire: Genghis Khan: His Triumph and his Legacy''. Book Club Associates, London. 1976.
* {{Cite book
 | last1 = Buell
 | given1 = Paul D.
 | year = 2003
 | title = Historical Dictionary of the Mongol World Empire
 | publisher= The Scarecrow Press, Inc.
 | isbn = 0-8108-4571-7
 | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}
}}
* May, Timothy. &quot;The Mongol Art of War.&quot; Westholme Publishing, Yardley. 2007. ISBN 978-1-59416-046-2 / ISBN 1-59416-046-5
* May, Timothy. ''The Mongol Conquests in World History'' (Reaktion Books, distributed by University of Chicago Press; 2012) 319 pages
{{Commons category|Mongol Empire}}

==External links==
* [http://www.fsmitha.com/h3/h11mon.htm Genghis Khan and the Mongols]
* [http://www.allempires.com/article/index.php?q=The_Mongol_Empire The Mongol Empire]
* [http://www.accd.edu/sac/history/keller/Mongols/intro.html Mongols]
* [http://www.leader-values.com/Content/detail.asp?ContentDetailID=799 Genghis Khan Biography]
* [http://afe.easia.columbia.edu/mongols/ The Mongols in World History]
* [http://sd71.bc.ca/sd71/school/courtmid/Library/subject_resources/socials/mogolempire.htm The Mongol Empire for students]
* [http://www.paradoxplace.com/Insights/Civilizations/Mongols/Mongols.htm Paradoxplace Insight Pages on the Mongol Emperors]
* [http://depts.washington.edu/silkroad/texts/rubruck.html William of Rubruck's Account of the Mongols]
* [http://steppes.proboards23.com/index.cgi?board=board18&amp;action=print&amp;thread=1167258099 Mongol invasion of Rus (pictures)]
* [http://necrometrics.com/pre1700a.htm#Mongol Worldwide Death Toll]
* [http://bbs.keyhole.com/ubb/download.php?Number=758258 Mongol Empire Google Earth]

{{Mongol Empire}}
{{Empires}}

[[Category:Mongol Empire| 01]]
[[Category:Turkic dynasties]]
[[Category:Former monarchies of Asia]]
[[Category:Former countries in Central Asia]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1206]]
[[Category:1368 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Eurasian nomads]]
[[Category:Horse archer civilizations and empires]]
[[Category:Mongol Empire]]
[[Category:History of Mongolia]]
[[Category:History of Central Asia]]
[[Category:Mongols|Empire]]
[[Category:Khaganates]]

{{Link FA|nl}}
{{Link FA|ar}}
{{Link FA|sl}}
[[af:Mongoolse Ryk]]
[[ar:إمبراطورية المغول]]
[[an:Imperio Mongol]]
[[az:Böyük Monqol imperiyası]]
[[bn:মঙ্গোল সাম্রাজ্য]]
[[zh-min-nan:Bông-kó͘ Tè-kok]]
[[be:Мангольская імперыя]]
[[be-x-old:Мангольская імпэрыя]]
[[bg:Монголска империя]]
[[bs:Mongolsko carstvo]]
[[br:Impalaeriezh Vongol]]
[[ca:Imperi mongol]]
[[cs:Mongolská říše]]
[[cy:Ymerodraeth y Mongol]]
[[da:Mongolske kejserdømme]]
[[de:Mongolisches Reich]]
[[et:Mongolite riik]]
[[el:Αυτοκρατορία των Μογγόλων]]
[[es:Imperio mongol]]
[[eo:Mongola Imperio]]
[[eu:Mongolen Inperioa]]
[[fa:امپراتوری مغول]]
[[hif:Mongol Samrajya]]
[[fr:Empire mongol]]
[[gl:Imperio Mongol]]
[[ko:몽골 제국]]
[[hy:Մոնղոլական կայսրություն]]
[[hi:मंगोल साम्राज्य]]
[[hr:Mongolsko Carstvo]]
[[id:Kekaisaran Mongolia]]
[[is:Mongólaveldið]]
[[it:Impero mongolo]]
[[he:האימפריה המונגולית]]
[[ka:მონღოლთა იმპერია]]
[[kk:Шыңғыс хан империясы]]
[[sw:Milki ya Wamongolia]]
[[la:Imperium Mongolicum]]
[[lv:Mongoļu impērija]]
[[lb:Mongolescht Räich]]
[[lt:Mongolų imperija]]
[[hu:Mongol Birodalom]]
[[mk:Монголска Империја]]
[[ml:മംഗോള്‍ സാമ്രാജ്യം]]
[[mr:मंगोल साम्राज्य]]
[[arz:امبراطوريه مغوليه]]
[[ms:Empayar Mongol]]
[[mn:Их Монгол Улс]]
[[my:မွန်ဂိုအင်ပါယာ]]
[[nl:Mongoolse Rijk]]
[[ja:モンゴル帝国]]
[[no:Mongolriket]]
[[nn:Det mongolske riket]]
[[oc:Empèri Mongòl]]
[[pnb:منگول سلطنت]]
[[pl:Imperium mongolskie]]
[[pt:Império Mongol]]
[[ro:Imperiul Mongol]]
[[rue:Монґольска ріша]]
[[ru:Монгольская империя]]
[[sco:Mongol Empire]]
[[simple:Mongol Empire]]
[[sk:Mongolská ríša]]
[[sl:Mongolsko cesarstvo]]
[[ckb:ئیمپڕاتۆرێتیی مەغۆل]]
[[sr:Монголско царство]]
[[sh:Mongolsko Carstvo]]
[[fi:Mongolivaltakunta]]
[[sv:Mongolväldet]]
[[tl:Imperyong Monggol]]
[[ta:மங்கோலியப் பேரரசு]]
[[tt:Монгол империясе]]
[[th:จักรวรรดิมองโกล]]
[[tr:Moğol İmparatorluğu]]
[[tk:Mongol imperiýasy]]
[[uk:Монгольська імперія]]
[[ur:مغول سلطنت]]
[[ug:موڭغۇل ئىمپېرىيىسى]]
[[vi:Đế quốc Mông Cổ]]
[[war:Imperyo Mongol]]
[[yi:מאנגאלישע אימפעריע]]
[[zh-yue:蒙古帝國]]
[[diq:İmperatoriya Moğoli]]
[[bat-smg:Monguolu imperėjė]]
[[zh:蒙古帝国]]</text>
      <sha1>fcl5tjv78czwxu92z50uur6gzpylc5o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
