<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Neolithic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21189</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522247533</id>
      <parentid>522247037</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T22:44:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/148.166.201.13|148.166.201.13]] ([[User talk:148.166.201.13|talk]]) to last version by Malkin</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44516">[[File:Néolithique 0001.jpg|thumb|250px|An array of Neolithic artifacts, including bracelets, axe heads, chisels, and polishing tools. Neolithic stone implements are by definition polished and, except for specialty items, not chipped.]]
{{Refimprove|date=February 2012}}

{{Neolithic|257}}
The '''Neolithic''' Age, Era, or Period, νέος (néos, &quot;new&quot;) and λίθος (líthos, &quot;stone&quot;): or '''New Stone era''', was a period in the development of human [[technology]], beginning about 10,200 [[Radiocarbon dating#Calibration|cal.]] BCE according to the [[ASPRO chronology]] in some parts of the Middle East, and later in other parts of the world.&lt;ref name=Bellwood&gt;
[http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0631205667&amp;pageID=S00N&amp;checkSum=n2ERnZHriUc/fSrW7Myf4CEtIc8x5mVhcabli2BNrEs=# Figure 3.3] from ''First Farmers: The Origins of Agricultural Societies'' by [[Peter Bellwood]], 2004&lt;/ref&gt; It is traditionally considered as the last part of the [[Stone Age]]. The Neolithic followed the terminal [[Holocene]] ''[[Epipaleolithic]]'' period, beginning with the [[History of agriculture|rise of farming]], which produced the &quot;[[Neolithic Revolution]]&quot;, and ending when metal tools became widespread in the Copper Age ([[chalcolithic]]) or [[Bronze Age]] or developing directly into the [[Iron Age]], depending on the geographical region. The Neolithic is a measured progression of behavioral and cultural characteristics and changes, including the use of wild and domestic crops and the [[domestication|use of domesticated animals]].&lt;ref&gt;Some archaeologists have long advocated replacing &quot;Neolithic&quot; with a more descriptive term, such as &quot;Early Village Communities&quot;, although this has not gained wide acceptance.&lt;/ref&gt;

The beginning of the Neolithic culture is considered to be in the [[Levant]] ([[Jericho]], modern-day [[West Bank]]) about 10200-8800 cal. BCE. It developed directly from the Epipaleolithic [[Natufian]] culture in the region, whose people pioneered the use of wild [[cereal]]s, which then evolved into true [[farming]]. The Natufian period was between 12000-10200 cal. BCE and the so-called &quot;proto-neolithic&quot; is now included in the [[PPNA]] between 10200-8800 cal. BCE. As the Natufians had become dependent on wild cereals in their diet, and a sedentary way of life had begun among them, the climatic changes associated with the [[Younger Dryas]] are thought to have forced people to develop farming. By 10200-8800 cal. BCE, farming communities arose in the Levant and spread to [[Asia Minor]], North Africa and North [[Mesopotamia]]. Early Neolithic farming was limited to a narrow range of plants, both wild and domesticated, which included [[einkorn wheat]], [[millet]] and [[spelt]], and the keeping of [[origin of the domestic dog|dogs]], [[sheep]] and [[goat#History|goats]]. By about 6900-6400 cal. BC, it included domesticated [[cattle]] and [[domesticated pig|pig]]s, the establishment of permanently or seasonally inhabited settlements, and the use of [[pottery]].&lt;ref&gt;The [[potter's wheel]] was a later refinement that revolutionized the pottery industry.&lt;/ref&gt;

Not all of these cultural elements characteristic of the Neolithic appeared everywhere in the same order: the earliest farming societies in the [[Ancient Near East|Near East]] did not use pottery. In other parts of the world, such as Africa, [[South Asia]] and Southeast Asia, independent domestication events led to their own regionally-distinctive Neolithic cultures that arose completely independent of those in Europe and Southwest Asia. [[Jōmon period|Early Japanese]] societies used pottery ''before'' developing agriculture.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Habu|first=Junko|year=2004|title=Ancient Jomon of Japan|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=0-521-77213-3 (HB), ISBN 0-521-77670-8 (PB)|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike the [[Paleolithic]], when more than one human species existed, only one human species (''[[Homo sapiens sapiens]]'') reached the Neolithic. [[Homo floresiensis]] may have survived right up to the very dawn of the Neolithic, about 12,200 years ago.

The term ''Neolithic'' derives from the [[Greek language|Greek]] ''νεολιθικός'', ''neolithikos'', from ''νέος'' ''neos'', &quot;new&quot; + ''λίθος'' ''lithos'', &quot;stone&quot;, literally meaning &quot;New [[Stone Age]].&quot; The term was invented by [[John Lubbock, 1st Baron Avebury|Sir John Lubbock]] in 1865 as a refinement of the [[three-age system]].

==Periods by pottery phase==
In the Middle East, cultures identified as Neolithic began appearing by in the 10th millennium BC.&lt;ref name=Bellwood/&gt; Early development occurred in the [[Levant]] (e.g., [[Pre-Pottery Neolithic A]] and [[Pre-Pottery Neolithic B]]) and from there spread eastwards and westwards. Neolithic cultures are also attested in southeastern [[Anatolia]] and northern Mesopotamia by c. 8000 BC.

The [[prehistoric Beifudi site]] near [[Yi County, Hebei|Yixian]] in Hebei Province, China, contains relics of a culture contemporaneous with the [[Cishan culture|Cishan]] and [[Xinglongwa culture|Xinglongwa]] cultures of about 5000–6000 BC, neolithic cultures east of the [[Taihang Mountains]], filling in an archaeological gap between the two Northern Chinese cultures. The total excavated area is more than 1,200 square meters and the collection of neolithic findings at the site consists of two phases.&lt;ref name=&quot;archdis&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.kaogu.cn/en/detail.asp?ProductID=982
|title=New Archaeological Discoveries and Researches in 2004 — The Fourth Archaeology Forum of CASS
|publisher=Institute of Archaeology — Chinese Academy of Social Sciences
|accessdate=2007-09-18
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Neolithic 1 – Pre-Pottery Neolithic A (PPNA)===

Sites in the [[Levant]] ([[Jericho]], [[Palestine]] &amp; Jbeil ([[Byblos]]), Lebanon) that go back to around 9500 to 9000 BC. are considered the beginning of the Neolithic 1 (PPNA). The actual date is not established with certainty due to different results in [[carbon dating]] by scientists in the [[British Museum]] and Philadelphia laboratories{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}. The [[Tahunian]] and [[Heavy Neolithic]] have caused further problems with the timeline.

An early temple area in southeastern Turkey at [[Göbekli Tepe]] dated to 10,000 BCE may be regarded as the beginning of the Neolithic 1. This site was developed by nomadic hunter-gatherer tribes, evidenced by the lack of permanent housing in the vicinity. This temple site may be the oldest known human-made place of worship.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The World's First Temple&quot;, Archaeology magazine, Nov/Dec 2008 p 23.&lt;/ref&gt; At least seven stone circles, covering {{convert|25|acre|m2}}, contain limestone pillars carved with animals, insects and birds. Stone tools were used by perhaps as many as hundreds of people to create the pillars, which may have supported roofs.

The major advance of Neolithic 1 was true farming. In the proto-Neolithic [[Natufian]] cultures, wild cereals were harvested, and perhaps early seed selection and re-seeding occurred. The grain was ground into flour. [[Emmer wheat]] was domesticated, and animals were herded and domesticated ([[animal husbandry]] and [[selective breeding]]).

In the 21st century, remains of [[Ficus|figs]] were discovered in a house in Jericho dated to 9400 BC. The figs are of a mutant variety that cannot be pollinated by insects, and therefore the trees can only reproduce from cuttings. This evidence suggests that figs were the first cultivated crop and mark the invention of the technology of farming. This occurred centuries before the first cultivation of grains.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Joyce [http://www.npr.org/s.php?sId=5446137&amp;m=1 &quot;Ancient Figs May Be First Cultivated Crops&quot;], NPR.org, June 2, 2006, last accessed 28 January 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Settlements became more permanent with circular houses, much like those of the Natufians, with single rooms. However, these houses were for the first time made of [[mudbrick]]. The settlement had a surrounding stone wall and perhaps a stone tower (as in Jericho). The wall served as protection from nearby groups, as protection from floods, or to keep animals penned. There are also some enclosures that suggest grain and meat storage.

===Neolithic 2 – Pre-Pottery Neolithic B (PPNB)===
The Neolithic 2 (PPNB) began around 8800 cal. BCE according to the [[ASPRO chronology]] in the Levant ([[Jericho]], Palestine).&lt;ref name=Bellwood/&gt; As with the PPNA dates there are two versions from the same laboratories noted above. But this terminological structure is not convenient for southeast [[Anatolia]] and settlements of the middle Anatolia basin. This era was before the [[mesolithic|Mesolithic era]].

Settlements have rectangular mudbrick houses where the family lived together in single or multiple rooms. Burial findings suggest an [[ancestor cult]] where people preserved skulls of the dead, which were plastered with mud to make facial features. The rest of the corpse may have been left outside the settlement to decay until only the bones were left, then the bones were buried inside the settlement underneath the floor or between houses.

===Neolithic 3 – Pottery Neolithic (PN)===
The Neolithic 3 (PN) began around 6400 cal. BCE in the [[Fertile Crescent]].&lt;ref name=Bellwood/&gt; By then distinctive cultures emerged, with pottery like the [[Halafian]] (Turkey, Syria, Northern Mesopotamia) and [[Ubaid period|Ubaid]] (Southern Mesopotamia). This period has been further divided into '''PNA''' (Pottery Neolithic A) and '''PNB''' (Pottery Neolithic B) at some sites.

The Chalcolithic period began about 4500 BC, then the [[Bronze Age]] began about 3500 BC, replacing the Neolithic cultures.

==Periods by region==

===Fertile Crescent===
Around 10200 BC, the first fully developed Neolithic cultures belonging to the phase [[Pre-Pottery Neolithic A]] (PPNA) appeared in the fertile crescent.&lt;ref name=Bellwood/&gt; Around 10,700 to 9400 BC, a settlement was established in Tell Qaramel, 25 kilometers north of [[Aleppo]]. The settlement included 2 temples dating back to 9650.&lt;ref name=eduskrypt&gt;
[http://www.eduskrypt.pl/yet_another_sensational_discovery_by_polish_archaeologists_in_syria-info-6775.html Yet another sensational discovery by polish archaeologists in Syria]. eduskrypt.pl. 21 June 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Around 9000 BC during the PPNA, the world's first town, [[Jericho]], appeared in the Levant. It was surrounded by a stone and marble wall and contained a population of 2000–3000 people and a massive stone tower.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9043547/Jericho &quot;Jericho&quot;], Encyclopædia Britannica&lt;/ref&gt; Around 6400 BC the [[Halaf culture]] appeared in Lebanon, Israel and Palestine, Syria, Anatolia, and Northern Mesopotamia and subsisted on dryland agriculture.

In 1981 a team of researchers from the [[Maison de l'Orient et de la Méditerranée]], including [[Jacques Cauvin]] and Oliver Aurenche divided Near East neolithic chronology into ten periods (0 to 9) based on social, economic and cultural characteristics.&lt;ref name=&quot;boustani&quot;&gt;Haïdar Boustani, M., [http://www.usj.edu.lb/mpl/pdf/1.pdf The Neolithic of Lebanon in the context of the Near East: State of knowledge] (in French), Annales d'Histoire et d'Archaeologie, Uinversite Saint-Joseph, Beyrouth, Vol. 12–13, 2001–2002. (PDF) . Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002 [[Danielle Stordeur]] and [[Frédéric Abbès]] advanced this system with a division into five periods. [[Natufian]] (1) between 12000 and 10200 cal. BCE, [[Khiamian]] (2) between 10200-8800 cal. BCE, [[PPNA]]: Sultanian (Jericho), [[Mureybet]]ian, early PPNB (''PPNB ancien'') (3) between 8800-7600 cal. BCE, middle PPNB (''PPNB moyen'') 7600-6900 cal. BCE, late PPNB (''PPNB récent'') (4) between 7500 and 7000 BC and a PPNB (sometimes called PPNC) transitional stage (''PPNB final'') (5) where Halaf and [[dark faced burnished ware]] begin to emerge between 6900-6400 cal. BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Stordeur, Danielle., Abbès Frédéric., [http://www.persee.fr/web/revues/home/prescript/article/bspf_0249-7638_2002_num_99_3_12712 Du PPNA au PPNB : mise en lumière d'une phase de transition à Jerf el Ahmar (Syrie)], Bulletin de la Société préhistorique française, Volume 99, Issue 3, pp. 563–595, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; They also advanced the idea of a transitional stage between the PPNA and PPNB between 8800 and 8600 BC at sites like [[Jerf el Ahmar]] and [[Tell Aswad]].&lt;ref name=&quot;exoriente&quot;&gt;[http://www.exoriente.org/associated_projects/ppnd_summary.php PPND – the Platform for Neolithic Radiocarbon Dates – Summary]. exoriente. Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Southern Mesopotamia===
Alluvial plains ([[Sumer]]/[[Elam]]). Little rainfall makes [[irrigation]] systems necessary. [[Ubaid period|Ubaid]] culture from 6900 BC.

===North Africa===
[[File:African cave paintings.jpg|thumb|Algerian cave paintings depicting hunting scenes]]
Domestication of [[sheep]] and [[goats]] reached Egypt from the Near East possibly as early as 6000 BC{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}. [[Graeme Barker]] states &quot;The first indisputable evidence for domestic plants and animals in the Nile valley is not until the early fifth millennium bc in northern Egypt and a thousand years later further south, in both cases as part of strategies that still relied heavily on fishing, hunting, and the gathering of wild plants&quot; and suggests that these subsistence changes were not due to farmers migrating from the Near East but was an indigenous development, with cereals either indigenous or obtained through exchange.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Graeme Barker|title=The Agricultural Revolution in Prehistory: Why Did Foragers Become Farmers?|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fkifXu2gx4YC&amp;pg=PA292|accessdate=3 December 2011|date=25 March 2009|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-955995-4|pages=292–293}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other scholars argue that the primary stimulus for agriculture and domesticated animals (as well as mud-brick architecture and other Neolithic cultural features) in Egypt was from the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;Aikhenvald, Alexandra Y; RMW Dixon ''Areal Diffusion and Genetic Inheritance: Problems in Comparative Linguistics'' p. 35 [OUP Oxford (2 March 2006) ISBN 978-0-19-928308-8]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Fekri A. Hassan|title=Droughts, food and culture: ecological change and food security in Africa's later prehistory|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kVJwQsZUwxYC&amp;pg=PA164|accessdate=3 December 2011|year=2002|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-0-306-46755-4|pages=164–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Kevin Shillington|title=Encyclopedia of African history: A-G|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Ftz_gtO-pngC&amp;pg=PA521|accessdate=3 December 2011|year=2005|publisher=CRC Press|isbn=978-1-57958-245-6|pages=521–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
[[File:Golemata Majka.jpg|thumb|left|160px|Female figure from [[Tumba Madžari]], [[Republic of Macedonia]]]]
[[File:European Late Neolithic.gif|thumb|Map showing distribution of some of the main culture complexes in [[Neolithic Europe]], ca. 3500 BC]]
[[File:Skara Brae house 1 5.jpg|thumb|[[Skara Brae]], Scotland. Evidence of home furnishings (shelves)]]
In southeast [[Neolithic Europe|Europe]] agrarian societies first appeared in the [[7th millennium BC]], attested by one of the earliest farming site of Europe, discovered in [[Vashtëmi]], southeastern [[Albania]] and dating back to 6,500 BC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Dawn Fuller| date=April 16, 2012 | title=UC research reveals one of the earliest farming sites in Europe| publisher=Phys.org| url=http://phys.org/news/2012-04-uc-reveals-earliest-farming-sites.html| accessdate=April 18, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | date=April 16, 2012 | title=One of Earliest Farming Sites in Europe Discovered| publisher=ScienceDaily| url=http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/04/120416113013.htm| accessdate=April 18, 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Anthropomorphic figurines have been found in the Balkans from 6000 BC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.macedonian-heritage.gr/HellenicMacedonia/en/img_A11a.html Female figurine, circa 6000 BC, Nea Nikomidia, Macedonia, Veroia, (Archaeological Museum), Greece]. Macedonian-heritage.gr. Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt; and in Central Europe by ca. 5500 BC. Among the earliest cultural complexes of this area are included the [[Sesklo]] culture in Thessaly, which later expanded in the Balkans giving [[Starčevo–Kőrös–Criş culture (disambiguation)|Starčevo-Körös]] (Cris), [[Linearbandkeramik]], and [[Vinča culture|Vinča]]. Through a combination of [[cultural diffusion]] and [[human migration|migration of peoples]], the Neolithic traditions spread west and northwards to reach northwestern Europe by around 4500 BC. The [[Vinča culture]] may have created the earliest system of writing, the [[Vinča signs]], though it is almost universally accepted amongst archeologists{{Who|date=December 2008}} that the [[Sumerian cuneiform]] script was the earliest true form of writing and the [[Vinča signs]] most likely represented [[pictograms]] and [[ideograms]] rather than a truly developed form of writing.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} The [[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture]] built enormous settlements in Romania, Moldova and Ukraine from 5300 to 2300 BC. The [[megalith]]ic temple complexes of [[Ġgantija]] on the Mediterranean island of [[Gozo Island|Gozo]] (in the Maltese archipelago) and of [[Mnajdra]] (Malta) are notable for their gigantic Neolithic structures, the oldest of which date back to c. 3600 BC.&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[File:Holies.jpg|thumb|The Holy of Holies, Hypogeum, Malta|{{Deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 31 December 2008|date=February 2012}}]] --&gt; The [[Hypogeum of Ħal-Saflieni]], [[Paola, Malta|Paola]], Malta, is a subterranean structure excavated c. 2500 BC; originally a sanctuary, it became a [[necropolis]], the only prehistoric underground temple in the world, and showing a degree of artistry in stone sculpture unique in prehistory to the Maltese islands.

===South and East Asia===
The earliest Neolithic site in South Asia is [[Mehrgarh]], dated to 7500 BC, in the Kachi plain of [[Balochistan (Pakistan)|Baluchistan]], Pakistan; the site has evidence of farming (wheat and barley) and herding (cattle, sheep and goats).&lt;ref&gt;Hirst, K. Kris. 2005. [http://archaeology.about.com/od/mterms/g/mehrgarh.htm &quot;Mehrgarh&quot;]. ''Guide to Archaeology''&lt;/ref&gt;

In South India, the Neolithic began by 3000 BC and lasted until around 1400 BC when the Megalithic transition period began. South Indian Neolithic is characterized by Ashmounds since 2500 BC in Karnataka region, expanded later to [[Tamil Nadu]].

In East Asia, the earliest sites include [[Pengtoushan culture]] around 7500 BC to 6100 BC, [[Peiligang culture]] around 7000 BC to 5000 BC.

The 'Neolithic' (defined in this paragraph as using polished stone implements) remains a living tradition in small and extremely remote and inaccessible pockets of [[West Papua (region)|West Papua]] (Indonesian New Guinea). Polished stone [[adzes|adze]] and axes are used in the present day ({{As of|2008}} CE) in areas where the availability of metal implements is limited. This is likely to cease altogether in the next few years as the older generation die off and steel blades and chainsaws prevail.

In 2012, news was released about a new farming site discovered in [[Munam-ri]], [[Goseong, Gangwon|Goseong]], [[Gangwon Province (South Korea)|Gangwon Province]], [[South Korea]], which may be the earliest farmland known to date in east Asia.&lt;ref&gt;The Archaeology News Network. 2012. [http://archaeologynewsnetwork.blogspot.fr/2012/06/neolithic-farm-field-found-in-south.html &quot;Neolithic farm field found in South Korea&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;No remains of an agricultural field from the Neolithic period have been found in any East Asian country before, the institute said, adding that the discovery reveals that the history of agricultural cultivation at least began during the period on the [[Korean Peninsula]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Korea Times. 2012. [http://www.koreatimes.co.kr/www/news/nation/2012/06/117_113810.html &quot;East Asia's oldest remains of agricultural field found in Korea&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; The farm was dated between 3600 and 3000 B.C. Pottery, stone projectile points, and possible houses were also found. &quot;In 2002, researchers discovered prehistoric [[earthenware]], [[jade]] earrings, among other items in the area.&quot; The research team will perform [[Accelerator mass spectrometry]] (AMS) dating to retrieve a more precise date for the site.

===America===
In [[Mesoamerican chronology|Mesoamerica]], a similar set of events (i.e., crop domestication and sedentary lifestyles) occurred by around 4500 BC, but possibly as early as 11,000–10,000 BC. However, [[Formative stage]] is used instead of mid-late Neolithic, [[Archaic period in the Americas|Archaic Era]] is used instead of Early Neolithic, and [[Paleo-Indians|Paleo-Indian]] for the preceding period. These cultures are usually not referred to as belonging to the Neolithic; in America different terms are used, see [[List of archaeological periods (Mesoamerica)]].&lt;ref name = &quot;W&amp;P&quot; &gt;{{cite book | author=Gordon R. Willey and Philip Phillips | title=Method and Theory in American Archaeology | publisher= University of Chicago Press| year=1957 | isbn=0-226-89888-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Formative stage is equivalent to the [[Neolithic Revolution]] period in Europe, Asia, and Africa. In the Southwestern United States it occurred from 500 to 1200 C.E. when there was a dramatic increase in population and development of large villages supported by agriculture based on [[dryland farming]] of maize, and later, beans, squash, and domesticated turkeys. During this period the bow and arrow and ceramic pottery were also introduced.&lt;ref name=NRSW&gt;{{cite journal|coauthors=Kohler TA, M Glaude, JP Bocquet-Appel and Brian M Kemp|title=The Neolithic Demographic Transition in the North American Southwest|journal=American Antiquity 73(4):|year=2008|volume=73|issue=4|pages=645–669|accessdate=June 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social organization==
[[File:Néolithique 0008.jpg|thumb|left|Anthropomorphic Neolithic figurine]]
[[File:MotherGoddessFertility.JPG||thumb|left|Anthropomorphic Female Neolithic ceramic figurine]]
During most of the Neolithic age, people lived in small [[tribe]]s composed of multiple bands or lineages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard D. Katz Rigby 2000 352&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Evolutionary Origins of Morality: Cross-disciplinary Perspectives |author=Leonard D. Katz Rigby |url= http://books.google.com/?id=inmTyPPdR5oC&amp;pg=RA1-PA158 |year=2000 |location=United kingdom|page=352 |publisher=Imprint Academic |isbn=0-7190-5612-8|page =158}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is little [[scientific evidence]] of developed [[social stratification]] in most Neolithic societies; social stratification is more associated with the later [[Bronze Age]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Jonas Langer |author2=Melanie Killen |title=Piaget, evolution, and development |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=haCAIME9vnEC&amp;pg=PA258 |accessdate=3 December 2011 |year=1998 |publisher=Psychology Press |isbn=978-0-8058-2210-6 |pages=258–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although some late Neolithic societies formed complex stratified chiefdoms similar to [[Polynesia]]n societies such as the [[Ancient Hawaii]]ans, most Neolithic societies were relatively simple and egalitarian.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard D. Katz Rigby 2000 352&quot;/&gt; However, Neolithic societies were noticeably more hierarchical than the [[Paleolithic]] cultures that preceded them and [[hunter-gatherer]] cultures in general&lt;ref&gt;[http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761555928_5/Stone_Age.html#howtocite &quot;Stone Age,&quot; Microsoft Encarta Online Encyclopedia 2007] © 1997–2007 Microsoft Corporation. All Rights Reserved. Contributed by Kathy Schick, B.A., M.A., Ph.D. and Nicholas Toth, B.A., M.A., Ph.D. [http://www.webcitation.org/5kyWqKoah Archived] 2009-11-01.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=b1&gt;{{cite book|author=Russell Dale Guthrie |title=The nature of Paleolithic art |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3u6JNwMyMCEC&amp;pg=PA420 |accessdate=3 December 2011 |year=2005 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |isbn=978-0-226-31126-5 |pages=420–}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[domestication of animals]] ([[Circa|c.]] 8000 BC) resulted in a dramatic increase in social inequality. Possession of livestock allowed competition between households and resulted in inherited inequalities of wealth. Neolithic pastoralists who controlled large herds gradually acquired more livestock, and this made economic inequalities more pronounced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bahn, Paul 1996&quot;&gt;Bahn, Paul (1996) &quot;The atlas of world archeology&quot; Copyright 2000 The brown Reference Group plc&lt;/ref&gt; However, evidence of social inequality is still disputed, as settlements such as [[Catal Huyuk]] reveal a striking lack of difference in the size of homes and burial sites, suggesting a more egalitarian society with no evidence of the concept of capital, although some homes do appear slightly larger or more elaborately decorated than others.

Families and households were still largely independent economically, and the household was probably the center of life.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}} However, excavations in [[Central Europe]] have revealed that early Neolithic [[Linear Ceramic culture]]s (&quot;''Linearbandkeramik''&quot;) were building large arrangements of [[circular ditches]] between 4800 BC and 4600 BC. These structures (and their later counterparts such as [[causewayed enclosure]]s, [[burial mound]]s, and [[henges|henge]]) required considerable time and labour to construct, which suggests that some influential individuals were able to organise and direct human labour — though non-hierarchical and voluntary work remain strong possibilities.

There is a large body of evidence for fortified settlements at ''Linearbandkeramik'' sites along the [[Rhine]], as at least some villages were fortified for some time with a [[palisade]] and an outer ditch.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.holysmoke.org/fem/fem0156.htm Idyllic Theory of Goddess Creates Storm]. Holysmoke.org. Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Krause (1998) under External links, places.&lt;/ref&gt; Settlements with palisades and weapon-traumatized bones have been discovered, such as at the [[Talheim Death Pit]] demonstrates &quot;...systematic violence between groups&quot; and warfare was probably much more common during the Neolithic than in the preceding Paleolithic period.&lt;ref name=b1/&gt; This supplanted an earlier view of the Linear Pottery Culture as living a &quot;peaceful, unfortified lifestyle.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gimbutas (1991) page 143.&lt;/ref&gt;

Control of labour and inter-group conflict is characteristic of corporate-level or 'tribal' groups, headed by a charismatic individual; whether a '[[Big man (anthropology)|big man]]' or a proto-[[Tribal chief|chief]], functioning as a lineage-group head. Whether a non-hierarchical system of organization existed is debatable and there is no evidence that explicitly suggests that Neolithic societies functioned under any dominating class or individual, as was the case in the [[chiefdoms]] of the European [[Bronze Age|Early Bronze Age]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Ian Kuijt|title=Life in Neolithic farming communities: social organization, identity, and differentiation|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kz79KLC6yLoC&amp;pg=PA317|accessdate=3 December 2011|date=30 June 2000|publisher=Springer|isbn=978-0-306-46122-4|pages=317–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Theories to explain the apparent implied egalitarianism of Neolithic (and Paleolithic) societies have arisen, notably the [[Marxist]] concept of [[primitive communism]].

==Shelter==
[[File:Neolithic house.JPG|thumb|Reconstruction of Neolithic house in [[Tuzla]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]]]
The shelter of the early people changed dramatically from the [[paleolithic]] to the neolithic era. In the paleolithic, people did not normally live in permanent constructions. In the neolithic, mud brick houses started appearing that were coated with plaster.&lt;ref name=firstcity&gt;[http://www2.bc.edu/~mcdonadh/course/huyuk.html Shane, Orrin C. III, and Mine Küçuk. &quot;The World's First City.&quot;] Archaeology 51.2 (1998): 43–47.&lt;/ref&gt; The growth of agriculture made permanent houses possible. Doorways were made on the roof, with ladders positioned both on the inside and outside of the houses.&lt;ref name=firstcity/&gt; The roof was supported by beams from the inside. The rough ground was covered by platforms, mats, and skins on which residents slept. {{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

==Farming==
{{Main|Neolithic Revolution}}
[[File:CucuteniAgriculture.JPG|thumb|left|A [[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture]] [[antler|deer antler]] [[Ard (plough)|plough]]]]
[[File:HMB Essen und Kochgerät Jungsteinzeit.jpg|thumb|left|Food and cooking items retrieved at a European Neolithic site: [[millstone]]s, charred bread, grains and small apples, a clay cooking pot, and containers made of antlers and wood]]
A significant and far-reaching shift in human [[subsistence]] and lifestyle was to be brought about in areas where crop [[farm]]ing and cultivation were first developed: the previous reliance on an essentially [[nomad]]ic [[hunter-gatherer]] [[list of subsistence techniques|subsistence technique]] or [[Transhumance|pastoral transhumance]] was at first supplemented, and then increasingly replaced by, a reliance upon the foods produced from cultivated lands. These developments are also believed to have greatly encouraged the growth of settlements, since it may be supposed that the increased need to spend more time and labor in tending crop fields required more localized dwellings. This trend would continue into the Bronze Age, eventually giving rise to [[town]]s, and later [[city|cities]] and [[State (polity)|state]] whose larger populations could be sustained by the increased productivity from cultivated lands.

The profound differences in human interactions and subsistence methods associated with the onset of early agricultural practices in the Neolithic have been called the ''[[Neolithic Revolution]]'', a term [[neologism|coined]] in the 1920s by the Australian archaeologist [[Vere Gordon Childe]].

One potential benefit of the development and increasing sophistication of farming technology was the possibility of producing surplus crop yields, in other words, food supplies in excess of the immediate needs of the community. Surpluses could be stored for later use, or possibly traded for other necessities or luxuries. Agricultural life afforded securities that pastoral life could not, and sedentary farming populations grew faster than nomadic.

However, early farmers were also adversely affected in times of [[famine]], such as may be caused by [[drought]] or [[pest control|pests]]. In instances where agriculture had become the predominant way of life, the sensitivity to these shortages could be particularly acute, affecting agrarian populations to an extent that otherwise may not have been routinely experienced by prior hunter-gatherer communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bahn, Paul 1996&quot;/&gt; Nevertheless, agrarian communities generally proved successful, and their growth and the expansion of territory under cultivation continued.

Another significant change undergone by many of these newly-agrarian communities was one of [[diet (nutrition)|diet]]. Pre-agrarian diets varied by region, season, available local plant and animal resources and degree of pastoralism and hunting. Post-agrarian diet was restricted to a limited package of successfully cultivated cereal grains, plants and to a variable extent domesticated animals and animal products. Supplementation of diet by hunting and gathering was to variable degrees precluded by the increase in population above the carrying capacity of the land and a high sedentary local population concentration. In some cultures, there would have been a significant shift toward increased starch and plant protein. The relative nutritional benefits and drawbacks of these dietary changes and their overall impact on early societal development is still debated.

In addition, increased population density, decreased population mobility, increased continuous proximity to domesticated animals, and continuous occupation of comparatively population-dense sites would have altered [[sanitation]] needs and patterns of [[disease]].

==Technology==
Neolithic peoples were skilled farmers, manufacturing a range of tools necessary for the tending, harvesting and processing of crops (such as [[sickle]] blades and [[grinding stone]]s) and food production (e.g. [[pottery]], bone implements). They were also skilled manufacturers of a range of other types of stone tools and ornaments, including [[projectile point]]s, [[bead]]s, and [[statuette]]s. But what allowed forest clearance on a large scale was the polished [[stone axe]] above all other tools. Together with the [[adze]], fashioning wood for shelter, structures and [[canoe]]s for example, this enabled them to exploit their newly-won farmland.

Neolithic peoples in the Levant, Anatolia, Syria, northern Mesopotamia and [[Central Asia]] were also accomplished builders, utilizing mud-brick to construct houses and villages. At [[Çatalhöyük|Çatal höyük]], houses were [[plaster]]ed and painted with elaborate scenes of humans and animals. In [[Europe]], [[Neolithic long house|long houses]] built from [[wattle and daub]] were constructed. Elaborate [[tomb]]s were built for the dead. These tombs are particularly numerous in [[Ireland]], where there are many thousand still in existence. Neolithic people in the [[British Isles]] built [[long barrow]]s and [[chamber tomb]]s for their dead and [[causewayed camp]]s, henges, flint mines and [[cursus]] monuments. It was also important to figure out ways of preserving food for future months, such as fashioning relatively airtight containers, and using substances like [[salt]] as preservatives.

The peoples of the [[Americas]] and the [[Pacific]] mostly retained the Neolithic level of tool [[technology]] until the time of European contact. Exceptions include copper [[hatchet]]s and [[spear]]heads in the [[Great Lakes (North America)|Great Lakes]] region.

==Clothing==
Most clothing appears to have been made of animal skins, as indicated by finds of large numbers of bone and antler pins which are ideal for fastening leather, but not cloth. However, [[woolen|wool]] cloth and [[linen]] might have become available during the British Neolithic, as suggested by finds of perforated stones which (depending on size) may have served as [[Spindle (textiles)|spindle whorls]] or [[loom]] weights. The clothing worn in the Neolithic Age might be similar to that worn by [[Ötzi the Iceman]], although he was not British and not Neolithic (since he belonged to the later [[Copper age]]).

==Early settlements==
[[File:tripolye hut.jpg|thumb|right|Reconstruction of a Cucuteni-Trypillian hut, in the Tripillian Museum, Ukraine.]]

Neolithic [[List of archaeological sites|human settlements]] include:
* [[Göbekli Tepe]] in Turkey, c. 11,000–9000 BC
* [[Tell Qaramel]] in [[Syria]], 10,700–9400 BC
* [[Franchthi Cave]] in [[Greece]], epipalaeolithic (c. 10,000 BC) settlement, reoccupied between 7500–6000 BC
* [[Lahuradewa]] in [[India]], 7000 BC&lt;ref name=&quot;Thanjan2011&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Davis K. Thanjan|title=Pebbles|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=P9BLBh7XqnkC&amp;pg=PA31|accessdate=4 July 2011|date=12 January 2011|publisher=Bookstand Publishing|isbn=978-1-58909-817-6|pages=31–}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jericho]] in [[West bank]], Neolithic from around 8350 BC, arising from the earlier [[Epipaleolithic]] [[Natufian culture]]
* [[Nevali Cori]] in [[Turkey]], c. 8000 BC
* [[Ganj Dareh]] in [[Iran]], c. 7000 BC
[[File:CatalHoyukSouthArea.JPG|thumb|right|The Archaeological Site of [[Çatal Hüyük]] in the [[Konya]] Plain in [[Turkey]]|200px]]
* [[Çatalhöyük]] in [[Turkey]], 7500 BC
* [[Pengtoushan culture]] in [[China]], 7500 – 6100 BC
* [['Ain Ghazal]] in [[Jordan]], 7250–5000 BC
* [[Chogha Bonut]] in [[Iran]], 7200 BC
* [[Jhusi]] in [[India]], 7100 BC
* [[Karanovo, Sliven Province|Karanovo]] in Bulgaria, 6200 BC
* [[Petnica]] in [[Serbia]], 6000 BC
* [[Sesklo]] in [[Greece]], 6850 BC (with a ±660 year margin of error)
* [[Dispilio Tablet|Dispilio]] in [[Greece]], c. 5500 BC
*[[Padah-Lin Caves]] in [[Burma]], c. 6000 BC
* [[Jiahu]] in [[China]], 7000 to 5800 BC
* [[Mehrgarh]] in [[Pakistan]], 7000 BC
* [[Knossus]] on [[Crete]], c. 7000 BC
* [[Porodin]] in [[Republic of Macedonia]], 6500 BC&lt;ref name=eliznik&gt;[http://www.eliznik.org.uk/EastEurope/History/balkans-map/developed-neolithic.htm#nogo Developed Neolithic period, 5500 BC]. Eliznik.org.uk. Retrieved on 2011-12-03.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Vrshnik (Anzabegovo) in [[Republic of Macedonia]], 6500 BC&lt;ref name=eliznik/&gt;
* [[Pizzo di Bodi]] (Varese), [[Lombardy]] in [[Italy]], c. 6320 ±80 BC
* Sammardenchia in Friuli, [[Italy]], c. 6050 ±90 BC,
* [[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture]], 5500–2750 BC, in [[Ukraine]], [[Moldova]] and [[Romania]] first salt works
* [[Tabon Cave|Tabon Cave Complex]] in [[Quezon, Palawan]], [[Philippines]] 5000 – 2000 BC {{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}
* [[Hemudu culture]] in [[China]], 5000 – 4500 BC, large scale rice plantation
* around 2000 settlements of [[Trypillian culture]], 5400 – 2800 BC
* [[Tell Zeidan]] in northern Syria, from about 5500 to 4000 BC.
* The [[Megalithic Temples of Malta|Megalithic Temples]] of [[Malta]], 3600 BC
* [[Knap of Howar]] and [[Skara Brae]], [[Orkney]], [[Prehistoric Scotland|Scotland]], from 3500 BC and 3100 BC respectively
* [[Brú na Bóinne]] in [[Ireland]], c. 3500 BC
* [[Lough Gur]] in [[Ireland]] from around 3000 BC
* [[Lajia]] in [[China]], 2000 BC

The world's oldest known engineered [[roadway]], the [[Sweet Track]] in [[England]], dates from 3800 BC and the world's oldest free-standing structure is the neolithic temple of [[Ggantija]] in [[Gozo]], [[Malta]].

==List of cultures and sites==
[[File:Orkney Skara Brae.jpg|thumb|right|280px|Excavated dwellings at [[Skara Brae]] (Orkney, Scotland), Europe's most complete Neolithic village]]
''Note: Dates are very approximate, and are only given for a rough estimate; consult each culture for specific pie time periods.''

'''Early Neolithic''' &lt;br /&gt;
''Periodization: [[Neolithic#Neolithic 1 – Pre-Pottery Neolithic A (PPNA)|The Levant]]: 10,000 to 8500 BC; [[Mesolithic Europe|Europe]]: 5000 to 4000 BC; Elsewhere: varies greatly, depending on region.''
*[[Beixin culture]]
*[[Cishan culture]]
*[[Dudeşti culture]]
*[[Franchthi Cave|Franchthi Cave people]]
**Earliest European Neolithic site: 20th to 3rd millennium BC
*[[Sesclo|Sesclo village culture]]
*[[Starčevo–Kőrös–Criş culture|Starcevo-Criş culture]]
**(also known as the [[Starčevo culture|Starčevo-Körös-Criş culture]])

'''Middle Neolithic''' &lt;br /&gt;
''Periodization: [[Neolithic#Neolithic 2 – Pre-Pottery Neolithic B (PPNB)|The Levant]]: 8500 to 6500 BC; [[Neolithic Europe|Europe]]: 4000 to 3500 BC; Elsewhere: varies greatly, depending on region.''
*[[Baodun culture]]
**[[Jinsha (archaeological site)|Jinsha settlement]] and [[Sanxingdui]] mound.
*[[Cardium Pottery|Cardium Pottery culture]]
*[[Comb Ceramic culture]]
*[[Corded Ware|Corded Ware culture]]
*[[Cortaillod culture]]
*[[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture]]
*[[Dadiwan culture]]
*[[Dawenkou culture]]
*[[Daxi culture]]
**[[Chengtoushan|Chengtoushan settlement]]
*[[Grooved ware people]]
**[[Skara Brae]], et al.
*[[Erlitou culture]]
**[[Xia Dynasty]]
*[[Ertebølle culture]]
*[[Hembury|Hembury culture]]
*[[Hemudu culture]]
*[[Hongshan culture]]
*[[Houli culture]]
*[[Horgen|Horgen culture]]
*[[Liangzhu culture]]
*[[Linear Pottery culture]]
**[[Goseck circle]], [[Circular ditches|et al.]]
*[[Longshan culture]]
*[[Majiabang culture]]
*[[Majiayao culture]]
*[[Peiligang culture]]
*[[Pengtoushan culture]]
*[[Pfyn culture]]
*[[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture|Precucuteni culture]]
*[[Qujialing culture]]
*[[Shijiahe culture]]
*[[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture|Trypillian culture]]
*[[Vinča culture]]
*[[Windmill Hill culture]]
**[[Stonehenge]]
*[[Xinglongwa culture]]
**[[Beifudi|Beifudi site]]
*[[Xinle culture]]
*[[Yangshao culture]]
**[[Banpo]] and [[Xishuipo]] settlements.
*[[Zhaobaogou culture]]

'''Later Neolithic''' &lt;br /&gt;
''[[Neolithic#Neolithic 3 – Pottery Neolithic (PN)|Periodization]]: 6500 to 4500 BC; [[Neolithic Europe|Europe]]: 3500 to 3000 BC; Elsewhere: varies greatly, depending on region.''

'''Eneolithic''' &lt;br /&gt;
''Periodization: [[Copper Age|Middle East]]: 4500 to 3300 BC; [[Chalcolithic Europe|Europe]]: 3000 to 1700 BC; [[Metallurgy in pre-Columbian Mesoamerica|Elsewhere]]: varies greatly, depending on region. In the Americas, the Eneolithic ended as late as the 1800s for some people.''
*[[Beaker culture]]
*[[Cucuteni-Trypillian culture]]
*[[Funnelbeaker culture]]
*[[Gaudo Culture]]
*[[Lengyel culture]]
*[[Varna culture]]

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break|width=50%}}
*[[Megalith]]
*[[Neolithic Europe]]
*[[Neolithic Revolution]]
*[[Neolithic religion]]
*[[Neolithic tomb]]
{{col-break|width=50%}}
*[[Ötzi the Iceman]]
*[[Synoptic table of the principal old world prehistoric cultures]]
*[[Paleolithic]]
*[[Rock art of the Djelfa region]]
{{col-end}}

==Footnotes==
&lt;!--This article uses the Cite.php citation mechanism. If you would like more information on how to add references to this article, please see http://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Extension:Cite/Cite.php --&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
* {{Cite book
| publisher = Wiley-Blackwell
| isbn = 0-631-20566-7
| last = Bellwood
| first = Peter
| title = First Farmers: The Origins of Agricultural Societies
| year = 2004
}}
*Pedersen, Hilthart (2008), &quot;Die jüngere Steinzeit auf Bornholm&quot;, München &amp; Ravensburg. ISBN 978-3-638-94559-2
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
{{Commons|Neolithic|Neolithic}}
*{{cite web|last=McNamara|first=John|title=Neolithic Period|publisher=World Museum of Man|year=2005|url=http://worldmuseumofman.org/neolithic1.htm|accessdate=2008-04-14}}
*{{cite news|last=Rincon|first=Paul|title=Brutal lives of Stone Age Britons|publisher=BBC News|date= 11 May 2006|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/4757861.stm|accessdate=2008-04-14}}
*[http://anthropology.rice.edu/WorkArea/linkit.aspx?LinkIdentifier=id&amp;ItemID=472 Current Directions in West African Prehistory – McIntosh &amp; McIntosh (1983)]
*[http://www.omniglot.com/writing/vinca.htm Vincha Neolithic Script]
*[http://ubprehistoire.free.fr/index.html UB Préhistoire — Enseignements sur le Néolithique]

{{Prehistoric technology}}

[[Category:Neolithic| ]]
[[Category:Holocene]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

{{Link FA|ast}}
[[als:Neolithikum]]
[[ar:عصر حجري حديث]]
[[an:Neolitico]]
[[ast:Neolíticu]]
[[az:Neolit dövrü]]
[[bn:নব্য প্রস্তর যুগ]]
[[ba:Неолит]]
[[be:Неаліт]]
[[be-x-old:Нэаліт]]
[[bg:Новокаменна епоха]]
[[bs:Neolitik]]
[[br:Neolitik]]
[[ca:Neolític]]
[[cv:Неолит]]
[[cs:Neolit]]
[[cy:Oes Newydd y Cerrig]]
[[da:Yngre stenalder]]
[[de:Jungsteinzeit]]
[[et:Neoliitikum]]
[[el:Νεολιθική περίοδος]]
[[es:Neolítico]]
[[eo:Neolitiko]]
[[eu:Neolito]]
[[fa:دوران نوسنگی]]
[[fr:Néolithique]]
[[fy:Neolitikum]]
[[ga:Neoiliteach]]
[[gl:Neolítico]]
[[ko:신석기 시대]]
[[hi:नवपाषाण युग (नियोलिथिक)]]
[[hr:Mlađe kameno doba]]
[[id:Neolitik]]
[[is:Nýsteinöld]]
[[it:Neolitico]]
[[he:תקופת האבן החדשה]]
[[jv:Neolitik]]
[[kn:ನವಶಿಲಾಯುಗ]]
[[ka:ნეოლითის ხანა]]
[[kk:Неолит]]
[[ky:Неолит]]
[[la:Neolithicum]]
[[lv:Neolīts]]
[[lt:Neolitas]]
[[hu:Újkőkorszak]]
[[mk:Неолит]]
[[ml:നവീനശിലായുഗം]]
[[mt:Neolitiku]]
[[ms:Zaman Neolitik]]
[[my:ကျောက်ခေတ်သစ်]]
[[nl:Neolithicum]]
[[nds-nl:Neolithicum]]
[[ja:新石器時代]]
[[no:Neolittisk tid]]
[[nn:Yngre steinalder]]
[[oc:Neolitic]]
[[pnb:نیولتھک]]
[[pl:Neolit]]
[[pt:Neolítico]]
[[ro:Neolitic]]
[[ru:Неолит]]
[[sq:Neoliti]]
[[scn:Neuliticu]]
[[simple:Neolithic]]
[[sk:Neolit]]
[[sl:Neolitik]]
[[sr:Неолит]]
[[sh:Neolit]]
[[su:Neolitikum]]
[[fi:Neoliittinen kausi]]
[[sv:Neolitikum]]
[[ta:புதிய கற்காலம்]]
[[th:ยุคหินใหม่]]
[[tr:Cilalı Taş Devri]]
[[uk:Неоліт]]
[[ur:جدید زمانہ پتھر]]
[[ug:يېڭى تاش قۇرال دەۋرى]]
[[vi:Thời đại đồ đá mới]]
[[vls:Neolithicum]]
[[war:Neolitiko]]
[[zh-yue:新石器時代]]
[[zh:新石器时代]]</text>
      <sha1>eytusscdebsmeup1x3r0kwqhuqaaqfv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
