<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ninth Crusade</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>635111</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516705985</id>
      <parentid>516705976</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-08T21:04:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/76.177.24.207|76.177.24.207]] to version by Braincricket. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1258927) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13224">{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{Infobox Military Conflict
|conflict=Ninth Crusade
|partof=the [[Crusades]]
|image=[[Image:EdwardICrusadeMap.jpg|200px]]
|caption=Operations during the Ninth Crusade.
|date=1271–1272
|place=[[Near East]]
|result=End of Crusades in the Middle East.&lt;br&gt;Beginning of the end for Crusader States in the Levant.
|combatant1= [[Crusaders]] and [[Mongols]]
*[[File:France Ancient.svg|15px]] [[France in the Middle Ages|Kingdom of France]]
**[[File:Image-Blason Sicile Péninsulaire.svg|15px]] [[Anjou]]
*[[Image:Armoiries Chypre.svg|15px]] [[Kingdom of Cyprus]]
**[[Image:Armoiries de Jérusalem.svg|15px]] [[Kingdom of Jerusalem|Jerusalem]]
*[[Image:Armoiries Bohémond VI d'Antioche.svg|15px]] [[Principality of Antioch]]
**[[Image:Armoiries Bohémond VI d'Antioche.svg|15px]] [[County of Tripoli|Tripoli]]
*[[Image:England COA.svg|15px]] [[Kingdom of England]]
*[[Image:Il-Khanate Flag.svg|15px]] [[Ilkhanate]]
**[[Image:Armoiries Héthoumides.svg|15px]] [[Armenian Kingdom of Cilicia|Armenian Cilicia]]
|combatant2= [[Mamluks]]
*[[Image:Mameluke Flag.svg|15px]] [[Bahri dynasty|Bahris]]
|combatant3=
|commander1=[[Image:Image-Blason Sicile Péninsulaire.svg|15px]] [[Charles I of Naples|Charles I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Image:Armoiries Chypre.svg|15px]] [[Hugh III of Cyprus]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Image:England COA.svg|15px]] [[Edward I of England|Prince Edward]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Image:Armoiries Bohémond VI d'Antioche.svg|15px]] [[Bohemond VI of Antioch|Bohemond VI]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Image:Il-Khanate Flag.svg|15px]] [[Abaqa Khan]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Image:Armoiries Héthoumides.svg|15px]] [[Leo II, King of Armenia|Leo II]]
|commander2=[[Image:Mameluke Flag.svg|15px]] [[Baibars]]
|commander3=
|strength1=60,000&lt;ref&gt;''The Gospel in All Lands'', Methodist Episcopal Church Missionary Society,  Methodist Episcopal Church, p. 262&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2=Unknown
|strength3=
|casualties1=Unknown
|casualties2=Unknown
|casualties3=
|notes=
}}
{{Crusade}}

The '''Ninth Crusade''', which is sometimes grouped with the [[Eighth Crusade]], is commonly considered to be the last major [[Middle Ages|medieval]] [[Crusade]] to the [[Holy Land]]. It took place in 1271–1272.

[[Louis IX of France]]'s failure to capture [[Tunis]] in the [[Eighth Crusade]] led [[Edward I of England|Prince Edward of England]] to sail to [[Acre, Israel|Acre]] in what is known as the Ninth Crusade. The Ninth Crusade saw several impressive victories for Edward over [[Baibars]]. Ultimately the Crusade did not so much fail as withdraw, since Edward had pressing concerns at home and felt unable to resolve the internal conflicts within the remnant Outremer territories. It is arguable that the Crusading spirit was nearly &quot;extinct,&quot; by this period as well.&lt;ref&gt;''A Manual of Church History'', Albert Henry Newman, p. 461&lt;/ref&gt; It also foreshadowed the imminent collapse of the last remaining crusader strongholds along the Mediterranean coast.

==Prologue==
Following the Mamluk victory over the [[Mongols]] in 1260 at the [[Battle of Ain Jalut]] by [[Qutuz]] and his general [[Baibars]], Qutuz was assassinated, leaving Baibars to claim the sultanate for himself. As Sultan, Baibars proceeded to attack the Christian crusaders at [[Arsuf]], [[Athlith]], [[Haifa]], [[Safad]], [[Jaffa]], [[Ashkelon|Ascalon]], and [[Caesarea]]. As the Crusader fortress cities fell one by one, the Christians sought help from Europe, but assistance was slow in coming. 

In 1268 Baibars captured [[Antioch]], thereby destroying the last remnant of the [[Principality of Antioch]], securing the Mamluk northern front and threatening the small Crusader [[County of Tripoli]].

[[Louis IX of France]], having already organized a large crusader army with the intent of attacking Egypt, was diverted instead to [[Tunis]], where Louis himself died in 1270. [[Edward I of England|Prince Edward]] of England arrived in Tunis too late to contribute to the remainder of the crusade in Tunis. Instead, he continued on his way to the Holy Land to assist [[Bohemund VI of Antioch|Bohemund VI]], Prince of Antioch and Count of Tripoli, against the Mamluk threat to [[Tripoli]] and the remnant of the [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]].

==Crusader operations in the Holy Land==
It was decided that Edward along with Louis' brother [[Charles of Anjou]] would take their forces onward to Acre, capital of the remnant of the Kingdom of Jerusalem and the final objective of Baibars' campaign. The army of Edward and Charles arrived in 1271, just as Baibars was besieging [[Tripoli, Lebanon|Tripoli]], which as the last remaining territory of the County of Tripoli was full of tens of thousands of Christian refugees. From their bases in Cyprus and Acre, Edward and Charles managed to attack Baibars' interior lines and break the siege. 

As soon as Edward arrived in Acre, he made some attempts to form a [[Franco-Mongol alliance]], sending an embassy to the [[Mongol Empire|Mongol]] ruler of [[Persia]] [[Abagha]], an enemy of the Muslims. The embassy was led by Reginald Rossel, Godefroi of Waus and John of Parker, and its mission was to obtain military support from the Mongols.&lt;ref&gt;''Histoire des Croisades III'', René Grousset, p. 653. Grousset quotes a contemporary source (&quot;Eracles&quot;, p. 461) explaining that Edward contacted the Mongols &quot;por querre secors&quot; (&quot;To ask for help&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt; In an answer dated September 4, 1271, Abagha agreed for cooperation and asked at what date the concerted attack on the Mamluks should take place.

The arrival of the additional forces from England and Hugh III of Cyprus, under the command of Edward's younger brother [[Edmund Crouchback, 1st Earl of Lancaster|Edmund]] emboldened Edward, who engaged in a raid on the town of [[Qaqun]]. At the end of October 1271, a small force of Mongols arrived in Syria and ravaged the land from [[Aleppo]] southward. However Abagha, occupied by other conflicts in [[Turkestan]] could only send 10,000 Mongol horsemen under general [[Samagar]] from the occupation army in [[Great Seljuq Empire|Seljuk]] [[Anatolia]], plus auxiliary Seljukid troops. Despite the relatively small force though, their arrival still triggered an exodus of Muslim populations (who remembered the previous campaigns of [[Kithuqa]]) as far south as [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;''Histoire des Croisades III'', René Grousset, p. 653.&lt;/ref&gt; 

But the Mongols did not stay, and when the Mamluk leader Baibars mounted a counter-offensive from Egypt on November 12, the Mongols had already retreated beyond the [[Euphrates]].

In the interim, Baibars came to suspect there would be a combined land-sea attack on Egypt. Feeling his position sufficiently threatened, he endeavoured to head off such a maneuver by building a fleet. Having finished construction of the fleet, rather than attack the Crusader army directly, Baibars attempted to land on [[Cyprus]] in 1271, hoping to draw [[Hugh III of Cyprus]] (the nominal [[King of Jerusalem]]) and his fleet out of Acre, with the objective of conquering the island and leaving Edward and the crusader army isolated in the Holy Land. However, in the ensuing naval campaign the fleet was destroyed and Baibars' armies were forced back.  

Following this victory, Edward realized that to create a force capable of retaking Jerusalem it would be necessary to end the internal unrest within the Christian state, and so he mediated between Hugh and his unenthusiastic [[knight]]s from the [[Ibelin]] family of Cyprus.  In parallel to the mediation, [[Edward I of England|Prince Edward]] and King Hugh began negotiating a truce with Sultan Baibars; a 10 year, 10 month and 10 day agreement was reached in May 1272, at Caesarea. Almost immediately Prince Edmund departed for England, while Edward remained to see if the treaty would hold. The following month, Baibars attempted to assassinate Edward. Edward killed the assassin but received a festering wound from a poisoned dagger in the process, further delaying Edward's own departure. In September 1272, Edward departed Acre for Sicily and, while recuperating on the island, he first received news of the death of his son John, and then a few months later news of the death of his [[Henry III of England|father]].  In 1273 Edward started his homeward journey via Italy, Gascony and Paris. Edward finally reached England in the summer of 1274, and was crowned King of England on August 19, 1274.

==Aftermath==
&lt;!-- removed link to deleted image April 8, 2009 [[Image:Beibars.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Artistic illustration of [[Baibars]] in battle]] --&gt;
[[Image:Last Crusader.jpg|thumb|200px|right|[[Romantic art|Romantic]] portrayal of the &quot;Last Crusader&quot;. Increasing Muslim victories and Christian defeats led to the end of the Crusades.]]
Edward had been accompanied by Theobald Visconti, who became [[Pope Gregory X]] in 1271. Gregory called for a new crusade at the [[Council of Lyons]] in 1274, but nothing came of this. Meanwhile, new fissures arose within the Christian states when [[Charles I of Sicily|Charles of Anjou]] took advantage of a dispute between [[Hugh III of Cyprus|Hugh III]], the [[Knights Templar]], and the [[Venice|Venetians]] in order to bring the remaining Christian state under his control. Having bought [[Mary of Antioch]]'s claims to the [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]], he attacked Hugh III, causing a [[civil war]] within the rump kingdom. In 1277, [[Roger of San Severino]] captured Acre for Charles. 

Although the internecine war within the crusaders' ranks was debilitating, it provided the opportunity for a single commander to take control of the crusade in the person of Charles. However, this hope was dashed when Venice suggested a crusade be called not against the Mamluks but against [[Constantinople]], where [[Michael VIII]] had recently re-established the [[Byzantine Empire]] and driven out the Venetians. Pope Gregory would not have supported such an attack, but in 1281 [[Pope Martin IV]] assented to it; the ensuing fiasco helped lead to the [[Sicilian Vespers]] on March 31, 1282, instigated by Michael VIII, and Charles was forced to return home. This was the last expedition launched against the Byzantines in Europe or the Muslims in the Holy Land. 

The remaining nine years saw an increase in demands from the [[Mamluks]], including tribute, as well as increased persecution of pilgrims, all in contravention of the [[treaty|truce]].  In 1289, Sultan [[Qalawun]] gathered a large army and invested the remnants of the county of Tripoli, ultimately laying siege to the capital and taking it after a bloody assault. The attack on Tripoli however was particularly devastating to the [[Mamluks]] as the Christian resistance reached fanatical proportions and Qalawun lost his eldest and most able son in the campaign. He waited another two years to regather his strength.  

In 1291, a group of pilgrims from Acre came under attack and in retaliation killed nineteen Muslim merchants in a Syrian [[Caravan (travellers)|caravan]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}} Qalawun demanded they pay an extraordinary amount in compensation. When no reply came, the Sultan used it as a pretext to [[Siege of Acre (1291)|besiege Acre]] and finish off the last independent [[Crusader state]] occupying the Holy Land. Qalawun died during the siege,{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}} leaving Khalil, the sole surviving member of his family, as Mamluk Sultan. With Acre seized, the Crusader States ceased to exist. The center of power of the Crusaders was moved northwards to [[Tartous|Tortosa]] and eventually offshore to Cyprus. In 1299, a Mongol army led by [[Ghazan Khan]] led a series of successful raids against the Mamluks in an [[Battle of Wadi al-Khazandar|area ]] northeast of [[Homs]] to as far south as [[Gaza]]. He finally withdrew from Syria in 1300.  The Mongols and their [[Armenian Kingdom of Cilicia|Cilician Armenian]] allies led another campaign to recapture [[Syria]], but were soon defeated by the [[Mamluks]] at the [[Battle of Shaqhab]] in 1303.  The last remaining foothold on the [[Holy Land]], [[Arwad|Ruad Island]], was [[Fall of Ruad|lost]]  in 1302/1303. The period of the [[Crusades]] to the [[Holy Land]] was over, 208 years after [[Pope Urban II]] called for the first of these holy wars.

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*&quot;Histoire des Croisades III&quot;, René Grousset

&lt;!--The German system for numbering the crusades is different--&gt;

[[Category:Ninth Crusade|*]]

[[ar:الحملة الصليبية التاسعة]]
[[bn:নবম ক্রুসেড]]
[[ca:Novena Croada]]
[[cs:Devátá křížová výprava]]
[[de:Kreuzzug des Prinzen Eduard]]
[[et:Üheksas ristisõda]]
[[es:Novena Cruzada]]
[[eu:Bederatzigarren Gurutzada]]
[[fr:Neuvième croisade]]
[[it:Nona crociata]]
[[he:מסע הצלב התשיעי]]
[[mk:Деветта крстоносна војна]]
[[arz:الحمله الصليبيه التاسعه]]
[[ms:Perang Salib Kesembilan]]
[[nl:Negende Kruistocht]]
[[no:Det niende korstog]]
[[pt:Nona Cruzada]]
[[sk:Deviata križiacka výprava]]
[[sr:Девети крсташки рат]]
[[fi:Yhdeksäs ristiretki]]
[[th:สงครามครูเสดครั้งที่ 9]]
[[tr:Dokuzuncu Haçlı Seferi]]
[[uk:Дев'ятий хрестовий похід]]
[[zh:第九次十字军东征]]</text>
      <sha1>at7d6rp6ohuffb32uv9ynvx65h8hne7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
