<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Oral history</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22687</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521783895</id>
      <parentid>519670679</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T05:48:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Download</username>
        <id>6912407</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Czech oral history */gen fixes, [[WP:AWB/T|typos fixed]]: so called → so-called using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29930">{{Globalize|date=April 2012}}
'''Oral history''' is the collection and study of [[history|historical]] information about individuals, families, important events, or everyday life using audiotapes, videotapes, or transcriptions of planned [[interview]]s. These interviews are conducted with people who participated in or observed past events and whose memories and perceptions of these are to be preserved as an aural record for future generations. Oral history strives to obtain information from different perspectives, and most of these cannot be found in written sources. ''Oral history'' also refers to information gathered in this manner and to a written work (published or unpublished) based on such data, often preserved in [[archives]] and large [[libraries]].&lt;ref name=&quot;columbia&quot;&gt;[http://encyclopedia2.thefreedictionary.com/oral+history Article on ''oral history'' from the Columbia Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc-clio.com/ODLIS/odlis_o.aspx#oralhistory Definition of ''oral history'' from the Online Dictionary for Library and Information Science]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yourdictionary.com/oral-history Definition of ''oral history'' from the American Heritage Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/oral+history Definition of ''oral history'' from the Oxford Online Dictionaries]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The term is sometimes used in a more general sense to refer to any information about past events that people who experienced them tell anybody else,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.macmillandictionary.com/dictionary/american/oral-history Definition of ''oral history'' from the Macmillan Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/british/oral-history Definition of ''oral history'' from the Cambridge Advanced Learner's Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; but professional [[historian]]s usually consider this to be [[oral tradition]]. However, as the Columbia Encyclopedia&lt;ref name=&quot;columbia&quot;/&gt; explains: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;Primitive societies have long relied on oral tradition to preserve a record of the past in the absence of written histories. In Western society, the use of oral material goes back to the early Greek historians [[Herodotus]] and [[Thucydides]], both of whom made extensive use of oral reports from witnesses. The modern concept of oral history was developed in the 1940s by [[Allan Nevins]] and his associates at Columbia University.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Oral history in modern times==
Oral history has become an international movement in historical research. Oral historians in different countries have approached the collection, analysis, and dissemination of oral history in different modes. However, it should also be noted that there are many ways of creating oral histories and carrying out the study of oral history even within individual national contexts.

In the words of the Columbia Encyclopedia:&lt;ref name=&quot;columbia&quot;/&gt; 
&lt;blockquote&gt;The discipline came into its own in the 1960s and early 70s when inexpensive tape recorders were available to document such rising social movements as civil rights, feminism, and anti–Vietnam War protest. Authors such as [[Studs Terkel]], [[Alex Haley]], and [[Oscar Lewis]] have employed oral history in their books, many of which are largely based on interviews. In another important example of the genre, a massive archive covering the oral history of American music has been compiled at the [[Yale School of Music]]. By the end of the 20th cent. oral history had become a respected discipline in many colleges and universities. At that time the Italian historian [[Alessandro Portelli]] and his associates began to study the role that memory itself, whether accurate or faulty, plays in the themes and structures of oral history. Their published work has since become standard material in the field, and many oral historians now include in their research the study of the subjective memory of the persons they interview.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Oral history in Britain and Northern Ireland==

Since the early 1970s, oral history in Britain has grown from being a method in folklore studies (see for example the work of the [[School of Scottish Studies]] in the 1950s) to becoming a key component in community histories. Oral history continues to be an important means by which non-academics can actively participate in the compilation and study of history. However, practitioners across a wide range of academic disciplines have also developed the method into a way of recording, understanding, and archiving narrated memories. Influences have included women's history and labour history.

In Britain the [[Oral History Society]] has played a key role in facilitating and developing the use of oral history. A more complete account of the history of oral history in Britain and Northern Ireland can be found at &quot;Making Oral History&quot; on the [[Institute of Historical Research]]'s website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.ac.uk/makinghistory/resources/articles/oral_history.html|title=Making Oral History|publisher=[[Institute of Historical Research]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During 1998 and 1999, forty BBC local radio stations recorded personal oral histories from a broad cross-section of the population for the series The Century Speaks. The result was 640 half-hour radio documentaries, broadcast in the final weeks of the millennium, and one of the largest single oral history collections in Europe, the Millennium Memory Bank (MMB). The interview based recordings are held by the British Library Sounds' in the oral history collection.&lt;ref&gt;http://sounds.bl.uk/Oral-history&lt;/ref&gt;

In one of the largest memory project anywhere, The BBC in 2003-6 invited its audiences to send in recollections of the homefront in the Second World War. It put 47,000 of the recollections online, along with 15,000 photographs.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/ BBC, &quot;WW2 People's War&quot; (2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern oral history in the United States==

===Elite studies===
In 1948, [[Alan Nevins]], a [[Columbia University]] historian, established the Columbia Oral History Research Office, with a mission of recording, transcribing, and preserving oral history interviews. In 1967, American oral historians founded the [[Oral History Association]], and British oral historians founded the Oral History Society in 1969. There are now numerous national organizations and an [[International Oral History Association]], which hold workshops and conferences and publish newsletters and journals devoted to oral history theory and practices. 

Oral history began with a focus on national leaders,&lt;ref&gt;Ritchie 2010 considers Senators and other top leaders.&lt;/ref&gt; but has expanded to include groups representing the entire population.  Scientists, for example, have been covered in numerous oral history projects.  Doel (2003) discusses the use of oral interviews by scholars as primary sources, He lists major oral history projects in the history of science begun after 1950. Oral histories, he concludes, can augment the biographies of scientists and help spotlight how their social origins influenced their research. Doel acknowledges the common concerns historians have regarding the validity of oral history accounts. He identifies studies that used oral histories successfully to provide critical and unique insight into otherwise obscure subjects, such as the role scientists played in shaping US policy after World War II. Interviews furthermore can provide road maps for researching archives, and can even serve as a fail-safe resource when written documents have been lost or destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Doel, Ronald E. &quot;Oral History of American Science: a Forty-year Review.&quot; ''History of Science'' 2003 41(4): 349-378.&lt;/ref&gt;  Launius (2003) shows the huge size and complexity of the The National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) oral history program since 1959. NASA systematically documented its operations through oral histories. They can help to explore broader issues regarding the evolution of a major federal agency. The collection consists primarily of oral histories conducted by scholars working on books about the agency. Since 1996, however, the collection has also included oral histories of senior NASA administrators and officials, astronauts, and project managers, part of a broader project to document the lives of key agency individuals. Launius emphasizes efforts to include such less-well-known groups within the agency as the Astrobiology Program, and to collect the oral histories of women in NASA.&lt;ref&gt;Roger D. Launius, &quot;'We Can Lick Gravity, but Sometimes the Paperwork Is Overwhelming': NASA , Oral History, and the Contemporary Past.&quot; ''Oral History Review'' 2003 30(2): 111-128.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Folklore roots and ordinary people===
Contemporary oral history involves recording or transcribing eyewitness accounts of historical events. Some [[anthropologists]] started collecting recordings (at first especially of [[Native American mythology|Native American folklore]]) on phonograph cylinders in the late 19th century. In the 1930s, the [[Federal Writers' Project]]—part of the [[Works Progress Administration]] (WPA)—sent out interviewers to collect accounts from various groups, including surviving witnesses of the Civil War, slavery, and other major historical events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lcweb2.loc.gov/ammem/wpaintro/wpahome.html|title=American Life Histories|work=[[Federal Writers' Project|WPA Writers' Project 1936–1940]]|publisher=[[Library of Congress]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Library of Congress]] also began recording traditional American music and folklore onto [[acetate discs]]. With the development of audio tape recordings after World War II, the task of oral historians became easier. 

In 1946, [[David P. Boder]], a professor of psychology at the [[Illinois Institute of Technology]] in Chicago, traveled to Europe to record long interviews with &quot;displaced persons&quot;—most of them Holocaust survivors. Using the first device capable of capturing hours of audio—the [[wire recording|wire recorder]]—Boder came back with the first recorded Holocaust testimonials and in all likelihood the first recorded oral histories of significant length.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Marziali|first=Carl|date=26 October 2001|url=http://www.thisamericanlife.org/Radio_Episode.aspx?sched=895|title=Mr. Boder Vanishes|work=[[This American Life]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many state and local historical societies have oral history programs. Sinclair Kopp (2002) report on the Oregon Historical Society's program. It began in 1976 with the hiring of Charles Digregorio, who had studied at Columbia with Nevins. Thousands of sound recordings, reel-to-reel tapes, transcriptions, and radio broadcasts have made it one of the largest collections of oral history on the Pacific Coast. In addition to political figures and prominent businessmen, the Oregon Historical Society has done interviews with minorities, women, farmers, and other ordinary citizens, who have contributed extraordinary stories reflecting the state's cultural and social heritage. Hill (2004) encourages oral history projects in high school courses. She demonstrates a lesson plan that encourages the study of local community history through interviews. By studying grassroots activism and the lived experiences of its participants, her high school students came to appreciate how African Americans worked to end Jim Crow laws in the 1950s.

Naison (2005) describes the Bronx African American History Project, an oral community history project developed by the Bronx County Historical Society. Its goal was to document the histories of black working- and middle-class residents of the South Bronx neighborhood of Morrisania in New York City since the 1940s.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Naison, The Bronx African American History Project.&quot; ''OAH Newsletter'' 2005 33(3): 1, 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Oral history in Post-communist countries ==

=== Czech oral history ===
Czech oral history (likewise the oral history applied in others so called post communist countries) did not experience that building period in 1960s and 1970s, partly at the beginning in 1980s, where in the world is spoken about social movement more than a method. With knowledge of the thing I can say that this development was in its beginning probably necessary and well- founded. Understandable (in its beginning) was also some political activism. In 1970s and 1980s in Czech Republic (similarly in other countries of so-called socialist block) was OH absolutely unknown. History and historians did not know about it. Isolate attempts to invite witnesses for scientific project ended without accomplishment (ideological task, guiltlessness of method, imperfect technique, etc.). Hypothetically, if the OH had been discovered earlier for Czech historians, it could have acted positive and surely combative activist role (as A. Freund. P. Thomson and many others speak about it) like in other authoritative regimes. It could have aimed at enquiry of proscribe groups: dissent or prisoners of conscience. To cognate research or any other allusion about just mentioned groups of fellow – citizen was until 1989 totally avoided by communist historiography. Oral History was for the first time used in the mid 1990s but we can speak about some kind of progress for past six years, as Sean Field speaks about it, when it has transformed from disregard and criticized to possibly respect. In last three years one can even speak about boom of Oral History.&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.iisg.nl/esshc/programme.asp?selyear=12&amp;pap=10270&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2000, The Oral History Center (COH) at the Institute of Contemporary History, Academy of Sciences, Czech Republic (AV ČR)  was established.&lt;ref name=&quot;coh.usd.cas.cz&quot;&gt;http://www.coh.usd.cas.cz/en/about-us&lt;/ref&gt;

====Czech oral history projects====
''Students in the Period of the Fall of Communism - Life Stories“'', published as the book One Hundred Student Revolutions by M. Vaněk and M. Otáhal(1999), was funded by the Grant Agency AV ČR.
The project ''„Political Elites and Dissidents during the Period of So-called Normalization - Historical Interviews“'' was funded by the GA ČR and resulted in two publications: Victors? Vanquished(2005), a two-volume collection of 50 exemplary interviews; and a compilation of original interpretive essays entitled The Powerful?! or Helpless?! These publications demonstrate that oral history can contribute greatly to our understanding of many interesting fields in human lives and history itself, such as the motives behind the dissidents' activities, the formation of opposition groups, communication between dissidents and state representatives and the emergence of ex-communist elites and their decision-making processes. 
''„An Investigation into Czech Society during the „Normalization“ Era: Biographic Narratives of Workers and the Intelligentsia“'' (funded by the Grant Agency AV ČR). The book of interpretations (called &quot;Ordinary People...?!&quot;)(2009). 
All oral history centers in the Czech Republic emphasize educational activities (seminars, lectures, conferences), archiving and maintaining interview collections, and providing consultations to those interested in the method.&lt;ref name=&quot;coh.usd.cas.cz&quot;/&gt;

==Methods==
Historians, folklorists, anthropologists, sociologists, journalists, linguists, and many others employ some form of interviewing in their research.  Although multi-disciplinary, oral historians have promoted common ethics and standards of practice, most importantly the attaining of the “informed consent” of those being interviewed.  Usually this is achieved through a [[deed of gift]], which also establishes copyright ownership that is critical for publication and archival preservation.

Oral historians generally prefer to ask open-ended questions and avoid leading questions that encourage people to say what they think the interviewer wants them to say.  Some interviews are “life reviews”, conducted with people at the end of their careers. Other interviews focus on a specific period or a specific event in people's lives, such as in the case of war veterans or survivors of a hurricane.  

Feldstein (2004) considers oral history to be akin to journalism, Both are committed to uncovering truths and compiling narratives about people, places, and events. Felstein says each could benefit from adopting techniques from the other. Journalism could benefit by emulating the exhaustive and nuanced research methodologies used by oral historians. The practice of oral historians could be enhanced by utilizing the more sophisticated interviewing techniques employed by journalists, in particular, the use of adversarial encounters as a tactic for obtaining information from a respondent.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Feldstein, &quot;Kissing Cousins: Journalism and Oral History.&quot; ''Oral History Review'' 2004 31(1): 1-22&lt;/ref&gt; 

The first oral history archives focused on interviews with prominent politicians, diplomats, military officers, and business leaders. By the 1960s and '70s, interviewing began to be employed more often when historians investigated [[history from below]].  Whatever the field or focus of a project, oral historians attempt to record the memories of many different people when researching a given event.  Interviewing a single person provides a single perspective. Individuals may misremember events or distort their account for personal reasons.  By interviewing widely, oral historians seek points of agreement among many different sources, and also record the complexity of the issues.  The nature of memory—both individual and community—is as much a part of the practice of oral history as are the stories collected.

==Legal interpretation and relationship to historical truth==

In 1997 the [[Supreme Court of Canada]], in the [[Delgamuukw v. British Columbia]] trial, ruled that oral histories were just as important as written testimony. Of oral histories, it said &quot;that they are tangential to the ultimate purpose of the fact-finding process at trial – the determination of the historical truth.&quot;

Writers who use oral history have often discussed its relationship to historical truth. [[Gilda O'Neill]] writes in ''Lost Voices'', an oral history of [[East End of London|East End]] hop-pickers: &quot;I began to worry. Were the women's, and my, memories true or were they just stories? I realised that I had no 'innocent' sources of evidence - facts. I had, instead, the stories and their tellers' reasons for remembering in their own particular ways.'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Gilda O'Neill|publisher=Arrow|title=Lost Voices|isbn=978-0-09-949836-0|page=146}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Duncan Barrett]], one of the co-authors of ''[[The Sugar Girls]]'' describes some of the perils of relying on oral history accounts: &quot;On two occasions, it became clear that a subject was trying to mislead us about what happened – telling a self-deprecating story in one interview, and then presenting a different, and more flattering, version of events when we tried to follow it up. [...] often our interviewees were keen to persuade us of a certain interpretation of the past, supporting broad, sweeping comments about historical change with specific stories from their lives.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.historyworkshop.org.uk/oral-history-creative-non-fiction-telling-the-lives-of-the-sugar-girls/ |title= Oral History &amp; Creative Non-Fiction: Telling the Lives of the Sugar Girls|publisher= History Workshop Online|date= 11 March 2012|accessdate=2012-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alessandro Portelli argues that oral history is valuable nevertheless: &quot;it tells us less about events as such than about their meaning [...] the unique and precious element which oral sources force upon the historian [...] is the speaker's subjectivity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Portelli |first1=Alessandro |title=The Peculiarities of Oral History |journal=History Workshop Journal |volume=No. 12(1) |issue=1981 |pages=96–107}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
National and international organizations promote scholarship in the field. The ''Oral History Review''&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.historycooperative.org/ohrindex.html home page]&lt;/ref&gt; is a scholarly journal begun in 1974. H-ORALHIST is an H-Net Discussion Network established in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.h-net.org/~oralhist/ homepage]&lt;/ref&gt; It works by email and knits together an international network of researchers interested in creating and using oral history. Its daily email reach 3400 subscribers with discussions of current projects, teaching methods, and the state of historiography in the field. H-ORALHIST is especially interested in methods of teaching oral history to graduate and undergraduate students in diverse settings. H-ORALHIST publishes syllabi, outlines, handouts, bibliographies, tables of contents of journals, guides to term papers, listings of new sources, library catalogs and archives, and reports on new software, datasets, and other materials. H-ORALHIST posts announcements of conferences, fellowships, and jobs. It also carries information about new books and commissions book reviews.

==See also==
* [[National Day of Listening]]
* [[Oral history preservation]]
* [[Oral tradition]]
* [[Regional Oral History Office]] (ROHO), [[Bancroft Library]], [[University of California, Berkeley]]
* [[Louie B. Nunn Center for Oral History]], [[University of Kentucky#Libraries|University of Kentucky Libraries]]
* [[Southern Oral History Program]], [[University of North Carolina]]
* [[StoryCorps]]

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

==Further reading==
* Vansina, Jan. &quot;Oral Tradition as History&quot; University of Wisconsin Press, 1985.
* {{cite book|editor1-last=Charlton|editor1-first=Thomas L.|editor2-first= Lois E.|editor2-last=Myers|editor3-first=Rebecca|editor3-last=Sharpless|title=History of Oral History: Foundations and Methodology|year=2007|isbn=978-0-7591-0230-9|publisher=[[Rowman &amp; Littlefield|AltaMira Press]]}}
* Doel, Ronald E. &quot;Oral History of American Science: a Forty-year Review.&quot; ''History of Science'' 2003 41(4): 349-378. Issn: 0073-2753 Fulltext: Ebsco
* Feldstein, Mark. &quot;Kissing Cousins: Journalism and Oral History.&quot; ''Oral History Review'' 2004 31(1): 1-22. Issn: 0094-0798 Fulltext: online at History Cooperative, University of California Journals, SwetsWise, and Ebsco
* Grele, Ronald J. et al. ''Envelopes of Sound: The Art of Oral History'' Praeger Publishers, 1991 [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=53518808 online edition]
* Hill, Iris Tillman. &quot;Community Stories: a Curriculum for High School Students.&quot; ''Magazine of History'' 2004 18(2): 43-45. Issn: 0882-228x Fulltext: in Ebsco
* Hoopes, James. ''Oral History: An Introduction for Students'' U of North Carolina Press, 1979. [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=6460621 online edition]
* Kelin, Daniel, II.  ''To Feel as Our Ancestors Did: Collecting and Performing Oral Histories.'' Heinemann, 2005. 200 pp.
* Launius, Roger D. &quot;'We Can Lick Gravity, but Sometimes the Paperwork Is Overwhelming': NASA , Oral History, and the Contemporary Past.&quot; ''Oral History Review'' 2003 30(2): 111-128. Issn: 0094-0798 Fulltext: in University of California Journals, Swetswise and Ebsco
* {{cite book|last=Leavy|first=Patricia|title=Oral History: Understanding Qualitative Research|year=2011|isbn=978-0-19-539509-9|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]}}
* Naison, Mark. &quot;The Bronx African American History Project.&quot; ''OAH Newsletter'' 2005 33(3): 1, 14. Issn: 1059-1125 Fulltext: at Oah Newsletter and Ebsco
* {{cite book|last=Ritchie|first=Donald A.|title=The Oxford Handbook of Oral History|year=2010|isbn=978-0-19-533955-0|publisher=Oxford University Press}}
* {{cite book|last1=Sommer|first1=Barbara W.|last2=Quinlan|first2=Mary Kay|title=The Oral History Manual|edition=2|year=2009|isbn=978-0-7591-1157-8|publisher=AltaMira Press}}
* Sinclair, Donna and Kopp, Peter. &quot;Voices of Oregon: Twenty-five Years of Professional Oral History at the Oregon Historical Society.&quot; ''Oregon Historical Quarterly'' 2002 103(2): 250-263. Issn: 0030-4727
* {{cite book|last=Stokes|first=Cynthia|title=Like It Was: A Complete Guide to Writing Oral History|year=2000|isbn=978-0-915924-12-7|publisher=[[Teachers &amp; Writers Collaborative]]}}
* Tomes, Nancy. &quot;Oral History In The History Of Medicine.&quot; ''Journal of American History''  1991 78(2): 607-617. ISSN: 0021-8723  online in Jstor and Ebsco

==External links==
* From the [[British Library]]:
:* [http://www.bl.uk/learning/histcitizen/foodstories/index.html Food Stories] - Food-related oral history recordings from the BL Sound Archive
:* [http://www.bl.uk/oralhistory Oral history collections and activities, including National Life Stories]
* From the [[Federal government of the United States|US Government]]:
:*[http://oralhistory.clerk.house.gov Oral History of the US House of Representatives]
:*[http://www.senate.gov/pagelayout/history/g_three_sections_with_teasers/oralhistory.htm US Senate Oral History Project]
* From [[Academia]]:
:* [http://ohda.matrix.msu.edu/ Oral History in the Digital Age] at [[Michigan State University]] (East Lansing, Michigan)
:* [http://digital.library.louisville.edu/cdm/landingpage/collection/afamoh/ African American Oral History Collection] at [[University of Louisville]] (Louisville, Kentucky)
:* [http://digital.library.louisville.edu/cdm/landingpage/collection/mazzoli/ Romano L. Mazzoli Oral History Collection] at [[University of Louisville]] (Louisville, Kentucky)
:*[http://library.uvic.ca/site/spcoll/military/miloral.html Canadian Military Oral History Collection] at [[University of Victoria]], Special Collections
:* [http://www.americancenturyproject.org American Century Oral History Project] at [[St. Andrew's Episcopal School (Maryland)|St. Andrew's Episcopal School]] is one of the largest pre-collegiate oral history projects and archives in the US
* [http://www.witness-to-war.org Over 600 oral histories of combat veterans], from the Witness to War Foundation (non-profit)
* [http://www.inthefirstperson.com In the First Person] - index of 2,500+ collections of international oral histories in English
* [http://www.ericdigests.org/1996-4/oral.htm Oral history in the teaching of US History]
* [http://graphics8.nytimes.com/packages/html/nyregion/20050812_WTC_GRAPHIC/met_WTC_histories_full_02.html NYC records from Sept. 11] - includes more than 12,000 pages of oral histories as told by 503 firefighters, paramedics, and emergency medical technicians
*[http://thehistorymakers.com The HistoryMakers]: African American Video Oral History Archive (non-profit)
*[http://www.firstpersonusa.org FirstPersonUSA.org] - a project of citizen historians concerned with preserving the memories of ordinary Americans
*[http://www.voicesthroughcorridors.co.uk Voices Through Corridors] - Oral History accounts of hospital patients and staff in Walsall

===World War II===
* [http://www.aptv.org/alabamaww2/index.asp WWII: Alabama Remembers] Documentary produced by [[Alabama Public Television]]
* [http://www.gpb.org/wwii Georgia World War II Oral History Project] Documentary produced by [[Georgia Public Broadcasting]]
* [http://video.idahoptv.org/video/2187192860 Idaho Homefront: WWII] Documentary produced by [[Idaho Public Television]]
* [http://www.iptv.org/iowastories/story.cfm/wwii/9626/iowas_wwii_stories_2007/video Iowa's WWII Stories] Documentary produced by [[Iowa Public Television]]
* [http://watch.opb.org/video/1249338083 Oregon at War] Oral History Documentary produced by [[Oregon Public Broadcasting]]
* [http://www.recollectionsofwwii.co.uk Recollections of WWII] - Directory of United Kingdom Oral History Collections Relating to WWII
* [http://www.prairiepublic.org/television/prairie-public-on-demand/world-war-ii-prairie-memories-episode-1 World War II Prairie Memories (1/3)] Oral History Documentary produced by [[Prairie Public Television]]

===Organizations===
* [http://www.h-net.org/~oralhist/  H-ORALHIST is an H-Net Discussion Network (or edited Blog) established in 2006]
* [http://storytelling.concordia.ca Centre for Oral History and Digital Storytelling] - [[Concordia University (Quebec)|Concordia University]]
* [http://www.acoh.com.au The Australian Centre for Oral History]
* [http://www.ohaa.net.au/ Oral History Association of Australia]
* [http://www.ihtp.cnrs.fr/ Institut d'histoire du temps présent] {{fr}}
* [http://cord.nhb.gov.sg/cord/public/internetSearch/ Oral History Centre (Singapore)]

===Technical===
* [http://www.oralhistory.org/technology/audio_basics/ Digital Audio and Portable Recorders: The Basics] by Doug Boyd
* [http://www.oralhistory.org/do-oral-history/principles-and-practices/ General principles and best practices for oral history]
* [http://www.fmomo.org Dédalo Project] - Open software platform for management of intangible cultural heritage and oral history
* [http://www.le.ac.uk/emoha/training.html Advice on how to conduct oral history interviewing] from the East Midlands Oral History Archive
* [http://www.attendonline.com/Testimony/testimony.html Testimony software] from the Australian Centre for Oral History
* [http://www.bl.uk/reshelp/findhelprestype/sound/anaudio/manual.html The manual of analogue restoration techniques] by Peter Copeland is designed to aid audio engineers and audio archivists, and is available via the British Library Sound Archive

[[Category:Oral communication]]
[[Category:Historiography]]
[[Category:Oral history| ]]

[[be-x-old:Вусная гіcторыя]]
[[cs:Orální historie]]
[[de:Oral History]]
[[es:Historia oral]]
[[eo:Buŝa historio]]
[[fa:تاریخ شفاهی]]
[[he:היסטוריה שבעל פה]]
[[lb:Oral History]]
[[nl:Mondelinge geschiedenis]]
[[ja:オーラル・ヒストリー]]
[[pl:Historia mówiona]]
[[pt:História Oral]]
[[ru:Устная история]]
[[simple:Oral history]]
[[sl:Ustni zgodovinski viri]]
[[su:Sajarah lisan]]
[[fi:Muistitietohistoria]]
[[th:ประวัติศาสตร์บอกเล่า]]
[[uk:Усна історія]]
[[zh:口述歷史]]</text>
      <sha1>79daklupbfc2gxu8v5aq89bbgvuj1o6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
