<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Partitions of Poland</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43794</id>
    <restrictions>move=:edit=</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>520864585</id>
      <parentid>520679624</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T07:28:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hedviberit</username>
        <id>10296339</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35921">[[File:Partitions of Poland.png|thumb|The three partitions of the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]]]]
[[File:Allegory of the 1st partition of Poland crop.jpg|thumb|Allegory of the [[First Partition of Poland|1st partition]] of [[Poland]], showing [[Catherine II of Russia]] (left), [[Joseph II of Austria]] and [[Frederick the Great of Prussia]] (right) quarelling over their territorial seizures]]
[[File:Alegoria Umarlej Polski.jpg|thumb|[[Włodzimierz Tetmajer]], ''Allegory of Dead Poland'', St. Nicholas Cathedral, [[Kalisz]]]]
The '''Partitions of Poland''' or '''Partitions of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth''' – three [[partition (politics)|partitions]] which took place in the second half of the 18th century and ended the existence of the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] ({{lang-pl|Rzeczpospolita Obojga Narodów}}; {{lang-lt|Abiejų Tautų Respublika}}), resulting in the elimination of sovereign [[Poland]] for 123 years. The partitions were perpetrated by the [[Russian Empire]], the [[Kingdom of Prussia]] and [[Habsburg Monarchy|Habsburg Austria]], which divided up the Commonwealth lands among themselves progressively in the process of territorial seizures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robert Bideleux, Ian Jeffries. ''A History of Eastern Europe: Crisis and Change.'' Routledge: 1998 p.156.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Judy Batt, Kataryna Wolczuk. ''Region, State and Identity in Central and Eastern Europe. ''Routledge: 2002, p.153.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nancy Sinkoff. &quot;Out of the Shtetl: Making Jews Modern in the Polish Borderlands.&quot; ''Society of Biblical Literature'': 2004, p.271.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;republika.pl&quot;&gt;[http://www.republika.pl/unpack/1/dok02b.html  &quot;Polish Facts and Figures&quot; at Republika.pl]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[First Partition of Poland]], which the Poles proved incapable of resisting, was decided on August 5, 1772. Two decades later, Russian and Prussian troops entered Poland again and the [[Second Partition of Poland|Second Partition]] was signed on January 23, 1793. Austria did not participate in the Second Partition. The [[Third Partition of Poland]] took place on October 24, 1795, as soon as the Polish [[Kościuszko Uprising]] was defeated. With this partition, the independent Polish state ceased to exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot;/&gt;

In English, the term &quot;Partitions of Poland&quot; is sometimes used geographically as [[toponymy]], to mean the three parts (sectors, or provinces) that the partitioning powers divided Poland into, i.e.: the [[Austrian partition]], the [[Prussian partition]] and the [[Russian partition]]. In Polish, on the other hand, there are two separate words for the two meanings. The consecutive acts of dividing or partitioning of Poland are referred to as ''rozbiór'' (plural: ''rozbiory''), while the term ''zabór'' (pl. ''zabory'') means each part of the Commonwealth seized in 1772–1795 and turned into a new province of either Imperial Russia, Prussia or Austria. In Polish historiography, the term [[#&quot;Fourth Partition&quot;|&quot;Fourth Partition of Poland&quot;]] has also been used, in reference to any subsequent annexation of Polish lands by foreign invaders. The term &quot;Fourth Partition&quot; in a temporal sense can also mean the diaspora communities that played important political role in reestablishing the Polish sovereign state after 1918.

== History ==
=== Prelude ===
[[File:Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth in 1772.PNG|266px|thumb|right|The [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] in 1772]]

During the reign of [[Władysław IV Vasa|Władysław IV]] (1632–48), the ''[[liberum veto]]'' had evolved. This policy of parliamentary procedure was based on the assumption of the political equality of every &quot;gentleman&quot;, with the corollary that unanimous consent was needed for all measures&lt;!-- source: (EB.) --&gt;. A single [[member of parliament]]'s belief that a measure was injurious to his own constituency (usually simply his own estate), even after the act had already been approved, became enough to strike the act. It became increasingly difficult to get action taken. The ''liberum veto'' also provided openings for foreign diplomats to get their ways, through bribing nobles to exercise it. &lt;!-- (Encyclopaedia Britannica.) --&gt; Thus, one could characterise Poland–Lithuania in its final period (mid-18th century) before the partitions as already in anarchy and not a completely sovereign state. Alternatively, one might be tempted to visualize it almost as a [[vassal state]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;/&gt; or in modern terms, a [[Russian Empire|Russian]] [[satellite state]], with Russian [[tsar]]s effectively choosing Polish kings. This applies particularly to the last Commonwealth King [[Stanisław August Poniatowski]], who for some time had been a lover of Russian Empress [[Catherine II of Russia|Catherine the Great]].

In 1730 the neighbours of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth ([[Rzeczpospolita]]), namely Prussia, Austria and Russia, signed a secret agreement to maintain the ''status quo'': specifically, to ensure that the Commonwealth laws would not change. Their alliance later became known in Poland as the &quot;[[Alliance of the Three Black Eagles]]&quot; (or ''Löwenwolde's Treaty''), because all three states used a black eagle as a state symbol (in contrast to the white eagle, a symbol of Poland). The Commonwealth had been forced to rely on Russia for protection against the rising [[Kingdom of Prussia]], while Prussia was demanding a slice of the northwest in order to unite its Western and Eastern portions, although this would leave the Commonwealth with a [[Baltic Sea|Baltic]] coast only in [[Latvia]] and [[Lithuania]]. &lt;!-- source EB --&gt; The Commonwealth could never be liquidated unless its longtime ally, [[Habsburg Monarchy|Austria]], allowed it,{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} and first Catherine had to use diplomacy to win Austria to her side.

The Commonwealth had remained neutral in the [[Seven Years' War]], though sympathizing with the alliance of France, [[Habsburg Monarchy|Austria]], and Russia, and allowing Russian troops access to its western lands as bases against [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussia]]. [[Frederick II of Prussia]] retaliated by ordering enough Polish currency counterfeited to severely affect the Polish economy. Through the [[szlachta|Polish nobles]] whom Russia controlled and the Russian Minister to Warsaw, ambassador and Prince [[Nicholas Repnin]], Empress Catherine the Great forced a constitution on the Commonwealth at the so-called [[Repnin Sejm]] of 1767, named after ambassador Repnin, who ''de facto'' dictated the terms of that Sejm (and who ordered the capture and exile  of some vocal opponents of his policies to [[Kaluga]] in Russian Empire.,&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;&gt;Hamish M. Scott, ''The Emergence of the Eastern Powers, 1756–1775'',
Cambridge University Press, 2001, ISBN 0-521-79269-X, [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN052179269X&amp;id=lc8EMD0JYUAC&amp;pg=PA182&amp;lpg=PA182&amp;dq=Repnin+Poland&amp;sig=VSKuu8NyPzm00Z6Rw1BNdGb0FP4 Gooble Print, p.181-182]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Steed,&quot;&gt;H. Wickham Steed, [http://historicaltextarchive.com/books.php?op=viewbook&amp;bookid=2&amp;cid=26 A Short History of Austria-Hungary and Poland], 1914, NCYCLOPÆDIA BRITANNICA, INC. Retrieved on 3 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugh Seton-Watson&quot;/&gt; including [[bishop]] [[Józef Andrzej Załuski]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Cas&quot;&gt;Various, ''The Story of My Life'', Penguin Classics, 2001, ISBN 0-14-043915-3, [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0140439153&amp;id=-0F8CRLDPv4C&amp;pg=PA528&amp;lpg=PA528&amp;dq=1773+Siberia+Sejm&amp;sig=LzpFpeGuq9h3dWWoWnEqqiUu0QY Google Print, p.528]&lt;/ref&gt; and others). This new constitution undid the reforms made in 1764 under [[Stanisław August Poniatowski|Stanisław II]]. The ''liberum veto'' and all the old abuses of the last one and a half centuries were guaranteed as unalterable parts of this new constitution (in the so-called ''[[cardinal laws]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugh Seton-Watson&quot;&gt;[[Hugh Seton-Watson]], ''The Russian Empire, 1801-1917'', Oxford University Press, 1967, ISBN 0-19-822152-5, [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0198221525&amp;id=40KbWNve4XkC&amp;pg=PA44&amp;lpg=PA44&amp;dq=repnin+polish+1768&amp;sig=mdyC3nxT-IkUW3NnZS79Xw_G4KU Google Print, p.44]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RB&quot;&gt;Richard Butterwick, ''Poland-Lithuania's Last King and English Culture: Stanisław August Poniatowski, 1732-1798'', Oxford University Press, 1998, ISBN 0-19-820701-8, [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0198207018&amp;id=ySzrq3JwjBEC&amp;pg=PA169&amp;lpg=PA169&amp;dq=Repnin+Poland&amp;sig=0Bxt16H98TPzTXWxvISsVeieWSw Google Print, p.169]&lt;/ref&gt;). Repnin also demanded religious freedom for the Protestant and [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox Christians]], and the resulting reaction among some of Poland's Roman Catholics, as well as the deep resentment of Russian intervention in the Commonwealth's domestic affairs, led to the War of the [[Bar Confederation|Confederation of Bar]]  from 1768–1772, where the Poles tried to expel Russian forces from Commonwealth territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugh Seton-Watson&quot;/&gt; The irregular and poorly commanded Polish forces had little chance in the face of the regular Russian army and suffered a major defeat. Adding to the chaos was a [[Ukraine|Ukrainian]] [[Cossack]] and peasant rebellion, the [[Koliyivschyna]], which erupted in 1768 and resulted in massacres of [[szlachta|noblemen]] (szlachta), Jews, [[Uniates]], and Catholic priests before it was put down by Polish and Russian troops.

In 1769 Austria annexed a small territory of [[Spisz]] and in 1770 - [[Nowy Sącz]] and [[Nowy Targ]]. These territories had been a bone of contention between Poland and [[Hungary]], which was a part of the Austrian crown lands.

=== First Partition ===
{{Main|First Partition of Poland}}
[[File:Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth 1773-1789.PNG|thumb|right|300px|Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth after the First Partition as a protectorate of Russian Empire 1773–1789]]

In February, 1772, the agreement of partition was signed in [[Vienna]]. Early in August the Russian, Prussian and Austrian troops simultaneously entered the Commonwealth and occupied the provinces agreed upon among themselves. On August 5, 1772, the occupation manifesto was issued, much to the consternation of a country too exhausted by the endeavors of the Confederation of Bar to offer successful resistance;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot;&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/466910/Partitions-of-Poland  &quot;Partitions of Poland.&quot;] (2008). [[Encyclopædia Britannica]] Online. Retrieved June 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; nonetheless several battles and sieges took place, as Polish troops refused to lay down their arms (most notably, in [[Tyniec]], [[Częstochowa]] and [[Kraków]]).

The partition treaty was ratified by its signatories on September 22, 1772. [[Frederick II of Prussia]] was elated with his success; Prussia took most of the Polish [[Royal Prussia]] that stood between its possessions in the [[Kingdom of Prussia]] and the [[Margraviate of Brandenburg]], taking Ermland ([[Warmia]]), [[Royal Prussia]] without the city of [[Gdańsk|Danzig]] (Gdańsk) (which in 1773 became a new [[Provinces of Prussia|province]] called [[West Prussia]]), northern areas of [[Greater Poland]] along the [[Noteć]] River (the [[Netze District]]), and parts of [[Kuyavia]], (also the Prussian city of [[Toruń|Thorn]] [Toruń]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot;/&gt; Despite token criticism of the partition from Austrian Empress [[Maria Theresa of Austria|Maria Theresa]], Austrian statesman [[Wenzel Anton Graf Kaunitz]] was proud of wresting as large a share as he did, with the rich salt mines of [[Bochnia]] and [[Wieliczka]]. To Austria fell Zator and Auschwitz ([[Oświęcim]]), part of [[Little Poland]] embracing parts of the counties of Kraków and Sandomir and the whole of Galicia, less the City of Kraków. [[Catherine II of Russia|Catherine of Russia]] was also very satisfied. By this &quot;diplomatic document&quot; Russia came into possession of that section of [[Livonia]] that had remained in Commonwealth control, and of [[Belarus]] embracing the counties of [[Vitebsk]], [[Polatsk|Polotsk]] and [[Mstislavl]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Rejtan Upadek Polski Matejko.jpg|thumb|300px|''Rejtan - The Fall of Poland'', oil on canvas by Jan Matejko, 1866, 282 x 487 cm, [[Royal Castle in Warsaw]].]]

By this partition the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] lost about 30% of its territory and half of its population,&lt;ref name=&quot;Brit&quot;/&gt; (four million people), of which a large portion had not been ethnically Polish. By seizing northwestern Poland, Prussia instantly gained control over 80% of the Commonwealth's total foreign trade. Through levying enormous customs duties, Prussia accelerated the collapse of the Commonwealth.

After having occupied their respective territories, the three partitioning powers demanded that King [[Stanisław August Poniatowski|Stanisław]] and the [[Sejm]] approve their action. When no help was forthcoming and the armies of the combined nations occupied Warsaw to compel by force of arms the calling of the assembly, no alternative could be chosen save passive submission to their will. The so-called [[Partition Sejm]], with Russian military forces threatening the opposition, on September 18, 1773, signed the treaty of cession, renouncing all claims of the Commonwealth to the occupied territories.

=== Second Partition ===
{{Main|Second Partition of Poland}}
[[File:Rzeczpospolita Rozbiory 2.png|thumb|300px|After the Second Partition (1793)]]

By 1790, on the political front, the First Polish Republic had deteriorated into such a helpless condition that it was successfully forced into an unnatural and ultimately deadly alliance with its enemy, Prussia. The [[Polish-Prussian alliance|Polish–Prussian Pact]] of 1790 was signed. The conditions of the Pact contributed greatly to the succeeding and final two partitions of Poland–Lithuania. The [[Constitution of May 3, 1791|May Constitution of 1791]] enfranchised the bourgeoisie, established the separation of the three branches of government, and eliminated the abuses of the [[Repnin Sejm]]. Those reforms prompted aggressive actions on the part of its neighbours, wary of the potential renaissance of the Commonwealth. Arguing that Poland had fallen prey to the radical [[Jacobinism]] then at high tide in France, Russian forces invaded the Commonwealth in 1792.

In the [[Polish–Russian War of 1792|War in Defense of the Constitution]], pro-Russian conservative Polish [[magnate]]s, the [[Targowica Confederation|Confederation of Targowica]], fought against Polish forces supporting the constitution, believing that Russians would help them restore the [[Golden Liberty]]. Abandoned by their Prussian allies, Polish pro-constitution forces, faced with Targowica units and the regular Russian army, were defeated. Prussia signed a treaty with Russia, agreeing that Polish reforms would be revoked and both countries would receive chunks of Commonwealth territory. In 1793, deputies to the [[Grodno Sejm]], last [[Sejm]] of the Commonwealth, in the presence of the Russian forces, agreed to Russian territorial demands. In the 2nd partition, Russia and Prussia helped themselves to enough more land so that only one-third of the 1772 population remained in Poland. Prussia named its newly gained province [[South Prussia]], with [[Poznań|Posen]] (and later Warsaw) as the capital of the new province.

Targowica confederates, who did not expect another partition, and the king, [[Stanisław August Poniatowski]], who joined them near the end, both lost much prestige and support. The reformers, on the other hand, were attracting increasing support, and in 1794 the [[Kościuszko Uprising]] began.

=== Third Partition ===
{{Main|Third Partition of Poland}}

Kosciuszko's ragtag insurgent armies won some initial successes, but they eventually fell before the superior forces of the Russian Empire. The partitioning powers, seeing the increasing unrest in the remaining Commonwealth, decided to solve the problem by erasing any independent Polish state from the map. On 24 October 1795 their representatives signed a treaty, dividing the remaining territories of the Commonwealth among their three countries.

The Russian part included 120,000&amp;nbsp;km² and 1.2 million people with [[Vilnius]], the Prussian part (new provinces of [[New East Prussia]] and [[New Silesia]]) 55,000&amp;nbsp;km² and 1 million people with Warsaw, and the Austrian 47,000&amp;nbsp;km² with 1.2 million and [[Lublin]] and Kraków.

===Summary===
{|class=wikitable
|-
|+ Cumulative division of the Commonwealth territory&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Norman |last=Davies |title=God's Playground. A History of Poland. The Origins to 1795 |volume=I |edition=revised | page=394 |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-19-925339-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! rowspan=2| Partition
! colspan=2| To Austria
! colspan=2| To Prussia
! colspan=2| To Russia
! colspan=2| Total annexed
! colspan=2| Total remaining
|-
! Area || % || Area  || % || Area  || % || Area  || % || Area  || %
|-
| bgcolor=#ffdddd | 1772 || {{convert|81900|km2|abbr=on}} || 11.17% || {{convert|36300|km2|abbr=on}} || 4.94% || {{convert|93000|km2|abbr=on}} || 12.68% || {{convert|211200|km2|abbr=on}} || 28.79% || {{convert|522300|km2|abbr=on}} || 71.20%
|-
| bgcolor=#ddddff | 1793 || — || — || {{convert|57100|km2|abbr=on}} ||7.78% || {{convert|250200|km2|abbr=on}} || 34.11% || {{convert|307300|km2|abbr=on}} || 41.89% || {{convert|215000|km2|abbr=on}} || 29.31%
|-
| bgcolor=#dddddd | 1795 || {{convert|47000|km2|abbr=on}} || 6.40% || {{convert|48000|km2|abbr=on}} || 6.55% || {{convert|120000|km2|abbr=on}} || 16.36% || {{convert|215000|km2|abbr=on}} || 29.31% || &lt;center&gt;'''None''' || &lt;center&gt;0%
|-
| '''Total''' || {{convert|128900|km2|abbr=on}} || '''14.57%''' || {{convert|141400|km2|abbr=on}} || '''19.27%''' || {{convert|463200|km2|abbr=on}} || '''66.16%''' || {{convert|733500|km2|abbr=on}} || '''100%''' ||  ||
|}
During the [[Napoleonic Wars]] and in their immediate aftermath the borders between partitioning powers shifted several times, changing the numbers seen in the preceding table. Following the [[Congress of Vienna]], Russia controlled 82% of the pre-1772 Commonwealth's territory (this includes its [[puppet state]] of [[Congress Poland]]), Austria 11%, and Prussia 7%.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Po przyłączeniu do obwodu białostockiego w 1807 roku do cesartwa i utworzeniu osiem lat później Królestwa Polskiego wnuk Katarzyny zjednoczył pod swoim berłem około 82% przedrozbiorowego terytorium Rzeczypospolitej (dla porównania - Austria 11%, Prusy 7%). &quot;[in:] Basil Kerski, Andrzej Stanisław Kowalczyk. Realiści z wyobraźnią. [[Uniwersytet Marii Curie-Skłodowskiej]]. 2007 page. 318 ISBN 978-83-227-2620-4&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
[[Image:Map of the partition of the Kingdom of Poland and the Grand Duchy of Lithuania from 1799.jpg|thumb|right|200px|&quot;A map of the Kingdom of Poland and the Grand Duchy of Lithuania including Samogitia and Curland divided according to their dismemberments with the Kingdom of Prussia&quot; from 1799.]]
The [[King of Poland]], [[Stanisław August Poniatowski]], under Russian military escort left for [[Grodno]] where he [[abdication|abdicated]] on November 25, 1795; next he left for [[Saint Petersburg]], Russia, where he would spend his remaining days. This act ensured that Russia would be seen as the most important of the partitioning powers.

As a result of the Partitions, Poles were forced to seek a change of status quo in Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;LRJohnson&quot;&gt;Lonnie R. Johnson, ''Central Europe: Enemies, Neighbors, Friends'', Oxford University Press, 1996, ISBN 0-19-510071-9, [http://books.google.com/books?id=e_m13Hk3AFEC&amp;pg=PA128&amp;ots=R9iFhEIGFV&amp;dq=%22partitions+of+Poland%22&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=Kw4fmCPIq_ATgIZQSAr0N6S5IlA#PPA129,M1 Google Print, p.127-128]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wandycz&quot;&gt;[[Piotr Stefan Wandycz]], ''The Price of Freedom: A History of East Central Europe from the Middle Ages to the Present'', Routledge (UK), 2001, ISBN 0-415-25491-4, [http://books.google.com/books?id=E8H08OiOouoC&amp;pg=PA133&amp;vq=%22percent+of+the+population%22&amp;dq=The+Price+of+Freedom:+A+History+of+East+Central+Europe+from+the+Middle+Ages+to+the+Present&amp;source=gbs_search_s Google Print, p.133]&lt;/ref&gt; Polish poets, politicians, noblemen, writers, artists, many of whom were forced to emigrate (thus the term [[Great Emigration]]) became the revolutionaries of the 19th century, as desire for freedom and liberty became one of the defining parts of [[Polish romanticism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WHZaw&quot;&gt;W. H. Zawadzki, ''A Man of Honour: Adam Czartoryski as a Statesman of Russia and Poland, 1795-1831'', Oxford University Press, 1993, ISBN 0-19-820303-9
[http://books.google.com/books?id=hwZASJRHjLIC&amp;pg=PA330&amp;dq=Polish+romantic+revolutionaries&amp;sig=kGTiU4OwRfAtsNi0kbNSbfODuBg Google Print, p.330]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;StefanAuer&quot;&gt;Stefan Auer, ''Liberal Nationalism in Central Europe'', Routledge, 2004, ISBN 0-415-31479-8, [http://books.google.com/books?id=b2IRot3UaQ0C&amp;pg=RA2-PA60&amp;ots=Xyinrgi2Jf&amp;dq=Polish+romantic+revolutionaries&amp;sig=aL7G6NL27FzH1 m-InI8OGK40XK0 Google Print, p.60]&lt;/ref&gt; Polish revolutionaries participated in uprisings in [[Prussia]], the [[Austrian Empire]] and [[Imperial Russia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DieterDowe&quot;&gt;Dieter Dowe, ''Europe in 1848: revolution and reform'', Berghahn Books, 2001, ISBN 1-57181-164-8, [http://books.google.com/books?id=B3qRFCn5CHoC&amp;pg=PA180&amp;dq=Polish+romantic+revolutionaries&amp;sig=cOYtkxH_i8lEX_0VUMEVhwGLVWs Google Print, p.180]&lt;br&gt;''While it is often and quite justifiably remarked that there was hardly a barricade or battlefield in Europe between 1830 and 1870 where no Poles were fighting, this is especially true for the revolution of 1848/1849.''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Polish legions (Napoleonic period)|Polish legions]] fought alongside [[Napoleon]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Carrib&quot;&gt;[[Jan Pachonski]], [[Reuel K. Wilson]]. ''Poland's Caribbean Tragedy: A Study of Polish Legions in the Haitian War of Independence 1802-1803''. East European Monographs, 1986. ISBN 0-88033-093-7. [http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/43a/038.html review and notes on the book].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NapSoc&quot;&gt;[[Elena I. Fedosova]], ''[http://www.napoleon-series.org/ins/scholarship98/c_polish.html Polish Projects of Napoleon Bonaparte]'', The Journal of the International Napoleonic Society, 1/2/98&lt;/ref&gt; and under the slogan of ''[[For our freedom and yours]]'' participated widely in the [[Spring of Nations]] (particularly [[Hungarian Revolution (1848)]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;DieterDowe&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fofay&quot;&gt;[http://www.globalprovince.com/ghl.htm Gods, Heroes, &amp; Legends]&lt;/ref&gt;

Poland would be briefly resurrected—if in a smaller frame—in 1807, when Napoleon set up the [[Duchy of Warsaw]]. After his defeat and the implementation of the [[Congress of Vienna]] treaty in 1815, the Russian-dominated [[Congress Poland|Congress Kingdom of Poland]] was created in its place. After the Congress, Russia gained a larger share of Poland (with [[Warsaw]]) and, after crushing [[November Uprising|an insurrection in 1831]], the Congress Kingdom's autonomy was abolished and Poles faced confiscation of property, deportation, forced military service, and the closure of their own universities. After the [[January Uprising|uprising of 1863]], [[Russification]] of Polish secondary schools was imposed and the [[literacy]] rate dropped dramatically. In the Austrian portion, Poles fared better, and were allowed to have representation in Parliament and to form their own universities, and Kraków and Lemberg (Lwów/Lviv) became centers of Polish culture and education. Meanwhile, Prussia [[Germanisation of Poles during Partitions|Germanized]] the entire school system of its Polish subjects, and had no more respect for Polish culture and institutions than the Russian Empire. In 1915 a [[client state]] of the [[German Empire]] and [[Austria-Hungary]] was proposed and accepted by the [[Central Powers]] of World War I: the [[Kingdom of Poland (1916–1918)|Regency Kingdom of Poland]]. After the end of World War I, the [[Central Powers]]' surrender to the [[Allies of World War I|Western Allies]], the chaos of the [[Russian Revolution of 1917|Russian Revolution]] and the [[Treaty of Versailles]] finally allowed and helped the restoration of Poland's full independence after 123 years.

== &quot;Fourth Partition&quot; ==
The terminology describing the partitions of Poland can be somewhat confusing, as the first three partitions are sometimes used to refer to the three dates on which Poland was divided (1772, 1793, and 1795) and sometimes to the three geographic divisions (the German or Prussian partition, Austrian partition, and Russian partition).  The term &quot;Fourth Partition&quot; has also been used in both a temporal and a spatial sense.

The term '''&quot;Fourth Partition of Poland&quot;''' may refer to any subsequent division of Polish lands, specifically:
* after the [[Napoleonic Era]], the 1815 division of the [[Duchy of Warsaw]] at the [[Congress of Vienna]];
* the 1832 incorporation of the &quot;[[Congress Poland|Congress Kingdom]]&quot; into Russia, and the 1846 incorporation of the [[Free City of Kraków|Republic of Kraków]] into Austria; and
* the 1939 division of Poland between [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] and the [[Soviet Union]] pursuant to the [[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brecher&quot;&gt;{{en icon}} {{cite book | author =Michael Brecher| coauthors =Jonathan Wilkenfeld | title =A Study of Crisis | year =1997 | pages =255 | publisher =University of Michigan Press| isbn=0-472-10806-9 | url =http://books.google.com/books?visbn=0-472-10806-9&amp;id=GjY7aV_6FPwC&amp;pg=PA255&amp;lpg=PA254&amp;dq=Zeligowski+state&amp;sig=uzmRepBmlI5W8pFsddP5qXsuBU0}}&lt;/ref&gt;
If one accepts more than one of those events as partitions, fifth and sixth partitions can be counted, but these terms are very rare.

The term &quot;Fourth Partition&quot; was also used in the 19th and 20th centuries to refer to diaspora communities who maintained a close interest in the project of regaining Polish independence.&lt;ref&gt;Cygan, Mary. 1998. “Inventing Polonia: Notions of Polish American identity, 1870-1990.” Prospects 23, pp. 209-246.&lt;/ref&gt;  Sometimes termed [[Polish diaspora|Polonia]], these expatriate communities often contributed funding and military support to the project of regaining the Polish nation-state.  Diaspora politics were deeply affected by developments in and around the homeland, and vice versa, for many decades.&lt;ref&gt;Lopata, Helena Znaniecka.  1994.  Polish Americans.  New Brunswick, NJ:  Transaction Publishers.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Historiography ==
As historian [[Norman Davies]] stated, because the [[Balance of power in international relations|balance of power equilibrium]] was observed, many contemporary observers accepted explanations of the &quot;enlightened apologists&quot; of the partitioning state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies:Europe&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dav283&quot;&gt;Norman Davies, God's Playground: A History of Poland in Two Volumes, Oxford University Press, 2005, ISBN 0-19-925339-0, [http://books.google.com/books?id=b912JnKpYTkC&amp;pg=RA1-PA283&amp;vq=the+coincidence+of+view&amp;dq=noble+paradise+peasant+hell+purgatory&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=Majcm4VX29AJBOcijElu99V9iBA Google Print, p.283]&lt;/ref&gt; 19th century historians from countries that carried out the partitions,  such as 19th century Russian scholar [[Sergey Solovyov]], and their 20th century followers, argued that partitions were justified, as the [[Commonwealth of Both Nations|Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] had degenerated to the point of being partitioned because the counterproductive principle of ''[[liberum veto]]'' made decision-making on divisive issues, such as a wide-scale social reform, virtually impossible. Solovyov specified the cultural, language and religious break between the supreme and lowest layers of the society in the east regions of the Commonwealth, where the [[Bielorussian]] and [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]] [[serf]] [[peasantry]] was Orthodox. Russian authors emphasized the historical connections between Belarus, Ukraine and Russia, as former parts of the medieval old Russian state where dynasty of [[Rurikid]]s reigned ([[Kievan Rus]]).&lt;ref&gt;E.g., [[Sergey Solovyov]]'s ''History of the Downfall of Poland'' (Moscow, 1863).&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, [[Nikolay Karamzin]] wrote: “Let the foreigners denounce the partition of Poland: we took what was ours.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://rys-arhipelag.ucoz.ru/publ/6-1-0-133 Н.М. Карамзин. Записка о древней и новой России в ее политическом и гражданском отношениях]&lt;/ref&gt; Russian historians often stressed that Russia annexed primarily Ukrainian and Belorussian provinces with Eastern Slavic inhabitants,&lt;ref&gt;Nicholas V. Riasanovsky, ''Old Russia, the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe'', American Slavic and East European Review, Vol. 11, No. 3. (Oct., 1952), pp. 171-188&lt;/ref&gt; although many [[Ruthenians]] were no more enthusiastic about Russia than about Poland, and ignoring ethnically Polish and Lithuanian territories also being annexed on a large scale (including the annexation of the undeniably Polish capital of [[Warsaw]]). A new justification for partitions arose with the [[Russian Enlightenment]], as Russian writers such as [[Gavrila Derzhavin]], [[Denis Fonvizin]], and [[Alexander Pushkin]] stressed degeneration of Catholic Poland and the need to &quot;civilize&quot; it by its neighbors.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakSarmatia&quot;&gt;[[Andrzej Nowak (historian)|Andrzej Nowak]], ''[http://www.ruf.rice.edu/~sarmatia/197/Nowak.html The Russo-Polish Historical Confrontation]'', The [[Sarmatian Review]], January 1997, Volume XVII, Number 1&lt;/ref&gt;

Nonetheless other 19th century contemporaries were much more skeptical; for example, British jurist Sir [[Robert Phillimore]] discussed the partition as a violation of [[international law]];&lt;ref name=&quot;&quot;&gt;Sir [[Robert Phillimore]], ''Commentaries Upon International Law'', 1854
T. &amp; J. W. Johnson, [http://books.google.com/books?id=JZIBAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA319&amp;dq=justification+%22partitions+of+Poland%22 Google Print, p.819]&lt;/ref&gt; German jurist [[Heinrich Bernhard Oppenheim]] presented similar views.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oppen&quot;&gt;Sharon Korman, ''The Right of Conquest: The Acquisition of Territory by Force in International Law and Practice'', Oxford University Press, 1996, ISBN 0-19-828007-6, [http://books.google.com/books?id=ueDO1dJyjrUC&amp;pg=PA101&amp;ots=0QRuhW-IOX&amp;dq=justification+%22partitions+of+Poland%22&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=qHZN8Xd2pXnHITuIR1csI5Rwj38 Google Print, p.101]&lt;/ref&gt; Other older historians who challenged such justifications for the Partitions included French historian [[Jules Michelet]], British historian and politician [[Thomas Babington Macaulay, 1st Baron Macaulay]], and [[Edmund Burke]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies:Europe&quot;&gt;[[Norman Davies]], ''Europe: A History'', Oxford University Press, 1996, ISBN 0-19-820171-0, [http://books.google.com/books?id=jrVW9W9eiYMC&amp;pg=PA842&amp;ots=NxIryuNZCG&amp;dq=%22partitions+of+Poland%22&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=6toNL7i7vYdMFu0HPyJStPqhHqM#PPA661,M1 Google Print, p.661]&lt;/ref&gt; Edmund Burke was alone in criticizing the immorality of this act.&lt;ref&gt;[http://original.britannica.com/eb/article-28200/Poland Poland The First Partition]&lt;/ref&gt;

More recent studies claim that partitions happened when the Commonwealth had been showing the beginning signs of a slow recovery and see the last two partitions as an answer to strengthening reforms in the Commonwealth and the potential threat they represented to its neighbours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wandycz&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies:Europe&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakSarmatia&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Army_Duchy&quot;&gt;[http://web2.airmail.net/napoleon/polish_army.html The Army of Grand Duchy of Warsaw]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buffalohist3May&quot;&gt;Hon. Carl L. Bucki, , University of Buffalo's History of Poland series, [http://info-poland.buffalo.edu/classroom/constitution.html The Constitution of May 3, 1791]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schroeder&quot;&gt;[[Paul W. Schroeder]], ''The Transformation of European Politics 1763–1848'', Oxford University Press, 1996, ISBN 0-19-820654-2, [http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=ISBN0198206542&amp;id=BS2z3iGPCigC&amp;pg=PA84&amp;lpg=PA84&amp;dq=Poland+%22constitutional+monarchy%22&amp;sig=VDTkfWKi5PAqIlCIKlGa6tha6lw Google print p.84]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GRussell&quot;&gt;Geoffrey Russell, ''The Making of Modern Europe, 1648-1780'', Routledge, 2003, ISBN 0-415-30155-6, [http://books.google.com/books?id=uxi8h67Siy4C&amp;pg=RA1-PA548&amp;dq=justifications+for+the+partitions+of+Poland&amp;sig=caQfD9rmFt4sWHAwscwzBcXG6wE Google Print, p.548]&lt;/ref&gt;

Several scholars focused on the economic motivations of the partitioning powers. [[Jerzy Czajewski]] wrote that the Russian peasants were escaping from Russia to the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]] in significant enough numbers to become a major concern for the Russian Government sufficient to play a role in its decision to partition the Commonwealth.&lt;ref name=&quot;promemoria&quot;&gt;[[Jerzy Czajewski]], ''&quot;Zbiegostwo ludności Rosji w granice Rzeczypospolitej&quot;'' (Russian population exodus into the Rzeczpospolita), Promemoria journal, October 2004 nr. (5/15), ISSN 1509-9091 , [http://www.promemoria.pl/arch/2004_15/2004_15.html Table of Content online], Polish language&lt;/ref&gt; Increasingly in the 18th century until the partitions solved this problem, Russian armies raided territories of the Commonwealth, officially to recover the escapees, but in fact kidnapping many locals.&lt;ref name=&quot;promemoria&quot;/&gt; [[Hajo Holborn]] noted that Prussia aimed to take control of the lucrative [[Baltic grain trade]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Holborn1982&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Hajo Holborn|title=A History of Modern Germany: 1648-1840|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=yeXYMV3CZ0IC&amp;pg=PA256|accessdate=16 February 2012|date=1 December 1982|publisher=Princeton University Press|isbn=978-0-691-00796-0|page=256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Trivia ==
The [[Ottoman Empire]] was the only country in the world that refused to accept the liquidation of the Republic of Poland as a result of partition and reserved a place in its diplomatic corps for an Ambassador of Lehistan (Poland).

The [[Italian National Anthem]] contains a reference to the partition.

== See also ==
* [[Three Emperors' Corner]]
* [[Ambassadors and envoys from Russia to Poland (1763–1794)]]
* [[Administrative division of Polish territories after partitions]]
* [http://pl.wikisource.org/wiki/Kategoria:Rozbiory_Polski Partitions of Poland, sources in Polish]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Partitions of Poland}}
*{{pl icon}} Krzysztof Wroński, [http://www.historycy.pl/Strony/Artykuly/2006%2001/Rozbiory.html Rozbiory Polski w XVIII w. &quot; ich uwarunkowania i skutki]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Partitions Of Poland}}
[[Category:Partitions of Poland|* 1]]

{{Link FA|de}}

[[ar:تقاسم بولندا]]
[[be:Рэч Паспалітая#Падзелы Рэчы Паспалітай]]
[[be-x-old:Падзелы Рэчы Паспалітай]]
[[bg:Подялби на Полша]]
[[ca:Repartiment de Polònia]]
[[cs:Dělení Polska]]
[[da:Polens tre delinger]]
[[de:Teilungen Polens]]
[[et:Poola jagamised]]
[[es:Particiones de Polonia]]
[[eo:Dispartigoj de Pollando-Litovio]]
[[fr:Partages de la Pologne]]
[[gl:Particións de Polonia]]
[[ko:폴란드 분할]]
[[hy:Լեհաստանի բաժանումներ]]
[[hr:Tri podjele Poljske]]
[[id:Pemisahan Polandia]]
[[is:Skiptingar Póllands]]
[[it:Spartizioni della Polonia]]
[[he:חלוקת פולין]]
[[ka:პოლონეთის დანაწილება]]
[[lv:Polijas dalīšanas]]
[[lt:Abiejų Tautų Respublikos padalijimai]]
[[hu:Lengyelország három felosztása]]
[[nl:Poolse Delingen]]
[[ja:ポーランド分割]]
[[no:Polens-Litauens tre delinger]]
[[pl:Rozbiory Polski]]
[[pt:Partilhas da Polônia]]
[[ro:Împărțirile Poloniei]]
[[ru:Разделы Речи Посполитой]]
[[simple:Partitions of Poland]]
[[sr:Поделе Пољске]]
[[fi:Puolan jaot]]
[[sv:Polens delningar]]
[[uk:Поділи Речі Посполитої]]
[[fiu-vro:Poola jagamisõq]]
[[war:Pagbahin han Polonya]]
[[zh:瓜分波蘭]]</text>
      <sha1>kluqcsv0wtp1w8iz99zuar1vkk1xmvr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
