<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Philosophy of history</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>177438</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522283841</id>
      <parentid>521956098</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T04:35:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrescoBot</username>
        <id>9021902</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/Links|link syntax/spacing]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="52344">{{for|the work by Hegel|Lectures on the Philosophy of History}}
{{Campaignbox Theories of History}}

The term '''philosophy of history''' refers to the theoretical aspect of history, in two senses. It is customary to distinguish '''critical philosophy of history''' from '''speculative philosophy of history'''. Critical philosophy of history is the &quot;theory&quot; aspect of the discipline of academic history, and deals with questions such as the nature of historical evidence, the degree to which objectivity is possible, etc. Speculative philosophy of history is an area of [[philosophy]] concerning the eventual significance, if any, of human history.&lt;ref&gt;E.g. W. H. Walsh, ''Introduction to the Philosophy of History'' (1951) ch.1 s.2.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, it speculates as to a possible [[teleology|teleological]] end to its development—that is, it asks if there is a design, purpose, directive principle, or finality in the processes of human history. Part of Marxism, for example, is speculative philosophy of history. Another example is the &quot;historiosophy&quot;, term coined by [[Gershom Scholem]] to describe his understanding of history and [[metaphysics]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/scholem/ Gershom Scholem], ''[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Though there is some overlap between the two aspects, they can usually be distinguished; modern professional historians tend to be skeptical about speculative philosophy of history.

Sometimes critical philosophy of history is included under [[historiography]]. Philosophy of history should not be confused with the [[history of philosophy]], which is the study of the development of philosophical ideas through time.

Speculative philosophy of history asks at least three basic questions:
* What is the proper unit for the study of the human past — the individual [[subject (philosophy)|subject]]? The [[family]], ''[[polis]]'' (&quot;city&quot;) or [[Sovereignty|sovereign]] territory? The [[civilization]] or culture? Or the whole of the human species?
* Are there any broad patterns that we can discern through the study of the human past?  Are there, for example, patterns of [[progress (history)|progress]]? Or cycles?  Is history deterministic? Or are there no patterns or cycles, and is human history random? Related to this is the study of individual agency and its impact in history, functioning within, or opposed to, larger trends and patterns.
* If history can indeed be said to progress, what is its ultimate direction? What (if any) is the driving force of that progress?

==Pre-modern history==
In the ''[[Poetics (Aristotle)|Poetics]]'', [[Aristotle]] argued that poetry is superior to history because poetry speaks of what ''must'' or ''should'' be [[truth|true]] rather than merely what ''is'' true. This reflects early axial concerns (good/bad, right/wrong) over metaphysical concerns for what &quot;is&quot;. Accordingly, classical historians felt a duty to ennoble the world. In keeping with philosophy of history, it is clear that their philosophy of value imposed upon their process of writing history—philosophy influenced method and hence product.

[[Herodotus]], considered by some as the first systematic historian, and, later, [[Plutarch]] freely invented [[discourse|speeches]] for their historical figures and chose their historical subjects with an eye toward [[moral]]ly improving the reader. History was supposed to teach one good examples to follow. The assumption that history &quot;should teach good examples&quot; influenced how history was written. Events of the past are just as likely to show bad examples that are not to be followed, but these historians would either not record them or re-interpret them to support their assumption of history's purpose. {{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

From the Classical period to the [[Renaissance]], historians alternated between focusing on subjects designed to improve mankind and on a devotion to fact. History was composed mainly of [[hagiography|hagiographies]] of [[sovereignty|monarchs]] or [[epic poetry]] describing [[hero]]ic gestures such as the [[Song of Roland]] about the [[Battle of Roncevaux Pass]], during [[Charlemagne]]'s first campaign to conquer the [[Iberian peninsula]].

In the 14th century, [[Ibn Khaldun]], who is considered one of the fathers of the philosophy of history, discussed his philosophy of history and society in detail in his ''[[Muqaddimah]]'' (1377). His work was a culmination of earlier works by [[Social theory#Sociology in medieval Islam|Sociology in medieval Islam]] in the spheres of [[Islamic ethics]], [[political science]], and [[Historiography of early Islam|historiography]], such as those of [[al-Farabi]], [[Ibn Miskawayh]], al-Dawwani, and [[Nasir al-Din al-Tusi]].&lt;ref name=Mowlana&gt;H. Mowlana (2001). &quot;Information in the Arab World&quot;, ''Cooperation South Journal'' '''1'''.&lt;/ref&gt; Ibn Khaldun often criticized &quot;idle [[superstition]] and uncritical acceptance of historical data.&quot; As a result, he introduced a [[scientific method]] to the philosophy of history, which was considered something &quot;new to his age,&quot; and he often referred to it as his &quot;new science,&quot; which is now associated with [[historiography]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Ibn Khaldun]], Franz Rosenthal, N. J. Dawood (1967), ''The Muqaddimah: An Introduction to History'', p. x, [[Princeton University Press]], ISBN 0-691-01754-9.&lt;/ref&gt; His [[historical method]] also laid the groundwork for the observation of the role of [[State (polity)|state]], [[communication]], [[propaganda]], and [[systematic bias]] in history.&lt;ref name=Mowlana/&gt;

By the 18th century, historians had turned toward a more [[positivist]] approach focusing on [[fact]] as much as possible, but still with an eye on telling histories that could instruct and improve. Starting with [[Fustel de Coullanges]] and [[Theodor Mommsen]], historical studies began to progress towards a more modern scientific form. In the [[Victorian era]], the debate in [[historiography]] thus was not so much whether history was intended to improve the [[Reading (process)|reader]], but what causes turned history and how historical change could be understood.

==Cyclical and linear history==
{{further|Social cycle theory}}

Given that human beings currently believe themselves to be the only Earthly creatures capable of abstract thought, a perception of time, and a manipulation of thought concerning the past, the future and the present, an inquiry into the nature of history is based in part on some working understanding of time in the human experience.

History (as contemporarily understood by Western thought), tends to follow an assumption of linear progression: &quot;this happened, and then that happened; that happened because this happened first.&quot;  This is in part a reflection of Western Thought's foundation of [[Causality|cause and effect]].

Most ancient cultures held a [[Religion and mythology|mythical]] conception of history and [[time]] that was not [[linear]]. They believed that history was cyclical with alternating Dark and Golden Ages. [[Plato]] called this the Great Year, and other Greeks called it an aeon or eon. Examples are the ancient doctrine of [[eternal return]], which existed in [[Ancient Egypt]], the [[Indian religions]], or the [[Ancient Greece|Greek]] [[Pythagoreans]]' and the [[Stoics]]' conceptions. In ''The Works and Days'', [[Hesiod]] described five [[Ages of Man]]: the [[Gold Age]], the [[Silver Age]], the [[Bronze Age]], the [[Greek Heroic Age|Heroic Age]] and the [[Iron Age]], which began with the [[Dorian invasion]]. Other scholars suggest there were just four ages, corresponding to the four metals, and the Heroic age was a description of the Bronze Age. A four age count would be in line with the Vedic or Hindu ages known as the Kali, Dwapara, Treta and Satya [[yuga]]s. The Greeks believed that just as mankind went through four stages of character during each rise and fall of history so did government. They considered [[democracy]] and [[monarchy]] as the healthy regimes of the higher ages; and [[oligarchy]] and [[tyranny]] as corrupted regimes common to the lower ages.

In the East [[Social cycle theory|cyclical theories of history]] were developed in China (as a theory of [[dynastic cycle]]) and in the Islamic world by [[Ibn Khaldun]].

The story of [[the Fall of Man]] from the [[Garden of Eden]] in Judaism and Christianity can be seen in a similar light, which would give the basis for [[theodicy|theodicies]], which attempts to reconcile the existence of evil in the world with the existence of God creating a global explanation of history with the belief in a [[Messianic Age]]. Theodicies claimed that history had a progressive direction leading to an [[eschatological]] end, such as the [[Apocalypse]], given by a superior power. [[Augustine of Hippo]], [[Thomas Aquinas]] or [[Jacques-Bénigne Bossuet|Bossuet]] in his ''Discourse On [[Universal History]]'' (1679) formulated such theodicies, but [[Leibniz]], who coined the term, was the most famous philosopher who created a theodicy. Leibniz based his explanation on the [[principle of sufficient reason]], which states that anything that happens, does happen for a specific reason. Thus, what man saw as evil, such as wars, epidemia and natural disasters, was in fact only an effect of his perception; if one adopted [[God's view]], this evil event in fact only took place in the larger divine plan. Hence, theodicies explained the necessity of evil as a relative element that forms part of a larger plan of history. Leibniz's principle of sufficient reason was not, however, a gesture of [[fatalism]]. Confronted with the antique [[problem of future contingents]], Leibniz invented the theory of &quot;[[compossible worlds]]&quot;, distinguishing two types of necessity, to cope with the problem of determinism.

During the [[Renaissance]], cyclical conceptions of history would become common, illustrated by the [[decline of the Roman Empire]]. [[Machiavelli]]'s ''[[Discourses on Livy]]'' (1513–1517) are an example. The notion of [[Empire]] contained in itself its ascendance and its [[decadence]], as in [[Edward Gibbon]]'s ''[[The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire]]'' (1776), which was placed on the ''[[Index Librorum Prohibitorum]]''.

[[Social cycle theory|Cyclical conceptions]] were maintained in the 19th and 20th centuries by authors such as [[Oswald Spengler]], [[Nikolay Danilevsky]], and [[Paul Kennedy]], who conceived the human past as a series of repetitive rises and falls. Spengler, like Butterfield was writing in reaction to the carnage of the first World War, believed that a civilization enters upon an era of [[Caesarism]] after its soul dies. He thought that the soul of the West was dead and Caesarism was about to begin.

The recent development of mathematical models of long-term secular sociodemographic cycles has revived interest in cyclical theories of history (see, for example, [http://www.eeb.uconn.edu/faculty/turchin/HistDyn.htm ''Historical Dynamics''] by [[Peter Turchin]], or ''Introduction to Social Macrodynamics''&lt;ref&gt;[http://urss.ru/cgi-bin/db.pl?cp=&amp;page=Book&amp;id=37484&amp;lang=en&amp;blang=en&amp;list=14 URSS.ru]&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Andrey Korotayev]] ''et al.'').

== Sustainable History ==

''&quot;Sustainable History and the Dignity of Man&quot;'' is a philosophy of history proposed by [[Nayef Al-Rodhan]], where history is defined as '''a durable progressive trajectory in which the quality of life on this planet or all other planets is premised on the guarantee of human dignity for all at all times under all circumstances.'''&lt;ref&gt;Nayef R.F. Al-Rodhan, Sustainable History and the Dignity of Man: A Philosophy of History and Civilisational Triumph (Berlin: [http://www.lit-verlag.de/isbn/3-643-80005-3 LIT], 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; This theory views history as a linear progression propelled by [[good governance]], which is, in turn, to be achieved through balancing the emotional, amoral, and egoistic elements of [[human nature]] with the human dignity needs of reason, security, [[human rights]], accountability, transparency, justice, opportunity, innovation, and inclusiveness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gcsp.ch/Globalisation/Publications/Faculty-Publications/Books-and-Edited-Volumes/Sustainable-History-and-the-Dignity-of-Man-A-Philosophy-of-History-and-Civilisational-Triumph GCSP]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Human dignity''' lies at the heart of this theory and is paramount for ensuring the sustainable history of humankind. Among other things, [[human dignity]] means having a positive sense of self and instilling individuals with respect for the communities to which they belong. Thus, reconciling humans' predisposition for emotionally self-interested behavior with the imperatives of human dignity appears as the one of the most important challenges to global policymakers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pressclub.ch/menu/events/event_060710_1130.htm Geneva Press Club]&lt;/ref&gt; At national level, they have to protect their citizens against violence and provide them with access to food, housing, clothes, health care, and education. Basic welfare provision and security are fundamental to ensuring human dignity. Environment and ecological considerations need to be addressed as well. Finally, cultural diversity, inclusiveness and participation at all levels, of all communities are key imperatives of human dignity.

In this respect, the sustainable history philosophy challenges existing concepts of [[civilisations]], such as [[Samuel Huntington (political scientist)|Samuel Huntington's]] ''[[Clash of civilisations|'clash of civilisations''']].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bookpleasures.com/websitepublisher/articles/2610/1/-Sustainable-History-and-the-Dignity-of-Man-Reviewed-By-Norm-Goldman-of-Bookpleasurescom/Page1.html Bookpleasures]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Instead, it argues that human civilisation should not be thought of as consisting of numerous separate and competing civilisations, but rather it should be thought of collectively as only one human civilisation. Within this civilisation are many geo-cultural domains that comprise'' [[sub-cultures]]. ''[[Nayef Al-Rodhan]]'' ''envisions human civilisation as an ocean into which the different geo-cultural domains flow like rivers,'' &quot;The Ocean Model of one Human Civilization&quot;. ''At points where geo-cultural domains first enter the ocean of human civilisation, there is likely to be a concentration or dominance of that culture. However, over time, all the rivers of geo-cultural domains become one. There is fluidity at the ocean's centre and cultures have the opportunity to borrow between them. Under such historical conditions the most advanced forms of human enterprise can thrive and lead us to a'' 'civilisational triumph'. ''Nevertheless, there are cases where geographical proximity of various cultures can also lead to friction and conflict.

[[Nayef Al-Rodhan]] concludes that within an increasingly globalised, interconnected and interdependent world, human dignity cannot be ensured globally and in a sustainable way through sole national means. A genuine global effort is required to meet the minimum criteria of human dignity globally. Areas such as conflict prevention, socio-economic justice, gender equality, protection of human rights, environmental protection require a holistic approach and a common action.

==The Enlightenment's ideal of progress==
{{further|Age of Enlightenment |Social progress}}

During the ''Aufklärung'', or Enlightenment, history began to be seen as both linear and irreversible. [[Condorcet]]'s interpretations of the various &quot;stages of humanity&quot; or [[Auguste Comte]]'s [[positivism]] were one of the most important formulations of such conceptions of history, which trusted [[social progress]]. As in [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau]]'s ''[[Emile: Or, On Education|Emile]]'' (1762) treatise on education (or the &quot;art of training men&quot;), the ''Aufklärung'' conceived the human species as perfectible: [[human nature]] could be infinitely developed through a well-thought [[pedagogy]]. In ''[[What is Enlightenment?]]'' (1784), [[Immanuel Kant]] defined the ''Aufklärung'' as the capacity to think by oneself, without referring to an exterior authority, be it a prince or tradition:

{{quotation|Enlightenment is when a person leaves behind a state of immaturity and dependence (''Unmündigkeit'') for which they themselves were responsible. Immaturity and dependence are the inability to use one's own [[intellect]] without the direction of another. One is responsible for this immaturity and dependence, if its cause is not a lack of intelligence or education, but a lack of determination and courage to think without the direction of another. ''[[wikt:Sapere aude|Sapere aude]]! Dare to know!'' is therefore the slogan of the [[Enlightenment in Western secular tradition|Enlightenment]].}}

In a paradoxical way, [[Kant]] supported in the same time [[enlightened despotism]] as a way of leading humanity towards its [[autonomy]]. He had conceived the process of history in his short treaty ''[[Idea for a Universal History with a Cosmopolitan Purpose]]'' (1784). On one hand, enlightened despotism was to lead nations toward their liberation, and progress was thus inscribed in the scheme of history; on the other hand, liberation could only be acquired by a singular gesture, ''Sapere Aude''! Thus, autonomy ultimately relied on the individual's &quot;determination and courage to think without the direction of another.&quot;

After Kant, [[Hegel]] developed a complex theodicy in the ''[[Phenomenology of Spirit]]'' (1807), which based its conception of history on [[dialectics]]: the negative (wars, etc.) was conceived by Hegel as the motor of history. Hegel argued that history is a constant process of dialectic clash, with each [[thesis]] encountering an opposing idea or event  [[antithesis]]. The clash of both was &quot;superated&quot; in the [[Thesis, antithesis, synthesis|synthesis]], a conjunction that conserved the contradiction between thesis and its antithesis while [[Aufheben|sublating]] it. As [[Marx]] famously explained afterwards, concretely that meant that if [[Louis XVI of France|Louis XVI]]'s monarchic rule in France was seen as the thesis, the [[French Revolution]] could be seen as its antithesis. However, both were sublated in [[Napoleon]], who reconciled the revolution with the ''[[Ancien Régime]]''; he conserved the change. Hegel thought that [[reason]] accomplished itself, through this dialectical scheme, in History. Through [[Manual labour|labour]], man transformed nature so he could recognize himself in it; he made it his &quot;home.&quot; Thus, reason spiritualized nature. Roads, fields, fences, and all the modern infrastructure in which we live is the result of this spiritualization of nature. Hegel thus explained social progress as the result of the labour of reason in history. However, this dialectical reading of history involved, of course, contradiction, so history was also conceived of as constantly conflicting: Hegel theorized this in his famous [[Slave-master dialectic|dialectic of the lord and the bondsman]].

According to Hegel,
{{quotation|One more word about giving instruction as to what the world ought to be. Philosophy in any case always comes on the scene too late to give it... When philosophy paints its gray in gray, then has a shape of life grown old. By philosophy's gray in gray it cannot be rejuvenated but only understood. The [[owl of Minerva]] spreads its wings only with the falling of the dusk.|&lt;ref&gt;Hegel, [[Philosophy of Right]] (1820), &quot;Preface&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Thus, philosophy was to explain ''Geschichte'' (history) afterward. Philosophy is always late, it is only an interpretation of what is rational in the real&amp;mdash;and, according to Hegel, only what is recognized as rational is real. This idealist understanding of philosophy as interpretation was famously challenged by [[Karl Marx]]'s ''[[Theses on Feuerbach|11th thesis on Feuerbach]]'' (1845): &quot;''Philosophers have hitherto only interpreted the world in various ways; the point, however, is to change it.''&quot;

===Social evolutionism===
{{further|Sociocultural evolution}} &lt;!-- the time sphere --&gt;
Inspired by the Enlightenment's ideal of progress, social evolutionism became a popular conception in the 19th century. [[Auguste Comte]]'s (1798–1857) [[positivism|positivist]] conception of history, which he divided into the theological stage, the metaphysical stage and the positivist stage, brought upon by modern science, was one of the most influential doctrines of progress. The [[Whig interpretation of history]], as it was later called, associated with scholars of the [[Victorian era|Victorian]] and [[Edwardian period|Edwardian]] eras in [[United Kingdom|Britain]], such as [[Henry Maine]] or [[Thomas Macaulay]], gives an example of such influence, by looking at human history as progress from savagery and ignorance toward peace, prosperity, and science. Maine described the direction of progress as &quot;from status to contract,&quot; from a world in which a child's whole life is pre-determined by the circumstances of his birth, toward one of mobility and choice.

The publication of [[Charles Darwin|Darwin]]'s ''[[The Origin of Species]]'' in 1859 introduced [[human evolution]]. However, it was quickly transposed from its original biological field to the social field, in &quot;[[social Darwinism]]&quot; theories. [[Herbert Spencer]], who coined the term &quot;[[survival of the fittest]],&quot; or [[Lewis Henry Morgan]] in ''[[Ancient Society]]'' (1877) developed evolutionist theories independent from Darwin's works, which would be later interpreted as social Darwinism. These 19th-century [[unilineal evolution]] theories claimed that societies start out in a ''primitive'' state and gradually become more [[civilisation|civilised]] over time, and equated the culture and technology of Western civilisation with progress.

[[Ernst Haeckel]] formulated his [[recapitulation theory]] in 1867, which stated that &quot;[[ontogeny recapitulates phylogeny]]&quot;: the evolution of each individual reproduces the species' evolution, such as in the development of [[embryos]]. Hence, a child goes through all the steps from primitive society to modern society. This was later discredited.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} Haeckel did not support Darwin's theory of [[natural selection]] introduced in ''[[The Origin of Species]]'' (1859), rather believing in a [[Jean-Baptiste Lamarck|Lamarckian]] [[inheritance of acquired characteristics]].

Progress was not necessarily, however, positive. [[Arthur Gobineau]]'s ''[[An Essay on the Inequality of the Human Races]]'' (1853–55) was a [[decadence|decadent]] description of the evolution of the &quot;[[Aryan race]]&quot; which was disappearing through [[miscegenation]]. Gobineau's works had a large popularity in the so-called [[scientific racism]] theories that developed during the [[New Imperialism]] period.

After the [[World War I|first world war]], and even before [[Herbert Butterfield]] (1900–1979) harshly criticized it, the Whig interpretation had gone out of style. The bloodletting of that conflict had indicted the whole notion of linear progress. [[Paul Valéry]] famously said: &quot;We civilizations now know ourselves mortal.&quot;

However, the notion itself didn't completely disappear. ''[[The End of History and the Last Man]]'' (1992) by [[Francis Fukuyama]] proposed a similar notion of progress, positing that the worldwide adoption of [[liberal democracy|liberal democracies]] as the single accredited political system and even modality of human consciousness would represent the &quot;[[End of History]]&quot;. Fukuyama's work stems from an [[Alexandre Kojève|Kojevian]] reading of [[Hegel]]'s ''[[Phenomenology of Spirit]]'' (1807).

Unlike [[Maurice Godelier]] who interprets history as a process of transformation, [[Tim Ingold]] suggests that history is a movement of [[autopoiesis]]&lt;ref&gt;Ingold, T. On the Distinction between Evolution and History. Social Evolution &amp; History,. Vol. 1, num. 1. 2002. Pp. 5-24. P. 9, [http://www.socionauki.ru/journal/articles/130380/ socionauki.ru]&lt;/ref&gt;

A key component to making sense of all of this is to simply recognize that all these issues in social evolution merely serve to support the suggestion that how one considers the nature of history will impact the interpretation and conclusions drawn about history. The critical under-explored question is less about history as content and more about history as process.

In 2011 [[ Steven Pinker ]] wrote a history of violence and humanity from an evolutionary perspective in which he shows that violence has declined statistically over time.&lt;ref&gt;&quot; The better angels of our nature, a history of violence and humanity &quot;, by [[ Steven Pinker]], published 2012 by Penguin books ISBN978-0-141-03464-5&lt;/ref&gt;

===The validity of the &quot;Great man theory&quot; in historical studies===

{{Further2|[[Hero#The validity of the &quot;hero&quot; in historical studies|The validity of the &quot;hero&quot; in historical studies]]|[[Great man theory]]}}

After [[Hegel]], who insisted on the role of &quot;[[Great man theory|great men]]&quot; in history, with his famous statement about [[Napoleon]], &quot;I saw the Spirit on his horse&quot;, [[Thomas Carlyle]] argued that history was the biography of a few central individuals, ''[[hero]]es'', such as [[Oliver Cromwell]] or [[Frederick the Great]], writing that &quot;The history of the world is but the biography of great men.&quot; His heroes were political and military figures, the founders or topplers of states. His history of great men, of geniuses good and evil, sought to organize change in the advent of greatness. Explicit defenses of Carlyle's position have been rare in the late 20th century. Most philosophers of history contend that the motive forces in history can best be described only with a wider lens than the one he used for his portraits. A.C. Danto, for example, wrote of the importance of the individual in history, but extended his definition to include ''social individuals,'' defined as &quot;individuals we may provisionally characterize as containing individual human beings amongst their parts. Examples of social individuals might be social classes [...], national groups [...], religious organizations [...], large-scale events [...], large-scale social movements [...], etc.&quot; (Danto, &quot;The Historical Individual&quot;, 266, in ''Philosophical Analysis and History,'' edited by Williman H. Dray, Rainbow-Bridge Book Co., 1966). The Great Man approach to history was most popular with professional historians in the 19th century; a popular work of this school is the ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition]]'' (1911), which contains lengthy and detailed biographies about the great men of history. For example to read about (what is known today as) the &quot;[[Migrations Period]],&quot; consult the biography of [[Attila the Hun]].

After [[Marx]]'s [[historical materialism|conception of a materialist history]] based on the [[class struggle]], which raised attention for the first time to the importance of social factors such as economics in the unfolding of history, [[Herbert Spencer]] wrote &quot;You must admit that the genesis of the great man depends on the long series of complex influences which has produced the race in which he appears, and the social state into which that race has slowly grown....Before he can remake his society, his society must make him.&quot;

The [[Annales School]], founded by [[Lucien Febvre]] and [[Marc Bloch]], were a major landmark on the shift from a history centered on [[subject (philosophy)|individual subjects]] to studies concentrating in [[geography]], economics, [[demography]], and other social forces. [[Fernand Braudel]]'s studies on the [[Mediterranean Sea]] as &quot;hero&quot; of history, [[Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie]]'s history of [[climate]], etc., were inspired by this School.

==Does history have a teleological sense?==

''For further information: [[Social progress]] and [[Progress (history)]]''

[[Theodicy]] claimed that history had a progressive direction leading to an [[eschatological]] end, given by a superior power. However, this transcendent teleological sense can be thought as [[Immanence|immanent]] to human history itself. Hegel probably represents the epitome of teleological philosophy of history. Hegel's teleology was taken up by [[Francis Fukuyama]] in his ''[[The End of History and the Last Man]]'' (see ''Social evolutionism'' above). Thinkers such as [[Nietzsche]], [[Michel Foucault]], Althusser or [[Deleuze]] deny any teleological sense to history, claiming that it is best characterized by discontinuities, ruptures, and various time-scales, which the [[Annales School]] had demonstrated.

Schools of thought influenced by [[Hegel]] see history as progressive, too &amp;mdash; but they saw, and see progress as the outcome of a [[dialectic]] in which factors working in opposite directions are over time reconciled (see above). History was best seen as directed by a ''[[Zeitgeist]]'', and traces of the Zeitgeist could be seen by looking backward. Hegel believed that history was moving man toward &quot;[[civilization]]&quot;, and some also claim he thought that the [[Prussia]]n state incarnated the &quot;[[End of History]]&quot;. In his ''Lessons on the History of Philosophy'', he explains that each epochal philosophy is in a way the whole of philosophy; it is not a subdivision of the Whole but this Whole itself apprehended in a specific modality.

===Historical accounts of writing history===
{{further|Historiography}}
A classic example of history being written by the victors—or more precisely, by the survivors&lt;ref name=&quot;wah&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=Writing African History|author=Philips, John Edward|publisher=University Rochester Press|year=2006|pages=26–27}}&lt;/ref&gt;—would be the scarcity of unbiased information that has come down to us{{Who|date=August 2011}} about the [[Carthage|Carthaginians]]. Roman historians left tales of cruelty and [[human sacrifice]] practiced by their longtime enemies; however no Carthaginian was left alive to give their side of the story.

Similarly, we only have the [[History of Christianity|Christian]] side of how Christianity came to be the dominant religion of Europe. However, we know very little about other European religions, such as [[Paganism]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} We have the European version of the [[European colonisation of the Americas|conquest of the Americas]], with an interpretation of the native version of events only emerging to popular consciousness since the early 1980s. We have [[Herodotus|Herodotus's]] Greek history of the [[Persian Wars]], but the Persian recall of the events is little known in Western Culture.

In many respects, the head of state may be guilty of cruelties or even simply a different way of doing things. In some societies, however, to speak of or write critically of rulers can amount to conviction of treason and death. As such, in many ways, what is left as the &quot;official record&quot; of events is oft influenced by one's desire to avoid exile or execution.

However, &quot;losers&quot; in certain time periods often have more of an impetus than the &quot;winners&quot; to write histories that comfort themselves and [[self-justification|justify]] their own behavior.&lt;ref name=&quot;wah&quot;/&gt; Examples include the historiography of the [[American Civil War]], where it can be argued that the losers (Southerners) have written more history books on the subject than the winners and, until recently, dominated the national perception of history. Confederate generals such as [[Robert E. Lee|Lee]] and [[Thomas J. Jackson|Jackson]] are generally held in higher esteem than their Union counterparts. Popular films such as ''[[Cold Mountain (film)|Cold Mountain]]'', ''[[Gone with the Wind (film)|Gone with the Wind]]'' and ''[[The Birth of a Nation]]'' have told the story from the Southern viewpoint. Also, despite &quot;losing&quot; the [[Vietnam War]], the United States produces more scholarship on the war than any other country, including Vietnam.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Triumph Revisited: Historians Battle for the Vietnam War|author=Wiest, Andrew A.|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2010|page=224}}&lt;/ref&gt; Popular history abounds with condemnations of the cruelty of [[African slave trade]]rs and [[Colonization of Africa|colonists]], despite the &quot;winning&quot; status of those people in their heyday.&lt;ref name=&quot;wah&quot;/&gt;

As is true of [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|pre-Columbian populations of America]], the historical record of America being [[European colonization of the Americas|&quot;discovered&quot; by Europeans]] is now sometimes presented as a history of invasion, exploitation and dominance of a people who had been there before the Europeans. This reinterpretation of the historical record is called [[historical revisionism]], which can take the form of [[historical revisionism (negationism)|negationism]], which is the denial of [[genocide]]s and [[crimes against humanity]]. The revision of previously accepted historical accounts is a constant process in which &quot;today's winners are tomorrow's losers&quot;, and the rise and fall of present institutions and movements influence the way historians see the past.&lt;ref name=&quot;wah&quot;/&gt; In the same sense, the teaching, in [[Education in France|French secondary schools]], of the [[Algerian War of Independence#Historiography of the war and of colonialism|Algerian War of Independence and of colonialism]], has been criticized by several historians, and is the subject of frequent debates. Thus, in contradiction with the February 23, 2005 [[French law on colonialism|law on colonialism]], voted by the [[Union for a Popular Movement|UMP]] conservative party, historian Benjamin Stora notes that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;As Algerians do not appear in their &quot;indigenous&quot; conditions and their sub-citizens status, as the [[Nationalism and resistance in Algeria|history of nationalist movement]] is never evoqued, as none of the great figures of the resistance &amp;mdash; [[Messali Hadj]], [[Ferhat Abbas]] &amp;mdash; emerge nor retain attention, in one word, as no one explains to students what has been colonisation, we make them unable to understand why the decolonisation took place.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiploApril&quot;&gt;[http://mondediplo.com/2001/04/04algeriatorture Colonialism through the school books - The hidden history of the Algerian war], ''[[Le Monde diplomatique]]'', April 2001 {{en icon}}/{{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Obviously the victors do have advantages in promoting their version of events, even if they don't erase their enemies completely from existence. The victors may have control over the churches, the courts and schools. This may give the ruling elites nearly total control over the molding of consciousness and discourse over those they rule. In [[dictatorship]]s, ruthless [[censorship]] allows only the state-approved version of events to be made public, and much that happened remains secret if it proved hurtful to the ruling elite.  [[Liberal democracy|Liberal democracies]] are not immune however. In the West for example, the [[Concentration of media ownership|concentration of media]] into ever fewer hands has given the captains of major media and the [[Public Relations]] industry increased control over the parameters of public discourse that form the boundaries of debate we all have in classrooms, and with friends and co-workers on matters such as war and politics.

===Michel Foucault's analysis of historical and political discourse===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Hero]] --&gt;

The historico-political [[discourse]] analyzed by [[Michel Foucault]] in ''Society Must Be Defended'' (1975–76) considered [[truth]] as the fragile product of a historical struggle, first conceptualized under the name of &quot;[[race struggle]]&quot; &amp;mdash; however, &quot;race&quot;'s meaning was different from today's biological notion, being closer to the sense of &quot;nation&quot; (distinct from [[nation-states]]; its signification is here closer to &quot;people&quot;). [[Boulainvilliers]], for example, was an exponent of nobility rights. He claimed that the French nobility were the racial descendants of the Franks who invaded France (while the Third Estate was descended from the conquered Gauls), and had right to power by virtue of right of conquest. He used this approach to formulate a historical thesis of the course of French political history&amp;mdash;a critique of both the monarchy and the Third Estate. Foucault regarded him as the founder of the historico-political discourse as political weapon.

In Great Britain, this historico-political discourse was used by the bourgeoisie, the people and the aristocracy as a means of struggle against the monarchy - cf. [[Edward Coke]] or [[John Lilburne]]. In France, [[Boulainvilliers]], [[Nicolas Fréret]], and then [[Sieyès]], [[Augustin Thierry]], and [[Cournot]] reappropriated this form of discourse. Finally, at the end of the 19th century, this discourse was incorporated by racialist biologists and [[eugenicists]], who gave it the modern sense of &quot;race&quot; and, even more, transformed this popular discourse into a &quot;[[state racism]]&quot; (Nazism). According to Foucault, Marxists also seized this discourse and took it in a different direction, transforming the [[essentialist]] notion of &quot;race&quot; into the historical notion of &quot;[[class struggle]]&quot;, defined by socially structured position: capitalist or proletarian. This displacement of discourse constitutes one of the bases of Foucault's thought: discourse is not tied to the [[subject (philosophy)|subject]], rather the &quot;subject&quot; is a construction of discourse. Moreover, discourse is not the simple [[ideological]] and mirror reflexion of an economical [[infrastructure]], but is a product and the battlefield of multiples forces&amp;mdash;which may not be reduced to the simple [[dualist]] [[contradiction]] of two energies.

Foucault shows that what specifies this discourse from the juridical and philosophical discourse is its conception of truth: truth is no longer absolute, it is the product of &quot;race struggle&quot;. History itself, which was traditionally the [[sovereign]]'s science, the [[legend]] of his glorious feats, became the discourse of the people, a political stake. The subject is not any more a neutral [[arbitrate]], judge or [[legislator]], as in [[Solon]]'s or [[Kant]]'s conceptions. Therefore, - what became - the &quot;[[historical subject]]&quot; must search in history's furor, under the &quot;juridical code's dried blood&quot;, the multiple [[contingency|contingencies]] from which a fragile [[rationality]] temporarily finally emerged. This may be, perhaps, compared to the [[sophist]] discourse in Ancient Greece. Foucault warns that it has nothing to do with [[Machiavelli]]'s or [[Hobbes]]'s discourse on war, for to this popular discourse, the [[sovereignty|Sovereign]] is nothing more than &quot;an illusion, an instrument, or, at the best, an enemy. It is {the historico-political discourse} a discourse that beheads the king, anyway that dispenses itself from the sovereign and that denounces it&quot;.

===History and education===

{{Further|Education|Pedagogy|Philosophy of education}}
Since [[Plato]]'s ''[[Republic (Plato)|Republic]]'', civic education and instruction has had a central role in politics and the constitution of a common identity. History has thus sometimes become the target of [[propaganda]], for example in [[historical revisionism (negationism)|historical revisionist]] attempts. Plato's insistence on the importance of education was relayed by Rousseau's ''[[Emile: Or, On Education]]'' (1762), a necessary counterpart of ''The [[Social Contract]]'' (also 1762). [[Public education]] has been seen by republican regimes and the Enlightenment as a prerequisite of the masses' progressive emancipation, as conceived by [[Kant]] in ''[[What is Enlightenment?|Was Ist Aufklärung?]]'' (What Is Enlightenment?, 1784).

The creation of modern education systems, instrumental in the construction of [[nation-states]], also passed by the elaboration of a common, national history. [[History textbooks]] are one of the many ways through which this common history was transmitted. ''[[Le Tour de France par deux enfants]]'', for example, was the [[French Third Republic|Third Republic]]'s classic textbook for elementary school: it described the story of two French children who, following the German annexation of the [[Alsace-Lorraine]] region in 1870, go on a ''tour de France'' during which they become aware of France's diversity and the existence of the various ''[[patois]]''.

In most societies, schools and curricula are controlled by governments. As such, there is always an opportunity for governments to impose. Granted, often governments in free societies serve to protect freedoms, check [[hate speech]] and breaches of constitutional rights; but the power itself to impose is available to use the education system to influence thought of malleable minds, positively or negatively, towards truth or towards a version of truth. A recent example of the fragility of government involvement with history textbooks was the [[Japanese history textbook controversies]].

===Narrative and history===
A current popular conception considers the value of narrative in the writing and experience of history. Important analysts in this area include [[Paul Ricœur]], [[Louis Mink]], [[W.B. Gallie]] and [[Hayden White]]. Some have doubted this approach because it draws fictional and historical narrative closer together, and there remains a perceived &quot;fundamental bifurcation between historical and fictional narrative&quot; (Ricœur, vol. 1, 52). In spite of this, most modern historians, such as [[Barbara Tuchman]] or [[David McCullough]], would consider narrative writing important to their approaches. The theory of narrated history (or historicized narrative) holds that the structure of lived experience, and such experience narrated in both fictional and non-fictional works (literature and historiography) have in common the figuration of ''temporal experience.&quot; In this way, narrative has a generously encompassing ability to &quot;'grasp together' and integrate[] into one whole and complete story&quot; the &quot;composite representations&quot; of historical experience (Ricœur x, 173). Louis Mink writes that, &quot;the significance of past occurrences is understandable only as they are locatable in the ensemble of interrelationships that can be grasped only in the construction of narrative form&quot; (148). Marxist theorist [[Fredric Jameson]] also analyzes historical understanding this way, and writes that &quot;history is inaccessible to us except in textual form […] it can be approached only by way of prior (re)textualization&quot; (82).

===History as propaganda: Is history always written by the victors?===

{{see also|Truth by consensus}}

In his &quot;Society must be Defended&quot;, [[Michel Foucault]] posited that the victors of a social struggle use their political dominance to suppress a defeated adversary's version of historical events in favor of their own [[propaganda]], which may go so far as [[historical revisionism (political)|historical revisionism]] (see ''Michel Foucault's analysis of historical and political discourse'' above). Nations adopting such an approach would likely fashion a &quot;universal&quot; theory of history to support their aims, with a teleological and deterministic philosophy of history used to justify the inevitableness and rightness of their victories (see ''The Enlightenment's ideal of progress'' above). Philosopher Paul Ricoeur has written of the use of this approach by totalitarian and Nazi regimes, with such regimes &quot;exercis[ing] a virtual violence upon the diverging tendencies of history&quot; (''History and Truth'' 183), and with fanaticism the result. For Ricoeur, rather than a unified, teleological philosophy of history, &quot;We carry on several histories simultaneously, in times whose periods, crises, and pauses do not coincide. We enchain, abandon, and resume several histories, much as a chess player who plays several games at once, renewing now this one, now the another&quot; (''History and Truth'' 186). For Ricoeur, [[Marx]]'s unified view of history may be suspect, but is nevertheless seen as:

&lt;blockquote&gt;''the'' philosophy of history ''par excellence'': not only does it provide a formula for the dialectics of social forces&amp;mdash;under the name of historical materialism&amp;mdash;but it also sees in the proletarian class the reality, which is at once universal and concrete and which, although it be oppressed today, will constitute the unity of history in the future. From this standpoint, the proletarian perspective furnishes both a theoretical meaning ''of'' history and a practical goal ''for'' history, a principle of explication and a line of action. (''History and Truth'' 183)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Walter Benjamin]] believed that [[Marxist]] historians must take a radically different view point from the [[bourgeois]] and [[idealist]] points of view, in an attempt to create a sort of [[history from below]], which would be able to conceive an alternative conception of history, not based, as in classical historical studies, on the philosophical and juridical discourse of [[sovereignty]]--an approach that would invariably adhere to major states (the victors') points of view.

[[George Orwell]]'s ''[[Nineteen Eighty-Four]]'' is a fictional account of the manipulation of the historical record for nationalist aims and manipulation of power. In the book, he wrote, &quot;He who controls the present, controls the past. He who controls the past, controls the future.&quot; The creation of a &quot;national story&quot; by way of management of the historical record is at the heart of the debate about history as propaganda. To some degree, all nations are active in the promotion of such &quot;national stories,&quot; with ethnicity, nationalism, gender, power, heroic figures, class considerations and important national events and trends all clashing and competing within the narrative.

==The judgement of history==
In [[Hegel]]'s philosophy of history, the expression ''Weltgeschichte ist das Weltgericht'' (World History is a tribunal that judges the World) is used to assert the view that History is what judges men, their actions and their opinions.

Since the 20th century, Western historians have disavowed the aspiration to provide the &quot;judgement of history.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Curran2000p413&quot;&gt;Curran, Vivian Grosswald (2000) ''Herder and the Holocaust: A Debate About Difference and Determinism in the Context of Comparative Law'' in F. C. DeCoste, Bernard Schwartz (eds.) ''Holocaust's Ghost: Writings on Art, Politics, Law and Education'' [http://books.google.com/books?id=lLnBSq7YP0gC&amp;pg=PA413&amp;lpg=PA413 pp.413-5]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkinson1988p800&quot;/&gt; The goals of historical judgements or interpretations are separate to those of [[legal judgement]]s, that need to be formulated quickly after the events and be final.&lt;ref name=&quot;Curran2000p415&quot;&gt;Curran, Vivian Grosswald (2000) ''Herder and the Holocaust: A Debate About Difference and Determinism in the Context of Comparative Law'' in F. C. DeCoste, Bernard Schwartz (eds.) ''Holocaust's Ghost: Writings on Art, Politics, Law and Education'' [http://books.google.com/books?id=lLnBSq7YP0gC&amp;pg=PA415&amp;lpg=PA415 p.415]&lt;/ref&gt; The issue of [[collective memory]] is related to the issue of the &quot;judgement of history.&quot;

Related to the issue of historical judgement are those of the pretension to neutrality and objectivity.&lt;ref&gt;Rubinoff, Lionel ''History, Philosophy and Historiography: Philosophy and the Critique of Historical Thinking'', in William Sweet ''The Philosophy of History: A Re-Examination'', Chapter 9 [http://books.google.com/books?id=vjtv_AOBJ4MC&amp;pg=PA171&amp;lpg=PA171 p.171]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Holland [http://books.google.com/books?id=cdsvVatrQ_AC&amp;pg=RA3-PA7-IA5 Access to History: Russia and its Rulers 1855-1964 (OCR): Histroical Themes] p.7 &lt;/ref&gt; Analytical and critical philosophers of history have debated whether historians should express judgements on historical figures, or if this would infringe on their supposed role.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkinson1988p800&quot;&gt;Parkinson, G.H.R ''An Encyclopedia of Philosophy'' [http://books.google.com/books?id=IqbJnEYKpW4C&amp;pg=PA807 pp.800, 807, 820]&lt;/ref&gt; In general, [[positivist]]s and neopositivists oppose any any value-judgement as unscientific.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parkinson1988p800&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Eschatology]]
*[[Historical method]]
*[[Historiography]]
*[[World history]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Berkhofer, Robert F. ''Beyond the great story: history as text and discourse.'' (Harvard University Press, 1995)
* Berlin, Isaiah. ''Three critics of the Enlightenment: Vico, Hamann, Herder,'' (2000)
* Rose, Elizabeta &quot;The Philosophy of History&quot; Writings of the Contemporary World (2011)
* Collingwood, R. G. ''The idea of history.'' (1946)
* Danto, Arthur Coleman. ''Analytical philosophy of history'' (1965)
* Dilthey, Wilhelm. ''Introduction to the human sciences'' ed. by R. A. Makkreel and F. Rodi. (1883; 1989)
* Gardiner, Patrick L. ''The nature of historical explanation.'' (1952)
* Gardiner, Patrick L. ed. ''The philosophy of history, Oxford readings in philosophy.'' (1974)
*Mink, Louis O. &quot;Narrative form as a cognitive instrument.&quot; in ''The writing of history: Literary form and historical understanding,'' Robert H. Canary and Henry Kozicki, eds. Madison, Wisconsin: The University of Wisconsin Press, 1978.
*[[Paul Ricoeur|Ricoeur, Paul]]. ''Time and Narrative,'' Volume 1 and 2, University Of Chicago Press, 1990.
*---. ''History and Truth.'' Translated by Kathleen McLaughlin and David Pellauer. Chicago and London: U of Chicago P, 1983.
*[[Fredric Jameson|Jameson, Frederic]]. ''The Political Unconscious: Narrative as a Socially Symbolic Act,'' Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1981.
*[[Herbert J. Muller|Muller, Herbert J]]. ''The Uses of the Past,'' New York, New York: Oxford University Press, 1952.
* Walsh, W.H. ''An Introduction to Philosophy of History.'' 1951.
* White, Hayden V. ''Metahistory: The Historical Imagination in Nineteenth-Century Europe.'' (Johns Hopkins University Press, 1973).
* White, Hayden V. ''The Fiction of Narrative: Essays on History, Literature, and Theory, 1957-2007.'' (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2010). Ed. Robert Doran.
* Gisi, Lucas Marco: ''Einbildungskraft und Mythologie. Die Verschränkung von Anthropologie und Geschichte im 18. Jahrhundert'', Berlin, New York: de Gruyter, 2007.

==External links==
* [http://www.galilean-library.org/int18.html An Introduction to the Philosophy of History] by Paul Newall, aimed at beginners.
* Daniel Little, [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/history/ Philosophy of History], Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy
*[http://vlib.iue.it/carrie/texts/carrie_books/paksoy-7/  IDENTITIES: How Governed, Who Pays?]
*[http://www.humboldt.edu/~essays/sandis.html The Explanation of Action in History] by Constantine Sandis, Essays in Philosophy, Vol. 7, No. 2, June 2006.
*[http://www.culturahistorica.es/welcome.html Web Portal on Philosophy of History, Historiography and Historical Culture]
*{{Cite Americana|History, Logic of|author=[[Hugo Münsterberg]]}}
*[http://www.inth.ugent.be The International Network for Theory of History]

{{Philosophy topics}}
{{Time Topics}}
{{Chronology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Philosophy Of History}}
[[Category:Philosophy of history| ]]
[[Category:Philosophy by field|His]]
[[Category:Historiography]]
[[Category:Theories of history]]
[[Category:Political philosophy]]
[[Category:Social philosophy]]

[[az:Tarix fəlsəfəsi]]
[[be:Філасофія гісторыі]]
[[bg:Философия на историята]]
[[ca:Filosofia de la història]]
[[cs:Filosofie dějin]]
[[de:Geschichtsphilosophie]]
[[et:Ajaloofilosoofia]]
[[es:Filosofía de la historia]]
[[fa:فلسفه تاریخ]]
[[fr:Philosophie de l'histoire]]
[[hr:Filozofija povijesti]]
[[is:Söguspeki]]
[[it:Filosofia della storia]]
[[he:פילוסופיה של ההיסטוריה]]
[[kk:Тарих философиясы]]
[[lt:Istorijos filosofija]]
[[hu:Történelemfilozófia]]
[[nl:Geschiedfilosofie]]
[[ja:歴史哲学]]
[[pl:Filozofia historii]]
[[pt:Filosofia da história]]
[[ro:Filozofia istoriei]]
[[ru:Философия истории]]
[[sq:Filozofia e historisë]]
[[sl:Filozofija zgodovine]]
[[sr:Филозофија историје]]
[[sh:Filozofija historije]]
[[fi:Historianfilosofia]]
[[sv:Historiefilosofi]]
[[tr:Tarih felsefesi]]
[[uk:Філософія історії]]
[[zh:历史哲学]]</text>
      <sha1>hxauhjxhuqk986m9gbhai1zjz9fh11n</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
