<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pre-Columbian era</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>90001</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518436014</id>
      <parentid>518434450</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-18T02:32:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Heironymous Rowe</username>
        <id>6129588</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 518434450 by [[Special:Contributions/128.83.206.164|128.83.206.164]] ([[User talk:128.83.206.164|talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="59699">[[File:Ameicas 1000 BCE crop.png|thumb|240px|right|Simple map of subsistence methods in the Americas at 1000 BCE.
{{legend|#FEFE00|hunter-gatherers ([[Mesolithic]])}}
{{legend|#00FE00|simple farming societies ([[Neolithic]])}}
{{legend|#FE7334|complex farming societies (tribal [[chiefdom]]s or [[civilization]]s)}}
]]
The '''pre-Columbian era''' incorporates all [[archaeology of the Americas|period subdivisions]] in the [[history of the Americas|history and prehistory of the Americas]] before the appearance of significant European influences on the American continents, spanning the time of the  [[migration to the New World|original settlement]] in the [[Upper Paleolithic]] period to [[European colonization of the Americas|European colonization]] during the [[Early Modern period]].

While the phrase &quot;pre-Columbian era&quot; literally refers only to the time preceding [[Christopher Columbus]]'s voyages of 1492, in practice the phrase usually is used to denote the entire history of [[indigenous peoples of the Americas|American indigenous cultures]] until those cultures were conquered or significantly influenced by Europeans, even if this happened decades or centuries after Columbus's first landing. For this reason the alternative terms of '''Precontact Americas''', '''Pre-Colonial Americas''' or '''Prehistoric Americas''' are also in use. In areas of [[Hispanic America]] the term usually used is '''Pre-Hispanic'''.

Many pre-Columbian [[civilization]]s established hallmarks which included permanent settlements, cities, [[agriculture]], civic and [[monument]]al [[architecture]], major [[earthworks (archaeology)|earthworks]], and [[Complex society|complex societal hierarchies]]. Some of these civilizations had long faded by the time of the first permanent European and African arrivals (c. late 15th–early 16th centuries), and are known only through [[archaeology of the Americas|archaeological investigations]]. Others were contemporary with the colonial period, and were described in historical accounts of the time. A few, such as the [[Maya civilization|Maya]], had their own written records. Because many Christian Europeans of the time viewed such texts as [[heresy|heretical]], men like [[Diego de Landa]] destroyed many texts in pyres, even while seeking to preserve native histories. Only a few hidden documents have survived in their original languages, while others were transcribed or dictated into Spanish, giving modern historians glimpses of ancient culture and knowledge.

[[Indigenous peoples of the Americas]] continue to evolve after the pre-Columbian era. Many of these peoples and their descendants continue traditional practices, while evolving and adapting new cultural practices and technologies into their lives.
{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

==History==
[[File:PreColumbian American cultures.png|thumb|Major cultural areas of the pre-Columbian Americas: {{legend0|#4747a1|Arctic}} {{legend0|#50828e|Northwest}} {{legend0|#40895d|Aridoamerica}} {{legend0|#b4581b|Mesoamerica}} {{legend0|#548434|Isthmo-Colombian}} {{legend0|#b1c759|Caribbean}} {{legend0|#b94343|Amazon}} {{legend0|#8b782a|Andes}}]]
[[File:Nordamerikanische Kulturareale en.png|thumb|Cultural areas of pre-Columbian North America]]

===Asiatic migration===
{{main|Settlement of the Americas|Paleo-Indians}}
{{see|Genetic history of indigenous peoples of the Americas}}
Asian nomads are thought to have entered the Americas via the [[Bering Land Bridge]] (Beringia), now the [[Bering Strait]] and possibly along the Northwest coast. Genetic evidence found in [[Amerindian]]s' maternally inherited [[mitochondrial DNA]] (mtDNA) supports the theory of multiple genetic populations migrating from Asia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cyberwest.com/cw09/v9scwst1.html Study confirms Bering land bridge flooded later than previously believed] Cyberwest online, July 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nps.gov/bela/html/history.htm Bering Land Bridge] US National Park System&lt;/ref&gt; Over the course of millennia, [[Paleo-Indians]] spread throughout North America and South America. Exactly when the first group of people migrated into the [[Americas]] is the subject of much debate. One of the earliest identifiable cultures was the [[Clovis culture]], with sites dating from some 13,000 years ago. However, older sites dating back to 20,000 years ago have been claimed. Some [[Indigenous Amerindian genetics|genetic]] studies estimate the colonization of the Americas dates from between 40,000 to 13,000 years ago.&lt;ref name=SpencerWells2&gt;{{cite book|first1=Spencer |last1=Wells |first2=Mark |last2=Read |title=The Journey of Man - A Genetic Odyssey|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WAsKm-_zu5sC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=The%20Journey%20of%20Man&amp;pg=PA138#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true|format=Digitised online by Google books|publisher=Random House|isbn= 0-8129-7146-9|accessdate=2009-11-21|year=2002|pages=138–140}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The chronology of migration models is currently divided into two general approaches. The first is the ''short chronology theory'' with the first movement beyond Alaska into the New World occurring no earlier than 14,000 – 17,000 years ago, followed by successive waves of immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2008/03/080313-first-americans.html |title=Americas Settled 15,000 Years Ago, Study Says |work=National Geographic News |date=March 13, 2008 |accessdate=2011-06-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dnaa&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |url=http://encarta.msn.com/text_701509129___0/First_Americans.html |title= First Americans|work=Southern Methodist University-David J. Meltzer, B.A., M.A., Ph.D.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi= 10.1016/j.ajhg.2007.11.013 |last= Fagundes |first= Nelson J.R. |coauthors= Ricardo Kanitz, Roberta Eckert, Ana C.S. Valls, Mauricio R. Bogo, Francisco M. Salzano, David Glenn Smith, Wilson A. Silva, Marco A. Zago, Andrea K. Ribeiro-dos-Santos, Sidney E.B. Santos, Maria Luiza Petzl-Erler, and Sandro L.Bonatto |title= Mitochondrial Population Genomics Supports a Single Pre-Clovis Origin with a Coastal Route for the Peopling of the Americas |journal= American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=82 |issue=3 |year=2008 |pages=583–592 |pmid= 18313026 |pmc= 2427228}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.multiculturalcanada.ca/Encyclopedia/A-Z/p4/1 |title=Beginnings to 1500 C.E. |work=Encyclopedia of Canada's Peoples}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second belief is the ''long chronology theory'', which proposes that the first group of people entered the hemisphere at a much earlier date, possibly 50,000 - 40,000 years ago or earlier.&lt;ref name=&quot;national&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Atlas of the Human Journey |url=https://genographic.nationalgeographic.com/genographic/atlas.html?era=e003 |work=National Genographic}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/?id=Obgdz8auwkMC&amp;pg=PA11&amp;lpg=PA11&amp;dq=8000+years+ago+in+the+americas#v=onepage&amp;q=8000%20years%20ago%20in%20the%20americas&amp;f=false |title=Indians in the Americas: the untold story |work=By William Marder|accessdate=2009-11-17 |isbn=978-1-58509-104-1 |author1=Marder, William |date=2005-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kind&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bradshawfoundation.com/journey/|title=Jorney of mankind|work=Brad Shaw Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=_0u2y_SVnmoC&amp;pg=RA1-PA682&amp;lpg=RA1-PA682&amp;dq=old+crow+caves+debate#v=onepage&amp;q=old%20crow%20caves%20debate&amp;f=false |title=Archaeology of prehistoric native America: an encyclopedia|work= Guy E. Gibbon, Kenneth M. Ames |year=1998 |accessdate= 2010-10-31|isbn= 978-0-8153-0725-9|author1=Gibbon, Guy E|author2=Ames, Kenneth M}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Artifacts have been found in both North and South America which have been [[carbon dating|dated]] to 14,000 [[Before Present|BP]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Noble |first=John |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/04/science/04fossil.html |title=Evidence Supports Earlier Date for People in North America, NYT, April 4, 2008 |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=2008-04-04 |accessdate=2011-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and humans are thought to have reached [[Cape Horn]] at the southern tip of South America by this time. The [[Inuit]] and related peoples arrived separately and at a much later date, probably during the [[first millennium]] CE, moving across the ice from [[Siberia]] into [[Alaska]].

===North America===
{{main|Aboriginal peoples in Canada#History|Native Americans in the United States#History|Pre-Columbian Mexico}}
{{see also|List of archaeological periods (North America)}}
After the migration or migrations, it was several thousand years before the first complex civilizations arose, at the earliest emerging 5000 BCE.{{cn|date=September 2012}} [[Paleo-Indian]] inhabitants of the Americas were [[hunter-gatherer]]s. Many Arctic, Subarctic, and coastal peoples hunted and gathered, while agriculture was adopted in appropriate regions. Within this timeframe, roughly pertaining to the [[History of Mesoamerica (Paleo-Indian)|Paleo-Indian Period]], the [[Archaic period in the Americas|Archaic Period]], the [[Early Woodland Period]], the [[Middle Woodland Period]] and the [[Late Woodland Period]], numerous [[archaeological culture]]s have been identified.

Early [[Paleoamerican]]s soon spread throughout the Americas, diversifying into many hundreds of culturally distinct tribes.&lt;ref&gt;Jacobs (2002).&lt;/ref&gt; Paleo-Indian adaptation across North America was likely characterized by small, highly mobile bands consisting of approximately 20 to 50 members of an extended family. These groups moved from place to place as preferred resources were depleted and new supplies were sought.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi= 10.2307/281017 |last= Kelly |first= Robert L. |coauthors= Lawrence C. Todd |title= Coming into the Country: Early Paleo-Indian Hunting and Mobility |url= http://jstor.org/stable/281017 |journal= American Antiquity |volume=53 |issue= 2 |year=1988 |pages=231–244}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paleo-Indian groups were efficient hunters and carried a variety of tools. These included highly efficient projectile points/knives (PP/Ks) of the types mentioned above{{Ambiguous|date=July 2011}}, as well as less distinctive implements used for butchering and hide processing. During much of the Paleo-Indian period, bands are thought to have subsisted primarily through hunting now-extinct [[megafauna]] such as [[mastodon]] and [[bison antiquus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Breitburg |first= Emanual |coauthors= John B. Broster, Arthur L. Reesman, and Richard G. Strearns |title= Coats-Hines Site: Tennessee's First Paleo-Indian Mastodon Association |journal= Current Research in the Pleistocene |volume=13 |year=1996 |pages=6–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The North American climate finally stabilized by 8000 BCE; climatic conditions were very similar to today's.&lt;ref name=&quot;icaage&quot;&gt;J. Imbrie and K.P.Imbrie, ''Ice Ages: Solving the Mystery'', (Short Hills, NJ: Enslow Publishers) 1979.&lt;/ref&gt;  This led to widespread migration, [[Plant cultivation|cultivation]] and subsequently a  dramatic rise in population all over the Americas.&lt;ref name=&quot;icaage&quot;/&gt;  Over the course of thousands of years, American indigenous peoples domesticated, bred and cultivated a large array of plant species. These species now constitute 50–60% of all crops in cultivation worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allbusiness.com/agriculture-forestry-fishing-hunting/331083-1.html |title=&quot;Native Americans: The First Farmers.&quot; '&amp;#39;AgExporter'&amp;#39; October 1, 1999 |publisher=Allbusiness.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the vastness and variety of the climates, [[ecology]], [[vegetation]], [[fauna]], and landforms, ancient peoples migrated and coalesced separately into numerous separate peoples of distinct [[linguistics|linguistic]] and cultural groups.&lt;ref&gt;Fagan, Brian M. ''People of the Earth: An Introduction to World Prehistory,'' University of California: Harper Collins, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the oral histories of many of the indigenous peoples of the Americas, they have been living there since their genesis, described by a wide range of traditional [[creation stories]].

====Middle Archaic period====
As early as 6500 BCE, people in the Lower Mississippi Valley at the [[Monte Sano (mound complex)|Monte Sano]] site were building complex [[earthworks (archaeology)|earthwork]] [[mound]]s to express their religious ceremonies and cosmology.  This is the earliest dated mound of numerous sites of mound complexes found in present-day [[Louisiana]], [[Mississippi]] and [[Florida]], from thousands of years before the construction of [[pyramids]] in Egypt. Since the late twentieth century, archeologists have explored and dated these sites.  They have found that they were built by [[hunter-gatherer]] societies, whose people occupied the sites on a seasonal basis, and who had not yet developed ceramics. [[Watson Brake]], a large complex of eleven platform mounds, was constructed beginning in 3400 BCE and added to over 500 years. This has changed earlier assumptions that complex construction arose only after societies had adopted agriculture, become sedentary, often developed stratified hierarchy, and generally also developed ceramics. These ancient people had organized to build complex mound projects from a different basis.

====Late Archaic period====
[[File:Louisiana - Poverty Point - Karte (English version).png|thumb|right|Poverty Point, 1500 BCE]]
Until the accurate dating of Watson Brake and similar sites, the oldest mound complex was thought to be [[Poverty Point]], also located in the Lower Mississippi Valley. Built about 1500 BCE, it is the centerpiece of a culture extending over 100 sites on both sides of the Mississippi. The Poverty Point site has earthworks in the form of six concentric half-circles, divided by radial aisles, together with some mounds. The entire complex is nearly a mile across.

Mound building was continued by succeeding cultures, who built numerous sites in the middle Mississippi and Ohio River valleys as well, adding effigy mounds, conical and ridge mounds and other shapes.

====Woodland period====
{{Main|Woodland period}}
[[File:Mound City Chillicothe Ohio HRoe 2008.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Hopewell mounds from the [[Hopewell Culture National Historical Park|Mound City Group]] in Ohio]]
The [[Woodland period]] of North American pre-Columbian cultures refers to the time period from roughly 1000 [[Common Era|BCE]] to 1000 CE in the eastern part of North America. The term &quot;Woodland&quot; was coined in the 1930s and refers to prehistoric sites between the [[Archaic period in the Americas|Archaic period]] and the [[Mississippian culture]]s. The [[Adena culture]] and the ensuing [[Hopewell tradition]] during this period built monumental earthwork architecture and established continent-spanning trade and exchange networks.

This period is considered a developmental stage without any massive changes in a short period, but instead having a continuous development in stone and bone tools, leather working, textile manufacture, tool production, cultivation, and shelter construction. Some Woodland peoples continued to use spears and [[atlatl]]s until the end of the period, when they were replaced by [[bow and arrow|bows and arrows]].

====Mississippian culture====
{{Main|Mississippian Culture}}
[[File:Casqui Parkin Site HROE 2009 01.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Mississippian site in Arkansas, [[Parkin Archeological State Park|Parkin Site]], circa 1539. Illustration by Herb Roe.]]
The Mississippian culture was spread across the Southeast and Midwest from the Atlantic coast to the edge of the plains, from the Gulf of Mexico to the Upper Midwest, although most intensively in the area along the [[Mississippi River]] and [[Ohio River]]. One of the distinguishing features of this culture was the construction of complexes of large earthen [[Platform mound|mounds]] and grand plazas, continuing the [[mound builder (people)|moundbuilding]] traditions of earlier cultures. They grew [[maize]] and other crops intensively, participated in an extensive trade network, and had a complex stratified society.  The Mississippians first appeared around 1000 CE, following and developing out of the less agriculturally intensive and less centralized Woodland period. The largest urban site of this people, [[Cahokia]] &amp;mdash; located near modern [[East St. Louis, Illinois]] &amp;mdash; may have reached a population of over 20,000.  Other chiefdoms were constructed throughout the Southeast, and its trade networks reached to the Great Lakes and Gulf of Mexico. At its peak, between the 12th and 13th centuries, Cahokia was the most populous city in North America, and was not surpassed by European-American cities in population until 1800.  Larger cities were constructed in Mesoamerica and South America. [[Monk's Mound]], the major ceremonial center of Cahokia, remains the largest earthen construction of the prehistoric [[New World]]. The culture reached its peak in ''c.'' 1200-1400, and in most places, it seems to have been in decline before the arrival of the Europeans.

Many Mississippian [[List of sites and peoples visited by the Hernando de Soto Expedition|groups]] were encountered by the [[Hernando de Soto]] Expedition of the 1540s, mostly with disastrous results for both sides. Unlike the Spanish expeditions in Mesoamerica, who conquered vast empires with relatively few men, the de Soto expedition wandered the American Southeast for four years, becoming more bedraggled, losing more men and equipment, and eventually arriving in [[Mexico]] as a fraction of its original size. The local people fared much worse though, as the fatalities of diseases introduced by the expedition devastated the populations and produced much social disruption. By the time Europeans returned a hundred years later, nearly all of the Mississippian groups had vanished, and vast swaths of their territory were virtually uninhabited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Hudson, Charles M.|title =Knights of Spain, Warriors of the Sun| year =1997 | publisher=University of Georgia Press|authorlink=Charles M. Hudson (author)}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clr}}

===Historic tribes===
When the Europeans arrived, [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|indigenous peoples of North America]] had a wide range of lifeways from sedentary, agrarian societies to semi-nomadic [[hunter-gatherer]] societies. Many formed new [[tribe]]s or confederations in response to European colonization. These are often classified by [[cultural region]]s, loosely based on geography. These can include the following:
* [[Arctic]], including [[Aleut people|Aleut]], [[Inuit]], and [[Yupik peoples]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of the Subarctic|Subarctic]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of the Northeastern Woodlands|Northeastern Woodlands]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of the Southeastern Woodlands|Southeastern Woodlands]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of the Great Plains|Great Plains]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of the Great Basin|Great Basin]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of the Northwest Plateau|Northwest Plateau]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of the Pacific Northwest Coast|Northwest Coast]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of California|California]]
* [[Indigenous peoples of the Southwest|Southwest]] ([[Oasisamerica]])

Many pre-Columbian societies were sedentary, such as the [[Pueblo peoples]], [[Mandan]], [[Hidatsa]], and others too numerous to mention, and some established large settlements, even cities, such as [[Cahokia]], in what is now the United States of America. The [[Iroquois|Iroquois League of Nations]] or &quot;People of the Long House&quot; was a politically advanced, democratic society, which is thought by some historians to have influenced the [[United States Constitution]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=The Effect of the Iroquois Constitution on the United States Constitution|first=Janet L.|last= Daly| url=http://www.ipoaa.com/iroquois_constitution_united_states.htm|publisher=Fitchburg State College|year=1997|accessdate=2010-10-31|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=dCMcnBRKR-0C&amp;pg=PA62&amp;dq=Iroquois%2BUS+constitution#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true|title=33 questions about American history you're not supposed to ask|first=Thomas E|last= Woods|page=62|publisher=Crown Forum|year=1st ed, 2007|isbn=978-0-307-34668-1|accessdate=2010-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the [[United States Senate|Senate]] passing a resolution to this effect in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.senate.gov/reference/resources/pdf/hconres331.pdf | accessdate=2008-11-23 | title=H. Con. Res. 331, October 21, 1988 | publisher=United States Senate}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other historians have contested this interpretation and believe the impact was minimal, or did not exist, pointing to numerous differences between the two systems and the ample precedents for the Constitution in European political thought.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shannon&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Shannon | first = TJ | title = Indians and Colonists at the Crossroads of Empire: The Albany Congress of 1754 | location = Ithaca | publisher = [[Cornell University Press]] |year = 2000 | pages = [http://books.google.com/books?id=Gz-ApAxMaPIC&amp;pg=PA6#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 6–8] | isbn = 0-8014-8818-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Tooker&gt;{{cite book |editor=Clifton JA |title=The Invented Indian: cultural fictions and government policies |publisher=Transaction Publishers |location=New Brunswick, N.J., U.S.A |year=1990 |pages= [http://books.google.ca/books?id=ARbVmr941TsC&amp;pg=PA107#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 107–128] | chapter = The United States Constitution and the Iroquois League |isbn=1-56000-745-1 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=2010-11-24 | author = Tooker E}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://hnn.us/articles/12974.html | title=Did the Founding Fathers Really Get Many of Their Ideas of Liberty from the Iroquois? | publisher=[[George Mason University]] | accessdate=2011-01-05 | last = Rakove | first = J | date = 2005-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mesoamerica===
{{see|Mesoamerican chronology}}
[[File:Yaxchilan 1.jpg|thumb|One of the pyramids in the upper level of [[Yaxchilán]]]]
[[File:Telamones Tula.jpg|thumb|right|Atlantes at [[Tula, Hidalgo|Tula]], [[Hidalgo (Mexico)|Hidalgo]]]]

[[Mesoamerica]] is the region extending from central Mexico south to the northwestern border of [[Costa Rica]] that gave rise to a group of stratified, culturally related agrarian civilizations spanning an approximately 3,000-year period before the European discovery of the New World by Christopher Columbus. ''Mesoamerican'' is the adjective generally used to refer to that group of pre-Columbian cultures. This refers to an environmental area occupied by an assortment of ancient cultures that shared religious beliefs, art, architecture, and technology in the Americas for more than three thousand years.

Between 2000 and 300 BCE, complex cultures began to form in Mesoamerica. Some matured into advanced pre-Columbian Mesoamerican civilizations such as the [[Olmec]], [[Teotihuacan]], [[Maya civilization|Maya]], [[Zapotec civilization|Zapotec]], [[Mixtec]], [[Huastec people|Huastec]], [[Tarascan state|Purepecha]], [[Toltec]], and Mexica (also known as the [[Aztecs]], an incorrect name coined in the 1900s by Alexander von Humboltd. The &quot;Aztecs&quot; were actually known as the [[Aztec_Triple_Alliance|Triple Alliance]], since they were three smaller kingdoms loosely united together.&lt;ref name=&quot;1491 by Charles C. Mann&quot;&gt;1491 by Charles C. Mann&lt;/ref&gt;){{Page needed|date=July 2011}}, which flourished for nearly 3,500 years before first contact with Europeans.

These indigenous civilizations are credited with many inventions in: building [[pyramid]]-temples, [[mathematics]], [[astronomy]], medicine, writing, highly accurate [[calendar]]s, fine arts, intensive agriculture, [[engineering]], an [[abacus]] calculator, and complex [[theology]]. They also invented the wheel, but it was used solely as a toy. They also used native [[copper]], [[silver]] and [[gold]] for metalworking, in which they used very advanced methods.

Archaic inscriptions on rocks and rock walls all over northern Mexico (especially in the state of [[Nuevo León]]) demonstrate an early propensity for counting in Mexico. Their number system was [[base 20]] and included [[zero]]. These very early and ancient count-markings were associated with astronomical events and underscore the influence that astronomical activities had upon Mexican natives before the arrival of Europeans. In fact, many of the later Mexican-based civilizations carefully built their cities and ceremonial centers according to specific astronomical events.

The biggest Mesoamerican cities such as [[Teotihuacan]], [[Tenochtitlan]], and [[Cholula (Mesoamerican site)|Cholula]] were among the largest in the world. These cities grew as centers of commerce, ideas, ceremonies, and theology, and they radiated influence outwards onto neighboring cultures in central Mexico.

While many city-states, kingdoms, and empires competed with one another for power and prestige, Mesoamerica can be said to have had five major civilizations: The Olmec, Teotihuacan, the Toltec, the Mexica and the Maya. These civilizations (with the exception of the politically fragmented Maya) extended their reach across Mexico—and beyond—like no others. They consolidated power and distributed influence in matters of trade, art, politics, technology, and theology. Other regional power players made economic and political alliances with these four civilizations over the span of 4,000 years. Many made war with them, but almost all peoples found themselves within these five spheres of influence.

====Olmec civilization====
{{Main|Olmec}}
The earliest known civilization is the Olmec. This civilization established the cultural blueprint by which all succeeding indigenous civilizations would follow in Mexico. Pre-Olmec civilization began with the production of pottery in abundance, around 2300 BCE in the [[Grijalva River]] delta. Between 1600 and 1500 BCE, the Olmec civilization had begun, with the consolidation of power at their capital, a site today known as [[San Lorenzo Tenochtitlán]] near the coast in southeast [[Veracruz]].&lt;ref name=OLMECS&gt;{{cite book|title=The Olmecs : America's First Civilization|authorlink= Richard Diehl|last=Diehl|first=Richard A.|publisher=Thames and Hudson|year=2004|location=London|isbn=0-500-28503-9|pages=9–25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Olmec influence extended across Mexico, into [[Central America]], and along the [[Gulf of Mexico]]. They transformed many peoples' thinking toward a new way of government, pyramid-temples, writing, astronomy, art, mathematics, economics, and religion. Their achievements paved the way for the greatness of the Maya civilization in the east and the civilizations to the west in central Mexico.

====Teotihuacan civilization====
{{Main|Teotihuacan}}
The decline of the Olmec resulted in a power vacuum in Mexico. Emerging from that vacuum was Teotihuacan, first settled in 300 BCE. By 150 CE, Teotihuacan had risen to become the first true [[metropolis]] of what is now called North America. Teotihuacan established a new economic and political order never before seen in Mexico. Its influence stretched across Mexico into Central America, founding new dynasties in the Maya cities of [[Tikal]], [[Copan]], and [[Kaminaljuyú]].  Teotihuacan's influence over the Maya civilization cannot be understated: it transformed political power, artistic depictions, and the nature of economics. Within the city of Teotihuacan was a diverse and cosmopolitan population. Most of the regional ethnicities of Mexico were represented in the city, such as [[Zapotec civilization|Zapotecs]] from the Oaxaca region. They lived in apartment communities where they worked their trades and contributed to the city's economic and cultural prowess. By 500 CE, Teotihuacan had become the largest city in the world. Teotihuacan's economic pull impacted areas in northern Mexico as well. It was a city whose monumental architecture reflected a monumental new era in Mexican civilization, declining in political power about 650 CE&amp;mdash;but lasting in cultural influence for the better part of a millennium, to around 950 CE.
[[File:Uxmal-mexico.jpg|thumb|Maya architecture at [[Uxmal]]]]

====Maya civilization====
{{Main|Maya civilization}}
Contemporary with Teotihuacan's greatness was the greatness of the Maya civilization. The period between 250 CE and 650 CE was a time of intense flourishing of Maya civilized accomplishments. While the many Maya city-states never achieved political unity on the order of the central Mexican civilizations, they exerted a tremendous intellectual influence upon Mexico and Central America. The Maya built some of the most elaborate cities on the continent, and made innovations in mathematics, astronomy, and calendrics. The Mayans also evolved the only true writing system native to the Americas using pictographs and syllabic elements in the form of [[text (literary theory)|text]]s and [[codex|codice]]s inscribed on stone, pottery, wood, or highly perishable books made from bark paper.

====Aztec/Mexica/Triple Alliance civilization====
{{Main|Aztec}}
With the decline of the [[Toltec]] civilization came political fragmentation in the [[Valley of Mexico]]. Into this new political game of contenders to the Toltec throne stepped outsiders: the [[Mexica]]. They were also a desert people, one of seven groups who formerly called themselves &quot;Azteca&quot;, in memory of [[Aztlán]], but they changed their name after years of migrating. Since they were not from the Valley of Mexico, they were initially seen as crude and unrefined in the ways of [[Nahua peoples|Nahua]] civilization. Through political maneuvers and ferocious fighting skills, they managed to become the rulers of Mexico as the head of the 'Triple Alliance' (which included two other &quot;Aztec&quot; cities, Texcoco and Tlacopan).

Latecomers to Mexico's central [[plateau]], the Mexica thought of themselves, nevertheless, as heirs of the civilizations that had preceded them. For them, arts, sculpture, architecture, engraving, feather-mosiac work, and the calendar, were because of the former inhabitants of Tula, the Toltecs.

The Mexica-Aztecs were the rulers of much of central Mexico by about 1400 (while Yaquis, Coras and Apaches commanded sizable regions of northern desert), having subjugated most of the other regional states by the 1470s.  At their peak, 300,000 Mexica{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} presided over a wealthy tribute-empire comprising about 10 million people{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} (almost half of Mexico's 25 million&lt;ref name=&quot;1491 by Charles C. Mann&quot;/&gt;{{Page needed|date=July 2011}} people). The modern name &quot;Mexico&quot; comes from their name.

Their capital, [[Tenochtitlan]], is the site of modern-day capital of Mexico, [[Mexico City]].  At its peak, it was one of the largest cities in the world{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} with population estimates of 300,000{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}. The market established there was the largest ever seen by the [[conquistador]]s on arrival.

===South America===
[[File:Fazenda Colorada.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Geoglyphs on deforested land in the Amazon rainforest.]]
By the first millennium, South America's vast rainforests, mountains, plains, and coasts were the home of tens of millions of people.  Some groups formed permanent settlements. Among those groups were the Chibchas (or &quot;Muiscas&quot; or &quot;Muyscas&quot;), Valdivia and the Tairona. The [[Chibchas]] of [[Colombia]], [[Valdivia Culture|Valdivia]] of [[Ecuador]], the [[Quechuas]] of [[Peru]], and the [[Aymara people|Aymara]] of [[Bolivia]] were the four most important sedentary Amerindian groups in South America. From the 1970s, numerous [[geoglyph]]s have been discovered on deforested land in the [[Amazon rainforest]], [[Brazil]], leading to claims about an ancient complex Amazonian civilization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/15/world/americas/land-carvings-attest-to-amazons-lost-world.html?_r=1|title=Once Hidden by Forest, Carvings in Land Attest to Amazon’s Lost World|author=Simon Romero|publisher=''The New York Times''|date=January 14, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Antiquity |year=2009 |volume=83 |issue=322 |pages=1084–1095 |title=Pre-Columbian geometric earthworks in the upper Purús: a complex society in western Amazonia  |author=Martti Pärssinen, Denise Schaan and Alceu Ranzi |doi= |url=http://antiquity.ac.uk/ant/083/ant0831084.htm |format= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The theory of pre-Columbian contact across the South Pacific Ocean between South America and [[Polynesia]] has received support from several lines of evidence, although solid confirmation remains elusive. A diffusion by human agents has been put forward to explain the pre-Columbian presence in [[Oceania]] of several [[plant cultivation|cultivated plant]] species native to South America, such as the [[bottle gourd]] (''Lagenaria siceraria'') or [[sweet potato]] (''Ipomoea batatas''). Direct [[archaeological]] evidence for such pre-Columbian contacts and transport has been lacking, however. A 2007 paper published in ''[[PNAS]]'' put forward [[DNA]] and archaeological evidence that domesticated [[chicken]]s had been introduced into South America via Polynesia by late pre-Columbian times.&lt;ref&gt;Storey ''et al.'' 2007&lt;/ref&gt; These findings were challenged by a later study published in the same journal, that cast doubt on the dating calibration used and presented alternative [[mtDNA]] analyses that disagreed with a Polynesian genetic origin.&lt;ref&gt;Gongora ''et al.'' 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The origin and dating remains an open issue.  Whether or not early Polynesian-American exchanges occurred, there are no discernible human-genetic, archaeological, cultural or linguistic legacies of that contact.

====Norte Chico or Caral====
{{Main|Norte Chico civilization}}
[[File:Caral-Supe in Peru.jpg|thumb|The ancient city of [[Caral]]]]
On the north-central coast of present-day [[Peru]], Norte Chico or Caral (as known in Peru) was a civilization that emerged around 3000 BCE (contemporary with urbanism's rise in [[Mesopotamia]].) It is considered one of the six [[cradles of civilization]] in the world.  It had a cluster of large-scale urban settlements of which the [[Sacred City of Caral]], in the Supe valley, is one of the largest and best studied sites. Norte Chico or Caral is the oldest known [[civilization]] in the [[Americas]] and persisted until around 1800 BCE.

====Valdivia====
{{Main|Valdivia Culture}}
The [[Valdivia culture]] was concentrated on the coast of [[Ecuador]]. Their existence was recently discovered by archeological findings. Their culture is the oldest in the Americas, spanning from 3500 to 1800 BCE. The Valdivia lived in a community of houses built in a circle or oval around a central plaza.  They were sedentary people who lived off farming and fishing, though occasionally they hunted for deer. From the remains that have been found, scholars have determined that Valdivians cultivated [[maize]], [[kidney beans]], [[squash (plant)|squash]], [[cassava]], hot peppers, and [[cotton]] plants, the last of which was used to make clothing. Valdivian pottery initially was rough and practical, but it became showy, delicate, and big over time. They generally used red and gray colors; and the polished dark red pottery is characteristic of the Valdivia period. In its ceramics and stone works, the Valdivia culture shows a progression from the most simple to much more complicated works.

====Cañaris====
{{Main|Cañaris}}
The Cañari were the indigenous natives of today's Ecuadorian provinces of [[Cañar Province, Ecuador|Cañar]] and [[Azuay]]. They were an elaborate civilization with advanced architecture and complex religious beliefs.  The Inca destroyed and burned most of their remains.  The Cañari's old city was replaced twice, first by the Incan city of Tomipamba, and later by the colonial city of [[Cuenca, Ecuador|Cuenca]]. The city was also believed to be the site of [[El Dorado]], the city of gold from the mythology of Colombia. (see Cuenca)

The Cañari were most notable for having repelled the Incan invasion with fierce resistance for many years until they fell to Tupac Yupanqui. Many of their descendants are still present in Cañar.  The majority did not mix with the colonists or become Mestizos.
[[File:Museolarco.jpg|thumb|[[Larco Museum]] houses the largest private collection of pre-Columbian art. [[Lima]], [[Peru]].]]

====Chavín====
{{Main|Chavín culture}}
The Chavín, a South American preliterate civilization, established a trade network and developed agriculture by 900 BCE, according to some estimates and archeological finds. Artifacts were found at a site called Chavín in modern Peru at an elevation of 3,177 meters. The Chavín civilization spanned from 900 to 300 BCE.

====Chibchas====
{{Main|Chibcha}}
The Chibcha linguistic communities were the most numerous, the most territorially extended and the most socio-economically developed of the pre-Hispanic Colombians. By the 3rd century, the Chibchas had established their civilization in the northern [[Andes]]. At one point, the Chibchas occupied part of what is now [[Panama]], and the high plains of the Eastern Sierra of [[Colombia]].

The areas which they occupied in Colombia were the present-day Departments of Santander (North and South), Boyacá and Cundinamarca.  This is where the first farms and industries were developed.  It is also where the independence movement originated. They are currently the richest areas in Colombia. The Chibcha developed the most populous zone between the Mayan and Inca empires. Next to the [[Quechua people|Quechua]] of Peru and the [[Aymara people|Aymara]] in Bolivia, the Chibcha of the eastern and north-eastern Highlands of Colombia developed the most notable culture among the [[sedentism|sedentary]] indigenous peoples in South America.

In the Oriental Andes, the Chibcha comprised several tribes who spoke the same language (Chibchan). They included the following: the [[Muisca]], [[Guane culture|Guane]], [[Lache people|Lache]], [[Cofán]], and [[Chitareros]].

====Moche====
{{Main|Moche}}
The Moche thrived on the north coast of Peru approximately 1,500&amp;ndash;2,000 years ago.  The heritage of the Moche is seen in their elaborate burials.  Some were recently excavated by [[UCLA]]'s [[Christopher B. Donnan]] in association with the [[National Geographic Society]].

As skilled artisans, the Moche were a technologically advanced people.  They traded with distant peoples such as the Maya.  What has been learned about the Moche is based on study of their ceramic pottery; the carvings reveal details of their daily lives. The [[Larco Museum]] of [[Lima]], [[Peru]] has an extensive collection of such ceramics.  They show that the people practiced [[human sacrifice]], had blood-drinking rituals, and that their religion incorporated non-procreative sexual practices (such as [[fellatio]]).

====Inca Empire====
{{Main|Inca Empire}}
Holding their capital at the great [[cougar]]-shaped city of [[Cuzco]], the Inca civilization dominated the Andes region from 1438 to 1533.  Known as  ''Tawantinsuyu'', or &quot;the land of the four regions&quot;, in [[Quechua languages|Quechua]], the Inca civilization was highly distinct and developed.  Inca rule extended to nearly a hundred linguistic or ethnic communities, some 9 to 14 million people connected by a 25,000 kilometer [[Inca road system|road system]]. Cities were built with precise, unmatched stonework, constructed over many levels of mountain terrain. [[Terrace farming]] was a useful form of agriculture. There is evidence of excellent metalwork and even successful [[brain surgery]] in Inca civilization.
{{wide image|95 - Machu Picchu - Juin 2009.jpg|600px|The iconic [[Machu Picchu]], symbol of the Inca civilization.|center}}
{{clr}}

====Cambeba====
{{Main|Cambeba}}
Also known as the Omagua, Umana and Kambeba, the Cambeba are an [[Indigenous peoples of Brazil|indigenous people]] in Brazil's [[Amazon Basin|Amazon]] valley. The Cambeba were a populous, organized society in the late [[Pre-Columbian South America|Pre-Columbian era]] whose population suffered steep decline in the early years of the [[Columbian Exchange]]. The [[Spanish people|Spanish]] explorer [[Francisco de Orellana]] traversed the [[Amazon River]] during 16th Century and reported densely populated regions running hundreds of kilometers along the river. These populations left no lasting monuments, possibly because they used local wood as their construction material as stone was not locally available. While it is possible Orellana may have exaggerated the level of development among the Amazonians, their semi-nomadic descendants have the odd distinction among tribal indigenous societies of a hereditary, yet landless, [[aristocracy]]. Archaeological evidence has revealed the continued presence of semi-domesticated orchards, as well as vast areas of land enriched with [[terra preta]]. Both of these discoveries, along with Cambeba ceramics discovered within the same archaeological levels suggest that a large and organized civilization existed in the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/09/03/AR2010090302302.html?hpid=artslot |title=Scientists find evidence discrediting theory Amazon was virtually unlivable (Juan Forero. Washington Post, Sunday, September 5, 2010) |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |date=2010-09-05 |accessdate=2011-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Agricultural development==
{{See also|Columbian Exchange|Pre-Columbian engineering in the Americas}}
Early inhabitants of the Americas developed agriculture, developing and breeding [[maize]] (corn) from ears 2–5&amp;nbsp;cm in length to the current size we are familiar with today. [[Potato]]es, [[tomato]]es, [[tomatillo]]s (a husked green tomato), [[pumpkin]]s, [[chili pepper]]s, [[Squash (plant)|squash]], [[bean]]s, [[pineapple]], [[sweet potato]]es, the [[Cereal|grains]] [[quinoa]] and [[amaranth]], [[cocoa bean]]s, [[vanilla]], [[onion]], [[peanut]]s, [[Strawberry|strawberries]], [[Raspberry|raspberries]], [[Blueberry|blueberries]], [[Blackberry|blackberries]], [[papaya]], and [[avocado]]s were among other plants grown by natives. Over two-thirds of all types of food crops grown worldwide are native to the Americas.

The natives began using fire in a widespread manner. Intentional burning of vegetation was taken up to mimic the effects of natural fires that tended to clear forest understories, thereby making travel easier and facilitating the growth of herbs and berry-producing plants that were important for both food and medicines.  This created the [[Pre-Columbian savannas of North America]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Owen2002&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.srs.fs.usda.gov/sustain/report/terra2/terra2.htm|title=Chapter 2 (TERRA–2): The History of Native Plant Communities in the South|last=Owen|first=Wayne|year=2002|work=Southern Forest Resource Assessment Final Report|publisher=U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Southern Research Station|accessdate=2008-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While not as widespread as in other areas of the world (Asia, Africa, Europe), native Americans did have [[livestock]]. In Mexico as well as Central America, natives had domesticated [[deer]] which was used for meat and possibly even milk. Andean societies had [[llama]]s and [[alpaca]]s for the same reasons, as well as for [[Working animal|beasts of burden]]. [[Guinea pig]]s were raised for meat in the [[Andes]]. [[Iguana]]s were another source of meat in Mexico, Central, and northern South America. Domesticated [[turkeys]] were common in Central America and in some regions of North America; they were valued for their meat, feathers, and, possibly (though less likely), eggs. There is documentation of Central Americans utilizing hairless dogs, especially the [[Xoloitzcuintle]] breed, for their meat.

By the 15th century, maize had been transmitted from [[Mexico]] and was being farmed in the [[Mississippi embayment]], as far as the [[East Coast of the United States]], and as far north as southern Canada. Potatoes were utilized by the Inca, and [[chocolate]] was used by the Aztec.

==Genetics==
[[File:Map of gene flow in and out of Beringia.jpg|right|thumb|140px|Schematic illustration of maternal (mtDNA) gene-flow in and out of Beringia, from 25,000 years ago to present.|alt=Schematic illustration of maternal geneflow in and out of Beringia.Colours of the arrows correspond to approximate timing of the events and are decoded in the coloured time-bar. The initial peopling of Berinigia (depicted in light yellow) was followed by a standstill after which the ancestors of indigenous Americans spread swiftly all over the New World while some of the Beringian maternal lineages–C1a-spread westwards. More recent (shown in green) genetic exchange is manifested by back-migration of A2a into Siberia and the spread of D2a into north-eastern America that post-dated the initial peopling of the New World.]]
{{Main|Indigenous Amerindian genetics}}
The  [[haplogroup]] most commonly associated with  [[Indigenous Amerindian genetics]] is [[Haplogroup Q1a3a (Y-DNA)]].&lt;ref name=demographic&gt;{{cite web|year=2003 |url=http://www.ucl.ac.uk/tcga/tcgapdf/Bortolini-AJHG-03-YAmer.pdf |title=Y-Chromosome Evidence for Differing Ancient Demographic Histories in the Americas|format=PDF|work=Department of Biology, University College, London; Departamento de Gene´tica, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Porto Alegre, Brazil; Instituto Venezolano de Investigaciones Cientı´ficas, Caracas, Venezuela; Departamento de Gene´tica, Universidade Federal do Parana´, Curitiba, Brazil; 5Department of Anthropology, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque; 6Laboratorio de Gene´tica Humana, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá´; Victoria Hospital, Prince Albert, Canada; Subassembly of Medical Sciences, Mongolian Academy of Sciences, Ulaanbaatar, Mongolia; Laboratorio de Gene´tica Molecular, Facultad de Medicina, Universidad de Antioquia, Medellı´n, Colombia; Universite´ de Montreal |publisher=University College London 73:524–539|accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Y-DNA, like [[Mitochondrial DNA|mtDNA]], differs from other nuclear [[chromosome]]s in that the majority of the Y chromosome is unique and does not recombine during [[meiosis]]. This has the effect that the historical pattern of mutations can easily be studied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Orgel L |title=Prebiotic chemistry and the origin of the RNA world | url=http://www.d.umn.edu/~pschoff/documents/OrgelRNAWorld.pdf |journal=Crit Rev Biochem Mol Biol |volume=39 |issue=2 |pages=99–123 |pmid=15217990 | doi = 10.1080/10409230490460765|format=PDF |year=2004|accessdate=2010-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The pattern indicates [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Indigenous Amerindians]] experienced two very distinctive genetic episodes; first with the initial-peopling of the [[Americas]], and secondly with [[European colonization of the Americas]].&lt;ref name=SpencerWells2&gt;{{cite book|first1=Spencer |last1=Wells |first2=Mark |last2=Read |title=The Journey of Man - A Genetic Odyssey|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=WAsKm-_zu5sC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=The%20Journey%20of%20Man&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|format=Digitised online by Google books|publisher=Random House|isbn= 0-8129-7146-9|accessdate=2009-11-21|year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Genebase&gt;{{cite web|title=Learn about Y-DNA Haplogroup Q  |first=Wendy Tymchuk Senior Technical Editor |url=http://www.genebase.com/tutorial/item.php?tuId=16|format=Verbal tutorial possible |publisher=Genebase Systems |year=2008|accessdate=2009-11-21|quote=Haplogroups are defined by unique mutation events such as single nucleotide polymorphisms, or SNPs.  These SNPs mark the branch of a haplogroup, and indicate that all descendents of that haplogroup at one time shared a common ancestor. The Y-DNA SNP mutations were passed from father to son over thousands of years. Over time, additional SNPs occur within a haplogroup, leading to new lineages.  These new lineages are considered subclades of the haplogroup.  Each time a new mutation occurs, there is a new branch in the haplogroup, and therefore a new subclade. Haplogroup Q, possibly the youngest of the 20 Y-chromosome haplogroups, originated with the SNP mutation M242 in a man from Haplogroup P that likely lived in Siberia approximately 15,000 to 20,000 years before present}}&lt;/ref&gt; The former is the determinant factor for the number of [[gene]] lineages and founding [[haplotype]]s present in today's Indigenous Amerindian [[Population history of American indigenous peoples|populations]].&lt;ref name=Genebase/&gt;

Human settlement of the [[New World]] occurred in stages from the [[Bering Sea|Bering sea coast line]], with an initial 20,000-year layover on [[Beringia]] for the [[Founder effect|founding population]].&lt;ref name=First&gt;{{cite web  | title = First Americans Endured 20,000-Year Layover - Jennifer Viegas, Discovery News  | url =http://dsc.discovery.com/news/2008/02/13/beringia-native-american.html  | accessdate = 2009-11-18|quote=Archaeological evidence, in fact, recognizes that people started to leave Beringia for the New World around 40,000 years ago, but rapid expansion into North America didn't occur until about 15,000 years ago, when the ice had literally broken  | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}} [http://dsc.discovery.com/news/2008/02/13/beringia-native-american-02.html page 2]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=first2&gt;{{cite web|title=New World Settlers Took 20,000-Year Pit Stop|first=Ker |last=Than|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2008/02/080214-america-layover.html|publisher=National Geographic Society|year=2008|accessdate=2010-01-23|quote=Over time descendants developed a unique culture—one that was different from the original migrants' way of life in Asia but which contained seeds of the new cultures that would eventually appear throughout the Americas}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Microsatellite (genetics)|micro-satellite]] diversity and distributions of the Y lineage specific to South America indicates that certain Amerindian populations have been isolated since the initial colonization of the region.&lt;/small&gt;.&lt;ref name=subclades&gt;{{cite web|title=Summary of knowledge on the subclades of Haplogroup Q|url=http://64.40.115.138/file/lu/6/52235/NTIyMzV9K3szNTc2Nzc=.jpg?download=1|publisher= Genebase Systems|year=2009|accessdate=2009-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Na-Dené]], [[Inuit]] and [[Alaska Natives|Indigenous Alaskan]] populations exhibit [[haplogroup Q (Y-DNA)]] mutations, however are distinct from other indigenous Amerindians with various mtDNA mutations.&lt;ref name=NaDene&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1073/pnas.95.23.13994 |author=Ruhlen M |title=The origin of the Na-Dene |journal=Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America |volume=95 |issue=23 |pages=13994–6 |year=1998 |month=November |pmid=9811914 |pmc=25007 |url=http://www.pnas.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=9811914}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Zhivotovsky&gt;{{cite journal |author=Zegura SL, Karafet TM, Zhivotovsky LA, Hammer MF |title=High-resolution SNPs and microsatellite haplotypes point to a single, recent entry of Native American Y chromosomes into the Americas |journal=Molecular Biology and Evolution |volume=21 |issue=1 |pages=164–75 |year=2004 |month=January |pmid=14595095 |doi=10.1093/molbev/msh009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=inuit&gt;{{cite web|title=mtDNA Variation among Greenland Eskimos. The Edge of the Beringian Expansion|url=http://www.cell.com/AJHG/abstract/S0002-9297%2807%2963257-1 |first=Juliette Saillard, Peter Forster, Niels Lynnerup1, Hans-Jürgen Bandelt and Søren Nørby|work=Laboratory of Biological Anthropology, Institute of Forensic Medicine, University of Copenhagen, Copenhagen, McDonald Institute for Archaeological Research,University of Cambridge, Cambridge, University of Hamburg, Hamburg|year=2000|accessdate=2009-11-22|quote=The relatively lower coalescence time of the entire haplogroup A2 including the shared sub-arctic branches A2b (Siberians and Inuit) and A2a (Eskimos and Na-Dené)  is probably due to secondary expansions of haplogroup A2 from the Beringia area, which would have averaged the overall internal variation of haplogroup A2 in North America.}}&lt;/ref&gt; This suggests that the earliest migrants into the northern extremes of North America and [[Greenland]] derived from later populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Native American Mitochondrial DNA Analysis Indicates That the Amerind and the Nadene Populations Were Founded by Two Independent Migrations|url=http://www.genetics.org/cgi/content/abstract/130/1/153|first=A. Torroni, T. G. Schurr, C. C. Yang, EJE. Szathmary, R. C. Williams, M. S. Schanfield, G. A. Troup, W. C. Knowler, D. N. Lawrence, K. M. Weiss and D. C. Wallace|work=Center for Genetics and Molecular Medicine and Departments of Biochemistry and Anthropology, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, Georgia|publisher=Genetics Society of America. Vol 130, 153-162|accessdate=2009-11-28|quote=The divergence time for the Nadene portion of the HaeIII np 663 lineage was about 6,000-10,000 years. Hence, the ancestral Nadene migrated from Asia independently and considerably more recently than the progenitors of the Amerinds}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==See also==
{{Portal|History|Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Indigenous peoples of North America|Aboriginal peoples in Canada}}
* [[List of pre-Columbian civilizations]]
*[[Metallurgy in pre-Columbian America]]
* [[Pre-Inca cultures]] in Peru
* [[Pre-Columbian trans-oceanic contact]]
* [[Pre-Columbian population]]
* ''[[1491: New Revelations of the Americas Before Columbus]]''
{{clr}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

;Biblogaphy
{{refbegin|30em}}
*{{cite journal |author=Brown, Michael D. |coauthors=Seyed H. Hosseini, Antonio Torroni, Hans-Jürgen Bandelt, Jon C. Allen, Theodore G. Schurr, Rosaria Scozzari, Fulvio Cruciani, and Douglas C. Wallace |year=1998 |month=December |title=mtDNA haplogroup X: An ancient link between Europe/Western Asia and North America? |journal=[[American Journal of Human Genetics]] |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=[[Cell Press]]|volume=63 |issue=6 |pages=1852–1861 |pmc=1377656  |doi=10.1086/302155 |oclc=207127248 |issn=0002-9297 |pmid=9837837}}
*{{cite book |author=Fernández-Armesto, Felipe |authorlink=Felipe Fernández-Armesto |year= 1987 |title=Before Columbus: Exploration and Colonisation from the Mediterranean to the Atlantic: 1229-1492 |series=New studies in medieval history series |location=Basingstoke, Hampshire |publisher=[[Macmillan Education]] |isbn=0-333-40382-7 |oclc=20055667}}
*{{cite journal |author=Gongora, Jaime |coauthors=Nicolas J. Rawlence, Victor A. Mobegi, Han Jianlin, Jose A. Alcalde, Jose T. Matus, Olivier Hanotte, Chris Moran, J. Austin, Sean Ulm, Atholl J. Anderson, Greger Larson, and Alan Cooper |year=2008 |month=July |title=Indo-European and Asian origins for Chilean and Pacific chickens revealed by mtDNA |journal=[[Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences]] |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=[[United States National Academy of Sciences|NAS]] |volume=105 |issue=30 |pages=10308–10313 |pmc=2492461 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0801991105 |issn=0027-8424 |oclc=237029642 |pmid=18663216}}
*{{cite book |author=Mann, Charles C. |authorlink=Charles C. Mann |year=2005 |title=[[1491: New Revelations of the Americas Before Columbus]] |location=New York |publisher=[[Knopf]] |isbn=978-1-4000-4006-3 |oclc=56632601 }}
*{{cite journal |author=Schurr, Theodore G. |coauthors=Scott W. Ballinger, Yik-Yuen Gan, Judith A. Hodge, D. Andrew Merriwether, Dale N. Lawrence, William C. Knowler, Kenneth M. Weiss, and Douglas C. Wallace |year=1990 |month=March |title=Amerindian mitochondrial DNAs have rare Asian mutations at high frequencies, suggesting they derived from four primary maternal lineages |journal=[[American Journal of Human Genetics]] |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=[[Cell Press]] |volume=46 |issue=3 |pages=613–623 |pmc=1683611 |oclc=120356210|issn=0002-9297 |pmid=1968708}}
*{{cite book |author=Sorenson, John L. |authorlink=John L. Sorenson |coauthors=and Carl L. Johannessen |year=2006 |chapter=Biological evidence for pre-Columbian transoceanic voyages |editor=Victor H. Mair (ed.) |title=Contact and Exchange in the Ancient World |series=Perspectives on the global past series |location=Honolulu |publisher=[[University of Hawaiʻi Press|University of Hawai{{okina}}i Press]] |pages=238–297 |isbn=0-8248-2884-4 |oclc=62896389}}
*{{cite journal |author=Storey, Alice A. |coauthors=José Miguel Ramírez, Daniel Quiroz, David V. Burley, David J. Addison, Richard Walter, Atholl J. Anderson, Terry L. Hunt, J. Stephen Athens, Leon Huynen, and Elizabeth A. Matisoo-Smith |year=2007 |month=June |title=Radiocarbon and DNA evidence for a pre-Columbian introduction of Polynesian chickens to Chile |journal=[[Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences]] |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=[[United States National Academy of Sciences|NAS]] |volume=104 |issue=25 |pages=10335–10339 |doi=10.1073/pnas.0703993104 |pmc=1965514 |issn=0027-8424 |oclc=144764031 |pmid=17556540}}
*{{cite book |author=Wright, Ronald |authorlink=Ronald Wright |year=2005 |title=Stolen Continents: 500 Years of Conquest and Resistance in the Americas |edition=1st Mariner Books |location=Boston, Massachusetts|publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin]] |isbn=0-618-49240-2 |oclc=57511483}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.tiwanakuarcheo.net/10_prehistory/GUIAintro.html Central Andes Prehistoric Sequence]
* [http://www.museocaprai.it/en/tecnica_Tessuti_Precolombiani.htm Pre Columbian textiles – Virtual Museum of Textile Arts]
* [http://www.precolumbian.us/ McGuiness Publishing site on pre-Columbian archaeological topics]
* [http://www.laiesken.net/arqueologia/index_en.html Arqueologia Iberoamericana] – Open access international scientific journal devoted to the archaeological study of the American and Iberian peoples. It contains numerous research articles on pre-Columbian America.

{{Navboxes|list =
{{Pre-Columbian}}
{{Pre-Columbian North America}}
{{Indigenous peoples of the Americas}}
{{Cultural areas of indigenous North Americans}}
}}

[[Category:Pre-Columbian era| ]]
[[Category:History of indigenous peoples of the Americas|+]]
[[Category:Historical eras]]

[[ar:عصر قبل كولومبي]]
[[bg:Доколумбова Америка]]
[[ca:Amèrica precolombina]]
[[cs:Předkolumbovská Amerika]]
[[da:Præcolumbiansk]]
[[de:Präkolumbisch]]
[[es:América precolombina]]
[[eo:Antaŭkolumba Ameriko]]
[[fa:دوران پیشاکلمبی]]
[[fr:Civilisation précolombienne]]
[[gl:América precolombina]]
[[ko:미국의 역사 (1493년 이전)]]
[[hr:Pretkolumbovska Amerika]]
[[id:Pra-Columbus]]
[[it:Civiltà precolombiane]]
[[he:התקופה הפרה-קולומביאנית]]
[[la:America praecolumbiana]]
[[mk:Претколумбовски период]]
[[ms:Pra-Columbia]]
[[nl:Precolumbiaans]]
[[ja:先コロンブス期]]
[[no:Førkolumbisk]]
[[nn:Førkolumbisk]]
[[pt:Era pré-colombiana]]
[[ro:Civilizații precolumbiene]]
[[ru:Доколумбовы цивилизации]]
[[simple:Pre-Columbian]]
[[sk:Predkolumbovská kultúra]]
[[sl:Predkolumbovska Amerika]]
[[sh:Pretkolumbovska era]]
[[fi:Esikolumbiaaninen]]
[[sv:Förcolumbiansk tid]]
[[tr:Kolomb öncesi Amerika]]
[[uk:Культура доколумбової Америки]]
[[zh-classical:先哥倫布]]
[[zh:前哥倫布時期]]</text>
      <sha1>09ltjfy46s00kc1ann8ffbansuuoryr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
