<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Prehistory of Australia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2645668</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520941731</id>
      <parentid>519478991</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T19:36:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>109.152.169.197</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>undo vandalism</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21895">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}
{{Use Australian English|date=January 2012}}
{{History of Australia}}
The '''prehistory of Australia''' is the period between the first human habitation of the Australian continent and the first definitive sighting of Australia by Europeans in 1606, which marks the start of consistent documentation of Australia. This period is estimated to have lasted between 40,000 and 60,000 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.stonepages.com/news/archives/000236.html | title=Australia colonized earlier than previously thought? | date= 24 July 2003 | accessdate=2 November 2007 | publisher=stonepages.com, Paola Arosio &amp; Diego Meozzi }} – reporting on news in ''The West Australian (19 July 2003)''&lt;/ref&gt; 

This era is referred to as [[prehistory]] rather than history because of the scarcity of written records of human events in Australia which pre-date this contact.

==Arrival==
:''See also [[Early human migrations#South Asia and Australia]]''
[[File:Sunda shelf.jpg|thumb|left|340px|The map shows the probable extent of land and water at the time of the last glacial maximum and when the sea level was probably more than 150m lower than today; it illustrates the formidable sea obstacle that migrants would have faced.]]
The minimum widely-accepted timeframe for the arrival of humans in Australia is placed at least 40,000 years ago.&lt;ref&gt;Hiscock, Peter. (2008). ''Archaeology of Ancient Australia''. Routledge: London. ISBN 0-415-33811-5&lt;/ref&gt; Many sites dating from this time period have been excavated. 

Archaeological evidence indicates human habitation at the upper [[Swan River (Western Australia)|Swan River, Western Australia]] by about 40,000 years ago. [[Tasmania]], which was connected to the continent by a land bridge, was inhabited at least 30,000 years ago.&lt;ref&gt;Lourandos, pp84-87&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/08/science/08abor.html?ex=1187236800&amp;en=3051874ea83b3233&amp;ei=5070 | title=From DNA Analysis, Clues to a Single Australian Migration | work=The New York Times | date=8 May 2007 | last=Wade | first=Nicholas }}&lt;/ref&gt; Others have claimed that some sites are up to 60,000 years old, but these claims are not universally accepted.&lt;ref&gt;Lourandos, pp87-88&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Palynology|Palynological]] evidence from South Eastern Australia suggests an increase in fire activity dating from around 120,000 years ago. This has been interpreted as representing human activity, but the dating of the evidence has been strongly challenged.&lt;ref&gt;Lourandos, p88&lt;/ref&gt;  

Charles Dortch has identified chert and calcrete flake stone tools, found at [[Rottnest Island]] in Western Australia, as possibly dating to at least 50,000 years ago. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.stonepages.com/news/archives/000236.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hesp, Patrick A., Murray-Wallace, Colin V. and C. E. Dortch, (1999), &quot;Aboriginal occupation on Rottnest Island, Western Australia, provisionally dated by Aspartic Acid Racemisation assay of land snails to greater than 50 ka&quot; (Australian Archaeology, No 49 (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;  This seems to tie in accurately with [[Uranium-thorium dating|U/Th]] and [[Carbon-14 dating|14C]] results of a flint tool found embedded in Tamala limestone (Aminozone C)&lt;ref&gt;Charles Dortch, West Australian 23 June 2003&lt;/ref&gt; as well as both mtDNA and Y chromosome studies on the genetic distance of Australian Aboriginal genomes from African and other Eurasian ones.

Migration was achieved during the closing stages of the [[Pleistocene]], when sea levels were  much lower than they are today. Repeated episodes of extended [[Glacier|glaciation]] during the Pleistocene [[epoch (geology)|epoch]], resulted in decreases of sea levels by more than 100 metres in Australasia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lourandos, p80&quot;&gt;Lourandos, p80&lt;/ref&gt; 

The continental coastline extended much further out into the [[Timor Sea]], and Australia and [[New Guinea]] formed a single landmass (known as [[Australia (continent)|Sahul]]), connected by an extensive [[land bridge]] across the [[Arafura Sea]], [[Gulf of Carpentaria]] and [[Torres Strait]]. Nevertheless, the sea still presented a major obstacle so it is theorised that these ancestral people reached Australia by island hopping.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lourandos, p80&quot;/&gt; Two routes have been proposed. One follows an island chain between [[Sulawesi]] and New Guinea and the other reaches North Western Australia via [[Timor]].&lt;ref&gt;Lourandos, p81&lt;/ref&gt; However, an alternative theory, involving accidental colonisation as a result of tsunamis, has recently been proposed.&lt;ref&gt;[[Rupert Gerritsen]] (2011) ''Beyond the Frontier: Explorations in Ethnohistory'', Batavia Online Publishing: Canberra. pp.70–103. ISBN 978-0-9872141-4-0&lt;/ref&gt; 

The sharing of animal and plant species between [[Australia-New Guinea]] and nearby [[Indonesia]]n islands is another consequence of the early land bridges, which closed when sea levels rose with the end of the last glacial period. The sea level stabilised to near its present levels about [[4th millennium BC|6000 years ago]], flooding the land bridge between Australia and New Guinea.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

It is unknown how many populations settled in Australia prior to European colonisation. Both &quot;trihybrid&quot; and single-origin hypotheses have received extensive discussion;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.sydneyline.com/Pygmies%20Extinction.htm | last = Windschuttle | first = Keith  | coauthors = Gillin, Tim  | title= The extinction of the Australian pygmies | month =  June | year =  2002 | accessdate=2 November 2007 | publisher=Keith Windschuttle (The Sydney Line)}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, the issue has become [[politicised]], with the assumption of a single origin tied in to ethnic solidarity, and multiple entry used to justify white seizure of Aboriginal lands {{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}. There is little objective data to settle the issue one way or the other.  

[[Human Genome Diversity Project|Human genomic]] differences are being studied to find possible answers, but there is still insufficient evidence to distinguish a &quot;wave invasion model&quot; from a &quot;single settlement&quot; one. Some Y chromosomal studies indicate a recent influx of Y chromosomes from the Indian subcontinent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal 
 |url=http://nitro.biosci.arizona.edu/zdownload/papers/CurrentBiology.pdf | title=Gene Flow from the Indian Subcontinent to Australia: Evidence from the Y Chromosome | author=Alan J. Redd | coauthors = June Roberts-Thomson, Tatiana Karafet, Michael Bamshad, Lynn B. Jorde,J.M. Naidu, Bruce Walsh, Michael F. Hammer  | date = 16 April 2002  | journal=Current Biology  | volume = 12  | pages = 673–677  | publisher=Elsevier Science  | location = Orlando, Florida, USA  | format = pdf | accessdate=2 November 2007 | doi=10.1016/S0960-9822(02)00789-3 
 |pmid=11967156 
 |issue=8 
 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Advent of fire farming and megafauna extinctions==
Archaeological evidence (in the form of charcoal) indicates that fire, already a growing part of the Australian landscape, became much more frequent as hunter-gatherers used it as a tool to drive game, to produce a green flush of new growth to attract animals, and to open up impenetrable forest.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} Densely grown areas became more open [[sclerophyll]] forest, open forest became grassland. Fire-tolerant species became predominant: in particular, [[eucalyptus]], [[acacia]], and grasses.

[[File:Bassian plain 14000 BP.jpg|thumb|300px|right|The shoreline of Tasmania and Victoria about 14,000 years ago, as sea levels were rising, showing some of the human archaeological sites]]
The changes to the fauna were even more dramatic: the [[megafauna]], species significantly larger than humans, disappeared, and many of the smaller species were wiped out too. All told, about 60 different vertebrates became extinct, including the [[Diprotodon]] family (very large marsupial herbivores that looked rather like hippos), several large flightless birds, carnivorous kangaroos, a five metre lizard and [[Meiolania]], a tortoise the size of a small car.{{cn|date=June 2012}}

The direct cause of the mass extinctions is uncertain: it may have been fire, hunting, climate change or a combination of all or any of these factors, although the rapid decline of many species means the once popular [[climate change]] explanation is no longer favoured. With no large herbivores to keep the understorey vegetation down and rapidly recycle soil nutrients with their dung,  fuel build-up became more rapid and fires burned hotter, further changing the landscape.

The period from 18,000 to 15,000 years ago saw increased aridity of the continent with lower temperatures and less rainfall than currently prevails. Between 16,000 and 14,000 years BP the rate of sea level rise was most rapid rising about 50 feet in 300 years according to Peter D. Ward.&lt;ref&gt;Peter D. Ward, pp30, ''The Flooded Earth. Our Future in a World Without Ice Caps'', Basic Books, New York, 2010, ISBN 978-0-465-00949-7&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the Pleistocene, roughly 13,000 years ago, the [[Torres Strait]] connection, the Bassian Plain between modern-day [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] and [[Tasmania]], and the link from [[Kangaroo Island]] began disappearing under the rising sea.  

From that time on, the [[Tasmanian Aborigines]] were geographically isolated. By 9,000 years ago small islands in [[Bass Strait]], as well as [[Kangaroo Island]] were no longer inhabited.

Linguistic and genetic evidence shows that there has been long-term contact between Australians in the far north and the [[Austronesian]] people of modern-day New Guinea and the islands, but that this appears to have been mostly trade with a little intermarriage, as opposed to direct colonisation.  [[Makassar|Macassan]] [[Proa|praus]] are also recorded in the Aboriginal stories from [[Broome, Western Australia|Broome]] to the [[Gulf of Carpentaria]], and there were some semi-permanent settlements established, and cases of Aboriginal settlers finding a home in Indonesia.

==Culture and technology==
The last 5000 years were characterised by a general amelioration of the climate and an increase in temperature and rainfall and the development of a sophisticated [[tribe|tribal social structure]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} The main items of trade were songs and dances, along with [[flint]], precious stones, shells, seeds, spears, food items, etc. 

The [[Pama–Nyungan languages|Pama–Nyungan language]] phylum which extends from [[Cape York Peninsula|Cape York]] to the south west covered all of Australia except for the south east and Arnhem Land. There was also a marked continuity of religious ideas and stories throughout the country, with some [[songlines]] crossing from one side of the continent to the other. 

The initiation of young boys and girls into adult knowledge was marked by ceremony and feasting. Behaviour was governed by strict rules regarding responsibilities to and from uncles, aunts, brothers and sisters as well as in-laws. The [[Australian Aboriginal kinship|kinship systems]] observed by many communities included a division into [[Kinship#Lineages, clans, phratries, moieties, and matrimonial sides|moieties]], with restrictions on intermarrying dictated by the moiety an individual belonged to.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

Describing prehistoric Aboriginal culture and society during her 1999 [[Boyer Lectures|Boyer Lecture]], Australian historian and anthropologist [[Inga Clendinnen]] explained:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;They [...] developed steepling thought-structures – intellectual edifices so comprehensive that every creature and plant had its place within it. They travelled light, but they were walking [[atlas]]es, and walking encyclopedias of [[natural history]]. [...] Detailed observations of [[nature]] were elevated into drama by the development of multiple and multi-level narratives: narratives which made the intricate relationships between these observed phenomena memorable.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These dramatic narratives identified the recurrent and therefore the timeless and the significant within the fleeting and the idiosyncratic. They were also very human, charged with [[morality|moral]] significance but with pathos, and with humour, too – after all, the [[Dreamtime]] creatures were not austere divinities, but fallible beings who happened to make the world and everything in it while going about their creaturely business. Traditional Aboriginal culture effortlessly fuses areas of understanding which Europeans 'naturally' keep separate: ecology, cosmology, theology, social morality, art, comedy, tragedy – the observed and the richly imagined fused into a seamless whole.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Inga Clendinnen, [[Boyer Lectures]], [http://www.abc.net.au/rn/boyers/stories/s71107.htm &quot;Inside the Contact Zone: Part 1&quot;], 5 December 1999&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Political and religious power rested with community elders rather than hereditary chiefs. Disputes were settled communally in accordance with an elaborate system of tribal law. Vendettas and feuds were not uncommon, especially when laws and taboos were broken.

Cremation of the dead was practised by 25,000 years ago, possibly before anywhere else on Earth, and early artwork in [[Koonalda Cave]], [[Nullarbor Plain]], has been dated back to 20,000 years ago.&lt;ref&gt;[[Geoffrey Blainey|BLAINEY, Geoffrey]], ''Triumph of the Nomads: A History of Aboriginal Australia'', 1976, ISBN 0-87951-084-6, p.84&lt;/ref&gt;

It has been estimated that in 1788 there were approximately half a million [[Australian Aborigine|Australian Aboriginal people]], although other estimates have put the figure as high as a million or more.&lt;ref&gt;Neil Thomson, pp153, ''Indigenous Australia: Indigenous Health'' in James Jupp (ed), ''The Australian people: an encyclopedia of the nation, its people and their Origins'', Cambridge University Press, 2001. ISBN 052180789 This article says the likely aboriginal population of Australia in 1788 was around 750,000 or even over a million. There was also a chart from the Australian Bureau of Statistics – Experimental Projections of the Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Population, Canberra, ABS, 1998 – with estimated populations for each state and for Australia as a whole total being 418,841. Epidemics of smallpox occurred in 1789 and 1829–31. The article notes that there is evidence these epidemics traveled several hundred kilometres 'severely depopulating' tribes who had not yet had first contact with Europeans.&lt;/ref&gt; These populations formed hundreds of distinct cultural and language groups. Most were hunter-gatherers with rich oral histories and advanced land-management practices developed over thousands of years since the ecological destruction of the initial colonisation phase.

In the most fertile and populous areas, they lived in semi-permanent settlements. In the fertile [[Murray River|Murray Basin]], the gathering and hunting economies to be found elsewhere on the continent had in large part given way to fish farming.  Sturt's expedition along the Murray led to a belief that the Aboriginal groups there were practicing agriculture as a result of the presence of large hay-stacks, used as permanent grain stores.&lt;ref&gt;Flood, Josephine (1984), &quot;Archaeology of the Dreamtime&quot; (Uni of Hawaii Press)&lt;/ref&gt;

Little interest was shown by white settlers in the bulk of the Aboriginal people, and so little is known of their cultures and languages. Diseases decimated some indigenous populations just prior to the period where most Aborigines came into direct contact with Europeans. When [[James Cook|Cook]] first claimed [[New South Wales]] for Britain in 1770, the native population may have consisted of as many as 600 distinct tribes speaking 200–250  distinct [[Australian Aboriginal languages|languages]] and over 600 distinct [[dialects]] and sub-dialects.&lt;ref&gt;RMW Dixon, pp18, ''The Languages of Australia'', Cambridge University Press, 2010. ISBN 978110801785 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Invalid length.}} Dixon says &quot;There were around 600 distinct tribes in Australia, speaking between them about 200 different languages.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kerry Mallan, pp53, ''Language Politics and Minority Rights'' in Witold Tulasiewicz, Joseph I. Zajda (eds), ''Language awareness in the curriculum'', James Nicholas Publishers, Albert Park, ISBN 1-875408-21-5 Estimates 200 languages and over 600 dialects in 1788&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Harold Koch, pp23 ''An overview of Australian traditional languages'' in Gerhard Leitner, Ian G. Malcolm (eds), ''The habitat of Australia's aboriginal languages: past, present and future'' Says that some 250 distinct languages present in 1788&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contact outside Australia==
The people living along the northern coastline of Australia, in the [[Kimberley region of Western Australia|Kimberley]], [[Arnhem Land]], [[Gulf of Carpentaria]] and [[Cape York Peninsula|Cape York]] had encounters with various visitors for many thousands of years. People and traded goods moved freely between Australia and New Guinea up to and even after the eventual flooding of the [[land bridge]] by rising sea levels, which was completed about 6000 years ago. 

However, trade and intercourse between the separated lands continued across the newly-formed [[Torres Strait]], whose 150&amp;nbsp;km-wide channel remained readily navigable with the chain of [[Torres Strait Islands]] and [[coral reefs|reefs]] affording intermediary stopping points. The islands were settled by different seafaring [[Melanesian]] cultures such as the [[Torres Strait Islanders]] over 2500 years ago, and cultural interactions continued via this route with the Aboriginal people of northeast Australia.

Indonesian &quot;[[Bajau]]&quot; fishermen from the [[Maluku Islands|Spice Islands]] (e.g. [[Banda Islands|Banda]]) have fished off the coast of Australia for hundreds of years. [[Macassan contact with Australia|Macassan]] traders from [[Sulawesi]] regularly visited the coast of northern Australia to fish for trepang, an edible [[sea cucumber (food)|sea cucumber]] to trade with the Chinese since at least the early 18th century. [[Tamil people|Tamil]] sea-farers also had knowledge of Australia and [[Polynesia]] before European contact.&lt;ref name=&quot;tamils_spread&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Origin and Spread of the Tamils|last=Dikshitar|first=V. R. Ramachandra|authorlink=V. R. Ramachandra Dikshitar|publisher=Adyar Library|year=1947|pages= 30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There was a high degree of cultural exchange, evidenced in [[Australian Aboriginal art|Aboriginal rock and bark paintings]], the introduction of technologies such as dug-out canoes and items such as tobacco and tobacco pipes, Macassan words in Aboriginal languages (e.g. ''Balanda'' for white person), and descendants of [[Malay race|Malay]] people in Australian Aboriginal communities and vice versa, as a result of intermarriage and migration.

The myths of the people of [[Arnhem Land]] have preserved accounts of the trepang-catching, rice-growing [[Baijini]] people, who, according to the myths, were in Australia in the earliest times, before the Macassans. The Baijini have been variously interpreted by modern researchers as a different group of presumably South East Asian people, such as [[Bajau]] visitors to Australia who may have visited Arnhem Land before the Macassans,
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
|first=Ronald Murray |last=Berndt|first2= Catherine Helen |last2=Berndt
|publisher=F. W. Cheshire |year=1954
|title=Arnhem Land: its history and its people
|series=Volume 8 of Human relations area files: Murngin
|url= http://books.google.com/?id=MosgAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=baijini+bajau&amp;q=+bajau#search_anchor
|page=34
|ref=harv
|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Berndt|2005|p=55}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a mythological reflection of the experiences of some Yolŋu people who have travelled to [[Sulawesi]] with the Macassans and came back,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Swain|1993|p=170}}&lt;/ref&gt; or, in more fringe views, even as visitors from China.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
|first=Joseph |last=Needham
|publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=1971
|isbn=0-521-07060-0
|title=Science and civilisation in China |volume= 4
|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=l6TVhvYLaEwC&amp;pg=PA538&amp;dq=baijini
|page=538
|ref=harv
|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Australian archaeology]]
*[[Ten Canoes]], a 2006 film about Australian prehistory
*[[Mungo Man]]
*[[Dreamtime]], Aboriginal mythology about Australian prehistory

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
* Lourandos, H., ''Continent of Hunter-Gatherers: New Perspectives in Australian Prehistory'' (Cambridge University Press, 1997)
* Isaacs, Jennifer (ed.), ''Australian Dreaming: 40,000 Years of Aboriginal History'' (New Holland Publishers, 2005, pp.&amp;nbsp;304, ISBN 1-74110-258-8)
* [[Geoffrey Blainey|Blainey, Geoffrey]], ''Triumph of the Nomads: A History of Aboriginal Australia'' (The Overlook Press, 1976, pp.&amp;nbsp;285, ISBN 0-87951-084-6)

{{Australia topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Prehistory Of Australia}}
[[Category:Articles with inconsistent citation formats]]
&lt;!--This is not intended to be a precise year, but it serves the purpose of putting this article in the right place in the sequence of era articles at the top of the category.--&gt;
[[Category:Australian Aboriginal culture]]
[[Category:History of Indigenous Australians]]
[[Category:Prehistoric Oceania|Australia]]
[[Category:National prehistories]]
[[Category:History of Australia before 1788]]

[[es:Prehistoria de Australia]]
[[fr:Préhistoire de l'Australie]]
[[ga:Réamhstair na hAstráile]]
[[lt:Australijos priešistorė]]
[[ro:Preistoria Australiei]]
[[ru:Доисторическая Австралия]]
[[simple:Ancient Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>gxno56np8nnqkxey8s568t9bfp1t0gy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
