<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Prussian Crusade</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13582734</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521245379</id>
      <parentid>520161295</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T19:33:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Diwenck</username>
        <id>17544668</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Invitation of the Teutonic Knights */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33996">[[Image:Baltic Tribes c 1200.svg|thumb|300px|Baltic tribes and Prussian clans ca. 1200.]]

The '''Prussian Crusade''' was a series of 13th-century campaigns of [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] [[Crusades|crusaders]], primarily led by the [[Teutonic Knights]], to [[Christianization|Christianize]] the [[Prussian mythology|pagan]] [[Old Prussians]]. Invited after earlier unsuccessful expeditions against the Prussians by [[Poland|Polish]] princes, the Teutonic Knights began campaigning against the Balts in 1230. By the end of the century, having quelled several [[Prussian Uprisings]], the Knights had established control over Prussia and administered the Prussians through their [[monastic state of the Teutonic Knights|monastic state]].

==Early missions and conflicts==
{{Campaignbox Crusades}}
[[Wulfstan of Hedeby]], an agent of [[Alfred of Wessex]], recorded the seafaring and cattle-herding Prussians as a strong and independent nation.&lt;ref&gt;Christiansen, p. 38&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mieszko I of Poland|Mieszko I]] of the [[Polans (western)|Polans]] tried to extend his realm from land he had just conquered around the mouth of the [[Oder]] as far as Prussia.&lt;ref&gt;Gieysztor, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; [[Boleslaw I of Poland]] sent [[Adalbert of Prague]] to preach among the Prussians in 997, but the missionary was killed by the pagans. After some initial success among the Prussians, Adalbert's successor, [[Bruno of Querfurt]], was also killed in 1009.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, pp. 22-23&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Poles]] waged war with the neighboring Prussians, [[Sudovians]], and [[Wends]] over the following two centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gieysztor, p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://eprints.infodiv.unimelb.edu.au/archive/00001942/01/Upload_Recent_Issues_in_Polish_Historiography_of_the_Crusades.pdf Recent Issues in Polish Historiography of the Crusades]  Darius von Güttner Sporzyński. 2005&lt;/ref&gt; While the Poles sought the conversion of the Prussians and control of their land, the Prussians engaged in lucrative raids for slaves in the bordering territories of [[Chełmno Land]] and [[Masovia]].&lt;ref&gt;Urban, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; Many Prussians nominally accepted [[baptism]] only to revert to pagan beliefs after hostilities ended. [[Henry of Sandomierz]] was killed fighting the Prussians in 1166.&lt;ref&gt;Gieysztor, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bolesław IV the Curly|Boleslaw IV]] and [[Casimir II of Poland|Casimir II]] each led large armies into Prussia; while Boleslaw's forces were defeated in [[guerilla warfare]], Casimir imposed peace until his death in 1194.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; King [[Valdemar II of Denmark|Valdemar II]] of [[Denmark]] supported Danish expeditions against [[Sambia|Samland]] until his capture by [[Henry, Count of Schwerin]], in 1223.

In 1206, the [[Cistercians|Cistercian]] bishop [[Christian of Oliva]], with the support of the King of Denmark and Polish dukes, found a better reception than expected upon his arrival in the war-torn Chełmno Land. Inspired, he travelled to [[Rome]] to prepare for a larger mission. When he returned to [[Chełmno]] in 1215, however, Christian found the Prussians hostile, possibly out of outrage at the actions of the [[Livonian Order|Sword-Brothers]] in [[Livonia]]&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; or fear of Polish expansion.&lt;ref&gt;Urban, p. 51&lt;/ref&gt; The pagan Prussians invaded Chełmno Land, Masovia, and [[Pomerellia]],&lt;ref name=&quot;G94&quot;&gt;Gieysztor, p. 94&lt;/ref&gt; besieged Chełmno and [[Lubawa]], and forced converts to return to the old beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the growing intensity of attacks,&lt;ref&gt;Gieysztor, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Honorius III]] sent a [[papal bull]] to Christian in March 1217 allowing him to begin preaching a [[crusades|crusade]] against the militant Prussians. The following year the pagans attacked Chełmno Land and Masovia again, plundering 300 cathedrals and churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;W33&quot;&gt;Wyatt, p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; Duke [[Conrad of Masovia]] succeeded in expelling the Prussians by paying a huge tribute, which only encouraged the Prussians, however.&lt;ref name=&quot;W33&quot;/&gt;

==Crusade of 1222/23==

[[Image:Prussian clans 13th century.png|thumb|300px|Map of the Prussian clans in the 13th century.]]

Honorius III called for a crusade under the leadership of Christian of Oliva and chose as [[papal legate]] the Archbishop of [[Gniezno]], [[Wincenty I Niałek]].&lt;ref name=&quot;W33&quot;/&gt; German and Polish crusaders began gathering in Masovia in 1219, but serious planning only began in 1222 upon the arrival of nobles such as Duke [[Henry II the Pious|Henry of Silesia]], Archbishop Laurentius of [[Wrocław]], and Laurentius of [[Lebus]]. Numerous Polish nobles began endowing Christian's [[Bishopric of Prussia]] with estates and castles in Chełmno Land during the meantime. The lords agreed that the primary focus was to rebuild the defenses of Chełmno Land, especially Chełmno itself, whose fortress was almost completely rebuilt.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; By 1223, however, most of the crusaders had left the region, and the Prussians devastated Chełmno Land and Masovia yet again, forcing Duke Conrad to seek refuge in the castle of [[Płock]]. The Balts even reached [[Gdańsk]] (Danzig) in Pomerellia.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1225&lt;ref name=&quot;M720&quot;&gt;McClintock, p. 720&lt;/ref&gt; or 1228,&lt;ref&gt;Perlbach, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; fourteen [[northern Germany|north German]] knights were recruited by Conrad and Christian to form a [[military order]]. First granted the estate of Cedlitz in [[Kuyavia]] until the completion of a castle at [[Dobrzyń]], the group became known as the [[Order of Dobrzyń]] (or Dobrin).&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; The Knights of Dobrzyń initially had success driving the Prussians from Chełmno Land, but a pagan counterattack against them and Conrad killed most of the Order. The survivors were granted asylum in Pomerania by Duke [[Swantopelk II of Pomerania|Swantopelk II]]. The [[Order of Calatrava]], granted a base near Gdańsk, was also ineffective.&lt;ref name=&quot;G94&quot;/&gt;

==Invitation of the Teutonic Knights==
[[Image:Hermann von Salza Painting.jpg|thumb|right|[[Hermann von Salza]], Grand Master of the Teutonic Knights]]
While in Rome, Christian of Oliva had made the acquaintance of [[Hermann von Salza]], the [[Grand Masters of the Teutonic Knights|Grand Master]] of the [[Teutonic Knights]] from 1209-39. With the permission of Duke Conrad of Masovia and the Masovian nobility, Christian requested aid from the Teutonic Knights against the pagan Prussians in 1226. Stability with the Prussians would then allow Conrad to pursue becoming [[High Duke of Poland]].&lt;ref&gt;Christiansen, p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; While Hermann was interested in the Polish offer, his focus was on assisting Emperor [[Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick II]] with the [[Fifth Crusade]]. Because the Teutonic Order had recently been expelled from the [[Burzenland]] in the [[Kingdom of Hungary]], Hermann also desired greater autonomy for his forces in future endeavors.

Hermann met with Frederick II at [[Rimini]] and suggested that the subjugation of the Prussians would make the [[Holy Roman Empire]]'s borders easier to defend against invaders.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Holy Roman Emperor]] gave his approval of the enterprise in the [[Golden Bull of Rimini]] of 1226, granting them Chełmno Land, or [[Chełmno Land|Culmerland]], and any future conquests. The mission to convert the Prussians remained under the command of Bishop Christian of Oliva.&lt;ref&gt;Christiansen, p. 83&lt;/ref&gt;

Before beginning the campaign against the Prussians, the Teutonic Knights allegedly signed the [[Treaty of Kruszwica]] with the Poles on June 16, 1230, by which the Order was to receive Culmerland and any future conquests, similar to the terms of the Golden Bull of Rimini. The agreement has been disputed by historians; the document has been lost and many Polish historians have doubted its authenticity and the Teutonic Order's territorial claims. However, recent studies by Polish historians have established the treaty's legitimacy.&lt;ref&gt;Dariusz Sikorski, 'Neue Erkenntnisse ueber das Kruschwitzer Privileg' in ''Zeitschrift fuer Ostmitteleuropa-Forschung'', 51 (2002), p. 317-350&lt;/ref&gt; From the viewpoint of Duke Conrad, Chełmno was only to be used as a temporary base against the Prussians and future conquests were to be under the authority of the Duke of Masovia. Hermann von Salza saw the document as granting the Order autonomy in all territorial acquisitions, aside from allegiance to the [[Holy See]] and the [[Holy Roman Emperor]].&lt;ref&gt;Halecki, p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Golden Bull of Rieti]] issued by [[Pope Gregory IX]] in 1234 reaffirmed the Order's control of conquered lands, placing them only under the authority of the [[Holy See]].

The 14th century chronicler [[Peter von Dusburg]] mentioned eleven tribal districts in Prussia: [[Bartia]], [[Chełmno Land|Culmerland]] (formerly under Polish control), [[Galindia]], [[Nadrovia]], [[Natangia]], [[Pogesania]], [[Pomesania]], [[Sambia|Samland]], [[Scalovia]], [[Yotvingians|Sudovia]], and [[Warmia|Ermland]]. Peter estimated that while most tribes could muster about 2,000 cavalry, Samland could raise 4,000 cavalry and 40,000 infantry, while Sudovia had 6,000 cavalry and &quot;an almost innumerable multitude of other warriors&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;U43&quot;&gt;Urban, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, the Prussians of ravaged Culmerland could raise fewer troops than the other tribes. Galindia, a forested wilderness of lakes and rivers, also had a small population to raise troops from. Modern estimates indicate a total Prussian population of 170,000, smaller than that suggested by Peter von Dusburg.&lt;ref name=&quot;U43&quot;/&gt;

==Initial Teutonic campaigns==

After receiving or forging the claim to Culmerland in 1230,&lt;ref&gt;Due to a clerical mistake by [[Peter von Dusburg]], the arrival of the Teutonic Knights has sometimes been given as 1226; see Töppen, pp. 276-79. Töppen states von Landsberg arrived in Masovia in 1230, while Fahne states von Landsberg arrived ca. 1228; see Fahne, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; Hermann dispatched Conrad von Landsberg&lt;ref&gt;Fahne, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; as his envoy&lt;ref&gt;Töppen, p. 276&lt;/ref&gt; with a small force of seven Teutonic Knights and 70-100 squires and sergeants&lt;ref name=&quot;U52&quot;&gt;Urban, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt; to Masovia as a vanguard. They took possession of Vogelsang ([[German language|German]] for &quot;bird song&quot;), a castle being built by Conrad opposite the future [[Toruń|Thorn (Toruń)]];&lt;ref name=&quot;U52&quot;/&gt; other sources indicate that two knights constructed Vogelsang in 1229, but were killed by Prussians soon after.&lt;ref name=&quot;S101&quot;&gt;Seward, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; This region south of the [[Vistula]] River was relatively safe with a mixed Christian and pagan population, and Conrad von Landsberg ordered a small raid against pagans across the Vistula.&lt;ref name=&quot;U52&quot;/&gt; Led by [[Hermann Balk]], reinforcements numbering twenty knights and 200 sergeants arrived at Vogelsang in 1230 after the castle's completion.&lt;ref name=&quot;S101&quot;/&gt; Hermann von Salza could not spare any more, as the Order's primary bases of operation were in [[Outremer]] and [[Armenia]].

While the earlier Polish expeditions had usually marched eastward into the Prussian wilderness, the Order focused in the west to establish fortresses along the Vistula River. They campaigned annually whenever crusading knights from the west arrived. The early campaigns were primarily composed of Polish, German, and Pomeranian crusaders, as well as some Prussian militiamen auxiliaries. The Polish and Pomerellian dukes proved essential through their providing of troops and bases. Most of the secular crusaders would return to their homes after the end of the campaigns, leaving the monastic Teutonic Knights the task of consolidating the gains and garrisoning the newly built forts, most of which were small and made of timber.&lt;ref name=&quot;C106&quot;&gt;Christiansen, p. 106&lt;/ref&gt; Some secular Polish knights were granted vacant territories, especially in Culmerland, although most of the conquered territory was retained by the Teutonic Order. Colonists from the Holy Roman Empire began to immigrate eastward, allowing the foundation of a new town each year, many of which were granted [[Kulm law]].&lt;ref&gt;Urban, p. 57&lt;/ref&gt;

The crusaders began campaigning against the neighboring [[Pomesanians]] and their leader [[Pipin]]. Advancing from [[Nieszawa|Nessau (Nieszawa)]] with the aid of Conrad of Masovia, Balk took control of ruins at modern [[Toruń]] and advanced toward the pagan-occupied [[Rogów]]{{Disambiguation needed|date=June 2011}}. A local Prussian captain defected and handed that castle to the crusaders, who then destroyed the Prussian fort of [[Quercz]] or [[Gurske]]. The defecting captain then tricked Pipin into being captured by the Knights, ending Prussian resistance in the Culmerland.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, pp. 92-93&lt;/ref&gt; By 1232, the Knights had established or rebuilt fortresses at [[Chełmno|Culm (Chełmno)]] and Thorn. Pope Gregory IX called for reinforcements, which included 5,000 veterans under the leadership of the [[Burgrave]] of [[Magdeburg]].&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;

In summer 1233, the Knights led a crusading army of 10,000&lt;ref name=&quot;U56&quot;&gt;Urban, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; and established a fortress at [[Kwidzyn|Marienwerder (Kwidzyn)]] in [[Pomesania]]. The Pomerellian dukes [[Swantopelk II of Pomerania|Swantopelk]] and [[Sambor II of Pomerania|Sambor]] supported a smaller army for an invasion of [[Pogesania]] during the winter of 1233-34. After a close battle, the pagan [[Pogesanians]] were routed on the frozen [[Sirgune]] River by the arrival of the ducal cavalry, &lt;ref name=&quot;U56&quot;/&gt; and the battlefield was subsequently known as the &quot;Field of the Dead&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt; The building of a fortress at [[Radzyń Chełmiński|Rehden (Radzyń Chełmiński)]] stabilized the eastern Culmerland in 1234.&lt;ref&gt;Christiansen, p. 105&lt;/ref&gt;

The bishop of Prussia, Christian of Oliva, claimed two-thirds of conquered territory, granting one-third to the Teutonic Order. The papal legate [[William of Modena]] mediated between the two sides, granting the Knights two-thirds but reserving extra rights for the bishop. The Teutonic Knights also sought the incorporation of the small [[Order of Dobrzyń]] into the larger Teutonic Order. Conrad of Masovia was furious with this proposal and demanded the return of the [[Dobrzyń Land]], which the Knights were reluctant to do; Duke Conrad subsequently refused to aid the crusaders any further.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; With the approval of the pope and the bishop of Płock, the Teutonic Knights assimilated the Order of Dobrzyń in a bull on April 19, 1235; the displeased Conrad of Masovia had the castle of Dobrzyń returned to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;M720&quot;/&gt; In 1237 the Teutonic Knights assimilated the [[Livonian Brothers of the Sword|Sword-Brothers]] or Livonian Order, a military order active in [[Livonia]], after they were nearly wiped out by [[Lithuanians]] in the [[Battle of Saule]].

With the support of [[Henry III, Margrave of Meissen]], in 1236, the crusaders advanced north along both banks of the Vistula and forced the submission of most [[Pomesanians]]. Although Henry did not participate in the 1237 campaign against the [[Pogesanians]], the margrave supplied the Order with two large river-boats which defeated the smaller craft used by the Prussian tribes. Near the Prussian settlement of [[Truso]], [[Elbląg|Elbing (Elbląg)]] was founded with colonists from [[Lübeck]], while [[Dzierzgoń|Christburg (Dzierzgoń)]] protected the land east of Marienwerder.

From 1238-40, the Teutonic Knights campaigned against the [[Bartians]], [[Natangians]], and [[Warmians]]. A small force of crusading knights were slaughtered besieging the Warmian fort of [[Honeida]],&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 143&lt;/ref&gt; leading Marshal Dietrich von Berheim to return with a larger army. When the Warmian commander Kodrune advised that the pagans should surrender and convert, Honeida's own garrison killed him, leading Dietrich to order a successful capture of the fort.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; The fort on the [[Vistula Lagoon]] was renamed [[Balga]] and rebuilt in 1239 to protect the Order's territory in [[Warmia|Ermeland]]. A Prussian counterattack to reclaim the fort failed, and the local Prussian leader Piopso was killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;W152&quot;&gt;Wyatt, p. 152&lt;/ref&gt; Seasonal reinforcements led by [[Otto I, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg]],&lt;ref name=&quot;W152&quot;/&gt; consolidated Teutonic control over [[Natangia]] and [[Bartia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;C106&quot;/&gt;

In a bull of October 1, 1243, [[Pope Innocent IV]] and William of Modena divided Prussia into the Dioceses of [[Bishopric of Culm|Culm]], [[Bishopric of Pomesania|Pomesania]], [[Archbishopric of Warmia|Ermeland]], and [[Bishopric of Samland|Samland]], although the territory of the last had not yet been conquered.

==First Prussian Uprising==
[[Image:Teutonic Order 1260.png|thumb|300px|right|Teutonic state ca. 1260]]
The Teutonic Knights' further advance into Prussia was slowed by the outbreak of the [[Prussian uprisings#The First Prussian Uprising (1242–1249)|First Prussian Uprising]] in 1242. Alarmed by the crusaders' rapid expansion into territory bordering his lands, the Christian Duke [[Swantopelk II of Pomerania|Swantopelk]] of [[Pomerellia]] allied with the conquered Prussians and supported an armed rebellion against the crusaders. The Teutonic Order's capacity to resist was weakened, as there were fewer German crusaders arriving and the Polish princes were feuding amongst themselves.

The crusaders' cavalry and crossbow artillery proved overwhelming in level terrain, but the Prussians were more experienced and maneuverable in smaller skirmishes in wooded terrain. While the Prussian and Pomerellian troops captured the majority of the Order's castles and defeated the Knights at [[Battle of Rensen|Rensen]] in 1244, they lacked the siege capabilities to finish the Knights off. The Germans used their politics and diplomacy to divide Swantopelk from the Prussians. The Poles sought the Pomerellian prince's territory along the Vistula, while the papal legate, the future [[Pope Urban IV]], wanted the Christians to direct their energies against pagans instead of each other. Swantopelk ceased aiding the Prussians in 1248, while most of the latter agreed to peace in the [[Treaty of Christburg]] in February 1249. The treaty granted civil liberties and considerable autonomy to native converts to Christianity. While the majority of tribes followed the terms of the treaty, intermittent fighting continued until 1253, with the [[Natangians]] even defeating the Order at [[Battle of Krücken|Krücken]] in November 1249.

==Samland==

After the western Prussians were pacified by the early 1250s, the Teutonic Knights continued their advance north and east, next facing the [[Sambians]] of thickly-populated [[Sambia|Samland]]. [[Komtur]] Heinrich Stango of Christburg led an army across the Vistula Lagoon in 1252, with the intention of attacking [[Romuva (temple)|Romuve]]. The Sambians defeated the crusaders in battle, however, killing Stango in the process.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, pp. 203-204&lt;/ref&gt; To replace the fallen soldiers, the pope and [[Poppo von Osterna]], the new Grand Master, began preaching a crusade against the Sambians. In 1253 Poppo and the Provincial Master, [[Dietrich von Grüningen]], as well as the Margrave of Meissen, reduced the rebellious [[Galindians]], but did not severely punish them; the Order was concerned that the Prussians would seek to join Poland if they were pressed too greatly.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, pp. 209-210&lt;/ref&gt; With the rebellious tribes pacified, Pope Innocent IV directed [[Dominican Order|Dominican]] monks to preach the crusade, and the Order sent embassies to the Kings of [[Hungary]], [[Bohemia]], and the princes of the [[Holy Roman Empire]]. While the Order waited for the crusaders to arrive in Prussia, the [[Livonian Brothers of the Sword|Livonian branch]] founded [[Klaipėda|Memel (Klaipėda)]] along the [[Curonian Lagoon]] to prevent the Samogitians from assisting the Sambians.

The 60,000-strong crusading army which gathered for the campaign included [[Bohemians]] and [[Austrians]] under the command of King [[Ottokar II of Bohemia]], [[Moravians (ethnic group)|Moravians]] under Bishop [[Bruno of Olomouc|Bruno of Olmütz]], [[Saxons]] under Margrave [[Otto III, Margrave of Brandenburg|Otto III of Brandenburg]], and a contingent brought by [[Rudolph I of Germany|Rudolph of Habsburg]].&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, pp. 212-213&lt;/ref&gt; The Sambians were crushed at the [[Battle of Rudau]], and the fort's garrison surrendered quickly and underwent baptism. The crusaders then advanced against [[Quedenau]], Waldau, [[Caimen]], and [[Gvardeysk|Tapiau (Gvardeysk)]]; the Sambians who accepted baptism were treated considerately, but those who resisted received no mercy from the crusaders. Samland was conquered in January 1255 in a campaign lasting less than a month.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, pp. 214-216&lt;/ref&gt; Near the pagan settlement of [[Tvangste]], the Teutonic Knights founded [[Königsberg]] (&quot;King's Mountain&quot;), named in honor of the Bohemian king. [[Braniewo|Braunsberg (Braniewo)]], possibly named in honor of Bruno of Olmütz or Bruno of Querfurt, was also founded nearby. The Knights built the castle [[Znamensk, Kaliningrad Oblast|Wehlau (Znamensk)]] at the junction of the [[Łyna River|Alle]] and [[Pregel]] Rivers to guard against pagan [[Sudovians|Sudovian]], [[Nadrovians|Nadrovian]], and [[Scalovians|Scalovian]] attacks on Christian Prussians and Germans in Samland. Thirsko, a Christian Sambian chief, and his son Maidelo were entrusted with Wehlau.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyatt, pp. 216-217&quot;&gt;Wyatt, pp. 216-217&lt;/ref&gt; With the assistance of Sambian levies, the Teutonic Order advanced further into Natangia, capturing the fortresses of Capostete and Ocktolite near [[Wohnsdorf]]. The Natangian leader Godecko and his two sons were killed resisting the advance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyatt, pp. 216-217&quot;/&gt;

==The Great Prussian Uprising (1260–1274)==

The Livonian Order had been campaigning into [[Samogitia]], which was northeast of the Prussians. The pagan [[Samogitians]] received a two year truce in 1259, with the Christians expecting the pagans to accept Christianity. In 1259 the Samogitians decided to retain their pagan independence, however.&lt;ref name=&quot;U59&quot;&gt;Urban, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; They defeated the Livonian Order at the [[Battle of Skuodas]] in 1259, and then inflicted a crushing defeat on the crusaders in the [[Battle of Durbe]] in 1260. The pagan victory inspired the Prussians to rebel again, starting the [[Great Prussian Uprising]] the same year. In the minds of the indigenous peoples, the pagan victories reinforced the validity of their pre-Christian beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;Urban p.59&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite their territorial gains in Prussia, the primary emphasis of the Teutonic Knights was still the [[Holy Land]], and few reinforcements could be spared for the Baltic. The German princes of the Holy Roman Empire were distracted by the imperial succession, and few seasonal crusaders came to the assistance of the Prussian Brothers; the first reinforcements were defeated at [[Battle of Pokarwis|Pokarwis]] in 1261. The Order had most of its Prussian castles destroyed during the early 1260s. Besides Prussia, the pagans also raided Livonia, Poland, and [[Volhynia]].

The crusaders began to stem the uprising with the assistance of [[Albert I, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg]], and [[Henry III, Margrave of Meissen|Henry III, Landgrave of Thuringia]], in 1265. In the following year German crusading reinforcements were provided by Margraves [[Otto III, Margrave of Brandenburg|Otto III]] and [[John I, Margrave of Brandenburg|John I]] of Brandenburg, and the castle of [[Ushakovo|Brandenburg (Ushakovo)]] was founded in their honor. King Ottokar II of Bohemia briefly returned to Prussia in 1267-68, but was deterred by poor weather, while Margrave [[Dietrich II, Margrave of Meissen|Dietrich II]] of [[Meissen]] also campaigned with the Order in 1272.&lt;ref name=&quot;Christiansen, p. 108&quot;&gt;Christiansen, p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; The crusaders gradually killed or forced the surrender of each Prussian tribes' war leader.

As a result of the uprising, many native Prussians lost some of the rights they had received in the Treaty of Christburg and were subsequently reduced to [[serfdom]]. Numerous Prussians fled to the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]] or to [[Yotvingians|Sudovia]], while others were resettled by the crusaders. The tribal chiefs who remained in Prussia became vassals of the Teutonic Knights, who began rebuilding their castles in stone or brick.

==Later campaigns==

Although the Teutonic Knights' offensive capability was greatly weakened during the Great Pagan Uprising, they did engage in some campaigns against the pagan on their eastern flank. The Bartians, Natangians, and Warmians had ostensibly converted to Christianity, but the [[Sudovians]] and Lithuanians to their east remained pagan and continued their border warfare with the Teutonic Knights. Led by [[Skomantas of Sudovia|Skalmantas]] during the Great Uprising, the Sudovians sacked [[Bartoszyce|Bartenstein (Bartoszyce)]] in [[Bartia]], which was to be the focal point of their borders. Defenseless against the Sudovians, the Natangians and Bartians allied with the Teutonic Knights for protection, although little assistance could be provided initially. The Christian Natangians clans gathered in 1274 and killed 2,000 of the Sudovian raiders; Grand Master [[Anno von Sangerhausen]] recruited Thuringians and Meisseners to complete the Teutonic recovery of Natangia.&lt;ref&gt;Urban, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt;

Anno's successor as Grand Master, [[Hartmann von Heldrungen]], directed the Provincial Master of Prussia, [[Conrad von Thierberg the Elder]], to attack eastward from Königsberg along the Pregel River to separate the Sudovians from the [[Nadrovians]]. [[Vogt]] Theodoric of Samland and his militia sacked two river forts and plundered a large amount of treasure and goods. Theodoric led another crusading force, including Teutonic Knights, 150 sergeants, and Prussian infantry, against another Nadrovian fort. Although the natives attempted to surrender after siege ladders were placed, most of the warriors were slaughtered by the crusaders, with only a few natives surviving to be resettled. Conrad then led the Knights past the destroyed border forts to assault the Nadrovians main redoubt of Kaminiswike, defended by 200 warriors. Most of the natives were killed after the Knights stormed the fortress, and the Nadrovian clans surrendered soon afterward to become auxiliaries of the crusaders.&lt;ref&gt;Urban, pp. 64-65&lt;/ref&gt;

The Teutonic Knights then used [[Nadrovia]] and Memel as bases against [[Scalovia]] on the lower [[Nemunas|Memel River]]. Scalovia would then serve as a base against pagan Samogitia, which separated Teutonic Prussia from Teutonic Livonia. Because of this threat, the Lithuanians provided assistance to the pagan [[Scalovians]], and the crusaders and pagans each engaged in border raids to distract enemy forces. Because the pagans were strongly defended in the wilderness, the Teutonic Knights focused on travelling up the Memel River toward the strong pagan fort [[Ragnit]]. Theodoric of Samland led 1,000 men in the assault. Artillery fire forced the defenders from the ramparts, allowing the crusaders to storm the walls with ladders and slaughter most of the pagans. Theodoric also captured [[Romige]] on the other bank of the Memel. The Scalovians retaliated by sacking [[Labiau]] near Königsberg. Conrad von Thierberg escalated the conflict by sending a large raid against Scalovia. [[Nicholas von Jeroschin]] documented the crusaders as killing and capturing numerous pagans. When the Scalovian warriors went in pursuit of the captured pagans, Conrad shattered the would-be rescuers in an ambush which killed the pagan leader, Steinegele. Most Scalovian nobles quickly surrendered to the Knights in the battle's aftermath.&lt;ref&gt;Urban, p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;

The Teutonic Knights planned to advance against Samogitia after conquering Scalovia, but the outbreak of a [[Prussian uprisings#Further uprisings and aftermath|new rebellion]] engineered by Skalmantas of the Sudovians delayed the campaign. In 1276-77 the Sudovians and Lithuanians raided Culmerland and burned settlements near the castles of Rehden, Marienwerder, [[Zantyr|Zantir]], and Christburg. Theodoric of Samland was able to convince the Sambians not to rebel, and the Natangians and Warmians followed suit.&lt;ref&gt;Urban, p. 70&lt;/ref&gt; Conrad von Thierberg the Elder led 1,500 men into Kimenau in summer 1277, and crushed a Sudovian army of 3,000 near the Winse forest.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 259&lt;/ref&gt; Many Pogesanians fled to the Lithuanians and were resettled at [[Hrodna|Gardinas]], while the ones who remained in Prussia were resettled by the crusaders, probably near [[Malbork Castle|Marienburg (Malbork)]]. This new brick castle, built to replace Zantir, guarded against further rebellions with Elbing and Christburg. The central Prussian tribes surrendered to the crusaders by 1277.&lt;ref name=&quot;Christiansen, p. 108&quot;/&gt;

The crusaders and Sudovians engaged in [[guerilla warfare]], which the Sudovians were particularly adept at. However, they lacked the sheer numbers to deal with their German, Polish, and Volhynian adversaries, and the Sudovian nobility began gradually surrendering one by one. Marshal [[Conrad von Thierberg the Younger]] raided [[Pokima]], capturing large amounts of cattle, horses, and prisoners. They then successfully ambushed the 3,000-strong force of pursuing Sudovians, losing only six Christians in the process.&lt;ref&gt;Urban, p. 71&lt;/ref&gt; In 1280 the Sudovians and Lithuanian invaded Samland, but the alerted Order had fortified their castles and deprived the raiders of provisions. While the pagans were in Samland, Komtur Ulrich Bayer of Tapiau led a devastating counter-raid into Sudovia.&lt;ref&gt;Wyatt, p. 262&lt;/ref&gt; The Polish prince [[Leszek the Black]] achieved two significant victories over the pagans, securing the Polish border, and Skalmantas fled Sudovia to Lithuania.

In summer 1283, Conrad von Thierberg the Younger was named Provincial Master of Prussia and led a large army into Sudovia, finding little resistance. The Knight Ludwig von Liebenzell, who had once been a captive of the Sudovians, negotiated the surrender of 1,600 Sudovians and their leader Katingerde, who were subsequently resettled in Samland. Most of the remaining Sudovians were redistributed to Pogesania and Samland; Skalmantas was pardoned and allowed to settle at [[Balga]]. Sudovia was left unpopulated, becoming a border wilderness that protected Prussia, Masovia, and Volhynia from the Lithuanians.&lt;ref&gt;Urban, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; The Prussians rebelled in short-lived uprisings in 1286 and 1295, but the crusaders firmly controlled the Prussian tribes by the end of 13th century.

The Prussian populace retained many of their traditions and way of life, especially after the [[Treaty of Christburg]] protected the rights of converts. The Prussian uprisings led to the crusaders only applying these rights to the most powerful converts, however, and the pace of conversion slowed. After the Prussians were militarily defeated in the second half of the 13th century, they were gradually subjected to Christianization and cultural assimilation during the following centuries as part of the [[monastic state of the Teutonic Knights]]. With the fall of [[Acre, Israel|Acre]] and [[Outremer]] and the securing of Prussia, the Order then turned its focus against Christian Pomerellia, which separated Prussia from [[Holy Roman Empire|imperial]] [[Duchy of Pomerania|Pomerania]], and against [[Lithuanian Crusade|pagan Lithuania]].

==Footnotes==

{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==

*{{cite book|last=Christiansen|first=Erik|title=The Northern Crusades|year=1997|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|page=287|isbn=0-14-026653-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Fahne|first=Anton|title=Livland: Ein Beitrag zur Kirchen- und Sitten-Geschichte|year=1875|publisher=Schaub'sche Buchhandlung|location=Düsseldorf|page=240|isbn=}} {{de icon}}
*{{cite book|last=Gieysztor|first=Aleksander|authorlink=Aleksander Gieysztor|coauthors=Stefan Kieniewicz, Emanuel Rostworowski, Janusz Tazbir, and Henryk Wereszycki|title=History of Poland|year=1979|publisher=PWN|location=Warsaw|page=668|isbn=83-01-00392-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Halecki|first=Oskar|authorlink=Oskar Halecki|title=A History of Poland|year=1970|publisher=Roy Publishers|location=New York|page=366|isbn=0-679-51087-7}}
*{{cite book|last=McClintock|first=John|coauthors=James Strong|title=Cyclopædia of Biblical, Theological, and Ecclesiastical Literature: Vol. VIII: PET-RE|year=1883|publisher=Harper &amp; Brothers|location=New York|page=1086|isbn=}}
*{{cite book|last=Perlbach|first=Max|title=Preussisch-Polnische Studien zur Geschichte des Mittelalters|year=1886|publisher=Max Niemeyer|location=Halle|page=128|isbn=}} {{de icon}}
*{{cite book|last=Seward|first=Desmond|title=The Monks of War: The Military Religious Orders|year=1995|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|page=416|isbn=0-14-019501-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Töppen|first=Max|title=Geschichte der Preussischen Historiographie von P. v. Dusburg bis aus auf K. Schütz|year=1853|publisher=Verlag von Wilhelm Hertz|location=Berlin|page=290|isbn=}} {{de icon}}
*{{cite book|last=Urban|first=William|title=The Teutonic Knights: A Military History|year=2003|publisher=Greenhill Books|location=London|page=290|isbn=1-85367-535-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Wyatt|first=Walter James|title=The History of Prussia, Volume 1|year=1876|publisher=Longmans, Green and Co.|location=London|page=506}}

==See also==
*[[Livonian Crusade]]
*[[Wendish Crusade]]
*[[Prussian Uprisings]]

[[Category:History of Prussia]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Teutonic Knights]]
[[Category:Wars involving Poland]]
[[Category:Prussian Crusade|*]]

[[be-x-old:Прускі крыжовы паход]]
[[hr:Pruski križarski rat]]
[[lt:Kryžiaus žygiai į Prūsiją]]
[[pt:Cruzada Prussiana]]
[[ru:Прусский крестовый поход]]
[[sh:Pruski križarski rat]]</text>
      <sha1>dbztnled6goir0z0xke7889ddhx0n07</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
