<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Romantic music</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25916</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522320871</id>
      <parentid>522320855</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T12:09:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/190.58.208.64|190.58.208.64]] to version by 192.5.215.250. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1327137) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11660">{{About|the genre of music|the traditional term in music|Romance (music)|other uses|Romantic (disambiguation){{!}}Romance}}
{{Expand further|date=March 2012}}
{{History of European art music}}

'''Romantic music''' is a term describing a style of [[history of music|Western classical music]] that began in the late 18th or early 19th century. It was related to and in Germany dominated [[Romanticism]], the artistic and literary movement that arose in the second half of the 18th century in [[Europe]].

Romantic music as a movement evolved from the formats, genres and musical ideas established in earlier periods, such as the [[classical period (music)|classical period]], and went further in the name of expression and syncretism of different art forms with music. Romanticism does not necessarily refer to [[romantic love]], though that theme was prevalent in many works composed during this time period, both in literature, painting, or music. Romanticism followed a path that led to the expansion of formal structures for a composition set down or at least created in their general outlines in earlier periods, and the end result is that the pieces are &quot;understood&quot; to be more passionate and expressive, both by 19th century and today's audiences. Because of the expansion of form (those elements pertaining to form, key, instrumentation and the like) within a typical composition, and the growing idiosyncrasies and expressiveness of the new composers from the new century, it thus became easier to identify an artist based on his work or style.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

Romantic music attempted to increase emotional expression and power to describe deeper truths or human feelings, while preserving but in many cases extending the formal structures from the classical period, in others, creating new forms that were deemed better suited to the new subject matter. The subject matter in the new music was now not only purely abstract, but also frequently drawn from other art-form sources such as literature, or history (historical figures) or nature itself.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

==Background==
[[File:Caspar David Friedrich 032.jpg|thumb|230px|''[[Wanderer Above the Sea of Fog]],'' by [[Caspar David Friedrich]] is an example of Romantic painting.]]
===Romanticism===
The [[Romanticism|Romantic]] movement was an artistic, literary, and intellectual movement that originated in the second half of the 18th century in Europe and strengthened in reaction to the [[Industrial Revolution]] (Encyclopædia Britannica n.d.). In part, it was a revolt against social and political norms of the [[Age of Enlightenment]] and a reaction against the scientific [[rationalization (sociology)|rationalization]] of nature (Casey 2008). It was embodied most strongly in the visual arts, music, and literature, but had a major impact on historiography (Levin 1967,{{Pn|date=September 2012}}), education (Gutek 1987, ch. 12 on [[Johann Heinrich Pestalozzi]]{{Pn|date=September 2012}}&lt;!--Page numbers instead of a verbal description, please.--&gt;) and natural history (Nichols 2005,{{Pn|date=September 2012}}).

===Musical language===
The term Romanticism, when applied to music, can be viewed as an artistic response to social, cultural, economic and political influences that had their beginning in the early nineteenth century and lasted through the twentieth century.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

===The effects of Romanticism in music===
{{Section OR|date=March 2012}}
* A freedom in form and design; a more intense personal expression of emotion in which fantasy, imagination and a quest for adventure play an important part.
* Emphasis on lyrical, songlike melodies; adventurous [[modulation (music)|modulation]]; richer [[harmony (music)|harmonies]], often [[chromatic]], with striking use of discords.
*Greater sense of ambiguity: especially in [[tonality]] or harmonic function, but also in [[rhythm]] or [[Meter_(music)#Meter_in_classical_music|meter]].
* Denser, weightier textures with bold dramatic contrasts, exploring a wider range of [[pitch (music)|pitch]], dynamics and tone-colours.
* Expansion of the orchestra, sometimes to gigantic proportions; the invention of the valve system leads to development of the brass section whose weight and power often dominate the texture.
* Rich variety of types of piece, ranging from songs and fairly short piano pieces to huge musical canvasses with lengthy time-span structures with spectacular, dramatic, and dynamic climaxes.
* Closer links with other arts lead to a keener interest in [[programme music]] (programme symphony, [[symphonic poem]], concert overture).
* Shape and unity brought to lengthy works by use of recurring themes (sometimes transformed/developed): idée fixe ([[Berlioz]]), thematic transformations ([[Liszt]]), [[Leitmotif]] ([[Wagner]]), motto theme.
* Greater technical virtuosity – especially from pianists, violinists and flautists.
*The idea of instrumental music composed without reference to anything other than itself.
*The elevation of the performer as genius as demonstrated through the virtuosity of Paganini and Liszt.

==History==

==Trends of the 19th century==
=== Non-musical influences ===
Examples of music inspired by literary / artistic sources include Liszt's ''[[Faust Symphony]]'', ''[[Dante Symphony]]'', his [[symphonic poems]] and his ''[[Annees de Pelerinage]]'', [[Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky|Tchaikovsky's]] ''[[Manfred Symphony]]'', [[Gustav Mahler|Mahler's]] [[Symphony No. 1 (Mahler)|First Symphony]], the piano cycles of [[Robert Schumann]] and the tone poems of [[Richard Strauss]]. [[Franz Schubert|Schubert]] included material from his [[lieder]] in some of his extended works, and others, such as Liszt, transcribed opera arias and songs for solo instrumental performance.

Events and changes that happen in society such as ideas, attitudes, discoveries, inventions, and historical events always affect music. For example, the [[Industrial Revolution]] was in full effect by the late 18th century and early 19th century. This event had a very profound effect on music: there were major improvements in the mechanical valves, and keys that most woodwinds and brass instruments depend on. The new and innovative instruments could be played with more ease and they were more reliable (Schmidt-Jones &amp; Jones 2004, 3). The new instruments often had a bigger, fuller, better-tuned sound. Orchestras grew larger from the days of Beethoven onwards, and were on their way to professionalization .

Another development that had an effect on music was the rise of the middle class.  Composers before this period lived on the patronage of the aristocracy (Schmidt-Jones 3). Many times their audience was small, composed mostly of the upper class and individuals who were knowledgeable about music (Schmidt-Jones &amp; Jones 2004, 3). The Romantic composers, on the other hand, often wrote for public concerts and festivals, with large audiences of paying customers, who had not necessarily had any music lessons (Schmidt-Jones &amp; Jones 2004, 3).  Composers of the Romantic Era, like [[Elgar]], showed the world that there should be &quot;no segregation of musical tastes&quot; (Young 1967, 525) and that the &quot;purpose was to write music that was to be heard&quot; (Young 1967, 527).

==See also==
*[[List of Romantic composers]]
*[[Neoromanticism (music)]]

==References==
*Beard, David, and Kenneth Gloag. 2005. ''Musicology: The Key Concepts''. Cornwall: Routledge.
* Casey, Christopher. 2008. &quot;'Grecian Grandeurs and the Rude Wasting of Old Time': Britain, the Elgin Marbles, and Post-Revolutionary Hellenism&quot;. [http://web1.johnshopkins.edu/foundations/wp-content/pdfs/foundations-full-3-1-pdf.pdf ''Foundations'' 3, no. 1]:31–64 (Accessed 24 September 2012).
*{{cite web|author=Encyclopædia Britannica |url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9083836 |title=Romanticism |publisher=Britannica.com |date= n.d. |accessdate=2010-08-24}}
*Gutek, Gerald Lee. 1987. ''A History of the Western Educational Experience''.{{Full|date=September 2012}}&lt;!--Place and publisher needed.--&gt;
*Levin, David. 1967. ''History as Romantic Art: Bancroft, Prescott, and Parkman''.{{Full|date=September 2012}}&lt;!--Place, publisher needed.--&gt;
*Nichols, Ashton. 2005. &quot;Roaring Alligators and Burning Tygers: Poetry and Science from William Bartram to Charles Darwin&quot;. ''Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society'' 149, no. 3:304–15.
*Schmidt-Jones, Catherine, and Russell Jones. 2004. ''Introduction to Music Theory''. [Houston, TX]: Connexions Project. ISBN 1-4116-5030-1
*Young, Percy Marshall. 1967. ''A History of British Music''. London: Benn.

==Further reading==
*[[Friedrich Blume|Blume, Friedrich]]. 1970. ''Classic and Romantic Music''. New York: W. W. Norton.
*Cavalletti, Carlo. 2000. ''Chopin and Romantic Music'', translated by Anna Maria Salmeri Pherson. Hauppauge, NY: Barron's Educational Series. (Hardcover) ISBN 0-7641-5136-3 ; ISBN 978-0-7641-5136-1.
*[[Carl Dahlhaus|Dahlhaus, Carl]]. 1980. ''Between Romanticism and Modernism: Four Studies in the Music of the Later Nineteenth Century''. Berkeley: University of California Press.
*Dahlhaus, Carl. 1979. &quot;Neo-Romanticism&quot;. ''19th-Century Music'' 3, no. 2 (November): 97–105.
*[[Alfred Einstein|Einstein, Alfred]]. 1947. ''Music in the Romantic Era''. New York: W. W. Norton.
*Kravitt, Edward F. 1992. &quot;Romanticism Today&quot;. ''The Musical Quarterly'' 76, no. 1 (Spring): 93–109.
*[[Leon Plantinga|Plantinga, Leon]]. 1984. ''Romantic Music: A History of Musical Style in Nineteenth-Century Europe''. A Norton Introduction to Music History. New York: W. W. Norton. ISBN 0-393-95196-0; ISBN 978-0-393-95196-7.
*[[Charles Rosen|Rosen, Charles]]. 1995. ''The Romantic Generation''. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press. ISBN 0-674-77933-9.
*Rummenhöller, Peter. 1989. ''Romantik in der Musik: Analysen, Portraits, Reflexionen''. Munich: Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag; Kassel and New York: Bärenreiter.
*Samson, Jim. 2001. &quot;Romanticism&quot;. ''The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians'', second edition, edited by [[Stanley Sadie]] and [[John Tyrrell (professor of music)|John Tyrrell]]. London: Macmillan Publishers.

==External links==
* [http://public.wsu.edu/~brians/hum_303/romantic.html Music of the Romantic Era]
* [http://library.thinkquest.org/15413/history/history-rom.htm The Romantic Era]
* [http://www.essentialsofmusic.com/eras/romantic.html Era on line]

{{music topics}}
{{Romanticism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Romantic Music}}
[[Category:19th century in music]]
[[Category:Romantic composers]]
[[Category:Romantic music| ]]
[[Category:Romanticism]]

{{Link GA|eo}}
{{Link FA|eo}}

[[bg:Музика на романтизма]]
[[ca:Romanticisme musical]]
[[cs:Romantismus (hudba)]]
[[da:Romantikkens musik]]
[[de:Musik der Romantik]]
[[et:Romantism (muusika)]]
[[es:Música del Romanticismo]]
[[eo:Romantisma muziko]]
[[fa:موسیقی رمانتیک]]
[[fr:Musique romantique]]
[[ko:낭만주의 음악]]
[[id:Musik romantik]]
[[it:Musica del romanticismo]]
[[he:המוזיקה הקלאסית בתקופה הרומנטית]]
[[ms:Muzik era romantis]]
[[nl:Romantiek (muziek)]]
[[ja:ロマン派音楽]]
[[no:Romantisk musikk]]
[[nn:Romantisk musikk]]
[[pl:Muzyka romantyczna]]
[[pt:Era Romântica]]
[[ru:Музыка периода романтизма]]
[[scn:Mùsica rumàntica]]
[[simple:Romantic music]]
[[sk:Romantizmus (hudba)]]
[[sl:Romantična glasba]]
[[sh:Romantizam (muzika)]]
[[fi:Romantiikan musiikki]]
[[sv:Romantikens musik]]
[[th:ดนตรียุคโรแมนติก]]
[[uk:Музика епохи романтизму]]
[[zh:浪漫主義音樂]]</text>
      <sha1>ak3ytbhyj3lmq8yu6xlapp8zm66mvlu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
