<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Scramble for Africa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>286469</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521570136</id>
      <parentid>521569809</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T21:36:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tobby72</username>
        <id>9107368</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 521569809 by [[Special:Contributions/109.148.100.157|109.148.100.157]] ([[User talk:109.148.100.157|talk]]) rvv</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="68809">{{about||information on the colonization of Africa prior to the 1880s, including Carthaginian and early European colonization|Colonisation of Africa|the book by Thomas Pakenham|The Scramble for Africa}}

{{Refimprove|date=September 2011}}
[[File:Punch Rhodes Colossus.png|thumb|300px|''[[The Rhodes Colossus]]'', an 1892 [[caricature]] of [[Cecil Rhodes]] after announcing plans for a [[telegraph]] line from [[Cape Town]] to [[Cairo]]. For ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'' by [[Edward Linley Sambourne]].]]
{{Scramble for Africa}}
{{Exploration of Africa}}

The '''Scramble for Africa''', also known as the '''Race for Africa''' or '''Partition of Africa'''&lt;ref&gt;McKay, John P.; Hill, Bennett D.; Buckler, John; Ebrey, Patricia Buckley; Beck, Roger B.; Crowston, Clare Haru; Wiesner-Hanks, Merry E.  '' [http://books.google.com/books?id=ZLkOVE93dX8C&amp;dq=0312682980&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=8QaRTOr-LJT2swON_62yDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwAA A History of World Societies: From 1775 to Present] ''. Eighth edition. Volume C – From 1775 to the Present. (2009). [http://www.bedfordstmartins.com/ Bedford/St. Martin's]: Boston/New York. ISBN 978-0-312-68298-9. ISBN 0-312-68298-0. &quot;By 1883 Europe had caught 'African fever,' and the race for territory was on.&quot; (McKay 738)&lt;/ref&gt; was a process of invasion, occupation, colonization and annexation of [[Africa]]n territory by [[Europe]]an powers during the [[New Imperialism]] period, between 1881 and [[World War I]] in 1914.&lt;!--[[Europe|European]] powers during the [[New Imperialism]] period, during the latter part of the nineteenth century and the early part of the twentieth.{{sfn|Hobsbawm|1994|p=}}{{sfn|Pakenham|1991|p=}}--&gt; As a result of the heightened tension between European states in the last quarter of the 19th century, the partitioning of Africa may be seen as a way for the Europeans to eliminate the threat of a Europe-wide war over Africa.&lt;ref&gt;R. Robinson, J. Gallagher and A. Denny, ''Africa and the Victorians'', London, 1965, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; The last 59 years of the 19th century saw transition from &quot;informal imperialism&quot; of control through military influence and economic dominance to that of direct rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shillington&quot;&gt;Kevin Shillington, ''History of Africa''. Revised second edition (New York: Macmillian Publishers Limited, 2005), 301.&lt;/ref&gt;

Attempts to mediate imperial competition, such as the [[Berlin Conference]] (1884–85), failed to establish definitively the competing powers' claims.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} Many African polities, states and rulers (such as the [[The Ashanti|Ashanti]], the [[Ethiopian Empire|Abyssinians]], the [[Morocco|Moroccans]], the [[Dervish State|Somalis]], the [[Benin Empire]] and the [[Zulu people|Zulus]]) sought to resist this wave of European aggression.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Fall of the Asante Empire: The Hundred-Year War For Africa's Gold Coast |publisher=Amazon.co.uk |id={{ASIN|0743236386|country=uk}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the industrial revolution had provided the European armies with advanced weapons such as machine guns, which African armies found difficult to resist (with the exception of the [[Ethiopian Empire|Abyssinians]], who were indeed successful).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Matabele Campaign: being a narrative of the campaign in suppressing the native rising in Matabeleland and Mashonaland, 1896 |publisher=Amazon.co.uk  |id={{ASIN|0543848086|country=uk}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, unlike their European counterparts, African rulers, states and people did not at first form a continental united front although within a few years, a Pan-African movement did emerge:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://catalogue.nla.gov.au/Record/2129768 |title=Pan-Africanism and nationalism in West Africa, 1900–1945; a study in ideology and social classes, by J. Ayodele Langley |publisher=Catalogue.nla.gov.au |date= |accessdate=2010-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[first Pan-African Conference]] was held in London in 1900.

==Background==
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2011}}
{{NewImperialism}}
[[File:Davidlivingstone cropped.jpg|upright|left|thumb|[[David Livingstone]], early explorer of the interior of Africa and fighter against the [[African slave trade|slave trade]].]]
[[Portuguese Empire|The Portuguese]] had been the first post-[[Middle Ages]] Europeans to firmly establish settlements, trade posts, permanent fortifications and ports of call along the coast of the African continent, from the beginning of the [[Age of Discovery]], in the 15th century. There was little interest in, and less knowledge of, the interior for some two centuries thereafter.

European exploration of the African interior began in earnest at the end of the 18th century. By 1835, Europeans had mapped most of northwestern Africa. In the middle decades of the 19th century, the most famous of the European explorers were [[David Livingstone]] and [[Henry Morton Stanley|H. M. Stanley]], both of whom mapped vast areas of [[Southern Africa]] and [[Central Africa]]. Arduous expeditions in the 1850s and 1860s by [[Richard Francis Burton|Richard Burton]], [[John Hanning Speke|John Speke]] and [[James Augustus Grant|James Grant]] located the [[African Great Lakes|great central lakes]] and the source of the [[Nile]]. By the end of the 19th century, Europeans had charted the Nile from its source, traced the courses of the [[Niger River|Niger]], [[Congo River|Congo]] and [[Zambezi River]]s, and realized the [[natural resources|vast resources]] of Africa.

Even as late as the 1870s, European states still controlled only 10 percent of the African continent, all their territories being near the coast. The most important holdings were [[Angola (Portugal)|Angola]] and [[Mozambique (Portugal)|Mozambique]], held by [[Portugal]]; the [[Cape Colony]], held by the [[United Kingdom]]; and [[French rule in Algeria|Algeria]], held by [[France in the nineteenth century|France]]. By 1914, only [[Ethiopia]], [[Liberia]] and the [[Dervish State]] were independent of European control.

Technological advancement facilitated overseas expansionism. [[Industrialisation]] brought about rapid advancements in transportation and communication, especially in the forms of [[Steamboat|steam navigation]], [[Rail transport|railways]], and [[Telegraphy|telegraphs]]. Medical advances also were important, especially medicines for [[tropical disease]]s. The development of [[quinine]], an effective treatment for [[malaria]], enabled vast expanses of the tropics to be accessed by Europeans.

==Causes==

===Africa and global markets===
[[File:Colonial Africa 1913 map.svg|thumb|300px|Areas controlled by European colonial powers on the African continent in 1913, shown along with current national boundaries.

{{Legend|#f7fab2|[[Belgian colonial empire|Belgian]]}}
{{Legend|#fbc5c0|[[British Empire|British]]}}
{{Legend|#b6e3fc|[[French colonial empire|French]]}}
{{Legend|#bbfdd9|[[German colonial empire|German]]}}
{{Legend|#d2f89b|[[Italian Colonial Empire|Italian]]}}
{{Legend|#c0a6f2|[[Portuguese Empire|Portuguese]]}}
{{Legend|#eaaff7|[[Spanish Empire|Spanish]]}}
{{Legend|#f6f6f6|Independent]]}}

[[Sub-Saharan Africa]], one of the last regions of the world largely untouched by &quot;informal imperialism&quot;, was also attractive to Europe's ruling elites for economic and racial reasons. During a time when Britain's [[balance of trade]] showed a growing deficit, with shrinking and increasingly [[protectionism|protectionist]] continental markets due to the [[Long Depression]] (1873–96), Africa offered [[United Kingdom|Britain]], [[German Empire|Germany]], [[French Third Republic|France]], and other countries an open market that would garner them a trade surplus: a market that bought more from the colonial power than it sold overall.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shillington&quot; /&gt; Britain, like most other industrial countries, had long since begun to run an unfavourable balance of trade (which was increasingly offset, however, by the income from overseas investments).

As Britain developed into the world's first post-industrial nation, financial services became an increasingly important sector of its economy. Invisible financial exports kept Britain out of the red, especially [[capital investments]] outside Europe, particularly to the developing and open markets in Africa such as to the white settler colonies, the [[Middle East]], [[South Asia]] and [[Southeast Asia]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

In addition, surplus capital was often more profitably invested overseas, where cheap materials, limited competition, and abundant raw materials made a greater premium possible. Another inducement for imperialism arose from the demand for raw materials unavailable in Europe, especially [[copper]], [[cotton]], [[rubber]], [[palm oil]], [[Cocoa bean|cocoa]], [[diamonds]], [[tea]], and [[tin]], to which European consumers had grown accustomed and upon which European industry had grown dependent. Additionally, Britain wanted the southern and eastern coasts of Africa for stopover ports on the route to Asia and its empire in India.&lt;ref&gt;Lynn Hunt, ''The Making of the West'': volume C, Bedford: St. Martin, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in Africa – exclusive of the area which became the [[Union of South Africa]] in 1910 – the amount of capital investment by Europeans was relatively small, compared to other continents. Consequently, the companies involved in tropical African commerce were relatively small, apart from [[Cecil Rhodes]]'s [[De Beers Mining Company]].  Rhodes had carved out [[Rhodesia]] for himself; [[Léopold II of Belgium]] later, and with considerably greater brutality, exploited the [[Congo Free State]]. These events might detract from the pro-imperialist arguments of colonial [[Lobbying|lobbies]] such as the ''[[Alldeutscher Verband]]'', [[Francesco Crispi]] and [[Jules Ferry]], who argued that sheltered overseas markets in Africa would solve the problems of low prices and over-production caused by shrinking continental markets.

[[John A. Hobson]] argued, in ''[[Imperialism (Hobson)|Imperialism]]'', that this shrinking of continental markets was a key factor of the global &quot;New Imperialism&quot; period.

[[William Easterly]] of [[New York University]], however, disagrees with the link made between capitalism and imperialism, arguing that colonialism is used mostly to promote state-led development rather than &quot;corporate&quot; development. He has stated that &quot;imperialism is not so clearly linked to capitalism and free markets... historically there has been a closer link between colonialism/imperialism and state-led approaches to development.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.nyu.edu/fas/dri/aidwatch/2009/09/the_imperial_origins_of_statel.html|title=The Imperial Origins of State-Led Development|last=Easterly|first=William|date=September 17, 2009|publisher=New York University Blogs|accessdate=2009-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Strategic rivalry===
While tropical Africa was not a large zone of investment, other regions overseas were. The vast interior between the gold and diamond-rich [[Southern Africa]] and [[Egypt]], had, however, key strategic value in securing the flow of overseas trade. Britain was thus under intense political pressure to secure lucrative markets against encroaching rivals, in [[China]] and the British Empire's eastern colonies, most notably [[British India|India]], [[British Malaya|Malaya]], [[Australia]] and [[New Zealand]]. Thus, securing the key waterway between East and West – the [[Suez Canal]] – was crucial. The rivalry between the UK, France, Germany and the other European powers account for a large part of the colonization. Thus, while Germany, which had been unified under [[Prussia]]'s rule only after the 1866 [[Battle of Sadowa]] and the 1870 [[Franco-Prussian War]], was hardly a colonial power before the New Imperialism period, it would eagerly participate in the race. A [[industrial revolution|rising industrial power]] close on the heels of Britain, it had not yet had the chance to control overseas territories, mainly due to its late unification, its fragmentation in various states, and its absence of experience in modern navigation. This would change under [[Otto von Bismarck]]'s leadership, who implemented the ''[[Weltpolitik]]'' (World Politics) and, after putting in place the basis of France's isolation with the [[Dual Alliance, 1879|Dual Alliance]] with [[Austria-Hungary]] and then the 1882 [[Triple Alliance (1882)|Triple Alliance]] with Italy, called for the 1884–85 Berlin Conference, which set the rules of effective control of a foreign territory. Germany's [[expansionism]] would lead to the [[Tirpitz Plan]], implemented by [[Alfred von Tirpitz|Admiral von Tirpitz]], who would also champion the various [[Fleet Acts]] starting in 1898, thus engaging in an [[arms race]] with Britain. By 1914, they had given Germany the second largest naval force in the world (roughly 40% smaller than the [[Royal Navy]]). According to von Tirpitz, this aggressive naval policy was supported by the [[National Liberal Party (Germany)|National Liberal Party]] rather than by the conservatives, thus demonstrating that the main supports of the European nation states' imperialism were the rising [[middle class]]es.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alfred von Tirpitz]], ''Erinnerungen'' (1919), quoted by [[Hannah Arendt]], ''[[The Origins of Totalitarianism]]'', section on Imperialism, chapter I, part 3.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Slave boat1869.jpg|thumb|Slaves captured from the Congo aboard an [[Arab slave trade|Arab slave ship]] intercepted by the [[Royal Navy]] (1869). One of the chief justifications for the colonization of Africa was the suppression of the slave trade.]]
The scramble for African territory also reflected a concern for the acquisition of military and naval bases for strategic purposes and the exercise of power on an international scene. The ability to influence international events depended largely upon new weapons – steel ships driven by steam power – and for the maintenance of these growing navies, coaling stations and ports of call were required. Defence bases were also needed for the protection of sea routes and communication lines, particularly of expensive and vital international waterways such as the [[Suez Canal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1982&quot;&gt;H. R. Cowie, ''Imperialism and Race Relations''. Revised edition, Nelson Publishing, Volume 5, 1982.&lt;/ref&gt;

Colonies were also seen as important aspects of &quot;[[Balance of power in international relations|balance of power]]&quot; negotiations – useful as items of exchange at times of international bargaining. Colonies carrying a heavy native population were also important as a source of military power; Britain and France used large numbers of [[Sepoy#Sepoys_in_British_India|British Indian]] and North African soldiers respectively in many of their colonial wars. In the great age of [[nationalism]] there was strong pressure for a nation to acquire an empire as a status symbol; the idea of &quot;greatness&quot; became inextricably linked with the sense of &quot;[[White Man's Burden|duty]]&quot; that many European nations used to justify their imperialistic ambitions.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1982&quot;/&gt;

====Bismarck's ''Realpolitik''====
Germany began its world expansion in the 1880s under Bismarck's leadership, encouraged by the national middle class. Some of them, claiming themselves of [[Friedrich List]]'s thought, advocated expansion in the [[Philippines]] and in [[Timor]]; others proposed to set themselves in Formosa (modern [[Taiwan]]), etc. At the end of the 1870s, these isolated voices began to be relayed by a real imperialist policy, which was backed by [[mercantilism|mercantilist thesis]]. In 1881, [[Wilhelm Hübbe-Schleiden|Hübbe-Schleiden]], a lawyer, published ''Deutsche Kolonisation'', according to which the &quot;development of national [[political consciousness|consciousness]] demanded an independent overseas policy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.paris4.sorbonne.fr/fr/IMG/pdf/navette-7.pdf German colonial imperialism: a late and short-term phenomenon] (PDF) by Bernard Poloni, in &quot;Imperialism, hegemony, leadership&quot;, 26 March 2004 Conference in the [[Sorbonne University]], Paris {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pan-germanism]] was thus linked to the young nation's imperialist drives. In the beginning of the  1880s, the ''[[Deutscher Kolonialverein]]'' was created, and got its own magazine in 1884, the ''Kolonialzeitung''. This colonial lobby was also relayed by the nationalist ''[[Alldeutscher Verband]]''. Generally Bismarck was opposed to widespread German colonialism, but he had to resign at the insistence of the new German Emperor [[Wilhelm II]] on 18 March 1890. Wilhelm II instead adopted a very aggressive policy of colonisation and introduced colonial expansion in the 20th century with the ''[[Weltpolitik]]'' (‘World Politics’) strategy.

Germany thus became the third largest colonial power in Africa. Nearly all of its overall empire of 2.6 million square kilometres and 14 million colonial subjects in 1914 was found in its African possessions of Southwest Africa, Togoland, the Cameroons, and Tanganyika. The scramble for Africa led Bismarck to propose the 1884–85 Berlin Conference. Following the 1904 ''[[Entente cordiale]]'' between France and the UK, Germany tried to isolate France in 1905 with the [[First Moroccan Crisis]]. This led to the 1905 [[Algeciras Conference]], in which France's influence on Morocco was compensated by the exchange of other territories, and then to the [[Agadir Crisis]] in 1911. Along with the 1898 [[Fashoda Incident]] between France and the UK, this succession of [[international crisis|international crises]] reveals the bitterness of the struggle between the various imperalist nations, which ultimately led to World War I.

====Clash of rival imperial powers====
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2011}}
[[File:Battle of Adwa Tapestry Closeup.png|thumb|300px|This scene from an Ethiopian tapestry depicts the Ethiopian triumph against Italian forces at the [[Battle of Adwa]]. The Italo-Ethiopian War of 1895–96 distinguished Ethiopia as the only African state to maintain independence in the 19th century with a decisive show of force.]]
While [[Pierre Savorgnan de Brazza]] was exploring the [[Kongo Kingdom]] for France, [[Henry Morton Stanley]] also explored it in the early 1880s on behalf of [[Léopold II of Belgium]], who would have his personal [[Congo Free State]].  While pretending to advocate [[humanitarianism]] and denounce [[slavery]], Leopold II used the most inhumane tactics to exploit his newly acquired lands. His crimes were revealed by 1905, but he remained in control until 1908, when he was forced to turn over control to the Belgian government.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | last1 = Merriman | first1 = John.
 | title = A History of Modern Europe: From the Renaissance to Present
 | edition = 3
|place = New York
 | publisher = [[W.W. Norton &amp; Co.]]
 |pages = 819–820
 | year = 2010
 | isbn = 978-0-393-93433-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

France occupied [[Tunisia]] in May 1881 (and Guinea in 1884), which partly convinced [[Italy]] to join the German-Austrian [[Dual Alliance, 1879|Dual Alliance]] in 1882, thus forming the [[Triple Alliance (1882)|Triple Alliance]]. The same year, Britain occupied [[Egypt]] (hitherto an autonomous state owing nominal fealty to the [[Ottoman Empire]]), which ruled over Sudan and parts of [[Chad]], [[Eritrea]], and [[Somalia]]. In 1870 and 1882, Italy took possession of the first parts of [[Eritrea]], while Germany declared [[Togoland]], the [[Cameroons]] and [[South West Africa]] to be under its protection in 1884. [[French West Africa]] (AOF) was founded in 1895, and [[French Equatorial Africa]] in 1910.

Italy continued its conquest to gain its &quot;[[place in the sun]]&quot;. Following the defeat of the [[First Italo–Ethiopian War]] (1895–1896), it acquired [[Italian Somaliland]] in 1889–90 and the whole of Eritrea (1899). In 1911, it engaged in a [[Italo-Turkish War|war with the Ottoman Empire]], in which it acquired [[Tripolitania]] and [[Cyrenaica]] (modern [[Libya]]). [[Enrico Corradini]], who fully supported the war, and later merged his group in the early [[National Fascist Party|fascist party]] (PNF), developed in 1919 the concept of ''Proletarian Nationalism'', supposed to legitimise Italy's imperialism by a mixture of [[socialism]] with [[nationalism]]: &quot;We must start by recognizing the fact that there are proletarian nations as well as proletarian classes; that is to say, there are nations whose living conditions are subject...to the way of life of other nations, just as classes are. Once this is realised, nationalism must insist firmly on this truth: Italy is, materially and morally, a proletarian nation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Enrico Corradini]], ''Report to the First Nationalist Congress'', Florence, 3 December 1919.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Second Italo-Abyssinian War]] (1935–36), ordered by [[Benito Mussolini]], would actually be one of the last colonial wars (that is, intended to colonize a foreign country, opposed to [[wars of national liberation]]), occupying [[Ethiopia]] which had remained the last African independent territory apart from Liberia, for five years. The [[Spanish Civil War]], marking a new phase of what some call the [[European Civil War]], began in [[Spanish Morocco]] in 1936.

On the other hand, the British abandoned their &quot;[[splendid isolation]]&quot; in 1902 with the [[Anglo-Japanese Alliance]], which would enable the [[Empire of Japan]] to be victorious during the [[Russo-Japanese War|war against Russia]] (1904–1905). The UK then signed the ''[[Entente cordiale]]'' with France in 1904, and, in 1907, the [[Triple Entente]] which included Russia, thus pitted against the Triple Alliance which [[Otto von Bismarck|Bismarck]] had patiently assembled.

====American Colonization Society and foundation of Liberia====
[[File:jamesmonroe-npgallery.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[James Monroe]], first president of the ACS and [[US president]] (1817–25). He invented the [[Monroe Doctrine]], base of the [[United States non-interventionism|US isolationism]] during the 19th century.]]
[[File:Joseph Jenkins Roberts.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Joseph Jenkins Roberts]] became the first president of [[Liberia]], one of the two independent African nations (alongside [[Ethiopia]]) at the time of European control and domination.]]
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2011}}
{{Main|American Colonization Society|History of Liberia}}
The [[United States]] took part, marginally, in this enterprise, through the [[American Colonization Society]] (ACS), established in 1816 by [[Robert Finley]]. The ACS offered emigration to [[Liberia]] (&quot;Land of the Free&quot;), a colony founded in 1820, to [[History of slavery in the United States|free black slaves]]; emancipated slave [[Lott Carey]] actually became the first American [[Baptist]] [[missionary]] in Africa. This colonisation attempt was resisted by the native people.

The ACS was led by [[Southern United States|Southerners]], and its first president was [[James Monroe]], from [[Virginia]], who became the fifth [[president of the United States]] from 1817 to 1825. One of the main proponents of American colonisation of Africa was the same man who proclaimed, in his 1823 [[State of the Union]] address, the US opinion that European powers should no longer [[European colonization of the Americas|colonise the Americas]] or interfere with the affairs of sovereign nations located in the Americas. In return, the US planned to stay neutral in wars between European powers and in wars between a European power and its colonies. However, if these latter type of wars were to occur in the Americas, the U.S. would view such action as hostile toward itself. Monroe's famous statement &amp;ndash; known as the [[Monroe Doctrine]] &amp;ndash; was the basis of [[United States non-interventionism|United States isolationism]] during the 19th century.

Although the Liberia colony never became quite as big as envisaged, it was only the first step in the American colonisation of Africa, according to its early proponents. Thus, [[Jehudi Ashmun]], an early leader of the ACS, envisioned an American empire in Africa. Between 1825 and 1826, he took steps to lease, annex, or buy tribal lands along the coast and along major rivers leading inland. Like his predecessor Lt. [[Robert Stockton]], who in 1821 established the site for [[Monrovia]] by &quot;persuading&quot; a local chief referred to as &quot;King Peter&quot; to sell Cape Montserado (or [[Cape Mesurado]]) by pointing a pistol at his head, Ashmun was prepared to use force to extend the colony's territory. In a May 1825 treaty, King Peter and other native kings agreed to sell land in return for 500 bars of tobacco, three barrels of rum, five casks of powder, five umbrellas, ten iron posts, and ten pairs of shoes, among other items. In March 1825, the ACS began a quarterly, ''The African Repository and Colonial Journal'', edited by Rev. [[Ralph Randolph Gurley]] (1797–1872), who headed the Society until 1844. Conceived as the Society's propaganda organ, the Repository promoted both colonisation and Liberia.

The Society controlled the colony of Liberia until 1847 when, under the perception that the British might annex the settlement, Liberia was proclaimed a free and independent state, thus becoming the first African [[decolonisation|decolonised]] state. By 1867, the Society had sent more than 13,000 emigrants. After the [[American Civil War]] (1861–65), when many blacks wanted to go to Liberia, financial support for colonisation had waned. During its later years the society focused on educational and missionary efforts in Liberia rather than further emigration.

==Crises prior to the First World War==

===Colonization of the Congo===
[[File:Henry Morton Stanley.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Henry Morton Stanley]]]]
[[David Livingstone]]'s explorations, carried on by [[Henry Morton Stanley]], excited imaginations. But at first, Stanley's grandiose ideas for colonisation found little support owing to the problems and scale of action required, except from [[Léopold II of Belgium]], who in 1876 had organised the [[Association Internationale Africaine|International African Association]]. From 1869 to 1874, Stanley was secretly sent by Léopold II to the [[Congo Basin|Congo]] region, where he made treaties with several African chiefs along the Congo River and by 1882 had sufficient territory to form the basis of the [[Congo Free State]]. Léopold II personally owned the colony from 1885 and used it as a source of [[ivory]] and [[rubber]].
[[File:Pierre Savorgnan de Brazza.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Pierre Savorgnan de Brazza]] in his version of &quot;native&quot; dress, photographed by [[Félix Nadar]]]]
While Stanley was exploring Congo on behalf of Léopold II of Belgium, the Franco-Italian marine officer [[Pierre Savorgnan de Brazza|Pierre de Brazza]] travelled into the western Congo basin and raised the French flag over the newly founded [[Brazzaville]] in 1881, thus occupying today's [[Republic of the Congo]]. Portugal, which also claimed the area due to old treaties with the native [[Kongo Empire]], made a treaty with Britain on 26 February 1884 to block off the Congo Society's access to the Atlantic.

By 1890 the Congo Free State had consolidated its control of its territory between [[Kinshasa|Leopoldville]] and [[Kisangani|Stanleyville]] and was looking to push south down the [[Lualaba River]] from Stanleyville. At the same time the [[British South Africa Company]] of [[Cecil Rhodes]] (who once declared, &quot;all of these stars... these vast worlds that remain out of reach. If I could, I would annex other planets&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[S. Gertrude Millin]], ''Rhodes'', London, 1933, p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt;) was expanding north from the [[Limpopo River]] sending the [[Pioneer Column]], guided by [[Frederick Selous]], through [[Matabeleland]] and starting a colony in Mashonaland. To the West, attention was drawn to the land where their expansions would meet [[Katanga Province|Katanga]], site of the [[Yeke Kingdom]] of [[Msiri]]. As well as being the most powerful ruler militarily in the area, Msiri traded large quantities of copper, ivory and slaves, and rumours of gold reached European ears. The scramble for Katanga was a prime example of the period. Rhodes and the BSAC sent two expeditions to Msiri in 1890 led by [[Alfred Sharpe]], who was rebuffed, and [[Joseph Thomson (explorer)|Joseph Thomson]] who failed to reach Katanga. In 1891 Leopold sent four CFS expeditions. The [[Le Marinel Expedition]] could only extract a vaguely worded letter. The [[Delcommune Expedition]] was rebuffed. The well-armed [[Stairs Expedition]] had orders to take Katanga with or without Msiri's consent; Msiri refused, was shot, and the expedition cut off his head and stuck it on a pole as a &quot;barbaric lesson&quot; to the people. The [[Bia Expedition]] finished off the job of establishing an administration of sorts and a &quot;police presence&quot; in [[Katanga Province|Katanga]]. [[Image:MutilatedChildrenFromCongo.jpg|thumb|Native Congo Free State labourers who failed to meet rubber collection quotas were often punished by having their hands cut off]]
The half million square kilometres of Katanga came into Leopold's possession and brought his African realm up to {{Convert|2300000|km2}}, about 75 times larger than Belgium. The Congo Free State imposed such a [[terror regime]] on the colonised people, including mass killings and forced labour, that Belgium, under pressure from the [[Congo Reform Association]], ended Leopold II's rule and annexed it in 1908 as a colony of Belgium, known as the [[Belgian Congo]].
[[File:Punch congo rubber cartoon.jpg|thumb|left|upright|A hard-hitting 1906 ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'' cartoon depicting [[King Leopold II]] of [[Belgium]] as a rubber vine and snake entangling a [[Belgian Congo|Congolese]] man.]]

King Leopold II of Belgium's brutality in his former colony of the [[Congo Free State]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Bourne |first=Henry Richard Fox |title=Civilisation in Congoland: A Story of International Wrong-doing |url=http://books.google.com/?id=jWccAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=%22Civilisation+in+Congoland%22#PPR3,M1 |accessdate=2007-09-26 |year=1903 |publisher=P. S. King &amp; Son |location=London |page=253}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Forbath |first=Peter |title=The River Congo: The Discovery, Exploration and Exploitation of the World's Most Dramatic Rivers |year=1977 |publisher=[Harper &amp; Row] |location= |isbn=0-06-122490-1 |page=374}}&lt;/ref&gt; now the [[DRC]], was well documented; up to 8 million of the estimated 16 million native inhabitants died between 1885 and 1908.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT 30.08.2012&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/books/98/08/30/daily/leopold-book-review.html |title=&quot;King Leopold's Ghost&quot;: Genocide With Spin Control |author=Michiko Kakutani |date=30 August 1998 |newspaper=The New York Times |accessdate=2 February 2012}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to the former British diplomat [[Roger Casement]], this depopulation had four main causes: &quot;indiscriminate war&quot;, starvation, reduction of births and diseases.{{sfn|Hochschild|2006|pp=226–32}} [[African trypanosomiasis|Sleeping sickness]] ravaged the country and must also be taken into account for the dramatic decrease in population; it has been estimated that sleeping sickness and [[smallpox]] killed nearly half the population in the areas surrounding the lower [[Congo River]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=8DSa_viBgsgC&amp;pg=&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The Cambridge history of Africa: From the earliest times to c. 500 BC]''.&quot; John D. Fage (1982) [[Cambridge University Press]], p. 748. ISBN 0-521-22803-4&lt;/ref&gt;

Estimates of the total death toll vary considerably. As the first census did not take place until 1924, it is difficult to quantify the population loss of the period. [[Casement Report|Casement's report]] set it at three million.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.urome.be/fr2/reflexions/casemrepo.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Rubinstein]] wrote: &quot;More basically, it appears almost certain that the population figures given by [[Adam Hochschild|Hochschild]] are inaccurate. There is, of course, no way of ascertaining the population of the Congo before the twentieth century, and estimates like 20 million are purely guesses. Most of the interior of the Congo was literally unexplored if not inaccessible.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rubinstein, W. D. (2004). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=nMMAk4VwLLwC&amp;pg=&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Genocide: a history]''. Pearson Education. pp. 98–99. ISBN 0-582-50601-8&lt;/ref&gt; See [[Congo Free State]] for further details including numbers of victims.

A similar situation occurred in the neighbouring French Congo. Most of the resource extraction was run by concession companies, whose brutal methods resulted in the loss of up to 50 percent of the indigenous population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Vansina |first=Jan |title=Paths in the Rainforest |year=1966 |publisher=University of Wisconsin Press |location=Madison |page=239}}&lt;/ref&gt; The French government appointed a commission, headed by de Brazza, in 1905 to investigate the rumoured abuses in the colony. However, de Brazza died on the return trip, and his &quot;searingly critical&quot; report was neither acted upon nor released to the public.{{sfn|Hochschild|2006|pp=280–1}} In the 1920s, about 20,000 forced labourers died building a railroad through the French territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Coquéry-Vidrovitch |first=Catherine |title=Le Congo au temps des grandes compagnies concessionaires 1898–1930 |year=1971 |publisher=Mouton |location=Paris |page=195}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Suez Canal===
{{Main|Suez Canal}}
[[Ferdinand de Lesseps]] had obtained many concessions from [[Isma'il Pasha]], the [[Khedive]] of Egypt and Sudan, in 1854–56, to build the Suez Canal. Some sources estimate the workforce at 30,000,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arte.tv/fr/connaissance-decouverte/aventure-humaine/Cette_20semaine/1291022.html L'Aventure Humaine: ''Le canal de Suez'', Article de l'historien Uwe Oster].&lt;/ref&gt; but others estimate that 120,000 workers died over the ten years of construction due to malnutrition, fatigue and disease, especially [[cholera]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/5195068.stm BBC News website:The Suez Crisis — Key maps].&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly before its completion in 1869, Khedive Isma'il borrowed enormous sums from British and French bankers at high rates of interest. By 1875, he was facing financial difficulties and was forced to sell his block of shares in the Suez Canal. The shares were snapped up by Britain, under its [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]], [[Benjamin Disraeli]], who sought to give his country practical control in the management of this strategic waterway. When Isma'il repudiated Egypt's foreign debt in 1879, Britain and France seized joint financial control over the country, forcing the Egyptian ruler to abdicate, and installing his eldest son [[Tewfik Pasha]] in his place. The Egyptian and Sudanese ruling classes did not relish foreign intervention. During the 1870s, European initiatives against the [[slave trade]] caused an economic crisis in northern Sudan, precipitating the rise of [[Mahdist]] forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Domke, D. Michelle|url=http://www.american.edu/ted/ice/sudan.htm |title=ICE Case Studies; Case Number: 3; Case Identifier: Sudan; Case Name: Civil War in the Sudan: Resources or Religion?
| publisher = [[Inventory of Conflict and Environment]] (via the [[School of International Service]] at the [[American University]]) |date= November 1997|accessdate=8 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1881, the [[Mahdist revolt]] erupted in Sudan under [[Muhammad Ahmad]], severing Tewfik's authority in Sudan. The same year, Tewfik suffered an even more perilous rebellion by his own Egyptian army in the form of the [[Urabi Revolt]]. In 1882, Tewfik appealed for direct British military assistance, commencing Britain's occupation of Egypt. A joint British-Egyptian military force ultimately defeated the Mahdist forces in Sudan in 1898. Thereafter, Britain (rather than Egypt) seized effective control of Sudan.

===Berlin Conference (1884–85)===
{{Main|Berlin Conference}}
The occupation of Egypt, and the acquisition of the Congo were the first major moves in what came to be a precipitous scramble for African territory. In 1884, [[Otto von Bismarck]] convened the 1884–85 Berlin Conference to discuss the Africa problem. The diplomats put on a humanitarian façade by condemning the [[Slavery|slave trade]], prohibiting the sale of [[alcoholic beverage]]s and firearms in certain regions, and by expressing concern for missionary activities. More importantly, the diplomats in [[Berlin]] laid down the rules of competition by which the great powers were to be guided in seeking colonies. They also agreed that the area along the Congo River was to be administered by [[Léopold II of Belgium]] as a neutral area, known as the [[Congo Free State]], in which trade and navigation were to be free. No nation was to stake claims in Africa without notifying other powers of its intentions. No territory could be formally claimed prior to being effectively occupied. However, the competitors ignored the rules when convenient and on several occasions war was only narrowly avoided.

===Britain's occupation of Egypt and South Africa===
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2011}}
[[File:Boercamp1.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Boer]] women and children in a [[concentration camp]] during the [[Second Boer War]] (1899–1902)]]
Britain's occupations of [[Egypt]] and the [[Cape Colony]] contributed to a preoccupation over securing the source of the [[Nile River]]. Egypt was occupied by British forces in 1882 (although not formally declared a protectorate until 1914, and never an actual colony); [[Sudan]], [[Nigeria]], [[Kenya]] and [[Uganda]] were subjugated in the 1890s and early 20th century; and in the south, the Cape Colony (first acquired in 1795) provided a base for the subjugation of neighbouring African states and the Dutch [[Afrikaner]] settlers who had left the Cape to avoid the British and then founded their own republics. In 1877, [[Theophilus Shepstone]] annexed the [[South African Republic]] (or Transvaal – independent from 1857 to 1877) for the British. The UK consolidated its power over most of the colonies of [[South Africa]] in 1879 after the [[Anglo-Zulu War]]. The Boers protested and in December 1880 they revolted, leading to the [[First Boer War]] (1880–81). British Prime Minister [[William Ewart Gladstone|William Gladstone]] signed a peace treaty on 23 March 1881, giving self-government to the [[Boers]] in the Transvaal. The [[Jameson Raid]] of 1895 was a failed attempt by the British South Africa Company and the [[Johannesburg Reform Committee]] to overthrow the Boer government in the Transvaal. The [[Second Boer War]] was about control of the gold and diamond industries and was fought between 1899 and 1902; the independent Boer republics of the [[Orange Free State]] and of the South African Republic (Transvaal) were this time defeated and absorbed into the British Empire.

===Fashoda Incident===
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2011}} &lt;!-- There is a main article, but it is also under-referenced. --&gt;
{{Main|Fashoda Incident}}
[[File:LeCommandantMarchand.jpg|thumb|Contemporary illustration of Major [[Jean-Baptiste Marchand|Marchand]]'s trek across Africa.]]
The 1898 Fashoda Incident was one of the most crucial conflicts on Europe's way to consolidating holdings in the continent. It brought Britain and [[French Third Republic|France]] to the verge of war but ended in a major strategic victory for Britain, and provided the basis for the 1904 ''[[Entente Cordiale]]'' between the two rival countries. It stemmed from battles over control of the Nile headwaters, which caused Britain to expand in the Sudan.

[[File:Julesferry.jpg|left|thumb|upright|[[Jules Ferry]], French republican who, as prime minister, directed the negotiations which led to the establishment of a [[protectorate]] in Tunis (1881), prepared the December 17, 1885 treaty for the occupation of Madagascar; directed the exploration of the Congo and of the Niger region; and organised the conquest of [[Indochina]]. He resigned after the 1885 [[Sino-French War|Tonkin incident]].]]

The French thrust into the African interior was mainly from [[West Africa]] (modern day [[Senegal]]) eastward, through the [[Sahel]] along the southern border of the Sahara, a territory covering modern day [[Senegal]], [[Mali]], [[Niger]], and [[Chad]]. Their ultimate aim was to have an uninterrupted link between the [[Niger River]] and the Nile, thus controlling all trade to and from the Sahel region, by virtue of their existing control over the Caravan routes through the Sahara. The British, on the other hand, wanted to link their possessions in [[Southern Africa]] (modern South Africa], [[Botswana]], [[Zimbabwe]], [[Lesotho]], [[Swaziland]], and [[Zambia]]), with their territories in [[East Africa]] (modern [[Kenya]]), and these two areas with the Nile basin. [[Sudan]] (which in those days included modern day Uganda) was obviously key to the fulfilment of these ambitions, especially since Egypt was already under British control. This &quot;red line&quot; through Africa is made most famous by [[Cecil Rhodes]]. Along with [[Alfred Milner|Lord Milner]] (the British colonial minister in South Africa), Rhodes advocated such a &quot;Cape to Cairo&quot; empire linking by rail the Suez Canal to the mineral-rich Southern part of the continent. Though hampered by German occupation of [[Tanganyika]] until the end of World War I, Rhodes successfully lobbied on behalf of such a sprawling East African empire.

If one draws a line from [[Cape Town]] to [[Cairo]] (Rhodes' dream), and one from [[Dakar]] to the [[Horn of Africa]] (now [[Ethiopia]], [[Eritrea]], [[Djibouti]] and Somalia), (the French ambition), these two lines intersect somewhere in eastern Sudan near [[Fashoda Incident|Fashoda]], explaining its strategic importance. In short, Britain had sought to extend its East African empire contiguously from Cairo to the [[Cape of Good Hope]], while France had sought to extend its own holdings from Dakar to the Sudan, which would enable its empire to span the entire continent from the [[Atlantic Ocean]] to the [[Red Sea]].

A French force under [[Jean-Baptiste Marchand]] arrived first at the strategically located fort at Fashoda soon followed by a British force under [[Horatio Kitchener|Lord Kitchener]], commander in chief of the British army since 1892. The French withdrew after a standoff, and continued to press claims to other posts in the region. In March 1899 the French and British agreed that the source of the Nile and [[Congo River]]s should mark the frontier between their spheres of influence.

===Moroccan Crisis===
{{Main|First Moroccan Crisis|Second Moroccan Crisis}}
[[File:Abdelhafid.jpg|thumb|The Moroccan [[Sultan]] [[Abdelhafid of Morocco|Abdelhafid]], who led an anti-imperialist resistance during the [[Agadir Crisis]]]]
Although the 1884–85 Berlin Conference had set the rules for the scramble for Africa, it had not weakened the rival imperialisms. The 1898 Fashoda Incident, which had seen France and the UK on the brink of war, ultimately led to the signature of the 1904 ''[[Entente cordiale]]'', which reversed the influence of the various European powers. As a result, the new German power decided to test the solidity of the influence, using the contested territory of [[Morocco]] as a battlefield.

Thus, on 31 March 1905 [[Wilhelm II of Germany|Kaiser Wilhelm II]] visited [[Tangiers]] and made a speech in favor of Moroccan independence, challenging French influence in Morocco. France's influence in Morocco had been reaffirmed by Britain and Spain in 1904. The Kaiser's speech bolstered French nationalism and with British support the French foreign minister, [[Théophile Delcassé]], took a defiant line. The crisis peaked in mid-June 1905, when Delcassé was forced out of the ministry by the more conciliation-minded premier [[Maurice Rouvier]]. But by July 1905 Germany was becoming isolated and the French agreed to a conference to solve the crisis. Both France and Germany continued to posture up until the conference, with Germany mobilizing reserve army units in late December and France actually moving troops to the border in January 1906.

The 1906 [[Algeciras Conference]] was called to settle the dispute. Of the thirteen nations present the German representatives found their only supporter was [[Austria-Hungary]]. France had firm support from Britain, Russia, Italy, Spain, and the U.S. The Germans eventually accepted an agreement, signed on 31 May 1906, where France yielded certain domestic changes in Morocco but retained control of key areas.

However, five years later the second Moroccan crisis (or [[Agadir Crisis]]) was sparked by the deployment of the German gunboat ''[[SMS Panther|Panther]]'', to the port of [[Agadir]] on 1 July 1911. Germany had started to attempt to surpass [[United Kingdom|Britain]]'s [[History of the Royal Navy|naval supremacy]] – the British navy had a policy of remaining larger than the next two naval fleets in the world combined. When the British heard of the ''Panther'''s arrival in Morocco, they wrongly believed that the Germans meant to turn Agadir into a naval base on the Atlantic.

The German move was aimed at reinforcing claims for compensation for acceptance of effective French control of the [[North Africa]]n kingdom, where France's pre-eminence had been upheld by the 1906 Algeciras Conference. In November 1911 a convention was signed under which Germany accepted France's position in Morocco in return for territory in the [[French Equatorial Africa]]n colony of [[Middle Congo]] (now the [[Republic of the Congo]]).

France subsequently established a full [[protectorate]] over Morocco (30 March 1912), ending what remained of the country's formal independence. Furthermore, British backing for France during the two Moroccan crises reinforced the Entente between the two countries and added to Anglo-German estrangement, deepening the divisions that would culminate in World War I.
[[File:Sayyid Mohammed Abdullah Hassan.jpeg|thumb|upright|Statue of Sayyid [[Mohammed Abdullah Hassan]], the &quot;Mad Mullah&quot;, who led a twenty-year long anti-imperial resistance war.]]

===Dervish resistance===
Following the [[Berlin conference]] at the end of the 19th century, the [[British people|British]], [[Italian people|Italians]] and [[Ethiopia]]ns sought to claim lands owned by the Somalis such as the [[Warsangali Sultanate]], the [[Ajuuraan State]] and the [[Gobroon Dynasty]].

The [[Dervish State]] was a response established by [[Muhammad Abdullah Hassan]], a Somali religious leader who gathered Muslim soldiers from across the [[Horn of Africa]] and united them into a loyal army known as the ''Dervishes''. This Dervish army enabled Hassan to carve out a powerful state through conquest of lands sought after by the Ethiopians and the European powers. The Dervish State successfully repulsed the British Empire four times and forced it to retreat to the coastal region.&lt;ref&gt;Kevin Shillington, ''Encyclopedia of African History'' (CRC Press, 2005), p. 1406.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to these successful expeditions, the Dervish State was recognized as an ally by the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] and [[German Empire|German]] empires. The [[Turkish people|Turks]] also named Hassan [[Emir]] of the Somali nation,&lt;ref&gt;I. M. Lewis, ''The Modern History of Somaliland: from nation to state'' (Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson: 1965), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; and the Germans promised to officially recognize any territories the Dervishes were to acquire.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas P. Ofcansky, ''Historical Dictionary of Ethiopia'' (The Scarecrow Press, Inc.: 2004), p. 405.&lt;/ref&gt;

After a quarter of a century of holding the British at bay, the Dervishes were finally defeated in 1920 as a direct consequence of Britain's new policy of [[Airstrike|aerial bombardment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Samatar | first = Said Sheikh | title = Oral Poetry and Somali Nationalism | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 1982 | pages = 131 &amp; 135 | isbn = 0-521-23833-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Colonial encounter==

===Colonial consciousness and exhibitions===
[[File:African Pigmies CNE-v1-p58-B.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Pygmies]] and a European. Some pygmies would be exposed in [[human zoo]]s, such as [[Ota Benga]] displayed by [[eugenicist]] [[Madison Grant]] in the [[Bronx Zoo]].]]

====Colonial lobby====
In its earlier stages, imperialism was generally the act of individual explorers as well as some adventurous merchantmen. The colonial powers were a long way from approving without any dissent the expensive adventures carried out abroad. Various important political leaders such as [[William Ewart Gladstone|Gladstone]] opposed colonisation in its first years. However, during his second premiership in 1880–1885 he could not resist the colonial lobby in his cabinet, and thus did not execute his electoral promise to disengage from Egypt. Although Gladstone was personally opposed to imperialism, the [[class conflict|social tensions]] caused by the [[Long Depression]] pushed him to favor [[jingoism]]: the imperialists had become the &quot;parasites of [[patriotism]]&quot; ([[John A. Hobson|Hobson]]&lt;ref&gt;[[John A. Hobson]], ''[[Imperialism (Hobson)|Imperialism]]'', 1902, p. 61 (quoted by Arendt).&lt;/ref&gt;). In [[French Third Republic|France]], then [[Radical-Socialist Party (France)|Radical]] politician [[Georges Clemenceau]] also adamantly opposed himself to it: he thought colonisation was a diversion from the &quot;blue line of the [[Vosges mountains|Vosges]]&quot; mountains, that is [[revanchism]] and the patriotic urge to reclaim the [[Alsace-Lorraine]] region which had been annexed by the German Empire with the 1871 [[Treaty of Frankfurt (1871)|Treaty of Frankfurt]]. Clemenceau actually made [[Jules Ferry]]'s cabinet fall after the 1885 [[Sino-French War|Tonkin disaster]]. According to [[Hannah Arendt]] in ''[[The Origins of Totalitarianism]]'' (1951), this expansion of national sovereignty] on overseas territories contradicted the unity of the [[nation state]] which provided citizenship to its population. Thus, a tension between the [[Moral universalism|universalist]] will to respect human rights of the colonised people, as they may be considered as &quot;citizens&quot; of the nation state, and the imperialist drives to cynically [[exploitation|exploit]] populations deemed inferior began to surface. Some, in colonising countries, opposed what they saw as unnecessary evils of the colonial administration when left to itself; as described in [[Joseph Conrad]]'s ''[[Heart of Darkness]]'' (1899) – contemporary of [[Rudyard Kipling|Kipling]]'s ''[[The White Man's Burden]]'' – or in [[Louis-Ferdinand Céline]]'s ''[[Journey to the End of the Night]]'' (1932).

Thus, colonial lobbies were progressively set up to legitimise the Scramble for Africa and other expensive overseas adventures. In Germany, in France, in Britain, the middle class began to claim strong overseas policies to insure the market's growth. In 1916, [[Vladimir Lenin]] published ''[[Imperialism, the Highest Stage of Capitalism]]'' describing this phenomenon. Even in lesser powers, voices like [[Enrico Corradini]] began to claim a &quot;place in the sun&quot; for so-called &quot;proletarian nations&quot;, bolstering [[nationalism]] and [[militarism]] in an early prototype of [[fascism]].

====Colonial propaganda and jingoism====

=====Colonial exhibitions=====
{{Refimprove section|date=September 2011}}
[[File:Dellepiane-exposition-nationale-coloniale-1906.jpg|thumb|Poster for the 1906 [[Colonial Exhibition]] in [[Marseilles]] (France)]]
However, by the end of World War I the colonial empires had become very popular almost everywhere in Europe: [[public opinion]] had been convinced of the needs of a colonial empire, although most of the metropolitans would never see a piece of it. [[Colonial exhibition]]s had been instrumental in this change of popular mentalities brought about by the colonial [[propaganda]], supported by the colonial lobby and by various scientists. Thus, the conquest of territories were inevitably followed by public displays of the [[indigenous people]] for scientific and leisure purposes. Karl Hagenbeck, a German merchant in wild animals and future entrepreneur of most Europeans zoos, thus decided in 1874 to exhibit [[Samoa]] and [[Sami people]] as &quot;purely natural&quot; populations. In 1876, he sent one of his collaborators to the newly conquered Egyptian Sudan to bring back some wild beasts and [[Nubians]]. Presented in Paris, London and Berlin, these Nubians were very successful. Such &quot;[[human zoos]]&quot; could be found in Hamburg, Antwerp, Barcelona, London, Milan, New York, Warsaw, etc., with 200,000 to 300,000 visitors attending each exhibition. [[Tuaregs]] were exhibited after the French conquest of [[Timbuktu]] (discovered by [[René Caillé]], disguised as a Muslim, in 1828, thereby winning the prize offered by the French ''Société de Géographie''); [[Malagasy people|Malagasy]] after the occupation of [[Madagascar]]; [[Dahomey Amazons|Amazons]] of [[Abomey]] after [[Behanzin]]'s mediatic defeat against the French in 1894. Not used to the climatic conditions, some of the indigenous exposed died, such as some [[Galibis]] in Paris in 1892.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.africultures.com/anglais/articles_anglais/43blanchard.htm From human zoos to colonial apotheoses: the era of exhibiting the Other], by Pascal Blanchard, Nicolas Bancel, and Sandrine Lemaire&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:TintinCongo.jpg|thumb|left|English-edition cover of [[Hergé]]'s ''[[Tintin in the Congo]]'' (1930-31). ''Le Petit Vingtième'' magazine staged a triumphant return of &quot;Tintin&quot; and &quot;Snowy&quot; to [[Brussels]] on 9 July 1931. They were accompanied by ten Congolese and met by Hergé himself.]] --&gt;

Geoffroy de Saint-Hilaire, director of the Parisian Jardin d'acclimatation, decided in 1877 to organise two &quot;ethnological spectacles&quot;, presenting Nubians and [[Inuit]]. The public of the Jardin d'acclimatation doubled, with a million paying entrances that year, a huge success for these times. Between 1877 and 1912, approximatively thirty &quot;ethnological exhibitions&quot; were presented at the Jardin zoologique d'acclimatation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.monde-diplomatique.fr/2000/08/BANCEL/14145.html &quot;These human zoos of the Colonial Republic&quot;], ''[[Le Monde diplomatique]]'', August 2000, {{fr icon}} ([http://mondediplo.com/2000/08/07humanzoo Translation] {{en icon}})&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Negro villages&quot; would be presented in Paris' 1878 and 1879 World's Fair; the 1900 World's Fair presented the famous [[diorama]] &quot;living&quot; in Madagascar, while the Colonial Exhibitions in Marseilles (1906 and 1922) and in Paris (1907 and 1931) would also display human beings in cages, often nudes or quasi-nudes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.discoverparis.net/newsletter.html?insight=3162983825694464 |title=February 2003, the end of an era |publisher=Discoverparis.net |date= |accessdate=2010-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nomadic &quot;[[Senegal]]ese villages&quot; were also created, thus displaying the power of the colonial empire to all the population.

In the U.S., [[Madison Grant]], head of the [[New York Zoological Society]], exposed [[Pygmies|Pygmy]] [[Ota Benga]] in the [[Bronx Zoo]] alongside the apes and others in 1906. At the behest of Grant, a prominent [[scientific racist]] and [[eugenicist]], zoo director Hornaday, placed Ota Benga in a cage with an orangutan and labeled him &quot;The Missing Link&quot; in an attempt to illustrate [[Darwinism]], and in particular that Africans like Ota Benga are closer to apes than were Europeans. Other colonial exhibitions included the 1924 [[British Empire Exhibition]] and the successful 1931 Paris &quot;Exposition coloniale.&quot;

===Extermination of the Namaqua and the Herero===
{{Main|Herero and Namaqua genocide}}
[[File:Baartman.jpg|thumb|left|upright|A 19th-century [[caricature]] of the &quot;[[Hottentot Venus]]&quot;. [[Saartje Baartman]], a [[Khoisan]] woman, was exhibited naked and in a cage as a sideshow attraction in England, fueling the African Association's indignation. After her death, her genitals were dissected and cast in wax. [[Nelson Mandela]] formally requested France to return her remains, which had been kept at the Parisian [[Musée de l'Homme]] until 1974.]]
[[File:Surviving Herero.jpg|thumb|Surviving [[Herero people|Herero]], emaciated, after their escape through the [[Omaheke]] desert.]]
In 1985, the [[United Nations]]' Whitaker Report classified Germany's turn of the 19th to 20th century attempt to exterminate the [[Herero people|Herero]] and [[Namaqua]] people of [[South-West Africa]] as one of the earliest attempts at [[genocide]] in the 20th century. In total, some 65,000 Herero (80% of the total Herero population), and 10,000 Namaqua (50% of the total Namaqua population) were killed between 1904 and 1907. Characteristic of this genocide was death by starvation and the poisoning of the population's wells whilst they were trapped in the [[Namib Desert]].

==Colonialism leading to World War I==
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2011}}
During the New Imperialism period, by the end of the 19th century, Europe added almost {{Convert|9000000|mi2}} – one-fifth of the land area of the globe – to its overseas colonial possessions. Europe's formal holdings now included the entire African continent except [[Ethiopia]], [[Liberia]], and [[Saguia el-Hamra]], the latter of which would be integrated into [[Spanish Sahara]]. Between 1885 and 1914 Britain took nearly 30% of Africa's population under its control; 15% for France, 11% for Portugal, 9% for Germany, 7% for Belgium and 1% for [[Italy]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} [[Nigeria]] alone contributed 15 million subjects, more than in the whole of [[French West Africa]] or the entire German colonial empire. It was paradoxical that Britain, the staunch advocate of free trade, emerged in 1914 with not only the largest overseas empire thanks to its long-standing presence in [[British Raj|India]], but also the greatest gains in the &quot;scramble for Africa&quot;, reflecting its advantageous position at its inception. In terms of surface area occupied, the French were the marginal victors but much of their territory consisted of the sparsely populated [[Sahara]].

The political imperialism followed the economic expansion, with the &quot;colonial lobbies&quot; bolstering [[chauvinism]] and [[jingoism]] at each crisis in order to legitimise the colonial enterprise. The tensions between the imperial powers led to a succession of crises, which finally exploded in August 1914, when previous rivalries and alliances created a domino situation that drew the major European nations into the [[First World War]]. [[Austria-Hungary]] attacked [[Serbia]] to avenge the murder by Serbian agents of Austrian crown prince Francis Ferdinand, [[Russia]] would mobilise to assist allied Serbia, Germany would intervene to support Austria-Hungary against Russia. Since Russia had a military alliance with France against Germany, the [[German General Staff]], led by [[Helmuth von Moltke the Younger|General von Moltke]] decided to realise the well prepared [[Schlieffen Plan]] to invade France and quickly knock her out of the war before turning against Russia in what was expected to be a long campaign. This required an invasion of Belgium which brought Britain into the war against Germany, Austria-Hungary and their allies. German [[U-Boat]] campaigns against ships bound for Britain eventually drew the [[United States]] into what had become World War I. Moreover, using the Anglo-Japanese Alliance as an excuse, [[Japan]] leaped onto this opportunity to conquer German interests in [[China]] and the [[Pacific]] to become the dominating power in Western Pacific, setting the stage for the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] (starting in 1937) and eventually World War II.

==African colonies listed by colonizing power==

===Belgium===
[[File:Congo belge campagne 1918.jpg|thumb|[[Force Publique]] soldiers in the Belgian Congo. At its peak, the FP had 19,000 African soldiers, led by 420 white officers.]]
*[[Congo Free State]] and [[Belgian Congo]] (today's [[Democratic Republic of the Congo]])
*[[Ruanda-Urundi]] (comprising modern [[Rwanda]] and [[Burundi]], 1922–62)

===France===
{|
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[French West Africa]] :
**[[Mauritania]]
**[[Senegal]]
**[[Albreda]] (1681–1857, now part of [[Gambia]])
**[[French Sudan]] (now [[Mali]])
**[[French Guinea]] (now [[Guinea]])
**[[Ivory Coast]]
**[[Colony of Niger|Niger]]
**[[French Upper Volta]]  (now [[Burkina Faso]])
**[[French Dahomey]]  (now [[Benin]])
**[[French Togoland]] (1916–60, now [[Togo]])
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[French Equatorial Africa]] :
**[[Gabon]]
**[[French Cameroun]] (1922–60)
**[[French Congo]]   (now [[Republic of the Congo]])
**[[Oubangi-Chari]]  (now [[Central African Republic]])
**[[Colonial Chad|Chad]]
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[French North Africa]] :
**[[French Algeria]]
**[[French Protectorate of Tunisia]]
**[[French Morocco]]
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[French East Africa]] :
**[[Madagascar]]
**[[Comoros]]
**[[Scattered islands in the Indian Ocean]]
**[[French Somaliland]] (now [[Djibouti]])
|}

===Germany===
*[[German Kamerun]] (now [[Cameroon]] and part of [[Nigeria]], 1884–1916)
*[[German East Africa]] (now [[Rwanda]], [[Burundi]] and most of [[Tanzania]], 1885–1919)
*[[German South-West Africa]] (now [[Namibia]], 1884–1915)
*[[German Togoland]] (now [[Togo]] and eastern part of [[Ghana]], 1884–1914)
[[File:Africa1898.png|thumb|French map of Africa c. 1898 with colonial claims. British possessions are in yellow; French possessions in pink; Belgian in orange; German in green; Portuguese in purple; Italian in striped pink; Spanish in striped orange; independent Ethiopia in brown]]

===Italy===
*[[Italian North Africa]]
**[[Italian Libya]]

*[[Italian East Africa]]
**[[Italian Eritrea]]
**[[Italian Somaliland]]
**[[Italian Ethiopia]]

===Portugal===
{|
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Portuguese West Africa]]&lt;br /&gt;(now [[Angola]])
**Mainland [[Angola]]
**[[Portuguese Congo]]&lt;br /&gt;(now [[Cabinda Province]] of [[Angola]])
*[[Portuguese East Africa]]&lt;br /&gt;(now [[Mozambique]])
*[[Portuguese Guinea]]&lt;br /&gt;(now [[Guinea-Bissau]])
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Cape Verde Islands]]
*[[São Tomé e Príncipe]]
**[[São Tomé Island]]
**[[Príncipe Island]]
**[[Fort of São João Baptista de Ajudá]]&lt;br /&gt;(now [[Ouidah]], in [[Benin]])
|}

===Russia===
{|
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Sagallo]] (Now [[Djibouti]], 1889)
|}

===Spain===
{|
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Spanish North Africa]]
**Northern [[Spanish Morocco]]
***Chefchaouen (''Chauen'')
***Jebala (''Yebala'')
***Kert
***Loukkos (''Lucus'')
***Rif
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Spanish West Africa]]
**Southern Spanish Morocco
***[[Cape Juby]]
***[[Ifni]]
**[[Spanish Sahara]]&lt;br /&gt;(now [[Western Sahara]])
***[[Río de Oro]]
***[[Saguia el-Hamra]]
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Spanish Guinea]]&lt;br /&gt;(now [[Equatorial Guinea]])
**[[Bioko|Fernando Poo]]
**[[Río Muni]]
**[[Annobón]]
|}

===United Kingdom===
[[File:1899railroad salisbury.jpg|thumb|Opening of the railway in [[Southern Rhodesia|Rhodesia]], 1899]]
The British were primarily interested in maintaining secure communication lines to [[India]], which led to initial interest in [[Egypt]] and [[South Africa]]. Once these two areas were secure, it was the intent of British colonialists such as [[Cecil Rhodes]] to establish a Cape-Cairo railway. Control of the [[Nile]] was viewed as strategic and commercial advantage.

{|
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[British Egypt|Egypt]]
*[[Anglo-Egyptian Sudan]] (1899–1956)
*[[British Somaliland]] (now part of [[Somalia]])
*[[British East Africa]]:
**[[Kenya Colony]]
**[[Uganda Protectorate]]
**[[Tanzania]] :
***[[Tanganyika Territory]] (1919–61)
***[[Zanzibar]]
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Bechuanaland]] (now [[Botswana]])
*[[Southern Rhodesia]] (now [[Zimbabwe]])
*[[Northern Rhodesia]] (now [[Zambia]])
*[[Union of South Africa|British South Africa]]
**[[South Africa]] :
***[[Transvaal Colony]]
***[[Cape Colony]]
***[[Colony of Natal]]
***[[Orange River Colony]]
**[[South-West Africa]] (from 1915, now [[Namibia]])
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[The Gambia]]
*[[Sierra Leone]]
*[[Colonial Nigeria|Nigeria]]
*[[British Togoland]] (1916–56, today part of [[Ghana]])
*[[Cameroons]] (1922–61, now parts of [[Cameroon]] and [[Nigeria]])
*[[British Gold Coast]] (now [[Ghana]])
*[[Nyasaland]] (now [[Malawi]])
*[[Basutoland]] (now [[Lesotho]])
*[[Swaziland]]
|}

===Independent states===
*[[Liberia]], founded by the [[American Colonization Society]] of the [[United States]] in 1821; declared independence in 1847
*[[Ethiopian Empire]] ([[Ethiopian Empire|Abyssinia]]) had its borders re-drawn with [[Italian Eritrea]] briefly occupied by [[Italy]] from 1936–1941 during the [[Abyssinia Crisis]]

==See also==
*[[African Atlantis]]
*[[Banana Wars]]
*[[Chronology of colonialism]]
*[[Civilizing mission]]
*[[Decolonization of Africa]]
*[[Impact and evaluation of colonialism and colonization]]
*[[List of Colony and possessions of France]]
*[[List of former sovereign states#Pre-colonial Africa]]
*[[List of largest empires]]
*[[Scientific racism]]
*[[White African]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
&lt;!--* {{cite book
  |last = Arendt |first = Hannah |authorlink = Hannah Arendt
  |year = 1958 |origyear = 1951 |title = [[The Origins of Totalitarianism]]
  |location = Cleveland, OH |publisher = Meridian
  |isbn =  |ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  |last = Hobsbawm |first = Eric |authorlink = Eric Hobsbawm
  |year = 1994 |origyear = 1987 |title = The Age of Empire: 1875–1914
  |location = London |publisher = Abacus
  |isbn = 978-0-349-10598-7 |ref = harv
  }}--&gt;
* {{cite book
  |last = Hochschild |first = Adam |authorlink = Adam Hochschild
  |year = 2006 |origyear = 1998 |title = King Lepold's Ghost: A Story of Greed, Terror, and Heroism in Colonial Africa
  |location = London |publisher = Pan Books
  |isbn = 978-0-330-44198-8 |ref = harv
  }}
&lt;!--
* [[Sven Lindqvist|Lindqvist, Sven]]. ''Exterminate All the Brutes'' (''Utrota varenda jävel'', 1992)
*{{cite book
  |last1 = Olusoga |first1 = David |last2 = Erichsen |first2 = Casper W
  |year = 2011 |origyear = 2010
  |title = The Kaiser's Holocaust: Germany's Forgotten Genocide
  |location = London |publisher = Faber and Faber
  |isbn = 978-0-571-23142-3 |ref = harv
  }}--&gt;
* {{cite book
  |last = Pakenham |first = Thomas |authorlink = Thomas Pakenham (historian)
  |year = 1992 |origyear = 1991 |title = [[The Scramble for Africa (book)|The Scramble for Africa]]
  |location = London |publisher = Abacus
  |isbn = 978-0-349-10449-2 |ref = harv
  }}

==External links==
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/print/0,3858,4460659-103681,00.html Belgium exhumes its colonial demons]
{{Africa topics}}
{{Great power diplomacy}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Scramble For Africa}}
[[Category:19th century in Africa]]
[[Category:19th century in international relations]]
[[Category:20th century in international relations]]
[[Category:European colonisation in Africa]]
[[Category:Geopolitical rivalry]]
[[Category:History of Africa]]
[[Category:History of international relations]]
[[Category:New Imperialism]]
[[Category:Articles with images not understandable by color blind users]]

[[af:Wedloop om Afrika]]
[[ar:الهروع إلى أفريقيا]]
[[an:Reparto d'Africa]]
[[ast:Repartición d'África]]
[[bn:আফ্রিকা দখলের লড়াই]]
[[be:Каланіяльны падзел Афрыкі]]
[[ca:Cursa per l'Àfrica]]
[[cy:Yr Ymgiprys am Affrica]]
[[da:Kapløbet om Afrika]]
[[de:Wettlauf um Afrika]]
[[es:Reparto de África]]
[[eo:Disdivido de Afriko]]
[[eu:Afrikaren banaketa]]
[[fa:تقسیم آفریقا]]
[[fr:Partage de l'Afrique]]
[[ko:아프리카 분할]]
[[hi:अफ्रीका के लिये हाथापाई]]
[[hr:Utrka za Afriku]]
[[id:Perebutan Afrika]]
[[it:Storia del colonialismo in Africa]]
[[he:המרוץ לאפריקה]]
[[lad:Partajamiento de Afrika]]
[[hu:Hajsza Afrikáért]]
[[ms:Perebutan Afrika]]
[[mwl:Partilha de la África]]
[[nl:Wedloop om Afrika]]
[[ja:アフリカ分割]]
[[no:Kappløpet om Afrika]]
[[nn:Kappløpet om Afrika]]
[[pl:Wyścig o Afrykę]]
[[pt:Partilha de África]]
[[ro:Lupta pentru Africa]]
[[ru:Колониальный раздел Африки]]
[[scn:Culunialismu n Africa]]
[[simple:Scramble for Africa]]
[[sr:Osvajanje Afrike]]
[[sh:Utrka za Afriku]]
[[sv:Kapplöpningen om Afrika]]
[[tl:Pag-aagawan para sa Aprika]]
[[th:การล่าอาณานิคมในแอฟริกา]]
[[uk:Колоніальний розподіл Африки]]
[[war:Pag-aragaw para ha Aprika]]
[[yo:Ìjàdù fún Áfríkà]]
[[zh:瓜分非洲]]</text>
      <sha1>rxb1typptja0054co0xw793mi1jf0l1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
