<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Secondary source</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23499848</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520633117</id>
      <parentid>520630368</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T19:26:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Saddhiyama</username>
        <id>5160420</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/173.62.181.209|173.62.181.209]] ([[User talk:173.62.181.209|talk]]) identified as [[WP:VAND|vandalism]] to last revision by ClueBot NG. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15329">{{selfref|For the use of this term in Wikipedia's policies, see [[Wikipedia:No original research#Primary, secondary, and tertiary sources|Wikipedia:No original research]].}}

In [[Scholarly method|scholarship]], a '''secondary source'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lib.umd.edu/guides/primary-sources.html Primary, Secondary and Tertiary Sources, UM Libraries]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-public.jcu.edu.au/libcomp/assist/guides/azguides/JCUPRD_030412  Primary, Secondary &amp; Tertiary Sources] - James Cook University&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[document]] or [[recording]] that relates or discusses [[information]] originally presented elsewhere. A secondary source contrasts with a [[primary source]], which is an original source of the information being discussed; a primary source can be a person with direct knowledge of a situation, or a document created by such a person.

Secondary sources involve generalization, analysis, synthesis, interpretation, or evaluation of the original information. ''Primary'' and ''secondary'' are relative terms, and some sources may be classified as primary or secondary, depending on how it is used.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ithacalibrary.com/sp/subjects/primary  Research Guides: Primary and secondary sources] - Ithaca College Library&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| last=Kragh| first=Helge| title=An Introduction to the Historiography of Science| year=1989| publisher=Cambridge University Press| isbn=0-521-38921-6| url=http://books.google.com/?id=d2zy_QSq2b0C&amp;pg=PA121&amp;lpg=PA121&amp;dq=%22secondary+source%22+historiography|page=121|quote=[T]he distinction is not a sharp one. Since a source is only a source in a specific historical context, the same source object can be both a primary or secondary source according to what it is used for.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last1=Delgadillo|first1=Roberto|last2=Lynch|first2=Beverly|title=Future Historians: Their Quest for Information|url=http://crl.acrl.org/content/60/3/245.full.pdf+html|journal=College &amp; Research Libraries|year=1999|pages=245–259, at 253|quote=[T]he same document can be a primary or a secondary source depending on the particular analysis the historian is doing}},&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last1=Monagahn|first1=E.J.|last2=Hartman|first2=D.K.|year=2001|title=Historical research in literacy |journal=Reading Online|volume=4|issue=11|url=http://www.readingonline.org/articles/art_index.asp?HREF=/articles/handbook/monaghan/index.html|quote=[A] source may be primary or secondary, depending on what the researcher is looking for.}}&lt;/ref&gt; An even higher level, the [[tertiary source]], such as an encyclopedia or dictionary, resembles a secondary source in that it contains analysis, but attempts to provide a broad introductory overview of a topic.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Veit and Christopher Gould, ''Writing, Reading, and Research'' (8th ed. 2009) p 335&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classification==
Many sources can be considered either primary or secondary, depending on the context in which they are used.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Kragh|1989|p=121}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the distinction between ''primary'' and ''secondary'' sources is subjective and contextual,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Dalton|Charnigo|2004|p=419 n.18}}.&lt;/ref&gt; so that precise definitions are difficult to make.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Delgadillo|Lynch|1999|p=253}}.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, if a historical text discusses old documents to derive a new historical conclusion, it is considered to be a primary source for the new conclusion, but a secondary source of information found in the old documents.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}} Other examples in which a source can be both primary and secondary include an [[obituary]]&lt;ref name=Duffin&gt;{{Citation|last=Duffin|first=Jacalyn|title=History of Medicine: A Scandalously Short Introduction|url=http://books.google.com/?id=__oDQ6yDO7kC&amp;pg=PA366&amp;dq=%22secondary+source%22+historiography|year=1999|publisher=University of Toronto Press|isbn=0-8020-7912-1|page=366}}&lt;/ref&gt; or a survey of several volumes of a journal counting the frequency of articles on a certain topic.&lt;ref name=Duffin/&gt;

Whether a source is regarded as primary or secondary in a given context may change, depending upon the present state of knowledge within the field.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Henige|first=David|authorlink=David Henige|title=Primary Source by Primary Source? On the Role of Epidemics in New World Depopulation|journal=Ethnohistory|volume=33|issue=3|year=1986|pages=292–312, at 292|doi=10.2307/481816|jstor=481816|publisher=Duke University Press|quote=[T]he term 'primary' inevitably carries a relative meaning insofar as it defines those pieces of information that stand in closest relationship to an event or process ''in the present state of our knowledge''. Indeed, in most instances the very nature of a primary source tells us that it is actually derivative.…[H]istorians have no choice but to regard certain of the available sources as 'primary' since they are as near to truly original sources as they can now secure.}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, if a document refers to the contents of a previous but undiscovered letter, that document may be considered &quot;primary&quot;, since it is the closest known thing to an original source, but if the letter is later found, it may then be considered &quot;secondary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Henige|1986|p=292}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Attempts to map or model scientific and scholarly communication need the concepts of primary, secondary and further &quot;levels&quot;. One such model is the [[UNISIST model]] of information dissemination. Within such a model these concepts are defined in relation to each other, and the acceptance of this way of defining the concepts are connected to the acceptance of the model.

Some other [[modern language]]s use more than one word for the English word &quot;source&quot;. [[German language|German]] usually uses ''Sekundärliteratur'' (&quot;secondary literature&quot;) for secondary sources for historical facts, leaving ''Sekundärquelle'' (&quot;secondary source&quot;) to [[historiography]]. A ''Sekundärquelle'' is a source which can tell about a lost ''Primärquelle'' (&quot;primary source&quot;), such as a letter quoting from minutes which are no longer known to exist, so cannot be consulted by the historian.

===In science and technology===
In the sciences, a [[Review journal|review article]] or [[meta-analysis]] are both examples of a secondary source. A [[book review]] that contains the judgment of the reviewer about the book is a primary source for the reviewer's opinion, and a secondary source for the contents of the book.&lt;ref name=&quot;Princeton&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://wordnetweb.princeton.edu/perl/webwn?s=book%20review|title=Book reviews |accessdate=September 22, 2011 |publisher=Princeton |year=2011 |author=Princeton|work=Scholarly definition document }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VirginiaTech&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.lib.vt.edu/find/byformat/bookreviews.html|title=Book reviews |accessdate=September 22, 2011 |publisher=Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University |year=2011 |author=Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University|work=Scholarly definition document }}&lt;/ref&gt; A summary of the book within a review is a secondary source. Some [[academic journals]] only publish reviews. A report of an experiment conducted by the author can be considered a primary sources information. A survey of previous work in the field in a primary peer-reviewed source is secondary source information. This vastly increases the amount of secondary source information available when there are few reviews in a field.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

====Health sciences====
In a medical research, primary source materials are defined as &quot;original research papers written by the scientists who actually conducted the study.&quot; An example of primary source material is the Purpose, Methods, and Results sections of a research paper (in [[IMRAD]] style) in a scientific journal by the authors who conducted the study.&lt;ref name=Garrand2010&gt;{{cite book|author=Garrard, Judith |title=Health Sciences Literature Review Made Easy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=CSbfIcjQUcsC&amp;pg=PA30#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=16 September 2012|date=25 October 2010|publisher=Jones &amp; Bartlett Publishers|isbn=978-1-4496-1868-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Examples of secondary source materials include a summary of the literature in the Introduction of a scientific paper published in a journal, a description of what is known about a disease or treatment in a chapter in a reference book, or a synthesis written to review available literature.&lt;ref name=Garrand2010/&gt;

Some scientific document [[search engine]]s, such as [[PubMed]], allow users to limit their searches to reviews and meta-analyses. Secondary sources can help trace the history of scientific and mathematical ideas, including who is credited as the original source of the idea.{{citation needed|date=September 2012}}

====Library and information science====
In [[library and information science]]s, secondary sources are generally regarded as those sources that summarize or add commentary to [[primary sources]] in the context of the particular information or idea under study.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lib.umd.edu/guides/primary-sources.html &quot;Primary, secondary and tertiary sources&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.library.jcu.edu.au/LibraryGuides/primsrcs.shtml &quot;Library Guides: Primary, secondary and tertiary sources&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Mathematics ====
An important use of secondary sources in the field of [[mathematics]] has been to make difficult mathematical ideas and proofs from primary sources more accessible to the public;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Edwards|first=H.M.|authorlink=Harold Edwards (mathematician)|title=Riemann's Zeta Function|year=2001|publisher=Courier Dover Publications|publication-place=Mineola, New York|isbn=0-486-41740-9|page=xi|url=http://books.google.com/?id=5uLAoued_dIC&amp;pg=PR9&amp;dq=%22primary+sources%22|quote=The purpose of a secondary source is to make the primary sources accessible to you. If you can read and understand the primary sources without reading this book, more power to you. If you read this book without reading the primary sources you are like a man who carries a sack lunch to a banquet}}&lt;/ref&gt; in other sciences [[tertiary source]]s are expected to fulfill the introductory role.

===In humanities and history===
Secondary sources in history and humanities are usually books or [[academic journal|scholarly journal]], from the perspective of a later interpreter, especially by a later scholar. In the humanities, a [[peer review]]ed article is always a secondary source.
The delineation of sources as [[primary sources|primary]] and secondary first arose in the field of [[historiography]], as historians attempted to identify and classify the sources of historical writing.  In scholarly writing, an important objective of classifying sources is to determine the independence and reliability of sources.&lt;ref&gt;Helge (1989), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; In  original scholarly writing, historians rely on primary sources, read in the context of the scholarly interpretations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Cipolla|publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Co.|title=Between Two Cultures: An Introduction to Economic History|year=1992|isbn=978-0-393-30816-7|url=http://books.google.com/?id=GIqRTlepwmoC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=cipolla}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Following the Rankean model established by German scholarship in the 19th century, historians make heavy use of [[archive]]s of primary sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Frederick C. Beiser|title=The German Historicist Tradition|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fQ1k6w0dFIMC&amp;pg=PA254|year=2011|publisher=Oxford U.P.|page=254}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, most undergraduate research projects rely chiefly on secondary source material, with perhaps snippets of primary sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Charles Camic|author2=Neil Gross|author3=Michele Lamont|title=Social Knowledge in the Making|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0l7iDZY-MSoC&amp;pg=PA107|year=2011|publisher=U. of Chicago Press|page=107}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Law====
In the legal field, source classification is important because the persuasiveness of a source usually depends upon its history. Primary sources may include cases, constitutions, statutes, administrative regulations, and other sources of binding legal authority, while secondary legal sources may include books, articles, and encyclopedias.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Bouchoux|first=Deborah E.|year=2000|title=Cite Checker: A Hands-On Guide to Learning Citation Form|page=45|publisher=Thomson Delmar Learning|isbn=0-7668-1893-4|url=http://books.google.com/?id=RJ4vlBrWu0MC&amp;pg=PA45&amp;dq=%22primary+sources%22+%22science+citation%22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Legal writers usually prefer to cite primary sources because only primary sources are authoritative and [[precedent]]ial, while secondary sources are only persuasive at best.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Bouchoux|2000|p=45}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Family history====
&quot;A secondary source is a record or statement of an event or circumstance made by a non-eyewitness or by someone not closely connected with the event or circumstances, recorded or stated verbally either at or sometime after the event, or by an eye-witness at a time after the event when the fallibility of memory is an important factor.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Harland, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, according to this definition, a first hand account written long after the event &quot;when the fallibility of memory is an important factor&quot; is a secondary source, even though it may be the first published description of that event.

====Autobiographies====
An autobiography can be a secondary source in history or the humanities when used for information about topics other than its subject. For example, many first hand accounts of events in [[World War I]] written in the post-war years were influenced by the then prevailing perception of the war which was significantly different from contemporary opinion.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes, particularly the introduction&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Primary source]]
*[[Tertiary source]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Jules R. Benjamin, ''A Student's Guide to History'' (2003)
* Edward H. Carr, ''What is History?'' (New York: Vintage Books, 1961).
* Wood Gray, ''Historian's handbook, a key to the study and writing of history'' (Houghton Mifflin, 1964).
*Derek Harland, ''A Basic Course in Genealogy: Volume two, Research Procedure and Evaluation of Evidence'', (Bookcraft Inc, 1958)
* Richard Holmes, ''Tommy'' (HarperCollins, 2004)
* Martha C. Howell and Walter Prevenier, ''From Reliable Sources: An Introduction to Historical Methods'' (2001)
* Richard A. Marius and Melvin E. Page, ''A Short Guide to Writing About History'' (5th Edition) (2004)
* Hayden White, ''Metahistory: the historical imagination in nineteenth-century Europe'' (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1973)

==External links==
*[http://www.lib.auburn.edu/bi/typesofsources.htm Identifying Primary, Secondary, and Tertiary Sources]


[[Category:Historiography]]
[[Category:Library science]]
[[Category:Information science]]
[[Category:Secondary sources| ]]

[[ca:Font secundària]]
[[de:Sekundärliteratur]]
[[es:Fuente secundaria]]
[[eo:Sekundara literaturo]]
[[fr:Source secondaire]]
[[id:Sumber sekunder]]
[[hu:Másodlagos forrás]]
[[hr:Sekundarna literatura]]
[[mk:Секундарни извори на информации]]
[[ms:Sumber kedua]]
[[nl:Secundaire literatuur]]
[[pl:Źródło wtórne]]
[[pt:Fonte secundária]]
[[sv:Sekundär källa]]
[[zh:二次文献]]</text>
      <sha1>bvk43ecejczebwemdppicv7fo0rx22i</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
