<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Shang Dynasty</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43465</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521546142</id>
      <parentid>521546124</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T18:41:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/63.230.57.29|63.230.57.29]] to version by Siafu. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1316125) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39148">{{Infobox Former Country
|native_name = &lt;big&gt;商朝&lt;/big&gt;
|conventional_long_name =Shang Dynasty
|common_name = Shang Dynasty
|national_motto =
|continent = Asia
|region    = Pacific
|country   = China
|era       = [[Bronze Age]]
|status    = Kingdom
|government_type = Monarchy
|year_start  = 1600 BC
|year_end    = 1046 BC
|p1 = Xia Dynasty
|s1 = Zhou Dynasty
|event_start =
|event_end   = [[Battle of Muye]]
|event1      =
|date_event1 =
|event2      =
|date_event2 =
|event3      =
|date_event3 =
|event4      =
|event5      =
|date_event5 =
|image_map    = Shang dynasty.svg
|image_map_caption  = Remnants of advanced, stratified societies dating back to the Shang period have been found in the Yellow River Valley.
|capital          = [[Yinxu|Anyang]]
|common_languages = [[Old Chinese]]
|Philosophy =
|religion = [[Chinese folk religion]]
|currency   =
|leader1      =
|leader2      =
|year_leader1 =
|year_leader2 =
|title_leader = [[Emperor of China|King]]
|legislature  =
|stat_year1 = 1122 BC est.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | format = [[PDF]] | last1 = Turchin| first1 = Peter| last2 = Adams| first2 = Jonathan M | last3 = Hall | first3 = Thomas D | title = East-West Orientation of Historical Empires | journal = Journal of world-systems research | date = December 2006 | volume = 12| issue= 2|pages= 219–29|url= http://jwsr.ucr.edu/archive/vol12/number2/pdf/jwsr-v12n2-tah.pdf | accessdate= 12 August 2010 | issn= 1076-156x}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|stat_area1 = 1250000
|stat_pop1  =
|stat_year2 =
|stat_area2 =
|stat_pop2  =
}}
{{Contains Chinese text}}
{{History of China|BC=1}}
{{chinese|c=商朝|p=Shāng Cháo|poj=Siong-tiâu|wuu=saon zau|l=Shang Dynasty|c2=殷代|p2=Yīn Dài|poj2=Tiâu-tāi|wuu2=in de|l2=Yin Dynasty}}
The '''Shang Dynasty'''  (Chinese: [[wiktionary:商|商]][[wiktionary:朝|朝]]; pinyin: shāng cháo) or '''Yin Dynasty''' ([[wiktionary:殷|殷]][[wiktionary:代|代]]; pinyin: yīn dài), according to [[Chinese historiography|traditional historiography]], ruled in the [[Yellow River]] valley in the second millennium BC, succeeding the [[Xia Dynasty]] and followed by the [[Zhou Dynasty]].  The classic account of the Shang comes from texts such as the ''[[Classic of History]]'', ''[[Bamboo Annals]]'' and ''[[Records of the Grand Historian]]''.  According to the traditional chronology based upon calculations by [[Liu Xin]], the Shang ruled between 1766 BC and 1122 BC, but according to the chronology based upon the ''Bamboo Annals'', they ruled between 1556 BC and 1046 BC. The results of the [[Xia–Shang–Zhou Chronology Project]] place them between 1600 BC and 1046 BC.

Archaeological work at the [[Yinxu|Ruins of Yin]] (near modern day [[Anyang]]), which has been identified as the last Shang capital, uncovered eleven major Yin royal tombs and the foundations of palaces and ritual sites, containing weapons of war and remains from both animal and human sacrifices.  Tens of thousands of [[bronze]], [[jade]], [[stone]], [[bone]], and [[ceramic]] artifacts have been obtained.  The workmanship on the bronzes attests to a high level of civilization.

A few bronze artifacts featured inscriptions, but most direct information comes from [[oracle bone]]s – turtle shells, cattle [[scapula]]e, or other bones, which bear [[glyphs]] that form the first significant corpus of recorded [[Chinese character]]s.
More than 20,000 were discovered in the initial scientific excavations during the 1920s and 1930s, and over four times as many have been found since.  The inscriptions on the oracle bones are [[divination]]s, and they provide critical insight into many topics from the politics, economy, and religious practices to the art and medicine of this early stage of Chinese civilization.&lt;ref&gt;Keightley (2000).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Traditional accounts==
Several events concerning the Shang dynasty are mentioned in various [[Chinese classics]], including the ''[[Classic of History]]'' and the ''[[Commentary of Zuo]]''.  Working from all the available documents, the Han dynasty historian [[Sima Qian]] assembled a sequential account of the Shang dynasty as part of his ''[[Records of the Grand Historian]]''.  His history describes some events in detail, while in other cases only the name of a king is given.&lt;ref&gt;Keightley (1999), pp. 233–235.&lt;/ref&gt;  A closely related, but slightly different, account is given by the ''[[Bamboo Annals]]''.  The ''Annals'' were interred in 296 BC, but the received versions have a complex history and there are controversies regarding the various versions.&lt;ref&gt;Keightley (1978b)&lt;/ref&gt;

Sima Qian calls both the dynasty and its final capital by the name ''Yīn'' (殷), a popular term that has been synonymous with the Shang throughout history, and is often used specifically to describe the later half of the Shang dynasty. In Japan and Korea, the Shang are still referred to almost exclusively as the Yin (''In'') dynasty. However the word does not appear in the oracle bones, and seems to have been the [[Zhou Dynasty|Zhou]] name for the earlier dynasty.&lt;ref&gt;Keightley (1999), p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rise===
Sima Qian's &quot;Annals of the Yin&quot; begins by describing the predynastic founder of the Shang lineage, Xie (偰) — also appearing as Qi (契) — as having been miraculously conceived when [[Jiandi]], a wife of [[Emperor Ku]], swallowed an egg dropped by a black bird.  Xie is said to have helped [[Yu the Great]] to control the [[Great Flood (China)|Great Flood]] and for his service to have been granted a place called Shang as a fief.&lt;ref&gt;Keightley (1999), p. 233, with additional details from the ''Historical Records''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sima Qian relates that the dynasty itself was founded 13 generations later, when Xie's descendent [[Tang of Shang|Tang]] overthrew the impious and cruel final [[Xia Dynasty|Xia]] ruler in the [[Battle of Mingtiao]].  The ''Records'' recount events from the reigns of Tang, [[Tai Jia]], [[Tai Wu|Dai Mou]], [[Pan Geng]], [[Wu Ding]], [[Wu Yi (ruler)|Wu Yi]] and the depraved final king [[Di Xin]], but the rest of the Shang rulers are merely mentioned by name.  According to the ''Records'', the Shang moved their capital five times, with the final move to Yin in the reign of Pan Geng inaugurating the golden age of the dynasty.&lt;ref&gt;Keightley (1999), p. 233.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fall===
Di Xin, the last Shang king, is said to have committed suicide after his army was defeated by [[King Wu of Zhou|Wu of Zhou]]. Legends say that his army and his equipped slaves betrayed him by joining the Zhou rebels in the decisive [[Battle of Muye]]. According to the [[Yizhoushu]] and [[Mencius]] the battle was very bloody. The classic, [[Ming Dynasty|Ming]]-era novel ''[[Fengshen Yanyi]]'' retells the story of the war between Shang and Zhou as a conflict where rival factions of gods supported different sides in the war.

After the Shang were defeated, King Wu allowed Di Xin's son [[Wu Geng]] to rule the Shang as a [[vassal]] kingdom.  However, Zhou Wu sent three of his brothers and an army to ensure that Wu Geng would not rebel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pkucn.com/redirect.php?tid=228246 邶、鄘二國考]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ch.shvoong.com/humanities/1230377-%E5%91%A8%E5%88%9D-%E4%B8%89%E7%9B%91-%E4%B8%8E%E9%82%B6-%E9%84%98-%E5%8D%AB%E5%9C%B0%E6%9C%9B%E7%A0%94%E7%A9%B6/ 周初“三监”与邶、鄘、卫地望研究 ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csscipaper.com/chinahistory/xianqin/110612.html “三监”人物疆地及其地望辨析 ——兼论康叔的始封地问题]&lt;/ref&gt; After Zhou Wu's death, the Shang joined the [[Three Guards|Three Governors' Rebellion]] against the [[Duke of Zhou]], but the rebellion collapsed after three years, leaving Zhou in control of Shang territory.

After Shang's collapse, Zhou's rulers forcibly relocated &quot;Yin diehards&quot; (殷頑) and scattered them throughout Zhou territory.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guoxue.com/jrxz/lztdzdxl/yuan231.htm 一 被剥削者的存在类型]&lt;/ref&gt; Some surviving members of the Shang royal family collectively changed their surname from the ancestral name Zi (子) to the name of their fallen dynasty, Yin. The family retained an aristocratic standing and often provided needed administrative services to the succeeding Zhou Dynasty. The ''[[Shiji]]'' states that [[King Cheng of Zhou]], with the support of his regent and uncle, the Duke of Zhou, [[enfeoffment|enfeoff]]ed Weiziqi (微子啟), a brother of Di Xin, as the ruler of [[Wey (state)|Wei]].{{Clarify|reason=is Wei in this period a province, kingdom? Any links?|date=September 2010}} [[Shangqiu|Shang]], the eponymous first capital of the former Shang dynasty, would become the capital of Weiziqi's state. In time, this territory would become the [[state of Song]], and the descendants of Shang royalty reigning there as Dukes would maintain rites honoring the dead Shang kings until they were conquered by Qin in 286 BC. [[Confucius]] was said to have been a descendant of the Shang kings or priests through the Dukes of Song.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |title=An Introduction to Confucianism|author=Xinzhong Yao
 |publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2000|page=23|isbn=0521644305
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |title=Confucianism and Christianity: A Comparative Study of Jen and Agape
 |author=Xinzhong Yao|publisher=Sussex Academic Press|year=1997
 |page=29|isbn=1898723761
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |title=Confucius &amp; Confucianism: The Essentials|author=Lee Dian Rainey
 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|year=2010|page=66|isbn=1405188413
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Guzhu ([[:zh:孤竹国|孤竹國]]){{Clarify|reason=is Guzhu a city, a province, something else?|date=September 2010}}, located in what is now [[Tangshan]], was formed by another remnant of the Shang, and was destroyed by [[Duke Huan of Qi]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://guzhuwenhua.com/index.asp 中国孤竹文化网]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guoxue.com/xsjy/2000.7/guzhuguo.htm 解开神秘古国 ——孤竹之谜]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lulong.ccoo.cn/bendi/culture-2.html 孤竹析辨]&lt;/ref&gt; Many Shang clans that migrated northeast after the dynasty's collapse were integrated into [[Yan (state)|Yan]] culture during the [[Western Zhou]] period.  These clans maintained an elite status and continued practicing the sacrificial and burial traditions of the Shang.&lt;ref name=SunYan&gt;Sun (2006).&lt;/ref&gt;

Both Korean and Chinese legends state that a disgruntled Shang prince named [[Jizi]], who had refused to cede power to the Zhou, left China with a small army.  According to these legends, he founded a state known as [[Gija Joseon]] in Northwest Korea during the [[Gojoseon]] period of ancient Korean history. However, the historical accuracy of these legends is widely debated by scholars.

==Early Bronze Age archaeology==
{{Main|Shang archaeology}}
Before the 20th century, the [[Zhou Dynasty]] (1046–256 BC) was the earliest Chinese dynasty that could be verified from its own records.  However during the [[Song Dynasty]] (960–1279 AD), [[antiquarian]]s collected [[bronze]] ritual vessels attributed to the Shang era, some of which bore inscriptions.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 33&quot;&gt;Fairbank 33.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Yellow River valley ===
[[Image:Yinxu.jpg|thumb|right|The site of [[Yin (city)|Yin]], the capital (1350–1046 BC) of the Shang Dynasty, also called Yin Dynasty]]
In 1899, it was found that Chinese pharmacists were selling &quot;[[Oracle bone|dragon bones]]&quot; marked with curious and archaic characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 33&quot;/&gt; These were finally traced back in 1928 to a site (now called [[Yinxu]]) near [[Anyang]], north of the [[Yellow River]] in modern [[Henan]] province, where the [[Academia Sinica]] undertook archeological excavation until the [[Second Sino-Japanese War|Japanese invasion]] in 1937.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 33&quot;/&gt;

Archaeologists focused on the Yellow River valley in Henan as the most likely site of the states described in the traditional histories.
After 1950, remnants of an earlier walled city were discovered near [[Zhengzhou]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 33&quot;/&gt;
It has been determined that the earth walls at Zhengzhou, erected in the 15th century BC, would have been {{convert|20|m|ft}} wide at the base, rising to a height of {{convert|8|m|ft}}, and formed a roughly rectangular wall {{convert|7|km|mi|sigfig=1}} around the ancient city.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 34&quot;&gt;Fairbank, 34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 43&quot;&gt;Needham, Volume 4, Part 2, 43.&lt;/ref&gt;
The rammed earth construction of these walls was an inherited tradition, since much older fortifications of this type have been found at Chinese [[Neolithic]] sites of the [[Longshan culture]] (c. 3000–2000 BC).&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 34&quot;/&gt;

In 1959, the site of the [[Erlitou culture]] was found in [[Yanshi]], south of the Yellow River near [[Luoyang]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 34&quot;/&gt; [[Radiocarbon dating]] suggests that the Erlitou culture flourished ca. 2100 BC to 1800 BC. They built large palaces, suggesting the existence of an organized state.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 34 35&quot;&gt;Fairbank, 34–35.&lt;/ref&gt;

Chinese historians living in later periods were accustomed to the notion of one dynasty succeeding another, and readily identified the Zhengzhou and Erlitou sites with the early Shang and [[Xia Dynasty]] of traditional histories.
The actual political situation in early China may have been more complicated, with the Xia and Shang being political entities that existed concurrently, just as the early [[Zhou dynasty|Zhou]], who established the successor state of the Shang, are known to have existed at the same time as the Shang.&lt;ref name=SunYan /&gt;

=== Other sites ===
{{location map+|China Northern Plain relief
 | caption=Major archaeological sites in north and central China from the second millenium BC
 | width=250|float=right|places=
  {{location map~|China Northern Plain relief
   | label=[[Erlitou culture|Erlitou]]|lat_deg=34.7|lon_deg=112.7
   | mark=Purple pog.svg|position=left}}
  {{location map~|China Northern Plain relief
   | label=[[Erligang culture|Zhengzhou]]|lat_deg=34.75|lon_deg=113.68
   | mark=Red pog.svg|position=right}}
  {{location map~|China Northern Plain relief
   | label=[[Panlongcheng]]|lat_deg=30.69|lon_deg=114.27
   | mark=Red pog.svg|position=right}}
  {{location map~|China Northern Plain relief
   | label=[[Yinxu|Anyang]]|lat_deg=36.12|lon_deg=114.32
   | mark=Orange pog.svg|position=right}}
  {{location map~|China Northern Plain relief
   | label=[[Sanxingdui]]|lat_deg=31.0|lon_deg=104.2
   | mark=Orange pog.svg|position=right}}
  {{location map~|China Northern Plain relief
   | label=[[Wucheng culture|Wucheng]]|lat_deg=29.18|lon_deg=116.01
   | mark=Orange pog.svg|position=bottom}}
}}
The [[Erligang culture]] represented by the Zhengzhou site is found across a wide area of China, even as far northeast as the area of modern [[Beijing]], where at least one burial in this region during this period contained both Erligang-style [[bronzes]] and local-style [[gold]] jewelry.&lt;ref name=SunYan /&gt;  The discovery of a [[Chenggu]]-style ''ge'' [[dagger-axe]] at Xiaohenan demonstrates that even at this early stage of Chinese history, there were some ties between the distant areas of north China.&lt;ref name=SunYan /&gt;
The [[Panlongcheng]] site in the middle Yangtze valley was an important regional center of the Erligang culture.&lt;ref&gt;Bagley (1999), pp. 168–171.&lt;/ref&gt;

Accidental finds elsewhere in China have revealed advanced civilizations contemporaneous with but culturally unlike the settlement at Anyang, such as the walled city of [[Sanxingdui]] in Sichuan.
Western scholars are hesitant to designate such settlements as belonging to the Shang dynasty.&lt;ref&gt;Bagley (1999), pp. 124–125.&lt;/ref&gt;
Also unlike the Shang, there is no known evidence that the Sanxingdui culture had a system of writing.  The Shang state at Anyang is thus generally considered the first verifiable civilization in Chinese history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lin, 2007&quot;&gt;Lin, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
In contrast, the earliest layers of the [[Wucheng culture|Wucheng site]], pre-dating Anyang, have yielded pottery fragments containing short sequences of symbols, suggesting that they may be a form of writing quite different in form from [[oracle bone script|oracle bone characters]], but the sample is too small for decipherment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Chinese history: a manual | first=Endymion | last=Wilkinson | publisher=Harvard Univ Asia Center | edition=2nd | year=2000 | isbn=978-0-674-00249-4 | page=382 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=Iron and Steel in Ancient China | first=Donald B. | last=Wagner | publisher=BRILL | year=1993 | isbn=978-90-04-09632-5 | page=20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=The Origins of Chinese Civilization | editor1-first=David N. | editor1-last=Keightley | editor2-first=Noel | editor2-last=Barnard | publisher=University of California Press | year=1983 | isbn=978-0-520-04229-2 | chapter=Recent archaeological evidence relating to the origin of Chinese characters | last=Cheung | first=Kwong-yue | others=trans. Noel Barnard | pages=323–391 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Late Shang at Anyang==
[[Image:Oracle bones pit.JPG|thumb|right|Oracle bones pit at Yin]]
The oldest extant direct records date from around 1200 BC at Anyang, covering the reigns of the last nine Shang kings.
The Shang had a fully developed system of writing, preserved on [[Chinese bronze inscriptions|bronze inscriptions]] and a small number of other writings on pottery, jade and other stones, horn, etc., but most prolifically on [[oracle bones]].&lt;ref&gt;Qiu 2000, p.60&lt;/ref&gt; The complexity and sophistication of this writing system indicates an earlier period of development, but direct evidence of that development is still lacking.
Other advances included the invention of many musical instruments and observations of [[Mars]] and various [[comet]]s by Shang astronomers.{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}

Their civilization was based on [[agriculture]] and augmented by [[hunting]] and [[animal husbandry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PoI&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Beck | first = Roger B. | authorlink = | coauthors = Linda Black, Larry S. Krieger, Phillip C. Naylor, Dahia Ibo Shabaka, | title = World History: Patterns of Interaction | publisher = McDougal Littell | year = 1999 | location = Evanston, IL | pages = | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = 0-395-87274-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;
In addition to war, the Shang also practiced [[human sacrifice]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NGC&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.slashcontrol.com/free-tv-shows/ngc-presents/4006945677-shang-dynasty-human-sacrifice| title=Shang Dynasty Human Sacrifice|last=Flad|first=Dr. Rowan |date=28 Feb. 2010| work= NGC Presents| publisher=National Geographic| accessdate=3 Mar. 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Cowry|Cowry shells]] were also excavated at [[Anyang]], suggesting trade with coast-dwellers, but there was very limited sea trade in ancient China since China was isolated from other large civilizations during the Shang period.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 35&quot;&gt;Fairbank, 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Trade relations and diplomatic ties with other formidable powers via the [[Silk Road]] and Chinese voyages to the Indian Ocean did not exist until the reign of [[Emperor Wu of Han|Emperor Wu]] during the [[Han Dynasty]] (206 BC–221 AD).&lt;ref name=&quot;sun 161 167&quot;&gt;Sun 1989, 161-167.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;chen 67 71&quot;&gt;Chen 2002, 67-71.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Court life===
[[File:Tomb Fu Hao YinXu.jpg|thumb|right|Bronzewares from the excavated [[tomb of Fu Hao]]]]
At the excavated royal palace of [[Yinxu]], large stone pillar bases were found along with [[rammed earth]] foundations and platforms, which according to Fairbank, were &quot;as hard as cement.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 33&quot;/&gt;  These foundations in turn originally supported 53 buildings of wooden [[timber framing|post-and-beam]] construction.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 33&quot;/&gt; In close proximity to the main palatial complex, there were underground pits used for storage, servants' quarters, and housing quarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank 33&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Gu wine vessel from the Shang Dynasty.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Bronze ''gū'' ritual wine vessel]]
Many Shang royal tombs had been tunneled into and ravaged by [[Grave robbing|grave robbers]] in ancient times,&lt;ref name=&quot;thorp 239&quot;&gt;Thorp, 239.&lt;/ref&gt; but in the spring of 1976, the [[Tomb of Fu Hao|discovery of Tomb 5]] at Yinxu revealed a tomb that was not only undisturbed, but one of the most richly furnished Shang tombs that archaeologists had yet come across.&lt;ref name=&quot;thorp 240&quot;&gt;Thorp, 240.&lt;/ref&gt; With over 200 bronze ritual vessels and 109 inscriptions of [[Fu Hao|Lady Fu Hao]]'s name, archaeologists realized they had stumbled across the tomb of the militant consort to [[Wu Ding|King Wu Ding]], as described in 170 to 180 Shang oracle bones.&lt;ref name=&quot;thorp 240 245&quot;&gt;Thorp, 240 &amp; 245.&lt;/ref&gt; Along with bronze vessels, [[stoneware]] and pottery vessels, bronze weapons, [[Chinese jade|jade]] figures and hair combs, and bone hairpins were found.&lt;ref name=&quot;thorp 242&quot;&gt;Thorp, 242 &amp; 245.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;li 1980&quot;&gt;Li (1980), 393–394.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Valenstein &amp; Hearn, 77.&lt;/ref&gt; Historian Robert L. Thorp states that the large assortment of weapons and ritual vessels in her tomb correlate with the [[Oracle bone script|oracle bone accounts]] of her military career and involvement in Wu Ding's [[ancestor worship|ritual ancestral sacrifices]].&lt;ref name=&quot;thorp 245&quot;&gt;Thorp, 245.&lt;/ref&gt;

The capital was the center of a glittering court life. Over time, court rituals to appease spirits developed, and in addition to his secular duties, the king would serve as the head of the [[ancestor worship]] cult. Often, the king would even perform oracle bone divinations himself, especially near the end of the dynasty. Evidence from excavations of the royal tombs indicates that royalty were buried with articles of value, presumably for use in the afterlife. Perhaps for the same reason, hundreds of commoners, who may have been [[Slavery|slave]]s, were buried alive with the royal corpse.

A line of hereditary Shang kings ruled over much of northern China, and Shang troops fought frequent wars with neighboring settlements and nomadic herdsmen from the inner Asian [[steppe]]s. The Shang king, in his oracular divinations, repeatedly shows concern about the ''fang'' groups, the barbarians living outside of the civilized ''tu'' regions, which made up the center of Shang territory{{Clarify|reason=are tu areas all of Shang or only the Shang heartland?|date=September 2010}}.  In particular, the ''tufang'' group of the [[Yan Mountains|Yanshan]] region were regularly mentioned as hostile to the Shang.&lt;ref name=SunYan /&gt;

Apart from their role as the head military commanders, Shang kings also asserted their social supremacy by acting as the high priests of society and leading the divination ceremonies.&lt;ref name=&quot;pie ebrey 14&quot;&gt;Ebrey, 14.&lt;/ref&gt; As the oracle bone texts reveal, the Shang kings were viewed as the best qualified members of society to offer sacrifices to their royal ancestors and to the high god Di, who in their beliefs was responsible for the rain, wind, and thunder.&lt;ref name=&quot;pie ebrey 14&quot;/&gt;

==Kings==
{{anchor|kings|king list|emperors}}
Shang kings are conventionally referred to by [[posthumous name]]s, of which the last character is one of the [[heavenly stem]]s.

The earliest records are the [[oracle bone]]s inscribed during the reigns of the Shang kings from [[Wu Ding]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | title = Chinese history: a manual | first = Endymion | last = Wilkinson| publisher = Harvard Univ Asia Center | edition = 2nd | year = 2000 | isbn = 978-0-674-00249-4 | page = 397 | postscript = . }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The oracle bones do not contain king lists, but they do record the sacrifices to previous kings and the ancestors of the current king, which follow a standard schedule. From this evidence, scholars have assembled the implied king list and genealogy, finding that it is in substantial agreement with the later accounts, especially for later kings in the dynasty.

The kings, in the order of succession derived from the oracle bones, are here grouped by generation:&lt;ref&gt;Keightley (1985) 185–187.&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em auto 1em auto;&quot;
! Generation
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Older brothers of patriarch
! Line of descent
! Younger brothers
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 17 || || || || 大乙 [[King Tang of Shang of China|Dà Yǐ]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 16 || || || || 大丁 [[Da Ding of Shang|Dà Dīng]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|According to the ''Historical Records'' and the ''[[Mencius (book)|Mencius]]'', Da Ding (also known as Tai Ding) died before he could ascend to the throne.  However in the oracle bones he receives rituals like any other king.}} ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 15 || || || || 大甲 [[Tai Jia|Dà Jiǎ]] || 卜丙 [[King Bu Bing of Shang of China|Bǔ Bǐng]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|According to the ''Historical Records'', Bu Bing (also known as Wai Bing) and 仲壬 [[Zhong Ren]] (not mentioned in the oracle bones) were younger brothers of Dai Ting and preceded Da Jia (also known as Dai Jia).  However the ''Mencius'', the ''[[Commentary of Zuo]]'' and the ''Book of History'' state that he reigned after Da Jia, as also implied by the oracle bones.}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 14 || || || align=&quot;center&quot; | {{refn|group=lower-alpha|The ''Historical Records'' include a king [[Wo Ding]] not mentioned in the oracle bones.}} || 大庚 [[Tai Geng|Dà Gēng]] || 小甲 [[Xiao Jia|Xiǎo Jiǎ]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|The ''Historical Records'' have Xiao Jia as the son of Da Geng (known as Tai Geng) in the &quot;Annals of Yin&quot;, but as a younger brother (as implied by the oracle bones) in the &quot;Genealogical Table of the Three Ages&quot;.}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 13 || || || || 大戊 [[Tai Wu|Dà Wù]] || 呂己 [[Yong Ji|Lǚ Jǐ]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|According to the ''Historical Records'', Lü Ji (there called Yong Ji) reigned before Da Wu (there called Tai Wu).}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 12 || || || || 中丁 [[Zhong Ding|Zhōng Dīng]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|The kings from Zhong Ding to Nan Geng are placed in the same order by the ''Historical Records'' and the oracle bones, but there are some differences in genealogy, as described in the articles on individual kings.}} || 卜壬 [[Wai Ren|Bǔ Rén]]
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 11 || || || 戔甲 [[He Dan Jia|Jiān Jiǎ]] || 祖乙 [[Zu Yi|Zǔ Yǐ]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 10 || || || || 祖辛 [[Zu Xin|Zǔ Xīn]] || 羌甲 [[Wo Jia|Qiāng Jiǎ]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|The status of Qiang Jia varies over the history of the oracle bones.  During the reigns of Wu Ding, Di Yi and Di Xin, he was not included in the main line of descent, a position also held by the ''Historical Records'', but in the intervening reigns he was included as a direct ancestor.}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 9 || || || || 祖丁 [[Zu Ding|Zǔ Dīng]] || 南庚 [[Nan Geng|Nán Gēng]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|According to the ''Historical Records'', Nan Geng was the son of Qiang Jia (there called Wo Jia).}}
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 8 || 象甲 [[King Yang Jia|Xiàng Jiǎ]] || 盤庚 [[Pan Geng|Pán Gēng]] || 小辛 [[Xiao Xin of Shang|Xiǎo Xīn]] || 小乙 [[Xiao Yi of Shang|Xiǎo Yǐ]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 7 || || || || 武丁 [[Wu Ding|Wǔ Dīng]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 6 || || align=&quot;center&quot; | {{refn|group=lower-alpha|The oracle bones and the ''Historical Records'' include an older brother 祖己 [[Zu Ji|Zǔ Jǐ]] who did not reign.}} || 祖庚 [[Zu Geng of Shang|Zǔ Gēng]] || 祖甲 [[Zu Jia|Zǔ Jiǎ]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 5 || || || 廩辛 [[Lin Xin|Lǐn Xīn]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|Lin Xin is named as a king in the ''Historical Records'' and oracle bones of succeeding reigns, but not those of the last two kings.}} || 康丁 [[Geng Ding|Kāng Dīng]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 4 || || || || 武乙 [[Wu Yi (ruler)|Wǔ Yǐ]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 3 || || || || 文武丁 [[Wen Ding|Wén Wǔ Dīng]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 2 || || || || 帝乙 [[Di Yi|Dì Yǐ]] ||
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 1 || || || || 帝辛 [[Di Xin|Dì Xīn]]{{refn|group=lower-alpha|also referred to as Zhòu (紂), Zhòu Xīn (紂辛) or Zhòu Wáng (紂王) or by adding &quot;Shāng&quot; (商) in front of any of these names.}} ||
|}
;Notes
{{reflist|group=lower-alpha}}

===Bronze working===
[[Image:HouMuWuDingFullView.jpg|thumb|right|Houmuwu Ding made in the Shang Dynasty is the heaviest piece of bronze work found in China so far]]
{{main|Chinese ritual bronzes}}
[[Image:Liu Ding.jpg|thumb|right|A late Shang dynasty bronze ding vessel with [[taotie]] motif]]
Chinese bronze casting and pottery advanced during the Shang dynasty, with bronze commonly being used for art rather than weapons.{{Inconsistent}}
As far back as c. 1500 BC, the early Shang Dynasty engaged in large-scale production of [[bronze]]-ware vessels and weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey 17&quot;&gt;Ebrey, 17.&lt;/ref&gt; This production required a large labor force that could handle the mining, refining, and transportation of the necessary [[copper]], [[tin]], and [[lead]] ores. This in turn created a need for official managers that could oversee both hard-laborers and skilled artisans and craftsmen.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey 17&quot;/&gt; The Shang royal court and aristocrats required a vast amount of different bronze vessels for various ceremonial purposes and events of religious [[divination]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey 17&quot;/&gt;  Ceremonial rules even decreed how many bronze containers of each type a nobleman or noblewoman of a certain rank could own. With the increased amount of bronze available, the army could also better equip itself with an assortment of bronze weaponry. Bronze was also used for the fittings of [[spoke]]-wheeled [[Chariot (Ancient China)|chariot]]s, which appeared in China around 1200 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;pie ebrey 14&quot; /&gt;

===Military===
[[Image:CMOC Treasures of Ancient China exhibit - bronze battle axe.jpg|thumb|right|A bronze [[axe]] of the Shang dynasty]]
Bronze weapons were an integral part of Shang society.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Sawyer|first=Ralph|title=The Art of War|year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Shang infantry were armed with a variety of stone and bronze weaponry, including ''máo'' spears, ''yuè'' pole-axes, ''gē'' pole-based [[dagger-axe]]s, composite bows, and bronze or leather helmets.&lt;ref&gt;Wang Hongyuan (1993).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sawyer 35&quot;&gt;Sawyer, 35.&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[chariot]] first appeared in China during the reign of Wu Ding.  Oracle bone inscriptions suggest that the western enemies of the Shang used limited numbers of chariots in battle, but the Shang themselves used them only as mobile command vehicles and in royal hunts.  A crucial factor in the Zhou conquest of the Shang may have been their more effective use of chariots.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Shaughnessy |first=Edward L. |title=Historical Perspectives on The Introduction of The Chariot Into China |journal=Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies |volume=48 |issue=1 |year=1988 |pages=189–237 |jstor=2719276}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the Shang depended upon the military skills of their nobility, Shang rulers could mobilize the masses of town-dwelling and rural commoners as conscript laborers and soldiers for both campaigns of defense and conquest.&lt;ref name=&quot;sawyer 33&quot;&gt;Sawyer, 33.&lt;/ref&gt; Aristocrats and other state rulers were obligated to furnish their local garrisons with all necessary equipment, armor, and armaments. The Shang king maintained a force of about a thousand troops at his capital and would personally lead this force into battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;sawyer 34&quot;&gt;Sawyer, 34.&lt;/ref&gt; A rudimentary military bureaucracy was also needed in order to muster forces ranging from three to five thousand troops for border campaigns to thirteen thousand troops for suppressing rebellions against Shang authority.

===Gallery===
&lt;gallery caption=&quot;Late Shang artifacts&quot;&gt;
File:Ring with coiled dragon design.jpg|[[Jade]] ring in the shape of a [[Chinese dragon|dragon]]
File:Jade deer.jpg|Jade carved deer
File:Jade fish.jpg|Jade carved fish
File:Jade tiger.jpg|Jade carved tiger
File:Gefuding Gui.jpg|[[Bronze]] gefuding guǐ vessel
File:Yuefu You.jpg|Bronze yuefu you vessel
File:Pou with four ram head.jpg|Bronze ''pou'' vessel with four ram heads
File:Zun with animal mask.jpg|Bronze ''[[zūn]]'' ritual vessel
File:Gong Fu Yi Gong.jpg|Bronze ''[[guang (vessel)|guang]]'' ritual ewer
File:Shang-Bronze1.jpg|Bronze pot with lid and handle
File:Ritual wine container in shape of owl, Shang Dynasty.jpg|A late Shang, ritual bronze wine vessel ([[zun]]) in the unusual shape of an owl with a domed head for its lid
File:Hache Yue Musée Guimet 1107.jpg|Bronze ''yuè'' axe
File:Shang-ZhouFace14-10thcenturyBCE.jpg|Shang/Zhou sculpture, 14–10th century BC
File:China shang white pottery pot.JPG|White pottery with a carved geometric pattern
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[Chinese sovereign]]
*[[Chinese mythology]]
*[[Historical capitals of China]]

==References==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

;Bibliography
* {{cite book | first = Robert | last = [[Robert Bagley|Bagley]] | chapter = Shang archaeology | editor1-first = Michael | editor1-last = Loewe | editor2-first = Edward L. | editor2-last = Shaughnessy | title = [[The Cambridge History of Ancient China]] | location = Cambridge | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 1999 | pages = 124–231 | isbn = 978-0-521-47030-8 }}
*Chang, Kwang-Chih (1980). ''Shang Civilization''. Yale University Press. ISBN 0-300-02885-7, ppbk.
*Chang-Qun, Duan, Xue-Chun, Gan, Wang, Jeanny and Chien, Paul K.  (1998). ''Relocation of Civilization Centers in Ancient China: Environmental Factors''. Allen Press on behalf of the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences.
*Chen, Yan (2002). ''Maritime Silk Route and Chinese-Foreign Cultural Exchanges''. Beijing: Peking University Press. ISBN 7-301-03029-0.
*Ebrey, Patricia Buckley, Anne Walthall, James B. Palais (2006). ''East Asia: A Cultural, Social, and Political History''. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company. ISBN 0-618-13384-4.
*Fairbank, John King and Merle Goldman (1992). ''China: A New History; Second Enlarged Edition'' (2006). Cambridge: MA; London: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press. ISBN 0-674-01828-1
*Keightley, David N. (1978). ''Sources of Shang History: The Oracle-Bone Inscriptions of Bronze Age China.'' University of California Press, Berkeley. Large format hardcover, ISBN 0-520-02969-0 (out of print); A 1985 paperback 2nd edition is still in print, ISBN 0-520-05455-5.
* {{cite journal | first = David N. | last = Keightley | title = The Bamboo Annals and Shang-Chou Chronology | journal = Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies | volume = 38 | issue = 2 | year = 1978b | pages = 423–438 | jstor = 2718906 }}
* {{cite book | first = David N. | last = Keightley | chapter = The Shang: China's first historical dynasty | editor1-first = Michael | editor1-last = Loewe | editor2-first = Edward L. | editor2-last = Shaughnessy | title = The Cambridge History of Ancient China | location = Cambridge | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 1999 | pages = 232–291 | isbn = 978-0-521-47030-8 }}
*Keightley, David N. (2000). ''The Ancestral Landscape: Time, Space, and Community in Late Shang China (ca. 1200–1045 B.C.)''. China Research Monograph 53, Institute of East Asian Studies, University of California – Berkeley. ISBN 1-55729-070-9, ppbk.
*Lee, Yuan-Yuan and Shen, Sin-yan. (1999). ''Chinese Musical Instruments (Chinese Music Monograph Series)''. Chinese Music Society of North America Press. ISBN 1-880464-03-9
*Li, Chu-tsing. &quot;The Great Bronze Age of China,&quot; ''Art Journal'' (Volume 40, Number 1/2, 1980): 390–395.
*{{Cite journal
  | first = Ershen
  | last =  Lin
  | author =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = A Critical Review on the Rise of Civilization, the Formation of the State, and Early Slavery
  | version = draft
  | publisher = The Science &amp; Philosophy Forums (2005–2008)
  | date = 19 July 2007
  | url = http://www.sciencechatforum.com/bulletin/viewtopic.php?t=7172&amp;sid=f837c13276b97867e490fffc89749352
  | format =
  | accessdate = 3 Mar. 2009}}
*Needham, Joseph (1986). ''Science and Civilization in China: Volume 4, Part 3''. Taipei: Caves Books, Ltd.
*Sawyer, Ralph D. and Mei-chün Lee Sawyer (1994). ''Sun Tzu's The Art of War''. New York: Barnes and Noble Inc. ISBN 1-56619-297-8
*{{cite journal | last1 = Shen | first1 = Sinyan | year = 1987 | title = Acoustics of Ancient Chinese Bells | url = | journal = Scientific American | volume = 256 | issue = | page = 94 }}
*Sun, Guangqi (1989). ''History of Navigation in Ancient China''. Beijing: Ocean Press. ISBN 7-5027-0532-5.
*{{cite journal|last=Sun|first=Yan|title=Colonizing China's Northern Frontier: Yan and Her Neighbors During the Early Western Zhou Period|year=2006|journal=International Journal of Historical Archaeology|volume=10|issue=2|pages=159–177|doi=10.1007/s10761-006-0005-3}}
*Thorp, Robert L. &quot;The Date of Tomb 5 at Yinxu, Anyang: A Review Article,&quot; ''Artibus Asiae'' (Volume 43, Number 3, 1981): 239–246.
*Valenstein, Suzanne G. and Maxwell Hearn. &quot;Asian Art, by Martin Lerner; Alfreda Murck; Barbara B. Ford,&quot; ''Recent Acquisitions (Metropolitan Museum of Art)'' (Number 1985/1986, 1985): 72–88.
*Wang, Hongyuan 王宏源 (1993). ''The Origins of Chinese Characters'' 漢字字源入門. Sinolingua, Beijing, ISBN 7-80052-243-1, ppbk.

==Further reading==
* Timperley, Harold J. ''The Awakening of China in Archaeology; Further Discoveries in Ho-Nan Province, Royal Tombs of the Shang Dynasty, Dated Traditionally from 1766 to 1122 B.C.. 1936''.

==External links==
{{Commons|Shang Dynasty}}
*[http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/ANCCHINA/SHANG.HTM Shang Dynasty at Washington State University]
*[http://www1.chinaculture.org/library/2008-02/15/content_36909.htm Zhengzhou Shang City Site]

{{S-start}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Dynasties in Chinese history]]|before=[[Xia Dynasty]]|after=[[Zhou Dynasty]]|years=ca. 1600–ca. 1047 BC}}
{{S-end}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

[[Category:1046 BC disestablishments in China]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1600 BC]]
[[Category:Shang Dynasty|*]]
[[Category:Former countries in Chinese history]]

{{Link GA|fr}}
{{Link GA|no}}

[[ar:مملكة شانغ]]
[[az:Şan sülaləsi]]
[[zh-min-nan:Siong]]
[[bg:Шан]]
[[bs:Dinastija Shang]]
[[br:Tierniezh Shang]]
[[ca:Dinastia Shang]]
[[ceb:Dinastiyang Shang]]
[[cs:Šang]]
[[cy:Brenhinllin Shang]]
[[da:Shang-dynastiet]]
[[de:Shang-Dynastie]]
[[et:Shangi dünastia]]
[[es:Dinastía Shang]]
[[eo:Dinastio Shang]]
[[eu:Shang dinastia]]
[[fa:دودمان شانگ]]
[[fr:Dynastie Shang]]
[[fy:Sjang]]
[[gl:Dinastía Shang]]
[[gan:商]]
[[hak:Sông-chhèu]]
[[ko:상나라]]
[[hi:शांग राजवंश]]
[[id:Dinasti Shang]]
[[it:Dinastia Shang]]
[[he:שושלת שאנג]]
[[jv:Wangsa Shang]]
[[sw:Nasaba ya Shang]]
[[lt:Šangų dinastija]]
[[ms:Dinasti Shang]]
[[nl:Shang-dynastie]]
[[ja:殷]]
[[no:Shang-dynastiet]]
[[nn:Shang]]
[[pl:Dynastia Shang]]
[[pt:Dinastia Shang]]
[[ro:Dinastia Shang]]
[[ru:Шан (династия)]]
[[sq:Dinastia Shang]]
[[simple:Shang Dynasty]]
[[sk:Šang (dynastia)]]
[[sh:Dinastija Shang]]
[[fi:Shang-dynastia]]
[[sv:Shangdynastin]]
[[tl:Dinastiyang Shang]]
[[ta:சாங் அரசமரபு]]
[[th:ราชวงศ์ซาง]]
[[tr:Shang Hanedanı]]
[[uk:Династія Шан]]
[[ug:شاڭ سۇلالىسى]]
[[vi:Nhà Thương]]
[[zh-yue:商 (國)]]
[[zh:商朝]]</text>
      <sha1>pq3o24oaf4m1avaisblvwrwkllg0bkh</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
