<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Singing Revolution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>274394</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522383297</id>
      <parentid>520646257</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T21:06:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nimetapoeg</username>
        <id>17692954</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>revise category, more specific</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17858">{{refimprove|date=August 2011}}
{{about|the revolution in the [[Baltic States]] in the late 1980s|the 2006 film about the revolution in [[Estonia]]|The Singing Revolution}}

[[Image:Baltic Way.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Baltic Way]], reflecting the peak of the Singing Revolution]]
The '''Singing Revolution''' is a commonly used name for events between 1987 and 1991 that led to the restoration of the independence of [[Estonia]], [[Latvia]] and [[Lithuania]].&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite book | last=Thomson | first=Clare | title=The Singing Revolution: A Political Journey through the Baltic States | location=London  | publisher=Joseph | year=1992 | isbn=0-7181-3459-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last=Ginkel | first=John | year=2002  | month=September | title=Identity Construction in Latvia's &quot;Singing Revolution&quot;: Why inter-ethnic conflict failed to occur | journal=Nationalities Papers | volume=30| issue=3| pages=403–433 | doi=10.1080/0090599022000011697}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term was coined by an Estonian activist and artist, [[Heinz Valk]], in an article published a week after the June 10–11, 1988, spontaneous mass night-singing demonstrations at the [[Tallinn Song Festival Grounds]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=nI73PdnqQlcC&amp;pg Between Utopia and Disillusionment By Henri Vogt; p 26] ISBN 1-57181-895-2&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
{{Main|Baltic states under Soviet rule}}
{{Eastern Bloc sidebar}}
After [[World War II]], the [[Baltic States]] had been fully incorporated into the [[USSR]] after [[military occupation]] and [[annexation]] first [[Occupation and annexation of the Baltic states by the Soviet Union (1940)|in 1940]] and then [[Occupation and annexation of the Baltic states by the Soviet Union (1944)|again in 1944]]. [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] introduced &quot;''[[glasnost]]''&quot; (openness) and &quot;''[[perestroika]]''&quot; (restructuring) in 1985, hoping to stimulate the failing Soviet economy and encourage productivity, particularly in the areas of consumer goods, the liberalisation of co-operative businesses and the service economy. Glasnost rescinded limitations on [[Freedom (political)|political freedoms]] in the Soviet Union which led to problems within the non-Russian nations occupied in the build-up to war in the 1940s.

Hitherto unrecognised issues previously kept secret by the Moscow government were admitted to in public, causing dissatisfaction within the Baltic States. Combined with the [[Soviet war in Afghanistan|war in Afghanistan]] and the nuclear fallout in [[Chernobyl disaster|Chernobyl]], grievances were aired in a publicly explosive and politically decisive manner.  Estonians were concerned about the [[demographic threat]] to their national identity posed by the influx of individuals from foreign ethnic groups to work on such large Soviet development projects as phosphate mining.&lt;ref&gt;''Estonia and the Estonians'',  Toivo U. Raun,  Hoover Press, 2001, p. 223&lt;/ref&gt;

Access to Western emigre communities abroad and, particularly in Estonia, informal relations with [[Finland]] and access to Finnish TV showing the Western lifestyle also contributed to widespread dissatisfaction with the Soviet system and provoked mass demonstrations as repression on dissidents, nationalists, religious communities and ordinary consumers eased substantially towards the end of the 1980s.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

Massive demonstrations against the Soviet regime began after widespread liberalisation of the regime failed to take into account national sensitivities. It was hoped by [[Politburo of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Moscow]] that the non-Russian nations would remain within the USSR despite the removal of restrictions on freedom of speech and national icons (such as the local pre-1940 flags).{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} However the situation deteriorated to such an extent that by 1989 there were campaigns aimed at freeing the nations from the Soviet Union altogether.

==Estonia==
From 1987, a cycle of mass [[Demonstration (people)|demonstrations]] featuring spontaneous singing eventually collected 300,000 [[Estonians]] in [[Tallinn]] to sing national songs and [[hymn]]s that were strictly forbidden {{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} during the years of the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] occupation, as [[Estonian rock|Estonian rock musicians]] played.

On 14 May 1988, the first expression of national feeling occurred during the [[Tartu]] Pop Music Festival. Five patriotic songs were first performed during this festival. People linked their hands together and a tradition had begun.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

In June the Old Town Festival was held in Tallinn, and after the official part of the festival, the participants moved to [[The Tallinn Song Festival Grounds|the Song Festival Grounds]] and similarly started to sing patriotic songs together spontaneously.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

On 26–28 August 1988, the Rock Summer Festival was held, and patriotic songs, composed by [[Alo Mattiisen]], were played.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

On 11 September 1988, a massive song festival, called &quot;[[Song of Estonia]]&quot;, was held at the Tallinn Song Festival Arena. This time nearly 300,000 people came together, more than a quarter of all Estonians. On that day political leaders were participating actively, and were for the first time insisting on the restoration of independence.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

On 16 November 1988, the legislative body of Estonia issued the [[Estonian Sovereignty Declaration]]. In 1990 Estonia had been the first Soviet republic to defy the Soviet army by offering alternative service to Estonian residents scheduled to be drafted. Most Estonians, however, simply began avoiding the draft.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

The Singing Revolution lasted over four years, with various protests and acts of defiance. In 1991, as Soviet tanks attempted to stop the progress towards independence, the Estonian [[Supreme Soviet]] together with the [[Congress of Estonia]] proclaimed the restoration of the independent [[Sovereign state|state]] of Estonia and repudiated Soviet legislation. People acted as human shields to protect radio and TV stations from the Soviet tanks. Through these actions Estonia regained its independence without any bloodshed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stateofworldliberty.org/report/results.html State of World Liberty ]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 22 August 1991, [[Iceland]] became the first nation to recognise the newly restored independence of Estonia. Today, a plaque commemorating this event is situated on the outside wall of the Foreign Ministry, which itself is situated on Islandi Väljak 1, or &quot;Iceland Square 1&quot;. The plaque reads; &quot;The Republic of [[Iceland]] was the first to recognize, on 22 August 1991, the restoration of the independence of the Republic of Estonia&quot;, in [[Estonian language|Estonian]], [[Icelandic language|Icelandic]] and [[English language|English]].

Independence was declared on the late evening of August 20, 1991, after an agreement between different political parties was reached. The next morning Soviet troops, according to Estonian TV, attempted to storm [[Tallinn TV Tower]] but were not successful.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etv.ee/index.php?0536408 History of ETV (in Estonian)]&lt;/ref&gt; The Communist hardliners' [[1991 Soviet coup d'état attempt|coup attempt]] failed amid mass pro-democracy demonstrations in Moscow led by [[Boris Yeltsin]].

==Latvia==

During the second half of the 1980s as [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] introduced [[glasnost]] and [[perestroika]] in the [[USSR]], which rolled back restrictions to freedom in the Soviet Union, aversion to the Soviet regime had grown into the third [[Latvian National Awakening]], which reached its peak in mid-1988. 

In 1986, it became widely known to the public that the USSR was planning to build another [[hydroelectric power plant]] on Latvia's largest river [[Daugava]], and that a decision had been made to build a subway in [[Riga]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} Both of these projects planned by Moscow could have led to the destruction of Latvia's landscape and cultural and historical heritage. In the press journalists urged the public to protest against these decisions. The public reacted immediately, and in response the [[Environmental Protection Club]] was founded on February 28, 1987. During the second half of the 1980s the Environmental Protection Club became one of the most influential mass movements in the region and began to make demands for the restoration of Latvia's independence.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

On June 14, 1987, the anniversary of the 1941 deportations, the human rights group &quot;[[Helsinki-86]]&quot;, which had been founded a year earlier, organised people to place flowers at the [[Freedom Monument (Riga)|Freedom Monument]] (Latvia's symbol of independence that was erected in 1935). This was an unprecedented event that demonstrated the rebirth of national self-confidence in Latvia.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

On June 1 and 2, 1988, the Writers' Union held a congress during which the democratisation of society, Latvia's economic sovereignty, the cessation of immigration from the USSR, the transformation of industry and the protection of Latvian language rights were discussed by delegates. Over the course of this conference, for the first time in post-war Latvia, the secret protocol of the &quot;[[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact]]&quot;, which had determined Latvia's fate after 1939, was publicly acknowledged.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

The congress of the Writers' Union stirred up public opinion and provided an additional stimulus for the general process of [[Romantic nationalism|national revival]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

In the summer of 1988, two of the most important organisations of the revival period began to assemble themselves - the [[Latvian People's Front]] (LPF) and the [[Latvian National Independence Movement]] (LNIM). Soon afterwards the more radically inclined [[Citizens' Congress of the Republic of Latvia|Citizens' Congress]] called for complete non-compliance with the representatives of the Soviet regime.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} All of these organizations had a common goal: the restoration of democracy and independence. On October 7, 1988, there was a mass public demonstration, calling for Latvia's independence and the establishment of regular judicial order. On October 8 and 9 the first congress of the Latvian People's Front was held. This organization, which attracted 200,000 members, became the main representative of the return to independence.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

On August 23, 1989, the fiftieth anniversary of the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact, the People's Fronts of all three Baltic countries held a huge demonstration of unity - the &quot;[[Baltic Way]]&quot;. A {{convert|600|km|0|abbr=on}} long human &quot;chain&quot; from Tallinn through Riga to [[Vilnius]] was assembled. This was a symbolic demonstration of the people's call for independence from the Soviet Union.

New elections to the [[Supreme Soviet]] took place on March 18, 1990, in which the supporters of independence gained a victory. On May 4, 1990, the new Supreme Soviet of the Latvian SSR adopted a motion, &quot;[[On the Restoration of Independence of the Republic of Latvia|Declaration of Independence]]&quot;, which called for the restoration of the inter-war Latvian state and the 1922 Constitution.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

In January 1991, however, pro-communist political forces attempted to restore Soviet power. With the use of force, attempts were made to overthrow the new assembly. Latvian demonstrators managed to stop the Soviet troops from re-occupying strategic positions, and these events are known as the &quot;[[January 1991 events in Latvia|Days of the Barricades]]&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

On August 19, 1991, an unsuccessful attempt at a [[1991 Soviet coup d'état attempt|coup d'état]] took place in Moscow when a small group of prominent Soviet functionaries failed to regain power due to large pro-democracy demonstrations in Russia. This event resulted in Latvia swiftly moving toward independence.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} After the coup's failure the Supreme Soviet of the Latvian Republic announced on August 21, 1991, that the transition period to full independence declared on May 4, 1990 had come to an end. Therefore Latvia was proclaimed a fully independent nation whose judicial foundation stemmed back to the statehood that existed before the occupation on June 17, 1940.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

==Lithuania==
{{main|Sąjūdis}}

Thousands of people regularly gathered in public places across Lithuania and sang [[national song]]s and [[Roman Catholic]] [[hymn]]s. The popularity of patriotic songs had risen significantly during this period.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} Many popular singers had followed this trend, often using the poetry of nationalist poets, such as [[Bernardas Brazdžionis]] or [[Justinas Marcinkevičius]] as the lyrics of their songs. [[Roko Maršas|Rock March]] also promoted awareness of the issue among the people.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

On June 3, 1988, the [[Sąjūdis]], a political and social movement to lead the independence and pro-democracy movement, was established.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

[[Image:UkmPaminkl.JPG|thumb|250px|[[Ukmergė]]'s monument of independence, &quot;Lituania Restituta&quot;, restored in 1989.]]

The active nationalist opposition towards the regime culminated in the return of [[Vilnius Cathedral]], formerly used as a museum of fine arts, to the Catholic community on 21 October 1988,  followed by the gradual restoration of national symbols, which included the erection or restoration of independence monuments throughout the country. The [[Tautiška giesmė|national anthem of Lithuania]] and the traditional national [[Flag of Lithuania|Tricolore]] were legalised in Lithuania on 18 November 1988, officially replacing the [[flag of Lithuanian SSR|flag]] and the [[anthem of the Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

Five decades after Lithuania was occupied and incorporated into the Soviet Union, Lithuania became the first republic to [[Act of the Re-Establishment of the State of Lithuania|declare its independence]] from the USSR on March 11, 1990, and was later followed by Latvia and Estonia. However, almost all nations in the international community, except [[Iceland]], hesitated to recognise independence for Lithuania until August 1991.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

The Soviet military responded harshly. On January 13, 1991, fourteen non-violent protesters in Vilnius died and hundreds were injured defending the [[Vilnius Television Tower]] and the [[Seimas|Parliament]] from Soviet assault troops and tanks. Lithuanians referred to the event as [[January Events#January 13|Bloody Sunday]]. The discipline and courage of its citizens - linking arms and singing in the face of tanks and armour-piercing bullets - avoided a much greater loss of life and showed the world that Lithuania's citizens were prepared to defend national independence.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

The international governments recognised Lithuanian independence after the failure of the [[1991 Soviet coup d'état attempt|coup d'état]] in August 1991.

==See also==
* [[Baltic Way]]
* [[Collapse of Communism]]
* [[Dissolution of the Soviet Union]]
*[[Helsinki-86]]
* [[January 1991 events in Latvia]]
* [[January Events]] - [[Lithuania]]
* [[Non-violent revolution]]

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Singing Revolution}}
* [http://lietuviu-bendruomene.org/lithuania.html A Lithuanian history, including information about Bloody Sunday]
* [http://talkinghistory.oah.org/arch2000.html Audio interviews of two leaders of Lithuania's Singing Revolution: Vytautas Landsbergis and Valdas Adamkus, current President of the Republic of Lithuania]
* [http://www.tallinn-life.com/tallinn/estonian-singing-revolution  Tallinn-Life: ''A Brief Guide to the Estonian Singing Revolution'']
* [http://www.estonianfreepress.com/2010/07/the-singing-revolution-should-be-known-by-the-whole-world/ ''The Singing Revolution'' Estonian Free Press interview to the director]
* [http://www.singingrevolution.com ''The Singing Revolution'', US documentary film of the Estonian Singing Revolution]

{{Restoration of Baltic independence}}
{{Eastern Bloc}}
{{Fall of Communism}}

[[Category:Eastern Bloc]]
[[Category:Singing Revolution| ]]
[[Category:20th-century revolutions]]
[[Category:History of Estonia]]
[[Category:Estonian music]]
[[Category:History of Latvia]]
[[Category:History of Lithuania (1945–1990)]]
[[Category:Nonviolent revolutions]]
[[Category:Soviet military occupations]]
[[Category:Decommunization]]
[[Category:Protests]]
[[Category:Estonian Soviet Socialist Republic]]
[[Category:20th century in Latvia]]
[[Category:20th century in Lithuania]]
[[Category:1988 in Estonia]]
[[Category:1988 in Latvia]]
[[Category:1988 in Lithuania]]
[[Category:1988 in international relations]]

[[be-x-old:Сьпяваючая рэвалюцыя]]
[[bg:Пееща революция]]
[[ca:Revolució Cantant]]
[[cs:Zpívající revoluce]]
[[de:Singende Revolution]]
[[et:Laulev revolutsioon]]
[[es:Revolución Cantada]]
[[eo:Kantanta Revolucio]]
[[fr:Révolution chantante]]
[[ko:노래 혁명]]
[[id:Revolusi Bernyanyi]]
[[it:Rivoluzione cantata]]
[[lv:Dziesmotā revolūcija]]
[[lt:Dainuojanti revoliucija]]
[[nl:Zingende revolutie]]
[[no:Den syngende revolusjonen]]
[[nn:Den syngande revolusjonen]]
[[pl:Śpiewająca rewolucja]]
[[pt:Revolução Cantada]]
[[ru:Поющая революция]]
[[fi:Laulava vallankumous]]
[[sv:Sjungande revolutionen]]
[[tr:Şarkı Devrimi]]</text>
      <sha1>l9v4kjzksn8e9ftgb6xemad712ktpdx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
