<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Social history</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>222291</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521795572</id>
      <parentid>519305776</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T08:21:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove unicode control characters (CHECKWIKI error 16) +general fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8535)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34537">{{for|a medical patient's social history as recorded by a hospital admission note|Social history (medicine)}}
{{Campaignbox Theories of History}}

'''Social history''', often called the '''new social history,''' is a branch of [[history]] that includes history of ordinary people and their strategies of coping with life. In its &quot;golden age&quot; it was a major growth field in the 1960s and 1970s among scholars, and still is well represented in history departments.&lt;ref&gt;The 1967-82 period was the &quot;golden age&quot; in Canada say Cross and Kealey (1983). vol 5 p 5&lt;/ref&gt; In the two decades from 1975 to 1995, the proportion of professors of history in American universities identifying with social history rose from 31% to 41%, while the proportion of political historians fell from 40% to 30%.&lt;ref&gt;Diplomatic dropped from 5% to 3%, economic history from 7% to 5%, and cultural history grew from 14% to 16%.  Based on full-time professors in U.S. history departments. Stephen H. Haber, David M. Kennedy, and Stephen D. Krasner, &quot;Brothers under the Skin: Diplomatic History and International Relations,&quot; ''International Security,'' Vol. 22, No. 1 (Summer, 1997), pp. 34-43 at p. 4 2; [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2539326 online at JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;  In the history departments of British universities in 2007, of the 5723 faculty members, 1644 (29%)  identified themselves with '''social history''' while [[political history]] came next with 1425 (25%).&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.history.ac.uk/ihr/Resources/Teachers/a27.html &quot;Teachers of History in the Universities of the UK 2007 - listed by research interest&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Old and new social history==
The older social history (before 1960) included numerous topics that were not part of the mainstream historiography of political, military, diplomatic and constitutional history. It was a hodgepodge without a central theme, and it often included political movements, like Populism, that were &quot;social&quot; in the sense of being outside the elite system. Social history was contrasted with [[political history]], [[intellectual history]] and the history of [[Great man theory|great men]]. English historian [[G. M. Trevelyan]] saw it as the bridging point between economic and political history, reflecting that, &quot;Without social history, economic history is barren and political history unintelligible.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=English Social History: A Survey of Six Centuries from Chaucer to Queen Victoria|author=[[G. M. Trevelyan]]|publisher=Book Club Associates|year=1973|chapter=Introduction|page=i|isbn=0-582-48488-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the field has often been viewed negatively as history with the politics left out, it has also been defended as &quot;history with the people put back in.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The People's State: East German Society from Hitler to Honecker|author=Mary Fulbrook|location=London|publisher=Yale University Press|year=2005|chapter=Introduction: The people's paradox|page=17|isbn=978-0-300-14424-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==New Social History movement==
The &quot;new social history&quot; exploded on the scene in the 1960s, quickly becoming one of the dominant styles of historiography in the U.S., Britain and Canada.  The French version, promulgated by the [[Annales School]], was very well organized and dominated French historiography, and influenced much of Europe and Latin America.  Americanist Paul E. Johnson recalls the heady early promise of the movement in the late 1960s:
:The New Social History reached UCLA at about that time, and I was trained as a quantitative social science historian. I learned that &quot;literary&quot; evidence and the kinds of history that could be written from it were inherently elitist and untrustworthy. Our cousins, the Annalistes, talked of ignoring heroes and events and reconstructing the more constitutive and enduring &quot;background&quot; of history. Such history could be made only with quantifiable sources. The result would be a &quot;History from the Bottom Up&quot; that ultimately engulfed traditional history and, somehow, helped to make a Better World. Much of this was acted out with mad-scientist bravado. One well-known quantifier said that anyone who did not know statistics at least through multiple regression should not hold a job in a history department. My own advisor told us that he wanted history to become &quot;a predictive social science.&quot;  I never went that far. I was drawn to the new social history by its democratic inclusiveness as much as by its system and precision. I wanted to write the history of ordinary people—to historicize them, put them into the social structures and long-term trends that shaped their lives, and at the same time resurrect what they said and did. In the late 1960s, quantitative social history looked like the best way to do that.&lt;ref&gt;Paul E. Johnson, &quot;Reflections: Looking Back at Social History,&quot; ''Reviews in American History'' Volume 39, Number 2, June 2011 [http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/reviews_in_american_history/v039/39.2.johnson.html online at [[Project MUSE]]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Social Science History Association, formed in 1976, brings together scholars from numerous disciplines interested in social history and publishes ''[[Social Science History]]'' quarterly.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.ssha.org/ the SSHA website]&lt;/ref&gt; The field is also the specialty of the ''[[Journal of Social History]]'', edited since 1967 by [[Peter Stearns]]&lt;ref&gt;. See [http://chnm.gmu.edu/jsh/ ''Journal of Social History'']&lt;/ref&gt;  It covers such topics as gender relations; race in American history; the history of personal relationships; consumerism; sexuality; the social history of politics; crime and punishment, and history of the senses. Most of the major historical journals have coverage as well.

However, after 1990 social history was increasingly challenged by cultural history, which emphasizes language and the importance of beliefs and assumptions and their causal role in group behavior.&lt;ref&gt;[[Lynn Hunt]] and Victoria Bonnell, eds., ''Beyond the Cultural Turn'' (1999).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Subfields==

===Demographic history===
The study of the lives of ordinary people was revolutionized in the 1960s by the introduction of sophisticated quantitative and demographic methods, often using individual data from the census and from local registers of births, marriages, deaths and taxes, as well as theoretical models from sociology such as [[social mobility]].  H-DEMOG is a daily email discussion group that covers the field broadly.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.h-net.org/~demog/ H-DEMOG]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Demographic history]] is the study of population history and demographic processes, usually using census or similar statistical data. It became an important specialty inside social history, with strong connections with the larger field of [[demography]], as in the study of the  [[Demographic Transition]].

===Black history===
Black history or [[African-American history]] studies African Americans and Africans in American history. The [[Association for the Study of African American Life and History]] was founded by [[Carter G. Woodson]] in 1915 and has 2500 members and publishes the ''[[Journal of African American History]],'' formerly the ''Journal of Negro History.'' Since 1926 it has sponsored [[Black History Month]] every February.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.asalh.org/ ASALH]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ethnic history===
[[Ethnic history]] is especially important in the U.S. and Canada, where major encyclopedias helped define the field.&lt;ref&gt;Stephan Thernstrom, ed. ''Harvard Encyclopedia of American Ethnic Groups'' (1980) [http://books.google.com/books?id=npQ6Hd3G4kgC  excerpt and text search]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Paul R.  Magocsi, ed. ''Encyclopedia of Canada's peoples'' (1999) [http://books.google.com/books?id=dbUuX0mnvQMC excerpt and text search]&lt;/ref&gt; It covers the history of ethnic groups (usually not including blacks or Native Americans).
*The Immigration and Ethnic History Society was formed in 1976 and publishes a journal for libraries and its 829 members.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.historians.org/affiliates/immigration_ethnic_his_soc.htm Immigration and Ethnic History Society]&lt;/ref&gt;
*The American Conference for Irish Studies, founded in 1960, has 1,700 members and has occasional publications but no journal.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.acisweb.com/index.php American Conference for Irish Studies]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The American Italian Historical Association was founded in 1966 and has 400 members; it does not publish a journal &lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.aihaweb.org/ American Italian Historical Association]&lt;/ref&gt;
*The American Jewish Historical Society is the oldest ethnic society, founded in 1892; it has 3,300 members and publishes ''American Jewish History''&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.ajhs.org American Jewish Historical Society] and [http://www.ajhs.org/academic/history.cfm journal]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Polish American Historical Association was founded in 1942, and publishes a newsletter and ''Polish American Studies,'' an interdisciplinary, refereed scholarly journal twice each year.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.polishamericanstudies.org/index.html PAHA website]&lt;/ref&gt;
* H-ETHNIC is a daily discussion list founded in 1993 with 1400 members; it covers topics of ethnicity and migration globally.&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.h-net.org/~ethnic/ H-ETHNIC website]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Labor history===
[[Labor history (discipline)]], deals with labor unions and the social history of workers. See for example [[Labor history of the United States]]  The Study Group on International Labor and Working-Class History was established: 1971 and has a membership of 1000.  It publishes ''International Labor and Working-Class History''.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.newschool.edu/gf/history/ilwch/ Study Group on International Labor and Working-Class History]&lt;/ref&gt; H-LABOR is a daily email-based discussion group formed in 1993 that reaches over a thousand scholars and advanced students.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.h-net.org/~labor/ H-LABOR website]&lt;/ref&gt;

Kirk (2010) surveys labour historiography in Britain since the formation of the Society for the Study of Labour History in 1960. He reports that labour history has been mostly pragmatic, eclectic and empirical; it has played an important role in historiographical debates, such as those revolving around history from below, institutionalism versus the social history of labour, class, populism, gender, language, postmodernism and the turn to politics. Kirk rejects suggestions that the field is declining, and stresses its innovation, modification and renewal. Kirk also detects a move into conservative insularity and academicism. He recommends a more extensive and critical engagement with the kinds of comparative, transnational and global concerns increasingly popular among labour historians elsewhere, and calls for a revival of public and political interest in the topics.&lt;ref&gt;Neville Kirk, &quot;Challenge, Crisis, and Renewal? Themes in the Labour History of Britain, 1960–2010,&quot; ''Labour History Review,'' Aug 2010, Vol. 75 Issue 2, pp 162-180&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile Navickas, (2011) examines recent scholarship including the histories of collective action, environment and human ecology, and gender issues, with a focus on work by James Epstein, Malcolm Chase, and Peter Jones.&lt;ref&gt;Katrina Navickas, &quot;What happened to class? New histories of labour and collective action in Britain,&quot; ''Social History,'' May 2011, Vol. 36 Issue 2, pp 192-204&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Richard Price, &quot;Histories of Labour and Labour History,&quot; ''Labour History Review,'' Dec 2010, Vol. 75 Issue 3, pp 263-270&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women's history===
[[Women's history]] exploded into prominence in the 1970s,&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.mtsu.edu/~kmiddlet/history/women.html American Women's History: A Research Guide]&lt;/ref&gt; and is now well represented in every geographical topic; increasingly it includes gender history.&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.amazon.com/dp/1405149604  Teresa A. Meade and Merry Wiesner-Hanks, eds. ''A Companion to Gender History'' (2006)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gender history===
Gender history focuses on women's history, the gender roles and homosexuality, in terms of actual behavior.  However the &quot;construction&quot; of gender roles is usually part of cultural history.&lt;ref&gt;Sharon Marcus, &quot;Queer Theory for Everyone: A Review Essay,&quot; ''Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society,'' Autumn 2005, Vol. 31 Issue 1, pp 191-218&lt;/ref&gt;

===History of the family===
The History of the family emerged as a separate field in the 1970s, with close ties to anthropology and sociology.&lt;ref&gt;Tamara K. Hareven, &quot;The history of the family and the complexity of social change,&quot; ''American Historical Review,'' Feb 1991, Vol. 96 Issue 1, pp 95-124&lt;/ref&gt; The trend was especially pronounced in the U.S. and Canada.&lt;ref&gt;Cynthia Comacchio, &quot;'The History  of Us': Social Science, History, and the Relations of Family in Canada,&quot; ''Labour / Le Travail,'' Fall 2000, Vol. 46, pp 167-220, with very thorough coverage.&lt;/ref&gt; It emphasizes on demographic patterns, and public policy.  It is quite separate from [[Genealogy]], though often drawing on the same primary sources such as censuses and family records.&lt;ref&gt;see [http://jfh.sagepub.com/ ''Journal of Family History'', quarterly since 1976]&lt;/ref&gt; An influential pioneering study was ''Women, Work, and Family'' (1978), by [[Louise A. Tilly]] and [[Joan W. Scott]]. It broke new ground with their broad interpretive framework and emphasis on the variable factors shaping women's place in the family and economy in France and England. It considered the interaction of production and reproduction in analysis of women's wage labor and thus helped to bring together labor and family history.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Dublin, &quot;Women, Work, and Family: The View from the United States,&quot; ''Journal of Women's History,'' Autumn 99, Vol. 11 Issue 3, pp 17-21&lt;/ref&gt;  Much work has been done on the dichotomy in women's lives between the private sphere and the public.&lt;ref&gt;D'Ann Campbell, ''Women at War with America: Private Lives in a Patriotic Era'' (1984)&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[history of childhood]] is a growing subfield.&lt;ref&gt;Peter N. Stearns, &quot;Social History and World History: Prospects for Collaboration.&quot; ''Journal of World History'' 2007 18(1): 43-52. Issn: 1045-6007 Fulltext: [[History Cooperative]]  and [[Project Muse]], deals with the history of childhood worldwide. See Peter N. Stearns, ''Childhood in World History'' (2005), A.R. Colon with P. A. Colon, ''A History of Children: A Socio-Cultural Survey across Millennia'' (2001), and Steven Mintz, ''Huck's Raft: A History of American Childhood'' (2006).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Joseph M. Hawes and N. Ray Hiner, &quot;Hidden in Plain View: The History of Children (and Childhood) in the Twenty-First Century,&quot; ''Journal of the History of Childhood &amp; Youth,'' Jan 2008, Vol. 1 Issue 1, pp 43-49&lt;/ref&gt;

===History of education===
{{main|History of education}}
Most histories of education deal with institutions or focus on the ideas histories of major reformers,&lt;ref&gt;Three fourths of British studies are institutional, says William Richardson, &quot;British Historiography of Education in International Context at the Turn of the Century, 1996-2006,&quot; ''History of Education'', July /Sept 2007, Vol. 36 Issue 4/5, pp 569-593,&lt;/ref&gt;  but a new social history has recently emerged, focused on who were the students in terms of social background and social mobility. In the U.S. attention has often focused on minority and ethnic students. In Britain, Raftery et al. (2007) looks at the historiography on social change and education in Ireland, Scotland, and Wales, with particular reference to 19th-century schooling. They developed distinctive systems of schooling in the 19th century that reflected not only their relationship to England but also significant contemporaneous economic and social change. This article seeks to create a basis for comparative work by identifying research that has treated this period, offering brief analytical commentaries on some key works, discussing developments in educational historiography, and pointing to lacunae in research.&lt;ref&gt;Deirdre Raftery, Jane McDermid, and Gareth Elwyn Jones, &quot;Social Change and Education in Ireland, Scotland and Wales: Historiography on Nineteenth-century Schooling,&quot; ''History of Education'', July/Sept 2007, Vol. 36 Issue 4/5, pp 447-463&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians have recently looked at the relationship between schooling and urban growth by studying educational institutions as agents in class formation, relating urban schooling to changes in the shape of cities, linking urbanization with social reform movements, and examining the material conditions affecting child life and the relationship between schools and other agencies that socialize the young.&lt;ref&gt;David A. Reeder, Schooling in the City: Educational History and the Urban Variable,&quot; ''Urban History,'' May 1992, Vol. 19 Issue 1, pp 23-38&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Juergen Herbst, &quot;The History of Education: State of the Art at the Turn of the Century in Europe and North America,&quot; ''Paedagogica Historica'' 35, no. 3 (1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

The most economics-minded historians have sought to relate education to changes in the quality of labor, productivity and economic growth, and rates of return on investment in education.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Sanderson, &quot;Educational and Economic History: The Good Neighbours,&quot; ''History of Education,'' July /Sept 2007, Vol. 36 Issue 4/5, pp 429-445&lt;/ref&gt;  A major recent exemplar is Claudia Goldin and Lawrence F. Katz, ''The Race between Education and Technology'' (2009), on the social and economic history of 20th century American schooling.

===Urban history===
{{main|Urban history}}
The &quot;new urban history&quot; emerged in the 1960s seeking to understand the &quot;city as process&quot; and, through quantitative methods, to learn more about the inarticulate masses in the cities, as opposed to the mayors and elites.&lt;ref&gt;Stephan Thernstrom and Richard Sennett, eds. ''Nineteenth-century Cities: Essays in the New Urban History'' (1970)&lt;/ref&gt;  A major early study was  [[Stephan Thernstrom]]'s ''Poverty and Progress: Social Mobility in a Nineteenth Century City'' (1964), which used census records to study [[Newburyport, Massachusetts]], 1850-1880. A seminal, landmark book, it sparked interest in the 1960s and 1970s in  quantitative methods, census sources,  &quot;bottom-up&quot; history, and the measurement of upward social mobility by different ethnic groups.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Frisch, &quot;''Poverty and Progress:'' A Paradoxical Legacy,&quot; ''Social Science History,'' Spring 1986, Vol. 10 Issue 1, pp 15-22&lt;/ref&gt; Other exemplars of the new urban history included  Kathleen Conzen,  ''Immigrant Milwaukee, 1836-1860'' (1976); Alan Dawley, ''Class and Community: The Industrial Revolution in Lynn'' (1975; 2nd ed. 2000); Michael B. Katz,  ''The People of Hamilton, Canada West'' (1976);&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.amazon.com/dp/159740411X/  excerpt and text search]&lt;/ref&gt; Eric H. Monkkonen, ''The Dangerous Class: Crime and Poverty in Columbus Ohio 1860-1865'' (1975); and Michael P. Weber, ''Social Change in an Industrial Town: Patterns of Progress in Warren, Pennsylvania, From Civil War to World War I.'' (1976).

There were no overarching social history theories that emerged developed to explain urban development. Inspiration from urban geography and sociology, as well as a concern with workers (as opposed to labor union leaders), families, ethnic groups, racial segregation, and women's roles have proven useful. Historians now view the contending groups within the city as &quot;agents&quot; who shape the direction of urbanization.&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Marsh and Lizabeth Cohen. &quot;Old Forms, New Visions: New Directions in United States Urban History,&quot; ''Pennsylvania History,'' Winter 1992, Vol. 59 Issue 1, pp 21-28&lt;/ref&gt; The subfield has flourished in Australia—where most people live in cities.&lt;ref&gt;Lionel Frost, and Seamus O'Hanlon, &quot;Urban History and the Future of Australian Cities,&quot; ''Australian Economic History Review'' March 2009, Vol. 49 Issue 1, pp 1-18&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rural history===
{{main|Rural history}}
[[Agricultural History]] handles the economic and technological dimensions, while [[Rural history]] handles the social dimension.  Burchardt (2007) evaluates the state of modern English rural history and identifies an &quot;orthodox&quot; school, focused on the economic history of agriculture. This historiography has made impressive progress in quantifying and explaining the output and productivity achievements of English farming since the &quot;agricultural revolution.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;On British rural history see Jeremy Burchardt, &quot;Agricultural History, Rural History, or Countryside History?&quot;  ''Historical Journal'' 2007 50(2): 465-481. Issn: 0018-246x&lt;/ref&gt; The celebratory style of the orthodox school was challenged by a dissident tradition emphasizing the social costs of agricultural progress, notably enclosure, which forced poor tenant farmers off the land. Recently, a new school, associated with the journal ''Rural History,'' has broken away from this narrative of agricultural change, elaborating a wider social history. The work of Alun Howkins has been pivotal in the recent historiography, in relation to these three traditions.&lt;ref&gt;Alun Howkins, ''The Death Rural England'' (2003) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/041513885X excerpt and text search]&lt;/ref&gt; Howkins, like his precursors, is constrained by an increasingly anachronistic equation of the countryside with agriculture. Geographers and sociologists have developed a concept of a &quot;post-productivist&quot; countryside, dominated by consumption and representation that may have something to offer historians, in conjunction with the well-established historiography of the &quot;rural idyll.&quot;  Most rural history has focused on the [[Southern United States|American South]]—overwhelmingly rural until the 1950s—but there is a &quot;new rural history&quot; of [[Union (American Civil War)|the North]] as well. Instead of becoming agrarian capitalists, farmers held onto preindustrial capitalist values emphasizing family and community. Rural areas maintained population stability; kinship ties determined rural immigrant settlement and community structures; and the defeminization of farm work encouraged the rural version of the &quot;women's sphere.&quot; These findings strongly contrast with those in the old frontier history as well as those found in the new urban history.&lt;ref&gt;Hal S. Barron, &quot;Rediscovering the Majority: The New Rural History  of the Nineteenth-Century North,&quot; ''Historical Methods,'' Fall 1986, Vol. 19 Issue 4, pp 141-152&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social history in Europe==

===France===
{{main|Annales School}}
Social history has dominated French historiography since the 1920s, thanks to the central role of the [[Annales School]].  Its journal '&quot;Annales'' focuses attention on the synthesizing of historical patterns identified from social, economic, and cultural history, statistics, medical reports, family studies, and even psychoanalysis.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Burke, ''The French Historical Revolution: The Annales School 1929–89'' (1990)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
{{main|Bielefeld School}}
Social history developed within West German historiography during the 1950s-60s as the successor to the national history discredited by [[National Socialism]].  The German brand of &quot;history of society&quot; - ''Gesellschaftsgeschichte'' - has been known from its beginning in the 1960s for its application of sociological and political modernization theories to German history. [[Modernization theory]] was presented by [[Hans-Ulrich Wehler]] (1931- ) and his [[Bielefeld School]] as the way to transform &quot;traditional&quot; German history, that is, national political history, centered on a few &quot;great men,&quot; into an integrated and comparative history of German society encompassing societal structures outside politics. Wehler drew upon the modernization theory of Max Weber, with concepts also from Karl Marx, Otto Hintze, Gustav Schmoller, Werner Sombart and [[Thorstein Veblen]].&lt;ref&gt;Roger Fletcher,  &quot;Recent Developments in West German Historiography: the Bielefeld School and its Critics.&quot; ''German Studies Review'' 1984 7(3): 451-480. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1428885 in Jstor]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1970s and early 1980s German historians of society, led by Wehler and [[Jürgen Kocka]] at the &quot;Bielefeld school&quot;  gained dominance in Germany by applying both modernization theories and social science methods. From the 1980s, however, they were increasingly criticized by proponents of the &quot;cultural turn&quot; for not incorporating culture in the history of society, for reducing politics to society, and for reducing individuals to structures. Historians of society inverted the traditional positions they criticized (on the model of Marx's inversion of Hegel). As a result, the problems pertaining to the positions criticized were not resolved but only turned on their heads. The traditional focus on individuals was inverted into a modern focus on structures, the traditional focus on culture was inverted into a modern focus on structures, and traditional emphatic understanding was inverted into modern causal explanation.&lt;ref&gt;Chris Lorenz, &quot;'Won't You Tell Me, Where Have All the Good Times Gone'? On the Advantages and Disadvantages of Modernization Theory for History.&quot; ''Rethinking History'' 2006 10(2): 171-200. Issn: 1364-2529 Fulltext: [[Ebsco]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hungary===
With the collapse of Communism in Hungary in 1989. Marxist historiography collapsed and social history came into its own, especially the study of the demography patterns of the early modern period. Research priorities have shifted toward urban history and the conditions of everyday life.&lt;ref&gt;Gabor Gyani, &quot;Trends in contemporary Hungarian historical scholarship,&quot; ''Social History,'' May 2009, Vol. 34 Issue 2, pp 250-260&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
{{main|Social history of Canada}}
Social history had a &quot;golden age&quot; in Canada in the 1970s, and continues to flourish among scholars. Its strengths include demography, women, labour, and urban studies.&lt;ref&gt;Michael S.  Cross, &quot;Social History,&quot; [http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/PrinterFriendly.cfm?Params=A1ARTA0007523 ''Canadian Encyclopedia'' (2008) online]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael S. Cross and Gregory S. Kealey, eds. ''Readings in Canadian Social History'' (5 vol., 1983), articles by scholars&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Michael Horn and Sabourin, Ronald, eds. ''Studies in Canadian Social History'' (1974). 480 pp. articles by scholars&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political history==
While the study of elites and political institutions has produced a large and growing body of scholarship, social historians have complained about elitism, and want more emphasis on the common people.  Political historians have responded with the new political history,&quot; which shifts attention to the behavior and values of voters.  Recently some scholars have tried a cultural approach to political history.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey L. Pasley, Andrew W. Robertson, and David Waldstreicher, eds. ''Beyond the Founders: New Approaches to the Political History of the Early American Republic'' (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;  Political historians complain that social historians are likely to put too much stress on the dimensions of class, gender and race, reflecting a leftist political agenda that assumes outsiders in politics are more interesting than the actual decision makers.&lt;ref&gt;Romain Huret, &quot;All in the Family Again? Political Historians and the Challenge of Social History,&quot; ''Journal of Policy History'', July 2009, Vol. 21 Issue 3, pp 239-263&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Marc Bloch]] (1886–1944). Medieval, [[Annales School]]
*[[Martin Broszat]] (1926–1989), Germany
*[[Natalie Zemon Davis]], (b. 1928) France
*[[Herbert Gutman]] (1928-1985), American black and labor history
*[[Eugene D. Genovese]] (b. 1930), American slavery
*[[Oscar Handlin]] (1915-2011), American ethnic
*[[Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie]], leader of [[Annales School]], France
*[[Ram Sharan Sharma]] (b. 1919), India
*[[Stephan Thernstrom]] (b. 1943), ethnic American; social mobility
*[[E. P. Thompson]] (1924–1993), British labour
*[[Hans-Ulrich Wehler]] (b. 1931), 19th century Germany, [[Bielefeld School]]
*[[History of sociology]]

==Bibliography==
* Adas, Michael. &quot;Social History and the Revolution in African and Asian Historiography,&quot; ''Journal of Social History'' 19 (1985): 335-378.
* Anderson, Michael. ''Approaches to the History of the Western Family 1500-1914'' (1995) 104pp [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0521557933 excerpt and text search]
* Cabrera, Miguel A.  ''Postsocial History: An Introduction.'' (2004). 163 pp.
* Cayton, Mary Kupiec, Elliott J. Gorn, and Peter W. Williams, eds. ''Encyclopedia of American Social History'' (3 vol 1993) 2653pp; long articles  pages by leading scholars; see v I: Part II, ''Methods and Contexts,'' pp 235–434
* Cross, Michael S. &quot;Social History,&quot; [http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/PrinterFriendly.cfm?Params=A1ARTA0007523 ''Canadian Encyclopedia'' (2008) online]
* Cross, Michael S. and Kealey, Gregory S., eds.  ''Readings in Canadian Social History'' (5 vol 1984). 243 pp.
* Dewald, Jonathan.  ''Lost Worlds: The Emergence of French Social History, 1815-1970.'' (2006). 241 pp.
* Eley, Geoff.  ''A Crooked Line: From Cultural History to the History of Society.'' (2005). 301 pp.
* Fairburn, Miles.  ''Social History: Problems, Strategies and Methods.'' (1999). 325 pp.
* Fass, Paula, ed. ''Encyclopedia of Children and Childhood: In History and Society,'' (3 vols. 2003).
* Fletcher, Roger. &quot;Recent Developments in West German Historiography: the Bielefeld School and its Critics.&quot; ''German Studies Review'' 1984 7(3): 451-480. Issn: 0149-7952 Fulltext: [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0149-7952(198410)7%3A3%3C451%3ARDIWGH%3E2.0.CO%3B2-E in Jstor]
* Hareven, Tamara K.  &quot;The History of the Family and the Complexity of Social Change,&quot; ''American Historical Review,'' Feb 1991, Vol. 96 Issue 1, pp 95–124 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2164019 in JSTOR]
* Henretta, James. &quot;Social History as Lived and Written,&quot; ''American Historical Review'' 84 (1979): 1293-1323 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1861469 in JSTOR]
* Kanner, Barbara.  ''Women in English Social History, 1800-1914: A Guide to Research'' (2 vol 1988-1990). 871 pp.
* Lloyd, Christopher.  ''Explanation in Social History.'' (1986). 375 pp.
* Lorenz, Chris. &quot;'Won't You Tell Me, Where Have All the Good Times Gone'? On the Advantages and Disadvantages of Modernization Theory for History.&quot; ''Rethinking History'' 2006 10(2): 171-200. Issn: 1364-2529 Fulltext: [[Ebsco]]
* Mintz, Steven. ''Huck's Raft: A History of American Childhood'' (2006). [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0674019989 excerpt and text search]
* Mintz, Steven and Susan Kellogg. ''Domestic Revolutions: A Social History Of American Family Life'' (1989) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/002921291X excerpt and text search]
* Mosley, Stephen. &quot;Common Ground: Integrating Social and Environmental History,&quot; ''Journal of Social History,'' Volume 39, Number 3, Spring 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;915–933, relations with [[Environmental History]], in [[Project MUSE]]
* Palmer, Bryan D., and Todd McCallum, &quot;Working-Class History&quot; [http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/PrinterFriendly.cfm?Params=A1ARTA0008710 ''Canadian Encyclopedia'' (2008)]
* Pomeranz, Kenneth. &quot;Social History and World History: from Daily Life to Patterns of Change.&quot; ''Journal of World History'' 2007 18(1): 69-98. Issn: 1045-6007 Fulltext: in [[History Cooperative]] and [[Project Muse]]
* Stearns, Peter N. &quot;Social History Today ... And Tomorrow,&quot; ''Journal of Social History'' 10 (1976): 129-155.
* Stearns, Peter N. &quot;Social History Present and Future.&quot; ''Journal of Social History''. Volume: 37. Issue: 1. (2003). pp 9+. [http://www.questia.com/read/5002024617?title=Social%20History%20Present%20and%20Future online edition]
* Stearns,  Peter, ed. ''Encyclopedia of Social History'' (1994) 856 pp.
* Stearns,  Peter, ed. ''Encyclopedia of European Social History from 1350 to 2000'' (5 vol 2000), 209 essays by leading scholars in 3000 pp.
* Sutherland, Neil. &quot;Childhood, History of,&quot; [http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=A1ARTA0001579 ''Canadian Encyclopedia'' (2008)]
* Thompson, E. P.  ''The Essential E. P. Thompson.'' (2001). 512 pp.  highly influential British historian of the working class
*  Thompson, F. M. L., ed.  ''The Cambridge Social History of Britain, 1750-1950.&quot; Vol. 1: ''Regions and Communities''.  Vol. 2:'' People and Their Environment''; Vol. 3: ''Social Agencies and Institutions.'' (1990). 492 pp.
* Tilly, Charles. &quot;The Old New Social History and the New Old Social History,&quot; ''Journal of Social History'' 7 (1984): 363-406;
* Timmins, Geoffrey. &quot;The Future of Learning and Teaching in Social History: the Research Approach and Employability.&quot; ''Journal of Social History'' 2006 39(3): 829-842. Issn: 0022-4529 Fulltext: [[History Cooperative]] and [[Project Muse]]
* Wilson, Adrian, ed.  ''Rethinking Social History: English Society, 1570-1920 and Its Interpretation.'' (1993). 342 pp.
* Zunz, Olivier, ed. ''Reliving the Past: The Worlds of Social History,'' (1985) [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=958580 online edition]

===Primary sources===
* Binder, Frederick M. and David M. Reimers, eds. ''The Way We Lived: Essays and Documents in American Social History.'' (2000). 313 pp.

====Notes====
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.iisg.nl International Institute of Social History]
* [http://www.ashp.cuny.edu American Social History Project]
* [http://www.socialhistory.org.uk/ Social History Society (UK)]
* [http://www.amsab.be Amsab-Institute of Social History (Belgium)]
* [http://www.victorianweb.org/history/sochistov.html Victorian-era social history]
* [http://www.sshm.org/ Society for the social history of medicine]
* [http://www.history.ac.uk/ihr/Resources/Historical/social.html History online]
* [http://www.ialhi.org International Association of Labour History Institutions]
* [http://www.dlfaquifer.org American Social History Online] (19th and 20th digital resources)
* [http://www.democracynow.org/2009/12/25/storycorps_national_social_history_project_records StoryCorps: National Social History Project Records Ordinary People Telling Their Stories] - video by ''[[Democracy Now!]]''

{{DEFAULTSORT:Social History}}
[[Category:Social history| ]]
[[Category:Fields of history]]

[[ar:تاريخ اجتماعي]]
[[bg:Социална история]]
[[ca:Història social]]
[[cs:Sociální dějiny]]
[[de:Sozialgeschichte]]
[[et:Sotsiaalajalugu]]
[[es:Historia social]]
[[fr:Histoire sociale]]
[[ko:사회사]]
[[he:היסטוריה חברתית]]
[[lt:Socialinė istorija]]
[[nl:Sociale geschiedenis]]
[[ja:社会史]]
[[no:Sosialhistorie]]
[[pl:Historia społeczna]]
[[fi:Sosiaalihistoria]]
[[sv:Socialhistoria]]</text>
      <sha1>llvpjls88bo0udcntsjbd6l53rkydgw</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
