<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Song Dynasty</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>56978</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522387787</id>
      <parentid>522345833</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T21:41:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>50.90.80.135</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Society and culture */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="112861">{{distinguish2|the [[Liu Song Dynasty]]}}
{{Infobox Former Country
|native_name = 宋
|conventional_long_name = Song&lt;!-- See the talk page before editing please. --&gt;
|common_name = Northern Song Dynasty
|national_motto =
|continent = Asia
|region    = China
|country   = China
|era       =
|status    = Empire
|status_text =
|government_type = Monarchy
|year_start  = 960
|year_end    = 1279&lt;!--putting AD or CE here breaks the category listings at the bottom of article--&gt;
|p1 = Tang Dynasty
|s1 = Yuan Dynasty
|event_start = [[Zhao Kuangyin]] taking over the throne of the [[Later Zhou Dynasty]]
|date_start  =
|event_end   = [[Battle of Yamen]]; the end of Song rule
|date_end    =
|year_exile_start = 1276
|year_exile_end   = 1279
|event1      = Jingkang Incident
|date_event1 = 1127
|event2      = Surrender of [[Hangzhou|Lin'an]]
|date_event2 = 1276
|event3      =
|date_event3 =
|event4      =
|date_event4 =
|event5      =
|date_event5 =
|image_map    = China 11a.jpg
|image_map_alt = A map showing the territory of the Song, Liao, and Xia dynasties. The Song dynasty occupies the east half of what constitutes the territory of the modern People's Republic of China, except for the northernmost areas (modern Inner Mongolia province and above). The Xia occupy a small strip of land surrounding a river in what is now Inner Mongolia, and the Liao occupy a large section of what is today northeast China.
|image_map_caption= Northern Song in 1111
|capital          = [[Kaifeng|Bianjing]] (汴京)&lt;small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(960–1127)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Hangzhou|Lin'an]] (臨安)&lt;small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(1127–1276)&lt;/small&gt;
|common_languages = [[Chinese language|Chinese]]
|religion         = [[Buddhism]], [[Taoism]], [[Confucianism]], [[Chinese folk religion]]
|currency         = [[Jiaozi (currency)|Jiaozi]], [[Huizi (currency)|Huizi]], [[Chinese cash (currency unit)|Chinese cash]], [[Chinese coin]], [[copper coins]] etc.
|leader1      = [[Emperor Taizu of Song|Emperor Taizu]]
|leader2      = [[Emperor Taizong of Song|Emperor Taizong]]
|leader3      = [[Emperor Zhenzong of Song|Emperor Zhenzong]]
|leader4      = [[Emperor Renzong of Song|Emperor Renzong]]
|leader5      = [[Emperor Yingzong of Song|Emperor Yingzong]]
|leader6      = [[Emperor Shenzong of Song|Emperor Shenzong]]
|leader7      = [[Emperor Zhezong of Song|Emperor Zhezong]]
|leader8      = [[Emperor Huizong of Song|Emperor Huizong]]
|leader9      = [[Emperor Qinzong of Song|Emperor Qinzong]]
|leader10     = [[Emperor Gaozong of Song|Emperor Gaozong]]
|leader11     = [[Emperor Xiaozong of Song|Emperor Xiaozong]]
|leader12     = [[Emperor Guangzong of Song|Emperor Guangzong]]
|leader13     = [[Emperor Ningzong of Song|Emperor Ningzong]]
|leader14     = [[Emperor Lizong of Song|Emperor Lizong]]
|leader15     = [[Emperor Duzong of Song|Emperor Duzong]]
|leader16     = [[Emperor Gongzong of Song|Emperor Gongzong]]
|leader17     = [[Emperor Duanzong of Song|Emperor Duanzong]]
|leader18     = [[Emperor Bing of Song|Emperor Bing]]
|year_leader1 = 960–976
|year_leader9  = 1126–1127
|year_leader10 = 1127–1162
|year_leader18 = 1278–1279
|title_leader = [[List of Song Emperors|Emperor]]
|deputy1      = [[Cai Jing]],
|deputy2      = [[Fan Zhongyan]],
|deputy3      = [[Han Tuozhou]],
|deputy4      = [[Li Fang (Song Dynasty)|Li Fang]],
|deputy5      = [[Qin Hui (Song Dynasty)|Qin Hui]],
|deputy6      = [[Sima Guang]],
|deputy7      = [[Tong Guan]],
|deputy8      = [[Wang Anshi]],
|deputy9      = [[Wen Tianxiang]],
|year_deputy1 = –
|year_deputy2 = –
|year_deputy3 =
|year_deputy4 = –
|year_deputy5 =
|year_deputy6 =
|year_deputy7 = –
|year_deputy8 = –
|year_deputy9 = –
|title_deputy = [[Chancellor of China|Chancellor]]
|legislature  =
|stat_year1 = 962 est.
|stat_area1 = 1050000
|stat_pop1  =
|stat_year2 = 1111 est.
|stat_area2 = 2800000
|stat_pop2  =
|stat_year3 = 1142 est.
|stat_area3 = 2000000
|stat_pop3  =
|stat_year4 = 1120
|stat_area4 =
|stat_pop4  = 118,800,000{{Cref|a}}
}}
{{ChineseText}}
{{History of China}}

The '''Song Dynasty'''  ({{zh|c=宋朝|p=Sòng Cháo}}; [[Wade-Giles]]: Sung Ch'ao; {{IPA-cmn|sʊ̂ŋ tʂʰɑ̌ʊ̯|IPA}}) was a ruling [[dynasties in Chinese history|dynasty]] in [[China]] between 960 and 1279; it succeeded the [[Five Dynasties and Ten Kingdoms Period]], and was followed by the [[Yuan Dynasty]]. It was the first government in world history to issue [[banknote]]s or paper money, and the first Chinese government to establish [[Naval history of China|a permanent standing navy]]. This dynasty also saw the first known use of [[gunpowder]], as well as first discernment of [[true north]] using a [[compass]].

The Song Dynasty is divided into two distinct periods: the Northern Song and Southern Song. During the '''Northern Song''' ({{zh|c=北宋}}, 960–1127), the Song capital was in the northern city of Bianjing (now [[Kaifeng]]) and the dynasty controlled most of [[China Proper|inner China]]. The '''Southern Song''' ({{zh|c=南宋}}, 1127–1279) refers to the period after the Song lost control of [[Northern and southern China|northern China]] to the [[Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)|Jin Dynasty]]. During this time, the Song court retreated south of the [[Yangtze River]] and established their capital at Lin'an (now [[Hangzhou]]). Although the Song Dynasty had lost control of the traditional birthplace of Chinese civilization along the [[Yellow River]], the Song economy was not in ruins, as the Southern Song Empire contained 60 percent of China's population  and a majority of the most productive agricultural land.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 167&quot;/&gt;  The Southern Song Dynasty considerably bolstered its [[navy|naval]] strength to defend its waters and land borders and to conduct [[Ancient maritime history#China|maritime]] missions abroad.

To repel the Jin, and later the [[Mongols]], the Song developed revolutionary new military technology augmented by the use of gunpowder. In 1234, the Jin Dynasty was conquered by the Mongols, who took control of northern China, maintaining uneasy relations with the Southern Song. [[Möngke Khan]], the fourth [[Khagan|Great Khan]] of the Mongol Empire, died in 1259 while besieging the city of [[Chongqing]]. His younger brother [[Kublai Khan]] was proclaimed the new Great Khan, though his claim was only partially recognized by the Mongols in the west. In 1271, Kublai Khan was proclaimed the [[Emperor of China]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=115}}&lt;/ref&gt; After two decades of sporadic warfare, Kublai Khan's armies [[Mongol conquest of the Song Dynasty|conquered the Song Dynasty]] in 1279. China was once again [[Mongol invasion of China|unified]], under the Mongol [[Yuan Dynasty]] (1271–1368).&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=76}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The population of China doubled in size during the 10th and 11th centuries. This growth came through expanded rice cultivation in central and southern China, the use of early-ripening rice from southeast and southern Asia, and the production of abundant food surpluses.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 156&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Brook|1998|p=96}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Northern Song census recorded a population of roughly 50 million, much like the [[Han Dynasty|Han]] and [[Tang Dynasty|Tang]] dynasties. This data is found in the ''[[Twenty-Four Histories|Standard Histories]]''. However, it is estimated that the Northern Song had a population of some 100 million people, and 200 million by the time of the [[Ming Dynasty]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Veeck|Pannell|Smith|Huang|2007|pp=103–104}}&lt;/ref&gt; This dramatic increase of population fomented an [[Economy of the Song Dynasty|economic revolution in premodern China]]. The expansion of the population was partially the cause for the gradual withdrawal of the central government from heavily regulating the market economy. A much larger populace also increased the importance of the lower gentry's role in grassroots administration and local affairs. Appointed officials in county and provincial centers relied upon the scholarly gentry for their services, sponsorship, and local supervision.

Social life during the Song was vibrant; social elites gathered to view and trade precious artworks, the populace intermingled at public festivals and private clubs, and cities had lively entertainment quarters. The spread of literature and knowledge was enhanced by the earlier invention of [[woodblock printing]] and the 11th-century invention of [[movable type]] printing. Pre-modern technology, science, philosophy, mathematics, engineering, and other intellectual pursuits flourished over the course of the Song. Philosophers such as [[Cheng Yi (philosopher)|Cheng Yi]] and [[Zhu Xi]] reinvigorated [[Confucianism]] with new commentary, infused  with [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] ideals, and emphasized a new organization of classic texts that brought out the core doctrine of [[Neo-Confucianism]].  Although the institution of the [[Imperial examination|civil service examinations]] had existed since the [[Sui Dynasty]], it became much more prominent in the Song period. This became a leading factor in the shift of an [[Chinese nobility|aristocratic]] elite to a [[scholar-bureaucrat|bureaucratic]] elite.

== History ==
{{main|History of the Song Dynasty}}
{{Further|List of emperors of the Song Dynasty}}

=== Northern Song, 960–1127 ===
{{Redirect|Northern Song}}
[[Emperor Taizu of Song]] (r. 960–976) unified China through conquering other lands during his reign, ending the upheaval of the [[Five Dynasties and Ten Kingdoms Period]]. In [[Kaifeng]], he established a strong central government over the empire. He ensured administrative stability by promoting the [[Imperial examination|civil service examination]] system of drafting state [[bureaucrat]]s by skill and merit (instead of [[Aristocracy (class)|aristocrat]]ic or military position) and promoted projects that ensured efficiency in communication throughout the empire.] One such a project was the creation by [[Chinese cartography|cartographers]] of detailed maps of each province and city which were then collected in a large [[atlas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 3 518&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|p=518}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also promoted groundbreaking science and technological innovations by supporting such works as the [[astronomical clock|astronomical]] [[clock tower]] designed and built by the engineer [[Zhang Sixun]].&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 469–471&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|pp=469–471}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Song Taizu.jpg|alt=Painted image of a portly man sitting in a red throne-chair with dragon-head decorations, wearing white silk robes, black shoes, and a black hat, and sporting a black mustache and goatee.|thumb|left|upright|[[Emperor Taizu of Song]] (r. 960–976), a court portrait painting]]
The Song court maintained diplomatic relations with [[Chola Dynasty|Chola India]], [[Fatimid|Fatimid Egypt]], [[Srivijaya]], the [[Kara-Khanid Khanate]] of [[Central Asia]], and other countries that were also trade partners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hall|1985|p=23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Sastri|1984|pp=173, 316}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Shen|1996|p=158}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brose 2008 258&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brose|2008|p=258}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it was China's closest neighboring states which would have the greatest impact on its domestic and foreign policy. From its inception under Taizu, the Song Dynasty alternated between warfare and diplomacy with the ethnic [[Khitan people|Khitans]] of the [[Liao Dynasty]] in the northeast and with the [[Tangut people|Tanguts]] of the [[Western Xia Dynasty]] in the northwest.  The Song Dynasty used military force in an attempt to quell the Liao Dynasty and recapture the [[Sixteen Prefectures]], a territory under Khitan control that was traditionally considered to be part of [[China proper]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mote 1999 69&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Mote|1999|p=69}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, Song forces were repulsed by the Liao forces who engaged in aggressive yearly campaigns into northern Song territory until 1005 when the signing of the [[Shanyuan Treaty]] ended these northern border clashes. The Song were forced to provide tribute to the Khitans, although paying this tribute did little damage to the overall Song economy since the Khitans were heavily dependent upon importing massive amounts of goods from the Song Dynasty.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 154&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=154}}.&lt;/ref&gt; More significantly, the Song state recognized the Liao state as its diplomatic equal.&lt;ref name=&quot;mote 1999 70 71&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Mote|1999|pp=70–71}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Song Dynasty managed to win several military victories over the Tanguts in the early 11th century, culminating in a campaign led by the polymath scientist, general, and statesman [[Shen Kuo]] (1031–1095).&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 8&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|p=8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, this campaign was ultimately a failure due to a rival military officer of Shen disobeying direct orders, and the territory gained from the Western Xia was eventually lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 9&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|p=9}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There was also a significant war fought against the [[Lý Dynasty]] of [[Vietnam]] from 1075 to 1077 over a border dispute and the Song's severing of commercial relations with the [[Đại Việt]] kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson 2008 207&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Anderson|2008|p=207}}.&lt;/ref&gt; After Lý forces inflicted heavy damages in a raid on [[Guangxi]], the Song commander Guo Kui (1022–1088) penetrated as far as Thăng Long (modern [[Hanoi]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Anderson|2008|p=208}}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, heavy losses on both sides prompted the Lý commander Thường Kiệt (1019–1105) to make peace overtures, allowing both sides to withdraw from the war effort; captured territories held by both Song and Lý were mutually exchanged in 1082, along with prisoners of war.&lt;ref name=&quot;anderson 2008 208 209&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Anderson|2008|pp=208–209}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Oreiller Guimet 291171.jpg|alt=An oval shaped pillow with flat sides. It is made of black cloth with an image of a white bird sitting on a branch stitched into it.|thumb|left|Pillow, sandstone with white and brown slip black, incised decoration, Northern Song Dynasty, 12th century]]
During the 11th century, political rivalries thoroughly divided members of the court due to the ministers' differing approaches, opinions, and policies regarding the handling of the Song's complex society and thriving economy. The idealist [[Chancellor of China|Chancellor]], [[Fan Zhongyan]] (989–1052), was the first to receive a heated political backlash when he attempted to make such reforms as improving the recruitment system of officials, increasing the salaries for minor officials, and establishing sponsorship programs to allow a wider range of people to be well educated and eligible for state service.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 163&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=163}}.&lt;/ref&gt; After Fan was forced to step down from his office, [[Wang Anshi]] (1021–1086) became Chancellor of the imperial court. With the backing of [[Emperor Shenzong of Song|Emperor Shenzong]] (1067–1085), Wang Anshi severely criticized the educational system and state bureaucracy. Seeking to resolve what he saw as state corruption and negligence, Wang implemented a series of reforms called the New Policies. These involved [[land tax]] reform, the establishment of several government [[monopolies]], the support of local [[militia]]s, and the creation of higher standards for the Imperial examination to make it more practical for men skilled in  statecraft to pass.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 164&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=164}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The reforms created political factions in the court. Wang Anshi's New Policies Group (Xin Fa), also known as the 'Reformers', were opposed by the ministers in the 'Conservative' faction led by the historian and Chancellor [[Sima Guang]] (1019–1086).&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 3 4&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|pp=3–4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  As one faction supplanted another in the majority position of the court ministers, it would demote rival officials and exile them to govern remote frontier regions of the empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 164&quot;/&gt;  One of the prominent victims of the political rivalry, the famous poet and statesman [[Su Shi]] (1037–1101), was jailed and eventually exiled for criticizing Wang's reforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 164&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Liao Dynasty - Guan Yin statue.jpg|alt=A wooden carving of a sitting Buddhist figure in loose fitting, painted robes.|thumb|upright|A [[Liao Dynasty]] [[polychrome]] wood-carved statue of [[Guan Yin]], [[Shanxi Province]], China, (907–1125)]]
While the central Song court remained politically divided and focused upon its internal affairs, alarming new events to the north in the Liao state finally came to its attention. The [[Jurchens|Jurchen]], a subject tribe within the Liao empire, rebelled against the Liao and formed their own state, the [[Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)|Jin Dynasty]] (1115–1234).&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 165&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=165}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Song official [[Tong Guan]] (1054–1126) advised [[Emperor Huizong of Song|Emperor Huizong]] (1100–1125) to [[Alliance on the Sea|form an alliance with the Jurchens]], and their joint military campaign toppled and completely conquered the Liao Dynasty by 1125. However, the poor performance and military weakness of the Song army was observed by the Jurchens who immediately broke the alliance with the Song, launching an invasion into Song territory in 1125 and another in 1127; in this latter invasion, the Jurchens captured not only the Song capital at Kaifeng, but the retired emperor Huizong, his successor [[Emperor Qinzong of Song|Qinzong]], and most of the Imperial court.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 165&quot;/&gt; This took place in the year of Jingkang ([[Chinese language|Chinese]] 靖康) and it is known as the [[Humiliation of Jingkang]] ([[Chinese language|Chinese]] 靖康之恥). The remaining Song forces regrouped under the self-proclaimed [[Emperor Gaozong of Song|Emperor Gaozong]] (1127–1162), and withdrew south of the [[Yangtze River]] to establish the Song Dynasty's new capital at Lin'an (in modern [[Hangzhou]]). The Jurchen conquest of northern China and shift of capitals from Kaifeng to Lin'an was the dividing line between the Northern Song Dynasty and Southern Song Dynasty.

=== Southern Song, 1127–1279 ===
[[File:China 11b.jpg|alt=A map showing the territory of the Song Dynasty after suffering losses to the Jin Dynasty. The western and southern borders remain unchanged from the previous map, however the northernmost third of the Song's previous territory is now under control of the Jin. The Xia dynasty's territory remains unchanged. In the southwest, the Song Dynasty is bordered by a territory about a sixth its size, Nanchao.|left|thumb|Southern Song in 1142]]
Although weakened and pushed south along the [[Huai River]], the Southern Song found new ways to bolster its strong economy and defend its own state against the Jin Dynasty. They had able military officers such as [[Yue Fei]] and [[Han Shizhong]]. The government sponsored massive [[shipbuilding]] and [[harbor]] improvement projects, and the construction of [[beacon]]s and seaport [[warehouse]]s  in order to support maritime trade abroad and the major international [[seaport]]s, such as [[Quanzhou]], [[Guangzhou]], and [[Xiamen]], that were sustaining China's commerce.&lt;ref name=&quot;wang 2000 14&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wang|2000|p=14}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 5&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|p=5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;paludan 1998 136&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Paludan|1998|p=136}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  To protect and support the multitudes of ships sailing for maritime interests into the waters of the [[East China Sea]] and [[Yellow Sea]] (to [[Korea]] and [[Japan]]), [[Southeast Asia]], the [[Indian Ocean]], and the [[Red Sea]], it was a necessity to establish an official standing [[navy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;shen 1996 159–161&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Shen|1996|pp=159–161}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Song Dynasty therefore established China's first permanent navy in 1132,&lt;ref name=&quot;paludan 1998 136&quot;/&gt; with a headquarters at Dinghai.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 476&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=476}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  With a permanent navy, the Song were prepared to face the naval forces of the Jin on the Yangtze River in 1161, in the [[Battle of Tangdao]] and the [[Battle of Caishi]]. During these battles the Song navy employed swift [[Paddle wheel ship#East Asia|paddle wheel driven]] naval vessels armed with [[trebuchet|trebuchet catapults]] aboard the decks that launched gunpowder [[bomb]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 476&quot;/&gt;  Although the Jin forces boasted 70,000 men on 600 warships, and the Song forces only 3,000 men on 120 warships,&lt;ref name=&quot;levathes 1994 43 47&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Levathes|1994|pp=43–47}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the Song Dynasty forces were victorious in both battles due to the destructive power of the bombs and the rapid assaults by paddle wheel ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 1 134&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986a|p=134}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The strength of the navy was heavily emphasized after that. A century after the navy was founded it had grown in size to 52,000 fighting marines.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 476&quot;/&gt; The Song government confiscated portions of land owned by the landed gentry in order to raise revenue for these projects, an act which caused dissension and loss of loyalty amongst leading members of Song society but did not stop the Song's defensive preparations.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 239&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=239}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;embree 1997 385&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Embree|Gluck|1997|p=385}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Adshead|2004|pp=90–91}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Financial matters were made worse by the fact that many wealthy, land-owning families—some which had officials working for the government—used their social connections with those in office in order to obtain tax-exempt status.&lt;ref name=&quot;rossabi 1988 80&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=80}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Wood Bodhisattva 2.jpg|alt=A wooden carving of a slightly overweight Buddha, sitting in a cross legged position. Clothing, including a shirt that covers the shoulders but leaves the chest exposed, and long, baggy pants, are carved into the statue.|thumb|upright|A seated wooden [[Bodhisattva]] statue, [[Jin Dynasty, 1115–1234|Jin Dynasty]] (1115–1234)]]
Although the Song Dynasty was able to hold back the Jin, a new considerable foe came to power over the steppe, deserts, and plains north of the Jin Dynasty. The [[Mongols]], led by [[Genghis Khan]] (r. 1206–1227), initially invaded the Jin Dynasty in 1205 and 1209, engaging in large raids across its borders, and in 1211 an enormous Mongol army was assembled to invade the Jin.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 235&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=235}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Jin Dynasty was forced to submit and pay tribute to the Mongols as [[vassal]]s; when the Jin suddenly moved their capital city from [[Beijing]] to Kaifeng, the Mongols saw this as a revolt.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 236&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=236}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Under the leadership of [[Ögedei Khan]] (r.1229–1241), both the Jin Dynasty and Western Xia Dynasty were conquered by  Mongol forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 236&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 1 139&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986a|p=139}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mongols also invaded [[Mongol invasions of Korea|Korea]], the [[Battle of Baghdad (1258)|Abbasid Caliphate]] of the Middle East, and [[Mongol invasion of Rus|Kievan Rus']]. The Mongols were at one time allied with the Song, but this alliance was broken when the Song recaptured the former imperial capitals of Kaifeng, [[Luoyang]] and [[Chang'an]] at the collapse of the Jin Dynasty. The Mongol leader [[Möngke Khan]] led a campaign against the Song in 1259, but died on August 11 during the [[Fishing Town|Battle of Fishing Town]] in [[Chongqing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 240&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=240}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Möngke's death and the ensuing succession crisis prompted [[Hulagu Khan]] to pull the bulk of the Mongol forces out of the Middle East where they were poised to fight the [[Bahri dynasty|Egyptian Mamluks]] (who defeated the Mongols at [[Battle of Ain Jalut|Ain Jalut]]). Although Hulagu was allied with [[Kublai Khan]], his forces were unable to help in the assault against the Song, due to Hulagu's war with the [[Golden Horde]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|pp=55–56}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kublai continued the assault against the Song, gaining a temporary foothold on the southern banks of the Yangtze.&lt;ref name=&quot;rossabi 1988 49&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=49}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Kublai made preparations to take [[Ezhou]], but a pending civil war with his brother [[Ariq Böke]]—a rival claimant to the Mongol Khaganate—forced Kublai to move with the bulk of his forces back north.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|pp=50–51}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In Kublai's absence, the Song forces were ordered by Chancellor Jia Sidao to make an opportune assault, and succeeded in pushing the Mongol forces back to the northern banks of the Yangzi.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=56}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There were minor border skirmishes until 1265, when Kublai won a significant battle in Sichuan.&lt;ref name=&quot;rossabi 1988 82&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=82}}.&lt;/ref&gt; From 1268 to 1273, Kublai blockaded the Yangzi River with his navy and [[Battle of Xiangyang|besieged Xiangyang]], the last obstacle in his way to invading the rich Yangzi River basin.&lt;ref name=&quot;rossabi 1988 82&quot;/&gt; Kublai officially declared the creation of the [[Yuan Dynasty]] in 1271. In 1275, a Song force of 130,000 troops under Chancellor [[Jia Sidao]] was defeated by Kublai's newly appointed commander-in-chief, general [[Bayan of the Baarin|Bayan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=88}}.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1276, most of the Song territory had been captured by Yuan forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 1 139&quot;/&gt;  In the [[Battle of Yamen]] on the [[Pearl River Delta]] in 1279, the Yuan army, led by the general [[Zhang Hongfan]], finally crushed the Song resistance. The last remaining ruler, the 8-year-old emperor [[Emperor Bing of Song|Emperor Huaizong of Song]] committed suicide, along with Prime Minister [[Lu Xiufu]] &lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=94}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and 800 members of the royal clan. On Kublai's orders, carried out by his commander Bayan, the rest of the former imperial family of Song were unharmed; the deposed [[Emperor Gong of Song|Emperor Gong]] was demoted, being given the title 'Duke of Ying', but was eventually exiled to [[Tibet]] where he took up a monastic life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=90}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Society and culture ==
{{main|Society of the Song Dynasty|Culture of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Chinesischer Maler des 12. Jahrhunderts (I) 001.jpg|alt=A square painting of a branch with a cluster of white flowers at the end. The branch is superimposed over a red square with rounded edges.|thumb|left|''The White Jasmine Branch'', early 12th century painting; small paintings in the style of round-albums that captured realistic scenes of nature were widely popular in the Southern Song period.]]
The Song Dynasty (or Sung Dynasty)&lt;ref&gt;[http://afe.easia.columbia.edu/song/ ''China in 1000 CE: The Most Advanced Society in the World'', in Ebrey, Patricia, &amp; Conrad Schirokauer, consultants, ''The Song Dynasty in China (960-1279): Life in the Song Seen through a 12th-century Scroll'' (&amp;#91;§&amp;#93; ''Asian Topics on Asia for Educators'') (Asia for Educators, Columbia Univ.)], as accessed October 6 &amp; 9, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; was an era of administrative sophistication and complex social organization. Some of the largest cities in the world were found in China during this period  (Kaifeng and Hangzhou had populations of over a million).&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 167&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank goldman 1992 89&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fairbank|Goldman|2006|p=89}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  People enjoyed various social clubs and  entertainment in the cities, and there were many schools and temples to provide the people with education and religious services.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 167&quot;/&gt;  The Song government supported multiple forms of [[social welfare]] programs, including the establishment of [[retirement home]]s, public [[clinic]]s, and [[pauper]]'s [[graveyard]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 167&quot;/&gt;  The Song Dynasty supported a widespread [[Postal administration|postal service]] that was modeled on the earlier [[Han Dynasty]] (202 BC – AD 220) postal system to provide swift communication throughout the empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 35&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=35}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The central government employed thousands of postal workers of various ranks and responsibilities to provide service for post offices and larger postal stations.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 36&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=36}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In rural areas, farming peasants either [[landowner|owned their own plots of land]], paid rents as [[tenant farmer]]s, or were [[serf]]s on large estates.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 155&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|1999|p=155}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although women were on a lower social tier than men (according to [[Confucianism|Confucian ethics]]), they enjoyed many social and legal privileges and wielded considerable power at home and in  their own small businesses. As Song society became more and more prosperous and parents on the bride's side of the family provided larger [[dowry|dowries]] for her marriage, women naturally gained many new legal rights in ownership of property.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 158&quot;/&gt; They were also equal in status to men in [[inheritance|inheriting family property]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|pp=170–171}}&lt;/ref&gt;  There were many notable and well-educated women and it was a common practice for women to educate their sons during their earliest youth.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 171&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=71}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|p=1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The mother of the scientist, general, diplomat, and statesman Shen Kuo taught him essentials of military strategy.&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 1&quot;/&gt; There were also exceptional women writers and poets such as [[Li Qingzhao]] (1084–1151), who became famous even in her lifetime.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 158&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|1999|p=158}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Huang Tingjian Fu Bo Shen Ci.jpg|alt=A landscape oriented parchment with twenty-one characters written vertically in seven columns.|thumb|right|[[Chinese calligraphy|Calligraphy]] of [[Huang Tingjian]] (1045–1105), a renowned calligrapher and associate of [[Su Shi]]]]
[[Religion in China]] during this period  had a great effect on people's lives, beliefs and  daily activities, and [[Chinese literature]] on spirituality was popular.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al. 2006 172&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=172}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The major deities of [[Daoism]] and [[Buddhism]], [[ancestor worship|ancestral spirits]] and the many deities of [[Chinese folk religion]] were worshiped with sacrificial offerings. Tansen Sen asserts that more [[Bhikkhu|Buddhist monks]] from [[India]] traveled to China during the Song than in the previous [[Tang Dynasty]] (618–907).&lt;ref name=&quot;sen 2003 13&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sen|2003|p=13}}.&lt;/ref&gt; With many ethnic foreigners traveling to China to conduct trade or live permanently, there came many foreign religions; religious minorities in China included [[Islam during the Song Dynasty|Middle Eastern Muslims]], the [[Kaifeng Jews]], and [[Manichaeism|Persian Manichaeans]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|pp=82–83}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Needham, Volume 4, Part 3, 465.&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=465}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The populace engaged in a vibrant social and domestic life, enjoying such public festivals as the [[Lantern Festival]] or the [[Qingming Festival]]. There were entertainment quarters in the cities provided a constant array of amusements. There were puppeteers, acrobats, theater actors, sword swallowers, snake charmers, [[Chinese folklore|storytellers]], singers and musicians, prostitutes, and places to relax including tea houses, restaurants, and organized banquets.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 167&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=167}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;China&quot;&gt;{{Citation |last= |first= |year=2007 |title=China |work=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]] |url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-71718/China |accessdate=June 28, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 222–225.&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|pp=222–225}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  People attended social clubs in large numbers; there were tea clubs, exotic food clubs, [[antiquarian]] and art collectors' clubs, horse-loving clubs, poetry clubs and music clubs.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 167&quot;/&gt; Like regional cooking and cuisines in the Song, the era was known for its regional varieties of performing arts styles as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;west 1997 69 70&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|West|1997|pp=69–70}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chinese opera|Theatrical drama]] was very popular amongst the elite and general populace, although [[Classical Chinese]]—not [[Vernacular Chinese|the vernacular language]]—was spoken by actors on stage.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 223&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|p=223}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=162}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The four largest drama theatres in Kaifeng could hold audiences of several thousand each.&lt;ref name=&quot;west 1997 76&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|West|1997|p=76}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There were also notable domestic pastimes, as people at home enjoyed activities such as the [[go board game|go]] and [[xiangqi]] board games.

=== Roles of Women ===
{{main|Society of the Song Dynasty}}
In the [[Song Dynasty]] men were more important than women. However, women could own land. There was also the practice of [[foot binding]], which only happened to women.

=== Civil service examinations and the gentry ===
{{main|Society of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Chinesischer Maler des 11. Jahrhunderts (III) 001.jpg|alt=A long, portrait oriented painting of a bare-chested, bearded man sitting on a mat under a tree, reading.|thumb|left|''Scholar in a Meadow'', [[Chinese painting]] of the 11th century]]
During this period greater emphasis was laid upon the [[civil service]] system of recruiting officials; this was based upon degrees acquired through competitive [[Imperial examination|examinations]], in an effort to select the most capable individuals for governance. Selecting men for office through proven merit [[Xiaolian|was an ancient idea in China]]. The civil service system became institutionalized on a small scale during the [[Sui Dynasty|Sui]] and [[Tang Dynasty|Tang]] dynasties, but by the Song period it became virtually the only means for drafting officials into the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 145 146&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|1999|pp=145–146}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The advent of widespread [[printing]] helped to widely circulate Confucian teachings and to educate more and more eligible candidates for the exams.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 147&quot;/&gt; This can be seen in the number of exam takers for the low-level prefectural exams rising from 30,000 annual candidates in the early 11th century to 400,000 candidates by the late 13th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 147&quot;/&gt; The civil service and examination system allowed for greater [[meritocracy]], [[social mobility]], and equality in competition for those wishing to attain an official seat in government.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 162&quot;/&gt;  By using Song state-gathered statistics, Edward A. Kracke, Sudō Yoshiyuki, and Ho Ping-ti supported the hypothesis that simply because one had a father, grandfather, or great-grandfather who had served as an official of state, it did not guarantee that one would obtain the same level of authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 162&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=162}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hartwell 1982 417&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hartwell|1982|pp=417–418}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hymes 1986 35 36&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hymes|1986|pp=35–36}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Robert Hartwell and Robert P. Hymes criticized this model, stating that it places too much emphasis on the role of the [[nuclear family]] and demonstrates only three paternal ascendants of exam candidates while ignoring the demographic reality of Song China, the significant proportion of males in each generation that had no surviving sons, and the role of the [[extended family]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hartwell 1982 417&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hymes 1986 35 36&quot;/&gt; Many felt disenfranchised by what they saw as a bureaucratic system that favored the land-holding class able to afford the best education.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 162&quot;/&gt;  One of the greatest literary critics of this was the official and famous poet [[Su Shi]]. Yet Su was a product of his times, as the identity, habits, and attitudes of the [[Scholar-bureaucrats|scholar-official]] had become less [[Aristocracy (class)|aristocrat]]ic and more [[bureaucrat]]ic with the transition of the periods from Tang to Song.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 159&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=159}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of the dynasty, government posts were disproportionately held by two elite social groups: a founding elite who had ties with the founding emperor and a semi-hereditary professional elite who used long-held clan status, [[Chinese kinship|family connections]] and marriage alliances to secure appointments.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hartwell|1982|pp=405–413}}.&lt;/ref&gt; By the late 11th century, the founding elite became obsolete while political partisanship and factionalism at court undermined the marriage strategies of the professional elite, which dissolved as a distinguishable social group and was replaced by a multitude of gentry families.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hartwell|1982|pp=416–420}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Porcelaine chinoise Guimet 241101.jpg|alt=Five pieces of pale green pottery. From left to right, a cylindrical bowl with a large, flat rim, a vase with a long, thin stem and a short, almost spherical body, a tall, thin glass, a wider vase with no stem, and a small opening at the top, and a vase with a long, but wide stem and an almost spherical body.|thumb|[[Longquan celadon]] wares from [[Zhejiang]], 13th century]]
[[File:Wang Juzheng's Spinning Wheel.jpg|alt=An older woman sits in front of a machine consisting of a vertically aligned wheel composed of about two dozen flat wooden spokes, with a string for an outside rim. The wheel is held up by a simple wooden pole stand. Two other older women watch the first.|thumb|''The Spinning Wheel'', a painting created by Northern Song artist Wang Juzheng, is one of the earliest representations of the invention]]
Due to China's enormous population growth and the body of its appointed scholar-officials being accepted in limited size (about 20,000 active officials during the Song period), the larger scholarly [[Gentry (China)|gentry class]] would now take over grassroots affairs on the vast local level.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank goldman 1992 106&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fairbank|Goldman|2006|p=106}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Excluding the scholar-officials in office, this elite social class consisted of exam candidates, examination degree-holders not yet assigned to an official post, local tutors, and retired officials.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank goldman 1992 101 106&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fairbank|Goldman|2006|pp=101–106}}.&lt;/ref&gt; These learned men, degree-holders, and local elites supervised local affairs and sponsored necessary facilities of local communities; any local magistrate appointed to his office by the government relied upon the cooperation of the few or many local gentry elites in the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank goldman 1992 106&quot;/&gt; For example, the Song government—excluding the educational-reformist government under Emperor Huizong—spared little amount of state revenue to maintain [[Zhou (country subdivision)|prefectural]] and [[County (People's Republic of China)|county]] schools; instead, the bulk of the funds for schools was drawn from private financing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Yuan|1994|pp=196–199}}&lt;/ref&gt; This limited role of government officials was a departure from the earlier Tang Dynasty (618–907), when the government strictly regulated commercial markets and local affairs; now the government withdrew heavily from regulating commerce and relied upon a mass of local gentry to perform necessary duties in local communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank goldman 1992 106&quot;/&gt;

The gentry distinguished themselves in society through their intellectual and antiquarian pursuits,&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 162 163&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|pp=162–163}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 148&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank goldman 1992 104&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fairbank|Goldman|2006|p=104}}.&lt;/ref&gt; while the homes of prominent landholders attracted a variety of [[courtier]]s including artisans, artists, educational tutors, and entertainers.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 92 93&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|pp=92–93}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the disdain for trade, commerce, and the merchant class exhibited by the highly cultured and elite exam-drafted scholar-officials, [[commercialism]] played a prominent role in Song culture and society.&lt;ref name=&quot;China&quot;/&gt; A scholar-official would be frowned upon by his peers if he pursued means of profiteering outside of his official salary; however, this did not stop many scholar-officials from managing business relations through the use of intermediary agents.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|pp=60–61, 68–69}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Law, justice, and forensic science ===
{{main|Society of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Chinesischer Maler des 12. Jahrhunderts (II) 001.jpg|alt=A painting of a play being staged in a courtyard. In the center, a man in loose black robes appears in mid-bow or mid-dance. To the left, two men dressed as guards are holding a third man, dressed in the same attire as the man in the center. To the right, a heavy set man sits in a throne. Behind him stand three women in white face paint and a man dressed in the same attire as the man in the center.|right|thumb|''The Broken Balustrade'', early 12th century painting]]
The Song [[Judiciary|judicial system]] retained most of the [[legal code]] of the earlier Tang Dynasty, the basis of [[traditional Chinese law]] up until the modern era.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 161&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=161}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Roving sheriffs maintained law and order in the municipal jurisdictions and occasionally ventured into the countryside.&lt;ref name=&quot;McKnight 1992 155 157&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|McKnight|1992|pp=155–157}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Official magistrates overseeing court cases were not only expected to be well-versed in written law but also to promote morality in society.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 161&quot;/&gt;  Magistrates such as the famed [[Bao Qingtian]] (999–1062) embodied the upright, moral judge who upheld justice and never failed to live up to his principles. Song judges specified the guilty person or party in a criminal act and meted out punishments accordingly, often in the form of [[caning]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 161&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 107&quot;/&gt; A guilty individual or parties brought to court for a criminal or civil offense were not viewed as wholly innocent until proven otherwise, while even accusers were viewed with a high level of suspicion by the judge.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 107&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|p=107}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to costly court expenses and immediate jailing of those accused of criminal offenses, people in the Song preferred to settle disputes and quarrels privately, without the court's interference.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 107&quot;/&gt;

Shen Kuo's ''[[Dream Pool Essays]]'' argued against traditional Chinese beliefs in [[anatomy]] (such as his argument for two throat valves instead of three); this perhaps spurred the interest in the performance of post-mortem [[autopsy|autopsies]] in China during the 12th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 30 31&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|pp=30–31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 30 31 footnote&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|pp=30–31, footnote 27}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The physician and judge known as [[Song Ci]] (1186–1249) wrote [[Collected Cases of Injustice Rectified|a pioneering work]] of [[forensic science]] on the examination of [[corpse]]s in order to determine cause of death (strangulation, poisoning, drowning, blows, etc.) and to prove whether death resulted from murder, suicide, or accidental death.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 170&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|p=170}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Song Ci stressed the importance of proper [[coroner]]'s conduct during autopsies and the accurate recording of the [[inquest]] of each autopsy by official clerks.&lt;ref name=&quot;sung 1981 12&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sung|1981|pp=12, 72}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Military and methods of warfare ===
{{main|Society of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Four Generals of Song.jpg|alt=A long, landscape oriented painting of eight figures. From left to right, the first, third, fifth, sixth, and eighth people are armed, with the first and last men most heavily armed, carrying both a bow and a sword, with the other three carrying either a bow or a sword but not both. Each of the men wears a thin, flat, black cap. The third and sixth figure are also a head shorter than the rest of the figures.|thumb|right|300px|&quot;Four Generals of Zhongxing&quot; by Southern Song Dynasty artist Liu Songnian (1174–1224); the renowned general [[Yue Fei]] (1103–1142) is the second person from the left.]]
The Song military was chiefly organized to ensure that the army could not threaten Imperial control, often at the expense of effectiveness in war.  Northern Song's Military Council operated under a Chancellor, who had no control over the imperial army.  The imperial army was divided among three marshals, each independently responsible to the Emperor.  Since the Emperor rarely led campaigns personally, Song forces lacked unity of command.&lt;ref&gt;Bai Shouyi, 2002, pp239&lt;/ref&gt;  The imperial court often believed that successful generals endangered royal authority, and relieved or even executed them (notably Li Gang,&lt;ref&gt;Bai Shouyi, 2002, pp250&lt;/ref&gt; [[Yue Fei]], and [[Han Shizhong]].&lt;ref&gt;Bai Shouyi, 2002, p254&lt;/ref&gt;)

Although the scholar-officials viewed [[Military history of China (pre-1911)|military soldiers]] as lower members in the hierarchic social order,&lt;ref name=&quot;graff higham 2002 25 26&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Graff|Higham|2002|pp=25–26}}.&lt;/ref&gt; a person could gain status and prestige in society by becoming a high-ranking military officer with a record of victorious battles.&lt;ref name=&quot;lorge 2005 43&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lorge|2005|p=43}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  At its height, the Song military had one million soldiers&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 164&quot;/&gt; divided into [[platoon]]s of 50 troops, companies made of two platoons, and one battalion composed of 500 soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;lorge 2005 45&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lorge|2005|p=45}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;peers 2006 130&quot;/&gt;  [[Crossbow]]men were separated from the regular infantry and placed in their own units as they were prized combatants, providing effective missile fire against cavalry charges.&lt;ref name=&quot;peers 2006 130&quot;/&gt;  The government was eager to sponsor new crossbow designs that could shoot at longer ranges, while crossbowmen were also valuable when employed as long-range [[sniper]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;peers 2006 130 131&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Peers|2006|pp=130–131}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Song cavalry employed a slew of different weapons, including halberds, swords, bows, spears, and '[[fire lance]]s' that discharged a gunpowder blast of flame and [[Fragmentation (weaponry)|shrapnel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;peers 2006 131&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Peers|2006|p=131}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Military strategy and military training were treated as science that could be studied and perfected; soldiers were tested in their skills of using weaponry and in their athletic ability.&lt;ref name=&quot;peers 2006 129&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Peers|2006|p=129}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The troops were trained to follow signal standards to advance at the waving of banners and to halt at the sound of bells and drums.&lt;ref name=&quot;peers 2006 130&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Peers|2006|p=130}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Song navy was of great importance during the consolidation of the empire in the 10th century; during the war against the [[Southern Tang]] state the Song navy employed tactics such as defending large floating [[pontoon bridge]]s across the [[Yangtze River|Yangzi River]] in order to secure movements of troops and supplies.&lt;ref name=&quot;graff higham 2002 87&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Graff|Higham|2002|p=87}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  There were large naval ships in the Song that could carry 1,000 soldiers aboard their decks,&lt;ref name=&quot;graff higham 2002 86 87&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Graff|Higham|2002|pp=86–87}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  while the swift-moving [[Paddle steamer|paddle-wheel crafts]] were viewed as essential fighting ships in any successful naval battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;graff higham 2002 86 87&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 422&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=422}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In a battle on January 23, 971, massive arrow fire from Song Dynasty crossbowmen decimated the [[war elephant]] corps of the [[Southern Han]] army.&lt;ref name=&quot;schafer 1957 291&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Schafer|1957|p=291}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This defeat not only marked the eventual submission of the Southern Han to the Song Dynasty, but also the last instance where a war elephant corps was employed as a regular division within a Chinese army.&lt;ref name=&quot;schafer 1957 291&quot;/&gt;

There was a total of 347 military treatises written during the Song period, as listed by the history text of the ''Song Shi'' (compiled in 1345).&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 19&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|p=19}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, only a handful of these military treatises have survived, which includes the ''[[Wujing Zongyao]]'' written in 1044. It was the first known book to have listed formulas for gunpowder;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 119&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|p=119}}.&lt;/ref&gt; it gave appropriate formulas for use in several different kinds of gunpowder bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 122 124&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=122–124}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It also provided detailed description and illustrations of double-piston pump [[flamethrower]]s, as well as instructions for the maintenance and repair of the components and equipment used in the device.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 82 84&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=82–84}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Arts, literature, and philosophy ===
{{main|Culture of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Wood Bodhisattva.jpg|alt=A wooden carving of a female human figure, sitting with one knee on the ground and one knee pointing up, with a hand resting on that knee. The carving includes loose fitting clothing, which is covered mainly in gold foil.|right|thumb|A wooden [[Bodhisattva]] statue from the Song Dynasty (960–1279)]]
The visual arts during the Song Dynasty were heightened by new developments such as advances in landscape  and portrait painting. The gentry elite engaged in the arts as  accepted pastimes of the cultured scholar-official, including  [[Chinese painting|painting]], composing [[Chinese poetry|poetry]], and writing [[Chinese calligraphy|calligraphy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 81 83&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|pp=81–83}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The poet and statesman Su Shi and his associate [[Mi Fu]] (1051–1107) enjoyed antiquarian affairs, often borrowing or buying art pieces to study and copy.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 163&quot;/&gt;  Poetry and [[Chinese literature|literature]] profited from the rising popularity and development of the [[ci (poetry)|ci poetry form]]. Enormous encyclopedic volumes were compiled, such as works of [[Chinese historiography|historiography]] and dozens of treatises on technical subjects. This included the [[universal history]] text of the ''[[Zizhi Tongjian]]'', compiled into 1000 volumes of 9.4 million written [[Chinese character]]s. The  genre of Chinese [[travel literature]] also became popular with the writings of the geographer [[Fan Chengda]] (1126–1193) and Su Shi, the latter of whom wrote the 'daytrip essay' known as ''[[Su Shi#Travel record literature|Record of Stone Bell Mountain]]'' that used [[persuasive writing]] to argue for a philosophical point.&lt;ref name=&quot;hargett 1985 74 76&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hargett|1985|pp=74–76}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Although an early form of the local geographic [[gazetteer]] existed in China since the 1st century, the matured form known as &quot;treatise on a place&quot;, or ''fangzhi'', replaced the old &quot;map guide&quot;, or ''tujing'', during the Song Dynasty.&lt;ref name=&quot;bol 2001 44&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Bol|2001|p=44}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The imperial courts of the emperor's palace  were filled with his entourage of court painters, calligraphers, poets, and storytellers. [[Emperor Huizong of Song|Emperor Huizong]] was  a renowned artist as well as a patron of the arts. A prime example of a highly venerated court painter was [[Zhang Zeduan]] (1085–1145) who painted an enormous [[panoramic painting]], ''[[Along the River During the Qingming Festival]]''. [[Emperor Gaozong of Song]] initiated a massive art project during his reign, known as the ''[[Eighteen Songs of a Nomad Flute]]'' from the life story of [[Cai Wenji]] (b. 177). This art project was a diplomatic gesture to the Jin Dynasty while he negotiated for the release of his mother from Jurchen captivity in the north.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 151&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|1999|p=151}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Chinesischer Maler von 1238 001.jpg|alt=A portrait of an older, balding man in a half pale green and half sky blue robe. He is sitting on an armchair holding a thin wooden stick, possibally a folded up fan.|thumb|left|upright|Portrait of the [[Zen]] Buddhist monk [[Wuzhun Shifan]], painted in 1238.]]
In [[Chinese philosophy|philosophy]], [[Chinese Buddhism]] had waned in influence but it retained its hold on the arts and on the charities of monasteries. Buddhism had a profound influence upon the budding movement of [[Neo-Confucianism]], led by  [[Cheng Yi (philosopher)|Cheng Yi]] (1033–1107) and [[Zhu Xi]] (1130–1200).&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 168&quot;/&gt;  [[Mahayana]] Buddhism influenced Fan Zhongyan and Wang Anshi through its concept of [[ethical]] [[universalism]],&lt;ref name=&quot;wright 1959 93&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wright|1959|p=93}}.&lt;/ref&gt; while Buddhist [[metaphysics]] had a deep impact upon the pre–Neo-Confucian doctrine of Cheng Yi.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 168&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=168}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The philosophical work of Cheng Yi in turn influenced Zhu Xi. Although his writings were not accepted by his contemporary peers, Zhu's commentary and emphasis upon the Confucian classics of the [[Four Books]] as an introductory corpus to Confucian learning formed the basis of the Neo-Confucian doctrine. By the year 1241, under the sponsorship of [[Emperor Lizong of Song|Emperor Lizong]], Zhu Xi's Four Books and his commentary on them became standard requirements of study for students attempting to pass the civil service examinations.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 169&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=169}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The East Asian countries of [[Japan]] and [[Korea]] also adopted Zhu Xi's teaching, known as the Shushigaku (朱子學, School of Zhu Xi) of Japan, and in Korea the Jujahak (주자학). Buddhism's continuing influence can be seen in painted artwork such as [[Lin Tinggui]]'s ''[[Arhat|Luohan]] Laundering''. However, the ideology was highly criticized and even scorned by some. The statesman and historian [[Ouyang Xiu]] (1007–1072) called the religion a &quot;curse&quot; that could only be remedied by uprooting it from [[Culture of China|Chinese culture]] and replacing it with Confucian discourse.&lt;ref name=&quot;wright 1959 88 89&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wright|1959|pp=88–89}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhism would not see a true revival in Chinese society until the Mongol rule of the Yuan Dynasty, with Kublai Khan's sponsorship of [[Tibetan Buddhism]] and [[Drogön Chögyal Phagpa]] as the leading [[lama]]. The [[Christianity|Christian]] sect of [[Nestorianism]]—which had entered China in the Tang era—would also be revived in China under Mongol rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 215&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|p=215}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cuisine and apparel ===
{{main|Culture of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Red lacquer tray with gold engraving, Song Dynasty.jpg|alt=A red, square tray with cut off corners. Inlaid into the tray in gold foil is a design depicting two birds perched on a branch of a large, lowering plant.|thumb|right|A red [[lacquerware]] food tray with gold foil engraving designs of two long-tailed birds and a peony, dated 12th to early 13th century.]]
[[Sumptuary law#China|Sumptuary laws]] regulated the food that one consumed and the clothes that one wore according to status and social class. The main food staples in the diet of the lower classes remained rice, pork, and salted fish.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 136&quot;/&gt; Clothing was made of hemp or cotton cloths, restricted to a color standard of black and white. Trousers were the acceptable attire for peasants, soldiers, artisans, and merchants, although wealthy merchants might choose to wear more ornate clothing and male blouses that came down below the waist. Acceptable apparel for scholar-officials was rigidly defined by social ranking system. However, as time went on this rule of rank-graded apparel for officials was not as strictly enforced. Each official was able to display his awarded status by wearing different-colored traditional [[Han Chinese clothing|silken robes]] that hung to the ground around his feet, specific types of headgear, and even specific styles of girdles that displayed his graded-rank of officialdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 127-130&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|pp=127–30}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Women wore long dresses, blouses that came down to the knee,  skirts and jackets with long or short sleeves, while women from wealthy families could wear purple scarves around their shoulders. The main difference in women's apparel from that of men was that it was fastened on the left, not on the right.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 129&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|p=129}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Song restaurant and tavern menus are recorded which list entrées for feasts, banquets, festivals, and carnivals. They reveal a diverse and lavish diet for those of the upper class. They could choose from a wide variety of meats and seafood, including shrimp, geese, duck, mussel, shellfish, [[fallow deer]], hare, partridge, pheasant, francolin, quail, fox, badger, clam, crab, and many others.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 134 137&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|pp=134–137}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rossabi 1988 78&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=78}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;west 1997 73&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|West|1997|p=73}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Dairy products were rare in Chinese cuisine at this time. Beef was rarely consumed since the bull was a valuable draft animal, and dog meat was absent from the diet of the wealthy, although the poor could choose to eat dog meat if necessary (yet it was not part of their regular diet).&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 135–136&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|pp=135–136}}.&lt;/ref&gt; People also consumed [[Date Palm|dates]], raisins, [[jujube]]s, pears, plums, apricots, pear juice, [[lychee]]-fruit juice, honey and ginger drinks,  [[papaya|pawpaw]] juice, spices and seasonings of [[Sichuan pepper]], [[ginger]], pimento, [[soy sauce]], [[Vegetable fats and oils|oil]], [[sesame oil]], salt, and vinegar.&lt;ref name=&quot;rossabi 1988 78&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;west 1997 86&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|West|1997|p=86}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The common diet of the poor was pork, salted fish, and rice.&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 136&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|p=134-137}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Economy, industry, and trade ==
{{main|Economy of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Qingming Festival 2.jpg|thumb|right|300px|alt=A long, horizontally aligned section of painting that details several large trading barges docked along a river. The barges have curved bottomed hull and vertical wooden walls that are topped in a line of roofing tiles, but do not have actual roofs. Only one of the ships has a mast, although all of the ships do have large rudders.|[[Junk (ship)|Chinese boats]] from [[Zhang Zeduan]]'s (1085–1145) painting ''[[Along the River During Qingming Festival]]''; Chinese ships of the Song period featured [[Hull (watercraft)|hulls]] with [[Bulkhead (partition)|watertight compartments]].]]
The economy  of the Song Dynasty was one of the most prosperous and advanced economies in the medieval world. Song Chinese invested their funds in [[joint stock company|joint stock companies]] and in multiple sailing vessels at a time when monetary gain was assured from the vigorous overseas trade and domestic trade along the [[Grand Canal (China)|Grand Canal]] and Yangzi River.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 157&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=157}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent merchant families and private businesses were allowed to occupy industries that were not already government-operated [[monopoly|monopolies]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 164&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 23&quot;/&gt; Both private and government-controlled industries met the needs of a growing Chinese population in the Song.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 164&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 23&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=23}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Both artisans and merchants formed [[guild]]s which the state had to deal with when assessing taxes, requisitioning goods, and setting standard worker's wages and prices on goods.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 157&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gernet 1962 88 94&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gernet|1962|pp=88, 94}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[iron industry]] was pursued by both private [[entrepreneur]]s who owned their own smelters as well as government-supervised smelting facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wagner 2001 178 179&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wagner|2001|pp=178–179, 181–183}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Song economy was stable enough to produce over a hundred million kilograms (over two hundred million pounds) of [[iron]] product a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 158&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=158}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Large-scale [[deforestation]] in China would have continued if not for the 11th century innovation of the use of [[coal]] instead of [[charcoal]] in  [[blast furnace]]s for smelting [[cast iron]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 158&quot;/&gt;  Much of this iron was reserved for  military  use in crafting weapons and armoring troops, but some was used to fashion the many  iron products needed to fill the demands of the growing domestic market. The iron trade within China was furthered by the building of new [[canal]]s which aided the flow of iron products from production centers to the large market found in the capital city.&lt;ref name=&quot;embree 1997 339&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Embree|Gluck|1997|p=339}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Song Dynasty Porcelain.jpg|alt=Three pieces of white porcelain. From left to right, a vase with a grooved, fat body, a short, thin stem, and small opening with a large flat rim extending from it, a simple bowl with a thin brown trim around the outside rim, and a container in the shape of a granary, with several viable support posts, a tiled roof, and a staircase leading to a door, all built into the piece.|thumb|right|''Left item'': A Northern Song qingbai-ware vase with a transparent blue-toned [[ceramic glaze]], from [[Jingdezhen]], 11th century; ''Center item'': A Northern or Southern Song qingbai-ware bowl with incised [[Nelumbo nucifera|lotus]] decorations, a metal rim, and a transparent blue-toned glaze, from Jingdezhen, 12th or 13th century; ''Right item'': A Southern Song [[scale model|miniature model]] of a [[granary]] with removable top lid and doorway, qingbai porcelain with transparent blue-toned glaze, Jingdezhen, 13th century.]]
The annual output of minted copper currency in 1085 alone reached roughly six billion coins.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 156&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|Walthall|Palais|2006|p=156}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The most notable advancement in the Song economy was the establishment of the world's first government issued paper-printed money, known as [[Jiaozi (currency)|Jiaozi]] (''see also [[Huizi (currency)|Huizi]]'').&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 156&quot;/&gt;  For the printing of [[banknote|paper money]] alone, the Song court established several government-run [[factories]] in the cities of [[Huizhou]], [[Chengdu]], [[Hangzhou]], and [[Anqi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 1 48&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|p=48}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The size of the workforce employed in  paper money factories was large; it was recorded in 1175 that the factory at Hangzhou employed more than a thousand workers a day.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 1 48&quot;/&gt;

The economic power of Song China heavily influenced foreign economies abroad. The [[Moroccan people|Moroccan]] [[geographer]] [[al-Idrisi]] wrote in 1154 of the prowess of Chinese merchant ships in the Indian Ocean and of their annual voyages that brought iron, swords, silk, velvet, porcelain, and various textiles to places such as [[Aden]] ([[Yemen]]), the [[Indus River]], and the [[Euphrates]] in modern-day Iraq.&lt;ref name=&quot;shen 1996 159–161&quot;/&gt;  Foreigners, in turn, had an impact on the Chinese economy. For example, many West Asian and Central Asian [[Muslim]]s went to [[China]] to trade, becoming a preeminent force in the import and export industry, while some were even appointed as officers supervising economic affairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Needham, Volume 4, Part 3, 465.&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | url = http://web.archive.org/web/20070208180239/www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/china_print.html | title = Islam in China (650–present): Origins | accessdate = 2007-08-01 | work = Religion &amp; Ethics - Islam | publisher = BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sea trade with the Southeast Pacific, the Hindu world, the Islamic world, and the East African world brought merchants great fortune and spurred an enormous growth in the [[shipbuilding]] industry of Song-era [[Fujian]] province.&lt;ref name=&quot;golas&quot;&gt;{{Citation |last=Golas |first=Peter |title=Rural China in the Song |journal=The Journal of Asian Studies |year=1980 |volume=39 |issue=2 |pages=291–325 |doi=10.2307/2054291 |jstor=2054291}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, there was risk involved in such long overseas ventures. It was to reduce the risk of losing money  on maritime trade missions abroad that, as the historians Ebrey, Walthall, and Palais write:

&lt;blockquote&gt;[Song era] investors usually divided their investment among many ships, and each ship had many investors behind it. One observer thought eagerness to invest in overseas trade was leading to an outflow of copper cash. He wrote, 'People along the coast are on intimate terms with the merchants who engage in overseas trade, either because they are fellow-countrymen or personal acquaintances....[They give the merchants] money to take with them on their ships for purchase and return conveyance of foreign goods. They invest from ten to a hundred strings of cash, and regularly make profits of several hundred percent'.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 159&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Technology, science, and engineering ==
{{main|Science and technology of the Song Dynasty|Architecture of the Song Dynasty}}
{{further|List of Chinese inventions|List of Chinese discoveries}}
[[File:Trebuchet1-intransit.jpg|alt=An ink on paper diagram of a trebuchet. A long arm with a spherical cap rests on top of a large square platform. The square platform is supported by four plain cut square beams, which connect to an open undercarriage. Rope hangs between the end of the pole that does not have the cap to the inside of the undercarriage, as far away from the start of the rope as possible. The assembly moves on four wheels attached to the sides of the undercarriage.|thumb|right|An illustration of a [[trebuchet]] catapult from the ''[[Wujing Zongyao]]'' manuscript of 1044. Trebuchets like this were used to launch the earliest type of explosive bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 117&quot;/&gt;]]

=== Gunpowder warfare ===
{{further|History of gunpowder}}
Advancements in weapons technology enhanced by gunpowder, including the evolution of the early [[flamethrower]], explosive [[grenade]], [[firearm]], [[cannon]], and [[land mine]], enabled the Song Chinese to ward off their militant enemies until the Song's ultimate collapse in the late 13th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 80&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|p=80}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 82&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|p=82}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 220–221&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=220–221}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 192&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|p=192}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rossabi|1988|p=79}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The ''[[Wujing Zongyao]]'' manuscript of 1044 was the first book in history to provide formulas for gunpowder and their specified use in different types of bombs.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 117&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|p=117}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  While engaged in a war with the [[Mongols]], in 1259 the official Li Zengbo wrote in his ''Kezhai Zagao, Xugaohou'' that the city of [[Qingzhou]] was manufacturing one to two thousand strong iron-cased bomb shells a month, dispatching to [[Xiangyang District, Xiangfan|Xiangyang]] and Yingzhou about ten to twenty thousand such bombs at a time.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 173 174&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=173–174}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  In turn, the invading Mongols employed northern Chinese soldiers and used these same type of gunpowder weapons against the Song.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 7 174 175&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=174–175}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  By the 14th century the firearm and cannon could also be found in Europe, India, and the Islamic Middle East, during the early age of [[gunpowder warfare]].

=== Measuring distance and mechanical navigation ===
[[History of the Han Dynasty|As early as the Han Dynasty]], when the state needed to effectively measure distances traveled throughout the empire, the Chinese relied on the mechanical [[odometer]] device.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 283&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=283}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese odometer came in the form of a wheeled-carriage, its inner gears functioning off the rotated motion of the wheels, and specific units of distance—the Chinese  [[li (unit)|li]]—marked by the mechanical striking of a drum or bell for auditory alarm.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 281–284&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|pp=281–282}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The  specifications for the 11th century odometer were written by Chief Chamberlain Lu Daolong, who is quoted extensively in the historical text of the ''Song Shi'' (compiled by 1345).&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 283 284&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|pp=283–284}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In the Song period, the odometer vehicle was also combined with another old complex mechanical device known as the [[South Pointing Chariot]].&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 291&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=291}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  This device, originally crafted by [[Ma Jun]] in the 3rd century, incorporated a [[differential (mechanical device)|differential gear]] that allowed a figure mounted on the vehicle to always point in the southern direction, no matter how the vehicle's wheels' turned about.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 287&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=287}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The device concept of the differential gear for this navigational vehicle is now found in all modern [[automobile]]s in order to apply the equal amount of [[torque]] to wheels rotating at different speeds.

=== Polymaths, inventions, and astronomy ===
{{Further|Chinese astronomy|List of Chinese inventions}}
[[File:Clock Tower from Su Song's Book.JPG|alt=A diagram of the interior of a clocktower. The clock mechanism has several large gears, however it is not apparent how they would receive stimulus to move.|thumb|upright|An interior diagram of the [[Astronomical clock|astronomical]] [[clocktower]] of [[Kaifeng]] featured in [[Su Song]]'s book, written by 1092 and published in printed form by the year 1094.]]
[[Polymath]] figures such as the statesmen [[Shen Kuo]] and [[Su Song]] (1020–1101) embodied advancements in all fields of study, including [[biology]], [[botany]], [[zoology]], [[geology]], [[mineralogy]], [[mechanics]], [[horology]], [[astronomy]], [[Traditional Chinese medicine|pharmaceutical medicine]], [[archeology]], [[mathematics]], [[cartography]], [[optics]], [[art criticism]], and more.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 148&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 1 136&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986a|p=136}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 446&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=446}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Shen Kuo was the first to discern [[magnetic declination]] of [[true north]] while experimenting with a compass.&lt;ref name=&quot;mohn 2003 1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Mohn|2003|p=1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;embree 1997 843&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Embree|Gluck|1997|p=843}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Shen theorized that geographical [[Climate change|climates gradually shifted]] over time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Chan|2002|p=15}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|p=614}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He created a theory of land formation involving concepts accepted in modern [[geomorphology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 23 24&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|pp=23–24}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He performed optical experiments with [[camera obscura]] just decades after [[Ibn al-Haytham]] was the first to do so.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 1 98&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=98}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He also improved the designs of astronomical instruments such as the widened astronomical [[Dream Pool Essays#Astronomy|sighting tube]], which allowed Shen Kuo to fix the position of the [[pole star]] (which had shifted over centuries of time).&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 17&quot;/&gt; Shen Kuo was also known for [[hydraulic]] clockworks, as he invented a new overflow-tank [[Water clock|clepsydra]] which had more efficient higher-order [[interpolation]] instead of linear interpolation in calibrating the measure of time.&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 17&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|p=17}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Su Song was best known for his horology treatise written in 1092, which described and illustrated in great detail his [[hydraulic]]-powered, {{convert|12|m|ft|abb=on}} tall [[astronomical clock|astronomical]] [[clock tower]] built in Kaifeng. The clock tower featured large astronomical instruments of the [[armillary sphere]] and [[celestial globe]], both driven by an early intermittently working [[escapement]] mechanism (roughly two centuries before the discrete [[verge escapement]] of true [[mechanical clock]]s appeared in [[Middle Ages|medieval]] [[clock]]works).&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 445&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=445}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 448&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=448}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Su Song's clock tower featured the world's first endless power-transmitting [[chain drive]],&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 111&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=111}}.&lt;/ref&gt; an essential mechanical device found in many practical uses throughout the ages, such as the [[bicycle]]. Su's tower featured a rotating gear wheel with 133 clock jack [[manikin]]s who were timed to rotate past shuttered windows while [[Striking clock|ringing gongs and bells, banging drums]], and presenting announcement plaques.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|pp=165, 445}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In his printed book, Su published a celestial atlas of five [[star chart]]s. These star charts feature a cylindrical projection similar to [[Mercator projection]], the latter being a cartographic innovation of [[Gerardus Mercator]] in 1569.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 569&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=569}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 3 208&quot;/&gt;

=== Mathematics and cartography ===
{{further|Chinese mathematics|Chinese geography}}
[[File:Song Dynasty Map.JPG|thumb|right|alt=An image, probably a printout of a photograph, of a map of eastern China, complete with rivers. The area of the map covered by land features a near perfect grid pattern, which because it does not overlap any text, is clearly the work of the original mapmaker.|The ''Yu Ji Tu'', or ''Map of the Tracks of Yu Gong'', carved into stone in 1137, located in the [[Stele Forest]] of [[Xi'an]]. This {{convert|3|ft|m|abbr=on}} squared map features a [[Scale (map)|graduated scale]] of 100 [[Li (unit)|li]] for each rectangular grid. China's coastline and river systems are clearly defined and precisely pinpointed on the map. [[Yu the Great|Yu Gong]] is in reference to the Chinese deity described in the [[History of geography#China|geographical chapter]] of the ''[[Classic of History]]'', dated 5th century BCE.]]
There were many notable improvements to [[Chinese mathematics]] during the Song era. The book published in 1261 by the mathematician [[Yang Hui]] (c. 1238–1298) provided the earliest Chinese illustration of [[Pascal's triangle]], although it was described earlier around 1100 by Jia Xian.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|pp=134–137}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Yang Hui also provided rules for constructing combinatorial arrangements in [[magic square]]s, provided theoretical proof for [[Euclid]]'s forty-third proposition about [[parallelogram]]s, and was the first to use negative coefficients of 'x' in [[quadratic equation]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|pp=46, 59–60, 104}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Yang's contemporary [[Qin Jiushao]] (c. 1202–1261) was the first to introduce the [[0 (number)|zero symbol]] into Chinese mathematics;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|p=43}}.&lt;/ref&gt; before this blank spaces were used instead of zeros in the system of [[counting rods]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|pp=62–63}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He is also known for working with the [[Chinese remainder theorem]], [[Heron's formula]], and astronomical data used in determining the [[winter solstice]]. Qin's major work was the ''[[Mathematical Treatise in Nine Sections]]'' published in 1247.

[[Geometry]] was essential to [[surveying]] and [[cartography]]. The [[Chinese cartography|earliest extant Chinese maps]] date to the 4th century BCE,&lt;ref name=&quot;hsu 1993 90 93&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hsu|1993|pp=90–93}}.&lt;/ref&gt; yet it was not until the time of [[Pei Xiu]] (224–271) that topographical [[elevation]], a formal [[Grid reference|rectangular grid]] system, and use of a standard graduated scale of distances was applied to terrain maps.&lt;ref name=&quot;hsu 1993 96 97&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Hsu|1993|pp=96–97}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 3 538 540&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|pp=538–540}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[List of Chinese inventions#R|Following a long tradition]], Shen Kuo created a [[raised-relief map]], while his other maps featured a uniform graduated scale of 1:900,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 22&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;temple 179&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Temple|1986|p=179}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A {{convert|3|ft|m|abbr=on}} squared map of 1137—carved into a stone block—followed a uniform grid scale of 100 li for each gridded square, and accurately mapped the outline of the coasts and river systems of China, extending all the way to India.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|pp=547–549, Plate LXXXI}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the world's oldest known terrain map in printed form comes from the edited encyclopedia of Yang Jia in 1155, which displayed western China without the formal grid system that was characteristic of more professionally made Chinese maps.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|pp=549, Plate LXXXII}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although [[gazetteer]]s had existed since 52 CE during the Han Dynasty and gazetteers accompanied by illustrative maps (Chinese: ''tujing'') since the Sui Dynasty, the illustrated gazetteer became much more common in the Song Dynasty, when the foremost concern was for illustrative gazetteers to serve political, administrative, and military purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hargett|1996|pp=406, 409–412}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Movable type printing ===
{{Further|History of printing in East Asia}}
[[File:Su Song Star Map 1.JPG|alt=A rectangular ink on paper diagram with several hundred dots, several of which are organized into constellations, such as a drawn bow (bottom center) and a tree (top left).|thumb|left|One of the [[star chart]]s from [[Su Song]]'s ''Xin Yi Xiang Fa Yao'' published in 1092, featuring cylindrical projection similar to [[Mercator projection]] and the corrected position of the [[pole star]] thanks to Shen Kuo's astronomical observations.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 569&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 3 208&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986b|p=208}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Su Song's celestial atlas of five star maps is actually the oldest in [[printing|printed]] form.&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 32&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|p=32}}.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The innovation of [[movable type]] printing was made by the artisan [[Bi Sheng]] (990–1051), first described by the scientist and statesman Shen Kuo in his ''[[Dream Pool Essays]]'' of 1088.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 5 part 1 201 203&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=201–203}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 27&quot;/&gt;  The collection of Bi Sheng's original clay-fired [[typeface]] was passed on to one of Shen Kuo's nephews, and was carefully preserved.&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 27&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|p=27}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 2 33&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986c|p=33}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Movable type enhanced the already widespread use of [[woodblock printing|woodblock methods of printing]] thousands of documents and volumes of written literature, consumed eagerly by an increasingly literate public. The advancement of printing had a deep impact on education and the scholar-official class, since more books could be made faster while mass-produced, printed books were cheaper in comparison to laborious handwritten copies.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 147&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|1999|p=147}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 159&quot;/&gt; The enhancement of widespread printing and [[print culture]] in the Song period was thus a direct [[catalyst]] in the rise of [[social mobility]] and expansion of the educated class of scholar elites, the latter which expanded dramatically in size from the 11th to 13th centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 147&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|2006|pp=159–160}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The movable type invented by Bi Sheng was ultimately trumped by the use of woodblock printing due to the limitations of the enormous [[Chinese character]] writing system, yet movable type printing continued to be used and was improved in later periods. The [[Yuan Dynasty]] scholar-official [[Wang Zhen (official)|Wang Zhen]] ([[floruit|fl.]] 1290–1333) implemented a faster typesetting process, improved Bi's baked-clay movable type character set with a wooden one, and experimented with tin-metal movable type.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=206–208, 217}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The wealthy printing patron [[Hua Sui]] (1439–1513) of the [[Ming Dynasty]] established China's first metal movable type (using bronze) in 1490.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=212–213}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1638 the [[Beijing]] [[Gazette]] switched their printing process from woodblock to movable type printing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Brook|1998|p=xxi}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yet it was during the [[Qing Dynasty]] that massive printing projects began to employ movable type printing. This includes the printing of sixty-six copies of a 5,020 volume long encyclopedia in 1725, the ''[[Gujin Tushu Jicheng]]'' (''Complete Collection of Illustrations and Writings from the Earliest to Current Times''), which necessitated the crafting of 250,000 movable type characters cast in bronze.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986e|pp=215–216}}.&lt;/ref&gt; By the 19th century the European style [[printing press]] replaced the old Chinese methods of movable type, while traditional woodblock printing in modern East Asia is used sparsely and for aesthetic reasons.

=== Hydraulic engineering and nautics ===
{{main|Science and technology of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Canallock.png|alt=A diagram of the pound lock system, from a bird's eye perspective and from a side perspective. The bird's eye view illustrates that water enters the enclosed area through two culverts on either side of the upper lock gate. The side view diagram illustrates how the elevation is higher before reaching the top gate than it is afterwards.|thumb|right|300px|A plan and side view of a canal [[pound lock]], a concept pioneered in 984 by the Assistant Commissioner of Transport for [[Huainan]], the engineer Qiao Weiyo.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=350}}.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
There were considerable advancements in [[hydraulic engineering]] and nautical technology during the Song Dynasty. The 10th century invention of the [[pound lock]] for canal systems allowed different water levels to be raised and lowered for separated segments of a canal, which significantly aided the safety of canal traffic and allowed for larger barges to pass through.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 350 351&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|pp=350–351}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There was the Song era innovation of [[Bulkhead (partition)|watertight bulkhead compartments]] for ships that allowed possible damage to the [[Hull (watercraft)|hull]] without sinking.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey et al 2006 159&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 463&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=463}}.&lt;/ref&gt; If ships were damaged, the Chinese of the 11th century discovered how to employ a [[drydock]] to repair boats while suspended out of water.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 660&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=660}}.&lt;/ref&gt; There Song Chinese used crossbeams to brace the ribs of ships in order to strengthen them in a skeletal like structure.&lt;ref name=&quot;graff higham 2002 86&quot;/&gt; [[Stern]]-mounted [[rudder]]s had been mounted on Chinese ships since the 1st century, as evidenced with a preserved Han tomb model of a ship. In the Song period the Chinese devised a way to mechanically raise and lower rudders in order for ships to travel in a wider range of water depths.&lt;ref name=&quot;graff higham 2002 86&quot;/&gt; The Song Chinese arranged the protruding teeth of anchors in a circular pattern instead of in one direction.&lt;ref name=&quot;graff higham 2002 86&quot;/&gt; David Graff and Robin Higham state that this arrangement &quot;[made] them more reliable&quot; for anchoring ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;graff higham 2002 86&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Graff|Higham|2002|p=86}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Arguably the most important nautical innovation of the Song period was the introduction of the [[magnetism|magnetic]] mariner's [[compass]] for [[navigation]] at sea.&lt;ref name=&quot;sivin III 22&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Sivin|1995|p=22}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The magnetic compass was first written of by Shen Kuo in his ''Dream Pool Essays'' of 1088, as well as [[Zhu Yu (author)|Zhu Yu]] in his ''Pingzhou Table Talks'' published in 1119.

=== Structural engineering and architecture ===
{{main|Architecture of the Song Dynasty}}
[[File:Zhengding Lingxiao Pagoda 3.jpg|alt=A wide, octagonal pagoda. It has four tall, functional floors made of brick, and an additional five, short, purely decorative floors made of wood. Each floor is separated by an eave, and the top five floor's eaves look as if they were simply stacked right on top of one another.|thumb|upright|The {{convert|42|m|ft|adj=on}} tall, brick and wood [[Lingxiao Pagoda]] of [[Zhengding]], [[Hebei]], built in 1045.]]
Architecture during the Song period reached new heights of sophistication. Authors such as [[Yu Hao]] and [[Shen Kuo]] wrote books outlining the field of architectural layouts, craftsmanship, and [[structural engineering]] in the 10th and 11th centuries, respectively. Shen Kuo preserved the written dialogues of Yu Hao when describing technical issues such as slanting [[strut]]s built into pagoda towers for diagonal wind bracing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=141}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  Shen Kuo also preserved Yu's specified dimensions and units of measurement for various building types.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|pp=82–84}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  The architect [[Architecture of the Song Dynasty#Treatise of Li Jie|Li Jie]] (1065–1110), who published the ''[[Yingzao Fashi]]'' ('Treatise on Architectural Methods') in 1103, greatly expanded upon the works of Yu Hao and compiled the standard building codes used by the central government agencies and by craftsmen throughout the empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guo 1998 4 6&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Guo|1998|pp=4–6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  He addressed the standard methods of construction, design, and applications of moats and fortifications, stonework, greater woodwork, lesser woodwork, wood-carving, turning and drilling, sawing, bamboo work, tiling, wall building, painting and decoration, brickwork,  glazed tile making, and provided proportions for [[mortar (masonry)|mortar]] formulas in [[masonry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 85&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=85}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Guo|1998|p=5}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  In his book, Li provided detailed and vivid illustrations of architectural components and cross-sections of buildings. These illustrations displayed various applications of [[corbel]] brackets, [[cantilever]] arms, [[mortise and tenon]] work of tie beams and cross beams, and diagrams  showing  the various building types of halls in graded sizes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|pp=96–100, 108–109}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  He also outlined the standard units of measurement and standard dimensional measurements of all building components described and illustrated in his book.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Guo|1998|pp=1–6}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Song-Imperial-Garden1.jpg|alt=A painting of people boating in a lake. There is a small island in the center of the lake, connected to the mainland by an arched bridge. The entire lake is surrounded by a low wall.|thumb|left|''Games in the Jinming Pool'', silk painting by [[Zhang Zeduan]], depiction of [[Kaifeng]], Northern Song era.]]
Grandiose building projects were supported by the government, including the erection of towering Buddhist [[Chinese pagoda]]s and the construction of enormous bridges (wood or stone, [[trestle]] or segmental [[arch bridge]]). Many of the pagoda towers built during the Song period were erected at heights that exceeded ten stories. Some of the most famous  are the [[Iron Pagoda]] built in 1049 during the Northern Song and the [[Liuhe Pagoda]] built in 1165 during the Southern Song, although [[:Category:Chinese pagodas|there were many others]]. The tallest is the [[Liaodi Pagoda]] of [[Hebei]] built in 1055, towering {{convert|84|m|ft|abbr=on}} in total height. Some of the bridges reached lengths of {{convert|1220|m|ft|abbr=on}}, with many being wide enough to allow two lanes of cart traffic  simultaneously over a waterway or ravine.&lt;ref name=&quot;volume 4 part 3 151 153&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|pp=151–153}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The government also oversaw construction of their own administrative offices, palace apartments, city fortifications, ancestral temples, and Buddhist temples.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 84&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=84}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The professions of the architect, craftsman, carpenter, and structural engineer were not seen as professionally equal to that of a Confucian scholar-official. Architectural knowledge had been passed down orally for thousands of years in China, in many cases from a father craftsman to his son. Structural engineering and architecture schools were known to have existed during the Song period; one prestigious engineering school was headed by the renowned bridge-builder [[Cai Xiang]] (1012–1067) in medieval [[Fujian]] province.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 153&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=153}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Yingzao Fashi 1.JPG|alt=A diagram showing multiple elaborately carved triangular brackets attached to each of the vertical support beams inside of a building.|thumb|right|[[Bracket (architecture)|Bracket]] arm clusters containing [[cantilever]]s, from [[Architecture of the Song Dynasty#Literature|Li Jie's]] building manual ''[[Yingzao Fashi]]'', printed in 1103.]]

Besides existing buildings and technical literature of building manuals, [[Architecture of the Song Dynasty#Architecture in Song artwork|Song Dynasty artwork]] portraying [[cityscape]]s and other buildings aid modern-day scholars in their attempts to reconstruct and realize the nuances of Song architecture. Song Dynasty artists such as [[Li Cheng (painter)|Li Cheng]], [[Fan Kuan]], [[Guo Xi]], [[Zhang Zeduan]], [[Emperor Huizong of Song]], and Ma Lin painted close-up depictions of buildings as well as large expanses of cityscapes featuring [[Arch bridge|arched bridges]], halls and [[Chinese pavilion|pavilions]], [[Pagoda|pagoda towers]], and distinct [[Chinese city wall]]s. The scientist and statesman Shen Kuo was known for his [[Art criticism|criticism of artwork]] relating to architecture, saying that it was more important for an artist to capture a holistic view of a landscape than it was to focus on the angles and corners of buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 115&quot;/&gt; For example, Shen criticized the work of the painter Li Cheng for failing to observe the principle of &quot;seeing the small from the viewpoint of the large&quot; in portraying buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;needham volume 4 part 3 115&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Needham|1986d|p=115}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

There were also pyramidal tomb structures in the Song era, such as the Song imperial tombs located in Gongxian, [[Henan]] province.&lt;ref name=&quot;steinhardt 1993 375&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Steinhardt|1993|p=375}}.&lt;/ref&gt; About {{convert|100|km|mi|abbr=on}} from Gongxian is another Song Dynasty tomb at Baisha, which features &quot;elaborate facsimiles in brick of Chinese timber frame construction, from door lintels to pillars and pedestals to bracket sets, that adorn interior walls.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;steinhardt 1993 375&quot;/&gt; The two large chambers of the Baisha tomb also feature conical-shaped roofs.&lt;ref name=&quot;steinhardt 1993 376&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Steinhardt|1993|p=376}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Flanking the avenues leading to these tombs [[:Image:Songling2.jpg|are lines of Song Dynasty stone statues]] of officials, tomb guardians, animals, and mythological creatures.

=== Archaeology ===
{{further|List of Chinese inventions#A}}
In addition to the Song gentry's antiquarian pursuits of art collecting, scholar-officials during the Song became highly interested in retrieving ancient relics from [[Archaeology|archaeological]] sites, in order to revive the use of ancient vessels in ceremonies of state ritual.&lt;ref name=&quot;fraser haber 1986 227&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fraser|Haber|1986|p=227}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Scholar-officials of the Song period claimed to have discovered ancient bronze vessels that were created as far back as the [[Shang Dynasty]] (1600–1046 BCE) which bore the [[Oracle bone script|writing characters of the Shang era]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fairbank goldman 1992 33&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fairbank|Goldman|2006|p=33}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Some attempted to recreate these bronze vessels by using imagination alone, not by observing tangible evidence of relics; this practice was criticized by Shen Kuo in his work of 1088.&lt;ref name=&quot;fraser haber 1986 227&quot;/&gt; Yet Shen Kuo had much more to criticize than this practice alone. Shen objected to the idea of his peers that ancient relics were products created by famous &quot;sages&quot; in lore or the [[Four occupations|ancient aristocratic class]]; Shen rightfully attributed the discovered handicrafts and vessels from ancient times as the work of artisans and commoners from previous eras.&lt;ref name=&quot;fraser haber 1986 227&quot;/&gt; He also disapproved of his peers' pursuit of archaeology simply to enhance state ritual, since Shen not only took an [[Interdisciplinarity|interdisciplinary]] approach with the study of archaeology, but he also emphasized the study of functionality and investigating what was the ancient relics' original processes of manufacture.&lt;ref name=&quot;fraser haber 1986 227&quot;/&gt; Shen used ancient texts and existing models of [[armillary sphere]]s to create one based on ancient standards; Shen described ancient weaponry such as the use of a [[Sight (device)|scaled sighting device]] on crossbows; while experimenting with [[Bar (music)|ancient musical measures]], Shen suggested hanging [[Bianzhong|an ancient bell]] by using a hollow handle.&lt;ref name=&quot;fraser haber 1986 227&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Liu Ding.jpg|alt=A heavily tarnished bronze bowl adorned with several carvings of squares that curl in on themselves at the bottom. It has three stubby, unadorned legs and two small, square handles coming off from the top rim.|thumb|left|Scholars of the Song claim to have collected ancient relics dating back as far as the [[Shang Dynasty]], such as this [[Ding (vessel)|bronze ''ding'' vessel]].]]
Despite the gentry's overriding interest in archaeology simply for reviving ancient state rituals, some of Shen's peers took a similar approach to the study of archaeology. His contemporary [[Ouyang Xiu]] (1007–1072) compiled an analytical catalogue of ancient rubbings on stone and bronze which pioneered ideas in early [[epigraphy]] and archeology.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebrey cambridge 148&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ebrey|1999|p=148}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During the 11th century, Song scholars discovered the ancient shrine of Wu Liang (78–151 AD), a scholar of the [[Han Dynasty]] (202 BC – 220 AD); they produced rubbings of the carvings and [[bas-relief]]s decorating the walls of his tomb so that they could be analyzed elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Hansen|2000|p=142}}.&lt;/ref&gt; On the unreliability of historical works written after the fact, scholar-official [[Zhao Mingcheng]] (1081–1129) stated &quot;...the inscriptions on stone and bronze are made at the time the events took place and can be trusted without reservation, and thus discrepancies may be discovered.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;rudolph 1963 170&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Rudolph|1963|p=170}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Historian R.C. Rudolph states that Zhao's emphasis on consulting contemporary sources for accurate dating is parallel with the concern of the German historian [[Leopold von Ranke]] (1795–1886),&lt;ref name=&quot;rudolph 1963 170&quot;/&gt; and was in fact emphasized by many Song scholars.&lt;ref name=&quot;rudolph 1963 172&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Rudolph|1963|p=172}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Song scholar Hong Mai (1123–1202) heavily criticized what he called the court's &quot;ridiculous&quot; archaeological catalogue ''Bogutu'' compiled during the Huizong reign periods of Zheng He and Xuan He (1111–1125).&lt;ref name=&quot;rudolph 1963 170 171&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Rudolph|1963|pp=170–171}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Hong Mai obtained old vessels from the Han Dynasty and compared them with the descriptions offered in the catalogue, which he found so inaccurate he stated he had to &quot;hold my sides with laughter.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;rudolph 1963 171&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Rudolph|1963|p=171}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Hong Mai pointed out that the erroneous material was the fault of Chancellor [[Cai Jing]] (1047–1126), who prohibited scholars from reading and consulting the written histories.&lt;ref name=&quot;rudolph 1963 171&quot;/&gt;

{{Clear}}

== See also ==
{{div col|colwidth=15em}}
* [[Four Great Books of Song]]
* [[Lu You]]
* [[Shao Yong]]
* [[Tang Clan]]
* [[Taxation in premodern China]]
* [[Tianchao Daguo]]
* [[Tiger Cave Kiln]]
* [[Wang Chongyang]]
* [[Water Margin]]
* [[Wen Tianxiang]]
* [[Zeng Gong]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes ==
{{Cnote|a|During the reign of the Song Dynasty the world population grew from about 250 million to approximately 330 million, a difference of 80 million. Please also see [[Medieval demography]].}}
{{Reflist|20em}}

== References ==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
*{{citation |last=Adshead |first=S. A. M. |title=T'ang China: The Rise of the East in World History |year=2004 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |location=New York |isbn=1-4039-3456-8 }} (hardback).
*{{citation |last=Anderson |first=James A. |editor-last=Wyatt |editor-first=Don J. |chapter='Treacherous Factions': Shifting Frontier Alliances in the Breakdown of Sino-Vietnamese Relations on the Eve of the 1075 Border War |title=Battlefronts Real and Imagined: War, Border, and Identity in the Chinese Middle Period |year=2008 |publisher=Palgrave MacMillan |location=New York |isbn=978-1-4039-6084-9 |pages=191–226 |url= }}
*{{Citation |last=Bai |first=Shouyi |year=2002 |title=An Outline History of China |edition=Revised |publisher=Foreign Languages Press |location=Beijing |isbn=7-119-02347-0 }}
*{{Citation |last=Bol |first=Peter K. |year=2001 |title=The Rise of Local History: History, Geography, and Culture in Southern Song and Yuan Wuzhou |journal=Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies |volume=61 |issue=1 |pages=37–76|doi=10.2307/3558587 |jstor=3558587 }}
*{{citation |last=Brook |first=Timothy |title=[[The Confusions of Pleasure: Commerce and Culture in Ming China]] |year=1998 |publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley |isbn=978-0-520-22154-3 }}
*{{citation |last=Brose |first=Michael C. |editor-last=Wyatt |editor-first=Don J. |chapter=People in the Middle: Uyghurs in the Northwest Frontier Zone |title=Battlefronts Real and Imagined: War, Border, and Identity in the Chinese Middle Period |year=2008 |publisher=Palgrave MacMillan |location=New York |isbn=978-1-4039-6084-9 |pages=253–289 |url= }}
*{{citation |last=Ebrey |first=Patricia Buckley |last2=Walthall |first2=Anne |last3=Palais |first3=James B. |title=East Asia: A Cultural, Social, and Political History |year=2006 |publisher=[[Houghton Mifflin]] |location=Boston |isbn=0-618-13384-4 |pages= |url= }}
*{{citation |last=Ebrey |first=Patricia Buckley |title=The Cambridge Illustrated History of China |year=1999 |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-66991-X |pages= |url= }} (paperback).
*{{Citation | last1=Embree |first1= Ainslie Thomas |last2=Gluck |first2=Carol |title=Asia in Western and World History: A Guide for Teaching |year=1997 |publisher=ME Sharpe |location=Armonk |isbn=1-56324-264-8 }}
*{{citation |last=Chan |first=Alan Kam-leung |last2=Clancey |first2=Gregory K. |last3=Loy |first3=Hui-Chieh |title=Historical Perspectives on East Asian Science, Technology and Medicine |year=2002 |publisher=[[Singapore University Press]] |location=Singapore |isbn=9971-69-259-7 }}
*{{citation |last=Fairbank |first=John King |last2=Goldman |first2=Merle |title=China: A New History |edition=2nd enlarged |year=2006 |origyear=1992 |publisher=The Belknap Press of [[Harvard University Press]] |location=Cambridge; London |isbn=0-674-01828-1 }}
*{{citation |last=Fraser |first=Julius Thomas |last2=Haber |first2=Francis C. |title=Time, Science, and Society in China and the West |year=1986 |publisher=[[University of Massachusetts Press]] |location=Amherst |isbn=0-87023-495-1 |pages= |url= }}
*{{citation |last=Gernet |first=Jacques |others=Translated by H. M. Wright |title=Daily Life in China on the Eve of the Mongol Invasion, 1250-1276 |year=1962 |publisher=[[Stanford University Press]] |location=Stanford |isbn=0-8047-0720-0 }}
*{{citation |last=Graff |first=David Andrew |last2=Higham |first2=Robin |title=A Military History of China |year=2002 |publisher=Westview Press |location=Boulder |isbn= }}
*{{Citation |last=Guo |first=Qinghua |year=1998 |title=Yingzao Fashi: Twelfth-Century Chinese Building Manual |journal=Architectural History: Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians of Great Britain |volume=41 |issue= |pages=1–13 }}
*{{citation |last=Hall |first=Kenneth |title=Maritime trade and state development in early Southeast Asia |year=1985 |publisher=[[University of Hawaii Press]] |location=Hawaii |isbn=0-8248-0959-9 }}
*{{citation |last=Hansen |first=Valerie |title=The Open Empire: A History of China to 1600 |year=2000 |publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Company |location=New York &amp; London |isbn=0-393-97374-3 }}
*{{Citation |last=Hargett |first=James M. |year=1985 |title=Some Preliminary Remarks on the Travel Records of the Song Dynasty (960–1279) |work=Chinese Literature: Essays, Articles, Reviews (CLEAR) |volume= |issue= |pages=67–93 |issn= }}
*{{Citation |last=Hargett |first=James M. |authorlink= |year=1996 |title=Song Dynasty Local Gazetteers and Their Place in The History of Difangzhi Writing |journal=Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies |volume=56 |issue=2 |pages=405–442|doi=10.2307/2719404 |jstor= 2719404 }}
*{{Citation |last=Hartwell |first=Robert M. |year=1982 |title=Demographic, Political, and Social Transformations of China, 750-1550 |journal=Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies |volume=42 |issue=2 |pages=365–442|doi=10.2307/2718941 |jstor= 2718941 }}
*{{citation |last=Hymes |first=Robert P. |title=Statesmen and Gentlemen: The Elite of Fu-Chou, Chiang-Hsi, in Northern and Southern Sung |year=1986 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-30631-0 }}
*{{Citation |last=Hsu |first=Mei-ling |year=1993 |title=The Qin Maps: A Clue to Later Chinese Cartographic Development |journal=Imago Mundi |volume=45 |issue= |pages=90–100 |doi=10.1080/03085699308592766 }}
*{{citation |last=Levathes |first=Louise |title=When China Ruled the Seas |year=1994 |publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]] |location=New York |isbn=0-671-70158-4 |pages= |url= }}
*{{citation |last=Lorge |first=Peter |title=War, Politics and Society in Early Modern China, 900–1795 |edition=1st |year=2005 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |location=New York |isbn= }}
*{{citation |last=McKnight |first=Brian E. |title=Law and Order in Sung China |year=1992 |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |location=Cambridge |isbn= }}
*{{citation |last=Mohn |first=Peter |title=Magnetism in the Solid State: An Introduction |year=2003 |publisher=Springer-Verlag |location=New York |isbn=3-540-43183-7 }}
*{{citation |last=Mote |first=F. W. |title=Imperial China: 900–1800 |year=1999 |publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] |location=Harvard |isbn= |pages= |url= }}
*{{citation |last=Needham |first=Joseph |title=Science and Civilization in China: Volume 1, Introductory Orientations |year=1986a |publisher=Caves Books |location=Taipei |isbn= }}
*{{citation |last=Needham |first=Joseph |title=Science and Civilization in China: Volume 3, Mathematics and the Sciences of the Heavens and the Earth |year=1986b |publisher=Caves Books |location=Taipei |isbn= }}
*{{citation |last=Needham |first=Joseph |title=Science and Civilization in China: Volume 4, Physics and Physical Technology, Part 2: Mechanical Engineering |year=1986c |publisher=Caves Books |location=Taipei |isbn= }}
*{{citation |last=Needham |first=Joseph |title=Science and Civilization in China: Volume 4, Physics and Physical Technology, Part 3: Civil Engineering and Nautics |year=1986d |publisher=Caves Books |location=Taipei |isbn= }}
*{{citation |last=Needham |first=Joseph |title=Science and Civilization in China: Volume 5, Chemistry and Chemical Technology, Part 7: Military Technology; The Gunpowder Epic |year=1986e |publisher=Caves Books |location=Taipei |isbn= }}
*{{citation |last=Paludan |first=Ann |title=Chronicle of the Chinese Emperors |year=1998 |publisher=[[Thames &amp; Hudson]] |location=London |isbn=0-500-05090-2 |pages= |url= }}
*{{citation |last=Peers |first=C. J. |title=Soldiers of the Dragon: Chinese Armies 1500 BC-AD 1840 |year=2006 |publisher=Osprey Publishing |location=Oxford |isbn= }}
*{{citation |last=Rossabi |first=Morris |title=Khubilai Khan: His Life and Times |year=1988 |publisher=[[University of California Press]] |location=Berkeley |isbn=0-520-05913-1 }}
*{{Citation |last=Rudolph |first=R. C. |year=1963 |title=Preliminary Notes on Sung Archaeology |journal=The Journal of Asian Studies |volume=22 |issue=2 |pages=169–177|doi=10.2307/2050010 |jstor= 2050010 }}
*{{citation |last=Sastri |first=Nilakanta, K.A. |title=The CōĻas |year=1984 |publisher=University of Madras |location=Madras |isbn= }}
*{{Citation |last=Schafer |first=Edward H. |year=1957 |title=War Elephants in Ancient and Medieval China |journal=Oriens |volume=10 |issue=2 |pages=289–291|doi=10.2307/1579643 |jstor= 1579643 }}
*{{citation |last=Sen |first=Tansen |title=Buddhism, Diplomacy, and Trade: The Realignment of Sino-Indian Relations, 600–1400 |year=2003 |publisher=Asian Interactions and Comparisons, a joint publication of the University of Hawaii Press and the Association for Asian Studies |location=Manoa |isbn=0-8248-2593-4 }}
*{{citation |last=Shen |first=Fuwei |title=Cultural flow between China and the outside world |year=1996 |publisher=Foreign Languages Press |location=Beijing |isbn=7-119-00431-X |pages= |url= }}
*{{citation |last=Sivin |first=Nathan |title=Science in Ancient China |year=1995 |publisher=VARIORUM, Ashgate Publishing |location=Brookfield, Vermont |isbn= }}
*{{Citation |last=Steinhardt |first=Nancy Shatzman |year=1993 |title=The Tangut Royal Tombs near Yinchuan |journal=Muqarnas: an Annual on Islamic Art and Architecture |volume=X |issue= |pages=369–381 |url=  }}
*{{citation |last=Sung |first=Tz’u |others=translated by Brian E. McKnight |chapter= |title=The Washing Away of Wrongs: Forensic Medicine in Thirteenth-Century China |year=1981 |publisher=[[University of Michigan Press]] |location=Ann Arbor |isbn=0-89264-800-7 }}
*{{citation |last=Temple |first=Robert |others=with a foreword by Joseph Needham |title=The Genius of China: 3,000 Years of Science, Discovery, and Invention |year=1986 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0-671-62028-2 }}
*{{citation |last=Veeck |first=Gregory |last2=Pannell |first2=Clifton W. |last3=Smith |first3=Christopher J. |last4=Huang |first4=Youqin |title=China's Geography: Globalization and the Dynamics of Political, Economic, and Social Change |year=2007 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers |location=Lanham |isbn=0-7425-5402-3 }}
*{{Citation |last=Wagner |first=Donald B. |year=2001 |title=The Administration of the Iron Industry in Eleventh-Century China |journal=Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient |volume=44 |issue= 2|pages=175–197 |url= |doi=10.1163/156852001753731033 }}
*{{citation |last=Wang |first=Lianmao |title=Return to the City of Light: Quanzhou, an eastern city shining with the splendour of medieval culture |year=2000 |publisher=Fujian People's Publishing House |location= |isbn= |pages= |url= }}
*{{Citation |last=West |first=Stephen H. |year=1997 |title=Playing With Food: Performance, Food, and The Aesthetics of Artificiality in The Sung and Yuan |journal=Harvard Journal of Asiatic Studies |volume=57 |issue=1 |pages=67–106|doi=10.2307/2719361 |jstor= 2719361 }}
*{{citation |last=Wright |first=Arthur F. |title=Buddhism in Chinese History |year=1959 |publisher=[[Stanford University Press]] |location=Stanford |isbn= |pages= |url= }}
*{{Citation |last=Yuan |first=Zheng |year=1994 |title=Local Government Schools in Sung China: A Reassessment |journal=History of Education Quarterly |volume=34 |issue=2 |pages=193–213|doi=10.2307/369121 |jstor= 369121 }}
{{Refend}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{Citation | author=Cotterell, Arthur. | title=The Imperial Capitals of China - An Inside View of the Celestial Empire| location=London | publisher=Pimlico | year=2007 | isbn=978-1-84595-009-5 | pages = 304 pages.}}
* {{Citation |last=Gascoigne |first=Bamber |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=The Dynasties of China: A History |year=2003 |publisher=Carroll &amp; Graf |location=New York |isbn=1-84119-791-2 }}
* {{Citation |last=Gernet |first=Jacques |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=A history of Chinese civilization |year=1982 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=0-521-24130-8 }}
* Giles, Herbert Allen (1939). ''A Chinese biographical dictionary (Gu jin xing shi zu pu)''. Shanghai: Kelly &amp; Walsh. (see here [http://books.google.com/books?id=BxH0PqdGTVUC&amp;pg=RA4-PA949&amp;lpg=RA4-PA949&amp;dq=yo+fei#PRA4-PA949,M1] for more)
* {{Citation |last=Kruger |first=Rayne |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=All Under Heaven: A Complete History of China |year=2003 |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |location=Chichester |isbn=0-470-86533-4 }}
* Tillman, Hoyt C. and Stephen H. West (1995). ''China Under Jurchen Rule: Essays on Chin Intellectual and Cultural History''. Albany, New York: State University of New York Press.
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category multi|Song Dynasty|Art of the Song Dynasty}}
* [http://www.chinaheritagequarterly.org/features.php?searchterm=006_elm.inc&amp;issue=006 Song Dynasty at China Heritage Quarterly]
* [http://www.bcps.org/offices/lis/models/chinahist/song.html Song Dynasty at bcps.org]
* [http://www.art-and-archaeology.com/timelines/china/song.html Song and Liao artwork]
* [http://www.xabusiness.com/china-resources/song-liao-jin-dynasties-paintings.htm Paintings of Song, Liao and Jin dynasties]
* [http://www.artsmia.org/art-of-asia/history/dynasty-sung.cfm Song Dynasty art with video commentary]
{{S-start}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Dynasties in Chinese history]]|before=[[Five Dynasties and Ten Kingdoms]]|after=[[Yuan Dynasty]]|years=960–1279}}
{{s-end}}
{{Song Dynasty topics}}
{{featured article}}
{{Empires}}

[[Category:States and territories established in 960]]
[[Category:Song Dynasty| ]]
[[Category:1279 disestablishments]]

{{Link FA|fr}}
{{Link GA|no}}
{{Link GA|pl}}
{{Link FA|zh}}
{{Link FA|hu}}

[[ar:أسرة سونغ]]
[[zh-min-nan:Sòng]]
[[bg:Сун]]
[[br:Tierniezh Song]]
[[ca:Dinastia Song]]
[[cv:Сун (патшалăх)]]
[[cs:Dynastie Sung]]
[[da:Song-dynastiet]]
[[de:Song-Dynastie]]
[[et:Songi dünastia]]
[[es:Dinastía Song]]
[[eo:Dinastio Song]]
[[eu:Song dinastia]]
[[fa:دودمان سونگ]]
[[fr:Dynastie Song]]
[[gan:宋]]
[[ko:송나라]]
[[hi:सोंग राजवंश]]
[[hr:Dinastija Sung]]
[[id:Dinasti Song]]
[[is:Songveldið]]
[[it:Dinastia Song]]
[[he:שושלת סונג]]
[[lv:Sun dinastija]]
[[lt:Songų dinastija]]
[[hu:Szung-dinasztia]]
[[mr:सोंग राजवंश]]
[[ms:Dinasti Song]]
[[mn:Сүн улс]]
[[nl:Song-dynastie]]
[[ja:宋 (王朝)]]
[[no:Song-dynastiet]]
[[nn:Song-dynastiet]]
[[pl:Dynastia Song]]
[[pt:Dinastia Sung]]
[[ro:Dinastia Song]]
[[ru:Империя Сун]]
[[sq:Dinastia Song]]
[[simple:Song Dynasty]]
[[sr:Династија Сонг]]
[[sh:Dinastija Sung]]
[[fi:Song-dynastia]]
[[sv:Songdynastin]]
[[ta:சொங் அரசமரபு]]
[[th:ราชวงศ์ซ่ง]]
[[uk:Династія Сун]]
[[vi:Nhà Tống]]
[[zh-classical:趙宋]]
[[war:Dinastiya Song]]
[[zh-yue:大宋]]
[[zea:Song-dynastie]]
[[zh:宋朝]]</text>
      <sha1>pqlpwuq1vg6aquw45jnsco2h6rh50od</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
