<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Third Crusade</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>106131</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521463850</id>
      <parentid>521460556</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T04:17:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>63.227.152.113</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29012">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict  = Third Crusade
| partof    = the [[Crusades]]
| image     = [[File:Siege of Acre.jpg|200px]]
| caption   = The [[Siege of Acre (1189–1191)|Siege of Acre]] was the first major confrontation of the Third Crusade
| date      = 1189–1192
| place     = [[Near East]] ([[Anatolia]], [[Levant]], [[Israel]])
| territory = Cyprus, Acre, Jaffa, and much of the Levantine coast are annexed under Crusader control.
| result    = [[Treaty of Ramla]]
* Jerusalem remains under Muslim control.
* Crusader victory in all military engagements.
* Italians consolidate control of Syrian ports.
* Muslims allow trade and unarmed Christian [[pilgrimages]] into the Holy Land.
| combatant1 = [[Crusaders]]
* [[File:Armoiries de Jérusalem.svg|15px]] [[Kingdom of Jerusalem]]
** [[File:Cross of the Knights Templar.svg|15px|border]] [[Knights Templar]]
** [[File:Den tyske ordens skjold.svg|15px]] [[Teutonic Knights]]
** {{nowrap|[[File:Cross of the Knights Hospitaller.svg|15px]] [[Knights Hospitaller]]}}
* [[File:Royal Arms of England (1189-1198).svg|15px]] [[Kingdom of England]]
** [[Angevin Empire]]
* [[File:Arms of the Kingdom of France (Ancien).svg|15px]] [[France in the Middle Ages|Kingdom of France]]
** [[File:Blason Blois Ancien.svg|15px]] [[Counts of Blois|Blois]]
* [[File:Holy Roman Empire Arms-single head.svg|15px]] [[Holy Roman Empire]]
** [[File:Coat of arms of Baden-Württemberg (lesser).svg|15px]] [[Duchy of Swabia|Swabia]]
** [[File:Gules a fess argent.svg|15px]] [[Duchy of Austria|Austria]]
** [[File:Armoiries Montferrat.png|15px]] [[March of Montferrat|Montferrat]]
** [[File:Small coat of arms of the Czech Republic.svg|15px|link=|alt=]] [[Bohemia]]
*[[File:Alex K Kingdom of Hungary.svg|12px]] [[Kingdom of Hungary]]
| combatant2 = [[Saracen]]s
* [[File:Flag of Ayyubid Dynasty.svg|15px]] [[Ayyubid dynasty|Ayyubids]]
* [[File:Flag of Jihad.svg|15px]] [[Zengid Dynasty|Zengids]]
* [[Sultanate of Rûm]]
----
* [[File:Komnenos-Isaac-Arms.svg|15px|border|link=|alt=]] [[Byzantine Empire]]
* [[File:Isaak_Comnenus_of_Cyprus_flag.svg|15px]] [[Cyprus]] (seat of rival claim to the Byzantine throne)
* [[File:Blason sicile famille Hauteville.svg|15px]] [[Kingdom of Sicily]]
| combatant3 =
| commander1 = Crusaders
* [[File:Arms of the Kingdom of France (Ancien).svg|15px]] [[Philip II of France]]
** [[File:Blason Blois Ancien.svg|15px]] [[Theobald V, Count of Blois|Theobald V]]
* [[File:Royal Arms of England (1189-1198).svg|15px]] [[Richard I of England]]
* [[File:Armoiries de Jérusalem.svg|15px]] [[Guy of Lusignan]]
* [[File:Armoiries de Jérusalem.svg|15px]] [[Henry II of Champagne]]
** [[File:Cross of the Knights Templar.svg|15px|border]] [[Robert de Sable]]
** [[File:Den tyske ordens skjold.svg|15px]] [[Grand Masters of the Teutonic Knights|Meister Sibrand]]
** {{nowrap|[[File:Cross of the Knights Hospitaller.svg|15px]] [[Garnier de Nablus]]}}
** [[File:Armoiries de Jérusalem.svg|15px]] [[Balian of Ibelin]]
* [[File:Holy Roman Empire Arms-single head.svg|15px]] [[Frederick I, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick I]]
** [[File:Coat of arms of Baden-Württemberg (lesser).svg|15px]] [[Frederick VI, Duke of Swabia|Fredrick VI]]
** [[File:Gules a fess argent.svg|15px]] [[Leopold V, Duke of Austria|Leopold V]]
** [[File:Armoiries Montferrat.png|15px]] [[Conrad of Montferrat]]
*[[File:Alex K Kingdom of Hungary.svg|12px]] [[Géza, royal prince of Hungary|Géza of Hungary]]
| commander2 = Saracens
* [[File:Flag of Ayyubid Dynasty.svg|15px]] [[Saladin|Ṣalāḥ ad-Dīn Yūsuf ibn Ayyūb (or Salaldin)]]
* [[Kilij Arslan II]]
----
* [[File:Komnenos-Isaac-Arms.svg|15px|border|link=|alt=]] [[Isaac II Angelus]]
* [[File:Isaak_Comnenus_of_Cyprus_flag.svg|15px]] [[Isaac Komnenos of Cyprus|Isaac Komnenos]]
* [[File:Blason sicile famille Hauteville.svg|15px]] [[Tancred of Sicily]]
| commander3  =
| strength1   = English: 8,000 men&lt;ref name=&quot;Chisholm294&quot;&gt;H. Chisholm, ''The Encyclopædia Britannica : A Dictionary of Arts, Sciences, Literature and General Information'', 294&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;French: 2,000 men&lt;ref name = &quot;Phillips66&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Germans: 100,000 men&lt;ref name = &quot;Phillips66&quot;/&gt;
| strength2   = Unknown
| strength3   =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| casualties3 =
| notes       =
| campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Crusades}}
{{Campaignbox Third Crusade}}
{{Campaignbox Crusades Battles}}
}}

The '''Third Crusade''' (1189–1192), also known as the '''Kings' Crusade''', was an attempt by European leaders to reconquer the [[Holy Land]] from [[Saladin]] (Ṣalāḥ ad-Dīn Yūsuf ibn Ayyūb). It was largely successful, but fell short of its ultimate goal—the reconquest of Jerusalem.

After the failure of the [[Second Crusade]], the [[Zengid dynasty]] controlled a unified [[Syria]] and engaged in a conflict with the [[Fatimid dynasty|Fatimid]] rulers of [[Egypt]], which ultimately resulted in the unification of Egyptian and Syrian forces under the command of Saladin, who employed them to reduce the Christian states and to recapture Jerusalem in 1187. Spurred by religious zeal, [[Henry II of England]] and [[Philip II of France]] ended their conflict with each other to lead a new crusade (although Henry's death in 1189 put the English contingent under the command of [[Richard I|Richard Lionheart]] instead). The [[elderly]] [[Holy Roman Emperor]] [[Frederick I, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick Barbarossa]] responded to the call to arms, and led a massive army across [[Anatolia]], but drowned in a river in Asia Minor on June 10, 1190, before reaching [[Palestine|the Holy Land]]. His death caused the greatest grief among the German Crusaders. Most of his discouraged troops left to go home.

After driving the Muslims from Acre, Frederick's successor [[Leopold V of Austria (Babenberg)|Leopold V of Austria]] and Philip left the Holy Land in August 1191. Saladin failed to defeat Richard in any military engagements, and Richard secured several more key coastal cities. Nevertheless, on September 2, 1192, Richard finalized a [[treaty]] with Saladin by which Jerusalem would remain under Muslim control, but which also allowed unarmed Christian [[pilgrim]]s and [[merchants]] to visit the [[Jerusalem|city]]. Richard departed the Holy Land on October 9. The successes of the Third Crusade would allow the Crusaders to maintain a considerable kingdom based in Cyprus and the Syrian coast. However, its failure to recapture Jerusalem would lead to the call for a [[Fourth Crusade]] six years later.

===Saladin's conquests===
Shawar was executed for his alliances with the Christian forces, and Shirkuh succeeded him as [[vizier]] of Egypt. In 1169, Shirkuh died unexpectedly after only weeks of rule. Shirkuh's successor was his nephew, Salah ad-Din Yusuf, commonly known as Saladin. Nur ad-Din died in 1174, leaving the new empire to his 11-year old son, [[As-Salih Ismail al-Malik|As-Salih]]. It was decided that the only man competent enough to uphold the [[jihad]] against the Franks was Saladin, who became sultan of both Egypt and Syria, and the founder of the [[Ayyubid dynasty]].

Amalric also died in 1174, leaving Jerusalem to his 13-year old son, [[Baldwin IV of Jerusalem|Baldwin IV]]. Although Baldwin suffered from [[leprosy]], he was an effective and active military commander, defeating Saladin at the [[battle of Montgisard]] in 1177, with support from [[Raynald of Châtillon]], who had been released from prison in 1176. Later, he forged an agreement with Saladin to allow free trade between Muslim and Christian territories.

Raynald also raided caravans throughout the region. He expanded his piracy to the [[Red Sea]] by sending galleys not only to raid ships, but to assault the city of [[Mecca]] itself. These acts enraged the Muslim world, giving Raynald a reputation as the most hated man in the Middle East.

Baldwin IV died in 1185 and the kingdom was left to his nephew [[Baldwin V]], whom he had crowned as co-king in 1183. [[Raymond III of Tripoli]] again served as regent. The following year, Baldwin V died before his ninth birthday, and his mother Princess [[Sibylla of Jerusalem|Sybilla]], sister of Baldwin IV, crowned herself queen and her husband, [[Guy of Lusignan]], king.

It was at this time that Raynald, once again, raided a rich caravan and had its travelers thrown in prison. Saladin demanded that the prisoners and their cargo be released. The newly crowned King Guy appealed to Raynald to give in to Saladin's demands, but Raynald refused to follow the king's orders.

[[File:Crusader States 1190.svg|thumb|right|300px|The Near East, c. 1190, at the outset of the Third Crusade.]]

===Siege of the Kingdom of Jerusalem===
:''Full article: [[Battle of Hattin]]; [[Siege of Jerusalem (1187)|Siege of Jerusalem]]''

It was this final act of outrage by Raynald which gave Saladin the opportunity he needed to take the offensive against the kingdom. He laid siege to the city of [[Tiberias]] in 1187. Raymond advised patience, but King Guy, acting on advice from Raynald, marched his army to the [[Hittin|Horns of Hattin]] outside of Tiberias.

The Frankish army, thirsty and demoralized, was destroyed in the ensuing battle. King Guy and Raynald were brought to Saladin's tent, where Guy was offered a goblet of water because of his great thirst . Guy took a drink and then passed the goblet to Raynald. Saladin would not be forced to protect the treacherous Raynald by allowing him to drink, as it was custom that if you were offered a drink, your life was safe. When Raynald accepted the drink, Saladin told his interpreter, &quot;say to the King: 'it is you who have given him to drink'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Lyons, Malcom Cameron and D. E. P. Jackson, ''Saladin: The Politics of the Holy War'', (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1982), 264.&lt;/ref&gt;  Afterwards, Saladin beheaded Raynald for past betrayals. Saladin honored tradition with King Guy; Guy was sent to Damascus and eventually ransomed to his people, one of the few captive crusaders to avoid execution.

By the end of the year, Saladin had taken [[Akko|Acre]] and [[Jerusalem]]. Pope [[Urban III]] is said to have collapsed and died upon hearing the news.&lt;ref&gt;Hans E. Mayer, ''The Crusades''. [[Oxford University Press]], 1965 (trans. John Gillingham, 1972), pg. 139.&lt;/ref&gt; However, at the time of his death, the news of the fall of Jerusalem could not yet have reached him, although he knew of the battle of Hattin and the fall of Acre.

==Preparations==
The new pope, [[Gregory VIII]] proclaimed that the capture of Jerusalem was punishment for the sins of Christians across Europe. The cry went up for a new crusade to the Holy Land. [[Henry II of England]] and [[Philip II of France]] ended their war with each other, and both imposed a &quot;[[Saladin tithe]]&quot; on their citizens to finance the venture. In Britain, [[Baldwin of Exeter]], the [[archbishop of Canterbury]], made a tour through Wales, convincing 3,000 men-at-arms to take up the cross, recorded in the ''Itinerary'' of [[Giraldus Cambrensis]].

[[File:Gustave dore crusades death of frederick of germany.jpg|thumb|left|250px|&quot;Death of Frederick of Germany&quot; by [[Gustav Dore]]]]

==Barbarossa's crusade==
The elderly [[Holy Roman Emperor]] [[Frederick I, Holy Roman Emperor|Frederick I Barbarossa]] responded to the call immediately. He took up the Cross at [[Mainz Cathedral]] on March 27, 1188 and was the first to set out for the Holy Land in May 1189 with an army of about 100,000 men, including 20,000 knights.&lt;ref name = &quot;Phillips66&quot;/&gt; An army of 2,000 men from the Hungarian prince Géza, the younger brother of the king [[Béla III of Hungary]] also went with Barbarossa to the Holy Land.&lt;ref name=&quot;Konstam124&quot;&gt;A. Konstam, ''Historical Atlas of The Crusades'', 124&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Byzantine Emperor]] [[Isaac II Angelus]] made a secret alliance with Saladin to impede Frederick's progress in exchange for his empire's safety. Meanwhile, the Sultanate of Rum promised Frederick safety through Anatolia, but after much raiding Frederick lost patience and on May 18, 1190, the [[German people|German]] army [[Battle of Iconium (1190)|sacked Iconium]], the capital of the [[Sultanate of Rüm]]. Nevertheless Frederick's horse slipped on June 10, 1190, while crossing the [[Saleph River]] throwing him against the rocks. He then drowned in the river. After this, much of his army returned to Germany, in anticipation of the upcoming Imperial election. His son [[Frederick VI, Duke of Swabia|Frederick of Swabia]] led the remaining 5,000 men to [[Antioch]]. There, the emperor's body was boiled to remove the flesh, which was interred in the Church of St. Peter; his bones were put in a bag to continue the crusade. In Antioch, however, the German army was further reduced by fever. Young Frederick had to ask the assistance of his kinsman [[Conrad of Montferrat]] to lead him safely to Acre, by way of Tyre, where his father's bones were buried.

==Richard and Philip's departure==
[[File:Philip Augustus arriving in Palestine - British Library Royal MS 16 G vi f350vr (detail).jpg|thumb|right|Philip II depicted arriving in Palestine]]
[[Henry II of England]] died on July 6, 1189 following a defeat by his son [[Richard I of England|Richard I]] (Lionheart) and Philip II. Richard inherited the [[coronation|crown]] and immediately began raising funds for the crusade. In July 1190, Richard and Philip set out jointly from [[Marseille|Marseille, France]] for [[Sicily]]. Philip II had hired a Genoese fleet to transport his army which consisted of 650 knights, 1,300 horses, and 1,300 squires to the Holy Land.&lt;ref name=&quot;Phillips66&quot;&gt;J. Phillips, ''The Fourth Crusade and the Sack of Constantinople'', 66&lt;/ref&gt;

[[William II of Sicily]] had died the previous year, and was replaced by [[Tancred of Sicily|Tancred]], who placed [[Joan of England, Queen consort of Sicily|Joan of England]]—William's wife and Richard's sister—in prison. Richard captured the capital city of [[Messina]] on October 4, 1190 and Joan was released. Richard and Philip fell out over the issue of Richard's marriage, as Richard had decided to marry [[Berengaria of Navarre]], breaking off his long-standing betrothal to Philip's half-sister [[Alys, Countess of the Vexin|Alys]]. Philip left Sicily directly for the Middle East on March 30, 1191, and arrived in Tyre in mid-May. He joined the siege of Acre on May 20. Richard did not set off from Sicily until April 10.

Shortly after setting sail from Sicily, Richard's armada of 100 ships (carrying 8,000 men) was struck by a violent storm. Several ships ran aground, including one holding Joan, his new fiancée Berengaria, and a large amount of treasure that had been amassed for the crusade. It was soon discovered that [[Isaac Dukas Comnenus]] of [[Cyprus]] had seized the treasure. The young women were unharmed. Richard entered [[Limassol]] on May 6, and met with Isaac, who agreed to return Richard's belongings and send 500 of his soldiers to the Holy Land. Once back at his fortress of [[Famagusta]], Isaac broke his oath of hospitality and began issuing orders for Richard to leave the island. Isaac's arrogance prompted Richard to conquer the island within days.

==Siege of Acre==
:''Full article: [[Siege of Acre (1189–1191)|Siege of Acre]]''

King Guy was released from prison by Saladin in 1189. He attempted to take command of the Christian forces at [[Tyre (Lebanon)|Tyre]], but [[Conrad of Montferrat]] held power there after his successful defence of the city from Muslim attacks. Guy turned his attention to the wealthy port of Acre. He amassed an army to besiege the city and received aid from Philip's newly arrived French army. However, it was still not enough to counter Saladin's force, which besieged the besiegers. In summer 1190, in one of the numerous outbreaks of disease in the camp, Queen Sibylla and her young daughters died. Guy, although only king by right of marriage, endeavoured to retain his crown, although the rightful heir was Sibylla's half-sister [[Isabella of Jerusalem|Isabella]]. After a hastily arranged divorce from [[Humphrey IV of Toron]], Isabella was married to Conrad of Montferrat, who claimed the kingship in her name.

During the winter of 1190–91, there were further outbreaks of dysentery and fever, which claimed the lives of [[Frederick VI, Duke of Swabia|Frederick of Swabia]], [[Patriarch Heraclius of Jerusalem]], and [[Theobald V of Blois]]. When the sailing season began again in spring 1191, [[Leopold V of Austria (Babenberg)|Leopold V of Austria]] arrived and took command of what remained of the imperial forces. Philip of France arrived with his troops from Sicily in May.

Richard arrived at Acre on June 8, 1191 and immediately began supervising the construction of siege weapons to assault the city. The city was captured on July 12.

Richard, Philip, and Leopold quarreled over the spoils of their victory. Richard cast down the German standard from the city, slighting Leopold. Also, in the struggle for the kingship of Jerusalem, Richard supported Guy, while Philip and Leopold supported Conrad, who was related to them both. It was decided that Guy would continue to rule, but that Conrad would receive the crown upon his death.

Frustrated with Richard (and in Philip's case, in poor health), Philip and Leopold took their armies and left the Holy Land in August. Philip left 10,000 French crusaders in the Holy Land and 5,000 silver marks to pay them.

Despite the treaty at Acre, Richard had the garrison (including women and children) massacred in full view of Saladin's camp. Not one prisoner could be saved in the subsequent effort Saladin made to rescue them by military force.&lt;ref&gt;[[Marshall Hodgson]], ''[[The Venture of Islam]] Conscience and History in a World Civilization Vol 2''. [[The University of Chicago]], 1958, pg. 267.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle of Arsuf==
:''Full article: [[Battle of Arsuf]]''

After the capture of Acre, Richard decided to march to the city of [[Jaffa]], where he could launch the attack on Jerusalem but on September 7, 1191, at [[Arsuf]], {{convert|30|mi|km|-1}} north of Jaffa, Saladin attacked Richard's army.

Saladin attempted to lure Richard's forces out to be easily picked off, but Richard maintained his formation until the [[Hospitallers]] rushed in to take Saladin's right flank, while the [[Knights Templar|Templars]] took the left. Richard then won the battle.

==Regicide and negotiations==
[[Image:Isle of Graia3.jpg|thumb|[[Saladin]] and [[Richard I of England|Richard]] assured the rights and protection of pilgrim and [[Caravan (travellers)|caravan]] routes that allowed [[travel]] to distant lands.]]
Following his victory, Richard took [[Jaffa]] and established his new headquarters there. He offered to begin negotiations with Saladin, who sent his brother, [[Al-Adil I|Al-Adil]] to meet with Richard. Negotiations (which had included an attempt to marry Richard's sister Joan to Al-Adil) failed, and Richard marched to [[Ashkelon|Ascalon]]. Richard's forces were halted nearly 12 times by the forces of Saladin commanded by [[Ayaz al-Tawil]] a powerful [[Mamluk]] leader, who died in combat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/71091453/The-Life-of-Saladin-Behaudin-Tekstualno |title=The Life of Saladin Behaudin Tekstualno |publisher=Scribd.com |date= |accessdate=2012-05-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Richard called on Conrad to join him on campaign, but he refused, citing Richard's alliance with King Guy. He too had been negotiating with [[Saladin]], as a defence against any attempt by Richard to wrest Tyre from him for Guy. However, in April, Richard was forced to accept Conrad as king of Jerusalem after an election by the nobles of the kingdom. Guy had received no votes at all, but Richard sold him Cyprus as compensation. Before he could be crowned, Conrad was stabbed to death by two [[Hashshashin]] in the streets of [[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]]. Eight days later, Richard's nephew [[Henry II of Champagne]] married Queen Isabella, who was pregnant with Conrad's child. It was strongly suspected that the king's killers had acted on instructions from Richard.

In July 1192, Saladin's army suddenly attacked and captured Jaffa with thousands of men, but Saladin had lost control of his army because of their anger for the massacre at [[Acre, Israel| Acre]]. It was believed that [[Saladin]] even told the Crusaders to shield themselves in the [[Citadel]] until he had regained control of his army.

On September 2, 1192, Richard and Saladin finalized a treaty by which [[Jerusalem]] would remain under [[Muslim]] control, but which also allowed unarmed Christian [[pilgrim]]s and [[trade]]rs to visit the city. Richard departed the [[Holy Land]] on October 9.

==Aftermath==
[[File:The Crusader States (1200).jpg|thumb|The Levant after the Third Crusade in 1200.|375px]]
Neither side was entirely discontent nor satisfied with the results of the war. Though Richard had deprived the Muslims of important coastal territories as a result of his consistent victories over Saladin, many Christians in the Latin West felt disappointed that he had elected not to pursue Jerusalem.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Procter
  | first = George
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = History of the crusades: their rise, progress, and results‏
  | publisher = R. Griffin and Co.
  | series =
  | volume =
  | edition =
  | year = ‏1854
  | location =
  | pages = 112–116
  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=Q8BmAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA92&amp;dq=Third+Crusade#v=onepage&amp;q=jerusalem&amp;f=false
  | doi =
  | isbn =
  | mr =
  | zbl =
  | jfm = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, many in the Islamic world felt disturbed that Saladin had failed to drive the Christians out of Syria and Palestine. Trade, however, flourished throughout the [[Middle East]] and in port cities along the [[Mediterranean Sea|Mediterranean]] coastline.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Crompton‏
  | first = Samuel Willard
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = The Third Crusade: Richard the Lionhearted vs. Saladin
  | publisher = [[Infobase Publishing‏]]
  | series = Great battles through the ages
  | volume =
  | edition =
  | year = 2003
  | location =
  | page = 64
  | url =
  | doi =
  | isbn =0-7910-7437-4
  | mr =
  | zbl =
  | jfm = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Saladin's servant and biographer Baha al-Din recounted Saladin's distress at the successes of the Crusaders:

&lt;blockquote&gt;'I fear to make peace, not knowing what may become of me. Our enemy will grow strong, now that they have retained these lands. They will come forth to recover the rest of their lands and you will see every one of them ensconced on his hill-top,' meaning in his castle, 'having announced, “I shall stay put” and the Muslims will be ruined.' These were his words and it came about as he said.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = al-Din
  | first = Baha
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors = D.S. Richards
  | title = The Rare and Excellent History of Saladin
  | publisher = [[Ashgate]]
  | series = Crusade Texts in Translation
  | volume = 7
  | edition = 1
  | year = 2002
  | location = Burlington, VT; Hampshire, England
  | page = 232
  | url =
  | doi =
  | isbn =0-7546-3381-0
  | mr =
  | zbl =
  | jfm = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Richard was arrested and imprisoned in December 1192 by [[Leopold V, Duke of Austria|Duke Leopold]], who suspected him of murdering his cousin Conrad of Montferrat, and had been offended by Richard casting down his standard from the walls of Acre. He was later transferred to the custody of [[Henry VI, Holy Roman Emperor]], and it took a ransom of one hundred and fifty thousand marks to obtain his release. Richard returned to [[England]] in 1194 and died of a crossbow bolt wound in 1199 at the age of 41.

In 1193, Saladin died of yellow fever. His heirs would quarrel over the succession and ultimately fragment his conquests.

Henry of Champagne was killed in an accidental fall in 1197. Queen Isabella then married for a fourth time, to [[Amalric II of Jerusalem|Amalric of Lusignan]], who had succeeded his brother Guy, positioned as King of Cyprus. After their deaths in 1205, her eldest daughter [[Maria of Montferrat]] (born after her father's murder) succeeded to the throne of Jerusalem.

Richard's decision not to attack Jerusalem would lead to the call for a [[Fourth Crusade]] six years after the third ended in 1192. However, Richard's victories facilitated the survival of a wealthy Crusader kingdom centered on Acre. Historian Thomas Madden summarizes the achievements of the Third Crusade:

&lt;blockquote&gt;...the Third Crusade was by almost any measure a highly successful expedition. Most of Saladin's victories in the wake of Hattin were wiped away. The Crusader kingdom was healed of its divisions, restored to its coastal cities, and secured in a peace with its greatest enemy. Although he had failed to reclaim Jerusalem, Richard had put the Christians of the Levant back on their feet again.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Madden
  | first = Thomas
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = The New Concise History of the Crusades
  | publisher = [[Rowman and Littlefield Publishers]]
  | series =
  | volume =
  | edition =
  | year = 2006
  | location = Lanham, Maryland
  | page = 95
  | url =
  | doi =
  | isbn =978-0-7425-3823-8
  | mr =
  | zbl =
  | jfm = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Accounts of events surrounding the Third Crusade were written by the anonymous authors of the ''Itinerarium Peregrinorum et Gesta Regis Ricardi'' (a.k.a. the ''[[Itinerarium Regis Ricardi]]''), the ''Old French Continuation of William of Tyre'' (parts of which are attributed to [[Ernoul]]), and by [[Ambroise]], [[Roger of Howden]], [[Ralph of Diceto]], and [[Giraldus Cambrensis]].

==References==
;References
{{reflist}}
;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
* [[Baha ad-Din ibn Shaddad|Beha-ed-Din]], ''The Life of Saladin''.
* ''De Expugnatione Terrae Sanctae per Saladinum'', translated by James A. Brundage, in ''The Crusades: A Documentary Survey''. Marquette University Press, 1962.
* ''La Continuation de Guillaume de Tyr (1184–1192)'', edited by Margaret Ruth Morgan. L'[[Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres]], 1982.
* [[Ambroise]], ''The History of the Holy War'', translated by Marianne Ailes. Boydell Press, 2003.
* Chronicle of the Third Crusade, a Translation of ''Itinerarium Peregrinorum et Gesta Regis Ricardi'', translated by Helen J. Nicholson. Ashgate, 1997.
* Peter W. Edbury, ''The Conquest of Jerusalem and the Third Crusade: Sources in Translation''. Ashgate, 1996.
* Francesco Gabrieli, (ed.) ''Arab Historians of the Crusades'', English translation 1969, ISBN 0-520-05224-2
* [[Steven Runciman]], ''A History of the Crusades, vol. II: The Kingdom of Jerusalem'', and vol. III: The Kingdom of Acre. [[Cambridge University Press]], 1952–55.
{{refend}}
*Lucas Villegas Aristizabal, &quot;Revisión de las crónicas de Ralph de Diceto y de la Gesta regis Ricardi sobre la participación de la flota angevina durante la Tercera Cruzada en Portugal&quot;, ''Studia Historica- Historia Medieval'' 27 (2009), pp.&amp;nbsp;153–170.

==External links==
*[http://www.historyavenue.com/third_crusade_1.html A History of the Third Crusade]

[[Category:Warfare of the Middle Ages]]
[[Category:Wars involving Arab Egypt]]
[[Category:Wars involving Cyprus]]
[[Category:12th-century crusades]]
[[Category:Third Crusade|*]]

{{Link GA|cs}}
{{Link FA|arz}}

[[ar:الحملة الصليبية الثالثة]]
[[an:Tercera cruzata]]
[[bn:তৃতীয় ক্রুসেড]]
[[be:Трэці крыжовы паход]]
[[bg:Трети кръстоносен поход]]
[[bs:Treći krstaški rat]]
[[br:Trede Kroaziadeg]]
[[ca:Tercera Croada]]
[[cs:Třetí křížová výprava]]
[[cy:Y Drydedd Groesgad]]
[[de:Dritter Kreuzzug]]
[[et:Kolmas ristisõda]]
[[el:Γ΄ Σταυροφορία]]
[[es:Tercera Cruzada]]
[[eu:Hirugarren Gurutzada]]
[[fa:جنگ سوم صلیبی]]
[[fr:Troisième croisade]]
[[ko:제3차 십자군]]
[[hr:Treći križarski rat]]
[[id:Perang Salib Ketiga]]
[[it:Terza crociata]]
[[he:מסע הצלב השלישי]]
[[jv:Perang Salib Katelu]]
[[ka:მესამე ჯვაროსნული ლაშქრობა]]
[[ku:Sefera xaçperestan a sêyem]]
[[la:Tertia expeditio sacra]]
[[mk:Трета крстоносна војна]]
[[arz:الحمله الصليبيه التالته]]
[[ms:Perang Salib Ketiga]]
[[mn:Загалмайтны гурав дахь аян]]
[[nl:Derde Kruistocht]]
[[ja:第3回十字軍]]
[[no:Det tredje korstog]]
[[pl:III wyprawa krzyżowa]]
[[pt:Terceira Cruzada]]
[[ro:Cruciada a treia]]
[[ru:Третий крестовый поход]]
[[sk:Tretia križiacka výprava]]
[[sl:Tretja križarska vojna]]
[[sr:Трећи крсташки рат]]
[[sh:Treći križarski rat]]
[[fi:Kolmas ristiretki]]
[[sv:Tredje korståget]]
[[th:สงครามครูเสดครั้งที่ 3]]
[[tr:Üçüncü Haçlı Seferi]]
[[uk:Третій хрестовий похід]]
[[ur:تیسری صلیبی جنگ]]
[[vi:Cuộc thập tự chinh thứ ba]]
[[zh:第三次十字军东征]]</text>
      <sha1>m2oann7nofrqr6lhb4m538lzge50u1w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
