<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Yuan Dynasty</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19606306</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522388184</id>
      <parentid>521300166</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T21:44:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TjBot</username>
        <id>11020855</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.2) (Robot: Adding [[als:Yuan-Dynastie]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="62495">{{Contains Chinese text}}
{{Infobox Former Country
|native_name            = &lt;big&gt;大元&lt;/big&gt;&lt;br&gt;Dai Ön Ulus
|conventional_long_name = Great Yuan
|common_name            = Yuan Dynasty
|continent              = Asia
|region                 = China
|country                = [[Mongol Empire]], [[China]]
|era                    = Middle ages
|status                 = Empire
|status_text            = '''Empire'''
|government_type        = [[Monarchy]]
|year_start             = 1279
|year_end               = 1368
|event_start            = Establishment
|date_start             = December 18
|event_end              = Fall of [[Khanbaliq|Dadu]]
|date_end               = September 14
|event_pre              = [[Genghis Khan]] was elected to be the emperor
|date_pre               = Spring, 1206
|event1                 = Conquest of Southern Song
|date_event1            = February 4, 1276
|event2                 = [[Battle of Yamen]]
|date_event2            = 1279
|event3                 =
|date_event3            =
|event4                 =
|date_event4            =
|event_pre              =
|date_pre               =
|event_post             =
|date_post              =
|p1                     = Mongol Empire
|flag_p1                =  White Sulde of the Mongol Empire.jpg
|image_p1               =
|p2                     = Song Dynasty
|flag_p2                =
|p3                     =
|flag_p3                =
|p4                     =
|flag_p4                =
|p5                     =
|flag_p5                =
|s1                     = Northern Yuan Dynasty
|flag_s1                =
|image_s1               =
|s2                     = Ming Dynasty
|flag_s2                =
|s3                     =
|flag_s3                =
|s4                     =
|flag_s4                =
|s5                     =
|flag_s5                =
|
|image_flag             =
|flag                   =
|flag_type              =
|
|image_coat             =
|symbol                 =
|symbol_type            =
|image_map              = Yuen Dynasty 1294 - Goryeo as vassal.png
|image_map_caption      = Yuan Dynasty in 1294 ([[Goryeo]] as vassal)
|capital                = [[Karakorum]], [[Khanbaliq|Dadu]] (modern [[Beijing]]), [[Xanadu|Shangdu]]
|capital_exile          =
|latd=39|latm=54|latNS=N|longd=116|longm=23|longEW=
|
|national_motto         =
|national_anthem        =
|common_languages       = [[Chinese language|Chinese]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mongolian language|Mongolian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Persian language|Persian]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YJibpHfnw94C&amp;dq=pusuman&amp;q=three+official+languages+yuan+china+mongolian+chinese+persian#v=snippet&amp;q=three%20official%20languages%20yuan%20china%20mongolian%20chinese%20persian&amp;f=false|title=Aspects of the Maritime Silk Road: From the Persian Gulf to the East China Sea|author=Ralph Kauz|editor=Ralph Kauz|year=2010|publisher=Otto Harrassowitz Verlag|edition=illustrated|location=|page=89|isbn=3-447-06103-0|pages=|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|religion               =  [[Buddhism]] ([[Chinese Buddhism|Chinese]] &amp; [[Tibetan Buddhism|Tibetan]]), [[Taoism]], [[Confucianism]], [[Chinese folk religion]], as well as [[Shamanism]]/[[Tengriism]], [[Christianity]] ([[Church of the East|Nestorian]]), [[Islam]]
|currency               = Predominantly [[Banknote|Paper Currency]] ([[Chao (currency)|Chao]]), with a small amount of [[Cash (Chinese coin)|Chinese cash]] in use
|
|leader1                = Kublai Khan
|leader2                = Ukhaatu Khan
|year_leader1           = 1260–1294
|year_leader2           = 1333–1370 (Cont.)
|leader_pre             = Genghis Khan
|year_leader_pre        = 1206–1227
|title_leader           = [[List of Emperors of the Yuan Dynasty|Emperor]]
|stat_year1             = 1310 est.
|stat_area1             = 14000000
|stat_pop1              =
|
|title_deputy = [[Chancellor of China|Chancellor]]
|legislature  =
|stat_year1 = 1290
|stat_area1 =
|stat_pop1  =75,306,000
|stat_year2 = 1293
|stat_area2 =
|stat_pop2  = 79,816,000
|stat_year3 = 1330
|stat_area3 =
|stat_pop3  = 84873000
|stat_year4 =1351
|stat_area4 =
|stat_pop4  =87587000
}}
{{History of China}}

The '''Yuan Dynasty''' ({{zh|c={{linktext|元|朝}}}}, &lt;small&gt;[[pinyin|p]]&lt;/small&gt; ''[[:wikt:元朝|Yuán Cháo]]''; [[Classical Mongolian language|Classical Mongolian]]: [[File:Dai Ön Yeke Mongghul Ulus.PNG|70px]] ''Dai Ön Yeke Mongghul Ulus''; [[Mongolian language|Modern Mongolian]]: [[File:Их Юань улс.PNG|70px]] {{lang|mn|''Их Юань улс''}}&lt;ref name=&quot;mname&quot;&gt;Also the ''Yekhe Yuan Ulus''. According to some sources such as Volker Rybatzki &amp; Igor de Rachewiltz's ''The Early Mongols: Language, Culture and History'' (p. 116), the full Mongolian name was ''Dai Ön Yeke Mongghul Ulus''.&lt;/ref&gt;) was the empire established by [[Kublai Khan]], the leader of [[Mongolian]] [[Borjigin]] clan, after [[Mongol Empire|Mongol]] conquered [[Jin Dynasty (1115–1234) |Jin]] and [[Southern Song Dynasty]] in [[China]]. Although the Mongols had ruled territories, which included today's northern China for decades, it was not until 1271 that Kublai Khan officially proclaimed the dynasty in the traditional Chinese style.&lt;ref&gt;Cambridge History of China, vol 6, p624&lt;/ref&gt; His realm{{spaced ndash}}the '''Great Yuan Empire''' (&lt;small&gt;[[traditional characters|t]]&lt;/small&gt; {{linktext|大|元|帝國}}, &lt;small&gt;[[simplified characters|s]]&lt;/small&gt; {{linktext|大|元|帝国}}, &lt;small&gt;[[pinyin|p]]&lt;/small&gt; ''Dà Yuán Dìguó''){{spaced ndash}}was by this point isolated from the other khanates and controlled only most of present-day [[China]] and its surrounding areas including modern [[Mongolia]].&lt;ref&gt;Christopher P.Atwood – Encyclopedia of Mongolia and the [[Mongol Empire]]&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first foreign dynasty to rule all of China and lasted until 1368, after which its remnants in Mongolia were known as the [[Northern Yuan Dynasty|Northern Yuan]].

The Yuan is considered both a successor to the [[Mongol Empire]] and as an imperial [[Dynasties in Chinese history|Chinese dynasty]]. In [[Chinese historiography|official Chinese histories]], the Yuan Dynasty bore the [[Mandate of Heaven]], following the [[Song Dynasty (960-1279)|Song Dynasty]] and preceding the [[Ming Dynasty]]. Although the dynasty was established by [[Kublai Khan]], he placed his grandfather [[Genghis Khan]] on the imperial records as the official founder of the dynasty as [[List of emperors of the Yuan Dynasty|Taizu]]. 

In addition to [[Emperor of China]], Kublai Khan also claimed the title of [[Great Khan]], supreme over the other successor khanates: the [[Chagatai Khanate|Chagatai]], the [[Golden Horde]], and the [[Ilkhanate]]. As such, the Great Yuan Empire was also sometimes referred to as the '''Empire of the Great Khan'''. However, although this claim of the emperors of the Yuan Dynasty was at times recognized by the western khans, their subservience was merely nominal and they each continued their own separate development.&lt;ref&gt;Micheal Prwadin – The Mongol Empire and its legacy&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;J.J.Saunders – The history of Mongol conquests&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rene Grousset – The Empire of Steppes&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Cleanup|section|date=March 2011}}
{{History of Mongolia}}

===Kublai Khan and Ariq Böke===
In 1259 Great Khan [[Möngke]] died while [[Kublai Khan]], his brother, was campaigning against the [[Song Dynasty]] in [[Northern and southern China|South China]] and [[Ariq Böke]], his other brother, commanded the Mongol homelands. A ''khuraldai'', or the great assembly of higher nobility took place in [[Karakorum]], then the capital of the Mongol Empire, which proclaimed Ariq Böke as the Great Khan in the traditional Mongolian style. Hearing of this, Kublai aborted his Chinese expedition and gathered another great assembly at his headquarters in the city of Kaiping ([[Shangdu]] in present-day [[Inner Mongolia]]) and, in 1260, he was proclaimed the Great Khan. However, this assembly convened by Kublai was deemed illegitimate from the perspective of the Mongolian tradition of throne inheritance: the empire already had Ariq Böke as legitimate Great Khan, who was in the capital.&lt;ref&gt;Dalai, Ch. The struggle for the Khaan throne during Kublai and his successors. - In: Tataro-Mongoly v Azii i Evrope. Moscow, 1977, p.325.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, it was said that that Kublai made extensive use of bribery of princes. Ariq Böke sent an ambassador to his brother: &quot;By the state's law, the Great Khan is proclaimed by the great assembly, but you have ignored the supreme doctrine; sitting in China and, following Chinese laws, you are acting autocratically.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ganbold et al., 2006. Ganbold, J., Munhtsetseg, T. Naran, A.D. and Puntsag, A. 2006. Mongolyn Yuan uls [The Mongolian Yuan State]. Ulaanbaatar.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kublai declared Ariq Böke to be a usurper, and, following the traditional Chinese custom, proclaimed the era name to be &quot;Zhong-tong&quot;. According to Chinese history, Kublai Khan gained the title of Emperor (''huang di''), although the Chinese [[Song Dynasty]] at that time still resisted him in South China. In 1261–1264, he fought against his brother, and eventually Ariq Böke was defeated and surrendered to Kublai. As the winning Great Khan, Kublai Khan now expected the allegiance of other khanates.

However, at this time the khans of the [[Golden Horde]] and of the [[Chagatai Khanate]] did not recognize Kublai Khan as the Great Khan. The conflicts between Kublai Khan and the khanates in [[Central Asia]] led by [[Kaidu]] had lasted for a few decades, until the beginning of the 14th century, when both of them had died. [[Hulagu Khan|Hülegü]], another brother of Kublai Khan, ruled his [[Ilkhanate]] and paid homage to the Great Khan but actually established an [[autonomous]] khanate, and after [[Ghazan|Ilkhan Ghazan]]'s enthronement in 1295, Kublai's successor [[Temür Khan, Emperor Chengzong of Yuan|Emperor Chengzong]] sent him a [[Seal (East Asia)|seal]] reading &quot;王府定國理民之寶&quot; in Chinese script to symbolize this.&lt;ref&gt;[[File:GhazanSeal1302LetterToBonifaceVIII.JPG|thumb|[[Seal (Chinese)|Seal]] of the Ilkhan Ghazan in a 1302 letter to [[Pope Boniface VIII]].]] The seal, in Chinese script, reads &quot;Seal certifying the authority of his Royal Highness to establish a country and govern its people&quot;. [[Vatican Library|Vatican]] Archives.&lt;/ref&gt; The four major successor khanates never came again under true one rule, and border clashes also frequently occurred among them, although Yuan Dynasty's nominal supremacy was recognized by the other three after the death of Kaidu.&lt;ref&gt;H.H.Howorth-History of the Mongols, vol.II p.288&lt;/ref&gt;

===Founding of the Dynasty===
[[File:YuanEmperorAlbumKhubilaiPortrait.jpg|thumb|200px|left|[[Kublai Khan]], [[Genghis Khan]]'s grandson and founder of the Yuan Dynasty]]
From the beginning of his reign (1260), Kublai Khan had adopted many customs from earlier Chinese dynasties, such as [[Chinese era name|era names]] and bureaucracy. He had several Chinese teachers attached to him since his early years. Not only did they explain him the Chinese history and ideology, but also permanently gave advice on governance.&lt;ref&gt;Dalai, 1977, op. cit., p.324.&lt;/ref&gt;

After winning the war against Ariq Böke, Kublai Khan began his reign over his empire with greater aspirations and self-confidence. In 1264, he transferred his headquarters to be near the capital of the former Jurchen [[Jin Dynasty (1115-1234)|Jin Dynasty]]. In 1266 he ordered the construction of his new capital at that site, in what is now the modern city of [[Beijing]]. The city had been called Zhongdu ({{zh|中都}}, lit. &quot;Central Capital&quot;) during the Jin Dynasty, and in 1272 it came to be known as [[Khanbaliq|Dadu]] ({{zh|c=大都|w=Ta-tu}}, &quot;Great Capital&quot;) in Chinese, Daidu to the Mongols, and Khanbalykh (&quot;City of the Khans&quot;) to the Turks.&lt;ref&gt;Rossabi, M., ''Khubilai Khan'', p131.&lt;/ref&gt; As early as 1264, Kublai decided to change the era name from Zhong-tong (中統) to Zhi-yuan (至元). With the desire to rule all of China, Kublai Khan formally claimed the [[Mandate of Heaven]] by proclaiming the new Yuan Dynasty in 1271 in the traditional Chinese style.&lt;ref&gt;Cambridge History of China, vol 6, p624&lt;/ref&gt; This would become the first non-Han dynasty to rule all of China.

The official title of the Dynasty, Da Yuan ({{zh|c=大元}}, &quot;Great Yuan&quot;), originates from a [[Chinese classics|Chinese classic text]] called ''[[I Ching]]'', &quot;大哉乾元&quot; (dà zāi qián yuán), literally translating to 'Great is the Heavenly and Primal', with &quot;qián&quot; being the symbol of the Heaven, and the Emperor. Therefore, Yuan was the first [[dynasty in China]] to use Da ({{zh|c=大}}, &quot;Great&quot;) in its official title, as well as being the first dynasty to use a title that did not correspond to an ancient region in China.&lt;ref&gt;[[Zhu Guozhen (Ming Dynasty)|Zhu Guozhen]] (1557–1632), ''Yong Zhuang Xiaopin'' (涌幢小品) Vol.2.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1272, Dadu officially became the capital of the Yuan Dynasty.

In the early 1270s, Kublai began his massive drive against [[Song Dynasty|Southern Song Dynasty]] in South China. By 1273, Kublai had blockaded the [[Yangzi River]] with his navy and besieged [[Xiangyang District, Xiangfan|Xiangyang]], the last obstacle in his way to capture the rich Yangzi River basin. In 1275, a Song force of 130,000 troops under [[Chancellor of China|Chancellor]] [[Jia Sidao]] was defeated by the Yuan force. By 1276, most of the Southern Song territory had been captured by Yuan forces. In 1279, the Yuan army led by the Chinese general [[Zhang Hongfan]] had crushed the last Song resistance at the [[Battle of Yamen]], which marked the end of the Southern Song and the onset of a united China under the Yuan. The Yuan Dynasty is traditionally given credit for reuniting China after several hundred years of fragmentation following the fall of the [[Tang Dynasty]].

After the founding of the dynasty, Kublai Khan was put under pressure by many of his advisers to further expand the sphere of influence of the Yuan through the traditional [[Sinocentrism|Sinocentric]] tributary system. However, the attempts to establish such tributary relationships were rebuffed and expeditions to [[Mongol invasions of Japan|Japan]] (twice), [[Mongol invasions of Vietnam|Dai Viet]] (twice during Kublai's rule&lt;ref&gt;An earlier expedition had failed in 1257/1258.&lt;/ref&gt;), and [[Mongol invasion of Java|Java]], would later meet with less success. Kublai established a puppet state in [[Mongol invasion of Burma|Myanmar]], which caused anarchy in the area, and the [[Pagan Kingdom]] was broken up into many regions warring with each another. In order to avoid more bloodshed and conflicts with the Mongols, Annam and [[Champa]] later established nominal tributary relations with the Yuan Dynasty.

===Rule of Kublai Khan===

Unlike his predecessors, Kublai established a government with institutions resembling the ones in earlier Chinese dynasties and made reforms to maintain his centralized rule.&lt;ref&gt;The Cambridge History of China, Volume 6, pg 424&lt;/ref&gt;

Kublai Khan was seen as a martial emperor, reforming much of China and its institutions, a process that would have taken decades to complete. For example, he consolidated his rule by centralizing &lt;ref name=&quot;Wood, F. 1995 p. 1-7&quot;&gt;Wood, F. (1995). &quot;Did Marco Polo go to China?&quot;, p. 1-7&lt;/ref&gt; the government of China &amp;mdash; making himself (unlike his predecessors) an [[absolute monarchy|absolute monarch]]. He divided his empire into ''Xing Zhongshusheng'' (行中書省), usually translated as &quot;branch Secretariat&quot; or &quot;province&quot;, each governing the areas of approximately two or three modern-day Chinese provinces, and this provincial-level government structure became the model for later [[Ming Dynasty|Ming]] and [[Qing Dynasty|Qing]] dynasties. Kublai Khan also reformed many other governmental and economic institutions, especially the tax system. Kublai Khan sought to govern China through traditional institutions,&lt;ref&gt;Rossabi, M. ''Khubilai Khan: His Life and Times'', p56&lt;/ref&gt; and also recognized that in order to rule China he needed to employ [[Han Chinese]] advisers and officials, though he never relied totally on Chinese advisers.&lt;ref&gt;Rossabi, M. ''Khubilai Khan: His Life and Times'', p115&lt;/ref&gt; Yet, the Hans were discriminated against politically. Almost all important central posts were monopolized by Mongols, who also preferred employing non-Hans from other parts of the Mongol domain in those positions for which no Mongol could be found. Hans were more often employed in non-Chinese regions of the empire{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}. In essence, society was divided into four classes in order of privilege: Mongols, [[Semu]] (&quot;Various sorts&quot;, for example: Central Asians), Northerners, and Southerners.&lt;ref&gt;Ed. Herbert Franke, Denis Twitchett, John King Fairbank-''The Cambridge History of China: Alien regimes and border states'', 907-1368, p. 631&lt;/ref&gt; During his lifetime, Kublai Khan built the capital of the Yuan, [[Khanbaliq|Dadu]], which is present-day Beijing, and made [[Xanadu|Shangdu]] ({{zh|c=上都}}, &quot;Upper Capital&quot;, known to [[Marco Polo]] as Xanadu) the summer capital. He also improved the agriculture of China, extending the [[Grand Canal (China)|Grand Canal]], highways and public granaries. Marco Polo, a Venetian merchant who served under Kublai Khan as an official, described his rule as benevolent: relieving the populace of taxes in times of hardship; building hospitals and orphanages; distributing food among the abjectly poor.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

[[File:Yuen Dynasty 1294 - Goryeo as vassal.png|thumb|300px|right|Yuan Dynasty 1294 circa, Goryeo as vassal]]
He also promoted science and religion, and strongly supported the [[Silk Road]] trade network, allowing the contacts between Chinese technologies and the western ones. It is worth mentioning that prior to meeting Marco Polo, Kublai Khan had met Nicolo Polo, Marco Polo's father and Matteo Polo. Through conversation with the two merchants, Kublai Khan developed a keen interest in the Latin world especially Christianity and sought to invite a hundred of missionaries through a letter written in Latin to the Pope so that they may convince the masses of idolators the errors of their belief. Thus Niccolo and Maffeo Polo served as ambasadors for Kublai Khan to the West. After having completed their mission of accompanying a young Mongol princess to marry the Mongol ruler Arghun, their perilous journey would end with them returning to Venice and meeting young Marco Polo of seventeen in 1271. The three returned to the East and once again met with Kublai Khan, and it was said that Marco Polo served as an emissary of Kublai Khan throughout his domain for seventeen years. Although Nicolo and Maffeo failed to bring back any missionaries with them or a letter from the Pope due to the Great Schism, they were successful in returning with oil from the lamp of God in Jerusalem.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wood, F. 1995 p. 1-7&quot;/&gt; Marco Polo's travels would later inspire many others like Christopher Columbus to chart the passage to the &quot;Middle Kingdom&quot; the realm of the East, present day China in search of wealth and splendor.

[[File:Yuan dynasty banknote with its printing plate 1287.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Yuan dynasty [[banknote]] with its printing plate, 1287.]]
He issued paper [[banknote]]s known as [[Chao (currency)|Chao]] (鈔) in 1273. Paper currency had been issued and used in China before Yuan time; by 960, the Song Dynasty, short of copper for striking coins, issued the first generally circulating notes. However, during the Song Dynasty, paper money was used alongside the coins. On the other hand, Yuan was the first dynasty in China to use paper currency as the predominant circulating medium. The Yuan bureaucrats made paper bills from the mulberry bark paper.

While he had claimed nominal supremacy over the rest of the Mongol Empire, his interest was clearly in China, along with the areas in its traditional [[Sinocentrism|Sinocentric]] tributary system. From the beginning of his reign, the other three khanates of the Mongol Empire became de facto independent and only one recognized him as [[Khagan]]. By the time of Kublai Khan’s death in 1294, this separation has deepened, although later Yuan emperors had nominal supremacy in the west til the end of their rule in China. The [[temple name]] given for Kublai Khan is Shizu ({{zh|c=世祖}}).

===Early rulers after Kublai===
[[File:Belt plaque with dragon design.jpg|thumb|200px|right|A Yuan Dynasty [[jade]] belt plaque featuring carved designs of a [[Chinese dragon|dragon]].]]
Succession was a problem for the Yuan Dynasty, later causing much strife and internal struggle. This emerged as early as the end of Kublai's reign. Kublai originally named his eldest son, [[Zhenjin]] ({{zh|c=真金}}) as the [[Crown Prince]] ({{zh|c=皇太子}}) &amp;mdash; but he died before Kublai in 1285. Thus, Zhenjin's third son, with the support of his mother Kökejin and the minister [[Bayan of the Baarin|Bayan]], succeeded the throne and ruled as [[Temür Khan, Emperor Chengzong of Yuan|Temür Khan]] or Emperor Chengzong for approximately 10 years following Kublai's death (between 1294 and 1307). Temür Khan decided to maintain and continue much of the work begun by his grandfather. He also made peace with the western Mongol khanates as well as the neighboring countries such as Vietnam, which recognized his nominal suzerainty and paid tributes for a few decades. However, the corruption in the Yuan Dynasty began during the reign of Temür Khan.

[[Külüg Khan, Emperor Wuzong of Yuan|Külüg Khan]] (Emperor Wuzong) came to the throne after the death of Temür Khan. Unlike his predecessor, he did not continue Kublai's work, but largely rejected it. Most significantly he introduced a policy called &quot;New Deals&quot;, and the central of this policy were monetary reforms. During his short reign (1307 to 1311), the government fell into financial difficulties, partly due to bad decisions made by Külüg. By the time he died, China was in severe debt and the Yuan court faced popular discontent.

The fourth Yuan emperor, [[Ayurbarwada Buyantu Khan, Emperor Renzong of Yuan|Buyantu Khan]] (Ayurbarwada) was a competent emperor. He was the first among the Yuan emperors who actively supported and adopted the mainstream [[Culture of China|Chinese culture]] after the reign of Kublai, to the discontent of some Mongol elite. He had been mentored by [[Li Meng (Yuan Dynasty)|Li Meng]], a [[Confucian]] academic. He made many reforms, including the liquidation of the Department of State Affairs ({{lang-zh|尚書省}}), which resulted in the execution of 5 of the highest ranking officials. Starting in 1313 the traditional [[imperial examination]]s were reintroduced for prospective officials, testing their knowledge on significant historical works. Also, he codified much of the law, as well as publishing or translating a number of Chinese books and works.

The next emperor, [[Gegeen Khan, Emperor Yingzong of Yuan|Gegeen Khan]], Ayurbarwada's son and successor, continued his father's policies to reform the government based on the Confucian principles, with the help of his newly appointed grand [[Chancellor of China|chancellor]] Baiju. During his reign, the Da Yuan Tong Zhi ([[Chinese language|Chinese]]: 大元通制, &quot;the comprehensive institutions of the Great Yuan&quot;), a huge collection of codes and regulations of the Yuan Dynasty began by his father, was formally promulgated.

===Later years of the Dynasty===
[[File:BailinTemple2.jpg|thumb|200px|left|The [[Pagoda of Bailin Temple|Bailin Temple Pagoda]] of Zhaoxian County, [[Hebei]] Province, built in 1330 during the Yuan Dynasty.]]
The last years of the Yuan Dynasty were marked by struggle, famine, and bitterness among the populace. The dynasty was, significantly, one of the shortest-lived dynasties in the [[history of China]], covering just a century, 1271 to 1368. In time, Kublai Khan's successors lost all influence on other Mongol lands across Asia, while the Mongols beyond the Middle Kingdom saw them as too Chinese. Gradually, they lost influence in China as well. The reigns of the later Yuan emperors were short and were marked by intrigues and rivalries. Uninterested in administration, they were separated from both the army and the populace. China was torn by dissension and unrest; [[outlaw]]s ravaged the country without interference from the weakening Yuan armies.

Regardless of the merits of his reign, [[Emperor Yingzong of Yuan China|Shidebala]] (Emperor Yingzong) ruled for only two years (1321 to 1323); his rule ended in a [[coup]] at the hands of five princes. They placed [[Emperor Taidingdi of Yuan China|Yesün Temür]] (or Taidingdi) on the throne, and, after an unsuccessful attempt to calm the princes, he also succumbed to [[regicide]]. Before Yesün Temür's reign, China had been relatively free from popular rebellions after the reign of Kublai. Yuan control, however, began to break down in those regions inhabited by ethnic minorities. The occurrence of these revolts and the subsequent suppression aggravated the financial difficulties of the Yuan government. The government had to adopt some measure to increase revenue such as selling offices, as well as curtailing its spending on some items.&lt;ref&gt;The Cambridge History of China By Denis Twitchett, Herbert Franke, John K. Fairbank, vol6, p.551&lt;/ref&gt;

When Yesün Temür died in Shangdu in 1328, [[Jayaatu Khan, Emperor Wenzong of Yuan|Tugh Temür]] was recalled to Dadu by the [[Qipchaq]] commander [[El Temür]]. He was installed as the emperor (Emperor Wenzong) in Dadu while Yesün Temür's son [[Ragibagh]] succeeded to the throne in Shangdu with the support of Yesün Temür's favorite retainer Dawlat Shah. Gaining support from princes and officers in Northern China and some other parts of the dynasty, Dadu-based Tugh Temür eventually won the civil war against Ragibagh in 1329. Afterwards, Tugh Temür abdicated in favour of his brother [[Kusala]] who was backed by Chagatai Khan [[Eljigidey]] and announced Dadu's intent to welcome him. However, Kusala suddenly died only 4 days after a banquet with Tugh Temür. He was supposedly killed with poison by El Temür, and Tugh Temür then remounted the throne. Tugh Temür also managed to send delegates to the western Mongol khanates such as [[Golden Horde]] and [[Ilkhanate]] to be accepted as the suzerain of Mongol world.&lt;ref&gt;The Cambridge History of China By Denis Twitchett, Herbert Franke, John K. Fairbank, vol6, p.550&lt;/ref&gt; However, he was mainly a puppet of the powerful official El Temür during his latter three-year reign. El Temür purged pro-Kusala officials and brought power to warlords, whose despotic rule clearly marked the decline of the dynasty.

[[File:Yuan coinage.jpg|thumb|right|Yuan coinage.]]
Due to the fact that the bureaucracy was dominated by El Temür, Tugh Temür is known for his cultural contribution instead. He adopted many measures honoring [[Confucianism]] and promoting [[Culture of China|Chinese cultural values]]. His most concrete effort to patronize Chinese learning was his founding of the Academy of the Pavilion of the Star of Literature ({{lang-zh|奎章閣學士院}}), first established in the spring of 1329, and was designed to undertake &quot;a number of tasks relating to the transmission of Confucian high culture to the Mongolian imperial establishment&quot;. The academy was responsible for compiling and publishing a number of books, but its most important achievement was its compilation of a vast institutional [[compendium]] named Jingshi Dadian ({{lang-zh|經世大典}}). He supported [[Zhu Xi]]'s [[Neo-Confucianism]] and also devoted himself in [[Buddhism]].

After the death of Tugh Temür in 1332 and subsequently the death of [[Rinchinbal Khan, Emperor Ningzong of Yuan|Rinchinbal]] (Emperor Ningzong) in the end of the same year, the 13-year-old [[Toghun Temür]] (Emperor Huizong), the last of the nine successors of Kublai Khan, was summoned back from [[Guangxi]] and succeeded to the throne after El Temür's death. Nevertheless, [[Bayan of the Merkid|Bayan]] became another powerful official as El Temür was in the beginning of his long reign. As Toghun Temür grew, he came to disapprove of Bayan's autocratic rule. In 1340 he allied himself with Bayan's nephew [[Toghtogha]], who was in discord with Bayan, and banished Bayan by coup. With the dismissal of Bayan, Toghtogha seized the power of the court. His first administration clearly exhibited fresh new spirit. He also gave a few early signs of a new and positive direction in central government. One of his successful projects was to finish the long-stalled official histories of the [[Liao Dynasty|Liao]], [[Jin Dynasty (1115–1234)|Jin]] and [[Song Dynasty|Song]] dynasties, which were eventually completed in 1345. Yet, Toghtogha resigned his office with the approval of Toghun Temür, which marked the end of his first administration, and he was not called back until 1349.

From the late 1340s onwards, people in the countryside suffered from frequent natural disasters such as droughts, floods and the resulting famines, and the government's lack of effective policy led to a loss of popular support. In 1351, the [[Red Turban Rebellion]] started and grew into a nationwide uprising. In 1354, when Toghtogha led a large army to crush the Red Turban rebels, Toghun Temür suddenly dismissed him for fear of betrayal. This resulted in Toghun Temür's restoration of power on the one hand and a rapid weakening of the central government on the other. He had no choice but to rely on local warlords' military power, and gradually lost his interest in politics and ceased to intervene in political struggles. He fled north to [[Shangdu]] from Dadu (present-day Beijing) in 1368 after the approach of the forces of the [[Míng Dynasty]] (1368–1644), founded by [[Zhu Yuanzhang]] in the south. He had tried to regain Dadu, which eventually failed; he died in [[Yingchang]] (located in present-day [[Inner Mongolia]]) two years later (1370). Yingchang was seized by the Ming shortly after his death. Some royal family members still lived in [[Henan]] today.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.xinmin.cn/domestic/zonghe/2007/02/06/149732.html 成吉思汗直系后裔现身河南巨幅家谱为证(组图)_新民网]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Prince of Liang]], [[Basalawarmi]] established a separate pocket of resistance to the Ming in [[Yunnan]] and [[Guizhou]], but his forces were decisively defeated by the Ming in 1381. By 1388 the remaining Yuan forces in [[Manchuria]] under Nahacu had also surrendered to the Ming Dynasty.

===Northern Yuan===
{{Main|Northern Yuan Dynasty}}
The Yuan remnants retreated to Mongolia after the fall of Yingchang to the Ming in 1370, where the name Great Yuan (大元) was formally carried on, and is known as the '''Northern Yuan''' (北元). According to Chinese political orthodoxy, there could be only one legitimate dynasty whose rulers were blessed by [[Heaven]] to rule as [[Emperor of China]] (see [[Mandate of Heaven]]), and so the Ming and the Northern Yuan denied each other's legitimacy as emperors of China, although the Ming did consider the previous Yuan which it had succeeded to be a legitimate dynasty. Historians generally regard [[Míng Dynasty]] rulers as the legitimate emperors of China after the Yuan Dynasty, though Northern Yuan rulers also claimed to rule over China, and continued to resist the Ming under the name &quot;Yuan&quot; or &quot;Northern Yuan&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The Northern Yuan rulers had also buttressed their claim on China at least up to the 15th century, who held tenaciously to the title of Emperor (or Great Khan) of the Great Yuan (Dai Yuwan Khaan, or 大元可汗). For more information regarding the use of the name Yuan among Mongols and the memory of it in later ages, see [https://qir.kyushu-u.ac.jp/dspace/bitstream/2324/9498/1/scs14p065.pdf].&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ming army pursued the Northern Yuan forces into Mongolia in 1372, but were defeated by the latter under [[Biligtü Khan, Emperor Zhaozong of Northern Yuan|Ayushridar]] and his general [[Köke Temür]]. They tried again in 1380, ultimately winning a decisive victory over Northern Yuan in 1388. Many Mongols were taken prisoner, and [[Karakorum (palace)|Karakorum]] (the Northern Yuan capital) was sacked in 1380. Eight years later, the Northern Yuan throne was taken over by [[Jorightu Khan, Emperor Xingyuan of Northern Yuan|Yesüder]], a descendant of [[Ariq Böke]], instead of the descendants of [[Kublai Khan]]. The following centuries saw a succession of Genghisid rulers, many of whom were mere figureheads put on the throne by those warlords who happened to be the most powerful. Periods of conflict with the Ming Dynasty intermingled with periods of peaceful relations with border trade. In 1402, [[Örüg Temür Khan]] (Guilichi) abolished the name Great Yuan; he was however defeated by [[Öljei Temür Khan]] (Bunyashiri), protege of [[Tamerlane]] (Timur Barulas) in 1403. A few decades later the new khan [[Dayan Khan|Batumongke]] (1464–1517/43) took the title ''Dayan'' meaning &quot;Da Yuan&quot; or &quot;Great Yuan&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[https://qir.kyushu-u.ac.jp/dspace/handle/2324/9498 Memory of the Dai Yuan ulus (the Great Yuan dynasty)]&lt;/ref&gt; and reunited the Mongols. His successors continued to rule until the submission to the [[Qing Dynasty]], ending the Northern Yuan in 1635.

==Impact==
[[File:Yuan Dynasty, porcelain dish, mid 14th century.jpg|thumb|left|A Yuan Dynasty blue-and-white [[porcelain]] dish with fish and flowing water design, mid fourteenth century, [[Freer Gallery of Art]].]]
[[File:Yuan chinese gun.jpg|thumb|right|[[Hand cannon]] from the Yuan Dynasty]]
[[File:ArmenianArchibishopJean1287.jpg|left|thumb|Archbishop John of Cilician Armenia, in a painting from 1287. His dress displays a [[Chinese dragon]], an indication of the thriving exchanges with the Mongols during the period.]]
A rich cultural diversity developed during the Yuan Dynasty. The major cultural achievements were the development of [[drama]] and the [[novel]] and the increased use of the [[Vernacular Chinese|written vernacular]]. The political unity of China and much of central Asia promoted trade between East and West. The Mongols' extensive West Asian and European contacts produced a fair amount of cultural exchange. The other cultures and peoples in the [[Mongol World Empire]] also very much influenced China. It had significantly eased trade and commerce across [[Asia]] until its decline; the communications between Yuan Dynasty and its ally and subordinate in [[Persia]], the [[Ilkhanate]], encouraged this development.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory G.Guzman - Were the barbarians a negative or positive factor in ancient and medieval history?, The historian 50 (1988), 568-70&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas T.Allsen - Culture and conquest in Mongol Eurasia, 211&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhism had a great influence in the Yuan government, and the Tibetan-rite [[Tantric Buddhism]] had significantly influenced China during this period. The Muslims of the Yuan Dynasty introduced [[Middle Eastern]] [[cartography]], [[astronomy]], medicine, clothing, and diet in East Asia. Middle Eastern crops such as [[carrot]]s, [[turnip]]s, new varieties of [[lemon]]s, [[eggplant]]s, and [[melon]]s, high-quality granulated [[sugar]], and [[cotton]] were all either introduced or successfully popularized during the Yuan Dynasty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mongol Empire p.611&quot;&gt;C.P.Atwood- Encyclopedia of Mongolia and the Mongol Empire, p.611&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Plate; Yuan Dynasty; Lacquer, wood, and fabric.jpg|thumb|A plate made of [[lacquerware| lacquer]], wood, and paper from the Yuan dynasty. The Chinese were able to perfect a method of making [[laquerware| lacquer]]. Decorating this plate are parrots and peonies. The parrot was a symbol of fidelity; and because of its ability to mimic human speech, it was believed to be a suitable companion to a woman whose husband was away from home.  The bird would be able to inform each person of the other's activities. The peony was a symbol of female virtue. When shown in full bloom, it is a token of love, affection, and feminine beauty.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite book | last1 = Birmingham Museum of Art | title = Birmingham Museum of Art: A Guide to the Collection | publisher = Giles | year = 2010 | location = London | pages = 28 | url = http://www.birminghammuseumstore.org/bmapu.html | accessdate = 2011-07-01 | isbn = 978-1-904832-77-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[Birmingham Museum of Art]].]]

Western musical instruments were introduced to enrich Chinese performing arts. From this period dates the conversion to [[Islam]], by Muslims of Central Asia, of growing numbers of Chinese in the northwest and southwest. [[Nestorianism]] and [[Roman Catholicism]] also enjoyed a period of toleration. [[Buddhism]] (especially [[Tibetan Buddhism]]) flourished, although [[Taoism]] endured certain persecutions in favor of Buddhism from the Yuan government. [[Confucian]] governmental practices and examinations based on the [[Chinese classic texts|Classics]], which had fallen into disuse in north China during the period of disunity, were reinstated by the Yuan court, probably in the hope of maintaining order over Han society. Advances were realized in the fields of travel literature, [[cartography]], [[geography]], and scientific education.

Certain Chinese innovations and products, such as purified [[Potassium nitrate|saltpetre]], printing techniques, [[porcelain]], [[playing cards]] and medical literature, were exported to Europe and Western Asia, while the production of thin [[glass]] and [[cloisonné]] became popular in China. The Yuan exercised a profound influence on the Chinese Ming Dynasty. The Ming Emperor Zhu Yuanzhang (1368–97) admired the Mongols' unification of China and adopted its garrison system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mongol Empire p.611&quot; /&gt;

The first recorded travels by Europeans to China and back date from this time. The most famous traveler of the period was the [[Venice|Venetian]] [[Marco Polo]], whose account of his trip to &quot;Cambaluc,&quot; the capital of the Great Khan, and of life there astounded the people of Europe. The account of his travels, ''Il milione'' (or, ''The Million'', known in English as the ''Travels of Marco Polo''), appeared about the year 1299. Some argue the accuracy of Marco Polo's accounts due to the lack of mentioning the Great Wall of China, tea houses, which would have been a prominent sight since Europeans had yet to adopt a tea culture, as well the practice of foot binding by the women in capital of the Great Khan. Some suggest that Marco Polo acquired much of his knowledge through contact with Persian traders since many of the places he named were in Persian.&lt;ref&gt;Frances, Wood. &quot;Did Marco Polo Go to China (London: Secker &amp; Warburg, 1995)&lt;/ref&gt;

The Yuan undertook extensive public works. Road and water communications were reorganized and improved. To provide against possible famines, [[granary|granaries]] were ordered built throughout the empire. The city of Beijing was rebuilt with new palace grounds that included artificial lakes, hills and mountains, and parks. During the Yuan period, Beijing became the terminus of the [[Grand Canal of China]], which was completely renovated. These commercially oriented improvements encouraged overland and maritime commerce throughout [[Asia]] and facilitated direct Chinese contacts with Europe. Chinese travelers to the West were able to provide assistance in such areas as hydraulic engineering. Contacts with the West also brought the introduction to China of a major food crop, [[sorghum]], along with other foreign food products and methods of preparation.

The Yuan Dynasty (1271–1368) was the first time that non-native Chinese people ruled all of China. In [[historiography of Mongolia]], it is generally considered to be the continuation of the Mongol Empire.&lt;ref&gt;''The Mongol Empire'' By [[Michael Prawdin]], Gerard Chaliand, ISBN 978-1-4128-0519-3&lt;/ref&gt; Mongols are widely known to worship the Eternal Heaven, and according to the traditional Mongolian ideology Yuan is considered to be &quot;the beginning of an infinite number of beings, the foundation of peace and happiness, state power, the dream of many peoples, besides it there is nothing great or precious&quot; which conquered the whole China.&lt;ref&gt;Ganbold et al., op. cit., 2006, p.20–21.&lt;/ref&gt; In traditional [[historiography of China]] on the other hand, the Yuan Dynasty is usually considered to be the legitimate dynasty between the [[Song Dynasty]] and the [[Ming Dynasty]]. Note, however, Yuan Dynasty is traditionally often extended to cover the Mongol Empire before [[Kublai Khan]]'s formal establishment of the Yuan in 1271, partly because Kublai had his grandfather [[Genghis Khan]] placed on the official record as the founder of the dynasty or Taizu ({{lang-zh|太祖}}). Despite the traditional historiography as well as the official views (including the government of the [[Ming Dynasty]] which overthrew the Yuan Dynasty), there also exist Chinese people who did not consider Yuan Dynasty as a legitimate dynasty of China, but a period of foreign domination. The latter believe that Han Chinese were treated as [[second-class citizen]]s, and China stagnated economically and scientifically. But there are also other views.

==Government==
The structure of the Yuan government took shape during the reign of [[Kublai Khan]] (1260–1294). While some changes took place such as the functions of certain institutions, the essential components of the government bureaucracy remained intact from the beginning to the end of the dynasty in 1368.

The bureaucracy system created by Kublai Khan reflected various cultures in the empire, including that of the [[Han Chinese]], [[Khitan people|Khitans]], [[Jurchen people|Jurchens]], [[Mongol]]s and [[Tibetan Buddhist]]s. While the official terminology of the institutions may indicate the government structure was almost purely that of native Chinese dynasties, the Yuan bureaucracy actually consisted of a mix of elements from different cultures. The Chinese-style elements of the bureaucracy mainly came from the native [[Tang Dynasty|Tang]], [[Song Dynasty|Song]], as well as Khitan [[Liao Dynasty|Liao]] and Jurchen [[Jin Dynasty (1115-1234)|Jin]] dynasties. Chinese advisers such as [[Liu Bingzhong]] and [[Yao Shu]] gave strong influence to Kublai's early court, and the central government administration was established within the first decade of Kublai's reign. This government adopted the traditional Chinese tripartite division of authority among [[civil affairs|civil]], [[military]], and [[Censorate|censorial]] offices, including the Central Secretariat ({{zh|中書省}}) to manage civil affairs, the Privy Council ({{zh|樞密院}}) to manage military affairs, and the Censorate ({{zh|御史臺}}) to conduct internal surveillance and inspection. The actual functions of both central and local government institutions however showed a major overlap between the civil and military jurisdictions, due to the Mongol traditional reliance on military institutions and offices as the core of governance. Nevertheless, such a civilian bureaucracy, with the Central Secretariat as the top institution that was (directly or indirectly) responsible for most other governmental agencies (such as the traditional Chinese-style [[Three Departments and Six Ministries|Six Ministries]]), was created in China. At various times another central government institution called the Department of State Affairs ({{zh|尚書省}}) mainly dealt with [[finance]] was established (such as during the reign of [[Külüg Khan, Emperor Wuzong of Yuan|Külüg Khan]] or Emperor Wuzong), but usually became abandoned shortly afterwards.

While the existence of these central government departments and the Six Ministries (which had been introduced since the [[Sui Dynasty|Sui]] and [[Tang Dynasty|Tang]] dynasties) gave a sinicized image in the Yuan administration, the actual functions of these ministries also reflected how Mongolian priorities and policies reshape and redirect those institutions. For example, the authority of the Yuan legal system, the [[Ministry of Justice]] did not extend to legal cases involving Mongols and [[Semuren]], where there were separate courts of justice for them. Cases involving members of more than one ethnic group were decided by a mixed board consisting of Chinese and Mongols. Another example was the insignificance of the [[Ministry of War]] compared with native Chinese dynasties, as the real military authority in Yuan times resided in the Privy Council.

==Society==
{{See also|Society of the Mongol Empire}}

=== Imperial lifestyle ===
[[File:Liu-Kuan-Tao-Jagd.JPG|thumb|right|Painting of Kublai Khan on a hunting expedition, by Chinese court artist Liu Guandao, c. 1280.]]
Since its invention in 1269, the [['Phags-pa script]], a unified script for spelling [[Mongolian language|Mongolian]]' [[Standard Tibetan|Tibetan]], and [[Chinese language|Chinese]] languages, was preserved in the court until the end of the Dynasty. Most of the Emperors could not master [[written Chinese]], but they could generally converse well in the language. The Mongol custom of long standing quda/marriage alliance with Mongol clans, the [[Onggirat]] and the Ikeres, kept the imperial blood purely Mongol until the reign of [[Tugh Temur]] whose mother was a [[Tangut people|Tangut]] concubine. The Mongol Emperors had built large palaces and pavilions, but some still continued to live as nomads at times. Nevertheless, a few other Yuan emperors actively sponsored cultural activities; an example is Tugh Temur (Emperor Wenzong), who wrote [[poetry]], [[painting|painted]], read [[Chinese classics|Chinese classical texts]], and ordered compilation of books.&lt;ref&gt;Frederick W. Mote-Imperial China 900-1800, p.471&lt;/ref&gt;

Kublai and his successors kept a [[Tibetan Buddhism|Tibetan]] lama of the [[Sakya]] order at court. Mongol patronage of [[Buddhism]] resulted in a number of monuments of Buddhist art. Mongolian Buddhist translations, almost all from Tibetan originals, began on a large scale after 1300. Many Mongols of the upper class such as the [[Jalayir]] and the Oronar nobels delighted in patronizing [[Confucian]] scholars and institutions. A considerable number of Confucian and Chinese historical works were translated into [[Mongolian language]].

The average Mongol garrison family of the Yuan Dynasty seems to have lived a life of decaying rural leisure, with income from the harvests of their Chinese tenants eaten up by costs of equipping and dispatching men for their tours of duty. The Mongols practiced debt slavery and by 1290 in all parts of the Mongol Empire Mongol commoners were selling their children into slavery. Seeing this as damaging the Mongol nation, Kublai forbade the sale abroad of the Mongols in 1291, and likewise [[Ilkhanate|Ilkhan]] [[Ghazan]] (1295–1304) in [[Persia]] budgeted funds to redeem Mongol slaves.

===Culture===
In the China of the Yuan, or Mongol era, various important developments in the arts occurred or continued in their development. These developments included the areas of painting, calligraphy, poetry, and theater, with many great artists and writers being famous today. Due to the coming together of painting, poetry, and calligraphy at this time many of the artists practicing these different pursuits were the same individuals, though perhaps more famed for one area of their achievements than others.  Often in terms of the development of [[Shan shui|landscape painting]] as well as the classical joining together of the arts of painting, poetry, and calligraphy, the [[Song Dynasty]] and the Yuan Dynasty are linked together. In the area of [[Chinese painting]] during the Yuan Dynasty there were [[:Category:Yuan Dynasty painters|many famous painters]]. In the area of [[Chinese calligraphy|calligraphy]] many of the great calligraphers were from the Yuan Dynasty era. In [[Yuan poetry]], the main development was the ''[[Qu (poetry)|qu]]'', which was used among other poetic forms by most of the [[:Category:Yuan Dynasty poets|famous Yuan poets]]. Many of the poets were also involved in the major developments in the [[Chinese opera|theater]] during this time, and the other way around, with people important in the theater becoming famous through the development of the ''[[Chinese Sanqu poetry|sanqu]]'' type of ''qu''. One of the key factors in the mix of the ''[[Zaju|zaju variety show]]'' was the incorporation of poetry both classical and of the newer ''qu'' form. One of the important cultural developments during the Yuan era was the consolidation of poetry, painting, and calligraphy into a unified piece of the type which tends to come to mind when people think of classical Chinese art. Another important aspect of Yuan times is the increasing incorporation of the then current, vernacular Chinese into both the ''qu'' form of poetry and the ''zaju'' variety show. Another important consideration regarding Yuan Dynasty arts and culture is that so much of it has survived in China, relatively to works from the [[Tang Dynasty]] and [[Song Dynasty]], which have often been better preserved in places such as the [[Shōsōin]], in Japan.

=== Social classes ===
[[File:Yuan porcelain buddha.JPG|thumb|A white porcelain Buddhist statue from the Yuan Dynasty]]
Politically, the system of government created by Kublai Khan was the product of a compromise between Mongolian patrimonial [[feudalism]] and the traditional Chinese [[autocratic]]-[[bureaucratic]] system. Nevertheless, socially the educated Chinese [[elite]] were in general not given the degree of esteem that they had been accorded previously under native Chinese dynasties. Although the traditional Chinese elite were not given their share of power, the Mongols and the [[Semu]]ren (various allied groups from [[Central Asia]] and the western end of the empire) largely remained strangers to the mainstream [[Chinese culture]], and this dichotomy gave the Yuan regime a somewhat strong &quot;[[Colonialism|colonial]]&quot; coloration.&lt;ref&gt;Ed. Herbert Franke, Denis Twitchett, John King Fairbank-''The Cambridge History of China: Alien regimes and border states'', 907-1368, p. 491-492&lt;/ref&gt; The unequal treatment is possibly due to the fear of transferring power to the ethnic Chinese under their rule. The Mongols and Semuren were given certain advantages in the dynasty, and this would last even after the restoration of the [[imperial examination]] in the early 14th century. In general there were very few North Chinese or Southerners reaching the highest-post in the government compared with the possibility that Persians did so in the [[Ilkhanate]].&lt;ref&gt;David Morgan-Who Ran the Mongol Empire?, Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland, No. 1 (1982), p.135&lt;/ref&gt; Later the [[Yongle Emperor]] of the [[Ming Dynasty]] had also mentioned about the discrimination existed during the Yuan Dynasty.&lt;ref&gt;In response to an objection against the use of &quot;barbarians&quot; in his government, the Yongle Emperor answered: &quot;... Discrimination was used by the Mongols during the Yuan dynasty, who employed only &quot;Mongols and Tartars&quot; and discarded northern and southern Chinese and this was precisely the cause that brought disaster upon them&quot;. David Morgan-Who Ran the Mongol Empire?, Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland, No. 1 (1982), pp.124-136&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mongols had employed foreigners long before the reign of Kublai Khan, the founder of the Yuan Dynasty. But during Kublai's reign a hierarchy of reliability was introduced in China. The population was divided into the following classes:

*Mongols
*[[Semu]]ren, including Uyghurs, immigrants from the west and some clans of [[Central Asia]]
*North Chinese, [[Khitans]], [[Jurchens]] and [[Koreans]]
*Southerners, or all subjects of the former Southern Song Dynasty

Partner merchants and non-Mongol overseers were usually either immigrants or local ethnic groups. Thus, in China they were [[Uighurs]], [[Turkestani]] and [[Persian people|Persian]] Muslims, and [[Christian]]s. Foreigners from outside the Mongol Empire entirely, such as the [[Marco Polo|Polo family]], were everywhere welcomed.

Despite the high position given to Muslims, some policies of the Yuan Emperors severe discriminated against them, restricting Halal slaughter and other Islamic practices like circumcision, as well as [[Kosher]] butchering for Jews, forcing them to eat food the Mongol way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islamicpopulation.com/asia/China/China_integration%20of%20religious%20minority.pdf|title=The Integration of Religious Minorities in China: The Case of Chinese Muslims|author=Donald Daniel Leslie|date=1998|page=12|publisher=The Fifty-ninth George Ernest Morrison Lecture in Ethnology|accessdate=30 November 2010}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Toward the end, corruption and the persecution became so severe that Muslim Generals joined [[Han Chinese]] in rebelling against the Mongols. The Ming founder [[Zhu Yuanzhang]] had Muslim Generals like [[Lan Yu (general)|Lan Yu]] who rebelled against the Mongols and defeated them in combat. Some Muslim communities had the name in Chinese which meant &quot;baracks&quot; and also mean &quot;thanks&quot;, many Hui Muslims claim it is because that they played an important role in overthrowing the Mongols and it was named in thanks by the Han Chinese for assisting them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?ei=lJ4GTpDdJ4P40gGJtay5Cw&amp;ct=result&amp;id=kkJwAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=Thus%2C+Changying+means+either+%22many+thanks%22+to+the+Hui+who+helped+drive+out+the+Mongols%2C+or+the+%22many+barracks%22+of+the+Hui+militia+eventually+established+there.+This+reflects+the+popular+belief+among+the+Hui+that+they+played+an+important&amp;q=popular+belief+mongols|title=Muslim Chinese: ethnic nationalism in the People's Republic|author=Dru C. Gladney|year=1991|publisher=Council on East Asian Studies, Harvard University|location=|page=234|edition=2, illustrated, reprint|isbn=0-674-59495-9|pages=|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Administrative divisions ==
[[File:Yuan Dynasty Administrative division.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Administrative divisions of the Yuan Dynasty.]]
The territory of the Yuan Dynasty was divided into the Central Region (腹裏) and places under control of various Xing Zhongshusheng (行中書省 or 行省) or the [[Xuanzheng Yuan]] (宣政院).

The Central Region, consisting of present-day [[Hebei]], [[Shandong]], [[Shanxi]], the south-eastern part of present-day [[Inner Mongolia]] and the [[Henan]] areas to the north of the [[Yellow River]], was considered the most important region of the dynasty and directly governed by Zhongshusheng (中書省, &quot;Secretariat&quot;) at [[Khanbaliq|Dadu]]; similarly, another top-level administrative department called the Xuanzheng Yuan governed the whole of modern-day [[Tibet]] and a part of [[Kashmir]].

Xing Zhongshusheng (行中書省, &quot;branch Secretariat&quot; or &quot;en-route Secretariat&quot;), or simply Xingsheng (行省), were provincial-level administrative organizations or institutions, sometimes roughly translated as &quot;[[Province]]&quot;, though they were not exactly provinces in modern sense. There were 11 Xing Zhongshusheng or Xingsheng in Yuan Dynasty.&lt;ref&gt;Duosang Mongol History, Vol. 1; Zhong-gou Tong-shi; History of Zhong-gou Border Nationalities; The New Yuan-shih&lt;/ref&gt;

#Gansu Xingsheng (甘肅行省) with [[Zhangye]] District as its seat of government. Under this came most of present-day [[Ningxia]] Hui Autonomous Region (originally the [[Tangut people|Tangut]] territory), south-eastern [[Gansu]] Province, and part of north-eastern [[Amdo]].
#Henan Jiangbei Xingsheng (河南江北行省) with [[Kaifeng]] District as its seat of government. Under this came the [[Henan]] areas to the south of the Yellow River, north-east Hubei, Jiangsu, the north-eastern part of Jiangxi Province.
#Huguang Xingsheng (湖廣行省) with [[Wuhan]] of the present-day [[Hubei]] Province as its seat of government. Under this came a part of south-east Hubei, [[Hunan]], [[Guangxi]], most of [[Guizhou]], and parts of south-western [[Guangdong]] Province.
#Jiangxi Xingsheng (江西行省) with [[Nanchang]] as its seat of government. Under this ya of present-day Jiangxi and Guangdong Province.
#Jiangzhe Xingsheng (江浙行省) with [[Hangzhou]] as its seat of government. Under this came [[Jiangsu]] and [[Anhui]] areas to the south of the [[Yangtze]] River, [[Zhejiang]], [[Fujian]], and a small area in the north-east of [[Jiangxi]] Province.
#Liaoyang Xingsheng (遼陽行省) with present-day [[Liaoyang]] District in Liaoning Province as its seat of government. Under this came north-east [[China]] and the northern part of [[Korea]].
#Lingbei Xingsheng (嶺北行省) with [[Karakorum]] as its seat of government. Under this province came the present-day [[Mongolia]], northern [[Inner Mongolia]] and parts of [[Siberia]].
#Shaanxi Xingsheng (陝西行省) with [[Xi'an]] as its seat of government. Under this came the majority of present-day [[Shaanxi]] Province, the south-western part of [[Inner Mongolia]], south-eastern [[Gansu]], north-western [[Sichuan]], and a small part of [[Qinghai]].
#Sichuan Xingsheng (四川行省) with [[Chengdu]] at its seat of government. Under this came most of present-day [[Sichuan]] Province and parts of south-western [[Shaanxi]].
#Yunnan Xingsheng (雲南行省) with [[Kunming]] as its seat of government. Under this came present-day [[Yunnan]] Province, parts of western [[Guizhou]] and north-eastern part of [[Burma]].
#Zhendong Xingsheng (征東行省) with [[Kaesong]] of present-day [[Korea]] as its seat. It was a special institution set up when Kublai Khan attempted to invade [[Japan]] in 1281, with the king of [[Goryeo]] as its head. The setting of this Xingsheng was considerably different from all other Xingsheng, and unlike other Xingsheng, Zhendong (征東), literally &quot;Conquer East&quot; or &quot;Eastern Expedition&quot;, was not a geographic name, and this institution was also referred to as &quot;Japanese Expedition Xingsheng&quot; (征日本行省) or just &quot;Japan Xingsheng&quot; (日本行省). It was abolished when the invasion of Japan had failed, though set up again later.

Below the level of Xing Zhongshusheng or Xingsheng, the largest political division was the circuit (道), followed by prefectures (府) operating under a prefect and subprefectures (州) under a subprefect. The lowest political division was the county (縣) overseen by a magistrate. This government structure at the provincial level was later copied by the [[Ming Dynasty|Ming]] and [[Qing Dynasty|Qing]] dynasties.

==See also==
*[[List of Emperors of the Yuan Dynasty]]
*[[Mongol Empire]]
*[[Yuan Dynasty family tree]]
*[[Jin Dynasty, 1115–1234|Jin Dynasty (金朝)]]
*[[Song Dynasty]]
*[[Ming Dynasty]]
*[[Western Xia]]
*[[History of Mongolia]]
*[[List of Mongol Khans]]
*[[Jun ware]]
*[[Mongol invasions]]
*[[Europeans in Medieval China]]
*[[Islam during the Yuan Dynasty]]
*[[Hua-Yi distinction]]

== Notes ==
{{Cnote|a|http://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%B8%AD%E5%9B%BD%E4%BA%BA%E5%8F%A3%E5%8F%B2#.E5.85.83}}

{{Cnote|b|http://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%B8%AD%E5%9B%BD%E4%BA%BA%E5%8F%A3%E5%8F%B2#.E5.85.83}}

==References==
{{Reflist|1}}

==Further reading==
*Chan Hok-lam and de Bary, W.T., ''Yuan Thought: Chinese Thought and Religion Under the Mongols'', (New York: Columbia University Press, 1982). ISBN 978-0-231-05324-2.
* {{cite book | author=Cotterell, Arthur. | title=The Imperial Capitals of China - An Inside View of the Celestial Empire| location=London | publisher=Pimlico | year=2007 | id=ISBN 9781845950095 | pages = 304 pages.}}
*Langlois, John D., ''China Under Mongol Rule'', (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1981). ISBN 978-0-691-10110-1.
* {{cite book | author=Paludan, Ann. | title=Chronicle of tasdasadtaehe China Emperors| location=London | publisher=Thames &amp; Hudson | year=1998 | id=ISBN 0-500-05090-2 | pages = 224 pages.}}
*Rossabi, M., ''Khubilai Khan: His Life and Times'', (Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1989). ISBN 978-0-520-06740-0.
* J. J. Saunders, ''The History of the Mongol Conquests'' (1971; rpr University of Pennsylvania Press, 2001 ISBN  	  0812217667.)

==External links==
{{ChineseText}}
*[http://www.kinabaloo.com/yd1.html Yuan Dynasty Earthen City Wall Park, Beijing]

{{S-start}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Dynasties in Chinese history]]|before=[[Song Dynasty]]|after=[[Ming Dynasty]]|years=1271-1368}}
{{S-end}}
{{Mongol Empire}}
{{Empires}}

{{coord|39|54|N|116|23|E|type:country_source:kolossus-ukwiki|display=title}}

[[Category:1368 disestablishments]]
[[Category:History of Mongolia]]
[[Category:Mongol Empire]]
[[Category:Yuan Dynasty|*]]
[[Category:Former countries in East Asia]]
[[Category:Borjigin]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1271]]
[[Category:Khaganates]]
{{Link GA|no}}

{{Link FA|zh}}

[[als:Yuan-Dynastie]]
[[ar:مملكة يوان]]
[[az:Yuan sülaləsi]]
[[bo:ཡོན་རྒྱལ་རབས།]]
[[ca:Dinastia Yuan]]
[[cv:Юань йăх-несĕлĕ]]
[[cs:Dynastie Jüan]]
[[cy:Brenhinllin Yuan]]
[[da:Yuan-dynastiet]]
[[de:Yuan-Dynastie]]
[[et:Yuani dünastia]]
[[es:Dinastía Yuan]]
[[eo:Dinastio Yuan]]
[[eu:Yuan dinastia]]
[[fa:سلسله یوآن]]
[[fr:Dynastie Yuan]]
[[gan:元]]
[[hak:Ngièn-chhèu]]
[[xal:Юан өнчин төр]]
[[ko:원나라]]
[[hi:युआन राजवंश]]
[[hr:Dinastija Yuan]]
[[id:Dinasti Yuan]]
[[is:Júanveldið]]
[[it:Dinastia Yuan]]
[[kk:Юань Империясы]]
[[lv:Juaņu impērija]]
[[lt:Juan dinastija]]
[[mr:युआन राजवंश]]
[[ms:Dinasti Yuan]]
[[mn:Юань улс]]
[[my:ယွမ်မင်းဆက်]]
[[nl:Yuan-dynastie]]
[[ja:元 (王朝)]]
[[no:Yuan-dynastiet]]
[[nn:Yuan-dynastiet]]
[[oc:Dinastia Yuan]]
[[pl:Dynastia Yuan]]
[[pt:Dinastia Yuan]]
[[ro:Dinastia Yuan]]
[[ru:Юань (династия)]]
[[sq:Dinastia Yuan]]
[[simple:Yuan Dynasty]]
[[sr:Династија Јуан]]
[[sh:Dinastija Yuan]]
[[fi:Yuan-dynastia]]
[[sv:Yuandynastin]]
[[tl:Dinastiyang Yuan]]
[[ta:யுவான் அரசமரபு]]
[[th:ราชวงศ์หยวน]]
[[tr:Yuan Hanedanı]]
[[uk:Династія Юань]]
[[ug:يۈەن سۇلالىسى]]
[[vi:Nhà Nguyên]]
[[fiu-vro:Yuani dünastia]]
[[zh-classical:元]]
[[war:Dinastiya Yuan]]
[[wuu:元朝]]
[[zh-yue:元朝]]
[[zh:元朝]]</text>
      <sha1>aw7rkb8a0fbbg1bhtqhgibq77hy94fj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
