<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Abolitionism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>38894</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522389331</id>
      <parentid>522122909</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T21:53:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Student7</username>
        <id>2745211</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>tweaked. by itself always refers to slavery</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="109679">{{Other uses}}
{{Redirect|Anti-slavery|the British NGO working for the eradication of slavery|Anti-Slavery International}}
[[File:BLAKE10.JPG|thumb|200px|right|[[Josiah Wedgwood#&quot;Am I Not a Man And a Brother?&quot;|&quot;''Am I Not A Man And A Brother?''&quot;]] 1787 medallion designed by [[Josiah Wedgwood]] for the anti-slavery campaign]]
[[File:Remember Your Weekly Pledge Massachusetts Anti-Slavey Society collection box.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Collection box for [[Massachusetts Anti-Slavery Society]]. Circa 1850.]]
{{slavery}}
'''Abolitionism''', used as a single word, was a movement to end [[slavery]], whether formal or informal.  

The term has become adopted by those seeking the abolishment of any perceived injustice to a group of people.  There are abolition movements to end human trafficking, the sex slave trafficking, abortion, children used in war, and many others.

In western Europe and the Americas, abolitionism was a historical movement to end the African [[slave trade]] and set slaves free. Although European colonists, beginning with the Spanish, initially enslaved natives, the [[Dominican Order|Dominican]] priest [[Bartolomé de las Casas]] helped convince the Spanish government to enact [[New Laws|the first European law abolishing colonial slavery]] in 1542; Spain weakened these laws by 1545. 

In the 17th century English [[Quakers]] and evangelical religious groups condemned slavery (by then applied mostly to Africans) as un-Christian; in the 18th century, abolition was part of the message of the [[First Great Awakening]] in the Thirteen Colonies; and in the same period, rationalist thinkers of the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] criticized it for violating the rights of man. The [[Somersett's case]] in 1772, which emancipated a slave in England, helped launch the British movement to abolish slavery. Though anti-slavery sentiments were widespread by the late 18th century, the colonies and emerging nations that used slave labor continued to do so: French and English territories in the [[West Indies]], South America, and the South of the United States. 

After the [[American Revolutionary War]] established the United States, northern states, beginning with [[Pennsylvania]] in 1780, passed legislation during the next two decades abolishing slavery, sometimes by gradual emancipation. Massachusetts ratified a [[Massachusetts Constitution|constitution]] that declared all men equal; [[freedom suits]] challenging slavery based on this principle brought an end to slavery in the state. In other states, such as Virginia, similar declarations of rights were interpreted by the courts to not apply to Africans.  During the following decades, the abolitionist movement grew in northern states, and Congress limited the expansion of slavery in new states admitted to the union. 

[[Revolutionary France]] abolished slavery in 1789, but it was restored by [[Napoleon]] in the French colonies more than a decade later after his subversion of the French Revolution. [[Haiti]] achieved independence from France in 1804 and brought an end to slavery in its territory, establishing the second republic in the western hemisphere. Britain banned the importation of [[African slaves]] in its colonies in 1807, and the United States followed in 1808. Britain abolished slavery throughout the [[British Empire]] with the [[Slavery Abolition Act 1833]], the [[French colonial empire|French colonies]] abolished it 15 years later, and slavery in the United States was abolished in 1865, after the [[American Civil War]], with the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution]].

In Eastern Europe, groups organized to abolish the enslavement of the [[Romani people|Roma]] in [[Wallachia]] and [[Moldavia]]; and to emancipate the [[serfs]] in Russia ([[Emancipation reform of 1861]]). It was declared illegal in 1948 under the Universal Rights of Man of the United Nations. The last country to abolish legal slavery was [[Mauritania]], where it was officially abolished by presidential decree in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://edition.cnn.com/interactive/2012/03/world/mauritania.slaverys.last.stronghold/index.html Slavery’s last stronghold]&quot;. CNN. March 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, child and adult slavery and [[Unfree labour|forced labour]] are illegal in most countries, as well as being against [[international law]], but a high rate of human trafficking for labor and for sexual bondage continues, believed to affect millions of adults and children.

==Great Britain==
{{Main|Slavery in Britain and Ireland}}
[[Image:William Murray of Mansfield.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[William Murray, 1st Earl of Mansfield|Lord Mansfield]] (1705–1793), whose opinion in [[Somerset's Case]] (1772) was widely taken to have held that slavery was illegal in England.]]

The last known form of enforced servitude of adults ([[villein]]age) had disappeared in England by the beginning of the 17th century. In a 1569 court case involving Cartwright, who had bought a slave from Russia, the court ruled that English law could not recognise slavery, as it was never established officially. This ruling was overshadowed by later developments.  It was upheld in 1700 by the Lord Chief Justice [[John Holt]] when he ruled that a slave became free as soon as he arrived in England.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.lib.msu.edu/DMC/African%20Journals/pdfs/PULA/pula003002/pula003002007.pdf V.C.D. Mtubani, &quot;African Slaves and English Law&quot;], ''PULA Botswana Journal of African Studies,'' Vol 3 No 2 November 1983, Retrieved 24 February 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to English colonists importing slaves to the North American colonies, by the 18th century, traders began to import slaves from Africa, India and East Asia (where they were trading) to [[London]] and [[Edinburgh]] to work as personal servants. Men who migrated to the North American colonies often took their East Indian slaves or servants with them, as [[East Indians]] have been documented in colonial records.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freeafricanamericans.com Paul Heinegg, ''Free African Americans of Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Maryland and Delaware'', 1999–2005], &quot;WEAVER FAMILY: Three members of the Weaver family, probably brothers, were called &quot;East Indians&quot; in Lancaster County,[VA] [court records] between 1707 and 1711.&quot;; &quot;‘The indenture of Indians (Native Americans) as servants was not common in Maryland...the indenture of East Indian servants was more common.&quot;, Retrieved 15 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indolink.com/Analysis/a121403-021037.php Francis C. Assisi, &quot;First Indian-American Identified: Mary Fisher, Born 1680 in Maryland&quot;], IndoLink, Quote: &quot;Documents available from American archival sources of the colonial period now confirm the presence of indentured servants or slaves who were brought from the Indian subcontinent, via England, to work for their European American masters.&quot;, Retrieved 20 April 2010&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some of the first [[freedom suits]], court cases in the British Isles to challenge the legality of slavery, took place in Scotland from 1755 to 1778. The cases were ''Montgomery v. Sheddan'' (1755), ''Spens v. Dalrymple'' (1769), and ''Knight v. Wedderburn'' (1778). Each of the slaves had been baptized in Scotland and challenged the legality of slavery. They set the precedent of legal procedure in British courts that would later lead to successful outcomes for the plaintiffs. In the first two cases, deaths of the plaintiff and defendant, respectively, brought an end before court decisions. The Knight case was decided in favor of the plaintiff, the former slave.&lt;ref name=&quot;The National Archives of Scotland&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nas.gov.uk/about/071022.asp |title=Slavery, freedom or perpetual servitude? – the Joseph Knight case |publisher=[[National Archives of Scotland]]|accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

African slaves were not bought or sold in London but were brought by masters from other areas. Together with people from other nations, especially non-Christian, Africans were considered foreigners, not able to be English subjects. At the time, England had no [[naturalization]] procedure. The African slaves' legal status was unclear until 1772 and [[Somersett's Case]], when the fugitive slave James Somersett forced a legal decision. Somersett had escaped, and his master, Charles Steuart, had him captured and imprisoned on board a ship, intending to ship him to [[Jamaica]] to be resold into slavery. While in London, Somersett had been [[baptism|baptised]]; three godparents issued a writ of ''[[habeas corpus]]''. As a result, [[William Murray, 1st Earl of Mansfield|Lord Mansfield]], Chief Justice of the [[King's Bench|Court of the King's Bench]], had to judge whether Somersett's abduction was legal or not under English [[Common Law]]. No legislation had ever been passed to establish slavery in England. The case received national attention, and five advocates defended Somersett. 

In his judgment of 22 June 1772, Mansfield declared: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The state of slavery is of such a nature that it is incapable of being introduced on any reasons, moral or political, but only by positive law, which preserves its force long after the reasons, occasions, and time itself from whence it was created, is erased from memory. It is so odious, that nothing can be suffered to support it, but positive law. Whatever inconveniences, therefore, may follow from a decision, I cannot say this case is allowed or approved by the law of England; and therefore the black must be discharged.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Frederick Charles Moncreiff (2006). ''The Wit and Wisdom of the Bench and Bar'', pp.85–86. The Lawbook Exchange, Ltd.,&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Although the [[Slavery at common law|exact legal implications]] of the judgement are unclear when analysed by lawyers, it was generally taken at the time to have determined that slavery did not exist under English common law and was thus prohibited in England.&lt;ref&gt;Mowat, Robert Balmain (1943). ''History of the English-Speaking Peoples,'' p. 162. Oxford University Press, 1943&lt;/ref&gt; The decision did not apply to other British territories; by then, for example, the American colonies had established slavery by positive laws.&lt;ref&gt;MacEwen, Martin. (2002). ''Housing, Race and Law: The British Experience'', p. 39, Routledge, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; The Somersett's case became a significant part of the common law of slavery in the English-speaking world, and it helped launch the movement to abolish slavery.&lt;ref&gt;Peter P. Hinks, John R. McKivigan, R. Owen Williams (2007) ''Encyclopedia of Antislavery and Abolition,'' p.643. Greenwood Publishing Group, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; 

After reading about the Somersett's Case, [[Joseph Knight (slave)|Joseph Knight]], an enslaved African who had been purchased by his master John Wedderburn in Jamaica and brought to Scotland, left him. Married and with a child, he filed a [[freedom suit]], on the grounds that he could not be held as a slave in Great Britain. In the case of ''[[Knight v. Wedderburn]]'' (1778), Wedderburn said that Knight owed him &quot;perpetual servitude&quot;. The [[Court of Session]]s of Scotland ruled against him, saying that [[chattel]] slavery was not recognised under the [[law of Scotland]], and slaves could seek court protection to leave a master or avoid being forcibly removed from Scotland to be returned to slavery in the colonies.&lt;ref name=&quot;The National Archives of Scotland&quot;/&gt; 

But at the same time, legally mandated, [[hereditary]] slavery of Scots persons in Scotland had existed from 1606&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| editor-last=Brown
| editor-first=K. M., et al.
| publication-place=St. Andrews
| publication-date=2007
| publisher = [[University of St. Andrews]]
| contribution = Regarding colliers and salters (ref: 1605/6/39)
|contribution-url=http://www.rps.ac.uk/search.php?action=fc&amp;fn=jamesvi_trans&amp;id=id7107
| title = The Records of the Parliaments of Scotland to 1707
| url =
| postscript=.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; until 1799, when [[coal mining|colliers]] and [[salters]] were legally [[emancipation|emancipated]] by an act of the [[Parliament of Great Britain]] (39 Geo.III. c56). Skilled workers, they were restricted to a place and could be sold with the works. A prior law enacted in 1775 (15 Geo.III. c. 28) was intended to end what the act referred to as &quot;a state of slavery and bondage,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document
|last=May
|first=Thomas Erskine
|author-link=Erskine May, 1st Baron Farnborough
|year=1895
|contribution=Last Relics of Slavery
|contribution-url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sCwYAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA274
|title=The Constitutional History of England (1760–1860)
|volume=II
|publisher=A. C. Armstrong and Son
|publication-date=1895
|publication-place=New York
|pages=274–275
|url=
|postscript=.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; but it was ineffectual, necessitating the 1799 act. 

[[Image:IgnatiusSancho.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Ignatius Sancho]] (c1729–1780) gained fame in his time as &quot;the extraordinary Negro&quot;.  To 18th-century British abolitionists, he became a symbol of the humanity of Africans and immorality of the slave trade.]]

===First steps===
Despite the ending of slavery in [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Great Britain]], the United States continued to rely on it as an institution in the South, and the [[British West Indies|West Indian colonies]] of the [[British Empire]] also kept slavery. In 1785, the English poet [[William Cowper]] wrote: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;We have no slaves at home – Then why abroad? Slaves cannot breathe in England; if their lungs receive our air, that moment they are free, They touch our country, and their shackles fall. That's noble, and bespeaks a nation proud. And jealous of the blessing. Spread it then, And let it circulate through every vein.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rhodes, Nick (2003). ''William Cowper: Selected Poems'', p.84. Routledge, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

In 1783, an anti-slavery movement began among the British public. That year a group of [[Quakers]] founded the first British abolitionist organization. The Quakers continued to be influential throughout the lifetime of the movement, in many ways leading the campaign.&lt;ref name=bbc-quakers&gt;{{cite news
| last = Tomkins
| first = Stephen
| title = BBC NEWS &amp;#124; Magazine &amp;#124; Keeping it under their hats
|publisher=BBC
| date = 22 March 2007
| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/6476645.stm
| accessdate =2 January 2008 | archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080102233937/http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/6476645.stm| archivedate= 2 January 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 June 1783, Sir Cecil Wray (Member of Parliament for [[Westminster (UK Parliament constituency)|Westminster]]) presented the Quaker petition to parliament. Also in 1783, [[Bishop Beilby Porteus|Dr Beilby Porteus]] issued a call to the [[Church of England]] to cease its involvement in the [[slave trade]] and to formulate a policy to improve the conditions of [[British African-Caribbean community|Afro-Caribbean]] [[slaves]]. The exploration of the African continent, by such British groups as the [[African Association]] (1788), promoted the abolitionists' cause. Such expeditions highlighted the legitimate, complex cultures of Africans; before the Europeans had considered them &quot;[[other]]&quot; and uncivilized. The African Association had close ties with [[William Wilberforce]], who became known as a prominent figure in the battle for abolition in the British Empire.&lt;ref&gt;Hague, William. 2008. &quot;William Wilberforce: The Life of the Great Anti-Slave Trade Campaigner&quot;. p. 327. HarperCollins, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Africans played an important part in the abolition movement. In Britain, [[Olaudah Equiano]], whose autobiography was published in nine editions in his lifetime, campaigned tirelessly against the slave trade.

One aspect of the history of abolitionism during this period was the effective use of images such as the famous Wedgewood medallion of 1787 and the engraving showing the horrific layout of the infamous slave ship, &quot;The Brooks&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''The Slave in European Art: From Renaissance Trophy to Abolitionist Emblem'', ed Elizabeth Mcgrath and Jean Michel Massing, London 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

===Growth of the movement===
[[Image:Wilberforce john rising.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[William Wilberforce]] (1759–1833), politician and philanthropist who was a leader of the movement to abolish the slave trade.]]

After the formation of the [[Committee for the Abolition of the Slave Trade]] in 1787, [[William Wilberforce]] led the cause of abolition through the parliamentary campaign. It finally abolished the [[slave trade]] in the British Empire with the [[Slave Trade Act 1807]]. He continued to campaign for the abolition of slavery in the British Empire, which he lived to see in the [[Slavery Abolition Act 1833]].

The [[Atlantic slave trade]], also called [[Triangle trade]], encompassed the trafficking in slaves by British [[merchants]] who exported manufactured goods from ports such as Bristol and Liverpool, sold or exchanged these for slaves in West Africa (where the African chieftain hierarchy was tied to slavery), and shipped the slaves to [[British colonies]] and other Caribbean countries or the [[British America|American colonies]]. There traders sold or exchanged the slaves for rum and sugar (in the Caribbean) and tobacco and rice (in the American South), which they took back to British ports. The merchants traded in three places with each round-trip. Political influence against the inhumanity of the slave trade grew strongly in the late 18th century. 

People of both European and African ethnicity worked for abolition of the slave trade and slavery. Well-known abolitionists in Britain included [[James Ramsay (abolitionist)|James Ramsay]], who had seen the cruelty of the trade at first hand; the [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] [[William Roscoe]] who courageously&lt;!---note that awkwardness of sentence cannot contain the fact that Liverpool was to a substantial extent dependent on the slave trade. So &quot;courageously&quot; means nothing to the uninformed reader--&gt; campaigned for parliament in the port city of [[Liverpool]] for which he was briefly M.P., [[Granville Sharp]], [[Thomas Clarkson]], [[Josiah Wedgwood]], who produced the [[Am I Not A Man And A Brother|&quot;''Am I Not A Man And A Brother?''&quot;]] medallion for the Committee; and other members of the [[Clapham Sect]] of [[Evangelicalism|evangelical]] reformers, as well as [[Quakers]]. 

The latter made up most of the Committee for the Abolition of the Slave Trade, and were the first to present a petition against the slave trade to the British Parliament. As [[Dissenters]], Quakers were not eligible to become British MPs in the late 18th and early 19th centuries. The Anglican evangelist [[William Wilberforce]] led the [[Parliament of Great Britain|parliamentary]] campaign. Clarkson became the group's most prominent researcher, gathering vast amounts of data, and gaining first hand accounts by interviewing sailors and former slaves at British ports such as [[Bristol]], Liverpool and London.
[[Image:Olaudah Equiano - Project Gutenberg eText 15399.png|thumb|right|150px|[[Olaudah Equiano]] (c1745–1797) was one of the most prominent Africans involved in the British debate for the abolition of the slave trade.]]
Mainly because of Clarkson's efforts, a network of local abolition groups was established across England. They campaigned through public meetings and the publication of [[pamphlets]] and [[petitions]]. One of the earliest books promoted by Clarkson and the Committee for the Abolition of the Slave Trade was the autobiography of the freed slave [[Olaudah Equiano]]. The movement had support from such freed slaves, from many denominational groups such as [[Swedenborgians]], Quakers, [[Baptists]], [[Methodists]] and others. They reached out for support from the new [[Industrial Revolution|industrial workers]] of the cities in the midlands and north of England. Even women and children, previously un-politicised groups, became involved in the campaign. At this time, women often had to hold separate meetings as there were social rules against their appearing in public meetings. They could not vote, nor could the majority of the men in Britain at the time.

The abolitionists negotiated with chieftains in West Africa to purchase land to establish  '[[Freetown]]' – a settlement for former slaves of the [[British Empire]] (the Poor Blacks of London) and the United States. Great Britain had promised freedom to American slaves who left rebel owners to join its cause during the American Revolutionary War.  It evacuated thousands of slaves together with its troops and transported 3,000 Black Loyalists to Nova Scotia for resettlement.  About a decade later, they were offered a chance to resettle in Freetown, and several hundred made the move. Freetown was the first settlement of the colony of [[Sierra Leone]], which was protected under a British Act of Parliament in 1807–8. British influence in West Africa grew through a series of negotiations with local chieftains to end trading in slaves. These included agreements to permit British navy ships to intercept chieftains' ships to ensure their merchants were not carrying slaves.
[[Image:BLAKE12.JPG|thumb|left|150px|[[William Blake|Blake's]] &quot;A Negro Hung Alive by the Ribs to a Gallows&quot;, an illustration to J. G. Stedman's ''Narrative, of a Five Years' Expedition, against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam'' (1796).]]

In 1796, [[John Gabriel Stedman]] published the memoirs of his five-year voyage to the [[Dutch Empire|Dutch]]-controlled [[Surinam]] in South America as part of a military force sent out to subdue [[Maroon (people)|bosneger]]s, former slaves living in the inlands. The book is critical of the treatment of slaves and contains many images by [[William Blake]] and [[Francesco Bartolozzi]] depicting the cruel treatment of runaway slaves. It was an example of what became a large body of abolitionist literature.

===Slave Trade Act 1807===
[[Image:EndOfSlaveTrade.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Plate to commemorate the abolition of the slave trade in 1807.]]

The [[Slave Trade Act 1807|Slave Trade Act]] was passed by the [[Parliament of the United Kingdom|British Parliament]] on 25 March 1807, making the slave trade illegal throughout the British Empire. The Act imposed a fine of £100 for every slave found aboard a British ship. At a time when Napoleon decided to revive slavery, which had been abolished during the [[French Revolution]], and to send his troops to re-enslave the people of [[Haiti]], Guadeloupe and the other French Caribbean possessions, the British took the moral high ground with their prohibition of the slave trade.

The act's intention was to entirely outlaw the slave trade within the [[British Empire]], but the lucrative trade continued through smuggling. Sometimes captains at risk of being caught by the [[Royal Navy]] would throw slaves into the sea to reduce their fines. In 1827, Britain defined participation in the slave trade as [[piracy]] and punishable by death. Between 1808 and 1860, the Royal Navy's [[West Africa Squadron]] seized approximately 1,600 slave ships and freed 150,000 Africans who were aboard.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/devon/content/articles/2007/03/20/abolition_navy_feature.shtml Jo Loosemore, &quot;Sailing against slavery&quot;], BBC, 20 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Britain took action against African leaders who refused to agree to British treaties to outlaw the trade, for example, in 1851 it deposed &quot;the usurping King of [[Lagos]]&quot;. Britain signed anti-slavery treaties with more than 50 African rulers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pdavis.nl/Background.htm#WAS &quot;The West African Squadron and slave trade&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Slavery Abolition Act 1833===
{{Main|Slavery Abolition Act 1833}}
[[Image:FriendsOfNegroEmancipation.jpg|thumb|left|150px|&quot;To the Friends of Negro Emancipation&quot;, an engraving in the West Indies, celebrating the abolition of slavery in the [[British Empire]] in 1833.]]
After the 1807 act, slaves were still held, though not sold, within the British Empire. In the 1820s, the abolitionist movement revived to campaign against the institution of slavery. In 1823 the first [[Anti-Slavery Society]] was founded in Britain. Many members had previously campaigned against the slave trade. In 1831 the slave [[Samuel Sharpe|Sam Sharpe]] led a Christmas rebellion in Jamaica, an event that catalyzed anti-slavery sentiment. 

On 28 August 1833, the [[Slavery Abolition Act]] was given [[Royal Assent]], which paved the way for the abolition of slavery within the [[British Empire]] and its colonies. On 1 August 1834, all slaves in the British Empire were [[emancipated]], but they were indentured to their former owners in an [[apprenticeship system]] that meant gradual abolition: the first set of apprenticeships came to an end on 1 August 1838, while the final apprenticeships were scheduled to cease on 1 August 1840, six years later.

On 1 August 1834, as the Governor in [[Port of Spain]], [[Trinidad]] addressed an audience about the new laws, the mostly elderly, unarmed slaves began chanting: &quot;Pas de six ans. Point de six ans&quot; (&quot;Not six years. No six years&quot;), drowning out his voice. Peaceful protests continued until the government passed a resolution to abolish [[apprenticeship]] and the slaves gained ''de facto'' freedom. Full emancipation for all slaves was legally granted on 1 August 1838, ahead of schedule, making Trinidad the first British slave society to fully end slavery.&lt;ref&gt;Dryden, John. 1992 &quot;Pas de Six Ans!&quot;, In: ''Seven Slaves &amp; Slavery: Trinidad 1777 – 1838'', by Anthony de Verteuil, Port of Spain, pp. 371–379.&lt;/ref&gt;
The government set aside £20 million for compensation of slave owners for their &quot;property&quot; across the Empire, but it did not offer the former slaves compensation or reparations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pdavis.nl/Legis_07.htm |title=Slavery Abolition Act 1833 |date=28 August 1833 |accessdate=4 June 2008| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080524010152/http://www.pdavis.nl/Legis_07.htm| archivedate= 24 May 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:The Anti-Slavery Society Convention, 1840 by Benjamin Robert Haydon.jpg|thumb|right|150px|&quot;The [[Anti-Slavery Society]] Convention, 1840&quot; by [[Benjamin Haydon]] (1841).]]

===Campaigning after the act===
In 1839, the [[British and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society]] attempted to outlaw slavery in other countries and also to pressure the government to help enforce the suppression of the slave trade by declaring [[slave traders]] [[pirate]]s and pursuing them. The world's oldest international human rights organization, it continues today as [[Anti-Slavery International]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://portal.unesco.org/education/en/ev.php-URL_ID=9462&amp;URL_DO=DO_PRINTPAGE&amp;URL_SECTION=201.html Anti-Slavery International] UNESCO. Retrieved 2011-10-11&lt;/ref&gt;

==France==
In 1315, [[Louis X of France|Louis X]], king of France, published a decree proclaiming that &quot;France signifies freedom&quot; and that any slave setting foot on the French ground should be freed. This prompted subsequent governments to circumscribe slavery in the [[French colonial Empire|overseas colonies]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.fr/books?id=480BBURkreYC&amp;pg=PA122&amp;lpg=PA122&amp;dq=The+French+Atlantic+triangle:+literature+and+culture+of+the+slave+trade&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=JLHt0HSVOh&amp;sig=jGgNK6Ek6fya_s6jHX6VEPPx3h4&amp;hl=fr&amp;ei=h4XkSpTOH4Gr4QbljvX5AQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CAsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Christopher L. Miller, ''The French Atlantic triangle: literature and culture of the slave trade'', p.20.]&lt;/ref&gt; 

As in other &quot;New World&quot; colonies, the French relied on the [[Atlantic slave trade]] for labor for their [[sugar cane]] [[plantations]] in their Caribbean colonies. The [[French West Indies]] included [[Anguilla]] (briefly), [[Antigua and Barbuda]] (briefly), [[Dominica]], Dominican Republic, [[Grenada]], [[Haïti]], [[Montserrat]] (briefly), [[Saint Lucia]], Saint Vincent and the Grenadines, [[Sint Eustatius]] (briefly), [[St Kitts and Nevis]] ([[St Kitts]], but not [[Nevis]]), [[Trinidad and Tobago]] ([[Tobago]] only), [[Saint Croix]] (briefly), [[Saint-Barthélemy]] (until 1784 when became Swedish for nearly a century), the northern half of [[Saint Martin]], and the current French [[Département d'outre-mer|overseas ''départements'']] of [[Martinique]] and [[Guadeloupe]] in the Caribbean sea. In addition, French colonists in ''[[La Louisiane]]'' in North America held slaves, particularly in the South around [[New Orleans]], where they established sugar cane plantations. Over time in all these areas, a class of [[free people of color]] developed, many of whom became educated and property owners.

[[Louis XIV]]'s ''[[Code Noir]]'' regulated the slave trade and institution in the colonies.  Any slave brought to Metropolitan France would be immediately considered free. Although the Code Noir authorized and codified corporal punishment against slaves under certain conditions, it forbid slave owners to torture them and encouraged them to instruct them. It was instrumental in asserting that Africans were human beings, endowed with a soul.

During the [[Age of Enlightenment]], many philosophers wrote pamphlets against slavery and its moral and economical justifications, including [[Montesquieu]] in ''[[The Spirit of the Laws]]'' (1748) or in the ''[[Encyclopédie]]'' In 1788, [[Jacques Pierre Brissot]] founded the [[Society of the Friends of the Blacks]] (''Société des Amis des Noirs'') to work for abolition of slavery. 

After the Revolution, on 4 April 1792, France granted [[free people of color]] full citizenship.

The revolt of slaves in the largest French colony of [[Saint-Domingue]] in 1791 was the beginning of what became the [[Haïtian Revolution]] led by [[Toussaint L'Ouverture]]. Rebellion swept through the north of the island, and many whites and free people of color were killed, as well as slaves. Slavery was first abolished in 1793 in St. Domingue by [[Sonthonax]], a French Commissioner sent by the Convention in order to safeguard the allegiance of the population to revolutionary France.

===First abolition of slavery (1794)===
[[Image:Brissot.jpg|thumb|150px|[[Jacques Pierre Brissot]] (1754–1793), who organised the [[Society of the Friends of the Blacks]] in 1788 in the midst of the [[French Revolution]].]]

The Convention, the first elected Assembly of the [[French First Republic|First Republic]] (1792–1804), on 4 February 1794, under the leadership of [[Maximilien Robespierre]], abolished slavery in law in France and its colonies. [[Henri Grégoire|Abbé Grégoire]] and the Society of the Friends of the Blacks were part of the abolitionist movement, which had laid important groundwork in building anti-slavery sentiment in the [[Metropolitan France|metropole]]. The first article of the law stated that &quot;Slavery was abolished&quot; in the French colonies, while the second article stated that &quot;slave-owners would be indemnified&quot; with financial compensation for the value of their slaves.  The French constitution passed in 1795 included in the declaration of the Rights of Man that slavery was abolished.

===Re-establishment of slavery (1802)===
[[Napoleon]] did not include any declaration of the Rights of Man in the Constitution promulgated in 1799. Lobbied by planters and concerned about revenues from the Caribbean islands, after becoming [[First Consul]], he decided to re-establish slavery. He promulgated the [[law of 20 May 1802]] and sent military governors and troops to the colonies to impose it. On 10 May 1802, [[Louis Delgrès|Colonel Delgrès]] launched a rebellion in Guadeloupe against Napoleon's representative, [[Antoine Richepanse|General Richepanse]]. The rebellion was repressed, and slavery was re-established. The news of this event sparked another wave of rebellion in Saint-Domingue. Although from 1802, Napoleon sent more than 20,000 troops to the island, two-thirds died due to warfare and yellow fever. He withdrew the remaining 7,000 troops and slaves achieved an independent republic they called [[Haïti]] in 1804. Seeing that he had lost Saint-Domingue, in 1803 Napoleon decided to sell the [[Louisiana Territory]] to the United States and end his attempt at empire in North America. The French governments initially refused to recognise Haiti. It forced the nation to pay a substantial amount of reparations (which it could ill afford) for losses during the revolution and did not recognise its government until the 1830s.

===Second abolition (1848)===
[[Image:Biard Abolition de l'esclavage 1849.jpg|thumb|left|150px|&quot;Abolition of Slavery in French Colonies, 1848&quot; by [[Auguste François Biard]] (1849).]]

On 27 April 1848, under the [[French Second Republic|Second Republic]] (1848–52), the [[decree-law]] of [[Victor Schoelcher|Schœlcher]] abolished slavery in the remaining colonies. The state bought the slaves from the ''colons'' (white colonists; ''[[:fr:Béké|Békés]]'' in [[Creole language|Creole]]), and then freed them.

At about the same time, France started colonising Africa. Its activities included [[population transfer|transferring]] the Native populations in several countries to [[mining|mines]], [[forestry]], and rubber plantations under isolated, harsh working conditions often compared to slavery.

Debates about the dimensions of colonialism continue. Passed on 10 May 2001, the [[Christiane Taubira|Taubira law]] officially acknowledges slavery and the Atlantic Slave Trade as a [[crime against humanity]]. 10 May was chosen as the day dedicated to recognition of the crime of slavery. Anti-colonial activists also want the French Republic to recognise [[African Liberation Day]].

Although France formally recognised slavery as a crime, four years later, the conservative [[Union for a Popular Movement]] (UMP) voted on 23 February 2005 for a French law to require teachers and textbooks to &quot;acknowledge and recognise in particular the positive role of the French presence abroad, especially in North Africa.&quot;  This resolution was met with public uproar and accusations of [[historical revisionism (negationism)|historic revisionism]], both inside France and abroad. 

Because of this law, [[Abdelaziz Bouteflika]], the president of [[Algeria]], refused to sign the envisioned &quot;friendly treaty&quot; with France. The writer and politician [[Aimé Césaire]], leader of the ''[[Négritude]]'' movement from [[Martinique]], refused to meet UMP leader [[Nicolas Sarkozy]], who cancelled his planned visit to the island. President [[Jacques Chirac]] (UMP) repealed the controversial law at the beginning of 2006.

==Moldavia and Wallachia==
{{Main|Slavery in Romania}}
In the principalities of [[Wallachia]] and [[Moldavia]] (both now part of [[Romania]]), the government held slavery of the [[Romani people|Roma]] (often referred to as Gypsies) [[Slavery in Romania|as legal]] at the beginning of the 19th century. The progressive pro-European and anti-Ottoman movement, which gradually gained power in the two principalities, also worked to abolish that slavery. Between 1843 and 1855, the principalities emancipated all of the 250,000 enslaved Roma people. Many migrated to Western Europe and North America.

==In the Americas==
Bartolomé de las Casas was a 16th-century [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] [[Dominican Order|Dominican]] priest, the first resident Bishop of [[Chiapas]]. As a settler in the [[New World]] he witnessed and opposed the poor treatment of the [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]] by the Spanish colonists. He advocated before King [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor]] on behalf of rights for the natives. Originally supporting the importation of African slaves as laborers, he eventually changed and became an advocate for the Africans in the colonies.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/3184668.stm |title=Columbus 'sparked a genocide' |accessdate=21 October 2006 |date=12 October 2003 |publisher=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Blackburn 1997: 136; Friede 1971:165–166. Las Casas' change in his views on African slavery is expressed particularly in chapters 102 and 129, Book III of his ''Historia''.&lt;/ref&gt;
His book, ''[[A Short Account of the Destruction of the Indies]],'' contributed to Spanish passage of colonial legislation known as the [[New Laws of 1542]], which abolished native slavery for the first time in European colonial history. It ultimately led to the [[Valladolid debate]].
[[File:Hugh Elliot.png|right|thumb|160px|[[Hugh Elliot]] was a noted abolitionist. Whilst Governor in the British West Indies, he was reported to be the driving force behind the arrest, trial and execution of a wealthy white planter [[Arthur William Hodge|Arthur Hodge]] for the murder of a slave.]]

===Latin America===
During the Independence Wars (1810–1822), slavery was abolished in most of Latin America. It continued in the region until 1873 in Puerto Rico, 1886 in Cuba, and 1888 in Brazil by the [[Lei Áurea]] or &quot;Golden Law.&quot; [[Chile]] declared [[freedom of wombs]] in 1811, followed by the [[United Provinces of the Río de la Plata]] in 1813, but without abolishing slavery completely. While Chile abolished slavery in 1823, Argentina did so with the signing of the [[Argentine Constitution of 1853]]. Slavery was abolished in Uruguay during the ''[[Uruguayan Civil War|Guerra Grande]]'', by both the government of [[Fructuoso Rivera]] and the [[government in exile]] of [[Manuel Oribe]].

===Canada===
{{main|Slavery in Canada}}
With slaves escaping to New York and New England, legislation for gradual emancipation was passed in [[Upper Canada]] (1793) and [[Lower Canada]] (1803). In Upper Canada the Assembly ruled that no slaves could be imported; slaves already in the province would remain enslaved until death, no new slaves could be brought into Upper Canada, and children born to female slaves would be slaves but must be freed at age 25. In practice, some slavery continued until abolished in the entire [[British Empire]] in the 1830s.&lt;ref&gt;Robin Winks, ''Blacks in Canada: A History'' (1971)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{clear}}

===United States===
The historian [[James M. McPherson]] defines an abolitionist &quot;as one who before the Civil War had agitated for the immediate, unconditional, and total abolition of slavery in the United States.&quot;  He does not include antislavery activists such as Abraham Lincoln or the Republican Party, which called for the gradual ending of slavery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=James M. McPherson|title=The Abolitionist Legacy: From Reconstruction to the Naacp|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sWfgQto81NsC&amp;pg=PA4|year=1995|publisher=Princeton U.P.|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first attempts to end slavery in the British/American colonies came from [[Thomas Jefferson]] and some of his contemporaries. Jefferson included strong anti-slavery language in the original draft of the [[United States Declaration of Independence|Declaration of Independence]], but other delegates took it out. As President, he signed the [[Act Prohibiting Importation of Slaves]] on March 2, 1807, and it took effect in 1808, which was the earliest allowed under the Constitution. In 1820 he privately supported the [[Missouri Compromise]], believing it would help to end slavery.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Peterson60|Peterson, 1960]] p.189&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#TJFslavery|Monticello Foundation, 2012]]&lt;/ref&gt; He left the anti-slavery struggle to younger men after that.{{sfn|Cogliano|2006|p=219}}

In the 1850s in fifteen states constituting the [[American South]], slavery was established legally. While it was fading away in the cities and border states, it remained strong in plantation areas that grew cotton for export, or sugar, tobacco or hemp. By the [[1860 United States Census]], the slave population in the United States had grown to four million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itd.nps.gov/cwss/manassas/social/introsoc.htm Introduction – Social Aspects of the Civil War], National Park Service&lt;/ref&gt; American abolitionism was based in the North, and white Southerners alleged it fostered slave rebellion. 

The white abolitionist movement in the North was led by social reformers, especially [[William Lloyd Garrison]], founder of the [[American Anti-Slavery Society]]; writers such as [[John Greenleaf Whittier]] and [[Harriet Beecher Stowe]]. Black activists included former slaves such as [[Frederick Douglass]]; and free blacks such as the brothers [[Charles Henry Langston]] and [[John Mercer Langston]], who helped found the Ohio Anti-Slavery Society.&lt;ref&gt;Leon F. Litwack and August Meier, eds., &quot;John Mercer Langston: Principle and Politics&quot;, in ''Black Leaders of the 19th century'', University of Illinois Press, 1991, pp. 106–111&lt;/ref&gt;  Some abolitionists said that slavery was criminal and a sin; they also criticized slave owners of using black women as concubines and taking sexual advantage of them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=James A. Morone|title=Hellfire Nation: The Politics Of Sin In American History|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=XnP-vMOiRREC&amp;pg=PA154|year= 2004|publisher=Yale U.P.|page=154}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Republican Party wanted to achieve the gradual extinction of slavery by market forces, for its members believed that free labor was superior to slave labor. Southern leaders said the Republican policy of blocking the expansion of slavery into the West made them second-class citizens, and challenged their autonomy. With the [[United States presidential election, 1860|1860 presidential victory]] of [[Abraham Lincoln]], seven Deep South states whose economy was based on cotton and slavery decided to secede and form a new nation. Others joined them. The [[American Civil War]] broke out in April 1861 with the firing on Fort Sumter in South Carolina.  In 1863, Lincoln issued the [[Emancipation Proclamation]], which freed slaves held in the [[Confederate States]]; most border states began their own emancipation programs. Thousands of slaves escaped to freedom behind Union Army lines, and in 1863 many men started serving as the [[United States Colored Troops]]. The [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution]] took effect in December 1865 and finally ended slavery throughout the United States.

====Calls for abolition====
The first American call to abolish slavery came in April 1688 when [[Quakers]] in [[Germantown, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|Germantown, Pennsylvania]] wrote a two-page condemnation of the practice and sent it to the governing bodies of their Quaker church, the [[Society of Friends]]. The Quaker establishment never took action. [[The 1688 Germantown Quaker Petition Against Slavery]] was an unusually early, clear and forceful argument against slavery and initiated the spirit that finally led to the end of slavery in the Society of Friends (1776) and in the state of [[Pennsylvania]] (1780).
[[Image:Thomas Paine.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[Thomas Paine]] (1737–1805), whose 1775 article &quot;African Slavery in America&quot; was one of the first article the United States which advocated abolishing slavery and freeing the slaves.]]
The [[Society for the Relief of Free Negroes Unlawfully Held in Bondage]] was the first American abolition society, formed 14 April 1775, in Philadelphia, primarily by Quakers. The society suspended operations in the Revolutionary war and was reorganized in 1784, with [[Benjamin Franklin]] as its first president.&lt;ref&gt;Richard S. Newman, ''The Transformation of American Abolitionism: Fighting Slavery in the Early Republic'' (U. of North Carolina Press, 2002)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rhode Island]] Quakers, associated with [[Moses Brown]], were among the first in America to free slaves. [[Benjamin Rush]] was another leader, as were many Quakers. [[John Woolman]] gave up most of his business in 1756 to devote himself to campaigning against slavery along with other Quakers.&lt;ref&gt;John Woolman. [http://historymatters.gmu.edu/d/6538/ A Quaker Abolitionist Travels Through Maryland and Virginia] Extract from The Journal of John Woolman, 1757, New York: Houghton Mifflin, 1909, 209–217.&lt;/ref&gt; Among the first articles advocating the emancipation of slaves and the abolition of slavery was written by [[Thomas Paine]].  Titled &quot;African Slavery in America&quot;, it appeared on 8 March 1775 in the ''[[The Pennsylvania Journal|Postscript to the Pennsylvania Journal and Weekly Advertiser]]'', more popularly known as ''The Pennsylvania Magazine'', or ''American Museum''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Thomas Paine|author2=Thomas Paul Slaughter|title=Common Sense and Related Writings|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Ls0x-NyF-HYC&amp;pg=PA57|year= 2001|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|page=57}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Abolition in the North====
Through the [[Northwest Ordinance]] of 1787, the [[Congress of the Confederation]] prohibited slavery in the territories northwest of the [[Ohio River]]. By 1804, abolitionists succeeded in passing legislation in most states north of the Ohio River and the [[Mason-Dixon Line]] that would eventually (in conjunction with the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|13th amendment]]) emancipate the slaves. While Massachusetts did not abolish slavery, its new constitution of 1780 declared the equal rights of men and became the standard against which slavery ceased. But, emancipation in some of the free states was so gradual that both New York and Pennsylvania, for example, still listed slaves in their 1840 census returns, and a small number of black slaves (18) were held in New Jersey in 1860 as &quot;perpetual apprentices&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=idktzKdgb7YC&amp;pg=PA471&amp;dq=1840+census+-+new+jersey+slaves&amp;cd=6#v=onepage&amp;q=page%20471&amp;f=false ''Dictionary of Afro-American Slavery''] By Randall M. Miller, John David Smith.  Greenwood Publishing Group, 1997. p.471.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.census.gov/prod2/decennial/documents/1860a-10.pdf Population of the United States in 1860, p313] Eight Census of the United States, 1860&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:John Jay (Gilbert Stuart portrait).jpg|thumb|right|150px|[[John Jay]] (1745–1829), who founded the [[New York Manumission Society]] in 1785.]]
The principal organized bodies to advocate this reform were the Pennsylvania Antislavery Society and the [[New York Manumission Society]].  The latter was headed by powerful politicians:  [[John Jay]], [[Alexander Hamilton]], later Federalists, and [[Aaron Burr]], later the Democratic-Republican Vice-President of the United States. That bill did not pass, because of controversy over the rights of freed slaves, although every member of the Legislature but one voted for some version of it. New York did enact a bill in 1799 that ended slavery over time, but made no provision for the rights of freedmen.  Free blacks were subject to [[Racial segregation in the United States#In the North|racial segregation]] and discrimination in the North.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIA4&quot;&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/aia/part4/4narr3.html &quot;Africans in America&quot;] – PBS Series – Part 4 (2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

At the United States [[Philadelphia Convention|Constitutional Convention]] of 1787, delegates debated over slavery, finally agreeing to protect the international slave trade for 20 years by not regulating it before 1808. By that time, all the states had passed individual laws abolishing or severely limiting the international buying or selling of slaves.&lt;ref&gt;Ira Berlin and Leslie Harris (2005); Gellman (2006);&lt;/ref&gt; The importation of slaves into the United States was officially banned on 1 January 1808.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/30/opinion/30foner.html Foner, Eric. &quot;Forgotten step towards freedom&quot;], ''New York Times.'' 30 December 2007,&lt;/ref&gt; No action was taken on the nation's internal domestic slave trade.

====Manumission by owners====
After 1776, [[Quaker]] and [[Moravian Church|Moravian]] advocates helped persuade numerous slaveholders in the [[Upper South]] to free their slaves.  Manumissions increased for nearly two decades.  Many individual acts of manumission freed thousands of slaves.  Slaveholders freed slaves in such number that the percentage of free Negroes in the [[Upper South]] increased sharply from one to ten percent, with most of that increase in [[Virginia]], [[Maryland]] and [[Delaware]].  By 1810 three-quarters of blacks in Delaware were free.  The most notable of individuals was [[Robert Carter III]] of Virginia, who freed more than 450 people by &quot;Deed of Gift&quot;, filed in 1791.  This number was more slaves than any single American had freed or would ever free.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Levy, ''The First Emancipator: Slavery, Religion and the Quiet Revolution of Robert Carter'', New York: Random House, 2005, p.xi&lt;/ref&gt;  Often slaveholders came to their decisions by their own struggles in the Revolution; their wills and deeds frequently cited language about the equality of men supporting their manumissions.  Slaveholders were also encouraged to do so because the economics of the area was changing.  They were shifting from labor-intensive tobacco culture to mixed crop cultivation and did not need as many slaves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter Kolchin 1994, pp.78, 81&quot;&gt;Peter Kolchin, ''American Slavery, 1619–1877'', New York: Hill and Wang, 1994, pp.78, 81–82&lt;/ref&gt;

The free black families began to thrive, together with African Americans free before the Revolution, mostly descendants of unions between working class white women and African men.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freeafricanamericans.com/ Paul Heinegg, ''Free African Americans of Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Maryland and Delaware''], 2005, Retrieved 15 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  By 1860, in Delaware 91.7 percent of the blacks were free, and 49.7 percent of those in Maryland.  These first free families often formed the core of artisans, professionals, preachers and teachers in future generations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peter Kolchin 1994, pp.78, 81&quot;/&gt;

====Western territories====
During the Congressional debate on 1820 [[Tallmadge Amendment]], which sought to limit slavery in [[Missouri]] as it became a state, [[Rufus King]] declared that &quot;laws or compacts imposing any such condition [slavery] upon any human being are absolutely void, because contrary to the law of nature, which is the law of God, by which he makes his ways known to man, and is paramount to all human control.&quot; The amendment failed and Missouri became a slave state.  According to historian [[David Brion Davis]], this may have been the first time in the world that a political leader openly attacked slavery's perceived legality in such a radical manner.

Beginning in the 1830s, the U.S. [[United States Postmaster General|Postmaster General]] refused to allow the mails to carry abolition pamphlets to the South.&lt;ref&gt;Schlesinger ''Age of Jackson'', p.190&lt;/ref&gt;  Northern teachers suspected of abolitionism were expelled from the South, and abolitionist literature was banned. Southerners rejected the denials of Republicans that they were abolitionists.  They pointed to [[John Brown (abolitionist)|John Brown's]] attempt in 1859 to start a slave uprising as proof that multiple Northern conspiracies were afoot to ignite bloody slave rebellions. Although some abolitionists did call for slave revolts, no evidence of any other Brown-like conspiracy has been discovered.&lt;ref&gt;David Brion Davis, ''Inhuman Bondage'' (2006) p 197, 409; Stanley Harrold, ''The Abolitionists and the South, 1831–1861'' (1995) p. 62; Jane H. and William H. Pease, &quot;Confrontation and Abolition in the 1850s&quot; ''Journal of American History'' (1972) 58(4): 923–937.&lt;/ref&gt; The North felt threatened as well, for as Eric Foner concludes, &quot;Northerners came to view slavery as the very antithesis of the good society, as well as a threat to their own fundamental values and interests&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Eric Foner. ''Free Soil, Free Labor, Free Men: The Ideology of the Republican Party Before the Civil War'' (1970),  p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;  However, many conservative Northerners were uneasy at the prospect of the sudden addition to the labor pool of a huge number of freed laborers who were used to working for very little, and thus seen as being willing to undercut prevailing wages.{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}. The famous, &quot;fiery&quot; Abolitionist, [[Abby Kelley Foster]], from [[Massachusetts]], was considered an &quot;ultra&quot; abolitionist who believed in full civil rights for all black people. She held to the views that the freed slaves would colonize Liberia. Parts of the anti-slavery movement became known as &quot;Abby Kellyism&quot;. She recruited [[Susan B Anthony]] to the movement.

====Colonization and the founding of Liberia====
[[Image:HClay.jpg|right|thumb|150px|[[Henry Clay]] (1777–1852), one of the three founders of the [[American Colonization Society]].]]
In the early part of the 19th century, a variety of organizations were established advocating the movement of black people from the United States to locations where they would enjoy greater freedom; some endorsed [[colony|colonization]], while others advocated emigration. During the 1820s and 1830s the [[American Colonization Society]] (A.C.S.) was the primary vehicle for proposals to return black Americans to freedom in Africa. It had broad support nationwide among white people, including prominent leaders such as [[Abraham Lincoln]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://academic.udayton.edu/race/02rights/slave07.htm#Free%20them Lincoln on Slavery]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Henry Clay]] and [[James Monroe]], who saw this as preferable to [[emancipation]], with Clay stating: &quot;unconquerable prejudice resulting from their color, they never could amalgamate with the free whites of this country. It was desirable, therefore, as it respected them, and the residue of the population of the country, to drain them off&quot;.&lt;ref name=ATH&gt;Maggie Montesinos Sale (1997). ''The slumbering volcano: American slave ship revolts and the production of rebellious masculinity.'' p.264. Duke University Press, 1997. ISBN 0-8223-1992-6&lt;/ref&gt; Clay argued that as blacks could never be fully integrated into society due to &quot;unconquerable prejudice&quot; by white Americans, it would be better for them to emigrate to Africa.&lt;ref name=ATH/&gt; There was however, considerable opposition among African Americans, many of whom did not see colonization as a viable or acceptable solution to their daunting problems in the United States. One notable opponent of such plans was the wealthy free black abolitionist [[James Forten]] of [[Philadelphia]].

After a series of attempts to plant small settlements on the coast of West Africa, the A.C.S. established the colony of [[Liberia]] in 1821–22. Over the next four decades, it assisted thousands of former slaves and free black people to move there from the United States. The disease environment they encountered was extreme, and most of the migrants died fairly quickly.  Enough survived to [[History of Liberia|declare independence]] in 1847.  American support for colonization waned gradually through the 1840s and 1850s, largely because of the efforts of abolitionists to promote emancipation of slaves and granting of American citizenship. [[Americo-Liberian]]s ruled Liberia continuously until the [[coup d'état|military coup]] of 1980.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2003/07/0721_030721_liberia.html History Haunts War-Torn Liberia]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Emigration====
The emigrationist tradition dated back to the Revolutionary War era. Initially, the thought was that free African Americans would want to emigrate to Africa, but over time other ideas became popular. After Haiti became independent, it tried to recruit African Americans to migrate there after it re-established trade relations with the United States. The [[Haitian Union]] was the name of a group formed to promote relations between the countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nikki&quot;&gt;Taylor, Nikki M. ''Frontiers of Freedom: Cincinnati's Black Community, 1802–1868.'' Ohio University Press, 2005, ISBN 0-8214-1579-4, pp. 50–79.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cincinnati]]'s Black community sponsored founding the [[Wilberforce Colony]], an initially successful settlement of African American immigrants to Canada. The colony was one of the first such independent political entities. It lasted for a number of decades and provided a destination for about 200 black families emigrating from a number of locations in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nikki&quot;/&gt;

====Religion and morality====
The [[Second Great Awakening]] of the 1820s and 1830s in religion inspired groups that undertook many types of social reform. For some that meant the immediate abolition of slavery because it was a sin to hold slaves and a sin to tolerate slavery.  &quot;Abolitionist&quot; had several meanings at the time. The followers of [[William Lloyd Garrison]], including [[Wendell Phillips]] and [[Frederick Douglass]], demanded the &quot;immediate abolition of slavery&quot;, hence the name.  A more pragmatic group of abolitionists, like Theodore Weld and Arthur Tappan, wanted immediate action, but that action might well be a program of gradual emancipation, with a long intermediate stage. &quot;Antislavery men&quot;, like [[John Quincy Adams]], did not call slavery a sin. They called it an evil feature of society as a whole. They did what they could to limit slavery and end it where possible, but were not part of any abolitionist group. For example, in 1841 Adams represented the [[United States v. The Amistad|Amistad]] African slaves in the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] and argued that they should be set free.[http://www.npg.si.edu/col/amistad/index.htm] In the last years before the war, &quot;antislavery&quot; could mean the Northern majority, like [[Abraham Lincoln]], who opposed ''expansion'' of slavery or its influence, as by the [[Kansas-Nebraska Act]], or the Fugitive Slave Act. Many Southerners called all these abolitionists, without distinguishing them from the Garrisonians.

Historian James Stewart (1976) explains the abolitionists' deep beliefs: &quot;All people were equal in God's sight; the souls of black folks were as valuable as those of whites; for one of God's children to enslave another was a violation of the Higher Law, even if it was sanctioned by the Constitution.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;James Brewer Stewart, ''Holy Warriors: The Abolitionists and American Slavery'' (1976)&lt;/ref&gt;

Slave owners were angry over the attacks on what some Southerners (including the politician [[John C. Calhoun]] [http://www.clemson.edu/welcome/history/forthill/calhoun.htm]) referred to as their [[peculiar institution]] of slavery. Starting in the 1830s, there was a vehement and growing ideological defense of slavery.&lt;ref&gt;David Brion Davis, ''Inhuman Bondage'' (2006) pp 186–192.&lt;/ref&gt; Slave owners claimed that slavery was a positive good for masters and slaves alike, and that it was explicitly sanctioned by God. Biblical arguments were made in defense of slavery by religious leaders such as the Rev. Fred A. Ross and political leaders such as [[Jefferson Davis]].&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell Snay, &quot;American Thought and Southern Distinctiveness: The Southern Clergy and the Sanctification of Slavery&quot;, ''Civil War History'' (1989) 35(4): 311–328; Elizabeth Fox-Genovese and Eugene D. Genovese, ''The Mind of the Master Class: History and Faith in the Southern Slaveholders' Worldview'' (2005), pp 505–27.&lt;/ref&gt; There were Southern biblical interpretations that directly contradicted those of the abolitionists, such as the theory that a curse on Noah's son Ham and his descendants in Africa was a justification for enslavement of blacks.

====Garrison and immediate emancipation====
[[Image:William garrison.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[William Lloyd Garrison]] (1805–1879), publisher of the abolitionist newspaper ''[[The Liberator (anti-slavery newspaper)|The Liberator]]'' and one of the founders of the [[American Anti-Slavery Society]].]]
A radical shift came in the 1830s, led by [[William Lloyd Garrison]], who demanded &quot;immediate emancipation, gradually achieved&quot;. That is, he demanded that slave-owners repent immediately, and set up a system of emancipation. [[Theodore Weld]], an evangelical minister, and [[Robert Purvis]], a free African American, joined Garrison in 1833 to form the [[American Anti-Slavery Society]] (Faragher 381). The following year Weld encouraged a group of students at Lane Theological Seminary to form an anti-slavery society. After the president, [[Lyman Beecher]], attempted to suppress it, the students moved to [[Oberlin College]]. Due to the students' anti-slavery position, Oberlin soon became one of the most liberal colleges and accepted African American students. Along with Garrison, were Northcutt and Collins as proponents of immediate abolition. These two ardent abolitionists felt very strongly that it could not wait and that action needed to be taken right away. [[Abby Kelley Foster]] became an &quot;ultra abolitionist&quot; and a follower of William Lloyd Garrison. She led [[Susan B. Anthony]] as well as Elizabeth Cady Stanton into the anti-slavery cause.  [[Image:Frederick Douglass as a younger man.jpg|thumb|right|150px|[[Frederick Douglass]] (1818–1895), a former slave whose memoirs, ''[[Narrative of the Life of Frederick Douglass, an American Slave]]'' (1845) and ''[[My Bondage and My Freedom]]'' (1855), became bestsellers which aided the cause of abolition.]]
After 1840 &quot;abolition&quot; usually referred to positions like Garrison's; it was largely an ideological movement led by about 3000 people, including free blacks and people of color, many of whom, such as [[Frederick Douglass]], and [[Robert Purvis]] and [[James Forten]] in Philadelphia, played prominent leadership roles. Douglass became legally free during a two year stay in England, as British supporters raised funds to purchase his freedom from his American owner Thomas Auld, and also helped fund his abolitionist newspapers in the US.&lt;ref&gt;Marianne Ruuth (1996). [http://books.google.com/books?id=4Lx8nXxmAlcC&amp;pg=PA118&amp;dq=Douglass+-+england+-+not+%22as+a+color,+but+as+a+man&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=DkicTsr7H4yz8QOFrIDMBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Douglass%20-%20england%20-%20not%20%22as%20a%20color%2C%20but%20as%20a%20man&amp;f=false Frederick Douglass] p.117-118. Holloway House Publishing, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; Abolitionism had a strong religious base including Quakers, and people converted by the revivalist fervor of the [[Second Great Awakening]], led by [[Charles Finney]] in the North in the 1830s. Belief in abolition contributed to the breaking away of some small denominations, such as the [[Free Methodist Church]].

[[Evangelicalism|Evangelical]] abolitionists founded some colleges, most notably [[Bates College]] in [[Maine]] and [[Oberlin College]] in [[Ohio]].  The well-established colleges, such as [[Harvard University|Harvard]], [[Yale]] and [[Princeton University|Princeton]], generally opposed abolition,{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} although the movement did attract such figures as Yale president [[Noah Porter]] and Harvard president [[Thomas Hill (clergyman)|Thomas Hill]].

In the North, most opponents of slavery supported other modernizing reform movements such as the [[temperance movement]], [[Public school (government funded)|public schooling]], and prison- and asylum-building. They were split bitterly on the role of women's activism.

Abolitionists like [[William Lloyd Garrison]] repeatedly condemned slavery for contradicting the principles of freedom and equality on which the country was founded. In 1854, Garrison wrote:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I am a believer in that portion of the Declaration of American Independence in which it is set forth, as among self-evident truths, &quot;that all men are created equal; that they are endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable rights; that among these are life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.&quot; Hence, I am an abolitionist. Hence, I cannot but regard oppression in every form – and most of all, that which turns a man into a thing – with indignation and abhorrence. Not to cherish these feelings would be recreancy to principle. They who desire me to be dumb on the subject of slavery, unless I will open my mouth in its defense, ask me to give the lie to my professions, to degrade my manhood, and to stain my soul. I will not be a liar, a poltroon, or a hypocrite, to accommodate any party, to gratify any sect, to escape any odium or peril, to save any interest, to preserve any institution, or to promote any object. Convince me that one man may rightfully make another man his slave, and I will no longer subscribe to the Declaration of Independence. Convince me that liberty is not the inalienable birthright of every human being, of whatever complexion or clime, and I will give that instrument to the consuming fire. I do not know how to espouse freedom and slavery together.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=No Compromise with Slavery |year=1854 |author=Wm. L. Garrison |url=http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?ammem/rbaapc:@field(DOCID+@lit(rbaapc11000div2))}}; also Mayer: ''All in the Fire'', pp. 65–67, 475.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[File:UncleTomsCabinCover.jpg|thumb|right|180px|''[[Uncle Tom's Cabin]]'' inflamed public opinion in the North and in Britain against the personified evils of slavery.]]

====''Uncle Tom’s Cabin''====
The most influential abolitionist tract was [[Uncle Tom's Cabin|''Uncle Tom’s Cabin'']] (1852), the best-selling novel and play by [[Harriet Beecher Stowe]]. Outraged by the [[Fugitive Slave Law of 1850]] (which made the escape narrative part of everyday news), Stowe emphasized the horrors that abolitionists had long claimed about slavery. Her depiction of the evil slave owner Simon Legree, a transplanted Yankee who kills the Christ-like Uncle Tom, outraged the North, helped sway British public opinion against the South, and inflamed Southern slave owners who tried to refute it by showing some slave owners were humanitarian.&lt;ref&gt;Noel B, Gerson, ''Harriet Beecher Stowe'' (1976) p.68&lt;/ref&gt;

====Irish Catholics====
[[Daniel O'Connell]], the Catholic leader of the Irish in Ireland, supported the abolition of slavery in the British Empire and in America. O'Connell had played a leading role in securing [[Catholic Emancipation]] (the removal of the civil and political disabilities of Roman Catholics in Great Britain and Ireland) and he was one of [[William Lloyd Garrison]]'s models. Garrison recruited him to the cause of American abolitionism.  O'Connell, the black abolitionist [[Charles Lenox Remond]], and the temperance priest [[Theobald Mathew (temperance reformer)|Theobald Mathew]] organized a petition with 60,000 signatures urging the Irish of the United States to support abolition. O'Connell also spoke in the United States for abolition.

[[File:1829-Frances-Wright-goose-caricature.jpg|left|thumb|150px|1829 editorial cartoon mocking the Scottish-born abolitionist [[Frances Wright]].]]
The [[Repeal Association]]s in the United States mostly took a pro-slavery position. Several reasons have been suggested for this: that Irish immigrants were competing with free blacks for jobs, and disliked having the same arguments used for Irish and for black freedom; that they were loyal to the [[United States Constitution]], which defended ''their'' liberties, and disliked the fundamentally extra-constitutional position of the Abolitionists; and that they perceived abolitionism as Protestant, and were therefore suspicious of them. In addition, slaveholders had no hesitation in voicing their support for the freedom of Ireland, a white nation outside the United States. However, it would be difficult to find evidence in the letters or oral tradition of immigrant families that would differentiate them from most Americans of the period.  In fact with most immigrants settling in the North, there was actually very little competition for work between poor immigrants and the North's relatively small African-American population.  Most of the energy of immigrant families was directed at securing their daily livings and spiritual lives with what was left over for politics channelled into local issues concerning public safety and education.

Radical Irish nationalists – those who broke with O'Connell over his refusal to contemplate the violent overthrow of British rule in Ireland – had a diversity of views about slavery. [[John Mitchel]], who spent the years 1853 to 1875 in America, was a passionate propagandist in favor of slavery; three of his sons fought in the [[Confederate States Army|Confederate Army]]. On the other hand, his former close associate [[Thomas Francis Meagher]] served as a [[Brigadier General#United States|Brigadier General]] in the [[United States Army]] during the [[American Civil War]].

The Catholic Church in America had long ties in slaveholding Maryland and Louisiana.  Despite a firm stand for the spiritual equality of black people, and the resounding condemnation of slavery by Pope Gregory XVI in his bull ''[[In Supremo Apostolatus]]'' issued in 1839, the American church continued in deeds, if not in public discourse, like most of America, to avoid confrontation with slaveholding interests. In 1842, the Archbishop of New York while denouncing slavery,  objected to O'Connell's petition if authentic as unwarranted foreign interference.  The Bishop of Charleston declared that, while Catholic tradition opposed slave trading, it had nothing against slavery.  However, in 1861, the Archbishop of New York wrote to Secretary of War Cameron: &quot;That the Church is opposed to slavery...Her doctrine on that subject is, that it is a crime to reduce men naturally free to a condition of servitude and bondage, as slaves.&quot;  No American bishop supported extra-political abolition or interference with state's rights before the Civil War.  During the Civil War, however, the Archbishop of New York, John Hughes, who was an ally of Lincoln and Seward would denounce Southern bishops as follows: &quot;In their periodicals in New Orleans and Charleston, they have justified the attitude taken by the South on principles of Catholic theology, which I think was an unnecessary, inexpedient, and, for that matter, a doubtful if not dangerous position, at the commencement of so unnatural and lamentable a struggle.&quot;

One historian observed that ritualist churches separated themselves from heretics rather than sinners; he observed that Episcopalians and Lutherans also accommodated themselves to slavery. (Indeed, one southern Episcopal bishop was a Confederate general.)  There were more reasons than religious tradition, however, as the Anglican Church had been the established church in the South during the colonial period.  It was linked to the traditions of landed gentry and the wealthier and educated planter classes, and the Southern traditions longer than any other church.  In addition, while the Protestant missionaries of the Great Awakening initially opposed slavery in the South, by the early decades of the 19th century, Baptist and Methodist preachers in the South had come to an accommodation with it in order to evangelize with farmers and artisans.  By the Civil War, the Baptist and Methodist churches split into regional associations because of slavery.&lt;ref&gt;Dooley 11–15; McKivigan 27 (ritualism), 30, 51, 191, Osofsky; ''ANB'' [[Leonidas Polk]]&lt;/ref&gt;

After O'Connell's failure, the American Repeal Associations broke up; but the Garrisonians rarely relapsed into the &quot;bitter hostility&quot; of American Protestants towards the Roman Church. Some antislavery men joined the [[Know Nothings]] in the collapse of the parties; but [[Edmund Quincy (1808-1877)|Edmund Quincy]] ridiculed it as a mushroom growth, a distraction from the real issues.  Although the Know-Nothing legislature of Massachusetts honored Garrison, he continued to oppose them as violators of fundamental rights to freedom of worship.

In deeds, however, if not by proclamations, the Irish would play a leading role in defeating the South and ending slavery.  General William Tecumseh Sherman, General Phil Sheridan, General George Meade, General John Reynolds, and Dennis Hart Mahan were all raised by Irish families.  Indeed Sherman and Sheridan attended mass at the same Catholic church in Ohio as children.  137 Irish immigrants were awarded the Medal of Honor for Civil War valor, far more than any other immigrant group.  After participating in the assault that broke the Confederate center at Antietam New York City's Irish Brigade would be worse than decimated in repeated desperate assaults on the stonewall at Fredericksburg on the eve of Emancipation.  In the war's little known last chapter, after Appomottox, General Phil Sheridan took command to the Union army's African-American 25th Corps and was sent by Grant with an armada to pacify Texas.  Later President Johnson would relieve Sheridan of command because of Sheridans aggressive enforcement of Reconstruction in Texas and Louisiana.

In the final analysis, none of Lincoln's most prominent opponents were Irish:  George McClellan, August Belmont, Fernando Wood, James Bennett, and Clement Vallandigham.  Of these only Bennett, who shared a mutual dislike of each other with the &quot;Archbishop of New York&quot; was a Catholic.

====Progress of abolition in the United States====
{{Main|Origins of the American Civil War|Slavery in the United States}}
{{See also|Timeline of the African-American Civil Rights Movement}}

=====To 1804=====
Although there were several groups that opposed slavery (such as the [[Society for the Relief of Free Negroes Unlawfully Held in Bondage]]), at the time of the founding of the Republic, there were few states which prohibited slavery outright. The [[United States Constitution|Constitution]] had several provisions which accommodated slavery, although none used the word.  Passed unanimously by the [[Congress of the Confederation]] in 1787, the [[Northwest Ordinance]] forbade slavery in the [[Northwest Territory]], a vast area which had previously belonged to individual states in which slavery was legal.
[[Image:Samuel Sewall.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[Samuel Sewall]] (1652–1730), judge who wrote ''The Selling of Joseph'' (1700) which denounced the spread of slavery in the American colonies.]]

American abolitionism began very early, well before the United States was founded as a nation. An early law abolishing slavery (but not temporary [[indentured servitude]]) in Rhode Island in 1652 floundered within 50 years.&lt;ref&gt;Lauber, Almon Wheeler, ''Indian Slavery in Colonial Times Within the Present Limits of the United States.'' New York: Columbia University, 1913. See also the Rhode Island Historical Society [http://www.rihs.org/faqatt.htm FAQ].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Samuel Sewall]], a prominent Bostonian and one of the judges at the [[Salem Witch Trials]], wrote The Selling of Joseph&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.masshist.org/objects/2004september.cfm |title=The Selling of Joseph: A Memorial |first1=Samuel |last1=Sewall |authorlink=Samuel Sewall |place=Boston |publisher=Bartholomew Green and John Allen ([[Massachusetts Historical Society]]) |year=1700 |accessdate=9 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; in protest of the widening practice of outright slavery as opposed to indentured servitude in the colonies. This is the earliest-recorded anti-slavery tract published in the future United States.

In 1777, [[Vermont]], not yet a state, became the first jurisdiction in North America to prohibit slavery: slaves were not directly freed, but masters were required to remove slaves from Vermont.  The first state to begin a gradual abolition of slavery was Pennsylvania, in 1780. All importation of slaves was prohibited, but none freed at first; only the slaves of masters who failed to register them with the state, along with the &quot;future children&quot; of enslaved mothers. Those enslaved in Pennsylvania before the 1780 law went into effect were not freed until 1847.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ushistory.org/presidentshouse/history/gradual.htm Pennsylvania's Gradual Abolition Act]&lt;/ref&gt;

Massachusetts took an opposite and much more radical position. Its Supreme Court ruled in 1783, that a black man was, indeed, a man; and therefore free under the state's constitution.

[[Image:US Slave Free 1789-1861.gif|thumb|250px|An animation showing when states and territories forbade or admitted slavery 1789–1861]]
[[Image:Lovejoyat1837AltonIllinoisRiot.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Wood engraving of proslavery riot in [[Alton, Illinois]] on 7 November 1837, which resulted in the murder of abolitionist [[Elijah Parish Lovejoy]] (1802–1837).]]
All of the other states north of [[Maryland]] began gradual abolition of slavery between 1781 and 1804, based on the Pennsylvania model. 

=====South=====
The institution remained solid in the South, however and that region's customs and social beliefs evolved into a strident defense of slavery in response to the rise of a stronger anti-slavery stance in the North. In 1835 alone abolitionists mailed over a million pieces of anti-slavery literature to the south. In response southern legislators banned abolitionist literature and encouraged harassment of anyone distributing it.

=====Immediate abolition=====
Abolitionists included those who joined the [[American Anti-Slavery Society]] or its auxiliary groups in the 1830s and 1840s as the movement fragmented.&lt;ref&gt;''Holy Warriors: The Abolitionists and American Slavery'' by James Brewer Stewart, p. 78''&lt;/ref&gt; The fragmented anti-slavery movement included groups such as the [[Liberty Party (1840s)|Liberty Party]]; the American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society; the American Missionary Association; and the Church Anti-Slavery Society. Historians traditionally distinguish between moderate antislavery reformers or gradualists, who concentrated on stopping the spread of slavery, and radical abolitionists or immediatists, whose demands for unconditional emancipation often merged with a concern for black civil rights. However, James Stewart advocates a more nuanced understanding of the relationship of abolition and antislavery prior to the Civil War:
&lt;blockquote&gt;While instructive, the distinction [between antislavery and abolition] can also be misleading, especially in assessing abolitionism's political impact. For one thing, slaveholders never bothered with such fine points. Many immediate abolitionists showed no less concern than did other white Northerners about the fate of the nation's &quot;precious legacies of freedom.&quot; Immediatism became most difficult to distinguish from broader anti-Southern opinions once ordinary citizens began articulating these intertwining beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=James Brewer Stewart|title=Holy Warriors: The Abolitionists and American Slavery|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3gR57ahFQBsC&amp;pg=PA78|year=1997|publisher=Macmillan|page=78}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Anti-slavery advocates were outraged by the murder of [[Elijah Parish Lovejoy]], a white man and editor of an abolitionist newspaper on 7 November 1837, by a pro-slavery mob in Illinois. Nearly all Northern politicians rejected the extreme positions of the abolitionists; [[Abraham Lincoln]], for example. Indeed many northern leaders including Lincoln, [[Stephen Douglas]] (the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] nominee in 1860), [[John C. Fremont]] (the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] nominee in 1856), and [[Ulysses S. Grant]] married into slave owning southern families without any moral qualms.

[[Image:LysanderSpooner.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[Lysander Spooner]] (1808–1887), an [[individualist anarchist]] who wrote ''[[The Unconstitutionality of Slavery]]'' (1845).]]

Antislavery as a principle was far more than just the wish to limit the extent of slavery. Most Northerners recognized that slavery existed in the South and the Constitution did not allow the federal government  to intervene there. Most Northerners favored a policy of gradual and compensated emancipation. After 1849 abolitionists rejected this and demanded it end immediately and everywhere. [[John Brown (abolitionist)|John Brown]] was the only abolitionist known to have actually planned a violent insurrection, though [[David Walker (abolitionist)|David Walker]] promoted the idea. The abolitionist movement was strengthened by the activities of free African-Americans, especially in the black church, who argued that the old Biblical justifications for slavery contradicted the [[New Testament]].

African-American activists and their writings were rarely heard outside the black community; however, they were tremendously influential to some sympathetic white people, most prominently the first white activist to reach prominence, [[William Lloyd Garrison]], who was its most effective propagandist. Garrison's efforts to recruit eloquent spokesmen led to the discovery of ex-slave [[Frederick Douglass]], who eventually became a prominent activist in his own right. Eventually, Douglass would publish his own, widely distributed abolitionist newspaper, the [[North Star (newspaper)|''North Star'']].

In the early 1850s, the American abolitionist movement split into two camps over the issue of the [[United States Constitution]]. This issue arose in the late 1840s after the publication of ''The Unconstitutionality of Slavery'' by [[Lysander Spooner]]. The Garrisonians, led by Garrison and [[Wendell Phillips]], publicly burned copies of the Constitution, called it a pact with slavery, and demanded its abolition and replacement. Another camp, led by [[Lysander Spooner]], [[Gerrit Smith]], and eventually Douglass, considered the Constitution to be an antislavery document. Using an argument based upon [[Natural Law]] and a form of [[social contract]] theory, they said that slavery existed outside of the Constitution's scope of legitimate authority and therefore should be abolished.

Another split in the abolitionist movement was along class lines. The artisan republicanism of [[Robert Dale Owen]] and [[Frances Wright]] stood in stark contrast to the politics of prominent elite abolitionists such as industrialist [[Arthur Tappan]] and his evangelist brother [[Lewis Tappan|Lewis]]. While the former pair opposed slavery on a basis of solidarity of &quot;wage slaves&quot; with &quot;chattel slaves&quot;, the [[Whig Party (United States)|Whiggish]] Tappans strongly rejected this view, opposing the characterization of Northern workers as &quot;slaves&quot; in any sense. (Lott, 129–130)
[[Image:John Brown, The Martyr.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Idealized portrait of [[John Brown (abolitionist)|John Brown]] being adored by an enslaved mother and child as he walks to his execution.]]
Many American abolitionists took an active role in opposing slavery by supporting the [[Underground Railroad]].&lt;ref&gt;Blight, David W. (2001)Passages to Freedom: The Underground Railroad in History and Memory. Smithsonian Books&lt;/ref&gt; This was made illegal by the federal [[Fugitive Slave Law of 1850]].  Nevertheless,  participants like [[Harriet Tubman]], [[Henry Highland Garnet]], [[Alexander Crummell]], [[Amos Noë Freeman]] and others continued with their work.  Abolitionists were particularly active in [[Ohio]], where some worked directly in the Underground Railroad.  Since the state shared a border with slave states, it was a popular place for slaves' escaping across the [[Ohio River]] and up its tributaries, where they sought shelter among supporters who would help them move north to freedom.  Two significant events in the struggle to destroy slavery were the [[Oberlin-Wellington Rescue]] and [[John Brown (abolitionist)|John Brown]]'s raid on [[Harpers Ferry]]. In the South, members of the [[abolitionist movement]] or other people opposing [[slavery]] were often targets of lynch mob violence before the [[American Civil War]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9B0CE7DD1639E733A2575BC1A96F9C946692D7CF Lynching an Abolitionist in Mississippi.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous known abolitionists lived, worked, and worshipped in Downtown Brooklyn, from [[Henry Ward Beecher]], who auctioned slaves into freedom from the pulpit of Plymouth Church, to [[Nathan Egelston]], a leader of the African and Foreign Antislavery Society, who also preached at Bridge Street AME and lived on Duffield Street. His fellow Duffield Street residents, Thomas and Harriet Truesdell were leading members of the Abolitionist movement. Mr. Truesdell was a founding member of the Providence Anti-slavery Society before moving to Brooklyn in 1851. Harriet Truesdell was also very active in the movement, organizing an antislavery convention in Pennsylvania Hall in Philadelphia. The Tuesdell's lived at 227 Duffield Street. Another prominent Brooklyn-based abolitionist was Rev. [[Joshua Leavitt]], trained as a lawyer at Yale who stopped practicing law in order to attend Yale Divinity School, and subsequently edited the abolitionist newspaper ''The Emancipator'' and campaigned against slavery, as well as advocating other social reforms. In 1841 Leavitt published his ''The Financial Power of Slavery'', which argued that the South was draining the national economy due to its reliance on slavery.

====John Brown====
[[Image:John brown abo.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[John Brown (abolitionist)|John Brown]] (1800–1859), abolitionist who advocated armed rebellion by slaves.  He slaughtered pro-slavery settlers in Kansas and in 1859 was hanged by the state of Virginia for leading an unsuccessful slave insurrection at Harpers Ferry.]]
Historian Frederick Blue called [[John Brown (abolitionist)|John Brown]] &quot;the most controversial of all 19th-century Americans.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Frederick J. Blue in ''American Historical Review'' (April 2006) v. 111 p 481-2.&lt;/ref&gt; When Brown was hanged after his attempt to start a slave rebellion in 1859, church bells rang, minute guns were fired, large memorial meetings took place throughout the North, and famous writers such as [[Ralph Waldo Emerson|Emerson]] and [[Henry David Thoreau]] joined many Northerners in praising Brown.&lt;ref&gt;David Potter, ''The Impending Crisis'' (1976), pp 378–379&lt;/ref&gt; Whereas Garrison was a pacifist, Brown resorted to violence. Historians agree he played a major role in starting the war. Some historians regard Brown as a crazed lunatic while David S. Reynolds hails him as the man who &quot;killed slavery, sparked the civil war, and seeded civil rights.&quot; For Ken Chowder he is &quot;the father of American terrorism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;David S. Reynolds, ''John Brown, Abolitionist: The Man Who Killed Slavery, Sparked the Civil War, and Seeded Civil Rights'' (2005); Ken Chowder, &quot;The Father of American Terrorism.&quot; ''American Heritage'' (2000) 51(1): 81+ online at [http://files.blog-city.com/files/M06/158072/b/chowder.pdf files.blog-city.com]{{dead link|date=June 2012}} [http://web.archive.org/web/20070808175559/files.blog-city.com/files/M06/158072/b/chowder.pdf archive version] and Stephen Oates quoted at [http://www.nps.gov/archive/hafe/jbrown/oates-text.htm nps.gov]{{dead link|date=June 2012}} [http://web.archive.org/web/20090510102805/www.nps.gov/archive/hafe/jbrown/oates-text.htm archive version]&lt;/ref&gt;

His famous raid in October 1859, involved a band of 22 men who seized the federal [[Harpers Ferry Armory]] at [[Harper's Ferry, West Virginia|Harper's Ferry, Virginia]], knowing it contained tens of thousands of weapons. Brown believed that the South was on the verge of a gigantic slave uprising and that one spark would set it off. Brown's supporters [[George Luther Stearns]], [[Franklin B. Sanborn]], [[Thomas Wentworth Higginson]], [[Theodore Parker]], [[Samuel Gridley Howe]] and [[Gerrit Smith]] were all abolitionist members of the [[Secret Six]] who provided financial backing for Brown's raid.  Brown's raid, says historian David Potter, &quot;was meant to be of vast magnitude and to produce a revolutionary slave uprising throughout the South.&quot; The raid was a fiasco. Not a single slave revolted.  Lt. Colonel Robert E. Lee of the U.S. Army was dispatched to put down the raid, and Brown was quickly captured. Brown was tried for treason against Virginia and hanged. At his trial, Brown exuded a remarkable zeal and single-mindedness that played directly to Southerners' worst fears. Few individuals did more to cause secession than John Brown, because Southerners believed he was right about an impending slave revolt. Shortly before his execution, Brown prophesied, &quot;the crimes of this guilty land will never be purged away; but with Blood.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;David Potter, ''The Impending Crisis: 1848–1861'' (1976), chapter 14, quote from p. 367. Allan Nevins, ''Ordeal of the Union: A House Dividing,'' pages 472–477 and ''The Emergence of Lincoln,'' vol 2, pages 71–97&lt;/ref&gt;

====American Civil War====
From the beginning of the [[American Civil War]], Union leaders identified slavery as the social and economic foundation of the Confederacy, and from 1862 were determined to end that support system. Meanwhile pro-Union forces gained control of the [[Border States]] and began the process of emancipation in Maryland, Missouri and West Virginia. Lincoln issued the [[Emancipation Proclamation]] on 1 January 1863, and in the next 24 months it effectively ended slavery throughout the Confederacy. The passage of the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Thirteenth Amendment]] (ratified in December  1865) officially ended slavery in the United States, and freed the 50,000 or so remaining slaves in the border states.&lt;ref&gt;Eric Foner, ''The Fiery Trial: Abraham Lincoln and American Slavery'' (2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable opponents of slavery==
{{Main|List of opponents of slavery}}

==National abolition dates==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Slavery]] --&gt;
{{Main|Abolition of slavery timeline}}

==Commemoration==
The abolitionist movements and the abolition of slavery have been commemorated in different ways around the world in modern times. The United Nations General Assembly declared 2004 the [[International Year to Commemorate the Struggle against Slavery and its Abolition]]. This proclamation marked the bicentenary of the birth of the first black state, Haiti. Numerous exhibitions, events and research programmes were connected to the initiative.

2007 witnessed major exhibitions in British museums and galleries to mark the anniversary of the 1807 abolition act – 1807 Commemorated&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.history.ac.uk/1807commemorated |title=1807 Commemorated |publisher=Institute for the Public Understanding of the Past and the Institute of Historical Research |year=2007 |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 2008 marks the 201st anniversary of the Abolition of the Slave Trade in the British Empire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Slave Trade Act 1807 UK |url=http://www.anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/huk-1807act.htm |publisher=anti-slaverysociety.addr.com }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It also marks the 175th anniversary of the Abolition of Slavery in the British Empire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Slavery Abolition Act 1833 UK |url=http://www.anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/huk-1833act.htm |publisher=anti-slaverysociety.addr.com }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Faculty of Law at the University of Ottawa held a major international conference entitled, &quot;Routes to Freedom:  Reflections on the Bicentenary of the Abolition of the Slave Trade&quot;, from 14 to 16 March 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.abolition1807-2007.uottawa.ca |title=Les Chemins de la Liberté : Réflexions à l'occasion du bicentenaire de  l'abolition de l'esclavage / Routes to freedom : Reflections on the Bicentenary of the Abolition of the Slave Trade |publisher=[[University of Ottawa]], Canada |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Actor and human rights activist [[Danny Glover]] delivered the keynote speech announcing the creation of two major scholarships intended for University of Ottawa law students specializing in international law and social justice at the conference's gala dinner.

Brooklyn, New York has begun work on commemorating the abolitionist movement in New York.

==Contemporary abolitionism==
On 10 December 1948, the [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] of the United Nations adopted the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]]. Article 4 states:
:''No one shall be held in slavery or servitude; slavery and the slave trade shall be prohibited in all their forms.''

Although outlawed in most countries, slavery is nonetheless practiced secretly in many parts of the world.  Enslavement still takes place in the United States, Europe, and Latin America,&lt;ref&gt;[[Kevin Bales|Bales, Kevin]]. ''Ending Slavery: How We Free Today's Slaves.'' University of California Press, 2007, ISBN 978-0-520-25470-1&lt;/ref&gt; as well as parts of Africa, the Middle East, and South Asia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/slavery.htm Does Slavery Still Exist?]. Anti-Slavery Society.&lt;/ref&gt; There are an estimated 27 million victims of slavery worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.un.org/Pubs/chronicle/2005/issue3/0305p28.html |title=Slavery in the Twenty-First Century |publisher=UN Chronicle |year= 2005 |volume=Issue 3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In Mauritania alone, estimates are that up to 600,000 men, women and children, or 20% of the population, are enslaved.  Many of them are used as [[bonded labour]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/6938032.stm |title=Mauritanian MPs pass slavery law |news= [[BBC]] |work=BBC News |date=9 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Modern-day abolitionists have emerged over the last several years, as awareness of slavery around the world has grown, with groups such as [[Anti-Slavery International]], the [[American Anti-Slavery Group]], [[International Justice Mission]], and [[Free the Slaves]] working to rid the world of slavery. [[Zach Hunter]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/Story?id=2951434&amp;page=1 |title=Just 15, He Leads Fight to Abolish Slavery |newspaper=[[ABC News]] |date=15 March 2007 |accessdate=27 November 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20101025101901/http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/Story?id=2951434&amp;page=1| archivedate= 25 October 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; for example, began a movement called Loose Change to Loosen Chains&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lc2lc.org/ |title=Lc2lc homepage |accessdate=27 November 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20101104080614/http://www.lc2lc.org/| archivedate= 4 November 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; when he was in seventh grade. Also featured on [[CNN]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/video/#/video/specials/2007/05/15/heroes.zach.hunter.cnn |publisher=CNN |title=video of Zach Hunter}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other national news organizations, Hunter has gone on to help inspire other teens and young adults to take action against injustice with his books, ''Be the Change'' and ''Generation Change''.

In the United States, The Action Group to End Human Trafficking and Modern-Day Slavery is a coalition of NGOs, [[Foundation (nonprofit organization)|foundations]] and corporations working to develop a policy agenda for abolishing slavery and human trafficking.  Since 1997, the [[United States Department of Justice]] has, through work with the [[Coalition of Immokalee Workers]], prosecuted six individuals in Florida on charges of slavery in the agricultural industry.  These prosecutions have led to freedom for over 1000 enslaved workers in the tomato and orange fields of South Florida.  This is only one example of the contemporary fight against slavery worldwide.  Slavery exists most widely in  agricultural labor, apparel and sex industries, and service jobs in some regions.

In 2000, the United States passed the Victims of Trafficking and Violence Protection Act (TVPA) &quot;to combat trafficking in persons, especially into the sex trade, slavery, and involuntary servitude.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/documents/organization/10492.pdf '''Public Law 106–386 – 28 October 2000, Victims of trafficking and Violence Protection Act of 2000''']&lt;/ref&gt; The TVPA also &quot;created new law enforcement tools to strengthen the prosecution and punishment of traffickers, making human trafficking a Federal crime with severe penalties.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acf.hhs.gov/trafficking/about/TVPA_2000.pdf US Department of Health and Human Services, TVPA Fact Sheet]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Department of State]] publishes the annual Trafficking in Persons Report, identifying countries as either Tier 1, Tier 2, Tier 2 Watch List or Tier 3, depending upon three factors: &quot;(1) The extent to which the country is a country of origin, transit, or destination for severe forms of trafficking; (2) The extent to which the government of the country does not comply with the TVPA's minimum standards including, in particular, the extent of the government's trafficking-related corruption; and (3) The resources and capabilities of the government to address and eliminate severe forms of trafficking in persons.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.state.gov/g/tip/rls/tiprpt/2008/105376.htm |title=US Department of State Trafficking in Persons Report 2008, Introduction |publisher=state.gov}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Abolition of slavery timeline]]
*[[Allan Ramsay (artist)#Abolitionism and Queen Charlotte's paintings|Abolitionism and Queen Charlotte's paintings]]
*[[American Anti-Slavery Society]]
*[[American and Foreign Anti-Slavery Society]], a spin-off of the American Anti-Slavery Society
*[[Anti-Slavery International]]
*[[Anti-Slavery Society]]
*[[Come-outer]]
*[[Compensated emancipation]]
*[[List of opponents of slavery]]
*[[James Redpath]]
*[[Slavery in the British and French Caribbean]]
*[[Slavery in the British Virgin Islands]]
*[[The Slave Power]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==

===Great Britain and World===
{{Refbegin|2}}
* Bader-Zaar, Birgitta: [http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2011120524 ''Abolitionism in the Atlantic World: The Organization and Interaction of Anti-Slavery Movements in the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries''], [[European History Online]], Mainz: [[Institute of European History]], 2010, retrieved: June 14, 2012.
* Brown, Christopher Leslie. ''Moral Capital: Foundations of British Abolitionism'' (2006)
* Davis, David Brion, ''The Problem of Slavery in the Age of Revolution, 1770–1823'' (1999); ''[[The Problem of Slavery in Western Culture]]'' (1988)
* Drescher, Seymour. ''Abolition: A History of Slavery and Antislavery'' (2009)
* Finkelman, Paul, ed. ''Encyclopedia of Slavery'' (1999)
* Gordon, M. ''Slavery in the Arab World'' (1989)
* Gould, Philip.  ''Barbaric Traffic: Commerce and Antislavery in the 18th-century Atlantic World'' (2003)
* Hellie, Richard. ''Slavery in Russia: 1450–1725'' (1982)
* Hinks, Peter, and John McKivigan, eds. ''Encyclopedia of Antislavery and Abolition'' (2 vol. 2006) ISBN 0-313-33142-1; 846pp; 300 articles by experts
* Hochschild, Adam. ''Bury the Chains, Prophets and Rebels in the Fight to Free an Empire's Slaves'' (2005)
* Kolchin, Peter. ''Unfree Labor; American Slavery and Russian Serfdom'' (1987)
* Morgan, Kenneth. ''Slavery and the British Empire: From Africa to America'' (2008)
* Rodriguez, Junius P., ed. &quot;Encyclopedia of Emancipation and Abolition in the Transatlantic World&quot; (2007)
* Rodriguez, Junius P., ed. ''The Historical Encyclopedia of World Slavery'' (1997)
* Thomas, Hugh. ''The Slave Trade: The Story of the Atlantic Slave Trade: 1440–1870'' (2006)
{{Refend}}

===United States and Canada===
{{Refbegin|2}}
* Abzug, Robert H. ''Cosmos Crumbling: American Reform and the Religious Imagination''. Oxford, 1994. ISBN 0-19-503752-9.
*  Bacon, Jacqueline.  ''The Humblest May Stand Forth: Rhetoric, Empowerment, and Abolition''. Univ of South Carolina Press, 2002. ISBN 1-57003-434-6.
* Barnes, Gilbert H. ''The Anti-Slavery Impulse 1830–1844''. Reprint, 1964. ISBN 0-7812-5307-1.
* Berlin, Ira and Leslie Harris. ''Slavery in New York''. New Press, 2005. ISBN 1-56584-997-3.
* Blue, Frederick J.  ''No Taint of Compromise: Crusaders in Antislavery Politics.'' Louisiana State Univ Press, 2004. ISBN 0-8071-2976-3.
* Bordewich, Fergus M.  ''Bound for Canaan: The Underground Railroad and the War for the Soul of America.'' HarperCollins, 2005. ISBN 0-06-052430-8.
*{{cite book|last=Cogliano|first=Francis D|ref=harv |isbn=978-0-7486-2499-7|title=Thomas Jefferson: Reputation and Legacy|publisher=Edinburgh University Press|year=2006}}
*{{cite book|last=Crawford|first=Alan Pell|ref=harv|isbn=978-1-4000-6079-5 |title=Twilight at Monticello: The Final Years of Thomas Jefferson|authorlink=Alan Pell Crawford|publisher=Random House|year=2008}}
* Davis, David Brion, ''Inhuman Bondage: The Rise and Fall of Slavery in the New World'' Oxford, 2006. ISBN 0-19-514073-7.
* Filler, Louis. ''The Crusade Against Slavery 1830–1860''. 1960. ISBN 0-917256-29-8.
*{{cite book |title=I've Got a Home in Glory Land: A Lost Tale of the Underground Railroad|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ANv1C6liU1QC|first1=Karolyn Smardz |last1=Frost |first2=Kwasi (Cover design) |last2=Osei |first3=Sunny (Cover art) |last3=South|place=New York |publisher=Farrar, Straus and Giroux |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-374-16481-2}} ISBN 978-0-374-53125-6.  Winner, 2007 [[Governor General's Awards|Governor General's Literary Award for Nonfiction]]; Nominee (Nonfiction), [[National Book Critics Circle Award]] 2007.  See, [[Governor General's Award for English language non-fiction]].
* David Nathaniel Gellman. ''Emancipating New York: The Politics of Slavery And Freedom, 1777–1827'' Louisiana State Univ Press, 2006. ISBN 0-8071-3174-1.
* Griffin, Clifford S. ''Their Brothers' Keepers: Moral Stewardship in the United States 1800–1865''. Rutgers Univ Press, 1967. ISBN 0-313-24059-0.
* Harrold, Stanley. ''The Abolitionists and the South, 1831–1861''. Univ Press of Kentucky, 1995. ISBN 0-8131-0968-X.
* Harrold, Stanley. ''The American Abolitionists''. Longman, 2000. ISBN 0-582-35738-1.
* Harrold, Stanley. ''The Rise of Aggressive Abolitionism: Addresses to the Slaves''. Univ Press of Kentucky, 2004. ISBN 0-8131-2290-2.
* Hassard, John. ''The Life of John Hughes: First Archbishop of New York''. Arno Press, 1969
* Horton, James Oliver. &quot;Alexander Hamilton: Slavery and Race in a Revolutionary Generation&quot; ''New-York Journal of American History'' 2004 65(3): 16–24. ISSN 1551–5486
* Huston, James L. &quot;The Experiential Basis of the Northern Antislavery Impulse.&quot; ''Journal of Southern History'' 56:4 (November 1990): 609–640.
* Mayer, Henry ''All on Fire: William Lloyd Garrison and the Abolition of Slavery'' St. Martin's Press, 1998. ISBN 0-312-18740-8.
* McKivigan, John R. ''The War Against Proslavery Religion: Abolitionism and the Northern Churches, 1830–1865'' Cornell Univ Press, 1984. ISBN 0-8014-1589-6.
* McPherson, James M. ''The Abolitionist Legacy: From Reconstruction to the NAACP'' Princeton Univ Press, 1975. ISBN 0-691-04637-9.
* Osofsky, Gilbert. &quot;Abolitionists, Irish Immigrants, and the Dilemmas of Romantic Nationalism&quot; ''American Historical Review'' 1975 80(4): 889–912. ISSN 0002-8762 in JSTOR
* Perry, Lewis and Michael Fellman, eds. ''Antislavery Reconsidered: New Perspectives on the Abolitionists''. Louisiana State Univ Press, 1979. ISBN 0-8071-0889-8.
* Peterson, Merrill D. ''John Brown: The Legend Revisited''. Univ Press of Virginia, 2002. ISBN 0-8139-2132-5.
*{{cite book |title=The Jefferson Image in the American Mind |page=548 |last= Peterson |first=Merrill D. |ref=Peterson60 |year=1960 |pages=548 |publisher=University of Virginia Press. |ISBN=0-8139-1851-0}}
* Pierson, Michael D. ''Free Hearts and Free Homes: Gender and American Antislavery Politics''. Univ of North Carolina Press, 2003. ISBN 0-8078-2782-7.
* Schafer, Judith Kelleher. ''Becoming Free, Remaining Free: Manumission and Enslavement in New Orleans, 1846–1862''. Louisiana State Univ Press, 2003. ISBN 0-8071-2862-7.
* Salerno,  Beth A. ''Sister Societies: Women's Antislavery Organizations in Antebellum America''. Northern Illinois Univ Press, 2005. ISBN 0-87580-338-5.
* Speicher, Anna M. ''The Religious World of Antislavery Women: Spirituality in the Lives of Five Abolitionist Lecturers''. Syracuse Univ Press, 2000. ISBN 0-8156-2850-1.
* Stauffer, John.  ''The Black Hearts of Men: Radical Abolitionists and the Transformation of Race.'' Harvard Univ Press, 2002. ISBN 0-674-00645-3.
*{{cite web|url=http://www.monticello.org/site/plantation-and-slavery/thomas-jefferson-and-slavery|title=Thomas Jefferson and Slavery |ref=TJFslavery |publisher=Monticello.org |date=2010-12-02 |accessdate=2012-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Ferling|2000|p=135}}
* Vorenberg, Michael.  ''Final Freedom: The Civil War, the Abolition of Slavery, and the Thirteenth Amendment''. Cambridge Univ Press, 2001. ISBN 0-521-65267-7.
* Zilversmit, Arthur. ''The First Emancipation: The Abolition of Slavery in the North''. University of Chicago Press, 1967. ISBN 0-226-98332-3.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
&lt;references/&gt;
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Collier's Poster|Abolitionists}}
* [http://www.memoirestbarth/EN/ Mémoire St Barth | History of St Barthélemy (archives &amp; history of slavery, slave trade and their abolition)], Comité de Liaison et d'Application des Sources Historiques.
*[http://www.parliament.uk/slavetrade Largest Surviving Anti Slave Trade Petition from Manchester, UK 1806]
*[http://www.footnote.com/viewer.php?image=4346710 Original Document Proposing Abolition of Slavery 13th Amendment]
*[http://www.tls.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,25340-2597455,00.html &quot;John Brown's body and blood&quot;] by Ari Kelman: a review in the [http://tls.timesonline.co.uk/ TLS], 14 February 2007.
* [http://www.ltscotland.org.uk/abolition/ ''Scotland and the Abolition of the Slave Trade – schools resource'']
* [http://www.brown.edu/Research/Slavery_Justice/documents/SlaveryAndJustice.pdf Report of the Brown University Steering Committee on Slavery and Justice]
* [http://www.yale.edu/glc/events/cbss/Miers.pdf Twentieth Century Solutions of the Abolition of Slavery]
* ''[http://www.altonweb.com/history/lovejoy/ Elijah Parish Lovejoy: A Martyr on the Altar of American Liberty]''
* [http://www.brycchancarey.com/abolition/ Brycchan Carey's pages listing British abolitionists]
*[http://www.blackhistory4schools.com/slavetrade/ Teaching resources about Slavery and Abolition on blackhistory4schools.com]
* [http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/pathways/blackhistory/rights/abolition.htm The National Archives (UK): The Abolition of the Slave Trade]
*[http://www.sheffield.gov.uk/libraries/archives-and-local-studies/publications/slavery-and-abolition Towards Liberty: Slavery, the Slave Trade, Abolition and Emancipation] Produced by Sheffield City Council's Libraries and Archives (UK)]
* [http://www.realnews-online.com/rn0112.htm The slavery debate]
* [http://www.kshs.org/places/johnbrown/index.htm John Brown Museum]
*[http://americanabolitionist.liberalarts.iupui.edu/ American Abolitionism]
*[http://anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/huk-history.htm History of the British abolitionist movement by Right Honourable Lord Archer of Sandwell]
*[http://www.gresham.ac.uk/event.asp?PageId=45&amp;EventId=476 &quot;Slavery – The emancipation movement in Britain&quot;], lecture by James Walvin at [[Gresham College]], 5 March 2007 (available for video and audio download)
*[http://teacher.scholastic.com/activities/bhistory/underground_railroad/index.htmThe Underground Railroad: Escape from Slavery | Scholatic.com]
*[http://www.virtualmuseum.ca/blackhistory/ &quot;Black Canada and the Journey to Freedom&quot;]
*[http://www.history.ac.uk/1807commemorated 1807 Commemorated]
*[http://www.theactiongroup.org/index.htm The Action Group]
*[http://www.state.gov/g/tip/rls/tiprpt/2008/ US Department of State Trafficking in Persons Report 2008]
*[http://www.freedomcenter.org/ National Underground Railroad Freedom Center] in Cincinnati, Ohio
*[http://theliberatorfiles.com The Liberator Files], Horace Seldon's collection and summary of research of William Lloyd Garrison's ''[[The Liberator (anti-slavery newspaper)|The Liberator]]'' original copies at the Boston Public Library,  Boston, Massachusetts.
*[http://research.udmercy.edu/find/special_collections/digital/baa/ University of Detroit Mercy Black Abolitionist Archive], a collection of over 800 speeches by antebellum blacks and approximately 1,000 editorials from the period.
*[http://histclo.com/Act/work/slave/ast/abol.html Abolitionist movement]

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{Black British topics}}

[[Category:Abolitionism| ]]
[[Category:Political movements]]
[[Category:African diaspora history]]
[[Category:Slavery]]

[[ar:التحرير من العبودية]]
[[az:Abolisionizm]]
[[bg:Аболиционизъм]]
[[ca:Abolicionisme]]
[[cs:Abolicionismus]]
[[da:Abolitionist]]
[[de:Abolitionismus]]
[[et:Abolitsionism]]
[[es:Abolicionismo]]
[[eo:Aboliciismo]]
[[fa:مخالفت با بردگی]]
[[fr:Abolitionnisme]]
[[gl:Abolicionismo]]
[[ko:노예 제도 폐지 운동]]
[[hy:Աբոլիցիոնիզմ]]
[[hr:Abolicionisti]]
[[id:Abolisionisme]]
[[it:Abolizionismo]]
[[he:התנועה לביטול העבדות]]
[[kk:Аболиционизм]]
[[sw:Ukomeshaji wa Biashara ya Watumwa]]
[[ht:Abolisyon esklavaj]]
[[lv:Abolicionisms (kustība par verdzības atcelšanu)]]
[[lt:Abolicionizmas]]
[[hu:Abolicionizmus]]
[[mk:Аболиционизам]]
[[ml:അടിമത്തനിരോധന പ്രസ്ഥാനം]]
[[ms:Abolisionisme]]
[[nl:Abolitionisme (slavernij)]]
[[ja:奴隷制度廃止運動]]
[[no:Abolisjonisme]]
[[nn:Abolisjonisme]]
[[pl:Abolicjonizm]]
[[pt:Abolicionismo]]
[[ro:Aboliționism]]
[[ru:Аболиционизм]]
[[simple:Abolitionism]]
[[sk:Abolicionizmus]]
[[sl:Abolicionizem]]
[[sr:Аболиционизам]]
[[sh:Abolicionizam]]
[[fi:Abolitionismi]]
[[sv:Abolitionism]]
[[ta:அடிமை ஒழிப்புக் கோட்பாடு]]
[[th:การเลิกทาส]]
[[tk:Abolisionizm]]
[[uk:Аболіціонізм]]
[[zh:廢奴主義]]</text>
      <sha1>mzgn1jtem0yyr49s8p6qborwfa6p8us</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
