<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Adam and Eve</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11473533</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522442037</id>
      <parentid>522439084</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T06:32:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Editor2020</username>
        <id>6046894</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/Hturt eht s'ti|Hturt eht s'ti]] ([[User talk:Hturt eht s'ti|talk]]) to last version by Xanchester</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26363">{{Other uses}}
[[File:Lucas Cranach the Elder-Adam and Eve 1533.jpg|thumb|right|&quot;Adam and Eve&quot; by [[Lucas Cranach the Elder]]]]

'''[[Adam]] and [[Eve]]''', according to the [[creation myth]] of the [[Abrahamic religions]], were the [[First man or woman|first man and woman]]. 

In [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]], God fashions Adam from dust and places him in the [[Garden of Eden]], where he is to have dominion over the plants and animals. Eve is later created to be his companion. God places [[Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil|a tree]] in the garden which he prohibits Adam and Eve from eating from. However, a serpent tricks them into eating from it, and they are subsequently expelled from the garden for disobeying God, who visits upon them and their progeny numerous hardships as punishment. 

Interpretations and beliefs regarding Adam and Eve and the story revolving around them vary across religions and sects. 

==Narrative==
[[Image:Adam et Eve chaire cathedrale Bruxelles.jpg|thumb|left|Adam and Eve expelled from Eden, detail of a Baroque pulpit]]
{{See also|Genesis creation narrative}}

===Genesis 2===
[[Yahweh]] fashions a man (Heb. ''adam'', &quot;man&quot; or &quot;mankind&quot;) from the dust (Heb. ''adamah'') and blows the [[Pneuma|breath of life]] into his nostrils, then plants a garden (the [[Garden of Eden]]) and causes to grow in the middle of the garden the [[Tree of the knowledge of good and evil]] and the [[Tree of life (biblical)|Tree of life]]. God sets the man in the garden &quot;to work it and watch over it,&quot; permitting him to eat from all the trees in the garden except the Tree of Knowledge, &quot;for on the day you eat of it you shall surely die.&quot;

God brings the animals to the man for him to name. None of them are found to be a suitable companion for the man, so God causes the man to sleep and creates a woman from a part of his body (English-language tradition describes the part as a rib, but the Hebrew word ''tsela'', from which this interpretation is derived, has multiple meanings; see the Textual Note, below). Describing her as &quot;bone of my bones, flesh of my flesh,&quot; the man calls his new help-mate &quot;woman&quot; (Heb. ''ishshah''), &quot;for this one was taken from a man&quot; (Heb. ''ish''). This sundering, a making of two from one, predicates reunification in marriage, in which two will be made one: &quot;On account of this a man leaves his father and his mother and clings to his woman.&quot; The chapter ends by establishing the state of primeval innocence, noting that the man and woman were naked and not ashamed, and so provides the departure point for the subsequent narrative in which wisdom is gained through disobedience at severe cost.

===Genesis 3===
[[File:Michelangelo Sündenfall.jpg|400px|right|The fall depicted in the [[Sistine Chapel]] by [[Michelangelo]]]]
{{See also|Fall of man}}
The [[serpent (Bible)|serpent]], &quot;more wise than any beast of the field,&quot; tempts the woman to eat &quot;of the fruit of the tree in the midst of the garden&quot;, telling her that &quot;Ye shall not surely die&quot; and it will make her to be as god, knowing good and evil. After some thought about &quot;the tree to be desired to make wise&quot;, the woman took of the fruit and did eat. She then gives the fruit to the man, who eats also, &quot;and the eyes of the two of them were opened.&quot; Aware now of their nakedness, they make coverings of fig leaves and hide from the sight of God.

God asked them what they have done, and man and woman defer responsibility. The man blames the woman for giving him the fruit, but implies a sentiment that God is also at fault for making the woman in the first place (&quot;The woman Thou gavest to be with me, she gave me the fruit of the tree, and I ate&quot;), while the woman blames the serpent for seducing her to disobedience (&quot;The serpent beguiled me and I ate&quot;). God curses the serpent &quot;above all animals,&quot; causing it to lose its legs and to become an eternal enemy of the human race. God then passes judgment for the disobedience of the man and woman, condemning the man to sustain life through hard labor and the woman to create new life through painful childbirth.

[[File:Orvieto062.jpg|thumb|left|&quot;Expulsion from Paradise&quot;, marble bas-relief by [[Lorenzo Maitani]] on the [[Orvieto Cathedral]], Italy]]
Adam named his wife Eve (Heb. ''hawwah'') &quot;because she was the [[Hebat|mother of all living]]&quot; and Adam receives his name &quot;the man&quot;, changing from &quot;eth-ha'adham&quot;, before the fall to &quot;ha'Adham&quot;(with article/command), to Adam after the fall(disobedience). Eve/woman is also established as subordinate to Adam/man. Then Yahweh banished &quot;the man&quot; from the Garden and posted two [[cherub]]s, with flaming swords, at the entrance to the Garden of Eden in order to block the way to the Tree of life, &quot;lest he put out his hand ... and eat, and live forever.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Genesis|3:22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genesis 4 and 5===
Genesis four tells of the birth of [[Cain]] and [[Abel]], Adam and Eve's first children, while Genesis 5 gives Adam's genealogy past that. Adam and Eve are listed as having three children, Cain, Abel and [[Seth]], then &quot;other sons and daughters&quot;.{{bibleref2c|Gen|5:4|NIV}}

==Textual notes==
*&quot;...a living being&quot; ({{bibleverse||Genesis|2:7|HE}}) - God breathes into the man's nostrils and he becomes ''[[Nephesh|nefesh hayya]].'' The earlier translation of this phrase as &quot;living soul&quot; is now recognised as incorrect: &quot;nefesh&quot; signifies something like the English word &quot;being&quot;, in the sense of a corporeal body capable of life; the concept of a &quot;soul&quot; in our sense did not exist in Hebrew thought until around the 2nd century BC, when the idea of a bodily resurrection gained popularity.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Harry Orlinski's Notes to the NJPS Torah&lt;/ref&gt;

*&quot;...tree of knowledge of good and evil...&quot; ({{bibleverse||Genesis|2:9|HE}}) - The tree imparts knowledge of ''tov wa-ra'', &quot;good and bad&quot;. The traditional translation is &quot;good and evil&quot;, but ''tov wa-ra'' is a fixed expression denoting &quot;everything,&quot; rather than a moral concept.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

*&quot;...you shall surely die&quot; ({{bibleverse||Genesis|2:16-17|HE}}) - Adam is told that if he eats of the forbidden tree the consequence will be ''moth tamuth,'' &quot;die a death&quot;, indicating not merely death but emphatically so. As Adam does not in fact die immediately on eating the fruit, some exegetes have argued that it means &quot;you shall die eventually,&quot; so that Adam and Eve would have had immortality in the Garden, but lost it by eating the forbidden fruit. However, the grammar does not support this reading, nor does the narrative: Adam and Eve are expelled from the Garden lest they eat of the second tree, the tree of life, and gain immortality. ({{bibleverse||Genesis|3:22|HE}})&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Another explanation is that Adam will undergo &quot;a spiritual death&quot;. The 2nd century Book of [[Jubilees]] (4:29–31) explained that &quot;one day&quot; is equivalent to a thousand years and thus Adam died within that same &quot;day&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://wesley.nnu.edu/biblical_studies/noncanon/ot/pseudo/jubilee.htm Online translation of Jubilees&lt;/ref&gt; the Greek [[Septuagint]], on the other hand, has &quot;day&quot; translated into the Greek word for a twenty-four hour period.

*&quot;...a rib...&quot; ({{bibleverse||Genesis|2:21–24|HE}}) - Hebrew ''tsala`'' or ''tsela'' (from strongs concordance #6760 Prime Root) can mean curve, limp, adversity and side. &quot;tsal'ah&quot; (fem of #6760) being side, chamber, rib, or beam. The traditional reading of &quot;rib&quot; has been questioned recently by feminist theologians who suggest it should instead be rendered as &quot;side&quot;, supporting the idea that woman is man's equal and not his subordinate.&lt;ref&gt;For the reading &quot;side&quot; in place of traditional &quot;rib&quot;, see Mignon R. Jacobs, ''Gender, Power, and Persuasion: The Genesis Narratives and Contemporary Perspectives'', Baker Academic, 2007, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; Such a reading shares elements in common with [[Aristophanes]]' story of the origin of love and the separation of the sexes in [[Plato's Symposium]].&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Robert Alter, ''The Art of Biblical Narrative'', Basic Books, 1983, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; Exegesis focused on literal biological interpretation has suggested that the &quot;rib&quot; was in fact the [[baculum]], a bone present in several orders of mammals. This suggestion is based upon observations that men and women have the same number of ribs, and that the human body does not contain a baculum,&lt;ref name=&quot;Gilbert-2001&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal  | last1 = Gilbert | first1 = Scott F. | last2 = Zevit | first2 = Ziony | title = Congenital human baculum deficiency: the generative bone of Genesis 2:21–23. | journal = Am J Med Genet | volume = 101 | issue = 3 | pages = 284–5 | month = Jul | year = 2001 | doi =  10.1002/ajmg.1387| PMID = 11424148 }}&lt;/ref&gt; although some primates have very small or vestigial baculi, and other orders of mammals also lack the bone entirely.

==Abrahamic traditions==
===Jewish traditions===
Even in ancient times, the presence of two distinct accounts of the creation of the first man (or couple) was noted. The first account says &quot;male and female [God] created them&quot;, implying simultaneous creation, whereas the second account states that God created Eve subsequent to the creation of Adam. The [[Midrash Rabbah]] - Genesis VIII:1 reconciled the two by stating that Genesis 1, &quot;male and female He created them&quot;, indicates that God originally created Adam as a [[hermaphrodite]], bodily and spiritually both male and female, before creating the separate beings of Adam and Eve. Other rabbis suggested that Eve and the woman of the first account were two separate individuals, the first being identified as [[Lilith]], a figure elsewhere described as a night demon.

Genesis does not tell how long Adam and Eve were in the Garden of Eden, but the 2nd century BC [[Book of Jubilees]] provides more specific information. It states (ch3 v17) that the serpent convinced Eve to eat the fruit on the 17th day of the 2nd month in the 8th year after Adam's creation. It also states that they were removed from the Garden on the new moon of the fourth month of that year (ch3 v33).

According to traditional Jewish belief Adam and Eve are buried in the [[Cave of Machpelah]], in [[Hebron]].

===Christianity===
[[File:Temptation Adam Eva.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Adam]], [[Eve]], and the (female) [[serpent (Bible)|Serpent]] (often identified as [[Lilith]]) at the entrance to [[Notre Dame de Paris|Notre Dame Cathedral]] in Paris. Medieval Christian art often depicted the Edenic Serpent as a woman, thus both emphasizing the Serpent's seductiveness as well as its relationship to Eve. Several early [[Church Fathers]], including [[Clement of Alexandria]] and [[Eusebius of Caesarea]], interpreted the Hebrew &quot;Heva&quot; as not only the name of Eve, but in its aspirated form as &quot;female serpent.&quot;]]

The story of Adam and Eve forms the basis for the Christian doctrine of [[original sin]]: &quot;Sin came into the world through one man and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because all men sinned,&quot; said [[Paul of Tarsus]] in his [[Epistle to the Romans]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hti.umich.edu/cgi/k/kjv/kjv-idx?type=citation&amp;book=Romans&amp;chapno=5&amp;startverse=12&amp;endverse= Romans 5:12]&lt;/ref&gt; although Chapter 3 of Genesis does not use the word &quot;sin&quot; and Genesis 3:24 makes clear that the couple are expelled &quot;lest he put forth his hand and take also of the tree of life, and eat, and live for ever&quot;. [[St Augustine of Hippo]] (354–430), working with a Latin translation of the epistle, understood Paul to have said that Adam's sin was hereditary: &quot;Death passed upon (i.e. spread to) all men because of Adam, [in whom] all sinned&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;For a brief overview see [[Robin Lane Fox]], &quot;The Unauthorized Version&quot;, 1991, pp. 15–27 passim&lt;/ref&gt; Original sin, the concept that man is born in a condition of sinfulness and must await redemption, thus became a cornerstone of Western Christian theological tradition; the belief is not shared by Judaism or the Orthodox churches,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stmaryorthodoxchurch.org/orthodoxy/articles/2004-hughes-sin.php Orthodox beliefs]&lt;/ref&gt; and has been dropped by some post-Reformation churches such as the Congregationalists and [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]. 

Because Eve tempted Adam to eat of the fatal fruit, some early [[Fathers of the Church]] held her and all subsequent women to be the first sinners, and especially responsible for the Fall. &quot;You are the devil's gateway,&quot; [[Tertullian]] told his female listeners in the early 2nd century, and went on to explain that they were responsible for the death of Christ: &quot;On account of your desert (i.e. punishment for sin), that is, death, even the Son of God had to die.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tertullian.org/anf/anf04/anf04-06.htm Tertullian, &quot;De Cultu Feminarum&quot;, Book I Chapter I, ''Modesty in Apparel Becoming to Women in Memory of the Introduction of Sin Through a Woman'' (in &quot;The Ante-Nicene Fathers&quot;)]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1486 the [[Dominican Order|Dominicans]] Kramer and Sprengler used similar tracts in ''[[Malleus Maleficarum]]'' (&quot;Hammer of Witches&quot;) to justify the persecution of &quot;witches&quot;. 

Over the centuries, a system of uniquely Christian beliefs has developed from the Adam and Eve story. [[Baptism]] has become understood as a washing away of the stain of hereditary sin in many churches, although its original symbolism was apparently rebirth. Additionally, the serpent that tempted Eve was interpreted to have been [[Satan]], or that Satan was using a serpent as a [[spokesperson|mouthpiece]], although there is no mention of this identification in the Torah and it is not held in Judaism.

===Gnostic and Manichaean traditions===
{{See also|Gnostics|Manichaeans}}
[[Gnostic Christianity]] discussed Adam and Eve in two known surviving texts, namely the &quot;[[Apocalypse of Adam]]&quot; found in the [[Nag Hammadi]] documents and the &quot;[[Testament of Adam]]&quot;. The creation of Adam as [[Protanthropos]], the original man, is the focal concept of these writings.

The [[Manichean]] conception of Adam and Eve is [[pessimistic]]. According to them, the copulative action of two demons, Adam and Eve were born to further imprison the soul in the material universe.  

:&quot;Mani said, 'Then Jesus came and spoke to the one who had been born, who was Adam, and … made him fear Eve, showing him how to suppress (desire) for her, and he forbade him to approach her… Then that (male) [[Archon]] came back to his daughter, who was Eve, and lustfully had intercourse with her. He engendered with her a son, deformed in shape and possessing a red complexion, and his name was Cain, the Red Man.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religiousstudies.uncc.edu/jcreeves/manichaean_version_of_genesis_2-4.htm Manichaean beliefs]&lt;/ref&gt;

Another Gnostic tradition held that Adam and Eve were created to help defeat Satan. The serpent, instead of being identified with Satan, is seen as a hero by the [[Ophites]]. Still other Gnostics believed that Satan's fall, however, came after the creation of humanity. As in Islamic tradition, this story says that Satan refused to bow to Adam due to pride. Satan said that Adam was inferior to him as he was made of fire, whereas Adam was made of clay. This refusal led to the [[fall of Satan]] recorded in works such as the [[Book of Enoch]].

===Islamic tradition===
[[Image:Islamic Adam &amp; Eve.jpg|thumb|Painting from Manafi al-Hayawan (The Useful Animals), depicting Adam and Eve, From [[Maragheh]] in [[Iran]], 1294–99]] 

{{main|Biblical narratives and the Quran#Adam and Eve (آدم Adam and حواء Hawwaa)}}
{{also|Forbidden fruit#Islamic tradition}}

In [[Islam]], [[Adam#Islamic view|{{transl|ar|DIN|Adam}}]] (''Adem''; [[Arabic language|Arabic]]: '''آدم''' ), whose role is being the father of [[Human|mankind]], is looked upon by [[Muslim]]s with reverence. {{transl|ar|DIN|Eve}} (''{{Unicode|Hawwāʾ}}''; [[Arabic language|Arabic]]: ''' حواء ''') is the &quot;mother of mankind&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Historical Dictionary of Prophets in Islam and Judaism'', Wheeler, ''Adam and Eve''&lt;/ref&gt; Eve is referred to in the {{transl|ar|DIN|Quran}} as Adam's spouse (Qur'an surah 4: Surah An-Nisa' 1).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite quran|4|1|s=ns}}:''O! mankind ! Be dutiful to your Lord, Who created you from a single person (Adam), and from him (Adam) He created his wife [[Eve#Eve_in_Islam|Hawwa (Eve)]], and from them both He created many men and women;''&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Tafsir Al-Qummi|Al-Qummi's]] [[tafsir]] of [[Garden of Eden|Eden]], such place was not entirely earthly. According to the {{transl|ar|DIN|Quran}}, both [[Biblical narratives and the Quran#Adam and Eve (آدم Adam and حواء Hawwaa)|{{transl|ar|DIN|Adam}} and {{transl|ar|DIN|Eve}}]] ate the [[Forbidden fruit#Islamic tradition|forbidden fruit]] in a ''Heavenly'' Eden (''See also'' [[Jannah]]). As a result, they were both sent down to Earth as [[Names of God in the Qur'an|God]]'s representatives. Each person was sent to a mountain peak; Adam on [[Al-Safa and Al-Marwah|Al-Safa]], and Eve on [[Al-Safa and Al-Marwah|Al-Marwa]]. In this Islamic tradition, Adam wept 40 days until he repented, after which God sent down the [[Black Stone]], teaching him the [[hajj]]. According to a prophetic [[hadith]], Adam and Eve reunited in the plain of 'Arafat, near [[Mecca]].{{citation needed|date=August 2012}} They had two sons together, [[Cain and Abel in Islam|Qabil and Habil]].

The concept of ''original sin'' does not exist in [[Islam]] because [[Adam and Eve#Islamic tradition|Adam and Eve]] were forgiven by [[Names of God in the Qur'an|God]]. When God orders the angels to bow to Adam, [[Devil (Islam)|''{{transl|ar|DIN|ʾIblīs}}'']] questioned, &quot;why should I bow to man, I am made of pure fire and he is made of soil&quot;. The [[Liberal movements within Islam]] have viewed God's commanding the angels to bow before Adam as an exaltation of humanity, and as a means of supporting [[human rights]], others view it as an act of showing Adam that the biggest enemy of humans on earth will be their ego.&lt;ref&gt;[[Javed Ahmed Ghamidi]], Mizan, Lahore: Dar al-Ishraq, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

==Art and literature==
Adam and Eve were used by [[early Renaissance art]]ists as a theme to represent female and male nudes. Later, the nudity was objected to by more modest elements, and fig leaves were added to the older pictures and sculptures, covering their [[genital]]s. The choice of the [[fig tree|fig]] was a result of Mediterranean traditions identifying the unnamed Tree of knowledge as a fig tree, and since fig leaves were actually mentioned in Genesis as being used to cover Adam and Eve's nudity.

Treating the concept of Adam and Eve as the historical truth introduces some logical dilemmas. One such dilemma is whether they should be depicted with [[navel]]s (the [[Omphalos (theology)|Omphalos theory]]). Since they were created fully grown, and did not develop in a uterus, they would not have been connected to an umbilical cord as were all born humans. Paintings without navels looked unnatural and some artists obscure that area of their bodies, sometimes by depicting them covering up that area of their body with their hand or some other intervening object.

[[John Milton]]'s ''[[Paradise Lost]]'' is a famous 17th-century [[epic poem]] written in [[blank verse]] which explores the story of Adam and Eve in great detail.

American painter [[Thomas Cole]] painted ''The Garden of Eden'' (1828), with lavish detail of the first couple living amid waterfalls, vivid plants, and attractive deer.&lt;ref&gt;Exhibit at the [[Amon Carter Museum]] in [[Fort Worth, Texas|Fort Worth]], [[Texas]]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mark Twain]] wrote humorous and satirical diaries of Adam and Eve.

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:Abreha-wa-atsbeha-church02.jpg|Adam and Eve depicted in a mural in Abreha wa Atsbeha Church, Ethiopia. 
Image:Tizian_091.jpg|''Adam and Eve'' by [[Titian]].
Image:Adam_and_Eve_by_Lucas_Cranach_(I).jpg|''Adam and Eve'' by [[Lucas Cranach the Elder]].
Image:Albrecht Dürer 002.jpg|[[Adam and Eve (Dürer)|Adam and Eve]]'' by [[Albrecht Dürer]].
File:M. v. Heemskerck-Musée des Bx-Arts Strasbourg-Gédéon-Adam Eve-Ausschnitt 2.jpg|Adam and Eve by [[Maarten van Heemskerck]] ([[Musée des Beaux-Arts de Strasbourg]]). Note the emphasis of the gender difference by the use of different skin colours.
File:Adam and Eve from a copy of the Falnama.jpg|Adam and Eve from a copy of the ''Falnama'' (''Book of Omens'') ascribed to Ja´far al-Sadiq, ca. 1550, [[Safavid dynasty]], Iran. 
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Science vs. literalism==
Some Christians believe all humans did not descend from a historical Adam and Eve, saying that the field of [[human genetics]] indicates this concept is impossible. Genetic evidence indicates humans descended from a group of at least 10,000 people due to the amount of [[human genetic variation]]. If all humans descended from two individuals several thousand years ago, it would require an impossibly high mutation rate to account for the observed variation. This has caused some [[Biblical literalist|literalists]] to move away from a [[literal interpretation]] and belief in [[creation myth]], while others continue to believe in what they see as a fundamental doctrine of the Christian faith.&lt;ref name=&quot;Question&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Evangelicals Question The Existence Of Adam And Eve |author=Barbara Bradley Hagerty |newspaper=[[All Things Considered]] |date=August 9, 2011 |url=http://www.npr.org/2011/08/09/138957812/evangelicals-question-the-existence-of-adam-and-eve}} [http://www.npr.org/templates/transcript/transcript.php?storyId=138957812 Transcript]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
[[File:B Escorial 18.jpg|thumb|Adam &amp; Eve, illuminated manuscript circa 950, [[Escorial Beatus]]]]
*[[Adam and Eve (LDS Church)]]
*[[Ask and Embla]]
*[[Balbira &amp; Kalmana]]
*[[Biblical narratives and the Qur'an]]
*[[Christian naturism]]
*[[Conflict of Adam and Eve with Satan]]
*[[Creation myth]]
*[[Generations of Adam]]
*[[Mitochondrial Eve]]
*[[Pre-Adamite]]
*[[Y-chromosomal Adam]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}
&lt;!-- No longer referenced:  #{{note|JE}}[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=527&amp;letter=E&amp;search=Eve Jewish Encyclopedia]--&gt;
&lt;!-- No longer referenced:  #{{note|ecceveritas2}} [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11312a.htm Original Sin]--&gt;
&lt;!-- No longer referenced:  #{{note|sumer1}} [[Enki]] (from En = Lord, Ki = Earth) and [[Ninhursag]] (from Nin = Lady, (K)hur = Mountain, Sag = Sacred)--&gt;
&lt;!-- No longer referenced:  #{{note|sumer2}} (called by the Sumerians, the Anunaki from Anu = Heaven, Na = And, Ki = Earth)--&gt;
&lt;!-- No longer referenced:  #{{note|sumer3}} See Dr Gwendolyn Leick -- Assyriology PhD (Univ. Graz - Austria), lecturer at Richmond College and Univ. Glamorgan --&gt;
&lt;!-- No longer referenced:  #{{note|sumer4}} [http://www.meta-religion.com/World_Religions/Ancient_religions/Mesopotamia/Epic_of_gilgamesh/biblical_parallels_in_sumerian_l.htm Biblical parallels in Sumerian mythology]--&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
: {{cite book
|last= Alter
|first=Robert 
|authorlink = Robert Alter
|title=The Five Books of Moses 
|year=2004
|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company 
|isbn=0-393-33393-0
|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=ZcMhkJ8a708C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=he+Five+Books+of+Moses&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=s7bATsiWFYjHmQX_6LXKBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=he%20Five%20Books%20of%20Moses&amp;f=false
|ref=harv
}}
* Mahmoud Ayoub, ''The Qur'an and its Interpreters'', SUNY: Albany, 1984.
* R. Patai, ''The Jewish Alchemists'', Princeton University Press, 1994.
* Fazale Rana and [[Hugh Ross (creationist)|Ross, Hugh]], ''Who Was Adam: A Creation Model Approach to the Origin of Man'', 2005, ISBN 1-57683-577-4
* ''Sibylline Oracles'', III; 24–6. This Greek acrostic also appears in 2 Enoch 30:13.
* David Rohl, ''Legend: The Genesis of Civilisation'', 1998
* Bryan Sykes, ''The Seven Daughters of Eve''
* C.S. Lewis, ''The Lion, The Witch and the Wardrobe&quot;
* Adam Mackie, The Importance of being Adam - Alexo 1997 (only 2000 copies published)
* [[Robin Lane Fox]], ''The Unauthorized Version'', Penguin, 1991 (no ISBN available)
* Philip C. Almond, 'Adam and Eve in Seventeenth-Century Thought (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999, 2008)
* [[Brian O. Murdoch]], ''The Apocryphal Adam and Eve in Medieval Europe: Vernacular Translations and Adaptations of the Vita Adae et Evae''. Oxford University Press, 2009. ISBN 978-0-19-956414-9.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary}}
{{commons}}
*[http://www.Bible-Genealogy.com Bible Genealogy]
*[http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/world/human.html First Human Beings] ([[Library of Congress]])
*[http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/~humm/Topics/Lilith/alphabet.html The Story of Lilith in ''The Alphabet of Ben Sira'']
*[http://www.islamfrominside.com/Pages/Podcasts/Fall%20of%20Adam%20podcast.html Islamic view of the fall of Adam (audio)]
*[http://www.adam-and-eve.org/ 98 classical images of Adam and Eve]
*[http://wesley.nnu.edu/biblical_studies/noncanon/ot/pseudo/jubilee.htm The Book of Jubilees]
*[http://www.paradoxplace.com/Church_Stuff/Christian_Themes/Adam_&amp;_Eve.htm Adam and Eve in Medieval Reliefs, Capitals, Frescoes, Roof Bosses and Mosaics]
*[http://www.aug.edu/augusta/iconography/adamEve.html &quot;Adam and Eve&quot; in ''Christian Iconography'']
*[http://www.fairytalechannel.org/2007_12_06_archive.html Translation of Grimm's Fairy Tale No. 180, Eve's Unequal Children, a German Fairy Tale about Adam and Eve]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Adam And Eve}}
[[Category:Adam and Eve| ]]
[[Category:Biblical phrases]]
[[Category:Creation myths]]
[[Category:Hebrew Bible topics]]
[[Category:Abrahamic mythology]]
[[Category:Monomyths]]
[[Category:Duos]]
[[Category:Book of Genesis]]

[[af:Adam en Eva]]
[[cs:Adam a Eva]]
[[de:Adam und Eva]]
[[es:Adán y Eva]]
[[eo:Adamo kaj Evo]]
[[fa:آدم و حوا]]
[[fy:Adam en Eva]]
[[gl:Adán e Eva]]
[[ko:아담과 하와]]
[[hr:Adam i Eva]]
[[id:Adam dan Hawa]]
[[is:Adam og Eva]]
[[he:אדם וחוה]]
[[lt:Adomas ir Ieva]]
[[hu:Ádám és Éva]]
[[mk:Адам и Ева]]
[[ml:ആദാമും ഹവ്വായും]]
[[nl:Adam en Eva]]
[[ja:アダムとイヴ]]
[[no:Adam og Eva]]
[[nn:Adam og Eva]]
[[pl:Adam i Ewa]]
[[pt:Adão e Eva]]
[[ro:Adam și Eva]]
[[ru:Адам и Ева]]
[[sq:Adami dhe Eva]]
[[sk:Adam a Eva]]
[[sr:Адам и Ева]]
[[sv:Adam och Eva]]
[[tl:Adan at Eba]]
[[tr:Âdem ile Havva]]
[[ur:حوّا]]
[[vi:Adam và Eva]]
[[wa:Adan ey Eve]]
[[war:Adan ngan Eba]]</text>
      <sha1>layte5ha3ujwtxk358isxhr1iqa2olo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
