<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Animism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1423</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522076989</id>
      <parentid>521410207</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T22:28:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.211.47.120</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>deleted now-redundant sentence. thank you to whoever is helping me improve this article.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25065">'''Animism''' (from [[Latin]] ''anima'' &quot;[[Soul (spirit)|soul]], [[life]]&quot;)&lt;ref name = &quot;ooviqc&quot;&gt;Segal, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; is the religious belief that [[nature|natural phenomena]], including animals, plants, and sometimes even inanimate [[physical body|natural objects]], possess a [[spirituality|spiritual]] [[essence]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Animism: Respecting the Living World|last=Harvey|first=Graham|page=9|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=2006|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=q2np2LCDmIMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source}}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, animism is used in the [[anthropology of religion]] as a term for the religion of [[indigenous people|indigenous tribal peoples]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Ritual and Belief: Readings in the Anthropology of Religion|first=David|last=Hicks|publisher=[[Rowman Altamira]]|edition=3|year=2010|page=359|quote=Tylor's notion of animism—for him the first religion—included the assumption that early ''Homo sapiens'' had invested animals and plants with souls....}}&lt;/ref&gt; especially prior to the development of [[civilization]] and [[organized religion]]s. Although each tribe is unique in its specific mythologies and rituals, the term animism is often used to describe the most common thread of native tribespeoples' spiritual or supernatural perspectives. Some non-tribal people also consider themselves animists (such as author [[Daniel Quinn]]) and, of course, not all peoples who describe themselves as a tribe would describe themselves as animist. Even most animist native tribal people do not have a word in their languages that corresponds to &quot;animism&quot;; it is a purely anthropological term rather than one self-designated by tribespeople themselves.

Animism encompasses the beliefs that there is no separation between the [[Spirituality|spiritual]] and physical (or [[material]]) world, and [[Soul (spirit)|soul]]s or [[spirit]]s exist, not only in [[human]]s, but also in all other [[animal]]s, [[plant]]s, [[rock (geology)|rock]]s, [[geographic]] features such as [[mountain]]s or [[river]]s, or other entities of the natural environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;bob&quot;&gt;&quot;The concept that humans possess souls and that souls have life apart from human bodies before and after death is central to animism, along with the ideas that animals, plants, and celestial bodies have spirits&quot; (Wenner).&lt;/ref&gt; Animism may further attribute souls to abstract concepts such as words, [[true name]]s, or metaphors in [[mythology]]. Examples of Animism can be found in forms of [[Shinto]], [[Serer religion|Serer]], [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]], [[Jainism]], [[Pantheism]], [[Paganism]], and [[Neopaganism]].

Throughout European history, philosophers such as [[Aristotle]] and [[Thomas Aquinas]], among others, contemplated the possibility that souls exist in animals, plants, and people; however, the currently accepted definition of animism was only developed in the 19th century by [[Sir Edward Tylor]], who created it as &quot;one of [[anthropology]]'s earliest concepts, if not the first&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bird-David-67&quot;&gt;Bird-David, 1999: p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the anthropologist [[Tim Ingold]], animism shares similarities to [[totemism]] but differs in its focus on individual spirit beings which help to perpetuate life, whereas totemism more typically holds that there is a primary source, such as the land itself or the ancestors, who provide the basis to life. Certain indigenous religious groups such as the [[Australian Aborigines]] are more typically totemic, whereas others like the [[Inuit]] are more typically animistic in their worldview.&lt;ref&gt;Ingold, Tim. (2000). &quot;Totemism, Animism and the Depiction of Animals&quot; in ''The Perception of the Environment: Essays on Livelihood, Dwelling and Skill''. London: Routledge, pp. 112-113.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
[[File:Edward Burnett Tylor.jpg|right|thumb|[[Edward Burnett Tylor|Sir Edward Tylor]] was responsible for forming the definition of animism currently accepted in anthropology.]]
The term ''Animism'' appears to have been first developed as ''animismus'' by German scientist [[Georg Ernst Stahl]], circa 1720, to refer to the &quot;doctrine that animal life is produced by an immaterial soul.&quot; The actual English language form of ''animism'', however, can only be attested to 1819.&lt;ref&gt;Harper, Douglas. (2001). http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=animism&lt;/ref&gt; The term was taken and redefined by the [[anthropology|anthropologist]] [[Edward Burnett Tylor|Sir Edward Tylor]] in his 1871 book ''Primitive Culture'', in which he defined it as &quot;the general doctrine of souls and other spiritual beings in general.&quot;

According to Tylor, animism often includes &quot;an idea of pervading life and will in nature&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Tylor, E.B. [http://books.google.com/books?ei=ZHSWTJCnEcL38AbutNWMDA&amp;ct=result&amp;output=text&amp;id=AucLAAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=primitive+culture&amp;q=doctine+of+souls#v=snippet&amp;q=%22the%20doctrine%20of%20souls%20and%20other%20spiritual%20beings%20in%20general%22&amp;f=false Primitive Culture]. London: John Murray, 1871. p. 260.&lt;/ref&gt; i.e., a belief that natural objects other than humans have souls. As a self-described &quot;confirmed scientific rationalist&quot;, Tylor believed that this view was &quot;childish&quot; and typical of &quot;cognitive underdevelopment&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Bird-David, 1999: pp. 67-68&lt;/ref&gt; and that it was therefore common in &quot;primitive&quot; peoples such as those living in [[hunter gatherer]] societies.

Tylor's definition of animism has since largely been followed by anthropologists, such as [[Émile Durkheim]], [[Claude Lévi-Strauss]] and [[Tim Ingold]]. However, some anthropologists, such as Nurit Bird-David, have criticised the Tylorian concept of animism, believing it to be outdated.&lt;ref&gt;Bird-David, N. (1999) “Animism” revisited: On Personhood, Environment and Relational Epistemology, Current Anthropology, 40s:S67-S91&lt;/ref&gt;

==Motivation==
{{See|anthropology of religion|psychology of religion}}
Animism in the widest sense, i.e., thinking of objects as animate, and treating them as if they were animate, is near-universal.
[[Jean Piaget]] applied the term in [[child psychology]] in reference to an implicit understanding of the world in a child's mind which assumes that all events are the product of intention or consciousness. Piaget explains this with a cognitive inability to distinguish the external world from one's internal world. [[Developmental psychology]] has since established that the distinction of animate vs. inanimate things is an abstraction acquired by [[learning]].{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}

The justification for attributing life to objects was stated by [[David Hume]] in his ''[[The Natural History of Religion|Natural History of Religion]]'' (Section III): &quot;There is a universal tendency among mankind to conceive all beings like themselves, and to transfer to every object those qualities with which they are familiarly acquainted, and of which they are intimately conscious.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=zp97KA1prvUC&amp;pg=PR19&amp;lpg=PR19&amp;dq=%22There+is+an+universal+tendency+among+mankind+to+conceive+all+beings+like+themselves,+and+to+transfer+to+every+object+those+qualities+with+which+they+are+familiarly+acquainted,+and+of+which+they+are+intimately+conscious%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=HOqvUgffdx&amp;sig=uFjv8xMCN1l3BpJCsDFD5Bzylcg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=result#PPR20,M1 The Natural History of Religion. D. Hume. p. xix].&lt;/ref&gt;

Lists of phenomena, from the contemplation of which &quot;the savage&quot; was led to believe in animism, have been given by Sir [[E. B. Tylor]], [[Herbert Spencer]], [[Andrew Lang]], and others; a controversy arose between the former as to the priority of their respective lists.{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}} Among these phenomena are [[Altered state of consciousness|trance states]], [[dream]]s, and [[hallucination]]s.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}

==Animism and religion==
Animism is a belief held in many religions around the world, and is not, as some have purported, a type of religion in itself.{{citation needed|date=November 2011|Author Daniel Quinn, a prominent promoter of animism, considers animism a religion}} It is a belief, such as [[shamanism]], [[polytheism]] or [[monotheism]], that is found in several religions.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}  In modern usage, the term is sometimes used improperly as a catch-all classification of &quot;other world religions&quot; alongside major organized religions.

===Tylor's theory===
Some theories have been put forward that the anthropocentric belief in animism among early humans was the basis for the later evolution of religions. In one such theory, put forward by Sir E. B. Tylor, early humans initially, through mere observation, recognized what might be called a soul, life-force, spirit, breath or animus within themselves; that which was present in the body in life and absent in death. These early humans equated this soul with figures which would appear in dreams and visions. These early human cultures later interpreted these spirits to be present in animals, the living plant world, and even in natural objects in a form of animism. Eventually, these early humans grew to believe that the spirits were invested and interested in human life, and performed rituals to propitiate them. These rituals and beliefs eventually evolved over time into the vast array of “developed” religions. According to Tylor, the more scientifically advanced the society, the less that society believed in Animism; however, any remnant ideologies of souls or spirits, to Tylor, represented “survivals” of the original animism of early humanity.

===World view===
In many animistic world views found in [[hunter-gatherer]] cultures, the human being is often regarded as on a roughly equal footing with other animals, plants, and natural forces.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez-Armesto, p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, it is morally imperative to treat these agents with respect. In this world view, humans are considered a part of nature, rather than superior to, or separate from it.

===Death===
It is not surprising to find that many peoples respect and even worship animals (see ''[[totem]]'' or ''[[animal worship]]''), often regarding them as relatives. It is clear that widespread respect was paid to animals as the abode of dead ancestors, and much of the [[cult]]s to dangerous animals is traceable to this principle; though there is no need to attribute an animistic origin to it.&lt;ref name=&quot;brit&quot;&gt;&quot;Animism&quot;, ''Encyclopædia Britannica''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mythology===
A large part of mythology is based upon a belief in souls and spirits — that is, upon animism in its more general sense. [[Urarina]] myths that portray plants, inanimate objects, and non-human animals as personal beings are examples of animism in its more restrictive sense.&lt;ref&gt;Dean, Bartholomew 2009 ''Urarina Society, Cosmology, and History in Peruvian Amazonia'', Gainesville: University Press of Florida ISBN 978-0-8130-3378-5 [http://www.upf.com/book.asp?id=DEANXS07].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Distinction from Pantheism===
Animism is not the same as [[Pantheism]], although the two are sometimes confused. Some faiths and religions are even both pantheistic and animistic. One of the main differences is that while animists believe everything to be spiritual in nature, they do not necessarily see the spiritual nature of everything in existence as being united (monism), the way pantheists do. As a result, animism puts more emphasis on the uniqueness of each individual soul. In Pantheism, everything shares the same spiritual essence, rather than having distinct spirits and/or souls.&lt;ref&gt;Paul A. Harrison ''Elements of Pantheism'' 2004, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carl McColman ''When Someone You Love Is Wiccan: A Guide to Witchcraft and Paganism for Concerned Friends, Nervous parents and Curious Co-Workers'' 2002, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt;

==Science and animism==

Some early scientists such as [[Georg Ernst Stahl]] (1659-1734) and [[Francisque Bouillier]] (1813–1899) had supported a form of animism which life and mind, the directive principle in evolution and growth, holding that all cannot be traced back to chemical and mechanical processes, but that there is a directive force which guides energy without altering its amount. An entirely different class of ideas, also termed animistic, is the belief in the world soul [[anima mundi]], held by philosophers such as [[Friedrich Wilhelm Joseph von Schelling|Schelling]] and others.&lt;ref&gt;Émile Durkheim, Neil Gross, Robert Alun Jones ''Durkheim's Philosophy Lectures'' 2004, p. 286&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:Hn7YQ8UPFwoJ:www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2557375/pdf/medhistsuppl00043-0019.pdf+Albert+Lemoine+animism&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=uk&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESiW8_7Sb7QUbkPcqdX7ZnlxAV3D5HkS8D3uX4EJpkJSDB1Wi8LCSxG8C9IS1eBDejYUrJ3C226pdb4jZKlEs46sYdKpI--8gBwRAxBN_VVOe88GmB42SBV1BA2dw-tbQqslr_wQ&amp;sig=AHIEtbRPgkzyOihfB1RUPkY2tY2cFbdDtg&amp;safe=active Animism, Vitalism, And The Medical University Of Montpellier]&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 20th century [[William McDougall (psychologist)|William McDougall]] defended a form of animism in his book ''Body and Mind: A History and Defence of Animism'' (1911).

The physicist [[Nick Herbert (physicist)|Nick Herbert]] has argued for &quot;quantum animism&quot; in which mind permeates the world at every level.&lt;ref&gt;Graham Harvey ''Animism: respecting the living world'' 2005, p. 190&lt;/ref&gt; [[Werner Krieglstein]] wrote regarding his quantum animism:

{{blockquote|Herbert's quantum animism differs from traditional animism in that it avoids assuming a dualistic model of mind and matter. Traditional dualism assumes that some kind of spirit inhabitats a body and makes it move, a ghost in the machine. Herbert's quantum animism presents the idea that every natural system has an inner life, a conscious center, from which it directs and observes its action.&lt;ref&gt;Werner J. Krieglstein ''Compassion: a new philosophy of the other'' 2002, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt;}}
The terms animism and [[panpsychism]] have become related in recent years. The biologist [[Rupert Sheldrake]] has supported a form of animism which [[David Skrbina]] calls &quot;a unique form of panpsychism&quot;. Sheldrake in his book ''The Rebirth of Nature: New Science and the Revival of Animism'' (1991) has claimed that Morphic fields &quot;animate organisms at all levels of complexity, from galaxies to giraffes, and from ants to atoms&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;David Skrbina ''Panpsychism in the West'' 2005, p. 200&lt;/ref&gt; In his book ''The Science Delusion'' (2012) he wrote that the philosophy of the organism ([[organicism]]) has updated the ideas of animism as it treats all of nature as alive.&lt;ref&gt;Rupert Sheldrake ''The Science Delusion'' Coronet Books, 2012 ISBN 1-4447-2792-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples of animist traditions==
{{See|Folk religion|Shamanism}}

*[[Shinto]], the traditional religion of [[Japan]], is highly animistic. In Shinto, spirits of nature, or [[kami]], are believed to exist everywhere, from the major (such as the goddess of the sun), which can be considered [[polytheism|polytheistic]], to the minor, which are more likely to be seen as a form of animism.
*Many traditional beliefs in [[the Philippines]] still practised to an extent today are animist and [[spiritism|spiritist]] in origin in that there are rituals aimed at pacifying malevolent spirits or are [[apotropaic magic|apotropaic]] in nature. An extension of this is the [[sacred cockfight]], ”a popular form of fertility worship among almost all Southeast Asians”&lt;ref&gt;Nat in My Classroom! Using Spirit Worship to Infuse Southeast Asia into the K-16 Classroom - Marc Jason Gilbert, Department of History and Sociology, North Georgia College and State University, Dahlonega, Georgia [http://tuninst.net/Myanmar/Nat-worship/nat-in-classroom/nat-in-classroom.htm] &lt;/ref&gt; considered by some in the [[Judeo-Christian]] ethic as a form of [[Baal|’fertility worship’]] or [[Baalim]]. These beliefs have persisted despite (and have been influenced by) the introduction of [[Islam in the Philippines|Islam]] and [[Roman Catholicism in the Philippines|Catholicism]] to the islands in the 13th and 16th centuries, respectively.
*There are some [[Hinduism|Hindu]] groups which may be considered animist. The coastal [[Karnataka]] has a different tradition of praying to spirits (see also [[Folk Hinduism]]). Likewise a popular Hindu ritual form of worship of North Malabar in Kerala, India is the Tabuh Rah blood offering to [[Theyyam]] gods, despite being forbidden in the Vedic philosophy of sattvic Hinduism, Jainism and Buddhism, Theyyam deities are propitiated through the cock sacrifice where the religious cockfight is a religious exercise of offering blood to the [[Theyyam]] gods.
*Many traditional Native American religions are fundamentally animistic. See, for example, the Lakota Sioux prayer [[Mitakuye Oyasin]]. The [[Iroquois|Haudenausaunee]] Thanksgiving Address, which can take an hour to recite, directs thanks towards every being - plant, animal and other.
*The [[New Age]] movement commonly purports animism in the form of the existence of nature spirits.&lt;ref&gt;Wouter J. Hanegraaff ''New Age religion and Western culture'' 1998, p. 199&lt;/ref&gt;
*Modern [[Neopaganism|Neopagans]], especially Eco-Pagans, sometimes like to describe themselves as animists, meaning that they respect the diverse community of living beings and spirits with whom humans share the world/cosmos.&lt;ref&gt;Murphy Pizza, James R. Lewis ''Handbook of Contemporary Paganism'', 2008, pp. 408-409&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[New tribalist]] [[United States|American]] author [[Daniel Quinn]] identifies himself as an animist and defines animism not as a religious belief but a religion itself,&lt;ref&gt;Ishmael.org: Q and A #75. (1997). http://www.ishmael.org/Interaction/QandA/Detail.CFM?Record=75|&lt;/ref&gt; though with no holy scripture, organized institutions, or established dogma.&lt;ref&gt;Ishmael.org: Q and A #400. http://www.ishmael.org/Interaction/QandA/Detail.CFM?Record=400&lt;/ref&gt; He considers animism the first worldwide religion, common among all tribal societies before the advent of the [[Neolithic Revolution|Agriculture Revolution]] and its resulting [[globalization|globalized culture]], along with the proliferation of this culture's organized, &quot;salvationist&quot; religions.&lt;ref&gt;Quinn, Daniel. ''The Story of B.'' New York: Bantam Books. 1997&lt;/ref&gt; His first discussions of animism appear in his two 1994 books: his novel, ''[[The Story of B]]'', and his [[autobiography]], ''[[Providence: The Story of a Fifty-Year Vision Quest]]''.
*The [[Aluk]] religion in the [[Toraja]] society and the people of Tana Toraja, embrace religious rituals such as the funeral ceremony where a [[sacred cockfight]], known as bulangan londong or saung, is an integral part of the ceremony and considered sacred because of the spilling of blood on the earth in spiritual appeasement.&lt;ref&gt;incito tour - PT. INCITO PRIMA - Re: Funeral Ceremony in Toraja - Authorized by: Department of Law and Human Rights of Republic of Indonesia [http://www.incitoprima.com/details.php?catid=5&amp;aid=5]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
;General
{{Portal|Philosophy|Mythology|Religion|Spirituality}}
{{div col|cols=3}}
* [[Anecdotal cognitivism]]
* [[Animatism]]
* [[Celtic polytheism]]
* [[Fairies]]
* [[Folk religion]]
* [[Hyang|Hyang (Indonesian mythology)]]
* [[Hylozoism]]
* [[Mana]]
* [[Nature worship]]
* [[Panpsychism]]
* [[Ryukyuan Shinto]]
* [[Shamanism in Siberia]]
* [[Shamanism]]
* [[Shinto]]
* [[Tree worship]]
* [[Wildlife totemization]]
* [[Witchcraft]]
{{div col end}}

;Related
{{div col|cols=3}}
* [[Monotheism]]
* [[Pantheism]]
* [[Polytheism]]
* [[Tengriism]]
* [[Theism]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
* Adler, Margot. ''Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-Worshippers, and Other Pagans in America''. Penguin, 2006.
* &quot;Animism&quot;. ''The Columbia Encyclopedia''. 6th ed. 2001-07. [http://www.bartleby.com/65/an/animism.html ''Bartleby.com''. Bartleby.com Inc. (10 July 2008)].
* Armstrong, Karen. ''A History of God: The 4,000-Year Quest of Judaism, Christianity and Islam''. Ballantine Books, 1994.
* Bird-David, Nurit. 1991. &quot;Animism Revisited: Personhood, environment, and relational epistemology&quot;, ''Current Anthropology'' 40, pp.&amp;nbsp;67–91. Reprinted in Graham Harvey (ed.) 2002. [http://books.google.com/books?id=PaLyYm7kFsAC&amp;pg=PR1&amp;dq=Readings+in+Indigenous+Religions&amp;sig=JbLAs8L73O17IWhb22kasr5bCek#PPR1,M1 ''Readings in Indigenous Religions''] (London and New York: Continuum) pp.&amp;nbsp;72–105.
* Cunningham, Scott. ''Living Wicca: A Further Guide for the Solitary Practitioner''. Llewellyn, 2002. -- {{verify credibility|date=January 2011}}
* Dean, Bartholomew 2009 ''Urarina Society, Cosmology, and History in Peruvian Amazonia'', Gainesville: University Press of Florida ISBN 978-0-8130-3378-5, [http://www.upf.com/book.asp?id=DEANXS07].
* Fernandez-Armesto, Felipe. ''Ideas that Changed the World''. Dorling Kindersley, 2003.
* {{cite book|author=Higginbotham, Joyce|title=Paganism: An Introduction to Earth- Centered Religions'|publisher=Llewellyn|year=2002|isbn=|url=}}{{verify credibility|date=January 2011}}
* 'Lamphun's Little-Known Animal Shrines' (Animist traditions in Thailand) in: Forbes, Andrew, and Henley, David, ''Ancient Chiang Mai'' Volume 1. Chiang Mai ,Cognoscenti Books, 2012.
* {{cite book|author=Segal, Robert|title=Myth: A Very Short Introduction|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2004|isbn=|url=}}
* Wenner, Sara. &quot;Basic Beliefs of Animism&quot;. [http://www.mnsu.edu/emuseum/cultural/religion/animism/beliefs.html ''Emuseum''. 2001. Minnesota State University, (10 July 2008)].

==Further reading==
* Hallowell, A. Irving. &quot;Ojibwa ontology, behavior, and world view&quot; in Stanley Diamond (ed.) 1960. ''Culture in History'' (New York: Columbia University Press). Reprinted in Graham Harvey (ed.) 2002. ''Readings in Indigenous Religions'' (London and New York: Continuum) pp.&amp;nbsp;17–49.
* Harvey, Graham. 2005. ''Animism: Respecting the Living World'' (London: Hurst and co.; New York: Columbia University Press; Adelaide: Wakefield Press).
* Ingold, Tim: 'Rethinking the animate, re-animating thought'. Ethnos, 71(1) / 2006: pp.&amp;nbsp;9–20.
* [[Wilhelm Maximilian Wundt|Wundt, W.]] (1906). ''Mythus und Religion'', Teil II. Leipzig 1906 (''Völkerpsychologie'', volume II).
* Quinn, Daniel. ''The Story of B''
* Käser, Lothar: ''Animismus. Eine Einführung in die begrifflichen Grundlagen des Welt- und Menschenbildes traditionaler (ethnischer) Gesellschaften für Entwicklungshelfer und kirchliche Mitarbeiter in Übersee''. Liebenzeller Mission, Bad Liebenzell 2004, ISBN 3-921113-61-X.
** mit dem verkürzten Untertitel ''Einführung in seine begrifflichen Grundlagen'' auch bei: Erlanger Verlag für Mission und Okumene, Neuendettelsau 2004, ISBN 3-87214-609-2.
* Badenberg, Robert: &quot;How about 'Animism'? An Inquiry beyond Label and Legacy&quot;. In: ''Mission als Kommunikation. Festschrift für Ursula Wiesemann zu ihrem 75.Geburtstag'', edited by Klaus W. Müller. VTR, Nürnberg 2007; ISBN 978-3-937965-75-8 and VKW, Bonn 2007; ISBN 978-3-938116-33-3.

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.roboethics.org/icra2007/contributions/KITANO%20Animism%20Rinri%20Modernization%20the%20Base%20of%20Japanese%20Robo.pdf Animism, Rinri, Modernization; the Base of Japanese Robotics]
* [http://www.snopes.com/religion/soulweight.asp Urban Legends Reference Pages: Weight of the Soul][http://www.ishmael.org/Interaction/QandA/list.cfm]
*[http://www.animist-network.de/index_e.html Animist Network]

{{Philosophy topics}}
{{philosophy of religion}}
{{witchcraft}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Animism| ]]
[[Category:Anthropology of religion]]
[[Category:Animals in religion]]
[[Category:Polytheism]]
[[Category:Inuit culture]]

[[ar:إحيائية]]
[[az:Animizm]]
[[be:Анімізм]]
[[bg:Анимизъм]]
[[bs:Animizam]]
[[ca:Animisme]]
[[cs:Animismus]]
[[da:Animisme]]
[[de:Animismus]]
[[et:Animism]]
[[el:Ανιμισμός]]
[[es:Animismo]]
[[eo:Animismo]]
[[eu:Animismo]]
[[fa:روح‌باوری]]
[[fr:Animisme]]
[[fy:Animisme]]
[[fur:Animisim]]
[[gl:Animismo]]
[[ko:애니미즘]]
[[hi:सर्वात्मवाद]]
[[hr:Animizam]]
[[io:Animismo]]
[[id:Animisme]]
[[ia:Animismo]]
[[is:Andatrú]]
[[it:Animismo]]
[[he:אנימיזם]]
[[jv:Animisme]]
[[ka:ანიმიზმი]]
[[kk:Анимизм]]
[[ky:Анимизм]]
[[lv:Animisms]]
[[lt:Animizmas]]
[[li:Animisme]]
[[hu:Animizmus]]
[[mk:Анимизам]]
[[ml:അനിമിസം]]
[[ms:Animisme]]
[[nl:Animisme (religie)]]
[[ja:アニミズム]]
[[pih:Animism]]
[[no:Animisme]]
[[nn:Animisme]]
[[oc:Animisme]]
[[ps:ساباوري]]
[[nds:Animismus]]
[[pl:Animizm]]
[[pt:Animismo]]
[[ro:Animism]]
[[ru:Анимизм]]
[[sq:Animizëmi]]
[[scn:Animismu]]
[[simple:Animism]]
[[sk:Animizmus]]
[[sl:Animizem]]
[[sr:Анимизам]]
[[sh:Animizam]]
[[fi:Animismi]]
[[sv:Animism]]
[[tl:Animismo]]
[[tt:Анимизм]]
[[tr:Animizm]]
[[uk:Анімізм]]
[[ur:روحیت]]
[[vi:Thuyết vật linh]]
[[bat-smg:Anėmėzmos]]
[[zh:泛靈論]]</text>
      <sha1>bnv83mmummmua0kwvs8epltr134x2f5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
