<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anthropomorphism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19009060</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520806228</id>
      <parentid>520062575</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T21:35:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ekedolphin</username>
        <id>154833</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added pareidolia to &quot;see also&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36116">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
[[File:The North Wind and the Sun - Wind - Project Gutenberg etext 19994.jpg|thumb|In this illustration by [[Milo Winter]] of the [[Aesop]]'s fable, ''[[The North Wind and the Sun]]'', an anthropomorphic North Wind tries to strip a traveler of his cloak.]]
'''Anthropomorphism''' or '''personification''' is any attribution of [[human]] characteristics (or characteristics assumed to belong only to humans) [[zoomorphism|to other animals]], non-living things, phenomena, material states, objects or abstract concepts, such as organizations, governments, [[spirits]] or [[deities]]. The term was coined in the mid 1700s.&lt;ref name=&quot; 'anthropomorphism' coining date&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Harper|first=Douglas|title=Online Etymology Dictionary|url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=anthropomorphism&amp;searchmode=none|publisher=Douglas Harper}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot; 'personification' coining date 2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Merriam-Webster|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/anthropomorphism|publisher=Merriam-Webster}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Examples include animals and plants and forces of [[nature]] such as [[winds]], rain or the [[sun]] depicted as creatures with human motivations, and/or the abilities to [[reason]] and converse. The term derives from the combination of the [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|ἄνθρωπος}} (''{{lang|grc-Latn|ánthrōpos}}''), &quot;human&quot; and {{lang|grc|μορφή}} (''{{lang|grc-Latn|morphē}}''), &quot;shape&quot; or &quot;form&quot;.

As a [[Literary technique|literary device]], anthropomorphism is strongly associated with art and storytelling where it has [[ancient]] roots. Most cultures possess a long-standing [[fable]] tradition with anthropomorphised animals as characters that can stand as commonly recognised [[Type (metaphysics)|types]] of human behavior. In contrast to this, conventional Western science, as well as such religious doctrines as the Christian [[Great Chain of Being#The Great Chain of Being|Great Chain of Being]] propound the opposite, [[anthropocentric]] belief that animals, plants and non-living things, unlike humans, lack [[spirituality|spiritual]] and mental attributes, immortal [[soul]]s, and anything other than relatively limited awareness.

==Pre-history==
[[File:Lion man photo.jpg|thumb|&quot;[[Lion man of the Hohlenstein Stadel]]&quot;]]

From the beginnings of human [[behavioural modernity]] in the [[Upper Paleolithic]], about 40,000 years ago, examples of [[zoomorphic]] (animal-shaped) works of art occur that may represent the earliest evidence we have of anthropomorphism. One of the oldest known is an [[ivory]] sculpture, the [[Lion man of the Hohlenstein Stadel]], Germany, a human-shaped [[figurine]] with a lion's head, determined to be about 32,000 years old.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lion-human1&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
  | title =  Lionheaded Figurine
  | url = http://www.showcaves.com/english/explain/Archaeology/Loewenfrau.html
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lion-human2&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
  | last = Dalton
  | title =  Lion Man Oldest Statue
  | publisher = VNN World
  | date = 1 January 2004
  | url = http://www.vnn.org/world/WD0401/WD01-8500.html
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

It is not possible to say what exactly these [[prehistoric]] artworks represent. A more recent example is [[The Sorcerer (cave art)|The Sorcerer]], an enigmatic cave painting from the [[Trois Frères|Trois-Frères Cave]], Ariège, France: the figure's significance is unknown, but it is usually interpreted as some kind of great spirit or master of the animals. In either case there is an element of anthropomorphism.

This anthropomorphic art has been linked by [[archaeologist]] [[Steven Mithen]] with the emergence of more systematic hunting practices in the Upper Palaeolithic (Mithen 1998). He proposes that these are the product of a change in the [[Modularity of mind|architecture of the human mind]], an increasing [[Steven Mithen#Cognitive fluidity|fluidity]] between the [[natural history]] and social [[Multiple intelligences|intelligences]], where anthropomorphism allowed hunters to [[Empathy|empathetically]] identify with hunted animals and better predict their movements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Thinking About Thinking |first= Howard|last= Gardner|authorlink= Howard Gardner|newspaper= New York Review of Books|date= 9 October 1997|url= http://cogweb.ucla.edu/Abstracts/Gardner_on_Mithen.html|quote= I find most convincing Mithen's claim that human intelligence lies in the capacity to make connections: through using metaphors|accessdate =8 May 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100329103807/http://cogweb.ucla.edu/Abstracts/Gardner_on_Mithen.html| archivedate= 29 March 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In religion and mythology==
{{Main|Anthropotheism}}
In religion and [[mythology]], anthropomorphism refers to the perception of a divine being or beings in human form, or the recognition of human qualities in these beings. 

Ancient mythologies frequently represented the divine as a god or gods with human forms and qualities. These gods resemble human beings not only in appearance and personality; they exhibited many human behaviors which were used to explain natural phenomena, creation, and historical events. The gods fell in love, married, had children, fought battles, wielded weapons, and rode horses and chariots. They feasted on special foods, and sometimes required sacrifices of food, beverage, and sacred objects to be made by human beings. Some anthropomorphic gods represented specific human concepts, such as love, war, fertility, beauty, or the seasons. Anthropomorphic gods exhibited human qualities such as beauty, wisdom, and power, and sometimes human weaknesses such as greed, [[hatred]], [[jealousy]], and uncontrollable anger. Greek gods such as [[Zeus]] and [[Apollo (god)|Apollo]] were often depicted in human form exhibiting both commendable and despicable human traits.

Anthropomorphism in this case is referred to as [[anthropotheism]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=anthropotheism |url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/Anthropotheism |year=2008 |work=Ologies &amp; -Isms |publisher=The Gale Group, Inc. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

From the perspective of adherents to religions in which humans were created in the form of the divine, the [[phenomenon]] may be considered [[theomorphism]], or the giving of divine qualities to humans.

[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church) teaches that both [[God in Mormonism|God the Father]] and [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]] have physical, resurrected bodies, the image of which humans were created in.

Anthropomorphism has cropped up as a [[Anthropomorphism (heresy)|Christian heresy]], particularly prominently with the [[Audians]] in third century Syria, but also in fourth century Egypt and tenth Century Italy.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy|title=Anthropomorphism, Anthropomorphites|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01558c.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This often was based on a literal interpretation of [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] 1:27: &quot;So God created man in His own image, in the image of God created He him; male and female created He them&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;1728Cyclopedia&quot;&gt;{{1728}} [http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/HistSciTech/HistSciTech-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=HistSciTech000900240147&amp;isize=L Anthropomorphite].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism===
Some religions, scholars, and philosophers found objections to anthropomorphic deities. The Greek philosopher [[Xenophanes]] (570–480 BCE) said that &quot;the greatest god&quot; resembles man &quot;neither in form nor in mind&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Xenophanes god quote&quot;&gt;[[Clement of Alexandria]], ''Miscellanies'' V xiv 109.1–3&lt;/ref&gt; Anthropomorphism of God is rejected by Judaism and Islam, which both believe that God is beyond human limits of comprehension. Judaism's rejection grew during the [[Hasmonean]] period (circa 300 BCE) due to Greek philosophy becoming incorporated in Jewish belief.{{ref|Book of [[Philo]], gravestones found at
[[Bet Shearim]] cemetery with inscriptions about a body-less deity, [[Josephus]]}} Judaism's rejection grew further following the [[Muslim Renaissance]] (10 century AD) later codified in 13 principles of Jewish faith authored by [[Maimonides]] in the 12th century.&lt;ref&gt;Rambam, Book of Science, Fundamentals of Torah, chapter 1, Section 8: &quot;It is stated in the Torah and books of the prophets that God has no body, as stated 'Since G-d your God is the god (literally ''gods'') in the heavens above and in the earth below&quot; and a body cannot be in both places. And it was said 'Since you have not seen any image' and it was said 'To who would you compare me, and I would be equal to them?' and if he was a body, he would be like the other bodies.&quot; Although many sources show that even after this, imagining God in a personified way was not always considered a sin to many. (Rabbi Abraham Ben David's response to Maimonides)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hindus]] do not reject the [[concept]] of God in the [[abstraction|abstract]] unmanifested but note problems; [[Lord Krishna]] said in the [[Bhagavad Gita]], Chapter 12, Verse 5, that it is much more difficult to focus on God as the unmanifested than God with form, i.e., using anthropomorphic icons ([[murtis]]), due to human beings' need to perceive via the senses.&lt;ref&gt;Hinduism: Beliefs and Practices, by Jeanne Fowler, pgs. 42–43, at [http://books.google.com/books?id=RmGKHu20hA0C&amp;pg=PA42&amp;dq=Hinduism+murtis+shiva+linga&amp;lr=&amp;cd=18#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Books.Google.com] and Flipside of Hindu symbolism, by M. K. V. Narayan at pgs. 84–85 at [http://books.google.com/books?id=ewRfp4qpvt4C&amp;pg=PA84&amp;dq=Hinduism+murtis+saligrama&amp;lr=&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Books.Google.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book ''Faces in the Clouds: A New Theory of Religion'', [[Stewart Elliot Guthrie|Stewart Guthrie]] theorizes that all religions are anthropomorphisms that originate due to the brain's tendency to detect the presence or vestiges of other humans in natural phenomena.&lt;ref name=&quot;SE Guthrie religion ref&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Guthrie
|first=Stewart Elliot
|authorlink=Stewart Elliott Guthrie
|title= Faces in the Clouds: A New Theory of Religion
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=dZNAQh6TuwIC&amp;dq=Faces+in+the+Clouds:+A+New+Theory+of+Religion&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA7,M1
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|page=7
|year=1995
|isbn=0-19-509891-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In literature==

===Fables===
[[File:Syrischer Maler von 1354 001.jpg|thumb|From the [[Panchatantra]]: Rabbit fools Elephant by showing him the reflection of the moon.]]
Anthropomorphism, sometimes referred to as [[personification]], is a well established [[literary device]] from ancient times. It extends back to before [[Aesop's Fables]]&lt;ref&gt;''The Hawk and the Nightingale'', recorded by [[Hesiod]] in his ''[[Works and Days]]'' is regarded by some as the earliest fable attributable to a literary work. See for instance {{cite encyclopedia | encyclopedia = Britanica | pages = 410 | year = 1910 }}: &quot;The poem also contains the earliest known fable in Greek literature&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; in 6th century BC Greece and the collections of linked [[fables]] from India, the ''[[Jataka tales|Jataka Tales]]'' and ''[[Panchatantra]]'', which employ anthropomorphised animals to illustrate principles of life. Many of the [[stereotypes of animals]] that are recognised today, such as the wiley fox and the proud lion, can be found in these collections. Aesop's anthropomorphisms were so familiar by the 1st century AD that they coloured the thinking of at least one philosopher:

{{quote|And there is another charm about him, namely, that he puts animals in a pleasing light and makes them interesting to mankind. For after being brought up from childhood with these stories, and after being as it were nursed by them from babyhood, we acquire certain opinions of the several animals and think of some of them as royal animals, of others as silly, of others as witty, and others as innocent.|[[Apollonius of Tyana]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Apollonius&quot; /&gt;}}

Apollonius noted that the fable was created to teach [[wisdom]] through fictions that are meant to be taken as fictions, contrasting them favourably with the poets' stories of the [[Greek mythology|gods]] that are sometimes taken literally. Aesop, &quot;by announcing a story which everyone knows not to be true, told the truth by the very fact that he did not claim to be relating real events&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apollonius&quot;&gt;Philostratus, Flavius (c.210 AD). ''[http://www.livius.org/ap-ark/apollonius/life/va_5_11.html The Life of Apollonius]'', 5.14. Translated by F.C. Conybeare. the Loeb Classical Library (1912)&lt;/ref&gt; The same consciousness of the fable as fiction is to be found in other examples across the world, one example being a traditional Ashanti way of beginning tales of the anthropomorphic [[trickster]]-spider [[Anansi]]: &quot;We do not really mean, we do not really mean that what we are about to say is true. A story, a story; let it come, let it go.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
  | author = Kwesi Yankah
  | title = The Akan Trickster Cycle: Myth or Folktale?
  | publisher = Trinidad University of the West Indes
  | year = 1983
  | url = https://scholarworks.iu.edu/dspace/bitstream/2022/125/1/Akan_Yankah.pdf
  | format = PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fairy tales===
Anthropomorphic motifs have been common in [[fairy tales]] from the earliest ancient examples set in a mythological context to the great collections of the [[Grimm's Fairy Tales|Brothers Grimm]] and [[Charles Perrault|Perrault]]. The ''[[Tale of Two Brothers]]'' (Egypt, 13th century BC) features several talking cows and in ''[[Cupid and Psyche]]'' (Rome, 2nd century AD) [[Zephyrus]], the west wind, carries [[Cupid and Psyche|Psyche]] away. Later an [[ant]] feels sorry for her and helps her in her quest.

===Modern literature===
[[File:Down the Rabbit Hole.png|thumb|[[John Tenniel|John Tenniel']]s depiction of [[White Rabbit|this anthropomorphic rabbit]] was featured in the first chapter of [[Lewis Carroll]]'s ''[[Alice's Adventures in Wonderland]]'']]
Building on the popularity of fables and fairy tales, specifically [[Children's literature|''children's'' literature]] began to emerge in the 19th century with works such as ''[[Alice's Adventures in Wonderland]]'' (1865) by [[Lewis Carroll]], ''[[The Adventures of Pinocchio]]'' (1883) by [[Carlo Collodi]] and ''[[The Jungle Book]]'' (1894) by [[Rudyard Kipling]], all employing anthropomorphic elements. This continued in the 20th century with many of the most popular titles having anthropomorphic characters,&lt;ref name=&quot;top50&quot;&gt;
{{cite news |title= The top 50 children's books|newspaper= The Telegraph|date= 22 Feb 2008|url= http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1579457/The-top-50-childrens-books.html}} and
{{cite news |title= Narnia triumphs over Harry Potter|author= Sophie Borland|newspaper= The Telegraph|date= 22 Feb 2008|url= http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1579456/Narnia-triumphs-over-Harry-Potter.html}}
&lt;/ref&gt; examples being ''The Tales of [[Beatrix Potter]]''  ([[1901 in literature|1901 onwards]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Beatrix Potter|url=http://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/prints_books/features/potter/index.html|publisher=Victoria and Albert Museum}}: &quot;Beatrix Potter is still one of the world's best-selling and best-loved children's authors. Potter wrote and illustrated a total of 28 books, including the 23 Tales, the 'little books' that have been translated into more than 35 languages and sold over 100 million copies.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Wind in the Willows]]'' (1908) by [[Kenneth Grahame]], ''[[The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe]]'' by [[C. S. Lewis]] and ''[[Winnie-the-Pooh (book)|Winnie-the-Pooh]]'' (1926) by [[A. A. Milne]].
In many of these stories the animals can be seen as representing facets of human personality and character.&lt;ref name = &quot;gamble&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Gamble|first=Nikki|last2= Yates|first2= Sally|title=Exploring Children's Literature|year=2008|publisher=Sage Publications Ltd;|isbn=978-1-4129-3013-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; As [[John Rowe Townsend]] remarks, discussing ''The Jungle Book'' in which the boy [[Mowgli]] must rely on his new friends the bear [[Baloo]] and the black panther [[Bagheera]], &quot;The world of the jungle is in fact both itself and our world as well&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;gamble&quot; /&gt; Another notable work is [[George Orwell]]'s ''[[Animal Farm]]''.

The [[Juvenile fantasy|fantasy]] genre developed from mythological, fairy tale and [[Romance (heroic literature)|Romance]] motifs&lt;ref&gt;John Grant and John Clute, ''[[The Encyclopedia of Fantasy]]'', p 621, ISBN 0-312-19869-8&lt;/ref&gt; and characters, sometimes with anthropomorphic animals. The [[Best selling books|best-selling]] examples of the genre are ''[[The Hobbit]]''&lt;ref&gt;100 million copies sold: [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/dorset/7302101.stm BBC]: Tolkien's memorabilia go on sale. 18 March 2008&lt;/ref&gt;'' (1937) and [[The Lord of the Rings]]''&lt;ref&gt;150 million sold, a 2007 estimate of copies of the full story sold, whether published as one volume, three, or some other configuration.[http://www.thestar.com/entertainment/article/203389 The Toronto Star] 16 April 2007&lt;/ref&gt; (1954–1955), both by [[J. R. R. Tolkien]], books peopled with talking creatures such as ravens, spiders and the dragon [[Smaug]] and a multitude of anthropomorphic [[goblins]] and [[elves]]. John D. Rateliff calls this the &quot;[[Doctor Dolittle]] Theme&quot; in his book ''The History of the Hobbit''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title= The History of the Hobbit: Return to Bag-end|last= Rateliff|first= John D.|year= 2007|publisher= [[HarperCollins]]|location= London|isbn= 978-0-00-723555-1|page=654}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Tolkien saw this anthropomorphism as closely linked to the emergence of human language and [[myth]]: &quot;...The first men to talk of 'trees and stars' saw things very differently. To them, the world was alive with mythological beings... To them the whole of creation was &quot;myth-woven and elf-patterned&quot;.'&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = The Inklings: C. S. Lewis, J. R. R. Tolkien, Charles Williams and Their Friends | last = Carpenter | first = Humphrey | year = 1979 | isbn = 0-395-27628-4 | page = 43 | publisher = Houghton Mifflin | location = Boston }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 20th century, the children's [[picture book]] market expanded massively.&lt;ref&gt;It is estimated that the UK market for children's books was worth GBP 672m in 2004. [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0EIN/is_2005_Nov_9/ai_n15786010/ The Value of the Children's Picture Book Market...]&lt;/ref&gt; Perhaps a majority of picture books have some kind of anthropomorphism,&lt;ref name=&quot;top50&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Why we're all animal lovers|author= Ben Myers|newspaper= The Guardian|date= 10 June 2008|url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/booksblog/2008/jun/10/whywereallanimallovers
}}&lt;/ref&gt; with popular examples being ''[[The Very Hungry Caterpillar]]'' (1969) by [[Eric Carle]] and ''[[The Gruffalo]]'' (1999) by [[Julia Donaldson]].

Anthropomorphism in literature and other media led to a sub-culture known as [[Furry fandom]], which promotes and creates stories and artwork involving anthropomorphic animals, and the examination and interpretation of humanity through anthropomorphism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Patten|first=Fred|authorlink= Fred Patten|year=2006|title=Furry! The World's Best Anthropomorphic Fiction|pages=427–436|publisher=ibooks|isbn=1-59687-319-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various Japanese [[manga]] have used anthropomorphism as the basis of their story. Examples include ''[[Squid Girl]]'' (anthropomorphised squid), ''[[Hetalia: Axis Powers]]'' (humanised countries) and ''[[Upotte!!]]'' (humanised guns).

===Film and television===
Some of the most notable examples are the [[Walt Disney]] characters, [[Mickey Mouse]], [[Donald Duck]], [[Goofy]], [[Oswald the Lucky Rabbit]]; the [[Looney Tunes]] characters, [[Bugs Bunny]], [[Daffy Duck]], [[Porky Pig]]; and an array of others from the 1920s to present day.

Since the 1960s, anthropomorphism has also been represented in various animated TV shows such as ''[[Biker Mice From Mars]]'' (1993–1996) and ''[[SWAT Kats: The Radical Squadron]]'' (1993–1995).  ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]'', first aired in 1987, features four pizza-loving anthropomorphic turtles with a great knowledge of ninjutsu, led by their anthropomorphic rat sensei, Master Splinter.

''[[Tugs (TV series)|TUGS]]'' (1988) is a British children's series, set in the 1920s, featuring anthropomorphic [[tugboat]]s. They moved like real boats but would sometimes perform certain actions without the aid of humans although not seen. Like real boats they obeyed maritime laws but would sometimes perform actions of their own will.

''[[Sonic the Hedgehog (1991 video game)|Sonic the Hedgehog]]'', a game released in 1991, features a speedy blue hedgehog as the protagonist. This series' characters are almost all anthropomorphic animals such as foxes, cats, and other hedgehogs who are able to speak and walk on their hind legs like normal humans. As with most anthropomorphisms of animals, clothing is of little or no importance, where some characters may be fully clothed while some only wear shoes and gloves.

Another example in video games is &quot;[[Super Mario Bros.]]&quot;, which was released in 1985. Some of the characters include [[Yoshi]], a dinosaur who is able to talk, run and jump, and [[Bowser (character)|Bowser]], a &quot;Koopa&quot; that is able to perform most human characteristics, with some exceptions, as he can breathe fire.

In the American animated TV series ''[[Family Guy]]'', one of the show's main characters, [[Brian Griffin|Brian]], is a dog. Brian shows many human characteristics – he walks upright, talks, smokes and drinks Martinis – but also acts like a normal dog in other ways; for example he cannot resist chasing a ball.

A Canadian-[[New Zealand]]-American animated TV show called ''[[Turbo Dogs]]'' (2008) starred anthro dog characters.
In 2010, a [[French American|French-American]] animated TV show ''[[The Mysteries of Alfred Hedgehog]]'' was mostly consisted of [[woodland]] anthropomorphic characters.

In the films ''[[Cars (film)|Cars]]'' (2006) and ''[[Cars 2]]'' (2011), all the characters are anthropomorphized vehicles.

A British TV series, ''[[Thomas and Friends]]'', features anthropomorphised trains, airplanes, helicopters and cars.

In the motion picture ''[[Fantastic Mr. Fox (film)|Fantastic Mr. Fox]]'' (2009), most of the characters are anthropomorphic animals very similar to the style seen in the [[Furry Fandom]]. They are given especially human characteristics such as body shape, hands and clothing, among other things.

==Art history==

===Claes Oldenburg===
[[Claes Oldenburg]]'s soft sculptures are commonly described as anthropomorphic. Depicting common household objects, Oldenburg's sculptures were considered [[Pop Art]]. Reproducing these objects, often at a greater size than the original, Oldenburg created his sculptures out of soft materials. The anthropomorphic qualities of the sculptures were mainly in their sagging and malleable exterior which mirrored the not so idealistic forms of the human body. In &quot;Soft Light Switches&quot; Oldenburg creates a household light switch out of Vinyl. The two identical switches, in a dulled orange, insinuate nipples. The soft vinyl references the aging process as the sculpture wrinkles and sinks with time.

===Minimalism===
In the essay &quot;Art and Objecthood&quot;, [[Michael Fried]] makes the case that &quot;[[Literalist art]]&quot; ([[Minimalism]]) becomes theatrical by means of anthropomorphism. The viewer engages the minimalist work, not as an autonomous art object, but as a theatrical interaction. Fried references a conversation in which Tony Smith answers questions about his &quot;six-foot cube, Die.&quot; 

Q: Why didn't you make it larger so that it would loom over the observer?
A: I was not making a monument.
Q: then why didn't you make it smaller so that the observer could see over the top?
A: I was not making an object.

Fried implies an anthropomorphic connection by means of &quot;a surrogate person-that is, a kind of statue.&quot; 

The minimalist decision of &quot;hollowness&quot; in much of their work, was also considered by Fried, to be &quot;blatantly anthropomorphic.&quot; This &quot;hollowness&quot; contributes to the idea of a separate inside; an idea mirrored in the human form. Fried considers the Literalist art's &quot;hollowness&quot; to be &quot;biomorphic&quot; as it references a living organism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Fried|first=Michael|title=Art and Objecthood|year=1998|publisher=University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|isbn=0-226-26319-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post Minimalism===
Curator [[Lucy Lippard]]'s Eccentric Abstraction show, in 1966, sets up [[Briony Fer]]'s writing of a post minimalist anthropomorphism. Reacting to Fried's interpretation of minimalist art's &quot;looming presence of objects which appear as actors might on a stage&quot;, Fer interprets the artists in Eccentric Abstraction to a new form of anthropomorphism. She puts forth the thoughts of Surrealist writer [[Roger Caillous]], who speaks of the &quot;spacial lure of the subject, the way in which the subject could inhabit their surroundings.&quot;  Caillous uses the example of an insect who &quot;through camouflage does so in order to become invisible... and loses its distinctness.&quot; For Fer, the anthropomorphic qualities of imitation found in the erotic, organic sculptures of artists [[Eva Hesse]] and [[Louise Bourgeois]], are not necessarily for strictly &quot;mimetic&quot; purposes. Instead, like the insect, the work must come into being in the &quot;scopic field... which we cannot view from outside.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Fer|first=Briony|title=Objects Beyond Objecthood|journal=Oxford Art Journal|year=1999|volume=22|pages=25–36}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In science==

In the scientific community, the use of anthropomorphic language that suggests animals have intentions and emotions has traditionally been deprecated as indicating a lack of [[Objectivity (science)|objectivity]]. [[Biology|Biologists]] have been warned to avoid assumptions that animals share any of the same mental, social, and emotional capacities of humans, and to rely instead on strictly observable evidence.&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to {{cite book |title= Social Creatures: A Human and Animal Studies Reader |last= Flynn|first= Cliff|year= 2008|publisher= Lantern Books| url = http://www.anthropress.org/excerpt.html?session=51678f1a4141f8aadcf5fd7898cdc296&amp;cat=&amp;isbn=9781590561232&amp;expid=534 |isbn= 1-59056-123-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1927 [[Ivan Pavlov]] wrote that animals should be considered &quot;without any need to resort to fantastic speculations as to the existence of any possible subjective states&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ryder, Richard. ''Animal Revolution: Changing Attitudes Towards Speciesism''. Berg, 2000, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, ''The Oxford companion to animal behaviour'' (1987) advised that &quot;one is well advised to study the behaviour rather than attempting to get at any underlying emotion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Masson and McCarthy 1996, xviii&lt;/ref&gt; Some scientists, like William M Wheeler (writing apologetically of his use of anthropormorphism in 1911), have used anthropomorphic language in metaphor to make subjects more humanly comprehensible or memorable.&lt;ref&gt;For example: &quot;The larval insect is, if I may be permitted to lapse for a moment into anthropomorphism, a sluggish, greedy, self-centred creature, while the adult is industrious, abstemious and highly altruistic...&quot;{{cite journal |last= Wheeler|first=  William Morton|authorlink= William Morton Wheeler|year= November 1911|title= Insect parasitism and its peculiarities|journal= Popular Science|volume=79 |page=443 |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the impact of [[Charles Darwin]]'s ideas in ''[[The Expression of the Emotions in Man and Animals]]'' ([[Konrad Lorenz]] in 1965 called him a &quot;[[patron saint]]&quot; of [[ethology]])&lt;ref name=&quot;Darwin&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal | pmc = 1279921 | pmid = 12042386 | year = 2002 | month = Jun | author = Black, J | title = Darwin in the world of emotions | volume = 95 | issue = 6 | pages = 311–3 | issn = 0141-0768 | journal = Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine | url = http://www.jrsm.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=12042386 | format = Free full text | doi = 10.1258/jrsm.95.6.311 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ethology has generally focused on [[behaviour]], not on [[emotion in animals]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Darwin&quot; /&gt; Though in other ways Darwin was and is the epitome of science, his acceptance of anecdote and anthropomorphism{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} stands out in sharp contrast to the lengths to which later scientists would go to overlook apparent [[mindedness]], [[selfhood]], [[individuality]] and [[agency (sociology)|agency]]{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}:

{{cquote|&quot;Even insects play together, as has been described by that excellent observer, [[P. Huber]], who saw ants chasing and pretending to bite each other, like so many puppies.&quot;|30px|30px|[[Charles Darwin]], ''[[The Descent of Man]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Darwin |first=Charles |title=The Descent of Man |year=1871 |page=39 |url=http://darwin-online.org.uk/EditorialIntroductions/Freeman_TheDescentofMan.html |edition=1st}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The study of [[great apes]] in their own environment has changed attitudes to anthropomorphism.&lt;ref&gt;Also in captivity: &quot;A thoroughgoing attempt to avoid anthropomorphic description in the study of temperament was made over a two-year period at the Yerkes laboratories. All that resulted was an almost endless series of specific acts in which no order or meaning could be found. On the other hand, by the use of frankly anthropomorphic concepts of emotion and attitude one could quickly and easily describe the peculiarities of individual animals... Whatever the anthropomorphic terminology may seem to imply about conscious states in chimpanzee, it provides an intelligible and practical guide to behavior.&quot; {{cite journal |doi= 10.1037/h0063033 |last= Hebb|first= Donald O.|authorlink= Donald O. Hebb|year= 1946|title=  Emotion in man and animal: An analysis of the intuitive processes of recognition|journal= Psychological Review|volume= 53|page=  88|pages= 88–106 |pmid= 21023321 |issue= 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1960s the three so-called &quot;[[Leakey's Angels]]&quot;, [[Jane Goodall]] studying [[chimpanzee]]s, [[Dian Fossey]] studying [[gorilla]]s and [[Biruté Galdikas]] studying [[orangutan]]s, were all accused of &quot;that worst of ethological sins – anthropomorphism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;cited in Masson and McCarthy 1996, p9 [http://books.google.com/books?id=UcbYqb8D4IEC&amp;pg=PR19&amp;dq=Jane+Goodall+controversy&amp;lr=&amp;ei=wQ_fS9mEGpm6yQT-1PHDCQ&amp;cd=52#v=onepage&amp;q=Jane%20Goodall%20controversy&amp;f=false%20 Google books]&lt;/ref&gt;  The charge was brought about by their descriptions of the great apes in the field; it is now more widely accepted that [[empathy]] has an important part to play in research. 

[[Frans de Waal]] wrote: &quot;To endow animals with human emotions has long been a scientific [[taboo]].  But if we do not, we risk missing something fundamental, about both animals and us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Frans de Waal (1997-07). &quot;Are We in Anthropodenial?&quot;. ''Discover''. pp. 50–53.&lt;/ref&gt; Alongside this has come increasing awareness of the [[Great ape language|linguistic abilities]] of the great apes and the recognition that they are tool-makers and have individuality {{Reference necessary|text=and culture.|date=August 2011}}

Writing of [[cats]] in 1992, veterinarian [[Bruce Fogle]] points to the fact that &quot;both humans and cats have identical [[neurochemicals]] and regions in the brain responsible for emotion&quot; as proof that &quot;it is not anthropomorphic to credit cats with emotions such as jealousy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Fogle|first=Bruce|title=If Your Cat Could Talk|year=1992|publisher=Dorling Kindersley|location=London|isbn=9781405319867|pages=11|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?ei=8SoCULxEx52IB9rroPYH&amp;id=r17xU3z5SaUC&amp;dq=if+your+cat+could+talk+fogle&amp;q=anthropomorphic#search_anchor}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Antonym===

In the context of the sciences, the term ''anthropomorphism'' has been deprecated to the point that, when applied to a scientist, the term functions as a pejorative (see above). However, there is also a risk of straying off the path of objectivity when scientists choose to assume that only humans possess any degree of certain traits.&lt;ref&gt;cite|web url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/anthropocentrism title=Merriam Webster – Anthropocentrism.&lt;/ref&gt; This assumption is called [[anthropocentrism]], practitioners of which either believe in or unintentionally form an outlook of human exceptionalism. Darwin - to the chagrin of many religious philosophers - dismissed these ideas of human exceptionalism in his book [[The Descent of Man]] by saying that our differences are &quot;only in degree, and not in kind&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;cite|web url=http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/2300/pg2300.html title=The Descent Of Man&lt;/ref&gt;

==In sports==
[[File:Lyo and Merly in Hong Kong.jpg|thumb|[[Lyo and Merly]], [[2010 Summer Youth Olympics]] in [[Singapore]].]]
[[File:Las Meninas Mininas.JPG|thumb|Version of [[Las Meninas]] with anthropomorphic cats]]

Anthropomorphic animals are often used as [[mascot]]s for sports teams or sporting events.

==See also==
{{Portal|Children's literature}}
{{colbegin}}
* [[Aniconism]]: antithetic concept
* [[Animism]]
* [[Modeling language|Anthropomorphic modeling language]] [[Service-oriented modeling framework]]
* [[Anthropic principle]]
* [[Anthropocentrism]]
* [[Anthropology]]
* [[Funny animal]]
* [[Furry fandom]]
* [[Great Chain of Being]]
* [[Humanoid]]
* [[Kemono]]
* [[Moe anthropomorphism]]
* [[National personification]]
* [[Pareidolia]]: seeing faces in everyday objects
* [[Pathetic Fallacy]]
* [[Speciesism]]
* [[Talking animals in fiction]]
* [[Zoomorphism]]
{{colend}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{cite book |title= When Elephants Weep: Emotional Lives of Animals|last= Masson|first= Jeffrey Moussaieff|authorlink= Jeffrey Moussaieff Masson|coauthors= Susan McCarthy |year= 1996|publisher= Vintage|isbn= 0-09-947891-9 |page= 272}}
*{{cite book |title= The Prehistory Of The Mind: A Search for the Origins of Art, Religion and Science |last= Mithen|first= Steven |authorlink= Steven Mithen|year= 1998|publisher= Phoenix |isbn= 978-0-7538-0204-5 |page= 480}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|wikt=anthropomorphism|commons=Category:Anthropomorphism}}
*[http://crl.ucsd.edu/~ahorowit/Encyclopedia-anthrop.pdf &quot;Anthropomorphism&quot; entry in the Encyclopedia of Human-Animal Relationships] (Horowitz A., 2007)
*[http://www.daviddarling.info/encyclopedia/A/anthropomorphism.html &quot;Anthropomorphism&quot; entry in the Encyclopedia of Astrobiology, Astronomy, and Spaceflight]
*[http://gogd.tjs-labs.com/gallery-view?keyword=ANTHRO%25 &quot;Anthropomorphism&quot; in mid-century American print advertising.] Collection at The Gallery of Graphic Design.

[[Category:Anthropomorphism| ]]
[[Category:Modernism]]
[[Category:Descriptive technique]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[af:Vermensliking]]
[[als:Anthropomorphismus]]
[[ar:مذهب التأنيس]]
[[az:Antropomorfizm]]
[[be:Антрапамарфізм]]
[[bg:Антропоморфия]]
[[br:Denheñvelegezh]]
[[ca:Antropomorfisme]]
[[cs:Antropomorfismus]]
[[da:Antropomorfisme]]
[[de:Anthropomorphismus]]
[[et:Antropomorfism]]
[[el:Ανθρωπομορφισμός]]
[[es:Antropomorfismo]]
[[eo:Antropomorfismo]]
[[eu:Antropomorfismo]]
[[fa:انسان‌دیسی]]
[[fr:Anthropomorphisme]]
[[gl:Antropomorfismo]]
[[ko:의인화]]
[[id:Antropomorfisme]]
[[ia:Anthropomorphismo]]
[[it:Antropomorfismo]]
[[he:האנשה]]
[[ka:ანთროპომორფიზმი]]
[[kk:Антропоморфизм]]
[[ku:Antropomorfîzm]]
[[ky:Антропоморфизм]]
[[lv:Antropomorfisms]]
[[hu:Antropomorfizmus]]
[[ms:Antropomorfisme]]
[[nl:Antropomorfisme]]
[[ja:擬人観]]
[[no:Antropomorfisme]]
[[nn:Antropomorfisme]]
[[pl:Antropomorfizacja]]
[[pt:Antropomorfismo]]
[[ro:Antropomorfism]]
[[ru:Антропоморфизм]]
[[simple:Anthropomorphism]]
[[sk:Antropomorfizmus]]
[[sl:Antropomorfizem]]
[[sr:Антропоморфизам]]
[[sh:Antropomorfizam]]
[[fi:Antropomorfismi]]
[[sv:Antropomorfism]]
[[ta:மாந்தவுருவகம்]]
[[th:มานุษยรูปนิยม]]
[[tr:İnsan biçimcilik]]
[[uk:Антропоморфізм]]
[[ur:انسنہ]]
[[zh:擬人論]]</text>
      <sha1>nl0b25jnhmock5drhw7nqhtahkykbt0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
