<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Anti-Defamation League</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27243620</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521909980</id>
      <parentid>521355633</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T23:56:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Professortimithy</username>
        <id>7474607</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Origin */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="62531">{{Other uses}}
{{Infobox organization
|name         = Anti-Defamation League
|image        = Adllogo.png
|size         = 100px
|caption      = Logo of the Anti-Defamation League
|motto        = To stop the defamation of the Jewish people…to secure justice and fair treatment to all.
|formation    = October 1913
|headquarters = New York City, New York, United States
|type         = [[Civil rights|Civil rights law]]
|leader_title = Director
|leader_name  = [[Abraham Foxman]]
|key_people   = [[Sigmund Livingston]] (Founder)&lt;br&gt;Robert Sugarman (Chairman)
|website      = [http://www.adl.org/ www.adl.org/]
}}
{{Antisemitism}}
The '''Anti-Defamation League''' ('''ADL''') is an international [[non-governmental organization]] based in the [[United States]]. Describing itself as &quot;the nation's premier civil rights/human relations agency&quot;, the ADL states that it &quot;fights anti-Semitism and all forms of bigotry, defends democratic ideals and protects civil rights for all,&quot; doing so through &quot;information, education, legislation, and advocacy.&quot;&lt;ref name=ADLCharter&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/about.asp |title=About ADL |accessdate=May 28, 2007 |publisher=ADL }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adl.org/about_more.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

Founded in October 1913 by [[B'nai B'rith|The Independent Order of B'nai B'rith]], a [[Jew]]ish [[service organization]] in the United States, its original mission statement was &quot;to stop, by appeals to reason and conscience and, if necessary, by appeals to law, the [[defamation]] of the [[Jew|Jewish people]]. Its ultimate purpose is to secure justice and fair treatment to all citizens alike and to put an end forever to unjust and unfair [[discrimination]] against and ridicule of any sect or body of citizens.&quot;&lt;ref name=ADLCharter/&gt; The ADL has 29 offices in the United States and three offices in other countries, with its headquarters located in [[New York City]]. Since 1987, [[Abraham Foxman]] has been the national director in the United States. The national chairman in the United States is Robert Sugarman.

==Origin==
Founded in October 1913 by [[Sigmund Livingston]], the ADL's charter states, &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The immediate object of the League is to stop, by appeals to reason and conscience and, if necessary, by appeals to law, the defamation of the Jewish people. Its ultimate purpose is to secure justice and fair treatment to all citizens alike and to put an end forever to unjust and unfair discrimination against and ridicule of any sect or body of citizens.&quot;&lt;ref name=ADLCharter/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Livingston established the ADL in direct response to the 1913 trial of [[Leo Frank]], a Jewish factory manager and B'nai B'rith chapter president in [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], convicted of &amp;mdash;and, posthumously, pardoned for&amp;mdash; murdering a 13 year old female employee.&lt;ref name=Steinberg-Brent&gt;{{cite book|last1=Steinberg-Brent|first1=|last2=a|first2=|title=Jews On Trial|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6iBVTKhV53QC&amp;pg=PA95+Steinberg-Brent|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=7 April 2005|publisher=KTAV Publishing House, Inc.|isbn=978-0-88125-868-4|pages=95–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dlg&gt;{{cite web|title=The Leo Frank Case|url=http://georgiainfo.galileo.usg.edu/leofrank.htm|publisher=Digital Library of Georgia|author=Charles Pou|quote=...the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith was founded in New York; its founding was based largely on the Leo Frank case and its aftermath.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Goals==
===Fighting anti-Semitism, bigotry, and racism===
The stated purpose of the ADL is to fight &quot;[[Antisemitism|Anti-Semitism]] and all forms of [[bigotry]] (in the United States) and abroad, combat international [[terrorism]], probe the roots of [[hate|hatred]], advocate before the [[United States Congress]], come to the aid of victims of bigotry, develop educational programs, and serve as a public resource for government, media, law enforcement, and the public, all towards the goal of countering and reducing hatred.&quot;

Historically, the ADL has opposed groups and individuals it considered to be anti-Semitic and/or [[Racism|racist]], including: [[Nazism|Nazis]], the [[Ku Klux Klan]], [[Henry Ford]], Father [[Charles Coughlin]] (leader of the [[Christian Front (United States)|Christian Front]]), the [[Christian Identity]] movement, the [[German-American Bund]], [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazis]], the [[Militia (United States)|American militia]] movement and [[white power skinhead]]s (although the ADL acknowledges that there are also non-racist [[skinhead]]s).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/racist_skinheads/ |title=Racist Skinhead Project |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6DD1530F93AA15757C0A962958260 NY Times article: &quot;A.D.L. Acknowledges Nonracist Skinheads&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The ADL publishes reports on a variety of countries, regarding alleged incidents of anti-Jewish attacks and propaganda.

The ADL maintains that some forms of [[Anti-Zionism]] and [[criticism of Israel]] are actually [[anti-Semitism]]. The Anti-Defamation League states:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Criticism of particular Israeli actions or policies in and of itself does not constitute anti-Semitism. Certainly the sovereign State of Israel can be legitimately criticized just like any other country in the world. However, it is undeniable that there are those whose [[criticism of Israel]] or of &quot;Zionism&quot; is used to mask anti-Semitism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/israel/advocacy/how_to_respond/anti_semitism_criticism.asp?xflag=1 |title=Anti-Semitism and Criticism of Israel |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The ADL gives out its [[Courage to Care Award]] to honor rescuers of Jews during the Holocaust era.

The ADL publishes a list of the &quot;ten leading organizations responsible for maligning Israel in the US&quot;, which have included a group calling for the United States to &quot;stop funding Israeli apartheid&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Benhorin, Yitzhak [http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3969798,00.html Jewish group makes ADL blacklist] y net news, 15 October 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Qumsiyeh, Mazin [http://www.salem-news.com/articles/october162010/israel-human-rights-mq.php Israel, ADL, ICNC and Human Rights] Salem-News.com, 16 October 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2010, the ADL condemned remarks by Haham [[Ovadia Yosef]] that the sole purpose of non-Jews was to serve the people of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;Mozgovaya, Natasha [http://www.haaretz.com/jewish-world/adl-slams-shas-spiritual-leader-for-saying-non-jews-were-born-to-serve-jews-1.320235?localLinksEnabled=false ADL slams Shas spiritual leader for saying non-Jews 'were born to serve Jews'] Haaretz Service, 20 October 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Separation of church and state==
One of the ADL's major focuses is religious freedom for people of all faiths.&lt;ref name = &quot;RelFree&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.adl.org/main_Religious_Freedom/default.htm
|title = Religious Freedom
|accessdate = December 2, 2007
|publisher = Anti-Defamation League
|quote = Safeguarding religious freedom for all Americans – whether in the majority or minority.
| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20071019030116/http://www.adl.org/main_Religious_Freedom/default.htm| archivedate= 19 October 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}
&lt;/ref&gt; In the context of public schools, the ADL has taken the position that because [[creationism]] and [[intelligent design]] are religious beliefs, and the government is prohibited from endorsing the beliefs of any particular religion, they should not be taught in [[science]] classrooms: &quot;The U.S. Constitution guarantees the rights of Americans to believe the religious theories of creation (as well as other theories) but it does not permit them to be taught in public school science classes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://adl.org/issue_religious_freedom/create/creationism_QA.asp |title=Religion in the Science Class? Why Creationism and Intelligent Design Don't Belong |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the ADL supports the legal precedent that it is [[constitutionality|unconstitutional]] for the government to post the [[Ten Commandments]] in courthouses, schools, and other public places: &quot;True religious liberty means freedom from having the government impose the religion of the majority on all citizens.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://adl.org/10comm/Prohibitions.asp |title=The Ten Commandments Controversy: A First Amendment Perspective – Prohibitions on Display of the Ten Commandments |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ADL has also condemned the public school [[Bible]] curriculum published by the [[National Council on Bible Curriculum in Public Schools]], saying that it raises &quot;serious constitutional problems&quot; and &quot;advocates the acceptance of one faith tradition's interpretation of the Bible over another.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=ADL Says Bible Teaching Guide for Public Schools 'Unacceptable' |publisher=ADL |date=November 7, 2005 |url=http://www.jewsonfirst.org/05a/public024.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ADL opposed [[California Proposition 8 (2008)|Proposition 8]] and supported the [[Matthew Shepard Act]].

==Defending other religions==
Stating that its one of its goals is to defend not only Jews, but also &quot;all citizens alike and to put an end forever to unjust and unfair discrimination against and ridicule of any sect or body of citizens,&quot; the ADL has periodically made statements against misrepresentations of other faiths. For example, when the [[anti-Mormon]] film &quot;[[The God Makers (film)|The God Makers]]&quot; was produced, Rhonda M. Abrams, Central Pacific (San Francisco) Regional Director for the ADL wrote a critical review, including the following statement:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Had a similar movie been made with either Judaism or Catholicism as its target, it would be immediately denounced for the scurrilous piece that it is. I sincerely hope that people of all faiths will similarly repudiate &quot;The Godmakers&quot; as defamatory and untrue, and recognize it for what it truly represents—a challenge to the religious liberty of all.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairlds.org/pubs/tagm/tagm34.html Letter to Dr. Richard Lindsay], Director of Public Communications, The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, May 25, 1984&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Tracking &quot;extremists&quot;==
The ADL keeps track of the activities of various &quot;extremist&quot; groups and movements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://adl.org/main_Extremism/default.htm |title=Extremism |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ADL Director Abe Foxman, &quot;Our mission is to monitor and expose those who are anti-Jewish, racist, anti-democratic, and violence-prone, and we monitor them primarily by reading publications and attending public meetings …. Because extremist organizations are highly secretive, sometimes ADL can learn of their activities only by using undercover sources … [who] function in a manner directly analogous to investigative journalists.  Some have performed great service to the American people—for example, by uncovering the existence of right-wing extremist paramilitary training camps—with no recognition and at considerable personal risk.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A League of His Own,&quot; letter to the editor, ''The Village Voice'' 38:20 (May 18, 1993)&lt;/ref&gt;  A person apprehended in connection to the [[2002 white supremacist terror plot]] had drawn a cartoon of himself blowing up the Boston offices of the ADL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |

publisher=New York Times |
date=July 16, 2002 |
title=Boston Couple Plotted Blasts to Incite Race War, Prosecutor Says |
url=http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/16/national/16PLOT.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADL regularly releases reports on anti-Semitism and extremist activities on the far left and the far right.  For instance, as part of its Law Enforcement Agency Resource Network (L.E.A.R.N.), the ADL has published information about the Militia Movement&lt;ref name=&quot;militia&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/learn/ext_us/Militia_M.asp?LEARN_Cat=Extremism&amp;LEARN_SubCat=Extremism_in_America&amp;xpicked=4&amp;item=mm |title=The Militia Movement – Extremism in America |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; in America and a guide for law enforcement officials titled ''Officer Safety and Extremists''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://adl.org/learn/safety/Whysafety.asp |title=Officer Safety and Extremists: An Overview for Law Enforcement Officers |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; An archive of &quot;[[Mark Pitcavage#Militia Watchdog|The Militia Watchdog]]&quot; research on U.S. right-wing extremism (including groups not specifically cited as anti-Semitic) from 1995 to 2000 is also available on the ADL website.&lt;ref name=&quot;militia&quot; /&gt;

In the 1990s, some details of the ADL's monitoring activities became public and controversial, including the fact that the ADL had gathered information about some non-extremist groups.

===Role in arrest of potential assassins of Barack Obama===
In October 2008 the ADL reportedly assisted the US [[Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms]] (ATF) by providing, on request, information on [[Daniel Cowart]] and [[Paul Schlesselman]] and their associates and contacts, and on their ties to the [[Supreme White Alliance]]. Shortly thereafter the two men were arrested on charges of plotting to murder dozens of African Americans and [[2008 Barack Obama assassination scare in Tennessee|plotting to assassinate US President-elect Barack Obama]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/PresRele/NeoSk_82/5380_82.htm ADL Applauds Law Enforcement for Preventing Killing Spree and Obama Assassination Attempt], ADL Press Release, October 27, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1225199589269&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull ADL helped probe into neo-Nazis], Jewish Telegraph Agency (JTA)(reprinted by the Jerusalem Post), October 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Holocaust awareness==
The ADL holds that it is important to remember the [[Holocaust]], in order to prevent such an event from ever coming to pass again. Along with sponsoring events and fighting [[Holocaust denial|Holocaust deniers]] and revisionists, the ADL has been active in urging action to stop modern-day &quot;[[ethnic cleansing]]&quot; and [[genocide]] in places such as [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia]] and [[Darfur]], [[Sudan]].

The ADL spoke out against an advertising campaign by [[People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals]] (PETA) beginning in 2003 that equated meat-eating with the Holocaust. A press release from the ADL stated that &quot;PETA's effort to seek 'approval' for their 'Holocaust on Your Plate' campaign is outrageous, offensive and takes [[chutzpah]] to new heights. Rather than deepen our revulsion against what the Nazis did to the Jews, the project will undermine the struggle to understand the Holocaust and to find ways to make sure such catastrophes never happen again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=ADL Denounces Peta for its &quot;Holocaust On Your Plate&quot; Campaign; Calls Appeal for Jewish Community Support 'The Height Of Chutzpah' |publisher=ADL |date=February 24, 2003 |url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/HolNa_52/4235_52.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; On May 5, 2005, PETA issued an apology for comparing the treatment of farm animals to the victims of the Nazi concentration camps. PETA President Ingrid Newkirk said she realized that the campaign had caused pain: &quot;This was never our intention, and we are deeply sorry.&quot;

The ADL has for many years refused to acknowledge that the [[Armenian genocide]] constituted a [[genocide]].  The ADL has actively engaged in efforts to oppose Congressional affirmation of the Armenian Genocide.  Under pressure to do so, the national ADL issued a &quot;Statement on the Armenian Genocide&quot; on August 21, 2007.  The statement declared, &quot;The consequences of those actions were indeed tantamount to genocide.&quot; Activists felt that the statement was not a full, unequivocal acknowledgment of the Armenian genocide, because the use of the qualifier &quot;tantamount&quot; was seen as inappropriate, and the use of the word &quot;consequences&quot; was seen as an attempt to circumvent the international legal definition of genocide by avoiding any language that would imply intent, a crucial aspect of the 1948 UN Genocide Convention definition.  The ADL convened its national meeting in New York City in early November at which time the issue of the Armenian Genocide was discussed.  Upon conclusion, a one sentence press statement was issued that &quot;The National Commission of the Anti-Defamation League (ADL) today, at its annual meeting, decided to take no further action on the issue of the Armenian genocide.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adl.org/PresRele/Mise_00/5162_00.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political positions==

The ADL supports the [[Jewish state]] and has vociferously opposed resolutions such as the [[UN General Assembly Resolution 3379|1975 United Nations resolution]] ([[UN General Assembly Resolution 4686|revoked in 1991]]) that had equated Zionism and racism,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/durban/adl_quotes.asp |title=U.N. World Conference Against Racism |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; and attempts to revive that formulation at the 2001 U.N. [[World Conference Against Racism]] in [[Durban]], [[South Africa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/durban/un_anti-zionism.asp |title=U.N. World Conference Against Racism |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADL honors individuals throughout the year for various reasons. On September 23, 2003, at its Tribute to Italy Dinner, the ADL awarded Italian prime minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]] the ADL's distinguished statesman award, an honor &quot;conferred on world leaders who exhibit a commitment to furthering the achievement of regional and world peace, and who possess a special commitment to promoting human and civil rights.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://adl.org/international/lfe/speech_berlusconi.asp |title=Speech by Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi at the Anti-Defamation League Tribute to Italy Dinner |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; Berlusconi is also known for his staunch pro-Israel stance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |
url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/Flash.aspx/145288 |
title=Pro-Israel Italian leader Berlusconi To Visit in May |
date=April 22, 2008 |
publisher=Arutz Sheva}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |
title=Netanyahu Nixes Meeting With Obama Envoy |
date=June 23, 2009 |
url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2009/06/23/world/main5106588.shtml?source=related_story |
publisher=CBS News}} &quot;Berlusconi's pro-Israel stance has made Italy perhaps Israel's best friend in Europe.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADL has spoken out against [[red-baiting]] and [[McCarthyism]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

In 2006 the ADL condemned Senate Republicans in the United States for attempting to ban [[same-sex marriage]] with the [[Federal Marriage Amendment]] and praised its demise, calling it &quot;discrimination&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=ADL Welcomes Demise Of Same-Sex Marriage Amendment; Expresses 'Dismay' At Senate Vote |publisher=ADL |date=June 7, 2006 |url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/DiRaB_41/4832_41.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; That same year the ADL warned that the debate over [[illegal immigration]] was drawing [[neo-nazis]] and [[anti-Semites]] into the ranks of the [[The Minuteman Project Inc.|Minutemen Project]].

In 1974 ADL national leaders Arnold Forster and Benjamin R. Epstein published a book called ''The [[New Anti-Semitism]]'' (New York, 1974), arguing that a new kind of anti-Semitism is on the rise. In 1982, ADL national leader Nathan Perlmutter and his wife, Ruth Ann Perlmutter, released a book entitled ''The Real Anti-Semitism in America'' (New York, 1982). In 2003, ADL's national director Abraham Foxman published ''Never Again? The Threat of the New Anti-Semitism'' (San Francisco, 2003), where on page 4 he states: &quot;We currently face as great a threat to the safety and security of the Jewish people as the one we faced in the 1930s—if not a greater one.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;adl.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/Anti_semitism/never_again.asp |title=Never Again? The Threat of the New Anti-Semitism |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, during a hearing for Florida House Bill 11 (Crimes Against Homeless Persons) which was to revise the list of offenses judged to be hate crimes in Florida by adding a person's homeless status,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title = flhouse.gov HB 11 – Crimes Against Homeless Persons
| url = http://flhouse.gov/Sections/Bills/billsdetail.aspx?BillId=42143&amp;
| accessdate = April 22, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the League lobbied against the bill, which subsequently passed in the House by a vote of 80 to 28 and was sent to the Senate,&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title = flhouse.gov HB 11 Apr 20 2010 – Voting record Florida House of Representatives
| url = http://flhouse.gov/Sections/Bills/floorvote.aspx?VoteId=10836&amp;BillId=42143&amp;
| accessdate = April 22, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; taking the position that adding more categories to the list would dilute the effectiveness of the law, which already includes race, religion, sexual orientation, disability, and age.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Homeless could be added to Florida's hate crimes law
| url = http://www.miamiherald.com/2010/04/21/1589541/homeless-could-be-added-to-floridas.html?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+StatelineorgRss-CrimeCourts+(Stateline.org+RSS+-+Crime+%26+Courts)
| accessdate = April 22, 2010
}} ''Miami Herald'', Miami Herald Media Co., April 21, 2010, by Lee Logan, Tallahassee Bureau: &quot;During a committee hearing on the bill, the Anti-Defamation League spoke against the bill, arguing that adding more categories to the hate crimes law would dilute its effect. But lawmakers were swayed by arguments in favor of protecting the homeless.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADL supports [[Comprehensive Immigration Reform Act of 2007|Comprehensive]] and [[DREAM Act]] legislation that would provide conditional permanent residency to certain illegal aliens of good moral character who graduate from U.S. high schools, arrived in the United States as minors, and lived in the country continuously for at least five years prior to the bill's enactment.{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}

==Interfaith camp==
ADL's New England Regional Office has also established a faith-based initiative called &quot;The Interfaith Youth Leadership Program,&quot; better known as &quot;Camp If,&quot; or Camp Interfaith. Involving teenagers of the Christian, Jewish, and Islamic faiths, the camp brings the teens together for a week at camp where the teens bond and learn about each other's cultures. The camp has emerged as a new attempt to foster good relations between younger members of the Abrahamic faiths.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Siek |first=Stephanie V. |date=April 6, 2006 |title=A different kind of camp |journal=[[The Boston Globe]] |url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2006/04/06/a_different_kind_of_camp/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relations with ethnic groups==
===Relations with Arabs and Muslims===
{{See also|Projects working for peace among Israelis and Arabs}}
ADL publications on condemning bigotry towards Arabs, Muslims, Blacks and members of other minorities have often been used in synagogue adult education programs, and as part of Jewish-Christian and Jewish-Muslim inter-faith dialogue.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}

The ADL is sometimes at odds with Arab and Muslim groups, particularly over issues involving Israel and antisemitism. For instance, the ADL regularly publishes updates to its web site reviewing and cataloguing negative portrayals of Jews in Arab nations' media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/main_Arab_World/default.htm |title=Anti-Semitism in the Muslim/Arab World |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 18, 2004 the ADL issued a news release&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=ADL Statement On The Muslim Student Union at UC-Irvine   |publisher=ADL |date=June 18, 2004 |url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/Mise_00/4520_00.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; about the [[University of California Irvine]] (UCI) Muslim Students Union in which the ADL alleged that the student group had invited speakers to campus who &quot;made public declarations of support for Hamas, advocated suicide bombings and called for the destruction of Israel.&quot; For graduation Group members chose to wear [[Green in Islam|green]] (the traditional colour of Islam) graduation stoles bearing the ''[[Shahada]]'', the Islamic [[declaration of faith]]. The ADL's press release described the Shahada as &quot;a declaration of faith that has been closely identified with Palestinian terrorists,&quot; and claimed that [[suicide bomber]]s connected to the Palestinian group [[Hamas]] wear green armbands and headbands inscribed with the ''Shahada'' as a symbol of their movement, and further stated, &quot;We are troubled that members of the [[(UCI) Muslim Students Union]] have chosen to display symbolism that is closely identified with Palestinian terrorist groups and that can be especially offensive to Jewish students.&quot;

A news release from the [[Council on American-Islamic Relations]] denied that the stoles were expressions of support for terrorism, called the ADL's comments &quot;bigoted statements&quot;, and demanded an apology; the organization's communications director Sabiha Khan said: &quot;The ADL's hate-filled Islamophobic rhetoric labels all Muslims as terrorists, because every Muslim believes in the declaration of faith as the essence of Islam.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cair-net.org/default.asp?Page=articleView&amp;id=1085&amp;theType=NR |title=Muslims Demand Apology for ADL's 'Hate-Filled Rhetoric' |date=June 19, 2001 |publisher=[[Council on American-Islamic Relations]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ADL released a clarifying statement saying the ADL has nothing against the Muslim statement of faith and that, &quot;It was never our intent to offend anyone and we apologize to those who took offense.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://releases.usnewswire.com/GetRelease.asp?id=32363&lt;/ref&gt;

===Relations with African-Americans===
The ADL has worked to combat racism against all racial groups, including racism against blacks. In 1997, the ''National Center for Black-Jewish Relations'' of [[Dillard University]], a [[historically black college|historically black university]] in [[New Orleans]] awarded the director of the ADL, Abraham H. Foxman, with the first Annual Martin Luther King, Jr. – Donald R. Mintz Freedom and Justice Award.

In 2004, the ADL became the lead partner in the ''Peace and Diversity Academy'', a new New York City public high school with predominantly black and Hispanic students.

In celebration of Black History Month, the ADL created and distributed lesson plans to middle and high school teachers about [[Shirley Chisholm]], the first black woman elected to the US Congress, and an important civil rights leader.

The ADL has also publicly charged certain African Americans with anti-Semitism:

* The ADL has catalogued a three-decade history of [[Nation of Islam]] leader [[Louis Farrakhan]] espousing anti-Semitic rhetoric such as claims that certain Jews are &quot;not real Jews&quot; and are &quot;wicked deceivers of the American people&quot; who &quot;sucked [Americans'] blood,&quot; and that powerful Jews promote homosexuality and control black leadership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/special_reports/farrakhan_own_words2/farrakhan_own_words.asp |title=Farrakhan In His Own Words |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; Farrakhan first attracted the attention of the ADL with comments in a March 11, 1984 radio broadcast saying that &quot;Hitler was a very great man,&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;finalcall&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=Farrakhan and the Jewish Rift; How It All Started |journal=[[The Final Call]] |url=http://www.finalcall.com/perspectives/rift.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Farrakhan insists he was using the word 'great' in the sense of 'Great Depression' or 'great white shark'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.noi.org/statements/rift/Wanniski12-22-1997.htm Memo, 12–22–97; Letter From Farrakhan&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and on June 24, 1984 describing the Jewish state as &quot;structured on injustice, thievery, lying and deceit and using the name of God to shield your dirty religion under His holy and righteous name.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;finalcall&quot; /&gt; The ADL has urged various groups including the NAACP (whose leader [[Benjamin Chavis]] developed a working relationship with Farrakhan in 1994) to dissociate themselves from Farrakhan and his views.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Foxman |first=Abraham H. |authorlink=Abraham Foxman |date=July 20, 1994 |title=Today's N.A.A.C.P. Draws on History; Set Farrakhan Aside |journal=[[The New York Times]] |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7DE143EF933A15754C0A962958260&amp;n=Top%2fReference%2fTimes%20Topics%2fSubjects%2fR%2fReligion%20and%20Belief}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1984 ''[[The Boston Globe]]'' reported that then ADL national director, Nathan Perlmutter, said Rev. [[Jesse Jackson]], Sr. was anti-Semitic, after Jackson referred to New York City as &quot;Hymietown&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |date=February 23, 1984 |title=Post Reaffirms Report On Jackson Comment |journal=[[The New York Times]] |pages=13 |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FA0E10FB3B5D0C708EDDAB0894DC484D81}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |date=February 27, 1984 |title=Jackson Admits Saying 'Hymie' And Apologizes At A Synagogue |journal=[[The New York Times]] |pages=16 |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30A14F83C5D0C748EDDAB0894DC484D81}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the ADL later reconciled with Jackson and has worked with him on the issue of the Iranian Jewish community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=Rev. Jesse Jackson Meets with Iranian Jewish Families Pledges to Intercede on Behalf of Imprisoned Jews |publisher=ADL |date=June 11, 1999 |url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASInt_13/3401_13.asp}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Film Director [[Spike Lee]] was criticized by the Anti-Defamation League for his portrayal of Jewish nightclub owners Moe and Josh Flatbush in his 1990 film ''[[Mo' Better Blues]]''. The Anti-Defamation League claimed that the characterizations of the nightclub owners &quot;dredge up an age-old and highly dangerous form of anti-Semitic stereotyping,&quot; and &quot;...disappointed that Spike Lee – whose success is largely due to his efforts to break down racial stereotypes and prejudice – has employed the same kind of tactics that he supposedly deplores.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |date=August 16, 1990 |title=Spike Lee's Jews and the Passage From Benign Cliche Into Bigotry|journal=[[The New York Times]] |author=Caryn James|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D6113DF935A2575BC0A966958260}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lee's portrayal also angered the B'nai B'rith and other such Jewish organizations causing Lee to apologize via an Opinion-Editorial article in ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |date=August 13, 2006 |title=The Angriest Auteur|journal=[[New York Magazine]] |author=Ariel Levy|url=http://nymag.com/movies/profiles/19144/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* During the 2002 election cycle, the ADL, in a letter to ''The New York Times'', harshly criticized [[Congressional Black Caucus]] member [[Cynthia McKinney]] of Georgia for launching attacks perceived as racial against her Jewish opponent. According to an August 19, 2002 article in ''The New York Times'' ADL Director Abraham Foxman said, &quot;it made sense that Jewish Americans would want to contribute to efforts to replace Ms. McKinney.&quot;
* In February 2005, ADL National Director Abraham Foxman called it hypocritical for hip-hop producer [[Russell Simmons]] to lead an ad campaign against anti-Semitism while also, according to Foxman's view, defending or excusing Louis Farrakhan's anti-Semitic statements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=ADL Calls on Russell Simmons to Distance Himself from Minister Farrakhan   |publisher=ADL |date=February 14, 2005 |url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASUS_12/4645_12.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year the ADL urged prominent black leaders including Simmons to reconsider their support for Farrakhan and [[Malik Zulu Shabazz]] organizing the [[Millions More Movement]] and to &quot;stand up&quot; against black anti-Semitism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=ADL Urges Prominent African-American Leaders to Reconsider Their Support for the &quot;Millions More Movement&quot; |publisher=ADL |date=May 2, 2005 |url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASUS_12/4707_12.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Simmons, responding to ADL Director Abraham Foxman, said &quot;simply put, you are misguided, arrogant, and very disrespectful of African Americans and most importantly your statements will unintentionally or intentionally lead to a negative impression of Jews in the minds of millions of African Americans.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.millionsmoremovement.com/news/russell-simmons05-09-2005.htm |title=Russell Simmons Responds to Abraham Foxman about the Millions More Movement |last=Simmons |first=Russell |authorlink=Russell Simmons |date=May 9, 2005 |publisher=[[Millions More Movement]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Foxman replied, &quot;If there were a Jewish event which was led by an out-and-out racist, I would expect Black leaders to say to me that ADL should have nothing to do with it. And I would agree with them, rather than condemn them for their action.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/media_watch/internet/20050510-Russell+Simmons.htm |title=Response to Russell Simmons |date=May 9, 2005 |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The ADL files controversy==
Since the 1930s the ADL has been gathering information and publishing reports on anti-Semitism, racism and prejudice, and on anti-Jewish, anti-Israel, racist, anti-democratic, violent, and extremist individuals and groups.  As a result, the organization has amassed what it once called a &quot;famous storehouse of accurate, detailed, unassailable information on extremist individuals and organizations.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/ADLHistory/1930_1940.asp |title=1930–1940 The World and ADL Were Changing... |work=History of the ADL |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over the decades the ADL has assembled thousands of files.

One of its sources was '''Roy Bullock''', a person who collected information and provided it to the ADL as a secretly paid independent contractor over 32 years.  Bullock often wrote letters to various groups and forwarded copies of their replies to the ADL, clipped articles from newspapers and magazines, and maintained files on his computer. He also used less orthodox, and possibly illegal, methods such as combing through trash and tapping into the [[White Aryan Resistance]]'s phone message system to find evidence of [[hate crime]]s.  Some of the information he obtained and then passed on to the ADL came from confidential documents (including intelligence files on various Nazi groups and driver's license records and other personal information on nearly 1,400 people) that were given to him by San Francisco police officer '''Tom Gerard'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paddock&quot;&gt;Richard C. Paddock, &quot;[http://articles.latimes.com/1993-04-13/news/mn-22383_1 New Details of Extensive ADL Spy Operation Emerge],&quot; Los Angeles Times, April 13, 1993, A1&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 8, 1993, police seized Bullock's computer and raided the ADL offices in [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]] and [[Los Angeles, California]]. A search of Bullock's computer revealed he had compiled files on 9,876 individuals and more than 950 groups across the political spectrum.  Many of Bullock's files concerned groups that did not fit the mold of extremist groups, hate groups, and organizations hostile to Jews or Israel that the ADL would usually be interested in.  Along with files on the Ku Klux Klan, White Aryan Resistance, Islamic Jihad and [[Jewish Defense League]] were data on the [[NAACP]], the [[African National Congress]] (ANC), the [[American Civil Liberties Union]] (ACLU), the [[United Auto Workers]], the AIDS activist group [[AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power|ACT UP]], [[Mother Jones (magazine)|Mother Jones magazine]], the [[Telegraph Agency of the Soviet Union|TASS]] Soviet/Russian news agency, [[Greenpeace]], [[Jews for Jesus]] and the [[National Lawyers Guild]]; there were also files on politicians including Democratic U.S. Representative [[Nancy Pelosi]], former Republican U.S. Representative [[Pete McCloskey]], and activist [[Lyndon LaRouche]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Paddock&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.refuseandresist.org/big_brother/011697antifa.html |title=The 'Public-Private Partnership' |last=Burghardt |first=Tom |date=January 16, 1997 |publisher=Antifa Info-Bulletin}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bullock told investigators that many of those were his own private files, not information he was passing on to the ADL.  An attorney for the ADL stated that &quot;We knew nothing about the vast extent of the files. Those are not ADL's files. … That is all [Bullock's] doing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Adams&quot;&gt;Meredith Jane Adams, [http://www.fpp.co.uk/docs/ADL/Trib030593.html &quot;Anti-Defamation League may have broken records laws&quot;], [[Chicago Tribune]], May 3, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;  As for its own records, the ADL indicated that just because it had a file on a group did not indicate opposition to the group. The San Francisco district attorney at the time accused the ADL of conducting a national &quot;[[spy]] network&quot;, but dropped all accusations a few months later.&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishsf&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Julie |last=Wiener |title=ADL settles with Arabs, others to wrap up 6-year lawsuit |url=http://www.jewishsf.com/content/2-0-/module/displaystory/story_id/12169/ |publisher=The Jewish News Weekly of Northern California |date=October 1, 1999}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the weeks following the raids, twelve civil rights groups led by the [[American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee]] and the [[National Lawyers Guild]], filed a lawsuit demanding ADL release its surveillance information and end its investigations, as well as be ordered to pay punitive damages.&lt;ref&gt;James Bolden, [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-2221305.html Coalition of Civil Rights Groups Sue Anti-Defamation League], [[Los Angeles Sentinel]], November 3, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;  The plaintiffs' attorney, former Representative McCloskey, claimed that information the ADL gathered constituted an invasion of privacy. The ADL, while distancing itself from Bullock, countered that it is entitled like any researcher or journalist to research organizations and individuals.  Richard Cohen, legal director of the [[Southern Poverty Law Center]] in Montgomery, Alabama, stated that like journalists, the ADL's researchers &quot;gather information however they can&quot; and welcome disclosures from confidential sources, saying &quot;they probably rely on their sources to draw the line&quot; on how much can legally be divulged.  Bullock admitted that he was overzealous, and that some of the ways he gathered information may have been illegal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adams&quot; /&gt;

The lawsuit was settled out of court in 1999. The ADL agreed to pay $175,000 for the court costs of the groups that sued it, promised that it would not seek information from sources it knew could not legally disclose such information, consented to remove sensitive information like criminal records or [[Social Security number]]s from its files, and spent $25,000 to further relations between the Jewish, Arab and black communities.  When the case was settled, [[Hussein Ibish]], director of communications for the [[American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee]] (ADC), claimed that the ADL had gathered data &quot;systematically in a program whose clear intent was to undermine civil rights and Arab-American organizations&quot;.  ADL national director Abraham Foxman called the ADC's claims &quot;absolutely untrue,&quot; saying that &quot;if it were true, they would have won their case&quot; and noting that no court found the ADL guilty of any wrongdoing.  The ADL released a statement saying that the settlement &quot;explicitly recognizes ADL's right to gather information in any lawful and constitutionally protected manner, which we have always done and will continue to do.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishsf&quot; /&gt;

===James Rosenberg===
A case which has been compared to the Bullock case was that of James Mitchell Rosenberg, AKA Jim Anderson. Rosenberg/Anderson was an undercover operative of the ADL who acted as an agent provocateur, posing as a racist right-wing paramilitary extremist. He appeared in this role as part of a TV documentary entitled &quot;Armies of the Right&quot; which premiered in 1981. Rosenberg was arrested that same year in New York for carrying an unregistered firearm in public view. In 1984, ADL fact-finding director [[Irwin Suall]] identified Rosenberg as an ADL operative in a court deposition.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey Kaplan, Heléne Lööw, [http://books.google.com/books?id=CjIYNrOO24IC&amp;pg=PA305&amp;lpg=PA305&amp;dq=jamie+rosenberg+provocateur&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=YIo3-evgU8&amp;sig=l_eYQBzzTMN5ad2RrZ-AxgJaLYg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=MhqPSom6C8mntgf6-qzOBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The cultic milieu: oppositional subcultures in an age of globalization], ISBN 0-7591-0204-X&lt;/ref&gt;

==Armenian Genocide controversy==
In 2007, Abraham Foxman came under criticism for his stance on the [[Armenian Genocide]]. The ADL had previously described it as a &quot;massacre&quot; and &quot;atrocity&quot;, but not a &quot;genocide&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;http&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/Mise_00/5114_00.htm
|title=ADL Statement on the Armenian Genocide
|date=August 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Foxman had earlier opposed calls for the U.S. Government to recognise it as a &quot;genocide&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jewcy.com/feature/2007-07-09/fire_foxman |title=Fire Foxman: Denying the Armenian Genocide should be the last atrocity perpetrated by the ADL chief.}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;I don't think congressional action will help reconcile the issue. The resolution takes a position; it comes to a judgment,&quot; said Foxman in a statement issued to the [[Jewish Telegraphic Agency]]. “The [[Turkey|Turks]] and [[Armenia]]ns need to revisit their past. The Jewish community shouldn't be the arbiter of that history, nor should the U.S. Congress, and &quot;a Congressional resolution on such matters is a counterproductive diversion and will not foster reconciliation between Turks and Armenians and may put at risk the Turkish Jewish community and the important multilateral relationship between Turkey, Israel and the United States.&quot;

In early August 2007, complaints about the Anti-Defamation League's refusal to acknowledge the [[Armenian Genocide]] led to the [[Watertown, Massachusetts]] unanimous town council decision to end their participation in the ADL &quot;No Place for Hate&quot; campaign. (Watertown is known for its Armenian population.) Also in August 2007, an editorial in ''[[The Boston Globe]]'' criticized the ADL saying that &quot;as an organization concerned about human rights, it ought to acknowledge the [[genocide]] against the Armenian people during [[World War I]], and criticize Turkish attempts to repress the memory of this historical reality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date= August 3, 2007 |url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/editorials/articles/2007/08/03/a_genocide_not_to_be_denied/ |title=A genocide not to be denied |publisher=[[Boston Globe]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Then on 17 August 2007, the ADL fired its regional [[New England]] director, Andrew H. Tarsy, for breaking ranks with the main organization and saying the ADL should recognize the genocide.&lt;ref name=obrien&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2007/08/18/adl_local_leader_fired_on_armenian_issue/
|title=ADL local leader fired on Armenian issue: Genocide question sparked bitter debate
|publisher=The Boston Globe
|first=Keith
|last=O'Brien
|date=August 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 21 August 2007 press release, the ADL changed its position to one of acknowledging the genocide but maintained its opposition to congressional resolutions aimed at recognizing it.&lt;ref name=&quot;http&quot;/&gt; Foxman wrote, &quot;the consequences of those actions,&quot; by the [[Ottoman Empire]] against Armenians, &quot;were indeed tantamount to genocide.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2007/08/22/adl_chief_bows_to_critics/
|title=ADL chief bows to critics: Foxman cites rift, calls Armenian deaths genocide
|first=Keith
|last=O'Brien
|date=August 22, 2007
|publisher=The Boston Globe}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Turkish government]] condemned the league's statement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2007/08/24/turkey_condemns_statement_by_adl/
|title=Turkey condemns statement by ADL
|first=Michael
|last=Levenson
|date=August 24, 2007
|publisher=The Boston Globe}}&lt;/ref&gt; Andrew H. Tarsy was rehired by the league on 27 August,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/city_region/breaking_news/2007/08/antidefamation_1.html
|title=Anti-Defamation League rehires New England director
|first=Keith
|last=O'Brien
|publisher=The Boston Globe
|date=September 7, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; though he has since chosen to step down from his position.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.thejewishadvocate.com/this_weeks_issue/news/?content_id=4108
|title=Tarsy Resignation Draws Mixed Emotions From Area Colleagues
|first=Rachel
|last=Axelbank
|publisher=Jewish Advocate
|date=December 6, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ADL was criticized by many in the Armenian community including ''The Armenian Weekly'' newspaper, in which writer Michael Mensoian stated:

{{quote|The belated backtracking of the Anti-Defamation League (ADL) in acknowledging the planned, systematic massacre of 1,500,000 Armenian men, women and children as &quot;…tantamount to genocide…&quot; is discouraging. Tantamount means something is equivalent. If it’s equivalent, why avoid using the term? For the ADL to justify its newly adopted statement because the word genocide did not exist at the time indicates a halfhearted attempt to placate Armenians while not offending Turkey. Historians use the term genocide simply because it is the proper term to describe the horrific events that the Ottoman Turkish government unleashed on the Armenian people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hairenik.com/armenianweekly/com08250702p.htm &quot;The Armenian Weekly&quot;, Volume 73, No. 34, August 25, 2007, By Michael G. Mensoian]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

After Foxman's capitulation, the New England ADL pressed the organization's national leadership to support a congressional resolution acknowledging the genocide.&lt;ref name=Woolhouse/&gt; After hours of closed-door debate at the annual national meeting in New York, the proposal was ultimately withdrawn.&lt;ref name=Woolhouse/&gt; The organization issued a statement saying it would &quot;take no further action on the issue of the Armenian genocide.&quot; The ADL had earlier received direct pressure from the Turkish Foreign ministry.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.co.il/hasite/spages/911393.html טורקיה לישראל: עזרו לנו לעצור הכרה אמריקאית בשואה הארמנית] Haaretz, 10/10/07, Barak Ravid&lt;/ref&gt; Tarsy submitted his resignation on December 4.&lt;ref name=Woolhouse&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2007/12/05/adls_regional_leader_resigns/
|title=ADL's regional leader resigns: Backers cite rift on genocide issue
|first=Megan
|last=Woolhouse
|publisher=The Boston Globe
|date=December 5, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Since August, some human rights commissions in other Massachusetts communities decided to follow Watertown's lead and withdraw from the ADL's No Place for Hate anti-discrimination program.&lt;ref name=Woolhouse/&gt;

==Criticism==
Linguist and activist [[Noam Chomsky]] has characterized ADL as having lost entirely its focus on civil rights issues to become solely an advocate for Israeli policy; he holds that ADL casts all left-wing opposition to Israeli interests as antisemitism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.nvg.org/~skars/ni/ni-c10-s20.html Noam Chomsky, Necessary Illusions, Appendix V, Segment 20]&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Role in cancellation of speech by Tony Judt at Polish Consulate===
The ADL, in addition to the [[American Jewish Committee]], was criticized by academic [[Tony Judt]] for allegedly pressuring the Polish Consul General in New York to cancel a scheduled appearance by Judt at a non-profit organization that rents space from the consulate. In an interview with the ''[[New York Sun]]'', Foxman claimed that the group &quot;had nothing to do with the cancellation&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Stoll |first=Ira |authorlink=Ira Stoll |date=October 4, 2006 |title=Poland Abruptly Cancels a Speech By Local Critic of the Jewish State |journal=[[The New York Sun]] |url=http://www.nysun.com/article/40911?page_no=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; insisting that the ADL only called to ask if the event was being sponsored by the Polish government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.adl.org/media_watch/newspapers/20061116-Chronicle+of+Higher+Ed.htm |title=Article on Free Speech and Israel Gets it Wrong |author= |last=Foxman |first=Abraham H. |authorlink=Abraham Foxman |date=November 16, 2006 |publisher=ADL}}&lt;/ref&gt; Polish Consul General Krzysztof Kasprzyk suggested in an interview with ''[[The Washington Post]]'' that calls by the ADL and the American Jewish Committee were &quot;exercising a delicate pressure&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;WP sparks&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Powell |first=Michael |date=October 9, 2006 |title=In N.Y., Sparks Fly Over Israel Criticism |journal=[[The Washington Post]] |pages=A03 |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/10/08/AR2006100800817.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In reference to the role of the ADL and American Jewish Committee in organizing the cancellations, Judt told ''The Washington Post'': &quot;This is serious and frightening, and only in America—not in Israel—is this a problem. These are Jewish organizations that believe they should keep people who disagree with them on the Middle East away from anyone who might listen.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WP sparks&quot; /&gt; The ADL denied the charges. According to Foxman, &quot;I think they made the right decision... He's taken the position that Israel shouldn't exist. That puts him on our radar.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WP sparks&quot; /&gt;

===Denver defamation suit===
According to an April 13, 2001 article in ''[[The Forward]]'', a federal judge &quot;lambasted the organization for labeling a nasty neighborhood feud as an anti-Semitic event&quot; and upheld most of William and Dorothy Quigley's $10 million [[lawsuit]] for [[slander and libel|defamation]].  In 1994, Candace and Mitchell Aronson, Jewish next door neighbors of the Quigleys, contacted the Denver ADL office, reporting overheard cordless phone conversations of the Quigleys discussing putting pictures of oven doors on the Aronsons' home (a reference to the Holocaust), burning the Aronson children and wishing the Aronsons had been killed in a suicide bombing. (The Quigleys later indicated that these remarks had been intended to be humorous.)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishsf.com/content/2-0-/module/displaystory/story_id/13674/edition_id/264/format/html/displaystory.html Jewish News Weekly]&lt;/ref&gt;  The Quigleys and the Aronsons had been engaged in an escalating series of petty disputes prior to this incident. The ADL also labelled the Quigleys as anti-Semites in a press conference which led to felony federal charges being filed against them.
Unknown to many at the time that the Aronsons were taping—including Mr. Thomas—was that Congress had amended federal wiretap law to make it illegal to record conversations on a cordless telephone, to transcribe the material and to use the transcriptions for any purpose.

Without knowing about the change, the Aronsons used the tapes as the basis for a federal civil lawsuit against the Quigleys in December 1994. A day later, Mr. Rosenthal appeared at a news conference with the Aronsons in which he described their encounter with the Quigleys as ''a vicious anti-Semitic campaign,'' based solely on conversations he and associates had with the Aronsons. Later that day, Mr. Rosenthal expanded on his remarks in an interview on a Denver radio talk show.

Two days later, Mr. Thomas used the tapes as the basis for filing criminal charges against the Quigleys.

But after Mr. Thomas learned of the change in the wiretap law and heard on the tapes the context of Mrs. Quigley's remarks, he dropped all charges but one, a misdemeanor traffic violation against Mr. Quigley for the incident in the street. In an open letter released to reporters, Mr. Thomas apologized to the Quigleys, saying he found no evidence that either had engaged in ''anti-Semitic conduct or harassment.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2000/05/13/us/privacy-rights-win-over-bias-charges-in-defamation-case.html?pagewanted=3&amp;src=pm | work=The New York Times | title=Privacy Rights Win Over Bias Charges In Defamation Case | date=May 13, 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New antisemitism controversy===
{{Main|New antisemitism}}
In 1974, ADL national leaders Arnold Forster and Benjamin R. Epstein published a book called ''The New Anti-Semitism'' (New York, 1974), arguing that a new kind of anti-Semitism is on the rise. In 1982, ADL national leader Nathan Perlmutter and his wife, Ruth Ann Perlmutter, released a book entitled ''The Real Anti-Semitism in America'' (New York, 1982). In 2003, ADL's national director Abraham Foxman published ''Never Again? The Threat of the New Anti-Semitism'' (San Francisco, 2003), where on page 4 he states: &quot;We currently face as great a threat to the safety and security of the Jewish people as the one we faced in the 1930s—if not a greater one.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;adl.org&quot; /&gt;

In 2005, [[Norman G. Finkelstein]] published ''[[Beyond Chutzpah: On the Misuse of Anti-Semitism and the Abuse of History]]'' which devotes Part 1 to &quot;The Not-So-New 'New Anti-Semitism'.&quot; In a 2006 appearance on [[Amy Goodman]]'s [[Democracy Now!]], Finkelstein denied there was any evidence for a rise of a new anti-Semitism in either Europe or North America. He continued, &quot;Every time Israel comes under international pressure, as it did recently because of the war crimes committed in Lebanon, it steps up the claim of anti-Semitism, and all of Israel's critics are anti-Semitic.&quot;  According to Finkelstein, the ADL and Foxman, its president, have advanced this &quot;preposterous&quot; deception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.democracynow.org/article.pl?sid=06/08/30/1418200 |title=Congressmember Weiner Gets It Wrong On Palestinian Group He Tried To Bar From U.S. |date=August 30, 2006 |publisher=[[Democracy Now!]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conflict with Jews for the Preservation of Firearms Ownership===
ADL is an advocate for [[gun control]] legislation.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://www.adl.org/civil_rights/platformcommittee-2004.pdf
|title= ADL Presentation to the Platform Committees of the Democratic and Republican National Conventions – June 2004
|accessdate= January 23, 2008
|date=
|year= 2004
|month=
|format=pdf
|work=
|publisher= ADL
|pages=
|language=
|doi=
|quote= The Anti-Defamation League has been an advocate for strong, effective, and sensible gun control legislation.
| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080227040630/http://www.adl.org/civil_rights/platformcommittee-2004.pdf| archivedate= 27 February 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The ADL supported the District of Columbia before the US Supreme Court in ''[[District of Columbia v. Heller]]'' which argued that the city's ban on the possession of handguns and any functional firearms, even for self-defense in the home is not prohibited by the [[Second Amendment to the United States Constitution|Second Amendment]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite press release
|title=ADL To Supreme Court: States Should Regulate Firearms
|publisher=ADL
|date=January 11, 2008
|url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASUS_12/4645_12.htm
|quote=&quot;The League urged the Court to ensure that states retain the ability to keep guns out of the hands of &quot;violent bigots.&quot;&quot;
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The League urged the Court to ensure that states retain the ability to keep guns out of the hands of &quot;violent bigots.&quot;

Gun rights group [[Jews for the Preservation of Firearms Ownership]] (JPFO) has been highly critical of the Anti-Defamation League. In pamphlets such as &quot;Why Does the ADL Support Nazi-Based Laws?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Liberty Crew (September 20, 2007) [http://www.jpfo.org/alerts/alert20070920.htm &quot;Why Does the ADL Support Nazi-Based Laws?&quot;] JPFO.org.&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;JPFO Facts vs. ADL Lies,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Editors (1997–1999) [http://www.jpfo.org/filegen-a-m/jpfacts.htm &quot;JPFO Facts vs. ADL Lies.&quot;] JPFO.org.&lt;/ref&gt; the JPFO has accused the ADL of undermining the welfare of the Jewish people by promoting [[gun control]]. In a 2007 handbill the JPFO accused Director Abraham Foxman of knowingly supporting the &quot;use of Nazi gun control laws in America.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;JPFO editors [http://www.jpfo.org/images02/handbill-adl.jpg &quot;The Anti-Defamation League Is Anti-American.&quot;] JPFO.org.&lt;/ref&gt; Foxman has written about the JPFO: &quot;[[Anti-Semitism]] has a long and painful history, and the linkage to gun control is a tactic by Jews for the Preservation of Firearms Ownership to manipulate the fear of anti-Semitism toward their own end.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Foxman, Abraham H. (May 21, 1995) [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D6123CF932A15756C0A963958260 &quot;N.R.A. Doesn't Represent George Bush or Even Most Members; Jewish Pro-Gun Group.&quot;] ''New York Times.''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Park 51 Community Center controversy===
On July 28, 2010 the ADL issued a statement in which it expressed opposition to the [[Park51]] Community Center, which sponsors planned to build near [[World Trade Center site|Ground Zero]] in New York. The ADL stated, &quot;The controversy which has emerged regarding the building of a Community Center at this location is counterproductive to the healing process. Therefore, under these unique circumstances, we believe the City of New York would be better served if an alternative location could be found.&quot;&lt;ref name =&quot;berk&quot;/&gt; The ADL denounced what it saw as bigoted attacks on the project. Foxman opined that some of those who oppose the [[Mosque at Ground Zero|mosque]] are &quot;bigots&quot;, and that the plan's proponents may have every right to build the mosque at that location. Nevertheless, he appealed to the builders to consider the sensitivities of the victims' families, saying that building the mosque at that site would unnecessarily cause more pain for families of some victims of 9/11.&lt;ref name =&quot;berk&quot;&gt;Jacob Berkman , [http://blogs.jta.org/telegraph/article/2010/07/30/2740283/adl-opposes-world-trade-center-mosque ADL opposes World Trade Center Mosque], [[Jewish Telegraphic Agency]] , July 30, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Jacoby |first=Susan |url=http://newsweek.washingtonpost.com/onfaith/spirited_atheist/2010/08/ground_zero_mosque_protected_by_first_amendment--but_its_still_salt_in_a_wound.html |title=The Spirited Atheist: Ground Zero mosque protected by First Amendment-but it's still salt in a wound|publisher=The Washington Post |date=August 6, 2010 |accessdate=August 6, 2010| archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20100817115334/http://newsweek.washingtonpost.com/onfaith/spirited_atheist/2010/08/ground_zero_mosque_protected_by_first_amendment--but_its_still_salt_in_a_wound.html| archivedate= 17 August 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes6&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/05/opinion/l05mosque.html?_r=1 | work=The New York Times | title=The ADL, the Mosque and the Fight Against Bigotry | date=August 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/PresRele/CvlRt_32/5820_32.htm Statement On Islamic Community Center Near Ground Zero], Anti-Defamation League, July 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

This opposition to the Community Center led to criticism of the statement from various parties, including one ADL board member, the [[American Jewish Committee]], the [[JCRC|Jewish Community Relations Council of New York]], Rabbi [[Irwin Kula]], columnists [[Jeffrey Goldberg]] and [[Peter Beinart]], the [[Interfaith Alliance]],&lt;ref&gt;Adam Dickter, [http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/new_york/wake_adl_jewish_groups_back_ground_zero_mosque In Wake Of ADL, Jewish Groups Back Ground Zero Mosque], [[The Jewish Week]], August 3, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Shalom Center]].&lt;ref&gt;Grace Rauh, [http://manhattan.ny1.com/content/top_stories/123265/jewish-leaders-rally-in-support-of-wtc-mosque/ Jewish Leaders Rally In Support Of WTC Mosque], [[NY1]], August 5, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview with the ''[[New York Times]]'' Abe Foxman published a statement in reaction to criticism.&lt;ref&gt;Abraham H. Foxman, [http://www.adl.org/ADL_Opinions/Interfaith/Mosque_Ground_Zero.htm The Mosque at Ground Zero], originally published in [[Huffington Post]], August 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In protest of ADL’s stance, [[CNN]] host [[Fareed Zakaria]] returned the Hubert H. Humphrey First Amendment Freedoms Prize the ADL awarded him in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2010/US/08/07/new.york.zakaria.adl/ CNN host returns ADL award over stance on Islamic center], [[CNN]], August 9, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  ADL chair Robert G. Sugarman responded to a critical ''[[New York Times]]'' editorial&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/04/opinion/04wed1.html?scp=1&amp;sq=a%20monument%20to%20tolerance&amp;st=cse A Monument to Tolerance], [[New York Times]] editorial, August 3, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; writing, &quot;we have publicly taken on those who criticized the mosque in ways that reflected anti-Muslim bigotry or used the controversy for that purpose&quot; and stating that the ADL has combated [[Islamophobia]].&lt;ref&gt;Robert G. Sugarman, [http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/05/opinion/l05mosque.html?_r=1&amp;adxnnl=1&amp;adxnnlx=1282132985-9m+Y3Rc9pdRKUlCtmrVoxA Letter to New York Times], [[New York Times]], August 4, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Antisemitism in the United States]]
*[[American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee]]
*[[Conference of Presidents of Major American Jewish Organizations]]
*[[Gay &amp; Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation]]
*[[Jewish Council for Public Affairs]]
*[[Israel lobby in the United States]]
*[[Membership discrimination in California social clubs]]
*[[Southern Poverty Law Center]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Antisemitism topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Organized Jewish Life in the United States}}

[[Category:Anti-Defamation League| ]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Jewish political organizations]]
[[Category:Israel–United States relations|Anti-Defamation League]]
[[Category:Zionism]]
[[Category:Anti-racist organizations in the United States]]
[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:Anti-neo-Nazi organizations]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1913]]
[[Category:Jewish organizations based in the United States]]

[[ar:رابطة مكافحة التشهير]]
[[cs:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[da:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[de:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[es:Liga Antidifamación]]
[[fa:اتحادیه ضد افترا]]
[[fr:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[hsb:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[it:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[he:הליגה נגד השמצה]]
[[ja:名誉毀損防止同盟]]
[[no:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[pl:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[ru:Антидиффамационная лига]]
[[tr:İftira ve İnkârla Mücadele Birliği]]
[[fi:Anti-Defamation League]]
[[uk:Антидефамаційна ліга]]
[[yi:עי די על]]
[[zh:反誹謗聯盟]]</text>
      <sha1>lapqevq2j9uvh28gpqyln9t073lcftb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
