<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Apatheism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>722119</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520786581</id>
      <parentid>511178593</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T18:59:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Paine Ellsworth</username>
        <id>9092818</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* No evidence */ add Section parameter to maint. tag</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7935">{{multiple issues|
{{more footnotes|date=April 2012}}
{{ref improve|date=April 2012}}
}}
{{Atheism and Irreligion Sidebar}}
'''Apatheism''' ({{IPAc-en|ˌ|æ|p|ə|ˈ|θ|iː|ɪ|z|əm}} a [[portmanteau]] of ''[[apathy]]'' and ''[[theism]]/[[atheism]]''), also known as '''[[pragmatism|pragmatic]] atheism''' or (critically) as '''practical atheism''', is acting with apathy, disregard, or lack of interest towards belief or disbelief in a [[deity]].  Apatheism describes the ''manner'' of acting towards a belief or lack of a belief in a deity; so applies to both theism and atheism.  An apatheist is also someone who is not interested in accepting or denying any claims that [[gods]] exist or do not exist. In other words, an apatheist is someone who considers the question of the existence of gods as neither meaningful nor relevant to his or her life.

'''Apathetic agnosticism''' (also called '''pragmatic agnosticism''') acknowledges that any amount of debate can neither prove, nor disprove, the existence of one or more deities, and if one or more deities exist, they do not appear to be concerned about the fate of humans. Therefore, their existence has little impact on personal human affairs and should be of little theological interest.

Apatheists hold that if it were possible to prove that God exists, their behavior would not change. Similarly, there would be no change if someone proved that God does not exist.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/apatheism.htm Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance: Apatheism: &quot;Does God exist? I don't know &amp; I don't really care&quot;] B.A. Robinson&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Historically, practical atheism was considered by some people to be associated with moral failure, willful ignorance, and impiety. Those considered practical atheists were said to behave as though God, ethics, and social responsibility did not exist; they abandoned duty and embraced [[hedonism]]. According to the French Catholic philosopher [[Étienne Borne]], &quot;Practical atheism is not the denial of the existence of God, but complete godlessness of action; it is a moral evil, implying not the denial of the absolute validity of the moral law but simply rebellion against that law.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Borne|first=Étienne|title=Atheism|year=1961|publisher=New York: Hawthorn Books|isbn=0-415-04727-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 21st century, pragmatic atheism has been seen in a more positive light. The journalist [[Jonathan Rauch]] believes that &quot;apatheism is to be celebrated as nothing less than a major civilizational advance. Religion, as countless acts of violence in the name of God have underscored, remains the most divisive and volatile of social forces... Apatheism, therefore, should not be assumed to represent a lazy recumbency... Just the opposite: it is the product of a determined cultural effort to discipline the religious mindset, and often of an equally determined personal effort to master the spiritual passions. It is not a lapse. It is an achievement.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Rauch, Jonathan, ''Let It Be: Three Cheers for Apatheism'', ''[[The Atlantic Monthly]]'', May 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of apatheism==
An apatheist may justify their decision using one of these perspectives, or they may combine all of the below to create their own attitude towards faith.

=== Absence of religious motivation ===
This apatheistic argument states that morals are present in human society and do not rely on religion to be a part of the human experience. Apatheists recognize that religion may provide a &quot;comfort&quot; for many people around the world, but apatheists do not need religion to be content with the morality of their lives and therefore live without it{{citation needed|date= July 2012}}. This is known as &quot;moral apatheism&quot;.

=== Indifference ===
Indifference is better known as [[indifferentism]], the belief that all religions are equal in value. Use of indifferentism in this context was popularized by [[Immanuel Kant|Kant]] in his ''[[Critique of Pure Reason]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees&quot;&gt;Rees, D.A. (1954) [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2182293 &quot;Kant, Bayle and Indifferentism,&quot;] ''The Philosophical Review,'' 63(4)&lt;/ref&gt; Kant argues that indifferentism represents an extreme form of [[skepticism]] that argues that there is no rational ground for accepting any philosophical position.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees&quot;/&gt;  According to the Catholic Church, this type of absolute indifferentism results in a willingness to concede any position.{{citation needed|date=November 2010}}  It is often associated with [[moral relativism]].

The Catholic Church ascribes indifferentism to all [[atheism|atheistic]], [[materialism|materialistic]], [[pantheism|pantheistic]], and [[agnosticism|agnostic]] philosophies, as well as [[religious pluralism|religious pluralist]] philosophy, such as that espoused by [[Jean-Jacques Rousseau|Rousseau]].&lt;ref&gt;Fox, J. (1910) [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07759a.htm &quot;Religious Indifferentism,&quot;] The Catholic Encyclopedia.&lt;/ref&gt;

Indifference is the perspective exemplified by the following statement: &quot;Since the existence of God can never be proven, nor can it be disproven, I won't waste my time asking questions to which there are no answers.&quot;{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}

=== No evidence ===
{{Citations missing|section|date= July 2012}}
This argument takes a more scientific perspective, criticizing blind faith (faith without logical evidence to support it).  It argues that if a deity or deities truly wanted people to believe in them, then said deity or deities could demonstrate their existence with miracles, and explain their plan(s) for humanity or the lack thereof.  Being [[omnipotent|all-powerful]], if they truly wanted humans to believe, they could send a [[divine providence|divine sign]] not left up to interpretation.  Since they do not seem to care if humans believe or not, apatheists will not care until they show them a reason to, and perhaps not even if such an event occurred{{citation needed|date= July 2012}}. (This is in essence the [[argument from nonbelief]].)

==Quotes==
The eighteenth century [[France|French]] philosopher [[Denis Diderot]], when accused of being an atheist, replied that he simply did not care whether God existed or not. In response to [[Voltaire]], he wrote that &quot;It is very important not to mistake [[Conium|hemlock]] for [[parsley]]; but not at all so to believe or not in God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Herrick |first=Jim |title=Against the Faith |year=1985 |pages=75 |location=London |publisher=Glover &amp; Blair |isbn=0-906681-09-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jonathan Rauch]] described apatheism as &quot;a disinclination to care all that much about one's own religion, and an even stronger disinclination to care about other people's&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Rauch, Jonathan, ''[http://www.jonathanrauch.com/jrauch_articles/apatheism_beyond_religion/index.html Let It Be: Three Cheers for Apatheism]'', ''[[The Atlantic Monthly]]'', May 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Agnosticism]]
*[[Cosmicism#.22Cosmic_indifference.22|Cosmic indifference]]
*[[Ignosticism]]
*[[Indifferentism]]
*[[God in Buddhism]]
*[[Nontheism]]
*[[Postchristianity]]
*[[Post-theism]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.hermetic.com/dionysos/apatheist.htm Apatheism, Allognosticism, and the American Religious Landscape.]
*[http://atheism.about.com/library/glossary/general/bldef_apatheist.htm Apatheism defined on Atheism.about.com]
*[http://www.abc.net.au/newsradio/txt/s1620158.htm  ABC New Radio:wordwatch, Apatheism]
*[http://apatheticagnostic.org/ Apathetic Agnostics]

{{irreligion}}
{{Belief systems}}

[[Category:Secularism]]
[[Category:Pragmatism]]
[[Category:Nontheism]]

[[ca:Agnosticisme apàtic]]
[[es:Apateísmo]]
[[fa:اپاتئیسم]]
[[id:Apateisme]]
[[ia:Apatheismo]]
[[it:Apateismo]]
[[lt:Pragmatinis ateizmas]]
[[nl:Apatheïsme]]
[[no:Apateisme]]
[[pl:Apateizm]]
[[pt:Apateísmo]]
[[ru:Апатеизм]]
[[sl:Apateizem]]
[[fi:Apateismi]]
[[sv:Apateism]]
[[zh:远神论]]</text>
      <sha1>943g6wlaoa78avfugu394o5jrtht9vh</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
