<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Apocatastasis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>405839</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510971153</id>
      <parentid>499383179</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-05T20:58:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>R'n'B</username>
        <id>2300502</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Disambiguated: [[Axiochus]] → [[Axiochus (dialogue)]], [[Kingdom of Israel]] → [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34603">{{universalism}}
'''Apocatastasis''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|æ|p|oʊ|k|ə|ˈ|t|æ|s|t|ə|s|ɨ|s}}; from {{lang-el|ἀποκατάστασις}}, also anglicized as '''apokatastasis''') is reconstitution, restitution,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eliyah.com/cgi-bin/strongs.cgi?file=greeklexicon&amp;isindex=apokatastasis Strong's Greek Lexicon] retrieved September 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; or restoration to the original or primordial condition.&lt;ref&gt;Faith-based Radicalism: Christianity, Islam and Judaism, p. 59, Christiane Timmerman, 2007: &quot;The usual view taken of Peter's use of the ''apokatastasis'' of &quot;all things&quot; is that it refers to the restoration of the Kingdom of Israel and/or the Garden of Eden and not &quot;all things that ever existed&quot;.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology and definition==
The [[LSJ|Liddell and Scott Lexicon]] entry (with expansion of definitions and references), gives the following examples of usage:
:'''ἀποκατάστᾰσις''' , εως, ἡ, restoration, re-establishment;
:* “τοῦ ἐνδεοῦς” [[Aristotle]] ''[[Magna Moralia|MM]]'', 1205a4; into its nature εἰς φύσιν id. 1204b 36, 1205b 11;
:* return to a position, [[Epicurus]], ''Epistolae'', 1, p.8 U.;
:* especially of military formations, reversal of a movement, [[Asclepiodotus (philosopher)|Asclepiodotus]], ''Tacticus'', 10.1, 10:6, etc.; :generally
:* of all things “πάντων” ''[[Acts of the Apostles|Acts]]'', 3.21;
:* of souls, [[Proclus Philosophus|Proclus]], ''Institutio Theologica'', 199.
:* of the body back into its old form “τῆς φύσιος ἐς τὸ ἀρχαῖον” [[Aretaeus Medicus]] CD 1.5;  recovery from sickness, SA 1.10;
:* “τῶν ὁμήρων εἰς τὰς πατρίδας” [[Polybius]] 3.99.6;  εἰς ἀ. ἐλθεῖν, into the restoration of the affairs of a city, 4.23.1;
:Astrological uses:
:* ἀ. ἄστρων return of the stars to the same place in the heavens as in the former year, [[Plutarch]] 2.937f, [[Diodorus Siculus]] 12.36, etc.;
:* periodic return of the cosmic cycle, [[Stoicorum Veterum Fragmenta]] 2.184,190;
:* of a planet, return to a place in the heavens occupied at a former epoch, [[Antiochus Atheniensis Astrologus]] ap. Cat.Cod.Astr. 7.120,121; but, zodiacal revolution, [[Paulus Alexandrinus Astrologus]] Paul.Al.T.1; opposite: '''antapocatastasis''' ἀνταπ. (q. v.), [[Dorotheus Astrologus]] Doroth. ap. Cat.Cod.Astr.2.196.9;
:* restoration of sun and moon after eclipse, [[Plato]] ''[[Axiochus (dialogue)|Axiochus]]''370b.

The word is reasonably common in [[papyri]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/wordfreq?lang=greek&amp;lookup=a%29pokata%2Fstasis Perseus database entries for ''apokatastasis''] listing as follows:
1 [[Friedrich Preisigke]], ''Sammelbuch griechischer Urkunden aus Aegypten'';
7 P.Oxy., The [[Oxyrhynchus Papyri]];
7 [[Polybius]], Histories;
2 [[Flavius Josephus]], [[Antiquities of the Jews]];
2 [[Diodorus Siculus]], Library;
3 Stud.Pal., [[Studien zur Palaeographie und Papyruskunde]];
1 Acts 3:21 [[New Testament]];
1 [[PSI, Papiri greci e latini]];
1 [[Diogenes Laertius]], [[Lives of Eminent Philosophers]];
2 P.Cair.Masp., ''Papyrus grecs d'époque byzantine'', Catalogue général des antiquités égyptiennes du Musée du Caire;
3 P.Ryl, [[Rylands Papyri]];
1 P.Col., [[Columbia Papyri]];
2 P.Flor., Papiri greco-egizii, [[Papiri Fiorentini]];
3 [[Aretaeus]], The Extant Works of Aretaeus, The Cappadocian.;
1 [[UPZ, Urkunden der Ptolemäerzeit]] (ältere Funde);
1 P.Ross.Georg., Papyri russischer und georgischer Sammlungen;
1 P.Cair.Isid., The [[Archive of Aurelius Isidorus]] in the Egyptian Museum, Cairo, and the University of Michigan;
1 P.Abinn., The [[Abinnaeus Archive]]: Papers of a Roman Officer in the Reign of Constantius II;
1 Pap.Choix, Choix de papyrus grecs: Essai de traitement automatique;
1 P.Athen.Xyla, P.Sta.Xyla: The Byzantine Papyri of the Greek Papyrological Society,;
1 O.Joach., Die Prinz-Joachim-Ostraka&lt;/ref&gt;

==Concepts==
===Stoicism===
According to Edward Moore of St. Elias School of Orthodox Theology, Nebraska, ''Apokatastasis'' was first properly conceptualized in early [[Stoicism|Stoic thought]], particularly by [[Chrysippus]] whose thinking was influenced by the theory of recurrence and cosmic cycles in Babylonian astronomical thought. The return (''apokatastasis'') of the planets and stars to their proper ''celestial signs'', namely their original positions, would spark a conflagration of the universe (''[[ekpyrosis]]''). The original position was believed to consist of an alignment of celestial bodies with [[Cancer (astrology)|Cancer]].  Thereafter, from fire, rebirth would commence, and this cycle of alternate destruction and recreation was correlated with a divine  [[Logos]]. ''Antapocatastasis'' is a counter-recurrence when the stars and planets align with [[Capricorn (astrology)|Capricorn]], which would mark destruction by a universal flood.&lt;ref&gt;Edward Moore, ''Origen of Alexandria and St. Maximus the Confessor'', Universal-Publishers, 2005 pp.25-27.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Origen of Alexandria]] correlated the Stoic's concept of the rebirth and reconstruction of the cosmos with the active guidance and sustenance of the Logos, which is taken to be an emanation of Zeus, when Zeus turns his thoughts outwards once more.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/o/origen.htm Origen of Alexandria (185-254). The Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy.] Retrieved September 20, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In Origen's understanding, in [[Stoicism|Stoic]] philosophy, the [[cosmos]] is a physical expression of [[Zeus]]' perfect thoughts and ''apocatastasis'' is the contraction when Zeus returns to self-contemplation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first1=Edward |last1=Moore |month=January |year=2003 |title=Origen of Alexandria and apokatastasis: Some Notes on the Development of a Noble Notion |journal=Quodlibet Journal |volume=5 |issue=1 |issn=1526-6575 |url=http://www.quodlibet.net/articles/moore-origen.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Leibniz]] explored both Stoic and his understanding of Origen's philosophy in two essays written shortly before his death, ''Apokatastasis'' and ''Apokatastasis panton'' (1715).&lt;ref&gt;Allison Coudert ''Leibniz and the Kabbalah'' p110 1995 &quot;Having initially accepted the idea of apocatastasis in the pre-Origen and primarily Stoic sense that this world and everything in it was bound to return again and again in endless cycles of repetition, Leibniz came to embrace Origen's wholly..&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Judaism===
The concept of &quot;restore&quot; or &quot;return&quot; in the [[Hebrew Bible]] is the common Hebrew verb ''שׁוּב'' (''shuwb/shuv''),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blueletterbible.org/lang/lexicon/lexicon.cfm?Strongs=H7725&amp;t=KJV ''shuwb'', lexicon and Bible usage]&lt;/ref&gt; as used in Malachi 4:2, the only use of the verb form of apocatastasis in the Septuagint. This is used in the &quot;restoring&quot; of the fortunes of Job, and is also used in the sense of rescue or return of captives, and in the restoration of Jerusalem.

This is similar to the concept of [[tikkun olam]] in [[Hasidic Judaism|hassidic]] [[Judaism]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Löwy, ''Redemption and utopia: Jewish libertarian thought in Central Europe : a study in elective affinity,'' Stanford University Press, 1992 p.64.&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Testament===
The word, ''apokatastasis'', only appears once in the Bible in Acts 3:21.&lt;ref&gt;Greek: ὃν δεῖ οὐρανὸν μὲν δέξασθαι ἄχρι χρόνων ''ἀποκαταστάσεως'' πάντων ὧν ἐλάλησεν ὁ θεὸς διὰ στόματος τῶν ἁγίων ἀπ᾿ αἰῶνος αὐτοῦ προφητῶν. Vulgate: ''quem oportet caelum quidem suscipere usque in tempora restitutionis omnium quae locutus est Deus per os sanctorum suorum a saeculo prophetarum''&lt;/ref&gt; Peter heals a handicapped beggar and then addresses the astonished onlookers. His sermon sets Jesus in the Jewish context, the fulfiller of the [[Covenant (biblical)|Abrahamic Covenant]], and says:
:&quot;[Jesus] whom heaven must receive until the time for restoring (''apocatastasis'') all the things about which God spoke by the mouth of his holy prophets long ago&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;English Standard Version {{bibleverse||Acts|3:21|ESV}}&lt;/ref&gt; or in a less literal translation:
:&quot;He [Jesus] must remain in heaven until the time comes for God to restore (''apocatastasis'') everything, as he promised long ago through his holy prophets.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;New International Version {{bibleverse||Acts|3:21|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both these translations use &quot;time&quot; (singular) to translate &quot;χρόνων&quot; (&quot;of times&quot;).  A strictly literal translation of the whole verse is:
:&quot;whom it behoveth heaven, indeed, to receive till times of a restitution of all things, of which God spake through the mouth of all His holy prophets from the age.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Young's Literal Translation {{bibleverse||Acts|3:21|YLT}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Grammatically, the [[relative pronoun]] &quot;ὧν&quot; (&quot;of which&quot;, [[Ancient Greek grammar|genitive plural]]), could refer to &quot;χρόνων&quot; (&quot;of times&quot;), in which case the central phrase would mean &quot;till a restitution of all times of which God spake&quot;, or to &quot;πάντων&quot; (&quot;of all&quot; or &quot;of all things&quot;), meaning &quot;till times of a restitution of all things of which God spake&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Darrell L. Bock ''Acts'' 2007 &quot;The relative pronoun ὧν (''hon'', of which) could refer back to &quot;the seasons&quot; of which God spoke (Bauernfeind 1980: 69) or to &quot;all things&quot; of which God spoke (so Conzelmann 1987: 29; Barrett 1994: 206, nearest referent).&lt;/ref&gt; The examples given show that the phrase is usually understood, seeing &quot;all (things) of which God spoke&quot; as the nearest [[referent]], to speak of a restitution of all things of which God spoke, not of all times of which God spoke.

The usual view taken of Peter's use of the &quot;''apokatastasis'' of all the things about which God spoke&quot; is that it refers to the restoration of the [[Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)|Kingdom of Israel]] and/or the [[Garden of Eden]] and not &quot;all things that ever existed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Fitzmeyer ''The Acts of the Apostles,'' (The Anchor Yale Bible Commentaries) pp.283-293&lt;/ref&gt;

The verbal form of ''apokatastasis'' is found in the [[Septuagint]] [[Malachi]] 3:23LXX (i.e. {{bibleverse||Malachi|4:6|ESV}}), a prophecy of [[Elijah]] ''turning back'' the hearts of the children to their fathers; in {{bibleverse||Matthew|17:11|ESV}} (&quot;he will ''restore'' all things&quot;), echoing Malachi, and in {{bibleverse||Hebrews|13:19}} (&quot;that I may be ''restored'' to you the sooner&quot;).

Shortly before the phrase in Acts 3:21 comes, in {{Bibleverse||Acts|3:19b|NIV}} or {{Bibleverse-nb||Acts|3:20a|ESV}},&lt;ref&gt;The [[Textus Receptus]] divides the verses ''after'' this phrase, a division that is followed by the [[King James Version]] and several other translations in various languages.&lt;/ref&gt; the similar phrase, &quot;times of refreshing&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;ὅπως ἂν ἔλθωσιν καιροὶ ἀναψύξεως ἀπὸ προσώπου τοῦ κυρίου; Latin [[Vulgate]]: ''ut cum venerint tempora refrigerii a conspectu Domini''&lt;/ref&gt; Nineteenth-century &quot;Eckermann interprets the 'apocatastasis of all things' to mean the universal emendation of religion by the doctrine of Christ, and the 'times of refreshing' to be the day of renewal, the times of the Messiah.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cyclopaedia of Biblical, theological, and ecclesiastical literature: John McClintock, James Strong - 1883&lt;/ref&gt;

===Patristic Christianity===
The significance of ''apocatastasis'' in early Christianity is today being re-evaluated. In particular it is now questioned whether [[Origen]], often listed as the most notable advocate of [[universal salvation]] did in fact teach or believe in such a doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;Crouzel, Henri ''Origen'' 1990, p. 285&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Root J. R. “Universalism,” in EDT, ed. WA Elwell, 2nd ed.  Grand Rapids: Baker, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/Journey-Back-God-Problem-Academy/dp/0199841144/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1340675842&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=Journey+Back+to+God Scott, Mark. ''Journey Back to God: Origen on the Problem of Evil''. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2012]&lt;/ref&gt;

Frederick W. Norris, in his article &quot;Apokatastasis&quot; in ''The Westminster Handbook to Origen'' (2004), states that the positions that Origen takes on the issue of universal salvation have often seemed to be contradictory. &quot;In scattered places Origen says quite clearly that he thinks all created intelligence will be restored to God at the end of time. In other places he says, equally clearly, that only souls who make the choice for God and practice the virtues God demands will come to rest in heaven. Those who do not live for God shall suffer eternally in hell or perhaps be annihilated there. If in coming years Origen's treatise on the resurrection is rediscovered, this apparent contradiction may be settled.&quot;  He concludes: &quot;One could not know in advance which audience would be most likely to accept the gospel, because of the hope engendered by God's overpowering love or because of the fear stimulated by God's threat of hell coupled with God's demand for ethical living. Most audiences of hearers or readers include both groups; knowing this, Origen the pastoral preacher probably kept his view of salvation economically 'open' for a greater effectiveness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=riEdrWEDFq0C&amp;pg=PA59&amp;dq=Westminster+handbook+origen+apokatastasis&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Ft95Tdr8JcqnhAe3ypjhBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false John Anthony McGuckin (editor), ''The Westminster Handbook to Origen'' (Westminster John Knox Press 2004 ISBN 978-0-664-22472-1), article &quot;Apokatastasis&quot;, pp. 59-62;] see also Elisabeth Dively Lauro in the article on [[Universalism]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bruce Demarest, “on apokatastasis”, The Evangelical Dictionary of Theology, p. 67. TP.&lt;/ref&gt;

Konstantinovsky (2009)&lt;ref&gt;Konstantinovsky  ''Evagrius Ponticus: the making of a gnostic'' 2009 p171&lt;/ref&gt; states that the uses of ''apocatastasis'' in Christian writings prior to the [[Synod of Constantinople (543)]] and the [[anathema]] (553) pronounced against &quot;[[Origenist]]s&quot; and [[Evagrius Ponticus]] were neutral and referred primarily to concepts similar to the general &quot;restoration of all things spoken&quot; (''restitutio omnium quae locutus est Deus'') of Peter in Acts 3:21 and not for example the [[universal reconciliation]] of all souls which had ever been. The term ''apocatastasis'' is not mentioned in the 553 anathema.

A form of ''apocatastasis'' was also attributed to [[Gregory of Nyssa]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Morwenna |last=Ludlow |chapter=Patristic Eschatology |chapterurl=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=U32mir3alW8C&amp;pg=PA30 |title=Universal salvation: eschatology in the thought of Gregory of Nyssa and Karl Rahner |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=2000 |pages=30–7 |isbn=978-0-19-827022-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; and possibly the [[Ambrosiaster]], attributed to [[Ambrose of Milan]]. [[Gregory of Nazianzus]] discussed it without reaching a decision.

A local [[Synod of Constantinople (543)]] condemned a form of apocatastasis as being [[Anathema]], and the Anathema was formally submitted to the [[Second Council of Constantinople|Fifth Ecumenical Council of Constantinople]] (553). Since ''apocatastasis'' had been used earlier in writers commenting on Peter's use in the New Testament, the form of ''apocatastasis'' condemned in 543 and 553 was a later development.&lt;!-- BUT WHAT EXACTLY refs needed--&gt;

[[Origen of Alexandria]]'s other teachings about the possibility of glorified man falling again also played a role in that condemnation.&lt;ref name=&quot;origen&quot;/&gt; In fact, most historians today would recognize a distinction between Origen's own teachings (or at least those that have survived) and the theological positions of later &quot;Origenists&quot;. Even beliefs long attributed to Origen himself, such as a Platonic version of souls existing before bodies, the possibility of a second fall, are found to be much more nuanced and difficult to pin down in Origen's own writings. The Anathema against apocatastasis, or more accurately, against the belief that hell is not eternal, was not ratified despite support from the Emperor, and it is absent from the Anathemas spoken against Origen at Constantinople II.{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}}

The [[Alexandrian school]] adapted Platonic terminology and ideas to Christianity while explaining and differentiating the new faith from all the others.&lt;ref name=&quot;origen&quot;&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11306b.htm Catholic Encyclopedia, Origin of Alexandria] retrieved September 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04045a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia, Clement of Alexandria] retrieved September 22, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Proponents cited [[Bible|Biblical]] passage in [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20cor.%2015:28;&amp;version=31; ''1 Corinthians 15:28''] (&quot;When he has done this, then the Son himself will be made subject to him who put everything under him, so that God may be all in all.&quot;) in support.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

===Gnosticism===
The [[gnostic]] [[Gospel of Philip]] ''180-350c'' contains the term itself but does not teach universal reconciliation:
::&quot;There is a rebirth and an image of rebirth. It is certainly necessary to be born again through the image. Which one? Resurrection. The image must rise again through the image. The bridal chamber and the image must enter through the image into the truth: this is the restoration (apokatastasis). Not only must those who produce the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, do so, but have produced them for you. If one does not acquire them, the name (&quot;Christian&quot;) will also be taken from him.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnosis.org/naghamm/gop.html Gospel of Philip]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Meaning of apocatastasis in Christian theology==
===Early Christianity===

[[Clement of Alexandria]] (c.150 - c. 215) generally uses the term ''apokatastasis'' to refer to the &quot;restoration&quot; of the &quot;gnostic&quot; Christians, rather than that of the universe or of all Christians, but with universal implications.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew C. Itter ''Esoteric teaching in the Stromateis of Clement of Alexandria'' 2009 p200 &quot;Clement uses the term ''apokatastasis'' and its cognates generally to refer to the gnostic elect rather than to an eschatological restoration of the universe, or to a restoration of the faithful as a whole. Where he does mention or imply a restoration of the whole it is through the medium of the restoration of the gnostic. ... Hence, while some uses of ''apokatastasis'' appear to refer simply to the gnostic elect, by extension, they have universal implications.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

As indicated above, the position of [[Origen]] (186-284) is disputed, with works as recent as the New Westminster Dictionary of Church History presenting him as speculating that the apocatastasis would involve universal salvation.&lt;ref name=NWDCH/&gt;

In early Christian theological usage ''apocatastasis'' meant the ultimate restoration of all things to their original state, which early exponents believed would still entail a purgatorial state,&lt;ref&gt;Robert Benedetto, James O. Duke ''The new Westminster dictionary of church history'' Vol.1 2008 p37 &quot;Though often equated with universalism (the salvation of all beings), early exponents couched the ''apokatastasis'' in God's eschatological victory over evil, which would still entail a purgatorial state.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Both [[Origen]] and [[Gregory of Nyssa]] hoped that all creatures would be saved.&lt;ref name=NWDCH&gt;Robert Benedetto, James O. Duke ''The new Westminster dictionary of church history'' Vol.1 2008 p37 &quot;Origen (186-284) theorized the ''apokatastasis'' as a recovery of the prehistoric ''stasis'', or rest, enjoyed by spiritual creatures before their fall and embodiment. ... Gregory of Nyssa (335-395) shared Origen's hope of all creatures being saved but argued that the final restoration would be a return not to a prehistorical unity but to that ultimate perfection that God originally projected for humanity&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; The word was still very flexible at that time, but in the mid-6th century it became virtually a technical term referring, as usually today, to a specifically Origenistic doctrine of universal salvation.&lt;ref name=ML&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=D_U1887kuFgC&amp;pg=PA38&amp;dq=apocatastasis+universalism&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=jxB1TdCuEsKqhAfjutxK&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwBzgo#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Morwenna Ludlow, ''Universal Salvation: Eschatology in the Thought of Gregory of Nyssa and Karl Rahner'' (Oxford University Press 2001 ISBN 978-0-19-827022-5), p. 38]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Maximus the Confessor]] outlined God's plan for &quot;universal&quot; salvation alongside warnings of everlasting punishment for the wicked.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Benedetto, James O. Duke ''The new Westminster dictionary of church history'' Vol.1 2008 p37 &quot;To the extent that Gregory of Nyssa heavily modified the notion of apokatastasis, while Maximus the Confessor (580–662) later outlined the divine plan for universal salvation alongside warnings of everlasting punishment for the wicked&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Luther===
The Vulgate translation of ''apokatastasis'', &quot;in tempora restitutionis omnium quae locutus est Deus&quot; (the restitution of all things of which God has spoken) was taken up by Luther to mean the day of the restitution of the creation, but in Luther's theology the day of restitution was also the day of resurrection and judgment, not the restitution of the wicked.&lt;ref&gt;Luther ''Exegetica opera latina'' Elsperger - 1861 p432 &quot;Si autem Pater est futurus perpetuo, ergo semper manet pater, semper generat filios usque ad diem illum restitutionis omnium,&quot; etc.&lt;/ref&gt; In Luther's Bible he rendered Greek ''apokatastasis'' with German ''herwiedergebracht werde'', &quot;will be brought back.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;welcher mus den Himel einnemen bis auff die zeit da er wider bracht werde alles was Gott geredt hat durch den mund aller seiner heiligen Propheten von der Welt an&quot; ([http://lutherbibel.net/ Luther (1545), ''Die gantze Heilige Schrifft: Deudsch''), modernized as: &quot;welcher muss den Himmel einnehmen bis auf die Zeit, da herwiedergebracht werde alles, was Gott geredet hat durch den Mund aller seiner heiligen Propheten von der Welt an&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; This sense continued to be used in Lutheran sermons.&lt;ref&gt;Wilhelm Beste ''Die bedeutendsten Kanzelredner'' 1886 &quot;Der Herr Matthesius hat drei Stunden vor seinem seligen Abschiede eine ganze Predigt von diesem Wort gethan. Gottlob, der jüngste Tag ist dies restitutionis omnium. Da wird uns der Herr Jesus Alles wieder an die Seite setzen,..&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Luther explicitly disowned belief that the devils would ultimately reach blessedness.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Denn ichs (=ich es) nicht halte mit denen, so da lehren, daß die Teufel auch werden endlich zur Seligkeit kommen&quot; (Vom Abendmahl Christi Bekenntnis, in [http://books.google.com/books?id=NQIRAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA372&amp;dq=%22Denn+ichs+nicht+halte+mit+denen,+so+da+lehren,+da%C3%9F+die+Teufel+auch+werden+endlich+zur+Seligkeit+kommen%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=6f55Tcy-JIPJhAfY26z1Bg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCcQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Denn%20ichs%20nicht%20halte%20mit%20denen%2C%20so%20da%20lehren%2C%20da%C3%9F%20die%20Teufel%20auch%20werden%20endlich%20zur%20Seligkeit%20kommen%22&amp;f=false ''Dr. Martin Luther's sämmtliche Werke'', Volume 30, p. 372]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;According to Mark Ellingsen, Luther in a letter to Rechenberg &quot;held out the hope of universal salvation&quot; for human beings ([http://books.google.com/books?id=SodSn6hgHnIC&amp;pg=PA58&amp;dq=luther+%22universal+salvation%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ShB6TefYBZGwhAfSuOD-Bg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=luther%20%22universal%20salvation%22&amp;f=false Mark Ellingsen, ''Reclaiming Our Roots'' (Continuum International 2000 ISBN 978-1-56338-292-5), p. 58]).&lt;/ref&gt;

===19th-century Universalism===
During the 19th and early 20th centuries several histories published by [[Universalist]]s, including [[Hosea Ballou]] (1829), [[Thomas Whittemore (Universalist)|Thomas Whittemore]] (1830), [[John Wesley Hanson]] (1899) and [[George T. Knight (Universalist)|George T. Knight]] (1911), argued that belief in universal reconciliation was found in [[early Christianity]] and in the [[Reformation]], and ascribed Universalist beliefs to Origen, Clement of Alexandria, and others.

===Recent works===
In recent writing, apocatastasis is generally understood as involving some form of [[universal reconciliation]], without necessarily attributing this understanding to Origen and other Fathers of the Church.
* Augustin Gretillat, in his ''Exposé de théologie systématique'' (1892), described ''apocatastasis'' as universal reconciliation.
* Heinrich Adolf Köstlin, in the &quot;Realencyklopädie für protestantische Theologie&quot; (Leipzig, 1896), I, 617, article &quot;Apokatastasis&quot;, translated in the [[Schaff-Herzog Encyclopedia of Religious Knowledge]], described ''apocatastasis'' as universal reconciliation.
* [[Pierre Batiffol]], as translated in the article &quot;Apocatastasis&quot; in the old [[Catholic Encyclopedia]] (1911), defined apocatastasis as &quot;a name given in the history of theology to the doctrine which teaches that a time will come when all free creatures shall share in the grace of salvation; in a special way, the devils and lost souls.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://oce.catholic.com/index.php?title=Apocatastasis ''Catholic Encyclopedia'', art. &quot;Apocatastasis&quot;, vol. I, pp. 599-600]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maurice Arthur Canney (1921) stated that &quot;Apocatastasis became a theological term denoting the doctrine ... that all men would be converted and admitted to everlasting happiness&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=FRoMAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=apocatastasis&amp;dq=apocatastasis&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=JMdoTaXtEJGzhAfNtNTsDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwBTigAQ Maurice Arthur Canney, ''An Encyclopaedia of Religions'' (Routledge 1921), p. 28).&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Albrecht Oepke (1933) wrote in his article ''Apokatastasis'' in [[Kittel]]'s ''Theological Dictionary of the New Testament'' (the first three volumes of which were published between 1933 and 1938) that &quot;Apokatastasis cannot denote the conversion of persons but only the reconstitution or establishment of things.&quot;
* Professor [[Constantinos Patrides|Constantinos A. Patrides]] surveyed the history of apocatastasis in his ''Salvation of Satan''.&lt;ref name=&quot;CAP&quot; &gt;{{cite journal |title=The salvation of Satan|first=C.&amp;nbsp;A.|last=Patrides|authorlink=Constantinos Patrides|journal=Journal of the History of Ideas|volume=28|number=4|month=October–December|year=1967|pages=467–478|jstor=2708524|ref=harv}} reprinted in {{cite book |chapter='A principle of infinite love': The salvation of Satan|title=Premises and motifs in Renaissance literature|first=C. A.|last=Patrides|authorlink=Constantinos Patrides|origyear=1967|year=1982|pages=|jstor=2708524|ref=harv|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, New Jersey}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*G. C. Berkouwer, in ''The Return of Christ'' (1972) devoted a whole chapter, under the heading &quot;Apocatastasis?&quot;, to the topic of universal reconciliation, &quot;sometimes technically known as apocatastasis&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=8FWcNG5U4t8C&amp;pg=PA402&amp;dq=apocatastasis&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=gL1oTd_LAo6xhAe1sM2fDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=apocatastasis&amp;f=false G. C. Berkouwer, ''The Return of Christ'' (Eerdmans 1972 ISBN 978-0-8028-4812-3), chapter 13 (pp. 387-423)]&lt;/ref&gt;
*John Meyendorff, in ''Byzantine Theology: Historical Trends and Doctrinal Themes'' (1987) explained the doctrine of ''apocatastasis'' as &quot;the idea that the whole of creation and all of humanity will ultimately be 'restored' to their original state of bliss.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=GoVeDXMvY-8C&amp;pg=PA222&amp;dq=apocatastasis&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=3cNoTbmRIs6YhQfBlJXtDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEgQ6AEwBjha#v=onepage&amp;q=apocatastasis&amp;f=false John Meyendorff, ''Byzantine Theology: Historical Trends and Doctrinal Themes'' (Fordham University Press 1987 ISBN 978-0-8232-0967-5), p. 222).]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Michael McGarry, in ''A Dictionary of the Jewish-Christian Dialogue'' (1995), explains apocatastasis as &quot;one particular Christian expression of a general theology of universalism ... the belief that at the end of time all creatures – believers and sinners alike – would be restored in Christ.&quot;&lt;ref name=DJCD&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=GsDNhImlaXgC&amp;pg=PA229&amp;dq=apocatastasis&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=aMFoTZfWKY-KhQeK0fWhDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwATg8#v=onepage&amp;q=apocatastasis&amp;f=false Leon Klenicki, Geoffrey Wigoder, ''A Dictionary of the Jewish-Christian Dialogue'' (Stimulus Foundation 1995 ISBN 0-8091-3582-5), p. 228]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Peter Stravinskas, in the short article on apocatastasis in ''Our Sunday Visitor's Catholic Encyclopedia'' (1998)&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=vJ78Vd4O9d4C&amp;pg=PA86&amp;dq=apocatastasis+universalism&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=NhZ1Tav3FOiqhAfutqQw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CFAQ6AEwCTg8#v=onepage&amp;q=apocatastasis%20universalism&amp;f=false Peter M. J. Stravinskas, ''Our Sunday Visitor's Catholic Encyclopedia'' (Our Sunday Visitor Publishing Division 1998 ISBN 0-87973-669-0), p. 86).]&lt;/ref&gt; and the still shorter entry in his ''Catholic Dictionary'' (1993),&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=7fSv9cV0M18C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Stravinskas+Catholic+Dictionary&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ITB7TeilAoKKhQeAiIHzBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=apocatastasis&amp;f=false Peter M. J. Stravinskas, ''Catholic Dictionary'' (Our Sunday Visitor Publishing Division 1993 ISBN 0-87973-390-X), p. 76]&lt;/ref&gt; defines it as the belief &quot;that all rational creatures are saved, including the fallen angels and unrepentant sinners&quot;.
* ''A Concise Dictionary of Theology'' (2000) describes apocatastasis as &quot;a theory ... that all angels and human beings, even the demons and the damned, will ultimately be saved&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=jQooODXx-2wC&amp;pg=PA183&amp;dq=apocatastasis&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=zONoTfK5OYOxhQf16NTsDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAThQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22universal%20restoration%22&amp;f=false Gerald O'Collins, Edward G. Farrugia, ''A Concise Dictionary of Theology'' (Paulist Press 2000 ISBN 0-567-08354-3), pp. 14-15]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Morwenna Ludlow (2001), in ''Universal Salvation: Eschatology in the Thought of Gregory of Nyssa and Karl Rahner'', writes that, though the meaning was very flexible until the mid-6th century, &quot;the word ''apokatastasis'' is now usually used to refer to a specifically Origenistic doctrine of universal salvation&quot;.&lt;ref name=ML/&gt;
* Peter L. Berger, in his book ''Questions of Faith'' (2003), calls apocatastasis &quot;the conviction that, in the end, all will be saved and the entire creation will be reconciled with God&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=mcvaNLPo4HYC&amp;pg=PA154&amp;dq=Luther+apocatastasis&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=tdB5TdXBG4mDhQeAhbTtBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwBDgK#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Peter L. Berger, ''Questions of Faith'' (Wiley, John and Sons 2003 ISBN 978-1-4051-0848-5), p. 154]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ''Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church'' (third edition 2005) explains the term as meaning the doctrine of the ultimate salvation of all.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Apocatastasis. The Greek name (ἀποκατάστασις) for the doctrine that ultimately all free moral creatures – angels, men, and devils – will share in the grace of salvation&quot; (''Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church'' (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3), article &quot;Apocatastasis&quot;); cf. article &quot;Universalism&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* Justo L. González, in ''Essential Theological Terms'' (2005), says that &quot;theories of the apocatastasis usually involve the expectation that in the end all, including the devil, will be saved&quot;.&lt;ref name=ETT&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=DU6RNDrfd-0C&amp;pg=PA12#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Justo L. González, ''Essential Theological Terms'' (Presbyterian Pub Corp 2005 ISBN 978-0-664-22810-1), p. 12]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Daniel L. Akin]], in ''A Theology for the Church'' (2007), explains ''apocatastasis'' as &quot;the idea that all things will be ultimately reconciled to God through Christ – including the damned in hell and even Satan and his demons&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=elzlVK5c3dQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Daniel+L.+Akin,+#v=onepage&amp;q=apocatastasis&amp;f=false Daniel L. Akin, ''A Theology for the Church'' (B&amp;H Publishing Group 2007 ISBN 978-0-8054-2640-3), p. 878]&lt;/ref&gt;

Stravinskas identifies apocatastasis with universalism or universal reconciliation, and some of the older sources do so also.&lt;ref&gt;In addition, two recent works that do not discuss apocatastasis give the corresponding Greek word as the source from which &quot;universalism&quot; is derived: [http://books.google.com/books?id=AMUpn_AK8iQC&amp;pg=PA330&amp;dq=apocatastasis+universalism&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=sg11TeySF4KKhQet0JxG&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwBjgU#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false James K. Walker, ''The Concise Guide to Today's Religions and Spirituality'' (Harvest House Publishers 2007 ISBN 978-0-7369-2011-7)] (p. 330), and [http://books.google.com/books?id=KakgvDxdbXwC&amp;pg=PA816&amp;dq=apocatastasis+universalism&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SBl1TYfFJ5GGhQeUqNy6Cw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCYQ6AEwADge#v=onepage&amp;q=apocatastasis%20universalism&amp;f=false Ramesh Chopra, ''Encyclopaedic Dictionary of Religion: Q-Z'' (Isha Books 2005 ISBN 81-8205-287-4)] (p. 816).&lt;/ref&gt; But most writers do not simply identify apocatastasis with [[universal reconciliation]]. González points out that a distinction exists, in that &quot;it is possible to hold universalist views without believing that all of creation will return to its original state&quot;.&lt;ref name=ETT/&gt; And both Ludlow&lt;ref name=ML/&gt; and McGarry&lt;ref name=DJCD/&gt; state that the word ''apokatastasis'' is today usually understood as referring to one specific doctrine of universal salvation, not to all versions of universalism.

== See also ==
* [[Christian Universalism]]
* [[Monad (Greek philosophy)]]
* [[Panentheism]]
* [[Problem of evil]]
* [[Restorationism]]
* [[Tikkun Olam|Repairing the World (Judaism)]]
* [[Trinitarian Universalism]]
* [[Universal reconciliation]]
* [[World to Come]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

[[Category:New Testament Greek words and phrases]]
[[Category:Christian eschatology]]
[[Category:Christian soteriology]]
[[Category:Patristics]]
[[Category:Christian Universalism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[de:Apokatastasis]]
[[es:Apocatástasis]]
[[fr:Apocatastase]]
[[ko:만물회복설]]
[[it:Apocatastasi]]
[[no:Apokatastasis]]
[[pl:Apokatastaza]]
[[pt:Apocatástase]]
[[ru:Апокатастасис]]
[[sl:Apokastaza]]
[[sr:Апокатастаза]]
[[sv:Apokatastasis]]</text>
      <sha1>sm7wcnnd1eue4u6srrnvnz7nud9kb8f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
