<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ara Pacis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>187111</id>
    <revision>
      <id>512114878</id>
      <parentid>512096061</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-13T03:08:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cynwolfe</username>
        <id>1831212</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>no, Augustus didn't celebrate a triumph; that's the whole idea of an Altar of Peace (see talk page for more explanation)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28628">[[Image:AraPacisFullFrontal2.JPG|thumb|''Ara Pacis Augustae'', the &quot;Altar of Augustan Peace&quot;, as reassembled]]
[[Image:RomaAraPacis ProcessioneNordParticolare.jpg|thumb|Ara Pacis:Detail of the processional frieze showing members of the Senate (north face)]]
[[Image:RomaAraPacis ProcessioneSudParticolare.jpg|thumb|Ara Pacis: Processional frieze showing Augustus as high priest of Rome, accompanied by members of his family(south face)]]
[[Image:Arapacis,jpg.jpg|thumb|right|Ara Pacis: the so-called  &quot;[[Tellus (goddess)|Tellus]]&quot; panel]]
The '''''Ara Pacis Augustae''''' ([[Latin]], &quot;Altar of Augustan Peace&quot;; commonly shortened to '''''Ara Pacis''''') is an [[altar]] to [[Pax (mythology)|Peace]], envisioned as a [[List of Roman deities|Roman goddess]].  It was commissioned by the [[Roman Senate]] on 4 July 13 BC to honor the return of [[Augustus]] to Rome after three years in [[Hispania]] and [[Gaul]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;On my return from Spain and Gaul in the consulship of Tiberius Nero and Publius Quintilius after successfully arranging affairs in those provinces, the senate resolved that an altar of the Augustan Peace should be consecrated next to the [[Campus Martius]] in honor of my return, and ordered that the magistrates and priests and [[Vestal Virgins]] should perform an annual sacrifice there....By new laws passed on my proposal I brought back into use many exemplary practices of our ancestors which were disappearing in our time, and in many ways I myself transmitted exemplary practices to posterity for their imitation.&quot; (''Acts of the Divine Augustus'' 2.2; 8.5.&lt;/ref&gt; and was consecrated on 30 January 9 BC by the [[Roman Senate|Senate]] to celebrate the peace established in the Empire after Augustus's victories.&lt;ref name=crow&gt;{{Cite journal| last =Crow  | first =Charlotte  | title =The Ara Pacis  | journal =History Today  | volume =56  | issue =6  | page =5  | month =June | year =2006}}; Samuel Ball Platner.&lt;/ref&gt; The altar was meant to be a vision of the [[Religion in ancient Rome|Roman civil religion]].  It sought to portray the peace and fertile prosperity enjoyed as a result of the ''[[Pax Augusta]]'' (Latin, &quot;Augustan peace&quot;) brought about by the military supremacy of the [[Roman empire]], and act as a visual reminder of the [[Julio-Claudian dynasty]] that was bringing it about.

The Altar was originally located on the northern outskirts of Rome,&lt;ref&gt;It stood precisely a [[Roman mile]] from the boundary of the ''[[pomerium]]'', the sacred precinct of Rome itself, as Mario Torelli pointed out in ''Typology and Structure of Roman Historical Reliefs'' (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press) 1982.&lt;/ref&gt; on the west side of the [[Via Flaminia]], in the northeastern corner of the [[Campus Martius]], a formerly open area that Augustus developed as a complex of monuments; the Ara Pacis Augustae stood in the flood plain of the river Tiber, where it became buried under four metres of silt over the centuries.

==The Altar==
The ''Ara Pacis'' stood within an enclosure elaborately and finely sculpted entirely in gleaming white marble, depicting scenes of traditional Roman piety, in which the Emperor and his family were portrayed in the act of offering [[sacrifice]]s to the gods.  Various figures bring forth cattle to be sacrificed.  Some have their [[toga]]s drawn over their heads, like a hood; this signifies that they are acting in their official capacity as priests.  Others wear [[Bay laurel|laurel]] [[Crown (headgear)|crown]]s, traditional symbols of victory.  Men, women, and children all approach the gods. Themes of civil peace are linked to themes of the dynastic [[Julio-Claudian]] claims, and the importance of religion as a civilizing force, in rites of which some were consciously being revived for the occasion, according to Augustus himself.

The Altar is universally recognized as a masterpiece, the most famous surviving example of Augustan sculpture; the life-sized figures in the procession are not idealized types, as are typically found in [[Greek statue|Greek sculpture]], but rather portraits of individuals, some of them recognizable today.

[[Karl Galinsky|G. Karl Galinsky]] pointed out&lt;ref&gt;Galinsky, &quot;Venus in a relief of the Ara Pacis Augustae,&quot; ''American Journal of Archeology'' '''70''' (1966:223-243 )&lt;/ref&gt; that the sculpture of the Ara Pacis is primarily symbolic rather than decorative, and that its [[iconography]] has several levels of significance. Studies of the Ara Pacis and similar public Roman monuments traditionally address the potent political symbolism of their decorative programs, that emphasizes dynastic and other imperial policies. The Ara Pacis is seen to embody without conscious effort the deep-rooted ideological connections among cosmic sovereignty, military force and fertility that were first outlined by [[Georges Dumézil]],&lt;ref&gt;Dumézil, ''L'idéologie tripartite des Indo-Européens'' (Brussels 1958), and more specific to Rome, his ''Jupiter, Mars, Quirinus: essai sur la conception Indo-Européen de la société et les origines de Rome'' (Paris 1941).&lt;/ref&gt; connections which are attested in early Roman culture and more broadly in the substructure of [[Indo-European]] culture at large.&lt;ref&gt;Dumézil's cultural construct was applied in detail to the Ara Pacis by G. Freibergs, C. S. Littleton and U. Strutynski, &quot;Indo-European Tripartition and the Ara Pacis Augustae: An Excursus in Ideological Archeology&quot; ''Numen'' '''33'''.1 (June 1986:3-32).&lt;/ref&gt; It has been suggested by Peter Holliday&lt;ref&gt;Holliday, &quot;Time, History, and Ritual on the Ara Pacis Augustae&quot; ''The Art Bulletin'' '''72'''.4 (December 1990:542-557).&lt;/ref&gt; that the Altar's imagery of the [[Golden Age]], usually discussed as mere poetic allusion, actually appealed to a significant component of the Roman populace. The program of the Ara Pacis addressed this group's very real fears of cyclical history, and promised that the rule of Augustus would avert the cataclysmic destruction of the world predicted by contemporary models of historical thought.

==The figures==
The long friezes of the Ara Pacis (the North and South Walls, so called today because of the modern layout) contain figures advancing towards the West who participate in a state of thanksgiving to celebrate the Peace created by Augustus.  These figures fall into four categories: [[lictor]]s (men carrying [[fasces]], bodyguards of magistrates); priests (three of the four major ''[[Collegium|collegia]]'' – ''[[Pontifices]]'', ''[[Epulones|Septemviri]]'', and ''[[Quindecimviri sacris faciundis|Quindecimviri]]''): women and children (generally from the imperial family, represented in portraiture); and attendants (a few anonymous figures necessary for religious purposes).

In addition there are two or three non-Roman children, who may be guests (or hostages) in Rome.  Their identification by their non-Roman costume and their participation in the ceremony advertises to all that Rome is the centre of the world, and that other nations send their young to Rome to learn Roman ways, so great is Rome's reputation.

The ceremony took place in the summer of 13 BC, but not necessarily on 4 July, when the Senate voted to build the Ara Pacis.

==The east and west walls==
The East and West walls each contain two panels, one well preserved and one represented only in fragments.

The East Wall contains a badly preserved scene of a female warrior (''bellatrix''), possibly [[Roma (mythology)|Roma]], apparently sitting on a [[War trophy|pile of weapons confiscated from the enemy]], thus forcing peace upon them by rendering them unable to make war.  This scene has been reconstructed based on coins that depict such a seated Roma.  When the monument was being reconstructed at its present site,  Edmund Buchner and other scholars sketched what the panel may have looked like.  This interpretation, though widely accepted, can not be proved correct, as so little of the original panel survives.

The other panel is more controversial in its subject, but far better preserved.  A goddess sits amid a scene of fertility and prosperity with twins on her lap.  Scholars have suggested that the goddess is Italia, Tellus (Earth), Venus, or Peace (other views also circulate).  Peace (Pax Augusta) makes the most sense since the entire scene depicts the benefits of peace, and the monument is the &quot;Altar of Augustan Peace,&quot; not the &quot;Altar of Italy&quot; or &quot;the Altar of Earth.&quot;  The exact identity of the goddess remains debated, however.&lt;ref&gt;For full discussion of the identification as Pax Augusta, see Nancy de Grummond, &quot;Pax Augusta and the Horae on the Ara Pacis Augustae,&quot; American Journal of Archaeology, 94 (1990) 663-677. See also Gaius Stern, &quot;Women Children and Senators on the Ara Pacis Augustae&quot; University of California Berkeley dissertation 2006, chapter 9.&lt;!--has this been published?--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

The West Wall also contains two panels.  The fragmentary panel called &quot;The [[Lupercalia|Lupercal]] Panel&quot; apparently preserves the moment when [[Romulus and Remus]] were discovered by [[Faustulus]] the shepherd, while Mars looks on.

The better preserved scene depicts the sacrifice of a pig (the standard sacrifice when Romans made a peace treaty) by an old priest and two attendants.  In 1907 this scene was identified by Johannes Sieveking&lt;ref&gt;Sieveking,  &quot;Zur Ara Pacis&quot; ''Jahresheft des Österreichischen Archeologischen Institut'' '''10''' (1907).&lt;/ref&gt;  as the moment when [[Aeneas]], newly arrived in Italy, sacrificed a sow and her piglets to Juno, as told by [[Virgil]] and others. In the 1960s, Stephan Weinstock challenged this identification (and the very identity of the entire monument), citing numerous discrepancies that Sieveking and his followers had failed to notice between Virgil's version and the panel.  Subsequently, Paul Richardson proposed,&lt;ref&gt;Rehak, &quot;Rethinking the Meaning of the Ara Pacis Augustae&quot; ''The Art Bulletin'' '''83''', 2001, Rehak credits Richardson and Eleni Eliades above FN 1 on page 201 of this article.&lt;/ref&gt; and Paul Rehak later published&lt;ref&gt;Rehak, &quot;Rethinking the Meaning of the Ara Pacis Augustae&quot; ''The Art Bulletin'' '''83''', 2001&lt;/ref&gt; an alternative identification of the scene as [[Numa Pompilius]], the Roman king associated with Peace and the [[Gates of Janus]].

==North wall==
The north wall has about 46 extant or partially extant figures.  The first two foreground figures are [[lictor]]s, carrying [[fasces]] (bundles of rods symbolizing Roman authority).  The next set of figures consists of priests from the college of the [[Epulones|Septemviri epulones]], so identified by an incense box they carry with special symbols.  One member of this college is missing in a gap.

After them follows the ''collegium'' of the ''[[quindecimviri sacris faciundis]]'', also identified by the incense box carried by a public slave among them.  Although the name suggests this college has exactly fifteen members, the size of the college has grown to 23, including Augustus and [[Agrippa]], who appear on the South Frieze.  The other twenty-one members are present here.  Two very badly damaged figures in the middle are split by a gap.  From photos, the gap appears to affect a single figure, but as Koeppel, Conlin, and Stern have proven, in-site examination reveals that one is a foreground and the other a background figure.

The last portion of the North Frieze consists of members of the imperial family.  Many scholars identify the veiled, leading figure as [[Julia the Elder|Julia, daughter of Augustus]].  Since Julia appears on the South Frieze, it is more likely that this figure is [[Octavia Minor]].  Other figures in the entourage might include Marcella (a daughter of Octavia), Iullus Antonius (a son of Mark Antony), and two boys and a girl of the imperial family.  In 1894, and again in 1902 and 1903, Eugen Petersen suggested that [[Gaius Caesar|Gaius]] and [[Lucius Caesar]] are the two boys dressed in &quot;Trojan&quot; costume for the equestrian event called the [[Lusus Troiae|Troy Game]], which was held in 13&amp;nbsp;BC for the dedication of the [[Theater of Marcellus]].&lt;ref&gt;I.M. Le M. Du Quesnay, ''Horace, ''Odes 4.5: ''Pro Reditu Imperatoris Caesaris Divi Filii Augusti'',&quot; in ''Homage to Horace: A Bimillenary Celebration'' (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995), p. 143 [http://books.google.com/books?id=Bby6t3zOq9oC&amp;pg=PA142&amp;dq=lusus+intitle:Homage+intitle:to+intitle:Horace&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=iFdITLHaCqPonQf1zITaDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=lusus%20intitle%3AHomage%20intitle%3Ato%20intitle%3AHorace&amp;f=false online]; Mario Torelli, ''Typology and Structure of Roman Historical Reliefs'' (University of Michigan Press, 1992), pp. 48–49, 60 [http://books.google.com/books?id=4012VYCWYqwC&amp;pg=PA60&amp;dq=%22Lusus+Troiae%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=0&amp;as_miny_is=&amp;as_maxm_is=0&amp;as_maxy_is=&amp;num=100&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=47#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Lusus%20Troiae%22&amp;f=false  online.]&lt;/ref&gt; But as Charles Brian Rose has noted, &quot;The variable value of the Eastern costume and the uneasy interaction of Trojan and Parthian iconography can make it difficult to determine whether one is viewing the founders of the Romans or their fiercest opponents.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Charles Brian Rose, &quot;The Parthians in Augustan Rome,&quot; in ''American Journal of Archaeology'' 109 (2005), p. 44, discussed pp. 36–44. Rose points out that only Gaius would have been of an age to participate in the Troy Game in 13 BC.&lt;/ref&gt; The youth wearing Hellenistic Greek clothing suited to a Hellenistic prince is sometimes identified as Gaius in the guise of a ''[[camillus]]'',&lt;ref&gt;John Pollini, The Portraiture of Gaius and Lucius Caesar, (1987), 24–26.&lt;/ref&gt; an adolescent attendant of the [[Flamen Dialis]].&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''Life of Numa Pomilius'' Numa 7.4.&lt;/ref&gt; This figure has also been interpreted as [[Ptolemy of Mauretania]] representing [[Africa (Roman province)|Africa]], along with a German boy (Europe) and a Parthian prince ([[Asia (Roman province)|Asia]]).&lt;ref&gt;Gaius Stern, &quot;Women Children and Senators on the Ara Pacis Augustae&quot; Berk. diss. 2006, chapter 8; Bridget Buxton also employed these identifications (on Stern's advice) in an earlier study &quot;Rome at the Crossroads&quot; (Berk. diss. 2003).  See also Kleiner and Buxton, &quot;Pledges of Empire:  The Ara Pacis and the Donations of Rome,&quot; AJA (2008), 57–89.&lt;/ref&gt;

==South wall==
The South Wall has seen a great deal of scholarship and the greatest number of academic debates.  Unlike the North Wall, where most of the heads are new (not authentic ancient heads, but modern creations), the heads of the figures on the South Wall are mostly original.  Some half dozen figures are recognizable from looking at other surviving statues of members of the imperial family.  Nevertheless, much debate has taken place over many of these figures, including Augustus, Agrippa, Tiberius, Julia, and Antonia.

Augustus - The figure of Augustus was not discovered until the 1903 excavation, and his head was damaged by the cornerstone of the Renaissance palazzo built on top of the original Ara Pacis site.  Today Augustus is better recognized by his hair style than his face.  He was identified in 1903 immediately.

Agrippa - In the absence of the panel including Augustus, early scholars debated whether this figure was Augustus or Agrippa or Lepidus.  In the same 1907 article mentioned above, Sieveking proposed that this figure was Lepidus, the ''Pontifex Maximus.''  Sieveking later reversed himself with a series of peculiar suggestions.  In 1926 Loewy compared the Louvre Agrippa and that in Copenhagen (and others) to the Ara Pacis to show icongographic similarity.&lt;ref&gt;E. Loewy &quot;Bemerkungen zur Ara Pacis,&quot; ''JöAr''. 23 (1926), 53-61.&lt;/ref&gt;  Aside from a very small minority of scholars (most vehemently defending Lepidus in ''Rom. Mitt'' in the 1930s was [[Ludwig Curtius]]), the rest of the academy agreed this figure is Agrippa.

Julia (Livia) - many scholars continue to see the Julia figure as Livia under the reasoning that Livia has to be on the Ara Pacis.  Indeed Livia does appear somewhere (she could hardly be excluded), but by 13 BC Julia had politically eclipsed Livia, as has been understood and explained by many scholars.&lt;ref&gt;Just to name a few, Stern, &quot;Livia Augusta on the Ara Pacis,&quot; CAMWS-SS, Winston-Salem, NC, Oct. 2004; Du Rocher, ''Histoire de la Rome Antique'' (Paris 1997), 52-53; Boschung &quot;Die Bildistypen der iulisch-claudischen Kaiserfamilien,&quot; JRA 6 (1993), 49; Inez Scott Ryberg &quot;The Procession of the Ara Pacis,&quot; ''MAAR'' 19 (1949), 77-101; and others.  The identification dates back to Milani in 1891.&lt;/ref&gt;  Furthermore, Livia has no bond to Agrippa, whereas Julia was his wife and expected to be the unofficial empress of Rome for decades, during and beyond Augustus' lifetime.  Julia also better personified Augustus' new pro-natalism program, having already given birth to four surviving children.  Nevertheless, a majority of scholars in 2000 preferred to see this figure as Livia.

Tiberius - This figure was Tiberius as early as 1891 by Milani, an identification that was rarely questioned until the 1940s.  Moretti, in making the glass museum for the Ara Pacis at Mussolini's command, guessed that the two consuls (Tiberius and Varus) of 13 flank Augustus, so he saw this figure as M. Valerius Messalla.&lt;ref&gt;Moretti ''Ara Pacis'' (1937), 37-44, ''Ara pacis Augustae''(1948), 220, figs. 166-67, pl. 26, (1957)&lt;/ref&gt;  V.H. von Poulsen proposed Iullus Antonius.&lt;ref&gt;von Poulsen (1946), ''Acta archaeologica'' 17, 32 ff, followed by Toynbee (1953), 85; J. Benario (1960), 348; Polacco (1960-61), 620-21; etc.&lt;/ref&gt;  But as has been well established, Augustus is flanked by priests, and this figure is Tiberius.  Boschung and Bonanno have both matched the face to early period Tiberius statuary.

Antonia, Drusus, and Germanicus - In 1880 H. Dütschke proposed the correct identity for Antonia and Drusus, but saw the toddler as Claudius (incorrectly).&lt;ref&gt;H. Dütschke, &quot;Ueber ein römisches Relief mit Darstellung der Familie des Augustus,&quot; ''Gelehrtenschule des Johanneums zu Hamburg''(1880)&lt;/ref&gt;  A. von Domaszewski amended this family identification and correctly saw the child as Germanicus.  He also suggested that the Ara Pacis is arranged in family groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Domaszewski 1903&quot;&gt;A. von Domaszewski, &quot;Die Familie des Augustus auf der Ara Pacis ''JoAI'' 6 (1903) 57 ff.&lt;/ref&gt;  He also correctly determined that the two-year old child could only be Germancius, whose exact birth in 24 May 15 BC is known.  This helps prove that the ceremony is an event in 13, although a few scholars continued to argue the ceremony was that of 9 BC.

The Domitii Ahenobarbi - In the same 1903 article, von Domaszewski also proposed that the last family on the South Wall is that of the father of the emperor Nero (born Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus).&lt;ref name=&quot;Domaszewski 1903&quot;/&gt;  This identification remains widespread today.  However, there are some dissenters from this theory.  Stern claims that these figures cannot possibly be the Domitii Ahenobarbi, on the basis of the belief that [[Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus (consul 32)|Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus]], whom von Domaszewski saw as the boy of the family, was not born until after the monument's completion.&lt;ref&gt;Gaius Stern, &quot;Nero’s Father and Other Romantic Figures on the Ara Pacis Augustae,&quot; CAMWS, St. Louis, MO, Apr. 2004, &quot;Women, Children and Senators on the Ara Pacis Augustae,&quot; (Berk diss. 2006).&lt;/ref&gt; Syme claims that it is just the identification of the children that is incorrect, preferring to identify the boy figure as an otherwise unknown elder son and the girl figure as an otherwise unknown elder daughter of Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus and Antonia Major.&lt;ref&gt; Sir Ronald Syme, &quot;Neglected Children on the Ara Pacis,&quot; in ''AJArch'' 88 (1984), pp. 583-589&lt;/ref&gt;  In defence of the identification of the group as the Domitii Ahenobarbi and of the boy as Gnaeus, Pollini has pointed out that Suetonius specifically mentions that Nero's father went &quot;to the East on the staff of the young Gaius Caesar&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Suetonius, ''Life of Nero'' 5.1&lt;/ref&gt; This campaign is known to have begun in 2 BC,&lt;ref&gt;John Pollini, &quot;Ahenobarbi, Appuleii and Some Others on the Ara Pacis&quot;, ''AJArch'' 90 (1986), p. 455&lt;/ref&gt;  which means that Gnaeus Ahenobarbus must have already been of a mature age by that year. Pollini reasons that the subsequent career delay of Ahenobarbus is likely due to his documented unpleasant character, and points out that the careers of other members of the family were also affected by their display of undesirable traits, notably [[Augustus]]' youngest grandson, [[Agrippa Postumus]], and [[Germanicus]]' brother, the later emperor, [[Claudius]].&lt;ref&gt;John Pollini, &quot;Ahenobarbi, Appuleii and Some Others on the Ara Pacis&quot;, ''AJArch'' 90 (1986), pp. 455-6&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Excavation and conservation==
The first fragmentary sculptures were rediscovered in 1568 beneath the basilica San Lorenzo in Lucina, and have found their way to the [[Villa Medici]], the [[Vatican Museums|Vatican]], the [[Uffizi]] and the [[Louvre]]. In 1859 further sculptural fragments were found under  [[Cinema Nuovo Olimpia|Teatro Olimpia]], part of the Peretti Palace in via in Lucina, close to the Italian Parliament Building and the sculptures were recognized as having belonged to the same monument.

In 1903, when [[Friedrich von Duhn]] recognized that the reliefs belonged to the Ara Pacis, known from Augustus' memoir, a request was sent to the Ministry of Public Education to continue the excavations. Their success was made possible by the generosity of Edoardo Almagià, who, as well as giving his permission for the exploration, donated in advance whatever should be discovered underneath the palace and made an ongoing financial contribution to the expenses of the excavation.

By July of that year, it became clear that the conditions were extremely difficult and that the stability of  [[Cinema Nuovo Olimpia|Teatro Olimpia]] might well be compromised.

When about half the monument had been examined and 53 fragments recovered, the excavation was called to a halt. In February 1937, the Italian Cabinet decreed that for the 2000th anniversary of the birth of Augustus, the excavations should recommence, using the most advanced technology.    Seventy cubic metres of ground under what was by then the [[Cinema Nuovo Olimpia]] were frozen, whilst the altar was extracted.

In 1938 [[Benito Mussolini]] built a protective building for the Altar, as it had been reconstructed by Vittorio Ballio Morpurgo, near the [[Mausoleum of Augustus]] (moving the Altar in the process) as part of his attempt to create an ancient Roman &quot;theme park&quot; to glorify [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Fascist Italy]].&lt;ref name=crow/&gt;

A new cover building, designed by American architect [[Richard Meier]], now stands on the same site as Mussolini's.&lt;ref name=crow/&gt; The new building opened in 2006 to controversy.&lt;ref name=crow/&gt; [[Nicolai Ouroussoff]], of the ''[[New York Times]]'' described the new building as &quot;a flop&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| last =Ouroussoff | first =Nicolai |authorlink=Nicolai Ouroussoff | title =An Oracle of Modernism in Ancient Rome | quote=That the building is a flop is therefore a major disappointment. Designed by Richard Meier for a site at the edge of a Fascist-era piazza overlooking the Tiber River, the museum boasts a muscular main hall built to house the Ara Pacis, an altar erected as a symbol of Roman peace — that is, military conquest — from around 9 BC. The building’s glistening glass and travertine shell has all of Mr. Meier’s usual flourishes, from the expansive use of glass to obsessive grids. | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/25/arts/design/25paci.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin | work=[[New York Times]] | date =2006-09-25 | accessdate =2007-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The presiding right-wing mayor [[Gianni Alemanno]], backed since July 2008 by culture undersecretary Francesco Maria Giro said he would tear down the new structure.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2008/aug/13/architecture.art|title=I just don't get modern art, says Italy's culture minister|work=[[The Guardian]]|accessdate=2008-08-13|first=Tom|last=Kington|date=13 August 2008 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| last =Sanderson | first =Rachel | coauthors = Mills, Don | title =Modern building stirs Roman passions | pages =A.19 | publisher =[[National Post]] | date =2006-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Rome mayor vows to remove museum  |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7379564.stm |quote=The city of Rome's newly elected right-wing mayor has caused waves by vowing to rip down a controversial museum created by a US architect. Gianni Alemanno said the Ara Pacis Museum, which encases a 2,000-year-old sacrificial altar, &quot;will be removed&quot;.  |work=[[BBC]] |accessdate=2008-08-17 | date=2008-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mayor Alemmano has since changed his stance on the building and has agreed with Mr. Meier to modifications including drastically reducing the height of the wall between an open-air space outside the museum and a busy road along the Tiber river. The city plans to build a wide pedestrian area along the river and run the road underneath it. &quot;It's an improvement,&quot; says Meier, adding that &quot;the reason that wall was there has to do with traffic and noise. Once that is eliminated, the idea of opening the piazza to the river is a good one.&quot; The mayor’s office said Alemanno hopes to complete the project before the end of his term in 2013.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.france24.com/en/20100407-modern-scar-housing-roman-altar-be-modified ]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Imperial cult (Ancient Rome)|Imperial cult]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Conlin, Diane Atnally 1997. ''The Artists of the Ara Pacis: The Process of Hellenization in Roman Relief Sculpture'' (Studies in the History of Greece and Rome University of North Carolina Press)
*Peter J. Holliday, &quot;Time, History, and Ritual on the Ara Pacis Augustae&quot; ''The Art Bulletin'' '''72'''.4 (December 1990:542-557) {{doi|10.2307/3045761}}
*Rossini, Orietta 2006. ''Ara Pacis'', Milan, Electa/.  ISBN 88-370-4379-1

==External links==
{{Commons}}
*[http://www.arapacis.it/ Official web site of the Ara Pacis Museum of Rome]
** [http://en.arapacis.it/ English version]
*[http://cdm.reed.edu/ara-pacis/ Comprehensive, high quality photo documentation of the Ara Pacis Augustae]
* [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Gazetteer/Places/Europe/Italy/Lazio/Roma/Rome/_Texts/PLATOP*/Ara_Pacis.html Samuel Ball Platner, ''A Topographical Dictionary of Ancient Rome'': Ara Pacis]
*[http://en.arapacis.it/ The official web site of the Ara Pacis Museum in English]
* [http://arachne.uni-koeln.de/arapacis/index.html Browser with high-quality images]
* [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Gazetteer/Places/Europe/Italy/Lazio/Roma/Rome/Ara_Pacis/home.html Several pages with photos of the sculpture]
*[http://employees.oneonta.edu/farberas/arth/arth200/politics/roman_imp_sculpt.html &quot;Roman Power and Roman Imperial Sculpture&quot;]
*[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/12857394/site/newsweek/ Article concerning Meier's museum housing the Ara Pacis]
*[http://travel2.nytimes.com/2006/09/25/arts/design/25paci.html Article from the New York Times, September 25 2006, &quot;An Oracle of Modernism in Ancient Rome&quot; by Nicolai Ouroussoff]
*[http://www.richardmeier.com/PROJECTS/AraPacis.html ''Description from Richardmeier.com'': Ara Pacis]
*[http://www.ara-pacis-museum.com/ Ara Pacis Museum.com: Reference website devoted to the Ara Pacis and the Ara Pacis Museum]

{{Rome landmarks}}

{{Coord|41|54|23|N|12|28|32|E|region:IT_type:landmark|display=title}}

[[Category:Augustan building projects]]
[[Category:1st-century BC architecture]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman architecture]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Rome]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman buildings and structures in Rome]]
[[Category:Altars]]
[[Category:Augustan sculptures]]
[[Category:Relocated buildings and structures]]
[[Category:Augustus in Ancient Roman sculpture]]

[[bg:Олтар на мира]]
[[ca:Ara Pacis]]
[[de:Ara Pacis]]
[[es:Ara Pacis]]
[[fr:Autel de la paix d'Auguste]]
[[gl:Ara pacis]]
[[ko:평화의 제단]]
[[hr:Ara Pacis]]
[[it:Ara Pacis]]
[[he:ארה פקיס]]
[[la:Ara Pacis Augustae]]
[[hu:Ara Pacis Augustae]]
[[nl:Ara Pacis]]
[[ja:アラ・パキス]]
[[pl:Ara Pacis]]
[[pt:Ara Pacis]]
[[ro:Ara Pacis]]
[[ru:Алтарь Мира]]
[[sh:Ara Pacis]]
[[fi:Ara Pacis]]
[[sv:Ara Pacis]]
[[tr:Ara Pacis]]
[[uk:Вівтар миру]]
[[zh:和平祭坛博物馆]]</text>
      <sha1>332qr930k9efqg27e10q8eoy8mypxyf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
