<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Assumption of Mary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>259335</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517214508</id>
      <parentid>517214289</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-11T15:15:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>History2007</username>
        <id>3684925</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35099">{{Redirect|Assunta|the hospital in Malaysia|Assunta Hospital}}
{{Redirect|Santa Maria Assunta|churches with this dedication|Santa Maria Assunta (churches)}}
{{About|the theological concept|works of art with this title|Assumption of the Virgin Mary in Art}}

{{Infobox saint
|name=The Assumption of Mary into Heaven
|feast_day=August 15 (Universal)
|venerated_in=[[Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eastern Orthodox Church]]
|image=Baroque Rubens Assumption-of-Virgin-3.jpg
|imagesize=200px
|caption=&quot;''La Asuncion de la Virgen''&quot;. [[Rubens]] circa. 1626''
|attributes=Mary assumed or elevated into Heaven with surrounding cherubs or saints
|patronage=[[Asuncion, Paraguay]]&lt;br&gt; [[Republic of Malta]]&lt;br&gt; [[Roman Catholicism in Thailand]]
|approval=Pope Pius XII
}}

The '''Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary into Heaven''', informally known as '''The Assumption''', according to the [[Christian beliefs]] of the [[Roman Catholic Church]], [[Eastern Orthodoxy]], [[Oriental Orthodoxy]], and parts of [[Anglicanism]], was the  [[Entering heaven alive|bodily taking up]] of the [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Virgin Mary]] into [[Heaven (Christianity)|Heaven]] at the end of her earthly life.  

The [[Roman Catholic Church]] teaches as [[Dogma (Roman Catholic)|dogma]] that the Virgin Mary &quot;having completed the course of her earthly life, was assumed body and soul into heavenly glory.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pope Pius XII: [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_p-xii_apc_19501101_munificentissimus-deus_en.html &quot;''Munificentissimus Deus'' - Defining the Dogma of the Assumption&quot;], par. 44. Vatican, November 1, 1950&lt;/ref&gt; This doctrine was [[dogmatic definition|dogmatically defined]] by [[Pope Pius XII]] on November 1, 1950, in his [[Apostolic Constitution]] ''[[Munificentissimus Deus]]'' by exercising [[papal infallibility]].&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of Catholicism'' by Frank K. Flinn, J. Gordon Melton 207 ISBN 0-8160-5455-X page 267&lt;/ref&gt; While the Catholic Church and [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] believe in the [[Dormition of the Theotokos]], which is the same as the Assumption,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_p-xii_apc_19501101_munificentissimus-deus_en.html Munificentissimus Deus, 17] In the liturgical books which deal with the feast either of the dormition or of the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin there are expressions that agree in testifying that, when the Virgin Mother of God passed from this earthly exile to heaven, what happened to her sacred body was, by the decree of divine Providence, in keeping with the dignity of the Mother of the Word Incarnate, and with the other privileges she had been accorded.&lt;/ref&gt;, the death of Mary has not been dogmatically defined. In the churches which observe it, the Assumption is a major [[feast day]], commonly celebrated on August 15. In many [[Catholic countries]], the feast is also marked as a [[Holy Day of Obligation]].

In his August 15, 2004, homily given at [[Lourdes]], [[Pope John Paul II]] quoted John 14:3 as one of the scriptural bases for understanding the dogma of the Assumption of Mary. In this verse, Jesus tells his disciples at the [[Last Supper]], &quot;If I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again, and will receive you to myself; that where I am, you may be there also.&quot; According to Catholic theology, Mary is the pledge of the fulfillment of Christ's promise.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wf-f.org/JPII_LourdesHomily.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The feast of the Assumption on August 15 is a public holiday in many countries, including Austria, Belgium, Chile, Colombia, Croatia, Ecuador, France, Germany (Bavaria and Saarland only), Greece, Lebanon, Lithuania, Italy, Malta, Mauritius,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bungalowvanille.com/2011/03/public-holidays-2012/|title=Mauritius public holidays 2012|publisher=|accessdate=28 january 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Poland, Portugal, Romania, Senegal, Slovenia, Spain, Switzerland (8 cantons only) and Vanuatu.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;''Columbus World Travel Guide'', 25th Edition&lt;/ref&gt; In Eastern Orthodox churches following the [[Julian Calendar]], the feast day of Assumption of Mary falls on August 28.

==History of the belief==
Although the Assumption (Latin: ''assūmptiō'', &quot;taken up&quot;) was only relatively recently defined as [[papal infallibility|infallible]] [[dogma]] by the Catholic Church, and in spite of a statement by [[Saint Epiphanius of Salamis]] in &lt;small&gt;AD&lt;/small&gt; 377 that no one knew whether Mary had died or not,&lt;ref&gt;Epiphanius, Panarion, Haer. 78.10–11, 23&lt;/ref&gt; [[New Testament apocrypha#Fate of Mary|apocryphal accounts]] of the assumption of Mary into heaven have circulated since at least the 4th century. The [[Catholic Church]] itself interprets chapter 12 of the [[Book of Revelation]] as referring to it.&lt;ref&gt;Apostolic Constitution, ''Munificentissimus Deus'', para 27, Vaticsn (1950)&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest known narrative is the so-called ''Liber Requiei Mariae'' (''The Book of Mary's Repose''), which survives intact only in an [[Ge'ez language|Ethiopic]] translation.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen J. Shoemaker, [http://www.oup.com/uk/catalogue/?ci=9780199210749 ''Ancient Traditions of the Virgin Mary's Dormition and Assumption''] (Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]], 2002, 2006). A complete translation of this earliest text appears at pp. 290–350&lt;/ref&gt; Probably composed by the 4th century, this Christian [[apocrypha]]l narrative may be as early as the 3rd century. Also quite early are the very different traditions of the [http://www.uoregon.edu/~sshoemak/texts/Syriac/Six%20Books%20Wright.pdf ''&quot;Six Books&quot; Dormition narratives'']. The earliest versions of this apocryphon are preserved by several [[Syriac language|Syriac]] manuscripts of the 5th and 6th centuries, although the text itself probably belongs to the 4th century.&lt;ref&gt;William Wright, [http://www.uoregon.edu/~sshoemak/texts/Syriac/Six%20Books%20Wright.pdf ''&quot;The Departure of my Lady Mary from this World,&quot;''] ''The Journal of Sacred Literature and Biblical Record'', 6 (1865): 417–48 and 7 (1865): 108–60. See also Agnes Smith Lewis, ed., Apocrypha Syriaca, Studia Sinaitica, XI (London: C. J. Clay and Sons, 1902).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:saintmaryghaxaq.JPG|thumb|left|180px|Assumption statue, 1808 by [[Mariano Gerada]], [[Ghaxaq]], [[Malta]]]]
Later apocrypha based on these earlier texts include the [http://www.uoregon.edu/~sshoemak/texts/dormitionG2/dormitionG2.htm ''De Obitu S. Dominae''], attributed to [[John the Theologian|St. John]], a work probably from around the turn of the 6th century that is a summary of the &quot;Six Books&quot; narrative. The story also appears in [http://www.uoregon.edu/~sshoemak/texts/dormitionL/dormitionL1.htm ''De Transitu Virginis''], a late 5th century work ascribed to [[Melito of Sardis|St. Melito of Sardis]] that presents a theologically redacted summary of the traditions in the ''Liber Requiei Mariae''. The ''Transitus Mariae'' tells the story of the apostles being transported by white clouds to the deathbed of Mary, each from the town where he was preaching at the hour.
The ''[[Decretum Gelasianum]]'' in the 490s declared some ''transitus Mariae'' literature apocryphal.

An Armenian letter attributed to [[Dionysus the Areopagite]] also mentions the event, although this is a much later work, written sometime after the 6th century. [[John of Damascus]], from this period, is the first church authority to advocate the doctrine under his own name. His contemporaries, [[Gregory of Tours]] and [[Modestus of Jerusalem]], helped promote the concept to the wider church.

In some versions of the story the event is said to have taken place in [[Ephesus]], in the [[House of the Virgin Mary]], although this is a much more recent and localized tradition. The earliest traditions all locate the end of Mary's life in [[Jerusalem]] (see &quot;[[Mary's Tomb]]&quot;). By the 7th century a variation emerged, according to which one of the apostles, often identified as [[Thomas (apostle)|St Thomas]], was not present at the death of Mary, but his late arrival precipitates a reopening of Mary's tomb, which is found to be empty except for her grave clothes. In a later tradition, Mary drops her girdle down to the apostle from heaven as testament to the event.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf08.vii.xliii.html#vii.xliii-Page_594 Ante-Nicene Fathers - ''The Writings of the Fathers Down to A.D. 325''], vol. 8 page 594&lt;/ref&gt; This incident is depicted in many later paintings of the Assumption.

Teaching of the Assumption of Mary became widespread across the Christian world, having been celebrated as early as the 5th century and having been established in the East by Emperor Maurice around AD 600.&lt;ref name=Alban140 &gt;''Butler's Lives of the Saints'' by Alban Butler, Paul Burns 1998 ISBN 0860122573 pages 140-141 &lt;/ref&gt; It was celebrated in the West under [[Pope Sergius I]] in the 8th century and [[Pope Leo IV]] then confirmed the feast as official.&lt;ref name=Alban140 /&gt; Theological debate about the Assumption continued, following the Reformation, climaxing in 1950 when Pope [[Pius XII]] defined it as dogma for the [[Catholic Church]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Vatican-deus_en&quot;&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_p-xii_apc_19501101_munificentissimus-deus_en.html Apostolic Constitution Munificentissimus Deus, no 44]&lt;/ref&gt; Catholic theologian [[Ludwig Ott]] stated, &quot;The idea of the bodily assumption of Mary is first expressed in certain transitus-narratives of the fifth and sixth centuries.... The first Church author to speak of the bodily assumption of Mary, in association with an apocryphal transitus B.M.V., is St. Gregory of Tours.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ludwig Ott, Fundamentals of Catholic Dogma (Rockford: Tan, 1974), pp. 209–210&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] writer [[Eamon Duffy]] states that &quot;there is, clearly, no historical evidence whatever for it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Eamon Duffy, What Catholics Believe About Mary (London: Catholic Truth Society, 1989), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Catholic Church has never asserted nor denied that its teaching is based on the apocryphal accounts. The Church documents are silent on this matter and instead rely upon other sources and arguments as the basis for the doctrine.

==Catholic teaching==
{{Roman Catholic Mariology|Catholic Mariology}}
In this [[Roman Catholic dogma|dogmatic statement]], the phrase &quot;having completed the course of her earthly life,&quot; leaves open the question of whether the Virgin Mary died before her assumption or whether she was assumed before death; both possibilities are allowed. Mary's assumption is said to have been a divine gift to her as the 'Mother of God'. Ludwig Ott's view is that, as Mary completed her life as a shining example to the human race, the perspective of the gift of assumption is offered to the whole human race.&lt;ref&gt;Ludwig Ott's ''Fundamentals of Catholic Dogma, pp250 ff&lt;/ref&gt;

In Ludwig Ott's ''Fundamentals of Catholic Dogma'' he states that &quot;the fact of her death is almost generally accepted by the Fathers and Theologians, and is expressly affirmed in the Liturgy of the Church&quot;, to which he adduces a number of helpful citations, and concludes that &quot;for Mary, death, in consequence of her freedom from [[original sin]] and from personal sin, was not a consequence of punishment of sin. However, it seems fitting that Mary's body, which was by nature mortal, should be, in conformity with that of her [[Jesus|Divine Son]], subject to the general law of death&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Fundamentals of Catholic Dogma, Ludwig Ott, Book III, Pt. 3, Ch. 2, §6, ISBN 0-89555-009-1&lt;/ref&gt; The point of her bodily death has not been infallibly defined, and many believe that she did not die at all, but was assumed directly into Heaven. The dogmatic definition within the Apostolic Constitution [[Munificentissimus Deus]] which, according to Roman Catholic dogma, infallibly proclaims the doctrine of the Assumption leaves open the question whether, in connection with her departure, Mary underwent bodily death; that is, it does not dogmatically define the point one way or the other, as shown by the words &quot;having completed the course of her earthly life&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Vatican-deus_en&quot; /&gt;

On November 1, 1950, [[Pope Pius XII]] solemnly declared:

:''By the authority of our Lord Jesus Christ, of the Blessed Apostles Peter and Paul, and by our own authority, we pronounce, declare, and define it to be a divinely revealed dogma: that the Immaculate Mother of God, the ever Virgin Mary, having completed the course of her earthly life, was assumed body and soul into heavenly glory''&lt;ref&gt;Constitution [[Munificentissimus Deus]], no 44 [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_p-xii_apc_19501101_munificentissimus-deus_en.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

Roman Catholic theologians consider this declaration by [[Pius XII]] to be an [[ex cathedra]] use of Papal Infallibility.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/audiences/alpha/data/aud19930324en.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Creative Fidelity: Weighing and Interpreting Documents of the Magisterium, by [[Francis A. Sullivan]], chapter 6&lt;/ref&gt; Although Pope [[Pius XII]] deliberately left open the question of whether Mary died before her Assumption, the more common teaching of the early Fathers is that she did die.&lt;ref&gt;As the Virgin Mary, in the view of the [[Catholic Church]], remained an ever-virgin and sinless, it is viewed that the Virgin Mary could not thus suffer the consequences of [[Original Sin]], which is chiefly Death. http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3819.htm Nicea II Session 6 Decree&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ewtn.com/library/COUNCILS/NICAEA2.HTM#2 Nicaea II Definition, &quot;without blemish&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Assumption and Dormition (Eastern Christianity) compared==
[[File:Dormition de la Vierge.JPG|thumb|left|200px|The Dormition: ivory plaque, late 10th-early 11th century ([[Musée de Cluny]]).]]
The [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] Feast of the Assumption is celebrated on August 15, and the [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]] and [[Eastern Catholics]] celebrate the [[Dormition of the Theotokos]] (the falling asleep of the Mother of God) on the same date, preceded by a 14-day [[fasting|fast]] period. Eastern Orthodox Christians believe that Mary died a natural death, that her soul was received by Christ upon death, and that her body was resurrected on the third day after her death and that she was taken up into heaven bodily in anticipation of the general [[resurrection]]. Her tomb was found empty on the third day. &quot;...Orthodox tradition is clear and unwavering in regard to the central point [of the Dormition]: the Holy Virgin underwent, as did her Son, a physical death, but her body – like His – was afterwards raised from the dead and she was taken up into heaven, in her body as well as in her soul. She has passed beyond death and judgement, and lives wholly in the Age to Come. The Resurrection of the Body ... has in her case been anticipated and is already an accomplished fact. That does not mean, however, that she is dissociated from the rest of humanity and placed in a wholly different category: for we all hope to share one day in that same glory of the Resurrection of the Body which she enjoys even now.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop Kallistos (Ware) of Diokleia, in: Festal Menaion [London: Faber and Faber, 1969], p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Catholics also believe that Mary first died before being assumed, but they add that she was miraculously resurrected before being assumed, while others believe she was assumed bodily into Heaven without first passing through death.&lt;ref&gt;''The Catholicism Answer Book: The 300 Most Frequently Asked Questions'' by John Trigilio, Kenneth Brighenti 2007 ISBN 1-4022-0806-5 page 64&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Ancient Traditions of the Virgin Mary's Dormition and Assumption'' by Stephen J. Shoemaker 2006 ISBN 0-19-921074-8 page 201&lt;/ref&gt; As mentioned earlier, this aspect of the Assumption is not authoritatively defined in Catholic theology, and either understanding may be legitimately held by Catholics. [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholics]] observe the Feast as the Dormition. Many theologians note by way of comparison that in the [[Catholic Church]], the Assumption is dogmatically defined, while in the Eastern Orthodox tradition, the Dormition is less dogmatically than liturgically and mystically defined. Such differences spring from a larger pattern in the two traditions, wherein [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] teachings are often dogmatically and authoritatively defined – in part because of the more centralized structure of the [[Catholic Church]]– while in Eastern Orthodoxy, many doctrines are less authoritative.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/johndamascus-komesis.html Three Sermons on the Dormition of the Virgin] by [[John of Damascus]], from the Medieval Sourcebook&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mary's heavenly birthday==
[[File:Tizian 041.jpg|thumb|180px|Possibly the most famous rendition of the subject in Western art, [[Titian]]'s ''Assunta'' (1516–18).]]
The Assumption is important to many Catholic and Orthodox Christians as the Virgin Mary's heavenly birthday (the day that Mary was received into Heaven). Her acceptance into the glory of Heaven is seen by them as the symbol of the promise made by Jesus to all enduring Christians that they too will be received into paradise. The Assumption of Mary is symbolised in the [[Fleur-de-lys]] Madonna.

The present Italian name of the holiday, ''&quot;Ferragosto&quot;'', may derive from the Latin name, ''Feriae Augusti'' (&quot;Holidays of the [[Emperor Augustus]]&quot;),&lt;ref name=&quot;Pianigiani&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Pianigiani, Ottorino|title=Vocabolario etimologico della lingua italiana|year=1907|url=http://www.etimo.it/?term=ferragosto}}&lt;/ref&gt; since the month of August took its name from the emperor. The Solemnity of the Assumption on August 15 was celebrated in the eastern Church from the 6th Century. The [[Catholic Church]] adopted this date as a [[Holy Day of Obligation]] to commemorate the Assumption of the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]], the real physical elevation of her sinless soul and incorrupt body into Heaven.

The Solemnity of the Assumption on August 15 is a public holiday in many countries, including Andorra, Austria, Belgium, Burundi, Cameroon, Central African Republic, Chile, Republic of Congo, Côte d'Ivoire, Croatia, Colombia, Cyprus, East Timor, France, Gabon, Greece, Republic of Guinea, Haiti, Italy, Lebanon, Lithuania, Luxembourg, Republic of Macedonia, Madagascar, Malta, Mauritius, Republic of Moldova, Monaco, Paraguay, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Rwanda, Senegal, Seychelles, Slovenia, Spain, Switzerland, Tahiti, Togo, and Vanuatu.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot; /&gt; It is also a holiday in some predominantly Catholic states of Germany, including [[Bavaria]] and [[Saarland]]. In Guatemala it is observed in [[Guatemala City]] and in the town of [[Santa Maria Nebaj]], both of which claim her as their [[patron saint]]. Also, this day is combined with [[Mother's Day]] in Costa Rica. In many places, religious parades and popular festivals are held to celebrate this day. Prominent Catholic and Orthodox countries in which Assumption day is an important festival but is not recognized by the state as a public holiday include Argentina, Brazil, Czech Republic, Ireland, Mexico, the Philippines and Russia. In Canada, Assumption Day is the Fête Nationale of the [[Acadian]]s, of whom she is the patron saint. Businesses close on that day in heavily francophone parts of [[New Brunswick]], Canada. The Virgin Assumed in Heaven is also patroness of the [[Maltese Islands]] and her feast, celebrated on 15 August, apart from being a public holiday in Malta is also celebrated with great solemnity in all the local churches especially in the seven localities known as the Seba' Santa Marijiet. In [[Anglicanism]] and [[Lutheranism]], the feast is kept, but without official use of the word &quot;Assumption&quot;.

==Anglican views==
Although the Assumption of Mary is not an Anglican doctrine, 15 August is observed by some within Anglicanism as a feast day in honour of Mary. The ''[[Book of Common Prayer]]'' in the versions of the [[Scottish Episcopal Church]] and the [[Anglican Church of Canada]] mark the date as the Falling Asleep of the Blessed Virgin Mary. In the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America]], the day is observed as the Holy Day of Saint Mary the Virgin. In the [[Church of England]] the day is a [[Festival (Church of England)|Festival]] of the Blessed Virgin Mary. In some churches of the [[Anglican Communion]] and the [[Continuing Anglican]] churches, many [[Anglo-Catholics]] often observe the feast day as the Assumption.

The [[Anglican-Roman Catholic International Commission]] agreed statement on the Virgin Mary assigns a place for both the Dormition and the Assumption in Anglican devotion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/angl-comm-docs/rc_pc_chrstuni_doc_20050516_mary-grace-hope-christ_en.html Mary: Grace and Hope in Christ]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Protestant views==
The Protestant Reformer [[Heinrich Bullinger]] believed in the assumption of Mary. His 1539 polemical treatise against idolatry &lt;ref&gt;''De origine erroris libri duo'' (On the Origin of Error, Two Books) [http://books.google.com/books?id=EXLscQAACAAJ&amp;dq=%22De+origine+erroris+libri+duo%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=RjnCTba2KIudgQfjw7jnAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwATgy]. &quot;In the ''De origine erroris in divorum ac simulachrorum cultu'' he opposed the worship of the saints and iconolatry; in the ''De origine erroris in negocio Eucharistiae ac Missae'' he strove to show that the Catholic conceptions of the Eucharist and of celebrating the Mass were wrong. Bullinger published a combined edition of these works in [[Octavo|4 °]] (Zurich 1539), which was divided into two books, according to themes of the original work.”
''The Library of the Finnish nobleman, royal secretary and trustee Henrik Matsson (ca. 1540-1617)'', Terhi Kiiskinen Helsinki: Academia Scientarium Fennica (Finnish Academy of Science), 2003, ISBN 951-41-0944-9 ISBN 9789514109447, p. 175 [http://www.google.com/search?q=%22he+opposed+the+worship+of+the+saints+and+iconolatry%22&amp;hl=en&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;hs=WVr&amp;rls=org.mozilla%3Aen-US%3Aofficial&amp;num=10&amp;lr=&amp;ft=i&amp;cr=&amp;safe=images&amp;tbs=#q=%22he+opposed+the+worship+of+the+saints+and+iconolatry%22&amp;hl=en&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;hs=WVr&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;num=10&amp;lr=&amp;ft=i&amp;cr=&amp;safe=images&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;tbo=u&amp;tbs=,bks:1&amp;source=og&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=wp&amp;fp=e0e76270dccd6427]
&lt;/ref&gt; expressed his belief that Mary's ''sacrosanctum corpus'' (&quot;sacrosanct body&quot;) had been assumed into heaven by angels:

{{quote|''Hac causa credimus ut Deiparae virginis Mariae purissimum thalamum et spiritus sancti templum, hoc est, sacrosanctum corpus ejus deportatum esse ab angelis in coelum.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://astronomie-rara.ethbib.ethz.ch/zuz/content/pageview/937157 ''De origine erroris'', Caput XVI (Chapter 16), p. 70 (thumbnail 146)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/br&gt;

For this reason we believe that the Virgin Mary, Begetter of God, the most pure bed and temple of the Holy Spirit, that is, her most holy body, was carried to heaven by angels.&lt;ref&gt;''The Thousand Faces of the Virgin Mary'' (1996), [[George Tavard|George H. Tavard]], Liturgical Press ISBN 0-8146-5914-4 ISBN 9780814659144, p. 109. [http://books.google.com/books?id=Y3gtHzATNB4C&amp;pg=PA109&amp;dq=%22sancti+templum,+hoc+est%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=V7DBTb-eMYns0gGswqC4Cg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22sancti%20templum%2C%20hoc%20est%22&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Most modern Protestants neither teach nor believe in the Assumption of Mary, as they see no [[Sola Scriptura|Biblical basis]] for it. Although most churches within [[Lutheranism]] do not teach the Assumption of Mary, August 15 is a Lesser Feast in celebration of &quot;Mary, Mother of Our Lord&quot;, according to the [[Calendar of Saints (Lutheran)|Calendar of Saints]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.liturgybytlw.com/LessFest/MaryMoth.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ctkelc.org/sermons/sermons_kil/20100815.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://wmltblog.org/2011/08/st-mary-mother-of-our-lord/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scriptural sources==
[[File:Shrine of Our Lady of Perpetual Help, San Luis Potosi city, San Luis Potosi state, Mexico14.jpg|left|thumb|A statue of the Assumption of the [[Virgin Mary]] in [[San Luis Potosí, San Luis Potosí|San Luis Potosí, Mexico]]. ]]
As mentioned, recent papal scholarship has cited John 14:3 as evidence of the Assumption in principle if not formally. Near the end of a review of the doctrine's history – a review which serves as the bulk of [[Munificentissimus Deus]] – [[Pope Pius XII]] tells us: &quot;All these proofs and considerations of the holy Fathers and the theologians are based upon the Sacred Writings as their ultimate foundation.&quot; Precedent to this, he cites many passages that have been offered in support of this teaching:

&lt;blockquote&gt;29. ...the holy writers...employed statements and various images and analogies of Sacred Scripture to Illustrate and to confirm the doctrine of the Assumption, which was piously believed... On the feast day of the Assumption, while explaining the prophet's words: &quot;I will glorify the place of my feet,&quot; [Isaiah 60:13] he [i.e. St. Anthony of Padua] stated it as certain that the divine Redeemer had bedecked with supreme glory his most beloved Mother from whom he had received human flesh. He asserts that &quot;you have here a clear statement that the Blessed Virgin has been assumed in her body, where was the place of the Lord's feet...&quot;

30. ...St. Albert the Great... in a sermon which he delivered on the sacred day of the Blessed Virgin Mary's annunciation, explained the words &quot;Hail, full of grace&quot; [Luke 1:28]-words used by the angel who addressed her-the Universal Doctor, comparing the Blessed Virgin with Eve, stated clearly and incisively that she was exempted from the fourfold curse that had been laid upon Eve [cf. Genesis 3:16]...

32. Along with many others, the Seraphic Doctor held the same views. He considered it as entirely certain that...God...would never have permitted her body to have been resolved into dust and ashes. Explaining these words of Sacred Scripture: &quot;Who is this that comes up from the desert, flowing with delights, leaning upon her beloved?&quot; [Song of Songs 8:5] and applying them in a kind of accommodated sense to the Blessed Virgin, he reasons thus: &quot;From this we can see that she is there bodily...her blessedness would not have been complete unless she were there as a person. The soul is not a person, but the soul, joined to the body, is a person. It is manifest that she is there in soul and in body. Otherwise she would not possess her complete beatitude. ...&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Pope also cites, significantly in paragraph 39, 1st Corinthians 15, where we read (vv. 21–26):

&lt;blockquote&gt;For by a man came death, and by a man the resurrection of the dead. And as in Adam all die, so also in Christ all shall be made alive. But every one in his own order: the firstfruits Christ, then they that are of Christ, who have believed in his coming. Afterwards the end, when he shall have delivered up the kingdom to God and the Father, when he shall have brought to nought all principality, and power, and virtue. For he must reign, until he hath put all his enemies under his feet. And the enemy death shall be destroyed last: For he hath put all things under his feet.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In this passage Paul alludes to [[Genesis 3:15]] (in addition to the primary reference of Psalms 8:6), where it is prophesied that the [[seed of the woman]] will crush Satan with his feet. Since, then, Jesus arose to Heaven to fulfill this prophecy, it follows that the woman would have a similar end, since she shared this enmity with Satan. The pope comments thus in paragraph 39:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...although subject to [Jesus, who is] the new Adam, [Mary, the new Eve] is most intimately associated with him in that struggle against the infernal foe which, as foretold in the protoevangelium [i.e. Genesis 3:15], would finally result in that most complete victory over the sin and death which are always mentioned together in the writings of the Apostle of the Gentiles. Consequently, just as the glorious [[resurrection of Jesus]] was an essential part and the final sign of this victory, so that struggle which was common to the Blessed Virgin and her divine Son should be brought to a close by the glorification of her virginal body, for the same Apostle says: &quot;When this mortal thing hath put on immortality, then shall come to pass the saying that is written: Death is swallowed up in victory.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The pope also mentions (in paragraph 26) Psalms 132, a liturgical psalm commemorating the return of the Ark of God to Jerusalem&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usccb.org/nab/bible/psalms/psalm132.htm#foot1 USCCB - NAB - Psalm 132&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and lamenting its subsequent loss. The second half of the psalm says that the loss will be recompensed in the New Covenant, and so it is hopefully prayed, &quot;Arise, O Lord, into thy resting place: thou and the ark, which thou hast sanctified&quot; (v. 8). Since the Church sees this New Covenant ark in Mary, it understands that she was taken into Heaven in the same manner as the Lord – that is, body and soul.

In the same paragraph, the pope mentions also Psalms 45:9–17 for support of a heavenly Queen present bodily with the heavenly King Jesus, and Song of Songs 3:6, 4:8, and 6:9, which speaks of David's lover &quot;that goeth up by the desert, as a pillar of smoke of aromatical spices, of myrrh, and frankincense, and of all the powders of the perfumer&quot;. Regarding the Marian interpretations of those passages from Psalms 132 to Song of Songs 6:9 and those in between, the pope did, however, consider them &quot;rather free in their use of events and expressions taken from Sacred Scripture&quot; (paragraph 26).

Finally, he mentions in the next paragraph &quot;that woman clothed with the sun [Revelation 12:1–2] whom John the Apostle contemplated on the Island of Patmos&quot; as support for the doctrine. The text seems to parallel this woman with the woman of the Genesis 3 prophecy (and hence Mary): for in verse 9 the passage recalls &quot;that old serpent&quot; of Genesis 3, and reflects the prophecy that God would place &quot;enmities between thee [i.e. Satan] and the woman, and thy seed and her seed&quot; when it says that Satan &quot;was angry against the woman: and went to make war with the rest of her seed&quot; (Rev. 12:17).

All these passages – viz., John 14:3, Isaiah 60:13, Luke 1:28, Song of Songs 8:5, 1st Corinthians 15:21–26, Psalms 132:8, Psalms 45:9–17, Song of Songs 3:6, 4:8, 6:9, Genesis 3:15, and Revelation 12:1–2 – are drawn upon as Scriptural support of the Assumption both in that original document, and today by Catholic apologists.

==Armenian tradition==
In the [[Armenians|Armenian]] tradition, a cultural custom of blessing of the [[grapes]] is annually observed each August 12, the in religious commemoration of the Feast of the [[Dormition of the Theotokos]]. While the blessing of the grapes are not exactly associated with the Assumption of the Virgin Mary into heaven,  the blessing is nonetheless viewed as a liturgy of thanksgiving by farmers for a plentiful season of harvest and is generally considered a family day by the [[Armenian peoples]]. Women often bring baskets of grapes into the church, where a deacon or priest blesses the fruit after the [[Divine Liturgy]] and is then followed by a public meal or celebration.

==See also==
*[[Assumption Cathedral (disambiguation)|Assumption Cathedral]]
*[[Immaculate Conception]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
{{Commons category|Assumption of Mary}}
*Duggan, Paul E. (1989). ''The Assumption Dogma: Some Reactions and Ecumenical Implications in the Thought of English-speaking Theologians''. Emerson Press, Cleveland, Ohio
*Shoemaker, Stephen J. (2002, 2006). [http://www.oup.com/uk/catalogue/?ci=9780199210749 ''Ancient Traditions of the Virgin Mary's Dormition and Assumption'']. Oxford University Press, Oxford. ISBN 0-19-925075-8 (Hardcover 2004, Reprint), ISBN 0-19-921074-8 (Paperback 2006)

==External links==
*[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_p-xii_apc_19501101_munificentissimus-deus_en.html &quot;''Munificentissimus Deus'' - Defining the Dogma of the Assumption&quot;] Vatican, November 1, 1950
*[http://www.uoregon.edu/~sshoemak/texts/dormindex.htm Early Traditions of the Virgin Mary's Dormition and Assumption] a collection of early Dormition and Assumption narratives with introductions

{{Virgin Mary}}
{{Catholicism}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Assumption Of Mary
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Assumption Of Mary}}
[[Category:Marian dogmas]]
[[Category:Glorious Mysteries]]
[[Category:Christian miracle narrative]]
[[Category:Religious holidays]]
[[Category:Anglican Mariology]]
[[Category:Saints days]]
[[Category:Christian festivals and holy days]]
[[Category:Catholic holy days]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox liturgical days]]
[[Category:Christian holidays]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic Mariology]]
[[Category:Pope Pius XII mariology]]

[[ar:عيد رفع مريم]]
[[an:Asumpción de Santa María]]
[[be-x-old:Усьпеньне]]
[[bg:Успение на Пресвета Богородица]]
[[bar:Hoach-Insrfrauntåg]]
[[br:Gouel Maria Hanter-Eost]]
[[ca:Assumpció de Maria]]
[[cs:Svátek Nanebevzetí Panny Marie]]
[[de:Mariä Aufnahme in den Himmel]]
[[el:Κοίμηση της Θεοτόκου]]
[[es:Asunción de María]]
[[eo:Ĉielenpreno de Maria]]
[[eu:Mariaren Jasokunde]]
[[fr:Assomption de Marie]]
[[ko:성모 승천]]
[[hy:Աստվածածնի վերափոխման տոն]]
[[hr:Velika Gospa]]
[[io:Asunciono]]
[[id:Maria Diangkat ke Surga]]
[[ia:Assumption de Maria]]
[[it:Assunzione di Maria]]
[[he:חג עליית מרים]]
[[ka:მიძინება ყოვლადწმიდისა ღვთისმშობელისა (მარიამობა)]]
[[sw:Maria kupalizwa mbinguni]]
[[kv:Успенньӧ]]
[[la:Assumptio Beatae Mariae Virginis]]
[[lb:Léiffrawëschdag]]
[[lt:Žolinė]]
[[li:Maria Hemelvaart]]
[[hu:Mária mennybevétele]]
[[mk:Успение на Пресвета Богородица]]
[[nl:Maria-Tenhemelopneming]]
[[nds-nl:Moregodsdag]]
[[ja:聖母の被昇天]]
[[no:Jomfru Marias opptagelse i himmelen]]
[[pl:Wniebowzięcie Najświętszej Maryi Panny]]
[[pt:Assunção de Maria]]
[[ro:Adormirea Maicii Domnului]]
[[ru:Вознесение Девы Марии]]
[[sl:Marijino vnebovzetje]]
[[sr:Велика Госпојина]]
[[sh:Velika Gospa]]
[[sv:Jungfru Marie himmelsfärd]]
[[th:แม่พระรับเกียรติยกขึ้นสวรรค์]]
[[uk:Успіння Богородиці]]
[[vec:Asunsion de Maria]]
[[vi:Lễ Đức Mẹ Lên Trời]]
[[wa:Grande Notru-Dame]]
[[bat-smg:Žuolėnė]]
[[zh:圣母蒙召升天]]</text>
      <sha1>10mq0unpb70kpdh2qccn36zlq1o3qop</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
