<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Astrology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2122</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522333669</id>
      <parentid>522333628</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T14:16:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>The elephant</username>
        <id>1810581</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Undid revision 522332884 by [[Special:Contributions/94.187.125.238|94.187.125.238]] ([[User talk:94.187.125.238|talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="67555">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{Distinguish|Astronomy}}
{{Ast box}}
'''Astrology''' consists of a number of [[belief systems]] which hold that there is a relationship between astronomical phenomena and events in the human world. In the West, astrology most often consists of a system of [[horoscope]]s that claim to explain aspects of a person's [[personality]] and predict future events in their life based on the positions of the sun, moon, and other planetary objects at the time of their birth. Many cultures have attached importance to astronomical events, and the [[Hindu astrology|Indians]], [[Chinese astrology|Chinese]], and [[Mayans]] developed elaborate systems for predicting terrestrial events from celestial observations. 
 
Among [[Indo-European]] peoples, astrology has been dated to the third millennium [[BCE]], with roots in [[Calendrical calculation|calendrical]] systems that are used to predict shifts and to interpret celestial cycles as signs of divine communications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Koch-Westenholz|first=Ulla|title=Mesopotamian astrology : an introduction to Babylonian and Assyrian celestial divination|year=1995|publisher=Museum Tusculanum Press|location=Copenhagen|isbn=978-87-7289-287-0|pages=Foreword,11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through most of its history, astrology was considered a scholarly tradition. It was accepted in political and academic contexts, and was connected with other studies, such as [[astronomy]], [[alchemy]], [[meteorology]], and medicine.&lt;ref name=Kassell&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kassell|first=Lauren|title=Stars, spirits, signs: towards a history of astrology 1100–1800|journal=Studies in History and Philosophy of Science Part C: Studies in History and Philosophy of Biological and Biomedical Sciences|date=5 May 2010|volume=41|issue=2|pages=67–69|doi=10.1016/j.shpsc.2010.04.001}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the 17th century, new scientific concepts in astronomy (such as [[heliocentrism]]) called astrology into question, and subsequent controlled studies failed to confirm its predictive value. Astrology thus lost its academic and theoretical standing.

Astrology is a [[pseudoscience]], and as such has been rejected by the scientific communities as having no explanatory power for describing the universe. Where astrology has been [[falsifiable]], it has been falsified.&lt;ref name=Zarka /&gt;{{rp|424}} Since the enlightenment, particularly from the introduction of [[classical mechanics]], common belief in astrology has largely reduced.&lt;ref name=Brit&gt;{{cite web|first=David E. Pingree, Robert Andrew Gilbert|title=Astrology - Astrology in modern times|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/39971/astrology/35979/Astrology-in-modern-times|publisher=Encyclopaedia Britannica|accessdate=7 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Astrology#Scientific appraisal|Scientific testing]] of astrology has been conducted, and no evidence has been found to support any of the premises or purported effects outlined in astrological traditions. Furthermore, there is no proposed mechanism of action by which the positions and motions of stars and planets could affect people and events on Earth that does not contradict well understood, basic aspects of biology and physics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Vishveshwara|first=edited by S.K. Biswas, D.C.V. Mallik, C.V.|title=Cosmic perspectives : essays dedicated to the memory of M.K.V. Bappu|year=1989|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge [England]|isbn=0521343542|edition=1. publ.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|249}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=ed. by Peter D. Asquith|title=Proceedings of the Biennial Meeting of the Philosophy of Science Association, vol. 1|year=1978|publisher=Reidel u.a.|location=Dordrecht u.a.|isbn=978-0-917586-05-7|url=http://www.cavehill.uwi.edu/bnccde/PH29A/thagard.html}}
* {{cite web|title=Chapter 7: Science and Technology: Public Attitudes and Understanding|url=http://www.nsf.gov/statistics/seind06/c7/c7s2.htm#c7s2l3|work=science and engineering indicators 2006|publisher=National Science Foundation|accessdate=28 July 2012|quote=About three-fourths of Americans hold at least one pseudoscientific belief; i.e., they believed in at least 1 of the 10 survey items[29]&quot; ...&quot; Those 10 items were extrasensory perception (ESP), that houses can be haunted, ghosts/that spirits of dead people can come back in certain places/situations, telepathy/communication between minds without using traditional senses, clairvoyance/the power of the mind to know the past and predict the future, astrology/that the position of the stars and planets can affect people's lives, that people can communicate mentally with someone who has died, witches, reincarnation/the rebirth of the soul in a new body after death, and channeling/allowing a &quot;spirit-being&quot; to temporarily assume control of a body.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Etymology ==
[[File:Marcantonio Raimondi - Two Women with the Signs of Libra and Scorpio.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Marcantonio Raimondi engraving: 15th cent.]]

The word [[wikt:astrology|astrology]] comes from the early [[Latin]] word ''[[wikt:astrologia|astrologia]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=astrology |title = astrology |first = Douglas |last = Harper |authorlink = Douglas Harper |work = [[Online Etymology Dictionary]] |accessdate = 2011-12-06 |quote = Differentiation between astrology and astronomy began late 1400s and by 17c. this word was limited to &quot;reading influences of the stars and their effects on human destiny.&quot; }}&lt;/ref&gt; deriving from the Greek noun {{lang|grc|[[wikt:ἀστρολογία|ἀστρολογία]]}}, 'account of the stars'. ''Astrologia'' later passed into meaning 'star-divination' with ''[[wikt:astronomia|astronomia]]'' used for the scientific term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title = [[Oxford English Dictionary]] |chapter= astrology, n.| chapterurl = http://www.oed.com/viewdictionaryentry/Entry/12267 |edition = Second |date = 1989; online version September 2011 | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]]| quote = In Old French and Middle English astronomie seems to be the earlier and general word, astrologie having been subseq. introduced for the ‘art’ or practical application of astronomy to mundane affairs, and thus gradually limited by 17th cent. to the reputed influences of the stars, unknown to science. Not in Shakespeare.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Principles and practice ==
[[File:Vitruvian macrocosm.jpg|thumb|[[Robert Fludd|Robert Fludd's]] 16th century illustration of man the microcosm within the universal macrocosm]]
Advocates have defined astrology as a symbolic language, an [[art]] form, a [[science]], and a method of divination.&lt;ref&gt;''The New Encyclopaedia Britannica, Encyclopaedia Britannica,' v.5, 1974, p. 916&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dietrich, Thomas: 'The Origin of Culture and Civilization,'' Phenix &amp; Phenix Literary Publicists, 2005, p. 305&lt;/ref&gt;

Although most cultural systems of astrology share common roots in ancient philosophies that influenced each other, many have unique methodologies which differ from those developed in the West. These include Hindu astrology (also known as &quot;Indian astrology&quot; and in modern times referred to as &quot;Vedic astrology&quot;) and Chinese astrology, both of which have influenced the world's cultural history.

=== Western ===
{{Details|Western astrology}}
[[Western astrology]] is a form of [[divination]] based on the construction of a [[horoscope]] for an exact moment, such as a person's birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Philip P. Wiener, ed. in chief|title=Dictionary of the history of ideas|year=1974|publisher=Scribner|location=New York|isbn=0-684-13293-1|url=http://xtf.lib.virginia.edu/xtf/view?docId=DicHist/uvaBook/tei/DicHist1.xml;brand=default;}}&lt;/ref&gt; It uses the tropical zodiac, which is aligned to the [[ Equinox|equinoctial points]].&lt;ref&gt;James R. Lewis, 2003. ''The Astrology Book: the Encyclopedia of Heavenly Influences''. Visible Ink Press. Online at Google Books.&lt;/ref&gt;

Western astrology is founded on the movements and relative positions of celestial bodies such as the Sun, Moon, planets, which are analyzed by their movement through [[Astrological sign|signs]] of the [[zodiac]] (spatial divisions of the [[ecliptic]]) and by their [[Astrological aspect|aspects]] (angles) relative to one another. They are also considered by their placement in [[House (astrology)|houses]] (spatial divisions of the sky).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hone|first=Margaret|title=The Modern Text-Book of Astrology|year=1978|publisher=L. N. Fowler &amp; Co. Ltd.|location=Romford, U.K.|isbn=0852433573|pages=21-89}}&lt;/ref&gt; Astrology's modern representation in western popular media is usually reduced to [[sun sign astrology]], which considers only the zodiac sign of the Sun at an individual's date of birth, and  represents only 1/12 of the total chart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Riske|first=Kris|title=Llewellyn's Complete Book of Astrology|year=2007|publisher=Llewellyn Publications|location=Minnesota, USA|isbn=978-0-7387-1071-6|pages=5-6; 27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The names of the zodiac correspond to the names of the constellations originally within the respective segment and are in Latin.{{cn|date=August 2012}}

Along with [[tarot divination]], astrology is one of the core studies of [[Western esotericism]], and as such has influenced systems of [[magic (paranormal)|magical]] belief not only among Western esotericists and [[Hermeticism|Hermeticists]], but also belief systems such as [[Wicca]] that have borrowed from or been influenced by the Western esoteric tradition. [[Tanya Luhrmann]] has said that &quot;all magicians know something about astrology,&quot; and refers to a [[table of correspondences]] in [[Starhawk]]'s ''[[The Spiral Dance]]'', organized by [[planets in astrology|planet]], as an example of the astrological lore studied by magicians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Luhrmann&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Persuasions of the witch's craft: ritual magic in contemporary England | publisher=Harvard University Press | author=Luhrmann, Tanya | year=1991 | pages=147–151 | isbn=0-674-66324-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Brooklyn Museum - Page from an Astrological Treatise.jpg|upright|thumb|left|Page from an Astrological Treatise, ca. 1750]]

=== Indian and South Asian ===
{{Details|Hindu astrology}}
Hindu astrology originated with western astrology.&lt;ref name=Pingree1978&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pingree|first=David|title=Indian Astronomy|journal=Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society|date=18|year=1978|month=December|volume=122|series=American Philosophical Society|issue=6|pages=361-364|url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/986451|accessdate=4 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|361}} In the earliest [[Indian astronomy]] texts, the year was believed to be 360 days long, similar to that of Babylonian astrology, but the rest of the early astrological system bears little resemblance.&lt;ref name=Pingree1963&gt;{{cite journal|last=Pingree|first=David|title=Astronomy and Astrology in India and Iran|journal=Isis|year=1963|month=June|volume=54|series=The University of Chicago Press on behalf of The History of Science Society|issue=2|pages=229-246|url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/228540}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|229}} Later, the Indian techniques were augmented with some of the Babylonian techniques.&lt;ref name=Pingree1963 /&gt;{{rp|231}} Hindu astrology is oriented toward predicting one's fate or destiny.&lt;ref name=Braha&gt;{{cite book|last=Braha|first=James|title=How to predict your future : secrets of eastern &amp; western astrology{{verify credibility|date=August 2012}}|year=1995|publisher=Hermetician Press|location=Hollywood, FL|isbn=9780935895070}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|237}}{{verify-credibility|date=August 2012}} Hindu astrology relies on the [[Sidereal and tropical astrology|sidereal zodiac]] in which the signs of the zodiac are aligned to the position of the corresponding constellations in the sky. In order to maintain this alignment, Hindu astrology uses an adjustment, called ''[[ayanamsa]]'', to take into account the [[sidereal time|gradual precession]] of the [[Great Year|vernal equinox]] (the gradual shift in the orientation of the Earth's axis of rotation). In Hindu astrology the equinox occurs when the Sun is 6 degrees in Pisces. Western astrology places the equinox at the beginning of Aries, about 23 degrees after the equinox in the Hindu system.&lt;ref name=Braha /&gt;{{verify-credibility|date=August 2012}} Hindu astrology also includes several sub-systems of zodiac division, and employs the notion of [[bandhu]]: connections that, according to the [[Vedas]] link the outer and the inner worlds.{{fact|date=July 2012}}

[[Astrology in Sri Lanka|Sri Lankan astrology]] is largely based on Hindu astrology with some modifications to bring it in line with [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] teachings. [[Tibetan astrology]] also shares many of these components but has also been strongly influenced by Chinese culture and acknowledges a circle of animal signs similar to that of the Chinese zodiac (see below).{{cn|date=August 2012}}

=== Chinese and East-Asian ===
{{Details3|[[Chinese astrology]] and [[Chinese zodiac]]|this topic}}
Chinese astrology has a close relation with [[Chinese philosophy]] (theory of the three harmonies: heaven, earth and man) and uses concepts such as [[yin and yang]], the [[wu xing|Five phases]], the 10 [[Celestial stems]], the 12 [[Earthly Branches]], and [[shichen]] (時辰 a form of timekeeping used for religious purposes). The early use of Chinese astrology was mainly confined to [[political astrology]], the observation of unusual phenomena, identification of [[portent (divination)|portent]]s and the selection of auspicious days for events and decisions.&lt;ref name=Kistemaker&gt;{{cite book|first=Sun, Xiaochun|title=The Chinese sky during the Han : constellating stars and society|year=1997|publisher=Brill|location=Leiden|isbn=978-90-04-10737-3|coauthors=Kistemaker, Jacob}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|22,85,176}}

The constellations of the Zodiac of western Asia and Europe were not used; instead the sky is divided into [[Three Enclosures]] (三垣 sān yuán), and [[Twenty-eight Mansions]] (二十八宿 èrshíbā xiù) in twelve Ci ([[:zh:分野|十二次]]).&lt;ref&gt;F. Richard Stephenson, &quot;Chinese Roots of Modern Astronomy&quot;, ''New Scientist'', 26 June 1980. See also [http://www.lamost.org/~yzhao/history/xiu28.html 二十八宿的形成与演变]&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese zodiac of twelve [[Astrological sign#Chinese zodiac signs|animal signs]] is said to represent twelve different types of personality. It is based on cycles of years, lunar months, and two-hour periods of the day (the shichen). The zodiac traditionally begins with the sign of the [[Rat (zodiac)|Rat]], and the cycle proceeds through 11 other animals signs: the [[Ox (zodiac)|Ox]], [[Tiger (zodiac)|Tiger]], [[Rabbit (zodiac)|Rabbit]], [[Dragon (zodiac)|Dragon]], [[Snake (zodiac)|Snake]], [[Horse (zodiac)|Horse]], [[Goat (zodiac)|Goat]], [[Monkey (zodiac)|Monkey]], [[Rooster (zodiac)|Rooster]], [[Dog (zodiac)|Dog]] and [[Pig (zodiac)|Pig]].&lt;ref&gt;Theodora Lau, ''The Handbook of Chinese Horoscopes'', pp2-8, 30–5, 60–4, 88–94, 118–24, 148–53, 178–84, 208–13, 238–44, 270–78, 306–12, 338–44, Souvenir Press, New York, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Complex systems of predicting fate and destiny based on one's birthday, birth season, and birth hours, such as ''ziping'' and [[Zi wei dou shu|Zi Wei Dou Shu]] ({{zh|s=紫微斗数|t=紫微斗數|p=zǐwēidǒushù}}) are still used regularly in modern day Chinese astrology. They do not rely on direct observations of the stars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://books.google.bg/books?id=raKRY3KQspsC&amp;pg=PA76&amp;dq=astrology+in+China+Springer&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=7NILUNvWDeeq0AWD1djHCg&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA | title=Astrology in China | publisher=Springer | work=Encyclopaedia of the History of Science, Technology, and Medicine in Non-Western Cultures | date=1997 | accessdate=July 22, 2012 | editor=Selin, Helaine|editor-link=Helaine Selin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Korean zodiac is identical to the Chinese one. The Vietnamese zodiac is almost identical to Chinese zodiac except that the second animal is the [[water buffalo (zodiac)|Water Buffalo]] instead of the Ox, and the fourth animal is the [[cat (zodiac)|Cat]] instead of the Rabbit. The Japanese zodiac includes the [[Wild Boar]] instead of the Pig. The Thai zodiac includes a [[naga (mythology)|Naga]] in place of the Dragon and begins, not at Chinese New Year, but at either on the first day of fifth month in Thai lunar calendar, or during the Songkran festival (now celebrated every 13–15 April), depending on the purpose of the use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=การเปลี่ยนวันใหม่ การนับวัน ทางโหราศาสตร์ไทย การเปลี่ยนปีนักษัตร โหราศาสตร์  ดูดวง ทำนายทายทัก |url=http://www.myhora.com/%E0%B8%AA%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%9E%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%99%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%AB%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A8%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%AA%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%A3%E0%B9%8C/%E0%B8%81%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%99%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%9A%E0%B8%A7%E0%B8%B1%E0%B8%99%E0%B8%97%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%87%E0%B9%82%E0%B8%AB%E0%B8%A3%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%A8%E0%B8%B2%E0%B8%AA%E0%B8%95%E0%B8%A3%E0%B9%8C-004.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{Main|History of astrology}}

=== Ancient world ===
{{Details3|[[Babylonian astrology]] and [[Hellenistic astrology]]|ancient astrology}}

Astrology, in its broadest sense, is the search for meaning in the sky. It has therefore been argued that astrology began as a study as soon as human beings made conscious attempts to measure, record, and predict seasonal changes by reference to astronomical cycles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Campion|first=Nicholas|title=History of western astrology. Volume II, The medieval and modern worlds.|year=2009|publisher=Continuum.|location=London [u.a.]|isbn=978-1-4411-8129-9|edition=1. publ.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|2,3}} Early evidence of such practices appears as markings on bones and cave walls, which show that lunar cycles were being noted as early as 25,000 years ago; the first step towards recording the Moon’s influence upon tides and rivers, and towards organizing a communal calendar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Marshack|first=Alexander|title=The roots of civilization : the cognitive beginnings of man's first art, symbol and notation|year=1991|publisher=Moyer Bell|location=Mount Kisco, N.Y.|isbn=978-1-55921-041-6|edition=Rev. and expanded.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|81ff}} Agricultural needs were also met by increasing knowledge of constellations, whose appearances change with the seasons, allowing the rising of particular star-groups to herald annual floods or seasonal activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Evelyn-White|first=Hesiod ; with an English translation by Hugh G.|title=The Homeric hymns and Homerica|year=1977|publisher=Harvard University Press|location=Cambridge, Mass.|isbn=978-0-674-99063-0|edition=Reprinted.|quote=Fifty days after the solstice, when the season of wearisome heat is come to an end, is the right time to go sailing. Then you will not wreck your ship, nor will the sea destroy the sailors, unless Poseidon the Earth-Shaker be set upon it, or Zeus, the king of the deathless gods|pages=663-677}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{verify-inline|date=July 2012}} By the third millennium BCE, widespread civilizations had developed sophisticated awareness of celestial cycles, and are believed to have consciously oriented their temples to create alignment with the heliacal risings of the stars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Aveni|first=David H. Kelley, Eugene F. Milone ; foreword by Anthony F.|title=Exploring ancient skies an encyclopedic survey of archaeoastronomy|year=2005|publisher=Springer|location=New York|isbn=978-0-387-95310-6|page=268|edition=Online-Ausg.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is scattered evidence to suggest that the oldest known astrological references are copies of texts made during this period. Two, from the [[Venus tablet of Ammisaduqa]] (compiled in [[Babylon]] around 1700 BCE) are reported to have been made during the reign of king [[Sargon of Akkad]] (2334–2279 BCE).&lt;ref&gt;Two texts which refer to the 'omens of Sargon' are reported in E. F. Weidner, ‘Historiches Material in der Babyonischen Omina-Literatur’ ''Altorientalische Studien'', ed. Bruno Meissner, (Leipzig, 1928-9), v. 231 and 236.&lt;/ref&gt; Another, showing an early use of [[electional astrology]], is ascribed to the reign of the [[Sumer]]ian ruler [[Gudea of Lagash]] (ca. 2144–2124 BCE). This describes how the gods revealed to him in a dream the constellations that would be most favorable for the planned construction of a temple.&lt;ref&gt;From scroll A of the ruler Gudea of Lagash, I 17 – VI 13. O. Kaiser, ''Texte aus der Umwelt des Alten Testaments'', Bd. 2, 1–3. Gütersloh, 1986–1991. Also quoted in A. Falkenstein, ‘Wahrsagung in der sumerischen Überlieferung’, ''La divination en Mésopotamie ancienne et dans les régions voisines''. Paris, 1966.&lt;/ref&gt; However, there is controversy about whether they were genuinely recorded at the time or merely ascribed to ancient rulers by posterity. The oldest undisputed evidence of the use of astrology as an integrated system of knowledge is therefore attributed to the records of the first dynasty of [[Mesopotamia]] (1950–1651 BCE).

The system of Chinese astrology was elaborated during the [[Zhou dynasty]] (1046–256 BC) and flourished during the [[Han Dynasty]] (2nd century BC to 2nd century AD), during which all the familiar elements of traditional Chinese culture – the Yin-Yang philosophy, theory of the 5 elements, Heaven and Earth, Confucian morality – were brought together to formalise the philosophical principles of Chinese medicine and divination, astrology and alchemy.&lt;ref name=Kistemaker /&gt;{{rp|3,4}}

=== Medieval Islamic world ===
{{Details|Astrology in medieval Islam}}
[[File:Translation of Albumasar Venice 1515 De Magnis Coniunctionibus.jpg|thumb|alt=Image of a Latin astrological text |[[Latin]] translation of Abū Maʿshar's ''De Magnis Coniunctionibus'' (‘Of the great [[Conjunction (astronomy and astrology)|conjunctions]]’), [[Venice]], 1515.]]Astrology was taken up by Islamic scholars following the collapse of [[Alexandria]] to the Arabs in the 7th century, and the founding of the [[Abbasid Caliphate|Abbasid empire]] in the 8th. The second Abbasid [[caliph]], [[Al Mansur]] (754–775) founded the city of [[Baghdad]] to act as a centre of learning, and included in its design a library-translation centre known as ''Bayt al-Hikma'' ‘Storehouse of Wisdom’, which continued to receive development from his heirs and was to provide a major impetus for Arabic-Persian translations of Hellenistic astrological texts. The early translators included [[Mashallah ibn Athari|Mashallah]], who helped to elect the time for the foundation of Baghdad,&lt;ref name=Biruni&gt;{{cite book|author=Bīrūnī, Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad|title=The chronology of ancient nations|year=1879.|publisher=London, Pub. for the Oriental translations fund of Great Britain &amp; Ireland by W. H. Allen and co.|LCCN=01006783|chapter=VIII}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Sahl ibn Bishr]], (''a.k.a.'' ''Zael''), whose texts were directly influential upon later European astrologers such as [[Guido Bonatti]] in the 13th century, and [[William Lilly]] in the 17th century. Knowledge of Arabic texts started to become imported into Europe during the [[Latin translations of the 12th century]], the effect of which was to help initiate the European [[Renaissance]].

Other important Arabic astrologers include [[Ja'far ibn Muhammad Abu Ma'shar al-Balkhi|Albumasur]] and [[Al Khwarizmi]], the Persian mathematician, astronomer and astrologer, who is considered the father of [[algebra]] and the [[algorithm]]. The Arabs greatly increased the knowledge of astronomical cycles, and many of the [[List of traditional star names|star names]] that remain in common use today, such as [[Aldebaran]], [[Altair]], [[Betelgeuse]], [[Rigel]] and [[Vega]] retain the legacy of their language.

=== Since 1900 ===
{{expand section|date=September 2012}}
Astrology saw a popular revival from the nineteenth century as part of a general revival of [[spiritualism]] and later [[New Age]] philosophy&lt;ref name=Campion-2009 /&gt;{{rp|239-249}}, and through the influence of mass media such as newspaper horoscopes&lt;ref name=Campion-2009 /&gt;{{rp|259-263}} and [[astrology software]]. Early in the twentieth century psychologist Carl Jung developed some concepts concerning astrology,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=selected|first=C.G. Jung ;|title=C.G. Jung Letters : 1906-1950.|year=19uu|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, NJ|isbn=978-0-691-09895-1|coauthors=Hull, edited by Gerhard Adler, in collaboration with Aniela Jaffé ; translations from the German by R.F.C.|quote=Letter from Jung to Freud, 12 June 1911 “I made horoscopic calculations in order to find a clue to the core of psychological truth.”}}&lt;/ref&gt; which led to the development of [[psychological astrology]].&lt;ref name=Campion-2009&gt;{{cite book|last=Campion|first=Nicholas|title=History of western astrology. Volume II, The medieval and modern worlds.|year=2009|publisher=Continuum.|location=London [u.a.]|isbn=9781441181299|edition=1. publ.|quote=At the same time, in Switzerland, the psychologist Carl Gustav Jung (1875–1961) was developing sophisticated theories concerning astrology...}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|251-256}}&lt;ref&gt;Gieser, Suzanne. ''The Innermost Kernel, Depth Psychology and Quantum Physics. Wolfgang Pauli’s Dialogue with C.G.Jung'', (Springer, Berlin, 2005) p. 21 ISBN 3-540-20856-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Campion, Nicholas. &quot;''Prophecy, Cosmology and the New Age Movement. The Extent and Nature of Contemporary Belief in Astrology.''&quot;( Bath Spa University College, 2003) via Campion, Nicholas, ''History of Western Astrology'', (Continuum Books, London &amp; New York, 2009) pp. 248, 256, ISBN 978-1-84725-224-1&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cultural influence ==
{{Main|Cultural influence of astrology}}
In the West there have been occasional reports of political leaders consulting astrologers. [[Louis de Wohl]] worked as an astrologer for the British intelligence agency [[MI5]], after it was claimed that [[Hitler]] used astrology to time his actions. The War Office was &quot;interested to know what Hitler's own astrologers would be telling him from week to week&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=JrdVAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=5bADAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6779,6948658&amp;dq=hitler-astrologer&amp;hl=en | title=The Strange Story Of Britain's &quot;State Seer&quot; | publisher=The Sydney Morning Herald | date=August 30, 1952 | accessdate=July 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In fact de Wohl's predictions were so inaccurate that he was soon labelled a &quot;complete charlatan&quot; and it was later shown that Hitler considered astrology to be &quot;complete nonsense&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2008/mar/04/nationalarchives.secondworldwar | title=Star turn: astrologer who became SOE's secret weapon against Hitler | publisher=The Guardian | date=March 4, 2008 | accessdate=July 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; After [[John Hinckley|John Hinckley's]] attempted assassination of U.S. President [[Ronald Reagan]], first lady [[Nancy Reagan]] commissioned astrologer [[Joan Quigley]] to act as the secret White House astrologer. However, Quigley's role ended in 1988 when it became public through the memoirs of former chief of staff, [[Donald Regan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Regan|first=Donald T.|title=For the record : from Wall Street to Washington|year=1988|publisher=Harcourt Brace Jovanovich|location=San Diego|isbn=0-15-163966-3|edition=1st ed.}}
* {{cite book|last=Quigley|first=Joan|title=What does Joan say? : my seven years as White House astrologer to Nancy and Ronald Reagan|year=1990|publisher=Birch Lane Press|location=Secaucus, NJ|isbn=1-55972-032-8}}
* {{cite news|first=Cynthia Gorney|title=The Reagan Chart Watch; Astrologer Joan Quigley, Eye on the Cosmos|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/access/73606295.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=May+11%2C+1988&amp;author=Cynthia+Gorney&amp;pub=The+Washington+Post+%28pre-1997+Fulltext%29&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=c.01&amp;desc=The+Reagan+Chart+Watch%3B+Astrologer+Joan+Quigley%2C+Eye+on+the+Cosmos|publisher=The Washington Post|accessdate=17 July 2012|newspaper=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Bdrates of Japan since 1950.svg|thumb|right|Birth and death rates of Japan since 1950, with the sudden drop in hinoeuma year(1966)]]
In [[India]], there is a long-established and widespread belief in astrology. It is commonly used for daily life, particularly in matters concerning marriage and career, and makes extensive use of [[electional astrology|electional]], [[horary astrology|horary]] and [[karmic astrology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wideind&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=BV Raman Dies |publisher=New York Times, 23 December 1998 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1998/12/23/world/bangalore-venkata-raman-indian-astrologer-dies-at-86.html |accessdate= 2009-05-12 |first=Michael T. |last=Kaufman |date=23 December 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fof&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Fame and Fortune |author=Dipankar Das, May 1996 |url=http://www.lifepositive.com/mind/predictive-sciences/astrology.asp |accessdate=2009-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indian politics has also been influenced by astrology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/428081.stm | title=Soothsayers offer heavenly help | publisher=BBC News | accessdate=July 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It remains considered a branch of the [[Vedanga]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In countries such as India, where only a small intellectual elite has been trained in Western physics, astrology manages to retain here and there its position among the sciences.&quot; David Pingree and Robert Gilbert, &quot;Astrology; Astrology In India; Astrology in modern times&quot;. [[Encyclopædia Britannica]], 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mohan Rao, Female foeticide: where do we go? Indian Journal of Medical Ethics Oct-Dec2001-9(4)[http://www.issuesinmedicalethics.org/094co123.html]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, Indian scientists and politicians debated and critiqued a proposal to use state money to fund research into astrology,&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC_India&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/sci_tech/highlights/010531_vedic.shtml |title=Indian Astrology vs Indian Science |publisher=BBC |date=31 May 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; resulting in permission for Indian universities to offer courses in Vedic astrology.&lt;ref name=&quot;UGC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Guidelines for Setting up Departments of Vedic Astrology in Universities Under the Purview of University Grants Commission|url=http://www.education.nic.in/circulars/astrologycurriculum.htm|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110512154221/http://www.education.nic.in/circulars/astrologycurriculum.htm|archivedate=2011-05-12|publisher=Government of India, Department of Education|accessdate=26 March 2011|quote=There is an urgent need to rejuvenate the science of Vedic Astrology in India, to allow this scientific knowledge to reach to the society at large and to provide opportunities to get this important science even exported to the world,}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2011, the Bombay High Court reaffirmed astrology's standing in India when it dismissed a case which had challenged its status as a science.&lt;ref&gt;'Astrology is a science: Bombay HC', [http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Astrology-is-a-science-Bombay-HC/articleshow/7418795.cms The Times of India], 3 February 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Japan]], a strong belief in astrology has led to dramatic changes in the fertility rate and the number of abortions in the years of &quot;Fire Horse&quot;. Women born in these years are called ''hinoeuma'', and believed to be unmarriageable and to bring bad luck to their father or husband. In 1966, the number of babies born in Japan dropped by over 25% as parents tried to avoid the stigma of having a daughter born in the hinoeuma year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1bTGN21ev2MC&amp;pg=PA22&amp;dq=hinoeuma&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=66cLUMDsPMuxrAfBso3ICA&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAQ | title=Japanese childrearing: two generations of scholarship | date=1996 | accessdate=July 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=uAOrAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA22&amp;dq=hinoeuma&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=66cLUMDsPMuxrAfBso3ICA&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwAw | title=The Political Economy of Japan: Cultural and social dynamics | date=1992 | accessdate=July 22, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Scientific appraisal ==
Astrology is a [[pseudoscience]]&lt;ref name=SandPSandAstroSoc&gt;{{cite web|first=Sven Ove Hansson, Edward N. Zalta|title=Science and Pseudo-Science|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/pseudo-science/|publisher=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy|accessdate=6 July 2012}}
* {{cite web|title=Astronomical Pseudo-Science: A Skeptic's Resource List |publisher=Astronomical Society of the Pacific |url=http://www.astrosociety.org/education/resources/pseudobib.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hartmann&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hartmann|first=P|coauthors=Reuter M, Nyborga H|title=The relationship between date of birth and individual differences in personality and general intelligence: A large-scale study|journal=Personality and Individual Differences|year=2006|month=May|volume=40|issue=7|pages=1349–1362|doi=10.1016/j.paid.2005.11.017|quote=To optimise the chances of finding even remote relationships between date of birth and individual differences in personality and intelligence we further applied two different strategies. The first one was based on the common chronological concept of time (e.g. month of birth and season of birth). The second strategy was based on the (pseudo-scientific) concept of astrology (e.g. Sun Signs, The Elements, and astrological gender), as discussed in the book ‘‘Astrology: Science or superstition?’’ by Eysenck and Nias (1982).}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|1350}} that has not demonstrated its effectiveness in [[Empiricism|controlled studies]] and has no scientific validity.&lt;ref name=Zarka /&gt;&lt;ref name=Cosmic&gt;{{cite book|first=Jeffrey Bennett, Megan Donohue, Nicholas Schneider, Mark Voit|title=The cosmic perspective|year=2007|publisher=Pearson/Addison-Wesley|location=San Francisco, Calif.|isbn=0805392831|pages=82–84|edition=4th ed.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|85}} The majority of professional astrologers rely on performing astrology-based personality tests and making relevant predictions about the remunerators future.&lt;ref name=Cosmic /&gt;{{rp|83}} Those who continue to have faith in astrology have been characterized as doing so &quot;in spite of the fact that there is no verified scientific basis for their beliefs, and indeed that there is strong evidence to the contrary.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;humanist&quot; /&gt; [[Astrophysicist]] [[Neil deGrasse Tyson]] commented on astrological belief, saying that &quot;part of knowing how to think is knowing how the laws of nature shape the world around us. Without that knowledge, without that capacity to think, you can easily become a victim of people who seek to take advantage of you&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/aponline/20010827/aponline135357_000.htm|work=The Washington Post|date=27 August 2001|title=Ariz. Astrology School Accredited}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The former astrologer, and scientist, Geoffrey Deans and psychologist Ivan Kelly&lt;ref name=FailToPredict&gt;{{cite news|last=Matthews|first=Robert|title=Astrologers fail to predict proof they are wrong|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1439101/Astrologers-fail-to-predict-proof-they-are-wrong.html|accessdate=13 July 2012|newspaper=The Telegraph|date=17 Aug 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; conducted a large scale scientific test, involving more than one hundred [[cognitive]], [[behavioral]], [[physiological|physical]] and other variables, but found no support for astrology.&lt;ref name=Geoffrey&gt;{{cite journal|title=Is Astrology Relevant to Consciousness and Psi?|author=Dean G, Kelly I.W.|journal=Journal of Consciousness Studies|year=2003|volume=10|issue=6-7|pages=175-198}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, a meta-analysis was conducted pooling 40 studies consisting of 700 astrologers and over 1000 birth charts. Ten of the tests, which had a total of 300 participants, involved subjects picking the correct chart interpretation out of a number of others which were not the astrologically correct chart interpretation (usually 3 to 5 others). When the date and other obvious clues were removed no significant results were found to suggest there was any preferred chart.&lt;ref name=Geoffrey /&gt;{{rp|190}} A further test involved 45 confident{{efn|The level of confidence was self rated by the astrologers themselves.}} astrologers, with an average of 10 years experience and 160 participants (out of an original sample size of 1198 participants) who strongly favoured certain characteristics in the [[Eysenck Personality Questionnaire]] to extremes.&lt;ref name=Geoffrey /&gt;{{rp|191}} The astrologers performed much worse than merely basing decisions off the individuals age, and much worse than 45 control subjects who did not use birth charts at all.{{efn|Also discussed in {{cite book|last=Martens|first=Ronny|title=Making sense of astrology|year=1998|publisher=Prometheus Books|location=Amherst, N.Y.|isbn=1573922188|coauthors=Trachet, Tim}}}}&lt;ref name=Geoffrey /&gt;{{rp|191}}

Science and non-science are often distinguished by the criterion of [[falsifiability]]. The criterion was first proposed by [[philosopher of science]] [[Karl Popper]]. To Popper, science does not rely on [[Inductive_reasoning|induction]], instead scientific investigations are inherently attempts to falsify existing theories through novel tests. If a single test fails, then the theory is falsified. Therefore, any test of a scientific theory must prohibit certain results which will falsify the theory, and expect other specific results which will be consistent with the theory. Using this criterion of falsifiability, astrology is a pseudoscience.&lt;ref name=PopperStanford&gt;{{cite web|authors=Stephen Thornton, Edward N. Zalta (older edition)|title=Karl Popper|url=http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/popper/|publisher=Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy}}&lt;/ref&gt; Popper regarded astrology as &quot;pseudo-empirical&quot; in that &quot;it appeals to observation and experiment&quot;, but &quot;nevertheless does not come up to scientific standards&quot;.&lt;ref name=Popper /&gt;{{rp|44}} 

In 1953, sociologist [[Theodor W. Adorno]] conducted a study of the astrology column of a Los Angeles newspaper as part of a project examining mass culture in capitalist society. Adorno concluded that astrology was a large-scale manifestation of systematic irrationalism, where individuals were subtly being led to believe that the author of the column was addressing them directly through the use of flattery and vague generalizations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adorno&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://journal.telospress.com/content/1974/19/13.short|title=The Stars Down to Earth: The Los Angeles Times Astrology Column|author=Theodor W. Adorno | journal=Telos | year=1974 | month=Spring | volume=1974 | issue=19 | pages=13-90 | doi=10.3817/0374019013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cognitive bias ===
{{see also|Forer effect}}
It has also been suggested that much of the continued faith in astrology could be [[Psychology|psychologically]] explained as a matter of [[cognitive bias]].&lt;ref name=Eysenck1982&gt;{{cite book|last=Eysenck|first=H.J.|title=Astrology : science or superstition?|year=1984|publisher=Penguin Books|location=Harmondsworth|isbn=0-14-022397-5|coauthors=Nias, D.K.B.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|42-48}} In 1949 [[Bertram Forer]] conducted a personality test on students.&lt;ref name=Forer&gt;{{cite journal|last=Forer|first=Bertram R.|title=The fallacy of personal validation: a classroom demonstration of gullibility.|journal=The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology|date=1 January 1949|volume=44|issue=1|pages=118–123|doi=10.1037/h0059240|accessdate=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; While seemingly giving the students individualized results, he instead gave each student exactly the same sheet that discussed their personality. The personality descriptions were taken from a book on Astrology. When the students were asked to comment on the accuracy of the test with a rating more than 40% gave it the top mark of 5 out of 5, and the average rating was 4.2.&lt;ref name=Paul&gt;{{cite book|last=Paul|first=Annie Murphy|title=The cult of personality testing : how personality tests are leading us to miseducate our children, mismanage our companies, and misunderstand ourselves.|year=2005|publisher=Free Press|location=New York, N.Y.|isbn=0743280725|edition=1st pbk. ed.|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|134, 135}} The results of this study have been replicated in numerous other studies.&lt;ref name=Rogers&gt;{{cite journal|last=Rogers|first=P.|coauthors=Soule, J.|title=Cross-Cultural Differences in the Acceptance of Barnum Profiles Supposedly Derived From Western Versus Chinese Astrology|journal=Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology|date=5 March 2009|volume=40|issue=3|pages=381–399|doi=10.1177/0022022109332843}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|382}} Thus, study of this Barnum/Forer effect has been mostly focused on the level of acceptance of fake horoscopes and fake astrological personality profiles.&lt;ref name=Rogers /&gt;{{rp|382}} Recipients of these personality assessments consistently fail to distinguish common and uncommon personality descriptors.&lt;ref name=Rogers /&gt;{{rp|383}}

By a process known as self-attribution, it has been shown in numerous studies that individuals with knowledge of astrology tend to describe their personality in terms of traits compatible with their star sign. The effect is heightened when the individuals were aware the personality description was being used to discuss astrology. Individuals who were not familiar with astrology had no such tendency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wunder|first=Edgar|title=Self-attribution, sun-sign traits, and the alleged role of favourableness as a moderator variable: long-term effect or artefact?|journal=Personality and Individual Differences|date=1 December 2003|volume=35|issue=8|pages=1783–1789|doi=10.1016/S0191-8869(03)00002-3|quote=The effect was replicated several times (Eysenck &amp; Nias 1981,1982; Fichten &amp; Sunerton, 1983; Jackson, 1979; Kelly, 1982; Smithers &amp; Cooper, 1978), even if no reference to astrology was made until the debriefing of the subjects (Hamilton, 1995; Van Rooij, 1994, 1999), or if the data were gathered originally for a purpose which has nothing to do with astrology at all (Clarke, Gabriels, &amp; Barnes, 1996; Van Rooij, Brak, &amp; Commandeur, 1988), but the effect is stronger when a cue is given to the subjects that the study is about astrology (Van Rooij 1994). Early evidence for sun-sign derived self-attribution effects has already been reported by Silverman (1971) and Delaney &amp; Woodyard (1974). In studies with subjects unfamiliar with the meaning of the astrological sun-sign symbolism, no effect was observed (Fourie, 1984; Jackson &amp; Fiebert, 1980; Kanekar &amp; Mukherjee, 1972; Mohan, Bhandari, &amp; Meena, 1982; Mohan and Gulati, 1986; Saklofske, Kelly, &amp; McKerracher, 1982; Silverman &amp; Whitmer, 1974; Veno &amp; Pamment, 1979). }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Lack of consistency ===
Testing the validity of astrology can be hard because there is no consensus amongst astrologers as to what astrology is or what it can predict.&lt;ref name=Cosmic /&gt;{{rp|83}} Most professional astrologers are paid to predict the future or describe a person's personality and life, but most horoscopes only make vague untestable statements that can almost apply to any individual.&lt;ref name=Cosmic /&gt;{{rp|83}} Astrologers avoid making verifiable predictions and instead rely on making vague statements which allows them to try to avoid falsification.&lt;ref name=Popper&gt;{{cite book|last=Popper|first=Karl|title=Conjectures and refutations : the growth of scientific knowledge|year=2004|publisher=Routledge|location=London|isbn=0-415-28594-1|edition=Reprinted.|chapter=}}
* The relevant piece is also published in, {{cite book|last=Schick Jr|first=Theodore,|title=Readings in the philosophy of science : from positivism to postmodernism|year=2000|publisher=Mayfield Pub|location=Mountain View, CA|isbn=0767402774|pages=33-39}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|48-49}}

[[Georges Charpak]] and Henri Broch dealt with claims from astrology in the book ''Debunked! ESP, Telekinesis, and other Pseudoscience''.&lt;ref name=CharpakObit&gt;{{cite web|last=Giomataris|first=Ioannis|title=Nature Obituary Georges Charpak (1924–2010)|url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v467/n7319/full/4671048a.html|publisher=Nature|accessdate=13 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; They pointed out that astrologers have only a small knowledge of astronomy and that they often do not take into account basic features such as the [[Precession#Axial precession (precession of the equinoxes)|precession of the equinoxes]] which would change the position of the sun with time; they commented on the example of Elizabeth Teissier who claimed that &quot;the sun ends up in the same place in the sky on the same date each year&quot; as the basis for claims that two people with the same birthday but a number of years apart should be under the same planetary influence. Charpak and Broch noted that &quot;there is a difference of about twenty-two thousand miles between Earth's location on any specific date in two successive years&quot; and that thus they should not be under the same influence according to astrology. Over a 40 years period there would be a difference greater than 780,000 miles.&lt;ref name=Charpak&gt;{{cite book|last=Charpak|first=Georges|title=Debunked! : ESP, telekinesis, and other pseudoscience|year=2004|publisher=Johns Hopkins Univ. Press|location=Baltimore [u.a.9|isbn=0801878675|coauthors=Holland, Henri Broch ; translated by Bart K.|url=http://books.google.ie/books?id=DpnWcMzeh8oC&amp;q=astrology#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|page=6,7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The tropical zodiac has no connection to the stars and avoids the issue with precession moving the constellations as long as they make no reference to the constellations themselves being in the associated zodiacal sign.&lt;ref name=Charpak /&gt; Charpak and Broch, noting this, referred to astrology based on the tropical zodiac as being &quot;empty boxes that have nothing to do with anything and are devoid of any consistency or correspondence with the stars&quot;.&lt;ref name=Charpak/&gt; Sole usage of the tropical zodiac is inconsistent with references made, by the same astrologers, to the [[Age of Aquarius]] which is dependent on when the vernal point enters the constellation of Aquarius.&lt;ref name=Zarka /&gt;

Some astrologers make claims that the position of all the planets must be taken into account, but astrologers were unable to predict the existence of Neptune based on mistakes in horoscopes. Instead Neptune was predicted using [[Newton's law of universal gravitation]].&lt;ref name=Cosmic/&gt; The grafting on of Uranus, Neptune and Pluto into the astrology discourse was done on an ad-hoc basis.&lt;ref name=Zarka /&gt;

On the demotion of Pluto to the status of [[dwarf planet]], Philip Zarka of the Paris Observatory in Meudon, France wondered how astrologers should respond:&lt;ref name=Zarka /&gt;

{{quote|Should astrologers remove it from the list of luminars [Sun, Moon and the 8 planets other than earth] and confess that it did not actually bring any improvement? If they decide to keep it, what about the growing list of other recently discovered similar bodies (Sedna, Quaoar. etc), some of which even have satellites (Xena, 2003EL61)?}}

=== Lack of mechanism ===
Astrology has been criticized for failing to provide a [[Physical property|physical mechanism]] that links the movements of celestial bodies to their purported effects on human behaviour. In a lecture in 2001, [[Stephen Hawking]] stated &quot;The reason most scientists don't believe in astrology is because it is not consistent with our theories that have been tested by experiment.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=British Physicist Debunks Astrology in Indian Lecture |agency=Associated Press |url=http://www.beliefnet.com/story/63/story_6346_1.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1975, amid increasing popular interest in astrology, ''The Humanist'' magazine presented a rebuttal of astrology in a statement put together by [[Bart J. Bok]], Lawrence E. Jerome, and [[Paul Kurtz]].&lt;ref name=&quot;humanist&quot; /&gt; The statement, entitled ‘Objections to Astrology’, was signed by 186 astronomers, physicists and leading scientists of the day. They said that there is no scientific foundation for the tenets of astrology and warned the public against accepting astrological advice without question. Their criticism focused on the fact that there was no mechanism whereby astrological effects might occur:
{{quote|We can see how infinitesimally small are the gravitational and other effects produced by the distant planets and the far more distant stars. It is simply a mistake to imagine that the forces exerted by stars and planets at the moment of birth can in any way shape our futures.&lt;ref name=&quot;humanist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Objections to Astrology: A Statement by 186 Leading Scientists |publisher=The Humanist, September/October 1975 |url=http://www.americanhumanist.org/about/astrology.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090318140638/http://www.americanhumanist.org/about/astrology.html|archivedate=18 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Philosophy of Science and the Occult|chapter=Objections to Astrology: A Statement by 186 Leading Scientists|year=1982|publisher=State University of New York Press|location=Albany|isbn=0-87395-572-2|pages=14–18|author=Bok, Bart J.|coauthors=Lawrence E. Jerome, Paul Kurtz|editor=Patrick Grim}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Astronomer [[Carl Sagan]] declined to sign the statement. Sagan said he took this stance not because he thought astrology had any validity, but because he thought that the tone of the statement was authoritarian, and that dismissing astrology because there was no mechanism (while &quot;certainly a relevant point&quot;) was not in itself convincing. In a letter published in a follow-up edition of ''The Humanist'', Sagan confirmed that he would have been willing to sign such a statement had it described and refuted the principal tenets of astrological belief. This, he argued, would have been more persuasive and would have produced less controversy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Humanist_letter&quot;&gt;[http://thehumanist.org/the-humanist-archive/ The Humanist], volume 36, no.5 (1976).&lt;/ref&gt;

Many astrologers claim that astrology is scientific.&lt;ref name=ChrisFrench&gt;{{cite web|last=Chris|first=French|title=Astrologers and other inhabitants of parallel universes|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/2012/feb/07/astrologers-parallel-universes|publisher=The Guardian|work=7 February 2012|accessdate=8 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of these astrologers have proposed conventional causal agents such as electromagnetism and gravity.&lt;ref name=ChrisFrench/&gt;&lt;ref name=SundayTimes /&gt; Scientists dismiss these mechanisms as implausible&lt;ref name=ChrisFrench /&gt; since, for example, the magnetic field, when measured from earth, of a large but distant planet such as Jupiter is far smaller than that produced by ordinary household appliances.&lt;ref name=SundayTimes&gt;{{cite web|last=Randi|first=James|title=UK MEDIA NONSENSE — AGAIN|url=http://www.randi.org/jr/052104uk.html|work=21 May 2004|publisher=Swift, Online newspaper of the [[JREF]]|accessdate=8 July 2012|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110722055123/http://randi.org/jr/052104uk.html||archivedate=22 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other astrologers prefer not to attempt to explain astrology,&lt;ref name=&quot;Harding-prejudice&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Prejudice in Astrological Research |author=M. Harding |publisher=Correlation, Vol 19(1) |url=http://www.astrozero.co.uk/astroscience/harding.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{dubious|date=June 2012|reason=While this person is an astrologer and does make the statement, it seems an inappropriate source to generalize to more than one astrologer}} and instead give it supernatural explanations such as [[divination]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Curry|first=Geoffrey Cornelius ; foreword by Patrick|title=The moment of astrology : origins in divination|year=2003|publisher=Wessex Astrologer|location=Bournemouth|isbn=1-902405-11-0|edition=Rev. and expanded 2nd ed.|quote=despite all appearances of objectivity and natural law. It is divination despite the fact that aspects of symbolism can be approached through scientific method, and despite the possibility that some factors in horoscopy can arguably be validated by the appeal to science.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|xxii}} Carl Jung sought to invoke synchronicity to explain results on astrology from a single study he conducted, where no statistically significant results were observed. Sychronicity itself is considered to be neither testable nor falsifiable.&lt;ref name=Shermer&gt;{{cite book|last=editor|first=Michael Shermer,|title=The Skeptic encyclopedia of pseudoscience.|year=2002|publisher=ABC-CLIO|location=Santa Barbara, Calif.|isbn=1576076539|page=241}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study was subsequently heavily criticised for its non-random sample and its use of statistics and also its lack of consistency with astrology.{{efn|Jung made the claims, despite being aware that there was no statistical significance in the results. Looking for coincidences post hoc is of very dubious value, see [[Misuse_of_statistics#Data_dredging]].&lt;ref name=Shermer /&gt;}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Samuels|first=Andrew|title=Jung and the post-Jungians|year=1990|publisher=Tavistock/Routledge|location=London|isbn=0203359291|page=80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Carlson's experiment ===
Across several centuries of testing, the predictions of astrology have never been more accurate than that expected by chance alone.&lt;ref name=Cosmic /&gt; One approach used in testing astrology quantitatively is through [[blind experiment]]. When specific predictions from astrologers were tested in rigorous experimental procedures in the Carlson test, the predictions were [[falsifiability|falsified]].&lt;ref name=Zarka /&gt;

The [[Shawn Carlson|Shawn Carlson's]] double-blind chart matching tests, in which 28 astrologers agreed to match over 100 natal charts to psychological profiles generated by the [[California Psychological Inventory]] (CPI) test, is one of the most renowned tests of astrology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Muller|first=Richard|title=Web site of Richard A. Muller, Professor in the Department of Physics at the University of California at Berkeley,|accessdate=2011-08-02|year=2010|url=http://muller.lbl.gov/homepage.html}}''My former student Shawn Carlson published in Nature magazine the definitive scientific test of Astrology.''&lt;br&gt;
{{cite web|last=Maddox|first=Sir John|title=John Maddox, editor of the science journal Nature, commenting on Carlson's test|year=1995|accessdate=2011-08-02|url=http://www.randi.org/encyclopedia/astrology.html}} ''&quot; ... a perfectly convincing and lasting demonstration.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CritThink /&gt; The experimental protocol used in Carlson's study was agreed to by a group of physicists and astrologers prior to the actual experiment itself.&lt;ref name=Zarka&gt;{{cite journal|last=Zarka|first=Philippe|title=Astronomy and astrology|journal=Proceedings of the International Astronomical Union|date=2011|volume=5|issue=S260|pages=420–425|doi=10.1017/S1743921311002602}}&lt;/ref&gt; Astrologers, nominated by the [[National Council for Geocosmic Research]], acted as the astrological advisors, and helped to ensure, and agreed, that the test was fair.&lt;ref name=CritThink /&gt;{{rp|117}}&lt;ref name=Carlson/&gt;{{rp|420}} They also chose 26 of the 28 astrologers for the tests (the other 2 being interested astrologers who volunteered afterwards) themselves.&lt;ref name=Carlson/&gt;{{rp|420}} The astrologers came from both Europe and the United states. &lt;ref name=CritThink&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Jonathan C.|title=Pseudoscience and extraordinary claims of the paranormal : a critical thinker's toolkit|year=2010|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|location=Malden, MA|isbn=9781405181235}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|117}} The astrologers helped to draw up the central proposition of [[natal astrology]] to be tested.&lt;ref name=Carlson/&gt;{{rp|419}} Published in ''[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]'' in 1985, the study found that predictions based on natal astrology were no better than chance, and that the testing &quot;clearly refutes the astrological hypothesis&quot;.&lt;ref name=Carlson&gt;{{cite journal|last=Carlson|first=Shawn|title=A double-blind test of astrology|journal=Nature|year=1985|volume=318|pages=419–425|url=http://muller.lbl.gov/papers/Astrology-Carlson.pdf|doi=10.1038/318419a0|issue=6045|bibcode = 1985Natur.318..419C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Gauquelin's research ===
{{main|Mars effect}}
[[File:Mars effect12.jpg|thumb|right|The initial [[Mars effect]] finding, showing the relative frequency of the [[diurnal motion|diurnal position]] of Mars in the birth charts (N = 570) of &quot;eminent athletes&quot; (red solid line) compared to the expected results [after [[Michel Gauquelin]] 1955]&lt;ref name=Gauquelin-1955&gt;{{cite book|last=Gauquelin|first=Michel|title=L'influence des astres : étude critique et expérimentale|year=1955|publisher=Éditions du Dauphin|location=Paris}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

In 1955, astrologer, and psychologist [[Michel Gauquelin]] stated that although he had failed to find evidence to support such indicators as the [[Astrological signs|zodiacal signs]] and [[Astrological aspects|planetary aspects]] in astrology, he had found positive correlations between the [[Diurnal motion|diurnal positions]] of some of the [[Planets in astrology|planets]] and success in professions (such as doctors, scientists, athletes, actors, writers, painters, etc.) which astrology traditionally associates with those planets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gauquelin-1955&quot; /&gt; The best-known of Gauquelin's findings is based on the positions of Mars in the [[natal chart]]s of successful athletes and became known as the &quot;[[Mars effect]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;gauquelin-last&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gauquelin|first=Michel|title=Is There Really a Mars Effect?|journal=Above &amp; Below Journal of Astrological Studies|year=1988|month=Fall|issue=11|pages=4–7|url=http://www.theoryofastrology.com/gauquelin/mars_effect.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study conducted by seven French scientists attempted to replicate the claim, but found no statistical evidence, and attributed the effect to selective bias on Gauquelin's part, accusing him of attempting to persuade them to add or delete names from their study.&lt;ref&gt;Benski, Claude, et al., The &quot;Mars Effect&quot; (Amherst, NY: Prometheus Books, 1996).&lt;/ref&gt;

Geoffrey Dean has suggested that the effect may be caused by self-reporting of birth dates by parents rather than any issue with the study by Gauquelin. The suggestion is that a small subset of the parents may have had changed birth times to be consistent with better astrological charts for a related profession. The sample group was taken from a time where belief in astrology was more common. Gauquelin had failed to find the Mars effect in more recent populations. where a nurse or doctor recorded the birth information. The number of births under astrologically undesirable conditions was also lower, indicating more evidence that parents choose dates and times to suit their beliefs. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Jonathan C.|title=Pseudoscience and extraordinary claims of the paranormal : a critical thinker's toolkit|year=2010|publisher=Wiley-Blackwell|location=Malden, MA|isbn=9781405181235}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|116}}

== Theological criticisms ==
{{see also|Christianity and astrology|Jewish views on astrology|Muslim views on astrology}}
Some of the practices of astrology were contested on theological grounds by medieval Muslim astronomers such as [[Al-Farabi]] (Alpharabius), [[Ibn al-Haytham]] (Alhazen) and [[Avicenna]]. They said that the methods of astrologers conflicted with orthodox religious views of [[Ulema|Islamic scholars]] through the suggestion that the Will of God can be known and predicted in advance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Saliba |first=George |authorlink=George Saliba |year=1994b |title=A History of Arabic Astronomy: Planetary Theories During the Golden Age of Islam |publisher=[[New York University Press]] |isbn=0-8147-8023-7 |pages=60 &amp; 67–69 |postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, Avicenna’s 'Refutation against astrology' ''Risāla fī ibṭāl aḥkām al-nojūm'', argues against the practice of astrology while supporting the principle of planets acting as the agents of divine causation which express God's absolute power over creation. Avicenna considered that the movement of the planets influenced life on earth in a deterministic way, but argued against the capability of determining the exact influence of the stars.&lt;ref&gt;Catarina Belo, Catarina Carriço Marques de Moura Belo, ''Chance and determinism in Avicenna and Averroës'', p. 228. Brill, 2007. ISBN 90-04-15587-2.&lt;/ref&gt; In essence, Avicenna did not refute the essential dogma of astrology, but denied our ability to understand it to the extent that precise and fatalistic predictions could be made from it.&lt;ref&gt;[[George Saliba]], ''Avicenna'': 'viii. Mathematics and Physical Sciences'. Encyclopaedia Iranica, Online Edition, 2011, available at http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/avicenna-viii&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ibn Qayyim Al-Jawziyya]] (1292–1350), in his ''Miftah Dar al-SaCadah'', also used [[physics|physical]] arguments in astronomy to question the practice of judicial astrology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Ibn Qayyim al-Jawziyyah: A Fourteenth Century Defense against Astrological Divination and Alchemical Transmutation|first=John W.|last=Livingston|journal=Journal of the American Oriental Society|volume=91|issue=1|year=1971|pages=96–103|doi=10.2307/600445|jstor=600445|postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt; He recognized that the [[star]]s are much larger than the [[planet]]s, and argued:

{{blockquote|And if you astrologers answer that it is precisely because of this distance and smallness that their influences are negligible, then why is it that you claim a great influence for the smallest heavenly body, Mercury? Why is it that you have given an influence to al-Ra's and al-Dhanab, which are two imaginary points [ascending and descending nodes]?|Ibn Qayyim Al-Jawziyya&lt;ref name=Livingston&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Ibn Qayyim al-Jawziyyah: A Fourteenth Century Defense against Astrological Divination and Alchemical Transmutation|first=John W.|last=Livingston|journal=Journal of the American Oriental Society|volume=91|issue=1|year=1971|pages=96–103 [99]|doi=10.2307/600445|jstor=600445|postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Belief in astrology is incompatible with [[Catholicism|Catholic]] beliefs&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=editor|first=Peter M.J. Stravinskas,|title=Our Sunday visitor's Catholic encyclopedia|year=1998|publisher=Our Sunday Visitor Pub.|location=Huntington, Ind.|isbn=0879736690|edition=Rev. ed.|page=111}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as free will.&lt;ref name=Hess /&gt; According to the [[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]: {{blockquote|All forms of divination are to be rejected: recourse to Satan or demons, conjuring up the dead or other practices falsely supposed to &quot;unveil&quot; the future. Consulting horoscopes, astrology, palm reading, interpretation of omens and lots, the phenomena of clairvoyance, and recourse to mediums all conceal a desire for power over time, history, and, in the last analysis, other human beings, as well as a wish to conciliate hidden powers. They contradict the honor, respect, and loving fear that we owe to God alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Catechism of the Catholic Church - Part 3|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p3s2c1a1.htm|accessdate=8 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;|Catechism of the Catholic Church}} 

[[St. Augustine]] believed that astrology conflicted with church doctrine, but he grounded his opposition with non-theological reasons such as the failure of astrology to explain twins who behave differently although are conceived at the same moment and born at approximately the same time.&lt;ref name=Hess&gt;{{cite book|last=Hess|first=Peter M.J.|title=Catholicism and science.|year=2007|publisher=Greenwood|location=Westport|isbn=9780313331909|page=11|edition=1. publ.|coauthors=Allen, Paul L.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[List of astrological traditions, types, and systems]]

== Notes ==
{{notes}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
&lt;!--({{NoMoreLinks}})--&gt;
&lt;!--| DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF |--&gt;
&lt;!--| LINKS. If you think that your link might be useful, do not add it here, |--&gt;
&lt;!--| but put it on this article's discussion page first or submit your link |--&gt;
&lt;!--| to the appropriate category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org)|--&gt;
&lt;!--| and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template. |--&gt;
&lt;!--| |--&gt;
&lt;!--| Links that have not been verified WILL BE DELETED. |--&gt;
&lt;!--| See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details |--&gt;
&lt;!--({{NoMoreLinks}})--&gt;
{{Sister project links}}
* {{dmoz|Society/Religion_and_Spirituality/Divination/Astrology/}}
* [http://cura.free.fr/DIAL.html Digital International Astrology Library] at [http://cura.free.fr/index.html# C.U.R.A. (Centre Universitaire de Recherche en Astrologie) International Astrology Research Center]; (Retrieved 15 November 2011).
* [http://www.astrology-and-science.com/a-meet2.htm Astrologer meets client - Tricks of the trade]
* [http://www.skepsis.nl/astrot.html The Astrotest]
&lt;!--See the talk page before changing this--&gt;
{{Astrology-footer}}
{{Pseudoscience}}
{{Constellations/historic}}
{{Divination}}
{{Theology}}
{{Philosophy topics}}

&lt;!--This list intentionally does not contain categories of which astrology is a subcategory.--&gt;

[[Category:Astrology| ]]
[[Category:Hermeticism]]
[[Category:Mysticism]]
[[Category:Popular psychology]]
[[Category:Superstitions]]
[[Category:Symbolism]]
[[Category:Pseudoscience]]
[[Category:Cultural studies]]
[[Category:Theories of history]]

&lt;!--interwiki--&gt;

[[af:Astrologie]]
[[ar:علم التنجيم]]
[[an:Astrolochía]]
[[ast:Astroloxía]]
[[az:Astrologiya]]
[[bn:জ্যোতিষশাস্ত্র]]
[[zh-min-nan:Chiam-chhiⁿ-ha̍k]]
[[be:Астралогія]]
[[be-x-old:Астралёгія]]
[[bg:Астрология]]
[[bs:Astrologija]]
[[br:Steredouriezh]]
[[ca:Astrologia]]
[[cs:Astrologie]]
[[cy:Sêr-ddewiniaeth]]
[[da:Astrologi]]
[[de:Astrologie]]
[[et:Astroloogia]]
[[el:Αστρολογία]]
[[es:Astrología]]
[[eo:Astrologio]]
[[eu:Astrologia]]
[[fa:ستاره‌بینی]]
[[fr:Astrologie]]
[[fy:Astrology]]
[[gl:Astroloxía]]
[[gu:જ્યોતિષવિદ્યા]]
[[ko:점성술]]
[[hy:Աստղագուշակություն]]
[[hi:फलित ज्योतिष]]
[[hr:Astrologija]]
[[io:Astrologio]]
[[id:Astrologi]]
[[ia:Astrologia]]
[[ie:Astrologie]]
[[is:Stjörnuspeki]]
[[it:Astrologia]]
[[he:אסטרולוגיה]]
[[jv:Astrologi]]
[[kn:ಜ್ಯೋತಿಷ್ಯ]]
[[ka:ასტროლოგია]]
[[kk:Астрология]]
[[sw:Unajimu]]
[[ht:Astroloji]]
[[la:Astrologia]]
[[lv:Astroloģija]]
[[lt:Astrologija]]
[[hu:Asztrológia]]
[[mk:Астрологија]]
[[ml:ജ്യോതിഷം]]
[[mt:Astroloġija]]
[[arz:تنجيم]]
[[ms:Astrologi]]
[[my:ဗေဒင်]]
[[nl:Astrologie]]
[[ja:占星術]]
[[no:Astrologi]]
[[nn:Astrologi]]
[[nrm:Astrologie]]
[[nov:Astrologia]]
[[oc:Astrologia]]
[[uz:Astrologiya]]
[[pl:Astrologia]]
[[pt:Astrologia]]
[[ro:Astrologie]]
[[ru:Астрология]]
[[sa:फलज्योतिषं]]
[[stq:Astrologie]]
[[sq:Astrologjia]]
[[scn:Astroluggìa]]
[[simple:Astrology]]
[[sk:Astrológia]]
[[sl:Astrologija]]
[[sr:Астрологија]]
[[sh:Astrologija]]
[[su:Astrologi]]
[[fi:Astrologia]]
[[sv:Astrologi]]
[[tl:Astrolohiya]]
[[ta:சோதிடம்]]
[[te:జ్యోతిషశాస్త్రం]]
[[th:โหราศาสตร์]]
[[tr:Astroloji]]
[[uk:Астрологія]]
[[ur:نجوم]]
[[vec:Astrołogia]]
[[vi:Chiêm tinh học]]
[[wa:Asterlodjeye]]
[[vls:Astrologie]]
[[wo:Gëstubiddiw]]
[[yi:אסטראלאגיע]]
[[zh-yue:占星術]]
[[zh:占星学]]</text>
      <sha1>7py1r7kfoooyyyrqz542pffj8c0npk2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
