<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Auspice</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>462184</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520022564</id>
      <parentid>511422141</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T21:22:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Magioladitis</username>
        <id>1862829</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Types of auspices */clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8481)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13741">{{distinguish|Auspicious|Hospice}}
{{for|the werewolf caste lunar phase in [[Werewolf: The Apocalypse]]|Auspice (World of Darkness)}}
[[Image:Rider BM B1.jpg|thumb|280px|A confident rider, surrounded by birds of good omen is approached by a [[Nike (mythology)|Nike]] bearing victor's wreaths on this [[Laconia]]n black-figured ''[[kylix (drinking cup)|kylix]]'', ca. 550–530 BCE]] 
An '''auspice''' ([[Latin]]: '''''auspicium'''''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tfd.com/auspice auspice - definition of auspice by the Free Online Dictionary, Thesaurus and Encyclopedia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; from '''''auspex''''') is literally &quot;one who looks at birds&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wordinfo.info/words/index/info/view_unit/258/?letter=A&amp;spage=16 auspic-, auspec- + (Latin: to look, to observe in order to make a prediction; to see omens; from ''auspex'' [genitive form ''auspicis''&amp;#93; ''avi-'', stem of ''avis'', &quot;bird&quot; plus ''-spex'', &quot;observer&quot;, from ''specere'')&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; a diviner who reads [[omen]]s from the observed flight of birds.  This type of omen reading was already a millennium old in the time of [[Classical Greece]]: in the fourteenth-century BCE diplomatic correspondence preserved in Egypt called the &quot;[[Amarna correspondence]]&quot;, the practice was familiar to the king of Alasia in Cyprus who  has need of an 'eagle diviner' to be sent from Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;J.A. Knudtzon, ''Die El-Amarna Tafeln'' (1915:no. 35.26) noted in [[Walter Burkert]], ''The Orientalizing Revolution: Near Eastern Influences on Greek Culture in the Early Archaic Age'' (1992), p 42.&lt;/ref&gt; This earlier, indigenous practice of divining by bird signs, familiar in the figure of [[Calchas]], the bird-diviner to [[Agamemnon]], who has led the army (''[[Iliad]]'' I.69), was largely replaced by sacrifice-divination through inspection of the sacrificial victim's liver— ''[[haruspices]]''— during the [[Orientalizing Period|Orientalizing period]] of archaic Greek culture. [[Plato]] notes that [[hepatoscopy]] held greater prestige than augury by means of birds.&lt;ref&gt;Walter Burkert 1992:49, noting Plato's ''Phaedrus'' 244C.&lt;/ref&gt;  

In [[Religion in ancient Rome|ancient Roman religion]], the '''auspices''' provided divine signs to be interpreted by an [[augur]] (Latin plural: augures, English plural: augurs).  An augur would perform a ceremony (known as &quot;taking the auspices&quot;) and would read flight patterns of birds in the sky.  Depending upon the birds, the auspices from the gods could be favorable or unfavorable (''auspicious'' or ''inauspicious''). Sometimes bribed or politically motivated augures would fabricate unfavorable auspices in order to delay certain state functions, such as elections.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} [[Pliny the Younger]] attributes the invention of auspicy to [[Tiresias]] the seer of [[Thebes (Greece)|Thebes]], the generic model of a seer in the Greco-Roman literary culture.

One of the most famous auspices is the one which is connected with the founding of Rome. Once the founders of Rome, [[Romulus]] and [[Remus]], arrived at the [[Palatine Hill]], the two argued over where the exact position of the city should be. Romulus was set on building the city upon the Palatine, but Remus wanted to build the city on the strategic and easily fortified [[Aventine Hill]]. The two agreed to settle their argument by testing their abilities as augures and by the will of the gods. Each took a seat on the ground apart from one another, and, according to [[Plutarch]], Remus saw six vultures, while Romulus saw twelve.

==Auspices in Ancient Rome==
{{main|augur}}
In ancient Rome, the appointment and inauguration of any magistrate, decisions made within the people’s assembly and the advancement of any campaign always required a positive ''auspicium''. Unlike in Greece where oracles played the role of messenger of the Gods, in Rome it was through birds that Jupiter’s will was interpreted.&lt;ref&gt;Aves internun-tiae JoviS) Cic. de Divin. ii. 34; Interpretes Jovis optimi maximi publici augures, Cic. de  Leg. ii. 8&lt;/ref&gt; Auspices showed Romans what they were to do, or not to do; giving no explanation for the decision made except that it was the will of the Gods. It would be difficult to execute any public act without consulting the auspices.

It was believed that if an augur committed an error in the interpretation of the signs or, vitia, it was considered offensive to the gods and often was said to have disastrous effects unless corrected.&lt;ref&gt;Potter, David. ''Prophets and Emperors''. (Harvard University: Cambridge, Massachusetts 1994. p. 152&lt;/ref&gt; Elections, the passing of laws and wars were all put on hold until the people were assured the Gods agreed with their actions. The men who interpreted these signs, revealing the will of the gods were called augures. Similar to records of court precedents, augures kept books containing records of past signs, the necessary rituals and prayers and other tricks of their trade to help other augures and even member of the aristocracy understand the fundamentals of augury.&lt;ref&gt;Potter, David. ''Prophets and Emperors''. (Harvard University: Cambridge, Massachusetts 1994. p. 154&lt;/ref&gt;

The augures themselves were not the ones with the final say. Though they had the power to interpret the signs, it was ultimately the responsibility of the magistrate to execute decisions as to future actions.&lt;ref&gt;spectio, Cic. Phil. 2,81&lt;/ref&gt; The magistrates were also expected to understand the basic interpretations as they were often expected to take the auspices whenever they undertook any public business.&lt;ref name=&quot;Potter153&quot;&gt;Potter, David. ''Prophets and Emperors''. (Harvard University: Cambridge, Massachusetts 1994. p. 153&lt;/ref&gt; 

Until 300 BC only [[Patrician (ancient Rome)|patricians]] could become augures. Plebeian assemblies were forbidden to take augury and hence had no input as to whether a certain law, war or festival should occur. Cicero, an augur himself, accounts how the monopoly of the patricians created a useful barrier to the encroachment of the ''[[populares]]''&lt;!--this makes no sense, since ''populares'' were quite often patricians and could be augures--&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;F. Guillaumont, Philosophe et augure, recherches sur la théorie cicéronienne de la divination, 1984. Brills New Pauly footnote 7 “Augures”.&lt;/ref&gt;  However in 300 BC a new law Lex Ogulnia, increased the number of augures from four to nine and required that five of the nine be plebeians, granting, for the first time, the ability to interpret the will of the Gods to lower classes. With this new power, it was not only possible for plebeians to determine the gods will in their favor but it was also now possible for plebeians to critique unfair interpretations by patricians.

==History of auspices==
According to unanimous testimony from ancient sources the use of auspices as a means to decipher the will of the Gods was more ancient than Rome itself. The use of the word is usually associated with Latins as well as the earliest Roman citizens. Though some modern historians link the act of observing Auspices to the Etruscans, Cicero accounts in his text De Divinatione several differences between the auspicial of the Romans and the Etruscan system of interpreting the will of the Gods. Cicero also mentions several other nations which, like the Romans, paid attention to the patterns of flying birds as signs of God’s will but never once mentions this practice while discussing the Etruscans.&lt;ref&gt;Cic. de Div. I.41, II.35, 38; de Nat. Deor. II.4&lt;/ref&gt; Though auspices were prevalent before the Romans, Romans are often linked with auspices because of both their connection to Rome’s foundation and because Romans were the first to take the system and lay out  such fixed and fundamental rules for the reading of auspices that it remained an essential part of Roman culture. Stoics, for instance, maintained that if there are gods, they care for men, and that if they care for men they must send them signs of their will.&lt;ref&gt;Cic. de Leg. ii. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of auspices==
There were five different types of auspices. Of these, the last three formed no part of the ancient auspices.

;ex caelo [''from the sky'']: This auspice involved the observation of thunder and lightning and was often seen as the most important auspice.&lt;ref&gt;Serv. ad Virg. Aen. II.693; Cic. de Div. II.18, &amp;c.; Festus, s.v. Coelestia&lt;/ref&gt; Whenever an augur reported that Jupiter had sent down thunder and lightning, no [[comitia]] (a gathering deemed to represent the entire Roman population) could be held.&lt;ref&gt;Cic. de Div. II.14, Philipp. V.3&lt;/ref&gt;

;ex avibus [''from birds'']: Though auspices were typically bird signs, not all birds in the sky were seen as symbols of the will of the Gods. There were two classes of birds: [[Oscines]], who gave auspices via their singing; and [[Alites]], who gave auspices via how they flew.&lt;ref&gt;Cic. de Div. II.34&lt;/ref&gt; The Oscines included ravens, crows, owls and hens, each offering either a favorable omen (''auspicium ratum'') or an unfavorable depending on which side of the Augur's designated area they appeared on.&lt;ref&gt;Plaut. Asin. II.1.12; Cic. de Div. I.39&lt;/ref&gt; The birds of the Alites were the eagle, the vulture, the [[avis sanqualis]], also called [[ossifraga]], and the [[immussulus]] or [[immusculus]].&lt;ref&gt;cf. Virg. Aen. I.394; Liv. I. 7, 34; Festus, s.v. sanqualis; Plin. H. N. X.7&lt;/ref&gt; Some birds like the [[Picus Martius]], the [[Feronius]], and the [[Parrha]] could be considered among the oscines and the alites. Every movement and every sound made by these birds had a different meaning and interpretation according to the different circumstances, or times of the year when it was observed.

;ex tripudiis [''from the &quot;dance&quot; (of birds feeding)'']: These auspices were read by interpreting the eating patterns of chickens and were generally used on military expeditions. [[Cicero]] shows that at one point, any bird could perform the ''tripudium''&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=6RYhAQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA601&amp;lpg=PA601&amp;dq=The+Romans+used+chickens+for+oracles&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=OpWs3qaTCq&amp;sig=JQkBl7qznVphAkr5c_EsrNfQP6c&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=cpxLUNv2CIjq2QX0yYHwBA&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=sacred%20chickens&amp;f=false] A classical and archaeological dictionary of the manners, customs, laws, institutions, arts, etc. of the celebrated nations of antiquity, and of the middle ages: To which is prefixed A synoptical and chronological view of ancient history - P. Austin Nuttall - Printed for Whittaker and co., 1840 - page 601&lt;/ref&gt; [sacred dance], but that as the practice progressed it soon began customary to use only chickens. The chickens were kept in a cage under the care of the ''pullarius'' (keeper of the auspice chickens) who, when the time came, released the chickens and threw at them some form of bread of cake. If the chickens refused to come out or eat, or uttered a cry, or beat their wings, or flew away, the signs were considered unfavourable.&lt;ref&gt;Liv. X.40; Val. Max. I.4 §3&lt;/ref&gt;  Conversely, if the chicken left its cage to feast so that something fell from its mouth and landed on the ground, these signs were termed ''tripudium solistimum'' (or ''tripudium quasi terripavium solistimum'') [from ''solum'', the ground], according to the ancient writers&lt;ref&gt;Cic. de Div. II.34),&lt;/ref&gt;), and were considered to be a favourable sign.

;ex quadrupedibus [''from quadrupeds'']: Auspices could also be taken from animals who walked on four feet, though these auspices were not part of the original science of augurs, and were never used for state affairs. Often these auspices took the form of a fox, wolf, horse, or dog who crossed a person's path, or was found in an unusual location— the meaning could be interpreted, by an appointed augur, as some form of will of the Gods.&lt;ref&gt;See e.g. Hor. Carm. iii. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;

;ex dīrīs [''from portents'']: This category of auspices represented every other event or occurrence which could result in an auspice which does not fit into the above categories. Often actions of sneezing, stumbling, and other slightly abnormal events could be taken as a sign from the Gods to be interpreted.&lt;ref&gt;cf. Serv. ad Virg. Aen. IV.453&lt;/ref&gt;

==Offered and requested signs==
There were two classifications of auspice signs, [[Glossary of ancient Roman religion#auspicia impetrativa|impetrative]] (''impetrativa'', sought or requested) and [[Glossary of ancient Roman religion#auspicia oblativa|oblative]] (''oblativa'', unsought or offered). Signs that fall under the category of ''impetrativa'' were signs that resulted due to the actions performed by the augur during the reading of the auspice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Potter153&quot;/&gt; The other category of signs, ''oblativa'', were momentous events which occurred unexpectedly, while the magistrate was either taking auspices or participating in public debate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Potter153&quot;/&gt; ''Ex Caelo'' (&quot;from the sky&quot;) signs of thunder and lightning or other natural phenomena, would be considered an “offered” sign. Unless the magistrate was accompanied by an augur it was up to them to decide whether or not the “offered” sign was significant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Potter153&quot;/&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Augur]]

==References==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{1728}}

[[Category:Ancient Roman religion]]
[[Category:Classical oracles]]
[[Category:Divination]]

[[ca:Auspici]]
[[cs:Auspicia]]
[[da:Auspicier]]
[[de:Auspizien]]
[[es:Auspicio]]
[[fa:شگون]]
[[fr:Auspicia]]
[[hy:Աուսպիցիաներ]]
[[io:Auspicio]]
[[it:Auspicia]]
[[ka:აუსპიციუმი]]
[[lt:Auspicijos]]
[[nl:Auspicium]]
[[no:Auspicier]]
[[pl:Auspicjum]]
[[pt:Auspício]]
[[ru:Ауспиции]]
[[sv:Auspicier]]
[[uk:Ауспіції]]</text>
      <sha1>7tgsuqyj83tllze4rizqz6947bbx81x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
