<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Baptism for the dead</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18950667</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521316906</id>
      <parentid>521307242</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T06:12:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Drewbigs</username>
        <id>17280090</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* LDS Church doctrine */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="46386">[[File:Nauvoo Temple basement.png|thumb|right|300px|[[Temple architecture (LDS Church)|Floorplan]] of the [[Nauvoo Temple]] basement. The basement of the temple was used as the [[baptistery]], containing a large [[baptismal font]] in the center of the main room.]]

'''Baptism for the dead''', '''vicarious baptism''' or '''proxy baptism''' today commonly refers to the religious practice of [[Baptism (Mormonism)|baptizing]] a person on behalf of one who is dead—a living person receiving the ordinance on behalf of a deceased person.

Baptism for the dead is best known as a doctrine of the [[Latter Day Saint movement]], where it has been practiced since 1840.  It is currently practiced by [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church), where it is performed only in dedicated [[List of temples of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|temples]], as well as in several (but not all) other current [[List of sects in the Latter Day Saint movement|factions]] of the Latter-day Saint movement.  Those who practice this rite view baptism as an indispensable requirement to enter the [[Kingdom of God]], and thus practice Baptism for the Dead to give those who have died without ever having had the opportunity to receive baptism the opportunity to receive it by proxy. The LDS Church teaches that those who have died may choose to accept or reject the baptism done on their behalf.

The modern term itself is derived from a phrase &quot;baptised for the dead&quot; occurring twice in the [[New Testament]] ({{sourcetext|source=Bible|version=King James|book=1 Corinthians|chapter=15|verse=29}}), though the meaning of that phrase is an open question among scholars. Early [[heresiologists]] [[Tertullian]] (''Against Marcion'' 10) and [[Chrysostom]] (''Homilies'' 40) attributed the practice to the [[Marcionite]]s, whom they identified as a heretical &quot;[[gnostic]]&quot; group.&lt;ref&gt;Everett Ferguson ''Baptism in the early church: history, theology, and liturgy ''  2009 p299 &quot;Tertullian twice in an antiheretical context comments on 1 Corinthians 15:29, “ baptism for the dead.”4 Later writers say the Marcionites practiced baptism on behalf of the dead.5 It was also said that they ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently the practice was forbidden by the [[Catholic Church]], and is not practiced in modern [[mainstream Christianity]], whether [[Catholic]], [[Eastern Orthodox]], or [[Protestant]].

==Practice==

===The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints===
In the practice of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (or &quot;Mormons&quot;), a living person, acting as proxy, is [[Baptism (Latter Day Saints)|baptized]] by immersion on behalf of a deceased person.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}} After giving a short prayer that includes the name of the deceased individual, the proxy is immersed briefly in the water, then brought up again. Baptism for the dead is a distinctive [[Ordinance (Mormonism)|ordinance]] of the church and is based on the belief that baptism is a required ordinance for entry into the [[Kingdom of God]].

===Community of Christ===
Some members of the early [[Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints]] (now known as the [[Community of Christ]]) also believed in baptism for the dead,&lt;ref name=&quot;centerplace1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.centerplace.org/library/study/bap4dead.htm |title=Baptism For The Dead |publisher=Centerplace.org |date= |accessdate=2012-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; but it was never officially sanctioned by that organization, and was considered highly controversial.&lt;ref name=&quot;centerplace1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.centerplace.org/library/books/DifferencesThatPersist.pdf |title=Differences That Persist between the RLDS and LDS Churches |format=PDF |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2012-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A revelation and two letters written by [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]] appertaining to baptism for the dead were removed from the RLDS ''[[Doctrine and Covenants]]'' by a [[World Conference (Community of Christ)|church general conference]] in 1970. {{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} &lt;!-- where can we read about this? --&gt;

===Other Latter Day Saint churches===
In the [[Restoration Branches]] movement, which broke from the RLDS Church in the 1980s, the question of Baptism for the Dead is at best unsettled, reflecting their RLDS origin. Many adherents reject the validity of this ordinance completely.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.centerplace.org/rlds/AResponseToPaulTrask.htm ]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other Latter Day Saint denominations that accept baptism for the dead include the [[Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints (Strangite)]] and [[The Church of Jesus Christ (Cutlerite)]]. The Strangite Church performed baptisms for the dead during the 1840s in [[Voree, Wisconsin]] and later during the 1850s on [[Beaver Island, Michigan]]. In each case, the practice was authorized by revelation given by [[James J. Strang]]. The question of whether the Strangite Church still practices proxy baptism is an open one, but belief is considered orthodox.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.strangite.org/BaptismDead.htm |title=Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints – Mormons – Baptism for the Dead |publisher=Strangite.org |date=2004-01-01 |accessdate=2012-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cutlerite practice permits baptisms for the dead to be performed in baptismal fonts in Cutlerite meetinghouses (of which only two exist today, one in [[Clitherall, Minnesota]] and the other in [[Independence, Missouri]]). Though Cutlerites believe in the concept of temples, it is not required that baptisms for the dead be performed in one. The meetinghouse baptismal fonts are used for baptism of the living ''and'' for the dead. Cutlerites have practiced baptisms for the dead sporadically throughout their history (including during the early 1990s), but it is not known if they still do so. As with the LDS Church and the Strangite Church, belief in this doctrine is considered orthodox.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}

===Other Christian Churches===
As part of their Sacraments, the [[New Apostolic Church]] and [[Old Apostolic Church]] also practices [[Baptism]] for the Dead, as well as [[Eucharist|Communion]] and Sealing to the Departed. In this practice a proxy or substitute is baptised in the place of an unknown number of deceased persons. According to NAC and OAC doctrine the deceased do not enter the body of the substitute.

In the [[Reformed Old Apostolic Church]] it is believed that all deceased persons that are baptised reside within the body of the substitute.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

===Outside of Christianity===
Outside of Christianity, proxy baptisms are practiced by the [[Mandaeanism|Mandaeans]] of [[Iraq]] and [[Iran]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mandaeanunion.org/History/EN_History_007.htm | title=A Brief Note on the Mandaeans: Their History, Religion and Mythology| publisher=Mandaean Society in America}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins in Christianity==
Tertullian (''Against Marcion'' 10) attributes the practice of 1 Corinthians &quot;baptised for the dead&quot; to the [[Marcionite]]s, and [[Epiphanius of Salamis]] (''Panarion'' 28) to [[Cerinthus]], as the custom of baptizing dead bodies and giving the [[Eucharist]] to them&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=xNssAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA652&amp;dq=baptized+for+the+dead&amp;lr=&amp;cd=12#v=onepage&amp;q=baptized%20for%20the%20dead&amp;f=false |title=Cyclopaedia of Biblical, Theological, and Ecclesiastical Literature – John McClintock, James Strong – Google Boeken |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; has sometimes been interpreted as baptism ''for'' the dead. Thus John A. Tvedtnes, a Hebrew and early Christian scholar at [[Brigham Young University]] writes:
{{cquote|That baptism for the dead was indeed practiced in some [[orthodoxy|orthodox]] Christian circles is indicated by the decisions of two late fourth century councils. The fourth canon of the [[Synod of Hippo]], held in 393, declares, &quot;The Eucharist shall not be given to dead bodies, nor baptism conferred upon them.&quot; The ruling was confirmed four years later in the sixth canon of the [[Synods of Carthage|Third Council of Carthage]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last=Tvedtnes |first=John A| title=Baptism for the Dead: The Coptic Rationale| accessdate=2007-03-04| url=http://www.fairlds.org/apol/misc/misc23.html| publisher=Foundation for Apologetic Information and Research| location=Provo, UT |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061007200016/http://www.fairlds.org/apol/misc/misc23.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[John Chrysostom]] (''Homilies'' 40) alleges a similar practice among the [[Marcionites]] of the same century: if one of their followers who was [[catechumen|being prepared for baptism]] died before receiving baptism, the dead person's corpse was addressed with the question whether he wished to be baptized, whereupon another answered affirmatively and was baptized for the dead person.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clerus.org/bibliaclerusonline/EN/cfz.htm#bn |title=John Chrysostom, Homily XL on 1 Corinthians |publisher=Clerus.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same passage, explained Paul's mention of people being &quot;baptized ''for'' the dead&quot; as a reference to the profession of faith in their own [[Resurrection of the dead|future resurrection]] that Christians made before being baptized.

===1 Corinthians 15:29===
In the context of insisting that &quot;in Christ shall all be made alive .. Christ the firstfruits; afterward they that are Christ's&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:22–23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paul wrote in {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:29|KJV}}: &quot;Else what shall they do which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? why are they then baptized for the dead?&quot; Different views have been expressed on the meaning of the phrase &quot;baptized for the dead&quot;, and on whether Paul gave his approval to the practice.

====Meanings of the verb ''baptizein''====
The Greek verb in Paul's phrase &quot;baptized for the dead&quot; is ''baptizein'', which in Jewish Greek has a wider reference than &quot;baptism&quot;, applying primarily to the masculine noun ''baptismos'' &quot;ritual washing&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueletterbible.org/lang/lexicon/lexicon.cfm?Strongs=G909&amp;t=KJV |title=masculine noun baptismos 4x NT uses |publisher=Blueletterbible.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The verb occurs four times in the Septuagint in the context of ritual washing, ''baptismos'': Judith cleansing herself from menstrual impurity, [[Naaman]] washing seven times to be cleansed from leprosy, etc.&lt;ref&gt;Philippe Wolff ''Baptism: The Covenant and the Family'' 2009 p45 &quot;This word occurs but four times in the Septuagint, and in no case with the Baptist meaning. 1st. &quot;Judith baptized herself in a fountain of water, by the camp.&quot; (Judith xii. 7.) She was then purifying herself from her uncleanness.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In the New Testament only, the verb ''baptizein'' can also relate to the neuter noun ''baptisma'' &quot;baptism&quot;, a [[neologism]] unknown in the [[Septuagint]] and other pre-Christian Jewish texts.&lt;ref&gt;Jonathan David Lawrence ''Washing in Water: Trajectories of Ritual Bathing in the Hebrew Bible and Second Temple Literature'' (Atlanta: Society of Biblical Literature, 2006), p294&lt;/ref&gt; This broadness in the meaning of ''baptizein'' is reflected in English Bibles rendering &quot;wash,&quot; where Jewish ritual washing is meant, for example in Mark 7:4, which states that the Pharisees &quot;except they wash (Greek &quot;baptize&quot;), they do not eat&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;ἐὰν μὴ βαπτίσωνται οὐκ ἐσθίουσιν.`&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;baptize&quot; where ''baptisma'', the new Christian rite, is intended. The older ritual washing use of ''baptizein'' is relevant in the context of funerals since any Jew coming into contact with the dead body must undertake ritual washing.&lt;ref&gt;Geoffrey Wigoder ''The Encyclopedia of Judaism'' 1989 p768 &quot;The dead body renders the house in which it is situated and anyone coming in contact with the body ritually impure, tame met. ... (ritual washing of the body). Any person touching a corpse must wash his hands as soon as possible&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Second Temple]] and early [[Rabbinical]] period the regulations on &quot;ritual washing&quot; (Greek masculine noun ''baptismos'') expanded and multiplied. This is documented in the [[Halakhah]] Tractate Yadayim&lt;ref&gt;[[Jacob Neusner]] ''The Halakhah: An Encyclopaedia of the Law of Judaism''  2000 &quot;TRACTATE YADAYIM I. AN OUTLINE OF THE HALAKHAH OF YADAYIM The hands are deemed perpetually unclean, a realm of uncleanness — fingertips to wrist — distinct from the rest of the body.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Dead Sea Scrolls]]&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence.''Washing in Water: Trajectories of Ritual Bathing in the Hebrew Bible and Second Temple Literature'' (Atlanta: Society of Biblical Literature, 2006) chapter ''Dead Sea Scrolls''&lt;/ref&gt; [[Peter Leithart]] (2007) suggests that Paul's comment &quot;why do they..&quot; is an analogy between baptism (i.e. neuter concept noun ''baptisma'') with Jewish ritual washing (i.e. masculine concrete noun ''baptismos'') for contact with the dead following the Mosaic regulations in Numbers 19.&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter Leithart|Peter J. Leithart]] ''The Baptized Body'' 2007 p136 &quot;Paul uses a distancing third person—“they” baptize for the dead. Why not “we”? Paul might well be referring to Jewish practices. Under the ceremonial laws of Torah, every washing was a washing “for the dead” (cf. Num. 19). Uncleanness was a ceremonial form of death, and through washings of various sorts the unclean dead were restored to life in fellowship with..&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase &quot;ritually washed for the dead&quot; does not occur in [[intertestamental]] literature, but a possibly related idea of [[prayer for the dead]] occurs in [[2 Maccabees]]. Since the New Testament idea of &quot;baptism&quot; (Greek ''baptisma''), the rite of baptism, is not mentioned in the verse, it is open to interpretation whether the verb ''baptizein'' refers to &quot;ritual washing&quot; (Greek ''baptismos'') or &quot;the rite of baptism&quot; (Greek ''baptisma'') or is an analogy between both.&lt;ref&gt;Alan C. Mitchell, Daniel J. Harrington ''Hebrews'' 2007 p119 &quot;2. instruction about cleansings, laying on of hands, resurrection of the dead, and eternal judgment: The word for &quot;cleansings,&quot; baptismos, is not exclusively used for Christian baptism, as is baptisma&quot; ([[BDAG]], 165)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Meaning of the phrase====
Some interpret &quot;baptized for the dead&quot; as a metaphor for martyrdom, as in {{bibleverse||Mark|10:38}} and {{bibleverse||Luke|12:50}} baptism is a metaphor for suffering or martyrdom; accordingly they would translate it as &quot;being baptized with a view to death&quot;.&lt;ref name=Tyndale&gt;Tyndale Bible Dictionary, 2001, ISBN 978-0-8423-7089-9, article ''Baptism for the dead''&lt;/ref&gt; In this interpretation, the phrase is closely linked with what Paul says immediately afterwards&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:30–32}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the suffering that he himself faces and is enabled to endure precisely because of his faith in his resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christiananswers.net/q-eden/edn-r001.html |title=What does the Bible mean when it refers to the &quot;Baptism of the dead?&quot; |publisher=Christiananswers.net |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.visualbiblealive.com/resources.php?encyc_id=877&amp;img_id=88150&amp;action=encyclopedia&amp;frame=divEncyc |title='&amp;#39;Baptism for the Dead'&amp;#39; |publisher=Visual Bible Alive |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; This interpretation is similar to that of John Chrysostom.

Others interpret the phrase as referring to simple baptism of an individual.  For [[Martin Luther]] it regarded a practice of being baptized ''above'' (the first of the meanings of the preposition ὑπέρ, generally translated in this passage as ''for'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://artfl.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/getobject.pl?c.74:7:143.lsj |title=Liddell and Scott: ὑπέρ |publisher=Artfl.uchicago.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; the tombs of the dead. [[John Calvin]] saw it as a reference to being baptized when close to death.&lt;ref name=Tyndale/&gt;

The third interpretation sees the phrase as referring to vicarious baptism on behalf of dead people performed in the belief that the dead were thereby benefitted in some way. This belief is put forward as the reason why, when Paul compares the Corinthians' experience to that of the Israelites in crossing the Red Sea and being fed on manna, he insists that the Israelites were not thereby prevented from sinning.&lt;ref name=Tyndale/&gt;

====Approved by Paul?====
The Tyndale Bible Dictionary concludes that Paul probably did not approve the practice of baptism for the dead. He refers to its practitioners as &quot;they&quot;, not as &quot;you&quot; (the Corinthian Christians to whom he wrote).&lt;ref&gt;Tyndale Bible Dictionary (Tyndale House 2001 ISBN 978-0-8423-7089-9), P. 146&lt;/ref&gt; The note in the Catholic [[New American Bible]] is more cautious: &quot;Baptized for the dead: this practice is not further explained here, nor is it necessarily mentioned with approval, but Paul cites it as something in their experience that attests in one more way to belief in the resurrection.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usccb.org/nab/bible/1corinthians/1corinthians15.htm |title=New American Bible, note on 1 Corinthians 15:29 |publisher=Usccb.org |date=2011-03-13 |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In this, it stays close to what [[Tertullian]] wrote in the year 207 or 208, when he said that Paul's only aim in alluding to the practice of baptism for the dead, &quot;whatever it may have been&quot;, was &quot;that he might all the more firmly insist upon the resurrection of the body, in proportion as they who were vainly baptized for the dead resorted to the practice from their belief of such a resurrection.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/03125.htm |title=Tertullian, Against Marcion, book V, chapter 10 |publisher=Newadvent.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other views====
[[Elaine Pagels]] (1992) seeks to explain 1 Corinthians as having reference to the [[Valentinius|Valentinian]] sect later numbered among the &quot;[[Gnostic]]&quot; heresies.&lt;ref&gt;Elaine H. Pagels ''The gnostic Paul: gnostic exegesis of the Pauline letters'' 1992 p83 &quot;Paul now argues his case for the resurrection from the practice of baptism for the dead. ... According to their own sacramental practice, the pneumatic elect receive baptism for &quot;the dead&quot; that is, for the psychics.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; However Pagels view of Paul's epistles is not supported by other scholars.

Trinitarian Christian denominations generally do not accept the Latter-day Saint interpretation of &quot;baptism for the dead&quot;, mentioned in {{sourcetext|source=Bible|version=King James|book=1 Corinthians|chapter=15|verse=29}}, though a few other contemporary Christian churches do practice such an ordinance.{{citation needed|date=February 2012}}

==LDS Church doctrine==
[[File:Salt Lake temple baptismal font.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Baptismal font in the [[Salt Lake Temple]], circa 1912, where baptisms for the dead are performed by proxy. The font rests on the backs of twelve oxen representing the [[Twelve Tribes of Israel]]]]

Members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints believe that baptism is a prerequisite for entry into the kingdom of God as stated by [[Jesus]] in {{sourcetext|source=Bible|version=King James|book=John|chapter=3|verse=5}}: &quot;Except that a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God&quot; ([[King James Version of the Bible|KJV]]).

The LDS Church teaches that performing baptisms for the dead allows this saving [[Ordinance (Latter Day Saints)|ordinance]] to be offered on behalf of those who have died without accepting or knowing Jesus Christ or his teachings during their mortal lives. It is taught that this is the method by which all who have lived upon the earth will have the opportunity to receive baptism and to thereby enter the Kingdom of God. 

Among other Biblical references, Latter-day Saints cite Peter's statements that Jesus preached to the spirits of the dead (KJV 1 Peter 3:19; 4:6) as evidence that God in his justice provides an opportunity for the deceased to hear and accept the gospel, if they don't receive that chance in mortality. As Peter affirmed in Acts 2:37-38, the next step after acceptance of the gospel is baptism for the remission of sins, which &quot;doth also now save us&quot; (KJV 1 Peter 3:21).

The LDS Church teaches that those in the afterlife who have been baptized by proxy are free to accept or reject the ordinance done on their behalf. Baptism on behalf of a deceased individual is not binding if that individual chooses to reject it in the afterlife.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document |url= http://lds.org/study/topics/baptisms-for-the-dead?lang=eng |contribution= Baptisms for the Dead |title= Gospel Study: Study by Topic |work= LDS.org |publisher= [[LDS Church]] |accessdate= 2011-09-19 |postscript= &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |last= Condie |first= Spencer J. |author-link= Spencer J. Condie |title= The Savior's Visit to the Spirit World |journal= [[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]] |month= July |year= 2003 |publisher= LDS Church |url= http://lds.org/ensign/2003/07/the-saviors-visit-to-the-spirit-world?lang=eng |pages= 32–36 |accessdate= 2011-09-19 |quote= No one will be coerced into accepting ordinances performed on his or her behalf by another. Baptism for the dead offers an opportunity, but it does not override a person’s agency. But if this ordinance is not performed for them, deceased persons are robbed of the choice to accept or reject baptism. |postscript= &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Any member of the LDS Church, male or female, who is at least 12 years old and holds a current temple recommend may act as a proxy in this ordinance. Men must also hold the [[Aaronic priesthood (Latter Day Saints)|Aaronic Priesthood]] prior to entering the temple. A man must act as proxy for a deceased man, and a woman must act as proxy for a deceased woman. The concept of a spiritual proxy is compared by some in the LDS Church to the belief that Jesus acted as proxy for every human when he atoned for the sins of the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Hinckley |first= Gordon B. |author-link= Gordon B. Hinckley |title= Be Thou an Example | year= 1981 |publisher= [[Deseret Book]] | page=133 |quote= In the sanctity of their appointments we commune with him and reflect on his Son, our Savior and Redeemer, the Lord Jesus Christ, who served as proxy for each of us in a vicarious sacrifice in our behalf. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Only an adult male holder of the [[Melchizedek priesthood (LDS Church)|Melchizedek priesthood]] who has undergone the [[Endowment (Latter Day Saints)|Endowment]] ordinance may baptize others as proxies for the dead.

===Modern origin===
According to The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, the practice of baptism for the dead is based on a revelation received by the prophet [[Joseph Smith, Jr.|Joseph Smith]]. He first taught the doctrine at the [[funeral]] sermon of a deceased member of the church, [[Seymour Brunson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Cook| first=Lyndon| coauthors=Andrew F. Ehat| title=The Words of Joseph Smith |  month=June | year=1991| publisher=Grandin Book Co.| isbn=0-910523-39-8 | page=49}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a letter written on October 19, 1840, to the [[Quorum of the Twelve Apostles]] of the church (who were on a mission in the [[United Kingdom]] at the time), Smith refers to the passage in {{sourcetext|source=Bible|version=King James|book=1 Corinthians|chapter=15|verse=29}} (KJV):
{{cquote|I presume the doctrine of &quot;baptism for the dead&quot; has ere this reached your ears, and may have raised some inquiries in your minds respecting the same.  I cannot in this letter give you all the information you may desire on the subject; but aside from knowledge independent of the [[Bible]], I would say that it was certainly practiced by the ancient churches; and [[Paul of Tarsus|Saint Paul]] endeavors to prove the doctrine of the resurrection from the same, and says, &quot;Else what shall they do which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? Why are they then baptized for the dead?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[[History of the Church (Joseph Smith)|History of the Church]]'' '''4''':231&lt;/ref&gt;}}

LDS Church [[Standard Works|scripture]] expands further upon this doctrine and states that such baptisms are to be performed in [[Temple (LDS Church)|temples]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Doctrine and Covenants]] {{sourcetext|source=The Doctrine and Covenants|book=Covenant 124|verse=29}}, {{sourcetext|source=The Doctrine and Covenants|book=Covenant 127|verse=5|range=-10}} and {{sourcetext|source=The Doctrine and Covenants|book=Covenant 128}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vicarious baptism is performed in connection with other vicarious ordinances in temples of the LDS Church, such as the [[Endowment (Latter Day Saints)|Endowment]] and [[celestial marriage]].

Initially, women could be baptized for dead men, and vice versa; this, however, was changed in order to ensure that the person being baptized for a dead man could also be ordained on their behalf to the priesthood.&lt;ref&gt;Brigham Young (Aug. 31, 1873), ''[[Journal of Discourses]]'' '''16''':160.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genealogy and baptism===
The LDS Church holds that deceased persons who have not accepted or had the opportunity to accept the gospel of Christ in this life will have the opportunity to accept the gospel in the afterlife.  As all must follow Jesus Christ, they must also receive all the ordinances that a living person is expected to receive, including baptism. For this reason, members of the LDS Church are encouraged to research their [[genealogy]]. This research is then used as the basis for church performing temple ordinances for as many deceased persons as possible. As a part of these efforts, [[Mormons]] have performed temple ordinances on behalf of a number of high profile people. Of particular interest are: the [[Founding Fathers]] of the U.S., [[President of the United States|Presidents]] of the U.S., [[Pope John Paul II]], [[John Wesley]], [[Christopher Columbus]], [[Adolf Hitler]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://nowscape.com/mormon/hitler_temple_records.htm |title = Mormons Attempt to Hide Temple Baptism for Hitler |archiveurl  = http://www.webcitation.org/5wQ7zTIXI |archivedate = 2011-02-11 |accessdate  = 2011-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; and others.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

While members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints consider it a great service to perform vicarious ordinances for the deceased, some non-members have taken offense. To be sensitive to the issue of proxy baptizing for non-Mormons that are not related to church members, the church in recent years has published a general policy of performing temple ordinances only for direct ancestors of church members. For example, the church is in the process of removing sensitive names (such as Jewish Holocaust victims) from its [[International Genealogical Index]] (IGI). [[D. Todd Christofferson]] of the church's [[Quorums of the Seventy#Presidency of the Seventy|Presidency of the Seventy]] stated that removing the names is an &quot;ongoing, labor intensive process requiring name-by-name research ... When the Church is made aware of documented concerns, action is taken ... Plans are underway to refine this process.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}} The LDS Church keeps records of the temple ordinances performed for deceased persons, however the [[FamilySearch#&quot;New&quot; FamilySearch|new FamilySearch]], a web application for accessing the church's genealogical databases, shows information on temple ordinances only to registered LDS Church members and not to non-members.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = | first = | year = | title = Finding Ordinance Dates on the International Genealogical Index (IGI) | url = https://help.familysearch.org/kb/Local_Support/en/Consultants/memos/en/13%20Finding%20Ordinance%20Dates%20on%20the%20International%20Genealogical%20Index.pdf | accessdate = 27 February 2012 | quote = To see ordinance information in the IGI, members must be registered in FamilySearch.org as a Church member. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, a directive from the Vatican [[Congregation for the Clergy]] directed Catholic dioceses to prevent the LDS Church from &quot;microfilming and digitizing information&quot; contained in Catholic sacramental registers so that those whose names were contained therein would not be subjected to vicarious Mormon baptism,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://genealogy.about.com/b/2008/05/05/vatican-orders-catholic-parish-registers-off-limits-to-lds-church.htm |title=Vatican Orders Catholic Parish Registers Off-Limits to LDS Church |publisher=Genealogy.about.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/0802443.htm |title=CNS STORY: Vatican letter directs bishops to keep parish records from Mormons |publisher=Catholicnews.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; even though the Vatican had previously declared that Mormon baptism was invalid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20010605_battesimo_mormoni_en.html |title=Response on the validity of baptism conferred by Ťmormonsť |publisher=Vatican.va |date=2001-06-05 |accessdate=2011-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==

===Baptisms for the dead by the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints===
{{See also|Criticism of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints#Baptism for the dead|l1=Criticism of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints: Baptism for the dead}}

====Jewish Holocaust victims====

The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints performs vicarious baptisms for individuals regardless of their race, sex, creed, religion, or morality. Some members of the LDS Church have been baptized for both victims and perpetrators of the [[Holocaust]], including [[Anne Frank]] and [[Adolf Hitler]], contrary to Church policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video| title=Wiesel to Mormon Church: stop proxy baptisms of Jews| Author=MSNBC's The Last Word with Lawrence O'Donnell| year=2012| url=http://video.msnbc.msn.com/the-last-word/46407233#46407233}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some [[Jew]]ish Holocaust survivors and some Jewish organizations have objected to this practice.

The LDS Church has urged members to submit the names of only their own ancestors for ordinances, and to request permission of surviving family members of people who have died within the past 95 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |title=Member's Guide to Temple and Family History Work |year=2009 |url=http://www.lds.org/manual/members-guide-to-temple-and-family-history-work/chapter-7-providing-temple-ordinances?lang=eng}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hundreds of thousands of improperly submitted names not adhering to this policy have been removed from the records of the church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| title=Mormons, Jews Set Up Group to Study Concerns| journal=Meridian Magazine| year=2005| url=http://www.meridianmagazine.com/churchupdate/050412study.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Latter-day Saint [[Apostle (Latter Day Saints)|apostle]] [[Boyd K. Packer]] has stated the LDS Church is clear that it uses the public records it collects for temple ordinance work.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last= Packer |first= Boyd K |authorlink= Boyd K. Packer  |title= The Holy Temple |year= 1980 |publisher= [[Bookcraft]] |isbn= 0-88494-411-5 |page= 266 |quote= For a number of years the Church had negotiated with the government of Israel for permission to microfilm the archives of that nation. These records, including many carefully kept genealogies, are priceless records of the human family and have a tie to great events in the history of the world. The officials had learned all they wanted to know about the Church storage procedures and were impressed. They insisted however that someone be sent to talk to them about the doctrine relating to our desire for their records. They wanted to know why we wanted their records. In 1977 I received the assignment to go to Israel and meet with their official archivists and scholars on the matter ... I explained to them our great interest in the Old Testament and our kinship with Israel. We talked of family, of patriarchal lineage and blessings. We talked of the doctrine of agency. But all of these things were not central to the point. It might seem that in order to obtain a favorable decision we would have to be &quot;diplomatic&quot; and not mention ordinances—especially baptism. But we were on the Lord's errand, and so I told them—plainly, bluntly—that we desired their records in order to provide baptism, Christian baptism, for their forebears and for ours. The reaction was immediate and intense. The meeting thereafter was most interesting! We came away uncertain as to the outcome. But we were on the Lord's errand. We were serving the work of redemption for the dead. We had told the truth without any shade of misrepresentation. In due time the answer came. We received approval to microfilm and preserve those records which were sanctified by the suffering of our brethren of the house of Israel. |postscript= &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the guidelines, some members of the church have submitted the names of Holocaust victims, and prominent [[Nazi]]s, such as [[Heinrich Himmler]], for vicarious baptism without adequate permission. In December 2002, independent researcher [[Helen Radkey]] published a report showing that, following a 1995 promise from the church to remove Jewish Nazi victims from its International Genealogical Index, the church's database included the names of about 19,000 who had a 40 to 50 percent chance &quot;to be Holocaust victims ... in Russia, Poland, France, and Austria.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.jewishgen.org/infofiles/ldsagree.html|title= The Issue of The Mormon Baptisms of Jewish Holocaust Victims and Other Jewish Dead: Mormons Hijack Dead or Alive Jewish Souls |accessdate=2009-01-27 |author = Bernard I. Kouchel | work= |publisher= JewishGen|date= | archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20081218151532/http://www.jewishgen.org/InfoFiles/ldsagree.html| archivedate= 18 December 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Allison |last= Hoffman |coauthors= |title= Jewish group wants Mormons to stop proxy baptisms |curly=y |work= Jerusalem Post|page= |date= 10 November 2008 |accessdate=11 November 2008|quote= |url= http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1225910087233&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull}}&lt;/ref&gt; Genealogist [[Bernard Kouchel]] conducted a search of the International Genealogical Index, and discovered that many well known Jews had been vicariously baptized, including [[Maimonides]], [[Albert Einstein]], and [[Irving Berlin]], without family permission.&lt;ref name=stop&gt;{{Citation | last = Gladstone| first = Bill| title = Jewish Officials Press Mormons to Stop Baptizing Deceased Jews | newspaper = Jewish Telegraphic Agency | date = December 12, 2002| url = http://archive.jta.org/article/2002/12/12/2912561/jewish-officials-press-mormons-to-stop-baptizing-deceased-jews }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=anotherpromise&gt;{{Citation | last = Gladstone| first = Bill| title = Mormons Renew Their Vow to Stop Baptizing Deceased Jews| newspaper = Jewish Telegraphic Agency| publication-place = | volume = | issue = | date = December 13, 2002| url =  http://archive.jta.org/article/2002/12/13/2912588/mormons-renew-their-vow-to-stop-baptizing-deceased-jews}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Church official D. Todd Christofferson told the ''[[New York Times]]'' that the church expends massive amounts of resources attempting to purge improperly submitted names, but that it is not feasible to expect the church to find each and every last one, and that the agreement in 1995 did not place this type of responsibility on the centralized church leadership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last=Urbina| first=Ian| title=Again, Jews Fault Mormons Over Posthumous Baptisms | work=New York Times| date=2003-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jewish groups such as the [[Simon Wiesenthal Center]] spoke out against the vicarious baptism of Holocaust perpetrators and victims in the mid-1990s and again in the 2000s when they discovered the practice, which they consider insensitive to the living and the dead, was continuing.&lt;ref&gt;Vicarious baptism had even been performed for Simon Wiesenthal himself after his death. The Center found the practice insulting and an affront to [[Judaism|Jews]] who died because of their religion. Rabbi [[Marvin Hier]] of the center said: &quot;If these people did not contact the Mormons themselves, the adage should be: Don't call me, I'll call you. With the greatest of respect to them, we do not think they are the exclusive arbitrators of who is saved.&quot; {{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2002/US/West/12/10/baptizing.the.dead.ap/|title=Mormons meet with Jews over baptizing Holocaust victims| publisher=CNN.com}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Aaron Breitbart, a researcher with the Center believes the church was showing insensitivity to the living and their dead ancestors. &quot;They did not get baptized when they were alive and they had a choice, and doing so after they are dead is beyond the ethical bounds.&quot; ''National Post'', June 6, 2001, Jan Cienski&lt;/ref&gt; The associate dean of the Simon Wiesenthal Center, Abraham Cooper, complained that infamous figures such as [[Adolf Hitler]] and [[Eva Braun]] appeared on LDS genealogical records: &quot;Whether official or not, the fact remains that this is exactly the kind of activity that enraged and hurt, really, so many victims of the Holocaust and caused alarm in the Jewish community.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Salt Lake Tribune'', October 9, 1999,  Bob Mims&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Adolf Hitler was baptized on September 4, 1993, endowed on October 12, 1993, and sealed to his parents and to Eva Braun on June 14, 1994 in the Los Angeles Temple. [http://www.nowscape.com/mormon/hitler_temple_records.htm nowscape.com] {{Verify credibility|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--restored citation.  The reason you can't find it in the IGI is that embarrassing entries are removed, as the reference demonstrates--&gt;

In 2008, the [[American Gathering of Jewish Holocaust Survivors and their Descendants|American Gathering of Jewish Holocaust Survivors]] announced that, since the church had repeatedly violated previous agreements, it would no longer negotiate with the church to try to prevent vicarious baptism. Speaking on the anniversary of [[Kristallnacht]], Ernest Michel, a Holocaust survivor who reported on the [[Nuremberg Trials]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.roberthjackson.org/Ernest_Michel/|title= Ernest Michel: Holocaust survivor saw justice served as Nuremberg correspondent |accessdate=12 November 2008 |work= |publisher= Robert H. Jackson Center|date= }}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}} speaking as the honorary chairman of the American Gathering of Holocaust Survivors, called on the LDS Church to &quot;implement a mechanism to undo what [they] have done&quot;, and declared that the LDS Church had repeatedly violated their agreements, and that talks with Mormon leaders were now ended. Jewish groups, he said, would now turn to the court of public opinion for justice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hajela&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first= Deepti|last= Hajela|coauthors= Jennifer Dobner |title= Jewish group wants Mormons to stop proxy baptisms|curly=y |agency= Associated Press|page= |date=11 November 2008 |accessdate=11 November 2008|quote= |url= http://ap.google.com/article/ALeqM5j9l-R1TIM_X5myzSoEzLN7QnqdSwD94C9QH80}}{{dead link|date=November 2012|bot=Legobot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Michel called the practice a revision of history that plays into the hands of [[Holocaust denial|Holocaust deniers]], stating: &quot;They tell me, that my parents' Jewishness has not been altered but ... 100 years from now, how will they be able to guarantee that my mother and father of blessed memory who lived as Jews and were slaughtered by Hitler for no other reason than they were Jews, will someday not be identified as Mormon victims of the Holocaust?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hajela&quot;/&gt;

Church officials, in response, stated that the church does not teach that vicarious baptisms coerce deceased persons to become Mormons, nor does the church add those names to its list of church members.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url= http://www.mormonnewsroom.org/article/background-explanation-of-temple-baptism |contribution= Background Explanation of Temple Baptism |title= Newsroom |work= mormonnewsroom.org |publisher= LDS Church }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url= http://www.mormonnewsroom.org/article/religious-freedom-allows-both-mormons-and-jews-to-honor-their-ancestors |contribution= Religious Freedom Allows Both Mormons and Jews to Honor Their Ancestors |title= Newsroom |work= mormonnewsroom.org |publisher= LDS Church }}&lt;/ref&gt; Church officials have also stated that, in accordance with the 1995 agreement, it has removed more than 300,000 names of Jewish Holocaust victims from its databases, as well as subsequently removing names later identified by Jewish groups. Church officials have also stated that a new version of the database, [[FamilySearch#&quot;New&quot; FamilySearch|New FamilySearch]], has been developed and is currently being implemented that would help prevent the submission of Holocaust victim names for temple ordinances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Buddy |last=Blankenfeld|title=Jewish group at odds with LDS Church over temple work for ancestors|work=ABC 4 News|date=11 November 2008|accessdate=11 November 2008|url=http://www.abc4.com/content/about_4/links_numbers/story.aspx?content_id=d1c20f95-896e-4cc0-a5d3-52dd7d9f5467}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2012, the issue re-emerged after it was found that the parents of Holocaust survivor and Jewish rights advocate [[Simon Wiesenthal]] were added to the genealogical database.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mormons baptise parents of Nazi-hunter Simon Wiesenthal|work=BBC News|date=15 February 2012|accessdate=16 February 2012|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-17036046}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterward, news stories announced that [[Anne Frank]] had been baptized by proxy for the ninth time, at a Latter-day Saint temple in the Dominican Republic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Mormon Baptism Targets Anne Frank—Again|work= Huffington Post|date=21 February 2012 |accessdate=3 March 2012|url= http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/02/21/mormons-posthumous-baptism-anne-frank_n_1292102.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Barack Obama's mother====
In May 2009, it was discovered that [[Barack Obama|President Barack Obama's]] mother, [[Stanley Ann Dunham]], &quot;who died in 1995, was baptized posthumously into The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day{{sic}} Saints last year during her son's campaign.  The White House declined to comment Tuesday [May 5, 2009].&quot;&lt;ref name = stack&gt;{{cite news| last=Fletcher Stack| first=Peggy|authorlink=Peggy Fletcher Stack| title=Obama's mother posthumously baptized into LDS Church | work=Salt Lake Tribune| date=2009-05-05| url=http://www.sltrib.com/faith/ci_12301237}}&lt;/ref&gt; The June 4, 2008 baptism was performed in the [[Provo Utah Temple]], and a week later the ritual of [[Endowment (Mormonism)|endowment]] was performed on behalf of Dunham. LDS Church spokesman Scott Trotter confirmed that someone did perform a proxy baptism for Dunham, but said it was &quot;counter to [LDS] Church policy for a church member to submit names for baptism for persons to whom they are not related.&quot;  &lt;ref name = stack/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Ancestor liberation]]
* [[Celestial marriage]]
* [[Criticism of the Latter Day Saint movement]]
* [[Posthumous marriage#Mormonism|Posthumous marriage in Mormonism]]
* [[Prayer for the dead]]
* [[Sealing power]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* [[B. H. Roberts|Roberts, B.H.]] (editor); ''[[History of the Church (Joseph Smith)|History of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]''; [[The Deseret Book Company]]; ISBN 0-87579-490-4 (revised 2nd edition, softcover, 1975)
* Tvedtnes, John A.; ''Baptism for the Dead: The Coptic Rationale''; Retrieved Aug 19, 2003, from http://www.fairlds.org/apol/misc/misc23.html
* &quot;LDS Church Reaffirms No Proxy Baptisms of Jews&quot;, ''[[The Salt Lake Tribune]]'', 12 December 2002.

==External links==
{{Americana Poster|Baptism for the Dead}}
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/mormon/ritesrituals/baptismdead.shtml Baptism for the Dead] The BBC's Religion and Ethics report
*[http://www.ctlibrary.com/ct/1998/august10/8t9063.html Directions: Did Paul Baptize for the Dead?] From Christianity Today
* [http://www.ccel.org/s/schaff/encyc/encyc01/htm/iii.ix.xiii.htm New Schaff-Herzog Encyclopedia of Religious Knowledge], at [[Christian Classics Ethereal Library]]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02258b.htm Catholic Encyclopedia:Baptism], see section titled: &quot;Baptism of the dead&quot;
* {{citation|title = Mormon Baptism For the Dead: History and Explanation of an Unusual Ritual|publisher = Huffington Post|first = Samuel|last = Brown|url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/samuel-brown/mormon-dead-baptism-explanation_b_1279739.html|date = February 23, 2012}}
* {{citation|title = Q&amp;A about Mormon baptisms for the dead|authorlink = Peggy Fletcher Stack|first = Peggy Fletcher|last = Stack|publisher = [[Salt Lake Tribune]]|date = March 2, 2012|url = http://www.sltrib.com/sltrib/faith/53632863-142/baptism-church-dead-holocaust.html.csp}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Baptism For The Dead}}
[[Category:Aftermath of the Holocaust]]
[[Category:Baptism]]
[[Category:Genealogy and The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]
[[Category:Mormonism-related controversies]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saint temple practices]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saint concepts of the afterlife]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saint ordinances, rituals, and symbolism]]
[[Category:New Testament words and phrases]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saint terms]]
[[Category:1840 establishments]]
[[Category:1840 in religion]]
[[Category:First Epistle to the Corinthians]]

[[cs:Křest za mrtvé]]
[[de:Totentaufe]]
[[pt:Batismo para a morte]]
[[fi:Sijaistoimitukset (mormonismi)]]
[[sv:Dop för de döda]]</text>
      <sha1>oks4fwheqm7s84m9w4iyiezipp8r6df</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
