<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Beelzebub</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19010124</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521904031</id>
      <parentid>521758851</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T23:10:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove unicode control characters (CHECKWIKI error 16) +general fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8535)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18012">{{Other uses}}
{{Redirect3|Baalzebub|For the genus of spider, see [[Ray spider]]}}
{{pp-move-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Expert-subject|Ancient Near East|date=November 2008}}
[[File:Beelzebub and them with him.jpg|250px|right|thumb|&quot;Beelzebub and them that are with him shoot arrows&quot; from [[John Bunyan]]'s ''The Pilgrim's Progress'' (1678)]]
'''Beelzebub''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|b|iː|ˈ|ɛ|l|z|ɨ|b|ʌ|b}} {{respell|bee|EL|zə-bub}} or {{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|iː|l|z|ɨ|b|ʌ|b}} {{respell|BEEL|zə-bub}}; ({{lang-he|בעל זבוב}}, ''Baʿal Zəvûv'' {{lang-ar|بعل الذباب}}, ''Ba‘al az-Zubab'';, literally &quot;Lord of the Flies&quot;; {{lang-el|Βεελζεβούλ}}, ''Velzevoúl''; {{lang-la|Beelzebūb}}), with numerous archaic variants,&lt;ref&gt;Such as Belzebud, Beezelbub, Beazlebub, Belzaboul, Beelzeboul, Baalsebul, Baalzebubg, Belzebuth, Beelzebuth, and Beelzebus.&lt;/ref&gt; is a Semitic [[deity]] that was worshiped in the [[Philistine]] city of [[Ekron]]. In later Christian and Biblical sources, he is referred to as another name for [[Satan]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matt.%2010:25,%2012:24&amp;version=NIV biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; and in demonology, is one of the [[seven princes of Hell|seven princes]] of [[Hell in Christian beliefs|Hell]].

==Hebrew Bible==
The source for the name Ba‘al Zebûb / Beelzebub is in {{Bibleref2|2Kings|1:2-3,6,16|NIV|2 Kings 1:2-3, 6, 16}}, where King [[Ahaziah of Israel|Ahaziah]] of [[Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)|Israel]], after seriously injuring himself in a fall, sends messengers to inquire of Ba‘al Zebûb, the god of the Philistine city of [[Ekron]], to learn if he will recover.

:[[Ahaziah of Israel|Ahaziah]] fell through the lattice in his upper chamber at [[Samaria]] and was injured. So he sent messengers whom he instructed: &quot;Go inquire of Baal-zebub, the god of Ekron, whether I shall recover from this injury.&quot; ([[Jewish Publication Society|JPS]] translation)

[[Elijah]] the Prophet then condemns Ahaziah to die by [[Yahweh]]'s words because Ahaziah sought counsel from Ba‘al Zebûb rather than from Yahweh.

''Ba‘al Zəbûb'' is variously understood to mean &quot;lord of the flies&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Βεελζεβούλ, ὁ indecl. (v.l. Βεελζεβούβ and Βεεζεβούλ W-S. §5, 31, cp. 27 n. 56) Beelzebul, orig. a Philistine deity; the name בַּעַל זְבוּב means Baal (lord) of the flies (4 Km 1:2, 6; Sym. transcribes βεελζεβούβ; Vulgate Beelzebub; TestSol freq. Βεελζεβούλ,-βουέλ).&quot;, Arndt, W., Danker, F. W., &amp; Bauer, W. (2000). A Greek-English lexicon of the New Testament and other early Christian literature (3rd ed.) (173). Chicago: University of Chicago Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;1. According to 2 Kgs 1:2–6 the name of the Philistine god of Ekron was Lord of the Flies (Heb. ba‘al zeaûḇ), from whom Israel’s King Ahaziah requested an oracle.&quot;, Balz, H. R., &amp; Schneider, G. (1990-). Vol. 1: Exegetical dictionary of the New Testament (211). Grand Rapids, Mich.: Eerdmans.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The etymology of Beelzebul has proceeded in several directions. The variant reading Beelzebub (Syriac translators and Jerome) reflects a long-standing tradition of equating Beelzebul with the Philistine deity of the city of Ekron mentioned in 2 Kgs 1:2, 3, 6, 16. Baalzebub (Heb ba˓al zĕbûb) seems to mean “lord of flies” (HALAT, 250, but cf. LXXB baal muian theon akkarōn, “Baal-Fly, god of Akkaron”; Ant 9:2, 1 theon muian).&quot;, Lewis, &quot;Beelzebul&quot;, in Freedman, D. N. (1996). Vol. 1: The Anchor Yale Bible Dictionary (639). New York: Doubleday.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;On the basis zebub, ‘flies’, the name of the god was interpreted as ‘Lord of the flies’; it was assumed that he was a god who could cause or cure diseases.&quot;, Herrmann, &quot;Baal Zebub&quot;, in Toorn, K. v. d., Becking, B., &amp; Horst, P. W. v. d. (1999). Dictionary of deities and demons in the Bible DDD (2nd extensively rev. ed.) (154). Leiden; Boston; Grand Rapids, Mich.: Brill; Eerdmans.&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;lord of the (heavenly) dwelling&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It is not as probable that b‘l zbl, which can mean “lord of the (heavenly) dwelling” in Ugaritic, was changed to b‘l zbb to make the divine name an opprobrius epithet. The reading Beelzebul in Mt. 10:25 would then reflect the right form of the name, a wordplay on “master of the house” (Gk oikodespótēs).&quot;, McIntosh, &quot;Baal-Zebub&quot;, in Bromiley, G. W. (1988; 2002). Vol. 1: The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia, Revised (381). Wm. B. Eerdmans.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;An alternative suggested by many is to connect zĕbûl with a noun meaning “ (exalted) abode.”&quot;, Lewis, &quot;Beelzebul&quot;, in Freedman, D. N. (1996). Vol. 1: The Anchor Yale Bible Dictionary (639). New York: Doubleday.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In contemporary Semitic speech it may have been understood as ‘the master of the house’; if so, this phrase could be used in a double sense in Mt. 10:25b.&quot;, Bruce, &quot;Baal-Zebub, Beelzebul&quot;, in Wood, D. R. W., &amp; Marshall, I. H. (1996). New Bible dictionary (3rd ed.) (108). Leicester, England; Downers Grove, Ill.: InterVarsity Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Originally the name of a [[Philistine]] god,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;For etymological reasons, Baal Zebub must be considered a Semitic god; he is taken over by the Philistine Ekronites and incorporated into their local cult.&quot;, Herrmann, &quot;Baal Zebub&quot;, in Toorn, K. v. d., Becking, B., &amp; Horst, P. W. v. d. (1999). Dictionary of deities and demons in the Bible DDD (2nd extensively rev. ed.) (154). Leiden; Boston; Grand Rapids, Mich.: Brill; Eerdmans.&lt;/ref&gt; 

''Ba'al'', meaning &quot;Lord&quot; in [[Ugaritic]], was used in conjunction with a descriptive name of a specific god. [[Jewish]] scholars have interpreted the title of &quot;Lord of Flies&quot; as the Hebrew way of calling Ba'al a pile of dung and comparing Ba'al followers to flies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://eastonsbibledictionary.com/beelzebub.htm Easton's Bible Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=498&amp;letter=B Jewishencyclopedia.com]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Septuagint]] renders the name as ''Baalzebub'' (βααλζεβούβ) and as ''Baal muian'' (βααλ μυιαν, &quot;Baal of flies&quot;), but [[Symmachus the Ebionite]] may have reflected a tradition of its offensive ancient name when he rendered it as ''Beelzeboul''.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholars are divided, in regard to the god of Ekron, between the belief that ''zebub'' may be the original affix to Baal and that it is a substitute for an original ''zbl'' which, after the discoveries of Ras Shamra, has been connected with the title of &quot;prince&quot;, frequently attributed to [[Baal]] in mythological texts.{{citation needed|date=November 2012}} In addition to the intrinsic weakness of this last position, which is not supported by the versions, is the fact that it was long ago suggested that there was a relationship between the Philistine god and cults of fly or apotropaic divinities appearing in the Hellenic world, such as [[Myiagros|Zeus Apomyios or Myiagros]].{{citation needed|date=November 2012}} It is exactly this last connection which is confirmed by the Ugaritic text when we examine how Baal affects the expulsion of the flies which are  the patient's sickness.{{citation needed|date=November 2012}} According to Francesco Saracino (1982) this series of elements may be inconclusive as evidence, but the fact that in relationship to Baal Zebub, the two constituent terms are here linked, joined by a function (''ndy'') that is typical of some divinities attested in the Mediterranean world, is a strong argument in favor of the authenticity of the name of the god of Ekron, and of his possible therapeutic activities, which are implicit in {{Bibleref2|2Kings|1:2-3|NIV|2 Kings 1:2-3}}, etc.&lt;ref&gt;Saracino, Francesco. &quot;Ras Ibn Hani 78/20 and Some Old Testament Connections&quot;. ''Vetus Testamentum''. Vol. 32, Fasc. 3 (Jul., 1982), pp. 338-343.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Second temple period literature==
In the ''[[Testament of Solomon]]'', a Hellenistic Jewish text but with substantial Christian interpolations, Beelzebul (not Beelzebub) appears as prince of the demons and says (6.2) that he was formerly a leading heavenly angel who was (6.7) associated with the star Hesperus (which is the normal Greek name for the planet [[Venus]] (Αφροδíτη) as evening star). Seemingly, Beelzebul here is simply Satan/[[Lucifer]]. Beelzebul claims to cause destruction through tyrants, to cause demons to be worshipped among men, to excite priests to lust, to cause jealousies in cities and murders, and to bring on war.

==Rabbinical literature==
Rabbinical literature commentary equates Baal Zebub of Ekron as lord of the &quot;fly.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The Babylonian Talmud, Vol. 1 of 9: Tract Sabbath - Page 186 &quot;made themselves Baal-berith for a god&quot;; by Baal-berith is meant the Zebub (fly) idol of Ekron, and every idolater (at that time) made an image of his idol in miniature in order to keep it constantly at hand and to be able at any time to take it out, ..&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/2732-beelzebub Jewish Encyclopedia - Beelzebub]&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''Beelzebub'' in rabbinical texts is a mockery of the Ba'al religion, which ancient Hebrews considered to be idol (or false God) worship.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=Vtj0wSsw1JcC&amp;pg=PA31&amp;lpg=PA31&amp;dq=baal+hammon+Beelzebub#v=onepage&amp;q=baal%20hammon%20Beelzebub&amp;f=false Books.google.com], The Routledge dictionary of gods and goddesses, devils and demons By Manfred Lurker&lt;/ref&gt;

==New Testament==
In {{Bibleref2|Mark|3:22}}, the [[Pharisee]]s accuse [[Jesus]] of [[Exorcism#Jesus|driving out demons]] by the power of Beelzeboul, prince of demons, the name also appearing in the expanded version in {{Bibleref2|Matthew|12:24,27|NIV}} and {{Bibleref2|Luke|11:15,18-19|NIV}}. The name also occurs in {{Bibleref2|Matthew|10:25|NIV}}.

:Jesus knew their thoughts and said to them, Every kingdom divided against itself will be ruined, and every city or household divided against itself will not stand. If Satan drives out Satan, he is divided against himself. How then can his kingdom stand? And if I drive out demons by Beelzebul, by whom do your people drive them out? So then, they will be your judges. But if I drive out demons by the Spirit of God, then the kingdom of God has come upon you.─{{Bibleref2|Matthew|12:25-28|NIV}}

It is unknown whether Symmachus was correct in identifying these names, because we otherwise know nothing about either of them. ''Zeboul'' might derive from a slurred pronunciation of ''zebûb''; from ''zebel'', a word used to mean &quot;dung&quot; in the Targums; or from Hebrew ''zebûl'' found in {{Bibleref2|1Kings|8:13|NIV|1 Kings 8:13}} in the phrase ''bêt-zebûl'', &quot;lofty house&quot;.

In any case, the form ''Beelzebub'' was substituted for ''Beelzeboul'' in the [[Syriac]] translation and Latin [[Vulgate]] translation of the gospels, and this substitution was repeated in the [[King James Version of the Bible]], the resulting in the form ''Beelzeboul'' being mostly unknown to Western European and descendant cultures until some more recent translations restored it.

Beelzebub is also identified in the [[New Testament]] as Satan, the &quot;prince of the demons&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In NT Gk. beelzeboul, beezeboul (Beelzebub in TR and AV) is the prince of the demons (Mt. 12:24, 27; Mk. 3:22; Lk. 11:15, 18f.), identified with Satan (Mt. 12:26; Mk. 3:23, 26; Lk. 11:18).&quot;, Bruce, &quot;Baal-Zebub, Beelzebul&quot;, Wood, D. R. W., &amp; Marshall, I. H. (1996). New Bible dictionary (3rd ed.) (108). Leicester, England; Downers Grove, Ill.: InterVarsity Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Besides, Matt 12:24; Mark 3:22; Luke 11:15 use the apposition ἄρχων τῶν δαιμονίων ‘head of the →Demons’.&quot;, Herrmann, &quot;Baal Zebub&quot;, in Toorn, K. v. d., Becking, B., &amp; Horst, P. W. v. d. (1999). Dictionary of deities and demons in the Bible DDD (2nd extensively rev. ed.) (154). Leiden; Boston; Grand Rapids, Mich.: Brill; Eerdmans.&lt;/ref&gt; Biblical scholar [[Thomas Kelly Cheyne]] suggested that it might be a derogatory corruption of ''Ba‘al Zəbûl'', &quot;Lord of the High Place&quot; (i.e., Heaven) or &quot;High Lord&quot;.&lt;ref name =&quot;wex&quot;&gt;''[[Born to Kvetch]]'', [[Michael Wex]], St. Martin's Press, New York, 2005, ISBN 0-312-30741-1&lt;/ref&gt; 

In [[Arabic language|Arabic]], {{where|date=November 2012}} the name is retained as ''Ba‘al dhubaab / zubaab'' (بعل الذباب), literally &quot;Lord of the flies&quot;. {{citation needed|date=November 2012}}

==Christian tradition==
[[File:Velzevul.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Beelzebub from [[Russian icon]] of [[Harrowing of Hell]]]]
Texts of the ''[[Acts of Pilate]]'' (also known as the ''Gospel of Nicodemus'') vary in whether they use ''Beelzebul'' or ''Beelzebub''. The name is used by [[Hades]] as a secondary name for Satan, but it may vary with each translation of the text; other versions give the name Beelzebub as Beelzebub, but separates him from Satan.

===Christian demonology and occult===
[[File:Beelzebub.png|thumb|150px|left|Beelzebub as depicted in [[Collin de Plancy]]'s ''[[Dictionnaire Infernal]]'' (Paris, 1863)]]
Beelzebub is commonly described as placed high in [[Hell|Hell's]] hierarchy; he was of the order of [[Seraph]]im, which in Hebrew means &quot;fiery serpents&quot;.{{citation needed|date=November 2012}} According to the stories of the 16th-century occultist [[Johann Weyer]], Beelzebub led a successful revolt against [[Satan]],&lt;ref name=&quot;rudwin87&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Rudwin|first=Maximilian|title=The Devil in Legend and Literature|publisher=AMS Press|location=New York|year=1970|origyear=1931|edition=2nd|page=76|isbn=0-404-05451-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the chief lieutenant of Lucifer, the Emperor of Hell, and presides over the Order of the Fly.  Similarly, the 17th-century exorcist [[Sebastien Michaelis]], in his ''Admirable History'' (1612), placed Beelzebub among the three most prominent fallen [[angel]]s, the other two being Lucifer and [[Leviathan]], whereas two 18th-century works identified an unholy trinity consisting of Beelzebub, Lucifer, and [[Astaroth]]. [[John Milton]] featured Beelzebub seemingly as the second-ranking of the many fallen [[cherubim]] in the epic poem ''[[Paradise Lost]]'', first published in 1667. Milton wrote of Beelzebub, &quot;than whom, Satan except, none higher sat.&quot; Beelzebub is also a character in [[John Bunyan]]'s ''[[The Pilgrim's Progress]]'', first published in 1678.

[[Sebastien Michaelis]] associated Beelzebub with the deadly sin of pride. However, according to [[Peter Binsfeld]], Beelzebub was the demon of [[gluttony]], one of the other [[seven deadly sins]], whereas [[Francis Barrett (occultist)|Francis Barrett]] asserted that Beelzebub was the prince of false gods.  In any event, Beelzebub was frequently named as an object of [[supplication]] by confessed [[witch]]es.

Within religious circles, the accusation of demon possession has been used as both an insult and an attempt to categorise unexplained behavior. Not only have the [[Pharisees]] disparagingly accused Jesus of using Beelzebub's demonic powers to heal people (Luke 11:14-26), but others have been labeled possessed for acts of an extreme nature. Down through history, Beelzebub has been held responsible for many cases of [[demon possession]], such as that of Sister Madeleine de Demandolx de la Palud, [[Aix-en-Provence]] in 1611, whose relationship with Father Jean-Baptiste Gaufridi led not only to countless traumatic events at the hands of her inquisitors but also to the torture and execution of that &quot;bewitcher of young nuns&quot;, Gaufridi himself. Beelzebub was also imagined to be sowing his influence in Salem, Massachusetts: his name came up repeatedly during the [[Salem witch trials]], the last large-scale public expression of witch hysteria in North America or Europe, and afterwards, Rev. [[Cotton Mather]] wrote a [[pamphlet]] entitled ''Of Beelzebub and his Plot''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20020921203915/http://www.4literature.net/Cotton_Mather/Of_Beelzebub_and_His_Plot ''Of Beelzebub and his Plot'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

*[[Baʿal]]
*[[Beelzebufo]] (prehistoric frog)
*[[Belial]]
*[[Harrowing of Hell]]
*[[Ishtar Gate]]
*''[[Lord of the Flies (novel)|Lord of the Flies]]''

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02388c.htm ''Catholic Encyclopedia'':] Beelzebub
*[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=498&amp;letter=B ''Jewish Encyclopedia'':] Beelzebub

==Bibliography==
* {{it}} {{cite book|last=Garbini|first=Giovanni|title=I filistei : gli antagonisti di Israele|year=1997|publisher=Rusconi|location=Milano|isbn=88-18-88046-2|edition=1. ed.}}
* {{en}} {{cite journal|last=MacLaurin|first=E. C. B.|title=Beelzeboul|journal=Novum Testamentum|year=1978|month=April|volume=20|issue=1|pages=156–160|jstor=1560470}}
* {{en}} {{cite book|last=Rahmouni|first=Aicha|title=Divine Epithets in the Ugaritic Alphabetic Texts|year=2008|publisher=Brill, Leiden|pages=159–161}} (concerning the use of ''zbl b'l'' in Ugarit)
* {{en}} {{cite book|last=editors|first=Karel van der Toorn, Bob Becking, Pieter W. van der Horst,|title=Dictionary of deities and demons in the Bible (DDD)|year=1998|publisher=Brill|location=Leiden|isbn=90-04-11119-0|edition=2., extensively rev. ed.}}

[[Category:Abrahamic mythology]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Demons in Christianity]]
[[Category:Demons in Judaism]]
[[Category:Testament of Solomon]]
[[Category:Satan]]

[[bn:বাইলজাবাব]]
[[bg:Велзевул]]
[[ca:Belzebú]]
[[cs:Belzebub]]
[[cy:Beelsebwl]]
[[da:Beelzebub]]
[[de:Beelzebub]]
[[et:Peltsebul]]
[[es:Belcebú]]
[[eo:Belzebubo]]
[[fr:Belzébuth]]
[[ko:베엘제붑]]
[[hr:Belzebub]]
[[is:Belsíbúbb]]
[[it:Beelzebub]]
[[he:בעל זבוב (אל)]]
[[lt:Belzebubas]]
[[hu:Belzebub]]
[[nl:Beëlzebub]]
[[ja:ベルゼブブ]]
[[no:Beelzebub]]
[[pl:Belzebub]]
[[pt:Belzebu]]
[[ro:Beelzebul]]
[[ru:Вельзевул]]
[[sk:Baal-zebúb]]
[[sl:Belcebub]]
[[sr:Belzebub]]
[[fi:Beelzebub]]
[[sv:Beelzebub]]
[[tl:Beelzebub]]
[[th:เบลเซบับ]]
[[uk:Вельзевул]]
[[wo:Beelsebul]]
[[zh:巴力西卜]]</text>
      <sha1>9qbuxtgxghy0mqrt2striclmicd46xt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
