<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Biblical inerrancy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>301913</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521299638</id>
      <parentid>518166125</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T03:00:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>StAnselm</username>
        <id>4007668</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */ Added wikilinks, reworded to eliminate unsubstantiated claim</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51134">{{About|the conservative Christian doctrinal position|Jewish doctrinal positions|Rabbinic literature}}
{{distinguish|Biblical infallibility}}

{{Bible related}}

'''Biblical inerrancy''' is the [[doctrine]] that the [[Bible]] is accurate and totally free of error (except for errors made in translation or transcription), that &quot;Scripture in the original manuscripts does not affirm anything that is contrary to fact.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Grudem90&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|first=Wayne A.|last=Grudem|authorlink=Wayne Grudem|title=Systematic theology: an introduction to biblical doctrine|publisher=[[Inter-Varsity Press]]|location=[[Leicester]]|year=1994|page=90|isbn=978-0-85110-652-6|oclc=29952151}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some equate ''inerrancy'' with ''[[biblical infallibility|infallibility]]''; others do not.&lt;ref&gt;McKim, DK, ''Westminster dictionary of theological terms'', Westminster John Knox Press, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Geisler, N. L. (ed), ''Inerrancy'', Zondervan, 1980, p. 22. &quot;The trouble is that such a distinction is nowhere to be found in Jesus' own teaching. and seems to be precluded by His testimony both to the unqualified historical accuracy and the inspiration of the Old Testament. .. The attempt to discriminate ... seems to be a product of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Advocates of biblical inerrancy, called biblical inerrantists, generally believe that the original text was without error because God inspired the authors and redactors of the Bible. Although none of the original manuscripts currently exist, some biblical inerranists argue that the original text has been perfectly preserved and passed down through time. Others hold that scholarly reconstructions come as near as possible to the original text and so can be said to be inerrant. These reconstructions are based upon scholars' comparison of thousands of biblical manuscripts (such as the [[Dead Sea Scrolls]]) and thousands of biblical citations in the writings of the early [[Church Fathers]].&lt;ref&gt;McCann, Vincent. ''The Bible: Inerrant and Infallible?'' Spotlight Ministries, 2001. [http://www.spotlightministries.org.uk/inner.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terms and opinions==
Another often-used adjective to characterize the Bible is &quot;infallible&quot;. From dictionary definitions, Frame (2002) insists that this is a stronger term than &quot;inerrant&quot;. &quot;'Inerrant' means there are no errors; 'infallible' means there ''can be'' no errors.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Frame, John M. &quot;Is the Bible Inerrant?&quot; IIIM Magazine Online, Volume 4, Number 19, May 13 to May 20, 2002 [http://reformedperspectives.org/files/reformedperspectives/theology/TH.Frame.inerrancy.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Yet he agrees that &quot;modern theologians insist on redefining that word also, so that it actually says less than 'inerrancy.'&quot; [[Harold Lindsell|Lindsell]] (1978) states that &quot;The very nature of inspiration renders the Bible infallible, which means that it cannot deceive us. It is inerrant in that it is not false, mistaken, or defective.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Harold Lindsell|Lindsell, Harold]]. ''The Battle for the Bible.'' Zondervan, 1978, p.31. ISBN 978-0-310-27681-4&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Judaism]] had never promulgated a belief in the literal word of the [[Hebrew Bible]], hence the co-existence of the [[Oral Torah]].&lt;ref&gt;Schimmel, H. Chaim, ''The Oral Law: The rabbinic contribution to Torah Shebe'al Peh'', 2nd, revised ed., Feldheim Publishers, Jerusalem, 1996, pp.19-21&lt;/ref&gt;
Within [[Christianity]], some mainstream [[Evangelical]] and [[Protestant]] groups adhere to the current inerrancy of [[Scripture]] as it reads today. However, some note that &quot;Evangelical scholars ... doubt that accepting the doctrine of biblical inerrancy is the best way to assert their belief in biblical authority.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopædia Britannica'', &quot;Evangelicalism&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
The editors of the ''[[New American Bible]]'' summarize the [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] view:
:[[Pope Leo XIII]] in his encyclical ''[[Providentissimus Deus]]'' . . . reaffirmed the decisions of the [[Council of Trent]] and emphasized that the Bible in all its parts was inspired and that a stated fact must be accepted as falling under inspiration, down to the most insignificant item; that is, ''the whole Bible is the Word of God''.&lt;ref&gt;
&quot;Origin, Inspiration, and History of the Bible&quot; preface in ''[[New American Bible]]'', Church Edition (Wichita, KS: [[DeVore &amp; Sons Inc.#Fireside Publishing|Fireside Bible Publishers]], 2005-2006), p. xxii, Copyright © [[Confraternity of Christian Doctrine]], ISBN 1-55665-493-6, ISBN 978-1-55665-490-9.
&lt;/ref&gt;

In an article for ''The Catholic Study Bible'', &quot;The Bible in Catholic Life&quot;, [[Daniel J. Harrington|Daniel J. Harrington, S.J.]] highlights the teachings found in the [[Second Vatican Council]]'s document ''Dogmatic Constitution on Divine Revelation'' (''[[Dei Verbum]]'') which he says &quot;should be taken as the authoritative climax of a long series of developments in the Church's attitude toward the Bible.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
Harrington, Daniel J., &quot;The Bible in Catholic Life,&quot; in ''The Catholic Study Bible'', Donald Senior, General Editor, Oxford University Press, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;
This conciliar document states:
{{quote|Since, therefore, all that the inspired authors, or sacred writers, affirm should be regarded as affirmed by the Holy Spirit, we must acknowledge that the books of Scripture firmly, faithfully and without error teach that truth which God, for the sake of our salvation, wished to see confided to the sacred Scriptures.
}}
The document then cites {{Bibleref2|2Tim|3:16-17||2 Timothy 3:16-17}}.&lt;ref&gt;
''Dogmatic Constitution on Divine Revelation'', ''Vatican Council II: The Conciliar and Post-Conciliar Documents'', Costello Publishing, 1975.&lt;/ref&gt;

Conservative theologians in some religions often{{fact|date=September 2012}} use the term &quot;inerrancy&quot;: in Christianity to refer to the [[Old Testament|Old]] and [[New Testament]]s, in [[Islam]] to refer to the [[Qur'an]], and in other religions to refer to their own holy books.

Some literalist or conservative Christians teach that the Bible lacks error in every way in all matters: chronology, history, biology, sociology, psychology, politics, physics, math, art, and so on.&lt;ref name=&quot;inerrancy&quot;&gt;
{{cite book|last=Geisler &amp; Nix|publisher=Moody Press, Chicago|year=1986|title=A General Introduction to the Bible|isbn= 0-8024-2916-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Other Christians believe that the Scriptures are always right (do not err) only in fulfilling their primary purpose: revealing God, God's vision, God's purposes, and God's good news to humanity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tolerance&quot;&gt;
Robinson, B.A. &quot;Inerrancy: Is the Bible free of error? All points of view.&quot; Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance, 2008-SEP-01. Web: 25 January 2010. [http://www.religioustolerance.org/inerrant.htm Inerrancy: Is the Bible free of error?']
&lt;/ref&gt;

Mainstream [[Judaism]] and [[Christian]] traditions hold that the [[Torah]] or Pentateuch of the Hebrew Bible was physically written by [[Moses]] — not by God himself, although in the process of transcription many thousands of times copyists have allowed errors, or (some suggest) even forgeries in the text to accumulate.&lt;ref&gt;
Tov, Emanuel, ''Textual criticism of the Hebrew Bible'', Uitgeverij Van Gorcum, 2001, p.213&lt;/ref&gt; According to this position, God originally spoke through a select person to reveal his purpose, character and plan for humanity. However the Bible does record some direct statements from God (i.e.,''&quot;Thus says the Lord ...&quot;, &quot;And God said ...&quot;,'' etc.). The significance of most phrases, their parts, grammar, and occasionally individual words, letters and even [[Cantillation|pronunciation]] in the Hebrew Bible are the subject of many rabbinic [[Baraita of Rabbi Ishmael|discussions]] in the [[Talmud]].

==History==
During the 18th and 19th centuries, various episodes of the Bible (for example the [[Genesis flood narrative|Noahide worldwide flood]],&lt;ref&gt;Plimer, Ian (1994), ''Telling Lies for God: Reason vs Creationism'', Random House&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Genesis creation narrative|creation in six days]], and the [[Adam and Eve|creation of women from a man's rib]]) began increasingly to be seen as legendary. This led to an increasing questioning as to the veracity of Biblical texts. According to an article in ''Theology Today'' published in 1975, &quot;There have been long periods in the history of the church when biblical inerrancy has not been a critical question. It has in fact been noted that only in the last two centuries can we legitimately speak of a formal doctrine of inerrancy. The arguments pro and con have filled many books, and almost anyone can join in the debate.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;infallible&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Coleman|journal=Theology Today| volume = 31|issue = 4|year=1975|title=Biblical Inerrancy: Are We Going Anywhere?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1970s and '80s, however, the debate in theological circles, which centered on the issue of whether or not the Bible was [[Biblical infallibility|infallible]] or both infallible and inerrant, came into the spotlight. Some notable Christian [[seminary|seminaries]], such as [[Princeton Theological Seminary]] and [[Fuller Theological Seminary]], were formally adopting the doctrine of infallibility while rejecting the doctrine of inerrancy.

The other side of this debate focused largely around the magazine ''[[Christianity Today]]'' and the book entitled ''The Battle for the Bible'' by Harold Lindsell.&lt;ref&gt;Lindsell, Harold. ''The Battle for the Bible.'' Zondervan, 1978. ISBN 978-0-310-27681-4&lt;/ref&gt; The author asserted that losing the doctrine of the inerrancy of [[Scripture]] was the thread that would unravel the church. [[Christian fundamentalism|Conservative Christians]] rallied behind this idea, agreeing that once ''[[sola scriptura]]'' Christians disregard the ultimate truthfulness of the Bible, anything can become justifiable.

==Textual tradition of the New Testament==
{{See also|Biblical canon|Bible translations|Textual criticism}}

There are over 5,600 Greek [[manuscript]]s containing all or part of the [[New Testament]], as well as over 10,000 Latin manuscripts, and perhaps 500 other manuscripts of various other languages. Additionally, there are the [[Patristic]] writings which contain copious quotes, across the early centuries, of the scriptures.

Most of these manuscripts date to the [[Middle Ages]]. The oldest complete copy of the New Testament, the [[Codex Sinaiticus]], which includes two other books&lt;ref&gt;The [[Epistle of Barnabas]] and [[The Shepherd of Hermas]]&lt;/ref&gt; not now included in the accepted NT canon, dates to the 4th century. The earliest fragment of a New Testament book is the [[Rylands Library Papyrus P52]] which dates to the mid 2nd century and is the size of a business card. Very early manuscripts are rare.

The average NT manuscript is about 200 pages, and in all, there are about 1.3 million pages of text. No two manuscripts are identical, except in the smallest fragments, and the many manuscripts which preserve New Testament texts differ among themselves in many respects, with some estimates of 200,000 to 300,000 differences among the various manuscripts.&lt;ref&gt;See Ehrman, ''Lost Christianities: The Battles for Scripture and the Faiths We Never Knew'', p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Bart D. Ehrman|Bart Ehrman]],&lt;ref&gt;See Ehrman, ''Lost Christianities: The Battles for Scripture and the Faiths We Never Knew'', p. 220&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Most changes are careless errors that are easily recognized and corrected. Christian scribes often made mistakes simply because they were tired or inattentive or, sometimes, inept. Indeed, the single most common mistake in our manuscripts involves &quot;[[orthography]]&quot;, significant for little more than showing that scribes in antiquity could spell no better than most of us can today. In addition, we have numerous manuscripts in which scribes have left out entire words, verses, or even pages of a book, presumably by accident. Sometimes scribes rearranged the words on the page, for example, by leaving out a word and then reinserting it later in the sentence.}}

In the 2008 Greer-Heard debate series, noted New Testament scholars [[Bart Ehrman]] and [[Daniel B. Wallace]] discussed these variances in detail. Wallace mentioned that understanding the meaning of the number of variances is not as simple as looking at the number of variances, but one must consider also the number of manuscripts, the types of errors, and among the more serious discrepancies, what impact they do or do not have.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|editor-first= Robert B.|editor-last= Stewart|year= 2011|title= The Reliability of the New Testament: Bart Ehrman and Daniel Wallace in Dialogue|location= Minneapolis, Minnesota|publisher= [[Fortress Press]]|isbn= 978-0-8006-9773-0|oclc= 646121910 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

For hundreds of years, biblical and textual scholars have examined the manuscripts extensively. Since the eighteenth century, they have employed the techniques of [[textual criticism]] to reconstruct how the extant manuscripts of the New Testament texts might have descended, and to recover earlier [[recension]]s of the texts. However, [[Authorized King James Version|King James Version (KJV)]]-only inerrantists often prefer the traditional texts (i.e., [[Textus Receptus]] which is the basis of KJV) used in their churches to modern attempts of reconstruction (i.e., [[Novum Testamentum Graece|Nestle-Aland Greek Text]] which is the basis of modern translations), arguing that the [[Holy Spirit]] is just as active in the preservation of the scriptures as in their creation. These inerrantists are found particularly in non-Protestant churches, but also a few Protestant groups hold such views.

KJV-only inerrantist [[Jack Moorman]] says that at least 356 doctrinal passages are affected by the differences between the Textus Receptus and the Nestle-Aland Greek Text.&lt;ref&gt;Jack Moorman, ''Missing In Modern Bibles - Is the Full Story Being Told?'', Bible for Today, 1989, 83 pages&lt;/ref&gt;

Some familiar examples of Gospel passages in the Textus Receptus thought to have been added by later interpolaters and omitted in the Nestle Aland Greek Text include the [[Pericope Adulteræ]], {{Bibleref2c|Jn|7:53-8:11}} the [[Comma Johanneum]], {{Bibleref2c|1Jn|5:7–8|NIV|1 Jn 5:7–8}} and the longer ending in [[Mark 16]].{{Bibleref2c|Mk|16:9-20}}

Many modern Bibles have footnotes to indicate areas where there is disagreement between source documents. Bible commentaries offer discussions of these.

===Inerrantist response===
====Evangelical inerrantists====
[[Evangelical Christians]] generally accept the findings of [[textual criticism]], and nearly all modern translations, including the popular [[New International Version]], work from a Greek New Testament based on modern textual criticism.

Since this means that the manuscript copies are not perfect, inerrancy is only applied to the original autographs (the manuscripts written by the original authors) rather than the copies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grudem90&quot;/&gt; For instance, the [[Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy]] says, &quot;We affirm that inspiration, strictly speaking, applies only to the autographic text of Scripture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.churchcouncil.org/ICCP_org/Documents_ICCP/English/01_Biblical_Inerrancy_A&amp;D.pdf|title=Chicago Statement on Biblical Innerancy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Less commonly, more conservative views are held by some groups:

====King James Only inerrantists====
A faction of those in the &quot;[[King James Only movement]]&quot; rejects the whole discipline of [[textual criticism]] and holds that the translators of the [[King James Version]] English Bible were guided by God, and that the KJV thus is to be taken as the authoritative English Bible. However, those who hold this opinion do not extend it to the KJV translation into English of the [[Biblical apocrypha|Apocryphal]] books, which were produced along with the rest of the Authorized Version. Modern translations differ from the KJV on numerous points, sometimes resulting from access to different early texts, largely as a result of work in the field of textual criticism. Upholders of the KJV-only position nevertheless hold that the [[Protestant]] canon of KJV is itself an inspired text and therefore remains authoritative. The King James Only movement asserts that the KJV is the ''sole'' [[English language|English]] translation free from error.&lt;!-- Some hold that the King James Version is the only translation into ''any'' language that is free from error. --&gt;

====Textus Receptus====
Similar to the King James Only view is the view that [[King James Only#Similar Movements in Non-English Speaking Countries|translations must be derived from]] the [[Textus Receptus]] in order to be considered inerrant. As the King James Version is an English translation, this leaves speakers of other languages in a difficult position, hence the belief in the Textus Receptus as the inerrant source text for translations to modern languages. For example, in Spanish-speaking cultures the commonly accepted &quot;KJV-equivalent&quot; is the [[Reina-Valera]] 1909 revision (with different groups accepting, in addition to the 1909 or in its place, the revisions of 1862 or 1960). It should also be noted that the [[New King James Version]] was also translated from the Textus Receptus.

==Justifications==
A number of reasons are offered by Christian theologians to justify Biblical inerrancy.

[[Norman Geisler]] and [[William Nix]] (1986) claim that scriptural inerrancy is established by a number of observations and processes, which include:&lt;ref name=&quot;inerrancy&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| last=[[Norman Geisler]] and [[William Nix]]
| publisher=Moody Press, Chicago
| year=1986
| title=A General Introduction to the Bible
| isbn= 0-8024-2916-5
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:* The historical accuracy of the Bible
:* The Bible's claims of its own inerrancy
:* Church history and tradition
:* One's individual experience with God

[[Daniel B. Wallace]], Professor of New Testament at [[Dallas Theological Seminary]], divides the various evidences into two approaches - deductive and inductive approaches.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bible.org/page.php?page_id=4200 My Take on Inerrancy], [http://www.bible.org/ bible.org] website&lt;/ref&gt;

===Deductive justifications===
The first deductive justification is that the Bible claims to be inspired by God (for instance &quot;All Scripture is God-breathed and is useful for teaching, rebuking, correcting and training in righteousness&quot;{{Bibleref2c|2Tim|3:16|NIV|2 Tim 3:16}}) and because God is perfect, the Bible must also be perfect, and hence free from error. For instance, the statement of faith of the [[Evangelical Theological Society]] says, &quot;The Bible alone, and the Bible in its entirety, is the Word of God written and is therefore inerrant in the autographs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etsjets.org/?q=about About the ETS], [[Evangelical Theological Society]] web site&lt;/ref&gt;

Supportive of this, is the idea that God cannot lie. W J Mcrea writes:&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Bible then makes two basic claims: it asserts unequivocally that God cannot lie, and that the Bible is the Word of God. It is primarily from a combination of these facts that the argument for inerrancy comes.&lt;ref&gt;McRea, WJ, ''A book to die for'', Clements publishing, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;And Grenz has: &lt;blockquote&gt;
Because God cannot lie and because Scripture is inspired by God, the bible must be wholly true. This syllogism may be valid for establishing inerrancy, but it cannot define the concept.&lt;ref&gt;Grenz, SJ, ''Theology for the community of God'', Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Also, from Geisler:&lt;blockquote&gt;Those who defend inerrancy are deductivists pure and simple. They begin with certain assumptions about God and the Scriptures, namely, that God cannot lie and the Scriptures are the Word of God. From these assumptions inerrantists deduce that the Bible is without error.&lt;ref&gt;Geisler, NL, ''Inerrancy'', Zondervan, 1980, p271.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A second reason offered is that [[Jesus]] and the apostles used the [[Old Testament]] in a way which assumes it is inerrant. For instance in {{Bibleref2|Galatians|3:16}}, [[Paul the Apostle|Paul]] bases his argument on the fact that the word &quot;seed&quot; in the Genesis reference to &quot;Abraham and his seed&quot;, is singular rather than plural. This (as claimed) sets a precedent for inerrant interpretation down to the individual letters of the words.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bible 1984&quot;&gt;&quot;Bible, Inerrancy and Infallibility of&quot;, by P.D.Feinberg, in ''Evangelical Dictionary of Theology'' (Baker, 1984, Ed. W.Elwell)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Now the promises were spoken to Abraham and to his seed. He does not say, &quot;And to seeds,&quot; as (referring) to many, but (rather) to one, &quot;And to your seed,&quot; that is, Christ.{{Bibleref2c|Gal|3:16}}}}

Similarly Jesus said that every minute detail of the Old Testament Law must be fulfilled,{{Bibleref2c|Mt|:18}} indicating (it is claimed) that every detail must be correct.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bible 1984&quot; /&gt;

{{quote|For verily I say unto you, Till heaven and earth pass, one jot or one tittle shall in no wise pass from the law, till all be fulfilled.| {{Bibleref2|Mt|5:18|KJV}}, KJV}}

Although in these verses Jesus and the apostles are only referring to the [[Old Testament]], the argument extends to the [[New Testament]] writings, because {{Bibleref2|2Peter|3:16|NIV|2 Peter 3:16}} accords the status of Scripture to New Testament writings also: &quot;He (Paul) writes the same way in all his letters... which ignorant and unstable people distort, as they do the other Scriptures.&quot;{{Bibleref2c|2Peter|3:16|NIV|2 Pet 3:16}} &lt;ref&gt;[http://beta.biblestudytools.com/mybst/default.aspx?type=library&amp;contentid=88104&amp;category=REF Bible, Inspiration of], by Nigel M. de S. Cameron, in &quot;''Baker's Evangelical Dictionary of Biblical Theology''&quot;, Edited by Walter A. Elwell, Baker, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;

Another deductive argument would be the strength of falsifiability. The argument is that Biblical inerrancy is a falsifiable stance (it can be proven false). In this case, if errors are proven in the Biblical text then the stance of Biblical inerrancy is itself false.

===Inductive justifications===
Wallace describes the inductive approach by enlisting the [[Presbyterian]] theologian [[Benjamin Breckinridge Warfield]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;In his ''Inspiration and Authority of the Bible'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Warfield 48&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Warfield|first1=Benjamin|authorlink=Benjamin Breckinridge Warfield|editor1-last=Craig|editor1-first=Samuel|editor1-link=Samuel G Craig|others=with introduction by [[Cornelius Van Til]]|title=The Inspiration and Authority of the Bible|edition=1st|publisher=[[Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing Company]]|location= [[Phillipsburg, New Jersey|Phillipsburg]], [[New Jersey]]|isbn=978-0-87552-527-3|oclc=223791198|year=1948}}&lt;/ref&gt; Warfield lays out an argument for inerrancy that has been virtually ignored by today's evangelicals. Essentially, he makes a case for inerrancy on the basis of inductive evidence, rather than deductive reasoning. Most evangelicals today follow E. J. Young's deductive approach toward bibliology, forgetting the great articulator of inerrancy. But Warfield starts with the evidence that the Bible is a historical document, rather than with the presupposition that it is inspired.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bible.org/article/my-take-inerrancy|title=My Take on Inerrancy|author=Daniel B. Wallace|publisher=bible.com|accessdate=17 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Inspiration====
In the [[Nicene Creed]] Christians confess their belief that the Holy Spirit &quot;has spoken through the prophets.&quot; This creed has been normative for Roman Catholics, Eastern Orthodox, Anglicans, Lutherans and all mainline Protestant denominations except for those descended from the non-credal [[Stone-Campbell movement]]. As noted by [[Alister E. McGrath]], &quot;An important element in any discussion of the manner in which Scripture is inspired, and the significance which is attached to this, is 2 Timothy 3:16-17, which speaks of Scripture as 'God-breathed' (''theopneustos'').&quot; According to McGrath, &quot;the reformers did not see the issue of inspiration as linked with the absolute historical reliability or factual inerrancy of the biblical texts.&quot; He says, &quot;The development of ideas of 'biblical infallibility' or 'inerrancy' within Protestantism can be traced to the United States in the middle of the nineteenth century.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McGrath, Alister E., ''Christian Theology: An Introduction'', Oxford: Blackwell Publishers, 1994; 3rd ed. 2001. p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt;

People who believe in inerrancy think that the Bible does not merely contain the Word of God, but every word of it is, because of verbal inspiration, the direct, immediate word of God.&lt;ref&gt;
{{bibleverse|2|Timothy|3:16|50}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|2:13|50}}, {{bibleverse|1|Thessalonians|2:13|50}}, {{Bibleref2|Romans|3:2|50}}, {{bibleverse|2|Peter|1:21|50}}, {{bibleverse|2|Samuel|23:2|50}}, {{Bibleref2|Hebrews|1:1|50}}, {{Bibleref2|John|10:35|50}}, {{Bibleref2-nb|| John|16:13|50}}, {{Bibleref2-nb|| John|17:17|50}}, {{cite book|last=Engelder|first=Theodore E.W.|url=http://www.archive.org/details/MN41551ucmf_1|title=Popular Symbolics: The Doctrines of the Churches of Christendom and of Other Religious Bodies Examined in the Light of Scripture|page=26|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1934}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lutheran [[Apology of the Augsburg Confession]] identifies Holy Scripture with the Word of God&lt;ref&gt;&quot;God's Word, or Holy Scripture&quot; from the [http://www.bookofconcord.org/defense_2_originalsin.php Apology of the Augsburg Confession, Article II, of Original Sin]&lt;/ref&gt; and calls the Holy Spirit the author of the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;the Scripture of the Holy Ghost.&quot; [http://www.bookofconcord.org/defense_greeting.php Apology to the Augsburg Confession, Preface, 9]&lt;/ref&gt; Because of this, Lutherans confess in the [[Formula of Concord]], &quot;we receive and embrace with our whole heart the prophetic and apostolic Scriptures of the Old and New Testaments as the pure, clear fountain of Israel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bookofconcord.org/sd-ruleandnorm.php The Solid Declaration of the Formula of Concord, &quot;Rule and Norm&quot;, 3.]&lt;/ref&gt; Lutherans (and other Protestants) believe apocryphal books are not inspired nor written by prophets, and that they contain errors and were never included in the &quot;Palestinian Canon&quot; that Jesus and the Apostles are said to have used,&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.lcms.org/ca/www/cyclopedia/02/display.asp?t1=C&amp;word=CANON.BIBLE Bible, Canon in the Christian Cyclopedia]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore are not a part of Holy Scripture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engelder 1934 27&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Engelder|first=Theodore E.W.|url=http://www.archive.org/details/MN41551ucmf_1|title=Popular Symbolics: The Doctrines of the Churches of Christendom and Of Other Religious Bodies Examined in the Light of Scripture|page=27|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1934}}&lt;/ref&gt; The prophetic and apostolic Scriptures are authentic as written by the prophets and apostles. A correct translation of their writings is God's Word because it has the same meaning as the original Hebrew and Greek.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engelder 1934 27&quot; /&gt; A mistranslation is not God's word, and no human authority can invest it with divine authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engelder 1934 27&quot; /&gt;

However, the 19th century Anglican biblical scholar [[Samuel Rolles Driver|S.R. Driver]] held a contrary view, saying that, &quot;as inspiration does not suppress the individuality of the biblical writers, so it does not altogether neutralise their human infirmities or confer upon them immunity from error.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Driver, S.R., Church Congress speech, cited in F.W. Farrar, ''The Bible: Its Meaning and Supremacy'', Longmans, Green, and Co., 1897.&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, J.K. Mozley, an early 20th century Anglican theologian has argued:
{{quote|That the Bible is inspired is, indeed, a primary Christian conviction; it is from this that certain consequences have been drawn, such as infallibility and inerrancy, which retain their place in Christian thought because they are held to be bound up with the affirmation of inspiration. But the deductions can be rejected without any ambiguity as to the fact of inspiration. Neither 'fundamentalists' nor sceptics are to be followed at this point... the Bible is inspired because it is the adequate and indispensible vehicle of revelation; but inspiration does not amount to dictation by God.&lt;ref&gt;Mozley, J.K., &quot;The Bible: Its Unity, Inspiration, and Authority,&quot; in W.R. Matthews, ed., ''The Christian Faith: Essays in Explanation and Defense'', Harper and Bros., 1936. pp. 58-59.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Divine authority====
For a believer in biblical inerrancy, Holy Scripture is the Word of God, and carries the full authority of God. Every single statement of the Bible calls for instant and unqualified acceptance.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Matthew|4:3|31}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|4:3|31}}, {{bibleref2|Genesis|3:1|31}}, {{bibleref2|John|10:35|31}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|24:25|31}}, {{bibleref2|Psalm|119:140|31}}, {{bibleref2|Psalm|119:167|31}}, {{cite book|last=Engelder|first=Theodore E.W.|url=http://www.archive.org/details/MN41551ucmf_1|title=Popular Symbolics: The Doctrines of the Churches of Christendom and Of Other Religious Bodies Examined in the Light of Scripture|page=27|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1934}}, {{cite book|last=Graebner|first=Augustus Lawrence|url=http://showcase.netins.net/web/bilarson/bibliology.txt|title=Outlines Of Doctrinal Theology|pages=8–9|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1910}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every doctrine of the Bible is the teaching of God and therefore requires full agreement.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Thessalonians|2:15|31}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|24:25-27|31}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|16:29-31|31}}, {{bibleverse|2|Timothy|3:15-17|31}},
{{bibleref2|Jeremiah|8:9|31}}, {{bibleref2|Jeremiah|23:26|31}}, {{bibleref2|Isaiah|8:19-20|31}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|14:37|31}}, {{bibleref2|Galatians|1:8|31}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|17:11|31}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|15:14-15|31}}, {{cite book|last=Graebner|first=Augustus Lawrence|url=http://showcase.netins.net/web/bilarson/bibliology.txt|title=Outlines Of Doctrinal Theology|pages=8–10|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1910}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every promise of the Bible calls for unshakable trust in its fulfillment.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Thessalonians|2:13|31}}, {{bibleverse|2|Corinthians|1:20|31}}, {{bibleref2|Titus|1:2-3|31}}, {{bibleverse|2|Thessalonians|2:15|31}}, {{bibleverse|2|Peter|1:19|31}},
{{cite book|last=Graebner|first=Augustus Lawrence|url=http://showcase.netins.net/web/bilarson/bibliology.txt|title=Outlines Of Doctrinal Theology|pages=8–9|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1910}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every command of the Bible is the directive of God himself and therefore demands willing observance.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Deuteronomy|12:32|31}}, {{bibleref2-nb|Deuteronomy|5:9-10|31}}, {{bibleref2|James|2:10|31}}, {{bibleref2|Joshua|1:8|31}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|16:29|31}}, {{bibleverse|2|Timothy|3:16|31}}, {{cite book|last=Graebner|first=Augustus Lawrence|url=http://showcase.netins.net/web/bilarson/bibliology.txt|title=Outlines Of Doctrinal Theology|pages=8–11|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1910}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sufficiency====
According to some believers, the Bible contains everything that they need to know in order to obtain salvation and to live a Christian life,&lt;ref&gt;
{{bibleverse|2|Timothy|3:15-17|31}}, {{bibleref2|John|5:39|31}}, {{bibleref2-nb|John|17:20|31}}, {{bibleref2|Psalm|19:7-8|31}}, {{cite book|last=Engelder|first=Theodore E.W.|url=http://www.archive.org/details/MN41551ucmf_1|title=Popular Symbolics: The Doctrines of the Churches of Christendom and Of Other Religious Bodies Examined in the Light of Scripture|page=28|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1934}}&lt;/ref&gt; and there are no deficiencies in Scripture that need to be filled with by [[sacred tradition|tradition]], pronouncements of the Pope, [[Revelation (Latter Day Saints)|new revelations]], or present-day [[development of doctrine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Isaiah|8:20|50}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|16:29-31|50}}, {{bibleverse|2|Timothy|3:16-17|31}}, {{cite book|last=Graebner|first=Augustus Lawrence|url= http://showcase.netins.net/web/bilarson/bibliology.txt|title=Outlines Of Doctrinal Theology|page=13|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1910}}{{dead link|date=June 2012}}, {{cite book|last=Engelder|first=Theodore E.W.|url=http://www.archive.org/details/MN41551ucmf_1|title=Popular Symbolics: The Doctrines of the Churches of Christendom and Of Other Religious Bodies Examined in the Light of Scripture|page=28|location=Saint Louis, MO|publisher=Concordia Publishing House|year=1934}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Clarifications==
===Accuracy===
Harold Lindsell points out that it is a &quot;gross distortion&quot; to state that people who believe in inerrancy suppose every statement made in the Bible is true (as opposed to accurate).&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindsell&quot;&gt;Lindsell, Harold. &quot;The Battle for the Bible&quot;, Zondervan Publishing House, Grand Rapids, Michigan, USA (1976), pg. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; He indicates there are expressly false statements in the Bible which are reported accurately.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindsell&quot; /&gt; He notes that &quot;All the Bible does, for example in the case of Satan, is to report what Satan actually said. Whether what he said was true or false is another matter. Christ stated that the devil is a liar.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindsell&quot; /&gt;

===Limitations===
Many who believe in the ''Inspiration'' of scripture teach that it is ''[[biblical infallibility|infallible]]'' but not inerrant. Those who subscribe to infallibility believe that what the scriptures say regarding matters of faith and Christian practice are wholly useful and true. Some denominations that teach infallibility hold that the historical or scientific details, which may be irrelevant to matters of faith and Christian practice, may contain errors. Those who believe in inerrancy hold that the scientific, geographic, and historic details of the scriptural texts in their original manuscripts are completely true and without error, though the scientific claims of scripture must be interpreted in the light of its [[phenomenology (science)|phenomenological]] nature, not just with strict, clinical literality, which was foreign to historical narratives.&lt;ref name=&quot;inerrancy&quot; /&gt;

Proponents of biblical inerrancy generally do not teach that the Bible was dictated directly by God, but that God used the &quot;distinctive personalities and literary styles of the writers&quot; of scripture and that [[Biblical inspiration|God's inspiration]] guided them to flawlessly project his message through their own language and personality.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy|Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy]], Article VIII&lt;/ref&gt;

Infallibility and inerrancy refer to the original texts of the Bible. And while conservative scholars acknowledge the potential for human error in transmission and translation, modern translations are considered to &quot;faithfully represent the originals&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy|Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy]], Article X&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
===Scientific and historical criticism===
{{See also|Criticism of the Bible|Internal consistency of the Bible|Science and the Bible|The Bible and history}}
Biblical inerrancy has been criticized on the grounds that many statements, including, but not exclusively, [[history]] or [[science]] that are found in Scripture, if taken literally, rather than phenomenologically, are untenable or contradictory. Inerrancy is argued to be a [[Modus tollens|falsifiable]] proposition: if the Bible is found to contain any mistakes or [[Internal consistency of the Bible|contradictions]], the proposition of strict inerrancy has been refuted.

===Theological criticism===
''Theological criticism'' refers to criticisms which are that the Bible does not teach, or require, its own inerrancy.

Proponents of biblical inerrancy often prefer the translations of {{bibleverse|2|Timothy|3:16|9}} that render it as &quot;all scripture is given by inspiration of God,&quot; and they interpret this to mean that the whole Bible is inerrant. However, critics of this doctrine think that the Bible makes no direct claim to be inerrant or infallible. [[C. H. Dodd]] argues the same sentence can also be translated &quot;Every inspired scripture is also useful...&quot; nor does the verse define the [[Biblical canon]].&lt;ref&gt;Dodd, C. H. ''The Authority of the Bible'', London, 1960. p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; In context, this passage refers only to the Old Testament writings understood to be scripture at the time it was written.&lt;ref&gt;New Jerusalem Bible, study edition, page 1967, DLT 1994&lt;/ref&gt; However, there are indications that Paul's writings were being considered, at least by the author of the [[Second Epistle of Peter]],{{Bibleref2c|2Peter|3:16|9|2 Pet 3:16}} as comparable to the Old Testament.&lt;ref&gt;New Jerusalem Bible, page 2010, footnote (i) DLT 1985&lt;/ref&gt;

The idea that the Bible contains no mistakes is mainly justified by appeal to [[prooftext]]s that refer to its divine inspiration. However, this argument has been criticized as [[circular reasoning]], because these statements only have to be accepted as true if the Bible is already thought to be inerrant. None of these texts say that because a text is inspired, it is therefore always correct in its historical statements.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

In the introduction to his book ''Credible Christianity'', Anglican Bishop [[Hugh Montefiore]], makes this comment:
:The doctrine of biblical inerrancy seems inherently improbable, for two reasons. Firstly, the Scriptures contain what seem to be evident errors and contradictions (although great ingenuity has been applied to explain these away). Secondly, the books of the Old and New Testaments did not gain their place within the &quot;canon&quot;, or list of approved books, as soon as they were written. The Old Testament canon was not closed until late in the Apostolic age, and the New Testament canon was not finally closed until the fourth century. If all the Bible's contents were inerrant, one would have thought that this would have become apparent within a much shorter period.&lt;ref&gt;Montefiore, Hugh. ''Credible Christianity: The Gospel in Contemporary Society'', London: Mowbray, 1993; Grand Rapids, Eerdmans, 1994. p. 5. ISBN 0-8028-3768-9&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Meaning of the &quot;Word of God&quot; ====
Much debate over the kind of authority that should be accorded biblical texts centers on what is meant by the &quot;Word of God&quot;. The term can refer to [[Logos (Christianity)|Christ himself]] as well as to the proclamation of his ministry as [[kerygma]]. However, biblical inerrancy differs from this orthodoxy in viewing the Word of God to mean the entire text of the Bible when interpreted didactically as God's teaching.&lt;ref&gt;James Barr, ''Fundamentalism'' p.72ff, SCM 1977.&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of the Bible itself as Word of God, as being itself God's revelation, is criticized in [[neo-orthodoxy]]. Here the Bible is seen as a unique witness to the people and deeds that do make up the Word of God. However, it is a wholly human witness.&lt;ref&gt;James Barr, ''Fundamentalism'' pp.218-219 SCM 1977&lt;/ref&gt; All books of the Bible were written by human beings. Thus, whether the Bible is—in whole or in part&lt;ref&gt;[[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] claims of the [[Ethical Decalogue]] and [[Ritual Decalogue]] that these are God's word.&lt;/ref&gt;—the Word of God is not clear. However, critics argue that the Bible can still be construed as the &quot;Word of God&quot; in the sense that these authors' statements may have been representative of, and perhaps even directly influenced by, God's own knowledge.

There is only one instance in the Bible where the phrase &quot;the Word of God&quot; refers to something &quot;written&quot;. The reference is to the [[Ten Commandments|Decalogue]]. However, most of the other references are to reported speech that is preserved in the Bible. The New Testament also contains a number of statements which refer to passages from the Old Testament as God's words, for instance {{Bibleref2|Romans|3:2}} (which says that the Jews have been &quot;entrusted with the very words of God&quot;), or the book of [[Epistle to the Hebrews|Hebrews]], which often prefaces Old Testament quotations with words such as &quot;God says.&quot; The Bible also contains words spoken by human beings ''about'' God, such as [[Eliphaz (Job)|Eliphaz]] ({{Bibleref2|Job|42:7}}) and the prayers and songs of the Psalter. That these are God's words addressed to us was at the root of a lively medieval controversy.&lt;ref&gt;Uriel Simon, &quot;Four Approaches to the Book of Psalms&quot; chap. 1&lt;/ref&gt; The idea of the word of God is more that God is encountered in scripture, than that every line of scripture is a statement made by God.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander Ryrie, &quot;Deliver Us From Evil&quot;, DLT 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

While the phrase &quot;the Word of God&quot; is never applied to the modern Bible within the Bible itself, supporters of inerrancy argue that that is simply because the Biblical canon was not closed. In {{Bibleref2|1Th|2:13|NIV|1 Thessalonians 2:13}}, the [[apostle Paul]] wrote to the church in [[Thessalonica]] &quot;when you received the word of God which you heard from us, you welcomed it not as the word of men, but as it is in truth, the word of God.&quot;

===Translation===
{{See also|Bible errata|Bible translations|English translations of the Bible}}

Translation has given rise to a number of issues, as the original languages are often quite different in grammar as well as word meaning. While the [[Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy]] states that inerrancy applies only to the original [[language]]s, some believers trust their own translation to be the accurate one. One such group of believers is known as the [[King James Only movement]]. For readability, clarity, or other reasons, translators may choose different wording or sentence structure, and some translations may choose to paraphrase passages. Because some of the words in the original language have ambiguous or difficult to translate meanings, debates over the correct interpretation occur.

Criticisms are also sometimes raised because of inconsistencies arising between different English translations of the Hebrew or Greek text. Some Christian interpretations are criticized for reflecting specific doctrinal bias.{{citation needed|date=March 2011}}

====The virgin birth====
One translation problem concerns the New Testament assertion that Jesus Christ was [[virgin birth of Jesus|born of a virgin]]. If the Bible were inerrant, then this would be true. However, critics have suggested that the use of the word ''virgin'' may have been merely a translation error.
{{bibleref2|Matthew|1:22-1:23|31}} reads: &quot;All this took place to fulfill what the Lord had said through the prophet: 'The ''virgin'' will be with child and will give birth to a son, and ''they'' will call him Immanuel'—which means, 'God with us.'&quot; Critics have argued that Matthew was referring to the prophet [[Isaiah]], but the Greek text he was using was mistaken in its translation of the word ''[[almah]]'' (&quot;עלמה&quot;) in {{Bibleref2|Isaiah|7:14}}:&lt;blockquote&gt;Therefore the Lord himself will give you a sign. Behold, the virgin [(''almah'')] shall conceive and bear a son, and shall call his name Immanuel.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On this point, Browning's ''A Dictionary of the Bible'' states that in the [[Septuagint]], &quot;the Greek ''parthenos'' was used to translate the Hebrew ''almah'', which means a 'young woman'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Browning, WRF, ''A dictionary of the Bible'', Oxford University Press, 2004. Entry for ''virgin birth''.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, &quot;As early as the 2nd cent. CE, the Jewish {{sic|?|contraversialist|expected=controversialist}} Trypho was pointing out that the Hebrew did not mean a virgin.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;See also, [http://www.piney.com/FathJustinDiaTrypho.html Dialogue of Justin Martyr, with Trypho, a Jew, LXIII]&lt;/ref&gt; The dictionary also notes that &quot;the earliest writers of the [New Testament] (Mark and Paul) show no knowledge of such a virginal conception.&quot;

Another writer, [[David Strauss]] in ''The Life of Jesus'', has: &quot;... [the question] ought to be decided by the fact that the word does not signify an immaculate, but a marriageable young woman.&quot; He suggests that Isaiah was referring to events of his own time, and that the young woman in question may have been &quot;perhaps the prophet's own wife.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Strauss, DF., ''The life of Jesus'', Calvin Blanchard, NY, 1860, p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity}}

* [[An Historical Account of Two Notable Corruptions of Scripture]]
* [[Biblical hermeneutics]]
* [[Biblical infallibility]]
* [[Biblical literalism]]
* [[Bibliolatry]]
* [[Chicago Statement on Biblical Inerrancy]]
* [[Divine providence]]
* [[Historical criticism]]
* [[Internal consistency of the Bible]]
* [[John Calvin's view of Scripture]]
* [[Religious skepticism]]
* [[Textual criticism]]
* ''[[What the Bible Really Teaches: A Challenge for Fundamentalists]]''

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* [[Bart D. Ehrman]], 2003. ''Lost Christianities: The Battles for Scripture and the Faiths We Never Knew''. Oxford University Press, Inc. ISBN 0-19-518249-9
* [[Charles Caldwell Ryrie]] (1981). ''What you should know about inerrancy''. ISBN 0-8024-8785-8
* [http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19651118_dei-verbum_en.html Dei Verbum] Dogmatic Constitution on Divine Revelation (1965)
* Ethelbert W.Bullinger, ''Figures of Speech Used in the Bible'' Grand Rapids, Mich.: Baker Book House, 1970.
* [[Gleason Archer]], 2001. ''New Encyclopedia of Bible Difficulties''. ISBN 0-310-24146-4
* {{Cite journal| last = Finkelstein| first = Israel| authorlink = Israel Finkelstein| last2 = Silberman| first2 = Neil Asher| title = [[The Bible Unearthed|The Bible Unearthed: Archaeology's New Vision of Ancient Israel and the Origin of Its Sacred Texts]]| publisher = Simon and Schuster| location = New York| year = 2001| isbn = 0-7432-2338-1| url = http://books.google.com/books?lr=&amp;q=Finkelstein+Bible+Unearthed+Exodus+unoccupied&amp;btnG=Search+Books| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt; }}.
* Herzog, Ze'ev. &quot;Deconstructing the walls of Jericho.&quot; [[Ha'aretz]] October 29, 1999. Web: [http://mideastfacts.org/facts/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=32&amp;Itemid=34 Deconstructing the walls of Jericho].
* [[John Walvoord]] (1990). ''What We Believe: Understanding and Applying the Basics of Christian Life''. ISBN 0-929239-31-8
* Kathleen C. Boone: ''The Bible Tells Them So: The Discourse of Protestant Fundamentalism'', State Univ of New York Press 1989, ISBN 0-88706-895-2
* [[N. T. Wright]], ''The Last Word: Beyond Bible Wars to a New Understanding of the Authority of Scripture.'' Harper-San Francisco, 2005. ISBN 0-06-081609-4{{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (4) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}
* Norman Geisler and Thomas Howe, (1999) ''When Critics Ask: A Popular Handbook on Bible Difficulties.''
* Norman Geisler and William E. Nix., ''A General Introduction to the Bible'', Moody Publishers; Rev&amp;Expndd edition (August 1986), ISBN 0-8024-2916-5
* [[Norman Geisler]], ed. (1980). ''Inerrancy''. ISBN 0-310-39281-0.
* [[R. C. Sproul|Sproul, R. C.]]. ''Hath God Said?'' ([https://ecom.ligonier.org/ecom/product.asp?idProduct=HAT01VC video series]).
* Walter C. Kaiser, Peter H. Davids, [[F. F. Bruce]], Manfred T. Brauch. (1996). ''Hard Sayings of the Bible''
* [[B. B. Warfield|Warfield, B. B.]] (1977 reprint). ''Inspiration and Authority of Bible'', with a lengthy introductory essay by [[Cornelius Van Til]]. ISBN 0-8010-9586-7.

==External links==
{{External links|date=April 2010}}

===Classification===
* [http://www.cesame-nm.org/index.php?name=Sections&amp;req=viewarticle&amp;artid=43&amp;page=4 ''The Bible: Is it a True and Accurate Account of Creation? (Part 2): The Position of Major Christian Denominations on Creation and Inerrancy'']{{dead link|date=June 2012}}, Walter B. Murfin, David F. Beck, 13 April 1998, hosted on [http://www.cesame-nm.org/index.php Coalition for Excellence in Science and Math Education] website
* [http://www.pcusa.org/101/101-bible.htm Presbyterian Church beliefs of the Bible]
* [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p1s1c2a3.htm#104 Roman Catholic Church beliefs of the Bible]
* [http://www.sbc.net/bfm/bfm2000.asp Southern Baptist Church beliefs of the Bible]
* [http://www.elca.org/What-We-Believe/New-or-Returning-to-Church/Dig-Deeper/The-Bible.aspx Evangelical Lutheran Church in America beliefs of the Bible]
* [http://www.lcms.org/graphics/assets/media/LCMS/wa_bible1.pdf Lutheran Church - Missouri Synod beliefs of the Bible]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}
* [http://www.lcms.org/graphics/assets/media/LCMS/wa_elca-lcms.pdf The difference between the ELCA and the LCMS]{{dead link|date=June 2012}} (from the viewpoint of the LCMS)

===Supportive links===
* [http://homepage.mac.com/shanerosenthal/reformationink/bbwauthority.htm The Authority and Inspiration of the Scriptures] by [[B. B. Warfield]]
* [http://www.garyhabermas.com/articles/crj_recentperspectives/crj_recentperspectives.htm Recent Perspectives on the Reliability of the Gospels] by Gary R. Habermas
* [http://www.infidels.org/library/magazines/tsr/1992/4/4inerr92.html Why I Believe in the Inerrancy of the Scriptures] by Dave Miller (see Farrell Till below)
* [http://www.wlsessays.net/subject/I/Inerrancy Scholarly articles on Inerrancy from the Wisconsin Lutheran Seminary Library]
* [http://www.verselink.org/topics/tenreasons/tenreasons1.html Ten reasons why I believe the Bible is The Word of God] by R. A. Torrey
* [http://www.ntwrightpage.com/Wright_Bible_Authoritative.htm How Can The Bible be Authoritative?] by [[N.T. Wright]]
* [http://www.goodcatholicbooks.org/inerrancy/inerrancy-scripture.html On the Inerrancy of Scripture] by Thomas Bolin

===Critical links===
* [http://www.quodlibet.net/perry-inerrancy.shtml Dissolving the Inerrancy Debate (a postmodern view)]
* [http://www.infidels.org/library/magazines/tsr/1992/4/4evide92.html Bible Inerrancy: A Belief Without Evidence] [[Farrell Till]]'s rebuttal to Dave Miller's defense (see above)
* [http://www.newtonproject.sussex.ac.uk/prism.php?id=73 Isaac Newton's Views on the Corruption of Scripture]
* [http://www.thenazareneway.com/textual_analysis/most_notable_corruptions.htm The Two Most Notable Corruptions of Scripture, by Isaac Newton]

{{Christian theology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Biblical Inerrancy}}
[[Category:Evangelicalism]]
[[Category:Christian fundamentalism]]
[[Category:Christian theology of the Bible]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Error]]

[[ca:Inerrància bíblica]]
[[de:Fundamentalistische Exegese]]
[[es:Inerrancia bíblica]]
[[fr:Inerrance biblique]]
[[id:Ineransi Alkitab]]
[[it:Infallibilità delle Scritture]]
[[ja:聖書の無誤性]]
[[pt:Inerrância bíblica]]
[[zh:圣经无错谬]]</text>
      <sha1>dwdqfhl1sdtrkion7cmimo9p64a8q33</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
