<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Biblical Sabbath</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16975235</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522085964</id>
      <parentid>518209100</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T23:33:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sanya3</username>
        <id>4529251</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Commandments]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="67948">[[File:KorenGodReposing.jpg|thumb|right|Illustration from the first engraved Christian Bible in [[Russian (language)|Russian]] (1696), depicting [[God]] reposing on Sabbath.]]
{{For||Shabbat|Sabbath in seventh-day churches}}
'''Biblical Sabbath''' is a weekly day of [[leisure|rest]] or time of worship. It is observed differently in [[Judaism and Christianity]] and informs a similar occasion in several other faiths. Though many viewpoints and definitions have arisen over the millennia, most originate in the same textual tradition.

Sabbath in the [[Bible]] is first mentioned in the [[Genesis creation narrative]], where the seventh day is set aside as a day of rest and made holy by God. Observation and remembrance of Sabbath is one of the [[Ten Commandments]] (the fourth in the original [[Jewish]], the [[Eastern Orthodox]], and most [[Protestant]] traditions, the third in [[Roman Catholic]] and [[Lutheran]] traditions). Most people who observe Biblical Sabbath regard it as having been instituted as a &quot;perpetual [[Covenant (Biblical)|covenant]] [for] the [[Israelites|children of Israel]]&quot; ({{Bibleverse||Exodus|31:13-17|KJV}}, {{Bibleverse||Exodus|23:12|KJV}}, {{Bibleverse||Deuteronomy|5:13-14|KJV}}), a rule which also [[Proselyte#Rules for proselytes in the Torah|applies to proselytes]], and a sign in respect for the day during which God rested after having completed creation in six days ({{Bibleverse||Genesis|2:2-3}}, {{Bibleverse||Exodus|20:8-11}}). Isaiah extends the term to include even corrupted rest-day traditions ({{Bibleverse||Isaiah|1:13}}).

{{Bible related}}

==Etymology==
===Sabbath===
The Anglicized term &quot;Sabbath&quot; is in [[Hebrew]] ''Shabbath'' (שבת, now usually ''[[Shabbat]]'', [[Strong's Concordance]] number 7676). It derives from the verb of same Hebrew spelling but different pointing (''shabath'', 7673, often ''shavat''), defined as &quot;''repose'', i.e. ''desist'' from exertion&quot; (often &quot;rest&quot; or &quot;cease&quot;). (Another noun form of this root, ''shebeth'' (&quot;cessation&quot;, 7674), is identical to the infinitive (7675) of the common word &quot;to sit&quot; (''yashav'', 3427).) ''Shabbath'' is the intensified form and is used only for a weekly cessation, 107 times in the [[Tanakh]].

[[File:Shabbatai1.jpg|thumb|left|[[Sabbatai Zevi]] in 1665.]]
The name form is &quot;Shabbethai&quot; (''Shabb&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;thay'', &quot;restful&quot;, 7678), a name appearing [[List of minor Biblical figures#Shabbethai|three times]] in the [[Tanakh]], and the name of [[Sabbatai Zevi]]. The [[Talmud]] also contains a pun on ''shebeth'', where it secondarily means &quot;[[dill]]&quot;, a spice. Another related word is modern Hebrew ''shevita'', a [[labor strike]], with the same focus on active cessation of labor. And in over thirty languages other than English, the common name for [[Saturday]] is a cognate of &quot;Sabbath&quot;.

The rarely attested Babylonian ''Sapattu&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;'' or ''Sabattu&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;'' is cognate, but is said to be monthly rather than weekly, on the evidence of the reconstruction of a broken tablet; this word is regarded as a form of [[Sumer]]ian ''sa-bat'' (&quot;mid-rest&quot;), attested in [[Akkadian language|Akkadian]] as ''um nuh libbi'' (&quot;day of mid-repose&quot;). It is unclear which form of the concept is older.

The dependent Greek cognate is ''Sabbaton'' (''4521''), used in the [[New Testament]] 68 times in 62 verses. Two inflections, Hebrew ''Shabbathown'' (7677) and Greek &quot;σαββατισμός&quot; (''Sabbatismós'', ''4520''), are both translated &quot;sabbatism&quot; in Strong's (a &quot;special holiday&quot; or &quot;the ''repose'' of Christianity&quot;). The Hebrew form refers to [[High Sabbaths]]. The Greek form is cognate to the [[Septuagint]] verb ''sabbatizo'' (e.g., {{Bibleverse||Exodus|16:30}}; {{Bibleverse||Leviticus|23:32}}; {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|26:34}}; {{Bibleverse|2|Chronicles|36:21}}). In English, the concept of &quot;[[Sabbatical]]&quot; is cognate to these two forms.

The [[King James Bible]] uses the English form &quot;sabbath(s)&quot; 172 times. In the [[Old Testament]], &quot;sabbath(s)&quot; translates ''Shabbath'' all 107 times (including 35 plurals), plus ''shebeth'' three times, ''shabath'' once, and the related ''mishbath'' once (plural). In the [[New Testament]], &quot;sabbath&quot; translates ''Sabbaton'' 59 times and ''prosabbaton'' once (the day before Sabbath); ''Sabbaton'' is also translated as &quot;week&quot; nine times, by [[synecdoche]].

===Shmita===
The year of ''[[Shmita]]'' (Hebrew ''sh&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt;mittah'', שמטה, Strong's 8059), also called Sabbatical Year, is the seventh year of the seven-year agricultural cycle mandated by the [[Torah]] for the [[Land of Israel]]. During ''Shmita'', the land is left to lie fallow and all agricultural activity—including plowing, planting, pruning, and harvesting—is forbidden by Torah law. The term is translated &quot;release&quot; five times in the [[Book of Deuteronomy]] (from the root ''shamat'', &quot;''desist'', ''remit''&quot;, 8058).

==Textual tradition==
===Tanakh===
====Law====
*[[Book of Genesis]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Genesis|1:1-2:4}}, God [[Genesis creation narrative|creates]] the [[heaven]]s and earth in six days (each day is defined as evening and morning) and [[leisure|rests]] on the seventh day, which he thus confers with special status.&lt;blockquote&gt;So God blessed the seventh day and made it holy, because on it God rested from all his work that he had done in Creation. —{{Bibleverse||Genesis|2:3|ESV}}&lt;/blockquote&gt; This passage uses root form ''shabath'', rather than intensified form ''Shabbath''; neither the noun form nor a positive Sabbath command appears in Genesis. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Genesis|8:4}}, [[Noah's ark]] comes to &quot;rest&quot; in the seventh month (later revealed as the month of ''Shabbathown''); here the word for &quot;rest&quot; is not ''shabath'' but its synonym ''nuwach'', the root of [[Noah]]'s name.
*[[Book of Exodus]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Exodus|16:23-29}}, immediately after the Exodus from Egypt, Sabbath is revealed as the day upon which [[manna]] and manna gathering is to cease weekly; the first of many Sabbath commands is given, in both positive and negative forms.&lt;blockquote&gt;Six days you shall gather it, but on the seventh day, which is a Sabbath, there will be none .... Remain each of you in his place; let no one go out of his place on the seventh day. —{{Bibleverse||Exodus|16:26|ESV}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Exodus|16:29|ESV}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;In {{Bibleverse-nb||Exodus|20:8-11}}, one month later, it is enjoined to be remembered as a memorial of Creation, as one of the [[Ten Commandments]], the covenant revealed after God liberated Israel from Egyptian bondage. &lt;blockquote&gt;Remember the Sabbath day, to keep it holy. Six days you shall labor, and do all your work, but the seventh day is a Sabbath to the {{LORD}} your God. On it you shall not do any work .... For in six days the {{LORD}} made heaven and earth, the sea, and all that is in them, and rested on the seventh day. Therefore the {{LORD}} blessed the Sabbath day and made it holy. —{{Bibleverse||Exodus|20:8-11|ESV}}&lt;/blockquote&gt; In {{Bibleverse-nb||Exodus|31:12-17}}, Sabbath is affirmed as a perpetual sign and [[covenant (Biblical)|covenant]], and [[Sabbath breaking|Sabbath-breakers]] are to be [[list of capital crimes in the Torah|cut off from the assembly or killed]]. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Exodus|35:2-3}}, lighting fire on Sabbath is forbidden.
{{Ten Commandments series}}
*[[Book of Leviticus]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|16:31}}, [[Yom Kippur]] is stated to be &quot;Sabbath of Sabbaths&quot;. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|19}}, many of the Ten Commandments are repeated, including Sabbath ({{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|19:3}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|19:29-30}}). In {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|23}}, Moses defines weekly Sabbath, along with seven annual [[High Sabbaths]], which do not necessarily occur on weekly Sabbath and are additional to the weekly &quot;{{LORD}}'s Sabbaths&quot;. One High Sabbath, [[Day of Atonement]], is specifically defined as occurring from the evening of the prior day until the following evening. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|24:8}}, the [[showbread]] is to be laid out in the [[tabernacle]] every Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|25:2-6}}, ''[[Shmita]]'' is given as a year of rest for land every seven years. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|26:2}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|26:34-35}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Leviticus|26:43}}, Sabbath is again enjoined, and Moses warns of the curse that if Israel disobeys, it will go into exile while the land enjoys Sabbaths denied to it during the time of rebellion.
*[[Book of Numbers]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Numbers|15:32-36}}, a man gathering firewood on Sabbath is put to death; the potential punishment for [[Sabbath breaking|desecrating Sabbath]] (stoning) is the most severe in Jewish law. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Numbers|28-29}}, the [[korban|offerings]] for Sabbath, new moon, and High Sabbaths are enjoined.
*[[Book of Deuteronomy]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Deuteronomy|5:12-14}}, the Ten Commandments are restated; instead of referring again to Creation, Sabbath is enjoined to be observed as a memorial or sign of [[The Exodus]] and [[Redemption (theology)|Redemption]] of Israel from Egypt under God's protection.

[[File:Shofar for the Sabbath from the Matson Collection, ca. 1934-39 (LOC).jpg|thumb|right|[[Yemenite Jew]] blowing the ''[[shofar]]'' (ram's-horn trumpet) for Sabbath in the 1930s.]]

====Prophets====
*[[2 Kings]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Kings|4:23}}, when [[Elisha]]'s patroness goes away suddenly to seek him, her husband questions why, since it was neither new moon nor Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Kings|11:5-9}}, [[Jehoash of Judah|Joash]] becomes king, protected from usurper [[Athaliah]] by the additional troops present for changing of duty on Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Kings|16}}, the colonnade built for Sabbath use and its royal entranceway are removed from the temple by King [[Ahaz]].
*[[Book of Isaiah]]: [[Isaiah]] mentions Sabbath repeatedly, including in its first and last chapters. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Isaiah|1:13}}, he describes corrupted Sabbath tradition, called by God &quot;your&quot; assembly (as opposed to his own). In {{Bibleverse-nb||Isaiah|56:1-8}} and {{Bibleverse-nb||Isaiah|58:13-14}}, Isaiah commends honoring the holiness of Sabbath, rather than using it to go one's own way or to do idly as one pleases. Because of this passage, it is customary, in Judaism, to avoid talk about money or business matters on Sabbath; and, among [[Latter-day Saints]], to give full attention to spiritual matters, to perform only righteous activities, and to prepare only simple foods on Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Isaiah|66:22-23}}, he foresees what is understood as the Messianic Kingdom, in which new moons and Sabbaths are occasions for the righteous to worship in God's presence, and to meditate on the unquenched fire consuming the wicked.
*[[Book of Jeremiah]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Jeremiah|17:19-27}}, Jeremiah declaims against carrying burdens out of houses or out of the city gates on Sabbath, as was commonly done by merchants in his day. Jeremiah also prophesies that Israel will be a desolation for seventy years ({{Bibleverse-nb||Jeremiah|25:11}}), interpreted later as land Sabbaths as also prophesied by Moses.
*[[Book of Ezekiel]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Ezekiel|20:12-26}}, Ezekiel records God's giving of laws, precepts, and Sabbaths, and Israel's rejecting them; Sabbaths are explicitly called a sign between God and Israel. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Ezekiel|22:8}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ezekiel|22:23-31}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ezekiel|23:38}}, he states that Israel has profaned and hidden its eyes from Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Ezekiel|44:24}}, Ezekiel foresees a Messianic Temple, in which the priests keep Sabbath as truly holy. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Ezekiel|45:17}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ezekiel|46:1-12}}, he sees the east gate shut on the &quot;six working days&quot; and open on Sabbath and new moon, and a prince making burnt offerings on those festivals as well.
*[[Book of Hosea]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Hosea|2:11}}, casting Israel as an adulterous wife, God vows to end &quot;her&quot; festivals, new moons, and Sabbaths.
*[[Book of Amos]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Amos|8:5}}, Amos objects to those who inquire when Sabbath or new moon will be over so that marketing can begin again, classifying this practice as comparable to that of dishonest weights.

[[File:Der Samstug (Saturday).jpg|thumb|right|&quot;Der Samstug (Sabbath)&quot;, Frederich Campe, 1800: German Jews, wearing baretta hats, gather outside a synagogue on Sabbath.]]

====Writings====
*[[Book of Psalms]]: {{Bibleverse-nb||Psalm|92}} is a song specifically for Sabbath.
*[[Book of Lamentations]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Lamentations|1:7}}, Israel's enemies gloat over its &quot;cessation&quot; (''mishbath''), after the destruction of the first temple. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Lamentations|2:6}}, this destruction and Israel's rejection is linked to Israel forgetting its appointed times and Sabbaths.
*[[Book of Nehemiah]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Nehemiah|9:14}}, the Levites, who have called a public fast, thank God for Sabbath, the [[mitzvoth]] (commandments), and the Torah. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Nehemiah|10:31-33}}, the people respond by swearing not to buy on Sabbath or holy day. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Nehemiah|13:15-22}}, Nehemiah observes many kinds of business transacted on Sabbath, rejects it as profanation, locks the city gates for the whole of Sabbath and has them guarded, and threatens force against merchants who spend the night outside. Sabbath begins after evening shadows fall on the gates.
*[[1 Chronicles]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Chronicles|9:32}}, the task of preparing Sabbath showbread is shown to have been assigned to kinsmen of [[Korah]] from the clan of [[Kohath]]. In {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Chronicles|23:31}}, [[King David]] assigns Levites to stand and sing thanks and praise whenever the burnt offerings are given for Sabbath, new moon, and the other designated days.
*[[2 Chronicles]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Chronicles|2:4}} (2:3, Hebrew) and {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Chronicles|8:12-13}}, Solomon dedicates the first temple for daily, weekly, monthly, and annual offerings. In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Chronicles|23:4-8}}, [[Jehoash of Judah|Joash]] becomes king, protected from usurper [[Athaliah]] by the additional troops present for changing of duty on Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Chronicles|31:3}}, [[Hezekiah]] rededicates the same offerings as Solomon. In the last chapter of the Tanakh in Hebrew order (at {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Chronicles|36:21}}), the prophecies of Moses and Jeremiah are combined as having been fulfilled in seventy years of captivity in [[Babylon]], during which the land kept its Sabbaths.

[[File:Sabbatarian Meeting House.jpg|thumb|right|Oldest Sabbatarian Meeting House in America ([[Seventh Day Baptist]]), built in 1729 in [[Newport, Rhode Island]], now owned by [[Newport Historical Society]].]]

===New Testament===
====Gospels====
[[Gospel of Matthew|Matthew]], [[Gospel of Mark|Mark]], and [[Gospel of Luke|Luke]] contain several [[Synoptic Gospels|synoptic]] accounts, which [[Gospel of John|John]] occasionally concurs in.
*[[Exorcism in Capernaum]] ({{Bibleverse||Mk.|1:21-39}}, {{Bibleverse||Lk.|4:31-43}}): Jesus makes a practice of teaching in the [[Capernaum]] synagogue on Sabbath. One Sabbath he exorcises an [[unclean spirit]], and also heals Peter's wife's mother. After sundown that day, he heals many people, and early in the morning of the first day, he goes out to pray alone.
*[[Lord of Sabbath]] ({{Bibleverse||Mt.|12:1-8}}, {{Bibleverse||Mk.|2:23-28}}, {{Bibleverse||Lk.|6:1-5}}): When his disciples pick heads of wheat and eat them, Jesus tells objectors that, because Sabbath was made for man, the [[Son of Man]] is Lord of Sabbath. Sabbatarians believe that Sabbath-keeping is central to following Christ, and that he highly regarded Sabbath; some non-Sabbatarian Protestants and Catholics believe that Christ has power to [[Abrogation of Old Covenant laws|abrogate]] Sabbath via a &quot;better dispensation&quot;, and that he did so as with all [[ceremonial law]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.reformed.org/master/index.html?mainframe=/ethics/sabbath/sabbath_Dabney.html|chapter=The Christian Sabbath: Its Nature, Design and Proper Observance|pages=497-8|first=Robert L|last=Dabney|title=Discussions of Robert L. Dabney|volume=1|publisher=Center for Reformed Theology and Apologetics}}&lt;/ref&gt; The doctrine that Christ &quot;made&quot; all Creation ({{Bibleverse||Jn.|1:3-10}}, {{Bibleverse||Col.|1:16}}) implies that &quot;Sabbath was made&quot;, and observed, by Christ ({{Bibleverse||Mk.|2:27}}), during Creation; this is taken as earning him the identification &quot;Lord of Sabbbath&quot;.
*[[Healing of the Withered Hand]] ({{Bibleverse||Mt.|12:9-21}}, {{Bibleverse||Mk.|3:1-6}}, {{Bibleverse||Lk.|6:6-11}}): Knowing he is being watched, Jesus heals a man who had a withered hand, arguing that doing good and saving life is permitted and right on Sabbath. This passage follows his proclamation as Lord of Sabbath in Mark and Luke, but in Matthew follows his quotation of {{Bibleverse||Jer.|6:16}} that he would give rest for his disciples' souls; this is taken as indicating Matthew intended to teach that Sabbath's true or spiritual fulfillment is found in coming to Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Lincoln, Prof. Andrew T.|editor=Carson, D. A|chapter=Sabbath, rest and eschatology in the New Testament|title=From Sabbath to Lord's Day|publisher=Zondervan|date=1982|pages=197–220}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Rejection of Jesus]] ({{Bibleverse||Mk.|6:1-6}}, {{Bibleverse||Lk.|4:16-30}}): As is his custom, Jesus attends the [[Nazareth]] synagogue on Sabbath and [[Lection|stands to read]]. He preaches against skeptical demands for miracles and states that he is rejected there in his hometown.
*Events unique to [[Gospel of John|John]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||John|5:9-18}}, Jesus heals a paralytic at the [[Pool of Bethesda]] and tells him to carry his mat, spurring accusations of Sabbath-breaking. In {{Bibleverse-nb||John|7:22-23}}, Jesus argues that healing in general is equivalent to permitted Sabbath activity of [[Circumcision in the Bible|circumcision]], regarded as a cleansing ritual. In {{Bibleverse-nb||John|9}}, Jesus makes clay with spittle on Sabbath and heals a man born blind, and is investigated by [[Pharisees]].
*Events unique to [[Gospel of Luke|Luke]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Luke|13:10-17}}, Jesus heals a woman who had been bent over double for 18 years, arguing that setting her free is equivalent to permitted Sabbath activity of loosing one's animals to water them. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Luke|14:1-6}}, Jesus heals a man with [[dropsy]] (swollen with fluid), arguing that this is equivalent to permitted Sabbath activity of rescuing an animal from a well. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Luke|18:9-14}}, Jesus' parable of the [[Pharisee and the Publican]], the [[Pharisee]] fasts twice a week, literally twice per Sabbath (the word ''Sabbaton'' means &quot;week&quot; by [[synecdoche]]).
*[[Olivet Discourse]], unique to [[Gospel of Matthew|Matthew]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Matthew|24}}, describing then-future [[apocalypse]]s such as the [[Second Coming]], Jesus requests prayer (at {{Bibleverse-nb||Matthew|24:20}}) that the coming time, when Judah must escape to the hills, not occur in winter or on Sabbath. Sabbatarians believe that Jesus based on this text expected Sabbath to be kept long after his death;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|quote=After the Christian dispensation was fully set up .... even then Christians were bound to a strict observation of the sabbath.|first=Jonathan|last=Edwards|authorlink=Jonathan Edwards (theologian)|title=First Sermon: The Perpetuity of the Sabbath|url=http://www.westminsterconfession.org/worship/perpetuity-and-change-of-the-sabbath.php}}&lt;/ref&gt; others believe Jesus foresaw a non-Sabbatarian future community hampered by surrounding Sabbatarianism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.worldslastchance.com/biblical-christian-beliefs/sabbath-in-the-bible.html|title=Sabbath in the Bible|chapter=The Sabbath and the Gospels|publisher=World's Last Chance|year=2004-2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Crucifixion of Jesus]] ({{Bibleverse||Mt.|27}}, {{Bibleverse||Mk.|15}}, {{Bibleverse||Lk.|23}}, {{Bibleverse||Jn.|19}}): Jesus is crucified on Preparation Day, the day before Sabbath; differing [[chronology of Jesus|chronologies]] interpret this either as [[Good Friday|Friday]] (before weekly Sabbath) or [[Quartodeciman|Nisan 14]] (before High Sabbath) or both. [[Joseph of Arimathaea]] buries him before this Sabbath begins. The women who wished to prepare his body keep Sabbath rest according to the commandment, intending to finish their work on the first day of the week (the day after weekly Sabbath); one reading of the text permits &quot;they rested&quot; to include a hint that the body of Jesus rests on Sabbath as well. Seventh-day Sabbatarians see no change in God's law, regarding it as in force and affirmed by the evangelists after Jesus died on the cross.&lt;ref name=wohlberg/&gt; Others regard Sabbath as changed by the cross, either to Lord's Day or to spiritual Sabbath.
*[[Resurrection of Jesus]] ({{Bibleverse||Mt.|28}}, {{Bibleverse||Mk.|16}}, {{Bibleverse||Lk.|24}}, {{Bibleverse||Jn.|20}}): Jesus is raised from the dead by God and appears publicly on the first day of the week to several women. Jesus appears to Peter and again on the evening beginning the second day (i.e., after two disciples traveled seven miles from [[Emmaus]], having begun when it was almost evening and getting dark, {{Bibleverse||Lk.|24:28-36}}). The text stating that &quot;Jesus rose early on the first day of the week&quot; ({{Bibleverse||Mk.|16:9|NIV}}) is often inferred as speaking indirectly of Sabbath change; this conclusion is not direct in any Scripture, and the verse is not found in the two most ancient manuscripts (the [[Sinaiticus]] and [[Codex Vaticanus Graecus 1209|Vaticanus]]) and some other ancient manuscripts, though it appears in [[Irenaeus]] and [[Hippolytus of Rome|Hippolytus]] in the second or third century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Oxford NIV Scofield Study Bible|others=[[Cyrus Scofield|Scofield, C.I.]], ed.; English, E. Schuyler, chmn|year=1984|location=[[New York City]]|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|origyear=1909|page=1047|chapter=Mark 16:9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ten Commandments Monument.jpg|thumb|right|A [[Judeo-Christian]] [[Ten Commandments]] monument on the grounds of the [[Texas State Capitol]].]]

====Epistles====
*[[Book of Acts]] 1-18: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Acts|1:12}}, the distance from the [[Mount of Olives]] to [[Jerusalem]] is called &quot;Sabbath journey&quot;, the distance permitted to be walked on Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Acts|2}}, the [[Holy Spirit|Spirit of God]] is given to the disciples of Christ on [[Pentecost]], who baptize 3,000 people into the apostolic fellowship; though the weekday is not mentioned, this is usually calculated as falling on the day after Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Acts|13:13-45}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Acts|16:13}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Acts|17:2}}, and {{Bibleverse-nb||Acts|18:4}}, as is his custom, Paul preaches on Sabbath to communal gatherings of Jewish and Gentile Christians, usually in synagogue, in [[Pisidian Antioch]], [[Philippi]], [[Thessalonica]], and [[Corinth]] (the meeting of Philippians was a riverside women's prayer group, in Gentile territory). Seventh-day Sabbatarians believe that Luke's recording Paul's sitting down in the synagogue indicates they kept a rest day and affirmed the seventh day as Sabbath,&lt;ref name=wohlberg/&gt; while others believe that Paul merely preached on days that the Jewish portion of his audience would be available. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Acts|15:19-29}}, the [[Apostolic Decree]], James proposes four limited rules for Gentile [[proselytes]] in response to the question of whether Gentiles should be directed to follow the Mosaic Law; the apostles then write that no greater burden is laid on the Gentiles. James also states that Moses is read every Sabbath, which can be construed either as discounting Moses as too unnecessary to promote (the Law being split into parts with Gentiles ordered to follow only [[Noachide Laws]]), or as supporting Moses as too ubiquitous to promote (the Law being a unity to grow into).
*{{Bibleverse||Acts|20}}: When the Christians meet to break bread, during an all-night worship service in [[Troad|Troas]], Paul preaches and raises Eutychus from the dead, the night after Sabbath (i.e., Saturday night and Sunday morning); the first day had begun at sundown (cf. {{Bibleverse||Judges|14:17-18}}). Though Paul's special farewell service, this event is otherwise considered a regular Christian [[Eucharist]]ic observance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=The Catholic Encyclopedia|title=Sunday|date=1913|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14335a.htm|quote=The practice of meeting together on the first day of the week for the celebration of the Eucharistic Sacrifice is indicated.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Hard Nuts Cracked|author=Richards, H.M.S|page=6|url=http://www.sabbathtruth.com/faq/arguments-refuted/articletype/articleview/articleid/1026/if-the-early-christians-kept-sabbath-.aspx|quote=After all there is nothing in the Scriptures to show that the celebration of the Lord's Supper was confined to any particular day of the week.}} Cf. {{Bibleverse||Acts|2:46}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Paul then immediately walks eighteen miles from Troas to [[Assos]], boards a boat, and continues to [[Mitylene]]. Seventh-day Sabbatarians state that Paul (as a lifelong Sabbath keeper) would not have done so on Sunday, if he had regarded Sunday as Sabbath. Non-Sabbatarians state that Paul did not keep any day of the week as Sabbath (citing his later passages) and that the early church met on the first day of the week but without rigor. First-day Sabbatarians state that he did not extend the travel prohibition to the first day.
*[[Book of Romans]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Romans|14:5-6}}, without mentioning Sabbath, Paul emphasizes being fully convinced of one's practice, whether esteeming one day above another, or esteeming every day alike. Each interpretative framework regards this passage as demonstrating that ritual observance of others' Sabbaths is not required, but is optional according to the conscience of each individual Christian.
*[[1 Corinthians]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Corinthians|7:1}}, Paul exhorts readers to follow his example in religious practice as he follows Christ's. In {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Corinthians|16:1-2}}, Paul encourages the setting aside of money on the day after Sabbath for a collection for the Christians in Jerusalem; it is not stated whether this is in conjunction with a first-day group meeting. As in {{Bibleverse||Acts|20}}, the word &quot;week&quot; translates ''Sabbaton'' in &quot;the first day of the week&quot;.
*[[Epistle to the Galatians|Galatians]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Galatians|4:10-11}}, spiritual enslavement to special days, months, seasons, and years is rejected. In context, Paul speaks of enslavement to &quot;the elemental things of the world&quot; and &quot;those weak and miserable principles&quot; ({{Bibleverse-nb||Galatians|4:3}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Galatians|4:9}}), and allegorizes the Israelites as &quot;children who are to be slaves&quot; ({{Bibleverse-nb||Galatians|4:24}}). The theme of {{Bibleverse-nb||Galatians|5}} is freedom. Seventh-day Sabbatarians believe Paul was promoting freedom in Sabbath observance and rejecting either observance of non-Levitical [[Gnostic]] practices, or else [[legalism (theology)|legalistic]] observance of Biblical festivals (cf. {{Bibleverse||Colossians|2:9-17}});&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Jewish New Testament Commentary|author=Stern, David H.|date=1992|publisher=Jewish New Testament Publications, Inc|location=[[Clarksville, Maryland]]|isbn=965-359-008-1|page=557|chapter=Notes on Gal. 4:8-10|quote=When Gentiles observe these Jewish holidays ... out of fear induced by Judaizers who have convinced them that unless they do these things, God will not accept them, then they are not obeying the ''Torah'' but subjugating themselves to legalism .... An alternative interpretation, however, is that the 'days, months, seasons and years' of this passage do not refer to the Jewish holidays at all but to pagan Gentile feasts, naturally and directly reflecting 'those weak and miserable elemental spirits.' According to this understanding Sha'ul was worried that his ex-pagan converts might be returning to these pagan festivals.}}&lt;/ref&gt; others believe Paul spoke about Judaizers and was rejecting seventh-day Sabbath as not prescribed in the New Covenant, represented by [[Mount Zion]] above and by freedom.
*[[Colossians]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Colossians|2:9-17}}, the rule is laid down that no one should pass judgment on anyone else in regard to High Sabbaths, new moon, and Sabbath. Paul states that these yet remain as a shadow of Messianic events that are still coming as of his writing. The withholding of judgment has been interpreted variously as indicating either maintenance, transference, or abolition of Sabbath. First-day Sabbatarians and non-Sabbatarians often regard the Mosaic law as being the &quot;record of debt&quot; (ESV) nailed to the cross. Some seventh-day Sabbatarians regard only High Sabbaths as abolished due to their foreshadowing the cross, holding it impossible for weekly Sabbath (which preceded sin) to foreshadow deliverance from sin in the cross.&lt;ref name=lostday6&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.sabbathtruth.com/faq/advanced-topics/the-lost-day-of-history.aspx|title=The Lost Day Of History|chapter=6. Doesn't Colossians 2:14-17 do away with the seventh-day Sabbath?|publisher=Amazing Facts|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others regard Sabbath, new moon, and High Sabbaths not as nailed to the cross but as foreshadowing the eternal plan of God.&lt;ref name=howard&gt;{{cite book|last=Howard|first=Kevin|title=The Feasts of the Lord|year=1997|publisher=Zion's Hope|isbn=0-7852-7518-5, 9780785275183|pages=224|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YTCsOwAACAAJ&amp;dq=the+feasts+of+the+lord&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=thPjTseeM8TetgePvqHoAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CEoQ6AEwAA}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Book of Hebrews]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Hebrews|4:1-11}}, Sabbath texts are analyzed with the conclusion that some form of Sabbath-keeping (''sabbatismos'') remains for God's people; the term generically means any literal or spiritual Sabbath-keeping.
*[[Revelation]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Revelation|1:10}}, [[John the Beloved]] states that he was &quot;in Spirit&quot; in the &quot;[[Lord's Day]]&quot;, a term apparently familiar to his readers, without mentioning Sabbath. First-day Sabbatarians hold that this means he was worshipping on [[Sunday]], the day of Christ's resurrection (cf. {{Bibleverse||Acts|20:7}}, {{Bibleverse|1|Corinthians|16:2}}, later [[patristic]] writings). Seventh-day Sabbatarians hold that this means he was brought by the Spirit into a vision of the [[Day of the Lord]] (cf. {{Bibleverse||Isaiah|58:13-14}}, etc.). Both lay claim to the name &quot;Lord's Day&quot; for Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Revelation|20:1-10}}, the millennial reign of Christ is described, which is often interpreted as a seventh (Sabbatical) [[millennium]].

===Apocrypha===
*[[1 Esdras]]: {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Esdras|1:58}} quotes {{Bibleverse|2|Chronicles|36:21}}, relying on the prophecies of {{Bibleverse||Jeremiah|25}} and of {{Bibleverse||Leviticus|26}}. In {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Esdras|5:52}}, [[Joshua the High Priest]] and [[Zerubbabel]] lead the rededication of the altar for Sabbath, new moon, and (annual) holy feasts.
*[[1 Maccabees]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Maccabees|1:39-45}}, under [[Antiochus IV Epiphanes]], Jerusalem's Sabbaths become a reproach and profanation. In {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Maccabees|2:32-41}}, he wars against the [[Maccabees]] and followers on Sabbath, one thousand of whom are killed after refusing to come out; [[Mattathias]] and his friends decree they will battle on Sabbath in [[self-defense]]. In 9:34-49, [[Bacchides (general)|Bacchides]] prepares to attack on Sabbath but is defeated by [[Jonathan Maccabeus]]. In 10:34, [[Demetrius I Soter]] declares that Jews will be free to celebrate feasts, Sabbaths, new moons, and solemn days, but is not received.
*[[2 Maccabees]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Maccabees|5:25-26}}, a [[Mysian]] captain named Apollonius attacks all those celebrating Sabbath. In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Maccabees|6:6-11}}, Antiochus criminalizes Sabbath and ancient fasts, and those keeping Sabbath secretly in caves are burned to death. In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Maccabees|8:26-28}}, after defeating [[Nicanor (Seleucid general)|Nicanor]]'s army, the men of [[Judas Maccabeus]] leave off pursuit on Preparation Day, instead gathering spoil, occupying themselves about Sabbath, and praising and thanking God; after Sabbath they distribute the spoil to the maimed, widows, and orphans, and then themselves and their servants. In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Maccabees|12:38-39}}, Judas's men reach [[Adullam]] and purify themselves when the seventh day comes, according to custom, and keep Sabbath there, burying those dead in battle on the day after, according to custom (i.e., the first day). In {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Maccabees|15:1-4}}, Nicanor resolves to attack Judas in [[Samaria]] on Sabbath but is entreated to forbear by the Jews accompanying him, who argue that the living Lord commanded the seventh day to be kept in holiness.
*[[Judith]]: In {{Bibleverse-nb||Judith|8:6}}, Judith fasts and lives in a tent for three years and four months, except for Sabbath eve, Sabbath, new moon eve, new moon, and feasts and solemn days. In {{Bibleverse-nb||Judith|10:2}}, it is repeated that she only dwelt in her house for Sabbath and feast days.
*[[Infancy Gospel of Thomas]] 2.1-5: The five-year-old Jesus forms twelve sparrows out of clay on Sabbath, which then fly away, chirping; he also gathers together flowing water into pure pools by his word at the same time, and pronounces an efficaceous curse on the child who disperses the pools. Jews object to Joseph about these things.
*[[Gospel of Thomas]] 27: Jesus warns, &quot;Fast as regards the world ... Observe the Sabbath as a Sabbath.&quot;
*[[Gospel of Peter]] 2.5, 7.27: Herod commends the swift burial of Jesus because it is the day before Sabbath and the [[Feast of Unleavened Bread]]. That day, after the ninth hour (3:00 p.m.), the disciples mourn and weep &quot;night and day until the Sabbath&quot; (sunset or 6:00 p.m.; the idiom &quot;night and day&quot; can import a portion of a day).
*[[Gospel of Nicodemus]] (Acts of Pilate) 1.1, 2.6, 4.2, 6.1, 12.1-2, 15.6, 16.1-2: Annas, Caiaphas, and others accuse Jesus of polluting Sabbath and wanting to [[Antinomianism|destroy Torah]], because he healed on Sabbath. Joseph of Arimathea is arrested and sealed up in a room on the day of Jesus' death, the day before Sabbath; he is ordered by a council to be dishonored on the day after Sabbath, but is not found when the door is opened. Joseph later testifies (on the day before another Sabbath) that he had remained locked up all Sabbath but, on midnight the day after, beheld a lightning flash and was led outside by the risen Jesus.
*[[Acts of Paul]], in the latter half of the second century: Paul prays &quot;on the Sabbath as the Lord's Day [''kyriake''] drew near.&quot;

==Frameworks==
[[File:ShabbatableS.jpg|160px|thumb|left|Table set for ''Shabbat'' eve.]]
Three primary interpretative frameworks exist, with many subcategories. Interpretation is complicated by the differing meanings attributed to unambiguous seventh-day Sabbath prior to the [[resurrection of Jesus]]; the ambiguity of events after the resurrection, including first-day and seventh-day events ({{Bibleverse||Ac.|20:7}}, {{Bibleverse|1|Cor.|16:2}}, perhaps {{Bibleverse||Rev.|1:10}}; {{Bibleverse||Ac.|1:12}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|13:13-45}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|15:19-29}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|16:13}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|17:2}}, and {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|18:4}}); and several early Christian observances being attested as daily or on nonspecific days ({{Bibleverse||Mk.|2:1-2}}, {{Bibleverse||Lk.|19:47-20:1}}, {{Bibleverse||Ac.|2:42-47}}). Early Christians also observed Jewish practices as a sect of Judaism ({{Bibleverse||Ac.|3:1}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|5:27-42}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|21:18-26}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|24:5}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|24:14}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|28:22}}), and observed Tanakh feasts (Passover, {{Bibleverse||Ac.|12:3-4}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|20:6}}, {{Bibleverse|1|Cor.|5:7-8}}, {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Cor.|15:20}}, {{Bibleverse||Jude|12}}; Pentecost, {{Bibleverse||Ac.|2:1}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|18:21}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|20:16}}, {{Bibleverse|1|Cor.|16:8}}; Atonement, {{Bibleverse||Ac.|27:9}}). Interpreters of each framework consider the high regard for the [[New Covenant]] described in {{Bibleverse||Jer.|31:31}} (cf. {{Bibleverse||Heb.|8:1-13}}) as supporting their Sabbath positions.

===Seventh day===
{{Main|Shabbat|Sabbath in seventh-day churches}}
[[File:Havdal.jpg|right|thumb|Observing the Sabbath-closing ''[[havdalah]]'' ritual in 14th-century Spain.]]
[[Seventh-day Sabbatarians]] rest on the seventh Hebrew day. Jewish ''[[Shabbat]]'' is observed from sundown on [[Friday]] until the appearance of three stars in the sky on [[Saturday]] night; it is also observed by a minority of Christians. [[Activities prohibited on Shabbat|Thirty-nine activities prohibited on ''Shabbat'']] are listed in Tractate ''[[Shabbat (Talmud)|Shabbat]]'' ([[Talmud]]). Customarily, ''Shabbat'' is ushered in by lighting [[candle]]s shortly before sunset, at [[halakhic]]ally calculated times that change from week to week and from place to place. ''Shabbat'' ends approximately one hour after sunset by rabbinical ordinance to extend the Tanakh's sunset-to-sunset Sabbath into the first day of the week. The Jewish interpretation usually states that the New Covenant ({{Bibleverse||Jer.|31:31}}) refers to the future Messianic Kingdom.

Several Christian denominations (such as [[Seventh Day Baptist]], [[Seventh-day Adventist]], [[Sabbath Rest Advent Church]], [[Church of God (Seventh Day)]], and other [[Church of God (disambiguation)|Churches of God]]) observe Sabbath similarly to or less rigorously than Judaism, but observance ends at Saturday sunset instead of Saturday nightfall. Like the Jews with ''Shabbat'', they believe that keeping [[seventh-day Sabbath]] is a moral responsibility, equal to that of any of the [[Ten Commandments]], that honors God as Creator and Deliverer. The Christian seventh-day interpretation usually states that Sabbath belongs inherently to all nations ({{Bibleverse||Ex.|20:10}}, {{Bibleverse||Is.|56:6-7}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Is.|66:22-23}}) and remains part of the New Covenant after the [[crucifixion of Jesus]] ({{Bibleverse||Lk.|23:56}}, {{Bibleverse||Mt.|24:20}}, {{Bibleverse||Ac.|16:13}}, {{Bibleverse||Heb.|8:10}}).&lt;ref name=wohlberg&gt;{{cite web|title=Sabbath Basics|author=Wohlberg, Steve|url=http://www.whitehorsemedia.com/articles/?d=81}} {{Cite book|title=Truth Left Behind|chapter=Ten Reasons why the Sabbath is ''not Jewish''|url=http://www.whitehorsemedia.com/articles/?d=85}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.sabbathtruth.com/faq/advanced-topics/the-lost-day-of-history.aspx|title=The Lost Day Of History|chapter=8. But wasn't the Sabbath changed to Sunday at Christ's death or resurrection?|publisher=Amazing Facts|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many seventh-day Sabbatarians also use &quot;[[Lord's Day]]&quot; to mean the seventh day, based on Scriptures in which God calls the day &quot;my Sabbath&quot; ({{Bibleverse||Ex.|31:13|NIV}}) and &quot;to the {{LORD}}&quot; ({{Bibleverse-nb||Ex.|16:23|NIV}}); some count Sunday separately as Lord's Day and many consider it appropriate for communal worship (but not for first-day rest, which would be considered breaking the Ten Commandments&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Anti-Sabbath Arguments: Are They Really Right?|author=Wohlberg, Steve|url=http://www.whitehorsemedia.com/articles/?d=81|work=Truth Left Behind}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

In this way, [[Ignatius of Antioch|St. Ignatius]] saw believers &quot;no longer observing the [Jewish] Sabbath, but living in the observance of the Lord's Day&quot;, and amplified this point as follows: &quot;Let us therefore no longer keep the Sabbath after the Jewish manner, and rejoice in days of idleness .... But let every one of you keep the Sabbath after a spiritual manner, rejoicing in meditation on the law, not in relaxation of the body, admiring the workmanship of God, and not eating things prepared the day before, nor using lukewarm drinks, and walking within a prescribed space, nor finding delight in dancing and plaudits which have no sense in them. And after the observance of the Sabbath, let every friend of Christ keep the Lord's Day as a festival, the resurrection-day, the queen and chief of all the days.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=[[Ignatius of Antioch|St. Ignatius]]|title=Epistle to the Magnesians|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.v.iii.ix.html|volume=9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Seventh-day Adventist]] official 28 fundamental beliefs (at 20) state:&lt;blockquote&gt;The beneficent Creator, after the six days of Creation, rested on the seventh day and instituted the Sabbath for all people as a memorial of Creation. The fourth commandment of God's unchangeable law requires the observance of this seventh-day Sabbath as the day of rest, worship, and ministry in harmony with the teaching and practice of Jesus, the Lord of the Sabbath. The Sabbath is a day of delightful communion with God and one another. It is a symbol of our redemption in Christ, a sign of our sanctification, a token of our allegiance, and a foretaste of our eternal future in God's kingdom. The Sabbath is God's perpetual sign of His eternal covenant between Him and His people. Joyful observance of this holy time from evening to evening, sunset to sunset, is a celebration of God's creative and redemptive acts. (Gen. 2:1-3; Ex. 20:8-11; Luke 4:16; Isa. 56:5, 6; 58:13, 14; Matt. 12:1-12; Ex. 31:13-17; Eze. 20:12, 20; Deut. 5:12-15; Heb. 4:1-11; Lev. 23:32; Mark 1:32.)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.adventist.org/beliefs/fundamental/index.html|title=Fundamental Beliefs|volume=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Doctrinal Points of the [[Church of God (7th day)]] (Salem Conference, at 17) state:&lt;blockquote&gt;We should observe the seventh day of the week (Saturday), from even to even, as the Sabbath of the Lord our God. Evening is at sunset when day ends and another day begins. No other day has ever been sanctified as the day of rest. The Sabbath Day begins at sundown on Friday and ends at sundown on Saturday. Genesis 2:1-3; Exodus 20:8-11; Isaiah 58:13-14; 56:1-8; Acts 17:2; Acts 18:4, 11; Luke 4:16; Mark 2:27-28; Matthew 12:10-12; Hebrews 4:1-11; Genesis 1:5, 13-14; Nehemiah 13:19.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.churchofgod-7thday.org/Publications/Doctrinal%20Points%20Final%20Proof.pdf|title=Doctrinal Points of the Church of God (7th Day)|location=[[Salem, West Virginia]]|page=18|publisher=The Church of God Publishing House}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Both Jewish and Christian seventh-day interpretation usually state that Jesus' teachings relate to the Pharisaic position on Sabbath observance, and that Jesus kept seventh-day Sabbath throughout his life on earth.

====Sunday law====
{{Main|Seventh-day Adventist eschatology}}
Noticing the rise of [[blue law]]s, the [[Seventh-day Adventist]] church in particular has traditionally taught that in the [[end time]] a coalition of religious and secular authorities will enforce an international Sunday law; church pioneers saw observance of [[seventh-day Sabbath]] as a &quot;mark&quot; or &quot;seal&quot; or test of God's people that seals them, even as those who do not observe Sunday rest will be persecuted and killed. [[Ellen G. White]] interpreted {{Bibleverse||Dan.|7:25}}, {{Bibleverse||Rev.|13:15}}, {{Bibleverse||Rev.|7}}, {{Bibleverse||Ezek.|20:12-20}}, and {{Bibleverse||Ex.|31:13}} in this way, describing the subject of persecution in prophecy as being about Sabbath commandments.

===First day===
{{Main|Sabbath in Christianity}}
[[First-day Sabbatarians]] worship communally on the first (Hebrew or Roman) day. In most Christian denominations ([[Roman Catholic]], some [[Eastern Orthodox]], and most [[Protestant]]), &quot;[[Sabbath in Christianity|Sabbath]]&quot; is a synonym of &quot;[[Lord's Day]]&quot; ([[Sunday]]), which is kept in commemoration of the [[resurrection of Christ]], and often celebrated with the [[Eucharist]] (Catholic Catechism 2177).&lt;ref name=ccc/&gt; It is often also the day of [[leisure|rest]]. Lord's Day is considered both the first day and the [[The eighth day (Christian)|&quot;eighth day&quot;]] of the [[seven-day week]], symbolizing both first creation and new creation (2174).&lt;ref name=ccc&gt;{{Cite book|title=Catechism of the Catholic Church|edition=2d|publisher=[[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]]|location=[[New York City]]|year=1997|author=United States Catholic Conference, Inc.|chapter=You Shall Love the Lord Your God with All Your Heart, and with All Your Soul, and with All Your Mind, Article 3, The Third Commandment (2168-2195)|pages=580–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Alternatively, in some calendars, Sunday is designated the seventh day of the week.) Relatively few Christians regard first-day observance as entailing all of the ordinances of ''Shabbat''. This interpretation usually states that the Holy Spirit through the Apostles instituted the worship celebration of the first day to commemorate Jesus' resurrection, and that the New Covenant transfers Sabbath-keeping (whether defined as rest or communal worship or both) to the first day by implication.&lt;ref&gt;James Cardinal Gibbons, The Faith of Our Fathers (1917 edition), p. 72-73 (16th Edition, p. 111; 88th Edition, p. 89). &quot;You may read the Bible from Genesis to Revelation, and you will not find a single line authorizing the sanctification of Sunday. The Scriptures enforce the religious observance of Saturday, a day which we never sanctify.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In Roman Catholicism, the transfer is described as based on their church's authority and [[papal infallibility]].&lt;ref&gt;Catholic Virginian, October 3, 1947, p. 9, article &quot;To Tell You the Truth.&quot; &quot;For example, nowhere in the Bible do we find that Christ or the Apostles ordered that the Sabbath be changed from Saturday to Sunday. We have the commandment of God given to Moses to keep holy the Sabbath day, that is the 7th day of the week, Saturday. Today most Christians keep Sunday because it has been revealed to us by the [Roman Catholic] church outside the Bible.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Roman Catholics (and many Protestants) view the first day as a day for assembly for worship (2178, {{Bibleverse||Heb.|10:25}}),&lt;ref name=ccc/&gt; but consider a day of rigorous rest not obligatory on Christians ({{Bibleverse||Rom.|14:5}}, {{Bibleverse||Col.|2:16}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sabbath|work=The Catholic Encyclopedia|date=1913|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13287b.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Catholics count the prohibition of servile work as transferred from seventh-day Sabbath to Sunday (2175-6),&lt;ref name=ccc/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ten Commandments|work=The Catholic Encyclopedia|date=1913|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13287a.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; but do not hinder participation in &quot;ordinary and innocent occupations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sabbatarians|work=The Catholic Encyclopedia|date=1913|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13287a.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, second-century father [[Justin Martyr]] believed in keeping perpetual Sabbath by repentance,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=[[Justin Martyr]]|title=Dialogue with Trypho|volume=12|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.viii.iv.xii.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; holding that Gentile Christians need not rest as Jews were commanded;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=[[Justin Martyr]]|title=Dialogue with Trypho|volume=23|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.viii.iv.xxiii.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; but he accepted extant non-Judaizing seventh-day Sabbatarian Christians &quot;in all things as kinsmen and brethren&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=[[Justin Martyr]]|title=Dialogue with Trypho|volume=47|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.viii.iv.xlvii.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In other Protestant denominations, Lord's Day is kept as a rest day with similar rigor as [[Jewish Sabbath]]. The [[Westminster Confession of Faith]] 21:7-8, a [[Reformed]] Sabbatarian creed, states:&lt;blockquote&gt;As it is the law of nature, that, in general, a due proportion of time be set apart for the worship of God; so, in His Word, by a positive, moral, and perpetual commandment binding all men in all ages, He has particularly appointed one day in seven, for a Sabbath, to be kept holy unto him (Ex. 20:8, 20:10-11, Is. 56:2, 56:4, 56:6-7): which, from the beginning of the world to the resurrection of Christ, was the last day of the week: and, from the resurrection of Christ, was changed into the first day of the week (Ge. 2:2-3, 1 Cor. 16:1-2, Ac. 20:7), which, in Scripture, is called the Lord's Day (Rev. 1:10), and is to be continued to the end of the world, as the Christian Sabbath (Ex. 20:8, 20:10, Mt. 5:17). This Sabbath is to be kept holy unto the Lord when men, after a due preparing of their hearts, and ordering of their common affairs beforehand, do not only observe an holy rest all the day from their own works, words, and thoughts about their worldly employments and recreations (Ex. 20:8, 16:23, 16:25-26, 16:29-30, 31:15-17, Is. 58:13, Neh. 13:15-19, 13:21-22), but also are taken up the whole time in the public and private exercises of His worship, and in the duties of necessity and mercy (Is. 58:13).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.reformed.org/documents/wcf_with_proofs/|title=Westminster Confession of Faith|volume=21.7-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Assemblies====
{{main|Lord's Day}}
The following textual evidence for first-day assembly is usually combined with the notion that the rest day should follow the assembly day to support first-day Sabbatarianism. On the first day of the week (usually considered the day of [[First Fruits#Biblical|Firstfruits]]), after Jesus has been raised from the dead ({{Bibleverse||Mk.|16:9|NIV}}), he appears to [[Mary Magdalene]], [[Saint Peter|Peter]], [[Cleopas]], and others. &quot;On the evening of that first day of the week&quot; (Roman time), or the evening beginning the second day (Hebrew time), the resurrected Jesus appears at a meeting of ten apostles and other disciples ({{Bibleverse||Jn.|20:19|NIV}}). The same time of the week &quot;a week later&quot; (NIV) or, more literally, &quot;after eight days again&quot; inclusive (KJV), Jesus appears to the eleven apostles and others ({{Bibleverse||Jn.|20:26}}). After Jesus ascends ({{Bibleverse||Ac.|1:9}}), on the feast of [[Pentecost]] or [[Shavuot]] (the 50th day from Firstfruits and thus usually calculated as the first day of the week), the Spirit of God is given to the disciples, who baptize 3,000 people into the apostolic fellowship. Later, on one occasion in [[Troad|Troas]], the early Christians meet on the first day (Hebrew) to break bread and to listen to Christian preaching ({{Bibleverse||Ac.|20:7}}). Paul also states that the churches of [[Corinth]] and [[Galatia]] should set aside donations on the first day for collection ({{Bibleverse|1|Cor.|16:2}}). [[Didache]] 14:1 (AD 70-120?) contains an ambiguous text, translated by Roberts as, &quot;But every Lord's day gather yourselves together, and break bread, and give thanksgiving&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=[[Didache]]|chapter=14:1|url=http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/didache-roberts.html|publisher=Early Christian Writings|others=Roberts, trans}}&lt;/ref&gt; the first clause in Greek, &quot;[[wikt:κατά|κατά]] {{lang|grc|[[wikt:κυριακήν|κυριακήν]]}} [[wikt:δέ|δέ]] [[wikt:κύριος|κυρίου]]&quot;, literally means &quot;On the Lord's of the Lord&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Holmes, M|title=The Apostolic Fathers: Greek Texts and English Translations}}&lt;/ref&gt; and translators supply the elided noun (e.g., &quot;day&quot;, &quot;commandment&quot; (from 13:7), or &quot;doctrine&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Strand, Kenneth A.|title=The Sabbath in Scripture and History|pages=347–8|location=[[Washington, D.C.]]|publisher=Review and Herald Publishing Association|date=1982}} In {{Cite book|author=Morgan, Kevin|title=Sabbath Rest|pages=37–8|year=2002|publisher=TEACH Services, Inc}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gleason Archer regards this as one of only two extrabiblical Christian uses of &quot;κυριακήν&quot; where it does not clearly refer to Sunday.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Archer, Gleason|title=An Encyclopedia of Bible Difficulties|authorlink=Gleason Archer}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=October 2010}} Breaking bread may refer to [[communion (Christian)|Christian fellowship]], [[agape feast]]s, or [[Eucharist]] (cf. {{Bibleverse||Ac.|2:42}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|20:7}}). Other interpreters believe these references do not support the concept of transfer of the seventh-day rest, and some add that they do not sufficiently prove that Sunday observance was an established practice in the primitive New Testament church.

By the second century, [[Justin Martyr]] stated, &quot;We all gather on the day of the sun&quot; (recalling both the creation of light and the resurrection);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=[[Justin Martyr]]|title=First Apology|volume=67}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Epistle of Barnabas]] on {{Bibleverse||Is.|1:13}} stated the eighth-day assembly marks the resurrection and the new creation: &quot;He is saying there: 'It is not these sabbaths of the present age that I find acceptable, but the one of my own appointment: the one that, after I have set all things at rest, is to usher in the Eighth Day, the commencement of a new world.' (And we too rejoice in celebrating the Eighth Day; because that was when Jesus rose from the dead, and showed Himself again, and ascended into heaven.)&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|others=Staniforth, Maxwell, trans|title=[[Epistle of Barnabas]]|volume=15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Unspecified day===
{{Main|Non-Sabbatarianism}}
[[Non-Sabbatarian]]s affirm human liberty not to observe a weekly rest or worship day. While keepers of weekly days usually believe in religious liberty,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Shabbat|author=Berkowitz, Richard &amp; Michele|publisher=Lederer Publications|location=[[Baltimore]]|date=1991|isbn=1-880226-00-6|pages=11–2|quote=We have a remembrance–a physical Sabbath day–to remind us anew of our spiritual freedom in him .... Observance paints a sacred picture of what it is like to be united in faith with Messiah Yeshua. One other reason to observe Shabbat is ''God has a blessing for us.''}}&lt;/ref&gt; non-Sabbatarians are particularly free to uphold Sabbath principles, or not, without limiting observance to either Saturday or Sunday. Some advocate Sabbath rest on any chosen day of the week, and some advocate Sabbath as a symbolic metaphor for rest in Christ; the concept of &quot;Lord's Day&quot; is usually treated as synonymous with &quot;Sabbath&quot;. The non-Sabbatarian interpretation usually states that Jesus' obedience and the New Covenant fulfilled the laws of Sabbath, which are thus often considered abolished or abrogated.

Some of Jesus' teachings are considered as redefining the Sabbath laws of the Pharisees ({{Bibleverse||Lk.|13:10-17}}, {{Bibleverse||Jn.|5:16-18}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Jn.|9:13-16}}). Since Jesus is understood to have fulfilled [[Torah]] ({{Bibleverse||Mk.|2:28}}, {{Bibleverse||Mt.|5:17}}), non-Sabbatarian Christians believe that they are not bound by Sabbath as [[legalism (theology)|legalists]] consider themselves to be. Non-Sabbatarians can thus exhibit either [[Christian liberty]] or [[antinomianism]]. On principles of religious liberty, non-Sabbatarian Jews similarly affirm their freedom not to observe ''Shabbat'' as [[Orthodox Jew]]s do.

Non-Sabbatarian Christians also cite {{Bibleverse|2|Cor.|3:2-3}}, in which believers are compared to &quot;a letter from Christ, the result of our ministry, written ... not on tablets of stone but on tablets of human hearts&quot;; this interpretation states that Christians accordingly no longer follow the Ten Commandments with dead orthodoxy (&quot;tablets of stone&quot;), but follow a new law written upon &quot;tablets of human hearts&quot;. {{Bibleverse-nb|2|Cor.|3:7-11}} adds that &quot;if the ministry that brought death, which was engraved in letters on stone, came with glory ..., will not the ministry of the Spirit be even more glorious? .... And if what was fading away came with glory, how much greater is the glory of that which lasts!&quot; This is interpreted as teaching that new-covenant Christians are not under the Mosaic law, and that Sabbath-keeping is not required. Further, because &quot;love is the fulfillment of the law&quot; ({{Bibleverse||Rom.|13:10}}), the new-covenant &quot;law&quot; is considered to be based entirely upon love and to rescind Sabbath requirements.

Non-Sabbatarians who affirm that Sabbath-keeping remains for God's people (as in {{Bibleverse||Heb.|4:9}}) often regard this as present spiritual rest and/or future heavenly rest rather than as physical weekly rest. For instance, Irenaeus saw Sabbath rest from secular affairs for one day each week as a sign of the way that Christians were called to permanently devote themselves to God&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Against Heresies|volume=3.16.1|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.ix.vi.xvii.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an eschatological symbol.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Against Heresies|volume=4.33.2|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.ix.vii.xxxiv.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Interpretations==
===Genesis 2===
Based on Genesis 2:1-4, Sabbath is considered by seventh-day Sabbatarians to be the first holy day mentioned in the Bible, with God, Adam, and Eve being the first to observe it. In order to reconcile an [[omnipotent]] God with a resting on the seventh day of [[Genesis creation narrative|Creation]], the notion of active cessation from labor, rather than passive rest, has been regarded as a more consistent reading of God's activity in this passage. Non-Sabbatarians and many first-day Sabbatarians consider this passage not to have instituted observance of Sabbath, which they place as beginning with Moses and the manna. [[Walter Brueggemann]] emphasizes Sabbath is rooted in the history of the [[Book of Exodus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Brueggemann|first=Walter|authorlink=Walter Brueggemann|title=The Land: Place as Gift, Promise, and Challenge in Biblical Faith|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gFQQAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=2011-09-28|edition=2d|year=2002|publisher=Fortress Press|isbn=978-0-8006-3462-9|series=Overtures to Biblical Theology|pages=60, 225|quote=The tradition of Deuteronomy appeals for Sabbath on more historical grounds. Sabbath is rooted in the history of Exodus, which led to the land of fulfillment.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Matthew 5===
Jesus' statement, &quot;Do not think that I have come to abolish the Law or the Prophets; I have not come to abolish them but to fulfill them,&quot; is highly debated. Some non-Sabbatarians and others such as [[Anabaptists]] believe Jesus greatly reformed the Law and thus that Sabbath could only be justified if it were reaffirmed by Jesus. [[Antinomianism]], generally regarded as a [[heresy]], holds that, because Jesus accomplished all that was required by the law, thus &quot;fulfilling&quot; it, he made it unnecessary for anyone to do anything further. Strict Sabbatarians follow or expand [[Augustine]]'s statement in ''Reply to Faustus'' that Jesus empowered his people to obey the law and gave additional commands that furthered its true intentions. This passage is often related to Colossians 2, from which maintenance, transference, or abolition of Sabbath are variously taught.

===Colossians 2===
The [[English Standard Version]] at {{Bibleverse||Col.|2:16-7}} (&quot;Therefore let no one pass judgment on you in questions of food and drink, or with regard to a festival or a new moon or a Sabbath. These are a shadow of the things to come, but the substance belongs to Christ.&quot;) is taken as affirming non-Sabbatarian freedom from obligations to Sabbath, whether this means only annual Sabbaths ({{Bibleverse||Lev.|23:4–44}})&lt;ref name=col2/&gt; or specifically weekly Sabbath ({{Bibleverse||Lev.|23:1–3}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|quote=The false teacher(s) were advocating a number of Jewish observances, arguing that they were essential for spiritual advancement .... The old covenant observances pointed to a future reality that was fulfilled in the Lord Jesus Christ (cf. Heb. 10:1). Hence, Christians are no longer under the Mosaic covenant (cf. Rom. 6:14–15; 7:1–6; 2 Cor. 3:4–18; Gal. 3:15–4:7). Christians are no longer obligated to observe OT dietary laws ('food and drink') or festivals, holidays, and special days ('a festival ... new moon ... Sabbath,' Col. 2:16), for what these things foreshadowed has been fulfilled in Christ. It is debated whether the Sabbaths in question included the regular seventh-day rest of the fourth commandment, or were only the special Sabbaths of the Jewish festal calendar.|title=[[Holy Bible]], [[English Standard Version]]|chapter=Notes on Col. 2:16-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; This passage's threefold categorization of events is parallel to {{Bibleverse||Num.|28-29}}, {{Bibleverse|1|Chr.|23:31}}, {{Bibleverse|2|Chr.|2:4}}, {{Bibleverse||Is.|1:13}}, {{Bibleverse||Ezek.|45:17}} ({{Bibleverse||Lev.|23}} mentions Sabbaths and festivals but not new moons). Accordingly, non-Sabbatarians and some first-day Sabbatarians believe this passage indicates Sabbath-keeping is part of an [[Old Covenant]] that is not mandatory (cf. {{Bibleverse||Heb.|8:13}}). Seventh-day Sabbatarians and strict first-day Sabbatarians believe this passage indicates that weekly Sabbath remains to be kept as a shadow of things future to Paul's day&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Jewish New Testament Commentary|author=Stern, David H.|date=1992|publisher=Jewish New Testament Publications, Inc|location=[[Clarksville, Maryland]]|isbn=965-359-008-1|page=611|chapter=Notes on Col. 2:17|quote='''These are a shadow of things that are coming''', meaning the good things that will happen when [[Yeshua]] returns.}} Both verbs in 17a are present tense.&lt;/ref&gt; and/or a memorial of creation past.&lt;ref name=col2&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.sabbathtruth.com/faq/frequently-asked-questions/articletype/articleview/articleid/929/please-explain-colossians-214.aspx|chapter=Please explain Colossians 2:14|title=The Law and the Sabbath|author=Walker, Allen|pages=113–116}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, {{Bibleverse||Col.|2:13-5}} states, &quot;And you, who were dead in your trespasses and the uncircumcision of your flesh, God made alive together with him, having forgiven us all our trespasses, by canceling the record of debt that stood against us with its legal demands. This he set aside, nailing it to the cross. He disarmed the rulers and authorities and put them to open shame, by triumphing over them in him.&quot; The ESV footnote regards &quot;''in it'' (that is, the [[Christian cross|cross]])&quot; as equivalent to the closing ''in him'' ([[Christ]]). First-day Sabbatarians and non-Sabbatarians regard Sabbath as changed, either to Lord's Day or to spiritual Sabbath, by the &quot;record of debt&quot; being nailed to the cross. Some seventh-day Sabbatarians regard only High Sabbaths as abolished due to their foreshadowing the cross, holding it impossible for weekly Sabbath (which preceded sin) to foreshadow deliverance from sin in the cross.&lt;ref name=lostday6/&gt; Others see the &quot;record of debt&quot; (accusations) as distinct from God's unchanging law, believing it to be in force and affirmed by the evangelists after Jesus died on the cross,&lt;ref name=wohlberg/&gt; taking Sabbath, new moon, and High Sabbaths not as nailed to the cross but as foreshadowing the eternal plan of God.&lt;ref name=howard/&gt;

===Hebrews 4===
The [[hapax legomenon|unique word]] ''sabbatismos'' in Hebrews 4:9 is translated &quot;rest&quot; in the [[Authorized Version]] and others; &quot;Sabbath rest&quot; in the [[New International Version]] and other modern translations; &quot;Sabbatism&quot; (a [[transliteration]]) in the [[Darby Bible]]; &quot;Sabbath observance&quot; in the [[Scriptures 98 Edition]]; and &quot;Sabbath keeping&quot; in the [[Bible in Basic English]]. The word also appears in [[Plutarch]], ''De Superstitione'' 3 (Moralia 166A); [[Justin Martyr|Justin]], ''Dialogue with Trypho'' 23:3; [[Epiphanius of Salamis|Epiphanius]], ''[[Panarion|Adversus Haereses]]'' 30:2:2; ''Martyrium Petri et Pauli'' 1; and ''[[Apostolic Constitutions]]'' 2:36:2. Andrew Lincoln states, &quot;In each of these places the term denotes the observance or celebration of the Sabbath .... Thus the writer to the Hebrews is saying that since the time of Joshua an observance of the Sabbath rest has been outstanding.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lincoln, Prof. Andrew T|title=From Sabbath to Lord's Day (symposium)|page=213}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sabbatarians believe the primary abiding Christian duty intended is weekly Sabbath-keeping, while non-Sabbatarians believe it is spiritual or eschatological Sabbath-keeping; both meanings may be intended. Justin uses ''sabbatismos'' in ''Trypho'' 23:3 to mean weekly Sabbath-keeping.

However, Justin does not speak of Hebrews 4, instead holding that there is no longer any need for weekly Sabbath-keeping for anyone. [[Hippolytus of Rome]], in the early third century, interpreted the term in Hebrews 4 to have special reference to a [[millennialism|millennial]] Sabbath kingdom after six millennia of labor. [[St. Chrysostom]] interpreted the term as having reference to three rests: God's rest from His labor on the seventh day, the rest of the Israelites in arriving in Canaan, and the heavenly (eschatological) rest for the faithful. He argued that the &quot;rest&quot; which &quot;has been outstanding&quot; is the heavenly rest, since the first two rests had already been going on. He also interpreted weekly Sabbath as a symbol of this heavenly rest: &quot;And well did he conclude the argument. For he said not rest but 'Sabbath-keeping'; calling the kingdom 'Sabbath-keeping,' by the appropriate name, and that which they rejoiced in and were attracted by. For as, on the Sabbath He commands to abstain from all evil things; and that those things only which relate to the Service of God should be done, which things the Priests were wont to accomplish, and whatsoever profits the soul, and nothing else; so also [will it be] then.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[John Chrysostom]]|title=6th Homily on the Epistle to the Hebrews|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf114.v.x.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Matthew Henry]] calls this &quot;a rest of grace, and comfort, and holiness, in the gospel state. And a rest in glory, where the people of God shall enjoy the end of their faith, and the object of all their desires .... undoubtedly the heavenly rest, which remains to the people of God, and is opposed to a state of labour and trouble in this world. It is the rest they shall obtain when the Lord Jesus shall appear from heaven .... God has always declared man's rest to be in him, and his love to be the only real happiness of the soul.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=[[Matthew Henry|Henry, Matthew]]|title=Concise Commentary on the Whole Bible}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is taken to support the belief that Sabbath-keeping is a metaphor for the eternal &quot;rest&quot; that Christians enjoy in Christ, prefigured by the promised land of Canaan.

===Hebrews 8===
Non-Sabbatarians and some first-day Sabbatarians believe Hebrews 8 indicates Sabbath-keeping is not mandatory, because &quot;in that he saith, a new covenant, he hath made the first old&quot; ({{Bibleverse||Heb.|8:13}} KJV; or &quot;obsolete&quot; NIV). Seventh-day Sabbatarians and strict first-day Sabbatarians believe Hebrews 8 indicates the Law of God (including Sabbath) remains on the hearts of God's people to be kept, but not fallibly as in the older covenant ({{Bibleverse||Heb.|8:9–10}}).

==See also==
*[[Sabbath in Judaism]]
*[[Non-Sabbatarianism]]
*[[Remember the Sabbath and keep it holy]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Shabbat}}
{{Ten Commandments}}

[[Category:Biblical criticism|Sabbath]]
[[Category:Christianity-related controversies]]
[[Category:Judeo-Christian topics]]
[[Category:Old Testament theology]]
[[Category:Ancient Christian controversies]]
[[Category:Early Christianity and Judaism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Sabbath]]
[[Category:Commandments]]

[[de:Sabbatianer]]
[[hu:Szombatosok]]
[[ro:Sabatul biblic]]</text>
      <sha1>rc0x874q6ik8cs0lkka5h81jccjrw4z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
