<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bishops' Bible</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>174117</id>
    <revision>
      <id>506611114</id>
      <parentid>462376664</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-09T20:02:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>63.239.180.70</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9428">[[File:Bishops Bible Elizabeth I 1569.jpg|thumb|Though not formally dedicated to [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth]], the Bishops' Bible includes a portrait of the queen on its title page. The 1569 [[quarto]] edition shows Elizabeth accompanied by female [[personification]]s of Justice, Mercy, Fortitude, and Prudence.]]
The '''Bishops' Bible''' is an [[English language|English]] [[Bible translations|translation]] of the [[Bible]] which was produced under the authority of the established [[Church of England]] in 1568.  It was substantially revised in 1572, and this revised edition was to be prescribed as the base text for the [[Authorized King James Version]] of 1611.  

==History==
The thorough [[Calvinism]] of the [[Geneva Bible]] (displayed in the marginal notes more so than in the translation itself) offended the high-church party of the Church of England, to which almost all of its [[bishop]]s subscribed.  They associated Calvinism with [[Presbyterianism]], which sought to replace government of the church by bishops ([[episcopal polity|Episcopalian]]) with government by lay elders. However, they were aware that the [[Great Bible]] of 1539 —which was the only version then legally authorized for use in Anglican worship—was severely deficient; in that much of the [[Old Testament]] and [[Biblical Apocrypha|Apocrypha]] was translated from the Latin [[Vulgate]], rather than from the original [[Hebrew]], [[Aramaic]] and [[Greek language|Greek]]. In an attempt to replace the objectionable Geneva translation, they circulated one of their own, which became known as the Bishops' Bible.  

The promoter of the exercise, and the leading figure in translating was [[Matthew Parker]], [[Archbishop of Canterbury]]. It was at his instigation that the various sections translated by Parker and his fellow bishops were followed by their initials in the early editions. For instance, at the end of the book of [[Deuteronomy]], we find the initials &quot;W.E.&quot;, which, according to a letter Parker wrote to Sir [[William Cecil, 1st Baron Burghley|William Cecil]], stands for [[William Alley]], [[Bishop of Exeter]]. Parker tells Cecil that this system was &quot;to make [the translators] more diligent, as answerable for their doings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Pollard
  | first =Alfred W. 
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = The Holy Bible: 1611 Edition, King James Version.
  | publisher =Hendrickson
  | year =2003
  | location = Peabody, MA
  | pages =22–3
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =  
  | isbn =1-56563-160-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unhappily, Parker failed to commission anyone to act as supervisory editor for the work completed by the various translators—and was too busy to do so himself, and accordingly translation practice varies greatly from book to book. Hence, in most of the Hebrew Bible (as is standard in English Versions) the [[Yahweh|tetragrammaton]] YHWH is represented by &quot;the Lord&quot;, and the Hebrew &quot;Elohim&quot; is represented by &quot;God&quot;. But in the Psalms the practice is the opposite way around. The books that Parker himself worked on are fairly sparingly edited from the text of the Great Bible, while those undertaken by [[Grindal]] of London emerged much closer to the Geneva text.

[[File:Elizabeth I Frontispiece Bishops Bible 1568.jpg|thumb|left|In this edition, Elizabeth is flanked by allegorical [[virtues]] of [[Faith]] and [[Charity (virtue)|Charity]].  Elizabeth therefore represents [[Hope]].  Beneath the portrait is a Latin text from Romans 1:16]]
The bishops depute to revise the [[Biblical Apocrypha|Apocrypha]] appear to have delivered very little, as the text in these books reproduce that of the [[Great Bible]] broadly the same. As the Apocrypha of the Great Bible was translated from the Latin [[Vulgate]], the Bishops' Bible cannot strictly claim to have been entirely translated from the original tongues.

The Bishops' Bible was first published in 1568,&lt;ref name=&quot;herb&quot;&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Herbert
  | first = A. S. 
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Historical Catalogue of Printed Editions of the English Bible 1525–1961 
  | publisher = American Bible Society
  | year =1968
  | location =New York
  | pages =125–480
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =  
  | isbn = 564-00130-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; but was then re-issued in an extensively revised form in 1572. In the revision a number of switches were made to the New Testament in the direction of more &quot;ecclesiastical&quot; language (e.g. introducing the term &quot;charity&quot; into I Corinthians 13), but otherwise to correct the text more in line with that found in the Geneva Bible; and in the Old Testament, the Psalms from the Great Bible were printed alongside those in the new translation—which had proved impossible to sing. From 1577 the new psalm translation was dropped altogether; while further incremental changes were made to the text of the New Testament in subsequent editions. The Bible had the authority of the royal warrant, and was the second version appointed to be read aloud in church services (cf. [[Great Bible]], [[Authorized King James Version|King James Bible]]). It failed to displace the Geneva Bible as a domestic Bible to be read at home, but that was not its intended purpose. The intention was for it to be used in church as what would today be termed a pulpit Bible. The version was more grandiloquent than the Geneva Bible. The first edition was exceptionally large and included 124 full-page illustrations. The second and subsequent editions were rather smaller, around the same size as the first printing of the King James Bible, and mostly lacked illustrations other than frontispieces and maps. The text lacked most of the notes and cross-references in the Geneva Bible, which contained much controversial [[theology]], but which were helpful to people among whom the Bible was just beginning to circulate in the [[vernacular]]. The last edition of the complete Bible was issued in 1602,&lt;ref name=&quot;herb&quot; /&gt; but the New Testament was reissued until at least 1617.&lt;ref name=&quot;herb&quot; /&gt; William Fulke published several parallel editions up to 1633,&lt;ref name=&quot;herb&quot; /&gt; with the New Testament of the Bishops' Bible alongside the [[Douay-Rheims Bible|Rheims New Testament]], specifically to controvert the latter's polemical annotations. The Bishops' Bible or its New Testament went through over 50 editions, whereas the Geneva Bible was reprinted more than 150 times.

==Legacy==
The translators of the [[Authorized King James Version|King James Version]] were instructed to take the 1602 edition of the Bishops' Bible as their basis, although several other existing translations were taken into account. After it was published in 1611, the King James Version soon took the Bishops' Bible's place as the ''de facto'' standard of the Church of England. Later judgments of the Bishops' Bible have not been favorable; David Daniell, in his important edition of [[William Tyndale]]'s [[New Testament]], states that the Bishops' Bible &quot;was, and is, not loved. Where it reprints Geneva it is acceptable, but most of the original work is incompetent, both in its scholarship and its verbosity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Daniell
  | first =David 
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Tyndale's New Testament  
  | publisher =Yale
  | year =1989
  | location = New Haven
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =  
  | isbn = 0-300-04419-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike Tyndale's translations and the Geneva Bible, the Bishops' Bible has rarely been reprinted. The most available reprinting of its New Testament portion (minus its marginal notes) can be found in the fourth column of the ''New Testament Octapla'' edited by Luther Weigle, chairman of the translation committee that produced the [[Revised Standard Version]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Weigle
  | first =Luther A. 
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =The New Testament Octapla: Eight English Versions of the New Testament in the Tyndale-King James Tradition
  | publisher =Thomas Nelson
  | year =1962
  | location =NY
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =  
  | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bishops' Bible is also known as the &quot;[[Bible errata|Treacle Bible]]&quot; because of its translation of Jeremiah 8:22 which reads &quot;Is there not treacle at [[Gilead]]?&quot;, a rendering also found in several earlier versions as well such as the Great Bible.{{Fact|date=January 2009}} In the Authorized Version of 1611, &quot;treacle&quot; was changed to &quot;[[balm]]&quot;.
{{BibleHistory}}

==References==
{{wikisource|Bible (Bishops')}}
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*''[[Matthew Bible]]''
*''[[Great Bible]]''
*''[[Geneva Bible]]''

==External links==
*[http://www.studylight.org/desk/?l=en&amp;query=genesis+1&amp;section=0&amp;translation=bis&amp;oq=genesis&amp;new=1/The Studylight Version of the Bishops Bible Text.];From Studylight, An incomplete Version, lacking in the Apocrypha, which existed in the original, but in the original spelling.
*[http://studybible.info/Bishops Bishops Bible on StudyBible.info] — Includes the Apocrypha.
* [http://www.bible-researcher.com/bishops1.html Online version of Sir Frederic G. Kenyon’s article] in ''[[Hastings' Dictionary of the Bible]]'', 1909

{{English Bible translation navbox}}

[[Category:1568 books]]
[[Category:Early printed Bibles]]
[[Category:History of Christianity in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:History of the Church of England]]
[[Category:16th-century Christian texts]]
[[Category:English Bible translations]]

[[de:Bischofsbibel]]</text>
      <sha1>ba9o8s9vnm7fnsprghwyhvf3xpbt6wg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
