<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Born again (Christianity)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4950</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517653787</id>
      <parentid>517645776</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-14T00:24:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Guðsþegn</username>
        <id>297649</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/99.29.150.185|99.29.150.185]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31606">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Redirect|New Birth}}

In Christianity, to be '''born again''' is to undergo a &quot;spiritual rebirth&quot; ([[Regeneration (theology)|regeneration]]) of the human soul or spirit, contrasted with the physical birth everyone experiences. The origin of the term &quot;born again&quot; is the [[New Testament]]: &quot;[[Jesus]] replied, 'Very truly I tell you, no one can see the [[kingdom of God]] without being ''born again''.'&quot;{{Bibleref2c|John|3:3|NIV|Jn 3:3 NIV}}&lt;ref&gt;or &quot;born from above&quot; according to some other translations&lt;/ref&gt; It is a term associated with [[salvation]] in Christianity. Individuals who profess to be born again often state that they have a personal relationship with Jesus Christ.&lt;ref name=Price&gt;{{cite book|author=Robert M. Price|title=Beyond Born Again: Toward Evangelical Maturity|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MEYaWhQnd0QC&amp;pg=PA53&amp;dq=personal+relationship+with+jesus+christ+born+again#v=onepage&amp;q=personal%20relationship%20with%20jesus%20christ%20born%20again&amp;f=false|publisher=[[Wildside Press]]|quote=&quot;I have a personal relationship with Jesus Christ.&quot; If you are an Evangelical Christian you can remember saying these words probably more times than you can count. If on the other hand you are not &quot;Born Again,&quot; you may have heard this phrase from an Evangelical inviting you to establish such a relationship with Christ.|year=1993|accessdate=30 July 2011|isbn=9781434477484}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bornstein&gt;{{cite book|author=Erica Bornstein|title=The spirit of development: Protestant NGOs, morality, and economics in Zimbabwe|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=RQM1kPlOFBkC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;dq=personal+relationship+with+jesus+christ+born+again#v=onepage&amp;q=personal%20relationship%20with%20jesus%20christ%20born%20again&amp;f=false|publisher=[[Stanford University Press]]|quote=A senior staff member in World Vision's California office elaborated on the importance of being &quot;born again,&quot; emphasizing a fundamental &quot;relationship&quot; between individuals and Jesus Christ: &quot;. . . the importance of a personal relationship with Christ [is] that it's not just a matter of going to Christ or being baptized when you are an infant. We believe that people need to be regenerated. They need a spiritual rebirth. The need to be born again . . .You must be born again before you can see, or enter, the Kingdom of Heaven.&quot;|year=2005|accessdate=30 July 2011|isbn=9780804753364}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lever&gt;{{cite book|author=A. B. Lever|title=And God Said...|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=d1fWE9H8zJYC&amp;pg=PA291&amp;dq=personal+relationship+with+jesus+christ+born+again#v=onepage&amp;q=personal%20relationship%20with%20jesus%20christ%20born%20again&amp;f=false|quote=From speaking to other Christians I know that the distinction of a born again believer is a personal experience of God that leads to a personal relationship with Him.|year=2007|accessdate=30 July 2011|isbn=9781604771152}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Methodism}}
To many historic church denominations, to be &quot;born again&quot; was understood as [[baptismal regeneration|spiritual regeneration]] via the [[sacrament]] of [[baptism]] by the power of water and word. This is still the understanding in [[Roman Catholicism]], some parts of [[Anglicanism]],&lt;ref&gt;See the section on Anglicanism in [[Baptismal regeneration#brganglican|Baptismal regeneration]]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lutheranism]] and [[Eastern Orthodoxy]]. However, beginning sometime after the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]], being ''born again''&lt;ref name=&quot;GoodWord&quot;&gt;&quot;born-again.&quot; ''Good Word Guide.'' London: A&amp;C Black, 2007. Credo Reference. 30 July 2009&lt;/ref&gt; has been predominantly understood by some Protestants (of the &quot;[[anabaptist]]&quot; branch) to be an experience of [[Religious conversion|conversion]] symbolized by water baptism, and rooted in a commitment to one's own personal faith in Jesus Christ for salvation. This same belief is also an integral part of [[Methodist]] doctrine,&lt;ref name=&quot;Methodist&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Samuel Fallows (Bishop); Herbert Lockwood Willett|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=bJfwsFxFPD8C&amp;pg=PA1154&amp;dq=methodism+new+birth#v=onepage&amp;q=methodism%20new%20birth&amp;f=false|title=The popular and critical Bible encyclopædia and scriptural dictionary, fully defining and explaining all religious terms, including biographical, geographical, historical, archæological and doctrinal themes, to which is added an exhaustive appendix illustrated with over 600 maps and engravings|publisher=Chicago, Howard-Severance Co.|quote=The New Birth. Regeneration is an important Methodist doctrine, and is the new birth, a change of heart. All Methodists teach that &quot;Except a man be born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God.&quot; It is the work of the Holy Spirit and is a conscious change in the heart and the life.|year=1901|accessdate=19 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Primal&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Charles Spencer Smith, Daniel Alexander Payne|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gmDZAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA266&amp;dq=born+again+methodism#v=onepage&amp;q=born%20again%20methodism&amp;f=false|title=A History of the African Methodist Episcopal Church|publisher=Johnson Reprint Corporation|quote=Whatever the Church may do, and there is much that it can and should do, for the betterment of man's physical being, its primal work is the regeneration of man's spiritual nature. Methodism has insisted on this as the supreme end and aim of the Church.|year=1922|accessdate=19 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is connected with the doctrine of [[Justification (theology)|Justification]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Justification&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=6kI6AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA172&amp;dq=methodism+new+birth#v=onepage&amp;q=methodism%20new%20birth&amp;f=false|author=Robert Southey; Charles Cuthbert Southey|title=The Life of Wesley: And the Rise and Progress of Methodism|quote=Connected with his doctrine of the New Birth was that of Justification, which he affirmed to be inseparable from it, yet easily to be distinguished, as being not the same, but of a widely different nature. In order of time, neither of these is before the other; in the moment we are justified by the grace of God, through the redemption that is in Jesus, we are also born of the Spirit; but in order of thinking, as it is termed, Justification precedes the New Birth.|publisher=[[Nabu Press]]|date=16 March 2010|accessdate=5 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following an interpretation of, for instance, {{Bibleref2|Ezekiel|36:26|ESV}},&lt;ref&gt;&quot;And I will give you a new heart, and a new spirit I will put within you. And I will remove the heart of stone from your flesh and give you a heart of flesh&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; adherents of the ''Born again'' concept believe that when a person accepts Jesus as the [[Messiah]] and receives the Holy Spirit, a radical &quot;change of heart&quot;  occurs{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}. This change is marked by an aversion to [[sin]] and a passion for obedience to the [[Law of Christ|commandments of Jesus Christ]], as outlined in the [[Christian scriptures]]. Many{{Who|date=March 2012}} associate the term &quot;born again&quot; with the revelation of a new concept, or an experience of [[Religious conversion|conversion]], defined as mental assent to the acceptance of Jesus Christ as one's personal Savior; though some believe that this experience or mental assent (See [[Gnosticism]]) is not alone sufficient to merit [[Christian salvation]]. Rather, in addition, this is brought about by [[repentance]], the aforementioned &quot;new birth&quot; of the Holy Spirit, and faith in [[Jesus Christ]]'s [[propitiation]] for sins.&lt;ref&gt;fundamentalism. (2010). In ''Encyclopædia Britannica.'' Retrieved 17 September 2010, from Encyclopædia Britannica Online&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Oxford English Dictionary]], finding examples going back to 1961, defines the adjective ''born-again'' as:
:Of, pertaining to, or characterized by (an experience of) new birth in Christ or spiritual renewal; of a Christian: placing special emphasis on this experience as a basis for all one's actions, evangelical.&lt;ref&gt;''Oxford English Dictionary''.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Origin===
====Biblical foundation====
The [[Authorized King James Version|King James' Version]] uses the phrase ''born again'' three times. Two are found in chapter 3 of the Gospel of John, verses 3 and 7. Jesus is speaking to [[Nicodemus]], a [[Pharisee]] described as &quot;a ruler of the Jews&quot;, who says that, because of his miracles, Jesus is known &quot;to be a teacher come from God&quot;. Jesus immediately replies: &quot;Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born again, he cannot see the kingdom of God.&quot;(KJV).&lt;ref name=&quot;MSM&quot; /&gt;
A few verses later Jesus is reported as saying:
:::Marvel not that I said unto thee, Ye must be born again. / The wind bloweth where it listeth, and thou hearest the sound thereof, but canst not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: so is every one that is born of the Spirit.
John's Gospel was written in Greek, and the Greek word translated as ''again'' is ''ανωΘεν'' (anothen), which could mean ''again'', or ''from above''. This latter translation is preferred by the [[New Revised Standard Version]].&lt;ref name = &quot;MSM&quot; /&gt;

The third and last mention of the phrase is in the First Letter of Peter, verses {{Bibleref2|1 Peter|1:22-23|KJV|22-23}}. The King James Bible translates this as:
:::Seeing ye have purified your souls in obeying the truth through the Spirit unto unfeigned love of the brethren, [see that ye] love one another with a pure heart fervently: / Being born again, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God, which liveth and abideth for ever.
Here, the Greek word translated as ''born again'' is ''αναγεγεννημενοι'' (anagegennemenoy).&lt;ref name = &quot;SJF&quot;&gt;Fisichella, SJ., ''Taking Away the Veil: To See Beyond the Curtain of Illusion'', iUniverse, 2003, pp. 55-56.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Interpretations====
The traditional Jewish understanding of the promise of salvation was that being rooted in &quot;the seed of Abraham&quot; referred to physical lineage from Abraham. Jesus explained to Nicodemus that this doctrine was in error—that every person must have two births—the natural birth of the physical body, the other of the water and the spirit.&lt;ref&gt;Emmons, Samuel B. ''A Bible Dictionary.'' BiblioLife, 2008. ISBN 978-0-554-89108-8.&lt;/ref&gt; This discourse with Nicodemus established the Christian belief that all human beings—whether Jew or Gentile—must be &quot;born again&quot; of the spiritual seed of Christ. The [[Apostle Peter]] further reinforced this understanding in {{Bibleref2|1Peter|1:23|KJV|1 Peter 1:23}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;SJF&quot; /&gt; The ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' states that &quot;A controversy existed in the primitive church over the interpretation of the expression ''the [[seed of Abraham]]''. It is &lt;nowiki&gt;[the Apostle Paul's]&lt;/nowiki&gt; teaching in one instance that all who are Christ's by faith are Abraham's seed, and heirs according to promise. He is concerned, however, with the fact that the promise is not being fulfilled to the seed of Abraham (referring to the Jews).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Driscoll, James F. &quot;Divine Promise (in Scripture).&quot; The Catholic Encyclopedia. Vol. 12. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1911. 15 Nov 2009 &lt;http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12453a.htm&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charles Hodge]] writes that &quot;The subjective change wrought in the soul by the grace of God, is variously designated in Scripture&quot; with terms such as new birth, resurrection, new life, new creation, renewing of the mind, dying to sin and living to righteousness, and translation from darkness to light.&lt;ref name=Hodge1&gt;Hodge, Charles. &quot;Regeneration.&quot; ''Systematic Theology-Volume III.'' Web: &lt;http://www.ccel.org/ccel/hodge/theology3.iii.i.i.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Jesus Christ used the &quot;birth&quot; analogy in tracing spiritual newness of life to a divine beginning. Contemporary Christian theologians have provided explanations for &quot;born from above&quot; being a more accurate translation of the original Greek word transliterated ''anōthen.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblestudytools.com/lexicons/greek/nas/anothen.html ''The New Testament Greek Lexicon.''] 30 July 2009. Online:&lt;/ref&gt; [[Frank Stagg (theologian)|Theologian Frank Stagg]] cites two reasons why the newer translation is significant:
# The emphasis &quot;from ''above''&quot; (implying &quot;from ''Heaven''&quot;) calls attention to the source of the &quot;newness of life.&quot; Stagg writes that the word &quot;again&quot; does not include the ''source'' of the new kind of beginning
# More than personal improvement is needed. &quot;...a new destiny requires a new origin, and the new origin must be from God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stagg, Evelyn and Frank. ''Woman in the World of Jesus.'' Philadelphia: Westminster Press, 1978. ISBN 0-664-24195-6&lt;/ref&gt;

An early example of the term in its more modern use is found in the sermons of [[John Wesley]]. In the sermon printed under the title of ''A New Birth'', he said &quot;none can be holy unless he be born again&quot;, and &quot;except he be born again, none can be happy even in this world. For ... a man should not be happy who is not holy.&quot; Also, &quot;I say, [a man] may be born again and so become an heir of salvation.&quot; Wesley also states infants who are baptized are born again, but for adults it is different:&lt;blockquote&gt;... our church supposes, that all who are baptized in their infancy, are at the same time born again. ... But ... it is sure all of riper years, who are baptized, are not at the same time born again.&lt;ref&gt;Wesley, J., ''The works of  the Reverend John Wesley'', Methodist Episcopal Church, 1831, pp. 405–406.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Denominational positions==
For American Christians, ''The Oxford Handbook of Religion and American Politics'' notes: &quot;The [[General Social Survey|GSS]] ... has asked a born-again question on three occasions ... 'Would you say you have been 'born again' or have had a 'born-again' experience?&quot; The Handbook says that &quot;Evangelical, black, and Latino Protestants tend to respond similarly, with about two-thirds of each group answering in the affirmative. In contrast, only about one third of mainline Protestants and one sixth of Catholics (Anglo and Latino) claim a born-again experience.&quot; However, the handbook suggests that &quot;born-again questions are poor measures even for capturing evangelical respondents. ... it is likely that people who report a born-again experience also claim it as an identity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford Handbook of Religion and American Politics'', OUP, p16.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Catholicism===
At the [[Council of Trent]], on 15 November 1551, the necessity for a ''second conversion'' after [[baptism]] was delineated:&lt;ref name=&quot;Trent&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Ross Thomas Hindman|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=COVi91uaZJEC&amp;pg=PA85&amp;dq=born+again+1428++Catechism+Catholic+Church#v=onepage&amp;q=born%20again%201428%20%20Catechism%20Catholic%20Church&amp;f=false|title=The Great Divide|quote=''Session 14'' (November 15, 1551): The necessity of a &quot;second conversion&quot; after baptism is confirmed. According to the Catechism: &quot;''This second conversion is an uninterrupted task for the whole Church who, clasping sinners to her bosom, is at once holy and always in need of purification, and follows constantly the path of penance and renewal''&quot; (Catechism § 1428).|date=21 September 2008|accessdate=19 October 2009|isbn=9781606476017}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{quote|This second conversion is an uninterrupted task for the whole Church who, clasping sinners to her bosom, is at once holy and always in need of purification, and follows constantly the path of penance and renewal. Jesus' call to conversion and penance, like that of the prophets before him, does not aim first at outward works, &quot;sackcloth and ashes,&quot; fasting and mortification, but at the conversion of the heart, interior conversion ([[Catechism of the Catholic Church]] § 1428 &amp; 1430).}}

[[David MacDonald (Christian musician)|David MacDonald]], a Catholic [[Christian apologetics|apologist]], has written in regards to paragraph 1428, that &quot;this endeavor of conversion is not just a human work. It is the movement of a 'contrite heart,' drawn and moved by [[Divine grace|grace]] to respond to the merciful love of God who loved us first.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MacDonald&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=David MacDonald|url=http://www.davidmacd.com/catholic/born_again_catholics.htm|title=Are Catholics Born Again?|quote= I think that greater common ground can be found if we compare the Evangelical &quot;Born Again&quot; experience to the Catholic &quot;Second Conversion&quot; experience which is when a Catholic surrenders to Jesus with an attitude of &quot;Jesus, take my will and my life, I give everything to you.&quot;  This is a spontaneous thing that happens during the journey of faithful Catholics who &quot;get it.&quot; Yup, the Catholic Church teaches a personal relationship with Christ:  The Catechism says: 1428 Christ's call to conversion continues to resound in the lives of Christians. This second conversion is an uninterrupted task for the whole Church who, &quot;clasping sinners to her bosom, [is] at once holy and always in need of purification, [and] follows constantly the path of penance and renewal.&quot; This endeavor of conversion is not just a human work. It is the movement of a &quot;contrite heart,&quot; drawn and moved by grace to respond to the merciful love of God who loved us first. 1430 Jesus' call to conversion and penance, like that of the prophets before him, does not aim first at outward works, &quot;sackcloth and ashes,&quot; fasting and mortification, but at the conversion of the heart, interior conversion. The Pope and the Catechism are two of the highest authorities in the Church. They are telling us to get personal with Jesus.|year=2003|accessdate=19 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protestant===
In ''The Encylopedia of Protestantism'', JG Melton writes: &quot;While often associated with [[Evangelical Christianity]], the [born again] phenomenon is common across the entire spectrum of Protestant churches.&quot; He continues: &quot;In churches that emphasise evangelism, the 'born-again' experience tends to become the norm, and everyone is expected to recount such an experience.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Melton, JG, ''The Encylopedia of Protestantism'', Infobase publishing, 2009, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt;

The only mention of the phrase in the [[39 Articles]] of the [[Church of England]] is in article XV, which is headed &quot;Of Christ alone without Sin&quot;. In part, it reads: &quot;sin, as S. John saith, was not in Him. But all we the rest, although baptized and born again in Christ, yet offend in many things: and if we say we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eskimo.com/~lhowell/bcp1662/articles/articles.html] Accessed 8 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Evangelical]] Protestants employ the translation of John 3:3 as &quot;born again&quot; rather than &quot;from above&quot;. 
&quot;Although many evangelicals allow that conversion can be a process, generally they see it as a specific, identifiable moment of time when a person simply and sincerely trusts in Jesus Christ as savior.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MSM&quot;&gt;Mullen, MS., in Kurian, GT., ''The Encyclopedia of Christian Civilization'', J. Wiley &amp; Sons, 2012, p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt; They teach that to see the [[Kingdom of God]] one has to be born again. 
They also use the biblical verse of Romans 10:9 &quot;That if you confess with your mouth, 'Jesus is Lord', and believe in your heart that God raised him from the dead, you will be saved.&quot; So, to be born again means to be saved because in order to be saved one has to confess Jesus is Lord with one's mouth and believe it in one's heart. Also, to be born again means to follow Romans 10:10 that &quot;with your heart that you believe and are justified, and it is with your mouth that you profess your faith and are saved&quot;. &lt;ref&gt;Graham, RC. ''I healed you with my word'', Xulan, 2007, p. 414.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jehovah's Witnesses===
[[Jehovah’s Witnesses]] believe that individuals do not have the power to be born again, because it is God who calls and selects his followers. This follows from the verse in John 6:44, &quot;No man can come to me, except the Father which hath sent me draw him.&quot; (King James Version) They consider that when Jesus said in John 3:5 that one has to be born from &quot;water and the spirit&quot; to enter the kingdom of God, it was not a command but a necessity, because the text states &quot;Ye must be born again&quot;. On this point, their publishing organisation, the [[Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society of Pennsylvania]], prefers the translation: &quot;should be born from above&quot;. They write: &quot;Thus, according to that alternate rendering, the new birth originates 'from above'—that is, 'from heaven,' or 'from the Father.' ... Yes it is caused by God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Watchtower, ''BORN AGAIN What Does It Mean?: THE NEW BIRTH A Personal Decision?'', www.watchtower.org,[http://www.watchtower.org/e/20090401/article_03.htm] Accessed 8 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

For further evidence, Jehovah's Witnesses note that in Mark 1:9-10, after Jesus was baptised in water by John the Baptist, he was baptised by the spirit symbolised by a dove. Also, in Acts 1:5, Jesus assured his disciples that they too would soon be baptised in holy spirit: &quot;For John truly baptized with water; but ye shall be baptized with the Holy Ghost not many days hence.&quot; (KJV) The Watchtower states: &quot;Note that Jesus first got baptized with water. Then he received the holy spirit. Similarly, the early disciples had first been baptized in water ... and then they received the holy spirit.&quot; This occurred &quot;On the day of Pentecost in the year 33 C.E.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Watchtower, ''BORN AGAIN What Does It Mean?: THE NEW BIRTH How Does It Take Place?'', www.watchtower.org,[http://www.watchtower.org/e/20090401/article_05.htm] Accessed 8 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Public stances==
In recent history, ''born again'' is a term that has been widely associated with the [[Evangelicalism|evangelical]] Christian renewal since the late 1960s, first in the United States and then later around the world. Associated perhaps initially with [[Jesus movement|Jesus People]] and the Christian counterculture, ''born again'' came to refer to a conversion experience, accepting Jesus Christ as Lord and Savior in order to be saved from Hell and given eternal life with God in Heaven, and was increasingly used as a term to identify devout believers.&lt;ref name = &quot;MSM&quot; /&gt; By the mid 1970s, ''born again'' Christians were increasingly referred to in the mainstream media as part of the born again movement.

In 1976, Watergate conspirator [[Chuck Colson]]'s book ''Born Again'' gained international notice. [[Time (magazine)|''Time'' magazine]] named him &quot;One of the 25 most influential Evangelicals in America.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/covers/1101050207/photoessay/5.html The 25 Most Influential Evangelicals in America.]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term was sufficiently prevalent that during the year's Presidential campaign, most notably with [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic party]] nominee [[Jimmy Carter]] describing himself as &quot;born again&quot; in the first ''[[Playboy]]'' magazine interview of an American Presidential candidate.  Modern musicians such as [[Little Richard]],&lt;ref name=&quot;whitep83&quot;&gt;White, Charles (2003), p. 83 (see text under photo on opposite page). ''The Life and Times of Little Richard: The Authorised Biography.'' Omnibus Press.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Mark Farner]], [[Dan Peek]], [[Donna Summer]], [[Bob Dylan]],&lt;ref&gt;Cott (ed.), ''Dylan on Dylan: The Essential Interviews'', 279–285&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kerry Livgren]], [[Dave Hope]], [[Dave Mustaine]], [[Nicko McBrain]], [[Roger McGuinn]], [[Ted Nugent]], [[Kanye West]], [[Carrie Underwood]], [[Johnny Cash]], [[Brian Welch]], [[Keith Farley]], [[Cliff Richard]], [[Charlie Daniels]], [[Randy Travis]], [[Alice Cooper]], [[Steven Tyler]], [[Mariah Carey]], [[Nick Cannon]], and [[Lou Gramm]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbn.com/media/player/index.aspx?s=/vod/AL24v2_WS |title=Lou Gramm Knows What Love Is - CBN TV - Video |publisher=Cbn.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; were artists whose born again conversions had an impact on modern culture.  Others such as department store magnate [[James Cash Penney]], [[Chick-fil-A]] founder [[S. Truett Cathy|Truett Cathy]], actor/martial artist [[Chuck Norris]], wrestlers [[Shawn Michaels]], [[Chris Jericho]], [[AJ Styles]], [[Ted DiBiase]] and [[Sting (wrestler)|wrestler Sting]], and actors [[Jesse McCartney]], [[Kirk Cameron]], and [[Mr. T]] are also mentioned as being born again. Born-again athletes like [[New York Jets]] quarterback [[Tim Tebow]], [[St. Louis Rams]] quarterback [[Sam Bradford]] and former Rams [[Superbowl XXXIV]] winning quarterback [[Kurt Warner]], Olympic hurderler [[Lolo Jones]], boxer [[Katie Taylor]] and [[New York Knicks]] player [[Jeremy Lin]]. Former [[Alabama]] governor and American presidential candidate [[George Wallace]] became born again in the late 1970s, which led him to apologize for his earlier [[segregationist]] views.

===Chuck Colson===
In his book ''Born Again'' (1976 and 2008), [[Watergate Scandal|Watergate]] conspirator [[Charles Colson|Chuck Colson]] describes his path to faith in conjunction with his criminal imprisonment and played a significant role in solidifying the &quot;born again&quot; identity as a cultural construct in the US. He writes that his spiritual experience followed considerable struggle and hesitancy to have a &quot;personal encounter with God.&quot; He recalls:&lt;blockquote&gt;... while I sat alone staring at the sea I love, words I had not been certain I could understand or say fell from my lips: &quot;Lord Jesus, I believe in You. I accept You. Please come into my life. I commit it to You.&quot;  With these few words...came a sureness of mind that matched the depth of feeling in my heart. There came something more: strength and serenity, a wonderful new assurance about life, a fresh perception of myself in the world around me.&lt;ref&gt;Colson, Charles W. ''Born Again.'' Chosen Books (Baker Publishing), 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Born-again and US politics==
The first born-again President of the United States was [[Jimmy Carter]] in 1976.&lt;ref&gt;Hough, JF., ''Changing party coalitions'', Algora Publishing, 2006, p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;In the 1980 campaign, all three of the major candidates ... stated that they had been born-again&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Utter, GH. and Tru, JL.,''Conservative Christians and political participation: a reference handbook'', ABC-CLIO, 2004, p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[The Gallup Organization]] reported that &quot;In 2003, 42% of U.S. adults said they were born-again or evangelical; the 2004 percentage is 41%.&quot; Also, &quot;Black Americans are far more likely to identify themselves as born-again or evangelical, with 63% of blacks saying they are born-again, compared with 39% of white Americans. &quot; and &quot;Republicans are far more likely to say they are born-again (52%) than Democrats (36%) or independents (32%).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/14632/who-has-been-born-again.aspx |title=Winseman. A.L., '&amp;#39;Who has been born again'&amp;#39;, Gallup, 2004 |publisher=Gallup.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
===Biblical arguments===
The quotation from the Gospel of John has raised some questions about the meaning and authenticity of the phrase &quot;born again&quot;. In the chapter, [[Nicodemus]] is puzzled and asks Jesus what he means by saying that &quot;Ye must be born again&quot;. He questions: &quot;How can a man re-enter his mother's womb?&quot; Scholar [[Bart D. Ehrman]] says that this confusion is because in Greek (the language of the gospel) the word ''again'' is ambiguous. It might mean ''again'' or ''a second time'' or ''from above'', which would explain Nicodemus' confusion. However, the Jews at Jesus' time were actually speaking Aramaic, in which language there would not have been a double meaning. Ehrman says that this raises questions about the authenticity of the dialogue, the meaning of the words, and, therefore, the use of the phrase.&lt;ref&gt;[[Bart D. Ehrman|Ehrman, B.D.]], Referred to in Edward T. Babinski ''The &quot;Born Again&quot; Dialogue In the Gospel of John (Another Reason To Doubt Its Authenticity)'' from http://etb-biblical-errancy.blogspot.com/2012/04/born-again-dialogue-in-gospel-of-john.html Accessed 25 Feb 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

A 19th century source notes that the phrase was not mentioned by the other Evangelists, nor by the Apostles except Peter. &quot;It was not regarded by any of the Evangelists but John of sufficient importance to record.&quot; And, without John, &quot;we should hardly have known that it was necessary for one to be born again.&quot; This suggests that &quot;the text and context was meant to apply to Nicodemus particularly, and not to the world.&quot; Otherwise, it would have been mentioned more often.
&lt;ref&gt;LeFevre, CF. and Williamson, ID., ''The Gospel anchor''. Troy, NY, 1831–32, p. 66. [http://books.google.com/books?id=3T4rAAAAYAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Names inspired by the term==
The idea of being &quot;born again in Christ&quot; inspired some common European [[forename]]s: French [[René]]/[[Renée]] (also used in the Netherlands), Dutch [[Renaat]]/Renate, Italian, Spanish and Portuguese [[Renatus|Renato/Renata]], Latin [[Renatus|Renatus/Renata]], which all mean &quot;reborn&quot;, &quot;born again&quot;.

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity}}
* [[Altar call]] – invitation to become a Christian; given at a church service or event.
* [[Baptism]] – referred to in Jesus' born-again discourse with Nicodemus (&quot;born of water and spirit&quot;)
* [[Baptismal regeneration]] – overview of doctrinal debate about the effect of the baptism rite.
* [[Born-again virgin]] – a person who, though not still a virgin, chooses to live as one.
* [[Dvija]], or twice-born – in Hinduism, a person who has formally taken on the roles of one of the first three castes.
* [[Evangelism]] – practice of sharing about Christianity to those who are not Christians.
* [[Holy Spirit]] – referred to in Jesus' born-again discourse with Nicodemus (&quot;born of water and spirit&quot;)
* [[Monergism]] – belief that being born again is entirely God's work (and not the believer's work)
* [[Sinner's prayer]] – the prayer of a person seeking forgiveness and wanting to become a Christian.
* [[Justus Velsius#London: more religious turmoil|Justus Velsius]] – 16th century Dutch dissident who promoted the view that through new birth man could become like Christ

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.umcmission.org/Find-Resources/Global-Worship-and-Spiritual-Growth/John-Wesley-Sermons/Sermon-45-The-New-Birth The New Birth], [[John Wesley]], sermon #45.  Wesley's teaching on being born again, and argument that it is fundamental to Christianity.
* [http://www.monergism.com/thethreshold/articles/onsite/monergism_short.html Monergistic Regeneration? (Calvinist/Reformed)] - discusses [[monergism]], the view that the new birth is entirely the work of God (as opposed to [[synergism]] which teaches that the believer is also active to some extent.)
* [http://www.bluffton.edu/~humanities/2/newbirth.htm New Birth], a 16th century work by anabaptist preacher [[Menno Simons]], c. 1537, revised c. 1550

{{Methodism footer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Born Again (Christianity)}}
[[Category:Biblical phrases]]
[[Category:Charismatic and Pentecostal Christianity]]
[[Category:Christian fundamentalism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Controversies]]
[[Category:Criticisms]]
[[Category:Evangelicalism]]
[[Category:Scandals]]

[[ar:ولادة جديدة]]
[[cs:Znovuzrození]]
[[de:Erweckungsbewegung]]
[[es:Cristiano renacido]]
[[fr:Born again (christianisme)]]
[[it:Rinascita (religione)]]
[[lt:Naujai gimę]]
[[hu:Újjászületés]]
[[nl:Wedergeboorte (christendom)]]
[[ja:新生 (キリスト教)]]
[[pl:Nowe narodzenie]]
[[ro:Naștere din nou (Creștinism)]]
[[simple:Born again Christianity]]
[[fi:Uudestisyntyminen]]
[[sv:Pånyttfödelse]]
[[vi:Tái sinh]]
[[zh:重生 (基督教)]]</text>
      <sha1>m8k7psftu877jqsnh7hchjrqxfjhw35</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
