<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Brahmin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>244747</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522308449</id>
      <parentid>522308117</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T09:48:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sudhirkbhargava</username>
        <id>1645354</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Claimants of Brahmin Status */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="60231">{{About|the social caste|the moth family|Brahmaeidae|similarly spelled words|Brahman (disambiguation)}}

{{Infobox caste
| caste_name    = Brahmin (Brahmana) Avinash
| list_style = text-align:left;
|{{flagicon|India}} [[india]]
| {{flagicon|Nepal}} [[Nepal]]
| {{flagicon|Arab League}} [[Arab League|Arab States]]
| {{flagicon|Australia}} [[Australia]]
| {{flagicon|Bangladesh}} [[Bangladesh]]
| {{flagicon|Bhutan}} [[Bhutan]]
| {{flagicon|Burma}} [[Burma]]
| {{flagicon|Canada}} [[Canada]]
| {{flagicon|Fiji}} [[Fiji]]
| {{flagicon|France}} [[France]]
| {{flagicon|Germany}} [[Germany]]
| {{flagicon|Guyana}} [[Guyana]]
| {{flagicon|Indonesia}} [[Indonesia]]
| {{flagicon|Kenya}} [[Kenya]]
| {{flagicon|Malaysia}} [[Malaysia]]
| {{flagicon|Mauritius}} [[Mauritius]]
| {{flagicon|New Zealand}} [[New Zealand]]
| {{flagicon|Pakistan}} [[Pakistan]]
| {{flagicon|Singapore}} [[Singapore]]
| {{flagicon|South Africa}} [[South Africa]]
| {{flagicon|Sri Lanka}} [[Sri Lanka]]
| {{flagicon|Suriname}} [[Suriname]]
| {{flagicon|Thailand}} [[Thailand]]
| {{flagicon|Trinidad and Tobago}} [[Trinidad and Tobago]]
| {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom]]
| {{Flagicon|United States}} [[United States]]
| religions    = [[File:Om.svg|15px]] [[Hinduism]]
}}

[[File:AgasthiyarG.jpg|thumb|right|Rishi [[Agastya]], one of seven [[veda|vedic sages]] extolled at many places in the [[Vedas]] and author of Agastya Samhita]]

{{Hinduism}}
'''Brahmin''' (also called '''Brahmana'''; from the [[Sanskrit]] {{IAST|brāhmaṇa}}  {{lang|sa|ब्राह्मण}}) is a term in the traditional [[Hindu societies]] of [[Nepal]] and [[India]].

[[Brahman]], Brahmin, and Brahma have different meanings. Brahman refers to the Supreme Self. Brahmin (or Brahmana) refers to an individual, while the word [[Brahma]] refers to the creative aspect of the universal consciousness. The English word ''brahmin'' is an anglicised form of the Sanskrit word ''{{IAST|Brāhman}}a''. In the [[Smriti]] view, there are four &quot;varnas&quot; or classes: the Brahmins, the [[Kshatriya]]s, the [[Vaishya]]s, and the [[Shudra]]s (outcastes, [[chandalas]]). The Atreya smriti 141-142 enjoins that:
{{quote|janmana jayate shudrah&lt;br&gt;
''One is a [[Shudra]] by birth''&lt;br&gt;
samskarad dvija ucyate&lt;br&gt;
''By observing [[Sanskara]] one becomes a [[Dvija]]''&lt;br&gt;
vedapathi bhaved viprah&lt;br&gt;
''By studying the [[Vedas]] one becomes a Vipra''&lt;br&gt;
brahma janati brahmanah&lt;br&gt;
''One who knows Brahman is a Brahmana'' }}

Brahmins were engaged in attaining the highest spiritual knowledge ([[brahmavidya]]) and adhered to different branches (shakhas) of Vedas. This was described to be a difficult path of discipline of body, mind, and intellect. However, certain persons, though very few in number, were born into other varnas but dedicated themselves to such an austere life that they were also recognized as Brahmins in ancient India (e.g., sage [[Vishwamitra]], a non-brahmin who attained brahmavidya and composed the [[Gayatri mantra]] was venerated as &quot;Brahmarishi&quot;, not by caste but by title / pre-fix accorded to him by the well-read in general in those days).

Historically, the semantic change from a tribal state into the Hindu state of the jati-varna matrix saw the conversion and absorption of tribals into the Brahmin class, through adoption of the priestly occupation.&lt;ref&gt;Indian Economic and Social History Review 1987, Himanshu P Ray, 24: 443&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ancient India: a history of its culture and civilization, Damodar Dharmanand Kosambi, p.166-170&lt;/ref&gt; In medieval and colonial India, people in different occupations also proselytized themselves into Brahmins, usually upon leading an austere life, gaining positions of power or upon becoming wealthy.&lt;ref&gt;A social history of India, by SN Sadasivan&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Castes and tribes of Southern India, By Edgar Thurston, K. Rangachari&lt;/ref&gt;

The priestly class is expected to practice self-abnegation and play the role of being the custodians of [[Dharma]] (as a Brāhman who is well versed in Vedic texts).{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} The fee paid to the Brahmana for performance of a sacrifice was considered as a return for the priestly duties.

==History==
{{Main|History of Hinduism}}
[[File:Thai 4 Buddies.jpg|right|thumb|A four-faced statue of [[Brahma]] ([[Phra Phrom]]), the Creator of World and the [[Vedas]], [[Thailand]].]]
Most [[sampradaya]]s (sects) of modern Brahmins claim to take inspiration from the Vedas. According to orthodox Hindu tradition, the Vedas are ''{{IAST|apauruṣeya}}'' and ''anādi'' (beginning-less), and are revealed truths of eternal validity. The Vedas are considered ''[[Śruti]]'' (&quot;that which is heard&quot;) and are the paramount source on which Brahmin tradition claims to be based. Śruti texts include the four Vedas (the [[Rigveda]], the [[Yajurveda]], the [[Samaveda]] and the [[Atharvaveda]]), and their respective [[Brahmanas]], [[Aranyakas]] and [[Upanishads]].

In 1931, Brahmins accounted for 4.32% of the total population of the subcontinent. Today, it comprises 3% of the total population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vedah.net/manasanskriti/Brahmins.html#Brahmin_Population]&lt;/ref&gt; In West Bengal the figures stand at 5%, whereas in Uttar Pradesh, Himachal Pradesh, Rajasthan, Bihar and Orissa the Brahmin population is quite near 10%.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

Megasthenes writes, that Brahmins are, &quot;''philosophers who are first in rank but form the smallest class in point of number.''&quot;&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;P. 184 ''Chandragupta Maurya And His Times'' By Radhakumud Mookerji&lt;/ref&gt; He also compares the Brahmins to the non-Brahmin [[Shramana]]s. Megasthenes also writes, &quot;''The philosophers are of two kinds: (I) Brachmanes and (2) Sarmanes. The Brachmanes are the best esteemed, for they have a more consistent dogmatic system.''&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;

==Practices==
[[Image:Yajna1.jpg|right|thumb|x216px|text|A Hindu priest performs a [[Yajna]] with offerings and chants into a consecrated fire.]]
Brahmins, basically adhere to the principles of the [[Vedas]], related to the texts of the [[Śruti]] and [[Smriti]] which are some the foundations of [[Hinduism]], and practise [[Sanatana Dharma]]. Vedic ''{{IAST|Brāhmaṇas}}'' have six occupational duties, of which three are compulsory&amp;nbsp;— studying the Vedas, performing Vedic rituals and practicing dharma. By teaching the insights of the Vedic literature which deals with all aspects of life including spirituality, philosophy, yoga,{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} religion, rituals, temples, arts and culture,{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} music, dance, grammar, pronunciation, metre, astrology,{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} astronomy,{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} logic, law, medicine,{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} surgery,{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} technology, martial arts,{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} military strategy, etc. By spreading its philosophy, and by accepting back from the community, the Brahmins receive the necessities of life.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

Brahmins practice [[vegetarianism]] or [[lacto-vegetarianism]] which has been a custom for centuries, dating back to the pre-Christian era.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} However, some Brahmins inhabiting regions of [[History of Mithila|Mithila]], [[Punjab, India|Punjab]], [[Kashmir]], [[Himachal Pradesh]], [[West Bengal]] and [[Nepal]], are non-vegetarian.

Most Brahmin sects wear the [[Yagnopaveetham]] (or sacred thread) that is a symbol of initiation to the Gayatri recital. This ritual is often referred to as [[Upanayana]]. This marks the learning of the Gayatri hymn. Brahmin sects also generally identify themselves as belonging to a particular [[Gotra]], a classification based on patrilineal descent, which is specific for each family and indicates their origin.

==Brahmin communities==

The Brahmin castes may be broadly divided into two regional groups: [[Pancha-Gauda]] Brahmins from the Northern part of India (considered to be the region north of the [[Vindhya Range|Vindhya]] mountains) and Pancha-Dravida Brahmins from the region south of the Vindhya mountains as per the [[shloka]] asdof Kalhana. This shloka was composed only in the 11th century CE.{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}

==Pancha-Gauda==
{{main|Pancha-Gauda}}
सारस्वताः कान्यकुब्जा गौडा उत्कलमैथिलाः, पञ्चगौडा इति ख्याता विन्ध्स्योत्तरवासिनः ||

Those from ''[[Uttarapatha]]'' (''Aryavarta'') ([[North India|northern]] and eastern India) approximately ordered according to geographical regions.

===Saankal Dvipiy Brahaman===
*[[Sakdwipe Brahmins]]
* [[Saryupareen Brahmins]]
* [[Assamese Brahmins]]
* [[Kamrupi Brahmins]]
* [[Kanyakubja Brahmin]]s
* [[Sanadhya Brahmin]]s
* [[Bhumihar Brahmin]]s
* [[Bengali Brahmin]]s
* [[Bahun]]
* [[Goswami]]
* [[Manipuri Brahmin]]s
* [[Garhwali Brahmin]]s

===Gauda Brahmins===
[[Gaur brahmin]]
Among Gaur brahmana of Haryana,Rajasthan &amp; west Uttar Pradesh,Adi Gaur /Pachauri,Sanadhya &amp; Paliwal are also Gaur brahmans.

===Rajasthan===
* '''[[Vishwakarma (caste)|Jangid Brahmin]]'''
Jangid Brahman are the followers of Angira Rishi. The sect of Jangid Brahmins are widely found in Rajasthan. Jangid Brahmins are now also found in Uttar Pradesh, Madhya Pradesh and Nepal.

* '''[[Bagra (caste)|Bagra Brahmin]]'''
Bagra Brahmin (pronounced as Bagda) is a part of the Brahmin community mainly concentrated in and around Jaipur district of Rajasthan, India, although members of this community can be found throughout India and also in foreign countries.

===Bias Brahmins===
The [[Bias Brahmin]]s, or sometimes pronounces ''Vyas'' are a Brahmin caste found in the Indian state of [[Haryana]]. They are also known as Bararia and Srimali.&lt;ref name=&quot;MLSharma&quot;&gt;People of India Hayana Volume XXIII edited by M.L Sharma and A.K Bhatia pages 92 to 96 Manohar&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''bias'' means a preacher in [[Sanskrit]], and Bias Brahmin are a group of [[Nagar Brahmins]], who settled in [[Haryana]] some six centuries ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;MLSharma&quot;/&gt;

===Saraswat Brahmins===
[[File:Shri Gaudapadacharya Statue.jpg|thumb|x216px|right|text|Adi Guru Shri Gauḍapādāchārya, the grand guru of [[Adi Shankara|Shri Adi Shankaracharya]] and the first historical proponent of [[Advaita Vedanta]], also believed to be the founder of [[Shri Gaudapadacharya Math]].]]
*[[Saraswat Brahmin]]s
*[[Goud Saraswat Brahmin]]s
*[[Chitrapur Saraswat Brahmin]]s
*[[Rajapur Saraswat Brahmin]]s
*[[Kudaldeshkar gaud Brahmin]] s
*[[Mohyal]]s

===Goswami (Dashnam) Brahmins===
*[[Saraswatī, Puri and Bharatī-associated with the Dakshinamnaya Sringeri Sharada Peetham (in the south)]]
*[[Tīrtha and Ashrama-associated with the Dwaraka Math (in the West)]]
*[[Giri, Parvata and Sagara-associated with Jyotir Math (in the North)]]
*[[Vana and Aranya-associated with the Govardhana Math (in the East)]]

===Kamarupa (Assamese) Brahmins===
[[Assamese Brahmins|Main article: Assamese Brahmins]]

[[Kamrupi Brahmins|See also: Kamrupi Brahmins]]

Assamese Brahmins are found mostly in [[Lower Assam]], [[Upper Assam]] i.e. throughout the [[Brahmaputra Valley]]. They are believed to have their origins in ancient [[Kannauj]], and have migrated during the [[Kamarupa]] period to Lower Assam and then to the rest of the Brahmaputra Valley. With respect to faith and customs, Brahmins in Assam are the same as other Brahmin communities across India. Each Brahmin family within the community identify themselves to a specific [[Gotra]]. Sarma/Sharma, Bhagawati, Goswami, Chakraborty are a few common Assamese Brahmin surnames.

[[Kamarupa|Kamrupi]] kings were known to take regular advice from Brahmins for political and religious purposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| surname= Singh | given= G.P | title= Historical Research Into Some Aspects Of The Culture And Civilization Of North east India }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Kamrupi king [[Bhaskar Varman]] regularly grant land, cows etc. to Brahmins and issue copper plate seals mentioning the same.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation| surname= Vasu | given= Nagendranath | title= The Social History of Kamarupa }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Utkala Brahmins (Orissa)===
* [[Utkala Brahmin]]
The Sanskrit text Brāhmaṇotpatti-Mārtaṇḍa by Pt. Harikrishna Śāstri mentions that a king named Utkala invited Brahmins from the Gangetic Valley to perform a [[yajna]] in Jagannath-Puri in [[Orissa]]. When the yajna ended, these Brahmins laid the foundation of Lord Jagannath there and settled around [[Orissa]], [[Jharkhand]] and [[Medinipur]]. The Utkala Brahmins are of three classes 1) Shrautiya (vaidika), 2) Sevayata and 3) Halua Brahmins.

===Maithil Brahmins (Mithila)===
* [[Maithil Brahmin]]s
Maithil Brāhamaṇas, are a group of Brahmins typically originating from and living in and around [[Mithila (India)|Mithila]], which is part of North Bihar. They are a community of highly cohesive, traditional Brahmins who strive to follow rites and rituals according to ancient Hindu canons.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} They have a reputation for orthodoxy and interest in learning.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} A large number of Maithil Brahmins migrated a few centuries ago to adjoining areas of South-east Bihar and Jharkhand, as well as to adjoining Terai regions of Nepal. Most of the Maithil Brahmins are Śāktas (worshippers of Śakti) . [[Maithili language|Maithili]] is their mother tongue, though many use [[Angika language|Angika]] (a south-eastern dialect of Maithili) as their mother tongue.

===Nepali Brahmin===

See [[Brahmin#Nepal 2|Nepal]].

===Kashmiri Pandits===
[[File:Kashmir-hindu-priests.jpg|thumb|right|Three Hindu priests writing religious texts. 1890s, Jammu and Kashmir.]]
* [[Kashmiri Pandits]]

==Pancha-Dravida==
कर्णाटकाश्च तैलंगा द्राविडा महाराष्ट्रकाः, गुर्जराश्चेति पञ्चैव द्राविडा विन्ध्यदक्षिणे || (Karnatakaashcha Telangaa Dravidaa Maharashtrakaaha, Gurjarashcheti panchauva dravidaa vindhyadakshine) &lt;br /&gt;
Brahmins who live in south of Vidhya mountains are called Pancha-Dravida Brahmins and they are divided in to following groups.
* Karnataka
* Telugu
* Dravida (Tamil Nadu)
* Maharashtra
* Gujarat

===Andhra Pradesh===
Brahmins of Andhra Pradesh known as [[Telugu Brahmins]] are broadly classified into four groups: [[Vaidiki Brahmins]], [[Niyogi]], [[Aaraama Dravidulu|Dravida Brahmins]], and [[Vaikhanasas|Vaikhānasa]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vedah.net/manasanskriti/Brahmins.html#Brahmins_of_Andhra_Pradesh Article on Brahmins of Andhra Pradesh at Vepachedu Educational Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Vaidiki Brahmins]] are further divided into the following sub-categories: Dravidlu (Aadi Shaivulu, Shaivulu), Vaidiki Velanadu, Vaidiki Venginadu, Vaidiki Kosalanadu or Kasalnadu, Vaidiki Mulakanadu, Vaidiki Murikinadu, Vaidiki Telaganya (Originated from Telangana but might have migrated to other regions).{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}

[[Niyogi]]s are further divided into the following subcategories: Nandavarika Niyogi, Prathama Shakha Niyogi, Aaru Vela Niyogulu, Golkonda Vyapari, Karanaalu, Sistukaranalu, Karana kamma vyaparlu, Karanakammulu.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vedah.net/manasanskriti/Brahmins.html&lt;/ref&gt;
Each Rishi's name is mentioned in the Yajurveda (4.3.3).
Sanaga (Son of Manu (Shiva))
Sanatana (Son of Maya (Vishnu))
Abhuvana (Son of Tvashta (Brahma of four faces))
Pratanan (Son of Shilpi (Indra))
Another sub-section, known as [[Dravidulu|Dravida Brahmins]], is made up of a group of Saraswat Brahmins who migrated to Andhra Pradesh from Tamil Nadu.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} They had originally migrated to Tamil Nadu from Saurashtra. Islamic invasions affected this group by forcing its slow migration from Kashmir to Andhra Pradesh via Gujarat and Tamil Nadu.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} As a result of their migration from Tamil Nadu, this group of Brahmins is known as Dravida Brahmins or [[Aaraama Dravidulu|Dravidlu]]. They remain with the Vedic traditions.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} This sect is also related to the [[Vadama]] Brahmins.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

===Gujarat===
Gurjara Brāhmans refer to the Brahmins of Gujarāt, and are subdivided into many groups and subcastes. Many of them have origins in Rajasthan. Some of the sub-categories are:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brahmsamaj.org Bardai Brahmins]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Girinarayan Brahmin]], Shrigod Brahmin, [[Sachora Brahmin]], [[Anavil Brahmin]], [[Sidhra-Rudhra Brahmins]], Prashnora Brahmins, [[Vadadra Brahmin]], [[Sree gauda Brahmin]], [[Trivedi Mewada Brahmin]], [[Palival Brahmin (Dasha and visha)]], [[Modh|Modh Brahmin]], Tapodhan Brahmin, [http://www.brahmsamaj.org/?p=311 Audichya Brahmin], [[Sahastra Audichya Gorwal Brahmin]], [[Nagar Brahmin]], [http://www.brahmsamaj.org/?p=128 Pushkarna Brahmin], [[Saurashtra Bhatt Mewada Brahmin]], [[Saurashtra Trivedi Mewad Brahmin]], [[Chauriyasi Mewada Brahmin]], [http://www.brahmsamaj.org/?p=206 Rajgor Brahmin] (Gujarat Origin), [[Khedaval|Bajkhedawal Brahmins]] (origin [[Kheda]] in central Gujarat or Khedbrahma in north Gujarat), [[Jangid Brahmin]], [[Rajgor Brahmin]], [[Bhattmewada Brahmins|Bhatt Mewada Brahmin]], [[Shrimali Brahmins]] and Chvyan Brahmin (or bharah gaon Brahmin), [[Adhyagoud Brahmins]] (Rajasthan origin) and [[Jaiswal Brahmin]] (North-Indian origin),Rayakwad Brahmin(Kubabthal region)

Kanaujiya or Kanyakumbj Brahmins migrated from [[Kanauj]] and entered the [[Kutch]] area via [[Sindh]] along with the [[lohana]]s.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} They are divided into the categories bhuvdiyas, vondhiyas and sandhliyas, according to their village temple. Others in Gujarat are mainly found in Jamnagar, Morbi, Junaghath and Rajkot. Surnames like Bhatt, Kaileyas, Bhaglani, Pingal, Lakhlani, Ghediya etc. are common among them.

===Maharashtra===
They include the following : [[Goud Saraswat Brahmin]]s, [[Chitpavan|Chitpavan Brahmin]]s (Konkanastha), [[Daivadnya Brahmin]]s, [[Deshastha Brahmin]]s, [[Karhade Brahmin]]s and [[Devrukhe|Devrukhe Brahmins]].

===Karnataka===
Kannada Brāhmans(ಕನ್ನಡ ಬ್ರಾಹ್ಮಣ): The Brāhmans of the Carnatic, or the Canarese country. The Canarese area comprises Mysore State, and the British Districts of Canara, Dharwar and Belgaum.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;The Tribes and Castes of the Central Provinces of India By R.V. Russell&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Kannada Brahmins]] :{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}
These are further subdivided into the following castes : [[Babbur Kamme]] Brahmins, Badaganadu Brahmins, [[Deshastha Brahmin]], [[Hale naadu Karnataka Brahmins]], [[Havyaka Brahmin]], [[Hasan Iyengars]], [[Hebbar Iyengars]], [[Hoysala Karnataka]] Brahmins, [[Jangam]] Brahmins, [[Karhade Brahmin]], [[Koota Brahmins]], [[Madhva Brahmins]], [[Mandyam Iyengars]], [[Mysore Iyengars]], [[Vishwabrahmin]], [[Niyogi|Niyogi Brahmins]], [[Panchagrama Brahmins]], [[Sankethi people|Sankethi Brahmins]], [[Sattada vaishnava Brahmins]], [[Shukla Yajurveda]] Brahmins, [[Smartha Brahmins]], [[Srivaishnava Brahmins]], [[Sthanika Brahmins]], [[Ulucha Kamme]] Brahmins
*[[Mysore Iyers]]
*[[Ashtagrama Iyer]]
*[[Tuluva Brahmins]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boloji.com/places/0019.htm The Tale of Tuluva Brahmins]&lt;/ref&gt; which consist of [[Kandavara Brahmins]], [[Karhade Brahmin]]s, [[Padia Brahmins]], [[Saklapuri Brahmins]], [[Shivalli Brahmins]], [[Smartha Shivalli Brahmins]], [[Sthanika Brahmins]], Padarthi Brahmins

===Tamil Nadu===
*[[Iyer]] (sub-divided further into [[Vadama]], [[Vathima]], [[Brahacharanam]], [[Ashtasahasram]], [[Sholiyar]], [[Dikshitar]], Kaniyalar, Prathamasaki)
*[[Iyengar]] (sub-divided into [[Vadakalai]] and [[Thenkalai]])

===Kerala===

Kerala Brahmins include the following categories of Brahmins: [[Namboothiri Brahmin]], [[Shivalli Tulu Brahmins of Kerala|Embranthiri]], [[Pushpaka Brahmin]] (subdivided into [[Nambissan]]s and [[Unni]]s), Sharada Brahmins, [[Vishwabrahmins]]

==Gotras and pravaras==
{{See also|Classification of Brahmins}}
Brahmins classify themselves on the basis of their [[patrilineal]] descent from a notable ancestor.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}  These ancestors are either ancient Indian sages or [[kshatriyas]] (warriors), who chose to become Brahmins.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}  The major gotras that trace descent from sages are: [[Shri Vatsya]], [[Kanva]], [[Jamadagni]], [[Bhrigu]], [[Bharadvâja]], [[Kaundinya]], [[Gautama Maharishi]], [[Sandilya]], [[Bhrigu]], [[Vashista]], [[Parāshara]], [[Atryasa]], [[Harithasa]], [[Kashyapa]], and [[Agastya]] gotra.  Other gotras are [[Mitra]], [[Vishvamitra]] and [[Chaurasia]] gotra.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

In general, [[gotra]] denotes any person who traces descent in an unbroken male line from a common male ancestor. Pāṇini defines gotra for grammatical purposes as 'apatyam pautraprabhrti gotram' (IV. 1. 162), which means: &quot;the word gotra denotes the progeny (of a sage) beginning with the son's son&quot;. When a person says, &quot;I am Kashypasa-gotra&quot;, he means that he traces his descent from the ancient sage Kashyapa by unbroken male descent. This enumeration of eight primary gotras seems to have been known to [[Pāṇini]]. These gotras are not directly connected to Prajapathy or latter brama.{{Clarify|date=May 2012}} The offspring (apatya) of these Eight are gotras; and others than these are called 'gotrâvayava'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vedah.net/manasanskriti/Brahmins.html#Brahmin_Sages_and_Branches Article on Gotras of Brahmins at Vepachedu Educational Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Provide Vepachedu's Sources&lt;/sup&gt;{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

The gotras are divided into three tiers of ganas, then into pakshas, and finally into individual gotras. According to the Âsvalâyana-srautasûtra, there are four subdivisions of the Vashista gana, viz. [[Upamanyu]], [[Parāshara]], [[Kundina]] and [[Vashista]] (other than the first three). The first has survived in the [[Bhrigu]] and [[Angiras (sage)|Āngirasa]] gana. According to Baudh, the principal eight gotras were divided into pakshas. The pravara of Upamanyu is [[Vashista]], Bharadvasu, Indrapramada; the pravara of the Parâshara gotra is [[Vashista]], Shâktya, Pârâsharya; the pravara of the Kundina gotra is Vashista, Maitrâvaruna, Kaundinya and the pravara of Vashistas other than these three is simply Vashista. Therefore some define pravara as the group of sages that distinguishes the founder (lit. the starter) of one gotra from another.

There are two kinds of pravaras, 'sishya-prasishya-rishi-parampara' and 'putrparampara'. Gotrapravaras can be ekarsheya, dwarsheya, triarsheya, pancharsheya, saptarsheya, and up to 19 rishis. Kashyapasa gotra has at least two distinct pravaras in Andhra Pradesh: one with three sages (triarsheya pravara) and the other with seven sages (saptarsheya pravara). This pravara may be either sishya-prasishya-rishi-parampara or putraparampara. Similarly, Srivatsasa gotra has five sages or is called Pancharsheya and are the descendants of Jamadagni. For a sishya-prasishya-rishi-parampara marriage it is not acceptable if half, or more than half, of the rishis are the same in both bride and bridegroom gotras. If it is putraparampara, a marriage is totally unacceptable even if one rishi matches.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vedah.net/manasanskriti/Brahmins.html Article on Gotras and pravaras of Brahmins at Vepachedu Educational Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Provide Vepachedu's Sources-&lt;/sup&gt;{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

==Sects and Rishis==
Due to the diversity in religious and cultural traditions and practices, and the [[Vedic]] schools to which they belong, [[Brahmins]] are further divided into various subcastes. During the sutra period, roughly between 1000 BCE to 200 BCE, Brahmins became divided into various [[Shakha]]s (branches), based on the adoption of different Vedas and different rescension Vedas. Sects for different denominations of the same branch of the Vedas were formed, under the leadership of distinguished teachers among the Brahmins.

There are several Brahmin law givers, such as [[Angiras (sage)|Angiras]], [[Apasthambha]], [[Atri]], [[Bhrigu]], [[Brihaspati]], [[Boudhayana]], [[Daksha]], [[Gautama (Hindu sage)|Gautama]], [[Harita]], [[Katyayana]], [[Likhita]], [[Manu (Hinduism)|Manu]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/manu/manu02.htm Manu Smriti on learning of the Vedas]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Parasara]], [[Samvarta]], [[Shankha]], [[Shatatapa]], [[Ushanasa]], [[Vashista]], [[Vishnu]], [[Vyasa]], [[Yajnavalkya]], and [[Yama (Hinduism)|Yama]]. These twenty-one rishis were the propounders of the [[Smriti]]s. The oldest among these smritis are Apastamba, Baudhayana, Gautama, and Vashista [[Sūtra|Sutras]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vedah.net/manasanskriti/Brahmins.html#Brahmin_Sages_and_Branches Article on various sects and rishis of Brahmins at Vepachedu Educational Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Provide Vepachedu's Sources&lt;/sup&gt;{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

===Descendants of the Brahmins===
Many [[India]]ns and non-Indians claim descent from the Vedic Rishis of both Brahmin and non-Brahmin descent.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} For example, the [[Dasharna]] and [[Naga people|Nagas]] are said to be the descendants of [[Kashyapa|Kashyapa Muni]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} The descent of Brahmins is generally indicated by the gotra, which refers to his patrilineage. It is indicated by the name of the 'great sage' to whose descent the Brahmin is said to belong.

The [[Vishwakarmas]] are the descendants of Pancha Rishis or Brahmarishies. According to [[Yajurveda]] and [[Brahmanda purana]], they are Sanaka, Sanatana, Abhuvanasa, Prajnasa, and Suparnasa.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

The [[Panchal]] movement to reclaim Brahminical rights claimed that the Panchals have Brahminic culture, or sacraments, and perform their ceremonies according to Vedic Rituals.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

The [[Kani (tribe)|Kani]] tribe of [[South India]] claim to descend from [[Agastyar|Agastya Muni]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

The Gondhali, Kanet, Bhot, Lohar, Dagi, and Hessis claim to be from [[Renuka|Renuka Devi]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

The Kasi Kapadi Sudras claim to originate from the Brahmin Sukradeva. Their duty was to transfer water to the sacred city of [[Varanasi|Kashi]].&lt;ref&gt;Bhanu, B. V., ''People of India'', p. 948.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Padmashalis claim they came from the Maharishi [[Markandeya]], who wrote the Markandeya Purana.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

The Saini (gardener) community claim in one of their stories that they descended from a Brahmin and call themselves Parpadh Brahman, which in course of time became Phulmali.&lt;ref&gt;P. 845, People of India: Rajasthan edited by K. S. Singh&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Dadheech Brahmins]]/dayama Brahmin trace their roots from [[Dadhichi|Dadhichi Rishi]]. Many [[Jat]] clans claim to descend from [[Dadhichi|Dadhichi Rishi]] while the [[Dudi|Dudi Jats]] claim to be in the lineage of Duda Rishi.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

[[Lord Buddha]] was a descendant of [[Angiras (sage)|Angiras]]a through [[Gautama (Hindu sage)|Gautama]]. There were [[Kshatriyas]] of other clans whose members descend from [[Angiras (sage)|Angiras]]a, to fulfill a childless king's wish.&lt;ref&gt;''Classical Dictionary of Hindu Mythology and Religion, Geography, History and Literature'', by John Dowson, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

The (so-called) backward caste [[Matang]]s claim to descend from [[Matang Muni]], who became a Brahmin through his [[karma]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

According to one legend, the nomadic tribe of [[Kerala]], the Kakkarissi, were descendants of a Brahmin who came out of the mouth of [[Garuda]], the vehicle of [[Lord Vishnu]].{{citation needed|date=March 2012}}

The [[Roman Catholic Brahmin]] caste among the [[Goan Catholics]] and [[Mangalorean Catholics]] are descended from [[Konkani Brahmins]] who converted to Roman Catholicism during the [[Portuguese India|Portuguese colonial rule]] in [[Goa]].

===Claimants of Brahmin Status===
In Andhra Pradesh the Panchanamvaru, the artisan caste of five groups (goldsmith, carpenters, blacksmiths, brasiers and stone-cutters)
claim to descend from Vishwakarma and his five sons (Manu, Maya, Silpa, Tvastra and Daivagna), and claim to be Vishwa-Brahmin.&lt;ref&gt;P. 165 ''Encyclopaedia of India, Volume 27'' by Pran Nath Chopra&lt;/ref&gt; The Vipravinodins also claim the status.&lt;ref&gt;P. 104, ''Proceedings... annual conference, Issue 16'' by National Center for the Study of Collective Bargaining in Higher Education and the Professions, Baruch College, CUNY, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

In Bengal (West Bengal State and Bangladesh) the [[Namasudras]], now named as Namasudra (Namassej) also claimed Brahmin status. It is claimed {{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} that King Ballal Sen expelled them from society and declared them as out-castes. A Vyavastha &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/81487552/Namasudra-VYAVASTHA-page-1-PARTIAL-REMOVAL-OF-HATRED-TAGGING|title=Vyabastha}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/81485522/Namasudra-VYAVASTHA-Page-2|title=Vyabastha2nd p}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/81485900/Namasudra-VYAVASTHA-page-3|title=Vyabastha-Signatories}}&lt;/ref&gt; was signed in 1901 by forty odd Brahmin pundits, headed by Chief Brahmin pundit (Nabadwip) of Bengal. This is supported by Dr. Nihar Ray in &quot;The History Of Bengali People , Ancient Period&quot;, published in &quot;Desh&quot;, The Famous Bengali Literary Magazine in 1951, and included in the special issue of &quot;Articles of One Century&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ray 1994&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=History of the Bengali People: Ancient Period |first=Niharranjan |last=Ray |publisher=Orient Longman |year=1994 |isbn=978-0-86311-378-9 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=sEBuAAAAMAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is claimed that the 1931 census of India shows that the two states of the Ganga River Valley basin, Uttar Pradesh and Bihar, had a 10% Brahmin population and adjacent Orissa also had a 10% population, but Bengal had exactly half, 5%. Dr. N.R. Ray mentions in his book that Namasudra (Namassejas) are the Lost Tribe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ray 1994&quot;/&gt;

In Gujarat, the [[Brahmbhatt]]s, [[Brahmakshatriya]]s, [[Panchal]]s, and [[Shrimali Soni]]s claim Brahmin status.

In Haryana, the [[Tyagi|Tagas]] claim to be a Brahmins who had abandoned the priestly profession and taken to agriculture.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

In Karnataka, the Sthanika Brahmins claim to be Saiva Brahmins.&lt;ref&gt;P, 1343 ''People of India: Volume 27, Part 3'' by Kumar Suresh Singh, Anthropological Survey of India&lt;/ref&gt;

In Punjab, the Misari of the Multan Langrials claim descent from Brahmins of Bikanir.&lt;ref&gt;P. 130 The Pakistan gazetteer, Volume 3 By Cosmo Publications (Firm)&lt;/ref&gt; Both the [[Langrial clan|Langrail]] and Golia claim that they were Brahmin Charans.&lt;ref&gt;P. 368 ''A glossary of the tribes and castes of the Punjab and North-West frontier'' By H.A. Rose&lt;/ref&gt;

In Uttar Pradesh the Oudh [[Belwar]] also claim descent from the [[Sanadhya Brahmin]] caste.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

 
[[File:The Reciting Brahman.jpg|thumb|The Reciting Brahman Illustration from Sougandhika Parinaya, 19th Century]]
Even in the time of the Buddha there were a few Brahmins who took up laboring professions. For example, Subhadra, the loast convert of the Buddha, and a Brahmin by caste was a barber by profession in Atuma village.&lt;ref&gt;P. 95 ''Buddha: His Life, His Teachings, His Order:
Together with the History of the Buddhism'' by Manmatha Nath Dutt, Society for the Resuscitation of Indian Literature&lt;/ref&gt;

Brahmins have taken on many professions&amp;nbsp;– from being priests, ascetics and scholars to warriors and business people, as is attested for example in Kalhana's Rajatarangini.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} Brahmins with the qualities of Kshatriyas are known as '[[Brahmakshatriya]]s'.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} An example mentioned in mythology is the sage [[Parashurama]] who is considered an [[avatar]] of Vishnu. Sage Parashurama is portrayed as a powerful warrior who defeated the Haiheya kshatriyas twenty one times, was an expert in the use of weapons, and trained others to fight without weapons. He is said to have established the [[Bhumihar| Bhumihar Brahmin]]s as landowners once he destroyed the Kshatriya race.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crooke 1999 1809 at page 64&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
| first = William
| last = Crooke
| authorlink = William Crooke
| title = The Tribes and Castes of the North-Western Provinces and Oudh
| publisher=[[Asian Educational Services]]
| location = 6A, Shahpur Jat, New Delhi-110049, India
| year =1999
| pages =1809 (at page 64)
| isbn = 81-206-1210-8
}}&lt;/ref&gt; These Brahmins, after having mostly abandoned their priestly functions (although some still perform), took to land-owning (Zamindar) as a profession.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crooke 1999 1809 at page 64&quot;/&gt;

Brahmin sects that have taken up the profession of medicine include the Vaidya (or Baidya) Brahmins of [[Bengal]], with surnames Gupta, Dasgupta and Senguptas.&lt;ref&gt;http://saraswatdirectory.com/saraswat6.php&lt;/ref&gt; They are considered descendants of [[Dhanvantari]], the Hindu god of medicine and father of [[Ayurveda]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

Kshatriya Brahmin &lt;ref&gt;P. 29, ''Cultural History from the Matsyapurāṇa'', by Sureshachandra Govindlal Kantawala&lt;/ref&gt; and Brahma-kshatriya &lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot;&gt;P. 201, ''Professor A.L. Basham, My Guruji and Problems and Perspectives of Ancient'', by Sachindra Kumar Maity&lt;/ref&gt; are terms associated with people of both the Brahmin and Kshatriya caste components. 

===Brahmin Kings===

Among the Royal Rajput households, Brahmins who became the personal teachers and protectors of the royal princes rose to the status of [[Rajpurohit]] and taught the princes everything, including martial arts.

They would also become the keepers of the Royal lineage and its history. They would also be the protectors of the throne in case the regent was orphaned and a minor. The well-known Brahmin [[Chanakya]] was a Rajpurohit for [[Chandragupta Maurya]], founder of the Mauryan empire, who helped Chandragupta get a grip on the well-established Nanda Empire and prevent [[Alexander the Great]] from invading India. The [[Pallava]] kings also claimed to be Brahmakshatriyas.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} [[Jayavarman I|King Jayavarma I]] of [[Kambuja]] (Kampuchea) of 781 A.D. was a Brahma-kshatriya.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot; /&gt; [[Lalitaditya|King Lalitaditya Muktapida]] of [[Kashmir]] ruled all of India and even Central Asia.

King Rudravarma of [[Champa|Champa (Vietnam)]] of 657 A.D. was the son of a Brahmin father.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot; /&gt;

Medieval king [[Samrat Hem Chandra Vikramaditya]] or [[Hemu]], born into a family of Purohits, started the manufacture of cannons for the first time in North India in 1540s, with Portuguese know-how and dealt in gunpowder supplies to [[Sher Shah Suri]]'s army. Later he became Prime Minister and Chief of Army of the Suris and Emperor of North India in 1556, defeating Akbar's army at [[Agra]] and [[Battle for Delhi]] at Tughlakabad Fort in Delhi.&lt;ref&gt;Page on Samrat Hem Chandra Vikramaditya on wikipedia&lt;/ref&gt;

Brahmins with the qualities of a [[Vaisya]] or merchant are known as 'Brahmvyasya'.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} An example of such persons are people of the Ambastha&lt;ref&gt;P. 37 ''Asian Medical Systems: A Comparative Study'' By Charles Leslie&lt;/ref&gt; caste, which exist in South India.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} They perform medical work, and claim that from ancient times they have practised [[Ayurveda]] and have been [[Vaidya]]s (or doctors).{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} During British rule, when the government desired to promote caste mobility, they started bearing the [[Yagnopaveetham|sacred thread]] also, but neither the government nor the Hindu oligarchs supported any such sanction {{Disambiguation needed|date=March 2012}}.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

==Sampradayas==
The three [[sampradaya]]s (sects) of Brahmins, mostly in [[South India]] are the [[Smartism|Smarta sampradaya]], the [[Srivaishnavism|Srivaishnava sampradaya]] and the [[Madhvacharya|Madhva sampradaya]].

===Smartism===
''[[Smartism]]''  (or Smarta [[Sampradaya]], ''Smarta Tradition'', as it is termed in [[Sanskrit]]) is a liberal or nonsectarian [[religious denomination|denomination]] of the [[Hinduism|Hindu]] religion.  This tradition is based on the Advaithic teachings of Adi Sankaracharya.  He united various sects of Hinduism under on umbrella by accepting all the major Hindu deities as forms of the one [[Brahman]].  He implored the Smarthas to have an Ishta devatha in the form of Siva, Sakthi, Vishnu, Ganesha,  Murugan (Subrahmanya) or Sun.  The term Smarta refers to adherents who follow the [[Vedas]] and [[Shastras]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

===Vaishnavism===
One form of Vaishnavism is Madhwa (Dwaita Sampradaya), and the other is Sri Vaishnava ([[Vishishtadvaita]] sampradaya).
Madhwa Brahmins are mainly located in the Carnatic plains and some of them are seen in Andhra, Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu and Kerala. They follow the teachings of Sri [[Madhvacharya]], who was born in South Canara district of Karnataka in the 12th Century. He preached [[Dvaita]], which says that God and atma (soul) are different entities, which is contradictory to the teachings of [[Adi Shankara|Sri Adi Sankaracharya]], who preached [[Advaita vedanta]] (non-duality). In South India, Sri Vaishnava sampradayam was propagated by Srimad [[Ramanujacharya]].

===Shaivism===

[[Shaivism]] (sometimes called ''Shivaism'') is a belief system where [[Lord Shiva]] is worshipped as the Supreme Lord. It is a derivative faith of the core Vedic tradition.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} [[Saiva]] sects contains many subsects, such as Asdisaivas, Rudrasaivas, Veerasiavas, Paramasaivas, etc. [[Ravana]], the ruler of [[Lanka]] in the Hindu epic [[Ramayana]], was a staunch Siva devotee, who was the grandson of creator Brahma.

===Buddhism===
{{See also|Buddhist Brahmins}}

Brahmins(caste) were treated as equals to all the rest, in the eyes of the Buddha and there are countless references to Brahmins throughout the Buddhist scriptures also.Buddha rejected the notion of gradation along caste lines and of the legitimacy of the higher social status,as well as the notion of ritual purity as claimed by the Brahmins compared to others&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=27th Sutta of Digha Nikaya|url=http://www.columbia.edu/itc/religion/f2001/edit/docs/aggannasutta.pdf|work=Digha Nikaya|publisher=columbia university}}&lt;/ref&gt; . Many of the major Buddhist followers  and teachers were from Brahmins. They include [[Sariputra]], [[Maudgalyayana]], [[Mahakashyapa]], [[Nagarjuna]], [[Asvaghosha]], [[Padmasambhava]], [[Shantarakshita]], [[Nagasena]], [[Kumarajiva]] and [[Shantideva]], all of whom were referred by their titles devoid of their caste as Arahats etc. The word Brahmin, meaning &quot;priest class&quot;, was redefined by the Buddha and it continued to be used alongside [[Arahat]] in their relevant contexts.&lt;ref name=Buddhanet&gt;{{cite web|title=verse 385;verse 386|url=http://www.buddhanet.net/dhammapada/d_brahmi.htm|work=Dhammapada|publisher=Buddhanet}}&lt;/ref&gt; Max Muller points out that in the Dhamapada, Buddha etymologizes the word &quot;Bahama&quot;, the Prakrit form of &quot;Brahmana&quot;, by playing off the Sanskrit/Prakrit etymon -bra.

In the [[Digha Nikaya|Ambattha Sutra]], we find the Buddha debated many Brahmins who were clearly not Arahats. Also in many important [[dharanis]], Brahmins are mentioned in an entirely different capacity from Arahats, and therefore there is a marked difference depending on the context. The Buddha insisted that Brahmins had to live up to seek the truth ,hence reach liberation(Nirvana) through the Dhamma, and this could not be by ascriptive factor of birth alone. In the [[Dhammapada]], the Buddha mentions Brahmins and Arahats in very different capacities and dedicates an entire chapter to what it means to be a real Brahmin called the Brahmana-vagga as well.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buddhanet.net/dhammapada/d_brahmi.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The Buddha did not believe in caste discrimination but he did endorse a fair division of labour based on merit and equality, while condemning pathological division of labour through slavery , forced labour ,superstition etc. According to him, Brahmins were not to discriminate against lower castes and those of their own who joined the sangha, through the notion of purity and superior social status ,which according to the buddha was false.&lt;ref name=Buddhanet&gt;{{cite web|title=verse 385;verse 386|url=http://www.buddhanet.net/dhammapada/d_brahmi.htm|work=Dhammapada|publisher=Buddhanet}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=27th Sutta of Digha Nikaya|url=http://www.columbia.edu/itc/religion/f2001/edit/docs/aggannasutta.pdf|work=Digha Nikaya|publisher=columbia university}}&lt;/ref&gt;but were to serve them wholeheartedly. Many sutras indicate that the Buddha himself was a Brahmin in a previous life and, due to his good merit as in the previous lives, was reborn as the Buddha.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jatakaonline.com/jataka-tales/0011-the-first-prophecy&lt;/ref&gt; 

The notion of ritual purity provided a conceptual foundation for the caste system, by identifying occupations and duties associated with impure or taboo objects as being themselves impure. Regulations imposing such a system of ritual purity and taboos are absent from the Buddhist monastic code, and not generally regarded as being part of Buddhist teachings&lt;ref&gt;{{Harv|Robinson|Johnson|Thanissaro|2005|p=51}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the contrary, the early Buddhist scriptures defined purity as determined by one's state of mind, and refer to anyone who behaves unethically, of whatever caste, as &quot;rotting within&quot;, or &quot;a rubbish heap of impurity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sue Hamilton, ''Early Buddhism: A New Approach: The I of the Beholder.'' Routledge 2000, pages 47, 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

There are many places in which the Buddha explains his use of the word ''brahman''. At [[Sutta Nipata]] 1.7, ''Vasala Sutta'', verse 12, he states: &quot;Not by birth is one an outcast; not by birth is one a brahman. By deed one becomes an outcast, by deed one becomes a brahman.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/kn/snp/snp.1.07.piya.html Translation by Piyadassi Thera]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jainism===
* The first convert of [[Mahavira]], the 24th [[Tirthankara]] of [[Jainism]] was [[Indrabhuti]] (aka Gautamswami) the Brahmin, who headed a group of other Brahmins and converted them to [[Jainism]]. He was from the village Gobbar (also called Govarya) near [[Rajgriha]]. It is said that the Tapsas, who were competing with Gautama to reach the top of a hill, achieved moksha by seeing Gautama win.&lt;ref&gt;P.21 ''Jaina-rūpa-maṇḍana =: Jaina Iconography'' By Umakant Premanand Shah&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sajjambhava was another born from Rajgriha and was elected the head of the Jain temple. He is famous for his composition of the &quot;Dasavaikalika Sutra.&quot;
* Acharya Vidyanand is a Brahmin of the Dhigambar Jain sect and compiled in the Sanskrit language, &quot;Ashta Shahastri&quot; with eight thousand verses.
* Acharya Shushil Kumar, known better to Jains as &quot;Guruji&quot;, was born a Vaidik in the Shakarpur village of the Haryana province. At the age of 15, he took Diksha (became a sanyassin) into the Sthanakvasi, a Swhetambara sub-sect.
* Reputedly a wealthy Brahmin named Dhangiri, in the town of Tumbhivan, lost his interest in wealth and decided to take Diksha, after hearing the sermons of the Jain Acharya Sinhgiri.
* Umasvati was a composer who was so loved by Jains that he is considered by the Dhigambar sect to be a Dhigambar member and the Svetambara sect to be a Svetambara member.
*Akalanka of the 8th century is said to the pioneer in the field of Jain logic.&lt;ref&gt;P. 374 ''Buddhist phenomenology: a philosophical investigation of Yogācāra Buddhism'' By Dan Lusthaus&lt;/ref&gt;
* There is a Brahmin community in South Karnataka which is traditional follower of Jainism and is known as Jain Brahmin. They have a hostel for students in Mysore, known as Jain Brahmin Hostel. This community is different from the Jain priests in Jain temples.

===Miscellaneous sects===
There are additional sampradayas, which are not as widely followed:

The [[Mahima Religion|Mahima Dharma]] or [[Satya mahima dharma|&quot;Satya Mahima Alekha Dharma&quot;]] was founded by the Brahmin Mukunda Das of present-day Orissa, popularly known by followers as Mahima Swami according to the ''Bhima Bhoi'' text.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;[http://www.orissa.gov.in/e-magazine/Orissareview/may2005/engpdf/mahima_dharma_bhima_bhoi_biswanathbaba.pdf &quot;Mahima Dharma, Bhima Bhoi and Biswanathbaba&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; He was born in the last part of the 18th century, in the former state of Baudh, a son of Ananta Mishra. He was Brahmin by caste as mentioned in Mahima Vinod of ''Bhima Bhoi'' in Vol.11. This sampradaya is similar to Vaishnavism. Although the members of this sect do not worship [[Vishnu|Lord Vishnu]] as their [[Ishta-Deva]], they believe that the [[Srimad Bhagavatam]] is sacred. The founder of this sect was a Vaishnavite before founding the new order.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt; This sampradaya was founded in the latter part of the 18th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt;

There is also the [[Avadhuta|Avadhoot Panth]], wherein [[Dattatreya|Lord Dattatreya]] and his forms such as [[Narasimha Saraswati]] and [[Sai Baba of Shirdi]] are worshiped. Lord Dattatreya is worshiped by many as the Hindu trinity&amp;nbsp;– [[Brahma]], [[Vishnu]] and [[Shiva]] in one divine entity. Many even worship Dattatreya as an [[Avatar]] of Vishnu or of [[Shiva]].

==Nepal==
[[Bahun]] is a colloquial Nepali term for a member of the Pahari or &quot;hill&quot; Brahmin (ब्राह्मण) caste, who are traditionally educators, scholars and priests of Hinduism. They are also known as Barmu in Newari. Brahmins are the second largest caste group in Nepal (31% of the population), with the Chhetri (Kshatriya) being the first (42%).{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} Brahmins were inhabitants of Nepal in prehistoric times.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} The Brahmin community is the major part of the indigenous Khas community of Nepal.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} They moved eastward along Xinjiang province of China, Western Tibet, the Himalayan foothills from Kashmir and Kumao/Garwal. They settled first in the Karnali River basin, then the Gandaki and finally the Kosi basin and into Sikkim and Bhutan.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

Some [[Jaiswal Brahmin]]s are Chaurasi Brahmins from Nepal or North India.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} There are references about Brahmins of Nepal in bansawali and purans. By tradition—and by civil law until 1962—they represented the highest of the four Hindu varna or castes.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} Bahuns from the &quot;hills&quot; have been represented disproportionately in Nepal's education system, political parties and civil service since the country was unified by Prithvi Narayan Shah and his heirs in the 18th century.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} The top leaders of the all the major parties are also Bahuns: the Maoist opposition (Pushpa Kamal Dahal and Baburam Bhattarai), the Communist Party of Nepal (Unified Marxist-Leninist) [[Jhalanath Khanal, Madhav Kumar (Nepal)]], and the Nepali Congress ([[Sushil Koirla]]).

Very often, Khas Bahuns can be identified by their middle names being Dev (देव), Nath (नाथ), Mani (मणि), Raj (राज), Prasad (प्रसाद), Devi (देवी) or Kumari (कुमारी). They never use bahadur (बहादुर) in their names because it is associated mainly with Chhetris (Kshatriya) and &quot;martial tribes&quot;.

The Brahman caste in Nepal includes numerous family names such as:
* A अ&amp;nbsp;– Acharya (आचार्य), Adhikari (अधिकारी), Arjel (अर्जेल)/Arjyal (अर्ज्याल)/Aryal (अर्याल), Awasthi (अवस्थी)
* Ā आ&amp;nbsp;– Atreya (आत्रेय),
* B ब&amp;nbsp;– Badal (बडाल), Banskota (बास्कोटा), Baral (बराल), Bastakoti (बस्ताकोटी), Bastola (बास्तोला), Basyal/Bashyal/Basel (बस्याल/ बश्याल/ बसेल)
* Bh भ&amp;nbsp;– Bhandari (भन्डारी), Bhatta (भट्ट), Bhattarai (भट्टराई), Bhetuwal (भेटुवाल), Bhurtel (भुर्तेल), Bhusal (भुसाल / भुषाल)
* Ch च&amp;nbsp;– Chalise (चालिसे), Chapagain (चापगाईँ), Chataut (चटौत), Chaulagain (चौलागाई)/चाम्लागांइ, Chiluwal (चिलुवाल)
* D द&amp;nbsp;– Dahal (दहाल), Devkota (देवकोटा)
* D ड&amp;nbsp;– Dallakoti (डल्लाकोटी), Dumre (डुम्रे)
* Dh ढ&amp;nbsp;– Dhakal (ढकाल), Dhungel (ढुंगेल), Dhital (धिताल)
* G ग&amp;nbsp;– Gajurel (गजुरेल), Gaudel (गौडेल), Gautam (गौतम), Gotame (गोतामे), Guragain/Gurangain (गुरागाईँ), Gyanwali (ज्ञवाली), Gaire (गैरे), Gauli (गौली)
* Gh घ&amp;nbsp;– Ghimire (घिमिरे)
* H ह&amp;nbsp;– Humagain (हुमगाईँ)
* J ज&amp;nbsp;– Jaisi(जैसी), Joshi (जोशी)
* K क&amp;nbsp;– Kafle (कफ्ले/काफ्ले), Kalakheti (कलाखेती), Kandel (कंडेल)/Kadel (कडेल), Koirala (कोइराला)
* Kh ख&amp;nbsp;– Khanal (खनाल), Kharel (खरेल), Khatiwada (खतिवडा)
* L&amp;nbsp;– Lamsal(लम्साल), Lekhak (लेखक), Lohani (लोहनी), Lamichhane
* M म&amp;nbsp;– Mainali (मैनाली), Maratha (मराठा), Mishra (मिश्र)
* N&amp;nbsp;– Nepal (नेपाल), Neupane (नेउपाने/न्यौपाने), Niroula (निरौला), Nyaupane (न्यौपाने)
* O ओ&amp;nbsp;– Ojha (ओझा), Oli (ऑळी)
* P प&amp;nbsp;– Prasai(n) (प्रसाईं), Parajuli(पराजुली), Pageni (पंगेनी), Pandey (पाँडे/पाण्डे), Pandit (पण्डित), Pant (पन्त), Pathak (पाठक), Pokhrel/Pokharel (पोखरेल), Paudyal (पौड्याल)/Poudyal/Paudel (पौडेल), Pudasiani (पुडासैनी), Pyakurel (प्याकुरेल), Panthi (पन्थि)
* Ph फ&amp;nbsp;– Phuyal (फुयाल)
* R र&amp;nbsp;– Regmi (रेग्मी), Rijal (रिजाल), Rimal (रिमाल), Rishal (रिशाल)
* Sh श&amp;nbsp;– Sharma (शर्मा), Shivakoti (शिवाकोटी)
* S स&amp;nbsp;– Sangraula (संग्रौला), Sapkota (सापकोटा), Satyal (सत्याल), Sedhain (सेढाई), Sigdel (सिग्देल), Simkhada (सिम्खडा),Subedi (सुवेदी),
* T त&amp;nbsp;– Timilsina (तिमल्सेना/तिमील्सिना), Tiwari (तिवारी), Tripathi (त्रिपाठी)
* Th थ&amp;nbsp;– Thapaliya (थपलिया)
* W व&amp;nbsp;– Wagle (वाग्ले)
* U उ&amp;nbsp;– Upadhyaya (उपाध्याय), Upreti/Uprety (उप्रेती)
*
The Audichya Brahmin community is connected with [[Parashurama]] (Bhargava-Gotra), and are said to have earned a good deal of confidence and respect among kings.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

==Burma (Myanmar)==
{{Burmese characters}}
&lt;!--[[File:A robed Burmese Brahmin priest of Konbaung Dynasty.jpg|thumb|Depiction of a Brahmin during the [[Konbaung dynasty]] ]] --&gt;
[[File:Manipuri astrologers and brahmins.jpg|thumb|Manipuri astrologers and Brahmins in Burma, 1900]]
Historically, Brahmins, known as ''ponna'' ({{my|ပုဏ္ဏား}}) in modern-day [[Burmese language|Burmese]], formed an influential group in Burma prior to British colonialism. Until the 1900s, ''ponna'' referred to [[overseas Indians|Indians]] who had arrived prior to colonial rule, distinct from ''kala'', Indians who arrived during British rule. During the [[Konbaung dynasty]], court Brahmins were consulted by kings before moving royal capitals, waging wars, making offerings to Buddhist sites like the [[Mahamuni Buddha]], and for astrology.&lt;ref name=&quot;leider&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Leider |first=Jacques P. |year= |title=Specialists for Ritual, Magic and Devotion: The Court Brahmins of the Konbaung Kings |journal=The Journal of Burma Studies |volume=10 |pages=159–180 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; Burmese Brahmins can be divided into four general groups, depending on their origins:
* Manipur Brahmins ({{lang-my|မုနိပူရဗြာဟ္မဏ}}): Brahmins who were sent to Burma after [[Manipur]] became a Burmese vassal state in the 1700s and ambassadors from Manipur
* Arakanese Brahmins ({{lang-my|ရခိုင်ဗြာဟ္မဏ}}): Brahmins brought to Burma from [[Rakhine State|Arakan]] after it was conquered by the Konbaung king [[Bodawpaya]]
* Sagaing Brahmins: the oldest Brahmins in Burmese society, who consulted the [[Pyu]], [[Burman]]{{disambiguation needed|date=May 2012}} and [[Mon people|Mon]] kingdoms prior to the Konbaung dynasty
* Indian Brahmins: Brahmins who arrived with British colonial rule when Burma became a part of the [[British Raj]]

According to Burmese chronicles, Brahmins in Burma were subject to the four-[[caste system]], which included brahmanas ({{my|ဗြာဟ္မဏ}}), kshatriyas ({{my|ခတ္တိယ}}), vaishya ({{my|ဝေဿ}}), and shudra ({{my|သုဒ္ဒ}}). Because the Burmese monarchy enforced the caste system for Indians, Brahmins who broke caste traditions and laws were subject to punishment. In the Arakanese kingdom, punished Brahmins often became ''kyun ponna'' ({{my|ကျွန်ပုဏ္ဏား}}), literally 'slave Brahmins', who made flower offerings to Buddha images and performed menial tasks. During the [[Konbaung dynasty]], caste was indicated by the number of ''[[salwe]]'' (threads) worn; Brahmins wore nine, while the lowest caste wore none. Brahmins are also fundamental in the Nine-God cult, called the Nine Divinities (''Phaya Ko Su'' {{my|ဘုရားကိုးစု}}) which is essentially a Burmese [[Puja (Buddhism)|puja]] (''puzaw'' in Burmese) for appeasing nine divinities, [[Buddha]] and the eight [[arhat|arahats]], or a group of nine deities, five Hindu gods and four [[Nat (spirit)|nat spirits]].&lt;ref name=&quot;leider&quot;/&gt; This practice continues to be practiced in modern-day Burma.

==Thailand==
Brahmins in Thailand are known as 'Phram' or 'Paahm' and claim ancestry to Indian Brahmins who migrated to Thailand in the 6th century AD &lt;ref&gt;P. 91 ''Thailand into the spirit world'' by Marlane Guelden&lt;/ref&gt; There are fewer Brahmins in Thailand than in Burma.

One of the theories that orthodox Brahmins of Thailand believe in is that the earth shall be destroyed by fire, and that a new Earth will be created after the destruction.&lt;ref&gt;P. 327 ''The London encyclopaedia: or Universal dictionary of science, art ..., Volume 6''&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 19th century at Bangkok all the medical practitioners were Chinese or Cochin - Chinese, while astronomy and divination was in the hands of the Brahmins.&lt;ref&gt;P. 18 ''Chambers's papers for the people, Volumes 9-10'' By William Chambers, Robert Chambers&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=Note}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* ''[[Swami Sahajanand Saraswati]] Rachnawali'' (Selected works of Swami Sahajanand Saraswati), Prakashan Sansthan, [[Delhi]], 2003.
* [[Baldev Upadhyaya]], Kashi Ki Panditya Parampara, Sharda Sansthan, [[Varanasi]], 1985.
* M.A. Sherring, Hindu Tribes and Castes as Reproduced in Benaras, [[Asian Educational Services]], New Delhi, First ed 1872, new ed 2008.
* Jogendra Nath Bhattacharya, Hindu Castes and Sects, [[Munshiram Manoharlal]], Delhi, first edition 1896, new edition 1995.
* E. A. H. Blunt, The Caste System of North India, S. Chand Publishers, 1969.
* [[Christopher Alan Bayly]], Rulers, Townsmen, and Bazaars: North Indian Society in the Age of British Expansion, 1770–1870, [[Cambridge University Press]], 1983.
* Anand A. Yang, Bazaar India: Markets, Society, and the Colonial State in Bihar, [[University of California Press]], 1999.
* Acharya [[Hazari Prasad Dwivedi]] Rachnawali, [[Rajkamal Prakashan]], [[Delhi]].
* Bibha Jha, ''Bhumihar Brahmins: A Sociological Study'', PhD thesis submitted to the [[Patna University]].
* [[M. N. Srinivas]], Social Change in Modern India, [[Orient Longman]], [[Delhi]], 1995.
* [[Mahavir Prasad Dwivedi]] essays.
* {{Cite journal
 | last =Apte
 | first =
 | author-link =
 | last2 =
 | first2 =
 | author2-link =
 | editor-last=
 | editor-first =
 | year =1965
 | title =
 | edition =Fourth Revised and Enlarged
 | volume =
 | place =New Delhi
 | publisher=Motilal Banarsidass
 | isbn =
 | ref =harv
 | postscript =&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}.
* {{Cite journal
 | last =Apte
 | first =
 | author-link =
 | last2 =
 | first2 =
 | author2-link =
 | editor-last=
 | editor-first =
 | year =1966
 | title =
 | edition =Reprint 1997
 | volume =
 | place =New Delhi
 | publisher=
 | isbn =
 | ref =harv
 | postscript =&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}.
* {{Cite journal
 | last =Macdonell
 | first =
 | author-link =
 | last2 =
 | first2 =
 | author2-link =
 | editor-last=
 | editor-first =
 | year =1924
 | title =
 | edition =1966
 | volume =
 | place =New Delhi
 | publisher=
 | isbn =
 | ref =harv
 | postscript =&lt;!--None--&gt;
 }}.
* {{Cite journal
 | last =Monier-Williams
 | first =Monier
 | author-link =
 | last2 =
 | first2 =
 | author2-link =
 | editor-last=
 | editor-first =
 | year =1899
 | title =
 | edition =
 | volume =
 | place =Delhi
 | publisher=
 | id =
 | isbn =
 | doi =
 | oclc =
 | url =
 | accessdate =
 | ref =harv
 | postscript =&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}.
* {{Cite book
 | last =
 | first =
 | author-link =
 | last2 =
 | first2 =
 | author2-link =
 | editor-last=Sontakke
 | editor-first =N. S.
 | publication-date =
 | year =1972
 | title ={{IAST|}}
 | edition =First
 | volume =
 | publication-place =Pune
 | place =
 | publisher={{IAST|}}
 | id =
 | isbn =
 | doi =
 | oclc =
 | url =
 | accessdate =
 | editor3-last=Rājvade
 | editor3-first=V. K.
 | ref =harv
 | postscript =&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}.

==External links==
* [http://brahminpatrika.blogspot.in/ Brahmin Patrika Blog]
* [http://kamakoti.org/hindudharma/part5/chap39.htm Daily duties of Brahmins]
* [http://www.hindubrahmin.com Brahmin Information Portal] at Hindubrahmin.com
* [http://www.kamat.com/kalranga/people/brahmins/list.htm List of Brahmin Castes and Sub-castes] at Kamat.com

[[Category:Social groups of India]]
[[Category:Social groups of Rajasthan]]
[[Category:Hindu communities]]
[[Category:Hindu dynasties]]
[[Category:Brahmins| ]]
[[Category:Varnas in Hinduism]]
[[Category:Hindu philosophical concepts]]
[[Category:Sanskrit words and phrases]]
[[Category:Indo-Aryan peoples]]
[[Category:Priestly castes]]

[[af:Brahmaan]]
[[ar:برهمن]]
[[bn:ব্রাহ্মণ (বর্ণ)]]
[[ca:Bramans]]
[[cs:Bráhmana]]
[[da:Brahmin]]
[[de:Brahmane]]
[[et:Braahman]]
[[es:Brahmán (casta)]]
[[eo:Brahmo]]
[[fr:Brahmane]]
[[gu:બ્રાહ્મણ]]
[[ko:브라만 (카스트)]]
[[hi:ब्राह्मण]]
[[id:Brahmana]]
[[is:Brahmani]]
[[it:Brahmano]]
[[ka:ბრაჰმანი (ვარნა)]]
[[kk:Брахманизм]]
[[lt:Brahmanai]]
[[hu:Bráhmin]]
[[ml:ബ്രാഹ്മണർ]]
[[mr:ब्राह्मण (वर्ण)]]
[[nl:Brahmaan]]
[[new:ब्राह्मण]]
[[ja:バラモン]]
[[or:ବ୍ରାହ୍ମଣ]]
[[pnb:برہمن]]
[[pl:Bramin]]
[[pt:Brâmane]]
[[ru:Брахманы]]
[[sa:ब्राह्मणः]]
[[simple:Brahmin]]
[[sr:Брамани]]
[[sh:Brahmani]]
[[fi:Bramiini]]
[[sv:Brahmin]]
[[te:బ్రాహ్మణులు]]
[[th:พราหมณ์]]
[[uk:Брагмани]]
[[ur:برہمن]]
[[vi:Bà-la-môn]]
[[zh:婆罗门]]</text>
      <sha1>t86kbnhx7qsye0zgw1jsea5njschsar</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
