<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Canadian Unitarian Council</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7663</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515235619</id>
      <parentid>497440752</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-30T00:57:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>206.116.217.83</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Sources */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10225">{{distinguish|United Church of Canada}}
{{Infobox Organization
|name= Canadian Unitarian Council
|image= Canadian Unitarian Council logo.svg
|size=
|caption= The official logo of the CUC, based upon the [[flaming chalice]] motif and featuring a [[maple leaf]].
|abbreviation = CUC
|formation= May 14, 1961
|extinction=
|type= [[religious organization]]
|purpose= To serve Unitarian Universalist congregations and individuals in [[Canada]]
|headquarters = [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]], Canada
|location= Canada
|leader_title= Executive Director
|leader_name= Vyda Ng (interim)&lt;ref&gt;http://cuc.ca/vyda-ng-chosen-as-cuc-interim-executive-director/&lt;/ref&gt;
|affiliations = [[International Council of Unitarians and Universalists]]
|membership= 5,150&lt;ref&gt;http://cuc.ca/archive/whos_who//Admin/phil/InfoTopics2008February.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
|language=
|key_people=
|num_staff=
|budget=
|website= [http://www.cuc.ca www.cuc.ca]
}}

The '''Canadian Unitarian Council''' (CUC) is the national body for [[Unitarian Universalist]]s in [[Canada]].

The CUC is a member of the [[International Council of Unitarians and Universalists]].

== Principles and sources ==
''&quot;The Principles and Sources of Our Religious Faith&quot;'' from the Canadian Unitarian Council &lt;ref&gt;http://cuc.ca/principles-and-sources/ Principles and Sources&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Principles ===
We, the member [[wikt:congregation|congregations]] of the Canadian Unitarian Council, covenant to affirm and promote:
* the inherent worth and dignity of every person;
* justice, equity, and compassion in human relations;
* acceptance of one another and encouragement to spiritual growth in our congregations;
* a free and responsible search for truth and meaning;
* the right of conscience and the use of the democratic process within our congregations and in society at large;
* the goal of world community with peace, liberty, and justice for all;
* respect for the interdependent web of all existence of which we are a part.

=== Sources ===
The living tradition which we share draws from many sources:
* direct experience of that transcending mystery and wonder, affirmed in all cultures, which moves us to a renewal of the spirit and an openness to the forces which create and uphold life;
* words and deeds of prophetic women and men which challenge us to confront powers and structures of evil with justice, compassion, and the transforming power of love;
* wisdom from the world's religions which inspires us in our [[ethical]] and spiritual life;
* Jewish and Christian teachings which call us to respond to God's love by loving our neighbours as ourselves;
* Humanist teachings which counsel us to heed the guidance of reason and the results of [[science]], and warn us against idolatries of the mind and spirit;
* spiritual teachings of Earth-centred traditions which celebrate the sacred circle of life and instruct us to live in harmony with the rhythms of nature.

Grateful for the religious pluralism which enriches and ennobles our faith, we are inspired to deepen our understanding and expand our vision. As free congregations we enter into this covenant, promising to one another our mutual trust and support.

(Reproduced here with permission)

The current [http://cuc.ca/principles-and-sources/ Principles and Sources] are based on the UUA's [http://www.uua.org/aboutuua/principles.html Principles and Purposes]. The CUC had a [http://www.cuc.ca/statement/ task force] whose mandate was to consider revising them.

== Organization ==
[[Image:CUC Regions Map.jpg|thumb|right|350px|A map of all four CUC regions]]

The CUC is divided into four regions: &quot;BC&quot; ([[British Columbia]]), &quot;Western&quot; ([[Alberta]] to [[Thunder Bay]]), &quot;Central&quot; (between Thunder Bay and [[Kingston, Ontario|Kingston]]), and &quot;Eastern&quot; (Kingston, [[Ottawa]] and everything east of that).&lt;ref&gt;[http://cuc.ca/archive/programs/regions.htm Regions of the CUC]&lt;/ref&gt; However, for [[Young Religious Unitarian Universalists]] (YRUU) programming in Canada, the &quot;Central&quot; and &quot;Eastern&quot; regions are combined to form a youth region known as &quot;QuOM&quot; (Quebec, Ontario and the Maritimes), giving the youth only three regions for their activities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cuc.ca/archive/youth/regions.htm Regions and Congregations&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Member congregations are served by volunteer Service Consultants, Congregational Networkers, and a series of other committees. There are two directors of regional services, one for the Western two regions, and one for the Eastern two regions. The Director of Lifespan Learning oversees development of [[religious education]] programming.

== Founding ==
This section quoted from [http://www.cuc.ca/archive/who_we_are/colony_to_nation.htm THE CUC: FROM COLONY TO NATION 1961-2002] by Rev. Dr. Charles W. Eddis:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The formation of the CUC was a long-held dream. Proposals to form a Canadian organization were made by G.C. Holland, minister of the Ottawa church, in 1898, Samuel A. Eliot, President of the American Unitarian Association in 1908, Charles Huntingdon Pennoyer, minister of the Halifax Universalist Church in 1909, and Horace Westwood, a Unitarian minister in Winnipeg in 1913. In 1946 The Commission on the Work of the Churches of the British Unitarians recommended that “the Assembly should interest itself in the formation of a Canadian Unitarian Association which many Unitarians there believe to be necessary.”

The first native seeds were planted with the publication of The Canadian Unitarian in Ottawa from 1940 to 1946, a small newsletter distributed with the newsletters of Canadian churches. After the Second World War, the growth of the Unitarians in Canada began to show the strength which would make some Canadian organization feasible, if not imperative. Unitarians, most notably Toronto ministers, generated considerable media attention from the centre of Canada’s English-language media. The Unitarian Service Committee of Canada, founded in 1945, was receiving considerable attention both in city newspapers and on television, so much so that the word “Unitarian” became a household world, though its meaning was not that widely known. In 1946 there were six Icelandic Unitarian churches with 272 members, and five English-speaking churches with 1,049 members. The Universalists had five churches with 459 members. In 1961 there were three Universalist churches with 68 members, and three Icelandic and eleven English-speaking Unitarian churches with 3,476 members, and in addition 22 Unitarian fellowships with 773 members. The Universalists almost disappeared in Canada, outside of a small rural church in southwest Ontario, and were probably saved in the other two surviving locations by influx of Canadian Unitarians. By contrast, Unitarian membership more than tripled in the same fifteen years. In 1953 there were six Unitarian ministers serving congregations in Canada. Ten years later there were five ministers in the Toronto area alone.

In early April, 1961, a meeting with delegates from ten congregations was held in Montreal. The plan was approved 8 to 1, with the understanding that “The Council will function within the framework of the continental Unitarian Universalist Association.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
(Reproduced with permission)

== Relationship to the Unitarian Universalist Association ==
Up until July 2002, almost all member congregations of the CUC were also members of the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] (UUA). In the past, most services to CUC member congregations were provided by the UUA. However, with an agreement in 2001 between the UUA and CUC, from July 2002 onwards most services have been provided by the CUC to its own member congregations.

The Canadian Unitarian Universalist youth of the day disapproved of this change in relationship.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} It is quite evident in the words of this statement, which was adopted by the attendees of the 2001 youth conference held at the Unitarian Church of Montreal: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;We the youth of Canada are deeply concerned about the direction the CUC seems to be taking. As stewards of our faith, adults have a responsibility to take into consideration the concerns of youth. We are opposed to making this massive jump in our evolutionary progress.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://cuc.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/canu_july2001.pdf Debating the autonomy resolution&amp;nbsp;— Youth are worried&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The UUA continues to provide services relating to ministerial settlement as well as a very small amount of the youth (14–20) and young adult (18–35) programming and services.

== Unitarians and Universalists ==
While the name of the organization is the Canadian Unitarian Council, the CUC includes congregations with Unitarian, Universalist, Unitarian Universalist and Universalist Unitarian in their names. Changing the name of the CUC has occasionally been debated, but there have been no successful motions. To recognize the diversity, the abbreviation is often written as U*U (and playfully read as &quot;You star, you&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://cuc.ca/archive/whos_who/ed/ed_letter_nov_2003.htm Unitarian*Universalist--You Star, You!]&lt;/ref&gt; Note, not all CUC members like this playful reading and so when these people write the abbreviation they leave out the star(*), just writing UU instead.&lt;ref&gt;http://cuc.ca/wp-content/uploads/2011/10/canu_spring2004_final.pdf Letters to the Editor&amp;nbsp;— NO ASTERISKS PLEASE&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Religion}}
*[[First Unitarian Congregation of Toronto]]
*[[Congregationalist polity]]
*[[Lotta Hitschmanova]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.cuc.ca/ Official Website of The Canadian Unitarian Council]
*[http://www.usc-canada.org/ Unitarian Service Committee of Canada]
*[http://cuc.ca/archive/who_we_are/colony_to_nation.htm THE CUC: FROM COLONY TO NATION 1961-2002]
*[http://cuc.ca/congregations/ Unitarian Universalist Congregations in Canada]

{{Unitarian, Universalist and Unitarian Universalist topics}}

[[Category:Unitarian Universalism in Canada]]
[[Category:Unitarian Universalist organizations]]
[[Category:Religious organizations based in Canada]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1961]]

[[pl:Kanadyjska Rada Unitarian]]</text>
      <sha1>487zg73e1x9bqu5ygxmehmrr2bm384e</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
