<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Canon (priest)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1067968</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522271002</id>
      <parentid>522190284</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T02:24:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.127.183.73</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Honorary canons */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12266">[[File:Master of the Spes Nostra 001.jpg|thumb|right|225px|''Four canons with Sts Augustine and Jerome by an open grave, with the Visitation''. Master of the Spes Nostra (active c. 1500-1520, Northern Netherlands)]]
[[Image:Kannunik College.JPG|thumb|right|225px|Kanunnik Petrus-Ludovicus Stillemans (1821-1902), canon of the [[Seminary]], [[Sint Niklaas]], [[Flanders]].]]
[[Image:Kannunik 2.jpg|thumb|right|225px|Another [[Flemish people|Flemish]] canon in official clerical dress of canons.]]
[[Image:Sint-Salvatorskapittel Bruges Precious Blood 2008.JPG|thumb|right|225px|Canons, [[Bruges]], [[Belgium]].]]

A '''canon''' (from the [[Latin]] ''canonicus'', itself derived from the [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|κανονικός}}, ''kanonikós'', &quot;relating to a rule&quot;, &quot;regulary&quot;) is a [[priest]] or [[Minister (Christianity)|minister]] who is a member of certain bodies of the [[Christianity|Christian]] [[clergy]] subject to an ecclesiastical rule ([[Canon law|canon]]).

Originally, a canon was a [[cleric]] living with others in a clergyhouse or, later, in one of the houses within the precinct of or close to a [[cathedral]] and ordering his life according to the orders or rules of the church. This way of life grew common (and is first documented) in the eighth century. In the eleventh century, some churches required clergy thus living together to adopt the rule first proposed by [[Augustine of Hippo|Saint Augustine]] that they renounce private wealth. Those who embraced this change were known as Augustinians or [[Canons Regular]], whilst those who did not were known as [[Secular clergy|secular]] canons.

==Secular canons==

In the [[Roman Catholic Church]], the members of the [[Chapter (religion)|chapter]] of a [[cathedral]] ([[cathedral chapter]]) or of a [[collegiate church]] (so called after their chapter) are canons. Depending on the title of the church, several languages use specific titles, e.g., in German ''Domherr or Domkapitular'' in a ''Dom'' (i.e., cathedral), ''Stiftsherr'' in a prelature that has the status of a ''Stift'' (notably under a [[prince of the Church]]).

One of the functions of the cathedral chapter in the [[Roman Catholic Church]] was to elect a [[Vicar Capitular]] (now named a Diocesan Administrator) to serve during a [[sede vacante]] period of the [[diocese]]. Since the 1983 revision of the [[Code of Canon Law]], this responsibility belongs to the college of [[consultor]]s, unless the national Bishops Conference decides that the functions that canon law ascribes to the college of consultors, including this one, are to be entrusted to the cathedral chapter.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P1R.HTM Canon 502 §3 of the Code of Canon Law]&lt;/ref&gt;

All canons of the [[Church of England]] have been secular since the [[English Reformation|Reformation]], although an individual canon may himself also be a member of a religious order. Mostly, however, they are ordained, that is, priests or members of the clergy. Today, the system of canons is retained almost exclusively in connection with cathedral churches. A canon is a member of the [[chapter (religion)|chapter]] of (for the most part) priests, headed by a [[Dean (religion)|dean]], which is responsible for administering a [[cathedral]] or certain other churches that are styled [[collegiate churches]]. The dean and chapter are the formal body which has legal responsibility for the cathedral and for electing the (arch)bishop. 

===Honorary canons===

&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Regent's Park College, Oxford]] --&gt;

The title of Canon is still given in many [[diocese]]s to senior [[parish]] priests (including but not limited to some Area Deans, Rural Deans and their lieutenants and similar) as a largely honorary title. It is usually awarded in recognition of long and dedicated service to the diocese. Honorary canons are members of the chapter in name but are non-residential and receive no [[Remuneration|emoluments]]. They are entitled to call themselves canon and have a role in the administration of the cathedral. 

Generally speaking, canons in the [[Anglican Communion]] are of this sort, and thus are equivalent to a [[monsignor]] in the Catholic Church, often wearing the violet or violet-trimmed [[cassock]] which is associated with that rank.

Honorary canons within the Catholic Church have no longer been nominated after the [[Second Vatican Council]], although the French president, currently [[François Hollande]], is ex officio the &quot;first and only honorary canon&quot; of the [[Basilica of St John Lateran]], a title inherited from the Kings of France, who have held it since Henry IV of France. Also, priests (and honorary chaplains)of the Sovereign Military Order of Malta and the Equestrian Order of the Holy Sepulchre are, in fact, honorary canons of these respective Orders and have the right to the honorific title of &quot;Canon&quot; and &quot;Monsignor&quot; in addition to the choir dress of a canon, which includes the mozetta (black with purple piping for Malta and white with a red Jerusalem cross for Holy Sepulchre.)&lt;ref&gt;Insignia according to Gammarelli and Barbiconi&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.google.com/imgres?q=mozzetta+cappellano+magistrale+malta&amp;um=1&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=N&amp;tbo=d&amp;qscrl=1&amp;rlz=1T4GGNI_enUS500US500&amp;biw=1600&amp;bih=714&amp;tbm=isch&amp;tbnid=ea3AwLiKmXaZkM:&amp;imgrefurl=http://www.iagiforum.info/viewtopic.php%3Ff%3D2%26t%3D4502%26start%3D0&amp;docid=0oy87gNj7oaChM&amp;imgurl=http://www.smomge.org/Brianz.jpg&amp;w=311&amp;h=449&amp;ei=S7qdUMy-B8PX0QHZ0YDACA&amp;zoom=1&amp;iact=hc&amp;vpx=499&amp;vpy=115&amp;dur=7564&amp;hovh=270&amp;hovw=187&amp;tx=94&amp;ty=147&amp;sig=114858509990863049397&amp;page=1&amp;tbnh=146&amp;tbnw=96&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=38&amp;ved=1t:429,r:4,s:0,i:86&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lay canons===

In addition to canons who are clerks in [[holy orders]], cathedrals in the Anglican communion may also appoint lay persons as canons. The rank of ''&quot;lay canon&quot;'' is especially conferred upon [[Chancellor (ecclesiastical)|diocesan chancellors]] (the senior legal officer of the diocese, who is usually, though not exclusively, a lay person).

Since the reign of [[Henry IV of France|King Henry IV]], the [[heads of state]] of [[France]] have been granted by the [[pope]] the title of sole honorary canon of [[Saint John Lateran]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cef.fr/catho/actus/archives/2007/20071219sarkozy.php &quot;Le président Sarkozy chanoine d'honneur de la basilique Saint-Jean de Latran&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The proto-canon of the Basilica of St. Mary Major is still the King of Spain. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/various/basiliche/sm_maggiore/en/capitolo/capitolo.htm Liberian Chapter. The Chapter of Saint Mary Major]&lt;/ref&gt; 

It has traditionally been said that the [[King of England]] (now of the [[United Kingdom]]) is a canon or [[prebendary]] of [[St David's Cathedral|St David’s Cathedral]], [[Wales]]. However, this is based on a misconception. The canonry of St Mary’s College, St David’s became the property of the [[The Crown|Crown]] on the [[dissolution of the monasteries]]. The King was never a canon of St David’s, even as a layman. See The [[Thirty-Nine Articles of Religion]] (1562) Article 37.

'''Canon-Professors at Oxford'''

§2 of The Church of England (Miscellaneous Provisions) Measure 1995&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opsi.gov.uk/uk-church-measures/1995/ukcm_19950002_en_1#l1g2 Church of England (Miscellaneous Provisions) Measure 1995 No. 2&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; was passed for the express purpose of enabling [[Christ Church, Oxford]], to appoint not more than two lay canons. One of the motivations for this provision was the fact that, under the Ecclesiastical Commissioners Act 1840 (§6), the position of [[Regius Professor of Ecclesiastical History]] in the [[University of Oxford]] was annexed to a Residentiary Canonry of the [[Christ Church, Oxford|cathedral]], meaning that the [[Regius Professor of Ecclesiastical History|Regius professorship]] could be held only by an Anglican priest. Following the death of [[Peter Hinchliff]] in 1995 the [[Regius Professor of Ecclesiastical History|Regius professorship]] was held by [[Henry Mayr-Harting]], a [[Roman Catholic]] layman, from 1997 until 2003, and was taken up by another lay person, [[Sarah Foot]], in [[Michaelmas Term]] 2007. Three other [[Faculty of Theology, University of Oxford#Professors|Statutory Professorships]], the [[Regius Professor of Divinity|Regius Professorship of Divinity]], [[Lady Margaret Professor (Oxford)|Lady Margaret Professorship of Divinity]], and [[Regius Professorship of Moral and Pastoral Theology]], are annexed to canonries of [[Christ Church, Oxford|Christ Church]] and must be held by Anglican priests.

===Minor canons===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Ozias Thurston Linley]] --&gt;

[[Minor canon]]s are those clergy who are members of the cathedral's establishment and take part in the daily services but are not part of the formal Chapter.  These are generally more junior clergy, who in a parish church would be serving a [[curate|curacy]].

==Canons regular==
{{main|Canons Regular}}
Canons regular are the members of certain religious orders in the Roman Catholic Church (not to be confused with clerics regular), composed of priests and some choir canons who live in community, together in the past with lay brothers. There are a variety of congregations of canons, some of whom are part of the Confederation of [[Canons Regular]] of St. Augustine.
* [[Canons Regular of the Lateran]] or St. Saviour, who seem to date back to [[Pope Alexander II]] (1063)
* [[Order of the Canons Regular of Premontre]]; [[Norbertines]] founded by St. Norbert (1120)
* [[Canons Regular of the Holy Cross of Coimbra|Order of the Holy Cross (Canons Regular)]] founded in Portugal in 1131 and re-founded in 1977
* [[Canons Regular of the Order of the Holy Cross]] (the Crosiers), founded at Clair-lieu, near Huy, in Belgium, in 1211
* [[Swiss Congregation of Canons Regular of Saint Maurice of Agaune]]
* [[Gilbertine Order]], a solely English order of canons regular, which became extinct under King [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]]
* [[Canons Regular of the Immaculate Conception]], a congregation of Canons Regular founded in France in 1871

Many bishops endeavoured to imitate St. Augustine and St. Eusebius, and to live a common life with the clergy of their church. Rules taken from the sacred canons were even drawn up for their use, of which the most celebrated is that of [[St. Chrodegang]], [[Bishop of Metz]] (766). In the tenth century, this institution declined; the canons, as the clergy attached to a church and living a common life were called, began to live separately; some of them, however, resisted this relaxation of discipline, and even added poverty to their common life. This is the origin of the canons regular. [[Pope Benedict XII]] by his constitution ''Ad decorem'' (15 May 1339) prescribed a general reform of the canons regular. The [[canons regular]] ex professo united Holy Orders with religious life, and being attached to a church, devoted themselves to promoting the dignity of [[divine]] [[worship]]. With [[monks]], Holy Orders are incidental and secondary, and are superadded to the religious life. With canons as with the clerks regular, Holy Orders are the principal thing, and the religious life is superadded to the Holy Orders.

==See also==
* [[Canoness]]
* [[Index of religious honorifics and titles]]

==Notes and references==
{{refs}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cricusa.com/ Canons Regular of the Immaculate Conception]
* [http://www.abbeynews.com/Abbey-Home.html/ Canons Regular of Premontre, Orange County, California]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Canon (Priest)}}
[[Category:Catholic priesthood]]
[[Category:Christian religious leaders]]
[[Category:Ecclesiastical titles]]
[[Category:Anglican ecclesiastical offices]]

&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;

[[an:Calonche]]
[[ca:Canonge]]
[[cs:Kanovník]]
[[da:Kannik]]
[[de:Kanoniker]]
[[es:Canónigo]]
[[eo:Kanoniko]]
[[fr:Chanoine]]
[[ko:의전사제]]
[[hr:Kanonik]]
[[io:Kanoniko]]
[[id:Kanon (pendeta)]]
[[is:Kórsbróðir]]
[[it:Canonico]]
[[lt:Kanauninkas]]
[[li:Kanunnik]]
[[hu:Kanonok]]
[[nl:Seculiere kanunnik]]
[[ja:律修司祭]]
[[no:Kannik]]
[[pl:Kanonik]]
[[pt:Cônego]]
[[ru:Каноник]]
[[sl:Kanonik]]
[[sh:Kanonik]]
[[fi:Kaniikki]]
[[sv:Kanik]]
[[uk:Канонік]]
[[zh:法政牧師]]</text>
      <sha1>p2o9htk8y5j6z7w5bvs60b8bw27kllu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
