<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Cardinal (Catholicism)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6221</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519743078</id>
      <parentid>517223667</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T11:36:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[war:Kardinal (Katolisismo)]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42798">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:CardinalCoA PioM.svg|thumb|right|180px|The coat of arms of a cardinal is indicated by a red [[galero]] (wide-brimmed hat) with 15 tassels on each side (the [[motto]] and [[Escutcheon (heraldry)|escutcheon]] are proper to the individual cardinal).]]
A '''cardinal''' is a senior [[Ecclesiology|ecclesiastical]] official, usually an ordained [[Bishop (Catholic Church)|bishop]], and ecclesiastical [[Prince of the Church|prince of the Catholic Church]]. Cardinals are collectively known as the [[College of Cardinals]], which as a body elects a new [[pope]]. The duties of the cardinals include attending the meetings of the College and making themselves available individually or in groups to the pope if he requests their counsel. Most cardinals have additional duties, such as leading a [[diocese]] or [[archdiocese]] or running a [[Dicastery|department]] of the [[Roman Curia]].

A cardinal's other main function is [[papal election|electing the pope]] whenever, by death or resignation, the seat becomes vacant. In 1059, the right of electing the pope was reserved to the principal clergy of Rome and the bishops of the seven [[Suburbicarian diocese|suburbicarian see]]s. During the ''[[sede vacante]]'', the period between a pope's death and the election of his successor, the day-to-day governance of the Church as a whole is in the hands of the College of Cardinals. The right to enter the [[Papal conclave|conclave]] of cardinals who elect the pope is now limited to those who have not reached the age of 80 years on the day of the pope's death or resignation.

The term ''cardinal'' at one time applied to any priest permanently assigned or [[incardinated]] to a church,&lt;ref name=&quot;CE-cardinal&quot;&gt;{{CathEncy | wstitle=Cardinal (1) | title=Cardinal | last=Sägmüller | first=Johannes Baptist}}&lt;/ref&gt; or specifically to the senior priest of an important church, based on the Latin ''cardo'' (hinge), meaning &quot;principal&quot; or &quot;chief&quot;. The term was applied in this sense as early as the ninth century to the priests of the ''tituli'' (parishes) of the [[diocese of Rome]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CE-cardinal&quot; /&gt; A remnant of these earlier cardinals is retained by the [[Church of England]], where the title of &quot;[[Cardinal (Church of England)|cardinal]]&quot;  is still held by the two senior members of the College of Minor [[Canon (priest)|Canons]] of [[St Paul's Cathedral]].

In the twelfth century the practice of appointing ecclesiastics from outside Rome as cardinals began, with each of them being assigned a church in Rome as his [[titular church]], or being linked with one of the suburbicarian dioceses, while still being incardinated in a diocese other than that of Rome.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

==History==
{{Further2|[[Papal selection before 1059]]}}
[[Image:Cardinal Richelieu (Champaigne).jpg|thumb|right|155 px|[[Cardinal Richelieu]], chief minister of [[France]].]]
The election of the pope was not always reserved to the cardinals; the pope was originally elected by the clergy and the people of the [[diocese of Rome]]. In [[medieval]] times, Roman nobility gained influence. The Holy Roman Emperors had a hand in choosing the pontiff. But as the pope gained greater political independence, the right of election was with the bull ''[[In nomine Domini]]'' reserved to cardinals in 1059, leaving the emperor only with a vague right of approbation.

However the influence of temporal rulers, notably the French kings, largely reemerged via cardinals of certain nationalities or politically significant movements; there even developed traditions entitling certain monarchs — e.g. of Austria, Spain, and Portugal — to nominate one of their trusted clerical subjects to be created cardinal, a so-called [[crown-cardinal]].

In theory, the pope could substitute another body of electors for the College of Cardinals. Some proposed that the [[Synod of Bishops (Catholic)|Synod of Bishops]] should perform this function, a proposal that was not accepted, because, among other reasons, the Synod of Bishops can only meet when called by the pope.

In [[Early Modern period|early modern]] times, cardinals often had important roles in secular affairs. In some cases, they took on powerful positions in government. An example of this was found in [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]]'s England where his chief minister was [[Thomas Wolsey|Cardinal Wolsey]]. An even more prominent example is that of [[Cardinal Richelieu]], whose power was so great that he was for many years the real ruler of France.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=rXSqwPFMn3oC Henry Kitchell Webster, Hutton Webster, Early European History], p. 604&lt;/ref&gt; Richelieu was so successful that his successor, [[Cardinal Mazarin|Jules Mazarin]], was also a cardinal. [[Guillaume Dubois]] and [[André-Hercule de Fleury]] complete the list of the &quot;four great&quot; cardinals to have ruled [[France]].

As of 2012, the youngest cardinal is [[Rainer Woelki]] (born 1956, elevated 2012) - the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Berlin|Archbishop of Berlin]]. The oldest living cardinal, following the death of [[Paul Augustin Mayer|Cardinal Mayer]] in 2010, is [[Ersilio Tonini]], the Archbishop [[Emeritus]] of Ravenna-Cervia (born 1914, elevated 1994).

==College and orders of cardinalate==
[[Pope Sixtus V]] limited the number of cardinals to 70, composed of six cardinal bishops, 50 cardinal priests, and 14 cardinal deacons; however, [[Pope John XXIII]] began to exceed the overall limit of 70, and this continued under his successors. At the start of 1971, [[Pope Paul VI]] set an age limit of eighty years for electors, who were to number no more than 120, but set no limit to the number of cardinals as a whole, including those over eighty. (As a result of the setting of the age limit at the start of 1971, twenty-five living cardinals, including the last three surviving cardinals elevated by Pope Pius XI, lost the right to participate in a conclave.) Since Popes can [[dispensation (Catholic Church)|dispense]] from church laws,&lt;ref&gt;[http://newcesite.com/2008/02/08/81136/ Are There Any Limitations on the Power of the Pope?]&lt;/ref&gt; they have sometimes brought the number of cardinals under the age of 80 to more than 120, perhaps calculating that the number would be sufficiently reduced by the time the need for a conclave would arise.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americancatholic.org/Messenger/May2005/Wiseman.asp#F1 Electing a New Pope]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://papam.wordpress.com/2010/11/19/november-20-2010-cardinal-creating-conistory-college-at-203-121-electors-82-non-electors/ College at 203, 121 Electors &amp; 82 Non-Electors]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;There would also have been 121 under-80 cardinals after Pope Benedict XVI's 2007 consistory, if Cardinal [[Stephen Fumio Hamao]] had not died between the announcement of the consistory and the date on which it was held.&lt;/ref&gt;  And in fact, since the 120 limit was enacted, no conclave has been held with even a full 120 entitled to participate. Pope Paul VI also increased the number of cardinal bishops by giving that rank to patriarchs of the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]] who are made cardinals.

==Titular church==
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2012}}
[[Image:Theodor Kardinal Innitzer -001-.jpg|thumb|right|160px|[[Theodor Innitzer|Cardinal Innitzer]], [[Archbishop of Vienna]] and Cardinal-Priest of [[San Crisogono]]]]
Each cardinal takes on a [[titular church]], either a church in the city of Rome or one of the [[Suburbicarian diocese|suburbicarian see]]s. The only exception is for patriarchs of Eastern Catholic Churches. The [[Dean of the College of Cardinals]] in addition to such a titular church also receives the [[Bishop of Ostia|titular bishopric of Ostia]], the primary suburbicarian see. Cardinals governing a [[particular Church]] retain that church.

== Title and reference style ==

Since 1630, cardinals have taken the [[style (address)|style]] ''[[His Eminence|Eminence]]''. In accordance with tradition, they sign by placing the title &quot;Cardinal&quot; (abbreviated ''Card.'') after their personal name and before their surname as, for instance, &quot;John Card(inal) Doe&quot; or, in [[Latin]], &quot;Ioannes Card(inalis) Cognomen&quot;. Similarly, the official signature of popes inserts the Latin title ''Papa'' (abbreviated ''Pp.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01022a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia:''Ecclesiastical Abbreviations'']&lt;/ref&gt;) immediately after the personal name, as &quot;Benedictus Pp. XVI&quot; for Pope Benedict  XVI. Some writers, such as James-Charles Noonan,&lt;ref&gt;Noonan, ''The Church Visible'', p. 205&lt;/ref&gt; hold that, in the case of cardinals, the form used for signatures should be used also when referring to them, even in English; and this is the usual but not the only way of referring to cardinals in Latin.&lt;ref&gt;An Internet search will uncover some hundreds of examples of &quot;Cardinalis Ioannes &lt;surname&gt;&quot;, examples modern and centuries-old (such as [http://www.uni-mannheim.de/mateo/camenahist/hsj/t2/HSJ_2_2.html this from 1620)], and the phrase &quot;dominus cardinalis Petrus Caputius&quot; is found in a [http://regesten.regesta-imperii.de/anzeige.php?pk=&amp;bandanzeige=&amp;begriffe=&amp;q=&amp;offset=&amp;uri=1250-00-00_1_0_5_1_2_1798_5014a&amp;rpk=&amp;i=&amp;band=&amp;nr= document of 1250.]&lt;/ref&gt; Several influential stylebooks, both secular&lt;ref&gt;&quot;At first reference Cardinal John Doe. At subsequent references the cardinal or Doe&quot; ([http://handbook.reuters.com/index.php?title=R&amp;oldid=514#32.34 Reuters Handbook of Journalism]). The [[Associated Press]] stylebook, quoted by Douglas LeBlanc on [http://www.getreligion.org/?p=2391 Anglicanism out of AP style at the ''Times''?] agrees fully: &quot;The preferred form for first reference is to use ''Cardinal'', ''Archbishop'' or ''Bishop'' before the individual's name: ''Cardinal Timothy Manning, archbishop of Los Angeles''. On second reference, ''Manning'' or ''the cardinal''.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and religious,&lt;ref&gt;The [http://docs.google.com/gview?a=v&amp;q=cache:0VPXjzsIfPEJ:holynameprovince.org/publications/pdf/HNPStyleBook_Aug08.pdf Publications Style Book of the Franciscan Holy Name Province] lays down: &quot;Use the form 'Cardinal John Smith' instead of the older 'John Cardinal Smith'&quot;, and cites the Catholic News Service stylebook.&lt;/ref&gt; however, indicate that the correct form for referring to a cardinal in English is as &quot;Cardinal &lt;Name&gt; &lt;Surname&gt;. This style is also generally followed on the websites of the Holy See and [[episcopal conference]]s.&lt;ref&gt;The websites of [http://www.vatican.va/phome_en.htm the Holy See] (except for signatures), and of the Episcopal Conferences in [http://www.usccb.org/ the United States], [http://www.catholicchurch.org.uk/ccb/catholic_church/the_church_in_england_and_wales/cardinal England and Wales], [http://www.catholiccommunications.ie/Dioceses/armagh.html Ireland] and the [http://www.acbc.catholic.org.au/bishops/bcmembers.asp Australia] agree with the stylebooks. The [http://www.bpsconfscot.com/Members/tabid/426/Default.aspx Bishops' Conference of Scotland] uses both styles side by side. On diocesan sites, the &quot;John Cardinal Doe&quot; style is found on, for example, those of [http://www.rcab.org/People/cardinalOMalley.html Boston], [http://www.archdiocese-chgo.org/ Chicago], [http://www.dublindiocese.ie/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=blogcategory&amp;id=19&amp;Itemid=30 Dublin], [http://www.archny.org/about-us/edward-cardinal-egan/ New York], [http://www.archtoronto.org/about_us/cardinal_bishops.html Toronto], [http://www.adw.org/about/our_bishops.asp Washington], [http://www.diogh.org/bishops_dinardo.htm Galveston-Houston], [http://www.aodonline.org/AODOnline/Meet+the+Bishops+12188/Adam+Cardinal+Maida+2244/Tribute.htm Detroit], [http://www.sacbc.org.za/Site/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=20&amp;Itemid=30 Durban], [http://www.archdioceseofcolombo.com/2_1.php, Colombo], [http://archbom.org/ Bombay], and the &quot;Cardinal John Doe&quot; on, for example, those of [http://www.armagharchdiocese.org/cardinal Armagh],[http://www.archdiocese.la/archbishop/profile.html Los Angeles], [http://www.archdiocese-phl.org/rigali/biorigali.htm Philadelphia], [http://www.archdiocese-edinburgh.org.uk/cardinal_about.htm St Andrews and Edinburgh], [http://www.wn.catholic.org.nz/?sid=10 Wellington], [http://www.rcdow.org.uk/cardinal/default.asp?library_ref=1&amp;category_ref=8 Westminster].&lt;/ref&gt;

A well-known instance of the &quot;John Cardinal Doe&quot; style is that in the proclamation, in Latin, of the election of a new pope by the cardinal protodeacon: &quot;''Annuntio vobis gaudium magnum; habemus Papam: Eminentissimum ac Reverendissimum Dominum, Dominum (first name) Sanctae Romanae Ecclesiae Cardinalem (last name), ...''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/elezione/index_en.htm Benedict XVI, 19 April 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; (Meaning: &quot;''I announce to you a great joy; we have a Pope: The Most Eminent and Most Reverend Lord, Lord (first name) Cardinal of the Holy Roman Church (last name), ...''&quot;)

==Orders==
===Cardinal bishop===
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2012}}
[[Image:Sodano.jpg|thumb|right|150px|[[Angelo Sodano|Cardinal Sodano]], current Dean of the College]]
Cardinal bishops (cardinals of the Episcopal Order) are among the most senior [[prelates]] of the Catholic Church. Though nowadays most cardinals are also bishops, the term Cardinal bishops only refers to the cardinals that are titular bishops of one of the &quot;[[suburbicarian diocese|suburbicarian]]&quot; sees. 

In early times the privilege of [[papal election]] was not reserved to the cardinals, and for centuries the pope was customarily a Roman priest and never a bishop from elsewhere; to preserve [[apostolic succession]] the rite of consecrating the pope as a [[bishop]] had to be performed by someone who was already a bishop. The rule remains that, if the person elected pope is not yet a bishop, he is consecrated by the Dean of the College of Cardinals, the Cardinal [[bishop of Ostia]].

The [[Dean of the College of Cardinals]], the ''[[primus inter pares]]'' of the College of Cardinals, is elected by the cardinal bishops holding suburbicarian sees from among their own number, an election, however, that must be approved by the pope. Formerly the position of Dean belonged to the longest-serving of the cardinal bishops, all six of whom then headed a suburbicarian see. Though these sees are now seven (Ostia and Velletri having been separated in 1914), there are only six cardinal bishops, since the Dean always adds the title of Ostia to his original suburbicarian diocese. Due to the increasing involvement of the Cardinal bishops in the curia, their dioceses (except Ostia, which is administered by the Holy See) are administered by diocesan bishops.

Currently the cardinal bishops of the suburbicarian diocese are:
* [[Angelo Sodano]], Cardinal [[Bishop of Ostia]] and [[Bishop of Albano|Albano]], [[Dean of the College of Cardinals]], former [[Cardinal Secretary of State]]
* [[Roger Etchegaray]], [[Cardinal Bishop of Porto-Santa Rufina]], Vice-Dean, President emeritus of the [[Pontifical Council for Justice and Peace]]
* [[Giovanni Battista Re]], [[bishop of Sabina|Cardinal Bishop of Sabina-Poggio Mirteto]], Prefect Emeritus of the Congregation for Bishops
* [[Francis Arinze]], [[Cardinal Bishop of Velletri-Segni]], Prefect Emeritus of the [[Congregation for Divine Worship and the Discipline of the Sacraments]].
* [[Tarcisio Bertone]], [[Cardinal Bishop of Frascati]], [[Cardinal Secretary of State]] and [[Camerlengo of the Holy Roman Church]]
* [[José Saraiva Martins]], [[Cardinal Bishop of Palestrina]], Prefect Emeritus of the [[Congregation for the Causes of Saints]]

For a period ending in the mid-20th century, long-serving cardinal priests were entitled to fill vacancies that arose among the cardinal bishops, just as [[cardinal deacon]]s of ten years' standing are still entitled to become cardinal priests. Since then, cardinals have been advanced to cardinal bishop exclusively by Papal appointment.

In 1965 [[Pope Paul VI]] decreed in his [[motu proprio]] ''Ad Purpuratorum Patrum'' that [[patriarch]]s of the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]] who were named cardinals would also be part of the episcopal order, ranked after the six cardinal bishops of the suburbicarian sees (who had been relieved of direct responsibilities for those sees by [[Pope John XXIII]] three years earlier). Not holding a suburbicarian see, they cannot elect the dean nor become dean. The three [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern]] patriarchs who are now cardinal bishops are the following:
* [[Nasrallah Sfeir]], [[List of Maronite Patriarchs|Patriarch Emeritus of Antioch]] for the [[Maronite]]s
* [[Emmanuel III Delly]], [[List of Chaldean Catholic Patriarchs of Babylon|Patriarch of Babylon for the Chaldeans]]
* [[Antonios Naguib]], [[List of Coptic Catholic Patriarchs of Alexandria|Patriarch of Alexandria for the Copts]]

The [[Latin Rite]] [[Patriarch of Lisbon|Patriarchs of Lisbon]] and [[Patriarch of Venice|Venice]], while in practice always made cardinals at the [[consistory]] after they take possession of their sees, are made cardinal priests, not cardinal bishops. Although the incumbents of such prestigious sees are consistently created cardinal, no see carries an actual right to the cardinalate.

===Cardinal priest===
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2012}}
[[Image:Eugenio Sales.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Eugênio Sales|Cardinal Sales]], Cardinal [[Protopriest]] until 2012.]]
Cardinal priests are the most numerous of the three orders of cardinals in the Catholic Church, ranking above the cardinal deacons and below the cardinal bishops. Those who are named cardinal priests today are generally [[Bishop (Catholic Church)|bishop]]s of important [[diocese]]s throughout the world, though some hold [[Roman Curia|Curial]] positions.

In modern times the name &quot;cardinal priest&quot; is interpreted as meaning a cardinal who is of the order of priests. Originally, however, this referred to certain key priests of important churches of the Diocese of Rome, who were recognized as the ''cardinal'' priests, the important priests chosen by the pope to advise him in his duties as [[Bishop]] of [[diocese of Rome|Rome]] (the Latin ''cardo'' means &quot;hinge&quot;). Certain clerics in many dioceses at the time, not just that of Rome, were said to be the key personnel — the term gradually became exclusive to Rome to indicate those entrusted with electing the bishop of Rome, the pope.
[[Image:Wolsey.jpg|thumb|right|[[Thomas Wolsey|Cardinal-priest Wolsey]]]]
While the cardinalate has long been expanded beyond the Roman pastoral clergy and [[Roman Curia]], every cardinal priest has [[titular church]] in Rome, though they may be bishops or archbishops elsewhere, just as cardinal bishops are given one of the [[suburbicarian diocese]]s around Rome. [[Pope Paul VI]] abolished all administrative rights cardinals had with regard to their titular churches, though the cardinal's name and coat of arms are still posted in the church, and they are expected to preach there if convenient when they are in Rome.

While the number of cardinals was small from the times of the [[Roman Empire]] to the [[Renaissance]], and frequently smaller than the number of recognized churches entitled to a cardinal priest, in the 16th century the College expanded markedly. In 1587 [[Pope Sixtus V]] sought to arrest this growth by fixing the maximum size of the College at 70, including 50 cardinal priests, about twice the historical number. This limit was respected until 1958, and the list of titular churches modified only on rare occasions, generally due to a building falling into disrepair. When [[Pope John XXIII]] abolished the limit, he began to add new churches to the list, which Popes [[Pope Paul VI|Paul VI]] and [[Pope John Paul II|John Paul II]] continued to do. Today there are close to 150 titular churches, out of over 300 churches in Rome.

The cardinal who is the longest-serving member of the order of cardinal priests is titled ''cardinal [[protopriest]]''. He had certain ceremonial duties in the conclave that have effectively ceased because he would generally have already reached age 80, at which cardinals are barred from the conclave. The current cardinal protopriest is [[Paulo Evaristo Arns]] of [[Brazil]].

===Cardinal deacon===
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2012}}
The cardinal deacons are the lowest-ranking cardinals. Cardinals elevated to the diaconal order are either officials of the [[Roman Curia]] or priests elevated after their 80th birthday. Bishops with diocesan responsibilities, however, are created cardinal priests.

Cardinal deacons derive originally from the seven deacons in the [[Papal Household]] and the seven deacons who supervised the Church's works in the districts of [[Rome]] during the early Middle Ages, when church administration was effectively the government of Rome and provided all social services. Cardinal deacons are given title to one of these deaconries. 

Under the 1587 decree of [[Pope Sixtus V]], which fixed the maximum size of the [[College of Cardinals]], there were 14 cardinal deacons. Later the number increased. As of 2005, there were over 50 churches recognized as cardinalatial deaconries, though there were only 30 cardinals of the order of deacons. Cardinal deacons have long enjoyed the right to &quot;opt for the order of cardinal priests&quot; (''optazione'') after they have been cardinal deacons for 10 years. They may on such elevation take a vacant &quot;[[titular church|title]]&quot; (a church allotted to a cardinal priest as the Roman church with which he is associated) or their diaconal church may be temporarily elevated to a cardinal priest's &quot;title&quot; for that occasion. When elevated to cardinal priests, they take their precedence according to the day they were first made cardinal deacons (thus ranking above cardinal priests who were elevated to the college after them, regardless of order).

When not celebrating Mass but still serving a liturgical function, such as the semiannual ''[[Urbi et Orbi]]'' papal blessing, some Papal Masses and some events at Ecumenical Councils, cardinal deacons can be recognized by the [[dalmatic]]s they would don with the simple white mitre (so called ''mitra simplex'').

====Cardinal protodeacon====
The [[Cardinal protodeacon]], the senior cardinal deacon in order of appointment to the College of Cardinals, has the privilege of [[Habemus Papam|announcing a new pope's election]] and name (once he has been ordained to the Episcopate&lt;ref&gt;Ap. Const. [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_22021996_universi-dominici-gregis_en.html Universi Dominici Gregis, No. 89]&lt;/ref&gt;) from the central balcony at the [[Basilica of Saint Peter]] in [[Vatican City State]]. In the past, during papal coronations, the Proto-Deacon also had the honor of bestowing the pallium on the new pope and crowning him with the [[papal tiara]]. However, Pope John Paul I chose not to be crowned and opted for a simpler papal inauguration ceremony, and his two successors followed that example. However, the Proto-Deacon still has the privilege of bestowing the pallium on a new pope at his papal inauguration. “Acting in the place of the [[Roman Pontiff]], he also confers the [[pallium]] upon [[Metropolitan bishop#Roman Catholic|metropolitan bishops]] or gives the [[pallium]] to their proxies.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P19.HTM Canon 355 §2]&lt;/ref&gt; The current Cardinal Proto-Deacon is [[Jean-Louis Tauran]].

====Protodeacons since 1911====
{{unreferenced section|date=July 2012}}
[[Image:Jean-Louis Tauran in Granada, February 2010.jpg|thumb|right|350px|[[Jean-Louis Tauran|Cardinal Tauran]], current Cardinal [[Protodeacon]].]]
*[[Francesco Salesio Della Volpe]] (4 January 1911 – 5 November 1916)
*[[Gaetano Bisleti]] (5 November 1916 – 17 December 1928)
*[[Camillo Laurenti]] (17 December 1928 – 16 December 1935)
*[[Camillo Caccia-Dominioni]] (16 December 1935 – 12 November 1946)
*[[Nicola Canali]] (12 November 1946 – 3 August 1961)
*[[Alfredo Ottaviani]] (3 August 1961 – 26 June 1967)
*[[Arcadio Larraona Saralegui]], [[Claretians|CMF]] (26 June 1967 – 28 April 1969)
*[[William Theodore Heard]] (28 April 1969 – 18 May 1970)
*[[Antonio Bacci]] (18 May 1970 – 20 January 1971)
*[[Michael Browne (cardinal)|Michael Browne]], [[Dominican Order|OP]] (20 January 1971 – 31 March 1971)
*[[Federico Callori di Vignale]] (31 March 1971 – 8 August 1971)
*[[Charles Journet]] (8 August 1971 – 5 March 1973)
*[[Pericle Felici]] (5 March 1973 – 30 June 1979)
*[[Sergio Pignedoli]] (30 June 1979 – 15 June 1980)
*[[Umberto Mozzoni]] (15 June 1980 – 2 February 1983)
*[[Opilio Rossi]] (2 February 1983 – 22 June 1987)
*[[Giuseppe Caprio]] (22 June 1987 – 26 November 1990)
*[[Aurelio Sabattani]] (26 November 1990 – 5 April 1993)
*[[Duraisamy Simon Lourdusamy]] (5 April 1993 – 29 January 1996)
*[[Eduardo Martínez Somalo]] (29 January 1996 – 9 January 1999)
*[[Pio Laghi]] (9 January 1999 – 26 February 2002)
*[[Luigi Poggi]] (26 February 2002 – 24 February 2005)
*[[Jorge Medina Estévez]] (24 February 2005 – 23 February 2007)
*[[Darío Castrillón Hoyos]] (23 February 2007 – 1 March 2008)
*[[Agostino Cacciavillan]] (1 March 2008 – 21 February 2011)
*[[Jean-Louis Tauran]] (21 February 2011 – present)

==Special types of cardinals==
===Camerlengo===
The Cardinal [[Camerlengo of the Holy Roman Church]], assisted by the Vice-Camerlengo and the other prelates of the office known as the Apostolic Camera, has functions that in essence are limited to a period of [[sede vacante]] of the papacy. He is to collate information about the financial situation of all administrations dependent on the Holy See and present the results to the College of Cardinals, as they gather for the [[papal conclave]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19880628_pastor-bonus-roman-curia_en.html#ADMINISTRATIVE%20SERVICES ''Pastor bonus'': Administrative Services]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cardinals who are not bishops===
{{refimprove section|date=July 2012}}
Until 1917 it was possible for someone who was not a priest, but only in [[minor orders]], to become a cardinal (see &quot;lay cardinals&quot;, below), but they were enrolled only in the order of cardinal deacons. For example, in the 16th century, [[Reginald Pole]] was a cardinal for 18 years before he was ordained a priest. In 1917 it was established that all cardinals, even cardinal deacons, had to be priests,&lt;ref&gt;Canon 232 §1 of the 1917 Code of Canon Law&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1962, [[John XXIII]] set the norm that all cardinals be bishops.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}} Consequently, canon 351 of the 1983 Code of Canon Law requires that a cardinal be at least in the order of [[priesthood (Catholic Church)|priesthood]] at his appointment, and that those who are not already [[bishop (Catholic Church)|bishops]] must receive episcopal consecration, a rule from which [[Dispensation (Catholic Church)|dispensation]] may be obtained from the pope, as by Cardinals [[Roberto Tucci]], [[Albert Vanhoye]], [[Domenico Bartolucci]] and most recently [[Karl Josef Becker]].

A cardinal who is not a bishop is still entitled to wear and use the episcopal vestments and other [[pontificalia]] (episcopal regalia: [[mitre]], [[crozier]], [[zucchetto]], [[pectoral cross]] and ring). Almost all of the prominent priests who were elevated to the cardinalate as cardinal-deacons were near or over the age of 80 when elevated,{{citation needed|date=July 2012}} and so would not have participated in a papal conclave. For those priests over 80 who became cardinal-deacons and were not ordained to the episcopacy, this is the highest position they can normally attain in the Church hierarchy (though all cardinals rank above bishops in rank and order of precedence, those cardinals who are not bishops do not have the right to perform the functions reserved solely to bishops, such as ordination).

===&quot;Lay cardinals&quot;===
{{Main|Lay cardinal}}
At various times there have been cardinals who had only received [[tonsure#Western Christianity|first tonsure]] and [[minor orders]] but not yet been [[Holy Orders|ordained]] as [[deacon]]s or priests. Though [[clergy|clerics]], they were inaccurately called &quot;[[lay cardinal]]s&quot; and were permitted to marry. [[Teodolfo Mertel]] was among the last of the lay cardinals. When he died in 1899 he was the last surviving cardinal who was not at least ordained a priest. With the revision of the [[Code of Canon Law]] promulgated in 1917 by [[Pope Benedict XV]], only those who are already priests or bishops may be appointed cardinals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/LAT0813/_PO.HTM canon 232 §1] of the 1917 Code of Canon Law&lt;/ref&gt; Since the time of [[Pope John XXIII]] a priest who is appointed a cardinal must be consecrated a bishop, unless he obtains a dispensation.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P18.HTM canon 351 §1] of the 1983 Code of Canon Law&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cardinals ''in pectore'' or secret cardinals==
{{Main|In pectore}}
In addition to the named cardinals, the pope may name secret cardinals or cardinals ''[[in pectore]]'' (Latin for ''in the breast'').

During the [[Western Schism]] many cardinals were created by the contending popes. Beginning with the reign of [[Pope Martin V]],&lt;ref name=&quot;CE-cardinal&quot; /&gt; cardinals were created without publishing their names until later, termed ''creati et reservati in pectore''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.fiu.edu/~mirandas/consistories-xv.htm#MartinV | title=Consistories of Martin V - 23 July 1423 (II), Note | work=The Cardinals of the Holy Roman Church}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A cardinal named ''in pectore'' is known only to the pope; not even the cardinal so named is necessarily aware of his elevation, and in any event cannot function as a cardinal while his appointment is ''in pectore''. Today, cardinals are named ''in pectore'' to protect them or their congregations from reprisals if their identities were known.

If conditions change, so that the pope judges it safe to make the appointment public, he may do so at any time. The cardinal in question then ranks in precedence with those raised to the cardinalate at the time of his ''in pectore'' appointment. If a pope dies before revealing the identity of an ''in pectore'' cardinal, the cardinalate expires. Some{{who|date=July 2012}} speculate that the pope could leave instructions in writing, perhaps in his will, for the appointment to be made known after his death; but it is difficult to imagine a case in which the pope would consider that his own death would remove the obstacle in the way of publishing the name.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

Of the 232 cardinals that [[Pope John Paul II]] elevated, four were named ''in pectore''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.vatican.va/news_services/press/documentazione/documents/santopadre_biografie/giovanni_paolo_ii_biografia_breve_en.html | title=His Holiness John Paul II Short Biography | work=[[Holy See]] Press Office | date=30 June 2005 | accessdate=20 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.vatican.va/news_services/press/documentazione/documents/santopadre_biografie/giovanni_paolo_ii_biografia_pontificato_en.html#2003 | title=His Holiness John Paul II Biography | work=[[Holy See]] Press Office | date=30 June 2005 | accessdate=20 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The identities of three of these were subsequently revealed:
* [[Ignatius Kung Pin-Mei]], [[Bishop (Catholic Church)|Bishop]] of [[Shanghai]], [[People's Republic of China]] - made cardinal 1979, revealed 1991, died 2000.
* [[Marian Jaworski]], [[Archbishop]] of [[Lviv]], [[Ukraine]] - made cardinal 1998, revealed 2001.
* [[Jānis Pujāts]], Archbishop of [[Riga]], [[Latvia]] - made cardinal 1998, revealed 2001.
* The fourth cardinal was created in 2003. John Paul II did not reveal this cardinal's identity prior to his death, or in the 15-page testament he wrote during his papacy and which was released after his death. Consequently, this cardinalate expired. Some suspect that this &quot;secret Cardinal&quot; was Archbishop [[Stanisław Dziwisz]], a close, longtime friend of John Paul II. However, he was made a cardinal at the 24 March 2006 consistory anyway, as was announced by [[Pope Benedict XVI]] on 22 February 2006.

==Vesture and privileges==
{{Main|Pontifical vestments}}
[[Image:Cardinal Théodore Adrien Sarr 2.JPG|thumb|right|150px|[[Théodore Adrien Sarr|Cardinal Sarr]] with a ferraiolo, and wearing a red cassock, but not the rest of the choir dress]]
[[Image:Kardinaal III Danneels en Kasper.JPG|thumb|right|150px|Cardinals [[Walter Kasper]] (left) and [[Godfried Danneels]] (right) wearing their [[choir dress]]: [[scarlet (color)|scarlet]] ([[red]]) [[cassock]], white [[rochet]] trimmed with [[lace]], scarlet [[mozetta]], scarlet [[biretta]] (over the usual scarlet [[zucchetto]]), and [[pectoral cross]] on cord.]]

When in [[choir dress]], a [[Latin Rite|Latin-rite]] cardinal wears [[scarlet (color)|scarlet]] garments — the blood-like [[red]] symbolizes a cardinal's willingness to die for his faith.&lt;ref&gt;Pope Benedict ... He told them that the red signifies the dignity of their new office and that they must be ready &quot;even to the point of spilling your blood for the increase of the Christian faith, for peace and harmony among the people of God, for freedom and the spread of the Holy Roman Catholic Church.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/news/local-national/article3196655.ece Applause and tears in Basilica greet Pontiff] (26 November 2007) ''Belfast Telegraph''. Retrieved 2008-06-01. Quote: &quot;In a ceremony televised across the world cardinal-elect Sean Brady knelt before Pope Benedict XVI and pledged his allegiance to the Church before receiving his special red birretta — a symbol of a cardinal's dignity and willingness to shed blood for the increase of the Christian faith.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Excluding the [[rochet]] — which is always white — the scarlet garments include the [[cassock]], [[mozzetta]], and [[biretta]] (over the usual scarlet [[zucchetto]]). The biretta of a cardinal is distinctive not merely for its scarlet color, but also for the fact that it does not have a pompon or tassel on the top as do the birettas of other prelates.  Until the 1460s, it was customary for cardinals to wear a [[violet (color)|violet]] or [[blue]] cape unless granted the privilege of wearing red when acting on papal business. His normal-wear [[simar]] is black but has scarlet [[piping (sewing)|piping]] and a scarlet [[fascia (vestment)|fascia]] (sash-like belt). Occasionally, a cardinal wears a scarlet ''[[ferraiolo]]'' which is a cape worn over the shoulders, tied at the neck in a bow by narrow strips of cloth in the front, without any 'trim' or piping on it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title=Instruction on the dress, titles and coat-of-arms of cardinals, bishops and lesser prelates. | publisher=[[L'Osservatore Romano]], English ed. | date=17 April 1969 | pages=vol.4 | url=http://www.fiu.edu/~mirandas/instruction69.htm | accessdate=1 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is because of the scarlet color of cardinals' vesture that the [[cardinal (bird)|bird of the same name]] has become known as such.{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}

[[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholic]] cardinals continue to wear the normal dress appropriate to their liturgical tradition, though some may line their cassocks with scarlet and wear scarlet fascias, or in some cases, wear Eastern-style cassocks entirely of scarlet. (There is a photograph&lt;ref&gt;[http://photos1.blogger.com/blogger/6322/78/1600/SlypyjGalero1.jpg photograph]&lt;/ref&gt; of [[Josyf Slipyj]], [[Major Archbishop]] of the [[Ukrainian Catholic Church]] and Cardinal, wearing a galero on top of his red [[klobuk]].)

In previous times, at the [[consistory]] at which the pope named a new cardinal, he would bestow upon him a distinctive wide-brimmed hat called a [[galero]]. This custom has been discontinued,{{when|date=July 2012}} and the investiture now takes place with the scarlet biretta. In [[ecclesiastical heraldry]], however, the scarlet galero is still displayed on the cardinal's [[coat of arms]]. Cardinals had the right to display the galero in their cathedral, and when a cardinal died, it would be suspended from the ceiling above his tomb. Some cardinals will still have a galero made, even though it is not officially part of their apparel.{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}

To symbolize their bond with the [[papacy]], the pope gives each newly appointed cardinal a gold ring,&lt;ref&gt;[Michael Paulson [http://www.boston.com/news/globe/city_region/paulson/blog/2006/03/25/index.html Bling! examination of the ring of Cardinal O'Malley, with photos. Boston.com [[Boston Globe]]] 25 March 2006. Retrieved 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; which is traditionally [[hand-kiss|kissed]] by Catholics when greeting a cardinal (as with a [[bishop]]'s episcopal ring). The pope chooses the image on the outside: under [[Pope Benedict XVI]] it is a modern depiction of the crucifixion of Jesus, with [[Virgin Mary|Mary]] and [[John the Evangelist|John]] to each side. The ring includes the pope's coat of arms on the inside.

Cardinals have in [[canon law (Catholic Church)|canon law]] a &quot;privilege of forum&quot; (i.e., exemption from being judged by ecclesiastical tribunals of ordinary rank): only the pope is competent to judge them in matters subject to ecclesiastical jurisdiction (cases that refer to matters that are spiritual or linked with the spiritual, or with regard to infringement of ecclesiastical laws and whatever contains an element of sin, where culpability must be determined and the appropriate ecclesiastical penalty imposed). This does not exempt them from being judged for alleged violations of civil law. The pope either decides the case himself or delegates the decision to another tribunal, usually one of the tribunals or congregations of the Roman Curia. Absent such delegation, other [[ecclesiastical court]]s, even the [[Roman Rota]], are incompetent to judge a case against a cardinal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P5A.HTM Canon 1405 §1 and canon 1406 §2]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons|Cardinals’ coat of arms}}
{{Portal| Catholicism }}
[[Image:Cardinal Gavalin.jpg|thumb|right|150px|[[George Pell|Cardinal Pell]] wearing the ordinary dress of a cardinal: black cassock with scarlet (red) [[piping (sewing)|piping]] and buttons, scarlet [[fascia (vestment)|fascia]] (sash), pectoral cross on a chain, and a scarlet zucchetto.]]
[[Image:Missione del Guaricano-cardinale Tarcisio Bertone.jpg|right|150px|thumb|[[Tarcisio Bertone|Cardinal Bertone]] in dress for hot tropical countries (white cassock with scarlet piping and buttons)]]
*[[Henry I of Portugal|Cardinal-King]]
*[[Cardinal-Infante]]
*[[Cardinal-nephew]]
*[[Cardinal protector#Catholic|Cardinal protector]]
*[[College of Cardinals]] (organized by date of appointment)
*[[Consistory#Roman Catholic Church|Consistory]]
*[[Prince of the Church]]
*[[Size of the College of Cardinals]]
*[[List of the creations of the cardinals]]
*[[:Category:Lists of cardinals|Lists of cardinals]]
*[[List of living cardinals]]
*[[Catholic Church hierarchy#Cardinals|Catholic Church hierarchy]]
*[[Bishop (Catholic Church)#Cardinal|Bishop (Catholic Church)]]

==Bibliography==
*{{CathEncy | wstitle=Ecclesiastical Addresses | last=Battandier | first=Albert}}
&lt;!-- *Mirriam-Webster (1997 HTML edition). [https://www.cs.harvard.edu/oldwikis/data/mW/Mwed00000140.html Handbook of Style] — Clerical and Religious forms of address. Accessdate=2006-09-22. --&gt;
*{{cite book | last=Noonan, Jr. | first=James-Charles | title=The Church Visible: The Ceremonial Life and Protocol of the Roman Catholic Church | year=1996 | publisher=Viking | isbn=0-670-86745-4}}
*{{CathEncy | wstitle=Cardinal (1) | title=Cardinal | last=Sägmüller | first=Johannes Baptist}}

==References==
{{Reflist|3oem}}

==External links==
*Salvador Miranda. [http://www.fiu.edu/~mirandas/cardinals.htm The Cardinals of the Holy Roman Church]. A digital resource consisting of the biographical entries of the cardinals from 900 to 2009 and of the events and documents concerning the origin of the Roman cardinalate and its historical evolution
*[http://popes-and-papacy.com/wordpress/?p=571 Next Cardinal Creating Consistory by Pope Benedict XVI -- The Required Background Data] (including statistical data and links). Popes and the Papcy website (Anura Guruge). Retrieved 2010-09-08.
*[http://www.gcatholic.com/hierarchy/cardinals.htm Giga-Catholic Information on all Cardinals]
**[http://www.gcatholic.com/hierarchy/cardinals-alive-precedence.htm List of All Cardinals By Precedence] by Giga-Catholic Information
**[http://www.gcatholic.com/hierarchy/cardinals-title-c2.htm List of all Cardinal Titular Churches] by Giga-Catholic Information
**[http://www.gcatholic.com/hierarchy/cardinals-title-c3.htm List of all Cardinal Deaconries] by Giga-Catholic Information
* [http://www.catholic-pages.com/hierarchy/cardinals_list.asp Catholic-pages List of Cardinals]

{{catholicism}}

&lt;!-- categories in order of most specific to most general --&gt;

[[Category:College of Cardinals| ]]
[[Category:Ecclesiastical titles]]
[[Category:Bishops by type]]
[[Category:Religious leadership roles]]

{{Link GA|uk}}
{{Link FA|fi}}

[[ar:كاردينال]]
[[be:Кардынал]]
[[be-x-old:Кардынал]]
[[bg:Кардинал]]
[[br:Kardinal]]
[[ca:Cardenal]]
[[ceb:Kardenal (Katolisismo)]]
[[cs:Kardinál]]
[[da:Kardinal (katolske kirke)]]
[[de:Kardinal]]
[[et:Kardinal]]
[[el:Καρδινάλιος]]
[[eml:Cardinäl]]
[[es:Cardenal]]
[[eo:Kardinalo]]
[[eu:Kardinal (katolizismoa)]]
[[fa:کاردینال]]
[[fr:Cardinal (religion)]]
[[ga:Cairdinéal]]
[[gl:Cardeal (relixión)]]
[[ko:추기경]]
[[hr:Kardinal]]
[[io:Kardinalo]]
[[id:Kardinal]]
[[it:Cardinale]]
[[he:חשמן]]
[[ka:კარდინალი (რელიგია)]]
[[kk:Кардинал]]
[[sw:Kardinali]]
[[la:Cardinalis]]
[[lv:Kardināls]]
[[lb:Kardinol]]
[[lt:Kardinolas]]
[[lmo:Cardinal]]
[[hu:Bíboros]]
[[mk:Кардинал]]
[[mt:Kardinal]]
[[arz:كاردينال]]
[[my:ကာဒင်နယ်ဂိုဏ်းချုပ်]]
[[nl:Kardinaal (geestelijke)]]
[[ja:枢機卿]]
[[no:Kardinal]]
[[nn:Kardinal]]
[[uz:Cardinale]]
[[pl:Kardynał]]
[[pt:Cardeal]]
[[ro:Cardinal]]
[[ru:Кардинал]]
[[simple:Cardinal (Catholicism)]]
[[sk:Kardinál]]
[[sl:Kardinal]]
[[sr:Кардинал]]
[[sh:Kardinal]]
[[fi:Kardinaali]]
[[sv:Kardinal]]
[[tl:Kardenal (Katolisismo)]]
[[ta:கர்தினால்]]
[[th:พระคาร์ดินัล]]
[[tr:Kardinal]]
[[uk:Кардинал]]
[[vec:Cardinałe]]
[[vi:Hồng y]]
[[war:Kardinal (Katolisismo)]]
[[bat-smg:Kardėnuols]]
[[zh:樞機]]</text>
      <sha1>gb09ml09inyft3rfdtd275ruiwkqooi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
