<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Catechism of the Catholic Church</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>194260</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516367857</id>
      <parentid>515624871</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-06T20:53:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John of Reading</username>
        <id>11308236</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Typo/[[WP:AWB/GF|general]] fixing, replaced: Derivated → Derived using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16722">[[Image:Emblem of the Catechism of the Catholic Church.jpg|right|thumb|220px|The logo is adapted from a Christian tombstone in the [[Catacombs_of_Rome#Catacombs_of_Domitilla|catacombs of Domitilla]] in Rome&lt;ref&gt;From the ''Copyright Information'', pg. iv.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The  '''''Catechism of the Catholic Church''''' (or '''''CCC''''') is a [[catechism]] promulgated for the [[Catholic Church]] by [[Pope John Paul II]].

== Publication history ==
The decision to publish a catechism was taken at the Extraordinary Assembly of the [[Synod of Bishops (Catholic)|Synod of Bishops]] that was convened by [[Pope John Paul II]] on 25 January 1985 for the 20th anniversary of the close of the [[Second Vatican Council]], and in 1986, the pope put a commission composed of 12 bishops and cardinals in charge of the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;FIDEI DEPOSITUM&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19921011_fidei-depositum_en.html | title=FIDEI DEPOSITUM | accessdate=2007-10-05 | date=1992-10-11 | publisher=Libreria Editrice Vaticana}}&lt;/ref&gt; The commission was assisted by a seven member committee including diocesan bishops and experts in [[theology]] and [[catechesis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FIDEI DEPOSITUM&quot;/&gt;

The text was approved by [[Pope John Paul II]] on 25 June 1992, and promulgated by him on 11 October 1992, the 30th anniversary of the opening of the [[Second Vatican Council]], with his [[apostolic constitution]], ''[[Fidei depositum]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;FIDEI DEPOSITUM&quot;/&gt;

It was published in the French language in 1992&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Catéchisme de l'Église Catholique |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1992 |publisher=Mame/Plon |location=Tours/Paris |isbn=2-266-00585-5 |pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was then translated into many other languages. In the United States, the English translation was published by the U.S. bishops in 1994,&lt;ref&gt;copyright 1994, United States Catholic Conference, Inc., Libreria Editrice Vaticana&lt;/ref&gt; with a note that it was &quot;subject to revision according to the Latin typical edition (''editio typica'') when it is published.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Copyright Information, p. ii.)&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 15, 1997—the [[Solemnity]] of the [[Assumption of Mary|Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary]]—Pope John Paul II promulgated the [[Ecclesiastical Latin|Latin]] typical edition, with his [[apostolic letter]], ''Laetamur Magnopere''.&lt;ref&gt;The Latin-text copyright is 1994, 1997, Libreria Editrice Vaticana, Citta del Vaticano.&lt;/ref&gt; The Latin text, which became the official text of reference (''editio typica''),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ewtn.com/library/PAPALDOC/JP2LAETM.HTM | title=LATIN EDITION OF CATECHISM PROMULGATED | accessdate=2007-10-05 | date=1997-09-17 | publisher=[[L'Osservatore Romano]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; amended the contents of the provisional French text at a few points.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.scborromeo.org/ccc/updates.htm | title=MODIFICATIONS from the Edito Typica | accessdate=2007-10-05 | publisher=Amministrazione Del Patrimonio Della Sede Apostolica}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the changes consisted in the inclusion of the position on [[death penalty]] that is defended in [[John Paul II]]'s [[encyclical]] [[Evangelium Vitae]] of 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://old.usccb.org/sdwp/national/criminal/catechism.shtml|title=The death penalty and the catechism|date=|publisher=[[United States Conference of Catholic Bishops]]|accessdate=12 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result, the earlier translations from the French into other languages (including English) had to be amended and re-published as &quot;second editions&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;In the U.S., the bishops then published a new English translation, from the official Latin text. (English translation of the ''Catechism of the Catholic Church: Modifications from the Editio Typica'', copyright 1997, United States Catholic Conference, Inc.—Libreria Editrice Vaticana.) The U.S. bishops added a &quot;Glossary and ''Index Analyticus''&quot; (copyright 2000, United States Catholic Conference, Inc.) and published the new translation, with glossary and index, as the ''Catechism of the Catholic Church, Second Edition,'' &quot;revised in accordance with the official Latin text promulgated by Pope John Paul II&quot;. (From the title page.)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Doctrinal value ==
In [[Fidei depositum|Fidei Depositum]], [[Pope John Paul II]] declared that the Catechism of the Catholic Church was ''&quot;a valid and legitimate instrument for ecclesial communion and a sure norm for teaching the faith'',&lt;ref name=&quot;FIDEI DEPOSITUM&quot;/&gt; and stressed that it ''&quot;is not intended to replace the local catechisms duly approved by the ecclesiastical authorities, the diocesan Bishops and the Episcopal Conferences&quot;''.&lt;ref name=&quot;FIDEI DEPOSITUM&quot;/&gt;

== Contents ==
A [[catechism]] has been defined as &quot;a summary of principles, often in question-and-answer format&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bennetyee.org//http_webster.cgi?catechism&amp;method=exact]&lt;/ref&gt; Documents of religious instruction have been written since the beginning of Christianity and the catechism is typically an assemblage of these smaller documents into one large compilation of Church doctrine and teachings.

The Catechism of the Catholic Church, for which the usual English-language abbreviation is ''CCC'',{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}} is instead a source on which to base such catechisms (e.g. ''[[Youcat]]'' and the ''[[United States Catholic Catechism for Adults|U.S. Catholic Catechism for Adults]]'') and other expositions of Catholic doctrine, called a &quot;major catechism.&quot; It was given, as stated in the [[Apostolic Constitution]] ''[[Fidei depositum]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19921011_fidei-depositum_en.html]&lt;/ref&gt; with which its publication was ordered, &quot;that it may be a sure and authentic reference text for teaching catholic doctrine and particularly for preparing local catechisms.&quot; The ''CCC'' is in fact not in question and answer format. What corresponds the more common idea of a catechism is perhaps the ''Compendium of the Catechism of the Catholic Church''.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

''CCC'' is arranged in four principal parts:
* The Profession of Faith (the [[Apostle's Creed]])
* The Celebration of the Christian Mystery (the Sacred [[Liturgy]], especially the [[sacrament]]s)
* Life in Christ (including [[The Ten Commandments in Roman Catholic theology]])
* Christian Prayer (including [[Lord's Prayer|The Lord's Prayer]])

This scheme is often referred to as the “Four Pillars” of the Faith.  The contents are abundantly footnoted with references to sources of the teaching, in particular the [[Bible|Scriptures]], the [[Church Fathers]], and the [[Ecumenical council|Ecumenical Councils]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usccb.org/catechism/resource/lev94art.htm#structure]&lt;/ref&gt; and other authoritative Catholic statements, principally those issued by recent Popes.

The section on Scripture in the ''CCC'' (nos. 101–141) recovers the Patristic tradition of &quot;spiritual [[exegesis]]&quot; as further developed through the scholastic doctrine of the &quot;four senses.&quot; This return to spiritual exegesis is based on the Second Vatican Council's 1965 &quot;Dogmatic Constitution on Divine Revelation&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19651118_dei-verbum_en.html &quot;Dogmatic Constitution on Divine Revelation&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; which taught that Scripture should be &quot;read and interpreted in light of the same Spirit by whom it was written&quot; (''Dei Verbum'' 12). The ''CCC'' amplifies ''Dei Verbum'' by specifying  that the necessary spiritual interpretation should be sought through the  four senses of Scripture (nos. 111, 113, 115–119),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__PQ.HTM (nos. 111, 113, 115–119)]&lt;/ref&gt; which encompass the literal sense and the three spiritual senses (allegorical, moral, and anagogical).

The literal sense (no. 116) pertains to the meaning of the words themselves, including any figurative meanings. The spiritual senses (no. 117) pertain to the significance of the things (persons, places, objects or events) denoted by the words. Of the three spiritual senses, the allegorical sense is foundational. It relates persons, events, and institutions of earlier covenants to those of later covenants, and especially to the New Covenant. Building on the allegorical sense, the moral sense instructs in regard to action, and the anagogical sense points to man's final destiny. The teaching of the ''CCC'' on Scripture has encouraged the recent pursuit of [[Covenantal Theology (Roman Catholic)|covenantal theology]], an approach that employs the four senses to structure salvation history via the biblical covenants.

== Comments ==

American Catholic bishops have stated that, though theological opinion was not intended to be a part of ''CCC'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.usccb.org/catechism/resource/lev94art.htm#structure | title=The New Catechism: An Overview | accessdate=2007-10-05 | date=1994-02-07 |publisher=United States Conference of Catholic Bishops Office for the Catechism | last=Levada | first=Archbishop William J. |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070929103226/http://www.usccb.org/catechism/resource/lev94art.htm#structure &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; it in fact &quot;does not distinguish between matters of faith and theological opinion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first=Michael J. | last=Wrenn |coauthors=Whitehead, Kenneth D. | title=Flawed Expectations: The Reception of the Catechism of the Catholic Church | publisher=[[Ignatius Press]] | year=1996 | isbn=0-89870-591-6 | page=208}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A commentator, quoting [[Pope Paul VI]] to the effect that the Catholic Church has made a conscious attempt to adopt &quot;a more humble and fraternal attitude ... that of a search for the truth&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Amerio&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first=Romano | last=Amerio | title=Iota Unum: A Study of Changes in the Catholic Church in the XXth Century | year=1996 | publisher=Sarto House | isbn=0-9639032-1-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; claims that ''CCC'' displays a shift away from presenting dogma as fact and toward presenting the Catholic faith itself as a search for truth. Referring also to the statement in the Apostolic Constitution  ''Fidei Depositum'' that &quot;the contents are often presented in a new way in order to respond to the questions of our age,&quot; he claims that the &quot;new catechesis…attempts to produce [[existentialism|existential]] reactions rather than intellectual conviction.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amerio&quot;/&gt;

In 1992, [[Joseph Ratzinger|Joseph]] [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger|Ratzinger]] (now [[Pope Benedict XVI]]) noted&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.usccb.org/catechism/resource/rat92art.htm#intro | title=The Catechism of the Catholic Church in Context |accessdate=2007-10-05 | date=1992-12-09 | publisher=United States Conference of Catholic Bishops Office for the Catechism |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070926234355/http://www.usccb.org/catechism/resource/rat92art.htm#intro &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;:

{{cquote|It clearly show[s] that the problem of what we must do as human beings, of how we should live our lives so that we and the world may become just, is the essential problem of our day, and basically of all ages. After the fall of ideologies, the problem of man—the moral problem—is presented to today's context in a totally new way: What should we do? How does life become just? What can give us and the whole world a future which is worth living? Since the catechism treats these questions, it is a book which interests many people, far beyond purely theological or ecclesial circles.}}

== Derived works ==
The ''Compendium of the Catechism of the Catholic Church'' was published in 2005, and the first edition in English in 2006. It is a more concise and [[dialogic]] version of the CCC. The text is available in twelve languages on the Vatican website,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc/index.htm Vatican website]&lt;/ref&gt; which also gives the text of the Catechism itself in nine languages.

[[YouCat]], a catechism for the youth based on the Catechism of the Catholic Church and on the Compendium of the catechism of the Catholic Church, was published in 2011. Some critics argue that its teachings on the status of non-Catholic religions, homosexuality, contraception, euthanasia, evolution, and Scripture are departures from traditional Catholic doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://catholicintl.com/index.php/component/content/article/54-pastoral/570-the-vaticans-youcat-catechism-weak-on-homosexuality-contraception-euthanasia-evolution-and-scripture The Vatican’s “YouCat” Catechism: Weak on Homosexuality, Contraception, Euthanasia, Evolution, and Scripture]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lifesitenews.com/news/youth-catechism-also-wrong-on-euthanasia-other-religions-vatican-admits/ Youth Catechism Also Wrong on Euthanasia, Other Religions, Vatican Admits]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
&lt;span id=&quot;ExtLinksEnglishCCC&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
*''Catechism of the Catholic Church'' – English translation (U.S.A., 2nd edition) (English translation of the ''Catechism of the Catholic Church: Modifications from the Editio Typica'', copyright 1997, United States Catholic Conference, Inc., Libreria Editrice Vaticana) (Glossary and ''Index Analyticus'', copyright 2000, U.S. Catholic Conference, Inc.). ISBN 1-57455-110-8
*''Compendium of the Catechism of the Catholic Church'' – English translation (USCCB, 2006). ISBN 1-57455-720-3
*'''United States Catholic Catechism for Adults''' – English &quot;... resource for preparation of catechumens in the Rite of Christian Initiation of Adults and for ongoing catechesis of adults&quot; ([http://www.usccbpublishing.org/productdetails.cfm?sku=5-450 USCCB], 2006). ISBN 1-57455-450-6

===Sites that carry the full ''CCC'' text ===
*[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc/index.htm Holy See - Archive - Catechism of the Catholic Church]; in Traditional Chinese, English, French, Italian, Latin, Latvian, [[Malagasy]], Portuguese, and Spanish (as of 17 July 2011)
*[http://overkott.dyndns.org/ccc-search.htm Fulltext Search] Latin ''[[editio typica]]''; English text revised in accordance with the Latin ''[[editio typica]]''
*[http://www.usccb.org/catechism/text/index.shtml United States Conference of Catholic Bishops]; English – Second edition (revised in accordance with the Latin ''[[editio typica]]'')
*[http://www.scborromeo.org/ccc.htm St. Charles Borromeo Catholic Church, Picayune, Miss., USA]; English – Second edition (revised in accordance with the Latin ''[[editio typica]]''), with full text search and list of changes between the First and Second editions

===Sites that carry comments on the ''CCC''===
*[http://www.usccb.org/catechism/ US Catholic Bishops Conference: Office for the Catechism]
*[http://www.catholicity.com/catechism/  Catechism of the Catholic Church Simplified] - A condensation of the text, not the text itself
*[http://www.sspx.org/New_Catechism/new_catechism__is_it_catholic_I.htm The New Catechism: Is it Catholic?]

===Text of the ''Compendium of the CCC''===
*[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc/index.htm Compendium at Vatican/Holy See website] available in Byelorussian, English, French, German, Hungarian, Indonesian, Italian, Lithuanian, Portuguese, Romanian, Russian, Slovenian, Spanish, and Swedish (as of 17 July 2011)
{{Commons category|Catechisms}}
{{John Paul II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Catechism Of The Catholic Church}}
[[Category:Catechisms of the Catholic Church]]
[[Category:Catholic theology and doctrine| ]]

[[be:Катэхізіс Каталіцкай царквы]]
[[ca:Catecisme de l'Església Catòlica]]
[[ceb:Katesismo sa Simbahang Katoliko]]
[[cs:Katechismus katolické církve]]
[[da:Katekismus for den Katolske Kirke]]
[[de:Katechismus der Katholischen Kirche]]
[[es:Catecismo de la Iglesia católica]]
[[eo:Katekismo de la Katolika Eklezio]]
[[fr:Catéchisme de l'Église catholique]]
[[ko:가톨릭교회 교리서]]
[[id:Katekismus Gereja Katolik]]
[[it:Catechismo della Chiesa Cattolica]]
[[jv:Katekismus Gréja Katulik]]
[[sw:Katekisimu ya Kanisa Katoliki]]
[[la:Catechismus Catholicae Ecclesiae]]
[[nl:Catechismus van de Katholieke Kerk]]
[[ja:カトリック教会のカテキズム]]
[[no:Den katolske kirkes katekisme]]
[[pl:Katechizm Kościoła Katolickiego]]
[[pt:Catecismo da Igreja Católica]]
[[ru:Катехизис Католической церкви]]
[[simple:Catechism of the Catholic Church]]
[[sk:Katechizmus Katolíckej cirkvi]]
[[sv:Katolska kyrkans katekes]]
[[uk:Катехизм католицької церкви]]
[[zh:天主教教理]]</text>
      <sha1>126o302j7ponc6gdxpzmgt4dk5z8gcm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
