<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Cherub</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>159239</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520275520</id>
      <parentid>520240998</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T15:29:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Edmapa</username>
        <id>4547010</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 520240581 by [[Special:Contributions/69.133.109.6|69.133.109.6]] ([[User talk:69.133.109.6|talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16298">{{About|a type of angelic being|the depictions of winged babies erroneously called cherubs|Putto|other uses}}
{{Multiple issues|cleanup=January 2012|refimprove=January 2012|citation style=June 2012}}
[[Image:Giusto de' menabuoi, adamo ed eva, 1376-78, battistero di Padova.jpg|thumb|right|250px|St. Michael the Archangel guarding the entrance of the [[Garden of Eden]]&lt;ref name=&quot;EDEN&quot;&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Genesis+3:24&amp;version=9 Genesis 3:24 (King James Version)] at Bible Gateway.com&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Giusto de' Menabuoi]] ''ca.'' 1377.]]

A '''cherub''' ([[Hebrew language|Heb]]. '''כְּרוּב''', pl. '''כְּרוּבִים''', [[English language|eng.]] trans ''kərūv'', pl. ''kərūvîm'', dual ''kərūvāyim'' [[Latin|lat.]] ''cherub[us]'', pl ''cherubi[m]'', [[Akkadian language|Assyrian]] '''ܟܪܘܒܐ''') is a type of spiritual being mentioned in the [[Hebrew Bible]] and cited later on in the [[Christian biblical canons]], usually associated with the presence of God. The plural can be written as '''cherubim''', '''cherubims'''&lt;sup&gt;KJV&lt;/sup&gt; or '''cherubs'''. In modern English the word ''cherub'' is sometimes used for what are strictly [[putti]] — baby or toddler angels in art. This article is concerned with the original sense of the word.

Cherubim are mentioned in the [[Torah]] (five books of Moses), the [[Book of Ezekiel]], the [[ Book of Genesis]], and the [[Book of Isaiah]]. They are also mentioned in the books of [[1 Kings]], [[2 Kings]], [[1 Chronicles]], and [[2 Chronicles]] mainly in the construction of the [[Temple in Jerusalem|House of God]]. There is only one mention in the New Testament, in Hebrews 9:5, referring to the [[mercy seat]] of the [[Ark of the Covenant]].

==Origins==

The Hebrew term ''cherubim'' is [[cognate]] with the [[Assyria]]n term ''karabu'', [[Akkadian language|Akkad]]ian term ''kuribu'', and [[Babylonia]]n term ''karabu''; the Assyrian term means 'great, mighty', but the Akkadian and Babylonian cognates mean 'propitious, blessed'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;Jewish Encyclopedia&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;devaux&quot;&gt;De Vaux, Roland (tr. John McHugh), ''Ancient Israel: Its Life and Institutions'' (NY, McGraw-Hill, 1961)&lt;/ref&gt; In some regions the Assyro-Babylonian term came to refer in particular to spirits which served [[Mesopotamian mythology|the gods]], in particular to the [[shedu]] (human-headed winged [[Bull (mythology)|bull]]s);&lt;ref name=&quot;devaux&quot; /&gt; the Assyrians sometimes referred to these as ''kirubu'', a term grammatically related to ''karabu''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;/&gt; They were originally a version of the [[shedu]], protective deities sometimes found as pairs of colossal statues either side of objects to be protected, such as doorways.&lt;ref name=&quot;devaux&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;peake&quot;&gt;''[[Peake's commentary on the Bible]]''&lt;/ref&gt; However, although the shedu were popular in [[Mesopotamia]], [[archaeology|archaeological remains]] from the [[Levant]] suggest that they were quite rare in the immediate vicinity of the Israelites.&lt;ref name=&quot;peake&quot; /&gt; The related [[Lammasu]] (human-headed winged [[lion]]s — to which the [[sphinx]] is similar in appearance), on the other hand, were the most popular winged-creature in [[Phoenicia]]n art, and so scholars suspect that Cherubim were originally a form of Lammasu.&lt;ref name=&quot;peake&quot; /&gt; In particular, in a scene reminiscent of Ezekiel's dream, the [[Megiddo Ivories]] — [[ivory]] carvings found at [[Tel Megiddo|Megiddo]] (which became a major Israelite city) — depict an unknown king being carried on his throne by hybrid winged-creatures.&lt;ref name=&quot;wright&quot;&gt;Wright, G. Ernest, ''Biblical Archaeology'' (Philadelphia, Westminster Press, 1957)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Louvre lion gate DSC00914.jpg|thumb|left|A pair of ''shedu''&lt;!--despite the filename--&gt;, protecting a doorway (the body of the creatures extending into the distance).]]
The Lammasu was originally depicted as having a king's head, a lion's body, and an eagle's wings, but because of the artistic beauty of the wings, these rapidly became the most prominent part in imagery;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;/&gt; wings later came to be bestowed on men, thus forming the stereotypical image of an [[angel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wright&quot; /&gt; The [[griffin]] — a similar creature but with an eagle's head rather than that of a king — has also been proposed as an origin, arising in Israelite culture as a result of [[Hittites|Hittite]] usage of griffins (rather than being depicted as aggressive beasts, Hittite depictions show them seated calmly, as if guarding),&lt;ref name=&quot;wright&quot; /&gt; and some have proposed that ''griffin'' may be cognate to ''cherubim'',&lt;ref name=&quot;propp&quot;&gt;William H. Propp, ''Exodus 19-40'', volume 2A of ''The Anchor Bible'', New York: Doubleday, 2006, ISBN 0-385-24693-5, ''Notes'' to Exodus 15:18, page 386, referencing:[[Julius Wellhausen]], [[Prolegomena zur Geschichte Israels|''Prolegomena to the History of Israel'']], Edinburgh: Black, 1885, page 304.&lt;br /&gt;Also see: [[Robert S. P. Beekes]],''Etymological Dictionary of Greek'', volume 1, Leiden and Boston: Brill, 2010 ISBN 978-90-04-17420-7, page 289, entry for γρυπος,&quot;From the archaeological perspective, origin in Asia Minor (and the Near East: Elam) is very probable.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; but Lammasu were significantly more important in Levantine culture, and thus more likely to be the origin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;/&gt;

Early Semitic tradition conceived the cherubim as guardians, being devoid of human feelings, and holding a duty both to represent the gods and to guard sanctuaries from intruders, in a comparable way to an account found on Tablet 9 of the inscriptions found at [[Nimrud]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;/&gt; In this view, cherubim, like the shedu, were probably originally depictions of storm deities, especially the storm winds.&lt;ref name=&quot;propp&quot; /&gt; This view is offered as a hypothesis to explain the reason for cherubim being described as acting as the chariot of the {{LORD}} in Ezekiel's visions, the [[Books of Samuel]],&lt;ref&gt;1 Samuel 4:4, 2 Samuel 6:2, 2 Samuel 22:11&lt;/ref&gt; the parallel passages in the later [[Book of Chronicles]],&lt;ref&gt;1 Chronicles 13:6&lt;/ref&gt; and passages in the early [[Book of Psalms|Psalms]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot;/&gt; &quot;and he rode upon a cherub and did fly: and he was seen upon the wings of the wind&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;2 Samuel 22:11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Psalms 18:10&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the Bible==
Cherubim first appear in the Bible in the [[Garden of Eden]], to guard the way to the [[Tree of life]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EDEN&quot;/&gt;

In [[Isaiah]] 37:16, [[Hezekiah]] prays, addressing [[Yahweh]] as &quot;enthroned above the Cherubim&quot; (referring to the [[mercy seat]]).

Cherubim feature at some length in the [[Book of Ezekiel]]. When they first appear in chapter one, when Ezekiel was &quot;by the river Chebar&quot;, they are not called ''cherubim'', but he saw &quot;the likeness of four living creatures&quot;. (Ezekiel 1:5) Each of them had four faces and four wings, with straight feet with a sole like the sole of a calf's foot, and &quot;hands of a man&quot; under their wings. Each had four faces: The face of a man, the face of a lion on the right side, the face of an ox on the left side, and the face of an eagle. (Ezekiel 1:6-10)

In Ezekiel chapter ten, another full description of the Cherubim appears with slight differences in details. Three of the four faces are the same; man, lion and eagle; but where chapter one had the face of an ox, Ezekiel 10:14 says &quot;face of a cherub&quot;. Ezekiel equates the Cherubim of chapter ten with the living creature of chapter one by saying: &quot;This ''is'' the living creature that I saw by the river of Chebar&quot;, in Ezekiel 10:15, and in Ezekiel 10:20 he said: &quot;This ''is'' the living creature that I saw under the God of Israel by the river of Chebar; and I knew that they ''were'' the cherubim.&quot;

In a psalm of David that appears in 2 Samuel 22:11 and Psalms 18:10, David said that the {{LORD}} &quot;rode upon a cherub, and did fly: and he was seen upon the wings of the wind.&quot;

The words ''Cherub'' and ''Cherubim'' appear many other times in the holy scriptures, referring to the Cherubim of beaten gold on the mercy seat of the [[Ark of the Covenant]], and images on the curtains of the tabernacle, and in Solomon's temple, including two Cherubim made of olive wood overlaid with gold that were ten cubits high.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+kings%206:23-6:35&amp;version=KJV 1 kings 6:23-6:35 KJV - And within the oracle he made two - Bible Gateway]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-biblical Judaism==
[[File:Tetramorph meteora.jpg|thumb|A cherub, according to traditional Christian [[iconography]].]]
Many forms of [[Judaism]] teach belief in the existence of angels, including Cherubim within the [[Jewish angelic hierarchy]]. The existences of angels is generally widely contested within traditional rabbinic Judaism; there is, however, a wide range of views on what angels actually are, and how literally one should interpret biblical passages associated with them.

In [[Kabbalah]] there has long been a strong belief in Cherubim, with the Cherubim, and other angels, regarded as having mystical roles. The [[Zohar]], a highly significant collection of books in Jewish mysticism, states that the Cherubim were led by one of their number, named Kerubiel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia&quot; /&gt;

On the other end of the philosophical spectrum is the view of Rabbi Moshe ben Maimon, better known as [[Maimonides]]. He had a neo-Aristotelian interpretation of the Bible. Maimonides writes that to the wise man, one sees that what the Bible and Talmud refer to as &quot;angels&quot; are actually allusions for the various laws of nature; they are the principles by which the physical universe operates. &quot;Guide of the Perplexed&quot; II:4 and II:6.

:For all forces are angels! How blind, how perniciously blind are the naive?! If you told someone who purports to be a sage of Israel that the Deity sends an angel who enters a woman's womb and there forms an embryo, he would think this a miracle and accept it as a mark of the majesty and power of the Deity, despite the fact that he believes an angel to be a body of fire one third the size of the entire world. All this, he thinks, is possible for God. But if you tell him that God placed in the sperm the power of forming and demarcating these organs, and that ''this'' is the angel, or that all forms are produced by the Active Intellect; that here is the angel, the &quot;vice-regent of the world&quot; constantly mentioned by the sages, then he will recoil.
:For he {the naive person} does not understand that the true majesty and power are in the bringing into being of forces which are active in a thing although they cannot be perceived by the senses....Thus the Sages reveal to the aware that the imaginative faculty is also called an angel; and the mind is called a '''cherub'''. How beautiful this will appear to the sophisticated mind, and how disturbing to the primitive.&quot;

[[Maimonides]] says (Guide for the Perplexed III:45) that the figures of the cherubayim were placed in the sanctuary only to preserve among the people the belief in angels, there being two in order that the people might not be led to believe that they were the image of God.

[[Reform Judaism]] and [[Reconstructionist Judaism]] generally either drop references to angels or interpret them metaphorically{{citation needed|date= July 2011}}.

Cherubs are discussed within the [[midrash]] literature. The two cherubayim placed by [[God]] at the entrance of paradise (Gen. iii. 24) were angels created on the third day, and therefore they had no definite shape; appearing either as men or women, or as spirits or angelic beings (Genesis Rabbah xxi., end). The cherubim were the first objects created in the universe (Tanna debe Eliyahu R., i. beginning). The following sentence of the Midrash is characteristic: &quot;When a man sleeps, the body tells to the neshamah (soul) what it has done during the day; the neshamah then reports it to the nefesh (spirit), the nefesh to the angel, the angel to the cherub, and the cherub to the seraph, who then brings it before God (Leviticus Rabbah xxii.; Eccl. Rabbah x. 20).

A midrash states that when Pharaoh pursued Israel at the Red Sea, God took a cherub from the wheels of His throne and flew to the spot, for God inspects the heavenly worlds while sitting on a cherub. The cherub, however, is &quot;something not material&quot;, and is carried by God, not vice versa (Midr. Teh. xviii. 15; Canticles Rabbah i. 9).

In the passages of the [[Talmud]] that describe the heavens and their inhabitants, the seraphim, ofannim, and ḥayyot are mentioned, but not the cherubim (Ḥag. 12b); and the ancient liturgy also mentions only these three classes.
[[Image:Ezekiel's vision.jpg|right|thumb|300px|One traditional depiction of the cherubim and chariot vision, based on the description by Ezekiel.]]
In the [[Talmud]], [[Yose ha-Gelili]] holds,&lt;ref&gt;[[Berakhot (Talmud)|Berakhot]] 49b&lt;/ref&gt; when the [[Birkat HaMazon]] (Grace after Meals) is recited by at least ten thousand seated at one meal, a special blessing, &quot;Blessed is Ha-Shem our God, the God of Israel, [[Shekhinah|who dwells]] between the Cherubim&quot;, is added to [[Jewish services|the regular liturgy]].

==Catholicism==
In [[Catholic]] [[theology]], following the writings of [[Pseudo-Dionysius the Areopagite|Pseudo-Dionysius]], the cherubim are the second highest rank in the [[Christian angelic hierarchy|angelic hierarchy]], following the [[Seraph]]im.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.esoteric.msu.edu/VolumeII/CelestialHierarchy.html Dionysius the Areopagite's Celestial Hierarchy] - See Chapter VII&lt;/ref&gt; In western art, [[Putto|Putti]] are sometimes mistaken for Cherubim, although they look nothing alike.

==Depictions==
There were no cherubim in [[Herod's Temple|Herodian reconstruction of the Temple]], but according to some authorities, its walls were painted with figures of cherubim.&lt;ref&gt;Yoma 54a&lt;/ref&gt; In Christian art they are often represented with the faces of a lion, ox, eagle, and man peering out from the center of an array of four wings (Ezekiel 1:5-11, 10:12,21 Revelation 4:8); ([[seraphim]] have six); the most frequently encountered descriptor applied to cherubim in Christianity is many-eyed, and in depictions the wings are often shown covered with a multitude of eyes (showing them to be all seeing beings). Since the [[Renaissance]], in Western Christianity cherubim have become confused with [[putto|putti]]—innocent souls, looking like winged children, that sing praises to God daily—that can be seen in innumerable church [[fresco]]es and in the work of painters such as [[Raffaello Santi|Raphael]].

{{Commons|Cherubs}}

==See also==
* [[Cupid]] and [[Kamadeva]]
* [[Cherubism]] (medical condition)
* [[Christian angelic hierarchy|Hierarchy of Angels]]
* [[Putto]]
* [[Seraph]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Yaniv, Bracha, ''The Cherubim on Torah Ark Valances'', Jewish Art Department, [[Bar-Ilan University]], published in ''Assaph: Studies in Art History'', Vol.4, 1999

==External links==
* ''Jewish Encyclopedia'': [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=434&amp;letter=C Cherub]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03646c.htm ''Catholic Encyclopedia'':] Cherubim
* [http://www.oztorah.com/2009/09/the-cherubim-some-problems-and-pointers/ The Cherubim - some pointers and problems by Rabbi Dr Raymond Apple]

{{Christian angelic hierarchy}}

[[Category:Angels in Judaism]]
[[Category:Angels in Christianity]]
[[Category:Tabernacle and Jerusalem Temples]]
[[Category:Hebrew Bible]]
[[Category:Classes of angel]]

[[be:Херувім]]
[[bg:Херувим]]
[[ca:Querubí]]
[[cs:Cherub]]
[[da:Kerub]]
[[de:Cherub]]
[[el:Χερουβείμ]]
[[es:Querubín]]
[[eo:Kerubo]]
[[fr:Chérubin]]
[[ko:커룹]]
[[hy:Քերովբեներ]]
[[hr:Kerubin]]
[[io:Kerubo]]
[[id:Kerub]]
[[it:Cherubino]]
[[he:כרוב (תנ&quot;ך)]]
[[ka:ქერუბიმი]]
[[la:Cherubim]]
[[lt:Cherubinas]]
[[hu:Kerub]]
[[ml:കെരൂബ്]]
[[ms:Kerub]]
[[nl:Cherubijn]]
[[ja:智天使]]
[[no:Kjeruber]]
[[nn:Kjerubar]]
[[pl:Cherub]]
[[pt:Querubim]]
[[ro:Heruvim]]
[[ru:Херувимы]]
[[sk:Cherubín]]
[[sr:Херувими]]
[[sh:Kerubin]]
[[fi:Kerubi]]
[[sv:Kerub]]
[[tl:Kerubin]]
[[th:เครูบ]]
[[uk:Херувим]]
[[bat-smg:Cherubins]]
[[zh:智天使]]</text>
      <sha1>lk0lws26sno9fcnwy4zvge9mevmzozm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
