<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Child sacrifice</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>54385</id>
    <revision>
      <id>511482280</id>
      <parentid>510238284</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-09T04:08:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrescoBot</username>
        <id>9021902</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/Links|link syntax/spacing]] and minor changes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16521">{{See also|Religious abuse|Infanticide}}

'''Child sacrifice''' is the [[ritual]]istic killing of [[child]]ren in order to please, propitiate or force a [[god]] or [[supernatural]] beings in order to achieve a desired result. As such, it is a form of [[human sacrifice]].

{{Homicide}}

==Pre-Columbian cultures==
{{Main|Child sacrifice in pre-Columbian cultures}}

===Aztec culture===
[[Archeologist]]s have found remains of 42 children sacrificed to [[Tlaloc]] (and a few to [[Ehécatl]], [[Quetzalcoatl]] and [[Huitzilopochtli]]) in the offerings of the [[Great Pyramid of Tenochtitlan]] by the [[Aztecs]] of pre-Columbian [[Mexico]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.conaculta.gob.mx/saladeprensa/2002/25mar/tlaloc.htm – article in Spanish&lt;/ref&gt; {{further2|[[Tlaloc#Rites and rituals]]}}

===Inca culture===
The [[Inca]] culture sacrificed children in a ritual called ''[[capacocha]]''. Their frozen corpses are still being discovered in the [[South America]]n mountaintops. The first of these corpses, a female child who had died from a blow to the skull, was discovered in 1995 by Johan Reinhard.&lt;ref&gt;http://gallery.sjsu.edu/sacrifice/precolumbian.html - &quot;Pre-Columbian Andean Sacrifices&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Other methods of sacrifice included [[strangulation]] and simply leaving the children, who had been given an intoxicating drink, to lose consciousness in the extreme cold and low-oxygen conditions of the mountaintop, and to die of [[Hypothermia|exposure]].

===Moche culture===
The [[Moche]] of northern [[Peru]] practiced mass sacrifices of men and boys.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.exn.ca/mummies/story.asp?id=1999041452 – [[Discovery Channel]] article&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancient Near East==
=== Tanakh (Hebrew Bible) ===
References in the Tanakh point to an awareness of human sacrifice in the history of [[ancient Near Eastern]] practice. The king of Moab gives his firstborn son and heir as a whole burnt offering (''olah'', as used of the Temple sacrifice). It is apparently effective, as his enemy is promptly repelled by a 'great wrath' ({{bibleverse|2|Kings|3:27|HE}}). In the book of the prophet [[Micah (prophet)|Micah]], one asks, 'Shall I give my firstborn for my sin, the fruit of my body for the sin of my soul?' ({{bibleverse||Micah|6:7|HE}}), and receives a response, 'He has shown all you people what is good. And what does Yahweh require of you? To act justly and to love mercy and to walk humbly with your God.' ({{bibleverse||Micah|6:8|HE}}) The Tanakh also implies that the [[Ammon (nation)|Ammonites]] offered child sacrifices to [[Moloch]].

In Leviticus 18:21, 20:3 and Deuteronomy 12:30-31, 18:10, the [[Torah]] contains a number of imprecations against and laws forbidding child sacrifice. [[James Kugel]] argues that the Torah's specifically forbidding child sacrifice indicates that it happened in Israel as well.&lt;ref&gt;&quot; It was not just among Israel's neighbors that child sacrifice was countenanced, but apparently within Israeli itself. Why else would biblical law specifically forbid such things – and with such vehemence?&quot; [[James Kugel]] (2008). ''How to Read the Bible'' , p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mark S. Smith]] argues that the mention of &quot;Topeth&quot; in Isaiah 30:27–33 indicates an acceptance of child sacrifice in the early Jerusalem practices, to which the law in Leviticus 20:2–5 forbidding child sacrifice is a response.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;These passages indicate that in the seventh century child sacrifice was a Judean practice performed in the name of Yahweh…In Isaiah 30:27-33 there is no offense taken at the tophet, the precinct of child sacrifice. It would appear that the Jerusalemite cult included child sacrifice under Yahwistic patronage; it is this that Leviticus 20:2-5 deplores.&quot; [[Mark S. Smith]] (2002). ''The early history of God: Yahweh and the other deities in ancient Israel'', pp. 172–178.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jon D. Levenson]], [[Susan Nidditch]] and [[Susan Ackerman]] have stated that at least some [[Israelites]] believed child sacrifice was a legitimate part of ancient Israelite religion.&lt;ref&gt;
*Jon D. Levenson (1993). ''The Death and Resurrection of the Beloved Son'', Yale University Press, p. 5. &quot;only at a particular stage rather late in the history of Israel was child sacrifice branded as counter to the will of YHWH and thus ipso facto idolatrous.&quot;
*Susan Nidditch (1993). ''War in the Hebrew Bible: A Study in the Ethics of Violence'', Oxford University Press, p. 47. &quot;While there is considerable controversy about the matter, the consensus over the last decade concludes that child sacrifice was a part of ancient Israelite religion to large segments of Israelite communities of various periods.&quot;
*Susan Ackerman (1992). ''Under Every Green Tree: Popular Religion in Sixth-Century Judah'', Scholars Press, p. 137. &quot;the cult of child sacrifice was felt in some circles to be a legitimate expression of Yawistic faith.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

{{bibleverse||Genesis|22|HE}} relates the [[binding of Isaac]], in which [[God]] tests [[Abraham]] by asking him to present his son, [[Isaac]], as a sacrifice on [[Moriah|Mount Moriah]]. No reason is given within the text. Abraham agrees to this command without arguing. The story ends with an [[angel]] stopping Abraham at the last minute and making Isaac's sacrifice unnecessary by providing a ram, caught in some nearby bushes, to be sacrificed instead. [[Francesca Stavrakopoulou]] has speculated that it is possible that the story &quot;contains traces of a tradition in which Abraham does sacrifice Isaac.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It may be that the biblical story contains traces of a tradition in which Abraham does sacrifice Isaac, for in Gen.22:19 Abraham appears to return from the mountain without Isaac&quot;. [[Francesca Stavrakopoulou]] (2004). ''King Manasseh and child sacrifice: biblical distortions of historical realities'', pp. 193–194.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Richard Elliott Friedman]] has argued that the story may have originally had Abraham carrying out the sacrifice of Isaac, but that later repugnance at the idea of a human sacrifice led a redactor to add the lines in which a ram is substituted for Isaac.&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard Elliott Friedman]] (2003). ''The Bible With Sources Revealed'', p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt; Rabbi A.I. Kook, first Chief Rabbi of Israel, stressed that the climax of the story, commanding Abraham not to sacrifice Isaac, is the whole point: to put an end to the ritual of child sacrifice, which contradicts the morality of a perfect and giving (not taking) monotheistic God.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Olat Reiya&quot;, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another instance of human sacrifice mentioned in the Tanakh is the sacrifice of [[Jephthah]]'s daughter in {{bibleverse||Judges|11|HE}}. Jephthah is victorious in battle against the children of Ammon and vows to sacrifice to God whatsoever comes to greet him at the door when he returns home. The vow is stated in {{bibleverse||Judges|11:31|HE}} as
:Then it shall be, that whatsoever cometh forth of the doors of my house to meet me, when I return in peace from the children of Ammon, shall surely be the LORD's, and I will offer it up for a burnt offering''.&quot; When he returns from battle, his virgin daughter runs out to greet him. That he actually does sacrifice her is shown in verse 11:39 &quot;''And it came to pass at the end of two months, that she returned unto her father, who did with her according to his vow which he had vowed''&quot;. This example seems to be the exception rather than the rule, however, as the verse continues &quot;''And she was a virgin. From this comes the Israelite custom that each year the young women of Israel go out for four days to commemorate the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite.''&quot; However, some have questioned the traditional interpretation of the literal sacrifice of Jephthah's daughter. There is evidence to support that her sacrifice was in fact, not her life, but living in perpetual virginity. See [[Jephthah#Sacrifice controversy|Sacrifice Controversy]].

===Phoenicia and Carthage===
{{See also|Religion in Carthage}}
Carthage was notorious to its neighbors for child sacrifice. [[Plutarch]] (ca. 46–120 AD) mentions the practice, as do [[Tertullian]], [[Paulus Orosius|Orosius]] and [[Diodorus Siculus]]. However, [[Livy]] and [[Polybius]] do not. The [[Hebrew Bible]] also mentions what appears to be child sacrifice practiced at a place called the [[Tophet]] (&quot;roasting place&quot;) by the [[Canaan]]ites, ancestors of the [[Carthaginians]], and by some Israelites.

Some of these sources suggest that babies were roasted to death on a heated bronze statue. According to Diodorus Siculus, &quot;There was in their city a bronze image of Cronus extending its hands, palms up and sloping toward the ground, so that each of the children when placed thereon rolled down and fell into a sort of gaping pit filled with fire.&quot;(Bib. Hist. 20.14.6)

Sites within [[Carthage]] and other [[Phoenicia]]n centers revealed the remains of infants and children in large numbers; some historians{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} interpret this as evidence for frequent and prominent child sacrifice to the god [[Ba'al]] Hammon.

The accuracy of such stories is disputed by some modern historians and archaeologists.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/05146/510878.stm Carthage tries to live down image as site of infanticide&lt;/ref&gt;  At Carthage, a large cemetery exists that combines the bodies of both very young children and small animals, and those who argue in favor of child sacrifice have argued that if the animals were sacrificed then so too were the children.&lt;ref name=&quot;plosone.org&quot;&gt;Skeletal Remains from Punic Carthage Do Not Support Systematic Sacrifice of Infants http://www.plosone.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0009177&lt;/ref&gt;  However, recent archaeological work has produced a detailed breakdown of the age of the buried children and based on this, and especially on the presence of pre natal individuals - that is still births, it is also argued that this site is consistent with the burial of children who had died from natural causes in a society that had a high infant mortality rate - as Carthage is assumed to have been. I.e. this data supports the view that Tophets were cemeteries for those who died shortly before or after birth, regardless of the cause.&lt;ref name=&quot;plosone.org&quot;/&gt;

Greek, Roman and Israelite writers refer to Phoenician child sacrifice. However, some historians have disputed this interpretation, suggesting instead that these were resting places for children miscarried or who died in infancy.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} Skeptics suggest that the bodies of children found in Carthaginian and Phoenician cemeteries were merely the cremated remains of children that died naturally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=GUfAW0dEcrQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Phoenicians&amp;cd=7#v=onepage&amp;q=child%20sacrifice&amp;f=false The Phoenicians Elsa Marston p55]&lt;/ref&gt; Sergio Ribichini has argued that the Tophet was &quot;a child necropolis designed to receive the remains of infants who had died prematurely of sickness or other natural causes, and who for this reason were &quot;offered&quot; to specific deities and buried in a place different from the one reserved for the ordinary dead&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sergio Ribichini, &quot;Beliefs and Religious Life&quot; in Moscati, Sabatino (ed), ''The Phoenicians'', 1988, p.141&lt;/ref&gt; The few Carthaginian texts which have survived make absolutely no mention of child sacrifice, though most of them pertain to matters entirely unrelated to religion, such as the practice of agriculture.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

According to Lawrence and Wolff, in 1984, there was a consensus among scholars that Carthaginian children were sacrificed by their parents, who would make a vow to kill the next child if the gods would grant them a favor: for instance that their shipment of goods were to arrive safely in a foreign port.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| last = Stager
| first = Lawrence
| coauthors = Samuel. R. Wolff
| title = Child sacrifice in Carthage: religious rite or population control?
| journal = Journal of Biblical Archeological Review
| volume = January
| pages = 31–46
| year = 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt; They placed their children alive in the arms of a bronze statue of:

{{cquote|the lady Tanit ...&amp;nbsp;. The hands of the statue extended over a brazier into which the child fell once the flames had caused the limbs to contract and its mouth to open ...&amp;nbsp;. The child was alive and conscious when burned ... [[Philo]] specified that the sacrificed child was best-loved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| last = Brown
| first = Shelby
| title = Late Carthaginian Child Sacrifice and Sacrificial Monuments in their Mediterranean Context
| publisher = Sheffield Academic Press
| year = 1991
| pages = 22–23
| isbn = 1-85075-240-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Later commentators have compared the accounts of child sacrifice in the Old Testament with similar ones from Greek and Latin sources speaking of the offering of children by fire as sacrifices in the [[Punic]] city of [[Carthage]], which was a Phoenician colony. [[Cleitarchus]], [[Diodorus Siculus]] and [[Plutarch]] all mention burning of children as an offering to [[Cronus]] or [[Saturn (mythology)|Saturn]], that is to [[Ba`al Hammon|Ba'al Hammon]], the chief god of Carthage (see [[Interpretatio graeca]] for clarification). Issues and practices relating to Moloch and child sacrifice may also have been overemphasized for effect. After the Romans finally defeated Carthage and totally destroyed the city, they engaged in post-war propaganda to make their archenemies seem cruel and less civilized.

===Pre-Islamic Arabia===
The Quran documents pagan Arabians sacrificing their children to idols.{{cite quran|6|137}}

==Prehistoric Britain==
A young child was found buried with its skull split by a weapon at [[Woodhenge]]. This was interpreted by the excavators as a child sacrifice.&lt;ref name=def&gt;[[Ronald Hutton]], ''The Pagan Religions of the Ancient British Isles: Their Nature and Legacy'', ISBN 0-631-18946-7, page 90.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Uganda ==
In the early 21st century Uganda has experienced a revival of child sacrifice and in spite of government attempts to downplay the issue an investigation by the [[BBC]] into human sacrifice in [[Uganda]] found that ritual killings of children are more common than Ugandan authorities admit.&lt;ref&gt;Tim Whewell, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/newsnight/8441813.stm &quot;Witch-doctors reveal extent of child sacrifice in Uganda&quot;], BBC News, 7 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt; There are many indicators that politicians and politically connected wealthy businessmen are involved in sacrificing children which has become a commercial enterprise.&lt;ref&gt;Rogers, Chris 2011. Where child sacrifice is a business, BBC News Africa (11 October):  Http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-15255357#story_continues_1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;ANPPCAN 2010. Child Sacrifice epidemic during festival and election period (16 December 2010): www.anppcanug.org/wp-content/uploads/Child-Sacrifice-epidemic-during-festival-and-election-period.docx&lt;/ref&gt;

== Controversy ==
Precious little actual [[archeological]] evidence of widespread child sacrifice exists, leading some archaeologists to propose that child [[sacrifice]] may have been less prevalent than historical documents may suggest. In the case of Carthage, for instance, the only reports of child sacrifice come from Roman sources. It is possible that, being mortal enemies of the Carthaginians, the classic historians may have engaged in a sort of [[propaganda]] against their enemies.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} This can also be seen in the Jewish case: as they accused others in the [[Near East]] of child sacrifice, they themselves would come to be accused of it in [[blood libel]] cases.

In other cases, such as the [[Aztec]] and [[Inca]] child sacrifices, archaeological evidence has supported the written sources, and even added new information that keeps the debate open.

== See also ==
* [[Child cannibalism]]
* [[Child sacrifice in pre-Columbian cultures]]
* [[Child sacrifice in Uganda]]
* [[Religion in Carthage]]
* [[Binding of Isaac]]
* [[Infanticide]]
* [[Early infanticidal childrearing]]
* [[Human sacrifice]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource|Child-Sacrifice among European Witches}}
* [http://www.ugpulse.com/articles/daily/news.asp?about=Child%20survives%20sacrifice&amp;ID=7046 11/04/2008 Child survives sacrifice in Uganda ''UGPulse.com'']
* [http://projectsx.dartmouth.edu/classics/history/bronze_age/lessons/les/15.html#20 Minoan Child Sacrifice]
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}

[[Category:Child sacrifice]]

[[bg:Жертвоприношение на деца]]</text>
      <sha1>hby9jlih483z87yslpg3q4yz5du2t42</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
