<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chrismation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>76430</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520105966</id>
      <parentid>520074537</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T12:39:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anglicanus</username>
        <id>4280508</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Term is not commonly known in Anglicanism or Lutheranism as a alternative to confirmation.  Chrismation in these churches refers to the annointing with chrism in baptism which isn't confirmation.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9527">'''Chrismation''' is the name given in [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox]], [[Oriental Orthodoxy|Oriental Orthodox]] and [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholic]] churches, as well as in the [[Assyrian Church of the East]] initiation rites, to the [[sacrament]] or [[Sacred Mysteries|mystery]] more commonly known in the West as [[confirmation (sacrament)|confirmation]], although [[Italian language|Italian]] normally uses ''cresima'' (chrismation), rather than ''confermazione'' (confirmation).
{{TOCright}}
The term ''chrismation'' is used because the recipient of the sacrament is [[Anointing|anointed]] with ''[[Chrism]]'', which according to [[Eastern Christianity|eastern Christan]] belief, the Apostles sanctified and introduced for all priests to use as a replacement for [[Laying on of hands#Eastern Christianity|laying on of hands]] by the Apostles&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith8420] &quot;The Sanctification of the Holy Chrism &amp;mdash; Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America&quot;, Retrieved 2012-01-28&lt;/ref&gt; and consists of a &quot;mixture of forty sweet-smelling substances and pure olive oil&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gialopsos,p 35&lt;/ref&gt; [[Consecrated#Eastern_churches|sanctified]] by a bishop with some older Chrism added in,&lt;ref&gt;Sokolof, p103&lt;/ref&gt; in the belief that some trace of the initial Chrism sanctified by the Apostles is contained therein.

==Liturgical form==

===Eastern Orthodox Church===

====Common part of the rite====
The priest anoints the recipient with Chrism, making the [[sign of the cross]] on the forehead, eyes, ears, nostrils, breast, back, hands and feet using the following words each time:
:&quot;The seal of the gift of the [[Holy Spirit]]&quot; (in [[Greek language|Greek]]: {{lang|grc|Σφραγὶς δωρεᾶς Πνεύματος Ἁγίου}}).

The Chrism is washed off by a priest seven days later, according to the written [[rubrics]],&lt;ref&gt;Great Book of Needs, pp 47-52&lt;/ref&gt; the newly baptized wearing their white [[Chiton (costume)|chitons]] and not washing their anointed parts for that period.  However, in the case of infant baptism (and often also with adult chrismation contemporary practice), the ablution is performed immediately after the rite of chrismation.&lt;ref&gt;Sokolof, pp 118-119&lt;/ref&gt;

====As part of the baptismal rite====

Typically, one becomes a member of the Church by baptism and chrismation performed by a priest as a single service.
&lt;ref&gt;Great Book of Needs, pp 61-87; Sokolof, pp 116-117&lt;/ref&gt;

====Subsequent to baptism performed by a layman====

&lt;ref&gt;Great Book of Needs, pp 115-119; Sokolof, pp 117-118&lt;/ref&gt;

====At the reconciliation of apostates====

In the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] the sacrament may be conferred more than once and it is customary to receive apostates by repeating chrismation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith7101] &quot;Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America &amp;mdash; The Stand of the Orthodox Church on Controversial Issues&quot;, Retrieved 2011-12-28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orthodox.net/articles/baptism.html] &quot;St Nicholas Russian Orthodox Church, McKinney, Texas &amp;mdash; Chrismation and special circumstances&quot;, Retrieved 2011-12-28&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Methodios I of Constantinople|Saint Methodius of Constantinople]]&lt;ref&gt;Great Book of Needs, pp 113-114&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Great Book of Needs, pp 115-119&lt;/ref&gt;

====At the reception of certain converts====

Although normally administered in conjunction with baptism, in some cases chrismation alone may be used to receive [[Religious conversion#Christianity|convert]]s to Orthodoxy through the exercise of ''[[Economy (Eastern Christianity)#Ecclesiastical economy|economia]]''.  Although practice in this regard varies, in general, if a convert comes to Orthodoxy from another Christian confession and has previously undergone a rite of baptism in the Trinitarian Formula (&quot;in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit&quot;), he or she may be received into the Orthodox Church through the sacrament of chrismation, after which receiving the Holy Eucharist.  If, however, a convert comes from a Christian confession that baptizes in the name of Jesus (such as [[Oneness Pentecostals]]), from one which practices an invalid, non-Trinitarian baptism (such as [[Mormons]] or [[Jehovah's Witnesses]]) or from one that does not practice baptism at all (such as [[Religious Society of Friends|Quakers]] or [[The Salvation Army]]), baptism is a prerequisite for chrismation - an initiate must always be validly baptized into the death of Jesus in the name of the Holy Trinity before any further holy mysteries or sacraments of initiation can be administered. The use of ''economia'' is at the discretion of, and subject to the guidelines imposed by, the local [[bishop]].&lt;ref&gt;Great Book of Needs, pp 133-114; Sokolof, pp 119-120&lt;/ref&gt;

The sacrament of chrismation is an extension of the day of [[Pentecost]], on which the Holy Spirit was poured out on the Apostles.  It is by chrismation that a person becomes a layperson &amp;mdash; a member of the ''laos'' (laity), the people of God. [[Metropolitan bishop|Metropolitan]] [[Metropolitan Kallistos|Kallistos]] (Timothy Ware) explains:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Through Chrismation every member of the Church becomes a prophet, and receives a share in the royal priesthood of Christ; all Christians alike, because they are chrismated, are called to act as conscious witnesses to the Truth.  &quot;You have an anointing (''chrisma'') from the Holy One, and know all things&quot; ({{Bibleverse||1John|2:20}}).&lt;ref&gt;Ware, 279&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Oriental Orthodox Churches===

==Sacramental theology==

===Eastern Churches===
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2012}}
Unlike in the [[Western Christianity|western Churches]] (e.g., [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] and [[Anglican Communion|Anglican]]), where confirmation is typically reserved to those of &quot;the age of reason&quot;, chrismation in the [[Eastern Christianity|Eastern Churches]], (including [[Eastern Catholic|Eastern Rite Catholic Churches]]), is ordinarily administered immediately after [[baptism]], most commonly infant baptism, and immediately (or at least shortly) before one's first reception of Holy Communion. This sacramental rite may be performed by a [[presbyter]] (priest). After receiving this sacrament, the recipient is eligible to receive the [[Eucharist]]. In the Eastern tradition, chrismation shows the unity of the church through the bishop in the continuation of the Apostolic faith, because the Chrism used is presented to the priest by the bishop and (together with the [[antimension]]) is the symbol of the priest's permission from the bishop to perform the sacraments (see [[Faculty (instrument)|faculty]]). Although priests in the Eastern churches are universally granted this faculty, it is thus ultimately considered a sacrament granted by a bishop and associated with that Apostolic office. Furthermore, because some of the previously sanctified Chrism is mixed with the newly sanctified Chrism, there is a belief that the Chrism contains a remnant of, or at least a connection to, the same Chrism which was sanctified by the [[Apostles]] in the first century, and thus is a symbol of [[Apostolic succession]].

===Oriental Orthodox===
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2012}}
The Coptic Orthodox Church follows a tradition that states while the Apostles used to give Confirmation by the laying on of the hands, they found they were not able to communicate such power. Thus they ordered the collection of the spices which were used to anoint Christ's body, and they were mixed with oil, forming, according to Coptic tradition, the first chrism, or &quot;myron&quot;, which, according to tradition, was brough to Egypt by St Mark. The Coptic communion believes that, since that time, the &quot;myron&quot; has been remade 28 times.

===Assyrian Church of the East===
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2012}}
The Assyrian Church of the East, which recognizes the ''[[Latrocinium]]'' or &quot;[[Second Council of Ephesus]]&quot; of 449 as an ecumenical council, has some similar views to the Eastern Orthodox regarding sacramental theology in chrismation.

==Works cited==
*{{Citation
|last=Gialopsos
|first=Philip G.
|year=1997
|title=The seven sacraments of the Greek Orthodox Church
|publisher= Black Swan Books, Inc., ABAA, ILAB
|publication-place=[[Richmond, Virginia]], USA
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Ware
|first=Timothy (Kallistos)
|year=1963
|publication-date=1997
|title=The Orthodox Church
|publisher=[[Penguin Books]]
|publication-place=[[London]], UK
|isbn=978-0-14-013529-9
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Sokolof
|first=Archpriest Dimitrii
|year=1899
|publication-date=2001
|title=Manual of the Orthodox Church's Divine Services
|place=[[Jordanville, New York]]
|publisher=[[Holy Trinity Monastery (Jordanville, New York)|Holy Trinity Monastery]]
|isbn=0-88465-067-7
|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/sokolof/services.toc.html
}}
*{{Citation
|year=2000
|publication-date=2000
|title=The Great Book of Needs: Expanded and Supplemented (Volume 1): The Holy Mysteries (v. 1)
|pages=132–136
|place=[[South Canaan Township, Pennsylvania|South Canaan, Pennsylvania]]
|publisher=[[Saint Tikhon's Orthodox Theological Seminary|Saint Tikhon's Seminary Press]]
|isbn=1-878997-56-4
|url=http://www.stspress.com/products-page/service-books/great-book-of-needs-vol-1/
}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Eastern Christian liturgy]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[et:Õlitamise sakrament]]
[[id:Krisma]]
[[ja:傅膏機密]]
[[ru:Миропомазание]]
[[fi:Mirhavoitelu]]
[[sv:Konfirmation]]
[[uk:Миропомазання]]</text>
      <sha1>5kmapsxyxyc9j9llvvf2x4ygchike6f</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
