<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Christian Peacemaker Teams</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19697962</id>
    <revision>
      <id>505049341</id>
      <parentid>503049904</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-31T05:18:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>George100</username>
        <id>1032465</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Work in the Palestinian territories */ convert 2 dead links to refs</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16300">'''Christian Peacemaker Teams''' ('''CPT''') is an international organization set up to support teams of peace workers in conflict areas around the world. These teams believe that they can lower the levels of violence through nonviolent direct action, [[human rights]] documentation, and [[nonviolence]] training. CPT sums their work up as &quot;...committed to reducing violence by ''getting in the way'' &quot;. CPT has a full-time corps of over 30 activists who currently work in [[Colombia]], [[Iraq]], the [[West Bank]], the [[United States–Mexico border]], and [[Kenora]], [[Ontario]], [[Canada]]. These teams are supported by over 150 reservists who spend two weeks to two months a year on location.[[Image:Palestine - road block removal.jpg|thumb|300px|alt=Palestinians removing roadblock|Palestinians remove a roadblock while a member of CPT stands behind them.]] 
 
==Christianity and CPT==
CPT has its roots in the historic [[peace churches]] of North America, and its four supporting denominations are the [[Mennonite Church USA]], [[Mennonite Church Canada]], [[Church of the Brethren]], and the [[Religious Society of Friends]]. It is also sponsored by several Christian groups: &quot;Every Church a Peace Church&quot;, &quot;On Earth Peace&quot;, &quot;Presbyterian Peace Fellowship&quot;, &quot;[[Baptist Peace Fellowship of North America]]&quot;, and the &quot;[[Congregation of St. Basil]]&quot;. In conflict areas it works in partnership with [[Jewish]], [[Muslim]] and secular peace organizations, such as the [[International Solidarity Movement]] and [[Peace Brigades International]]. Another component of CPT's work is to engage &quot;...congregations, meetings and support groups at home to play a key advocacy role with policy makers.&quot;&lt;ref name=cpt_history&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpt.org/publications/history.php |title=CPT's history statement |publisher=Cpt.org |date= |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although it is a Christian-based organization, CPT does not engage in any type of [[missionary]] activity. Their website states &quot;While CPTers have chosen to follow Jesus Christ, they do not proselytize.&quot;&lt;ref name=cpt_faq&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpt.org/publications/faq.php |title=Cpt'S Faq |publisher=Cpt.org |date= |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has raised the question of what distinguishes them from similar &quot;secular&quot;, organizations;

&lt;BLOCKQUOTE&gt;&quot;All the groups resemble one another other in that they all work to stop violence, but according to CPT's Web site, it has an advantage over secular groups: &quot;In Muslim areas, the Christian nature of CPT helps to create confidence because of a shared sense of monotheism.&quot; The group does not believe that its Christianity might also put it at a dangerous disadvantage in areas of the world where religious tensions run high.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/story?id=1760925&amp;page=2 |title=ABC coverage of CPT |publisher=Abcnews.go.com |date=2006-03-23 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;

Their website also states that Corp members are Christians, there is not faith requirement for members of CPT's short-term delegations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpt.org/about/faq |title=Christian Peacemaker Teams Frequent Questions |publisher=Christian Peacemaker Teams |accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example one of the CPT delegates who was held hostage in Iraq, [[Harmeet Singh Sooden]], is a [[Sikh]].

The [[Mennonite Church USA Archives]] is the repository of the official records of Christian Peacemaker Teams.

==History==
[[Image:2004 CSIS Protest.jpg|thumb|300px|A 2004 protest by CPT outside the Toronto office of the [[Canadian Security Intelligence Service]] (CSIS), protesting the detention of non-citizens under [[security certificate]]s.]]
The inspiration for the group came from [[Ron Sider]] at the [[Mennonite World Conference]] in 1984. At it, Sider criticized [[Mennonites]] and [[Brethren in Christ]] for reducing their peace witness to simple [[conscientious objection]]:
&lt;BLOCKQUOTE&gt;
Unless we Mennonites and Brethren in Christ are ready to start to die by the thousands in dramatic vigorous new exploits for peace and justice, we should sadly confess that we really never meant what we said....

Unless comfortable North American and European Mennonites and Brethren in Christ are prepared to risk injury and death in nonviolent opposition to the injustice our societies foster and assist in Central America, the Philippines, and South Africa, we dare never whisper another word about pacifism to our sisters and brothers in those desperate lands....

Unless we are prepared to pay the cost of peacemaking, we have no right to claim the label or preach the message.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cpt.org/resources/writings/sider Statement by Ron Sider]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;
After a series of meetings, [[Gene Stoltzfus]] was hired as the first staff person for the new organization in 1988. Over the next few years CPT trainings and conferences explored various models for international peacemaking. In 1990, just before the [[Gulf War]], CPT sent a team of 13 to Iraq for 10&amp;nbsp;days. This delegation proved to be the first of a number the group sent its first delegations to [[Haiti]], [[Iraq]], and the [[West Bank]].

==Iraq activities==
CPT has operated in Iraq since October 2002. Since the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]], they have worked with and advocated for families of people detained by the [[U.S. Military]] and collected stories of detainee [[Physical abuse|abuse]]. In January 2004 they released a report documenting routine abuse of Iraqi prisoners held by [[Coalition Provisional Authority]], well before the photographs of [[Abu Ghraib]] prisoners brought international attention to the issue.&lt;ref name=CPTIraq&gt;[http://www.cpt.org/iraq/detainee_summary_report.htm CPT report]{{dead link|date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hostage crisis===
{{Main|2005-2006 Christian Peacemaker hostage crisis}}
On 26 November 2005, four human rights workers associated with CPT were kidnapped in [[Baghdad]]:
* [[James Loney (peace activist)|James Loney]], 41, of [[Toronto]], [[Canada]], program coordinator for CPT Canada
* [[Harmeet Singh Sooden]], 32, of [[Canada]], an electrical engineer and former [[McGill University|McGill]] student who was living in [[New Zealand]]
* [[Norman Kember]], 74, of [[London]], [[United Kingdom|UK]], a retired professor of medical studies
* [[Tom Fox (peace worker)|Tom Fox]], 54, of [[Clearbrook, Virginia]], [[U.S.]], a leader of youth programs at Langley Hill [[Quaker|Friends]] Meeting
The four had planned to visit the [[Muslim Clerics Association]], an influential group of [[Sunni]] religious leaders formed in 2003 after the collapse of Saddam Hussein's regime, and were about 100&amp;nbsp;metres from the entrance to a mosque where the meeting was to take place when they were abducted. Their captors are a previously unknown group, the [[Swords of Righteousness Brigade]]. The hostages were shown on a video broadcast released worldwide on 29 November by Arab satellite channel [[Al Jazeera]]. The captors branded their hostages as spies posing as Christian peace activists. The captors threatened to kill the hostages unless the US freed all Iraqi prisoners held in the US and Iraq.

A body found in Iraq on 10 March 2006 was identified later that day as being that of Tom Fox.&lt;ref name=tom&gt;[http://www.thestar.com/NASApp/cs/ContentServer?pagename=thestar/Layout/Article_Type1&amp;c=Article&amp;cid=1142031016360&amp;call_pageid=968332188854 U.S. hostage taken with Canadians killed], ''[[Toronto Star]]'', March 10, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; During the crisis, the news had broken that he had performed for a long time with the [[United States Marine Band]].

On March 23, 2006, the three remaining hostages were rescued from a house near the town of [[Mishahda]] by a multinational force. None of the kidnappers were found in the house at the time. The ''[[telegraph.co.uk|Telegraph (UK)]]'' reported that &quot;A deal had been struck with a man detained the previous night who was one of the leaders of the kidnappers. He was allowed a telephone call to warn his henchmen to leave the kidnap house. When the troops moved in and found the prisoners alive, they also let him go as promised.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2006/03/25/wkemb25.xml&amp;sSheet=/portal/2006/03/25/ixportaltop.html |title=Telegraph article |publisher=Telegraph article |date=2010-02-05 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The rescue force was led by elements of 'Task Force Black' - a multinational counter-kidnap unit consisting of British, American and Canadian [[JTF2]] special forces. They were supported by 'Task Force Maroon', a support unit made up of British Paras and marines.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,7374-2102543,00.html Timesonline.com article]{{dead link|date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Royal Canadian Mounted Police]] and [[Canadian Security Intelligence Service]] were also involved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/20060323/canadian_aid_hostages_060323/20060323?hub=World |title=Elite Canadian soldiers helped free hostages: CTV |publisher=CTV.ca |date= |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The three surviving hostages were in good medical condition. While captive, they had been allowed to exercise and Kember had received medication he needs.&lt;ref&gt;[[New York Times]] coverage [http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/international/AP-Iraq-Hostages-Freed.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although happy that the hostages were freed, CPT placed the responsibility for the kidnapping on the coalition itself: &quot;We believe that the illegal occupation of Iraq by Multinational Forces is the root cause of the insecurity which led to this kidnapping and so much pain and suffering in Iraq.&quot; CPT initially made no mention of appreciation to coalition forces for the rescue in its statement, but did so in a later addenda after considerable media attention.&lt;ref name=CPTAnnounce&gt;[http://cpt.org/iraq/response/06-23-03statement.htm#freed CPT comments] on the release of hostages&lt;/ref&gt; It was reported that the CPT had not cooperated with the [[Special Air Service|SAS]] officials who coordinated the rescue. CPT co-director Doug Pritchard stated that they did not want a &quot;military raid&quot; to occur and preferred to work with diplomats.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2087-2104094,00.html Kember’s muted thanks fuels SAS rescue row - Sunday Times - Times Online]{{dead link|date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Work in Colombia==

CPT has had a team based in [[Barrancabermeja]], [[Colombia]] since 2001. The focus of their work has been accompanying a number of communities along the Opon river, a tributary of the [[Magdalena River]]. The farmers and fishers from these communities displaced themselves in 2000 due to heavy fighting in 2000 between the [[United Self-Defense Forces of Colombia]] (AUC) and the [[Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia]] (FARC). Since the community members returned to their homes in 2001, the team has had a nearly daily presence in the area to support the people, work to prevent intimidation by both AUC and FARC and document human rights abuses if they occur. The team also works with Colombian women's groups and human rights groups based in Barrancabermeja in an effort to reduce threats and violent acts carried out by the AUC in the city.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cpt.org/colombia/colombia.php CPT in Colombia] from Christian Peacemaker Teams website. Retrieved 28 March 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Work in Chiapas, Mexico==

CPT has, in the past, also been involved in Chiapas, Mexico, where violence had erupted between the [[Zapatista Army of National Liberation]] and the Mexican government. CPT's long-term presence began in June 1998.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cpt.org/publications/chronology.php Christian Peacemaker Teams Activities 1984-2000], from Christian Peacemakers Teams website, accessed May 16, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  In Chiapas, CPT partnered with a Christian civil society group called [[Las Abejas]] (the Bees) that shares a commitment to pacifism. Their joint activities included going to the bases of the Mexican military to pray.&lt;ref&gt;Marco Tavanti, ''Las Abejas: Pacifist Resistance and Syncretic Identities in a Globalizing Chiapas'' (New York: Routledge, 2003), p. 190&lt;/ref&gt;

==Work in the Palestinian territories ==

CPT has two teams in the [[Palestinian territories]], one in [[Hebron]] and one in [[At-tuwani]]. Part of their daily routines includes school patrol, and monitoring settler violence and soldier home invasions. The teams also work against home demolitions. The CPT says the Israeli occupation is &quot;violent&quot;, and that reconciliation between Palestinians and Israelis can only flourish when the occupation ends.&lt;ref name=ctp_views&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/shared/spl/hi/picture_gallery/07/middle_east_christian_peacemakers0_hebron/html/6.stm |title=In pictures: Christian Peacemakers, Hebron, Occupation |publisher=BBC News |date= |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, two CPT members, Kim Lamberty and Chris Brown in At-Tuwani were severely injured when Israeli settlers attacked them as they were walking children to school.&lt;ref name=pt_attacks&gt; {{cite web | url = http://www.cpt.org/archives/2004/oct04/0013.html | title = HEBRON DISTRICT: Kim Lamberty's report on the September 29 settler attack | accessdate = 2012-07-31 | date = Oct 11 2004 | work = CPTnet | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050601124429/http://www.cpt.org/archives/2004/oct04/0013.html | archivedate = 2005-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; {{cite news | first = Caryle | last = Murphy | title = D.C. Volunteer Finds No Peace On West Bank Palestinian Students' Escort Attacked | date = 2004-10-09 | url = http://www.sfcg.org/articles/westbank.pdf | work = [[Washington Post]] | accessdate = 2012-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A few days later, the team, along with [[Operation Dove]] and [[Amnesty International]] members were again attacked. In response to these attacks, the Israeli Knesset Committee for Children's Rights initiated an order to have soldiers escort the Palestinian children to school in At-Tuwani.&lt;ref name=amnest_attacks&gt;[http://news.amnesty.org/index/ENGMDE150992004 Amnesty International statement],  [http://www.cpt.org/palestine/at-tuwani/documents/CPT_OD_2005_2006_school_patrol_report.htm CPT's report]
&lt;/ref&gt; However, CPT's report records that as of 10 November 2006, settlers had attacked or harassed the schoolchildren 40 times, in spite of the order by the Israeli Knesset Committee for Children's Rights to protect the children.

CPT has however condemned Palestinian violence against Israeli civilians. For example, when Egged bus #18 was bombed two Sundays in a row, CPTer Kathy Kern publicized the fact that she would ride the bus the following Sunday in protest.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}

==Further reading==
*Brown, Tricia Gates ''Getting in the Way: Stories from Christian Peacemaker Teams'', Herald Press, 2005.
*Clark, H., 2009. ''People Power: Unarmed Resistance and Global Solidarity'', Pluto Press.
*Gish, Arthur G. ''Hebron Journal: Stories of Nonviolent Peacemaking'', Herald Press, 2001.
*Kern, Kathleen. ''In Harm's Way: A History of Christian Peacemaker Teams'', Cascade Books, 2008.
*Mahony, L. &amp; Eguren, L.E., 1997. ''Unarmed Bodyguards: International Accompaniment for the Protection of Human Rights'', West Hartford, Conn: Kumarian Press.
*Moser-Puangsuwan, Y. &amp; Weber, T., 2000. ''Nonviolent Intervention Across Borders'', University of Hawaii Press.
*The official records of CPT are housed at the [http://www.mcusa-archives.org/ Mennonite Church USA Archives] in Goshen IN

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==See also==
* [[Christian pacifism]]
* [[Muslim Peacemaker Teams]]
* [[Mennonite Church USA Archives]]
* [[Peace makers]]

==External links==
* [http://www.cpt.org Christian Peacemaker Teams] - official central website for CPT

[[Category:Christian interfaith and secular relations]]
[[Category:Christian pacifism]]
[[Category:Mennonitism]]
[[Category:Peace organizations]]
[[Category:Anti–Iraq War groups]]
[[Category:Non-governmental organizations involved in the Israeli–Palestinian conflict]]
[[Category:Christian organizations]]
[[Category:Nonviolence organizations]]
[[Category:Church of the Brethren]]

[[pdc:Christian Peacemaker Teams]]
[[de:Christian Peacemaker Teams]]
[[sv:Christian Peacemaker Teams]]</text>
      <sha1>tszosxzlrzcla21keblvjo6ilaisn6s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
