<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Church militant and church triumphant</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>522984</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521242919</id>
      <parentid>508111085</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-03T19:13:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>96.241.153.177</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7051">[[Image:Museo di santa maria novella, cappellone degli spagnoli, affreschi di andrea di bonaiuto 8.JPG|thumb|320px|right|''The Church Militant and the Church Triumphant'', fresco by [[Andrea da Firenze]] in [[Basilica of Santa Maria Novella|Santa Maria Novella]], c. 1365]]
In [[Christian theology]], the [[Christian Church]], or '''Church Universal''', is traditionally divided into:
*the '''Church Militant''' (''Ecclesia Militans''), comprising [[Christians]] on earth who are living; Christian militia, who struggle against sin, the devil and &quot;..the rulers of the darkness of this world, against spiritual wickedness in high places&quot; (Ephesians 6:12).
*the '''Church Triumphant''' (''Ecclesia Triumphans''), comprising those who are in [[Heaven]], and
*the '''Church Suffering''', a.k.a. ''Church Padecent'' or ''Church Penitent'' (''Ecclesia Penitens'') or '''Church Expectant''' (''Ecclesia Expectans''), comprising those Christians presently in [[Purgatory]]. This latter term is only applicable to [[Roman Catholic theology]].

These terms are often used in the context of the doctrine of the [[Communion of Saints]]; although Christians may be physically separated from each other by the barrier of death, they nonetheless remain united to each other in one Church, and support each other in prayer.

The [[Latin]] word ''militans'' has a primary meaning of &quot;serving as a [[soldier]], [[military]]&quot;, but it acquired a secondary meaning of &quot;to struggle, to make an effort&quot;, which is the intended sense here.  Christians on earth (the Church Militant) are still struggling against sin in order that, when they die, they might go to heaven and be members of the Church Triumphant, those who have triumphed over sin.  However, if this struggle is successful, but not completely so, then after death they temporarily become members of the Church Suffering before ultimately joining the Church Triumphant.

The Catholic Church commemorates the Church Triumphant and the Church Suffering on two consecutive days:  [[All Saints' Day|All Saints Day]] on November 1 (the Church Triumphant), and [[All Souls Day]] on November 2 (the Church Suffering).

These terms are not used in the modern [[Catechism of the Catholic Church]], the authoritative collection of the teaching of [[Catholicism]], first published in 1994. Many contemporary Catholics might consider them belonging to another age. However, the teaching these terms represent is precisely restated in paragraph 954 of the Catechism, which quote [[Lumen Gentium]], the Constitution on the Church of the [[Second Vatican Council]]: 

''The three states of the Church. &quot;When the Lord comes in glory, and all his angels with him, death will be no more and all things will be subject to him. But at the present time some of his disciples are pilgrims on earth. Others have died and are being purified, while still others are in glory, contemplating 'in full light, God himself triune and one, exactly as he is&quot;''' [http://www.scborromeo.org/ccc/p123a9p5.htm (CCC 954)] [[File:Blessed Be the Host of the King of Heaven… - Google Art Project.jpg|thumb|400px|''[[Ecclesia militans]]'', one of the largest icons in existence]]

The [[Methodist Church]] defines the Church Militant as &quot;engaged in constant warfare against the world, the flesh and the [[devil]], and in that respect is distinguished from the Church Triumphant.&quot;&lt;ref name=Methodism&gt;{{cite book|author=Bishop H.M. Turner, D.D., LL.D.|title=The Genius and Theory of Methodist Polity, or the Machinery of Methodism|url=http://docsouth.unc.edu/church/turnerpolity/turner.html|quote=13 Q. What do the visible and invisible church constitute? A. The church militant, or military church, which is engaged in constant warfare against the world, the flesh and the devil, and in that respect is distinguished from the &quot;church triumphant.&quot; 14 Q. What do you mean by &quot;Church Triumphant?&quot; A. The church triumphant is in heaven, and consists of those who have washed their robes and made them immaculate and pure &quot;in the blood of the Lamb.&quot; 15 Q. The church militant then is upon earth? A. Yes; and comprehends all Christian denominations; viz., Methodists, Presbyterians, Baptists, Congregationalists, Episcopalians and many others. 16 Q. Do you mean to say that it takes all the church denominations of the world to constitute the &quot;church militant?&quot; A. I do. For all these so-called churches are only so many religious societies forming the &quot;Church militant,&quot; which are recognized by Christ in the aggregate.|publisher=[[African Methodist Episcopal Church]]|year=1885|accessdate=7 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Church Militant includes all [[Christian denominations]], such as Methodists, [[Presbyterians]], [[Baptists]], [[Congregationalists]], [[Anglicanism|Episcopalians]], among many others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Methodism&quot;/&gt; In the same fashion, it defines the Church Triumphant as &quot;in heaven, and consists of those who have washed their robes and made them immaculate and pure in the [[Blood of Christ|blood of the Lamb]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Methodism&quot;/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}
*[http://www.ewtn.com/library/THEOLOGY/SPIRCATH.HTM#07 ''The Spirit of Catholicism'', ch. 7-8 (&quot;The Communion of Saints&quot;)] by [[Karl Adam (theologian)|Karl Adam]]
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04171a.htm Communion of Saints] - article from the [[Catholic Encyclopedia]]
*[http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19641121_lumen-gentium_en.html ''Lumen Gentium'' (Dogmatic Constitution on the Church), n. 49]

==External links==
*[http://www.ewtn.com/faith/Teachings/chura1.htm The Catholic Church is the Mystical Body of Christ] by Fr. William G. Most

;Images:
* &quot;''[http://www.kfki.hu/~arthp/html/a/andrea/firenze/triumph.html The Church Militant and Triumphant]''&quot;. 1365-68. [[Fresco]] by [[Andrea da Firenze]]. [[Cappella Spagnuolo]], [[Santa Maria Novella]], [[Florence]].
* &quot;''[http://www.wga.hu/frames-e.html?/html/r/raphael/4stanze/1segnatu/2/disputa1.html Disputation of the Holy Sacrament (La Disputa)]''&quot;. 1510-11. [[Fresco]] by [[Raffaello Sanzio]]. [[Stanza della Segnatura]], [[Palazzi Pontifici]], [[Vatican City|Vatican]].
*[http://www.imagesonline.bl.uk/britishlibrary/controller/subjectidsearch?id=10618&amp;&amp;idx=1&amp;startid=10081 Image from ''The Desert of Religion, and other poems and religious pieces''], depicting the Church Suffering (bottom) being lifted up to heaven and the Church Triumphant (top) through the prayer of the Church Militant (middle)
* [http://biblia.com/images/purgatory-mass.gif The Church Triumphant (top) and the Church Militant (middle) praying for the Church Suffering (bottom)]
* [http://uvoc.org/All_Saints/All_Saints_Pic.jpg The Church Triumphant (top) and the Church Militant (bottom) praying for the Church Suffering (bottom left and right)] by René de Cramer

[[Category:Catholic doctrines]]
[[Category:Ecclesiology]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[de:Streitende und Triumphierende Kirche]]
[[eo:Videbla eklezio]]
[[ia:Ecclesia militante e ecclesia triumphante]]
[[pt:Igreja Militante]]</text>
      <sha1>q2ywundm0dgeyqzxsvirhjoy95q6zcb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
