<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Confession (religion)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>217474</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521795415</id>
      <parentid>520761648</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T08:19:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove unicode control characters (CHECKWIKI error 16) +general fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8535)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26242">:''&quot;Confess&quot; and &quot;Confessing&quot; redirect here. For the evangelical protestant movement, see [[Confessing Movement]]. For statements of faith, see [[Confession of faith]]. For other uses, see [[Confess (disambiguation)]] and [[Confession (disambiguation)]].
{{religion primary|date=May 2009}}
{{refimprove|date=October 2009}}

[[File:St.leonhard-ffm-beichtstuhl001.jpg|thumb|Traditional [[confessional]]]]
[[File:Iglesia de San Joaquín-Confesionario.JPG|thumb|A confessional in [[Colombia]]]]
[[File:Confessional.JPG|thumb| Pilgrims queueing to confess at [[Međugorje]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]].]]

'''Confession''' is the acknowledgment of sin (or one's sinfulness) or wrongs. It is a religious practice in a number of faith traditions.

==Christianity==

===Catholicism===
{{Main|Sacrament of Penance (Catholic Church)}}

[[File:Confessional Modern.jpg|thumb|left|Modern confessional in the Church of the Holy Name, [[Dunedin]], [[New Zealand]]. The penitent may kneel on the kneeler or sit in a chair facing the priest (not shown)]]

In Catholic teaching, the [[Sacrament of Penance (Catholic Church)|Sacrament of Penance]] is the method of the Church by which individual men and women may confess sins committed after baptism and have them [[absolution|absolved]] by a priest. Although it is not mandatory, the Catholic rite is traditionally conducted within a [[confessional]] box or booth. This sacrament is known by many names, including penance, reconciliation and '''confession''' (''[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]'', Sections 1423-1442). While official Church publications always refer to the sacrament as &quot;Penance&quot;, &quot;Reconciliation&quot; or &quot;Penance and Reconciliation&quot;, many laypeople continue to use the term &quot;Confession&quot; in reference to the Sacrament.

For the Catholic Church, the intent of this sacrament is to provide healing for the soul as well as to regain the grace of God, lost by sin. It is the only ordinary way to receive the forgiveness of God for serious (mortal) sins which if unforgiven condemn a person to Hell.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Catechism of the Catholic Church No. 1446|location=The Vatican|quote=Christ instituted the sacrament of Penance for all sinful members of his Church: above all for those who, since Baptism, have fallen into grave sin, and have thus lost their baptismal grace and wounded ecclesial communion. It is to them that the sacrament of Penance offers a new possibility to convert and to recover the grace of justification. The Fathers of the Church present this sacrament as &quot;the second plank [of salvation] after the shipwreck which is the loss of grace.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Church teaches that Catholic priests have been given the authority by God to exercise the forgiveness of sins here on earth and it is in God's Name by which the person confessing is forgiven.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Confession|url=http://www.catholicapologetics.info/thechurch/sacraments/confession.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=John 20:23|url=http://www.drbo.org/x/d?b=drb&amp;bk=50&amp;ch=20&amp;l=23#x}}&lt;/ref&gt; In theological terms, the priest acts ''[[in persona Christi]]'' and receives from the Church the power of jurisdiction over the penitent.

Recently, several electronic applications have been introduced that can aid a penitent in making a good confession, similar to printed works known as &quot;[[examination of conscience|examinations of conscience]]&quot;.  Such electronic aids, according to Vatican statements, cannot replace confession direct to a priest, as only a priest can confer sacramental absolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crunchgear.com/2011/02/09/confession-the-roman-catholic-app-doesnt-support-real-iconfessions/ crunchgear.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  As of February 2011, one widely publicized example was an &quot;app&quot; for the [[iPhone]] called &quot;[[Confession: A Roman Catholic App]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/confession-a-roman-catholic/ itunes.apple.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Council of Trent]] (''Session Fourteen, Chapter I'') quoted [[Gospel of John|John]] {{Bibleverse-nb||John|20:22-23|NAB}} as the primary [[Scriptural]] proof for the doctrine concerning this sacrament, but Catholics also consider [[Gospel of Matthew|Matthew]] {{Bibleverse-nb||Matthew|9:2-8|NAB}}, [[First Epistle to the Corinthians|1 Corinthians]] {{Bibleverse-nb|1|Cor|11:27|NAB}}, and {{Bibleverse||Matthew|16:17-20|KJV}} to be among the Scriptural bases for the sacrament.

The Catholic Church teaches that sacramental confession requires three &quot;acts&quot; on the part of the penitent: contrition (sorrow of the soul for the sins committed), disclosure of the sins (the 'confession'), and satisfaction (the 'penance', i.e. doing something to make amends for the sins).&lt;ref&gt;[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]], nn. 1450-1460.&lt;/ref&gt; The basic form of confession has not changed for centuries, although at one time confessions were made publicly.&lt;ref&gt;Hanna, E. (1911). The Sacrament of Penance. In The Catholic Encyclopedia. New York: Robert Appleton Company. Retrieved September 14, 2008 from New Advent: http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11618c.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Typically, the penitent begins sacramental confession by saying, &quot;Bless me Father, for I have sinned. It has been [time period] since my last confession.&quot; The penitent must then confess what he/she believes to be grave and [[mortal sin]]s, in both kind and number,&lt;ref&gt;[[1983 Code of Canon Law]], Can.  988 §1: http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P3H.HTM&lt;/ref&gt; in order to be reconciled with God and the Church. The sinner may also confess [[venial sin]]s; this is especially recommended if the penitent has no mortal sins to confess. According to the ''Catechism'', &quot;without being strictly necessary, confession of everyday faults (venial sins) is nevertheless strongly recommended by the Church. Indeed the regular confession of our venial sins helps us form our conscience, fight against evil tendencies, let ourselves be healed by Christ and progress in the life of the Spirit. By receiving more frequently through this sacrament the gift of the Father's Mercy, we are spurred to be merciful as He is merciful&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]], n. 1458.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Eastern Orthodoxy and Eastern Catholicism===
Within the [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox]] and [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholic]] churches, it is understood that the [[Sacred Mystery|Mystery]] of confession and repentance has more to do with the spiritual development of the individual and much less to do with purification. Sin is not seen as a stain on the soul, but rather a mistake that needs correction.

[[File:Ispoved.jpg|thumb|left|[[Russian Orthodox]] priest hearing confessions before [[Divine Liturgy]], Church of the [[Protection of the Theotokos]], [[Düsseldorf]], [[Germany]].]]

In general, the Orthodox Christian chooses an individual to trust as his or her spiritual guide. In most cases this is the parish priest, but may be a [[starets]] ([[Elder (Christianity)|Elder]], a monastic who is well known for his or her advancement in the spiritual life) or any individual, male or female, who has received permission from a bishop to hear confession. This person is often referred to as one's &quot;spiritual father&quot; or &quot;spiritual mother&quot;. Once chosen, the individual turns to his spiritual guide for advice on his or her spiritual development, confessing sins, and asking advice. Orthodox Christians tend to confess only to this individual and the closeness created by this bond makes the spiritual guide the most qualified in dealing with the person, so much so that no one can override what a spiritual guide tells his or her charges. What is confessed to one's spiritual guide is protected by the same [[seal of the Confessional|seal]] as would be any priest hearing a confession. While one does not have to be a priest to hear confession, only an [[cheirotonia|ordained]] priest may pronounce the [[absolution]].

Confession does not take place in a [[confessional]], but normally in the main part of the church itself, usually before an [[analogion]] ([[lectern]]) set up near the [[iconostasion]]. On the analogion is placed a [[Gospel Book]] and a blessing cross. The confession often takes place before an [[icon]] of [[Jesus Christ]]. Orthodox understand that the confession is not made to the priest, but to Christ, and the priest stands only as witness and guide. Before confessing, the penitent venerates the Gospel Book and cross, and places the thumb and first two fingers of his right hand on the feet of Christ as he is depicted on the cross. The confessor will often read an admonition warning the penitent to make a full confession, holding nothing back.

In cases of emergency, of course, confession may be heard anywhere. For this reason, especially in the [[Russian Orthodox Church]], the [[pectoral cross]] that the priest wears at all times will often have the Icon of Christ &quot;Not Made by Hands&quot; inscribed on it.

In general practice, after one confesses to one's spiritual guide, the parish priest (who may or may not have heard the confession) covers the head of the person with his [[Epitrachelion]] (Stole) and reads the Prayer of Absolution, asking God to forgive the transgression of the individual (the specific prayer differs between Greek and Slavic use). It is not uncommon for a person to confesses his sins to his spiritual guide on a regular basis but only seek out the priest to read the prayer before receiving [[Holy Communion]].

[[File:Исповедь берн собор.jpg|thumb|A penitent confessing his sins in the former [[Latin rite|Latin rite Catholic]], now [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church|Ukrainian Byzantine Rite Greek-Catholic church]] of the Bernhardines in [[Lviv]], [[Ukraine]].]]

In the [[Eastern Churches]], clergy often make their confession in the [[sanctuary]]. A bishop, priest, or deacon will confess at the [[Altar|Holy Table]] (Altar) where the Gospel Book and blessing cross are normally kept. He confesses in the same manner as a layman, except that when a priest hears a bishop's confession, the priest kneels.

Orthodox Christians should go to confession at least four times a year; often during one of the four fasting periods ([[Great Lent]], [[Nativity Fast]], [[Apostles' Fast]] and [[Dormition Fast]]). Many pastors encourage frequent confession and communion. In some of the [[monastery|monasteries]] on [[Mount Athos]], the monks will confess their sins daily.

Orthodox Christians will also practice a form of [[general confession]], referred to as the rite of &quot;Mutual Forgiveness&quot;. The rite involves an exchange between the priest and the congregation (or, in monasteries, between the [[Abbot|superior]] and the brotherhood). The priest will make a prostration before all and ask their forgiveness for sins committed in act, word, deed, and thought. Those present ask that God may forgive him, and then they in turn all prostrate themselves and ask the priest's forgiveness. The priest then pronounces a blessing. The rite of Mutual Forgiveness does not replace the Mystery of Confession and Absolution, but is for the purpose of maintaining Christian charity and a humble and contrite spirit. This general confession is practiced in monasteries at the first service on arising (the [[Midnight Office]]) and the last service before retiring to sleep ([[Compline]]). [[Old Believers]] will perform the rite regularly before the beginning of the [[Divine Liturgy]]. The best-known asking of mutual forgiveness occurs at [[Vespers]] on the [[Cheesefare Sunday|Sunday of Forgiveness]], and it is with this act that [[Clean Monday|Great Lent begins]].

===Anglicanism===
In the [[Anglicanism|Anglican]] tradition, confession and absolution is usually a component part of corporate worship, particularly at services of the Holy [[Eucharist]]. The form involves an exhortation to repentance by the priest, a period of silent prayer during which believers may inwardly confess their sins, a form of general confession said together by all present and the pronouncement of general absolution by the priest, often accompanied by the sign of the cross.

Private or auricular confession is also practiced by Anglicans and is especially common among [[Anglo-Catholics]]. The venue for confessions is either in the traditional [[confessional]], which is the common practice among Anglo-Catholics, or in a private meeting with the priest. Often a priest will sit in the sanctuary, just inside the communion rail, facing toward the altar and away from the penitent. Other times he will use a portable screen to divide himself and the penitent. Following the confession of sins and the assignment of penance, the priest makes the pronouncement of absolution.  The [[Seal of the Confessional and the Anglican Church|seal of the confessional]], as with Roman Catholicism, is absolute and any confessor who divulges information revealed in confession is subject to deposition and removal from office.

Historically, the practice of auricular confession was originally a highly controversial one within Anglicanism.  When priests began to hear confessions, they responded to criticisms by pointing to the fact that such is explicitly sanctioned in ''The Order for the Visitation of the Sick'' in the [[Book of Common Prayer]], which contains the following direction: &lt;blockquote&gt;
Here shall the sick person be moved to make a special Confession of his sins, if he feel his conscience troubled with any weighty matter. After which Confession, the Priest shall absolve him (if he humbly and heartily desire it).&lt;/blockquote&gt;  Auricular confession within mainstream Anglicanism became accepted in the second half of the 20th century; the 1979 Book of Common Prayer for the Episcopal Church in the USA provides two forms for it in the section &quot;The Reconciliation of a Penitent.&quot;

Private confession is also envisaged by the [[canon law]] of the [[Church of England]], which contains the following, intended to safeguard the Seal of the Confessional: &lt;blockquote&gt;

if any man confess his secret and hidden sins to the minister, for the unburdening of his conscience, and to receive spiritual consolation and ease of mind from him; we...do straitly charge and admonish him, that he does not at any time reveal and make known to any person whatsoever any crime or offence so committed to his trust and secrecy&lt;ref&gt;''(Proviso to Canon 113 of the Code of 1603, retained in the Supplement to the present Code)''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

There is no requirement for private confession, but a common understanding that it may be desirable depending on individual circumstances. An Anglican aphorism regarding the practice is &quot;All may; none must; some should&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Becker, Michael ''Confession: None must, All may, Some should''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protestantism===
Most [[Protestant]] churches believe that no intermediary except Christ is necessary between the Christian and God in order to be absolved from sins. Many mainline Protestant Churches include corporate confession in regular worship.  For instance the [[Presbyterian Church USA]]'s Directory of Worship, in directing the components or worship, states, &quot;A prayer of confession of the reality of sin in personal and common life follows. In a declaration of pardon, the gospel is proclaimed and forgiveness is declared in the name of Jesus Christ. God’s redemption and God’s claim upon human life are remembered.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcusa.org/oga/publications/2009-2011-boo.pdf pcusa.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Protestants confess their sins in private prayer before God, believing this suffices to gain God's pardon. However confession to another is often encouraged and in some sects or denominations required when a wrong has been done to a person as well as to God. Confession is then made to the person wronged and also to God, and is part of the reconciliation process. In cases where sin has resulted in the exclusion of a person from church membership due to unrepentance, public confession is often a pre-requisite to readmission. The sinner confesses to the church his or her repentance and is received back into fellowship. In both cases there is a required manner to the confessions: for sins between God and Man and for sins between Man and Man.

===Lutheranism===
{{Main|Confession in the Lutheran Church}}

[[File:ArticleXIOfConfession.JPG|209px|thumb|&quot;Private Absolution ought to be retained in the churches, although in confession an enumeration of all sins is not necessary.&quot; —''[[Augsburg Confession]]'', Article 9]]

[[Lutheranism|Lutheran]]s differ from other Protestants as they practice &quot;confession and absolution&quot; (in two forms). They, like Roman Catholics and many Anglicans, see {{Bibleverse||James|5:16|NIV}} and {{Bibleverse||John|20:22-23|NIV}} as biblical evidence for confession.&lt;ref name=&quot;small cat.&quot;&gt;''Luther's Small Catechism with Explanation''&lt;/ref&gt; The first form of confession and absolution is done at the [[Divine Service (Lutheran)|Divine Service]] with the assembled congregation (similar to the [[Anglican]] tradition). Here, the entire congregation pauses for a moment of silent confession, recites the ''[[confiteor]]'', and receives God's forgiveness through the pastor as he says the following (or similar): &quot;Upon this your confession and in the stead and by the command of my Lord Jesus Christ, I forgive you all your sins in the name of the Father and of  the Son and of the Holy Spirit.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;(''[[Lutheran Service Book]], Divine Service I'')&lt;/ref&gt;

The second form of confession and absolution is known as &quot;[[Holy Absolution]]&quot;, which is done privately to the pastor (commonly only upon request). Here the person confessing (known as the &quot;[[penitent]]&quot;) confesses individual their sins and makes an [[Act of Contrition#Lutheran version|act of contrition]] as the pastor, acting [[in persona Christi]], announces this following formula of absolution (or similar): &quot;In the stead and by the command of my Lord Jesus Christ I forgive you all your sins in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;(''[[Lutheran Service Book]], Individual Confession and Absolution'')&lt;/ref&gt; In the Lutheran Church, the pastor is bound by the [[Seal of the Confessional and the Lutheran Church|Seal of the Confessional]] (similar to the Roman Catholic tradition). [[Luther's Small Catechism]] says &quot;the pastor is pledged not to tell anyone else of sins to him in private confession, for those sins have been removed.&lt;ref&gt;small cat.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, the second form of confession and absolution fell into disuse; at the present time, it is, for example, expected before partaking of the [[Eucharist]] for the [[First Communion|first]] time.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Apology of the Augsburg Confession]]'', article 24, paragraph 1. Retrieved 2010-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mormonism===
[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] teaches that &quot;Confession is a necessary requirement for complete forgiveness.&quot; The sinner must confess both to those persons wronged by his sin and to God. Confession may also be required to an authorized [[Priesthood (Latter-day Saint)|Priesthood]] leader: &quot;Those transgressions requiring confession to a bishop are adultery, fornication, other sexual transgressions and deviancies, and sins of a comparable seriousness.&quot; The priesthood leader may counsel the sinner to submit to the authority of a [[disciplinary council]], but does not have the authority to forgive sin. However, the confession must be held in strict confidence unless the sinner grants permission to disclose it to the disciplinary council.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lds.org/ldsorg/v/index.jsp?vgnextoid=024644f8f206c010VgnVCM1000004d82620aRCRD&amp;locale=0&amp;sourceId=ed23ba9ff599b010VgnVCM1000004d82620a____&amp;hideNav=1 New Era: Confession]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Buddhism==
Buddhism has been from its inception primarily a renunciate and monastic tradition. Abstaining from sex and other worldly matters is very much a primary practice compared to Hinduism or the other Abrahamic religions where sex, pleasure and the accumulation of wealth can be seen in the context of doing God's will. Within the monastic framework (called the [[Vinaya]]) of the [[sangha]] regular confession of wrongdoing to superiors (elders; [[Pali]]: [[Thera]]) is mandatory. In the [[sutras]] of the [[Pali Canon]] [[Bhikkhu]]s confessed their wrongdoing to the Buddha himself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.san.beck.org/EC9-Buddha.html san.beck.org]&lt;/ref&gt;  That part of the Pali Canon called the [[Vinaya]] requires that monks confess their individual sins before the bi-weekly convening for the recitation of the [[Patimokkha]] .

== Islam ==
Declaration of faith (''[[shahada]]'') is one of the [[five pillars of Islam]] and is recited a minimum of nine times daily as part of each unit (''[[raka'ah]]'') of the five [[salat|daily prayers]]: a minimum of seventeen ''raka'at'' are performed daily, with the ''shahadah'' recited after every two.

The act of seeking forgiveness from God for sins is called ''[[Istighfar]]''. As in Judaism, confession of sins is made directly to God and not through man (except in asking for forgiveness from the victim of the sin). It is taught that sins are to be kept to oneself to seek individual forgiveness from God. Allah forgives those who seek his forgiveness and commit to themselves not to repeat the sin, although some sins in which another person is victimized are not forgiven unless that person forgives you, so they should also be asked for forgiveness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://qa.sunnipath.com/issue_view.asp?HD=12&amp;ID=4928&amp;CATE=10 qa.sunnipath.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sahih Muslim, Book 37, Tradition 6658&quot;&gt;[http://hadithcollection.com/sahihmuslim/165-Sahih%20Muslim%20Book%2037.%20Repentance%20And%20Exhortation%20Of%20Repentance/14849-sahih-muslim-book-037-hadith-number-6658.html hadithcollection.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Judaism==
{{Main|Confession in Judaism}}
In [[Judaism]], confession is an important part of attaining forgiveness for both sins against God and another man.  Confessions to God are done communally in the plural. Jews confess that &quot;''We'' have sinned.&quot;  In matters involving offenses against a fellow man, private confession to the victim is a requirement to obtaining forgiveness from the victim, which is generally a requirement to obtaining forgiveness from God. If the victim refuses to forgive, the offender confesses publicly, before larger and larger audience. Confession (viduy) is also performed on one's deathbed, if at all possible.

==Alcoholics Anonymous==
In the AA [[Twelve-Step Program]], confession is made in Step 5:  &quot;Admitted to God, to ourselves, and to another human being the exact nature of our wrongs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In early A.A., sharing and confession was an integral part of recovery for alcoholics. Both Bill Wilson and Dr. Bob truly believed that the Fifth Step was absolutely necessary if an alcoholic was to be cured. Even Anne Smith, commonly referred to as the 'Mother of A.A.,' believed that confession, or sharing of wrongs, was vital.&quot; Retrieved from http://aa-history.com/12stephistory2.html&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;If we decline to follow through with this step, our un-confessed sins will haunt us, resulting in the demise of our body and spirit. We will have to continue paying the penalty of our wrongdoings.&quot;

&quot;By completing the Fifth Step, we gain God’s forgiveness, supervision, and strength. We obtain complete forgiveness...&quot; [Quotes are from http://aa-history.com/12stephistory2.html]

==See also==
[[File:The confession.jpg|thumb|right|240px|''The confession'', by [[Pietro Longhi]], ca. 1750]]
*''[[A Confession (novel)|A Confession]]'' by [[Leo Tolstoy]] in which he describes his conversion to Christianity
*[[Absolution]]
*[[Augsburg Confession]], the central document describing the religious convictions of the [[Lutheran]] reformation
*[[Confession inscriptions of Lydia and Phrygia]] Roman-era Greek confession steles
* See ''[[Confessions]]'' for a list of books and albums of that title, most notably ''[[Confessions (St. Augustine)|Confessions]]'' by [[St. Augustine of Hippo]]
*[[Confession of faith]], a statement of doctrine
*[[Lay confession]]
*[[Manifestation of Conscience]]
*[[Nemo tenetur se ipsum accusare]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Commons category|Confessions}}
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11618c.htm The Catholic Encyclopedia's entries on the sacrament of reconciliation]
*[http://www.catholicliturgy.com/index.cfm/FuseAction/documentText/Index/2/SubIndex/40/ContentIndex/450/Start/446  Catholic celebration of the Sacrament of Penance (Rite of Penance)]
*[http://www.americancatholic.org/Features/Sacraments/Reconciliation.asp Confession - Catholic Sacrament of Reconciliation - Penance]
*[http://anglicanhistory.org/confession.html Anglicanism and Confession]
*[http://www.lcms.org/pages/internal.asp?NavID=522  Lutheran view on Confession]
*[http://copticchurch.net/topics/thecopticchurch/sacraments/3_repentance_confesstion.html Sacraments of Repentance and Confession] in the [[Coptic Orthodox Church]]
*[http://en.liturgy.ru/photo/f20.htm Confession in the Russian Orthodox Church] (photo)
*[http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/praxis/pr_confession.aspx Confession] Eastern Orthodox Church
*[http://www.churchfathers.org/category/sacraments/confession/ Church Fathers on Confession]

[[Category:Sacrament of Confession]]
[[Category:Christian theology]]
[[Category:Anglican sacraments]]
[[Category:Eastern Christian liturgy]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Latin loanwords]]

[[bg:Изповед]]
[[ca:Penitència]]
[[cs:Svátost smíření]]
[[da:Konfession]]
[[de:Beichte]]
[[es:Penitencia]]
[[eo:Konfeso]]
[[fa:اعتراف]]
[[fr:Confession]]
[[gd:Aideachadh]]
[[hr:Ispovijed]]
[[io:Konfesiono]]
[[id:Pengakuan dosa]]
[[ia:Confession]]
[[it:Penitenza (sacramento)]]
[[he:וידוי (נצרות)]]
[[ka:სინანული]]
[[la:Confessio]]
[[lt:Išpažintis]]
[[li:Biech]]
[[hu:Gyónás]]
[[mk:Исповед]]
[[nl:Biecht]]
[[ja:告解]]
[[no:Skriftemål]]
[[nn:Skrifte]]
[[pl:Sakrament pokuty i pojednania]]
[[pt:Confissão (sacramento)]]
[[ro:Pocăinţă (taină)]]
[[ru:Исповедь]]
[[sk:Sviatosť zmierenia]]
[[sl:Spoved]]
[[sr:Исповест]]
[[sv:Botens sakrament]]
[[tr:Günah çıkarma]]
[[uk:Сповідь]]
[[zh:告解]]</text>
      <sha1>h2r3mc2cwwlncijml9u7kbfz25uqdqv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
