<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Creed</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7212</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521399276</id>
      <parentid>521395470</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T19:37:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Moe Epsilon</username>
        <id>327589</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/76.226.14.136|76.226.14.136]] identified as test/vandalism using [[WP:STiki|STiki]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15400">{{About|a statement of belief|the American rock band|Creed (band)|other uses|Creed (disambiguation)}}
[[Image:Nicaea icon.jpg|thumb|[[Icon]] depicting [[Constantine I and Christianity|Emperor Constantine]] (center) and the Fathers of the [[First Council of Nicaea]] (325) as holding the [[Niceno-Constantinopolitan Creed]] of 381]]

A '''creed''' is a statement of [[belief]]—usually a [[statement of faith]] that describes the beliefs shared by a religious community—and is often recited as part of a religious service. When the statement of faith is longer and [[polemic]]al, as well as [[Didacticism|didactic]], it is not called a creed but a [[confession of faith]]. The term &quot;creed&quot; can also refer to a person's political or social beliefs or is sometimes used to mean religious affiliation.

One of the most widely used creeds in [[Christianity]] is the [[Nicene Creed]], first formulated in AD 325 at the [[First Council of Nicaea]]. It was based on Christian understanding of the [[Canonical Gospels]], the letters of the [[New Testament]] and to a lesser extent the [[Old Testament]]. Affirmation of this creed, which describes the [[Trinity]], is generally taken as a fundamental test of [[orthodoxy]] for most [[Christian denominations]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spurgeon.org/~phil/creeds/nicene.htm Johnson, Phillip R. &quot;The Nicene Creed.&quot;] Accessed 17 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Apostles' Creed]] is also broadly accepted. Some Christian denominations and other groups have rejected the [[Creed#Christians without creeds|authority of those creeds]].

[[Muslim]]s declare the ''[[shahada]]'', or testimony: &quot;I bear witness that there is no god but (the One) God ''(Allah)'', and I bear witness that Muhammad is God's messenger.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.islamiclearningmaterials.com/shahada.html &quot;Proclaiming the Shahada is the First Step Into Islam.&quot;] Islamic Learning Materials. Accessed: 17 May 2009. See also [http://www.ismailmohr.de/shahada.html &quot;The Shahada, or  Shahāda / kalimatu-sh-shahādah / kelime-i şehadet.&quot;] A. Ismail Mohr. Accessed: 28 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

Whether Judaism is creedal has been a point of some controversy. Although some say Judaism is noncreedal in nature, others say it recognizes a single creed, the ''[[Shema Yisrael]]'', which begins: &quot;Hear, O Israel: the LORD our God, the LORD is one.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Deut|6:4|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
{{see also|Credo}}
The word derives from the Latin ''credo'', which means &quot;I believe&quot; (because the Latin translation of the [[Apostles' Creed]] and the [[Nicene Creed]] both begin with this word) so a creed may also be called a [[credo]]. A creed is sometimes referred to as a [[symbol]] signifying a &quot;token&quot; by which persons of like beliefs might recognize each other.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}

==Christian creeds==
Several creeds have originated in [[Christianity]]. Some of them are:

===Creedal statement in 1 Corinthians 15===
{{Main|1 Corinthians 15}}
1 Corinthians 15, 3-7 includes an early creed about Jesus' death and resurrection which was probably received by Paul. The antiquity of the creed has been located by most biblical scholars to no more than five years after Jesus' death, probably originating from the [[Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem|Jerusalem apostolic community]].&lt;ref&gt;see Wolfhart Pannenberg, Jesus—God and Man translated Lewis Wilkins and Duane Pribe (Philadelphia: Westminster, 1968) p. 90; Oscar Cullmann, The Early church: Studies in Early Christian History and Theology, ed. A. J. B. Higgins (Philadelphia: Westminster, 1966) p. 66–66; R. E. Brown, The Virginal Conception and Bodily Resurrection of Jesus (New York: Paulist Press, 1973) pp. 81; Thomas Sheehan, First Coming: How the Kingdom of God Became Christianity (New York: Random House, 1986) pp. 110, 118; Ulrich Wilckens, Resurrection translated A. M. Stewart (Edinburgh: Saint Andrew, 1977) p. 2; Hans Grass, Ostergeschen und Osterberichte, Second Edition (Gottingen: Vandenhoeck und Ruprecht, 1962) p. 96; Grass favors the origin in Damascus.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Old Roman Creed===
{{Main|Old Roman Creed}}
The Old Roman Creed is an earlier and shorter version of the [[Apostles' Creed]]. It was based on the 2nd century Rules of Faith and the interrogatory declaration of faith for those receiving [[baptism]], which by the 4th century was everywhere tripartite in structure, following Matthew 28:19.

===Nicene Creed===
{{Main|Nicene Creed}}
The [[Nicene Creed]] reflects the concerns of the [[First Council of Nicaea]] in 325 which had as their chief purpose to establish what Christians believed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spurgeon.org/~phil/creeds/nicene.htm Kiefer, James E. &quot;The Nicene Creed.&quot;] Accessed 17 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

===Apostles' Creed===
{{Main|Apostles' Creed}}
The [[Apostles' Creed]] is widely used by most [[List of Christian denominations|Christian denominations]] for both [[liturgy|liturgical]] and [[catechetical]] purposes, most visibly by liturgical Churches of Western tradition, including the [[Latin Rite]] of the [[Roman Catholic Church]], [[Lutheranism]], the [[Anglican Communion]], and [[Western Orthodoxy]]. It is also used by [[Presbyterian]]s, [[Methodist]]s, and [[Congregational church|Congregationalists]].

===Chalcedonian Creed===
{{Main|Chalcedonian Creed}}
The Chalcedonian Creed was adopted at the Council of Chalcedon in 451 in Asia Minor. It defines that Christ is 'acknowledged in two natures', which 'come together into one person and hypostasis'.

===Athanasian Creed===
{{Main|Athanasian Creed}}
The Athanasian Creed (Quicumque vult) is a Christian statement of belief, focusing on Trinitarian doctrine and Christology. It is the first creed in which the equality of the three persons of the Trinity is explicitly stated, and differs from the Nicene and Apostles' Creeds in the inclusion of anathemas, or condemnations of those who disagree with the Creed.

===Tridentine Creed===
{{Main|Tridentine Creed}}
The Tridentine Creed was initially contained in the [[papal bull]] ''[[Iniunctum Nobis]]'', issued by [[Pope Pius IV]] on November 13, 1565.  The creed was intended to summarize the teaching of the [[Council of Trent]] (1545–1563).

===Masai Creed===
{{Main|Masai Creed}}
The Maasai Creed is a creed composed in  1960 by the [[Maasai people]] of East Africa in collaboration with  missionaries  from the [[Holy Ghost Fathers|Congregation of the Holy Ghost]]. The creed attempts to express the essentials of the Christian faith within the Maasai culture.

===Credo of the People of God===
{{Main|Credo of the People of God}}
The Credo of the People of God is a profession of faith that [[Pope Paul VI]] published with the ''[[motu proprio]]'' ''Solemni hac liturgia'' of 30 June 1968. Pope Paul VI spoke of it as &quot;a profession of faith, ... a creed which, without being strictly speaking a dogmatic definition, repeats in substance, with some developments called for by the spiritual condition of our time, the [[Nicene Creed|creed of Nicea]], the creed of the immortal tradition of the holy Church of God&quot;

==Christian confessions of faith==
{{Main|Confession of faith}}
Protestant denominations are usually associated with [[confession of faith|confessions of faith]], which are similar to creeds but usually longer and polemical, as well as didactic.

==Christians without creeds==
{{Main|Free Christian}}
Some Christian denominations, and particularly those descending from the [[Radical Reformation]], do not profess a creed. The Quakers, also known as the [[Religious Society of Friends]], believe that they have no need for creedal formulations of faith. The [[Church of the Brethren]] also espouses no creed, referring to the New Testament, as their &quot;rule of faith and practice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Martin, Harold S.: [http://www.brfwitness.org/?p=88 &quot;Forward&quot;], &quot;Basic Beliefs Within the Church of the Brethren&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] contrast &quot;memorizing or repeating creeds&quot; with acting to &quot;do what Jesus said&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Creeds—Any Place in True Worship?&quot;, ''Awake!'', October 8, 1985, ©Watch Tower, page 23, &quot;The opening words of a creed invariably are, “I believe” or, “We believe.” This expression is translated from the Latin word “credo,” from which comes the word “creed.” ...What do we learn from Jesus’ words? That it is valueless in God’s eyes for one merely to repeat what one claims to believe. ...Thus, rather than memorizing or repeating creeds, we must do what Jesus said&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Unitarian Universalism|Unitarian Universalists]], who practice probably the most liberal of all religions, do not share a creed.&lt;ref&gt;Maxwell, Bill. &quot;Leading the Unitarian Universalist Association, a faith without a creed.&quot; ''St. Petersburg Times.'' Apr 11, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Many evangelical Protestants similarly reject creeds as definitive statements of faith, even while agreeing with some creeds' substance. The [[Baptists]] have been non-creedal &quot;in that they have not sought to establish binding authoritative confessions of faith on one another&quot;.&lt;ref name=Avis&gt;Avis, Paul (2002) ''The Christian Church: An Introduction to the Major Traditions'', SPCK, London, ISBN 0-281-05246-8 paperback&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|p.111}} While many Baptists are not opposed to the ancient creeds, they regard them as &quot;not so final that they cannot be revised and re-expressed. At best, creeds have a penultimacy about them and, of themselves, could never be the basis of Christian fellowship&quot;.&lt;ref name=Avis/&gt;{{rp|p.112}} Moreover, Baptist &quot;confessions of faith&quot; have often had a clause such as this from the First London (Particular) Baptist Confession (Revised edition, 1646):
{{quote|Also we confess that we now know but in part and that are ignorant of many things which we desire to and seek to know: and if any shall do us that friendly part to show us from the Word of God that we see not, we shall have cause to be thankful to God and to them.}}

Similar reservations about the use of creeds can be found in the [[Restoration Movement]] and its descendants, the [[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)]], the [[Churches of Christ]], and the [[Christian churches and churches of Christ]].

Some religious leaders in traditional creedal Churches have also come to question the utility of creeds. Bishop [[John Shelby Spong]], retired [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal]] Bishop of Newark, has written that dogmas and creeds were merely &quot;a stage in our development&quot; and &quot;part of our religious childhood.&quot; In his book, ''Sins of the Scripture'', Spong claims that &quot;Jesus seemed to understand that no one can finally fit the holy God into his or her creeds or doctrines. That is idolatry.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;p. 227&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Many people said (the Apostles Creed), but they understood what it was saying and what they meant by that quite differently. No matter how hard they tried, they could not close out this perennial debate. They cannot establish a consensus and they could not agree on the meaning of that phrase which had been once &quot;delivered to the saints.&quot; It did not occur to these people that the task they were trying to accomplish was not a human possibility, that the mystery of God, including the God they believed they had met in Jesus, could not be reduced to human words and human concepts or captured inside human creeds. Nor did they understand that the tighter and more specific their words became, the less they would achieve the task of unifying the church. All creeds have ever done is to define those who are outside, who were not true believers; and thus their primarily achievement has been to set up eternal conflict between the &quot;ins&quot; and the &quot;outs,&quot; a conflict that has repeatedly degenerated into the darkest sort of Christian behavior, including imperialism, torture, persecution, death and war.&lt;ref&gt;Spong, John S. ''The sins of Scripture.'' HarperCollins, 2005. ISBN 978-0-06-076205-6, p.226&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Jewish creed==
{{see also|Jewish principles of faith}}
Whether [[Judaism]] is creedal in character has generated some controversy. [[Rabbi]] [[Milton Steinberg]] wrote that &quot;By its nature Judaism is averse to formal creeds which of necessity limit and restrain thought&quot; and asserted in his book ''Basic Judaism'' (1947) that &quot;Judaism has never arrived at a creed.&quot; The 1976 Centenary Platform of the [[Central Conference of American Rabbis]], an organization of [[Reform Judaism|Reform]] rabbis agrees that &quot;Judaism emphasizes action rather than creed as the primary expression of a religious live.&quot;

Others, however, characterize the [[Shema Yisrael]]{{Bibleref2c|Deut.|6:4}} as a creedal statement in strict [[monotheism]] embodied in a single prayer. &quot;Hear O Israel, the Lord is our God, the Lord is One&quot; ({{lang-he|שמע ישראל אדני אלהינו אדני אחד}}; [[Romanization of Hebrew|transliterated]] ''Shema Yisrael Adonai Eloheinu Adonai Echad''.) It is recited twice daily by all observant Jews, once when waking up, and once when going to bed.

==Islamic creed==
{{Main|Six Kalimas}}
The [[Islam]]ic creed is the [[Shahadah]], the proclamation لا اله الا الله محمد رسول الله ''(lā ʾilāha ʾillà-llāh, muḥammadun rasūlu-llāh)'' – “There is no god but [[Allah]]; [[Muhammad]] is Allah's messenger.” Taking this creed is one of the [[five pillars of Islam]].

==Non-religious creeds==
The term &quot;creed&quot; can be used to refer to a set of non-religious beliefs, like political or social beliefs. Some examples are the [[American's Creed]] and the [[Social Creed (Methodist)|Social Creed]] adopted by the Methodist Church (which contains both religious and social beliefs).

==See also==
* [[Articles of Faith]]

==Further reading==
* ''[http://yalepress.yale.edu/YupBooks/viewbook.asp?isbn=0300093896 Creeds and Confessions of Faith in the Christian Tradition]''. Edited by Jaroslav Pelikan and Valerie Hotchkiss. Published by [[Yale University Press]] in 2003.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.creeds.net/ The Creeds of Christendom] - A website linking to many formal Christian declarations of faith.
* [http://www.iclnet.org/pub/resources/christian-history.html#creeds Creeds and Canons] - A Guide to Early Church Documents from Internet Christian Library
* [http://www.internationalcreedforpeace.co.uk/ ICP Website International Creed for Peace]

[[Category:Belief]]
[[Category:Statements (religion)]]
[[Category:Religious belief and doctrine]]
[[Category:Religious terminology]]

[[ar:عقيدة دينية]]
[[gn:Arovia]]
[[bg:Верую (Символ на вярата)]]
[[ca:Credo]]
[[cs:Krédo]]
[[da:Bekendelsesskrift]]
[[de:Glaubensbekenntnis]]
[[et:Usutunnistus]]
[[es:Credo (catolicismo)]]
[[eo:Kredokonfeso]]
[[eu:Kredo]]
[[fo:Trúarjáttan]]
[[fr:Credo (religion)]]
[[gl:Credo]]
[[ko:신조]]
[[hy:Հավատո հանգանակ]]
[[id:Kredo]]
[[ia:Credo]]
[[is:Trúarjátning (kristni)]]
[[it:Credo religioso]]
[[he:אני מאמין (תפילה נוצרית)]]
[[kk:Сенім символы]]
[[la:Symbolum]]
[[hu:Hitvallás]]
[[nah:In Teōtlahtōlneltocōni]]
[[nl:Geloofsbelijdenis]]
[[ja:信条]]
[[no:Trosbekjennelse]]
[[nn:Truvedkjenning]]
[[mhr:Ӱшанымашын ӱжватаже]]
[[pl:Chrześcijańskie wyznania wiary]]
[[pt:Credo]]
[[ru:Символ веры]]
[[sl:Veroizpoved]]
[[fi:Uskontunnustus]]
[[sv:Trosbekännelse]]
[[ta:நம்பிக்கை அறிக்கை]]
[[uk:Символ Віри]]
[[zh:信經]]</text>
      <sha1>4guhs4mfq6lragj0dburxd5tutc58f9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
