<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Crypto-Judaism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>213517</id>
    <revision>
      <id>513003171</id>
      <parentid>512047873</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-16T23:12:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gobonobo</username>
        <id>784330</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>converting EL to ref</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30649">[[File:Judaica.jpg|thumb|250px|Judaica (clockwise from top): [[Shabbat]] candlesticks, [[Ritual washing in Judaism|handwashing cup]], [[Chumash (Judaism)|Chumash]] and [[Tanakh]], [[Sefer Torah|Torah]] [[yad|pointer]], [[shofar]], and [[etrog]] box]]
'''Crypto-Judaism''' is the secret adherence to [[Judaism]] while publicly professing to be of another faith; practitioners are referred to as &quot;crypto-Jews&quot; (origin from Greek '''kryptos - κρυπτός''', 'hidden'). The term crypto-Jew is also used to describe descendants who maintain some Jewish traditions of their ancestors, often secretly, while publicly adhering to other faiths, most commonly [[Catholicism]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Jacobs&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Hidden Heritage: The Legacy of the Crypto-Jews|last=Jacobs|first=J| year=2002| publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-23517-5|oclc=48920842|page={{page needed|date=September 2011}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=A History of the Jews in New Mexico|last=Tobias|first=HJ|publisher=University of New Mexico Press|year=1992|isbn=978-0-8263-1390-4|oclc=36645510|page={{page needed|date=September 2011}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Marrano Legacy: A Contemporary Crypto-Jewish Priest Reveals Secrets of His Double Life|last=Alexy|first=T|year=2003| publisher=University of New Mexico Press|isbn=978-0-8263-3055-0|oclc=51059087|page={{page needed|date=September 2011}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Sephardi Jewry: A History of the Judeo-Spanish Community, 14th-20th Centuries (Jewish Communities in the Modern World) |last=Benbassa|first=E|coauthors= Rodrique, A |year=2000|publisher=University of California Press|isbn=978-0-520-21822-2|oclc=154877054|page={{page needed|date=September 2011}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Jews of Spain: A History of the Sephardic Experience|last=Gerber|first=JS|year=1994|publisher=Free Press|isbn=978-0-02-911574-9|oclc=30339044|page={{page needed|date=September 2011}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; The phenomenon is especially associated with early modern Spain, following the [[Alhambra decree|expulsion of the Jews in 1492]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Levine&quot;&gt;Levine Melammed, Renee.  &quot;Women in Medieval Jewish Societies.&quot; ''Women and Judaism: New Insights and Scholarship''.  Ed. Frederick E. Greenspahn.  New York: New York University Press, 2009.  105-106.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Europe==
Officially, Jews who converted in Spain in the 14th and 15th centuries were known as [[New Christian|''Cristianos Nuevos'' (New Christians)]], but were commonly called ''[[converso]]s''.  Spain and Portugal passed legislation restricting their rights in the mother countries and colonies.  Despite the dangers of the Inquisition, many ''conversos'' continued to secretly and discreetly practice Jewish rituals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levine&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See David M. Gitlitz, ''Secrecy and Deceit: The Religion of the Crypto-Jews'' (Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 2002).&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Balearic Islands, numerous ''conversos'', also called [[Chuetas]], publicly professed [[Roman Catholicism]] but privately adhered to Judaism after the [[Alhambra decree]] of 1492 and during the [[Spanish Inquisition]].  They are among the most widely-known crypto-Jews.

Crypto-Judaism dates back to earlier periods when Jews were forced or pressured to convert by the rulers of places they lived in.

Some of the Jewish followers of [[Sabbatai Zevi]] ([[Sabbateans]]) formally converted to Islam, and later followers of [[Jacob Frank]] (&quot;Frankists&quot;) formally converted to Christianity, but maintained aspects of their versions of [[Messianic Judaism]].

Crypto-Jews persisted in Russia and Eastern European countries influenced by the Soviet Union after the rise of Communism with the [[October Revolution|Russian Revolution]] of 1917.  Rather than being forced to convert, all religion was regarded as undesirable, although some faiths were allowed to continue under strict supervision by the regime.  Since the end of Communism, many people in former Soviet states, including descendants of Jews, have publicly taken up the faith of their families again.

The &quot;[[Belmonte Jews]]&quot; of Portugal, dating from the 12th century, maintained strong secret traditions for centuries. A whole community survived in secrecy by maintaining a tradition of intermarriage and hiding all external signs of their faith. They and their practices were discovered only in the 20th century. Their rich Sephardic tradition of Crypto-Judaism is unique. Only recently did they contact other Jews.  Some now profess Orthodox Judaism, although many still retain their centuries-old traditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ourjerusalem.com/news/story/news20031018.html|title=For Portugal’s crypto-Jews, new rabbi tries to blend tradition with local custom|year=2003|last=Socolovsky|first=J|accessdate=2007-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Xuetes===
The [[Xueta]] are a minority on the [[Balearic Islands|Balearic]] island of [[Majorca]] (Mallorca) who are descended almost entirely from crypto-Jews, forced to convert in 1391. The term &quot;xueta&quot; literally translates to &quot;pig&quot;{{Citation needed|date=September 2012}} in [[Catalan language|Catalan]], similar to the old Spanish ([[Names given to the Spanish language|Castilian]]) term and ''[[marrano]]'', both of the same meaning.

Today, they comprise a population of 20,000–25,000 on an island of 750,000; they have professed [[Roman Catholicism]] for centuries but have only recently seen a lessening in tensions with ethnic Majorcans.  According to some [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] [[rabbi]]s, the majority of Xuetes are probably Jewish under [[Halakha|Jewish law]] (by descent from Jewish mothers) due to the low rate of [[Interreligious marriage|intermarriage]] with outside groups.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} Only recently have intermarriages between the two groups been more prevalent or noticeable.

During World War II, [[Nazi Germany]] was known to have pressured Majorcan religious authorities into surrendering the Xuetes, targeted because of their Jewish ancestry.  Reportedly the religious authorities refused the Nazi request.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

Several Xuetes are reported to have &quot;reconverted&quot; to Judaism.  Some have become rabbis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gitlitz&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title= Secrecy and Deceit: The Religion of the Crypto-Jews|year=2000|publisher=Jewish Publication Society of America|first=D|last=Gitlitz| isbn=978-0-8276-0562-6|oclc=33861844}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Neofiti===
The [[Neofiti]] were a group of crypto-Jews living in the [[Kingdom of Sicily]] which not only included the island of Sicily but nearly all of Southern Italy from the 13th to the 16th centuries.

==Asia==
There are, or have been, several communities of Crypto-Jews in Muslim lands.  The ancestors of the [[Daggatun]]s probably kept up their Jewish practises a long time after their nominal adoption of Islam.  A large community of Crypto-Jews lived in [[Mashhad]], near [[greater Khorasan|Khorassan]], where they were known as &quot;Jedid al-Islam&quot;, who were mass-converted to Islam around 1839. Most of this community left for Israel in 1946, but some have converted into Muslims and live in Iran today.&lt;ref name=&quot;JedidAlIslam&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |url=http://www.fis-iran.org/en/irannameh/volxix/mashhad-jewish-community |journal=Iran Nameh |volume=XIX |title=The &quot;Jadid Al-Islams&quot; of Mashhad |author=Jaleh Pirnazar |publisher=Foundation for Iranian Studies}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nissimi&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |url=http://www.sussex-academic.co.uk/sa/titles/jewish_studies/nissimi.htm |title=The Crypto-Jewish Mashhadis |author=Hilda Nissimi |isbn=978-1-84519-160-3 |date=December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the central [[Iran]]ian village of Sebe, local Muslims practice many Jewish customs, such as women lighting a candle on Friday night (the eve of the [[Shabbat|Jewish Sabbath]]). Before sundown on Friday, they prepare a small fire which they leave on throughout Saturday, so as not to ignite the fire on Sabbath.

==North America==
There are three distinct historical components to colonial roots of crypto-Judaism, largely restricted to Spanish-held territories in Mexico, each with distinct geographical and temporal aspects: early colonial roots, the frontier province of [[Nuevo León]], and the later northern frontier provinces.  The crypto-Jewish traditions have complex histories and are typically embedded in an amalgam of syncretic Roman Catholic and Judaic traditions.  In many ways resurgent Judaic practices mirrored indigenous peoples' maintaining their traditions practiced loosely under Roman Catholic veil.  In addition, Catholicism was syncretic, absorbing other traditions and creating a new creole religion.

===Early colonial period — 16th century===
However, Portugal in 1497 issued a similar decree that effectively converted all remaining Jewish children, making them wards of the state unless the parents also converted.  Therefore, many of the early crypto-Jewish migrants to Mexico in the early colonial days were technically first to second generation Portuguese with Spanish roots before that.  The number of such Portuguese migrants was significant enough that the label of &quot;Portuguese&quot; became synonymous with &quot;Jewish&quot; throughout the Spanish colonies.  [[Immigration to Mexico]] offered lucrative trade possibilities in a well-populated colony with nascent Spanish culture counterbalanced by a large non-Christian population.  Migrants thought the culture would be more tolerant since the lands were overwhelmingly populated by non-Christian indigenous peoples.

Colonial officials believed that many crypto-Jews were going to Mexico during the 16th century and complained in written documents to Spain that Spanish society in Mexico would become significantly Jewish.  Officials found and condemned clandestine synagogues in Mexico City. At this point, colonial administrators instituted [[cleanliness of blood|the Law of the Pure Blood]], which prohibited migration to Mexico for [[New Christian]]s (Cristiano Nuevo), i.e. anyone who could not prove to be Old Christians for at least the last three generations.  During this time, the administration initiated the [[Mexican Inquisition]] to ensure the Catholic orthodoxy of all migrants into Mexico.  The Mexico Inquisition was also deployed in the traditional manner to ensure orthodoxy of converted indigenous peoples.  The first victims of burnings or [[Auto de Fe|autos de fé]] of the Mexican Inquisition were indigenous converts convicted of heresy or crypto-Jews convicted of relapsing into their ancestral faith.{{Citation needed|date=April 2007}}

Except for the province of ''Nuevo León'', initiation of the Blood Purity Laws reduced the migration of conversos.

===Nuevo León — 1590s to early 17th century===
The history of the colonization of Mexico can be described as a northward expansion over increasingly hostile geography well-populated by angered tribes and loose confederations of indigenous peoples being conquered.  Spain financed the expansion by exploiting mineral wealth, using indigenous peoples as labor in mines, and establishing ''ranchos'' for raising livestock.  One troublesome region was a large expanse covering the North-Eastern quadrant of [[New Spain]] (Nueva España).  [[Chichimec]], [[Apache]] and other tribes were resistant to Christianization and &quot;settling&quot;.  They were perceived to render the frontier (''[[frontera]]'') a lawless and unsettled region.

[[Luis Carvajal y de la Cueva]] was a Portuguese New Christian royal accountant who received a royal charter to settle [[Nuevo León]], a large expanse of land in the hostile frontier.  Significantly, in the charter Carvajal y de la Cueva received an exemption from the usual requirement that he prove that all new settlers were &quot;old Christians&quot; rather than recently converted Jews or Muslims.  This exemption allowed people, especially Crypto-Jews, to come to Nuevo León who were legally barred from entering [[New Spain]] elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=La colonización del Nuevo Reino de León. Y la fundación de Monterrey, por el ilustre gobernador:  Don Luis Carvajal y de la Cueva. |date=June 2007 |url=http://www.rcadena.net/carvajal/carvajal.htm |accessdate=March 4, 2011 |language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Many of the 100 soldiers and 60 laborers Carabajal was authorized to bring to New Spain were Crypto-Jews.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=138&amp;letter=C Jewish Encyclopedia: Carabajal]. Accessed Mar 5, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

With Carvajal as governor, Monterrey was established as the center, currently in the state of Nuevo León.  Within a few years, some people reported to Mexico City that Jewish rites were being performed in the Northern Province and efforts to convert heathen indigenous peoples were lax.{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}} The principal economic activity of Carvajal and his associates seems to have been capturing [[Indigenous people of the Americas|Indians]] and selling them into slavery.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last1=Flint |first1=Richard |last2=Cushing |first2=Shirley  |title=Juan Morlete, Gaspar Castano de Sosa, and the Province of Nuevo Leon |publisher=New Mexico Office of the State Historian |url=http://www.newmexicohistory.org/filedetails.php?fileID=476 |accessdate=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Carvajal's  Lieutenant Governor, [[Gaspar Castaño de Sosa]], led a large  expedition to [[New Mexico]] in 1591 in an effort to establish a colony.  Castaño was arrested for this unauthorized expedition and sentenced to exile in the [[Philippines]].  The sentence was later reversed but he had already been killed in a slave revolt.&lt;ref&gt;Hammond, George P. and Rey, Apapito, ''The Rediscovery of New Mexico, 1580-1594'', Albuquerque: U of NM Press, 1966, pp. 48, 245-301&lt;/ref&gt;

The governor, his immediate family members, and others of his entourage were called to appear before the Inquisition in Mexico City.  They were arrested and jailed. The governor subsequently died in jail, while his family members were rehabilitated.  One of these was Anna Carvajal, a niece of the Governor. She and others were later again taken captive and sentenced to burning at the stake for relapsing.

The governor's nephews changed their name to Lumbroso.  One of these was Joseph Lumbroso, also known as [[Luis de Carabajal the younger|Luis de Carvajal el Mozo]], who is said to have circumcised himself in the desert to conform to Jewish law. His memoirs, letters and inquisition record survive. Two other nephews also changed their names to Lumbroso and migrated to Italy, where they became famous rabbis.

When Governor Carvajal was in office, the city of Monterrey became a destination for other crypto-Jews feeling the pressure of the Mexican Inquisition in the south of the territory.  Thus, the story of Nuevo León and the founding of Monterrey are significant as it attracted crypto-Jewish migrants from all parts of [[New Spain]].  They created one of the earliest Jewish-related communities in earlier Mexico.  (The Jewish communities in modern Mexico which practice their Judaism openly were not established until the considerable immigration from eastern Europe, Turkey and Syria in the late 19th century and 20th century.)

===Former Mexican territories in the modern-day southwestern U.S. 17th century–18th century===
Due to the activities of the Mexican Inquisition in Nuevo León, many crypto-Jewish descendants migrated to other frontier colonies further west to the trade routes passing through the towns of Sierra Madres Occidental and Chihuahua, Hermosillo and Cananea (Canaan) and further north on the trade route to Paso del Norte (Juarez/El Paso) and Santa Fe (both cities in the then colonial Province of New Mexico), Bisbee Arizona and somewhat less in Alta California.

In the former Spanish-held northern New Spain (modern-day [[Southwestern United States]]), some [[Hispanic]] Roman Catholics have stated a belief that they are descended from crypto-Jews and have started practicing Judaism. They often cite as evidence memories of older relatives practicing Jewish traditions. The crypto-Jews of New Mexico have been documented by several research scholars including Stanley M. Hordes,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=To The End of The Earth: A History of the Crypto-Jews of [[New Mexico]]|year=2005|last=Hordes|first=Stanley M.|isbn= 978-0-231-12937-4|publisher=Columbia University Press|pages=376}}&lt;/ref&gt; Janet Liebman Jacobs,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Hidden Heritage: The Legacy of the Crypto Jews]]|year=2002|last=Liebman Jacobs|first=Janet|isbn= 978-0-520-23517-5|publisher=University of California|pages=212}}&lt;/ref&gt; Schulamith Halevy, and Seth D. Kunin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Juggling Identities: Identity and Authenticity Among the Crypto-Jews]]|year=2009|last=Kunin|first=Seth D.|isbn= 978-0-231-14218-2|publisher=Columbia University Press|pages=288}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Only one researcher, folklorist Judith Neulander, has been skeptical of the authenticity of the Jewish ancestry of Hispanos of the Southwest, she argues that these remembered traditions could be those of [[Ashkenazi]], not [[Sephardi]], Jews and may possibly be constructed memories due to suggestion by proponents. She also argues that the Jewish traditions practiced by older relatives were introduced by groups of [[Evangelicalism|Evangelical Protestant]] [[Christian]]s who purposely acquired and employed Jewish traditions as part of their religious practices. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theatlantic.com/past/docs/issues/2000/12/ferry.htm |title=Mistaken Identity? The Case of New Mexico's &quot;Hidden Jews&quot; |date=December 2000 |publisher=[[The Atlantic]] |author=Barbara Ferry and Debbie Nathan}}&lt;/ref&gt; Neulander's theory has been directly addressed in Kunin's book &quot;Juggling Identities: Identity and Authenticity Among the Crypto-Jews&quot;. More recently, [[Evangelicalism|Evangelical Protestant]] [[Christian]]s have opened missionary groups aimed at cultivating evangelical doctrine in Southwestern American communities where crypto-Judaism had survived.

===Current times===
According to a recent study (December 2008) published in the American Journal of Human Genetics, 19.8 percent of modern Spaniards (and Portuguese) have DNA reflecting Sephardic Jewish ancestry (compared to 10.6 percent having DNA reflecting Moorish ancestors.[1]. The Sephardic result is in contradiction or not replicated in all the body of genetic studies done in Iberia and has been relativized by the authors themselves and questioned by Stephen Oppenheimer who estimate that much earlier migrations, 5,000 to 10,000 years ago from the Eastern Mediterranean might also have accounted for the Sephardic estimates. &quot;They are really assuming that they are looking at this migration of Jewish immigrants, but the same lineages could have been introduced in the Neolithic&quot;. The same authors in also a recent study (October 2008) attributed most of those same lineages in Iberia and the Balearic Islands as of Phoenician origin.The rest of genetic studies done in Spain estimate the Moorish contribution ranging from 2.5/3.4% to 7.7%.

Recent genetic research, however, has shown that many Latinos of the American Southwest may be descended from [[Anusim]] (Sephardic Jews who converted to Roman Catholicism). Michael Hammer, a research professor at the University of Arizona and an expert on Jewish genetics, said that fewer than 1% of non-Semites, but more than four times the entire Jewish population of the world, possessed the male-specific &quot;[[Y-chromosomal Aaron|Cohanim marker]]&quot; (which in itself is not necessarily carried by all Jews, but is prevalent among Jews claiming descent from hereditary priests), and 30 of 78 Latinos tested in [[New Mexico]] (38.5%) were found to be carriers. DNA testing of Hispanic populations also revealed between 10% and 15% of men living in New Mexico, south [[Texas]] and northern [[Mexico]] have a [[Y chromosome]] that traces back to the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.khazaria.com/genetics/abstracts-nonjews.html|title=Jewish Genetics:  Abstracts and Summaries.  Part 4:  Non-Jewish Israelites.|year=2005|publisher=[http://www.khazaria.com The American Center of Khazar Studies]|accessdate=2007-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is no certainty that these lineages are Middle Eastern, as they could also be of earlier Phoenician and later North African influence. Tunisians also rank very high with the Y- chromosome marker that is related to conahim. There could be a North African connection for this as well. There is no specific Jewish DNA marker and with so much moorish and Phoenician settlement in Spain one cannot tell the religion of the bearers ancestors.

In northern Mexico, [[Monterrey]], the capital city of the state of [[Nuevo León]], that shares a border with [[Texas]], is said to contain descendants of Crypto-Jews. The church in Agualeguas, Nuevo León, Mexico indeed has Star of David windows beneath the Christian cross atop the domed roof. The state of [[Jalisco]] has several cities with large numbers of [[Anusim]], mainly [[Guadalajara, Jalisco|Guadalajara]], [[Ciudad Guzmán]], and [[Puerto Vallarta]], although a steady influx of [[Ashkenazi]] Jews from Eastern Europe during the late 19th century and early to mid-20th century into Mexico City, Guadalajara, and [[Veracruz]] is also widely known.

In the Old Town area of Albuquerque New Mexico, the San Felipe de Neri Catholic Church, built in 1793 to replace the original 1706 mission church, contains a Star of David on the left and right sides of the altar; evidence of the influence of Crypto-Jews in New Mexico.  Many Jewish symbols can be found on cemetery headstones in Northern New Mexico, along side Catholic crosses.&lt;ref&gt;http://members.virtualtourist.com/m/p/m/d4efb/&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, there are about 40,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Jewish Year Book|The Jewish Year Book 2007]]|year=2007|last=Massil|first=SW (editor)|isbn= 978-0-85303-735-4|publisher=Mitchell Vallentine &amp; Company|pages=163}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mexican Jews, both [[Ashkenazi]] and [[Sephardi]].  Researchers and historians say that number would rise considerably if Anusim (or Crypto-Jews) were included in those estimates.

==Central, South America and Caribbean==
As in the American Southwest, in the department of [[Antioquia Department|Antioquia]], [[Colombia]], as well as in the greater [[Paisa Region|Paisa region]], many families also hold traditions and oral accounts of Jewish descent. In this population, Y chromosome genetic analysis has shown an origin of founders predominantly from &quot;southern Spain but also suggest that a fraction came from northern Iberia and that some possibly had a Sephardic origin&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Strong Amerind/White Sex Bias and a Possible Sephardic Contribution among the Founders of a Population in Northwest Colombia|last=Carvajal-Carmona|first=LG|coauthors=Soto ID, Pineda N, Ortiz-Barrientos D, Duque C, Ospina-Duque J, McCarthy M, Montoya P, Alvarez VM, Bedoya G, and Ruiz-Linares A|year=2000|journal=American Journal of Human Genetics|volume=67|issue=5|pages=1062–1066|pmid=11032790|doi=10.1016/S0002-9297(07)62956-5|pmc=1288568}} bad link&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Medellín]] tradition of the ''marranada'', where a [[pig]] is slaughtered, butchered and consumed on the streets of every neighborhood each [[Christmas]] has been interpreted as an annual affirmation of the rejection of Jewish law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pasaportecolombiano.wordpress.com/2007/12/07/medellin-resplandece-en-diciembre-la-luciernaga-de-colombia/|year=2007|title=Medellín resplandece en diciembre|last=Rodas|first=Albeiro|accessdate=2009-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A safe haven destination for [[Sephardic Jews|Sephardic]] [[Conversos]] during the Spanish Colony was [[Santa Cruz de la Sierra]].&lt;ref&gt;“Farewell España, The World The Sephardim Remembered”, written by Howard Sachar&lt;/ref&gt; In 1557 many Crypto-Jews joined [[Ñuflo de Chávez]] and were among the pioneers who founded the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;“History of the Jewish People”, written by Eli Birnbaum&lt;/ref&gt; During the 16th century several Crypto-Jews that faced persecution from the Inquisition and local authorities in nearby [[Potosí]], [[La Paz]] and [[Sucre|La Plata]] also moved to Santa Cruz for it was the most isolated urban settlement and because the Inquisition did not bother the [[Conversos]] there&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;&quot;Storm Clouds over the Bolivian Refuge&quot;, written by Sherry Mangan&lt;/ref&gt; for this frontier town was meant to be a buffer to the Portuguese and [[Guaraní people|Guaraní]] raids that threatened the mines of Peru.  Several of them settled in the city of Santa Cruz and its adjacent towns of [[Vallegrande]], Postrervalle, [[Portachuelo]], Terevinto, [[Pucarà, Bolivia]], [[Cotoca]] and others.&lt;ref&gt;“Los Judíos de Vallegrande”, El Deber, written by Mario Rueda Peña, November 23, 1995&lt;/ref&gt;

Several of the oldest Catholic families in Santa Cruz are in fact of Jewish origin; some traces of Judaic practices are still alive among them and have also influence the rest of the community. As recent as the 1920s, several families preserved seven-branched candle sticks and served dishes cooked with reminiscing [[kosher]] practices.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;  It is still customary among certain old families to light candles on Friday at sunset and to mourn the deaths of dear relatives on the floor.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; After almost five centuries, some of the descendants of these families still acknowledge their Jewish origin, but practice Catholicism (in certain cases with some Jewish syncretism).

Some Crypto-Jews established in the outskirts of [[San José, Costa Rica|San José]], [[Costa Rica]] since the XVI century. They passed as Catholics in public and practiced their Jewish rituals in privacy. In the town of Itzkazú (modern day Escazú) some Crypto-Jewish families could not achieve total secrecy of their condition and locals started to associate their rituals and unintelligible prayers in Hebrew as witchcraft. Since then, Escazú has been known in Costarrican folklore as the ¨city of the witches¨.

In addition to these communities, Roman Catholic-professing communities who are descendants of Crypto-Jews are said to exist in [[the Dominican Republic]], [[Cuba]], [[Jamaica]], Puerto Rico&lt;ref name=&quot;clara&quot;/&gt; and in various other Spanish-speaking countries of [[South America]], such as [[Argentina]], [[Venezuela]], [[Chile]] and [[Ecuador]].  From these communities comes the proverb, &quot;Catholic by faith, Jewish by blood&quot;.

All the above localities were former territories of either the Spanish or Portuguese Empires, where the Inquisition eventually followed and continued investigating Crypto-Jews who had settled there.  The Inquisition endured longer in the colonies than it had in Spain itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;clara&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sefarad.org/publication/lm/037/6.html|year=1999|title=The Inquisition in the New World|last=Steinberg-Spitz|first=Clara|accessdate=2007-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Famous Crypto-Jews==
*[[Dona Gracia Mendes Nasi]] was a 16th century international banker who created an escape network that saved thousands of Crypto-Jews from the Inquisition. She was also a patron of (Jewish) writers, and a diplomat on behalf of her people, who also attempted to start a modern state of Israel.
*[[José Luis Carvajal y de la Cueva|Luis de Carvajal]] was the governor of the state of [[Nuevo León]], a northern Mexico province in which the restriction against immigration from [[conversos]] was relaxed in order to encourage migration to the peril-fraught frontier.  He was responsible for bringing a significant group of crypto-Jewish conversos living in Portugal since the [[Spanish Inquisition|Expulsion]] of 1492.
*[[Luis de Carvajal el Mozo]], was the nephew of Jose Luis Carvajal y de la Cueva, the only crypto-Jew of the Spanish colonial era whose memoirs have been preserved.
*[[Antonio Fernandez Carvajal]] was a Portuguese merchant in London; &quot;like other Marranos in London, Carvajal prayed at the Catholic chapel of the Spanish ambassador, while simultaneously playing a leading role in the secret Jewish community, which met at the clandestine synagogue at Creechurch Lane.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DNB&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Oxford [[Dictionary of National Biography]]|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2004|last=Matthew|first=HCG (editor)|coauthor=Harrison, B (editor)|isbn=978-0-19-861411-1|oclc=166700558}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Some scholars of [[Judaic studies]] believe that [[Miguel de Cervantes]] may have been a crypto-Jew or of crypto-Jewish descent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cryptojews.com/Cervantes_Hebrew_Scriptures.html|title=Cervantes, Don Quijote, and the Hebrew Scriptures|year=2004|last=Larsen|first=KS|accessdate=2007-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Rodrigo Lopez (physician)|Rodrigo Lopez]], a converso who fled from Portugal to England and became physician to [[Queen Elizabeth I]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DNB&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{div col|cols=3}}
*[[Anusim]]
*[[Crypto-Christianity]]
*[[Crypto-Paganism]]
*[[Doctrine of mental reservation]]
*[[Dönmeh]]
*[[History of the Jews in Latin America]]
*[[History of the Jews in the Netherlands]]
*[[Jewish ethnic divisions]]
*[[Jewish history]]
*[[Kakure Kirishitan]]
*[[Limpieza de sangre]]
*[[Marrano]]
*[[Morisco]]
*[[Sephardic Jews in India]]
*[[Taqiyya]]
*[[Who Is A Jew?]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
*{{JewishEncyclopedia}}
*Gitlitz, David. ''Secrecy and Deceit: The Religion of the Crypto-Jews'', Albuquerque, NM: University of New Mexico Press, 2002

==External links==
*[http://www.dinur.org/resources/resourceCategoryDisplay.aspx?categoryid=445&amp;rsid=478 Resources &gt; Medieval Jewish History &gt; Expulsion from Spain and The Anusim] The Jewish History Resource Center, Project of the Dinur Center for Research in Jewish History, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem
*[http://www.donagraciaproject.org/ Donagraciaproject.org]
*[http://www.jackwhite.net/iberia/ The Story of Secret and Forcibly Converted Jews]
*[http://parentseyes.arizona.edu/bloom/carvajal.htm Luis Carvajal's 400th Yartzheit]
*[http://www.cryptojews.com/ Society for Crypto Judaic Studies]
*[http://www.miriamherrera.com/crypto-jewishlinks Crypto Jews/Anusim Resources ]
*[http://www.shavei.org Shavei Israel - a group tht helps our lost brethren return]
*[http://bethaderech.com/category/anusim/ Beth HaDerech - Returning to Judaism]

[[Category:Crypto-Judaism| ]]
[[Category:Passing (sociology)]]

[[bg:Криптоюдаизъм]]
[[ca:Criptojudaisme]]
[[de:Kryptojuden]]
[[es:Cripto-judaísmo]]
[[fr:Crypto-judaïsme]]
[[it:Cripto-Giudaismo]]
[[nl:Cryptojodendom]]
[[oc:Criptojudaïsme]]
[[pl:Kryptojudaizm]]
[[pt:Criptojudaísmo]]
[[ru:Криптоиудаизм]]
[[tr:Kripto Yahudilik]]</text>
      <sha1>6tnno8lqdsitq2x4lc5his0j3eted1w</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
