<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dabru Emet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>99405</id>
    <revision>
      <id>488859775</id>
      <parentid>484573392</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-23T18:53:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>190.62.158.155</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Controversy */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7703">{{Quotefarm|article|date=December 2008}}The '''Dabru Emet''' ([[Hebrew language|Heb.]] '''דברו אמת''' &quot;Speak [the] Truth&quot;) is a document concerning the relationship between [[Christianity]] and [[Judaism]]. It was signed by over 220 [[rabbi]]s and [[intellectual]]s from all branches of [[Judaism]], as individuals and not as representing any organisation or stream of Judaism. 

The Dabru Emet was first published on September 10th, 2000, in the [[New York Times]], and has since been used in Jewish education programs across the U.S. While affirming that there are theological differences between these two religions, the purpose of Dabru Emet is to point out common ground and a legitimacy of Christianity, for non-Jews, from the Jewish perspective. It is not an official document of any of the Jewish denominations per se, but it is representative of what many [[Jew]]s feel. 

== Controversy ==
There are various objections to ''Dabru Emet'' from within the Jewish community. 

Some hold that it understates the significant [[theology|theological]] differences between the two religions. Thus, most [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] and [[Reform Judaism|Reform]] rabbis have not signed it, although many do agree with most of the document. Very few [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox rabbis]] have signed it; The Institute for Public Affairs, of the ''Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations'' (commonly known as the [[Orthodox Union]]) issued this response:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ou.org/public/statements/2000/betty25.htm |title=Statement by Dr. David Berger Regarding Dabru Emet Ad - September 14, 2000 - OU/IPA Interactive Center at |publisher=Ou.org |date=2000-09-14 |accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|This is in many ways an admirable statement composed by people for whom I have high regard.  I agree with much of it, including the controversial but carefully balanced passage denying that [[Nazism]] was a [[Christianity|Christian]] phenomenon.  However, I did not agree to sign it for several reasons.  First, for all its exquisitely skillful formulation, it implies that Jews should reassess their view of Christianity in light of Christian reassessments of Judaism.  This inclination toward theological reciprocity is fraught with danger.  Second, although it is proper to emphasize that Christians &quot;worship the [[God]] of [[Abraham]], [[Isaac]], and [[Jacob]], creator of heaven and earth,&quot; it is essential to add that worship of [[Jesus]] of Nazareth as a manifestation or component of that God constitutes what [[halakha|Jewish law]] and theology call ''avodah zarah'', or foreign worship ([[idolatry]])—at least if done by a Jew.  Many Jews died to underscore this point, and the bland assertion that &quot;Christian worship is not a viable choice for Jews&quot; is thoroughly inadequate.  Finally, the statement discourages either community from &quot;insisting that it has interpreted Scripture more accurately than the other.&quot;  While intended for the laudable purpose of discouraging missionizing, this assertion conveys an uncomfortably relativistic message.}}

While agreeing with desire to encourage inter-faith dialogue and reconciliation, many Jews [who?] disagree with the section in Dabru Emet which holds that Christian theology is not in any way to blame for most of the last 2,000 years of [[anti-Semitism]], or [[the Holocaust]]. Instead, it is believed by many Jews that much of Christian theology and teachings have been deeply anti-Semitic. Jews point to statements in the [[New Testament]], such as {{bibleverse||John|8:43-47|31}}, which contain potentially divisive narratives about Jews:

{{Quote box|Because you are unable to hear what I say, you belong to your father, the [[devil]], and you want to carry out your father's desire!  He was a murderer from the beginning, not holding to the truth, for there is no truth in him! When he lies, he speaks his native language, for he is a liar and the father of lies!  Yet because I tell the truth, you do not believe me.  He who belongs to God hears what God says.  The reason that you do not hear is that you do not belong to God.}}

This statement prompted [[Protestant]] Christian pastor [[A. Roy Eckardt]] to describe these words as &quot;the road to [[Auschwitz]]&quot;. Many Jews agree, and thus cannot sign ''Dabru Emet''. 

Critics of ''Dabru Emet'' hold that it is false to claim that the Nazis would move on to exterminate Christians after they finished with the Jews. [[Germany]] and [[Austria]] had deeply religious Christian populations, and a majority of Christians in these nations supported the anti-Semitic Nazi policies throughout all of World War II.[Source?] In Germany over a half-million Christians developed a church that praised both Jesus and Hitler in their services [Source?]. Thus, many Jews feel that this document is white-washing Christian responsibility for the Holocaust [Source?].

The signatories signed as individuals, not representing any Jewish organisation or stream of Judaism.  Furthermore, it was a predominantly American effort, without any consultation or input from Jewish communities outside of the [[United States]].

==Reaction==

The European [[Lutheran]] Commission on the Church and the Jewish People (Lutherische Europäische Kommission Kirche und Judentum, LEKKJ), an [[umbrella organization]] representing twenty-five Lutheran church bodies in Europe, issued on May 12, 2003 ''A Response to Dabru Emet'':&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=A Response to Dabru Emet |publisher=[[International Council of Christians and Jews]] |date=2003-06-01 |url=http://www.jcrelations.net/en/?item=1981 |accessdate=2008-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|In its Driebergen Declaration (1991), the European Lutheran Commission on the Church and the Jewish People… rejected the traditional Christian “teaching of contempt” towards Jews and Judaism, and in particular, the anti-Jewish writings of [[Martin Luther]], and it called for the reformation of church practice in the light of these insights. Against this background, LEKKJ welcomes the issuance of Dabru Emet: A Jewish Statement on Christians and Christianity. We see in this statement a confirmation of our own work of these past years… We know that we must reexamine themes in Lutheran theology that in the past have repeatedly given rise to enmity towards Jews… Fully aware that ''Dabru Emet'' is in the first instance an intra-Jewish invitation to conversation, we see in this statement also an aid to us in expressing and living out our faith in such a way that we do not denigrate Jews, but rather respect them in their otherness, and are enabled to give an account of our own identity more clearly as we scrutinize it in the light of how others see us.}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Criticism of Dabru Emet==
*&lt;u&gt;How not to conduct Jewish-Christian dialogue&lt;/u&gt; Jon D Levenson; ''Commentary''; Dec 2001; Vol. 112(5)
*&lt;u&gt;Jewish-Christian dialogue&lt;/u&gt; Jon D Levenson; ''Commentary''; Apr 2002; Vol. 113(4)

==External links==
*[http://www.jcrelations.net/en/?item=1014 National Jewish Scholars Project - the text of Dabru Emet]
*[http://www.icjs.org/what/njsp/signers.html Signers of Dabru Emet]
* Hebrew translation: [http://www.catholic.co.il/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=420%3Adabru-emet-a-jewish-statement-on-christians-and-christianity&amp;catid=10%3Adocuments&amp;Itemid=16&amp;lang=he; http://yehoyada-amir.blogspot.com/]

==See also==
*[[Christianity]]
*[[Christian-Jewish reconciliation]]
*[[Judaism]]
*[[Relations between Catholicism and Judaism]]
*[[Religious Pluralism]]
*[[Tikva Frymer-Kensky]]

[[Category:Christian and Jewish interfaith topics]]
[[Category:Hebrew words and phrases]]

[[fr:Dabru Emet]]</text>
      <sha1>kemjqv23xy3ixe4u0ozym5l7c13iamk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
