<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Demonology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>174601</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521806195</id>
      <parentid>521216474</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T10:40:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Freediving-beava</username>
        <id>12829807</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed irrelevant link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27424">{{Other uses}}
{{paranormal}}
'''Demonology''' is the systematic study of [[demon]]s or beliefs about demons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/demonology &quot;Demonology&quot;] at Dictionary.com Unabridged, (v 1.1) Random House, Inc.. Retrieved January 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; It is the branch of [[theology]] relating to [[Supernatural|superhuman]] beings who are not [[Deity|god]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;hist&quot;&gt;[http://www.history.com/encyclopedia.do?articleId=207375 &quot;Demon&quot;] from Funk &amp; Wagnalls ''New Encyclopedia'', © 2006 World Almanac Education Group, retrieved from [http://www.history.com/ history.com]&lt;/ref&gt; It deals both with benevolent beings that have no circle of worshippers or so limited a circle as to be below the rank of gods, and with malevolent beings of all kinds. The original sense of &quot;demon&quot;, from the time of [[Homer]] onward, was a benevolent being,&lt;ref name=&quot;DDD&quot;&gt;van der Toorn, Becking, van der Horst (1999), ''Dictionary of Deities and Demons in The Bible'', Second Extensively Revised Edition, Entry: '''Demon''', pp. 235-240, William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, ISBN 0-8028-2491-9&lt;/ref&gt; but in English the name now holds connotations of malevolence. (In order to keep the distinction, when referring to the word in its original Greek meaning English uses the spelling &quot;[[Daemon]]&quot; or &quot;Daimon&quot;.)

Demons, when regarded as [[spirit]]s, may belong to either of the classes of spirits recognized by primitive [[animism]];&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01526a.htm Animism] at [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/index.html The Catholic Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt; that is to say, they may be human, or non-human, separable souls, or discarnate spirits which have never inhabited a body.  A sharp distinction is often drawn between these two classes, notably by the [[Melanesians]], several African groups, and others; the Arab [[jinn]], for example, are not reducible to modified human souls; at the same time these classes are frequently conceived as producing identical results, e.g. diseases.&lt;ref name=&quot;hist&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DDD&quot; /&gt;

The word ''[[wiktionary:demonology|demonology]]'' is from [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] {{lang|grc|[[wiktionary:δαίμων|δαίμων]]}}, ''daimōn'', &quot;divinity, divine power, god&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Autenrieth, A Homeric Lexicon&lt;/ref&gt; and {{lang|grc|[[wiktionary:-λογία|-λογία]]}}, ''[[wiktionary:-logia|-logia]]''.

== Prevalence of demons ==
[[File:Nachtmahr (Abildgaard).jpg|thumb|right|250px|&quot;[[The Nightmare|Nightmare]]&quot;, 1800, by [[Nikolaj Abraham Abildgaard]]]]
According to some societies, all the affairs of life are supposed to be under the control of spirits, each ruling a certain &quot;[[Classical element|element]]&quot; or even object, and themselves in subjection to a greater spirit.&lt;ref&gt;Ludwig, Theodore M., ''The Sacred Paths: Understanding the Religions of the World'', Second Edition, pp. 48-51, © 1989 Prentice-Hall, Inc., ISBN 0-02-372175-8&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the [[Inuit]] are said to believe in spirits of the sea, earth and sky, the winds, the clouds and everything in nature. Every cove of the seashore, every point, every island and prominent rock has its guardian spirit. All are potentially of the malignant type, to be propitiated by an appeal to knowledge of the supernatural.&lt;ref&gt;Rink, Henry (1875), [http://www.sacred-texts.com/nam/inu/tte/tte1-4.htm &quot;Chapter IV: Religion&quot;] of ''Tales and Traditions of the Eskimo'', London, 1875, at [http://www.sacred-texts.com/index.htm sacred-texts.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  Traditional [[Korea]]n belief posits that countless demons inhabit the natural world; they fill household objects and are present in all locations.  By the thousands they accompany travelers, seeking them out from their places in the elements.&lt;ref name=&quot;E1911&quot;&gt;[http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/DEM_DIO/DEMONOLOGY_L1alwv_demon_genius_.html Demonology] at the Online Encyclopedia, Originally appearing in Volume V08, Page 10 of the ''1911 Encyclopædia Britannica''&lt;/ref&gt;

In ancient [[Babylon]], demonology had an influence on even the most mundane elements of life, from petty annoyances to the emotions of love and hatred.  The numerous demonic spirits were given charge over various parts of the human body, one for the head, one for the neck, and so on.

Greek philosophers such as [[Porphyry (philosopher)|Porphyry]], who claimed influence from [[Platonic realism|Platonism]],&lt;ref&gt;Cumont, Franz (1911), [http://www.sacred-texts.com/cla/orrp/orrp19.htm ''The Oriental Religions in Roman Paganism''], Chapter VI: Persia, p. 267 at [http://www.sacred-texts.com sacred-texts.com]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Church Fathers|fathers of the Christian Church]], held that the world was pervaded with spirits,&lt;ref name=&quot;E1911&quot; /&gt; the latter of whom advanced the belief that demons received the worship directed at pagan gods.&lt;ref&gt;Augustine, [http://ccel.org/fathers/NPNF1-02/c1.8.htm ''The City of God''], Book 8, Chapter 24, at the [http://ccel.org/ Christian Classics Etherial Library]&lt;/ref&gt;

Many religions and cultures believe, or once believed, that what is now known as [[sleep paralysis]], was a form of physical contact with demons.

==Character of the spiritual world==
The ascription of malevolence to the world of spirits is by no means universal. In [[Central Africa]], the [[Mpongwe]] believe in local spirits, just as do the Inuit; but they are regarded as inoffensive in the main.  Passers-by must make some trifling offering as they near the spirits' place of abode; but it is only occasionally that mischievous acts, such as the throwing down of a tree on a passer-by, are, in the view of the natives, perpetuated by the class of spirits known as ''Ombuiri''.&lt;ref&gt;Hamill Nassau, Robert (Rev.) M.D., S.T.D., (1904), [http://www.sacred-texts.com/afr/fiwa/fiwa07.htm ''Fetichism in West Africa''], Chapter V: Spiritual Beings in Africa - Their Classes and Functions, Charles Scribners Son&lt;/ref&gt; So too, many of the spirits especially concerned with the operations of nature are conceived as neutral or even benevolent; the European peasant fears the [[Vegetation deity|corn-spirit]] only when he irritates him by trenching on his domain and taking his property by cutting the corn;&lt;ref&gt;Frazer, Sir James George (1922), [http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/f/frazer/james/golden/chapter46.html ''The Golden Bough: A Study of Magic and Religion''], Chapter 46, &quot;The Corn-Mother in Many Lands,&quot; at [http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/ The University of Adelaide Library]&lt;/ref&gt; similarly, there is no reason why the more insignificant personages of the [[pantheon (gods)|pantheon]] should be conceived as malevolent, and we find that the Petara of the [[Dayak people|Dyaks]] are far from indiscriminating and malignant, being viewed as invisible guardians of mankind.&lt;ref&gt;Greem, Eda (c. 1909), [http://anglicanhistory.org/asia/sarawak/green/04.html ''Borneo: The Land of River and Palm''] at the [http://anglicanhistory.org/ Project Canterbury] website&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==
{{See also|Classification of demons}}
Under the heading of demons are classified only such spirits as are believed to enter into relations with the human race; the term therefore includes:
# angels in the [[Judeo-Christian]] tradition that fell from grace,&lt;ref name=&quot;DDD&quot; /&gt;
# human [[Soul (spirit)|soul]]s regarded as [[genii]] or [[Familiar spirit|familiars]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/demon Demon], entry in the  ''Online Etymology Dictionary'', © 2001 Douglas Harper, hosted at [http://dictionary.reference.com dictionary.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
# such as receive a cult (e.g., [[ancestor worship]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;DDD&quot; /&gt;
# [[ghost]]s or other malevolent [[revenant (folklore)|revenants]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/ghost Ghost], entry in ''The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language'', Fourth Edition, Copyright © 2000, Houghton Mifflin Company, hosted at [http://dictionary.reference.com dictionary.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

Excluded are souls conceived as inhabiting another world. Yet just as gods are not necessarily spiritual, demons may also be regarded as corporeal; [[vampire]]s for example are sometimes described as human heads with appended entrails, which issue from the tomb to attack the living during the night watches. The so-called Spectre Huntsman of the Malay Peninsula is said to be a man who scours the firmament with his dogs, vainly seeking for what he could not find on Earth -a buck mouse-deer pregnant with male offspring; but he seems to be a living man; there is no statement that he ever died, nor yet that he is a spirit. The [[Incubus (demon)|incubi]] and [[succubus|Succubi]] of the [[Middle Ages]] are sometimes regarded as spiritual beings; but they were held to give proof of their bodily existence, such as offspring (though often deformed).&lt;ref&gt;Masello, Robert, ''Fallen Angels and Spirits of The Dark'', pp. 64-68, © 2004, The Berkley Publishing Group, 200 Madison Ave. New York, NY 10016, ISBN 0-399-51889-4&lt;/ref&gt; Belief in demons goes back many millennia. The [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrian]] faith teaches that there are 3,333 Demons, some with specific dark  responsibilities such as war, starvation, sickness, etc.

===Ancient Near East===
{{main|Mesopotamian demon}}
{{see|Asag| Pazuzu}}
In [[Babylonian mythology]], the seven evil deities were known as ''[[shedu]]'', or &quot;storm-demons&quot;. They were represented in [[Bull (mythology)|winged bull form]], derived from the colossal bulls used as protective genii of royal palaces, the name &quot;shed&quot; assumed also the meaning of a propitious genius in [[Babylon]]ian magic literature.&lt;ref&gt;See Delitzsch, ''Assyrisches Handwörterbuch''. pp. 60, 253, 261, 646; Jensen, ''Assyr.-Babyl. Mythen und Epen'', 1900, p. 453; [[Archibald Sayce]], l.c. pp. 441, 450, 463; [[François Lenormant|Lenormant]], l.c. pp. 48-51.&lt;/ref&gt; It was from Chaldea that the name &quot;shedu&quot; came to the Israelites, and so the  writers of the Tanach applied the word [[Shedim]]  to certain Canaanite deities. They also spoke of &quot;the destroyer&quot; (Exodus xii. 23) as a Lord who will &quot;strike down the Egyptians.&quot; In II Samuel xxiv; 16 and II Chronicles xxi. 15 the pestilence-dealing angel, that is spirit, called  &quot;the destroying angel&quot; (compare &quot;the angel of the Lord&quot; in II Kings xix. 35; Isaiah xxxvii. 36).

===Judaism===
{{main|Jewish demonology}}
Some scholars suggest that the origins of early Jewish demonology can be traced to two distinctive and often competing mythologies of evil — Adamic and Enochic, one of which was tied to the mishap of Adam and Eve in the Garden of Eden and the other to the fall of angels in the [[antediluvian]] period.&lt;ref&gt;A. Orlov, Dark Mirrors: Azazel and Satanael in Early Jewish Demonology (Albany, SUNY, 2011) 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, Adamic story traces the source of evil to Satan’s transgression and the [[Fall of Man|fall of Adam and Eve]] in Eden, a trend reflected in the Books of Adam and Eve that explains the reason for Satan’s demotion by his refusal to obey God’s command to venerate newly created Adam. In contrast, the early Enochic tradition bases its understanding of the origin of demons on the story of the fallen Watchers led by Azazel. Scholars believe that these two enigmatic figures - Azazel and Satan exercised formative influence on early Jewish demonology. While in the beginning of their conceptual journeys Azazel and Satan are posited as representatives of two distinctive and often rival trends tied to the distinctive etiologies of corruption, in later Jewish and Christian demonological lore both antagonists are able to enter each other’s respective stories in new conceptual capacities. In these later traditions Satanael is often depicted as the leader of the fallen angels while his conceptual rival Azazel is portrayed as a seducer of Adam and Eve.&lt;ref&gt;A. Orlov, Dark Mirrors: Azazel and Satanael in Early Jewish Demonology (Albany, SUNY, 2011) 7.&lt;/ref&gt; While historical [[Judaism]] never &quot;officially&quot; recognized a rigid set of doctrines about demons,&lt;ref&gt;Mack, Carol K., Mack, Dinah (1998), ''A Field Guide to Demons, Fairies, Fallen Angels and Other Subversive Spirits'', p. XXXIII, New York: Henry Holt and Co., ISBN 0-8050-6270-X&lt;/ref&gt; many scholars believe that its [[Babylonian captivity|post-exilic]] concepts of [[eschatology]], angelology, and demonology were influenced by [[Zoroastrianism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://net.bible.org/dictionary.php?word=Zoroastrianism '''Zoroastrianism'''] at [http://net.bible.org/home.php net.bible.org]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jahanian, Daryoush, M.D., [http://www.meta-religion.com/World_Religions/Zoroastrim/zoroastrian-biblical_connections.htm &quot;The Zoroastrian-Biblical Connections,&quot;] at [http://www.meta-religion.com/ meta-religion.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Some, however, believe that these concepts were received as part of the [[Kabbalah|Kabbalistic]] tradition&lt;ref&gt;Franck, Adolphe (1843), translated by Sossnitz, I. (1926), [http://www.sacred-texts.com/jud/rph/rph16.htm ''The Kabbalah'', or, ''The Religious Philosophy of the Hebrews''], Part Two, Chapter IV, &quot;Continuation of The Analysis of The Zohar: The Kabbalists' View of The World,&quot; p. 184 at [http://www.sacred-texts.com sacred-texts.com]&lt;/ref&gt; passed down from [[Adam (Bible)|Adam]], [[Noah]], and the Hebrew patriarchs.&lt;ref&gt;Mathers, S.L. McGregor (Translation from Latin - 1912), [http://www.sacred-texts.com/jud/tku/tku03.htm ''Kabbala Denudata: The Kabbala Unveiled''], Introduction, at [http://www.sacred-texts.com sacred-texts.com]&lt;/ref&gt; See [[Sefer Yetzirah]].

The [[Talmud]] declares that there are 7,405,926 demons, divided in 72 companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/heav_hel1.htm |title=The Afterlife: Ancient Christian Beliefs |publisher=Religioustolerance.org |date= |accessdate=2010-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- This needs a tractate/page number, and maybe a short quote, not an unreferenced claim on a website. Could also be a serious scholarly work on the topic. --&gt; While many people believe today that ''[[Lucifer]]'' and ''Satan'' are different names for the same being, not all scholars subscribe to this view.&lt;ref&gt;Davidson, Gustav (1967), ''A Dictionary of Angels, Including The Fallen Angels'', p. 176, Library of Congress Catalog Card Number: 66-19757&lt;/ref&gt; Use of the name &quot;Lucifer&quot; for the devil stems from a particular interpretation of {{bibleverse||Isaiah|14:3–20|NIV}}, a passage that does not speak of any fallen angel but of the defeat of a particular [[Babylon]]ian King, to whom it gives a title that refers to what in English is called the Day Star or Morning Star (in Latin, lucifer, meaning &quot;light-bearer&quot;, from the words lucem ferre). In {{bibleverse|2|Peter|1:19}} and elsewhere, the same Latin word lucifer is used to refer to the Morning Star, with no relation to the devil. It is only in post-[[Apostolic Age|New Testament times]] that the Latin word Lucifer was used as a name for the devil, both in religious writing and in fiction, especially when referring to him prior to his fall from Heaven.

There is more than one instance where demons are said to have come to be, as seen by the sins of the Watchers and the [[Grigori]], of [[Lilith]] leaving [[Adam and Eve|Adam]], of demons such as [[vampire]]s, impure spirits in [[Jewish mythology|Jewish folklore]] such as the [[dybbuk]], and of wicked humans that have become demons as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=245&amp;letter=D&amp;search=demonology Demonology] at [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/ jewishencyclopedia.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;wars&quot;&gt;Josephus, Flavius, [http://www.earlyjewishwritings.com/josephus.html ''Wars of The Jews''], Book VII, Chapter VI, Par. 3, at [http://www.earlyjewishwritings.com Early Jewish Writings]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
{{Main|Christian demonology}}
Christian demonology is the study of [[demon]]s from a [[Christianity|Christian]] point of view. It is primarily based on the [[Bible]] ([[Old Testament]] and [[New Testament]]), the [[exegesis]] of these scriptures, the scriptures of early Christian [[philosopher]]s and [[hermit]]s, [[tradition]], and [[legend]]s incorporated from other beliefs.

A number of authors throughout Christian history have written about demons for a variety of purposes.  Theologians like [[Thomas Aquinas]] wrote concerning the behaviors Christians should be aware of,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/summa/1114.htm Thomas Acquinas's Summa Theologica], Question 114, hosted on [[New Advent]]&lt;/ref&gt; while witchhunters like [[Heinrich Kramer]] wrote about how to find and what to do with [[Witch trials in Early Modern Europe|people they believed were involved with demons]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/pag/mm/index.htm Malleus Maleficarum], hosted on the Internet Sacred Text Archive&lt;/ref&gt;  Some texts are written with [[grimoire|instructions on how to summon demons]] in the name of God and often were claimed to have been written by individuals respected within the Church, such as the [[Lesser Key of Solomon]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/grim/lks/lks17.htm Lesser Key of Solomon, The Conjuration To Call Forth Any of the Aforesaid Spirits], hosted on [[Internet Sacred Text Archive]]&lt;/ref&gt; or [[The Grimoire of Pope Honorius]] (although these the earliest manuscripts were from well after these individuals had died).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/grim/bcm/bcm14.htm Arthur Edward Waite, Book of Ceremonial Magic, page 64] [http://www.sacred-texts.com/grim/bcm/bcm23.htm#page_106 and page 106]&lt;/ref&gt;  These latter texts were usually more detailed, giving names, ranks, and descriptions of demons individually and categorically.&lt;ref name=sacred&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sacred-texts.com/grim/bcm/bcm14.htm |title=Waite, page 64 |publisher=Sacred-texts.com |date= |accessdate=2010-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Most Christians commonly reject these texts as either diabolical or fictitious.&lt;ref name=sacred/&gt;

In modern times, some demonological texts have been written by Christians, usually in a similar vein of Thomas Aquinas, explaining their effects in the world and how faith may lessen or eliminate damage by them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=SFmrx7s7OtIC&amp;dq=Jessie+Penn-Lewis+war+on+the+saints&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=TCR4AVdC-L&amp;sig=N8TVdhBcTt1ev3YCFR-DvOwm9NY&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=QbnsSvbRCMqztgeM9fA6&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CBwQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Jessie Penn-Lewis, War on the Saints on Google Books], introductory chapter&lt;/ref&gt;  A few Christian authors, such as [[Jack Chick]] and [[John Todd]], write with intentions similar to Kramer, proclaiming that demons and their human agents are active in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;broken&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chick.com/catalog/comics/0102.asp |title=The Broken Cross - by Jack T. Chick |publisher=Chick.com |date= |accessdate=2009-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  These claims can stray from mainstream ideology, and may include such beliefs as that [[Christian rock]] is a means through which demons influence people.

Not all Christians believe that demons exist in the literal sense. There is the view that the language of exorcism in the New Testament is an example of what was once employed to describe the healings of what would be classified in modern days as epilepsy, mental illness etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.realdevil.info/4-1.htm |title=The Devil, Satan And Demons |publisher=Realdevil.info |date= |accessdate=2010-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===
{{main|Demons in Islam}}
In [[Islam]], the devil [[Iblis]] or [[Shaytan]] was a [[Genie|Jinn]]&lt;ref&gt;Qur'an 18:50 And when We said to the angels, Bow yourselves to Adam'; so they bowed themselves, save Iblis; he was one of the jinn, and committed ungodliness against his Lord's command&lt;/ref&gt; (humans are created from Earth, Angels from light, and jinn from 'smokeless fire'). The jinn, though, are not necessarily evil; they could be good-doers or sinners just like humans. Since the jinn and humans are the only kinds of creation who have the will to choose, the followers of Iblis could be jinn or human. The angels, on the other hand, are sinless and only obey the will of God.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.understanding-islam.com/related/text.asp?type=question&amp;qid=291 &quot;Who is Satan?&quot;] at understanding-islam.com&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Qur'an]], when God Ordered those witnessing the creation of Adam to prostrate before him (Adam), Iblis refused to do so and was therefore damned for refusal to obey God's Will.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/isl/quran/03805.htm ''The Qur'an'' (Yusuf Ali, tr.): Sūra 38: Sād: Section 5 (65-88)] at sacred-texts.com&lt;/ref&gt;

===Buddhism===
Traditionally, [[Buddhism]] affirms the existence of [[Hell#Buddhism|hells]]&lt;ref&gt;Boeree, Dr. C. George (2000), [http://webspace.ship.edu/cgboer/buddhacosmo.html Chapter: &quot;Buddhist Cosmology&quot;], ''An Introduction to Buddhism'', Shippensburg University&lt;/ref&gt; peopled by demons who torment sinners and tempt mortals to sin, or who seek to thwart their [[Bodhi|enlightenment]], with a demon named [[Mara (demon)|Mara]] as chief tempter, &quot;prince of darkness,&quot; or &quot;Evil One&quot; in Sanskrit sources.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kadampa.org/en/reference/glossary-of-buddhist-terms-a-e#Demon &quot;Demon&quot;] and [http://kadampa.org/en/reference/glossary-of-buddhist-terms-k-o#Mara &quot;Mara&quot;] in the ''Glossary of Buddhist Terms'' at [http://www.kadampa.org/ kadampa.org]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;strickman&quot;&gt;Strickmann, Michel. ''Chinese Magical Medicine'',(2002) Stanford: Stanford University Press. ISBN 0-8047-3449-6&lt;/ref&gt;

The followers of Mara were also called ''mara'', the devils, and are frequently cited as a cause of disease or representations of mental obstructions.&lt;ref name=&quot;strickman&quot;/&gt;
The ''mara'' became fully assimilated into the Chinese worldview, and were called ''mo''.

The idea of the imminent decline and collapse of the Buddhist religion amid a &quot;great cacophony of demonic influences&quot; was already a significant component of Buddhism when it reached China in the first century CE, according to Michel Strickmann.&lt;ref name=&quot;strickman&quot;/&gt; Demonic forces had attained enormous power in the world. For some writers of the time this state of affairs had been ordained to serve the higher purpose of effecting a &quot;preliminary cleansing&quot; that would purge and purify humanity in preparation for an ultimate, messianic renewal.&lt;ref name=&quot;strickman&quot;/&gt;

Medieval Chinese Buddhist demonology was heavily influenced by Indian Buddhism. Indian demonology is also fully and systematically described in written sources, though during Buddhism's millennium of direct influence in China, &quot;Chinese demonology was whipped into respectable shape,&quot; with a number of Indian demons finding permanent niches even in [[Taoist]] ritual texts.&lt;ref name=&quot;strickman&quot;/&gt;

===Hinduism===
{{see|Hindu demon}}
Hindu mythology include a range of spirits (Vetalas, Yakshas, Bhutas and Pishachas) that might be classified as demons. These spirits are souls of beings that have committed certain specific sins. As a purging punishment, they are condemned to roam without a physical form for a length of time, until a rebirth. Beings that died with unfulfilled desires or anger are also said to &quot;linger&quot; until such issues are resolved. Hindu text [[Atharvaveda]] gives an account of nature and habitats of such spirits including how to persuade/control them. There are occult traditions in Hinduism that seeks to control such spirits to do their bidding. Hindu text [[Garuda Purana]] details other kinds of punishments and judgments given out in [[Hell]]; this also given an account of how the spirit travels to nether world.

===Occult===
Practitioners of [[ceremonial magic]] sometimes attempt to constrain and command [[demon]]s to do their bidding, using methods such as the [[Goetia]] and [[The Book of Abramelin]].  The demons are often those mentioned in Christian  demonology.  These practitioners do not necessarily worship demons, but seek to deploy them to obtain their goals. Other followers of the occult do worship demons, and some refer to their religion as &quot;demonolatry.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ofs-demonolatry.org |title=OFS Demonolatry |publisher=OFS Demonolatry |date= |accessdate=2010-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Demonolators consider methods such as the [[Goetia]] very disrespectful towards the demons, and possibly dangerous for the operator.  They instead use forms of [[prayer]], [[magic (paranormal)|magic]], and [[ritual]] which petition the demons, asking for their aid rather than commanding them.

Demonolators are not identical to practitioners of [[Theistic Satanism]].  They worship other demons (such as [[Belial]] and [[Leviathan]]) either alongside, or instead of Satan. Some demonolators say that their form of demonolatry is a tradition, often familial, that is not related to the modern religious and philosophical movements collectively referred to as Satanism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ofs-demonolatry.org/faq.htm#prove |title=OFS Demonolatry |publisher=OFS Demonolatry |date= |accessdate=2010-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Not all of the occultists who worship demons use the word &quot;demonolator&quot; to describe themselves, nor do all belong to the specific group mentioned above.

===Zoroastrianism===
In the [[Zoroastrian]] tradition, [[Ahura Mazda]], as the force of good [[Amesha Spenta|Spenta Mainyu]], will eventually be victorious in a cosmic battle with an evil force known as [[Angra Mainyu]] or Ahriman.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tenets.zoroastrianism.com/zor33.html &quot;Who are the Zoroastrians,&quot;] at [http://tenets.zoroastrianism.com/ tenets.zoroastrianism.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Satanism===
{{Expand section|date=December 2009}}
{{main|Satanism|Theistic Satanism|LaVeyan Satanism}}
[[Satanism]] is a name for a diverse group of religions which regard demons in general and [[Satan]] in particular as positive entities, either as real entities to be worshipped (Theistic Satanism), or using Satan and other demons as symbols (LaVeyan Satanism). Some of them borrow concepts of the nature of demons from established religions such as [[Christianity]], [[Judaism]] or [[Islam]] while reversing these religions' negative value judgement in the matter, while others elaborate original concepts of their own about demons' character and abilities.

==See also==
* [[Conjuration]]
* [[Deal with the Devil]]
* [[Demon]]
* [[Exorcism]]
* [[List of theological demons]]
* [[Pentagram]]
* [[Nicolas Remy]]
* [[Spirit world (spiritualism)|Spirit world]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==
* {{cite book|last=Rémy|first=Nicholas|title=Demonolatry|publisher=University Books|year=1974}}
{{1911}}

==External links==
* [http://www.religiousdemonology.com ''Religious Demonology'':] Demonology from a Roman Catholic perspective, written by a member of the International Association of Exorcists.
* [http://www.sacred-texts.com/pag/kjd/kjd04.htm ''Demonology by James I'':] plain text version of King James' important work on Demonology.
[[Category:Demonology]]
[[Category:Left-Hand Path]]
[[Category:Mythography]]
[[Category:Witchcraft]]

[[ar:علم الشياطين]]
[[bg:Демонология]]
[[ca:Demonologia]]
[[cs:Démonologie]]
[[de:Dämonologie]]
[[et:Demonoloogia]]
[[es:Demonología]]
[[fr:Démonologie]]
[[hr:Demonologija]]
[[id:Demonologi]]
[[it:Demonologia]]
[[ka:დემონოლოგია]]
[[la:Daemonologia]]
[[nl:Demonologie]]
[[ja:悪魔学]]
[[no:Demonologi]]
[[pl:Demonologia]]
[[pt:Demonologia]]
[[ro:Demonologie]]
[[ru:Демонология]]
[[simple:Demonology]]
[[sr:Демонологија]]
[[fi:Demonologia]]
[[sv:Demonologi]]
[[tr:Demonoloji]]
[[uk:Демонологія]]
[[zh:魔鬼学]]</text>
      <sha1>s0ljacamsd0mw1qnc6bxu04mfy86ue8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
