<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>East–West Schism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>543935</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522455040</id>
      <parentid>522454924</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T09:36:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Esoglou</username>
        <id>11289927</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Growth in power of the see of Constantinople */ ref name</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="194658">{{Christianity}}
{{POV|date=October 2012}}
The '''East–West Schism''', sometimes known as the '''Great Schism''',&lt;ref&gt;The term &quot;Great Schism&quot; is sometimes also applied to the [[Western Schism]]. See &quot;Great Schism&quot;, ''Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church'', Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3.&lt;/ref&gt; is the medieval division of [[Chalcedonian Christianity]] into [[Greek East and Latin West|Eastern (Greek) and Western (Latin) branches]], which later became known as the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] and the [[Roman Catholic Church]], respectively. Relations between East and West had long been embittered by political and [[Roman Catholic-Eastern Orthodox ecclesiastical differences|ecclesiastical differences]] and [[Roman Catholic–Eastern Orthodox theological differences|theological disputes]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|editor=Cross, F. L., ed. |title=The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2005 |isbn=0-19-280290-9}}. See M. G. D'Agostino, Il Primato della Sede di Roma in Leone IX (1049–1054). Studio dei testi latini nella controversia greco-romana nel periodo pregregoriano, Edizioni San Paolo, Cinisello Balsamo 2008. See A. Bayer, Spaltung der Christenheit. Das sogennante Morgenlaendische Schisma von 1054, Koeln-Weimar-Wien 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent among these were the issues of &quot;[[filioque]]&quot;, whether leavened or [[unleavened bread]] should be used in the [[Eucharist]],&lt;ref&gt;A late 11th century pamphlet 'Against the Franks' [http://loki.stockton.edu/~papadema/Syndey_Palatianos.pdf] falsely attributed to [[Photios I of Constantinople|Photios]] lists this as second point, right after the filioque. J. Hergenröther, Monumenta Graeca ad Photium eiusque historiam pertinentiam, Regensburg 1869, pp. 62–71. Hans-Georg Beck, Byzantinisches Lesebuch, München 1982, pp. 245–247.&lt;/ref&gt; the Pope's claim to [[universal jurisdiction]], and the place of [[Constantinople]] in relation to the [[Pentarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;Martin Lembke, lecture in the course &quot;Meetings with the World's Religions&quot;, Centre for Theology and Religious Studies, Lund University, Spring Term 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pope Leo IX]] and [[Patriarch of Constantinople]] [[Michael Cerularius]] heightened the conflict by suppressing Greek and Latin in their respective domains. In 1054, [[Papal legate|Roman legates]] traveled to Cerularius to deny him the title [[Ecumenical Patriarch]] and to insist that he recognize the Church of Rome's claim to be the head and mother of the churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross&quot;/&gt; Cerularius refused. The leader  of the Latin contingent, [[Cardinal Humbert]], [[Excommunication|excommunicated]] Cerularius, while Cerularius in return excommunicated Cardinal Humbert and other legates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross&quot;/&gt; This was only the first act in a centuries-long process that eventually became a complete schism.&lt;ref&gt;Runciman 1955&lt;/ref&gt;

The validity of the Western legates' act is doubtful, since Pope Leo had died, while Cerularius's excommunication applied only to the legates personally.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross&quot;/&gt; Still, the Church split along [[doctrine|doctrinal]], [[theology|theological]], [[linguistics|linguistic]], [[politics|political]], and [[geography|geographical]] lines, and the fundamental breach has never been healed, with each side accusing the other of having fallen into [[heresy]] and of having initiated the division. The [[Crusades]], the [[Massacre of the Latins]] in 1182, the capture and [[sack of Constantinople]] in 1204, and the imposition of the [[Latin Patriarch of Jerusalem]] and the [[Latin Patriarch of Constantinople|Latin Patriarch]]s made reconciliation more difficult.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross&quot;/&gt; This included the taking of many precious religious artifacts and the destruction of the [[Library of Constantinople]].

Efforts were made to reunite the two churches in 1274 (by the [[Second Council of Lyon]]) and in 1439 (by the [[Council of Florence]]). Despite acceptance by the participating eastern delegations, no effective reconciliation was realized, since the Orthodox believe that the acts of councils must be ratified by the wider Church and the acts of these councils never attained widespread acceptance among Orthodox churches. In 1484, 31 years after the [[Fall of Constantinople]] to the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman Turks]], a Synod of Constantinople repudiated the Union of Florence, making official the position that had already been taken by Orthodox in general.

In 1965, the [[Paul VI|Pope Paul VI]] and the [[Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople]] [[Athenagoras I]] nullified the anathemas of 1054,&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross&quot;/&gt; although this nullification of measures taken against a few individuals was essentially a goodwill gesture and did not constitute any sort of reunion between churches.&lt;ref&gt;The absence of full communion between the churches is mentioned explicitly even in the permission that [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P2S.HTM canon 844 §3 of the Code of Canon Law] accords for the administering by Catholic ministers of the sacraments of penance, the Eucharist and anointing of the sick to spontaneously requesting members of eastern churches such as the Eastern Orthodox Church (as also the [[Oriental Orthodox]] churches and the [[Church of the East]]) and of western churches such as the Old Catholic Church.&lt;/ref&gt; Contacts between the two sides continue: Every year a delegation from each joins in the other's celebration of its patronal feast, [[Feast of Saints Peter and Paul|Saints Peter and Paul]] (29 June) for Rome and [[Feast of Saint Andrew|Saint Andrew]] (30 November) for Constantinople, and there have been a number of visits by the head of each to the other. The efforts of the Ecumenical Patriarchs towards reconciliation with the Catholic Church have often been the target of sharp criticism from some fellow Orthodox.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |publisher=Society of Saint John Chrysostom |year=2001 |journal=Eastern Churches journal |volume=8 |number=Issues 1–2 |page=149 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins and causes==

Eric Plumer writes that &quot;(t)he divergence of the Eastern and Western churches, leading ultimately to the East-West Schism, was a process of many centuries, influenced by a host of political, cultural and theological factors.&lt;ref name=&quot;GranfieldPhan2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Granfield|first1=Patrick|last2=Phan|first2=Peter C. |title=The Gift of the Church: A Textbook Ecclesiology in Honor of Patrick Granfield, O.S.B.|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2knW3bIxIYgC&amp;pg=PA37|accessdate=26 October 2012|date=1 November 2000|publisher=Liturgical Press|isbn=978-0-8146-5931-1|page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Similarly, Roger Haight asserts that, &quot;The [East-West Schism] should not be understood to have occurred in the mutual excommunications [of 1054]&quot;  because those excommunications were &quot;only one factor in a much longer and larger story involving cultural, political and theological factors.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Haight2004.p289&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Haight|first=Roger D. |title=Christian Community in History Volume 1: Historical Ecclesiology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=EDzSaqXK-aEC&amp;pg=PA289|accessdate=26 October 2012|date=16 September 2004|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-8264-1630-8|page=289}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Because so many factors contributed to the ever-widening separation between East and West, it is difficult to point to a specific date when it began or even identify a single primary cause of the schism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schadé2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Schadé|first=Johannes P. |title=Encyclopedia of World Religions|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=XRkfKdho-5cC&amp;pg=PT805|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=30 December 2006|publisher=Foreign Media Group|isbn=978-1-60136-000-7|page=805}}&lt;/ref&gt;  While most sources agree that the separation between East and West is clearly evident by the [[Photian schism]] in the ninth century, some point to tensions going back as far as the fourth century as the early signs of the separation between East and West.&lt;ref name=&quot;WozniukWozniuk2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Soloviev, |first1=V.S.|last2=Wozniuk|first2=Vladimir |title=Freedom, Faith, and Dogma: Essays by V. S. Soloviev on Christianity and Judaism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ftjKBRToMygC&amp;pg=PA14|accessdate=9 November 2012|date=1 July 2009|publisher=SUNY Press|isbn=978-0-7914-7536-2|page=14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Makrides2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Makrides|first=Vasilios N.|title=Hellenic Temples and Christian Churches: A Concise History of the Religious Cultures of Greece from Antiquity to the Present|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=kKOY5NsekfkC&amp;pg=PA68|accessdate=9 November 2012|date=1 September 2009|publisher=NYU Press|isbn=978-0-8147-9568-2|page=68}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

{{Main|History of the East–West Schism}}
{{See also|History of Christianity}}

The ecclesiological dimension of the East-West schism revolves around the authority of bishops within their dioceses and the lines of authority between bishops of different dioceses.  The organizational structure of bishops and dioceses is only one of the three major forms of ecclesiology employed by Christian churches but it is, at a first approximation, shared between the Catholic, Orthodox and Anglican churches.  However, although both East and West came to adopt the Ignatian tri-partite structure of bishops, elders and deacons, their definition of the authority of bishops evolved in different ways.  In particular, these churches differ sharply in their understanding of the authority of the Bishop of Rome.  As a consequence, the history of the schism is based substantially on the history of ecclesiological development in the Christian churches of the first millennium.

===Governance in the early Christian church===

Rodney Stark estimates that the number of Christians grew by approximately 40% a decade during the first and second centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stark1997&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Rodney |last=Stark |title=The Rise of Christianity|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=enTN1vi1YyIC|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=9 May 1997|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-067701-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This phenomenal growth rate forced Christian communities to evolve in order to adapt to their changes in the nature of their communities as well as their relationship with their political and socioeconomic environment. As the number of Christians grew, the Christian communities became larger, more numerous and farther apart geographically.  The passage of time also moved some Christians farther from the original teachings of the apostles giving rise to teachings that were considered heterodox and sowing controversy and divisiveness within churches and between churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haight2004.pp83-84&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Haight|first=Roger D. |title=Christian Community in History Volume 1: Historical Ecclesiology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=EDzSaqXK-aEC&amp;pg=PA83|accessdate=26 October 2012|date=16 September 2004|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-8264-1630-8|pages=83–84|quote=&quot;The churches were becoming ever more distant from their origins in space and time. They were growing and with growth came new or false teachings, the sources of controversy and division.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Robert Haight]]{{who|date=October 2012}} posits the development of ecclesiology in the form of &quot;Early Catholicism&quot; as one response to the problem of church unity.  Thus, the solution to division arising from heterodox teaching was the development of &quot;tighter and more standardized structures of ministry.  One of these structures is the tri-partite form of church leadership consisting of bishops, elders and deacons that Ignatius of Antioch urged churches to adopt, writing that &quot;You cannot have a church without these.&quot;  Over the course of the second century, this organizational structure became universal and continues to be used in the Catholic, Orthodox and Anglican churches as well as in some Protestant denominations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haight2004.pp83-84&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Haight|first=Roger D. |title=Christian Community in History Volume 1: Historical Ecclesiology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=EDzSaqXK-aEC&amp;pg=PA83|accessdate=26 October 2012|date=16 September 2004|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-8264-1630-8|pages=83–84}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite its mention of bishops, there is no clear evidence in the New Testament that supports the concepts of dioceses and monepiscopacy (i.e. the rule that all the churches in a geographic area should be ruled by a single bishop).  Scholars point to evidence that Christian communities such as Rome had many bishops and that the concept of monepiscopacy was still emerging when Ignatius was urging his tri-partite structure on other churches.&lt;ref&gt;Ronald Y.K. Fung as cited in {{cite book|author1=John Piper|author2=Wayne Grudem|title=Recovering Biblical Manhood and Womanhood: A Response to Evangelical Feminism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DECfuM4_YuoC&amp;pg=PA254|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=8 August 2006|publisher=Crossway|isbn=978-1-4335-1918-5|page=254}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Robert Williams posits that the &quot;origin and earliest development of episcopacy and monepiscopacy and the ecclesiastical concept of (apostolic) succession were associated with crisis situations in the early church.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Williams2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Williams|first=Robert Lee |title=Bishop Lists: Formation of Apostolic Succession of Bishops in Ecclesiastical Crises|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=LLW6qVX3DRoC&amp;pg=PA6|accessdate=28 October 2012|year=2005|publisher=Gorgias Press LLC|isbn=978-1-59333-194-8|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early assertions of the primacy of Rome===

The [[Primacy of the Bishop of Rome]] together with the [[Filioque|Filioque controversy]], remains one of the primary causes of the continuing schism between the Catholic and Orthodox churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kasper2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Kasper|first=Walter|title=The Petrine ministry: Catholics and Orthodox in dialogue : academic symposium held at the Pontifical Council for Promoting Christian Unity|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3mxbj99yRaQC&amp;pg=PA188|accessdate=22 December 2011|year=2006|publisher=Paulist Press|isbn=978-0-8091-4334-4|page=188|quote=The question of the primacy of the Roman pope has been and remains, together with the question of the Filioque, one of the main causes of separation between the Latin Church and the Orthodox churches and one of the principal obstacles to their union.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Underlying the issue of papal primacy is the interpretation of the role that bishops and patriarchs can legitimately exercise within their own realm of influence and what that realm of influence should be. &lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p154&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cleenewerck|first=Laurent |title=His Broken Body: Understanding and Healing the Schism Between the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA157|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=1 January 2008|publisher=Euclid University Press|isbn=978-0-615-18361-9|page=147-page157|quote=Ending with &quot;One could argue that the Great schism started with Victor, continued with Stephen and remained underground until the ninth century!&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Over the course of history, tensions have arisen when church leaders have been perceived to have overstepped their bounds. &lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p154&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cleenewerck|first=Laurent |title=His Broken Body: Understanding and Healing the Schism Between the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA157|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=1 January 2008|publisher=Euclid University Press|isbn=978-0-615-18361-9|page=147-page148|quote=Ending with &quot;One could argue that the Great schism started with Victor, continued with Stephen and remained underground until the ninth century!&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The church at Rome claimed a special authority over the other churches due, in part, to being the successors of the apostles Peter and Paul.  In the first three centuries, Rome gained increasing recognition as one of the centers of Christianity.  However, the extant documents of that era yield &quot;no clear-cut claims to, or recognition, of papal primacy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kling2005.p61&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Kling|first=David W. |title=The Bible in History:How the Texts Have Shaped the Times|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=61g19QTJk5UC&amp;pg=PA61|accessdate=31 October 2012|date=20 April 2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-988096-6|page=61|quote=Obviously, the church at Rome, given the dual presence of the apostles Peter and Paul, claimed a special authority. In the ﬁrst three centuries, church leaders and thinkers throughout the empire increasingly recognized Rome as a center of Christianity.  At the same time, the literary evidence yields no clear-cut claims to, or recognition of, papal primacy.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Catholic apologists have typically pointed to the 7th century controversy over the Filioque and the 9th century schism of [[Photios]] as the earliest signs of the growing schism,{{Citation needed|date=November 2012}} Orthodox apologists point to incidents as early as the 2nd century as examples of claims by Rome to papal primacy and rejection by Eastern Churches thereof.

An even 1st-century example occurred in the year 90, when a group of [[Ancient Corinth#Biblical Corinth|Corinthian]] clerics, who had been removed from their positions, petitioned the Bishop of Rome Pope Clement at the time for help.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p148&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cleenewerck|first=Laurent |title=His Broken Body: Understanding and Healing the Schism Between the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA155|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=1 January 2008|publisher=Euclid University Press|isbn=978-0-615-18361-9|page=148}}[http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA148#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

Towards the end of the 2nd century, [[Pope Victor I|Victor]], the Bishop of Rome, attempted to resolve the [Quartodecimanism|Quartodeciman controversy]] by excommunicating churches in the [[Roman province of Asia]].  This incident is cited by some Orthodox Christians as the first example of overreaching by the Bishop of Rome and resistance of such by Eastern churches. [[Laurent Cleenewerck]] suggests that this could be argued to be the first fissure between the Eastern and Western churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p155&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cleenewerck|first=Laurent |title=His Broken Body: Understanding and Healing the Schism Between the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA155|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=1 January 2008|publisher=Euclid University Press|isbn=978-0-615-18361-9|page=155|quote=One could argue that the Great schism started with Victor, continued with Stephen and remained underground until the ninth century!}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Quartodeciman controversy arose because Christians in the [[Roman province of Asia]] ([[Early centers of Christianity#Anatolia|Western Anatolia]]) celebrated [[Easter]] at the spring full moon, like the Jewish [[Passover]], while the churches in the rest of the world observed the practice of celebrating it on the following Sunday (&quot;the day of the resurrection of our Saviour&quot;)&lt;ref name=Eusebius23&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf201.iii.x.xxiv.html Eusebius, ''Church History'', chapter 23]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 155, [[Pope Anicetus|Anicetus]], Bishop of Rome presided over a church council at Rome that was attended by a number of bishops including [[Polycarp]], Bishop of Smyrna.  Although the council failed to reach agreement on the issue, ecclesiastical communion was preserved.&lt;ref name=OrthAns&gt;[http://www.orthodoxanswers.org/history Orthodox Answers: An Orthodox Christian Historical Timeline]&lt;/ref&gt; A generation later, synods of bishops in [[Syria Palaestina|Palestine]], [[Diocese of Pontus|Pontus]]([[Early centers of Christianity#Anatolia|Northern Anatolia]]) and [[Osrhoene]] in the east, and in Rome and [[Roman Gaul|Gaul]] in the west, unanimously declared that the celebration should be exclusively on Sunday.&lt;ref name=Eusebius23/&gt; In 193, [[Pope Victor I]] presided over a council in Rome and subsequently sent a letter about the matter to [[Polycrates of Ephesus]] and the churches of the Roman province of Asia.&lt;ref name=OrthAns/&gt; In the same year, Polycrates presided over a council at Ephesus attended by several bishops throughout that province, which rejected Victor's authority and kept the province's paschal tradition.&lt;ref name=OrthAns/&gt; Thereupon, Victor attempted to cut off Polycrates and the others who took this stance from the common unity, but later reversed his decision after bishops that included Saint [[Irenaeus]], [[Bishop of Lugdunum]] in Gaul, interceded, recommending that Victor adopt the more tolerant stance of his predecessor, Anicetus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf201.iii.x.xxv.html Eusebius, ''Church History'', chapter 24]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=[[Eusebius of Caesarea]] |title=Church History |volume=V |page=xxiv |quote=
&quot;But this did not please all the bishops. And they besought him to consider the things of peace, and of neighborly unity and love. Words of theirs are extant, sharply rebuking Victor. Among them was Irenæus, who, sending letters in the name of the brethren in Gaul over whom he presided, maintained that the mystery of the resurrection of the Lord should be observed only on the Lord’s day. He fittingly admonishes Victor that he should not cut off whole churches of God which observed the tradition of an ancient custom.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite Victor's failure to carry out his intent to excommunicate the Asian churches, many Catholic apologists point to this episode as evidence of papal primacy and authority in the early Church, citing the fact that none of the bishops challenged his right to excommunicate but rather questioned the wisdom and charity of doing so.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p155&quot;/&gt; Orthodox apologists argue that Victor had to relent in the end and note that the Eastern Churches never granted Victor presidency over anything other than the Church of Rome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p154&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cleenewerck|first=Laurent |title=His Broken Body: Understanding and Healing the Schism Between the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA157|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=1 January 2008|publisher=Euclid University Press|isbn=978-0-615-18361-9|page=1470-page157|quote=Ending with &quot;One could argue that the Great schism started with Victor, continued with Stephen and remained underground until the ninth century!&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Cleenewerck points out that Eusebius of [[Caesarea]] simply refers to Victor one of the &quot;rulers of the Churches&quot;, not the ruler of a yet unknown or unformed 'universal Church.'&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p155&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cleenewerck|first=Laurent |title=His Broken Body: Understanding and Healing the Schism Between the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA155|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=1 January 2008|publisher=Euclid University Press|isbn=978-0-615-18361-9|page=155}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ultimately, the Quartodeciman controversy not resolved by papal authority; it was only finally resolved by an ecumenical council, the [[First Council of Nicaea]]
.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p154&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cleenewerck|first=Laurent |title=His Broken Body: Understanding and Healing the Schism Between the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA157|accessdate=28 October 2012|date=1 January 2008|publisher=Euclid University Press|isbn=978-0-615-18361-9|page=147-page157|quote=Ending with &quot;One could argue that the Great schism started with Victor, continued with Stephen and remained underground until the ninth century!&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The rejection of Bishop [[Anicetus]]' position on the Quartodeciman, by Polycarp and later Polycrates' letter to Pope Victor I has been used by Orthodox theologians as proof against the argument that the Churches in Asia Minor accepted the [[Primacy of the Bishop of Rome]] and or the teaching of [[Papal supremacy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008.p154&quot;/&gt;

===Centers of Christianity===
John Binns{{who|date=October 2012}} specifically writes that, after the fall and destruction of Jerusalem by the Romans, the natural learning centers of the Church were [[Early centers of Christianity#Antioch|Antioch]] and [[Early centers of Christianity#Alexandria|Alexandria]]. Constantinople was not founded (that is, renamed from &quot;[[Byzantium]]&quot;) until after the [[First Council of Nicaea]] (325).

The historian [[Will Durant]] writes that, after [[Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem|Jerusalem]], the [[Early centers of Christianity#Rome|church of Rome]] naturally became the primary church, the capital of Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;&gt;[[Will Durant|Durant, Will]]. ''Caesar and Christ''. New York: Simon and Schuster. 1972&lt;/ref&gt; Rome had an early and significant Christian population.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;/&gt; It was closely identified with [[Paul the Apostle]], who preached&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Acts|28:17–31}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was [[martyr]]ed there, and the [[Saint Peter|Apostle Peter]], who was a martyr there as well; Peter was also considered chief among all the [[Apostles]] and the first [[Bishop of Rome]]. While the Eastern cities of Alexandria and Antioch produced theological works, the bishops of Rome focused on what Romans admittedly did best&amp;nbsp;— administration.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;/&gt;

In the early church, up until the ecumenical councils, Rome was regarded as an [[Early centers of Christianity|important center of Christianity]], especially since it was the capital of the Roman Empire. Bishops of churches in the eastern and southern Mediterranean generally recognized the persuasive leadership and authority of the Bishop of Rome.{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}} But these bishops did not acknowledge any juridical authority of Rome.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

In the [[Christianity in the 4th century|fourth century]], when the Roman emperors (reigning in Constantinople) were trying to control the Church, theological questions ran rampant throughout the Roman Empire.&lt;ref&gt;John Binns, ''An Introduction to the Christian Orthodox Churches'', Cambridge University Press, UK, 2002, pp 162–164&lt;/ref&gt; The influence of Greek speculative thought on Christian thinking led to all sorts of divergent and conflicting opinions.&lt;ref&gt;John Binns, ''An Introduction to the Christian Orthodox Churches'', Cambridge University Press, UK, 2002, p68&lt;/ref&gt; Theology was also used as a weapon against opponent bishops, because being branded a [[heresy|heretic]] was the only sure way for a bishop to be removed by other bishops—incompetence was not sufficient grounds for removal.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

===Growth in power of the see of Constantinople===
[[File:Ayasofya 2006-1.JPG|thumb||[[Hagia Sophia]], cathedral of Constantinople at the time of the schism]]

The bishop of [[Byzantium]] was under the authority of the [[metropolitan archbishop|metropolitan]] of [[Perinthus|Heraclea]] when in 330 [[Roman Emperor]] [[Constantine I]] moved his residence to this town, which, rebuilt on a larger scale, became known as [[Constantinople]]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fatheralexander.org/booklets/english/history_timothy_ware_1.htm Kallistos Ware, ''Orthodox Church'' ,  &quot;Byzantium: The Church of the Seven Councils&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter, the bishop's connection with the imperial court meant that he was able to free himself from ecclesiastical dependency on Heraclea and in little more than half a century to obtain recognition of next-after-Rome ranking from the first Council held within the walls of the new capital. The [[First Council of Constantinople]] (381), in which the Western bishops took no part and which the Latin Church recognized as ecumenical only in the mid-6th century, &lt;ref name=Idea/&gt; decreed: &quot;The Bishop of Constantinople, however, shall have the prerogative of honour after the Bishop of Rome; because Constantinople is New Rome&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.ix.viii.iv.html Canon 3]&lt;/ref&gt; thus raising it above the sees of Alexandria and Antioch.

Alexandria's objections to Constantinople's promotion, which led to a constant struggle between the two sees in the first half of the 5th century,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sankt-georgen.de/leseraum/schatz2-2.html Klaus Schatz: Primat und Reichskirchliche Strukturen im 5. – 9. Jahrhundert]&lt;/ref&gt; were supported by Rome, which proposed the theory that the most important sees were the three Petrine ones, with Rome in first place.&lt;ref name=Idea/&gt; However, after the [[Council of Chalcedon]] (451), the position of the Patriarchate of Alexandria was weakened by a division in which the great majority of its Christian population followed the form of Christianity that its opponents called [[Monophysitism]].&lt;ref name=Idea/&gt;

Emperor [[Theodosius I]], who called the Council of 381, divided the eastern Roman Empire into five &quot;dioceses&quot;: Egypt (under Alexandria), [[Diocese of the East|the East]] (under Antioch), [[Asia (Roman province)|Asia]] (under [[Ephesus]]), [[Pontus]] (under [[Caesarea Cappadociae]]), and [[Thrace]] (originally under [[Perinthus|Heraclea]], later under Constantinople);&lt;ref name=Idea&gt;[http://www.homolaicus.com/storia/medioevo/pentarchia/pentarchia.htm L'idea di pentarchia nella cristianità]&lt;/ref&gt; and the Council also decreed: &quot;The bishops are not to go beyond their dioceses to churches lying outside of their bounds, nor bring confusion on the churches; but let the Bishop of Alexandria, according to the canons, alone administer the affairs of Egypt; and let the bishops of the East manage the East alone, the privileges of the Church in Antioch, which are mentioned in the canons of [[First Council of Nicaea|Nice]], being preserved; and let the bishops of the Asian Diocese administer the Asian affairs only; and the Pontic bishops only Pontic matters; and the Thracian bishops only Thracian affairs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.ix.viii.iii.html Canon 2]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Council of Chalcedon]] (451), which marked a serious defeat of Alexandria, gave recognition, in a canon of disputed validity,&lt;ref name=Michalopulos&gt;&quot;According to the official ''acta'' of the council, twenty-seven canons were officially recognized. Sometime later, three additional canons were furtively inserted but one of these, Canon 28, was hastily removed on order from Pope Leo upon the recommendations of his legates, who coincidentally were not present when this particular canon was drafted. For several centuries thereafter, no more mention was made of Canon 28 and the following ones, 29 and 30 respectively, were viewed as commentary upon other canons and not as canons in and of themselves&quot; ([http://www.aoiusa.org/canon-28-and-eastern-papalism-cause-or-effect/ George C. Michalopulos, &quot;Canon 28 and Eastern Papalism: Cause or Effect?&quot;).]&lt;/ref&gt; to an extension of Constantinople's power over Pontus and Asia in addition to Thrace.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=XgRrh2M08p0C&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA95,M1 The Challenge of Our Past: Studies in Orthodox Canon Law and Church History, by John H. Erickson (St Vladimir's Seminary Press, 1991 ISBN 0-88141-086-1, ISBN 978-0-88141-086-0), p. 97]&lt;/ref&gt; The Council justified this decision on the grounds that &quot;the Fathers rightly granted privileges to the throne of old Rome, because it was the royal city&quot;, and that the First Council of Constantinople, &quot;actuated by the same consideration, gave equal privileges to the most holy throne of New Rome, justly judging that the city which is honoured with the Sovereignty and the Senate, and enjoys equal privileges with the old imperial Rome, should in ecclesiastical matters also be magnified as she is, and rank next after her&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xi.xviii.xxviii.html Canon 28]&lt;/ref&gt;  It thus attributed to the Council of 381 a grant to Constantinople of &quot;equal privileges&quot; to those enjoyed by &quot;Old Rome&quot;.

Although [[Pope Leo I]], whose delegates were absent when this resolution was passed, recognized the council as ecumenical and confirmed its doctrinal decrees, he rejected its canon 28 on the ground that it contravened the sixth canon of Nicaea and infringed the rights of Alexandria and Antioch.&lt;ref name=Idea/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Council_of_Chalcedon Encyclopædia Britannica 1911: ''Council of Chalcedon'']&lt;/ref&gt; However, by that time Constantinople, the permanent residence of the emperor, had in reality enormous influence, and had it not been for the opposition of Rome, its bishop could easily have been given first place among all the bishops.&lt;ref name=Idea/&gt;

In its disputed 28th canon, the Council also recognized an authority of Constantinople over bishops of dioceses &quot;among the barbarians&quot;, which has been variously interpreted as referring either to all areas outside the Byzantine Empire or only to those in the vicinity of Pontus, Asia and Thrace or to non-Greeks within the empire.&lt;ref name=Michalopulos/&gt; This canon would remain a constant source of friction between East and West until the mutual excommunications of 1054 made it irrelevant in that regard;&lt;ref name=&quot;McGuckin2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=McGuckin|first=John Anthony |title=The Orthodox Church: An Introduction to its History, Doctrine, and Spiritual Culture|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=KLIFfmipXcoC&amp;pg=PA32|accessdate=9 November 2012|date=18 October 2010|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|isbn=978-1-4443-3731-0|pages=32, 137}}&lt;/ref&gt; but controversy about its applicability to the authority it accorded to the patriarchate of Constantinople still continues.&lt;ref&gt;McGuckin (2010), p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;

Canon 9 of the Council also declared: &quot;If a bishop or clergyman should have a difference with the metropolitan of the province, let him have recourse to the Exarch of the Diocese, or to the throne of the Imperial City of Constantinople, and there let it be tried.&quot; This has been interpreted as conferring on the see of Constantinople a greater privilege than what any council ever gave Rome (Johnson, quoted by Schaff) or as of much lesser significance than that (Hefele, quoted by Schaff).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xi.xviii.ix.html Canon 9 and Notes]&lt;/ref&gt;

The patriarch of the imperial capital became in fact the leading bishop in the Byzantine Empire and &quot;headed a vast curia and other bishops who resided in Constantinople and constituted a permanent synod, which became the real governing body of the church&quot;.&lt;ref name=Schade(2006)&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=XRkfKdho-5cC&amp;q=%22one+universal+empire+was+sovereign%22 Johannes P. Schadé, ''Encyclopedia of World Religions'' (Foreign Media Group 2006 ISBN 978-1-60136000-7), section 8]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Patriarch John IV of Constantinople]], who died in 595, assumed the title of  &quot;Ecumenical Patriarch&quot;.&lt;ref name=Michalopulos&gt;[http://www.aoiusa.org/canon-28-and-eastern-papalism-cause-or-effect/ George C. Michalopulos, &quot;Canon 28 and Eastern Papalism: Cause or Effect?&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

By 661, Muslim Arabs had [[Muslim conquests|taken over]] the territories assigned to the patriarchates of Alexandria, Antioch and Jerusalem, which thereafter were never more than partially and temporarily recovered. In 732, [[Leo III the Isaurian]], in revenge for the opposition of [[Pope Gregory III]] to the emperor's [[iconoclasm (Byzantine)|iconoclast]] policies, transferred Sicily, Calabria and Illyria from the patriarchate of Rome (whose jurisdiction until then extended as far east as Thessalonica) to that of Constantinople.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/336200/Leo-III Encyclopædia Britannica: ''Leo III'']&lt;/ref&gt; The Constantinople patriarchate, after expanding eastward at the time of the Council of Chalcedon to take in Pontus and the Roman province of Asia, which at that time were still under the emperor's control, thus expanded equally to the west, and was practically coextensive with the Byzantine Empire.

The idea that with the transfer of the imperial capital from Rome to Constantinople primacy in the Church was also transferred is found in undeveloped form as early as [[John Philoponus]] (c. 490–c. 570); it was enunciated in its most advanced form by [[Photios I of Constantinople]] (c. 810–c. 893). Constantinople, as the seat of the ruler of the empire and therefore of the world, was the highest among the patriarchates and, like the emperor, had the right to govern them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myriobiblos.gr/texts/english/milton1_21.html Milton V. Anastos, ''Aspects of the Mind of Byzantium (Political Theory, Theology, and Ecclesiastical Relations with the See of Rome)'', Ashgate Publications, Variorum Collected Studies Series, 2001. ISBN 0-86078-840-7)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Constantine===
{{See also|Constantine I and Christianity|Byzantinism}}
[[File:Council of Constantinople 381 BnF MS Gr510 fol355.jpg|thumb|The [[Second Ecumenical Council]] whose additions to the [[Nicene Creed#The original Nicene Creed of 325|original Nicene Creed]] lay at the heart of one of the theological disputes associated with the East–West Schism. (Illustration, 879–882 AD, from manuscript, ''Homilies of [[Gregory of Nazianzus]]'', [[Bibliothèque nationale de France]])]]
When the Roman Emperor [[Constantine the Great]] legalized Christianity, he summoned the [[First Ecumenical Council]] at [[Nicaea (city)|Nicaea]] in 325 to resolve a number of issues which troubled the Church. The bishops at the council confirmed the position of the [[metropolitan see]]s of Rome and Alexandria as having authority outside their own province, and also the existing privileges of the churches in Antioch and the other provinces.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Let the ancient customs in Egypt, Libya and Pentapolis prevail, that the Bishop of Alexandria have jurisdiction in all these, since the like is customary for the Bishop of Rome also. Likewise in Antioch and the other provinces, let the Churches retain their privileges&quot; (First Ecumenical Council, [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.vii.vi.viii.html Canon VI]).&lt;/ref&gt; Later, these sees were called [[Patriarchate]]s{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} and were given an [[order of precedence]]: [[Rome]], though it was no longer capital of the empire, was given first place, then came [[Alexandria]] and [[Antioch]]. In a separate canon, the Council also approved the special honor given to [[Jerusalem in Christianity|Jerusalem]] over other sees subject to the same metropolitan.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Since custom and ancient tradition have prevailed that the Bishop of Ælia [i.e., Jerusalem] should be honored, let him, saving its due dignity to the Metropolis, have the next place of honor&quot; (First Ecumenical Council, [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.vii.vi.x.html Canon VII]&lt;/ref&gt;

Soon, Constantine erected a new capital at [[Byzantium]], a strategically placed city on the Bosporus. Constantine named it &quot;Nova Roma Constantinopolitana&quot; (''[[New Rome]] City of Constantine''),.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John Freely |title=The Companion Guide to Istanbul and Around the Marmara |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gxwB5fQeMWIC&amp;pg=PA5 |accessdate=2 June 2012 |date=1 October 2000 |publisher=Companion Guides |isbn=978-1-900639-31-6 |pages=5–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Jennifer Speake |title=Literature of Travel and Exploration: A to F |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=on2ShbwVzp4C&amp;pg=PA160 |accessdate=2 June 2012 |year=2003 |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis |isbn=978-1-57958-425-2 |pages=160–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Marcus Louis Rautman |title=Daily Life in the Byzantine Empire |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hs3iEyVRHKsC&amp;pg=PR17 |accessdate=2 June 2012 |year=2006 |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |isbn=978-0-313-32437-6 |pages=17–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Following the establishment of Constantinople (the ancient city of Byzantium) as the state capital of the Roman Empire in the early part of the fourth century, a series of significant ecclesiastical events saw the status of the Bishop of New Rome (as Constantinople was then called) elevated to its current position and privilege.[http://www.patriarchate.org/patriarchate/history]&lt;/ref&gt; Soon the local bishop's seat being established by [[Saint Andrew]] was elevated to Patriarch under Constantine, as [[Metrophanes of Byzantium]]&lt;ref&gt;St Metrophanes the first Patriarch of Constantinople. Saint Metrophanes, Patriarch of Constantinople, was a contemporary of St Constantine the Great (306–337). His father, Dometius, was a brother of the Roman emperor Probus (276–282). Seeing the falseness of the pagan religion, Dometius came to believe in Christ. During a time of terrible persecution of Christians at Rome, St Dometius set off to Byzantium with two of his sons, Probus and Metrophanes. They were instructed in the law of the Lord by Bishop Titus, a man of holy life. Seeing the ardent desire of Dometius to labor for the Lord, St Titus ordained him presbyter. After the death of Titus first Dometius (272–303) was elevated to the bishop's throne, and thereafter his sons, Probus (303–315) and in 316 St Metrophanes. The emperor Constantine once came to Byzantium, and was delighted by the beauty and comfortable setting of the city. And having seen the holiness of life and sagacity of St Metrophanes, the emperor took him back to Rome. Soon Constantine the Great transferred the capital from Rome to Byzantium and he brought St Metrophanes there. The First Ecumenical Council was convened in 325 to resolve the Arian heresy. Constantine the Great had the holy Fathers of the Council bestow upon St Metrophanes the title of Patriarch. Thus, the saint became the first Patriarch of Constantinople.[http://www.oca.org/FSLivesAllSaints.asp?SID=4&amp;M=6&amp;D=4]&lt;/ref&gt; at the time occupied the bishops seat before the New Capital was established. Constantinople is often described as '[[New Rome]]', because it imitated Rome in many ways and became the new capital of the empire.&lt;ref&gt;The Story of Civilization: The age of Faith; a history of medieval By [[Will Durant]], Ariel Durant pg 3 &quot;The city that Constantine had called Nova Roma, but which even in his lifetime had taken his name, had been founded on the Bosporus by Greek colonists about 657 bc For almost a thousand years it had been known as Byzantium;&quot; ASIN: B001DA7Q0I&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Lucius Boraks |title=Religions of the West |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=av6a7moNFw8C&amp;pg=PA48 |accessdate=2 June 2012 |year=1988 |publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |isbn=978-1-55612-141-8 |pages=48–}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Godfrey Higgins |title=Anacalypsis an Attempt to Draw Aside the Veil of the Saitic Isis: Or an Inquiry Into the Origin of Languages, Nations and Religions |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-sNBAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA625 |accessdate=2 June 2012 |year=1836 |publisher=Longman |pages=625–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Second Ecumenical Council]], held at the new capital in 381, elevated the see of Constantinople to a position ahead of the other chief metropolitan sees, except that of Rome, which was stated to have the greatest honor.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Bishop of Constantinople, however, shall have the prerogative of honor after the Bishop of Rome; ''because Constantinople is New Rome''&quot; (Second Ecumenical Council, [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.ix.viii.iv.html Canon III])&lt;/ref&gt; Mentioning in particular the provinces of [[Asia (Roman province)|Asia]], [[Pontus]] and [[Thrace]], it decreed that the synod of each province should manage the ecclesiastical affairs of that province alone, except for the privileges already recognized for [[Alexandria]] and [[Patriarch of Antioch|Antioch]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Let the Bishop of Alexandria, according to the canons, alone administer the affairs of Egypt; and let the bishops of the East manage the East alone, the privileges of the Church in Antioch, which are mentioned in the canons of Nice, being preserved; and let the bishops of the Asian Diocese administer the Asian affairs only; and the Pontic bishops only Pontic matters; and the Thracian bishops only Thracian affairs&quot; (Second Ecumenical Council, [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.ix.viii.iii.html Canon II])&lt;/ref&gt; In the Council of Chalcedon, held 70 years later, Constantinople was given power over Pontus and Thrace.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/chalcedon.html Council of Chalcedon, canon XXVIII]. Fordham.edu. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Council of Chalcedon===
The [[Council of Chalcedon|Fourth Ecumenical Council]] at [[Chalcedon]] in 451 confirmed the authority already held by Constantinople. There were now five patriarchs presiding over the Church within the [[Byzantine Empire]], in the following order of precedence: the [[Patriarch of Rome]], the [[Patriarch of Constantinople]], the [[Patriarch of Alexandria]], the [[Patriarch of Antioch]] and the [[Greek Orthodox Patriarch of Jerusalem|Patriarch of Jerusalem]] (see [[Pentarchy]]).

===Council in Trullo===
The West's rejection of the [[Quinisext Council]] of 692 also led to pressure from the Eastern Empire on the West to reject many Latin customs as non-Orthodox. The Latin practices that had got the attention of the other Patriarchates{{Citation needed|date=November 2012}} and that had been condemned by this Council included the practice of celebrating [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]] on weekdays in [[Great Lent|Lent]] (rather than having [[Liturgy of the Presanctified Gifts|Pre-Sanctified Liturgies]]);&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.liii.html Canon LII]&lt;/ref&gt; [[fasting]] on Saturdays throughout the year;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.lvi.html http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.lvi.html Canon LV]&lt;/ref&gt; omitting the &quot;[[Alleluia]]&quot; in Lent; depicting Christ as a [[Lamb of God|lamb]];&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.lxxxiii.html Canon LXXXII]&lt;/ref&gt; using unleavened bread.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.xii.html Canon XI]&lt;/ref&gt; Larger disputes were revealed regarding Eastern and Western attitudes toward [[clerical celibacy|celibacy]] for [[priest]]s and [[deacon]]s, with the Council affirming the right of married men to become priests (though forbidding priests to marry and forbidding bishops to live with their wives)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.vi.html Canon VI] and [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.vii.html Schaff, &quot;Excursus on the Marriage of the Clergy&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.xiii.html Canon XII]&lt;/ref&gt; and prescribing deposition for anyone who attempted to separate a clergyman other than a bishop from his wife, or for any cleric other than a bishop who dismissed his wife.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.xiv.html Canon XIII] and [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xiv.iii.xlix.html Canon XLVIII]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pope Sergius I]], who was of Syrian origin, rejected the council, preferring, he said, &quot;to die rather than consent to erroneous novelties&quot;. Though a loyal subject of the Empire, he would not be &quot;its captive in matters of religion&quot; and refused to sign the canons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=zomZk6DbFTIC&amp;pg=PA222&amp;dq=Ekonomou+%22captive+in+matters+of+religion%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Gw2cUI-xKsOzhAeNoIBo&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Ekonomou%20%22captive%20in%20matters%20of%20religion%22&amp;f=false Andrew J. Ekonomou, ''Byzantine Rome and the Greek Popes'' (Lexington Books 2007 ISBN 978-0-73911977-8), p. 222[&lt;/ref&gt; Emperor [[Justinian II]] ordered his arrest and abduction to Constantinople by the notoriously violent ''[[protospatharios]]'' Zacharias.&lt;ref&gt; Ekonomou (2007), p. 223&lt;/ref&gt; However, the militia of the [[exarchate of Ravenna]] frustrated the attempt.&lt;ref&gt;Ekonomou (2007), p. 224&lt;/ref&gt; Zacharias nearly lost his life in his attempt to arrest Sergius I.&lt;ref&gt;Ekonomou (2007), p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=UdB64ytwmaQC&amp;pg=PA64&amp;dq=%22Sergius+I%22++%22Justinian+II%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=RBWcUKWjMZC1hAepj4FA&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Sergius%20I%22%20%20%22Justinian%20II%22&amp;f=false Walter Ullmann, ''A Short History of the Papacy in the Middle Ages'' (2nd edition, Routledge 2003 ISBN 978-0-41530227-2), p. 64]&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, in [[Visigothic]] [[Hispania|Spain]], the council was ratified by the [[Eighteenth Council of Toledo]] at the urging of the king, [[Wittiza]], who was vilified by later chroniclers for his decision.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot;&gt;Collins, 19.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fruela I of Asturias]] reversed the decision of Toledo sometime during his reign (757–768).&lt;ref name=&quot;Collins&quot;/&gt;

The Eastern Orthodox churches hold this council be part of the Fifth and Sixth Ecumenical Councils, adding its canons thereto.

===Political division between East and West===
[[File:Byzantine Empire animated2.gif|thumb|left|450px|Changes in extent of the Empire ruled from Constantinople.&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt; 476 End of the Western Empire; 550 Conquests of Justinian I; 717 Accession of Leo the Isaurian; 867 Accession of Basil I; 1025 Death of Basil II; 1095 Eve of the First Crusade; 1170 Under Manuel I; 1270 Under Michael VIII Palaiologos; 1400 Before the fall of Constantinople&lt;/small&gt;]]
Disunion and territorial loss in the Roman Empire contributed to disunion in the Church. Emperor [[Diocletian]] divided the administration of the eastern and western portions of the Empire in the early 4th century, though subsequent leaders (including Constantine) within the same century aspired to and sometimes gained control of both regions. [[Theodosius I|Theodosius the Great]], who established [[First Council of Nicaea|Nicene]] Christianity as the official religion of the Roman Empire (see [[Edict of Thessalonica]]), was the last Emperor to rule over a united Roman Empire. Following his death in 395, the division into western and eastern halves, each for a few decades still under its own Emperor, was never undone, for the Western Roman Empire soon ceased to exist. In the early fifth century, its whole territory was overrun by Germanic tribes, and the year 476 saw the end even of the pretence of a Western Roman Emperor, when [[Odoacer]] forced [[Romulus Augustus]] to abdicate. The Eastern Roman Empire (known also as the [[Byzantine Empire]]) continued to thrive and in the 6th century recovered Italy and other sections of the western Mediterranean shore; but it soon lost most of these gains, although it held Rome, as part of the [[Exarchate of Ravenna]], until 751.

Thus, the political unity of what had been the Roman Empire fell. In the west, Christianity became mostly subject to the laws and customs of nations that owed no allegiance to the emperor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| editor=Ayer, John Cullen | title=A Source Book for Ancient Church History | year=1913 | publisher=Mundus Publishing (2008 reprint) | url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fM9y0Db-88wC | pp. 538-539}}&lt;/ref&gt; These [[Germanic peoples]], particularly the Franks, influenced and changed the Latin Church.&lt;ref&gt;Roman Revolutions and the Rise of Frankish Feudalism and Doctrine.
During the seventh century, however, the seeds of schism appear. The Visigoths in Spain had abandoned their Arian heresy and had become nominally Orthodox. But they preserved their Arian customs of church administration, which became that of the Carolingian Franks, and finally, of the Normans. The Visigoths began subjugating the Spanish Romans by replacing Roman bishops with Goths and by 654, had abolished Roman law.
During this same century, especially after 683, the Franks also had appointed Frankish bishops en masse and had rid their government administration of Roman officials.
Earlier, during the sixth and early seventh century, rebellions of leaders in Francia were joint conspiracies of Franks and Romans. By 673, however, the rebellions had become purely Frankish.
The fact that Constantinople sent its navy twice to Spain at the end of the seventh and beginning of the eighth century to reestablish the beachhead lost in 629 is testimony to the plight of Roman Christians in Spain. In the face of the victorious Arabs, who had completed their conquest of the Middle East and had driven across Northern Africa, within striking distance of Carthage, Constantinople seemed ill-prepared for such military ventures into Spain. However, judging from the pattern of events, it seems that these attempted East Roman landings in Spain were supposed to touch off a general uprising of the Christian and Jewish Romans in Spain and Gaul against Visigothic and Frankish rule. The success of such rebellions in Spain and Gaul would perhaps have helped Constantinople in stemming the Arab tidal wave, which at times seemed to swamp the whole empire.
At the Seventeenth Council of Toledo in 694, the Jews were condemned to slavery because they had confessed to a plot to overthrow the 'Christians' (meaning Goths) in Spain, with the help of &quot;those who dwelt in lands beyond the sea,&quot; the Roman, and not the later Arabic province of Africa, as is commonly believed. The Arabs at this time had not yet reached Carthage, the capital of this province or exarchate. Egica (687–701), the Gothic king, had fought off an attempt by the East Roman navy to reinstall the beachhead lost in 629. There can be no doubt that the Jews were condemned at this Seventeenth Council of Toledo in 694 for plotting with Constantinople and Spanish Romans for the overthrow of Gothic rule in Spain.
[[King Witiza]] (701-708/9), the son of Egica, also defeated an East Roman attempt to liberate some of the cities in Southern Spain. Since 698 the Arabs were in firm control of Carthage and its environs and were establishing their control in the area of Ceuta.
These attempts of Constantinople failed, and the Roman Berber (Numedian) governor of Ceuta[ 1 ]in 711, and a bit later, the Gallo Romans, chose what seemed the lesser evil by establishing ad hoc alliances with the Arabs against Visigoths and Franks. These Roman Arab alliances overthrew Visigothic rule in Spain (711–719), but were defeated by the  Frank warlord Charles Martel, first at Poitiers in 732, and then in Provence in 739.
The Roman revolts reduced Francia to the northern kingdoms of Austrasia and Neutrasia. Eudo, the Roman duke of Aquitane, who made the first mentioned alliance with the Arabs against the Franks[ 2 ], had temporarily occupied Paris itself in an attempt to keep the pro-Roman Merovingian Franks in power. It fell to Charles Martel, Pippin III, and Charlemagne to restore Frankish rule over Burgundy, Auvergne, Aquitane, Gascony, Septimania, and Provence.
Carolingian feudalism had its origin in the need to prevent the disaster which had overtaken the Visigoths in Spain. The Franks were obliged to develop and extend the already existing system of controlling slave populations. Their goal was to keep the Romans subjugated and pacified, first in Austrasia and Neustrasia, and then elsewhere in Gaul, and, finally, in Northern Italy, as circumstances permitted.[ 3 ]
While still consolidating their grip on Gaul, the Franks conquered Northern and Central Italian Romania in the middle of the eighth century, in the guise of liberators of Italic of Papal Romania from Lombard oppression. At this time, the papacy was deeply involved in the iconoclastic controversy, having taken a firm stand, against the Roman emperors and patriarchs of New Rome who supported the iconoclastic movement.
The Franks applied their policy of destroying the unity between the Romans under their rule and the Romans under the rule of Constantinople and the Arabs. They played one Roman party against the other, took neither side, and finally condemned both the iconoclasts and the Seventh Ecumenical Synod (786/7) at their own Council of Frankfurt in 794, in the presence of the legates of Pope Hadrian I (771–795), the staunch supporter of Orthodox practice. [http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.03.en.franks_romans_feudalism_and_doctrine.01.htm#s2]&lt;/ref&gt; Their obliteration of the Empire's boundaries and an outburst of missionary activity among these peoples who had no direct links with the [[Byzantine Empire|Eastern Roman Empire]] and among [[Celtic peoples]], who had never been part of the Roman Empire fostered the idea of a universal church free from association with a particular state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03096a.htm Gerland, Ernst. &quot;The Byzantine Empire&quot;] in The Catholic Encyclopedia. Vol. 3. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1908. Retrieved 9 November 2012&lt;/ref&gt; On the contrary, &quot;in the East Roman or Byzantine view, when the Roman Empire became Christian, the perfect world order willed by God had been achieved: one universal empire was sovereign, and coterminous with it was the one universal church&quot;; and, according to the author of the ''Encyclopedia of World Religions'', the Empire's state church came, by the time of the demise of the Empire in 1453, to merge psychologically with it to the extent that its bishops had difficulty in thinking of Christianity without an Emperor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=XRkfKdho-5cC&amp;q=%22one+universal+empire+was+sovereign%22&amp;redir_esc=y Johannes P. Schadé, ''Encyclopedia of World Religions (Foreign Media Group 2006 ISBN 978-1-60136000-7), article &quot;Byzantine Church&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; In the West, as a practical matter, the collapse of civil government left the Church in charge in many areas, and bishops took to administering secular cities and domains.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;/&gt; When royal and imperial rule reestablished itself, it had to contend with power wielded independently by the Church. In the East, however, imperial and, later, Islamic rule dominated the Eastern bishops.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;/&gt;

===Political and cultural separation===
{{See also|Byzantine Papacy}}

Following the [[Sack of Rome (410)|Sack of Rome]] by invading European Goths, Rome became increasingly isolated from the churches in the eastern and southern Mediterranean. This was a situation which suited and pleased many of the patriarchs and bishops of those churches.&lt;ref&gt;Aristeides Papadakis The Christian East and the Rise of the Papacy, SVS Press, NY, 1994 esp p14&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[John Romanides]], the rise of the [[Frankish Empire]] after the [[Goths]] and the fall of the [[Western Roman Empire]] saw the establishment of a [[Frankish Papacy|papacy beholden to the Franks]] from 752 to 844. These Frankish Popes were military leaders according to [[Saint Boniface]] known to &quot;shed the blood of Christians like that of the pagans.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;In the time of [[Pepin of Herstal|Pippin of Herestal]] (697–715) and [[Charles Martel]] (715–741), many of the Franks who replaced Roman bishops were military leaders who, according to [[Saint Boniface]], &quot;shed the blood of Christians like that of the pagans.&quot; FRANKS, ROMANS, FEUDALISM, AND DOCTRINE — [ Part 1 ] [http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.03.en.franks_romans_feudalism_and_doctrine.01.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;{{verify credibility|Boniface was a legate of these same popes who were rulers of the Papal States and may have been forced to defend them. Against the Lombards for starters. But this doesn't seem to jibe with anything else I have read|date=December 2011}}

The Eastern Orthodox theologian Romanides states that it was not until the rise of Charlemagne and his successors, and the influence of the [[Scholae Palatinae|Palatine School]] established by the Englishman Alcuin (735–804), that the Church of Rome became almost exclusively committed to Augustinian theology.&lt;ref&gt;Augustine never understood these two distinctions, nor the four keys previously discussed. '''Franco-Latin Christianity and doctrine began its first essay into theology and doctrine with the Palatine School established by Charlemagne at the end of the 8th century. This school knew only Augustine because its organizer the Saxon Alcuin (735–804) evidently knew only Augustine thoroughly. see Romanides&lt;/ref&gt;

===Papal supremacy and pentarchy===
[[File:Nicaea icon.jpg|thumb|Icon depicting [[Constantine I|the Emperor Constantine]] (centre) and the [[bishop]]s of the [[First Council of Nicaea]] (325) holding the [[Niceno-Constantinopolitan Creed|Niceno–Constantinopolitan Creed of 381]].]]

In 342 [[Pope Julius I]] wrote: &quot;The custom has been for word first to us [in the case of bishops under accusation, and notably in apostolic churches], and then for a just sentence to be passed from this place&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=Hje62q52XNsC&amp;pg=PA199&amp;dq=Nichols+%22bishops+under+accusation%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=82meUO_iJ4a7hAeghoC4BA&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Aidan Nichols, ''Rome and the Eastern Churches'' (Ignatius Press 2010 ISBN 978-1-58617282-4), p. 199]. This was also decreed by the [[Council of Sardica]], which declared Saint [[Athanasius]] to be the lawful bishop of Alexandria ([http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3815.htm Council of Sardica, canons 3-5]).&lt;/ref&gt; In 382 a synod in Rome under [[Pope Damasus I]] that protested against the raising of Constantinople to a position above that of Alexandria, spoke of Rome as &quot;the apostolic see&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Nichols (2010), p. 202&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Siricius]] (384-399) claimed for papal decretals the same binding force as decisions of synods, [[Pope Innocent I]] (401-417) said that all major judicial cases should be reserved for the see of Rome, and [[Pope Boniface I]] (418-422) declared that the church of Rome stands to &quot;the churches throughout the world as the head to its members&quot; and that bishops everywhere, while holding the one same episcopal office, must &quot;recognise those to whom, for the sake of ecclesiastical discipline, they should be subject&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Nichols (2010), p. 203&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Celestine I]] (422-432) considered that the condemnation of [[Nestorius]] by his own Roman synod in 430 was sufficient, but consented to the general council as &quot;of benefit in manifesting the faith&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nichols (2010), p. 203. The [[First Council of Ephesus]] in 431 stated that it Nestorius &quot;compelled thereto by the canons and by the letter of our most holy father and fellow-servant [[Pope Celestine I|Coelestine]], the Roman bishop&quot; ([http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.x.xi.html Decree of the Council against Nestorius).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Leo I]] and his successors rejected canon 28 of the [[Council of Chalcedon]], as a result of which it was not officially recorded even in the East until the 6th century.&lt;ref name=Michalopulos/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nichols (2010), p. 208]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Acacian schism]] (484-519), when, &quot;for the first time, West lines up against East in a clear-cut fashion&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Nichols (2010), pp. 209-210&lt;/ref&gt; ended with acceptance of a declaration insisted on by [[Pope Hormisdas]] (514-523) that &quot;I hope I shall remain in communion with the apostolic see in which is found the whole, true, and perfect stability of the Christian religion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Nichols (2010), p. 210; [http://books.google.com/books?id=5V1xelf69XAC&amp;pg=PT244&amp;dq=Hormisdas+formula+whitehead&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=KcGeUOzTCcWAhQfjyYCoCA&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false  Kenneth D. Whitehead, ''One, Holy, Catholic and Apostolic'' (Ignatius Press 2000 ISBN 978-0-89870802-8)]; [http://books.google.com/books?id=fM9y0Db-88wC&amp;pg=PT315&amp;dq=hormisdas+formula+ayer&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=vcKeUP6_DISJhQfK7oAo&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Joseph Cullen Ayer, Jr, ''A Source Book for Ancient Church History'' (Mundus Publishing 2008), p. 537]&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier, in 494, [[Pope Gelasius I]] (492-496) wrote to Byzantine Emperor [[Anastasius I (emperor)|Anastasius]], distinguishing the power of civil rulers from that of the bishops (called &quot;priests&quot; in the document), with the latter supreme in religious matters; he ended his letter with: &quot;And if it is fitting that the hearts of the faithful should submit to all priests in general who properly administer divine affairs, how much the more is obedience due to the bishop of that see which the Most High ordained to be above all others, and which is consequently dutifully honoured by the devotion of the whole Church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/gelasius1.asp Gelasius I on Spiritual and Temporal Power]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Nicholas I]] (858-867) made it clear that he believed the power of the papacy extended &quot;over all the earth, that is, over every church&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stpaulsirvine.org/html/TheGreatSchism.htm Bishop [[Kallistos Ware]], ''The Great Schism'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctlibrary.com/ch/1997/issue54/54h010.html Mark Galli, '&amp;#39;The Great Divorce'&amp;#39;]. Ctlibrary.com (1997-04-01). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Eastern Orthodox state that the 28th Canon of the [[Council of Chalcedon]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.xi.xviii.xxviii.html NPNF2-14. The Seven Ecumenical Councils – Christian Classics Ethereal Library]. Ccel.org (2005-06-01). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; explicitly proclaimed the equality of the Bishops of Rome and Constantinople,&lt;ref&gt;There are no primacies nor primates according to Roman Orthodox Canon Law, but only bishops with &quot;Seniority of Honor&quot; since all bishops are doctrinally equal. The Franco-Latin and Protestant translations of &quot;[[Seniority of honor]]&quot; by &quot;[[primacy of honor]]&quot; is theirs, not ours John Romanides [http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.16.en.romanity_romania_roumeli.01.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.monachos.net/content/patristics/studies-themes/251-council-of-chalcedon-451-resource-materials Council of Chalcedon, 451: Resource Materials]. Monachos.net (2012-05-28). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; and that it established the highest court of ecclesiastical appeal in Constantinople.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;

Eastern Orthodox argue that the seventh canon of the [[First Council of Ephesus|Council of Ephesus]] explicitly prohibited modification of the Nicene Creed by any man (not by Ecumenical church council) drawn up by the [[First Council of Nicaea|first Ecumenical Council]] in 325.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.ix.i.html NPNF2-14. The Seven Ecumenical Councils – Christian Classics Ethereal Library]. Ccel.org (2005-06-01). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; The Council made this prohibition in light of the fact that the earlier [[First Council of Constantinople|second Ecumenical Council]], had already modified the Creed adopted at Nicaea, making additions such as &quot;who proceeds from the Father&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The seventh canon of the Council of Ephesus declared: &quot;It is unlawful for any man to bring forward, or to write, or to compose a different (ἑτέραν) Faith as a rival to that established by the holy Fathers assembled with the Holy Ghost in Nicæa. But those who shall dare to compose a different faith, or to introduce or offer it to persons desiring to turn to the acknowledgment of the truth, whether from Heathenism or from Judaism, or from any heresy whatsoever, shall be deposed, if they be bishops or clergymen; bishops from the episcopate and clergymen from the clergy; and if they be laymen, they shall be [[anathematized]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;([http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3810.htm Extracts from the Acts of the Council of Ephesus]). The creed quoted in the Acts of the Council of Ephesus (the Third Ecumenical Council) is that of the first Ecumenical Council, not the creed as modified by the second Ecumenical Council, and so does not have additions such as &quot;who proceeds from the Father&quot; (''ibidem'').&lt;/ref&gt; Eastern Orthodox theologians state this change of the wording of the churches' original creed, was done to address various teachings outside of the church in specific the [[Macedonius I of Constantinople]] teaching which the council claimed was a distortion of the church's teaching on the Holy Spirit. This was not a change of the orthodoxy of the churches' original creed.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;However, the chief of the heretics who distorted the apostolic teaching concerning the Holy Spirit was Macedonius, who occupied the cathedra of Constantinople as archbishop in the 4th century and found followers for himself among former Arians and Semi-Arians. He called the Holy Spirit a creation of the Son, and a servant of the Father and the Son. Accusers of his heresy were Fathers of the Church like Sts. Basil the Great, Gregory the Theologian, Athanasius the Great, Gregory of Nyssa, Ambrose, Amphilocius, Diodores of Tarsus, and others, who wrote works against the heretics. The false teaching of Macedonius was refuted first in a series of local councils and finally at the Second Ecumenical Council of Constantinople in 381. In preserving Orthodoxy, the Second Ecumenical Council completed the Nicaean Symbol of Faith with these words: “And in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, the Giver of Life, Who proceedeth from the Father, Who with the Father and the Son is equally worshiped and glorified, Who spake by the Prophets,” as well as those articles of the Creed which follow this in the Nicaean-Constantinopolitan Symbol of Faith.&quot; Orthodox Dogmatic Theology: A Concise Exposition Protopresbyter [[Michael Pomazansky]] St Herman of Alaska Brotherhood press 1994 (ISBN 0-938635-69-7) [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0824/_P17.HTM]&lt;/ref&gt;

There were other less significant catalysts for the Schism however, including variance over [[liturgy|liturgical]] practices.

In Eastern Christendom the teaching of Papal Supremacy is called [[False Isidorean Decretals]]&lt;ref&gt;Specifically, the popes recurred to Saint Peter, whose memory was sacred among all Christians, evolving a proposition known in Orthodox Catholic Church History as “False Isidorean Decretals,” which alleges that Jesus made Peter head over all other Apostles setting him up as a Prince of the Church; that this headship after the death of Apostle Peter passed to subsequent Roman popes; and that therefore, the pope is the head of all bishops, a Vicar of Christ on earth. And as such he is alleged to be ipso facto an autocratic monarch of the Church, the Supreme Judge, higher than the Ecumenical Councils — one from whom all bishops and clerics receive gifts of Grace, their rights and “jurisdiction.” [http://www.orthodoxresearchinstitute.org/articles/dogmatics/krehel_orthodox_catholic_faith.htm#_ednref21]&lt;/ref&gt; as it is based on the false documents of Christian canon law under the name [[Pseudo-Isidore]]. The Orthodox East contests the teaching that Peter was the [[Patriarch of Rome]] as [[Irenaeus|St. Irenaeus]] says that [[Pope Linus]] was the first bishop of Rome and [[Pope Cletus]] the second.&lt;ref&gt;J. N. D. Kelly, ''Oxford Dictionary of Popes'', 2005&lt;/ref&gt; It is generally conceded that St. Peter was [[bishop of Antioch]] who was then succeeded by [[Saint Evodius|Evodius]] and [[Ignatius of Antioch|Ignatius]]. The Eastern Orthodox do not hold the primacy of the Pope of Rome over the Eastern church; they teach that the Pope of Rome is the first among equals. The [[Seven Ecumenical Councils]] were held in the East and called by the Eastern Emperors, Roman pontiffs never presided over any of them.&lt;ref&gt;The Orthodox attitude to the Papacy is admirably expressed by a twelfth-century writer, [[Nicetas of Nicomedia|Nicetas]], Archbishop of Nicomedia
:My dearest brother, we do not deny to the Roman Church the primacy amongst the five sister Patriarchates; and we recognize her right to the most honorable seat at an Ecumenical Council. But she has separated herself from us by her own deeds, when through pride she assumed a monarchy which does not belong to her office... How shall we accept decrees from her that have been issued without consulting us and even without our knowledge? If the Roman Pontiff, seated on the lofty throne of his glory, wishes to thunder at us and, so to speak, hurl his mandates at us from on high, and if he wishes to judge us and even to rule us and our Churches, not by taking counsel with us but at his own arbitrary pleasure, what kind of brotherhood, or even what kind of parenthood can this be? We should be the slaves, not the sons, of such a Church, and the Roman See would not be the pious mother of sons but a hard and imperious mistress of slaves (Quoted in S. Runciman, The Eastern Schism, p. 116).Orthodox Church by Bishop [[Kallistos Ware]] Part I: History. ISBN 978-0-14-014656-1
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Council of Constantinople in 867===
{{Main|Council of Constantinople (867)}}
At least three councils (867, [[Fourth Council of Constantinople (Roman Catholic)|869]], [[Fourth Council of Constantinople (Eastern Orthodox)|879]]) were held in Constantinople over the deposition of Ignatius by Emperor [[Michael III]] and the replacing of him by Photius. The Pope in disagreement in 863 then held a synod at the [[Lateran]] that reversed the Eastern Churches and the Emperor's action, and this was taken by the East as an unacceptable intervention of the Pope of Rome. The use of the Filioque was also condemned. Due to various conflicts arising during the replacement of [[Patriarch Ignatius of Constantinople]] by Photius, the [[Council of Constantinople (867)]] was convened via Photius, to address the question of Papal Supremacy over all of the churches and their patriarchs and the use of the Filioque.&lt;ref&gt;A. Fortescue, The Orthodox Eastern Church, pages 147–148;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Latin West pg171&quot;&gt;[[Andrew Louth]], Greek East and Latin West, pg171&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;S. Tougher pg69&quot;&gt;S. Tougher, The Reign of Leo VI, pg69&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;The Filioque: History of a Doctrinal Controversy pg103 By A. Edward Siecienski Publisher: Oxford University Press, USA (12 May 2010) ISBN 978-0-19-537204-5 [http://books.google.com/books?id=auT8VbgOe48C&amp;pg=PA103&amp;lpg=PA103&amp;dq=The+Filioque:+History+of+a+Doctrinal+Controversy++By+A.+Edward+Siecienski+Photius+filioque+867&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=oPcmBDltx2&amp;sig=97rn9ViBhF4hvccgp4OmnOMnrzU&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=j6HQS4ifCIPa8QST1tgw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CAkQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt; Pope Nicholas I was intervening in the appointing of Patriarchs in jurisdictions other than his own, (Patriarchs that were supposed to be equal to him) and in their confirmation process. At the time of the early church and these councils there were no other Patriarchs in the West other than Rome, whereas there were the four other Patriarchs of the East.

Pope Nicholas had attempted to remove Photius and reappoint Ignatius as the Patriarch of Constantinople by his own authority and decree. Thus the Pope was intervening in the matters of Imperial authority as well as the other churches of the East and their own internal councils and authorities, which they understood to be outside the Pope's own jurisdiction of Rome. The council of 867 was followed by the [[Fourth Council of Constantinople (Roman Catholic)|Council of Constantinople 869]]. The [[Fourth Council of Constantinople (Eastern Orthodox)|Council of Constantinople in 879]] then restored the conclusions of the Council of 867. The Roman Catholic Church rejects the councils of 867 and 879 but accepts the council of 869. [[Pope Nicholas I]] was deposed and the teaching of the Filioque was condemned in the council in 867.&lt;ref name=&quot;Latin West pg171&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;S. Tougher pg69&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A. Fortescue, The Orthodox Eastern Church, pages 147–148&lt;/ref&gt; The Council at Constantinople in 867 excommunicated [[Pope Nicholas I]], who was then replaced by [[Pope Adrian II]] (due to the death of Nicholas I), and rejected Nicholas' claims of primacy, his efforts to convert Bulgaria, and the addition of the Filioque in parts of the Latin Church.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of the Middle Ages, Volume 2
 By André Vauchez, Richard Barrie Dobson, Adrian Walford, Michael Lapidge Publisher: Routledge; 1 edition (1 April 2001) ISBN 978-1-57958-282-1 Product Dimensions: 11.1x9 [http://books.google.com/books?id=om4olQhrE84C&amp;pg=PA1016]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other points of conflict===
Many other issues increased tensions.
* Emperor [[Leo III the Isaurian]] outlawed the veneration of icons in the 8th century. This policy, which came to be called [[Iconoclasm]], was rejected by the West with the exception of [[Emperor Charlemagne]], who commissioned the [[Libri Carolini]] which affirmed a condemnation of the veneration of icons.
* The Western Church's insertion of &quot;[[Filioque]]&quot; into the [[Latin]] version of the [[Nicene Creed]] without holding a council with or gaining consent from the Eastern Churches.&lt;ref name=r1&gt;Quoting [[Aleksey Khomyakov]] on the Filioque and economy of the Eastern Churches and Roman Catholicism pg 87 The legal formalism and logical rationalism of the Roman Catholic Church have their roots in the Roman State. These features developed in it more strongly than ever when the Western Church without consent of the Eastern introduced into the Nicean Creed the Filioque clause. Such arbitrary change of the creed is an expression of pride and lack of love for one's brethren in the faith. &quot;In order not to be regarded as a schism by the Church, Romanism was forced to ascribe to the bishop of Rome absolute infallibility.&quot; In this way Catholicism broke away from the Church as a whole and became an organization based upon external authority. History of Russian Philosophy by [[N. O. Lossky]] ISBN 978-0-8236-8074-0&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the East, the patriarch Photius responded to the practice of certain Frankish monks in Jerusalem who attempted to impose the practice of the Filioque on their Eastern brothers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard P pg 529-530&quot;&gt;The HarperCollins Encyclopedia of Catholicism By [[Richard McBrien]], [[Harold Attridge]] [http://books.google.com/books?id=WlNfJC6RveAC&amp;pg=PA529 pp. 529–530] ISBN 978-0-06-065338-5&lt;/ref&gt;
* Disputes in the [[Balkans]], Southern Italy, and [[Sicily]] over whether Rome or Constantinople had ecclesiastical jurisdiction.
* In the East, endorsement of so-called [[Caesaropapism]], subordination of the church to the religious claims of the dominant political order, was most fully evident in the [[Byzantine Empire]] at the end of the first millennium, while in the West, where the decline of imperial authority left the Church a relatively independent political authority, there was growth of the power of the [[Papacy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Church and State in the Byzantine Empire|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761573998/Church_and_State.html#p3|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?id=1257013941639739|archivedate=2009-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John C. Dwyer, ''Church History'' (Paulist Press 1998 ISBN 978-0-8091-3830-2), p. 118&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matthew Bunson, ''Encyclopedia of the Roman Empire'' (Facts on File 2002 ISBN 978-0-8160-4562-4), pp. 115–116&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Deno John Geanakoplos, ''Constantinople and the West'' (University of Wisconsin Press 1989 ISBN 978-0-299-11884-6), p. 226&lt;/ref&gt;
* As a result of the [[Muslim conquests]] of the territories of the patriarchates of Alexandria, Antioch and Jerusalem, only two rival powerful centres of ecclesiastical authority, Constantinople and Rome, remained.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;During the decade following the death of the Prophet Muhammad in 632, his followers captured three of the five 'patriarchates' of the early church — Alexandria, Antioch, and Jerusalem — leaving only Rome and Constantinople.&quot; ([http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/507284/Roman-Catholicism/257669 Encyclopaedia Britannica]).&lt;/ref&gt;
* Certain [[liturgy|liturgical]] practices in the West that the East believed represented illegitimate innovation: the use of [[unleavened bread]] for the [[Eucharist]], for example (see [[Azymite]]).
*[[Clerical celibacy|Celibacy among Western priests]] (both monastic and parish), as opposed to the Eastern discipline whereby parish priests can be married men.

===Mutual excommunication of 1054===
Most of the direct causes of the Great Schism, however, are far less grandiose than the ''[[Filioque]]''. The relations between the papacy and the Byzantine court were good in the years leading up to 1054. The emperor [[Constantine IX]] and the [[Pope Leo IX]] were allied through the mediation of the [[Lombards|Lombard]] [[catepan of Italy]], [[Argyrus (Catepan of Italy)|Argyrus]], who had spent years in Constantinople, originally as a political prisoner.

Patriarch [[Michael I Cerularius|Michael I]] ordered a letter to be written to the [[bishop of Trani]] in which he attacked the &quot;[[Judaizers|Judaistic]]&quot; practices of the West, namely, the use of unleavened bread. The letter was to be sent by John to all the bishops of the West, including the Pope. John promptly complied, and the letter was passed to [[Humbert of Mourmoutiers]], the [[cardinal-bishop of Silva Candida]], who translated the letter into [[Latin]] and brought it to the Pope, who ordered a reply to be made to each charge and a defense of [[papal supremacy]] to be laid out in a response.

In 1054, Pope [[Leo IX]] sent a letter to Michael Cærularius, [[Patriarch of Constantinople]], that cited a large portion of the forgery called the [[Donation of Constantine]], believing it genuine.&lt;ref&gt;Migne's ''[[Patrologia Latina]]'', Vol. 143 (cxliii), Col. 744–769. Also Mansi, ''Sacrorum Conciliorum Nova Amplissima Collectio'', Vol. 19 (xix) Col. 635–656.&lt;/ref&gt; The official status of this letter is acknowledged in the 1913 ''Catholic Encyclopedia'', Volume 5, entry on Donation of Constantine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Knights of Columbus. Catholic Truth Committee |title=The Catholic encyclopedia: an international work of reference on the constitution, doctrine, discipline, and history of the Catholic Church |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-aSQNo8kNqIC&amp;pg=PA120 |accessdate=2 June 2012 |year=1913 |publisher=Encyclopedia Press |pages=120–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:&quot;The first pope who used it in an official act and relied upon it was Leo IX; in a letter of 1054 to Michael Cærularius, Patriarch of Constantinople, he cites the &quot;Donatio&quot; to show that the Holy See possessed both an earthly and a heavenly ''imperium'', the royal priesthood.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WikisourceCatholicEncyclopedia1913&quot;&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle=Donation of Constantine}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Leo IX assured the Patriarch that the donation was completely genuine, not a fable or old wives' tale, so only the apostolic successor to Peter possessed that primacy and was the rightful head of all the Church. The Patriarch rejected the claims of papal primacy.

Michael was convinced to cool the debate and thus attempt to prevent the impending breach. However, Humbert and the Pope made no concessions, and Humbert was sent with legatine powers to the imperial capital to resolve the questions raised, once and for all. Humbert, [[Pope Stephen IX|Frederick of Lorraine]], and Peter, [[Archbishop of Amalfi]], arrived in April 1054 and were met with a hostile reception; they stormed out of the palace, leaving the papal response with Michael, who in turn was even more angered by their actions. The patriarch refused to recognize their authority or, practically, their existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first =John J. |last= Norwich |title=The Normans in the South 1016–1130 |year=1967 |page=102}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Pope Leo died on 19 April 1054, the legates' authority legally ceased, but they effectively ignored this technicality.&lt;ref name=NorwichApogee&gt;{{Cite book|first =John J. |last= Norwich |title=Byzantium, The Apogee |year=1992 |pages=320–321}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to Michael's refusal to address the issues at hand, the legatine mission took the extreme measure of entering the church of the [[Hagia Sophia]] during the Divine Liturgy and placing a bull of [[excommunication]] on the altar.

The consummation of the East–West Schism is thus generally dated from the year 1054, when this sequence of events took place. However, these events only triggered the beginning of the schism, and it was not actually consummated by the seemingly mutual excommunications. The New Catholic Encyclopedia reports that the legates had been careful not to intimate that the bull of excommunication implied a general excommunication of the Byzantine Church. The bull excommunicated only Patriarch Michael I, Leo of Achrida, and their adherents. Thus, the New Catholic Encyclopedia argues that the dispute need not have produced a permanent schism any more than excommunication of any &quot;contumacious bishop.&quot; The schism began to develop when all the other Eastern patriarchs supported Michael I. According to the New Catholic Encyclopedia, it was the support of Emperor [[Michael VI Stratiotikos]] that impelled them to support Michael I.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|quote=&quot;...in 1053 he [Michael Caerularius] sends off a declaration of war, then shuts up the Latin churches at Constantinople, hurls a string of wild accusations, and shows in every possible way that he wants a schism, apparently for the mere pleasure of not being in communion with the West. He got his wish. After a series of wanton aggressions, unparalleled in church history, after he had begun by striking the pope's name from his diptychs, the Roman legates excommunicated him (16 July 1054). But still there was no idea of a general excommunication of the Byzantine Church, still less of all the East. The legates carefully provided against that in their Bull. They acknowledged that the emperor (Constantine IX, who was excessively annoyed at the whole quarrel), the Senate, and the majority of the inhabitants of the city were &quot;most pious and orthodox.&quot; They excommunicated Caerularius, Leo of Achrida, and their adherents. This quarrel, too, need no more have produced a permanent state of schism than the excommunication of any other contumacious bishop. The real tragedy is that gradually all the other Eastern patriarchs took sides with Caerularius, obeyed him by striking the pope's name from their diptychs, and chose of their own accord to share his schism. At first they do not seem to have wanted to do so. John III of Antioch certainly refused to go into schism at Caerularius's bidding. But, eventually, the habit they had acquired of looking to Constantinople for orders proved too strong. The emperor (not Constantine IX, but his successor) was on the side of his patriarch and they had learned too well to consider the emperor as their over-lord in spiritual matters too. Again, it was the usurped authority of Constantinople, the Erastianism of the East that turned a personal quarrel into a great schism.&quot; |title=New Catholic Encyclopedia |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13535a.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some have questioned the validity of the bull on the grounds that Pope Leo IX had died at that time and so the authority of the legates to issue such a bull is unclear.&lt;ref name=NorwichApogee /&gt;

The legates left for Rome two days after issuing the bull of excommunication, leaving behind a city near riot. The patriarch had the immense support of the people against the emperor, who had supported the legates to his own detriment. To assuage popular anger, the bull was burnt, and the legates were [[anathema]]tized. Only the legates were anathematized and, in this case too, there was no explicit indication that the entire Western church was being anathematized.

The bull of excommunication issued against Patriarch Michael by the papal legates made 11 accusations against Michael and &quot;the backers of his foolishness&quot;, beginning with that of promoting to the episcopacy men who have been castrated and of rebaptizing those already baptized in the name of the Trinity, and ending with the accusation of refusing communion and baptism to menstruating women and of refusing to be in communion with those who tonsure their heads and shave their beards. Denial of the procession of the Holy Spirit from the Son (with no mention of the Nicene Creed) is given seventh place in this list of eleven.&lt;ref name=NorwichApogee /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acad.carleton.edu/curricular/MARS/Schism.pdf Text of the bull of excommunication]. (PDF) . Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aftermath of the mutual excommunications===
{{multiple image
 | direction = vertical
 | width = 200
 | footer = 
 | image1 = Expansion of christianity.jpg
 | alt1 = 
 | caption1 = Division between the Eastern and Western Churches in [http://rbedrosian.com/Maps/ahgh66b.htm Atlas of the Historical Geography of the Holy Land] 
 | image2 = Great Schism 1054 with former borders.png
 | alt2 = 
 | caption2 = The religious distribution in 1054, according to [http://home.comcast.net/~DiazStudents/MiddleAgesChurchMap1.jpg home.comcast.net] and Dragan Brujić, ''Guide to the Byzantine World''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cartileonline.eu/carte/1025738/dragan-brujia-vodia-kroz-svet-vizantijeDragan Brujić, ''Vodič kroz svet Vizantije'' (Beograd 2005)], p. 51&lt;/ref&gt;
 }}

At the time of the excommunications, many contemporary historians, including Byzantine chroniclers, did not consider the event significant.&lt;ref&gt;John Binns, ''An Introduction to the Christian Orthodox Churches'' (Cambridge University Press 2002 ISBN 978-0-521-66738-8), p. 203&lt;/ref&gt; Francis Dvornik stated: &quot;In spite of what happened in 1054, the faithful of both church remained long unaware of any change in their relations and acts of intercommunion were so numerous that 1054 as the date of the schism becomes inadmissible.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Eastern Churches Quarterly. Church History and Christian Reunion'', January–March 1945, pp. 29–30, quoted in [http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1&amp;q=archdale+king+intercommunion&amp;btnG= Archdale King, ''The Rites of Eastern Christendom'' (Gorgias Press 2007 ISBN 978-1-59333-391-1), vol. 1, p. 6]&lt;/ref&gt; Kallistos Ware agrees: &quot;Even after 1054 friendly relations between East and West continued. The two parts of Christendom were not yet conscious of a great gulf of separation between them. … The dispute remained something of which ordinary Christians in the East and West were largely unaware.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bishop Kallistos (Ware), p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; The Russian Church felt so little separated from the Western that it instituted a liturgical feast to commemorate the largely violent transfer of the relics of Saint [[Nicholas of Myra]] from Asia to [[Bari]] in Italy in 1089.&lt;ref&gt;Dimiti Obolensky, ''Byzantium and the Slavs'' (St Vladimir's Seminary Press 1994 ISBN 978-0-88141-008-2), pp. 94–95&lt;/ref&gt; This fluidity explains in part the different interpretations of the geographical line of division in the two maps given here, one drawn up in the West, the other in a country where Eastern Orthodoxy predominates. Areas such as the extreme south of Italy are interpreted variously as adhering to either East or West. And even in areas whose rulers took one position, there were some who gave their allegiance to the other side. An example is [[Kingdom of Hungary]], where the Roman Catholic Church was upheld by the crown from the time of [[Stephen I of Hungary|Stephen I]], but &quot;monasteries and convents belonging to the Byzantine Church were founded sporadically in the eleventh century.&lt;ref&gt;Lövei&lt;/ref&gt;

Efforts were made in subsequent centuries by Popes and Patriarchs to heal the rift between the churches. However, a number of factors and historical events worked to widen the separation over time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Pnkxofhi4mQC&amp;pg=PA596|first=Clarence |title=The Oxford Handbook of Byzantine Studies |page=596|publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2008 |ISBN=978-0-19-925246-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fourth Crusade and other military conflicts===
{{Main|Fourth Crusade|Siege of Constantinople (1204)|Northern Crusades}}
{{See also|Massacre of the Latins}}
The participants (crusaders and Venetians) in the [[Fourth Crusade]] captured and sacked [[Constantinople]] in 1204,&lt;ref name=&quot;ccel.org&quot;&gt;During the Crusades the schism was deepened by the brutal atrocities of the French and Venetian soldiers in the pillage of Constantinople (1204), the establishment of a Latin empire, and the appointment by the pope of Latin bishops in Greek sees.318 Although this artificial empire lasted only half a century (1204–1261), it left a legacy of burning hatred in the memories of horrible desecrations and innumerable insults and outrages, which the East had to endure from the Western barbarians. Churches and monasteries were robbed and desecrated, the Greek service mocked, the clergy persecuted, and every law of decency set at defiance. In Constantinople &quot;a prostitute was seated on the throne of the patriarch; and that daughter of Belial, as she is styled, sung and danced in the church to ridicule the hymns and processions of the Orientals.&quot; Even Pope Innocent III. accuses the pilgrims that they spared in their lust neither age nor sex, nor religious profession, and that they committed fornication, adultery, and incest in open day (in oculis omnium), &quot;abandoning matrons and virgins dedicated to God to the lewdness of grooms.&quot; And yet this great pope insulted the Eastern church by the establishment of a Latin hierarchy on the ruins of the Byzantine empire.[http://www.ccel.org/s/schaff/history/4_ch05.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; looting [[Hagia Sophia|The Church of Holy Wisdom]] and various other Orthodox holy sites, and converting them to Latin Catholic worship. Various holy artifacts from these Orthodox holy places were then taken to the West. The victors set up in what had been the empire's territory a number of feudal [[crusader states]], of which the most important was the [[Latin Empire]] of Constantinople, thus initiating the period of Greek history known as [[Frangokratia]] (dominion by the Franks). The break-up of the Byzantine Empire is seen as a factor that led to its conquest by Islam. The crusaders also appointed a [[Latin Patriarch of Constantinople]]. An attempt by the Latin Empire to capture the city of [[Edirne|Adrianople]], then a [[Bulgaria]]n possession, was defeated in the [[Battle of Adrianople (1205)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ccel.org&quot;/&gt;

In northern Europe, the [[Teutonic Knights]], after their successes in the [[northern crusades]],&lt;ref name=Christiansen&gt;{{Cite book|last=Christiansen|first=Erik|title=The Northern Crusades|year=1997|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|page=287|isbn=0-14-026653-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; attempted to conquer also the [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] [[Russia]]n Republics of [[Pskov Republic|Pskov]] and [[Novgorod Republic|Novgorod]], an enterprise endorsed by [[Pope Gregory IX]].&lt;ref name=Christiansen/&gt; One of the major defeats they suffered was the [[Battle of the Ice]] in 1242. [[Sweden]] also undertook several [[Swedish-Novgorodian Wars|campaigns against Orthodox Novgorod]]. There were also conflicts between Catholic [[Poland]] and Orthodox Russia. Such conflicts solidified the schism between East and West.

===Reunion attempts===
The [[Second Council of Lyon]] was convoked to act on a pledge by Byzantine emperor [[Michael VIII Palaiologos|Michael VIII]] to reunite the Western and Eastern churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;World History&quot;&gt;Wetterau, Bruce. World history. New York: Henry Holt and company. 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; Wishing to end the Great Schism that divided [[Rome]] and [[Constantinople]], Gregory X had sent an embassy to Michael VIII Palaeologus. On 29 June 1274, Gregory X celebrated a [[Mass]] in St John's Church, where both sides took part. The council declared that the Roman church possessed “the supreme and full primacy and authority over the universal Catholic Church.” The council was seemingly a success, but did not provide a lasting solution to the schism; the Emperor was anxious to heal the schism, but the Eastern clergy proved to be obstinate. Michael VII's son and successor [[Andronikos II Palaiologos|Andronicus II]] repudiated the union.

In the 15th century, the eastern emperor [[John VIII Palaeologus]], pressed hard by the [[Ottoman Turks]], was keen to ally himself with the West, and to do so he arranged with [[Pope Eugene IV]] for discussions about reunion to be held again, this time at the [[Council of Ferrara-Florence]]. After several long discussions, the emperor managed to convince the Eastern representatives to accept the Western doctrines of Filioque, Purgatory and the supremacy of the Papacy. On 6 June 1439 an agreement was signed by all the Eastern bishops present but one, [[Mark of Ephesus]], who held that Rome continued in both [[heresy]] and [[Schism (religion)|schism]]. It seemed that the Great Schism had been ended. However, upon their return, the Eastern bishops found their agreement with the West broadly rejected by the populace and by civil authorities (with the notable exception of the Emperors of the East who remained committed to union until the [[Fall of Constantinople]] two decades later). The union signed at Florence has never been accepted by the Eastern churches.

===Fall of Constantinople===
{{Main|Fall of Constantinople}}
In 1453, the [[Eastern Roman Empire]] fell to the [[Ottoman Empire]]. But Orthodoxy was still very strong in [[Russia]] which became autocephalous (since 1448, although this was not officially accepted by Constantinople until 1589); and thus [[Moscow]] called itself the [[Third Rome]], as the cultural heir of [[Constantinople]].{{Citation needed|{{15 August 2012}}|date=August 2012}}

Eastern Christians expressed a belief that the Fall of Constantinople was God's punishment for the Emperor and clergy accepting the West's doctrines of Filioque, Purgatory, and the supremacy of the Papacy.{{Citation needed|{{15 August 2012}}|date=August 2012}} The West did not fulfill its promise to the Eastern Emperor of troops and support if he agreed to the reconciliation. The [[Sack of Constantinople]] is still considered proof by the East that the West ultimately succeeded in its endeavor to destroy the East.{{Citation needed|{{15 August 2012}}|date=August 2012}}

Under Ottoman rule, the Orthodox Church acquired power as an autonomous millet. The ecumenical patriarch was the religious and administrative ruler of the entire [[Millet (Ottoman Empire)#Orthodox Christians|Rum Millet]] (Ottoman administrative unit), which encompassed all the Eastern Orthodox subjects of the Empire. Those appointed to the role were chosen by the Muslim State. In fact, [[Mehmed II]] when he conquered the City formally assumed the legal function of the Byzantine Emperors, and the appointment of the patriarch [[Gennadius II]]. Mehmed and his agents did all they could to stamp out pro-Roman parties among the Greek Christians, and to that end Mehmed enormously strengthened the Greek church, as this helped to protect the Ottoman Sultunate from any united Christian foe.{{Citation needed|{{15 August 2012}}|date=August 2012}}

As a result of the Ottoman conquest, the entire Orthodox communion of the Balkans and the Near East became suddenly isolated from the West. For the next four hundred years, it would be confined within the Islamic world, with which it had little in common religiously or culturally. The [[Russian Orthodox Church]] and the Orthodox Churches from [[Wallachia]] and [[Moldavia]] were the only part of the Orthodox communion that remained outside the control of the Ottoman Empire.

===Rise of the Church of Moscow===
The growing might of the [[Grand Duchy of Moscow|Moscow]] contributed also to the growing authority of the Autocephalous Russian Church. In 1589, Metropolitan Job of Moscow became the first Patriarch of Moscow and All Rus'; making the Russian Church one of the five honorable Patriarchates.

However, in 1721 Tsar Peter I abolished completely the patriarchate and so the Church effectively became a department of the government, ruled by a Most Holy Synod composed of senior bishops and lay bureaucrats appointed by the Tsar himself. An independent (from the state) patriarchate was reestablished in 1917, but after the death in 1925 of Patriarch [[Tikhon of Moscow]], who had been persecuted by the Soviet authorities, the patriarchate remained vacant until 1943, when, during the Second World War, the Soviet government allowed somewhat greater freedom to the Church.

===Eastern Catholicism===
{{See also|Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches|Union of Brest|Union of Uzhhorod}}

The [[Eastern Catholic Churches]] consider themselves to have reconciled the East and West Schism by keeping their prayers and rituals similar to those of Eastern Orthodoxy, while also accepting the primacy of the Bishop of Rome. Some Eastern Orthodox charge that joining in this unity comes at the expense of ignoring critical doctrinal differences and past atrocities.

Since the beginnings of the Uniate movement, there have been periodic conflicts between the Orthodox and Uniate in [[Ukraine]] and [[Belarus]], then under [[Poland|Polish]] rule,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Dimitry Pospielovsky |title=The Orthodox Church in the History of Russia |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2cP0wc_E6yEC&amp;pg=PA96 |accessdate=2 June 2012 |year=1998 |publisher=St Vladimir's Seminary Press |isbn=978-0-88141-179-9 |pages=96–}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later also in [[Transylvania]] (see the [[Romanian Church United with Rome]]). During [[Russia]]'s [[Time of Troubles]] there was a [[Polish-Muscovite War (1605–1618)|plan]] by the conquering Polish monarchy (of [[Latin Rite]], not Uniate) to convert all of Russia to Roman Catholicism.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} The Russian national holiday, [[Unity Day (Russia)|Unity Day]], was established due to this conflict. [[Patriarch Hermogenes]] was martyred by the Poles and their supporters during this period (see also [[Polish-Lithuanian-Muscovite Commonwealth]]).&lt;ref&gt;Reverend R Thornton. ''Lives of Eminent Russian Prelates''. Kessinger Publishing, 2004. ISBN 1-4179-4649-0. Page 3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;He endured to the end and was accounted worthy of the crown of martyrdom: inflexible alike to prayers and threats, he was starved to death in prison, to be a pledge of deliverance to his country&quot;. – A N Mouravieff. ''A History of the Church of Russia'', 1842, reprinted 2004. ISBN 1-4179-1250-2. Page 166.&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar pressure was also used by the Orthodox against Eastern Catholic Churches such as the [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.risu.org.ua/eng/major.religions/greek.catholic/historical.survey/ The Ukrainian Greek Catholics: A Historical Survey]. Risu.org.ua. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

At a meeting in Balamand, [[Lebanon]] in June 1993, the Joint International Commission for the Theological Dialogue between the Roman Catholic Church and the Orthodox Church the delegates of the Eastern Orthodox Churches declared &quot;...and that what has been called '[[uniatism]]' ''can no longer be accepted either as a method to be followed nor as a model of the unity our Churches are seeking&quot;'' (section 12 of the [http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/ecumenism/balamand_txt.aspx document]).

At the same time, the Commission stated:
* Concerning the Eastern Catholic Churches, it is clear that they, as part of the Catholic Communion, have the right to exist and to act in response to the spiritual needs of their faithful.
* The Oriental Catholic Churches who have desired to re-establish full communion with the See of Rome and have remained faithful to it, have the rights and obligations which are connected with this communion.

===First Vatican Council===
The doctrine of papal primacy was further developed in 1870 at the [[First Vatican Council]] which declared that &quot;in the disposition of God the Roman church holds the preeminence of ordinary power over all the other churches&quot;. This council also affirmed the dogma of [[papal infallibility]], declaring that the infallibility of the Christian community extends to the pope himself, when he defines a doctrine concerning faith or morals to be held by the whole Church.

==Prospects for reconciliation==

Despite efforts on the part of Catholic Popes and Orthodox Patriarchs to heal the schism, only limited progress towards reconciliation has been made over the last half century. One stumbling block is the fact that the Orthodox and the Catholics have different perceptions of the nature of the divide.  The official Catholic teaching is that the Orthodox are schismatic meaning that there is nothing heretical about their theology, only their unwillingness to accept the [[Papal supremacy|supremacy of the Pope]] which is presented in Catholic teaching as an ecclesiological issue, not a theological one. With respect to Primacy of the Pope, the two churches agree that the Pope, as Bishop of Rome, has primacy although they continue to have different interpretations of what that primacy entails. 

The Roman Catholic Church's attitude was expressed by [[Pope John Paul II]] in the image of the Church &quot;breathing with her two lungs&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;“I, myself, have often spoken of the ‘two lungs’ – the East and the West – without which Europe could not breathe. There will be no peaceful Europe in the future, nor one whose civilization will shine forth, without this osmosis and this sharing of values which are different yet complementary. It is on this ‘humus’ that the Europeans are called to build up their common house” (John Paul II 22 December 1989)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/encyclicals/documents/hf_jp-ii_enc_25051995_ut-unum-sint_en.htmlEncyciclical ''Ut unum sint''], 54&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19901018_sacri-canones_lt.htmlApostolic Constitution '&amp;#39;Sacri Canones'&amp;#39;]. Vatican.va (1930-04-02). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; He meant that there should be a combination of the more rational, juridical, organisation-minded &quot;Latin&quot; temperament with the intuitive, mystical and contemplative spirit found in the east.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/apr/02/guardianobituaries.catholicismObituary of Pope John Paul II]. Guardian (2005-04-02). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ecclesiological reconciliation===

The Eastern Orthodox insist that the primacy is largely one of honor, the Pope being &quot;[[first among equals]]&quot; ''primus inter pares''. The Catholic Church, on the other hand, insists on the doctrine of Supremacy. It is widely understood that, if there is to be reconciliation, both sides will have to compromise on this doctrine. Although some commentators have proposed ways in which such compromise can be achieved, there is no official indication that such compromise is being contemplated.

In his book ''Principles of Catholic Theology'', Pope Benedict XVI (then Cardinal Ratzinger) assessed the range of &quot;possibilities that are open to Christian ecumenism.&quot;  He characterized the &quot;maximum demand&quot; of the West as the recognition by the East of and submission to the &quot;primacy of the bishop of Rome in the full scope of the definition of 1870...&quot;  The &quot;maximum demand&quot; of the East was described as a declaration by the West of the 1870 doctrine of papal primacy as erroneous along with the &quot;removal of the Filioque from the Creed and including the Marian dogmas of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.&quot;  Ratzinger asserted that &quot;(n)one of the maximum solutions offers any real hope of unity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleenewerck2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Cleenewerck|first=Laurent |title=His Broken Body: Understanding and Healing the Schism Between the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oeKOUb6OcG4C&amp;pg=PA120|accessdate=27 October 2012|date=1 January 2008|publisher=Euclid University Press|isbn=978-0-615-18361-9|page=120}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Ratzinger wrote that, &quot;Rome must not require more from the East than had been formulated and what was lived in the first millenium.&quot;  He concluded that, &quot; Reunion could take place in this context if, on the one hand, the East would cease to oppose as heretical the developments that took place in the West in the second millennium and would accept the Catholic Church as legitimate and orthodox in the form she had acquired in the course of that development, while on the other hand, the West would recognize the Church of the East as orthodox in the form she has always had.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RatzingerBoeve2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Ratzinger|first1=Joseph |last2=Boeve|first2=Lieven|last3=Mannion|first3=Gerard |title=The Ratzinger Reader: Mapping a Theological Journey|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=pEaxgHlMQbcC&amp;pg=PA162|accessdate=27 October 2012|date=8 July 2010|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-567-03214-0|page=162}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[declaration of Ravenna]] in 2007 re-asserted the belief that the bishop of Rome is indeed the ''protos'', although future discussions are to be held on the concrete ecclesiological exercise of papal primacy.

===Theological reconciliation===

{{refimprove section|date=October 2012}}

Jeffrey D. Finch asserts that &quot;the future of East-West rapprochement appears to be overcoming the modern polemics of neo-scholasticism and neo-Palamism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Michael J. Christensen |author2=Jeffery A. Wittung|title=Partakers of the Divine Nature: The History and Development of Deificiation in the Christian Traditions|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DgtUoMqm594C&amp;pg=PA244 |accessdate=2 June 2012 |date=31 January 2007|publisher=Fairleigh Dickinson Univ Press |isbn=978-0-8386-4111-8 |page=244}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eastern Orthodox reject the rational and philosophical foundations of Western Christianity as pagan and heretical and assert that until the Western Church learns to see God and know God as the Eastern Church does, there cannot be even the remotest possibility of reconciliation.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}}

These doctrinal issues center around the Orthodox perception that the Catholic theologians lack the actual experience of God called [[theoria]] and thereby fail to understand the importance of the Heart as [[Noetic]] or Intuitive faculty. It is what they consider to be the Catholic Church's reliance on pagan metaphysical philosophy and rational methods such as[[scholasticism]] rather than on intuitive experience of God (theoria) that causes Orthodox to consider the Catholic Church heretical. Other points of doctrinal difference include a difference regarding human nature as well as a difference regarding[[original sin]], [[purgatory]] and the [[Hell in Christian beliefs|nature of Hell]].

The most frequently discussed point of theological difference is embodied in the dispute regarding the inclusion of the [[Filioque]] in the Nicene Creed. In the view of the Roman Catholic Church, what it calls the legitimate complementarity of the expressions &quot;from the Father&quot; and &quot;from the Father and the Son&quot; does not, provided it does not become rigid, affect the identity of faith in the reality of the same mystery confessed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/_P17.HTM#XTCatechism of the Catholic Church, 248]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; The Orthodox, on the other hand, view inclusion of the phrase to be almost heretical (see also the [[East–West Schism#Trinity|Trinity section]]).

More importantly, the Orthodox see the Filioque as just the tip of the iceberg and really just a symptom of a much more deeply rooted problem of theology, one so deeply rooted that they consider it to be heretical and even, by some characterizations, an inability to &quot;see God&quot; and know God. This heresy is allegedly rooted in [[Frankish mythology|Frankish paganism]], [[Arianism]],[[Platonism|Platonist]] and [[Aristotelianism|Aristotelian]] philosophy and [[Thomas Aquinas|Thomist]] rational and objective[[Scholasticism]]. In opposition to what they characterize as pagan, heretical and &quot;godless&quot; foundations, the Orthodox rely on an intuitive and mystical knowledge and vision of God ([[Theoria]]) based on [[Hesychasm]] and [[noesis]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}}
While Catholics accept the Eastern Orthodox intuitive and mystical understanding of God as valid,{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} they consider it to be complementary to the rational and philosophical [[Scholasticism]] of [[Thomas Aquinas]].

====Sacraments====
Most Orthodox Churches through [[Economy (religion)|economy]] do not require Baptism in the Orthodox Church for one who has been previously baptized in the Roman Catholic Church. Most Orthodox jurisdictions, based on that same principle of economy, allow a sacramental marriage between an Orthodox Christian and some non-Orthodox Christians.
The Catholic Church allows its clergy to administer the sacraments of Penance, the Eucharist and Anointing of the Sick to members of the Eastern Orthodox Church, if these spontaneously ask for the sacraments and are properly disposed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/general-docs/rc_pc_chrstuni_doc_19930325_directory_en.html''Directory for the Application of Principles and Norms on Ecumenism'', 125]; cf.[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P2S.HTM ''Code of Canon Law'', canon 844 §3] and [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_PIN.HTM ''Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches'', canon 671 §3]&lt;/ref&gt; It also allows Catholics who cannot approach a Catholic minister to receive these three sacraments from clergy of the Eastern Orthodox Church, whenever necessity requires or a genuine spiritual advantage commends it, and provided the danger of error or indifferentism is avoided.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/general-docs/rc_pc_chrstuni_doc_19930325_directory_en.html''Directory for the Application of Principles and Norms on Ecumenism'', 123]; cf.[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P2S.HTM ''Code of Canon Law'', canon 844 §2] and [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_PIN.HTM ''Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches'', canon 671 §2]&lt;/ref&gt; Catholic canon law allows marriage between a Catholic and an Orthodox.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_PML.HTM ''Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches'', canon 813] and [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P40.HTM ''Code of Canon Law'', canon 1124]&lt;/ref&gt; The Orthodox Church will only administer the sacraments to Christians who aren't Orthodox if there is an emergency.

The Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches authorizes the local Catholic bishop to permit a Catholic priest, of whatever rite, to bless the marriage of Orthodox faithful who being unable without great difficulty to approach a priest of their own Church, ask for this spontaneously.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_PN5.HTM '&amp;#39;Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches'&amp;#39;, canon 833]. Intratext.com (2007-05-04). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; In exceptional circumstances Catholics may, in the absence of an authorized priest, marry before witnesses. If a priest who is not authorized for the celebration of the marriage is available, he should be called in, although the marriage is valid even without his presence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P3Z.HTM ''Code of Canon Law'', canon 1116] and [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_PN4.HTM ''Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches'', canon 832]&lt;/ref&gt; The Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches specifies that, in those exceptional circumstances, even a &quot;non-Catholic&quot; priest (and so not necessarily one belonging to an Eastern Church) may be called in.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_PN4.HTM '&amp;#39;Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches'&amp;#39;, canon 832]. Intratext.com (2007-05-04). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recent efforts at reconciliation==

Patriarchs of the Eastern Orthodox Church have shown a willingness to work with successive Popes of the Catholic Church in joint ecumenical efforts. A Joint Theological Commission meets regularly to identify areas where progress is needed in order to achieve reconciliation.

===Second Vatican Council===
A major event of the [[Second Vatican Council]], known as Vatican II, was the issuance by Pope Paul VI and Orthodox [[Patriarch Athenagoras]] of a joint expression of regret for many of the past actions that had led up to the Great Schism between the Western and Eastern churches, expressed as the [[Catholic-Orthodox Joint Declaration of 1965]]. At the same time, they lifted the mutual excommunications dating from the eleventh century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/speeches/1965/documents/hf_p-vi_spe_19651207_common-declaration_en.html |title=JOINT CATHOLIC-ORTHODOX DECLARATION OF HIS HOLINESS POPE PAUL VI AND THE ECUMENICAL PATRIARCH ATHENAGORAS I}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Joint Theological Commission===
{{Expand section|date=February 2009}}

The [[Joint International Commission for Theological Dialogue Between the Catholic Church and the Orthodox Church]] first met in Rhodes in 1980.

===Other moves toward reconciliation===

On a number of occasions, [[Pope John Paul II]] recited the Nicene Creed several times with patriarchs of the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] in [[Greek language|Greek]] according to the original text.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usccb.org/beliefs-and-teachings/dialogue-with-others/ecumenical/orthodox/filioque-church-dividing-issue-english.cfmAgreed Statement of the North American Orthodox-Catholic Theological Consultation, 25 October 2003]. Retrieved on 2012-10-17.&lt;/ref&gt; Both he and his successor, [[Pope Benedict XVI]], have recited the Nicene Creed jointly with Patriarchs [[Patriarch Demetrius I of Constantinople|Demetrius I]] and [[Bartholomew I]] in Greek without the ''Filioque'' clause.&lt;ref name=&quot;programme of the celebration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Video recording of joint recitation&quot;/&gt; 

In June 1995, [[Patriarch Bartholomew I]], who was elected as the 273rd [[Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople]] in October 1991, visited the [[Vatican City|Vatican]] for the first time, when he joined in the historic inter-religious day of prayer for peace at Assisi. Pope John Paul II and the Patriarch explicitly stated their mutual &quot;desire to relegate the excommunications of the past to oblivion and to set out on the way to re-establishing full communion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/PAPALDOC/BARTHDEC.HTM Common Declaration]. Ewtn.com (1995-06-29). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1999, [[John Paul II]] was the first pope since the Great Schism to visit an Eastern Orthodox country: [[Romania]]. Upon greeting John Paul II, the Romanian Patriarch [[Teoctist Arăpaşu|Teoctist]] stated: &quot;The second millennium of Christian history began with a painful wounding of the unity of the Church; the end of this millennium has seen a real commitment to restoring Christian unity.&quot; Pope John Paul II visited other heavily Orthodox areas such as [[Ukraine]], despite lack of welcome at times, and he said that healing the divisions between Western and Eastern Christianity was one of his fondest wishes.

In June 2004, the [[Ecumenical Patriarch]] Bartholomew I's visit to Rome for the [[Feast of Saints Peter and Paul]] (29 June) afforded him the opportunity for another personal meeting with Pope John Paul II, for conversations with the [[Pontifical Council for Promoting Christian Unity]] and for taking part in the celebration for the feast day in [[St. Peter's Basilica]].

The Patriarch's partial participation in the Eucharistic liturgy at which the Pope presided followed the program of the past visits of Patriarch Dimitrios (1987) and [[Patriarch Bartholomew I]] himself: full participation in the [[Liturgy of the Word]], joint proclamation by the Pope and by the Patriarch of the profession of faith according to the [[Nicene-Constantinopolitan Creed]] in Greek and as the conclusion, the final Blessing imparted by both the Pope and the Patriarch at the Altar of the Confessio.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/Theology/CATORT04.HTM Report on Catholic-Orthodox Relations]. Ewtn.com. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; The Patriarch did not fully participate in the Liturgy of the Eucharist involving the consecration and distribution of the [[Eucharist]] itself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/2004/documents/ns_lit_doc_20040629_rite_en.html Presentation of the Celebration]. Vatican.va (2004-06-29). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/speeches/2004/july/documents/hf_jp-ii_spe_20040701_jp-ii-bartholomew-i_en.html Common Declaration]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

In accordance with the Roman Catholic Church's practice of including the clause when reciting the Creed in Latin,&lt;ref&gt;Missale Romanum 2002 (Roman Missal in Latin), p. 513&lt;/ref&gt; but not when reciting the Creed in Greek,&lt;ref&gt;Ρωμαϊκό Λειτουργικό 2006 (Roman Missal in Greek), vol. 1, p. 347&lt;/ref&gt; Popes [[John Paul II]] and [[Benedict XVI]] have recited the Nicene Creed jointly with Patriarchs [[Patriarch Demetrius I of Constantinople|Demetrius I]] and [[Bartholomew I]] in Greek without the ''[[Filioque]]'' clause.&lt;ref name=&quot;programme of the celebration&quot;&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/2004/documents/ns_lit_doc_20040629_rite_en.html programme of the celebration]. Vatican.va (2004-06-29). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Video recording of joint recitation&quot;&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_MFg8FBOHDg Video recording of joint recitation]. Youtube.com. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism of reconciliation efforts===

The efforts of Orthodox patriarchs towards reconciliation with the Catholic Church has been strongly criticized by some elements of Eastern Orthodoxy, such as the Metropolitan of Kalavryta, Greece, in November 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mkka.blogspot.com/ The Metropolitan's own blog], reported also by [http://www.romfea.gr/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1932 this Religious News Agency] and the [http://web.archive.org/web/20090223192934/http://www.roacamerica.org/art-kiss-demetrios-latest.shtml Russian Orthodox]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mkka.blogspot.com/ The Metropolitan's own blog]. Mkka.blogspot.com. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090317064414/http://www.romfea.gr/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1932 Ο Πάπας, ο Πατριάρχης και η…ένωση των εκκλησιών]. romfea.gr&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roacamerica.org/art-kiss-demetrios-latest.shtml The kiss of Judas]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, Patriarch Bartholomew I issued an encyclical lauding the ongoing dialogue between the Orthodox Church and other Christian churches and criticizing those who are “unacceptably fanatical” in challenging such dialogue. The encyclical lamented that the dialogues between the two churches were being criticized in “an unacceptably fanatical way” by some who claim to be defenders of Orthodoxy despite the fact that these dialogues are being conducted “with the mutual agreement and participation of all local Orthodox Churches”. The Patriarch warned that &quot;such opponents raise themselves above episcopal synods and risk creating schisms&quot;. He further accused some critics of distorting reality to “deceive and arouse the faithful” and of depicting theological dialogue not as a pan-Orthodox effort, but an effort of the Ecumenical Patriarchate alone. As an example, he pointed to &quot;false rumors that union between the Roman Catholic and Orthodox Churches is imminent&quot; claiming that the disseminators of such rumors were fully aware that &quot;the differences discussed in these theological dialogues remain numerous and require lengthy debate&quot;. The Patriarch re-emphasized that &quot;union is not decided by theological commissions but by Church Synods&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Patriarch of Constantinople’s new encyclical defends Catholic-Orthodox dialogue |publisher=Catholic News Agency |date=Feb. 20, 2010 |accessdate=2011-01-27 |url=http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/news/patriarch_of_constantinoples_new_encyclical_defends_catholic-orthodox_dialogue/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Differences underlying the schism==

Jaroslav Pelikan emphasizes that &quot;while the East-West schism stemmed largely from political and ecclesiastical discord, this discord also reflected basic theological differences&quot;.  Pelikan further argues that the antagonists in the 11th century inappropriately exaggerated their theological differences whereas  modern historians tend to minimize them.  Pelikan asserts that the documents from that era evidence the &quot;depths of intellectual alienation that had developed between the two sections of Christendom.&quot;  While the two sides were technically more guilty of schism than heresy, they often charged each other with allegations of heresy.  Pelikan describes much of the dispute as dealing with &quot;regional differences in usages and customs&quot; some of which were adiaphorus (i.e. neither right nor wrong).  However, he goes on to say that while it was easy in principle to accept the existence of adiaphora, it was difficult in actual practice to distinguish customs which were innocuously adiaphoric from those that had doctrinal implications.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pelikan1977&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Pelikan |first=Jaroslav |title=The Christian Tradition: A History of the Development of Doctrine, Volume 2: The Spirit of Eastern Christendom (600-1700)|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Lr3ebI4iiwcC&amp;pg=PA170 |accessdate=26 October 2012 |date=15 July 1977|publisher=University of Chicago Press |ISBN=978-0-226-65373-0 |pages=170–171}}&lt;/ref&gt;



It is the position of Orthodox Christianity that Roman Catholic arguments in support of its teachings have relied on proofs from Fathers that have either been misinterpreted or so taken out of context as to misrepresent their true intent. It is the position of Orthodox Christianity that a closer examination of those supposed supports would have the effect of either not supporting the argument or have the opposite effect of supporting the counter-argument.

===Cultural differences===

The dominant language of the West was [[Latin]], whilst that of the East was [[Greek language|Greek]]. Soon after the fall of the Western Empire, the number of individuals who spoke both Latin and Greek began to dwindle, andcommunication between East and West grew much more difficult. With linguistic unity gone, cultural unity began to crumble  as well. The two halves of the Church were naturally divided along similar lines; they developed different [[rite]]s and had different approaches to religious doctrines. Although the Great Schism was still centuries away, its outlines were already perceptible.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orthodox.org.ph/content/view/211/50/ Orthodox Church in the Philippines – East-West Schism 01]. Orthodox.org.ph. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ecclesiological disputes===

Philip Sherrard, an Orthodox theologian asserts that the underlying cause of the East- West schism was and continues to be &quot;the clash of these two fundamentally irreconcilable ecclesiologies.&quot;  While some Catholics have adopted this view of papal primacy, it is more common for Catholics to insist on the primacy of Roman and papal authority based on patristic writings and conciliar documents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shaw2000&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Shaw|first=Russell B.|title=Papal Primacy in the Third Millennium|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fgJE4JweJBkC&amp;pg=PA40|accessdate=26 October 2012|year=2000|publisher=Our Sunday Visitor Publishing|isbn=978-0-87973-555-5|page=40}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Roger Haight characterizes the question of episcopal authority in the Church as &quot;acute&quot; with the &quot;relative standings of Rome and Constantinople a recurrent source of tension.&quot; Haight characterizes the difference in ecclesiologies as &quot;the contrast between a pope with universal jurisdiction and a combination of patriarchal superstructure with an episcopal and synodal communion ecclesiology analogous to that found in Cyprian.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Haight2004.p289&quot; /&gt; 

However, [[Nicholas Afansiev]] has criticized both the Catholic and Orthodox churches for &quot;subscribing to the universal ecclesiology of St. Cyprian of Carthage according to which only one true and universal church can exist.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DoyleBazzell2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Doyle|first1=Dennis |last2=Bazzell|first2=Pascal D.|last3=Furry|first3=Timothy J.|title=Ecclesiology and Exclusion: Boundaries of Being and Belonging in Postmodern Times|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=K_lvImfHGhYC&amp;pg=PA311|accessdate=27 October 2012|date=1 September 2012|publisher=Orbis Books|isbn=978-1-57075-982-6|page=311}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ecclesiological structure====
{{See also|Primacy of the Roman Pontiff|Eastern Orthodox Church organization}}

Haight characterizes the difference in ecclesiologies as &quot;the contrast between a pope with universal jurisdiction and a combination of patriarchal superstructure with an episcopal and synodal communion ecclesiology analogous to that found in Cyprian.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Haight2004.p290&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Haight|first=Roger D. |title=Christian Community in History Volume 1: Historical Ecclesiology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=EDzSaqXK-aEC&amp;pg=PA289|accessdate=26 October 2012|date=16 September 2004|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-8264-1630-8|page=290}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eastern Churches maintained the idea that every local city-church with its bishop, presbyters, deacons and people celebrating the [[Eucharist]] constituted the whole Church. In this view called Eucharistic ecclesiology (or more recently holographic ecclesiology), every bishop is [[Saint Peter]]'s successor in his church (&quot;the Church&quot;) and the churches form what [[Eusebius of Caesarea|Eusebius]] called a common union of churches. This implied that all bishops were ontologically equal, although functionally particular bishops could be granted special privileges by other bishops and serve as metropolitans, archbishops or patriarchs. Early on, the ecclesiology of the Roman Church was universal in nature, with the idea that the Church was a worldwide organism with a divinely (not functionally) appointed center: the Church/Bishop of Rome.

&quot;The Orthodox Church does not accept the doctrine of Papal authority set forth in the Vatican Council of 1870, and taught today in the Roman Catholic Church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Kallistos Ware]] The Orthodox Church [http://books.google.com/books?id=f7D-5Q-Q19MC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;dq=%22The+Orthodox+Church+does+not+accept+the+doctrine+of+Papal+authority+set+forth+in+the+Vatican+Council+of+1870,+and+taught+today+in+the+Roman+Catholic+Church.%22&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=%22The%20Orthodox%20Church%20does%20not%20accept%20the%20doctrine%20of%20Papal%20authority%20set%20forth%20in%20the%20Vatican%20Council%20of%201870%2C%20and%20taught%20today%20in%20the%20Roman%20Catholic%20Church.%22&amp;f=true]&lt;/ref&gt; The Orthodox Church has always maintained the original position of [[collegiality]] of the bishops resulting in the structure of the church being closer to a[[Confederation|confederacy]] in structure.&lt;ref&gt;Quoting Aleksey Khomyakov p. 87 The legal formalism and logical rationalism of the Roman Catholic Church have their roots in the Roman State. These features developed in it more strongly than ever when the Western Church without consent of the Eastern introduced into the Nicean Creed the filioque clause. Such arbitrary change of the creed is an expression of pride and lack of love for one's brethren in the faith. &quot;In order not to be regarded as a schism by the Church, Romanism was forced to ascribe to the bishop of Rome absolute infallibility.&quot; In this way Catholicism broke away from the Church as a whole and became an organization based upon external authority. Its unity is similar to the unity of the state: it is not super-rational but rationalistic and legally formal. Rationalism has led to the doctrine of the works of superarogation, established a balance of duties and merits between God and man, weighing in the scales sins and prayers, trespasses and deeds of expiation; it adopted the idea of transferring one person's debts or credits to another and legalized the exchange of assumed merits; in short, it introduced into the sanctuary of faith the mechanism of a banking house. History of Russian Philosophy by Nikolai LosskyISBN 978-0-8236-8074-0 p. 87&lt;/ref&gt; The Orthodox have [[synod]]s where the highest authorities in each Church community are brought together, but unlike Roman Catholicism no central individual or figure has the absolute and infallible last word on church doctrine. In practice, this has sometimes led to divisions among Greek, Russian, Bulgarian and Ukrainian Orthodox churches, as no central authority can serve as a rallying point for various internal disputes. The [[Second Vatican Council]] has re-asserted the importance of collegiality to a degree that appears satisfying to most if not all ecclesial parties.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

====Papal privilege and authority====
{{See also|Pseudo-Isidore|Donation of Constantine}}
The Roman Catholic Church's current official teachings about papal privilege and power that are unacceptable to the Eastern Orthodox churches are the dogma of the [[Papal infallibility|pope's infallibility]] when speaking officially &quot;from the chair of Peter (ex cathedra Petri)&quot; on matters of faith and morals to be held by the whole Church, so that such definitions are irreformable &quot;of themselves, and not by the consent of the Church&quot; (''ex sese et non ex consensu ecclesiae'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ewtn.com/library/COUNCILS/V1.htm#6 |title=Dogmatic Constitution on the Church of Christ, chapter 4}}&lt;/ref&gt; and have a binding character for all (Catholic) Christians in the world; the pope's direct episcopal jurisdiction over all (Catholic) Christians in the world; the pope's authority to appoint (and so also to depose){{Citation needed|date=January 2009|reason=Perhaps}} the bishops of all (Catholic) Christian churches except in the territory of a patriarchate;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_P51.HTM |title=Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches, canon 181}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the affirmation that the legitimacy and authority of all (Catholic) Christian bishops in the world derive from their union with the Roman see and its bishop, the Supreme Pontiff, the unique Successor of Peter and Vicar of Christ on earth.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009|reason=Perhaps, but [http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19641121_lumen-gentium_en.html''Lumen gentium''] says: &quot;The pastoral office or the habitual and daily care of their sheep is entrusted to them (the bishops) completely; nor are they to be regarded as vicars of the Roman Pontiffs, for they exercise an authority that is proper to them, and are quite correctly called 'prelates', heads of the people whom they govern.&quot;}}

Principal among the ecclesiastical issues that separate the two churches is the meaning of [[papal primacy]] within any future unified church. The Orthodox insist that it should be a &quot;primacy of honor&quot;, as in the ancient church and not a &quot;primacy of authority&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;as can be seen in the words of Archbishop [[Nicetas of Nicomedia]] of the Twelfth Century: “My dearest brother, we do not deny to the Roman Church the primacy among the five sister patriarchates and we recognize her right to the most honorable seat at the Ecumenical Council. But she has separated herself from us by her own deeds when through pride she assumed a monarchy which does not belong to her office… How shall we accept decrees from her that have been issued without consulting us and even without our knowledge? If the Roman pontiff seated on the lofty throne of his glory wished to thunder at us and, so to speak, hurl his mandates at us from on high and if he wishes to judge us and even to rule us and our churches, not by taking counsel with us but at his own arbitrary pleasure what kind of brotherhood, or even what kind of parenthood can this be? We should be the slaves not the sons, of such a church and the Roman see would not be the pious mother of sons but a hard and imperious mistress of slaves.”The Orthodox Church London by Ware, Kallistos St. Vladimir's Seminary Press 1995 ISBN 978-0-913836-58-3&lt;/ref&gt; whereas the Catholics see the pontiff's role as requiring for its exercise power and authority the exact form of which is open to discussion with other Christians.&lt;ref&gt;In 1995 Pope John Paul II wrote: &quot;With the power and the authority without which such an office would be illusory, the Bishop of Rome must ensure the communion of all the Churches.&quot; He invited &quot;Church leaders and their theologians to examine with me in a patient and fraternal dialogue on this subject, a dialogue in which, leaving useless controversies behind, we could listen to one another, keeping before us only the will of Christ for his Church and allowing ourselves to be deeply moved by his plea 'that they may all be one ... so that the world may believe that you have sent me' ([http://www.vatican.va/edocs/ENG0221/__PT.HTM Encyclical ''Ut unum sint''] section 96). The [http://orthodoxeurope.org/page/14/130.aspx#2 Ravenna document] of 13 October 2007 is one response to this invitation.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Orthodox belief, the test of catholicity is adherence to the authority of [[Religious text#Christianity|''Scripture'']] and then by the ''Holy Tradition'' of the church. It is not defined by adherence to any particular See. It is the position of the [[Orthodox Church]] that it has never accepted the pope as ''de jure'' leader of the entire church. All bishops are equal 'as Peter' therefore every church under every bishop (consecrated in apostolic succession) is fully complete (the original meaning of ''catholic'').{{cn|date=October 2012}}

Referring to Ignatius of Antioch&lt;ref&gt;Epistle to the Smyrnaeans - Chapter VIII.-Let Nothing Be Done Without the Bishop.&lt;/ref&gt;Carlton says
{{quote|&quot;Contrary to popular opinion, the word catholic does not mean &quot;universal&quot;; it means &quot;whole, complete, lacking nothing.&quot; ...Thus , to confess the Church to be catholic is to say that She possesses the fullness of the Christian faith. To say, however, that Orthodox and Rome constitute two lungs of the same Church is to deny that either Church separately is catholic in any meaningful sense of the term. This is not only contrary to the teaching of Orthodoxy, it is flatly contrary to the teaching of the Roman Catholic Church, which considered itself truly catholic&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
Carlton, C., (1999), &quot;The Truth: What Every Roman Catholic Should know about the Orthodox Church&quot;, (Regina Orthodox Press; Salisbury, MA), p22.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The church is in the image of the Trinity&lt;ref&gt;Lossky, V., (2002) ''The Mystical Theology of the Eastern Church'', (St Vladimirs Seminary Press; Crestwood, NY), p.176&lt;/ref&gt; and reflects the reality of the incarnation.
{{quote|&quot;The body of Christ must always be equal with itself…The local church which manifests the body of Christ cannot be subsumed into any larger organisation or collectivity which makes it more catholic and more in unity, for the simple reason that the principle of total catholicity and total unity is already intrinsic to it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sherrard, P., (1978) ''Church, Papacy and Schism: A Theological Enquiry.'' (Denise Harvey Publisher; Limni, Greece), p15&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Any changes to the understanding of the church would reflect a change in the understanding of the Trinity.

===Theological issues===

{{Main|Catholic - Orthodox theological differences|Contra Errores Graecorum}}

From the perspective of the Catholic Church, the ecclesiological issues are the central issue which is why they characterize the split between the two churches as a schism. In their view, the Eastern Orthodox are very close to them in theology and the Catholic Church does not consider the Orthodox beliefs to be heretical. However, from the perspective of Orthodox theologians, there are theological issues that run much deeper than just the theology around the primacy and/or supremacy of the Pope. In fact, unlike the Catholics who do not generally consider the Orthodox heretical, and speak instead about the Eastern &quot;schism&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13535a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia, '&amp;#39;The Eastern Schism'&amp;#39;]. Newadvent.org (1912-02-01). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; some prominent Orthodox theologians do consider the Catholic Church to be heretical on fundamental doctrinal issues of theology, such as the ''[[Filioque]]''.  These issues have a long history as can be seen in the 11th Century works of Orthodox theologian and saint [[Nikitas Stithatos]].

In the Roman Catholic Church too, some writers can be found who speak [[pejorative]]ly of the Eastern Orthodox Church and its theology, but these writers are marginal.&lt;ref&gt;An example is [http://www.traditioninaction.org/HotTopics/b004bht.htm Curiosities from the &quot;Orthodox&quot; Arena, by Atila Sinke Guimarães]&lt;/ref&gt; The official view of the Catholic Church is that expressed in the Decree ''Unitatis redintegratio'' of the [[Second Vatican Council]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;In the study of revelation East and West have followed different methods, and have developed differently their understanding and confession of God's truth. It is hardly surprising, then, if from time to time one tradition has come nearer to a full appreciation of some aspects of a mystery of revelation than the other, or has expressed it to better advantage. In such cases, these various theological expressions are to be considered often as mutually complementary rather than conflicting. Where the authentic theological traditions of the Eastern Church are concerned, we must recognize the admirable way in which they have their roots in Holy Scripture, and how they are nurtured and given expression in the life of the liturgy. They derive their strength too from the living tradition of the apostles and from the works of the Fathers and spiritual writers of the Eastern Churches. Thus they promote the right ordering of Christian life and, indeed, pave the way to a full vision of Christian truth.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_decree_19641121_unitatis-redintegratio_en.html ''Unitatis Redintegratio''] 17&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Trinity====
{{See also|Filioque}}

Although the Western churches do not consider the Eastern and Western understanding of the [[Trinity]] to be radically different, the Eastern Orthodox believe that the Western understanding is fatally flawed. The influence of St [[Augustine]] and, by extension, that of [[Thomas Aquinas]] in the western Mediterranean on this issue are not generally accepted in the Orthodox Church.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|quote=A basic characteristic of the Frankish scholastic method, mislead by Augustinian Platonism and Thomistic Aristotelianism, had been its naive confidence in the objective existence of things rationally speculated about. By following Augustine, the Franks substituted the patristic concern for spiritual observation, (which they had found firmly established in Gaul when they first conquered the area) with a fascination for metaphysics. They did not suspect that such speculations had foundations neither in created nor in spiritual reality. |title=Franks, Romans, Feudalism, and Doctrine — Part 2. Empirical Theology versus Speculative Theology -Empirical Theology|first=John S. |last=Romanides |url=http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.03.en.franks_romans_feudalism_and_doctrine.02.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various Orthodox theologians argue that the ''[[Filioque]]'' clause is symptomatic of this difference.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|quote=The ancient Orthodox teaching of the personal attributes of the Father, Son and Holy Spirit was distorted in the Latin Church by the creation of a teaching of the procession, outside of time and from all eternity, of the Holy Spirit from the Father and the Son — the Filioque. The idea that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Father and the Son originated in certain expressions of Blessed [[Augustine]]. It became established in the West as obligatory in the ninth century, and when Latin missionaries came to the Bulgarians in the middle of the ninth century, the Filioque was in their Symbol of Faith. |title=Orthodox Dogmatic Theology |first=Michael |last=Pomazansky |url=http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0824/_P14.HTM}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|quote=Augustine unknowingly rejects the doctrine of the ecumenical councils concerning the Old Testament Lord of glory incarnate and his Vatican and Protestant followers do the same |title=Part I: Augustine's Teachings Which Were Condemned As Those of Barlaam the Calabrian by the Ninth Ecumenical Council of 1351. |first=John S. |last=Romanides |url=http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.18.en.augustine_unknowingly_rejects_the_doctrine.01.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|quote=The pretext of the Filioque controversy was the Frankish acceptance of Augustine as the key to understanding the theology of the First and Second Ecumenical Synods. |first=John S. |last=Romanides |title=Filioque |url=http://www.geocities.com/trvalentine/orthodox/romanides_filioque.html|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/trvalentine/orthodox/romanides_filioque.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+23:19:24|archivedate=2009-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|quote=During the ensuing centuries long course of the controversy, the Franks not only forced the Patristic tradition into an Augustinian mold, but they confused Augustine's Trinitarian terminology with that of the Father's of the First and Second Ecumenical Synods. This is nowhere so evident as in the Latin handling of Maximos the Confessor's description, composed in 650, of the West Roman Orthodox Filioque at the Council of Florence (1438–42). The East Romans hesitated to present Maximos' letter to Marinos about this West Roman Orthodox Filioque because the letter did not survive in its complete form. |first=John S. |last=Romanides |title=Filioque |url=http://www.geocities.com/trvalentine/orthodox/romanides_filioque.html|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/trvalentine/orthodox/romanides_filioque.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+23:19:24|archivedate=2009-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Filioque'', [[Latin]] for &quot;and (from) the Son&quot;, was added in [[Western Christianity]] to the Latin text of the [[Nicene-Constantinopolitan Creed]], which also varies from the original Greek text in having the additional phrase ''Deum de Deo'' (God from God)&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=3lAOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA78&amp;lpg=PA78&amp;dq=bindley+%22deum+de+deo%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=E0c0SYkpQi&amp;sig=HNTux9XMSLGKuQscYLLajtGLgRo&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=kZR_UKv4DojIhAfLh4GABw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=bindley%20%22deum%20de%20deo%22&amp;f=false Thomas Herbert Bindley, ''The Oecumenical Documents of the Faith'' (Taylor &amp; Francis 1950, reprinted in 1980 by Greenwood Press, a division of Congressional Information Service ISBN 0-313-22197-9), p. 78]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Schaff/&gt; and in using the singular &quot;I believe&quot; (Latin, ''Credo'', Greek Πιστεύω) instead of the original &quot;We believe&quot; (Greek Πιστεύομεν),&lt;ref name=Schaff&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds1.iv.iii.html Schaff, ''Creeds of Christendom'']&lt;/ref&gt; which [[Oriental Orthodoxy]] preserves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armenianchurchlibrary.com/files/creed.pdf Nicene Creed] ([[Armenian Apostolic Church]]); [http://www.saintmaryhouston.org/index.php?q=content/about-us The Coptic Orthodox Church: Our Creed] ([[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria]]); [http://www.ninesaintsethiopianorthodoxmonastery.org/id18.html Nicene Creed] ([[Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church]]); [http://www.stmarysnova.org/documents/church-mission The Nicene Creed] ([[Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church]]); [http://sor.cua.edu/Liturgy/Common/NiceneCreed.html The Nicene Creed] ([[Syriac Orthodox Church]]).&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Assyrian Church of the East]], which is in communion neither with the Eastern Orthodox Church nor with Oriental Orthodoxy also uses &quot;We believe&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://assyrianchurch.org.au/about-us/faith/creed-of-nicaea Creed of Nicaea] ([[Assyrian Church of the East]])&lt;/ref&gt; ''Filioque'' states that the Holy Spirit proceeds from the Son as well as from the Father, a doctrine accepted by the [[Catholic Church]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p1s2c1p2.htm |title=Catechism of the Catholic Church |pages=246–248}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Anglicanism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.victorianweb.org/religion/39articles.html |title=Article 5 of the [[Thirty-Nine Articles]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by [[Protestantism|Protestant churches]] in general.&lt;ref&gt;Lutheranism ([http://www.bookofconcord.org/creeds.html Book of Concord], [http://www.angelfire.com/ny4/djw/lutherantheology.filioque.html The Nicene Creed and the Filioque: A Lutheran Approach]), Presbyterianism ([http://www.unionpresbyterian.com/Creeds/NiceneCreed.dsp Union Presbyterian Church], [http://www.presbyterian.org.nz/3368.0.html Presbyterian Church of Aotearoa New Zealand], [http://saintandrewsrpcga.org/nicene.html Reformed Presbyterian Church]); Methodism ([http://gbgm-umc.org/UMW/BIBLE/ncreed.html United Methodist Hymnal])&lt;/ref&gt; Christians of these groups generally include it when reciting the Nicene Creed. Nonetheless, these groups recognize that ''Filioque'' is not part of the original text established at the [[First Council of Constantinople]] in 381&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P17.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 247]&lt;/ref&gt; and they do not demand that others too should use it when saying the Creed.&lt;ref&gt;The Holy See encourages Eastern Catholics who had included ''Filioque'' in languages such as [[Syriac language|Syriac]] to remove it: &quot;Though it is quite true to say that the Spirit proceeds from both the 'Father and the Son', the Eastern Church, encouraged by the Holy See, has asked us to return to the original form of the Creed&quot; ([http://www.kaldu.org/14_Reformed_ChaldeanMass/QA_NewMass.html Q &amp; A on the Reformed Chaldean Mass]).&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, the Roman Catholic Church does not add the phrase corresponding to ''Filioque'' (καὶ τοῦ Υἱοῦ) to the [[Greek language|Greek]] text of the Creed, even in the [[liturgy]] for [[Latin Rite]] Catholics.&lt;ref name=&quot;PCPCU&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20091026205632/http://www.geocities.com/trvalentine/orthodox/vatican_clar_images.html Pontifical Council for Promoting Christian Unity: The Greek and the Latin Traditions regarding the Procession of the Holy Spirit] (scanned image of the English translation on ''L'Osservatore Romano'' of 20 September 1995); also [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/Athens/Atrium/8410/filioque.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+05:54:33 text with Greek letters transliterated] and [http://www.ewtn.com/library/CURIA/PCCUFILQ.HTM text omitting two sentences at the start of the paragraph that it presents as beginning with &quot;The Western tradition expresses first …&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

At the [[Fourth Council of Constantinople (Eastern Orthodox)|879–880 Council of Constantinople]] the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] anathematized the &quot;Filioque&quot; phrase, &quot;as a novelty and augmentation of the Creed&quot;, and in their 1848 encyclical the Eastern Patriarchs spoke of it as a heresy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1848orthodoxencyclical.html Encyclical of the Eastern Patriarchs, 1848 A Reply to the Epistle of Pope Pius IX, &quot;to the Easterns&quot;]. Fordham.edu. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; It was qualified as such by some of the Eastern Orthodox Church's saints, including [[Photios I of Constantinople]], [[Mark of Ephesus]], [[Gregory Palamas]], who have been called the Three Pillars of Orthodoxy.

The Eastern church believes by the Western church inserting the Filioque unilaterally (without consulting or holding council with the East) into the Creed that the Western church broke communion with the East.&lt;ref name=r1/&gt;

Orthodox theologians such as [[Vladimir Lossky]] criticize the focus of Western theology of God in 'God in uncreated essence' as misguided, which he alleges is a [[modalism|modalistic]] and therefore a speculative expression of God that is indicative of the [[Sabellianism|Sabellian]] heresy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Mystical Theology of the Eastern Church |first=Vladimir |last=Lossky |publisher=SVS Press |year=1997 |isbn= 0-913836-31-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Orthodox theologian [[Michael Pomazansky]] argues that, in order for the Holy Spirit to proceed from the Father and the Son in the Creed, there would have to be two sources in the deity (double procession), whereas in the one God there can only be one source of divinity, which is the Father hypostasis of the Trinity, not God's essence per se.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|quote=Oneness of Essence, and it is absolutely essential to distinguish this from another dogma, the dogma of the begetting and the procession, in which, as the Holy Fathers express it, is shown the Cause of the existence of the Son and the Spirit. All of the Eastern Fathers acknowledge that the Father is monos aitios, the sole Cause” of the Son and the Spirit. Orthodox Dogmatic Theology |first=Michael |last=Pomazansky |url=http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0824/_P14.HTM| title=On the procession of the Holy Spirit}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, Bishop Kallistos Ware suggests that the problem is more one of semantics than of basic doctrinal differences.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Filioque controversy which has separated us for so many centuries is more than a mere technicality, but it is not insoluble. Qualifying the firm position taken when I wrote The Orthodox Church twenty years ago, I now believe, after further study, that the problem is more in the area of semantics than in any basic doctrinal differences.&quot; (Bishop Kallistos Ware, Diakonia, quoted from Elias Zoghby's A Voice from the Byzantine East, p.43)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Experience of God (Theoria) vs Scholasticism====
{{Further|Hesychasm}}

[[Vladimir Lossky]], a noted modern [[Eastern Orthodox]] theologian, argues the difference in East and West is due to the [[Roman Catholic Church]]'s use of pagan metaphysical philosophy (and [[scholasticism]]) rather than actual experience of God called [[theoria]], to validate the theological dogmas of Roman Catholic Christianity. For this reason, Lossky argues that Eastern Orthodox and Roman Catholics have become &quot;different men&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;In the Introduction p. 21 &quot;We have become different men&quot; The Mystical Theology of the Eastern Church, by [[Vladimir Lossky]], SVS Press, 1997. (ISBN 0-913836-31-1) James Clarke &amp; Co Ltd, 1991. (ISBN 0-227-67919-9)&lt;/ref&gt; Other Eastern Orthodox theologians such as [[John Romanides]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Franks, Romans, Feudalism, and Doctrine — Part 2. Empirical Theology versus Speculative Theology -Empirical Theology|first=John S. |last=Romanides |url=http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.03.en.franks_romans_feudalism_and_doctrine.02.htm |quote=A basic characteristic of the Frankish scholastic method, misled by Augustinian Platonism and Thomistic Aristotelianism, had been its naive confidence in the objective existence of things rationally speculated about. By following Augustine, the Franks substituted the patristic concern for spiritual observation, (which they had found firmly established in Gaul when they first conquered the area) with a fascination for metaphysics. They did not suspect that such speculations had foundations neither in created nor in spiritual reality. No one would today accept as true what is not empirically observable, or at least verifiable by inference, from an attested effect. So it is with patristic theology. Dialectical speculation about God and the Incarnation as such are rejected. Only those things which can be tested by the experience of the grace of God in the heart are to be accepted. &quot;Be not carried about by divers and strange teachings. For it is good that the heart be confirmed by grace,&quot; a passage from Hebrews 13.9, quoted by the Fathers to this effect.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Metropolitan [[Hierotheos (Vlachos)|Hierotheos]] of [[Nafpaktos]] have made similar pronouncements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Knowledge of God according to St. Gregory Palamas |author=Metropolitan Hierotheos of Nafpaktos |url=http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b02.en.orthodox_psychotherapy.06.htm#2k |quote=&quot;As I have indicated, [[Barlaam of Seminara|Barlaam]] insisted that knowledge of God depends not on vision of God but on one's understanding. He said that we can acquire knowledge of God through [[philosophy]], and therefore he considered the prophets and apostles who saw the [[Tabor light|uncreated light]], to be below the philosophers. He called the uncreated light sensory, created, and &quot;inferior to our understanding&quot;. However, St. Gregory Palamas, a bearer of the Tradition and a man of revelation, supported the opposite view. In his theology he presented the teaching of the Church that uncreated light, that is, the [[theoria|vision of God]], is not simply a symbolic vision, nor sensory and created, nor inferior to understanding, but it is deification. Through deification man is deemed worthy of seeing God. And this deification is not an abstract state, but a union of man with God. That is to say, the man who beholds the uncreated light sees it because he is united with God. He sees it with his inner eyes, and also with his bodily eyes, which, however, have been altered by God's action. Consequently theoria is [[theosis|union with God]]. And this union is knowledge of God. At this time one is granted knowledge of God, which is above human knowledge and above the senses.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
According to the Orthodox teachings, [[Theoria]] can be achieved through ascetic practices like [[hesychasm]] (see St [[John Climacus]]), which was condemned as a heresy by [[Barlaam of Seminara]].

=====The heart reconciled with the mind higher than reason alone=====
Orthodox theologians charge that, in contrast to [[Orthodox theology]], western theology is based on philosophical discourse which reduces humanity and nature to cold mechanical concepts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Orthodox Dogmatic Theology: A Concise Exposition Protopresbyter Appendices New currents in Russian philosophico-theological thought Philosophy and Theology |first=Michael |last=Pomazansky |url=http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0824/_P2N.HTM}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Roman Catholicism rationalizes even the sacrament of the Eucharist: it interprets spiritual action as purely material and debases the sacrament to such an extent that it becomes in its view a kind of atomistic miracle. The Orthodox Church has no metaphysical theory of Transsubstantiation, and there is no need of such a theory. Christ is the Lord of the elements and it is in His power to do so that 'every thing, without in the least changing its physical substance' could become His Body. Christ's Body in the Eucharist is not physical flesh.&quot; History of Russian Philosophy by Nikolai Lossky ISBN 978-0-8236-8074-0 p. 87&lt;/ref&gt; Orthodox theologians argue that the mind (reason, rationality) is the focus of Western theology, whereas in Eastern theology, the mind must be put in the heart, so they are united into what is called nous, this unity as heart is the focus of Eastern Orthodox Christianity&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://byzantinesacredart.com/blog/2006/07/schism_of_mind_and_heart.html |title=Schism of Mind and Heart |first=Vincent |last=Rossi}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071011114120/http://www.acrod.org/sn/sn4a.shtml &quot;The Relationship between Prayer and Theology&quot; from the official website of &quot;The American Carpatho-Russian Orthodox Diocese&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; involving the unceasing [[Prayer of the heart]].&lt;ref&gt;Romanides: &quot;the unceasing prayer in the hearts which repairs the short-circuit between the heart and the brain.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Theological consequences of the division East and West=====
{{Further|Noetic|Noesis|Spiritual Warfare}}
In Orthodox theology, in the Eastern [[ascetic]] traditions one of the goals of ascetic practice is to obtain sobriety of consciousness, awakeness ([[nepsis]]). For humankind this is reached in the healing of whole person called the [[soul]], heart. When a person's heart is reconciled with their mind, this is referred to as a healing of the nous or the &quot;eye, focus of the heart or soul&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Neptic Monasticism&quot;&gt;[http://www.greekorthodoxchurch.org/neptic_monasticism.html Neptic Monasticism]. Greekorthodoxchurch.org. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Orthodox Psychotherapy CHAPTER III |author=Metropolitan Hierotheos Vlachos |publisher=Birth of Theotokos Monastery,Greece |date=1 January 2005 |isbn= 978-960-7070-27-2 |url=http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b02.en.orthodox_psychotherapy.03.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Part of this process is the healing and or reconciliation of humankind's [[reason]] being called ''logos'' or ''dianoia'' with the heart, soul.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/phronema/patristic-theology-romanides-chapter-1-what-is-the-human-nous.aspx What is the Human Nous?] by [[John Romanides]]&lt;/ref&gt; While mankind's spirit and body are energies vivified by the soul, Orthodoxy teaches man's sin, suffering, sorrow is caused by his heart and mind being a duality and in conflict.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;as the Trinitarian God is Nous, Word and Spirit, so the soul too has nous, word and spirit.&quot; (but in humans' case they &quot;are not hypostases&quot;) Metropolitan [[Hierotheos Vlachos]] (2005), [http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b02.en.orthodox_psychotherapy.03.htm#in ''Orthodox Psychotherapy''], Tr. Esther E. Cunningham Williams (Birth of Theotokos Monastery, Greece), ISBN 978-960-7070-27-2&lt;/ref&gt; According to Orthodox theology, lack of [[noetic]] understanding (sickness) can be neither circumvented nor satisfied by rational or discursive thought (i.e. [[systematization]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;Neptic Monasticism&quot;/&gt; and denying the needs of the human heart (a more Western expression would be the needs of the soul) causes various negative or destructive manifestations such as addiction, atheism and evil thoughts etc.&lt;ref&gt;[http://romanity.org/htm/rom.19.en.jesus_christ_the_life_of_the_world.01.htm#s3 &quot;JESUS CHRIST – THE LIFE OF THE WORLD&quot;], John S. Romanides&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b05.en.the_illness_and_cure_of_the_soul.02.htm#Fall &quot;THE ILLNESS AND CURE OF THE SOUL&quot;] Metropolitan Hierotheos of Nafpaktos&lt;/ref&gt; A cleaned, healed or restored Nous creates the condition of [[sobriety]] or nepsis of the mind.

=====The uncreated light=====
{{main|Hesychasm}}
{{See also|Tabor light|Nicholas Cabasilas}}
Orthodox theologians assert that the theological division of East and West culminated into a direct theological conflict known as the [[Gregory Palamas#The Hesychast controversy|Hesychasm controversy]] during several councils at Constantinople New Rome, between the years 1341–1351. They argue that this controversy highlighted the sharp contrast between what is embraced by the Roman Catholic Church as proper (or orthodox) theological dogma and how theology is validated and what is considered valid theology by the Eastern Orthodox. The essence of the disagreement is that in the East one cannot be a genuine true theologian or teach knowledge of God, without having experienced God, as is defined as the vision of God ([[theoria]]). At the heart of the issue was the teaching of the [[Essence-Energies distinction]]s (which states that while creation can never know God's uncreated essence, it can know His uncreated energies) by [[Gregory Palamas]].

====Original sin, free will and the Immaculate Conception====

=====Augustine's doctrine of original sin=====
{{See also|Traducianism}}
The Eastern Orthodox do not accept [[Augustine of Hippo|Augustine]]'s teaching of [[original sin]]. His interpretation of [[ancestral sin]] is rejected in the East as well. Nor is Augustine's teaching accepted in its totality in the West.&lt;ref name=Neuro/&gt; The Roman Catholic Church rejects [[traducianism]] and affirms [[creationism (soul)|creationism]]. Its teaching on original sin is largely based on but not identical with that of Augustine, and is opposed to the interpretation of Augustine advanced by [[Martin Luther]] and [[John Calvin]]. Its teaching departs from Augustine's ideas in some respects.&lt;ref name=Neuro&gt;&quot;Augustine claims that all humans have sinned in Adam. The [[Council of Orange|Council]], however, interprets Rom. 5:12 as saying that, 'By one man sin entered the world, and by sin death, and thus to all men [death] passed, in which all have sinned.' In other words all sin because of the spiritual death which each one suffers by not being in communion with the glory of God&quot;: Romanides&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stmaryorthodoxchurch.org/orthodoxy/articles/2004-hughes-sin.php Ancestral Versus Original Sin: An Overview with Implications for Psychotherapy] by V. Rev. Antony Hughes, M.Div St. Mary Antiochian Orthodox Church, Cambridge, Massachusetts&lt;/ref&gt; The Eastern Church makes no use at all of Augustine. Another Orthodox view is expressed by [[Christos Yannaras]], who described Augustine as &quot;the fount of every distortion and alteration in the Church's truth in the West&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;(The Freedom of Morality, p. 151n. Christos Yannaras)&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Church teachings on original sin=====
What the Eastern Orthodox accepts is that ancestral sin corrupted their existence (their bodies and environment) that each person is born into and thus we are born into a corrupted existence (by the ancestral sin of Adam and Eve)&lt;ref&gt;[http://store.holycrossbookstore.com/970730314.html The Ancestral SinJohn S. Romanides George S. Gabriel, translator]. Store.holycrossbookstore.com. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=June 2010}} and that &quot;original sin is hereditary. It did not remain only Adam and Eve's. As life passes from them to all of their descendants, so does original sin. We all of us participate in original sin because we are all descended from the same forefather, Adam.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20110726122920/http://www.gocanada.org/catechism/catorsin.htm Original Sin And Its Consequences]. Metropolitan Archbishop Sotirios, ''Orthodox Catechism: Basic Teachings of the Orthodox Faith''&lt;/ref&gt;

Both East{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} and West&lt;ref name=CCC405/&gt; hold that each person is not called to atone for the actual sin committed by Adam and Eve. Rather each person is called to overcome the corrupted world they are born into and seek salvation by way of the community established by God. By attaining the Holy Spirit which validates this community (church).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P28.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 797–798]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Here the two churches greatly differ, as to the meaning of attaining the Holy Spirit, both having radically different meanings East and West.&lt;ref&gt;A Comparison: Francis of Assisi and St. Seraphim of Sarov by Father George Macris [http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/praxis/francis_sarov.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;From Saint [[Seraphim of Sarov]] On Acquisition of the Holy Spirit by [[Nikolay Motovilov]][http://www.greekorthodoxchurch.org/saint_seraphim.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

The teaching of the Roman Catholic Church about [[original sin]] is that all people inherit the sin of Adam,&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20101027004307/http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p1s2c1p7.htm#III &quot;Following St. Paul, the Church has always taught that the overwhelming misery which oppresses men and their inclination towards evil and death cannot be understood apart from their connection with Adam's sin and the fact that '''he has transmitted to us a sin''' with which we are all born afflicted&quot; (Catechism of the Catholic Church, 403)] (emphasis added).&lt;/ref&gt; and the teaching of the Eastern Orthodox Church is that, as a result of Adam's sin, &quot;hereditary sin flowed to his posterity; so that everyone who is born after the flesh bears this burden, and experiences the fruits of it in this present world.&quot;&lt;ref name=Dositheus6&gt;[http://www.crivoice.org/creeddositheus.html Confession of Dositheus, Decree 6]. Crivoice.org (2011-11-11). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Western Church, &quot;original sin does not have the character of a personal fault in any of Adam's descendants&quot;,&lt;ref name=CCC405&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20101027004307/http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p1s2c1p7.htm#III Catechism of the Catholic Church, 405]&lt;/ref&gt; and the Eastern Church teaches that &quot;by these fruits and this burden we do not understand [actual] sin&quot;.&lt;ref name=Dositheus6/&gt; The Orthodox{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} and the Catholics&lt;ref name=CCC418/&gt; believe that people inherit only the spiritual sickness (in which all suffer and sin) of Adam and Eve, caused by their ancestral sin (what has flowed to them), a sickness leaving them weakened in their powers, subject to ignorance, suffering and the domination of death, and inclined to sin.&lt;ref name=CCC418&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 418]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Synergy and free will=====

The Eastern Orthodox Church teaches that each individual must choose God by their own [[free will]] and rejected Augustine's teaching of [[predestination]], interpreted as conflicting with free will, in which interpretation it is rejected also by the Roman Catholic Church.&lt;ref name=AugPred&gt;The meaning of St. Augustine's words (De dono persever., xxxv): &quot;Prædestinatio nihil est aliud quam præscientia et præparatio beneficiorum, quibus certissime liberantur [i.e. salvantur], quicunque liberantur&quot; (Predestination is nothing else than the foreknowledge and foreordaining of those gracious gifts which make certain the salvation of all who are saved)[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12378a.htm] differs from the [[Calvinism|Calvinist]] idea of [[Predestination (Calvinism)|]], since it speaks of predestination only to heaven, not to hell. The latter idea is excluded in Roman Catholic teaching ([http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P2O.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1037)], which holds that, when God establishes his eternal plan of &quot;predestination&quot;, he includes in it each person's free response to his grace ([http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1O.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 600).]&lt;/ref&gt;  Similarly, the Roman Catholic Church teaches that, even after the Fall, man remains free,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 407]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P5M.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1730]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; and that freedom in man is an &quot;outstanding manifestation of the divine image&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P5G.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1705]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; The view that the first steps of salvation are in the power of the individual without any need of divine grace, a view expounded by [[John Cassian]] and [[Faustus of Riez]],&lt;ref name=ODCC-Semipel&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3), article ''Semipelagianism''&lt;/ref&gt; was condemned by the Latin church in the local [[Council of Orange]] in 529.

The doctrine upheld by the Eastern Orthodox Church, is that salvation involves man freely giving the assent of faith to the Word of God and cooperating with the prompting of the Holy Spirit preceding and preserving his assent and also man sometimes by his own [[volition]] seeking salvation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://orthodoxyinfo.org/AzkoulFreeWill.htm Michael Azkoul, '&amp;#39;An Introduction to the Orthodox Christian Understanding of Free Will]. Orthodoxyinfo.org. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; This doctrine of [[synergy]] is comparable to saving a drowning man by throwing a rope to him, which he must choose whether or not to grab in order to receive the help offered.

&lt;!-- commenting out long discussion of Cassian which, when placed at the beginning of this section, seems to be presented to the reader with no clear explanation of why this is important and thus appears to be &quot;apropos of nothing&quot;.  I don't think we need this long discussion of Cassian at all but I am leaving it here for now pending further discussion on the Talk Page.

In the Eastern Orthodox Church, Cassian's doctrine is not referred to as Semipelagianism it is referred to as the theological doctrine of [[synergy]] or cooperation between man's will and the will of God. The working together of the Holy Spirit and each person, towards the person's salvation.

[[John Cassian]] (ca. 360 – 435), who is venerated as a saint by both the Eastern Orthodox and the Roman Catholic Church, is considered to be an early proponent of the view that in the sixteenth century became known as [[Semipelagianism]].&lt;ref name=ODCC-Semipel/&gt; Semipelagianism is a set of doctrines according to which, while admitting the need of [[divine grace]] for[[salvation]], the first steps sometimes are in the power of the individual, without the need for grace, which intervenes only later.&lt;ref name=ODCC-Semipel&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3), article ''Semipelagianism''&lt;/ref&gt; Cassian endeavored in his thirteenth chapter of Conferences section eleven to demonstrate from Biblical examples that God frequently awaits the good impulses of the natural will, before coming to its assistance with His supernatural grace. While the grace often preceded the will, as in the case of Matthew and Peter, he said, on the other hand the will frequently preceded the grace, as in the case of Zacchæus and the Good Thief on the Cross.&lt;ref&gt;Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series II/Volume XI/John Cassian/Conferences of John Cassian, Part II/Conference XIII/Chapter 11[[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series II/Volume XI/John Cassian/Conferences of John Cassian, Part II/Conference XIII/Chapter 11]]&lt;/ref&gt; Cassian's position has been described as a &quot;middle way&quot; between [[Pelagianism]], which taught that the will alone was sufficient to live a sinless life, and the view of [[Augustine of Hippo]], that emphasizes the absolute need for grace.&lt;ref name=AugPred&gt;The meaning of St. Augustine's words (De dono persever., xxxv): &quot;Prædestinatio nihil est aliud quam præscientia et præparatio beneficiorum, quibus certissime liberantur [i.e. salvantur], quicunque liberantur&quot; (Predestination is nothing else than the foreknowledge and foreordaining of those gracious gifts which make certain the salvation of all who are saved)[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12378a.htm] differs from the [[Calvinism|Calvinist]] idea of [[Predestination (Calvinism)|]], since it speaks of predestination only to heaven, not to hell. The latter idea is excluded in Roman Catholic teaching ([http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P2O.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1037)], which holds that, when God establishes his eternal plan of &quot;predestination&quot;, he includes in it each person's free response to his grace ([http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1O.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 600).]&lt;/ref&gt; Cassian's doctrine was against Augustine doctrine of predestination as well [[Calvinism]]'s [[predestination (Calvinism)|predestination]], which Calvin stated he based on Augustine's.

--&gt;

=====Immaculate Conception rejected by the East=====
Some Orthodox theologians also express the belief that the doctrine of [[Original Sin]] has led western theology to develop the doctrine about the &quot;[[Immaculate Conception]] of the [[Virgin Mary]]&quot; (which was defined by Pope Pius IX in 1854).&lt;ref&gt;Kallistos Ware. [http://books.google.com/books?id=HG8c-lUZIDEC&amp;pg=PA77 &quot;The Orthodox Way&quot;] ISBN 978-0-913836-58-3&lt;/ref&gt; Eastern theologians consider this doctrine to be wrong, since it claims that God Himself protected the [[Virgin Mary]] from the sickness of sin, so that she could give birth to [[Christ]], while they believe that the [[Virgin Mary]] was chosen to give birth to [[Christ]], because of{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} her own desire to love God and follow God's will.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ocf.org/OrthodoxPage/reading/ortho_cath.html] &quot;from '&amp;#39;the first instant of her conception, the Blessed Virgin Mary was, by a most singular grace and privilege of Almighty God, and in view of the merits of Jesus Christ, the Redeemer of the human race, preserved from all stain of Original Sin. It is a doctrine revealed by God, and therefore to be firmly and steadfastly believed by all the faithful'&amp;#39; (from the '&amp;#39;Bull Ineffabilis Deus'&amp;#39;).&quot; WHAT ARE THE DIFFERENCES BETWEEN ORTHODOXY AND ROMAN CATHOLICISM? By Father Michael Azkoul.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/inquirers/theotokos.aspx] &quot;However, we do believe that the Virgin Mary is an image, as St. Maximos the Confessor says, of the Christian goal of becoming Christ-like, of '&amp;#39;theosis'&amp;#39;. Just as the Theotokos gave birth to Christ in a bodily way, so we must, St. Maximos tells us, give birth to Christ in an unbodily or spiritual way. In so doing, we imitate her practical spiritual life, including the purity and humility by which she formed her free will into perfect obedience to the Will of God.&quot;, &quot;we cannot lose sight of the importance of free will in the development and expression of her rich personality.&quot; An Orthodox View of the Virgin Mary.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/ecumenism/encyc_1895.aspx &quot;The Patriarchal Encyclical of 1895&quot;]. Orthodoxinfo.com. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sin, Purgatory and Hell====

=====Purgatory=====
Another point of theological contention between the western and eastern churches, is the doctrine of [[purgatory]] (as it was shown at the [[Second Council of Lyons]] and the [[Council of Ferrara-Florence]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Thomas P. Rausch|author2=Catherine E. Clifford|title=Catholicism in the Third Millennium|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=o4jG7X95mMQC&amp;pg=PA200|accessdate=2 June 2012|date=1 February 2003|publisher=Liturgical Press|isbn=978-0-8146-5899-4|pages=200–}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was developed in time in western theology, according to which, &quot;all who die in God's grace and friendship, but still imperfectly purified, are indeed assured of their eternal salvation; but after death they undergo purification, so as to achieve the holiness necessary to enter the joy of heaven.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p123a12.htm#III Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1030]&lt;/ref&gt; However, some eastern theologians, while agreeing that there is beyond death a state in which believers continue to be perfected and led to full divinization, consider that it is a state not of punishment but of growth;&lt;ref name=Confessions/&gt; hold that suffering cannot purify sin, since they have a different view of sin and consider suffering as a result of a spiritual sickness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ocf.org/OrthodoxPage/reading/ortho_cath.html What Are The Differences Between Orthodoxy And Roman Catholicism? By Father Michael Azkoul]. Ocf.org. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Western theology usually considers sin not only as a sickness that weakens and impedes, but also as something that merits punishment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p3s1c1a8.htm &quot;Venial sin weakens charity; it manifests a disordered affection for created goods; it impedes the soul's progress in the exercise of the virtues and the practice of the moral good; it merits temporal punishment.&quot; Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1863]&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Bosom of Abraham=====
The Eastern Orthodox Church holds that &quot;there is a state beyond death where believers continue to be perfected and led to full divinization&quot;.&lt;ref name=Confessions&gt;Ted A. Campbell, ''Christian Confessions: a Historical Introduction'' (Westminster John Knox Press 1996 ISBN 0-664-25650-3), p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|reason=please find an orthodox source|date=June 2010}} Although some Orthodox{{Who|date=June 2010}} have described this intermediate state as &quot;[[purgatory]]&quot;, others distinguish it from aspects associated with it in the West: at the [[Council of Ferrara-Florence]], the Orthodox Bishop and Saint [[Mark of Ephesus]] argued that there are in it no purifying fires.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b24.en.life_after_death.05.htm#pu2 Life After Death] by Metropolitan [[Hierotheos (Vlachos)|Hierotheos]]&lt;/ref&gt; This also involves, according to Eastern theologians, differences about the way Heaven and Hell are taught and experienced.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Paradise and Hell are an energy of the uncreated grace of God, as men experience it, and therefore they are uncreated.[http://aggreen.net/beliefs/heaven_hell.html]&lt;/ref&gt; The teachings of the Eastern Orthodox Church, do not reflect the commonly held beliefs Western Christians, i.e. there is no Wrathful God in the sky,&lt;ref name=&quot;aggreen.net&quot;&gt;The idea that God is an angry figure who sends those He condemns to a place called Hell, where they spend eternity in torment separated from His presence, is missing from the Bible and unknown in the early church. While Heaven and Hell are decidedly real, they are experiential conditions rather than physical places, and both exist in the presence of God. In fact, nothing exists outside the presence of God. '''This is not the way traditional Western Christianity, Roman Catholic or Protestant,''' has envisioned the afterlife. In Western thought Hell is a location, a place where God punishes the wicked, where they are cut off from God and the Kingdom of Heaven. Yet this concept occurs nowhere in the Bible, and does not exist in the original languages of the Bible.[http://aggreen.net/beliefs/heaven_hell.html]&lt;/ref&gt; neither is there a heaven up in the sky.&lt;ref name=&quot;aggreen.net&quot;/&gt; Heaven, the Kingdom of God and eternal Damnation are both, being with and in the presence of God.

=====Damnation=====
Eastern Orthodox consider the teaching of punishment in the after life by Western Christianity&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://aggreen.net/beliefs/heaven_hell.html Heaven and Hell in the Afterlife]. Aggreen.net. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;What is evil? Is it not the estrangement from God Who is Life? 1 Is it not death? What does Western theology teach about death? All Roman Catholics and most Protestants consider death as a punishment from God. God considered all men guilty of Adam's sin and punished them by death, that is by cutting them away from Himself; depriving them of His live giving energy, and so killing them spiritually at first and later bodily, by some sort of spiritual starvation. Augustine interprets the passage in Genesis &quot;If you eat of the fruit of this tree, you will die the death&quot; as &quot;If you eat of the fruit of this tree, I will kill you&quot;.[http://www.orthodoxpress.org/parish/river_of_fire.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; a corruption of the original teaching of the eternal fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; The traditional Orthodox teaching is that &quot;those who reject Christ will face punishment. According to the Confession of Dositheus, persons go immediately to joy in Christ or to the torments of punishment&quot;.&lt;ref name=Confessions/&gt; &quot; This is different from the West's teaching of Damnation.&lt;ref&gt;When Death and Hades is placed in the fiery presence of God, in the &quot;lake of divine fire&quot;, it is destroyed, because it is in the very presence of God, death can not exist when God is present.

It is interesting to examine the Greek word for &quot;divine&quot;, it is from the Greek &quot;theion&quot;, which could also mean &quot;divine being&quot;, but also means &quot;sulfur', or in Old English &quot;brimstone&quot; [lit. 'burning stone']. As strange as that sounds to us, it is because of the ancient understanding of the cosmic order of the nature of all things. All people in all cultures from the Near East to the West understood that there were four 'elements', these were: Earth, Air, Fire, and Water. Their nature was that Earth and Water tended to go down toward Hades, and Air and Fire tended to go up toward heaven. This could plainly be seen when the heavenly fire, lighting, would hit a living tree and burn the &quot;life&quot; out of it. Anyone could see that the heat from the tree would go back to heaven in the fire, and the ash that remained would go down into the ground. But there was this mysterious yellowish earth substance that behaved very differently, when placed in a fire it burn so brightly that your eyes could not bear to look at it. As it burned, it would release the heavenly substance that was trapped inside and it would rise back to heaven. Clearly, this &quot;burning stone&quot; was a divine substance, and as such, it was simply called &quot;divinity. It was burned within a new temple to &quot;purify&quot; it before consecration, presumably when this burning stone released its divinity, it causes all evil things to flee from the temple, and thus was the temple readied for worship.

Yet the word 'theion' is translated as &quot;brimstone&quot; or &quot;sulfur&quot; in Luke 17:29, Rev. 9:17, 14:10, 20:10, 21:8, which is where 'fire and brimstone' comes out of heaven, but it is equally interchange with the words &quot;divine fire&quot;. Since this did not fit the translators' preconceived ideas, it is rendered always as brimstone in this context.

Elsewhere in Revelation it states that the &quot;heat comes out of heaven&quot; and burns the enemies of God, yet does not harm the ones with God's seal on their foreheads. So the same heat, the heat that is the very life and light that comes from God, burns the sinners, and does not harm the ones that love God.[http://aggreen.net/beliefs/heaven_hell.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

In Orthodox doctrine there is no place without God. In eternity there is no hiding from God. In Catholic theology, God is present everywhere not only by his power but in himself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/06612a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: '&amp;#39;The Nature and Attributes of God'&amp;#39;]. Newadvent.org (1909-09-01). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; Hell is a state of self-selected separation from God. In Orthodoxy torment for the damned is not some created place called Hell, where people are without God. As the English word [[Hell]] is not in the Greek bible, although the Greek word κόλασις, which now means &quot;the situation of spiritual punishment after the last judgement of those who died without repenting of their sins&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;η κατάσταση πνευματικής τιμωρίας μετά την τελική κρίση όσων πέθαναν χωρίς να έχουν μετανοήσει για τις αμαρτίες τους&quot; (Greek Dictionary Γ. Μπαμπινιώτη ''Λεξικό για το Σχολείο &amp; το Γραφείο'' 2004 ISBN 960-86190-4-1)&lt;/ref&gt; is found in the Greek Bible.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse||Matthew|25:46}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word Hades is not expressed as a place strictly of eternal damnation in the Greek bible either. It as the [[bosom of Abraham]] is where both [[Lazarus and Dives|Lazarus]] and the rich men existed; neither was in a separate place from God or one another.&lt;ref&gt;Luke 16:23 In hell, where he was in torment, he looked up and saw Abraham far away, '''with Lazarus by his side'''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the Gospel story of Lazarus and the Rich Man, Jesus clearly states that they both end up in the same place, in Hades. Hades of course is used to mean the same thing as Hebrew &quot;Sheol,&quot; it means the place to which souls descended to awake judgment by Jesus Christ, after His Resurrections and Ascension.&lt;/ref&gt;

While eastern theology considers the desire to sin, as the result of a spiritual sickness (caused by Adam and Eve's pride), which needs to be cured.&lt;ref&gt;[http://orthodoxeurope.org/page/10/1.aspx#24 &quot;Human nature, according to St Symeon, needs a physician who can heal it from its corruptibility, and this physician is Jesus Christ Himself.&quot; An Online Orthodox Catechism]. Orthodoxeurope.org (2003-09-24). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; One such theologian gives his interpretation of Western theology as follows: &quot;According to the holy Fathers of the Church, there is not an uncreated Paradise and a created Hell, as the Franco-Latin tradition teaches&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b24.en.life_after_death.07.htm Life After Death] by Metropolitan [[Hierotheos (Vlachos)|Hierotheos]]&lt;/ref&gt; The eastern Church, believes that hell or eternal damnation and heaven exist and are the same place, which is being with God, and that the very same Divine love (God's uncreated energies) which is a source of bliss and consolation for the righteous (because they love God, His love is Heaven for them), is also a source of torment (or a &quot;Lake of Fire&quot;) for sinners (because they don't love God, they will feel His love this way).&lt;ref&gt;[http://orthodoxeurope.org/page/10/1.aspx#53 An Online Orthodox Catechism]. Orthodoxeurope.org (2003-09-24). Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;the biblical concept of heaven and hell also becomes distorted, since the eternal fires of hell and the outer darkness become creatures also whereas, they are the uncreated glory of God as seen by those who refuse to love.&quot; [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/trvalentine/orthodox/romanides_filioque.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+23:19:24 Filioque] by [[John Romanides]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b24.en.life_after_death.07.htm#par2 Life After Death] by Metropolitan [[Hierotheos (Vlachos)|Hierotheos]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hell is not so much a place where God imprisons man, as a place where man, by misusing his free will, chooses to imprison himself. And even in Hell the wicked are not deprived of the love of God, but by their own choice they experience as suffering what the saints experience as joy. ‘The love of God will be an intolerable torment for those who have not acquired it within themselves&quot; ([http://books.google.com/books?id=dxqvWwPSCSwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Mystical+Theology+of+the+Eastern+Church&amp;as_brr=0#PPA234,M1 V. Lossky, The Mystical Theology of the Eastern Church, p. 234] ISBN 978-0-913836-31-6).&lt;/ref&gt; The Western Church speaks of heaven&lt;ref name=CCC1024&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P2M.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1024]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; and hell&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P2O.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1033]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 2012-06-02.&lt;/ref&gt; as states of existence rather than as places. Whereas in Eastern Orthodoxy there is no Hell per se, there is damnation or punishment in eternity for the rejection of God's grace.

==See also==
* [[Western Christianity]]
* [[Eastern Christianity]]
* [[Western Rite Orthodoxy]]
* [[Sobornost (journal)|''Sobornost'' (theological journal)]]
* [[Library of Constantinople]] destroyed by Western Crusaders during the sack of Constantinople

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
*Joseph P. Farrell. ''[http://dialectic.wordpress.com/ghd/ God, History, &amp; Dialectic: The Theological Foundations of the Two Europes and Their Cultural Consequences]''. Bound edition 1997. Electronic edition 2008.
*Aidan Nichols. [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0814650198 ''Rome and the Eastern Churches: a Study in Schism'']. 1992
*Romanides, John, ''The Cure of the Neurobiological Sickness of Religion, the Hellenic Civilization of the Roman Empire, Charlemagne's Lie of 794 and His Lie Today'' [http://romanity.org/htm/rom.02.en.the_cure_of_the_neurobiological_sickness_of_rel.03.htm]  [http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.02.en.the_cure_of_the_neurobiological_sickness_of_rel.01.htm]
*[[Steven Runciman]]. The Eastern Schism: A Study of the Papacy and the Eastern Churches during the XIth and XIIth Centuries. 1955
*Henry Chadwick. ''East and West: The Making of a Rift in the Church: From Apostolic Times until the Council of Florence''. Oxford University Press, 2003.

==External links==
*[http://www.fatheralexander.org/booklets/english/history_timothy_ware_1.htm#n4 Byzantium: The Great Schism, by Bp. Kallistos Ware]
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13535a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: ''The Eastern Schism'']
*[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/587056/Schism-of-1054 Encyclopaedia Britannica: ''Schism of 1054'']
*[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/speeches/1965/documents/hf_p-vi_spe_19651207_common-declaration_en.html Joint Catholic-Orthodox Declaration of Pope Paul VI and Ecumenical Patriarch Athenagoras I, 7 December 1965]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/inourtime/inourtime_20031016.shtml BBC Radio 4 round table: ''In Our Time: Schism'' (16 October 2003)] (audio)
*[http://www.orthodox.org.ph/content/view/211/50/ Orthodox Church in the Philippines: ''East–West Schism'']
*[http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/general/greatschism.aspx The Great Schism from Orthodox SCOBA]

{{Orthodoxy}}
{{Catholicism}}
{{Christian History|collapsed}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Religion in the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:East–West Schism| ]]
[[Category:1054]]
[[Category:11th-century Roman Catholicism]]
[[Category:11th-century Eastern Orthodoxy]]
[[Category:Schisms in Christianity]]
[[Category:Christianity-related controversies]]
[[Category:History of Christianity]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[af:Oosterse Skisma]]
[[ar:الانشقاق العظيم]]
[[an:Gran Scisma d'Orient]]
[[ast:Cisma d'Oriente]]
[[az:Xristianlıqda bölünmə]]
[[be:Раскол хрысціянскай царквы 1054 года]]
[[be-x-old:Вялікая схізма]]
[[bg:Източно-западна схизма]]
[[bs:Crkveni raskol]]
[[ca:Gran Cisma d'Orient]]
[[cs:Velké schizma]]
[[cy:Y Sgism Fawr]]
[[da:Det store skisma 1054]]
[[de:Morgenländisches Schisma]]
[[et:Suur kirikulõhe]]
[[el:Σχίσμα του 1054]]
[[es:Cisma de Oriente]]
[[eo:Orienta skismo]]
[[eu:Zisma Nagusia]]
[[fa:جدایی شرق و غرب]]
[[fr:Schisme de 1054]]
[[fy:Eastersk Skisma]]
[[gl:Gran Cisma]]
[[ko:동서 교회의 분열]]
[[hi:धार्मिक महाविच्छेद]]
[[hr:Crkveni raskol]]
[[id:Skisma Timur-Barat]]
[[is:Kirkjusundrungin]]
[[it:Grande Scisma]]
[[he:פילוג הכנסייה הנוצרית]]
[[ka:დიდი სქიზმა]]
[[lv:Lielā Shizma]]
[[hu:Nagy egyházszakadás]]
[[mk:Големата Шизма]]
[[ms:Perpecahan Timur-Barat]]
[[mwl:Grande Cisma de l Ouriente]]
[[nl:Oosters Schisma]]
[[ja:東西教会の分裂]]
[[no:Det store skisma 1054]]
[[nds:Greeksch Schisma]]
[[pl:Wielka schizma wschodnia]]
[[pt:Grande Cisma do Oriente]]
[[ro:Marea Schismă]]
[[ru:Раскол христианской церкви (1054)]]
[[scn:Scisma Granni]]
[[simple:Great Schism]]
[[sk:Východná schizma]]
[[sl:Velika shizma]]
[[ckb:لێکترازانی گەورە]]
[[sr:Велики раскол]]
[[fi:Suuri skisma]]
[[sv:Stora schismen 1054]]
[[tl:Paghahati ng Silangan-Kanluran]]
[[ta:பெரும் சமயப்பிளவு]]
[[tr:Doğu - Batı Kiliselerinin Ayrılması]]
[[uk:Розкол християнської церкви 1054]]
[[vi:Ly giáo Đông - Tây]]
[[fiu-vro:Suur kerkolaheq]]
[[war:Pagburublag han Sinirangan-Katundan]]
[[zh:東西教會大分裂]]</text>
      <sha1>08zoxfmvykpq8sdsrdltzfmscmp9qwt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
