<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ecclesiology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>651997</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518597208</id>
      <parentid>510342051</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-18T22:36:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>YFdyh-bot</username>
        <id>16428237</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[ca:Eclesiologia]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16439">[[File:Washington National Cathedral Twilight.jpg|thumb|upright|Washington National Cathedral]]

'''Ecclesiology''' usually refers to the [[Christian theology|theological study]] of the [[Christian Church]]. However, when the word was coined in England in the late 1830s, it was defined as the science of the building and decoration of [[Church (building)|church buildings]] and it is still, though rarely, used in this sense.

In its theological sense, ecclesiology deals with the [[Origins of Christianity|church's origin]], its relationship to [[Jesus]], its role in [[salvation]], its [[Church discipline|discipline]], its [[eschatology|destiny]], and its [[clergy|leadership]]. Since different ecclesiologies give shape to very different institutions, the word may also refer to a particular church or [[Christian denominations|denomination’s]] character, self-described or otherwise – hence phrases such as ''Roman Catholic ecclesiology'', ''Lutheran ecclesiology'', and ''ecumenical ecclesiology''.

==Etymology==
The roots of the word ''ecclesiology'' come from the [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] {{lang|grc|ἐκκλησίᾱ}}, ''ekklēsiā'' (Latin [[ecclesia]]) meaning &quot;[[wikt:congregation|congregation]], [[church (disambiguation)|church]]&quot;;{{#tag:ref|In the Greco-Roman world, ''ecclesia'' was used to refer to a lawful assembly, or a called legislative body.  As early as [[Pythagoras]], the word took on the additional meaning of a community with shared beliefs.&lt;ref&gt;Diogenes Laertius, 8.41 (available [http://www.mikrosapoplous.gr/dl/dl08.html online], retrieved 22 May 2008).&lt;/ref&gt;  This is the meaning taken in the Greek translation of the [[Hebrew Scriptures]] (the [[Septuagint]]), and later adopted by the Christian community to refer to the assembly of believers.&lt;ref&gt;F. Bauer, W. Danker, ''A Greek English Lexicon of the New Testament and other Early Christian Literature,'' third ed., (Chicago:University of Chicago Press, 2000), {{lang|grc|ἐκκλησία}}.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=notes}} and {{lang|grc|-λογία}}, ''[[-logy|-logia]]'', meaning &quot;words&quot;, &quot;knowledge&quot;, or &quot;logic&quot;, a combining term used in the names of sciences or bodies of knowledge.

Its first appearance in print, as ''ecclesialogy'', was in the quarterly journal ''[[The British Critic]]'' in 1837, in an article written by an anonymous contributor&lt;ref name=TCM48&gt;{{cite book|last=White|first=James F.|title=The Cambridge Movement: the ecclesiologists and the Gothic revival|url=http://www.google.co.uk/books?id=IOo8AAAAIAAJ|edition=revised|year=1979|publisher=Cambridge University Press|pages=48–9}}&lt;/ref&gt; who defined it thus: {{quote|We mean, then, by Ecclesialogy, a science which may treat of the proper construction and operations of the Church, or Communion, or Society of Christians; and which may regard men as they are members of that society, whether members of the Christian Church in the widest acceptation of the term, or members of some branch or communion of that Church, located in some separate kingdom, and governed according to its internal forms of constitution and discipline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Anon.|year=1837|title=Ecclesialogy|journal=[[The British Critic|The British Critic Quarterly Theological Review and Ecclesiastical Record]]|publisher=J.G. and F. Rivington|location=London|volume=XXII|issue=41|pages=218–248|url=http://www.google.co.uk/books?id=p2YYAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA220&amp;dq=Ecclesialogy&amp;cd=4#v=onepage&amp;q=Ecclesialogy&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

However in volume 4 of the [[Cambridge Camden Society]]'s journal ''The Ecclesiologist'', published in January 1845 that society (the CCS) claimed that they had invented the word ''ecclesiology'':&lt;ref name=TCM48 /&gt; {{quote|...as a general organ of Ecclesiology; that peculiar branch of science to which it seems scarcely too much to say, that this very magazine gave first its being and its name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=January 1845|title=Preface|journal=The Ecclesiologist|publisher=[[Cambridge Camden Society]]|volume=IV|issue=1|page=2|url=http://www.google.co.uk/books?id=8_5JAAAAMAAJ}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

''The Ecclesiologist'' was first published in October 1841 and dealt with the study of the building and decoration of churches. It particularly encouraged the restoration of Anglican churches back to their supposed Gothic splendour and it was at the centre of the wave of [[Victorian restoration]] that spread across England and Wales in the second half of the 19th century. Its successor ''Ecclesiology Today'' is still, as of 2011, being published by The Ecclesiological Society (successor to the CCS, now a [[registered charity]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ecclsoc.org/ |title=Church Architecture, Church furnishings, Church liturgy -  Homepage |publisher=The Ecclesiological Society |accessdate=2011-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The situation regarding the etymology has been summed up by [[Alister McGrath]]: &quot;'Ecclesiology' is a term that has changed its meaning in recent theology. Formerly the science of the building and decoration of churches, promoted by the Cambridge Camden Society, the Ecclesiological Society and the journal The Ecclesiologist, ecclesiology now stands for the study of the nature of the Christian church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=McGrath|first=Alister E.|title=The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Modern Christian Thought|chapter=Ecclesiology|page=127|year=1999|publisher=Blackwell|location=Oxford|url=http://www.google.co.uk/books?id=DvPMFcGIZgkC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Issues addressed by ecclesiology ==
{{Unreferenced|section|date=April 2012}}
* '''Who is the Church?'''  Is it a visible or earthly [[corporation]] or a unified, visible society—a &quot;church&quot; in the sense of a specific denomination or institution, for instance?  Or is it the body of all believing [[Christianity|Christians]] (see [[invisible church]]) regardless of their [[religious denomination|denominational]] differences and disunity?  What is the relationship between living Christians and [[saint|departed]] Christians (the &quot;[[cloud of witnesses]]&quot;) -- do they (those on Earth and those in Heaven) constitute together the Church?

* '''What is the relationship between a believer and the Church?''' That is, what is the role of corporate [[worship]] in the spiritual lives of believers?  Is it in fact necessary? Can salvation be found outside of formal membership in a given faith community, and what constitutes &quot;membership?&quot; ([[Baptism]]? Formal acceptance of a [[creed]]? Regular participation?)

* '''What is the [[authority]] of the Church?'''  Who gets to interpret the doctrines of the Church? Is the organizational structure itself, either in a single corporate body, or generally within the range of formal church structures, an ''independent vehicle'' of [[revelation]] or of [[God]]'s [[divine grace|grace]]?  Or is the Church's authority instead dependent on and derivative of a ''separate and prior divine revelation external to the organization'', with individual institutions being &quot;the Church&quot; only to the extent that they teach this message? For example, is the [[Bible]] a written part of a wider revelation entrusted to the Church as faith community, and therefore to be interpreted within that context? Or is the Bible the revelation itself, and the Church is to be defined as a group of people who claim adherence to it?

* '''What does the Church do?''' What are the [[sacrament]]s, divine ordinances, and [[liturgy|liturgies]], in the context of the Church, and are they part of the Church's mission to preach the [[Gospel]]? What is the comparative emphasis and relationship between [[worship]] service, [[spiritual formation]], and [[Mission (Christian)|mission]], and is the Church's role to create [[Disciple (Christianity)|disciple]]s of [[Christ]] or some other function? Is the Eucharist the defining element of the rest of the sacramental system and the Church itself, or is it secondary to the act of preaching? Is the Church to be understood as the vehicle for salvation, or the salvific presence in the world, or as a community of those already &quot;saved?&quot;

* '''How should the Church be governed?''' What was the mission and authority of the Apostles, and is this handed down through the sacraments today? What are the proper methods of choosing [[clergy]] such as [[bishop]]s and [[priest]]s, and what is their role within the context of the Church?  Is an [[Holy Orders|ordained]] clergy necessary? Who are the leaders of a church? Must there be a policy-making board of &quot;leaders&quot; within a church and what are the qualifications for this position, and by what process do these members become [[Holy Orders|official, ordained]] &quot;leaders&quot;? Must leaders and clergy be &quot;ordained,&quot; and is this possible  [[Apostolic succession|only by those who have been ordained by others]]?

* '''What are the roles of '[[spiritual gift]]s'''' in the life of the church?

* '''How does the Church's [[New Covenant]] relate to the [[Covenant (biblical)|covenants]]''' expressed in [[Bible|scripture]] with God's [[chosen people]], the Jewish people?

* '''What is the ultimate destiny of the Church''' in [[Christian eschatology]]?

== Roman Catholic ecclesiology ==
{{Unreferenced|section|date=April 2012}}
Roman Catholic ecclesiology today has a plurality of models and views, as with all Roman Catholic Theology since the acceptance of scholarly Biblical criticism that began in the early to mid 20th century.  This shift is most clearly marked by the encyclical [[Divino Afflante Spiritu]] in 1943.  Cardinal [[Avery Dulles]], S.J. contributed greatly to the use of models in understanding ecclesiology.  In his work Models of the Church, he defines four basic models of Church that have been prevalent throughout the history of the Catholic Church.  These include models of the Church as institution, as mystical communion, as herald, and as servant.

The ecclesiological model of Church as an Institution holds that the [[Catholic Church]] alone is the &quot;one, holy, catholic and apostolic Church&quot;, and is the only Church of divine and apostolic origin. This view of the Church is dogmatically defined Catholic doctrine, and is therefore [[de fide]]. In this view, the [[Catholic Church]]— composed of all baptized, professing Catholics, both clergy and laity— is the unified, visible society founded by [[Christ]] himself, and its hierarchy derives its spiritual authority through the centuries, via [[apostolic succession]] of its bishops, most especially through the [[bishop of Rome]] (the Pope) whose successorship comes from [[St. Peter the Apostle]], whom Christ gave &quot;the keys to the Kingdom of Heaven&quot;. Thus, the Popes, in the Catholic view, have a God-ordained universal jurisdiction over the whole Church on earth. The Catholic Church is considered Christ's mystical body, and the universal sacrament of salvation, whereby Christ enables men to receive sanctifying grace.

The model of Church as Mystical Communion draws on two major Biblical images, the first of the &quot;Mystical Body of Christ&quot; (as developed in Paul's Epistles) and the second of the &quot;People of God.&quot;  This ecclesiological model draws upon sociology and articulations of two types of social relationships: a formally organized or structured society (Gesellschaft) and an informal or interpersonal community (Gemeinschaft). The Roman Catholic theologian Arnold Rademacher maintained that the Church in its inner core is community (Gemeinschaft) and in its outer core society (Gesellschaft).  Here, the interpersonal aspect of the Church is given primacy and that the structured Church is the result of a real community of believers.  Similarly, [[Yves Congar]] argued that the ultimate reality of the Church is a fellowship of persons.  This ecclesiology opens itself to ecumenism and was the prevailing model used by the [[Second Vatican Council]] (itself considered by Roman Catholics an ecumenical council).  The Council, using this model, recognized in its document [[Lumen_Gentium#Ecclesiology_.28chapter_I.29|Lumen Gentium]] that the Body of Christ [[Subsistit in|subsists in]] a visible society governed by the [[Pope|Successor of Peter]] and by the Bishops in communion with him, although many elements of sanctification and of truth are found outside of its visible structure.

==Eastern Orthodox ecclesiology==
From the Orthodox perspective, the Church is one, even though She is manifested in many places. Orthodox ecclesiology operates with a plurality in unity and a unity in plurality. For Orthodoxy there is no ‘either / or’ between the one and the many. No attempt is made, or should be made, to subordinate the many to the one (the Roman Catholic model), nor the one to the many (the Protestant model). It is both canonically and theologically correct to speak of the Church and the churches, and vice versa.

==Protestant ecclesiology==
{{Main|Protestant ecclesiology}}

=== Magisterial Reformation ecclesiology ===
[[Martin Luther]] argued that because the Catholic Church had &quot;lost sight of the doctrine of grace&quot;, it had &quot;lost its claim to be considered as the authentic Christian church.&quot; ; this argument was open to the counter-criticism from Catholics that he was thus guilty of [[schism (religion)|schism]] and the heresy of [[Donatism]], and in both cases therefore opposing central teachings of the early Church and most especially the [[Church father]] [[St. Augustine of Hippo]].&lt;ref name=HT200&gt;McGrath, Alister. E. (1998). ''Historical Theology, An Introduction to the History of Christian Thought''. Oxford: Blackwell Publishers. p.200.&lt;/ref&gt; It also challenged the Catholic doctrine that the Catholic Church was [[indefectible]] and [[infallible]] in its dogmatic teachings.

=== Radical Reformation ecclesiology ===
There is no single &quot;Radical Reformation Ecclesiology&quot;. A variety of views is expressed among the various &quot;[[Radical Reformation]]&quot; participants.

A key &quot;Radical Reformer&quot; was [[Menno Simons]], known as an &quot;[[Anabaptist]]&quot;. He wrote:
:They verily are not the true congregation of Christ who merely boast of his name. But they are the true congregation of Christ who are truly converted, who are born from above of God, who are of a regenerate mind by the operation of the Holy Spirit through the hearing of the divine Word, and have become the children of God, have entered into obedience to him, and live unblamably in his holy commandments, and according to his holy will with all their days, or from the moment of their call.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=George|first=Timothy|title=Theology of the Reformers|year=1988|publisher=Broadman Press|location=Nashville, Tennessee|pages=285}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This was in direct contrast to the hierarchical, [[sacrament]]al ecclesiology that characterised the incumbent [[Roman Catholic]] tradition as well as the new [[Lutheran]] and other prominent [[Protestant]] movements of the [[Reformation]].

Some other Radical Reformation ecclesiology holds that &quot;the true church [is] in heaven, and no institution of any kind on earth merit[s] the name 'church of God.'&quot;&lt;ref name=HT200 /&gt;

==Notes==
{{refbegin}}
&lt;references group=notes/&gt;
{{refend}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{wiktionary}}
* [http://www.orthodox-church.info/ecclesiology.pdf A primer on Eastern Orthodox and Roman Catholic ecclesiology from an Orthodox perspective]
* [http://www.oodegr.com/english/biblia/episkopos1/perieh.htm Eucharist, Bishop, Church: The Unity of the Church in the Divine Eucharist and the Bishop during the First Three Centuries] by the Professor Metropolitan of Pergamus and  Chairman of the Athens Academy John Zizioulas

{{Christian theology}}
{{Christianityfooter}}
{{Theology}}

[[Category:Christian philosophy]]
[[Category:Christian group structuring]]
[[Category:Ecclesiology| ]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[az:Ekklesiologiya]]
[[be:Эклезіялогія]]
[[ca:Eclesiologia]]
[[cs:Ekleziologie]]
[[da:Ekklesiologi]]
[[de:Ekklesiologie]]
[[et:Eklesioloogia]]
[[el:Εκκλησιολογία]]
[[es:Eclesiología cristiana]]
[[fr:Ecclésiologie]]
[[gl:Eclesioloxía]]
[[id:Eklesiologi]]
[[it:Ecclesiologia]]
[[lv:Eklezioloģija]]
[[hu:Egyháztan]]
[[nl:Ecclesiologie]]
[[ja:教会論]]
[[no:Ekklesiologi]]
[[pl:Eklezjologia]]
[[pt:Eclesiologia]]
[[ru:Экклезиология]]
[[simple:Ecclesiology]]
[[sr:Еклисиологија]]
[[sh:Eklesiologija]]
[[fi:Kirkko-oppi]]
[[sv:Ecklesiologi]]
[[tr:Kilise bilimi]]
[[uk:Еклезіологія]]
[[zh:教会学]]</text>
      <sha1>g3jgizuo34fduqi0rtulzuu3erusopp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
