<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Eckankar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>380782</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522446818</id>
      <parentid>522446402</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T07:42:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sarunfeldt</username>
        <id>11092976</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>References to Akatha belong under &quot;Criticisms&quot; section or under a separate Wikipedia page on Akatha.  These sections lack citations and are argumentative.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29074">[[Image:USVA headstone emb-28.svg|thumb|Eckankar.]]
'''Eckankar''' is a new religious movement founded in the United States in 1965. It focuses on spiritual exercises claimed to enable practitioners to experience what its followers call &quot;the Light and Sound of God.&quot; The personal experience of this spiritual Light and Sound is a primary goal of the teaching. It claims to provide a personal, unique and individual spiritual inner path to understanding of self as soul, and development of higher awareness &quot;consciousness&quot; and God. An adherent of the religion is an ''Eckist''.

According to the Eckankar glossary, the term ''Eckankar'' means &quot;Co-Worker with God&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.com/glossary.html#eck A Glossary of ECK Terms]&lt;/ref&gt; Eckankar is described as &quot;Religion of the Light and Sound of God&quot;. Eckankar has also been described as &quot;The Ancient Science of Soul Travel,&quot; &quot;The Science of Total Awareness,&quot; and &quot;A Way of Life&quot;.
ECK is another word for the Holy Spirit, also known as the Audible Life Current, Life Force, or Light and Sound of God.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, ''Cosmic Sea of Words'', 55&lt;/ref&gt;

Linguistically, however, &quot;Eckankar&quot; derives from ''[[Ik Onkar|Ekankār]]'' or ''[[Ik Onkar|Ik Oankār]]'' (Sanskrit ''Eka Omkāra''), a [[Names of God|name for God]] given by [[Guru Nanak Dev|Guru Nānak]] and the very first word of the [[Mul Mantar|Mūl Mantra]] (recited everyday by Sikhs), the [[Japji Sahib|Japjī Sahib]], and the [[Guru Granth Sahib|Sri Guru Granth Sahib]] (Sikh holy scriptures). The word ''ek'' or ''ik'' is the number ''one'' in Hindī, Urdu, and Pañjabī (from the Sanskrit ''eka''). &quot;Ekankar&quot;, when written in the [[Gurmukhī alphabet]], is one of the two symbols of the Sikh faith (the other being the [[Khanda (Sikh symbol)|khanda]]) and can be found written or drawn on Sikh items, motor vehicles, and in all Sikh edifices and [[Gurdwara|Gurdwāra]] (temple).

Eckankar's headquarters are in [[Chanhassen, Minnesota]], southwest of [[Minneapolis]]. The Eckankar Temple, an outdoor chapel, an administrative building, and the ECK Spiritual Campus are located at this site.

==History==
The leader of Eckankar is known as the Mahanta,&lt;ref&gt;a word from the Prakrit languages of South Asia; [[mahant]] in modern Hindi. Mahanta is also a common surname in the state of Assam in India. Several public figures had this name, including [[Heerak Jyoti Mahanta]], Nani Mahanta, and most notably, [[Prafulla Kumar Mahanta]].&lt;/ref&gt; the Living ECK Master. According to Eckankar doctrine, the Living ECK Master is respected, but not worshipped, by followers of Eckankar and is seen as a spiritual guide for their own spiritual progress. [[Paul Twitchell]] founded Eckankar in 1965 as the Mahanta, the Living ECK Master and led it until his death in 1971. [[Darwin Gross]] (spiritual name: Dap Ren) then became the Mahanta serving until 1981. On October 23, 1981, [[Harold Klemp]] became the Mahanta and is the current spiritual leader of Eckankar.

==Teachings==
One of the basic tenets is that Soul (the true self) can leave the body in full consciousness and travel freely in other planes of reality.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Each and every man, when properly trained, is able to detach himself from the physical body while still living in that body in perfect health, and then travel to all parts of the outlying universe. Everyone has this ability whether he is conscious of it or not.&quot; -- Johnson, 1939, ''Path of the Masters'', page 343 (1985 pagination). Cited by Twitchell, ''Far Country'' chapter 5 page 117, ''Tiger's Fang'' ch 8 p 118, ''Spiritual Notebook'' pb ch 11 p 182&lt;/ref&gt; Eckankar emphasizes personal spiritual experiences as the most natural way back to God.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.org/SEW/ Eckankar: Spiritual Exercise of the Week]&lt;/ref&gt; These are attained via &quot;[[Soul Travel]]&quot;, shifting the awareness from the body to the inner planes of existence.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.187.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Certain [[mantra]]s or chants are used to facilitate spiritual growth. One important spiritual exercise of Eckankar is the singing or chanting of ''[[HU (Sufism)|HU]]''. The ''HU'' has been used in the [[Sufi]] and other mystical traditions, and is viewed in Eckankar as a &quot;love song to God&quot;. In American English, it is pronounced like the word &quot;hue&quot; in a long, drawn-out breath, and is sung for about 20 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;In Arabic, it is pronounced like the English word ''who''.&lt;/ref&gt; ECKists sing it alone or in groups.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.59.&lt;/ref&gt; ECKists believe this practice allows the student to step back from the overwhelming input of the physical senses and emotions and regain Soul's spiritually higher viewpoint.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.59.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dreams are regarded as important teaching tools, and members often keep [[dream journal]]s to facilitate study.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.org/dream.html Dreams: A Source of Inner Truth]&lt;/ref&gt; According to followers of Eckankar, dream travel often serves as the gateway to Soul Travel&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.org/soultravel.html Soul Travel]&lt;/ref&gt; or the shifting of one's consciousness to ever-higher states of being.

Eckankar teaches that &quot;spiritual liberation&quot; in one's lifetime is available to all and that it is possible to achieve Self-Realization (the realization of oneself as Soul) and God-Realization (the realization of oneself as a spark of God) in one's lifetime.&lt;ref&gt;In Indian philosophy, liberation during one's physical existence is called ''jivan mukti''. A major work on this theme is Fort &amp; Mumme, eds, 1996, ''Living Liberation in Hindu Thought'', Albany: SUNY Press.&lt;/ref&gt; The membership card for Eckankar states: &quot;The aim and purpose of Eckankar has always been to take Soul by Its own path back to Its divine source.&quot;

The ''Shariyat-Ki-Sugmad'', which means &quot;Way of the Eternal&quot;, is the holy scripture of Eckankar. The ''Shariyat'',&lt;ref&gt;The word ''shariyat'' or ''shariat'', used mostly in South Asia, is a derivative of the Arabic [[Sharia]].&lt;/ref&gt; as ECKists call it, is a set of two books that tell of spiritual meaning and purpose as written by the [[Mahanta]], the current head of Eckankar.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.59.&lt;/ref&gt;  

Some of the key beliefs taught in the ''Shariyat-Ki-Sugmad'' include [[Soul Travel]], [[karma]], [[reincarnation]], love, Light and Sound, and many other spiritual topics. ECKists believe Sugmad is the endless source from which all forms were created, and that the ECK, the Sound Current, flows out of Sugmad and into lower dimensions.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.59 &amp; p.187 &amp; p.194.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Shariyat-Ki-Sugmad'' is a set of two books and may now be considered scripture of Eckankar, however there are also a series of [[Satsang]] writings, that are available with yearly membership in Eckankar. There are Satsang classes available to study discourses with others, as well as individually.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.177.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Worship==

Eckankar emphasizes personal spiritual experiences as the most natural way back to God. These are attained via '''the Spiritual Exercises of ECK'''. Just as physical exercise helps one build physical vitality, Eckists use the spiritual exercises of ECK to help build spiritual vitality. There are many forms of spiritual exercise. Eckankar offers a Spiritual Exercise of the Week&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.org/spex.html] Spiritual Exercise of the Week &lt;/ref&gt; on it's website. 

One important spiritual exercise of Eckankar is the singing or chanting of '''HU'''. ''HU'' is an ancient name for God that has been used in many historical cultures including ancient Egypt and the Sufi tradition. HU is viewed in Eckankar as a &quot;love song to God&quot;. In American English, it is pronounced like the word &quot;hue&quot; in a long, drawn-out breath, and is sung for about 20 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;In Arabic, it is pronounced like the English word ''who''.&lt;/ref&gt; ECKists sing it alone or in groups. ECKists believe that singing HU draws one closer in state of consciousness to the Divine Being and that it can expand awareness, help one experience divine love, heal broken hears, offer solace in times of grief, and bring peace and calm.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eckankar.org/hu.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Eckankar hosts community HU Songs in most major cities and many local areas around the world. The Community HU Song is presented as a service to the local area and is open to people of all faiths. It consists of a 20 minute singing of the HU followed by a five minute contemplation. Attendees are invited to join in or merely observe silently. The Community HU Song is followed by a period of fellowship and refreshments.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.onlineprnews.com/news/230513-1337270208-eckankar-news-community-hu-song-to-uplift-all-people-spiritually.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Eckankar holds ECK Worship Services in most major cities and many local areas around the world. An ECK Worship service generally includes a HU Song and contemplation, a talk or panel discussion from members of the Eckankar Clergy, and often includes creative arts and group discussion.

Eckankar hosts a Worldwide Seminar in October and a Springtime Seminar every year. Eckankar also hosts annual seminars in many areas around the world. ECK seminars include speakers, creative arts, workshops, discussion groups and other activities. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.eckankar.org/Seminars/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spiritual leader==

===Harold Klemp===

[[Sri]] Harold Klemp is currently the ''Mahanta'', the Living ECK Master. His spiritual name is Wah Z. Eckankar always has a living master. Harold Klemp has authored numerous books, articles and discourses about the teachings of ECK. Audio and video recordings are available of his talks. He grew up on a Wisconsin farm, attended divinity school, and was a member of the [[Rosicrucian Order]]. In the 1960s he began studying the teachings of ECK. After years of rigorous spiritual training he became the Mahanta, the Living ECK Master in 1981.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.org/Harold/bioinfo.html Harold Bio Info]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;He has the ability to act as both the Inner and Outer Master for students of Eckankar.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, ''A Modern Prophet'', xii&lt;/ref&gt; Eckankar claims that &quot;many students of Eckankar report uplifting and life changing encounters with the inner Master, Wah Z, through dreams, spiritual exercises, soul travel experiences, and other means&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.org/Harold/stories.html Harold Stories]&lt;/ref&gt; Klemp claims that &quot;his teachings lift people and help them understand their own experiences in the Light and Sound of God&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, ''A Modern Prophet'', xii&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;As the Living ECK Master, Harold Klemp is responsible for the continued evolution of the Eckankar teachings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.org/Harold/bioinfo.html International Who's Who of Intellectuals]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins==
Although Twitchell founded Eckankar in 1965, ECKists claim that the basis for the Eckankar teachings dates back to the beginning of human life.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt;

Eckankar's headquarters was originally in Las Vegas, Nevada. Under the leadership of Darwin Gross, the organization was moved to Menlo Park, California in 1975. In 1986, Harold Klemp moved the base of operations to Minnesota, where it remains today.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;'Soul Travelers' Move,&quot; ''[[San Jose Mercury News]]'', 24 August 1986.&lt;/ref&gt;

Eckankar is accepted as a religion by the U.S. Army.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cem.va.gov/cem/hm/hmemb.asp US Military approved gravestone markers]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Beliefs==
Primary to the teaching is the belief that soul can leave the body. Also, the concepts of [[karma]] and [[reincarnation]] help to explain situations in life as the playing out of past causes.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, pp.186-187.&lt;/ref&gt;

The beliefs that individuals are responsible for their own destiny and that their decisions determine their future are important concepts to Eckankar. Eckankar students meet in open public services and classes to discuss personal experiences, topics, books and discourses.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.59.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the U.S. Department of State (International Religious Freedom Report for Côte d'Ivoire 2008), the current Nigerian branch of Eckankar describes its beliefs as &quot;a syncretistic religion founded in 1965 in Nigeria that sees human passion as an obstacle to uniting a person's divine qualities&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://64.233.167.104/search?q=cache:qtxc39Pk9Y8J:www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2001/5603.htm+bylaws+Eckankar+Inc.&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=21&amp;gl=us Highlighted Google page mentioning Eckankar / US Department of State 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current status==

Eckankar's {{convert|50000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} main &quot;Temple of ECK&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.com/Temple/index.html Eckankar: The Temple of ECK] in Chanhassen, Minnesota, USA&lt;/ref&gt; was dedicated in Chanhassen, Minnesota on October 22, 1990. As of late 2007, the largest capacity Eckankar Temple was in Port Harcourt, Rivers State, Nigeria, with a total capacity of 10,000.

The Eckankar &quot;EK&quot; symbol appears on the list of Available Emblems of Belief for Placement on Government Headstones and Markers by the United States Department of Veterans Affairs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cem.va.gov/cem/hm/hmemb.asp Available Emblems of Belief for Placement on Government Headstones and Markers – Burial &amp; Memorials]&lt;/ref&gt; Estimates on the number of Eckists worldwid ranges from 50,000 to 500,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religionfacts.com/big_religion_chart.htm The big religion chart] retrieved 9 November 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ceremonies and rites==
There are few personal requirements to be an ECKist; however, certain spiritual practices are recommended. Chief among these is daily practice of the &quot;Spiritual Exercises of ECK&quot; for 15–20 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.189.&lt;/ref&gt; The most basic ECK spiritual exercise is singing the word &quot;HU&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;...sound Hu is the beginning and the end of all sounds... The Supreme Being has been called by various names in different languages, but the mystics have known him as Hu, the natural name not man-made, the only name of the Nameless, which all nature constantly proclaims. The sound Hu is most sacred... The word Hu is the spirit of all sounds and of all worlds, and is hidden under them all...&quot; --Pir-o-Murshid Hazrat [[Inayat Khan]], quoted with proper attribution by Julian Johnson, ''The Path of the Masters'', chapter 11, subchapter 5, page 381 (1985 pagination). Cited in Paul Twitchell's ''The Flute of God'', chapter 6, page 75.&lt;/ref&gt; an ancient name for God, for upliftment and spiritual experiences.  A wide variety of spiritual exercises are offered, and members are encouraged to create their own. There are no dietary requirements, taboos, or enforced ascetic practices. Eckankar does not require potential members to leave their current faith to join.

There are a number of ceremonies an ECKist can experience as part of the teaching: 
* ECK Consecration Ceremony : Celebrating the entrance of the young and infant into Eckankar, and new life in the Light and Sound of God.
* ECK Rite of Passage : Celebrating the passage from youth into adulthood, usually around thirteen.
* ECK Wedding Ceremony : Celebrating the marriage bond as two ECKists commit their lives to one another before God.
* ECK Memorial Service : Honors the journey of Soul and welcomes It into the worlds beyond the physical.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.186.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Eckankar's original form, the Consecration Ceremony, Rite of Passage, and Memorial Service did not exist. Sri Harold Klemp, the Living ECK Master, added them later.

ECKists celebrate a spiritual new year on October 22. There is no organizational celebration of personal anniversaries, such as birthdays of the leaders.

==ECK Masters==
ECKists believe contact with Divine Spirit, which they call the ''ECK'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eckankar.org/glossary.html#eck A Glossary of ECK Terms]&lt;/ref&gt; can be made via the spiritual exercises of ECK and the guidance of the living ECK Master. It is held that the ECK Masters are here to serve all life irrespective of religious belief. The main Eckankar website offers this list of Masters: [http://www.eckankar.org/Masters/index.html Official Eckankar Masters List]&lt;ref&gt;From a disinterested and scholarly view, however, it's important to understand that, excepting Twitchell, none of these masters are historical figures. Like [[Blavatsky]]'s ascended masters of the Great White Brotherhood, there is no evidence from human history in any field of study to independently corroborate the historical existence of the ECK masters, other than the writings of Twitchell and his followers. &quot;Gopal Dās&quot; (&quot;Servant of Gopal,&quot; i.e. Krsna), a common name in [[Vaishnavism|Vaisnavism]], was the name of the first person initiated by Twitchell's guru Sant Kirpal Singh into the Sound and Light Path, but he was not a master.&lt;/ref&gt;

# [[Gopal Das]]
# [[Fubbi Quantz]]
# [[Kata Daki]]
# [[Lai Tsi]]
# [[Paul Twitchell]]
# [[Rami Nuri]]
# [[Rebazar Tarzs]]
# [[Towart Managi]]
# [[Yaubl Sacabi]]

==Related groups==
Several groups claimed to carry on the original teachings of Paul Twitchell and Eckankar. Sri Darwin Gross (now deceased) used the name Ancient Teaching of the Masters (ATOM), after being precluded from using the Eck terminology, Sri Paul Marché claims to carry on for his Master, Sri Darwin Gross using the name Dhunami [http://www.dhunami.org/], after being precluded from using the ATOM terminology. Other claimants include AKATHA [http://akatha.com/]—and Sri Timothy Arnold / Sri Kahtifji (The Mahaji) respectively.&lt;ref&gt;[http://santmat.livingcosmos.org/surat-shabd-yoga/ssy.mm.html Living Cosmos Santmat]&lt;/ref&gt; John-Roger's [[Movement of Spiritual Inner Awareness]] appears to have split from the main body of Eckankar, though Gross, Marché and Sri Kahtifji claim to be preserving the originality of the teachings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.paultwitchelltruth.com Paul Twitchell Truth.com]&lt;/ref&gt; John-Roger / [[Roger Delano Hinkins]] (2nd initiate) denies any connection to Eckankar beyond having once been a student of Paul Twitchell.{{citation needed|date=November 2010}}
More recently, former ECKist Ford Johnson formed a spiritual organization based on the idea that one does not need a master or spiritual guru to achieve spiritual enlightenment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetruth-seeker.com/openletter.asp The Truth Seeker]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.higherconsciousnesssociety.org/aboutHCS.asp Higher Consciousness Society]&lt;/ref&gt; Other former ECKists and their groups, like Sri Michael Owens's &quot;The Way of Truth: Path to God Realization&quot;; Sri Michael Turner's &quot;Yahoo group&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.yahoo.com/group/SFS Spiritual Freedom Satsang]&lt;/ref&gt; Sri Gary Olsen's &quot;MasterPath&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.masterpath.org MasterPath: Light and Sound is the Cutting Edge of Spirituality]&lt;/ref&gt; ex-6th initiate Jerry &quot;Sur Toma&quot; Mulvin's THE DIVINE SCIENCE OF LIGHT AND SOUND; and Evan Pritchard (author, ''From the Temple Within'') could be seen as individuals and organizations that maintain Eckankar-like cosmogonies.&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.59.&lt;/ref&gt; All these groups along with Eckankar were founded in the United States in the twentieth century.

[[David C. Lane]], a philosophy professor, discusses the phenomenon of those American teachers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vclass.mtsac.edu:930/phil/classnotes9.htm Introduction&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Lane suggests these might be seen more traditionally as an organic continuum or an historical school of &quot;American Shabd&quot; teachings, rather than a &quot;splintering&quot; of any movement. Lane is already distinguished in this particular subject{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}} for his research from the late 1990s concerning perceptions of distortions, plagiarism and concealment involving author Paul Twitchell during the first three decades of Eckankar's existence.     

The current leader of Eckankar has stated that members should feel free to leave Eckankar unbounded by guilt or fear.{{citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Criticism==
Internet communities of current members, ex-members and critics, such as the Usenet newsgroup alt.religion.eckankar, include discussion dating back more than ten years. Eckankar has been labeled a [[cult]] by some, including both former members and conservative Christian writers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icoc.us/view/?pageID=317591 Internet Church of Christ – List of Cults and Religions N-Z]&lt;/ref&gt;

After Twitchell's death in 1971, [[David C. Lane]] published a book&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20091026233847/http://geocities.com/eckcult/]&lt;/ref&gt; that claimed some of Twitchell's Eckankar books contained passages from other authors' books without proper citation. Lane claims Twitchell's ''The Far Country'' contains plagiarism (of ''With a Great Master in India''&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Julian. Beās: Radha Soami Satsang Beas, 1934, 1982, 1988, 1994. ISBN 81-8256-036-5&lt;/ref&gt; and ''The Path of the Masters'' by [[Julian Johnson]] of the [[Radha Soami Satsang Beas]]). 

Eckankar states that Twitchell's role was that of &quot;master compiler&quot;, saying;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;center&gt;'''Master Compiler [http://www.eckankar.org/Masters/Peddar/writings.html]'''&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;P&gt;

The high teachings of ECK had been scattered to the four corners of the world. The different masters each had parts and pieces of it, but they attached little requirements, or strings, to it: You must be a vegetarian, or you have to meditate so many hours a day if you want to really be a true follower on the path to God. And this was wrong for our day and age. It was geared for another culture.
&lt;P&gt;
Paul gathered up the whole teaching and took the best. Though it may be a strange thing to say, in this sense I see him as a master compiler. He gathered the golden teachings that were scattered around the world and made them readily available to us. So now we don't have to feel that we must spend ten or fifteen years in an ashram in India, sitting around in the dust with the flies, or locked in a walled-up little cell to keep our attention from the outside world, in order to live the spiritual life.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In 2007, Doug Marman, an Eckankar High Initiate, published ''The Whole Truth'', a biography of Paul Twitchell, refuting these claims made by Lane.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.littleknownpubs.com spiritualdialogues.com&lt;/ref&gt; The information is highly detailed and examines the criticisms point by point through verifiable historical references. Marman also examines the rarity of respectful dialog in an age of criticism.&lt;ref&gt;Marman, ''The Whole Truth''&lt;/ref&gt; In relation to this book, Twitchell's widow, Gail Twitchell, has written &quot;...finally, someone got the whole thing right ... Paul's work [put in] in the proper perspective.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiritualdialogues.com/: Spiritual Dialogs]&lt;/ref&gt; {{Verify credibility|date=May 2008}} Twitchell biographer and paranormal researcher [[Brad Steiger]]&lt;ref&gt;Steiger is the official author of ''In My Soul I Am Free'', Twitchell's authorised biography. However, the bulk of the book, maybe 90%, was written by Twitchell himself.&lt;/ref&gt; has also written and commended this work as the most researched and authoritative to date on Paul Twitchell. {{Verify credibility|date=May 2008}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiritualdialogues.com/: Spiritual Dialogs]&lt;/ref&gt;

Lane has published commentary on Marman's book, reaffirming his view that Twitchell tried to cover up his past associations and plagiarized several authors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://elearn.mtsac.edu/dlane/dougmarman.htm master index&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
However Harold Klemp has been criticized by several groups including AKATHA.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.akatha.com/uploads/9/4/9/6/9496706/hadjis-book-iii.pdf] Hadjis - Shariyat-Ki-Sugmad page 7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.akatha.com/free-audios-of-sri-kahtifjis-talks.html](Free Audio Recording titled “The history of AKATHA and its ties with old time ECKANKAR (pre 1972 and Sri Paul Twitchell.&lt;/ref&gt; and ATOM for losing sight of Paul Twitchell’s original teachings and creating a Religion and Cosmic consciousness path instead of a direct path back to Self-Realization, God-Realization and Eck Mastership as these groups claim Paul Twitchell clearly stated in his writings until his death in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.akatha.com/uploads/9/4/9/6/9496706/______hadjis-book-i.pdf] Hadjis – Shariyat-Ki-Sugmad Page 35.&lt;/ref&gt;

The emphasis has shifted away from out-of-body experiences to expansion of awareness through experiencing God's love in everyday matters. The final spiritual goal of all ECKists is to become conscious &quot;Co-workers&quot; with God.&lt;ref&gt;''Shariyat-Ki-Sugmad'', Books One and Two, 65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words''. Eckankar, 2009, p.59.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Contemporary Sant Mat movement]]
*[[Sri Darwin Gross]]
*[[Ik Onkar]]
*[[Karma]]
*[[Sri Harold Klemp]]
*[[Radha Soami]]
*[[Reincarnation]]
*[[Sant Mat]]
*[[Surat Shabd Yoga]]

==References==
{{reflist|3}}

== Bibliography ==
{{Further reading cleanup|date=January 2012}}
* Diem, Andrea Grace. ''The Guru in America''. A survey of offshoots of Sant Mat and Twitchell’s religion in the USA, by a religious scholar.
* Johnson, Ford. ''Confessions of a God Seeker: a journey to higher consciousness'', ONE Publishing.
* Johnson, Julian. ''The Path of the Masters: The Science of Surat Shabd Yoga: The Yoga of the Audible Life Stream'', France, 1939; USA, 1957; Beās, East Puñjab: [[Radha Soami Satsang Beas]], 1972, 1985, 1993. ISBN 81-8256-019-5 (Old copies of early editions available on Amazon.)
* Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words, The Eckankar Lexicon.'' Minneapolis: Eckankar,1998. ISBN 978-1-57043-307-8
* Klemp, Harold. ''A Cosmic Sea of Words, The ECKANKAR Lexicon''. Minneapolis: Eckankar, 2009. ISBN 978-1-57043-286-6
* Klemp, Harold. ''A Modern Prophet Answers Your Key Questions about Life.'' Minneapolis: Eckankar, 2010. ISBN 1-57043-142-6.
* Klemp, Harold (1989). ''The Secret Teachings'', Crystal, Minnesota: IWP. Mentions Kirpal Singh. ISBN 0-88155-082-5
* Lane, David Christopher, ''The Making of a Spiritual Movement: The Untold Story of Paul Twitchell and Eckankar'', Del Mar, California: Del Mar Press, 1990. ISBN 0-9611124-0-9  (Soft copies free online at David Lane's website. See http://web.archive.org/web/20091026233847/http://geocities.com/eckcult/)
* Marman, Doug (2007) ''The Whole Truth, The Spiritual Legacy of Paul Twitchell'', Ridgefield, Washington: Spiritual Dialogs Project. ISBN 978-0-9793260-0-4
* Twitchell, Paul (1971). ''The Far Country'', Menlo Park: IWP; Minneapolis: Eckankar. ISBN 0-914766-91-0
* Twitchell, Paul (1988). ''The Shariyat-Ki-Sugmad'', Books One and Two, Menlo Park: IWP; Minneapolis: Eckankar.

==External links==
{{External links|date=January 2012}}
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.eckankar.org Official website]
* [http://www.eckankarhistory.com EckankarHistory.com The Amazing Little Known Secret History of Eckankar]
* [http://www.religionfacts.com/a-z-religion-index/eckankar.htm ReligionFacts.com]
* [http://www.om-guru.com/html/saints/twitchell01.html Om Guru] Twitchell Biography
* [http://www.darwingrosstruthfile.homestead.com/dgtf.html Darwin Gross Truth Files]
* [http://www.akatha.com AKATHA the Ancient Science of Sahaji (Soul Travel in English)] AKATHA website claiming highest path
* [http://www.higherconsciousnesssociety.org/aboutHCS.asp Higher Consciousness Society] Ex-Eckankar High Initiate Ford Johnson's organization.
* [http://www.msia.org Movement of Spiritual Inner Awareness] Organization founded by a former Eckankar member
* [http://www.angelfire.com/hi2/eckankarsurvivors/rogue1.html Undoing the Damage of Rogue Light &amp; Sound Gurus]
* [http://www.stormpages.com/truthbeknown66/ Eckankar, A Spiritual Hoax] Anonymous criticism
* [http://groups.yahoo.com/group/EckankarSurvivorsAnonymous Eckankar Survivors Anonymous Yahoo Group] Anonymous criticism
* [http://elearn.mtsac.edu/dlane/ekdebates.htm The neural surfer: Eckankar]
* [https://www.europeanseminar.org/gb-index.html Eckankar News]
* [http://spiritualdialogues.com/thewholetruth.html The Whole Truth, Doug Marman]
* [http://soundofsamantabhadra.pbworks.com Sound of Samantabhadra] Discussion on Eckankar and claims on Buddhism

===Plagiarism discussion===
* [http://www.littleknownpubs.com/Dialog_Ch._One.htm Dialog in the Age of Criticism.] David Lane and Doug Marman discuss plagiarism
* [http://vclass.mtsac.edu:930/phil/center.htm Twitchell Plagiarism]

[[Category:Meditation]]
[[Category:New religious movements]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1965]]
[[Category:Shabd paths]]
[[Category:Monotheistic religions]]

[[de:Eckankar]]
[[fa:اکنکار]]
[[fr:Eckankar]]
[[id:Eckankar]]
[[nl:Eckankar]]
[[pl:Eckankar]]
[[pt:Eckankar]]
[[simple:Eckankar]]
[[fi:Eckankar]]
[[sv:Eckankar]]</text>
      <sha1>5gba7wdb3trd14l6c8t0l4r44wt4ud1</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
