<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ecumenism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>146656</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522409759</id>
      <parentid>522178370</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T00:57:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anupam</username>
        <id>1455149</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Opposition */ addition + reference</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41655">{{Refimprove|date=May 2009}}
{{Christianity}}

'''Ecumenism''' mainly refers to initiatives aimed at greater Christian unity or cooperation. It is used predominantly by and with reference to [[Christian denominations]] and [[Christian Church]]es separated by [[doctrine]], [[history]], and practice.  Within this particular context, the term ''ecumenism'' refers to the idea of a Christian unity in the literal meaning: that there should be a single Christian Church. Not to be confused with [[Nondenominational Christianity]].

The word contrasts with [[interfaith]] dialogue or interfaith pluralism aimed at unity or cooperation among diverse religions and referring to a worldwide 'religious unity' by the advocacy of a greater sense of shared [[spirituality]].

The word is derived from [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|οἰκουμένη}} (''[[oikoumene]]''), which means &quot;the whole inhabited world&quot;, and was historically used with specific reference to the [[Roman Empire]]. The ecumenical vision comprises both the search for the visible unity of the Church (Ephesians 4.3) and the 'whole inhabited earth' (Matthew 24.14) as the concern of all Christians.

In Christianity the qualification '''ecumenical''' is originally (and still) used in terms such as &quot;[[Ecumenical council]]&quot; and &quot;[[Ecumenical patriarch]]&quot; in the meaning of pertaining to the totality of the larger Church (such as the [[Catholic Church]] or the [[Orthodox Church]]) rather than being restricted to one of its constituent churches or [[diocese]]s. Used in this original sense, the term carries no connotation of re-uniting the historically separated Christian denominations.

==Christian ecumenism and interfaith pluralism==
Ecumenism is the movement within Christianity that aims at &quot;the recovery in thought, in action, and in organization, of the true unity between the Church's mission to the world (its apostolate) and the Church's obligation to be one.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Calling of the Church to Mission and to Unity,&quot; [[Theology Today]], vol. 9, no. 1 (April 1952): 15.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, ecumenism is the promotion of unity or cooperation between distinct religious groups or denominations of [[Christianity]]. Ecumenism is distinguished from and should not be misused to mean [[religious pluralism|interfaith pluralism]]. The [[interfaith]] movement strives for greater mutual respect, toleration, and co-operation among the [[Major world religions|world religions]]. Interfaith dialogue between representatives of diverse faiths, does not necessarily intend reconciling their adherents into full, [[organic unity]] with one another but simply to promote better relations.
[[File:ChristianFlagEtc CovenantPresbyterianLongBeach20050213 CopyrightKaihsuTai.jpg|thumb|left|320px|The [[Christian Flag]], which was designed to represent Christians, is paired with the flag of the United States of America and displayed next to the [[pulpit]] on the [[chancel]] of a church sanctuary.]]

For some Catholics it may, but not always, have the goal of reconciling all who profess Christian faith to bring them into a single, visible organization, i.e. through union with the [[Roman Catholic Church]].

For some [[Protestants]] spiritual unity, and often unity on the church's teachings on central issues, suffices. According to [[Lutheran]] theologian [[Edmund Schlink]], most important in Christian ecumenism is that people focus primarily on [[Jesus Christ|Christ]], not on separate church organizations. In Schlink's book ''Ökumenische Dogmatik'' (1983), he says Christians who see the risen Christ at work in the lives of various Christians or in diverse churches, realize that the unity of Christ's church has never been lost,&lt;ref&gt;[[Edmund Schlink]], ''Ökumenische Dogmatik'' (1983), pp. 694–701;  also his  &quot;Report,&quot; ''Dialog'' 1963, 2:4, 328.&lt;/ref&gt; but has instead been distorted and obscured by different historical experiences and by spiritual myopia. Both are overcome in renewed faith in Christ. Included in that is responding to his admonition (John 17; also Philippians 2) to be one in him and love one another as a witness to the world. The result of mutual recognition would be a discernible worldwide fellowship, organized in a historically new way.&lt;ref&gt;[[Edmund Schlink]], ''Ökumenische Dogmatik'' (1983), pp. 707–708; also Skibbe, ''A Quiet Reformer'' 1999, 122–4; Schlink, ''The Vision of the Pope'' 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

Standing against the modern ecumenist movement is the traditional Orthodox Church which staunchly maintains there is but one Church, and Orthodoxy is the Church. Thus, theories like &quot;sister church&quot; or &quot;two lungs&quot; are generally rejected, because in its view the Church is theologically indivisible. Leading the anti ecumenical movement in the 1980s was [[Fr. John Boylan]] of the [[Orthodox Church in America|OCA]].

An example of ecumenism is the invention of and growing usage of the [[Christian Flag]], which was designed to represent all of [[Christendom]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Prayer Foundation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.prayerfoundation.org/christian_flag.htm|title =The Christian Flag|publisher = Prayer Foundation|quote=The flag's most conspicuous symbol is the Christian cross, the most universal symbol for Christianity. The red color represents the blood of Christ and brings to mind his crucifixion.  Christians believe that Jesus Christ's death and resurrection is the means God uses to save believers from their sins. The cross and blood have been used since earliest Christianity to symbolize salvation through Jesus; in the words of the Apostle Paul, &quot;And having made peace through the blood of his cross, by him to reconcile all things unto himself;&quot; -Colossians 1:20. The white field draws on symbolism throughout the Bible equating white clothes with purity and forgiveness.  People who have been &quot;washed white as snow&quot; in the Bible have been cleansed from their sins (Isaiah 1:18; Psalm 51:2).  In conventional vexillology (the study of flags, their history and sybolism), a white flag is linked to surrender, a reference to the Biblical description Jesus' non-violence and surrender to God's will. The symbolism behind the blue canton has been interpreted to represent Heaven, truth, or the Christian ritual of Baptism in water.|accessdate = 2007–10–18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The flag has a white [[flag terminology|field]], with a red [[Latin cross]] inside a blue [[flag terminology|canton]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Prayer Foundation&quot;/&gt;

==Ecumenical movement==

The general understanding of the ecumenical movement is that it came from the Roman Catholic Church's attempts to reconcile with Christians who had become separated over theological issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howard C. Kee 1998&quot;&gt;Howard C. Kee et al., Christianity: a Social and Cultural History, 2nd ed. (Upper Saddle River, NJ.: Prentice Hall, 1998), 379-81.&lt;/ref&gt; After [[World War I]] the Catholic Church was not the only church which began to make changes within  the denomination. The world war had brought much devastation to many people. The church became a source of hope to those in need. In 1948 the first meeting of the World Council of Churches took place. Despite the fact that the meeting had been postponed due to World War 2, the council took place in Amsterdam with the theme of “Man’s Disorder and God’s Design”.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howard C. Kee 1998&quot;/&gt;  The focus of the church and the council following the gathering was on the damage created by the 2nd World War. The council and the movement went forward to continue the efforts of unity the church globally around the idea of helping all those in need whether it be a physical, emotional, or spiritual need. The movement led to an understanding amongst the churches that despite difference they could join together to be an element of great change in the world. To be an agent of hope and peace amongst the chaos and destruction that humans seem to create. More importantly the council and the movement lead to not only ecumenism but to the forming of councils amongst the denominations that connected churches across continental lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howard C. Kee 1998&quot;/&gt;
and dialogue is the heart of ecumenical cooperation.

==Three approaches to Christian unity==
{{Denominations of Christianity}}

For a significant part of the Christian world, one of the highest aims is the reconciliation of the various denominations by overcoming the historical divisions within Christianity. Still, approaches to ecumenism varies, i.e. while generally Protestants see it as agreements on teachings about central issues of faith, an organizational unity with mutual accountability between the parts, for Catholics and Orthodox the Christendom unity is approached within their more concrete understanding of the [[Body of Christ]] metaphor, this ecclesiological matter being closely linked to key theological issues (i.e. the [[Eucharist]]), demanding full dogmatic agreement before [[full communion]]. Thus, there are different answers even to the question ''[[ecclesiology|What is the Church?]]'', which finally is the goal of the ecumenist movement itself. However, the desire of unity is expressed by many denominations of [[Christendom]], generally that all who profess faith in Christ in sincerity, would be more fully cooperative and supportive of one another.

For the Catholic and Orthodox churches, the process of approaching one another is formally split in two successive stages: the &quot;dialogue of love&quot; and the &quot;dialogue of truth.&quot; To the former belong the mutual revocation in 1965 of the [[anathema]]s of 1054 (see below [[#Contemporary developments|Contemporary developments]]), returning the relics of [[Sabbas the Sanctified]] (a common saint) to [[Mar Saba]] in the same year, and the first visit of a Pope to an Orthodox country in a millennium ([[Pope]] [[John Paul II]] accepting the invitation of the [[Patriarch]] of the [[Romanian Orthodox Church]], [[Teoctist]], in 1999), among others. The later one, involving effective theological talks on matters of dogma, has yet to happen.

Christian ecumenism can be described in terms of the three largest divisions of Christianity: Roman Catholic, Eastern Orthodox, and Protestant.  While this underemphasizes the complexity of these divisions, it is a useful model.

===Catholicism===
{{Main|Catholic Church and ecumenism}}
The [[Catholic Church]] has always considered it a duty of the highest rank to seek full unity with estranged communions of fellow-Christians, and at the same time to reject what it saw as promiscuous and false union that would mean being unfaithful to or glossing over the teaching of Sacred Scripture and Tradition.

Before the [[Second Vatican Council]], the main stress was laid on this second aspect, as exemplified in canon 1258 of the 1917 Code of Canon Law:
#It is illicit for the faithful to assist at or participate in any way in non-Catholic religious functions.
#For a serious reason requiring, in case of doubt, the Bishop's approval, passive or merely material presence at non-Catholic funerals, weddings and similar occasions because of holding a civil office or as a courtesy can be tolerated, provided there is no danger of perversion or scandal.

The 1983 [[Canon law (Catholic Church)#Codification|Code of Canon Law]] has no corresponding canon. It absolutely forbids Catholic priests to concelebrate the Eucharist with members of communities not in full communion with the Catholic Church (canon 908), but allows, in certain circumstances and under certain conditions, other sharing in the sacraments. And the ''Directory for the Application of Principles and Norms on Ecumenism'', 102&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adoremus.org/EcumenismNorms.html Directory For The Application Of Principles And Norms On Ecumenism&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; states: &quot;Christians may be encouraged to share in spiritual activities and resources, i.e., to share that spiritual heritage they have in common in a manner and to a degree appropriate to their present divided state.&quot;

[[Pope John XXIII]], who convoked the Council that brought this change of emphasis about, said that the Council's aim was to seek renewal of the Church itself, which would serve, for those separated from the See of Rome, as a &quot;gentle invitation to seek and find that unity for which Jesus Christ prayed so ardently to his heavenly Father.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Encyclical [http://www.newadvent.org/library/docs_jo23ap.htm ''Ad Petri cathedram'']&lt;/ref&gt;

Some elements of the Roman Catholic perspective on ecumenism are illustrated in the following quotations from the Council's decree on ecumenism, ''[[Unitatis Redintegratio]]'' of 21 November 1964, and [[Pope John Paul II]]'s encyclical, ''[[Ut Unum Sint]]'' of 25 May 1995.

{{quote|Every renewal of the Church is essentially grounded in an increase of fidelity to her own calling. Undoubtedly this is the basis of the movement toward unity ... There can be no ecumenism worthy of the name without a change of heart. For it is from renewal of the inner life of our minds, from self-denial and an unstinted love that desires of unity take their rise and develop in a mature way. We should therefore pray to the Holy Spirit for the grace to be genuinely self-denying, humble. gentle in the service of others, and to have an attitude of brotherly generosity towards them. ... The words of St. John hold good about sins against unity: &quot;If we say we have not sinned, we make him a liar, and his word is not in us&quot;. So we humbly beg pardon of God and of our separated brethren, just as we forgive them that trespass against us.|&lt;ref&gt;[www.vatican.va/.../ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_decree_19641121_unitatis-redintegratio_en.html ''Unitatis Redintegratio''] 6-7&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote|Christians cannot underestimate the burden of long-standing misgivings inherited from the past, and of mutual misunderstandings and prejudices. Complacency, indifference and insufficient knowledge of one another often make this situation worse. Consequently, the commitment to ecumenism must be based upon the conversion of hearts and upon prayer, which will also lead to the necessary purification of past memories. With the grace of the Holy Spirit, the Lord's disciples, inspired by love, by the power of the truth and by a sincere desire for mutual forgiveness and reconciliation, are called to re-examine together their painful past and the hurt which that past regrettably continues to provoke even today.|&lt;ref&gt;Encyclical ''Ut unum sint'', 2[www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/encyclicals/documents/hf_jp-ii_enc_25051995_ut-unum-sint_en.html]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote|In ecumenical dialogue, Catholic theologians standing fast by the teaching of the Church and investigating the divine mysteries with the separated brethren must proceed with love for the truth, with charity, and with humility. When comparing doctrines with one another, they should remember that in Catholic doctrine there exists a &quot;hierarchy&quot; of truths, since they vary in their relation to the fundamental Christian faith. Thus the way will be opened by which through fraternal rivalry all will be stirred to a deeper understanding and a clearer presentation of the unfathomable riches of Christ.|&lt;ref&gt;''[[Unitatis Redintegratio]]'', 11[www.vatican.va/.../ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_decree_19641121_unitatis-redintegratio_en.html]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote|The unity willed by God can be attained only by the adherence of all to the content of revealed faith in its entirety. In matters of faith, compromise is in contradiction with God who is Truth. In the Body of Christ, &quot;the way, and the truth, and the life&quot; (Jn 14:6), who could consider legitimate a reconciliation brought about at the expense of the truth?...Even so, doctrine needs to be presented in a way that makes it understandable to those for whom God himself intends it.|&lt;ref&gt;Encyclical ''Ut unum sint'', 18-19[www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/encyclicals/documents/hf_jp-ii_enc_25051995_ut-unum-sint_en.html]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{quote|When the obstacles to perfect ecclesiastical communion have been gradually overcome, all Christians will at last, in a common celebration of the Eucharist, be gathered into the one and only Church in that unity which Christ bestowed on his Church from the beginning. We believe that this unity subsists in the Catholic Church as something she can never lose, and we hope that it will continue to increase until the end of time.|&lt;ref&gt;''[[Unitatis Redintegratio]]'', 4[www.vatican.va/.../ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_decree_19641121_unitatis-redintegratio_en.html]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

While some Eastern Orthodox Churches commonly baptize converts from the Catholic Church, thereby refusing to recognize the baptism that the converts have previously received, the Catholic Church has always accepted the validity of all the sacraments administered by the Eastern Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox Churches.

The Catholic Church likewise has never applied the terms &quot;[[heterodoxy|heterodox]]&quot; or &quot;[[heresy|heretic]]&quot; to the Eastern Orthodox Church or its members.  Even the term &quot;schism&quot;, as defined in canon 751 of its Code of Canon Law (&quot;the ''withdrawal'' of submission to the Supreme Pontiff or from communion with the members of the Church subject to him&quot;), does not, strictly speaking, apply to the situation of the concrete individual members of the Eastern Orthodox Church today as viewed by the Catholic Church.

===Eastern Orthodoxy===
The [[Oriental Orthodox]] and [[Eastern Orthodox]] churches are two distinct bodies of local churches. The churches within each body share [[full communion]], although there is not official communion between the two bodies. Both consider themselves to be the original church, from which the [[Western Christianity|West]] was divided in the 5th and 11th centuries, respectively (after the 3rd and 7th [[Ecumenical council]]s).

Many theologians of the Eastern and Oriental Orthodoxies engage in theological dialogue with each other and with some of the Western churches, though short of full communion. The Eastern Orthodox have participated in the [[interfaith]] movement, with students active in the [[World Student Christian Federation]] since the late 19th century and some Orthodox patriarchs enlisting their communions as charter members of the [[World Council of Churches]].

Nevertheless, the Orthodox have not been willing to participate in any redefinition of the Christian faith toward a reduced, minimal, anti-dogmatic and anti-traditional Christianity. Christianity for the Eastern Orthodox is the Church; and the Church is Orthodoxy&amp;mdash;nothing less and nothing else. Therefore, while Orthodox ecumenism is &quot;open to dialogue with the devil himself&quot;, the Orthodox have defined their position in the ecumenical movement as being &quot;witnesses to the truth&quot;, the goal being to reconcile the [[heterodox]] (i.e., non-Orthodox) back into Orthodoxy. {{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

Also Protestants and Roman Catholics are often referred to as &quot;heterodox&quot;, which simply means &quot;other believing&quot;, rather than as [[heresy|heretics]], implying that they did not willfully reject the Church.

===Anglicanism and Protestantism===
{{details|Anglican communion and ecumenism|the on-going dialogue between the Anglican Communion and the wider Church}}

The members of the [[Anglican Communion]] have generally embraced the Ecumenical Movement, actively participating in such organizations as the [[World Council of Churches]] and the [[NCCC]]. Most provinces holding membership in the Anglican Communion have special departments devoted to ecumenical relations; however, the influence of [[Liberal Christianity]] has in recent years caused tension within the communion, causing some to question the direction ecumenism has taken them.

Each member church of the Anglican Communion makes its own decisions with regard to [[intercommunion]]. Many of them are currently out of communion with other provinces of the Anglican Communion. The 1958 [[Lambeth Conference]] recommended &quot;that where between two Churches not of the same denominational or confessional family, there is unrestricted ''[[full communion|communio in sacris]]'', including mutual recognition and acceptance of ministries, the appropriate term to use is '[[full communion]],' and that where varying degrees of relation other than 'full communion' are established by agreement between two such churches the appropriate term is '[[intercommunion]].'

Full communion has been established between Provinces of the Anglican Communion and these Churches:
*[[Old Catholic Church]]es of Europe
*[[Philippine Independent Church]]
*[[Mar Thoma Syrian Church of Malabar]]
*[[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]]
*the [[Moravian Church]] in America, Northern and Southern Provinces

The [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopal Church]] is currently engaged in dialogue with the following religious bodies:
*[[Churches Uniting in Christ]] (CUIC)
*[[Eastern Orthodox Church]]
*[[Roman Catholic Church]]
*[[Presbyterian Church USA]]
*[[United Methodist Church]]
*[[Reformed Episcopal Church]] and the [[Anglican Province of America]]

Worldwide, an estimated forty million Anglicans belong to churches that do not participate in the Anglican Communion, a particular organization limited to one province per country. In these Anglican churches, there is strong opposition to the ecumenical movement and to membership in such bodies as the World and National Councils of Churches. Most of these churches are associated with the [[Continuing Anglican movement]] or the movement for [[Anglican realignment]]. While ecumenicalism in general is opposed, certain Anglican church bodies that are not members of the Anglican Communion--the [[Free Church of England]] and the [[Church of England in South Africa]], for example--have fostered close and cooperative relations with other evangelical (if non-Anglican) churches, on an individual basis.  

{{POV|Unreferenced section|date=May 2009}}

Nicolaus Ludwig, Count von [[Zinzendorf]], (1700–1760) the renewer of the [[Unitas Fratrum]]/ [[Moravian Church]] in the 18th Century, was the first person to use the word &quot;ecumenical&quot; in this sense.  His pioneering efforts to unite all Christians, regardless of denominational labels, into a &quot;Church of God in the Spirit&quot;---notably among [[Germans|German]] immigrants in [[Pennsylvania]]—were misunderstood by his contemporaries and 200 years before the world was ready for them.

The contemporary ecumenical movement for Protestants is often said to have started with the 1910 [[Edinburgh Missionary Conference]]. However this conference would not have been possible without the pioneering ecumenical work of the Christian youth movements: the [[Young Men's Christian Association]] (founded 1844), the [[Young Women's Christian Association]] (founded 1855), the [[World Student Christian Federation]] (founded 1895), and the '''Federal Council of Churches''' (founded 1908), predecessor to today's [[National Council of Churches USA]].
Led by [[Methodist]] layman [[John R. Mott]] (former YMCA staff and in 1910 the General Secretary of WSCF), the World Mission conference marked the largest Protestant gathering to that time, with the express purposes of working across denominational lines for the sake of [[Mission (Christian)|world missions]]. After the [[First World War]] further developments were the &quot;Faith and Order&quot; movement led by [[Charles Henry Brent]], and the &quot;[[Life and Work (conference)|Life and Work]]&quot; movement led by [[Nathan Soderblom]].  In the 1930s, the tradition of an annual [[World Communion Sunday]] to celebrate ecumenical ties was established in the [[Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.)|Presbyterian Church]] and was subsequently adopted by several other denominations.

Eventually, formal organizations were formed, including the [[World Council of Churches]] in 1948, the [[National Council of Churches]] in the USA in 1950, and [[Churches Uniting in Christ]] in 2002. These groups are moderate to liberal, theologically speaking, as Protestants are generally more liberal and less traditional than Anglicans, Orthodox, and Roman Catholics.

Protestants are now involved in a variety of ecumenical groups, working in some cases toward organic denominational unity and in other cases for cooperative purposes alone.  Because of the wide spectrum of Protestant denominations and perspectives, full cooperation has been difficult at times. [[Edmund Schlink]]'s ''Ökumenische Dogmatik'' 1983, 1997 proposes a way through these problems to mutual recognition and renewed church unity.

In 1999, the representatives of [[Lutheran World Federation]] and [[Roman Catholic Church]] signed The [[Joint Declaration on the Doctrine of Justification]],  resolving the conflict over the nature of [[Justification (theology)|Justification]] which was at the root of the [[Protestant Reformation]], although some conservative Lutherans did not agree to this resolution. On July 18, 2006 Delegates to the [[World Methodist Council|World Methodist Conference]] voted unanimously to adopt the Joint Declaration. [http://www.umc.org/site/c.gjJTJbMUIuE/b.1863123/k.FF49/World_Methodists_approve_further_ecumenical_dialogue.htm] [http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/0604186.htm]

==Contemporary developments==
[[Image:Taizé prayer.JPG|thumb|Ecumenical worship service at the [[monastery]] of [[Taizé]]]]

===Catholic-Orthodox dialogue===
The mutual [[anathema]]s (excommunications) of 1054, marking the [[East-West Schism|Great Schism]] between Western (Catholic) and Eastern (Orthodox) branches of Christianity, a process spanning several centuries, were revoked in 1965 by the Pope and the [[Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople]]. It is to be noted that the Canon Law of the Catholic Church states: &quot;An apostate from the faith, a heretic or a schismatic incurs a latae sententiae [automatic] excommunication, without prejudice to the provision of Can. 194 §1, n. 2; a cleric, moreover, may be punished with the penalties mentioned in Can. 1336 §1, nn. 1, 2 and 3.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ourladyswarriors.org/canon/c1364-1399.htm Code of Canon Law, Canon 1364-1399]&lt;/ref&gt; This penalty would include the Eastern Orthodox and other non-Catholic sects. Also, similar provisions exist in the Canon Law followed by the Eastern Orthodox.

The year 2006 saw a resumption of the series of meetings for theological dialogue between representatives of the Roman Catholic and the Eastern Orthodox Churches, suspended because of failure to reach agreement on the question of the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]], a question exacerbated by disputes over churches and other property that the Communist authorities once assigned to the Orthodox Church but whose restoration these Churches have obtained from the present authorities.

Catholic and Orthodox bishops in North America are engaged in an ongoing dialogue. They are meeting together periodically as the &quot;North American Orthodox-Catholic Theological Consultation&quot;. It has been meeting semi-annually since it was founded in 1965 under the auspices of the [[U.S. Bishops' Committee for Ecumenical and Interreligious Affairs]] of the [[United States Conference of Catholic Bishops]] and the Standing Conference of Canonical Orthodox Bishops in the Americas (SCOBA). The Canadian Conference of Catholic Bishops officially joined the Consultation as a sponsor in 1997. The Consultation works in tandem with the Joint Committee of Orthodox and Catholic Bishops which has been meeting annually since 1981. Since 1999 the Consultation has been discussing the [[Filioque clause]], with the hope of eventually reaching an agreed joint statement.

Similar dialogues at both international and national level continue between, for instance, Roman Catholics and Anglicans.

===Issues within Protestantism===

Contemporary developments in mainline Protestant churches have dealt a serious blow to ecumenism. The decision by the U.S. [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopal Church]] to ordain [[Gene Robinson]], an openly gay, non-celibate priest who advocates same-sex blessings, as bishop led the [[Russian Orthodox Church]] to suspend its cooperation with the Episcopal Church. Likewise, when the [[Church of Sweden]] decided to bless same-sex marriages, the Russian Patriarchate severed all relations with the Church, noting that &quot;Approving the shameful practice of same-sex marriages is a serious blow to the entire system of European spiritual and moral values influenced by Christianity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.pravda.ru/%20main/18/90/359/16696_gay.html Russian Orthodox Church condemns Lutheran gay weddings] ''Pravda,'' 30 December 2005. Accessed 24 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bishop [[Hilarion Alfeyev]] commented that the inter-Christian community is &quot;bursting at the seams.&quot; He sees the great dividing line - or &quot;abyss&quot; - not so much between old churches and church families as between &quot;traditionalists&quot; and &quot;liberals&quot;, the latter now dominating Protestantism, and predicted that other Northern Protestant Churches will follow suit and this means that the “ecumenical ship” will sink, for with the liberalism that is materializing in European Protestant churches, there is no longer anything to talk about.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.synod.com/synod/en/documents/enart_interviewrocor.html Bishop Hilarion Alfeyev: Will the Ecumenical Ship Sink?] The Official Website of the Synod of Bishops of the Russian Orthodox Church Outside of Russia. Accessed 24 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Organizations such as the [[World Council of Churches]], the [[National Council of Churches USA]], [[Churches Uniting in Christ]], [[Pentecostal Charismatic Peace Fellowship]] and [[Christian Churches Together]] continue to encourage ecumenical cooperation among Protestants, Eastern Orthodox, and, at times, Roman Catholics. There are universities such as the [[University of Bonn]] in Germany that offer degree courses in &quot;Ecumenical Studies&quot; in which theologians of various denominations teach their respective traditions and, at the same time, seek for common ground between these traditions.

Influenced by the ecumenical movement, the &quot;scandal of separation&quot; and local developments, a number of [[United and uniting churches]] have formed; there are also a range of mutual recognition strategies being practiced where formal union is not feasible.  An increasing trend has been the sharing of church buildings by two or more denominations, either holding separate services or a single service with elements of all traditions.

==Opposition==
=== Opposition from some Methodist Christians===
There are some in [[The United Methodist Church]] who oppose the forms of ecumenism which are &quot;not grounded in the doctrines of the Church&quot; due to the fear of compromisation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.episcopalchurch.org/documents/abrahampaper.pdf|title=United Methodist Evangelicals and Ecumenism|year=2012|publisher=Southern Methodist University|language=English|accessdate=11 November 2012|author=[[William J. Abraham]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, an article published in ''Catalyst Online: Contemporary Evangelical Perspectives for United Methodist Seminarians'' stated that false ecumenism might result in the &quot;blurring of theological and confessional differences in the interests of unity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://catalystresources.org/issues/303balmer.html|publisher=Catalyst Online: Contemporary Evangelical Perspectives for United Methodist Seminarians|year=1998|title=The Future of American Protestantism|language=English|accessdate=11 November 2012|author=[[Randall Balmer]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

=== Opposition from some Orthodox Christians===
{{See also|Sobornost}}
Despite many disagreements over ecumenism and how to approach interfaith dialog, there exists a sizable group of Orthodox Christians who are vehemently opposed to any kind of [[interfaith dialog]], whether with other Christian denominations or religions outside Christianity. They view ecumenism and interfaith dialog as being potentially pernicious to Orthodox Church Tradition; a &quot;weakening&quot; of Orthodoxy itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ecumenism Awareness Introduction|accessdate=2008-12-30|url=http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/ecumenism/|author=Patrick Barnes|publisher=Orthodox Christian Information Center}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Eastern Orthodox world, the monastic community of [[Mount Athos]], arguably the most important center of Orthodox spirituality, has voiced its concerns regarding the ecumenist movement and opposition to the participation of the Orthodox Church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Memorandum on the Participation of the Orthodox Church in the World Council of Churches|date=2007-02-18|accessdate=2008-11-01|url=http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/ecumenism/memorandum-on-the-participation-of-the-orthodox-church-in-the-world-council-of-churches.aspx|author=The Theological Committee of the Sacred Community of Mount Athos|publisher=orthodoxinfo.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

They regard modern ecumenism as compromising essential doctrinal stands in order to accommodate other Christians, and object to the emphasis on dialogue leading to intercommunion rather than conversion on the part of participants in ecumenical initiatives. [[Greek Old Calendarists]] also claim that the teachings of the [[Seven Ecumenical Councils]] forbid changing the church calendar through abandonment of the [[Julian calendar]]. The Inter-Orthodox Theological Conference entitled &quot;Ecumenism: Origins, Expectations, Disenchantment&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/ecumenism/thess_conclusions.aspx|title=Conclusions of the Inter-Orthodox Theological Conference &quot;Ecumenism: Origins Expectations Disenchantment&quot;|publisher=orthodox.info|accessdate=2008-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; organized in September 2004 by the [[Aristotelian University of Thessaloniki]] has drawn negative conclusions on ecumenism.

==Popular culture==

The word ''ecumenical'' arises in the ''[[Father Ted]]'' episode [[Tentacles of Doom]], in which Father Ted sets out to train Father Jack to say two all-encompassing phrases in response to questions from three visiting bishops, namely &quot;Yes&quot; and &quot;that would be an ecumenical matter&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0578519/quotes&lt;/ref&gt;

In the strategy game [[Europa Universalis III]], the player can select 'Ecumenism' as a National Idea. This increases tolerance of &quot;heretical religions&quot; (i.e. religions that are related to but not part of the state's religion) within the player's country.

==Ecumenical organizations==
&lt;!-- Please only put large ecumenical organizations here --&gt;
{{multicol}}
*[[Action of Churches Together in Scotland]]
*[http://www.aclc.info/ American Clergy Leadership Conference (ACLC)]
*[[Bose Monastic Community]]
*[[Byzantine Discalced Carmelites]]
*[[Campus Crusade for Christ]]
*[[Canadian Council of Churches]]
*[[Christian Churches Together]] in the USA
*[[Churches Together in Britain and Ireland]]
*[[Churches Together in England]]
*[[Churches Uniting in Christ]]
{{multicol-break}}
*[[Conference of European Churches]]
*[http://www.free-catholic.org/ Ecumenical Free Catholic Communion]
*[http://gospelmission.in Ecumenical Gospel Mission of India]
*[[Ecumenical Institute for Study and Dialogue]]
*[[Edinburgh Churches Together]]
*[[Fellowship of Saint Alban and Saint Sergius]]
*[[Franciscan Hermitage of Campello, Italy]]
*[http://www.tongilgyo.org/system/main_en Holy Spirit Association for the Unification of World Christianity (HSA-UWC/Unification Church/Unification Movement)]
*[[International Circle of Faith]]
*[[Iona Community]]
{{multicol-break}}
*[[National Council of the Churches of Christ in the U.S.A.]]
*[[New Monasticism]] related Communities
*[[Pentecostal Charismatic Peace Fellowship]]
*[[Pontifical Council for Promoting Christian Unity]]
*[[Prairie Centre for Ecumenism]]
*[[Society of Ordained Scientists]]
*[[Taizé Community]]
*[[Word Made Flesh]]
*[[World Alliance of Reformed Churches]]
*[[World Council of Churches]]
*[[World Student Christian Federation]]
{{multicol-end}}

==See also==
* [[Accord (coalition)|Accord Coalition]], uniting the religious &amp; non-religious concerned about religious inclusivity in education (England and Wales)
* [[Anonymous Christian]]
* [[Ecumenical council]]
* [[Inclusivism]]
* [[Invisible church]]
* [[One true church]]
* [[One true faith]]
* [[Postmodern Christianity]]
* [[Religious pluralism]]
* [[Socratic questioning]]
* [[Syncretism]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Bibliography ==
* Borkowski, James D. &quot;Middle East Ecumenism from an Anglican Perspective&quot; Cloverdale Books (2007) ISBN 978-1-929569-23-6 [http://www.cloverdalebooks.com/CloverdaleBooks/MiddleEastEcumenism.html]
* Hein, David. &quot;The Episcopal Church and the Ecumenical Movement, 1937–1997: Presbyterians, Lutherans, and the Future.&quot; ''Anglican and Episcopal History'' 66 (1997): 4–29.
* Hein, David. ''Geoffrey Fisher: Archbishop of Canterbury, 1945–1961''. Eugene, OR: Pickwick Publications, 2007. Chapters 2 (&quot;Chester and London&quot;) and 5 (&quot;Ecumenical Outreach&quot;) discuss relations between Anglicans and Free Churches, Roman Catholics, and Eastern Orthodox in the period 1940 to 1961.
* Hein, David. &quot;Radical Ecumenism.&quot; ''Sewanee Theological Review'' 51 (June 2008): 314–328. Proposes that mainline Protestants, such as Episcopalians, have much to learn from heirs of the Radical Reformation, including the Amish.
* ''A History of the Ecumenical Movement 1517-1948'', edited by Ruth Rouse and Stephen Charles Neill (Philadelphia: Westminster Press, 1954).
* ''The Ecumenical Advance: A History of the Ecumenical Movement, volume 2, 1948-1968'', edited by Harold E. Fey (London: S.P.C.K., 1970).
* ''A History of the Ecumenical Movement, volume 3, 1968-2000'', edited by John Briggs, Mercy Amba Oduyoye and Georges Tsetsis (Geneva: World Council of Churches, 2004).
* Kasper, Walter, ''That They May All Be One: The Call to Unity Today'' (London: Burns &amp; Oates, 2004).
* Kasper, Walter, ''Harvesting the Fruits: Aspects of Christian Faith in Ecumenical Dialogue'' (New York: Continuum, 2009).
* Mackay, John A., ''Ecumenics: The Science of the Church Universal'' (Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, Inc: 1964).
* Mastrantonis, George. &quot;Augsburg and Constantinople : The Correspondence between the Tübingen Theologians and Patriarch Jeremiah II of Constantinople on the Augsburg Confession.&quot; Holy Cross Orthodox Press (1982), reprinted (2005). ISBN 0-916586-82-0
* Metzger, John Mackay, ''The Hand and the Road: The Life and Times of John A. Mackay'' (Louisville, Kentucky: Westminster John Knox Press, 2010).
* ''Ut Unum Sint'' (“That they may be one”), an encyclical by Pope John Paul II of May 25, 1995 on commitment to ecumenism.
* ''Unitatis Redintegratio'' (&quot;Restoration of Unity&quot;), Second Vatican Council's Decree on Ecumenism, promulgated by Pope Paul VI on November 21, 1964.
* Visser ’t Hooft, Willem Adolf, “Appendix I: The Word ‘Ecumenical’ – Its History and Use,” in ''A History of the Ecumenical Movement 1517-1948'', edited by Ruth Rouse and Stephen Charles Neill (Philadelphia: Westminster Press, 1954), 735-740.
* Weigel, Gustave, S.J., ''A Catholic Primer on the Ecumenical Movement'' (Westminster, Maryland: Newman Press, 1957).
* McSorley, Harry J., [[Paulists|C. S. P]]., ''Luther: Right or Wrong? An Ecumenical-Theological Study of Luther's Major Work, [[On the Bondage of the Will|The Bondage of the Will]]'', Minneapolis, Minnesota, Augsburg Publishing House, 1968. [http://books.google.com/books?ei=ZkkQTbPjHcGclgeG-LSyDA&amp;ct=result&amp;id=KaRAAAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=Luther%3A+right+or+wrong+mcsorley&amp;q=mcsorley#search_anchor] Originally published under the German title: ''Luthers Lehre vom unfreien Willen: nach seiner Hauptschrift De servo arbitrio im Lichte der biblischen und kirchlichen Tradition'' [http://books.google.com/books?id=LeEQAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22luthers+lehre+vom+unfreien+willen+nach+seiner+hauptschrift+de+servo+arbitrio%22&amp;dq=%22luthers+lehre+vom+unfreien+willen+nach+seiner+hauptschrift+de+servo+arbitrio%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=_x8RTabqFcL38Abn46iqDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAg] in: ''Beiträge zur ökumenischen Theologie'', Band II, hrsg. (herausgegeben i.e. editor), H. Fries (Max Hueber Verlag: Munich, 1967). [http://books.google.com/books?id=xeMNAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22Beitr%C3%A4ge+zur+%C3%B6kumenischen+Theologie%22&amp;dq=%22Beitr%C3%A4ge+zur+%C3%B6kumenischen+Theologie%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=3hwRTc2SIYP78Aaemvi7Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA]

==External links==
{{Commons category|Ecumenism}}
*{{dmoz|Society/Religion_and_Spirituality/Christianity/Ecumenism}}
{{Religion topics}}
* [http://www.thinkunity.com Christian Mysticism is unity with all]

[[Category:Christian ecumenism| ]]
[[Category:Interfaith]]
[[Category:Religious pluralism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[bg:Икуменизъм]]
[[bs:Ekumenizam]]
[[ca:Ecumenisme]]
[[cs:Ekumenismus]]
[[da:Økumeni]]
[[de:Ökumenismus]]
[[es:Ecumenismo]]
[[eo:Ekumenismo]]
[[fr:Œcuménisme]]
[[ko:에큐메니컬 운동]]
[[hr:Ekumenizam]]
[[id:Ekumenisme]]
[[ia:Ecumenismo]]
[[it:Ecumenismo]]
[[kk:Экуменизм]]
[[sw:Ekumeni]]
[[la:Oecumenismus]]
[[lv:Ekumēnisms]]
[[lt:Ekumenizmas]]
[[hu:Ökumenizmus]]
[[ml:സഭൈക്യപ്രസ്ഥാനം]]
[[nl:Oecumene]]
[[ja:エキュメニズム]]
[[no:Økumenikk]]
[[nn:Økumenikk]]
[[pms:Ecumenism]]
[[pl:Ekumenizm]]
[[pt:Ecumenismo]]
[[ro:Ecumenism]]
[[ru:Экуменизм]]
[[sq:Ekumenizmi]]
[[simple:Ecumenism]]
[[sk:Ekumenizmus]]
[[sl:Ekumensko gibanje]]
[[sr:Екуменизам]]
[[sh:Ekumenizam]]
[[fi:Ekumenia]]
[[sv:Ekumenik]]
[[tr:Ekümeniklik]]
[[uk:Екуменізм]]
[[vi:Phong trào Đại Kết]]
[[zh:普世教會合一運動]]</text>
      <sha1>k3p95afj1s3gce2rszkrh2bs13dh3uq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
