<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Edgardo Mortara</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>347917</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516907229</id>
      <parentid>516904559</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-09T23:04:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing orphaned refs (&quot;dawkins169-172&quot; from rev 516837178)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18059">{{dablink|Not to be confused with [[Edoardo Mortara]].}}
[[File:EdgardoMortara.jpg|thumb|right|Edgardo Mortara (right) with his mother and brother (possibly Ericole or Aristide), c. 1880.]]
'''Edgardo Levi Mortara''' ([[Bologna]], [[Papal States]], August 27, 1851 &amp;ndash; [[Liège]], [[Belgium]], March 11, 1940) was an Italian boy who became the center of an international controversy when he was removed from his Jewish parents by authorities of the [[Papal States]] and raised as a Catholic. Mortara was born and raised Jewish during the first six years of his life, until he was taken from his family by Church authorities who took custody of the boy after receiving a report that he had been given [[emergency baptism]] by a domestic servant during a serious infantile illness. The rationale for this action was that in the Papal States, it was against the law for non-Catholics to raise Catholic children.  Mortara was adopted by [[Pope Pius IX]] and entered the seminary in his teens.

==The Mortara case==
===Removal from parents===
On 23 June 1858, in [[Bologna]], in the [[Papal States]], police arrived at the home of a Jewish couple, Salomone (&quot;Momolo&quot;) and Marianna Padovani Mortara, to take one of their eight children, six-year-old Edgardo, and transport him to [[Rome]] to be raised as a ward of the state. The police had orders from [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith|Holy Office]], authorized by [[Pope Pius IX]] This was done because Edgardo had been secretly baptised Catholic as an infant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode | title = The End of the Inquisition | series = Secret Files of the Inquisition | credits = David Rabinovich, producer, director| network = PBS | airdate = May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under Catholic doctrine, &quot;emergency&quot; baptism may be performed by anyone, man or woman, even if non-Christian, and was considered a valid type of baptism, as long as the individual who baptizes is in accord with Catholic tradition. Originally intended as a relief for Catholic families suffering high infant mortality rates, it had not been intended to be used for Jewish families. This rule allowed anyone to perform emergency baptism so the infant would not die unbaptised. Its use in the case of very ill Jewish children was accepted by the Christian population. After the baptism of Edgardo, which was attested to by the servant girl who had performed it, Edgardo was a Catholic in accordance with Catholic law. According to [[canon law]], which was also the law in the Papal States, non-Christians could not raise a Christian child, even if the child was their own. In 1912, in his testimony in favour of the [[beatification]] of [[Pope Pius IX]], Edgardo himself noted that the laws of the [[Papal States]] did not allow [[Roman Catholic|Catholics]] to work in the homes of Jewish families (one reason being to prevent this very situation from happening).&lt;ref name=&quot;elmtestzenit&quot;&gt;[http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/pope025501.htm Edgardo Levi-Mortara's Testimony for Beatification of Pius IX], originally published in English by ''[[Zenit News Agency]]'', September 20, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

David Kertzer has questioned whether the baptism, which had no witnesses, actually took place. In his 1997 book ''The Kidnapping of Edgardo Mortara'', Kertzer investigates the story and quotes from contemporary testimony.  It appears that Morisi told the local priests her story at a time when she was seeking to obtain a [[dowry]] from the Church, and investigations on behalf of the Mortaras revealed that she was reputed to be a thief.  It was reported that Edgardo's illness had not been life-threatening, thus not requiring an emergency baptism. On the other hand, other testimony was consistent with Morisi's story, and the Church authorities were evidently persuaded that she was telling the truth.

Edgardo was taken to a house for Roman [[Religious conversion|convert]]s (a &quot;House of [[Catechumen]]s&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dawkins169-172&quot;&gt;Dawkins, 2006, pp. 169&amp;ndash;172.&lt;/ref&gt;) in Rome, maintained at state expense. His parents were not allowed to see him for several weeks, and after this period were not allowed to see him unsupervised. Pius IX took a personal interest in the case (Kertzer confirms that the pope helped raise Edgardo), and all appeals to the Church were rebuffed. Church authorities told the Mortaras that they could have Edgardo back if they would convert to Catholicism, but they refused. According to Kertzer, the Mortaras had several audiences with the pope regarding the matter.

===Reaction and opposition===
The incident soon received extensive publicity both in Italy and internationally. In the [[Kingdom of Sardinia]], the largest independent state in Italy and the centre of the [[Liberalism|liberal]] [[Nationalism|nationalist]] movement for [[Italian unification]], both the government and the press used the case to reinforce their claims that the [[Papal States]] were ruled by [[Middle Ages|medieval]] [[obscurantism|obscurantists]] and should be liberated from Papal rule.

Protests were lodged by both Jewish organizations and prominent political and intellectual figures in [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|Britain]], the [[United States]], [[Zollverein|Germany]], [[Austrian Empire|Austria]], and [[France]]. Soon the governments of these countries added to calls for Edgardo to be returned to his parents. The French Emperor [[Napoleon III]], whose troops garrisoned [[Rome]] to protect the Pope against the Italian anti-clerical unificationists, also protested.

When a delegation of prominent Jews saw the Pope in 1859, he told them, &quot;I couldn't care less what the world thinks.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kertzer (1997), [http://books.google.ca/books?id=vGkVEjSG2PoC&amp;pg=PT261&amp;lpg=PT261&amp;dq=%22I+couldn't+care+less%22,+mortara&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=92AgXU3NH_&amp;sig=YfHMB_QDNhwkBGUOJ1dWeqbcBA4&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=r_hqTqS7CoSDsgLftYXvCA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CDkQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22I%20couldn't%20care%20less%22%2C%20mortara&amp;f=false Ch.15, p.261]&lt;/ref&gt; At another meeting, he brought Edgardo with him to show that the boy was happy in his care. In 1865 he said: &quot;I had the right and the duty to do what I did for this boy, and if I had to, I would do it again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| author = Levitan, Dov| url = http://www.biu.ac.il/JH/Parasha/eng/vayeshev/839Lev.doc |title=The Kidnapping of Edgardo Mortara|location=Bar-Ilan University|publisher=Parashat Hashavua Study Center|date=Parashat Va-Yeshev 5771, November 27, 2010| page=3|format=DOC|accessdate=September 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;De Mattei, p. 156&lt;/ref&gt; In a speech in 1871 defending his decision against his detractors, Pius said: &quot;Of these dogs, there are too many of them at present in Rome, and we hear them howling in the streets, and they are disturbing us in all places.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Kenneth | last = Stowe | title =Popes, Church, and Jews in the Middle Ages: Confrontation and Response| pages = 57&amp;ndash;58 | publisher = Ashgate Press | year = 2007 | isbn = 0-7546-5915-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = James | last = Carroll | title =Constantine's Sword: The Church and the Jews &amp;mdash; A History| pages = 379&amp;ndash;380 | publisher = Houghton Mifflin Books | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-618-21908-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mortara Incident may have helped persuade opinion that the Papal States should be conquered.  When the French garrison was withdrawn in 1870, and the Italian army [[Capture of Rome|assaulted the city]], Rome too was annexed by the newly unified, liberal [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Kingdom of Italy]].

The Mortara affair resulted in the origin of the Alliance Israelite Universelle in 1860. [[Adolphe Cremieux]] and other French-Jewish leaders formed the Alliance to advocate for all Jews who faced such circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| last = Lupovitch
| first = Howard N.
| title = Jews and Judaism in world history
| publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis
| date = 2009 
| location = New York, NY
| page = 172
| url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=F2Y9SSahLEkC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;dq=mortara,+affront,+liberalism&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=w-vkTrTtBsHW0QH8gI3BDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=mortara%2C%20affront%2C%20liberalism&amp;f=false
| isbn = 0-415-46204-5
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ordination and later life==
In 1859, after Bologna had been annexed to Piedmont, the Mortara parents made another effort to recover their son, but he had been taken to Rome. In 1870, when [[capture of Rome|Rome was captured]] from the Pope, they tried again, but Edgardo was then 19 and therefore legally an adult, and had declared his firm intention of remaining a Roman Catholic. In that year, he was assigned to France. The following year, his father died. In France, he entered the [[Augustinians|Augustinian order]], being [[Holy Orders|ordained]] a [[priest]] at the age of 23, and adopted the spiritual name ''Pius''.&lt;ref name = &quot;NCR&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
  | last = Allen
  | first = John L. jr.
  | title = Pope of infallibility set for beatification 
  | work = National Catholic Reporter, Online
  | publisher = 
  | date = September 1, 2000
  | url = http://natcath.org/NCR_Online/archives2/2000c/090100/090100l.htm
  | accessdate = 2011-12-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fr. Edgardo Mortara was sent as a [[missionary]] to cities such as [[Munich]], [[Mainz]] and [[Wrocław|Breslau]] to preach to the [[Jews]] there. He became fluent in a variety of languages. As he traveled widely, his effort to convince Jews to convert was mostly unsuccessful.&lt;ref name = &quot;NCR&quot; /&gt;

During a public-speaking engagement in Italy he reestablished communications with his [[mother]] and [[siblings]]. In 1895, he attended his mother's funeral, led by the [[rabbi]] of [[Bologna]]. His nieces and nephews, as adults, recalled the frequent visits from him.&lt;ref&gt;See Kertzer&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1897, he preached in [[St. Patrick's Cathedral, New York]], but [[Michael Corrigan]], the [[Archbishop of New York]], told the [[Holy See|Vatican]] that he opposed Mortara's efforts to evangelise Jews on the grounds that such efforts might embarrass the Church in the eyes of the [[United States]] government. Father Mortara asked Bishop Corrigan for financial support. The archbishop refused.&lt;ref name = &quot;NCR&quot; /&gt; 

Mortara died in 1940 at the abbey of Bouhay in Bressoux, near [[Liège]] in [[Belgium]], having spent his last years there.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Brechenmacher, ''Der Vatikan und die Juden. Geschichte einer unheiligen Beziehung vom 16. Jahrhundert bis zur Gegenwart'', Beck: München (2005), p. 113&lt;/ref&gt; He was 88 years old.

==Pope Pius IX's relationship with Jews==
{{Main|Pope Pius IX and Judaism}}
Civil law in the Papal States did not permit baptized Christians to be raised by non-Christians. Pope Pius IX, who had partially [[Jewish emancipation|emancipated the Jews]] living in the Papal States, found himself in a quandary. The Mortara case was the catalyst for far-reaching political changes; its repercussions are still being felt within the Catholic Church and in relations between the Church and some Jewish organizations. The incident, in its briefest outline: Mortara was taken from his home, raised a Catholic, ordained a priest, and remained a priest for the rest of his life.  In §1672 of his testimony for the beatification of Pius IX, Mortara stated &quot;I greatly desire the beatification and canonization of the Servant of God (Pius IX).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;elmtestzenit&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;At the conclusion of his deposition (§1695), Mortata states: &quot;I am firmly convinced, not only by the deposition I have given, but by the entire life of my august protector and father, that the Servant of God (Pius IX) is a saint. I have the almost instinctive conviction that one day he will be raised to the glory of the altars. For me it will be an intimate joy for my entire life and a great comfort in the hour of my death to have cooperated to the limits of my strength toward the success of this cause. I pray to God by the intercession of his Servant to have mercy on me and forgive my sins, and make me rejoice in his presence in Paradise.&quot; [http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/pope025501.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mortara affair increased discontent with the [[Temporal power (Papal)|temporal power of the papacy]] within Italy and produced calls from around the world, including [[Emperor Franz Josef]] and [[Napoleon III]], for Mortara to be returned to his parents, including 20 editorials in ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Cornwell, 2004, p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Mortara case attracted new attention around the turn of the 21st century because of the campaign to secure [[canonization|canonisation]] for [[beatification|Blessed]] Pius IX.&lt;ref name = &quot;NCR&quot; /&gt; Jewish groups and others, led by several descendants of the Mortara family, protested the Vatican's [[beatification]] of Pius in 2000. In 1997 [[David Kertzer]] published ''The Kidnapping of Edgardo Mortara'', which brought the case back to public attention. 

The story became the subject of a play, ''Edgardo Mine'' by [[Alfred Uhry]], and an opera, &quot;Il Caso Mortara&quot; by [[Francesco Cilluffo]], premiered February 25, 2010, by Dicapo Opera in New York City. An Irish film titled ''Edgardo Mortara'', based on the play and Kertzer's book, was planned to begin production via Miramax in October 2002 but the project was halted for lack of funds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2002/sep/18/news3 | work=The Guardian | title=Edgardo Mortara collapses | date=September 18, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}
* {{de}}

==References==
* [[John Cornwell (writer)|Cornwell, John]]. (2004) ''The Pope In Winter''. Viking. ISBN 0-670-91572-6.
* [[Richard Dawkins|Dawkins, Richard]]. (2006) ''[[The God Delusion]]''. Transworld Publishers. ISBN 0-593-05548-9.
*{{Cite book
| last = De Mattei, Roberto. transl. John Laughland
| first = 
| title = Pius IX
| publisher = Gracewing Publishing
| year = 2004
| location = Herefordshire, UK 
| pages = 153–158 
| url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=Jeie3FBTC1sC&amp;pg=PA153&amp;dq=%22The+Mortara+Affair%22,+Mattei&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=-HtrTtmHOOn10gHz0_TyBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
| isbn = 0-85244-605-5
}}
* [[David Kertzer|Kertzer, David I.]]  (1997) ''[http://www.davidkertzer.com/en/books/kidnapping_of_edgardo_mortara.html The Kidnapping of Edgardo Mortara]'' Random House. ISBN 0-679-76817-3.

==Further reading==
*{{Cite book
| last = Crean, Thomas
| first = 
| title = God is no delusion: a refutation of Richard Dawkins
| publisher = Ignatius Press
| year = 2007 
| location = San Francisco, CA
| page = 
| url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=aKKzfWETi48C&amp;pg=PT54&amp;dq=%22Edgardo+Mortara%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0NlqTse8NaLm0QHYsdnuBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Edgardo%20Mortara%22&amp;f=false
| isbn = 978-1-58617-231-2
}}
*{{Citation
| last = Levi-Mortara
| first = Edgardo
| title = Papal Sin: Structures of Deceit.
| publisher = EWTN/ZENIT
| title = Levi-Mortara's Testimony for Beatification of Pius IX 
| date = September 20, 2000
| url = http://www.ewtn.com/library/issues/ZMORTARA.HTM 
| accessdate = September 10, 2011}}
*{{Cite book
| last = Lubet, Steven
| first = 
| title = Nothing But the Truth: Why Trial Lawyers Don't, Can't, and Shouldn't Have to Tell the Whole Truth
| publisher = NYU Press
| year = 2002
| location = New York 
| pages = 28–50
| url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=OO7D7U9hzLMC&amp;pg=PA28&amp;dq=%22On+the+evening+of+June+23,+1858,+an+officer%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=BN5qTp23F-PH0AHX-bmQBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22On%20the%20evening%20of%20June%2023%2C%201858%2C%20an%20officer%22&amp;f=false
| isbn = 0-8147-5173-3
}}
*[[Alfred Uhry|Uhry, Alfred]], ''[http://www.davidkertzer.com/en/adaptations/edgardo_mine_play.html Edgardo Mine]'' (based on David Kertzer's book).
* {{Cite book
| last = Wills, Garry
| first = 
| title = Papal Sin: Structures of Deceit.
| publisher = Doubleday
| year = 2000 
| location = New York
| pages = 39–46
| url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=yGIBzzVKM30C&amp;pg=PT45&amp;dq=%22how+did+a+pope+get+into+the+kidnapping+business%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=SNZqTubEGM2ksQLgupTZBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 
| isbn = 0-385-49411-4
}}

== See also ==
* [[Jewish orphans controversy]]
* [[Elián González affair]]

==External links==
* [http://www.dannyscl.net/academic/mortara.pdf An account of the American reaction to the Mortara case], emphasizing the anti-Catholicism of the American response.
* Secret Files of the Inquisition [http://www.inquisitionproductions.com/episode4.html Episode 4] Concerns Edgardo Mortara and his relationship with the end of the Papal States, the unification of Italy, and the end of the Italian Inquisition.

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Mortara, Edgardo
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = August 27, 1851
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = March 11, 1940
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Mortara, Edgardo}}
[[Category:1851 births]]
[[Category:1940 deaths]]
[[Category:Anti-Catholicism]]
[[Category:Anti-Catholicism in Italy]]
[[Category:Antisemitism in Italy]]
[[Category:Antisemitic attacks and incidents]]
[[Category:Augustinian friars]]
[[Category:Christian and Jewish interfaith topics]]
[[Category:Converts to Roman Catholicism from Judaism]]
[[Category:History of the Papal States]]
[[Category:Italian Jews]]
[[Category:Italian Roman Catholic priests]]
[[Category:Italian Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Jewish history]]
[[Category:Kidnapped children]]
[[Category:Kidnapped Italian people]]
[[Category:People from Bologna]]
[[Category:Pope Pius IX]]

[[bg:Едгардо Мортара]]
[[de:Edgardo Mortara]]
[[es:Edgardo Mortara]]
[[fr:Affaire Mortara]]
[[id:Edgardo Mortara]]
[[it:Caso Edgardo Mortara]]
[[he:אדגרדו מורטארה]]
[[nl:Edgardo Mortara]]
[[ja:エドガルド・モルターラ]]
[[pl:Edgardo Mortara]]
[[pt:Edgardo Mortara]]
[[ro:Afacerea Edgardo Mortara]]
[[ru:Мортара, Эдгардо]]
[[fi:Edgardo Mortara]]</text>
      <sha1>h61ig5o13rb6286x43vab08dadxx3p8</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
