<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>First Vatican Council</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11390</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520560157</id>
      <parentid>520553433</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T08:28:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Esoglou</username>
        <id>11289927</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid unnecessary change</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14571">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox Ecumenical council
| council_name = First Vatican Council
| council_date = 1869–70&lt;br&gt;(formally closed in 1960 prior to the [[Second Vatican Council]])
| accepted_by  = [[Catholic Church]]
| previous     = [[Council of Trent]]
| next         = [[Second Vatican Council]]
| convoked_by  = [[Pope Pius IX]]
| presided_by  = [[Pope Pius IX]]
| attendance   = 744
| topics       = [[rationalism]], [[liberalism]], [[materialism]]; [[inspiration of Scripture]]; [[papal infallibility]]
| documents    = ''[[Dei Filius]]'', ''[[Pastor Aeternus]]''
}}
{{Ecumenical councils of the Catholic Church}}
[[File:Pio9vat1.jpg|thumb|300px|Drawing showing the First Vatican Council]]
The '''First Vatican Council''' was convoked by [[Pope Pius IX]] on 29 June 1868, after a period of planning and preparation that began on 6 December 1864.&lt;ref name=CE&gt;{{CathEncy| wstitle=Vatican Council| title =Vatican Council| first = K.  | last =KIRCH| authorlink = | accessdate =27 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; This twentieth [[ecumenical council]] of the [[Catholic Church]],&lt;ref name=EB&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/624002/First-Vatican-Council Encyclopaedia Britannica: ''First Vatican Council'']&lt;/ref&gt; held three centuries after the [[Council of Trent]], opened on 8 December 1869 and adjourned on 20 October 1870.&lt;ref name=CE/&gt; Unlike the five earlier General Councils held in Rome, which met in the [[Basilica of St. John Lateran|Lateran Basilica]] and are known as Lateran Councils, it met in the [[Saint Peter's Basilica|Vatican Basilica]], hence its name. Its best-known decision is its definition of [[papal infallibility]].

The Council was convoked to deal with the contemporary problems of the rising influence of rationalism, liberalism, and materialism.&lt;ref name=&quot;EB&quot;/&gt; Its purpose was, besides this, to define the Catholic doctrine concerning the Church of Christ.&lt;ref name=EWTN/&gt; There was discussion and approval of only two constitutions: the Dogmatic Constitution on the Catholic Faith and the First Dogmatic Constitution on the Church of Christ, the latter dealing with the primacy and infallibility of the Bishop of Rome.&lt;ref name=EWTN&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/COUNCILS/V1.htm First Vatican Council (1869-1870)]&lt;/ref&gt; The first matter brought up for debate was the dogmatic draft of Catholic doctrine against the manifold errors due to Rationalism.&lt;ref name=NA&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15303a.htm Catholic Encyclopaedia: ''Vatican Council'']&lt;/ref&gt;

== Papal infallibility ==

The doctrine of [[papal infallibility]] was not new and had been used by Pope Pius in defining as dogma, in 1854, the [[Immaculate Conception]] of Mary, the mother of Jesus.&lt;ref name=EB:Pius&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/462365/Pius-IX/5761/First-Vatican-Council Encyclopaedia Britannica: ''Pius IX'']&lt;/ref&gt; However, the proposal to define papal infallibility itself as dogma met with resistance, not because of doubts about the substance of the proposed definition, but because some considered it inopportune to take that step at that time.&lt;ref name=EB:Pius/&gt; [[Richard McBrien|McBrien]] divides the bishops attending [[Vatican I]] into three groups.  The first group, which McBrien calls the &quot;active infallibilists&quot;, was led by Manning and Senestrey.  This group took an extreme view that argued that all papal teachings were infallible and that papal infallibility was the foundation of the church's infallibility.  According to McBrien, the majority of the bishops were not so much interested in a formal definition of papal infallibility as they were in strengthening papal authority and, because of this, were willing to accept the agenda of the infallibilists.  A minority, some 20 percent of the bishops, opposed the proposed definition of papal infallibility on both ecclesiastical and pragmatic grounds.  They opposed the [[ultramontane]] centralist model of the Church because, in their opinion, it departed from the ecclesiastical structure of the early Christian church. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The HarperCollins encyclopedia of Catholicism |first=Richard P. |last=McBrien |publisher=HarperCollins |year=1995 |page=1297 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WlNfJC6RveAC&amp;pg=PA1297&amp;dq=papal+infallibility+orthodox&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Mj2NTpzMA4OOsQK8-_TOAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwBjge#v=onepage&amp;q=papal%20infallibility%20orthodox&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; From a pragmatic perspective, they feared that defining papal infallibility would alienate some Catholics, create new difficulties for union with non-Catholics, and provoke interference by governments in Church affairs.&lt;ref name=CE/&gt; Those who held this view included most of the German and Austro-Hungarian bishops, nearly half of the Americans, one third of the French, most of the [[Chaldean Catholic Church|Chaldaeans]] and [[Melkite Greek Catholic Church|Melkites]], and a few [[Armenian Catholic Church|Armenians]].&lt;ref name=CE/&gt; Only a few bishops appear to have had doubts about the dogma itself.&lt;ref name=CE/&gt;

== Dei Filius ==
{{Main|Dei Filius}}
On 24 April 1870, the dogmatic constitution on the Catholic faith ''[[Dei Filius]]'' was adopted unanimously. The draft presented to the Council on 8 March drew no serious criticism, but a group of 35 English-speaking bishops, who feared that the opening phrase of the first chapter, &quot;Sancta romana catholica Ecclesia&quot; (the holy Roman Catholic Church), might be construed as favouring the Anglican [[Branch Theory]], later succeeded in having an additional adjective inserted, so that the final text read: &quot;Sancta catholica apostolica romana Ecclesia&quot; (the holy Catholic Apostolic Roman Church).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Lacoste | first = Jean-Yves |chapter=Vatican I, Council of| title = Encyclopedia of Christian Theology | publisher = Routledge | location = New York | year = 2004 | isbn = 1-57958-250-8|page=1666|url=http://books.google.com/?id=nzTkg_A6CWkC }}&lt;/ref&gt; The constitution thus set forth the teaching of the &quot;Holy Catholic Apostolic Roman Church&quot; on God, revelation and faith.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/COUNCILS/V1.htm Roberto De Mattei, John Laughland, ''Pius IX''], page 137&lt;/ref&gt;

== Pastor aeternus ==

{{Main|Pastor aeternus}}

There was stronger opposition to the draft constitution on the nature of the Church, which at first did not include the question of papal infallibility,&lt;ref name=EB/&gt; but the majority party in the Council, whose position on this matter was much stronger,&lt;ref name=EB:Pius/&gt; brought it forward. It was decided to postpone discussion of everything in the draft except infallibility.&lt;ref name=EB:Pius/&gt; On 13 July 1870, the section on infallibility was voted on: 451 voted simply in favour (''placet''), 88 against (''non placet''), and 62 in favour but on condition of some amendment (''placet iuxta modum'').&lt;ref name=EB:Pius/&gt; This made evident what the final outcome would be, and some 60 members of the opposition left Rome so as not to be associated with approval of the document. The final vote, with a choice only between ''placet'' and ''non placet'', was taken on 18 July 1870, with 433 votes in favour and only 2 against defining as a dogma the infallibility of the pope when speaking ''ex cathedra''.&lt;ref name=EB/&gt; The two votes against were cast by Bishop [[Aloisio Riccio]], and Bishop [[Edward Fitzgerald (bishop)|Edward Fitzgerald]].&lt;ref name=NA/&gt;

The dogmatic constitution states that the Pope has &quot;full and supreme power of jurisdiction over the whole Church&quot; (chapter 3:9); and that, when he &quot;speaks ''ex cathedra'', that is, when, in the exercise of his office as shepherd and teacher of all Christians, in virtue of his supreme apostolic authority, he defines a doctrine concerning faith or morals to be held by the whole Church, he possesses, by the divine assistance promised to him in blessed Peter, that infallibility which the divine Redeemer willed his Church to enjoy in defining doctrine concerning faith or morals&quot; (chapter 4:9).

None of the bishops who had argued that proclaiming the definition was inopportune refused to accept it. Some Catholics, mainly of German language and largely inspired by the historian [[Johann Joseph Ignaz von Döllinger]] (who did not formally join the new group) formed the separate [[Old Catholic Church]] in protest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Encarta Encyclopedia: ''First Vatican Council|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761576278/first_vatican_council.html|work=|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5kwcD77Xf|archivedate=31 October 2009|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Suspension ==

Discussion of the rest of the document on the nature of the Church was to continue when the bishops returned after a summer break. However, in the meanwhile the [[Franco-Prussian War]] broke out. With the swift German advance and the capture of Emperor [[Napoleon III]], France was no longer in a position to protect the Pope's rule in Rome.  

Consequently, on 20 September 1870 the Kingdom of Italy [[Capture of Rome|captured Rome]] and annexed it. One month later, on 20 October 1870, Pope Pius IX suspended the Council indefinitely. It was never reconvened and formally closed in 1960 prior to [[Second Vatican Council]].

== Leaving Rome and reopening the council considered ==

[[Julius Hermann Moritz Busch|Moritz Busch]] recounts that [[Otto von Bismarck]] confided that, after the [[capture of Rome]], Pius IX considered leaving Rome and reopening the Council elsewhere:
{{bquote|As a matter of fact, he [Pius IX] has already asked whether we could grant him asylum. I have no objection to it—Cologne or Fulda. It would be passing strange, but after all not so inexplicable, and it would be very useful to us to be recognised by Catholics as what we really are, that is to say, the sole power now existing that is capable of protecting the head of their Church. [...] But the King [William I] will not consent. He is terribly afraid. He thinks all Prussia would be perverted and he himself would be obliged to become a Catholic. I told him, however, that if the Pope begged for asylum he could not refuse it. He would have to grant it as ruler of ten million Catholic subjects who would desire to see the head of their Church protected.&lt;ref&gt;Moritz Busch ''Bismarck: Some secret pages of his history'', Vol. I, Macmillan (1898) p. 220, entry for 8 November 1870&lt;/ref&gt;}}

He also reports:
{{bquote|Bucher brings me from upstairs instructions and material for a Rome despatch for the ''Kölnische Zeitung''. It runs as follows: &quot;Rumours have already been circulated on various occasions to the effect that the Pope intends to leave Rome. According to the latest of these the Council, which was adjourned in the summer, will be reopened at another place, some persons mentioning Malta and others Trient. [...] Doubtless the main object of this gathering will be to elicit from the assembled fathers a strong declaration in favour of the necessity of the Temporal Power. Obviously a secondary object of this Parliament of Bishops, convoked away from Rome, would be to demonstrate to Europe that the Vatican does not enjoy the necessary liberty, although the Act of Guarantee proves that the Italian Government, in its desire for reconciliation and its readiness to meet the wishes of the Curia, has actually done everything that lies in its power.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Moritz Busch ''Bismarck: Some secret pages of his history'', Vol. II, Macmillan (1898) pp.43-44, entry for 3 March 1872&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==References==
===Bibliography===
*[http://books.google.com/books?id=0XcpAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA449&amp;dq=%22the+last+days+of+papal+rome%22 ''The Last Days of Papal Rome''] by Raffaele De Cesare (1909) London, Archibald Constable &amp; Co.
* {{cite book | last = De Mattei| first = Roberto | title = Pius IX | publisher = Gracewing Publishing | location = Leominster | year = 2004 | isbn = 978-0-85244-605-8 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=Jeie3FBTC1sC|coauthor= John Laughland}}
* {{cite book | last = Hasler| first = August | title = How the Pope Became Infallible: Pius IX and the Politics of Persuasion | publisher = Doubleday | year = 1981}}
* {{cite book | last = Prusak | first = Bernard | title = The Church Unfinished: Ecclesiology through the Centuries | publisher = Paulist Press | location = New York | year = 2004 | isbn = 978-0-8091-4286-6|url=http://books.google.com/?id=sz21fd361-QC }}
* ''The Catholic Church in the Modern World'' by [[E.E.Y. Hales]] (Doubleday, 1958)

===Notes===
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commonscat|First Vatican Council}}
* [http://www.ewtn.com/library/COUNCILS/V1.htm EWTN: First Vatican Council (introduction and texts)]
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=Vatican Council}}
* [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/624002/First-Vatican-Council Encyclopaedia Britannica: ''First Vatican Council'']
* {{Cite EB1911|Vatican Council, The}}
* [http://www.papalencyclicals.net/Councils/ecum20.htm (The text)]

{{Ecumenical councils}}

[[Category:Pope Pius IX]]
[[Category:Ecumenical councils|Vatican I]]
[[Category:19th-century Roman Catholic Church Councils|Vatican 1]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic Church Councils held in Italy|Vatican 1]]
[[Category:First Vatican Council]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1869]]
[[Category:1870 disestablishments]]
[[Category:19th-century Roman Catholicism]]

[[ar:المجمع الفاتيكاني الأول]]
[[ca:Concili Vaticà I]]
[[cs:První vatikánský koncil]]
[[da:Det første Vatikankoncil]]
[[de:Erstes Vatikanisches Konzil]]
[[el:Α' Βατικάνεια Σύνοδος]]
[[es:Concilio Vaticano I]]
[[eo:Unua Vatikana Koncilio]]
[[fr:Premier concile œcuménique du Vatican]]
[[ga:An Chéad Comhairle Vatacáine]]
[[gl:Concilio Vaticano Primeiro]]
[[ko:제1차 바티칸 공의회]]
[[hr:Prvi vatikanski sabor]]
[[id:Konsili Vatikan I]]
[[it:Concilio Vaticano I]]
[[jv:Konsili Vatikan I]]
[[sw:Mtaguso wa kwanza wa Vatikano]]
[[la:Concilium Vaticanum Primum]]
[[lb:Éischt Vatikanescht Konzil]]
[[hu:Első vatikáni zsinat]]
[[nl:Eerste Vaticaans Concilie]]
[[ja:第1バチカン公会議]]
[[no:Første Vatikankonsil]]
[[pl:Sobór watykański I]]
[[pt:Concílio Vaticano I]]
[[ro:Conciliul Vatican I]]
[[ru:Первый Ватиканский собор]]
[[sk:Prvý vatikánsky koncil]]
[[sl:Prvi vatikanski koncil]]
[[sr:Prvi vatikanski sabor]]
[[sh:Prvi vatikanski sabor]]
[[fi:Vatikaanin ensimmäinen kirkolliskokous]]
[[sv:Första Vatikankonciliet]]
[[tr:Birinci Vatikan Konsili]]
[[uk:Перший Ватиканський собор]]
[[war:Syahan nga Konsilyo Vaticano]]
[[zh:第一次梵蒂岡大公會議]]</text>
      <sha1>mqiwinxixqihsh6nydjbg54pjtcxei0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
