<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Forgiveness</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>246042</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522114838</id>
      <parentid>520618794</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T03:21:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.176.188.208</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Christianity */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32934">{{Other uses}}
[[File:Marco aurelio e barbaros - museus capitolinos.jpg|thumb|Emperor [[Marcus Aurelius]] shows his [[clemence]] towards the vanquished after his success against tribes. ([[Capitoline Museum]] in Rome)]]

'''Forgiveness''' is the renunciation or cessation of [[resentment]], [[indignation]] or [[anger]] as a result of a perceived offense, disagreement, or mistake, or ceasing to demand [[punishment]] or [[restitution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;apa&quot;&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.apa.org/international/resources/forgiveness.pdf | title = American Psychological Association. ''Forgiveness: A Sampling of Research Results.'' | accessdate = 2009-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sapient&quot;&gt;{{cite web | year = 2011 | url = http://www.sapients.net/article/the-power-of-forgiveness/ | title = Sapients.Net ''Forgiveness: A Article on Forgiveness'' | accessdate = 2011-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Oxford English Dictionary]] defines forgiveness as 'to grant free pardon and to give up all claim on account of an offense or debt'. The concept and benefits of forgiveness have been explored in [[religion|religious]] thought, the [[social science]]s and [[medicine]].  Forgiveness may be considered simply in terms of the person who forgives including forgiving themselves, in terms of the person forgiven or in terms of the relationship between the forgiver and the person forgiven. In most contexts, forgiveness is granted without any expectation of [[restorative justice]], and without any response on the part of the offender (for example, one may forgive a person who is [[incommunicado]] or dead). In practical terms, it may be necessary for the offender to offer some form of acknowledgment, an [[apology]], or even just ask for forgiveness, in order for the wronged person to believe himself able to forgive.&lt;ref name=&quot;apa&quot;/&gt;

Most world religions include teachings on the nature of forgiveness, and many of these teachings provide an underlying basis for many varying modern day traditions and practices of forgiveness. Some religious doctrines or philosophies place greater emphasis on the need for humans to find some sort of divine forgiveness for their own shortcomings, others place greater emphasis on the need for humans to practice forgiveness of one another, yet others make little or no distinction between human and divine forgiveness.

== Research ==
[[File:Determinants of Forgiveness Graphic.JPG|thumb|300px|right|Factors determining the likelihood of forgiveness in an [[intimate relationship]].]]

Although there is presently no consensus for a psychological definition of forgiveness in the research literature, agreement has emerged that forgiveness is a process and a number of models describing the process of forgiveness have been published, including one from a radical behavioral perspective.&lt;ref&gt;Cordova,J., Cautilli,J., Simon, C. &amp; Axelrod-Sabtig, R (2006). Behavior Analysis of Forgiveness in Couples Therapy.  ''IJBCT, 2(2),'' Pg. 192 [http://www.behavior-analyst-online.org BAO]&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. Robert Enright from the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]] founded the International Forgiveness Institute and is considered the initiator of forgiveness studies. He developed a 20-Step Process Model of Forgiveness.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Robert Enright, ''Forgiveness is a Choice'', American Psychological Association , 2001 ISBN 1-55798-757-2&lt;/ref&gt; Recent work has focused on what kind of person is more likely to be forgiving. A longitudinal study showed that people who were generally more [[neuroticism|neurotic]], angry and hostile in life were less likely to forgive another person even after a long time had passed. Specifically, these people were more likely to still avoid their transgressor and want to enact revenge upon them two and a half years after the transgression.&lt;ref&gt;Maltby, J., Wood, A. M., Day, L., Kon, T. W. H., Colley, A., and Linley, P. A. (2008). [http://personalpages.manchester.ac.uk/staff/alex.wood/forgiveness.pdf Personality predictors of levels of forgiveness two and a half years after the transgression.] Journal of Research in Personality, 42, 1088-1094.&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies show that people who forgive are [[happiness|happier]] and healthier than those who hold resentments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.forgiving.org | title = Forgiving (Campaign for Forgiveness Research) | accessdate = 2006-06-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first study to look at how forgiveness improves physical health discovered that when people think about forgiving an offender it leads to improved functioning in their cardiovascular and nervous systems.&lt;ref&gt;Van Oyen, C. Witvilet, T.E. Ludwig and K. L. Vander Lann, &quot;Granting Forgiveness or Harboring Grudges: Implications for Emotions, Physiology and Health,&quot; ''Psychological Science'' no. 12 (2001):117-23&lt;/ref&gt; Another study at the University of Wisconsin found the more forgiving people were, the less they suffered from a wide range of illnesses. The less forgiving people reported a greater number of health problems.&lt;ref&gt;S. Sarinopoulos, &quot;Forgiveness and Physical Health: A Doctoral Dissertation Summary,&quot; ''World of Forgiveness'' no. 2 (2000): 16-18&lt;/ref&gt;

The research of Dr. Fred Luskin of [[Stanford University]] shows that forgiveness can be learned. Dr. Frederic Luskin's work is based on seven major research projects into the effects of forgiveness, giving empirical validity to the concept that forgiveness is not only powerful, but also excellent for your health. Dr. Fred Luskin author of the book &quot;Learning to forgive&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://learningtoforgive.com/ Learningtoforgive.com]&lt;/ref&gt; was presented with a Champion of Forgiveness award by the Forgiveness Alliance&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forgivenessalliance.org/ Forgivenessalliance.org]&lt;/ref&gt; for his groundbreaking work with forgiveness, reconciliation and peace.

In three separate studies, including one with Catholics and Protestants from Northern Ireland whose family members were murdered in the political violence, he found that people who are taught how to forgive become less angry, feel less hurt, are more optimistic, become more forgiving in a variety of situations, and become more compassionate and self-confident. His studies show a reduction in experience of stress, physical manifestations of stress, and an increase in vitality.&lt;ref&gt;Fred Luskin, Ph.D. ''Forgive for Good: A Proven Prescription for Health and Happiness'' (Harper, 2002)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Religious views ==
{{Further|Salvation|Sin}}

===Abrahamic===

==== Judaism ====
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Judaism]] --&gt;

In [[Judaism]], if a person causes harm, but then sincerely and honestly apologizes to the wronged individual and tries to rectify the wrong, the wronged individual is religiously required to grant forgiveness:

* &quot;It is forbidden to be obdurate and not allow yourself to be appeased.  On the contrary, one should be easily pacified and find it difficult to become angry.  When asked by an offender for forgiveness, one should forgive with a sincere mind and a willing spirit. . . forgiveness is natural to the seed of Israel.&quot;  ([[Mishneh Torah]], ''[[Teshuvah]]'' 2:10)

In Judaism, one must go ''to those he has harmed'' in order to be entitled to forgiveness.&lt;ref name = YomKippur&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.jewsuc.org/holiday4.htm | title = ''JewFAQ discussion of forgiveness on Yom Kippur'' | accessdate = 2006-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;   [One who sincerely apologizes three times for a wrong committed against another has fulfilled his or her obligation to seek forgiveness. ([[Shulchan Aruch]]) OC 606:1] This means that in Judaism a person cannot obtain forgiveness from God for wrongs the person has done to other people. This also means that, unless the victim forgave the perpetrator before he died, [[murder]] is unforgivable in [[Judaism]], and they will answer to [[God]] for it, though the victims' family and friends can forgive the murderer for the [[grief]] they caused them. The ''Tefila Zaka'' meditation, which is recited just before [[Yom Kippur]], closes with the following:

* &quot;I know that there is no one so righteous that they have not wronged another, financially or physically, through deed or speech.   This pains my heart within me, because wrongs between humans and their fellow are not atoned by Yom Kippur, until the wronged one is appeased. Because of this, my heart breaks within me, and my bones tremble; for even the day of death does not atone for such sins. Therefore I prostrate and beg before You, to have mercy on me, and grant me grace, compassion, and mercy in Your eyes and in the eyes of all people. For behold, I forgive with a final and resolved forgiveness anyone who has wronged me, whether in person or property, even if they slandered me, or spread falsehoods against me.  So I release anyone who has injured me either in person or in property, or has committed any manner of sin that one may commit against another [except for legally enforceable business obligations, and except for someone who has deliberately harmed me with the thought ‘I can harm him because he will forgive me'].  Except for these two, I fully and finally forgive everyone; may no one be punished because of me. And just as I forgive everyone, '''so may You grant me grace in the eyes of others, that they too forgive me absolutely'''.&quot;  [emphasis added]

Thus the &quot;reward&quot; for forgiving others is not God's forgiveness for wrongs done to others, but rather help ''in obtaining forgiveness from the other person.''

Sir [[Jonathan Sacks]], Chief Rabbi of the United Hebrew Congregations of the Commonwealth, summarized: &quot;it is not that God forgives, while human beings do not. To the contrary, we believe that just as only God can forgive sins against God, so only human beings can forgive sins against human beings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.chiefrabbi.org/thoughts/vayigash5766.pdf | title = ''Covenant and Conversation'' | accessdate = 2009-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jews observe a Day of Atonement [[Yom Kippur]] on the day before God makes decisions regarding what will happen during the coming year.&lt;ref name = YomKippur/&gt;  Just prior to Yom Kippur, Jews will ask forgiveness of those they have wronged during the prior year (if they have not already done so).&lt;ref name = YomKippur/&gt;  During Yom Kippur itself, Jews fast and pray for God's forgiveness for the transgressions they have made against God in the prior year.&lt;ref name = YomKippur/&gt;  Sincere repentance is required, and once again, God can only forgive one for the sins one has committed against God; this is why it is necessary for Jews also to seek the forgiveness of those people who they have wronged.&lt;ref name = YomKippur/&gt;

==== Christianity ====
[[Image:Rembrandt-The return of the prodigal son.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Rembrandt]] – “The Return of the [[Prodigal Son]]]]

In the New Testament, Jesus speaks of the importance of Christians forgiving or showing mercy towards others. The [[Parable of the Prodigal Son]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.comparativereligion.com/prodigal.html | title = The Parable of the Prodigal Son in Christianity and Buddhism | accessdate = 2009-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; is perhaps the best known instance of such teaching and practice of forgiveness.

In the [[Sermon on the Mount]], Jesus repeatedly spoke of forgiveness, “Blessed are the merciful, for they will be shown mercy.” Matthew 5:7 (NIV) “Therefore, if you are offering your gift at the altar and there remember that your brother has something against you, leave your gift there in front of the altar. First go and be reconciled to your brother; then come and offer your gift.” Matthew 5:23-24 (NIV) “And when you stand praying, if you hold anything against anyone, forgive him, so that your Father in heaven may forgive you your sins.” Mark 11:25 (NIV) “But I tell you who hear me: Love your enemies, do good to those who hate you, bless those who curse you, pray for those who mistreat you. If someone strikes you on one cheek, turn to him the other also.” Luke 6:27-29 (NIV) “Be merciful, just as your Father is merciful.” Luke 6:36 (NIV) “Do not judge, and you will not be judged. Do not condemn, and you will not be condemned. Forgive, and you will be forgiven.” Luke 6:37 (NIV)

Elsewhere, it is said, &quot;Then Peter came to Him and said, “Lord, how often shall my brother sin against me, and I forgive him? Up to seven times?” Jesus said to him, “I do not say to you, up to seven times, but up to seventy times seven. Matthew 18:21-22 (NKJV)

Jesus asked for God's forgiveness of those who crucified him. &quot;And Jesus said, 'Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do.'&quot; Luke 23: 34 (ESV)

==== Islam ====

[[Islam]] teaches that [[God in Islam|God]] is ''[[Al-Ghaffur]]'' &quot;The All-Forgiving&quot;, and is the original source of all forgiveness (''ghufran'' غفران).  Forgiveness often requires the [[repentance]] of those being forgiven.  Depending on the type of wrong committed, forgiveness can come either directly from Allah, or from one's fellow man who received the wrong.  In the case of divine forgiveness, the asking for divine forgiveness via repentance is important.  In the case of human forgiveness, it is important to both forgive, and to be forgiven.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.islamonline.com/news/articles/6/Forgiveness_Islamic_Perspective.html | title = Islam online. ''Forgiveness: Islamic Perspective'' | accessdate = 2009-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Islam does not teach [[universalism]], however, and the Qur'an states explicitly that God will not forgive idol worship ([[shirk (Islam)|shirk]]):
: ''God does not forgive idol worship (if maintained until death), and He forgives lesser offenses for whomever He wills. Anyone who idolizes any idol beside God has strayed far astray.'' (Qur'an 4:116)

The Qur'an never allows for violent behavior on the part of Muslim believers,&lt;ref&gt;Qur'an 9:12- ''&quot;Fight ye the chiefs of the unbelievers.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; except in the cases of defending one's religion, one's life, or one's property.  Outside of this, the Qu'ran makes no allowances for violent behavior.  From time to time certain Muslims have interpreted such Qur'anic allowances for &quot;defensive violence&quot; to include what other Muslims have viewed more as unwarranted and overly aggressive violence.  This interpretative debate about when to forgive and when to aggressively attack or defend continues to this day within the Muslim community.

The Qur'an makes it clear that, whenever possible, it is better to forgive another than to attack another.  The Qur'an describes the believers ([[Muslim]]s) as those who, ''avoid gross sins and vice, and when angered they forgive.'' (Qur'an 42:37) and says that ''Although the just requital for an injustice is an equivalent retribution, those who pardon and maintain righteousness are rewarded by GOD. He does not love the unjust.'' (Qur'an 42:40).

To receive forgiveness from God there are three requirements:

# Recognizing the offense itself and its admission before God.
# Making a commitment not to repeat the offense.
# Asking for forgiveness from God.

If the offense was committed against another human being, or against society, a
fourth condition is added:

# Recognizing the offense before those against whom offense was committed and before God.
# Committing oneself not to repeat the offense.
# Doing whatever needs to be done to rectify the offense (within reason) and asking pardon of the offended party.
# Asking God for forgiveness.

There are no particular words to say for asking forgiveness. However, Muslims are taught many phrases and words to keep repeating daily asking God's forgiveness. For example:

* ''Astaghfiru-Allah'', &quot;I ask forgiveness from Allah&quot;
* ''Subhanaka-Allah humma wa bi hamdika wa ash-hadu al la Ilaha illa Anta astaghfiruka wa atubu ilayk'', &quot;Glory be to You, Allah, and with You Praise (thanks) and I bear witness that there is no deity but You, I ask Your forgiveness and I return to You (in obedience)&quot;.

Islamic teaching presents the Prophet [[Muhammad]] as an example of someone who would forgive others for their ignorance, even those who might have once considered themselves to be his enemies.  One example of Muhammad's practice of forgiveness can be found in the [[Hadith]], the body of early Islamic literature about the life of Muhammad.  This account is as follows: &lt;br&gt;''The Prophet was the most forgiving person. He was ever ready to forgive his enemies. When he went to Ta’if to preach the message of Allah, its people mistreated him, abused him and hit him with stones. He left the city humiliated and wounded. When he took shelter under a tree, the angel of Allah visited him and told him that Allah sent him to destroy the people of Ta’if because of their sin of maltreating their Prophet. Muhammad prayed to Allah to save the people of Ta'if, because what they did was out of their ignorance.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.pakistanlink.com/religion/2000/04-14.html | title = Pakistanlink. ''Forgiveness in Islam'' | accessdate = 2009-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Bahá'í Faith ====
In the [[Bahá'í literature|Bahá'í Writings]], this explanation is given of how to be forgiving towards others:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Love the creatures for the sake of God and not for themselves. You will never become angry or impatient if you love them for the sake of God. Humanity is not perfect. There are imperfections in every human being, and you will always become unhappy if you look toward the people themselves. But if you look toward God, you will love them and be kind to them, for the world of God is the world of perfection and complete mercy. Therefore, do not look at the shortcomings of anybody; see with the sight of forgiveness.&quot;
&lt;br&gt; — [[`Abdu'l-Bahá]], ''The Promulgation of Universal Peace'', p. 92
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Eastern===

==== Buddhism ====
In [[Buddhism]], forgiveness is seen as a practice to prevent harmful thoughts from causing havoc on one’s mental well-being.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.psychjourney.com/Buddhism%20Series.htm | title = Psychjourney – Introduction to Buddhism Series | accessdate = 2006-06-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Buddhism recognizes that feelings of hatred and ill-will leave a lasting effect on our mind [[karma]].  Instead, Buddhism encourages the cultivation of thoughts that leave a wholesome effect.  &quot;In contemplating the law of karma, we realize that it is not a matter of seeking revenge but of practicing [[mettā]] and forgiveness, for the victimizer is, truly, the most unfortunate of all.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.abhayagiri.org/index.php/main/article/universal_loving_kindness/#top| title = Abhayagiri Buddhist Monastery -  Universal Loving Kindness | accessdate = 2009-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When resentments have already arisen, the Buddhist view is to calmly proceed to release them by going back to their roots.  Buddhism centers on release from delusion and suffering through meditation and receiving insight into the nature of reality.
Buddhism questions the reality of the passions that make forgiveness necessary as well as the reality of the objects of those passions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://josephsoleary.typepad.com/my_weblog/buddhism/index.html | title = Spirit of Vatican II: Buddhism – Buddhism and Forgiveness | accessdate = 2009-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  &quot;If we haven’t forgiven, we keep creating an identity around our pain, and that is what is reborn. That is what suffers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | year = 2006 | url = http://www.abhayagiri.org/index.php/main/article/preparing_for_death/#top | title = Abhayagiri Buddhist Monastery -  Preparing for Death | accessdate = 2006-06-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Buddhism places much emphasis on the concepts of ''[[Mettā]]'' (loving kindness), ''[[Karuṇā|karuna]]'' (compassion), ''[[mudita]]'' (sympathetic joy), and ''[[upekkhā]]'' (equanimity), as a means to avoiding resentments in the first place. These reflections are used to understand the context of suffering in the world, both our own and the suffering of others.

: “He abused me, he struck me, he overcame me, he robbed me’ — in those who harbor such thoughts hatred will never cease.”
: “He abused me, he struck me, he overcame me, he robbed me’ — in those who do not harbor such thoughts hatred will cease.”
: ([[Dhammapada]] 1.3-4; [[Dhammapada (Radhakrishnan translation)|trans. Radhakrishnan - see article]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/kn/dhp/dhp.01.than.html Accesstoinsight.org], translation by Thanissaro Bikkhu&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Hinduism ====

The concept of performing atonement from one's wrongdoing (Prayaschittha — Sanskrit: Penance), and asking for forgiveness is very much a part of the practice of [[Hinduism]]. Prayaschittha is related to the law of [[Karma]]. Karma is a sum of all that an individual has done, is currently doing and will do. The effects of those deeds and these deeds actively create present and future experiences, thus making one responsible for one's own life, and the pain in others.

Addressing Dhritarashtra, Vidura said: &quot;There is one only defect in forgiving persons, and not another; that defect is that people take a forgiving person to be weak. That defect, however, should not be taken into consideration, for forgiveness is a great power. Forgiveness is a virtue of the weak, and an ornament of the strong. Forgiveness subdues (all) in this world; what is there that forgiveness cannot achieve? What can a wicked person do unto him who carries the sabre of forgiveness in his hand? Fire falling on the grassless ground is extinguished of itself. And unforgiving individual defiles himself with many enormities. Righteousness is the one highest good; and forgiveness is the one supreme peace; knowledge is one supreme contentment; and benevolence, one sole happiness.&quot; (From the Mahabharata, Udyoga Parva Section XXXIII, Translated by Sri Kisari Mohan Ganguli).

An even more authoritative statement about forgiveness is espoused by [[Krishna]], who is considered to be an incarnation (''[[Avatar]]'') of [[Vishnu]] by Hindus. Krishna said in the [[Gita]] that forgiveness is one of the characteristics of one born for a divine state. It is noteworthy that he distinguishes those good traits from those he considered to be demoniac, such as pride, self-conceit and anger ([[Bhagavad Gita]], Chapter 16, verse 3).

Village priests may open their temple ceremonies with the following beloved invocation:

O Lord, forgive three sins that are due to my human limitations:
Thou art everywhere, but I worship thee here;
Thou art without form, but I worship thee in these forms;
Thou needest no praise, yet I offer thee these prayers and salutations,
Lord, forgive three sins that are due to my human limitations.

====Jainism====
{{See also|Micchami Dukkadam|Kshamavani}}
In [[Jainism]], forgiveness is one of the main virtues that needs to be cultivated by the Jains. ''Kṣamāpanā'' or supreme forgiveness forms part of one of the ten characteristics of ''[[Dharma (Jainism)|dharma]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Varni, Jinendra; Ed. Prof. Sagarmal Jain, Translated Justice T.K. Tukol and Dr. K.K. Dixit (1993). Samaṇ Suttaṁ. New Delhi: Bhagwan Mahavir memorial Samiti. verse 84&lt;/ref&gt; In the Jain prayer, (''[[pratikramana]]'') Jains repeatedly seek forgiveness from various creatures—even from ''ekindriyas'' or single sensed beings like plants and microorganisms that they may have harmed while eating and doing routine activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Jaini | first =Padmanabh | title =Collected Papers on Jaina Studies | publisher =Motilal Banarsidass Publ. | year =2000 | location =Delhi | isbn =81-208-1691-9 }}  p. 285&lt;/ref&gt; Forgiveness is asked by uttering the phrase, ''Micchāmi dukkaḍaṃ.'' ''Micchāmi dukkaḍaṃ'' is a [[Prakrit language]] phrase literally meaning &quot;may all the evil that has been done be fruitless.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Chapple. C.K. (2006) ''Jainism and Ecology: Nonviolence in the Web of Life'' Delhi:Motilal Banarasidas Publ. ISBN 978-81-208-2045-6 p.46&lt;/ref&gt; During ''[[samvatsari]]''—the last day of Jain festival ''[[paryusana]]''—Jains utter the phrase ''Micchami Dukkadam'' after ''[[pratikraman]]''. As a matter of ritual, they personally greet their friends and relatives ''micchāmi dukkaḍaṃ'' seeking their forgiveness. No private quarrel or dispute may be carried beyond samvatsari, and letters and telephone calls are made to the outstation friends and relatives asking their forgiveness.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, James (2003), Encyclopedia of Religion and Ethics Part 10, Kessinger Publishing ISBN 978-0-7661-3682-3 p.876&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Pratikraman]]'' also contains the following prayer:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last =Jaini | first =Padmanabh | title =Collected Papers on Jaina Studies | publisher =Motilal Banarsidass Publ. | year =2000 | location =Delhi | isbn =81-208-1691-9 }}  p.18 and 224&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;''Khāmemi savva-jīve savvë jive khamantu me / ''&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;''metti me savva-bhūesu, veraṃ mejjha na keṇavi //'' &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I ask pardon of all creatures, may all creatures pardon me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May I have friendship with all beings and enmity with none.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In their daily prayers and [[samayika]], Jains recite ''Iryavahi sutra'' seeking forgiveness from all creatures while involved in routine activities:&lt;ref&gt;Translated from Prakrit by Nagin J. shah and Madhu Sen (1993) ''Concept of Pratikramana'' Ahmedabad: Gujarat Vidyapith pp.25–26&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
May you, O Revered One!  Voluntarily permit me. I would like to confess my sinful acts committed while walking. I honour your permission. I desire to absolve myself of the sinful acts by confessing them.  I seek forgiveness from all those living beings which I may have tortured while walking, coming and going, treading on living organism, seeds, green grass, dew drops, ant hills, moss, live water, live earth, spider web and others. I seek forgiveness from all these living beings, be they — one sensed, two sensed, three sensed, four sensed or five sensed. Which I may have kicked, covered with dust, rubbed with ground, collided with other, turned upside down, tormented, frightened, shifted from one place to another or killed and deprived them of their lives. (By confessing) may I be absolved of all these sins.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Jain texts quote [[Mahavira|Māhavīra]] on forgiveness:&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite book | last =Jacobi | first =Hermann | authorlink =Hermann Jacobi | editor =(ed.) [[Max Müller|F. Max Müller]] | title =The Uttarādhyayana Sūtra | publisher =The Clarendon Press | year =1895 | location =Oxford | language =English: translated from Prakrit | url =http://www.sacred-texts.com/jai/sbe45/index.htm | series =[[Sacred Books of the East|Sacred Books of the East vol.45, Part 2]] | isbn =0-7007-1538-X }} ''Note: ISBN refers to the UK:Routledge (2001) reprint. URL is the scan version of the original 1895 reprint.''&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
By practicing ''prāyaṣcitta'' (repentance), a soul gets rid of sins, and commits no transgressions; he who correctly practises ''prāyaṣcitta'' gains the road and the reward of the road, he wins the reward of good conduct. By begging forgiveness he obtains happiness of mind; thereby he acquires a kind disposition towards all kinds of living beings; by this kind disposition he obtains purity of character and freedom from fear.
&lt;p&gt; — Māhavīra in ''Uttarādhyayana Sūtra'' 29:17–18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Even the code of conduct amongst the monks requires the monks to ask forgiveness for all transgressions:&lt;ref&gt;*{{cite book | last =Jacobi | first =Hermann | authorlink =Hermann Jacobi | editor =(ed.) [[Max Müller|F. Max Müller]] | title =The Kalpa Sūtra | publisher =The Clarendon Press | year =1884 | location =Oxford | language =English: translated from Prakrit | url =http://www.sacred-texts.com/jai/sbe22/sbe2200.htm | series =[[Sacred Books of the East|Sacred Books of the East vol.22, Part 1]] | isbn =0-7007-1538-X }} ''Note: ISBN refers to the UK:Routledge (2001) reprint. URL is the scan version of the original 1884'' reprint.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
If among monks or nuns occurs a quarrel or dispute or dissension, the young monk should ask forgiveness of the superior, and the superior of the young monk. They should forgive and ask forgiveness, appease and be appeased, and converse without restraint. For him who is appeased, there will be success (in control); for him who is not appeased, there will be no success; therefore one should appease one's self. 'Why has this been said, Sir? Peace is the essence of monasticism'.
&lt;p&gt; — ''Kalpa Sūtra'' 8:59&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==== Hoʻoponopono ====
[[Hoʻoponopono]] is an ancient Hawaiian practice of reconciliation and forgiveness, combined with prayer. Similar forgiveness practices were performed on islands throughout the [[Oceania|South Pacific]], including [[Samoa]], [[Tahiti]] and [[New Zealand]]. Traditionally Hoʻoponopono is practiced by healing priests or ''[[kahuna]] lapaʻau'' among family members of a person who is physically ill. Modern versions are performed within the family by a family elder, or by the individual alone.

== Popular recognition ==
The need to forgive is widely recognized by the public, but they are often at a loss for ways to accomplish it.  For example, in a large representative sampling of American people on various religious topics in 1988, [[the Gallup Organization]] found that 94% said it was important to forgive, but 85% said they needed some outside help to be able to forgive.  However, not even regular prayer was found to be effective.  The Gallup poll revealed that the only thing that was effective was &quot;[[meditation|meditative prayer]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gorsuch, R. L. &amp; Hao, J. Y. &quot;[http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=96262671 Forgiveness:  An exploratory factor analysis and its relationship to religious variables]&quot;, June 1993 ''Review of Religious Research'' 34 (4) 351-363.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Wikiquote}}
* [[A Course In Miracles]]
* [[Anantarika-karma]]
* [[Clementia]], Roman goddess of forgiveness (and [[Eleos]], her Greek counterpart)
* [[Compassion]]
* [[Contrition]]
* [[Ethics in religion]]
* [[Ho'oponopono]]
* [[Letter of Reconciliation of the Polish Bishops to the German Bishops]]
* [[Pardon]]
* [[Relational transgressions]]
* [[Repentance]]
* [[Unconditional love]]

== Notes ==
{{reflist|2}}

== References ==
{{Refbegin}}
* ''Balancing the Scales of Justices with Forgiveness and Repentance'', Randall J. Cecrle, 2007, ISBN 1-60266-041-7
* ''The Power of Forgiveness'', Marcus G. 2011, Sapients.Net
* ''Radical Forgiveness: Making Room for the Miracle'', Colin Tipping, 1997, ISBN 0-9704814-1-1
* ''Forgiving and Not Forgiving: Why Sometimes It's Better Not to Forgive'', Jeanne Safer, 2000, ISBN 0-380-79471-3
* Forgiveness: a Philosophical Exploration (Cambridge University Press, 2007), by Charles Griswold.  ISBN 978-0-521-70351-2.
* Hein, David. &quot;Regrets Only: A Theology of Remorse.&quot; ''The Anglican'' 33, no. 4 (October 2004): 5-6.
* Hein, David. &quot;Austin Farrer on Justification and Sanctification.&quot; ''The Anglican Digest'' 49.1 (2007): 51–54.
* Konstan, David, ''Before Forgiveness: The Origins of a Moral Idea'' (Cambridge/New York:  Cambridge University Press, 2010).
* Kramer, J. and Alstad D., The Guru Papers: Masks of Authoritarian Power, 1993, ISBN 1-883319-00-5
* Lampert, K.(2005); Traditions of Compassion: From Religious Duty to Social Activism. Palgrave-Macmillan; ISBN 1-4039-8527-8
* Fred Luskin, Ph.D. ''Forgive for Good: A Proven Prescription for Health and Happiness'' (Harper, 2002)
* Schmidt D. (2003); The Prayer of Revenge: Forgiveness in the Face of Injustice; ISBN 0-7814-3942-6
* ''Toxic Parents: Overcoming Their Hurtful Legacy and Reclaiming Your Life'', Susan Forward, 1990.
* ''The Railway Man: A POW's Searing Account of War, Brutality, and Foregiveness'', Eric Lomax,
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Commons category|Forgiveness}}
*{{DMOZ|/Society/Relationships/Forgiveness/}}
*[http://www.mindgarden.com/products/efins.htm Mindgarden.com] The Enright Forgiveness Inventory for Research
{{Christian Soteriology}}
{{Emotion-footer}}

[[Category:Buddhist ethics]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Christian theology]]
[[Category:Virtue]]
[[Category:Philosophy of love]]
[[Category:Positive psychology]]
[[Category:Religious behaviour and experience]]
[[Category:Religious ethics]]
[[Category:Spirituality]]
[[Category:Theology]]
[[Category:Emotions]]

[[az:Bağışlanma]]
[[bg:Прошка]]
[[br:Pardon]]
[[ca:Perdó]]
[[cs:Odpuštění]]
[[de:Vergebung]]
[[es:Perdón]]
[[eo:Pardono]]
[[eu:Barkamen]]
[[fr:Pardon]]
[[io:Mizerikordio]]
[[it:Perdono]]
[[he:סליחה]]
[[ms:Pengampunan]]
[[nl:Vergeving (algemeen)]]
[[no:Tilgivelse]]
[[pt:Perdão]]
[[scn:Pirdunu]]
[[sk:Odpustenie]]
[[sv:Förlåtelse]]
[[tl:Kapatawaran]]
[[uk:Прощення]]</text>
      <sha1>1n8dbcdjtepu0y1ajx7n9kanghlrykz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
