<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Full communion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>102689</id>
    <revision>
      <id>498855915</id>
      <parentid>498173026</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-22T16:53:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GrahamSmith</username>
        <id>2427052</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Disambiguated: [[Syrian Catholic Church]] → [[Syriac Catholic Church]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16195">In [[Christianity|Christian]] [[ecclesiology]], '''full communion''' is a relationship between church organizations or groups that mutually recognize their sharing the essential doctrines.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/ISSUES/ENGBISHO.TXT On Receiving Anglican clergy into the Catholic Church]; [http://www.catholic.com/library/How_to_Become_a_Catholic.asp How to become a Catholic]; [http://www.zenit.org/article-20753?l=english When an Orthodox joins the Catholic Church];[http://www.rcab.org/OfficeForWorship/RCIA_Participant_Qualification.html On Participants in RCIA and Confirmation]; [http://rightreason.ektopos.com/archives/2007/05/my_return_to_th.html My Return to the Catholic Church]; etc.&lt;/ref&gt;

For the [[Catholic Church]] and the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], full communion exists only between Christians who form a single church. [[Protestantism|Protestants]] understand full communion as instead a matter of practical relations among [[Christian denominations|denominations]] that nonetheless fully retain their distinct identities.

==Catholic Church==
The [[Catholic Church]] makes a distinction between full and partial communion. Where full communion exists, there is but one Church. Partial communion, on the other hand, exists where some elements of Christian faith are held in common, but complete unity on essentials is lacking. For instance, the Roman Catholic Church sees itself as in partial communion with Protestants, and as in much closer, but still incomplete, communion with the Orthodox Churches.

It has expressed this idea in many documents. The [http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_decree_19641121_unitatis-redintegratio_en.html Decree on Ecumenism] of the [[Second Vatican Council]], 3 states: &quot;... quite large communities came to be separated from ''full communion'' with the Catholic Church ... men who believe in Christ and have been truly baptized are in communion with the Catholic Church even though this ''communion is imperfect''&quot;. The [[Catechism of the Catholic Church]], citing documents of the Second Vatican Council and of [[Pope Paul VI]], states:
{{Quote|&quot;The Church knows that she is joined in many ways to the baptized who are honoured by the name of Christian, but do not profess the Catholic faith in its entirety or have not preserved unity or communion under the successor of Peter&quot; (''Lumen gentium'' 15). Those &quot;who believe in Christ and have been properly baptized are put in a certain, although imperfect, communion with the Catholic Church&quot; (''Unitatis redintegratio'' 3). ''With the Orthodox Churches'', this communion is so profound &quot;that it lacks little to attain the fullness that would permit a common celebration of the Lord's Eucharist&quot; (Paul VI, Discourse, 14 December 1975; cf. ''Unitatis redintegratio'' 13-18).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p123a9p3.htm#III Catechism of the Catholic Church, 838]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Full communion involves completeness of &quot;those bonds of communion &amp;ndash; faith, sacraments and pastoral governance &amp;ndash; that permit the Faithful to receive the life of grace within the Church.&quot;[http://clsa.org/content/files/USCCB_memo_2006_0405.pdf]

The [[particular Church]]es that form the Catholic Church are each seen, not as a separate body that has entered into practical arrangements concerning its relations with the others, but as the embodiment in a particular region or culture of the one Catholic Church.

The 28 May 1992 [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_28051992_communionis-notio_en.html ''Letter to the Bishops of the Catholic Church on some aspects of the Church understood as Communion''] expressed this idea as follows::
:The universal Church cannot be conceived as the sum of the particular Churches, or as a federation of particular Churches. It is not the result of the communion of the Churches, but, in its essential mystery, it is a reality ''ontologically'' and ''temporally'' prior to every ''individual'' particular Church.

This applies both to the [[Particular Church#Local particular Churches|local particular Churches]], such as [[diocese]]s or [[eparchy|eparchies]], in the Catholic Church and to the [[Particular Church#Autonomous particular Churches or Rites|&quot;sui iuris&quot; (autonomous) Churches]] within it.

The autonomous Catholic Churches in full communion with the [[Holy See]] are:
*Of [[Alexandrian Rite|Alexandria]]n liturgical tradition:
**[[Coptic Catholic Church]]
**[[Ethiopic Catholic Church]]
*Of [[Antiochene Rite|Antiochian]] liturgical tradition:
**[[Maronite Church]]
**[[Syriac Catholic Church|Syrian Catholic Church]]
**[[Syro-Malankara Catholic Church]]
*Of [[Armenian Rite|Armenian]] liturgical tradition:
**[[Armenian Catholic Church]]
*Of [[Byzantine Rite|Byzantine]] ([[Constantinople|Constantinopolitan]]) liturgical tradition:
**[[Albanian Byzantine Catholic Church]]
**[[Belarusian Greek Catholic Church]]
**[[Bulgarian Greek Catholic Church]]
**[[Byzantine Church of Croatia, Serbia and Montenegro]]
**[[Greek Byzantine Catholic Church]]
**[[Hungarian Greek Catholic Church]]
**[[Italo-Albanian Catholic Church]]
**[[Macedonian Greek Catholic Church]]
**[[Melkite Greek Catholic Church]]
**[[Romanian Church United with Rome, Greek-Catholic]]
**[[Russian Byzantine Catholic Church]]
**[[Ruthenian Catholic Church]]
**[[Slovak Greek Catholic Church]]
**[[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church]]
*Of [[East Syrian Rite|Chaldean or East Syrian]] tradition:
**[[Chaldean Catholic Church]]
**[[Syro-Malabar Church]]
*Of Western liturgical tradition:
**[[Latin Rite|Latin Church]]&lt;ref&gt;Of the various [[Latin liturgical rites]] used within the Latin particular Church, even those associated not with a religious order but with a geographical area do not constitute separate particular Churches. Thus there is no &quot;Ambrosian particular Church&quot; corresponding to the [[Ambrosian Rite]] in use in Milan and neighbouring areas of Italy and Switzerland, nor is there a &quot;Mozarabic Church&quot; in those parts of Spain where the [[Mozarabic Rite]] is practised. In the Latin Church, governance is uniform, even where liturgical rite is not.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Catholic Church sees itself as in partial, not full communion, with other Christian groups.  &quot;With the Orthodox Churches, this communion is so profound that it lacks little to attain the fullness that would permit a common celebration of the Lord's Eucharist&quot; ''[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]'' ([http://www.usccb.org/catechism/text/pt1sect2chpt3art9p3.htm 838]).

In fact, full communion is seen as an essential condition for sharing together in the [[Eucharist]], apart from exceptional circumstances, in line with the second-century practice witnessed to by Saint [[Justin Martyr]], who, in his ''[[First Apology]]'' [http://www.ccel.org/fathers/ANF-01/just/justinapology1.html#Section66], wrote: &quot;No one is allowed to partake (of the Eucharist) but the man who believes that the things which we teach are true, and who has been washed with the washing that is for the remission of sins, and unto regeneration, and who is so living as Christ has enjoined.&quot;

Accordingly, &quot;Catholic priests are forbidden to concelebrate the Eucharist with priests or ministers of Churches or ecclesial communities which do not have full communion with the Catholic Church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P38.HTM Canon 908] of the ''Code of Canon Law''; cf. [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/LAT0758/_P1S.HTM canon 702] of the ''Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches''&lt;/ref&gt;

The [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/general-docs/rc_pc_chrstuni_doc_19930325_directory_en.html Directory for the Application of Principles and Norms on Ecumenism, 122&amp;ndash;136] indicates the circumstances in which some sharing in sacramental life, especially the [[Eucharist]], is permitted with other Christians.

The norms there indicated for the giving of the Eucharist to other Christians are summarized in
[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P2T.HTM canon 844] of the ''Code of Canon Law'' as follows:
:§3. Catholic ministers administer the sacraments of penance, Eucharist, and anointing of the sick licitly to members of Eastern Churches which do not have full communion with the Catholic Church if they seek such on their own accord and are properly disposed. This is also valid for members of other Churches which in the judgment of the Apostolic See are in the same condition in regard to the sacraments as these Eastern Churches.
:§4. If the danger of death is present or if, in the judgement of the diocesan bishop or conference of bishops, some other grave necessity urges it, Catholic ministers administer these same sacraments licitly also to other Christians not having full communion with the Catholic Church, who cannot approach a minister of their own community and who seek such on their own accord, provided that they manifest Catholic faith in respect to these sacraments and are properly disposed.

The ''Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches'' indicates that the norms of the Directory apply also to the clergy and laity of the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]].&lt;ref&gt;''Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches'', [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/LAT0758/_P2F.HTM canons 908] and [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/LAT0758/_P3Z.HTM#4E 1440]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Eastern Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox churches==
{{See also|List of Orthodox Churches}}

[[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]] and [[Oriental Orthodoxy|Oriental Orthodox]] Christians have an understanding of what full communion means that is very similar to that of the Catholic Church. Though they have no figure corresponding to that of the Roman Catholic Pope, performing a function like that of the Pope's [[Petrine Office]], they see each of their [[autocephaly|autocephalous]] Churches as embodiments of, respectively, the one Eastern Orthodox Church or the one Oriental Orthodox Church. They too consider full communion an essential condition for common sharing in the Eucharist. The [[Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople]], as [[first among equals]] among the Eastern Orthodox autocephalous churches and their spiritual leader, though not having authority similar to that of the Roman Catholic Pope, serves as their spokesman. The [[Pope of the Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria]] holds a somewhat similar position in Oriental Orthodoxy.

For the autocephalous Churches that form the Eastern Orthodox Church, see [[Eastern Orthodox Church organization]]. Their number is somewhat in dispute.

The Churches of Oriental Orthodoxy are: the [[Coptic Christianity|Coptic]], [[Armenian Apostolic Church|Armenian Apostolic]], [[Eritrean Orthodox Church|Eritrean Orthodox]], [[Syriac Orthodox Church|Jacobite]], [[Indian Orthodox Church|Indian Orthodox]] and [[Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church]]es.

==Other churches==
Other churches see full communion between them as meaning that their members may licitly participate in each others' [[rite]]s, particularly in the partaking of the [[Eucharist]] in [[closed communion]] denominations, and involving also recognition of each other's offices of ministry as valid and thus, in most cases, interchangeability of ordained ministers.  Importantly, the existence of full communion, as thus understood, does not presume that there is no difference in rites or in doctrine between the two Churches, but rather that these differences do not touch on points defined as essential.

The word &quot;intercommunion&quot; is sometimes used of this arrangement, which is much less close than the unity between Churches that share a common history, such as the [[Anglican Communion]].

This understanding of &quot;full communion&quot; differs from that of the Roman Catholic Church and Eastern Christianity in that the churches that enter into such arrangements do not consider themselves as forming together a single church.

It is in the stronger sense of becoming a single church that the [[Traditional Anglican Communion]] sought &quot;full communion&quot; with the [[Roman Catholic Church]] as a ''[[sui iuris]]'' (particular Church) jurisdiction. Its membership is now deciding whether to accept the offer of full communion (again in the stronger sense) within the framework of [[personal ordinariate]]s of the [[Latin Rite]] of the Roman Catholic Church.

===Agreements between churches===
The following groupings of churches have arrangements for or are working on arrangements for:
* mutual recognition of members
* joint celebration of the Lord's Supper/Holy Communion/Eucharist (these churches practice [[open communion]])
* mutual recognition of ordained ministers
* mutual recognition of sacraments
* a common commitment to mission.

;Agreements completed
# The [[Anglican Communion]], the [[Old Catholic Church]], the [[Mar Thoma Syrian Church of India]], and the [[Philippine Independent Church]].
# The Churches of the [[Porvoo Communion]]
# The [[Anglican Church of Canada]] and the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in Canada]]
# The [[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)]] and the [[United Church of Christ]]
# The [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]] and each of the following: the member churches of the [[Lutheran World Federation]], the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America]], the [[Presbyterian Church USA]], the [[Reformed Church in America]], the [[United Church of Christ]], the [[United Methodist Church]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elca.org/Who-We-Are/Our-Three-Expressions/Churchwide-Organization/Communication-Services/News/Releases.aspx?a=4274] ''ELCA Shares Significant Actions with Ecumenical, Global Partners''&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Moravian Church]] in America.
# The [[Moravian Church]] and each of the following: the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]] and the [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopal Church]] USA.
# The [[United Methodist Church]] with the [[African Methodist Episcopal Church]], the [[African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church]], the [[Christian Methodist Episcopal Church]], and the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]].
# The [[United Church of Christ]] and each of the following: the [[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)]], the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]], [[Presbyterian Church USA]], and the [[Reformed Church in America]].
# The [[United Episcopal Church of North America]] and each of the following: the [[Anglican Catholic Church]], the [[Anglican Province of Christ the King]], and the [[Diocese of the Great Lakes]].
# The [[Anglican Province of America]] has intercommunion with the [[Reformed Episcopal Church]] and the [[Church of Nigeria]].

;Agreements in progress
# The [[United Methodist Church|United Methodist]] [[United Methodist Council of Bishops|Council of Bishops]] have approved interim agreements for sharing the Eucharist with the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.umc.org/interior.asp?ptid=1&amp;mid=7664 Council approves interim pacts with Episcopalians, Lutherans]&lt;/ref&gt;
# The [[Church of England]] is currently working toward full communion with the [[Methodist Church of Great Britain]].{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}
# Many of the [[Independent Catholic Churches]] are working toward full communion with each other and with the [[Old Catholic Church|Old-Catholic Union of Utrecht]].{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

==See also==
* [[Communion (Christian)]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.newmartyr.org.uk/branch.html Broken but Never Divided: An Eastern Orthodox Perspective]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Full Communion}}
[[Category:Christian group structuring]]
[[Category:Ecclesiology]]
[[Category:Christian ecumenism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[bs:Sestrinske crkve]]
[[ca:Comunió completa]]
[[cs:Společenství (křesťanství)]]
[[de:Kirchengemeinschaft]]
[[id:Komuni penuh]]
[[it:Piena comunione]]
[[nl:Communio (kerken)]]
[[ja:フル・コミュニオン]]
[[no:Kommunion (kirkefellesskap)]]
[[pl:Interkomunia]]
[[ru:Евхаристическое общение]]
[[simple:Full communion]]
[[sl:Polno občestvo]]
[[sh:Puno opštenje]]
[[sv:Sakramental enhet]]
[[uk:Євхаристійне спілкування]]</text>
      <sha1>78r3m6jz3henlolbjggs2c6mdsebugo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
