<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Great Apostasy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>82181</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516961747</id>
      <parentid>516682998</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-10T06:35:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Esoglou</username>
        <id>11289927</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>The state church of the Roman Empire was set up in 380</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="74341">{{For|the book by James E. Talmage|The Great Apostasy (book)}}
[[File:PapalPolitics2.JPG|right|thumb|''Antichristus'', a woodcut by Lucas Cranach of the pope using the temporal power to grant authority to a generously contributing ruler]]

The '''Great Apostasy''' is a term used by some religious groups to describe a general fallen state of traditional [[Christianity]], especially the [[Roman Catholic Church|Papacy]], because they claim it allowed the traditional Roman mysteries and deities of [[Sun|solar]] [[monism]] such as [[Mithras]] and [[Sol Invictus]] and [[idol worship]] back into the church, and is not representative of the [[Ministry of Jesus|faith founded by Jesus]] and his [[twelve Apostles]]: in short, in their opinion, the church has fallen into [[apostasy]].&lt;ref name = HN1&gt;{{Cite book | last = Newcomb | first = Harvey | authorlink = Harvey Newcomb | title = Great Apostasy: Being an Account of the Origin, Rise and Progress of Corruption and Tryanny in the Church of Rome | publisher = Kessinger Publishing | year = 2003 | pages = ix | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=XZ0JL9AhS0wC&amp;lpg=PA33&amp;dq=the%20great%20apostasy&amp;pg=PR9#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = JTC1&gt;{{Cite book | last = Talmage | first = James E.| authorlink = James E. Talmage | title = [[Jesus the Christ (book)|Jesus the Christ]] | publisher = LDS Church | year = 1973 | pages = 745–757 |edition= 40th ed |oclc= 2012826 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They feel that to conciliate the Pagans to nominal Christianity, the Catholic Church took measures to amalgamate the Christian and Pagan festivals &lt;ref&gt;Will Durant in The Story of Civilization, Volume 3, &quot;Caesar and Christ&quot;:
&lt;/ref&gt; so pagans would join the church; for example, bringing in the pagan festival of Easter as a substitute for the Pasch or Passover, although neither [[Jesus]] nor his [[Apostles]] enjoined the keeping of this or any other festival.&lt;ref&gt;Socrates, ''Church History'', 5.22, in {{cite web
 | last = Schaff
 | first = Philip
 | title = The Author's Views respecting the Celebration of Easter, Baptism, Fasting, Marriage, the Eucharist, and Other Ecclesiastical Rites.
 | work = Socrates and Sozomenus Ecclesiastical Histories
 | publisher = Calvin College Christian Classics Ethereal Library
 |date=July 13, 2005
 | url = http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf202.ii.viii.xxiii.html
 | accessdate = March 28, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Two Babylons, p.104-105&lt;/ref&gt;
It is officially agreed by the Catholic Church that it was magisterial [[Protestantism]] and [[Eastern Orthodoxy]] that fell into apostasy.

==Overview==
{{POV-section|date=January 2012}}
[[File:Bronnikov gimnpifagoreizev.jpg|thumb|right|350px|Greek [[mysticism]] influenced many early church theologians such as [[Clement of Alexandria]] and [[Origen]]. ]]
History shows that the early church especially in Rome, was influenced by pagan rituals and beliefs from the [[Roman imperial cult]], [[Hellenistic philosophy]], notably [[Neoplatonism]], and [[Gnosticism]]. Some modern scholars believe that the church in the early stages picked up pagan oral teachings from [[Palestine|Palestinian]] and [[Hellenistic civilization|Hellenistic]] sources which formed the basis of a secret oral tradition, which in the 4th century came to be called the [[disciplina arcani]]. Mainstream theologians{{who|date=January 2012}} believe it contained  liturgical details and certain other pagan traditions which remain a part of some branches of mainstream Christianity{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} (for example, the doctrine of [[Transubstantiation]] is thought to have been a part of this{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} by Catholic theologians{{who|date=January 2012}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;Stroumsa&quot;&gt;G.G. Stroumsa, ''Hidden Wisdom: Esoteric Traditions and the Roots of Christian Mysticism'', 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Frommann, ''De Disciplina Arcani in vetere Ecclesia christiana obticuisse fertur'', Jena 1833.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;E. Hatch, ''The Influence of Greek Ideas and Usages upon the Christian Church'', London, 1890, Chapter 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Important  esoteric influences on the church were the Christian theologians [[Clement of Alexandria]] and [[Origen]], the main figures of the [[Catechetical School of Alexandria]].&lt;ref&gt;Jean Danielou, ''Origen'', translated by Walter Mitchell, 1955.&lt;/ref&gt; Origen wrote about 6,000 books&lt;ref&gt;''Haer''., lxiv.63&lt;/ref&gt; - and it is unclear whether pagan traditions such [[reincarnation]] and the [[pre-existence]] of [[soul]]s formed part of [[Origen]]'s beliefs.

[[Protestantism|Protestants]], most significantly starting with [[Martin Luther]], who wrote the [[95 Theses]], and  [[Evangelical Christians]] not following the rites of Latin [[Catholic]] and [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] [[Christianity|Christian]] [[religious denomination|denominations]], have formally taught that the [[Bishop of Rome]], along with the Catholic Church, greatly abused the original teachings and practices of the [[Apostolic Age|primitive]] or ''original Christian church'' as depicted in the [[Acts of the Apostles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Acts|11:26}} Bible Verse Finder&lt;/ref&gt; They teach that the Papacy arose after the Roman Empire and slowly became corrupted as it strove to attain great dominion and authority, civil and ecclesiastical,&lt;ref&gt;The Council of Chalcedon (415, A.D.) made the following declaration in Canon 28: &quot;The Bishop of New Rome (Constantinople) shall enjoy the same honor as the Bishop of Old Rome, for the former possesses the same privileges.&quot; (Disciplinary Decrees of the General Councils, Schroeder, p. 125)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;He (Theodore I, bishop of Rome, 642-649 DJR) was the first Pope officially styled 'Sovereign Pontiff,' and the last whom the bishops called 'brother.' The pre-eminence of the first See and the extension of the Pontifical authority were becoming more necessary in proportion as the Church spread further her conquests.&quot; (Darras, Vol. II, p. 232).&lt;/ref&gt;  and retained pagan beliefs held during the Empire. It arrayed itself in a Christian garb on the heathen one that had dominated during the Roman Empire. For example, it reinstated the ceremonies and obligations of the [[Collegium Pontificum]] and the position of [[Pontifex Maximus]] of the ancient Roman polytheistic religion and created Christian orders to replace the ancient Roman ones such as the [[Vestal Virgin]]s and the [[flamen|flamines]]. 
[[File:95Thesen.jpg|thumb|The [[95 Theses]], circa 1517. Written in protest by [[Martin Luther]] against Church abuse.]] 

Following the [[Protestant Reformation]], Protestantism separated itself from Catholicism, and the subsequent denominations spawned from the Reformation have considered their own teachings to be [[Restorationism (Christian primitivism)|restorative in nature]], falling back to the basic tenets of [[Biblical law in Christianity|Biblical Christianity]] and [[Sola Scriptura]]. Although each denomination may differ in application, the essential ideas of the Reformation remain foundational. In turn, these views are taught in the modern descendant denominations, and historically these types of doctrinal stances account for the continuing separation of the denominations from the Catholic Church.

Protestant groups differ slightly in their perception of the types and the extent of errors evident in Catholic-Anglican-Orthodox traditions, and therefore their proposed corrections also differ, but all agree that the Catholic-Anglican-Orthodox tradition is to some important degree counter-biblical in the sense that it moves away from Scripture to reconcile many of its teachings and doctrine. This alleged &quot;corruption&quot; and resistance to reform by the traditional, especially Catholic, churches may sometimes be called ''The Great Apostasy'' by some religious groups. Although Protestant Christianity, as a whole, rejects the overall concept that the original Church (established by Jesus Christ) was thrown into complete anarchy and chaos through Catholicism, it does however assert that there was gross abuse of Biblical authority (especially by the [[Papacy]]) and a wandering from clear Biblical teachings prior to the Reformation.

In effect, some groups see themselves as uniquely restoring original Christianity. In their case, the term ''Great Apostasy'' is used more technically than above, directed in a sweeping way over all of Christianity beyond their group, indicating that true Christianity has not been preserved, but rather restored. These various groups differ as to exactly when the Great Apostasy took place and what the exact errors or changes were, but all of them make a similar claim that true Christianity was generally lost until it was disclosed again in themselves. The term ''Great Apostasy'' appears to have been coined in this narrower, technical sense, by &quot;[[Restorationism (Christian primitivism)|Restorationists]]&quot;. The term may sometimes be used in this sense by other groups claiming their unique authority as representing Christianity.

== Protestant Views ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}

[[Protestant Christianity]] separated itself from what it felt was the fulfilment of prophecy that there would be a falling away from the truth given by Jesus Christ and his apostles. They look to 2 Thessalonians  prediction regarding the &quot;falling away.&quot; 2 Thess. 2:3-12 says, &quot;Let no one deceive you by any means; for that Day will not come unless the falling away comes first, and the man of sin is revealed, the son of perdition, who opposes and exalts himself above all that is called God or that is worshiped, so that he sits as God in the temple of God, showing himself that he is God. Do you not remember that when I was still with you I told you these things? And now you know what is restraining, that he may be revealed in his own time. For the mystery of lawlessness is already at work; only he who now restrains will do so until he is taken out of the way. And then the lawless one will be revealed, whom the Lord will consume with the breath of His mouth and destroy with the brightness of His coming. The coming of the lawless one is according to the working of Satan, with all power, signs, and lying wonders, and with all unrighteous deception among those who perish, because they did not receive the love of the truth, that they might be saved. And for this reason God will send them strong delusion, that they should believe the lie, that they all may be condemned who did not believe the truth but had pleasure in unrighteousness.&quot; 

They felt Papacy fulfilled the falling away of the scriptures, for it agrees on the prophecy in all the following points: 

1. It has one official man as its head, and its claims are centered in him, the Bishop of Rome. 

2. The Bishop of Rome exalts himself against all that is called God; e.g., he is addressed by terms (Pope, Supreme Pontiff, Holy Father, etc.) which belong only to God, and that man came with and out of an apostasy, the very kind the apostles describe elsewhere (1 Tim. 4:1-3; Acts 20:28-31; 2 Pet. 2:1-3). 

3. He sits in the temple of God, e.g., his sphere of dominion is in the church or temple of God, as seen in the Papacy. 

4. His appearance was hindered by some force in Paul's time (2 Thess. 2:6-7); e.g., when the bishops of Rome began to assert power, they were in conflict with the Roman civil government; however, when the Roman empire collapsed, they quickly gained supremacy. 

5. The mystery of iniquity was already working in Paul's day (2 Thess. 2:7) and would continue until the Lord's coming (2 Thess. 2:8).

6.  The apostasy would produce fraudulent miracles, signs and wonders; e.g., supposed cures brought about by relics and shrines. 

7. The Lord shall destroy him with the brightness of His coming (2 Thess. 2:8). Only by a continual succession of the men of sin as seen in the line of men ascended to the title of Pope, could this be possible. 

Protestantism asserts that many abuses by Church leadership occurred prior to the Reformation in 1517 AD. Nevertheless, it does not suggest that these abuses led to a complete state of anarchy and apostate renderings of Scripture within the [[Early Church]]. In turn, from the Protestant perspective, abuses within the church led to a poor application of doctrine and Biblical Truths. Historically, this view is generally seen to have been declared by the contents of the ''[[95 Theses]]'' compiled by [[Martin Luther]].

To a large degree, Protestantism recognizes that the [[Constantine the Great and Christianity|formation of the Orthodox-Catholic Church under Caesar Constantine I]] (c. 325 AD) sought to bring stability, continuity and organization to the birth of the relatively new Christian faith. However, through decades of succession by poor, often politically motivated leadership, abuses of Scriptural application became prevalent. '''''In turn, Protestantism generally asserts that although Scripture itself remained pristine, the leaders and teachers became fouled.''''' To that end, most of Traditional Christianity agrees that the Biblical message itself was ultimately never lost to mankind. In addition, historical and archeological evidence - such as the [[Dead Sea Scrolls]] -  have provided a considerable measure of creditability to this position.

Additionally, Protestant [[Evangelicals]] concede that although the Early Church had not completely &quot;fallen away&quot; after the death of the first [[Apostle (Christian)|Apostles]], it fell under the control of the bishop of Rome and became governed by errant men with a poor understanding of Scripture.

==Reformed Perspective==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
[[File:John Calvin.jpg|thumb|[[John Calvin]] started the [[Protestant Reformation]] in 1536 AD]]
{{Main|Protestant Reformation}}
[[Calvinism|Calvinist]]s have taught that a gradual process of corruption was predicted in the [[New Testament]], that this process began within the [[Apostolic Age|New Testament era]] itself, and culminated in a self-proclaimed corrective brought about by the [[Protestant Reformation]]. The Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox Churches had developed from early on the idea of [[infallibility of the Church]] &amp;mdash; that the Church may speak entirely without error in particular councils or edicts; or that, in a less definable way, the Church is infallibly directed so that it always stands in the truth; and indeed, and claim that the Church has the promise of [[Jesus]] that it shall do so. The Roman Catholic Church also developed on the parallel and complementary idea of [[Papal Infallibility|papal infallibility]] &amp;mdash; that the pope may speak in the same capacity; this idea was finally [[Dogmatic definition|defined dogmatically]] at the [[First Vatican Council]] of 1870 and incorporated into doctrine. 

In contrast, Protestants believe that the Church has only spoken infallibly through the [[Christian Bible|Scriptures]] since the time of the [[Twelve apostles|Apostles]], and should not expect to be completely free of error at any time until the [[Eschatology|end of the world]], and rather must remain continually vigilant to maintain a Biblical (and therefore authoritative) doctrine and faith, or else fall away from the Christian faith and become an enemy of the truth.

In the Reformed view of church history, the true church cannot declare itself infallible, but rather calls itself ''ecclesia semper reformanda'' (&quot;the Church which must be always reformed&quot;), the church that is always repenting of error. This Protestant view is that people are naturally inclined to elevate [[tradition]] to equality with the written testimony of the [[Bible]], which is the word of God{{citation needed|date=August 2012}} (cf. [[Sacred Tradition]]). The reforming churches believe that human weakness is naturally drawn to a form of false religion that is worldly, pompous, [[ritual]]istic, [[anthropomorphism|anthropomorphic]], [[polytheism|polytheistic]], infected with [[magical thinking]] and [[legalism (theology)|legalism]], and that values human accomplishment more highly or more practically than the work of God ([[divine grace]]) is valued. Given the chance, people will substitute the sort of religion they naturally prefer, over the [[Gospel]], see also [[Cafeteria Christianity]]. The [[Hebrew Bible]] contains multiple episodes of [[backsliding]] by the very people who first received God's revelation; to the Protestant mind, this shows that teaching the Gospel is a [[Discourse on holiness#The choice of following the teachings|straight and narrow path]], one that requires that natural religion be held in check and that God's grace, holiness, and otherness be rigorously proclaimed.

===Temptations of power===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
According to these Reformers, even as early as the Apostles a natural process of corruption began, and reached a crucial point of development when the Christian church was made the official religion of the [[Roman Empire]] by [[Theodosius I]]. From this point on, compromise of the truth deepened over time until the church became thoroughly worldly and corrupt, so that the true faith was first no longer openly taught, and instead suppressed, and at times persecuted, and cast out. The persecuted church was attractive to rejected people; but worldly men were attracted to the same church when it began to wield power and possessions. Protestants also believe that the [[Roman Emperor]]s were not about to support a church that they did not control. The development of formal [[hierarchy]] within the Catholic Church, as opposed to local [[Wiktionary:autonomy|autonomy]] among Christian congregations, with levels of rank among the bishops, and a handful of [[patriarch]]s to supervise the bishops, is seen by some Protestants as conducive to imperial manipulation of the Church, susceptible to general control by capture of only a few seats of power.

Similarly, the defenses of the right belief and worship of the church resided in the [[bishop]]s, and Protestants theorize that the process of unifying the doctrine of the Church also concentrated power into their own hands (see also [[Ignatius of Antioch]], who advocated a powerful bishop), and made their office an instrument of power coveted by ambitious men. They charge that, through ambition and jealousy, the church has been at times, and not very subtly, subverted from carrying out its sacred aim. For the Reformers, the culmination of this gradual corruption was typified, in a concentrated way, in the office of the [[Pope]] who took on ancient titles such as [[Pontifex Maximus]] and supreme power in the church, which they characterized in its final form as being an usurpatious throne of [[Satan]]ic authority set up in pretense of ruling over the [[Kingdom of God]].

===The dangers of theology===
{{Cleanup-rewrite|2=section|date=March 2011}}
Theological controversy also had a polluting effect, according to this view of ''Apostasy'' as a gradual process, rather than a cataclysmic event. That is, in the process of defending the received truth, the Church became sullied by the engagements with its opponents both outside and within the Church. Giving power to men as Bishops and Priest with forgiving power equal to Christ, the Church become so much like the Devil, desiring of power over the masses.{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}}

For example, the Church defeated [[paganism]], but incorporated many of its idols as saints and was also susceptible to incorporating attitudes and traditions which are foreign to the biblical faith. Or, for another case, in the process of overcoming [[Arius]]' religious hero-worship{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} of Jesus&lt;!-- Wrong: Arius did NOT worship Jesus, and Arianism is the doctrine that denies Jesus' divinity--&gt;, the church absorbed hero-worshiping ideas, so that, while the doctrine of Jesus was rescued from the heresy, the same idea continued in the veneration of the [[Saints]], although veneration of the saints and martyrs long predated the Arian heresy. Similarly for the early battles with [[Marcion]] and [[Valentinius]] and [[Montanus]], perhaps even as early as [[Simon Magus]], see also [[Early Christianity]]. This corruption was not necessarily intentional although, in some cases, it is suggested that teachers of error brought in these pollutions deceitfully in order to escape detection.

===Compromise with folk religion===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2009}}
Especially in the worship of the Church, many Protestants viewed the [[Roman Catholic Mass]] as an amalgam of superstitious inventions more reminiscent of a pagan mystery rite than the simple discipline taught by the Apostles and practiced by the early church. A number of Protestant denominations tend to think of many of the Catholic [[holy days]], and most of the rituals, as accommodations to the popular tastes of unconverted people through the centuries, incompatible with biblical faith. Natural tastes for pomp and ceremony, and the sort of natural belief in [[mana]] and [[fetishism]] that seem common in unrevealed religions, and the natural man's wish to have sacred places to pray in, and sacred objects that enable mortals to touch the divine, tempted people away from the truth of the absolute sovereignty, holiness, and otherness of God.&lt;!-- The Church was failing at its teaching mission and made too easy accommodations to practices that [[folk religion]] could accept in this erroneous fashion.--&gt;

===Verses used to support apostasy of the Roman Catholic Church===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
{{Main|Historicism (Christian eschatology)|Whore of Babylon}}
Although [[Lutherans]] and [[Calvinists]] hold that the [[Ecumenical Council]]s of the early and [[medieval]] church are true expressions of the Christian faith, many assert{{Weasel-inline|date=February 2011}} that the councils are at times inconsistent with one another, and err on particular points. The true Church, they argue, will be mixed with alien influences and false beliefs, which is necessary in order for these impurities ultimately to be overcome and the truth to be vindicated.
The [[Westminster Confession of Faith]] (Calvinist), states:

:The purest churches under heaven are subject both to mixture and error; and some have so degenerated, as to become no churches of Christ, but [[synagogues]] of [[Satan]]. Nevertheless, there shall be always a church on earth, to worship God according to his will. ''(25:5)''

Therefore, although these groups believe that errors can and have come into the church, they deny that there has ever been a time when the truth was entirely lost. They affirm that there shall be times when errors shall predominate, as they believe is foretold in the [[Bible]]. First [[Second Timothy|Timothy]] 4:1-3 states:

:Now the Spirit speaketh expressly, that in the latter times some shall depart from the faith, giving heed to seducing spirits, and doctrines of devils;
:Speaking lies in hypocrisy; having their conscience seared with a hot iron;
:[[Celibacy|Forbidding to marry]], and commanding to [[Vegetarianism|abstain from meats]], which God hath created to be received with thanksgiving of them which believe and know the truth. ([[King James Version of the Bible|KJV]])

Acts 20:28-29
:Take heed therefore unto yourselves, and to all the flock, over the which the Holy Ghost hath made you overseers, to feed the church of God, which he hath purchased with his own blood.
:For I know this, that after my departing shall grievous wolves enter in among you, not sparing the flock. ([[King James Version of the Bible|KJV]])

Even Jesus warned:

:&quot;Then many will fall away, and they will betray one another and hate one another. And many [[false prophet]]s will arise and lead many astray. And because of the increase of [[antinomianism|lawlessness]], the love of many will grow cold. But the one who endures to the end will be saved. And this [[Gospel|good news]] of the [[Kingdom of God|kingdom]] will be proclaimed throughout the world, as a [[Great Commission|testimony to all the nations]]; and then the [[end times|end]] will come.&quot; [[Gospel of Matthew]] 24:10-14([[NRSV]])

According to this view, these verses foretold the rise of errors, among which they count the veneration of [[relic]]s, [[saints]] and the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]], importing [[polytheism]], [[idolatry]], and [[fetishism]] into Christianity; these are the &quot;seducing spirits and doctrines of devils.&quot;

The &quot;forbidding to marry&quot; and the &quot;commanding to abstain from meats&quot; (foods) were held to refer to the elaborate code, or [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Canon law]] of the Roman Catholic Church, involving [[clerical celibacy|priestly celibacy]], [[Lent]], and similar rules promulgated by the medieval church. Calvinists thought these rules were [[legalism (theology)|legalism]] and inappropriate impositions on the faithful.

&quot;Speaking lies in hypocrisy&quot; and &quot;having their conscience seared with a hot iron&quot; were held to refer to the general corruption of the Church as it became heir to the Roman [[Emperor]]s and claimed to rule an earthly [[monarchy|kingdom]], and its [[prelate]]s became [[authoritarian]] [[lord]]s of civil government, achieving a social rank never sought by [[Jesus]] himself (see also [[Evangelical counsels]] and {{bibleverse||John|18:36}}). The &quot;searing of the conscience&quot; was interpreted as referring to the [[Roman Catholic]] development of [[casuistry]] that sought to justify these various acts, and to excuse the sins of the powerful in exchange for gifts of land and money.

[[2 Thessalonians]] 2:3-12 was held also to refer to a coming great apostasy. This text announces that the [[Second Coming]] of Jesus and the gathering of the church to him, cannot come:

:unless the falling away comes first, and the [[man of sin]] is revealed, the [[son of perdition]], who opposes and exalts himself above all that is called God or that is worshiped, so that he sits as God in the temple of God, showing himself that he is God.

These were held to be [[prophecy|prophecies]] of the [[Pope]]'s claim to [[infallibility]] and to be the [[Vicar of Christ]], sitting in Jesus' seat and in his stead. This interpretation is the source of the traditional identification of the Pope as [[Antichrist]], which occurs throughout Protestant literature of the Reformation period and afterwards. Chapter XXV, article 6, of the [[Westminster Confession]], a confessional statement issued in 1646 and important to the [[Presbyterian]] and other branches of the English-speaking [[Reformed churches]], states that:

:''There is no other head of the Church but the Lord Jesus Christ: nor can the Pope of Rome in any sense be head thereof; but is that Antichrist, that man of sin and son of perdition, that exalteth himself in the Church against Christ, and all that is called God.''

This article was abrogated in 1967 by the [[Presbyterian Church (USA)]], the largest Presbyterian denomination in the United States. It remains officially in force in other Presbyterian denominations.

===&quot;Roman Catholic apostasy&quot; doctrine supplanted by dispensationalism===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
{{anchor|Dispensationalism}}
Most leaders in mainstream Protestant churches have changed what was held from the start of the Reformation and backed away from teaching the apostasy of the Roman Catholic Church as it is the largest in the world, which is now felt to be divisive, and to belong to the more vehement quarrels of another day. Conservative and [[fundamentalist]] churches insisted on these teachings the longest, and some still do, especially among the stricter Calvinists and [[Fundamentalists]]. The spread of [[dispensationalism]] doctrine has led conservative Protestants to drop the traditional interpreting of the Book of Revelation as predicting events that have taken place throughout history (historicism) and pushed it to some far off future events (futurism). This has resulted in a re-interpretation of the [[end times]]; and while Protestant fundamentalists may continue to believe that the Roman Church errs, they have dropped the Protestant Reformation view or are less likely to believe that the Pope is Antichrist.

Dispensationalists generally view passages such as 2 Thessalonians (referenced above) as referring to a [[Third Temple|reconstructed Temple in Jerusalem]] (see also [[Jerusalem in Christianity]] and [[Christian Zionism]]) in the last days. The great &quot;Falling Away&quot;, they tend to view as a present or future affair, in which not only Rome but all of the world's religions join against the truth, for the sake of a false peace and prosperity.

For an extensive 18th century [[Protestant]] perspective on the Great Apostasy, see the treatment on that subject by the [[Germany|German]] historian [[Johann Lorenz von Mosheim|J. L. Mosheim]], a [[Lutheran]], whose six volume work in Latin on ''Ecclesiastical History'' is referred to by some Protestants who emphasize a great apostasy.

===The result===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
In this view, it would be difficult to set a clear dividing line as to when the purported widespread Apostasy began but Paul tells us it was already starting at the last days of the Roman Empire and the rise of the power that would take control over Christianity after it. It was a gradual process of corruption, as venal and materialistic leaders came into the Church, in love with their own high office and authority, and power was consolidated by the bishop of Rome into one man. The Great Apostasy surely was complete, for purposes of the Reformers, when the [[Council of Trent]] emphatically rejected even a modified form of Protestant reformation for the Roman Catholic Church. The [[ultramontanism|ultramontane]] tendencies of Rome continued to increase until at least the [[First Vatican Council]], with its proclamation of both [[papal infallibility]] and [[political absolutism|papal absolutism]], down to early 20th century changes in [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Canon law]] that make it more clear today than it was in the past that the Pope is the absolute monarch of the Roman Catholic Church, answerable to no council, no other bishop, and indeed to no other man or woman. Here the Protestants see the completion of the Great Apostasy as one man makes himself above all others as the pagan Emperors before strove to be.

The [[Second Vatican Council]] stated the Church as the pilgrim &quot;people of God&quot; and the collegiality of all the bishops &quot;in communion&quot; with the Pope.

It is also important to note that this view of the general Apostasy does not mean that the [[Gospel]] had lost its power to save, or that all Christians during this time were denied [[Heaven]]; rather, the Reformers characterized the papacy and the hierarchy of priests, as an usurpatious government pretending to rule over the kingdom of God. God's grace preserved the true teachings and the [[Bible]] intact despite the corruption of those who were supposed to be official spokesmen for [[Christendom]].

==Restorationist perspective==
{{Main|Restorationism (Christian primitivism)}}

===Anabaptists===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
The [[Anabaptism|Anabaptists]] of the [[Protestant Reformation]] believe that the Church became corrupt when [[Constantine I]] ended the persecution of Christians with the [[Edict of Milan]], and was not recovered until the Anabaptists came along. Other Reformers set other dates or time periods when the Church corrupted itself, making it necessary for them to leave the Roman Catholic Church in order to re-establish the true Church. Several groups, including [[Baptists]] and [[Mennonite]]s, believe that besides the Great Apostasy there has also always been a &quot;little flock&quot;, a &quot;narrow way&quot; which struggled through persecution and remained faithful to the truth. For example, the Mennonites published a book called the ''[[Martyrs Mirror]]'' in 1660 that attempted to show that exclusive [[Believer's baptism]] was practiced and passed down in every century, and how those who held that belief were persecuted for it.

Some Anabaptist and Baptist groups have held that the Apostasy of the Roman Catholic Church was so complete as to nullify its claims to Christianity. Consequently, in these groups, repudiation of the [[ecumenical council]]s has followed, in a few minority cases engendering [[seventh-day Sabbatarianism]] and [[unitarianism]], along with [[believers baptism]] and [[pacifism]], and other anti-traditional views. Some of these views, more radical than other Protestants, were influential in the founding of the [[Restoration Movement]] and the Adventist churches in the United States in the 19th century and continue to be influential in the [[house church]] movement.

====Christians in military service and political office====
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
The fusion of church and state as seen in the Papacy is a central theme of the Anabaptist view of the Great Apostasy, and of their consequent assertion during the [[Protestant Reformation]] that the churches of Catholic Europe needed not simply reform, but a radical re-establishment based on the Bible alone. In sympathy with this assessment, philosopher [[Jacques Ellul]], in &quot;Anarchy and Christianity&quot;, mentions a dramatic shift in AD 313, at the [[Council of Elvira]]. Christians who held public office were no longer cast out of the church entirely as apostates, but were only cast out so long as they held office. At the [[Synod of Arles]] in 314, [[Christian pacifism]] was totally reversed; the third canon excommunicated soldiers who refused military service, or who mutinied. The seventh canon of that same council allowed Christians to be state officials, as long as they did not take part in pagan acts. With this, Ellul sees the end of the original [[anti-statist]], anti-militarist, [[Christian anarchy|anarchist Christianity]]. However, accounts of martyred Christian soldiers from the 100s, 200s and early 300s indicate that Christians were allowed to continue serving in the Roman army provided they did not sacrifice to the Roman gods, and that therefore the original church may not have been as anti-militarist as Ellul supposes. [[Ignatius of Antioch]]'s letters from the 100s, the use of deacons in the [[Acts of the Apostles]] and Paul's [[Pastoral epistles]] describing deacons, bishops and presbyters suggest that the early church was not anarchist in the way it governed itself internally.

===The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Apostolic Succession]] --&gt;
[[File:Joseph Smith first vision stained glass.jpg|right|thumb|LDS Church members believe that [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]] was called by God to restore the true teachings of Jesus Christ]]
According to [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church), the Great Apostasy started not long after Jesus' [[Ascension of Jesus Christ|ascension]]&lt;ref name = PMG35&gt;{{Cite book | title = Preach My Gospel (A Guide to Missionary Service) | publisher = LDS Church | year = 2004 | page = 35 | url = http://lds.org/languages/additionalmanuals/preachgospel/PreachMyGospel___06_03-1_TheRestoration__36617_eng_006.pdf | isbn = 0-402-36617-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and continued until [[Joseph Smith, Jr.|Joseph Smith]]'s [[First Vision]] in 1820. To [[Latter-day Saint]]s, the Great Apostasy is marked by:
*the difficulty of the [[Twelve apostles|Apostles]] to keep early Christians from distorting Jesus' teachings and to prevent the followers from dividing into different ideological groups;&lt;ref name = MARV1&gt;{{Cite book | last = Richards | first = LeGrand | authorlink = LeGrand Richards | title = A Marvelous Work and a Wonder | publisher = Deseret Book Company | year = 1976 | page = 24 | url = http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=udFopREPKMgC&amp;lpg=PR2&amp;ots=H49-xX0hBQ&amp;dq=a%20marvelous%20work%20and%20a%20wonder&amp;pg=PA25#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | isbn = 0-87747-161-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*the [[Persecution of Christians|persecution]] and [[martyr]]dom of the church's Apostles;&lt;ref name = GA1&gt;{{Cite book | last = Talmage | first = James E. | authorlink = James E. Talmage | title = The Great Apostasy | publisher = The Deseret News | year = 1909 | page = 68 | url =http://www.archive.org/stream/greatapostasycon00atalm#page/68/mode/2up | isbn = 0-87579-843-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*the loss of leaders with [[Priesthood (Latter Day Saints)|Priesthood authority]] to administer the church and its ordinances;&lt;ref name = Eyring&gt;{{Citation | last = Eyring | first = Henry B. | author-link = Henry B. Eyring | title = The True and Living Church | url =http://lds.org/ensign/2008/05/the-true-and-living-church?lang=eng | journal = [[Ensign (LDS magazine)|Ensign]] | publisher = LDS Church | pages = 20–24 | date = May 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*the lack of [[continuous revelation]] to instruct the leaders and guide the church;&lt;ref name = PMG35/&gt; and
*the corruption of Christian doctrine by [[Greek philosophy|Greek]] or other allegedly [[paganism|pagan]] philosophies such as [[Neo-Platonism]], [[Platonic realism]], [[Aristotle]]anism and [[Ascetic#Christianity|Asceticism]].&lt;ref name = GA2&gt;{{Cite book | last = Talmage | first = James E. | authorlink = James E. Talmage | title = The Great Apostasy | publisher = The Deseret News | year = 1909 | pages = 64–65 | url =http://www.archive.org/stream/greatapostasycon00atalm#page/68/mode/2up | isbn = 0-87579-843-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning in the 1st century and continuing up to the 4th century AD the various [[List of Roman Emperors|emperors]] of the [[Roman Empire]] carried out violent persecutions against Christians.&lt;ref name = burning&gt;{{Cite book | last = Renan | first = Joseph | authorlink = Joseph Renan | title = The History of the Origins of Christianity. Book IV. The Antichrist | publisher = Mathieson &amp; Company | year = 1890 | pages = 60–75 | url = http://www.ccel.org/ccel/renan/antichrist.viii.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Apostles, [[bishop]]s, [[Disciple (Christianity)|disciples]] and other leaders and followers of [[Jesus]] who would not compromise their faith were persecuted and martyred.

The LDS Church declares that all [[Priesthood (Latter Day Saints)|Priesthood]] leaders with authority&lt;ref name = PMG35/&gt; to conduct and perpetuate church affairs were either [[martyr]]ed, taken from the earth, or began to teach impure doctrines, causing a break in the necessary [[Apostolic Succession]]. Latter-day Saints believe that what survived was but a fragment of the light and truth that Jesus had established: the Church of Jesus Christ, as established by him, was no longer to be found on the earth. Survivors of the persecutions were overly-influenced by various pagan philosophies either because they were not well indoctrinated in Jesus' teachings or they corrupted their Christian beliefs (willingly, by compulsion, or with good intentions but without direct revelation from God to help them interpret said beliefs) by accepting non-Christian doctrines into their faith. Latter-day Saints believe that many plain and simple truths of the gospel of Christ were, therefore, lost.&lt;ref name = PMG35/&gt;

Latter-day Saints understand various writings in the [[New Testament]] to be an indication that even soon after Jesus' [[Ascension of Jesus Christ|ascension]] the Apostles struggled to keep early Christians from distorting Jesus' teachings and to prevent the followers from dividing into different ideological groups.&lt;ref name = Faust&gt;{{Citation | last = Faust | first = James E. | author-link = James E. Faust | title = The Restoration of All Things | url = http://lds.org/liahona/2006/05/the-restoration-of-all-things?lang=eng&amp;query=restoration+all+things | journal = [[Liahona (magazine)|Liahona]] | publisher = LDS Church | pages = 61–62, 67–68 | date = May 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Latter-day Saints claim that various Old Testament and New Testament scriptures, including teachings of Christ himself, prophesy of this &quot;falling away&quot; or &quot;apostasy.&quot;  The Christian believers who survived the persecutions took it upon themselves to speak for God, interpret, amend or add to his doctrines and ordinances, and carry out his work without proper authority and divine direction from God to do so. During this time, important doctrines and rites were lost or corrupted.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last= Merrill |first= Hyde M. |title= The Great Apostasy as Seen by Eusebius |url= http://lds.org/ensign/1972/11/the-great-apostasy-as-seen-by-eusebius?lang=eng |month= November |year= 1971 |journal= Ensign |publisher= LDS Church }}&lt;/ref&gt; Latter-day Saints point to the doctrine of the [[Trinity]] adopted at the [[First Council of Nicaea|Council of Nicaea]] as an example of how pagan philosophy corrupted Jesus' teachings. [[Mormonism]] teaches that God, the Eternal Father, His Son, Jesus Christ, and the Holy Ghost are not [[consubstantial|one substance]], but three separate and distinct beings forming one [[Godhead (Latter Day Saints)|Godhead]].&lt;ref&gt;{{lds|Doctrine and Covenants|dc|130|22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Latter-day Saints reject the early [[ecumenical council]]s for what they see as misguided human attempts without divine assistance to decide matters of doctrine, substituting debate or politics for divine [[revelation]]. Latter-day Saints believe that the often heated proceedings of such councils were evidence that the church was no longer led by revelation and divine authority.

Thus, Latter-day Saints refer to the &quot;restitution of all things&quot; mentioned in {{bibleverse||Acts|3:20-21}} and claim that a [[Restoration (Mormonism)|restoration]] of all the original and primary doctrines and rites of Christianity was necessary.&lt;ref name = Faust/&gt;  The LDS believe that God the Father and His Son, Jesus Christ, appeared to a 14-year old boy named [[Joseph Smith, Jr.|Joseph Smith]] and called him to be a prophet.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Roberts| first = B. H. | author-link = B. H. Roberts | title = [[History of the Church (Joseph Smith)|History of the Church]] | publisher = Deseret News Press | pages = 1–8  | year = 1902 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Later Peter, James, and John, three of Christ's apostles in the New Testament, appeared from heaven to Smith and ordained him an apostle.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = D&amp;C 27:12 | url = http://classic.scriptures.lds.org/en/dc/27/12#12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Through Christ's Priesthood authority and divine direction from Christ, the LDS believe that Joseph Smith was called and ordained to re-establish Christ's church. Hence, members of the LDS faith refer to their church as &quot;The Church of Jesus Christ.&quot;  The term &quot;latter-day saints&quot; refers to the fact that members of Christ's church were originally called &quot;saints&quot; and that The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is Christ's restored church in these, what LDS and other Christian denominations believe, are the last days prior to prophesied second coming of Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Cook | first = Quentin L. | author-link = Quentin L. Cook | title = Are You a Saint? | url = http://lds.org/liahona/2003/11/are-you-a-saint?lang=eng | journal = Liahona | publisher = LDS Church | pages = 95–96 | date = November 2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Latter-day Saints maintain that other religions—Christian or otherwise—have a ''portion'' of the truth, though mingled with inaccuracies due to misinterpretations of some doctrines, such as the nature of the Godhead, how [[Adam and Eve (Mormonism)|Adam and Eve]]'s [[Agency (LDS Church)|choice]] in the Garden of Eden and their fall advanced the [[Plan of salvation]], the need for modern divine revelation through living [[prophet]]s and apostles, and the universal divine potential of mankind. They claim that [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] is the restoration of Jesus' original church, has the authentic Priesthood authority, and all doctrines and ordinances of the Gospel, fulfilling many of the prophecies of Daniel, Isaiah and Malachi in the Old Testament and also the prophesies of Peter and Jesus in the New Testament. (See Ref.)  They also maintain that many other religions, Christian and otherwise, advance many good causes and do much good among the people insofar as they are led by the light of Christ, &quot;which lighteth every man that cometh into the world.&quot; (John 1:9)

===Adventists===
Most Adventist groups in the [[Millerites|Millerite]] tradition hold similar beliefs about the Great Apostasy as other Restorationist types of Christian faith. Some of these, most notably the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]],  have traditionally held that the apostate church formed when Bishop of Rome began to dominate and brought heathen corruption and allowed pagan idol worship and beliefs to come in, and formed the Roman Catholic Church, which teaches others traditions over Scripture, and to rest from their work on Sunday, instead of [[seventh-day Sabbath|Sabbath]], which is not in keeping with Scripture. 

[[Seventh-day Adventists]] teach that great apostasy corresponded with the rise of the power of the Roman Bishop which they see as the [[Papacy|Little Horn Power]] of Daniel 7 prophecy, which as predicted rose after the breakup of the Roman Empire. In 533 A.D. Justinian, the emperor of the Eastern Roman Empire, legally recognized the bishop (pope) of Rome as the head of all the Christian churches. Because of the Arian domination of some of the Roman Empire by the barbarian tribes, this authority could not be exercised by the bishop of Rome. Finally, in 538 A.D., Belisarius, one of Justinian's generals routed the Ostrogoths, the last of the barbarian kingdoms, from the city of Rome and the bishop of Rome could begin establishing his universal civil authority. So, by the military intervention of the Eastern Roman Empire, the bishop of Rome became all-powerful throughout the area of the old Roman Empire. 

[[Seventh-day Adventists]] view the length of time the apostate church unbridled power was permitted to rule as shown in Daniel 7:25 &quot;The little horn would rule a time and times and half a time&quot; or 1,260 years. The papacy ruled supremely in Europe from 538 A.D. when the last of the Arian tribes was forced out of Rome and into oblivion, until 1798 A.D. when the French general Berthier took the pope captive, which history records a period of 1,260 years.

[[Seventh-day Adventists]] believe that the [[mark of the beast]] refers to the apostate church which in the [[end times]] will legally enforce Sunday-worship. &quot;Those who reject God's memorial of creatorship — the Bible Sabbath — choosing to worship and honor Sunday in the full knowledge that it is not God's appointed day of worship, will receive the 'mark of the beast.{{'&quot;}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Seventh-day Adventists Believe (2nd ed) |publisher=Ministerial Association, [[General Conference of Seventh-day Adventists]] |year=2005 |page=196}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Sunday Sabbath is purely a child of the Papacy. It is the mark of the beast.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Advent Review, Vol. I, No. 2, August, 1850.&lt;/ref&gt; They see an apostate church that changed God's law in preference of pagan traditions, and allowed pagan beliefs and ceremonies into the church and brought oppression against and persecuted the true believers throughout the Dark Ages for 1260 years as prophesied in Revelation 12:6, 14-16.&lt;ref&gt;''The Great Controversy'' by Ellen White, p266. &quot;[http://egwdatabase.whiteestate.org/nxt/gateway.dll/egw-comp/section00000.htm/book01953.htm/chapter01971.htm Chap. 15 - The Bible and the French Revolution]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Seventh-day Adventists Believe (2nd ed)|publisher=Ministerial Association, [[General Conference of Seventh-day Adventists]]|year=2005|isbn=1-57847-041-2|pages=184–185}}&lt;/ref&gt; They see the Roman Papacy stepping in after the Roman Empire was taken out of the way and fulling 2 Thessalonians 2:7 (New International Version) &quot;For the secret power of lawlessness is already at work; but the one who now holds it back will continue to do so till he is taken out of the way.&quot;

===Jehovah's Witnesses===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
Like many groups, [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] strive to reflect Christianity as they believe it was practiced in the 1st century, the [[Apostolic Age]]. The Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society and its precursor organization, Zion's Watch Tower Tract Society, considers the Great Apostasy to have properly begun before the death of the last Apostle, along with the warning signs and precursors starting shortly after Jesus' ascension. Jehovah's Witnesses consider adoption of the [[Trinity]]--which they allege is based on a specious application of Greek [[Platonism|Platonic]] and sophistical philosophy and is a violation of the Scriptural precepts set forth beginning in the Law of Moses—as a prime indicator of apostasy. Jehovah's Witnesses consider that the falling away from faithfulness was already complete before the [[First Council of Nicaea|Council of Nicaea]], when the [[Nicene Creed]] was adopted, which then enshrined the [[Trinity]] doctrine as the central tenet of nominal &quot;Christian&quot; orthodoxy.

This group strictly abstains from political involvement and military service, for reasons similar to those cited by earlier Anabaptists, and they point to such entanglements as another aspect of apostasy, or the willful rebellion against God and rejecting his Word of truth. Jehovah's Witnesses also teach that Jesus' statements regarding his disciples being separate from the world at {{bibleverse|John|17:6|}}, {{bibleverse|John|17:14-16|}}, and {{bibleverse|John|18:36|}} demonstrates that it is Jesus' intention that his disciples follow the pattern he set for them, as he said at {{bibleverse|John|13:15|}}.

They cite {{bibleverse|2|Thessalonians|2:3|}} [see discussion above] as indicating that the apostasy prophesied by Jesus at {{bibleverse|Matthew|7:15|}}, {{bibleverse|Matthew|13:24-30|}} and {{bibleverse|Matthew|13:36-43|}}, as well as {{bibleverse|Matthew|24:24|}} (and others) had already began in the 1st century of the Common Era, prior to the formation of the Catholic Church as a religion separate and distinct from the true Christian faith as taught and practiced by Jesus and his 1st-century followers.

===Hyperdispensationalism===
{{main|Hyperdispensationalism|Ultradispensationalism}}
Hyperdispensationalism is described as a niche sect in Protestism which views Pauline Christianity or the beliefs and doctrines espoused by Paul of Tarsus through his writings, as the purest form of Christian faith and worship.
[[Ethelbert William Bullinger|E. W. Bullinger]] framed the position for very early apostasy thus:
&lt;blockquote&gt;We are told, on every hand, today, that we must go back to the first three centuries to find the purity of faith and worship of the primitive church! But it is clear from this comparison of Acts xix.10 and 2 Tim.i.15, that we cannot go back...even to the apostle's own life-time!...It was Pauline truth and teaching from which all had &quot;turned away&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Carey,Juanita &quot;E.W.Bullinger: A Biography&quot;, p.148,quoting from Bullinger's ''The Church Epistles''.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Traditionalist Catholic perspective==
[[Sedevacantism|Sedevancantists]] and certain other [[traditionalist Catholics]] believe that the Great Apostasy began at the time of the [[Second Vatican Council]], or with the election of [[Pope John XXIII]], or shortly thereafter.

Sedevacantists believe the differences between the Roman Catholic Church before and after Vatican II are essential in nature, and enough to regard the contemporary, official Catholic Church as not truly Catholic, sometimes pointing to the [[Church of England]] as a model. They also point to the precipitous drop in church attendance that occurred after the [[Mass of Paul VI|new rite of the Mass]] was made mandatory in the Catholic Church, along with more liberal interpretations of Church doctrine which are considered heretical in some circles. [http://www.truecatholic.org/heresiesjp2.htm]

Sedevacantists share the idea with Protestants that the Catholic Church, as represented by the [[Holy See|Vatican]] is in a fallen state and no longer truly Christian. However, they differ in that they accept the Church as it existed until Vatican II, usually until the death of [[Pope Pius XII]] and all his pronouncements regarding doctrine, faith, and morals, and the rite of Mass before [[Annibale Bugnini]]'s first innovations were introduced in the 1950s, whereas most Protestants believe that the Catholic Church began to fall away with the rise of the Emperor Constantine, his legalization of Christianity, and its latter establishment as the state religion of the Roman Empire. (Traditional Catholics argue that Constantine, as a pagan Emperor, would have had no authority over the Church in doctrinal matters anyway.)

==Responses of Roman Catholicism and Eastern Orthodoxy==
Both the [[Roman Catholic Church]] and the [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox Church]] contend that they are still in harmony with the teachings and practices Jesus gave the Apostles, and that Jesus' promise has been fulfilled: &quot;On this rock I will build my church, and the gates of Hell shall not prevail against it.&quot; And elsewhere, &quot;I will be with you until the end of the age.&quot; Also, &quot;The Father . . . will give you another [[Paraclete|Advocate]] to be with you always.&quot; And the passages of St. Paul describing the church as Christ's body and as the &quot;pillar and bulwark of the truth.&quot;  (1 Tim 3:15) They point to their [[apostolic succession]] (among other things) as evidence that they are maintaining authentic orthodox Christian teachings. They see claims of a complete apostasy (as opposed to a widespread revolt) as a denial of the promise that Jesus made (as recorded in scripture) to be with his Church &quot;until the end of time&quot;. They also claim that their ecclesiastical structure (e.g. the Biblical practice of having bishops) and liturgical practices have their essential roots in the teachings and practices of the Apostles and early Christian community, and are not the result of radical changes introduced by either the imperial government or new converts in the 4th century. Many elements of modern orthodox teachings are traced back to the writings of those known as the [[Ante-Nicene Fathers]]. In these writings there is found information about the [[sacrament]]s, organizational structure, and general Christian lifestyle. 

The Catholic Church also believes in a future event termed &quot;The Great Apostasy&quot; based on Biblical teachings.  First there is the quote from 2 Thess. 2:3-4 :&quot;Let no man deceive you by any means, for unless there come '''a revolt first, and the man of sin be revealed, the son of perdition,'''  Who opposeth, and is lifted up above all that is called God, or that is worshipped, so that he sitteth in the temple of God, shewing himself as if he were God&quot; which points to the Great Apostasy happening in the future, during the time of anti-Christ.  Furthermore, 2 Thessolonians identifies this with the anti-Christ, who is held back by the Pope: &quot;And now you know what withholdeth, that he may be revealed in his time.   For the mystery of iniquity already worketh; only that he who now holdeth, do hold, until '''he''' be taken out of the way. And then that wicked one shall be revealed whom the Lord Jesus shall kill with the spirit of his mouth; and shall destroy with the brightness of his coming, him, Whose coming is according to the working of Satan, in all power, and signs, and lying wonders&quot; (2 Thess. 2:6-9).  This verse clearly shows that a man, whom Catholics believe is the Pope, holds back the anti-Christ, until he is killed.  This is due to the fact that the man was already holding back the wicked one, and must be the office of the Pope or otherwise this man has lived for 2000 years. These verses again also show that the Great Apostasy is a future event.

The Early Church Fathers also predicted a future Great Apostasy in the Church, for example Hippolytus: &quot;And the churches too will wail with a mighty lamentation, because neither oblation nor incense is attended to, nor a service acceptable to God; but the sanctuaries of the churches will become like a garden-watcher's hut, and the Holy Body and Blood of Christ will not be shown in those days. The public service of God shall be extinguished.&quot; (Third Century)

Protestants claim, however, that the Roman Catholic Church has ''added'' to the Deposit of Faith handed down by the Apostles, especially since the time of Reformation, such as the [[Immaculate Conception]] and [[Assumption of Mary]] and [[Papal Infallibility]], though Catholics can point to Biblical support for each.  The Orthodox Church also believes in the Assumption (which is termed the Dormition). In the view of Protestants, these are new doctrines and they take Roman Catholicism further from the Protestant understanding of Biblical Christianity, even though Catholics provide the Bibilical citations supporting their views. Roman Catholics also counter that the Dogmas of the Assumption and Immaculate Conception are well-supported in the writings of early Church Fathers (although some Protestants question the way Catholic theologians cite and interpret early Christian writings, or whether they have the same validity as the Holy Scripture), in addition to being supported by Holy Scripture. 

Orthodox Churches also note that the Roman Catholic Church has added doctrines since the time of the [[East-West Schism]], which justifies disunity between Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox churches. At the same time, both Roman Catholicism and Eastern Orthodoxy see much of Protestantism as having jettisoned much Christian teaching and practice wholesale, and having added much non-Christian dogma as well. They also accuse Protestants of distorting Scripture itself to support their own claims, whether by faulty translations, misinterpretations, or ignoring passages of Scripture which support Catholicism or Orthodoxy against Protestantism.&lt;ref&gt;[A Discovery of the Manifold Corruptions of Holy Scriptures http://www.eclipseofthechurch.com/Library/Martin_Corruptions.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

While both the Catholic and Orthodox Churches can claim Apostolic Succession, the Orthodox Church claims to be the only Christian church that has remained unchanged since its establishment by Christ and His Apostles, though their current teachings on divorce and contraception are novelties. Of course, that's not entirely correct; all churches have changed since their founding. The Orthodox Churches do not consider changes as changes. But while the Orthodox Church sees corruption of doctrine and authority in the Catholic Church just as the Protestants do, they view Protestantism as essentially &quot;throwing the baby out with the bathwater&quot;, ultimately separating themselves from the Truth to a larger degree than the Catholics.

===Historic Perspective===
Protestants often assert that practices that seem especially strange to them, such as regular fasting {{dubious|date=September 2011}} (several Protestant Churches practice fasting), veneration of relics and icons, honoring the Virgin Mary (known as the [[Theotokos]] to the Orthodox and as [[Blessed Virgin Mary|Mother of God]] to Catholics), and observing special holy days, must have been introduced after the time of Constantine (or even introduced by Constantine as a way to lead the Church into paganism). Documents from the pre-Constantine church often show otherwise; however, there were several different Christian sects before Constantine. Fasting is a biblical practice from even Old Testament times, and was mentioned by Jesus in the [[Sermon on the Mount]] and reportedly practiced by him as well. Early Christian documents refer to the regular practice of fasting. For example, the [[Didache]] (or &quot;Teaching of the Twelve&quot;) instructs Christians to fast every Wednesday and Friday, a practice the Orthodox Church continues to this day. Every feast day is preceded (or followed, as with [[Shrove Tuesday]] followed by [[Ash Wednesday]]) by a fast as well, in part to avoid the excessive revelry of pagan feasting without moderation. The catacomb church was surrounded by relics of necessity, but accounts of early martyrdoms show that Christians regularly sought the remains of the martyrs for proper burial and veneration. (See the ''[[Martyrdom of Polycarp]]''.) Many of these early accounts associate miracles with the relics: mentioned in Acts are Paul's handkerchiefs which healed the sick ({{bibleverse||Acts|19:11-12}}). The ''[[Infancy Gospel of James]]'' is attributed to [[James the Just]] but was certainly written no later than the 2nd century; it lays out additional details of Mary's life. This &quot;gospel&quot; is viewed by the Orthodox Church as apocryphal, and beneficial as a teaching tool only. The practice of observing special holy days was borrowed from the Jews, who were commanded to observe such days by God. In the same way, other practices were borrowed from the Jewish liturgy as well, such as the use of incense and oil lamps.
{{Further|Eucharist in the Catholic Church|Clerical celibacy (Catholic Church)|Lent}}
Regarding &quot;forbidding to marry&quot; and the &quot;commanding to abstain from meats&quot; in 1 Timothy 4, (Paul might have spoken in general in regards to any new sects or doctrines which could arise) the Catholic Church responds:
:&quot;...Regarding the Church's discipline of celibacy, men and women freely abstain from the high and holy good of marriage so that they can more fully give themselves to God and His work. Marriage is not &quot;forbidden.&quot; Neither is it considered evil. See the Catechism of the Catholic Church (Catechism), numbers 1618-20, especially the quote from St. John Chrysostom. 1 Timothy 4:1-5 needs to be read in context. There were those in Paul's time that forbade marriage on heretical presuppositions that marriage was intrinsically evil, a teaching based in turn on the false belief that the body or all matter was evil, and only the Spirit was good. This [[Gnostic]] heresy became prevalent again in the second century. The heresy became manifest in later centuries as well, with groups like the Albigensians, who also fell away from the Catholic Faith...With regard to foods, none are forbidden to Catholics. Unlike vegetarians, we may eat meat; unlike Jews and Muslims, we may eat pork, shellfish, and other non-kosher foods. Fasting—a practice actively promoted in Scripture—and abstinence from certain foods at particular times are good spiritual disciplines, but there is no food from which Catholics must abstain at all times...So who is Paul condemning regarding abstinence? He is referring to [[Gnostics]] and their spiritual descendants. In ascetic Gnosticism, we find both practices Paul condemned in his First Letter to Timothy. Ascetic Gnostics categorically forbade marriage (which libertine Gnostics also did) and abstained from sexual intercourse and meat all the time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://catholicexchange.com/2003/03/04/82916/ |title=Doesn’t St. Paul Condemn Celibacy, Fasting and Abstaining From Meat? |publisher=Catholic Exchange |date=2003-03-04 |accessdate=2012-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Orthodox Church also defines the concept of ''[[oikonomia]]'' which is exercised to facilitate salvation or worship, and is exemplified in the New Testament: in Acts 16:3 St. Paul set aside the usual rule to circumcise Timothy, whose father was a gentile, to placate certain Jewish Christians. In both instances, economy was exercised to facilitate the salvation of some of the parties involved.

===Worldly ambitions===
There have certainly been times when the Church has seemingly benefited from its affiliation with ruling governments, and vice versa. There is also much evidence that the Church sought to subvert or undermine ruling governments to bring them under its influence. It used its agents or allowed the methods to be adopted for the acquisition of greater power and influence for the Roman Catholic Church. The Jesuits were seen as church's soldiers, and, in the view of some, given free rein to use whatever methods as outlined in the forged anti-Catholic document ''[[Monita Secreta]]'', also known as the &quot;Secret Instructions of the Jesuits&quot; published (1612 and 1614) in [[Kraków]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10487a.htm | title=Monita Secreta | publisher=www.newadvent.org | work=[[Catholic Encyclopedia]] | year=1911 | accessdate=2 August 2011 | author=Gerard, John}}&lt;/ref&gt; and were also accused of using [[casuistry]] to obtain justifications for the unjustifiable in their work (See: [[formulary controversy]]; Blaise Pascals' [[Lettres Provinciales]]).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Pascal: Adversary and Advocate&quot; Robert J. Nelson, Harvard University Press, 1981. p. 190&lt;/ref&gt; 

There are also times in its history when the Church has taken a doctrinal stance directly contrary to the interests of the State. The Council of Chalcedon introduced a religious schism that undermined the Byzantine Empire's unity. The Emperor called the following [[Ecumenical Council]] in an attempt to reach a compromise position that all parties could accept, urging those involved to do so. A compromise was not reached, and the schism persisted. Later emperors introduced policies of [[iconoclasm]]; yet many Christians and Church leaders resisted for decades, eventually triumphing when a later Empress ([[Irene (empress)|Irene]]) came to power who was sympathetic to their cause. In Russia, [[Basil Fool for Christ|Basil, a &quot;Fool for Christ&quot;]] repeatedly stood up to [[Ivan the Terrible]], denouncing his policies and calling him to repentance; for this and other reasons he was buried in the [[Saint Basil's Cathedral|cathedral that now popularly bears his name]] in Moscow. The Greek Orthodox Church survived roughly 400 years under the Muslim Ottoman Empire, preserving its faith when it would have been socially advantageous to convert to Islam. More recently, in the 20th century, the Russian Orthodox Church survived over 70 years of persecution under [[Communism]], while Christians in many Muslim countries continue to refuse assimilation, in places including Egypt, Palestine, Turkey, and Iraq. Therefore, it would be more correct to say that there have been times when the State has seen that it was to its advantage to cooperate with the Church and to adjust accordingly, than to advocate the opposite position. More importantly, there is a consistency in Christian teaching, beginning with the persecuted church of its first few centuries, to the more established [[state church of the Roman Empire]], to the again persecuted church of the various Muslim and communist regimes.

===Theological dangers===
{{POV|date=January 2012}}
In response to the claim that the Church's response to one heresy led to an overcorrection in the opposite direction, it can only be admitted that this is always a real danger, and history provides abundant examples. One famous example is [[Nestorius]], the Patriarch of Constantinople who so vigorously defended Jesus' humanity that he undermined Jesus' divinity; A brief definition of Nestorian [[Christology]] can be given as: &quot;[[Jesus Christ]], who is not identical with the Son but personally united with the Son, who lives in him, is one [[Hypostasis (philosophy)|hypostasis]] and one nature: human.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Lembke, lecture in the course &quot;Meetings with the World's Religions&quot;, Centre for Theology and Religious Studies, Lund University, Spring Term 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Orthodoxy and Catholicism believe that the Church's leaders have on the whole navigated the centuries between opposing errors, on occasion providing subtle clarifications or restatements of earlier doctrines. Some Church fathers have suggested that the abundance and variety of early controversies were a blessing, in that they enabled the Church to deal with most or all of the major questions surrounding the Christian faith in a rather brief period. Protestants who ignore or attack the historic church's conclusions are at best bound to fight the same fights all over again, running the same risk of overcorrecting in response to current doctrinal disputes.

Compounding this risk of overcorrection is the growing propensity among Protestants to split into different denominations when serious disagreements arise. This risks having two groups, one or both of whom err in different directions, rather than a single group that adheres to the purported truth without deviating to any extremes. Some Protestant denominations avoid this more successfully than others. Of those that avoid further schism, many of these ignore doctrinal differences within their ranks and just play down the importance of the issue, which eventually leads to a greater variety of beliefs within the denomination. This variety, and toleration of greater and greater differences in belief, has resulted in further deviations from historic Christianity.

===Natural or Popular Religion===
{{See also|Natural religion}}
{{POV|date=January 2012}}
Many liturgical practices and beliefs are asserted to be adapted from pagan customs or human preferences, however in some cases they were carried over from Temple [[Judaism]], which practices most Christians believe were first given to Moses and the high priests by God. The idea of setting aside specific places as holy, treating certain items used in the worship of God with reverence, all go back to the Hebrew Temple worship, and to the visions the Bible records of what worship in Heaven looks like, not just to pagan ideas about &quot;mana.&quot; The [[Roman Catholic Mass]] or Orthodox [[Divine Liturgy]] in many respects more closely resembles the Temple sacrifice than anything modern Jews practice, since in Judaism there is no current [[Temple in Jerusalem]], just the [[Temple Mount]]. In other cases, local customs have been deliberately adapted and imbued with Christian meaning in an effort to keep the Church incarnate and accessible to local Christians. For example, in many Orthodox Churches in Europe, there has grown a custom of blessing pussiwillows on Palm Sunday instead of palm branches, since palms do not grow that far north. When worship involves the use of the entire body, and all the senses, the Orthodox believe this becomes very helpful in learning to actively love God with all their &quot;mind, soul, heart and strength&quot; as God commands. Restricting worship to a mental exercise removes the &quot;strength&quot; element of loving God, assert some sources. Prohibiting the use of material, created objects in giving worship to the Creator, is to condemn all the sacrifices offered by the holy men and women recorded in the Old Testament and elsewhere. It also appears to reflect the subset of Gnostic beliefs that all material things of this world are inherently [[evil]], or at best temporary, and that only invisible, spiritual thoughts and actions can draw us closer to God. The Church has always fought against this idea, beginning with its 1st and 2nd century controversies with the [[Gnostic]]s of that day, including the assertion that [[Jesus]] is identified as an embodiment of the supreme being who became incarnate to bring ''gnōsis'' to the earth, as held by some Gnostic sects.&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlintro&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = An Introduction to Gnosticism and The Nag Hammadi Library | publisher = The Gnostic Society Library | url = http://www.gnosis.org/gnintro.htm | accessdate = 2009-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead it affirms that all [[Creation myth|creation]] was made [[Goodness and value theory|good]], and while it has since become corrupt, it is being redeemed by continually offering it back to God. The epitome of this action occurs in the Eucharistic sacrifice, which represents the offering of ourselves, all that we have, and the entire world back to God.

==See also==
{{div col}}
*[[Antinomianism]]
*[[Caesaropapism]]
*[[Constantinian shift]]
*[[Criticism of the Roman Catholic Church]]
*[[Mormonism and Christianity]]
*[[Sacralism]]
*[[Sedevacantism]]
*[[Summary of Christian eschatological differences]]
*[[Total depravity]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*[[Johann Lorenz Von Mosheim]]; ''De rebus Christianorum ante Constantinum Magnum Commentarii'' (6 vols.); (1753)
**Johann Lorenz Von Mosheim; ''Ecclesiastical History from the Birth of Christ to the Beginning of the Eighteenth Century'' (4 vols.), translated by Archibald Maclaine; (1758)
**Johann Lorenz Von Mosheim; ''Ecclesiastical History'', translated by James Murdock; (1851)
*[[James E. Talmage]]; ''[[The Great Apostasy (book)|The Great Apostasy]]''; [[Deseret Book]]; ISBN 0-87579-843-8 (1909; Softcover, February 1994)
*[[Hugh Nibley]]; [[Todd M. Compton]] and [[Stephen D. Ricks]], editors; ''Mormonism and Early Christianity''; [[Deseret Book]]; ISBN 0-87579-127-1 (Hardcover, 1987)
*[[Hugh Nibley]]; [http://maxwellinstitute.byu.edu/publications/books/?bookid=54 ''The World and the Prophets''] Maxwell Institute, BYU
*[[James L. Barker]]; ''Apostasy from the Divine Church''; [[Bookcraft]]; ISBN 0-88494-544-8 (1952; Hardcover 1984)
*[[Barry R. Bickmore]]; ''Restoring the Ancient Church''; Cornerstone Publishing, FAIR; ISBN 1-893036-00-6 (Paperback, 1999); [http://www.fair-lds.org/Merchant2/merchant.mvc?Screen=PROD&amp;Product_Code=FAIR-BB-99&amp;Category_Code=FP Available directly from the publisher]
*[[Kent P. Jackson]]; ''From Apostasy to Restoration''; [[Deseret Book]]; ISBN 1-57345-218-1 (Hardcover 1996)
*Holy Bible, King James Version, Isaiah 2:2,3; 5:20,21,25-29; 24:1-5; 28:10,11; 29:4,10-14,18,22-24; 49:22-23; 52:11,12; 54:1-3; 55:5; 56:6-8; 60:1-3,16. Malachi 3:1; 4:5,6.
*The ''[[Geneva Bible]]'' (1599), annotations of &quot;Fr. Junius&quot; to the [[Book of Revelation]], repr. L. L. Brown Publishing, ISBN 0-9629888-0-4 (1990)
*The ''[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1571-39articles.html Thirty-Nine Articles]'' of the Episcopal Church in America.

[[Category:Anti-Catholicism]]
[[Category:Christianity-related controversies]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saint doctrines, beliefs, and practices]]
[[Category:Christian primitivism]]
[[Category:4th-century Christianity]]
[[Category:Christian eschatology]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Latter Day Saint terms]]

[[bi:Bigfala Apostasi]]
[[es:Gran Apostasía]]
[[eo:Granda Apostateco]]
[[fr:Grande apostasie]]
[[io:Granda Apostateso]]
[[nl:Grote Afval]]
[[pt:Grande Apostasia]]</text>
      <sha1>i569p285quedcm5weif4b2pzy3g2txa</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
