<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Haitian Vodou</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5542305</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522279295</id>
      <parentid>522278811</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T03:48:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kgrad</username>
        <id>10242667</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Morality */ punctuation</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40039">{{Redirect|Voodoo doll}}
{{Cleanup|date=January 2008}}
{{Original research|date=November 2009}}

[[File:Haitian vodou altar to Petwo, Rada, and Gede spirits; November 5, 2010..jpg|thumb|350px|Vodou altar during a celebration for [[Guédé|Papa Guédé]] in [[Boston]]. This altar has offerings to three nations (''nanchons'') of [[loa]]: at top right are offerings to [[Rada loa|Rada]] spirits; at top left are those for the [[Petwo]] family; and those at bottom are for [[Guédé]].]]
'''Vodou'''{{sfn|Cosentino|1995a|p=xiii-xiv}}{{sfn|Brown|1991|}}{{sfn|Fandrich|2007|p=775}} ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|v|oʊ|d|uː}}, {{IPA-fr|vodu|lang}}, also written as '''Voodoo''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|v|uː|d|uː}}); '''Vodun'''{{sfn|Courlander|1988|p=88}}{{sfn|Thompson|1983|p=163-191}}, or '''Vodoun'''{{sfn|Courlander|1988|p=88}}{{sfn|Cosentino|1995a|p=xiv}} ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|v|oʊ|d|uː|n}}), etc.) is a [[syncretic]]{{sfn|Stevens-Arroyo|2002|p=37-58}} [[religion]] practiced chiefly in [[Haiti]] and the [[Haitian diaspora]]. Practitioners are called &quot;vodouists&quot; ([[French language|French]]: ''vodouisants'' {{IPA-fr|voduisɑ̃|}}) or &quot;servants of the spirits&quot; ([[Haitian Creole language|Haitian Creole]]: ''sèvitè'').{{sfn|Cosentino|1995b|p=25}}

Vodouists believe in a distant and unknowable creator god, ''Bondyè''. As Bondyè does not intercede in human affairs, vodouists direct their worship toward spirits subservient to Bondyè, called [[loa]].{{sfn|Gordon|2000|p=48}} Every loa is responsible for a particular aspect of life, with the dynamic and changing personalities of each loa reflecting the many possibilities inherent to the aspects of life over which they preside.{{sfn|Brown|1991|p=6}} In order to navigate daily life, vodouists cultivate personal relationships with the loa through the presentation of offerings, the creation of personal altars and devotional objects, and participation in elaborate ceremonies of music, dance, and [[spirit possession]].{{sfn|Brown|1991|p=4-7}}

Vodou originated in the [[France|French]] [[slavery|slave]] colony of [[Saint-Domingue]] in the 18th century, when African religious practice was actively suppressed, and enslaved Africans were forced to convert to Christianity.{{sfn|Gordon|2000|p=10}}{{sfn|Desmangles|1990|p=475}} Religious practices of contemporary Vodou are descended from, and closely related to, [[West African Vodun]] as practiced by the [[Fon people|Fon]] and [[Ewe people|Ewe]]. Vodou also incorporates elements and symbolism from other African peoples including the [[Yoruba people|Yorùbá]] and [[Kongo people|Bakongo]]; as well as [[Taíno people|Taíno]] religious beliefs, and European spirituality including [[Roman Catholicism|Roman Catholic Christianity]], European [[mysticism]], [[Freemasonry]], and other influences.{{sfn|Cosentino|1995b|p=25-55}}

==Names and Etymology==
''Vodou'' is a [[Haitian Creole language|Haitian Creole]] word that formerly referred to only a small subset of Haitian rituals.{{sfn|Brown|1995|p=205}} It is descended from an [[Ayizo language|Ayizo]] word referring to &quot;mysterious forces or powers that govern the world and the lives of those who reside within it, but also a range of artistic forms that function in conjunction with these ''vodun'' energies.&quot;{{sfn|Blier|1995|p=61}} In Haiti, practitioners occasionally use “vodou” to refer to Haitian religion generically, but it is more common for practitioners to refer to themselves as those who “serve the spirits” (''sèvitè'') by participating in ritual ceremonies, usually called a &quot;service to the [[loa]]&quot; (''sèvis loa'') or an &quot;African service&quot; (''sèvis gineh'').{{sfn|Brown|1995|p=205}} These terms can also be used to refer to the religion as a whole.

Outside of Haiti, the term ''vodou'' refers to the entirety of traditional Haitian religious practice.{{sfn|Brown|1995|p=205}}  
Originally written as ''vodun'', it is first recorded in ''Doctrina Christiana'', a 1658 document written by the King of [[Allada]]'s ambassador to the court of [[Philip IV of Spain]].{{sfn|Blier|1995|p=61}} In the following centuries, ''vodou'' was eventually taken up by non-Haitians as a generic descriptive term for traditional Haitian religion.{{sfn|Brown|1995|p=205}} There are many used orthographies for this word. Today, the spelling ''vodou'' is the most commonly accepted orthography in English.{{sfn|Cosentino|1995a|p=xiv}} Other potential spellings include ''vodou'', ''vodoun'', ''vaudoux'', and ''voodoo'', with ''vau-'' or ''vou-'' prefix variants reflecting French orthography, and a final ''-n'' reflecting the nasal vowel in West African or older, non-urbanized, Haitian Creole pronunciations. 

The spelling ''voodoo'', once very common, is now generally avoided by Haitian practitioners and scholars when referring to the Haitian religion.{{sfn|Courlander|1988|p=88}}{{sfn|Lane|1949|p=1162}}{{sfn|Thompson|1983|p=163}}{{sfn|Cosentino|1988|p=77}} This is both to avoid confusion with [[Louisiana voodoo]],{{sfn|Fandrich|2007|p=780}} a related but distinct set of religious practices, as well as to separate Haitian vodou from the negative connotations and misconceptions the term “voodoo” has acquired in popular culture.{{sfn|Fandrich|2007|p=775}}{{sfn|Hurbon|1995|p=181-197}}

==Beliefs==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Succubus]] --&gt;
[[File:PortAuPrinceMarche.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Vodou paraphernalia, [[Port-au-Prince]], Haiti.]]

===Deities===
Vodouisants believe in a supreme being called ''loa''. This belief is held in several West African religions, such as that of the [[Yoruba religion|Yoruba]], [[Odinani]], and [[Vodun]]. When it came in contact with Roman Catholicism, the supreme being was associated with the [[Judeo-Christian]] [[God]], the ''loa'' becoming the [[saints]].

====Loa====
[[File:VoodooValris.jpg|right|thumb|250px|A large sequined Vodou &quot;drapo&quot; or flag by the artist George Valris, depicting the [[veve]], or symbol, of the loa [[Loko Atison]].]]
Because Bondyè (God) is unreachable, Vodouisants aim their prayers to lesser entities, the spirits known as [[loa]], or ''mistè''. The most notable loa include [[Papa Legba]] (guardian of the crossroads), [[Erzulie#Maîtresse Mambo Erzulie Fréda Dahomey|Erzulie Freda]] (the spirit of love), [[Simbi]] (the spirit of rain and magicians), [[Azaka Medeh|Kouzin Zaka]] (the spirit of agriculture), and [[Marassa Jumeaux|The Marasa]], divine twins considered to be the first children of Bondye.{{sfn|Gordon|2002|p=54}}

These loa can be divided into 21 nations, which include the Petro, Rada, Congo and Nago.{{sfn|Alvarado|2011}} The Petro and the Rada contrast most with one another, because the Petro are hot or aggressive and restless, whereas the Rada are cool or calm and peaceful.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}

The loa also fall into family groups who share a surname, such as [[Ogou]], [[Erzulie|Ezili]], [[Azaka]] or [[Ghede]]. For instance, &quot;Ezili&quot; is a family, [[Erzulie#Erzulie Dantor|Ezili Danto]] and [[Erzulie#Maîtresse Mambo Erzulie Fréda Dahomey|Ezili Freda]] are two individual spirits in that family. Each family is associated with a specific aspect, for instance the Ogou family are soldiers, the Ezili govern the feminine spheres of life, the Azaka govern agriculture, the Ghede govern the sphere of death and fertility. Each of the loa is associated with a particular Roman Catholic saint.

Those in the Haitian Vodou practices that serve the [[loa]] are the [[Bokor]]. The Bokor are the Vodou priest/priestesses who can be hired to perform various sorcery. The Bokor practice both light and dark forms of magic. The Dark magic that they practice revolves mainly around the creation of zombies through the use of a mixture of poisons. These poisons are derived mainly from puffer fish and other poisonous substances.&lt;ref&gt;Wade Davis, [[The Serpent and the Rainbow (book)|The Serpent and the Rainbow]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Morality===
{{Refimprove section|date=January 2010}}
{{See also|Haitian Vodou and sexual orientation}}
Vodou's moral code focuses on the vices of dishonor and greed. There is also a notion of relative propriety&amp;mdash;and what is appropriate to someone with [[Damballah|Dambala Wedo]]  as their head may be different from someone with [[Ogoun|Ogou Feray]] as their head. For example, one spirit is very cool and the other is very hot. Coolness overall is valued, and so is the ability and inclination to protect oneself and one's own if necessary. Love and support within the family of the Vodou society seem to be the most important considerations. Generosity in giving to the community and to the poor is also an important value. One's blessings come through the community, and one should be willing to give back. There are no &quot;solitaries&quot; in Voodou&amp;mdash;only people separated geographically from their elders and house. A person without a relationship of some kind with elders does not practice Vodou as it is understood in Haiti and among Haitians.

There is a diversity of practice in Vodou across the country of Haiti and the Haitian diaspora. For instance, in the north of Haiti, the ''lave tèt'' (&quot;head washing&quot;) or ''kanzwe'' may be the only initiation, as it is in the Dominican Republic and Cuba, whereas in Port-au-Prince and the south they practice the ''kanzo'' rites with three grades of initiation{{spaced ndash}}kanzo senp, si pwen, and asogwe{{spaced ndash}}and the latter is the most familiar mode of practice outside Haiti. Some lineages combine both, as [[Mambo (Vodou)|Mambo]] [[Katherine Dunham]] reports from her personal experience in her book ''Island Possessed''.

While the overall tendency in Vodou is conservative in accord with its African roots, there is no singular, definitive form, only what is right in a particular house or lineage. Small details of service and the spirits served vary from house to house, and information in books or on the internet therefore may seem contradictory. There is no central authority or  &quot;[[pope]]&quot; in Haitian Vodou, since &quot;every mambo and houngan is the head of their own house&quot;, as a popular saying in Haiti goes. Another consideration in terms of Haitian diversity are the many sects besides the Sèvi Gine in Haiti such as the Makaya, Rara, and other secret societies, each of which has its own distinct pantheon of spirits.

==Practices==

===Liturgy and practice===
[[File:JacmelVodou.jpg|right|thumb|300px|Vodou ceremony, [[Jacmel]], [[Haiti]].]]
A Haitian Vodou temple is called an [[Hounfour]].{{sfn|Kilson|1976|p=345}} After a day or two of preparation setting up altars at an Hounfour, ritually preparing and cooking fowl and other foods, etc., a Haitian Vodou service begins with a series of prayers and songs in French, then a litany in Kreyòl and African &quot;langaj&quot; that goes through all the European and African saints and loa honored by the house, and then a series of verses for all the main spirits of the house. This is called the &quot;Priyè Gine&quot; or the African Prayer. After more introductory songs, beginning with saluting Hounto, the spirit of the drums, the songs for all the individual spirits are sung, starting with the [[Legba]] family through all the Rada spirits, then there is a break and the Petwo part of the service begins, which ends with the songs for the [[Guédé|Gede]] family.

As the songs are sung, participants believe that spirits come to visit the ceremony, by taking [[Spirit possession#In Haitian Vodou and African traditions|possession]] of individuals and speaking and acting through them. When a ceremony is made, only the family of those possessed is benefited.  At this time it is believed that devious mambo or houngan can take away the luck of the worshippers through particular actions. For instance, if a priest asks for a drink of champagne, a wise participant refuses. Sometimes these ceremonies may include dispute among the singers as to how a hymn is to be sung. In Haiti, these Vodou ceremonies, depending on the Priest or Priestess, may be more organized.  But in the United States, many vodouists and clergy take it as a sort of non-serious party or &quot;folly&quot;.

In a serious rite, each spirit is saluted and greeted by the initiates present and gives readings, advice, and cures to those who ask for help. Many hours later, as morning dawns, the last song is sung, the guests leave, and the exhausted hounsis, houngans, and mambos can go to sleep.

On the individual's household level, a Vodouisant or &quot;sèvitè&quot;/&quot;serviteur&quot; may have one or more tables set out for their ancestors and the spirit or spirits that they serve with pictures or statues of the spirits, perfumes, foods, and other things favored by their spirits. The most basic set up is just a white candle and a clear glass of water and perhaps flowers. On a particular spirit's day, one lights a candle and says an [[Lord's Prayer|Our Father]] and [[Hail Mary]], salutes Papa Legba and asks him to open the gate, and then one salutes and speaks to the particular spirit as an elder family member. Ancestors are approached directly, without the mediating of Papa Legba, since they are said to be &quot;in the blood&quot;.

===Priests===
[[File:Antique ceremonial suit for Haitian Vodou Voudun rites.jpg|thumb|150 px|Ceremonial suit for Haitian Vodou rites, [[Ethnological Museum of Berlin]], Germany.]]
[[Houngan]]s (Male Voodoo Priest) or [[Mambo (Vodou)|Mambos]] (Female Vodou Priest) are usually people who were chosen by the dead ancestors and received the divination from the deities while he or she was possessed. His or her tendency is to do good by helping and protecting others from spells, however they sometimes use their supernatural power to hurt or kill people. They also conduct ceremonies that usually take place &quot;Amba Peristil&quot; (under a Vodou Temple). However, non-Houngan or non-Mambo as Vodouisants are not [[Initiation|initiated]], and are referred to as being &quot;bossale&quot;; it is not a requirement to be an initiate to serve one's spirits. There are clergy in Haitian Vodou whose responsibility it is to preserve the rituals and songs and maintain the relationship between the spirits and the community as a whole (though some of this is the responsibility of the whole community as well). They are entrusted with leading the service of all of the spirits of their lineage. Sometimes they are &quot;called&quot; to serve in a process called &quot;being reclaimed&quot;, which they may resist at first.{{sfn|McAlister|1993|p=10-27}} Below the houngans and mambos are the hounsis, who are initiates who act as assistants during ceremonies and who are dedicated to their own personal mysteries.

A &quot;bokor&quot; is a sorcerer or magician who casts spells upon request. They are not necessarily priests, and may be practitioners of &quot;darker&quot; things and often not even accepted by the mambo or the houngan.
Or, a &quot;Bokor&quot; would be the Haitian term for a vodou priest or other, working both the light and dark arts of magic.

==History==

===Before 1685: From Africa to the Caribbean===
[[File:Gbe languages.png|thumb|200px|Area of [[West African Vodun]] practice, the religion with the greatest influence on Haitian Vodou.]]

The cultural area of the [[Fon people|Fon]], [[Ewe people|Ewe]], and [[Yoruba people|Yoruba]] peoples share common [[Metaphysics|metaphysical]] conceptions around a dual [[Cosmology|cosmological]] divine principle [[Nana Buluku]], the [[God]]-Creator, and the voduns(s) or God-Actor(s), daughters and sons of the Creator's twin children [[Mawu]] (goddess of the moon) and [[Lisa (mythology)|Lisa]] (god of the sun). The God-Creator is the [[cosmogonical]] principle and does not trifle with the mundane; the voduns(s) are the God-Actor(s) who actually govern earthly issues. The [[Dahomey mythology|pantheon of vodoun]] is quite large and complex.

West African Vodun has its primary emphasis on ancestors, with each family of spirits having its own specialized priest and priestess, which are often hereditary. In many African clans, deities might include [[Mami Wata]], who are gods and goddesses of the waters; [[Legba]], who in some clans is virile and young in contrast to the old man form he takes in Haiti and in many parts of Togo; [[Ogoun|Gu]] (or Ogoun), ruling iron and smithcraft; [[Sakpata]], who rules diseases; and many other spirits distinct in their own way to West Africa. 

A significant portion of Haitian Vodou often overlooked by scholars until recently is the input from the [[Kingdom of Kongo|Kongo]]. The entire northern area of Haiti is heavily influenced by Kongo practices. In northern Haiti, it is often called the [[Kongo Rite]] or Lemba, from the Lemba rituals of the [[Kingdom of Loango|Loango]] area and [[Mayombe]]. In the south, Kongo influence is called [[Petwo]] (Petro). Many loa (a Kikongo term) are of Kongo origin, such as [[Basimbi]], Lemba, etc.

In addition, the Vodun religion (distinct from Haitian Vodou) already existed in the United States previously to Haitian immigration, having been brought by enslaved West Africans, specifically from the Ewe, Fon, Mina, Kabaye, and Nago groups. Some of the more enduring forms survive in the [[Gullah|Gullah Islands]]. 

European [[colonialism]], followed by totalitarian regimes in West Africa, suppressed Vodun as well as other forms of the religion. However, because the Vodun deities are born to each African clan-group, and its clergy is central to maintaining the moral, social, and political order and ancestral foundation of its villagers, it proved to be impossible to eradicate the religion.

===1685-1791: Vodou in Colonial Saint-Domingue===
The majority of the Africans who were brought as slaves to Haiti were from Western and Central Africa. The survival of the belief systems in the [[New World]] is remarkable, although the traditions have changed with time and have even taken on some Catholic forms of worship.{{sfn|Stevens-Arroyo|2002|}} Two important factors, however, characterize the uniqueness of Haitian Vodou as compared to African Vodun; the transplanted Africans of Haiti, similar to those of [[Cuba]] and Brazil, were obliged to disguise their [[loa]] or spirits as [[Roman Catholic]] [[saint]]s, an element of a process called [[syncretism]].

Two keys provisions of the [[Code Noir]] by King [[Louis XIV of France]] in 1685 severely limited the ability of enslaved Africans in Saint-Domingue to practice African religions. First, the Code Noir explicitly forbade the open practice of all African religions.{{sfn|Desmangles|1990|p=475}} Second, it forced all slaveholders to convert their slaves to Catholicism within eight days of their arrival in Saint-Domingue.{{sfn|Desmangles|1990|p=475}} As a result, over the course of the 18th century, African religious practice in Saint-Domingue adapted to each of these provisions. First, African religious practice largely went underground, outside of the control of colonial authorities. Second, the diverse pantheon of African spirits that had already been incorporated into religious practice in Saint-Domingue was overlayed with images, practices, and rituals borrowed from Catholicism.{{sfn|Desmangles|1990|p=475}} [[Médéric Louis Élie Moreau de Saint-Méry]], a French observer writing in 1797, noted this religious [[syncretism]], commenting that the Catholic-style altars and votive candles used by Africans in Haiti were meant to conceal the Africanness of the religion.{{sfn|Moreau de Saint-Méry|1797}}

Vodou, as it is known in Haiti and the Haitian [[diaspora]], is the result of the pressures of many different cultures and ethnicities of people who were uprooted from Africa and imported to Haiti in the African slave trade. Under slavery, African culture and religion was suppressed, lineages were fragmented, and people pooled their religious knowledge and from this fragmentation became culturally unified. In addition to combining the spirits of many different African and Amerindian nations, Vodou has incorporated pieces of Roman Catholic liturgy to replace lost prayers or elements. Images of Catholic saints are used to represent various spirits or &quot;mistè&quot; (&quot;mysteries&quot;, actually the preferred term in Haiti), and many saints themselves are honored in Vodou in their own right. This syncretism allows Vodou to encompass the African, the [[Native American (Americas)|Indian]], and the European ancestors in a whole and complete way. It is truly a ''[[Haitian Creole|Kreyòl]]'' religion

===1791-1804: The Haitian Revolution===
The most historically important Vodou ceremony in Haitian history was the Bwa Kayiman or [[Bois Caïman]] ceremony of August 1791 that began the [[Haitian Revolution]], in which the spirit [[Ezili Dantor]] possessed a priestess and received a [[Creole Pig|black pig]] as an offering, and all those present pledged themselves to the fight for freedom.{{sfn|Markel|2009|}} This ceremony ultimately resulted in the liberation of the Haitian people from French [[French colonial empires|colonial]] rule in 1804, and the establishment of the first black people's [[republic]] in the history of the world and the second independent nation in the Americas. Haitian nationalists have frequently drawn inspiration by imagining their ancestors' gathering of unity and courage. Since the 1990s, some neo-evangelicals have interpreted the politico-religious ceremony at Bois Caïman to have been a pact with demons. This extremist view is not considered credible by mainstream Protestants, however conservatives such as Pat Robertson repeat the idea.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=McAlister|first=Elizabeth|title=From Slave Revolt to a Blood Pact with Satan: The Evangelical Rewriting of Haitian History|journal=Studies in Religion/Sciences Religieuses|year=2012|month=June|volume=41|issue=2|pages=187-215|doi=10.1177/0008429812441310}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Vodou in 19th Century Haiti===
{{Expand section|date=March 2012}}

===20th Century to the Present===
Today, Vodou is practiced not only by Haitians but by Americans and people of many other nations who have been exposed to Haitian culture. [[Haiti]]an [[Creole peoples|creole]] forms of Vodou exist in Haiti, the [[Dominican Republic]], eastern Cuba,{{sfn|Stevens-Arroyo|2002|p=37-58}} some of the outer islands of the [[Bahamas]], the United States, and anywhere that Haitians have emigrated to. There has been a re-emergence of the Vodun traditions in the United States, maintaining the same ritual and cosmological elements as in West Africa. These and other African-diasporic religions, such as Lukumi or Regla de Ocha (also known as [[Santería]]) in Cuba, and [[Candomblé]] and [[Umbanda]] in Brazil, have evolved among descendants of transplanted Africans in the Americas.

Many Haitians involved in the practice of Vodou have been initiated as Houngans or Mambos. Some vodouists with a hunger to live a life of wealth and power became practitioners so they could exploit foreigners and Haitians who are uneducated about Vodou, bringing them into a web of deceptions to collect large incomes in exchange for poor quality work.

In January 2010, after the [[2010 Haiti earthquake|Haiti earthquake]] there was an outburst of solidarity prayers in Benin with the victims. Traditional ceremonies were organized to appease the spirits and seek the blessing of ancestors for the Haitians. Also a ''&quot;purification ceremony&quot;'' was planned for Haiti.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} In a 2010 news story, CNN reported, &quot;At least 45 people, most of them Vodou priests, have been [[lynching|lynch]]ed in Haiti since the beginning of the cholera epidemic by angry mobs blaming them for the spread of the disease, officials said.{{sfn|Valme|2010|}}

==Demographics and Geographic Distribution==
Because of the religious syncretism (that is, the purposeful combination of contradictory and unrelated beliefs) between Catholicism and Vodou, it is difficult to estimate the number of Vodouists in Haiti. The CIA currently estimates that approximately 50% of Haiti's population practices Vodou, with nearly all Vodouists participating in one of Haiti's Christian denominations.{{sfn|CIA World Factbook}}

==Gallery of Haitian Vodou objects==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Antique ceremonial suit for Haitian Vodou.jpg|Ceremonial suit
File:Haitian Vodou fetish statue devil with twelve eyes.jpg|Statue of a [[djab]], a quick-working wild spirit.
File:Antique Haitian Vodou ceremonial drum.jpg|Ceremonial drum
File:Trop Pou Te Haitian Vodou banners.jpg|Banner reading &quot;Trop Pou Te&quot; in the [[Haitian Creole language]]
File:Vodou mirror museum exhibit.jpg|Mirrors represent doorways to the world of the dead.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Myths and misconceptions==
{{editorial|date=January 2012}}
Vodou is often associated with the lore of [[Satanism]], [[zombie]]s and &quot;voodoo dolls&quot;. Zombie creation has been referenced within rural Haitian culture,{{sfn|Davis|1988|}} but is not a part of the Vodou religion. Such manifestations fall under the auspices of the ''[[bokor]]'' or sorcerer rather than the priest of the Loa.

The practice of sticking pins in voodoo dolls has history in folk magic. &quot;Voodoo dolls&quot; are often associated with [[Louisiana Voodoo|New Orleans Voodoo]] and [[Hoodoo (folk magic)]] as well the magical devices of the [[poppet]] and the ''[[nkisi]]'' or ''bocio'' of West and Central Africa.

The dark side of Vodou is often a dramatic device of modern horror and action-adventure movies such as ''[[The Serpent and the Rainbow (film)|The Serpent and the Rainbow]]'' and ''[[Live and Let Die (film)|Live and Let Die]]'' (part of the [[Ian Fleming]] [[James Bond]] series). 

In April 1997, thirteen scholars gathered at the University of California Santa Barbara for a colloquium on Haitian Vodou.  From that meeting the ''Congress of Santa Barbara'' was created, also known as [[KOSANBA]].{{sfn|KOSANBA|}}

==Organizations==
In the aftermath of the Duvalier dictatorship, a number of individuals, including many houngan, sought to organize means of defense for Haitian Vodou from defamation by evangelical Christian missionaries and congregations. One of the first leading houngan to formally organize other houngan in solidarity was [[Wesner Morency]] (1959–2007), who established the Vodou Church of Haiti in 1998 (registered in 2001 by the Ministry of Justice) and the Commission Nationale pour la Structuration de Vodou (CONAVO). Another individual who has pursued the organization of houngan is [[Max Beauvoir]], who established and heads the [[National Confederation of Haitian Vodou]].

However, the ability to organize and speak on behalf of most, if not all Vodouisants is hampered by the spirituality's historically decentralized nature.

==See also==
{{Commons category|Voodoo}}
*[[Afro-American religion]]
*[[Baron Samedi]]
*[[Gullah]]
*[[Haitian mythology]]
*[[Haitian Vodou and sexual orientation]]
*[[Hoodoo (folk magic)|Hoodoo]]
*[[KOSANBA]]
*[[Kumina]]
*[[Louisiana Voodoo]]
*[[Obeah]]
*[[Santería]]
*[[Candomblé]]
*[[Winti]]
*[[West African Vodun]]
*[[Juju]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|15em}}

==References==
{{refbegin|30em}}

* {{cite book
  | last1 = Alvarado
  | first1 = Denise
  | year = 2011
  | title = The Voodoo Hoodoo Spellbook
  | publisher = Weiser Books
  | location = 
  | isbn = 1-57863-513-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Blier
  | first = Suzanne Preston 
  | editor-first = Cosentino 
  | editor-last = Donald J.
  | title = Sacred Arts of Haitian Vodou 
  | publisher = Los Angeles: UCLA Fowler Museum of Cultural History
  | year = 1995 
  | pages = 61–87
  | chapter = Vodun: West African Roots of Vodou
  | isbn = 0-930741-47-1
  | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Brown
  | first1 = Karen McCarthy
  | year = 1991
  | title = Mama Lola: A Vodou Priestess in Brooklyn
  | publisher = University of California Press
  | location = Berkeley
  | isbn = 0-520-22475-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Brown 
  | first = Karen McCarthy 
  | editor-first = Cosentino 
  | editor-last = Donald J.
  | title = Sacred Arts of Haitian Vodou 
  | publisher = Los Angeles: UCLA Fowler Museum of Cultural History
  | year = 1995 
  | pages = 205–223
  | chapter = Serving the Spirits: The Ritual Economy of Haitian Vodou
  | isbn = 0-930741-47-1
  | ref = harv
}}
*{{cite web
  |url = https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ha.html
  |title = Haiti 
  |last1 = CIA World Factbook
  |first1 = 
  |date =
  |work = 
  |publisher = Central Intelligence Agency
  |accessdate = 28 March 2012
  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Cosentino 
  | first = Donald J. 
  | title = More On Voodoo 
  | journal = African Arts  
  | volume = 21  
  | issue = 3 (May)  
  | pages = 77  
  | year = 1988  
  | jstor = 3336454  
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Cosentino 
  | first = Donald J. 
  | editor-first = Cosentino 
  | editor-last = Donald J.
  | title = Sacred Arts of Haitian Vodou 
  | publisher = Los Angeles: UCLA Fowler Museum of Cultural History
  | date = 1995b 
  | pages = 25–55
  | chapter = Introduction: Imagine Heaven
  | isbn = 0-930741-47-1
  | ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
  | last = Cosentino 
  | first = Henrietta B. 
  | editor-first = Cosentino 
  | editor-last = Donald J.
  | title = Sacred Arts of Haitian Vodou 
  | publisher = Los Angeles: UCLA Fowler Museum of Cultural History
  | date = 1995a 
  | pages = xiii-xiv 
  | chapter = The Sacred Arts of What? A Note on Orthography
  | isbn = 0-930741-47-1
  | ref = harv
}}
*{{cite journal
  | last1 = Courlander  
  | first1 = Harold  
  | title = The Word Voodoo 
  | journal = African Arts  
  | volume = 21  
  | issue = 2 (February)  
  | pages = 88  
  | year = 1988  
  | jstor = 3336535  
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last1 = Davis 
  | first1 = Wade
  | year = 1985
  | title = [[The Serpent and the Rainbow (book)|The Serpent and the Rainbow]]
  | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster Inc.
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 0-671-50247-6
  | ref = harv
  }}

*{{cite book
  | last1 = Davis 
  | first1 = Wade
  | year = 1988
  | title = Passage of Darkness:  The Ethnobiology of the Haitian Zombie
  | publisher = The University of North Carolina Press
  | location = Chapel Hill
  | isbn = 0-8078-4210-9
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last = Desmangles
  | first = Leslie G. 
  | title = The Maroon Republics and Religious Diversity in Colonial Haiti
  | journal = Anthropos  
  | volume = 85  
  | issue = 4/6  
  | pages = 475–482 
  | year = 1990  
  | jstor = 40463572  
  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last1 = Fandrich
  | first1 = Ina J.  
  | title = Yorùbá Influences on Haitian Vodou and New Orleans Voodoo
  | journal = Journal of Black Studies
  | volume = 37
  | issue = 5 (May)  
  | pages = 775–791  
  | year = 2007  
  | jstor = 40034365
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last1 = Lane 
  | first1 = Maria J. (ed.) 
  | year = 1949
  | title = Funk &amp; Wagnalls Standard Dictionary of Folklore, Mythology, and Legend 
  | location = 
  | isbn =  
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Gordon
  | first1 = Leah
  | year = 2000
  | title = The Book of Vodou
  | publisher = Barron's Educational Series
  | location = 
  | isbn = 0-7641-5249-1
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Hurbon
  | first = Laënnec 
  | editor-first = Cosentino 
  | editor-last = Donald J.
  | title = Sacred Arts of Haitian Vodou 
  | publisher = Los Angeles: UCLA Fowler Museum of Cultural History
  | year = 1995 
  | pages = 181–197
  | chapter = American Fantasy and Haitian Vodou
  | isbn = 0-930741-47-1
  | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Kilson
  | first1 = Martin (ed.)
  | last2 = Rotberg
  | first2 = Robert I. (ed.)
  | year = 1976
  | title = The African Diaspora: Interpretive Essays
  | publisher = Harvard University Press
  | location = Cambridge, MA
  | isbn = 0-674-00779-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite web
  |url = http://research.ucsb.edu/cbs/projects/haiti/kosanba/index.html 
  |title = KOSANBA: A Scholarly Association for the Study of Haitian Vodou 
  |last1 = KOSANBA
  |first1 = 
  |date =
  |work = 
  |publisher = University of California, Santa Barbara
  |accessdate = 22 March 2012
  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last1 = Markel
  | first1 = Thylefors  
  | title = 'Our Government is in Bwa Kayiman:' a Vodou Ceremony in 1791 and its Contemporary Signifcations
  | journal = Stockholm Review of Latin American Studies  
  | volume =   
  | issue = 4 (March)  
  | pages = 73–84  
  | year = 2009  
  | url = http://www.lai.su.se/gallery/bilagor/SRoLAS_No4_6.%20%E2%80%9DOur%20Government%20is%20in.pdf  
  | format = PDF  
  | accessdate = 2009-04-26
  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last1 = McAlister
  | first1 = Elizabeth  
  | title = Sacred Stories from the Haitian Diaspora:  A Collective Biography of Seven Vodou Priestesses in New York City
  | journal = Journal of Caribbean Studies  
  | volume = 9  
  | issue = 1 &amp; 2 (Winter)  
  | pages = 10–27  
  | year = 1993  
  | url = http://wesscholar.wesleyan.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1012&amp;context=div2facpubs 
  | accessdate = 2012-03-22
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Moreau de Saint-Méry
  | first1 = Médéric Louis Élie
  | year = 1797
  | title = Description topographique, physique, civile, politique et historique de la partie française de l'isle Saint-Domingue
  | publisher = Société des l'histoire des colonies françaises
  | location = Paris
  | isbn = 
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite journal
  | last1 = Stevens-Arroyo  
  | first1 = Anthony M.  
  | title = The Contribution of Catholic Orthodoxy to Caribbean Syncretism  
  | journal = Archives de Sciences Sociales des Religions  
  | volume = 19  
  | issue = 117 (January–March)  
  | pages = 37–58  | year = 2002  
  | url = http://assr.revues.org/index2477.html?file=1  
  | format = PDF  
  | accessdate = 2009-04-26
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last1 = Thompson
  | first1 = Robert Farris
  | year = 1983
  | title = Flash of the Spirit: African &amp; Afro-American Art &amp; Philosophy
  | publisher = Vintage
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 0-394-72369-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite web
  |url = http://www.cnn.com/2010/WORLD/americas/12/24/haiti.cholera.killings/index.html?hpt=Sbin%20Officials:%2045%20people%20lynched%20in%20Haiti%20amid%20cholera%20fears
  |title = Officials: 45 people lynched in Haiti amid cholera fears
  |last1 = Valme
  |first1 = Jean M.
  |date = 24 December 2010
  |work = 
  |publisher = CNN 
  |accessdate = 22 March 2012
  }}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin|30em}}
*Ajayi, Ade, J.F. &amp; Espie, Ian, A Thousand Years of West African History, Great Britain, University of Ibadan, 1967.
*Alapini Julien, Le Petit Dahomeen, Grammaire. Vocabulaire, Lexique En Langue Du Dahomey, Avignon, Les Presses Universelles, 1955.
*Anderson, Jeffrey. 2005. ''Conjure In African American Society''. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press.
*''Angels in the Mirror:  Vodou Musics of Haiti.''  Roslyn, New York:  Ellipsis Arts.  1997. Compact Disc and small book.
*Argyle, W.J., The Fon of Dahomey: A History and Ethnography of the Old Kingdom, Oxford, Oxford University Press, 1966.
*Bellegarde-Smith and Claudine, Michel. ''Haitian Vodou: Spirit, Myth &amp; Reality.'' Indiana University Press, 2006.
*Broussalis, Martín and Joseph Senatus Ti Wouj:&quot;Voodoo percussion&quot;, 2007. A CD with text containing the ritual drumming.
*Chesi, Gert, Voodoo: Africa's Secret Power, Austria, Perliner, 1980.
*Chireau, Yvonne. 2003. ''Black Magic: Religion and the African American Conjuring Tradition''. Berkeley: University of California Press.
*Cosentino, Donald. 1995. &quot;Imagine Heaven&quot; in ''Sacred Arts of Haitian Vodou''. Edited by Cosentino, Donald et al. Berkeley: University of California Press.
*Decalo, Samuel, Historical Dictionary of Dahomey, (People's Republic of Benin), N.J., The Scarecrow Press, Inc., 1976.
*Ellis, A.B., The Ewe Speaking Peoples of the Slave Coast of West Africa, Chicago, Benin Press Ldt, 1965.
*Fandrich, Ina J. 2005. ''The Mysterious Voodoo Queen, Marie Laveaux: A Study of Powerful Female Leadership in Nineteenth-Century New Orleans''. New York: Routledge.
*Filan, Kinaz. ''The Haitian Vodou Handbook''. Destiny Books (of Inner Traditions International), 2007.
*Herskovits, Melville J. (1971). Life in a Haitian Valley: Garden CITY, NEW YORK: DOUBLEDAY &amp; COMPANY, INC.
*Le Herisee, A. &amp; Rivet, P., The Royanume d'Ardra et son evangelisation au XVIIIe siecle, Travaux et Memories de &quot;'Institut d'Enthnologie, no. 7, Paris, 1929.
*Long, Carolyn. 2001. ''Spiritual Merchants: Magic, Religion and Commerce''. Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press.
*McAlister, Elizabeth.  2002.  ''Rara!  Vodou, Power, and Performance in Haiti and its Diaspora''.  Berkeley:  University of California Press.
*McAlister, Elizabeth.  1995.  &quot;[http://wesscholar.wesleyan.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1016&amp;context=div2facpubs|A Sorcerer's Bottle: The Visual Art of Magic in Haiti.]&quot;  In Donald J. Cosentino, ed., ''Sacred Arts of Haitian Vodou''.  UCLA Fowler Museum, 1995.
*McAlister, Elizabeth. 2000  &quot;[http://wesscholar.wesleyan.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1013&amp;context=div2facpubs|Love, Sex, and Gender Embodied:  The Spirits of Haitian Vodou.]&quot;  In J. Runzo and N. Martin, eds, Love, Sex, and Gender in the World Religions.  Oxford:  Oneworld Press.
*Malefijt, Annemarie de Waal (1989). Religion and Culture: An introduction to Anthropology of Religion. Long Groove, Illinois: Waveland Press, Inc.
*McAlister, Elizabeth.  1998.  &quot;[http://wesscholar.wesleyan.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1015&amp;context=div2facpubs|The Madonna of 115th St. Revisited:  Vodou and Haitian Catholicism in the Age of Transnationalism.]&quot;  In S. Warner, ed., Gatherings in Diaspora.  Philadelphia:  Temple Univ. Press.
*Rhythms of Rapture:  Sacred Musics of Haitian Vodou.  Smithsonian Folkways, 1005.  Compact Disc and Liner Notes
*Saint-Lot, Marie-José Alcide. 2003. ''Vodou: A Sacred Theatre''. Coconut Grove: Educa Vision, Inc.
*Tallant, Robert. &quot;Reference materials on voodoo, folklore, spirituals, etc. 6-1 to 6-5 -Published references on folklore and spiritualism.&quot; ''The Robert Tallant Papers''. New Orleans Public Library.  fiche 7 and 8, grids 1-22. Accessed 5 May 2005.
*Thornton, John K. 1988. &quot;On the trail of Voodoo: African Christianity in Africa and the Americas&quot; ''The Americas'' Vol: 44.3 Pp 261–278.
*Vanhee, Hein. 2002. &quot;Central African Popular Christianity and the Making of Haitian Vodou Religion.&quot; in ''Central Africans and Cultural Transformations in the American Diaspora'' Edited by: L. M. Heywood. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 243-64.
*Verger, Pierre Fátúmbí, Dieux d'Afrique: Culte des Orishas et Vodouns à l'ancienne Côte des Esclaves en Afrique et à Bahia, la Baie de Tous Les Saints au Brésil. 1954.
*Ward, Martha. 2004. ''Voodoo Queen: The Spirited Lives of Marie Laveau'' Jackson: University of Mississippi Press.
*Warren, Dennis, D., The Akan of Ghana, Accra, Pointer Limited, 1973. 9.
&lt;/div&gt;
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.havanatimes.org/?p=9966 Haiti in Cuba: Vodou, Racism &amp; Domination] by Dimitri Prieto, ''Havana Times'', June 8, 2009.
* [http://rara.wesleyan.edu Rara: Vodou, Power and Performance in Haiti and Its Diaspora].
* [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=122770590&amp;ps=cprs Voodoo Brings Solace To Grieving Haitians] - ''[[All Things Considered]]'' from [[NPR]]. Audio and transcript. January 20, 2010.
* [http://speakingoffaith.publicradio.org/programs/2010/vodou Living Vodou]. ''[[Speaking of Faith]]'' from [[American Public Media]]. Audio and [http://speakingoffaith.publicradio.org/programs/2010/vodou/transcript.shtml transcript]. February 4, 2010
* [http://www.thefirstpost.co.uk/60418,in-pictures,news-in-pictures,in-pictures-haiti-voodoo-christian-attack-earthquake-aid-earthquake Voodoo Alive and Well in Haiti] — slideshow by ''[[The First Post]]''
* [http://www.life.com/gallery/62471/inside-haitian-vodou#index/0 Inside Haitian Vodou] — slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''

{{Afro-American Religions}}
{{Religion topics}}

[[Category:Afro-American religion]]
[[Category:Vodou]]
[[Category:Christian interfaith and secular relations]]

[[hu:Vudu]]
[[nl:Vodou]]
[[pt:Vodu haitiano]]</text>
      <sha1>lu5c7bd1m6z8txsnhf47v7rfcuwhg2s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
