<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Harrowing of Hell</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>249524</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521796660</id>
      <parentid>517546604</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T08:37:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove unicode control characters (CHECKWIKI error 16) +general fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8535)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31200">[[Image:Harrowhell.jpg|frame|right|The Harrowing of Hell, depicted in the ''[[Petites Heures of Jean de France, Duc de Berry|Petites Heures de Jean de Berry]]'', 14th c. [[illuminated manuscript]] commissioned by [[John, Duke of Berry]].]]
The '''Harrowing of Hell''' ([[Latin language|Latin]] ''Descensus Christi ad Inferos'' &quot;the descent of Christ into hell&quot;) is a doctrine in [[Christian theology]] referenced in the [[Apostles' Creed]] and the [[Athanasian Creed|Athanasian Creed (Quicumque vult)]] that states that [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]] &quot;descended into [[Hell]]&quot;.

The lack of explicit scriptural references to Christ's [[descent to the underworld]] has given rise to controversy and differing interpretations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://64.33.81.65/ancient/descendit.htm D. Bruce Lockerbie, ''The Apostle's Creed: Do You Really Believe It'' ( Victor Books, Wheaton, IL) 1977:53-54, on-line text].&lt;/ref&gt; As an image in [[Christian art]], the harrowing is also known as the Anastasis (a Greek word for &quot;resurrection&quot;), considered a creation of [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine culture]] and first appearing in the [[Latin West|West]] in the early 8th century.&lt;ref&gt;Leslie Ross, entry on &quot;Anastasis&quot;, ''Medieval Art: A Topical Dictionary'' (Greenwood, 1996), pp. 10–11 [http://books.google.com/books?id=b-5YPoia7qwC&amp;pg=PA10&amp;dq=%22ANASTASIS.+Anastasis%22+intitle:Medieval+intitle:art&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=9Vw8TZ65DYHogQe836jwCA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22ANASTASIS.%20Anastasis%22%20intitle%3AMedieval%20intitle%3Aart&amp;f=false online].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Terminology ==
The [[Greek language|Greek]] wording in the ''Apostles' Creed'' is {{lang|grc|κατελθόντα εἰς τὰ κατώτατα}}, (&quot;katelthonta eis ta katôtata&quot;), and in [[Latin]] ''descendit ad inferos''. The Greek {{lang|grc|τὰ κατώτατα}} (&quot;the lowest&quot;) and the Latin ''inferos'' (&quot;those below&quot;) may also be translated as &quot;[[underworld]]&quot;, &quot;netherworld&quot;, or as &quot;abode of the dead.&quot; Modern versions of the Apostles' Creed often translate this more literally as &quot;he descended to the dead&quot;.

The word &quot;harrow&quot; comes from the [[Old English]] ''hergian'' meaning to harry or despoil and is seen in the homilies of [[Ælfric of Eynsham|Aelfric]], ''ca.'' 1000.&lt;ref&gt;''Harrow'' is a by-form of ''harry'', a military term meaning to &quot;make predatory raids or incursions&quot;[[OED]]&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''Harrowing of Hell'' refers not merely to the idea that Christ descended into Hell, as in the Creed, but to the rich tradition that developed later, asserting that he triumphed over ''inferos'', releasing Hell's captives, particularly [[Adam and Eve]], and the righteous men and women of [[Old Testament]] times.

== Sources ==

=== Scripture ===
[[Image:MantegnaDescentLimbo.gif|thumb|right|''Christ's Descent into [[Limbo]]'' by [[Andrea Mantegna]] and studio, c. 1470.]]

Several passages from the [[New Testament]] have been taken to imply that Christ descended into hell or the realm of the dead before the [[Ascension of Jesus|Ascension]].&lt;ref&gt;Ross, entry on &quot;Anastasis&quot;, ''Medieval Art'', p. 10. Ross cites Matthew 12:40 and Acts 2:24, 27, 31.&lt;/ref&gt; These include:

* {{bibleref2|Matthew|12:40}} draws a comparison between Jonah being swallowed by a huge fish, and Christ being three days in the earth.

* {{bibleref2|Acts|2:27}} and {{bibleref2|Acts|2:31}} declare in effect that [[Hades]] could not hold the crucified Christ.

* Two passages of [[First Epistle of Peter|1 Peter]] principally have been used as a basis for the ancient doctrine.

:* {{bibleref2|1Peter|3:19–20}} says that Jesus &quot;went and made a proclamation to the spirits in prison, who in former times did not obey, when God waited patiently in the days of Noah….&quot;&lt;ref&gt;New Revised Standard Version. In the original Greek: &quot;{{lang|grc|ἐν ᾧ καὶ τοῖς ἐν φυλακῇ πνεύμασιν πορευθεὶς ἐκήρυξεν, ἀπειθήσασίν ποτε ὅτε ἀπεξεδέχετο ἡ τοῦ θεοῦ μακροθυμία ἐν ἡμέραις Νῶε…}}.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

:* {{bibleref2|1Peter|4:6}} says that the gospel was &quot;proclaimed even to the dead…&quot; ([[NRSV]]). (&quot;{{lang|grc|εἰς τοῦτο γὰρ καὶ νεκροῖς εὐηγγελίσθη…}}&quot;)

* {{bibleref2|Ephesians|4:8–10}} has also been understood by others {{Who|date=March 2009}}to suggest a Harrowing of Hell doctrine: &quot;When he ascended on high, he led captives in his train and gave gifts to men.&quot;

: {{lang|grc|διὸ λέγει, ἀναβὰς εἰς ὕψος ᾐχμαλώτευσεν αἰχμαλωσίαν, ἔδωκεν δόματα τοῖς ἀνθρώποις. τὸ δὲ ἀνέβη τί ἐστιν εἰ μὴ ὅτι καὶ κατέβη εἰς τὰ κατώτερα [μέρη] τῆς γῆς; ὁ καταβὰς αὐτός ἐστιν καὶ ὁ ἀναβὰς ὑπεράνω πάντων τῶν οὐρανῶν, ἵνα πληρώσῃ τὰ πάντα.}}

: This is a truncated paraphrase adapting {{bibleref2|Psalm|68:18}}, with a changed point of view: &quot;When you ascended on high, you led captives in your train; you received gifts from men, even from the rebellious—that you, O {{LORD}} God, might dwell there.&quot; (NIV) The parenthetical verses 9–10 of Ephesians are widely read as an [[exegesis|exegetical gloss]] on the text. The word for &quot;lower parts&quot; (the comparative form: {{lang|grc|τὰ κατώτερα}}) is similar to the word used for &quot;Hell&quot; in the Greek version of the [[Apostles Creed]] (the superlative form: {{lang|grc|τὰ κατώτατα}}, English: &quot;lowest [places]&quot;). [[Frank Stagg (theologian)|Frank Stagg]] identifies three views of this passage from Ephesians:&lt;ref&gt;Stagg, Frank. ''New Testament Theology.'' Nashville: Broadman, p. 311.&lt;/ref&gt;
:* Jesus' burial, or
:* His descent into the underworld or Hell, or
:* His [[Incarnation]] as an act of deep humility. (see [[Philippians]] 2)
* {{bibleref2|Zechariah|9:11}} refers to prisoners in a waterless pit. &quot;As for thee also, by the blood of thy covenant I have sent forth thy prisoners out of the pit wherein is no water.&quot; The verses' reference to captives has been presented as a reflection of Yahweh's captives of the enemy in [[Book of Psalms|Psalm 68:17–18]]: &quot;God's chariots were myriad, thousands upon thousands; from Sinai the Lord entered the holy place. You went up to its lofty height; you took captives, received slaves as tribute. No rebels can live in the presence of God.&quot;
* {{bibleref2|Isaiah|24:21-22}} also refers to spirits in prison, reminiscent of Peter's account of a visitation to spirits in prison: &quot;And it shall come to pass in that day, that the {{LORD}} shall punish the host of the high ones that are on high, and the kings of the earth upon the earth. And they shall be gathered together, as prisoners are gathered in the pit, and shall be shut up in the prison, and after many days shall they be visited.&quot;

[[Image:Harrowing of Hell.jpg|thumb|left|A medieval ''Harrowing of Hell'', with [[Hellmouth]], engraving by [[Michael Burghers]] (1647/8–1727)]]&lt;!--this placement keeps sect. heading with text--&gt;

=== Early Christian teaching ===
The Harrowing of Hell was taught by [[theology|theologians]] of the [[early church]]: St [[Melito of Sardis]] (died ''c'' 180) ''Homily on the Passion''; [[Tertullian]] (''A Treatise on the Soul'', 55), [[Hippolytus (writer)|Hippolytus]] (''Treatise on Christ and Anti-Christ'') [[Origen]] (''[[Against Celsus]]'', 2:43), and, later, St [[Ambrose]] (died 397) all wrote of the Harrowing of Hell.

The Gospel of Matthew relates that immediately after Christ died, the earth shook, there was a [[Crucifixion darkness and eclipse]], the veil in the Temple was torn in two, and many people rose from the dead and walked about in Jerusalem and were seen by many people there. According to the apocryphal [[Acts of Pilate|Gospel of Nicodemus]], the Harrowing of Hell was foreshadowed by Christ's raising of [[Lazarus of Bethany|Lazarus]] from the dead prior to his own crucifixion. The hymns proper to the weekend suggest that John the Baptist prepared the way for Jesus in Hell by prophesying to those held there that Christ would soon release them, just as he prepared the way for Jesus on Earth.
[[File:Christ's Descent into Limbo by Dürer .png|thumb|upright|''Christ's Descent into Limbo'', woodcut by [[Albrecht Dürer]], ''c''1510]]
[[Image:5part-icon-Hell.jpg|thumb|right|[[Russian icon]] of Christ leading the righteous out of [[Hades]] (17th century, [[Solovetsky Monastery]]).]]

In the ''[[Acts of Pilate]]''—usually incorporated with the widely-read medieval ''Gospel of Nicodemus''—texts built around an original that might have been as old as the 3rd century A.D. with many improvements and embroidered interpolations, chapters 17 to 27 are called the ''Decensus Christi ad Inferos.'' They contain a dramatic dialogue between Hades and prince [[Satan]], and the entry of the King of Glory, imagined as from within Tartarus (see link below). &lt;!-- nothing about &quot;Lazarus is said to have prophesied to those in Hell both about his own imminent resurrection and Christ's coming resurrection and victory&quot; however --&gt; The richest, most circumstantial accounts of the Harrowing of Hell are found in medieval dramatic literature, such as the four great cycles of English [[mystery play]]s which each devote a separate scene to depict it, or in passing references in [[Dante]]'s ''[[Divine Comedy|Inferno]]''. The subject is found also in the Cornish mystery plays and the York and Wakefield cycles. These medieval versions of the story do not derive from the bare suggestion made in the Epistle ascribed to Peter, but come from the ''Gospel of Nicodemus.''{{Citation needed|date=April 2007}}
See &quot;The Apocryphal New Testament&quot; edited by Prof JK Elliott 1993 ISBN 0-19-826182-9 pp164

== Conceptions of the afterlife ==
{{main|Afterlife}}
The [[Old Testament]] view of the afterlife was that all people, whether righteous or unrighteous,  went to [[Sheol]] when they died. No Hebrew figure ever descended into Sheol and returned, although an apparition of the recently deceased Samuel briefly appeared to Saul when summoned by the [[Witch of Endor]]. [[Sheol#Sheol_in_the_intertestamental_literature|Several works]] from the [[Second Temple Judaism|Second Temple period]] elaborate the concept of Sheol, dividing it into sections based on the righteousness or unrighteousness of those who have died.

The New Testament maintains a distinction between Sheol, the common &quot;place of the dead&quot;, and the eternal destiny of those condemned at the [[Final Judgment]], variously described as [[Gehenna]], [[Outer Darkness|&quot;the outer darkness,&quot;]] or a [[Lake of fire|lake of eternal fire]]. Modern English translations of the Bible maintain this distinction (e.g. by translating ''Sheol'' as &quot;the Pit&quot; and ''Gehenna'' as &quot;[[Hell]]&quot;), but the influential King James Version used the word &quot;hell&quot; to translate both concepts.

The [[Hellenistic]] views of heroic descent into the Underworld and successful return follow traditions that are far older than the [[Greco-Roman mysteries|mystery religions]] popular at the time of Christ. The [[Epic of Gilgamesh]] includes such a scene, and it appears also in ''[[Odyssey]]'' XI. Writing shortly before the birth of Jesus, [[Vergil]] included it in the ''[[Aeneid]]''. What little we know of the [[worship]] in mystery religions such as the [[Eleusinian Mysteries]] and [[Mithraism]] suggests that a ritual death and rebirth of the initiate was an important part of their [[liturgy]]. Again, this has earlier parallels, in particular with the worship of [[Osiris]]. The ancient homily on ''The Lord's Descent into Hell'' may mirror these traditions by referring to [[baptism]] as a symbolic death and rebirth. (''cf.'' {{bibleref2|Colossians|2:9–15}}) Or, these traditions of [[Mithraism]] may be drawn from early Christian homilies.

== Interpretations of the doctrine ==

=== Roman Catholic ===
[[Image:HarrowingBermejo.jpg|thumb|left|220px|''Christ leads the patriarchs from Hell to Paradise'', by Bartolomeo Bertejo, Spanish, ca 1480: [[Methuselah]], [[Solomon]] and the [[Queen of Sheba]], and [[Adam (Bible)|Adam]] and [[Eve]] lead the procession of the righteous behind Christ.]]

There is an ancient [[homily]] on the subject, of unknown authorship, usually entitled ''The Lord's Descent into Hell'' that is the second reading at Office of Readings on [[Holy Saturday]] in the [[Roman Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/spirit/documents/spirit_20010414_omelia-sabato-santo_en.html The Lord's descent into hell]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Catechism of the Catholic Church]] states: &quot;By the expression 'He descended into Hell', the Apostles' Creed confesses that Jesus did really die and through his death for us conquered death and the devil 'who has the power of death' ({{bibleref2|Hebrews|2:14}}). In his human soul united to his divine person, the dead Christ went down to the realm of the dead. He opened Heaven's gates for the just who had gone before him.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p122a5p1.htm Catechism of the Catholic Church]'', p. 636–7.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the Catechism says, the word &quot;Hell&quot;—from the Norse, ''Hel''; in Latin, ''infernus, infernum, inferi''; in Greek, {{lang|grc|ᾍδης}} ([[Hades]]); in Hebrew, ''שאול'' (Sheol)—is used in Scripture and the Apostles' Creed to refer to the abode of all the dead, whether righteous or evil, unless or until they are admitted to Heaven (CCC 633). This abode of the dead is the &quot;Hell&quot; into which the Creed says Christ descended. His death freed from exclusion from Heaven the just who had gone before him: &quot;It is precisely these holy souls who awaited their Savior in Abraham's bosom whom Christ the Lord delivered when he descended into Hell&quot;, the Catechism states (CCC 633), echoing the words of the [[Roman Catechism]], 1,6,3. His death was of no avail to the damned.

Conceptualization of the abode of the dead as a place, though possible and customary, is not obligatory (Church documents, such as catechisms, speak of a &quot;state or place&quot;). Some maintain that Christ did not go to the  place of the damned, which is what is generally understood today by the word &quot;Hell&quot;. For instance, [[Thomas Aquinas]] taught that Christ did not descend into the &quot;Hell of the lost&quot; in his essence, but only by the effect of his death, through which &quot;he put them to shame for their unbelief and wickedness: but to them who were detained in [[Purgatory]] he gave hope of attaining to glory: while upon the holy Fathers detained in Hell solely on account of [[original sin]], he shed the light of glory everlasting.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/summa/4052.htm Summa Theologica, III, 52, art. 2]&lt;/ref&gt;

While some maintain that Christ merely descended into the &quot;limbo of the fathers&quot;, others, notably theologian [[Hans Urs von Balthasar]] (inspired by the visions of [[Adrienne von Speyr]]), maintain that it was more than this and that the descent involved suffering by Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;Reno, R.R. [http://www.firstthings.com/onthesquare/?p=1192 Was Balthasar a Heretic?] First Things, October 13, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  Since both [[John Paul II]] and [[Benedict XVI]] have lauded the theology of Balthasar, and because some do not see a precise doctrinal position of the Church on this point, some maintain that this is a matter on which differences and theological speculation are permissible without transgressing the limits of orthodoxy.&lt;ref&gt;Reno, R.R. [http://www.firstthings.com/onthesquare/?p=1192 Was Balthasar a Heretic?] First Things, October 13, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Eastern Orthodox ===
[[Image:Anastasis at Chora.jpg|thumb|300px|In ''Harrowing of Hades'', fresco in the ''parecclesion'' of the [[Chora Church]], [[Istanbul]], c.1315, raising Adam and Eve is depicted as part of the Resurrection icon, as it always is in the East.]]

Saint [[John Chrysostom]]'s ''[[Paschal Homily]]'' also addresses the Harrowing of Hades, and is typically read during the [[Paschal Vigil]], the major service of the Eastern Orthodox celebration of [[Easter|Pascha]] (Easter).

In the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], the Harrowing of Hades is celebrated annually on [[Holy and Great Saturday]], during the [[Vespers|Vesperal]] [[Divine Liturgy of Saint Basil]]. At the beginning of the service, the [[antependium|hangings]] in the church and the [[vestment]]s worn by the clergy are all somber [[Great Lent|Lenten]] colours (usually purple or black). Then, just before the [[Gospel]] reading, the [[liturgical colors]] are changed white and the deacon performs a [[censing]], and the priest strews [[Bay Laurel|laurel]] leaves around the church, symbolizing the broken gates of hell; this is done in celebration of the harrowing of Hades then taking place, and in anticipation of Christ's imminent resurrection.

The Harrowing of Hades is generally more common and prominent in Orthodox [[iconography]] compared to the Western tradition. It is the traditional [[icon]] for [[Holy Saturday]], and is used during the [[Paschal season]] and on Sundays throughout the year.

The traditional Eastern Orthodox icon of the [[Resurrection of Jesus]] does not depict simply the physical act of Jesus' coming out of the [[Holy Sepulchre|Tomb]], but rather it depicts what Orthodox Christians believe to be the spiritual reality of what his [[Death and resurrection of Jesus|Death and Resurrection]] accomplished.

The icon shows Jesus, vested in white and gold to symbolize his divine majesty, standing on the brazen gates of Hades (also called the &quot;Doors of Death&quot;), which are broken and have fallen in the form of a cross, illustrating the belief that by his death on the cross, Jesus trampled down death (see [[Paschal troparion]]). He is holding [[Adam (Bible)|Adam]] and [[Eve]] and pulling them up out of Hades. Traditionally, he is not shown holding them by the hands, but by their wrists, to illustrate the theological teaching that mankind could not pull himself out of his [[ancestral sin]], but that it could come about only by the work (''[[Essence-Energies distinction|energia]]'') of God. Jesus is surrounded by various righteous figures from the [[Old Testament]] ([[Abraham]], [[David]], etc.); the bottom of the icon depicts Hades as a chasm of darkness, often with various pieces of broken locks and chains strewn about. Quite frequently, one or two figures are shown in the darkness, bound in chains, who are generally identified as personifications of [[Death]] and/or the [[Devil]].

=== Lutheran ===

[[Martin Luther]], in a sermon delivered in Torgau in 1533, stated that Christ descended into Hell.

The [[Formula of Concord]] (a Lutheran confession) states, &quot;we believe simply that the entire person, God and human being, descended to Hell after his burial, conquered the devil, destroyed the power of Hell, and took from the devil all his power.&quot; (Solid Declaration, Art. IX)

Many attempts were made following Luther's death to systematize his theology of the descensus, whether Christ descended in victory or humiliation. For Luther, however, the defeat or &quot;[[Humiliation of Christ|humiliation]]&quot; of Christ is never fully separable from His victorious glorification. Some argued that Christ's suffering was completed with His words from the cross, &quot;It is finished&quot;, but this would obviously make His subsequent death and burial completely superfluous, while also obviating the need to suffer the penalty promised sinful man (death) as a substitute (the &quot;substitutionary atonement&quot; being a chief principle of Lutheran soteriology). Luther himself, when pressed to elaborate on the question of whether Christ descended to Hell in humiliation or victory responded, &quot;It is enough to preach the article to the laypeople as they have learned to know it in the past from the stained glass and other sources.&quot;

=== Calvinist ===

The [[Calvinist]] position is that if Christ had descended into Hell (place of eternal suffering), he would have had to bear [[Damnation|God's Curse]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} [[John Calvin]] expressed his concern that many Christians &quot;have never earnestly considered what it is or means that we have been redeemed from God's judgment. Yet this is our wisdom: duly to feel how much our salvation cost the Son of God.&quot; Calvin's conclusion is that &quot;Christ's descent into Hell was necessary for Christians' [[Atonement in Christianity|atonement]], because Christ did in fact endure the penalty for the sins of the redeemed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reformed.org/master/index.html?mainframe=/documents/Christ_in_hell/index.html Center for Reformed Theology and Apologetics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Latter-day Saints ===

The Harrowing of Hell has been a unique and important doctrine among members of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] since its founding in 1830 by [[Joseph Smith]], although members of the church (&quot;Mormons&quot;) usually call it by other terms, such as &quot;Christ's visit to the spirit world.&quot; Like Christian exegetes distinguishing between [[Sheol]] and [[Gehenna]], Latter-day Saints distinguish between the realm of departed spirits (the &quot;spirit world&quot;) and the portion (or state) of the wicked (&quot;spirit prison&quot;). The portion or state of the righteous is often referred to as &quot;paradise&quot;.

Perhaps the most notable aspect of Latter-day Saint beliefs regarding the Harrowing of Hell is their view on the purpose of it, both for the just and the wicked. [[Joseph F. Smith]], the sixth president of the Church, explained in what is now a canonized revelation, that when Christ died, &quot;there were gathered together in one place an innumerable company of the spirits of the just, . . . rejoicing together because the day of their deliverance was at hand. They were assembled awaiting the advent of the Son of God into the spirit world, to declare their redemption from the bands of death&quot; ([[Doctrine and Covenants|D&amp;C]] 138:12, 15-16).

In the LDS view, while Christ announced freedom from physical death to the just, he had another purpose in descending to Hell regarding the wicked. &quot;The Lord went not in person among the wicked and the disobedient who had rejected the truth, to teach them; but behold, from among the righteous, he organized his forces…and commissioned them to go forth and carry the light of the gospel to them that were in darkness, even to all the spirits of men; and thus was the gospel preached to the dead . . . to those who had died in their sins, without a knowledge of the truth, or in transgression, having rejected the prophets&quot; (D&amp;C 138:29-30, 32). From the Latter-day Saint viewpoint, the rescue of spirits was not a one-time event but an ongoing process that still continues. (D&amp;C 138) (1 Peter 4:6).

== Christian mortalism ==
The above views share the traditional Christian belief in the [[immortality of the soul]]. The [[soul sleep|mortalist]] view of the [[intermediate state]] requires an alternative view of the {{bibleref2|Acts|2:27}} and {{bibleref2|Acts|2:31}}, taking a view of the [[New Testament]] use of [[Hell]] as equivalent to use of [[Hades]] in the [[Septuagint]] and therefore to [[Sheol]] in the [[Old Testament]].&lt;ref&gt;Norman T. Burns, ''Christian Mortalism from Tyndale to Milton'' 1972 p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt; [[William Tyndale]] and [[Martin Bucer]] of Strassburg argued that Hades in Acts 2 was merely a metaphor for the grave. Other reformers [[Christopher Carlisle]] and [[Walter Deloenus]] in London, argued for the article to be dropped from the creed.&lt;ref&gt;''Descent into Hell'' in ''International Standard Bible Encyclopedia: A-D'' ed. and article Geoffrey W. Bromiley pp. 926-927.&lt;/ref&gt; The Harrowing of Hell was a major scene in traditional depictions of Christ's life avoided by [[John Milton]] due to his mortalist views.&lt;ref&gt;William Bridges Hunter ''Milton's English poetry: being entries from A Milton encyclopedia'' p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt; Mortalist interpretations of the Acts 2 statements of Christ being in Hades are also found among later Anglicans such as [[E. W. Bullinger]].&lt;ref&gt;E. W. Bullinger &quot;Hell&quot; in ''A Critical Lexicon and Concordance to the English and Greek New Testament'' pp. 367-369.&lt;/ref&gt;

While those holding mortalist views on the soul would agree on the &quot;harrowing of hell&quot; concerning souls, that there were no conscious dead for Christ to literally visit, the question of whether Christ himself was also dead, unconscious, brings different answers:
* to most [[Protestant]] advocates of &quot;[[soul sleep]]&quot; such as [[Martin Luther]], Christ himself was not in the same condition as the dead, and while his body was in Hades, Christ, as second person of the Trinity, was conscious in heaven.&lt;ref&gt;Kenneth Hagen ''A theology of Testament in the young Luther: the lectures on Hebrews'' 1974 p95 &quot;For Luther it refers to God's abandonment of Christ during the three days of his death:&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* to Christian mortalists who are also [[non-Trinitarian]], such as [[Socinians]] and [[Christadelphians]]&lt;ref&gt;Whittaker H.A. ''Studies in the Gospels''&lt;/ref&gt; the maxim &quot;the dead know nothing&quot; includes also Christ during the three days.

Of the three days, Christ says &quot;I was dead&quot; (Greek ''egenomen nekros'' ἐγενόμην νεκρὸς, Latin ''fui mortuus'') (Revelation 1:18).

== In art, music and literature ==
[[Image:Descent into hell-Russian Museum.jpg|thumb|''Harrowing of Hades'', an icon by [[Dionisius]], from the [[Ferapontov Monastery]].]]

{{unreferenced section|date=January 2011}}
'''Drama'''
* The earliest surviving Christian drama probably intended to be performed is the ''[[Harrowing of Hell (drama)|Harrowing of Hell]]'' found in the eighth-century ''[[Book of Cerne]]''.

'''Literature'''
* In [[Dante]]'s ''[[Divine Comedy|Inferno]]'' the Harrowing of Hell is mentioned in Canto IV by the pilgrim's guide [[Virgil]]. Virgil was in Hell in the first place because he was not exposed to Christianity in his lifetime, and therefore he actually describes in generic terms Christ as a 'mighty one' who rescued the Hebrew forefathers of Christianity, but left him behind in the very same circle. It is clear that he does not fully understand the significance of the event like Dante.
* Although the [[Orfeo]] legend has its origin in pagan antiquity, the Medieval [[Romance (heroic literature)|romance]] of [[Sir Orfeo]] has often been intrepreted as drawing parallels between the Greek hero and Jesus freeing souls from Hell,&lt;ref&gt;Elisabeth Henry, ''Orpheus with His Lute: Poetry and the Renewal of Life'' (Bristol Classical Press, 1992), pp. 38, 50–53, 81 ''et passim''; Elaine Treharne, &quot;Speaking of the Medieval&quot;, in ''The Oxford Handbook of Medieval Literature in English'' (Oxford University Press, 2010), p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; with the explication of Orpheus's descent and return from the underworld as an allegory for Christ's as early as the ''[[Pierre Bersuire|Ovide Moralisé]]'' (1340).&lt;ref&gt;John Block Friedman, ''Orpheus in the Middle Ages'' (Syracuse University Press, 2000), pp. 125–126.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[Stephen Lawhead]]'s novel ''Byzantium'' (1997), a young [[Irish monk]] is asked to explain Jesus' life to a group of [[Vikings]], who are particularly impressed with Jesus' &quot;[[Descent to the underworld|Helreið]]&quot;.

Parallels also exist in Jewish literature, but referencing legends of Enoch and Abraham's harrowings of the underworld, not related to Christian themes. These have been updated in [[Isaac Leib Peretz]]'s short story ''[[Neilah]] in [[Gehenna]]'', a Jewish [[hazzan]] descends to Hell and uses his unique voice to bring about the repentance and liberation of the souls imprisoned there.

'''Music'''
The subject of the harrowing of hell was the subject of several baroque [[oratorio]]s, most notably [[Salieri]]'s ''Gesù al Limbo'' (1803) to a text by Luigi Prividali.&lt;ref&gt;Recording and essay with Il Giudizio Finale; Te Deum. dir Alberto Turco, Bongiovanni&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Christian mythology]]
* [[Descent to the underworld]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* Trumbower, J. A., &quot;Jesus' Descent to the Underworld,&quot; in Idem, ''Rescue for the Dead: The Posthumous Salvation of Non-Christians in Early Christianity'' (Oxford, 2001) (Oxford Studies in Historical Theology), 91-108.
* Brinkman, Martien E., &quot;The Descent into Hell and the Phenomenon of Exorcism in the Early Church,&quot; in Jerald D. Gort, Henry Jansen and Hendrik M. Vroom (eds), ''Probing the Depths of Evil and Good: Multireligious Views and Case Studies'' (Amsterdam/New York, NY, 2007) (Currents of Encounter - Studies on the Contact between Christianity and Other Religions, Beliefs, and Cultures, 33).
* Alyssa Lyra Pitstick, ''Light in Darkness: Hans Urs von Balthasar and the Catholic Doctrine of Christ's Descent into Hel''l (Grand Rapids (MI), Eerdmanns, 2007).
* Gavin D'Costa, &quot;Part IV: Christ’s Descent into Hell,&quot; in Idem, ''Christianity and World Religions: Disputed Questions in the Theology of Religions'' (Oxford, Wiley-Blackwell, 2009),
* Georgia Frank, &quot;Christ’s Descent to the Underworld in Ancient Ritual and Legend,&quot; in Robert J. Daly (ed), ''Apocalyptic Thought in Early Christianity'' (Grand Rapids (MI), Baker Academic, 2009) (Holy Cross Studies in Patristic Theology and History), 211-226.

== External links ==
{{commons category|Harrowing of Hell}}
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07143d.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: Harrowing of Hell]
* [http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/HAN_HEG/HARROWING_OF_HELL.html Encyclopædia Britannica: Harrowing of Hell]
* [http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/actspilate.html ''Gospel of Nicodemus'': Descensus Christ ad inferos]''
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20071211142319/www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/gospelnicodemus.html The Gospel of Nicodemus] including the Descent into Hell
* [http://www.umm.maine.edu/faculty/necastro/drama/chester/play_18.html Harrowing of Hell] in the [[Chester Mystery Plays|Chester Cycle]]
* [http://www.patzinakia.ro/libri/Harrowing.html Le Harrowing of Hell dans les Cycles de York, Towneley et Chester]'', by Alexandra Costache-Babcinschi (ebook, French)
* [http://www.vatican.va/spirit/documents/spirit_20010414_omelia-sabato-santo_en.html Lord's Descent into Hell, The]
* [http://www.icon-art.info/topic.php?lng=en&amp;top_id=70&amp;mode=img Russian Orthodox iconography of the Harrowing of Hell]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/summa/405200.htm Summa Theologica: Christ's descent into hell]

{{Early Lutheran Controversies}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Harrowing Of Hell}}
[[Category:Christian iconography]]
[[Category:Christian miracle narrative]]
[[Category:Christian mythology]]
[[Category:Christian theology]]
[[Category:Christianity-related controversies]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Christianity and death]]

{{Link GA|ru}}
[[de:Höllenfahrt Christi]]
[[el:Κάθοδος του Χριστού στον Άδη]]
[[es:Descenso de Cristo a los infiernos]]
[[fr:Descente aux Enfers (Jésus)]]
[[it:Discesa di Cristo agli inferi]]
[[ja:キリストの地獄への降下]]
[[pl:Zstąpienie Chrystusa do piekieł]]
[[pt:Descida de Cristo ao Inferno]]
[[ro:Coborârea lui Hristos în iad]]
[[ru:Сошествие Христа в ад]]
[[th:การเสด็จสู่แดนผู้ตาย]]</text>
      <sha1>fpcdqaej9srgju7i0fyzq0dr36vl8pr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
