<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Harran</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>85547</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521993014</id>
      <parentid>519204732</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T12:53:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>88.89.151.200</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Assyrian period */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22830">{{Redirect|Carrhae|the battle|Battle of Carrhae}}
{{other uses|Harran (disambiguation)}}

{{Infobox settlement
|official_name        = Harran
|name_local           =  
|image_skyline        = Harran-beehouses.jpg
|imagesize            = 280px
|pushpin_map          = Turkey
|mapsize              = 280px
|map_caption          = Location of Harran in Turkey
|coordinates_region     = TR
|subdivision_type     = [[Countries of the world|Country]]
|subdivision_name     = {{TUR}}
|subdivision_type1    = [[Regions of Turkey|Region]]
|subdivision_name1    = [[Southeastern Anatolia Region|Southeastern Anatolia]]
|subdivision_type2    = [[Provinces of Turkey|Province]]
|subdivision_name2    = [[Şanlıurfa Province|Şanlıurfa]]
|area_magnitude       = 
|area_total_km2       = 704
|area_land_km2        = 
|area_water_km2       = 
|population_as_of     = 2000
|population_footnotes = 
|population_total     = 150,845
|population_urban     = 32114
|population_density_km2   = 43.1
|timezone             = [[Eastern European Time|EET]]
|utc_offset           = +2
|timezone_DST         = [[Eastern European Summer Time|EEST]]
|utc_offset_DST       = +3 
|latd=36 |latm=52 |lats=39 |latNS=N 
|longd=39 |longm=02 |longs=02 |longEW=E
|coordinates_display  = display=inline,title
|elevation_m          = 
|postal_code_type     = [[List of postal codes in Turkey|Postal code]]
|postal_code          = 63xxx
|area_code            = +(90)414
|website              = [http://www.harran.gov.tr/ Şanlıurfa Province Administrative District of Akçakale]
|footnotes            = 
}}

'''Harran''' ({{lang-ku|Herran}}) was a major ancient city in [[Upper Mesopotamia]] whose site is near the modern village of Altınbaşak, [[Turkey]], 24 miles (44 kilometers) southeast of [[Şanlıurfa]]. The location is in [[Districts of Turkey|a district]] of [[Şanlıurfa Province]] that is also named &quot;Harran&quot;.

A few kilometers from the village of Altınbaşak are the archaeological remains of ancient Harran, a major commercial, cultural, and religious center first inhabited in the [[Early Bronze Age III]] (3rd millennium BCE) period. It was known as ''Ḫarrānu'' in the [[Assyrian Empire|Assyrian]] period; possibly ''Ḫaran'' ({{unicode|חָרָן}}) in the [[Hebrew Bible]]; {{unicode|Κάῤῥαι}} or ''Carrhae'' under the [[Roman Empire]]; ''Hellenopolis'' ({{Unicode|῾Ελληνὀπολις}} 'Greek city') in the Early Christian period; and ''Ḥarrān'' (حرّان) in the Islamic period.&lt;ref&gt;David Noel Freedman ''et al.'', ''Eerdmans dictionary of the Bible'' ''s.v.'' Haran&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Encyclopedia of Islam]]'', ''s.v.'' Ḥarrān&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Syria2mil.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Harran and neighboring Syrian cities]]

==History==
The earliest records of Harran come from the [[Ebla tablets]] (c. 2300 BCE).  From these, it is known that an early king or mayor of Harran had married an [[Ebla]]ite princess, Zugalum, who then became &quot;queen of Harran&quot;, and whose name appears in a number of documents.  It appears that Harran remained a part of the regional Eblaite kingdom for some time thereafter. 

Royal letters from the city of [[Mari, Syria|Mari]] on the middle of the Euphrates, have confirmed that the area around the [[Balikh]] river remained occupied in ca. the 19th century BCE. A confederation of semi-nomadic tribes was especially active around the region near Harran at that time.&lt;ref&gt;G. Dossin, “Benjamites dans les Textes de Mari, “ ‘’Melanges Syriens Offerts a M. Rene Dussaud’’ (Paris, 1939), 986&lt;/ref&gt;

===Merchant outpost===
By the 19th Century BCE, Harran was established as a merchant outpost due to its ideal location. The community, well established before then, was situated along a trade route between the [[Mediterranean]] and the plains of the middle [[Tigris]].&lt;ref&gt;Tamara M. Green,''The city of the Moon god: religious traditions of Harran'' (ISBN 9004095136, ISBN 978-90-04-09513-7), 1992, p.19&lt;/ref&gt; It lay directly on the road from [[Antioch]] eastward to [[Nisibis]] and [[Ninevah]]. The Tigris could be followed down to the delta to [[Babylon]]. The fourth century Roman historian [[Ammianus Marcellinus]] (325/330–after 391) said, “From there (Harran) two different royal highways lead to Persia: the one on the left through [[Adiabene]] and over the Tigris; the one on the right, through Assyria and across the Euphrates.”&lt;ref&gt;Ammianus Marcellinus, R.G., XXIII.3.1&lt;/ref&gt; Not only did Harran have easy access to both the Assyrian and Babylonian roads, but also to north road to the Euphrates that provided easy access to Malatiyah and [[Asia Minor]].

According to Roman authors such as [[Pliny the Elder]], even through the [[classical antiquity|classical period]], Harran maintained an important position in the economic life of Northern Mesopotamia.&lt;ref&gt;Pliny, ‘’Naturalis Historia’’, XII. 40&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Assyrian period ===
In its prime Harran was a major Assyrian city which controlled the point where the road from [[Damascus]] joins the highway between [[Nineveh]] and [[Carchemish]]. This location gave Harran strategic value from an early date. Because Harran had an abundance of goods that passed through its region, it became a target for raids. In the 18th century, Assyrian king [[Shamshi-Adad I]] (1813 – 1781 BCE) launched an expedition to secure the Harranian trade route.

=== Hittite period ===
After the [[Suppiluliuma I]]–[[Shattiwaza]] treaty (14th century BCE) between the [[Hittite Empire]] and [[Mitanni]], Harran was burned by a Hittite army under [[Piyashshili]] in the course of the conquest of Mitanni.

=== Assyrian period ===
In the 13th century BCE, Assyrian king [[Adad-Nirari I]] reported that he conquered the &quot;fortress of Kharani&quot; and annexed it as a province.&lt;ref&gt;S. Smith, ''Babylonian Historical Texts'' (London, 1924), p.39&lt;/ref&gt; It is frequently mentioned in Assyrian inscriptions as early as the time of [[Tiglath-Pileser I]], about 1100 BCE, under the name Harranu ([[Akkadian language|Akkadian]] ''harrānu'', &quot;road, path; campaign, journey&quot;). Tiglath-Pileser had a fortress there, and mentioned that he was pleased with the abundance of elephants in the region. 

10th century BCE inscriptions reveal that Harran had some privileges of fiscal exemption and freedom from certain forms of military obligations. It had even been termed as the &quot;free city of Harran&quot;. However, in 763 BCE, it was sacked by a Harranian rebellion against Assyrian control that resulted in the loss of those privileges. Not until [[Sargon II]] restored order, in the late 8th century BCE, were those privileges restored.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, ''Babylonian Historical Texts'', p.39&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Median period ===
During the fall of the [[Neo-Assyrian Empire]], Harran became the stronghold of its last king, [[Ashur-uballit II]], who had retreated from [[Nineveh]] when it was sacked by [[Nabopolassar]] of Babylon and his [[Medes|Median]] allies in 612 BC. Harran was besieged and conquered by [[Nabopolassar]] and [[Cyaxares]] in 610 BC. It was briefly retaken by Ashur-uballit II and his Egyptian allies in 609 BC before it definitely fell to the Medes and Babylonians.&lt;ref&gt;A. K. Grayson, ''Assyrian and Babylonian Chronicles'', New York, 1975, 96 (Fall of Nineveh chronicle).&lt;/ref&gt; The last king of the Neo-Babylonian period, [[Nabonidus]], also originated from Harran as substantiated by evidence from the temple of stele of his mother Adad-Guppi, who is suspected by some to be of Assyrian origin. The city became a bastion for the worship of the moon god during the rule of Nabonidus from 555-536 BC, much to the consternation of the city of Babylon in the south where Marduk remained the primary deity.

=== Persian period ===
Harran became part of the [[Median Empire]] after the fall of Assyria, and subsequently passed to the [[Persia]]n [[Achaemenid dynasty]] in the 6th century BCE. It became part of the Persian province of '''Athura''', the Persian word for [[Assyria]]. The city remained in Persian hands until 331 BCE, when the soldiers of the [[Ancient Macedonians|Macedonian]] conqueror [[Alexander the Great]] entered the city.

=== Seleucid period ===
After the death of Alexander on June 11, 323 BCE, the city was contested by his successors: [[Perdiccas]], [[Antigonus Monophthalmus]], and [[Eumenes]] visited the city, but eventually it became part of the realm of [[Seleucus I Nicator]], of the [[Seleucid Empire]], and capital of a province called [[Osrhoene]] (the Greek rendering of the old name [[Urhai]]). For one and a half centuries the town flourished, and became independent when the [[Parthian Empire|Parthian dynasty]] of Persia occupied [[Babylonia]]. The Parthian and Seleucid kings were both happy with a buffer state, and the dynasty of the [[Arab]]ian Abgarides, technically a vassal of the Parthian &quot;[[Shahanshah|king of kings]]&quot;, was to rule Osrhoene for centuries. The main language spoken in Oshroene was [[Aramaic]], and the majority of people were Christian Assyrians.

=== Classical period ===
In Roman times, Harran was known as Carrhae, and was the location of the [[Battle of Carrhae]] in 53 BCE, in which the Parthians, commanded by general [[Surena]], defeated a large Roman army under the command of [[Marcus Licinius Crassus|Crassus]], who was killed.

Centuries later, the emperor [[Caracalla]] was murdered here at the instigation of [[Macrinus]] (217). The emperor [[Galerius]] was defeated nearby by the Parthians' successors, the [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid dynasty]] of Persia, in 296 CE. The city remained under Persian control until the fall of the Sassanids to the Arabs in 651 CE.

=== Early Islamic Harran ===
At the beginning of the Islamic period Harran was located in the land of the [[Mudar]] tribe ([[Diyar Mudar]]), the western part of northern Mesopotamia ([[Al-Jazira, Mesopotamia|Jazira]]). Along with ar-Ruha' ([[Şanlıurfa]]) and [[Ar-Raqqah]] it was one of the main cities in the region. During the reign of the [[Umayyad]] [[caliph]] [[Marwan II]] Harran became the seat of the caliphal government of the Islamic empire stretching from [[Spain]] to [[Central Asia]].

It was allegedly the [[Abbasid]] caliph [[al-Ma'mun]] who, while passing through Harran on his way to a campaign against the [[Byzantine Empire]], forced the Harranians to convert to one of the &quot;religions of the book&quot;, meaning [[Judaism]], Christianity, or Islam. The pagan people of Harran identified themselves with the Sabians in order to fall under the protection of Islam. Aramaean and Assyrian Christians remained Christian. Sabians were mentioned in the [[Qur'an]], but those were a group of [[Mandaeans]] (a [[Gnosticism|Gnostic]] sect) living in southern Mesopotamia. The relationship of the Harranian Sabians to the ones mentioned in the Qur'an is a matter of dispute. The Harranians may have identified themselves as Sabians in order to retain their religious beliefs.

[[File:Harranruins1.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Ruins of the University at Harran. It was one of the main Ayyubid buildings of the city, built in the classical revival style.]]

===Islam's first university===
During the late 8th and 9th centuries Harran was a centre for translating works of astronomy, philosophy, natural sciences, and medicine from [[Greek language|Greek]] to [[Syriac language|Syriac]] by [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], and thence to [[Arabic language|Arabic]], bringing the knowledge of the [[Classical antiquity|classical world]] to the emerging Arabic-speaking civilization in the south. [[Baghdad]] came to this work later than Harran. Many important scholars of natural science, astronomy, and medicine originate from Harran; they were non-Arab and non-Islamic ethnic [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], including possibly the alchemist [[Jābir ibn Hayyān]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Geber |title=Geber – LoveToKnow 1911}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The end of the Mandaeans===
In 1032 or 1033 the temple of the Sabians was destroyed and the urban community extinguished by an uprising of the rural, starving '[[Alid]]-[[Shiite]] population and impoverished urban Muslim militias. In 1059–60 the temple was rebuilt into a fortified residence of the [[Numayrid]]s, an Arab tribe assuming power in the Diyar Mudar (western [[Al-Jazira, Mesopotamia|Jazira]]) during the 11th century. The [[Zangi]]d ruler [[Nur al-Din Mahmud]] transformed the residence into a strong fortress.

===The Crusades===
During the [[Crusades]], on May 7, 1104, a decisive battle was fought in the [[Balikh River]] valley, commonly known as the [[Battle of Harran]]. However, according to [[Matthew of Edessa]] the actual location of the battle lies two days away from Harran. [[Albert of Aachen]] and [[Fulcher of Chartres]] locate the battleground in the plain opposite to the city of [[ar Raqqah|ar-Raqqah]]. During the battle, [[Baldwin of Bourcq]], [[County of Edessa|Count of Edessa]], was captured by troops of the [[Great Seljuq Empire]]. After his release Baldwin became [[Kingdom of Jerusalem|King of Jerusalem]].

At the end of 12th century Harran served together with ar-Raqqah as a residence of [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]] [[Ayyubid dynasty|Ayyubid]] princes. The Ayyubid ruler of the Jazira, [[Al-Adil I]], again strengthened the fortifications of the castle. In the 1260s the city was completely destroyed and abandoned during the [[Mongol invasions of Syria]]. The father of the famous [[Hanbali]]te scholar [[Ibn Taymiyyah]] was a refugee from Harran, settling in Damascus. The 13th century Arab historian [[Abu al-Fida]] describes the city as being in ruins.

== Modern Harran ==
[[File:Harran2.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Traditional mud brick [[Beehive house|&quot;beehive&quot; houses]] in the village of Harran, Turkey]]
[[File:Şanlıurfa districts.png|thumb|300px|Districts of Şanlıurfa]]
[[File:Harran main channel-GAP.jpg|thumb|300px|Harran main channel, built as a part of [[Southeastern Anatolia Project|GAP Project]] ]]
Harran is famous for its traditional [[Beehive house|'beehive' adobe houses]], constructed entirely without wood. The design of these makes them cool inside (essential in this part of the world) and is thought to have been unchanged for at least 3,000 years. Some were still in use as dwellings until the 1980s. However, those remaining today are strictly tourist exhibits, while most of Harran's population lives in a newly built small village about 2 kilometres away from the main site.

At the historical site the ruins of the city walls and fortifications are still in place, with one city gate standing, along with some other structures. Excavations of a nearby 4th century BC burial mound continue under archaeologist Dr [[Nurettin Yardımcı]].

The new village is poor and life is hard in the hot weather on this plain. The people here are now ethnic [[Arab]]s and live by long-established traditions. It is believed that these Arabs were settled here during the 18th century by the [[Ottoman Empire]]. The women of the village are tattooed and dressed in traditional [[Bedouin]] clothes. The [[Assyrians]] who once occupied the area for thousands of years have moved to other areas, although there are some [[Assyrian people|Assyrian]] villages in the general area. 

By the late 1980s the large plain of Harran had fallen into disuse as the streams of Cüllab and Deysan, its original water-supply had dried up. But the plain is irrigated by the recent [[Southeastern Anatolia Project]] and is becoming green again. Cotton and rice can now be grown.

== Religion ==
The city was the chief home of the Mesopotamian [[Lunar deity|moon god]] [[Sin (mythology)|Sin]], under the Assyrians and [[Neo-Babylonian Empire|Neo-Babylonians/Chaldeans]] and even into [[Roman Empire|Roman]] times. 

According to an early Arabic work known as ''Kitab al-Magall'' or the ''Book of Rolls'' (part of [[Clementine literature]]), Harran was one of the cities built by [[Nimrod]], when [[Peleg]] was 50 years old. The [[Syriac]] ''[[Cave of Treasures]]'' (ca. 350) contains a similar account of Nimrod's building Harran and the other cities, but places the event when [[Reu]] was 50 years old. The ''Cave of Treasures'' adds an ancient legend that not long thereafter, [[Tammuz (deity)|Tammuz]] was pursued to Harran by his wife's lover, [[Beelshamen|B'elshemin]], and that he (Tammuz) met his fate there when the city was then burnt.  

The pagan residents of Harran also maintained the tradition well into the tenth century AD, of being the site of Tammuz' death, and would conduct elaborate mourning rituals for him each year, in the [[Tammuz (Babylonian calendar)|month bearing his name]].

However, the Islamic historian [[Al-Masudi]] in his ''[[Meadows of Gold]]'' (ca. 950), as well as the Christian historian [[Bar Hebraeus]] (13th c.), both recounted a legend that Harran had been built by [[Cainan]] (the father of Abraham's ancestor [[Salah (biblical figure)|Shelah]] in some accounts), and had been named for another son of Cainan called Harran.

Sin's temple was rebuilt by several kings, among them the Assyrian [[Assur-bani-pal]] (7th century BCE) and the Neo-Babylonian [[Nabonidus]] (6th century BCE).
&lt;ref&gt;H. W. F. Saggs, Neo-Babylonian Fragments from Harran, Iraq, vol. 31, no. 2, pp. 166–169, 1969&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;C. J. Gadd, The Harran Inscriptions of Nabonidus, Anatolian Studies, vol. 8, pp. 35–92, 1958&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Herodian]] (iv. 13, 7) mentions the town as possessing in his day a temple of the moon.

Harran was a centre of [[East Syrian Rite|Assyrian Christianity]] from early on, and was the first place where purpose-built churches were constructed openly. However, although a bishop resided in the city, many people of Harran retained their ancient pagan faith during the Christian period, and ancient Mesopotamian/Assyrian gods such as Sin and Ashur were still worshipped for a time. In addition the [[Mandaeans|Mandean]] religion, a form of [[Gnosticism]], was born in Harran.

===Harran in scriptures===

{{Main|Haran (biblical place)}}

Premedieval Harran has been closely associated with the biblical place [[Haran (biblical place)|Haran]] (Hebrew: '''{{unicode|חָרָן}}''', transliterated: Charan). Very little is known about the premedieval levels of Harran&lt;ref&gt;Bienkowski &amp; Millard. ''Dictionary of the ancient Near East'' (ISBN 0812235576, ISBN 978-0-8122-3557-9), 2000, p.140&lt;/ref&gt; and even less for the patriarchal times. (Lloyd and Brice) &lt;ref&gt;Alexander &amp; Baker. Dictionary of the Old Testament: Pentateuch, (ISBN 0830817816, ISBN 978-0-8308-1781-8) 2003, p. 379&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars have yet to see what physical evidence will link this village of Harran to the biblical site where [[Abram]] and his family encamped as mentioned in {{bibleref2|Genesis|11:31–32,12:4–5|NIV|Genesis 11:31,32; 12:4,5}}

Biblical Haran was where [[Terah]], his son Abram ([[Abraham]]), his grandson [[Lot (Bible)|Lot]], and Abram's wife [[Sarah|Sarai]] settled while in route to [[Canaan]], coming from [[Ur Kaśdim|Ur of the Chaldees]] (Genesis 11:26–32). The region of this Haran is referred to variously as ''[[Paddan Aram]]'' and ''[[Aram Naharaim]]''. [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] 27:43 makes Haran the home of [[Laban (Bible)|Laban]] and connects it with [[Isaac]] and [[Jacob]]: it was the home of Isaac's wife Rebekah, and their son Jacob spent twenty years in Haran working for his uncle Laban (cf. Genesis 31:38&amp;41). The place-name should not be confused with the name of [[Haran]] (Hebrew: הָרָן), Abraham's brother and Lot's father — the two names are spelled differently in the original Hebrew. Islamic tradition does link Harran to ''Aran'', the brother of Abraham.

Prior to [[Sennacherib]]'s reign (704–681 BCE), Harran rebelled from the Assyrians, who reconquered the city (see [[Books of Kings|2 Kings]] 19:12 and [[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]] 37:12) and deprived it of many privileges – which King [[Sargon II]] later restored.

==Archaeology==
[[T. E. Lawrence]] (&quot;Lawrence of Arabia&quot;) surveyed the ancient Harran site. Decades later, in 1950, [[Seton Lloyd]] conducted a three-week archaeological survey there.&lt;ref&gt;Seton Lloyd and William Brice, Harran, Anatolian Studies, vol. 1, pp. 77–111, 1951&lt;/ref&gt; An [[United Kingdom|Anglo]]–[[Turkey|Turkish]] excavation was begun in 1951, ending in 1956 with the death of D. S. Rice.&lt;ref&gt;David Storm Rice, &quot;Medieval Harran. Studies on Its Topography and Monuments I&quot;, ''Anatolian Studies'' '''2''':36–84, 1952&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notables==
* [[Al-Battani]], Sabian astronomer and mathematician
* [[Ibn Taymiyyah]], Islamic scholar
* [[Hammad al-Harrani]], Islamic scholar
* [[Nabonidus]], the last Neo-Babylonian king
* [[Belshazzar]], Nabonidus's son and regent

==See also==
*[[Cities of the ancient Near East]]
*[[Short chronology timeline]]


==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Chwolsohn, Daniil Abramovic, ''Die Ssabier und der Ssabismus'', 2 vols. St. Petersburg, 1856. [Still a valuable reference and collection of sources]
* Green, Tamara, ''The City of the Moon God: Religious Traditions of Harran''. Leiden, 1992.
* Heidemann, Stefan, ''Die Renaissance der Städte in Nordsyrien und Nordmesopotamien: Städtische Entwicklung und wirtschaftliche Bedingungen in ar-Raqqa und Harran von der beduinischen Vorherrschaft bis zu den Seldschuken'' (Islamic History and Civilization. Studies and Texts 40). Leiden, 2002 .

== External links ==
* [http://www.pbase.com/dosseman/harran Pictures of the city]
* [http://www.livius.org/ha-hd/harran/harran.html More pictures]
* [http://www.anatolia.luwo.be/Harran.htm Harran Guide and Photo Album]
* [http://www.livius.org/ha-hd/harran/harran.html Livius.org: Harran (Carrhae)]
{{Commons category|Harran, Şanlıurfa}}
{{Districts of Turkey|provname=Şanlıurfa|image=Sanliurfa}}

{{Former settlements in Turkey}}
{{Tentative list of World Heritage Sites in Turkey}}

[[Category:Torah cities]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in Turkey]]
[[Category:Assyria]]
[[Category:Hurrian cities]]
[[Category:Former populated places in Turkey]]
[[Category:Populated places in Şanlıurfa Province]]
[[Category:History of Şanlıurfa Province]]

[[am:ካራን]]
[[ar:حران (تركيا)]]
[[bg:Харан]]
[[ca:Harran]]
[[cs:Harran]]
[[de:Harran]]
[[el:Χαρράν]]
[[es:Harrán]]
[[eo:Harran]]
[[fa:حران]]
[[fr:Harran]]
[[gl:Harran]]
[[ko:하란]]
[[hy:Խառան]]
[[hr:Haran]]
[[it:Harran]]
[[he:חרן]]
[[sw:Harran]]
[[ku:Herran]]
[[mrj:Харран]]
[[la:Carrhae]]
[[lt:Haranas]]
[[hu:Harrán]]
[[ms:Harran]]
[[nl:Harran (stad)]]
[[ja:ハッラーン]]
[[no:Harran (Mesopotamia)]]
[[pnb:ضلع ہاران]]
[[pl:Harran]]
[[pt:Harã]]
[[ro:Harran]]
[[ru:Харран]]
[[simple:Harran]]
[[sl:Harran]]
[[ckb:حەڕان]]
[[sr:Харан]]
[[sh:Harran]]
[[fi:Harran]]
[[sv:Harran]]
[[tl:Harran]]
[[tr:Harran]]
[[vi:Harran]]
[[diq:Heran]]
[[zh:哈兰 (土耳其)]]</text>
      <sha1>aqc4xvdp23yvsawo5fxr0s03uncopo3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
