<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Herem (censure)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>309330</id>
    <revision>
      <id>488906211</id>
      <parentid>474919854</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-24T00:09:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ChrisGualtieri</username>
        <id>16333418</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* In the Talmud, twenty-four offenses */TypoScan Project / General Fixes, typos fixed: israelite → Israelite using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14217">{{About||the same Hebrew word that means to devote or destroy|Herem (war or property)|the Kohanic gift|Herem (priestly gift)}}
'''''Herem''''' (or '''''Chērem''''' חרם), is the highest ecclesiastical censure in the [[Jew]]ish community. It is the total exclusion of a person from the Jewish community. It is a form of [[shunning]], and is similar to [[excommunication]] in the [[Catholic Church]].  Cognate terms in other Semitic languages include the [[Arabic language|Arabic]] term ''{{Unicode|[[haraam|ḥarām]]}}'' (forbidden, taboo, off-limits, sacred or immoral), and the [[Ethiopic]] ''`irm'' (meaning accursed).

The most famous case of a herem is that of [[Baruch Spinoza|Spinoza]], the seventeenth century philosopher.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} 

Also, [[Leon Trotsky]] and [[Grigory Zinoviev]] became subject of herem. Sometime in 1918, while Ukraine was under German occupation, the rabbis of [[Odessa]] pronounced herem against Trotsky, Zinoviev, and other Jewish [[Bolshevik]] leaders in the synagogue.&lt;ref&gt;Zinoviev cynically referred to this in his eulogy of Uritsky (the chief of the Petrograd Cheka, assassinated on August 30, 1918): &quot;When we read that in Odessa, under [[Skoropadsky]], the rabbis assembled in special council, and there these representatives of the rich Jews, officially, before the entire world, excommunicated from the Jewish community such Jews as Trotsky and me, your obedient servant, and others - no single hair of any of us has turned gray because of grief&quot;; Zinoviev, Sochineniia, 16:224, quoted in Bezbozhnik [The godless], no. 20 (12 September 1938).&lt;/ref&gt;

== Summary ==

Although developed from the [[Bible|Biblical]] ban, excommunication, as employed by the Rabbis during [[Talmud|Talmudic times]] and during the Middle Ages, it became a rabbinic institution, the object of which was to preserve Jewish solidarity. A system of laws was gradually developed by Rabbis, by means of which this power was limited, so that it became one of the modes of legal punishment by rabbinic courts. While it did not entirely lose its arbitrary character, since individuals were allowed to pronounce the ban of excommunication on particular occasions, it became chiefly a legal measure resorted to by a judicial court for certain prescribed offenses.

== Etymology and cognate terms ==

The three terms ''herem (censure)'', excommunication, ''[[herem (war or property)]]'' the devotion of enemies by annihilation in the [[Tanakh]], and ''[[herem (priestly gift)]]'' the devotion of property to a kohen, are all three variant English [[transliteration]]s of the same Hebrew noun. This noun comes from the [[semitic root]] [[Ḥ-R-M]].

There is also an identically spelled ([[homonym]]) Hebrew noun ''herem'', fisherman's net, which appears 9 times in the [[masoretic text]] of the Tanakh but has no etymological connection to ''herem'' as devoted objects.&lt;ref&gt;[[Brown Driver Briggs]] ''Hebrew Lexicon,'' entries ''herem'' 1, ''herem'' 2&lt;/ref&gt;

The Talmudic usage of ''herem'', for excommunication, can be distinguished from the usage of ''herem'' described in the Tanakh in the time of [[Joshua]] and the early Hebrew monarchy, which was the practice of consecration by total annihilation&lt;ref&gt;http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=124494788&amp;ps=cprs&lt;/ref&gt; at the command of Yahweh carried out against peoples such as the [[Midian]]ites, the [[Amalekites]], and the entire population of [[Jericho]].  The neglect of [[Saul]] to carry out such a command as delivered by [[Samuel (Bible)|Samuel]] resulted in the selection of David as his replacement.

== In the Talmud, twenty-four offenses ==
The Talmud speaks of twenty-four offenses that, in theory, were punishable by a form of ''[[niddui]]'' or temporary excommunication. [[Maimonides]] (as well as later authorities) enumerates the twenty-four as follows:
{{incoherent|date = November 2010}}
# insulting a learned man, even after his death;
# insulting a messenger of the court;
# calling an Israelite a &quot;slave&quot;;
# refusing to appear before the court at the appointed time;
# dealing lightly with any of the rabbinic or Mosaic precepts;
# refusing to abide by a decision of the court;
# keeping in one's possession an animal or an object that may prove injurious to others, such as a savage dog or a broken ladder;
# selling one's real estate to a non-Jew without assuming the responsibility for any injury that the non-Jew may cause his neighbors;
# testifying against one's Jewish neighbor in a non-Jewish court, and thereby causing that neighbor to lose money which he would not have lost had the case been decided in a Jewish court;
# a [[Kohen]] [[shochet]] (butcher) (all the more so an Israelite&lt;ref&gt;[[Eliezer ben Joel HaLevi|Raaviah]] to Chullin chap. 1225, Rabbi [[Meir of Rothenburg]] responsa 7 (mossad horav kook vol. 2 p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;) who refuses to give the [[Giving of the foreleg, cheeks and abomasum|foreleg, cheeks and abomasum]] of kosher-slaughtered livestock to another Kohen;
# violating the second day of a holiday, even though its observance is only a custom;
# performing work on the afternoon of the day preceding Passover;
# taking the name of God in vain;
# causing others to profane the name of God;
# causing others to eat holy meat outside of Jerusalem;
# making calculations for the calendar, and establishing festivals accordingly, outside of Israel;
# putting a stumbling-block in the way of the blind, that is to say, tempting another to sin ([[Lifnei iver]]);
# preventing the community from performing some religious act;
# selling forbidden (&quot;[[terefah]]&quot;) meat as permitted meat (&quot;kosher&quot;);
# failure by a &quot;[[shochet]]&quot; (ritual slaughterer) to show his knife to the rabbi for examination;
# [[masturbation]];
# engaging in business intercourse with one's divorced wife;
# being made the subject of scandal (in the case of a rabbi);
# declaring an unjustified excommunication.

For all practical purposes, most of these conditions no longer were considered as grounds for a ban since the end of the Talmudic era, around 600 CE.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

== The niddui ==

The &quot;niddui&quot; ban was usually imposed for a period of seven days (in Israel thirty days). If inflicted on account of money matters, the offender was first publicly warned (&quot;hatra'ah&quot;) three times, on Monday, Thursday, and Monday successively, at the regular service in the synagogue. During the period of niddui, no one except the members of his immediate household was permitted to associate with the offender, or to sit within four cubits of him, or to eat in his company. He was expected to go into mourning and to refrain from bathing, cutting his hair, and wearing shoes, and he had to observe all the laws that pertained to a mourner. He could not be counted in the number necessary for the performance of a public religious function. If he died, a stone was placed on his hearse, and the relatives were not obliged to observe the ceremonies customary at the death of a kinsman, such as the tearing of garments, [[Bereavement in Judaism|etc.]].

It was in the power of the court to lessen or increase the severity of the niddui. The court might even reduce or increase the number of days, forbid all intercourse with the offender, and exclude his children from the schools and his wife from the synagogue, until he became humbled and willing to repent and obey the court's mandates. According to one opinion, the apprehension that the offender might leave the Jewish fold on account of the severity of the excommunication did not prevent the court from adding [[rigor]] to its punishments so as to maintain its dignity and authority ([[Shulkhan Arukh]], [[Yoreh De'ah]], 334, 1, [[Moses Isserles|Rama's]] [[Gloss (transliteration)|gloss]], citing ''[[Alexander Susslein|Sefer Agudah]]''). This opinion is vehemently contested by the [[David HaLevi Segal|Taz]] (ibid.), who cites earlier authorities of the same opinion ([[Solomon Luria|Maharshal]]; [[Meir of Rothenburg|Maharam]]; [[Judah ben Eliezer ha-Levi Minz|Mahari Mintz]]) and presents proof of his position from the Talmud. Additionally, the Taz notes that his edition of the ''Sefer Agudah'' does not contain the cited position.

== The herem ==

If the offense was in reference to monetary matters, or if the punishment was inflicted by an individual, the laws were more lenient, the chief punishment being that men might not associate with the offender. At the expiration of the period the ban was raised by the court. If, however, the excommunicate showed no sign of penitence or remorse, the niddui might be renewed once and again, and finally the &quot;herem,&quot; the most rigorous form of excommunication, might be pronounced. This extended for an indefinite period, and no one was permitted to teach the offender or work for him, or benefit him in any way, except when he was in need of the bare necessities of life.

== The nezifah ==

A milder form than either niddui or herem was the &quot;nezifah&quot; ban. This ban generally only lasted one day. During this time the offender dared not appear before him whom he had displeased. He had to retire to his house, speak little, refrain from business and pleasure, and manifest his regret and remorse. He was not required, however, to separate himself from society, nor was he obliged to apologize to the man whom he had insulted; for his conduct on the day of nezifah was sufficient apology. But when a scholar or prominent man actually pronounced the formal niddui on one who had slighted him, all the laws of niddui applied. This procedure was, however, much discouraged by the sages, so that it was a matter of proper pride for a rabbi to be able to say that he had never pronounced the ban of excommunication. Maimonides concludes with these words the chapter on the laws of excommunication:(''[[Mishneh Torah]]'', Talmud Torah, vii. 13).

: &quot;Although the power is given to the scholar to excommunicate a man who has slighted him, it is not praiseworthy for him to employ this means too frequently. He should rather shut his ears to the words of the ignorant and pay no attention to them, as Solomon, in his wisdom, said, 'Also take no heed unto all words that are spoken' (Eccl. vii. 21). This was the custom of the early pious men, who would not answer when they heard themselves insulted, but would forgive the insolent. . . . But this humility should be practised only when the insult occurs in private; when the scholar is publicly 'insulted, he dares not forgive; and if he forgive he should be punished, for then it is an insult to the Torah that he must revenge until the offender humbly apologizes&quot;

== Since the Enlightenment ==

Except in rare cases in the [[Haredi]] and [[Chassidic]] communities, ''herem'' stopped existing after [[Haskalah|The Enlightenment]], when local Jewish communities lost their political autonomy, and Jews were integrated into the gentile nations in which they lived. {{Citation needed|date=January 2008}} In 1918, the Rabbinical Council of [[Odessa]], [[Russia]] (now in [[Ukraine]]), declared ''herem'' on [[Leon Trotsky]] and several other Jewish members of the [[Bolshevik]] movement.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}} 

In 2004, however, the [[High Court of South Africa]] upheld a herem against a [[Johannesburg]] businessman because he refused to pay his former wife [[alimony]] as ordered by a [[beth din]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roylaw.co.za/index.cfm?fuseaction=home.article&amp;pageID=6218762&amp;ArticleID=7315629 Judge upholds Jewish excommunication right]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://chareidi.shemayisrael.com/archives5765/noach/asa.htm South African Court Upholds Beis Din Cheirem]&lt;/ref&gt;

== As distinct from Catholic Church excommunication ==

The herem may best be compared to the now-defunct excommunication ''[[vitandus]].'' It is important to avoid confusing it with the Catholic excommunication as it is normally practiced to-day based on the word &quot;excommunication&quot;, as the current Catholic practice favors maintaining some relationship with the excommunicant whereas the herem is more akin to &quot;shunning&quot; as practiced by Anabaptists and some of their descendant communities.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} It is likewise important to note, however, the extreme rarity of the herem in modern Jewish life. Today it is almost exclusively imposed in cases where a spouse refuses to give a divorce, which prevents remarriage and which is sufficiently grievous that [[Maimonides]] suggested beating a divorce-refusing husband into granting one). With respect to the list of offenses theoretically resulting in excommunication Max Weber emphasizes the importance of focusing on the actual results of religious belief rather than official claims.&lt;ref&gt;Max Weber, The Protestant Ethic and The Spirit of Capitalism, pgs 55 and footnote 3 to Parsons translation&lt;/ref&gt; That such-and-such offense is listed in the [[Code of Canon Law]] or the [[Shulchan Aruch]] as punishable by excommunication is of some historical and perhaps theological interest but in terms of understanding actual religious life such laws are interesting only insofar as they were actually enforced.{{Or|date=September 2011}}

== See also ==
* [[Banishment in the Bible]]
* [[Excommunication]]
* [[Exile]]
* [[Heresy]]
* [[Heresy in Judaism]]
* [[Ostracism]]
* [[Pulsa diNura]]
* [[Shunning]]
* [[Taboo]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=1477&amp;letter=A Jewish Encyclopedia 1901: Anathema]
* [http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=199&amp;letter=B Jewish Encyclopedia 1901: Ban]
* [http://www.roylaw.co.za/index.cfm?fuseaction=home.article&amp;pageID=6218762&amp;ArticleID=7315629 South African High Court upholds Jewish right to pronounce herem]

[[Category:Jewish courts and civil law]]
[[Category:Hebrew words and phrases]]
[[Category:Disengagement from religion]]
[[Category:Judaism-related controversies]]
[[Category:Punishments in religion]]
[[Category:Religion-based wars]]
[[Category:Shunning]]
[[Category:People excommunicated by synagogues]]

[[de:Bann (Bibel)]]
[[es:Cherem]]
[[fr:Herem]]
[[it:Cherem]]
[[he:חרם (הלכה)]]
[[ja:ヘーレム]]
[[pl:Cherem]]
[[pt:Chérem]]
[[ru:Херем]]</text>
      <sha1>scaqbh40ixjlflfnqs3mzwbuvnbgix4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
