<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Herem (priestly gift)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>31471081</id>
    <revision>
      <id>489003733</id>
      <parentid>488888760</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-24T15:48:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Debresser</username>
        <id>6999039</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Better link.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9212">{{Kehuna and Kohanim}}
{{Technical|date=July 2011}}
{{About||the same Hebrew word, referring to the devotion of people and objects by war of annihilation|Herem (war or property)|the censure of excommunication|Herem (censure)}}
In the [[Tanakh]], the term '''''herem''''' (Hebrew חֵרֶם) is used, among other meanings, for an object or real property to be devoted to God, with God authorizing a ''[[kohen]]'' (Jewish priest) to be its receiving agent.&lt;ref&gt;Leviticus 27:28 et. al.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Twenty-four kohanic gifts ==

In [[Torah Laws|Torah law]], the positive [[mitzvah|commandment]] of a devoted thing is applied to the &quot;gifts of the priesthood&quot; (Hebrew מתנות כהונה ''matnat kehuna'') which entails giving &quot;devoted estate&quot; or &quot;devoted properties&quot; to a [[kohen]]. The gift of &quot;devoted things&quot; is listed as one of the [[twenty-four kohanic gifts]] and, of those twenty four, as one of ten gifts given to the priest even outside the [[land of Israel]] ([[Tosefta]] Challah 2:8, [[Talmud Bavli]] Hullin).

The nuances and complex specifics of the &quot;priestly gifts&quot; (''matnat kehuna'') and law on &quot;devoted things&quot; (''herem'') are deemed by [[Chazal]]{{who|date=November 2011}} as one of '''eight pillars of [[Torah Laws|Torah law]]''' that are &quot;principles of [[Halakha]]&quot;. See [[Tosefta]] to Hagigah 1:11 for a list of all eight.{{cn|date=November 2011}}

== Etymology ==

In [[Hebrew language]] the adjective ''herem'' (Hebrew חֵרֶם) means &quot;devoted thing&quot; or &quot;thing devoted to destruction&quot;. The term is used 29 times in the [[masoretic text]] of the Tanakh. An unrelated [[homonym]], the noun ''herem'' meaning &quot;fisherman's net&quot; (also חֵרֶם), is used a further 9 times.&lt;ref&gt;[[Brown Driver Briggs]] ''Hebrew Lexicon''&lt;/ref&gt; The adjective ''herem'' and the associate verb ''haram'' &quot;devote&quot; come from the [[semitic root]] [[Ḥ-R-M]] with cognates in the [[Syriac language]] and the [[Arabic language]].

The word &quot;devoted&quot; (''herem'') is understood by [[Maimonides]] as a &quot;complete and total transition&quot; from one status to another.&lt;ref&gt;''Rambam l'am, hilkhoth arakhin v'hromin'' chap. 6 note 2. [[Mossad Harav Kook]], Jerusalem &lt;/ref&gt; The [[Targum]]s define the word as a complete separation (Jerusalem Targum to Numbers 18:13, and [[Targum Yonathan]] to Isaiah 43:28). According to [[Samuel ben Meir]] this is the complete transition of an estate or object from ''hullin'' (mundane) status to that of ''kodesh'' (holy).&lt;ref&gt;[[Samuel ben Meir]] (c.1085–c.1158) ''Commentary on Numbers'' 21:2&lt;/ref&gt;

== Sources ==

The first of two sources of the commandment is stated in [[Leviticus]]:
{{quote|Notwithstanding no devoted thing, that a man shall devote unto the {{LORD}} of all that he hath, both of man and beast, and of the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed: every devoted thing [is] most holy unto the {{LORD}}.|Leviticus 27:28, [[KJV]]}}

The second source, unlike the first, explicitly instructs that the devoted thing be given to the priest;
{{quote|Every thing devoted in Israel shall be thine.|Numbers 18:14}}

In reconciling the two seemingly starkly differing instructions, [[Chazal]]{{Who|date=September 2011}} explained the two verses as detailing ''two'' types of devoted things; the former being &quot;hermei gavoah&quot; (devoted things specifically consecrated by its owner to the [[Temple in Jerusalem]]) whilst the latter as &quot;hermei kohanim&quot;, devoted things to be given the priest, as the estate or object was not designated by its owner to the [[Temple in Jerusalem]].

=== &quot;Devoted property&quot; in the territory of Joseph ===

Torah commentaries{{Who|date=September 2011}} to the verse &quot;And [[Eleazar]] the son of [[Aaron]] died and they buried him in at Givath the hill of [[Phinehas]] his son that was given to him in the mountain of [[Ephraim]] {Joshua 24:33) describe that the [[tribe of Joseph]] desired the merit that Eleazar the [[Kohen gadol|high priest]] should be buried in their territory. Thus, at the time of his demise designated Gibeah Phinehas (modern [[Awarta]]) as a ''herem'' estate; that is to be given the priests currently in duty as per the [[priestly divisions]]) and calculated to publicize the herem designation during the division cycle when Phinehas was in service, thus increasing the likelihood of Phinehas burying his father in the ''herem'' property, which ultimately happened ([[Meir Leibush ben Yehiel Michal]] on Joshua 24:33).

=== Sifre  ===

The [[Sifre]] (Hebrew סִפְרֵי ''siphrēy'', halakhic midrash to Numbers) attributes this particular priestly gift to the merit of [[Jochebed]] who deserved to be the mother of the priesthood, by mothering [[Aaron]], due to her rescuing the infants of Israel from the pharaonic decree of infanticide of Israelite newborns;

{{Quote|&quot;And ''Kotz'' gave birth to ''Onuv'' and to ''HaTzovevah'' and the families (of) ''Acharcheil'' the son of '''Harum''' (1 Chronicles 4:8); Ben (the son/child of) '''Herem'''&lt;ref&gt;Here the Mishna employs an [[exegesis]] on the name &quot;Harum&quot; by interchanging the Hebrew letter ה with a ח as they are both [[guttural]]ly produced&lt;/ref&gt; this is Jochebed as it is written &quot;''All '''herem''' in Israel to you will be (Numbers 18)''&quot;|Sifri to Numbers 10:29}}

=== Sifra ===

The [[Sifra]] (Aramaic: סִפְרָא ''siphra'', the Halakic midrash to Leviticus) describes the commandment to devote things as enabling the Israelite to do perform a commandment with objects that otherwise do not have a commandment attached to them. For example a non-kosher animal other than the firstborn of a donkey, by way of the Israelite making his possession thereof &quot;devoted&quot; (''herem''), he elevates it to &quot;holy&quot; (''[[kedushah]]'') (Sifra 42b as quoted in [[Midrash HaGadol]] to Leviticus 8:25).  [[Maimonides]], in his ''[[Mishneh Torah]],'' describes the act of creating a &quot;devoted&quot; estate a worthy act since it goes against the sin of [[miser]]hood. In addition, he also categorizes the initiation of devoted goods by an Israelite as an act of respect and honor to the [[God in Judaism|God of Israel]].&lt;ref&gt;Maimonides ''[[Mishneh Torah]], hilkhot arakhin v-hromim'' 8:12.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another quality describing the [[remedy]] of the devoted gift to the priest is described by the 14th Century ''[[Raya Mehemna]]'', a conversation between Moses and Elijah found as an addition to the [[Zohar]], as rectifying and healing the negative emotion of anger the initiator of a devotion of property may possess.&lt;ref&gt;''Raya mehemna'' 3 p. 179a&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Undesignated devoted things ===

Opinions differ as to the designation of undesignated devoted things (''stam herem'') {{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} in cases where the initiator of a devotion of property does not designate his property as consecrated to the [[temple in Jerusalem]] or the priests. Maimonides opines that this undesignated herem be given the priests by default. Maimonides further states that undesignated devoted property is considered mundane (''hullin'') and may be used by the priests for personal use. This is in contrast to the case where the person does designate his devoted property to be given the priests, where the said devoted property retains a holy (''kodesh'') state and cannot be itemized for personal use.&lt;ref&gt;Maimonides [[Mishneh Torah]], ''Hilkhot arakhin v-cheremin'' 6:1-4&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Dispension to the mishmaroth ===
{{Main|priestly divisions}}

An additional detail of allocation of devoted property is dependent on the type of object devoted; whether it is real estate or goods. According to ''rav'' [[Sheshet]], as cited in the Talmud, devotion of real estate is considered one of the four priestly gifts that is divided amongst the serving priestly division (''mishmar kehuna''), while tangible devoted goods are appropriated even to the individual priest not currently in active temple service ([[Jerusalem Talmud|Y]].[[Hallah (Talmud)|Hallah]] 27b).

== In modern times ==

The commandment to devote property, although practice infrequently today, still has [[halakha|halakhic]] implication in modern times:

=== In the diaspora ===

Considering that the gift of devoted property is listed as one of the ten priestly gifts that can be given to a priest outside of Jerusalem (similar to the [[Pidyon HaBen]] and the giving of the [[shoulder, cheeks and maw]]), some ''[[poskim]]'' have noted that both types of devoted things, both real estate and goods, are designated and given to the priest of the [[beth din]]'s choice.&lt;ref&gt;Mishneh Torah, ''Hilkhot arakhin v-hromin'' 8:11 (as per [[Ulla (Talmud)|Ulla]], quoted in Arakhin 29a)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Solomon Luria]] is of the opinion that the dedicator of devoted goods is required to specify that the property or items be given to a priest in order for a priest to be eligible as the recipient. In terms of the beth-din choosing an eligible kohen, Rabbi Luria opines that [[The status quo Kohen]] is sufficient to be the recipient of a devoted item and it to be &quot;mundane&quot; (''hullin'').&lt;ref&gt;(Hebrew) [[Solomon Luria]] on [[Bava Kamma]] end of minor chapter 35&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{The twenty-four kohanic gifts}}

[[Category:Priesthood (Judaism)]]
[[Category:Positive Mitzvoth]]

[[he:חרם (מתנות כהונה)]]</text>
      <sha1>iam023nn3u9ha0fx3x9rfga933nfy5q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
