<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hiram Abiff</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1998351</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520880020</id>
      <parentid>520827361</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-01T11:05:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fiddlersmouth</username>
        <id>16010066</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The Masonic Legend of Hiram Abiff */ Clarified &quot;Jurisdictions&quot; (which corrected my original error)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12108">{{Freemasonry2}}
'''Hiram Abiff''' (other spellings &quot;Huram&quot;,&lt;ref name=Huram&gt;&quot;Huram&quot; in the following translations: King James Version, American Standard Version, Bible in Basic English, Darby, Noah Webster, World English, Young's Literal. Source:[http://www.hebrewoldtestament.com/B14C002.htm#V13 http://www.hebrewoldtestament.com/B14C002.htm#V13]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Abif&quot;,&lt;ref name=HiramKey&gt;Lomas, Robert and Chris Knight. ''The Hiram Key.'' Arrow Books LTD, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://yorkrite.com/degrees/#2&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Huram-Abi&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Chronicles%202&amp;version=NIV&lt;/ref&gt; also known as &quot;the '''Widows's Son'''&quot;) is a character who figures prominently in an [[Allegory|allegorical]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Ritual&quot;&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Emulation Lodge Of Improvement
  | title = Emulation Ritual
  | publisher = Lewis Masonic
  | location = London
  |year=2007
  | isbn = 0-85318-244-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; play that is presented during the third [[Degree (freemasonry)|degree]] of Craft [[Freemasonry]]. In this play, Hiram is presented as being the chief [[architect]] of [[Solomon's Temple|King Solomon's Temple]], who is murdered by three ruffians during an unsuccessful attempt to force him to divulge the Master Masons' secret password.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Pritchard, &quot;Masonry Dissected&quot; (1730), in D. Knoop, G.P. Jones &amp; D. Hamer, ''The Early Masonic Catechisms'', Manchester University Press, 1963.&lt;/ref&gt; It is explained in the lecture that follows this play that the story is a lesson in fidelity to one's word, and in the brevity of life.

Numerous scholars, both Masonic and non-Masonic, have speculated that the character may have been based upon one or more Hirams that appear in the [[Bible]].&lt;ref&gt;*[http://www.oztorah.com/2010/01/hiram-abiff-the-ever-dying-gods/ Hiram Abiff and the ever-dying gods] - Discovery Lodge of Research, Sydney&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Masonic Legend of Hiram Abiff==

The tale of Hiram Abiff as passed down in Masonic Lodges underpins the third degree. It starts with his arrival in Jerusalem, and his appointment by Solomon as chief architect and master of works at the construction of his temple. As the temple is nearing completion, three fellowcraft masons from the workforce ambush him as he is alone in the building, demanding the secrets of a master mason. Hiram is challenged by each in turn, and at each refusal to divulge the information his assailant strikes him with a mason's tool (differing between jurisdictions). He is injured thus at the South and North entrances (leading to the ante-rooms in the wooden construction surrounding the temple proper), and finally at the main entrance in the East he is struck dead.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freemasons-freemasonry.com/legend_hiram_abif.html Pietre Stones] Kent Henderson, The Legend of Hiram Abif, retrieved 14th September 2012&lt;/ref&gt; His murderers hide his body under a pile of rubble, returning at night to move the body outside the city, where they bury it in a shallow grave marked with a sprig of acacia. As the Master is missed the next day, Solomon sends out a group of fellowcraft masons to search for him. The loose acacia is accidentally discovered, and the body exhumed to be given a decent burial. The hiding place of the &quot;three ruffians&quot; is also discovered, and they are brought to justice. Solomon informs his workforce that the secrets of a master mason are now lost, and replaces them with the gestures and ejaculations of the masons who discovered his body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/mas/morgan/morg14.htm William Morgan, Illustrations of Freemasonry, 1827] Second section of Master Mason lecture, retrieved 14th September 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Such is the general legend as related in the Anglo-American jurisdictions.

In [[Continental Freemasonry]] the tale is slightly different: a large number of master masons (not just Hiram) are working on the Temple, and the three ruffians are seeking the passwords and signs that will give them a higher wage. The result is the same, but this time it is master masons who find the body. The secrets are not lost, but Solomon orders them buried under the Temple, inscribed on Hiram's grave, and the same substitution is made as a mark of respect. The secrets &quot;lost&quot; in the other tradition are here given to new master masons as part of their ritual. In this version, Hiram is often renamed Adoniram.&lt;ref&gt;[http://reunir.free.fr/fm/rituels.htm Rituels] French language collection of ritual, 18th-early 19th century, retrieved 14th September 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

== Hirams in the Bible ==

There are three separate references to people named Hiram that were involved in the construction of the temple of Solomon:

* [[Hiram I|Hiram]], King of [[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]], is credited in [[Books of Samuel|2 Samuel]] 5:11 and 1 Kings 5:1-10 for having sent building materials and men for the original construction of the Temple in Jerusalem. In the Masonic drama,  &quot;Hiram, King of Tyre&quot; is clearly distinguished from &quot;Hiram Abiff&quot;. The former is clearly a king and the latter clearly a master craftsman. They can be confused in other contexts.&lt;ref&gt;1 Kings 5 &amp; 7:13-46 http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Kings%205,7:13-46&amp;version=NIV and 2 Chronicles 2:1-14 &amp; 4:11-16 http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Chronicles%202:1-14,4:11-16&amp;version=NIV&lt;/ref&gt;

*In [[1 Kings]] 7:13–14, Hiram is described as the son of a widow from the tribe of [[Naphtali]] who was the son of a Tyrian bronze worker, sent for by Solomon to cast the bronze furnishings and ornate decorations for the new temple. From this reference, Freemasons often refer to Hiram (with the added Abiff) as &quot;the widow's son.&quot; Hiram cast these bronzes in clay ground in the plain of the Jordan between [[Sukkot (place)|Succoth]] and [[Zaretan|Zarethan/Zeredathah]] (1 Kings 7:46-47).

* [[Books of Chronicles|2 Chronicles]] 2:13-14 relates a formal request from King Solomon of Jerusalem to King Hiram I of Tyre, for workers and for materials to build a new temple. King Hiram (Huram in Chronicles) responds &quot;And now I have sent a skillful man, endowed with understanding, ''Ḥuram 'abi.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hebrewoldtestament.com/B14C002.htm#V13 http://www.hebrewoldtestament.com/B14C002.htm#V13]&lt;/ref&gt; (the son of a woman of the daughters of Dan, and his father was a man of Tyre), skilled to work in gold and silver, bronze and iron, stone and wood, purple and blue, fine linen and crimson, and to make any engraving and to accomplish any plan which may be given to him, with your skillful men and with the skillful men of my lord David your father.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;2 Chronicles 2:13-14, New King James Version - From [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?book_id=14&amp;chapter=2&amp;version=50 BibleGateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase italicised above is translated in the [[New King James Version]] as &quot;Huram my master craftsman&quot;. Most translations of this passage take the &quot;'ab-&quot; in &quot;'abi&quot; as the construct state of 'abba, here translated as master. Older translations preferred to translate &quot;'ab-&quot; as father. The common translation of the -i suffix is &quot;my&quot;, giving the problematic reading that Hiram was sending his own father, also called Hiram. This is found in the [[Vulgate]], the [[Douay–Rheims Bible]] and in [[Wycliffe's Bible]].&lt;ref name=&quot;studylight.org&quot;&gt;http://www.studylight.org/desk/?l=en&amp;query=2+Chronicles+2&amp;section=0&amp;translation=vul&amp;oq=2ch%25202&amp;new=1&amp;nb=2ch&amp;ngt=Go+To%3A&amp;ng=2&amp;ncc=2&lt;/ref&gt; The other reading is as the old Hebrew genitive, and some variant of &quot;of my father&quot; is found in the [[Septuagint]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ecmarsh.com/lxx/Chronicles%20II/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Bishop's Bible]] and the [[Geneva Bible]].&lt;ref name=&quot;studylight.org&quot;/&gt; In his 1723 &quot;Constitutions&quot;, [[James Anderson]] announced that many problems with this text would be solved by reading &quot;'abi&quot; as the second part of a proper name, which he rendered as &quot;Hiram Abif&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Anderson&quot;&gt;[http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/libraryscience/25/ Anderson's 1723 Constitutions, in Franklin's 1734 reprint] retrieved 14th September 2012&lt;/ref&gt; agreeing with the translations of [[Martin Luther]]&lt;ref&gt;http://lutherbibel.net/&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Miles Coverdale|Miles Coverdale's]] reading of 2 Chronicles 4:16.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.studylight.org/desk/?l=en&amp;query=2+Chronicles+3&amp;section=0&amp;translation=mcb&amp;oq=2ch%25203&amp;new=1&amp;nb=2ch&amp;ng=3&amp;nnc=%A0%3E%3E%A0&amp;ncc=3 Coverdale Bible] 2 Chronicles 4:16, retrieved 20th September 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other accounts of a Biblical Hiram ==

[[Josephus|Flavius Josephus]] in his [[Antiquities of the Jews]] (Chapter 8:76) refers to Hiram as τεχνίτης, artificer, craftsman. &quot;Now Solomon sent for an artificer out of Tyre, whose name was Hiram: he was by birth of the tribe of [[Naphtali]], on his mother's side (for she was of that tribe); but his father was Ur, of the stock of the Israelites.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/jud/josephus/ant-8.htm Sacred Texts] Flavius Josephus, Antiquities of the Jews, Book VIII (in this version chapter 3 para 4 contains v76) retrieved 20th September 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

The most elaborate version of the legend occurs in [[Gérard de Nerval|Gérard de Nerval's]] 1851 account, [[Voyage to the Orient|Voyage en Orient]], where he relates the tale, inserting all the masonic passwords, as part of the story of the Queen of the Morning and &quot;Soliman&quot;, Prince of the Genii. This is an elaboration of the second version above, where the Master Craftsman is named Adoniram. Before his death, he undergoes mystical adventures as his tale is interwoven with that of Solomon and Balkis, the Queen of Sheba. The ruffians who kill him are under the instruction of Solomon himself. De Nerval relates the story as having been told in an Eastern coffee house over a two week period.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.org/details/womenofcairoscen011741mbp The Women Of Cairo, Scenes Of Life In The Orient, Volume Two] English translation of Gerard de Nerval, Voyage en Orient (1851), Harcourt, Brace &amp; Co, New York, 1930, pp244-380&lt;/ref&gt; A similar account is given in Heckethorn's &quot;The Secret Societies of all Ages and Countries&quot;, where Solomon plots to destroy Hiram because of the mutual love between Hiram and the Queen of Sheba.&lt;ref&gt;Charles William Heckethorn, The Secret Societies of all Ages and Countries, London, 1897, Vol ii, pp3-7&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other theories ==

According to authors [[Robert Lomas]] and [[Christopher Knight (author)|Christopher Knight]], Hiram Abiff would have been Egyptian king [[Seqenenre Tao II]], who met an extremely similar death.&lt;ref name=HiramKey/&gt;  This idea is dismissed by most Masonic scholars.

In his book The Sufis, the Afghan scholar Idries Shah suggested that [[Dhul-Nun al-Misri]] might have been the origin of the character Hiram Abiff in the Freemasonic Master Mason ritual. The link, he believes, was through the Sufi sect Al-Banna (&quot;The Builders&quot;) who built the Al-Aqsa Mosque and the Dome of the Rock in Jerusalem. This fraternity could have influenced some early masonic guilds which borrowed heavily from the Oriental architecture in the creation of the Gothic style.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Shah|first=Idries|title=The Sufis|year=1971|publisher=Anchor|isbn=0-385-07966-4|page=187}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== Additional references ==
* {{Cite book
  | last = de Hoyos
  | first = Arturo
  | last2 = Morris
  | first2 = S. Brent
  | title = Freemasonry in Context: History, Ritual, Controversy
  | publisher = Lexington Books
  | year = 2004
  | location = Lanham, Md.
  | isbn = 0-7391-0781-X}}

*{{cite book
  | last = Strong
  | first = James
  | title = Strong's Exhaustive Concordance of the Bible
  | publisher = Thomas Nelson Publishers
  |year=1990
  | isbn = 0-8407-6750-1}}

* Domenico V. Ripa Montesano, Vademecum di Loggia, Edizione Gran Loggia Phoenix&amp;nbsp;– Roma Italia 2009 ISBN 978-88-905059-0-4

[[Category:Masonic symbolism]]

[[ar:حيرام أبي]]
[[az:Hiram Usta]]
[[bg:Хирам Абиф]]
[[de:Hiram Abif]]
[[el:Χιράμ-αβίβ]]
[[es:Hiram Abif]]
[[fr:Hiram (artisan)]]
[[it:Hiram Abif]]
[[he:חירם ממטה נפתלי]]
[[pl:Hiram Abiff]]
[[pt:Hiram Abiff]]
[[ru:Хирам Абифф]]
[[sh:Hiram Abif]]
[[sv:Hiram Abif]]</text>
      <sha1>9xk4b750ehh52hjmunho4435nlrjrs4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
