<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Holy Synod</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>847622</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515205252</id>
      <parentid>505717528</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-29T20:32:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Merovingian</username>
        <id>29986</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* The Coptic Holy Synod */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8406">[[File:Highest authority of Russian Orthodox Church in 1917.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The Most Holy Governing Synod, highest authority of the Russian Orthodox Church in 1917, immediately after the election of the new patriarch.]]
In several of the [[autocephaly|autocephalous]] [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox]] churches and [[Eastern Catholic Churches]], the patriarch or head bishop is elected by a group of bishops called the '''Holy [[Synod]]'''. For instance, the Holy Synod is a ruling body of the [[Georgian Orthodox and Apostolic Church]].

In [[Oriental Orthodoxy]] the Holy Synod is the highest authority in the church&lt;ref name=&quot;Caselaw&quot;&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/nycodes/c103/a32.html Caselaw]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=March 2012}} and it formulates the rules and regulations regarding matters of church organisation, faith, and order of service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Document&quot;&gt;[http://lis.njleg.state.nj.us/cgi-bin/om_isapi.dll?clientID=136664&amp;depth=2&amp;hitsperheading=on&amp;infobase=statutes.nfo&amp;record={521C}&amp;softpage=Document42 Document&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=March 2012}}

==Early synods==
[[Image:Holy Synod Palace - Sofia .jpg|thumb|250px|left|Building of the Holy Synod of the Bulgarian Orthodox Church in Sofia]]
The principle of summoning a [[synod]] or council of ecclesiastical persons to discuss some grave question affecting the Church goes back, of course, to the very beginning of her history. Since the day when the [[Apostles]] met at [[Jerusalem]] to settle whether Gentile converts were to keep the Old Law ([[Acts of the Apostles|Acts]] 15:6&amp;ndash;29), it had been the custom to call together such gatherings as occasion required. Bishops summoned synods of their [[clergy]], [[Metropolitan bishop|metropolitan]]s and [[patriarch]]s summoned their suffragans, and then since 325 there was a succession of those greatest synods, representing the whole [[Catholic]] world, that are known as general councils.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07428a.htm|title=Holy Synod|work=[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Russian Holy Synod==
{{main|Most Holy Synod}}
[[File:Б.здание Святейшего Правительствующего Синода с церковью Семи Вселенских соборов.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Governing Senate|Senate]] and [[Most Holy Synod|Synod]] Building on [[Senate Square (Saint Petersburg)|Senate Square]], [[Saint Petersburg]]]]
The '''Most Holy Synod''' or '''Most Holy Governing Synod''' (Святейший Правительствующий Синод) was a congregation of [[Russian Orthodox Church|Orthodox church]] leaders in [[Russia]]. It was established by [[Peter I of Russia|Peter the Great]], [[Stefan Yavorsky]] and [[Feofan Prokopovich]] in January 1721 to replace the [[Patriarchate of Moscow]]. It was abolished following the [[February Revolution]] of 1917 and replaced with a restored [[patriarchate]] under [[Tikhon of Moscow]]. In modern Russia the [[Holy Synod of the Russian Orthodox Church]] is the highest governing body of the Russian Orthodox Church between [[Sobor]]s. It is headed by the [[Patriarch of Moscow and all the Rus']].

==The Greek Holy Synod==
The first other Orthodox Church to imitate the Russian Government by synod was that of [[Greece]]. The national assemblies of free Greece in 1822 and 1827 began the process of making their Church independent of the Patriarch of Constantinople. In 1833 the Greek Parliament formally rejected the patriarch's authority and set up a Holy Directing Synod in exact imitation of Russia. After much dispute the patriarch gave in and acknowledged the Greek synod, in 1850. Since then, the [[Church of Greece]] has been governed by a Holy Synod exactly as was the Church of Russia.

A law in 1852 regulated its rights and duties. It met at [[Athens]] under the presidency of the [[List of Archbishops of Athens|Metropolitan of Athens]]. Four other bishops were appointed by the Government as members for a year by vote. The members took an oath of fidelity to the king and government. Their deliberations were controlled by a royal commissioner, who was a layman chosen by government, just as the Russian oberprocuror. No act was valid without the commissioner's assent. There were also secretaries, writers, and a servant all appointed by the State. The Holy Synod was the highest authority in the Greek Church and had the same rights and duties as its Russian model, and was named in the liturgy instead of a patriarch.

After the proclamation of the Greek Republic in 1924, royal control of the Holy Synod naturally ceased, and with the elevation of the Metropolitan of Athens to an Archbishophric in 1932, the Archbishop began to be named in liturgies. Today, supreme authority is vested in the synod of all the diocesan bishops, who all have metropolitical status (the Hierarchy of the [[Church of Greece]]) under the presidency of the Archbishop of Athens and all Greece. This synod deals with general church questions. The Standing Synod is under the same presidency, and consists of the Primate and 12 bishops, each serving for one term on a rotating basis and deals with details of administration.

==Serbian Holy Synod==
The [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] is governed by a five-member Holy Synod. The patriarch is a permanent member, while the other four are bishops elected for two-year terms by the &quot;holy assembly of bishops&quot;, a body that represents all the metropolitans and other bishops of the church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1&amp;q=McGuckin+%22holy+assembly+of+bishops%22&amp;btnG= John Anthony McGuckin, ''Encyclopedia of Eastern Orthodox Christianity'' (John Wiley and Sons 2011 ISBN 9781405185394), vol. 1, p. 559]&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Coptic Holy Synod==
{{main|The Holy Synod of the Coptic Orthodox Church}}
The [[Holy Synod of the Coptic Orthodox Church]] of Alexandria is the highest authority in the [[Coptic Orthodox Church|Church of Alexandria]] &lt;ref name=&quot;Caselaw&quot;/&gt;{{Failed verification|date=March 2012}} and it formulates the rules and regulations regarding matters of church's organisation, faith, service's order.&lt;ref name=&quot;Document&quot;/&gt;{{Failed verification|date=March 2012}}  

The Synod is chaired by the [[Coptic Pope|Patriarch of Alexandria]] and the members are the Church's Metropolitans, Bishops, Chorbishops and the Patriarchal Vicar for Alexandria.

==Eastern Catholic Churches==
The [[Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches]] distinguishes between a patriarchal church's standing synod and a synod of its bishops. The standing synod consists of the patriarch and four bishops appointed for a five-year term. Of these four, three are elected by the patriarchal church's synod of bishops and one is appointed by the patriarch, while another four are designated in the same way to replace any member who is impeded.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19901018_codex-can-eccl-orient-1_lt.html#TITULUS_IV Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches, canon 115]&lt;/ref&gt; A synod of all the church's ordained bishops is called when a decision is required on a question that only it is authorized to decide, or when the patriarch, with the agreement of the standing synod, judges it to be necessary, or when at least one third of the bishops request that it be held to consider some specific matter. In addition, the canon law of some patriarchal churches requires that it be convoked at predetermined intervals.&lt;ref&gt;Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches, canon 106&lt;/ref&gt; Similar rules govern [[Eastern Catholic Churches]] headed not by a patriarch but by a major archbishop.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19901018_codex-can-eccl-orient-1_lt.html#TITULUS_V Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches, canon 152]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Caesaropapism]]
*[[Holy Synod of Jerusalem]]
*[[Holy Synod of Milan]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{catholic}}

[[Category:Eastern Orthodoxy]]
[[Category:Eastern Catholicism]]
[[Category:Ecclesiology]]
[[Category:Synods]]

[[bg:Свети синод]]
[[ca:Sant Sínode]]
[[de:Heiliger Synod]]
[[es:Sínodo Sagrado]]
[[fr:Saint Synode]]
[[hr:Sveti Sinod]]
[[hu:Szent Szinódus]]
[[it:Santo Sinodo]]
[[ja:聖シノド]]
[[no:Den hellige synode]]
[[ru:Священный синод]]
[[fi:Pyhä Synodi]]</text>
      <sha1>2eddrzc18lak1dep55e8xdkxl4oxlyp</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
