<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Holy See</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13393</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519964085</id>
      <parentid>519963839</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-26T15:35:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Alessandro57</username>
        <id>941995</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/CliffcCliffc|CliffcCliffc]] ([[User talk:CliffcCliffc|talk]]). ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23032">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
{{Roman Catholicism}}

The '''Holy See''' ({{lang-lat|Sancta Sedes}}, {{lang-it|Santa Sede}}) is the [[Diocese|episcopal jurisdiction]] of the [[Catholic Church]] in [[Rome]]. The [[Primacy of the Bishop of Rome|primacy]] of Rome makes its [[Bishop (Catholic Church)|bishop]] the worldwide leader of the church, commonly known as the [[Pope]]. Since Rome is the preeminent [[episcopal see]] of the Church, it contains the central government of the church, including various [[Dicastery|agencies]] essential to administration. Diplomatically, the Holy See acts and speaks for the whole [[Roman Catholic Church]]. It is also recognized by other subjects of international law as a [[Sovereignty|sovereign]] entity, headed by the Pope, with which [[diplomatic relations]] can be maintained.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Text taken directly from http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/europe/holy-see/ (viewed on 14 December 2011), on the website of the British Foreign &amp; Commonwealth Office.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Holy See's sovereignty has been recognized explicitly in many international agreements and is particularly emphasized in article 2 of the [[Lateran Treaty]] of 11 February 1929, in which &quot;Italy recognizes the sovereignty of the Holy See in the international field as an inherent attribute of its nature, in conformity with its tradition, and the requirements of its mission in the world.&lt;/ref&gt;

Often incorrectly referred to as &quot;the Vatican&quot;, the Holy See is not the same entity as the [[Vatican City]] State, which came into existence only in 1929; the Holy See, the [[Diocese of Rome|episcopal see of Rome]], dates back to early Christian times. Ambassadors are officially accredited not to the Vatican City State but to &quot;the Holy See&quot;, and papal representatives to states and international organizations are recognized as representing the Holy See, not the Vatican City State.

Though all [[episcopal see]]s may be considered &quot;holy&quot;, the expression &quot;the Holy See&quot; (without further specification) is normally used in international relations (and in the [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|canon law of the Roman Catholic Church]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG0017/_P19.HTM Code of Canon Law, canon 361], [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/LAT0758/_P7.HTM Code of Canons of the Eastern Churches, canon 48]&lt;/ref&gt; to refer to the See of Rome viewed as the central government of the Roman Catholic Church.

The British Foreign and Commonwealth Office speaks of Vatican City as the &quot;capital&quot; of the Holy See, although it compares the legal personality of the Holy See to that of [[the Crown]] in Christian monarchies and declares that the Holy See and the state of Vatican City are two international identities. It also distinguishes between the employees of the Holy See (2,750 working in the [[Roman Curia]] with another 333 working in the Holy See's diplomatic missions abroad) and the 1,909 employees of the state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/country-profile/europe/holy-see/ Foreign &amp; Commonwealth Office: Travel &amp; living abroad] Retrieved 8 January 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The British Ambassador to the Holy See uses more precise language, saying that the Holy See &quot;is not the same as the Vatican City State. … (It) is the universal government of the Catholic Church and ''operates from'' the Vatican City State.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sces.uk.com/articles/ambassadors-address-on-uk-holy-see-relations.html Ambassador's Address on UK-Holy See Relations] (emphasis added)&lt;/ref&gt; This agrees exactly with the expression used by the website of the United States Department of State, in giving information on both the Holy See and the Vatican City State: it too says that the Holy See &quot;operates from the Vatican City State&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3819.htm Background Note: Holy See]. State.gov (8 March 2011). Retrieved on 11 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organisation==
{{main|Roman Curia}}

The Pope governs the Catholic Church through the [[Roman Curia]]. The Roman Curia consists of a complex of offices that administer church affairs at the highest level, including the [[Secretariat of State (Vatican)|Secretariat of State]], nine [[Congregation (Roman Curia)|Congregations]], three [[Ecclesiastical court|Tribunals]], eleven Pontifical Councils, and seven Pontifical Commissions. The Secretariat of State, under the Cardinal Secretary of State, directs and coordinates the Curia. The incumbent, Cardinal [[Tarcisio Bertone]], is the See's equivalent of a prime minister. Archbishop [[Dominique Mamberti]], Secretary of the Section for Relations with States of the Secretariat of State, acts as the Holy See's [[minister of foreign affairs]]. Bertone and Mamberti were named in their respective roles by [[Pope Benedict XVI]] in September 2006.

[[File:Vatican City OSM 20110615.png|left|thumb|Vatican City]]
The Secretariat of State is the only body of the Curia that is situated within Vatican City. The others are in buildings in different parts of Rome that have extraterritorial rights similar to those of embassies.

Among the most active of the major Curial institutions are the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]], which oversees the Catholic Church's doctrine; the [[Congregation for Bishops]], which coordinates the appointment of bishops worldwide; the [[Congregation for the Evangelization of Peoples]], which oversees all missionary activities; and the [[Pontifical Council for Justice and Peace]], which deals with international peace and social issues.

Three tribunals exercise judicial power. The [[Roman Rota]] handles normal judicial appeals, the most numerous being those that concern alleged nullity of marriage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P5G.HTM Code of Canon Law, canons 1443–1444]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 11 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Apostolic Signatura]] is the supreme appellate and administrative court concerning decisions even of the Roman Rota and administrative decisions of ecclesiastical superiors (bishops and superiors of [[religious institute]]s), such as closing a parish or removing someone from office. It also oversees the work of other ecclesiastical tribunals at all levels.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P5G.HTM Code of Canon Law, canon 1445]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 11 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Apostolic Penitentiary]] deals not with external judgments or decrees, but with matters of conscience, granting absolutions from [[censure#Canon law|censures]], dispensations, commutations, validations, condonations, and other favours; it also grants [[indulgences]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19880628_pastor-bonus-roman-curia_en.html '&amp;#39;Pastor bonus'&amp;#39;, articles 117–120]. The Vatican. (28 June 1988). Retrieved on 11 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Prefecture for the Economic Affairs of the Holy See]] coordinates the finances of the Holy See departments and supervises the administration of all offices, whatever be their degree of autonomy, that manage these finances. The most important of these is the [[Administration of the Patrimony of the Apostolic See]].

The [[Prefecture of the Papal Household]] is responsible for the organization of the papal household, audiences, and ceremonies (apart from the strictly [[liturgical]] part).

The Holy See does not dissolve upon a Pope's death or resignation. It instead operates under a different set of laws ''[[sede vacante]]''. During this [[interregnum]], the heads of the [[dicasteries]] of the Roman Curia (such as the prefects of congregations) cease immediately to hold office, the only exceptions being the [[Major Penitentiary]], who continues his important role regarding absolutions and dispensations, and the [[Camerlengo of the Holy Roman Church]], who administers the [[temporalities]] (''i.e.'', properties and finances) of the See of St. Peter during this period. The government of the See, and therefore of the Catholic Church, then falls to the [[College of Cardinals]]. [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Canon law]] prohibits the College and the Camerlengo from introducing any innovations or novelties in the government of the Church during this period.

In 2001, the Holy See had a revenue of 422.098&amp;nbsp;billion [[Italian lire]] (about 202&amp;nbsp;million USD at the time), and a net income of 17.720&amp;nbsp;billion Italian lire (about 8&amp;nbsp;million USD).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zenit.org/article-1900?l=english &quot;Economic Report of the Holy See for 2000&quot;] Zenit 6 July 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

==Status in international law==
{{Main|Legal status of the Holy See}}
The Holy See has been recognised, both in state practise and in the writing of modern legal scholars, as a subject of [[public international law]], with rights and duties analogous to those of [[Sovereign state|States]]. Although the Holy See, as distinct from the Vatican City State, does not fulfil the long-established criteria in international law of [[Sovereign state|statehood]]—having a permanent population, a defined territory, a stable government and the capacity to enter into relations with other states&lt;ref&gt;These criteria for statehood were first authoritatively enunciated at the [[Montevideo Convention]] on Rights and Duties of States, signed by American states on 26 December 1933.&lt;/ref&gt;—its possession of full legal personality in [[international law]] is shown by the fact that it maintains diplomatic relations with 179&lt;ref name=DipRel&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/secretariat_state/documents/rc_seg-st_20010123_holy-see-relations_en.html situation since 27 July 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; states, that it is a ''member-state'' {{citation needed|date=September 2012}} in various intergovernmental international organizations, and that it is: &quot;respected by the international community of sovereign States and treated as a subject of international law having the capacity to engage in diplomatic relations and to enter into binding agreements with one, several, or many states under international law that are largely geared to establish and preserving peace in the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Araujo (Jurist)|Robert Araujo]] and John Lucal, Papal Diplomacy and the Quest for Peace, the Vatican and International Organizations from the early years to the League of Nations, Sapienza Press (2004), ISBN 1-932589-01-5, p. 16. ''See also'' James Crawford, The Creation of States in International Law, (1979) p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Diplomacy==
{{main|Foreign relations of the Holy See}}
{{further|Diplomatic missions of the Holy See|Holy See and the United Nations|Multilateral foreign policy of the Holy See}}
[[Image:Vatican relations.svg|thumb|500px|Foreign relations with the Holy See. {{legend|#007f00|Diplomatic relations}}
{{legend|#00ff00|Other relations}}
{{legend|#Dcc|No relations}}]]

Since medieval times the episcopal see of Rome has been recognized as a [[sovereignty|sovereign]] entity. The Holy See (not the State of Vatican City) maintains formal diplomatic relations with 179 sovereign states,&lt;ref name=DipRel/&gt; and also with the [[European Union]], and the [[Sovereign Military Order of Malta]], as well as having relations of a special character with the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]];&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/news_services/press/documentazione/documents/corpo-diplomatico_index_en.html#top Bilateral and Multilateral Relations of the Holy See]. The Vatican. (31 May 2007). Retrieved on 11 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zenit.org/article-34102?l=english|title=179 states have full diplomatic relations with the Holy See|publisher=[[Zenit News Agency]]|date=11 January 2012|accessdate=20 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 69 of the diplomatic missions accredited to the Holy See are situated in Rome. The Holy See maintains 180 permanent diplomatic missions abroad, of which 74 are non-residential, so that many of its 106 concrete missions are accredited to two or more countries or international organizations. The diplomatic activities of the Holy See are directed by the [[Secretariat of State (Vatican)|Secretariat of State]] (headed by the [[Cardinal Secretary of State]]), through the Section for Relations with States. There are 15 internationally recognized states with which the Holy See does not have relations.&lt;ref&gt;Afghanistan, Bhutan, Brunei, Comoros, Laos, [[the Maldives]], Mauritania, [[Myanmar]], North Korea, Oman, the People's Republic of China, Saudi Arabia, Somalia, Tuvalu and Vietnam. See: {{cite news|url=http://chiesa.espresso.repubblica.it/articolo/162301?eng=y|title=Mission Impossible: Eject the Holy See from the United Nations|work=chiesa:News, analysis, and documents on the Catholic Church, by Sandro Magister|date=21 August 2007|accessdate=3 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Holy See is the only European [[subject of international law]] that has official diplomatic relations with the Republic of China (Taiwan).

The Holy See is a member of various [[International organizations]] and groups including the [[International Atomic Energy Agency]] (IAEA), [[International Telecommunication Union]], the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] (OSCE), the [[Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons]] (OPCW) and the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]] (UNHCR). The Holy See is also a permanent [[observer status|observer]] in various international organizations, including the [[United Nations General Assembly]], the [[Council of Europe]], [[UNESCO]] (United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization), the [[World Trade Organization]] (WTO), and the [[Food and Agriculture Organization]] (FAO).

==Military and police==

Though, like various European powers, earlier Popes recruited Swiss mercenaries as part of an army, the Pontifical Swiss Guard was founded by Pope Julius II on 22 January 1506 as the personal bodyguard of the Pope and continues to fulfil that function. It is listed in the Annuario Pontificio under &quot;Holy See&quot;, not under &quot;State of Vatican City&quot;. At the end of 2005, the Guard had 134 members. Recruitment is arranged by a special agreement between the Holy See and Switzerland. All recruits must be Catholic, unmarried males with Swiss citizenship who have completed their basic training with the Swiss Army with certificates of good conduct, be between the ages of 19 and 30, and be at least 175&amp;nbsp;cm (5&amp;nbsp;ft 9 in) in height. Members are armed with small arms and the traditional halberd (also called the Swiss voulge), and trained in bodyguarding tactics.

*:''See: [[Vatican City#Military and police]]'' for more on this subtopic

==Relationship with the Vatican City and other territories==
The Holy See participates as an observer in [[African Union|AU]], [[Arab League]], [[Council of Europe]], [[Organization of American States|OAS]], [[International Organization for Migration|IOM]], and in the [[UN]] and its agencies [[FAO]], [[ILO]], [[UNCTAD]], [[UNEP]], [[UNESCO]], [[UN-HABITAT]], [[UNHCR]], [[United Nations Industrial Development Organization|UNIDO]], [[World Tourism Organization|UNWTO]], [[WFP]], [[WHO]], [[WIPO]]. It participates as a guest in [[Non-Aligned Movement|NAM]], and as a full member in [[IAEA]], [[OPCW]], [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe|OSCE]].

Although the Holy See is closely associated with the Vatican City, the independent territory over which the Holy See is [[Sovereignty|sovereign]], the two entities are separate and distinct. After the Italian takeover of the [[Papal States]] in 1870, the Holy See had no territorial sovereignty. In spite of some uncertainty among [[jurist]]s as to whether it could continue to act as an independent personality in international matters, the Holy See continued in fact to exercise the right to send and receive diplomatic representatives, maintaining relations with states that included the major powers of Russia, [[Prussia]] and [[Austria-Hungary]]. Where, in accordance with the decision of the 1815 [[Congress of Vienna]], the [[Nuncio]] was not only a member of the Diplomatic Corps but its Dean, this arrangement continued to be accepted by the other ambassadors. In the course of the 59 years during which the Holy See held no territorial sovereignty, the number of states that had diplomatic relations with it, which had been reduced to 16, actually increased to 29.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.30giorni.it/it/articolo.asp?id=10264 Lecture by Archbishop Giovanni Lajolo, 16 February 2006]. 30giorni.it. Retrieved on 11 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The State of the Vatican City was created by the [[Lateran Treaty]] in 1929 to &quot;ensure the absolute and visible independence of the Holy See&quot; and &quot;to guarantee to it an indisputable sovereignty in international affairs&quot; (quotations from the treaty). Archbishop [[Jean-Louis Tauran]], the Holy See's former Secretary for Relations with States, said that the Vatican City is a &quot;minuscule support-state that guarantees the spiritual freedom of the Pope with the minimum territory&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/secretariat_state/documents/rc_seg-st_doc_20020422_tauran_en.html Lecture by Archbishop Jean-Louis Tauran, 22 April 2002]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 11 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Holy See, not the Vatican City, maintains diplomatic relations with states.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/secretariat_state/documents/rc_seg-st_20010123_holy-see-relations_en.html Bilateral and Multilateral Relations of the Holy See]. Vatican.va. Retrieved on 11 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Foreign [[embassy|embassies]] are accredited to the Holy See, not to the Vatican City, and it is the Holy See that establishes [[treaty|treaties]] and [[concordat]]s with other sovereign entities. When necessary, the Holy See will enter a treaty on behalf of the Vatican City.

Under the terms of the Lateran Treaty, the Holy See has [[extraterritorial|extraterritorial authority]] over [[Properties of the Holy See|23 sites in Rome and five Italian sites outside of Rome]], including the Pontifical Palace at [[Castel Gandolfo]]. The same authority is extended under [[international law]] over the [[Apostolic Nunciature]] of the Holy See in a foreign country.

{{multiple image | width = 100 | footer = &lt;center&gt;Coats of arms of the Holy See and Vatican City&lt;/center&gt; | align = right | image1 = Holysee-arms-A.svg | alt1 = | caption1 = The Holy See | image2 = Coat of arms of the Vatican City.svg | alt2 = | caption2 = Vatican City State }}
==Coat of arms==
As indicated in [[Coats of arms of the Holy See and Vatican City]], the difference between the two coats of arms is that the arms of the Holy See have the gold key in [[bend (heraldry)|bend]] and the silver key in [[bend sinister]] (as also in the [[sede vacante]] coat of arms and in the external ornaments of the [[papal coats of arms]] of individual popes), while the reversed arrangement of the keys was chosen for the arms of the newly founded Vatican City State in 1929.

==&quot;Holy See&quot; and &quot;Apostolic See&quot;==
Every [[episcopal see]] is considered holy. In Greek, the adjective &quot;holy&quot; or &quot;sacred&quot; ({{lang|grc|ἱερά}}) is constantly applied to all such sees as a matter of course. In the West, the adjective is not commonly added, but it does form part of an official title of two sees: as well as Rome, the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Mainz|Bishopric of Mainz]] (the former [[Archbishopric of Mainz]]), which was also of [[prince-elector|electoral]] and [[primate (religion)|primatial]] rank, bears the title of &quot;the Holy See of Mainz&quot; (Latin: ''Sancta Sedes Moguntina'').

The term &quot;see&quot; comes from the Latin word &quot;sedes&quot;, meaning &quot;seat&quot;, which refers to the Episcopal throne ([[cathedra]]). The term &quot;[[Apostolic See]]&quot; can refer to any see founded by one of the [[Twelve Apostles|Apostles]], but, when used with the definite article, it is used in the Catholic Church to refer specifically to the see of the Bishop of Rome, whom that Church sees as successor of [[Saint Peter]], the Prince  of the [[Apostle (Christian)|Apostles]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11744a.htm] St. Peter, Prince of the Apostles&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Diocese of Rome]]
* [[Global organisation of the Catholic Church]]
* [[Holy Roman Church]]
* [[Patriarchate]]
* [[The Vatican Today News Portal]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* La Due, William J. ''The Chair of Saint Peter: A History of the Papacy''. (ISBN 1-57075-249-4)
* Heribert Franz Koeck, Die völkerrechtliche Stellung des Heiligen Stuhls. Dargestellt an seinen Beziehungen zu Staaten und internationalen Organisationen, Berlin 1975
* Heribert Franz Koeck, Holy See, in: Encyclopedia of Public International Law, Bd. 2, Oxford etc. 1995

==External links==
{{Commons category|Holy See}}
* [http://www.vatican.va/ The Holy See]
* [http://www.news.va/ The Holy See News Portal (News.va)]
* [http://www.youtube.com/vatican YouTube Vatican Channel]
* [http://www.cin.org/users/jgallegos/primacy.htm Primacy of the Apostolic See]
* [https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/vt.html CIA World Factbook on Holy See]
* [http://www.chiesa.espressonline.it/dettaglio.jsp?id=43322&amp;eng=y Between Venus and Mars, the Church of Rome Chooses Both]—The Holy See’s geopolitics analyzed in the light of the dominant doctrines
* [http://www.ellopos.net/politics/papacy.html The Holy See in the course of time, from an Orthodox perspective]

&lt;!-- sp --&gt;

{{Vatican City topics}}
{{Foreign relations of the Holy See}}
{{Papal symbols and ceremonial}}
{{Foreign relations of Europe}}
{{Latinunion}}
{{Catholicism}}

[[Category:Apostolic sees]]
[[Category:Holy See| ]]
[[Category:Canon law (Catholic Church)]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:United Nations General Assembly observers]]

[[ar:الكرسي الرسولي]]
[[an:Santa Seu]]
[[bs:Sveta Stolica]]
[[bg:Светият престол]]
[[ca:Seu Apostòlica]]
[[cv:Таса астул]]
[[ceb:Balaang Sede]]
[[cs:Svatý stolec]]
[[da:Den Hellige Stol]]
[[de:Heiliger Stuhl]]
[[et:Püha Tool]]
[[es:Santa Sede]]
[[eo:Apostola Seĝo]]
[[eu:Egoitza Santua]]
[[fa:سریر مقدس]]
[[fr:Saint-Siège]]
[[gl:Santa Sé]]
[[ko:성좌 (가톨릭)]]
[[hr:Sveta Stolica]]
[[id:Tahta Suci]]
[[ia:Sancte Sede]]
[[is:Páfastóll]]
[[it:Santa Sede]]
[[he:הכס הקדוש]]
[[jv:Takhta Suci]]
[[ka:წმინდა ეპარქია]]
[[sw:Ukulu mtakatifu]]
[[la:Sancta Sedes]]
[[hu:Vatikán#A Szentszék]]
[[mt:Santa Sede]]
[[arz:الكرسى البابوى]]
[[nl:Heilige Stoel]]
[[ja:聖座]]
[[no:Den hellige stol]]
[[pl:Stolica Apostolska]]
[[pt:Santa Sé]]
[[ro:Sfântul Scaun]]
[[ru:Святой Престол]]
[[si:ශුද්ධාසනය]]
[[simple:Holy See]]
[[sk:Svätá stolica]]
[[sl:Sveti sedež]]
[[sr:Света столица]]
[[fi:Pyhä istuin]]
[[sv:Heliga stolen]]
[[tl:Santa Sede]]
[[th:สันตะสำนัก]]
[[tr:Kutsal Makam]]
[[uk:Святий Престол]]
[[vec:Santa Sede]]
[[vi:Tòa Thánh]]
[[zh:聖座]]</text>
      <sha1>disbb5ujhjs6j0sdaabyjsm36x1z3jx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
