<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Iconostasis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>188848</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516487831</id>
      <parentid>511789649</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-07T15:15:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Martarius</username>
        <id>4905985</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Gallery */ -us</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24494">{{Refimprove|date=December 2007}}
[[Image:Iconostasis in Moscow.jpg|thumb|right|Five-panel [[Deesis]] row (center), Iconostasis in the [[Cathedral of the Annunciation]] in [[Moscow Kremlin]] by [[Theophanes the Greek]], 1405]]
In [[Eastern Christianity]] an '''iconostasis''' (plural: '''iconostases''') is a wall of [[icon]]s and religious paintings, separating the [[nave]] from the [[sanctuary]] in a [[Church (building)|church]]. ''Iconostasis'' also refers to a portable icon stand that can be placed anywhere within a church. The iconostasis evolved from the [[Byzantine architecture|Byzantine]] [[templon]], a process complete by the fifteenth century.

A direct comparison for the function of the main iconostasis can be made to the layout of the great Temple in Jerusalem. That Temple was designed with three parts. The holiest and inner-most portion was that where the Ark of the Covenant was kept. This portion, the Holy of Holies, was separated from the second larger part of the building's interior by a curtain, the &quot;veil of the temple&quot;. Only priests were allowed to enter the Holy of Holies. The third part was the entrance court. This architectural tradition for the two main parts can be seen carried forward in Christian churches and is still most demonstratively present in Eastern Orthodox churches where the iconostatsis divides the altar, the Holy of Holies containing the concecrated Eucharist - the manifestation of the New Covenant, from the larger portion of the church accessible to the faithful. In the Eastern Orthodox tradition only men can enter the altar portion behind the iconostasis.

The word comes from the [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|εἰκονοστάσι(-ον)}} (''eikonostási(-on)'', still in common use in Greece and Cyprus), which means &quot;icon stand&quot;.

==Location==
[[Image:Cathedral Uglich inside 01.jpg|thumb|left|220px|A six-row iconostasis at [[Uglich]] Cathedral. North Deacon's Door (left) and [[Holy Doors]] (right).]]
The [[nave]] is the main body of the church where most of the worshippers stand, and the [[sanctuary]] is the area around the [[altar]], east of the nave. The sanctuary is usually one to three steps higher than the nave. The Iconostasis does not sit directly on the edge of the sanctuary, but is usually set a few feet back from the edge of the top step. This forms a walkway in front of the iconostasis for the clergy, called a [[soleas]]. In the very center of the soleas is an extension (or [[Thrust stage|thrust]]), often rounded, called the [[Ambon (liturgy)|ambon]], on which the deacon will stand to give [[Ektenia|litanies]] during the services.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}

The iconostasis, though often tall, rarely touches the ceiling.  [[acoustics|Acoustically]], this permits the [[ekphonesis|ekphoneses]] (liturgical exclamations) of the clergy to be heard clearly by the faithful. In small, modern churches the iconostasis may be completely absent: in such cases it is replaced by a few small icons on [[analogion|analogia]] (lecterns), forming a virtual divide.

[[Image:Ipatios monastery Kostroma 15.jpg|thumb|The south Deacon's Door in the iconostasis at [[Ipatiev Monastery]], [[Kostroma]], Russia.]]
[[File:Manastirea Predeal Biserica1.jpg|thumb|left|Example of monastic church with no South Door ([[Predeal]] Monastery, Romania).]]

The iconostasis typically has three openings or sets of doors: the ''[[Royal Doors|Beautiful Gates]]'' or ''Holy Doors'' in the center, and the North and South Doors to either side.  The Beautiful Gates are sometimes called the ''Royal Doors'', but that name more properly belongs to the central doors connecting the [[narthex]], or porch, to the [[nave]].&lt;ref&gt;So called because the [[Emperor#The Eastern Emperors after 476|Emperor]] used to enter by these doors during official ceremonies at [[Hagia Sophia]] in [[Constantinople]].&lt;/ref&gt; They remain shut whenever a service is not being held.  Modern custom as to when they should be opened during services varies depending upon jurisdiction and local custom.

The North and South Doors are often called ''Deacons' Doors'' because the [[deacon]]s use them frequently. Icons of sainted deacons are often depicted on these doors (particularly [[St. Stephen]] the [[Protomartyr]] and [[Ephrem the Syrian|St. Ephrem the Syrian]]).  Alternatively, they may be called ''Angels' Doors'', and the [[Archangel]]s [[Michael (archangel)|Michael]] and [[Gabriel]] are often depicted there.  The South Door is typically the &quot;entrance&quot; door, and Michael is depicted there because he is the &quot;Defender&quot;; the North Door is the &quot;exit&quot;, and Gabriel is depicted here because  he is the &quot;Messenger&quot; of God.  These doors may also be casually referred to as the &quot;side doors&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

There are some exceptions where both the side doors depict Archangel Michael. The most notable exception is of the church of Saint George (Aghios Georgios) inside the Ecumenical Patriarchate of Constantinople (in today's Istanbul).

In many [[monastery]] churches and chapels (though often not in the [[Katholikon]], the monastery's main church) one may find iconostases with only two doors: the Holy Doors and the North Door. These churches are used for simpler monastic observances when only a [[hieromonk]] would be serving alone. Since the priest seldom uses the South Door when he is serving the Divine Liturgy, the chapel can be made smaller by omitting that door.

==Placement of icons==
[[Image:Ipatios monastery Kostroma 13.jpg|thumb|Mid-17th-century iconostasis at [[Ipatiev Monastery]]. To either side of the [[Holy Doors]] are [[Christ Pantokrator]] and the [[Theotokos]]; above them, the [[Great Feasts]]; above them, the [[Deesis]]; above that [[Prophet]]s to either side of [[Our Lady of the Sign]]; above them the [[Twelve apostles|Apostles]] to either side of the [[Holy Trinity]].]]

A number of guidelines or [[rubric]]s govern which icons are on which parts of the iconostasis, although there is some room for variation. In its fullest Slavic development it comprised five tiers of icons:

#The bottom tier is sometimes called ''Sovereign''. On the right side of the Beautiful Gates (from the nave facing forward) is an icon of Christ (often ''[[Christ Pantocrator|Pantokrator]]''), which symbolizes his [[Second Coming]]{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} and on the left side is an icon of the [[Theotokos]] ([[Mary, the mother of Jesus|Virgin Mary]]), symbolizing Christ's incarnation, and entrance into this world{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}. Therefore, all things take place between Christ's first and second coming. Other icons on this tier beside those on the doors themselves usually include depictions of the [[patron saint]] or [[feast day]] to which the church is [[consecration|dedicated]], [[St. John the Baptist]], [[St. Nicholas]], one or more of the [[Four Evangelists]] etc. Above this are two interchangeable tiers: the ''[[Deisis]]'' and the ''[[Twelve Great Feasts]]'':
#In the center of the ''[[Deisis]]'' is a large icon of Christ Enthroned.  To the left and right are icons of John the Baptist and the Theotokos in attitudes of supplication. They are often flanked by icons of the Archangels [[Michael (archangel)|Michael]] and [[Gabriel]], then Sts. [[Saint Peter|Peter]] and [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]], and then any other important Church Fathers that may be desired for inclusion as space allows.
#The ''Feasts'' tier contains icons of the twelve [[Great Feasts]] of the [[liturgical year]]. Above this, the top two tiers are also interchangeable with each other:
#The [[Old Testament]] [[Prophet]]s and [[Patriarchs (Bible)|Patriarch]]s—the latter including the twelve sons of [[Jacob]]—often to either side of an icon of [[Our Lady of the Sign]]; and
#the [[Twelve Apostles]], often to either side of and icon depicting either Christ at the Second Coming or the [[Holy Trinity]]. {{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

Occasionally one may find yet more tiers of smaller icons depicting saints of specially fervent local devotion.

It is also not uncommon to find an icon of the ''[[Mystical Supper]]'', which depicts the Last Supper, and by extension the [[Communion of Saints]] in the [[Kingdom of God]], somewhere above the Beautiful Gates.

The Sovereign tier is always present, but all the others may be omitted. Preference is given to the Deisis or the Feasts tiers if only some of them can be included.  Only the largest and most elaborate iconostases include all five.

==Rubrics==
[[Image:Gorskii 03982u.jpg|thumb|Chapel of the holy icon of [[Theotokos of Smolensk]] in the [[Assumption Cathedral in Smolensk]].]] [[File:TSL15.jpg|thumb|A [[Moscow Baroque]] icon screen in the [[Trinity Lavra]] in Sergeyev Posad]] [[File:Vladimir Putin 7 January 2008-11.jpg|thumb|[[Vladimir Putin]] in front of a [[Baroque]] icon screen in [[Veliky Ustyug]]]]
There are rules regarding who may enter or leave the sanctuary (altar), and by which door. Neither the Beautiful Gates (Holy/Tsar doors - central doors)) nor the space between them and the altar table may be used by laity under any circumstances, although infants are either carried into the altar through them in the &quot;[[Churching of women|churching]]&quot; rite if they are boys, or if they are girls, the infant is simply presented at the doors.&lt;ref&gt;Metropolitan PHILIP &quot;Prayers at the Churching of a Mother and her Child&quot; in ''A Pocket Prayer Book for Orthodox Christians'' (Englewood, New Jersey: 1956) p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bishop]]s may enter through the Beautiful Gates at any time; [[priest]]s and deacons may do so only at specific times during the services when the Gates are open (but during [[Bright Week]] they always enter and exit through them).  All others enter the sanctuary through the side doors.

In a [[convent]] only the [[abbess]] and elder [[nuns]] are permitted to enter the sanctuary(altar), and only by the side doors. The abbess may enter at any time, but the other nuns need a blessing to enter.
[[File:Holy Trinity Russian Orthodox Church 071215.jpg|thumb|Iconostasis at Holy Trinity Cathedral (Chicago, Illinois)]]
Male members of the laity who are usually allowed to enter the sanctuary include those involved in the running of the particular church, i.e. [[Cantor (church)|cantor]]s and [[chorister]]s, [[altar server]]s/acolytes, [[Sexton (office)|church keeper]]s and [[vestryman|vestrymen]], etc. Entering the sanctuary for no good reason or without a blessing is forbidden even if no religious service is being held at the time.

In the [[Romanian Orthodox Church|Romanian tradition]], on the day of the [[consecration]] of the altar in the church, the laity, including women, are permitted to enter and venerate the altar up until the beginning of the [[Vespers]] of Consecration.

These guidelines were developed over the course of many centuries, with both theologically symbolic and practical reasons for them.

==Theological implications==
The Iconostasis does not really &quot;separate&quot; the nave from the Holy of Holies; rather, it brings them together.  The Iconostasis is the link between heaven (the Holy of Holies) and the nave (The Holy Place).  Therefore everything is symbolic upon the Iconostasis.  The Icons of Christ the Theotokos and various saints and feasts are there because Christ, the Theotokos, the saints etc., lead us and guide us into the Holy of Holies. Therefore the personages on the Icons upon the Iconostasis guide us into heaven, and therefore the Iconostasis connects not separates. The Icons upon the Iconostasis also are windows and bridges into heaven (although all icons, no matter where, are windows and bridges into heaven). Therefore, in a sense the Iconostasis represents Christ, who is the connection, the door, between both realms.  The perfect explanation for the Iconostasis, and its uniting purpose, is seen in Hebrews 10:19-20, ''&quot;Therefore, brethren, since we have confidence to enter the sanctuary by the blood of Jesus, by the new and living way which he opened for us through the curtain, that is through his flesh.&quot;''

==Evolution==
[[Image:Iconostasis in St. Andrew's Church.JPG|thumb|left|200px|The baroque three-tier iconostasis designed by Rastrelli. In [[Saint Andrew's Church of Kiev]], [[Ukraine]]]]

Archaeological evidence from the [[Stoudios|St. John of Stoudios]] monastery in Constantinople suggests that the Iconostasis evolved from the early [[templon]]. A [[basilica]] dedicated to [[John the Baptist]] was built in 463 AD. In it the [[chancel]] barrier surrounded the altar in a π shape, with one large door facing the nave and two smaller doors on the other sides. Twelve piers held chancel slabs of about 1.6 meters in length. The height of the slabs is not known. The chancel barrier was not merely a low [[parapet]] (a short wall); remains of colonnettes have been found, suggesting that the barrier carried an [[architrave]] on top of the columns.&lt;ref name=&quot;myref-9&quot;&gt;Matthews, Thomas F. ''The Early Churches of Constantinople: Architecture and Liturgy''. [[Pennsylvania State University Press]], PA, 1971, ISBN 0-271-00108-9&lt;/ref&gt;

In early churches, including the &quot;Great Church&quot; [[Hagia Sophia]] in [[Constantinople]], the altar, at least in large churches, was under a [[ciborium (architecture)|ciborium]] (&quot;ciborion&quot;: κιβωριου in Greek), usually a structure with four columns and a domed canopy.  This had curtains on rods on all four sides, which were closed for sections of the liturgy, as is still performed in the [[Coptic Church|Coptic]] and [[Armenia]]n churches.&lt;ref&gt;The Orthodox [[Armenian Apostolic Church]] and Catholic [[Armenian Catholic Church]];&lt;/ref&gt; a comparison with the biblical [[Kodesh Hakodashim|Veil of the Temple]] was intended.  The small domed structures, usually with red curtains, that are often shown near the writing saint in early [[Evangelist portrait]]s, especially in the East, represent a ciborium,&lt;ref&gt;Bock covers the use and decline of ciborium curtains in considerable detail, though he is an old source.&lt;/ref&gt; as do the structures surrounding many manuscript portraits of medieval rulers.&lt;ref&gt;Grove, 2.1&lt;/ref&gt; As the iconostasis grew, the ciborium declined, although some late examples, by now invisible to the congregation, were produced.  

The templon gradually replaced all other forms of chancel barriers in Byzantine churches in the 6th, 7th, and 8th centuries except in [[Cappadocia]]. [[Sacred tradition]] ascribes the invention of the solid iconostasis to Saint [[Basil the Great]].

As late as the 10th century, a simple wooden chancel barrier separated the apse from the nave in the [[The underground city and Monasteries of Derinkuyu|rock-cut churches]] in [[Derinkuyu]], though by the late 11th century, the templon had become standard.  This may have been because of the veneration and imitation of the Great Church Hagia Sophia in Constantinople, though the columnar form of chancel barrier does predate Hagia Sophia.&lt;ref name=&quot;myref-7&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last=Kostof| first= Spiro| title=Caves of God: The Monastic Environment of Byzantine Cappadocia| publisher= [[MIT Press]]| location= Cambridge, MA| year= 1972| isbn= 0-262-11042-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:FederovIcons.jpg|thumb|Fedorov's [[Deesis]], recently added to the retroquire screen at [[Winchester Cathedral]], England. The differently situated [[rood screen]]s of Western medieval churches often achieved an effect comparable to the iconostasis.]]

In recent years, especially in the diaspora, there has been a liturgical movement favouring a more open style of Iconostasis.  These Iconostases may be only one or two tiers, with a wide opening for the royal doors.

The [[rood screen]]s or [[pulpitum]]s that most [[Roman Catholic]] large churches and cathedrals in many parts of Europe had acquired by late medieval times occupied a similar position between chancel and nave but had a different function.  The choir was usually east of the screen. Many survive, often most completely in [[Scandinavia]], and more were built in the [[Gothic Revival]], particularly in [[Anglican]] churches in [[England]].  In examples in wood  painted panels typically only went up to about waist height, with a section with wooden tracery above allowing a view through, and then a large carved beam supporting a [[rood cross]] [[crucifix]], often life-size, above.  Larger churches had stone screens, which might impede virtually all view by the congregation.

==Oriental Christianity==
The [[Oriental Orthodox]] churches which follow non-Byzantine rites differ among themselves about the use of the iconostasis. The [[Armenian Apostolic Church|Armenian]] and [[Syriac Christianity|Syriac]] churches often use a curtain, but not a solid iconostasis. The [[Coptic Orthodox Church|Coptic]] and [[Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church|Ethiopian]] churches use an iconostasis often made of latticework, so that it is semi-transparent.

[[File:Алтарь нижнего храма Преображенского собора (Валаам).jpg|thumb|Sanctuary of [[Transfiguration of Jesus|Holy Transfiguration]] Cathedral, [[Valaam]] [[Monastery]].]]
The name in [[Greek language|Greek]] for the Sanctuary is '''Ἱερόν Βῆμα''' (''Hieron Vema'', see [[Bemah]]), in [[Russian language|Russian]] it is called '''Сватий Олтар''' (''Svatiy Oltar''), an in Romanian it is called ''Sfântul Altar''.

The [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] has received the [[Sacred Tradition|Tradition]] of the Holy of Holies in the Temple area.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} The [[Holy Table]] (altar) in an Orthodox church is in a restricted area behind the iconostasis (icon screen). The entire area behind the iconostasis is known as the &quot;[[Altar]]&quot; or the &quot;Holy Place&quot;, and corresponds directly to the Holy of Holies in the Jerusalem Temple.

The iconostasis is usually punctuated by three doors, the middle one being the [[Holy Doors]] or Royal Doors (sometimes, in very small chapels, there will only be one side door). There will also be a [[veil]] behind the Holy Doors, usually embroided with the symbol of the Cherubim or a cross. Only Orthodox clergy or those who have permission to do so may enter the holy space behind the iconostasis. Bishops, priests and deacons are allowed to enter the Royal Doors, but only at specific times during the services; and they alone may stand in front of the Holy Table, or touch it. All others are forbidden to touch the Holy Table and must walk round behind it when serving. At the [[churching of women|churching]] of Orthodox children when they are 40 days old, if a male child has been baptized he will be brought inside the Sanctuary by the priest; the female child is instead placed in front of the [[icon]] of the [[Theotokos]] on the iconostasis.

Anyone lower in rank than a deacon must receive a blessing from the priest before he enters the Holy Place. Historically the only exceptions to the rule of non clerical males being forbidden to stand before the Holy Table have been the Russian [[Tsar]]s on the day of their [[coronation]]. After his [[anointing]], the new Tsar would be escorted through the Holy Doors to a small table set near the Holy Table, and there he would be given [[Holy Communion]] by the [[Metropolitan of Moscow]] in the same manner as priests. For the most part, women are forbidden to enter the sanctuary, with the exception of elderly [[nun]]s who may be blessed to assist the priest during services, and an [[abbess]] in her own [[monastery]], who is free to enter at any time. No one, male or female, typically is allowed to enter the sanctuary without good reason.

==Gallery==

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Iconostasis detail.jpg| [[Modern]] [[Cossack Baroque]] Iconostasis detail at [[St. Joseph the Betrothed Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church]]
Image:Osiosloukas2.JPG|[[Hosios Loukas]] ([[Byzantine architecture|Middle Byzantine]]), [[Distomo]], in [[Boeotia]], [[Greece]]
Image:A church in Parga.jpg|[[Parga]], [[Greece]]
Image:Nikozja savvas3.jpg|Church of [[Sabbas the Sanctified|St. Sabbas]], [[Nicosia]], [[Cyprus]]
Image:07Thessaloniki Agia Sophia05.jpg|[[Hagia Sophia (Thessaloniki)|Hagia Sophia, Thessaloniki]]
Image:07Thessaloniki Metropolitan04.jpg|[[Marble]] iconostasis at the Metropolitan Cathedral of St. [[Gregory Palamas]], [[Thessaloniki]]
Image:07Thessaloniki Taxiarches02.jpg|Chapel of the [[Archangel]]s, Thessalonika
File:Greek Orthodox Catholicon in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre, Jerusalem.jpg|Iconostasis at the Catholicon, [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]] (tomb of Jesus), Jerusalem.
Image:Iconostasis in Yaroslavl.png|Church of the [[Prophet Elias]], [[Yaroslavl]]
Image:Astrakhan Maria-Ascension cathedral interior.jpg|[[Dormition Cathedral (disambiguation)|Dormition Cathedral]], [[Astrakhan]]
Image:IconostasisOfBulgarianRockChurch.jpg|Rock church, northern [[Bulgaria]]
Image:Moscow Archangel Michael Cathedral interior.jpg|[[Cathedral of the Archangel Michael]], [[Moscow Kremlin]]
Image:Russia-Moscow-Kremlin Museums Exhibitions-15.jpg|Portion of Iconostas displayed in the Kremlin Museums
File:Church of the Descent of the Holy Spirit upon the Apostles (Sergiev Posad) 21.jpg|A church in [[Troitse-Sergiyeva Lavra]]
Image:Russia-Moscow-Kremlin Museums Exhibitions-3.jpg|Kremlin Museums
Image:Icon 01013 Stavni kiota. Blagoveschenie. Svyatye i apostoly.jpg|[[Holy Doors]] depicting the [[Annunciation]], [[Twelve apostles|Apostles]] and [[Saint]]s
Image:Kings Gate of iconostasis.JPG|[[Troyan Monastery]], [[Bulgaria]]
Image:Sarajevo old-orthodox church 03.jpg|Old Orthodox Church, [[Sarajevo]]
Image:ProfessorAngelopoulos88.JPG|[[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], [[USA]]
Image:Ortodoxa kyrkan i Torneå 2007-06-04.jpg|[[Tornio]], [[Finland]]
Image:Śnietnica ikonostas.JPG|Śnietnica, [[Poland]] ([[Greek Catholic]])
Image:Iconostasis at Saint Mary's Russian Orthodox Church in McKeesport, PA.jpg|[[McKeesport, PA]]
Image:Sv stefan interior.jpg|[[Bulgarian St. Stephen Church]] in [[Istanbul]]
File:Saint Vladimir Skete (Valaam Monastery) 09.jpg|Saint Vladimir Skete ([[Valaam Monastery]]), Church of St. [[Saint Ludmila|Ludmila]]
File:InteriorofaChapel.jpg|An improvised iconostasis in St.Dimitrius Chapel on the beach of [[Olympiaki Akti]], [[Greece]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{Commons|Iconostasis}}

==See also==
*[[Ambon (liturgy)|Ambon]]
*[[Soleas]]
*[[Templon]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*[[Franz Johann Joseph Bock|Bock, Franz Johann Joseph]], ''The Hangings of the Ciborium of the Altar'' (translated section of his ''Organ fur Christliche Kunst''), The Ecclesiologist, Volume 26, 1868, Ecclesiological Society/Stevenson, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=oeZJAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA301&amp;dq=ciborium,+evangelist+portrait&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=s4GxTbUf0PWyBqzfseAM&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false google books]
*&quot;Grove&quot;, van Hemeldonck, G., &quot;Ciborium (ii).&quot; In [[Grove Art Online]]. Oxford Art Online, [http://www.oxfordartonline.com/subscriber/article/grove/art/T017726 subscription required], (accessed April 25, 2011).

{{Wikisource1911Enc|Iconostasis}}
Efhalia Rentetzi,'' Le iconostasi delle chiese greche in Italia'', http://www.apostoliki-diakonia.gr/index_it.asp, Athens 2008

==External links==
* [http://members.virtualtourist.com/m/p/m/25de83 Photo of early iconostasis. Church of the Aposltes, Athens] 1000 AD
* [http://liternet.bg/publish9/mkoeva/nasledstvo/ikonostas_en.htm The Bulgarian orthodox iconostasis]

[[Category:Architectural elements]]
[[Category:Church architecture]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodoxy]]
[[Category:Eastern Catholicism]]
[[Category:Oriental Orthodoxy]]
[[Category:Eastern Christian liturgy]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox icons]]

[[be:Іканастас]]
[[bg:Иконостас]]
[[bs:Ikonostas]]
[[ca:Iconòstasi]]
[[cs:Ikonostas]]
[[de:Ikonostase]]
[[el:Εικονοστάσιο (τέμπλο)]]
[[es:Iconostasio]]
[[eo:Ikonostazo]]
[[eu:Ikonostasi]]
[[fr:Iconostase]]
[[hr:Ikonostas]]
[[it:Iconostasi]]
[[he:איקונוסטאזיס]]
[[ka:კანკელი]]
[[la:Iconostasis]]
[[lt:Ikonostasas]]
[[hu:Ikonosztáz]]
[[ml:ഐക്കണോസ്റ്റാസിസ്]]
[[nl:Iconostase]]
[[ja:イコノスタシス]]
[[no:Ikonostasis]]
[[nn:Ikonostas]]
[[pl:Ikonostas]]
[[pt:Iconóstase]]
[[ro:Iconostas]]
[[rue:Іконостас]]
[[ru:Иконостас]]
[[simple:Iconostasis]]
[[sk:Ikonostas]]
[[sr:Иконостас]]
[[sh:Ikonostas]]
[[fi:Ikonostaasi]]
[[sv:Ikonostas]]
[[uk:Іконостас]]
[[zh:聖幛]]</text>
      <sha1>7bgoo7697volyrdqyne6hvznl47wqub</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
