<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Indulgence</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>286356</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521412602</id>
      <parentid>519310956</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T21:20:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kismetmagic</username>
        <id>694729</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removed vandalism reference to &quot;Matching funds.&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40661">[[Image:Indulgence San Giovanni in Laterano 2006-09-07.jpg|thumb|Inscription on the [[Basilica of St. John Lateran]] in [[Rome]]: ''Indulgentia plenaria perpetua quotidiana toties quoties pro vivis et defunctis'' (English trans: &quot;Perpetual everyday plenary indulgence on every occasion for the living and the dead&quot;)]]
In [[Catholic Church|Catholic theology]], an '''indulgence''' is the full or partial remission of temporal punishment&lt;ref&gt;The difference between temporal and eternal punishment for sin, according to this theology, is explained below, under &quot;Catholic teaching&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; due for [[sins]] which have already been forgiven. The indulgence is granted by the [[Catholic Church]] after the sinner has [[Confession (religion)|confessed]] and received [[absolution]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P3I.HTM ''Code of Canon Law, (Cann. 992&amp;ndash;997) Indulgences'']; [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'', 4th ed., 1999.]&lt;/ref&gt; An indulgence is thus not forgiveness of sin nor release from the eternal punishment associated with [[hell in Christian beliefs]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Myths about Indulgences|url=http://www.catholic.com/tracts/myths-about-indulgences|publisher=Catholic Answers}}&lt;/ref&gt; The belief is that indulgences draw on the [[Treasury of Merit]] accumulated by [[Jesus|Christ's]] superabundantly meritorious sacrifice on the cross and the [[virtues]] and [[penances]] of the [[saint]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;World History&quot;&gt;Wetterau, Bruce. World history. New York: Henry Holt and company. 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; They are granted for specific [[good works]] and [[prayers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;World History&quot; /&gt; 

Indulgences replaced the severe penances of the [[early Church]].&lt;ref name=&quot;World History&quot; /&gt; More exactly, they replaced the shortening of those penances that was allowed at the intercession of those imprisoned and those awaiting martyrdom for the faith.&lt;ref name =&quot;Oxford:Indulgences&quot;&gt;Cross, F. L., ed. The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church. New York: Oxford University Press. 2005, article ''indulgences''&lt;/ref&gt;

Alleged abuses in selling and granting indulgences&lt;ref name=&quot;World History&quot; /&gt; were a major point of contention when [[Martin Luther]] initiated the [[Protestant Reformation]] (1517).

==Catholic teaching==
{{Roman Catholicism}}
According to the teachings outlined in the [[Catechism of the Catholic Church]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P4G.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church (CCC), 1472]&lt;/ref&gt; two distinct consequences follow when a person sins. A [[mortal sin]] (one that is grave and is committed knowingly and freely) is equivalent to refusing friendship of God and [[communion (Christian)|communion]] with the only source of eternal life. The loss of eternal life with God and the eternal death of Hell that this rejection entails is called the &quot;eternal punishment&quot; of sin. In addition, every sin, even those that, not being mortal, are called [[venial sin]]s, cause a turning from God through what the Catechism of the Catholic Church calls an unhealthy attachment to creatures, which must be purified either here on earth, or after death in the state called [[purgatory]]. The resulting need to break this attachment to creatures is another punishment for sin, referred to as &quot;temporal punishment&quot;, because, not being a total rejection of God, it is not eternal and can be overcome in time. Even when the sin is forgiven, the associated attachment to creatures may remain. The sinner must &quot;strive by works of mercy and charity, as well as by prayer and the various practices of [[Sacrament of Penance (Catholic Church)|penance]], to put off completely the 'old man' and to put on the 'new man'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P4G.HTM CCC, 1473]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Catholic doctrine of the [[Communion of Saints]] teaches that this work of cleansing or sanctification does not have to be done entirely by the person directly concerned since all Christians (indeed, all persons, each created by God), living and dead, are united as a single body that has Christ as head. The holiness of one profits others, well beyond the harm that the sin of one could cause others. Thus through the communion of saints, recourse not only to the merits of the saints in heaven but above all to those of Christ himself lets the [[Contrition|contrite]] sinner be more promptly and efficaciously purified of the punishments for sin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P4G.HTM CCC, 1474&amp;ndash;1477]&lt;/ref&gt;

In view of the Church's interpretation of the [[Power of the Keys|power of binding or loosing]] granted by Christ, the Church considers that it may administer to those under its jurisdiction the benefits of these merits in consideration of prayer or other pious works undertaken by the faithful.&lt;ref name =&quot;Oxford:Indulgences&quot; /&gt; This the Church does for individual Christians, not simply to aid them, but also to spur them to works of devotion, penance, and charity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P4G.HTM CCC, 1478]&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a common misconception that, according to the doctrine of the Catholic Church, indulgences [[Forgiveness of sin#Christianity|forgive sins]]: the Catholic Church teaches instead that indulgences only relieve the temporal punishment due because of the sins, and that a person is still required to have his grave [[Absolution|sins absolved]], ordinarily through the sacrament of [[Confession (religion)|Confession]], to receive [[salvation]].

Since those who have died in the state of grace (with all mortal sins forgiven) are members of the [[communion of saints]], it is the belief of the Catholic Church that the living can help those whose purification from their sins is not yet completed not only by prayer but also by obtaining indulgences for them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P4G.HTM CCC, 1479]&lt;/ref&gt; Since the Church on earth has no jurisdiction over the dead, indulgences can be gained for them only ''per modum suffragii'', i.e. by an act of [[Intercession of saints|intercession]].&lt;ref name =&quot;Oxford:Indulgences&quot;/&gt;

An indulgence may be plenary or partial, according as it remits all or only part of the temporal punishment that at that moment is due for sin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Normae de Indulgentiis, 2]&lt;/ref&gt; To gain a plenary indulgence, a person must exclude all attachment to sin of any kind, even venial sin, must perform the work or say the prayer for which the indulgence is granted, and must also fulfil the three conditions of [[Sacrament of Penance (Catholic Church)|sacramental confession]], [[Eucharist|Eucharistic communion]] and praying for the [[Holy actions#Intentions|intentions of the Pope]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Normae de Indulgentiis, 20]&lt;/ref&gt; The minimum condition for gaining a partial indulgence is to be contrite in heart: on this condition, a Catholic who performs the work or recites the prayer in question is granted, through the Church, remission of temporal punishment of the same worth as is obtained by the person's own action.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Normae de Indulgentiis, 4]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Present discipline ===
[[File:Socvillegas4jf.JPG|thumb|left|250px|[[Archbishop]] [[Socrates B. Villegas]] bestows the [[Easter Sunday|Easter]] Mass Plenary Indulgence in 2012 (St. John the Evangelist Metropolitan Cathedral, [[Dagupan City, Pangasinan]]).]]
By the bull [[Indulgentiarum Doctrina]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_p-vi_apc_19670101_indulgentiarum-doctrina_en.html ''Indulgentiarum doctrina'' text]&lt;/ref&gt; of 1 January 1967, [[Pope Paul VI]], responding to suggestions made at the [[Second Vatican Council]], substantially revised the practical application of the traditional doctrine.&lt;ref name=EnChr &gt;''The encyclopedia of Christianity, Volume 2'' by Erwin Fahlbusch 2001 ISBN 90-04-11695-8 page 695&lt;/ref&gt;

He made it clear that the Church's aim was not merely to help the faithful make due satisfaction for their sins, but chiefly to bring them to greater fervour of charity. For this purpose he decreed that partial indulgences, previously granted as the equivalent of a certain number of days, months, &quot;quarantines&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12593a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: ''Quarantines'']&lt;/ref&gt; (Lent-like forty-day periods) or years of canonical penance, simply supplement, and to the same degree, the remission that those performing the indulgenced action already gain by the charity and contrition with which they do it.&lt;ref name =&quot;Oxford:Indulgences&quot; /&gt;

The abolition of the classification by years and days made it clearer than before that repentance and faith are required not only for remission of eternal punishment for mortal sin but also for remission of temporal punishment for sin. In ''Indulgentiarum doctrina'' Pope Paul VI wrote: &quot;Indulgences cannot be gained without a sincere conversion of outlook and unity with God&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_p-vi_apc_19670101_indulgentiarum-doctrina_en.html ''Indulgentiarum doctrina''], art. 11&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same bull, Pope Paul ordered that the official list of indulgenced prayers and good works, which had been called the ''[[Raccolta]]'', be revised &quot;with a view to attaching indulgences only to the most important prayers and works of piety, charity and penance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Indulgentiarum doctrina'', norm 13&lt;/ref&gt; This removed from the list of indulgenced prayers and good works, now called the ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'']&lt;/ref&gt; many prayers for which various [[religious institute]]s, [[confraternity|confraternities]] and similar groups had succeeded in the course of centuries in obtaining grants of indulgences, but which could not be classified as among &quot;the most important&quot;. Religious institutes and the like, to which grants of plenary indulgences, for instance for visiting a particular church or shrine, had been previously made, were given a year from the date of promulgation of ''Indulgentiarum doctrina'' to have them confirmed, and any that were not confirmed (mostly in a more limited way than before)&lt;ref&gt;''Indulgentiarum doctrina'', norms 14 and 15&lt;/ref&gt; within two years became null and void.&lt;ref&gt;''Indulgentiarum doctrina'', Transitional Norms&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'', which is in Latin, differs from the Italian-language ''Raccolta'' that it replaced in listing &quot;only the most important prayers and works of piety, charity and penance&quot;. On the other hand, it includes new general grants of partial indulgences that apply to a wide range of prayerful actions, and it indicates that the prayers that it does list as deserving veneration on account of divine inspiration or antiquity or as being in widespread use are only ''examples''&lt;ref&gt;''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum, Aliae concessiones, Proœmium'', 2&lt;/ref&gt; of those to which the first these general grants applies: &quot;Raising the mind to God with humble trust while performing one's duties and bearing life's difficulties, and adding, at least mentally, some pious invocation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum, Concessiones'', I&lt;/ref&gt; In this way, the ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'', in spite of its smaller size, classifies as indulgenced an immensely greater number of prayers than were treated as such in the ''Raccolta''.

====Actions for which indulgences are granted====
There are four general grants of indulgence, which are meant to encourage the faithful to infuse a Christian spirit into the actions of their daily lives and to strive for perfection of charity. These indulgences are partial, and their worth therefore depends on the fervour with which the person performs the recommended actions:
# Raising the mind to God with humble trust while performing one's duties and bearing life's difficulties, and adding, at least mentally, some pious invocation.
# Devoting oneself or one's goods compassionately in a spirit of faith to the service of one's brothers and sisters in need.
# Freely abstaining in a spirit of penance from something licit and pleasant.
# Freely giving open witness to one's faith before others in particular circumstances of everyday life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Normae de Indulgentiis, Quattuor Concessiones Generaliores]&lt;/ref&gt;

Among the particular grants, which, on closer inspection, will be seen to be included in one or more of the four general grants, especially the first, the ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'' draws special attention&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Aliae concessiones, Proœmium, 7]&lt;/ref&gt; to four activities for which a plenary indulgence can be gained on any day, though only once a day:
# Piously reading or listening to [[Bible|Sacred Scripture]] for at least half an hour.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 30]&lt;/ref&gt;
# [[Eucharistic adoration|Adoration]] of Jesus in the [[Eucharist]] for at least half an hour.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 7 §1, 1º]&lt;/ref&gt;
# The pious exercise of the [[Stations of the Cross]] .&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 13, 2º]&lt;/ref&gt;
# Recitation of the [[Rosary]] or the [[Akathist]] in a church or oratory, or in a family, a religious community, an association of the faithful and, in general, when several people come together for an honourable purpose.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 17 §1, 1º and 23 §1]&lt;/ref&gt;

A plenary indulgence may also be gained on some occasions, which are not everyday occurrences. They include:
* Receiving, even by radio or television, the blessing given by the Pope ''[[Urbi et Orbi]]'' (to the city of Rome and to the world) or that which a bishop is authorized to give three times a year to the faithful of his diocese.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 4]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Taking part devoutly in the celebration of a day devoted on a world level to a particular religious purpose.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 5]&lt;/ref&gt; Under this heading come the annual celebrations such as the [[World Day of Prayer for Vocations]], and occasional celebrations such as [[World Youth Day]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wyd2008.org/index.php/en/media__1/news_archives/plenary_indulgence World Youth Day Archives]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cairns.catholic.org.au/wyd2008/journey.html Australian Catholic WYD 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Taking part for at least three full days in a [[retreat (spiritual)|spiritual retreat]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 10]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Taking part in some functions during the [[Week of Prayer for Christian Unity]] including its conclusion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 11]&lt;/ref&gt;

The prayers specifically mentioned in the ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'' are not of the [[Latin Rite]] tradition alone, but also from the traditions of the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]], such as the [[Akathistos]], [[Paraklesis]], ''Evening Prayer'', and ''Prayer for the Faithful Departed'' (Byzantine), ''Prayer of Thanksgiving'' (Armenian), ''Prayer of the Shrine'' and the ''Lakhu Mara'' (Chaldean), ''Prayer of Incense'' and ''Prayer to Glorify Mary the Mother of God'' (Coptic), ''Prayer for the Remission of Sins'' and ''Prayer to Follow Christ'' (Ethiopian), ''Prayer for the Church'', and ''Prayer of Leave-taking from the Altar'' (Maronite), and ''Intercessions for the Faithful Departed'' (Syrian).

Apart from the recurrences listed in the ''Enchiridion'', special indulgences are granted on occasions of special spiritual significance such as a [[Jubilee (Christian)|Jubilee Year]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/jubilee/indulgence/index.htm The Great Jubilee Indulgence]&lt;/ref&gt; or the centenary or similar anniversary of an event such as the apparition of [[Our Lady of Lourdes]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20071121_decreto-lourdes_en.html Grant of indulgence on the occasion of the 150th apparition of the Blessed Virgin Mary at Lourdes]&lt;/ref&gt; or the celebration of a World Youth Day.

Of particular significance is the plenary indulgence attached to the [[Apostolic Blessing]] that a priest is to impart when giving the sacraments to a person in danger of death, and which, if no priest is available, the Church grants to any rightly disposed Christian at the moment of death, on condition that that person was accustomed to say some prayers during life. In this case the Church itself makes up for the three conditions normally required for a plenary indulgence: sacramental confession, Eucharistic communion and prayer for the Pope's intentions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html Concessiones 12]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of indulgences==
===Early and medieval beliefs===
In the early church, especially from the third century on, ecclesiastic authorities allowed a confessor or a Christian awaiting martyrdom to intercede for another Christian in order to shorten the other's canonical penance.&lt;ref name =&quot;Oxford:Indulgences&quot; /&gt;

The [[Council of Epaon]] in 517 witnesses to the rise of the practice of replacing severe canonical penances with something new and milder. It became customary to commute penances to less demanding works, such as prayers, alms, fasts and even the payment of fixed sums of money depending on the various kinds of offences (tariff penances). By the tenth century some penances were not replaced but merely reduced in connection with pious donations, pilgrimages and similar meritorious works. Then, in the eleventh and twelfth centuries, the recognition of the value of these works began to become associated not so much with canonical penance but with remission of the temporal punishment due to sin.&lt;ref name =&quot;Covolo&quot;&gt;[http://www.catholicculture.org/library/view.cfm?recnum=1054 Enrico dal Covolo: The Historical Origin of Indulgences]&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest record of a plenary indulgence was [[Pope Urban II]]'s declaration at the [[Council of Clermont]] (1095) that he remitted all penance incurred by [[Crusades|crusaders]] who had confessed their sins in the [[Sacrament of Penance]], considering participation in the crusade equivalent to a complete penance.&lt;ref name =&quot;Covolo&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name =&quot;Oxford:Plenary&quot;&gt;Cross, F. L., ed. The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church. New York: Oxford University Press. 2005, article ''plenary indulgence''&lt;/ref&gt;

Theologians looked to God's mercy, the value of the Church's prayers, and the merits of the saints as the basis on which indulgences could be granted. Around 1230 the Dominican Hugh of St-Cher proposed the idea of a &quot;treasury&quot; at the Church's disposal, consisting of the infinite merits of Christ and the immeasurable abundance of the saints' merits, a thesis that was demonstrated by great scholastics such as [[Albertus Magnus]] and [[Thomas Aquinas]] and remains the basis for the theological explanation of indulgences.&lt;ref name =&quot;Covolo&quot; /&gt;

[[Image:Jeorg Breu Elder A Question to a Mintmaker c1500.png|thumb|right|250px|The sale of indulgences shown in ''A Question to a Mintmaker'', woodcut by [[Jörg Breu the Elder]] of Augsburg, circa 1530.]]

===Abuses===
{{redirect|Pardoner|the character in Chaucer's Canterbury Tales|The Pardoner's Tale}}

Indulgences became increasingly popular in the [[Middle Ages]] as a reward for displaying piety and doing good deeds, though, doctrinally speaking, the Church stated that the indulgence was only valid for temporal punishment for sins already forgiven in the [[Sacrament of Confession]]. The faithful asked that indulgences be given for saying their favourite prayers, doing acts of devotion, attending places of worship, and going on pilgrimage; [[Confraternity|confraternities]] wanted indulgences for putting on performances and processions; associations demanded that their meetings be rewarded with indulgences. Money raised by indulgences was used for many righteous causes, both religious and civil; building projects funded by indulgences include churches, hospitals, [[leper colonies]], schools, roads, and bridges.&lt;ref name =&quot;Covolo&quot; /&gt;

However, the later Middle Ages saw the growth of considerable abuses.  Greedy [[Commissary|commissaries]] sought to extract the maximum amount of money for each indulgence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | last = Kirsch | first = Johann Peter | title = The Reformation | encyclopedia = The Catholic Encyclopedia | volume = 12 | publisher = Robert Appleton Company | place = New York | year = 1911 | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12700b.htm (transcribed for New Advent by Marie Jutras) | accessdate = 23 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Professional &quot;pardoners&quot;&lt;ref name =&quot;Oxford:Indulgences&quot; /&gt; (''quaestores'' in Latin) - who were sent to collect alms for a specific project - practiced the unrestricted sale of indulgences. Many of these ''quaestores'' exceeded Church teachings, whether in avarice or ignorant zeal, and promised impossible rewards like salvation from eternal damnation in return for money.&lt;ref name =&quot;Covolo&quot; /&gt; With the permission of the Church, indulgences also became a way for Catholic rulers to fund expensive projects, such as [[Crusades]] and cathedrals, by keeping a significant portion of the money raised from indulgences in their lands.&lt;ref name =&quot;Covolo&quot; /&gt; There was a tendency to forge documents declaring that indulgences had been granted.&lt;ref name =&quot;Covolo&quot; /&gt; Indulgences grew to extraordinary magnitude, in terms of longevity and breadth of forgiveness.

[[File:Israhel van Meckenem The Mass of Saint Gregory.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Engraving]] of the ''[[Mass of Saint Gregory]]'' by [[Israhel van Meckenem]], 1490s, with an unauthorized indulgence at the bottom&lt;ref&gt;Shestack, 214&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The [[Fourth Lateran Council]] (1215) suppressed some abuses connected with indulgences, spelling out, for example, that only a one-year indulgence would be granted for the consecration of churches and no more than a 40-days indulgence for other occasions. The Council also stated that &quot;Catholics who have girded themselves with the cross for the extermination of the heretics, shall enjoy the indulgences and privileges granted to those who go in defense of the Holy Land.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/lateran4.html Fordham.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

But very soon these limits were widely exceeded. False documents were circulated with indulgences surpassing all bounds: indulgences of hundreds or even thousands of years.&lt;ref name =&quot;Covolo&quot; /&gt; In 1392, more than a century before [[Martin Luther]] published the [[95 Theses]], Pope [[Boniface IX]] wrote to the [[Bishop of Ferrara]] condemning the practice of certain [[Religious order#Catholic tradition|members of religious orders]] who falsely claimed that they were authorized by the pope to forgive all sorts of sins, and exacted money from the simple-minded among the faithful by promising them perpetual happiness in this world and eternal glory in the next.&lt;ref name=newadvent&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle=Indulgences|author=W.H. Kent}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An [[engraving]] by [[Israhel van Meckenem]] of the ''[[Mass of Saint Gregory]]'' contained a &quot;bootlegged&quot; indulgence of 20,000 years; one of the copies of this plate (not the one illustrated, but also from the 1490s) was altered in a later [[state (printmaking)|state]] to increase it to 45,000 years.  The indulgences applied each time a specified collection of prayers - in this case seven each of the [[Creed]], [[Lord's Prayer|Our Father]], and [[Hail Mary]] - were recited in front of the image.&lt;ref&gt;Parshall, 58 (quoted), and Shestack, 214 (illustrated in both).&lt;/ref&gt;  The image of the ''Mass of Saint Gregory'' had been especially associated with large indulgences since the [[Jubilee (Christian)|Jubilee Year]] of 1350 in Rome, when it was at least widely believed that an indulgence of 14,000 years had been granted for praying in the presence of the ''[[Imago Pietatis]]'' (&quot;Man of Sorrows&quot;), a popular pilgrimage destination in the [[basilica]] of [[Santa Croce in Gerusalemme]] in Rome.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Schiller | first = G  | title = Iconography of Christian Art, Vol. II | publisher = Lund Humphries | location = London | date = 1972 (English trans from German) | pages = 199–200 | isbn = 853313245}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protestant Reformation===
[[Image:Antichrist1.jpg|thumb|right|200px|The Pope as the Antichrist, signing and selling indulgences, from Luther's 1521 ''Passional Christi und Antichristi'', by [[Lucas Cranach the Elder]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://xroads.virginia.edu/~MA96/PUCK/part1.html#christi A Brief History of Political Cartoons]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Indulgence2.png|thumb|right|220px|Indulgence of Jeronimus Munghofer]]

The false doctrine and scandalous conduct of the &quot;pardoners&quot; were an immediate occasion of the [[Protestant Reformation]].&lt;ref name =&quot;Oxford:Indulgences&quot;/&gt; In 1517, [[Pope Leo X]] offered indulgences for those who gave alms to rebuild [[St. Peter's Basilica]] in [[Rome]]. The aggressive [[marketing]] practices of [[Johann Tetzel]] in promoting this cause provoked [[Martin Luther]] to write his [[The Ninety-Five Theses|Ninety-Five Theses]], condemning what he saw as the purchase and sale of [[salvation]]. In Thesis 28 Luther objected to a saying attributed to Tetzel: &quot;As soon as a coin in the coffer rings, a soul from purgatory springs&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Thesis 55 of Tetzel's ''One Hundred and Six Theses''. These &quot;Anti-theses&quot; were a reply to Luther’s ''[[Ninety-Five Theses]]'' and were drawn up by Tetzel’s friend and former Professor, [[Konrad Wimpina]]. Theses 55 &amp; 56 (responding to Luther's 27th Theses) read: &quot;For a soul to fly out, is for it to obtain the vision of God, which can be ''hindered by no interruption'', therefore he errs who says that the soul ''cannot fly out'' before the coin can jingle in the bottom of the chest.&quot; In, ''The reformation in Germany'', [[Henry Clay Vedder]], 1914, Macmillon Company, p. 405. [http://books.google.com/books?id=JQ4QAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA405&amp;dq=%22For+a+soul+to+fly+out,+is+for+it+to+obtain+the+vision+of+God%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=1nAnTeHnNcOblgfCmPHeAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22For%20a%20soul%20to%20fly%20out%2C%20is%20for%20it%20to%20obtain%20the%20vision%20of%20God%22&amp;f=false Books.google.com] ''Animam purgatam evolare, est eam visione dei potiri, quod nulla potest intercapedine impediri. Quisquis ergo dicit, non citius posse animam volare, quam in fundo cistae denarius possit tinnire, errat''. In: ''D. Martini Lutheri, Opera Latina: Varii Argumenti'', 1865, Henricus Schmidt, ed., Heyder and Zimmer, [[Frankfurt|Frankfurt am Main]] &amp; Erlangen, vol. 1, p. 300. (Reprinted: Nabu Press, 2010, ISBN 1-142-40551-6 ISBN 9781142405519). [http://books.google.com/books?id=s633jfx_uEUC&amp;pg=PA300&amp;dq=%22Quisquis+ergo+dicit,+non+citius+posse%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Dx4kTfLZKcH58AaOx8TTAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Quisquis%20ergo%20dicit%2C%20non%20citius%20posse%22&amp;f=false Books.google.com] See also: [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14539a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: Johann Tetzel]&lt;/ref&gt; The Ninety-Five Theses not only denounced such transactions as worldly but denied the Pope's right to grant pardons on God's behalf in the first place: the only thing indulgences guaranteed, Luther said, was an increase in profit and greed, because the pardon of the Church was in God's power alone.&lt;ref&gt;''Certum est, nummo in cistam tinniente augeri questum et avariciam posse: suffragium autem ecclesie est in arbitrio dei solius'' (Thesis 28).&lt;/ref&gt;

This oft-quoted saying was by no means representative of the ''official'' Catholic teaching on indulgences, but rather, more a reflection of Tetzel’s capacity to exaggerate. Yet if Tetzel overstated the matter in regard to indulgences for the ''dead'', his teaching on indulgences for the ''living'' was pure. German Catholic historian of the Papacy, [[Ludwig von Pastor]] explains:&lt;ref&gt;[[Ludwig von Pastor]], ''The History of the Popes, from the Close of the Middle Ages'', Ralph Francis Kerr, ed., 1908, B. Herder, St. Louis, Volume 7, pp. 347-348.
[http://books.google.com/books?id=Y1QZaRY6Q4UC&amp;pg=PA348&amp;dq=%22+a+most+clear+distinction+must+be+made+between+indulgences+for+the+living+and+those+for+the+dead%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=8HUyTd-cFsG78gbXxPH4CA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22%20a%20most%20clear%20distinction%20must%20be%20made%20between%20indulgences%20for%20the%20living%20and%20those%20for%20the%20dead%22&amp;f=false Books.google.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Above all, a most clear distinction must be made between indulgences for the living and those for the dead.&lt;br&gt;

As regards indulgences for the living, Tetzel always taught pure doctrine. The assertion that he put forward indulgences as being not only a remission of the temporal punishment of sin, but as a remission of its guilt, is as unfounded as is that other accusation against him, that he sold the forgiveness of sin for money, without even any mention of contrition and confession, or that, for payment, he absolved from sins which might be committed in the future. His teaching was, in fact, very definite, and quite in harmony with the theology of the Church, as it was then and as it is now, i.e., that indulgences &quot;apply only to the temporal punishment due to sins which have been already repented of and confessed&quot;....

The case was very different with indulgences for the dead. As regards these there is no doubt that Tetzel did, according to what he considered his authoritative instructions, proclaim as Christian doctrine that nothing but an offering of money was required to gain the indulgence for the dead, without there being any question of contrition or confession.
He also taught, in accordance with the opinion then held, that an indulgence could be applied to any given soul with unfailing effect. Starting from this assumption, there is no doubt that his doctrine was virtually that of the drastic proverb:
:“As soon as money in the coffer rings, the soul from purgatory's fire springs.&quot;

The [[Papal Bull]] of indulgence gave no sanction whatever to this proposition. It was a vague scholastic opinion, rejected by the Sorbonne in 1482, and again in 1518, and certainly not a doctrine of the Church, which was thus improperly put forward as dogmatic truth. The first among the theologians of the Roman court, Cardinal Cajetan, was the enemy of all such extravagances, and declared emphatically that, even if theologians and preachers taught such opinions, no faith need be given them. &quot;Preachers,&quot; said he, &quot;speak in the name of the Church only so long as they proclaim the doctrine of Christ and His Church; but if, for purposes of their own, they teach that about which they know nothing, and which is only their own imagination, they must not be accepted as mouthpieces of the Church. No one must be surprised if such as these fall into error.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

While Luther did not deny the Pope’s right to grant pardons for [[penance]] imposed by the Church, he made it clear that preachers who claimed indulgences absolved buyers from all punishments and granted them salvation were in error.&lt;ref&gt;''Errant itaque indulgentiarum predicatores ii, qui dicunt per pape indulgentias hominem ab omni pena solvi et salvari'' (Thesis 21).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Council of Trent===
On 16 July 1562, the [[Council of Trent]] suppressed the office of ''quaestores'' and reserved the collection of alms to two [[canon (priest)|canon members]] of the [[chapter (religion)|chapter]], who were to receive no remuneration for their work; it also reserved the publication of indulgences to the bishop of the diocese.&lt;ref&gt;[http://history.hanover.edu/texts/trent/ct21.html Session 21, chapter 9]&lt;/ref&gt; Then on 4 December 1563, in its final session, the Council addressed the question of indulgences directly, declaring them &quot;most salutary for the Christian people&quot;, decreeing that &quot;all evil gains for the obtaining of them be wholly abolished&quot;, and instructing bishops to be on the watch for any abuses concerning them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://history.hanover.edu/texts/trent/ct25.html Session 25, Decree on Indulgences]&lt;/ref&gt;

A few years later, in 1567, [[Pope Pius V]] cancelled all grants of indulgences involving any fees or other financial transactions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07783a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: article ''Indulgences'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;catholic.com&quot;&gt;&quot;Myths About Indulgences.&quot; Catholic Answers. Retrieved 16 Apr. 2008 [http://www.catholic.com/library/Myths_About_Indulgences.asp Myths about indulgences]&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Council of Trent, [[Clement VIII]] established a commission of Cardinals to deal with indulgences according to the mind of the Council. It continued its work during the pontificate of [[Paul V]] and published various bulls and decrees on the matter. But only [[Clement IX]] established a true [[Congregation of Indulgences]] (and Relics) with a Brief of 6 July 1669. In a ''[[motu proprio]]'' on 28 January 1904, [[Pius X]] joined the Congregation of Indulgences with that of Rites, but with the restructuring of the [[Roman Curia]] in 1908 all matters regarding indulgences was assigned to the Holy Office. In a ''motu proprio'' on 25 March 1915, [[Benedict XV]] transferred the Holy Office's Section for Indulgences to the [[Apostolic Penitentiary]], but maintained the Holy Office's responsibility for matters regarding the doctrine of indulgences.

==Eastern Orthodox Church==
[[Image:Orthodox Indulgence.jpg|thumb|300px|An 18th-century absolution certificate granted by the Patriarch of Jerusalem and sold by Greek monks in [[Wallachia]] (History Museum, [[Bucharest]])]]
The [[Eastern Orthodox Church]]es believe one can be absolved from sins by the Sacred Mystery of Confession, which in the East is preceded by a period of fasting.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} Because of differences in the theology of salvation, indulgences for the remission of temporal punishment of sin do not exist in [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodoxy]], but until the twentieth century there existed in some places a practice of absolution certificates (''συγχωροχάρτια &amp;ndash; synchorochartia'').

While some of these certificates were connected with any patriarch's decrees lifting for the living or the dead some serious ecclesiastical penalty, including excommunication, the [[Greek Orthodox Patriarch of Jerusalem]], with the approval of the [[Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople]], had the sole privilege, because of the expense of maintaining the Holy Places and paying the many taxes levied on them, of distributing such documents in large numbers to pilgrims or sending them elsewhere, sometimes with a blank space for the name of the beneficiary, living or dead, an individual or a whole family, for whom the prayers would be read.

[[Greek Orthodox Patriarch of Jerusalem]] [[Dositheos Notaras]] (1641&amp;ndash;1707) wrote: &quot;It is an established custom and ancient tradition, known to all, that the Most Holy Patriarchs give the absolution certificate (''συγχωροχάρτιον &amp;ndash; synchorochartion'') to the faithful people … they have granted them from the beginning and still do.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Δοσίθεος Νοταρᾶς, Ἱστορία περὶ τῶν ἐν Ἱεροσολύμοις πατριαρχευσάντων, Bucharest 1715, p. 88&lt;/ref&gt;

A Russian Orthodox source says that these certificates were in use among Greek Orthodox until the middle of the twentieth century, and were &quot;certificates which absolved from sins, which anyone could obtain, often for a specified sum of money. The absolution granted by these papers, according to Christos Yannaras, had no connection with any participation of the faithful in the Mystery of Penance, nor in the Mystery of the Eucharist&quot;. The same source interprets the Western indulgence also as absolution from sin, not as remission of temporal punishment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pravoslavie.ru/enarticles/041125153738#3 Indulgences in the History of the Greek Church]. Retrieved 11 April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*Parshall, Peter, in David Landau &amp; Peter Parshall, ''The Renaissance Print'', Yale, 1996, ISBN 0-300-06883-2
*Shestack, Alan; ''Fifteenth century Engravings of Northern Europe''; 1967, National Gallery of Art, Washington (Catalogue), LOC 67-29080

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{commons category|Indulgences}}
*[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_p-vi_apc_19670101_indulgentiarum-doctrina_en.html Pope Paul VI: Apostolic Constitution ''Indulgentiarum Doctrina'' whereby the Revision of Sacred Indulgences is Promulgated], 1 January 1967
*[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P3I.HTM Code of Canon Law (1983) concerning Indulgences]
*[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/tribunals/apost_penit/documents/rc_trib_appen_doc_20020826_enchiridion-indulgentiarum_lt.html ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'', 4th edition, 1999 (Latin)] (English translation: &quot;Manual of Indulgences&quot;, published by the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops, ISBN 1-57455-474-3)
*[http://www.catholicliturgy.com/index.cfm/FuseAction/DocumentContents/Index/2/DocumentIndex/547 English translation of ''Enchiridion Indulgentiarum'', 3rd edition (1986)]
*[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/audiences/1999/documents/hf_jp-ii_aud_29091999_en.html Pope John Paul II: General Audience talk on indulgences], 29 September 1999
*[http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p2s2c2a4.htm#X Catechism of the Catholic Church: ''Indulgences'']
*{{CathEncy|id=07783a}}
*[http://www.catholicculture.org/library/view.cfm?recnum=1054 Enrico dal Covolo: ''The Historical Origin of Indulgences'']
*[http://www.catholic.net/rcc/Periodicals/Faith/0910-96/article9.html Paul S. Czarnota: ''Indulgences'']
*[http://www.catholic.com/library/Primer_on_Indulgences.asp A Primer on Indulgences]
*[http://www.catholic.com/library/myths_about_indulgences.asp Myths about Indulgences]

[[Category:Sacrament of Confession]]
[[Category:16th-century Christianity]]
[[Category:Catholic theology and doctrine]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[ar:غفران (مسيحية)]]
[[bg:Индулгенция]]
[[bs:Oprost]]
[[ca:Indulgència]]
[[cs:Odpustek]]
[[da:Aflad]]
[[de:Ablass]]
[[et:Indulgents]]
[[el:Συγχωροχάρτι]]
[[es:Indulgencia]]
[[eo:Indulgenco]]
[[fa:آمرزش‌نامه]]
[[fr:Indulgence (catholicisme)]]
[[gl:Indulxencia]]
[[ko:대사 (가톨릭)]]
[[hr:Oprost]]
[[io:Induljenco]]
[[id:Indulgensi]]
[[it:Indulgenza]]
[[he:שטר מחילה]]
[[ka:ინდულგენცია]]
[[la:Indulgentia]]
[[lt:Indulgencija]]
[[li:Aaflaot]]
[[hu:Búcsú]]
[[ml:ദണ്ഡവിമോചനം]]
[[nl:Aflaat]]
[[ja:贖宥状]]
[[no:Avlat]]
[[nn:Avlat]]
[[oc:Indulgéncia]]
[[nds:Aflaat]]
[[pl:Odpust]]
[[pt:Indulgência]]
[[ro:Indulgență (creștinism)]]
[[ru:Индульгенция]]
[[sq:Indulgjenca]]
[[simple:Indulgence]]
[[sl:Cerkveni odpustki]]
[[sr:Опроштај грехова]]
[[sh:Oprost]]
[[fi:Ane]]
[[sv:Avlatsbrev]]
[[tr:Endüljans]]
[[uk:Індульгенція]]
[[zh:贖罪券]]</text>
      <sha1>7azo480bt5g4sf3ausuomw3j1ywy90p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
