<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Inquisition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15191</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522218537</id>
      <parentid>522218514</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T19:03:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/70.41.250.9|70.41.250.9]] to version by FrescoBot. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1326082) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40384">{{About|the Inquisition within the Roman Catholic Church}}

{{ref improve|date=October 2012}}
[[File:Galileo before the Holy Office.jpg|thumb|right|300px|A 19th-century depiction of Galileo before the Holy Office, by [[Joseph-Nicolas Robert-Fleury]]]]

The '''Inquisition''' (''Inquisitio Haereticae Pravitatis''; Inquiry on Heretical Perversity), was a group of decentralized institutions within the justice system of the [[Roman Catholic Church]] whose aim was to &quot;fight against [[Christian heresy|heretics]]&quot;. It started in [[Christianity in the 12th century|12th-century]] [[France]] to persecute [[heresy]], and was later expanded to other European countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lea1888&quot;/&gt; Inquisition practices were used also on offences against [[canon law]] other than heresy.

==Definition==

The term ''Inquisition'' can apply to any one of several institutions which fought against [[Christian heresy|heretics]] (or other offenders against [[canon law]]) within the justice system of the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. The term ''Inquisition'' is usually applied to that of the Catholic Church. It also refers to:&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/inquisition1.html Medieval Sourcebook: Inquisition - Introduction]&lt;/ref&gt;

* an [[ecclesiastical]] tribunal,
* the institution of the Catholic Church for combating heresy,
* a number of historical [[expurgation]] movements against heresy (orchestrated by some groups/individuals within the Catholic Church or within a Catholic state), or
* the trial of an individual accused of heresy.

Generally, the Inquisition movement was concerned only with the heretical behaviour of Catholic adherents or converts, and did not concern itself with those outside its jurisdiction, such as Jews or Muslims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salomon, H. P 2001 pp. 345-7&quot;&gt;Salomon, H. P. and Sassoon, I. S. D., in Saraiva, Antonio Jose. ''The Marrano Factory. The Portuguese Inquisition and Its New Christians, 1536-1765'' (Brill, 2001), Introduction pp. XXX.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Tribunals and institutions ==
Before 1100, the Catholic Church had already suppressed heresy, usually through a system of ecclesiastical proscription or imprisonment, but without using torture&lt;ref name=&quot;Lea1888&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Lea
|first= Henry Charles
|authorlink= Henry Charles Lea
|title=A History of the Inquisition In The Middle Ages
|volume= 1
|chapter=Chapter VII. The Inquisition Founded
|quote= The judicial use of torture was as yet happily unknown...
|year= 1888
|isbn=1-152-29621-3
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
and seldom resorting to executions.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Foxe
|first=John
|authorlink=John Foxe
|title=[[Foxe's Book of Martyrs]]
|chapter=Chapter V
|url=http://www.jesus.org.uk/vault/library/foxes_book_of_martyrs.pdf
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite encyclopedia
 | last = Blötzer
 | first = J.
 | encyclopedia = The Catholic Encyclopedia
 | title = Inquisition
 | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08026a.htm
 | accessdate = 2012-08-26
 | year = 1910
 | publisher = Robert Appleton Company
 | quote = ... in this period the more influential ecclesiastical authorities declared that the death penalty was contrary to the spirit of the Gospel, and themselves opposed its execution. For centuries this was the ecclesiastical attitude both in theory and in practice. Thus, in keeping with the civil law, some Manichæans were executed at Ravenna in 556. On the other hand. Elipandus of Toledo and Felix of Urgel, the chiefs of Adoptionism and Predestinationism, were condemned by councils, but were otherwise left unmolested. We may note, however, that the monk Gothescalch, after the condemnation of his false doctrine that Christ had not died for all mankind, was by the Synods of Mainz in 848 and Quiercy in 849 sentenced to flogging and imprisonment, punishments then common in monasteries for various infractions of the rule
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Such punishments had a number of ecclesiastical opponents, although some countries punished heresy with the [[death penalty]].&lt;!-- The extraordinary juxtaposition of secular countries with non-secular ones in the context of the Middle Ages would require extraordinary proof. Perhaps we could say &quot;some secular authorities&quot; used the death-penalty...--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite encyclopedia
 | last = Blötzer
 | first = J.
 | encyclopedia = The Catholic Encyclopedia
 | title = Inquisition
 | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08026a.htm
 | accessdate = 2012-08-26
 | year = 1910
 | publisher = Robert Appleton Company
 | quote = [...] the occasional executions of heretics during this period must be ascribed partly to the arbitrary action of individual rulers, partly to the fanatic outbreaks of the overzealous populace, and in no wise to ecclesiastical law or the ecclesiastical authorities.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Lea
|first= Henry Charles
|title=A History of the Inquisition In The Middle Ages
|volume= 1
|chapter=Chapter VII. The Inquisition Founded
|isbn=1-152-29621-3
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 12th century, to counter the spread of [[Catharism]], prosecution of heretics by some secular governments became more frequent. The Church charged councils composed of bishops and archbishops with establishing inquisitions (see [[Medieval Inquisition|Episcopal Inquisition]]). The first Inquisition was temporarily established in [[Languedoc]] (south of France) in 1184. In 1229 it was permanently established.  It was centered under the Dominicans&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08026a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt; in Rome and later at [[Carcasonne]] in Provence. Having full ownership of their property in the countries where it was set up. an international network was set up in these countries to check on any newcomers to a place and to track down any escapees. Its decentralised autonomous proceedings became difficult to control above all civil and other ecclesiastical laws even against the intercession of senior Bishops and even a few Popes.{{clarify|This is unclear. WHO is having problems controlling? The Church? The church did not run civil justice. Normally accusees preferred the Inquisition to civil authorities|date=October 2012}} Arrests could be made without any evidence, merely on suspicion.{{cn|date=October 2012}} According to [[Henry Charles Lea]] one of the worst cases of this being that of an old woman who found pork disagreeable and on refusing to eat it on an unfortunate Saturday was arrested for being a [[crypto-Jew ]] rather than being actually Catholic.{{fact|needs actual citation. Being Jewish was not a problem anyway. It was &quot;conversos&quot; in Portugal and Spain - to prevent being deported (and losing their property), some Jews officially converted to Christianity but did not do so in actuality. They were then subject to the Inquisition for heresy. This &quot;crypto-Jew&quot; comment needs to fall under that proviso|date=October 2012}}

==Use of torture==

[[File:Torture Inquisition.jpg|thumb|right|Two priests demand a heretic to repent as he is tortured.]][[Torture]] was previously forbidden by [[canon law]] but in 1252 [[Pope Innocent IV]] sanctioned the use of torture&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08026a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia]]&lt;/ref&gt; and also granted dispensation for the inquisitors to be present during its application.{{cn|date=October 2012}}
* Psychological Torture: was a potent weapon in the hands of the inquisitors. Prisoners were confronted with friends and relatives begging a confession;[[canon law]] still only permitted torture to be used once but actually it could be repeated after a delay by the use of the legal device of [[continuance]] the psychology of delay including [[continuance]] was common, lifting and lowering hopes sometimes over a period of years; prisoners were kept in a state of ignorance of their fate and that of their families and often a strict regime of confinement in chains or other devices on a meagre diet was employed.{{cn|date=October 2012}}
* Physical torture: In Spain the usual method was to bind the arms tightly behind the back, attach heavy weights to the legs, lift the victim from the ground by means of a pulley and then jerk down. An alternate [[waterboarding]] method was to strap the victim by the arms, waist, thighs and calves to a trestle like a ladder with sharp rungs and tighten the ropes, lacerating the flesh. The trestle was sloped head down, the head restrained and the mouth forced open with iron devices. Water was then intermittently introduced into the throat inducing gagging and vomiting. The more familiar [[rack]] was also used in later years, along with [[thumbscrews]] and other instruments.
* Humiliation: Victims, both men and women, were usually tortured naked. In addition, the victim were told that if they died under torture, that the Church would consider that they had committed suicide and would go straight to hell; whereas from the point of view of the torturers they had merely made a mistake or accident.{{fact|date=October 2012}}
* Relationship with Civil Law: Since the Church 'shed no blood' the guilty had to be handed over to the civil authorities for final punishment. Civil authorities only usually used torture as a means of actual punishment to the guilty, or as a means of gaining forensic information from criminals.{{fact|This makes it sound like civil authorities were more lenient than the church. This is unlikely and needs a really reliable citation|date=October 2012}} And unlike the inquisition often forbade the torture of women with its sexual overtones.{{cn|date=October 2012}} However, most of the torture methods the inquisition used were the same; the exception being those used in Germany and the Low Countries where other devices were used.{{cn|date=October 2012}}

==Treatment of women==
All prisoners were initially kept together and this led to violations of women by other prisoners and their guards.{{cn|date=October 2012}} Later{{when|date=October 2012}} orders were given that the sexes be separated.{{cn|date=October 2012}} Pregnant women as a vulnerable group became frequent{{fact|date=October 2012}} prisoners especially in Spain,with special accommodation but without the help of midwives or other women, consequently many endured extreme suffering and did not survive childbirth. Many babies were confiscated before their mothers were subjected to torture.
* Danger of witchcraft accusation: In 1484 the [[Innocent VIII]] papal bull [[summis desiderantes affectibus]] was issued to [[Kramer]] the author of the [[Malleus Maleficarum]] ,in defiance of his bishop, and [[Kramer]] included it in the preface to the book. Women were then open to arrest by the inquisition on suspicision of witchcraft. Although men as well as women could be open to this charge, the title of the book itself is feminine in gender and [[Kramer]] writes in section I of his [[misogynist]] work that: &quot;all witchcraft comes from carnal lust which is in women insatiable&quot;. Although in 1490 the Vatican decided that the book was false, in the face of the inquisition, and in fact in 1538 the [[Spanish Inquisition]] cautioned against using it, the damage had been done, and by means of printing the book went through sixteen editions up until 1669. Spreading from the Kramer's [[Tyrol]] where it originated to other [[Germanic States]] helping to fuel the witch hunts in amongst [[Protestant]] countries in the seventeenth century as well.
==Grand Inquisitor==
In the 13th century, [[Pope Gregory IX]] (reigned 1227–1241) assigned the duty of carrying out inquisitions to the [[Dominican Order]].{{clarify|Note that the above material claims that the Inquisition was permanent. Either it was or it wasn't|date=October 2012}} They used [[Inquisitorial system|inquisitorial procedures]], a legal practice common at that time. They judged heresy alone, using the local authorities to establish a tribunal and to prosecute heretics. After 1200, a [[Grand Inquisitor]] headed each Inquisition. The most notorious at the start of the sixteenth century being the first of the Spanish Inquisition [[Tomas Torquemada]]. Grand Inquisitions persisted until the mid 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://libro.uca.edu/lea1/append2.htm Lea, Henry Charles. ''A History of the Inquisition of Spain''], vol. 1, appendix 2&lt;/ref&gt;

==Modern times==

By 1500, the Catholic Church had reached an apparently dominant position as the established religious authority in western and central Europe dominating a faith-landscape in which [[Judaism]], [[Waldensianism]], [[Hussitism]], [[Lollardry]] and the finally conquered Muslims  [[al-Andalus]] (the Muslim-dominated Spain) hardly figured in terms of numbers or influence.  When the institutions of the Church felt themselves threatened by what they perceived as the heresy, and then [[Schism (religion)|schism]] of the [[Protestant Reformation]], they reacted. [[Pope Paul III|Paul III]] (Pope from 1534 to 1549) established a system of tribunals, administered by the &quot;Supreme Sacred Congregation of the Universal Inquisition&quot;, and staffed by cardinals and other Church officials. This system would later become known as the [[Roman Inquisition]]. In 1908 [[Pope Pius X|Pope Saint Pius X]] renamed the organisation: it became the &quot;Supreme Sacred Congregation of the Holy Office&quot;. This in its turn became the &quot;[[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_pro_14071997_en.html &quot;Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith&quot;]. Vatican: the Holy See. Retrieved 2012-08-26&lt;/ref&gt; in 1965, which name continues {{As of|2008|alt=to this day}}.

==Functional role==
In practice, the Inquisition would not itself pronounce sentence, but handed over convicted heretics to secular authorities for the punishment deemed fitting by the Church.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lea|first=Henry Charles|authorlink=|title=A History of the Inquisition In The Middle Ages|origdate=|origmonth=|accessdate=2009-10-07|edition=|series=|volume=1|date=|year=|month=|publisher=|location=|pages=|chapter=Chapter VII. The Inquisition Founded|chapterurl=http://bulfinch.englishatheist.org/mm/inquisition/Chapter7.htm|quote=Obstinate heretics, refusing to abjure and return to the Church with due penance, and those who after abjuration relapsed, were to be abandoned to the secular arm for fitting punishment.|isbn=1-152-29621-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The laws were inclusive of proscriptions against certain religious crimes (heresy, etc.), and the punishments included death by burning, although imprisonment often for life or banishment could be used. Thus the inquisitors generally knew what would be the fate of anyone so remanded, and cannot be considered to have divorced the means of determining guilt from its effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Kirsch|first=Jonathan|authorlink=|title=The Grand Inquisitors Manual: A History of Terror in the Name of God|origmonth=|accessdate=2010-06-04|publisher=HarperOne|location=|isbn=0-06-081699-6|origyear=2008-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Purpose==
The 1578 handbook for inquisitors spelled out the purpose of inquisitorial penalties: ''... quoniam punitio non refertur primo &amp; per se in correctionem &amp; bonum eius qui punitur, sed in bonum publicum ut alij terreantur, &amp; a malis committendis avocentur.'' Translation from the Latin: ''... for punishment does not take place primarily and per se for the correction and good of the person punished, but for the public good in order that others may become terrified and weaned away from the evils they would commit.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;''[[Directorium Inquisitorum]]'', edition of 1578, Book 3, pg. 137, column 1. Online in the [http://dlxs2.library.cornell.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=witch;cc=witch;q1=terre%2A;rgn=full%20text;idno=wit045;didno=wit045;view=image;seq=00000563 Cornell University Collection]; retrieved 2008-05-16.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Movements==
[[File:Escudo inquisicion.gif|thumb|Emblem of the Inquisition.]]
{{Anchor|Historic Inquisition movements}}
{{pov|date=October 2012}}
&lt;!--No references to these -stark- claims:: Because of its objective — combating heresy — the Inquisition had jurisdiction only over baptised members of the Church (which, however, encompassed the vast majority of the population in Catholic countries). Different areas faced different situations with regard to heresies and suspicion of heresies.--&gt;

Most of Medieval Western and Central Europe had a long-standing veneer of Catholic standardisation over traditional non-Christian practices, with intermittent localized occurrences of different ideas (such as [[Catharism]] or [[Platonism in the Renaissance|Platonism]]) and constantly recurring [[Religious antisemitism|anti-Semitic]] or [[anti-Judaism|anti-Judaic]] activity and conspiration.{{clarify|This needs to be stated more objectively. It is worded pov|date=October 2012}}

Exceptionally, Portugal and Spain in the late Middle Ages consisted largely of multicultural territories of Muslim and Jewish influence, conquered from the [[Islam]]ic states of [[Al-Andalus]] control, and the new Christian authorities could not assume that all their subjects would suddenly become and remain orthodox Catholics. So the Inquisition in [[Iberian Peninsula|Iberia]], in the lands of the [[Reconquista]] counties and kingdoms like [[Kingdom of León|Leon]], [[Kingdom of Castile|Castile]] and [[Kingdom of Aragon|Aragon]], had a special socio-political basis as well as more fundamentalistic religious motives. Later followed [[County of Portugal|Portugal]] in this fundamentalistic christianisation.{{clarify|I don't think Portugal was lumped together with Spain in the Inquisitions|date=October 2012}}

With the [[Protestant Reformation]], Catholic authorities became much more ready to suspect heresy in any new ideas,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Stokes|first=Adrian Durham|authorlink= Adrian Stokes (critic)|title=Michelangelo: a study in the nature of art|url=http://books.google.com/?id=_E7epqLi2CwC|accessdate= 2009-11-26|edition=2|series=Routledge classics|origyear=1955|year=2002|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-26765-6|page=39|pages=166|quote=Ludovico is so immediately settled in heaven by the poet that some commentators have divined that Michelangel is voicing heresy, that is to say, the denial of purgatory.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
including those of [[Renaissance humanism]],&lt;ref&gt;Erasmus, the arch-Humanist of the Renaissance, came under suspicion of heresy, see
{{cite book|last=Olney|first=Warren|title=Desiderius Erasmus; Paper Read Before the Berkeley Club, March 18, 1920.|url=http://books.google.com/?id=EdsdOSs6VRgC|accessdate=2009-11-26|year=2009|publisher=BiblioBazaar|isbn=978-1-113-40503-6|page=15|pages=32|quote=Thomas More, in an elaborate defense of his friend, written to a cleric who accused Erasmus of heresy, seems to admit that Erasmus was probably the author of ''Julius''.}}&lt;/ref&gt; previously strongly supported by many at the top of the Church hierarchy. The extirpation of heretics became a much broader and more complex enterprise, complicated by the politics of territorial Protestant powers, especially in northern Europe. The Catholic Church could no longer exercise direct influence in the politics and justice-systems of lands which officially adopted Protestantism. Thus war (the [[French Wars of Religion]], the [[Thirty Years War]]), massacre (the [[St. Bartholomew's Day massacre]]) and the missional&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Vidmar|first=John C.|authorlink=John Vidmar|title=The Catholic Church Through the Ages|year= 2005|publisher=Paulist Press|location=New York|isbn=978-0-8091-4234-7|page=241|pages=360}}&lt;/ref&gt; and propaganda work (by the [[Sacra congregatio de propaganda fide]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Soergel|first=Philip M.|title=Wondrous in His Saints: Counter Reformation Propaganda in Bavaria|year=1993|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|isbn=0-520-08047-5|pages=239}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the [[Counter-Reformation]] came to play larger roles in these circumstances, and the [[roman law]] type of a &quot;judicial&quot; approach to heresy represented by the Inquisition became less important overall.

Historians distinguish four different manifestations of the Christian Inquisition:
# the [[Medieval Inquisition]] (1184–16th century), including
## the [[Episcopal Inquisition]] (1184–1230s)
## the [[Papal Inquisition]] (1230s) and following Christian inquisitions
# the [[Spanish Inquisition]] (1478–1834)
# the [[Portuguese Inquisition]] (1536–1821)
# the [[Roman Inquisition]] (1542 – c. 1860)

===Medieval Inquisition===
{{Main|Medieval Inquisition}}
Historians use the term &quot;Medieval Inquisition&quot; to describe the various inquisitions that started around 1184, including the ''Episcopal Inquisition'' (1184–1230s) and later the ''[[Papal Inquisition]]'' (1230s). These inquisitions responded to large popular movements throughout Europe considered [[apostasy|apostate]] or heretical to [[Christianity]], in particular the [[Cathars]] in southern France and the [[Waldensians]] in both southern France and northern Italy. Other Inquisitions followed after these first inquisition movements. Legal basis for some inquisitorial activity came from [[Pope Innocent IV]]'s [[papal bull]] ''[[Ad extirpanda]]'' of 1252, which authorized and regulated the use of [[torture]] in investigating heresy.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Spanish Inquisition===
{{Main|Spanish Inquisition}}

[[File:Pedro Berruguete - Saint Dominic Presiding over an Auto-da-fe (1475).jpg|right|thumb| [[Pedro Berruguete]], ''Saint Dominic Presides over an Auto da Fe'' (c. 1495).&lt;ref name=&quot;Prado&quot;&gt;
[http://www.museodelprado.es/en/the-collection/online-gallery/on-line-gallery/obra/saint-dominic-presides-over-an-auto-da-fe/?no_cache=1 ''Saint Dominic Presides over an Auto da Fe''], [[Prado Museum]]. Retrieved 2012-08-26&lt;/ref&gt; Many artistic representations depict torture and [[execution by burning|burning at the stake]] as occurring during the ''[[auto-da-fé]]'' (Spanish for &quot;Act of Faith&quot;).]]

King [[Ferdinand II of Aragon]] and Queen [[Isabella I of Castile]] established the [[Spanish Inquisition]] in 1478. In contrast to the previous inquisitions, it operated completely under royal Christian authority, though staffed by clergy and orders, and independently of the [[Holy See]]. It operated in Spain and in all Spanish colonies and territories, which included the [[Canary Islands]], the [[Spanish Netherlands]], the [[Kingdom of Naples]], and all Spanish possessions in North, Central, and South America. It primarily targeted forced converts from Islam ([[Morisco]]s, [[Converso]]s and ''secret Moors'') and from [[Judaism]] ([[Converso]]s, [[Crypto-Judaism|Crypto-Jews]] and [[Marrano]]s) &amp;mdash; both groups still resided in Spain after the end of the [[Al-Andalus|Islamic control of Spain]] &amp;mdash; who came under suspicion of either continuing to adhere to their old religion or of having fallen back into it. Somewhat later the Spanish Inquisition took an interest in  [[Protestants]] of virtually any sect, notably in the [[Spanish Netherlands]], in heresy, and in witchcraft. In the [[Habsburg Spain|Spanish]] possessions of the [[Kingdom of Sicily]] and the [[Kingdom of Naples]] in southern Italy, which formed part of the Spanish Crown's hereditary possessions, it also targeted [[Greek Orthodox]] Christians.{{cn|date=October 2012}}

In the Americas, King Philip II set up two tribunals (each formally titled ''Tribunal del Santo Oficio de la Inquisición'') in 1569, one in [[Mexican Inquisition|Mexico]] and the other in [[Peruvian Inquisition|Peru]]. The Mexican office administered [[Real Audiencia of Mexico|Mexico]] (central and southeastern Mexico), [[Nueva Galicia]] (northern and western Mexico), the [[Audiencia Real|Audiencia]]s of [[Guatemala]] (Guatemala, Chiapas, El Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua, Costa Rica), and the [[Spanish East Indies]].  The Peruvian Inquisition, based in Lima, administered all the Spanish territories in South America and Panama.{{cn|date=October 2012}}

In Spain the institution survived until 1834.

===Portuguese Inquisition===
{{Main|Portuguese Inquisition}}
[[File:1685 - Inquisição Portugal.jpg|thumb|left|A copper engraving from 1685: &quot;Die Inquisition in Portugall&quot;]]

The Portuguese Inquisition formally started in [[Portugal]] in 1536 at the request of the [[King of Portugal]], [[João III]]. [[Manuel I of Portugal|Manuel I]] had asked [[Pope Leo X]] for the installation of the Inquisition in 1515, but only after his death (1521) did [[Pope Paul III]] acquiesce. The Portuguese Inquisition principally targeted the [[Sephardic Jews]], whom the state forced to convert to Christianity. Spain had expelled its Sephardic population in 1492 (see [[Alhambra decree]]); after 1492 many of these Spanish Jews left Spain for Portugal, but eventually were targeted there as well. The Portuguese Inquisition came under the authority of the King. At its head stood a [[Grande Inquisidor]], or General Inquisitor, named by the Pope but selected by the Crown, and always from within the [[royal family]].{{cn|date=October 2012}}

The Portuguese Inquisition held its first ''auto-da-fé'' in 1540. It concentrated its efforts on rooting out converts from other faiths (overwhelmingly [[Judaism]]) who did not adhere to the observances of Catholic orthodoxy; the Portuguese inquisitors mostly targeted the [[Jew]]ish &quot;[[New Christians]]&quot; (i.e. [[conversos]] or [[marranos]]). The Portuguese Inquisition expanded its scope of operations from Portugal to Portugal's [[colony|colonial]] possessions, including [[Brazil]], [[Cape Verde]], and [[Goa]], where it continued as a religious court, investigating and trying cases of breaches of the tenets of orthodox [[Roman Catholic]]ism until 1821. King [[John III of Portugal|João III]] (reigned 1521–57) extended the activity of the courts to cover [[censorship]], [[divination]], [[witchcraft]] and [[bigamy]]. Originally oriented for a religious action, the Inquisition had an influence in almost every aspect of Portuguese society: politically, culturally and socially. The [[Goa Inquisition]], an inquisition largely aimed at Catholic converts from [[Hinduism]] or [[Islam]] who were thought to have returned to their original ways, started in [[Goa]] in 1560. In addition, the Inquisition prosecuted non-converts who broke prohibitions against the observance of [[Hindu]] or Muslim rites or interfered with Portuguese attempts to convert non-Christians to Catholicism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Salomon, H. P 2001 pp. 345-7&quot;&gt;Salomon, H. P. and Sassoon, I. S. D., in Saraiva, Antonio Jose. ''The Marrano Factory. The Portuguese Inquisition and Its New Christians, 1536-1765'' (Brill, 2001), pgs. 345-7&lt;/ref&gt; Aleixo Dias Falcão and Francisco Marques set it up in the palace of the [[Sabaio]] [[Adil Khan]].

According to [[Henry Charles Lea]]&lt;ref&gt;[[H.C. Lea]], ''A History of the Inquisition of Spain'', vol. 3, Book 8&lt;/ref&gt; between 1540 and 1794 tribunals in Lisbon, Porto, Coimbra and Évora resulted in the burning of 1,175 persons, the burning of another 633 in effigy, and the penancing of 29,590. But documentation of 15 out of 689&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book|first1=António José|last1=Saraiva|author1-link=|first2=Herman Prins|last2=Salomon|author2-link=|firstn=I. S. D.|lastn= Sassoon|title=The Marrano Factory: the Portuguese Inquisition and its New Christians 1536-1765|url=http://books.google.com/?id=eG8xUFivagkC|accessdate=2010-04-13|origyear=First published in Portuguese in 1969|year=2001|publisher=Brill|location=|isbn=978-90-04-12080-8|page=102|pages=402|quote=|author8-link=Isaac S.D. Sassoon|author3=Sassoon, I. S. D
}}&lt;/ref&gt; autos-da-fé has disappeared, so these numbers may slightly understate the activity. In the wake of the [[Liberal Revolution of 1820]], the &quot;General Extraordinary and Constituent [[Court]]s of the Portuguese Nation&quot; abolished the Portuguese inquisition in 1821.

===Roman Inquisition===
{{Main|Roman Inquisition}}
In 1542 [[Pope Paul III]] established the '''Congregation of the Holy Office of the Inquisition''' as a permanent congregation staffed with [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinals]] and other officials. It had the tasks of maintaining and defending the integrity of the faith and of examining and proscribing errors and false doctrines; it thus became the supervisory body of local Inquisitions.&lt;!--pretty much copied from:--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
[http://galileo.rice.edu/chr/inquisition.html &quot;Christianity | The Inquisition&quot;.] The Galileo Project. Retrieved 2012-08-26&lt;/ref&gt; Arguably the most famous case tried by the Roman Inquisition involved [[Galileo Galilei]] in 1633.

The penances and sentences for those who confessed or were found guilty were pronounced together in a public ceremony at the end of all the processes. This was the ''sermo generalis'' or ''[[auto-da-fé]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia
 | last = Blötzer
 | first = J.
 | encyclopedia = The Catholic Encyclopedia
 | title = Inquisition
 | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08026a.htm
 | accessdate = 2012-08-26
 | year = 1910
 | publisher = Robert Appleton Company
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Penances (not matters for the Civil Authorities) might consist of a pilgrimage, a public scourging, a fine, or the wearing of a cross. The wearing of two tongues of red or other brightly colored cloth, sewn onto an outer garment in an &quot;X&quot; pattern, marked those who were under investigation. The penalties in serious cases were confiscation of property to the inquisition or imprisonment. This lead to the possibility of false charges over confiscation with those over a certain income, particularly rich [[maranos]]

Following the [[Papal States#French Revolution and Napoleonic era|French invasion]] of 1798, the new authorities sent 3,000 chests containing over 100,000 Inquisition documents to France from Rome. After the restoration of the Pope as the ruler of the [[Papal States]] after 1814, Roman Inquisition activity continued until the mid-19th century, notably in the well-publicised [[Mortara Affair]] (1858–1870). In 1908 the name of the Congregation became &quot;The Sacred Congregation of the Holy Office&quot;, which in 1965 further changed to &quot;[[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]]&quot;, as retained to {{As of|2008|alt=the present day}}. The Pope appoints a cardinal to preside over the Congregation, which usually includes ten other cardinals, as well as a [[prelate]] and two assistants, all chosen from the [[Dominican Order]]. The &quot;Holy Office&quot; also has an international group of consultants, experienced scholars in theology and canon law, who advise it on specific questions.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Reputation(s)==
{{Expand section|date=January 2010}}
With the sharpening of debate and of conflict between the Protestant [[Reformation]] and the Catholic [[Counter-Reformation]], Protestant societies came to see/use the Inquisition as a terrifying &quot;[[Other]]&quot; trope,&lt;ref&gt;
Compare {{cite book|last=Haydon|first=Colin|authorlink=|title=Anti-Catholicism in eighteenth-century England, c. 1714-80: a political and social study|url=http://books.google.com/?id=GR68AAAAIAAJ|accessdate=2010-02-28|series=Studies in imperialism|year=1993|publisher=Manchester University Press|location=Manchester|isbn=0-7190-2859-0|page=6|pages=276|quote=The popular fear of Popery focused on the persecution of heretics by the Catholics. It was generally assumed that, whenever it was in their power, Papists would extirpate heresy by force, seeing it as a religious duty. History seemed to show this all too clearly. [...] The Inquisition had suppressed, and continued to check, religious dissent in Spain. Papists, and most of all, the Pope, delighted in the slaughter of heretics. 'I most firmly believed when I was as boy', [[William Cobbett]] [born 1763], coming originally from rural Surrey, recalled, 'that the Pope was a prodigious woman, dressed in a dreadful robe, which had been made red by being dipped in the blood of Protestants'.}}&lt;/ref&gt; while staunch Catholics regarded the Holy Office as a necessary bulwark against the spread of reprehensible heresies. So it is necessary to realise evidence shows that those involved with the inquisition sincerely thought that they were doing God's work in extirpating what they considered [[heresy]] and opposition to the Roman Church. The very title of the humiliating spectacles of the '[[auto-da-fe]]' which means 'act of faith' shows this. Their acts were a consequence of their beliefs rather than any initial [[pathology]]: as for example in the Decretal of [[Pope Gregory IX]], BkV tit9. ''Crucesignati ad exterminationem heriticorum gaudent'' 'make the sign of the cross to the destruction of heretics rejoicing'.

==Derivative works==
Some of the fictional works mentioned below reflect the popular reputation of the Inquisition as much as its historicity.

The Inquisitions appear in many cultural works. Some include:
* [[Voltaire]]'s satire ''[[Candide]]'' (1759) has a scene featuring the Portuguese Inquisition, with the title character and Dr. Pangloss both found guilty of heresy.
* The short story by [[Edgar Allan Poe]], &quot;[[The Pit and the Pendulum]]&quot; (1842) takes place against the background of the Spanish Inquisition.
* ''[[The Grand Inquisitor]]'', a parable told by Ivan to Alyosha in Fyodor Dostoevsky's novel ''[[The Brothers Karamazov]]'' (1879–1880).
* [[The Spanish Inquisition (Monty Python)|The Spanish Inquisition]], the subject of a classic [[Monty Python]] sketch of 1970 (&quot;''Nobody'' expects the Spanish Inquisition!&quot;), became referenced conspicuously in the film ''[[Sliding Doors]]'' (1998).
* In [[Terry Pratchett]]'s ''[[Small Gods]]'', the [[Omnian]] church has a Quisition, with sub-sections called Inquisition and Exquisition: &quot;... some of the inquisitors had an enviable knowledge of the insides of the human body that is denied to all those who are not allowed to open it while it's still working ...&quot;
* In the [[Warhammer 40,000]] universe, the Holy Inquisition is one of the most powerful and influential factions in the Imperium of Man. Divided into many divisions (&quot;ordos&quot;), its agents are sworn to defend the Imperium from all threats, foreign and domestic. Inquisitors are authorised to burn entire planets and condemn billions of innocent souls to death in pursuit of this sacred duty. The three most prominent divisions of the Inquisition are the Ordo Xenos (which specialises in the study and destruction of aliens), the Ordo Malleus (demon slayers) and the Ordo Hereticus (witch hunters).
* In [[J.K. Rowling]]'s 2003 book ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]'', Professor Dolores Umbridge sets up an Inquisition at the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry], with herself as the High Inquisitor.
* ''[[Man of La Mancha]]'', a Broadway musical, tells the story of the classic novel ''[[Don Quixote]]'' as a play-within-a-play performed by prisoners as they await a hearing with the Spanish Inquisition.
* [[Arturo Ripstein]]'s 1973 film [[The Holy Office (film)|''The Holy Office'']] (''El santo oficio'') about the Inquisition in New Spain (Mexico).
* The 2006 film ''[[Goya's Ghosts]]'' features the Spanish Inquisition. The painter Goya attempts to save his muse, Ines, from persecution by the Holy Office.

==See also==
* [[Black Legend]]
* [[Historical revision of the Inquisition]]
* [[Inquisitorial system]]
* [[Marian Persecutions]]: Roman Catholic heretic-hunting in [[Tudor England]]
* [[Vatican Secret Archives]]

===Documents and works===
* ''[[Directorium Inquisitorum]]''
* ''[[Histoire de l'Inquisition en France]]''
* ''[[Malleus Maleficarum]]''

===Notable inquisitors===
* [[Grand Inquisitor|List of Grand Inquisitors]]
* [[Konrad von Marburg]]
* [[Tomás de Torquemada]]
* [[Bernardo Gui]]

===Notable cases===
* [[Trial of Joan of Arc]]
* [[Galileo affair|Trial of Galileo Galilei]]
* [[Edgardo Mortara|Edgardo Mortara's abduction]]
* [[Logroño trials]] against Basque witches.
* [[Giordano Bruno#Imprisonment, trial and execution, 1592–1600|Execution of Giordano Bruno]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite journal|doi=10.2307/1450541|last=Adler|first=E. N.|authorlink=Elkan Nathan Adler|year=1901|month=April|title=Auto de fe and Jew|journal=The [[Jewish Quarterly Review]]|volume=13|issue=3|pages=392–437|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|location=|issn=|jstor=1450541}}
* Burman, Edward, ''The Inquisition: The Hammer of Heresy'' (Sutton Publishers, 2004) ISBN 0-7509-3722-X. A new edition of a book first published in 1984, a general history based on the main primary sources.
* [[Warren H. Carroll|Carroll, Warren H.]], ''Isabel: the Catholic Queen'' Front Royal, Virginia, 1991 (Christendom Press)
* {{cite book|last=Foxe|first=John|authorlink=John Foxe|editor1-last=Chadwick|editor1-first=Harold J.|title=[[Foxe's Book of Martyrs|The new Foxe's book of martyrs/John Foxe; rewritten and updated by Harold J. Chadwick]]|origyear=1563|year=1997|publisher=Bridge-Logos|location=|language=|isbn=0-88270-672-1}}
* Given, James B, ''Inquisition and Medieval Society'' (Cornell University Press, 2001)
* Kamen, Henry, ''The Spanish Inquisition: A Historical Revision.'' (Yale University Press, 1999); ISBN 0-300-07880-3. This revised edition of his 1965 original contributes to the understanding of the Spanish Inquisition in its local context.
* [[Henry Charles Lea|Lea, Henry Charles]], ''A History of the Inquisition of Spain'', 4 volumes (New York and London, 1906–7)
* {{cite journal|last=Parker|first=Geoffrey|year=1982|title=Some Recent Work on the Inquisition in Spain and Italy|journal=Journal of Modern History|volume=54|issue=3}}
* Peters, Edward M., ''Inquisition'' (University of California Press, 1989); ISBN 0-520-06630-8
* {{cite book
|last= Twiss
|first= Miranda
|title= The Most Evil Men And Women In History
|year= 2002
|publisher= Michael O'Mara Books Ltd
|isbn= 978-1-85479-488-8}}
* [[William Thomas Walsh|Walsh, William Thomas]], ''Characters of the Inquisition'' (TAN Books and Publishers, Inc, 1940/97); ISBN 0-89555-326-0
* Whitechapel, Simon, ''Flesh Inferno: Atrocities of Torquemada and the Spanish Inquisition'' (Creation Books, 2003); ISBN 1-84068-105-5

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikisource}}
* [http://www.bede.org.uk/inquisition.htm Frequently Asked Questions About the Inquisition] by James Hannam
* {{Cite Americana|short=1|wstitle=Inquisition|year=1920}}
* [http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/History/Inquisition.html Jewish Virtual Library on the Spanish Inquisition]

&lt;!--spacing, please do not remove--&gt;

{{Christian History|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Inquisition| ]]
[[Category:Religious law]]
[[Category:Counter-Reformation]]
[[Category:Anti-Protestantism]]
[[Category:Christianity-related controversies]]
[[Category:Censorship in Christianity]]
[[Category:Antisemitism]]
[[Category:Catholic terms]]

{{Link GA|de}}
{{Link GA|pl}}
[[af:Inkwisisie]]
[[ar:محاكم التفتيش]]
[[an:Enquesición]]
[[ast:Inquisición]]
[[az:İnkvizisiya]]
[[ba:Инквизиция]]
[[be:Святая інквізіцыя]]
[[be-x-old:Сьвятая інквізыцыя]]
[[bg:Инквизиция]]
[[bar:Inquisition]]
[[bs:Inkvizicija]]
[[br:Ofis santel]]
[[ca:Inquisició]]
[[cs:Inkvizice]]
[[da:Inkvisition]]
[[de:Inquisition]]
[[et:Inkvisitsioon]]
[[el:Ιερά Εξέταση]]
[[es:Inquisición]]
[[eo:Inkvizicio]]
[[eu:Inkisizioa]]
[[fa:تفتیش عقاید]]
[[fr:Inquisition]]
[[fy:Ynkwisysje]]
[[ga:An tIonchoisne]]
[[gl:Inquisición]]
[[ko:종교 재판]]
[[hy:Ինկվիզիցիա]]
[[hi:न्यायाधिकरण (इनक्विज़िशन)]]
[[hr:Inkvizicija]]
[[io:Inquiziciono]]
[[id:Inkuisisi]]
[[it:Inquisizione]]
[[he:אינקוויזיציה]]
[[ka:ინკვიზიცია]]
[[lad:Inkisizion]]
[[la:Inquisitio haereticae pravitatis]]
[[lv:Inkvizīcija]]
[[lt:Inkvizicija]]
[[hu:Inkvizíció]]
[[mk:Инквизиција]]
[[ml:മതവിചാരണകൾ]]
[[arz:محاكم التفتيش]]
[[ms:Pasitan]]
[[nl:Inquisitie]]
[[ja:異端審問]]
[[no:Inkvisisjonen]]
[[nn:Inkvisisjonen]]
[[oc:Inquisicion]]
[[pl:Inkwizycja]]
[[pt:Inquisição]]
[[ro:Inchiziție]]
[[qu:Inkisisyun]]
[[ru:Святая инквизиция]]
[[sah:Инквизиция]]
[[sq:Inkuizicioni]]
[[scn:Santa Nquisizzioni]]
[[simple:Inquisition]]
[[sk:Inkvizícia]]
[[sl:Inkvizicija]]
[[sr:Инквизиција]]
[[sh:Inkvizicija]]
[[fi:Inkvisitio]]
[[sv:Inkvisitionen]]
[[tr:Engizisyon]]
[[uk:Інквізиція]]
[[zh:宗教裁判所]]</text>
      <sha1>ac4iw04wki4eoosjw18idck5v0ont0p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
