<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Irresistible grace</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>902776</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519370981</id>
      <parentid>519370882</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T11:28:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.169.107.53</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Biblical passages related to the doctrine */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19056">{{Grace in Christianity}}
{{Unbalanced|date=May 2010}}
{{Calvinism}}
'''Irresistible Grace''' (or '''efficacious grace''') is a [[doctrine]] in [[Christian theology]] particularly associated with [[Calvinism]], which teaches that the saving [[Divine grace|grace]] of [[God]] is effectually applied to those whom he has determined to save (the [[predestination|elect]]) and, in God's timing, overcomes their resistance to obeying the call of the [[gospel]], bringing them to [[faith]] in [[Jesus|Christ]].

==The doctrine==
According to Calvinism, those who obtain [[salvation]] do so, not by their own &quot;free&quot; will, but because of the sovereign grace of God. That is, men yield to grace, not finally because their [[conscience]]s were more tender or their faith more tenacious than that of other men. Rather, the willingness and ability to do God's will, are evidence of God's own faithfulness to save men from the power and the penalty of [[sin]], and since man is so corrupt that he will not decide and cannot be wooed to follow after God, God must powerfully intervene. In short, Calvinism argues that [[Regeneration (theology)|regeneration]] must precede faith.

[[John Calvin|Calvin]] says of this intervention that &quot;it is not violent, so as to compel men by external force; but still it is a powerful impulse of the Holy Spirit, which makes men willing who formerly were unwilling and reluctant,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=[[John Calvin]] |chapterurl=http://ccel.org/ccel/calvin/calcom34.xii.vii.html |chapter=John 6:41-45 |title=Commentary on John |volume=1 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[John Gill (theologian)|John Gill]] says that &quot;this act of drawing is an act of power, yet not of force; God in drawing of unwilling, makes willing in the day of His power: He enlightens the understanding, bends the will, gives an heart of flesh, sweetly allures by the power of His grace, and engages the soul to come to Christ, and give up itself to Him; he draws with the bands of love. Drawing, though it supposes power and influence, yet not always coaction and force: music draws the ear, love the heart, and pleasure the mind.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=John Gill |authorlink=John Gill (theologian) |chapterurl=http://bible.crosswalk.com/Commentaries/GillsExpositionoftheBible/gil.cgi?book=joh&amp;chapter=006&amp;verse=044&amp;next=045&amp;prev=043 |chapter=John 6:44 |title=John Gill's Exposition of the Bible |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jonathan Edwards (theologian)|Jonathan Edwards]] has sometimes been quoted&amp;mdash;notably by [[R. C. Sproul]]&amp;mdash;as referring to the irresistible call of God as the &quot;holy [[raptus|rape]] of the soul,&quot; but the phrase does not appear in Edwards' ''Works''. Instead, the phrase seems to have been coined by [[Puritan]] [[scholar]] Perry Miller, and many Calvinists distance themselves from it.{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}}

===Objections to the doctrine===
====Arminian====
[[Christianity|Christians]] associated with [[Arminianism]], notably followers of [[John Wesley]] and part of the [[Methodism|Methodist movement]], reject the Calvinist doctrine. Instead, they believe that God's [[prevenient grace]] is equally provided to all human beings alike, drawing them toward His love and salvation. In this view, (1) after God's universal dispensation of grace to mankind, the will of man, which was formerly adverse to God and unable to obey, can now choose to obey; and (2) although God's grace is a strong initial move to effect salvation, it can ultimately be resisted and rejected.

Both sides agree that the resistibility of grace is inexorably bound up with the theological system's view of humanity's [[total depravity|inability]] to respond to God and of the extent of God's [[Divine grace|grace]]. As Calvinist [[Charles Hodge]] says, &quot;The ([[Arminian]]) and ([[Roman Catholic]]) doctrine is true, if the other parts of their doctrinal system are true; and it is false if that system be erroneous. If the (Calvinistic) doctrine concerning the natural state of man since the fall, and the sovereignty of God in election, be Scriptural, then it is certain that sufficient grace does not become efficacious from the cooperation of the human will.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=[[Charles Hodge]] |chapterurl=http://ccel.org/ccel/hodge/theology2.iv.xiv.iii.html |chapter=Efficacious Grace |title=Systematic Theology |volume=2 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus the passages discussing those doctrines are also relevant here.

====Lutheran====
Like Calvinists, [[Lutheranism|Lutherans]] view the work of [[salvation]] as [[monergism|monergistic]] in which an unconverted or unrepentant person always resists and rejects God and his ways.&lt;ref&gt;[[Formula of Concord]]: [http://www.bookofconcord.org/fc-sd/freewill.html Solid Declaration, art. ii, par. 71]; [http://www.bookofconcord.org/fc-sd/freewill.html par. 18]&lt;/ref&gt; Even during conversion, the [[Formula of Concord]] says, humans resist &quot;the Word and will of God, until God awakens him from the death of sin, enlightens and renews him.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bookofconcord.org/fc-sd/freewill.html Solid Declaration, art. ii, par. 59]&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, they both see the preaching of the gospel as a [[means of grace]] by which God offers salvation.

Calvinists distinguish between a resistible, outward call to salvation given to all who hear the [[free offer of the gospel]], and an efficacious, inward work by the Holy Spirit. Every person is unwilling to follow the outward call to salvation until, as the [[Westminster Confession]] puts it, &quot;being quickened and renewed by the Holy Spirit, he is thereby enabled to answer this call, and to embrace the grace offered and conveyed by it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://reformed.org/documents/wcf_with_proofs/ch_X.html Westminster Confession of Faith, X.1,2].&lt;/ref&gt; Once inwardly renewed, every person freely follows God and his ways as &quot;not only the obligatory but the preferable good,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |chapterurl=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/boettner/predest.iv.v.html#iv.v-p28.2 |title=The Reformed Doctrine of Predestination |author=[[Loraine Boettner]] |chapter=Efficacious Grace |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and hence that special renewing grace is always effective.

Contrary to the Calvinist position, Lutherans hold that whenever the Holy Spirit works outwardly through the Word and sacraments, he always acts inwardly through them as well. Unlike Calvinists, Lutherans believe the Holy Spirit always works [[Efficacy|efficaciously]].&lt;ref name=WELSFAQ&gt;See [http://www.wels.net/cgi-bin/site.pl?1518&amp;cuTopic_topicID=10&amp;cuItem_itemID=15094 Calvinism and Lutheranism compared]&lt;/ref&gt; The Word heard by those that resist it is just as efficacious as the Word preached to those that [[Lutheranism#Conversion|convert]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Henry Eyster Jacobs]]: [http://showcase.netins.net/web/bilarson/jacobs19.txt A Summary of the Christian Faith]. Philadelphia: General Council of the Evangelical Lutheran Church in North America, 1905, pp. 216-17, {{cite book |last=Engelder |first=Theodore E.W. |url=http://www.archive.org/details/MN41551ucmf_1 |title=Popular Symbolics: The Doctrines of the Churches of Christendom and Of Other Religious Bodies Examined in the Light of Scripture |page=58 |location=Saint Louis, MO |publisher=Concordia Publishing House |year=1934}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Formula of Concord]] teaches that when humans reject the calling of the Holy Spirit, it is not a result of the Word being less efficacious. Instead, contempt for the means of grace is the result of &quot;the perverse will of man, which rejects or perverts the means and instrument of the Holy Ghost, which God offers him through the call, and resists the Holy Ghost, who wishes to be efficacious, and works through the Word...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bookofconcord.org/sd-election.php Solid Declaration, article xi, &quot;Election&quot;, par. 41]&lt;/ref&gt;

Lutherans are certain that the work of the Holy Spirit does not occur merely alongside the means of grace to regenerate, but instead is an integral part of them, always working through them wherever they are found. Lutherans teach that the Holy Spirit limits himself to working only through the means of grace and nowhere else.&lt;ref&gt;[[Smalcald Articles]], [http://www.bookofconcord.org/smalcald.php#confession part 8, &quot;Of Confession&quot;]: &quot;[I]n those things which concern the spoken, outward Word, we must firmly hold that God grants His Spirit or grace to no one, except through or with the preceding outward Word.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; so that those who reject the means of grace are simultaneously resisting and rejecting the Holy Spirit and the grace he brings.&lt;ref name=&quot;WELSFAQ&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wels.net/cgi-bin/site.pl?1518&amp;cuTopic_topicID=10&amp;cuItem_itemID=15094 |title=Calvinism and Lutheranism compared |accessdate=2009-03-30 |publisher=[[Wisconsin Evangelical Lutheran Synod]]}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Biblical passages related to the doctrine===
{{TULIP}}
The statement of [[Paul of Tarsus|St. Paul]] is said to confirm that those whom God [[Effectual calling|effectually calls]] necessarily come to full salvation: &quot;(T)hose whom (God) predestined He also called, and those whom He called He also justified, and those whom He justified He also glorified&quot; ([[Epistle to the Romans|Romans]] 8:28,30), but it is especially several verses from the [[John 6|sixth chapter]] of the [[Gospel of John]], which contains a record of Jesus' teaching on humanity's abilities and God's activities in salvation, that serves as the central [[proof text]] for the Calvinist doctrine:

* John 6:37,39: &quot;All that the Father gives me will come to me.... And this is the will of Him who sent me, that I should lose nothing of all that He has given me, but raise it up on the last day.&quot;[ESV]
* John 6:44–45: &quot;No one can come to me unless the Father who sent me draws him.... Everyone who has heard and learned from the Father comes to me.&quot;[ESV]
* John 6:65: &quot;(N)o one can come to me unless it is granted him by the Father.&quot;[ESV]
-
Proponents of Arminianism argue that the word &quot;draw&quot; ([[Greek language|Greek]]: {{lang|grc|ἕλκω}}, ''helkô'')&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3D%2333771&amp;layout.reflookup=e%29lkusw&amp;layout.reflang=greek |author=[[Henry George Liddell]], Robert Scott |title=helkô |encyclopedia=[[A Greek-English Lexicon]] |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; as used in John 6:44 does not require the sense of &quot;drag&quot;, though they admit this is the word's usual meaning (as in [http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=John+18:10,21:6,21:11;Acts+16:19,21:30;James+2:6 Jn. 18:10; 21:6; 21:11; Acts 16:19; 21:30; Jas. 2:6]). They point to John 12:32 as an example: &quot;And I, when I am lifted up from the earth, will draw all people to myself.&quot; Arminians interpret this to mean that Jesus draws all people to Himself but some are able resist this drawing since, if the call is truly irresistible, then all must come to Christ and be saved. They may also note that in the [[Septuagint]] version of Jeremiah 38:13, when Jeremiah is lifted out of the pit where he was left to die, this Greek verb is used for the action which his rescuers performed after he voluntarily secured the ropes under his armpits, and that this rescue was certainly performed in cooperation with Jeremiah's wishes. Therefore, they may argue, even if the semantics of &quot;draw&quot; are understood in the usual sense, this should only be taken to indicate the source of the power, not the question of whether the person being drawn independently desires the drawing, or to indicate that the drawing is done irrespective of their wishes.

Calvinists argue that (1) the word &quot;draw&quot; should be understood according to its usual [[semantics]] in both John 6:44 and 12:32; (2) the word &quot;all&quot; (translated &quot;all people&quot; in v. 12:32) should be taken in the sense of &quot;all kinds of people&quot; rather than &quot;every individual&quot;; and thus (3) the former verse refers to an irresistible internal call to salvation and the latter to the opening of the [[Kingdom of God]] to the [[Gentile]]s, not a universal, resistible internal call. Some have asserted on this basis that the text of John 6:44 can [[Entailment|entail]] either [[universalism]] or Calvinism, but not Arminianism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.geocities.com/elenctictheology/John-644.pdf |title=A Logical Analysis - John 6:44 |author=Brian Bosse |date=2005-10-11 |accessdate=2009-03-26|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071202231421/http://www.geocities.com/elenctictheology/John-644.pdf|archivedate=2007-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Arminian [[William Barclay (theologian)|William Barclay]] argues that &quot;man's resistance can defeat the pull of God&quot; mentioned in John 6:44, but [[Biblical exegesis|commentator]] [[Leon Morris]] contends that &quot;(n)ot one of (Barclay's) examples of the verb ('draw') shows the resistance as successful. Indeed we can go further. There is not one example in the New Testament of the use of this verb where the resistance is successful. Always the drawing power is triumphant, as here.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=[[Leon Morris]] |title=The Gospel According to John |edition=revised |date=1995 |page=328, n. 116}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The conversion of Paul the Apostle demonstrates the total contingency of man's salvation upon the absolute sovereignty of God, without cooperation from the individual. Acts 9:1-19:

Saul’s Conversion

9 Meanwhile, Saul was still breathing out murderous threats against the Lord’s disciples. He went to the high priest 2 and asked him for letters to the synagogues in Damascus, so that if he found any there who belonged to the Way, whether men or women, he might take them as prisoners to Jerusalem. 3 As he neared Damascus on his journey, suddenly a light from heaven flashed around him. 4 He fell to the ground and heard a voice say to him, “Saul, Saul, why do you persecute me?”

5 “Who are you, Lord?” Saul asked.

“I am Jesus, whom you are persecuting,” he replied. 6 “Now get up and go into the city, and you will be told what you must do.”

7 The men traveling with Saul stood there speechless; they heard the sound but did not see anyone. 8 Saul got up from the ground, but when he opened his eyes he could see nothing. So they led him by the hand into Damascus. 9 For three days he was blind, and did not eat or drink anything.

10 In Damascus there was a disciple named Ananias. The Lord called to him in a vision, “Ananias!”

“Yes, Lord,” he answered.

11 The Lord told him, “Go to the house of Judas on Straight Street and ask for a man from Tarsus named Saul, for he is praying. 12 In a vision he has seen a man named Ananias come and place his hands on him to restore his sight.”

13 “Lord,” Ananias answered, “I have heard many reports about this man and all the harm he has done to your holy people in Jerusalem. 14 And he has come here with authority from the chief priests to arrest all who call on your name.”

15 But the Lord said to Ananias, “Go! This man is my chosen instrument to proclaim my name to the Gentiles and their kings and to the people of Israel. 16 I will show him how much he must suffer for my name.”

17 Then Ananias went to the house and entered it. Placing his hands on Saul, he said, “Brother Saul, the Lord—Jesus, who appeared to you on the road as you were coming here—has sent me so that you may see again and be filled with the Holy Spirit.” 18 Immediately, something like scales fell from Saul’s eyes, and he could see again. He got up and was baptized, 19 and after taking some food, he regained his strength.

==History of the doctrine==
{{Main|History of Calvinist-Arminian debate}}

In the Catholic Church, debates concerning the respective role of efficacious grace and [[free will]] led to the establishment of the [[Congregatio de Auxiliis]] at the end of the 16th century by the Pope [[Clement VIII]]. The [[Dominican Order|Dominicans]] insisted on the role of the efficacious grace, but the [[Jesuit]]s embraced [[Molinism]], which postulated greater liberty in the will. These debates also led to the famous [[formulary controversy]] in France which pitted the [[Jansenist]]s against the Jesuits.

The doctrine is one of the so-called [[Five points of Calvinism]] that were defined at the [[Synod of Dort]] during the [[Quinquarticular Controversy]] with the Arminian [[Remonstrants]], who objected to the general predestinarian scheme of Calvinism. In Calvinist churches, the doctrine is most often mentioned in comparisons with other salvific schemes and their respective doctrines about the state of mankind after [[The Fall of Man|the Fall]], and it is not a common topic for [[sermon]]s or studies otherwise.

==See also==
{{Portal box|Calvinism|Christianity}}
*[[Justification (theology)|Justification]]
*[[Prevenient grace]]
*[[Total depravity]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
===Pro===
*[http://www.pbministries.org/books/gill/Doctrinal_Divinity/Book_6/book6_12.htm &quot;Of Effectual Calling&quot;] from [[John Gill (theologian)|John Gill's]] ''Body of Doctrinal Divinity''
*[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/edwards/works2.xi.iv.html &quot;Concerning Efficacious Grace&quot;] by [[Jonathan Edwards (theologian)|Jonathan Edwards]]
*[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/hodge/theology2.iv.xiv.iii.html &quot;Efficacious Grace&quot;], section 3.14.4 from [[Charles Hodge]]'s ''Systematic Theology''
*[http://www.founders.org/FJ48/article5_fr.html &quot;On Regeneration&quot;], a sermon by [[Charles Spurgeon]]
*[http://www.the-highway.com/Irresistible_Murray.html &quot;Irresistible Grace&quot;] by [[John Murray (theologian)|John Murray]]
*[http://www.ccel.org/b/boettner/predest/13.htm &quot;Efficacious Grace&quot;], chapter 13 from [[Loraine Boettner]]'s ''The Reformed Doctrine of Predestination''
*[http://www.monergism.com/thethreshold/articles/onsite/sproul01.html &quot;Regeneration Precedes Faith&quot;] by [[R. C. Sproul]]
*[http://www.monergism.com/thethreshold/articles/piper/irresistable.html&lt;!--Sic--&gt; &quot;Irresistible Grace&quot;] by [[John Piper (theologian)|John Piper]]
*[http://www.monergism.com/thethreshold/articles/topic/irresistable.html&lt;!--Sic--&gt; Many articles] on irresistible grace by various authors

===Con===
* [http://gbgm-umc.org/umhistory/wesley/sermons/serm-058.stm Sermon #58: &quot;On Predestination&quot;] by [[John Wesley]]
* [http://gbgm-umc.org/umhistory/wesley/sermons/serm-128.stm Sermon #128: &quot;Free Grace&quot;] by [[John Wesley]]
* [http://www.biblelife.org/calvinism_grace.htm Irresistible Grace]
* [http://www.revneal.org/Writings/on.htm Prevenient Grace] by Gregory Neal
* [http://www.fwponline.cc/v23n1/johnsixPt1_witzki.html Calvinism and John 6: An Exegetical Response] by Steve Witzki
* [http://www.fwponline.cc/v19n1switzki.html Free Grace or Forced Grace?] by Steve Witski

{{ Christian Soteriology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Irresistible Grace}}
[[Category:Calvinism]]
[[Category:Christian soteriology]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[fr:Grâce irrésistible]]
[[id:Anugerah yang tidak dapat ditolak]]
[[ia:Gratia irresistibile]]
[[it:Grazia irresistibile]]
[[pl:Łaska skuteczna]]
[[pt:Vocação eficaz]]</text>
      <sha1>psc5a0nhlo5fp7wszcid3tjw5g9hy02</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
