<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Isaac</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15192</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522303954</id>
      <parentid>522185725</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T08:50:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Johnkatz1972</username>
        <id>6455386</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Western scholarly views */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29172">{{For|other people of this name}}
{{Infobox saint
|name=Isaac
|birth_date=
|death_date=
|feast_day=
|venerated_in=[[Judaism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Christianity]]&lt;br&gt;[[Islam]]
|image=Isaac a Lover of Peace.jpg
|imagesize=250px
|caption=''Isaac digging for the wells'', imagined in a [[Bible]] [[illustration]] (c. 1900)
|birth_place=[[Canaan]]
|death_place=[[Canaan]]
|titles=Prophet, Seer, Second Hebrew Patriarch, Father of Israel, Holy Forefather
|beatified_date=
|major_shrine=''[[Cave of the Patriarchs]]'', [[Hebron]]
|beatified_by=
|canonized_date=
|canonized_place=
|influences=His father [[Abraham]]
|attributes=
|influenced=[[Jacob]], the [[Twelve Tribes of Israel]] as well as many [[Jew]]s, [[Christian]]s and [[Muslim]]s
|suppressed_date=
|issues=
|prayer=
|prayer_attrib=
}}

'''Isaac''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|aɪ|z|ə|k}};&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Longman pronunciation dictionary |first=John C. |last= Wells |authorlink=John C. Wells |publisher=Longman |location=Harlow, England |year=1990 |isbn=0-582-05383-8 |page=378}} entry &quot;Isaac&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; {{Hebrew name|יִצְחָק|Yitsẖak|Yiṣḥāq}}, &lt;small&gt;[[ISO 259-3]]&lt;/small&gt; ''Yiçḥaq'', &quot;he will laugh&quot;; {{lang-yi|יצחק}}, {{transl|yi|''Yitskhok''}}; {{lang-grc|Ἰσαάκ}}, {{transl|grc|''Isaak''}}; {{lang-la|Isaac}}; {{lang-ar|إسحاق}} or {{lang-ar|إسحٰق}}{{ref|A|[note A]}} ''{{transl|ar|ʼIsḥāq}}'') as described in the [[Hebrew Bible]], was the only son [[Abraham]] had with his wife [[Sarah]], and was the father of [[Jacob]] and [[Esau]]. Isaac was one of the three [[patriarchs (Bible)|patriarchs]] of the [[Israelites]]. According to the [[Book of Genesis]], Abraham was 100&amp;nbsp;years old when Isaac was born, and Sarah was beyond childbearing years.

Isaac was the only biblical patriarch whose name was not changed, and the only one who did not leave [[Canaan]]. Compared to those of Abraham and Jacob, Isaac's story relates fewer incidents of his life. He died when he was 180&amp;nbsp;years old, making him the longest-lived patriarch.

==Etymology==
The [[Anglicisation|anglicized]] name Isaac is a transliteration of the Hebrew term ''{{Unicode|Yiṣḥāq}}'' which literally means &quot;He laughs/will laugh.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Strongs&quot;&gt;''[[Strong's Concordance]]'', Strong, James, ed., ''Isaac'', ''Isaac's'', [http://www.blueletterbible.org/lang/lexicon/lexicon.cfm?Strongs=H3327&amp;t=KJV 3327 יִצְחָק] 3446, ''2464''.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Ugaritic language|Ugaritic]] texts dating from the 13th century BCE refer to the benevolent smile of the [[Canaanite religion|Canaanite]] deity [[El (deity)|El]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Isaac&quot;/&gt; Genesis, however, ascribes the laughter to Isaac's parents, Abraham and Sarah, rather than El. According to the biblical narrative, Abraham fell on his face and laughed when [[Elohim]] imparted the news of their son's eventual birth. He laughed because Sarah was past the age of childbearing; both she and Abraham were advanced in age. Later, when Sarah overheard three messengers of the Lord renew the promise, she laughed inwardly for the same reason. Sarah denied laughing when Elohim questioned Abraham about it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse||Genesis|17:15–19|HE}} {{Bibleverse-nb||Genesis|18:10–15|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|chapter=Isaac|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=174&amp;letter=I&amp;search=Isaac|first=Isidore|last=Singer|authorlink=Isidore Singer|year=1901–1906|title=[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]|publisher=Funk &amp; Wagnalls|location=New York|first2=Isaac|last2=Broydé|authorlink2=Isaac Broydé|editor-first=Isidore|editor-last=Singer|editor-link=Isidore Singer|editor3-last=et al|editor2-first=Cyrus|editor2-last=Adler|editor2-link=Cyrus Adler|accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|chapter=Sarah (Sarai)|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=245&amp;letter=S&amp;search=sarah|first=Emil G.|last=Hirsch|authorlink=Emil G. Hirsch|year=1901–1906|title=[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]|publisher=Funk &amp; Wagnalls|location=New York|first2=Wilhelm|last2=Bacher|authorlink2=Wilhelm Bacher|first3=Jacob Zallel|last3=Lauterbach|authorlink3=Jacob Zallel Lauterbach|first4=Joseph|last4=Jacobs|authorlink4=Joseph Jacobs|first5=Mary W.|last5=Montgomery|editor-first=Isidore|editor-last=Singer|editor-link=Isidore Singer|editor3-last=et al|editor2-first=Cyrus|editor2-last=Adler|editor2-link=Cyrus Adler|accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Isaac in Genesis==
''The account of Isaac from the [[Book of Genesis]]''

===Birth of Isaac===
[[Image:Rembrandt Harmensz. van Rijn 035.jpg|thumb|An angel prevents the sacrifice of Isaac. ''Abraham and Isaac'', [[Rembrandt]], 1634]]
It was prophesied to the patriarch Abraham that he would have a son and that his name should be called Isaac. When Abraham became one hundred years old, this son was born to him by his first wife Sarah.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|18:10–12|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though this was Abraham's second son&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|16:15|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; it was Sarah’s first and only child.

On the eighth day from his birth, Isaac was [[Religious male circumcision|circumcised]], as was necessary for all males of Abraham's household, in order to be in compliance with [[Yahweh]]'s covenant.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|21:1–5|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Isaac had been weaned, Sarah saw [[Ishmael]] mocking, and urged her husband to cast out [[Hagar (biblical person)|Hagar]] the bondservant and her son, so that Isaac would be Abraham's sole heir. Abraham was hesitant, but at God's order he listened to his wife's request.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|21:8–12|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Binding of Isaac===
{{main|Binding of Isaac}}
{{see also|Abraham#Abraham and Isaac|l1=Abraham and Isaac}}

At some point in Isaac's youth, his father Abraham brought him to Mount [[Moriah]]. At God's command, Abraham was to build a sacrificial altar and sacrifice his son Isaac upon it. After he had bound his son to the altar and drawn his knife to kill him, at the very last moment an [[angel]] of God prevented Abraham from proceeding. Rather, he was directed to sacrifice a nearby ram instead. This event served as a test of Abraham's [[Faith#Judaism|faith]] in God, not as an actual human sacrifice.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|22|HE}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Esau and Jacob Presented to Isaac.jpg|thumb|The birth of Esau and Jacob, as painted by [[Benjamin West]]]]

===Family life===
When Isaac was 40, Abraham sent [[Eliezer]], his steward, into [[Mesopotamia]] to find a wife for Isaac, from his nephew [[Bethuel]]'s family. Eliezer chose [[Rebecca|Rebekah]] for Isaac. After many years of marriage to Isaac, Rebekah had still not given birth to a child and was believed to be barren. Isaac prayed for her and she conceived. Rebekah gave birth to twin boys, Esau and Jacob. Isaac was 60 years old when his two sons were born. Isaac favored Esau, and Rebekah favored Jacob.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|25:20–28|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Occupation===
At the age of 75, Isaac moved to ''[[Abraham#Abram and Hagar|Beer-lahai-roi]]'' after his father died.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|25:11|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the land experienced famine, he removed to the [[Philistines|Philistine]] land of [[Gerar]] where his father once lived. This land was still under the control of [[Abimelech|King Abimelech]] as it was in the days of Abraham. Like his father, Isaac also deceived [[Abraham#Abraham and Abimelech|Abimelech]] about his wife and also got into the well business. He had gone back to all of the wells that his father dug and saw that they were all stopped up with earth. The Philistines did this after Abraham died. So, Isaac unearthed them and began to dig for more wells all the way to [[Beersheba]], where he made a pact with Abimelech, just like in the day of his father.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|26|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Giotto di Bondone 080.jpg|thumb|left|Isaac blessing his son,as painted by [[Giotto di Bondone]]]]

===Birthright===
Isaac grew old and became blind. He called his son Esau and directed him to procure some venison for him, in order to receive Isaac's blessing. While Esau was hunting, Jacob, after listening to his mother's advice, deceived his blind father by misrepresenting himself as Esau and thereby obtained his father's blessing, such that Jacob became Isaac's primary heir and Esau was left in an inferior position. According to Genesis 25:29-34, Esau had subsequently sold his birthright to Jacob for &quot;bread and ''a'' stew of lentils.&quot; Thereafter, Isaac sent Jacob into Mesopotamia to take a wife of his own family. After 20 years working for his uncle [[Laban (Bible)|Laban]], Jacob returned home. He reconciled with his twin brother Esau, then he and Esau buried their father, Isaac, in Hebron at the age of 180.&lt;ref name=&quot;JewishEncyclopedia&quot;&gt;''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]'', [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=174&amp;letter=I ''Isaac''].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|35:28–29|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other references ==
===New Testament===
The [[New Testament]] states Isaac was &quot;offered up&quot; by Abraham his father, and that Isaac blessed his sons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Easton&quot;/&gt; Paul contrasted Isaac, symbolizing [[Adiaphora#Adiaphora in Christianity|Christian liberty]], with the rejected older son Ishmael, symbolizing slavery;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Isaac&quot;&gt;''Encyclopedia of Religion'', ''Isaac''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Galatians|4:21–31|KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hagar is associated with the [[Sinai Peninsula|Sinai]] covenant, while Sarah is associated with the covenant of grace, into which her son Isaac enters.The [[Epistle of James]] chapter 2, verses 21-24&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||James|2:21–24|KJV}}&lt;/ref&gt; states that the sacrifice of Isaac shows that justification (in the Johannine sense) requires both faith and works.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC-Isaac&quot;&gt;''Encyclopedia of Christianity'', Bowden, John, ed., ''Isaac''.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Epistle to the Hebrews]], Abraham's willingness to follow God's command to sacrifice Isaac is used as an example of faith as is Isaac's action in blessing Jacob and Esau with reference to the future promised by God to Abraham&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Hebrews|11:17-20|ASV}}&lt;/ref&gt; In verse 19, the author views the release of Isaac from sacrifice as analogous to the [[resurrection of Jesus]], the idea of the sacrifice of Isaac being a prefigure of the sacrifice of Jesus on the [[Christian cross|cross]].&lt;ref&gt;see F.F. Bruce, ''The Epistle to the Hebrews'' Marshall. Morgan and Scott, 1964 p.308-313 for all this paragraph.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Qur'an===
The [[Qur'an]] mentions Isaac as prophet and a righteous man of [[God in Islam|God]]. Isaac and Jacob are mentioned as being bestowed upon Abraham as gifts of God, who then worshipped God only and were righteous leaders in the way of God:
{{Quote|And We bestowed on him Isaac and, as an additional gift, (a grandson), Jacob, and We made righteous men of every one (of them).&lt;br&gt;And We made them leaders, guiding (men) by Our Command, and We sent them inspiration to do good deeds, to establish regular prayers, and to practise regular charity; and they constantly served Us (and Us only).|Qur'an, [[sura]] 21 ([[Al-Anbiya]]), [[ayah]] 72-73&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|21|72|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{Quote|And WE gave him the glad tidings of Isaac, a Prophet, and one of the righteous.|Qur'an, [[sura]] 37 ([[As-Saaffat]]), [[ayah]] 112&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|37|112|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Testament of Isaac===
{{main|Testament of Isaac}}
The Testament of Isaac is a [[pseudonym]]ous text which was most likely composed in [[Greek language|Greek]] in [[Egypt]] after 100&amp;nbsp;CE. It is also dependent on the [[Testament of Abraham]]. In this testament, God sends the [[archangel]] [[Michael (archangel)|Michael]] to Isaac in order to inform him of his impending death. Isaac accepts God's decree but Jacob resists. Isaac in his bed-chamber tells Jacob of the inevitability of death. Isaac has a tour of [[heaven]] and [[hell]] shortly before his death in which God's compassion to repentant sinners is emphasized. In this testament, Isaac also talks with the crowds on the subjects of [[priest]]hood, [[asceticism]], and the moral life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dic&quot;/&gt;

==World views==
[[File:AbrahamIsaac.jpg|thumb|Isaac embraces his father Abraham after the [[Binding of Isaac]], early 1900s Bible illustration]]

===Jewish views===
[[File:Isaac Blessing Jacob - Govert Flinck.jpg|thumb|left|''Isaac Blessing [[Jacob]]'', painting by [[Govert Flinck]] ([[Rijksmuseum Amsterdam]])]]
In [[Rabbinic literature|rabbinical tradition]] the age of Isaac at the time of binding is taken to be 37 which contrasts with common portrayals of Isaac as a child.&lt;ref name=&quot;New EoJ&quot;&gt;''The New Encyclopedia of Judaism'', ''Isaac''.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[rabbi]]s also thought that the reason for the death of Sarah was the news of the intended sacrifice of Isaac.&lt;ref name=&quot;New EoJ&quot;/&gt; The sacrifice of Isaac is cited in appeals for the [[Atonement in Judaism|mercy of God]] in later [[Judaism|Jewish]] traditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica-Isaac&quot;&gt;''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]'', ''Isaac''.&lt;/ref&gt; The post-biblical Jewish interpretations often elaborate the role of Isaac beyond the biblical description and largely focus on Abraham's intended sacrifice of Isaac, called the ''aqedah'' (&quot;binding&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Isaac&quot;/&gt; According to a version of these interpretations, Isaac died in the sacrifice and was revived.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Isaac&quot;/&gt; According to many accounts of [[Aggadah]], unlike the Bible, it is [[Satan]] who is testing Isaac and not [[God in Judaism|God]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brill's New Pauly&quot;&gt;Brock, Sebastian P., ''Brill's New Pauly'', ''Isaac''.&lt;/ref&gt; Isaac's willingness to follow God's command at the cost of his death has been a model for many Jews who preferred [[martyr]]dom to violation of the [[halakha|Jewish law]].&lt;ref name=&quot;New EoJ&quot;/&gt;

According to the Jewish tradition Isaac instituted the afternoon prayer. This tradition is based on Genesis chapter 24, verse 63&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|24:63|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;Isaac went out to meditate in the field at the eventide&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;New EoJ&quot;/&gt;

Isaac was the only [[patriarch]] who stayed in Canaan during his whole life and though once he tried to leave, God told him not to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|26:2|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rabbinic tradition gave the explanation that Isaac was almost sacrificed and anything dedicated as a sacrifice may not leave the [[Land of Israel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;New EoJ&quot;/&gt; Isaac was the oldest of the biblical patriarchs at the time of his death, and the only patriarch whose name was not changed.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Isaac&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Easton&quot;&gt;Easton, M. G., ''Illustrated Bible Dictionary'', 3rd ed., ''Isaac''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Rabbinic literature also linked Isaac's blindness in old age, as stated in the Bible, to the sacrificial binding: Isaac's eyes went blind because the tears of angels present at the time of his sacrifice fell on Isaac's eyes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brill's New Pauly&quot;/&gt;

===Christian views===
{{Expand section|date=August 2012}}
The [[Early Christianity|early Christian church]] continued and developed the New Testament theme of Isaac as a type of Christ and the Church being both &quot;the son of the promise&quot; and the &quot;father of the faithful&quot;.  [[Tertullian]] draws a parallel between Isaac's bearing the wood for the sacrificial fire with Christ's carrying his cross.&lt;ref&gt;Cross and Livingstone, ''Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church'', 1974, art '''Isaac'''&lt;/ref&gt; and there was a general agreement that, while all the sacrifices of the Old Law were anticipations of that on Calvary, the sacrifice of Isaac was so &quot;in a pre-eminent way&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Kelly, J.N.D. ''Early Christian Doctrines'', A &amp; C Black, 1965.p.72&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic views===
{{Main|Islamic view of Isaac}}
'''Isaac''' ({{lang-ar|إسحاق}}&amp;lrm;{{ref|A|[note A]}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|ʾIsḥāq}}'') is revered by [[Muslim]]s to be a prophet and the patriarch of [[Islam]]. 

[[Islam]] considers Isaac as a [[Prophets of Islam|prophet of Islam]], and describes him as the father of the [[Israelites]] and a righteous [[servant of God]].

Isaac, along with [[Ishmael]], is highly important for Muslims for continuing to preach the message of [[monotheism]] after his father [[Abraham]]. Among Isaac's children was the follow-up Israelite patriarch [[Jacob]], who too is venerated an Islamic prophet.

Isaac is mentioned fifteen times by name in the [[Qur'an]], often with his father and his son, [[Jacob]].&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of Islam'', W. Montgomery Watt, ''Isaac''&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Qur'an]] states that Abraham received &quot;good tidings of Isaac, a prophet, of the righteous&quot;, and that God blessed them both (XXXVII: 12). In a fuller description, when [[angel]]s came to [[Abraham]] to tell him of the future punishment to be imposed on [[Sodom and Gomorrah]], his wife, [[Sarah]], &quot;laughed, and We gave her good tidings of Isaac, and after Isaac of (a grandson) Jacob&quot; (XI: 71-74); and it is further explained that this event will take place despite Abraham and Sarah's old age. Several verses speak of Isaac as a &quot;gift&quot; to Abraham (VI: 84; XIX: 49-50), and XXIX: 26-27 adds that [[God]] made &quot;prophethood and the Book to be among his offspring&quot;, which has been interpreted to refer to Abraham's two prophetic sons, his prophetic grandson [[Jacob]], and his prophetic great-grandson [[Islamic view of Joseph|Joseph]]. In the [[Qur'an]], it later narrates that Abraham also praised [[God]] for giving him Ishmael and Isaac in his old age (XIV: 39-41).

Elsewhere in the [[Qur'an]], Isaac is mentioned in lists: [[Islamic view of Joseph|Joseph]] follows the religion of his forefathers Abraham, Isaac and Jacob (XII: 38) and speaks of [[God]]'s favor to them (XII: 6); [[Jacob]]'s sons all testify their faith and promise to worship the [[God]] that their forefathers, &quot;Abraham, Ishmael and Isaac&quot;, worshiped (II: 127); and the Qur'an commands [[Muslim]]s to believe in the revelations that were given to &quot;Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob and the Patriarchs&quot; (II: 136; III: 84). In the [[Qur'an]]'s narrative of Abraham's near-sacrifice of his son (XXXVII: 102), the name of the son is not mentioned and debate has continued over the son's identity, though many feel that the identity is the least important element in a story which is given to show the courage that one develops through faith.&lt;ref&gt;''Concise Encyclopedia of Islam'', C. Glasse, ''Isaac''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Western scholarly views==

===Historicity===
Some scholars have described Isaac as &quot;a [[legend]]ary figure&quot; while others view him &quot;as a figure representing [[tribe|tribal]] history, though as a [[History|historical]] individual&quot; or &quot;as a [[nomad|seminomadic]] leader.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC1-Isaac&quot;&gt;''Eerdmans Encyclopedia of Christianity'', ''Isaac'', p. 744.&lt;/ref&gt;

The stories of Isaac, like other patriarchal stories of Genesis, are generally believed in liberal Western scholarship to have &quot;their origin in folk memories and oral traditions of the early Hebrew [[Pastoralism|pastoralist]] experience.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoCol-Isaac&quot;&gt;''[[Columbia Encyclopedia]]'', ''Isaac''.&lt;/ref&gt; Conservative Western scholarship believes the stories of Isaac, and other patriarchal stories in Genesis, to be factual. ''The Cambridge Companion to the Bible'' makes the following comment on the biblical stories of the patriarchs:

{{Quote|Yet for all that these stories maintain a distance between their world and that of their time of literary growth and composition, they reflect the political realities of the later periods. Many of the narratives deal with the relationship between the ancestors and peoples who were part of Israel’s political world at the time the stories began to be written down (eighth century B.C.E.). Lot is the ancestor of the [[Transjordan (Bible)|Transjordanian]] peoples of [[Ammon]] and Moab, and Ishmael personifies the nomadic peoples known to have inhabited north [[Arabian Peninsula|Arabia]], although located in the [[Old Testament]] in the [[Negev]]. Esau personifies [[Edom]] (36:1), and Laban represents the [[Aram (biblical region)|Aramean]] states to Israel’s north. A persistent theme is that of difference between the ancestors and the indigenous Canaanites… In fact, the theme of the differences between [[Kingdom of Judah|Judah]] and [[Land of Israel|Israel]], as personified by the ancestors, and the neighboring peoples of the time of the monarchy is pressed effectively into theological service to articulate the choosing by God of Judah and Israel to bring blessing to all peoples.”&lt;ref&gt;''The Cambridge Companion to the Bible'', p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to [[Martin Noth]], a scholar of the Hebrew Bible, the narratives of Isaac date back to an older cultural stage than that of the West-Jordanian Jacob.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC1-Isaac&quot;/&gt; At that era, the [[Israelite]] tribes were not yet sedentary. In the course of looking for grazing areas, they had come in contact in southern [[Palestine]] with the inhabitants of the settled countryside.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC1-Isaac&quot;/&gt; The biblical historian, A. Jopsen, believes in the connection between the Isaac traditions and the north, and in support of this theory adduces [[Book of Amos|Amos]] 7:9 (&quot;the high places of Isaac&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC1-Isaac&quot;/&gt;

[[Albrecht Alt]] and Martin Noth hold that, &quot;The figure of Isaac was enhanced when the theme of promise, previously bound to the cults of the 'God the Fathers' was incorporated into the Israelite creed during the southern-Palestinian stage of the growth of the [[Torah|Pentateuch]] tradition.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC1-Isaac&quot;/&gt; According to Martin Noth, at the Southern Palestinian stage of the growth of the Pentateuch tradition, Isaac became established as one of the biblical patriarchs, but his traditions were receded in the favor of Abraham.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC1-Isaac&quot;/&gt;

===Documentary hypothesis===
The name Isaac occurs 32 times in the Hebrew Bible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strongs&quot;/&gt; Variations of the formula &quot;Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob&quot; occur 23 times in the Hebrew Bible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dic&quot;&gt;''Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible'', ''Isaac'', p. 647.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[documentary hypothesis]], use of [[names of God]] indicates authorship, and [[Form criticism|form critic]]s variously assign passages like Genesis chapter 26, verses 6-11&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|26:6–11|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the [[Jahwist|Yahwist]] source, and Genesis chapter 20 verses 1-7, chapter 21, verse 1 to chapter 22, verse 14 and chapter 22, verse 19&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis.|20:1–7|HE}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Genesis|21:1–22:14|HE}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Genesis|22:19|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the [[Elohist]] source; this source-critical approach has admitted problems, in that the name &quot;Yahweh&quot; appears in Elohist material.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=A Short Introduction to the Hebrew Bible|author=Collins, John J.|publisher=Fortress Press |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-8006-6207-3 |page=49 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=pWNohGTPy48C}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the compilation hypothesis, the formulaic use of the word ''toledoth'' (generations) indicates that Genesis chapter 11, verse 27 to chapter 25, verse 19&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|11:27–25:19|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; is Isaac's record through Abraham's death (with Ishmael's record appended), and Genesis chapter 25, verse 19 to chapter 37, verse 2&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|25:19–37:2|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; is Jacob's record through Isaac's death (with Esau's records appended).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=[[Henry M. Morris|Morris, Henry M.]]|title=The Genesis Record: A Scientific and Devotional Commentary on the Book of Beginnings|pages=26–30|year=1976|publisher=[[Baker Book House]]|location=[[Grand Rapids, Michigan]]|isbn=0-8010-6004-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In art==
The earliest Christian portrayal of Isaac is found in the [[Catacombs of Rome|Roman catacomb]] [[fresco]]es.&lt;ref name=&quot;Early Christian Art&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Smith, Alison Moore|title=The Iconography of the Sacrifice of Isaac in Early Christian Art|jstor=497708|journal=American Journal of Archaeology|volume=26|issue=2|pages=159–173|doi=10.2307/497708|year=1922}}&lt;/ref&gt; Excluding the fragments, Alison Moore Smith classifies these artistic works in three categories:

{{Quote|&quot;Abraham leads Isaac towards the altar; or Isaac approaches with the bundle of sticks, Abraham having preceded him to the place of offering .... Abraham is upon a pedestal and Isaac stands near at hand, both figures in orant [[attitude (art)|attitude]] .... Abraham is shown about to sacrifice Isaac while the latter stands or kneels on the ground beside the altar. Sometimes Abraham grasps Isaac by the hair. Occasionally the ram is added to the scene and in the later paintings the [[Hand of God (art)|Hand of God]] emerges from above.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Early Christian Art&quot;/&gt;}}

==See also==
*[[Biblical narratives and the Qur'an]]

==Notes==
{{refbegin}}
* {{note|A|A}} &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:120%&quot;&gt;{{script/Arabic|إسحٰق}}&lt;/span&gt; ({{transl|ar|ʾIsḥ&lt;sup&gt;ā&lt;/sup&gt;q}}) is the traditional [[Koranic Arabic|Koran]]ic spelling after [[Arabic diacritics|vocalizing]] with a [[super script]] ''[[ا|{{transl|ar|DIN|ʾalif}}]]''.&amp;nbsp; In [[Modern Standard Arabic]], it is normally written &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:120%&quot;&gt;{{lang|ar|إسحاق}}&lt;/span&gt; ({{transl|ar|DIN|ʾIsḥāq}}).
{{refend}}
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{cite book | last=Browning | first=W.R.F | title=A dictionary of the Bible | publisher=Oxford University Press| year=1996| isbn=0-19-211691-6}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Paul Lagasse, Lora Goldman, Archie Hobson, Susan R. Norton | encyclopedia=The Columbia Encyclopedia | publisher=Gale Group | year=2000 | edition=6th | isbn=978-1-59339-236-9}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=P.J. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel, W.P. Heinrichs | encyclopedia=[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]] Online | publisher=Brill Academic Publishers | issn=1573-3912}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Erwin Fahlbusch, William Geoffrey Bromiley | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Christianity| publisher=Eerdmans Publishing Company, and Brill| year=2001| edition=1st| isbn=0-8028-2414-5}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=John Bowden | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Christianity| publisher=Oxford University Press| year=2005| edition=1st| isbn=0-19-522393-4}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | encyclopedia=The New Encyclopædia Britannica | publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, Incorporated; Rev Ed edition | year=2005 | isbn=978-1-59339-236-9}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Jane Dammen McAuliffe | encyclopedia=[[Encyclopedia of the Qur'an]] | publisher=Brill Academic Publishers | year=2005 | isbn=978-90-04-12356-4}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Geoffrey Wigoder | encyclopedia=The New Encyclopedia of Judaism | publisher=New York University Press | edition=2nd | year=2002 | isbn=978-0-8147-9388-6}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Lindsay Jones | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Religion| publisher=MacMillan Reference Books| year=2005| edition=2nd| isbn=978-0-02-865733-2}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=David Noel Freedman, Allen C. Myers, Astrid B. Beck | encyclopedia=Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible | publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans | year=2000 | edition=1st| isbn=978-0-8028-2400-4}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=174&amp;letter=I Isaac in Jewish Encyclopedia]
* [http://jss.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/XXXIV/1/95.pdf Abraham's son as the intended sacrifice (Al-Dhabih, Qur'an 37:99, Qur'an 37:99–113): Issues in qur'anic exegesis], journal of Semitic Studies XXX1V/ Spring 1989

{{Commons category-inline}}
*{{CathEncy|wstitle=Isaac}}
*{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Isaac}}

{{Adam to David}}
{{Prophets of the Tanakh}}
{{Prophets in the Qur'an|no}}
{{Catholic saints}}
{{Good article}}

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Isaac
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Biblical patriarch
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Canaan]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Canaan]]
}}
[[Category:Isaac| ]]
[[Category:Biblical patriarchs]]
[[Category:Book of Genesis]]
[[Category:Burials in Hebron]]
[[Category:Descendants of Eber]]
[[Category:Edom]]
[[Category:Old Testament saints]]
[[Category:People celebrated in the Lutheran liturgical calendar]]
[[Category:Prophets of Islam]]
[[Category:Torah people]]

[[ace:Ishaq]]
[[ar:إسحاق]]
[[az:İshaq]]
[[be:Ісак, патрыярх]]
[[bg:Исаак]]
[[bo:ཨི་སཱག]]
[[bs:Isak (prorok)]]
[[br:Izaag]]
[[ca:Isaac]]
[[cs:Izák]]
[[cy:Isaac]]
[[de:Isaak (Erzvater)]]
[[et:Iisak]]
[[el:Ισαάκ]]
[[es:Isaac]]
[[eo:Isaak]]
[[eu:Isaak]]
[[ee:Isak]]
[[fa:اسحاق]]
[[fr:Isaac]]
[[gl:Isaac]]
[[ko:이사악]]
[[hr:Izak]]
[[id:Ishak]]
[[it:Isacco]]
[[he:יצחק]]
[[ka:ისააკი]]
[[kk:Ысқақ]]
[[sw:Isaka]]
[[lad:Its.hak]]
[[lbe:ИсхӀакъ идавс]]
[[la:Isaac]]
[[lv:Īzāks]]
[[lt:Izaokas]]
[[hu:Izsák (Ábrahám fia)]]
[[ml:ഇസ്ഹാഖ് നബി]]
[[nl:Izaäk (aartsvader)]]
[[ja:イサク]]
[[no:Isak]]
[[nn:Patriarken Isak]]
[[oc:Isaac]]
[[ps:اسحاق]]
[[pl:Izaak]]
[[pt:Isaac]]
[[ro:Isac (personaj biblic)]]
[[rm:Isaac]]
[[ru:Исаак]]
[[simple:Isaac]]
[[so:Nabi Isxaaq C.S.]]
[[ckb:ئیسحاق]]
[[sr:Исак]]
[[fi:Iisak]]
[[sv:Isak (Bibeln)]]
[[tl:Isaac]]
[[ta:ஈசாக்கு]]
[[th:อิสอัค]]
[[tr:İshak]]
[[uk:Ісаак (син Авраама)]]
[[vi:Isaac (nhân vật Kinh Thánh)]]
[[yi:יצחק אבינו]]
[[diq:İshaq]]
[[zh:以撒]]</text>
      <sha1>e76ah4nwxv45lhvr5mgiy2g1cy3zqu5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
