<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ishmael</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>222788</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522361176</id>
      <parentid>521715858</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T18:09:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bensin</username>
        <id>219215</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* World views */ Remove unscourced statement since 2008 that &quot;some modern Arabs in Southern Palestine believe their tribes and houses to be of [[Isaac]]'s blood line.&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28367">{{Other uses}}
{{Infobox saint
|name = Ishmael
|birth_date =
|death_date =
|feast_day =
|venerated_in = [[Islam]]&lt;br&gt;[[Judaism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Christianity]]
|image = Navez Agar et Ismaël.jpg
|imagesize = 250px
|caption = A depiction of Hagar and Ishmael in the desert by [[François-Joseph Navez]]
|birth_place = [[Canaan]]
|death_place = [[Arabia]]
|titles = Prophet, Patriarch, Father of the Arabs, Constructor of the [[Kaaba]], ''Apostle to Arabia''
|beatified_date =
|beatified_place =
|beatified_by =
|canonized_date =
|canonized_place =
|influences = [[Abraham]]
|attributes =
|influenced = All of his descendants
|suppressed_date =
|issues =
|prayer =
|prayer_attrib =
}}

'''Ishmael''' ({{Hebrew Name|יִשְׁמָעֵאל|Yishma'el|Yišmāʻēl}} &lt;small&gt;[[ISO 259-3]]&lt;/small&gt; ''Yišmaˁel''; {{lang-el|Ισμαήλ}} ''Ismaēl''; {{lang-la|Ismael}}; {{lang-ar|إسماعيل}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|ʾIsmāʿīl}}'')  is a figure in the [[Hebrew Bible]] and the [[Qur'an]], and was [[Abraham]]'s first son according to [[Judaism|Jews]], [[Christianity|Christians]] and [[Islam|Muslims]]. Ishmael was born of Abraham's marriage to [[Sarah]]'s handmaiden [[Hagar (Bible)|Hagar]] ({{bibleverse||Genesis|16:3|NIV}}). According to the [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] account, he died at the age of 137 ({{bibleverse||Genesis|25:17|NIV}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic1913&quot;/&gt;

==Etymology==
Cognates of [[Hebrew]] ''Yishma'el'' existed in various ancient [[Semitic]] cultures,&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Ishmael&quot;&gt;Fredrick E. Greenspahn, ''Encyclopedia of Religion'', &quot;Ishmael&quot;, p.4551–4552&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation broken|date=October 2012}} including early [[Babylonian]] and [[Minæan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic1913&quot;/&gt; It is translated literally as &quot;[[El (god)|God]] has hearkened&quot;, suggesting that &quot;a child so named was regarded as the fulfillment of a divine promise&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Ishmael&quot;/&gt;{{Citation broken|date=October 2012}}

==Genesis narrative==
[[File:Pieter Pietersz. Lastman 001.jpg|thumb|The dismissal of Hagar, by [[Pieter Pietersz Lastman]]]]

''This is the account of Ishmael from {{bibleref2|Genesis|16,17,21,25|NIV|Genesis Chapters 16, 17, 21, 25}}''

===Birth===
In {{Bibleverse||Genesis|16|HE}}, the birth of Ishmael was planned by the Patriarch [[Abraham]]'s first wife, who at that time was known as [[Sarah|Sarai]]. She and her husband Abram (Abraham), sought a way to have children in order to fulfill the [[Abrahamic covenant]] that was established in {{Bibleverse||Genesis|15|HE}}. Since Sarai had yet to bear Abram a child, her idea was to offer her Egyptian handmaiden [[Hagar (biblical person)|Hagar]] to Abram, so that they could have a child by her. Abram consented to a marital arrangement taking Hagar as his second wife&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse||Genesis|16:3|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; when he was in his late 85th year of age. Customs of that time dictated that, although Hagar was the birth mother, any child conceived would belong to Sarai and Abram (Sarah and Abraham).&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/251469/Hagar &quot;Hagar&quot;]. ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]''. 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Bibleverse||Genesis|16:7-16|HE}} describes the naming of Ishmael, and [[Yahweh]]'s promise to Hagar concerning Ishmael and his descendants. This occurred at the well of Beer-lahai-roi, located in the desert region between Abram’s settlement and [[Shur (Bible)|Shur]]. Hagar fled here after Sarai dealt harshly with her for showing contempt for her mistress following her having become pregnant. Here, Hagar encountered an angel of Yahweh who instructed her to return and be submissive to Sarai so that she could have her child there. The blessing that this child's father was promised was that Abram's descendants would be as numerous as the dust of the earth. However, the promise would be to a son of Sarai; yet God would make of this child a great nation, who would be named Ishmael, because he was of the seed of Abram. The angel continued that &quot;he shall be a wild ass of a man: his hand shall be against every man, and every man's hand against him; and he shall dwell over against all his brethren.&quot; When Ishmael was born, Abram was 86 years old.

===Inheritance rights and the first circumcision===
{{See also|Isaac#Hebrew Bible|l1=Account of Isaac in the Hebrew Bible}}
When he was 13 years old, Ishmael was circumcised at the same time as all other males in Abraham's house becoming a part of the [[Brit milah|covenant]]  in a mass circumcision. This occurred because his father Abram was inaugurated as Abraham at the age of 99 and then initiated into the covenant by having himself and the males of his entire household circumcised. ({{Bibleverse||Genesis|17|HE}})

At the time of the covenant, God informed Abraham that his wife Sarah would give birth to a son, which he was instructed to name Isaac. God told Abraham that He would establish his covenant through Isaac, and when Abraham inquired as to Ishmael's role, God answers that Ishmael has been blessed and that He “will make him fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly; twelve princes shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation.” ({{Bibleverse||Genesis|17|HE}})

A year later, Ishmael's half-brother [[Isaac]] was born by Abraham to his first wife Sarah.

On the day of feasting during which Abraham celebrated the weaning of Isaac, Ishmael was “mocking” or &quot;playing with&quot; Isaac (the Hebrew word is ambiguous&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=53&amp;letter=H&amp;search=Hagar &quot;Hagar&quot;], ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]''&lt;/ref&gt;)&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic1913&quot;&gt;[[s:Catholic Encyclopedia (1913)/Ismael|''Catholic Encyclopedia'' (1913)]]&lt;/ref&gt; and Sarah asked Abraham to expel Ishmael and his mother, saying: &quot;Get rid of that slave woman and her son, for that slave woman's son will never share in the inheritance with my son Isaac.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|25:2–6|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; This proposition was grievous in Abraham's sight because of his son and the bondwoman, Hagar. Abraham only agreed when God told him that &quot;for in Isaac your seed shall be called&quot;, and that He would &quot;make a nation of the son of the bondwoman&quot; Ishmael, since he was a descendant of Abraham. ({{bibleverse||Genesis|21:11–13|NIV}})
[[File:Hagar and Ishmael in desert (Grigoriy Ugryumov).jpg|thumb|''Hagar and Ishmael in the Desert'', by Grigoriy Ugrumov (c. 1785)]]
At the age of 14, Ishmael was freed along with his mother. The Lord’s covenant made clear Ishmael was not to inherit Abraham’s house and that Isaac would be the seed of the covenant. Abraham gave him and his mother a supply of bread and water and sent them away. Hagar entered in the wilderness of [[Beer-sheba]] where the two soon ran out of water and Hagar, not wanting to witness the death of her son, set the boy some distance away from herself, and wept. &quot;And God heard the voice of the lad&quot; and sent his angel to tell Hagar, &quot;Arise, lift up the lad, and hold him in thine hand; for I will make him a great nation.&quot; And God &quot;opened her eyes, and she saw a well of water&quot;, from which she drew to save Ishmael's life and her own. &quot;And God was with the lad; and he grew, and dwelt in the wilderness, and became an archer.&quot; ({{Bibleverse||Genesis|21:14–21|HE}})

===Descendants===
After roaming the wilderness for some time, Ishmael and his mother settled in the [[Desert of Paran]], where he became an expert in [[archery]]. Eventually, his mother found him a wife from the land of [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|21:17-21|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had twelve sons who each became tribal chiefs throughout the regions from [[Havilah]] to [[Shur (Bible)|Shur]] (from [[Assyria]] to the border of Egypt).&lt;ref name=&quot;JewishEnc&quot;&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=277&amp;letter=I&amp;search=Ishmael &quot;Ishmael&quot;], ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]''&lt;/ref&gt; His sons were:&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse||Genesis|25:12-18|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

#[[Nebaioth]]
#[[Qedar|Kedar]], father of the [[Qedarite]]s, a northern Arab tribe that controlled the area between the Persian Gulf and the Sinai Peninsula. According to tradition, he is the ancestor of the [[Quraysh (tribe)|Quraysh]] tribe, and thus of [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=A Dictionary of the Bible: Including Biography, Natural History, Geography, Topography, Archæology, and Literature|url=http://bluehost.levendwater.org/books/Schaff%20A%20Dictionary%20of%20the%20Bible/index.htm|year=1880|publisher=[[American Missionary Fellowship|American Sunday-School Union]]|location=Philadelphia|page=494 [p. 502 on-line]|editor-first=Philip|editor-last=Schaff|editor-link=Philip Schaff|separator=,|postscript=|accessdate=April 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
#[[Adbeel]], established a tribe in northwest [[Arabia]].
#[[Mibsam]]
#Mishma
#[[Dumah (son of Ishmael)|Dumah]], associated with ''Adummatu'' described as &quot;a fortress of Arabia&quot; in [[Saudi Arabia]].
#[[List of minor Biblical figures#Massa|Massa]], father of a nomadic tribe that inhabited the Arabian desert toward [[Babylonia]].
#[[Hadad (Bible)|Hadad]]
#[[Tema (Son of Ishmael)|Tema]]
#[[Jetur (Son of Ishmael)|Jetur]]
#Naphish
#Kedemah
Ishmael also had one known daughter, [[Mahalath]] or [[Basemath]], the third wife of [[Esau]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=386&amp;letter=B&amp;search=Mahalath &quot;Mahalath&quot;], ''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

Ishmael also appeared with Isaac at the burial of Abraham.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|Genesis|25:9|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ishmael died at the age of 137.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Genesis|25:17|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Deuterocanonical references==
The book of [[Jubilees]] places the location and identity of the Ishmaelites as the Arab peoples residing in Arab territories. This is the current view for the majority of the Christian, Islamic and Jewish faiths. According to Biblical accounts the Arab people traditionally have had long-standing alliances with the descendants of the Assyrians and the Medes.

==World views==
[[Historian]]s and academics in the fields of [[linguistics]] and [[source criticism]] believe that the stories of Ishmael belong to the three strata of J, or [[Jahwist|Yahwist source]], the P, or [[Priestly source]], and  the E, or [[Elohist source]] (See [[Documentary hypothesis]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Catholic1913&quot;/&gt; For example, The narration in {{niv|Genesis|16|Genesis 16}} is of J type and the narration in {{niv|Genesis|21:8-21|Genesis 21:8-21}} is of E type.&lt;ref&gt;S. Nikaido(2001), p.1&lt;/ref&gt;

Islamic traditions consider Ishmael to be the ancestor of [[Arab]] people,&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Ishmael&quot;/&gt;{{Citation broken|date=October 2012}} excluding Arabs who are descendants of [[Yarab|Ya'rub]]. Arabs who are from Ishmael-descendant tribes are occasionally referred to as &quot;Arabized-Arabs&quot; to highlight their ancestry. The Prophet Muhammad was of these Arabs.

Jewish traditions are split between those, like [[Josephus]], who consider Ishmael the ancestor of the Arabs,&lt;ref&gt;Josephus, Antiquities of the Jews, Book I, Ch. 12; 2, 4&lt;/ref&gt; and those, like [[Maimonides]], who believe that the northern Arabs are descended from the sons of [[Keturah]], whom Abraham married after Sarah's death.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yctorah.org/component/option,com_docman/task,doc_view/gid,701/ &quot;Maimonides' 'True Religion': For Jews or All Humanity?&quot;, Menachem Kellner, in ''Meorot'' 7:1 (2008) p.5, n.21]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Judaism===
{{See also|Isaac#Jewish traditions|l1=Isaac in Jewish traditions}}
[[Judaism]] has generally viewed Ishmael as wicked though repentant (whereas Christianity omits any reference to repentance, which is sourced in the [[Talmud]]ic explanation of the [[Hebrew Bible]] &lt;ref&gt;http://www.chiefrabbi.org/UploadedFiles/thoughts/kitetse5767.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;).&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Ishmael&quot;/&gt; Judaism maintains that [[Isaac]] rather than Ishmael was the true heir of Abraham.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;/&gt;

In some Rabbinic traditions Ishmael is said to have had two wives; one of them named Aisha. This name corresponds to the Muslim tradition for the name of Muhammad's wife.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Ishmael&quot;/&gt;{{Citation broken|date=October 2012}} This is understood as a metaphoric representation of the Muslim world (first Arabs and then Turks) with Ishmael.&lt;ref&gt;Shalom Paul in The [[Oxford English Dictionary|Oxford Dictionary]] of Jewish Religion, p.358&lt;/ref&gt;

The name of an important 2nd century CE sage—[[Ishmael ben Elisha]], known as &quot;[[Rabbi Ishmael]]&quot; (רבי ישמעאל), one of the [[Tannaim]]—indicates that the Biblical Ishmael enjoyed a positive image among Jews of the time.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}}

Rabbinical commentators in the [[Midrash]] [[Genesis Rabbah]] also say that Ishmael's mother Hagar was the Pharaoh's daughter, thereby making Ishmael the grandson of the Pharaoh.  This could be why Genesis 17:20 refers to Ishmael as the father of 12 mighty princes.  According to Genesis 21:21, Hagar married Ishmael to an Egyptian woman, and if Rabbinical commentators are correct about Hagar being the daughter of the Pharaoh, his marriage to a woman selected by the Pharaoh's daughter could explain how and why his sons became princes.

However, according to other Jewish commentators, Ishmael's mother Hagar is identified with [[Keturah]], the woman Abraham married after the death of Sarah, stating that Abraham sought her out after Sarah's death. It is suggested that Keturah was Hagar's personal name, and that &quot;Hagar&quot; was a descriptive label meaning &quot;stranger&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chabad.org/parshah/article_cdo/aid/2636/jewish/The-Return-of-Hagar.htm &quot;The Return of Hagar&quot;], commentary on [[Chayei Sarah (parsha)|Parshah Chayei Sarah]], [[Chabad Lubavitch]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biu.ac.il/JH/Parasha/eng/chaye/sha.html &quot;Who Was Ketura?&quot;], [[Bar-Ilan University]]'s Parashat Hashavua Study Center, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ou.org/torah/ti/5763/chayeisara63.htm &quot;Parshat Chayei Sarah&quot;], ''Torah Insights'', [[Orthodox Union]], 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; This interpretation is discussed in the [[Midrash]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Bereshit Rabbah]] 61:4.&lt;/ref&gt; and is supported by [[Rashi]], [[Judah Loew ben Bezalel|Gur Aryeh]], [[Keli Yakar]], and [[Obadiah of Bertinoro]].  Rashi (Rabbi Shlomo Itzhaki) argues that &quot;Keturah&quot; was a name given to Hagar because her deeds were as beautiful as incense (hence: ''ketores''), and/or that she remained chaste from the time she was separated from Abraham—''keturah'' [ קְטוּרָה ''Q'turah'' ] derives from the [[Aramaic]] word for ''restrained''.

It is also said that Sarah was motivated by Ishmael's sexually frivolous ways because of the reference to his &quot;making merry&quot; (Gen. 21:9), a translation of the Hebrew word &quot;Mitzachek&quot;. This was developed into a reference to idolatry, sexual immorality or even murder; some rabbinic sources claim that Sarah worried that Ishmael would negatively influence Isaac, or that he would demand Isaac's inheritance on the grounds of being the firstborn. Regarding the word &quot;Mitzachek&quot; (again in Gen. 21:9) The Jewish Study Bible by [[Oxford University Press]] says this word in this particular context is associated with; &quot;Playing is another pun on Isaac's name (cf. 17.17; 18.12; 19.14; 26.8). Ishmael was 'Isaacing', or 'taking Isaac's place'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Adele Berlin, Marc Zvi Brettler |title=The Jewish Study Bible |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2004 |isbn=9780195297515 |page=[http://books.google.com/books?id=aDuy3p5QvEYC&amp;pg=PA44&amp;lpg=PA44&amp;dq=isaacing&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=YJis0Ifu28&amp;sig=jIlZLzxfow_p98d6aKpbdtAf3WY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=9K3dT6RckI3pAaaGiZAL&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=isaacing 44] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Also others take a more positive view, emphasizing Hagar's piety, noting that she was &quot;the one who had sat by the well and besought him who is the life of the worlds, saying 'look upon my misery[['&quot;]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dict&quot;&gt;Jeffrey, David L., ''A Dictionary of Biblical Tradition in English Literature'', Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 1992, p. 326 ISBN 0-8028-3634-8&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===
{{Six Islamic Prophets}}
{{See also|Islamic view of Ishmael|Islamic view of Hagar}}
Ishmael is recognized as an important [[Prophets of Islam|prophet]] and [[patriarch]] of [[Islam]]. [[Muslim]]s believe that Ishmael was the firstborn of [[Abraham]], born to him from his second wife [[Hagar]]. Ishmael is recognized by Muslims as the ancestor of several prominent [[Arab]] [[Tribes of Arabia|tribes]] and being the forefather of [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;''A-Z of Prophets in Islam and Judaism'', Wheeler, ''Ishmael''&lt;/ref&gt; Muslims also believe that Muhammad was the descendant of Ishmael that would establish a great nation, as promised by [[God in Abrahamic religions|God]] in the [[Old Testament]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=A Muslim primer: beginner's guide to Islam, Volume 2|last=Zeep|first=Ira G.|publisher=University of Arkansas Press|year=2000|isbn=978-1-55728-595-9|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{quote|And as for Ishmael, I have heard you: I will surely bless him; I will make him fruitful and will greatly increase his numbers. He will be the father of 12 rulers, and I will make them into a great nation.|[http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt0117.htm#20 Genesis 17:20]}}

====Ishmael in the Qur'an====
Ishmael is mentioned over ten times in the [[Qur'an]], often alongside other [[patriarch]]s and [[prophet]]s of ancient times. In XIX: 54, the Qur'an says: &quot;And make mention in the Scripture of Ishmael. He was a keeper of his promise, and he was a messenger, a prophet. He enjoined upon his people worship and almsgiving, and was most acceptable in the sight of his Lord.&quot; Later on, in XXXVIII: 48, Ishmael is mentioned together with [[Elisha]] and [[Dhul-Kifl]] as one of &quot;the patiently enduring and righteous, whom God caused to enter into his mercy.&quot; It is also said of [[Islamic view of Lot|Lot]], Elisha, [[Jonah]] and Ishmael, that God gave each one &quot;preference above the worlds&quot; (VI: 86). These references to Ishmael are, in each case, part of a larger context in which other holy prophets are mentioned. In other chapters of the Qur'an, however, which date from the [[Medinan sura|Medina period]], Ishmael is mentioned closely with his father [[Abraham]]: Ishmael stands alongside Abraham in their attempt to set up the [[Kaaba]] in [[Mecca]] as a place of monotheistic pilgrimage (II: 127-129) and Abraham thanks [[God]] for granting him Ishmael and [[Isaac]] in his old age (XIV: 35-41). Ishmael is further mentioned alongside the patriarchs who had been given revelations (II: 136) and [[Jacob]]'s sons promise to follow the faith of their forefathers, &quot;Abraham, Ishmael and Isaac&quot;, when testifying their faith (II: 133). In the narrative of the near-sacrifice of Abraham's son (XXXVII: 100-107), the son is not named and, although the general interpretation is that it was Ishmael, [[Tabari]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Isaac&quot;, ''Encyclopedia of Islam'', volume 4&lt;/ref&gt; maintained that it was Isaac. Most modern commentators, however, regard the son's identification as least important in a narrative which is given for its moral lesson.&lt;ref&gt;Glasse, C., &quot;Ishmael&quot;, ''Concise Encyclopedia of Islam''&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ishmael in Muslim literature====
[[File:Abraham sacrificicing his son, Ishmael Abraham cast into fire by Nimrod.JPG|thumb|Abraham sacrificicing his son, Ishmael Abraham cast into fire by Nimrod]]
The commentaries on the [[Qur'an]] and the numerous collections of ''[[Stories of the Prophets]]'' flesh out the Islamic perspective of Ishmael and detail his integral part in setting up the [[Kaaba]]. According to [[Muslim]] [[tradition]], Ishmael was buried in [[Al-Hijr]], inside the [[Sacred Mosque]].&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of Islam'' Volume 4, ''Ismail''&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Islamic theology|Islamic belief]], Abraham had prayed to [[God]] for a son and God heard his prayer. [[Muslim]] [[exegesis]] states that [[Sarah]] asked Abraham to marry her [[Egypt]]ian [[handmaiden]] [[Hagar]] because she herself was barren.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; Hagar soon bore Ishmael, who was the first son of Abraham. After Sarah gave birth to her own son, [[Isaac]], tension arose between the two women. According to [[exegesis]], [[God]] told Abraham to listen to Sarah, who said that both Hagar and Ishmael should be taken out of their household and into the desert.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; In [[Islamic]] [[tradition]], Abraham took Hagar and Ishmael to the desert himself, where he left them and returned to his household. In the desert, the young Ishmael cried with thirst.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; His mother searched for water, which resulted in her running seven times between the [[Al-Safa and Al-Marwah|Safa and Marwah]] hills, before God helped them by making spring water gush forth from the [[Zamzam well]], so both mother and son could rejuvenate themselves. To commemorate the bravery of Hagar and Ishmael, Muslims run between the [[Al-Safa and Al-Marwah|Safa and Marwah]] hills during [[Hajj]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

On one of his visits to [[Mecca]], [[Abraham]] is said to have asked his son to help him build the requested [[Kaaba]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|2|127|style=ref}})&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic traditions hold that the Kaaba was first built by [[Adam (Bible)|Adam]] and that Abraham and Ishmael rebuilt the Kaaba on the old foundations.&lt;ref&gt;Azraqi, ''Akhbar Makkah'', vol. 1, pp. 58-66&lt;/ref&gt; As Ishmael grew up in [[Arabia]], he is said to have become fluent in [[Arabic]]. In the genealogical trees that the early scholars drew,&lt;ref&gt;''Chronicles'', Tabari, Vol I: ''From Creation to Flood''&lt;/ref&gt; Ishmael was considered the ancestor of the Northern [[Arab]]s and Muhammad was linked to him through the lineage of the [[patriarch]] [[Adnan]].

===Christianity===
{{See also|Hagar (Bible)#Hagar in Christian tradition|Isaac#New Testament|l1=Hagar in Christian tradition|l2=Isaac in the New Testament}}
In some Christian biblical interpretations, Ishmael is used to symbolize the older&amp;mdash;now rejected&amp;mdash;Judaic tradition; Isaac symbolizes the new tradition of Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Ishmael&quot;/&gt;{{Citation broken|date=October 2012}}

According to the Genesis account, Ishmael and his mother were cast out of the house of Abraham at the request of Sarah, in order to make sure that Isaac would be Abraham's [[wikt:heir|heir]]. In the [[Epistle to the Galatians|book of Galatians]] (4:21–31), [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]] uses the incident to symbolize the relationship between Judaism, the older but now rejected tradition, and Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR-Ishmael&quot;/&gt;{{Citation broken|date=October 2012}} In Galatians 4:28–31,&lt;ref&gt;{{niv|Galatians|4:28–31|Galatians 4:28–31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hagar is associated with the [[Mosaic Covenant|Sinai covenant]], while Sarah is associated with the [[Covenant theology|covenant of grace]] into which her son Isaac enters.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoC-Isaac&quot;&gt;Encyclopedia of Christianity(Ed. John Bowden), Isaac&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bahá'í Faith===
The [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]] writings state that it was Ishmael, and not Isaac, who was the son that Abraham almost sacrificed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author = Bahá'u'lláh |authorlink = Bahá'u'lláh |year = 1976 |title = Gleanings from the Writings of Bahá'u'lláh |publisher = Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location = Wilmette, Illinois, USA |isbn = 0-87743-187-6 |url = http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/b/GWB/gwb-32.html#gr1 | pages = 75–76}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Bahá'í writings also state that the name is unimportant as either could be used: the importance is that both were symbols of sacrifice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = Interpretation in the Bahá'í Faith | first = Juan R.I. | last = Cole | journal = Baha'i Studies Review | volume= 5 | issue = 1 | year = 1995 | url = http://bahai-library.com/cole_interpretation_bahai_faith}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Shoghi Effendi]], there has also been another Ishmael, a prophet of [[Israel]], commonly known as [[Samuel]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Concerning the appearance of two Davids; there is a Tablet from 'Abdu'l-Bahá in which He says that just as there have been two Ishmaels, one the son of Abraham, and the other one of the Prophets of Israel, there have appeared two Davids, one the author of the Psalms and father of Solomon, and the other before Moses.&quot;
(Shoghi Effendi, Dawn of a New Day, pp. 86–87)&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Abraham]]
*[[Biblical narratives and the Qur'an]]
*[[Isaac]]
*[[Legends and the Qur'an]]
*[[List of names referring to El]]
*[[Prophets of Islam]]
*[[Stories of The Prophets]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliographic references==
; Books and journals
*{{cite book | last=Metzger | first=Bruce M | coauthors=Michael D Coogan  | title=The Oxford Companion To The Bible | publisher=Oxford University Press | year=1993| isbn=978-0-19-504645-8}}
*{{cite journal | last=Nikaido| first=S.| title=Hagar and Ishmael as Literary Figures: An Intertextual Study | journal=[[Vetus Testamentum]] | volume=51 | fasc=2 | year=2001 | doi=10.1163/156853301300102110 | page=219 | issue=2}}
*{{cite book | last=Werblowsky| first=R.J. Zwi | coauthors=Geoffrey Wigoder  | title=The Oxford Dictionary of Jewish Religion | publisher=Oxford University Press | year=1997| isbn=0-19-508605-8}}
*{{cite book | last=Quinn| first=Daniel  | title=Ishmael| publisher=Bantam Dell Pub Group | year=1993| isbn=0-553-56166-9}}

; Encyclopedias
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Hubert Cancik and Helmuth Schneider | encyclopedia=Brill's New Pauly- Antiquity | publisher=Brill Academic Publishers | year=2005| id=9004122703 | isbn=978}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Paul Lagasse, Lora Goldman, Archie Hobson, Susan R. Norton | encyclopedia=The Columbia Encyclopedia | publisher=Gale Group | year=2000 | edition=6th | isbn=978-1-59339-236-9}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=John Bowden | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Christianity| publisher=Oxford University Press| year=2005| edition=1st | isbn=0-19-522393-4}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=P.J. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel, W.P. Heinrichs | encyclopedia=[[Encyclopaedia of Islam]] Online | publisher=Brill Academic Publishers | issn=1573-3912}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Lindsay Jones | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Religion| publisher=MacMillan Reference Books| year=2005| edition=2nd | isbn=978-0-02-865733-2}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | encyclopedia=The New Encyclopædia Britannica | publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, Incorporated; Rev Ed edition | year=2005 | isbn=978-1-59339-236-9}}
*{{cite encyclopedia | editor=Jane Dammen McAuliffe | encyclopedia=[[Encyclopedia of the Qur'an]] | publisher=Brill Academic Publishers | year=2005 | isbn=978-90-04-12356-4}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Ishmael}}
*[http://www.johnpratt.com/items/docs/adam_gen/intro.html Genealogy from Adam to the Twelve Tribes]
*[http://www.islam101.com/history/people/prophets/Ismael.htm Ishmael in Islam]
*[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=277&amp;letter=I&amp;search=Ishmael ''The Jewish Encyclopedia'': Ishmael].
*[http://www.anchorite.org/blog/2006/07/31/biographical-study-on-ishmael/ Biographical Study on Ishmael]
*{{CathEncy|url=http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Catholic_Encyclopedia_(1913)/Ismael|title=Ismael}}
*[http://bahai9.com/Ishmael Ishmael in Bahá'í Faith]

{{Sons of Ishmael}}
{{Sons of Ishmael2}}
{{Prophets in the Qur'an}}
{{Qur'anic people}}

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Ishmael
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Prophet
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Canaan]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Arabia]]
}}
[[Category:Abraham]]
[[Category:Adnanites]]
[[Category:Angelic apparitions]]
[[Category:Arab history]]
[[Category:Arab culture]]
[[Category:Babylonian people]]
[[Category:Descendants of Eber]]
[[Category:Fertile Crescent]]
[[Category:Muslim views of biblical figures]]
[[Category:Prophets of Islam]]
[[Category:Torah people]]

[[ace:Isma'il]]
[[ar:إسماعيل]]
[[az:İsmail]]
[[bn:ইসমাইল]]
[[bg:Исмаил]]
[[ca:Ismael]]
[[cs:Izmael]]
[[da:Ismael]]
[[de:Ismael]]
[[es:Ismael]]
[[eo:Iŝmael]]
[[eu:Ismael]]
[[fa:اسماعیل]]
[[fr:Ismaël]]
[[ko:이스마엘]]
[[id:Ismael]]
[[it:Ismaele]]
[[he:ישמעאל]]
[[kk:Исмаил]]
[[lbe:Исмаил идавс]]
[[nl:Ismaël]]
[[ja:イシュマエル]]
[[no:Ismail]]
[[pl:Izmael]]
[[pt:Ismael]]
[[ro:Ismael]]
[[ru:Измаил (в Библии)]]
[[simple:Ishmael]]
[[ckb:ئیسماعیل]]
[[sr:Измаел]]
[[fi:Ismael]]
[[sv:Ismael]]
[[tl:Ismael]]
[[ta:இஸ்மவேல்]]
[[th:อิชมาเอล]]
[[tr:İsmail]]
[[uk:Ізмаїл (в Біблії)]]
[[diq:İsmail]]
[[zh:以实玛利]]</text>
      <sha1>c2vcha4zmufp2igvf2fqxw9b5lhmaiu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
