<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jewish Theological Seminary of America</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>67416</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510954474</id>
      <parentid>510954310</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-05T18:46:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.36.70.215</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Admission of female students */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45322">{{Infobox university
| name              = Jewish Theological Seminary of America
| native_name       = 
| image_name        = JTSA 122 Bway jeh.JPG
| image_size        = 180px
| image_alt         = JTSA building at 3080 Broadway in Manhattan
| caption           = JTSA building at 3080 Broadway in Manhattan
| latin_name        = 
| motto             = והסנה איננו אכל
| mottoeng          = And the [[Burning bush|bush]] was not consumed – [[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] 3:2 
| established       = 1886
| closed            = 
| type              = [[Private university|Private]]
| affiliation       = [[Conservative Judaism]]
| endowment         = 
| budget            = 
| officer_in_charge = 
| chairman          = 
| chancellor        = [[Arnold Eisen]]
| president         = 
| vice-president    = 
| superintendent    = 
| provost           = [[Alan Cooper (biblical scholar)|Alan Cooper]]
| vice_chancellor   = [[Marc Wolf]] &amp; [[Michael Greenbaum]]
| rector            = 
| principal         = 
| dean              = 
| director          = 
| head_label        = 
| head              = 
| academic_staff    = 
| administrative_staff  = 
| students          = 
| undergrad         = 
| postgrad          = 
| doctoral          = 
| other             = 
| city              = [[New York City]]
| state             = [[New York]]
| province          = 
| country           = [[United States]]
| coor              = {{coord|40|48|43|N|73|57|37|W|region:US-NY_type:edu|display=title,inline}}
| campus            = [[Urban area|Urban]]
| former_names      = 
| free_label        = Facebook
| free              = [http://www.facebook.com/JewishTheologicalSeminary JTS on Facebook]
| colors            = 
| colours           = 
| athletics         = 
| sports            = 
| nickname          = 
| mascot            = 
| affiliations      = 
| website           = [http://www.jtsa.edu/ www.jtsa.edu]
| logo              = 
| footnotes         = 
}}

The '''Jewish Theological Seminary of America''' (JTS or JTSA) is one of the academic and spiritual centers of [[Conservative Judaism]], and a major center for academic scholarship in Jewish studies.

JTS operates five schools: [[List College|Albert A. List College of Jewish Studies]] (which is affiliated with [[Columbia University]] and offers joint/double bachelors degree programs with both Columbia and [[Barnard College]]); The Graduate School; the William Davidson Graduate School of Jewish Education; the H. L. Miller Cantorial School and College of Jewish Music; and The Rabbinical School.  It also operates a number of research and training institutes.

==History==
=== Jewish Theological Seminary of Breslau===
{{main|Jewish Theological Seminary of Breslau}}
[[Rabbi]] [[Zecharias Frankel]] (1801–1875) at one time was in the traditional wing of the nascent [[Reform Judaism]] movement. After the second Reform rabbinic conference (1845, Frankfurt, [[Germany]]) he resigned after coming to believe that their positions were excessively radical.  In 1854 he became the head of a new rabbinical school, the [[Jewish Theological Seminary of Breslau]].  In his magnum opus ''Darkhei HaMishnah'' (''Ways of the [[Mishnah]]''), Frankel amassed scholarly support which showed that [[halakha|Jewish law]] was not static, but rather had always developed in response to changing conditions.  He called his approach towards [[Judaism]] 'Positive-Historical', which meant that one should accept Jewish law and tradition as normative, yet one must be open to changing and developing the law in the same historical fashion that Judaism has always historically developed.

===The Morais era (1886–1897)===
About this time in America, Rabbi [[Sabato Morais]] championed the reaction to American [[Reform Judaism|Reform]]. At one time Morais had been a voice for moderation within the coalition of Reformers. He had opposed the more radical changes, but was open to moderate changes that would not offend traditional sensibilities. After the Reform movement published the Pittsburgh Platform, Morais recognized the futility of his efforts and began the creation of a new rabbinical school in [[New York City]].  The &quot;Jewish Theological Seminary Association&quot; was founded with Morais as its President in 1886.&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishencyclopedia.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=297&amp;letter=J Jewish Theological Seminary of America] Jewish Encyclopedia.&lt;/ref&gt;

Morais was soon joined by [[Alexander Kohut]] and [[Bernard Drachman]], both of whom had received ''[[semicha]]'' (rabbinic ordination) at Rabbi Frankel's Breslau seminary. They shaped the curriculum and philosophy of the new school after Rabbi Frankel's seminary.  The first graduate to be ordained was Morris Mandel who went to lead [[Adas Israel congregation (Washington, D.C.)]].

Morais served as the president of the Jewish Theological Seminary of America until his death in 1897.

===The Schechter era (1902-1915)===

After Morais's death, the financial position of the association became precarious. In October 1901, a new organization was projected entitled the &quot;Jewish Theological Seminary of America,&quot; with which the association was invited to incorporate. This arrangement was carried into effect April 14, 1902. The new organization was endowed with a fund of over $500,000, and was presented with a suitable building on [[University Heights, Bronx|University Heights]] by Jacob H. Schiff. It obtained a charter from the state of New York (approved Feb. 20, 1902), &quot;for the perpetuation of the tenets of the [[Jewish religion]], the cultivation of [[Hebrew literature]], the pursuit of [[Biblical]] and archeological research, the advancement of Jewish scholarship, the establishment of a library, and the education and training of Jewish rabbis and teachers. It is empowered to grant and confer the degrees of [[Rabbi]], [[Ḥazan]], Master and Doctor of Hebrew Literature, and [[Doctor of Divinity]], and also to award certificates of proficiency to persons qualified to teach in [[Hebrew schools]].&quot; The reorganized seminary was opened on Sept. 15, 1902, in the old building of the Theological Seminary Association at 736 Lexington Avenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishencyclopedia.com&quot;/&gt;

[[Solomon Schechter]] assumed presidency of JTS, as well as serving as Professor of Jewish theology.&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishencyclopedia.com&quot;/&gt; In a series of papers he articulated an ideology for the nascent movement of [[Conservative Judaism]]. In 1913 he presided over the creation of the United Synagogue of America. (The name was changed in 1991 to the [[United Synagogue of Conservative Judaism]].)

Along with Schechter and [[Bernard Drachman]], professors at the Seminary at the time included: [[Louis Ginzberg]], professor of Talmud;  [[Alexander Marx]], professor of [[Jewish history|history]] and [[rabbinical literature]] and [[librarian]]; [[Israel Friedländer]],  professor of [[Hebrew Bible|Bible]]; Joseph Mayor Asher, professor of homiletics; and Joshua A. Joffe, instructor in Talmud.&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishencyclopedia.com&quot;/&gt;  In 1905, [[Israel Davidson]] joined the faculty, teaching [[Hebrew]] and [[Rabbinics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee Bycel p. 541&quot;&gt;David Ellenson and Lee Bycel, &quot;The JTS Rabbinical Curriculum&quot; in ''Tradition Renewed'', v. 2, p. 541&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[David Ellenson]] and Lee Bycel, &quot;each of these men was a distinguished scholar, and the academic reputation of the Seminary soared with the addition of these men to the faculty.... Schechter was determined to carve out the highest academic reputation for the Seminary.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee Bycel p. 541&quot;/&gt;

The rabbinical school had very high academic standards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee Bycel p. 544&quot;&gt;David Ellenson and Lee Bycel, &quot;The JTS Rabbinical Curriculum&quot; in ''Tradition Renewed'', v. 2, p. 544&lt;/ref&gt;  The curriculum focused especially on [[Talmud]], [[Halakha#Codes_of_Jewish_law|legal codes]], and classical [[rabbinic literature]], but aside from a little time for a Homiletics class, very little time was spent on practical training for serving in a rabbinical position.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee Bycel p. 544&quot;/&gt;

As of 1904 there were 37 students in the theological department, and 120 students took a set of courses designed for teachers (which later evolved into the Teachers Institute).&lt;ref name=&quot;jewishencyclopedia.com&quot;/&gt;

[[Mordechai Kaplan]] also joined the faculty during this period and became professor of homiletics (upon Joseph Mayor Asher's death)&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee Bycel p. 541&quot;/&gt; and also the first principal of a new school within JTS known as The Teachers Institute (TI).  The Teachers Institute opened in 1909.  A majority of its students were women, both because teaching was seen as a women's profession and because the Teachers Institute was one of the only institutions where women could obtain an advanced education in Jewish studies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/x11978.xml The Jewish Theological Seminary - The Teachers Institute 100th Anniversary&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  The Teachers Institute offered both undergraduate and graduate degrees.  (Its undergraduate division later evolved into the [[Albert A. List College of Jewish Studies]], and its graduate division evolved into the William Davidson Graduate School of Jewish Education.)

===The Adler era (1915-1940)===
In 1915, Schechter was succeeded by  [[Cyrus Adler]], the President of [[Dropsie College]].  A member of the board with impressive academic qualifications, he was initially seen as an interim replacement for Schechter.&lt;ref&gt;Ira Robinson, &quot;Cyrus Adler: President of the Jewish Theological Seminary, 1915-1940,&quot; in ''Tradition Renewed'', ed. Wertheimer, v.1, p. 108-110&lt;/ref&gt;  But no better chancellor was found, and Adler went on to serve as President until 1940.

During the 1920s, Adler explored the possibility of a merger with [[Yeshiva University]], but [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] leaders of [[Yeshiva University]] viewed JTS as insufficiently Orthodox.&lt;ref&gt;Ira Robinson, &quot;Cyrus Adler: President of the Jewish Theological Seminary, 1915-1940,&quot; in ''Tradition Renewed'', ed. Wertheimer, v.1, p. 123-125&lt;/ref&gt;

New faculty appointed during the early part of Adler's tenure included the Biblical scholar [[Jacob Hoschander]].&lt;ref&gt;Ira Robinson, &quot;Cyrus Adler: President of the Jewish Theological Seminary, 1915-1940,&quot; in ''Tradition Renewed'', ed. Wertheimer, v.1, p. 128-130&lt;/ref&gt;  In the 1920s, [[Boaz Cohen]] and [[Louis Finkelstein]], both of whom were ordained at JTS and completed their doctoral degrees at [[Columbia University]], joined the Talmud faculty.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Boaz Cohen (1899-1968),&quot; by Elias J. Bickerman and Edward M. Gershfield, ''Proceedings of the American Academy for Jewish Research,'' Vol. 37, (1969), pp. xxix-xxxi&lt;/ref&gt;  In the 1930s, Adler appointed [[H.L. Ginsberg]], [[Robert Gordis]], and [[Alexander Sperber]] as professors of Bible.  He also gave appointments to [[Israel Efros]], [[Simon Greenberg]], [[Milton Steinberg]], and [[Ismar Elbogen]].&lt;ref&gt;Ira Robinson, &quot;Cyrus Adler: President of the Jewish Theological Seminary, 1915-1940,&quot; in ''Tradition Renewed'', ed. Wertheimer, v.1, p. 138-139&lt;/ref&gt;

During his tenure, Adler groomed [[Louis Finkelstein]] as his chosen successor.  In 1931, he appointed Finkelstein to a full professorship.  Finkelstein became the Solomon Schechter Professor of Theology.  In 1937 Adler appointed Finkelstein as Provost.&lt;ref&gt;Ira Robinson, &quot;Cyrus Adler: President of the Jewish Theological Seminary, 1915-1940,&quot; in ''Tradition Renewed'', ed. Wertheimer, v.1, p. 140-141&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1930 the organization commissioned a new headquarters for 122nd Street and Broadway in a neo-colonial style, with a tower at the corner.  The architects were Gehron, Ross and Alley.

In 1931, the Seminary College of Jewish Studies was established for students who wanted college-level courses in Jewish studies but who were not preparing for teaching careers.  (The Seminary College of Jewish Studies later became the [[Albert A. List College of Jewish Studies]].)

===The Finkelstein era (1940-72)===

[[Louis Finkelstein]] became Chancellor of the Jewish Theological Seminary in 1940.  During his chancellorship, JTS made significant efforts to engage the American public.  One of its signature programs was a radio and television show called [[The Eternal Light]]. The show aired on Sunday afternoons, featuring well-known Jewish personalities like [[Chaim Potok]] and [[Elie Wiesel]]. Broadcasts did not involve preaching or prayer, but drew on history, literature and social issues to explore Judaism and Jewish holidays in a manner that was accessible to persons of any faith.  The show continued to run until 1985.

During the 1940s, the Jewish Theological Seminary established [[Camp Ramah]] as a tool for furthering [[Jewish education]]. The founders envisioned an informal camp setting where Jewish youth would reconnect with the [[synagogue]] and Jewish tradition, and a new cadre of American-born Jewish leadership could be cultivated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/x4763.xml The Jewish Theological Seminary – Record Group 28: Camp Ramah&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;   The first camp opened in [[Conover, Wisconsin]] in 1947.  The program was drawn up by [[Moshe Davis]] and [[Sylvia Ettenberg]] of the JTS Teachers' Institute.

In 1945, JTS established a new institution, the Leadership Training Fellowship, designed to educate young people within Conservative synagogues and guide them into Jewish public service.&lt;ref&gt;''Tradition Renewed'', v. 1, 197&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1952, the Jewish Theological Seminary opened a new school known as the Cantors Institute.  (The school was later renamed the H. L. Miller Cantorial School and College of Jewish Music.)  This was at roughly the same time that the other established American Jewish seminaries, [[Hebrew Union College]] and [[Yeshiva University]] opened cantorial schools.  Prior to this time, American cantors were often trained in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Discovering Jewish music, by Marsha Bryan Edelman, p. 134-5&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1950, Finkelstein created the Universal Brotherhood program, which &quot;brought together laymen interested in interpreting the ethical dimensions of Judaism to the wider society.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Tradition Renewed'', v.1, p.199&lt;/ref&gt; JTS expanded its public outreach in the 1950s with Finkelstein's development of JTS's Institute for Religious Studies and the establishment of its Herbert H. Lehman Institute of Ethics.

During the Finkelstein era, the Institute for Religious and Social Studies brought together Protestant, Roman Catholic and Jewish scholars for theological discussions. (In 1986, the name of the institute was changed to the Finkelstein Institute for Religious and Social Studies in Finkelstein's honor.)

In 1957, JTS announced plans to build a satellite campus in [[Jerusalem]] for JTS rabbinical students studying in Israel.  A building was completed in 1962.&lt;ref&gt;'Tradition Renewed'', v. 1, p. 200&lt;/ref&gt; (The campus eventually evolved into the home of the [[Schechter Institute of Jewish Studies]].)  In 1962, the seminary also acquired the Schocken Institute for Jewish Research and its library in Jerusalem.

In 1968, JTS received a charter from the State of New York to create an Institute for Advanced Studies in the Humanities, which conferred bachelor's, master's, and doctoral degrees.  The Institute was designed as a non-sectarian academic institute which would train future college and university professors.  Its first students enrolled in 1970.  The Institute later evolved into the Graduate School of the Jewish Theological Seminary.&lt;ref&gt;''Tradition Renewed'', v. 1, p. 240&lt;/ref&gt;

====Faculty during the Finkelstein era====
When Finkelstein took office, prominent faculty members included [[Louis Ginzberg]], [[Alexander Marx]], [[Mordecai Kaplan]], [[H.L. Ginsberg]], [[Robert Gordis]], and [[Boaz Cohen]].

In 1940, Finkelstein made his most significant academic appointment,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee Bycel p. 556&quot;&gt;David Ellenson and Lee Bycel, &quot;The JTS Rabbinical Curriculum&quot; in ''Tradition Renewed'', v. 2, p. 556&lt;/ref&gt; hiring the prominent Talmud scholar [[Saul Lieberman]] as Professor of Palestinian Literature and Institutions.  In 1948, Lieberman became dean of the Rabbinical School.  In 1958, he was named rector of the Seminary.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee Bycel p. 556&quot;/&gt;

In 1945, Finkelstein hired the theologian [[Abraham Joshua Heschel]], who had been teaching for a brief period at [[Hebrew Union College]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee Bycel p. 556&quot;/&gt;  During the course of his chancellorship, Finkelstein also gave academic appointments to other prominent scholars including [[Moshe Davis]] (1942), [[Shalom Spiegel]] (1943), [[Yochanan Muffs]] (1954), [[Max Kadushin]] (1960), [[Gerson Cohen]], [[David Weiss Halivni]], [[Judah Goldin]], [[Chaim Dimitrovsky]], and [[Seymour Siegel]].

Finkelstein appointed [[Max Arzt]] to serve as Vice-Chancellor of JTS in 1951, and he appointed Arzt as Israel Goldstein Professor of Practical Theology in 1962.&lt;ref&gt;''Conservative Judaism in America: a biographical dictionary and sourcebook'' by Pamela Susan Nadell, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt;

====Library fire====
{{main|Jewish Theological Seminary library fire}}
In April 1966 JTS's library caught fire. 70,000 books were destroyed, and many others were damaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;lostmemoryunesco&quot;&gt;[http://www.unesco.org/webworld/mdm/administ/pdf/LOSTMEMO.PDF LOST MEMORY - LIBRARIES AND ARCHIVES DESTROYED IN THE TWENTIETH CENTURY] ({{WebCite|http://www.webcitation.org/61Kj1muns}})&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Cohen era (1972-1986)===
[[Gerson D. Cohen]] became Chancellor of the Jewish Theological Seminary in 1972.

Prominent faculty during Cohen's chancellorship included [[David Weiss Halivni]] of the Talmud Department and [[José Faur]].  Both of these scholars resigned when the JTS faculty voted to ordain women as rabbis and as cantors in 1983.

[[Yochanan Muffs]], who had joined the JTS faculty in 1954, was a prominent professor of [[Bible]].  [[Max Kadushin]], who had joined the JTS faculty in 1960, taught ethics and rabbinic thought until his death in 1980.

In 1972, Cohen appointed [[Avraham Holtz]] as the dean of academic evelopment.  [[Neil Gillman]] served as Dean of the JTS Rabbinical School for much of the Cohen chancellorship.{{when|date=November 2010}} Morton Leifman served as Dean of the Cantors Institute.{{when|date=November 2010}}

Cohen oversaw the appointment of [[Judith Hauptman]] as the first female professor of Talmud at JTS.  Hauptman began teaching at JTS in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/biography/hauptman.html Judith Hauptman&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Joel Roth]], who had begun teaching at JTS in 1968, was appointed Associate Professor of Talmud upon completing his Ph.D. at JTS in 1973.  Roth went on to serve as the dean of the Rabbinical School from 1981 to 1984.  He was succeeded by [[Gordon Tucker]], who became dean of the Rabbinical School in 1984.

In June 1973, the Seminary's Institute for Advanced Studies in the Humanities was granted permission to grant Ph.D. degrees in [[Jewish History]], [[Hebrew Bible|Bible]], [[Talmud]], [[Jewish Philosophy]], and [[Hebrew]].  In 1975, the Seminary replaced the Institute for Advanced Studies in the Humanities with the Graduate School of the Jewish Theological Seminary, which brought together JTS's non-theological academic training programs.  Cohen appointed historian [[Ismar Schorsch]] as the first dean of the Graduate School.&lt;ref&gt;''Tradition Renewed'', v. 1, p. 240-1&lt;/ref&gt;

====Admission of female students====
Beginning in the 1970s, the topic of women's ordination was regularly discussed at JTS.&lt;ref&gt;''Women Who Would Be Rabbis: A History of Women's Ordination 1889-1985'' by Pamela S. Nadell, p. 214&lt;/ref&gt;  Women who unsuccessfully sought admission to the rabbinical school during the 1970s included [[Susannah Heschel]], daughter of JTS faculty member [[Abraham Joshua Heschel]].&lt;ref&gt;''Women Who Would Be Rabbis: A History of Women's Ordination 1889-1985'' by Pamela S. Nadell, p. 198&lt;/ref&gt;  After years of discussion, the JTS faculty voted to ordain women as rabbis and as cantors in 1983.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Encyclopedia of women and religion in North America, Volume 2 |last=Keller |first=Rosemary Skinner |coauthors=Rosemary Radford Ruether; Marie Cantlon |year=2006 |publisher=Indiana University Press |location=Bloomington, IN |isbn=0-253-34687-8 |page=551 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=WPILfbtT5tQC&amp;dq |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first female rabbi to graduate from the school (and the first female Conservative Jewish rabbi in the world) was [[Amy Eilberg]], who graduated and was ordained as a rabbi in 1985.&lt;ref&gt;http://my.brandeis.edu/profiles/one-profile?profile_id=1037&lt;/ref&gt; The first class of female rabbis that was admitted to JTS in 1984 included Rabbi [[Naomi Levy]], who later became a best-selling author&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishjournal.com/cover_story/article/a_rabbis_journey_a_mothers_anxious_path_20100914 A rabbi’s journey, a mother’s anxious path]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Nina Beth Cardin]], who became an author and environmental activist.&lt;ref&gt;Susan Josephs, [www.jwi.org/Page.aspx?pid=2034 Rabbi Nina Beth Cardin: Making the Environment a Jewish Priority]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Erica Lipitz]] and [[Marla Rosenfeld Barugel]] were the first women ordained as cantors by JTS (and the first female Conservative Jewish cantors in the world.) They were both ordained in 1987.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/cantors-american-jewish-women Cantors: American Jewish Women | Jewish Women's Archive&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Schorsch era (1986–2006)===
[[Ismar Schorsch]] became Chancellor of JTS in 1986.

Among his accomplishments was creating the William Davidson Graduate School of Jewish Education, which was established through an endowmen by [[William Davidson]] of Detroit in 1994.

Prominent faculty in the Talmud and Rabbinics department during Schorsch's chancellorship included  [[Joel Roth]], [[Mayer Rabinowitz]], [[David C. Kraemer]] and [[Judith Hauptman]].  Hauptman was the first woman appointed to teach Talmud at JTS.  The Bible department included [[David Marcus (biblical scholar)|David Marcus]] and [[Stephen A. Geller]].  The Jewish literature Department included [[David G. Roskies]].  The Jewish history department included  [[Jack Wertheimer]] and  [[Shuly Rubin Schwartz]].  The Jewish Philosophy department included [[Neil Gillman]] and [[Shaul Magid]].  In 2004, [[Alan Mittleman]] joined the Jewish Philosophy department and became head of JTS's Louis Finkelstein Institute for Religious and Social Studies.

The number of advanced programs in the Graduate School grew over the course of Schorsch's tenure.  The Graduate School came to describe itself as being &quot;the most extensive academic program in advanced Judaica in North America.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060112150849/www.jtsa.edu/graduate/admissions/brochure.pdf The Graduate School of the Jewish Theological Seminary], 1/2006 (from archive.org)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gordon Tucker]]'s tenure as dean of the Rabbinical School ended in 1992.  His predecessor, [[Joel Roth]], again became dean, serving in 1992-1993. Roth was succeeded by [[William Lebeau]], who served as dean from 1993-1999.  Lebeau was succeeded by Alan Kensky, and then Lebeau became dean of the Rabbinical School again in June 2002.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/about/communications/press/20052006/20060630.shtml &quot;Rabbi William Lebeau to Retire on July 1, 2007&quot;], Jewish Theological Seminary of America press release dated June 30, 2006. Accessed May 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998, [[Henry Rosenblum]] was appointed Dean of the H.L. Miller Cantorial School and College of Jewish Music at the Jewish Theological Seminary in 1998, becoming the first Hazzan to hold that position.  Rosenblum remained in this position until 2010.

===The Eisen era (2007-present)===

[[Arnold Eisen]], Koshland Professor of Jewish Culture and Religion and Chair of the Department of Religious Studies at Stanford University, took office as Chancellor-elect on July 1, 2006, the day after Schorsch stepped down.  Eisen assumed the position full time on July 1, 2007.

Eisen is the second non-rabbi, after [[Cyrus Adler]], to hold this post. He is also the first person with a [[social science]] background to serve as Chancellor; previous chancellors had backgrounds in [[Jewish]] [[history]] or [[Talmud]].

In January 2007, at the start of Eisen's chancellorship, [[Daniel S. Nevins]] was named the Dean of the Rabbinical School of the Jewish Theological Seminary of America, succeeding [[William H. Lebeau|Rabbi William Lebeau]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/about/communications/press/20062007/20070129.shtml &quot;Rabbi Daniel Nevins Named New Dean of The Rabbinical School of The Jewish Theological Seminary&quot;], Jewish Theological Seminary of America press release dated January 29, 2007. Accessed May 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  Biblical scholar [[Alan Cooper (biblical scholar)|Alan Cooper]] was named Provost.&lt;ref&gt;Chicago Tribune, Mar 23, 2007, Metro Section, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, [[Henry Rosenblum]] left the H.L. Miller Cantorial School as part of JTS's restructuring efforts, and Nevins also became responsible for oversight of the H.L. Miller Cantorial School.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tabletmag.com/life-and-religion/25551/endnote Endnote - by Marissa Brostoff - Tablet Magazine – Jewish News and Politics, Jewish Arts and Culture, Jewish Life and Religion&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2009, [[Goldman Sachs]] executive [[Abby Joseph Cohen]] was named Chairman of the Board of JTS, the first woman to hold the position.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.jta.org/telegraph/article/2009/06/12/1005840/jts-to-get-first-woman-chair-as-kekst-steps-down JTS to get first woman chair, as Kekst steps down. Accessed 10-26-10]&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2009, with funding from the Charles H. Revson Foundation and the Booth Ferris Foundation, JTS established The Center for Pastoral Education with the goal of teaching the art of pastoral care to seminary students and ordained clergy of all faiths.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/CenterforPastoralEducation.xml The Jewish Theological Seminary - Center for Pastoral Education&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  The Center was developed by Rabbi [[Mychal Springer]], formerly an Associate Dean of the Rabbinical School.  Springer became the Center's first director.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/x11808.xml#sp The Jewish Theological Seminary - Center for Pastoral Education&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, the [[Tikvah Fund]] endowed a new institute at JTS, the Tikvah Institute for Jewish Thought, which is &quot;devoted to the intellectual encounter between the best sources of Jewish and broader Western reflection on the deepest problems of human life.&quot;  According to the Seminary, &quot;JTS was selected by the Tikvah Fund based on its academic excellence and its mission to advance Jewish life in the modern world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/x11770.xml April 27, 2009: JTS Receives Tikvah Fund Grant to Create Tikvah Institute for Jewish Thought]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Alan Mittleman]], Chair of the Department of Jewish Thought, was appointed as its director.

Professor [[Burton L. Visotzky]] was appointed to replace Mittleman as director of the Louis Finkelstein Institute for Religious and Social Studies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/News/Press_Releases/LFI_Anouncement.xml The Jewish Theological Seminary - JTS Appoints New Director of the Louis Finkelstein Institute&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  His early work as director of the Finkelstein Institute focused on Muslim-Jewish dialogue.  In October 2010, a group of prominent Muslim and Jewish scholars and leaders, joined by the heads of several Christian seminaries, met at JTS for two days to discuss and compare the situations of Islam and Judaism in America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/new_york/conservative_seminary_getting_beyond_park51 At Conservative Seminary, Getting Beyond Park51] Accessed 10-26-10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Arnold Eisen, [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/arnold-m-eisen/jewish-seminary-muslim-workshop_b_773058.html Why a Jewish Seminary Must Find Common Ground With Islam]&lt;/ref&gt;

In May, 2011, Eisen launched “[http://www.jtsa.edu/CJBlog Conservative Judaism: A Community Conversation],” an interactive website featuring original essays on Conservative Judaism, with responses from Movement and Lay leaders and scholars.

====Admission of LGBT students====
Since March 2007, JTS has accepted openly gay students into their rabbinical and cantorial programs (the Seminary's other three schools upheld such non-discrimination policies prior to this date). A survey conducted prior to the decision indicated that 58% of the rabbinical student body supported this change.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/842238.html |publisher=Haaretz.com |title=NY Jewish seminary to accept gay students |last=shamir |first=Shlomo |date=2007-03-28 |accessdate=2009-01-06 |quote=A Conservative Jewish seminary in New York has agreed to admit gays and lesbians who want to become rabbis and cantors, but declined to take a stand on whether rabbis should officiate at same-sex unions. }}&lt;/ref&gt; The school issued a press release&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jtsa.edu/about/communications/press/20062007/20070326.shtml |publisher=JTSA |title=JTS to Accept Qualified Gay and Lesbian Rabbinical And Cantorial School Students |date=2007-03-26 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070818191505/http://www.jtsa.edu/about/communications/press/20062007/20070326.shtm |archivedate=2007-08-18 |quote=Note: The original page has been removed from school's web site}}&lt;/ref&gt; announcing the new admission policy, without taking a stance on same-sex unions. JTS marked the first year anniversary of the change with a special program. Some students who opposed the change in admission policy said they felt excluded from the day's program because it did not sufficiently recognize the pluralism in the student body. &lt;br /&gt;
In April 2011, JTS held a Yom Iyyun, or day of learning, about LGBTQ issues, and their intersection with Judaism.  [[Joy Ladin]], a transgender woman who teaches English at [[Yeshiva University]], gave a talk about her life.  Other programs included creating welcoming communities, and inclusive prayer, among others.  It was sponsored in part by [[Keshet (organization)|Keshet]], the Jewish social action group that works to see queer individuals included in all sectors of Jewish life.

====New Mission====

In May 2010, the Jewish Theological Seminary under [[Arnold Eisen]]'s leadership unveiled the following mission statement:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The Jewish Theological Seminary of America is a preeminent institution of Jewish higher education that integrates rigorous academic scholarship and teaching with a commitment to strengthening Jewish tradition, Jewish lives, and Jewish communities.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;JTS articulates a vision of Judaism that is learned and passionate, pluralist and authentic, traditional and egalitarian; one that is thoroughly grounded in Jewish texts, history, and practices, and fully engaged with the societies and cultures of the present. Our vision joins faith with inquiry; the covenant of our ancestors with the creative insights of today; intense involvement in the society and State of Israel with devotion to the flowering of Judaism throughout the world; service to the Jewish community, as well as to all of the communities of which Jews are a part: our society, our country, and our world.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;JTS serves North American Jewry by educating intellectual and spiritual leaders for Conservative Judaism and the vital religious center, training rabbis, cantors, scholars, educators, communal professionals, and lay activists who are inspired by our vision of Torah and dedicated to assisting in its realization.&lt;ref name=&quot;jtsvideo.net&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JTS drafts new mission statement&quot;&gt;[http://blogs.jta.org/philanthropy/article/2010/05/13/2394807/jts-drafts-new-mission-statement JTS drafts new mission statement]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Seminary sees its mission statement as based on six principles:&lt;ref name=&quot;JTS drafts new mission statement&quot;/&gt;
*Scholarship in Service to Judaism and the Jewish Community
*Excellence in Teaching and Learning
*Synergy (bringing students from its different schools together)
*Partnerships (with other institutions)
*Reaching New Types of Students
*Engaging and Strengthening [[Conservative Judaism]] and the Religious Center

==JTS and the Conservative Movement==
JTS was the founding institution of [[Conservative Judaism]] in America.  The [[United Synagogue of America]], the organization of Conservative synagogues, was founded by Solomon Schechter while he served as President of JTS.

During the chancellorship of [[Louis Finkelstein]], however, there were many tensions between JTS and the [[Conservative Judaism]] movement which it led.  JTS was often more traditional in matters of religious practice than the denomination as a whole.  Finkelstein was also perceived as focusing on American and world Jewry as a whole while paying little attention to the Conservative movement.

According to scholar Michael Panitz, the situation changed under Finkelstein's successors.  Under Chancellor [[Gerson Cohen]] (chancellor from 1972–86), JTS &quot;decisively embraced its identity as a Conservative Jewish institution, it thereby abandoned its earlier hopes to provide a non-denominational unifier for traditional and moderate American Jews.&quot;  The next chancellor, [[Ismar Schorsch]] (1986–2006), &quot;emerged as an outspoken advocate for Conservative Judaism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/judaica/ejud_0002_0011_0_10158.html Encyclopaedia Judaica]&lt;/ref&gt;  With the new mission statement introduced by Chancellor Arnold Eisen (2007-), the school has positioned itself as serving both &quot;Conservative Judaism&quot; and &quot;the vital religious center.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;jtsvideo.net&quot;&gt;[http://www.jtsvideo.net/newvision/mission.html New Vision of The Jewish Theological Seminary&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2010, JTS's website describes JTS as &quot;the academic and spiritual center of Conservative Judaism worldwide.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = Jewish Theological Seminary | url = http://www.jtsa.edu/Conservative_Judaism/The_History_and_Mission_of_JTS/Conservative_Movement_Affiliates.xml | title = Conservative Movement Affiliates | publisher = | date = | accessdate = 2010-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Others describe it as &quot;the academic and spiritual centre of Conservative Judaism in the United States.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/303646/Jewish-Theological-Seminary-of-America | title=The Encyclopædia Britannica |accessdate=2010-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A second important center for Conservative Judaism in the United States is the [[Ziegler School of Rabbinic Studies]] in California, founded by graduates of JTS in 1996.

==Current educational programs==
===Rabbinical School===

The Rabbinical School describes itself as offering &quot;an intensive program of study, personal growth, and spiritual development that leads to [[rabbinic]] ordination and a career of service to the Jewish community.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/x731.xml The Jewish Theological Seminary - The Rabbinical School&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2010, the rabbinical school requires five or six years of study.  Its curriculum requires extensive study of [[Talmud]], [[midrash]], [[Bible]], [[Jewish history]], [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] language, and various professional skills.  Students are required to spend the second year of the program at the [[Schechter Institute of Jewish Studies]] in [[Jerusalem]].

Students must choose a field of concentration during their studies.  Concentrations include:

*[[Bible]]
*[[Rabbinics]]
*[[Midrash]]
*[[Jewish history]]
*[[Jewish literature]]
*[[Jewish liturgy]]
*[[Jewish education]]
*[[Jewish philosophy]]
*Jewish [[women's studies]]
*[[Pastoral care]]

===Cantorial School===

The Cantorial School describes itself as training &quot;select advanced students as [[hazzanim]] (cantors) for congregational service or as teachers of Jewish music, choral directors, composers, or research scholars.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;jtsa.edu&quot;&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/x780.xml The Jewish Theological Seminary - H. L. Miller Cantorial School and College of Jewish Music&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The school is technically divided into two parts: the entity formally known as the ''H. L. Miller Cantorial School'' invests students as [[hazzanim]], while the entity known as the ''College of Jewish Music'' awards the Master's degree in Sacred Music.  All students in the Cantorial School are enrolled in both programs simultaneously.&lt;ref name=&quot;jtsa.edu&quot;/&gt;

At present, the first year of cantorial school at JTS is generally spent in [[Israel]].  The curriculum during the five years focuses on three main areas: general [[music]], [[Jewish music]] and [[Torah study|Jewish text study]].

===Graduate School===

The Graduate School of the Jewish Theological Seminary offers academic programs in advanced Jewish studies. It describes itself as offering &quot;the most extensive academic program in advanced Judaic Studies in North America.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtsa.edu/x15058.xml &quot;JTS Graduate School Sends Notable Cohort to the Association for Jewish Studies' Annual Conference,&quot;] accessed 11-23-2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The school grants MA, DHL, and PhD degrees in the areas of:

*Ancient [[Judaism]]
*[[Bible]] and Ancient [[Semitic]] Languages
*Interdepartmental Studies (MA only)
*[[Jewish art|Jewish Art]] and Visual Culture (MA only)
*[[Jewish History]]
*[[Jewish literature|Jewish Literature]]
*[[Jewish Philosophy]]
*Jewish Studies and [[Public Administration]] (MA only)
*Jewish Studies and [[Social Work]] (MA only)
*Jewish [[Women’s Studies]] (MA only)
*[[Jewish liturgy|Liturgy]]
*[[Medieval Jewry|Medieval Jewish]] Studies
*[[Midrash]]
*Modern Jewish Studies
*[[Talmud]] and [[Rabbinics]]

===William Davidson Graduate School of Jewish Education===

In 1994, [[William Davidson]] of Detroit, Michigan established a $15 million endowment at JTS to fund the William Davidson Graduate School of Jewish Education, which trains educators who can serve in Jewish institutions and elsewhere, in both formal and informal settings.  The Davidson School offers both master's and doctoral degrees.

===List College===
{{Main|List College}}
Albert A. List College of Jewish Studies ([[List College]]) is the undergraduate school of JTSA.  It is closely affiliated with [[Columbia University]]; almost all List College students are enrolled in dual-degree programs (BA/BA or BA/BS) with either [[Columbia University]]’s School of General Studies or [[Barnard College]].

==Additional Institutes at JTS==
* Tikvah Institute for Jewish Thought - devoted to the intellectual encounter between the best sources of Jewish and broader Western reflection on the deepest problems of human life.
*Melton Research Center for Jewish Education -  focuses on improving the quality of Jewish education in North America.
*Louis Finkelstein Institute for Religious and Social Studies -   focuses on interfaith relations and public affairs.
*Saul Lieberman Institute for Talmudic Research - develops modern and rigorous computer tools for Talmud study.
* Institute for Jewish Learning - focuses on advanced adult education.
*Center for Pastoral Education - focuses on the art of pastoral care.

==Notable alumni==
*[[Bella Abzug]], lawyer, Congresswoman, social activist, feminist leader
*[[Philip R. Alstat]], rabbi, counselor, and chaplain
*[[Bradley Shavit Artson]], dean of [[Ziegler School of Rabbinic Studies]]
*[[Herman Berlinski]] composer, organist, musicologist and choir conductor
*[[Ben Zion Bokser]], rabbi and scholar
*[[Daniel Boyarin]], professor of Talmudic Culture, Near Eastern Studies and Rhetoric, University of California at Berkeley
*[[Boaz Cohen]], JTS professor, and chairman of the Law Committee of the [[Rabbinical Assembly]]
*[[Gerson Cohen]], Jewish historian and JTS chancellor
*[[Menachem Creditor]], rabbi of Congregation Netivot Shalom, [[Berkeley, CA]], founder of ShefaNetwork.org, co-founder of [[Keshet Rabbis]]
*[[David G. Dalin]], historian
*[[Elliot N. Dorff]], scholar of Jewish ethics and theology, rector of [[American Jewish University]]
*[[Matthew Eisenfeld]], student killed in the [[Jaffa Road bus bombings]] in [[Jerusalem]]
*[[Amy Eilberg]],  the first female rabbi ordained in [[Conservative Judaism]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/08/19/nyregion/gerson-d-cohen-is-dead-at-66-ex-chancellor-of-jewish-seminary.html | work=The New York Times | first=Ari L. | last=Goldman | title=Gerson D. Cohen Is Dead at 66; Ex-Chancellor of Jewish Seminary | date=19 August 1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was ordained by JTS in 1985. 
*[[Ira Eisenstein]], Reconstructionist leader
*[[Louis Finkelstein]], longtime chancellor of JTS
*[[Neil Gillman]], theologian
*[[Ben-Zion Gold]], rabbi of Harvard Hillel
*[[Jonathan A. Goldstein]], Bible scholar
*[[Robert Gordis]], president of the [[Rabbinical Assembly]] and professor at JTS
*[[Daniel Gordis]], senior vice president of [[Shalem Center]]
*[[David M. Gordis]], former president of [[Hebrew College]]
*[[Arthur Green]], professor emeritus of Near Eastern and Judaic Studies at Brandeis, rector of [[Hebrew College]] rabbinical school
*[[Judith Hauptman]], feminist Talmud scholar
*[[Joseph H. Hertz]], British Chief Rabbi and author; first graduate of JTS
*[[Arthur Hertzberg]], rabbi and historian
*[[Brad Hirschfield]], co-president of CLAL, National Jewish Center for Learning and Leadership
*[[Rachel Isaacs]], the first openly lesbian rabbi ordained by JTS, which occurred in May 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lilith.org/pdfs/LILSu11_FINAL_Outandordained.pdf |author=Amy Stone |title=Out and Ordained |work=Lilith |date=Summer 2011 |accessdate=2011-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Max Kadushin]], rabbi and philosopher
*[[Ian Kagedan]], Canadian public servant
*[[Mordechai Kaplan]], philosopher, educator, founder of [[Reconstructionist Judaism]]
*[[William E. Kaufman]], [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] rabbi and Jewish [[Theology|theologian]]
*[[Irwin Kula]], co-president of CLAL, National Jewish Center for Learning and Leadership
*[[Lee I. Levine]], historian
*[[Albert L. Lewis]], rabbi
*[[David Lieber]], former president of the [[University of Judaism]]
*[[Abraham Lubin]], cantor
*[[Hershel Matt]], rabbi and professor at [[Reconstructionist Rabbinical College]]
*[[Marshall Meyer]], rabbi and human rights activist
*[[Jacob Neusner]], chair of Judaic Studies Department, Bard College
*[[David Nesenoff]], rabbi, independent filmmaker, and singer/songwriter
*[[David Novak]], scholar of Jewish philosophy, law, and ethics
*[[Norman Podhoretz]], Editor, [[Commentary (magazine)|''Commentary'']] magazine
*[[Chaim Potok]], author and rabbi
*[[Einat Ramon]], first Israeli-born woman ordained as a rabbi
*[[Paula Reimers]], rabbi and activist
*[[Arnold E. Resnicoff]], military chaplain and consultant to military and civilian leaders
*[[Joel Roth]], scholar of Talmud and Jewish law and former dean of the JTS rabbinical school
*[[Steven Rubenstein]], anthropologist
*[[Samuel Schafler]], president of [[Hebrew College]], superintendent of the Chicago Board of Jewish Education
*[[Ismar Schorsch]], Jewish historian and JTS chancellor
*[[Ira F. Stone]], rabbi, scholar of the [[Musar movement]], and professor at [[Reconstructionist Rabbinical College]]
*[[Gordon Tucker]], philosopher, legal scholar, and former dean of the JTS rabbinical school
*[[Henrietta Szold]], founder of Hadassah
*[[Mordecai Waxman]], rabbi, Temple Israel of Great Neck
*[[David Wolpe]], rabbi of [[Sinai Temple (Los Angeles, California)|Sinai Temple]], Los Angeles
*[[Rachel Isaacs]], first openly lesbian rabbi ordained by the Jewish Theological Seminary

==See also==
{{commons category|Jewish Theological Seminary of America}}
* [[Rabbinical Assembly]]
* [[Cantors Assembly]]
* [[Conservative Judaism]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.jtsa.edu/ Official website of the Jewish Theological Seminary]
* [http://mrbellersneighborhood.com/2010/06/covered-heads Brian Schwartz, &quot;Covered Heads,&quot; from Mr. Beller's Neighborhood]

{{Conservative Judaism}}
{{Columbia}}
{{NYC Colleges}}
{{Organized Jewish Life in the United States}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jewish Theological Seminary Of America}}
[[Category:Jewish Theological Seminary of America| ]]
[[Category:Columbia University]]
[[Category:Conservative Judaism]]
[[Category:Jewish seminaries]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1886]]
[[Category:Jewish universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Jewish universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Jews and Judaism in New York]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Upper West Side]]
[[Category:Seminaries and theological colleges in New York]]

[[ca:Jewish Theological Seminary of America]]
[[de:Jewish Theological Seminary]]
[[fr:Jewish Theological Seminary of America]]
[[it:Jewish Theological Seminary]]
[[he:בית המדרש לרבנים באמריקה]]
[[ja:ユダヤ教神学院]]
[[yi:יידישער טעאלאגישער סעמינאר]]
[[zh:美洲犹太教神学院]]</text>
      <sha1>g0rz5qvspgvr2nbn4rh439n0vxuory4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
