<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jews for Jesus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>66543</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521534555</id>
      <parentid>518117337</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T17:11:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>R'n'B</username>
        <id>2300502</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Disambiguated: [[Bethlehem Baptist Church]] → [[Bethlehem Baptist Church (Minneapolis)]]; Unlinked: [[Lines]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="61612">{{Christianity}}

'''Jews for Jesus''' is a [[Conservatism|conservative]], [[Christian]] [[evangelism|evangelical]] organization that focuses on the [[Conversion to Christianity|conversion]] of [[Jew]]s to [[Christianity]].&lt;ref name=RELTOL&gt;&quot;Their doctrinal statement is basically indistinguishable from Evangelical and other conservative Christian groups.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
* &quot;During my time with the mission, I found Jews for Jesus to be a Christian ministry (or Messianic, if you prefer) with a passion for the good news about Jesus...&quot;'' Pastor Lev Leigh. Hope Baptist Church. Richmond, CA ([http://www.forjewsforjesus.org/alumni/lj_leigh.html Letters From JFJ Alumni])
* &quot;... Jews for Jesus and other Christian groups who hold to the uniqueness of Christ.&quot; ([http://jfjonline.org/pub/other/press_releases/020819_catholic.htm Jews for Jesus Leader Contradicts American Catholic Bishops.] Jews for Jesus, Press Release. August 19, 2002)
* &quot;Clothed in colorful shirts with large writing identifying their Christian group, Jews for Jesus has been keeping up with the 24-hour-running city, handing out tens of thousands of literature and promoting their evangelistic campaign – Behold Your God – through media outlets.&quot; (''Christian Post''. [http://www.christianpost.com/article/20060706/jews-for-jesus-keeps-up-with-the-city-that-never-sleeps/])
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjudaism.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=319:is-qjews-for-jesusq-jewish-or-christian&amp;catid=27:missionary-groups--tactics-and-responses&amp;Itemid=228 Is &quot;Jews for Jesus&quot; Jewish or Christian?]&lt;/ref&gt; Its members consider themselves to be Jews – either as defined by Jewish law, or as according to the view of Jews for Jesus. Jews for Jesus defines &quot;Jewish&quot; in terms of parentage and as a birthright, regardless of religious belief.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;We believe that Jewishness is a birthright. It is inherited from our parents.
Our people are not of one culture; we have diverse cultural expressions (Ashkenazi/Sephardi, Georgian/Russian, Ethiopian, Persian, etc.). Our people are not of one religion. While Judaism might be the traditional religion for many Jewish people, Jews are still considered Jewish even though they might be atheists or even if they embrace other beliefs.
Those who say that Jews who believe in Jesus are errant Jews or misguided Jews are entitled to their opinions. But they are not entitled to negate our Jewishness. We are Jews by birth and that cannot change.&quot;[http://www.forjewsforjesus.org/qanda/index.html#jew_christian Jews for Jesus Q&amp;A: Can you explain how one can be a Jew and a Christian at the same time? That seems like a contradiction in terms]&lt;/ref&gt; The identification of Jews for Jesus as a [[Who is a Jew?|Jewish]] organization is rejected by [[Jewish denominations|Jewish religious denominations]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;There is virtual unanimity across all denominations [of [[Judaism]]] that Jews for Jesus are not Jewish.&quot; (Kaplan, Dana Evan. ''The Cambridge Companion to American Judaism'', Cambridge University Press, August 15, 2005, pp. 139–140).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CCAJ9&gt;&quot;For most American Jews, it is acceptable to blend some degree of foreign spiritual elements with Judaism. The one exception is Christianity, which is perceived to be incompatible with any form of Jewishness. Jews for Jesus and other Messianic Jewish groups are thus seen as antithetical to Judaism and are completely rejected by the majority of Jews&quot;. (Kaplan, Dana Evan. ''The Cambridge Companion to American Judaism'', Cambridge University Press, August 15, 2005, p. 9).
&lt;/ref&gt; and secular Jewish groups&lt;ref&gt;
* &quot;To make the record clear, Jews for Jesus is a Christian missionary organization – period.&quot; [http://www.jewsforjudaism.org/web/j4jlibrary/jewsforjesus.html Jews for Jesus: Jewish or Christian? You Decide], [[Jews for Judaism]] website, retrieved September 11, 2006.
* &quot;Messianic Jewish organizations, such as Jews for Jesus, often refer to their faith as fulfilled Judaism, in that they believe Jesus fulfilled the Messianic prophecies. Although Messianic Judaism claims to be Jewish, and many adherents observe Jewish holidays, most Jews regard Messianic Judaism as deceptive at best, fraudulent at worst. They charge that Messianic Judaism is actually Christianity presenting itself as Judaism.&quot; (Balmer, Randall. ''Encyclopedia of Evangelicalism'', Baylor University Press, November 2004, p. 448).
* &quot;I do not seek, of course, covertly (as sometimes Jews for Jesus do) or overtly, to convert myself, or any other Jew to Christianity...&quot; (Boyarin, Daniel. ''Border Lines: The Partition of Judaeo-Christianity'', University of Pennsylvania Press, July 2004, p. xii).
* &quot;Certain Christian missionary groups have now set up a front organization called &quot;Jews for Jesus,&quot; through which they entice naive Jews to Christianity...&quot; (Stolper, Pinchas. &quot;Was Jesus The Messiah? Let's Examine The Facts&quot;, in [[Aryeh Kaplan|Kaplan, Aryeh]]. ''Aryeh Kaplan Anthology: Volume 1'', Mesorah Publications, August 1991, p. 293).
* &quot;Even as I write, I fear that Christian missionaries or, even more insidiously, Jews for Jesus—people who (unlike the redeeming avant-garde of Christianity) believe that Judaism is superseded, and Jewish have no right to exist as Jews any more—will misuse my words. These people, who believe that Christianity has taken over Judaism like some succubus that must now govern the behavior of its host body, seek to abolish the Jewish religion.&quot; ([[Irving Greenberg|Greenberg, Irving]]. ''For the Sake of Heaven and Earth: The New Encounter Between Judaism and Christianity'', The Jewish Publication Society, October 2004, p. 97).
* &quot;It should now be clear to you why Jews have such a problem with 'Jews for Jesus' or other presentations of Messianic Judaism. I have no difficulty with Christianity. I even accept those Christians who would want me to convert to Christianity so long as they don't use coercion or duplicity and are willing to listen in good faith to my reasons for being Jewish. I do have a major problem with those Christians who would try to mislead me and other Jews into believing that one can be both Jewish and Christian.&quot; (Lotker, Michael. ''A Christian's Guide to Judaism'', Paulist Press, March 2004, p. 35).
* &quot;Evangelical Christians are engaged in aggressive and extensive missionary activity among Jews. Among other results, this has given rise to groups of 'messianic Jews', of which 'Jews for Jesus' is the most outstanding example. These are actually Jews who have adopted the evangelical Protestant faith and its precepts.&quot; ([[Robert S. Wistrich|Wistrich, Robert]], ''Terms of Survival'', Routledge (UK), March 1995, p. 343).
* &quot;Messianic Judaism is a Christian movement that began in the 1970s combining a mixture of Jewish ritual and Christianity. There are a vast and growing numbers of these groups, and they differ in how much Jewish ritual is mixed with conventional Christian belief. One end of the spectrum is represented by Jews For Jesus, who simply target Jews for conversion to Christianity using imitations of Jewish ritual solely as a ruse for attracting the potential Jewish converts. On the other end are those who don't stress the divinity of Jesus, but present him as the 'Messiah.'&quot; {{cite web
|url=http://www.messiahtruth.com/response.html
|title=Messiah Truth. Messianic Judaism: A Christian Missionary Movement
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Schiffman&gt;[http://www.jcrcny.org/pdf/sdpp/MEETINGTHECHALLENG2.pdf Meeting the Challenge: Hebrew Christians and the Jewish Community]&lt;/ref&gt; due to the Christian beliefs of its members. The group's evangelical activities have garnered mixed reactions from other Christian individuals and organizations, largely divided between [[Liberal Christianity|liberal]] and [[Conservatism|conservative]] lines.&lt;ref name=RELTOL&gt;Robinson, B. [http://www.religioustolerance.org/mess_jud3.htm Messianic Judaism. Jews for Jesus], [[Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance]], October 29, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Others who oppose the evangelism related activities of Jews for Jesus:
* Benjamin Hubbard; John Hatfield, James Santucci (1997). ''America's Religions. An Educator's Guide to Beliefs and Practices.'' Teacher Ideas Press, a Division of Libraries Unlimited, p.100. ISBN 1-56308-469-4.
* Balmer, Randall. ''Encyclopedia of Evangelicalism,'' Baylor University Press, November 2004, p. 448
* &quot;Today, many evangelical Christian-Protestant groups are spending between 100,000,000 and 150,000,000 dollars a year to transform Jews into Christians. The best known of these organization is Jews for Jesus...&quot;. (Berkley, E. George. ''Jews'', Branden Books, February 1997, p. 129).
* &quot;Thirdly, there is Jews for Jesus or, more generally, Messianic Judaism. This is a movement of people often of Jewish background who have come to believe Jesus is the expected Jewish messiah... They often have congregations independent of other churches and specifically target Jews for conversion to their form of Christianity.&quot; ([[Richard Harries, Baron Harries of Pentregarth|Harries, Richard]]. ''After the Evil: Christianity and Judaism in the Shadow of the Holocaust'', Oxford University Press, August 2003, p. 119.)
* &quot;...Jews for Jesus (Jews converted to 'born again' Christianity who are seeking to make more such converts...&quot;. ([[Martin E. Marty|Marty, Martin E.]] ''When Faiths Collide'', Blackwell Publishing, January 2005, p. 35).
* &quot;Jews for Jesus, the leading organization dedicated to converting Jews to Christianity, has long been a concern because of its aggressive proselytizing with a deceptive message: that Jews who accept Jesus as the son of God and their savior remain Jewish.&quot; [http://www.adl.org/special_reports/jews4jesus/jews4jesus.asp Jews for Jesus: Targeting Jews for Conversion with Subterfuge and Deception], [[Anti-Defamation League]], August 27, 2004, retrieved September 11, 2006.
* &quot;Jews for Jesus is a sect of a very different nature. This group... has a sole motivational goal of converting Jews to Christianity.&quot; Fogel, Keith and Marian E. ''Conversos of the Americas'', Xlibris Corporation, April 2004, p. 169).
* &quot;Jews for Jesus is an evangelical Christian organization ...&quot; [http://exjewsforjesus.org/j4jquestions/#who Who are the Jews for Jesus?] (exjewsforjesus.org)
* &quot;... its doctrine is strictly Christian in the fundamentalist/evangelical understanding of Christian faith&quot; [http://exjewsforjesus.org/j4jquestions/#christian%20or%20jewish Is Jews for Jesus a Christian organization, or is it a Jewish organization?] (exjewsforjesus.org)&lt;/ref&gt; Founded in 1973, Jews for Jesus employs more than 200 people,&lt;ref name=&quot;ministrywatch.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.ministrywatch.com/profile/jews-for-jesus.aspx ministrywatch.com]&lt;/ref&gt; estimates its adherents at 30,000 to 125,000 worldwide&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about &quot;About Jews for Jesus: How Many Jews for Jesus Are There?&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; and takes in about $20 million a year in donations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ecfa.org/MemberProfile.aspx?ID=6322 Evangelical Council for Financial Accountability]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Jews For Jesus logo.png|thumb|left|100px|Wordmark]]
The organization was founded by [[Moishe Rosen]] an ordained [[Baptist]] minister (who was born Jewish and converted to Christianity at the age of 17)&lt;ref&gt;[http://torahatlanta.com/NEW%20WEBSITE/Articles/The%20Real%20Jews%20for%20Jesus.html The Real Jews for Jesus. The Leaders] by Jason Levinson (Torah Atlanta)&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jhan Moskowitz]] an ordained [[Christian and Missionary Alliance]] minister and son of a holocaust survivor.  &lt;ref name=ADL_M&gt;[http://www.adl.org/special_reports/jews4jesus/methods.asp Jews for Jesus: Targeting Jews for Conversion with Subterfuge and Deception. Methods] ([[Anti-Defamation League]])&lt;/ref&gt; Rosen was the head of the San Francisco arm of the American Board of Missions to the Jews (an organization now known as [[Chosen People Ministries]]). In 1973, Rosen broke off from that organization,&lt;ref name=&quot;Balmer2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Randall Herbert Balmer|title=Encyclopedia of evangelicalism|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=syUupeVJOz4C&amp;pg=PA127|accessdate=21 August 2011|year=2002|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|isbn=978-0-664-22409-7|pages=127–|quote=Chosen People Ministries Shortly after Leopold Cohn arrived in New York City from Hungary in 1892, he forsook his Jewish heritage and converted to Christianity. He founded the Williamsburg Mission in 1894 and started a newsletter, ''Chosen People'', in an attempt to apprise Christians of evangelistic initiatives among the Jews. In 1924, Cohn gave the Williamsburg Mission a new name, the American Board of Missions to the Jews; the administration of the organization devolved in 1937 to Joseph H. Cohn, a graduate of Moody Bible Institute, after the death of his father, the mission's founder. The San Francisco arm of the American Board of Missions to the Jews, headed by Moishe Rosen, broke off from the national organization in 1973 to form Jews for Jesus. The original mission changed its name yet again in 1986, to Chosen People Ministries. The organization, now based in Charlotte, North Carolina, produces a daily radio program, ''Through Jewish Eyes'', occasional television specials, and various evangelistic materials.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in September of that year, incorporated Jews for Jesus as Hineni Ministries with its headquarters in the San Francisco area. Over the next few years, it established branches in other cities. From September 1979 - June 1980, it shut down its branches to retrain its missionaries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewsforjesus.org/about/timeline Jews for Jesus Timeline]&lt;/ref&gt; It then went on to open more branches, mostly in United States cities, in the 1980s, as well as abroad in the 1990s. Rosen remained its executive director until May 1996 when he was replaced by [[David Brickner]],&lt;ref name=RELTOL/&gt; also a Baptist minister.&lt;ref&gt;http://brickner.jewsforjesus.org/about.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Moishe Rosen died in May 2010. The organization has maintained its headquarters in or near San Francisco, California since its inception.&lt;ref name=&quot;JforJtimeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/timeline/ |title=Jews for Jesus Timeline |accessdate=21 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aims and organization==
Jews for Jesus is based in [[San Francisco]], [[California]]. Jews for Jesus official [[mission statement]] is &quot;to make the Messiahship of Jesus an unavoidable issue to our Jewish people worldwide.&quot; Through media advertisements, production and distribution of literature, producing music and organizing person-to-person [[evangelism]], the organization asserts that &quot;a specifically Jewish mission&quot; is necessary, saying, &quot;Jewish people tend to dismiss evangelistic methods and materials that are couched in Christian lingo, because they reinforce the assumption that Jesus is for 'them' not 'us'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/whatwedo] (Jews for Jesus)&lt;/ref&gt;

Jews for Jesus promotes awareness of the Jewish heritage of the Christian faith. Their website contains brief descriptions of Jewish festivals.&lt;ref name=judaica&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/judaica Jews for Jesus – Judaica]&lt;/ref&gt; The group also provides programs that provide their Christian interpretation of Jewish holidays such as [[Passover]], [[Sukkot]] and [[Hanukkah]], explaining what they consider messianic elements and how they believe these festivals are related to Jesus.

==Beliefs==
[[File:Jews for Jesus New York by David Shankbone.JPG|thumb|right|The [[New York City]] office of Jews for Jesus.]]
A summary of Jews for Jesus' beliefs:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/statementoffaith Statement of Faith] (Jews for Jesus) written January 1, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
* The [[Old Testament|Old]] and [[New Testament]]s, as originally written, are [[Biblical inspiration|divinely inspired]] and [[Biblical inerrancy|inerrant]].
* Recognition of the value of [[Rabbinic literature|traditional Jewish literature]], but only where it is supported by the Bible.
* God the creator exists as a trinity, is perfect, all wise, all powerful and all loving.
* [[Christian views of Jesus|Jesus is the Messiah]], the second person of the Trinity, was [[Virgin birth of Jesus|born of a virgin]], lived a sinless life, died for the sins of all humanity, [[Death and Resurrection of Jesus|rose again]], and is co-equal with God. [[Second Coming|Jesus will return]] to earth in the near future.
* People are saved through a belief in [[Salvation|Jesus as savior]] and an acknowledgment of their sins, not by their achievements.
* Heaven is a reward for those who are saved; Hell is a place of &quot;everlasting conscious punishment&quot; for the lost.
* Israel exists as a covenant people through whom God continues to accomplish His purposes and that the Church is composed of both Jews and Gentiles who acknowledge Jesus as Messiah and Redeemer.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Jews for Jesus takes the mainstream Christian positions that Jesus is the [[Jewish messiah|Messiah]], that his coming was prophesied in the [[Hebrew Bible]], and that Jesus is the [[son of God]], the second person of the [[Trinity]]. Jews for Jesus believes that their views of the Messiah are entirely compatible with the view of God presented in Jewish scriptures,&lt;ref name=3gods&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/answers/theology/believeinthreegods Don't Christians Believe in Three Gods?] (Jews for Jesus) January 1, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; and that the doctrine of the Trinity, fundamental to the Christian faith, is not entirely alien to Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;While it is true that the Old Testament portion of Scripture does not present as clear a picture of the [[Hypostasis (religion)|three-in-one/one-as-three]] Godhead, there are indications of the plurality of the Godhead in the Hebrew Scriptures.&quot;
[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/publications/newsletter/1987_06/trinity The Trinity in the Old Testament] by Catherine Damato. (Jews for Jesus) June 1, 1987&lt;/ref&gt;

According to an article on Jews for Jesus by B. Robinson of [[Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance]], &lt;blockquote&gt;
Their doctrinal statement is basically indistinguishable from Evangelical and other conservative Christian groups. ... They differ from some Evangelical Christian groups in their belief that [[Children of Israel|Israel]] continues to exist as a &quot;covenant people.&quot; They also integrate some Jewish customs and use [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] and [[Yiddish language|Yiddish]] in some literature.&lt;ref name=RELTOL/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Stated core values==
Jews for Jesus describes its core values in the following way:
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
They commit to:
* Direct Jewish evangelism as their priority
* An [[Apostle (Christian)|apostolic]] lifestyle of availability, vulnerability and mobility
* Striving for excellence in all that they do
* Deploying only front-line [[missionary|missionaries]] who are Jewish or married to Jews
* Principle-based operations and practice
* Accountability to their mission family and the body of Messiah
* Integrity and faithfulness
* Creativity in their staff
* Stepping out in courageous faith and taking risks for God.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/corevalues Core values] (Jews for Jesus) January 1, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;
{{col-2}}
Understanding that they:
* are under the authority of God and His word
* desire to honor Messiah [[Jesus|Y'shua]] and
* are dependent upon the enabling power of the [[Holy Spirit]]
{{col-end}}

==Leadership, funding and outreach==
Jews for Jesus is funded by donations from Messianic Jews and like-minded [[Christians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/finances |title=Finances| publisher=Jews for Jesus| accessdate=2008-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.torahatlanta.com/NEW%20WEBSITE/Articles/The%20Real%20Jews%20for%20Jesus.html The Real Jews for Jesus. Christian Dollars at Work] by Jason Levinson (Torah Atlanta)&lt;/ref&gt; It has a full-time staff of more than 200 employees&lt;ref name=&quot;ministrywatch.com&quot;/&gt; running branch offices in nine cities across the United States. There are also branch offices in Australia, Brazil, Canada (in Montreal and Toronto), France, Germany (in Essen), Hungary, Israel, Russia, South Africa, Switzerland, the United Kingdom and Ukraine (in Dnepropetrovsk, Kharkov, Kiev and Odessa). In addition to its English-language website, the group has websites in Hebrew, Portuguese, Polish, Persian, Italian, Spanish and Korean.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/branches &quot;About Jews for Jesus: Branches]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Evangelical Council for Financial Accountability]], the group's total income in [[Financial year|FY]] 2010 was US$20,728,530.&lt;ref name=ECFA&gt;[http://www.ecfa.org/MemberProfile.aspx?ID=6322 Jews for Jesus. Financial information for FY2010] ([[Evangelical Council for Financial Accountability]])&lt;/ref&gt;

==Evangelizing==
The majority of evangelism used by Jews for Jesus consists of handing out literature on the streets, one-on-one Bible studies, full-page ads in leading newspapers and magazines, ISSUES (an eight-page evangelistic publication for Jewish seekers) and internet evangelism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/what-we-do &quot;What We Do&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The organization uses colorful pamphlets and T-shirts to get their message across and is known for targeting populations of Jews which they see as receptive to their message,&lt;ref&gt;Targeting vulnerable population groups:
* &quot;The organization is also known for targeting vulnerable populations of Jews. New Jewish immigrants and college freshman as well as senior citizens and interfaith couples are easy targets for the organization.&quot; ([http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/Jews_for_Jesus.html Jews for Jesus] by Stephanie Persin. [[Jewish Virtual Library]])
* &quot;Since people are most vulnerable at times of personal change and transition, the missionaries center their efforts on a number of vulnerable Jewish populations, including high school and college students, senior citizens, and recent immigrants.&quot; ([http://www.nybr.org/NYBR_NL_Summer_2006.pdf Frequently Asked Questions About Hebrew-Christian Missionaries &amp; &quot;Jews for Jesus&quot;] [[New York Board of Rabbis]])
* &quot;Such congregations are designed to appear Jewish, but they are actually fundamentalist Christian churches which use traditional Jewish symbols to lure the most vulnerable of our Jewish people into their ranks.&quot;
([http://www.somethingjewish.co.uk/articles/475_messianic_congregati.htm Messianic congregations target Jews] by Rabbi Tovia Singer)
* &quot;Young men and women are particularly vulnerable to evangelicals because so often these adolescents are unsure of themselves, the world around them, and the adulthood that awaits them. ... The elderly are also perilously vulnerable...&quot; ([http://www.outreachjudaism.org/evangelizingthejews2.html Evangelizing the Jews, Part 2: Who is Most Vulnerable?] by Rabbi Tovia Singer (outreachjudaism.org). Also at [http://www.aish.com/jewishissues/jewishsociety/Evangelizing_the_Jews3_Part_2_Who_is_Most_Vulnerable$.asp Aish])
* &quot;Deceptive proselytizing is practiced on the most vulnerable of populations – residents of hospitals and old aged homes, confused youth, college students away from home. These proselytizing techniques are tantamount to coerced conversions and should be condemned.&quot; ([http://www.scjfaq.org/faq/17-05.html Soc.Culture.Jewish Newsgroups. Frequently Asked Questions and Answers])
* &quot;Individuals are most vulnerable to these groups and their tactics when they are lonely and hurting, overwhelmed or confused, away from their support system or have lost a loved one or a close friend.&quot; ([http://www.jewsforjudaism.org/web/mainpages/students-oncampus.html College Programs. Got Friends?] by Scott Hillman, ''Jews For Judaism'')
* &quot;Their efforts here have drawn criticism from mainstream Jews and some Christians, who accuse Jews for Jesus of leading the vulnerable – the young, the old, recent immigrants...&quot; ([http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2005-08-27/news/0508270010_1_jews-for-jesus-accept-jesus-missionaries Jews for Jesus missionaries find warmth, hostility] By Matthew Hay Brown (Baltimore Sun) August 27, 2005
* &quot;Nonetheless, JFJ continues to make this contradictory claim, purposefully focusing on young, naïve, or socially vulnerable populations with their campaigns. College students, recent immigrants (most notably Russian Jews), and the elderly are targets for conversion.&quot; ([http://www.christianaggression.org/item_display.php?type=ARTICLES&amp;id=1128484731 Jews for Jesus offends Jews and Christians] By Ethan Frenchman and Seth Mayer, ''Chicago Maroon''. October 4, 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;
such as recent immigrants, college students, senior citizens and interfaith couples. Regarding &quot;targeting,&quot; Jews for Jesus says this on its website: &quot;The term 'targeting' brings to mind darts or firearms. We can't imagine throwing the gospel at people or aiming to harm them with it. Actually, targeting is a propaganda term that has been misappropriated from the marketing profession. . . . Those who are not Christians use it to disparage evangelism. To scoffers and unbelievers it has a negative connotation. We avoid the term 'targeting' because we see the gospel as something to be presented freely rather than something to be sold. We don't throw our tracts at people; we hand them to those who want to take them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/faq#targeting Jews for Jesus FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; 
Stephanie Persin writes, &quot;Evangelists in the organization have been trained to recite phrases from the Old Testament and to use [[Yiddish]] words so as to convince potential converts that Jews for Jesus maintain Jewish traditions.&quot;&lt;ref name=ADL_M/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/Jews_for_Jesus.html Jews for Jesus] by Stephanie Persin ([[Jewish Virtual Library]])&lt;/ref&gt; Regarding Jewish traditions, Jews for Jesus says on its website: &quot;As for the accusation that we 'fraudulently use Jewish symbols and Jewish holidays,' we have a right to use Jewish symbols by virtue of our ancestry, and we have a right to celebrate Passover and other Jewish holidays and interpret them according to the teachings of Scripture. The accusation would only be valid if the [[Historical reliability of the Gospels|New Testament were false]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jews for Jesus FAQ&quot;&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/faq#symbols Jews for Jesus FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; On their official website, Jews for Jesus says that they give out 8 million pamphlets a year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/whatwedo What We Do]&lt;/ref&gt; They use college-age volunteers for some of their short-term evangelism campaigns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewsforjesus.org/join &quot;Get Involved&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Each July they send a team of 20 to 30 to [[New York City]], which they say has the world's largest and most diverse Jewish population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/join/swc SWC New York]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Affiliations and support==
On the Christian counter-cult site [[Christian countercult movement#Independent|Apologetics Index]], Jews for Jesus is listed as an orthodox member of the Christianity family.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apologeticsindex.org/2-messianic-jews Messianic Jews | Apologetics Index&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Jews for Jesus is a member of numerous evangelical Christian groups, including The [[World Evangelical Alliance]],&lt;ref name=Assoc&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/associations Associations] (Jews for Jesus)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ifmamissions.org/member.htm Members] (Interdenominational Foreign Mission Association)&lt;/ref&gt;
the [[Evangelical Council for Financial Accountability]],&lt;ref name=ECFA/&gt;&lt;ref name=Assoc/&gt;
the [[World Evangelical Fellowship]],
the [[Evangelical Fellowship of Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.evangelicalfellowship.ca/about/structure.asp Affiliates] (Evangelical Fellowship of Canada)&lt;/ref&gt;
the Canadian Council for Christian Charities, the Evangelical Alliance of Great Britain, the Evangelical Alliance of South Africa, the Fédération Evangélique de France (Evangelical Federation of France), and the Lausanne Consultation on Jewish Evangelism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/associations Associations and Memberships]&lt;/ref&gt;

Here is what some prominent evangelical Christians have said about Jews for Jesus:

[[J.I. Packer]], Board of Governors' Professor of Theology at [[Regent College]] in Vancouver, British Columbia: &quot;Jews for Jesus is a worldwide Christian mission that was born against the background of California's Jesus movement and has grown steadily ever since. Holding that Jesus of Nazareth -- God incarnate, crucified, risen, and now reigning -- is the true Messiah foretold in the Old Testament and the true fulfillment of Jewish hopes, the mission exists to press his claims on Jewish people everywhere. It is based on two principles.
First, Jews who receive Jesus Christ as their Lord and Savior and who are 'completed' and 'fulfilled' thereby do not need to leave behind their Jewish identity or break with Jewish ways. As Judaizing was not a theological requirement for the first gentile Christians, so gentilizing is not a cultural requirement for today's Jewish believers. Though they belong in the Christian church, which has been mainly gentile -- non-Jewish, that is -- for most of its life, within the church they are free to be as Jewish as they like.
Second, up-front, in-your-face challenge, with as much humor, chutzpah, and goodwill as possible, is the way to approach Jews evangelistically.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewsforjesus.org/about/forjewsforjesus/christian/packer &quot;Letter from J.I. Packer&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. [[Joseph M. Stowell III]], past president of [[Moody Bible Institute]], current president of [[Cornerstone University]] in Grand Rapids, Michigan, and author of over 20 Christian books: &quot;Since Moishe Rosen founded Jews for Jesus in the early 1970s, thousands of Jewish people have come to experience living faith in Jesus as their Messiah through this strategic ministry. And just as important, thousands of Gentiles have as well. We are proud that David Brickner, the executive director, and many others at Jews for Jesus are graduates of Moody Bible Institute. I'm privileged to be associated with them and I encourage you in your association with Jews for Jesus now and in the future.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/forjewsforjesus/christian/stowell &quot;Letter from Joseph Stowell&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Mark Bailey, President of [[Dallas Theological Seminary]]: &quot;I have watched the ministry of Jews for Jesus for twenty-five years. I have known their chairman of the board, Byron Spradlin, for the same period. Susan Perlman now serves on the board of Dallas Theological Seminary, and I am pleased to call Moishe Rosen and David Brickner my friends. All are committed followers of Messiah Jesus. I have always found the ministry of Jews for Jesus and their traveling musicians to be evangelical in their doctrine and appropriately evangelistic in their presentation. They are both creative and biblical in their communication of the gospel. They help lead the way in Jewish evangelism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/forjewsforjesus/christian/bailey &quot;Letter from Mark Bailey&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Stephen Piper]], Senior Pastor, [[Bethlehem Baptist Church (Minneapolis)|Bethlehem Baptist Church]], Minneapolis, Minnesota: &quot;For almost two decades I have followed with joy the ministry of Jews for Jesus. I say with joy&quot; because I love the gospel of the glory of Jesus the Messiah, and I love Jewish people, and I love bold, compassionate ways of connecting Jews and Jesus. All I have seen and all I know of Jews for Jesus makes me happy to say a rousing YES to their ministry. From Moshe Rosen to David Brickner I have admired the leadership. I have seen them up close and in action. I have been a partner in the Behold Your God mission in Minneapolis and have spoken to the band of bold witnesses before they hit the streets. I encourage my people to give support, and I have wished I had a fraction of the dedication and courage I see in the missionaries who put themselves at risk week in and week out. The risk is mainly from misunderstanding. It is inevitable. Bold, loving summons to believe on Jesus as the Messiah will be seen by some as arrogant,by others as abusive, by others as controlling, by others as ethnic assault, by others as the most precious gift ever given. I see it as obedience to Jesus and as the very embodiment of the love of Christ for lost sinners like me. 'Whoever has the Son has life; whoever does not have the Son of God does not have life.' (1 John 5:12) May God give Jews for Jesus faithfulness to offer the Son to all who need him—to the Jew first and also to the gentile.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jewsforjesus.org/about/forjewsforjesus/pastors/piper &quot;Letter from John Piper&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Torkild Masvie]], International Director, [[Caspari Center]], Jerusalem: &quot;I have known the Jews for Jesus organization and senior staff for years. They are an organization with fundamental integrity, i.e. they live up to their stated goals with no hidden agenda. They are characterized by their clear, sober, biblical theology which is in line with the principles of the reformation. They represent a clear voice against the separation of Jewish and Gentile believers in Messiah and encourage active membership of Jewish believers in Jesus in local churches.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/about/forjewsforjesus/messianic/masvie &quot;Letter from Torkild Masvie&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposition and criticism==
{{Undue-section|date=June 2011}}

One of the criticisms of Jews for Jesus surrounds the tactics they employ in their missionary and outreach programs. Critics say that the organization uses vague and misleading language along with deceptive tactics in its attempt to convert Jews to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/special_reports/jews4jesus/jfj_complete.pdf Jews for Jesus – Targeting Jews for Conversion with Subterfuge and Deception]&lt;/ref&gt; These tactics include statements that Jesus is the fulfillment of the Jewish prophecy of Messiah and attempts by Jews for Jesus to interpret core principles of Judaism in an effort to bring these Jewish principles into accord with Christian doctrines.&lt;ref name=Rosen1997&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/publications/issues/11_2/judaism Judaism Teaches... or Does It?] by Moishe Rosen (Jews for Jesus) March 1, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; To this end, critics say that Jews for Jesus uses the ambiguity in the definition of &quot;Jew&quot; and &quot;Jewish&quot; to confuse their prospective converts into believing there is a possibility of one being a follower of both Christianity and Judaism simultaneously.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjudaism.org/web/mainpages/missionary_cult_challenge.html Jews for Judaism, The Challenge of Missionaries and Cults]&lt;/ref&gt;

On its website in answer to a frequently asked question,&quot;How can I respond to the accusation that Jews for Jesus distorts Jewish religious symbols?,&quot; Jews for Jesus says, &quot;Regardless of what anyone says, we are Jews in that we are physically descended from Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. At the same time we are also Christians—those who believe in and follow Jesus, the Jewish Messiah. One classification does not cancel out the other, even though rabbis like to teach that Judaism and Christianity are mutually exclusive categories and hence are antithetical to one another.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jews for Jesus FAQ&quot;/&gt;

===Mainstream Judaism===
Belief in Jesus as [[deity]], [[son of God]], or even a non-divine [[Christ]]/[[Messiah]] or [[Prophet]] (as in [[Islam]]), is held as incompatible with Judaism by all [[Jewish denominations]].&lt;ref name=CCAJ9/&gt;&lt;ref name=incompat&gt;A belief in the divinity of Jesus is incompatible with Judaism:
* &quot;The point is this: that the whole Christology of the Church – the whole complex of doctrines about the Son of God who died on the Cross to save humanity from sin and death – is incompatible with Judaism, and indeed in discontinuity with the Hebraism that preceded it.&quot; Rayner, John D. ''A Jewish Understanding of the World'', Berghahn Books, 1998, p. 187. ISBN 1-57181-974-6
* &quot;It has always been recognized, for instance, after the rise of Christianity and Islam, that these two religions are incompatible with Judaism and that no Jew can consistently embrace them while remaining an adherent of Judaism.&quot; Neusner, Jacob &amp; Avery-Peck, Alan Jeffery. ''The Blackwell Reader in Judaism'', Blackwell Publishing, 2001, p. 8. ISBN 0-631-20738-4
* &quot;Aside from its belief in Jesus as the Messiah, Christianity has altered many of the most fundamental concepts of Judaism.&quot; [[Aryeh Kaplan|Kaplan, Aryeh]]. ''The Aryeh Kaplan Anthology: Volume 1, Illuminating Expositions on Jewish Thought and Practice'', Mesorah Publication, 1991, p. 264. ISBN 0-89906-866-9
* &quot;...the doctrine of Christ was and will remain alien to Jewish religious thought.&quot; Wylen, Stephen M. ''Settings of Silver: An Introduction to Judaism'', Paulist Press, 2000, p. 75. ISBN 0-8091-3960-X
* &quot;For a Jew, however, any form of shituf is tantamount to idolatry in the fullest sense of the word. There is then no way that a Jew can ever accept Jesus as a deity, mediator or savior (messiah), or even as a prophet, without betraying Judaism. To call oneself, therefore, a 'Hebrew-Christian,' a 'Jew for Jesus,' or in the latest version a 'messianic Jew,' is an oxymoron. Just as one cannot be a 'Christian Buddhist,' or a 'Christian for Krishna,' one cannot be a 'Jew for Jesus.'&quot; Schochet, Rabbi J. Immanuel. [http://www.cjnews.com/pastissues/99/july29-99/feature/feature2.htm &quot;Judaism has no place for those who betray their roots&quot;], ''[[Canadian Jewish News]]'', July 29, 1999.
* [http://www.nybr.org/missionaries.htm This July, Hebrew-Christian groups such as Jews for Jesus will work to convert Jews to another religion.] The Jewish Response to Missionaries (NY Board of Rabbis)
* [http://foundationstone.com.au/HtmlSupport/WebPage/Missionaries/missionariesAndCults.html Judaism and Jesus Don't Mix] (foundationstone.com)
* [http://whatjewsbelieve.org/explanation09.html Jews believe that &quot;Jews for Jesus,&quot; &quot;Messianic Jews,&quot; and &quot;Hebrew Christians&quot; are no longer Jews, even if they were once Jews] (whatjewsbelieve.org)
* &quot;If you believe Jesus is the messiah, died for anyone else's sins, is God's chosen son, or any other dogma of Christian belief, you are not Jewish. You are Christian. Period.&quot; (''[http://www.beliefnet.com/blogs/virtualtalmud/2006/08/jews-for-jesus-whos-who-whats-what.html Jews for Jesus: Who's Who &amp; What's What]'' by Rabbi Susan Grossman (beliefnet – virtualtalmud) August 28, 2006)
* &quot;For two thousand years, Jews rejected the claim that Jesus fulfilled the messianic prophecies of the Hebrew Bible, as well as the dogmatic claims about him made by the church fathers – that he was born of a virgin, the son of God, part of a divine Trinity, and was resurrected after his death. ... For two thousand years, a central wish of Christianity was to be the object of desire by Jews, whose conversion would demonstrate their acceptance that Jesus has fulfilled their own biblical prophecies.&quot; (''Jewish Views of Jesus'' by Susannah Heschel, in ''Jesus In The World's Faiths: Leading Thinkers From Five Faiths Reflect On His Meaning'' by Gregory A. Barker, editor. (Orbis Books, 2005) ISBN 1-57075-573-6. p.149)
* &quot;... there are limits to pluralism, beyond which a group is schismatic to the point where it is no longer considered Jewish. For example, everyone considers Messianic Judaism and belief in Buddha as outside of the Jewish sphere.&quot; (''[http://judaism.about.com/library/3_askrabbi_o/bl_simmons_messianicjews.htm Why did the majority of the Jewish world reject Jesus as the Messiah, and why did the first Christians accept Jesus as the Messiah?]'' by Rabbi [[Shraga Simmons]])
* &quot;No Jew accepts Jesus as the Messiah. When someone makes that faith commitment, they become Christian. It is not possible for someone to be both Christian and Jewish.&quot; (''[http://judaism.about.com/library/3_askrabbi_c/bl_jesus.htm Why don't Jews accept Jesus as the Messiah?]'' by Rabbi Barry Dov Lerner)&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993 the ''Task Force on Missionaries and Cults'' of the Jewish Community Relations Council of New York (JCRCNY) issued a statement which has been endorsed by the four major Jewish denominations: [[Orthodox Judaism]], [[Conservative Judaism]], [[Reform Judaism]], and [[Reconstructionist Judaism]], as well as national Jewish organizations.&lt;ref name=Schiffman/&gt; Based on this statement, the ''Spiritual Deception Prevention Project'' at the JCRCNY stated:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
On several occasions leaders of the four major [[Jewish denominations|Jewish movements]] have signed on to joint statements opposing Hebrew-Christian theology and tactics. In part they said: &quot;Though Hebrew Christianity claims to be a form of Judaism, it is not ... It deceptively uses the sacred symbols of Jewish observance ... as a cover to convert Jews to Christianity, a belief system antithetical to Judaism ... Hebrew Christians are in radical conflict with the communal interests and the destiny of the Jewish people. They have crossed an unbridgeable chasm by accepting another religion. Despite this separation, they continue to attempt to convert their former co-religionists.&quot;&lt;ref name=JCRCNY&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.jcrcny.org/PDF/7_6/Q_AHC.PDF Frequently Asked Questions About Hebrew-Christian Missionaries &amp; &quot;Jews for Jesus&quot;]}} Jewish Community Relations Council of New York. Spiritual Deception Prevention Project&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The director of a [[counter-missionary]] group ''Torah Atlanta'', Rabbi Efraim Davidson, stated that &quot;the Jews for Jesus use aggressive proselytizing to target disenfranchised or unaffiliated Jews, Russian immigrants and college students&quot; and that &quot;their techniques are manipulative, deceptive and anti-Semitic.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://torahatlanta.com/IntheNewsArticles/Portland.html Portland Jews Brace for Assault by 'Jews for Jesus'] By Paul Haist (Jewish Review) May 15, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

In his 1997 book ''The Vanishing American Jew: In Search of Jewish Identity for the Next Century'', [[Alan Dershowitz]] wrote: &quot;In America, and in other nations that separate church from state, one's Jewishness is a matter of self-definition ...&quot; but notes: &quot;I do not mean to include former Jews who practice Christianity under the deliberately misleading name Jews for Jesus. A Jew for Jesus already has a name: a Christian.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Dershowitz
 | first = Alan
 | title = The Vanishing American Jew: In Search of Jewish Identity for the Next Century
 | page = 324
 | publisher = Little, Brown; 1st ed.
 | year= 1997
 | isbn = 0-316-18133-1
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an interview for [[Beliefnet]], Orthodox Rabbi [[Irving Greenberg]], the author of ''For the Sake of Heaven and Earth'', said:
:&quot;There are Jews for Jesus who use the trappings of Judaism to bring people into a religion that teaches that Judaism is finished. Jews for Jesus are worse theologically than the mainstream of Catholicism or Protestantism, which now affirm that Judaism is a valid religion. Jews for Jesus say that it is not. They use the Jewish trappings, but de facto, they are teaching the classic Christian [[supersessionism]]--that Judaism was at best a foreshadowing of Christianity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beliefnet.com/story/187/story_18792.html Disagreeing in the Service of God]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Outreach Judaism===
[[Outreach Judaism]], a Jewish [[counter-missionary]] organization founded by Rabbi [[Tovia Singer]], aims to provide educational resources to individuals targeted by organizations such as Jews for Jesus.&lt;ref name=WOTM_Tovia&gt;[http://outreachjudaism.org/OutreachJudaism/uploads/videos/WOTM_Tovia.flv|Rabbi Tovia Singer interviewed by Way of the Master Radio]. See [[Flash Video]] for information on how to play this recording.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jews for Judaism===
[[Jews for Judaism]], established by Rabbi [[Bentzion Kravitz]] in 1986, is a Jewish organization aiming &quot;to strengthen and preserve Jewish identity through education and counseling that counteracts deceptive proselytizing targeting Jews for conversion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjudaism.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=20&amp;Itemid=464 Homepage Jews for Judaism]&lt;/ref&gt; The name ''Jews for Judaism'' is a deliberate [[parody]] of Jews for Jesus, as Jews for Jesus is one of the missionary organizations that Jews for Judaism was founded to counter.{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}

===Christian===
Some Western Christians object to evangelizing Jews because they see Jewish religious practice as valid in and of itself.&lt;ref&gt;Pluralistic opposition:
* [http://www.abrock.com/Attempt.html#valid Should Christians Attempt to Evangelize Jews? Israel's Covenant with God Remains Valid] by Allan R. Brockway
* [http://www.religioustolerance.org/chr_jcon3.htm Policies of mainline and liberal Christians towards proselytizing Jews] (religioustolerance.org)
* [http://www.jcrelations.net/en/?item=961 What about Christian Jews or Jewish Christians?] by Fritz Voll ([[International Council of Christians and Jews]]) [http://www.jcrelations.net/en/?id=1499 Ecumenical Considerations on Jewish-Christian Dialogue] (World Council of Churches)
* In the United Kingdom, there has been opposition to the activities of Jews for Jesus from the Council of Christians and Jews which has prohibited members of the organisation from joining its meetings, through the issuing of a Code of Conduct opposing Jewish proselytisation by Christians.{{Nonspecific|date=June 2011}}
* &quot;I normally defend my denomination. I'm loyal to it. But I have never targeted Muslims. I have never targeted Jews.&quot; &quot;Billy Graham Blasts Brethren&quot; by Eric J. Greenberg, ''The Jewish Week''. January 7, 2000, referring to a [[Southern Baptist Convention]] event in Chicago [http://www.beliefnet.com/News/2002/03/Billy-Graham-The-Jews.aspx]
* [http://torahatlanta.com/articles/Christian%20Scholars%20Group.html The Christian Scholars Group on Christian-Jewish Relations: &quot;Christians should not target Jews for conversion&quot;]. The Center for Christian-Jewish Learning at Boston College. September 1, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[Liberal Christianity|Liberal]] Protestant denominations that have issued statements criticizing evangelism of Jews include the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.elca.org/ecumenical/interreligious/jewish/guidelines.html '' Guidelines for Lutheran – Jewish Relations'', Evangelical Lutheran Church in America] . Retrieved July 5, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[United Church of Christ]] and the [[Presbyterian Church USA]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=Fi8sJ6iOX_cC&amp;pg=RA1-PA114&amp;lpg=RA1-PA114&amp;dq=%22United+Church+of+Christ%22+%22Jews+for+Jesus%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=9kLTXTd_iy&amp;sig=X7N82ORiuzFcTTihtjAf89Z674k&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=UnZRSov8BY_QtgObvviqDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6 Spector, S. ''Evangelicals and Israel'', 2008], Oxford University Press: Oxford, p. 114&lt;/ref&gt; which said in 1988 that Jews have their own covenant with God.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcusa.org/oga/publications/christians-jews.pdf ''A Theological Understanding of the Relationship Between Christians and Jews'', 199th General Assembly (1987) of the Presbyterian Church (USA)]&lt;/ref&gt; The Board of Governors of the Long Island Council of Churches opposes proselytizing of Jews, and voiced these sentiments in a statement that &quot;noted with alarm&quot; the &quot;subterfuge and dishonesty&quot; inherent in the &quot;mixing [of] religious symbols in ways which distort their essential meaning&quot;, and named Jews for Jesus as one of the three groups about whom such behavior was alleged.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/special_reports/jews4jesus/christian_responses.asp ''Jews for Jesus: Targeting Jews for Conversion with Subterfuge and Deception'', Anti-Defamation League] . Retrieved July 5, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, the sponsorship of Jews for Jesus by All Souls Church, Langham Place, a Conservative Evangelical Church in London, with a launch event on [[Rosh Hashanah]] launching a UK mission targeting the Jewish community led to the Interfaith Alliance UK a coalition of Jewish, Christian and Islamic religious leaders issuing a letter of protest to the Archbishop of Canterbury.&lt;ref&gt;''The Guardian'' [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2003/sep/26/religion.gayrights Imams join plea for gay tolerance] 26 September 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islamic interfaith conference===
The [[Interfaith Conference of Metropolitan Washington]] includes [[Muslims]], [[Jews]], and [[Liberal Christianity|liberal church]] groups.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ifcmw.org/node/28|IFCMW membership]&lt;/ref&gt; The Conference states that they &quot;support the right of all religions to share their message in the spirit of good will;&quot;&lt;ref name=PCUSA_IFCMW_SoP&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eif-pcusa.org/proselytism_statement.pdf |title=PCUSA's excerpt of the IFCMW's 'Statement on Proselytism' |accessdate=2011 June 21}}&lt;/ref&gt; however Rev. Clark Lobenstine, has condemned the &quot;proselytizing efforts&quot; of &quot;Jews for Jesus and other messianic Jewish groups.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A6464-2004Aug16.html |title=Conversion Outreach Plan Stirs Outrage. Jews for Jesus Trains 600 for Street Work |author=David Cho |work=Washington Post |date=August 17, 2004 |accessdate=2011-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; His wording matched the Conference's 1987 &quot;Statement on Proselytism,&quot;&lt;ref name=PCUSA_IFCMW_SoP/&gt; which makes claims against &quot;groups that have adopted the label of Hebrew Christianity, Messianic Judaism, or Jews for Jesus,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wellesley.edu/rellife/transformation/guide/Interreligious%20Dialogue.html |title=IFCMW Statement on Proselytism in a longer quote|accessdate=2011 June 21}}&lt;/ref&gt; so it is unclear which claims are directed at Jews for Jesus in particular.

A particularly strong opposition has emerged from Muslim imams and leaders in the light of the emergence of &quot;Messianic Muslim&quot; Evangelical missions directed at the Muslim community modeled on Jews for Jesus, with the presentation of Evangelical beliefs in Arabicised terms and encouragement of Muslims to become &quot;followers for 'Isa&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;See for example [http://www.ijfm.org/PDFs_IJFM/17_1_PDFs/Followers_of_Isa.pdf Messianic Muslim Followers of Isa]&lt;/ref&gt; and on 10 December 2003, a joint Jewish-Muslim Delegation supported by the Office of the Chief Rabbi in Great Britain together with Muslim imams presented a protest to the Bishop of London, Richard Chartres.

===Other===
''America's Religions. An Educator's Guide to Beliefs and Practices'' contains &quot;[a] note about Jews for Jesus, [[Messianic Judaism|Messianic Jews]], [[Hebrew Christians]], and similar groups: Jews in these groups who have converted to Christianity but continue to observe various Jewish practices are no longer considered part of the Jewish community in the usual sense.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Benjamin Hubbard 1997 100&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 |author=Benjamin Hubbard
 |coauthors=John Hatfield, James Santucci
 |title=America's Religions. An Educator's Guide to Beliefs and Practices
 |year=1997
 |page=100
 |publisher=Teacher Ideas Press, a Division of Libraries Unlimited
 |isbn=1-56308-469-4
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are several other organizations that oppose identification of Jews for Jesus as a Jewish group.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/mess_jud3.htm Jews for Jesus] by [[Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Balmer, Randall. ''Encyclopedia of Evangelicalism,'' Baylor University Press, November 2004, p. 448&lt;/ref&gt;

==Litigation==

===1987 – freedom of speech===
In the case of Board of Airport Commissioners of Los Angeles v. Jews for Jesus, Inc., 482 U.S. 569 (1987), The Supreme Court held that a law which banned &quot;First Amendment activities&quot; within the Central Terminal Area at L.A. International Airport to be invalid as substantially &quot;over broad,&quot; and therefore, invalid on its face. As Justice O'Connor stated, in her opinion, such a law could even be construed to prohibit a traveler from approaching a ticketing booth and asking when the flight from Des Moines was scheduled to arrive. The municipal agency in charge of [[Los Angeles International Airport]] had barred the group from distributing leaflets at the airport &quot;as part of a larger ban on what they described as [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] activities. Jews for Jesus challenged the airport's right to institute such a sweeping ban.&quot;&lt;ref name=ADL_LC&gt;[http://www.adl.org/special_reports/jews4jesus/legal_cases.asp Legal Cases Involving Jews for Jesus] (ADL)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Airport Comm'rs v. Jews for Jesus, Inc.'' {{Ussc|482|569|1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1992 – civil rights violations===
In 1992 the [[New York Court of Appeals]] ruled against Jews for Jesus in a suit the organization brought against the [[Jewish Community Relations Council of New York]] (JCRCNY), an umbrella group representing 60 Jewish agencies in the metropolitan New York area. The case addressed the JCRCNY's 1985 warning to Long Island rabbis that Jews for Jesus was seeking a venue to conduct a [[Passover seder]]. Jews for Jesus sued the JCRCNY for violating its civil rights; the decision upheld a lower court ruling that the JCRCNY communication did not &quot;go beyond the proposal stage&quot; and that there was no evidence that any of the Long Island rabbis had actually contacted establishments for the purpose of discriminating against Jews for Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/nyctap/I92_0038.htm Jews For Jesus, Inc., Et Al., Appellants, V. Jewish Community Relations Council Of New York, Inc., Et Al., Respondents&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1992 lawsuit brought by Jews for Jesus against the JCRCNY, the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit]] ruled that the efforts of the JCRCNY urging Jewish organizations not to patronize a New York country club because it allowed Jews for Jesus to hold its annual convention on its premises were not protected as an exercise of the JCRC's [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] rights.&lt;ref name=ADL_LC/&gt;

===1993 – refusal of automatic citizenship in Israel===
In 1993 the [[Supreme Court of Israel]], in a case involving a couple affiliated with Jews for Jesus, ruled that Jews who adhere to the Christian beliefs are regarded by Israeli law as &quot;members of a different faith,&quot; and are not eligible for the [[Law of Return|automatic citizenship that Israel grants Jews]]. This is done not to try to change Jewish Law, but to preserve the Jewish character of the State of Israel – i.e., that allowing in people whose sole mission is to get Jews to become Christians is inimical to one of the core ethics of the country (to be a haven for Jews).{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}} In its summary of the ruling, the [[Foreign Affairs Minister of Israel|Israel Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] stated that the belief that Jesus is the Messiah &quot;cannot be reconciled with Judaism&quot; and &quot;marks the clear separation between Judaism and Christianity.&quot;&lt;ref name=ADL_LC/&gt;

===1998 and 2005–2006 – online name===
Jews for Jesus has been involved in litigation regarding Internet use of its name. In 1998 they successfully sued Steven Brodsky for [[cybersquatting]] — registering the domain name jewsforjesus.org for a site criticizing the organization.&lt;ref name=ADL_LC/&gt; The domain now belongs to Jews for Jesus and is used for their main site.

In 2005 Jews for Jesus sued&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.circleid.com/posts/google_sued_for_trademark_infringement_on_third_level_subdomain/ Google Sued for Trademark Infringement Based on Third-Level Subdomain] by Eric Goldman (CircleID) December 30, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; [[Google]] for allowing a [[Blogspot]] user to put up a site at the third-level subdomain ''jewsforjesus.blogspot.com''. In September 2006 ''[[Christianity Today]]'' reported that &quot;Jews for Jesus settled out of court with a critical blogger identified as 'Whistle Blower' on jewsforjesus.blogspot.com. The evangelistic ministry assumed control of the site.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/2006/september/18.23.html Christianity Today News Briefs] September 1, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===2006 – misuse of Jackie Mason name===
In 2006 comedian and actor [[Jackie Mason]] filed a lawsuit against Jews for Jesus, alleging that they unlawfully distributed a pamphlet which used his name and likeness in a way that suggested he was a member of the group. In fact, Mason is Jewish and not associated with Jews for Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2006/SHOWBIZ/08/25/jackiemason.ap/index.html Comic sues Jews for Jesus]&lt;/ref&gt; Jews for Jesus has issued a detailed response to the allegation on their website.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/blog/20060825mason Press Release: Jews for Jesus and Jackie Mason] (Jews for Jesus) August 25, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

A judge of the [[United States District Court for the Southern District of New York]] denied a preliminary injunction against Jews for Jesus over the pamphlet, finding the distribution of the pamphlet to be protected by the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]], and also stated that the pamphlet did not suggest that Mason was a Christian.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewsforjesus.org/blog/20061108jackiemasondenied Jackie Mason Charges Against Jews For Jesus Denied By U.S. District Court], November 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2006, [[Jackie Mason]] dropped the lawsuit against Jews for Jesus after they issued a letter of apology to Mason. The group's executive director, [[David Brickner]], stated in the letter to Mason that he wanted &quot;to convey my sincere apologies for any distress that you felt over our tract.&quot; Brickner continued that he believed its publication was protected by the [[United States Constitution|Constitution]], but the group was willing in the interest of peace and love for Israel to retire the pamphlet. Mason replied in front of the federal court in Manhattan where he accepted the apology, &quot;There's no such thing as a Jew for Jesus. It's like saying a black man is for the [[Ku Klux Klan|KKK]]. You can't be a table and a chair. You're either a Jew or a [[Gentile]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/life/people/2006-12-05-mason_x.htm ''USA Today'',] [http://nymag.com/daily/intel/tags/religion nymag.com] (and many others) quoting an Associated Press release, December 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{columns-list|2|
* [[Christian-Jewish reconciliation]]
* [[Christianity and Judaism]]
* [[Dispensationalism]]
* [[Jewish Christians]]
* [[Jewish Messiah]]
* [[Jews for Judaism]]
* [[Judaism's view of Jesus]]
* [[Messianic Jews]]
* [[Outreach Judaism]]
* [[Supersessionism]]
* [[Who is a Jew?]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* ''Called to Controversy: The Unlikely Story of Moishe Rosen and the Founding of Jews for Jesus'' by Ruth Rosen (Thomas Nelson, 2012) ISBN 978-1-59555-491-8
* ''Not ashamed: The story of Jews for Jesus'' by Ruth Tucker (Multnomah Publishers, 2000) ISBN 978-1-57673-700-2
* ''Sentenced for Life: A Story of an Entry and an Exit into the World of Fundamentalist Christianity and Jews for Jesus'' by Jo Ann Schneider Farris (Writers Club Press, 2002) ISBN 0-595-24940-X
* ''Messianic Judaism: A rabbi's journey through religious change in America'' by Carol Harris-Shapiro (Beacon Press, 1999) ISBN 978-0-8070-1040-2
* ''Evangelizing the Chosen People: Missions to the Jews in America, 1880–2000'' by Yaakov Ariel (The University of North Carolina Press, 1999) ISBN 0-8078-2566-2
* ''Hawking God. A Young Jewish Woman's Ordeal in Jews for Jesus'' by Ellen Kamentsky (Sapphire Press, 1993) [http://www.skepticfiles.org/fw/defector.htm An excerpt]
* Jews for Jesus: An Anthropological Study by Juliene G. Lipson (AMS Press, 1990) ISBN 0-404-62605-X
* ''Smashing the Idols: A Jewish Inquiry into the Cult Phenomenon'' by Gary D. Eisenberg (Jason Aronson, 1988) ISBN 0-87668-974-8

==External links==
* [http://www.jewsforjesus.org/ Jews for Jesus] Official website
* [http://jewishmissions.com/ Jewish Missions - San Francisco] Website of Jews for Jesus missionaries in San Francisco
* [http://usedforjesus.com/ Ex-Jews for Jesus] website of former members of Jews for Jesus
* [http://www.aish.com/jewishissues/jewishsociety/Why_Jews_Dont_Believe_In_Jesus.asp Why Jews Don't Believe In Jesus]
* [http://www.faqs.org/faqs/judaism/FAQ/09-Antisemitism/section-18.html Who is financing &quot;Jews for Jesus&quot;?] (faqs.org)
* {{PDFlink|[http://blog.searchenginewatch.com/blog/pdf/jj_google_suit.pdf Complaint in lawsuit against Google over Blogspot subdomain]|1.46&amp;nbsp;MB}}
* [http://www.bocaratonnews.com/index.php?src=news&amp;category=LOCAL%20NEWS&amp;prid=6689 County Jewish organizations protest evangelical attempt] by Steven Reiskind (Boca Raton News) November 5, 2003
* [http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?apage=1&amp;cid=1150885948447&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull Jews for Jesus campaign targets NY Jews] by Gal Beckerman (July 10, 2006) [[Jerusalem Post]]
* [http://www.nypost.com/news/regionalnews/holy_hell_over_subway_jesus_regionalnews_jeremy_olshan___transit_reporter.htm Holy Hell Over Subway 'jesus' Ad Blitz Targets Jews] By Jeremy Olshan (New York Post) July 7, 2006
*[http://www.hebraicrootsnetwork.com The Hebrew Roots Network]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jews For Jesus}}
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1973]]
[[Category:Christian missions]]
[[Category:Christian missionaries]]
[[Category:Supersessionism]]
[[Category:Judaism-related controversies]]

[[de:Juden für Jesus]]
[[et:Juudid Jeesuse Eest]]
[[fr:Juifs pour Jésus]]
[[it:Ebrei per Gesù]]
[[he:יהודים למען ישוע]]
[[lt:Žydai už Jėzų]]
[[pt:Jews for Jesus]]
[[ru:Евреи за Иисуса]]
[[fi:Jews for Jesus]]
[[yi:זשוס פאר זשיסעס]]</text>
      <sha1>85u7sn8opiyppzflav7lx0e2ht7enrm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
