<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jihad</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16203</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521535884</id>
      <parentid>521124586</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T17:20:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rjensen</username>
        <id>313197</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Further reading */ add cite</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48516">{{Other uses}}
{{Over-quotation|date=March 2008}}
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Islam}}
'''Jihad''' ({{IPAc-en|lang|pron|dʒ|ɪ|ˈ|h|ɑː|d}}; {{lang-ar|جهاد}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|ǧihād}}'' {{IPA-ar|dʒiˈhæːd|}}), an [[List of Islamic terms in Arabic|Islamic term]], is a religious duty of [[Muslim]]s. In [[Arabic language|Arabic]], the word ''jihād'' translates as a noun meaning &quot;struggle&quot;.  ''Jihad'' appears 41 times in the [[Quran]] and frequently in the idiomatic expression &quot;striving in the way of God ''(al-jihad fi sabil [[Allah]])''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;morgan2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Essential Islam: a comprehensive guide to belief and practice|last=Morgan |first=Diane|authorlink=|coauthors=|year=2010|publisher=ABC-CLIO|location=|isbn=0-313-36025-1|page=87 |pages=263|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=U94S6N2zECAC&amp;pg=PA87|accessdate=5 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Merriam&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | editor=[[Wendy Doniger]] | encyclopedia=Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of World Religions | publisher=[[Merriam-Webster]] | year=1999 | isbn=0-87779-044-2}}, ''Jihad'', p.571&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MIC&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | editor=[[Josef W. Meri]] | encyclopedia=Medieval Islamic Civilization: An Encyclopedia | publisher=[[Routledge]] | year=2005 | isbn=0-415-96690-6}}, ''Jihad'', p.419&lt;/ref&gt; A person engaged in jihad is called a ''[[mujahid]]''; the plural is [[mujahideen]]. Jihad is an important religious duty for Muslims. A minority among the [[Sunni Islam|Sunni scholars]] sometimes refer to this duty as the sixth [[Five Pillars of Islam|pillar of Islam]], though it occupies no such official status.&lt;ref name=&quot;jih&quot;&gt;[[John Esposito]](2005), ''Islam: The Straight Path,'' pp.93&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Twelver]] [[Shi'a Islam]], however, Jihad is one of the 10 [[Practices of the Religion]].

There are two commonly accepted meanings of jihad: an inner spiritual struggle and an outer physical struggle.&lt;ref name=&quot;morgan2010&quot;/&gt; The &quot;greater jihad&quot; is the inner struggle by a believer to fulfill his religious duties.&lt;ref name=&quot;morgan2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=BBCjihad&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/beliefs/jihad_1.shtml|title= Jihad|accessdate= 20 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; This non-violent meaning is stressed by both Muslim&lt;ref&gt;[http://rissc.jo/index.php/english-publications.html Jihad and the Islamic Law of War]&lt;/ref&gt; and non-Muslim&lt;ref&gt;Rudolph Peters, ''Islam and Colonialism. The doctrine of Jihad in Modern History'' (Mouton Publishers, 1979), p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; authors. 

The &quot;lesser jihad&quot; is the physical struggle against the enemies of Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;morgan2010&quot;/&gt; This physical struggle can take a violent form or a non-violent form. The proponents of the violent form translate jihad as &quot;holy war&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;cf. e.g. BBC news article [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/8537925.stm Libya's Gaddafi urges 'holy war' against Switzerland]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rudolph Peters, ''Jihad in Medieval and Modern Islam'' (Brill, 1977), p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; although some [[Islamic studies]] scholars disagree.&lt;ref&gt;Patricia Crone, ''Medieval Islamic Political Thought'' ([[Edinburgh University Press]], 2005), p. 363&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Dictionary of Islam''&lt;ref name=&quot;morgan2010&quot;/&gt; and [[United Kingdom|British]]-American [[oriental studies|orientalist]] [[Bernard Lewis]] both argue jihad has a military meaning in the large majority of cases.&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Lewis, ''The Political Language of Islam'' (University of Chicago Press, 1988), p. 72. Cf. William M. Watt, ''Islamic Conceptions of the Holy War'' in: Thomas P. Murphy, ''The Holy War'' (Ohio State University Press, 1974), p. 143&lt;/ref&gt; Some scholars maintain non-violent ways to struggle against the enemies of Islam. An example of this is written debate, often characterized as &quot;jihad of the pen&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;DeLong-Bas (2010), p.3&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the BBC, a third meaning of jihad is the struggle to build a good society.&lt;ref name=BBCjihad/&gt; In a commentary of the hadith [[Sahih Muslim]], entitled al-Minhaj, the [[Islamic Golden Age|medieval Islamic]] scholar [[Yahya ibn Sharaf al-Nawawi]] stated that &quot;one of the collective duties of the community  as a whole (fard kifaya) is to lodge a valid protest, to solve problems of religion, to have knowledge of Divine Law, to command what is right and forbid wrong conduct&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sunnah.org/fiqh/jihad_judicial_ruling.htm|title= Jihad—A Misunderstood Concept from Islam|accessdate= 16 August 2006|author= Shaykh Hisham Kabbani|coauthors=Shaykh Seraj Hendricks, Shaykh Ahmad Hendricks|publisher=The Muslim Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Origins==
{{main | List of expeditions of Muhammad}}
{{Campaignbox Campaigns of Muhammad}}
The beginnings of Jihad are traced back to the words and actions of Muhammad and the Quran.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Rudolph Peters, Jihād (The Oxford Encyclopedia of the Islamic World); [http://www.oxfordislamicstudies.com/MainSearch.html Oxfordislamicstudies.] . Retrieved February 17, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; This encourages the use of Jihad against non-Muslims.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot;&gt;Jonathon P. Berkey, The Formation of Islam; Cambridge University Press: Cambridge, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; The Quran, however, never uses the term Jihad for fighting and combat in the name of Allah; qital is used to mean “fighting.” Jihad in the Quran was originally intended for the nearby neighbors of the Muslims, but as time passed and more enemies arose, the Quranic statements supporting Jihad were updated for the new adversaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot; /&gt; The first documentation of the law of Jihad was written by ‘Abd al-Rahman al-Awza’i and [[Muhammad ibn al-Hasan al-Shaybani]]. The document grew out of debates that had surfaced ever since Muhammad's death.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt;

==Usage of the term==
In [[Literary Arabic|Modern Standard Arabic]], ''jihad'' is one of the correct terms for a struggle for any cause, violent or not, religious or [[secularism|secular]] (though كفاح ''kifāḥ'' is also used).{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} For instance, [[Mahatma Gandhi]]'s [[satyagraha]] struggle for [[Indian independence]] is called a &quot;jihad&quot; in [[Arabic language|Modern Standard Arabic]] (as well as many other dialects of Arabic); the terminology is also applied to the fight for [[feminism|women's liberation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Al-Batal | first = Mahmoud | coauthors = Kristen Brustad, and Abbas Al-Tonsi | title = Al-Kitaab fii Ta&lt;sup&gt;c&lt;/sup&gt;llum al-&lt;sup&gt;c&lt;/sup&gt;Arabiyya, Part II | edition = 2 | year = 2006 | month = | publisher = [[Georgetown University Press]] | location = Washington, DC | language = Arabic, English | isbn = 978-1-58901-096-3 | chapter = 6-&quot;من رائدات الحركة النسائية العربية&quot; (One of the Pioneers of the Arabic Feminist Movement) | quote= To struggle or exert oneself for a cause........جاهََدَ، يجاهِد، الجهاد | ref = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term 'jihad' has accrued both violent and non-violent meanings. It can simply mean striving to live a moral and virtuous life, spreading and defending Islam as well as fighting injustice and oppression, among other things.&lt;ref&gt;Esposito (2002a), p.26&lt;/ref&gt; The relative importance of these two forms of jihad is a matter of controversy. A poll by [[The Gallup Organization|Gallup]] showed that a &quot;significant majority&quot; of Muslim [[Ethnic groups in Indonesia|Indonesians]] define the term to mean &quot;sacrificing one's life for the sake of Islam/God/a just cause&quot; or &quot;fighting against the opponents of Islam&quot;. In Lebanon, Kuwait, Jordan, and Morocco, the majority used the term to mean &quot;duty toward God&quot;, a &quot;divine duty&quot;, or a &quot;worship of God&quot;, with no militaristic connotations. Other responses referenced, in descending order of prevalence:
* &quot;A commitment to hard work&quot; and &quot;achieving one's goals in life&quot;
* &quot;Struggling to achieve a noble cause&quot;
* &quot;Promoting peace, harmony or cooperation, and assisting others&quot;
* &quot;Living the principles of Islam&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John L. Esposito, Dalia Mogahed, ''Who Speaks for Islam? What a Billion Muslims Really Think'' (Gallup, 2007) p. 20 f.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Distinction of &quot;greater&quot; and &quot;lesser&quot; jihad===
In his work, ''The History of Baghdad'', [[Al-Khatib al-Baghdadi]], an 11th-century Islamic scholar, referenced a statement by the [[Sahaba|companion of Muhammad]] [[Jabir ibn Abd-Allah]]. The reference stated that Jabir said, &quot;The Prophet... returned from one of his battles, and thereupon told us, 'You have arrived with an excellent arrival, you have come from the Lesser Jihad to the Greater Jihad—the striving of a servant (of [[Allah]]) against his desires (holy war).&quot;{{Verify credibility|date=March 2011}}&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcislam&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Jihad|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/beliefs/jihad_1.shtml|publisher=BBC|date=2009-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Fayd al-Qadir]] vol.4 pg. 511&lt;/ref&gt; This reference gave rise to the distinguishing of two forms of jihad: &quot;greater&quot; and &quot;lesser&quot;. Some Islamic scholars dispute the authenticity of this reference and consider the meaning of jihad as a holy war to be more important.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcislam&quot;/&gt;

According to the Muslim Jurist [[Ibn Hajar al-Asqalani]], the quote in which Muhammad is reported to have said that greater Jihad is the inner struggle, is from an unreliable source:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;This saying is widespread and it is a saying by Ibrahim ibn Ablah according to Nisa'i in al-Kuna. Ghazali mentions it in the Ihya' and al-`Iraqi said that Bayhaqi related it on the authority of Jabir and said: There is weakness in its chain of transmission.&quot; '''Hajar al Asqalani, Tasdid al-qaws, see also Kashf al-Khafaa’ (no.1362)'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sunnah.org/tasawwuf/jihad004.html Sunnah.org]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===The best of jihad===
During the [[Arab Spring]], many peaceful demonstrations in [[Arab countries]] faced violence and gunfire by their government's [[regime]]. The gunfires encouraged the protests and fed them to revolutions, based on their strong faith of what is called &quot;the best of jihad&quot;. The best of jihad was encouraged by their prophet, [[Muhammad]], saying:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.khilafah.com/index.php/analysis/middle-east/11132-protestors-lose-their-fear-of-the-egyptian-regime-and-perform-the-best-jihad-the-word-of-justice-in-front-of-the-oppressive-ruler Performing Best Jihad in Egypt] Accessed: May 9, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://muslimmatters.org/2011/02/01/reflections-on-the-protests-in-egypt The Need for Understanding and Tolerance] Accessed: May 11, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The best Jihad is the word of Justice in front of the oppressive Sultan [ruler].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Abu Dawud]], [[Tirmidhi]], [[ibn Majah]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In a battlefield context, when ''jihad'' is used to denote warfare, [[Ibn Nuhaas]] cited the following [[hadith]] to explain the meaning of the &quot;best Jihad&quot;:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Ibn Habbaan narrates: The Messenger of Allah was asked about
the best jihad. He said: “The best jihad is the one in which your
horse is slain and your blood is spilled.” '''[Al Baqarah 15]'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kalamullah.com/Books/MashariAl-AshwaqilaMasarial-Ushaaq-RevisedEdition.pdf Ibn Nuhaas, Book of Jihad, Translated by Nuur Yamani, p. 107]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In a similarly worded Hadith to the one above, [[Ibn Nuhaas]] cited a [[hadith]] from [[Musnad Ahmad ibn Hanbal]], where it states that the highest kind of Jihad, is &quot;“The person who is killed whilst spilling the last of his blood.”'''[Ahmed 4/144]'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kalamullah.com/Books/MashariAl-AshwaqilaMasarial-Ushaaq-RevisedEdition.pdf Ibn Nuhaas, Book of Jihad, Translated by Nuur Yamani, p. 177]&lt;/ref&gt;

It has also been reported that Muhammad considered performing [[hajj]] to be the best jihad for Muslim women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Hadith-usc|bukhari|4|52|43}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spiritual struggle===
Muslim scholar Mahmoud Ayoub states that &quot;The goal of true ''jihad'' is to attain a harmony between ''islam'' (submission), ''[[Iman (concept)|iman]]'' (faith), and ''[[ihsan]]'' (righteous living).&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mahmoud M. Ayoub, ''Islam: Faith and History'', pp. 68-69)&lt;/ref&gt;

In modern times, [[Pakistan]]i scholar and professor [[Fazlur Rahman Malik]] has used the term to describe the struggle to establish &quot;just moral-social order&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Fazlur Rahman, ''Major Themes of the Quran'', (Minneapolis: Bibliotheca Islamica, 1980), pp. 63-64.&lt;/ref&gt; while President [[Habib Bourguiba]] of [[Tunisia]] has used it to describe the struggle for economic development in that country.&lt;ref&gt;Rudolph Peters, ''Jihad in Classical and Modern Islam'' (Princeton, N.J.: Markus Weiner, 1996), pp. 116-17&lt;/ref&gt;

===Warfare (Jihad bil Saif)===
{{see|Mujahideen|Jihadism|Jihad fi sabil Allah}}
Within classical [[fiqh|Islamic jurisprudence]]—the development of which is to be dated into the first few centuries after the prophet's death&lt;ref&gt;Albrecht Noth, ''Der Dschihad: sich mühen für Gott''. In: Gernot Rotter, ''Die Welten des Islam: neunundzwanzig Vorschläge, das Unvertraute zu verstehen'' (Fischer Taschenbuch Verlag, 1993), p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;—jihad is the only form of warfare permissible under [[Sharia|Islamic law]], and may consist in wars against unbelievers, [[Apostasy|apostates]], rebels, highway robbers and dissenters renouncing the authority of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Majid Khadduri, ''War and Peace in the Law of Islam'' (The Johns Hopkinns Press, 1955), pp. 74-80&lt;/ref&gt; The primary aim of jihad as warfare is not the conversion of non-Muslims to Islam by force, but rather the expansion and defense of the [[Islamic state]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | title=Djihād | encyclopedia=Encyclopedia of Islam Online }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JPeters&quot;&gt;R. Peters (1977), p.3&lt;/ref&gt; In later centuries, especially in the course of the colonization of large parts of the Muslim world, emphasis has been put on non-militant aspects of the jihad. Today, some Muslim authors only recognize wars with the aim of territorial defense as well as the defense of religious freedom as legitimate.&lt;ref&gt;Rudolph Peters, ''Jihad in Classical and Modern Islam'' (Markus Wiener Publishers, 2005), p. 125&lt;/ref&gt;

Whether the Quran sanctions defensive warfare only or commands an all out war against non-Muslims depends on the interpretation of the relevant passages.&lt;ref&gt;Fred M. Donner, ''The Sources of Islamic Conceptions of War'', in: James Turner Johnson, ''Just War and Jihad'' (Greenwood Press, 1991), p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; This is because it does not explicitly state the aims of the war Muslims are obliged to wage; the passages concerning ''jihad'' rather aim at promoting fighters for the Islamic cause and do not discuss military ethics.&lt;ref&gt;Albrecht Noth, ''Heiliger Krieg und Heiliger Kampf in Islam und Christentum'' (Röhrscheid, 1966), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

In the classical manuals of Islamic jurisprudence, the [[Rules of war in Islam|rules associated with armed warfare]] are covered at great length. Such rules include not killing women, children and non-combatants, as well as not damaging cultivated or residential areas.&lt;ref&gt;Muhammad Hamidullah, ''The Muslim Conduct of State'' (Ashraf Printing Press 1987, pp. 205-208&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, modern Muslims have tried to re-interpret the Islamic sources, stressing that Jihad is essentially defensive warfare aimed at protecting Muslims and Islam.&lt;ref name=&quot;JPeters&quot;/&gt; Although [[Opinion of Islamic scholars on Jihad|some Islamic scholars have differed on the implementation of Jihad]], there is consensus amongst them that the concept of jihad will always include armed struggle against persecution and oppression.&lt;ref name=&quot;jihad&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Ghamidi | first = Javed | authorlink = Javed Ahmed Ghamidi | title = [[Mizan]] | publisher = [[Al-Mawrid|Dar ul-Ishraq]] |chapter=The Islamic Law of Jihad |chapter-url=http://www.studying-islam.org/articletext.aspx?id=771 | year = 2001 | doi = | {{OCLC|52901690}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;


====Civilization Jihad====

Civilization Jihad is the Islamic settlement process tasked with eliminating and destroying Western way of life from within. It is a stealth jihad that features [[propaganda]], political and [[psychological warfare]], [[influence operations]], [[lawfare]], [[subversion]], and other techniques with the goal to subvert American institutions and foundations. It targets law enforcement, politics, education, courts, financial elements, and military. The mission is led by the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] and its front organizations within the US. &lt;ref&gt;Boykin, William J., Harry Edward Soyster, Henry Cooper, Stephen C. Coughlin, Michael Del Rosso, Frank J. Gaffney Jr, John Guandolo, et al. Shariah: The Threat To America: An Exercise In Competitive Analysis. Center for Security Policy, 2010. &lt;/ref&gt;

===Debate===
Controversy has arisen over whether the usage of the term ''jihad'' without further explanation refers to military combat, and whether some have used confusion over the definition of the term to their advantage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.meforum.org/article/357 What Does Jihad Mean?] &quot;For example, [[Yasir Arafat]]'s May 1994 call in [[Johannesburg]] for a &quot;jihad to liberate [[Jerusalem]]&quot; was a turning point in the peace process; [[Israel]]is heard him speak about using violence to gain political ends and questioned his peaceable intentions. Both Arafat himself and his aides then clarified that he was speaking about a &quot;peaceful jihad&quot; for Jerusalem.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Middle East historian [[Bernard Lewis]] argues that &quot;the overwhelming majority of classical theologians, jurists, and traditionalists (specialists in the hadith) understood the obligation of jihad in a military sense.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Lewis, ''The Political Language of Islam'' (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1988), p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Lewis maintains that for most of the recorded history of Islam, from the lifetime of the Prophet [[Muhammad]] onward, the word jihad was used in a primarily military sense.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Bernard, ''[[The Crisis of Islam]]'', 2001 Chapter 2&lt;/ref&gt;

Bernard Lewis' interpretation on Jihad is partially correct according to ''Fiqh Made Easy: A Basic Textbook of Islamic Law'' which describes Jihad as being &quot;divided into four types:

# Jihad against the soul: Struggling against the soul to yearn for the Religion, act upon those teachings, and call others to them. (Paraphrased)
# Jihad against Shaytan: Struggling against Satan without doubts or desires.
# Jihad against the disbelievers and hypocrites: this is done with the tongue, hand, heart and wealth.
# Jihad against heretics, liars, and evilfolk: This is best done with the hand, if not the hand then the tongue, if that's not possible then the heart.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hoor-al-ayn.com/Books/Fiqh%20Made%20Easy.pdf ''Fiqh Made Easy: A Basic Text of Islamic Law; Saalikh bin Gahneem As-Sadlan] pg. 117-18''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Views of different Muslim groups==
===Ahmadiyya===
{{Main|Ahmadiyya view on Jihad}}
In [[Ahmadiyya|Ahmadiyya Islam]], jihad is primarily one's personal inner struggle and should not be used violently for political motives. Violence is the last option only to be used to protect religion and one's own life in extreme situations of persecution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theyworkforyou.com/whall/?id=2010-10-20a.284.0|title=Ahmadiyya Community, Westminster Hall Debate|publisher=TheyWorkForYou.com|accessdate=28 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sunni===
{{See also|Opinion of Islamic scholars on Jihad}}
Jihad has been classified either as ''al-jihād al-akbar'' (the greater jihad), the struggle against one's ego or self (''[[nafs]]''), or ''al-jihād al-asghar'' (the lesser jihad), the external, physical effort, often implying fighting (this is similar to the shiite view of jihad as well).

[[Gibril Haddad]] has analyzed the basis for the belief that internal jihad is the &quot;greater jihad&quot;, ''Jihad al-akbar''. Haddad identifies the primary historical basis for this belief in a pair of similarly worded [[hadith]], in which Mohammed is reported to have told warriors returning home that they had returned from the lesser jihad of struggle against non-Muslims to a greater jihad of struggle against lust. Although Haddad notes that the authenticity of both hadeeth is questionable, he nevertheless concludes that the underlying principle of superiority internal jihad does have a reliable basis in the Quran and other writings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haddad-LivingIslam&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.livingislam.org/n/dgjh_e.html |title=Documentation of &quot;Greater Jihad&quot; hadith |accessdate= August 16, 2006 |author= |last=Haddad |first=Gibril |authorlink=Gibril Haddad |coauthors= |date=2005-02-28 |year= |month= |work= |publisher=living Islam |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Haddad-SunniPath&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sunnipath.com/resources/Questions/qa00002862.aspx |title= Accusations on Shaykh Hamza Yusuf |accessdate=August 16, 2006 |author= |last=Haddad |first=Gibril |authorlink=Gibril Haddad |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher=sunnipath.com |pages= |language= |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060725001826/http://www.sunnipath.com/resources/Questions/qa00002862.aspx &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = July 25, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Note: In my opinion, Gibril meets reliable source standards because he's a published Islamic translator and scholar, writing within the area of his expertise-TheronJ--&gt;

In contrast, the [[Hanbali]] scholar [[Ibn Qayyim Al-Jawziyya]] did believe that &quot;internal Jihad&quot; is important&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.se/~m9783/n/dgjh_e.html Documentation of &quot;Greater Jihad&quot; hadith&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; but he suggests those [[hadith]] as weak which consider &quot;Jihad of the heart/soul&quot; to be more important than &quot;Jihad by the sword&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peacewithrealism.org/jihad/jihad03.htm ''Jihad'' in the ''Hadith''], ''Peace with Realism'', April 16, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Contemporary Islamic scholar [[Abdullah Yusuf Azzam]] has argued the hadith is not just weak but &quot;is in fact a false, fabricated hadith which has no basis. It is only a saying of Ibrahim Ibn Abi `Abalah, one of the Successors, and it contradicts textual evidence and reality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioscope.com/info/doc/jihad/azzam_caravan_6_conclusion.htm Join the caravan]&lt;/ref&gt;

Muslim jurists explained there are four kinds of ''jihad fi sabilillah'' (struggle in the cause of God):&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated3&quot;&gt;Majid Khadduri: ''War and Peace in the Law of Islam'', p.56&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Jihad of the heart''' ''(jihad bil qalb/nafs)'' is concerned with combatting [[the devil]] and in the attempt to escape his persuasion to evil. This type of Jihad was regarded as the greater jihad (''al-jihad al-akbar'').
* '''Jihad by the tongue''' ''(jihad bil lisan)'' is concerned with speaking the truth and spreading the word of Islam with one's tongue.
* '''Jihad by the hand''' ''(jihad bil yad)'' refers to choosing to do what is right and to combat injustice and what is wrong with action.
* '''Jihad by the sword''' ''(jihad bis saif)'' refers to ''qital fi sabilillah'' (armed fighting in the way of God, or holy war), the most common usage by [[Salafi]] Muslims and offshoots of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]].

Some contemporary [[Islamists]] have succeeded in replacing the greater jihad, the fight against desires, with the lesser jihad, the holy war to establish, defend and extend the Islamic state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hoover.org/publications/policyreview/3431076.html ''Understanding Jihad'', February, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sufic===
The Sufic view classifies &quot;Jihad&quot; into two; the &quot;[[Greater Jihad]]&quot; and the &quot;[[Lesser Jihad]]&quot;. Muhammad put the emphasis on the &quot;greater Jihad&quot; by saying that &quot;Holy is the warrior who is at war with himself&quot;. {{Citation needed|date=November 2009}} In this sense external wars and strife are seen but a satanic counterfeit of the true &quot;jihad&quot; which can only be fought and won within; no other Salvation existing can save man without the efforts of the man himself being added to the work involved of self-refinement. In this sense it is the western view of the [[Holy Grail]] which comes closest to the Sufic ideal; for to the Sufis Perfection is the Grail; and the Holy Grail is for those who after they become perfect by giving all they have to the poor then go on to become &quot;[[Abdal]]&quot; or &quot;changed ones&quot; like Enoch who was &quot;taken&quot; by God because he &quot;walked with God&quot;. ([[Book of Genesis|Genesis]]:5:24) here the &quot;Holy Ones&quot; gain the surname &quot;Hadrat&quot; or &quot;The Presence&quot;.

==History==
[[Image:Map of expansion of Caliphate.svg|350px|thumb|right|Age of the [[Caliph]]s {{legend|#a1584e|Expansion under [[Muhammad]], 622–632/A.H. 1-11}} {{legend|#ef9070|Expansion during the [[Rashidun Empire|Rashidun Caliphate]], 632–661/A.H. 11-40}} {{legend|#fad07d|Expansion during the [[Umayyad Caliphate]], 661–750/A.H. 40-129}}]]
===Early Muslim conquests===
{{main|Muslim conquests}}
Two years after the death of the Islamic prophet Muhammad in 632, Muslims under the leadership of caliph [[Umar]] began military campaigns against the [[Byzantine empire]] and the [[Sassanian empire]]. In the [[Battle of Yarmuk]] in 636, Muslims defeated the Byzantine army, forcing the empire to withdraw from Syria. The Byzantines surrendered near Cairo in 641. The conquest of [[Alexandria]], then capital of Egypt, took longer. Muslims faced little resistance from the locals as they had suffered under Byzantine rule. In the [[Battle of al-Qadisiyya]] in 637 where the Persian army was defeated. In 642, Muslims defeated the Persians at the [[Battle of Nahāvand]], opening up the plateau to Muslim conquest. Within 15 years Iran had been conquered. Muslims later pushed into [[central Asia]].&lt;ref&gt;Bonner, Michael (2006). ''Jihad in Islamic History''. New Jersey: [[Princeton University Press]]. p.58-59&lt;/ref&gt;

Often called &quot;the Great conquests&quot;, the role of Islam in them is debated. Medieval Arabic authors said that the conquests had been commanded by God. They were presented as orderly and disciplined, under the command of the caliph.&lt;ref&gt;Bonner (2006), p.60-1&lt;/ref&gt; Many modern explanations dispute the idea that jihad was a motivating force in the conquests. They hold that Arabs on the eve of the conquests were poor and desertification in the Arabian peninsula had reduced local resources. These explanations cite material causes as opposed to religion as the fundamental cause of the conquests. Some recent explanations cite both material and religious causes in the conquests.&lt;ref&gt;Bonner (2006), p.62-3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Muslim brotherhood===

{{Main|Muslim brotherhood}}

In 1928, Hassan al-Banna founded the Muslim Brotherhood, a rigidly conservative and highly secretive Egyptian-based organization dedicated to resurrecting a Muslim empire ([[Caliphate]]). According to al-Banna, &quot;It is the nature of Islam to dominate, not to be dominated, to impose its law on all nations and to extend its power to the entire planet.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;INVESTIGATIVE-MB&quot;&gt;[http://www.investigativeproject.org/documents/misc/355.pdf THE DEVELOPMENT OF MPAC'S ISLAMIST IDEOLOGY: A PRIMER] Investigative Project&lt;/ref&gt; The Muslim Brotherhood, also called Muslim Brethren (jamiat al-Ikhwan al-muslimun, literally Society of Muslim Brothers), it opposes secular tendencies of Islamic nations and wants return to the precepts of the Quran, and rejection of Western influences.&lt;ref name=&quot;JVL-MB&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Terrorism/muslimbrotherhood.html | title=The Muslim Brotherhood|publisher=JVL | accessdate=2010-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Al Bana was born out of the extreme Muslim right wing's desire to counter the ideology of modernization, the Brotherhood's platform included a strict interpretation of the [[Quran]] that glorified suicidal violence. Along with Al Banna, the grand Mufti of Jerusalem Haj-al Amin Al-Husseini was also an enormously influential Muslim leader of the time. Together, the two created a powerful and popular Islamist party by classically appealing to fundamentalist Islamic principals while blaming the world's problems on the Jews.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishtribune.ca/TribuneV2/content/view/551/5/ Jewish Tribune - German scholar alerts all to threat of Islamofascism]&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Banna also gave the group the motto it still uses today: &quot;Allah is our purpose, the Prophet our leader, the Quran our constitution, jihad our way and dying for God our supreme objective.&quot; The 9/11 Commission Report states the Brotherhood's influence on [[Osama bin Laden]] and on Sheik [[Omar Abdel Rahman]] responsible for the 1993 attack on the WTC.&lt;ref name=&quot;INVESTIGATIVE-MB&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldnetdaily.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=27149 The Quran: Suicide playbook, Farah]&lt;/ref&gt;
An important aspect of the Muslim Brotherhood ideology is the sanctioning of Jihad such as the 2004 fatwa issued by Sheikh Yousef Al-Qaradhawi making it a religious obligation of Muslims to abduct and kill U.S. citizens in Iraq.&lt;ref name=&quot;JVL-MB&quot; /&gt;

It advocated a war of Arabism and Islamic Jihad against the British and the Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;WISTRICH&quot;&gt;Samuel Totten, Paul Robert Bartrop, Steven L. Jacobs. Dictionary of Genocide: A-LVolume 1 of Dictionary of Genocide, Paul Robert Bartrop. ABC-CLIO, 2008. p. 226 ISBN 978-0-313-34642-2&lt;/ref&gt;

The Muslim brotherhood waged a &quot;Holy war&quot; against [[Syria]] after the [[Hama massacre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;totten&quot;&gt;Samuel Totten, Paul Robert Bartrop, Steven L. Jacobs. Dictionary of Genocide: A-LVolume 1 of Dictionary of Genocide, Paul Robert Bartrop. ABC-CLIO, 2008. [http://books.google.com/books?id=xWKjSc0ql3cC&amp;pg=PA181 p. 181] ISBN 978-0-313-34642-2&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[BBC]] explains how the roots of Jihad and the origins of [[Bin Laden]]'s concept of jihad can be traced back to two early 20th century figures, who started powerful Islamic revivalist movements in response to colonialism and its aftermath. al-Banna blamed the western idea of separation between religion and politics for Muslims' decline.
In the 1950s [[Sayed Qutb]], [[Muslim Brotherhood]]'s prominent member, took the arguments of al-Banna even further.
For Qutb, &quot;all non-Muslims were infidels - even the so-called ''people of the book'', the Christians and Jews,&quot; he also predicted an eventual clash of civilisations between Islam and the west.
&quot;Qutb inspired a whole generation of Islamists, including Ayatollah Khomeini.&quot;
The Muslim world widely accepted his ideology post Arabs' defeat in the 1967 war.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC-MB&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/1603178.stm BBC NEWS | Middle East | Analysis: The roots of jihad]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Muslim Brotherhood]] has been involved in violent attacks. From its Islamic theme in its symbolism: on its flag there's a brown square frames a green circle with a white perimeter. Two swords cross inside the circle beneath a red Quran. The cover of the Quran says: &quot;Truly, it is the Generous Quran.&quot; The Arabic beneath the sword handles translates as &quot;Be prepared.&quot; A reference to a Quranic verse that talks of preparing to fight the enemies of God.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adl.org/terrorism/symbols/muslim_brotherhood_1.asp Muslim Brotherhood - ADL Terrorist Symbol Database]&lt;/ref&gt; It is among 17 groups categorized as &quot;terrorist organizations&quot; by the [[Russia]]n government,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/5223458.stm BBC NEWS |  Europe |  Russia names 'terrorist' groups]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as in [[Egypt]], where they started to perform terrorist attacks, now banned by that government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://i-cias.com/e.o/mus_br_egypt.htm Muslim Brotherhood - Egypt]&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholar states that in &quot;The Muslim Brotherhood's Conquest of Europe,&quot; its real goal is to extend Islamic law [[Sharia]] throughout [[Europe]] and the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.meforum.org/article/687 The Muslim Brotherhood's Conquest of Europe :: Middle East Quarterly]&lt;/ref&gt;

Contemporary Islamism holds that Islam is now under attack, and therefore -experts explain- &lt;blockquote&gt;Jihad is now a war of defense, and as such has become not only a collective duty but an individual duty without restrictions or limitations. That is, to the Islamists, Jihad is a total, all-encompassing duty to be carried out by all Muslims – men and women, young and old. All infidels, without exception, are to be fought and annihilated, and no weapons or types of warfare are barred. Furthermore, according to them, current Muslim rulers allied with the West are considered apostates and infidels.
One major ideological influence in Islamist thought was Sayyid Qutb. Qutb, an Egyptian, was the leader of the Muslim Brotherhood movement. He was convicted of treason for plotting to assassinate Egyptian president Gamal Abd Al-Nasser and was executed in 1966. He wrote extensively on a wide range of Islamic issues. According to Qutb, &quot;There are two parties in all the world: the Party of Allah and the Party of Satan – the Party of Allah which stands under the banner of Allah and bears his insignia, and the Party of Satan, which includes every community, group, race, and individual that does not stand under the banner of Allah.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Contemporary Islamist Ideology Authorizing Genocidal Murder,
27 January 2004, MEMRI [http://www.memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=subjects&amp;Area=jihad&amp;ID=SR2504]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the &quot;Holy land foundation&quot; case of the [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]] Arab [[al-Arian]]'s involvement in funding terror organization, the Muslim Brotherhood's papers detailed plan to seize U.S. The Group's takeover plot emerged when revealed a handful of classified evidence detailing Islamist extremists' ambitious plans for a U.S. takeover.
Terrorism researchers said &quot;the memos and audiotapes, many translated from Arabic and containing detailed strategies by the international Islamist group the Muslim Brotherhood, are proof that extremists have long sought to replace the Constitution with Shariah, or Islamic law,&quot;  paving its way via a plot to form &quot;a complex network of seemingly benign Muslim organizations whose real job, according to the ([[United States|US]]) government, was to spread militant propaganda and raise money.&quot;
The [[Muslim Brotherhood]] created some American Muslim groups and sought influence in others, many of which are listed as unindicted co-conspirators in the Holy Land case, such as [[Council on American–Islamic Relations|CAIR]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dallasnews.com/sharedcontent/dws/news/localnews/stories/091707dnmetbrotherhood.35ce2b6.html Muslim Brotherhood's papers detail plan to seize U.S. |  News for Dallas, Texas |  [[Dallas Morning News]] |  Breaking News for Dallas-Fort Worth (September 17, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;On a website devoted to Ramadhan, the Muslim Brotherhood posted a series of articles by Dr. Ahmad 'Abd Al-Khaleq about Al-Walaa Wa'l-Baraa, an Islamic doctrine which, in its fundamentalist interpretation, stipulates absolute allegiance to the community of Muslims and total rejection of non-Muslims and of Muslims who have strayed from the path of Islam.
In his articles, the writer argues that according to this principle, a Muslim can come closer to Allah by hating all non-Muslims -Christians, Jews, atheists, or polytheists - and by waging jihad against them in every possible manner.&lt;ref name=&quot;MEMRI&quot;&gt;[http://www.memriiwmp.org/content/en/report.htm?report=2877 Muslim Brotherhood Website: Jihad Against Non-Muslims Is Obligatory]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Indeed, the Muslim Brotherhood has a long-standing war on the West. From 1948 until the 1970s it engaged in assassinations and terrorism in Egypt, and has indoctrinated many who went on to commit acts of terror.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.familysecuritymatters.org/terrorism.php Terrorism] FSM&lt;/ref&gt; Muslim Brotherhood's supreme guide issued the statement that [[Al Qaeda]]'s &quot;Bin Laden is a Jihad Fighter.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Muslim Brotherhood Supreme Guide: Bin Laden is a Jihad Fighter, Special Dispatch Series - No. 2001 - 25 July 2008, MEMRI
[http://www.memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Page=archives&amp;Area=sd&amp;ID=SP200108]&lt;/ref&gt;

The accused mastermind of the [[9/11]] terror massacre, [[Khalid Sheikh Mohammed]] was raised in [[Kuwait]] and joined the Muslim Brotherhood at age 16.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biography.com/notorious/crimefiles.do?action=view&amp;catName=Terrorrists&amp;profileId=266103 The Biography Channel - Notorious Crime Profiles Khalid Sheikh Mohammed - Serial Killers &amp; Other Criminals - Notorious Crime Files] The Biography Channel&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.scotsman.com/latestnews/-Khalid-Sheikh-Mohammed-make.4159045.jp Khalid Sheikh Mohammed: make me a martyr for 9/11-Scotsman.com News]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Warfare in Muslim societies ==
{{main|Islam and war}}
[[File:Fula jihad states map general c1830.png|thumb|The Fulani Jihad States of West Africa, c. 1830]]
The major imperial Muslim dynasties of [[Ottoman Turkey]] ([[Sunni]]) and [[Persia]] ([[Shia]]) each established systems of authority around traditional Islamic institutions. In the Ottoman empire, the concept of [[ghaza]] was promulgated as a sister obligation to jihad. The Ottoman ruler [[Mehmed II]] is said to have insisted on the conquest of Constantinople (Christian Byzantium) by justifying ''ghaza'' as a basic duty. Later Ottoman rulers would apply ''ghaza'' to justify military campaigns against the Persian [[Safavid]] dynasty. Thus both rival empires established a tradition that a ruler was only considered truly in charge when his armies had been sent into the field in the name of the true faith, usually against ''giaurs'' or heretics &amp;mdash; often meaning each other. The 'missionary' vocation of the Muslim dynasties was prestigious enough to be officially reflected in a formal title as part of a full ruler style: the Ottoman (many also had Ghazi as part of their name) Sultan [[Murad Khan II Khoja-Ghazi]], 6th Sovereign of the House of Osman (1421–1451), literally used [[Sultan ul-Mujahidin]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

The so-called [[Fulbe jihad state]]s and a few other jihad states in [[western Africa]] were established by a series of offensive wars.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.onwar.com/aced/data/uniform/usman1804.htm Onwar.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

The commands inculcated in the Quran (in five suras from the period after Muhammad had established his power) on Muslims to fight those who will neither embrace Islam nor pay a poll-tax (''[[Jizya]]'') were not interpreted as a general injunction on all Muslims constantly to make war on the infidels (originally only polytheists who claimed to be monotheists, not &quot;People of the Book&quot;, Jesus is seen as the last of the precursors of the Prophet Muhammed; the word infidel had different historical uses, notably used by the Crusaders to refer to the Muslims they were fighting against). It was generally supposed that the order for a general war can only be given by the [[Caliph]] (an office that was claimed by the Ottoman sultans), but Muslims who did not acknowledge the spiritual authority of the Caliphate (which is vacant), such as non-Sunnis and non-Ottoman Muslim states, always looked to their own rulers for the proclamation of a jihad; there has been in fact no universal warfare by Muslims on non-believers since the early caliphate. Some proclaimed Jihad by claiming themselves as [[mahdi]], e.g. the Sudanese [[Mahommed Ahmad]] in 1882.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field%28DOCID+sd0024%29 Sudan: The Mahdiyah, 1884-98]&quot;. US Library of Congress, A Country Study.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Non-Muslim opinions ==
The [[United States Department of Justice]] has used its own ''ad hoc'' definitions of jihad in indictments of individuals involved in terrorist activities:
*&quot;As used in this First Superseding Indictment, 'Jihad' is the Arabic word meaning 'holy war'. In this context, jihad refers to the use of violence, including paramilitary action against persons, governments deemed to be enemies of the fundamentalist version of Islam.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.milnet.com/2nd-indictment-hayat-dist-court.pdf Milnet.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;As used in this Superseding Indictment, 'violent jihad' or 'jihad' include planning, preparing for, and engaging in, acts of physical violence, including murder, maiming, kidnapping, and hostage-taking.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.findlaw.com/hdocs/docs/padilla/uspad111705ind.pdf Findlaw.com]&lt;/ref&gt; in the indictment against several individuals including [[José Padilla (prisoner)|José Padilla]].

In her book ''[[Muhammad: a Biography of the Prophet (book)|Muhammad: a Biography of the Prophet]]'', B.A. Robinson writes:

:&quot;Fighting and warfare might sometimes be necessary, but it was only a minor part of the whole jihad or struggle.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Robinson&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/isl_jihad.htm |title= The Concept of Jihad &quot;Struggle&quot; in Islam |accessdate=August 16, 2006 |author= B.A. Robinson |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= 2003-03-28 |publisher= Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance |archiveurl= |archivedate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Maxime Rodinson]], an [[Oriental studies|orientalist]], wrote that &quot;Jihad is a propagandistic device which, as need be, resorts to armed struggle &amp;ndash; two ingredients common to many ideological movements.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Maxime Rodinson. ''Muhammad''. Random House, Inc., New York, 2002. p. 351.&lt;/ref&gt;

In English-speaking countries, especially the [[United States]], the term &quot;jihadist&quot; has been used in Western media as a synonym for ''[[mujahid]]'', and frequently used to describe [[militant Islam]]ic groups, including but not restricted to [[Islamic terrorism]].

David Cook, author of ''Understanding Jihad'', said &quot;In reading Muslim literature — both contemporary and classical — one can see that the evidence for the primacy of spiritual jihad is negligible. Today it is certain that no Muslim, writing in a non- Western language (such as Arabic, Persian, Urdu), would ever make claims that jihad is primarily nonviolent or has been superseded by the spiritual jihad. Such claims are made solely by Western scholars, primarily those who study Sufism and/or work in interfaith dialogue, and by Muslim apologists who are trying to present Islam in the most innocuous manner possible.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cook166&quot;&gt;Cook, David. ''Understanding Jihad''. [[University of California Press]], 2005. Retrieved from [[Google Books]] on November 27, 2011. ISBN 0-520-24203-3, ISBN 978-0-520-24203-6.&lt;/ref&gt; Cook argued that &quot;Presentations along these lines are ideological in tone and should be discounted for their bias and deliberate ignorance of the subject&quot; and that &quot;[i]t is no longer acceptable for Western scholars or Muslim apologists writing in non-Muslim languages to make flat, unsupported statements concerning the prevalence — either from a historical point of view or within contemporary Islam—of the spiritual jihad.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cook166&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Islam}}
* [[Islamic military jurisprudence]]
* [[Opinion of Islamic scholars on Jihad]]
* [[Itmam al-hujjah]]
* [[Jihad in Hadith]]
* [[Jihad satire]]
* [[Mujahideen]]
* [[Ijtihad]]
* [[Militant Islam]]
* [[Islam and war]]
* [[Love Jihad]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
{{1911}}

== Further reading ==
* Hashami, Sohail H., ed. ''Just Wars, Holy Wars, and Jihads: Christian, Jewish, and Muslim Encounters and Exchanges''  (Oxford University Press; 2012) 434 pages;
* DeLong-Bas, Natana (2010). ''Jihad: Oxford Bibliographies Online Research Guide''. [[Oxford University Press]]
* ''Djihad'' in: ''[[The Encyclopaedia of Islam#2nd edition, EI2|The Encyclopaedia of Islam]]''.
* Alfred Morabia, Le Ğihâd dans l’Islâm médiéval. “Le combat sacré” des origines au XIIe siècle, Albin Michel, Paris 1993
* [[Rudolph Peters]]: ''Jihad in Classical and Modern Islam''
* Nicola Melis, “A Hanafi treatise on rebellion and ğihād in the Ottoman age (XVII c.)”, in ''Eurasian Studies'', Istituto per l’Oriente/Newham College, Roma-Napoli-Cambridge, Volume II; Number 2 (December 2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;215–226.
* [[Rudolph Peters]], ''Islam and Colonialism: The Doctrine of Jihad in Modern History'', “Religion and Society”, Mouton, The Hague 1979.
* [[Muhammad Hamidullah]]: ''Muslim Conduct of State''
* Muhammad Hamidullah: ''Battlefields of the Prophet Muhammad''
* [[John Kelsay]]: ''Just War and Jihad''
* [[Reuven Firestone]]: ''Jihad. The Origin of Holy War in Islam''
* [[Hadia Dajani-Shakeel]] and [[Ronald Messier]]: ''The Jihad and Its Times''
* [[Majid Khadduri]]: ''War And Peace in the Law of Islam''
* [[Hizb ut Tahrir]]: ''The Obligation of Jihad in Islam''
* [[Hassan al-Banna]]: ''Jihad''
* [[Sayyid Qutb]]: ''Milestones''
* [[Bernard Lewis]]: ''The Political Language of Islam''
* Suhas Majumdar: Jihad: The Islamic Doctrine of Permanent War; New Delhi, July 1994]
* [[Javed Ahmad Ghamidi]]: ''[[Mizan]]''
* [[Zaid Shakir]]: ''Jihad is not Perpetual Warfare''
* Biancamaria Scarcia Amoretti, Tolleranza e guerra santa nell’Islam, “Scuola aperta”, Sansoni, Firenze 1974
* J. Turner Johnson, The Holy War Idea in Western and Islamic Traditions, Pennsylvania State University Press, University Park, Pa. 1997
*{{cite book
|last = Malik
|first = S. K.
|year = 1986
|title = The Quranic Concept of War
|url = http://wolfpangloss.files.wordpress.com/2008/02/malik-quranic-concept-of-war.pdf
|publisher = Himalayan Books
|isbn = 81-7002-020-4
}}
*{{cite book
|last = Swarup
|first = Ram
|year = 1982
|title = [[Understanding Islam through Hadis]]
|publisher = Voice of Dharma
|isbn = 0-682-49948-X
}}
*{{cite book
|last = Trifkovic
|first = Serge
|year = 2006
|title = [[Defeating Jihad]]
|publisher = Regina Orthodox Press, USA
|isbn = 1-928653-26-X
}}
*{{cite book
|last = Phillips
|first = Melanie
|year = 2006
|title = [[Londonistan: How Britain is Creating a Terror State Within]]
|publisher = 	Encounter books
|isbn = 1-59403-144-4
}}
* [[Masood Ashraf Raja|Raja Masood Ashraf]]. {{cite journal|year=2009|title=Jihad in Islam: Colonial Encounter, the Neoliberal Order, and the Muslim Subject of Resistance.|journal=The American Journal of Islamic Social Sciences |volume=26|issue=4|pages=25}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Wikiversity}}
*[http://www.alislam.org/jihad/ Jihad in Islam]
*[http://www.alislam.org/terrorism.html Jihad and Terrorism]
*[http://blogs.omeriqbal.com/news/125 Jihad and Muslim Support for Suicide Bombings]
*[http://www.quranandwar.com/ The Qur'an and War: Observations on Islamic Just War]
*[http://www.islamic-vision.com/articles/26/1/Concept-of-Peace-Jihad-And-Condemnation-of-Terrorism-in-Islam/Page1.html Concept of Peace Jihad And Condemnation of Terrorism in Islam]
*[http://encarta.msn.com/encnet/refpages/RefArticle.aspx?refid=761582255 Jihad] ([http://www.webcitation.org/5kwrs0zr3 Archived] 2009-10-31), [[Encarta|Encarta Encyclopedia]]
*[http://www.britannica.com/ebc/article?tocId=9368558 Jihad], [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]
*[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=jihad&amp;searchmode=none EtymologyOnLine]
*[http://www.theage.com.au/news/opinion/why-the-bombers-are-so-angry-at-us/2005/07/22/1121539145036.html Why the bombers are so angry at us]
*[http://voi.org/books/jihad/ Jihãd] by Suhas Majumdar
*{{cite news|url=http://atimes.com/atimes/South_Asia/JJ10Df01.html|title=Making a mockery of jihad|author=Asghar Ali Engineer |date=October 10, 2008 |publisher=Asia Times|accessdate=2008-10-10}}
*[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/kabir-helminski/does-the-quran-really-adv_b_722114.html?view=print Does the Quran Really Sanction Violence Against 'Unbelievers'?] by Shaikh [[Kabir Helminski]], ''[[The Huffington Post]]''

[[Category:Arabic words and phrases]]
[[Category:Islamic terms]]
[[Category:Jihad| ]]

[[af:Djihad]]
[[ar:جهاد]]
[[an:Chihad]]
[[az:Cihad]]
[[bn:জিহাদ]]
[[bg:Джихад]]
[[bo:ལྗེས་ཧ་སྒྲིའམ།]]
[[bs:Džihad]]
[[ca:Gihad]]
[[ceb:Dyihad]]
[[cs:Džihád]]
[[cy:Jihad]]
[[da:Jihad]]
[[de:Dschihad]]
[[et:Džihaad]]
[[el:Τζιχάντ]]
[[es:Yihad]]
[[eo:Ĝihado]]
[[eu:Jihad]]
[[fa:جهاد]]
[[fr:Djihad]]
[[gl:Xihad]]
[[gu:જિહાદ]]
[[ko:지하드]]
[[hi:जिहाद]]
[[hr:Džihad]]
[[id:Jihad]]
[[ia:Jihad]]
[[it:Jihad]]
[[he:ג'יהאד]]
[[jv:Jihad]]
[[kk:Жиһад]]
[[sw:Jihadi]]
[[ku:Cîhad]]
[[la:Gihad]]
[[lv:Džihāds]]
[[lt:Džihadas]]
[[hu:Dzsihád]]
[[ml:ജിഹാദ്]]
[[ms:Jihad]]
[[nl:Jihad]]
[[ja:ジハード]]
[[ce:Гlазот]]
[[no:Jihad]]
[[nn:Jihad]]
[[pl:Dżihad]]
[[pt:Jihad]]
[[ro:Jihad]]
[[ru:Джихад]]
[[sq:Xhihadi]]
[[simple:Jihad]]
[[sk:Džihád]]
[[sl:Džihad]]
[[sr:Џихад]]
[[sh:Džihad]]
[[fi:Jihad]]
[[sv:Jihad]]
[[tl:Jihad]]
[[ta:ஜிகாத்]]
[[te:జిహాద్]]
[[th:ญิฮาด]]
[[tr:Cihad]]
[[uk:Джихад]]
[[ur:جہاد]]
[[zh-yue:聖戰]]
[[zh:圣战]]</text>
      <sha1>0msf4w4gkwmxfvqxoeakoog2udiqgre</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
