<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Last Judgment</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>161978</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519208543</id>
      <parentid>519208399</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-22T14:31:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ian.thomson</username>
        <id>2489738</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/75.99.238.162|75.99.238.162]] ([[User talk:75.99.238.162|talk]]) to last version by Oktanyum</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33030">{{redirect3|Judgment Day|For other uses, see [[Last Judgment (disambiguation)]] and [[Judgment Day (disambiguation)]]}}
[[Image:Stefan Lochner 006.jpg|thumb|370px|''The Last Judgment'' by [[Stefan Lochner|Lochner]] in the 15th century.]] 

The '''Last Judgment''', '''Final Judgment''', '''Day of Judgment''', '''Judgment Day''', or '''The Day of the Lord''' or [[Islamic view of the Last Judgment|in Islam]] '''Yawm al-Qiyāmah''' or '''Yawm ad-Din''' is part of the [[Abrahamic religions#Eschatological world view|eschatological world view of the Abrahamic religions]] and in the [[Frashokereti|Frashokereti of Zoroastrianism]]. 

In [[Christian theology]], it is the final and eternal judgment by [[God in Abrahamic religions|God]] of every [[nation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08552a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: General Judgment]: &quot;Few truths are more often or more clearly proclaimed in Scripture than that of the general judgment. To it the prophets of the Old Testament refer when they speak of the &quot;[[Day of the Lord]]&quot; ({{bibleverse||Joel|2:31}}; {{bibleverse||Ezekiel|13:5}}; {{bibleverse||Isaiah|2:12}}), in which the nations will be summoned to judgment by the Fathers. In the New Testament the [[Parousia]], or coming of Christ as Judge of the world, is an oft-repeated doctrine. The Saviour Himself not only foretells the event but graphically portrays its circumstances ({{bibleverse||Matthew|24:27}} sqq.; {{bibleverse-nb||Matthew|25:31}} sqq.). The Apostles give a most prominent place to this doctrine in their preaching ({{bibleverse||Acts|10:42}}; {{bibleverse-nb||Acts|17:31}}) and writings ({{bibleverse||Romans|2:5-16}}; {{bibleverse-nb||Romans|14:10}}; {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|4:5}}; {{bibleverse|2|Corinthians|5:10}}; {{bibleverse|2|Timothy|4:1}}; {{bibleverse|2|Thessalonians|1:5}}; {{bibleverse||James|5:7}}). Besides the name Parusia (parousia), or Advent ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:23}}; {{bibleverse|2|Thessalonians|2:19}}), the Second Coming is also called Epiphany, epiphaneia, or Appearance ({{bibleverse|2|Thessalonians|2:8}}; {{bibleverse|1|Timothy|6:14}}; {{bibleverse|2|Timothy|4:1}}; {{bibleverse||Titus|2:13}}), and [[Apocalypse]] (apokalypsis), or Revelation ({{bibleverse|2|Thessalonians|2:7}}; {{bibleverse|1|Peter|4:13}}). The time of the Second Coming is spoken of as &quot;that Day&quot; ({{bibleverse|2|Timothy|4:8}}), &quot;the day of the Lord&quot; ({{bibleverse|1|Thessalonians|5:2}}), &quot;the day of Christ&quot; ({{bibleverse||Philemon|1:6}}), &quot;the day of the Son of Man&quot; ({{bibleverse||Luke|17:30}}), &quot;the last day&quot; ({{bibleverse||John|6:39-40}}). The belief in the general judgment has prevailed at all times and in all places within the Church. It is contained as an article of faith in all the ancient creeds: &quot;He ascended into heaven. From thence He shall come to judge the living and the dead&quot; ([[Apostles' Creed]]). The two shall come again with glory to judge both the living and the dead&quot; ([[Nicene Creed]]). &quot;From thence they shall come to judge the living and the dead, at whose coming all men must rise with their bodies and are to render an account of their deeds&quot; ([[Athanasian Creed]]). Relying on the authority of [[Papias of Hierapolis|Papias]], several Fathers of the first four centuries advanced the theory of a thousand years' terrestrial reign of Christ with the saints to precede the end of the World (see article on MILLENNIUM). Though this idea is interwoven with the eschatological teachings of those writers, it in no way detracted from their belief in a universal world-judgment. Patristic testimony to this dogma is clear and unanimous.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The concept is found in all the [[Canonical gospels]], particularly the [[Gospel of Matthew]]. It will purportedly take place after the [[Resurrection of the Dead]] and the [[Second Coming of Christ]]. This belief has inspired numerous artistic depictions.

==Christian sources==
{{salvation}}
The [[doctrine]] and [[iconography|iconographic]] depiction of the &quot;Last Judgment&quot; are drawn from many passages from the [[Apocalyptic literature|apocalyptic]] sections of the Bible. It appears most directly in [[The Sheep and the Goats]] section of the [[Gospel of Matthew]] where the judgment is entirely based on help given or refused to &quot;the least of these&quot;:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usccb.org/nab/bible/matthew/matthew25.htm New American Bible and commentary.]: {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:40}} and {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:45}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;When the Son of Man comes in His glory. All the nations will be gathered before Him, and He will separate people one from another as a shepherd separates his sheep from the goats, and He will set the sheep on His right hand but the goats at the left. Then the king will say to those on His right hand, “Come, you blessed of My Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world; for I was hungry and you gave me food, I was thirsty and you gave me  drink, I was a stranger and you took Me in, I was naked and you clothed Me, I was sick and you visited me, I was in prison and you came to me.” ... “Assuredly, I say to you, inasmuch as you did it to one of the least of these My Brethren, you did it to me.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Then He will also say to those on the left hand, “Depart from Me, you cursed, into the everlasting fire prepared for the devil and his angels; for I was hungry and you gave Me no food, I was thirsty and you gave Me no drink, I was a stranger and you did not take Me in, naked and you did not clothe Me, sick and in prison and you did not visit Me.” ... “Assuredly, I say to  you, inasmuch as you did not do it to one of the least of these, you did not do it to me.” And these will go away into everlasting punishment, but the righteous into eternal life.&quot;(Matthew 25:31-36, 40-43, 45-46 NRSV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The doctrine is further supported by passages in the Books of [[Book of Daniel|Daniel]], [[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]] and the [[Book of Revelation|Revelation]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;And I saw a great white throne, and him that sat on it, from whose face the earth and the heaven fled away; and there was found no place for them.  And I saw the dead, small and great, stand before God; and the books were opened: and another book was opened, which is the book of life: and the dead were judged out of those things which were written in the books, according to their works.&quot; (Rev 20:11-12)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Adherents of [[millennialism]], mostly [[Protestant]] Christians, regard the two passages as describing separate events: the &quot;sheep and goats&quot; judgment will determine the final status of those persons alive at the end of the [[Tribulation]], and the &quot;[[Great White Throne]]&quot; judgment will be the final condemnation of the unrighteous dead at the end of all time, after the [[End of the world (religion)|end of the world]] and before the beginning of the eternal period described in the final two chapters of [[Book of Revelation|Revelation]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

Also, [[Matthew 3:10]]-[[Matthew 3:12|12]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Even now the axe is lying at the root of the trees; every tree therefore that does not bear good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire. ‘I baptize you with water for repentance, but one who is more powerful than I is coming after me; I am not worthy to carry his sandals. He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit and fire. His [[winnowing]] fork is in his hand, and he will clear his threshing-floor and will gather his wheat into the granary; but the chaff he will burn with unquenchable fire.’&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Matthew 13:40-43:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Just as the weeds are collected and burned up with fire, so will it be at the end of the age. The [[Son of Man]] will send his angels, and they will collect out of his kingdom all causes of sin and all [[antinomianism|evildoers]], and they will throw them into the furnace of fire, where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth. Then the righteous will shine like the sun in the kingdom of their Father. Let anyone with ears listen!&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Gospel of Luke|Luke]] 12:4-5,49:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;‘I tell you, my friends, do not fear those who kill the body, and after that can do nothing more. But I will warn you whom to fear: fear him who, after he has killed, has authority to cast into hell. Yes, I tell you, fear him! ... ‘I came to bring fire to the earth, and how I wish it were already kindled!'&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Christianity==
[[File:Das Jüngste Gericht (Memling).jpg|thumb|left|300px|[[Hans Memling|Memling's]] [[The Last Judgment (Memling)|Day of Judgement]], 1467-1471.]]

===Catholicism===
Belief in the last judgment (often linked with the [[General judgment]]) is held firmly inside [[Catholic Church|Catholicism]]. Immediately upon death each [[Soul (spirit)|soul]] undergoes the [[particular judgment]], and depending upon the state of the person's soul, goes to [[heaven]], [[purgatory]], or [[hell]].

The last judgment will occur after the [[resurrection of the dead]] and the reuniting of a person's soul with own physical body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P2G.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church 990]&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic Church teaches that at the time of the last judgment [[Second Coming of Christ|Christ will come in His glory]], and all the [[angels]] with him, and in his presence the truth of each man's relationship with God will be laid bare, and [[Universal resurrection|each person who has ever lived]] will be judged with perfect justice. Those already in heaven will remain in heaven; those already in hell will remain in hell; and those in purgatory will be released into heaven. Following the last judgment, the bliss of heaven and the pains of hell will be perfected in that those present will also be capable of physical bliss/pain. After the last judgment the universe itself will be renewed with a new heaven and a [[The New Earth|new earth]] in the [[World to Come]].

===Eastern Orthodoxy===
[[Image:MHS Sad Ostateczny XVII w Lipie p.jpg|thumb|''The last Judgment'' 17th-century [[icon]] from Lipie (Historic Museum in [[Sanok]], [[Poland]]).]]

[[Image:Voronet last judgment.jpg|thumb|The Last Judgement, mural from [[Voroneţ Monastery]], [[Romania]].]]

The [[Eastern Orthodox Church]] teaches that there are two judgments: the first, or &quot;Particular&quot; Judgment, is that experienced by each individual at the time of his or her death, at which time God will decide where&lt;ref&gt;The Orthodox do not have an understanding of &quot;Purgatory.&quot; Rather, they believe that the souls of the departed will await the Final Judgment either in heaven or hell--but that there are different levels of heaven and different levels of hell--and they believe that the prayers of the Church can help to ease the sufferings of the souls, but do not dogmatize as to how exactly this is accomplished.&lt;/ref&gt; the soul is to spend the time until the [[Second Coming]] of Christ (see [[Hades in Christianity]]). This judgment is generally believed to occur on the fortieth day after death. The second, [[General Judgment|&quot;General&quot;]] or &quot;Final&quot; Judgment will occur after the Second Coming. Although in modern times some have attempted to introduce the concept of [[Soul sleep]] into Orthodox thought about life after death, it has never been a part of traditional Orthodox teaching—in fact, it contradicts the Orthodox understanding of the intercession of the [[Saints#Eastern Orthodox|Saints]].

Eastern Orthodoxy teaches that salvation is bestowed by God as a free gift of [[Divine grace]], which cannot be earned, and by which forgiveness of sins is available to all. However, the deeds done by each person are believed to affect how he will be judged, following the Parable of the Sheep and the Goats. How forgiveness is to be balanced against behavior is not well-defined in scripture, judgment in the matter being solely Christ's. Similarly, although Orthodoxy teaches that salvation is obtained only through Christ and his Church, the fate of those outside the Church at the Last Judgment is left to the [[mercy of God]] and is not declared. [[Image:The Last Judgement - Vasnetsov.jpg|thumb|The Last Judgement, 1904]]

====Iconography====
The theme of the Last Judgment is extremely important in Orthodoxy. Traditionally, an Orthodox church will have a [[fresco]] or [[mosaic]] of the Last Judgment on the back (western) wall, (see the 12th-century mosaic pictured at the top of this page) so that the faithful, as they leave the services, are reminded that they will be judged by what they do during this earthly life. 

The [[icon]] of the Last Judgement traditionally depicts [[Christ Pantokrator]], enthroned in glory on a white throne, surrounded by the [[Theotokos]] (Virgin Mary), [[John the Baptist]], [[Apostles]], [[saint]]s and [[angel]]s. Beneath the throne the scene is divided in half with the &quot;mansions of the righteous&quot; ({{bibleverse||John|14:2|KJV}}), i.e., those who have been [[salvation|saved]] to Jesus' right (the viewer's left); and the torments of those who have been [[damnation|damned]] to his left. Separating the two is the [[Lake of fire|River of fire]] which proceeds from Jesus' left foot. For more detail, see below.

====Hymnography====
The theme of the Last Judgment is found in the [[funeral]] and [[Pannikhida|memorial hymnody]] of the Church, and is a major theme in the services during [[Great Lent]]. The second Sunday before the beginning of Great Lent is dedicated to the Last Judgment. It is also found in the hymns of the [[Octoechos (liturgy)|Octoechos]] used on Saturdays throughout the year.

===Protestantism===
====Amillennialism====
{{Main|Amillennialism}}
Amillennialism is common among some [[Mainline Protestant]] denominations such as the [[Lutheran]], [[Reformed]] and [[Anglican]] churches. Many, but not all, [[partial preterism|partial preterists]] are amillennialists. Amillennialism declined in Protestant circles with the rise of [[Postmillennialism]] and the resurgence of [[Premillennialism]] in the 18th and 19th centuries, but it has regained prominence in the West after World War II.

=====Lutheranism=====
[[Lutheranism|Lutherans]] do not believe in any sort of earthly millennial kingdom of Christ either before or after his second coming on the last day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Joh%2018:36;&amp;version=47; John 18:36], [http://www.bookofconcord.com/augsburgconfession.html#article17 Augsburg Confession, Article 17, Of Christ's Return to Judgment.]&lt;/ref&gt; On the last day,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|6:40|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|6:54|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; all the dead will be resurrected.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|5:21|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|5:28-29|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:32|31}}, {{bibleverse|2|Corinthians|5:10|31}}, {{bibleverse||Acts|24:15|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their souls will then be reunited with the same bodies they had before dying.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Romans|8:11|31}}, {{bibleverse||Philippians|3:21|31}}, {{bibleverse|2|Corinthians|5:10|31}}, {{bibleverse||Job|19:26|9}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:44|31}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:53|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|5:28|31}}, {{bibleverse||Revelation|20:12|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bodies will then be changed, those of the wicked to a state of everlasting shame and torment,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Daniel|12:2|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:41-46|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|5:29|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; those of the righteous to an everlasting state of celestial glory.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Daniel|12:1-2|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|5:29|31}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:52|31}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:42-44|31}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:49-53|31}}, {{bibleverse||Philippians|3:21|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|13:43|31}}, {{bibleverse||Revelation|7:16|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the resurrection of all the dead,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||John|6:40|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|6:44|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|11:24|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the change of those still living,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:51-52|31}}, {{bibleverse|1|Thessalonians|4:15-17|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; all nations shall be gathered before Christ,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matthew|25:32|31}}, {{bibleverse||Romans|14:10|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|5:22|31}}, {{bibleverse||Acts|17:31|31}}, {{bibleverse||Revelation|1:7|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he will separate the righteous from the wicked.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matthew|25:32|31}}, {{bibleverse||Mark|16:16|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christ will publicly judge&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Corinthians|5:10|31}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|4:5|31}}, {{bibleverse||Romans|2:5|31}}, {{bibleverse||Romans|2:16|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; all people by the testimony of their faith,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Ephesians|2:8-10|31}}, {{bibleverse|2|Corinthians|5:10|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:35-36|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:42-43|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[good works]]&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Isaiah|43:25|31}}, {{bibleverse||Ezekiel|18:22|31}}, {{bibleverse|1|John|2:28|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the righteous in evidence of their faith,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matthew|25:34-35|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|3:16-18|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|3:36|31}}, {{bibleverse||Revelation|14:13|31}}, {{bibleverse||Galatians|5:6|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|13:35|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[sin|evil works]] of the wicked in evidence of their unbelief.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matthew|25:42|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|7:17-18|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|3:18|31}}, {{bibleverse||John|3:36|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; He will judge in righteousness&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Romans|2:5|31}}, {{bibleverse||Acts|17:31|31}}, {{bibleverse||Romans|2:16|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the presence of all and men and angels,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Luke|9:26|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:31-32|31}}&lt;/ref&gt; and his final judgement will be just [[damnation]] to everlasting punishment for the wicked and a gracious gift of [[Eternal life (Christianity)|life everlasting]] to the righteous.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Matthew|25:41|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:34|31}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|25:46|31}}, {{cite book |last=Graebner |first=Augustus Lawrence |url=http://showcase.netins.net/web/bilarson/eschatology.txt|title=Outlines Of Doctrinal Theology |pages=233–8 |location=Saint Louis, MO |publisher=Concordia Publishing House |year=1910}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Millennialism====
{{Main|Millennialism}}
[[File:The Vision of the Last Judgment.png|thumb|right|[[William Blake]]'s ''Vision of the Last Judgment'' 1808]]
Particularly among those Protestant groups who adhere to a [[millennialism|millennialist]] eschatology, the Last Judgment is said to be carried out before the [[Great White Throne]] by [[Jesus Christ]] to either [[Eternal life (Christianity)|eternal life]] or [[Afterlife|eternal consciousness]] in the [[lake of fire]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnpcb.org/esv/search/?q=Luke+13%3A28 Passage: Luke 13:28 (ESV Bible Online)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnpcb.org/esv/search/?q=Matthew+25%3A30 Passage: Matthew 25:30 (ESV Bible Online)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnpcb.org/esv/search/?q=Matthew+24%3A51 Passage: Matthew 24:51 (ESV Bible Online)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; at the [[End times|end of time]]. Salvation is granted by [[Divine grace|grace]] based on the individual's surrender and commitment to [[Jesus Christ]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnpcb.org/esv/search/?q=john+3%3A16 Passage: john 3:16 (ESV Bible Online)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnpcb.org/esv/search/?q=romans+10%3A9-13 Passage: romans 10:9-13 (ESV Bible Online)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnpcb.org/esv/search/?q=eph+2%3A8-10 Passage: eph 2:8-10 (ESV Bible Online)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A second [[particular judgment]] they refer to as the [[Great White Throne|Bema Seat]] judgement occurs after (or as) salvation is discerned when awards are granted based on works toward heavenly treasures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnpcb.org/esv/search/?q=Matthew+6%3A19-24 Passage: Matthew 6:19-24 (ESV Bible Online)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; What happens after death and before the final judgment is hotly contested; some believe all people ''[[Psychopannychism|sleep]]'' in [[Sheol]] until the resurrection, others believe Christians dwell in Heaven and pagans wander the earth, and others consider the time to pass instantaneously. Nevertheless, the body is not fully ''redeemed'' until after ''Death'' is destroyed after the [[Great Tribulation]].

Protestant Millennialism falls into roughly two categories: [[Premillennialism|Premillennialist]] (Christ's second coming precedes the [[millennium]]) and [[Postmillennialism|Postmillennialist]] (which sees Christ's second coming as occurring after the millennium).

[[Dispensationalism|Dispensational]] premillennialism generally holds that Israel and the Church are separate. It also widely holds to the pretribulational return of Christ, which believes that Jesus will return before a seven year [[Tribulation]] followed by an additional return of Christ with his saints.

===Esoteric Christian tradition===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Afterlife]] --&gt;
:''See also: [[Second Coming#Esoteric Christian teachings|Second Coming (Esoteric Christian teachings)]] and [[Esoteric Christianity]]''
[[Image:Jugement dernier.jpg|thumb|''The Last Judgment'' by [[Michelangelo]]]]

Although the Last Judgment is preached by a great part of Christian mainstream churches; the [[Esoteric Christianity|Esoteric Christian]] tradition—composed, among others, by the [[Essenes]] and [[Rosicrucian]]s—the [[Spiritualism (religious movement)|Spiritualist movement]], [[Christian Science]], and some [[liberal theism|liberal]] theologies reject the traditional conception of the Last Judgment as inconsistent with an all-just and loving [[God]], in favor of some form of [[universalism|universal]] [[salvation]].

The [[Western Wisdom Teachings]] of the Rosicrucians teach that when the [[Second Coming of Christ|Day of Christ]] comes, marking the end of the current fifth or Aryan epoch, the human race will have to pass a final examination or last judgment, where, as in the ''Days of Noah'',&lt;ref&gt;Max Heindel, ''[http://www.rosicrucian.com/tin/tineng01.htm#Chapter_I The Days of Noah and of Christ]'' in Teachings of an Initiate (posthumous publication of collected works), ISBN 0-911274-19-7&lt;/ref&gt; the chosen ones or pioneers, the ''sheep'', will be separated from the ''goats'' or stragglers,&lt;ref&gt;Cf. {{Bibleref2|Matthew|25:31-35}}&lt;/ref&gt; by being carried forward into the next evolutionary period, inheriting the [[etheric plane|ethereal]] conditions of the [[New Galilee (Sixth Epoch)|New Galilee]] in the making. Nevertheless, it is emphasized that all beings of the human [[spiritual evolution|evolution]] will ultimately be saved in a distant future as they acquire a superior grade of [[consciousness]] and [[altruism]]. At the present period, the process of human evolution is conducted by means of successive [[reincarnation|rebirths]] in the physical world&lt;ref&gt;[[Max Heindel]], The Rosicrucian Christianity Lectures ([http://www.rosicrucian.com/rcl/rcleng01.htm#lecture1 The Riddle of Life and Death]), 1908, ISBN 0-911274-84-7&lt;/ref&gt; and the salvation is seen as being mentioned in [[Book of Revelation|Revelation]] 3:12 ([[KJV]]), which states &quot;Him that overcometh will I make a ''pillar'' in the temple of my God and ''he shall go no more out''&quot;. However, this western esoteric tradition states—like those who have had a [[near-death experience]]—that after the [[death]] of the physical body, at the end of each physical lifetime and after the [[life review]] period (which occurs before the [[silver cord]] is broken), it occurs a [[particular judgment|judgment]], more akin to a Final Review or End Report over one's [[life]], where the life of the subject is fully evaluated and scrutinized.&lt;ref&gt;Max Heindel, [http://www.rosicrucian.com/zineen/death5.htm Death and Life in Purgatory] -  [http://www.rosicrucian.com/zineen/death6.htm Life and Activity in Heaven]&lt;/ref&gt; This judgment is seen as being mentioned in [[Epistle to the Hebrews|Hebrews]] 9:27, which states that &quot;it is appointed unto men once to die, but ''after this the judgment''&quot;.

==Islam==
{{Main|Islamic view of the Last Judgment}}
In [[Islam]], ''Yawm al-Qiyāmah'' ({{lang-ar|يوم القيامة}} &quot;the Day of Resurrection&quot;) or ''Yawm ad-Din'' ({{lang-ar|يوم الدين}} &quot;the Day of Judgment&quot;)  is believed to be [[God in Islam|God's]] (Arabic: Allāh's) final assessment of humanity. The sequence of events (according to the most commonly-held belief) is the annihilation of all creatures, [[resurrection]] of the body, and the judgment of all sentient creatures.

The exact time when these events will occur is unknown, however there are said to be major&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inter-islam.org/faith/Majorsigns.html Major Signs before the Day of Judgment by Shaykh Ahmad Ali]&lt;/ref&gt; and minor signs&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inter-islam.org/faith/Signs-Of-Qiyaamah.htm Signs of Qiyaamah]&lt;/ref&gt; which are to occur near the time of ''Qiyamat'' ([[End time]]). Many verses of the Qu'ran, especially the earlier ones, are dominated by the idea of the nearing of the day of resurrection.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQ&quot;&gt;Isaac Hasson, ''Last Judgment'', [[Encyclopaedia of the Qur'an]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;&gt;L. Gardet, ''Qiyama'', [[Encyclopaedia of the Qur'an]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Belief in al-Qiyāmah is considered a fundamental tenet of faith by all Muslims.[4]. Belief in the day of Judgement is one of the six articles of faith. The trials and tribulations associated with it are detailed in both the Qur'an and the hadith, as well as in the commentaries of the Islamic expositors and scholarly authorities such as al-Ghazali, Ibn Kathir, Ibn Majah, Muhammad al-Bukhari, and Ibn Khuzaimah who explain them in detail. Every human, Muslim and non-Muslim alike, is believed to be held accountable for their deeds and are believed to be judged by God accordingly.[5]
 
-	
The importance of the 'last judgment' is underlined by the many references to it in the Qur'an and its many names. For example, it is also called &quot;the Day of Reckoning&quot;,[6] &quot;the Hour&quot;,[7][8] &quot;the Last Day&quot;,[9] &quot;Day of Judgment&quot;, &quot;Day of the Reckoning&quot;.

==Judaism==
In [[Judaism]], the day of judgment happens every year on [[Rosh Hashanah]] (a day which is also known as Yom HaDin, Judgment Day),  therefore the belief in a last day of judgment for all mankind is disputed. Some Rabbis hold that there will be such a day following the resurrection of the dead. Others hold that there is no need for that because of Rosh Hashanah. While yet others hold that this accounting and judgment happens when one dies. Yet others hold that the last judgment only applies to the nations and not the Jewish people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Will there be trial and judgment after the Resurrection?|url=http://www.askmoses.com/en/article/215,2097883/Will-there-be-trial-and-judgment-after-the-Resurrection.html|work=Will there be trial and judgment after the Resurrection?|publisher=Askmoses.com|accessdate=2 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Artistic representations==
{{main|Doom (painting)}}
[[File:Cathedrale Saint-Guy Prague facade sud mosaique Jugement dernier.jpg|thumb|The Last Judgment mosaic (14th-century), [[St. Vitus Cathedral|Saint Vitus Cathedral]], Prague, Czech Republic.]]
In art, the Last Judgment is a common theme in medieval and renaissance religious iconography.  Like most early iconographic innovations, its origins stem from [[Byzantine art]], although it was a much less common subject than in the West during the Middle Ages.&lt;ref&gt;Remarkably, only three Byzantine icons of the subject survive, all at [[St Catherine's, Sinai]]. Daly, 252&lt;/ref&gt;   In Western Christianity, it is often the subject depicted in medieval cathedrals and churches, either outside on the central [[Pediment|tympanum]] of the entrance, or inside on the (rear) west wall, so that the congregation attending church saw the image on either entering of leaving.  In the 15th century it also appeared as the central section of a [[triptych]] on [[altarpiece]]s, with the side panels showing heaven and hell. The usual composition has Christ seated high in the centre, flanked by angels and the [[Virgin Mary]] and [[John the Evangelist]] who are supplicating on behalf of the souls being judged (in what is called a [[Deesis]] group in Orthodoxy).  [[Saint Michael]] is often shown, either weighing souls on scales or directing matters, and there may be a large crowd of saints, angels, and the saved around the central group. 

At the bottom of the composition a crowd of souls are shown, often with some rising from their graves. These are being sorted and directed by angels into the saved and the damned.  Almost always the saved are on the viewer's left (so on the right hand of Christ), and the damned on the right. The saved are led up to [[heaven]], often shown as a fortified gateway, while the damned are handed over to devils who herd them down into [[hell]] on the right; the composition therefore has a circular pattern of movement.  Often the damned disappear into a [[Hellmouth]], the mouth of a huge monster, an image of [[Anglo-Saxon art|Anglo-Saxon]] origin.  The damned often include figures of high rank, wearing crowns, mitres and often the [[Papal tiara]] during the lengthy periods when there were [[antipopes]], or in Protestant depictions.  There may be detailed depictions of the torments of the damned.

The most famous Renaissance depiction is [[Michelangelo Buonarroti]]'s [[The Last Judgment (Michelangelo)|''The Last Judgment'']] in the [[Sistine Chapel]]. Included in this fresco is his self-portrait, as [[Bartholomew|St. Bartholomew]]'s [[flaying|flayed]] skin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Janson |first=H. W. |title=History of Art |edition=Second Edition |coauthors=Janson, Dora Jane |publisher=Prentis-Hall &amp; Harry N. Abrams |location=Englewood and New York |year=1977 |pages=428 |isbn=0-13-389296-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The image in [[Eastern Orthodox]] [[icon]]s has a similar composition, but usually less space is devoted to Hell, and there are often a larger number of scenes; the Orthodox readiness to label figures with inscriptions often allows more complex compositions.  There is more often a large group of saints around Christ (which may include animals), and the [[hetoimasia]] or &quot;empty throne&quot;, containing a cross, is usually shown below Christ, often guarded by archangels; figures representing [[Adam and Eve]] may kneel below it or below Christ.  A distinctive feature of the Orthodox composition, especially in Russian icons, is a large band leading like a chute from the feet of Christ down to Hell; this may resemble a striped snake or be a &quot;river of Fire&quot; coloured flame red.  If it is shown as a snake, it attempts to bite Adam on the heel, but as he is protected by Christ is unsuccessful.

==See also==
[[Image:Last Judgment (Povolzhie).jpg|thumb|right|Last Judgment(Russia, XVIII cent.)]]
* [[Apocatastasis]]
* [[Atonement in Christianity]]
* [[Christian Eschatology]]
* [[Day of Atonement]]
* [[General judgment]]
* [[God the Father in Western art]]
* [[Intermediate state]]
* [[Lawsuits against God]]
* [[New World Order (conspiracy)]]
* [[Particular judgment]]
* [[Plan of Salvation]] Mormon view
* [[Pralay]]
* [[Ragnarök]]
* [[Book of Revelation|Revelation]]
* [[Second Coming]]
* [[Yama (Buddhism and Chinese mythology)]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{sisterlinks|Last Judgment}}
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08552a.htm ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' &quot;General Judgment&quot;]
* [http://www.life.com/gallery/60451/judgment-day-past-and-future#index/0 Judgment Day Past and Future] - slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''
* Swedenborg, E. [http://swedenborgdigitallibrary.org/contets/LJ.html ''The Last Judgment and Babylon Destroyed. All the Predictions in the Apocalypse are at This Day Fulfilled''] (Swedenborg Foundation 1951)

{{Doomsday}}

[[Category:Last Judgement| ]]
[[Category:Biblical phrases]]
[[Category:Book of Revelation]]
[[Category:Christian eschatology]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Christ the King]]
[[Category:Judeo-Christian topics]]

[[ar:يوم القيامة]]
[[az:Məhşər]]
[[bg:Страшен съд]]
[[ca:Judici Final]]
[[cs:Poslední soud]]
[[da:Dommedag]]
[[de:Jüngstes Gericht]]
[[et:Viimnepäev]]
[[es:Juicio Final]]
[[eo:Lasta juĝo]]
[[fa:رستاخیز]]
[[fr:Jour du jugement]]
[[hak:Tsui-heu ke Sṳ́m-phan]]
[[ko:최후의 심판]]
[[hr:Sudnji dan]]
[[id:Pengadilan Terakhir]]
[[it:Giudizio Universale]]
[[he:יום הדין]]
[[sw:Kiyama]]
[[ku:Qiyamet]]
[[lt:Paskutinis teismas]]
[[ml:അന്ത്യന്യായവിധി]]
[[nl:Dag des oordeels]]
[[ja:最後の審判]]
[[kk:Қиямет]]
[[no:Dommens dag]]
[[pl:Sąd Ostateczny]]
[[pt:Juízo Final]]
[[ro:Judecata de Apoi]]
[[rm:Ultim giudizi]]
[[ru:Страшный суд]]
[[simple:Day of judgment]]
[[sk:Posledný súd (pojem)]]
[[sl:Sodni dan]]
[[sr:Страшни суд]]
[[sh:Sudnji dan]]
[[fi:Tuomiopäivä]]
[[sv:Yttersta domen]]
[[tr:Kıyamet günü]]
[[th:การพิพากษาครั้งสุดท้าย]]
[[uk:Страшний суд]]
[[zh:最后的审判]]</text>
      <sha1>ei3wrgab3nq9sfmokuv8qnl4xushmxm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
