<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>List of Jain temples</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7108808</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519647447</id>
      <parentid>519646697</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T21:51:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Puffin</username>
        <id>12846626</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>remove test images</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28361">{{cleanup|date=February 2011}}
{{dynamic list}}
{{Jainism}}
There are many [[Jainism|Jain]] [[Tirtha]] or pilgrimage sites throughout the [[Indian subcontinent]], many of which were built several hundred years ago. Many of these temples are classified according to [[Jainism#Sects|Jain sects]]. Many Jain Temples are found in other areas of the world. This article lists and documents prominent Jain temples and Tirthas around the world.

==India==

===Delhi===
[[File:Digambar Jain Lal Mandir, Chandni Chowk, Delhi.jpg|thumb|right|255px|[[Lal Mandir]] in [[Delhi]]]]

* Shri Digambar Jain Lal Mandir
* Naya Mandir
* Vaidwada Mandir
* Bada Mandir
* Shri Shantinath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Roop Nagar, Delhi - 110007
* Shri Jin Kushal Suri Jain Dadabari,(Chhoti Dadabari), R-Block, South Extension, Part-II, Opp. Ansal Plaza, Masjid Moth, New Delhi
* Shri Jin Dutt Suri Jain Dadabari &amp; Shri Aadinath Jain Mandir, Mehrauli, New Delhi
* Shri Vijay Vallabh Samarak &amp; Shri Vasupujya Swami Jain Shwetambar Mandir, P.O. Alipur, 24th km, G.T. Karnal Road, Delhi
* Shri Vasupujya Swami Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Rohini, Delhi
* Shri Sankheshwar Parshwnath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Naveen Shahadra, Delhi
* Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Gujarat Vihar, Delhi

===Uttarakhand===
'''Badrinath, District Chamoli'''
*Shri Ashtapad Digambar Jain Siddha Kshetra, Badrinath
Behind Bangad Dharmashala, At Post Badrinath, District Chamoli  

'Charan' of Lord Adinath have been installed here as a symbol of Kailash Parvat. Temple and Dharamshala are open from Akshay Tritiya to Sharad Pournima. Rest of the year everything is closed due to snowfall.  
Management  Trust: Shri Adinath adhyatmik Ashimsa Foundation, Indore.
President: Shri Pradeepkumar Kasliwal (0731 2413104)
Secretary: Shri Lalitkumar Badjatya (0731 - 2414104)
* Shri Chintamani Parshwnath Jain Shwetambar Tirth, Bhupatwala, Rishikesh Highway, Haridwar
* Shri Shantinath Swami Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Rishikesh

===Uttar Pradesh===
'''Hastinapur'''
*Digamber Jain Bada Mandir
*Jambudweep -  It is about 24 meter tall structure amidst the group of temples.
*Lotus Temple -  It is a small temple in the courtyard of Jambudweep. It is a House of Worship, popularly known as the Lotus Temple, is a Jain House of Worship and also a prominent attraction in Hastinapur. It was completed in 1989.
*Kailash Parvat - Its main building at the centre of the complex is a 131&amp;nbsp;ft (40 m)-high monument. There are 3 stages and 72 temples in this structue, 24 in each stage, representing the Tirthankaras of past, present, and future. Its height and location on the banks of the ravine of the once flowing Ganges River makes its presence felt from afar, and has ornamental detail spreading over the minutely carved ceilings, doorways, pillars, and panels. Many other new temples in its premises are still under construction.
* Ashtapad - It is the tallest (151&amp;nbsp;ft (46 m))brick structure in district Meerut. Maha pratishtha took place on 2 December 2009 under nishra of Gachhadipati Acharya Nityanand Surishwarji Maharaj. It has stone carvings and marble cutting on the topmost temple. The presiding deity is Shri Aadinath Bhagwan.
* Nishiaji - This is the place where footprints of Jain Tirthankaras are inscribed on marble stones.
* Shri Shantinath Jain Shwetambar Mandir &amp; Paarna Mandir, Hastinapur, District Meerut
* Bal-Aashram (Moolnayak Shri Mahavir Swami), Hastinapur, District Meerut

'''Bada Gaon, Bagpat'''
*Sri Parshwanath Digambar Temple- It is famous for a temple that houses an idol of Lord Parshvanath, the 23rd Tirthankara of Jainism. The idol was recovered from a local well, and the water of the well is reputed to have curative powers.

'''Varanasi'''
*Varanasi is the birthplace of four Tirthankars, namely, [[Suparshvanath]], [[Chandraprabha]], [[Shreyansanath]] and [[Parshvanath]].
*Bachraj Ghat Jain Temple
*Bhadaini ji Teerth Kshetra Jain Ghat Jain Temple
*Bhelupura Jain Temple
 
''' Sarnath '''
*Located 1 hour from Varanasi, Sarnath also features Jain temples.
*Digambara Jain Temple, Singhpura - Southwest of the Dhamekh Stupa, This Jain temple was built in 1824. According to belief, this is where Shreyanshnath, the 11th Jain tirthankara, was born.

'''Ghaziabad:'''
*Shri Digambar Jain Teerth Rishbhanchal [http://www.jainteerth.com/teerth/Rishabhanchal.asp%20Rishabhancha]- Vardhamanpuram, Near Village Moratha, Delhi-Meeruth Road, Ghaziabad (U.P.) Pin – 201001 Phone 0120-2788183, 2788428
*Parswanath Kavi Nagar Digamber Jain Mandir - It also has a Bird Hospital, a school and a full fledged Hospital run by Sakal Jain Samaj Ghaziabad.

'''Saharanpur:'''
*Shri Digambar Jain Temple, Jainbagh
*Shri Digambar Jain Temple, Awas Vikas

'''Sardhana:'''
* Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Sardhana

'''Ahikshetra, Bareilly:'''
*Shri Ahhichatra Parasvnath Tirthkshetra Digamber Jain Mandir - Ahichhatra has become a holy place (Kalyanak Kshetra) because of happening of two Kalyanaks viz. Tap kalyanak (penance) &amp; Gyan kalyanak (complete knowledge)of Bhagwan parsvanath. The word Ahichhatra has special meaning :- Ahi means &quot;serp&quot; - serpent &amp; Chhatra means &quot;covering&quot;. Actually it symbolizes the covering (Chhatra) provided by Dharnandra &amp; Padmavatimataji to Parsvnath ( during muni stage) at this place.
* Shri Parshwnath Jain Shwetambar Tirth, Ahichhatra

'''Moradabad:'''
* Shri Sumtinath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Civil Lines, Moradabad
* Shri Vijay Samudra Suri Ji Maharaj Samadhi, Delhi Road, Moradabad

'''Shrawasti:'''
* Jain Shwetambar Tirth, Shrawasti

'''Kaushambi:'''
* Jain Shwetambar Tirth, Kaushambi

'''Allahabad:'''
* Shri Aadinath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Purimtal, District Allahabad. (This is the place where Lord Aadinath, the first ''tirthankar''  attained ''Kewalgyan'', i.e. enlightenment)

===Haryana===
'''Gurgaon:'''
*Shri Parswanath Jain Mandir - Jain Petrol Supplying Company, Old Bus Stand, Hansi, Dist: Hissar, Haryana State, INDIA. Pin Code: 125033. Shikharbadh Jinalay. Phon No :: 016-63254006
*Shri Shantinath Jain Shwetambar Temple - Pratishtha held in 1995. The temple is run by Shri Atamnand Jain Shwetambar Shri Sangh, Sector-4, Gurgaon. The moolnayak bhagwan (presiding deity) of the temple/mandir is Shri Shantinath Bhagwan. The other gods in the temple are lord Jagvallabh Parashvnath, Lord Mahavir, Guru Gautam Swami, Padmawati Mata, Saraswati Mata and Manibhadra Veer Ji. The Mandir/temple also has a paasara which has a hall which can fit 200 people accompanied by 3-4 rooms.The temple compound also housed a charitable homeopathic dispensary with a qualified doctor. shri Shantinath jain Swetambar Temple/Mandir Sector 4, Gurgaon - 122001 Haryana India
*Shree Chandraprahu Digambar Jain, Prachin Aathishay Chetra - 500 Year Old mandir ji, nearby villages and in village jharsa have salty water but only in mandir ji premsis water like &quot;AMRIT &quot; is available. Address : Village Jharsa, ON National High 8 (Exit No. 9 ), Gurgaon, Haryana [http://www.jainmandirjharsa.com]

'''Ambala:'''
* Shri Suparshwnath Swami Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Halwai Bazar, Ambala City (more than 100 years old)
* Shri Shantinath Swami Jain Shwetambar MAndir, Jain Nagar, Ambala City
* Shri Chintamani Parshwnath Jain Shwetambar Mandir &amp; Shri Vijay Inderdinn Suri Ji Maharaj Samadhi, Behind Motor Market, G.T. Road, Ambala City
* Shri Vasupujya Swami Jain Shwetambar Mandir, 14-B, Preet Nagar, Near Mahesh Nagar, Opp. Kidzee Nursery School, Ambala Cantt
* Shri Digamber Jain Mandir - Gud Bazar, Ambala Cantt
* Shri Digamber Jain Lal Mandir - Mahesh Nagar, Ambala Cantt
* Shri Digamber Jain Mandir - Housing Board Colony, Ambala Cantt
* Shri Digamber Jain Mandir - Lal Kurti, Ambala Cantt
* Shri Digamber Jain Chaitalya - Mahesh Nagar, Ambala Cantt
* Shri Digamber Jain Mandir - Ambala City. Ambala City is Atishya kshetra where idol of Lord Vasupujya was found.

'''Yamunanagar:'''
* Shri Sumtinath Swami Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Yamunanagar
* Shri Aadinath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Sadhaura, District Yamunanagar
* Shri Mahavir Swami Jain Shweetambar Mandir, Jagadhri, District Yamunanagar

'''Faridabad:'''
* Shri Mahavir Swami Jain Shweetambar Mandir, Faridabad

'''Ranila:'''&lt;br /&gt;
Ranila is an Atishya kshetra where idol of first Jain Tirathankar Adinath was found by Ranjit Singh on the auspicious day of Dussehra. Ranila is located in Bhiwani District near Charkhi Dadri.

'''Hansi:'''&lt;br /&gt;
Hansi is an Atishya kshetra in Hissar District.

'''Kasan:'''&lt;br /&gt;
Kasan is an Atishya kshetra in Gurgaon District.

===Himachal Pradesh===
'''Kangra:'''
* Shri Aadinath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Opp. Kangra Fort, Kangra

===Punjab===
* Shri Parshwanath Jain Mandir, Village Vairowal, Distt. Tarn Taran. (The idols have now been transferred to Jain Shwetambar Temple, Kitchlu Nagar, Ludhiana)
* Shri Parshvanath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Sultanwind Road, Amritsar
* Shri Arnath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Amritsar
* Jain Digambar Mandir, Amritsar
* Jain Shwetamber Temple, Patti, District Amritsar
* Shri Aadinath Bhagwan Jain Shwetamber Temple, Jandiala Guru, District Amritsar
* Shri Vasupujya Swami Jain Shwetamber Temple, Hoshiarpur
* Shri Parshwnath Bhagwan Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Hoshiarpur
* Shri Munisuvrat Swami Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Jain Colony, Kangra Road, Hoshiarpur.
* Shri Sumtinath Swami Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Raikot
* Shri Kalikund Parshwnath Jain Shwetamber Temple, Daal Bazar, Ludhiana
* Shri Suparshwnath Swami Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Chaura Bazar, Ludhiana
* Shri Chintamani Parshwnath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Chawal Bazar, Ludhiana
* Shri Jagvallabh Parshwnath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Vijay Inder Nagar, Daba Road, Ludhiana
* Shri Aadinath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Civil Lines, Ludhiana
* Shri Kalyan Parshwnath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Kitchlu Nagar, Ludhiana
* Shri Vimalnath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Vallabh Colony, Shivpuri, Ludhiana
* Shri Aadinath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Hussainpura, Jalandhar Byepass, Ludhiana
* Shri Vimalnath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Mahavir Enclave, Ludhiana
* Shri Mahavir Swami Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Behind Radha Swami Satsang Ground, Hambran Road, Ludhiana
* Shri Mallinath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Jainpuram, Hambran Road, Ludhiana
* Shri Munisuvrat Swami Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Near Vardhman Spinning Mills, Chandigarh Road, Ludhiana
* Shri Vijay Vallabh Samadhi Mandir, Basant Road, Civil Lines, Ludhiana
* Shri Jain Dadabari, 70-Feet Road, Sunder Nagar, Ludhiana
* Shri Chintamani Parshwnath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Zira, District Ferozepur
* Shri Vijyanand Suri Ji Maharaj Janam Sthali, Lehra, Zira, District Ferozepur
* Shri Godi Ji Parshwnath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Jalandhar
* Shri Munisuvrat Swami Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Kapurthala
* Shri Aadinath Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Rupnagar (Ropar)
* Shri Aadinath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Gardhiwala, District Hoshiarpur
* Shri Parshwnath Swami Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Malerkotla, District Sangrur
* Shri Dharamnath Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Nakodar, District Jalandhar
* Shri Phoolchand Ji Maharaj Samadhi, Jagraon
* Jain Shwetamber Mandir, Batala, District Gurdaspur
* Shri Mahavir Swami Jain Shwetambar Mandir, Sector-28, Chandigarh
* Mata Chakreshwari Devi Jain Shwetambar Tirth &amp; Aadinath Jain Mandir, Sirhind, District Fatehgarh Sahib
* Jain Digambar Temple, Patiala, named (Shri Digamber Jain Mandir Patiala)
* Shri 1008 Lord Mahavir Digamber Jain Shikhar Baddh Mandir is located at Baba Deep Singh Nagar, Badi Nadi Pul, Patiala.

===Jharkhand===
* [[Shri Sammet Shikharji]], one of the holiest Jain pilgrimage, where 20 of the 24 tirthankars attained ''nirwaan'' (final freedom from the vicious cycle of birth &amp; death). Madhuban, District Giridih
* Shri Jain Shwetambar Tirth, Rijubalika (place where Lord Mahavira, the 24th and the last of the ''tirthankars'' attained ''kewalgyan'', i.e. enlightenment)

[[File:Sheetalnath jain temple photo 1914.jpg|thumb|Sheetalnath Jain temple in Kolkata]]

===West Bengal===
* [[Kolkata]]-There are many shwetamber and digamber jain temples in kolkata. Main shwetamber temples are situated at Maniktala, 96,canning street,Bhawnipore,Tullapati derasar in Bada Bazar,Hanspukharia,Ramesh Mitra road,tollygunge etc.
* [[Howrah]]- Key shwetamber derasar in howrah are sri apartment,Mallik fatak.
* [[Asanso]]l-There is a jain temple in Asansol devoted to Vaasupujya Bhagwan.

===Orissa===
* [[Udayagiri and Khandagiri Caves]]
* [[Digambara Jaina Temple, Khandagiri]], [[Bhubaneswar]]
* [[Parsvanath Jain Temple-I]], Khandagiri, [[Bhubaneswar]]
* [[Parsvanath Jain Temple-II]], Khandagiri, [[Bhubaneswar]]

===Gujarat===
[[File:Palitana.jpg|thumb|right|255px|[[Palitana Tirtha]]]]

* [[Mahudi]], The Jain Tirth - Padmaprabhu Swami and [[Lord Ghantakarna Mahavir]]
* [[Hutheesing Jain Temple]]
* [[Songadh Tirtha]]
* [[Muchhal Mahavir Temple]]
* Pujya Shri Jinchandraji Maharaj – Bandhu Triputi&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://jinjimaharaj.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=36&amp;Itemid=55 |title=Bandhu Tirth}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Palitana Tirtha]], most visited Jain temple in [[Gujarat]].
* [[Girnar]]
* [[Vataman]]
* [[Hutheesing Jain Temple]]
* [[Shri Shankeshwar Tirth]]
* [[Taranga (Jain Temple)]]
* [[Khambhat]]
* [[Kalikund]]
* [[Vallabhpure Tirth]]
* [[Magarwada Jain Temple]]

===Maharashtra===
[[File:Shri 1008 Shantinath Digambar Jain Teerth.jpg|thumb|right|255px|Shri 1008 Shantinath Digambar Jain Mandir &amp; 27 feet Shri 1008 Munisuvratnath Bhagwan]]

* [[Ellora_Caves#The_Jain_caves|Ellora Jain Caves]]
* [[Mangi-Tungi]]
* [[Kumbhoj]]
* [http://www.dharmachakra.in Dharmachakra Prabhav Tirtha, Nasik]
* Katraj Tirth, Pune
* [[Jintur]]
* [[Shantinath Jain Teerth]]
* [[Kesapuri,Majalgaon]]
* [[Kachaner,Aurangabad]]
* [[Ter,Latur]]
* [[Shree Mahavirswami Jain Temple, Chembur]]
* [[Shri Adeshwar Swetambhar Jain Mandir Temple of Shri Adinath Tirthankara]]
* [[Shri Swasthishri jinashen math nandani. Shiroli, Kholapur, Maharastra]]

===Rajasthan===
[[File:Mahavirji Temple.JPG|thumb|right|255px|[[Shri Mahavirji Jain Temple]], [[Rajasthan]]]]
[[File:Jain Temple Ranakpur.jpg|thumb|right|255px|Ranakpur Jain temple in [[Ranakpur]], [[Rajasthan]]]]
[[File:Ajmer India.JPG|thumb|right|255px|[[Ajmer Jain Temple]], Rajasthan]]

* [[Pratapgarh, Rajasthan|Pratapgarh]] has many ancient temples, among them Bamotar Shantinath is very famous, located 4&amp;nbsp;km from pratapgarh,40&amp;nbsp;km from Mandsaur(M.P.),95&amp;nbsp;km From chittorgarh.vPrincipal idol is of Bhagwan Shantinath. Vist www.humadjainsamaj.com
* [[Dilwara Temples]], [[Mount Abu]], [[Rajasthan]]
* [[Ranakpur Jain Temple]], [[Ranakpur]], [[Rajasthan]]
* [[Nakoda]], Barmer, [[Rajasthan]]
* [[Shri Mahavirji]], [[Sawai Madhopur]], [[Rajasthan]]
* [[Chand Khedi]], [[Jhalawar]], [[Rajasthan]]
* [[Tijara Jain Temple]], [[Alwar]], [[Rajasthan]]
* Golden Temple, the first Jain Temple in India to be covered by gold.[[Falna]], [[Rajasthan]]
* [[Osian, Jodhpur|Osian]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.shriosiyamataji.org/mahavirswamitemplehistory.html |title=Osiya Jain Temple}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sanganer]] (Sanghiji) The ancient Digamber Jain temple in Sanganer,is 14&amp;nbsp;km from Jaipur. The principal idol in the Sanghiji Temple is of Lord Adinath in the Padmasan (seated) posture. The whole of the temple is made of red stone with attractive images carved.
* [[Padampura]]
* Shri Chintamani Parswanath Jain Tample at Barmer Rajasthan.
* Shri Vimalnath Jain Tample at Rawali Gali, Balotra, Dist Barmer, Rajasthan.Shri Mahaveerji Jain Temple, Barmer.
* [[Shri Chintamani Jain Temple Bagol]]
* [[Andeshwar Parshwanath]]
* [[Soniji Ki Nasiyan]] ([[Ajmer Jain Temple]])
* [[Nareli Jain Temple]]
* [[Rishabhdeo]] Jain Temple

===Madhya Pradesh===
* [[Sarvodaya Digamber Jain Temple]], [[Amarkantak]]
* [[Bawangaja]]
* [[Gwalior]]'s fort is home to dozens of historical large size  Jain rock-cut sculptures,The Gopachal tirth.
* [[Sonagiri]], about 60&amp;nbsp;km from Gwalior, has scores of temples of 9th&amp;10th century on little hills.
* [[Bajrangadh]], [[Atisaya-kshetra]] in [[Guna]] district in [[Madhya Pradesh]], [[India]]
* [[Kundalpur]]
* Nageshwar Parshavanâtha Tirtha Near Ratlam MadhyaPradesh has a very big idol of Tirthankara Parshavanath.
* [[Maksi]]
* [[Mohankheda]]
* Nandishwardeep (Madiyaji), Jabalpur is the profound and amazing temples in Central India in Modern times.
* [[Jain temples of Khajuraho]]
* [[Paporaji]]
* [[Aharji]] is 17&amp;nbsp;km from district Tikamgarh(MP).
* [[Indore#Gommat_Giri|Gommat Giri]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://indore-travel-agents.com/indore-attractions/gomatgiri-indore.html|title=Gomat Giri Indore}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Indore]]
* [[BanediaJi]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jainteerth.com/teerth/Banediaji.asp|title=Banedia Jain Mandir}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Tehsil Depal-Pur, Dist. Indore (M.P.) Pin. 453115 Phone 07322-220231
*[[Siddhwarkoot]] Jain Siddh Kshetra at the banks of the river Reva, about 110&amp;nbsp;km from Indore.
Sidhwarkoot (Jain Tirth) 
Shri Siddhaverkoot is an ancient sacred. Siddha Kshetra surrounded by a series of hills full of natural beauty. From this place two Chakravarties, ten Kamdeos and three &amp; half crores of ascetic saints achieved the salvation,full &amp; finel freedom from world to enjoy the spiritual bliss for indefinite time.This place is situated on a plane on the top of a hill. Important of this place is described in Nirvankand.

===Karnataka===
[[File:1000-Pillar-Temple-Moodbidri-Left-Side-View.JPG|thumb|right|255px|[[Saavira Kambada Basadi]] in [[Moodbidri]], [[Karnataka]]]]

* [[Shravanabelagola]], a monumental statue of Saint Gomateshwar in [[Hassan district]], [[Karnataka]].
* [[Moodabidri]], Thousand Pillars Temple ([[Saavira Kambada Basadi]]) [[Dakshina Kannada]] district, [[Karnataka]].
* [[Karkala]], 1.Hiriyangadi Basadi 2.Chathurmukha Basadi 3.Padmavathi Kere Basadi in [[Udupi]] district, [[Karnataka]]. The famous single stone 42-feet (13 m) statue Gomateshwara (Lord Bahubali) is located about 1&amp;nbsp;km from the center of the town and is the second tallest in Karnataka .
* Vaaranga - This is an important Jain centre. The kere basadi is located in midst of a lake. There are many other basadis too.
* [[Venur]], a 35-feet Gomateshwara in [[Dakshina Kannada]] District, [[Karnataka]].
* [[Sargur]] in [[Mysore district]]
* [[Humcha]]
* Shri Shantisagar ashram shedbal, taluk: Athani, District :Belgaum.

===Kerala===
* [[Anantnath Swami Temple]] (also known as the '''Puliyarmala Jain Temple''') in Puliyarmala, outside of [[Kalpetta]] in  [[Wayanad district]], [[Kerala]].
* [[Chandra Prabhu Temple]] in Mattancherry, Kochi City, has recently been renovated by special Jain temple architect's. Kochi has a population of about 1500 Jains.

===Andhra Pradesh===
* [[Kulpakji]]
* Hrinmkar Teerth (Opp Nagarjuna University, on Highway ov Vijaywad-Guntur, [[Namburu]] Guntur District, Andhra Pradesh)

===Tamil Nadu===
[[File:Mel Sithamur Jain Math, Tamil Nadu.JPG|thumb|right|255px|[[Mel Sithamur Jain Math]], the residence of [[Bhattaraka Laxmisena]]]]
[[File:Thirakoil-mahaaveerar.JPG|thumb|right|255px|[[Thirakoil]] Hill and the Digambara Jain Temple]]
[[File:Mannargudi Mallinatha Swamy Temple.png|thumb|right|255px|[[Mannargudi Mallinatha Swamy Jain Temple]]]]
[[File:Upper Temple Complex at Tirumalai.jpg|thumb|right|255px|[[Arahanthgiri Jain Math]]]]
[[File:Karandai Digambar Jain Temple.jpg|thumb|right|255px|Karandai Digambar Jain Temple]]
[[File:Thirupanamur Digambar Jain Temple.jpg|thumb|right|255px|Thirupanamur Digambar Jain Temple]]
[[File:Ponnur Hils.jpg|thumb|right|255px|Ponnur Hils]]

Puja is done in the following old (built several centuries ago) and new (built in the last 100 years) Tamil Digambara Jain temples (in Alphabetical order):
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2&quot;&gt;
*Aadhinath Jain Temple, [[Cuddalore]] (old)
*Anumanthakudi, [[Sivagangai]] dt.(new)
*Adambakkam, [[Chennai]] Dt. (New)
*Agalur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Alagramam, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*[[Arahanthgiri Jain Math]], [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Arani (S.V.Nagaram), [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Arani (Pudukamur), [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*Arani (Saidapet), [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*Arani (Palayam), [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*Arani (Kosapalayam) [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*Arungulam [[Kanchipuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Arpaakkam, [[Kanchipuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Arugavur, Solai, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*[[Avadi]], [[Chennai]] Dt.(New)
*Ayalavadi, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*Cheyyar, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*Deepangudi, [[Nagapattinam]] Dt. (Old)
*Easaakolathur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Elangadu, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Eyyil, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Erumbur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt.(Old)
*[[George Town, Chennai|George Town]], [[Chennai]] Dt. (New)
*Gingee, [[Viluppuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Ilayangudi, [[Sivagangai]] Dt/ (New)
*Kannalam, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Kallapuliyur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Kallakullathur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. {old}
*Karanthai, [[Kanchipuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Karanthai, [[Thanjavur]] Dt. (Old)
*Keezh Villivanam, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Kilsathamangalam,  [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Koliyanur, Villupuram Dt.(Old)
*Kolathur, [[Chennai]] Dt. (New)
*Kovilampoondi, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt (Old)
*[[Kumbakonam]], [[Thanjavur]] Dt. (Old)
*[[Mannargudi Mallinatha Swamy Jain Temple]], [[Nagapattinam]] Dt. (Old)
*Melapandal, [[Vellore]] Dt. (New)
*Melmalaiyanur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*[[Mel Sithamur Jain Math]], [[Villupuram]] Dt.
*Mettu Street, [[Kanchipuram]] (New)
*Mudalur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Nallur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*[[Nanganallur]], [[Chennai]] Dt. (New)
*Naval, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Nedimolliyanur [[Villupuram]] Dt. {old}
*Nelliyankulam, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Othalavaadi, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*[[Pammal]], [[Chennai]] (New)
*Peranamallur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt (Old)
*Perani, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Periyakozhappalur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Perumandur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Perumbogai, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Ponnur Malai, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*[[Puzhal]], [[Chennai]] Dt. (New)
*Renderipet, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*R.Kunnathur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*Sathuvachari, [[Vellore]] Dt. (New)
*Sevur, [[Vellore]] Dt. (Old)
*Sitharaal, [[Nagercoil]] Dt. (Old)
*[[Sittanavasal]], [[Pudukottai]] Dt. (Old)
*Sitthamur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Oldest jain temple and Jain math)
*Somaasipadi, [[Thiruvannamalai]] (New)
*Thirunarunkundram, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Thiruparuthikundram, [[Kanchipuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Thirupanamoor, [[Kanchipuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Thachambadi, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Thatchur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Thayanur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
* [[Thirakoil]], Thiruvannamalai Dt. (Old)
* [[Jain sculpture in Thirupparankunram, Madurai, India|Thirupparankunram]], [[Madurai]] Dt.(Sangam literature Paripadal 19 step 51)
*[[Thiruvannamalai]], [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (New)
*Thondur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Tindivanam, [[Villupuram]] Dt (New)
*[[Valathi]] / Valathy, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*[[Vandavasi]], [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)
*Valapandal [[Vellore]] Dt. (Old)
*Veedur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Veeranamur, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Vellimedupettai, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Vempoondi, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Venbakkam, [[Kanchipuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Vizhukkam, [[Villupuram]] Dt. (Old)
*Vijayamangalam, [[Erode]] Dt. (Old)
*Virudur, [[Thiruvannamalai]] Dt. (Old)

==Pakistan==

===Punjab===
[[Image:SirkapJainTemple.JPG|thumb|An ancient Jain temple at [[Sirkap]], part of the [[Indo-Greek]] kingdom, near modern day [[Taxila]], [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]], [[Pakistan]]]]
* Jain [[Shwetambar]] Temple with [[Shikhar]],  Thari [[Bhabra|Bhabrian]] Lahore City.
* Jain [[Digambar]] Temple with Shikhar, Thari Bhabrian Lahore City.
* Jain Shwetambar Dada Wadi (Mini Temple), Guru Mangat in Lahore Cantt., foot prints in stone.
* Jain Digambar Temple with Shikhar, Old Anarkali Jain Mandir Chawk&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2007%5C06%5C01%5Cstory_1-6-2007_pg13_6 TEPA to remodel roads leading to Jain Mandir Chowk&lt;/ref&gt;: This temple was destroyed in the riots of 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/2546373.stm | work=BBC News | first=Aamir | last=Ghauri | title=Demolishing history in Pakistan | date=5 December 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Now an Islamic school is run in the former temple{{coord|31.561389|74.308056|region:PK_type:landmark_scale:2000_source:wikimapia}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wikimapia.org/#y=31561389&amp;x=74308056&amp;z=18&amp;l=0&amp;m=h&amp;v=2 Wikimapia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://jainsamaj.org/temples/pakistan.htm LIST OF JAIN TEMPLES IN PAKISTAN&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sindh===
* Jain Temple, [[Nagarparkar]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2009%5C05%5C04%5Cstory_4-5-2009_pg12_8 A ravaged Jain temple corroding away with time], Daily Times (Pakistan)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Jain Temple, [[Godiji|Gori]], original site of Godiji Parshwanath
* Jain Shwetamber Temple with Shikhar, Ranchod Line, [[Karachi]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Jain temples in Pakistan&quot;&gt;[http://www.jainworld.com/jaintemples/pakistan_temples.asp List of Jain temples in Pakistan], Jain World&lt;/ref&gt;
* Jain Shwetamber Temple, [[Hyderabad, Sindh|Hyderabad]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Jain temples in Pakistan&quot;/&gt;

== Jain Temples outside the Indian subcontinent==
There are several Jain temples in various countries outside the Indian subcontinent.

===Australia===
* Jain Temple, Melbourne&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.melbournejainsangh.org/contact-us/website-feedback.html |title=Melbourne Jain Sangh}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Jain Temple, Sydney - Lidcombe( Between Strathfield and Parramatta suburb)

===Belgium===
[[File:Templejaindanvers.jpg|thumb|right|255px|[[Antwerp Jain temple]] in Antwerp, Belgium]]

* [[Antwerp Jain Temple]] in [[Wilrijk]], Belgium.

===Canada===
* The Jain Society of Toronto has a Swethambar/Digambar temple in Toronto - www.jsotcanada.org
* Digambar Temple Shri Jain Mandir in Toronto.  247 Park Lawn Rd

===Hong Kong===
* [[Tsim Sha Tsui]], Hong Kong

===Japan===
* [[Jainism in Japan|Kobe]], Japan

===Kenya===
* The Oshwal Mahajanwadi located in Nairobi, Kenya.  The temple houses statues of 9 of the 24 [[Tirthankara]].
* Oshwal Centre in Nairobi, Kenya
* Mumuksh Mandal Digmabar Jain Mandir in Nairobi, Kenya
* Mombasa Derasar in Mombasa, Kenya

===Malaysia===
* Ipoh, Pera

* First Shikhar Bandhi Jain Deraser (Temple) dedicated to Shree Chintamani Parshvanath Bhagawan, Mata Padamavati Devi &amp; Mataji Sarasvati Devi in Ipoh

===Nepal===
* Jain Temple, Kathmandu

===Singapore===
* Jain Temple 18 Jalan Yasin, Singapore&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sjrs.org.sg/?page_id=80|title=SINGAPORE JAIN RELIGIOUS SOCIETY}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tanzania===
* Shree Jain Sangh in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania
* Zanzibar Derasar in Zanzibar, Tanzania

===UAE===
*[[Jain Temple Dubai]]

===United Kingdom===
[[File:The Jain Centre on Oxford Street - geograph.org.uk - 1034296.jpg|thumb|right|255px|The Jain Centre on Oxford Street, [[London]]]]

* The Jain Temple at 64-68 Colindale Avenue, London NW9 5DR is situated in the ''[[Jain Centre]]'' whose mission is improvement of spiritual and physical quality of life of Jain and wider communities.
* The Oshwal Centre located in Potters Bar, UK.  The temple is surrounded by landscaped gardens, statues of the 24 [[Tirthankara]], and 54 Otla representing the villages in India that the [[Visa Oshwal]] community originated from.
* The Jain temple in Leicester (UK) 32 Oxford Street,  Leicester     LE1 5XU
* The Jain temple at Harrow (London, UK) (digambar) 1 The Broadway Wealdstone Harrow  HA3 7EH
* The Jain temple at Kenton (UK) (ghar-derasar)557 Kenton Road  Kenton   Harrow    Middx HA3 9RS
* The Jain Temple at 99 Myrtle Road, Hounslow, Middx Near Asda, London UK (Digambar)
jainsamaj manchester www.jainsamajmanchester.org

===United States===
[[File:Jain Temple -02 by Jain Center of Greater Phoenix (JCGP).jpg|thumb|right|255px|[[Jain Center of Greater Phoenix]] (JCGP) in [[Phoenix, Arizona]]]]
* [[Siddhachalam]], New Jersey, USA
* [[Jain Center of America]]
* [[Jain Center of Greater Phoenix]]
* [http://www.jsgatemple.org Jain Society of Greater Atlanta]
* Jain Society of Greater Detroit,  Farmington Hills,  Michigan

==See also==
{{portal|Jainism}}
* [[Jain Temple]]
* [[Tirtha]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Jainism topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Jain Temples}}
[[Category:Jain temples and tirthas|*]]
[[Category:Jainism-related lists]]

[[hi:प्रमुख जैन तीर्थ]]</text>
      <sha1>ev1mhlmavkcpdgb1lrti7h7k97zal0b</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
