<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Manichaeism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19760</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520088978</id>
      <parentid>518935276</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T09:11:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>61.86.139.79</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The World of Light */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="73361">{{gnosticism}}
'''Manichaeism''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|m|æ|n|ɨ|k|iː|ɪ|z|əm}};&lt;ref&gt;{{OED|manichaeism}}&lt;/ref&gt;
in [[Modern Persian]] {{lang|fa-Arab|آیین مانی}} ''Āyin e Māni''; {{zh|c={{linktext|摩|尼|教}}|p={{linktext|Mó|ní |Jiào}}}}) was a major [[Gnosticism|gnostic]] [[religion]], originating in [[Sassanid Persia|Sassanid]] era [[Babylonia]]. Although most of the original writings of the founding [[prophet]] [[Mani (prophet)|Mani]] (in [[Persian language|Persian]]: مانی, [[Syriac]]: {{lang|syr-Syrc|ܡܐܢܝ}}, [[Latin]]: Manichaeus or Manes) (c. AD 216–276) have been lost, numerous translations and fragmentary texts have survived.

''Manichaean'' as used in contemporary popular discourse refers to someone who sees the world as a struggle between Good and Evil (see Figurative Use, below).

Manichaeism taught an elaborate [[cosmology]] describing the struggle between a good, spiritual world of light, and an evil, material world of darkness. Through an ongoing process which takes place in human history, light is gradually removed from the world of matter and returned to the world of light from which it came. Its beliefs were based on local [[Mesopotamian]] gnostic and religious movements,&lt;ref&gt;Widengren, Geo ''Mesopotamian elements in Manichaeism (King and Saviour II): Studies in Manichaean, Mandaean, and Syrian-gnostic religion'', Lundequistska bokhandeln, 1946.&lt;/ref&gt;

Manichaeism as a [[syncretistic]] form of oriental Christianity was quickly successful and spread far through the Aramaic-Syriac speaking regions,&lt;ref name=&quot;BeDuhnMirecki2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Jason BeDuhn|author2=Paul Allan Mirecki|title=Frontiers of Faith: The Christian Encounter With Manichaeism in the Acts of Archelaus|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=JQd8b5s5QBUC&amp;pg=PA6|accessdate=27 August 2012|year=2007|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-16180-1|pages=6–}}&lt;/ref&gt; it thrived between the third and seventh centuries, and at its height was one of the most widespread religions in the world. Manichaean churches and scriptures existed as far east as [[China]] and as far west as the [[Roman Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Welburn, ''Mani, the Angel and the Column of Glory: An Anthology of Manichaean Texts'' (Edinburgh: Floris Books, 1998), p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; It was widespread among the [[Roman legion|legions]] of the Roman Empire, who considered it a soldier's religion, and it was briefly the main rival to [[Christianity]] in the competition to replace classical [[paganism]]. Manichaeism survived longer in the East than in the West, and it appears to have finally faded away after the 14th century in southern China,&lt;ref&gt;[[Jason BeDuhn|Jason David BeDuhn]] ''The Manichaean Body: In Discipline and Ritual'' Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press. 2000 republished 2002 p.IX&lt;/ref&gt; contemporary to the decline in China of the [[Church of the East]] – see [[Ming Dynasty]].

An adherent of Manichaeism is called, especially in older sources&lt;ref&gt;Such as the Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers First Series, ed. Philip Schaff, writing of Augustine&lt;/ref&gt; a ''Manichee''. The religion is also referred to as Manicheanism (or Manichaeanism) and its adherents as ''Manicheans'' (or ''Manichaeans'').  By extension, the term &quot;manichean&quot; is widely applied (often disparagingly) as an adjective to a philosophy or attitude of moral [[dualism]], according to which a moral course of action involves a clear (or simplistic) choice between good and evil, or as a noun to people who hold such a view.

==History==
===Life of Mani===
[[File:Manicheans.jpg|thumb|Manichaean priests, writing at their desks. Manuscript from [[Gaochang|Khocho]], [[Tarim Basin]].]]
{{main|Mani (prophet)}}
Mani, an [[Arsacid]] Iranian by birth,&lt;ref&gt;1) Mary Boyce, &quot;Zoroastrians: their religious beliefs and practices&quot;, Routledge, 2001.  pg 111: &quot;He was Iranian, of noble Parthian blood...&quot; 2) Warwick Ball, &quot;Rome in the East: the transformation of an empire &quot;, Routledge, 2001.  pg 437: &quot;Manichaeism was a syncretic religion, proclaimed by the Iranian Prophet Mani.. 3) Sundermann, Werner, &quot;Mani, the founder of the religion of Manicheism in the 3rd century CE&quot;, Encyclopaeia Iranica, 2009. Sundermann [http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/mani-founder-manicheism summarizes the available sources] thus: ''&quot;According to the Fehrest, Mani was of Arsacid stock on both his father’s and his mother’s sides, at least if the readings al-ḥaskāniya (Mani’s father) and al-asʿāniya (Mani’s mother) are corrected to al-aškāniya and al-ašḡāniya (ed. Flügel, 1862, p. 49, ll. 2 and 3) respectively. The forefathers of Mani’s father are said to have been from Hamadan and so perhaps of Iranian origin (ed. Flügel, 1862, p. 49, 5–6). The Chinese Compendium, which makes the father a local king, maintains that his mother was from the house Jinsajian, explained by Henning as the Armenian Arsacid family of Kamsarakan (Henning, 1943, p. 52, n. 4 = 1977, II, p. 115). Is that fact, or fiction, or both? The historicity of this tradition is assumed by most, but the possibility that Mani’s noble Arsacid background is legendary cannot be ruled out (cf. Scheftelowitz, 1933, pp. 403–4). In any case, it is characteristic that Mani took pride in his origin from time-honored Babel, but never claimed affiliation to the Iranian upper class.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; was born AD 216 in [[Mesopotamia]] (Iraq), which was ruled by Persia,&lt;ref name=&quot;Coyle2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John Kevin Coyle|title=Manichaeism and Its Legacy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wnFz3tI0qOwC&amp;pg=PR13|accessdate=27 August 2012|date=15 September 2009|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-17574-7|pages=13–}}&lt;/ref&gt; then within the [[Sassanid Empire]] province of [[Asuristan]]. According to the [[Cologne Mani-Codex]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Mani-Kodex&quot;&gt;L. Koenen and C. Römer, eds., ''Der Kölner Mani-Kodex. Über das Werden seines Leibes. Kritische Edition,'' (Abhandlung der Reinisch-Westfälischen Akademie der Wissenschaften: Papyrologica Coloniensia '''14''') (Opladen, Germany) 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; Mani's parents were members of the religious sect of [[Elcesaites]]. The king of Persia put him to death in 274 or 277.&lt;ref name=&quot;Coyle2009&quot;/&gt;

Mani believed that the teachings of Buddha, Zoroaster, and Jesus were incomplete, and that his revelations were for the entire world, calling his teachings the &quot;Religion of Light.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coyle2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John Kevin Coyle|title=Manichaeism and Its Legacy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wnFz3tI0qOwC&amp;pg=PR13|accessdate=27 August 2012|date=15 September 2009|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-17574-7|pages=13–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Manichaean writings indicate that Mani received revelations when he was 12 and again when he was 24, and over this time period he grew dissatisfied with the Elchasaite sect he was born into.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reeves1996&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John C. Reeves|title=Heralds of That Good Realm: Syro-Mesopotamian Gnosis and Jewish Traditions|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ewM1xTuRQaoC&amp;pg=PA6|accessdate=27 August 2012|year=1996|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-10459-4|pages=6–}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Mani began preaching at an early age and was possibly influenced by contemporary Babylonian-Aramaic movements such as [[Mandaeanism]], and Aramaic translations of Jewish apocalyptic writings similar to those found at [[Qumran]] (such as the [[book of Enoch]] literature). With the discovery of the Mani-Codex, it also became clear that he was raised in a Jewish-Christian baptism sect, the [[Elcesaites]], and was influenced by their writings as well. According to biographies preserved by [[Ibn al-Nadim]] and the Persian polymath [[al-Biruni]], he allegedly received a revelation as a youth from a spirit, whom he would later call his ''Twin'' (Aramaic ''Tauma'' (תאומא), from which is also derived the name of the [[apostle Thomas]], the &quot;twin&quot;), his ''Syzygos'' (Greek for &quot;partner&quot;, in the [[Cologne Mani-Codex]]), his Double, his Protective Angel or 'Divine Self'. It taught him truths which he developed into a religion. His 'divine' Twin or true Self brought Mani to [[Self-realization]] and thus he became a 'gnosticus', someone with divine knowledge and liberating insight. He claimed to be the '[[Paraclete]] of the Truth', as promised in the [[New Testament]].

Mani composed seven writings, six of which were written in Syriac Aramaic. The seventh, the [[Shabuhragan]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Shabuhragan&quot;&gt;Middle Persian Sources: D. N. MacKenzie, ''Mani’s Šābuhragān'', pt. 1 (text and translation), BSOAS 42/3, 1979, pp. 500–34, pt. 2 (glossary and plates), BSOAS 43/2, 1980, pp. 288–310.&lt;/ref&gt; was written by Mani in [[Middle Persian]] and presented by him to the contemporary King of [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid Persia]], [[Shapur I]] in the Persian capital of [[Ctesiphon]]. Although there is no proof [[Shapur I]] was a Manichaean, he tolerated the spread of Manicheanism and refrained from persecuting it in his empire's boundaries.&lt;ref&gt;Welburn (1998), pp. 67–68&lt;/ref&gt; According to one tradition it was Mani himself who invented the unique version of the Syriac script called [[Manichaean script]], which was used in all of the Manichaean works written within the Persian Empire, whether they were in Syriac or Middle Persian, and also for most of the works written within the [[Uyghur Empire]]. The primary language of Babylon (and the administrative and cultural language of the Sassanid Empire) at that time was [[Middle Aramaic|Eastern Middle Aramaic]], which included three main dialects: [[Jewish Babylonian Aramaic|Judeo-Aramaic]] (the language of the [[Babylonian Talmud|Talmud]]), [[Mandaic language|Mandaean Aramaic]] (the language of the [[Mandaeism|Mandaean religion]]), and [[Syriac|Syriac Aramaic]], which was the language of Mani, as well as of the [[Syriac Christianity|Syriac Christians]]. &quot;[[Mani (name)|Mani]]&quot; is a [[Sanskrit]] name used in all three Aramaic dialects and therefore common among their speakers.

Manichaeism's views on Jesus are described by historians: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Jesus in Manichaeism possessed three separate identities (1) Jesus the Luminous, (2) Jesus the Messiah and (3) Jesus patibilis (the suffering Jesus).  (1) As Jesus the Luminous… his primary role was as supreme revealer and guide and it was he who woke Adam from his slumber and revealed to him the divine origins of his soul and its painful captivity by the body and mixture with matter.  Jesus the Messiah was a historical being who was the prophet of the Jews and the forerunner of Mani.  However, the Manicheans believed he was wholly divine.  He never experienced human birth as notions of physical conception and birth filled the Manichaeans with horror and the Christian doctrine of virgin birth was regarded as equally obscene.  Since he was the light of the world, where was this light, they asked, when he was in the womb of the Virgin?  (2) Jesus the Messiah was truly born at his baptism as it was on that occasion that the Father openly acknowledged his sonship.  The suffering, death and resurrection of this Jesus were in appearance only as they had no salvific value but were an exemplum of the suffering and eventual deliverance of the human soul and a prefiguration of Mani’s own martyrdom.  (3) The pain suffered by the imprisoned Light-Particles in the whole of the visible universe, on the other hand, was real and immanent.  This was symbolized by the 'mystic placing of the Cross whereby the wounds of the passion of our souls are set forth'.  On this mystical Cross of Light was suspended the Suffering Jesus (Jesus patibilis) who was 'the life and salvation of Man.'  This mystica cruxificio was present in every tree, herb, fruit, vegetable and even stones and the soil.  This constant and universal suffering of the captive soul is exquisitely expressed in one of the Coptic Manichaean psalms&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Manichaeism in the Later Roman Empire and Medieval China |first=Samuel N. C. |last=Lieu |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=hmNPz9teHqUC&amp;pg=PA161&amp;lpg=PA161&amp;dq=manichaeism+divinity+of+Jesus&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=DjJL3EMb8&amp;sig=zr9qj61_o4AnjtHh_oPhlfxFrJU&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dzQxT8eJOIrhggeIxe2XBQ&amp;ved=0CCAQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=manichaeism%20divinity%20of%20Jesus&amp;f=false |publisher= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Historians also note that Mani declared himself to be an &quot;apostle of Jesus Christ&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=57nFeeC3GKoC&amp;pg=PA315&amp;lpg=PA315&amp;dq=Mani+declared+he+was+an+apostle+of+Jesus&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=7erIBHwh-n&amp;sig=zzHmK2OmpAzP9wiObnkscgk7jbo&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=flgxT7ylPIKxsAKE0-XsBg&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Mani%20declared%20he%20was%20an%20apostle%20of%20Jesus&amp;f=false |title=The Manichean Debate, by Saint Augustine (Bishop of Hippo) |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Manichaean tradition is also noted to have claimed that Mani was the reincarnation of different religious figures from Buddha, Lord Krishna, Zoroaster, and Jesus. 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Other than incorporating the symbols and doctrine of dominant religious traditions, Manichaeism also incorporated the symbols and deities of indigenous traditions, in particular the Hindu deity Ganesha into its fold, demonstrated by the image available in the article, Manichaean art and calligraphy by Hans-Joachim Klimkeit. Mani was allegedly claiming to be the reincarnation of the Buddha, Lord Krishna, Zoroaster and Jesus depending on the context in which he was carrying out his preachings. Such strategic claims fostered a spirit of toleration among the Manicheans and the other religious communities and this particular feature greatly assisted them in gaining the approval of authorities to practice in different regions along the [[Silk Road]].&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://silkspice.wordpress.com/2011/04/ |title=The movement of the Manichaean tradition along the Silk Road |publisher=Silkspice.wordpress.com |date=2011-04-05 |accessdate=2012-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Also academics note that since much of what is known about Manichaeism comes from later 10th and 11th Century CE Islamic historians like [[Al-Biruni]] and especially the Shia Muslim Persian historian [[Ibn al-Nadim]] (and his work Fihrist); &quot;Islamic authors ascribed to Mani the claim to be the Seal of the Prophets&quot; This topic is discussed by an Israeli academic [[Guy Stroumsa|Guy G. Stroumsa]]&lt;ref&gt; {{cite web |url=http://pluto.huji.ac.il/~stroumsa/publications.htm |title=stroumsa}} &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; {{cite web |url=http://pluto.huji.ac.il/~stroumsa/Seal.pdf |title=stroumsa pdf}} &lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:ManichaeanElectaeKocho10thCentury.jpg|thumb|Manichaean Electae, Kocho, 10th century.]]
Another source of Mani's scriptures was original Aramaic writings relating to the book of Enoch literature (see the [[Book of Enoch]] and the [[Second Book of Enoch]]), as well as an otherwise unknown section of the book of Enoch called the &quot;[[Book of Giants]]&quot;. This book was quoted directly, and expanded on by Mani, becoming one of the original six Syriac writings of the Manichaean Church.  Besides brief references by non-Manichaean authors through the centuries, no original sources of &quot;The Book of Giants&quot; (which is actually part six of the &quot;Book of Enoch&quot;) were available until the 20th century.

Scattered fragments of both the original Aramaic &quot;Book of Giants&quot; (which were analysed and published by [[Józef Milik]] in 1976)&lt;ref&gt;J. T. Milik, ed. and trans., ''The Books of Enoch: Aramaic Fragments of Qumran Cave 4'', Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1976.&lt;/ref&gt; and of the Manichaean version of the same name (analyzed and published by [[Walter Bruno Henning|W.B. Henning]] in 1943)&lt;ref name=&quot;Henning&quot;&gt;In: Henning, W.B., ''The Book of Giants&quot;, BSOAS,Vol. XI, Part 1, 1943, pp. 52–74.&lt;/ref&gt; were found with the discovery in the twentieth century of the [[Dead Sea Scrolls]] in the Judaean Desert and the Manichaean writings of the [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] Manichaean kingdom in [[Turpan]]. Henning wrote in his analysis of them:

&lt;blockquote&gt;It is noteworthy that Mani, who was brought up and spent most of his life in a province of the Persian empire, and whose mother belonged to a famous Parthian family, did not make any use of the Iranian mythological tradition. There can no longer be any doubt that the Iranian names of Sām, Narīmān, etc., that appear in the Persian and Sogdian versions of the Book of the Giants, did not figure in the original edition, written by Mani in the Syriac language.&lt;ref name=&quot;Henning&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

From a careful reading of the Enoch literature and the Book of Giants, alongside the description of the Manichaean myth, it becomes clear that the &quot;Great King of Glory&quot; of this myth (a being that sits as a guard to the world of light at the seventh of ten heavens in the Manichaean myth,&lt;ref&gt;See Henning, ''A Sogdian Fragment of the Manichaean Cosmogony'', BSOAS, 1948&lt;/ref&gt;) is identical with the King of Glory sitting on the heavenly throne in the Enoch literature. In the Aramaic book of Enoch, in the Qumran writings in general, and in the original Syriac section of Manichaean scriptures quoted by [[Theodore bar Konai]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Konai&quot;/&gt; he is called &quot;malka raba de-ikara&quot; (the great king of glory).

Noting Mani's travels to the [[Kushan Empire]] (several religious paintings in [[Bamyan City|Bamiyan]] are attributed to him) at the beginning of his proselytizing career, [[Richard Foltz]] postulates [[Buddhist]] influences in Manichaeism:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Buddhist influences were significant in the formation of Mani's religious thought. The transmigration of souls became a Manichaean belief, and the quadripartite structure of the Manichaean community, divided between male and female monks (the &quot;elect&quot;) and lay followers (the &quot;hearers&quot;) who supported them, appears to be based on that of the Buddhist [[sangha]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Richard Foltz]], ''Religions of the Silk Road'', Palgrave Macmillan, 2nd edition, 2010, p. 71 ISBN 978-0-230-62125-1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

While Manichaeism was spreading, existing religions such as [[Christianity]] and [[Zoroastrianism]] were gaining social and political influence. Although having fewer adherents, Manichaeism won the support of many high-ranking political figures. With the assistance of the [[Sassanid Empire|Persian Empire]], Mani began missionary expeditions. After failing to win the favour of the next generation of Persian royalty, and incurring the disapproval of the Zoroastrian clergy, Mani is reported to have died in prison awaiting execution by the Persian Emperor [[Bahram I]]. The date of his death is estimated at AD 276&amp;ndash;277.

===Later history===
[[File:ManichaeismSpread.jpg|left|thumb|The spread of Manichaeism (AD 300&amp;ndash; 500). Map reference: World History Atlas, Dorling Kindersly.]]
Manichaeism continued to spread with extraordinary speed through both the east and west. It reached Rome through the apostle Psattiq by AD 280, who was also in [[Egypt]] in 244 and 251. It was flourishing in the [[Fayum]] area of Egypt in AD 290. Manichaean monasteries existed in Rome in 312 A.D. during the time of the Christian [[Pope Miltiades]].

The spread and success of Manichaeism were seen as a threat to other religions, and it was widely persecuted in Hellenistic, [[Christianity|Christian]], [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrian]], [[Islam]]ic,&lt;ref&gt;Manichaeans were the original [[Zindīq]]s. See: Mahmood Ibrahim, ''Religious Inquisition as Social Policy: The Persecution of the 'Zanadiqa' in the Early Abbasid Caliphate'', in Arab Studies Quarterly (ASQ), Vol. 16, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Buddhist]] cultures.

In 291, persecution arose in the Persian empire with the murder of the apostle Sisin by [[Bahram II of Persia|Bahram II]], and the slaughter of many Manichaeans. In AD 296, [[Diocletian]] decreed against the Manichaeans: &quot;We order that their organizers and leaders be subject to the final penalties and condemned to the fire with their abominable scriptures&quot;, resulting in many martyrdoms in Egypt and North Africa (see ''[[Diocletian Persecution#Manichean persecution|Diocletian Persecution]]''). By AD 354, [[Hilary of Poitiers]] wrote that the Manichaean faith was a significant force in southern Gaul. In AD 381 Christians requested [[Theodosius I]] to strip Manichaeans of their civil rights. He issued a decree of death for Manichaean monks in AD 382.

[[File:Tiffany Window of St Augustine - Lightner Museum.jpg|thumb|[[Augustine of Hippo|St. Augustine]] was once a Manichaean.]]
[[Augustine of Hippo]] (AD 354–430) converted to [[Christianity]] from Manichaeism, in the year 387. This was shortly after the Roman Emperor [[Theodosius I]] had issued a decree of death for Manichaeans in AD 382 and shortly before he declared Christianity to be the only legitimate religion for the Roman Empire in 391. According to his ''[[Confessions (St. Augustine)|Confessions]],'' after nine or ten years of adhering to the Manichaean faith as a member of the group of &quot;hearers&quot;, Augustine became a [[Christian]] and a potent adversary of Manichaeism (which he expressed in writing against his Manichaean opponent [[Faustus of Mileve]]), seeing their beliefs that knowledge was the key to salvation as too passive and not able to effect any change in one's life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Catholic Online |url=http://www.catholic.org/saints/saint.php?saint_id=418 |title=Catholic Online |publisher=Catholic.org |date=1976-04-04 |accessdate=2012-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I still thought that it is not we who sin but some other nature that sins within us.  It flattered my pride to think that I incurred no guilt and, when I did wrong, not to confess it... I preferred to excuse myself and blame this unknown thing which was in me but was not part of me.  The truth, of course, was that it was all my own self, and my own impiety had divided me against myself. My sin was all the more incurable because I did not think myself a sinner.  (''Confessions, Book V, Section 10'')&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Some modern scholars have suggested that Manichaean ways of thinking influenced the development of some of Augustine's ideas, such as the nature of good and evil, the idea of hell, the separation of groups into elect, hearers, and sinners, and the hostility to the flesh and sexual activity.&lt;ref&gt;A. Adam, ''Das Fortwirken des Manichäismus bei Augustin''. In: ZKG (69) 1958, S. 1–25.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Augustine Confessiones.jpg|thumb|left|A 13th-century manuscript from Augustine's book VII of ''[[Confessions (St. Augustine)|Confessions]]'' criticizing Manichaeism.]]

How Manichaeism may have influenced Christianity continues to be debated. Manichaeism may have influenced the [[Bogomilism|Bogomils]], [[Paulicianism|Paulicians]], and [[Cathar]]s. However, these groups left few records, and the link between them and Manichaeans is tenuous. Regardless of its accuracy the charge of Manichaeism was levelled at them by contemporary orthodox opponents, who often tried to make contemporary heresies conform to those combatted by the church fathers. Whether the [[dualism]] of the Paulicians, Bogomils, and Cathars and their belief that the world was created by a Satanic [[demiurge]] were due to influence from Manichaeism is impossible to determine. The Cathars apparently adopted the Manichaean principles of church organization. [[Priscillian]] and his followers may also have been influenced by Manichaeism. The Manichaeans preserved many [[apocrypha]]l Christian works, such as the [[Acts of Thomas]], that would otherwise have been lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Runciman&quot;&gt;Runciman, Steven, ''The Medieval Manichee: a study of the Christian dualist heresy.'' Cambridge University Press, 1947.&lt;/ref&gt;

Manichaeism maintained a sporadic and intermittent existence in the west ([[Mesopotamia]], [[Africa]], [[Spain]], [[France]], North [[Italy]], the [[Balkans]]) for a thousand years, and flourished for a time in the land of its birth (Persia) and even further east in Northern [[India]], Western China, and [[Tibet]]. While it had long been thought that Manichaeism arrived in China only at the end of the seventh century, a recent archaeological discovery demonstrated that it was already known there in the second half of the sixth century.&lt;ref name=&quot;La Vaissiere&quot;&gt;La Vaissière, Etienne de, &quot;Mani en Chine au VIe siècle.&quot; Journal Asiatique, 293–1, 2005, p. 357–378.&lt;/ref&gt;

It was adopted by the [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] ruler [[Khagan]] Boku Tekin (AD 759&amp;ndash;780) in 763, and remained the state religion for about a century before the collapse of the [[Uyghur Empire|Uyghur empire]] in 840. In the east it spread along trade routes as far as [[Chang'an]], the capital of the [[Tang Dynasty]] in [[China]]. In the ninth century, it is reported that the Muslim [[Caliph]] [[Al-Ma'mun]] tolerated a community of Manichaeans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m2501/is_n2_v16/ai_16502939/pg_5/ | work=Arab Studies Quarterly | first=Mahmood | last=Ibrahim | title=Religious inquisition as social policy: the persecution of the 'Zanadiqa' in the early Abbasid Caliphate | year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[al-Mahdi]] persecuted the Manichaeans, establishing an inquisition to root out their &quot;heresy&quot;, even resorting to outright massacre against them.&lt;ref&gt;Irfan Shahîd, ''Byzantium and the Arabs in the fourth century'', 1984, p. 425.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Song Dynasty|Song]] and [[Yuan Dynasty|Yuan]] dynasties of China remnants of Manichaeanism continued to leave a legacy contributing to sects such as the [[Red Turbans]].

Manichaeism claimed to present the complete version of teachings that were corrupted and misinterpreted by the followers of its predecessors Adam, Zoroaster, Buddha and Jesus. Accordingly, as it spread, it adapted new deities from other religions into forms it could use for its scriptures. Its original Aramaic texts already contained stories of Jesus. When they moved eastward and were translated into Iranian languages, the names of the Manichaean deities (or angels) were often transformed into the names of [[Zoroastrian]] [[yazata]]s. Thus ''{{Unicode|Abbā dəRabbūṯā}} '' (&quot;The Father of Greatness&quot;, the highest Manichaean deity of Light), in [[Middle Persian]] texts might either be translated literally as ''pīd ī wuzurgīh'', or substituted with the name of the deity ''[[Zurvan|Zurwān]]''. Similarly, the Manichaean primal figure ''{{Unicode|Nāšā Qaḏmāyā}} '' &quot;The Original Man&quot; was rendered &quot;Ohrmazd Bay&quot;, after the Zoroastrian god [[Ahura Mazda]]. This process continued in Manichaeism's meeting with [[Chinese Buddhism]], where, for example, the original Aramaic ''karia'' (the &quot;call&quot; from the world of Light to those seeking rescue from the world of Darkness), becomes identified in the Chinese scriptures with [[Guan Yin]] ({{lang|mul-Hant|觀音}} or Avalokitesvara in Sanskrit, literally, &quot;watching/perceiving sounds [of the world]&quot;, the Chinese [[Bodhisattva]] of Compassion).

===Later movements accused of &quot;Neo-Manichaeism&quot;===
During the Middle Ages, several movements emerged which were collectively described as &quot;Manichaean&quot; by the Catholic Church, and persecuted as Christian heresies through the establishment, in 1184, of the [[Medieval Inquisition|Inquisition]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Guy Stroumsa|Stroumsa, Gedaliahu G.]], ''Anti-Cathar Polemics and the Liber de duobus principiis'', in B. Lewis and F. Niewöhner, eds., Religionsgespräche im Mittelalter (Wolfenbütteler Mittelalter-Studien, 4; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1992), 169-183, p. 170&lt;/ref&gt; They included the [[Cathar]] and [[Albigensian]] churches of Western Europe. Other groups sometimes referred to as &quot;neo-Manichaean&quot; were the [[Paulician]] movement, which arose in Armenia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11583b.htm |title=CATHOLIC ENCYCLOPEDIA: Paulicians |publisher=Newadvent.org |date=1911-02-01 |accessdate=2012-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Bogomils]] in Bulgaria.&lt;ref name=&quot;Runciman&quot;/&gt; An example of this usage can be found in the published edition of the Latin Cathar text, the ''Liber de duobus principiis'' (''Book of the Two Principles''), which was described as &quot;Neo-Manichaean&quot; by its publishers.&lt;ref&gt;Dondaine, Antoine. O.P. ''Un traite neo-manicheen du XIIIe siecle: Le Liber de duobus principiis, suivi d'un fragment de rituel Cathare'' (Rome: Institutum Historicum Fratrum Praedicatorum, 1939)&lt;/ref&gt; As there is no presence of Manichaean mythology or church terminology in the writings of these groups, there has been some dispute among historians as to whether these groups were descendants of Manichaeism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01267e.htm |title=CATHOLIC ENCYCLOPEDIA: Albigenses |publisher=Newadvent.org |date=1907-03-01 |accessdate=2012-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Hungarian people|Hungarian]] Christianity, traces of Manichaeism can be found both in Catholicism and in Protestant Christianity, Manichaeian symbols are present in folk art, in Protestant churches and even on the [[Holy Crown]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

==Manichean teaching and belief==
===General===

Mani's teaching dealt with the origin of evil,&lt;ref name=&quot;Coyle2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=John Kevin Coyle|title=Manichaeism and Its Legacy|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wnFz3tI0qOwC&amp;pg=PR14|accessdate=27 August 2012|date=15 September 2009|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-17574-7|pages=14–}}&lt;/ref&gt; by addressing a theoretical part of the [[problem of evil]] by denying the omnipotence of God and postulating two opposite powers. Manichaean theology taught a [[dualism|dualistic]] view of good and evil. A key belief in Manichaeism is that the powerful, though not omnipotent good power (God) was opposed by the semi-eternal evil power (Satan). Humanity, the world and the soul are seen as the byproduct of the battle between God's proxy, Primal Man, and Satan. The human person is seen as a battleground for these powers: the soul defines the person, but it is under the influence of both [[light]] and [[dark]]. This contention plays out over the world as well as the human body—neither the Earth nor the flesh were seen as intrinsically evil, but rather possessed portions of both [[light]] and [[dark]]. Natural phenomena (such as rain) were seen as the physical manifestation of this spiritual contention. Therefore, the Manichaean worldview explained the existence of evil with a flawed creation God took no role in forming and was the result of Satan striking out against God.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bevan, A. A. 1930&quot;&gt;Bevan, A. A. (1930). &quot;Manichaeism&quot;. ''[[Encyclopaedia of Religion and Ethics]], Volume VIII'' Ed. [[James Hastings]]. London&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cosmogony===
[[File:Museum für Indische Kunst Dahlem Berlin Mai 2006 066.jpg|thumb|[[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] Manichaean clergymen, wall painting from the Khocho ruins, 10th/11th century AD. Located in the Museum für Indische Kunst, Berlin-Dahlem.]]
Manichaeism presented an elaborate description of the conflict between the spiritual world of light and the material world of darkness. The beings of both the world of darkness and the world of light have names. There are numerous sources for the details of the Manichaean belief. There are two portions of Manichaean scriptures that are probably the closest thing to the original Manichaean writings in their original languages that will ever be available. These are the Syriac-Aramaic quotation by the [[Nestorian Christian]] [[Theodore bar Konai]], in his Syriac &quot;Book of [[Scholia]]&quot; (&quot;''Ketba de-Skolion''&quot;, eighth century),&lt;ref name=&quot;Konai&quot;/&gt; and the Middle Persian sections of Mani's [[Shabuhragan]] discovered at [[Turpan]] (a summary of Mani's teachings prepared for [[Shapur I]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Shabuhragan&quot;/&gt;). These two sections are probably the original Syriac and Middle Persian written by Mani.

From these and other sources, it is possible to derive an almost complete description of the detailed Manichaean vision&lt;ref&gt;A completely sourced description (built around bar-Khoni's account, with additional sources), is found in: Jonas, Hans ''The Gnostic Religion'', 1958, Ch. 9: ''Creation, World History, Salvation According to Mani''.&lt;/ref&gt; (a complete list of Manichaean deities is outlined below). According to Mani, the unfolding of the universe takes place with three &quot;creations&quot;:

'''The First Creation''': Originally, good and evil existed in two completely separate realms, one the ''World of Light'', ruled by the ''Father of Greatness'' together with his five ''Shekhinas'' (divine attributes of light), and the other the ''World of Darkness'', ruled by the ''King of Darkness''.  At a certain point, the ''Kingdom of Darkness'' notices the ''World of Light'', becomes greedy for it and attacks it. The ''Father of Greatness'', in the first of three &quot;creations&quot; (or &quot;calls&quot;), calls to the ''Mother of Life'', who sends her son ''Original Man'' (''{{Unicode|Nāšā Qaḏmāyā}}'' in Aramaic), to battle with the attacking powers of Darkness, which include the ''Demon of Greed''.  The ''Original Man'' is armed with five different shields of light (reflections of the five ''Shekhinas''), which he loses to the forces of darkness in the ensuing battle, described as a kind of &quot;bait&quot; to trick the forces of darkness, as the forces of darkness greedily consume as much light as they can.  When the ''Original Man'' comes to, he is trapped among the forces of darkness.

'''The Second Creation''': Then the ''Father of Greatness'' begins the ''Second Creation'', calling to the ''Living Spirit'', who calls to his five sons, and sends a call to the ''Original Man'' (''Call'' then becomes a Manichaean deity). An answer (''Answer'' becomes another Manichaean deity) then returns from the ''Original Man'' to the ''World of Light''. The ''Mother of Life'', the ''Living Spirit'', and his five sons begin to create the universe from the bodies of the evil beings of the ''World of Darkness'', together with the light that they have swallowed.  Ten heavens and eight earths are created, all consisting of various mixtures of the evil material beings from the ''World of Darkness'' and the swallowed light.  The sun, moon, and stars are all created from light recovered from the ''World of Darkness''. The waxing and waning of the moon is described as the moon filling with light, which passes to the sun, then through the [[Milky Way]], and eventually back to the ''World of Light''.

'''The Third Creation''': Great demons (called ''[[archons]]'' in bar-Khonai's account) are hung out over the heavens, and then the ''Father of Greatness'' begins the ''Third Creation''.  Light is recovered from out of the material bodies of the male and female evil beings and demons, by causing them to become sexually aroused in greed, towards beautiful images of the beings of light, such as the ''Third Messenger'' and the ''Virgins of Light''. However, as soon as the light is expelled from their bodies and falls to the earth (some in the form of abortions – the source of [[fallen angel]]s in the Manichaean myth), the evil beings continue to swallow up as much of it as they can to keep the light inside of them.  This results eventually in the evil beings swallowing huge quantities of light, copulating, and producing Adam and Eve. The ''Father of Greatness'' then sends the ''Radiant Jesus'' to awaken Adam, and to enlighten him to the true source of the light that is trapped in his material body.  Adam and Eve, however, eventually copulate, and produce more human beings, trapping the light in bodies of mankind throughout human history. The appearance of the Prophet Mani was another attempt by the ''World of Light'' to reveal to mankind the true source of the spiritual light imprisoned within their material bodies.

===Outline of the beings and events in the Manichaean mythos===
Beginning with the time of its creation by Mani, the Manichaean religion had a detailed description of deities and events that took place within the Manichaean scheme of the universe.  In every language and region that Manichaeism spread to, these same deities reappear, whether it is in the original Syriac quoted by Theodore bar Konai,&lt;ref name=&quot;Konai&quot;/&gt; or the Latin terminology given by Saint Augustine from Mani's [[Fundamental Epistle|''Epistola Fundamenti'']], or the Persian and Chinese translations found as Manichaeism spread eastward.  While the original Syriac retained the original description which Mani created, the transformation of the deities through other languages and cultures produced incarnations of the deities not implied in the original Syriac writings.  This process began in Mani's lifetime, with &quot;The Father of Greatness&quot;, for example, being translated into Middle Persian as [[Zurvan]], a Zoroastrian supreme being.

====The World of Light====
*'''The Father of Greatness''' (Syriac: ܐܒܐ ܕܪܒܘܬܐ ''Abbā dəRabbūṯā''; Middle Persian: ''pīd ī wuzurgīh'',  or the Zoroastrian deity ''[[Zurvan|Zurwān]]''; Parthian: ''Pidar wuzurgift, Pidar roshn'')
*'''His Five [[shechina|Shekhinas]]''' (Syriac: ܚܡܫ ܫܟܝܢܬܗ ''khamesh shkhinatei''; Chinese: {{nowrap|{{linktext|五|种|大}} ''wǔ zhǒng dà,''}} {{grey|&quot;five great ones&quot;}}):&lt;ref&gt;Chart from: E. Waldschmidt and W. Lenz, Die Stellung Jesu im Manichäismus, Berlin, 1926, p 42.&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 40px;&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Shekhina:
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Reason
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Mind
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Intelligence
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Thought
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Understanding
|-
|Syriac
|{{linktext|ܗܘܢܐ}} ''haunâ''
|{{linktext|ܡܕܥܐ}} ''madde´â''
|{{linktext|ܪܥܝܢܐ}} ''reyana''
|{{linktext|ܡܚܫܒܬܐ}} ''mahšabtâ''
|{{linktext|ܬܪܥܝܬܐ}} ''tar´îtâ''
|-
|Parthian
|''bâm''
|''manohmêd''
|''uš''
|''andêšišn''
|''parmânag''
|-
|Chinese
|{{nowrap|{{linktext|相}} ''xiāng,''}} {{grey|&quot;phase&quot;}}
|{{nowrap|{{linktext|心}} ''xīn,''}} {{grey|&quot;heart&quot;}}
|{{nowrap|{{linktext|念}} ''niàn,''}} {{grey|&quot;idea&quot;}}
|{{nowrap|{{linktext|思}} ''sī,''}} {{grey|&quot;thought&quot;}}
|{{nowrap|{{linktext|意}} ''yì,''}} {{grey|&quot;meaning&quot;}}
|-
|Turkish
|qut
|ög
|köngül
|saqinç
|tuimaq
|-
|Greek
|νοῦς Nous
|εννοια
|φρονησις
|ενθυμησις
|λογισμος
|-
|Latin
|mens
|sensus
|prudentia
|intellectus
|cogitatio
|}
*'''The Great Spirit''' (Middle Persian: ''Waxsh zindag, Waxsh yozdahr''; Latin: ''Spiritus Potens'')

====The first creation====
*'''The Mother of Life''' (Syriac: ܐܡܐ ܕܚܝܐ ''ima de-khaye'')
*'''The First Man''' (Syriac: ܐܢܫܐ ܩܕܡܝܐ ''Nāšā Qaḏmāyā''; Middle Persian: ''[[Ohrmazd|Ohrmazd Bay]]'', the Zoroastrian god of light and goodness; Latin: ''Primus Homo'')
*'''His five Sons''' (the Five Light Elements; Middle Persian: ''[[Amesha Spenta|Amahrāspandan]]''; Parthian: ''panj rošn'')
**'''Ether''' (Middle Persian: ''frâwahr'', Parthian: ''ardâw'')
**'''Wind''' (Middle Persian and Parthian: ''wâd'')
**'''Light''' (Middle Persian and Parthian: ''rôšn'')
**'''Water''' (Middle Persian and Parthian: ''âb'')
**'''Fire''' (Middle Persian and Parthian: ''âdur'')
**His sixth Son, the '''Answer-God''' (Syriac: ܥܢܝܐ ''ania''; Middle Persian: ''khroshtag''; Chinese: 勢至 ''[[Mahasthamaprapta|Shì Zhì]]'' &quot;The Power of Wisdom&quot;, a Chinese Bodhisattva).  The answer sent by the ''First Man'' to the ''Call'' from the World of Light.
*'''The Living Self''' (made up of the five Elements; Middle Persian: ''Griw zindag, Griw roshn'')

====The second creation====
*'''The Friend of the Lights''' (Syriac: ܚܒܝܒ ܢܗܝܖܐ ''khaviv nehirei'').  Calls to:
*'''The Great Builder''' (Syriac: ܒܢ ܖܒܐ ''ban raba'').  In charge of creating the new world which will separate the darkness from the light.  He calls to:
*'''The Living Spirit''' (Syriac: ܪܘܚܐ ܚܝܐ ''rūḥā ḥayyā''; Middle Persian: ''[[Mithra|Mihryazd]]''; Chinese: 净活风 ''jing huo feng''; Latin: ''Spiritus Vivens''). Acts as a [[demiurge]], creating the structure of the material world.
*'''His five Sons''' (Syriac: ܚܡܫܐ ܒܢܘܗܝ ''khamsha benauhi'')
**'''The Keeper of the Splendour''' (Syriac: ܨܦܬ ܙܝܘܐ ''tzefat ziwa''; Latin: ''Splenditenens''). Holds up the ten heavens from above.
**'''The King of Honour''' (Syriac: ܡܠܟ ܫܘܒܚܐ ''melekh shubkha''; Latin: ''Rex Honoris'')
**'''The Adamas of Light''' (Syriac: ܐܕܡܘܣ ܢܘܗܪܐ ''adamus nuhra''; Latin: ''[[Adamas]]'').  Fights with and overcomes an evil being in the image of the King of Darkness.
**'''The Great King of Glory''' (Syriac: ܡܠܟܐ ܪܒܐ ܕܐܝܩܪܐ ''malka raba de-ikara''; Dead Sea Scrolls Aramaic: מלכא רבא דאיקרא ''malka raba de-ikara''; Latin: ''Rex Gloriosus''). A being which plays a central role in the [[Book of Enoch]] (originally written in Aramaic), as well as Mani's Syriac version of it, the [[Book of Giants]].  Sits in the [[Seven Heavens|seventh heaven]] of the ten heavens and guards the entrance to the world of light.
**'''Atlas''' (Syriac: ܣܒܠܐ ''sabala''; Latin: ''[[Atlas (mythology)|Atlas]]'').  Supports the eight worlds from below.
**His sixth Son, the '''Call-God''' (Syriac: ܩܪܝܐ ''karia''; Middle Persian: ''padvakhtag''; Chinese: 觀音 ''[[Guan Yin]]'' &quot;watching/perceiving sounds [of the world]&quot;, the Chinese Bodhisattva of Compassion).  Sent from the Living Spirit to awaken the First Man from his battle with the forces of darkness.

====The third creation====
*'''The Third Messenger''' (Syriac: ܐܝܙܓܕܐ ''īzgaddā''; Middle Persian ''narēsahyazad'', Parthian: ''hridīg frēštag''; Latin: ''tertius legatus'')
*'''Jesus the Splendour''' (Syriac: ܝܫܘܥ ܙܝܘܐ ''Yisho Ziwa''). Sent to awaken Adam and Eve to the source of the spiritual light trapped within their physical bodies.
*'''The Maiden of Light'''
*'''The Twelve Virgins of Light''' (Syriac: ܬܪܬܥܣܪܐ ܒܬܘܠܬܐ ''tratesra btultē''; Middle Persian ''kanīgān rōšnān''; Chinese: 日宮十二化女 ''ri gong shi er hua nyu''). Reflected in the twelve constellations of the [[Zodiac]].
*'''The Column of Glory''' (Syriac: ܐܣܛܘܢ ܫܘܒܚܐ ''esṭūn šubḥa'';  Middle Persian: ''srōš-ahrāy'', from [[Sraosha]]; Chinese: 蘇露沙羅夷, ''su lou sha luo yi'' and 盧舍那, ''lu she na'', both phonetic from Middle Persian ''srōš-ahrāy''). The path that souls take back to the ''World of Light''; corresponds to the [[Milky Way]].
*'''The Great [[Nous]]'''
*'''His five Limbs'''
**'''Reason'''
**'''Mind'''
**'''Intelligence'''
**'''Thought'''
**'''Understanding'''
*'''The Just Justice'''
*'''The Last God'''

====The World of Darkness====
*'''The King of Darkness''' (Syriac: ܡܠܟ ܚܫܘܟܐ ''melech kheshokha''; Middle Persian: ''[[Ahriman]]'', the Zoroastrian supreme evil being)
*'''His five evil kingdoms''' Evil counterparts of the five elements of light, the lowest being the kingdom of Darkness.
*'''His son''' (Syriac: ܐܫܩܠܘܢ ''Ashaklun''; Middle Persian: ''Az'', from the Zoroastrian demon, ''[[Azi Dahaka]]'')
*'''His son's mate''' (Syriac: ܢܒܪܘܐܠ ''Nebroel'')
**Their offspring – '''Adam and Eve''' (Middle Persian: ''[[Keyumars|Gehmurd]]'' and ''Murdiyanag'')
*'''Giants''' (Fallen Angels, also Abortions): (Syriac: ܝܚܛܐ ''yakhte'', &quot;abortions&quot; or &quot;those that fell&quot;; also: ܐܪܟܘܢܬܐ ''arkhonata'', the Gnostic ''[[Archons#Gnostic Archons|archons]]''; Greek, Coptic: ’Εγρήγοροι ''[[grigori|Egrēgoroi]]'', &quot;Giants&quot;). Related to the story of the [[fallen angel]]s in the [[Book of Enoch]] (which Mani used extensively in his [[Book of Giants]]), and the נפילים  ''[[nephilim]]'' described in Genesis (6:1–4), on which the story is based.

==Organization and religious practices==
===Organization of the Manichaean Church===
The Manichaean Church was divided into &quot;Elect&quot; – those who had taken upon themselves the vows of Manicheaism, and &quot;Hearers&quot; – those who had not, but still participated in the Church. The terms for these divisions were already common since the days of early Christianity. In the Chinese writings, the Middle Persian and Parthian terms are transcribed phonetically (instead of being translated into Chinese).&lt;ref&gt;G. Haloun and W. B. Henning, “The Compendium of the Doctrines and Styles of the Teaching of Mani, the Buddha of Light,” Asia Major, 1952, pp. 184–212, p. 195.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The '''Leader''', (Parthian: ''yamag''; Chinese: 閻默) Mani's designated successor, seated at the head of the Church in [[Ctesiphon]] (Babylonia).
*12 '''[[Apostle (Christian)|Apostles]]''' (Latin: ''magistri''; Middle Persian: ''možag''; Chinese: 慕闍)
*72 '''[[Bishop]]s''' (Latin: ''episcopi''; Middle Persian: ''aspasag'', ''aftadan''; Chinese: 拂多誕; see also: [[Seventy Disciples]])
*360 '''[[Presbyter]]s''' (Latin: ''presbyteri''; Middle Persian: ''mahistan'')
*The general body of the '''Elect''' (Latin: ''electi''; Middle Persian: ''ardawan'', ''dēnāwar'')
*The '''Hearers''' (Latin: ''auditores''; Middle Persian: ''niyoshagan'')

===The Bema Fest===
The most important religious observance of the Manichaeans was the Bema Fest, observed annually:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The [[Bema]] was originally, in the Syriac Christian churches a seat placed in the middle of the nave on which
the bishop would preside and from which the Gospel would be read. In the Manichean places of worship, the throne was a five-stepped altar, covered by precious cloths, symbolizing the five classes of the hierarchy. The top of the Bema was always empty, as it was the seat of Mani. The Bema was celebrated at the [[vernal equinox]], was preceded by fasts, and symbolized the [[Passion (Christianity)|passion]] of Mani, thus it was strictly parallel to the Christian [[Easter]].&lt;ref&gt;Skjærvø, Prods Oktor, ''An Introduction to Manicheism'', 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
While it is often presumed that the Bema seat was empty, there is some evidence from the Coptic Manichaean ''Bema Psalms'', that the Bema seat may have actually contained a copy of Mani's picture book, the [[Arzhang]].&lt;ref&gt;
Ort, L. J. R., ''Mani: a religio-historical description of his personality'', 1967, p. 254.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Primary sources==
[[File:Jinjiang Cao'an 20120229-10.jpg|thumb|Statue of prophet Mani as the &quot;Buddha of Light&quot; in [[Cao'an]] Temple in [[Jinjiang, Fujian]], &quot;a Manichean temple in Buddhist disguise&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Iranica|manicheism-1-general-survey|MANICHEISM i. GENERAL SURVEY}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is considered &quot;the only extant Manichean temple in China&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Iranica|chinese-turkestan-vii|CHINESE TURKESTAN: vii. Manicheism in Chinese Turkestan and China}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Mani wrote either seven or eight books, which contained the teachings of the religion. Only scattered fragments and translations of the originals remain.

The original six Syriac writings are not preserved, although their Syriac names have been. There are also fragments and quotations from them.  A long quotation, preserved by the eighth-century Nestorian Christian author [[Theodore bar Konai]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Konai&quot;&gt;Original Syriac in: Theodorus bar Konai, ''Liber Scholiorum, II'', ed. A. Scher, ''Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium scrip. syri'', 1912, pp. 311–8, ISBN 978-90-429-0104-9; English translation in: A.V.W. Jackson, ''Researches in Manichaeism'', New York, 1932, pp. 222–54.&lt;/ref&gt; shows that in the original Syriac Aramaic writings of Mani there was no influence of Iranian or [[Zoroastrian]] terms.  The terms for the Manichaean deities in the original Syriac writings are in Aramaic.  The adaptation of Manichaeism to the Zoroastrian religion appears to have begun in Mani's lifetime however, with his writing of the Middle Persian [[Shabuhragan]], his book dedicated to the King Shapuhr.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shabuhragan&quot;/&gt;  In it, there are mentions of Zoroastrian deities such as Ohrmazd, Ahriman, and Az.  Manichaeism is often presented as a Persian religion, mostly due to the vast number of Middle Persian, Parthian, and Soghdian (as well as Turkish) texts discovered by German researchers near [[Turpan]], in the [[Xinjiang]] (Chinese Turkestan) province of China, during the early 1900s. However, from the vantage point of its original Syriac descriptions (as quoted by Theodore bar Khonai and outlined below), Manichaeism may be better described as a unique phenomenon of Aramaic Babylonia, occurring in proximity to two other new Aramaic religious phenomena, [[Talmudic Academies in Babylonia|Talmudic Judaism]] and Babylonian [[Mandaeism]], which were also appearing in Babylonia in roughly the third century AD.

The original, but now lost, six sacred books of Manichaeism were composed in [[Syriac|Syriac Aramaic]], and translated into other languages to help spread the religion. As they spread to the east, the Manichaean writings passed through [[Middle Persian]], [[Parthian language|Parthian]], [[Sogdian language|Sogdian]], [[Tocharian languages|Tocharian]] and ultimately [[Uyghur language|Uyghur]] and [[Chinese language|Chinese]] translations. As they spread to the west, they were translated into [[Greek language|Greek]], [[Coptic language|Coptic]], and [[Latin]].

===Originally written in Syriac===
* [[Gospel of Mani|The Evangelion]] (Syriac: ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ; Greek, Coptic: Ευαγγελιον, meaning roughly &quot;good news&quot;). Also known as the ''Gospel of Mani''. Quotations from the first chapter were brought in Arabic by [[Ibn al-Nadim]], who lived in Baghdad at a time when there were still Manichaeans living there, in his book the &quot;Fihrist&quot; (written in 938), a catalog of all written books known to him.
* The Treasure of Life
* The Treatise (Coptic: πραγματεία)
* Secrets
* [[Book of Giants|The Book of Giants]]: Original fragments were discovered at [[Qumran]] (pre-Manichaean) and [[Turpan]].
* Epistles: Augustine brings quotations, in Latin, from Mani's [[Fundamental Epistle]] in some of his anti-Manichaean works.
* Psalms and Prayers.  A [[Coptic language|Coptic]] Manichaean Psalter, discovered in Egypt in the early 1900s, was edited and published by [[Charles Allberry]] from Manichaean manuscripts in the [[Chester Beatty Papyri|Chester Beatty collection]] and in the Berlin Academy, 1938-9.

===Originally written in Middle Persian===
* The [[Shabuhragan]], dedicated to [[Shapur I]]: Original Middle Persian fragments were discovered at [[Turpan]], quotations were brought in Arabic by [[al-Biruni]].

===Other books===
* The [[Arzhang|Ardahang]], the &quot;Picture Book&quot;.  In Iranian tradition, this was one of Mani's holy books which became remembered in later Persian history, and was also called Aržang, a [[Parthian language|Parthian]] word meaning &quot;Worthy&quot;, and was beautified with paintings. Therefore Iranians gave him the title of &quot;The Painter&quot;.
* The Kephalaia (Κεφαλαια), &quot;Discourses&quot;, found in Coptic translation.
* ''On the Origin of His Body'', the title of the [[Cologne Mani-Codex]], a Greek translation of an Aramaic book which describes the early life of Mani.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mani-Kodex&quot;/&gt;

===Non-Manichaean works preserved by the Manichaean Church===
* Some portions of the [[Book of Enoch]] literature.
* Some literature relating to the [[Thomas the Apostle|apostle Thomas]] (who by tradition went to India, and was also venerated in Syria), such as portions of the Syriac [[Acts of Thomas|The Acts of Thomas]], and the [[Psalms of Thomas]]. The [[Gospel of Thomas]] was also attributed to Manichaeans by the early Church Fathers.&lt;ref&gt;''&quot;Let none read the gospel according to Thomas, for it is the work, not of one of the twelve apostles, but of one of [[Mani (prophet)|Mani's]] three wicked disciples.&quot;''—[[Cyril of Jerusalem]], ''Cathechesis'' V (4th century)&lt;/ref&gt;
* The legend of [[Barlaam and Josaphat]] passed from an Indian story about the Buddha, through a Manichaean version, before it transformed into the story of a Christian Saint in the west.

===Later works===
[[File:摩尼教文獻.jpg|thumb|摩尼教文獻 The Chinese Manichaean &quot;Compendium&quot;]]
In later centuries, as Manichaeism passed through eastern Persian speaking lands and arrived at the [[Uyghur Empire]], and eventually the Uyghur kingdom of [[Turpan]] (destroyed around 1335), long hymn cycles and prayers were composed in Middle Persian and Parthian.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, [[Mary Boyce|Boyce, Mary]] ''The Manichaean hymn-cycles in Parthian'' (London Oriental Series, Vol. 3). London: Oxford University Press, 1954.&lt;/ref&gt; A translation of one of these produced the Manichaean Chinese Hymnscroll (the 摩尼教下部贊, which Lieu translates as &quot;Hymns for the Lower Section [i.e. the Hearers] of the Manichaean Religion&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lieu, Samuel N. C., ''Manichaeism in Central Asia and China'', 1998, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;), now available in its entirety (see the external links section).

===Critical and polemic sources===
Until discoveries in the 1900s of original sources, the only sources for Manichaeism were descriptions and quotations from non-Manichaean authors, either Christian, Muslim, Buddhist or Zoroastrian. While often criticizing Manichaeism, they also quoted directly from Manichaean scriptures. This enabled [[Isaac de Beausobre]], writing in the 18th century, to create a comprehensive work on Manichaeism, relying solely on anti-Manichaean sources.&lt;ref&gt;[[Isaac de Beausobre|de Beausobre, Isaac]], ''Histoire critique de Manichée et du Manichéisme'', 1734–1739, Amsterdam.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus quotations and descriptions in Greek and Arabic have long been known to scholars, as have the long quotations in Latin by Saint Augustine, and the extremely important quotation in Syriac by Theodore bar Khonai.

====Patristic depictions of Mani and Manchæeism====
[[Eusebius]] commented as follows:
{{quotation|''The error of the Manichees, which commenced at this time.''|In the mean time, also, that madman Manes, (Mani is of Persian or semetic origin) as he was called, well agreeing with his name, for his demoniacal heresy, armed himself by the perversion of his reason, and at the instruction of Satan, to the destruction of many. He was a barbarian in his life, both in speech and conduct, but in his nature as one possessed and insane. Accordingly, he attempted to form himself into a Christ, and then also proclaimed himself to be the very paraclete and the Holy Spirit, and with all this was greatly puffed up with his madness. Then, as if he were Christ, he selected twelve disciples, the partners of his new religion, and after patching together false and ungodly doctrines, collected from a thousand heresies long since extinct, he swept them off like a deadly poison, from Persia, upon this part of the world. Hence the impious name of the Manicheans spreading among many, even to the present day. Such then was the occasion of this knowledge, as it was falsely called, that sprouted up in these times.&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius. ''The Ecclesiastical History of Eusebius Pamphilus, Bishop of Caesarea,'' Translated from the originals by Christian Frederick Cruse.1939. Ch. XXXI.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Acta Archelai====
An example of how inaccurate some of these accounts could be is seen in the account of the origins of Manichaeism contained in the ''Acta Archelai''.  This was a Greek anti-manichaean work written before 348, most well known in its Latin version, which was regarded as an accurate account of Manichaeism until the end of the 19th century:
&lt;blockquote&gt;In the time of the Apostles there lived a man named [[Scythianus]], who is described as coming 'from Scythia,' and also as being 'a Saracen by race' ('ex genere Saracenorum'). He settled in Egypt, where he became acquainted with 'the wisdom of the Egyptians,' and invented the religious system which was afterwards known as Manichaeism. Finally he emigrated to Palestine, and, when he died, his writings passed into the hands of his sole disciple, a certain [[Terebinthus]]. The latter betook himself to Babylonia, assumed the name of Budda, and endeavoured to propagate his master's teaching. But he, like Scythianus, gained only one disciple, who was an old woman. After a while he died, in consequence of a fall from the roof of a house, and the books which he had inherited from Scythianus became the property of the old woman, who, on her death, bequeathed them to a young man named Corbicius, who had been her slave. Corbicius thereupon changed his name to Manes, studied the writings of Scythianus, and began to teach the doctrines which they contained, with many additions of his own. He gained three disciples, named Thomas, Addas, and Hermas. About this time the son of the Persian king fell ill, and Manes undertook to cure him; the prince, however, died, whereupon Manes was thrown into prison. He succeeded in escaping, but eventually fell into the hands of the king, by whose order he was flayed, and his corpse was hung up at the city gate.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
A. A. Bevan, who quoted this story, commented that it 'has no claim to be considered historical.'&lt;ref&gt;Bevan, A. A. (1930). &quot;Manichaeism&quot;. ''Encyclopaedia of Religion and Ethics, Volume VIII'' Ed. [[James Hastings]]. London&lt;/ref&gt;

=====View of Judaism in the ''Acta Archelai''=====
According to [[Hegemonius]]' portrayal of Mani, the devil god which created the world was the Jewish Jehovah. Hegemonius reports that Mani said, &quot;It is the Prince of Darkness who spoke with Moses, the Jews and their priests. Thus the Christians, the Jews, and the Pagans are involved in the same error when they worship this God. For he leads them astray in the lusts he taught them.&quot; He goes on to state: &quot;Now, he who spoke with Moses, the Jews, and the priests he says is the archont of Darkness, and the Christians, Jews, and pagans (ethnic) are one and the same, as they revere the same god. For in his aspirations he seduces them, as he is not the god of truth. And so therefore all those who put their hope in the god who spoke with Moses and the prophets have (this in store for themselves, namely) to be bound with him, because they did not put their hope in the god of truth. For that one spoke with them (only) according to their own aspirations.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Classical Texts: Acta Archelai of Mani |url=http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~iranian/Manicheism/Manicheism_II_Texts.pdf |format=PDF |page=76 |publisher=Fas.harvard.edu |date= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Central Asian and Iranian primary sources===
In the early 1900s, original Manichaean writings started to come to light when German scholars led by [[Albert Grünwedel]], and then by [[Albert von Le Coq]], began excavating at [[Gaochang]], the ancient site of the Manichaean Uyghur Kingdom near Turpan, in Chinese Turkestan (destroyed around AD 1300). While most of the writings they uncovered were in very poor condition, there were still hundreds of pages of Manichaean scriptures, written in three Iranian languages (Middle Persian, Parthian, and Sogdian) and old Turkish.  These writings were taken back to Germany, and were analyzed and published at the [[Prussian Academy of Sciences|Preußische Akademie der Wissenschaften]] in Berlin, by Le Coq and others, such as [[Friedrich W. K. Müller]] and [[Walter Bruno Henning]].  While the vast majority of these writings were written in a version of the Syriac script known as [[Manichaean script]], the German researchers, perhaps for lack of suitable fonts, published most of them using Hebrew letters (which could easily be substituted for the 22 Syriac letters).

Perhaps the most comprehensive of these publications was ''Manichaeische Dogmatik aus chinesischen und iranischen Texten'' (''Manichaean Dogma from Chinese and Iranian texts''), by [[Ernst Waldschmidt]] and Wolfgang Lentz, published in Berlin in 1933.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ernst Waldschmidt|Waldschmidt, E.]], and Lentz, W., ''Manichäische Dogmatik aus chinesischen und iranischen Texten'' (SPAW 1933, No. 13)&lt;/ref&gt;  More than any other research work published before or since, this work printed, and then discussed, the original key Manichaean texts in the original scripts, and consists chiefly of sections from Chinese texts, and Middle Persian and Parthian texts transcribed with Hebrew letters.  (After the Nazi party gained power in Germany, the Manichaean writings continued to be published during the 1930s, but the publishers no longer used Hebrew letters, instead transliterating the texts into Latin letters.)

===Coptic primary sources===
Additionally, in 1930, German researchers in Egypt found a large body of Manichaean works in Coptic.  Though these were also damaged, many complete pages survived and, beginning in 1933, were analyzed and published in Berlin before World War II, by German scholars such as [[Hans Jakob Polotsky]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Hans Jakob Polotsky]] and Karl Schmidt, ''Ein Mani-Fund in Ägypten, Original-Schriften des Mani und seiner Schüler''. Berlin: Akademie der Wissenschaften 1933.&lt;/ref&gt; Some of these Coptic Manichaean writings were lost during the war.

===Chinese primary sources===
After the success of the German researchers, French scholars visited China and discovered what is perhaps the most complete set of Manichaean writings, written in Chinese. These three Chinese writings are today kept in London, Paris, and Beijing. Some of the scholars involved with their initial discovery and publication were [[Édouard Chavannes]], [[Paul Pelliot]], and [[Aurel Stein]]. The original studies and analyses of these writings, along with their translations, first appeared in French, English, and German, before and after World War II. The complete Chinese texts themselves were first published in Tokyo, Japan in 1927, in the [[Taisho Tripitaka]], volume 54. While in the last thirty years or so they have been republished in both Germany (with a complete translation into German, alongside the 1927 Japanese edition),&lt;ref&gt;Schmidt-Glintzer, Helwig, ''Chinesische Manichaeica'', Wiesbaden, 1987&lt;/ref&gt; and China, the Japanese publication remains the standard reference for the Chinese texts.

===Greek life of Mani, Cologne codex===
In Egypt a small [[codex]] was found and became known through antique dealers in [[Cairo]]. It was purchased by the [[University of Cologne]] in 1969. Two of its scientists, Henrichs and Koenen, produced the first edition known since as the [[Cologne Mani-Codex]], which was published in four articles in the ''Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik''. The ancient [[papyrus]] manuscript contained a [[Greek language|Greek]] text describing the life of Mani. Thanks to this discovery, much more is known about the man who founded one of the most influential world religions of the past.

==Figurative use==
The terms &quot;Manichaean&quot; and &quot;Manichaeism&quot; are sometimes used figuratively as a synonym of the more general term &quot;[[dualist]]&quot; with respect to a philosophy or outlook.&lt;ref&gt;[http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/Manichaean Oxford Dictionaries: Manichaean], [http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/Manichaeism Manichaeism]&lt;/ref&gt; They are often used to suggest with a somewhat disparaging undertone that the world view in question simplistically reduces the world to a struggle between Good and Evil. For example, Jean-Paul Sartre in the essay ''[[Anti-Semite and Jew]]'' referred to the [[Anti-Semitism|Anti-Semitic]] world view as &quot;a form of Manichaeism&quot;, since &quot;it explains the course of the world by the struggle of the principle of Good with the principle of Evil&quot; (the &quot;principle of Evil&quot; being equated, by an Anti-Semitic person, with the Jews). Similarly, [[Zbigniew Brzezinski]] used the phrase &quot;Manichaean paranoia&quot; in reference to [[POTUS|U.S. President]] [[George W. Bush]]'s world view (in the [[The Daily Show with Jon Stewart]], March 14, 2007); Brzezinski elaborated that he meant &quot;the notion that he (Bush) is leading the forces of good against the empire of evil&quot;.

==See also==
{{div col|cols=3}}

===Manichaean figures===
*[[Mani (prophet)]]
*[[Mar Ammo]] (third century)
*[[Mar Zaku]] (third century)
*[[Pattig]] (third century)
*[[Faustus of Mileve]] (fourth century)
*[[Agapius (Manichaean)]] (fourth or fifth centuries)
*[[Abū Hilāl al-Dayhūri]] (eighth century)

===Gnostic and early Christian===
*[[Church of the East]]
*[[Gnosticism]]
*[[Mandaeanism]]

===Persian religions===
*[[Mazdakism]]
*[[Yazdanism]]
*[[Zoroastrianism]]
*[[Zurvanism]]

===Other===
*[[Assyro-Babylonian religion]]
*[[Hiwi al-Balkhi]]
*[[Indo-Iranian religion]]
*[[Ming Cult]]
*[[Muhammad al Warraq]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

=== Books and articles ===
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2&quot;&gt;
*{{cite book
|coauthors=Hugo Ibscher
|editor=[[Charles Allberry|Allberry Charles R. C.]]
|title=Manichaean Manuscripts in the Chester Beatty Collection: Vol II, part II: A Manichaean Psalm Book
|year=1938
|publisher=W. Kohlammer
|location=Stuttgart}}
*{{cite book
|last=Beatty
|first=Alfred Chester
|editor=Charles Allberry
|title=A Manichean Psalm-Book, Part II
|year=1938
|location=Stuttgart}}
*{{cite book
|last=Beausobre, de
|first=Isaac
|authorlink=Isaac de Beausobre
|title=Histoire critique de Manichée et du Manichéisme
|year=1734–1739
|location=Amsterdam
|isbn=0-8240-3552-6
|publisher=Garland Pub.}}
*{{cite book
|last=BeDuhn
|first=Jason David
|title=The Manichaean Body: In Discipline and Ritual
|isbn=0-8018-7107-7
|year=2002
|publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press
|location=Baltimore}}
*{{cite book
|last=Cross
|first=F. L.
|coauthors=E. A. Livingstone
|title=The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church
|year=1974
|location=London: Oxford UP
|isbn=0-19-211545-6
|publisher=Oxford University Press}}
*{{cite conference
|last=Favre
|first=Francois
|date=2005-05-05
|title=Mani, the Gift of Light
|conference=Renova symposium
|location=Bilthoven, The Netherlands}}
*{{cite book
|last=Foltz
|first=Richard
|authorlink=Richard Foltz
|title=Religions of the Silk Road
|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan
|location=New York
|isbn=978-0-230-62125-1
|year=2010}}
* {{cite book |first=Richard |last=Foltz |authorlink=Richard Foltz |title=Spirituality in the Land of the Noble: How Iran Shaped the World's Religions |publisher=Oneworld publications |location=Oxford |year=2004 |isbn=1-85168-336-4}}
*{{cite book
|last=Gardner
|first=Iain
|coauthors=Samuel N. C. Lieu
|title=Manichaean Texts from the Roman Empire
|isbn=0-521-56822-6
|year=2004
|publisher=Cambridge Univ. Press
|location=Cambridge}}
*&lt;!--ref name=&quot;1988a&quot;--&gt;{{cite book
|last=Giversen
|first=Soren
|title=The Manichaean Coptic Papyri in The Chester Beatty Library Vol. III: Psalm Book part I.
|edition=Facsimile
|year=1988
|publisher=Patrick Crammer
|location=Geneva}} (Cahiers D'Orientalism XVI) 1988a
*&lt;!--ref name=&quot;1988b&quot;--&gt;{{cite book
|last=Giversen
|first=Soren
|title=The Manichaean Coptic Papyri in The Chester Beatty Library ''Vol. IV: Psalm Book part II''.
|edition=Facsimile
|year=1988
|publisher=Patrick Crammer
|location=Geneva}} (Cahiers D'Orientalism XVI) 1988b
*{{cite book
|last=Gulácsi
|first=Zsuszanna
|title=Manichaean art in Berlin Collections
|year=2001
|location=Turnhout}} (Original Manichaean manuscripts found since 1902 in China, Egypt, Turkestan to be seen in the Museum of Indian Art in Berlin.)
*Heinrichs, Albert; Ludwig Koenen, ''Ein griechischer Mani-Kodex'', 1970 (ed.) ''Der Kölner Mani-Codex'' ( P. Colon. Inv. nr. 4780), 1975&amp;ndash;1982.
*La Vaissière, Etienne de, &quot;Mani en Chine au VIe siècle&quot;,'' Journal Asiatique'', 293–1, 2005, p.&amp;nbsp;357–378.
*{{cite book
|last=Legge
|first=Francis
|title=Forerunners and Rivals of Christianity, From 330 B.C. to 330 A.D.
|origyear=1914
|format=reprinted in two volumes bound as one
|year=1964
|publisher=University Books
|location=New York
|id=LC Catalog 64-24125}}
*{{cite book
|last=Lieu
|first=Samuel
|title=Manichaeism in the later Roman Empire and medieval China
|year=1992
|publisher=J. C. B. Mohr
|location=Tübingen
|isbn=0-7190-1088-8}}
*Mani (216&amp;ndash;276/7) and his 'biography': the Codex Manichaicus Coloniensis (CMC):
*{{cite book
|last=Melchert
|first=Norman
|title=The Great Conversation: A Historical Introduction to Philosophy
|publisher=McGraw Hill
|year=2002
|isbn=0-19-517510-7}}
*{{cite book
|last=Runciman
|first=Steven
|authorlink=Steven Runciman
|title=The Medieval Manichee: a study of the Christian dualist heresy
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|year=1982
|origyear=1947
|isbn=0-521-28926-2}}
*{{cite book
|last=Welburn
|first=Andrew
|title=Mani, the Angel and the Column of Glory
|isbn=0-86315-274-0
|year=1998
|publisher=Floris
|location=Edinburgh}}
*{{cite book
|last=Widengren
|first=Geo
|title=Mani and Manichaeism
|year=1965
|publisher=Weidenfeld and Nicholson
|location=London}}
*{{cite journal
|last=Wurst
|first=Gregor
|year=2001
|month=July
|title=Die Bema-Psalmen
|journal=Journal of Near Eastern Studies
|volume=60
|issue=3
|pages=203–204
|doi=10.1086/468925}}
&lt;/div&gt;
*{{Cite book | title = Mani the Angel and the Column of Glory | first = Andrew | last = Welburn | publisher = Floris Books | year =1998| isbn = 0-86315-274-0}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}

===Outside articles===
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09591a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia – Manichæism] public domain, published 1917.
*[http://www.manichaeism.de International Association of Manichaean Studies]
*[http://www.anchist.mq.edu.au/doccentre/Zayton.htm Manichaean and Christian Remains in Zayton (Quanzhou, South China)]
*[http://www.iranchamber.com/religions/articles/manichaeism1.php Religions of Iran: Manichaeism] by I.J.S. Taraporewala

===Manichaean sources in English translation===
*[http://gnosis.org/library/Mani.html A summary of the Manichaean creation myth]
*[http://gnosis.org/library/manis.htm Manichaean Writings]
*[http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~iranian/Manicheism Manicheism]. Complete bibliography and selection of Manichaean source texts in PDF format:
**[http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~iranian/Manicheism/Manicheism_I_Intro.pdf A thorough bibliography and outline of Manichaean Studies]
**[http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~iranian/Manicheism/Manicheism_II_Texts.pdf A number of key Manichaean texts in English translation]
*[http://www.sacred-texts.com/chr/giants/giants.htm The Book of the Giants] by [[W.B. Henning]], 1943
*[http://www.essenes.net/pdf/Hymnscroll.pdf The Manichaean Chinese Hymnscroll]

===Secondary Manichaean sources in English translation===
*[[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series I/Volume IV/Manichaean Controversy/Against the Epistle of Manichaeus/Chapter 1|St. Augustine Against the Fundamental Epistle of Manichaeus]]
* [http://www4.nau.edu/manichaean/acta.htm Acta Archelai]

===Manichaean sources in their original languages===
*[http://www.uni-koeln.de/phil-fak/ifa/NRWakademie/papyrologie/Manikodex/bildermani.html Photos of the Entire Koeln Mani-Kodex] (Greek).
*[http://www.hebrewchinese.com/maninaya.pdf The Syriac Manichaean work quoted by Theodor bar Khonai]
*D. N. MacKenzie, “Mani’s Šābuhragān,” pt. 1 (text and translation), BSOAS 42/3, 1979, pp.&amp;nbsp;500–34,[http://www.essenes.net/pdf/Mani%27s%20Sabuhragan.pdf] pt. 2 (glossary and plates), BSOAS 43/2, 1980, pp.&amp;nbsp;288–310 [http://www.essenes.net/pdf/Mani%20SabuhraganII%20.pdf].
*[http://www.bbaw.de/forschung/turfanforschung/dta/m/dta_m_index.htm Photos of the Original Middle Persian Manichaean Writings/Fragments Discovered at Turpan] (The index of this German site can be searched for additional Manichaean material, including photos of the original Chinese Manichaean writings)
*Chinese Manichaean Scriptures: [http://ccbs.ntu.edu.tw/BDLM/sutra/chi_pdf/sutra22/T54n2141B.pdf 摩尼教殘經一] (&quot;Incomplete Sutra one of Manichaeism&quot;)&amp; [http://ccbs.ntu.edu.tw/BDLM/sutra/chi_pdf/sutra22/T54n2141A.pdf 摩尼光佛教法儀略](&quot;The Mani Bright Buddha teaching plan&quot;) &amp; [http://ccbs.ntu.edu.tw/BDLM/sutra/chi_pdf/sutra22/T54n2140.pdf 下部贊](&quot;The Lower Part Praises&quot;)

===Secondary Manichaean sources in their original languages===
*[http://www.sant-agostino.it/latino/contro_lettera_mani/index.htm Augustine's Contra Epistolam Manichaei] (Latin)

{{Religion topics}}

[[Category:Esotericism]]
[[Category:Gnosticism]]
[[Category:Iranian religions]]
[[Category:Iranian peoples]]
[[Category:Late Antiquity]]
[[Category:Manichaeism]]
[[Category:Patristics]]
[[Category:Religion in Iran]]
[[Category:Religion in China]]
[[Category:Nontrinitarian denominations]]

[[ar:مانوية]]
[[az:Manilik]]
[[be:Маніхейства]]
[[be-x-old:Маніхейства]]
[[bg:Манихейство]]
[[ca:Maniqueisme]]
[[cs:Manicheismus]]
[[da:Manikæisme]]
[[de:Manichäismus]]
[[el:Μανιχαϊσμός]]
[[es:Maniqueísmo]]
[[eo:Manikeismo]]
[[eu:Manikeismo]]
[[fa:دین مانوی‌]]
[[fr:Manichéisme]]
[[fy:Manicheïsme]]
[[ga:An Mhainicéasaíocht]]
[[gl:Maniqueísmo]]
[[ko:마니교]]
[[hy:Մանիքեություն]]
[[hi:मानी धर्म]]
[[hr:Manihejstvo]]
[[io:Manikeismo]]
[[id:Maniisme]]
[[ia:Manicheismo]]
[[it:Manicheismo]]
[[he:מניכאיזם]]
[[ka:მანიქეიზმი]]
[[ky:Манихейчилик]]
[[hu:Manicheizmus]]
[[ml:മനിക്കേയവാദം]]
[[arz:مانويه]]
[[ms:Manichaeisme]]
[[nl:Manicheïsme]]
[[ja:マニ教]]
[[no:Manikeisme]]
[[oc:Maniqueïsme]]
[[pl:Manicheizm]]
[[pt:Maniqueísmo]]
[[ro:Maniheism]]
[[ru:Манихейство]]
[[simple:Manichaeism]]
[[sk:Manicheizmus]]
[[sl:Manihejstvo]]
[[sr:Манихејство]]
[[sh:Manihejstvo]]
[[fi:Manikealaisuus]]
[[sv:Manikeism]]
[[tt:Манихейлык]]
[[th:นิกายเม้งก่า]]
[[tr:Mani dini]]
[[uk:Маніхейство]]
[[vi:Mani giáo]]
[[diq:Maniheizm]]
[[zh:摩尼教]]</text>
      <sha1>s73pnabhr1l2atzga07ew4wbynzvzak</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
