<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Marcionism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>301005</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519101982</id>
      <parentid>511461433</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-21T23:19:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Samatva</username>
        <id>118430</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Marcionism in Modern history */ Fix broken link</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31967">[[File:Markion.jpg|thumb|[[Marcion of Sinope]]]]
'''Marcionism''' was an [[Early Christian]] [[Dualism|dualist]] [[belief system]] that originated in the teachings of [[Marcion of Sinope]] at [[Rome]] around the year 144&lt;ref&gt;(115 years and 6 months from the [[Crucifixion]], according to [[Tertullian]]'s reckoning in ''Adversus Marcionem'', xv)&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[Christianity in the 2nd century]]).

Marcion believed [[Jesus Christ]] was the [[Messiah|savior]] sent by [[God in Christianity|God]], and [[Paul of Tarsus]] was his chief [[Apostle (Christian)|apostle]], but he rejected the [[Hebrew Bible]] and the [[Yahweh|God of Israel]]. Marcionists believed that the [[Divine retribution|wrathful Hebrew God]] was a separate and lower entity than the [[Love of God|all-forgiving God]] of the [[New Testament]]. This belief was in some ways similar to [[Gnostic Christianity|Gnostic Christian theology]]; notably, both are ''[[dualistic]]'', that is, they posit opposing gods, forces, or principles: one higher, spiritual, and &quot;good&quot;, and the other lower, material, and &quot;evil&quot; (compare [[Manichaeism]]), in contrast to the orthodox Christian view that &quot;evil&quot; has no independent existence, but is a [[privation]] or lack of &quot;good&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[St Thomas Aquinas]], ''Summa Theologiae'' Prima Pars, Q. 14 A. 10; Q. 49 A. 3.; [[Psuedo-Dionysius the Areopagite]], ''On the Divine Names'', 4; iv. 31&lt;/ref&gt; a view shared by the eminent Jewish theologian [[Moses Maimonides]].&lt;ref&gt;''Guide for the Perplexed'' 3,10&lt;/ref&gt;

Marcionism, similar to [[Gnosticism]], depicted the Hebrew God of the Old Testament as a tyrant or [[demiurge]] (see also [[God as the Devil]]). Marcion was labeled a gnostic by [[Philip Schaff]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Marcion was the most earnest, the most practical, and the most dangerous among the Gnostics, full of energy and zeal for reforming, but restless rough and eccentric. He has a remote connection with modern questions of biblical criticism and the canon. He anticipated a rationalistic opposition to the Old Testament and to the Pastoral Epistles, but in a very arbitrary and unscrupulous way. He could see only superficial differences in the Bible, not the deeper harmony. He rejected the heathen mythology of the other Gnostics, and adhered to Christianity as the only true religion; he was less speculative, and gave a higher place to faith. But he was utterly destitute of historical sense, and put Christianity into a radical conflict with all previous revelations of God; as if God had neglected the world for thousands of years until he suddenly appeared in Christ. He represents an extreme [[anti-Jewish]] and pseudo-Pauline tendency, and a magical supranaturalism, which, in fanatical zeal for a pure primitive Christianity, nullifies all history, and turns the gospel into an abrupt, unnatural, phantomlike appearance. Marcion was the son of a bishop of Sinope in Pontus, and gave in his first fervor his property to the church, but was excommunicated by his own father, probably on account of his heretical opinions and contempt of authority..86 He betook himself, about the middle of the second century, to Rome (140–155), which originated none of the Gnostic systems, but attracted them all. There he joined the Syrian Gnostic, [[Cerdo (gnostic)|Cerdo]].&quot; ''History of the Christian Church'', Volume II: Ante-Nicene Christianity. A.D. 100-325. Marcion and his School by PHILIP SCHAFF [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/hcc2.v.xiii.xvi.html]&lt;/ref&gt; while other scholars have rejected that categorization. [[Development of the New Testament canon#Marcion of Sinope|Marcion's canon]] consisted of eleven books: [[Gospel of Marcion|A gospel]] consisting of ten sections from the Gospel of Luke edited by Marcion; and ten of [[Pauline epistles|Paul's epistles]]. All other epistles and gospels of the [[Canon of the New Testament|27 book New Testament canon]] were rejected.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/hcc2.v.xiii.xvi.html Eusebius' Church History]&lt;/ref&gt; Paul's epistles enjoy a prominent position in the Marcionite canon, since Paul is credited with correctly transmitting the universality of Jesus' message. Other authors' epistles were rejected since they seemed to suggest that Jesus had simply come to found a [[Jewish Christianity|new sect within broader Judaism]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} Religious tribalism of this sort seemed to echo ''Yahwism'', and was thus regarded as a corruption of the &quot;Heavenly Father&quot;'s teaching.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}} 

Marcionism was denounced by its opponents as [[heresy]], and written against, notably by [[Tertullian]], in a five-book treatise ''Adversus Marcionem'', written about 208. Marcion's writings are lost, though they were widely read and numerous manuscripts must have existed.  Even so, many scholars (including [[Henry Wace (Anglican priest)|Henry Wace]]) claim it is possible to reconstruct and deduce a large part of ancient Marcionism through what later critics, especially Tertullian, said concerning Marcion.

==History==
{{Main|Marcion of Sinope}}

According to [[Tertullian]] and other writers of the mainstream Church (which scholars refer to as [[Proto-orthodox Christianity]]), the movement known as Marcionism began with the teachings and [[excommunication]] of Marcion around 144.  Marcion was reportedly a wealthy shipowner, the son of a bishop of [[Sinop, Turkey|Sinope]] of [[Pontus]], [[Asia Minor]]. He arrived in Rome c. 140, soon after [[Bar Kokhba's revolt]].  That revolution, along with other [[Jewish-Roman wars]] (the [[Great Jewish Revolt]] and the [[Kitos War]]), provides some of the historical context of the founding of Marcionism; see also [[Anti-Judaism#Anti-Judaism in the Roman Empire|Anti-Judaism in the Roman Empire]]. Marcion was excommunicated from the Catholic Church because he was threatening to make schisms in the church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnosis.org/library/marcion/Mead.htm Mead 1931, pp.241-249]&lt;/ref&gt;

Marcion used his personal wealth, (particularly a donation returned to him by the Catholic Church after he was excommunicated), to fund an ecclesiastical organization. Marcionism continued in the [[Western world|West]] for 300 years, although Marcionistic ideas persisted much longer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.berdyaev.com/berdiaev/berd_lib/1928_336.html Berdyaev Online Library]&lt;/ref&gt;

The organization continued in the [[Eastern world|East]] for some centuries later, particularly outside the [[Byzantine Empire]] in areas which later would be dominated by [[Manichaeism]].

===Schism within Marcionism===
By the reign of emperor [[Commodus]] Marcionism was divided into various opinions with various leaders; among whom was Apelles, whom [[Rhodo]] describes as: &quot;...priding himself on his manner of life and his age, acknowledges one principle, but says that the prophecies are from an opposing principle, being led to this view by the responses of a maiden by name Philumene, who was possessed by a demon&quot;.

But others, among whom were Potitus and Basilicus, held to two principles, as did Marcion himself. Others consider that there are not only two, but three natures. Of these, Syneros was the leader and chief.&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius of Caesarea, ''Ecclesiastical History'', Book v. Chapter xiii.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Teachings==

The premise of Marcionism is that many of the [[Ministry of Jesus|teachings of Christ]] are incompatible with the actions of  the [[Yahweh|God of the Old Testament]]. Focusing on the [[Pauline Christianity|Pauline traditions]] of the Gospel, Marcion felt that all other conceptions of the Gospel, and especially any association with the Old Testament religion, was opposed to, and a [[backsliding]] from, the truth. He further regarded the arguments of Paul regarding [[law and gospel]], wrath and grace, works and faith, flesh and spirit, sin and righteousness, death and life, as the essence of religious truth.  He ascribed these aspects and characteristics as two principles, the righteous and wrathful God of the Old Testament, who is at the same time identical with the creator of the world, and a second God of the Gospel, quite unknown before Christ, who is only love and mercy.&lt;ref&gt;[[Adolf von Harnack]], ''History of Dogma'', vol. 1, ch. 5, [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/harnack/dogma1.ii.iii.v.html#ii.iii.v-Page_269 p. 269]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Marcionites held [[maltheism|maltheistic]] views of the God of the Hebrew Bible (known to some Gnostics as [[Yaltabaoth]]), that he was inconsistent, jealous, wrathful and genocidal, and that the material world he created was defective, a place of suffering; the God who made such a world is a bungling or malicious [[demiurge]]. 

{{cquote|In the God of the [Old Testament] he saw a being whose character was stern justice, and therefore anger, contentiousness and unmercifulness. The law which rules nature and man appeared to him to accord with the characteristics of this God and the kind of law revealed by him, and therefore it seemed credible to him that this God is the creator and lord of the world ({{lang|grc|κοσμοκράτωρ}} [English transliteration: kosmokrator/cosmocrator]). As the law which governs the world is inflexible and yet, on the other hand, full of contradictions, just and again brutal, and as the law of the Old Testament exhibits the same features, so the God of creation was to Marcion a being who united in himself the whole gradations of attributes from justice to malevolence, from obstinacy to inconsistency.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Harnack, ''idem.'', [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/harnack/dogma1.ii.iii.v.html#ii.iii.v-Page_271 p.271]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In Marcionite belief, [[Christ]] was not a [[Jewish Messiah]], but a spiritual entity that was sent by the [[Monad (Gnosticism)|Monad]] to reveal the truth about existence, and thus allowing humanity to escape the earthly trap of the demiurge. Marcion called God, the Stranger God, or the Alien God, in some translations, as this deity had not had any previous interactions with the world, and was wholly unknown. See also the [[Unknown God]] of [[Hellenistic philosophy|Hellenism]].

In various popular sources, Marcion is often reckoned among the [[Gnostics]], but as the ''Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (3rd ed.)'' puts it, &quot;it is clear that he would have had little sympathy with their mythological speculations&quot; (p.&amp;nbsp;1034). In 1911 [[Henry Wace (Anglican priest)|Henry Wace]] stated: 

{{cquote|A modern divine would turn away from the dreams of [[Valentinius|Valentinianism]] in silent contempt; but he could not refuse to discuss the question raised by Marcion, whether there is such opposition between different parts of what he regards as the word of God, that all cannot come from the same author.}}

A primary difference between Marcionites and Gnostics was that the Gnostics based their theology on ''secret wisdom'' (as, for example, [[Valentinius]] who claimed to receive the ''secret wisdom'' from [[Theudas (teacher of Valentinius)|Theudas]] who received it direct from Paul) of which they claimed to be in possession, whereas Marcion based his theology on the contents of the Letters of Paul and the recorded sayings of Jesus &amp;mdash; in other words, an argument from scripture, with Marcion defining what was and was not scripture. Also, the [[Christology]] of the Marcionites is thought to have been primarily [[Docetism|Docetic]], denying the human nature of Christ. This may have been due to the unwillingness of Marcionites to believe that Jesus was the son of both God the Father and the demiurge. Classical Gnosticism, by contrast, held that Jesus was the son of both, even having a natural human father; that he was both the Messiah of Judaism and the world Savior.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}  Scholars of [[Early Christianity]] disagree on whether to classify Marcion as a Gnostic: [[Adolf Von Harnack]] does not classify Marcion as a Gnostic,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webcom.com/gnosis/library/marcion/Harnack.html Article on Adolf Von Harnack]&lt;/ref&gt; whereas [[G. R. S. Mead]] does.&lt;ref&gt;[[G. R. S. Mead]], ''Fragments of a Faith Forgotten: Some Short Sketches among the Gnostics of the First Two Centuries'' (London, 1906), [http://books.google.com/books?id=TgRv8m2WGy8C&amp;pg=PA246&amp;dq=%22it+is+evident+that+the+Marcionite+tradition%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Tu09TYKOMsOclgexprH-Bg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=%22it%20is%20evident%20that%20the%20Marcionite%20tradition%22&amp;f=false p. 246.]&lt;/ref&gt; Von Harnack argued that Marcion was not a Gnostic in the strict sense because Marcion rejected elaborate creation myths, and did not claim to have special revelation or secret knowledge. Mead claimed Marcionism makes certain points of contact with Gnosticism in its view that the creator of the material world is not the true deity, rejection of materialism and affirmation of a transcendent, purely good spiritual realm in opposition to the evil physical realm, the belief Jesus was sent by the &quot;True&quot; God to save humanity, the central role of Jesus in revealing the requirements of salvation, the belief Paul had a special place in the transmission of this &quot;wisdom&quot;, and its docetism. According to the 1911 [[Encyclopædia Britannica]] article on Maricon:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/MAL_MAR/MARCION.html |title=MARCION - Online Information article about MARCION |publisher=Encyclopedia.jrank.org |date= |accessdate=2012-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|It was no mere school for the learned, disclosed no mysteries for the privileged, but sought to lay the foundation of the Christian community on the pure [[gospel]], the authentic institutes of [[Christ]]. The pure gospel, however, Marcion found to be everywhere more or less corrupted and mutilated in the Christian circles of his time. His undertaking thus resolved itself into a reformation of [[Christendom]]. This reformation was to deliver Christendom from [[Judaizers|false Jewish doctrines]] by restoring the [[Pauline Christianity|Pauline conception of the gospel]], Paul being, according to Marcion, the only [[Twelve apostles|apostle]] who had rightly understood the new message of [[salvation]] as delivered by Christ. In Marcion's own view, therefore, the founding of his church—to which he was first driven by opposition—amounts to a reformation of Christendom through a return to the gospel of Christ and to Paul; nothing was to be accepted beyond that. This of itself shows that it is a mistake to reckon Marcion among the [[Gnostics]]. A [[dualist]] he certainly was, but he was not a Gnostic.}}

Marcionism shows the influence of [[Hellenistic]] philosophy on Christianity, and presents a moral critique of the Old Testament from the standpoint of [[Platonism]]. According to Harnack, the sect may have led other Christians to introduce a formal statement of beliefs into their liturgy (see [[Creed]]) and to formulate a canon of authoritative [[sacred text|Scripture]] of their own, thus [[Development of the New Testament canon|eventually producing the current canon of the New Testament]]. 

{{cquote|As for the main question, however, whether he knew of, or assumes the existence of, a written New Testament of the Church in any sense whatever, in this case an affirmatory answer is most improbable, because if this were so he would have been compelled to make a direct attack upon the New Testament of the Church, and if such an attack had been made we should have heard of it from Tertullian. Marcion, on the contrary, treats the Catholic Church as one that 'follows the Testament of the Creator-God,' and directs the full force of his attack against this Testament and against the falsification of the Gospel and of the Pauline Epistles. His polemic would necessarily have been much less simple if he had been opposed to a Church which, by possessing a New Testament side by side with the Old Testament, had ''ipso facto'' placed the latter under the shelter of the former. In fact Marcion’s position towards the Catholic Church is intelligible, in the full force of its simplicity, only under the supposition that the Church had not yet in her hand any 'litera scripta ''Novi Testamenti''.'&lt;ref&gt;Harnack, ''Origin of the New Testament'', appendix 6, [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/harnack/origin_nt.v.vi.html#v.vi-Page_222 pp. 222-23]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Marcion is believed to have imposed a severe morality on his followers, some of whom suffered in the persecutions. In particular, he refused to re-admit those who recanted their faith under Roman persecution; see also [[Lapsi (Christian)]].

==Marcionite canon==
{{see also|Development of the New Testament canon#Marcion of Sinope}}

[[Tertullian]] claimed Marcion was the first to separate the ''New Testament'' from the ''Old Testament''.&lt;ref&gt;McDonald &amp; Sanders, editors, ''The Canon Debate'', 2002, chapter 18 by Everett Ferguson, page 310, quoting Tertullian's ''De praescriptione haereticorum'' 30: &quot;Since Marcion separated the New Testament from the Old, he is necessarily subsequent to that which he separated, inasmuch as it was only in his power to separate what was previously united. Having been united previous to its separation, the fact of its subsequent separation proves the subsequence also of the man who effected the separation.&quot; Page 308, note 61 adds: &quot;[Wolfram] Kinzig suggests that it was Marcion who usually called his Bible ''testamentum'' [Latin for testament].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  Marcion is said to have gathered [[scripture]]s from Jewish tradition, and juxtaposed these against the sayings and teachings of Jesus in a work entitled the ''Antithesis''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnosis.org/library/marcion/antithes.htm Gnostic Society Library] presentation of Marcion's ''Antithesis''&lt;/ref&gt; Besides the ''Antithesis'', the Testament of the Marcionites was also composed of a ''Gospel of Christ'' which was [[Gospel of Marcion|Marcion's version]] of Luke, and that the Marcionites attributed to Paul, that was different in a number of ways from the version that is now regarded as canonical.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marcionite-scripture.info/Marcionite_Bible.htm Marcionite Research Library] presentation of ''The Gospel of Marcion''&lt;/ref&gt;  It seems to have lacked all prophecies of Christ's coming, as well as the Infancy account, the baptism, and the verses were more terse in general. It also included ten of the [[Pauline Epistles]] (but not the [[Pastoral Epistles]] or the [[Epistle to the Hebrews]], and, according to the Muratonian canon, included a Marcionite pseudo-Paul's [[epistle to the Alexandrians]] and an [[epistle to the Laodiceans]])&lt;ref&gt;Mead 1931.&lt;/ref&gt; In bringing together these texts, Marcion redacted what is perhaps the first [[Development of the New Testament canon|New Testament canon]] on record, which he called the Gospel and the Apostolikon, which reflects his belief in the writings of Jesus and the apostle Paul respectively.

The Prologues to the Pauline Epistles (which are not a part of the text, but short introductory sentences as one might find in modern study Bibles &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/harnack/origin_nt.v.i.html |title=Origin of the New Testament - Christian Classics Ethereal Library |publisher=Ccel.org |date=2005-07-22 |accessdate=2012-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;), found in several older Latin [[codex|codices]], are now widely believed to have been written by Marcion or one of his followers. Harnack notes:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/harnack/origin_nt.iii.ii.html |title=Origin of the New Testament - Christian Classics Ethereal Library |publisher=Ccel.org |date=2005-07-22 |accessdate=2012-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

{{cquote|We have indeed long known that Marcionite readings found their way into the ecclesiastical text of the Pauline Epistles, but now for seven years we have known that Churches actually accepted the Marcionite prefaces to the Pauline Epistles! De Bruyne has made one of the finest discoveries of later days in proving that those prefaces, which we read first in [[Codex Fuldensis]] and then in numbers of later manuscripts, are Marcionite, and that the Churches had not noticed the cloven hoof.}}

Conversely, several early Latin codices contain Anti-Marcionite prologues to the Gospels.

==Reaction to Marcion by early Christians==

According to a remark by [[Origen]] (''Commentary on the Gospel of Matthew'' 15.3), Marcion &quot;prohibited allegorical interpretations of the scripture&quot;. [[Tertullian]] disputed this in his treatise against Marcion, as did [[Henry Wace (Anglican priest)|Henry Wace]]: 

{{cquote|The story proceeds to say that he asked the Roman presbyters to explain the texts, &quot;A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit,&quot; and &quot;No man putteth a piece of new cloth unto an old garment,&quot; texts from which he himself deduced that works in which evil is to be found could not proceed from the good God, and that the Christian dispensation could have nothing in common with the Jewish. Rejecting the explanation offered him by the presbyters, he broke off the interview with a threat to make a schism in their church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/info/marcion-wace.html Wace's article on Marcion]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Tertullian, along with [[Epiphanius of Salamis]], also charged that Marcion set aside the gospels of Matthew, Mark and John, and used [[Gospel of Luke|Luke]] alone.&lt;ref&gt;From the perspectives of Tertullian and Epiphanius (when the four gospels had largely canonical status, perhaps in reaction to the challenge created by Marcion), it appeared that Marcion rejected the non-Lukan gospels, however, in Marcion's time, it may be that the only gospel he was familiar with from Pontus was the gospel that would later be called Luke. It is also possible that Marcion's gospel was actually modified by his critics to became the gospel we know today as Luke, rather than the story from his critics that he changed a canonical gospel to get his version. For example, compare Luke 5:39 to 5:36-38, did Marcion delete 5:39 from his Gospel or was it added later to counteract a Marcionist interpretation of 5:36-38? One must keep in mind that we only know of Marcion through his critics and they considered him a major threat to the form of Christianity that they knew. John Knox (the modern writer, not to be confused with [[John Knox]] the Protestant Reformer) in ''Marcion and the New Testament: An Essay in the Early History of the Canon'' (ISBN 0-404-16183-9) proposed that Marcion's Gospel may have preceded Luke's Gospel and Acts.[http://ontruth.com/marcion.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Tertullian cited Luke 6:43-45 (a good tree does not produce bad fruit)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tertullian.org/articles/evans_marc/evans_marc_04book1_eng.htm Tertullian &quot;Against Marcion&quot; 1.2]&lt;/ref&gt; and Luke 5:36-38 (nobody tears a piece from a new garment to patch an old garment or puts [[New Wine into Old Wineskins|new wine in old wineskins]]),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tertullian.org/articles/evans_marc/evans_marc_10book4_eng.htm Tertullian &quot;Against Marcion&quot; 4.11.9]&lt;/ref&gt; in theorizing that Marcion set about to recover the authentic teachings of Jesus. [[Irenaeus]] claimed, 

{{cquote|[Marcion's] salvation will be the attainment only of those souls which had learned his doctrine; while the body, as having been taken from the earth, is incapable of sharing in salvation.&lt;ref&gt;''[[On the Detection and Overthrow of the So-Called Gnosis|Against Heresies]]'', [http://ccel.org/fathers2/ANF-01/anf01-58.htm#P6650_1591742 1.27.3]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Tertullian also attacked this view in ''[[De Carne Christi]]''.

[[Hippolytus (writer)|Hippolytus]] reported that Marcion's phantasmal (and Docetist) Christ was &quot;revealed as a man, though not a man&quot;, and did not really die on the cross.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tertullian.org/articles/evans_marc/evans_marc_02intro.htm Tertullian ''Adversus Marcionem'' (&quot;Against Marcion&quot;)], translated and edited by Ernest Evans&lt;/ref&gt; However, Ernest Evans, in editing this work, observes:

{{cquote|This may not have been Marcion's own belief. It was certainly that of Hermogenes (cf. Tertullian, ''Adversus Hermogenem'') and probably other gnostics and Marcionites, who held that the intractability of this matter explains the world's many imperfections.}}

==Recent scholarship==

In ''Lost Christianities'', [[Bart Ehrman]] contrasts the Marcionites with the [[Ebionites]] as polar ends of a spectrum with regard to the Old Testament.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beliefnet.com/story/150/story_15091_1.html Interview with Bart Ehrman about Lost Christianities]&lt;/ref&gt; Ehrman acknowledges many of Marcion's ideas are very close to what is known today as &quot;Gnosticism&quot;, especially its rejection of the Jewish God, the Old Testament, and the material world, and his elevation of Paul as the primary apostle. In the PBS documentary, [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/religion/ From Jesus to Christ], narrated by [[Elaine Pagels]], Ehrman, [[Karen King]], and other secular New Testament scholars, Marcion's role in the formation of the [[Development of the New Testament canon|New Testament canon]] is discussed as pivotal, and the first to explicitly state it. There were early Christian groups, such as the Ebionites, that did not accept Paul as part of their canon.

Robert M. Price, a New Testament scholar at Johnnie Colemon Theological Seminary, considers the Pauline canon problem:&lt;ref&gt;[http://depts.drew.edu/jhc/Rpcanon.html ''The Evolution of the Pauline Canon'' by Robert Price]&lt;/ref&gt; how, when, and who collected Paul's epistles to the various churches as a single collection of epistles. The evidence that the early church fathers, such as Clement, knew of the Pauline epistles is unclear. Price investigates several historical scenarios and comes to the conclusion and identifies Marcion as the first person known in recorded history to collect Paul's writings to various churches together as a canon, the Pauline epistles. Robert Price summarizes, 

{{cquote|But the first collector of the Pauline Epistles had been Marcion. No one else we know of would be a good candidate, certainly not the essentially fictive Luke, Timothy, and Onesimus. And Marcion, as Burkitt and Bauer show, fills the bill perfectly.&lt;ref&gt;Price&lt;/ref&gt;}}

If this is correct, then Marcion's role in the formation and development of Christianity is pivotal.

==Marcionism in Modern history==

Historic Marcionism, and the church Marcion himself established, appeared to die out around the 5th century, although similarities between Marcionism and [[Paulicianism]], a later heresy in the same geographical area, indicate that Marcionist ideas may have survived and even contributed to heresies in Bulgaria and France. Whether or not that is the case, Marcion's influence and criticism of the Old Testament are discussed to this very day. Marcionism is discussed in recent textbooks on early Christianity, such as ''Lost Christianities'' by Bart Ehrman. Marcion claimed to find problems in the Old Testament; problems which many modern thinkers cite today (see [[Criticism of the Bible]] and [[Biblical law in Christianity]]), especially its alleged approval of atrocities and genocide.

Many [[atheists]], [[agnostics]], and [[secular humanists]] agree with Marcion's examples of Bible atrocities, and cite the same passages of the Old Testament to discredit Christianity and Judaism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infidels.org/library/modern/donald_morgan/atrocity.html Biblical Atrocities], compiled by Donald Morgan&lt;/ref&gt; Most Christians agree with Marcion that the Old Testament's alleged approval of genocide and murder are inappropriate models to follow today.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} Some Christian scholars, such as [[Gleason Archer]] and [[Norman Geisler]], have dedicated much of their time to the attempt to resolve these perceived difficulties, while others have argued that ''just punishments'' (divine or human), even capital punishments, are not genocide or murder because murder and genocide are ''unjustified'' by definition (see [[Christian Reconstructionism]]).

On the other hand, because of the rejection of the Old Testament which originates in the [[Jewish Bible]], the Marcionites have been believed by some [[Christian]]s to be [[anti-Semitism|anti-Jewish]]. Indeed, the word ''Marcionism'' has sometimes been used in modern times to refer to anti-[[Jewish]] tendencies in Christian churches, especially when such tendencies have been thought to be surviving residues of ancient Marcionism.

During the [[Nazi Germany|Nazi]] period, some aspects of Marcion's ideas were appropriated by the [[German Christians]]. They advocated a complete rejection of everything Jewish in Christianity, which they termed &quot;[[Positive Christianity]]&quot;. These ideas fell out of favor after Germany's defeat in World War II. (See also [[Nazism and Religion]])

For some, the postulated problems of the Old Testament, and the appeal of Jesus are such that they identify themselves as modern day Marcionites, and follow his solution in keeping the New Testament as sacred scripture, and rejecting the Old Testament canon and practices. A term sometimes used for these groups is &quot;New Testament Only Christians&quot;. [[Carroll R. Bierbower]] is a pastor of a church he says is Marcionite in theology and practice.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marcionite-scripture.info/Carroll_Bierbower.htm The Antithesis], by Dr. Carroll R. Bierbower.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Cathar]] movement, historically and in modern times, reject the Old Testament for the reasons Marcion enunciated. It remains unclear whether the 11th century Cathar movement is in continuation of earlier Gnostic and Marcion streams, or represents an independent re-invention. [[John Lindell]], a former Methodist and Unitarian Universalist pastor, advocates Christian [[deism]], which does not include the Old Testament as part of its theology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://christiandeistfellowship.com/ The Human Jesus and Christian Deism]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Antitactae]]
*[[Antinomianism]]
*[[Christianity and Judaism]]
*[[Christology]]
*[[Gnosticism]]
*[[God as the Devil]]
*[[Montanism]]

==Notes==
{{Cleanup-link rot|date=March 2012}}
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Commons category|Marcion}}

==References==
* Baker, David L., ''Two Testaments, One Bible'' (second edn; Leicester: Inter-Varsity, 1991): pp.&amp;nbsp;35, 48-52.
* Legge, Francis, ''Forerunners and Rivals of Christianity, From 330 B.C. to 330 A.D. '' (1914), reprinted in two volumes bound as one, University Books New York, 1964. LC Catalog 64-24125.
* McGowan, Andrew, Associate Professor of Early Christian History at the Episcopal Divinity School, Cambridge, Massachusetts [http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/journal_of_early_christian_studies/v009/9.3mcgowan.html ''Journal of Early Christian Studies'', Vol. 9]
* Mead, G.R.S., [http://www.gnosis.org/library/marcion/Mead.htm ''Gospel of Marcion Fragments of a Faith Forgotten''], London and Benares, 1900; 3rd Edition 1931.
* Price, Robert M. [http://depts.drew.edu/jhc/Rpcanon.html ''The Evolution of the Pauline Canon''].
*Riparelli, Enrico, ''Il volto del Cristo dualista. Da Marcione ai catari'', Peter Lang, Bern - Berlin - Bruxelles - Frankfurt am Main - New York - Oxford - Wien 2008, 368 pp.&amp;nbsp;ISBN 978-3-03911-490-0

==External links==
*[http://www.marcionite-scripture.info/ The Marcionite Research Library]
*{{CathEncy|wstitle=Marcionites}}

[[Category:144 establishments]]
[[Category:Nontrinitarianism]]
[[Category:Schisms in Christianity]]
[[Category:Ancient Christian controversies]]
[[Category:Christian denominations, unions, and movements established in the 2nd century]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Heresy in Christianity]]

[[bg:Маркионизъм]]
[[ca:Marcionisme]]
[[cs:Markionismus]]
[[de:Markionismus]]
[[es:Marcionismo]]
[[eo:Marciono]]
[[fa:مرقیونیه]]
[[gl:Marcionismo]]
[[ia:Marcionismo]]
[[it:Marcionismo]]
[[he:מרקיוניזם]]
[[lt:Markionizmas]]
[[nl:Marcionisme]]
[[pl:Marcjonizm]]
[[pt:Marcionismo]]
[[ro:Marcionism]]
[[ru:Маркионитство]]
[[simple:Marcionism]]
[[sr:Маркионство]]
[[sh:Markionstvo]]
[[fi:Markionismi]]
[[zh:馬吉安主義]]</text>
      <sha1>ixvqjj8efuxirfevj7avccnpiyvlu74</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
