<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Marian apparition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>85106</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522452190</id>
      <parentid>522452132</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T08:58:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>125.60.209.72</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Our Lady of Laus */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="89679">[[File:Fra bartolomeo 02 Vision of St Bernard with Sts Benedict and John the Evangelist.jpg|thumb|right|270px|''The Vision of St Bernard'', by [[Fra Bartolommeo]], c. 1504 ([[Uffizi]]).]]
[[File:Marian apparitions around the world.jpg|thumb|Marian apparitions around the world]]

A '''Marian apparition''' is an event in which someone believes the [[Blessed Virgin Mary (Roman Catholic)|Blessed Virgin Mary]] has [[supernatural]]ly appeared to one or more people. They are often named after the town where they were reported, or on the [[sobriquet]] given to Mary on the occasion of the apparition. They have been interpreted in [[religious]] terms as [[theophany|theophanies]].

Marian apparitions sometimes are reported to recur at the same site over an extended period of time. In the majority of Marian apparitions only a few people report having witnessed the apparition. Exception to this include [[Zeitoun apparitions|Zeitoun]], and [[Our Lady of Assiut|Assiut]] where thousands claimed to have seen her over a period of time.

==Apparitions and appearances==
[[File:Newspaper fatima.jpg|thumb|right|275px|A photostatic copy of a page from ''Ilustração Portuguesa'', October 29, 1917, showing the crowd looking at the [[miracle of the sun]] during the Fátima apparitions (attributed to the [[Blessed Virgin Mary (Roman Catholic)|Blessed Virgin Mary]])]]
The term &quot;appearance&quot; has been used in different apparitions within a wide range of contexts and experiences. And its use has been different with respect to Marian apparitions and [[visions of Jesus and Mary|visions of Jesus Christ]].

In some apparitions such as [[Our Lady of Lourdes]] or [[Our Lady of Fátima]] an actual vision is reported, fully resembling that of a person being present. In some of these reports the viewers (at times children) do not initially report that they saw the Virgin Mary, but that they saw &quot;''a Lady''&quot; (often but not always dressed in white) and had a conversation with her. In these cases the viewers report experiences that resemble the visual and verbal interaction with a person present at the site of the apparition. In most cases, there are no clear indications as to the auditory nature of the experience, i.e. whether the viewers heard the voices via airwaves or an &quot;interior&quot; or subjective sense of communication. Yet, the 1973 messages of [[Our Lady of Akita]], are due to Sister [[Agnes Katsuko Sasagawa]] who had been totally deaf before 1973 (and remained deaf until 1982 when she was cured during Sunday Mass as foretold in her messages), suggesting means of communication other than airwaves.

In some apparitions just an image is reported, often with no verbal interaction, and no conversation. An example is the reported apparitions at [[Our Lady of Assiut]] in which many people reported a bright image atop a building, accompanied by photographs of the image. The photographs at times suggest the silhouette of a statue of the Virgin Mary but the images are usually subject to varying interpretations, and critics suggest that they may just be due to various visual effects of unknown origin. However, such ''image-like'' appearances are hardly ever reported for [[visions of Jesus and Mary]]. In most cases these involve some form of reported communication.

And apparitions should be distinguished from [[interior locutions]] in which no visual contact is claimed. In some cases of reported interior locutions such as those of Father [[Stefano Gobbi]] a large amount of text is produced, but no visual contact is claimed. Interior locutions usually do not include an auditory component, but consist of inner voices. Interior locutions are generally not classified as apparitions.

Physical contact is hardly ever reported as part of Marian apparitions, unlike in cases of interaction with [[Jesus Christ]]. In rare cases a physical artifact is reported in apparitions. A well known example is the image of [[Our Lady of Guadalupe]], which is reported to have been miraculously imprinted on the cloak of Saint [[Juan Diego]].

==Catholic belief==
[[File:Eternal father painting guadalupe.jpg|thumb|200px|right|[[God the Father|Eternal Father]] painting the [[Virgin of Guadalupe]]. Anonymous, 18th century, an example of [[Roman Catholic Marian art]] related to an apparition]]
According to the doctrine of the Catholic Church, the era of public revelation ended with the death of the last living [[Twelve Apostles|Apostle]]. A Marian apparition, if deemed genuine by Church authority, is treated as [[private revelation]] that may emphasize some facet of the received public revelation for a specific purpose, but it can never add anything new to the deposit of faith. The Church will confirm an apparition as worthy of belief, but belief is never required by divine faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Private and public revelation | work=Catholic Culture | url=http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/most/getwork.cfm?worknum=162 | accessdate=January 11, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Holy See]] has officially confirmed the apparitions at [[Our Lady of Guadalupe|Guadalupe]], [[Saint-Étienne-le-Laus]], Paris (Rue du Bac, [[Miraculous Medal]]), [[La Salette, Isère|La Salette]], [[Our Lady of Lourdes|Lourdes]], [[Our Lady of Fátima|Fátima]], [[Pontmain]], [[Beauraing]], and [[Our Lady of Banneux|Banneux]].&lt;ref&gt;John Delaney, ''A Woman Clothed with the Sun''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.circleofprayer.com/approved-apparitions.html Circle of Prayer - Apparitions &amp; Private Revelation&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

As a historical pattern, Vatican approval of apparitions seems to have followed general acceptance of a vision by well over a century in most cases. According to Father Salvatore M. Perrella of the [[Marianum|Marianum Pontifical Institute]] in Rome, of the 295 reported apparitions studied by the [[Holy See]] through the centuries only 12 have been approved, the latest being the May 2008 approval of the 17th- and 18th-century apparitions of [[Our Lady of Laus]].&lt;ref&gt;Vatican News on [[Benoite Rencurel]] http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/avantgo/new.php?n=12546&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Catholic News on [[Benoite Rencurel]] http://www.catholic.org/international/international_story.php?id=27848&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Catholic News http://catholicnewsagency.com/new.php?n=12546&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Catholic News http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/new.php?n=12588&lt;/ref&gt; Other apparitions continue to be approved at the local level, e.g. the December, 2010 local approval of the 19th-century apparitions of [[Our Lady of Good Help]], the first recognized apparition in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/news/wisconsin-chapel-approved-as-first-us-marian-apparition-site/ Wisconsin chapel approved as first US Marian apparition site]&lt;/ref&gt;

An authentic apparition is believed not to be a subjective experience, but a real and objective intervention of divine power. The purpose of such apparitions is to recall and emphasize some aspect of the Christian message. The church states that cures and other miraculous events are not the purpose of Marian apparitions, but exist primarily to validate and draw attention to the message.&lt;ref&gt;''Dictionary of Mary'', Catholic Book Publishing Co. New York. 1985, Imprimatur, p25-26&lt;/ref&gt; Apparitions of Mary are held as evidence of her continuing active presence in the life of the church, through which she &quot;cares for the brethren of her son who still journey on earth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Papal Encyclical ''Lumen Gentium'' 62, Vatican.&lt;/ref&gt;

Not all claims of visitations are dealt with favourably by the Roman Catholic Church. For example, claimed apparitions of Our Lady, under the title of &quot;Our Lady of the Roses, Mary, Help of Mothers&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roses.org Roses.org]&lt;/ref&gt;, Jesus Christ and various saints at [[Bayside, Queens|Bayside, New York]] have not been condoned or sanctioned in any way, nor those at the [[Necedah Shrine]] in [[Necedah, Wisconsin|Necedah]], [[Wisconsin]]. The behavior of Ms [[Veronica Lueken]] and Mary Ann Van Hoof, who claimed these heavenly favors, was deemed not to compare favorably with the &quot;quiet pragmatism&quot; of St. [[Bernadette Soubirous]] — Church authorities are said to use Bernadette as a model by which to judge all who purport to have visitations. Indeed, both women seriously criticized the Roman Catholic Church hierarchy, allegedly even harshly, and Mrs. Van Hoof is said to have subsequently left Roman Catholicism for an independent local [[Old Catholic Church]].

Possibly the best-known apparition sites are [[Our Lady of Lourdes|Lourdes]] and [[Our Lady of Fátima|Fátima]]&lt;ref&gt;''Dictionary of Mary'', Catholic Book Publishing Co. New York. 1985, Imprimatur, p25&lt;/ref&gt; Over sixty spontaneous healings, out of thousands reported at the Lourdes Spring, have been classified as &quot;inexplicable&quot; by the [[physician]]s of the Lourdes Bureau, a medical centre set up by the Church in association with local medical institutes to assess possible miracles. The [[Three Secrets of Fátima]] received a great deal of attention in the Catholic and secular press.

===Criteria for evaluating apparitions===
{{Roman Catholic Mariology}}
{{see also|Normae Congregationis}}
In 1978 the Sacred [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] (formerly ''of the Holy Office'') issued &quot;Norms of the Congregation for Proceeding in Judging Alleged Apparitions and Revelations&quot; containing the following provisions:&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ewtn.org/vexperts/showmessage_print.asp?number=419853&amp;language=en&lt;/ref&gt;
* The diocesan bishop can initiate a process on his own initiative or at the request of the faithful to investigate the facts of an alleged apparition. The bishop may refrain from looking into it if he chooses, especially if he thinks that not much will come of the event.
* The national conference of bishops may intervene if the local diocesan bishop refers it to him or if the event becomes important nationally or at least in more than one diocese.
* The Apostolic See (the [[Holy See|Vatican]]) can also intervene at the request of the local bishop himself, at the request of a group of the faithful, or on its own initiative.

The steps of the investigation are mandated as follows:
An initial evaluation of the facts of the alleged event, based on both positive and negative criteria:
:Positive Criteria
::# moral certainty (the certainty required to act morally in a situation of doubt) or at least great probability as to the existence of a private revelation at the end of a serious investigation into the case
::# evaluation of the personal qualities of the person in question (mental balance, honesty, moral life, sincerity, obedience to Church authority, willingness to practice faith in the normal way, etc.)
::# evaluation of the content of the revelations themselves (that they do not disagree with faith and morals of the Church, freedom from theological errors)
::# the revelation results in healthy devotion and spiritual fruits in people's lives (greater prayer, greater conversion of heart, works of charity that result, etc.)
:Negative Criteria
::# glaring errors in regard to the facts
::# doctrinal errors attributed to God, the Blessed Virgin Mary, or to the Holy Spirit in how they appear
::# any pursuit of financial gain in relation to the alleged event
::# gravely immoral acts committed by the person or those associated with the person at the time of the event
::# psychological disorders or tendencies on the part of the person or persons associated

After this initial investigation, if the occurrence meets the criteria, positive and negative, an initial cautionary permission can be granted that states: &quot;for the moment, there is nothing opposed to it&quot;. This permits public participation in the devotion in regard to the alleged apparition.

Ultimately, a final judgment and determination needs to be given, giving approval or condemnation of the event.

===Local diocese approval===
If the local bishop authorizes devotion inspired by an apparition to proceed based on an initial assessment, that permission does not constitute formal approval, which recognizes an event as being supernatural in origin. Such approval may follow years or even centuries later. A recent example of such a delay is the case of [[Our Lady of Laus]], in which devotion was approved by the local diocese in 1665, but obtained formal recognition as a supernatural event only in 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;catholic&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/news/vatican_recognizes_marian_apparitions_in_france/
|title = Vatican recognizes Marian apparitions in France
|publisher =Catholic News Agency
|accessdate =2011-02-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/view.cfm?id=8296
|publisher=Catholic World News (republished from ''The Wanderer'')
|author=Paul Likoudis
|accessdate=2011-02-20
|title=Our Lady of Laus Now On a Par with Lourdes
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=perrella&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/new.php?n=12588
|publisher=Catholic News Agency
|date=8 May 2008
|title=Expert explains Church’s criteria for confirming Marian apparitions
|accessdate=22 February 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Moreover, Marian apparitions often involve complications at the local diocese, and a letter of approval or disapproval from a local bishop, does not automatically signal approval or denial. A recent example is the apparitions of [[Our Lady of Kibeho]] in the 1980s in [[Kibeho]], [[Rwanda]]. In 1982 the teenagers who saw the visions reported truly gruesome sights and said that the Virgin Mary asked everyone to pray to prevent a terrible war. Some today regard the visions as an ominous foreshadowing of the [[Rwandan Genocide]] of 1994, and particularly in that specific location in 1995, where some teenagers died a decade after their vision. The apparitions were accepted by the local bishop (accused by many of complicity in the genocide himself), but have not been given final approval by the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]].&lt;ref&gt;Our Lady of Kibeho [http://www.michaeljournal.org/kibeho.htm Our Lady of Sorrows]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/OLKIBEHO.HTM EWTN on Our Lady of Kibeho]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kibeho article&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anzacday.org.au/history/peacekeeping/anecdotes/kibeho.html UN Report on Kibeho]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Apparitions and statues===
Marian apparitions are sometimes reported along with [[weeping statues]] of the [[BVM(RC)|Virgin Mary]]. However, to date only one single example of a combined weeping statue and apparition (namely [[Our Lady of Akita]]) has been approved by the [[Holy See|Vatican]] and the rest have usually been dismissed as hoaxes.

==Impact of apparitions==
[[File:Notre-Dame du Laus (Pindreau - 2).JPG|thumb|265px|right|Monument with a representation of an apparition of [[Our Lady of Laus|Our Lady]] to [[Benoîte Rencurel]], the shepherdess visionary from [[Saint-Étienne-le-Laus]], [[France]].]]

While Marian apparitions may at times seem like fanciful tales even to devout Catholics, factual analysis indicates that the effect of apparitions on the Roman Catholic Church has been significant. Marian apparitions have led to, or affected, the Catholic Church, [[Roman Catholic Mariology]] and the lives of millions of Roman Catholics in several ways:

:* The conversion of millions of people to Roman Catholicism.
:* The construction of some of the largest [[Roman Catholic Marian churches]] ever.
:* The formation of the largest [[Marian Movements and Societies]] ever.
:* The spread of Marian devotions (such as the [[rosary]]) to millions of people.
:* The declaration of specific Marian dogmas and doctrines.
:* Hundreds of millions of Marian pilgrimages.

A few cases can illustrate these items.

===Conversions and shrines===
[[File:Basilica-PlazaMariana.jpg|thumb|270px|left|[[Basilica of Our Lady of Guadalupe]] in [[Mexico City]].]]
By all accounts, when [[Juan Diego]], age 57, reported the apparition of [[Our Lady of Guadalupe]] on [[Tepeyac]] hill in Mexico in 1531, he did not receive a lot of attention in [[Rome]], since the Church was busy with the challenges of the [[Protestant Reformation]] of 1521 to 1579 and perhaps very few Cardinals in Rome had ever heard the details of Mexico and its environs. Yet, just as a large number of people were leaving the Catholic Church in Europe as a result of the Reformation, [[Our Lady of Guadalupe]] was instrumental in adding almost 8 million people to the ranks of Catholics in the Americas between 1532 and 1538. The number of Catholics in South America has grown significantly over the centuries. Eventually with tens of millions of followers, Juan Diego had an effect on [[Roman Catholic Mariology|Mariology]] in the Americas and beyond, and was eventually declared [[venerable]] in 1987. Juan Diego was declared a [[saint]] in 2002. Furthermore, the [[Basilica of Our Lady of Guadalupe]] on [[Tepeyac]] hill in Mexico is now the third largest Catholic Church in the world, after [[Saint Peter's Basilica]] in Rome and the [[Basilica of the National Shrine of Our Lady of Aparecida]] in Brazil. Recent reported apparitions such as [[Medjugorje]] have also attracted a large following.

===Societies and devotions===
The Marian apparition of [[Our Lady of Fátima]] on a remote mountain top to three young Portuguese children in 1917 also seemed fanciful and the local administrator initially jailed the children and threatened that he would boil them one by one in a pot of oil. However, over the years the effect of Fátima has been undeniable. With over 25 million registered Catholic members, the [[Blue Army of Our Lady of Fátima]] (which was approved by [[Pope Pius XII]] in 1947) is the largest [[Marian Society]] in the world. And the message of Fátima has inspired the spread of other devotions. An example is [[Our Lady's Rosary Makers]] formed by Brother [[Sylvan Mattingly]] in 1949 with $25 to distribute free rosaries, based on his devotion to Fátima. [[Our Lady's Rosary Makers]] has since distributed hundreds of millions of free rosaries to Catholic missions worldwide.

===Mariology===
[[File:Inmaculada Concepcion (La Colosal).jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Bartolomé Esteban Murillo|Murillo]]'s [[Immaculate Conception]], 1650]]
Marian apparitions such as [[Our Lady of Lourdes]] (which promoted [[Immaculate Conception]]) have also influenced the direction of [[Roman Catholic Mariology]], as illustrated by the ''[[ex cathedra]]'' exercise of [[Papal infallibility]] on the [[Dogma (Roman Catholic)|dogma]] of [[Immaculate Conception]]. This also illustrated that unlike most Roman Catholic theology, which originates from the upper levels of the Church, Mariology has quite often been driven from the ground up by the tens of millions of Catholics with a special devotion to the [[BVM(RC)|Blessed Virgin]]. As Marian apparitions create strong emotions among large numbers of Roman Catholics, they lead to [[sensus fidelium]]. This strong response among Catholics in turn influences the higher levels of the Roman Catholic hierarchy as [[sensus fidei]] gains strength.

To this end, the official [[Holy See|Vatican]] website ''[[Agenzia Fides]]'' stated in 2004 that:

:&quot;The [[dogma]] of the [[Immaculate Conception]] was defined by [[Pius IX]] not so much because of proofs in [[Scripture]] or ancient [[tradition]], but due to a profound [[sensus fidelium]], a century-old sense of the faithful, and the Magisterium&quot;.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.fides.org/eng/approfondire/totustuus/immacolata02.html Agenzia Fides - Congregazione per l'Evangelizzazione dei Popoli&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Vatican quotes in this context the [[encyclical]] [[Fulgens Corona]], where [[Pius XII]] supported such a faith.&lt;ref&gt;Fulgens Corona, 10&lt;/ref&gt; In several Marian teachings, the &quot;theology of the people&quot; such as the immaculate Conception, the profound and century-old sense of the faithful has taken precedence over academic theology.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

===Pilgrimages===
Marian apparitions are also responsible for tens of millions of Marian pilgrimages per year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/ZSHRINE.HTM Zenit News]&lt;/ref&gt; About 5 million pilgrims visit [[Lourdes]] every year and within France only Paris has more hotels than Lourdes. And about 10 million pilgrims visit [[Our Lady of Guadalupe]] each year, where each mass can accommodate up to 40,000 people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stpeter.co.uk/Guadalupe.htm Pilgrims to Our Lady of Guadalupe]&lt;/ref&gt; Thus each decade, just Lourdes and Guadalupe amount to over one hundred million Catholic pilgrimages, based on Marian apparitions to two people on two remote hilltops.

The [[Sanctuary of Our Lady of Fátima]] also attracts a large number of [[Roman Catholics]], and every year pilgrims fill the country road that leads to the shrine with crowds that approach one million on May 13 and October 13, the significant dates of Fatima apparitions.&lt;ref&gt;Trudy Ring, 1996, ''International Dictionary of Historic Places'', ISBN 978-1-884964-02-2 page 245&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, about four million pilgrims visit the basilica every year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-destinations.com/portugal/fatima-shrine-of-our-lady-of-fatima.htm Sacred Destinations]&lt;/ref&gt;

In Canada, millions of Americans and Canadians have visited the national shrine of [[Our Lady of the Cape]], in [[Cap-de-la-Madeleine]], Quebec, where the first pilgrimages began in 1888.

==Historical feasts==
A number of feasts based on historical traditions involving apparitions are celebrated in the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. These apparitions do not technically fall in the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] approved category, since they generally predate the formation of the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] in 1542. They are recognized based on the papal declaration of the feast day rather than formal analysis by the Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith.

===Our Lady of the Pillar===
In the year AD&amp;nbsp;39, according to tradition, the Virgin Mary appeared to [[Saint James the Great]], in [[Zaragoza]], Spain. The vision is now called [[Our Lady of the Pillar]] and is the only reported Marian apparition before her Assumption. The [[Basilica of Our Lady of the Pillar]] was built in Zaragoza, Spain and a key piece of [[Roman Catholic Marian art]], the statue of ''Our Lady of the Pillar'', refers to this apparition.

===Our Lady of the Snow===
[[Our Lady of the Snow]] is based on a legend that during the pontificate of [[Pope Liberius]], during the night of August the 5th, snow fell on the summit of the [[Esquiline Hill]] in Rome. Based on a vision that night, a basilica was built in honour of Our Lady, on the spot that had been covered with snow.

The church built there is now the basilica of [[Santa Maria Maggiore]], and the feast was celebrated at that church for centuries on August 5 each year. However, there was no mention of this alleged miracle in historical records until a few hundred years later, not even by Pope [[Sixtus III]] in his dedicatory inscription, and it may be that the legend has no historical basis. However, in the 14th century the feast was extended to all the churches of Rome and finally it was made a universal feast by Pope [[Pius V]].&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Catholic Encyclopedia (1913)/Our Lady of the Snow|Catholic encyclopedia, Our Lady of the Snow]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Our Lady of Walsingham===
According to the tradition of [[Our Lady of Walsingham]], the Virgin Mary appeared in a vision to [[Richeldis de Faverches]], a devout Saxon noblewoman, in 1061 in Walsingham, England, instructing her to construct a shrine resembling the place of the [[Annunciation]].  The shrine passed into the care of the Canons Regular sometime between 1146 and 1174.

Late in 1538, King [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]]’s soldiers [[Dissolution of the Monasteries|sacked the priory]] at Walsingham, killed two monks and destroyed the shrine.  In 1897 [[Pope Leo XIII]] re-established the restored 14th century Slipper Chapel as a Roman Catholic shrine.  The Holy House had been rebuilt at the Catholic Church of the Annunciation at King's Lynn (Walsingham was part of this Catholic parish in 1897).

Today there are two shrines at Walsingham: the Roman Catholic shrine centered on the Slipper Chapel and the Holy House maintained by the [[Church of England]].  There are also two separate feast days: September 24 in the Roman Catholic Church and October 15 in the [[Anglican Communion]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walsinghamanglican.org.uk/welcome/index.htm Anglican Walsingham shrine]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walsingham.org.uk/romancatholic/history.html Catholic Walsingham shrine]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Our Lady of the Rosary===
The apparition of [[Our Lady of the Rosary]] is by tradition attributed to [[Saint Dominic]] in 1208 in the church of [[Prouille]], in France. According to the attribution, the Virgin Mary appeared to [[Saint Dominic]] and introduced him to the [[rosary]].&lt;ref&gt;Catherine Beebe, ''St. Dominic and the Rosary'' ISBN 0-89870-518-5&lt;/ref&gt;

Some sources suggest that [[Alan de Rupe]] (rather than Saint Dominic) was the major influence on the rosary in the 15th century, while other sources seek a middle ground to these two views.&lt;ref&gt;History of the Rosary http://www.ewtn.com/library/ANSWERS/ROSARYHS.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Catholic Encyclopedia http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13184b.htm&lt;/ref&gt; For centuries, [[Dominican Order|Dominicans]] became instrumental in spreading the rosary and emphasizing the Catholic belief in the [[power of the rosary]].&lt;ref&gt;History of the Dominicans http://www.domcentral.org/study/ashley/ds02ital2.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1571 [[Pope Pius V]] instituted &quot;Our Lady of Victory&quot; as an annual feast to commemorate the victory of [[Battle of Lepanto (1571)|Lepanto]], the victory being attributed to Our Lady. In 1969, [[Pope Paul VI]] changed the name of the feast to [[Our Lady of the Rosary]].&lt;ref&gt;''Calendarium Romanum'' (Libreria Editrice Vaticana, 1969), p. 105&lt;/ref&gt;

===Our Lady of Mount Carmel===
The [[Blessed Virgin Mary]] is said to have appeared to Saint [[Simon Stock]], who was Prior General of the [[Carmelite Order]] in the mid 13th century.&lt;ref&gt;Louis Saggi, O.Carm; [http://carmelnet.org/biographies/SimonStock.pdf Saint Simon Stock (XIII Century) Saint, Priest] - Scholarly historical information&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest reference to the tradition of his Marian apparition, dating from the late 14th century, states that &quot;St. Simon was an [[English people|Englishman]], a man of great holiness and devotion, who always in his prayers asked the [[Blessed Virgin Mary|Virgin]] to favor his Order with some singular privilege. The Virgin appeared to him holding the [[Scapular of Our Lady of Mount Carmel|Brown Scapular]] in her hand saying, 'This is for you and yours a privilege; the one who dies in it will be saved.'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;catholic.net&quot;&gt;Eamon R. Carroll, O.Carm; [http://www.catholic.net/index.php?option=dedestaca&amp;id=3309 Medieval Devotion to Mary Among the Carmelites]&lt;/ref&gt; A scapular is an apron-like garment that forms part of the Carmelite [[religious habit]],&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Jotischky; [http://books.google.com/books?id=gfjHzeh6QBEC&amp;printsec=frontcover ''The Carmelites and Antiquity. Mendicants and their Pasts in the Middle Ages'']. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; and in the original context the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]]'s promise was an assurance that religious who persevered in their [[religious vocation|vocation]] would be saved; beginning in the latter half of the 16th century the small devotional scapular became very popular as a [[sacramentals|sacramental]].&lt;ref name=&quot;catholic.net&quot;/&gt;

The historicity of Saint Simon Stock's vision is disputed,&lt;ref&gt;The Order of Carmelites website; [http://www.ocarm.org/pls/ocarm/consultazione.mostra_pagina?id_pagina=648 Simon Stock]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fr. Kieran Kavanaugh, OCD, Zenit News Service. [http://www.zenit.org/article-23225?l=english Brown Scapular: A Silent Devotion] July 16, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and as a result today neither the liturgy for the Feast of [[Our Lady of Mount Carmel]] (which originally had no association with [[Scapular of Our Lady of Mount Carmel|scapular]] devotion, but became strongly connected with Saint Simon Stock's vision in the 17th century&lt;ref&gt;Herbert Thurston, S.J., [http://books.google.com/books?id=RAUQAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA59&amp;lpg=PA59&amp;dq=%22peter+swanyngton%22+scapular+ecclesiastical&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=9lAt3TSkAE&amp;sig=6xlE3cRcVmdALp20EzS_Z6Tf_RE&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=cY_BSpKNDYvclAf-jpzvBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false &quot;The Origin of the Scapular -- A Criticism.&quot;] ''The Irish Ecclesiastical Record'' Vol XVI July–December 1904. pp. 59-75. Dublin: Browne &amp; Nolan, Limited.&lt;/ref&gt;), nor that of Saint Simon Stock make any reference to the vision of Mary or the scapular.&lt;ref&gt;Bede Edwards, OCDS. ''Carmel Clarion'' Volume XXI, pp 17-22. &quot;St. Simon Stock--The Scapular Vision &amp; the Brown Scapular Devotion.&quot; July–August 2005, Discalced Carmelite Secular Order, Washington Province.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Brown Scapular]] itself remains warmly approved and recommended by the [[Catholic Church]].&lt;ref&gt;In his 2001 &quot;Message to the Carmelite Family&quot; on the occasion of the 750th anniversary of the apparition of Our Lady to St. Simon Stock, Pope John Paul II wrote that &quot;I too have worn the Scapular of Carmel over my heart for a long time!&quot; [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/speeches/2001/documents/hf_jp-ii_spe_20010326_ordine-carmelo_en.html Message of John Paul II to the Carmelite Family] March 25, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; Various devotional sources&lt;ref&gt;Such as [http://www.salvemariaregina.info/SalveMariaRegina/SMR-104.html Fatima and the Scapular], page found 2010-06-24.&lt;/ref&gt; quote an interview with [[Lucia Santos]] in which she speaks about the Brown Scapular, saying &quot;Our Lady wants all to wear the Scapular&quot;, especially when praying the Rosary, because &quot;the ''[[Rosary and Scapular]]'' are inseparable&quot;.

==Approved apparitions==
A Roman Catholic approved Marian apparition is one that has been examined by the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] either based on the criteria listed above (or internal procedures in place before that) and has been granted approval either through the local Bishop based on the direction of the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] or received a direct approval from the [[Holy See]].

Although a local bishop may provide a preliminary assessment (and allow the devotion to proceed forward), formal approval can only be provided after detailed analysis by the [[Holy See]]. For instance, although the apparitions at [[Our Lady of Laus]] were recognized by the local diocese in 1665, they received approval from the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] centuries later, in 2008.

Apparitions favored by the [[Holy See]] usually:

:* Become the site of major [[Roman Catholic Marian churches]] such as [[Lourdes]], France or the [[Basilica of Our Lady of Guadalupe]] on [[Tepeyac]] hill in Mexico.

:* Receive papal visits such as Popes [[Paul VI]]'s, [[John Paul II]]'s and [[Benedict XVI]]'s visits to [[Fátima, Portugal]] and [[Beauraing]], Belgium.

However, a papal visit does not amount to a formal approval.

Some apparitions such as in [[Assiut]], Egypt have been approved by the [[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria|Coptic Church]] and can be called ''approved'' but not Roman Catholic approved.

[[File:Virgen de guadalupe1.jpg|Our Lady of Guadalupe|thumb|right|180px|[[Our Lady of Guadalupe]].]]

===Approved by the Roman Catholic Church===

====Our Lady of Guadalupe====
The 1531 apparition of [[Our Lady of Guadalupe]] was reported by Saint [[Juan Diego]]. He said he saw an early morning vision of the [[BVM(RC)|Virgin Mary]] in which he was instructed to build an abbey on the Hill of [[Tepeyac]] in Mexico. The local prelate did not believe his account and asked for a miraculous sign, which was later provided as an icon of [[Our Lady of Guadalupe]] permanently imprinted on the saint’s cloak where he had gathered roses. Over the years, Our Lady of Guadalupe became a symbol of the Catholic faith in Mexico and the Mexican diaspora.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011|reason=Vatican Source}}

====Our Lady of Laus====
The apparitions of [[Our Lady of Laus]] between 1664 and 1718 in [[Saint-Étienne-le-Laus]], [[France]] to [[Benoîte Rencurel]], a young shepherdess are the first Marian apparitions approved in the 21st century by the [[Roman Catholic Church]].&lt;ref name=&quot;catholic&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url =http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/avantgo/new.php?n=12546| title = Phi Vatican recognizes Marian apparitions in France| publisher =Catholic News Agency| accessdate =2008-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The apparitions were recognized by the diocese of the Roman Catholic Church on September 18, 1665. They were approved by the Vatican on May 5, 2008. Currently, the site where the apparitions took place receives more than 120,000 pilgrims a year.

====Our Lady of the Miraculous Medal====
[[File:Miraculous medal.jpg|thumb|200px|left|The [[Miraculous Medal]]]]
The vision of [[Our Lady of the Miraculous Medal]] is said to have appeared to Saint [[Catherine Labouré]] in 1830 in the convent of [[Rue du Bac, Paris]]. She reported that one night in the chapel, the [[BVM(RC)|Blessed Virgin Mary]] appeared to her and asked that a medallion be made to a design that she dictated. The lady added that, &quot;All who wear this medal will receive great [[Divine grace|graces]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10115a.htm Catholic encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt; After spending two years examining her claims, her priest eventually took the information to his [[archbishop]]. The medal eventually produced came to be referred to as the [[Miraculous Medal]]. The front of the medal displays a picture of the virgin as she appeared to Catherine Labouré. The design on the reverse includes the letter M and a cross. [[Pope John Paul II]] used a slight variation of the reverse image as his coat of arms, the [[Marian Cross]]. This is a plain cross with an M underneath the right-hand bar, to signify the Blessed Virgin standing at the foot of the Cross while Jesus was being crucified.

Sister Justine Bisqueyburu is said to have also had an apparition in 1840 within the same chapel at Rue du Bac as Saint [[Catherine Labouré]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.famvin.org/wiki/Justine_Bisqueyburu Vincentian site]&lt;/ref&gt; These visitations instituted the [[Green Scapular]], which involves a very simple devotion to the [[Immaculate Heart of Mary]] and is associated with healing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenscapular.com/ Society of the Green Scapular].&lt;/ref&gt; The Green Scapular has its own association&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenscapular.com/ Society of the Green Scapular], page found 2010-06-25.&lt;/ref&gt; but has not yet been approved by the [[Holy See]] and does not have an associated confraternity.&lt;ref&gt;Ann Ball, 2003 ''Encyclopedia of Catholic Devotions and Practices'' ISBN 0-87973-910-X page 217&lt;/ref&gt;

====Our Lady of La Salette====
The apparitions of [[Our Lady of La Salette]] were reported in [[La Salette, Isère|La Salette]] in France in 1846 by two [[shepherd]] children, [[Mélanie Calvat]] and [[Maximin Giraud]], followed by numerous accounts of [[miracle|miraculous]] healings. The [[Roman Catholic Church]] investigated the claims and found them basically credible. However, in the late 19th century controversy surrounded the claims of one of the seers, Mélanie Calvat in a France hostile to religion. Recent releases from the [[Vatican Secret Archives]]&lt;ref&gt;Laurentin, René &amp; Corteville, Michel, Découverte du secret de la Salette, Fayard, Paris, 2002, p. 2; The secret was rediscovered October 3, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; may have clarified the situation to some extent, but some controversy still remains attached to this apparition.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011|reason=Vatican Source}}

====Our Lady of Lourdes====
In 1858 Saint [[Bernadette Soubirous]] was a 14-year-old shepherd girl who lived near the town of [[Lourdes]] in France. One day she reported a vision of a [[Our Lady of Lourdes|miraculous Lady]] who identified Herself as &quot;the Immaculate Conception&quot; in subsequent visions. In the second vision she was asked to return again and she had 18 visions overall. According to Saint Bernadette, the Lady held a string of Rosary beads and led Saint Bernadette to the discovery of a buried spring, also requesting that the local priests build a chapel at the site of the visions and lead holy processions there. Eventually, a number of chapels and churches were built at Lourdes as the [[Sanctuary of Our Lady of Lourdes]]—which is now a major Catholic pilgrimage site. One of these churches, the [[Basilica of St. Pius X]] can accommodate 25,000 people and was dedicated by the future [[Pope John XXIII]] when he was the Papal Nuncio to France.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011|reason=Vatican Source}}

====Our Lady of Pontmain====
The apparitions at [[Our Lady of Pontmain]], France also called [[Our Lady of Hope]] were reported in 1871 by a number of young children.&lt;ref name=dayton&gt;[http://campus.udayton.edu/mary/buby/mfl1.htm ''Apparitions of the Modern Era'', Univ.of Dayton]&lt;/ref&gt;

The final approval for the apparitions of Our Lady of Hope was given in 1932 by Eugenio Cardinal Pacelli, who later became [[Pope Pius XII]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

====Our Lady of Fátima====
[[File:ChildrensofFatima.jpg|thumb|right|220px|[[Lúcia Santos|Lúcia dos Santos]] (left) with her cousins [[Jacinta and Francisco Marto]], at [[Fátima, Portugal|Fátima]], Portugal, 1917.]]
The visions of the Virgin Mary appearing to three shepherd children at [[Our Lady of Fátima]] in Portugal in 1917 were declared worthy of belief by the Catholic Church in 1930. Five popes — [[Pope Pius XII|Pius XII]], [[Pope John XXIII|John XXIII]], [[Pope Paul VI|Paul VI]], [[Pope John Paul II|John Paul II]], and [[Pope Benedict XVI|Benedict XVI]] — have supported the Fátima messages as supernatural. John Paul II was particularly attached to Fátima and credited Our Lady of Fátima with saving his life after he was shot in Rome on the Feast Day of Our Lady of Fátima in May 1981. He donated the bullet that wounded him on that day to the [[Sanctuary of Our Lady of Fátima]].&lt;ref&gt;Razaq Raj, 2007, ''Religious Tourism and Pilgrimage Festivals'', ISBN 978-1-84593-225-1 page 214&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas W. Petrisk, 1998, ''The Fatima Prophecies'', St. Andrews Press, ISBN 978-1-891903-30-4 page 285&lt;/ref&gt; Benedict XVI, on May 13, 2010, prayed and gave the second [[Golden Rose]] to Our Lady of Fátima and also pronounced in front of more than 500,000 pilgrims a reference to the Fátima prophecy about the triumph of the [[Immaculate Heart of Mary]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholic.org/international/international_story.php?id=36550&amp;wf=rsscol Catholic Online (www.catholic.org) - Our Lady of Fatima: Pope Benedict's Homily. 'I too Have Come as a Pilgrim']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/homilies/2010/documents/hf_ben-xvi_hom_20100513_fatima_en.html Vatican - Homily of His Holiness Benedict XVI on the occasion of the 10th anniversary of the Beatification of Jacinta and Francisco, young shepherds of Fátima. Esplanade of the Shrine of Our Lady of Fátima. Thursday, 13 May 2010.]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1925, eight years after the Fátima events, [[Lúcia Santos|Sister Lúcia]] reported another set of apparitions, which became known as the [[Pontevedra apparitions]].&lt;ref&gt;[[EWTN]] [http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/bios2000.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Notre Dame University]] [http://www.nd.edu/~mary/classic/firstsat.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Catholic News Agency]] [http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/new.php?n=8654]&lt;/ref&gt; Also [[Alexandrina Maria da Costa|Blessed Alexandrina of Balasar]] reported several apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary (following the Our Lady of Fátima request of [[Pope Pius XII Consecration to the Immaculate Heart of Mary|World Consecration to the Immaculate Heart of Mary]]).&lt;ref&gt;«The Angelus», June 2000, Volume XXIII, No. 6 (Canada) by Rev. Fr. Fabrice Delestre [http://alexandrinabalasar.free.fr/alexandrina_of_portugal_and_the_consecration.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Our Lady of Beauraing====
The 33 apparitions of [[Our Lady of Beauraing]] were reported in Belgium between November 1932 and January 1933 by five local children ranging in age from 9 to 15 years. From 1933 to World War II, pilgrims flocked to the little village of [[Beauraing]]. The final approbation for the apparition was granted on July 2, 1949 under the authority of the [[Holy Office]] by the decree of Andre-Marie Charue, Bishop of [[Namur (city)|Namur]], Belgium.&lt;ref&gt;Ann Ball, 2003 ''Encyclopedia of Catholic Devotions and Practices'' ISBN 0-87973-910-X pages 73-74&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Francois Leuret, 2006 ''Modern Miraculous Cures - A Documented Account Of Miracles And Medicine'' ISBN 1-4067-9918-1 page 63&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matthew Bunson, 2008, The Catholic Almanac, ISBN 978-1-59276-441-9 page 123&lt;/ref&gt; These apparitions are also known as the ''[[Virgin of the Golden Heart]]''.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011|reason=Vatican Source}}

====Our Lady of Banneux====
[[File:Banneux Maagd der armen.jpg|thumb|left|200px|The miraculous spring of [[Our Lady of Banneux]], in [[Belgium]].]]

The apparitions of [[Our Lady of Banneux]] were reported by a young child, [[Mariette Beco]] a native of [[Banneux]], Belgium in the 1930s. They are also known as the [[Virgin of the Poor]]. The apparitions were approved by the Roman Catholic Church in 1949.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Freze, 1993, ''Voices, Visions, and Apparitions'', OSV Publishing ISBN 0-87973-454-X&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;van Houtryve, ''La Vierge des Pauvres'', Banneux, 1947&lt;/ref&gt;

Beco reported eight visions of the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]] between January 15 and March 2, 1933. She reported seeing a Lady in White who declared herself the ''Virgin of the Poor'' and told her: &quot;Believe in me and I will believe in you&quot;. In one vision, the Lady reportedly asked Mariette to drink from a small spring and later said that the spring was for healing. Over time the site drew pilgrims. Today, the small spring yields about 2,000 gallons of water a day with many reports of miraculous healings.&lt;ref&gt;Memorare http://www.memorare.com/mary/app1933.html&lt;/ref&gt;

====Our Lady of Akita====
The apparitions of [[Our Lady of Akita]] were reported in 1973 by Sister [[Agnes Katsuko Sasagawa]] in the remote area of Yuzawadai, near the city of [[Akita, Akita|Akita]] in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://members.chello.nl/~l.de.bondt/Akita.htm Our Lady of Akita]&lt;/ref&gt; For several decades, Agnes Sasagawa had encountered many health problems but her health reportedly improved after drinking water from [[Lourdes]]. After going totally deaf, she went to live with the nuns in the remoteness of Yuzawadai. In 1973 she reported apparitions of the [[BVM(RC)|Virgin Mary]], as well as [[stigmata]] and a weeping statue of the Virgin Mary that continued to weep over the next six years on 101 occasions. According to [[EWTN]], up to November 2011 no ecclesiastical decree appears to exist from the Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith.&lt;ref name=&quot;EWTN on Akita approval&quot;&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/mary/akita.htm EWTN on Akita approval]&lt;/ref&gt;
However, some individuals, such as former Ambassador of the Philippines to the Holy See, Mr. Howard Dee, have stated that they were given private assurances by Cardinal Ratzinger of the authenticity of Akita. ''In any case, in keeping with the current norms, given the absence of a repudiation of Bp. Ito's decision by his successors, or by higher authority, the events of Akita continue to have ecclesiastical approval.''.&lt;ref name=&quot;EWTN on Akita approval&quot;/&gt;

====Approved by a local Church ordinary====
The apparitions of [[San_Francisco_de_Cuapa#Reported apparition of the Virgin Mary|Our Lady of Cuapa]] began on April 15, 1980, in [[San Francisco de Cuapa]], [[Nicaragua]]. The Virgin Mary repeatedly appeared to Bernardo Martinez, a [[sacristan]], and according to the visionary this began when he saw a strange light emanating from a statue of the Virgin Mary in the parish church. In May, when walking through the fields, he claimed that he saw a vision of the Virgin Mary, who encouraged him to pray the rosary and promote peace saying: ''&quot;Make Peace. Don't ask Our Lord for peace because, if you do not make it, there will be no peace&quot;''.&lt;ref&gt;Miriam and Stephen Weglian, &quot;Let Heaven and Earth Unite&quot;, page 24, Faith Publishing Company, Milford Ohio, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; At this time, Nicaragua was going through a civil war. The [[Sandinista]] government was facing armed opposition from the [[Contras]]. Bernardo Martinez claimed that the Blessed Virgin Mary ordered him to burn bad books, which was interpreted to mean Marxist books. The auxiliary [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Managua|Bishop of Managua]] complied with this request. Sandinista commentators responded by describing the apparition as 'Saint Mary of the [[Contras]]', 'Our Lady of [[Oliver North]] and Our Lady of Cuapa.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.envio.org.ni/articulo/3184 &quot;Nicaragua Church-State Relations A Chronology - Part II&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; On November 13, 1982, the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Juigalpa|Bishop of Juigalpa]] released an official statement as Bishop of the area where the apparitions took place assuring the faithful of the authenticity of the events. The apparitions at San Francisco de Cuapa are thus among the few Marian apparitions approved by the [[Catholic Church]] in the twentieth century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.miraclehunter.com/marian_apparitions/statements/index.html#cuapa Miracle Hunter web-site]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, Silvio Sirias wrote a novel, ''&quot;Bernardo and the Virgin&quot;'' based on these events.&lt;ref&gt;Silvio Sirias, Bernardo and the Virgin, Northwestern University Press, 2005 ISBN 978-0-8101-2427-1&lt;/ref&gt;

The apparitions of [[Our Lady of Kibeho]] began on November 28, 1981 in the African college of Kibeho, Rwanda. The Virgin Mary repeatedly appeared to Alphonsine Mumureke, Nathalie Mukamazimpaka, and Marie Claire Mukangango. The apparition identified herself in the native Rwandan dialect as “Nyina wa Jambo&quot;, ( &quot;Mother of the Word&quot;), which is synonymous with &quot;Mother of God.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/OLKIBEHO.HTM] EWTN statement on Kibeho&lt;/ref&gt; The apparitions communicated various messages to the schoolchildren, urging the people to love each other, and warning of an apocalyptic vision of Rwanda descending into violence and hatred, foretelling the 1994 Rwandan Genocide. In 2001 the Holy See released the declaration of Bishop Misago of Gikongoro approving the apparitions. The Marian sanctuary at Kibeho was named &quot;Shrine of [[Our Lady of Sorrows]]&quot; in 1992, two years before the genocide. An estimated 500,000 pilgrims visit the site every year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kibeho.org/en/shrine.php] Kibeho Shring Site&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/news_services/press/sinodo/documents/bollettino_21_xi-ordinaria-2005/02_inglese/b17_02.html#-_H.E._Most._Rev._Frédéric_RUBWEJANGA,_Bishop_of_Kibungo_(Kibungo,_RWANDA)] Bishop Rubwejanga's statement on Devotion to Our Lady of Kibeho&lt;/ref&gt;

The apparitions of [[Our Lady of Good Success]] began on 2 February 1594 at the Conceptionist Convent in Quito, Ecuador. The Virgin Mary repeatedly appeared to Venerable Mother Mariana de Jesus Torres, identifying herself as 'Our Lady of Good Success'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How the Church verifies Mary's visits as God's Ambassador|url=http://www.therecord.com.au/site/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=2583&amp;Itemid=29|accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Conceptionists celebrate their 500th anniversary|url=http://www.hoy.com.ec/noticias-ecuador/concepcionistas-cumplen-500-anos-500997.html|accessdate=2011-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Thousands turn out for procession of Our Lady of Good Success|url=http://www.lahora.com.ec/index.php/noticias/show/1041414/-1/Fieles_despiden_a_la_Virgen_del_Buen_Suceso_.html|accessdate=2011-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The apparition requested that a statue be made in her likeness and made several predictions concerning a crisis in the church specifically a fall in vocations, a lack of availability of the sacraments and a fall in moral standards in the 20th century.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} The apparitions were approved by the local Bishop, Salvador de Riber on 2 February 1611. In 1991 The Vatican granted the canonical coronation of our Lady of Good Success as 'Queen of Quito' after being petitioned by the Archbishop of Quito.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Marian Messenger|url=http://www.ncregister.com/daily-news/marian-messenger/|accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The apparitions of [[Shrine of Our Lady of Good Help|Our Lady of Good Help]] were reported by Adele Brise in 1859. In December 2010, Bishop David L. Ricken of [[Green Bay, Wisconsin]] approved the apparition as worthy of belief, as the first Marian apparition approved in the United States at the local level.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/1005014.htm Catholic News Service]&lt;/ref&gt; In Robinsonville (now called Champion) WI, a young Belgian immigrant woman named [[Adele Brise]] was walking through a wooded area when she saw a beautiful woman standing between a maple and a hemlock tree. She saw the lady again on her way to Mass, and walked past her again. After Mass she told her priest about the apparition, and he told her to ask the Lady &quot;In God's name, who are you and what do you want of me?&quot; When Adele walked past the spot again, the Lady was there, and Adele asked what she was told by the priest. The Lady replied, &quot;I am the Queen of Heaven who prays for the conversion of sinners.&quot; She gave Adele the mission to teach the children of the area their [[Catechism]], which Adele did faithfully. Soon after, Adele's father built a small chapel between the trees, and later two more churches were built on the spot before the present brick church, built in 1942. The apparitions,attributed to [[Our Lady of Good Help]], were approved on December 8, 2010, by [[Bishop]] [[David Ricken]] of the [[Diocese of Green Bay]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gbdioc.org/newsevents/news/857-worthy-of-belief.html Diocese of Green Bay]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Approved by the Coptic Orthodox Church===
Some apparitions have been approved by authorities of the [[Coptic Orthodox Church]]. For an apparition to be approved, the [[Pope of the Coptic Orthodox Church]] sends an official delegation made of bishops and priests, all of whom must witness the apparition and document miracles associated with it.{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}

====Our Lady of Zeitoun====
[[Our Lady of Zeitoun]] was a mass Marian apparition that occurred in the [[Zeitoun]] district of [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]], over a period of 2–3 years beginning on April 2, 1968, in the period after the [[six day war]]. It was reportedly witnessed by many thousands of people, including Egyptian President [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]], and captured by newspaper photographers and [[Egypt]]ian television. According to witnesses, the [[Blessed Virgin Mary|Virgin Mary]] appeared in different forms over the [[Coptic Orthodox]] [[Church (building)|Church]] of [[Saint Mary]] at Zeitoun for a period of 2–3 years. The apparitions lasted from a few minutes up to several hours and were sometimes accompanied by dove-shaped luminous bodies. The sick and blind are said to have been cured, and many people [[religious conversion|converted]] to [[Christianity]] as a result. In a statement dated May 4, 1968, the [[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria|Patriarchate of Cairo]] and [[Kyrillos VI]] stated that they considered the events at Zeitoun as valid, and that they had received many reports of immediate healings during the reported apparitions.&lt;ref&gt;''St. Mary in the Orthodox concept'' by Tadrous Y. Malaty 1978 ISBN 0-908000-07-3 pages 116-120 [http://books.google.com/books?id=InhALPtMqfsC&amp;pg=PA72&amp;dq=orthodox+mary+devotion&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ZWIWTYeYO83r4Aa2gr2GAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAjgK#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pearl Zaki (1977). Our Lord's Mother visits Egypt in 1968. Dar El Alam El Arabi. p. 24, 27.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NKHaNMTRF1o&amp;feature=related Video of the Virgin Mary apparition in Cairo, Egypt from 1968-1970]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Our Lady of Assiut====
The apparitions of [[Our Lady of Assiut]] were also mass apparitions in [[Assiut]], [[Egypt]] during 2000 and 2001 and many thousands of witnesses produced photographs of them, which were reprinted in several newspapers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zeitun-eg.org/assiut.htm Our Lady of Assiut]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/862081.stm BBC News on Assiut]&lt;/ref&gt; The reports state that during mass, pictures hung on the wall inside the altar, which show St Mary with a dove above her started to illuminate first, then the light from the dove in the pictures started to flow down. The lights thereafter appeared above the church as well and were seen by thousands of people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zeitun-eg.org/assiut2006.htm Assiut apparition account]&lt;/ref&gt; The Coptic church approved of the apparitions.

===Approved by the Anglican Communion===

====Our Lady of Lourdes====
The Anglican Communion has officially recognized the apparition of [[Our Lady of Lourdes]] and has built an Anglican Marian Shrine on the location, relatively close the Roman Catholic shrine. In September 2008 [[Rowan Williams]], the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] made a pilgrimage to Lourdes and preached at the shrine.&lt;ref&gt;McNally, Terrence, ''What Every Catholic Should Know about Mary'' ISBN 1-4415-1051-6 page 169&lt;/ref&gt;

====Our Lady of Walsingham====
Father [[Alfred Hope Patten]], appointed as the [[Church of England]] Vicar of Walsingham in 1921, ignited Anglican interest in the pre-Reformation pilgrimage. It was his idea to create a new statue of [[Our Lady of Walsingham]] based on the image depicted on the seal of the medieval priory. In 1922 the statue was set up in the Parish Church of Saint Mary and regular pilgrimage devotion followed. From the first night that the statue was placed there, people gathered around it to pray, asking Mary to join her prayers with theirs.
In the United States the National Shrine to Our Lady of Walsingham for the Episcopal Church is located in [[Grace Episcopal Church (Sheboygan, Wisconsin)]]. Our Lady of Walsingham is remembered by Roman Catholics on 24 September and by Anglicans on 15 October. A parish of the Pastoral Provision named for Our Lady of Walsingham is in Houston, Texas. A Western Rite Antiochian Orthodox parish named for Our Lady of Walsingham is in Mesquite, Texas.

====Our Lady of Yankalilla====
In August 1994 an image was said to have become visible on a wall behind the altar of a 137-year-old Anglican stone church in [[Yankalilla, South Australia]]. The image was interpreted as an image of the Virgin Mary's face, shoulders, and abdomen. The image supposedly depicts Mary holding the crucified Christ in the manner of a [[pietà]]. Her gaze is directed toward the tabernacle below, which contains the consecrated eucharistic bread. It is also claimed that an image of a rose appeared at the bottom of the larger image. In December 1996, the [[Diocese of The Murray|Bishop of The Murray]] blessed the church as &quot;The Shrine of Our Lady of Yankalilla&quot; and it has become a popular pilgrimage site for Australian Anglicans.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mytravelguide.com/attractions/profile-79378805-Australia_Adelaide_Shrine_Of_Our_Lady_Of_Yankalilla_The_.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Apparitions with no or undocumented approval==

A list of some notable reports of Marian apparitions is provided below. The apparitions discussed here do not have approval, and only those apparitions listed and explained in the sections above have received either [[Roman Catholic church|Roman Catholic]] or [[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria|Coptic]] approval, and the others shown in the table here are simply based on legend, reports of individuals or are still awaiting approval. There are hundreds of other reported apparitions around the world without major references or church investigations and they can not be included in this section, due to their lack of notability.

A number of claimed apparitions sites still not fully approved continue to gather pilgrims and become the site of major [[Roman Catholic Marian churches|Marian basilicas]]. The apparitions at these sites are often the subject of legends. An example is [[Our Lady of Walsingham]] where according to legend the Blessed Virgin appeared in a vision to a noblewoman in 1061 and her son built a simple wooden structure there that later became an abbey. No details of the content of vision have been preserved, but pilgrims continued to arrive at Walsingham for centuries until [[Thomas Cromwell, 1st Earl of Essex|1st Earl of Essex]] destroyed it in 1538.

[[File:nostra signora della guardia2.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Shrine of Nostra Signora della Guardia|Shrine of Our Lady of Guardia]].]]
The 1490 apparition reported by Italian peasant Benedetto Pareto regarding [[Our Lady of Guardia]] is somewhat similar, but has a happier ending. Pareto also reported that the Virgin Mary appeared to him and asked him to build a church atop the mountain. Pareto at first refused, saying that he was just a poor man, but he eventually built a small wooden structure, which in time gathered many pilgrims. The [[Shrine of Our Lady of Guardia]] is now a thriving basilica atop Mount Figogna, near [[Genoa]] Italy.

Some major [[Roman Catholic Marian churches|Marian basilicas]] and traditions are based on legends that do not involve any specific apparitions, but sacred objects that are assumed to have been associated with apparitions. The key example is the [[Basilica of the National Shrine of Our Lady of Aparecida]] in [[Aparecida]], [[Brazil]]. It is the second-largest Catholic place of worship in the world, second only to [[St. Peter's Basilica]] in [[Vatican City]], and the largest [[Mariology(RC)|Marian]] Church in the world, receiving over 6 million pilgrims a year. There is no specific vision or apparition associated with [[Our Lady of Aparecida]], and it is based on a simple wooden statue of the Blessed Virgin (found by fishermen) that over the centuries drew millions of pilgrims, based on its reported healing powers. The festivals surrounding [[Our Lady of Chiquinquirá]] in [[Venezuela]] are based on a piece of wood that, according to legend, grew luminous with the image of the Blessed Virgin in 1709. In the case of [[Our Lady of Kazan]], legend holds that the Blessed Virgin revealed the location of the precious icon to a 10 year old girl in 1579.

The [[Basilica of Our Lady of Good Health]] in [[Velankanni]], [[Tamil Nadu]] in southern India does, however, have a legend that involves a number of apparitions. There is no historical record of the apparition of [[Our Lady of Good Health]] but the oral tradition suggests that there was an apparition to a Hindu boy in mid 16th century and later Portuguese sailors were saved by another apparition. Also another one major Marian apparitions in [[India]] is of [[Korattymuthy]] at [[Koratty]] in [[Kerala]]. Similarly, the legend [[Our Lady of La Vang]] is based on an apparition to a group of Vietnamese Catholics in the rain forest in 1798, and the site of a basilica.

The Basilica of our [[Our Lady of Siluva]] in [[Siluva]], [[Lithuania]] is also based on a legend of an apparition to four children in 1608, and houses a famous painting (perhaps based on [[Salus Populi Romani]]) called ''Our Lady of Siluva'', usually considered Lithuania's greatest treasure.&lt;ref&gt;[http://campus.udayton.edu/mary//resources/siluva.html Our Lady of Siluva]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ourladyofsiluva.com/our_lady Our Lady of Siluva website]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although both [[She Shan Basilica]] in [[Shanghai]], China and [[Our Lady of China]] in [[Donglu]], near Beijing, were popular pilgrimage sites at one time, with the arrest and imprisonment of the Catholic bishops in the 1950s by the communists and with the establishment of the [[Chinese Patriotic Catholic Association]] against the Vatican, these pilgrimages have slowed down.

The [[Sanctuary of Our Lady of Lichen]], the largest church in Poland (and the 11th largest in the world) is based on legends on the Virgin Mary appearing to different people in the Lichen area in the early 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lichen.pl Lichen Basilica]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/travels/documents/hf_jp-ii_spe_07061999_lichen_en.html Vaticanwebsite: John Paul II at Lichen]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Knock shrine.JPG|thumb|right|200px|The altar sculptures at [[Knock Shrine|Shrine of Our Lady of Knock]], based on the description of the apparition.]]
The [[Knock Shrine|Sanctuary of Our Lady of Knock]] in Ireland is based on a reported appearance of the Virgin Mary along with [[Jesus Christ]] and other saints in Ireland in 1879.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.knock-shrine.ie/ Shrine of Our Lady of Knock - Official website]&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1941 and 1988, Felisa Sistiaga reported several apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary as [[Our Lady of Sorrows]] in Umbe, near [[Bilbao]], [[Spain]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.virgendeunbe.net/ ''Virgen Pura Dolorosa de Umbe'' - Official website dedicated to the apparitions of Our Lady of Sorrows in Umbe]&lt;/ref&gt; The messages left by Our Lady were very similar to that given in the [[Garabandal apparitions|Marian apparitions of Garabandal]].

In 1945, two children - Marcelina Barroso Expósito and Afra Brígido Blanco - reported several apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary as [[Our Lady of Sorrows]] near [[La Codosera]], in the [[province of Badajoz]], [[Extremadura]], [[Spain]]. A few years later, the [[Bishop of Badajoz]] gave permission for the construction of a large [[Marian shrine]] in the place of the apparitions and one of the visionaries, Marcelina, became a cloistered [[nun]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historiadelacodosera.es/chandavila.htm What occurred at La Codosera? - The apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary]&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 4, 1947, seven-year-old Angela Volpini was grazing cattle near her hometown of Casanova Staffora, near [[Oltrepò Pavese]] in northwest Italy, when she felt someone embrace her from behind and lift her up. Assuming it was her aunt, she turned around and saw &quot;a woman's face -- beautiful, sweet and unknown.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ricerca.gelocal.it/laprovinciapavese/archivio/laprovinciapavese/2008/04/06/PT3PO_PQ301.html This child who saw the Madonna]. In ''La Provincia Pavese'' April 6, 2008, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; The apparitions occurred on the fourth day of every month for ten years, and many were filmed. Ms. Volpini's father supported her, but her mother, while believing in the apparitions, feared for the girl's life.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;I stood close to my mother's room and I saw her talking to a statue of the Madonna, crying 'This is my daughter. You can't do that to her. You've already experienced what it's like losing a son. Leave her alone.'&quot;[http://ricerca.gelocal.it/laprovinciapavese/archivio/laprovinciapavese/2008/04/06/PT3PO_PQ301.html This child who saw the Madonna]. In ''La Provincia Pavese'' April 6, 2008, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; The local priest, Father Gianni Baget Bozzo, believed the child and formed a lifelong friendship with her. He often compared the apparitions to those of [[Our Lady of Lourdes]]. On his death May 8, 2009, he left one-sixth of his fortune to Volpini.&lt;ref&gt;[http://translate.google.com/translate?sl=auto&amp;tl=en&amp;js=n&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;layout=2&amp;eotf=1&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fricerca.gelocal.it%2Flaprovinciapavese%2Farchivio%2Flaprovinciapavese%2F2010%2F03%2F12%2FPZ4PO_PZ403.html Angela Volpini heir of Don Baget Bozzo], in ''La Provincia Pavese'' March 12, 2010, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; People who believe in Ms. Volpini's experiences formed a devotional organization called ''Nova [[Cana]]''—the name invented by Ms. Volpini herself—to commemorate the events.

[[File:035MadonnaRivelazione.jpg|thumb|left|200px|The grotto of the marian apparition in [[Tre Fontane]], [[Rome]], [[Italy]].]]
Between 1958 and 1962, Mathew Lashut reported several apparitions of the Virgin Mary on a forest near [[Turzovka]], a town in north-western [[Slovakia]]. This apparition was predicted to come about as “a second [[Lourdes]]&quot; or &quot;the Lourdes of Slovakia” by the [[Germany|German]] [[Roman Catholic|Catholic]] [[Christian mysticism|mystic]] and [[stigmatic]] [[Therese Neumann]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicrevelations.org/PR/matous%20losuta.htm The apparitions of Virgin Mary in Turzovka, Czeckoslovakia (1958-1962)] Retrieved on October 2, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The reported apparitions of [[Our Lady of Kibeho]] in 1982 included exceptionally long and dramatic visions lasting eight hours. According to the teenage visionaries, in 1982 the Virgin Mary asked everyone to pray to prevent a terrible war. A war and genocide eventually took place at the same location in 1995 and claimed the lives of some of visionaries. The apparitions were accepted by the local [[Roman Catholic]] bishop, Bishop Misago, but have not been given final approval by the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.michaeljournal.org/kibeho.htm Messages of Our Lady of Sorrows in Kibeho, Rwanda] Our Lady of Kibeho&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/OLKIBEHO.HTM JUDGEMENT ON THE APPARITIONS OF KIBEHO] EWTN on Our Lady of Kibeho&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sunday.ninemsn.com.au/sunday/cover_stories/article_1869.asp?s=1 Remembering the forgotten Diggers] Kibeho article&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anzacday.org.au/history/peacekeeping/anecdotes/kibeho.html Witness to Genocide -- A Personal Account of the 1995 Kibeho Massacre] UN Report on Kibeho&lt;/ref&gt; The bishop himself went on trial for nine months on charges of involvement in the genocide but was not convicted.&lt;ref&gt;*[http://www.thetablet.co.uk/article/6834 Article about the bishop's trial] ''The Tablet''&lt;/ref&gt;

The reported apparitions of [[Our Lady of America]] in 1956 in Rome City, Indiana, did receive a positive response from the local bishop and have been Canonically-approved by several Archbishops and Bishops, but no decision has been rendered with regard to the supernatural origin and characters of the reported apparitions.  Pilgrims arrive daily to pray and offer their devotion in the Our Lady Mother of Mercy Chapel, which sits on the grounds of what is now Sylvan Springs.&lt;ref&gt;[[EWTN]] [http://www.ewtn.com/library/BISHOPS/burkeolamer.HTM]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://campus.udayton.edu/mary/resources/ourladyofamerica.htm University of Dayton]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Catholic News Service]] [http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/0704623.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

The fact that pilgrims continue arriving at a reported apparition site and the fact that church figures a continent away may be sympathetic towards the apparition does not mean that approval has been obtained. For instance, although the Village of [[Pellevoisin]] in France does receive pilgrims, and there is a small shrine of Our Lady of Pellevoisin in St. Paul's church in New York, according to the University of Dayton Marian Library, archbishops of [[Bourges]] have never pronounced on the subject of Pellevoisin and have been very reserved on the topic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://campus.udayton.edu/mary/questions/yq2/yq324.htm University of Dayton on Pellevoisin]&lt;/ref&gt; However, various independent (and colorful) ''lists of apparitions'' websites declare Pellevoisin as approved, with no clear reference for the approval.

The apparitions reported between 1945 and 1959 by Ida Peerdeman in [[Amsterdam]] as [[The Lady of all Nations]] include a short prayer called the Amsterdam Blessing. In May 2002, Bishop [[Jozef Marianus Punt]] of Haarlem-Amsterdam issued a letter that declared this apparition as having a supernatural origin. However, this apparition has not been officially approved by the [[Holy See]], and has approval only at the local bishop level.&lt;ref&gt;[[EWTN]] on [[Our Lady of All Nations]][http://www.ewtn.com/expert/answers/our_lady_of_all_nations.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.de-vrouwe.net/english/index.html?d__May_31__2002__Approbation_of_the_Apparitions258.htm Approbation of the Apparitions in Amsterdam]&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1968 and 1976, a young boy named Jesús José reported several apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary as [[Our Lady of Graces]] in Onuva, near [[La Puebla del Río]], [[province of Seville]], [[Spain]]. In the last apparition, the message from heaven explains that ''«Onuva means: Land of Mercy, Land of Mercy!»''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pt.scribd.com/doc/60913201/Mensajes-de-Onuva EL MENSAJE DE ONUVA - Apariciones de la Virgen en España. ONUVA, tierra de misericordia y de reparación a los Scmos. Corazones de Jesús y María]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ltmanowa GL1.2.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Shrine of Our Lady of [[Litmanová]], situated in northern [[Slovakia]].]]
Between 1990 and 1995, two young girls - Ivetka Korcakova (born 1978) and Katka Ceselkova (born 1977) - reported several apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary under the title of ''The Immaculate Purity'' on the Zvir Mountain, in [[Litmanová]], a village of northern [[Slovakia]]. During these religious events, the visionaries were accompanied by many priests and now there is a [[Shrines to the Virgin Mary|Marian shrine]] on the place of apparitions. Many people, not only Slovaks, make pilgrimages to this location to celebrate the [[Mass (liturgy)|Divine Liturgy]] and obtain water from a holy stream.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.litmanova.net/ ''I am the Immaculate Purity'' - The apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary in Litmanová (Slovakia)] Retrieved on October 1, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1992, some reported apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary under the title of ''Virgin of the Eucharist'' in [[Manduria]], south of [[Italy]], are also receiving many attention worldwide, in particular by the Catholic youth. Debora Marasco, the visionary, founded a Catholic Movement for the young people named &quot;Manduria for Young People&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.giovanipromanduria.org/ Manduria for Young People Movement]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.verginedelleucaristia.net/ The Virgin of the Eucharist (Manduria, Italy)]&lt;/ref&gt; A similar phenomenon with Catholic youth is occurring near [[São Marcos da Serra]], in [[Algarve]], [[Portugal]], were other reported apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary under the title of ''Mother of Goodness'' attract, since 1999, many young people and [[Priesthood (Catholic Church)|priests]] to the place of apparitions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.maedabondade.com/ The Blessed Mother of Goodness (São Marcos da Serra, Algarve, Portugal)]&lt;/ref&gt; The Holy See has never officially approved or disapproved these apparitions.

Several apparition related sites on the internet exist, often with detailed messages that sound pious, accompanied by testimonies from local witnesses, and even local priests and bishops. However, these representations do not always amount to authenticity or Vatican approval. An example is the website for the apparitions of ''Our Lady of the Eucharist'' in [[Rome]] since the year 2000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.madredelleucaristia.it Our Lady of the Eucharist]&lt;/ref&gt; The website for ''Our Lady of the Eucharist'' includes a clear letter and a photo from Bishop Claudio Gatti who approved the apparition. Yet a more detailed search of the same website produces a letter from the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] reducing the said Bishop to lay rank following a series of meetings at the Vatican on this and other matters (e.g. the Bishop's position of marriage for priests). The Bishop now uses the title ''ordained by God'' rather than Catholic Bishop.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.madredelleucaristia.it/eng/lettreserv.htm Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith letter on Bishop Gatti]&lt;/ref&gt; At [[Our Lady of Soufanieh|Soufanieh]], a suburb of [[Damascus]] a series of apparitions have reportedly been observed between 1982 and 2004, without any approval to date.&lt;ref&gt;Sbalchiero in: Laurentin/ Sbalchiero (2007), p. 1093-1097.&lt;/ref&gt;

As a general pattern, in most cases, formal Vatican approval for apparitions usually requires at least a century, even if the local diocese issues a preliminary letter permitting devotions. For instance, [[Our Lady of Laus]] was recognized by the local bishop in 1665 but was only granted approval by the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] in 2008. As current examples, [[Our Lady of Kibeho]] have received recognition from the local diocese, but there has been no formal approval from the [[Holy See]]. The same with the 1973 apparitions of [[Our Lady of Akita]].

Some purported Marian apparitions initiated events that led to [[Schism (religion)|schism]] of [[Catholics]] forming their own [[Breakaway Catholic Churches|independent churches]] as a result of Rome's disapproval of them. Notable examples include the revelations of [[Feliksa Kozłowska]] between 1893 and 1918, which led to the founding of the [[Mariavite Church|Mariavite]] and the [[Old Catholic Mariavite Church|Old Catholic Mariavite]] churches. Others include the [[Palmarian Catholic Church]], which began after a series of purported apparitions in [[Palmar de Troya]], while [[Fraternite Notre Dame]], a [[Traditionalist Catholic]] church traces its origins to apparitions that were reported in [[Frechou]], [[France]], and is led by Bishop Jean Marie Kozik who was consecrated by [[Vietnam]]ese Archbishop [[Ngo Dinh Thuc]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fraternitenotredame.com/Pages/EN_Pages/EN_History/EN_History-01.html&lt;/ref&gt;

An apparition of [[Blessed Virgin Mary (Roman Catholic)|Our Lady]] at Batim is the supposed appearance by the Virgin Mary in the compound of Igreja de São Simão e Judas (Church of Saint Simon and Jude), [[Batim]]-[[Ganxim]] in [[Goa]]. The first sighing is purported to have been made by Iveta Gomes on the 24th September, 1994. Others have since claimed to have seen the Virgin Mary, as well as other miracles, at this location.&lt;ref name=&quot;TimesOfIndia&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Mystic claims that Mary appeared at Batim apparition|date=Mar 26, 2012|url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2012-03-26/goa/31240050_1_batim-pilgrims-prayer|accessdate=13 April 2012|newspaper=The Times of India, Panjim|date=26 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though the apparition has no Episcopal approval, the Church has not raised any objection to the gathering of people at the site, in expression of their faith.&lt;ref name=&quot;TimesOfIndia&quot; /&gt;

&lt;!--

NOTICE ON ADDING APPARITIONS

Before you add an apparition, please do several
web searches to make sure it has not been declared
as fake. E.g., &quot;Our Lady of Surbiton&quot; used to be in this
table, but a simple Google search showed that the
Vatican had declared it a fraud. It has now
been removed. And several unofficial sites such as the
Miracle Hunter, etc. have very inaccurate information
and entries made here can not rely on them.

Moreover any apparition added must meet the criteria
for [[Wikipedia:Notability]] else it must be deleted.

Thank you.

--&gt;

==Apparitions condemned by church authorities==
Not all reports of visions and apparitions are taken seriously by church authorities. For instance, the messages reported by Catalina Rivas were later found to correspond to exact pages of books written by others, and published instructional literature for Catholic seminarians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://skepdic.com/rivasdocuments2.html Carmelita Rivas messages]&lt;/ref&gt; Claimed apparitions and miracles at Holy Love Ministries in Elyria, Ohio were denounced by local Bishop Richard Lennon as &quot;not supernatural in origin&quot; and &quot;forbid members of the clergy of any ecclesiastical jurisdiction&quot; to celebrate the Sacraments on the site.&lt;ref&gt;[http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_dfR_xG2hpmw/Sv4RExIxXnI/AAAAAAAAGIw/x5xdbNwhIhY/s1600-h/Holy+Love+Decree.jpg Decree by Bishop Richard Lennon]&lt;/ref&gt; He also declared &quot;that the Confraternity of the United Hearts of Jesus and Mary is not an approved association of the Christian faithful in the Diocese of Cleveland and may not legitimately use the name 'Catholic' or represent itself as a Catholic group.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://catholicexchange.com/2009/11/20/124186/ Article explaining the Church's position]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Cantabria Garabandal iglesia lou.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Parish church of [[Garabandal apparitions|San Sebastian de Garabandal]] village, north of [[Spain]].]]
The reported [[Garabandal apparitions]] from 1961 to 1965 were examined by the local Bishop and were declared as not having evidence of being of supernatural origin. However the apparitions were not declared as a hoax and the possibility of future approval was left open.&lt;ref&gt;[[EWTN]] on Garabandal [http://www.ewtn.com/library/bishops/garaband.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Judith Albright, 1997, ''Our Lady at Garabandal'', ISBN 1-880033-04-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Conchita Gonzales, 1983, ''Miracle at Garabandal'', ISBN 0-385-18890-0&lt;/ref&gt; At Garabandal, an apparition by [[Saint Michael, the Archangel]] was reported first, announcing the arrival of the Virgin Mary (under the title of [[Our Lady of Mount Carmel]]).&lt;ref&gt;Michael Freze, 1993, ''Voices, Visions, and Apparitions'', OSV Publishing ISBN 0-87973-454-X page 267&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Church in Međugorje, B-H, June 4th 2007 (2).jpg|thumb|200px|left|The statue and the Marian shrine of [[Međugorje]] ([[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]).]]
Among recent visions, the reported apparitions of The Virgin Mary to six children in [[Međugorje]] in 1981 have received much attention despite official condemnation by the local Bishop. The [[Our Lady of Međugorje]] messages are published and distributed worldwide and often emphasize five key elements: Daily prayer of the [[Rosary based prayers#Holy Rosary|Holy Rosary]], Fasting on Wednesdays and Fridays, Daily reading of the [[Bible]], Monthly Confessions and [[Holy Communion]]. On March 17, 2010, the [[Holy See|Vatican]] announced it was beginning a formal investigation of the apparitions at Medugorje.  [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[Camillo Ruini]] is to head the commission that will study the matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| first=Nicole | last=Winfield | url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20100317/ap_on_re_eu/eu_vatican_shrine | title=Vatican studies visions of Virgin Mary in Bosnia | publisher=Assocated Press | date=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The visions at [[Medjugorje]] have been condemned by Bishop [[Pavao Žanić]]. The Bishop affirms his complete certainty that Our Lady did not appear in Medjugorje. The Commission to investigate the apparitions has continually underlined the theological and disciplinary difficulties posed by the events and the messages of Medjugorje.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ewtn.com/library/BISHOPS/ZANICMED.HTM&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Holy See]] had not overturned the ruling by the Bishop at this time. In 1991, the Zadar document declaired, &quot;On the basis of the investigations so far it can not be affirmed that one is dealing with supernatural apparitions and revelations.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ewtn.com/expert/answers/medjugorje.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Purported locutions received by the late [[Veronica Lueken]] from 1968-1994 were declared invalid by Bishop [[Francis Mugavero]], then Bishop of the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Brooklyn]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/Library/NEWAGE/MUGABAY.TXT EWTN on Bayside apparitions]&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, reports of ''Our Lady of Surbiton'' claiming that the Virgin Mary appeared every day under a pine tree in England were flatly rejected by the Vatican as a fraud.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1563941/Vatican-rejects-woman's-Virgin-Mary-claim.html Vatican rejects Our Lady of Surbiton]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some reported apparitions attract negative publicity at the location of the apparition. For instance, the latter parts of the reported messages from [[Gianna Talone]] were disapproved by the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Baltimore]] and a group of [[Emmitsburg, Maryland]] residents started a campaign against Talone and accused her of running a cult.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emmitsburg.net/cult_watch/news_reports/we_do_not_believe2.htm Emmitsburg website]&lt;/ref&gt; To date, the [[Holy See]] has let the Talone matter rest at the local level of the archdiocese.

==Criticism==
Some Protestant Christians and non-Christians regard claims of Marian apparitions as being [[hallucination]]s encouraged by [[superstition]], and occasionally simply as deliberate [[hoaxes]] to attract attention. Many such apparitions are reported in economically depressed areas, attracting many pilgrims who bring trade and money into the region. For instance, some sources dispute the very existence of [[Saint Juan Diego]].&lt;ref&gt;Stafford Poole, 2006, ''The Guadalupan Controversies in Mexico'' Stanford University Press. ISBN 978-0-8047-5252-7&lt;/ref&gt;

Some spontaneous healings reported at apparition sites such as [[Lourdes]] are also disputed by some scientists{{Who|date=November 2009}}. Other scientists{{Who|date=November 2009}} have claimed that a handful of unexplained cures have occurred; the [[Lourdes Medical Bureau]] has recorded sixty &quot;inexplicable&quot; healings that match its requirements. Critics maintain that some other healings are incomplete, leaving the sufferer with disabilities or chronic illness, and that other claimed healings are likely to be the relatively rare but unmiraculous [[spontaneous remission]] of illness or injury. Such remissions might be expected to occur in a few of the large numbers of ill (and perhaps credulous) people who visit such sites. That viewpoint is debated by religious people{{Who|date=May 2011}} and by some in the medical profession{{Who|date=May 2011}}. The Lourdes Medical Bureau claims that it will not review cases of claimed healing involving illnesses known sometimes to go into remission by themselves, or incomplete healings, or those that take place gradually.&lt;ref&gt;Ruth Harris, 1999, ''Lourdes: Body and Spirit in the Secular Age'', Penguin Books&lt;/ref&gt; although it counts cases of tumors, which are remissible.

==Further reading==
* {{cite book
| first=Francis W.
| last=Johnston
| title=Fatima: the Great Sign
| publisher=Augustine
| location=Chulmleigh
| year=1980
| isbn=0-85172-723-9
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Francis W.
| last=Johnston
| title=Fatima: the Great Sign
| publisher=Tan Books and Publishers
| location=Rockford, Illinois
| year=1980
| isbn=0-89555-163-2
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Kevin
| last=McClure
| title=The Evidence for Visions of the Virgin Mary
| publisher=Aquarian Press
| location=Wellingborough
| year=1983
| isbn=0-85030-351-6
}}
* {{cite book
| first=René
| last=Laurentin
| title=The Apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary Today
| publisher=Veritas Publications
| location=Dublin
| year=1990, revised 1991
| isbn=1-85390-054-9 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (9) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}, ISBN 1-85390-119-9
| authorlink=René Laurentin
}}
* {{cite book
| first=René
| last=Laurentin
| title=An Appeal from Mary in Argentina: the Apparitions of San Nicolás
| publisher=Faith Publishing Company/The Riehle Foundation
| location=Milford, Ohio
| year=1990
| isbn=0-9625975-5-4
| authorlink=René Laurentin
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Josyp (with Michael H. Brown)
| last=Terelya
| title=Josyp Terelya - WITNESS
| publisher=Faith Publishing Company/The Riehle Foundation
| location=Milford, Ohio
| year=1991
| isbn=1-877678-17-1
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Michael H.
| last=Brown
| title=The Final Hour
| publisher=Faith Publishing Company/The Riehle Foundation
| location=Milford, Ohio
| year=1992
| isbn=1-880033-03-8
}}
* {{cite book
| first=René
| last=Laurentin
| title=The Cause of Liberation in the USSR
| publisher=Queenship Publishing Company
| location=Goleta, California
| year=1993
| isbn=1-882972-07-4
| authorlink=René Laurentin
}}
* {{cite book
| first=David
| last=Blackbourn
| title=Marpingen: Apparitions of the Virgin Mary in Nineteenth-Century Germany
| publisher=[[Alfred A. Knopf]]
| location=New York
| year=1994
| isbn=0-679-41843-1
| authorlink=David Blackbourn
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Catherine M.
| last=Odell
| title=Those Who Saw Her: Apparitions of Mary
| publisher=[[Our Sunday Visitor]]
| location=Huntington
| year=1995
| isbn=0-87973-664-4 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (4) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Michael H.
| last=Brown
| title=The Day Will Come
| publisher=Charis
| location=Ann Arbor, Michigan
| year=1996
| isbn=0-89283-944-9
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Janice T.
| last=Connell
| title=Meetings with Mary: Visions of The Blessed Mother
| publisher=[[Ballantine Books]]
| location=United States
| year=1996
| isbn=0-345-39705-3
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Michael H.
| last=Brown
| title=The Last Secret
| publisher=Charis
| location=Ann Arbor, Michigan
| year=1998
| isbn=1-57918-339-5
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Michael H.
| last=Brown
| title=Seven Days with Mary
| publisher=Faith Publishing Company/The Riehle Foundation
| location=Milford, Ohio
| year=1998
| isbn=1-880033-26-7
}}
* {{cite book
| first=G. Scott
| last=Sparrow
| title=Sacred Encounters with Mary
| publisher=Thomas More Association/[[Ave Maria Press]]
| location=Chicago
| year=2004
| isbn=1-59471-047-3
}}
* {{cite book
| first=Michael H.
| last=Brown
| title=Tower of Light
| publisher=[http://www.spiritdaily.com/ Spirit Daily Publications]
| location=Palm Coast, Florida
| year=2007
| isbn=0-615-14372-5
}}

==See also==
{{Wikipedia books|Mary and Mariology}}
* [[Visions of Jesus and Mary]]
* [[Roman Catholic Mariology]]
* [[Blessed Virgin Mary (Roman Catholic)]]
* [[Blessed Virgin Mary]]
* [[Shrines to the Virgin Mary]]
* [[Marian devotions]]
* [[Dogma (Roman Catholic)]]
* [[Immaculate Heart of Mary]]
* [[Weeping statue]]
* [[Perceptions of religious imagery in natural phenomena]]

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==External links==
* [http://www.marypages.com/ Foundation Marypages Design: The Apparitions of the Blessed Virgin Mary, Crowned Queen of Heaven]
* [http://www.miraclehunter.com/ The Miracle Hunter: Marian Appartitions] (with links to letters from local bishops in some cases)
* [http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/indexapp.htm The Catholic Community Forum: Marian Apparitions]
* [http://www.santuario-fatima.pt/ Fátima - Official Website]
* [http://www.medjugorje.hr/en/ Medjugorje - Official Website]
* [http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/MARIAN.htm Eternal Word Television Network: MARIAN APPARITIONS IN THE AMERICAS]

{{1917 Fatima events}}
{{Private revelation}}
&lt;!--

The link to Catholic planet was removed twice because it is based on the views of a single person, who acts as judge jury and apparition approver. That site is a key example of what ''low quality'' means in terms of Wikipedia references. Please see the talk page. Therefore, please do not add Catholic planet, or similar low quality sites to the list on this page, for they will be removed rather quickly. Thank you.

The link to Emmitsburg town's website was also removed. Please: It is a local town website. Please do not make it sound like it is a major repository of Marian knowledge. It is not reliable enough for Wikipedia. Please do not add it any more, for it will be reverted very quickly. Thanks.

Removed www.roses.org not notable, doesn't add to article

--&gt;

==Gallery of apparition-based Marian churches==
{{Main|Roman Catholic Marian churches}}

Marian apparitions, and sacred objects related to them, have led to the construction of some of the largest [[Roman Catholic Marian churches]].

&lt;Gallery&gt;
Image:Piazza Esquilino, Santa Maria Maggiore.JPG|[[Santa Maria Maggiore]], [[Rome]], 5th century
Image:Basilica_del_Pilar_ZaragozaAragon%28Spain%29.jpg|[[Basilica of Our Lady of the Pillar]] [[Zaragoza]] Spain, 1681
Image:Panorama LaSalette.jpg|Basilica of [[Our Lady of La Salette]], [[France]]
Image:Nostra signora della guardia2.jpg|[[Shrine of Nostra Signora della Guardia|Nostra Signora della Guardia]], [[Genoa]], 1889
Image:Our Lady of Lourdes Basilica.jpg|[[Sanctuary of Our Lady of Lourdes]], 1864
Image:Candelaria BW 4.JPG|[[Basilica of Candelaria]], [[Tenerife]] ([[Spain]]), 1959
Image:Fatima.jpg|[[Our Lady of Fatima Basilica]], [[Fátima, Portugal]]
Image:Vailankanni Basilica.JPG|[[Basilica of Our Lady of Good Health]], [[Vailankanni]], India
Image:Knockbasilica.JPG|Basilica of [[Our Lady of Knock]], [[Ireland]]
Image:Church in Međugorje, B-H, June 4th 2007 (4).jpg|[[Our Lady of Međugorje]], [[Međugorje]]
Image:Notre-dame-du-Laus (basilique - 2).JPG|Basilica of [[Our Lady of Laus]], [[France]]
Image:Nossa Senhora de Peneda.JPG|Sanctuary of Our Lady of Peneda, [[Arcos de Valdevez]], [[Portugal]]
Image:Santuario nacional.jpg| Basilica of [[Basilica of the National Shrine of Our Lady of Aparecida|Our Lady of Aparecida]], [[Aparecida]], [[Brazil]], 1955
Image:Basilica of Our Lady of Guadalupe (new).JPG|[[Basilica of Our Lady of Guadalupe]], [[Mexico]] 1974
Image:3 Stary Lichen 44.jpg|[[Sanctuary of Our Lady of Licheń]], [[Stary Licheń]], [[Poland]], 2004
&lt;/gallery&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Marian Apparition}}
[[Category:Marian apparitions| ]]
[[Category:Anglican Mariology]]
[[Category:Paranormal]]
[[Category:Miracles]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic Mariology]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[cs:Mariánská zjevení]]
[[de:Marienerscheinung]]
[[es:Aparición mariana]]
[[eo:Maria Apero]]
[[fa:تجلی مریم]]
[[fr:Apparition mariale]]
[[gl:Aparición mariana]]
[[ko:성모 발현]]
[[it:Apparizioni e altre manifestazioni mariane]]
[[la:Apparitiones Virginis Mariae]]
[[hu:Szűz Mária-jelenések]]
[[nl:Mariaverschijning]]
[[ja:聖母の出現]]
[[pl:Objawienia Maryjne]]
[[pt:Aparições marianas]]
[[ru:Явления Девы Марии]]
[[sq:Shfaqja mariane]]
[[fi:Marian ilmestys]]
[[ta:மரியாவின் காட்சிகள்]]
[[vi:Đức Mẹ hiện ra]]</text>
      <sha1>fhh3hiuefh98u3galbp1rvmh30jvymg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
