<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Michael (archangel)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>318621</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522080577</id>
      <parentid>522075584</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T22:53:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>History2007</username>
        <id>3684925</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/199.216.46.209|199.216.46.209]] ([[User talk:199.216.46.209|talk]]) to last version by ClueBot NG</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58386">{{Redirect|Saint Michael}}
{{For|Roman Catholic views and prayers|Saint Michael (Roman Catholic)}}
&lt;!--THIS ARTICLE USED TO HAVE TOO MANY IMAGES AND THEY WERE CLEANED UP AND
AN IMAGE GALLERY WAS CREATED. PLEASE DO NOT ADD ADDITIONAL IMAGES SINCE THAT
WAS MAKING THE TEXT HARD TO READ AND CREATED OVERLAP PROBLEMS ON DIFFERENT
SCREEN SIZES. IF YOU HAVE NEW (AND &quot;IMPORTANT&quot;) IMAGES THEY CAN BE ADDED
TO THE GALLERY AT THE END OF THE PAGE, NOT IN THE BODY OF THE ARTICLE.
--&gt;
{{Infobox saint
|name=Archangel Michael
|birth_date=
|death_date=
|feast_day=November 8 (New Calendar Eastern Orthodox Churches) / November 21 (Old Calendar Eastern Orthodox Churches), September 29 (&quot;[[Michaelmas]]&quot;); May 8; many other local and historical feasts
|venerated_in=[[Anglican Communion|Anglicanism]], [[Catholic Church|Catholicism]], [[Eastern Orthodoxy]], [[Oriental Orthodoxy]], [[Lutheranism]], [[Islam]], [[Judaism]]
|image=Mikharkhangel.jpg
|imagesize=200px
|caption=A 13th-century Byzantine icon from [[Saint Catherine's Monastery, Mount Sinai]]
|birth_place=
|death_place= 
|titles=Archangel
|beatified_date= 
|beatified_place= 
|beatified_by=
|canonized_date=[[pre-congregation]]
|canonized_place=
|canonized_by=
|attributes=[[Archangel]]; Treading on a dragon; carrying a banner, scales, and sword
|patronage=Guardian of the Catholic Church;&lt;ref name=Alban &gt;Alban Butler, The lives of the fathers, martyrs, and other principal saints Published by B. Dornin, 1821 page 117&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kiev]], protector of the Jewish people,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bible gateway, Daniel 12:1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=daniel%2012;&amp;version=31 |title=Bible gateway, Daniel 12:1 |publisher=Biblegateway.com |date= |accessdate=2010-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; police officers,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jcpdes.com/stmichael.html&lt;/ref&gt; military, grocers, mariners, paratroopers&lt;ref&gt;http://www.catholic.org/saints/saint.php?saint_id=308&lt;/ref&gt;
|major_shrine=
|suppressed_date=
|issues=}}

'''Michael''' ({{lang-he|מִיכָאֵל}} (pronounced {{IPA-he|ˌmixäˈʔel|}}), ''Micha'el'' or ''Mîkhā'ēl''; {{lang-el|Μιχαήλ}}, ''Mikhaḗl''; {{lang-la|Michael}} or ''Míchaël''; {{lang-ar|ميخائيل}}, ''Mīkhā'īl'') is an [[archangel]] in Jewish, Christian, and Islamic teachings. [[Roman Catholics]], the [[Eastern Orthodox]], [[Anglicans]], and [[Lutherans]] refer to him as '''Saint Michael the Archangel''' and also simply as ''Saint Michael''. [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox Christian]]s refer to him as the ''[[Taxiarch]] Archangel Michael'' or simply Archangel Michael.

In Hebrew, ''Michael'' means &quot;who is like God&quot; (''mi''-who, ''ke''-as or like, ''[[El (deity)|El]]''-deity), which is traditionally interpreted as a rhetorical question: &quot;[[Who is like God?]]&quot; (which expects an answer in the negative) to imply that ''no one'' is like [[God]]. In this way, Michael is reinterpreted as a symbol of humility before God.&lt;ref&gt;''Studies in Revelation'' by Hampton J. Keathley, 3rd, J. Hampton Keathley III 1997 ISBN 0-7375-0008-5 page 209 [http://books.google.com/books?id=lBqQFSTDyQ0C&amp;pg=PA209&amp;dq=%22who+is+like+god%22+rhetorical&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=IH-jTN7nBIqOjAeL6ZyKAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22who%20is%20like%20god%22%20rhetorical&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Hebrew Bible]] Michael is mentioned three times in the [[Book of Daniel]], once as a &quot;great prince who stands up for the children of your people&quot;. The idea that Michael was the advocate of the Jews became so prevalent that in spite of the rabbinical prohibition against appealing to angels as intermediaries between God and his people, Michael came to occupy a certain place in the Jewish liturgy.

In the [[New Testament]] Michael leads God's armies against Satan's forces in the [[Book of Revelation]], where during the [[war in heaven]] he defeats Satan. In the [[Epistle of Jude]] Michael is specifically referred to as an &quot;archangel&quot;. Christian sanctuaries to Michael appeared in the 4th century, when he was first seen as a healing angel, and then over time as a protector and the leader of the army of God against the forces of evil. By the 6th century, devotions to Archangel Michael were widespread both in the [[Eastern Christianity|Eastern]] and [[Western Church]]es. Over time, teachings on Michael began to vary among Christian denominations.

==Scriptural references==

===Hebrew Bible===
&lt;!--THIS ARTICLE USED TO HAVE TOO MANY IMAGES AND THEY WERE CLEANED UP AND
AN IMAGE GALLERY WAS CREATED. PLEASE DO NOT ADD ADDITIONAL IMAGES SINCE THAT
WAS MAKING THE TEXT HARD TO READ AND CREATED OVERLAP PROBLEMS ON DIFFERENT
SCREEN SIZES. IF YOU HAVE NEW (AND &quot;IMPORTANT&quot;) IMAGES THEY CAN BE ADDED
TO THE GALLERY AT THE END OF THE PAGE, NOT IN THE BODY OF THE ARTICLE.
--&gt;
[[File:Guido Reni 031.jpg|200px|thumb|[[Guido Reni]]'s Michael (in [[Santa Maria della Concezione]] church, Rome, 1636) tramples Satan. A mosaic of the same painting decorates ''St. Michael's Altar'' in [[St. Peter's Basilica]].]]

In the [[Hebrew Scriptures]], and hence in the [[Old Testament]], the prophet [[Daniel]] experiences a vision after having undergone a period of fasting. In the vision in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Daniel#10:13|Daniel 10:13-21]] an angel identifies Michael as the protector of [[Israel]]. Daniel refers to Michael as a &quot;prince of the first rank&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Who's who in the Jewish Bible'' by David Mandel 2007 ISBN 0-8276-0863-2 page 270&lt;/ref&gt; Later in the vision in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Daniel#12:1|Daniel 12:1]] Daniel is informed about the role of Michael during the &quot;time of the End&quot; when there will be &quot;distress such as has not happened from the beginning of nations&quot; and that:&lt;ref&gt;''Daniel: Wisdom to the Wise: Commentary on the Book of Daniel'' by Zdravko Stefanovic 2007 ISBN 0-8163-2212-0 page 391&lt;/ref&gt;

:&quot;At that time Michael, the great prince who protects your people, will arise.&quot;

In view of this, Michael is seen as playing an important role as the protector of Israel, and later of the [[Christian Church]].

Although the three references to Michael in the [[Book of Daniel]] 10:13, 10:21 and 12:1 are to the same individual who acts in similar ways in all three cases, the last one is set at the &quot;[[end times]]&quot; while the first two refer to local time in Persia.&lt;ref&gt;''Daniel: a reader's guide'' by William H. Shea 2005 ISBN 0-8163-2077-2 pages 270-271&lt;/ref&gt; These are the only three references to Archangel Michael in the Hebrew Bible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richard&quot;/&gt;   

The references to the &quot;captain of the host of the Lord&quot; encountered by [[Book of Joshua|Joshua]] in the early days of his campaigns in the [[Promised Land]] 
([[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Joshua#5:13|Joshua 5:13-15]]) have at times been interpreted as Michael the Archangel, but there is no theological basis for that assumption, given that Joshua then worshiped this figure, and angels are not to be worshiped. Some scholars also point that the figure may refer to God himself.&lt;ref&gt;''Yahshua, the Man Behind the Glory'' by Jarid Miller ISBN 1-4500-9880-0 pages 15-16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Joshua'' by J. Gordon McConville, Stephen Williams 2010 ISBN 0-8028-2702-0 pages 29-30&lt;/ref&gt; In the book of Joshua's account of the fall of Jericho, Joshua &quot;looked up and saw a man standing in front of him with a drawn sword in his hand&quot;. When the still unaware Joshua asks which side of the fight the Archangel is on, the response was, &quot;neither...but as commander of the army of the Lord I have now come&quot;.

===New Testament===
The [[Book of Revelation]] ([[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Revelation#12:7|12:7-9]]) describes a [[war in heaven]] in which Michael, being stronger, defeats Satan:&lt;ref name=Art13 &gt;''Revelation 12-22'' by John MacArthur 2000 ISBN 0-8024-0774-9 pages 13-14&lt;/ref&gt;

:&quot;...there was war in heaven. Michael and his angels fought against the dragon, and the dragon and his angels fought back. But he was not strong enough, and they lost their place in heaven.&quot;

After the conflict, Satan is thrown to earth along with the [[fallen angel]]s, where he (&quot;that ancient serpent called the devil&quot;) still tries to &quot;lead the whole world astray&quot;.&lt;ref name=Art13 /&gt;

Separately, in the [[Epistle of Jude]] [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Jude#1:9|1:9]] Michael is specifically referred to as an &quot;archangel&quot; when he again confronts Satan:&lt;ref name=Guiley &gt;''The encyclopedia of angels'' by Rosemary Guiley 2004 ISBN 0-8160-5023-6 page 49&lt;/ref&gt;

:&quot;Michael the archangel, when contending with the devil he disputed about the body of Moses&quot;

A reference to an &quot;archangel&quot; also appears in the [[First Epistle to the Thessalonians]] {{bibleverse-nb|1|Thessalonians|4:16}}

:&quot;... the Lord himself shall descend from heaven, with a shout, with the voice of the archangel, and with the trump of God: and the dead in Christ shall rise first&quot; ([[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/1 Thessalonians#4:16|American Standard Version of 1901]], a version that uses the definite article, &quot;''the'' archangel&quot;, absent in the original Greek and in English translations such as the ([http://www.esvbible.org/search/1Th4.16/ English Standard Version of 2001], which has: &quot;the Lord himself will descend from heaven with a cry of command, with the voice of an archangel, and with the sound of the trumpet of God&quot;).

This archangel who heralds the [[second coming of Christ]] is not named,&lt;ref name=Guiley /&gt; but is probably Michael.&lt;ref name=Lees&gt;[http://www.internationalstandardbible.com/M/michael.html John A. Lees, &quot;Michael&quot; in James Orr (editor), ''The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia'' (Eerdmans 1939)]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Qur'an===
Michael ([[Arabic]]: ميخائيل, ''Mikhail'' ميكائيل, ''Mikael'' ), is one of the two archangels mentioned in the [[Qur'an]], alongside [[Jibreel]] (Gabriel). In the Qur'an, Michael is mentioned once only, in [[Sura 2]]:98: &quot;Whoever is an enemy to God, and His angels and His messengers, and Jibreel and Mikhail! Then, lo! God (Himself) is an enemy to the disbelievers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Qur'an, sura 2 ([[Al-Baqara]]), ayat 98 {{Cite quran|2|98|s=ns}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Muslims believe that the reference in [[Sura 11]]:69 is Michael, one of the three angels who visited [[Abraham]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

==Religious traditions==

===Judaism===
According to rabbinic Jewish tradition, Michael acted as the advocate of Israel, and sometimes had to fight with the princes of the other nations (cf. Daniel 10:13) and particularly with the angel [[Samael]], Israel's accuser. Michael's enmity with Samael dates from the time when the latter was thrown down from heaven. Samael took hold of the wings of Michael, whom he wished to bring down with him in his fall; but Michael was saved by God.&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Pirke R. El. xxvi&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Jewish Encyclopedia - Michael | work = Jewish Encyclopedia | url = http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=560&amp;letter=M#1833 | accessdate=2009-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Michael is also said to have had a dispute with Samael over the soul of Moses.&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Deut. Rabbah xi. 6&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:MichaelHebreo.jpg|thumb|150px|Michael in [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]]]]
The idea that Michael was the advocate of the Jews became so prevalent that in spite of the rabbinical prohibition against appealing to angels as intermediaries between God and his people, Michael came to occupy a certain place in the Jewish liturgy. There were two prayers written beseeching him as the prince of mercy to intercede in favor of Israel: one composed by Eliezer ha-Kalir, and the other by Judah ben Samuel he-Hasid. But appeal to Michael seems to have been more common in ancient times. Thus Jeremiah is said to have addressed a prayer to him.&lt;ref&gt;Baruch Apoc. Ethiopic, ix. 5&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;When a man is in need he must pray directly to God, and neither to Michael nor to [[Gabriel]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Yer. Ber. ix. 13a&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[rabbi]]s declare that Michael entered upon his role of defender at the time of the biblical patriarchs. Thus, according to Rabbi Eliezer ben Jacob, it was Michael who rescued Abraham from the furnace into which he had been thrown by Nimrod (Midrash Genesis Rabbah xliv. 16). It was Michael, the &quot;one that had escaped&quot; (Genesis 14:13), who told Abraham that Lot had been taken captive (Midrash Pirke R. El.), and who protected Sarah from being defiled by Abimelech. He announced to Sarah that she would bear a son and he rescued Lot at the destruction of Sodom.&lt;ref&gt;Talmud B. M. 86b&lt;/ref&gt;

====Midrash====
It is said that Michael prevented [[Isaac]] from being sacrificed by his father by substituting a ram in his place, and saved [[Jacob]], while yet in his mother's womb, from being killed by Samael.&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Abkir, in Yalḳ., Gen. 110&lt;/ref&gt; Later Michael prevented Laban from harming Jacob.(''[[Pirke De-Rabbi Eliezer]]'', xxxvi). It was Michael who wrestled with Jacob and who afterward blessed him.&lt;ref&gt;Targum of Pseudo-Jonathan on Genesis 32:25; ''Pirke De-Rabbi Eliezer'', xxxvii&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[midrash]] ''Exodus Rabbah'' holds that Michael exercised his function of advocate of Israel at the time of the Exodus also, when Satan (as an adversary) accused the Israelites of idolatry and declared that they were consequently deserving of death by [[drowning]] in the Red Sea. Michael is also said to have destroyed the army of [[Sennacherib]].&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Exodus Rabbah xviii. 5&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
&lt;!--THIS ARTICLE USED TO HAVE TOO MANY IMAGES AND THEY WERE CLEANED UP AND
AN IMAGE GALLERY WAS CREATED. PLEASE DO NOT ADD ADDITIONAL IMAGES SINCE THAT
WAS MAKING THE TEXT HARD TO READ AND CREATED OVERLAP PROBLEMS ON DIFFERENT
SCREEN SIZES. IF YOU HAVE NEW (AND &quot;IMPORTANT&quot;) IMAGES THEY CAN BE ADDED
TO THE GALLERY AT THE END OF THE PAGE, NOT IN THE BODY OF THE ARTICLE.
--&gt;

====Early Christian views and devotions====
[[File:Michael4.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Statue of Archangel Michael at the [[University of Bonn]], slaying Satan as a dragon. ''[[Quis ut Deus]]'' is inscribed on his shield.]]
The early Christians regarded some of the [[martyr]]s such as [[Saint George]], and [[Theodore of Amasea|Saint Theodore]], as military patrons ; but to St Michael they gave the care of their sick and he was first venerated as a healer in [[Phrygia]] (modern-day Turkey).&lt;ref name=Cathenc &gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10275b.htm |title=Catholic encyclopedia: '&amp;#39;St. Michael the Archangel'&amp;#39; |publisher=Newadvent.org |date=1911-10-01 |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The earliest and most famous sanctuary to Saint Michael in the ancient near east was also associated with healing waters. It was the ''[[Michaelion]]'' built in early 4th century by [[Emperor Constantine]] at [[Chalcedon]], on the site of an earlier Temple called ''Sosthenion''.&lt;ref name=Richard &gt;''Saint Michael the Archangel in medieval English legend'' by Richard Freeman Johnson 2005 ISBN 1-84383-128-7 pages 33-34&lt;/ref&gt; 

A painting of the Archangel slaying a serpent became a major art piece at the Michaelion after Constantine defeated [[Licinius]] near there in 324, eventually leading to the standard [[iconography]] of Archangel Michael as a [[warrior saint]] slaying a dragon.&lt;ref name=Richard /&gt; The Michaelion was a magnificent church and in time became a model for hundreds of other churches in [[Eastern Christianity]] which spread devotions to the Archangel.&lt;ref&gt;''Sacred and Legendary Art'' by Anna Jameson 2004 ISBN 0-7661-8144-8 page 92&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 4th century, [[Basil the Great|Saint Basil the Great]]'s homily (''De Angelis'') placed Saint Michael over all the angels. He was called ''&quot;Archangel&quot;'' because he is the prince of the other angels.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; Into the 6th century, the view of Michael as a healer continued in Rome, when after a plague the sick slept at night in the church of ''[[Castel Sant'Angelo]]'' (dedicated to him for saving Rome), waiting for his manifestation.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt;&lt;ref name=Butler320 &gt;Alban Butler, The lives of the fathers, martyrs, and other principal saints Published by J. Duffy, 1866 page 320&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 6th century the growth of devotions to the saint in the [[Western Church]] were manifested by the feasts dedicated to him, as recorded in the [[Leonine Sacramentary]]. The 7th century [[Gelasian Sacramentary]] included the feast ''&quot;S. Michaelis Archangeli&quot;'', as did the 8th century [[Sacramentary#The Gregorian Sacramentary|Gregorian Sacramentary]].&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; Some of these documents refer to a no longer extant ''Basilica Archangeli'' on [[via Salaria]] in Rome.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt;

The [[angelology]] of [[Pseudo-Dionysius the Areopagite|Pseudo-Dionysius]] which was widely read as of the 6th century gave Michael a rank in the [[celestial hierarchy]].&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; Later, in the 13th century, others such as [[Bonaventure]] believed that he is the prince of the [[Seraphim]], the first of the nine angelic orders. According to [[Thomas Aquinas|Saint Thomas Aquinas]] (''[[Summa Theologica|Summa]]'' Ia. 113.3), he is the Prince of the last and lowest choir, the angels.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt;

====Roman Catholicism====
[[File:Jacopo vignali, san michele arcangelo libera le anime del purgatorio.jpg|thumb|200px|Archangel Michael ''[[Saint Michael (Roman Catholic)#Saving souls at the hour of death|reaching to save souls in purgatory]]'', by [[Jacopo Vignali]], 17th century]]
Roman Catholics often refer to Michael as &quot;Saint Michael&quot;, a title that does not indicate [[Canonization|canonisation]], any more than it does for Saint Peter and Saint Paul. He is generally referred to in Christian [[litany|litanies]] as &quot;Saint Michael&quot;, as in the [[Litany of the Saints]]. In the shortened version of this litany used in the [[Easter Vigil]], he alone of the angels and archangels is mentioned, omitting Saint Gabriel and [[Raphael (archangel)|Saint Raphael]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1&amp;q=Cadwallader+Michael+Chonai&amp;btnG= Alan H. Cadwallader, Michael Trainor, ''Colossae in Space and Time'' (Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht 2011 ISBN 978-3-525-53397-0), p. 323]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Saint Michael (Roman Catholic)|Roman Catholic teachings]] Saint Michael has four main roles or offices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10275b.htm |title=Catholic encyclopedia |publisher=Newadvent.org |date=1911-10-01 |accessdate=2010-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; His first role is the leader of the Army of God and the leader of heaven's forces in their triumph over the powers of hell.&lt;ref name=Donna60 &gt;Donna-Marie O'Boyle, ''Catholic Saints Prayer Book'' OSV Publishing, 2008 ISBN 1-59276-285-9 page 60&lt;/ref&gt; He is viewed as the angelic model for the virtues of the ''spiritual warrior'', with the conflict against evil at times viewed as the ''battle within''.&lt;ref name=Starr2 &gt;Mirabai Starr, Saint Michael: The Archangel, Published by Sounds True, 2007 ISBN 1-59179-627-X page 2&lt;/ref&gt;

The second and third roles of Michael in Catholic teachings deal with death. In his second role, Michael is the angel of death, carrying the souls of all the deceased to heaven. In this role, at the hour of death, Michael descends and gives each soul the chance to redeem itself before passing, thus consternating the devil and his minions. Catholic prayers often refer to this role of Michael. In his third role, he weighs souls in his perfectly balanced scales (hence Michael is often depicted holding scales).&lt;ref&gt;Mirabai Starr, ''Saint Michael: The Archangel'', 2007 ISBN 1-59179-627-X page 39&lt;/ref&gt; 

In his fourth role, St Michael, the special patron of the Chosen People in the Old Testament, is also the guardian of the Church; it was thus not unusual for the angel to be revered by the military orders of knights during the [[Middle Ages in history|Middle Ages]]. This role also extends to his being the patron saint of a number of cities and countries.&lt;ref&gt;Alban Butler, ''The lives of the fathers, martyrs, and other principal saints'' Published by B. Dornin, 1821 page 117&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Michael McGrath, ''Patrons and Protectors'' Published by Liturgy Training, 2001 ISBN 1-56854-109-0&lt;/ref&gt;

Roman Catholicism includes traditions such as the ''[[Prayer to Saint Michael]]'' which specifically asks for the faithful to be &quot;defended&quot; by the saint.&lt;ref&gt;[[EWTN]] Prayer to St Michael [http://www.ewtn.com/devotionals/prayers/michael.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matthew Bunson ''The Catholic Almanac's Guide to the Church'' OSV Publishing, 2001 ISBN 0-87973-914-2 page 315&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Amy Welborn, ''The Words We Pray'' Loyola Press, 2004 ISBN 0-8294-1956-X, page 101&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Chaplet of Saint Michael]]'' consists of nine salutations, one for each choir of angels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ann Ball page 123&quot;&gt;Ann Ball, ''2003 Encyclopedia of Catholic Devotions and Practices'' ISBN 0-87973-910-X page 123&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[EWTN]] [http://www.ewtn.com/devotionals/prayers/chaplet-of-st-michael.htm The Chaplet of St. Michael the Archangel]&lt;/ref&gt;

It should be noted that the Roman Catholic traditions and teachings concerning St. Michael the Archangel are ''not'' required beliefs and practices but rather are strongly encouraged as a means of individuals and congregations increasing in spiritual strength against evil.

====Eastern and Oriental Orthodoxy====
[[File:ArchAngelMoscow.jpg|thumb|150px|left|Archangel Michael statue [[Kiev]], [[Ukraine]], where he is the [[patron saint]].&lt;ref name=Fairbairn /&gt;]]
The [[Eastern Orthodox]] accord Michael the title &quot;Archistrategos&quot;, or &quot;Supreme Commander of the Heavenly Hosts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1&amp;q=Baun+%22Michael+Archistrategos%22&amp;btnG= Jane Baun, ''Tales from Another Byzantium'' (Cambridge University Press 2007 ISBN 978-0-521-82395-1), p. 391 et passim]&lt;/ref&gt; The Eastern Orthodox pray to their guardian angels and above all to Michael and Gabriel.&lt;ref&gt;''Eastern Orthodox Theology: A Contemporary Reader'' by Daniel B. Clendenin 2003 ISBN 0801026512 page 75&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eastern Orthodox have always had strong devotions to angels, and the trend continues to date with the term &quot;Bodiless Powers&quot; applied to them.&lt;ref name=EOEnc/&gt; A number of feasts dedicated to Archangel Michael are celebrated by the Eastern Orthodox throughout the year.&lt;ref name=EOEnc&gt;''The Encyclopedia of Eastern Orthodox Christianity'' by John Anthony McGuckin 2011 ISBN 1405185392 page 30&lt;/ref&gt;

Archangel Michael is mentioned in a number of Eastern Orthodox hymns and prayer, and his icons are widely used within Eastern Orthodox churches.&lt;ref name=B16 &gt;''The Eastern Orthodox Church: Its Thought and Life'' by Ernst Benz 2008 ISBN 0202362981 page 16&lt;/ref&gt; In many Eastern Orthodox icons, Christ is accompanied by a number of angels, Michael being a predominant figure among them.&lt;ref name=B16 /&gt;

In Russia many monasteries, cathedrals, court and merchant churches are dedicated to the Chief Commander Michael, and most Russian cities have a church or chapel dedicated to the Archangel Michael.&lt;ref&gt;''A Geography of Russia and Its Neighbors'' by Mikhail S. Blinnikov 2010 ISBN page 203&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Architectures of Russian Identity, 1500 to the Present'' by James Cracraft 2003 ISBN 0801488281 page 42&lt;/ref&gt;

The place of Michael in the [[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria]] is a [[intercession of saints|saintly intercessor]], where he is seen as the one who presents to God the prayers of the just, who accompanies the souls of the dead to heaven, who defeats the devil. He is celebrated liturgically on the 12th of each month.&lt;ref&gt;''Two Thousand Years of Coptic Christianity'' by Otto Friedrich August Meinardus 2010 ISBN 977-424-757-4 pages 27, 117, 147&lt;/ref&gt; In Alexandria, a church was dedicated to him in the early fourth century on the 12th of the month of Ba'unah. On the 12th of the [[month of Hathor]] is the celebration of Michael's appointment in heaven, where Michael became the chief of the angels.&lt;ref&gt;''Money, Land and Trade: An Economic History of the Muslim Mediterranean'' by Nelly Hanna 2002 ISBN 1-86064-699-9 page 226&lt;/ref&gt;

====Protestant views====
[[File:€2 commemorative coin Germany 2008.png|thumb|150px|[[St. Michaelis Church, Hamburg|St. Michaelis Luthern Church]] on the €2 coin 2008]]
Most Protestant Christians (excluding [[Anglicans]]) generally reject the [[intercession of saints]] as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;''Holy People of the World: A Cross-Cultural Encyclopedia'' by Phyllis G. Jestice 2004 ISBN 1-57607-355-6 page 888&lt;/ref&gt; However, an unofficial [[Anglican]] prayer of preparation before Mass includes a confession to &quot;Michael the Archangel&quot; as well as other saints such as [[John the Baptist]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Anglican Service Book: A Traditional Language Adaptation of the 1979 Book of Common Prayer Together With the Psalter or Psalms of David &amp; Additional Devotations'' 1991 ISBN 0-9629955-0-9 pages 238-239&lt;/ref&gt;

Protestant denominations generally recognize only two archangels, Michael and [[Gabriel (archangel)|Gabriel]], usually emphasizing Michael, unlike Judaism, Roman Catholicism, and Eastern Orthodoxy which may at times recognize seven (and in rare cases eight) archangels, with Michael, Gabriel, and [[Raphael (archangel)|Raphael]] generally regarded with an elevated status, e.g. being the only archangels honored by name in Catholicism.&lt;ref&gt;''Renewal Theology: Systematic Theology from a Charismatic Perspective'' by J. Rodman Williams 1996 ISBN 0-310-20914-5 page 183&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Encyclopedia of Angels'' by Rosemary Guiley 2004 ISBN 0-8160-5023-6 page 31&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some early [[Protestant]] scholars identified Michael with the [[Pre-existence of Christ|pre-incarnate Christ]], basing their view, partly on the juxtaposition of the &quot;child&quot; and the archangel in Revelation 12, and partly on the attributes ascribed to him in Daniel.&lt;ref name=Lees/&gt; Similarly in 1751 [[Anglican]] bishop Robert Clayton held that Michael was the [[Logos (Christianity)|Logos]] and Gabriel the [[Holy Spirit (Christianity)|Holy Spirit]], an extreme position which resulted in his prosecution, just before he died.&lt;ref&gt;''The Church of England c.1689-c.1833: From Toleration to Tractarianism'' by John Walsh, Colin Haydon and Stephen Taylor 1993 ISBN 0-521-41732-5 page 47&lt;/ref&gt;

Michael continues to be recognized among Protestants by key churches dedicated to him, e.g. [[St. Michaelis Church, Hamburg]], a famous [[Lutheran Church]] which appears on the coins of the [[European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;''Frommer's European Cruises &amp; Ports of Call'' by Jerry Brown and Fran Wenograd Golden 2004 ISBN 0-7645-4290-7 page 352&lt;/ref&gt;

At Bach's time, the annual feast of Michael and all the angels on 29 September was regularly celebrated with a festive service, for which Bach composed several cantatas, for example the [[Chorale cantata (Bach)|chorale cantata]] ''[[Herr Gott, dich loben alle wir, BWV 130]]'' in 1724.

====Jehovah's Witnesses====
{{See also|Jehovah's witnesses#Jehovah and Jesus Christ|l1=Jehovah's Witnesses beliefs about Jesus}}

[[Jehovah's Witnesses]] believe Michael to be another name for [[Jesus Christ]] in heaven, in his pre-human and post-resurrection existence.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated218&quot;&gt;Reasoning from the Scriptures, 1985, Watchtower Bible and Tract Society, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; They assert that, because a definite article is used at Jude 9 when referring to &quot;Michael the Archangel&quot;, and because the term &quot;archangel&quot; is used only in the singular in the Bible, never clearly in the plural, that therefore Michael is the only archangel, and therefore synonymous with Jesus, who is described at {{Bibleverse|1|Thessalonians|4:16|ESV}} as descending &quot;with a cry of command, with the voice of an archangel, and with the sound of the trumpet&quot;. They also understand Jesus as saying in [[Book of Revelation]] 3:12 that on &quot;the one that conquers&quot; he will write &quot;that new name of mine&quot;.&lt;ref&gt; http://www.jw.org/en/publications/bible/revelation/3/#v-12&lt;/ref&gt;

They believe the prominent roles assigned to Michael at Daniel 12:1 and Revelation 12:7; 19:14, 16 are identical to Jesus' roles, as the one chosen to lead God's people, and as the one who &quot;stands up&quot;, identifying them as the same spirit being. Because they identify Michael with Jesus, he is therefore considered the first and greatest of all God's heavenly sons, God's chief messenger who takes the lead in vindicating God's [[sovereignty]], sanctifying his name, fighting the wicked forces of Satan, and protecting God's covenant people on earth.&lt;ref&gt;''What Does The Bible Really Teach?'' Chapter 9 Paragraph 4 under the heading A WAR IN HEAVEN, also see appendix of same publication, pages 218-219. Published by Jehovah's Witnesses 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Jehovah's Witnesses also identify Michael with the &quot;[[Angel of the Lord]]&quot; who led the Israelites in the wilderness. &lt;ref&gt; &quot;Your Leader Is One, the Christ&quot; - ''The Watchtower - Announcing Jehovah's Kingdom'' - September 15, 2010, pg 21. &lt;/ref&gt;

====Seventh-day Adventists====
{{See also|Seventh-day Adventist theology#Christ and the Archangel Michael|l1=Seventh-day Adventist beliefs about Michael}}

[[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventists]] believe that Michael is another name for the Heavenly Christ, and another name for the [[Logos (Christianity)|Word-of-God]] (as in [[John 1]]) before He became incarnate as Jesus.  ''Archangel'' (meaning &quot;Chief of the Angels&quot;) was the leadership position held by the Word-of-God as Michael while among the angels.  So according to Adventist theology, Michael was considered the &quot;eternal Word&quot;, and not a created being or created angel, and the one by whom all things were created.  The Word was then born incarnate as Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;''Seventh Day Adventists: What do they believe?'' by Val Waldeck Pilgrim Publications (April 5, 2005) page 16&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventists]] believe the name &quot;Michael&quot; is significant in showing who it is, just as &quot;Immanuel&quot; (which means &quot;God with us&quot;) is about who Jesus is. They believe that name &quot;Michael&quot; signifies &quot;one who is God&quot; and that as the &quot;Archangel&quot; or &quot;chief or head of the angels&quot; He led the angels and thus the statement in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Revelation 12:7-9|Revelation 12:7-9]] identifies Jesus as Michael.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adventistworld.org/article.php?id=787&amp;search=law |title=The Remnant |publisher=Adventist World |date= |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventists]] believe that the term 'Michael' is but one of the many titles applied to the Son of God, the second person of the Godhead. But, according to Adventists, such a view does not in any way conflict with the belief in His full deity and eternal pre-existence, nor does it in the least disparage His person and work.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sdanet.org/atissue/books/qod/index.htm Seventh-day Adventists Answer Questions on Doctrine], Review and Herald Publishing Association, Washington, D.C., 1957. Chapter 8 &quot;Christ, and Michael the Archangel&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Seventh-day Adventist view, the statement in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/1 Thessalonians#4:13|1 Thessalonians 4:13-18]]: ''&quot;For the Lord himself shall descend from heaven, with a shout, with the voice of the archangel, and with the trump of God&quot;'' identifies Jesus as Archangel, which is Michael.&lt;ref name=AdventistRef /&gt; And the Seventh-day Adventists believe that [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#5:25|John 5:25-29]] also confirms that Jesus and Michael are the same.&lt;ref name=AdventistRef &gt;''Bible readings for the home'' by 7th Day Adventists, London 1949 page 266 [http://books.google.com/books?id=lETMH_kCeJcC&amp;pg=PA266&amp;dq=John+5:25+adventist+michael&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=y9zUTuSFO4OcsAbr_bizAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventists]] believe there is and can only be one archangel and that one Archangel is named Michael and yet in Scripture is shown as doing what also applies to Christ even from the beginning, so is Christ pre-incarnate. There was a perception that Adventists were relegating Jesus to something less than [[divinity|divine]] or less than God but that is not valid since Seventh-day Adventism theology teaches and is expressly [[Trinitarianism|Trinitarian]].&lt;ref&gt;Jerry A. Moon, [http://www.sdanet.org/atissue/trinity/moon/moon-trinity1.htm The Adventist Trinity Debate Part 1: Historical Overview] and [http://www.sdanet.org/atissue/trinity/moon/moon-trinity2.htm The Adventist Trinity Debate Part 2: The Role of Ellen G. White]. Copyright 2003 Andrews University Press. See also &quot;[http://www.sdanet.org/atissue/trinity/gane-thesis/index.htm The Arian or Anti-Trinitarian Views Presented in Seventh-day Adventist Literature and the Ellen G. White Answer]&quot; by Erwin Roy Gane&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.ministrymagazine.org/archive/2009/February/the-trinity.html The Trinity in Seventh-day Adventist History]&quot; by Merlin D. Burt. ''[[Ministry (magazine)|Ministry]]'' February 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

====The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints====
{{See also|Beliefs and practices of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints}}
[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|Latter-day Saints]] (also known informally as [[Mormons]]) believe that Michael is [[Adam]], the [[Ancient of Days]] (Dan. 7), a prince, and the patriarch of the human family and that Michael assisted [[Jehovah]] (the heavenly form of [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]]) in the creation of the world under the direction of [[God the Father]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last=Millet | first=Robert L. | title=The Man Adam | magazine=Liahona | year=1998 | month=February | url=http://lds.org/liahona/1998/02/the-man-adam?lang=eng }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{lds|Doctrine and Covenants|dc|27|11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{lds|Doctrine and Covenants|dc|107|53|56}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{lds|Doctrine and Covenants|dc|128|21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Feasts, patronages and orders==

===Feasts===
In the [[Roman Catholic calendar of saints]], [[Calendar of saints (Church of England)|Anglican Calendar of Saints]], and the [[Calendar of Saints (Lutheran)|Lutheran Calendar of Saints]], the archangel's feast is celebrated on [[Michaelmas]] Day. The day is also considered the feast of Saints [[Gabriel]], and [[Raphael (archangel)|Raphael]] or the ''Feast of Saint Michael and All Angels''. On the Western [[Christian calendar]] the feast is celebrated on 29 September.&lt;ref&gt;''Saint Michael the Archangel in medieval English legend'' by Richard Freeman Johnson 2005 ISBN 1-84383-128-7 page 105&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], Saint Michael's principal feast day is November 8 (November 21 by most Orthodox churches since they use the [[Julian calendar]]), where he is honored along with the rest of the ''&quot;Bodiless Powers of Heaven&quot;'' (i.e. [[angel]]s) as their Supreme Commander, and the ''[[Miracle of the Archangel Michael at Chonae#Miracle of the Archangel Michael|Miracle at Chonae]]'' is commemorated on September 6.&lt;ref&gt;''Icons and saints of the Eastern Orthodox Church'' by Alfredo Tradigo 2006 ISBN 0-89236-845-4 page 46&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Blackwell Companion to Eastern Christianity'' 2010 by Ken Parry ISBN 1-4443-3361-5 page 242&lt;/ref&gt;

===Patronages and orders===
&lt;!--
If you want to add patronages here, be SURE to add [[WP:RS]] references, and not just claim them, if you do not want them deleted soon. 
--&gt;
In late [[medieval Christianity]], Michael, together with [[Saint George]], became the [[patron saint]] of [[chivalry]] and is now also considered the patron saint of police officers and the military.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ann Ball, 2003 ''Encyclopedia of Catholic Devotions and Practices'' ISBN 0-87973-910-X page 586&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:COA of Kyiv Kurovskyi.svg|130px|thumb|[[Coat of arms of Kiev]]]]
In mid to late 15th century, France was one of only four courts in [[Western Christianity|Western Christendom]] without an order of knighthood.&lt;ref name=Dacre &gt;''The Knights of the Crown: The Monarchical Orders of Knighthood in Later Medieval Europe 1325-1520'' by D'Arcy Jonathan Dacre Boulton 2000 ISBN 0-85115-795-5 pages 427-428&lt;/ref&gt; Later in the 15th century, [[Jean Molinet]] glorified the primordial feat of arms of the archangel as &quot;the first deed of knighthood and chivalrous prowess that was ever achieved.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Noted by [[Johan Huizinga]], ''[[The Autumn of the Middle Ages|The Waning of the Middle Ages]]'' (1919, 1924:56.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus Michael was the natural patron of the first [[chivalric order]] of France, the [[Order of Saint Michael]] of 1469.&lt;ref name=Dacre /&gt; In the [[British honours system]], a chivalric order founded in 1818 is also named for these two saints, the [[Order of St Michael and St George]].&lt;ref&gt;Angels in the early modern world By Alexandra Walsham, Cambridge University Press, 2006 ISBN 0-521-84332-4 page 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Order of Michael the Brave]] is Romania's highest military decoration.

Apart from his being a patron of warriors, the sick and the suffering also consider Archangel Michael their patron saint.&lt;ref&gt;''Patron Saints'' by Michael Freze 1992 ISBN 0-87973-464-7 page 170&lt;/ref&gt; Based on the legend of his 8th century [[Vision (spirituality)|apparition]] at [[Mont-Saint-Michel]], France, the Archangel is the patron of [[sailors|mariners]] in this famous sanctuary.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; After the evangelisation of Germany, where mountains were often dedicated to pagan gods, Christians placed many mountains under the patronage of the Archangel, and numerous mountain chapels of St. Michael appeared all over Germany.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; He has been the patron saint of [[Brussels]] since the Middle Ages.&lt;ref&gt;''Netherlandish sculpture 1450-1550'' by Paul Williamson 2002 ISBN 0-8109-6602-6 page 42&lt;/ref&gt; The city of [[Arkhangelsk]] in Russia is named for the Archangel. [[Ukraine]] and its capital [[Kiev]] also consider Michael their patron saint and protector.&lt;ref name=Fairbairn &gt;''Eastern Orthodoxy through Western eyes'' by Donald Fairbairn 2002 ISBN 0-664-22497-0 page 148&lt;/ref&gt;

An [[Anglican]] sisterhood dedicated to Saint Michael under the title of the [[Community of St Michael and All Angels]] was founded in 1851.&lt;ref&gt;''All Saints Sisters of the Poor: An Anglican Sisterhood in the Nineteenth Century (Church of England Record Society)'' by Susan Mumm 200 ISBN 0-85115-728-9 page 48&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Congregation of Saint Michael the Archangel]] (CSMA), also known as the ''Michaelite Fathers'', is a religious order of the Roman Catholic Church founded in 1897.

==Major shrines==
&lt;!--DO NOT ADD SMALL PARISH CHURCHES TO THIS SECTION. IT IS FOR MAJOR SHRINES. --&gt;
:''For a larger gallery (and hence a structured list) of church images, please see'': [[:Commons:Structured gallery of churches dedicated to Archangel Michael|Saint Michael church gallery]].
* [[St. Michael and St. Gudula Cathedral]], in [[Brussels]], Belgium
* [[Mont Saint-Michel]], [[Normandy]], France - a [[World Heritage Site]]
* [[St. Michael's Cathedral (Toronto)]], Canada[[File:Chrám svatého Michala v Kyjevě.jpg|thumb|250px|[[St. Michael's Golden-Domed Monastery]] in [[Kiev]] ([[Ukraine]]).]]
* [[St. Michael's Cathedral (Izhevsk)]], Russia
* [[St. Michael's Cathedral, Qingdao]], China
* [[Chudov Monastery]] in the Moscow [[Kremlin]]
* [[Archangel Cathedral]] in the [[Moscow Kremlin]] - a World Heritage Site
* [[Monte Sant'Angelo sul Gargano]], [[Gargano]], Italy - a World Heritage Site
* [[St Michael's Mount]], [[Cornwall]], UK
* [[St. Michael's Basilica, Miramichi]], Canada
* [[Skellig Michael]], off the [[Ireland|Irish]] west coast - a World Heritage Site
* [[Coventry Cathedral|St Michael's Cathedral]], [[Coventry]], UK
* [[St. Michael's Golden-Domed Monastery]], [[Kiev]], [[Ukraine]]
* [[Michaelerkirche (Vienna)|St Michael's Church]] in [[Vienna]], Austria
* [[Basilica of St Michael the Archangel]], Tayabas, Quezon, Philippines
* [[Saint Michael's church, Berlin]]
* [[St. Michael's Cathedral (Belgrade)|St. Michael's Cathedral]] in [[Belgrade]], [[Serbia]]

==Legends==

===Judaism===
There is a legend which seems to be of Jewish origin, and which was adopted by the [[Copt]]s, to the effect that Michael was first sent by God to bring [[Nebuchadnezzar]] (c. 600 BC) against Jerusalem, and that Michael was afterward very active in freeing his nation from Babylonian captivity.&lt;ref&gt;[[Émile Amélineau|Amélineau]], &quot;Contes et Romans de l'Egypte Chrétienne&quot;, ii. 142 et seq&lt;/ref&gt;
According to midrash [[Genesis Rabbah]], Michael saved [[Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego|Hananiah]] and his companions from the [[Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego|Fiery furnace]].&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Genesis Rabbah xliv. 16&lt;/ref&gt; Michael was active in the time of [[Esther]]: &quot;The more Haman accused Israel on earth, the more Michael defended Israel in heaven&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Esther Rabbah iii. 8&lt;/ref&gt; It was Michael who reminded [[Ahasuerus]] that he was [[Mordecai]]'s debtor;&lt;ref&gt;[[Targum to Esther]], vi. 1&lt;/ref&gt; and there is a legend that Michael appeared to the high priest [[Hyrcanus]], promising him assistance.&lt;ref&gt;comp. Josephus, &quot;Ant.&quot; xiii. 10, § 3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christendom===
[[File:Michael Miracle Icon Sinai 12th century.jpg|thumb|200px|A 12th-century [[icon]] of the ''[[Miracle of the Archangel Michael at Chonae|Miracle at Chonae]]'', from [[Saint Catherine's Monastery]], [[Mount Sinai]].]]
The [[Orthodox Church]] celebrates the [[Miracle of the Archangel Michael at Chonae|Miracle at Chonae]] on September 6.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; The legend states that the pagans directed a stream against the sanctuary of St Michael to destroy it, but Archippus (the custodian) prayed to Michael, the archangel appeared and split the rock to open up a new bed for the stream, directing the flow away from the church and sanctifying forever the waters which came from the new gorge.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; The spring which came forth after this event is said to have special healing powers.&lt;ref&gt;Alan H. Cadwallader, Michael Trainor, ''Colossae in Space and Time'' (Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht 2011 ISBN 978-3-525-53397-0), p. 323&lt;/ref&gt; The legend existed in earlier times, but the 5th-7th century texts that refer to the miracle at Chonae formed the basis of specific paradigms for &quot;properly approaching&quot; angelic intermediaries for more effective prayers within the Christian culture.&lt;ref name=Peers &gt;''Subtle bodies: representing angels in Byzantium'' by Glenn Peers 2001 Univ of Calif Press ISBN 0-520-22405-1 page 144 [http://books.google.com/books?id=kaonEi_dCJIC&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=Chonae+michael+miracle+university+california&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=CTq-Tsy6EczqOa-SpdMB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a late 5th century legend in [[Cornwall]], UK that the Archangel appeared to fishermen on [[St Michael's Mount]].&lt;ref name=Cornwall /&gt; According to author Richard Freeman Johnson this legend is likely a nationalistic twist to a myth.&lt;ref name=Cornwall &gt;''Saint Michael the Archangel in medieval English legend'' by Richard Freeman Johnson 2005 ISBN 1-84383-128-7 page 68&lt;/ref&gt; Cornish legends also hold that the mount itself was constructed by giants&lt;ref&gt;''Popular Romances of the West of England'' by Robert Hunt 2009 ISBN 0-559-12999-8 page 238&lt;/ref&gt; and that [[King Arthur]] battled a giant there.&lt;ref&gt;''Myths and Legends of Britain and Ireland'' by Richard Jones 2006 ISBN 1-84537-594-7 page 17&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RomaCastelSantAngelo-2.jpg|thumb|left|200px|''[[Castel Sant'Angelo]]'' in Rome, with Michael's statue atop.]]
The legend of the apparition of the Archangel at around 490 AD at a secluded hilltop cave on [[Monte Gargano]] in Italy gained a following among the [[Lombards]] in the immediate period thereafter, and by the 8th century pilgrims arrived from as far away as England.&lt;ref&gt;''The Medieval state: essays presented to James Campbell'' by John Robert Maddicott, David Michael Palliser, James Campbell 2003 ISBN 1-85285-195-3 pages 10-11&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Roman Breviary]] then recorded it on May 8, the date on which the Lombards attributed their 663 victory over the [[Greece|Greek]] [[Naples|Neopolitan]] to the intercession of the Archangel.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; The [[Sanctuary of Monte Sant'Angelo]] at Gargano is a major Catholic pilgrimage site.

According to Roman legends, while a devastating plague persisted in Rome, Archangel Michael appeared with a sword over the [[mausoleum]] of [[Hadrian]], in apparent answer to the prayers of Pope St [[Gregory I the Great]] (c. 590-604) that the plague should cease. After the plague ended, in honor of the occasion, the pope called the mausoleum ''&quot;[[Castel Sant'Angelo]]&quot;'' (Castle of the Holy Angel), the name by which it is still known.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt;&lt;ref name=Butler320 /&gt;

[[File:Mont Saint-Michel France.jpg|thumb|200px|The [[Mont-Saint-Michel]] in [[Normandy]], France]]
According to [[Normandy|Norman]] legend, Michael is said to have appeared to [[St Aubert]], [[Bishop of Avranches]], in 708, giving instruction to build a church on the rocky islet now known as [[Mont Saint-Michel]].&lt;ref name=MonkM &gt;''Mont-Saint-Michel: a monk talks about his abbey'' by Jean-Pierre Mouton, Olivier Mignon 1998 ISBN 2-7082-3351-3 pages 55-56&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CathMont &gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10551a.htm |title=Catholic encyclopedia '&amp;#39;Mont-Saint-Michel'&amp;#39; |publisher=Newadvent.org |date=1911-10-01 |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pilgrim /&gt; In 966 the [[Duke of Normandy]] commissioned a [[Order of St. Benedict|Benedictine]] abbey on the mount, and it remains a major pilgrimage site.&lt;ref name=pilgrim &gt;''Pilgrimage: from the Ganges to Graceland : an encyclopedia, Volume 1'' by Linda Kay Davidson, David Martin Gitlitz 2002 ISBN 1-57607-004-2 page 398&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Portugal|Portuguese]] [[Carmelites|Carmelite]] nun, [[Antónia d'Astónaco]], had reported an apparition and [[private revelation]] of the [[Saint Michael (Roman Catholic)|Archangel Michael]] who had told to this devoted [[Servant of God#Roman Catholicism|Servant of God]], in 1751, that he would like to be honored, and God glorified, by the praying of nine special invocations. These nine invocations correspond to invocations to the nine choirs of angels and origins the famous [[Chaplet of Saint Michael]]. This private revelation and prayers were approved by [[Pope Pius IX]] in 1851.&lt;ref&gt;Ann Ball, 2003 Encyclopedia of Catholic Devotions and Practices ISBN 0-87973-910-X page 123&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[EWTN]] [http://www.ewtn.com/devotionals/prayers/chaplet-of-st-michael.htm The Chaplet of Saint Michael the Archangel]&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1961 to 1965, four young schoolgirls had reported several apparitions of Archangel Michael in the small village of [[San Sebastian de Garabandal|Garabandal]], Spain. At Garabandal, the apparitions of the Archangel Michael were mainly reported as announcing the arrivals of the [[Blessed Virgin Mary|Virgin Mary]]. The [[Catholic Church]] has neither approved nor condemned the [[Garabandal apparitions]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Freze, 1993, ''Voices, Visions, and Apparitions'', OSV Publishing ISBN 0-87973-454-X page 267&lt;/ref&gt;

==Art and literature==

===In literature===
In the English [[epic poem]] ''[[Paradise Lost]]'' by [[John Milton]], Michael commands the army of angels loyal to God against the rebel forces of [[Satan]]. Armed with a sword from God's armory, he bests Satan in personal combat, wounding his side.&lt;ref&gt;John Milton, ''Paradise Lost'' 1674 [http://www.dartmouth.edu/~milton/reading_room/pl/book_6/index.shtml Book VI line 320]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Artistic depictions===
{{Main|Archangel Michael in Christian art}}
[[File:7 archangels.jpg|thumb|left|180px|Early 20th century Russian [[icon]] of the [[Seven Archangels|7 Holy Angels]], with Michael in the front.]]

Most Jewish teachings interpret the [[Ten Commandments|Second Commandment]] as against the use of &quot;graven images&quot; as visual art.&lt;ref&gt;''The Ten commandments for Jews, Christians, and others'' by Roger Van Harn 2007 ISBN 0-8028-2965-1 page 26&lt;/ref&gt; Islamic art's focus on [[calligraphy]], rather than painting and sculpture, similarly derives from the association of [[idolatry]] with the depiction of human or angelic forms.&lt;ref&gt;''Faith &amp; philosophy of Islam'' by Shamim Akhter 2009 ISBN 81-7835-719-4 page 286&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Everything Understanding Islam Book'' by Christine Huda Dodge 2003 ISBN 1-58062-783-8 page 244&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Christian art]], Archangel Michael may be depicted alone or with other angels such as [[Gabriel]]. Some depictions with Gabriel date back to the 8th century, e.g. the stone casket at [[Mortain|Notre Dame de Mortain]] church in France.&lt;ref name=rich141 /&gt; 

The widely reproduced image of ''[[Our Mother of Perpetual Help]]'', an icon of the [[Cretan school]], depicts Michael on the left carrying the lance and sponge of the [[crucifixion of Jesus]], with Gabriel on the right side of [[Madonna and Child|Mary and Jesus]].&lt;ref&gt;''Icons and saints of the Eastern Orthodox Church'' by Alfredo Tradigo 2006 ISBN 0-89236-845-4 page 188&lt;/ref&gt; 

In many depictions Michael is represented as an angelic warrior, fully armed with helmet, sword, and shield.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; The shield may bears the Latin inscription ''[[Quis ut Deus]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Ann Ball, 2003 ''Encyclopedia of Catholic Devotions and Practices'' ISBN 0-87973-910-X page 520&lt;/ref&gt; He may be standing over a serpent, a dragon, or the defeated figure of Satan, whom he sometimes pierces with a lance.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt; The iconography of Michael slaying a serpent goes back to the early 4th century, when [[Emperor Constantine]] defeated [[Licinius]] at the [[Battle of Adrianople (324)|Battle of Adrianople]] in 324 AD, not far from the ''[[Michaelion]]'' a church dedicated to Archangel Michael.&lt;ref name=Richard /&gt; 

Constantine felt that Licinius was an agent of Satan, and associated him with the serpent described in the [[Book of Revelation]] ([[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Revelation#12:9|12:9]]).&lt;ref&gt;''Constantine and the Christian empire'' by Charles Matson Odahl 2004 ISBN 0-415-17485-6 page 315&lt;/ref&gt; After the victory, Constantine commissioned a depiction of himself and his sons slaying Licinius represented as a serpent - a symbolism borrowed from the Christian teachings on the Archangel to whom he attributed the victory. A similar painting, this time with the Archangel Michael himself slaying a serpent then became a major art piece at the Michaelion and eventually lead to the standard [[iconography]] of Archangel Michael as a [[warrior saint]].&lt;ref name=Richard /&gt;

In other depictions Michael may be holding a pair of scales in which he weighs the souls of the departed and may hold the [[book of life]] (as in the [[Book of Revelation]]), to show that he takes part in the judgment.&lt;ref name=Cathenc /&gt;&lt;ref name=rich141 /&gt; However this form of depiction is less common than the slaying of the dragon.&lt;ref name=rich141 &gt;''Saint Michael the Archangel in medieval English legend'' by Richard Freeman Johnson 2005 ISBN 1-84383-128-7 pages 141-147&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michelangelo]] depicted this scene on the altar wall of the [[Sistine Chapel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vaticanstate.va/EN/Monuments/The_Vatican_Museums/Sistine_Chapel--p--5.htm |title=Vatican website: Sistine Chapel |publisher=Vaticanstate.va |date= |accessdate=2010-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Byzantine art]] Michael was often shown as a princely court dignitary, rather than a warrior who battled Satan or with scales for weighing souls on the [[Day of Judgement]].&lt;ref&gt;''Saints in art'' by Rosa Giorgi, Stefano Zuffi 2003 ISBN 0-89236-717-2 pages 274-276&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Rublev Arhangel Mikhail.jpg|[[Andrei Rublev]]'s standalone depiction c. 1408
File:3Erzengel-Botticini.jpg|Michael (left) with archangels [[Raphael (archangel)|Raphael]] and [[Gabriel]], by [[Francesco Botticini|Botticini]], 1470
File:MemlingJudgmentCenter-crop.jpg|''Weighing souls'' on [[Last Judgment|Judgement Day]] by [[Hans Memling]], 15th century
File:GIORDANO, Luca fallen angels.jpg|Michael defeating the [[fallen angel]]s, by [[Luca Giordano]] c. 1660–65 
File:Lorenzo d'Alessandro da San Severino - The Crucifixion; Saint Michael - Walters 37496 - Reverse.jpg|Michael tramples the devil.  [[The Walters Art Museum]].
File:St.michaeljf.JPG|Icon of Michael at [[Trinoma]] chapel ([[Philippines]])
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Saints}}
{{Commons category|Archangel Michael}}
* [[Biblical cosmology]]
* [[Chaplet of Saint Michael]]
* [[Fallen angel]]s
* [[Prayer to Saint Michael]]
* [[San Michele]]
* [[War in Heaven]]
* [[Warrior saint]]s

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10275b.htm ''Catholic Encyclopedia'': St. Michael]
* [http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=560&amp;letter=M ''Jewish Encyclopedia'': Michael]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=MMQUAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA563&amp;dq=michael+mikah+el+like+god&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=GHvQSoqNLIjWzASmqa3fDQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Wilhelm Gesenius and Edward Robinson, ''A Hebrew and English lexicon of the Old Testament'']
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=u3MZAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PT59&amp;dq=michael+mikah+el+like+god&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=GHvQSoqNLIjWzASmqa3fDQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false A comprehensive dictionary of the English language by Joseph Emerson Worcester]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=M5YVAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PT52&amp;dq=michael+mikah+el+like+god&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=J3vQSp7HOojWzASmqa3fDQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false A pronouncing, explanatory, and synonymous dictionary of English by Joseph Emerson Worcester]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=gT86hw4gAi0C&amp;pg=PA81&amp;dq=michael+mikah+el+like+god&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=J3vQSp7HOojWzASmqa3fDQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Prophets and Apostles by Joseph Ponessa,Laurie Watson Manhardt]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=aJP_1RgsDzwC&amp;pg=PA340&amp;dq=michael+mi+kah+el+like+god&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=83rQSqaLL6O4ywT-643vDQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Connections: a guide to types and symbols in the Bible by Glen Carpenter]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=pNX28yR3YSgC&amp;pg=PA859&amp;dq=michael+mikah+el+like+god&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=cXvQSqTuOaG8zgSv1NDeDQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Super Giant Print Dictionary and Concordance by David K. Stabnow]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=amlXOOaSuLMC&amp;pg=PA197&amp;dq=michael+%22who+is+like%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=OLLPSsuSNYjWzAStru3FBA#v=onepage&amp;q=michael%20%22who%20is%20like%22&amp;f=false The Oxford guide to people &amp; places of the Bible By Bruce M. Metzger,Michael D. Coogan]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=Zkla5Gl_66oC&amp;pg=PA347&amp;dq=michael+%22who+is+like%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=z7TPSvaRAqfCyATau9zIBA#v=onepage&amp;q=michael%20%22who%20is%20like%22&amp;f=false The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia by Geoffrey W. Bromiley]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=j9db9kGwG3MC&amp;pg=PA533&amp;dq=michael+%22who+is+like%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=uLTPStqKFqCIzQTxzpDLBA#v=onepage&amp;q=michael%20%22who%20is%20like%22&amp;f=false All the People in the Bible by Richard R. Losch]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=-WC7UgQHQlcC&amp;pg=PA362&amp;dq=michael+%22who+is+like%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=uLTPStqKFqCIzQTxzpDLBA#v=onepage&amp;q=michael%20%22who%20is%20like%22&amp;f=false A dictionary of the Bible by Samuel Rolles Driver]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=Yzmi5_408K4C&amp;pg=PA270&amp;dq=michael+%22who+is+like%22&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=E7LPSqa-EIvyyASbw7nIBA#v=onepage&amp;q=michael%20%22who%20is%20like%22&amp;f=false Who's who in the Jewish Bible by David Mandel]
* [http://books.google.co.ve/books?id=iRMaAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PR101&amp;dq=michael+%22who+is+like%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=0bLPSsa5EIr-zQTe4dXZBA#v=onepage&amp;q=michael%20%22who%20is%20like%22&amp;f=false History of Christian names, Volumen 1 by Charlotte Mary Yonge]

{{Old Testament Saints}}{{New Testament people}}{{Angels in Abrahamic Religions}}
{{Private revelation}}{{Catholic saints}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Michael
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Michael (Archangel)}}
[[Category:Michael (archangel)| ]]
[[Category:Archangels]]
[[Category:Perspectives on Jesus]]
[[Category:Individual angels]]
[[Category:Hebrew Bible topics]]
[[Category:Old Testament saints]]
[[Category:Deities in the Hebrew Bible]]
[[Category:Angels in Christianity]]
[[Category:Angels in Judaism]]
[[Category:Angels in Islam]]
[[Category:Christian saints]]
[[Category:Oriental Orthodox saints]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox saints]]
[[Category:People celebrated in the Lutheran liturgical calendar]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic saints]]
[[Category:Anglican saints]]

{{Link GA|de}}
[[af:Michael (aartsengel)]]
[[am:ሚካኤል]]
[[ar:رئيس الملائكة ميخائيل]]
[[an:Sant Miguel Arcánchel]]
[[arc:ܡܝܟܐܝܠ (ܡܠܐܟܐ)]]
[[az:Mikayıl (mələk)]]
[[bar:Michael (Erzengl)]]
[[be:Міхаіл, архістратыг]]
[[bg:Михаил (архангел)]]
[[br:Arc'hael Mikael]]
[[ca:Sant Miquel Arcàngel]]
[[cs:Michael (archanděl)]]
[[cy:Mihangel]]
[[da:Ærkeenglen Mikael]]
[[de:Michael (Erzengel)]]
[[et:Miikael]]
[[el:Αρχάγγελος Μιχαήλ]]
[[es:Arcángel Miguel]]
[[eo:Sankta Mikaelo]]
[[eu:Mikel goiaingerua]]
[[fa:میکائیل]]
[[fr:Michel (archange)]]
[[fy:Aartsingel Michaël]]
[[ga:Naomh Mícheál (an tArdaingeal)]]
[[gl:Arcanxo Miguel]]
[[ko:미카엘 (대천사)]]
[[hr:Sveti Mihovil]]
[[bpy:সাও মিগুৱেল আর্কানজো]]
[[id:Mikhael]]
[[it:Arcangelo Michele]]
[[he:מיכאל]]
[[ka:მიქაელ მთავარანგელოზი]]
[[kk:Микаил]]
[[sw:Malaika Mikaeli]]
[[ku:Mikaîl]]
[[lv:Miķelis]]
[[lt:Arkangelas Mykolas]]
[[lmo:San Michee (sant)]]
[[hu:Mihály arkangyal]]
[[mk:Архангел Михаил]]
[[ml:മിഖായേൽ മാലാഖ]]
[[mt:Arkanġlu Mikiel]]
[[ms:Mikail]]
[[nah:Migueltzin Huēyangel]]
[[nl:Michaël (aartsengel)]]
[[ja:ミカエル]]
[[no:Erkeengelen Mikael]]
[[nn:Erkeengelen Mikael]]
[[nrm:Saint Miché]]
[[pl:Archanioł Michał]]
[[pt:Miguel (arcanjo)]]
[[ksh:Michael (Erzengel)]]
[[ro:Arhanghelul Mihail]]
[[ru:Архангел Михаил]]
[[sq:Mihael (kryengjël)]]
[[scn:San Micheli Arcancilu]]
[[sk:Michal (anjel)]]
[[sl:Sveti Mihael]]
[[sr:Архангел Михаил]]
[[sh:Mihael (arhanđeo)]]
[[fi:Mikael (arkkienkeli)]]
[[sv:Mikael (ärkeängel)]]
[[te:మీకాయీల్]]
[[th:อัครทูตสวรรค์มีคาเอล]]
[[chr:ᎹᎩ]]
[[tr:Mikâil]]
[[uk:Архангел Михаїл]]
[[ur:میکائیل]]
[[vec:San Michièl Arcànxoło]]
[[zh:米迦勒]]</text>
      <sha1>94a2c831yism2htxgzeo3plf9u48q9v</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
