<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Minor orders</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>495267</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519735110</id>
      <parentid>519730184</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T10:29:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Esoglou</username>
        <id>11289927</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Eastern Christianity */ copyedit</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11234">'''Minor orders''' are ranks of [[Minister (Christianity)|church ministry]] lower than [[major orders]].&lt;ref name=ConciseODCC&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1O95-MinorOrders.html The Concise Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CE&gt;[http://oce.catholic.com/index.php?title=Minor_Orders Auguste Boudinhon, &quot;Minor Orders&quot; in ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' 1911]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Roman Catholic Church]] in its [[Latin Rite]] traditionally distinguished between the major orders (holy orders) of [[bishop]], [[priesthood (Catholic Church)|priest]], [[deacon]] and [[subdeacon]], and four minor orders, that of [[acolyte]], [[exorcist]], [[Reader (liturgy)|lector]] and [[porter (doorkeeper)|porter]] (in descending sequence).&lt;ref name=ConciseODCC/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?q=1829+catechism+council+trent+%22greater+or+holy+orders%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books&amp;tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1 Catechism of the Council of Trent (Dublin 1829), p. 310]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1972, the minor orders were renamed &quot;ministries&quot;, with those of lector and acolyte being kept throughout the Latin Church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/motu_proprio/documents/hf_p-vi_motu-proprio_19720815_ministeria-quaedam_lt.html ''Ministeria quaedam''], II: &quot;The orders hitherto called minor are henceforth to be spoken of as 'ministries'.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; All four minor orders are still conferred on members of some Roman Catholic [[religious institute]]s and [[society of apostolic life|societies of apostolic life]] authorized to observe the [[Tridentine Mass|1962 form of the Roman Rite]].

In the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], the three minor orders in use are those of subdeacon, [[cantor (church)|cantor]] and  lector.&lt;ref name=ConciseODCC/&gt;

==Roman Catholic Church==

From the beginning of the 3rd century there is evidence in [[Western Christianity]] of the existence of what became the four minor orders (acolytes, exorcists, doorkeepers and readers), as well as of cantors and ''fossores'' (tomb diggers). The evidence for readers is probably the earliest. In the West, unlike the East, where imposition of hands was used, the rite of ordination was by the handing over to them of objects seen as instruments of the office.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?q=Villien+%22fossores+etc%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books&amp;tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1 A. Villien, H.W. Edwards, ''History and Liturgy of the Sacraments'', pp. 237ff.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Council of Sardica]] (343) mentions the lectorate alone as obligatory before ordination to the diaconate. The obligation to receive all four minor orders appears to date only from a time when they ceased to indicate exercise of an actual function. Even in the early years of the 20th century, no minimum age, other than that of [[age of reason (canon law)|that of the use of reason]], was laid down for receiving minor orders.&lt;ref name=CE/&gt; However, the 1917 [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Code of Canon Law]] laid down that nobody was to be given [[cleric]]al [[tonsure]], which had to be received before minor orders, before beginning the regular course of theological studies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/LAT0813/_P36.HTM Canon 976 of the 1917 Code of Canon Law]&lt;/ref&gt; Before the entry into force of that Code, it was an almost universal custom to confer all four minor orders at one time, since the bishop was authorized to dispense from the rule that each order had to be exercised for some time before reception of the next highest order.&lt;ref name=CE/&gt; Today, as indicated in the 1983 Code of Canon Law, anyone who is to be ordained to the diaconate must already have received the ministries of lector and acolyte and exercised them for a suitable period, with an interval of at least six months between becoming an acolyte and becoming a deacon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P3R.HTM Code of Canon Law, canon 1035]&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1917 Code of Canon Law also restricted conferral of tonsure and any order below that of the presbyterate to those who intended to become priests and who were judged likely to be worthy priests.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/LAT0813/_P36.HTM Canon 973 of the 1917 Code of Canon Law]&lt;/ref&gt; Previously, there were [[lay cardinal]]s and others, including the famous [[Franz Liszt]], who received minor orders alone. They could even marry and remain clerics, the status of belonging to the clergy being at that time conferred through clerical tonsure, provided that they married only once and that to a virgin; but by the early 20th century a cleric who married was considered to have forfeited his clerical status.&lt;ref name=CE/&gt; Today, a man who receives what were previously called minor orders is not yet a cleric, since today one becomes a cleric only upon ordination to the diaconate,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__PX.HTM Code of Canon Law, canon 266]&lt;/ref&gt; a rule that applies even to members of institutes authorized to observe the 1962 form of the Roman Rite,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_commissions/ecclsdei/documents/rc_com_ecclsdei_doc_20110430_istr-universae-ecclesiae_en.html Instruction on the Application of the Apostolic Letter ''Summorum Pontificum''], 30&lt;/ref&gt; such as the [[Priestly Fraternity of St. Peter]] and others under the care of the [[Pontifical Commission Ecclesia Dei]].

In the early 20th century, Auguste Boudinhon said that, on the grounds that minor orders did not originate with Jesus or the apostles, the view that minor orders and the subdiaconate were [[sacrament]]al, a view held by several [[Middle Ages|medieval]] theologians, was no longer held.&lt;ref name=CE/&gt; The slightly earlier G. van Noort said that the view of their sacramentality, which was held by most [[scholasticism|scholastic]] theologians, including [[Thomas Aquinas]], was then held only by a few, among whom he mentioned [[Louis Billot]] (1846-1931) and Adolphe Tanquerey (1854-1932).&lt;ref&gt;G. van Noort (revised by J.P. Verhaar), ''Tractatus de sacramentis'' (Paul Brand, Bussum, Netherlands 1930), vol. II, pp. 145-146&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1950s, Antonio Piolanti recognized as orders only episcopacy, priesthood (presbyterate) and diaconate,&lt;ref&gt;Antonius Piolanti, ''De Sacramentis'' (fifth edition, Marietti 1955), pp. 461-463&lt;/ref&gt; the three whose transmission is reserved to bishops.&lt;ref&gt;Piolanti 1955, pp. 463-468&lt;/ref&gt; In speaking of the hierarchical structure of the Church, the [[Second Vatican Council]] mentioned only these three orders, not minor orders or subdiaconate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19641121_lumen-gentium_en.html Dogmatic Constitution on the Church ''Lumen gentium'']&lt;/ref&gt;

By [[Pope Paul VI]]'s [[motu proprio]] ''Ministeria quaedam'' of 15 August 1972, the term &quot;minor orders&quot; has been replaced by that of &quot;ministries&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/paul_vi/motu_proprio/documents/hf_p-vi_motu-proprio_19720815_ministeria-quaedam_lt.html ''Ministeria quaedam'', II]&lt;/ref&gt; Two of what were called minor orders, those of reader and acolyte, are kept throughout the [[Latin Church]], and national [[episcopal conference]]s are free to use the term &quot;subdeacon&quot; in place of that of &quot;acolyte&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Ministeria quaedam'', IV&lt;/ref&gt; The motu proprio specified the functions of each of these two ministries,&lt;ref&gt;''Ministeria quaedam'', IV-VI&lt;/ref&gt; A prescribed interval, as decided by the Holy See and the national episcopal conference, is to be observed between receiving them.&lt;ref&gt;''Ministeria quaedam'', X&lt;/ref&gt; Candidates for diaconate and for priesthood must receive both ministries and exercise them for some time before receiving holy orders.&lt;ref&gt;''Ministeria quaedam'', XI&lt;/ref&gt; 

Conferral of the minor orders or ministries is by the [[Ordinary (officer)|ordinary]]: either a diocesan [[bishop (Catholic Church)|bishop]] or someone who is [[Catholic Church hierarchy#Equivalents of diocesan bishops in law|equivalent in law to a diocesan bishop]] or, in the case of clerical religious institutes and societies of apostolic life, a major superior.&lt;ref&gt;''Ministeria quaedam'', IX&lt;/ref&gt; The two ministries that are in use throughout the Latin Church could be conferred even on men&lt;ref&gt;''Ministeria quaedam'', VII&lt;/ref&gt; who are not candidates for holy orders.&lt;ref&gt;''Ministeria quaedam'', III&lt;/ref&gt;

==Eastern Christianity==
Eastern Christianity traditionally views the subdeacon as a minor order,&lt;ref&gt;Faulk, Edward. ''101 Questions &amp; Answers on Eastern Catholic Churches''. New York: Paulist Press, 2007, p. 51&lt;/ref&gt; unlike the practice of the West which considered it a major order.  The other common minor order is lector (reader). The minor order of porter is mentioned historically in some service-books, but no longer is given; all of the rights and responsibilities of each minor order are viewed as contained in the subdiaconate.&lt;ref name=&quot;CE&quot;/&gt;

The 22 ''[[sui iuris]]'' [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Churches]] that are in union with Rome have their traditional minor orders, governed by their own particular law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_P93.HTM#D ''CCEO, Title X, Canon 327''], 1992. Retrieved 2008-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; In all Eastern Catholic Churches, subdeacons are minor clerics, since admission to major orders is by ordination as [[deacon]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_PFK.HTM#1O CCEO, Title 12, Canon 560] and [http://www.intratext.com/IXT/ENG1199/_PFP.HTM#H Canon 565], 1992. Retrieved 2008-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; The Byzantine tradition allows for several orders of minor clerics. The ''sui iuris'' Byzantine Catholic Metropolitan Church of Pittsburgh, also called the Byzantine-Ruthenian Church, has the minor orders of [[acolyte|candle bearer]], [[cantor (church)|cantor]], lector and subdeacon, and in English uses the term &quot;ordination&quot; for their cheirothesis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.byzcath.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=334 Particular Law for the Byzantine-Ruthenian Church in the USA] (29 June 1999).  Retrieved 2008-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt; The minor orders of candle bearer and cantor are given before [[tonsure]] during ordination to the lectorate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eparchy-of-van-nuys.org/docs/newsletter_9810.html#ORDINATIONS Eparchial Newsletter] 
(October–November 1998) ''eparchy-of-van-nuys.org'' Accessed 2007-11-28&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastern Orthodox Churches routinely confer the minor orders of lector and subdeacon, and some jurisdictions also ordain cantors. Ordination to minor orders is done by a bishop at any public worship service, but always outside the context of the Divine Liturgy.&lt;ref name=&quot;SLOC&quot;&gt;''The Sacramental Life of the Orthodox Church'', Calivas (2005) [http://www.goarch.org/en/ourfaith/articles/article7106.asp ''Minor orders'']&lt;/ref&gt; The order of taper-bearer is now used as part of ordination as a lector. The orders of doorkeepers, exorcists, and acolytes are no longer in common use.&lt;ref&gt;''Orthodox Wiki, Minor Orders'', N.D. [http://orthodoxwiki.org/Minor_orders] Retrieved 2008-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Holy Orders]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

[[Category:Minor orders| ]]

[[de:Niedere Weihe]]
[[es:Órdenes menores]]
[[fr:Ordres mineurs]]
[[is:Vígslustig klerka]]
[[it:Ordini minori]]
[[nl:Lagere en hogere wijdingen]]
[[pl:Święcenia niższe]]
[[ru:Малые чины]]</text>
      <sha1>cul8rnw6t2b8j7fkn1i3fsy1m7g3zrs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
