<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Miracle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>52041</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519608605</id>
      <parentid>519608400</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T17:59:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>James086</username>
        <id>1482496</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/75.145.254.34|75.145.254.34]] ([[User talk:75.145.254.34|talk]]): Assuming good faith reversion. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36909">{{Other uses}}
{{POV-check|date=July 2012}}
[[File:Folio 171r - The Raising of Lazarus.jpg|thumb|250px|''The [[Raising of Lazarus]]'', (c. 1410) from the ''[[Très Riches Heures du Duc de Berry]]'', [[Musée Condé]], France.]]
A '''miracle''' is an event attributed to [[God|divine]] intervention. Alternatively, it may be an event attributed to a [[Thaumaturgy|miracle worker]], [[saint]], or religious leader. A miracle is sometimes thought of as a perceptible interruption of the laws of nature. Others suggest that  God may work ''with'' the laws of nature to perform what people see as miracles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sproule 1992 65–66&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Sproule
  | first = R C
  | title = Essential Truths of the Christian Faith
  | publisher = Tyndale
  | year = 1992
  | location =
  | pages = 65–66
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =0-8423-2001-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Theologian]]s say that, with [[divine providence]], God regularly works through created nature yet is free to work without, above, or against it as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;McLaughlin&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
  | last = McLaughlin
  | first = R
  | title = Do Miracles Happen Today?
  | work = IIIM Online
  | publisher = Reformed Perspectives Magazine
  | date = May 2002
  | url =http://www.thirdmill.org/newfiles/ra_mclaughlin/TH.Mclaughlin.miracles.html
  | doi =
  | accessdate =2 February 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In casual usage, &quot;miracle&quot; is seen as any event that is statistically unlikely but beneficial, (such as surviving a natural disaster), or simply a &quot;wonderful&quot; occurrence, regardless of likelihood, such as a birth. Other miracles might be: survival of a terminal illness, escaping a life threatening situation or 'beating the odds'. Some [[coincidence]]s may be seen as miracles.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Halbersam
  | first = Yitta
  | title = Small Miracles
  | publisher = Adams Media Corp
  | year = 1997
  | location =
  | pages =
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | isbn =1-55850-646-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The rapid German recovery after the [[Second World War]] was sometimes called the [[German Miracle]].

The word is often used to give an impression of great and unusual value in a trivial context: [[Miracle Whip]], a commercial food product; [[Fort Myers Miracle]], a sports team.

This article deals with miracles as supernatural, not the other usages described.

==Explanations for miracles==
A miracle is sometimes thought of as a perceptible interruption of the laws of nature. Others suggest that  [[God in Abrahamic religions|God]] may work ''with'' the laws of nature to perform what people see as miracles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sproule 1992 65–66&quot;/&gt; Some [[theologian]]s say that, with [[divine providence]], God regularly works through created nature yet is free to work without, above, or against it as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;McLaughlin&quot;/&gt;

===Supernatural acts===
A miracle is a phenomenon not fully explained by known [[laws of nature]], or an act by some [[supernatural]] entity or unknown, outside force. Some scientist-theologians suggest that miracles are not violations of the laws of nature but &quot;exploration of a new regime of physical experience&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}

Criteria for classifying an event as a miracle vary. Often a [[religious text]], such as the [[Bible]] or [[Quran]], states that a miracle occurred, and believers accept this as a fact. Many conservative religious believers hold that in the absence of a plausible, parsimonious scientific theory, the best explanation for these events is that they were performed by a supernatural being, and cite this as evidence for the existence of a god or gods. Some adherents of [[monotheistic religion]]s assert that miracles, if established, are [[evidence]] for the existence of an [[Omnipotence|omnipotent]], [[Omniscience|omniscient]], and benevolent God.

===Events planned by God===
In rabbinic [[Judaism]], many [[rabbi]]s mentioned in the [[Talmud]] held that the laws of nature were inviolable. The idea of miracles that contravened the laws of nature were hard to accept; however, at the same time they affirmed the truth of the accounts in the [[Tanakh]]. Therefore some explained that miracles were in fact natural events that had been set up by God at the beginning of time.

In this view, when the walls of [[Jericho]] fell, it was not because God directly brought them down. Rather, God planned that there would be an [[earthquake]] (or some such other natural disaster) at that place and time, so that the city would fall to the Israelites. Instances where rabbinic writings say that God made miracles a part of [[creation myth|creation]] include [[Midrash]] ''Genesis Rabbah'' 5:45; Midrash ''Exodus Rabbah'' 21:6; and [[Talmud|Ethics of the Fathers/Pirkei Avot 5:6.]]

===Nonliteral interpretations of biblical accounts===
[[Biblical literalism]] is not rigidly believed by all scholars: Non-literal interpretations of some scripture are held by both classical and modern thinkers.  This may include the use of [[figure of speech]], [[allegory]], and [[exegesis]].

In [[Book of Numbers|Numbers]] 22 is the story of [[Balaam]] and the talking [[donkey]]. Many hold that for miracles such as this, one must either assert the literal truth of this [[Old Testament|biblical story]], or one must then reject the story as false. However, some Jewish commentators (e.g. [[Saadiah Gaon]] and [[Maimonides]]) hold that stories such as these were never meant to be taken literally in the first place. Rather, these stories should be understood as accounts of a [[prophet]]ic experience, which are [[dream]]s or [[vision (religion)|visions]]. (Of course, such dreams and visions could themselves be considered miracles.)

[[Joseph H. Hertz]], a 20th century [[Meforshim|Jewish biblical commentator]], writes that these verses &quot;depict the continuance on the subconscious plane of the mental and moral conflict in Balaam's soul; and the dream apparition and the speaking donkey is but a further warning to Balaam against being misled through avarice to violate God's command.&quot;

==Religious texts==

===Hebrew Bible===
Descriptions of miracles (Hebrew ''Ness, נס'') appear in the [[Tanakh]]. Examples include prophets, such as [[Elijah]] who performed miracles like the raising of a widow's dead son (1 Kings 17:17–24) and [[Elisha]] whose miracles include multiplying the poor widow's jar of oil (2 Kings 4:1–7) and restoring to life the son of the woman of Shunem (2 Kings 4:18–37).

===New Testament===

The gospels record three sorts of miracles performed by Jesus: exorcisms, cures, and nature wonders.&lt;ref name = &quot;ActJIntro&quot;&gt;[[Robert W. Funk|Funk, Robert W.]] and the [[Jesus Seminar]]. ''The acts of Jesus: the search for the authentic deeds of Jesus.'' HarperSanFrancisco. 1998. Introduction, p. 1–40&lt;/ref&gt; In [[John the Evangelist|St John]]'s [[Gospel of John|Gospel]] the miracles are referred to as &quot;signs&quot; and the emphasis is on God demonstrating his underlying normal activity in remarkable ways.&lt;ref&gt;see e.g. [[John Polkinghorne|Polkinghorne]] op cit. and a commentary on the Gospel of John, such as [[William Temple (archbishop)|William Temple]]'s ''Readings in St John's Gospel'' (see e.g. p. 33) or [[Tom Wright (theologian)|Tom Wright]]'s ''John for Everyone''&lt;/ref&gt; In the New Testament, the greatest miracle is the [[resurrection of Jesus]], the event central to Christian faith.

Jesus explains in the [[New Testament]] that miracles are performed by [[faith]] in God.  &quot;If you have faith as small as a mustard seed, you can say to this mountain, 'move from here to there' and it will move.&quot; ([[Gospel of Matthew]] 17:20). After Jesus returned to heaven, the book of Acts records the disciples of Jesus praying to God to grant that miracles be done in his name, for the purpose of convincing onlookers that he is alive. ([[Acts of the Apostles|Acts]] 4:29–31).

Other passages mention [[false prophet]]s who will be able to perform miracles to deceive &quot;if possible, even the elect of Christ&quot; (Matthew 24:24). 2 Thessalonians 2:9 says, &quot;And then shall that Wicked be revealed, whom the Lord shall consume with the spirit of His mouth, and shall destroy with the brightness of His coming: Even him, whose coming is after the working of Satan with all power and signs and lying wonders, and with all deceivableness of unrighteousness in them that perish; because they received not the love of the Truth, that they might be saved.&quot; Revelation 13:13,14 says, &quot;And he doeth great wonders, so that he maketh fire come down from heaven on the earth in the sight of men, and deceiveth them that dwell on the earth by the means of those miracles which he had power to do in the sight of the beast; saying to them that dwell on the earth, that they sould make an image to the beast, which had the wound by a sword, and did live.&quot; Revelation 16:14 says, &quot;For they are the spirits of devils, working miracles, which go forth unto the kings of the earth and of the whole world, to gather them to the battle of that great day of God Almighty.&quot; Revelation 19:20says, &quot;And the beast was taken, and with him the false prophet that wrought miracles before him, with which he deceived them that had received the mark of the beast, and them that worshipped his image. These both were cast alive into a lake of fire burning with brimstone.&quot; These passages indicate that signs, wonders, and miracles are not necessarily committed by God.

===Qur'an===
[[File:Miraj by Sultan Muhammad.jpg|thumb|upright|A 16th century [[Persian miniature painting]] celebrating Muhammad's ascent into the Heavens, a journey known as the [[Isra and Mi'raj|Miraj]]. Muhammad's face is veiled, a common practice in [[Islamic art]].]]
{{Main|Islamic view of miracles|Miracles of Muhammad}}
{{See also|Occasionalism}}

Miracle in the [[Qur'an]] can be defined as a supernatural intervention in the life of human beings.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQ-Miracle&quot;&gt;Denis Gril, ''Miracles'', [[Encyclopedia of the Qur'an]]&lt;/ref&gt; According to this definition, Miracles are present &quot;in a threefold sense: in sacred [[history]], in connection with [[Muhammad]] himself and in relation to revelation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQ-Miracle&quot;/&gt; The Qur'an does not use the technical [[Arabic]] word for miracle (''Muʿd̲j̲iza'') literally meaning &quot;that by means of which [the Prophet] confounds, overwhelms, his opponents&quot;. It rather uses the term 'Ayah' (literally meaning sign).&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI-Miracle&quot;&gt;A.J. Wensinck, ''Muʿd̲j̲iza'', [[Encyclopaedia of Islam|Encyclopedia of Islam]]&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''Ayah'' is used in the Qur'an in the above mentioned threefold sense: it refers to the &quot;verses&quot; of the Qur'an (believed to be the divine speech in [[Natural language|human language]]; presented by [[Muhammad]] as his chief Miracle); as well as to miracles of it and the signs (particularly those of creation).&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQ-Miracle&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI-Miracle&quot;/&gt;

To defend the possibility of miracles and God's omnipotence against the encroachment of the independent secondary causes, some medieval [[Islamic theology|Muslim theologians]] such as [[Al-Ghazali]] rejected the idea of [[Causality|cause and effect]] in essence, but accepted it as something that facilitates humankind's investigation and comprehension of natural processes. They argued that the nature was composed of uniform atoms that were &quot;re-created&quot; at every instant by God. Thus if the soil was to fall, God would have to create and re-create the accident of heaviness for as long as the soil was to fall. For Muslim theologians, the laws of nature were only the customary sequence of apparent causes: customs of God.&lt;ref&gt;Robert G. Mourison, The Portrayal of Nature in a Medieval Qur’an Commentary, Studia Islamica, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

==Claims of miracles==

===Religious groups===

====Buddhism====
The ''Haedong Kosung-jon'' of Korea (Biographies of High Monks) records that King [[Beopheung of Silla]] had desired to promulgate Buddhism as the state religion. However, officials in his court opposed him. In the fourteenth year of his reign, Beopheung's &quot;Grand Secretary&quot;, [[Ichadon]], devised a strategy to overcome court opposition. Ichadon schemed with the king, convincing him to make a proclamation granting Buddhism official state sanction using the royal seal. Ichadon told the king to deny having made such a proclamation when the opposing officials received it and demanded an explanation. Instead, Ichadon would confess and accept the punishment of execution, for what would quickly be seen as a forgery. Ichadon prophesied to the king that at his execution a wonderful miracle would convince the opposing court faction of Buddhism's power. Ichadon's scheme went as planned, and the opposing officials took the bait. When Ichadon was executed on the 15th day of the 9th month in 527, his prophecy was fulfilled; the earth shook, the sun was darkened, beautiful flowers rained from the sky, his severed head flew to the sacred Geumgang mountains, and milk instead of blood sprayed 100 feet in the air from his beheaded corpse. The omen was accepted by the opposing court officials as a manifestation of heaven's approval, and Buddhism was made the state religion in 527 CE.&lt;ref&gt;Korea: a religious history, James Huntley Grayson, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Honchō Hokke Reigenki'' (c. 1040) of Japan contains a collection of Buddhist miracle stories.&lt;ref&gt;Keene, Donald. ''Twenty Plays of the Nō Theater.'' Columbia University Press, New York, 1970. Page 238.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Christianity====
{{Main|Miracles of Jesus}}
[[C.S. Lewis]], [[Norman Geisler]], [[William Lane Craig]], and other Christians have argued that miracles are reasonable and plausible. For example, Lewis said that a miracle is something that comes totally out of the blue. If for thousands of years a woman can become pregnant only by sexual intercourse with a man, then if she were to become pregnant without a man, it would be a miracle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =Are Miracles Logically Impossible?| publisher =Come Reason Ministries, Convincing Christianity| url =http://www.comereason.org/phil_qstn/phi060.asp| accessdate =2007-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =&quot;Miracles are not possible,&quot; some claim. Is this true?| publisher =ChristianAnswers.net| url =http://www.christiananswers.net/q-eden/edn-t011.html| accessdate =2007-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title =A Jurisprudential Analysis Of Hume’s &quot;in Principal&quot; Argument Against Miracles| author =Paul K. Hoffman| publisher =Christian Apologetics Journal, Volume 2, No. 1, Spring, 1999; Copyright ©1999 by Southern Evangelical Seminary| url =http://www.ses.edu/journal/articles/2.1Hoffman.pdf|format=PDF| accessdate =2007-11-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071026160950/http://www.ses.edu/journal/articles/2.1Hoffman.pdf |archivedate = October 26, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been numerous claims of miracles by people of most Christian denominations, including but not limited to [[faith healing]]s and [[exorcism|casting out demon]]s. Miracle reports are especially prevalent in [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]] and [[Pentecostalism|Pentecostal]] or [[Charismatic Movement|Charismatic]] churches.

=====Catholic Church=====
{{See also|Marian apparition|Stigmata|Incorruptibility}}
The [[Catholic Church]] recognizes miracles as being works of [[God]], either directly, or through the prayers and [[intercession of saints|intercessions]] of a specific [[saint]] or saints. There is usually a specific purpose connected to a miracle, e.g. the conversion of a person or persons to the Catholic faith or the construction of a church desired by God. The Church says that it tries to be very cautious to approve the validity of putative miracles. The Catholic Church says that it maintains particularly stringent requirements in validating the miracle's authenticity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://jcgi.pathfinder.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,982807,00.html Pathfinder.com]&lt;/ref&gt; The process is overseen by the [[Congregation for the Causes of Saints]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.30giorni.it/us/articolo.asp?id=3664 30giorni.it] {{it icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Catholic Church has recognised several events as miracles, some of them occurring in modern times. Before a person can be accepted as a saint, they must be confirmed as having performed two miracles posthumously. In the procedure of [[Beatification and canonisation of Pope John Paul II|beatification of Pope John Paul II]], who died in 2005, the Vatican announced on 14 January 2011 that [[Pope Benedict XVI]] had confirmed that  the recovery of Sister Marie Simon-Pierre from [[Parkinson's disease]] was a miracle.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC-beatify&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-12191423|title=Pope Benedict Paves Way to Beatification of John Paul II|work=bbc.news.co.uk|accessdate=14 January 2011|date=14 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Catholic Church, confirmed miracles have withstood the test of modern [[Scientific method|scientific scrutiny]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}} Among the more notable miracles approved by the Church are several [[Eucharistic miracle]]s wherein the [[sacramental bread]] and wine are [[transubstantiation|transformed into Christ's flesh and blood]], such as the [[Miracle of Lanciano]].

According to 17th century documents, a young Spanish [[miracle of Calanda|man's leg was miraculously restored]] to him in 1640 after having been amputated two and a half years earlier.&lt;ref&gt;[[Messori, Vittorio]] (2000): Il miracolo. Indagine sul più sconvolgente prodigio mariano. – Rizzoli: Bur.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another miracle approved by the Church is the [[Miracle of the Sun]], which occurred near [[Our Lady of Fatima|Fátima, Portugal]] on October 13, 1917. Anywhere between 70,000 and 100,000 people, who were gathered at a [[Cova da Iria|cove]] near Fátima, witnessed the sun dim, change colors, spin, dance about in the sky, and appear to plummet to earth, radiating great heat in the process. After the ten-minute event, the ground and the people's clothing, which had been drenched by a previous rainstorm, were both dry.

[[Velankanni]] (Mary) can be traced to the mid-16th century and is attributed to three miracles: the apparition of [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]] and the [[Christ]] Child to a slumbering shepherd boy, the curing of a lame buttermilk vendor, and the rescue of [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] sailors from a violent sea storm.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vailankannishrine.org/miracle.php  Velankanni shrine miracle]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to these, the Catholic Church attributes miraculous causes to many otherwise inexplicable phenomena on a case-by-case basis. Only after all other possible explanations have proven inadequate may the Church assume Divine intervention and declare the miracle worthy of veneration by the faithful. The Church does not, however, enjoin belief in any extra-Scriptural miracle as an [[Articles of Faith|article of faith]] or as necessary for [[salvation]].

[[Thomas Aquinas|St. Thomas Aquinas]], a prominent [[Doctor_of_the_church#Catholicism|Doctor of the Catholic Church]], divided miracles into three types in his ''[[Summa contra Gentiles]]'':&lt;blockquote&gt;These works that are sometimes done by God outside the usual order assigned to things are wont to be called miracles: because we are astonished (''admiramur'') at a thing when we see an effect without knowing the cause. And since at times one and the same cause is known to some and unknown to others, it happens that of several who see an effect, some are astonished and some not: thus an astronomer is not astonished when he sees an eclipse of the sun, for he knows the cause; whereas one who is ignorant of this [[science]] must needs wonder, since he knows not the cause. Wherefore it is wonderful to the latter but not to the former. Accordingly a thing is wonderful simply, when its cause is hidden simply: and this is what we mean by a miracle: something, to wit, that is wonderful in itself and not only in respect of this person or that. Now God is the cause which is hidden to every man simply: for we have proved above that in this state of life no man can comprehend Him by his intellect. Therefore properly speaking miracles are works done by God outside the order usually observed in things.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

Of these miracles there are various degrees and orders. The &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;highest degree&lt;/font&gt; in miracles comprises those works wherein something is done by God, that nature can never do: for instance, that two bodies occupy the same place, that the sun recede or stand still, that the sea be divided and make way to passers by. Among these there is a certain order: for the greater the work done by God, and the further it is removed from the capability of nature, the greater the miracle: thus it is a greater miracle that the sun recede, than that the waters be divided.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

The &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;second degree&lt;/font&gt; in miracles belongs to those whereby God does something that nature can do, but not in the same order: thus it is a work of nature that an animal live, see and walk: but that an animal live after being dead, see after being blind, walk after being lame, this nature cannot do, but God does these things sometimes by a miracle. Among these miracles also, there are degrees, according as the thing done is further removed from the faculty of nature.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

The &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;third degree&lt;/font&gt; of miracles is when God does what is wont to be done by the operation of nature, but without the operation of the natural principles: for instance when by the power of God a man is cured of a fever that nature is able to cure; or when it rains without the operation of the principles of nature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Contra Gentiles, lib. III cap. 101|first=St. Thomas|last=Aquinas|author-link=Thomas Aquinas|url=http://josephkenny.joyeurs.com/CDtexts/ContraGentiles3b.htm#101}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Islam====
[[Sufi]] biographical literature records claims of miraculous accounts of men and women. The miraculous prowess of the Sufi holy men includes ''firasa''([[clairvoyance]]), the ability to disappear from sight, to become completely invisible and practice ''buruz''([[exteriorization]]). The holy men reportedly tame wild beasts and traverse short distances in a very short time span. They could also produce food and rain in seasons of drought, heal the sick and help barren women become pregnant.&lt;ref name=&quot;sufi&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=4nWa8y-HiB0C&amp;pg=PA48 The heirs of the prophet: charisma and religious authority in Shi'ite Islam By Liyakatali Takim]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sufismjournal.org/history/history.html SAINTS AND MIRACLES]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Judaism====
During the first century BCE, a variety of religious movements and splinter groups developed amongst the Jews in [[Iudaea Province|Judea]]. A number of individuals claimed to be miracle workers in the tradition of [[Elijah]] and [[Elisha]], the ancient Jewish prophets. The Talmud provides some examples of such Jewish miracle workers, one of whom is [[Honi HaM'agel]], who was famous for his ability to successfully pray for rain.&lt;ref&gt;Mishnah [[Ta'anit (Talmud)|Ta'anit]] 3:8 [http://www.mechon-mamre.org/b/h/h29.htm Hebrew text at Mechon-Mamre]&lt;/ref&gt;

Most [[Chasidic]] communities are rife with tales of miracles that follow a yechidut, a spiritual audience with a [[tzadik]]: barren women become pregnant, cancer tumors shrink, wayward children become pious.&lt;ref&gt;The encyclopedia of Jewish myth, magic and mysticism, Geoffrey W. Dennis, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidim]] claim that miracles can take place in merit of partaking of the shirayim (the leftovers from the [[rebbe]]'s meal), such as miraculous healing or blessings of wealth or piety.

===Individuals===
Individuals who are claimed to have performed miracles include:
{{multicol}}
* [[Aharon Rokeach]]
* [[Akhtar Raza]]
* [[Apollonius of Tyana]]
* [[Arunagirinathar]]
* [[Asenath Barzani]]
* [[Audrey Marie Santo]]
* [[Baal Shem of London]]
* [[Baal Shem Tov]]
* [[Baba Sali]]
* [[Buddha]]
* [[Chaim Elazar Spira]]
* [[Chaim Zanvl Abramowitz]]
* [[Ephraim Alnaqua]]
* [[Escrava Anastacia]]
* [[Jacob Cochran]]
* [[Jacob Frank]]
* [[Jesus of Nazareth]]
* [[Joseph ben Abraham Gikatilla]]
* [[Maiden of Ludmir]]
* [[Mansur Al-Hallaj]]
* [[Moses Botarel]]
* [[Muhammad]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Nathan Adler]]
* [[Rabbi Meir]]
* [[Raghavendra Swami]]
* [[Ramakrishna]]
* [[Ramalinga Swamigal]]
* [[Ramana Maharshi]]
* [[Rav Jonah]]
* [[Sabbas the Sanctified]]
* [[Sabbatai Zevi]]
* [[Sai Baba of Shirdi]]
* [[Sathya Sai Baba]]
* [[Sarkar Waris Pak]]
* [[Shalom Sharabi]]
* [[Shmelke of Nikolsburg]]
* [[Shimon bar Yochai]]
* [[Swami Vivekananda]]
* [[Vespasian]]
* [[Yeshayah Steiner]]
* [[Yissachar Dov Rokeach (I)]]
* [[Yitzchak Kaduri]]
* [[Yosef Yozel Horwitz]]
* [[Sree Narayana Guru]]
{{multicol-end}}

==Criticism==
[[Thomas Paine]], one of the Founding Fathers of the American Revolution, wrote “All the tales of miracles, with which the Old and New Testament are filled, are fit only for impostors to preach and fools to believe”.&lt;ref&gt;The Writings of Thomas Paine, Volume 4, page 289, Putnam &amp; Sons, 1896&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Thomas Jefferson]], principal author of the Declaration of Independence of the United States, edited a version of the Bible in which he removed sections of the New Testament containing supernatural aspects as well as perceived misinterpretations he believed had been added by the Four Evangelists.&lt;ref&gt;Jeremy Kosselak (November 1998). The Exaltation of a Reasonable Deity: Thomas Jefferson’s Bible of Christianity. (Communicated by: Dr. Patrick Furlong). Indiana University South Bend – Department of History. [http://www.iusb.edu/~journal/1999/Paper9.html IUSB.edu], Retrieved 2007-02-19&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;R.P. Nettelhorst. Notes on the Founding Fathers and the Separation of Church and State. Quartz Hill School of Theology. [http://www.theology.edu/journal/volume2/ushistor.htm Theology.edu] Retrieved 2007-02-20.&lt;/ref&gt; Jefferson wrote, &quot;The establishment of the innocent and genuine character of this benevolent moralist, and the rescuing it from the imputation of imposture, which has resulted from artificial systems, [footnote: e.g. The immaculate conception of Jesus, his deification, the creation of the world by him, his miraculous powers, his resurrection and visible ascension, his corporeal presence in the Eucharist, the Trinity; original sin, atonement, regeneration, election, orders of Hierarchy, etc. —T.J.] invented by ultra-Christian sects, unauthorized by a single word ever uttered by him, is a most desirable object, and one to which Priestley has successfully devoted his labors and learning.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Letter to William Short (31 October 1819), published in &quot;The Works of Thomas Jefferson in Twelve Volumes&quot;, Federal Edition, Paul Leicester Ford, ed., New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1904, Vol. 12, pp. 141–142.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Robert G. Ingersoll|Robert Ingersoll]] wrote, &quot;Not 20 people were convinced by the reported miracles of Christ, and yet people of the nineteenth century were coolly asked to be convinced on hearsay by miracles which those who are supposed to have seen them refused to credit.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[New York Times]], p. 8, April 24, 1882&lt;/ref&gt;

Writer [[Christopher Hitchens]], when asked for his favorite Bible story replied “Casting the first stone” is a lovely story, even though we’ve found out how much it wasn’t in the Bible to begin with. And the first of the miracles. Jesus changes water into wine. You can’t object to that.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[New York Magazine]], April 26, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Biologist and atheist [[Richard Dawkins]] criticises the belief in miracles as a subversion of [[Occam's Razor]].&lt;ref&gt;''[[The God Delusion]]''&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[John Adams]], second President of the United States, wrote, &quot;The question before the human race is, whether the God of nature shall govern the world by his own laws, or whether priests and kings shall rule it by fictitious miracles?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John Adams, letter to Thomas Jefferson, June 20, 1815&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Elbert Hubbard]], American writer, publisher, artist, and philosopher, wrote &quot;A '''miracle''' is an event described by those to whom it was told by people who did not see it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Elbert Hubbard, The Philistine (1909)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[American Revolutionary War]] patriot and hero [[Ethan Allen]] wrote &quot;In those parts of the world where learning and science have prevailed, '''miracles''' have ceased; but in those parts of it as are barbarous and ignorant, '''miracles''' are still in vogue.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ethan Allen, Reason, the Only Oracle of Man, 1784&lt;/ref&gt;

===Philosophers' explanations===

====Aristotelian and Neo-Aristotelian====
The [[Aristotelian view of God]] does not include direct intervention in the order of the natural world. [[Jew]]ish neo-[[Aristotelianism|Aristotelian]] [[philosophy|philosophers]], who are still influential today, include [[Maimonides]], [[Samuel ben Judah ibn Tibbon]], and [[Gersonides]]. Directly or indirectly, their views are still prevalent in much of the religious Jewish community. &lt;!-- Christian and Muslim neo-Aristotelian philosophers should also be discussed in this section; also please note if their works are still studied and accepted today, and if so, by whom. --&gt;

====Baruch Spinoza====
In his [[Theologico-Political Treatise]] [[Baruch Spinoza|Spinoza]] claims that miracles are merely lawlike events whose causes we are ignorant of. We should not treat them as having no cause or of having a cause immediately available. Rather the miracle is for combating the ignorance it entails, like a political project. See [[Epistemic theory of miracles]].

====David Hume====
{{Main|Of Miracles}}

According to the philosopher [[David Hume]], a miracle is &quot;a transgression of a law of nature by a particular volition of the Deity, or by the interposition of some invisible agent.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/miracles/ Miracles] on the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/ref&gt; The crux of his argument is this: &quot;No testimony is sufficient to establish a miracle, unless the testimony be of such a kind, that its falsehood would be more miraculous, than the fact which it endeavours to establish.&quot;

====Søren Kierkegaard====
The philosopher [[Søren Kierkegaard]], following Hume and [[Johann Georg Hamann]], a Humean scholar, agrees with Hume's definition of a miracle as a transgression of a law of nature,&lt;ref&gt;[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-4189(195110)31%3A4%3C274%3AHAK%3E2.0.CO%3B2-2 Hume and Kierkegaard] by Richard Popkin&lt;/ref&gt; but Kierkegaard, writing as his pseudonym ''Johannes Climacus'', regards any historical reports to be less than certain, including historical reports of such miracle transgressions, as all historical knowledge is always doubtful and open to approximation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stolaf.edu/collections/kierkegaard/newsletters/Newsletter43.pdf Kierkegaard on Miracles]&lt;/ref&gt;

====James Keller====
[[James Keller]] states that &quot;The claim that God has worked a miracle implies that God has singled out certain persons for some benefit which many others do not receive implies that God is unfair.”&lt;ref&gt;Keller, James. “A Moral Argument against Miracles,” Faith and Philosophy. vol. 12, no 1. Jan 1995. 54–78&lt;/ref&gt; An example would be &quot;If God intervenes to save your life in a car crash, then what was he doing in [[Auschwitz concentration camp|Auschwitz]]?&quot;. Thus an all-powerful, all-knowing and just God, predicated in Christianity, would not perform miracles.

====Littlewood====
{{main|Littlewood's law}}
British mathematician [[J. E. Littlewood]] suggested that individuals should statistically expect one-in-a-million events (&quot;miracles&quot;) to happen to them at the rate of about one per month. By Littlewood's  definition, seemingly miraculous events are actually commonplace.

==See also==
*[[A Course in Miracles]]
*[[Act of God]]
*[[Cessationism]]
*[[Existence of God]]
*[[Lourdes effect]]
*[[Magic and religion]]
*[[Međugorje]]
*[[Miracles at Lourdes]]
*[[Miracles (book)]]
*[[Paranormal]]
*[[Pieter De Rudder]]
*[[Scientific skepticism]]
*[[Signs and wonders]]
*[[Snake handling]]
*[[Snake oil]]
*[[Spontaneous remission]] (&quot;medical miracles&quot;)
*[[Weeping statue]]

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|2}}
{{refbegin|2}}

===General references and books===

* Colin Brown. ''Miracles and the Critical Mind''. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1984. (Good survey).
* Colin J. Humphreys, ''Miracles of Exodus''. Harper, San Francisco, 2003.
* Chavda, Mahesh, ''Only Love Can Make a Miracle''. Charlotte: Mahesh Chavda Ministries, 1990.
* Krista Bontrager, &quot;It’s a Miracle! Or, is it?&quot;, [http://www.reasons.org/resources/apologetics/its_a_miracle.shtml?main#_edn8 Reasons.org]
* Eisen, Robert (1995). ''Gersonides on Providence, Covenant, and the Chosen People''. [[State University of New York Press]].
* Goodman, Lenn E. (1985). ''Rambam: Readings in the Philosophy of Moses Maimonides''. Gee Bee Tee.
* Kellner, Menachem (1986). ''Dogma in Medieval Jewish Thought''. [[Oxford University Press]].
* [[C. S. Lewis]]. ''Miracles: A Preliminary Study''. New York, Macmillan Co., 1947.
* [[C. F. D. Moule]] (ed.). ''Miracles: Cambridge Studies in their Philosophy and History''. London, A.R. Mowbray 1966, ©1965 (Good survey of Biblical miracles as well).
* [[Graham Twelftree]]. ''Jesus the Miracle Worker: A Historical and Theological Study''. IVP, 1999. (Best in its field).
* Woodward, Kenneth L. (2000). ''The Book of Miracles''. New York: [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]. ISBN 0-684-82393-4.
* M. Kamp, MD. Bruno Gröning. The miracles continue to happen. 1998, (Chapters 1–4), [http://www.bruno-groening.org/english/mwf/buchauszug/defaultb-auszug.htm Bruno-Groening.org]
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
*[[Harry Houdini|Houdini, Harry]] ''Miracle Mongers and Their Methods: A Complete Expose'' [[Prometheus Books]]; Reprint edition (March 1993) originally published in 1920 ISBN 0-87975-817-1.
* [[Andrew Dickson White]] (1896 first edition. A classic work constantly reprinted) ''A History of the Warfare of Science with Theology in Christendom'', See chapter 13, part 2, ''Growth of Legends of Healing: the life of [[Saint Francis Xavier]] as a typical example''.
* Rory Roybal [http://www.miraclesormagic.com Miracles or Magic?]. Xulon Press, 2005.
*{{Cite book
| last = Graves
| first = Wilfred
| author-link = Wilfred Graves, Jr.
| title = Popular and elite understandings of miracles in enlightened England. A dissertation submitted to the Center for Advanced Theological Studies in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy 
| publisher = Fuller Theological Seminary, School of Theology
| year = 2007
| location = Pasadena, CA
| page = 
| url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=fWP3XxGZAw0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
| isbn = 
}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote|Miracles}}
{{Commons category|Miracles}}
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://www.smajournalonline.com/pt/re/smj/fulltext.00007611-200712000-00016.htm SMAjournalonline.com], the history of thinking about miracles in the West
* [http://www.mukto-mona.com/Articles/yuktibaadi.htm Mukto-mona.com], an Indian Skeptic's explanation of miracles: By Yuktibaadi, compiled by [[Basava Premanand]]
* [http://www.skepdic.com/miracles.html Skepdic.com], skeptic's dictionary on miracles
* Andrew Lang, [http://www.psychanalyse-paris.com/823-Science-and-Miracles.html Psychanalyse-paris.com], &quot;Science and 'Miracles'&quot;, ''The Making of Religion'' Chapter II, Longmans, Green, and Co., London, New York and Bombay, 1900, pp.&amp;nbsp;14–38.
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=Miracle}}
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Miracle}}
* &quot;[http://www.disf.org/en/Voci/86.asp Miracle]&quot; in the Interdisciplinary Encyclopedia of Religion and Science.
* [http://www.cbn.com/media/player/index.aspx?s=/vod/PST15 CBN Video:  Living a Life of Miracles]
* [http://www.cbn.com/media/player/index.aspx?s=/vod/PST45 CBN Video:  Miracles Outside the Church Walls]
* [http://www.ibethel.tv/channel/5/testimonies Personal Accounts of Miracles]
* [http://www.weeklyblitz.net/1058/the-miracle-things The Miracle Things – WeeklyBlitz]

{{philosophy of religion}}
{{Philosophy topics}}
{{Private revelation}}

[[Category:Miracles| ]]

[[ar:معجزة (دين)]]
[[bs:Čudo]]
[[ca:Miracle]]
[[cs:Zázrak]]
[[da:Mirakel]]
[[de:Wunder]]
[[et:Ime]]
[[el:Θαύμα]]
[[es:Milagro]]
[[eo:Miraklo]]
[[eu:Mirari]]
[[fa:معجزه]]
[[fr:Miracle]]
[[gl:Milagre]]
[[ko:기적]]
[[hr:Čudo]]
[[io:Miraklo]]
[[id:Mukjizat]]
[[ia:Miraculo]]
[[is:Kraftaverk]]
[[it:Miracolo]]
[[he:נס]]
[[ka:მირაკლი]]
[[ht:Mirak]]
[[la:Miraculum]]
[[lt:Stebuklas]]
[[hu:Csoda]]
[[nl:Wonder]]
[[ja:奇跡]]
[[no:Mirakel]]
[[nn:Mirakel]]
[[pl:Cud (religia)]]
[[pt:Milagre]]
[[ro:Miracol]]
[[ru:Чудо]]
[[sq:Mrekullia]]
[[simple:Miracle]]
[[sk:Zázrak]]
[[ckb:پەرچوو]]
[[sr:Čudo]]
[[fi:Ihme]]
[[sv:Mirakel]]
[[tl:Himala]]
[[tr:Mucize]]
[[uk:Диво]]
[[yi:נס]]
[[zh:奇跡]]</text>
      <sha1>tg2j5z3iw4dabispaxh5vmu0fyvtk3h</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
