<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mitzvah</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>231394</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522082837</id>
      <parentid>511563304</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T23:09:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sanya3</username>
        <id>4529251</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Commandments]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14877">{{Dablink|This article is about beliefs in Judaism. For the Jewish rite of passage, see [[Bar Mitzvah and Bat Mitzvah]].}}
{{Jews and Judaism sidebar|religion}}
In its primary meaning, the Hebrew word '''''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}''''' (&quot;commandment&quot;, {{lang-he-n|מִצְוָה}}, {{IPA-he|mit͡sˈva|}}, [[Biblical Hebrew|Biblical]]: ''{{transl|he|miṣwah}}''; plural {{Hebrew|מִצְווֹת}} ''{{transl|he|mitzvot}}'' {{IPA-he|mit͡sˈvot|}}, Biblical: ''{{transl|he|miṣwoth}}''; from {{Hebrew|צִוָּה}} ''{{transl|he|ṣiwwah}}'' &quot;command&quot;) refers to precepts and commandments as commanded by God. It is a word used in [[Judaism]] to refer to the [[613 Mitzvot|613 commandments]] given in the [[Torah]] (at [[Mount Sinai]], where all the Jews accepted the Torah, saying &quot;We will do, and we will listen&quot;) and the [[Mitzvah#Rabbinical mitzvot|seven rabbinic commandments]] instituted later for a total of 620. According to the [[Talmud|teachings of Judaism]], all [[Moral code|moral laws]] are, or are derived from, [[Divine law|divine commandments]].

In its secondary meaning, Hebrew ''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}'', as with English &quot;commandment,&quot; refers to a moral deed performed as a religious duty. As such, the term ''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}'' has also come to express an act of human kindness. The tertiary meaning of ''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}'' also refers to the fulfillment of a ''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}''.

The opinions of the [[Talmud]]ic [[rabbi]]s are divided between those who seek the [[Teleology|purpose]] of the ''{{transl|he|mitzvot}}'' and those who do not question them. The latter argue that if the reason for each ''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}'' could be determined, people might try to achieve what they see as the purpose of the ''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}'', without actually performing the mitzvah itself (&quot;Lishma&quot;), which would become self-defeating. The former believe that if people were to understand the reason and the purpose for each ''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}'', it would actually help them to observe and perform the {{transl|he|mitzvah}} (some mitzvot are given reasons in the Torah).

==Hebrew Bible==
The feminine noun ''{{transl|he|mitzvah}}'' ({{Hebrew|מִצְוָה}}) occurs over 180 times in the [[Masoretic Text]] of the [[Hebrew Bible]]. The first use is in [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] 26:5 where God says that [[Abraham]] has &quot;obeyed my voice, and kept  my charge, my commandments ({{Hebrew|מִצְוֹתַי}} ''{{transl|he|mitzvotai}}''), my statutes, and my laws.&quot; In the [[Septuagint]] the word is usually translated with ''entole'' ({{lang|grc|ἐντολὴ}}).&lt;ref&gt;Philip Leroy Culbertson, ''A word fitly spoken'', 1995, p. 73. &quot;See also Lieberman, Texts and Studies, 212, where he shows that the Greek ''entole'' is parallel to ''mitzvah,'' both coming to suggest a particular emphasis on charitable alms.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Second Temple period]] funeral inscriptions the epithet ''phil-entolos'', &quot;lover of the commandments,&quot; was sometimes inscribed on Jewish tombs.&lt;ref&gt;''The Journal of Jewish studies'' Volume 51, 2000 &quot;Note, however, by way of example, the funerary epithet philentolos (lover of the commandments), coined from the stock [[Septuagint|LXX]] word for commandment, ''entole'' (Heb. ''mitzvah''), and the LXX allusions in that most favoured of all Romano-Jewish ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Other words are also used in Hebrew for commands and statutes, for example the [[Ten Commandments]] (עשרת הדיברות) are the &quot;Ten Words&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Rooker, ''The Ten Commandments: Ethics for the Twenty-First Century'', 2010, p. 3. &quot;The Significance of the Ten Commandments in the Old Testament&quot; The Ten Commandments are literally the “Ten Words” (aseret haddebarêm) in Hebrew. The use of the term dabar, “word,” in this phrase distinguishes these laws from the rest of ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rabbinical enumeration==
{{main|613 Mitzvot}}
The [[Tanakh]] does not state that there are 613 commandments. The Rabbis{{Who|date=September 2011}} came to assume{{When|date=September 2011}} that the Law of the Torah comprised 613 commandments. According to Rabbi Simlai, as quoted in the [[Talmud]], [[613 Mitzvot|this enumeration of 613 commandments]] was representative of the following.

{{cquote|365 negative commandments like the number of days in the solar year, and 248 positive commandments corresponding to a person's limbs|author=Talmud, tractate Makkoth, 23b}}

Three of the negative commandments fall under the category of [[self-sacrifice under Jewish Law]], meaning &quot;one should [let himself] be killed rather than transgress the prohibition.&quot;

The number 613 can also be obtained by [[gematria]] (a traditional method of number substitution). The gematria value for the word &quot;Torah&quot; is 611, which corresponds to the number of commandments given via [[Moses]], with the remaining two being identified as the first two of the [[Ten Commandments]], which tradition holds were the only ones given [[revelation|by the Mouth of God Himself]]. (Jews are also reminded of the 613 commandments by the ''[[Tzitzit]]'', known as 'fringes' or 'strings'.{{citation needed|date=September 2011}})

According to [[Rabbi Ishmael]], only the principal commandments of these 613 were given on [[Mount Sinai]], the remainder having been given in the [[Tent of Meeting]]. [[Rabbi Akiba]], on the other hand, was of the opinion that they were all given on Mount Sinai, repeated in the Tent of Meeting, and declared a third time by Moses before his death. According to the [[Midrash]], all divine commandments were given on Mount Sinai, and no prophet could add any new one.&lt;ref&gt;Midrash Sifra to Leviticus 27:34; Talmud, Yoma 80a.&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[rabbinic literature]] there are a number of works, mainly by the [[Rishonim]], that were composed to determine which commandments belong in this enumeration:
* [[Maimonides]]' ''[[Sefer Hamitzvot]]'' (&quot;Book of Commandments&quot;), on which there is a critical commentary by [[Nachmanides]];
* ''[[Sefer ha-Chinuch]]'' (&quot;Book of Education&quot;), attributed to [[Rabbi]] Aaron ha-Levi of Barcelona (the Ra'ah);
* ''Sefer ha-Mitzvoth ha-Gadol'' (&quot;Large book of Commandments&quot;) by Rabbi Moses of Coucy;
* ''Sefer ha-Mitzvoth ha-Katan'' (&quot;Small book of Commandments&quot;) by Rabbi Isaac of Corbeil;
* ''Sefer Yere'im'' (&quot;Book of the [God-]fearing&quot;) by Rabbi Eliezer of Metz (not a clear enumeration);
* ''Sefer Mitzvot HaShem'' (&quot;The book of God's Commandments&quot;) by Rabbi Boruch Bentshar of Sokol;
* ''Sefer ha-Mitzvoth'' by [[Rabbi]] [[Yisrael Meir Kagan]] (the &quot;Chafetz Chaim&quot;) - this work only deals with the commandments that are applicable at the present time.

==Rabbinical mitzvot==
The Biblical mitzvot are referred to in the Talmud as ''[[D'Oraita and D'Rabbanan|Mitzvot d'oraita]]'', translated as ''commandments of the Law (Torah)''. In contradistinction to this are rabbinical commandments, referred to as ''[[D'Oraita and D'Rabbanan|Mitzvot d'rabbanan]]''. Mitzvot d'rabbanan are a type of [[takkanah]]. Among the more important ''mitzvot d'rabbanan'' are:
* To recite [[List of Jewish prayers and blessings|a blessing]] for each enjoyment
* To [[Ritual washing in Judaism|ritually wash]] the hands before eating a meal with bread
* To prepare lights in advance of [[Shabbat]] (one of the reasons is to have peace in the home)
* To construct an [[Eruv]] to permit carrying to and within public areas on [[Shabbat]]
* To recite the [[Hallel]] psalms on holy days
* To light the [[Hanukkah]] [[Chanukkiyah|lights]]
* To read the [[Scroll of Esther]] on [[Purim]]

These seven rabbinical commandments are treated like Biblical commandments insofar as, prior to the performance of each, a [[Berakhah|benediction]] is recited, i.e.:
: &quot;Blessed are You, O {{Lord}} our God, King of the universe, Who has commanded us ...&quot;
They give rise to the phrase &quot;Keter Torah&quot; (&quot;The Crown of the Torah&quot;) as the numeric value of Keter is 620 (613+7).

The divine command is considered implied in the general law to follow any instructions of the religious authorities ([[Deuteronomy]] 17:11, and 32:7; Shab. 23a). In addition, many of the specific details of the Biblical mitzvot are only derived via rabbinical application of the [[Oral Torah]](Mishna/Gemarah); for example, the reading of the Shema (Deuteronomy 6:4-7), the binding of the [[tefillin]] and the fixing of the [[mezuzah]] (Deuteronomy 6:8-9), and the saying of [[Birkat Hamazon|Grace After Meals]] (Deuteronomy 8:10).

==Six constant mitzvot==
Out of the 613 Mitzvot mentioned in the Torah, there are six mitzvot which the [[Sefer Hachinuch]] calls &quot;constant mitzvot&quot;: ''&quot;We have six mitzvot which are perpetual and constant, applicable at all times, all the days of our lives&quot;.''

# To believe in [[Names of God in Judaism|God]], and that he created all things.
# Not to believe in anything else other than God.
# To believe in God's Oneness.
# To fear God.
# To love God.
# Not to pursue the passions of your heart and stray after your eyes.

==Academic treatment==
In modern [[Documentary hypothesis|Biblical scholarship]], six different law codes are considered to compose the body of the Torah's text:
* The [[Ten Commandments]].
* The [[Covenant Code]] follows, and provides more detailed laws.
* The [[Ritual Decalogue]], roughly summarising the Covenant Code, is presented after a brief narrative describing the design for the [[Ark of the Covenant]] and [[Tabernacle]].
* The [[Priestly Code]], containing extensive laws concerning rituals and more general situations is given from above the ''mercy seat'' in the Tabernacle, once the Ark and Tabernacle have been completed. This code is extended further when events occur not quite covered by the law, causing Moses to ask Yahweh for greater clarification.
* The [[Holiness Code]] is contained within the Priestly Code, close to the end, but is a distinct subsection placing particular emphasis on things which are holy, and which should be done to honour the holy. It also contains the warnings from Yahweh about what will occur if the laws are not followed, as well as promises for the event that the laws are followed.
* The [[Deuteronomic Code]] is remembered by Moses, in his last speeches before death, both covering the ground of prior codes, but also further laws not recorded earlier, which Moses has, by this point, &quot;remembered&quot;.

In Biblical criticism, not accepted throughout the Jewish world, these codes are studied separately, particularly concerning the features unique, or first appearing, in each. Many of the mitzvot enumerated as being from one or other of these codes are also present in others, sometimes phrased in a different manner, or with additional clauses. Also, themes, such as idolatry, sexual behaviour, ritual cleanliness, and offerings of sacrifice, are shared among all six codes, and thus, in more religiously motivated [[theology|theological]] studies, it is often the case that the mitzvot are organised instead by theme, rather than the location in which they are found within the Bible.

==The Mitzvot and Jewish law==
{{main|Halakha}}
In rabbinic thought, God's will is the source of, and authority for, every moral and religious duty. In this way, the Mitzvot thus constitute the Divinely instituted ''rules of conduct''. In rabbinic thought, the commandments are usually divided into two major groups, positive commandments (obligations) – ''mitzvot aseh'' [מצות עשה] and negative commandments (prohibitions) – ''mitzvot lo ta'aseh'' [מצות לא תעשה].

The system describing the practical application of the commandments is known as ''[[Halakha]]'', loosely ''Jewish Law''. The Halakha is the development of the Mitzvot as contained in the ''written law'', via discussion and debate in the [[Oral Torah|Oral law]], as recorded in the [[rabbinic literature]] of the classical era, especially the [[Mishnah]] and the [[Talmud]].

The Halakha dictates and influences a wide variety of behavior of [[Orthodox Judaism|traditionalist Jews]].

Many of these laws concern only special classes of people—such as [[Kingdom of Judah|kings]] or [[Kohanim]] (the priesthood), [[Levite]]s, or [[Nazarite]]s -- or are conditioned by local or temporary circumstances of the Jewish nation, as, for instance, the agricultural, sacrificial, and Levitical laws.

The majority view of classical rabbis was that the commandments will still be applicable and in force during the [[Messianic Age]]. However, a significant minority of rabbis held that most of the commandments will be nullified by, or in, the messianic era. Examples of such rabbinic views include:
* That the grain-offering of Judah and Jerusalem will be pleasing to God as in the days of old, and as in ancient years. ([[Book of Malachi|Malachi]] 3:4)
* That today we should observe the commandments. (Babylonian Talmud, Tractate Avodah Zarah 3a, 4b).
* That today we should observe the commandments, because we will not observe them in the world to come (Rashi).
* That in the future all sacrifices, with the exception of the Thanksgiving-sacrifice, will be discontinued. (Midrash Vayikra Rabbah 9:7)
* That all sacrifices will be annulled in the future. (Tanchuma Emor 19, Vayikra Rabbah 9:7)
* That God will permit what is now forbidden (Midrash Shochar Tov, Mizmor 146:5).
* That most mitzvot will no longer be in force. (Babylonian Talmud, Tractate Niddah 61b and Tractate Shabbat 151b).

There is no authoritative answer accepted within Judaism as to which mitzvot, if any, would be annulled in the Messianic era. This is a subject of academic debate and, not being viewed as an immediately practical question, is usually passed over in favor of answering questions of the practical halachah. It is important to note that in the Messianic era itself there are different stages. In addition there is a dispute between [[Maimonides]] and [[Nachmonides]] whether the ultimate Messianic state will be bodies with souls or souls alone. So that the various opinions as to the annulment of Biblical prohibitions need to be understood in this context.

==See also==
* [[Aveira]] (Transgression)
* [[Tao]] (Chinese)
* [[Dharma]] (Hindu/Buddhist/Sikh)
* [[Emil Fackenheim]]
* [[Fard]] (Islamic)
* [[Mitzvah goreret mitzvah]]
* [[Halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai]]

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.daat.ac.il/daat/mahshevt/hamitsvot/shaar-2.htm Maimonides Sefer HaMitzvot (Hebrew Fulltext)]

{{Jewish life}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Hebrew words and phrases]]
[[Category:Jewish law and rituals| Mitzvah]]
[[Category:Mitzvoth]]
[[Category:Commandments]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;
[[ar:ميتزفة]]
[[bar:Mitzwa]]
[[ca:Mitsvà]]
[[cs:Micva]]
[[de:Mitzwa]]
[[es:Mitzvá]]
[[eo:Micvo]]
[[fr:Mitzvah]]
[[it:Mitzvah]]
[[he:מצווה]]
[[nl:Mitswa]]
[[ja:ミツワー]]
[[pl:Micwa]]
[[pt:Mitzvá]]
[[ro:Mițvot]]
[[ru:Мицва]]
[[sk:Micva]]
[[sv:Mitzva]]
[[tr:Mitsva]]
[[yi:מצווה]]</text>
      <sha1>lu2lhz7v3i5tpr4891w4ad8wdhr83mm</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
