<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Monasticism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19626</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520228275</id>
      <parentid>519190462</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T06:52:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>YFdyh-bot</username>
        <id>16428237</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[eo:Monaĥismo]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24178">{{Refimprove|date=April 2010}}
[[Image:Trappist praying 2007-08-20 dti.jpg|thumb|[[Trappist]] [[monk]] praying in his cell.]]
'''Monasticism''' (from [[Greek language|Greek]] μοναχός, ''monachos'', derived from μόνος, ''monos'', &quot;alone&quot;) is a [[religion|religious]] way of life that involves renouncing [[world (theology)|worldly]] pursuits to fully devote one's self to spiritual work. The origin of the word is from [[Ancient Greek]], and the idea originally related to [[Buddhist monk]]s in 550 BC.

In the [[Catholic]], [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Orthodox]], and [[Copts|Coptic]] Christian [[traditions]], [[males]] pursuing a monastic life are generally called ''[[monk]]s'' while [[female]] monastics are called ''[[nuns]]''.  Both monks and nuns are considered ''monastics''. The way of addressing monastics differs between the Christian traditions.  For a general rule, in Roman Catholicism, monks and nuns are called brother or sister, while in Orthodox Christianity, they are called father or mother.  This is not an absolute rule as their address varies depending on their rank and monastic tradition.  Some other religions also include monastic elements, most notably [[Buddhism]], but also [[Hinduism]] and [[Jainism]], though the expressions differ considerably.

==Buddhism==
{{Main|Buddhist monasticism}}
The [[Sangha]] or community of ordained [[Buddhist]] [[bhikkhu]]s (similar to monks) and original [[bhikkhuni]]s (similar to nuns) was founded by [[Gautama Buddha]] during his lifetime over 2500 years ago. This communal monastic lifestyle grew out of the lifestyle of earlier sects of wandering [[Asceticism|ascetics]], some of whom the Buddha had studied under. It was initially fairly [[eremitic]] or reclusive in nature. Bhikkhus and bhikkunis were expected to live with a minimum of possessions, which were to be voluntarily provided by the lay community.&lt;ref name=&quot;bhikku&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.dhammadana.org/sangha/monks.htm |title=What is a bhikkhu? |publisher=En.dhammadana.org |date= |accessdate=2012-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lay followers also provided the daily food that bhikkhus required, and provided shelter for bhikkhus when they were needed.&lt;ref name=&quot;bhikku&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Young monks of Drepung.jpg|thumb|300px|Young Buddhist bhikkhus in [[Tibet]].]]
After the [[Parinibbana]] (Final Passing) of the Buddha, the Buddhist monastic order developed into a primarily [[cenobitic]] or communal movement. The practice of living communally during the rainy [[vassa]] season, prescribed by the Buddha, gradually grew to encompass a settled monastic life centered on life in a community of practitioners. Most of the modern disciplinary rules followed by bhikkhus and bhikkhunis — as encoded in the [[Patimokkha]] — relate to such an existence, prescribing in great detail proper methods for living and relating in a community of bhikkhus or bhikkhunis. The number of rules observed varies with the order; [[Theravada]] bhikkhus follow around 227 rules. There are a larger number of rules specified for bhikkhunis (nuns).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.buddhistchannel.tv/index.php?id=70,8074,0,0,1,0 |title=The Bhikkhuni question |publisher=Buddhistchannel.tv |date=2009-04-28 |accessdate=2012-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Buddhist monastic order consists of the male [[bhikkhu]] assembly and the female [[bhikkhuni]] assembly. Initially consisting only of males, it grew to include females after the Buddha's stepmother, [[Mahaprajapati]], asked for and received permission to live as an ordained practitioner.

Bhikkhus and bhikkhunis are expected to fulfill a variety of roles in the Buddhist community. First and foremost, they are expected to preserve the doctrine and discipline now known as Buddhism. They are also expected to provide a living example for the laity, and to serve as a &quot;field of merit&quot; for lay followers—providing laymen and women with the opportunity to earn merit by giving gifts and support to the bhikkhus. In return for the support of the laity, bhikkhus and bhikkhunis are expected to live an austere life focused on the study of Buddhist doctrine, the practice of meditation, and the observance of good moral character.&lt;ref name=&quot;bhikku&quot;/&gt;

A bhikkhu (the term in the [[Pāli|Pali]] language) or Bhikshu (in [[Sanskrit]]), first ordains as a ''Samanera'' (novice). Novices often ordain at a young age, but generally no younger than eight. Samaneras live according to the [[Ten Precepts (Buddhism)|Ten Precepts]], but are not responsible for living by the full set of monastic rules. Higher ordination, conferring the status of a full Bhikkhu, is given only to men who are aged 20 or older. Bhikkhunis follow a similar progression, but are required to live as Samaneras for longer periods of time- typically five years.

The disciplinary regulations for bhikkhus and bhikkhunis are intended to create a life that is simple and focused, rather than one of deprivation or severe asceticism. However, celibacy is a fundamental part of this form of monastic discipline.

==Christianity==
{{Main|Christian monasticism}}
{{See also|Coptic monasticism|Eastern Christian monasticism}}
[[File:St. Anthony's Monastery 2006.jpg|thumb|The [[Monastery of Saint Anthony]] in Egypt, built over the tomb of [[Anthony the Great|Saint Anthony]], the &quot;Father of Christian Monasticism&quot;.]]
Monasticism in Christianity provided the origins of the words &quot;[[monk]]&quot; and &quot;[[monastery]]&quot; which comprises several diverse forms of religious living. It began to develop early in the history of the Church,  but is not mandated as an institution in the scriptures. It has come to be regulated by religious rules (e.g. the [[Rule of St Basil#Rule of St. Basil|Rule of St Basil]], the [[Rule of St Benedict]]) and, in modern times, the Church law of the respective apostolic Christian churches that have forms of [[Monk|monastic]] living.

The Christian monk embraces the monastic life as a vocation for God. His goal is to attain [[Immortality#Christianity|eternal life]] in his presence. The rules of monastic life are codified in the [[Evangelical counsels|&quot;counsels of perfection&quot;]]. 
[[Image:Coptic monks.jpg|thumb|left|Coptic monks between 1898 and 1914]]
In the beginning, in [[Syria]] and then in [[Egypt]], Christians felt called to a more reclusive or [[Hermit|eremitic]] form of monastic living (in the spirit of the &quot;Desert Theology&quot; for the purpose of spiritual renewal and return to God). Saint [[Anthony the Great]] is cited by [[Pope Athanasius I of Alexandria|Athanasius]] as one of these early &quot;Hermit monks&quot;. Especially in the [[Middle East]], eremitic monasticism continued to be common until the decline of [[Syriac Christianity]] in the late Middle Ages.

The need for some form of organized spiritual guidance was obvious; and around 318 Saint [[Pachomius]] started to organize his many followers in what was to become the first Christian [[Cenobium|cenobitic]] or communal [[monastery]]. Soon, similar institutions were established throughout the Egyptian desert as well as the rest of the eastern half of the Roman Empire. Notable [[Monastery|monasteries]] of the East include:
* [[Monastery of Saint Anthony]], one of the oldest Christian monasteries in the world.
* [[Mar Awgin]] founded a monastery on [[Mt. Izla]] above [[Nisibis]] in [[Mesopotamia]] (~350), and from this monastery the cenobitic tradition spread in Mesopotamia, Persia, Armenia, Georgia and even India and China.
* St. [[Sabbas the Sanctified]] organized the monks of the Judean Desert in a monastery close to [[Bethlehem]] (483), now known as [[Mar Saba]], which is considered the mother of all monasteries of the [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]] churches.
* [[Saint Catherine's Monastery, Mount Sinai]] was founded between 527 and 565 in the Sinai desert by order of Emperor [[Justinian I]].

In the West, the most significant development occurred when the rules for monastic communities were written, the [[Rule of St Basil]] being credited with having been the first. The precise dating of the [[Rule of the Master]] is problematic; but it has been argued on internal grounds that it antedates the so-called [[Rule of Saint Benedict]] created by [[Benedict of Nursia]] for his monastery in [[Monte Cassino]], Italy (c. 529), and the other [[Benedictine]] monasteries he himself had founded (cf. [[Order of St Benedict]]). It would become the most common rule throughout the Middle Ages and is still in use today. The [[Augustinian Rule]], due to its brevity, has been adopted by various communities, chiefly the [[Canons Regular]]. Around the 12th century, the [[Franciscan]], [[Carmelite]], [[Dominican Order|Dominican]], [[Servite Order]] (see [[Servants of Mary]]) and [[Augustinian]] [[mendicant order]]s chose to live in city [[convent]]s among the people instead of being secluded in monasteries.

Today new expressions of Christian monasticism, many of which [[ecumenical]], are developing in places such as the [[Bose Monastic Community]] in Italy, the [[Monastic Fraternities of Jerusalem]] throughout Europe, and the [[Taize Community|Taizé Community]] in France, and the mainly Evangelical Protestant [[New Monasticism]].

==Hinduism==
{{See also|Dashanami Sampradaya}}
In their quest to attain the [[spirituality|spiritual]] goal of life, some Hindus choose the path of monasticism ([[Sannyasa]]). Monastics commit themselves to a life of [[simplicity]], [[celibacy]], detachment from worldly pursuits, and the contemplation of God.&lt;ref&gt;Swami Bhaskarananda, ''Essentials of Hinduism'' 112 (Viveka Press 1994) ISBN 1-884852-02-5&lt;/ref&gt; A Hindu monk is called a s''anyāsī, sādhu'', or ''swāmi''.&lt;ref&gt;[[R.S. McGregor]], ''The Oxford Hindi-English Dictionary'' (5th ed. 1999) ISBN 0-19-563846-8&lt;/ref&gt; A nun is called a ''sanyāsini'', ''sādhvi'', or ''swāmini''. Such renunciates are accorded high respect in Hindu society, because their outward renunciation of selfishness and worldliness serves as an inspiration to householders who strive for ''mental'' renunciation. Some monastics live in monasteries, while others wander from place to place, trusting in God alone to provide for their physical needs.&lt;ref&gt;Alex Michaels, Hinduism: Past and Present 316 (Princeton 1998) ISBN 0-691-08953-1&lt;/ref&gt; It is considered a highly meritorious act for a lay devotee to provide [[sadhu]]s with food or other necessaries. [[Sadhu|Sādhus]] are expected to treat all with respect and compassion, whether a person may be poor or rich, good or wicked. They are also expected to be indifferent to praise, blame, pleasure, and pain.&lt;ref&gt;Swami Bhaskarananda, ''Essentials of Hinduism'' 112 (Viveka Press 1994) ISBN 1-884852-02-5.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[sadhu|sādhu]] can typically be recognized by his ochre-colored clothing. Generally, [[Vaisnavism|Vaisnava]] monks shave their heads except for a small patch of hair on the back of the head, while [[Saivism|Saivite]] monks let their hair and beard grow uncut.

A ''sadhu's'' vow of renunciation typically forbids him from:
* owning personal property apart from a bowl, a cup, two sets of clothing and medical aids such as eyeglasses;
* having any contact with, looking at, thinking of or even being in the presence of women;
* eating for pleasure;
* possessing or even touching money or valuables in any way, shape or form;
* maintaining personal relationships.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

==Islam==
Islam does not allow the practice of monasticism.&lt;ref&gt;Bey, Essad. Mohammed. Translated by Helmut Ripperger. Britain: London, 1938. Pg. 315&lt;/ref&gt; The stand of Islam is that while prohibiting sexual license, it is also against suppressing the sexual urge, and, accordingly, it calls people toward marriage, prohibiting renunciation and castration.  As long as a [[Muslim]] man possess the means to marry, he is not permitted to refrain from marriage on the grounds that he has dedicated himself to the service or the worship of [[Allah]] and to a life of monasticism and renunciation of the world.{{Citation needed|date=August 2012}} 

The expression &quot;لاَ رَهْبَانِيَّةَ فِي الإِسْلاَمِ&quot;  “There is no (room for) monasticism in Islam”, is witnessed in numerous Islamic sources.&lt;ref&gt;This tradition has been reported in Majma'ul Bayan under رهب as also in al-Nihayah of Ibn Kathir.&lt;/ref&gt;
It has been reported that Abu Qulabah narrated:  ''Some of the Companions of the Prophet (peace be on him) decided to relinquish the world, forsake their wives, and become like monks. The Prophet (peace be on him) told them with asperity, People before you perished because of their asceticism; they made excessive demands on themselves until Allah brought hardships on them: you can still see a few of them remaining in monasteries and temples. Then worship Allah and do not associate anything with Him, perform the Hajj and the ‘Umrah, be righteous, and all affairs will be set right for you.'' (Reported by ‘Abdur Razzaq, Ibn Jarir, and Ibn al-Mundhir)

==Jainism==
{{Main|Jain monasticism}}
In [[Jainism]], monasticism is encouraged and respected. Rules for monasticism are rather strict. A Jain ascetic has neither a permanent home nor any possessions, wandering barefoot from place to place except during the months of [[Chaturmas]]. The quality of life they lead is difficult because of the many constraints placed on them. They don't use a vehicle for commuting and always commute barefoot from one place to another, irrespective of the distance. They don't possess any materialistic things and also don't use the basic services like that of a phone, electricity etc. They don't prepare food and live only on what people offer them.&lt;ref&gt;''www.jainstudy.org/jsc1.99-JainismAtAGlance.htm''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Judaism==
{{See also|Nazirite}}
[[Judaism]] does not encourage the monastic ideal of celibacy and poverty. To the contrary - all of the [[Torah]]'s [[Mitzvos|Commandments]] are a means of sanctifying the physical world. As further disseminated through the teachings of the [[Baal shem tov|Yisrael Ba'al Shem Tov]], the pursuit of permitted physical pleasures is encouraged as a means to &quot;serve God with joy&quot; (Deut. 28:47).

However, until the [[Destruction of the second temple]], about two thousand years ago, taking [[Nazirite]] vows was a common feature of the religion. Nazirite Jews (in Hebrew: נזיר) abstained from grape products, haircuts, and contact with the dead.&lt;ref&gt;Maimonides ''Mishne Torah Hilkhot Nazirut'' 1:1&lt;/ref&gt; However, they did not withdraw from general society, and they were permitted to marry and own property; moreover, in most cases a Nazirite vow was for a specified time period and not permanent.&lt;ref&gt;Maimonides ''Hilkhot Nazirut'' 3:1&lt;/ref&gt; In Modern Hebrew, the term &quot;Nazir&quot; is most often used to refer to non-Jewish monastics.

Unique among Jewish communities is the monasticism of the [[Beta Israel]] of Ethiopia, a practice believed to date to the 15th century.

A form of asceticism was practiced by some individuals in pre-World War II European Jewish communities. Its principal expression was ''prishut'', the practice of a married [[Talmud]] student going into self-imposed exile from his home and family to study in the [[kollel]] of a different city or town.&lt;ref&gt;[[Yaffa Eliach|Eliach]], Y. ''There Once Was A World'' (Back Bay Books, 1998), p. 780.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tidhar, D. (1947). ''Entsiklopedyah le-halutse ha-yishuv u-vonav'' (Vol. 1, p. 79). Retrieved from [http://www.tidhar.tourolib.org/tidhar/view/1/79]&lt;/ref&gt; This practice was associated with, but not exclusive to, the [[Perushim]].

The [[Essenes]] (in [[Modern Israeli Hebrew|Modern]] but not in [[Ancient Hebrew]]: {{Hebrew|אִסִּיִים}}, ''Isiyim''; [[Koine Greek|Greek]]: Εσσηνοι, Εσσαιοι, or Οσσαιοι; ''Essēnoi, Essaioi, Ossaioi'') were a [[Jewish]] [[sect]] that flourished from the 2nd century BCE to the 1st century CE which some scholars claim seceded from the [[Zadokite]] priests.&lt;ref&gt;F.F. Bruce, Second Thoughts On The Dead Sea Scrolls. Paternoster Press, 1956.&lt;/ref&gt; Being much fewer in number than the [[Pharisees]] and the [[Sadducees]] (the other two major sects at the time), the Essenes lived in various cities but congregated in communal life dedicated to [[asceticism]], [[voluntary poverty]], daily immersion, and abstinence from worldly pleasures, including (for some groups) [[marriage]]. Many separate &lt;!-- pagchur?? --&gt; but related religious groups of that era shared similar [[mysticism|mystic]], [[Jewish eschatology|eschatological]], [[Jewish Messiah|messianic]], and [[asceticism|ascetic]] beliefs. These groups are collectively referred to by various scholars as the &quot;Essenes.&quot; [[Josephus]] records that Essenes existed in large numbers, and thousands lived throughout [[Judaea (Roman province)|Roman Judæa]].

The Essenes have gained fame in modern times as a result of the discovery of an extensive group of religious documents known as the [[Dead Sea Scrolls]], which are commonly believed to be Essenes' library—although there is no proof that the Essenes wrote them.  These documents include preserved multiple copies of the [[Hebrew Bible]] untouched from as early as 300 BCE until their discovery in 1946. Some scholars, however, dispute the notion that the Essenes wrote the Dead Sea Scrolls.&lt;ref&gt;Hillel Newman, Ph.D Bar Ilan University : ''Proximity to Power and Jewish Sectarian Groups of the Ancient Period'' Brill ISBN 90-04-14699-7.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rachel Elior]], a prominent [[Israelis|Israeli]] scholar, even questions the existence of the Essenes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first=Ofri |last=Ilani |date=13 March 2009 |title=Scholar: The Essenes, Dead Sea Scroll 'authors,' never existed |url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1070797.html |work=[[Haaretz]] |accessdate=17 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=time20090316&gt;{{Cite news|first=Tim |last=McGirk |date=16 March 2009 |title=Scholar Claims Dead Sea Scrolls 'Authors' Never Existed |url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1885421,00.html |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |accessdate=17 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=elior-responds&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jwest.wordpress.com/2009/03/15/rachel-elior-responds-to-her-critics/ |title=Rachel Elior Responds to Her Critics |publisher=Jim West |date=15 March 2009 |accessdate=17 March 2009}}{{Verify credibility|date=March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other religions or movements==
* [[Ananda Marga]] has both monks and nuns (i.e. [[celibacy|celibate]] male and female [[acharya]]s or [[missionary|missionaries]]) as well as a smaller group of family acharyas. The monks and nuns are engaged in all kinds of direct services to society, so they have no scope for permanent retreat. They do have to follow strict celibacy, poverty and many other rules of conduct during as well as after they have completed their training.
* [[Bön]] is believed to have a rich monastic history. Bön monasteries exist today, and the monks there practice Bön-Buddhism.
* [[Manichaeism]] had two types of followers, the auditors, and the elect. The elect lived apart from the auditors to concentrate on reducing the material influences of the world. They did this through strict celibacy, poverty, teaching, and preaching. Therefore the elect were probably at least partially monastic.
* [[Scientology]] maintains a &quot;fraternal order&quot; called the [[Sea Organization]] or just [[Sea Org]]. They work only for the [[Church of Scientology]] and have signed billion year contracts. Sea Org members live communally with lodging, food, clothing, and medical care provided by the Church.
* [[Sikhism]] and the [[Bahá’í Faith]] both specifically forbid the practice of monasticism. Hence there are no Sikh or Bahá’í monk conclaves or brotherhoods.
* [[Taoism]] has some sects with [[monk]]s and [[nun]]s.
* The [[Transcendental Meditation movement]] sponsors two monastic groups: the Thousand-Headed Purusha for men and the Mother Divine for women.&lt;ref name=Williamson&gt;{{Cite book|last=Williamson|first=Lola |title=Transcendent in America:Hindu-Inspired Meditation Movements as New Religion |publisher=NYU Press|year=2010|isbn=978-0-8147-9450-0|page=103}}&lt;/ref&gt; The US residences for the groups were in [[Maharishi Sthapatya Veda#Purusha Capital|Heavenly Mountain, North Carolina]].&lt;ref name=Williamson/&gt; There is also a Purusha program at an [[ashram]] in [[Uttarkashi]], [[India]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.goerie.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070811/LIFESTYLES03/708110323/-1/RSS |last=Massing|first=Dana|title=TM quiets mind, rests body says Erie man|work=Erie Times-News|date=August 11, 2007|page= 1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Global Mother Divine Organization is described as the women's wing of the [[Global Country of World Peace]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gmdousa.org/indigenous-grandmothers/aboutus.html|archivedate=October 7, 2010|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5tILsvCiI|title=The Global Mother Divine Organization: About Us|publisher=gmdousa.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Zoroastrianism]] holds that active participation in life through good thoughts, good words and good deeds is necessary to ensure happiness and to keep chaotic influences at bay. This ''active'' participation is a central element in [[Zoroaster]]'s concept of [[free will]], and Zoroastrianism rejects all forms of [[asceticism]] and monasticism.

==See also==
* [[Carmelite Rule of St. Albert]]
* &quot;[[Into Great Silence]]&quot;-  Documentary of life within the Carthusian monastery of La Grande Chartreuse by Philip Groning.
* [[Matha]]
* [[Order (religious)]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Fracchia, Charles. ''Living Together Alone: The New American Monasticism''. Harper &amp; Row, 1979. ISBN 0-06-063011-6.
* Gruber, Mark. 2003. ''Sacrifice In the Desert: A Study of an Egyptian Minority Through the Lens of Coptic Monasticism''. Lanham: University Press of America. ISBN 0-7618-2539-8
* Johnston, William M. (ed.). 2000. ''Encyclopedia of Monasticism''. 2 vols., Chicago: Fitzroy Dearborn Publishers.
* Knowles, David. Christian Monasticism. London: World University Library, 1969
* Lawrence, C. H. 2001. ''Medieval Monasticism: Forms of Religious Life in Western Europe in the Middle Ages'' (3rd Edition). New York: Longmans. ISBN 0-582-40427-4
* [[George Zarnecki|Zarnecki, George.]] 1985. &quot;The Monastic World: The Contributions of the Orders&quot;. Pp.&amp;nbsp;36–66, in Evans, Joan (ed.). 1985. ''The Flowering of the Middle Ages.'' London: Thames and Hudson Ltd.

==External links==
* [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/8733 The Hermits by Charles Kingsley (Gutenberg)]
* [http://st-takla.org/Links/Coptic-Links-04_Monasteries.html Links to Coptic Orthodox Monasteries of Egypt and the world]
* [http://www.historyfish.net/monastics/monastics.html Historyfish.net: texts and articles regarding the Western Christian monastic tradition.]
* [http://www.historyfish.net/monastics/monasticlife.html Abbot Gasquet's English Monastic Life. Full Text + Illustrations.]
* [http://www.historyfish.net/abbeys/photochrom_abbeys.html Public Domain Photochrom photographs, Abbeys, Cathedrals, Holy Sites and the Holy Land.]
* [http://www.historyworld.net/wrldhis/PlainTextHistories.asp?historyid=ab88 History of Monasticism]
* [http://doc0mr.tripod.com/id23.html Monasticism] Immaculate Heart of Mary's Hermitage
* [http://www.atmajyoti.org/mo_woman.asp &quot;Woman&quot;&amp;nbsp;– The correct perspective for the monastic]&amp;nbsp;– An eastern point of view
* [http://www.francis.or.kr/IndexE.html Korean Franciscan Brotherhood]
* [http://www.stanthonysmonastery.org/Monasticism.htm Orthodox Monasticism] Saint Anthony's Greek Orthodox Monaster

{{Religion topics}}
{{Simple living}}

[[Category:Monasticism| ]]
[[Category:Religious behaviour and experience]]

[[bg:Монашество]]
[[cs:Mnišství]]
[[de:Monastisch]]
[[dsb:Mnichojstwo]]
[[et:Munklus]]
[[el:Μοναχισμός]]
[[eo:Monaĥismo]]
[[fa:رهبانیت]]
[[hy:Վանականություն]]
[[id:Monastisisme]]
[[it:Monachesimo]]
[[he:נזיר]]
[[pl:Monastycyzm]]
[[pt:Monasticismo]]
[[ru:Монашество]]
[[sr:Монаштво]]
[[sh:Monaštvo]]
[[sv:Monastisk]]
[[th:ชีวิตอารามวาสี]]
[[uk:Чернецтво]]
[[vi:Đan sĩ]]
[[yi:מאנאך]]
[[zh:修行制度]]</text>
      <sha1>cpeh2swacmdzribtui1u3svvoz7umoy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
