<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Monotheism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19522</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522242415</id>
      <parentid>521721770</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T22:03:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>84.13.1.119</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Proto-Indo-European religion */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="80475">{{God}}
'''Monotheism''' (from [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] {{lang|grc|[[:wikt:μόνος|μόνος]]}}, ''monos'', &quot;single&quot;, and {{lang|grc|[[:wikt:θεός|θεός]]}}, ''theos'', &quot;god&quot;) is the belief in the existence of one [[deity|god]] or in the oneness of God.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Monotheism&quot;, ''Britannica'', 15th ed. (1986), '''8''':266.&lt;/ref&gt; Monotheism is characteristic of [[Atenism]], [[Bahá'í Faith]], [[Christianity]], [[Hinduism]], [[Islam]], [[Ravidassia]], [[Judaism]], [[Sabians|Sabianism]], [[Sikhism]] and [[Zoroastrianism]].&lt;ref&gt;monotheism 2012. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. Retrieved 12 January 2012, from http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/390101/monotheism&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin and development==
The word ''[[:wikt:monotheism|monotheism]]'' is derived from the [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] {{lang|grc|[[:wikt:μόνος|μόνος]]}} (''monos'')&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3D%2368642 Monos], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', at Perseus&lt;/ref&gt; meaning &quot;single&quot; and {{lang|grc|[[:wikt:θεός|θεός]]}} (''theos'')&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3D%2348292 Theos], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', at Perseus&lt;/ref&gt; meaning &quot;[[God (male deity)|god]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;The compound {{lang|el|μονοθεισμός}} is current only in [[Modern Greek]]. There is a single attestation of {{lang|grc|μονόθεον}} in a Byzantine hymn (''Canones Junii'' 20.6.43; A. Acconcia Longo and G. Schirò, ''Analecta hymnica graeca, vol. 11 e codicibus eruta Italiae inferioris''. Rome: Istituto di Studi Bizantini e Neoellenici. Università di Roma, 1978)&lt;/ref&gt; The English term was first used by [[Henry More]] (1614–1687).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=An Explanation of the Grand Mystery of Godliness |last=More |first=Henry |year=1660 |publisher= Flesher &amp; Morden |location=London |page= 62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some writers such as [[Karen Armstrong]] believe that the concept of monotheism sees a gradual development out of notions of [[henotheism]] (worshiping a single god while accepting the existence or possible existence of other deities) and [[monolatrism]] (the recognition of the existence of many gods, but with the consistent worship of only one deity).{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}} {{Dubious|date=January 2012}} However, the historical incidences of monotheism are so rare, that it's difficult to support any theory of the natural progression of religions from [[polytheism]] to henotheism to monotheism.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}

Two examples of monolatrism developing from polytheism are the [[Aten]] cult in the reign of the [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptian]] [[pharaoh]] [[Akhenaten]], as well as the rise of [[Marduk]] from the tutelary of Babylon to the claim of universal supremacy.

In Iran, [[Zoroastrianism]], [[Ahura Mazda]] appears as a supreme and transcendental deity. Depending on the date of [[Zoroaster]] (usually placed in the [[early Iron Age]]), this may be one of the earliest documented instances of the emergence of [[monism]] in an [[Indo-European religion]].

In the [[ancient Near East]], each [[Cities of the Ancient Near East|city]] had a local patron deity, such as [[Shamash]] at [[Larsa]] or [[Sin (mythology)|Sin]] at [[Ur]]. The first claims of global supremacy of a specific god date to the [[Late Bronze Age]], with [[Akhenaten]]'s ''[[Great Hymn to the Aten]]'' (speculatively connected to [[Judaism]] by [[Sigmund Freud]] in his ''[[Moses and Monotheism]]''). However the [[date of the Exodus]] is disputed, and it is not definitive whether the setting of the biblical Exodus event is prior to or following Akhenaten's reign. Furthermore it is not clear to what extent Akhenaten's Atenism was monotheistic rather than henotheistic with Akhenaten himself identified with the god Aten.

Currents of monism or monotheism emerge in [[Vedic period|Vedic India]] earlier, with e.g. the [[Nasadiya Sukta]]. In the [[Indo-Iranians|Indo-Iranian]] tradition, the [[Rigveda]] exhibits notions of [[monism]], in particular in the comparatively late [[RV 10|tenth book]], also dated to the early Iron Age, e.g. in the [[Nasadiya sukta]].

Ethical monotheism and the associated concept of absolute [[good and evil]] emerge in [[Zoroastrianism]] and [[Judaism]], later culminating in the doctrines of [[Christology]] in [[early Christianity]] and later (by the 7th century) in the ''[[tawhid]]'' in [[Islam]]. In [[Kalam|Islamic theology]], a person who spontaneously &quot;discovers&quot; monotheism is called a ''[[ḥanīf]]'', the original ''ḥanīf'' being [[Abraham]].

Austrian anthropologist [[Wilhelm Schmidt (linguist)|Wilhelm Schmidt]] in the 1910s postulated an ''[[Urmonotheismus]]'', &quot;original&quot; or &quot;primitive monotheism.&quot;

==Definitions==
{{ConceptionsofGod}}
{{Further|Comparative religion|Conceptions of God|Theism}}
Monotheism is the belief in a singular [[God]], in contrast to [[polytheism]], the belief in several [[Deity|deities]]. Polytheism can, however, be reconcilable with inclusive monotheism ([[monolatrism]]) or other forms of [[monism]]. The distinction between inclusive monotheism and polytheism is not clear or objective in light of that.

==Forms==
{{Unreferenced section|date=May 2012}}
* [[Deism]] posits the existence of a single god, the Designer of the designs in Nature. Some Deists believe in an impersonal god that does not intervene in the world, while other Deists believe in intervention through Providence.
* [[Trinity|Trinitarian monotheism]] is the Christian doctrine of belief in one God who is three distinct [[Hypostasis (philosophy)|persons]]; God the Father ([[Yahweh]]), God the Son ([[Christ Jesus]]) and God the Holy Spirit ([[Holy Spirit (Christianity)|Holy Ghost]]).
* Monotheism is often contrasted with theistic [[dualism]] (ditheism). However, in dualistic theologies such as that of [[Gnosticism]], the two deities are not of equal rank, and the role of the Gnostic [[demiurge]] is closer to that of the [[Devil]]&lt;ref&gt;The Jewish concept of [[Satan]] is sharply different from the Christian concepts of [[Satan]] and the [[Devil]]. In short, the Jewish ''satan'' is not a fallen angel with own free will but rather an angelic servant of God (an acting force of God) under full control of God himself. The Jewish ''satan'' means adversary or prosecutor and is not to be confused with the Christian [[Antichrist]] or [[Satan#Christianity|Devil]]&lt;/ref&gt; in Christian [[Trinity|trinitarian]] theology than a [[Diarchy|diarch]] on equal terms with God (who is represented in pantheistic fashion, as [[Pleroma]]).
* [[Henotheism]] involves devotion to a single god while accepting the existence of other gods. Though similar, it contrasts drastically with monotheism, the worship of a single deity independent of the [[ontology|ontological]] claims regarding that deity. [[Hinduism]] is sometimes overgeneralized to as [[henotheistic]].&lt;ref name=heno&gt;See {{harvnb|Michaels|2004|p=xiv}} and {{cite web |url=http://ancienthistory.about.com/cs/egyptmyth/g/henotheism.htm |title=Henotheism |accessdate=2007-07-05 |last=Gill |first= N.S |work= |publisher=[[About.com|About, Inc]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Monism]] is the type of monotheism found in Hinduism, encompassing [[pantheism]] and [[panentheism]], and at the same time the concept of a [[personal god]].
* [[Pantheism]] holds that [[Universe|the universe]] itself is God. The existence of a transcendent being extraneous to nature is denied.
* [[Panentheism]] is a form of monistic monotheism which holds that God is all of existence, containing, but not identical to, [[Universe|the Universe]]. The one God is omnipotent and all-pervading, the universe is part of God, and God is both [[Immanence|immanent]] and [[transcendence (religion)|transcendent]].
* [[Polytheism|Substance monotheism]], found in some indigenous African religions, holds that the many gods are different forms of a single underlying substance.
* [[Tawhīd]] is a rigorous form of monotheism practiced by Muslims that God is a single, indivisible being, with none being equal or related to him.

==Atenism==
{{Main|Atenism}}
[[Amenhotep IV]] initially introduced [[Atenism]] in Year 5 of his reign (1348/1346 BC), raising the Aten to the status of [[Supreme God]], after initially permitting the continued worship of the traditional gods.&lt;ref&gt;Rosalie David, op. cit., p.125&lt;/ref&gt; To emphasise the change, Aten's name was written in the [[cartouche]] form normally reserved for Pharaohs, an innovation of Atenism. This religious reformation appears to coincide with the proclamation of a [[Sed festival]], a sort of royal jubilee intended to reinforce the Pharaoh's divine powers of kingship. Traditionally held in the thirtieth year of the Pharaoh's reign, this possibly was a festival in honour of Amenhotep III, whom some Egyptologists think had a [[coregency]] with his son Amenhotep IV of two to twelve years.

Year 5 is believed to mark the beginning of Amenhotep IV's construction of a new capital, [[Akhetaten]] (''Horizon of the Aten''), at the site known today as [[Amarna]]. Evidence of this appears on three of the boundary stelae used to mark the boundaries of this new capital. At this time, Amenhotep IV officially changed his name to Akhenaten (''Agreeable to Aten'') as evidence of his new worship. The date given for the event has been estimated to fall around January 2 of that year. In Year 7 of his reign (1346/1344 BCE) the capital was moved from [[Thebes, Egypt|Thebes]] to Akhetaten (near modern [[Amarna]]), though construction of the city seems to have continued for two more years. In shifting his court from the traditional ceremonial centres Akhenaten was signalling a dramatic transformation in the focus of religious and political power.

The move separated the Pharaoh and his court from the influence of the priesthood and from the traditional centres of worship, but his decree had deeper religious significance too—taken in conjunction with his name change, it is possible that the move to Amarna was also meant as a signal of Akhenaten's symbolic death and rebirth. It may also have coincided with the death of his father and the end of the coregency. In addition to constructing a new capital in honor of Aten, Akhenaten also oversaw the construction of some of the most massive [[Egyptian temple|temple]] complexes in ancient Egypt, including one at [[Karnak]] and one at Thebes, close to the old temple of [[Amun]].

In Year 9 (1344/1342 BCE), Akhenaten strengthened the Atenist regime, declaring the Aten to be not merely the supreme god, but the ''only'' god, a universal deity, and forbidding worship of all others, including the veneration of idols, even privately in people's homes—an arena the Egyptian state had previously not touched in religious terms. Aten was addressed by Akhenaten in prayers, such as the ''[[Great Hymn to the Aten]]'': &quot;O Sole God beside whom there is none&quot;. The Egyptian people were to worship Akhenaten; only Akhenaten and Nefertiti could worship Aten.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hart|first=George|title=The Routledge dictionary of Egyptian gods and goddesses|year=2nd ed. 2005|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0-415-34495-1|page=39}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Indigenous American tradition==
Traditional Native Americans believe in a creator, variously referred to as [[Great Spirit]], Great Creator or Great One, who is the originator of creation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Garrett|first=M.T.|title=Understanding the &quot;Medicine&quot; of Native American Traditional Values: An Integrative Review.|journal=Counseling and Values|year=1999|month=January|volume=43|pages=84–98|doi=10.1002/j.2161-007X.1999.tb00131.x|accessdate=1 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Indo-European religions==

===Proto-Indo-European religion===
{{main|Proto-Indo-European religion}}
In the [[Proto-Indo-European]] religion, the supreme god is [[Dyeus]], as the word &quot;Dyeus&quot; is literally used in many [[Indo-European]] language cognates to denote a supreme god.

In western Eurasia, the ancient traditions of the Slavic religion had elements of monotheism, of a supreme deity known by many names worshiped by some tribes. The most common name of the supreme deity is [[Perun]] and was identified with the Christian God after Christianization.

In speaking of Henotheism, Indo-European religions have had shifting tendencies regarding their supreme god.  Consider the ruler of lightning: the supreme god [[Zeus]], [[Perun]], [[Jupiter (mythology)|Jupiter]] controlled lightning himself; while in Norse mythology [[Odin]] delegated the power of lightning to his son [[Thor]]. In this vein, phenomena controlled by any single henotheistic god differ widely among various Indo-European religions.

===Indo-Iranian religions===
{{main|Proto-Indo-Iranian religion}}

====Indian religions====
{{see also|Indian religions}}

=====Hinduism=====
{{Main|Hindu views on monotheism|God in Hinduism|}}
{{See also|Hindu denominations}}
[[Image:Vishnuvishvarupa.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Krishna]] displays his Vishvarupa (Universal Form) to [[Arjuna]] on the battlefield of Kurukshetra.]]
As an old religion, [[Hinduism]] inherits religious concepts spanning monotheism, [[polytheism]], [[panentheism]], [[pantheism]], [[monism]], and [[Atheism in Hinduism|atheism]] among others;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Rogers| first = Peter|title = Ultimate Truth, Book 1| publisher = AuthorHouse| year = 2009| page = 109| url = http://books.google.com/?id=e3kf6GtwaT0C&amp;pg=PA109| isbn = 978-1-4389-7968-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Chakravarti| first = Sitansu| title = Hinduism, a way of life| publisher = Motilal Banarsidass Publ.| year = 1991| page = 71| url = http://books.google.com/?id=J_-rASTgw8wC&amp;pg=PA71| isbn =  978-81-208-0899-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EBpolytheism&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-38143/polytheism |title=Polytheism|accessdate= 2007-07-05 |year=2007 |work= Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher= Encyclopædia Britannica Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Pattanaik| first = Devdutt| title = The man who was a woman and other queer tales of Hindu lore| publisher = Routledge| year = 2002| page = 38| url = http://books.google.com/?id=Odsk9xfOp6oC&amp;pg=PA38| isbn = 978-1-56023-181-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its concept of God is complex and depends upon each individual and the tradition and philosophy followed.

Hindu views are broad and range from monism, through pantheism and panentheism (alternatively called monistic theism by some scholars) to monotheism and even atheism. Hinduism cannot be said to be purely polytheistic, as all great{{Weasel-inline|date=May 2012}} Hindu religious leaders have repeatedly stressed that while God's forms are many and the ways to communicate with him are many, God is one.{{citation needed|date=August 2012}} The ''[[Puja (Hinduism)|puja]]'' of the ''[[murti]]'' is a way to communicate with the abstract one God (''[[Brahman]]'') which creates, sustains and dissolves creation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.islam101.com/religions/hinduism/conceptOfGod.htm |title=Concept Of God In Hinduism By Dr Naik |publisher=Islam101.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Rig Veda]] 1.164.46,
:''{{IAST|Indraṃ mitraṃ varuṇamaghnimāhuratho divyaḥ sa suparṇo gharutmān,}}''
:''{{IAST|ekaṃ sad viprā bahudhā vadantyaghniṃ yamaṃ mātariśvānamāhuḥ}}''
:&quot;They call him Indra, Mitra, Varuṇa, Agni, and he is heavenly nobly-winged Garuda.
:To what is One, sages give many a title they call it Agni, Yama, Mātariśvan.&quot;(trans. [[Ralph T.H. Griffith|Griffith]])

Traditions of Gaudiya Vaishnavas, the [[Nimbarka Sampradaya]] and followers of [[Swaminarayan]] and [[Vallabha]]  consider Krishna to be the source of all [[avatar]]s,&lt;ref name = jsn&gt;''Bhagawan Swaminarayan bicentenary commemoration volume, 1781-1981.'' p. 154: ...Shri Vallabhacharya [and] Shri Swaminarayan... Both of them designate the highest reality as Krishna, who is both the highest avatara and also the source of other avataras. To quote R. Kaladhar Bhatt in this context. &quot;In this transcendental devotieon (Nirguna Bhakti), the sole Deity and only&quot; is Krishna. [http://books.google.com/books?id=_Q0YAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=Avatara+Swaminarayan+Krishna+origina%3B&amp;dq=Avatara+Swaminarayan+Krishna+origina%3B New Dimensions in Vedanta Philosophy - Page 154], Sahajānanda, [http://books.google.com/books?q=+subject:%22Vedanta%22 Vedanta]. 1981&lt;/ref&gt; and the source of [[Vishnu]] himself, or to be the same as [[Narayana]]. As such, he is therefore regarded as ''[[Svayam Bhagavan]]''.&lt;ref name = &quot;Delmonico2004&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Delmonico, N.
| year = 2004
| title = The History Of Indic Monotheism And Modern Chaitanya Vaishnavism
| journal = The Hare Krishna Movement: the Postcharismatic Fate of a Religious Transplant
| isbn = 978-0-231-12256-6
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=mBMxPdgrBhoC&amp;pg=PA31&amp;dq=Vaisnava+monotheism
| accessdate = 2008-04-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Elkman1986&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| author = Elkman, S.M.
| coauthors = Gosvami, J.
| year = 1986
| title = Jiva Gosvamin's Tattvasandarbha: A Study on the Philosophical and Sectarian Development of the Gaudiya Vaishnava Movement
| publisher = Motilal Banarsidass Pub
| isbn =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Dimock1989&gt;{{cite book
| author = Dimock Jr, E.C.
| coauthors = Dimock, E.C.
| year = 1989
| title = The Place of the Hidden Moon: Erotic Mysticism in the Vaisnava-Sahajiya Cult of Bengal
| publisher = University Of Chicago Press
| isbn =
}} [http://books.google.com/books?id=EAYa1BtUTm0C&amp;pg=PA132&amp;dq=Svayam+bhagavan&amp;sig=jcyEA-4tyPoddQmWg-FnYKDBgEY page 132]&lt;/ref&gt;

When [[Krishna]] is recognized to be ''Svayam Bhagavan'', it can be understood that this is the belief of [[Gaudiya Vaishnavism]],&lt;ref name=Kennedy1925&gt;{{cite book
| author = Kennedy, M.T.
| year = 1925
| title = The Chaitanya Movement: A Study of the Vaishnavism of Bengal
| publisher = H. Milford, Oxford university press
| isbn =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Vallabha Sampradaya]],&lt;ref name = &quot;flood&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| author = Flood, Gavin D.
| authorlink = Gavin Flood
| title = An introduction to Hinduism
| publisher = Cambridge University Press
| location = Cambridge, UK
| year = 1996
| page = 341
| isbn = 0-521-43878-0
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=KpIWhKnYmF0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=gavin+flood
| accessdate = 2008-04-21
}} &quot;Early Vaishnava worship focuses on three deities who become fused together, namely Vasudeva-Krishna, Krishna-Gopala, and Narayana, who in turn all become identified with Vishnu. Put simply, Vasudeva-Krishna and Krishna-Gopala were worshiped by groups generally referred to as Bhagavatas, while Narayana was worshipped by the Pancaratra sect.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Nimbarka Sampradaya]], where Krishna is accepted to be the source of all other avatars, and the source of [[Vishnu]] himself. This belief is drawn primarily &quot;from the famous statement of the Bhagavatam&quot;&lt;ref name=Gupta2007&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gupta, Ravi M.
| coauthors =
| year = 2007
| title = Caitanya Vaisnava Vedanta of Jiva Gosvami
| publisher = Routledge
| isbn = 0-415-40548-3
}}&lt;/ref&gt; (1.3.28).&lt;ref name = Rosen&gt;''Essential [[Hinduism]]'' S. Rosen, 2006, Greenwood Publishing Group [http://books.google.com/books?id=VlhX1h135DMC&amp;pg=PA124&amp;dq=Krishna+is+the+original+Personality+of+Godhead p.124] ISBN 0-275-99006-0&lt;/ref&gt; A different viewpoint differing from this theological concept is the concept of [[Krishna]] as an ''[[avatar]]'' of [[Narayana]] or [[Vishnu]]. It should be however noted that although it is usual to speak of Vishnu as the source of the avataras, this is only one of the names of the God of [[Vaishnavism]], who is also known as [[Narayana]], [[Vasudeva]] and Krishna and behind each of those names there is a divine figure with attributed supremacy in [[Vaishnavism]].&lt;ref name = Krishna4&gt;
{{cite book
|author=Matchett, Freda
|title=Krsna, Lord or Avatara? the relationship between Krsna and Visnu: in the context of the Avatara myth as presented by the Harivamsa, the Visnupurana and the Bhagavatapurana
|publisher=Routledge
|location=Surrey
|year=2000
|page=4
|isbn=0-7007-1281-X
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Rig Veda discusses monotheistic thought, as do the [[Atharva Veda]] and [[Yajur Veda]]:
&quot;Devas are always looking to the supreme abode of Vishnu&quot; (''tad viṣṇoḥ paramaṁ padaṁ sadā paśyanti sṻrayaḥ'' [[Rig Veda]] 1.22.20)

&quot;The One Truth, sages know by many names&quot; ([[Rig Veda 1]].164.46)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vedavid.org/1sb/1.164c.html |title=Rig Veda: A Metrically Restored Text with an Introduction and Notes, HOS, 1994 |publisher=Vedavid.org |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;When at first the unborn sprung into being, He won His own dominion beyond which nothing higher has been in existence&quot; ([[Atharva Veda]] 10.7.31)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vedah.com/org2/literature/atharva_veda/spritual_hymns.html Atharva Veda: Spiritual &amp; Philosophical Hymns]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;There is none to compare with Him. There is no parallel to Him, whose glory, verily, is great.&quot; ([[Yajur Veda]] 32.3)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vedah.com/org2/literature/yajur_veda/the_transcendent.html Shukla Yajur Veda: The transcendental &quot;That&quot;]{{dead link|date=June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The number of auspicious qualities of God are countless, with the following six qualities (''bhaga'') being the most important:
* ''Jñāna'' (omniscience), defined as the power to know about all beings simultaneously
* ''Aishvarya'' (sovereignty, derived from the word [[Ishvara]]), which consists in unchallenged rule over all
* ''Shakti'' (energy), or power, which is the capacity to make the impossible possible
* ''Bala'' (strength), which is the capacity to support everything by will and without any fatigue
* ''Vīrya'' (vigor), which indicates the power to retain immateriality as the supreme being in spite of being the material cause of mutable creations
* ''Tejas'' (splendor), which expresses His self-sufficiency and the capacity to overpower everything by His spiritual effulgence&lt;ref name= Tapasyananda&gt;{{cite book
 | author = Tapasyananda
 | year =  1991
 | title =  Bhakti Schools of Vedānta
 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=Q_VtAAAACAAJ
 | isbn = 81-7120-226-8
 | publisher = Sri Ramakrishna Math
 | location = Madras
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Shaivite]] tradition, the ''[[Shri Rudram]]'' ([[Sanskrit]] श्रि रुद्रम्), to which the Chamakam (चमकम्) is added by scriptural tradition, is a Hindu ''[[stotra]]'' dedicated to [[Rudra]] (an epithet of [[Shiva]]), taken from the [[Yajurveda]] (TS 4.5, 4.7).&lt;ref&gt;For an overview of the Śatarudriya see: Kramrisch, pp. 71-74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For a full translation of the complete hymn see: Sivaramamurti (1976)&lt;/ref&gt; Shri Rudram is also known as ''Sri Rudraprasna'', ''{{IAST|Śatarudrīya}}'', and ''Rudradhyaya''. The text is important in [[Vedanta]] where [[Shiva]] is equated to the Universal supreme God. The hymn is an early example of enumerating the [[Names of God|names of a deity]],&lt;ref&gt;For the {{IAST|Śatarudrīya}} as an early example of enumeration of divine names, see: Flood (1996), p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt; a tradition developed extensively in the [[sahasranama]] literature of [[Hinduism]].

The [[Nyaya]] school of Hinduism has made several arguments regarding a monotheistic view. The Naiyanikas have given an argument that such a god can only be one. In the ''Nyaya Kusumanjali'', this is discussed against the proposition of the ''[[Mimamsa]]'' school that let us assume there were many demigods (''[[Deva (Hinduism)|deva]]s'') and sages (''[[rishi]]s'') in the beginning, who wrote the Vedas and created the world. Nyaya says that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
[If they assume such] omniscient beings, those endowed with the various superhuman faculties of assuming infinitesimal size, and so on, and capable of creating everything, then we reply that the ''law of parsimony'' bids us assume only one such, namely Him, the adorable Lord. There can be no confidence in a non-eternal and non-omniscient being, and hence it follows that according to the system which rejects God, the tradition of the Veda is simultaneously overthrown; there is no other way open.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In other words, Nyaya says that the polytheist would have to give elaborate proofs for the existence and origin of his several celestial spirits, none of which would be logical, and that it is more logical to assume one eternal, omniscient god.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

=====Sikhism=====
{{Main|Sikh beliefs|Ik Onkar|Mul Mantra}}
[[File:Sikh Temple Manning Drive Edmonton Alberta Canada 01A.jpg|thumb|A Sikh temple, known as ''Nanaksar Gurudwara'', in [[Alberta]], Canada.]]
Sikhi is a monotheistic&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Mark Juergensmeyer
|first=Gurinder Singh Mann
|authorlink=|year=2006
|title=The Oxford Handbook of Global Religions
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|location=US
|isbn=978-0-19-513798-9
|page=41
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Ardinger
|first=Barbara
|authorlink=
|year=2006
|title=Pagan Every Day: Finding the Extraordinary in Our Ordinary Lives
|publisher=Weisfer
|location=
|isbn=978-1-57863-332-6
|page=13
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[revealed religion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nesbitt2005&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Nesbitt
|first=Eleanor M.
|title=Sikhi: a very short introduction
|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fvTK_CfkeasC&amp;pg=PP6
|accessdate=19 July 2010
|date=15 November 2005
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|isbn=978-0-19-280601-7
|page=136}}&lt;/ref&gt;
God in Sikhi is called ''[[Waheguru|Vāhigurū]]'', and is [[Nirankar|shapeless]], [[akaal|timeless]], and [[Alakh Niranjan|sightless]]: ''{{unicode|niraṅkār}}'', ''akaal'', and ''alakh''. God is present (''[[sarav viāpak]]'') in all of creation. God must be seen from &quot;the inward eye&quot;, or the &quot;heart&quot;. Sikhi devotees must [[meditate]] to progress towards enlightenment, as its rigorous application permits the existence of communication between God and human beings.&lt;ref name=&quot;p252&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Parrinder
|first=Geoffrey
|authorlink=
|year=1971
|title=World Religions:From Ancient History to the Present
|publisher=Hamlyn Publishing Group
|location=USA
|isbn=978-0-87196-129-7
|page=252}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sikhism is a monotheistic faith&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religionfacts.com/sikhism/beliefs.htm |title=Sikh Beliefs and Doctrine |publisher=ReligionFacts |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.multifaithcentre.org/sikhism/71-a-short-introduction-to-sikhism- |title=A Short Introduction to Sikhism |publisher=Multifaithcentre.org |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; that arose in northern [[India]] during the 16th and 17th centuries. [[Sikh]]s believe in one, timeless, omnipresent, supreme creator. The opening verse of the [[Guru Granth Sahib]], known as the [[Mul Mantra]], signifies this:

:{{lang-pa|ੴ ਸਤਿ ਨਾਮੁ ਕਰਤਾ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਨਿਰਭਉ ਨਿਰਵੈਰੁ ਅਕਾਲ ਮੂਰਤਿ ਅਜੂਨੀ ਸੈਭੰ ਗੁਰ ਪ੍ਰਸਾਦਿ ॥}}
:[[Transliteration]]: Ik ōaṅkār (or ikoo) sat nām karatā purakh nirabha'u niravair akāl mūrat ajūnī saibhaṁ gur prasād.
:{{lang-en|There is only One God. The Name Is Truth. Creative Being Personified. No Fear. No Hatred. Image Of The Timeless One, Beyond Birth, Self-Existent.}} By Guru's Grace ~

The word &quot;ੴ&quot; (&quot;Ik ōaṅkār&quot;) has two components. The first is ੧, the digit &quot;1&quot; in [[Gurmukhi]] signifying the singularity of the creator. Together the word means: &quot;There is only one god&quot;.

It is often said that the 1430 pages of the Guru Granth Sahib are all expansions on the Mul Mantra. Although the Sikhs have many names for God, some derived from [[Islam]] and [[Hinduism]], they all refer to the same Supreme Being.

The Sikh holy scriptures refer to the One God who pervades the whole of space and is the creator of all beings in the [[universe]]. The following quotation from the Guru Granth Sahib highlights this point:
{{quote|
&quot;Chant, and meditate on the One God, who permeates and pervades the many beings of the whole Universe. God created it, and God spreads through it everywhere. Everywhere I look, I see God. The Perfect Lord is perfectly pervading and permeating the water, the land and the sky; there is no place without Him.&quot;|Guru Granth Sahib, Page 782}}

However there is a strong case for arguing that the Guru Granth Sahib teaches [[monism]] due to its non-dualistic tendencies:
{{quote| 
{{lang-pa|&quot;ਸਹਸ ਪਦ ਬਿਮਲ ਨਨ ਏਕ ਪਦ ਗੰਧ ਬਿਨੁ ਸਹਸ ਤਵ ਗੰਧ ਇਵ ਚਲਤ ਮੋਹੀ ॥੨॥&quot;}}&lt;br&gt;
{{lang-en|&quot;You have thousands of Lotus Feet, and yet You do not have even one foot. You have no nose, but you have thousands of noses. This Play of Yours entrances me.&quot; ||2||&quot;[[Guru Granth Sahib]], Page 13}}}}

Sikhs believe that God has been given many names, but they all refer to the One [[God]], [[VāhiGurū]]. Sikhs believe that members of other religions such as Islam, Hinduism and [[Christianity]] all worship the same [[God]], and the names [[Allah]], [[Ar-Rahim|Rahim]], [[Al-Karim|Karim]], [[Hari]], [[Rama|Raam]] and [[Brahman|Paarbrahm]] are frequently mentioned in the Sikh holy scriptures. Although there is no set reference to God in Sikhism, the most commonly used Sikh reference to God is [[Akal Purakh]] (which means &quot;the true immortal&quot;) or [[Waheguru]], the Primal Being.

====Iranian religions====
{{main|Iranian religions}}

=====Zoroastrianism=====
{{Main|Zoroastrianism}}
[[File:Faravahar-Gold.svg|thumb|right|[[Faravahar]] (or Ferohar), one of the primary symbols of Zoroastrianism, believed to be the depiction of a Fravashi (guardian spirit)]]

Zoroastrianism [[Idiosyncrasy|idiosyncratically]] combines [[Cosmology|cosmogonic]] dualism and [[Escathology|escathological]] monotheism which makes it unique among the religions of the world. Zoroastrianism proclaims an evolution through time from [[dualism]] to monotheism.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = Buddhism in China: A Historical Sketch | journal = The Journal of Religion| id =  | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Zoroastrianism is a monotheistic religion&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Boyce|first=Mary|title=Zoroastrians: Their Religious Beliefs and Practices|publisher=Routledge|location=London|year=2007|pages=19–20|isbn=978-0-415-23903-5|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; (although early Zoroastrianism is often regarded{{who|date=January 2012}} as dualist) which was once one of the largest religions on Earth. Zoroastrianism is generally believed to have been founded around the 1st millennium BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia of Religion 2nd edition&lt;/ref&gt; By some scholars,{{who|date=January 2012}} the Zoroastrians (&quot;Parsis&quot; or &quot;Zartoshtis&quot;) are credited with being the first monotheists and having had significant influence in the formation of currently larger world religions. Figures put the number of adherents at up to 3.5 million,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adherents.com/Religions_By_Adherents.html#Zoroastrianism |title=Major Religions Ranked by Size |publisher=Adherents.com |date= |accessdate=2012-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; ranging from regions in South Asia and spread across the globe.

=====Bahá'í Faith=====
{{Main|God in the Bahá'í Faith}}
[[File:House of Worship Germany 2007.jpg|thumb|Bahá'í House of Worship, [[Langenhain]], Germany]]

God in the Bahá'í Faith is too great for humans to fully comprehend and human primitive understanding of God is achieved through his revelations via his divine intermediary Manifestations.&lt;ref name=&quot;hatcher_huri&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
|last = Hatcher
|first = John S.
|year = 2005
|title = Unveiling the Hurí of Love
|periodical = Journal of Bahá'í Studies
|volume = 15
|issue = 1
|pages = 1–38 | ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;manifestation&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
|first = Juan
|last = Cole
|year = 1982
|title = The Concept of Manifestation in the Bahá'í Writings
|periodical = Bahá'í Studies
|volume = monograph 9
|pages = 1–38
|url = http://bahai-library.com/cole_concept_manifestation | ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Bahá'í faith, such Christian doctrines as the [[Trinity]] are seen as compromising the Bahá'í view that God is single and has no equal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = Jesus Christ in the Baha'i Writings | first = Robert | last = Stockman | journal = Baha'i Studies Review | volume= 2 | issue = 1 | number = 1 | url = http://bahai-library.com/articles/stockman.jesus.html | ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;
And the very existence of the Bahá'í Faith is a challenge to the Islamic doctrine of the finality of Muhammad's revelation.&lt;ref&gt;*{{Cite book
|last = Lewis
|first = Bernard
|year = 1984
|title = [[The Jews of Islam]]
|publisher = Princeton University Press
|place = Princeton
|isbn = 0-691-00807-8
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
God in the Bahá'í Faith communicates to humanity through divine intermediaries, known as [[Manifestations of God]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Psmith107-108&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Smith | first = Peter | year = 2008 | title = An Introduction to the Baha'i Faith | publisher = Cambridge University Press | place = Cambridge | isbn=0-521-86251-5 | pages = 107ff }}&lt;/ref&gt; These Manifestations establish religion in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;manifestation&quot; /&gt; It is through these divine intermediaries that humans can approach God, and through them God brings divine revelation and law.&lt;ref name=&quot;BFaith-115-123&quot;&gt;{{cite book | first = William | last = Hatcher | year = 1985 | title = The Bahá'í Faith | publisher = Harper &amp; Row | location = San Francisco | isbn = 0060654414 | pages=115–123}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]] view of [[God]] is monotheistic. God is the imperishable, uncreated being who is the source of all existence.&lt;ref name=&quot;BFaith-74&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hatcher|1985|p=74}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is described as &quot;a personal God, unknowable, inaccessible, the source of all Revelation, eternal, [[omniscience|omniscient]], [[omnipresence|omnipresent]] and [[omnipotence|almighty]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Psmith106&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Smith|2008|p=106}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Effendi|1944|p=139}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although transcendent and inaccessible directly, his image is reflected in his creation. The purpose of creation is for the created to have the capacity to know and love its creator.&lt;ref name=&quot;Psmith111&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Smith|2008|p=111}}&lt;/ref&gt; God communicates his will and purpose to humanity through intermediaries, known as [[Manifestations of God]], who are the prophets and messengers that have founded religions from prehistoric times up to the present day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Psmith107-108&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Smith|2008|pp=107–108}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Oneness of God is one of the core teachings of the [[Bahá'í Faith]]. Bahá'ís believe that there is one supernatural being, God, who has created all existence. God is described as &quot;a personal God, unknowable, inaccessible, the source of all rvievelation, eternal, omniscient, omnipresent and almighty.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first = Shoghi |last = Effendi |authorlink = Shoghi Effendi |year = 1944 |title = God Passes By |publisher = Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location = Wilmette, Illinois, USA |page = 139 |isbn = 0-87743-020-9 |url = http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/se/GPB/gpb-9.html#gr26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

God is taught to be a [[personal god]], too great for humans to fully understand him.  The [[Obligatory Bahá'í prayers|obligatory prayers]] in the Bahá'í Faith involve explicit monotheistic testimony.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last = Smith |first = P. |year = 1999 |title = A Concise Encyclopedia of the Bahá'í Faith |publisher = Oneworld Publications |location = Oxford, UK |isbn = 1-85168-184-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last = Momen |first = M. |year = 1997 |title = A Short Introduction to the Bahá'í Faith |publisher = One World Publications |location = Oxford, UK |isbn = 1-85168-209-0 |url = http://bahai-library.com/momen_short_introduction_bahais }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===European religions===

====Hellenistic religion====
{{main|Hellenistic religion}}
[[File:Columns of the Temple of Apollo at Delphi, Greece.jpeg|thumb|Remains of the [[Temple of Apollo (Delphi)|Temple of Apollo]] at Delphi, Greece.]]
&quot;The One&quot; (Τὸ Ἕν) is a concept that arises in [[Platonism]], although the writings of [[Plato]] himself are still cast in polytheistic terminology. The [[Euthyphro dilemma]], for example, is formulated as &quot;Is the pious loved by the gods because it is pious, or is it pious because it is loved by the gods?&quot;
But Plato prefigures monotheism by looking for the absolute Truth, as in the [[allegory of the cave]], and the absolute Good, as in the   [[Form of the Good]].
Later, [[Hellenistic religion]], including [[Hellenistic Judaism]], and especially [[Neoplatonism]], formulate monotheism explicitly.

The development of pure (philosophical) monotheism is a product of the [[Late Antiquity]]. During the 2nd to 3rd centuries, [[origins of Christianity|early Christianity]] was just one of several competing religious movements advocating monotheism.

A number of oracles of [[Apollo]] from  [[Didyma]] and [[Clarus]], the  so-called &quot;theological oracles&quot;,  dated to the 2nd and 3rd century CE, proclaim that there is  only one highest god, of whom the gods of polytheistic religions are mere manifestations or servants.&lt;ref&gt;[[Dictionary of Deities and Demons in the Bible]], s.v. &quot;Apollo&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
Similarly, the cult of [[Dionysus]] as practiced in Cyprus seems to have developed into strict monotheism  by the 4th century; together with [[Mithraism]] and other sects the cult formed an instance of &quot;pagan monotheism&quot; in direct competition with [[Early Christianity]] during [[Late Antiquity]].&lt;ref&gt;E. Kessler, ''Dionysian Monotheism in Nea Paphos, Cyprus'': &quot;two monotheistic religions, Dionysian and Christian, existed contemporaneously in Nea Paphos during the 4th century C.E. [...]  the particular iconography of Hermes and Dionysos in the panel of the Epiphany of Dionysos [...] represents the culmination of a pagan iconographic tradition in which an infant divinity is seated on the lap of another divine figure; this pagan motif was appropriated by early Christian artists and developed into the standardized icon of the Virgin and Child. Thus the mosaic helps to substantiate the existence of pagan monotheism.&quot;   [ ([http://www.huss.ex.ac.uk/classics/conferences/pagan_monotheism/abstracts.html Abstract])&lt;/ref&gt;

Aristotle's concept of the &quot;Uncaused Cause&quot; - never incorporated into the polytheistic ancient Greek religion - has been used by many exponents of Abrahamic religions to justify their arguments for the existence of the Judeo-Christian-Islamic God of the Abrahamic religions.

The [[Hypsistarian]]s were a religious group who believed in a most high god, according to Greek documents. Later revisions of this Hellenic religion were adjusted towards Monotheism as it gained consideration among a wider populace. The worship of Zeus as the head-god signaled a trend in the direction of monotheism, with less honour paid to the fragmented powers of the lesser gods.

==Abrahamic religions==
{{POV-section|date=September 2011}}
{{Further|Abrahamic religions}}
The major source of monotheism in the modern [[Western World]] is the narrative of the [[Hebrew Bible]], the scripture of [[Judaism]]. The text of the Bible states that Judaism began with divine revelations from &quot;[[God in Judaism|God most high]]&quot; to Abraham [Gen. 14-15] and to the people of Israel at mount Sinai [Exodus 20].  The understanding of the transmitters of the biblical text was that the Bible uniformly presents one God as creator of the world and the only power controlling history. In their understanding, references to other &quot;gods&quot; are to non-existent entities or angelic servants of God, to whom humans mistakenly ascribe reality and power. e.g. Babylonian Talmud, Megilla 7b-17a. &lt;!-- Dubious material ; docu,entary hypothesis is w/o relevance here concerning monotheism ; many statements should be underlied by sources prior to publication here:
The [[documentary hypothesis]] asserts that the actual origins of Judaism lie in the history of the kingdoms of Judah and Israel, c.1,000-586&amp;nbsp;BCE. Both kingdoms had Yahweh as their state god (i.e., the god of the royal court and of the kingdom), while worshiping many other gods.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} In the 8th century the Assyrian royal propaganda claimed universal dominion (meaning dominion over all other gods) for the Assyrian state god Ashur. In reaction to this, certain circles in Israel stressed the unique power of Yahweh as a sign of national independence. When Israel was destroyed by Assyria (c.721&amp;nbsp;BCE) refugees brought this form of theism to Judah, where it was upheld during the reigns of at least two kings.{{Who|date=October 2011}} At this stage (late 7th century), Judaism was not strictly monotheistic, but Yahweh was recognised as without peer and supreme over all other gods.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}{{Dubious|date=October 2011}} The hypothesis posits a next stage, beginning with the fall of Judah to Babylon, when a small circle of priests and scribes gathered around the exiled royal court developed the first idea of Yahweh as the sole God of the world. The tendency to monotheism was accelerated by the fall of Babylon to the Persians in 538, which allowed the exiles to seize control of the new Persian province of Judah.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} --&gt;

[[Early Christianity]], originally one of many sects within Judaism, emerged as a distinctive faith around the beginning of the second century when some believe followers of Christ refused to join the [[Bar Kokhba revolt]].  There are strong indications that the difference between the new testament that Christians believe and Jewish covenant is one of spiritual Life within the believer rather than ones of religious traditional difference or historic separation.  Christ's leaving of the physical temple in Jerusalem and to establishing of God's dwelling in the spirit of man is an example of this.  Most Jews believe that Jehovah's presence dwelt in the physical temple whereas most Christians maintain that Christ (the second of the Holy Trinity) makes his dwelling in believers through the Holy Spirit (the third of the Holy Trinity). Christianity's form of monotheism was distinctive from that of Judaism in that there was a concept that the [[Godhead (Judaism)|Godhead]] was revealed to be three &quot;persons&quot; known today as the [[Holy Trinity]]. Islam emerged in the 7th century CE as a reaction to both Christianity and Judaism, drawing from thematic elements of Gnosticism&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Tisdall|first=William|title=The Sources of Islam: A Persian Treatise|year=1911|publisher=Morrison and Gibb LTF|location=London|pages=46–74}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rudolph|first=Kurt|title=Gnosis: The Nature And History of Gnosticism|year=2001|publisher=T&amp;T Clark Int'l|location=London|isbn=978-0567086402|pages=367–390}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lawson|first=Todd|title=Gnostic Apocalypse and Islam: Qur'an, Exegesis, Messianism and the Literary Origins of the Babi Religion|year=2011|publisher=Routledge|location=London|isbn=978-0415495394}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hoeller|first=Stephan A.|title=Gnosticism: New Light on the Ancient Tradition of Inner Knowing|year=2002|publisher=Quest Books|location=Wheaton, IL, USA|isbn=978-0835608169|pages=155–174}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Andrew|title=The Gnostics: History, Tradition, Scriptures, Influence.|year=2008|publisher=Watkins|isbn=978-1905857784}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Andrew|title=The Lost Sayings of Jesus: Teachings from Ancient Christian, Jewish, Gnostic, and Islamic Sources--Annotated &amp; Explained|year=2006|publisher=Skylight Paths Publishing|isbn=978-1594731723}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Van Den Broek|first=Roelof|title=Gnosis and Hermeticism from Antiquity to Modern Times|year=1998|publisher=State University of New York Press|isbn=978-0791436110|pages=87–108}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Tillman|first=Nagel|title=The History of Islamic Theology from Muhammad to the Present|year=2000|publisher=Markus Wiener Publishers|location=Princeton, NJ|isbn=978-1558762039|pages=215–234}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and stating that the Christian and Jewish scriptures were corrupted, but with a version of monotheism based on that of Judaism.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} Jewish and Islamic scholars each recognize the other faith as being pure monotheists as opposed to the rest of the world's religions having corrupt monotheism or polytheism. Since they share a common theology, their differences are in that [[Judaism]] sees [[Islam]] as a non-related monotheistic faith and [[Islam]] seems [[Judaism]] as incomplete due to a lack of recognition of [[Jesus]] as the messiah and the prophethood of [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.godsholymountain.org/papers/islam.pdf |format=pdf |title=The Jewish Approach to Islam |deadurl=no |accessdate=11 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As they traditionally profess a concept of monotheism with a singular [[God the father|person]] as God, Judaism&lt;ref name=RebShmuleyKosherJoshkel&gt;{{cite book|last=Boteach|first=Shmuley|title=Kosher Jesus|year=5772 (2012)|publisher=Gefen Books|location=Springfield, NJ|isbn=9789652295781|pages=47ff, 111ff, 152ff,}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Islam reject the Christian idea of monotheism. Judaism uses the term [[Shituf]] to refer to ways of worshiping God that Jews don't think is monotheistic. Muslims deny the Christian doctrine of the [[Trinity]] and divinity of [[Jesus]], considering it to be polytheism.&lt;ref&gt;[[Louis Maracci|Ludovico Marracci]] (1734), the confessor of [[Pope Innocent XI]], states:
William Montgomery Watt, ''Islam and Christianity today: A Contribution to Dialogue'', Routledge, 1983, p.45
&lt;blockquote&gt; That both Mohammed and those among his followers who are reckoned orthodox, had and continue to have just and true notions of God and his attributes, appears so plain from the Koran itself and all the Muslim laws, that it would be loss of time to refute those who suppose the God of Mohammed to be different from the true God. &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Judaism===
{{Main|God in Judaism|Names of God in Judaism}}
God in religious Judaism today is strictly monotheistic.&lt;ref&gt;[[Maimonides]], [[13 Principles of Faith|13 principles of faith]], Second Principle&lt;/ref&gt; This God of Israel is regarded as the God of [[Abraham]], [[Isaac]] and [[Jacob]], and is believed to be the ultimate cause of all existence. [[YHWH]] ({{lang-he|יהוה}}) is the proper [[Names of God in Judaism|Name of God in Judaism]]. Another name of God is [[Elohim]], designating his justice. Elohim relates to the interaction between God and the creation, and it means &quot;the One who is the totality of powers, forces and causes in the universe&quot;. God is an indivisible one God; as the [[Shema Yisrael]] states, its first, pivotal, words are:
:'''שְׁמַע יִשְׂרָאֵל יְהוָה אֱלֹהֵינוּ יְהוָה אֶחָד''' - ''Sh'ma Yisra'el [[YHWH]] Eloheinu YHWH Eḥad'' - &quot;Attention Israel, [[Adonay]] God, Adonay One&quot;.

The [[Hebrew Bible]] commands the Israelites not to worship other gods, but only the [[Yahweh|God of Israel]] who brought them out of Egypt (Ex. 20:1-4; Deut. 5:6-7).

The concept of Yahweh enlarged through the exile of Babylon and Yahweh was responsible for what happened to Israel. All the events and enemies around Israel were instruments in the divine hand because Yahweh is the only God and no other gods existed.

One of the best-known statements of Rabbinical Judaism on monotheism occurs in [[Maimonides]]' [[13 principles of faith|13 Principles of faith]], Second Principle:

{{quote|[[God]], the Cause of all, is one. This does not mean one as in one of a pair, nor one like a species (which encompasses many individuals), nor one as in an object that is made up of many elements, nor as a single simple object that is infinitely divisible. Rather, God is a unity unlike any other possible unity. This is referred to in the Torah (Deuteronomy 6:4): &quot;Hear Israel, the Lord is our God, the Lord is one.&quot;}}

The ancient roots of monotheistic Judaism lie in the Bronze Age polytheistic Ancient Semitic religions, specifically Canaanite religion, a syncretization with elements of Zoroastrianism and of the worship of Yahweh reflected in the early prophetic books of the Hebrew Bible. Both archaeological evidence and the Biblical texts document tensions between groups comfortable with the worship of Yahweh alongside local deities such as Asherah and Baal and those insistent on the worship of Yahweh alone during the monarchal period.&lt;ref&gt;1 Kings 18, Jeremiah 2; Othmar Keel, Christoph Uehlinger, Gods, Goddesses, and Images of God in Ancient Israel, Fortress Press (1998); Mark S. Smith, The Origins of Biblical Monotheism: Israel’s Polytheistic Background and the Ugaritic Texts, Oxford University Press (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Othmar Keel, Christoph Uehlinger, Gods, Goddesses, and Images of God in Ancient Israel, Fortress Press (1998); Mark S. Smith, The Origins of Biblical Monotheism: Israel’s Polytheistic Background and the Ugaritic Texts, Oxford University Press (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Hebrew Bible, [[Jerusalem]] was a [[Jebusite]] fortress, conquered by the Israelites and made into their capital around 1000 BCE ([[Edwin R. Thiele]] dates [[David]]'s conquest of Jerusalem to 1003 BCE). As a result, the Jebusite cult exerted considerable influence on Israelite religion. The Jebusites observed an astral cult involving ''[[Shalim|Shalem]]'', an astral deity identified with the [[Evening star]] in [[Ugaritic mythology]], besides [[Tzadik|Tzedek]] &quot;righteousness&quot; and [[El (god)|El]] [[Elyon]], the &quot;most high God&quot;.

During the 8th century BCE, worship of Yahweh in Israel was in competition with many other cults, described by the Yahwist faction collectively as [[Baal]]s. The oldest books of the [[Hebrew Bible]], written in the 8th century BCE reflect this competition, as in the books of [[Book of Hosea|Hosea]] and [[Book of Nahum|Nahum]], whose authors lament the &quot;apostasy&quot; of the people of Israel, threatening them with the wrath of God if they do not give up their polytheistic cults.

The oldest writings of Judaism that survive directly date from the Hellenistic period. This includes Hebrew and Aramaic papyri with biblical fragments such as the Dead Sea Scrolls, and Greek documents such as the Septuagint. Scholars contend that the development of a strict monotheism was the result of cultural diffusion between Persians and Hebrews, or as a result of the contact of Israelite and Greek cultures.

====The Shema====
{{Main|Shema}}
[[File:Shema.JPG|right|thumb|The first paragraph of the Shema seen in a [[Torah scroll]]]]

[[Judaism]]'s earliest [[Jewish history|history]], [[Jewish principles of faith|beliefs]], [[613 mitzvot|laws]], and [[Minhag|practices]] are preserved and taught in the [[Torah]] (the first part of the [[Hebrew Bible]]), dating from around 600&amp;nbsp;BCE.  It provides a clear textual source for the rise and development of what is named Judaism's [[ethical monotheism]] which means that:

:''(1) There is one God from whom emanates one morality for all humanity. (2) God's primary demand of people is that they act decently toward one another...The God of ethical monotheism is the God first revealed to the world according to the [[Jewish Bible]]. Through it, we can establish God's four primary characteristics:
#God is supernatural.
#God is personal.
#God is good.
#God is holy.
:''...in the study of Hebrew history: Israel's monotheism was an ethical monotheism.'' [http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/mono.html Dennis Prager]

When Moses returned with the [[Ten Commandments]], the second of those stated that &quot;you shall have no other gods before me&quot; ([[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] 20:3), right after the first, which affirmed the existence of God. Furthermore, Israelites recite the [[Shema Yisrael]] (&quot;Hear, O Israel&quot;) which partly says, &quot;Hear, O Israel: YHWH is our God, YHWH is one,&quot; meaning that Israel was to worship none of the gods of other peoples. Monotheism was and is the central tenet of the Israelite and the [[Judaism|Jewish religion]].

{| style=&quot;width:100%;&quot;
|+'''The Shema'''
|Hebrew ||שמע ישראל יי אלהנו יי אחד
|-
|Common transliteration ||Shema Yisrael Adonai Eloheinu Adonai Echad
|-
|English ||Hear, O Israel! The Lord is our God! The Lord is One!
|}

The literal word meanings are roughly as follows:
*Shema — 'listen' or 'hear.' The word also implies comprehension.
*Yisrael — 'Israel', in the sense of the people or congregation of Israel
*Adonai — often translated as 'Lord', it is used in place of the [[Tetragrammaton]]
*Eloheinu — 'our God', a plural noun (said to imply majesty rather than plural number) with a pronominal suffix ('our')
*Echad — 'one'

In this case, ''Elohim'' is used in the plural as a form of respect and not polytheism.

''Gen.1:26'' And Elohim said, Let ''us'' make man in ''our'' image, after ''our'' likeness: and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing that creepeth upon the earth.

[[Elohim]] is morphologically plural in form in Hebrew, but generally takes singular agreement when it refers to the God of Israel (so the verb meaning &quot;said&quot; in this verse is ''vayyomer'' ויאמר with singular inflection, and not ''vayyomru'' ויאמרו with plural inflection), and yet in this case the &quot;our&quot; and &quot;us&quot; seems to create a presumption of plurality, though it may just be God talking to angels and not another god.

Judaism, however, insists that the &quot;Lord is One,&quot; as in the Shema, and at least two interpretations exist to explain the Torah's use of the plural form. The first is that the plural form &quot;Elohim&quot; is analogous to the [[royal plural]] as used in English. The second is that, in order to set an example for human kings, Elohim consulted with his court (the angels, just created) before making a major decision (creating man). An alternative explanation by [[Mark S. Smith]] is that the notion of divinity underwent radical changes throughout the period of early [[Israelites|Israelite]] identity. Smith has said that the ambiguity of the term ''Elohim'' is the result of such changes, cast in terms of &quot;vertical translatability&quot; by Smith (2008); i.e. the re-interpretation of the gods of the earliest recalled period as the [[national god]] of the [[monolatrism]] as it emerged in the 7th to 6th century BCE in the [[Kingdom of Judah]] and during the [[Babylonian captivity]], and further in terms of monotheism by the emergence of Rabbinical Judaism in the 2nd century CE.&lt;ref&gt;[[Mark S. Smith]], [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=CmCVZ5mHsboC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Mark+S.+Smith,+God+in+translation&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=FzHThONctW&amp;sig=DJrqxkl7xwwXlGbVcY0V0hldC6Y&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=cv8CTLDPGcyeccuv3NUB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''God in translation: deities in cross-cultural discourse in the biblical world''], vol. 57 of Forschungen zum Alten Testament, Mohr Siebeck, 2008, ISBN 978-3-16-149543-4, p. 19.;&lt;BR /&gt;Smith, Mark S. (2002), &quot;The Early History of God: Yahweh and the Other Deities in Ancient Israel&quot; (Biblical Resource Series)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
{{Section OR|date=October 2011}}
{{Attributes of God}}
{{Main|God in Christianity}}
From earlier than the times of the [[Nicene Creed]], 325&amp;nbsp;CE, Christianity advocated&lt;ref&gt;''Examples of ante-Nicene statements'':
{{quote|Hence all the power of magic became dissolved; and every bond of wickedness was destroyed, men's ignorance was taken away, and the old kingdom abolished God Himself appearing in the form of a man, for the renewal of eternal life.|St. Ignatius of Antioch in ''Letter to the Ephesians'', ch.4, shorter version, Roberts-Donaldson translation}}
{{quote|We have also as a Physician the Lord our God Jesus the Christ the only-begotten Son and Word, before time began, but who afterwards became also man, of Mary the virgin.  For ‘the Word was made flesh.' Being incorporeal, He was in the body; being impassible, He was in a passable body; being immortal, He was in a mortal body; being life, He became subject to corruption, that He might free our souls from death and corruption, and heal them, and might restore them to health, when they were diseased with ungodliness and wicked lusts|St. Ignatius of Antioch in ''Letter to the Ephesians'', ch.7, shorter version, Roberts-Donaldson translation}}
{{quote|The Church, though dispersed throughout the whole world, even to the ends of the earth, has received from the apostles and their disciples this faith: ...one God, the Father Almighty, Maker of heaven, and earth, and the sea, and all things that are in them; and in one Christ Jesus, the Son of God, who became incarnate for our salvation; and in the Holy Spirit, who proclaimed through the prophets the dispensations of God, and the advents, and the birth from a virgin, and the passion, and the resurrection from the dead, and the ascension into heaven in the flesh of the beloved Christ Jesus, our Lord, and His manifestation from heaven in the glory of the Father ‘to gather all things in one,' and to raise up anew all flesh of the whole human race, in order that to Christ Jesus, our Lord, and God, and Savior, and King, according to the will of the invisible Father, ‘every knee should bow, of things in heaven, and things in earth, and things under the earth, and that every tongue should confess; to him, and that He should execute just judgment towards all...|St. Irenaeus in ''Against Heresies'', ch.X, v.I, {{Citation | last = Donaldson| first = Sir James|title = Ante Nicene Fathers, Volume 1: Apostolic Fathers, Justin Martyr, Irenaeus | publisher = Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company| year = 1950| isbn = 978-0802880871}}}}

{{quote|For, in the name of God, the Father and Lord of the universe, and of our Savior Jesus Christ, and of the Holy Spirit, they then receive the washing with water|Justin Martyr in ''First Apology'', ch. LXI, {{Citation | last = Donaldson| first = Sir James|title = Ante Nicene Fathers, Volume 1: Apostolic Fathers, Justin Martyr, Irenaeus | publisher = Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company| year = 1950| isbn = 978-0802880871}}}}
&lt;/ref&gt; the triune [[Holy Mystery|mystery]]-nature of [[God in Christianity|God]] as a normative profession of faith. Christians have held that in scriptural references to 'God the Father' ([[Epistle to the Philippians|Philippians]] {{bibleverse-nb||Phil|1:2|NASB|}}, [[1 Peter|1_Peter]] {{bibleverse-nb||1Peter|1:2|NASB}}) 'God the Son' ([[Gospel of John|John]]{{bibleverse-nb||John|1:1|NASB}}, {{bibleverse-nb||John|1:14|NASB}}, [[Epistle to the Hebrews|Hebrews]] {{bibleverse-nb||Hebrews|1:8|NASB}}, [[Epistle to the Colossians|Colossians]] {{bibleverse||Col|2:9|NASB|}}) and 'God the Holy Spirit' ([[Acts of the Apostles|Acts]] {{bibleverse-nb||Acts|5:3-4|NASB|}}) are referring to or describing the different divine [[hypostases|persons]].  But they also still believe that passages of the [[New Testament]], such as 1 Corinthians 8:4 &quot;... and that [there is] none other God but one.&quot;,
and the [[Old Testament]], such as Isaiah 45:5 &quot;I [am] the {{LORD}}, and [there is] none else, [there is] no God beside me&quot;, reveal God as being 'one'.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|1Cor.8:4;Isaiah.45:5||9|1 Corinthians 8:4 and Isaiah 45:5}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2012 article in ''[[Free Inquiry]]'' magazine revealed how ancient Hebrews attempted to remove polytheistic notions from the original Hebrew scriptures, yet many remain in the Christian Bible.&lt;ref name=&quot;FI2012&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| journal = Free Inquiry| volume = 32| issue = 5| year = 2012| pages = 39–45| title = A Tale of Two Tomes| last = Paulkovich| first = Michael B.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Christian notion of a triune [[Godhead (Christianity)|Godhead]] and the doctrine of a [[Hypostatic union|man-god]] [[Christ Jesus]] as [[God incarnate#Christianity|God incarnate]] is rejected by adherents of Judaism and Islam. Modern Christians, though, believe their God is triune meaning that the three persons of the [[Trinity]] are in one union in which each person is also wholly God. Christians also do not believe that one of the three divine figures is God alone and the other two are not but that all three are mysteriously God and one. Thus all three are in union as one God of [[Homoousian|one essence]], and different from many gods just as God may materialized himself in water, 'one in element' but may be ice, water, or gas without changing its element. This analogy itself however is not descriptive of the Holy Trinity but of [[Sabellianism]] which is one God with different modes or &quot;masks.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}} Other sects like [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] and [[Mormonism]] do not share those views on the Trinity.

Historically, most Christian churches have taught that the nature of God is a ''[[Sacred mysteries|mystery]]'', in the original, technical meaning; something that must be revealed by [[special revelation]] rather than deduced through [[general revelation]]. Among [[early Christians]] there was considerable debate over the nature of [[Godhead (Christianity)|Godhead]], with some denying the incarnation but not the deity of Jesus ([[Docetism]]) and others later calling for an [[Arianism|Arian]] conception of God. Despite at least one earlier local [[Council of Alexandria|synod]] rejecting the claim of Arius, this [[Christology|Christological]] issue was to be one of the items addressed at the [[First Council of Nicaea]].

However, some Christian faiths such as Mormonism argue that the Godhead is in-fact three separate individuals which include; God the Father, God the Son (Jesus Christ), and God the Holy Ghost. Each individual having a distinct purpose in the grand existence of human kind. Furthermore, Mormons believe that before the &quot;Council of Nicaea,&quot; the predominant belief among many early Christians was that the Godhead was three separate individuals. Mormons look to the New Testament for proof of this doctrinal belief such as in John 17:3, &quot;And this is life eternal, that they might know Thee, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent.&quot; Later on Christ prays in John 17:21, &quot;That they all may be one; as thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee, that they also may be one in us: that the world may believe that thou hast sent me.&quot; Clarifying that Jesus Christ is not in God physically but that they are one in purpose; which purpose is to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man. Finally, in the last moments of Jesus Christ's mortal existence, Jesus prays to the Father, &quot;Father, why hast Thou forsaken me?&quot; This statement reflecting the supposed reality that Christ is a distinct separate individual who sought for help from His Father in Heaven in Christ greatest hour of need. 

The First Council of Nicaea, held in [[Nicaea (city)|Nicaea]] in [[Nicaea]] (in present-day [[Turkey]]), convoked by the [[Roman Emperors|Roman Emperor]] [[Constantine I (emperor)|Constantine I]] in 325, was the first [[ecumenical council|ecumenical]]&lt;ref&gt;''Ecumenical'', from [[Koine Greek]] [[Oikoumene|oikoumenikos]], literally meaning worldwide the earliest extant uses of the term for a council are in Eusebius's ''Life of Constantine'' 3.6 [http://khazarzar.skeptik.net/books/eusebius/vc/gr/index.htm] around 338 &quot;{{lang|grc|σύνοδον οἰκουμενικὴν συνεκρότει}}&quot; (he convoked an Ecumenical council), Athanasius's Ad Afros Epistola Synodica in 369 [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/2819.htm], and the Letter in 382 to [[Pope Damasus I]] and the Latin bishops from the [[First Council of Constantinople]][http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-14/Npnf2-14-63.htm#TopOfPage]&lt;/ref&gt; council of [[bishop]]s of the [[Roman Empire]], and most significantly resulted in the first uniform Christian [[doctrine]], called the [[Nicene Creed]]. With the creation of the creed, a precedent was established for subsequent 'general ([[ecumenical]]) councils of bishops' ([[synod]]s) to create statements of belief and [[Canon law|canons]] of doctrinal [[orthodoxy]]— the intent being to define unity of beliefs for the [[Christian Church|Church]] and address[[heresy|heresies]] ideas.

One purpose of the council was to resolve [[Arian controversy|disagreements]] in [[Early centers of Christianity#Alexandria|Alexandria]] over the nature of [[Jesus]] in relationship to the Father; in particular, whether Jesus was of the [[Homoousia|same substance]] as [[God the Father]] or merely of [[Homoiousia|similar substance]]. All but two bishops took the first position; while [[Arius]]' argument failed.

Christian orthodox traditions (Eastern Orthodox, Oriental Orthodox, Roman Catholic, and most Protestants) follow this decision, which was reaffirmed in 381 at the [[First Council of Constantinople]] and reached its full development through the work of the [[Cappadocian Fathers]]. They consider God to be a triune entity, called the [[Trinity]], comprising the three &quot;persons&quot; [[God the Father]], [[God the Son]], and [[God the Holy Spirit]], the three of this unity are described as being &quot;of the same substance&quot; ({{lang|grc|[[ousia|ὁμοούσιος]]}}). Christians overwhelmingly assert that monotheism is central to the Christian faith, as the Nicene Creed (and others), which gives the orthodox Christian definition of the Trinity, begins: &quot;I believe in one God&quot;.

[[Deism]] is a [[philosophy of religion]] which arises in the Christian tradition during the Early Modern period. It postulates that there is a God who however does not intervene in human affairs.

[[Unitarianism]] is a Christological doctrine in contrast with Trinitarian Christianity, postulating that Jesus was completely human [[messiah]].&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15047a.htm The dogma of the Trinity]'' at 'Catholic Encyclopedia', ed. Kevin Knight at New Advent website&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===
{{Main|God in Islam|Tawhid|Hanif|}}
[[File:Qur'anic Manuscript - 3 - Hijazi script.jpg|thumb|upright|Quran manuscript from the 7th century CE, written on [[vellum]] in the [[Hijazi script]].]]
In Islam, [[Allāh]] (God) is [[omnipotence|all-powerful]] and [[omniscience|all-knowing]], the creator, sustainer, ordainer and judge of the universe.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoQ-Quran&quot;&gt;Gerhard Böwering, ''God and his Attributes'', [[Encyclopedia of the Quran]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;esp22&quot;&gt;John L. Esposito, ''Islam: The Straight Path'', Oxford University Press, 1998, p.22&lt;/ref&gt; [[God in Islam]] is strictly singular (''[[tawhid]]'')&lt;ref&gt;John L. Esposito, ''Islam: The Straight Path'', Oxford University Press, 1998, p.88&lt;/ref&gt; unique (''wahid'') and inherently One (''ahad''), all-merciful and omnipotent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;&quot;Allah.&quot; [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]. 2007. Encyclopædia Britannica&lt;/ref&gt; Allāh exists without place&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica p3&quot;&gt;Britannica Encyclopedia, ''Islam'', p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Qur'an]] states that &quot;No vision can grasp Him, but His grasp is over all vision. God is above all comprehension, yet is acquainted with all things&quot; (Qur'an 6:103)&lt;ref name=&quot;esp22&quot;/&gt; Allāh is the only God and the same God worshiped in [[Christianity]] and [[Judaism]]. ({{cite quran|29|46|style=nosup|expand=no}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;Peters1&quot;&gt;F.E. Peters, ''Islam'', p.4, Princeton University Press, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

The Qur'an asserts the existence of a single and absolute truth that transcends the world; a unique and indivisible being who is independent of the creation.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncRel&quot;&gt;Vincent J. Cornell, Encyclopedia of Religion, Vol 5, pp.3561-3562&lt;/ref&gt; The Qur'an rejects binary modes of thinking such as the idea of a [[dualism|duality]] of God by arguing that both [[Goodness and evil|good and evil]] generate from God's creative act. God is a universal god rather than a local, tribal or parochial one; an absolute who integrates all affirmative values and brooks no evil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barlas96&quot;&gt;Asma Barlas, Believing Women in Islam, p.96&lt;/ref&gt;

''Tawhid'' constitutes the foremost article of the Muslim [[Shahada|profession of faith]], &quot;There is no god but God, Muhammad is the messenger of God.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI&quot;&gt;D. Gimaret, ''Tawhid'', [[Encyclopedia of Islam]]&lt;/ref&gt; To attribute divinity to a created entity is the only unpardonable sin mentioned in the [[Qur'an]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Barlas96&quot;/&gt; Muslims believe that the entirety of the Islamic teaching rests on the principle of ''tawhid''.&lt;ref&gt;Ramadan (2005), p.230&lt;/ref&gt;

As they traditionally profess a concept of monotheism with a singular [[God the father|person]] as God, Judaism&lt;ref name=RebShmuleyKosherJoshkel&gt;{{cite book|last=Boteach|first=Shmuley|title=Kosher Jesus|year=5772 (2012)|publisher=Gefen Books|location=Springfield, NJ|isbn=9789652295781|pages=47ff, 111ff, 152ff,}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Islam reject the Christian idea of monotheism. Judaism uses the term [[Shituf]] to refer to ways of worshiping God that Jews don't think is monotheistic. Muslims deny the Christian doctrine of the [[Trinity]] and divinity of [[Jesus]], construing it to be ''[[Shirk (Islam)|shirk]]''.

====Sabianism====
{{Main|Sabians}}
According to the Qur'an, the Sabians were an Abrahamic religious group.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;the Jews, the Sabians, and the Christians.&quot; Bernard Lewis, The Jews of Islam, 1987, page 13&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Hadith]] accounts them as converts to Islam,&lt;ref&gt;e.g. Sahih Bukhari Book #7 Hadith #340, Book #59 Hadith #628, and Book #89 Hadith #299 etc.&lt;/ref&gt; while their identity in later Islamic literature became a matter of discussion and investigation.

==Chinese view==
{{Main|Shangdi|Tian|Mohism}}
[[File:天-bronze.svg|thumb|upright|[[Shang Dynasty]] [[bronze script]] character for ''tian'' (天), which translates to Heaven and sky.]]
The orthodox faith system held by most dynasties of [[China]] since at least the [[Shang Dynasty]] (1766&amp;nbsp;BCE) until the modern period centered on the worship of ''[[Shangdi]]'' (literally &quot;Above Sovereign&quot;, generally translated as &quot;God&quot;) or [[Tian|Heaven]] as an omnipotent force.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Homer H. Dubs, &quot;Theism and Naturalism in Ancient Chinese Philosophy,&quot; ''Philosophy of East and West'', Vol. 9, No. 3/4, 1959&lt;/ref&gt; This faith system pre-dated the development of [[Confucianism]] and [[Taoism]] and the introduction of [[Buddhism]] and [[Christianity]]. It has features of monotheism in that Heaven is seen as an omnipotent entity, endowed with personality but no corporeal form. From the writings of [[Confucius]] in the ''[[Analects]]'', we find that Confucius himself believed that Heaven cannot be deceived, Heaven guides people's lives and maintains a personal relationship with them, and that Heaven gives tasks for people to fulfill in order to teach them of virtues and morality.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; However, this faith system was not truly monotheistic since other lesser gods and spirits, which varied with locality, were also worshiped along with ''Shangdi''.  Still, variants such as [[Mohism]] approached high monotheism, teaching that the function of lesser gods and ancestral spirits is merely to carry out the will of ''Shangdi'', akin to angels in Western civilization. In [[Mozi]]'s ''Will of Heaven'' (天志), he writes:

{{quote box |width=60em |align=center
|quote=&quot;I know Heaven loves men dearly not without reason. Heaven ordered the sun, the moon, and the stars to enlighten and guide them. Heaven ordained the four seasons, Spring, Autumn, Winter, and Summer, to regulate them. Heaven sent down snow, frost, rain, and dew to grow the five grains and flax and silk that so the people could use and enjoy them. Heaven established the hills and rivers, ravines and valleys, and arranged many things to minister to man's good or bring him evil. He appointed the dukes and lords to reward the virtuous and punish the wicked, and to gather metal and wood, birds and beasts, and to engage in cultivating the five grains and flax and silk to provide for the people's food and clothing. This has been so from antiquity to the present.&quot;

且吾所以知天之愛民之厚者有矣，曰以磨為日月星辰，以昭道之；制為四時春秋冬夏，以紀綱之；雷降雪霜雨露，以長遂五穀麻絲，使民得而財利之；列為山川谿谷，播賦百事，以臨司民之善否；為王公侯伯，使之賞賢而罰暴；賊金木鳥獸，從事乎五穀麻絲，以為民衣食之財。自古及今，未嘗不有此也。
|source=''Will of Heaven'', Chapter 27, Paragraph 6, ca. 5th Century BCE
}}

Worship of ''Shangdi'' and Heaven in ancient China includes the erection of shrines, the last and greatest being the [[Temple of Heaven]] in Beijing, and the offering of prayers. The ruler of China in every Chinese dynasty would perform annual sacrificial rituals to ''Shangdi'', usually by slaughtering a completely healthy bull as sacrifice.  Although its popularity gradually diminished after the advent of Taoism and Buddhism, among other religions, its concepts remained in use throughout the pre-modern period and have been incorporated in later religions in China, including terminology used by early Christians in China. Despite the rising of non-theistic and pantheistic spirituality contributed by Taoism and Buddhism, Shangdi was still praised up until the end of the [[Qing Dynasty]], surprisingly as the last ruler of Qing declared himself [[son of heaven]], literally son of God.

Islam and Christianity became the forerunners of Monotheism in China there on.
The 100-word eulogy written by the [[Hongwu Emperor|founder of the Ming dynasty]] states his comment on Islam.

==Tengriism==
{{See also|Tengriism|Tengri}}
Originally [[shamanism|shamanistic]] practices that have over time may once have been monotheistic later once since deification of an [[Earth Mother]] to the Sky father as a Duality, also including ancestor worship and an addition for a &quot;sun deity&quot;, polytheizing the religion and more deities were incorporated after-wards. Tengri may have been synonymous with ''[[Tian]]'' in Chinese traditions as well as a possible fore-runner to pre-Buddhist [[Tibet]]an [[Bön]], also having their tradition root from Siberia, once sect ranging from monotheism, again branches off into [[animism]], causing an ill-defined complex systematized religion. At its monotheistic state, it was the major religion among the [[Nomadic Empires]] of [[Eurasia]]. Until the rise of [[Christianity]], [[Islam]] and [[Tibetan Buddhism]], the religion largely ceased, especially [[Buddhism]] which the rejection of a [[creator god]], Tengri has been heavily diminished or clove in such communities. It is relatively unsure what sect of [[Tengriism]] was practiced by the [[Nomadic Empires]] as some would worship a single sky god while others would worship partners with the god such as the additional deities. It has been noted that [[Atilla the Hun]] of the [[Hunnic Empire]] was a [[pagan]] according to Roman records, however it is also thought that monotheistic [[Tengriism]] was practiced by the [[Mongolian Empire]] before the advent of [[Buddhism]] which explicitly rejected a [[creator god]].

In [[Sino-Tibetan peoples|Sino-Tibetan]] and [[Mythology of the Turkic and Mongolian peoples|Turco-Mongol]] traditions, the Supreme God is commonly referred to as the ruler of Heaven, or the Sky Lord granted with omnipotent powers, but it has largely diminished in those regions due to [[ancestor worship]], [[Taoism]]'s [[pantheistic]] views and Buddhism's rejection of a creator God, although Mahayana Buddhism does seem to keep a sense of divinity. On some occasions in the mythology, the Sky Lord as identified as a male has been associated to mate with an Earth Mother, while some traditions kept the omnipotence of the Sky Lord unshared.

==New religious movements==
{{Expand section|date=July 2012}}
Various [[New religious movements]], such as [[Cao Dai|Cao Đài]], [[Tenrikyo]], and [[Cheondoism]], are monotheistic.

==See also==
* [[Abrahamites]]
* [[Deconstruction and religion]]
* [[Dharma]]
* [[Kashmir Shaivism]]
* [[Post-monotheism]]
* [[The People of Monotheism]]
* [[Unmoved mover]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*Dever, William G.; (2003). ''Who Were the Early Israelites?'', William B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., Grand Rapids, MI.
*[[Hans Köchler|Köchler, Hans]]. ''The Concept of Monotheism in Islam and Christianity''. Vienna: Braumüller, 1982. ISBN 3-7003-0339-4 ([http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN3700303394&amp;id=zMuipwd5MTEC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=isbn:3700303394&amp;sig=1c9OhvIyAcsl3rd7KvxhZrpPl1I Google Print])
*Leibowitz, Ilya. [http://acheret.co.il/en/?cmd=articles.326&amp;act=read&amp;id=2052 Monotheism in Judaism as a Harbinger of Science], [http://acheret.co.il/en Eretz Acheret] Magazine
*Silberman, Neil A.; and colleagues, Simon and Schuster; (2001) ''The Bible Unearthed'' New York.
*Whitelam, Keith; (1997). ''The Invention of Ancient Israel'', Routledge, New York.

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
*{{Wiktionary-inline}}
{{Prone to spam|date=June 2012}}
{{Z148}}&lt;!--     {{No more links}}

       Please be cautious adding more external links.

Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising.

     Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed.

 See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.

If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on
the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at
the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) and link there  using {{Dmoz}}.

--&gt;
* [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/monotheism/ Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]
* [http://www.christianmonotheism.com/ Christian Monotheism (biblical unitarians)]
* [http://www.deism.com/ Deism]

{{Navboxes
|list=
{{History of religions}}
{{Theism}}
{{philosophy of religion}}
{{Theology}}
{{Philosophy topics}}
}}

[[Category:Monotheism| ]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[ar:ديانات توحيدية]]
[[an:Monoteísmo]]
[[az:Monoteizm]]
[[bn:একেশ্বরবাদ]]
[[be:Монатэізм]]
[[be-x-old:Монатэізм]]
[[bg:Монотеизъм]]
[[bo:ལྷ་གཅིག་ཆོས་ལུགས།]]
[[bs:Monoteizam]]
[[br:Undoueegezh]]
[[ca:Monoteisme]]
[[ceb:Monoteismo]]
[[cs:Monoteismus]]
[[cy:Undduwiaeth]]
[[da:Monoteisme]]
[[de:Monotheismus]]
[[dv:އެއްކައުވަންތަކަން]]
[[et:Monoteism]]
[[el:Μονοθεϊσμός]]
[[es:Monoteísmo]]
[[eo:Monoteismo]]
[[eu:Monoteismo]]
[[fa:یکتاپرستی]]
[[hif:Monotheism]]
[[fr:Monothéisme]]
[[fy:Monoteisme]]
[[gl:Monoteísmo]]
[[ko:일신교]]
[[hy:Միաստվածություն]]
[[hi:एकेश्वरवाद]]
[[hr:Monoteizam]]
[[io:Monoteismo]]
[[id:Monoteisme]]
[[ia:Monotheismo]]
[[is:Eingyðistrú]]
[[it:Monoteismo]]
[[he:מונותאיזם]]
[[kn:ಏಕೀಶ್ವರವಾದ]]
[[ka:მონოთეიზმი]]
[[kk:Монотеизм]]
[[ht:Monoteyis]]
[[lad:Monoteizmo]]
[[la:Monotheismus]]
[[lv:Monoteisms]]
[[lb:Monotheismus]]
[[lt:Monoteizmas]]
[[ln:Bolandi nzámbe mɔ́kɔ́]]
[[lmo:Monoteism]]
[[hu:Egyistenhit]]
[[mk:Монотеизам]]
[[ml:ഏകദൈവവിശ്വാസം]]
[[ms:Monoteisme]]
[[mn:Монотеизм]]
[[my:တစ်ဆူတည်းသောဘုရားကိုကိုးကွယ်ခြင်း]]
[[nl:Monotheïsme]]
[[ja:一神教]]
[[nap:Monoteismo]]
[[no:Monoteisme]]
[[nn:Monoteisme]]
[[oc:Monoteïsme]]
[[pa:ਇੱਕ ਪ੍ਰਮੇਸਰਵਾਦ]]
[[pnb:اک اللہ نوں مننا]]
[[pap:Monotheismo]]
[[pl:Monoteizm]]
[[pt:Monoteísmo]]
[[ro:Monoteism]]
[[rue:Монотеізм]]
[[ru:Монотеизм]]
[[sah:Монотеизм]]
[[sco:Monotheism]]
[[sq:Monoteizmi]]
[[scn:Monoteismu]]
[[simple:Monotheism]]
[[sk:Monoteizmus]]
[[sl:Monoteizem]]
[[szl:Můnotejizm]]
[[ckb:یەکتاپەرستی]]
[[sr:Монотеизам]]
[[sh:Monoteizam]]
[[fi:Monoteismi]]
[[sv:Monoteism]]
[[ta:ஒரு கடவுட் கொள்கை]]
[[tt:Монотеизм]]
[[te:ఏకేశ్వరవాదం]]
[[th:เอกเทวนิยม]]
[[tr:Tektanrıcılık]]
[[uk:Монотеїзм]]
[[ur:توحیدیت]]
[[vi:Thuyết độc thần]]
[[fiu-vro:Monoteism]]
[[war:Monoteismo]]
[[yi:מאנאטעיזם]]
[[zh-yue:一神論]]
[[bat-smg:Muonuoteėzmos]]
[[zh:一神論]]</text>
      <sha1>4u4k0qzw97wcerhuiczv0ebd3y34e71</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
