<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nestorianism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22065</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522427581</id>
      <parentid>521295578</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T03:46:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iconr</username>
        <id>17749199</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15886">{{For|the church sometimes known as the Nestorian Church|Church of the East}}
'''Nestorianism''' is a  [[Christology|Christological]] doctrine advanced by [[Nestorius]], [[Patriarch of Constantinople]] from 428–431. The doctrine, which was informed by Nestorius's studies under [[Theodore of Mopsuestia]] at the [[School of Antioch]], emphasizes the disunion between the human and divine natures of [[Jesus]]. Nestorius' teachings brought him into conflict with some other prominent church leaders, most notably [[Cyril of Alexandria]], who criticized especially his rejection of the title ''[[Theotokos]]'' (&quot;Bringer forth of God&quot;) for the [[Virgin Mary]]. Nestorius and his teachings were eventually condemned as [[heresy|heretical]] at the [[First Council of Ephesus]] in 431 and the [[Council of Chalcedon]] in 451, leading to the [[Nestorian Schism]] in which churches supporting Nestorius broke with the rest of the Christian Church. Afterward many of Nestorius' supporters relocated to [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid]] [[Persia]], where they affiliated with the local Christian community, known as the [[Church of the East]]. Over the next decades the Church of the East became increasingly Nestorian in doctrine, leading it to be known alternately as the Nestorian Church.

Nestorianism is a form of [[dyophysitism]], and can be seen as the antithesis to [[monophysitism]], which emerged in reaction to Nestorianism. Where Nestorianism holds that Christ had two loosely-united natures, divine and human, monophysitism holds that he had but a single nature, his human nature being absorbed into his divinity. A brief definition of Nestorian [[Christology]] can be given as: &quot;[[Jesus Christ]], who is not identical with the Son but personally united with the Son, who lives in him, is one [[Hypostasis (philosophy)|hypostasis]] and one nature: human.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Martin Lembke, lecture in the course &quot;Meetings with the World's Religions&quot;, Centre for Theology and Religious Studies, Lund University, Spring Term 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Both Nestorianism and monophysitism were condemned as heretical at the [[Council of Chalcedon]]. Monophysitism survived and developed into the [[Miaphysitism]] of the modern [[Oriental Orthodox]] churches.

Following the exodus to [[Persia]], scholars expanded on the teachings of Nestorius and his mentors, particularly after the relocation of the [[School of Edessa]] to the Persian city of [[Nisibis]] in 489 (where it became known as the [[School of Nisibis]]). Nestorianism never again became prominent in the Roman Empire or later [[Europe]], though the spread of the Church of the East in and after the 7th century spread it widely across [[Asia]]. However, not all churches affiliated with the Church of the East appear to have followed Nestorian Christology; indeed, the modern [[Assyrian Church of the East]], which reveres Nestorius, does not follow all historically Nestorian doctrine.

==Nestorian doctrine==
[[Image:nestorianism.svg|right|190px|thumb|In the Nestorian view, the human and divine persons of Christ are separate&lt;ref name=HoganDissentCreed&gt; Hogan, ''Dissent from the Creed''. pages 123-125.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Nestorius]] developed his [[Christology|Christological]] views as an attempt to rationally explain and understand the incarnation of the divine [[Logos (Christianity)|Logos]], the Second Person of the Holy Trinity as the man [[Jesus Christ]]. He had studied at the [[School of Antioch]] where his mentor had been [[Theodore of Mopsuestia]]; Theodore and other Antioch theologians had long taught a [[Biblical literalism|literalist]] interpretation of the Bible and stressed the distinctiveness of the human and divine natures of Jesus. Nestorius took his Antiochene leanings with him when he was appointed [[Patriarch of Constantinople]] by Eastern Roman Emperor [[Theodosius II]] in 428.

Nestorius' teachings became the root of controversy when he publicly challenged the long-used title ''[[Theotokos]]'' (Bringer forth of [[God]]) for the [[Virgin Mary]]. He suggested that the title denied Christ's full humanity, arguing instead that Jesus had two natures, the divine Logos and the human Jesus. As such he proposed ''[[Christotokos]]'' (Bringer forth of [[Christ]]) as a more suitable title for Mary.

Nestorius' opponents found his teaching too close to the heresy of [[adoptionism]] – the idea that Christ had been born a man who had later been &quot;adopted&quot; as God's son. Nestorius was especially criticized by [[Cyril of Alexandria|Cyril]], [[Pope of Alexandria|Pope (Patriarch) of Alexandria]], who argued that Nestorius' teachings undermined the unity of Christ's divine and human natures at the [[Incarnation (Christianity)|Incarnation]]. Some argued that Nestorius overemphasized Christ's human nature, and others held that the distinction between human and divine natures implied belief in two Christs.&lt;ref&gt;Jerry Bentley, ''Old World Encounters: Cross-Cultural Contacts and Exchanges in Pre-Modern Times'' (New York: Oxford University Press, 1993), 105.&lt;/ref&gt; Nestorius himself always insisted that his views were orthodox, though they were deemed [[heresy|heretical]] at the [[First Council of Ephesus]] in 431, leading to the [[Nestorian Schism]], when churches supportive of Nestorius broke away from the rest of the Christian Church. A more elaborate Nestorian theology developed from there, which came to see Christ as having two natures united, or [[Hypostasis (philosophy)|hypostases]], &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=The Catholic Encyclopedia|title=Nestorius and Nestorianism|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10755a.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}{{Dubious|date=September 2010}} the divine Logos and the human Christ. However, this formulation was never adopted by all churches termed &quot;Nestorian&quot;. Indeed, the modern [[Assyrian Church of the East]], which reveres Nestorius, does not fully subscribe to Nestorian doctrine, though it does reject the title Theotokos.&lt;ref name=BritannicaNestorius&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/409867/Nestorius &quot;Nestorius&quot;]. ''Encyclopædia Britannica''. Retrieved January 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nestorian Schism and early history==
{{Main|Nestorian Schism}}
Nestorianism became a distinct sect following the [[Nestorian Schism]], beginning in the 430s. Nestorius had come under fire from Western theologians, most notably [[Cyril of Alexandria]]. Cyril had both theological and political reasons for attacking Nestorius; on top of feeling that Nestorianism was an error against true belief, he also wanted to denigrate the head of a competing patriarchate. Cyril and Nestorius asked [[Pope Celestine I]] to weigh in on the matter. Celestine found that the title ''Theotokos'' was orthodox, and authorized Cyril to ask Nestorius to recant. Cyril, however, used the opportunity to further attack Nestorius, who pleaded with Emperor [[Theodosius II]] to call a council so that all grievances could be aired.&lt;ref name=BritannicaNestorius/&gt;

In 431 Theodosius called the [[First Council of Ephesus]]. However, the council ultimately sided with Cyril, holding that Christ is one subsistence and nature, and that the Virgin Mary is the mother of God. The council accused Nestorius of [[heresy]], and deposed him as patriarch.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.monachos.net/patristics/christology/cyril_to_nestorius_3.shtml {{dead link|date=December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nestorianism was officially anathematized, a ruling reiterated at the [[Council of Chalcedon]] in 451. However, a number of churches, particularly those associated with the [[School of Edessa]], supported Nestorius – though not necessarily his doctrine – and broke with the churches of the West. Many of Nestorius' supporters relocated to [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid]] [[Persia]], home to a vibrant but persecuted Christian minority.&lt;ref name=Britannica&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/409819/Nestorians &quot;Nestorian&quot;]. ''Encyclopædia Britannica''. Retrieved January 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nestorianism and the Persian Church==
{{Main|Church of the East}}
[[Image:Museum für Indische Kunst Dahlem Berlin Mai 2006 061.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Nestorian priests in a procession on [[Palm Sunday]], in a 7th- or 8th-century wall painting from a Nestorian church in [[Gaochang|Qocho]], China]]
[[Persia]] had long been home to a Christian community that had been persecuted by the [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrian]] majority, which had accused it of Roman leanings. In 424, the Persian Church declared itself independent of the [[Byzantine]] and all other churches, in order to ward off allegations of foreign allegiance. Following the Nestorian Schism, the Persian Church increasingly aligned itself with the Nestorians, a measure encouraged by the Zoroastrian ruling class. The Persian Church became increasingly Nestorian in doctrine over the next decades, furthering the divide between [[Chalcedonian Christianity]] and the Nestorians. In 486 the Metropolitan of [[Nisibis]], [[Barsauma]], publicly accepted Nestorius' mentor, [[Theodore of Mopsuestia]], as a spiritual authority. In 489 when the School of Edessa in [[Mesopotamia]] was closed by Byzantine Emperor [[Zeno (emperor)|Zeno]] for its Nestorian teachings, the school relocated to its original home of Nisibis, becoming again the [[School of Nisibis]], leading to a wave of Nestorian immigration into Persia. The Persian patriarch [[Mar Babai I]] (497–502) reiterated and expanded upon the church's esteem for Theodore, solidifying the church's adoption of Nestorianism.&lt;ref name=Britannica/&gt;

Now firmly established in [[Persia]], with centers in Nisibis, [[Ctesiphon]], and [[Gundeshapur]], and several [[metropolitan see]]s, the Nestorian Persian Church began to branch out beyond the Persian [[Sassanid Empire]]. However, through the 6th century the church was frequently beset with internal strife and persecution from the Zoroastrians. The infighting led to a schism, which lasted from 521 until around 539, when the issues were resolved. However, immediately afterward Roman-Persian conflict led to the persecution of the church by the Sassanid King [[Khosrau I]]; this ended in 545. The church survived these trials under the guidance of Patriarch [[Mar Abba I]], who had converted to Christianity from Zoroastrianism.&lt;ref name=Britannica/&gt;

The church emerged stronger after this period of ordeal, and increased missionary efforts farther afield. Missionaries established dioceses in the [[Arabian Peninsula]] and [[India]] (the [[Saint Thomas Christians]]). They made some advances in [[Egypt]], despite the strong [[Monophysite]] ([[Oriental Orthodox]]) presence there.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, [http://books.google.com/books?id=p2mUxxxGt_sC&amp;pg=PA62&amp;dq=nestorian+egypt+oriental+orthodox&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=nestorian%20egypt%20oriental%20orthodox&amp;f=false ''Christian Confessions''], p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; Missionaries entered [[Central Asia]] and had significant success converting local [[Tartars|Tartar]] tribes. Nestorian missionaries were firmly established in China during the early part of the [[Tang Dynasty]] (618&amp;ndash;907); the Chinese source known as the [[Nestorian Stele]] records a mission under a Persian proselyte named [[Alopen]] as introducing Nestorian Christianity to China in 635. Following the [[Muslim conquest of Persia]], completed in 644, the Persian Church became a protected ''[[dhimmi]]'' community under the [[Rashidun Caliphate]]. The church and its communities abroad flourished under the Caliphate; by the 10th century it had fifteen metropolitan sees within the Caliphate's territories, and another five elsewhere, including in China and India.&lt;ref name=Britannica/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Syriac Christianity}}
*[[Church of the East]]
*[[Aramaic primacy]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* Luise Abramowski, &quot;Der Bischof von Seleukia-Ktesiphon als Katholikos und Patriarch der Kirche des Ostens,&quot; in Dmitrij Bumazhnov u. Hans R. Seeliger (hg), ''Syrien im 1.-7. Jahrhundert nach Christus. Akten der 1. Tübinger Tagung zum Christlichen Orient (15.-16. Juni 2007).''  (Tübingen, Mohr Siebeck, 2011) (Studien und Texte zu Antike und Christentum / Studies and Texts in Antiquity and Christianity, 62),
* Baum, Wilhelm; Winkler, Dietmar W (1 January 2003). [http://print.google.com/print?hl=en&amp;id=yt0X840SjpEC ''The Church of the East: A Concise History''], London: Routledge.  ISBN 0-415-29770-2.  Google Print, retrieved 16 July 2005.
* {{Cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10755a.htm |title=Nestorius and Nestorianism|publisher=Catholic Encyclopedia}}
* Seleznyov, Nikolai N., &quot;Nestorius of Constantinople: Condemnation, Suppression, Veneration, With special reference to the role of his name in East-Syriac Christianity&quot; in: [http://poj.peeters-leuven.be/content.php?url=issue&amp;journal_code=JECS&amp;issue=3&amp;vol=62 Journal of Eastern Christian Studies] 62:3-4 (2010): 165-190.
* Henri Bernard, ''La decouverte des Nestoriens Mongols aux Ordos et I'histoire ancienne du Christianisme en Extreme-Orient,'' Tianjin, Hautes Etudes, 1935.
* Lev N. Gumilev. ''Poiski vymyshlennogo tsarstva'' (in Russian, &quot;Looking for the mythical kingdom&quot;). Moscow, Onyx Publishers, 2003. ISBN 5-9503-0041-6.
* {{Cite book|last=Hill|first=Henry, ed |title=Light from the East: A Symposium on the Oriental Orthodox and Assyrian Churches |publisher= Anglican Book Centre |location= Toronto|year=1988}}
* {{Cite book|author=Rossabi, Morris|title=Voyager from Xanadu: Rabban Sauma and the first journey from China to the West|year=1992|isbn=4-7700-1650-6|publisher=[[Kodansha International Ltd.]]}}
* {{Cite book|author=Stewart, John|title=Nestorian missionary enterprise, the story of a church on fire|year=1928|publisher=Edinburgh, T. &amp; T. Clark}}
*{{Cite book|title=The ecclesiastical organisation of the Church of the East, 1318-1913|author=Wilmshurst, David|page=4|publisher=Peeters Publishers|year=2000|isbn=978-90-429-0876-5}}

==External links==
{{wikisourcecat|Nestorianism}}
* {{Cite web|url=http://www.nestorian.org/index.html|publisher=Nestorian.org |title=Unofficial Web Site of the &quot;Church of the East&quot;}}
* {{Cite web|url=http://www.anchist.mq.edu.au/doccentre/Zayton.htm|title=Manichaean and (Nestorian) Christian Remains in Zayton (Quanzhou, South China)|author=Lieu, Sam; Parry, Ken|accessdate=January 24, 2010|publisher=[[Macquarie University]]}}
*{{Cite web|author=Dickens, Mark|title=The Church of the East|year=1999|accessdate=February 6, 2010|publisher=Oxus Communications|url=http://www.oxuscom.com/ch-of-east.htm}}
{{Theology}}

[[Category:Assyrian Church of the East]]
[[Category:Nestorianism]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Heresy in Christianity]]

[[ar:نسطورية]]
[[az:Nəsranilik]]
[[bg:Несторианство]]
[[bs:Nestorijanstvo]]
[[ca:Nestorianisme]]
[[cs:Nestoriánství]]
[[de:Nestorianismus]]
[[el:Νεστοριανισμός]]
[[es:Nestorianismo]]
[[eo:Nestorianismo]]
[[eu:Nestorianismo]]
[[fa:نسطوری]]
[[fr:Nestorianisme]]
[[gl:Nestorianismo]]
[[ko:네스토리우스파]]
[[hy:Նեստորականություն]]
[[hr:Nestorijanstvo]]
[[id:Nestorianisme]]
[[is:Nestoríanar]]
[[it:Nestorianesimo]]
[[he:נסטוריאניזם]]
[[ka:ნესტორიანელობა]]
[[kk:Несторианшылдық]]
[[ky:Несторийчилик]]
[[la:Nestorianismus]]
[[lt:Nestoriečiai]]
[[mk:Несторијанство]]
[[ml:നെസ്തോറിയൻ സിദ്ധാന്തം]]
[[arz:نسطوريه]]
[[nl:Nestorianisme]]
[[ja:ネストリウス派]]
[[no:Nestorianisme]]
[[pl:Nestorianizm]]
[[pt:Nestorianismo]]
[[ro:Nestorianism]]
[[ru:Несторианство]]
[[simple:Nestorianism]]
[[sk:Nestoriánstvo]]
[[sl:Nestorijanstvo]]
[[sr:Несторијанство]]
[[sh:Nestorijanstvo]]
[[fi:Nestoriolaisuus]]
[[sv:Nestorianism]]
[[tl:Nestoryanismo]]
[[tr:Nasturiler]]
[[uk:Несторіанство]]
[[zh-classical:景教]]
[[zh:景教]]</text>
      <sha1>i4wkrvzsxp1e78vaortqmjy5cvdvemv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
