<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Norse mythology</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23417070</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522123553</id>
      <parentid>521393884</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T04:34:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>24.12.166.174</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="43590">{{Expand Danish|Nordisk mytologi|date=April 2011}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2011}}
{{Cite check|article|date=May 2011 | reason=The citations, save only one, do not point to any text in the article whatsoever}}
{{Norse paganism}}
'''Norse mythology''', a subset of [[Germanic mythology]], is the overall term for the myths, legends and beliefs about supernatural beings of [[Norse paganism|Norse pagans]]. It flourished prior to the [[Christianization of Scandinavia]], during the [[Early Middle Ages]], and  passed into [[Nordic folklore]], with some aspects surviving to the modern day. The mythology from the [[Romanticist]] [[Viking revival]] came to be  an [[Norse mythological influences on later literature|influence on modern literature]] and [[Norse mythology in popular culture|popular culture]].

Norse mythology is the study of the myths told in Germanic countries (Germany, The Netherlands, Denmark, Sweden, Norway, Iceland, Faroe Islands) during the pre-Christian times, especially during the [[Viking Age]].

==Sources==
[[File:Mjollnir.png|thumb|left|[[Mjolnir]] pendants were worn by Norse pagans during the 9th to 10th centuries. This Mjolnir pendant was found at Bredsätra in [[Öland]], [[Sweden]].]]
[[File:The Tree of Yggdrasil.jpg|thumb|The title page of Olive Bray's English translation of the ''Poetic Edda'' depicting the tree [[Yggdrasil]] and a number of its inhabitants (1908) by W. G. Collingwood.]]
{{nowrap|Most of the existing}} records on Norse mythology date from the 11th to 18th century, having gone through more than two centuries of oral preservation in what was at least officially a Pagan society. At this point scholars started recording it, particularly in the ''[[Edda]]s'' and the ''[[Heimskringla]]'' by [[Snorri Sturluson]], who believed that pre-Christian deities trace real historical people. There is also the Danish ''[[Gesta Danorum]]'' by [[Saxo Grammaticus]], where the Norse gods are more strongly [[Euhemerus|Euhemerized]].
The [[Prose Edda|''Prose'' or ''Younger Edda'']] was written in the early 13th century by [[Snorri Sturluson]], who was a leading [[skáld]], chieftain, and [[diplomacy|diplomat]] in [[Iceland]]. It may be thought of primarily as a handbook for aspiring skálds. It contains [[prose]] explications of traditional &quot;[[kennings]],&quot; or compressed metaphors found in poetry.  These prose retellings make the various tales of the Norse gods systematic and coherent.

The ''[[Poetic Edda]]'' (also known as the ''Elder Edda'') was committed to writing about 50 years after the ''Prose Edda.'' It contains 29 long poems, of which 11 deal with the Germanic deities, the rest with legendary heroes like [[Sigurd]] the Volsung (the [[Sigurd|Siegfried]] of the German version ''[[Nibelungenlied]]''). Although scholars think it was transcribed later than the other Edda, the language and poetic forms involved in the tales appear to have been composed centuries earlier than their transcription.

Besides these sources, there are surviving legends in Norse folklore. Some of these can be correlated with legends appearing in other Germanic literature e.g. the tale related in the [[Anglo-Saxon language|Anglo-Saxon]] ''[[Finnsburg Fragment|Battle of Finnsburgh]]'' and the many allusions to mythological tales in ''[[Deor]]''. When several partial references and tellings survive, scholars can deduce the underlying tale. Additionally, there are hundreds of place names in the Nordic countries named after the gods.

A few runic inscriptions, such as the [[Rök Runestone]] and the [[Kvinneby amulet]], make references to the mythology. There are also several [[runestone]]s and [[image stone]]s that depict scenes from Norse mythology, such as [[Thor]]'s fishing trip, [[Sigurd stones|scenes depicting Sigurd (Sigfried) the dragon slayer]], [[Odin]] and [[Sleipnir]], Odin being devoured by Fenrir, and one of the surviving stones from the [[Hunnestad Monument]] appears to show [[Hyrrokkin]] riding to [[Baldr]]'s funeral ([http://web.telia.com/~u85906673/asar/hyrrok.html DR 284]).

In Denmark, one image stone depicts [[Loki]] with curled dandy-like mustaches and lips that are sewn together and the British [[Gosforth cross]] shows several mythological images.

==Cosmology==
{{cleanup|section|date=April 2010}}
[[File:The Wolves Pursuing Sol and Mani.jpg|thumb|right|&quot;The Wolves Pursuing [[Sól (Sun)|Sol]] and [[Máni|Mani]]&quot; (1909) by [[John Charles Dollman|J. C. Dollman]].]]
{{Main|Norse cosmology}}

In Norse mythology there are &quot;[[nine worlds]]&quot; (''Níu Heimar in Old Norse''),&lt;ref&gt;Völuspá 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vafþrúðnismál 43&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 34&lt;/ref&gt; each joined to the other via the &quot;World Tree&quot; [[Yggdrasil]]. A list of these worlds can only be deduced from the limited sources given to us in the two eddas. A complete list of the nine worlds is never mentioned entirely, in either of the eddas.

:A summary list of the worlds, with an example reference to where they are mentioned, either in the older Poetic or younger Prose Edda. (in no particular order) -

:* '''[[Ásgarðr]]''', world of the [[Æsir]]. (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Hymiskviða 6&lt;/ref&gt; and Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 2&lt;/ref&gt;)
:* '''[[Vanaheimr]]''', world of the [[Vanir]]. (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Vafþrúðnismál 39&lt;/ref&gt; and Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 23&lt;/ref&gt;)
:* '''[[Álfheimr]]''', world of the [[Álfar]] (Elves). (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Grímnismál 5&lt;/ref&gt; and Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 17&lt;/ref&gt;)
:* '''[[Miðgarðr]]''', world of humans. (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Völuspá 55&lt;/ref&gt; and Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 8&lt;/ref&gt;)
:* '''[[Jötunheimr]]''', world of the [[Jötnar]] (Giants). (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Völuspá 52&lt;/ref&gt; and Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 1&lt;/ref&gt;)
:* '''[[Niðavellir]]''', world of the [[Dvergar]] (Dwarfs). (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Völuspá 41&lt;/ref&gt;) / '''[[Svartálfaheimr]]''' (Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 34&lt;/ref&gt;)
:* '''[[Múspell]]''', world of fire and the Fire Jötnar. (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Völuspá 50&lt;/ref&gt; and Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 4&lt;/ref&gt;) / '''[[Múspellsheimr]]''' (Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 5&lt;/ref&gt;)
:* '''[[Niflhel]]''', world of ice and mist, into which the wicked dead are cast. (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Vafþrúðnismál 43&lt;/ref&gt; and Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 3&lt;/ref&gt;) / '''[[Niflheimr]]''' (Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 5&lt;/ref&gt;)
:* [[Hel (location)|'''Hel''']], world of the inglorious dead, located within '''Niflhel'''&lt;ref&gt;Baldrs draumar 6–8&lt;/ref&gt;/'''Niflheimr'''&lt;ref&gt;Grímnismál 34&lt;/ref&gt; and ruled over by the goddess of the underworld [[Hel (being)|Hel]]. (Poetic&lt;ref&gt;Alvíssmál 21&lt;/ref&gt; and Prose&lt;ref&gt;Gylfaginning 3&lt;/ref&gt;)

Each world also had significant places within. [[Valhalla]] is [[Odin]]'s hall located in [[Asgard]]. It was also home of the [[Einherjar]], who were the souls of the greatest warriors. These warriors were selected by the [[Valkyries]]. The [[Einherjar]] would help defend the gods during [[Ragnarok]].

These worlds are connected by [[Yggdrasil]], the world tree, with [[Asgard]] at its top. Chewing at its roots in [[Niflheim]] is [[Nidhogg]], a ferocious [[Serpent (symbolism)|serpent]] or [[dragon]]. Asgard can be reached by [[Bifrost]], a rainbow bridge guarded by [[Heimdall]], a god who can see and hear for a hundred [[League (unit)|league]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Edwardes|first1=Marian|last2=Spence|first2=Lewis|authorlink2=Lewis Spence|title=Dictionary of Non-Classical Mythology|year=1912|publisher=J M  Dent|location=London|page=80|oclc=1440698}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Supernatural beings===
[[File:Ydun (1858) by H. W. Bissen - angle.jpg|thumb|&quot;[[Iðunn|Ydun]]&quot; (1858) by [[Herman Wilhelm Bissen]].]]
Numerous beings exist in Norse mythology, including the [[Æsir]] and [[Vanir]], two groups of gods, the [[Jötunn|Jötnar/Jättar]] (Giants), the [[light elves|Álfar/Alver]] (Elves) and the [[Norse dwarves|Dvergar/Dvärgar]] (Dwarves). The distinction between Æsir and Vanir is relative, for the two are said to have made peace, exchanged hostages and reigned together after the events of the [[Æsir–Vanir War]].

In addition, there are many other beings: [[Fenrir]] the gigantic [[wolf]], [[Jörmungandr]] the sea-serpent (or &quot;worm&quot;) that is coiled around Midgard, and [[Hel (being)|Hel]], ruler of [[Hel (location)|Helheim]]. These three monsters are described as the progeny of [[Loki]]. Other creatures include [[Huginn and Muninn]] (thought and memory, respectively), the two ravens who keep Odin, the chief god, apprised of what is happening on earth, since he gave an eye to the [[Well of Mimir]] in his quest for wisdom, [[Geri and Freki]] Odin's two wolves, [[Sleipnir]], Loki's eight legged horse son belonging to Odin and [[Ratatoskr]], the squirrel which scampers in the branches of Yggdrasil.

{{Main|List of Norse gods and goddesses}}

===''Völuspá''===
In the ''Poetic Edda'' poem ''[[Völuspá]]'' (&quot;Prophecy [''spá''] of the [[völva]]&quot;), Odin, the chief god of the Norse pantheon, has conjured up the spirit of a dead völva and commanded this spirit to reveal the past and the future. She is reluctant; she cries, &quot;What do you ask of me? Why tempt me?&quot; Since she is already dead, she shows no fear of Odin, and continually taunts him, &quot;Well, would you know more?&quot;  But Odin insists: if he is to fulfill his function as king of the gods, he must possess all knowledge. Once the völva has revealed the secrets of past and future, she falls back into oblivion: &quot;I sink now&quot;.

====Abiogenesis and anthropogenesis====
According to Norse myth, the beginning of life was fire and ice, with the existence of only two worlds: Muspelheim and Niflheim. When the warm air of Muspelheim hit the cold ice of Niflheim, the jötunn [[Ymir]] and the icy cow [[Audhumla|Auðhumla]] were created. Ymir's foot bred a son and a man and a woman emerged from his armpits, making Ymir the progenitor of the [[Jötunn|Jötnar]]. Whilst Ymir slept, the intense heat from Muspelheim made him sweat, and he sweated out [[Surtr]]{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}, a jötunn of fire. Later Ýmir woke and drank Auðhumla's milk. Whilst he drank, the cow Audhumbla licked on a salt stone. On the first day after this a man's hair appeared on the stone, on the second day a head and on the third day an entire man emerged from the stone. His name was [[Búri]] and with an unknown jötunn female he fathered [[Borr]] (Bor), the father of the three gods [[Odin]], [[Vili]] and [[Vili and Vé|Ve]].

When the gods felt strong enough they killed Ymir. His [[Ymir's blood|blood]] flooded the world and drowned all of the jötunn, except two. But jötnar grew again in numbers and soon there were as many as before Ymir's death. Then the gods created seven more worlds using Ymir's flesh for dirt, his blood for the Oceans, rivers and lakes, his bones for stone, his brain as the clouds, his skull for the heaven. Sparks from Muspelheim flew up and became stars.

One day when the gods were walking they found two tree trunks. They transformed them into the shape of humans. Odin gave them life, Vili gave them mind and Ve gave them the ability to hear, see, and speak. The gods named them [[Ask and Embla|Askur and Embla]] and built the kingdom of Middle-earth for them; and, to keep out the jötnar, the gods placed a gigantic fence made of Ymir's eyelashes around Middle-earth.

The völva goes on to describe [[Yggdrasill]] and three [[norns]]; [[Urður]] (Wyrd), [[Verðandi]] and [[Skuld]].  She then describes the war between the Æsir and Vanir and the murder of [[Baldur]], Óðinn's (Odin) handsome son whom everyone but Loki loved. (The story is that everything in existence promised not to hurt him except mistletoe. Taking advantage of this weakness, Loki made a projectile of [[mistletoe]] and tricked [[Höður]], Óðinn's (Odin) blind son and Baldur's brother, into using it to kill Baldur. [[Hel (being)|Hel]] said she would revive him if everyone in the nine worlds wept. A female jötunn - [[Thokk]], who may have been Loki in shape-shifted form - did not weep.) After that she turns her attention to the future.

====Ragnarök====
{{Main|Ragnarök}}
'''Ragnarök'''(&quot;Twilight of the Gods&quot;), also called Götterdämmerung, means the end of the cosmos in Norse mythology. It will be preceded by Fimbulvetr, the winter of winters. Three such winters will follow each other with no summers in between. Conflicts and feuds will break out, even between families, and all morality will disappear. This is the beginning of the end.
The wolf Skoll will finally devour the sun, and his brother Hati will eat the moon, plunging the earth [into] darkness. The stars will vanish from the sky. The cock Fjalar will crow to the giants and the golden cock Gullinkambi will crow to the gods. A third cock will raise the dead.
The earth will shudder with earthquakes, and every bond and fetter will burst, freeing the terrible wolf Fenrir. The sea will rear up because Jormungand, the Midgard Serpent, is twisting and writhing in fury as he makes his way toward the land. With every breath, Jormungand will stain the soil and the sky with his poison. The waves caused by the serpent's emerging will set free the ship Naglfar, and with the giant Hymir as their commander, the giants will sail towards the battlefield. From the realm of the dead a second ship will set sail, and this ship carries the inhabitants of hell, with Loki as their helmsman. The fire giants, led by the giant Surt, will leave Muspell in the south to join against the gods. Surt, carrying a sword that blazes like the sun itself, will scorch the earth.
Meanwhile, Heimdall will sound his horn, calling the sons of Odin and the heroes to the battlefield. From all the corners of the world, gods, giants, dwarves, demons and elves will ride towards the huge plain of Vigrid (&quot;battle shaker&quot;) where the last battle will be fought. Odin will engage Fenrir in battle, and Thor will attack Jormungand. Thor will be victorious, but the serpent's poison will gradually kill the god of thunder. Surt will seek out the swordless Freyr, who will quickly succumb to the giant. The one-handed Tyr will fight the monstrous hound Garm and they will kill each other. Loki and Heimdall, age-old enemies, will meet for a final time, and neither will survive their encounter. The fight between Odin and Fenrir will rage for a long time, but finally Fenrir will seize Odin and swallow him. Odin's son Vidar will at once leap towards the wolf and kill him with his bare hands, ripping the wolf's jaws apart.
Then Surt will fling fire in every direction. The nine worlds will burn, and friends and foes alike will perish. The earth will sink into the sea.
After the destruction, a new and idyllic world will arise from the sea and will be filled with abundant supplies. Some of the gods will survive, others will be reborn. Wickedness and misery will no longer exist and gods and men will live happily together. The descendants of Lif and Lifthrasir will inhabit this earth.

==Kings and heroes==
{{Main|Legendary sagas}}
[[File:Sigurd.svg|thumbnail|250px|The [[Ramsund carving]] depicting passages from the [[Völsunga saga]]]]
The mythological literature relates the legends of heroes and kings{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}, as well as supernatural creatures. These clan and kingdom founding figures possessed great importance as illustrations of proper action or national origins. The heroic literature may have fulfilled the same function as the [[national epic]] in other European literatures, or it may have been more nearly related to tribal identity. Many of the legendary figures probably existed{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}, and generations of Scandinavian scholars have tried to extract history from myth in the [[Norse saga|sagas]].

Sometimes the same hero resurfaces in several forms depending on which part of the Germanic world the epics survived such as [[Wayland the Smith|Weyland]]/[[Völund]] and [[Siegfried (opera)|Siegfried]]/[[Sigurd]], and probably [[Beowulf (hero)|Beowulf]]/[[Bödvar Bjarki]]. Other notable heroes are [[Hagbard]], [[Starkad]], [[Ragnar Lodbrok]], [[Sigurd Ring]], [[Ivar Vidfamne]] and [[Harald Hildetand]]. Notable are also the [[shieldmaiden]]s who were ordinary women who had chosen the path of the warrior.  These women function both as heroines and as obstacles to the heroic journey.

==Norse worship==
{{Off-topic|date=May 2010}}
{{Main|Norse paganism|Blót}}

===Centres of faith===
[[File:Gamla uppsala.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Gamla Uppsala]], the centre of worship in Sweden until the temple was destroyed in the late 11th century.]]
The Nordic tribes rarely or never had temples in a modern sense. The Blót, the form of worship practiced by the ancient Scandinavian and Germanic people, resembled that of the [[Celtic mythology|Celts]] and [[Balts]]. It occurred either in [[sacred grove]]s, at home, or at a simple altar of piled stones known as a &quot;[[horgr]].&quot; However, there seem to have been a few more important centres, such as [[Kaupang|Skiringssal]] in Norway, [[Lejre]] in Denmark and [[Gamla Uppsala|Uppsala]] in Sweden. [[Adam of Bremen]] claims that there was a [[temple at Uppsala]] with three wooden statues of Odin (the chief god), Thor (the god of thunder) and Freyr (the god of love).

===Priests===
While a kind of priesthood seems to have existed, it never took on the professional and semi-hereditary character of the Celtic [[Druidry|druid]]ical class. This was because the [[shamanistic]] tradition was maintained by women, the [[Völva]]s. It is often said that the [[Germanic king]]ship evolved out of a priestly office. This priestly role of the king was in line with the general role of [[gothi]], who was the head of a kindred group of families (for this social structure, see [[norse clans]]), and who administered the sacrifices.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}

===Human sacrifice===
[[File:Midvinterblot.jpeg|right|250px|thumb|&quot;[[Midvinterblot]]&quot; (1915) by [[Carl Larsson]].]]
A unique eye-witness account of Germanic [[human sacrifice]] survives in [[Ibn Fadlan]]'s account of a [[Rus' (people)|Rus]] [[ship burial]], where a slave-girl had volunteered to accompany her lord to the next world. More indirect accounts are given by [[Tacitus]], [[Saxo Grammaticus]] and [[Adam von Bremen]].

However, the [[Ibn Fadlan]] account is actually a burial ritual. Current understanding of Norse mythology suggests an ulterior motive to the slave-girl's 'sacrifice'. It is believed that in Norse mythology a woman who joined the corpse of a man on the funeral pyre would be that man's wife in the next world. For a slave girl to become the wife of a lord was an obvious increase in status.  Although both religions are of the Indo-European tradition, the sacrifice described in the [[Ibn Fadlan]] account is not to be confused with the practice of [[Sati (practice)|Sati]].

The ''Heimskringla'' tells of Swedish King [[Aun]] who sacrificed nine of his sons in an effort to prolong his life until his subjects stopped him from killing his last son [[Ongentheow|Egil]]. According to Adam of Bremen, the Swedish kings sacrificed male slaves every ninth year during the [[Yule]] sacrifices at the Temple at Uppsala. The Swedes had the right not only to elect kings but also to depose them, and both king [[Domalde]] and king [[Olof Trätälja]] are said to have been sacrificed after years of famine.
Odin, also known as all father, hung himself in order to gain his own knowledge, thereby allowing him to know all in the world. A possible practice of Odinic sacrifice by strangling has some archeological support in the existence of bodies such as [[Tollund Man]] that perfectly preserved by the acid of the [[Jutland]] [[peat]]bogs, into which they were cast after having been strangled. However, scholars possess no written accounts that explicitly interpret the cause of these stranglings, which could obviously have other explanations.

==Interactions with Christianity==
{{Off-topic|date=May 2011}}
[[File:Ansgarius predikar Christna läran i Sverige by Hugo Hamilton.jpg|thumb|&quot;Ansgarius predikar Christna läran i Sverige&quot; (1839) by Hugo Hamilton. An 1830 portrayal of [[Ansgar]], a Christian missionary invited to Sweden by its king [[Björn at Hauge]] in 829.]]
[[File:Sejdmen.jpg|thumb|One form of [[Execution (legal)|execution]] occurred during the Christianization of [[Norway]]. King [[Olaf Tryggvason]] had male [[völva]]s (sejdmen) tied and left on a [[skerry]] at ebb to drown in the sea. (1897 illustration by Halfdan Egedius)]]
{{See also|Christianization of Scandinavia}}

An important note in interpreting this mythology is that often the closest accounts that scholars have to &quot;pre-contact&quot; times were written by Christians. The ''Younger Edda'' and the ''Heimskringla'' were written by Snorri Sturluson in the 13th century, over two hundred years after Iceland became [[Christianized]].  This results in Snorri's works carrying a large amount of [[Euhemerism#Euhemerism and the Early Christians Christian Euhemerism|Euhemerism]].&lt;ref&gt;Faulkes, Anthony. &quot;Introduction&quot; In Snorri Sturlusson, ''Prose Edda'' (Ed.) page xviii. Everyman, 1987. ISBN 0-460-87616-3&lt;/ref&gt;

Virtually all of the saga literature came out of [[Iceland]], a relatively small and remote island, and even in the climate of religious tolerance there, Snorri was guided by an essentially Christian viewpoint. The ''[[Heimskringla]]'' provides some interesting insights into this issue. Snorri introduces Odin as a mortal warlord in Asia who acquires magical powers, settles in Sweden, and becomes a [[demi-god]] following his death. Having undercut Odin's divinity, Snorri then provides the story of a pact of Swedish King [[Aun]] with Odin to prolong his life by sacrificing his sons. Later in the Heimskringla, Snorri records in detail how converts to Christianity such as [[Saint Olaf]] Haraldsson brutally converted Scandinavians to Christianity.

Trying to avert civil war, the Icelandic parliament voted in Christianity, but for some years tolerated heathenry in the privacy of one's home. Sweden, on the other hand, had a series of civil wars in the 11th century, which ended with the burning of the [[Temple at Uppsala]].{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}} In [[England]], Christianization occurred earlier and sporadically, rarely by force. Conversion by coercion was sporadic throughout the areas where Norse gods had been worshipped. However, the conversion did not happen overnight. Christian clergy did their utmost to teach the populace that the Norse gods were demons, but their success was limited and the gods never became ''evil'' in the popular mind in most of Scandinavia.

The length of time Christianization took is illustrated by two centrally located examples of Lovön and Bergen. Archaeological studies of graves at the Swedish island of [[Lovön]] have shown that the Christianization took 150–200 years, and this was a location close to the kings and bishops. Likewise in the bustling trading town of Bergen, many runic inscriptions have been found from the 13th century, among the [[Bryggen inscriptions]]. One of them says ''may Thor receive you, may Odin own you'', and a second one is a [[galdra]] which says ''I carve curing runes, I carve salvaging runes, once against the elves, twice against the trolls, thrice against the [[Jötunn|thurs]]''. The second one also mentions the dangerous [[Valkyrie]] [[Skögul]]. Another contrast in Norse beliefs is the [[Gimle]], the supposed &quot;high heaven&quot;, which is thought to be a Christian addition to Norse mythology, and the [[Ragnarokk]], the &quot;fate&quot; of [[Æsir]] gods. This seems to be a Christian addition to the native mythology, since it ends the &quot;reign&quot; of the [[Æsir]] gods.

There are few accounts from the 14th to the 18th century, but the clergy, such as [[Olaus Magnus]] (1555) wrote about the difficulties of extinguishing the old beliefs. The story related in ''[[Þrymskviða]]'' appears to have been unusually resilient, like the romantic story of [[Hagbard and Signy]], and versions of both were recorded in the 17th century and as late as the 19th century. In the 19th and early 20th century Swedish folklorists documented what commoners believed, and what surfaced were many surviving traditions of the gods of Norse mythology. However, the traditions were by then far from the cohesive system of Snorri's accounts. Most gods had been forgotten and only the hunting Odin and the jötunn-slaying Thor figure in numerous legends. [[Freyja]] is mentioned a few times and Baldr only survives in legends about place names.

Other elements of Norse mythology survived without being perceived as such, especially concerning supernatural beings in [[Scandinavian folklore]]. Moreover, the Norse belief in destiny has been very firm until modern times. Since the Christian [[hell]] resembled the abode of the dead in Norse mythology one of the names was borrowed from the old faith, ''Helvíti'' i.e. ''Hel's punishment''. Many elements of the [[Yule]] traditions persevered, such as the Swedish tradition of slaughtering the pig at Christmas ([[Christmas ham]]), which originally was part of the sacrifice to Freyr.

==Modern influences==

{| style=&quot;float: right; margin: 1em 0 1em 1em&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Day (Old Norse)
! Meaning
|-
| Mánadagr || Moon's day
|-
| Týsdagr || Tyr's day
|-
| Óðinsdagr || Odin's day
|-
| Þórsdagr || Thor's day
|-
| Frjádagr || Freyja's day
|-
| Laugardagr || Washing day
|-
| Sunnudagr/Dróttinsdagr  || Sun's day/Lord's day
|}

The Nordic gods have left numerous traces in modern vocabulary and elements of every day western life in most [[North Germanic language]] speaking countries. An example of this is some of the names of the days of the week: modelled after the names of the days of the week in [[Latin]] (named after Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, and Saturn), the names for Tuesday through to Friday were replaced with Nordic equivalents of the Roman gods and the names for Monday and Sunday after the Sun and Moon. In Scandinavia, Saturday is called &quot;Lørdag&quot;, the &quot;Bath Day&quot;, in English and Dutch, &quot;Saturn&quot; was not replaced, while in German, Saturday was renamed after the definition of [[Biblical Sabbath|Sabbath]] (meaning the day of rest).

{|border=&quot;1&quot; cell-spacing=&quot;1&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
! style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; | Day
! style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; | Swedish 
! style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; | Danish/Norwegian 
! style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; | German
! style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; | Dutch
! style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot; | Origin
|-
|-
| [[Monday]]    ||  Måndag    ||  Mandag    ||  Montag   || Maandag   |||  Day of the [[Moon]]
|-
| [[Tuesday]]     ||  Tisdag  ||  Tirsdag  ||  Dienstag   || Dinsdag  |||  Day of [[Tyr]] (Swedish, Danish and Norwegian), day of the [[thing (assembly)]] (Dutch and German)
|-
| [[Wednesday]]    ||  Onsdag   ||  Onsdag   ||  Mittwoch  || Woensdag |||  Day of [[Odin]] (Woden or Wotan), middle of [[week]] (German)
|-
| [[Thursday]]    ||  Torsdag   ||  Torsdag   ||  Donnerstag  || Donderdag  |||  Day of [[Thor]]/Donar or [[thunder]] (both words derive from the same root)
|-
| [[Friday]]     ||  Fredag  ||  Fredag  ||  Freitag  || Vrijdag    |||  Day of [[Freyja]] or [[Frigg]]
|-
| [[Saturday]]          ||  Lördag  ||  Lørdag  || Samstag  || Zaterdag   ||| Day of [[Saturn]] (English and Dutch), day of bath (Swedish, Danish and Norwegian), [[Biblical Sabbath|Sabbath]] (German) 
|-
| [[Sunday]]         ||  Söndag  ||  Søndag  ||  Sonntag  || Zondag    |||  Day of the [[Sun]]
|}

===Viking revival===
[[File:Freya and Heimdall by Blommer.jpg|thumbnail|&quot;[[Heimdallr]] returns the necklace [[Brísingamen]] to [[Freyja]]&quot; by [[Swedish people|Swedish]] painter [[Nils Blommér]].]]
{{Main|Viking revival}}

Early modern editions of Old Norse literature  begins in the 16th century, e.g. ''Historia de gentibus septentrionalibus'' (Olaus Magnus, 1555) and the first edition of the
13th century ''[[Gesta Danorum]]'' ([[Saxo Grammaticus]]), in 1514. The pace of publication increased during the 17th century with Latin translations of the [[Edda]] (notably Peder Resen's ''Edda Islandorum'' of 1665). The renewed interest of [[Romanticism]] in the Old North had political implications and the [[Geatish Society]], of which poet and historian [[Erik Gustaf Geijer]] was a founder-member, popularized this myth to a great extent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wolf-Knuts|first=Ulrika|editor=Fabio Mugnaini, ''et al''|title=The Past in the Present. A Multidisciplinary Approach|year=2006|publisher=[[Coimbra Group]]|location=Florence, Italy|isbn=88-89726-01-6|pages=187–8|chapter=Folklorism, nostalga, and cultural heritage}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

A focus for early British enthusiasts was George Hicke, who published a ''Linguarum vett. septentrionalium thesaurus'' in 1703&amp;ndash;5. In the 1780s, [[Denmark]] offered to cede [[Iceland]] to Britain in exchange for [[Crab Island]]{{disambiguation needed|date=February 2012}} ([[West Indies]]), and in the 1860s Iceland was considered as a compensation for British support of Denmark in the [[Slesvig-Holstein]] conflicts. During this time, British interest and enthusiasm for Iceland and Nordic culture grew dramatically.'''

===Germanic Neopaganism===
{{Main|Germanic Neopaganism}}

Romanticist interest in the Old North gave rise to [[Ariosophy|Germanic mysticism]] involving various schemes of occultist &quot;[[Runology]]&quot;, notably following [[Guido von List]] and his ''[[Das Geheimnis der Runen]]'' (1908) in the early 20th century.

Since the 1970s, there have been revivals of the old Germanic religion as [[Germanic Neopaganism]] (''Ásatrú'') in both [[Europe]] and the [[United States]].

===Modern popular culture===
{{Main|Norse mythology in popular culture}}

Norse mythology influenced [[Richard Wagner]]'s use of literary themes from it to compose the four operas that make up ''[[Der Ring des Nibelungen]]'' (''The Ring of the Nibelung'').

The [[Viking metal]] music genre focuses on [[Viking age]] and Norse Mythology as inspiration for lyrics. Examples include [[Bathory (band)|Bathory]], [[Falkenbach]], among others. A broader definition of &quot;viking metal&quot; may also include Viking-themed or norse-themed Folk metal ([[Turisas]], [[Ensiferum]], [[Finntroll]], [[Týr (band)|Týr]]), Doom metal ([[Doomsword]]), and Death metal ([[Amon Amarth]]).

Subsequently, [[J. R. R. Tolkien]]'s writings, especially ''[[The Silmarillion]]''(Which was later written by Tolkein's son with his notes about middle-earth), were heavily influenced by the indigenous beliefs of the pre-Christian Northern Europeans. As his related novel ''[[The Lord of the Rings]]'' became popular, elements of its fantasy world moved steadily into popular perceptions of the fantasy genre. In many fantasy novels today can be found such Norse creatures as [[elf|elves]], [[Dwarf (Germanic mythology)|dwarves]], and [[Jötunn|frost jötnar]].

Another prominent appearance of Norse mythology in popular culture is in the [[Marvel Universe]]. In the Marvel Universe, the Norse [[wiktionary:Pantheon|Pantheon]] and related elements play a prominent part, especially [[Thor (Marvel Comics)|Thor]] who has been one of the longest running [[superhero]]es for the company. The Asgardians are interpreted as not being gods in a literal sense, but their godlike powers are of supernatural origin. This reinvention of the Norse deities has been featured in the [[Marvel Cinematic Universe]] film franchise and is the plot focus of the 2011 film ''[[Thor (film)|Thor]]'' and elaborated in the 2012 crossover film ''[[The Avengers (2012 film)|The Avengers]]'', and is yet to be explored further in the 2013 sequel ''[[Thor: The Dark World]]''.

There is also a video game series entitled [[The Elder Scrolls]] where one of the playable characters is a Norse-like race named the Nords who live in the northern province of Tamriel, Skyrim (Also the name of the fifth game in the series). The gameworld does include Giants, Elves, and a few [[ice age]] creatures.  The game includes folklore &amp; anthropology similar to that of the real pre-Christian Norse.  For instance, what would be Valhalla is called Sovngarde. Architecture of the Skyrim Nords is also heavily influenced by actual [[Norse architecture]].

The video game [[Max Payne]] contains many allusions to Norse mythology, particularly the myth of Ragnarök. Most of the elements in the game are named for figures from Norse mythology.

The fantasy novels [[Runemarks]] and [[Runelight]], by ''[[Chocolat (novel)|Chocolat]]'' author [[Joanne Harris]], are strongly influenced by Norse mythology and tell the story of surviving Norse gods in a world post-Ragnarok.

==See also==
{{Portal|Mythology}}
''Spelling of names in Norse mythology often varies depending on the nationality of the source material. For more information see [[Old Norse orthography]]''.
* [[Alliterative verse]]
* [[List of Germanic deities]]
* [[List of valkyrie names in Norse mythology]]
* [[Norse mythology in popular culture]]
* [[Numbers in Norse mythology]]
* [[Project Runeberg]]—a Nordic equivalent to [[Project Gutenberg]]
* [[Viking revival]]

=== Primary sources ===
* ''[[Gesta Danorum]]''
* ''[[Poetic Edda|The Poetic Edda]]''
* ''[[Prose Edda|The Prose Edda]]''
* ''[[Ynglinga saga]]''
* [[Saga]]s

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==

=== General secondary works ===
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{aut|Abram, Christopher}} (2011). ''Myths of the Pagan North: the Gods of the Norsemen''. London: Continuum. ISBN 978-1-84725-247-0.
* {{aut|Aðalsteinsson, Jón Hnefill}} (1998). ''A Piece of Horse Liver: Myth, Ritual and Folklore in Old Icelandic Sources'' (translated by Terry Gunnell &amp; [[Joan Turville-Petre]]). Reykjavík: Félagsvísindastofnun. ISBN 9979-54-264-0.
* {{aut|Andrén, Anders. Jennbert, Kristina. Raudvere, Catharina.}} (editors) (2006). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=gjq6rvoIRpAC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Old Norse Religion in Long-Term Perspectives: Origins, Changes and Interactions]''. Lund: Nordic Academic Press.  ISBN 91-89116-81-X.
* {{aut|Branston, Brian}} (1980). ''Gods of the North''. London: Thames and Hudson. (Revised from an earlier hardback edition of 1955). ISBN 0-500-27177-1.
* {{aut|Christiansen, Eric}} (2002). ''The Norsemen in the Viking Age''. Malden, Mass.: Blackwell. ISBN 1-4051-4964-7.
* {{aut|Clunies Ross, Margaret}} (1994). ''Prolonged Echoes: Old Norse Myths in Medieval Northern Society, vol. 1: The Myths''. Odense: Odense Univ. Press. ISBN 87-7838-008-1.
* {{aut|[[Hilda Ellis Davidson|Davidson, H. R. Ellis]]}} (1964). ''Gods and Myths of Northern Europe''. Baltimore: Penguin. New edition 1990 by Penguin Books. ISBN 0-14-013627-4. (Several [[runestone]]s)
* {{aut|[[Hilda Ellis Davidson|Davidson, H. R. Ellis]]}} (1969). ''Scandinavian Mythology''. London and New York: Hamlyn. ISBN 0-87226-041-0. Reissued 1996 as ''Viking and Norse Mythology''. New York: Barnes and Noble.
* {{aut|[[Hilda Ellis Davidson|Davidson, H. R. Ellis]]}} (1988). ''Myths and Symbols in Pagan Europe''. Syracuse, NY: Syracuse Univ. Press. ISBN 0-8156-2438-7.
* {{aut|[[Hilda Ellis Davidson|Davidson, H. R. Ellis]]}} (1993). ''The Lost Beliefs of Northern Europe''. London &amp; New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-04937-7.
* {{aut|[[Jan de Vries (linguist)|de Vries, Jan]].}} ''Altgermanische Religionsgeschichte'', 2 vols., 2nd. ed., Grundriss der germanischen Philologie, 12–13. Berlin: W. de Gruyter.
* {{aut|DuBois, Thomas A.}} (1999). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=g2-Lga0r62MC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Nordic+Religions+in+the+Viking+Age&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Nordic Religions in the Viking Age]''. Philadelphia: Univ. Pennsylvania Press. ISBN 0-8122-1714-4.
* {{aut|[[Georges Dumézil|Dumézil, Georges]]}} (1973). ''Gods of the Ancient Northmen''. Ed. &amp; trans. Einar Haugen. Berkeley: University of California Press. ISBN 0-520-03507-0.
* {{aut|[[Jacob Grimm|Grimm, Jacob]]}} (1888). ''Teutonic Mythology'', 4 vols. Trans. S. Stallybras. London. Reprinted 2003 by Kessinger. ISBN 0-7661-7742-4, ISBN 0-7661-7743-2, ISBN 0-7661-7744-0, ISBN 0-7661-7745-9. Reprinted 2004 Dover Publications. ISBN 0-486-43615-2 (4 vols.), ISBN 0-486-43546-6, ISBN 0-486-43547-4, ISBN 0-486-43548-2, ISBN 0-486-43549-0.
** [http://www.northvegr.org/lore/grimmst/index.php Northvegr: Grimm's Teutonic Mythology]
* {{aut|[[John Lindow|Lindow, John]]}} (1988). ''Scandinavian Mythology: An Annotated Bibliography'', Garland Folklore Bibliographies, 13. New York: Garland. ISBN 0-8240-9173-6.
* {{aut|[[John Lindow|Lindow, John]]}} (2001). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=KlT7tv3eMSwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Norse Mythology: A Guide to the Gods, Heroes, Rituals, and Beliefs]''. Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]]. ISBN 0-19-515382-0. (A dictionary of Norse mythology.)
* {{aut|Mirachandra}} (2006). ''Treasure of Norse Mythology Volume I'' ISBN 978-3-922800-99-6&lt;!--good ISBN - book in German--&gt;.
* {{aut|[[Lotte Motz|Motz, Lotte]]}} (1996). ''The King, the Champion and the Sorcerer: A Study in Germanic Myth''. Wien: Fassbaender. ISBN 3-900538-57-3.
* {{aut|O'Donoghue, Heather}} (2007). ''From Asgard to Valhalla  : the remarkable history of the Norse myths''. London: I. B. Tauris. ISBN 1-84511-357-8.
* {{aut|Orchard, Andy}} (1997). ''Cassell's Dictionary of Norse Myth and Legend''. London: Cassell. ISBN 0-304-36385-5.
* {{aut|Page, R. I.}} (1990). ''Norse Myths (The Legendary Past)''. London: British Museum; and Austin: University of Texas Press. ISBN 0-292-75546-5.
* {{aut|Price, Neil S}} (2002). ''The Viking Way: Religion and War in Late Iron Age Scandinavia''. Uppsala: Dissertation, Dept. Archaeology &amp; Ancient History. ISBN 91-506-1626-9.
* {{aut|Simek, Rudolf}} (1993). ''Dictionary of Northern Mythology''.  Trans. Angela Hall. Cambridge: D. S. Brewer. ISBN 0-85991-369-4. New edition 2000, ISBN 0-85991-513-1.
* {{aut|[[Karl Joseph Simrock|Simrock, Karl Joseph]]}} (1853–1855) ''Handbuch der deutschen Mythologie''.
* {{aut|Svanberg, Fredrik}} (2003). ''Decolonizing the Viking Age''. Stockholm: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell. ISBN 91-22-02006-3(v. 1); 9122020071(v. 2).
* {{aut|[[Gabriel Turville-Petre|Turville-Petre, E O Gabriel]]}} (1964). ''Myth and Religion of the North: The Religion of Ancient Scandinavia''. London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson. Reprinted 1975, Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press. ISBN 0-8371-7420-1.
{{Refend}}

===Romanticism===
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{aut|[[Rasmus B. Anderson|Anderson, Rasmus]]}} (1875).  ''Norse Mythology, or, The Religion of Our Forefathers''. Chicago: S.C. Griggs.
* {{aut|[[H. A. Guerber|Guerber, H. A.]]}} (1909). ''Myths of the Norsemen: From the Eddas and Sagas''. London: George&amp;nbsp;G. Harrap. Reprinted 1992, Mineola, N.Y.: Dover. ISBN 0-486-27348-2.
* {{aut|Keary, A &amp; E}} (1909), ''The Heroes of Asgard''. New York: Macmillan Company. Reprinted 1982 by Smithmark Pub. ISBN 0-8317-4475-8. Reprinted 1979 by Pan Macmillan ISBN 0-333-07802-0.
** [http://www.mainlesson.com/display.php?author=keary&amp;book=asgard&amp;story=_contents Baldwin Project: The Heroes of Asgard]
* {{aut|[[Hamilton Wright Mabie|Mable, Hamilton Wright]]}} (1901). ''Norse Stories Retold from the Eddas''. Mead and Company. Reprinted 1999, New York: Hippocrene Books. ISBN 0-7818-0770-0.
** [http://www.mainlesson.com/display.php?author=mabie&amp;book=norse&amp;story=_contents Baldwin Project: Norse Stories Retold from the Eddas]
* {{aut|Mackenzie, Donald A}} (1912). ''Teutonic Myth and Legend''. New York: W H Wise &amp; Co. 1934. Reprinted 2003 by University Press of the Pacific. ISBN 1-4102-0740-4.
** [http://www.sacred-texts.com/neu/tml/index.htm Sacred Texts: Teutonic Myth and Legend].
* {{aut|[[Viktor Rydberg|Rydberg, Viktor]]}} (1889). ''Teutonic Mythology'', trans. Rasmus B. Anderson. London: Swan Sonnenschein &amp; Co. Reprinted 2001, Elibron Classics. ISBN 1-4021-9391-2. Reprinted 2004, Kessinger Publishing Company. ISBN 0-7661-8891-4.
** [http://www.northvegr.org/lore/rydberg/index.php Rydberg's Teutonic Mythology] (Displayed by pages)
* {{aut|[[Laurence Waddell|Waddell, L. A.]]}} (1930). ''The British Edda''. London: Chapman &amp; Hall.
{{Refend}}

=== Modern retellings ===
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{aut|[[Padraic Colum|Colum, Padraic]]}} (1920). ''The Children of Odin: A Book of Northern Myths'', illustrated by [[Willy Pogány]]. New York, Macmillan. Reprinted 2004 by Aladdin, ISBN 0-689-86885-5.
** [http://www.sacred-texts.com/neu/ice/coo/index.htm Sacred Texts: The Children of Odin]. (Illustrated.)
* {{aut|[[Kevin Crossley-Holland|Crossley-Holland, Kevin]]}} (1981). ''The Norse Myths''. New York: Pantheon Books. ISBN 0-394-74846-8. Also released as ''The Penguin Book of Norse Myths: Gods of the Vikings''. Harmondsworth: Penguin. ISBN 0-14-025869-8.
* {{aut|[[Ingri and Edgar Parin d'Aulaire|d'Aulaire, Ingri and Edgar]]}} (1967). &quot;d'Aulaire's Book of Norse Myths&quot;. New York, New York Review of Books.
* {{aut|[[Peter Andreas Munch|Munch, Peter Andreas]]}} (1927). ''Norse Mythology: Legends of Gods and Heroes'', Scandinavian Classics. Trans. Sigurd Bernhard Hustvedt (1963). New York: American-Scandinavian Foundation. ISBN 0-404-04538-3.
**[http://www.vaidilute.com/books/munch/munch-contents.html etext of Munch]
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.heimskringla.no  Old Norse Prose and Poetry] (heimskringla.no)
*[http://www.hi.is/~eybjorn/ugm/skindex/skindex.html Jörmungrund: Skálda- &amp; vísnatal Norrœns Miðaldkveðskapar Index of Old Norse/Icelandic Skaldic Poetry] (in Icelandic)
*[http://www.septentrionalia.net/index.php Old texts in original languages]

{{Norse paganism topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Norse Mythology}}
[[Category:Norse mythology| ]]
[[Category:Vikings]]

{{Link GA|no}}
{{Link GA|sv}}
{{Link FA|es}}
{{Link FA|hr}}
[[ar:ميثولوجيا إسكندنافية]]
[[az:German-skandinav mifologiyası]]
[[be-x-old:Скандынаўская міталёгія]]
[[bg:Скандинавска митология]]
[[bs:Nordijska mitologija]]
[[ca:Mitologia nòrdica]]
[[cv:Скандинави халаплăхĕ]]
[[cs:Severská mytologie]]
[[da:Nordisk mytologi]]
[[de:Nordische Mythologie]]
[[et:Skandinaavia mütoloogia]]
[[el:Σκανδιναβική μυθολογία]]
[[es:Mitología nórdica]]
[[eo:Nord-ĝermana mitologio]]
[[eu:Eskandinaviar mitologia]]
[[fa:اساطیر اسکاندیناوی]]
[[fo:Ásatrúgv]]
[[fr:Mythologie nordique]]
[[gl:Mitoloxía nórdica]]
[[ko:북유럽 신화]]
[[hy:Սկանդինավյան դիցաբանություն]]
[[hr:Nordijska mitologija]]
[[id:Mitologi Nordik]]
[[ia:Mythologia nordic]]
[[is:Norræn goðafræði]]
[[it:Mitologia norrena]]
[[he:מיתולוגיה נורדית]]
[[ka:სკანდინავიური მითოლოგია]]
[[la:Religio Germanica]]
[[lv:Skandināvu mitoloģija]]
[[lt:Skandinavų mitologija]]
[[hu:Skandináv mitológia]]
[[mk:Нордиска митологија]]
[[ms:Mitos Norse]]
[[nl:Noordse mythologie]]
[[ja:北欧神話]]
[[no:Norrøn mytologi]]
[[nn:Norrøn gudelære]]
[[nov:Skandinavi mitologia]]
[[pl:Mitologia nordycka]]
[[pt:Mitologia nórdica]]
[[ro:Mitologie nordică]]
[[ru:Германо-скандинавская мифология]]
[[sco:Norse Meethology]]
[[sk:Severská mytológia]]
[[sl:Nordijska mitologija]]
[[sr:Нордијска митологија]]
[[fi:Skandinaavinen muinaisusko]]
[[sv:Nordisk mytologi]]
[[tl:Mitolohiyang Nordiko]]
[[ta:நோர்சு தொன்மவியல்]]
[[th:เทพปกรณัมนอร์ส]]
[[tr:İskandinav mitolojisi]]
[[uk:Скандинавська міфологія]]
[[vi:Thần thoại Bắc Âu]]
[[zh:北欧神话]]</text>
      <sha1>p4yaa7ujj7sgxuxycjwogwk6ypiahky</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
