<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Old Testament</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22326</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521561154</id>
      <parentid>521561137</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T20:30:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/174.228.68.133|174.228.68.133]] to version by Anbu121. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1316433) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34149">{{About|[[Christian Bible]]|the Jewish [[Tanakh]]|Hebrew Bible}}
{{Christianity|state=collapsed}}
{{Bible related}}

The '''Old Testament''' is a Christian term for a collection of religious writings of [[Israelites|ancient Israel]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones 2001, p.215&quot;&gt;Jones (2001), p.215&lt;/ref&gt; that form the major and first section of [[Christian Bible]]s, in contrast to the Christian [[New Testament]] which deals explicitly with the [[Christianity in the 1st century|1st century Christianity]]. The [[Development of the Hebrew Bible canon|Hebrew Canon]] approved by [[Rabbinic Judaism]] included only certain [[Biblical Hebrew|Hebrew]]/[[Biblical Aramaic|Aramaic]] books but not all. Some of these [[scriptures]] vary markedly between differing [[Christian denominations]]; [[Protestants]] accept only the [[Hebrew Bible]]'s canon but divide it into 39 books, while [[Catholics]], the [[Eastern Orthodox]], [[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria|Coptic]] and [[Ethiopian church]]es recognise a considerably larger collection.&lt;ref&gt;Barton (2001), p.3&lt;/ref&gt;

The books can be broadly divided into the [[Pentateuch]], which tells how God selected Israel to be his [[chosen people]]; the history books telling the history of the [[Israelite]]s from their [[conquest of Canaan]] to their [[Babylonian exile|defeat and exile in Babylon]]; the poetic and &quot;wisdom&quot; books dealing, in various forms, with [[Ethics|questions of good and evil in the world]]; and the [[Nevi'im|books of the biblical prophets]], warning of the consequences of turning away from God. For the Israelites who were its original authors and readers these books told of their own unique relationship with God and their relationship with [[proselytes]], but the overarching [[Messiah|messianic]] nature of Christianity has led Christians from the [[Early Christianity|very beginning of the faith]] to see the Old Testament as a [[Typology (theology)|preparation]] for the [[New Covenant]] and [[New Testament]].

==Content==
{{main|Biblical canon}}
The Old Testament contains 39 (Protestant) or 46 (Catholic) or more (Orthodox and other) books, divided, very broadly, into the [[Pentateuch]] (meaning &quot;five books&quot;), the historical books, the [[Sapiential Books|&quot;wisdom&quot; books]] and the prophets.&lt;ref&gt;Boadt (1984), pp.11, 15-16&lt;/ref&gt; The difference of seven books between the Catholic and Protestant canons stems from the fact that the early Christians used a Greek translation of the Jewish scriptures, called the [[Septuagint]].&lt;ref&gt;Boadt (1984), p.18&lt;/ref&gt; The Protestant churches later dropped those books which were not accepted by the Jews. The following table shows the arrangement of the holy books in the [[Tanach|Jewish Bible]] and the Old Testament ''(Jewish bibles count 24 books, as shown here, but Christian bibles divide Samuel, Kings, Chronicles, Ezra-Nehemiah and the Minor Prophets, bringing the total to 39; books additional to the Hebrew Bible in italics):''&lt;ref&gt;Barton (2001), p.11&lt;/ref&gt; 
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!width=&quot;20%&quot; |Hebrew Bible
!width=&quot;20%&quot; |Greek Bible
!width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;align: left;&quot;|Notes
|-style=&quot;text-align:left; vertical-align:top;&quot;
! Torah (Law)
! Pentateuch
|
|-style=&quot;text-align:left; vertical-align:top;&quot;
| Genesis&lt;br /&gt;Exodus&lt;br /&gt;Leviticus&lt;br /&gt;Numbers&lt;br /&gt;Deuteronomy
| Genesis&lt;br /&gt;Exodus&lt;br /&gt;Leviticus&lt;br /&gt;Numbers&lt;br /&gt;Deuteronomy
|width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;align: left;&quot;| 
|-style=&quot;text-align:left; vertical-align:top;&quot;
! Prophets
! History
|
|-style=&quot;text-align:left; vertical-align:top;&quot;
| Joshua&lt;br /&gt;Judges&lt;br /&gt;Samuel&lt;br /&gt;Kings&lt;br /&gt;Isaiah&lt;br /&gt;Jeremiah&lt;br /&gt;Ezekiel&lt;br /&gt;Minor Prophets (single book)
| Joshua&lt;br /&gt;Judges&lt;br /&gt;Ruth&lt;br /&gt;1 Samuel&lt;br /&gt;2 Samuel&lt;br /&gt;1 Kings&lt;br /&gt;2 Kings&lt;br /&gt;1 Chronicles&lt;br /&gt;2 Chronicles&lt;br /&gt;''1 Esdras''&lt;br /&gt;Ezra&lt;br /&gt;Nehemiah&lt;br /&gt;Esther ''(with additions)''&lt;br /&gt;''Judith''&lt;br /&gt;''Tobit''&lt;br /&gt;''1-4 Maccabees''
|The Prophets collection in the Hebrew Bible get its name because the books were attributed to prophets, not because they all contain prophecy. Ruth, Chronicles, Ezra and Nehemiah, have been moved from the Writings collection in the Hebrew Bible to the History collection in the Old Testament, as the organising principle is subject matter rather than authorship.

&quot;Minor prophets&quot; means short, not unimportant.
|-style=&quot;text-align:left; vertical-align:top;&quot;
! Writings
! Wisdom
|
|-style=&quot;text-align:left; vertical-align:top;&quot;
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | Psalms&lt;br /&gt;Job&lt;br /&gt;Proverbs&lt;br /&gt;Ruth&lt;br /&gt;Song of Songs&lt;br /&gt;Ecclesiastes&lt;br /&gt;Lamentations&lt;br /&gt;Esther&lt;br /&gt;Daniel&lt;br /&gt;Ezra-Nehemiah&lt;br /&gt;Chronicles
|Psalms&lt;br /&gt;Proverbs&lt;br /&gt;Ecclesiastes&lt;br /&gt;Song of Songs&lt;br /&gt;Job&lt;br /&gt;''Wisdom of Solomon''&lt;br /&gt;''Ecclesiasticus''
|Chronicles is the last book in the Hebrew canon, showing Israel restored to Jerusalem and history at an end; in the Old Testament it is part of the ongoing history which will end in the New Testament.

Rabbi Tovia Singer said that it was done so to stipulate that Jesus of Nazareth was the [[Christ|Christian Messiah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Singer|first=Rabbi Tovia|title=Let's get Biblical Audio|url=http://www.outreachjudaism.org/faq|publisher=outreachjudaism.org|accessdate=2 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-style=&quot;text-align:left; vertical-align:top;&quot;
! Prophets
|
|-style=&quot;text-align:left; vertical-align:top;&quot;
|Minor prophets (12 books)&lt;br /&gt;Isaiah&lt;br /&gt;Jeremiah&lt;br /&gt;''Baruch''&lt;br /&gt;Lamentations&lt;br /&gt;''Letter of Jeremiah''&lt;br /&gt;Ezekiel&lt;br /&gt;''Susannah''&lt;br /&gt;Daniel ''(with additions)''
| The order of the prophets has been reversed in modern Old Testaments so the last words are those of the minor prophet Malachi, predicting the return of the prophet Elijah and &quot;the coming of the great and dreadful day of the {{Sc|L|ORD}}&quot; (Malachi 4:5).
|}

==Composition==
The first five books - [[book of Genesis|Genesis]], [[book of Exodus|Exodus]], [[Leviticus]], [[book of Numbers]] and [[Deuteronomy]] - make up the [[Torah]], the story of Israel from the [[Genesis creation narrative]] to the death of [[Moses]]. Few scholars today doubt that it reached its present form in the [[Yehud Medinata|Persian period (538-332 BC)]], and that its authors were the elite of exilic returnees who controlled the [[Second Temple|Temple at that time]].&lt;ref&gt;Blenkinsopp (1998), p.184&lt;/ref&gt; The books of [[book of Joshua|Joshua]], [[book of Judges|Judges]], [[books of Samuel|Samuel]] and [[books of Kings|Kings]] follow, forming a history of Israel from the [[Conquest of Canaan]] to the [[Siege of Jerusalem (587 BC)|Siege of Jerusalem c.587 BC]]: there is a broad consensus among scholars that these originated as a single work (the so-called &quot;[[Deuteronomistic history]]&quot;) during the [[Babylonian exile]] of the 6th century BC.&lt;ref&gt;Rogerson (2003), pp.153-154&lt;/ref&gt; The two [[Books of Chronicles]] cover much the same material as the Pentateuch and Deuteronomistic history and probably date from the 4th century BC.&lt;ref&gt;Coggins (2003), p.282&lt;/ref&gt; Chronicles links with the books of [[Ezra-Nehemiah|Ezra and Nehemiah]], which were probably finished during the 3rd century BC.&lt;ref&gt;Grabbe (2003), pp.213-214&lt;/ref&gt; Catholic and Orthodox Old Testaments contain two (Catholic Old Testament) to four (Orthodox) [[Books of Maccabees]], written in the 2nd and 1st centuries BC.

The history books make up around half the total content of the Old Testament. Of the remainder, the books of the various prophets - [[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]], [[Book of Jeremiah|Jeremiah]], [[Book of Ezekiel|Ezekiel]], [[Book of Daniel|Daniel]] and the twelve &quot;[[minor prophets]]&quot; - were written between the 8th and 6th centuries BC, with the exceptions of [[Book of Jonah|Jonah]] and [[Book of Daniel|Daniel]], which were written much later.&lt;ref&gt;Miller (1987), pp.10-11&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;wisdom&quot; and other books - [[Book of Job|Job]], [[Book of Proverbs|Proverbs]] and so on - date from between the 5th century BC and the 2nd or 1st BC, with the exception of some of the [[Psalms]].&lt;ref&gt;Crenshaw (2010), p.5&lt;/ref&gt;

==Themes==
God is consistently depicted as the one who created the world and guides its history. He is not, however, consistently presented as the only god who exists. Nevertheless, he is always depicted as the only God whom Israel is to worship, and both Jews and Christians have always interpreted the bible as an affirmation of the oneness of God.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton 2001, p.9&quot;&gt;Barton (2001), p.9&lt;/ref&gt;

The Old Testament stresses the special relationship between God and his [[chosen people]], Israel, but includes instructions for [[proselyte]]s as well. This relationship is expressed in the [[biblical covenant]] (contract) between the two, received by Moses. The law codes in books such as [[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] and especially [[Deuteronomy]] are the terms of the contract: Israel swears faithfulness to [[Yahweh]], and God swears to be Israel's special protector and supporter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton 2001, p.9&quot;/&gt;

Further themes in the Old Testament include salvation, redemption, judgement, obedience and disobedience, faith and faithfulness, among others. Throughout there is a strong emphasis on ethics and ritual purity, both of which God demands, although some of the prophets and wisdom writers seem to question this, arguing that God demands social justice above purity, and perhaps does not even care about purity at all. The Old Testament's moral code enjoins fairness, intervention on behalf of the vulnerable, and the duty of those in power to administer justice righteously. It forbids murder, bribery and corruption, deceitful trading, and many sexual misdemeanors. All morality is traced back to God, who is the source of all goodness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton 2001, p.10&quot;&gt;Barton (2001), p.10&lt;/ref&gt; 

The question of evil plays a large part in the Old Testament. The problem the Old Testament authors faced was that a good God must have had just reason for bringing disaster (meaning notably, but not only, the Babylonian exile) upon his people. The theme is played out, with many variations, in books as different as the histories of Kings and Chronicles, the prophets like Ezekiel and Jeremiah, and in the wisdom books like Job and Ecclesiates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton 2001, p.10&quot;/&gt;

==From scripture to canon: formation of the Old Testament==
{{Main|Books of the Bible|Biblical canon}}
[[File:TextsOT.PNG|thumb|right|350px|The interrelationship between various significant ancient manuscripts of the Old Testament, according to the [[Encyclopaedia Biblica|Encyclopaedia Biblica (1903)]] Some manuscripts are identified by their [[Scribal abbreviation|siglum]]. LXX here denotes the original Septuagint.]]

===Greek, Latin and Protestant Old Testaments===
{{See also|Development of the Old Testament canon|Septuagint#Table of books|Development of the Hebrew Bible canon|Books of the Latin Vulgate}}
The process by which scriptures became canons and Bibles was a long one, and its complexities account for the many different Old Testaments which exist today. By about the 5th century BC Jews saw the five books of the [[Torah]] (the Old Testament Pentateuch) as having authoritative status; by the 2nd century BC the Prophets had a similar status, although without quite the same level of respect as the Torah; beyond that, the Jewish scriptures were fluid, with different groups seeing authority in different books.&lt;ref&gt;Brettler (2005), p.274&lt;/ref&gt;

The scriptures were translated into Greek between about 280-130 BC.&lt;ref&gt;Gentry (2008), p.302&lt;/ref&gt; At this stage (i.e., around the time of Christ) there was no collection of these scriptures - the various texts were read as separate scrolls. It was only in the early centuries of the Christian era that the scriptures began to be bound together into books and that Bibles as we know them today came to be invented. The Greek translations, called the [[Septuagint]], contained several books (using that term loosely) not found in the modern Hebrew Bible (1-2 [[Esdras]], [[Judith]], [[Book of Tobit|Tobit]], 1-4 [[Books of the Maccabees|Maccabees]], [[Wisdom of Solomon]], [[Sirach]], [[Baruch]], and numerous additions to other books), based loosely on chronology and &quot;literary typology&quot; (i.e. subject matter).&lt;ref&gt;Jones (2001), p.216&lt;/ref&gt; It continues in use to this day as the Old Testament of the [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox Church]].&lt;ref&gt;Würthwein (1995)&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 331, [[Constantine I and Christianity|Constantine I]] commissioned [[Eusebius]] to deliver [[Fifty Bibles of Constantine|fifty Bibles]] for the [[Church of Constantinople]]. [[Athanasius]]&lt;ref&gt;''Apol. Const. 4''&lt;/ref&gt; recorded [[Early centers of Christianity#Alexandria|Alexandrian]] scribes around 340 preparing Bibles for [[Constans]]. Little else is known, though there is plenty of speculation. For example, it is speculated that this may have provided motivation for canon lists, and that [[Codex Vaticanus]] and [[Codex Sinaiticus]] are examples of these Bibles. Together with the [[Peshitta]] and [[Codex Alexandrinus]], these are the earliest extant Christian Bibles.&lt;ref&gt;''The Canon Debate'', pages 414-415, for the entire paragraph&lt;/ref&gt;  There is no evidence among the [[First Council of Nicaea#The biblical canon|canons of the First Council of Nicaea of any determination on the canon]], however, [[Jerome]] (347-420), in his ''Prologue to Judith'', makes the claim that the [[Book of Judith]] was &quot;found by the Nicene Council to have been counted among the number of the Sacred Scriptures&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle=Book of Judith}}: Canonicity: &quot;...&quot;the Synod of Nicaea is said to have accounted it as Sacred Scripture&quot; (Praef. in Lib.). It is true that no such declaration is to be found in the Canons of Nicaea, and it is uncertain whether St. Jerome is referring to the use made of the book in the discussions of the council, or whether he was misled by some spurious canons attributed to that council&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Western Christianity]] or Christianity in the [[Western Roman Empire|Western half of the Roman Empire]], Latin had displaced Greek as the common language of the early Christians, and about 400 AD Pope [[Damasus I]] commissioned [[Jerome]], the leading scholar of the day, to produce an updated Latin bible to replace the [[Vetus Latina]]. Sometime in the centuries after the Septuagint (exactly when is disputed) the [[Rabbis]] (Jewish religious scholars and teachers) [[Development of the Hebrew Bible canon|defined the Jewish canon]], which is a much shorter canon of only 24 books, and Jerome used it (commonly called the [[Hebrew Bible]]) instead of the Greek Old Testament as the basis for his translation, citing &quot;Hebraica Veritas&quot; (Latin: Truth of the Hebrew). His [[Vulgate]] (i.e. common language) Old Testament became the standard bible used in the [[Western Christianity|Western Church]], specifically as the [[Sixto-Clementine Vulgate]], while the [[Eastern Christianity|Churches in the East]] continued, and still continue, to use the Septuagint.&lt;ref&gt;Würthwein (1995), pp.91-99&lt;/ref&gt;

Jerome had wanted to drop all the books that did not appear in the Hebrew Bible, but [[St Augustine]], a bishop and another great scholar of the day, opposed him and won the argument, notably at the [[Council of Carthage]] on 28 August 397. In the 16th century the Protestant reformers reopened the debate, and sided with Jerome, but only for their own congregations: yet although Protestant Bibles now have only those books that appear in the Jewish Bible, they have them in the order of the Greek Bible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton 1997, pp.80-81&quot;&gt;Barton (1997), pp.80-81&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic Church, largely in reaction to this attack on tradition, officially adopted a canon, the [[Canon of Trent]], which can be seen as following Augustine's Carthaginian Councils or the [[Council of Rome]],&lt;ref&gt;Augustine's &quot;2 of Esdras&quot; could be [[1 Esdras]] and Ezra-Nehemiah as in the [[Septuagint]] and Orthodox canon or [[Book of Ezra|Ezra]] and [[Book of Nehemiah|Nehemiah]] as in the [[Vulgate]] and Catholic canon.&lt;/ref&gt; and includes most, but not all, of the Septuagint ([[3 Ezra]] and 3 and 4 [[Maccabees]] are excluded);&lt;ref&gt;Soggin (1987), p.19&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Anglican]]s after the [[English Civil War]] adopted a compromise position, restoring the [[39 Articles]] and keeping the extra books that were excluded by the [[Westminster Confession of Faith]], but only for private study and for [[Anglican Liturgy|reading in churches]], while [[Lutheran]]s kept them for private study, gathered in an appendix as [[Biblical Apocrypha]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Barton 1997, pp.80-81&quot;/&gt;

===Other versions===
While the Hebrew, Greek and Latin versions of the Hebrew Bible are the best known Old Testaments, there were others. At much the same time as the Septuagint was being produced, translations were being made into Aramaic, the language of Jews living in Palestine and the Near East and likely the [[Aramaic of Jesus|language of Jesus]]: these are called the Aramaic [[Targum]]s, from a word meaning &quot;translation&quot;, and were used to help Jewish congregations understand their scriptures. For Aramaic Christians there was a [[Syriac]] translation of the Hebrew Bible called the [[Peshitta]], as well as versions in [[Coptic language|Coptic]] (the everyday language of Egypt in the first Christian centuries, descended from ancient Egyptian), [[Ethiopic]] (for use in the Ethiopian church, one of the oldest Christian churches), [[Armenian people|Armenian]] (Armenia, a former kingdom, now part of modern northeast Turkey, was the first to adopt Christianity as its official religion), and [[Arabic]].&lt;ref&gt;Würthwein (1995), pp.79-90, 100-104&lt;/ref&gt;

==Christian theology and the Old Testament==
{{Main|Christian views on the old covenant}}
Christianity is based on the claim that the [[historical Jesus]] was also the supernatural [[Christ]], the Saviour. This claim is in turn based on Jewish understandings of the meaning of the Hebrew term [[messiah]], which, like the Greek &quot;Christ&quot;, means &quot;anointed&quot;. In the Hebrew Scriptures it describes a king anointed with oil on his accession to the throne: he becomes &quot;The LORD's anointed&quot; or [[Yahweh]]'s Anointed. By the time of Jesus, some Jews{{who|date=August 2012}} expected that a flesh and blood descendant of David (the &quot;[[Son of David]]&quot;) would come to establish a real Jewish kingdom in Jerusalem, instead of the [[Iudaea province|Roman province]]; others{{who|date=August 2012}} stressed the [[Son of Man]], a distinctly other-worldly figure who would appear as a [[Last judgment|judge at the end of time]]; and some{{who|date=August 2012}} harmonised the two by expecting a this-worldly messianic kingdom which would last for a set period and be followed by the other-worldly age or [[World to Come]]. Some{{who|date=August 2012}} thought the Messiah was already present, but unrecognised due to Israel's sins; some{{who|date=August 2012}} thought that the Messiah would be announced by a fore-runner, probably [[Elijah]] (as promised by the prophet Malachi, whose book now ends the Old Testament and precedes [[Gospel of Mark|Mark]]'s account of [[John the Baptist]]). None predicted a Messiah who suffers and dies for the sins of all the people.&lt;ref&gt;Farmer (1991), pp.570-571&lt;/ref&gt; The story of Jesus' death therefore involved a profound shift in meaning from the tradition of the Old Testament.&lt;ref&gt;Juel (2000), pp.236-239&lt;/ref&gt;

The name &quot;Old Testament&quot; reflects Christianity's understanding of itself as the [[Supersessionism|fulfillment]] of Jeremiah's prophesy of a [[New Covenant]] (which is similar to &quot;testament&quot; and often conflated) to replace the existing [[Covenant (biblical)|covenant]] between God and Israel (Jeremiah 31:31).&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones 2001, p.215&quot;/&gt; The emphasis, however, has shifted from Judaism's understanding of the covenant as an eternal contract between God and Israel to one between God and those who are &quot;in Christ&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Herion (2000), pp.291-292&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Abrogation of Old Covenant laws]]
* [[Book of Job in Byzantine illuminated manuscripts]]
* [[Books of the Bible]]
* [[Covenant (biblical)]]
* [[Expounding of the Law]]
* [[Hebrew Bible: Timeline]]
* [[Law and Gospel]]
* [[List of ancient legal codes]]
* [[List of Hebrew Bible manuscripts]]
* [[Non-canonical books referenced in the Bible]]
* [[Quotations from the Hebrew Bible in the New Testament]]
* [[Supersessionism]]
* [[Biblical narratives and the Quran]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{Cite book|last=Bandstra|first=Barry L|title=Reading the Old Testament: an introduction to the Hebrew Bible|publisher=Wadsworth|year=2004|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=vRY9mTUZKJcC&amp;pg=PA489&amp;lpg=PA489&amp;dq=Bandstra,+Barry+L+%282004%29.+Reading+the+Old+Testament:+an+introduction+to+the+Hebrew+Bible&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Barton|first=John|title=How the Bible came to be|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1997|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=UfU4_9M4N2YC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=How+the+Bible+came+to+be+Barton&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Barton|first=John|chapter=Introduction to the Old Testament|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=3surkLVdw3UC&amp;pg=PA6&amp;dq=B.+Collecting+the+Hebrew+Scriptures&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q=B.%20Collecting%20the%20Hebrew%20Scriptures&amp;f=false|editor=John Barton, John Muddiman|title=Oxford Bible Commentary|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2001}}
*{{Cite book|last=Blenkinsopp|first=Joseph|chapter=The Pentateuch|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=PSHCRgS_SAUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Cambridge+companion+to+biblical+interpretation&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=John Barton|title=The Cambridge companion to biblical interpretation|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1998}}
*{{Cite book|last=Boadt|first=Lawrence|title=Reading the Old Testament: an introduction|publisher=Paulist Press|year=1984|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=LGQNT6G_do8C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Reading+the+Old+Testament:+an+introduction&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Brettler|first=Marc Zvi|title=How to read the Bible|publisher=Jewish Publication Society|year=2005|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=39nQafdJ_ssC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Brettler+how+to+read+the+bible&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Bultman|first=Christoph|chapter=Deuteronomy|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=3surkLVdw3UC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Oxford+Bible+commentary&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=Deuteronomy&amp;f=false|editor=John Barton, John Muddiman|title=Oxford Bible Commentary|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2001}}
*{{Cite book|last=Coggins|first=Richard J|chapter=1 and 2 Chronicles|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA153&amp;lpg=PA153&amp;dq=Chronicles+Richard+J+Coggins&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=Deuteronomy%20John%20W%20Rogerson&amp;f=false|editor=James D. G. Dunn and John William Rogerson|title=Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003}}
*{{Cite book|last=Crenshaw|first=James L|title=Old Testament wisdom: an introduction|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=2010|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=tKpWNrkO8dEC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Old+Testament+wisdom:+an+introduction++By+James+L.+Crenshaw&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Davies|first=G.I|chapter=Introduction to the Pentateuch|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=3surkLVdw3UC&amp;pg=PA12&amp;dq=Oxford+Bible+Commentary+Introduction+to+the+Pentateuch&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q=Oxford%20Bible%20Commentary%20Introduction%20to%20the%20Pentateuch&amp;f=false|editor=John Barton|title=Oxford Bible Commentary|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1998}}
*{{Cite book|last=Dines|first=Jennifer M|title=The Septuagint|publisher=Continuum|year=2004|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=Qv8Riv3QIbQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Dines+Septuagint&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Farmer|first=Ron|chapter=Messiah/Christ|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=goq0VWw9rGIC&amp;pg=PA570&amp;cad=3#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=Watson E. Mills, Roger Aubrey Bullard|title=Mercer dictionary of the Bible|publisher=Mercer University Press|year=1991}}
*{{Cite book|last=Gentry|first=Peter R|chapter=Old Greek and Later Revisors|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=NoCJKyxEujEC&amp;pg=PA301&amp;dq=Old+Greek+and+Later+Revisors:+Can+we+always+distinguish+them?&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q=Old%20Greek%20and%20Later%20Revisors%3A%20Can%20we%20always%20distinguish%20them%3F&amp;f=false|editor=Raija Sollamo, Anssi Voitila, Jutta Jokiranta|title=Scripture in transition|publisher=Brill|year=2008}}
*{{Cite book|last=Grabbe|first=Lester L|chapter=Ezra|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA153&amp;lpg=PA153&amp;dq=Deuteronomy+John+W+Rogerson&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=Deuteronomy%20John%20W%20Rogerson&amp;f=false|editor=James D. G. Dunn and John William Rogerson|title=Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003}}
*{{Cite book|last=Hasel|first=Gerhard F|title=Old Testament theology: basic issues in the current debate|publisher=Eerdmans|year=1991|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=yJJ6bE0kt1YC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Old+Testament+theology&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Herion|first=Gary A|chapter=Covenant|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=qRtUqxkB7wkC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=Old%20Testament&amp;f=false|editor=David Noel Freedman|title=Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2000}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Jobes|first1=Karen H|last2=Silva|first2=Moises|title=Invitation to the Septuagint|publisher=Baker Academic|year=2005}}
*{{Cite book|last=Jones|first=Barry A|chapter=Canon of the Old Testament|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=qRtUqxkB7wkC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=Old%20Testament&amp;f=false|editor=David Noel Freedman|title=Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2000}}
*{{Cite book|last=Juel|first=Donald|chapter=Christ|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=qRtUqxkB7wkC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Eerdmans+Dictionary+of+the+Bible&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=David Noel Freedman|title=Eerdmans Dictionary of the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2000}}
*{{Cite book|last=McLay|first=Tim|title=The use of the Septuagint in New Testament research|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=41rx-TDIF9gC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Use+of+the+Septuagint+in+New+Testament+Research&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Miller|first=John W|title=How the Bible came to be|publisher=Paulist Press|year=2004|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=a4VnOt-jstoC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Miller|first=John W|title=Meet the prophets: a beginner's guide to the books of the biblical prophets|publisher=Paulist Press|year=1987|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=mHXM3wjVP-gC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Meet+the+prophets:+a+beginner%27s+guide+to+the+books+of+the+biblical+prophets&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Rogerson|first=John W|chapter=Deuteronomy|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA153&amp;lpg=PA153&amp;dq=Deuteronomy+John+W+Rogerson&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=Deuteronomy%20John%20W%20Rogerson&amp;f=false|editor=James D. G. Dunn and John William Rogerson|title=Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003}}
*{{Cite book|last=Schniedewind|first=William M|title=How the Bible Became a Book|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=tCTVc8_2vVQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=How+the+Bible+Became+a+Book&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|publisher=Cambridge|year=2004}}
*{{Cite book|last=Soggin|first=J. Alberto|title=Introduction to the Old Testament|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1987|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=mqSNsKXnHQgC&amp;pg=PA40&amp;dq=Soggin+Hebrew+bible&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q=Soggin%20Hebrew%20bible&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Würthwein|first=Ernst|title=The text of the Old Testament: an introduction to the Biblia Hebraica|publisher=Eerdmans|year=1995|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=FSNKSBObCYwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=W%C3%BCrthwein+The+Text+of+the+Old+Testament&amp;ct=book-thumbnail#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}

==Further reading==
* [[Bernhard Anderson|Anderson, Bernhard]]. ''Understanding the Old Testament''. (ISBN 0-13-948399-3 )
* Bahnsen, Greg, et al., ''Five Views on Law and Gospel''. (Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 1993).
* Berkowitz, Ariel and D'vorah. ''Torah Rediscovered''. 4th ed. Shoreshim Publishing, 2004. ISBN 0-9752914-0-8
* Dever, William G. ''Who Were the Early Israelites?'' William B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., Grand Rapids, MI, 2003. ISBN 0-8028-0975-8
* [[Gerhard von Rad]]: ''Theologie des Alten Testaments.'' Band 1–2, München, 8. Auflage 1982/1984, ISBN
* Hill, Andrew and John Walton. ''A Survey of the Old Testament.'' 2nd ed. Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 2000. ISBN 0-310-22903-0 .
* Kuntz, John Kenneth. ''The People of Ancient Israel: an introduction to Old Testament Literature, History, and Thought'', Harper and Row, 1974. ISBN 0-06-043822-3
* Lancaster, D. Thomas. ''Restoration: Returning the Torah of God to the Disciples of Jesus.'' Littleton: First Fruits of Zion, 2005.
* Rouvière, Jean-Marc. ''Brèves méditations sur la Création du monde'' Ed. L'Harmattan, Paris, 2006
* Salibi, Kamal. ''The Bible Came from Arabia'', London, Jonathan Cape, 1985 ISBN 0-224-02830-8
* Schmid, Konrad. ''The Old Testament: A Literary History'',Fortress Press, Minneapolis, 2012. ISBN 978-0-8006-9775-4
* Silberman, Neil A., et al. ''The Bible Unearthed''. Simon and Schuster, New York, 2003. ISBN 0-684-86913-6 (paperback) and ISBN 0-684-86912-8 (hardback)
* Sprinkle, Joe M. ''Biblical Law and Its Relevance: A Christian Understanding and Ethical Application for Today of the Mosaic Regulations.'' Lanham, MD: University Press of America, 2006. ISBN 0-7618-3371-4 (clothbound) and ISBN 0-7618-3372-2 (paperback)
* Papadaki-Oekland, Stella. Byzantine Illuminated Manuscripts of the Book of Job. ISBN 2-503-53232-2 &amp; ISBN 978-2-503-53232-5

==External links==
* [http://www.churchfathers.org/category/scripture-and-tradition/old-testament-canon/ Church Fathers on the Old Testament Canon]
* [http://www.biblegateway.com/ Full texts of the Old (and New) Testaments including full Catholic canon]
* [http://www.lafeuilledolivier.com/Ecritures/OT.htm Protestant Old Testament on a single page]
* [http://www.tyndale.ca/seminary/mtsmodular/reading-rooms/oldt Old Testament Reading Room - Extensive online OT resources (incl. commentaries), Tyndale Seminary]
* [http://oyc.yale.edu/religious-studies Old Testament Video Lectures from Yale University]
* [http://www.bible.x10host.com/ Old Testament stories and commentary]
* [http://www.lds.org/gospellibrary/materials/OT_Timeline_000.pdf Old Testament Timeline]
* [http://www.tanakhml.org Christian Hebrew Bible] ([[Biblia Hebraica Stuttgartensia]] and [[King James Version]])

{{Christianityfooter}}

{{Books of the Bible}}
{{Ancient Near East}}

[[Category:Bible]]
[[Category:Christian law]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Hebrew Bible]]
[[Category:Hebrew Bible topics]]
[[Category:Judeo-Christian topics]]
[[Category:Old Testament]]
[[Category:Rastafarian texts]]

[[af:Ou Testament]]
[[ar:عهد قديم]]
[[an:Antigo Testamento]]
[[arc:ܕܝܬܝܩܝ ܥܬܝܩܬܐ]]
[[ast:Vieyu Testamentu]]
[[az:Əhdi-Ətiq]]
[[bn:পুরাতন নিয়ম (বাইবেল)]]
[[zh-min-nan:Kū-iok Sèng-keng]]
[[be:Стары Запавет]]
[[be-x-old:Стары Запавет]]
[[bg:Стар завет]]
[[bar:Oits Testament]]
[[bs:Stari Zavjet]]
[[br:Testamant Kozh]]
[[ca:Antic Testament]]
[[cv:Кивĕ Халал]]
[[ceb:Daang Tugon]]
[[cs:Starý zákon]]
[[co:Anticu Testamentu]]
[[cy:Yr Hen Destament]]
[[da:Det Gamle Testamente]]
[[de:Altes Testament]]
[[et:Vana Testament]]
[[el:Παλαιά Διαθήκη]]
[[es:Antiguo Testamento]]
[[eo:Malnova testamento]]
[[eu:Itun Zaharra]]
[[fa:عهد عتیق]]
[[fo:Gamla Testamenti]]
[[fr:Ancien Testament]]
[[fy:Alde Testamint]]
[[fur:Vecjo Testament]]
[[gd:Seann Tiomnadh]]
[[gl:Antigo Testamento]]
[[hak:Khiu-yok Sṳn-kîn]]
[[ko:구약성경]]
[[hy:Հին Կտակարան]]
[[hi:पुराना नियम]]
[[hsb:Stary zakoń]]
[[hr:Stari zavjet]]
[[io:Anciena Testamento]]
[[id:Perjanjian Lama]]
[[ia:Vetere Testamento]]
[[ie:Ancian Testament]]
[[it:Antico Testamento]]
[[he:הברית הישנה]]
[[jv:Prajanjèn Lawas]]
[[kn:ಹಳೆ ಒಡಂಬಡಿಕೆ]]
[[ka:ძველი აღთქმა]]
[[kk:Көне келісім]]
[[rw:Isezerano rya Kera]]
[[sw:Agano la Kale]]
[[ht:Ansyen Testaman]]
[[ku:Peymana Kevin]]
[[lbe:Бух Аманат]]
[[la:Vetus Testamentum]]
[[lv:Vecā Derība]]
[[lb:Aalt Testament]]
[[lt:Senasis Testamentas]]
[[ln:Boyókani bwa Kala]]
[[lmo:Antigh Testament]]
[[hu:Ószövetség]]
[[mk:Стар Завет]]
[[mg:Testamenta Taloha]]
[[ml:പഴയ നിയമം]]
[[mi:Kawenata Tawhito]]
[[mr:जुना करार]]
[[arz:العهد القديم]]
[[ms:Perjanjian Lama]]
[[cdo:Gô-iók Séng-gĭng]]
[[mn:Хуучин Гэрээ]]
[[my:ဓမ္မဟောင်းကျမ်း]]
[[fj:Na Veiyalayalati Makawa]]
[[nl:Oude Testament]]
[[nds-nl:Oolde Testement]]
[[ja:旧約聖書]]
[[no:Det gamle testamente]]
[[nn:Det gamle testamentet]]
[[nrm:Vuus testament]]
[[tpi:Olpela Testamen]]
[[pl:Stary Testament]]
[[pt:Antigo Testamento]]
[[ty:Faufaa Tahito]]
[[ro:Vechiul Testament]]
[[rm:Vegl Testament]]
[[qu:Ñawpa Rimanakuy]]
[[ru:Ветхий Завет]]
[[se:Boares testameanta]]
[[sm:'O le Feagaiga Tuai]]
[[sg:Fini Testament]]
[[sco:Auld Testament]]
[[sq:Besëlidhja e Vjetër]]
[[scn:Anticu Tistamentu]]
[[si:පැරණි ගිවිසුම]]
[[simple:Old Testament]]
[[sk:Starý zákon]]
[[sl:Stara zaveza]]
[[so:Axdigii Hore]]
[[sr:Стари завет]]
[[sh:Stari zavjet]]
[[fi:Vanha testamentti]]
[[sv:Gamla Testamentet]]
[[tl:Lumang Tipan]]
[[ta:பழைய ஏற்பாடு]]
[[th:พันธสัญญาเดิม]]
[[tr:Eski Ahit]]
[[uk:Старий Заповіт]]
[[vep:Vanh Zavet]]
[[vi:Cựu Ước]]
[[yo:Májẹ̀mú Láéláé]]
[[zh-yue:舊約]]
[[diq:Ehdo Kıhan]]
[[bat-smg:Senāsis Testamėnts]]
[[zh:旧约圣经]]</text>
      <sha1>hazrjpztv2vknqj2jouvp0ilc7yrenj</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
