<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Oriental Orthodoxy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21468377</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520698020</id>
      <parentid>520025949</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T04:03:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>213.16.193.34</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Geographical distribution */ corrects figures for Kerala (relating them to the source cited)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20230">{{Eastern Christianity}}
'''Oriental Orthodoxy''' is the faith of those [[Eastern Christianity|Eastern Christian]] Churches that recognize only the first three [[ecumenical council]]s — the [[First Council of Nicaea]], the [[First Council of Constantinople]] and the [[First Council of Ephesus]]. They rejected the [[dogmatic definition]]s of the [[Council of Chalcedon]] held in 451 AD in [[Chalcedon]]. Hence, these '''Oriental Orthodox Churches''' are also called '''Old Oriental Churches''', [[Miaphysite|Miaphysite Churches]], or the [[Non-Chalcedonian]] Churches, known to [[Western Christianity]] and much of [[Eastern Orthodoxy]] as [[Monophysite]] Churches (although the Oriental Orthodox themselves reject this description as inaccurate, having rejected teachings of both [[Nestorius]] and [[Eutyches]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;first seven&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Davis, [[Society of Jesus|SJ]]|first=Leo Donald|title=The First Seven Ecumenical Councils (325-787): Their History and Theology (Theology and Life Series 21)|year=1990|publisher=Michael Glazier/Liturgical Press|location=Collegeville, MN|isbn=978-0-8146-5616-7|pages=342}}&lt;/ref&gt; These churches are in full communion with each other but not with the Eastern Orthodox Churches. Slow dialogue towards restoring communion began in the mid-20th century. &lt;ref name=&quot;sor.cua.edu&quot;&gt;[http://sor.cua.edu/Ecumenism/20010317oomtg4.html Syrian Orthodox Resources – Middle Eastern Oriental Orthodox Common Declaration]&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the potentially confusing nomenclature (Oriental meaning Eastern), Oriental Orthodox churches are distinct from those that are collectively referred to as the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]]. The Oriental Orthodox communion comprises six churches:  [[Coptic Orthodox]], [[Ethiopian Orthodox]], [[Eritrean Orthodox]], [[Syriac Orthodox]], [[Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church]] or [[Indian Orthodox Church]] and [[Armenian Apostolic Church|Armenian Apostolic]] churches.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wcc-coe.org/wcc/what/ecumenical/ooc-e.html Oriental Orthodox Churches&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; These churches, while being in communion with one another, are hierarchically independent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pluralism.org/affiliates/student/allen/Oriental-Orthodox/Home.html An Introduction to the Oriental Orthodox Churches&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Oriental Orthodox Churches and the rest of the Church split over differences in [[Christology|Christological]] terminology. The [[First Council of Nicaea]] (325) declared that Jesus Christ is [[God in Christianity|God]], that is to say, &quot;consubstantial&quot; with the Father; and the [[First Council of Ephesus]] (431) that Jesus, though divine as well as human, is only one being ([[hypostatic union|hypostasis]]).  Twenty years after Ephesus, the [[Council of Chalcedon]] declared that Jesus is one person in two complete natures, one human and one divine. Those who opposed Chalcedon likened its doctrine to the [[Nestorianism|Nestorian heresy]], condemned at Ephesus, that Christ was two distinct beings, one divine (the Logos) and one human (Jesus).

==History==
{{Main|History of Oriental Orthodoxy}}
[[File:StAnthony.jpg|thumb|right|Coptic icon of [[Anthony the Great|St. Anthony the Great]]]]

The [[Schism (religion)|schism]] between the Oriental Orthodox and the rest of Christendom occurred in the 5th century.  The separation resulted in part from the refusal of [[Pope Dioscorus I of Alexandria|Pope Dioscorus]], Patriarch of Alexandria and the other 13 Egyptian Bishops, to accept the [[Christology|Christological]] [[dogma]]s promulgated by the Council of Chalcedon, which held that [[Jesus]] is in two natures: one divine and one human. They would accept only &quot;of or from two natures&quot; but not &quot;in two natures.&quot;
To the hierarchs who would lead the Oriental Orthodox, the latter phrase was tantamount to accepting [[Nestorianism]], which expressed itself in a terminology incompatible with their understanding of Christology. Nestorianism was understood as seeing Christ in two separate natures, human and divine, each with different actions and experiences; in contrast Cyril of Alexandria advocated the formula &quot;one nature of the Incarnate Word of God,&quot; stressing the unity of the Incarnation over all other considerations. It is not entirely clear that Nestorius himself was a Nestorian.  

The Oriental Orthodox churches were therefore often called [[Monophysite]], although they reject this label, as it is associated with Eutychian Monophysitism; they prefer the term &quot;[[Miaphysite]]&quot; churches. Oriental Orthodox Churches reject what they consider to be the heretical Monophysite teachings of [[Apollinaris of Laodicea]] and [[Eutyches]], the [[Dyophysite]] definition of the Council of Chalcedon, and the Antiochene Christology of [[Theodore of Mopsuestia]], [[Nestorius of Constantinople]], [[Theodoret of Cyrus]], and [[Ibas of Edessa]].

Christology, although important, was not the only reason for the Alexandrian Church's refusal to accept the declarations of the Council of Chalcedon; political, ecclesiastical and imperial issues were hotly debated during that period.

In the years following Chalcedon the patriarchs of Constantinople intermittently remained in communion with the non-Chalcedonian patriarchs of Alexandria, Antioch, Jerusalem, (see [[Henotikon]]) while Rome remained out of communion with the latter and in unstable communion with Constantinople. It was not until 518 that the new Byzantine Emperor, [[Justin I]] (who accepted Chalcedon), demanded that the Church in the Roman Empire accept the Council's decisions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07470a.htm CATHOLIC ENCYCLOPEDIA: Pope St. Hormisdas&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Justin ordered the replacement of all non-Chalcedonian bishops, including the patriarchs of Antioch and Alexandria. The extent of the influence of the [[Bishop of Rome]] in this demand has been a matter of debate. [[Justinian I]] also attempted to bring those monks who still rejected the decision of the Council of Chalcedon into communion with the greater church. The exact time of this event is unknown, but it is believed to have been between 535 and 548. [[Abraham (Copt)|St Abraham of Farshut]] was summoned to Constantinople and he chose to bring with him four monks. Upon arrival, Justinian summoned them and informed them that they would either accept the decision of the Council or lose their positions. Abraham refused to entertain the idea. [[Theodora (6th century)|Theodora]] tried to persuade Justinian to change his mind, seemingly to no avail.  Abraham himself stated in a letter to his monks that he preferred to remain in exile rather than subscribe to a faith contrary to that of [[Athanasius]].

By the 20th century the Chalcedonian schism was not seen with the same importance, and from several meetings between the authorities of the [[Holy See]] and the Oriental Orthodoxy, reconciling declarations emerged in the common statement of the Syriac Patriarch (Mar [[Ignatius Zakka I Iwas]]) and the Pope ([[John Paul II]]) in 1984.

{{cquote|The confusions and schisms that occurred between their Churches in the later centuries, they realize today, in no way affect or touch the substance of their faith, since these arose only because of differences in terminology and culture and in the various formulae adopted by different theological schools to express the same matter. Accordingly, we find today no real basis for the sad divisions and schisms that subsequently arose between us concerning the doctrine of Incarnation. In words and life we confess the true doctrine concerning Christ our Lord, notwithstanding the differences in interpretation of such a doctrine which arose at the time of the Council of Chalcedon.&lt;ref&gt;From the common declaration of [[Pope John Paul II]] and HH Mar [[Ignatius Zakka I Iwas]], June 23, 1984&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to the canons of the Oriental Orthodox Churches, the four bishops of [[Rome]], [[Alexandria]], [[Ephesus]] and [[Antioch]] were all given status as [[Pentarchy|Patriarchs]]; in other words, the ancient apostolic centres of Christianity, by the First Council of Nicaea (predating the schism) &amp;mdash; each of the four patriarchs was responsible for those bishops and churches within his own area of the Universal Church, (with the exception of the [[Armenian Patriarchate of Jerusalem|Patriarch of Jerusalem]], who was independent of the rest).  Thus, the Bishop of Rome has always been held by the others to be fully sovereign within his own area, as well as &quot;First-Among-Equals&quot;, due to the traditional belief that the [[Twelve Apostles|Apostles]] [[Saint Peter]] and [[Paul the Apostle|Saint Paul]] were martyred in Rome.

The technical reason for the schism was that the bishops of Rome and Constantinople excommunicated the non-Chalcedonian bishops in 451 for refusing to accept the &quot;in two natures&quot; teaching, thus declaring them to be out of communion. Recent declarations indicate that the Holy See now regards itself as being in a state of partial communion with the other patriarchates.{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}

The highest office in Oriental Orthodoxy is that of Patriarch. There are Patriarchs within the local Oriental Orthodox communities of the Armenian, Coptic, Eritrean, Ethiopian, and Syrian Orthodox Churches. The title of Pope, as used by [[Pope Shenouda III of Alexandria]] (Pope of the [[Coptic Orthodox Church]]) has the meaning of 'Father' and is not a jurisdictional title. However, the Coptic Pope holds the honor of being &quot;first among equals&quot;, as the Ecumenical Patriarch does among the Eastern Orthodox, and as such he functions as the president of pan-jurisdictional gatherings of the Oriental Orthodox.

==Geographical distribution==
[[File:World Orthodoxy.JPG|right|thumb|500px|Distribution of Orthodox Christianity in the world by country
{{Columns |width=210px
|col1 =
'''[[Eastern Orthodoxy]]'''
{{legend|#000055|Main religion (more than 75%)}}
{{legend|#0000aa|Main religion (50% - 75%)}}
{{legend|#0000ff|Important minority religion (20% - 50%)}}
{{legend|#5555ff|Important minority religion (5% - 20%)}}
{{legend|#aaaaff|Minority religion (1% - 5%)}}
|col2 =
'''Oriental Orthodoxy'''
{{legend|#550000|Main religion (more than 75%)}}
{{legend|#d40000|Main religion (50% - 75%)}}
{{legend|#ff0000|Important minority religion (20% - 50%)}}
{{legend|#ff5555|Important minority religion (5% - 20%)}}
{{legend|#ffaaaa|Minority religion (1% - 5%)}}
}}
]]

Oriental Orthodoxy is a dominant religion in [[Armenia]] (94%), the ethnically Armenian [[Nagorno-Karabakh Republic]] (95%), and in [[Ethiopia]] (43%, the total Christian population being 62%), especially in two regions in [[Ethiopia]]: [[Amhara Region|Amhara]] (82%) and [[Tigray Region|Tigray]] (96%), as well as the chartered city of [[Addis Ababa]] (75%).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csa.gov.et/pdf/Cen2007_firstdraft.pdf Ethiopia: 2007 Census]&lt;/ref&gt; It is also one of two dominant religions in [[Eritrea]] (50%). It is a minority in [[Egypt]] (9%),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/eg.html| title=The World Factbook: Egypt| publisher=[[CIA]]| accessdate=2010-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sudan]] (3–5% out of the 15% of total Christians), [[Syria]] (2–3% out of the 10% of total Christians), [[Lebanon]] (10% of the 40% of Christians in Lebanon) and [[Kerala]], [[India]] (7% out of the 20% of total Christians in Kerala)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.syrianchurch.org/MalankaraChurch/DEFAULT.HTM]&lt;/ref&gt;.  In terms of total number of members, the Ethiopian Church is the largest of all Oriental Orthodox Churches, and is second among all Orthodox Churches among Eastern and Oriental Churches (exceeded in number only by the [[Russian Orthodox Church]]).

==Oriental Orthodox Communion==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Panentheism]] --&gt;

The Oriental Orthodox Communion is a group of churches within Oriental Orthodoxy which are all in [[full communion]] with each other.  The communion includes:

* The [[Armenian Apostolic Church]]
** The [[Mother See of Holy Etchmiadzin]]
** The [[Holy See of Cilicia]]
** The [[Armenian Patriarch of Constantinople|Armenian Patriarchate of Constantinople]]
** The [[Armenian Patriarchate of Jerusalem]]
* The [[Syriac Orthodox Church]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.syrian-orthodox.com/]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church]]
* The [[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria]]
** The [[British Orthodox Church]]
** The [[French Coptic Orthodox Church]]
* The [[Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church]]
* The [[Eritrean Orthodox Tewahedo Church]]

== Internal disputes ==
{{unreferenced section|date=November 2010}}
There are numerous ongoing internal disputes within the Oriental Orthodox Churches. These disputes result in lesser or greater degrees of impaired communion.

===Armenian Apostolic===

The least divisive of these disputes is within the [[Armenian Apostolic Church]], between the Catholicosate of Etchmiadzin and the [[Holy See of Cilicia|Catholicosate of the Great House of Cilicia]]. The division of the two Catholicosates stemmed from frequent relocations of Church headquarters due to political and military upheavals.

The division between the two Sees intensified during the Soviet period. By some Western Bishops and clergy the Holy See of Etchmiadzin was seen as a captive Communist puppet. Sympathizers of this established congregations independent of Etchmiadzin, declaring loyalty instead to the See based in [[Antelias]] in [[Lebanon]]. The division was formalized in 1956 when the Antelias (Cilician) See broke away from the Echmiadzin See. Though recognising the supremacy of the [[Catholicos of All Armenians]], the [[List of Armenian Catholicoi of Cilicia|Catholicos of Cilicia]] administers the clergy and dioceses independently. The dispute, however, has not at all caused a breach in communion between the two churches.

===Oriental Orthodox Indians===

The next least divisive dispute is among Indians who are Oriental Orthodox. This dispute is between two jurisdictional bodies among Oriental Orthodox Indians: the [[Jacobite Syrian Christian Church]] and the [[Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church]]. The former is an archdiocese of the [[Syriac Orthodox Church]]. It experiences a certain degree of autonomy, but is ultimately responsible to the Syriac Orthodox Patriarch of Antioch. The latter, on the other hand, is entirely independent of the [[Syriac Orthodox Church]], rejecting any form of jurisdictional submission to the Syriac Patriarch. Though the church was united for a brief period from 1958 to 1975. In 1972, then Patriarch Ignatius Ya`qub III excommunicated the Indian Catholicos Baselios Augen I, when the [[Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church]] questioned the infamous patriarchal bull which denied the priesthood of [[Thomas the Apostle|St. Thomas]]. The current Syriac Patriarch, [[Ignatius Zakka I Iwas]], maintains this excommunication. However, the Catholicos Baselios Augen I, or his successors, never excommunicated Ignatius Ya`qub III in retribution nor removed the clause that maintains Syrian Patriarchs Spiritual authority from its constitution.

==Occasional confusions==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Kottayam Orthodox.jpg||thumb|left|[[Kottayam]] St.Mary's Orthodox Church&lt;br /&gt;
Indo-Persian Architecture of a Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church. It is a mix of Hindu and Persian Christian religious architecture]] --&gt;

The [[Assyrian Church of the East]] is sometimes incorrectly described as an Oriental Orthodox church, though its origins lie in disputes that predated the Council of Chalcedon and it follows a different Christology from Oriental Orthodoxy. The historical [[Church of the East]] was the church of [[Persia]], and declared itself separate from the [[state church of the Roman Empire]] in 424 – 27 years before Chalcedon. Theologically, the Church of the East was affiliated with the [[dyophysite]] doctrine of [[Nestorianism]], and thus rejected the [[First Council of Ephesus]], which declared Nestorianism heretical in 431. The Christology of the Oriental Orthodox churches in fact developed as a reaction to Nestorian Christology, which emphasizes the distinctness of the human and divine natures of Christ.

There are many overlapping [[Saint Thomas Christians|ecclesiastical jurisdictions in India]], mostly with a Syriac liturgical heritage centered in the state of [[Kerala]].  The autonomous [[Malankara Jacobite Syriac Orthodox Church]], which comes under the Syriac Orthodox Church is quite often confused with the [[Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church]] as the latter uses a similar name. 

{{Christianity|expand-eastern=yes}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Oriental Orthodoxy}}
* [[List of Orthodox Churches]]
* [[Eastern Orthodoxy]]
* [[Western Rite Orthodoxy]]
* [[Saint Thomas Christians]]
* [[Antiochian Catholic Church in America]]
* [[List of Christian denominations]]
* [[List of Christian denominations by number of members]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* Betts, Robert B., [http://www.anagnosis.gr/index.php?pageID=295&amp;la=eng&amp;page=2 ''Christians in the Arab East''], Lycabbetus Press (Athens, 1978)
* Charles, R. H. ''The Chronicle of John, Bishop of Nikiu: Translated from [[Hermann Zotenberg|Zotenberg]]'s Ethiopic Text'', 1916. Reprinted 2007. Evolution Publishing, ISBN 978-1-889758-87-9. [http://www.evolpub.com/CRE/CREseries.html#CRE4]

==External links==
* [http://www.orientalorthodoxchurches.com/ Oriental Orthodox Churches]
* [http://www.orthodoxunity.org Orthodox Unity]
* [http://www.prounione.urbe.it/dia-int/oo-rc_syrindia/doc/i_oo-rc_syrindia_1984.html Common declaration of Pope John Paul II and HH Mar Ignatius Zakka I Iwas]
* [http://sor.cua.edu/Ecumenism/RC.html Joint declarations between the Syriac Orthodox and Roman Catholic Churches]
* [http://www.anglicancommunion.org/ministry/ecumenical/dialogues/oriental/index.cfm Dialogue with the Oriental Orthodox Churches on the Anglican Communion website.]
* [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/sub-index/index_ancient-oriental-ch.htm Dialogue with the Oriental Orthodox Churches on the Vatican website.]
* [http://independent.academia.edu/EIRINIARTEMINationalandCapodistrianUniversityofAthens/Papers/1721697/The_rejection_of_the_term_Theotokos_by_Nestorius_Constantinople The rejection of the term Theotokos by Nestorius Constantinople]

{{Oriental Orthodoxy}}
{{Eastern Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox Christians}}

[[Category:Eastern Christianity]]
[[Category:Oriental Orthodoxy| ]]
[[Category:Non-Chalcedonianism]]

[[als:Altorientalische Kirchen]]
[[ar:أرثوذكسية مشرقية]]
[[frp:Églléses des três concilos]]
[[bg:Нехалкедонски църкви]]
[[ca:Antigues esglésies orientals]]
[[cs:Východní pravoslavné společenství]]
[[de:Altorientalische Kirchen]]
[[et:Vanad oriendikirikud]]
[[el:Προχαλκηδόνιες Εκκλησίες]]
[[es:Antiguas iglesias orientales]]
[[fr:Églises des trois conciles]]
[[ga:Ortadocsacht an oirthir]]
[[ko:오리엔탈 정교회]]
[[hy:Արևելյան ուղղափառ եկեղեցիներ]]
[[hr:Istočne pravoslavne Crkve]]
[[id:Gereja Ortodoks Oriental]]
[[ia:Orthodoxia oriental]]
[[is:Austrænar rétttrúnaðarkirkjur]]
[[it:Chiese orientali antiche]]
[[he:נצרות אוריינטלית]]
[[sw:Waorthodoksi wa Mashariki]]
[[la:Ecclesiae Veteres Orientales]]
[[hu:Antikhalkédóni egyházak]]
[[mk:Древноисточни цркви]]
[[ml:ഓറിയന്റൽ ഓർത്തഡോക്സ് സഭകൾ]]
[[nl:Oriëntaals-orthodoxe Kerken]]
[[ja:東方諸教会]]
[[no:Orientalsk-ortodokse kirker]]
[[nn:Orientalske ortodokse kyrkjer]]
[[pl:Kościoły orientalne]]
[[pt:Igrejas não calcedonianas]]
[[ro:Bisericile vechi orientale]]
[[ru:Древневосточные церкви]]
[[scn:Chiesa Ortudossa Urientali]]
[[simple:Oriental Orthodox Church]]
[[sk:Orientálna ortodoxná cirkev]]
[[sr:Древноисточне цркве]]
[[sh:Prethalkedonske crkve]]
[[fi:Orientaaliortodoksiset kirkot]]
[[sv:Orientaliskt ortodoxa]]
[[th:ออเรียนทัลออร์ทอดอกซ์]]
[[tr:Doğu Ortodoks Kiliseleri]]
[[uk:Давньосхідні церкви]]
[[zh:東方正統教會]]</text>
      <sha1>qdva36mlv9hg6czvv6z7lm5i1xqta30</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
