<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Original sin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22735</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519808382</id>
      <parentid>518688879</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-25T19:00:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bgwhite</username>
        <id>264323</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fix id #63</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="64973">{{Other uses2|Original Sin}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2012}}
[[File:Michelangelo Buonarroti 022.jpg|300px|thumb|right|[[Michelangelo]]'s painting of the sin of Adam and Eve from the [[Sistine Chapel ceiling]]]]

'''Original sin''', also called '''[[ancestral sin]]''',&lt;ref&gt;Examples: [http://books.google.com/books?id=SUjKOoQsCyUC&amp;pg=PA119&amp;lpg=PA119&amp;dq=%22baptism+removes+the+ancestral+sin%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=WvN674NJ0K&amp;sig=xWY-WeO5kwn2OdlpagQrW2SaL98&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=hyw6UI6IKM-YhQfOx4HoBA&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=%22baptism%20removes%20the%20ancestral%20sin%22&amp;f=false Alexander Golitzin, ''On the Mystical Life'' by Saint Symeon (St Vladimir's Seminary Press 1995 ISBN 9780881411447), p.119]; [http://books.google.ie/books?id=ltNLs6fI73cC&amp;pg=PA190&amp;lpg=PA190&amp;dq=%22far-descended+ancestral+sin%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Wg2Hi4PaWc&amp;sig=1j62vU6Tt4rW7D8I_sKhnEOMzmA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=BD86UN6sMoixhAepq4Bo&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=%22far-descended%20ancestral%20sin%22&amp;f=false Adam L. Tate, ''Conservatism and Southern Intellectuals, 1789-1861'' (University of Missouri Press 2005 ISBN 9780826215673), p. 190]; [http://books.google.ie/books?id=6ePZFD9BOB4C&amp;pg=PA32&amp;lpg=PA32&amp;dq=%22cleansing+away+the+ancestral+sin%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Q_UQR1wCNA&amp;sig=BLWCH5n-tLMlixBb8e347sR-oIA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=aC46UOPJHIqohAf-soCQBg&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=%22cleansing%20away%20the%20ancestral%20sin%22&amp;f=false Marcelle Bartolo-Abel, ''God's Gift to Humanity'' (Apostolate-The Divine Heart 2011 ISBN 9780983348016), p. 32]; [http://books.google.com/books?id=N0e9guRLMVEC&amp;pg=PA62&amp;lpg=PA62&amp;dq=%22this+ancestral+sin+is+essential%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=n5TFLhT9qJ&amp;sig=LOX4bSYWg0f05kHosz8eLUvHMS8&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Xik6UKLPK4m3hAeH_IG4Bw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=%22this%20ancestral%20sin%20is%20essential%22&amp;f=false Ann Hassan, ''Annotations to Geoffrey Hill's Speech! Speech!'' (Punctum Books 2012 ISBN 97814681298470, p. 62]&lt;/ref&gt; is, according to a Christian theological doctrine, humanity's state of [[sin]] resulting from the [[fall of man]].{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}} This condition has been characterized in many ways, ranging from something as insignificant as a slight deficiency, or a tendency toward sin yet without collective guilt, referred to as a &quot;sin nature&quot;, to something as drastic as [[total depravity]] or automatic guilt of all humans through [[collective guilt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Brodd | first = Jefferey | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = World Religions | publisher = Saint Mary's Press | year = 2003 | location = Winona, MN | pages = |url = | isbn = 978-0-88489-725-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of ''original sin'' was first alluded to in the 2nd century by [[Irenaeus]], [[Bishop of Lyons]] in his controversy (written in Greek) with the [[dualistic cosmology|dualist]] [[Gnosticism|Gnostics]].{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}} Its scriptural foundation is based on the [[New Testament]] teaching of [[Paul the Apostle]] ({{bibleverse||Romans|5:12-21}} and {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|15:22}}). [[Tertullian]], [[Cyprian]], [[Ambrose]] and [[Ambrosiaster]] considered that mankind shares in Adam's sin, transmitted by human generation. Augustine's formulation of original sin was popular among [[Protestant Reformation|Reformers]], such as [[Martin Luther]] and [[John Calvin]] who equated original sin with [[concupiscence]], affirming that it persisted even after [[baptism]] and completely destroyed freedom.{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}} Within Roman Catholicism, the [[Jansenism|Jansenist]] movement, which the Church then declared heretical, also maintained that original sin destroyed freedom of will.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08285a.htm &quot;Jansenius and Jansenism&quot; in ''The Catholic Encyclopedia'']&lt;/ref&gt;

The doctrine is not found in [[Judaism]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/Original_Sin.html Judaism's Rejection Of Original Sin&lt;/ref&gt; or in [[Islam]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.religionfacts.com/islam/beliefs/human.htm/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.religionfacts.com/islam/beliefs/human.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of the doctrine==
The [[Apostolic Father]]s and the [[Apologist]]s mostly dealt with topics other than original sin. The doctrine of original sin was first developed in the 2nd-century [[Irenaeus]], [[Bishop of Lyons]]'s struggle against [[Gnosticism]].{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}} Irenaeus contrasted their doctrine with the view that the Fall was a step in the wrong direction by Adam, with whom, Irenaeus believed, his descendants had some solidarity or identity.&lt;ref&gt;J. N. D. Kelly ''Early Christian Doctrines'' (San Francisco: Harper Collins, 1978) p. 171, referred to in Daniel L. Akin, ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=elzlVK5c3dQC&amp;pg=PA432&amp;dq=JND+Kelly+#v=onepage&amp;q=JND%20Kelly&amp;f=false A Theology for the Church]'', p. 433&lt;/ref&gt; Irenaeus believed that Adam's sin had grave consequences for humanity, that it is the source of human sinfulness, mortality and enslavement to sin, and that all human beings participate in his sin and share his guilt.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel L. Akin, ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=elzlVK5c3dQC&amp;pg=PA433&amp;dq=Akin+Irenaeus+%22enslavement+to+sin%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=C-2BTaOvBIWxhQebqsm-BA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCcQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false A Theology for the Church]'' (B&amp;H Publishing 2007 ISBN 978-0-8054-2640-3), p. 433&lt;/ref&gt;

The Greek Fathers emphasized the cosmic dimension of the Fall, namely that since Adam human beings are born into a fallen world, but held fast to belief that man, though fallen, is free.{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}} They thus did not teach that human beings are deprived of free will and involved in [[total depravity]], which is one understanding of original sin.&lt;ref&gt;A. J. Wallace, R. D. Rusk, ''Moral Transformation: The Original Christian Paradigm of Salvation'' (New Zealand: Bridgehead, 2011), pp. 255 &amp; 258. ISBN 978-1-4563-8980-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;H. E. W. Turner, ''The Patristic Doctrine of the Redemption: A Study of the Development of Doctrine During the First Five Centuries'' (Eugene, OR: Wipf &amp; Stock Publishers, 2004) p. 71&lt;/ref&gt; During this period the doctrines of human depravity and the inherently sinful nature human flesh were taught by [[Gnosticism|Gnostics]], and orthodox Christian writers took great pains to counter them.&lt;ref&gt;Bernhard Lohse, ''A Short History of Christian Doctrine'' (Philadelphia, PA: Fortress Press, 1966), p. 104&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A. J. Wallace, R. D. Rusk, ''Moral Transformation: The Original Christian Paradigm of Salvation'' (New Zealand: Bridgehead, 2011), p. 258. ISBN 978-1-4563-8980-2&lt;/ref&gt; Christian Apologists insisted that God's future judgment of humanity implied humanity must have the ability to live righteously.&lt;ref&gt;[[Arthur Cushman McGiffert|Arthur C. McGiffert]], ''A History of Christian Thought: Volume 1, Early and Eastern'' (New York; London: C. Scribner's sons, 1932), p. 101&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A. J. Wallace, R. D. Rusk, ''Moral Transformation: The Original Christian Paradigm of Salvation'' (New Zealand: Bridgehead, 2011), pp. 258-259. ISBN 978-1-4563-8980-2&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Augustine ===
[[File:Sandro Botticelli 050.jpg|150px|thumb|right|[[Augustine of Hippo]] wrote that original sin is transmitted by concupiscence and enfeebles freedom of the will without destroying it.{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}}]]
[[Augustine of Hippo]] (354-430) taught that Adam's sin&lt;ref&gt;Augustine taught that Adam's sin was both an act of foolishness (''insipientia'') and of pride and disobedience to God of Adam and Eve. He thought it was a most subtle job to discern what came first: self-centeredness or failure in seeing truth. Augustine wrote to [[Julian of Eclanum]]: ''Sed si disputatione subtilissima et elimatissima opus est, ut sciamus utrum primos homines insipientia superbos, an insipientes superbia fecerit'' (''Contra Julianum'', V, 4.18; PL 44, 795). This particular sin would not have taken place if [[Satan]] had not sown into their senses ''&quot;the root of evil”'' (''radix Mali''): ''Nisi radicem mali humanus tunc reciperet sensus'' (''Contra Julianum'', I, 9.42; PL 44, 670)&lt;/ref&gt; is transmitted by [[concupiscence]], resulting in mankind becoming a ''massa damnata'' (mass of perdition, condemned crowd), with much enfeebled, though not destroyed, freedom of will.{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}} When Adam sinned, human nature was thenceforth transformed. Adam and Eve, via sexual reproduction, recreated human nature. Their descendants now live in sin, in the form of concupiscence, a term Augustine used in a [[Metaphysics|metaphysical]], not a [[Psychology|psychological]] sense.&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Aquinas]] explained Augustine's doctrine pointing out that the ''libido'' (''concupiscence''), which makes the original sin pass from parents to children, is not a ''libido actualis'', i.e. sexual lust, but ''libido habitualis'', i.e. a wound of the whole of human nature: ''Libido quae transmittit peccatum originale in prolem, non est libido actualis, quia dato quod virtute divina concederetur alicui quod nullam inordinatam libidinem in actu generationis sentiret, adhuc transmitteret in prolem originale peccatum. Sed libido illa est intelligenda habitualiter, secundum quod appetitus sensitivus non continetur sub ratione vinculo originalis iustitiae. Et talis libido in omnibus est aequalis'' (STh Iª-IIae q. 82 a. 4 ad 3).&lt;/ref&gt; Augustine insisted that concupiscence was not ''a being'' but a ''bad quality'', the privation of good or a wound.&lt;ref&gt;''Non substantialiter manere concupiscentiam, sicut corpus aliquod aut spiritum; sed esse affectionem quamdam malae qualitatis, sicut est languor''. (''De nuptiis et concupiscentia'', I, 25. 28; PL 44, 430; cf. ''Contra Julianum'', VI, 18.53; PL 44, 854; ibid. VI, 19.58; PL 44, 857; ibid., II, 10.33; PL 44, 697; ''Contra Secundinum Manichaeum'', 15; PL 42, 590.&lt;/ref&gt; He admitted that sexual concupiscence (''libido'') might have been present in the perfect human nature in paradise, and that only later it became disobedient to human will as a result of the first couple's disobedience to God's will in the original sin.&lt;ref&gt;Augustine wrote to [[Julian of Eclanum]]: ''Quis enim negat futurum fuisse concubitum, etiamsi peccatum non praecessisset? Sed futurus fuerat, sicut aliis membris, ita etiam genitalibus voluntate motis, non libidine concitatis; aut certe etiam ipsa libidine – ut non vos de illa nimium contristemus – non qualis nunc est, sed ad nutum voluntarium serviente'' (Contra Julianum, IV. 11. 57; PL 44, 766). See also his late work: ''Contra secundam Iuliani responsionem imperfectum opus'', II, 42; PL 45,1160; ibid. II, 45; PL 45,1161; ibid., VI, 22; PL 45, 1550-1551. Cf.{{cite book |title=Le mariage chrétien dans l'oeuvre de Saint Augustin. Une théologie baptismale de la vie conjugale |last= Schmitt|first=É. |year= 1983|series = Études Augustiniennes | location= Paris|page= 104}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Augustine's view (termed &quot;Realism&quot;), all of humanity was really present in Adam when he sinned, and therefore all have sinned. Original sin, according to Augustine, consists of the guilt of Adam which all humans inherit. As sinners, humans are utterly depraved in nature, lack the freedom to do good, and cannot respond to the will of God without [[divine grace]]. Grace is [[irresistible grace|irresistible]], results in conversion, and leads to [[perseverance of the saints|perseverance]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gonzalez&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|author=Justo L. Gonzalez
|title=A History of Christian Thought: Volume 2 (From Augustine to the eve of the Reformation)
|publisher=Abingdon Press
|date=1970-1975}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Augustine articulated his explanation in reaction to [[Pelagianism]], which insisted that humans have of themselves, without the necessary help of God's grace, the ability to lead a morally good life, and thus denied both the importance of baptism and the teaching that God is the giver of all that is good. Pelagius claimed that the influence of Adam on other humans was merely that of bad example. Augustine held that the effects of Adam's sin are transmitted to his descendants not by example but by the very fact of generation from that ancestor. A wounded nature comes to the soul and body of the new person from his/her parents, who experience ''libido'' (or ''concupiscence''). Augustine's view was that human procreation was the way the transmission was being effected. He did not blame, however, the sexual passion itself, but the spiritual ''concupiscence'' present in human nature, soul and body, even after baptismal regeneration.&lt;ref&gt;Sexual desire is, according to bishop of Hippo, only one - though the strongest - of many physical realisations of that spiritual libido: ''Cum igitur sint multarum libidines rerum, tamen, cum libido dicitur neque cuius rei libido sit additur, non fere assolet animo occurrere nisi illa, qua obscenae partes corporis excitantur. Haec autem sibi non solum totum corpus nec solum extrinsecus, verum etiam intrinsecus vindicat totumque commovet hominem animi simul affectu cum carnis appetitu coniuncto atque permixto, ut ea voluptas sequatur, qua maior in corporis voluptatibus nulla est; ita ut momento ipso temporis, quo ad eius pervenitur extremum, paene omnis acies et quasi vigilia cogitationis obruatur''. (De civitate Dei, XIV, 16; CCL 48, 438-439 [1-10]). See also: {{cite book |title=Le mariage chrétien dans l'oeuvre de Saint Augustin. Une théologie baptismale de la vie conjugale |last= Schmitt|first=É. |year= 1983|series = Études Augustiniennes | location= Paris|page= 97}}. See also Augustine's: ''De continentia'', 8.21; PL 40, 363; ''Contra Iulianum'' VI, 19.60; PL 44, 859; ibid. IV, 14.65, z.2, s. 62; PL 44, 770; ''[[De Trinitate]]'', XII, 9. 14; CCL 50, 368 [verse: IX 1-8]; ''De Genesi contra Manicheos'', II, 9.12, s. 60 ; CSEL 91, 133 [v.31-35]).&lt;/ref&gt; Christian parents transmit their wounded nature to children, because they give them birth, not the &quot;re-birth&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Regeneratus quippe non regenerat filios carnis, sed generat; ac per hoc in eos non quod regeneratus, sed quod generatus est, trajicit''. (''De gratia Christi et de peccato originali'', II, 40.45; CSEL 42, 202[23-25]; PL 44, 407.&lt;/ref&gt; Augustine used [[Cicero]]nian [[Stoicism|Stoic]] concept of passions, to interpret [[Paul the Apostle|St. Paul's]] doctrine of universal sin and redemption. In that view, also sexual desire itself as well as other bodily passions were consequence of the original sin, in which pure affections were wounded by vice and became disobedient to human reason and will. As long as they carry a threat to the dominion of reason over the soul they constitute moral evil, but since they do not presuppose consent, one cannot call them sins. Mankind will be liberated from passions, and pure affections will be restored only when all sin has been washed away and ended, that is in the resurrection of the dead.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. ''De civitate Dei'', ch. IX and XIV; ''On the Gospel of John'', LX (Christ's feelings at the death of Lazarus, Jn 11)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= J. Brachtendorf | year =1997 |title= Cicero and Augustine on the Passions|page= 307 |id= {{hdl|2042/23075}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Augustine believed that the only definitive destinations of souls are heaven and hell. He concluded that unbaptized infants go to hell as a consequence of original sin.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''Infernum''&quot;, literally &quot;underworld,&quot; later identified as [[Limbo#Limbo of Children|limbo]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Limbo: Past Catholic statements on the fate of unbaptized infants, etc. who have died&quot;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/limbo2.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; The Latin [[Church Fathers]] who followed Augustine adopted his position, which became a point of reference for Latin theologians in the Middle Ages.&lt;ref&gt;Study by International Theological Commission (19 January 2007), ''[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/cti_documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20070419_un-baptised-infants_en.html The Hope of Salvation for Infants Who Die Without Being Baptized]'', 19-21&lt;/ref&gt; In the later mediaeval period, some theologians continued to hold Augustine's view, others held that unbaptized infants suffered no pain at all: unaware of being deprived of the [[beatific vision]], they enjoyed a state of natural, not supernatural happiness. Starting around 1300, unbaptized infants were often said to inhabit the &quot;[[Limbo#Limbo of Infants|limbo of infants]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Study by International Theological Commission (19 January 2007), ''[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/cti_documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20070419_un-baptised-infants_en.html The Hope of Salvation for Infants Who Die Without Being Baptized]'', 22-25&lt;/ref&gt; The [http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p2s2c1a1.htm#VI ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', 1261] declares: &quot;As regards children who have died without Baptism, the Church can only entrust them to the mercy of God, as she does in her funeral rites for them. Indeed, the great mercy of God who desires that all men should be saved, and Jesus' tenderness toward children which caused him to say: 'Let the children come to me, do not hinder them,'&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Mark|10:14}}; cf. {{bibleverse|1|Tim|2:4}}&lt;/ref&gt; allow us to hope that there is a way of salvation for children who have died without Baptism. All the more urgent is the Church's call not to prevent little children coming to Christ through the gift of holy Baptism.&quot; But the theory of Limbo, while it &quot;never entered into the dogmatic definitions of the Magisterium ... remains ... a possible theological hypothesis&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Study by International Theological Commission (19 January 2007), ''[http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/cti_documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20070419_un-baptised-infants_en.html The Hope of Salvation for Infants Who Die Without Being Baptized]'', secondary preliminary paragraph; cf. paragraph 41.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cassian===
In the works of [[John Cassian]] (ca. 360 – 435), ''Conference'' XIII recounts how the wise monk [[Chaeremon]], of whom he is writing, responded to puzzlement caused by his own statement that &quot;man even though he strive with all his might for a good result, yet cannot become master of what is good unless he has acquired it simply by the gift of Divine bounty and not by the efforts of his own toil&quot; (chapter 1). In chapter 11, Cassian presents Chaeremon as speaking of the cases of Paul the persecutor and Matthew the publican as difficulties for those who say &quot;the beginning of free will is in our own power&quot;, and the cases of Zaccheus and the good thief on the cross as difficulties for those who say &quot;the beginning of our free will is always due to the inspiration of the grace of God&quot;, and as concluding: &quot;These two then; viz., the grace of God and free will seem opposed to each other, but really are in harmony, and we gather from the system of goodness that we ought to have both alike, lest if we withdraw one of them from man, we may seem to have broken the rule of the Church's faith: for when God sees us inclined to will what is good, He meets, guides, and strengthens us: for 'At the voice of thy cry, as soon as He shall hear, He will answer thee'; and: 'Call upon Me', He says, 'in the day of tribulation and I will deliver thee, and thou shalt glorify Me'. And again, if He finds that we are unwilling or have grown cold, He stirs our hearts with salutary exhortations, by which a good will is either renewed or formed in us.&quot;&lt;ref name=Conference13&gt;Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series II/Volume XI/John Cassian/Conferences of John Cassian, Part II/Conference XIII/Chapter 11 [[s:Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers: Series II/Volume XI/John Cassian/Conferences of John Cassian, Part II/Conference XIII/Chapter 11]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Cassian did not accept the idea of [[total depravity]], on which [[Martin Luther]] was to insist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reformation Europe&quot;&gt;Geoffrey Rudolph Elton, ''[http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1&amp;q=Elton+%22of+man%27s+total+depravity%22&amp;btnG= Reformation Europe]'' (Wiley-Blackwell 1999 ISBN 978-0-631-21384-0), p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; He taught that human nature is fallen or depraved, but not totally. Augustine Casiday states that, at the same time, Cassian &quot;baldly asserts that God's grace, not human free will, is responsible for 'everything which pertains to salvation' - even faith.&quot;&lt;ref name=Casiday-faith&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=fC0tYhHDHbEC&amp;pg=PA103&amp;lpg=PA103&amp;dq=cassian+baldly+asserts&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=OFvglZnBsV&amp;sig=NArSD9TzmzlWaaGNmWXDFF6CM3I&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=XQxATKKRHJr40wSO4NyZDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=cassian%20baldly%20asserts&amp;f=false Augustine Casiday, ''Tradition and Theology in St John Cassian'' (Oxford University Press 2007 ISBN 0-19-929718-5), p. 103]&lt;/ref&gt;  Cassian pointed out that people still have moral freedom and one has the option to choose to follow God. [[Colm Luibhéid]] says that, according to Cassian, there are cases where the soul makes the first little turn,&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=Uxaow-3qnRQC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;lpg=PA27&amp;dq=Cassian+after+one+chooses+God&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=EV0F97kl0S&amp;sig=hzP1s2J5iLsExz2_374bxxKj2xc&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=E05HTPzgI8P68Aaah4TZBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CCYQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Conferences By John Cassian, Colm Luibhéid]&lt;/ref&gt; but in Cassian's view, according to Casiday, any sparks of goodwill that may exist, not ''directly'' caused by God, are totally inadequate and only ''direct'' divine intervention ensures spiritual progress.&lt;ref name=Casiday&gt;[http://www.unisa.ac.za/contents/faculties/theology/chssa/docs/BookReviews-XXXV_1_-May-23-07-2009.pdf STUDIA HISTORIAE ECCLESIASTICAE May/Mei 2009 Volume XXXV No/Nr 1]&lt;/ref&gt; and Lauren Pristas says that &quot;for Cassian, salvation is, from beginning to end, the effect of God's grace.&quot;&lt;ref name=Pristas&gt;[http://escholarship.bc.edu/dissertations/AAI9329276/ Lauren Pristas, ''The Theological Anthropology of John Cassian'']&lt;/ref&gt;

===Church reaction===
Opposition to Augustine's ideas about original sin, which he had developed in reaction to [[Pelagianism]], arose rapidly,&lt;ref&gt;A. J. Wallace, R. D. Rusk, ''Moral Transformation: The Original Christian Paradigm of Salvation'' (New Zealand: Bridgehead, 2011), pp. 284-285. ISBN 978-1-4563-8980-2&lt;/ref&gt; After a long and bitter struggle the general principles of Augustine's teaching were confirmed within Western Christianity by many councils, especially the [[Councils of Orange|Second Council of Orange]] in 529.{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}} However, while the Church condemned Pelagius, it did not endorse Augustine entirely&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=IEPQP87xFcUC&amp;pg=PA73&amp;lpg=PA73&amp;dq=Zackrison+%22did+not+entirely%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=FG1GjxHIuM&amp;sig=qlmBhIWheCvpYHx7IGxueznOHU8&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=8xc2UMeOHsOXhQfawoCwCg&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Zackrison%20%22did%20not%20entirely%22&amp;f=false Edwin Zackrison, ''In the Loins of Adam'' (iUniverse 2004 ISBN 9780595307166), p. 73]&lt;/ref&gt; and, while Augustine's authority was accepted, he was interpreted in the light of writers such as Cassian.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=kEXOzNeSgWoC&amp;pg=PA58&amp;lpg=PA58&amp;dq=Gonz%C3%A1lez+%22such+writers+as+Cassian%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=sPIWCTHUxR&amp;sig=Xh74CSz8cwXylcSFCS6ylacWy6g&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=OBk2UIqjGtSwhAfWjID4Cw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Gonz%C3%A1lez%20%22such%20writers%20as%20Cassian%22&amp;f=false Justo L. González, ''A History of Christian Thought'' (Abingdon Press 2010 ISBN 9781426721915), vol. 2, p. 58]&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the followers of Augustine identified original sin with [[concupiscence]]&lt;ref&gt;In Catholic theology, the meaning of the word &quot;concupiscence&quot; is the movement of the sensitive appetite contrary to the operation of the human reason. The apostle St Paul identifies it with the rebellion of the 'flesh' against the 'spirit' Concupiscence stems from the disobedience of the first sin. It unsettles man's moral faculties and, without being in itself an offence, inclines man to commit sins&quot; ([http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P8P.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', n. 2515]).&lt;/ref&gt; in the psychological sense, but this identification was challenged by the 11th-century Saint [[Anselm of Canterbury]], who defined original sin as &quot;privation of the righteousness that every man ought to possess&quot;, thus separating it from concupiscence. In the 12th century the identification of original sin with concupiscence was supported by [[Peter Lombard]] and others, but was rejected by the leading theologians in the next century, chief of whom was [[Thomas Aquinas]]. He distinguished the supernatural gifts of Adam before the Fall from what was merely natural, and said that it was the former that were lost, privileges that enabled man to keep his inferior powers in submission to reason and directed to his supernatural end. Even after the fall, man thus kept his natural abilities of reason, will and passions. Rigorous Augustine-inspired views persisted among the [[Franciscans]], though the most prominent Franciscan theologians, such as [[Duns Scotus]] and [[William of Ockham]], eliminated the element of concupiscence.

===Protestant reformation===
[[Martin Luther]] (1483-1546) asserted that humans inherit Adamic guilt and are in a state of sin from the moment of conception. The second article in [[Lutheranism]]'s [[Augsburg Confession]] presents its doctrine of original sin in summary form:

{{quote|It is also taught among us that since the fall of Adam all men who are born according to the course of nature are conceived and born in sin. That is, all men are full of evil lust and inclinations from their mothers’ wombs and are unable by nature to have true fear of God and true faith in God. Moreover, this inborn sickness and hereditary sin is truly sin and condemns to the eternal wrath of God all those who are not born again through Baptism and the Holy Spirit. Rejected in this connection are the [[Pelagianism|Pelagians]] and others who deny that original sin is sin, for they hold that natural man is made righteous by his own powers, thus disparaging the sufferings and merit of Christ.&lt;ref&gt;Theodore G. Tappert, &lt;cite&gt;The Book of Concord: The Confessions of the Evangelical Lutheran Church&lt;/cite&gt;, (Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1959), 29.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Luther, however, also agreed with the Roman Catholic doctrine of the [[Immaculate Conception]] (that Mary was conceived free from original sin) by saying:
{{quote|[Mary] is full of grace, proclaimed to be entirely without sin. God's grace fills her with everything good and makes her devoid of all evil. God is with her, meaning that all she did or left undone is divine and the action of God in her. Moreover, God guarded and protected her from all that might be hurtful to her.&lt;ref&gt;Luther's Works, American edition, vol. 43, p. 40, ed. H. Lehmann, Fortress, 1968&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Protestant [[Protestant Reformation|Reformer]] [[John Calvin]] (1509-1564) developed a [[systematic theology]] of Augustinian Protestantism by interpretation of [[Augustine of Hippo]]'s notion of original sin. Calvin believed that humans inherit Adamic guilt and are in a state of sin from the moment of conception. This inherently sinful nature (the basis for the [[Calvinism|Calvinistic]] doctrine of &quot;[[total depravity]]&quot;) results in a complete alienation from God and the total inability of humans to achieve reconciliation with God based on their own abilities. Not only do individuals inherit a sinful nature due to Adam's fall, but since he was the federal head and representative of the human race, all whom he represented inherit the guilt of his sin by imputation. [[Redemption (religious)|Redemption]] by Jesus Christ is the only remedy.

[[John Calvin]] defined original sin in his ''[[Institutes of the Christian Religion]]'' as follows: {{quote|Original sin, therefore, seems to be a hereditary depravity and corruption of our nature, diffused into all parts of the soul, which first makes us liable to God's wrath, then also brings forth in us those works which Scripture calls &quot;works of the flesh&quot; (Gal 5:19). And that is properly what Paul often calls sin. The works that come forth from it--such as adulteries, fornications, thefts, hatreds, murders, carousings--he accordingly calls &quot;fruits of sin&quot; (Gal 5:19-21), although they are also commonly called &quot;sins&quot; in Scripture, and even by Paul himself.&lt;ref&gt;John Calvin, ''The Institutes of the Christian Religion'', II.1.8, LCC, 2 vols., trans. Ford Lewis Battles, ed. John T. McNeill (Philadelphia: Westminster, 1960), 251 (page 217 of CCEL edition). Cf. [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/calvin/institutes.html ''Institutes of the Christian Religion''] at the [[Christian Classics Ethereal Library]]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Council of Trent===
The [[Council of Trent]] (1545-1563), while not pronouncing on points disputed among Catholic theologians, condemned the teaching that in baptism the whole of what belongs to the essence of sin is not taken away, but is only cancelled or not imputed, and declared the concupiscence that remains after baptism not truly and properly &quot;sin&quot; in the baptized, but only to be called sin in the sense that it is of sin and inclines to sin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ewtn.com/library/councils/trent5.htm Decree 5 concerning original sin]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1567, soon after the close of the Council of Trent, [[Pope Pius V]] went beyond Trent by sanctioning Aquinas's distinction between nature and supernature in Adam's state before the Fall, condemned the identification of original sin with concupiscence, and approved the view that the unbaptized could have right use of will.{{sfn|ODCC|2005|p=Original sin}}

==Christian doctrines==
[[File:B Escorial 18.jpg|150px|thumb|right|Illuminated parchment, Spain, circa AD 950-955, depicting the Fall of Man, cause of original sin.]]

===Anglicanism===
The original formularies of the Church of England also continue in the Reformation understanding of Original Sin. In the [[Thirty-Nine Articles]], Article IX &quot;Of Original or Birth-sin&quot; states:
{{quote|Original Sin standeth not in the following of Adam, (as the Pelagians do vainly talk;) but it is the fault and corruption of the Nature of every man, that naturally is ingendered of the offspring of Adam; whereby man is very far gone from original righteousness, and is of his own nature inclined to evil, so that the flesh lusteth always contrary to the spirit; and therefore in every person born into this world, it deserveth God's wrath and damnation. And this infection of nature doth remain, yea in them that are regenerated; whereby the lust of the flesh, called in the Greek, Φρονεμα σαρκος, which some do expound the wisdom, some sensuality, some the affection, some the desire, of the flesh, is not subject to the Law of God. And although there is no condemnation for them that believe and are baptized, yet the Apostle doth confess, that concupiscence and lust hath of itself the nature of sin.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.anglicansonline.org/basics/thirty-nine_articles.html&lt;/ref&gt;}}

However, more recent doctrinal statements (e.g. the 1938 report ''Doctrine in the Church of England'') permit a greater variety of understandings of this doctrine. The 1938 report summarizes:
{{quote|Man is by nature capable of communion with God, and only through such communion can he become what he was created to be. &quot;Original sin&quot; stands for the fact that from a time apparently prior to any responsible act of choice man is lacking in this communion, and if left to his own resources and to the influence of his natural environment cannot attain to his destiny as a child of God.&lt;ref&gt;''Doctrine in the Church of England'', 1938, London: SPCK; p. 64&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Catholicism===
The ''[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]'' says:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
By his sin Adam, as the first man, lost the original holiness and justice he had received from God, not only for himself but for all humans.

Adam and Eve transmitted to their descendants human nature wounded by their own first sin and hence deprived of original holiness and justice; this deprivation is called &quot;original sin&quot;.

As a result of original sin, human nature is weakened in its powers, subject to ignorance, suffering and the domination of death, and inclined to sin (this inclination is called &quot;concupiscence&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', 416-418]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Catholic Church teaches that every human person born on this earth is made in the image of God.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1B.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 357]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ignatius.com/Products/MIG-P/man-the-image-of-god.aspx Cardinal Christoph Schonborn, ''Man the Image of God'']&lt;/ref&gt;  Within man &quot;is both the powerful surge toward the good because we are made in the image of God, and the darker impulses toward evil because of the effects of Original Sin.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usccb.org/beliefs-and-teachings/what-we-believe/morality/  United States Conference of Catholic Bishops, &quot;Made in the Image of God&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, it explicitly denies that we inherit ''guilt'' from anyone, maintaining that instead we inherit our fallen nature. In this it differs from the Calvinism/Protestant position that each person actually inherits Adam's guilt, and teaches instead that &quot;original sin does not have the character of a personal fault in any of Adam's descendants ... but the consequences for nature, weakened and inclined to evil, persist in man&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;vatican.va&quot;/&gt; &quot;In other words, human beings do not bear any 'original guilt' from Adam and Eve's particular sin.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacredheartprescott.com/Assets/PDFs/Baptism/OriginalSin.pdf What the Catholic Church Teaches about Original Sin]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Church has always held baptism to be &quot;for the remission of sins&quot;, and, as mentioned in [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', 403], infants too have traditionally been baptized, though not guilty of any actual personal sin. The sin that through baptism was remitted for them could only be original sin, with which they were connected by the very fact of being a human. The first comprehensive theological explanation of this practice of baptizing infants, guilty of no actual personal sin, was given by Saint [[Augustine of Hippo]], not all of whose ideas on original sin have been adopted by the Catholic Church. Indeed the Church has condemned the interpretation of some of his ideas by certain leaders of the [[Protestant Reformation]].

The ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'' explains that in &quot;yielding to the tempter, Adam and Eve committed a ''personal sin'', but this sin affected ''the human nature'' that they would then transmit in a ''fallen state'' … original sin is called &quot;sin&quot; only in an analogical sense: it is a sin &quot;contracted&quot; and not &quot;committed&quot; — a state and not an act&quot; ([http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', 404).] This &quot;state of deprivation of the original holiness and justice … transmitted to the descendants of Adam along with human nature&quot; ([http://www.vatican.va/archive/compendium_ccc/documents/archive_2005_compendium-ccc_en.html#The%20Profession%20of%20the%20Christian%20Faith ''Compendium of the Catechism of the Catholic Church'', 76)] involves no personal responsibility or personal guilt on their part (cf. ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', 405). Personal responsibility and guilt were Adam's, who because of his sin, was unable to pass on to his descendants a human nature with the holiness with which it would otherwise have been endowed, in this way implicating them in his sin. The doctrine of original sin thus does not impute the sin of the father to his children, but merely states that they inherit from him a &quot;human nature deprived of original holiness and justice&quot;, which is &quot;transmitted by propagation to all mankind&quot; ([http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', 404).]

In the theology of the [[Catholic Church]], original sin is regarded as the general condition of [[sin]]fulness, that is (the absence of holiness and perfect charity) into which humans are born, distinct from the [[actual sin]]s that a person commits. This teaching explicitly states that &quot;original sin does not have the character of a personal fault in any of Adam's descendants&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;vatican.va&quot;&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church, 405]&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, human beings do not bear any &quot;original guilt&quot; from Adam's particular sin, which is his alone. The prevailing view, also held in Eastern Orthodoxy, is that human beings bear no guilt for the sin of Adam. The Catholic Church teaches: &quot;By our first parents' sin, the devil has acquired a certain domination over man, even though ''man remains free''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p1s2c1p7.htm#III Item 407] in section 1.2.1.7. Emphasis added.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Catholic doctrine of the [[Immaculate Conception]] of [[Mary, the mother of Jesus|Mary]] is that Mary was conceived free from original sin: &quot;the most Blessed Virgin Mary was, from the first moment of her conception, by a singular grace and privilege of almighty God and by virtue of the merits of Jesus Christ, Savior of the human race, preserved immune from all stain of original sin.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pius IX, ''Ineffabilis Deus'' (1854) quoted in ''Catechism of the Catholic Church'', 491 [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p122a3p2.htm#490]&lt;/ref&gt; The doctrine sees her as an exception to the general rule that human beings are not immune from the reality of original sin.

===Eastern Orthodoxy===
The [[Eastern Orthodox]]'s version of ''original sin'' originates with the Devil, &quot; for the devil sinneth from the beginning. (1 John iii. 8)&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pravoslavieto.com/docs/eng/Orthodox_Catechism_of_Philaret.htm Catechism of St. Philaret], questions 157&lt;/ref&gt; They acknowledge that the introduction of [[ancestral sin]]&lt;ref&gt;The term &quot;ancestral sin&quot; is also used, as in [[Greek language|Greek]] προπατορικὴ ἁμαρτία (e.g. [http://www.parembasis.gr/2003/03_10_16.htm Πόλεμος και φτώχεια - η ορθόδοξη άποψη,] [http://www.monipetraki.gr/sarakosti.html Η νηστεία της Σαρακοστής], [http://www.oodegr.com/oode/protestant/luther_antimonaxismos1.htm Πώς στράφηκε ο Λούθηρος κατά του Μοναχισμού - του Γεωργίου Φλωρόφσκυ]) or προπατορικὸ ἁμάρτημα (e.g. [http://www.apostoliki-diakonia.gr/GR_MAIN/catehism/theologia_zoi/themata.asp?contents=selides_katixisis/contents_TaIeraMistiria.asp&amp;main=kat010&amp;file=4.4.1.htm Απαντήσεις σε ερωτήματα δογματικά - Ανδρέα Θεοδώρου, εκδ. Αποστολικής Διακονίας, 1997, σελ. 156-161,] [http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b26.e.i_despotikes_eortes.01.htm Θεοτόκος και προπατορικό αμάρτημα])&lt;/ref&gt; into the human race affected the subsequent environment for mankind (see also [[traducianism]]). However, they never accepted Augustine of Hippo's notions of original sin and hereditary guilt.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stmaryorthodoxchurch.org/orthodoxy/articles/2004-hughes-sin.php stmaryorthodoxchurch.org]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Orthodox Churches accept the teachings of [[John Cassian]], as do Catholic Churches eastern and western,&lt;ref name=&quot;Reformation Europe&quot;/&gt; in rejecting the doctrine of [[Total Depravity]], by teaching that human nature is &quot;fallen&quot;, that is, depraved, but not totally. Augustine Casiday states that Cassian &quot;baldly asserts that God's grace, not human free will, is responsible for 'everything which pertains to salvation' - even faith.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Casiday-faith&quot;/&gt;  Cassian points out that people still have moral freedom and one has the option to choose to follow God. [[Colm Luibhéid]] says that, according to Cassian, there are cases where the soul makes the first little turn,&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; while Augustine Casiday says that, in Cassian's view, any sparks of goodwill that may exist, not ''directly'' caused by God, are totally inadequate and only ''direct'' divine intervention ensures spiritual progress.&lt;ref name=&quot;Casiday&quot;/&gt; and Lauren Pristas says that &quot;for Cassian, salvation is, from beginning to end, the effect of God's grace.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pristas&quot;/&gt;

Eastern orthodoxy accept the doctrine of ancestral sin.&lt;ref name=&quot;stmary&quot;&gt;See {{cite web|url=http://www.stmaryorthodoxchurch.org/orthodoxy/articles/2004-hughes-sin.php|title=Ancestral Versus Original Sin: An Overview with Implications for Psychotherapy|accessdate=2006-05-11|last=Hughes|first=Antony|publisher=St. Mary Orthodox Church|location=Cambridge, Mass.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/Ancestral-sin-John-S-Romanides/dp/0970730314 John S. Romanides, &quot;The Ancestral Sin (Zephyr Pub 2002 ISBN 978-0-9707303-1-2]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;While the traditional term in Latin Christiandom is &quot;peccatum originale,&quot; with reference to the &quot;origin&quot; of the human race, the traditional term in Greek is &quot;προπατορική αμαρτία&quot; (or &quot;προπατορικό αμάρτημα&quot;, more rarely &quot;προγονική αμαρτία&quot;), with reference to the &quot;ancestor&quot; of the human race). This is the term used also by Roman Catholics when speaking or writing in Greek.&lt;/ref&gt; which indicates that &quot;original sin is hereditary. It did not remain only Adam and Eve's. As life passes from them to all of their descendants, so does original sin &quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gocanada.org/catechism/catorsin.htm Metropolis ''Basic Teachings of the Orthodox Faith''by Greek Orthodox Metropolitan Archbishop Sotirios of Toronto (Canada): ''Original Sin and Its Consequences'']&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Orthodox Church in America makes clear the distinction between &quot;fallen nature&quot; and &quot;fallen man&quot; and this is affirmed in the early teaching of the Church whose role it is to act as the catalyst that leads to true or inner redemption. Every human person born on this earth bears the image of God undistorted within themselves.&lt;ref&gt;Glory to God for all things [http://fatherstephen.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/do-not-resent-do-not-react-keep-inner-stillness]./&lt;/ref&gt; In the Orthodox Christian understanding, they explicitly deny that mankind inherited ''guilt'' from anyone. Rather, they maintain that we inherit our fallen nature. While humanity does bear the consequences of the original, or first, sin, humanity does not bear the personal guilt associated with this sin. Adam and Eve are guilty of their willful action; we bear the consequences, chief of which is death.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fr. John Matusiak, http://www.oca.org/QA.asp?ID=4&amp;SID=3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Methodist===
The [[Methodist Church]], founded by [[John Wesley]], upholds Article VII in the [[Articles of Religion (Methodist)|Articles of Religion]] in the ''[[Book of Discipline (United Methodist)|Book of Discipline of the Methodist Church]]'': {{quote|Original sin standeth not in the following of Adam (as the Pelagians do vainly talk), but it is the corruption of the nature of every man, that naturally is engendered of the offspring of Adam, whereby man is very far gone from original righteousness, and of his own nature inclined to evil, and that continually.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.umc.org/interior.asp?ptid=1&amp;mid=1649 The United Methodist Church: The Articles of Religion of the Methodist Church - Article V—Of the Sufficiency of the Holy Scriptures for Salvation]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Here is a direct comment on original sin by Wesley. &quot;“The Scripture does not, that I remember, anywhere say, in express words, that the sin of Adam is imputed to his children; or, that the sins of believers are imputed to Christ; or, that the righteousness of Christ is imputed to believers: but the true meaning of these expressions is sufficiently found in several places of Scripture.” “Yet since these express words and phrases, of the imputation of Adam’s sin to us, of our sins to Christ, and of Christ’s righteousness to us, are not plainly written in Scripture we should not impose it on every Christian, to use these very expressions. Let every one take his liberty, either of confining himself to strictly Scriptural language, or manifesting his sense of these plain Scriptural doctrines, in words and phrases of his own.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?q=%22that+the+sins+of+believers+are+imputed+to+Christ%22&amp;hl=en&amp;tbm=bks&amp;ei=GyaYT-HROceEhQeKvOXoBQ&amp;start=10&amp;sa=N John Wesley, &quot;A Plain Explication of the Doctrine of Imputed Sin and Imputed Righteousness&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Wesley also stated that strictly speaking, nothing is sin but a willful transgression of a known commandment of God: &quot;One thing we should all agree on is that all have sinned and come short of the glory of God, and are in need of a Savior. I personally feel that the only Scriptural definition of sin is; sin is the willful transgression of a known commandment of God.&quot; {{Citation needed|reason=reliable source needed for the whole sentence|date=April 2012}}

===Seventh-day Adventism===
[[Seventh-day Adventists]] have not held to or been comfortable with the [[Augustine of Hippo|Augustinian]]/[[Calvinism|Calvinistic]] understanding of original sin, taught in terms of original guilt, but hold more to what
could be termed the [[Total depravity|&quot;total depravity&quot;]] tradition.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bibelschule.info/streaming/Woodrow-W.-Whidden---Adventist-Theology---The-Wesleyan-Connection_23617.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; According to Augustine and Calvin, mankind inherits not only Adam's depraved nature but also the actual guilt of his transgression, and Adventist look more toward the Wesleyan model.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pfandl original sin&quot;&gt;{{Citation|author=Gerhard Pfandl|url=http://www.adventistbiblicalresearch.org/documents/sinoriginal-web.pdf|title=Some thoughts on Original Sin|publisher=Biblical Research Institute}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early Adventists Pioneers (such as George Storrs and [[Uriah Smith]]) tended to de-emphasise the morally corrupt nature inherited from Adam, while stressing the importance of actual, personal sins committed by the individual. They thought of the &quot;sinful nature&quot; in terms of physical mortality rather than moral depravity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pfandl original sin&quot;/&gt; Traditionally, Adventists look at sin in terms of willful transgressions, and that Christ triumphed over sin. Adventism believe that Christ is both our Substitute and our Example.&lt;ref name=&quot;Christ's Human Nature&quot;&gt;[http://www.amazingfacts.org/FreeStuff/OnlineLibrary/tabid/106/ctl/ViewMedia/mid/447/IID/87/LNG/en/SC/R/Default.aspx?7=Christ%27s-Human-Nature Christ's Human Nature]&lt;/ref&gt; They base their belief on texts such as &quot;Whosoever committeth sin transgresseth also the law: for sin is the transgression of the law.&quot; (1 John 3:4)&lt;ref&gt;[http://qod.andrews.edu/docs/16_larry_kirkpatrick.doc Questions on Doctrines Documents via Andrews University]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The authoritative Adventist position is outlined by reference to publicly available theological positions available on the [[General Conference of the Seventh-day Adventist Church]]’s official website on theological doctrine, the [[Biblical Research Institute]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adventistbiblicalresearch.org/ adventistbiblicalresearch.org]&lt;/ref&gt; One such article commenting on original sin can be found
[http://www.adventistbiblicalresearch.org/documents/wesleyanconnectionSDA.htm here].

===Other doctrinal views===

====American Restoration Movement====
{{Unreferenced section|date=August 2012}}

In Campbellism, the [[Restoration Movement]] Churches' concept of ''original sin'' is that Adam and Eve brought sin into the world through disobedience. Adam's sin made mankind predisposed towards sin so that every person sins. However, mankind does not share Adam's guilt nor are they held accountable for his sin. 
They support the concept that individually, men and women are held responsible for their own personal sins. They use Ezekiel 18 to reference verses 1-4, where God's people are rebuked for suggesting that children would die/suffer for their father's sins. Verses 19 and 20, where guilt is not shared between a son and his father, and verses 30 and 31 where God's people are judged according to their own ways. A common belief among [[Campbellite]]s is that Adam and Eve sinned as a result of their making a wrong free-will choice when they were tempted by the serpent, and as a result brought &quot;the knowledge of good and evil&quot; upon themselves and all people after them. Although man still retains his free-will it is this &quot;knowledge of good and evil&quot; that makes it difficult for him to live without committing sin.

====Latter-day Saints====
{{third-party|date=August 2012}}
{{see also|Adam and Eve (LDS Church)}}

In the [[Latter Day Saint movement]], ''original sin'' is viewed as a necessary transgression needed to experience joy in order to fulfill the commandment to &quot;multiply and replenish&quot; the earth (Gen 1:28).&lt;ref&gt;[[Book of Mormon]], 2 Nephi 2:22-25: 22. And now, behold, if Adam had not transgressed he would not have fallen, but he would have remained in the garden of Eden. And all things which were created must have remained in the same state in which they were after they were created; and they must have remained forever, and had no end. 23. And they would have had no children; wherefore they would have remained in a state of innocence, having no joy, for they knew no misery; doing no good, for they knew no sin. 24. But behold, all things have been done in the wisdom of him who knoweth all things. 25. Adam fell that men might be; and men are, that they might have joy. ([[Book of Mormon]], 2 Nephi 2:22-25)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Pearl of Great Price (Latter Day Saints)|Pearl of Great Price]], Moses 5:10-11: 10. And in that day Adam blessed God and was filled, and began to prophesy concerning all the families of the earth, saying: Blessed be the name of God, for because of my transgression my eyes are opened, and in this life I shall have joy, and again in the flesh I shall see God. 11. And Eve, his wife, heard all these things and was glad, saying: Were it not for our transgression we never should have had seed, and never should have known good and evil, and the joy of our redemption, and the eternal life which God giveth unto all the obedient.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Mormonism]], everyone will be punished for their own individual sins and not for any transgression of Adam or Eve.&lt;ref&gt;[http://scriptures.lds.org/en/a_of_f/1 Articles of Faith, article #2]&lt;/ref&gt; Three of their thirteen [[Articles of Faith]] state:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://scriptures.lds.org/en/a_of_f/1 |title=The Articles of the Faith |accessdate=2008-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ol start=2&gt;&lt;li&gt; We believe that men will be punished for their own sins, and not for Adam’s transgression.
&lt;li&gt; We believe that through the Atonement of Christ, all mankind may be saved, by obedience to the laws and ordinances of the Gospel.
&lt;li&gt; We believe that the first principles and ordinances of the Gospel are: first, Faith in the Lord Jesus Christ; second, Repentance; third, Baptism by immersion for the remission of sins; fourth, Laying on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost.
&lt;/ol&gt;
Therefore, Mormons do not believe that children come into the world with any guilt, because Jesus Christ atoned for &quot;original guilt&quot;. Therefore, the sins of the parents cannot be answered upon the heads of their children.&lt;ref&gt;Moses 6:53-54 in the [[Pearl of Great Price]]: 53. And our father Adam spake unto the Lord, and said: Why is it that men must repent and be baptized in water? And the Lord said unto Adam: Behold I have forgiven thee thy transgression in the Garden of Eden.
54. Hence came the saying abroad among the people, that the Son of God hath atoned for original guilt, wherein the sins of the parents cannot be answered upon the heads of the children, for they are whole from the foundation of the world.&lt;/ref&gt; It is also considered that children are incapable of committing sin and therefore have no need of baptism until age eight when they can begin to learn to discern right from wrong and are thus capable of sin and can be held accountable.&lt;ref&gt;Book of Mormon, Moroni 8:8-9: 8. Listen to the words of Christ, your Redeemer, your Lord and your God. Behold I came into the world not to call the righteous but sinners to repentance; the whole need no physician, but they that are sick; wherefore, little children are whole, for they are not capable of committing sin; wherefore the curse of Adam is taken from them in me, that it hath no power over them; and the law of circumcision is done away in me. 9. And after this manner did the Holy Ghost Manifest the word of God unto me; wherefore my beloved son, I know that it is solemn mockery before God, that ye should baptize little children.&lt;/ref&gt; Little children who die before reaching the age of accountability (even though they are unbaptized) are automatic heirs of salvation and are saved in the [[Celestial Kingdom]] of God through the atonement of Jesus Christ. Furthermore those who die &quot;without the law&quot; are under no condemnation nor accountability.&lt;ref&gt;Book of Mormon, Moroni 8:22-24: 22. For behold that all little children are alive in Christ, and also all they that are without the law. For the power of redemption cometh on all them that have no law; wherefore, he that is not condemned, or he that is under no condemnation, cannot repent; and unto such baptism availeth nothing— 23. But it is mockery before God, denying the mercies of Christ, and the power of his Holy Spirit, and putting trust in dead works. 24. Behold, my son, this thing ought not to be; for repentance is unto them that are under condemnation and under the curse of a broken law.&lt;/ref&gt; Those incapable of understanding right from wrong, such as the [[mentally handicapped]], are also saved under the atonement of Jesus Christ without baptism. Any adults who die without a knowledge of God's commands (Law) do need baptism, which they can receive in the spiritual realm by accepting the Latter-day Saint vicarious practice of [[Baptism for the dead]].

====Swedenborgianism====
In [[Swedenborgianism]], [[exegesis]] of the first 11 chapters of Genesis from ''The First Church'', has a view that [[Adam]] is not an individual person. Rather, he is a symbolic representation of the &quot;Most Ancient Church&quot;, having a more direct contact with heaven than all other successive churches.{{sfn|Swedenborg|1749-56|p=410: [url=http://books.google.com/books?id=U3tQJ9j_1ToC&amp;pg=PR3&amp;lpg=PR3&amp;dq=Arcana+Coelestia+john+f+potts&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=kiaZ2hbwTG&amp;sig=P-jzl0rzPlua-881yeIcjKLo2ZY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=hW0yUKu6A6OSiAKtmoDgAw&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=ancient%20church%20adam&amp;f=false n. 1101-1150]}} Swedenborg's view of original sin is referred to as ''hereditary evil'', which passes from generation to generation.{{sfn|Swedenborg|1749-56|p=96, n.313: &quot;But as to hereditary evil, the case is this. Everyone who commits actual sin thereby induces on himself a nature, and the evil from it is implanted in his children, and becomes hereditary. It thus descends from every parent, from the father, grandfather, great-grandfather, and their ancestors in succession, and is thus multiplied and augmented in each descending posterity, remaining with each person, and being increased in each by his actual sins, and never being dissipated so as to become harmless except in those who are being regenerated by the Lord. Every attentive observer may see evidence of this truth in the fact that the evil inclinations of parents remain visibly in their children, so that one family, and even an entire race, may be thereby distinguished from every other.&quot;}} It cannot be completely abolished, but can be tempered when someone reforms their own life,{{sfn|Swedenborg|1749-56|p=229, n.719:&quot;There are evils in man which must be dispersed while he is being regenerated, that is, which must be loosened and attempered by goods; for no actual and hereditary evil in man can be so dispersed as to be abolished. It still remains implanted; and can only be so far loosened and attempered by goods from the Lord that it does not injure, and does not appear, which is an arcanum hitherto unknown. Actual evils are those which are loosened and attempered, and not hereditary evils; which also is a thing unknown.&quot;}} and are thus held accountable only for their own sins.{{sfn|Swedenborg|1749-56|p=336, n.966: &quot;It is to be observed that in the other life no one undergoes any punishment and torture on account of his hereditary evil, but only on account of the actual evils which he himself has committed.&quot;}}

==Original sin and extraterrestrials==
In an interview entitled &quot;Aliens Are My Brother&quot;, granted to [[L'Osservatore Romano]], the Vatican newspaper, Father [[José Gabriel Funes]], director of the [[Vatican Observatory]], stated: &quot;In my opinion this possibility (of life on other planets) exists&quot;; &quot;intelligent beings, created by God may exist in outer space&quot; and &quot;some aliens could even be free from original sin&quot; concluding &quot;there could be (other beings) who remained in full friendship with their creator&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/scienceNewsMolt/idUKL146364620080514 | work=Reuters | title=Vatican scientist says belief in God and aliens is OK | date=14 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/24598261/]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://catholicnewsagency.com/new.php?n=12628 Catholic News Agency]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/7399661.stm?lsm | work=BBC News | first=David | last=Willey | title=Vatican says aliens could exist | date=13 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea that on other planets beings could exist in an [[Fall of man|unfallen]] state was explored by [[C. S. Lewis]] in his novel ''[[Out of the Silent Planet]]''.

And on 5 March 2009, [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] Brother [[Guy Consolmagno]], another astronomer working at the Vatican Observatory, told the BBC, in relation to the search for Earth-like worlds about to be embarked upon by the [[Kepler Mission|Kepler Space telescope]], that &quot;we Jesuits are actively involved in the search for Earth-like planets. The idea that there could be other intelligent creatures made by God in a relationship with God is not contrary to traditional Judeo-Christian thought. The Bible has many references to, or descriptions of, non-human intelligent beings; after all, that's what angels are. Our cousins on other planets may even have their own salvation story – including other examples of the incarnation of the second person of the Trinity. We are open to whatever the Universe has for us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/7918497.stm |title=Is there anybody out there? |accessdate=3 March 2009 | work=BBC News |date=5 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With regard to the attribution to &quot;the Vatican&quot; of similar statements by individuals working for the [[Holy See]], official spokesman Father [[Federico Lombardi]], also a Jesuit, published on 21 February 2009 a declaration that they must not be mistaken for statements of the Holy See— they are only statements of this individual Jesuit priest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://212.77.1.245/news_services/bulletin/news/23450.php?index=23450&amp;lang=it Declaration by the Director of the Press Office of the Holy See, Reverend Father Federico Lombardi, S.J.] Retrieved 22 February 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
Historian [[Robin Lane Fox]] argues that the foundation of the doctrine of ''original sin'', that was accepted by the Church, was based on a ''mis-translation'' of [[Paul the Apostle]]'s [[Epistle to the Romans]] ({{bibleverse||Romans|5:12-21}}) by Augustine, in his &quot;On the Grace of Christ, and on Original Sin&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Fox|first=Robin Lane|title=The unauthorized version : truth and fiction in the Bible|year=2006|publisher=Penguin|location=London|isbn=9780141022963}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity|Religion}}
{{div col|cols=3}}
*[[Actual sin]]
*[[Ancestral sin]]
*[[Deadly sin]]
*[[Divine grace]]
*[[Eternal sin]] (aka unforgivable or unpardonable sin)
*[[Fall of Man]]
*[[Hamartiology]]
*[[Immaculate Conception]]
*[[Incurvatus in se]]
*[[Internal sin]]
*[[Justification (theology)]]
*[[Mortal sin]]
*[[Pandora's box]]
*[[Prevenient grace]]
*[[Sin]]
*[[The Antichrist (book)]]
*[[Total depravity]]
*[[Venial sin]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Ibid|date=March 2010}}
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite journal|last=Brachtendorf|first=J.|title=Cicero and Augustine on the Passions|journal=Revue des Etudes Augustiniennes|year=1997|volume=43|url=http://documents.irevues.inist.fr/bitstream/handle/2042/23075/AUGUST_1997_43_2_289.pdf?sequence=1|pages=289–308|publisher=Institut d'études augustiniennes|location=Paris}}
* {{cite book|last=Catechism|first=U.S. Catholic Church|title=Catechism of the Catholic Church : with modifications from the Editio Typica.|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wRrxsUhIEZcC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Catechism+of+the+Catholic+Church&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=g45Vduiunk&amp;sig=RZOP4R1PO-es4qynjjpJvThd-Cg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=InU0ULHPB6jziwLnwYCQCg&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAg#v=snippet&amp;q=freedom%20put%20to%20test&amp;f=false|year=2003|publisher=Doubleday|location=New York|isbn=9780385508193|edition=2nd|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Kelly|first=J.N.D.|title=Early Christian doctrines|year=2000|publisher=[[Continuum International Publishing Group|Continuum]]|location=London|isbn=9780826452528|edition=5th rev. ed.}}
*{{cite book|last=ODCC|first=ed. by Frank Leslie Cross|title=The Oxford dictionary of the Christian Church|chapter=Original sin|year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|isbn=9780192802903|author-link=Frank Leslie Cross|edition=3rd rev.|coauthors=Elizabeth A. Livingstone|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Swedenborg|first=Emanuel|author-link=Emanuel Swedenborg|title=Arcana Coelestia, Vol. 1 of 8|year=1749-56|publisher=Forgotten Books|isbn=9781606201077|edition=2008 Reprint|coauthors=Trans. by John F. Potts}}
* {{cite book|last=Trapè|first=Agostino|title=S. Agostino, introduzione alla dottrina della grazia|year=1987|publisher=Nuova Biblioteca agostiniana|series = Collana di Studi Agostiniani 4|volume = I - Natura e Grazia|location=Roma|isbn=88-311-3402-7|pages=422}}
* {{cite book|last=Turner|first=H.E.W|title=The patristic doctrine of redemption : a study of the development of doctrine during the first five centuries / by H.E.W. Turner.|publisher=[[Wipf &amp; Stock Publishers]]|location=Eugene, Or.|isbn=9781592449309|edition=2004 Reprint}}
* {{cite book|last=Wallace|first=A.J.|title=Moral transformation : the original Christian paradigm of salvation|year=2010|publisher=Bridgehead Publishing|location=New Zealand|isbn=9781456389802|coauthors=R. D. Rusk}}

==External links==
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/11312a.htm Article &quot;Original Sin&quot; in Catholic Encyclopedia]
* [http://www.bookofconcord.org/augsburgdefense/2_originalsin.html ''The Book of Concord''] ''The Defense of the Augsburg Confession'', Article II: Of Original Sin; from an early Protestant perspective, part of the [[Augsburg Confession]].
* [http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.10.en.original_sin_according_to_st._paul.01.htm Original Sin According To St. Paul] by [[John S. Romanides]]
* [http://silouanthompson.net/2008/12/ancestral-versus-original-sin/ Ancestral Versus Original Sin] by Father Antony Hughes, St. Mary Antiochian Orthodox Church, Cambridge, Massachusetts
* [http://www.mbrem123.com/man/origsin.php Original Sin] by Michael Bremmer

;Catholicism
*{{cite web|last=Creed5|first=Council of Trent|title=Canones et Decreta Dogmatica Concilii Tridentini: Fifth Session, Decree concerning Original Sin|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds2.v.i.i.iii.html|publisher=at www.ccel.org|author=Council of Trent|date=June 17, 1546}}

{{Hamartiology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Original Sin}}
[[Category:Christian philosophy]]
[[Category:Christian hamartiology]]
[[Category:Jewish mysticism]]
[[Category:Christian theology]]
[[Category:Adam and Eve]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Sin]]

[[ar:الخطيئة الأصلية]]
[[bg:Първороден грях]]
[[ca:Pecat original]]
[[cs:Prvotní hřích]]
[[da:Arvesynd]]
[[de:Erbsünde]]
[[et:Pärispatt]]
[[el:Προπατορικό αμάρτημα]]
[[es:Pecado original]]
[[eo:Prapeko]]
[[fa:گناه نخستین]]
[[fr:Péché originel]]
[[gl:Pecado orixinal]]
[[ko:원죄]]
[[hr:Istočni grijeh]]
[[id:Dosa asal]]
[[it:Peccato originale]]
[[he:החטא הקדמון]]
[[sw:Dhambi ya asili]]
[[la:Peccatum originale]]
[[lv:Iedzimtais grēks]]
[[hu:Eredendő bűn]]
[[ml:ആദിപാപം]]
[[nl:Erfzonde]]
[[ja:原罪]]
[[no:Arvesynd]]
[[pl:Grzech pierworodny]]
[[pt:Pecado original]]
[[ro:Păcat originar]]
[[ru:Первородный грех]]
[[simple:Original sin]]
[[sk:Prvotný hriech]]
[[sl:Izvirni greh]]
[[sr:Првородни грех]]
[[sh:Praroditeljski grijeh]]
[[fi:Perisynti]]
[[sv:Arvsynd]]
[[tl:Kasalanang orihinal]]
[[th:บาปกำเนิด]]
[[uk:Перворідний гріх]]
[[zh:原罪]]</text>
      <sha1>2q3emlqtv3xv0zyum4728cw79poi823</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
