<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Parousia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24393</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519168665</id>
      <parentid>518041156</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-22T08:53:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>178.149.117.242</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9792">{{Religious text primary|date=November 2011}}
'''Parousia''' ([[Help:IPA_for_Greek|IPA]]: ''{{IPAc-en|icon|p|ə|ˈ|r|uː|z|i|ə}}''; [[Greek alphabet|Greek]]: ''Παρουσία'') is an [[ancient Greek]] word meaning presence, arrival, or official visit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dparousi%2Fa Entry for parousia in the Liddell–Scott lexicon]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classical usage==
# '''''Physical presence, arrival''''' – The main use is the physical presence of a person,&lt;ref&gt;[[LSJ]] A. presence, of persons, δεσπότου, etc., A.Pers. 169, etc. ; ἀνδρῶν π., = ἄνδρες οἱ παρόντες, E.Alc.606 ; πόλις μείζων τῆς ἡμετέρας π., = ἡμῶν τῶν παρόντων, Th.6.86 ; παρουσίαν μὲν οἶσθα . . φίλων, ὡς οὔτις ἡμῖν ἐστιν, i.e. that we have no friends present to assist us, S.El.948 ; of things, “κακῶν” E.Hec.227, Ar.Th.1049 ; “ἀγαθῶν” Pl.Grg.497e : abs., παρουσίαν ἔχειν, = παρεῖναι, S.Aj.540 ; “τὰ τῆς τύχης . . κοινὰς [ἔχει] τὰς παρουσίας” D.Prooem.39 ; “αὐτὸ τὸ ἀγαθὸν [αἴτιον] τῇ π. τοῖς ἄλλοις τοῦ ἀγαθὰ εἶναι” Arist.EE1217b5, cf. Pl.Phd. 100d, etc.&lt;/ref&gt; which where that person is not already present refers to the prospect of the physical arrival of that person,&lt;ref&gt;[[LSJ]] &quot;2. arrival, ἡμῶν κοινόπουν π. S.El.1104, cf. E.Alc.209, Th.1.128 ; “εἰς Ἰταλίαν” D.H.1.45&lt;/ref&gt; especially the visit of a royal or official personage&lt;ref&gt;[[LSJ]] &quot;βασιλέως, etc., PTeb.48.14 (ii B. C.), IPE12.32A85 (Olbia, iii B.C.), etc.; of a god, IG42(1).122.34(Epid.).&lt;/ref&gt; and sometimes as an extension of this usage, a formal &quot;occasion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;LSJ &quot;3. occasion, v.l. in S. El.1251. 4. π. τισὶ ποιεῖσθαι entertain them on their official visits, OGI139.9 (Philae, ii B.C.).&lt;/ref&gt; In astrological usage it refers to the presence of a planet at a point on the zodiac.&lt;ref&gt;, “ἤτοι κατὰ παρουσίαν ἢ κατὰ συμμαρτυρίαν” Vett.Val.49.26.&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''''Property''''' – A less common and distinct secondary meaning is to refer to a person's material substance, property, or inheritance,&lt;ref&gt;“ὡς . . ἔχομεν παρουσίας” Pl.Com.177, cf. Men.471 ; “π. χρημάτων” Crates Com.16.&lt;/ref&gt; including contribution in money.&lt;ref&gt;, Sch. Luc.Phal.1.3 (pl.).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Septuagint==
The term occurs only twice in the [[Septuagint]] (2 Maccabees 8:12 and 15:21) in its ordinary meaning of arrival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Israel Perkins |last=Warren |title=The Parousia |year=1879 |chapter=The Term and Signification |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=nNhGAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA9 |page=2–16 |quote=It is found but twice in the Septuagint (2 Macc. 8:12 ; 15:21), and there only in its ordinary secular meaning.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==New Testament==
The word is used 24 times in the [[New Testament]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blueletterbible.org/lang/lexicon/lexicon.cfm?Strongs=G3952&amp;t=KJV New Testament usages 24x]&lt;/ref&gt; Of these, six uses refer to the coming of individuals: Stephanas, Fortunatus, and Achaicus (1Co.16:17), Titus (2Co.7:6 &amp; 7) the physical &quot;presence&quot; of Paul himself (2Co.10:10, Php.1:26, 2:12), and a 7th use to the &quot;coming of the [[Man of Lawlessness|lawless one]]&quot; (2Thess.2:9). The other seventeen uses refer to the [[Second Coming of Christ]], except the one case in which it refers to the coming of the &quot;Day of God&quot; (2Pe.3:12, see also [[The Day of the Lord]]).

The word parousia is found in the following verses: Matthew 24:3, 27, 37, 39; 1 Corinthians 15:23; 1 Thessalonians 2:19; 3:13; 4:15; 5:23; 2 Thessalonians 2:1, 8, 9; James 5:7, 8; 2 Peter 1:16; 3:4, 12; 1 John 2:28.

==Theological usage==
{{main|Second Coming of Christ}}
The main use in theology is to refer to the second coming of Christ. However [[Karl Barth]] considered that category of parousia includes [[Resurrection of Jesus|Resurrection Sunday]] and the Acts&amp;nbsp;2 [[Pentecost]] as well, and therefore that the New Testament parousia is not limited to his final return.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Joseph L. |last=Mangina |chapter=Reconciliation has eschatological force |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=8a5Buh4QzZQC&amp;pg=PA118 |title=Karl Barth: theologian of Christian witness |year=2004 |page=118 |quote=This will occur at Christ's final coming or parousia. Yet Barth expands the category of parousia to include Easter and Pentecost as well; the parousia is not limited to his final return (IV/3, 293 ff.)&quot; |publisher=Ashgate |location=Aldershot |isbn=978-0-7546-0458-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related terms==
The following Greek-English words may be related to, and can be distinguished from, ''parousia'':
* [[wikt:epiphany|epiphany]] &quot;appearing&quot;: The Greek word ''epiphaneia'' was often used by Greeks to describe the glorious manifestation of the gods, and by the Romans as a title for the Emperor.&lt;ref&gt;
{{quote|Henceforth there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, will award to me on that Day, and not only to me but also to all who have loved his appearing.|II Timothy 4:8}}
{{quote|Awaiting our blessed hope, the appearing of the glory of our great God and Saviour Jesus Christ.|Titus 2:13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[apocalypse]], &quot;revealing&quot;, &quot;revelation&quot;: To disclose what is invisible.&lt;ref&gt;{{quote|So that you are not lacking in any spiritual gift, as you wait for the revealing of our Lord Jesus Christ, who will sustain you to the end, guiltless in the Day of our Lord Jesus Christ.|I Corinthians 1:7–8}}
{{quote|And to grant rest with us to you who are afflicted, when the Lord Jesus is revealed from heaven with his mighty angels in flaming fire, inflicting vengeance upon those who do not know God and upon those who do not obey the gospel of our Lord Jesus. They shall suffer the punishment of eternal destruction from the face of the Lord and from the glory of his might, when he comes on that Day to be glorified in his saints, and to be marvelled at in all who have believed.|II Thessalonians 1: 7 ff.}}
{{quote|You have to suffer various trials so that the genuineness of your faith, more precious than gold that perishes yet refined with fire, may be found to the praise and glory and honour at the revelation of Jesus Christ, whom having not seen you love.|I Peter 1: 7}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-----LOOKS LIKE OR – IN WHAT WAY IS &quot;DAY&quot; RELATED TO &quot;ARRIVAL&quot;??  
Day: The day of days when the Messiah returns to reward and punish. 

{{quote|For it is not the hearers of the Law who are righteous before God, but the doers of the Law who will be justified. When Gentiles who are without the Law do naturally what the Law requires, they show the work of the Law written on their hearts and their conscience witnesses to it by accusing or excusing their behaviour, revealed on the Day, when according to my gospel, God judges the secrets of men by Christ Jesus.|Romans 2:13–16}}

{{quote|For we must all appear before the tribunal seat of Christ in order that each one may receive an award commensurate with what he has done in the body, good or worthless.    For we shall all stand before the tribunal seat of God, for it is written; “As I live, says the Lord, every knee shall bow to me, and every tongue confess to God.” So each of us shall give account of himself to God.|Romans 14: 10-12}}

{{quote|Now if any one builds on the foundation with gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay or stubble, each ones’ work will be manifested because the Day will disclose it, because it will be revealed with fire, and the fire will test what sort of work each one has done. If the work done remains he will receive a reward, but if any ones work is burned up, he will suffer loss, yet be saved nevertheless through fire.|II Corinthians 5:10}}

{{quote|Let us consider how to stir up one another to love and good works, not neglecting to meet together as the habit is of some, but encouraging one another, and all the more as you see the Day approaching. For if we sin deliberately after receiving the knowledge of the truth, there remains no more sacrifice for sins, but a fearful expectation of judgement which will devour the adversaries.|Hebrews 10:26–31}}

{{quote|For as the Father raises the dead and gives them life, so also the Son gives life to whom he will. The Father judges no one, but has given all judgement to the Son, that all may honour the Son even as they honour the Father.... Truly truly, I say to you, the hour is coming, and now is, when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God, and those who hear shall live. For as the Father has life in himself, so he has granted the Son also to have life in himself, and has given him authority to execute judgement because he is the Son of Man. Do not marvel at this because an hour is coming when all who are in the tombs will hear his voice, and come out, those who have done good things to a resurrection of life, but those who have done evil things to a resurrection of judgement.|John 5:21–29}}

{{quote|And just as it is appointed for men to die once, and after this judgement, so also Christ having been offered once to bear the sins of many, will appear a second time not to deal with sin but to save those who eagerly wait for him.|Hebrews 9:27}}------&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:New Testament Greek words and phrases]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[ar:باروسيا]]
[[az:Parusiya]]
[[ca:Parusia]]
[[cs:Parusie]]
[[de:Parusie]]
[[es:Parusía]]
[[fr:Parousie]]
[[ia:Parousia]]
[[it:Parusia]]
[[pl:Paruzja]]
[[ru:Парусия]]
[[sr:Парусија]]
[[sk:Parusia]]</text>
      <sha1>g121v0jj4smxs8xx1ww4rz9ertr1r29</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
