<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Passover</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23059</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521869373</id>
      <parentid>521826342</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T19:19:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ReformedArsenal</username>
        <id>15109262</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/Lisa|Lisa]] ([[User talk:Lisa|talk]]) identified as [[WP:VAND|vandalism]] to last revision by ReformedArsenal. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="56122">{{About|the Jewish holiday}}
{{Redirect|Pesakh|the military leader|Pesakh (general)}}
''
{{Infobox holiday
|image = Pessach Pesach Pascha Judentum Ungesaeuert Seder datafox.jpg
|caption = 
|holiday_name = Passover
|official_name = [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]]: '''פסח''' (''Pesach'')
|observedby = [[Judaism|Jews]], [[Samaritan]]s, some [[Christians]] including [[Malayali Nasrani Christians]], [[Knanaya]] and followers of [[Messianic Judaism]].
|begins = 15th day of [[Nisan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.timeanddate.com/holidays/jewish/first-day-of-passover |title=First day of Passover |work=timeanddate.com |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rabbinicalcollege.edu.au/holidays/passover/pesach_cdo/aid/871715/jewish/What-Is-Passover.htm |title=What Is Passover? |publisher=Rabbinical College of Australia and N.Z. |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|ends = 21st day of [[Nisan]] in [[Israel]], and among some liberal [[Jewish diaspora|Diaspora Jews]]; 22nd day of [[Nisan]] outside of [[Israel]] among more traditional Diaspora Jews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.timeanddate.com/holidays/jewish/last-day-of-passover |title=Last day of Passover |work=timeanddate.com |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|celebrations = In Jewish practice, one or two festive [[Passover Seder|Seder]] meals – first two nights; in the times of the [[Temple in Jerusalem]], the [[Passover sacrifice]]. In Samaritan practice, men gather for a religious ceremony on [[mount Gerizim]] that includes the ancient cow Sacrifice.
|date2012 = sunset of Friday 6 April to nightfall of Friday 13 April&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;Saturday 14 April (7th day)
|date2013 = sunset of Monday 25 March to nightfall of Monday 1 April&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;Tuesday 2 April (7th day)
|date2014 = sunset of Monday 14 April to nightfall of Monday 21 April&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;Tuesday 22 April (7th day)
|date2015 = sunset of Friday 3 April to nightfall of Friday 10 April&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;Saturday 11 April (7th day)
|type = One of the [[Three Pilgrim Festivals]]
|significance = Celebrates the [[The Exodus|Exodus]], the freedom from [[slavery]] of the [[Children of Israel]] from [[History of ancient Egypt|ancient Egypt]] that followed the [[Ten Plagues]].&lt;br /&gt;
Beginning of the 49 days of [[Counting of the Omer]]
|relatedto = [[Shavuot]] (&quot;Festival of Weeks&quot;) which follows 49 days from the second night of Passover.
}}

'''Passover''' ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], [[Yiddish language|Yiddish]]: פֶּסַח ''Pesach,'' [[Tiberian Hebrew|Tiberian]]: {{IPA-he|pɛsaħ||He-Pesach.ogg}}, [[Modern Hebrew]]: /ˈpesaχ/ ''Pesah, Pesakh,'' Yiddish: ''Peysekh, Paysakh, Paysokh'') is a [[Jew]]ish festival.  It commemorates the story of [[the Exodus]], in which the [[ancient Israelites]] were freed from [[slavery]] in [[ancient Egypt|Egypt]].  Passover begins on the 15th day of the month of [[Nisan]] in the [[Jewish calendar]], which is in spring in the [[Northern Hemisphere]], and is celebrated for seven or eight days.  It is one of the most widely observed Jewish holidays.

In the narrative of [[the Exodus]], the Bible tells that [[Names of God|God]] helped the [[Children of Israel]] escape slavery in Egypt by inflicting [[ten plagues]] upon the Egyptians before the [[Pharaoh]] would release his Israelite slaves; the tenth and worst of the plagues was the death of the Egyptian first-born.  The Israelites were instructed to mark the doorposts of their homes with the blood of a spring lamb and, upon seeing this, the spirit of the Lord knew to ''pass over'' the first-borns in these homes, hence the name of the holiday.{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:11-13|HE}} There is some debate over where the term is actually derived from.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:12|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When the Pharaoh freed the Israelites, it is said that they left in such a hurry that they could not wait for bread dough to rise (leaven). In commemoration, for the duration of Passover no [[leaven|leavened bread]] is eaten, for which reason it is called &quot;The Festival of the Unleavened Bread&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Lev|23:6|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Numbers|28:17|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Numbers|33:3|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Matzo]]'' (flat unleavened bread) is a symbol of the holiday.

Together with [[Shavuot]] (&quot;Pentecost&quot;) and [[Sukkot]] (&quot;Tabernacles&quot;), Passover is one of the [[three pilgrimage festivals]] (''Shalosh Regalim'') during which the entire Jewish populace historically made a pilgrimage to the [[Temple in Jerusalem]].&lt;ref&gt;David M. Gitlitz &amp; Linda Kay Davidson ''Pilgrimage and the Jews'' (Westport: CT: Praeger, 2006), 24-35.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Samaritan]]s still make this pilgrimage to [[Mount Gerizim]], but only men participate in public worship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.ynet.co.il/english/articles/0,7340,L-3394699,00.html |date=2007-05-02 |last=K'fir |first=Amnon |title=The Samaritans' Passover sacrifice |publisher=ynet news |accessdate=2008-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/854549.html |newspaper=Haaretz |title=Ancient Samaritan sect marks Passover sacrifice near Nablus |date=2007-01-05 |accessdate=2008-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Date and duration==

The Passover begins on the 15th day of the month of [[Nisan]], which typically falls in March or April of the [[Gregorian calendar]]. Passover is a spring festival, so the 14th day of Nisan begins on the night of a full [[moon]] after the northern [[vernal equinox]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} To ensure that Passover did not start before spring, the tradition in ancient Israel held that the first day of Nisan would not start until the barley was ripe, being the test for the onset of spring.&lt;ref&gt;The barley had to be &quot;eared` out&quot; (ripe) in order to have a wave-sheaf offering of the first fruits according to the Law. {{cite book |title=Secrets of Time |last=Jones |first=Stephen |year=1996}} This also presupposes that the cycle is based on the northern hemisphere seasons.&lt;/ref&gt; If the barley was not ripe, or various other phenomena&lt;ref&gt;&quot;..., when the fruit had not grown properly, when the winter rains had not stopped, when the roads for Passover pilgrims had not dried up, and when the young pigeons had not become fledged. The council on intercalation considered the astronomical facts together with the religious requirements of Passover and the natural conditions of the country.&quot; - {{Cite book | last=Spier | first=Arthur | title=The Comprehensive Hebrew Calendar | year=1952 | publisher=Behrman House, Inc. | location=New York}}, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; indicated that spring was not yet imminent, an [[Intercalation (timekeeping)|intercalary month]] ([[Adar II]]) would be added. However, since at least the 4th century, the date has been fixed mathematically.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In the fourth century, ... the patriarch [[Hillel II]] ... made public the system of calendar calculation which up to then had been a closely guarded secret. It had been used in the past only to check the observations and testimonies of witnesses, and to determine the beginning of the spring season.&quot; - Spier 1952, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Land of Israel|Israel]], Passover is the seven-day holiday of the Feast of Unleavened Bread, with the first and last days observed as legal holidays and as holy days involving abstention from work, special prayer services, and holiday meals; the intervening days are known as [[Chol HaMoed]] (&quot;Weekdays of the Festival&quot;). Diaspora Jews historically observed the festival for eight days, and most still do. [[Reform Judaism|Reform]] and [[Reconstructionist Judaism|Reconstructionist Jews]] and Israeli Jews, wherever they are, usually observe the holiday over seven days. The reason for this extra day is due to enactment of the [[Wise old man|Sages]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} It is thought by many scholars that Jews outside of Israel could not be certain if their local calendars fully conformed to practice of the Temple at Jerusalem, so they added an extra day. But as this practice only attaches to certain (major) sacred days, others posit the extra day may have been added to accommodate people who had to travel long distances to participate in communal worship and ritual practices; or the practice may have evolved as a compromise between conflicting interpretations of Jewish Law regarding the calendar; or it may have evolved as a safety measure in areas where Jews were commonly in danger, so that their enemies would not be certain on which day to attack.&lt;ref&gt;De Lange, Nicholas (2000). An Introduction to Judaism. New York, N.Y.: Cambridge University Press. p. 97&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Karaite Jews]] and [[Samaritan]]s use different versions of the Jewish calendar, which are often out of sync with the modern Jewish calendar by one or two days.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} In 2009, for example, Nisan 15 on the Jewish calendar used by Rabbinical Judaism corresponds to April 9. On the calendars used by Karaites and Samaritans, ''Abib'' or ''Aviv'' 15 (as opposed to 'Nisan') corresponds to April 11 in 2009. The Karaite and Samaritan Passovers are each one day long, followed by the six day Festival of Unleavened Bread – for a total of seven days.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

==Biblical origin==
[[File:Israel's Escape from Egypt.jpg|thumb|Illustration of [[The Exodus]] from Egypt, 1907]]
Called the feast of [[Matza|unleavened bread]] (Hebrew ''hag hamatzot '') in the [[Hebrew Bible]], the commandment to keep Passover is recorded in the [[Book of Leviticus]]:
&lt;blockquote&gt;In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month between the two evenings is the Lord's Passover. And on the fifteenth day of the same month is the feast of unleavened bread unto the Lord; seven days ye shall eat unleavened bread. In the first day ye shall have a holy convocation; ye shall do no manner of servile work. And ye shall bring an offering made by fire unto the Lord seven days; in the seventh day is a holy convocation; ye shall do no manner of servile work. ({{bibleverse||Leviticus|23:5|HE}})&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The biblical regulations for the observance of the festival require that all leavening be disposed of before the beginning of the 15th of Nisan&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|13:7|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; An unblemished lamb or goat is to be set apart on Nisan 10,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:3|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; and slaughtered on Nisan 14 at dusk.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:6|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; The literal meaning of the Hebrew is &quot;between the two evenings&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:6|ESV}} English Standard Version&lt;/ref&gt; a phrase which is, however, not defined. It is then to be eaten &quot;that night&quot;, Nisan 15,&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus 12:8&quot;&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:8|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; roasted, without the removal of its internal organs&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:9|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; with unleavened bread and bitter herbs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus 12:8&quot;/&gt; Nothing of the sacrifice on which the sun rises may be eaten, but must be burned.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:10|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sacrifices may only be performed in a specific place prescribed by God (for Judaism, Jerusalem, and for Samaritans, Mount Gerizim).&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|16:2|HE}},{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|16:5|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The biblical regulations pertaining to the original Passover also include how the meal is to be eaten: &quot;with your loins girded, your shoes on your feet, and your staff in your hand; and ye shall eat it in haste: it is the {{lord}}'s passover&quot; ([http://www.bibler.org/versions/american_standard/asv_exodus12_sml.htm#exodus_12:11 Exodus 12:11]).

Some of these details can be corroborated, and to some extent amplified, in extrabiblical sources. The removal (or &quot;sealing up&quot;) of the leaven is referred to in the [[Elephantine papyri]], an Aramaic papyrus from 5th century BCE Elephantine in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;James B. Prichard, ed., The Ancient Near East-An Anthology of Texts and Pictures, Volume 1, Princeton University Press, 1958, p. 278.&lt;/ref&gt; The slaughter of the lambs on the 14th is mentioned in ''[[Jubilees|The Book of Jubilees]]'', a Jewish work of the Ptolemaic period, and by the Herodian-era writers [[Josephus]] and [[Philo]]. These sources also indicate that &quot;between the two evenings&quot; was taken to mean the afternoon.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;On the feast called Passover...they sacrifice from the ninth to the eleventh hour&quot;, Josephus, ''Jewish War'' 6.423-428, in ''Josephus III, The Jewish War, Book IV-VII'', Loeb Classical Library, Harvard University Press, Cambridge, 1979. Philo in one place (''Special Laws'' 2.148) states that the victims are sacrificed &quot;from noon till eventide&quot;, and in another place (''Questions on Exodus'' 1.11) that the sacrifices begin at the ninth hour. According to Jubilees 49.12, &quot;it is not fitting to sacrifice [the Passover] during any time of light except during the time of the border of evening.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; ''Jubilees'' states the sacrifice was eaten that night,&lt;ref&gt;Jubilees 49.1.&lt;/ref&gt; and together with Josephus states that nothing of the sacrifice was allowed to remain until morning.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;And what is left of its flesh from the third of the night and beyond, they shall burn with fire,&quot; ''Jubilees'' 49.12. &quot;We celebrate [the Passover] by fraternities, nothing of the sacrificial victims being kept for the morrow,&quot; Josephus, ''Antiquities'' 3.248.&lt;/ref&gt; Philo states that the banquet included hymns and prayers.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The guests assembled for the banquet have been cleansed by purificatory lustrations, and are there...to fulfill with prayers and hymns the custom handed down by their fathers.&quot; Philo, Special Laws 2.148, in ''Philo VII: On the Decalog; On the Special Laws I-III'', Loeb Classical Library, Harvard University Press, Cambridge, 1937.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Biblical commandments concerning the Passover (and the Feast of Unleavened Bread) stress the importance of remembering: And thou shalt remember that thou wast a bondman in Egypt; and thou shalt observe and do these statutes.&quot; ({{Bibleverse||Deuteronomy|16:12|HE}}) {{Bibleverse||Exodus|12:14|HE}} commands, in reference to God's sparing of the firstborn from the [[Ten Plagues|Tenth Plague]]: And this day shall be unto you for a memorial, and ye shall keep it a feast to the lord; throughout your generations ye shall keep it a feast by an ordinance for ever.
{{Bibleverse||Exodus|13:3|HE}} repeats the command to remember:Remember this day, in which you came out of Egypt, out of the house of bondage, for by strength the hand of the {{LORD}} brought you out from this place.

==Etymology==
{{Jews and Judaism sidebar}}
The verb &quot;''pasàch''&quot; ({{lang-he|פָּסַח}}) is first mentioned in the [[Torah]] account of [[the Exodus]] from Egypt ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:23|HE}}), and there is some debate about its exact meaning: the commonly held assumption that it means &quot;He passed over&quot;, in reference to God &quot;passing over&quot; the houses of the Hebrews during the final of the Ten [[Plagues of Egypt]], stems from the translation provided in the [[Septuagint]] (''παρελευσεται'' in {{bibleverse||Exodus|12:23|HE}}, and ''εσκεπασεν'' in {{bibleverse||Exodus|12:27|HE}}). Judging from other instances of the verb, and instances of [[Parallelism (rhetoric)|parallelism]], a more faithful translation may be &quot;he hovered over, guarding.&quot; Indeed, this is the image invoked by the verb in [[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]] 31:5: &quot;As birds hovering, so will the Lord of hosts protect Jerusalem; He will deliver it as He protecteth it, He will rescue it as He ''passeth over''&quot; (כְּצִפֳּרִים עָפוֹת&amp;mdash;כֵּן יָגֵן יְהוָה צְבָאוֹת, עַל-יְרוּשָׁלִָם; גָּנוֹן וְהִצִּיל, פָּסֹחַ וְהִמְלִיט.) ({{bibleverse||Isaiah|31:5|HE}}) Both meanings become apparent in Exodus 12:23 when parsed as: the Lord will pass (hover, guard) over the door, and will not suffer the destroyer (destroying angel is commanded to pass by the children of Israel) to come in unto your houses to smite.  Targum Onkelos translates pesach as &quot;he had pity&quot;.

The English term &quot;Passover&quot; is first known recorded in the [[English language]] in [[William Tyndale]]'s translation of the Bible, later appearing in the [[King James Version of the Bible|King James Version]] as well.

The term ''Pesach'' ({{lang-he|פֶּסַח}}) may also refer to the [[Domestic sheep|lamb]] or [[Domestic goat|goat]] which was designated as the Passover sacrifice (called the ''[[Korban]] Pesach'' in [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]]). Four days before the Exodus, the Hebrews were commanded to set aside a lamb.({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:3|HE}}) and inspect it daily for blemishes. During the day on the 14th of Nisan, they were to slaughter the animal and use its blood to mark their lintels and door posts. Up until midnight on the 15th of Nisan, they were to consume the lamb. Each family (or group of families) gathered together to eat a meal that included the meat of the ''Korban Pesach'' while the Tenth Plague ravaged Egypt.

In subsequent years, during the existence of the [[Tabernacle (Judaism)|Tabernacle]] and later the [[Temple in Jerusalem]], the Passover offering (Hebrew ''korban Pesach'') was eaten during the [[Passover Seder]] on the 15th of Nisan. However, following the destruction of the Temple, no sacrifices may be offered or eaten. The ''Seder Korban Pesach'', a set of scriptural and Rabbinic passages dealing with the Passover sacrifice, is customarily recited during or after the [[Jewish services|''Mincha'']] (afternoon prayer) service on the 14th on Nisan.&lt;ref&gt;Eliyahu Kitov, ''The Book of Our Heritage: The Jewish Year and Its Days of Significance,'' Feldheim, 1997, p. 562.&lt;/ref&gt; The story of the ''Korban Pesach'' is also retold at the Passover Seder,meaning order, and the symbolic food which represents it on the [[Passover Seder Plate|Seder Plate]] is usually a roasted lamb [[wiktionary:shank|shankbone]] or chicken wing.

==Passover offering, ''korban Pesach''==
{{main|Korban Pesach}}
When the [[Temple in Jerusalem]] was standing, the focus of the Passover festival was the Passover sacrifice (Hebrew ''korban Pesach'') also known as the &quot;Paschal Lamb&quot;). Every family large enough to completely consume a young lamb or wild goat was required to offer one for sacrifice at the Jewish Temple on the afternoon of the 14th day of Nisan,({{bibleverse||Numbers|9:11|HE}}) and eat it that night, which was the 15th of Nisan  ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:6|NIV}}). If the family was too small to finish eating the entire offering in one sitting, an offering was made for a group of families. The sacrifice could not be offered with anything leavened,({{bibleverse||Exodus|23:18|HE}}) and had to be roasted, without its head, feet, or inner organs being removed ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:9|HE}}) and eaten together with unleavened bread (''[[matzo]]'') and bitter herbs (''[[maror]]'').  One had to be careful not to break any bones from the offering, ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:46|HE}}) and none of the meat could be left over by morning ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:10|HE}}{{bibleverse||Exodus|23:18|HE}}).

Because of the Passover sacrifice's status as a sacred offering, the only people allowed to eat it were those who had the obligation to bring the offering. Among those who could not offer or eat the Passover lamb were: An [[apostate]] ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:43|HE}}), a [[Indentured servant|servant]] ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:45|HE}}), an [[Brit milah|uncircumcised man]] ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:48|HE}}), a person in a state of [[Tohorot|ritual impurity]], except when a majority of Jews are in such a state (''[[Pesahim]]'' 66b), and a non-Jew. The offering had to be made before a [[quorum]] of 30 (''[[Pesahim]]'' 64b). In the Temple, the [[Levites]] sang [[Hallel]] while the [[Kohen|priests]] performed the sacrificial service. Men and women were equally obligated regarding the offering (''[[Pesahim]]'' 91b).

Women were obligated, as men, to perform the Korban Pesach and to participate in a Seder.

==Today==
Today, in the absence of the Temple, the [[mitzvah]] of the ''Korban Pesach'' is memorialized in the ''Seder Korban Pesach&lt;ref&gt;Eliyahu Kitov, The Book of Our Heritage: The Jewish Year and Its Days of Significance, Feldheim, 1997, p. 562.&lt;/ref&gt;'', recited in the afternoon of Nisan 14, and in the form of symbolic food placed on the [[Passover Seder Plate]], which is usually a roasted [[humerus|shankbone]]. The eating of the [[afikoman]] substitutes for the eating of the ''Korban Pesach'' at the end of the Seder meal ([[Mishnah]] Pesachim 119a). Many [[Sephardi Jews]] have the custom of eating lamb or goat meat during the Seder in memory of the ''Korban Pesach''.

==Removing all chametz==
[[File:BiurChametz2010.jpg|thumb|250px|Burning chametz on the morning of the seder]]
[[Chametz#What is chametz?|Chametz]] (חמץ, &quot;[[leavening]]&quot;) is made from one of five types of grains combined with water and left to stand for more than eighteen minutes. The consumption, keeping, and owning of ''chametz'' is forbidden during Passover. Yeast and fermentation are not themselves forbidden as seen for example by wine, which is required, rather than merely permitted. According to Halakha, the ownership of such ''chametz'' is also proscribed.

''Chametz'' does not include [[baking soda]], [[baking powder]] or like products. Although these are defined in English as leavening agents, they leaven by chemical reaction, not by biological fermentation. Thus, bagels, waffles and pancakes made with baking soda and matzo meal are considered permissible, while bagels made with  sourdough and pancakes and waffles made with yeast are prohibited.

The Torah commandments regarding ''chametz'' are:
*To remove all ''chametz'' from one's home, including things made with chametz, before the first day of Passover. ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:15|HE}}). It may be simply used up, thrown out (historically, destroyed by burning), or given or sold to non-Jews (or non-Samaritans, as the case may be).
*To refrain from eating ''chametz'' or mixtures containing ''chametz'' during Passover. ({{bibleverse||Exodus|13:3|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Exodus|12:20|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|16:3|HE}}).
*Not to possess ''chametz'' in one's domain (i.e. home, office, car, etc.) during Passover ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:19|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|16:4|HE}}).

Observant Jews spend the weeks before Passover in a flurry of thorough housecleaning, to remove every morsel of ''chametz'' from every part of the home. [[Halakha|Jewish law]] requires the elimination of [[olive]]-sized or larger quantities of leavening from one's possession, but most housekeeping goes beyond this. Even the cracks of kitchen counters are thoroughly scrubbed, for example, to remove any traces of flour and yeast, however small. Any item or implement that has handled ''chametz'' is generally put away and not used during Passover.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/ultra-orthodox-burn-leavened-food-before-passover-begins-1.356761 Ultra Orthodox burn leavened food before Passover]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[hotel]]s, [[resort]]s, and even [[cruise ship]]s across [[United States|America]], [[Europe]] and [[Israel]] also undergo a thorough housecleaning to make their premises &quot;kosher for Pesach&quot; to cater to observant Jews.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

===Interpretations for abstinence from leaven or yeast===
Some Scholars suggest that the command to abstain from leavened food or yeast suggests that sacrifices offered to God involve the offering of objects in &quot;their least altered state&quot;, that would be nearest to the way in which they were initially made by God.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bokser&quot;&gt;Bokser Baruch M (1992) “Unleavened Bread and Passover, Feasts of” in The Anchor Bible Dictionary, ed. David Noel Freedman (New York: Doubleday), 6:755-765&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Greenberg&quot;&gt;Greenberg, M (1974) &quot;Lessons on Exodus&quot;. New York&lt;/ref&gt; According to other scholars the absence of leaven or yeast means that leaven or yeast symbolizes corruption and spoiling.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bokser&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;Sarna&quot;&gt;Sarna N (1986) &quot;Exploring Exodus&quot;. New York&lt;/ref&gt; In any case the main entity in Passover according to Judaism is the [[Korban Pesach|sacrificial lamb]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bokser&quot;/&gt;

==Search for, and burning of leaven==
Traditionally, Jews do a formal search for remaining leaven (Hebrew ''chametz'', as in ''bedikat chametz'') after nightfall on the evening before Passover. A blessing is read (על ביעור חמץ – ''al biyur chametz'', &quot;on the removal of leaven&quot;), and one or more members of the household proceed from room to room to check that no crumbs remain in any corner. In very traditional families, the search may be conducted by the head of the household; in more modern-style{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} families, the children may be the ones who do the search, under the supervision of their parents.

It is customary to turn off the lights and conduct the search by [[candle]]light, using a feather and a wooden spoon: candlelight effectively illuminates corners without casting shadows; the feather can dust crumbs out of their hiding places; and the wooden spoon which collects the crumbs can be burned the next day with the ''chametz''. However, most contemporary Jewish-Orthodox authorities permit using a flashlight, while some strongly encourage it due to the danger coupled with using a candle.
Because the house is assumed to have been thoroughly cleaned by the night before Passover, there is some concern that making a blessing over the search for ''chametz'' will be for naught (''bracha l'vatala'') if nothing is found. Thus, 10 morsels of bread smaller than the size of an olive are traditionally hidden throughout the house in order to ensure that some ''chametz'' will be found.

On the morning of the 14th of [[Nisan]], any leavened products that remain in the householder's possession, along with the 10 morsels of bread from the previous night's search, are burned (''s'rayfat chametz''). The head of the household repeats the declaration of ''biyur chametz'', declaring any ''chametz'' that may not have been found to be null and void &quot;as the dust of the earth&quot;. Should more ''chametz'' actually be found in the house during the Passover holiday, it must be burnt as soon as possible.

Unlike ''chametz'', which can be eaten any day of the year except during Passover, kosher for Passover foods can be eaten year-round. They need not be burnt or otherwise discarded after the holiday ends. The sole exception is the historic [[Animal sacrifice|sacrificial lamb]], which is  never part of the modern Jewish holiday but is still a principal feature of Falashah, Karaite and Samaritan observance. The meat of this lamb, which is slaughtered and cooked on the evening of Passover, must be completely consumed before the morning.({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:15|HE}})

==Sale of chametz==
''Chametz'' may be sold rather than discarded, especially in the case of relatively valuable forms such as [[liquor]] [[distillation|distilled]] from wheat, with the products being repurchased afterward. In some cases, they may never leave the house, instead being formally sold while remaining in the original owner's possession in a locked cabinet until they can be repurchased after the holiday. Modern observance may also include sealing cabinets and drawers which contain &quot;Chametz&quot; shut by using adhesive tape, which serves a similar purpose to a lock but also shows evidence of tampering. Although the practice of selling &quot;Chametz&quot; dates back many years, some contemporary rabbinical authorities have come to regard it with disdain – since the supposed &quot;new owner&quot; never takes actual possession of the goods.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

The sale of ''chametz'' may also be conducted communally via a [[rabbi]], who becomes the &quot;agent&quot; for all the community's Jews through a halakhic procedure called a ''kinyan'' (acquisition). Each householder must put aside all the ''chametz'' he is selling into a box or cupboard, and the rabbi enters into a contract to sell all the ''chametz'' to a non-Jew (who is not obligated to observe the commandments) in exchange for a small [[down payment]] (''e.g.'' $1.00), with the remainder due after Passover. This sale is considered completely binding according to Halakha, and at any time during the holiday, the buyer may come to take or partake of his property. The rabbi then re-purchases the goods for less than they were sold at the end of the holiday.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.torahlearningcenter.com/jhq/question169.html Pesach questions and answers] by the Torah Learning Center.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Separate dishes==
Due to the Torah injunction not to eat ''chametz'' during Passover, ({{bibleverse||Exodus|12:15|HE}}) observant families typically own complete sets of serving dishes, glassware and silverware (and in some cases, even separate dishwashers and sinks) which have never come into contact with ''chametz'', for use only during Passover. Under certain circumstances, some ''chametz'' utensils can be immersed in boiling water (''hagalat keilim'') to purge them of any traces of ''chametz'' that may have accumulated during the year. Many [[Sephardi Jews|Sephardic]] families thoroughly wash their year-round glassware and then use it for Passover, as the Sephardic position is that [[glass]] does not absorb enough traces of food to present a problem. Similarly, ovens may be used for Passover either by setting the self-cleaning function to the highest degree for a certain period of time, or by applying a [[blow torch]] to the interior until the oven glows red hot (a process called ''libun gamur'').&lt;ref name=&quot;WSJblowtorch&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
  | last = Lagnado
  | first = Lucette
  | title = As Passover Nears, These Rabbis Are Getting Out Their Blowtorches
  | pages = A1
  | newspaper = The Wall Street Journal
  | location = New York
  | date = 18 April 2011
  | url = http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704628404576264751651607740.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Matzah==
[[Image:Machine-made Shmura Matzo.jpg|thumb|250px|Matzah]]

A symbol of the Passover holiday is [[matzo]], an unleavened flatbread made solely from flour and water which is continually worked from mixing through baking, so that it is not allowed to rise. Matzo may be made by machine or by hand; the latter type of matzo, called ''shmura matzo'' (&quot;watched&quot; or &quot;guarded&quot; matzo), is the bread of preference for the Passover Seder in Orthodox Jewish communities. The Torah contains a Divine commandment to eat matzo, specifically, on the first night of Passover and to eat only unleavened bread (in practice, matzo) during the entire week of Passover.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|12:18|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently the eating of matzo figures prominently in the [[Passover Seder]]. There are several explanations for this.

The Torah says that it is because the Hebrews left Egypt with such haste that there was no time to allow baked bread to rise; thus flat, unleavened bread, matzo, is a reminder of the rapid departure of the Exodus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.askmoses.com/article.html?h=107&amp;o=60495 |title=Thought For Food: An Overview of the Seder | work =AskMoses.com – Judaism, Ask a Rabbi – Live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other scholars teach that in the time of the Exodus, matzo was commonly baked for the purpose of traveling because it preserved well and was light to carry (making it similar to [[hardtack]]), suggesting that matzo was baked intentionally for the long journey ahead.

Matzo has also been called ''Lechem Oni'' (Hebrew: &quot;bread of poverty&quot;). There is an attendant explanation that matzo serves as a symbol to remind Jews what it is like to be a poor slave and to promote humility, appreciate freedom, and avoid the inflated ego symbolized by more luxurious leavened bread.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askmoses.com/article.html?h=107&amp;o=450 What is the kabbalistic view on chametz?] by Rabbi Yossi Marcus&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Shmura Matzo.jpg|right|250px|thumb|Handmade ''shmura matzo'']]In the weeks before Passover, matzos are prepared for holiday consumption. In [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jewish]] communities, men traditionally gather in groups (&quot;''[[Chavruta|chaburas]]''&quot;) to bake a special version of handmade matzo called &quot;''shmura matzo''&quot;, or &quot;guarded matzo&quot;, for use at the Seder. These are made from wheat that is guarded from contamination by chametz from the time of summer [[harvest]] to its baking into matzos five to ten months later.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishaz.com/jewishnews/050422/matzo.shtml These Matzos are often begun to be produced in early November]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Shmura matzo'' dough is rolled by hand, resulting in a large and round matzo. ''Chaburas'' also work together in machine-made matzo factories, which produce the typically square-shaped matzo sold in stores.

The baking of ''shmura matzo'' is labor-intensive, as only 18–22 minutes is permitted between the mixing of flour and water to the conclusion of baking and removal from the oven; however, most are completed within 5 minutes of being kneaded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishaz.com/jewishnews/050422/matzo.shtml|title=Making matzo: A time-honored tradition&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, only a small number of matzos can be baked at one time, and the ''chabura'' members are enjoined to work the dough constantly so that it is not allowed to ferment and rise. A special cutting tool is run over the dough just before baking to prick any bubbles which might make the matza puff up;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishfederations.org/page.aspx?id=42416 Making Matzah the Old-Fashioned Way]&lt;/ref&gt; this creates the familiar dotted holes in the matzo.

After the matzos come out of the oven, the entire work area is scrubbed down and swept to make sure that no pieces of old, potentially leavened dough remain, as any stray pieces are now ''chametz'', and can contaminate the next batch of matzo.

==Fast of the Firstborn==
On the morning of the Passover seder, firstborn sons are commanded to observe the [[Fast of the Firstborn]] which commemorates the salvation of the Hebrew firstborns. According to Exodus (12:29), God struck down all Egyptian firstborns while the Israelites were not affected. However, it is customary for synagogues to  conduct a ''[[siyum]]'' (ceremony marking the completion of a section of [[Torah]] learning) right after morning prayers, and the celebratory meal that follows cancels the firstborn's obligation to fast.

==Passover seder==
[[File:Sedertable.jpg|thumb|250px|Table set for the Passover Seder]]
{{Main|Passover Seder}}
It is traditional for Jewish families to gather on the first night of Passover (first two nights in communities outside the land of Israel) for a special dinner called a [[Passover seder|seder]] (סדר&amp;mdash;derived from the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] word for &quot;order&quot;, referring to the very specific order of the ritual). The table is set with the finest china and silverware to reflect the importance of the meal. During this meal, the story of the Exodus from Egypt is retold using a special text called the [[Haggadah]]. Four cups of wine are consumed at various stages in the narrative. The Haggadah divides the night's procedure into 15 parts:

#''Kadeish'' קדש – recital of [[Kiddush]] blessing and drinking of the first cup of wine
#''Urchatz'' ורחץ – the washing of the hands – without blessing
#''Karpas'' כרפס – dipping of the ''[[karpas]]'' in salt water
#''Yachatz'' יחץ – breaking the middle matzo; the larger piece becomes the ''[[afikoman]]'' which is eaten later during the ritual of ''Tzafun''
#''Maggid'' מגיד – retelling the Passover story, including the recital of &quot;[[the four questions]]&quot; and drinking of the second cup of wine
#''Rachtzah'' רחצה – second washing of the hands – with blessing
#''Motzi'' מוציא – traditional blessing before eating [[bread]] products
#''Matzo'' מצה – blessing before eating [[matzo]]
#''Maror'' מרור – eating of the [[maror]]
#''Koreich'' כורך – eating of a sandwich made of matzo and maror
#''Shulchan oreich'' שולחן עורך – lit. &quot;set table&quot;&amp;mdash;the serving of the holiday meal
#''Tzafun'' צפון – eating of the ''[[afikoman]]''
#''Bareich'' ברך – blessing after the meal and drinking of the third cup of wine
#''[[Hallel]]'' הלל – recital of the Hallel, traditionally recited on festivals; drinking of the fourth cup of wine
#''Nirtzah'' נירצה – [[conclusion]]

These 15 parts parallel the 15 steps in the [[Temple in Jerusalem]] on which the [[Levite]]s stood during Temple services, and which were memorialized in the 15 [[Book of Psalms|Psalms]] (#120-134) known as ''Shir HaMa'alot'' ({{lang-he|שיר המעלות}}, &quot;Songs of Ascent&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kolhator.org.il/shir_hamaalot.php ''Shir Ha Ma'a lot''.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The seder is replete with questions, answers, and unusual practices (e.g. the recital of [[Kiddush]] which is not immediately followed by the blessing over bread, which is the traditional procedure for all other holiday meals) to arouse the interest and curiosity of the children at the table. The children are also rewarded with nuts and candies when they ask questions and participate in the discussion of the Exodus and its aftermath. Likewise, they are encouraged to search for the ''[[afikoman]]'', the piece of matzo which is the last thing eaten at the seder. Audience participation and interaction is the rule, and many families' seders last long into the night with animated discussions and much singing. The seder concludes with additional songs of praise and faith printed in the Haggadah, including ''[[Chad Gadya]]'' (&quot;One Little Kid&quot; or &quot;One Little Goat&quot;).

==Maror==
[[File:3TypesMaror.jpg|right|250px|thumb|Types of maror: grated [[horseradish]], [[romaine lettuce]], whole horseradish root]]
[[Maror]] symbolizes the bitterness of slavery in [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]]. The following verse from the [[Torah]] underscores that symbolism: &quot;And they embittered (''ve-yimareru'' וימררו) their lives with hard labor, with mortar and with bricks and with all manner of labor in the field; any labor that they made them do was with hard labor&quot; ([[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] 1:14).

[[File:SederPlate.jpg|thumb|250px|Silver seder plate]]

==Four cups of wine==
There is a Rabbinic requirement that four cups of wine are to be drunk during the seder meal. This applies to both men and women. The Mishnah says (Pes. 10:1) that even the poorest man in Israel has an obligation to drink. Each cup is connected to a different part of the seder: the first cup is for Kiddush, the second cup is connected with the recounting of [[the Exodus]], the drinking of the third cup concludes [[Birkat Hamazon]] and the fourth cup is associated with Hallel.

==Participation of children==

===The four questions===

{{See also|The four questions}}
Children have a very important role in the Passover seder. Traditionally the youngest child is prompted to ask questions about the Passover seder, beginning with the words, ''Mah Nishtana HaLeila HaZeh'' (Why is this night different from all other nights?). The questions encourage the gathering to discuss the significance of the symbols in the meal. The questions asked by the child are:

:Why is this night different from all other nights?
:On all other nights, we eat either unleavened or leavened bread, but tonight we eat only unleavened bread?
:On all other nights, we eat all kinds of vegetables, but tonight, we eat only bitter herbs?
:On all other nights, we do not dip [our food] even once, but tonight we dip twice?
:On all other nights, we eat either sitting or reclining, but tonight we only recline?

Often the leader of the seder and the other adults at the meal will use prompted responses from the Haggadah, which states, &quot;The more one talks about [[The Exodus|the Exodus from Egypt]], the more praiseworthy he is.&quot; Many readings, prayers, and stories are used to recount the story of the Exodus. Many households add their own commentary and interpretation and often the story of the Jews is related to the theme of liberation and its implications worldwide.

===Afikoman===

[[File:Haggadah 14th cent.jpg|thumb|200px|14th century Haggadah]]
The ''afikoman'' &amp;mdash; an integral part of the Seder itself &amp;mdash; is used to engage the interest and excitement of the children at the table. During the fourth part of the Seder, called ''Yachatz'', the leader breaks the middle piece of matzo into two. He sets aside the larger portion as the ''afikoman''. Many families use the ''afikoman'' as a device for keeping the children awake and alert throughout the Seder proceedings by hiding the ''afikoman'' and offering a prize for its return. Alternatively, the children are allowed to &quot;steal&quot; the ''afikoman'' and demand a reward for its return. In either case, the ''afikoman'' must be consumed during the twelfth part of the Seder, ''Tzafun''.

===Concluding songs===

After the Hallel, the fourth glass of wine is drunk, and participants recite a prayer that ends in &quot;Next year in Jerusalem!&quot;.  This is followed by several lyric prayers that expound upon God's mercy and kindness, and give thanks for the survival of the Jewish people through a history of exile and hardship.  &quot;Echad Mi Yodea&quot; (&quot;Who Knows One?&quot;) is a playful song, testing the general knowledge of the children (and the adults). Some of these songs, such as &quot;Chad Gadiyah&quot; are allegorical.

==Hol Hamoed==
In [[Land of Israel|Israel]], Passover lasts for seven days with the first and last days being major [[Jewish holidays]]. In [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] and [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] communities, no work is performed on those days, with most of the rules relating to the observances of [[Shabbat]] being applied. A seder is held on the first day.

Outside Israel, in [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] and [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] communities, the holiday lasts for eight days with the first two days and last two days being major holidays. A seder is conducted twice, on both the first and second days. In the intermediate days necessary work can be performed. [[Reform Judaism]] observes Passover over seven days, with the first and last days being a major holidays. The Seder is held on the first day.

Like the holiday of [[Sukkot]], the intermediary days of Passover are known as [[Chol HaMoed]] (festival weekdays) and are imbued with a semi-festive status. It is a time for family outings and picnic lunches of matzo, hardboiled eggs, fruits and vegetables, and Passover treats such as [[macaroon]]s and homemade candies.

Passover cake recipes call for [[potato starch]] or Passover cake flour made from finely granulated matzo instead of regular flour, and a large amount of eggs  to achieve fluffiness. Cookie recipes use [[matzo farfel]] (broken bits of matzo) or ground nuts as the base. For families with [[Eastern Europe]]an backgrounds, [[borsht]], a soup made with [[beet]]s, is a Passover tradition.
[[File:Wonder Pot cake.jpg|150px|thumb|A Passover brownie cake baked in a [[Wonder Pot]].]]
While kosher for Passover packaged goods are available in stores, some families opt to cook everything from scratch during Passover week. In [[Israel]], families that do not [[kashrut|kasher]] their ovens can bake cakes, casseroles, and even meat&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Roast in the Wonder Pot&quot;, ''The Kosher For Pesach Cookbook'' (1978). Jerusalem:Yeshivat Aish HaTorah Women's Organization, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; on the [[kitchen stove|stovetop]] in a [[Wonder Pot]], an Israeli invention consisting of three parts: an [[aluminium]] pot shaped like a [[Bundt cake|Bundt pan]], a hooded cover perforated with venting holes, and a thick, round, metal disc with a center hole which is placed between the Wonder Pot and the flame to disperse heat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://israelity.com/tag/the-wonder-pot/ |title=Nostalgia Sunday |last=Neiman |first=Rachel |accessdate=2010-04-01 |date=2008-06-15 |publisher=21c Israelity blog}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Counting of the Omer==
Beginning on the second night of Passover, the 16th day of Nisan,&lt;ref&gt;[[Karaite Jews]] begin the count on the Sunday within the holiday week. This leads to Shavuot for the Karaites always falling on a Sunday.&lt;/ref&gt; Jews begin the practice of the [[Counting of the Omer]], a nightly reminder of the approach of the holiday of [[Shavuot]] 50 days hence. Each night after the evening prayer service, men and women recite a special blessing and then enumerate the day of the Omer. On the first night, for example, they say, &quot;Today is the first day in (or, to) the Omer&quot;; on the second night, &quot;Today is the second day in the Omer.&quot; The counting also involves weeks; thus, the seventh day is commemorated, &quot;Today is the seventh day, which is one week in the Omer.&quot; The eighth day is marked, &quot;Today is the eighth day, which is one week and one day in the Omer,&quot; etc.

When the [[Temple in Jerusalem|Temple stood in Jerusalem]], a sheaf of new-cut barley was presented before the altar on the second day of Unleavened Bread. Josephus writes&lt;blockquote&gt;
On the second day of unleavened bread, that is to say the sixteenth, our people partake of the crops which they have reaped and which have not been touched till then, and esteeming it right first to do homage to God, to whom they owe the abundance of these gifts, they offer to him the first-fruits of the barley in the following way. After parching and crushing the little sheaf of ears and purifying the barley for grinding, they bring to the altar an ''assaron'' for God, and, having flung a handful thereof on the altar, they leave the rest for the use of the priests. Thereafter all are permitted, publicly or individually, to begin harvest.&lt;ref&gt;Josephus, Antiquities 3.250-251, in Josephus IV Jewish Antiquities Books I-IV, Loeb Classical Library, Harvard University Press, Cambridge, 1930, pp. 437-439.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Since the destruction of the Temple, this offering is brought in word rather than deed.

One explanation for the Counting of the Omer is that it shows the connection between Passover and Shavuot. The physical freedom that the Hebrews achieved at the Exodus from Egypt was only the beginning of a process that climaxed with the spiritual freedom they gained at the giving of the Torah at [[Biblical Mount Sinai|Mount Sinai]]. Another explanation is that the newborn nation which emerged after the Exodus needed time to learn their new responsibilities vis-a-vis Torah and [[mitzvot]] before accepting God's law. The distinction between the Omer offering&amp;mdash;a measure of barley, typically animal fodder&amp;mdash;and the Shavuot offering&amp;mdash;two loaves of wheat bread, human food&amp;mdash;symbolizes the transition process.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

==Seventh day of Passover==
''[[Shvi'i shel Pesach]]'' (שביעי של פסח &quot;seventh [day] of Passover&quot;) is another full [[Jewish holiday]], with special prayer services and festive meals. Outside the [[Land of Israel]] in the [[Jewish diaspora]], ''Shvi'i shel Pesach'' is celebrated on both the seventh and eighth days of Passover. This holiday commemorates the day the [[Children of Israel]] reached the [[Red Sea]] and witnessed both the miraculous &quot;Splitting of the Sea,&quot; the drowning of all the Egyptian chariots, horses and soldiers that pursued them, and the [[Passage of the Red Sea]]. According to the [[Midrash]], only the [[Pharaoh]] was spared to give testimony to the miracle that occurred.

[[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidic]] [[Rebbe]]s traditionally hold a ''[[Tish (Hasidic celebration)|tish]]'' on the night of ''Shvi'i shel Pesach'' and place a cup or bowl of water on the table before them. They use this opportunity to speak about the Splitting of the Sea to their disciples, and sing songs of praise to God.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

== Second Passover ==
The &quot;Second Passover&quot; ([[Pesach Sheni]]) on the 14th of Iyar in the [[Hebrew Calendar]] is mentioned in the [[Hebrew Bible]] ([[Book of Numbers|Numbers]] 9:6-13) as a make-up day for people who were unable to offer the pesach sacrifice at the appropriate time due to ritual impurity or distance from [[Jerusalem]]. Just as on the first Pesach night, breaking bones from the second Paschal offering (Numbers 9:12) or leaving meat over until morning (Numbers 9:12) is prohibited.

Today, Pesach Sheni on the 14th of Iyar has the status of a very minor holiday (so much so that many of the Jewish people have never even heard of it, and it essentially does not exist outside of [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] and traditional [[Conservative Judaism]]). There are not really any special prayers or observances that are considered Jewish law. The only change in the liturgy is that in some communities ''[[Tachanun]]'', a penitential prayer omitted on holidays, is not said. There is a custom, though not Jewish law, to eat just one piece of matzo on that night.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.torah.org/learning/yomtov/omer/5755/vol1no21.html|title=Pesach Sheini}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Traditional foods==
[[File:Matzah brei serving.jpg|250px|right|thumb|[[Matzah brei]] (fried [[matzo]] and egg), a popular Passover dish]]
Because the house is free of chametz for eight days, the Jewish household typically eats different foods during the week of Passover. These include:

* ''[[Matzah brei]]'' – Softened matzo fried with egg and fat; served either savory or sweet
* Matzo cereal – Matzo meal boiled in water and often served with milk and butter
* Matzo [[kugel]] – A kugel made with matzo instead of noodles
* ''[[Charoset]]'' – Chopped or ground apples and nuts in wine
* ''Chrain'' – Horseradish and beet relish
* [[Gefilte fish]] – Poached fish patties or fish balls made from a mixture of ground deboned fish, mostly [[carp]] or [[pike (fish)|pike]]
* [[Chicken soup]] with [[matzah ball]]s (''kneydlach'') – Chicken soup served with matzo-meal dumplings
* [[Rice]], often with [[saffron]] or [[raisin]]s – Nearly all [[Sephardi Jews]] and many [[Mizrachi Jews]] consider rice to be an essential food for the Passover table; [[Ashkenazi Jews]] and [[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidic Jews]] do not eat rice during Passover as a matter of [[minhag]]. According to the [[Talmud]]&lt;ref&gt;The Talmud notes: &quot;What are the two cooked foods served at the [[Passover Seder|Seder]] table? [[Rav Huna]] said, 'Spinach and rice'&quot; ([[Pesahim]] 114b).&lt;/ref&gt; and the commentary of [[Rashi]], rice is not ''chametz''. However, there is a concern that in storage, rice may have been contaminated with even one kernel of wheat or other grains. Those who eat rice inspect it carefully prior to cooking.

==Sermons, liturgy, and song==

The story of Passover, with its message that slaves can go free, and that the future can be better than the present, has inspired a number of religious sermons, prayers, and songs—including [[Spiritual (music)|spirituals]] (what used to be called &quot;Negro Spirituals&quot;), within the African-American community.

Rabbi [[Philip R. Alstat]], an early leader of [[Conservative Judaism]], known for his fiery rhetoric and powerful oratory skills, wrote and spoke in 1939 about the power of the Passover story during the rise of Nazi persecution and terror:&lt;ref&gt;The Canadian Jewish Chronicle, March 31, 1939&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Perhaps in our generation the counsel of our Talmudic sages may seem superfluous, for today the story of our enslavement in Egypt is kept alive not only by ritualistic symbolism, but even more so by tragic realism. We are the contemporaries and witnesses of its daily re-enactment. Are not our hapless brethren in the German Reich eating &quot;the bread of affliction&quot;?  Are not their lives embittered by complete disenfranchisement and forced labor? Are they not lashed mercilessly by brutal taskmasters behind the walls of concentration camps? Are not many of their men-folk being murdered in cold blood? Is not the ruthlessness of the Egyptian Pharaoh surpassed by the sadism of the Nazi dictators?&lt;br /&gt;And yet, even in this hour of disaster and degradation, it is still helpful to &quot;visualize oneself among those who had gone forth out of Egypt.&quot; It gives stability and equilibrium to the spirit.  Only our estranged kinsmen, the assimilated, and the de-Judaized, go to pieces under the impact of the blow....But those who visualize themselves among the groups who have gone forth from the successive Egypts in our history never lose their sense of perspective, nor are they overwhelmed by confusion and despair.... It is this faith, born of racial experience and wisdom, which gives the oppressed the strength to outlive the oppressors and to endure until the day of ultimate triumph when we shall &quot;be brought forth from bondage unto freedom, from sorrow unto joy, from mourning unto festivity, from darkness unto great light, and from servitude unto redemption.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Influence on other religions==

===Christianity===
{{see also|Easter|Passover (Christian holiday)}}

The Christian feast of [[Maundy Thursday]] finds its roots in the Jewish feast of Passover, the night on which the [[Last Supper]] is generally thought to have occurred.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=1UWp5pi1SdUC&amp;pg=PA64&amp;dq=maundy+thursday+evening+jewish&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=mz57T9XcJOHv0gHhqISbBg&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=maundy%20thursday%20evening%20jewish&amp;f=false|title = Worship and Festivals|publisher=[[Heinemann (publisher)|Heinemann]]|author=Gwyneth Windsor, John Hughes|quote=On the Thursday, which is known as Maundy Thursday, Christians remember the Last Supper which Jesus had with his disciples. It was the Jewish Feast of the Passover, and the meal which they had together was the traditional ''Seder'' meal, eaten that evening by the Jews everywhere.|date=Nov 21, 1990|accessdate = 2009-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===

In Islam, only the [[Turkic Karaites]] observe Passover traditions in the evening following the last day of Tashriq (the evening after the 13th of [[Dhu al-Hijjah]]).

== See also ==
* [[Passover Seder]]
* [[Passover Seder Plate]]
* [[Gebrochts]]
* [[Kitniyot]]
* [[Fast of the Firstborn]]
* [[Haggadah of Pesach]]
* [[Passover (Christian holiday)]]
* [[Quartodecimanism]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Passover}}
{{NIE Poster|year=1905}}
*[http://www.passover.net/ Guide to Passover – chabad.org]
*[http://ph.yhb.org.il/en/ 'Peninei Halachah' Jewish Law – Yhb.org.il ]
*[http://www.aish.com/h/pes/mm/48972121.html Aish.com Passover Primer]
*[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/11933-passover Jewish Encyclopedia: Passover]
*[http://torahvort.com/jewiki/index.php/Pesach Passover article]
*[http://www.akhlah.com/holidays/pesach/passover.php Akhlah: The Jewish Children's Learning Network]
*[http://www.torahforme.org/ Torah for me]
*[http://jewishholidaysonline.com/pesach Secular dates for passover]
* {{NYTtopic|subjects/p/passover}}

{{Passover Footer}}
{{Jewish and Israeli holidays}}
{{US Holidays}}
{{Time in religion and mythology}}

[[Category:Passover| ]]
[[Category:April observances]]
[[Category:March observances]]
[[Category:Hallel]]
[[Category:Jewish holy days]]
[[Category:Spring holidays]]

[[als:Pessach]]
[[ar:عيد الفصح اليهودي]]
[[bg:Пасха]]
[[bar:Pessach]]
[[ca:Pasqua jueva]]
[[ceb:Pesaḥ]]
[[cs:Pesach]]
[[da:Pesach]]
[[de:Pessach]]
[[es:Pésaj]]
[[eo:Pesaĥo]]
[[fa:پسح]]
[[fr:Pessa'h]]
[[fur:Pasche ebraiche]]
[[gl:Pessach]]
[[ko:유월절]]
[[hr:Pasha]]
[[id:Paskah Yahudi]]
[[is:Páskahald gyðinga]]
[[it:Pesach]]
[[he:פסח]]
[[ka:ფესახი]]
[[sw:Pasaka ya Kiyahudi]]
[[lad:Pesah]]
[[la:Pascha]]
[[lv:Pesahs]]
[[lt:Pascha]]
[[hu:Pészah]]
[[mk:Пасха]]
[[ml:പെസഹാ (യഹൂദമതം)]]
[[arz:عيد الفصح]]
[[ms:Paskah Yahudi]]
[[mn:Дээгүүр өнгөрөх баяр]]
[[nl:Pesach]]
[[ja:過越]]
[[no:Pesach]]
[[nn:Pesah]]
[[pnb:پیساخ]]
[[pl:Pesach]]
[[pt:Pessach]]
[[ro:Pesah]]
[[ru:Песах]]
[[simple:Passover]]
[[sk:Pesach]]
[[sl:Pasha]]
[[sr:Пасха]]
[[fi:Pesah]]
[[sv:Pesach]]
[[tl:Pesaḥ]]
[[ta:பாஸ்கா]]
[[th:ปัสคา]]
[[tr:Hamursuz Bayramı]]
[[uk:Песах]]
[[ur:پیساخ]]
[[vi:Lễ Vượt Qua]]
[[yi:פסח]]
[[diq:Pesax]]
[[zh:逾越節]]</text>
      <sha1>plbmc3zml800t2hftxtrok9vv43n997</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
