<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Peace</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24702</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521545947</id>
      <parentid>521545925</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T18:40:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/24.249.166.115|24.249.166.115]] to version by 167.80.244.204. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1316123) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32304">{{About|the idea of full harmony and the absence of hostility}}
{{Refimprove|date=January 2007}}
{{Cleanup-rewrite|date=May 2009}}

[[File:Fountain of Time full front.jpg|thumb|280px|''[[Fountain of Time]]'' honors the first 100 years of peace between [[Great Britain]] and the [[United States]] resulting from the signing of the [[Treaty of Ghent]] in 1814.]]
[[File:Peace button large.png|thumb|The [[peace sign]], one of [[peace symbols|several symbols used to represent peace]]]]

'''Peace''' is a state of harmony characterized by the lack of violent conflict and the freedom from fear of violence.   Commonly understood as the absence of hostility, peace also suggests the existence of healthy or newly healed [[interpersonal relationship|interpersonal]] or [[international relations]]hips, prosperity in matters of social or economic welfare, the establishment of equality, and a working political order that serves the true interests of all. In international relations, [[peacetime]] is not only the absence of [[war]] or violent conflict, but also the presence of positive and respectful cultural and economic relationships.

== Etymology ==
From the Latin [[pax]], meaning &quot;freedom from civil disorder,&quot; the English word came into use in various personal greetings from c.1300 as a translation of the Hebrew [[shalom]]. Such a translation is, however, imprecise, as [[Shalom]], which is also cognate with the Arabic &quot;[[S-L-M|salaam]]&quot;, has multiple other meanings in addition to peace, including justice, good health, safety, well-being, prosperity, equity, security, good fortune, and friendliness. At a personal level, peaceful behaviors are kind, considerate, [[respect]]ful, just, and tolerant of others' beliefs and behaviors—tending to manifest [[good faith|goodwill]].

This latter understanding of peace can also pertain to an individual's introspective sense or concept of her/himself, as in being &quot;at peace&quot; in one's own mind, as found in European references from c.1200. The early English term is also used in the sense of &quot;[[Silence|quiet]]&quot;, reflecting calm, serene, and meditative approaches to family or group relationships that avoid quarreling and seek [[tranquility]] — an absence of disturbance or agitation.

In many languages the word for peace is also used a greeting or a farewell, for example the Hawaiian word [[Aloha]], as well as the Arabic word [[S-L-M|salaam]].  In English the word peace is occasionally used as a farewell, especially for the dead, as in the phrase 'Rest In Peace' [[Rest In Peace|RIP]].

Buddhists believe that peace can be attained once all suffering ends. They regard all suffering as stemming from cravings (in the extreme, greed), aversions (fears), or delusions. To eliminate such suffering and achieve personal peace, followers in the path of the Buddha adhere to a set of teachings called the Four Noble Truths — a central tenet in Buddhist philosophy.
 
Islam means submission. The title &quot;Muslim&quot;—etymologically directly related to salaam and the name Islam—means a person who submits to Allah in salaam. The submission to Allah (the Arabic proper noun for &quot;The God&quot;, One and Only) is based on humility. An attitude of humility within one's own self cannot be accomplished without total rejection of violence, and a personal attitude and alignment toward peace.

==Religious beliefs and peace {{anchor|Religion}}==
{{redirect|Peace of God|the medieval movement|Peace and Truce of God}}
[[File:Gari-Melchers-Peace-Highsmith.jpeg|thumb|250px|[[Gari Melchers]], Mural of Peace, 1896.]]

Religious beliefs often seek to identify and address the basic problems of human life, including the conflicts between, among, and within persons and societies.

Many [[Christians]] call their prophet [[Jesus of Nazareth]] the &quot;Prince of Peace&quot;, and see him as a [[messiah]] (savior or deliverer), the &quot;[[Christ]]&quot;, who manifested as the [[Son of God]] on Earth to establish [[God's Kingdom]] of Peace, wherein persons, societies, and all of Creation are to be healed of evil.  For persons to enter this Kingdom and experience peace, Christians believe that one must develop a personal relationship with [[Jesus Christ]], who stated: &quot;Come to me, all you who labor and are burdened, and I will give you rest. Take my yoke upon you and learn from me, for I am meek and humble of heart; and you will find rest for your souls. For my yoke is easy, and my burden light.&quot; ({{bibleverse||Matthew|11:28-30|NAB}}) According to Pope [[Benedict XVI]], &quot;Peace is achieved by consciences that are open to the truth and to love&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/angelus/2011/documents/hf_ben-xvi_ang_20110101_world-day-peace_en.html  Message for World Day of Peace. Jan. 1, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; Elsewhere Benedict links peace to ecology: &quot;humanity, if it truly desires peace, must be increasingly conscious of the links between natural ecology, or respect for nature, and human ecology. Experience shows that disregard for the environment always harms human coexistence, and vice versa. It becomes more and more evident that there is an inseparable link between peace with creation and peace among men. Both of these presuppose peace with God. The poem-prayer of Saint Francis, known as &quot;the Canticle of Brother Sun&quot;, is a wonderful and ever timely example of this multifaceted ecology of peace&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/messages/peace/documents/hf_ben-xvi_mes_20061208_xl-world-day-peace_en.html Message for World Day of Peace, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Buddhist]]s believe that peace can be attained once all suffering ends. They regard all suffering as stemming from cravings (in the extreme, greed), aversions (fears), or delusions. To eliminate such suffering and achieve personal peace, followers in the path of the [[Buddha]] adhere to a set of teachings called the [[Four Noble Truths]] — a central tenet in Buddhist philosophy.

[[Islam]] means submission. The title &quot;[[Muslim]]&quot;—etymologically directly related to [[S-L-M|salaam]] and the name [[Islam]]—means a person who submits to [[Allah]] in [[S-L-M|salaam]].  The submission to Allah (the Arabic proper noun for &quot;The God&quot;, One and Only) is based on humility. An attitude of humility within one's own self cannot be accomplished without total rejection of violence, and a personal attitude and alignment toward peace.
{{See also|Catholic peace traditions|Peace in Islamic philosophy}}

===Inner peace===
{{main|Inner peace}}
Inner peace (or peace of mind) refers to a state of being mentally and spiritually at peace, with enough [[knowledge]] and understanding to keep oneself strong in the face of discord or stress. Being &quot;at peace&quot; is considered by many to be healthy [[homeostasis]] and the opposite of being stressed or anxious. Peace of mind is generally associated with bliss and happiness.

Peace of mind, serenity, and calmness are descriptions of a disposition free from the effects of stress. In some cultures, inner peace is considered a state of consciousness or enlightenment that may be cultivated by various forms of training, such as prayer, meditation, t'ai chi ch'uan ([[T'ai chi ch'uan|太极拳, tàijíquán]]) or yoga, for example. Many spiritual practices refer to this peace as an experience of knowing oneself. Finding inner peace is often associated with traditions such as [[Buddhism]] and [[Hinduism]] as well as the [[New Age]] movement. Inner peace is also the first of four concepts to living life in the [[rave]] culture acronym [[PLUR]].

=== Satyagraha ===
{{Main|Satyagraha}}
'''Satyagraha''' ({{lang-sa|सत्याग्रह}} {{IAST|''satyāgraha''}}) is a philosophy and practice of [[nonviolent resistance]] developed by [[Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi]] (also known as &quot;Mahatma&quot; Gandhi). He deployed satyagraha techniques in campaigns for [[India]]n independence and also during his earlier struggles in [[South Africa]].

The word [[satyagraha]] itself was coined through a public contest that Gandhi sponsored through the newspaper he published in South Africa, 'Indian Opinion', when he realized that neither the common, contemporary Hindu language nor the English language contained a word which fully expressed his own meanings and intentions when he talked about his nonviolent approaches to conflict. According to Gandhi's autobiography, the contest winner was Maganlal Gandhi (presumably no relation), who submitted the entry 'sadagraha', which Gandhi then modified to 'satyagraha'. Etymologically, this Hindic word means 'truth-firmness', and is commonly translated as 'steadfastness in the truth' or 'truth-force'.

Satyagraha theory also influenced [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] during the campaigns he led during the [[civil rights movement]] in the United States. The theory of satyagraha sees means and ends as inseparable. Therefore, it is contradictory to try to use violence to obtain peace. As Gandhi wrote: “They say, 'means are, after all, means'. I would say, 'means are, after all, everything'. As the means so the end...”&lt;ref&gt;R. K. Prabhu &amp; U. R. Rao, editors; from section [http://www.mkgandhi.org/momgandhi/chap45.htm “The Gospel Of Sarvodaya], of the book [http://www.mkgandhi.org/momgandhi/momindex.htm The Mind of Mahatma Gandhi], Ahemadabad, India, Revised Edition, 1967.&lt;/ref&gt; A contemporary quote sometimes attributed to Gandhi, but also to [[A. J. Muste]], sums it up: 'There is no way to peace; peace is the way.'

==Justice and injustice==
Since classical times, it has been noted that peace has sometimes been achieved by the victor over the vanquished by the imposition of ruthless measures. In his book ''[[Agricola (book)|Agricola]]'' the Roman historian [[Tacitus]] includes eloquent and vicious polemics against the rapacity and greed of Rome. One, that Tacitus says is by the [[Caledonia]]n chieftain [[Calgacus]], ends ''Auferre trucidare rapere falsis nominibus imperium, atque ubi solitudinem faciunt, pacem appellant.'' (To ravage, to slaughter, to usurp under false titles, they call empire; and where they make a desert, they call it peace. — Oxford Revised Translation).

More recently, advocates for radical reform in justice systems have called for a public policy adoption of non-punitive, non-violent [[Restorative Justice]] methods, and many of those studying the success of these methods, including a [http://cpcjalliance.org/themes/restorative-justice-working-group/ United Nations working group on Restorative Justice], have attempted to re-define justice in terms related to peace. From the late 2000s on, a Theory of Active Peace has been proposed which conceptually integrates justice into a larger peace theory.

==Movements and activism==

===Peace movement===
{{Main|Peace movement}}

[[File:Peace Tattoo San Diego County Fair 2009.jpg|thumb|Peace Tattoo and Peace Signs, San Diego County Fair, Del Mar, California, 2009]]A '''peace movement''' is a [[social movement]] that seeks to achieve ideals such as the ending of a particular war (or all wars), or minimizing inter-human violence in a particular place or type of situation, often linked to the goal of achieving [[world peace]]. Means to achieve these ends usually include advocacy of [[pacifism]], [[non-violent resistance]], [[diplomacy]], [[boycott]]s, [[moral purchasing]], supporting anti-war political candidates, [[Demonstration (people)|demonstrations]], and [[lobbying]] to create legislation.

===Pacifism===
{{Main|Pacifism}}

'''Pacifism''' is the categorical opposition to any forms of [[war]] or [[violence]] as a means of settling disputes or gaining advantage. Pacifism covers a spectrum of views ranging from the belief that international disputes can and should be peacefully resolved; to calls for the abolition of the institutions of the military and war; to opposition to any organization of society through governmental force ([[Anarcho-pacifism|anarchist]] or [[Libertarianism|libertarian]] pacifism); to rejection of the use of physical violence to obtain political, economic or social goals; to opposition to violence under any circumstance, including defense of self and others.

Pacifism may be based on [[morality|moral]] principles (a [[deontological]] view) or [[pragmatism]] (a [[consequentialist]] view). Principled pacifism holds that violence of any form is an inappropriate response to conflict, and is morally wrong.  Pragmatic pacifism holds that the costs of war and inter-personal violence are so substantial that better ways of resolving disputes must be found. Pacifists in general reject theories of [[Just War]].

===Organizations===

====United Nations====
{{Main|United Nations}}
The United Nations (UN) is an international organization whose stated aims are to facilitate cooperation in international law, international security, economic development, social progress, human rights, and achieving world peace. The UN was founded in 1945 after World War II to replace the League of Nations, to stop wars between countries, and to provide a platform for dialogue.

{{See also|List of United Nations peacekeeping missions}}
[[Image:United Nations peacekeeping missions 2009.svg|thumb|[[List of UN peacekeeping missions|UN peacekeeping missions]]. Dark blue regions indicate current missions, while light blue regions represent former missions.]]
The UN, after approval by the [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]], sends [[peacekeeping|peacekeepers]] to regions where armed conflict has recently ceased or paused to enforce the terms of peace agreements and to discourage combatants from resuming hostilities. Since the UN does not maintain its own military, peacekeeping forces are voluntarily provided by member states of the UN. The forces, also called the &quot;Blue Helmets&quot;, who enforce UN accords are awarded [[United Nations Medal]]s, which are considered [[international decoration]]s instead of [[military decoration]]s. The peacekeeping force as a whole received the [[Nobel Peace Prize]] in 1988.

====Nobel Peace Prize====
{{Main|Nobel Peace Prize}}
The highest honor awarded to peace maker is the [[Nobel Prize in Peace]], awarded since 1901 by the [[Norwegian Nobel Committee]]. It is awarded annually to internationally notable persons following the prize's creation in the will of [[Alfred Nobel]]. According to Nobel's will, the Peace Prize shall be awarded to the person who

{{cquote|...shall have done the most or the best work for fraternity between nations, for the abolition or reduction of standing armies and for the holding and promotion of peace congresses.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://nobelprize.org/alfred_nobel/will/short_testamente.html | accessdate = 2008-03-31 | title = Excerpt from the Will of Alfred Nobel | publisher = [[Nobel Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

====Rhodes Scholarships and other fellowships====
In creating the [[Rhodes Scholarships]] for outstanding students from the United States, Germany and much of the British Empire, [[Cecil Rhodes]] wrote in 1901 that 'the object is that an understanding between the three great powers will render war impossible and educational relations make the strongest tie'.&lt;ref&gt;http://files.rhodes.gethifi.com/Ottawa_September_2011_To_render_war_impossible.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  This peace purpose of the Rhodes Scholarships was very prominent in the first half of the 20th century, and has become prominent again under Warden of the Rhodes House [[Donald Markwell]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rhodeshouse.ox.ac.uk/news/cecil-rhodess-vision-of-peace-highlighted&lt;/ref&gt; This vision greatly influenced Senator [[J. William Fulbright]] in the goal of the Fulbright fellowships to promote international understanding and peace, and has guided many other international fellowship programs.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.politics.ox.ac.uk/materials/news/Fulbright_18May12_Arndt.pdf , http://www.rhodeshouse.ox.ac.uk/news/honouring-j-william-fulbright&lt;/ref&gt;

====Gandhi Peace Prize====
{{main|Gandhi Peace Prize}}
The International Gandhi Peace Prize, named after [[Mahatma Gandhi]], is awarded annually by the [[Government of India]]. It is launched as a tribute to the ideals espoused by Gandhi in 1995 on the occasion of the 125th anniversary of his birth. This is an annual award given to individuals and institutions for their contributions towards social, economic and political transformation through non-violence and other Gandhian methods. The award carries Rs. 10 million in cash, convertible in any currency in the world, a plaque and a citation. It is open to all persons regardless of nationality, race, creed or sex.

====Paul Bartlett Ré Peace Prize====
{{Main|Paul Bartlett Ré Peace Prize}}
The [[Paul Bartlett Ré Peace Prize]], named after the artist [[Paul Ré]], is awarded bi-annually by the [[University of New Mexico]] (UNM).

====Student Peace Prize====
{{Main|Student Peace Prize}}
The [[Student Peace Prize]] is awarded biennially to a student or a student organization that has made a significant contribution to promoting peace and human rights.

====Other====
{{See also|Peace museums}}
A peace museum is a museum that documents historical peace initiatives. Many peace museums also provide advocacy programs for nonviolent conflict resolution. This may include conflicts at the personal, regional or international level.

Smaller institutions:
* [[Randolph Bourne Institute]]
* The [[McGill Middle East Program]] of Civil Society and Peace Building
* [[International Festival of Peace Poetry]]

==Monuments==
The following are monuments to peace:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Name
! Location
! Organization
! Meaning
|-
| [[Japanese Peace Bell]]
| [[New York City]], NY, USA
| [[United Nations]]
| World peace
| [[File:Japanese Peace Bell of United Nations.JPG|100px]]
|-
| [[Fountain of Time]]
| [[Chicago]], IL, USA
| [[Chicago Park District]]
| 100 years of peace between the USA and UK
| [[File:Fountain of Time front1.jpg|100px]]
|-
| Confederate Memorial&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arlingtoncemetery.org/Visitor_information/Confederate_Memorial.html File:War Abs.jpg]&lt;/ref&gt;
| Arlington, Va, USA
| [[Arlington National Cemetery]]
| Southern States choosing peace over war
| [[File:Confederate Memorial Arlington Cemetery LOC13525v.jpg|100px]]
|-
|[[International Peace Garden]]
|[[North Dakota]], [[Manitoba]]
|non-profit organization
|Peace between the US and Canada, World peace
| [[File:2009-0521-CDNtrip003-PeaceGarden.jpg|100px]]
|-
|[[Peace Arch]]
|border between US and Canada, near [[Surrey, British Columbia]].
|non-profit organization
|Built to honor the first 100 years of peace between [[Great Britain]] and the [[United States]] resulting from the signing of the [[Treaty of Ghent]] in 1814.
| [[File:Peace Arch.JPG|100px]]
|-
|[[Statue of Europe]]
|[[Brussels]]
|[[European Commission]]
|Unity in Peace in Europe
|[[File:Statue of Europe-(Unity-in-Peace).jpg|100px]] 
|}

==Theories==
{{Expand section|date=April 2008}}
Many different theories of &quot;peace&quot; exist in the world of [[peace studies]], which involves the study of conflict transformation, disarmament, and cessation of violence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.einaudi.cornell.edu/peaceprogram/ einaudi.cornell.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; The definition of &quot;peace&quot; can vary with religion, culture, or subject of study.

One definition is that peace is a state of balance and understanding in yourself and between others, where respect is gained by the acceptance of differences, tolerance persists, conflicts are resolved through dialog, people's rights are respected and their voices are heard, and everyone is at their highest point of serenity without social tension.{{citation}}

===Game theory===
{{Main|Peace war game}}
The Peace War Game is a [[game theory]] approach to peace and conflict studies. An [[iterated game]] originally played in academic groups and by [[computer simulation]] for years to study possible strategies of [[cooperation]] and [[aggression]].&lt;ref&gt;Shy, O., 1996, ''[[industrial organization|Industrial Organization]]: Theory and Applications'', Cambridge, Mass.: The [[MIT]] Press.&lt;/ref&gt; As peace makers became richer over time, it became clear that making war had greater costs than initially anticipated. The only [[strategy]] that acquired wealth more rapidly was a &quot;[[Genghis Khan]]&quot;, a constant aggressor making war continually to gain resources. This led to the development of the &quot;provokable nice guy&quot; [[strategy]], a peace-maker until attacked, improved upon merely to win by occasional forgiveness even when attacked. Multiple players continue to gain wealth cooperating with each other while bleeding the constant aggressor. Such actions led in essence to the development of the [[Hanseatic League]] for trade and mutual defense following centuries of [[Viking]] depredation.&lt;ref&gt;from conversation with [http://sa.ncsu.edu/S&amp;A/faculty/troost/troost_vita.html NCSU Professor of Sociology Kay M. Troost]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Democratic peace theory===
{{Main|Democratic peace theory}}
The democratic peace theory holds that democracies will never go to war with one another.

===Theory of 'Active Peace'===
Borrowing from the teachings of Norwegian theorist [[Johan Galtung]], one of the pioneers of the field of [[Peace and conflict studies|Peace Research]], on 'Positive Peace',&lt;ref&gt;Galtung, J: ''Peace by peaceful means: peace and conflict, development and civilization'', page 32. Sage Publications, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; and on the writings of Maine Quaker [http://199.33.141.23/COMMUNITY/FacultyPages/Cox/thewaysofpeace/wopindex.html Gray Cox], a consortium of theorists, activists, and practitioners in the experimental [http://woolman.ning.com John Woolman College] initiative have arrived at a theory of Active Peace.  This theory posits in part that Peace is part of a triad, which also includes justice and wholeness (or well-being), an interpretation consonant with scriptural scholarly interpretations of the meaning of the early Hebrew word S-L-M or 'Shalom', called by some [http://www.amazon.com/Shalom-Bibles-Salvation-Justice-Peace/dp/0916035913 the Bible's word for salvation, justice, and peace].  Furthermore, the consortium have integrated Galtung's teaching of the meanings of the terms peacemaking, peacekeeping, and peacebuilding, to also fit into a triadic and interdependent formulation or structure.  Vermont Quaker John V. Wilmerding, Jr., convener of this 'John Woolman College of Active Peace', posits five stages of growth applicable to individuals, communities, and societies, whereby one transcends first the 'surface' awareness that most people have of these kinds of issues, emerging successively into acquiescence, pacifism, passive resistance, active resistance, and finally into Active Peace, dedicating themselves to peacemaking, peacekeeping, and/or peace building.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Wilmerding | first = John | title = The Theory of Active Peace | url=http://internationalpeaceandconflict.ning.com/forum/topics/the-theory-of-active-peace | accessdate = 07 February 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Many Peaces===
Following [[Wolfgang Dietrich]],Wolfgang Sützl&lt;ref&gt;[[Wolfgang Dietrich]]/Wolfgang Sützl: A Call for Many Peaces; in: Dietrich, Wolfgang, Josefina Echavarría Alvarez, Norbert Koppensteiner eds.: Key Texts of Peace Studies; LIT Münster, Vienna, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Innsbruck School of Peace Studies]], some peace thinkers have abandoned any single and all-encompassing definition of peace. Rather, they promote the idea of Many Peaces. They argue that since no singular, correct definition of peace can exist, peace should be perceived as a plurality. This post-modern understanding of peace(s) was based on the philosophy of [[Jean Francois Lyotard]]. It served as a fundament for the more recent concept of trans-rational peace(s) and elicitive conflict transformation.

===Trans-rational Peaces===
In 2008 [[Wolfgang Dietrich]] enlarged his earlier approach of the Many Peaces to the so-called &quot;five families&quot; of peace interpretations: the energetic, moral, modern, post-modern and trans-rational approach.&lt;ref&gt;[[Wolfgang Dietrich]]: Interpretations of Peace in History and Culture; Palgrave Macmillan, London, 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Trans-rationality unites the rational and mechanistic understanding of modern peace in a relational and culture-based manner with spiritual narratives and energetic interpretations.&lt;ref&gt;[[Wolfgang Dietrich]], Josefina Echavarría Alvarez, Gustavo Esteva, Daniela Ingruber, Norbert Koppensteiner eds.: The Palgrave International Handbook of Peace Studies. A Cultural Approach; Palgrave MacMillan London, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The systemic understanding of trans-rational peaces advocates a client-centred method of conflict transformation, the so-called elicitive approach.&lt;ref&gt;[[John Paul Lederach]]: Preparing for Peace; Syracuse University Press, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;

==Peace and conflict studies==
[[Image:Peace-and-Prosperity-Vedder-Highsmith-detail-1.jpeg|thumb|250px|Detail from ''Peace and Prosperity'' (1896), [[Elihu Vedder]], Library of Congress [[Thomas Jefferson Building]], Washington, D.C.]]
{{Main|Peace and conflict studies}}
'''Peace and conflict studies''' is an [[academic field]] which identifies and analyses [[Violence|violent]] and [[Nonviolence|nonviolent]] behaviours, as well as the structural mechanisms attending violent and non violent [[social conflict]]s.  This is to better understand the processes leading to a more desirable [[human condition]].&lt;ref&gt;Dugan, 1989: 74&lt;/ref&gt; One variation,
'''Peace studies''' ([[irenology]]), is an [[Interdisciplinarity|interdisciplinary]] effort aiming at the prevention, [[de-escalation]], and solution of conflicts. This contrasts with [[war studies]] (polemology), directed at the efficient attainment of victory in conflicts. Disciplines involved may include [[political science]], [[geography]], [[economics]], [[psychology]], [[sociology]], [[international relations]], [[history]], [[anthropology]], [[religious studies]], and [[gender studies]], as well as a variety of others.

==Measuring and Ranking Peace==
Although peace is widely perceived as something intangible, various organizations have been making efforts to quantify and measure it. [[Global Peace Index|The Global Peace Index]] produced by [[Institute for Economics and Peace|the Institute for Economics and Peace]] is a known effort to evaluate peacefulness in countries based on 23 indicators of the presence/absence of violence. The last edition of the Index ranks 158 countries on their internal and external levels of peace. According to the 2012 Global Peace Index, Iceland is the most peaceful country in the world while Somalia is the least peaceful one. [[List of countries by Failed States Index|The Failed State Index]] created by the [[Fund for Peace]] focuses on risk for instability or violence in 177 nations. This index measures how fragile a state is by 12 indicators and subindicators that evaluate aspects of politics, social economy, and military facets in countries. The 2012 Failed State Index reports that the most fragile nation is Somalia, and the least fragile one is Finland. [[University of Maryland, College Park|University of Maryland]] publishes the Peace and Conflict Instability Ledger in order to measure peace. It grades 163 countries with 5 indicators, and pays the most attention to risk of political instability or armed conflict over a three-year period. The most recent ledger shows that the most peaceful country is Slovenia on the contrary Afghanistan is the most conflicted nation. Besides indicated above reports from the Institute for Economics and Peace, Fund for Peace, and University of Maryland, other organizations like the [[Economist Intelligence Unit]] and George Mason University release indexes that rank countries in terms of peacefulness.

==See also==
[[File:WikiConference India 2011 Jimmy Wales 4.jpg|thumb|right|250px|[[Jimmy Wales]] talking about [[NPOV]] as a means to peace at WikiConference India 2011]]

{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Catholic peace traditions]]
* [[Creative Peacebuilding]]
* [[Global Peace Index]]
* [[Group on International Perspectives on Governmental Aggression and Peace]] (GIPGAP)
* [[International Day of Peace]]
* [[Moral syncretism]]
* [[Peace education]]
* [[Peace in Islamic philosophy]]
* [[Peace Journalism]]
* [[Peace makers]]
* [[Peace One Day]]
* [[Peace symbol]]
* [[peacekeeping]]
* [[peacemaking]]
* [[Structural violence]]
* [[Sulh]]
* [[Suresh Joachim|World Cease fire day]]
* [[War resister]]
* [[World peace]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*[http://www.sas.upenn.edu/African_Studies/Articles_Gen/Letter_Birmingham.html Letter from Birmingham Jail] by [[Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr.]].
*&quot;Pennsylvania, A History of the Commonwealth,&quot; esp. pg. 109, edited by Randall M. Miller and William Pencak, The Pennsylvania State University Press, 2002.
*[http://www.peacefulsocieties.org/index.html Peaceful Societies, Alternatives to Violence and War] Short profiles on 25 peaceful societies.
*''The Path to Peace,'' by Laure Paquette

==External links==
{{Sister project links|Peace}}
* [http://www.carnegieendowment.org Carnegie Endowment for International Peace]
* [http://www.carnegiecouncil.org/index.html Lemonade a la Carnegie] accessed October 16, 2012
* [http://peacewiki.pbworks.com/ PeaceWiki]
* [http://peace.maripo.com/ Peace Monuments Around the World]
* {{dmoz|Society/Issues/Peace|Peace}}
* [http://www.frient.de Working Group on Peace and Development (FriEnt)]
* [http://www.quora.com/How-do-we-achieve-world-peace Answers to: &quot;How do we achieve world peace?&quot;]

&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;

{{Social and political philosophy}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

[[Category:Peace| ]]
[[Category:Core issues in ethics]]
[[Category:Nonviolence]]
[[Category:Pacifism]]
[[Category:Ethical principles]]
[[Category:Social concepts]]

[[af:Vrede]]
[[ar:سلام]]
[[an:Paz]]
[[arc:ܫܠܡܐ (ܫܝܢܐ)]]
[[ast:Paz]]
[[az:Sülh]]
[[bn:শান্তি]]
[[ba:Тыныслыҡ]]
[[be:Мір]]
[[be-x-old:Мір]]
[[bg:Мир]]
[[bo:ཞི་བདེ།]]
[[bs:Mir (stanje)]]
[[br:Peoc'h]]
[[ca:Pau]]
[[cs:Mír]]
[[ch:Pås]]
[[cy:Heddwch]]
[[da:Fred]]
[[pdc:Fridde]]
[[de:Frieden]]
[[et:Rahu]]
[[el:Ειρήνη]]
[[es:Paz]]
[[eo:Paco]]
[[eu:Bake]]
[[fa:صلح]]
[[hif:Santi]]
[[fr:Paix]]
[[fy:Frede]]
[[fur:Pâs]]
[[ga:Síocháin]]
[[gl:Paz]]
[[ko:평화]]
[[hr:Mir]]
[[id:Damai]]
[[ia:Pace]]
[[is:Friður]]
[[it:Pace]]
[[he:שלום]]
[[krc:Мамырлыкъ]]
[[ka:მშვიდობა]]
[[kk:Бейбітшілік]]
[[sw:Amani]]
[[ht:Lapè]]
[[ku:Aştî]]
[[la:Pax]]
[[lv:Miers]]
[[lt:Taika]]
[[hu:Béke]]
[[mk:Мир]]
[[ml:സമാധാനം]]
[[mr:शांतता]]
[[arz:سلام]]
[[mwl:Paç]]
[[nl:Vrede]]
[[new:शान्ति]]
[[ja:平和]]
[[no:Fred]]
[[nn:Fred]]
[[oc:Patz]]
[[pnb:امن]]
[[pcd:Pèx]]
[[pl:Pokój (polityka)]]
[[pt:Paz]]
[[ty:Pau]]
[[ksh:Vreede]]
[[ro:Pace]]
[[rm:Pasch]]
[[qu:Thak]]
[[rue:Мір]]
[[ru:Мир (отсутствие войны)]]
[[sq:Paqja]]
[[scn:Paci]]
[[si:සාමය]]
[[simple:Peace]]
[[sk:Mier]]
[[sl:Mir (družbeno stanje)]]
[[ckb:ئاشتی]]
[[sr:Мир]]
[[sh:Mir]]
[[fi:Rauha]]
[[sv:Fred]]
[[tl:Kapayapaan]]
[[ta:அமைதி]]
[[te:శాంతి]]
[[th:สันติภาพ]]
[[tg:Сулҳ]]
[[chr:ᏅᏩᏙ ᎯᏯᏛ]]
[[tr:Barış]]
[[uk:Мир]]
[[ur:امن]]
[[vec:Paxe]]
[[vi:Hòa bình]]
[[fiu-vro:Rahu]]
[[wa:Påye]]
[[war:Kalinawan]]
[[yi:פרידן]]
[[zh-yue:和平 (關係)]]
[[bat-smg:Taika]]
[[zh:和平]]</text>
      <sha1>4ysgi1bh9ju5nxw9a00es8j1fc51idf</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
