<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Perpetual virginity of Mary</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>715178</id>
    <revision>
      <id>500335161</id>
      <parentid>500330611</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-02T14:26:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>History2007</username>
        <id>3684925</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>lede does not need the ref if summarizes the body, but anyway....</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="43489">[[File:Vladimirskaya.jpg|thumb|The [[Theotokos of Vladimir|Vladimir]] [[Eleusa icon]] of the Ever Virgin Mary. The ''[[Aeiparthenos]]'' (Ever Virgin) title is widely used in [[Eastern Orthodox]] liturgy.&lt;ref&gt;''What Every Catholic Should Know about Mary'' by Terrence J. McNally 2009 ISBN 1-4415-1051-6 page 168 [http://books.google.com/books?id=IlJRXgcBVvoC&amp;pg=PA168&amp;dq=%22ever+virgin%22+orthodox&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0vFcTrbeB4nKsgaI9rzDDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22ever%20virgin%22%20orthodox&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The doctrine of the '''perpetual virginity of Mary''' expresses the [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Virgin Mary]]'s &quot;real and perpetual [[virginity]] even in the act of giving birth to [[Jesus]] the [[Incarnation (Christianity)|Son of God made Man]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=Miravalle56 /&gt;&lt;ref name=REBrown273 /&gt; According to the doctrine, Mary was ever-virgin ({{lang-grc|ἀειπαρθένος|aeiparthenos}}) for the whole of her life, making Jesus her only biological son, whose [[Virgin birth of Jesus|conception]] and [[Nativity of Jesus|birth]] are held to be miraculous.&lt;ref name=Miravalle56 /&gt;&lt;ref name=REBrown273 /&gt;

By the fourth century, the doctrine had been widely supported by the [[Church Fathers]], and by the seventh century it had been affirmed in a number of [[ecumenical councils]].&lt;ref name=BWell315 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Bromiley271 /&gt;&lt;ref name=ThemeM2 /&gt; The doctrine is part of the [[doctrine|teaching]] of [[Catholic Church|Catholicism]] and [[Anglo-Catholics]], as well as [[Orthodox Church|Eastern]] and [[Oriental Orthodoxy]], as expressed in their [[liturgy|liturgies]], in which they repeatedly refer to Mary as &quot;ever virgin&quot;.&lt;ref name=MWebster &gt;''Merriam-Webster's encyclopedia of world religions'' by Merriam-Webster, Inc. 1999 ISBN 0-87779-044-2 page 1134&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1K.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church'' §499]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ocf.org/OrthodoxPage/liturgy/liturgy.html Divine Liturgy of St John Chrysostom], [http://www.coptic.net/prayers/StBasilLiturgy.html Coptic Liturgy of St Basil], [http://www.copticchurch.net/topics/liturgy/liturgy_of_st_cyril.pdf Liturgy of St Cyril], [http://web.ukonline.co.uk/ephrem/lit-james.htm Liturgy of St James], [http://www.frmichel.najim.net/liturgyvid.pdf Understanding the Orthodox Liturgy] etc.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some early Protestant reformers such as [[Martin Luther]] supported the doctrine. However, later Reformed teaching largely abandoned it.&lt;ref name=Nally170 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Ted47 /&gt; The doctrine of perpetual virginity is, however, currently maintained by some [[Anglican]] and [[Lutheran]] theologians.&lt;ref name=MWebster /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Gregory Lee, ''Catholic, Lutheran, Protestant: a doctrinal comparison''. 1993 ISBN 978-0-615-16635-3 page 254&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bäumer, Remigius. ''Marienlexikon''. Gesamtausgabe. Leo Scheffczyk, ed. Regensburg: Institutum Marianum, 1994. ISBN 3-88096-891-8, p. 190. In particular, it was the lifelong belief of Luther himself (''Luther's Works''. The American Edition. Jaroslav J. Pelikan &amp; Helmut Lehmann, eds. 55 vols. St. Louis &amp; Philadelphia: CPH &amp; Fortress Press, 1955-1986. Vol. 22, pp. 214-215).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.btw3.com/classfiles/HT1/PerpetualVirginity.pdf B. Townsend Waddill III, &quot;The Perpetual Virginity of Mary&quot;.] Founding figures of Anglicanism such as [[Hugh Latimer]] and [[Thomas Cranmer]] &quot;followed the tradition that they had inherited by accepting Mary as 'ever virgin'&quot; (http://www.anglicancommunion.org/ministry/ecumenical/dialogues/catholic/arcic/docs/pdf/mary_commentary_Tim_Bradshaw.pdf Timothy Bradshaw, &quot;Commentary and Study Guide on the Seattle Statement ''Mary: Hope and Grace in Christ'' of the Anglican – Roman Catholic International Commission&quot;).]&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Doctrine and representations==
[[File:Boucicaut-Meister.jpg|thumb|left|180px|Annunciation, [[Hours of Jean de Boucicaut|Hours of Boucicaut]], c. 1405]]
The doctrine of the perpetual virginity of Mary, which is believed ''[[de fide]]'' (i.e. held by Catholics as being an essential part of faith), states that Mary was a virgin before, during and after giving birth for all her life.&lt;ref name=Miravalle56 &gt;Mark Miravalle, 1993, ''Introduction to Mary'', Queenship Publishing ISBN 978-1-882972-06-7, pages 56-64&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=REBrown273 /&gt; The threefold nature this doctrine (referring to ''before'', ''during'' and ''after'') thus subsumes the doctrine of the [[virgin birth of Jesus]].&lt;ref name=Miravalle56 /&gt;&lt;ref name=REBrown273 &gt;''Mary in the New Testament'' edited by Raymond Edward Brown 1978 ISBN 0-8091-2168-9 page 273&lt;/ref&gt;

The doctrine of perpetual virginity is also distinct from the dogma of the [[Immaculate Conception]] of Mary, which relates to the conception of the Virgin Mary herself without any stain (''macula'' in [[Latin]]) of [[original sin]].&lt;ref&gt;''A history of the church in the Middle Ages'' by F. Donald Logan, 2002, ISBN 0-415-13289-4, p150&lt;/ref&gt;

The Greek term ''[[Aeiparthenos]]'' (i.e. &quot;Ever Virgin&quot;) is attested to by [[Epiphanius of Salamis]] from the early 4th century.&lt;ref&gt;''Joseph, Mary, Jesus'' by Lucien Deiss, Madeleine Beaumont 1996 ISBN 0-8146-2255-0 page 30&lt;/ref&gt; It is widely used in the liturgy of the [[Eastern Orthodox]] Church.&lt;ref&gt;''The image of the Virgin Mary in the Akathistos hymn'' by Leena Mari Peltomaa 2001 ISBN 90-04-12088-2 page 127&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Catechism of the Catholic Church]] (item 499) also includes to the term Aeiparthenos and referring to the dogmatic constitution [[Lumen Gentium]] (item 57) states: &quot;Christ's birth did not diminish his mother's virginal integrity but sanctified it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Catechism of the Catholic Church'' by the Vatican, 2002 ISBN 0-86012-324-3 page 112&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p122a3p2.htm ''Vatican website'': Catechism item 499]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19641121_lumen-gentium_en.html Vatican website: ''Lumen Gentium'' item 57]&lt;/ref&gt; The doctrine of perpetual virginity is also held by some [[Anglican]] and some [[Lutheran]] churches, but not all of those churches endorse the doctrine.&lt;ref name=MWebster /&gt; Eastern Orthodox liturgical prayers typically end with &quot;Remembering our most holy, pure, blessed, and glorious Lady, the Theotokos and Ever Virgin Mary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Eastern Orthodoxy through Western eyes'' by Donald Fairbairn 2002 ISBN 0-664-22497-0 page 100&lt;/ref&gt;

The virginity of Mary at the time of her conception of Jesus is a key topic in [[Marian art in the Catholic Church]], usually represented as the [[annunciation to Mary]] by the Archangel [[Gabriel]] that she would virginally conceive a child to be born the Son of God. [[Fresco]]s depicting this scene have appeared in [[Roman Catholic Marian churches]] for centuries.&lt;ref&gt;Annunciation Art, Phaidon Press, 2004, ISBN 0-7148-4447-0&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest fresco of the annunciation is a 4th century depiction in the [[Catacomb of Priscilla]] in Rome.&lt;ref&gt;''The Annunciation to Mary'' by Eugene Laverdiere 2007 ISBN 1-56854-557-6 page 29&lt;/ref&gt;

Mary's virginity even after her conception of Jesus is regularly represented in the [[Christian art]] of both the [[Eastern Orthodox]] and [[Oriental Orthodox]] (as well as in early Western religious art) by including in Nativity scenes the figure of [[Salome (disciple)|Salome]], whom the [[Gospel of James]] presents as finding that Mary had preserved her virginity even in giving birth to her son.&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of Comparative Iconography'' by Helene E. Roberts 1998 ISBN 1-57958-009-2 page 904&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Treasures from the Ark: 1700 Years of Armenian Christian Art'' by Vrej Nersessian 2001 ISBN 0-7123-4699-6 page 167&lt;/ref&gt; In many [[iconography|icons]], Mary's perpetual virginity is signified by three stars that appear on her left, her right, and above her or on her head, which represent her virginity before, during and after giving birth.&lt;ref&gt;''Heroes of the icon: people, places, events'' by Steven Bigham 1998 ISBN 1-879038-91-9 page 47&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The icon handbook'' by David Coomler 1995 ISBN 0-87243-210-6 page 203&lt;/ref&gt;

== Development of the doctrine ==

===Early Church===
[[File:Nativity (Throne of Maximianus).jpg|thumb|180px|Artistic representation of Mary's virginity even after giving birth to Jesus, as recounted in the Protoevangelium of James]]
As of the second century, interest developed within the [[Early Christianity|early Church]] regarding the conception of Jesus and the virginity of Mary.&lt;ref name=ThemeM &gt;&quot;The Theme of Mary's Virginity&quot;, in ''Mary in the New Testament'' edited by Raymond Edward Brown 1978 ISBN 0-8091-2168-9 pages 267-277&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of early Christian writers accepted the virginal conception of Jesus via reliance on the accounts in the gospels of Luke and Matthew, yet, the focus of these early discussions was of virginity before birth, not during or afterwards.&lt;ref name=ThemeM /&gt;&lt;ref name=Rahner896 /&gt;

The interpretation of the Matthew 1:25 statement that Joseph &quot;knew her not till she had brought forth her firstborn son&quot; and of the various New Testament mentions of the [[Desposyni|brothers]] (and sisters) of Jesus is discussed below under the heading &quot;Scripture&quot;. Some early writers{{who?|date=May 2012}} interpreted Matthew's statement to mean that Joseph and Mary did have normal marital relations after Jesus' birth, and that [[James the Just|James]], [[Joses]], [[Jude, brother of Jesus|Jude]], and [[Simon (brother of Jesus)|Simon]] were the biological sons of [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]] and [[Saint Joseph|Joseph]]; and, thus, Jesus' half-brothers.&lt;ref&gt;M. DelCogliano Tradition and Polemic in Basil of Caesarea's Homily on the Theophany - Vigiliae Christianae, 2012 &quot;... objection to Mary's perpetual virginity, for which, however, there is scant evidence before the middle of the fourth century (to be discussed in more detail below), was based on an interpretation of Matthew 1:25, according to which Joseph refrained from marital relations with Mary.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

A second century document that paid special attention to Mary’s virginity was originally known as the ''[[Nativity of Mary]]'', but later became known as the ''[[Protoevangelium of James]]''.&lt;ref name=REBrown273 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;L. Gambero, ''Mary and the Fathers of the Church'' trans. T. Buffer (San Francisco: Ignatius, 1991), p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; The document tells of Mary’s virginity before giving birth, the miraculous way in which she gave birth, and her physical virginity even after giving birth.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wesley.nnu.edu/sermons-essays-books/noncanonical-literature/book-of-james-or-protevangelium ''Protoevangelium of James'' (M.R. James translation), XIX-XX]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;L. Gambero, ''Mary and the Fathers of the Church'' trans. T. Buffer (San Francisco: Ignatius, 1991), p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Quasten, ''Patrology'' 1:120-1.&lt;/ref&gt; The work also claims that Jesus' &quot;brothers&quot; and &quot;sisters&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse ||Matthew|13:56}} and {{bibleverse ||Mark|6:3}}&lt;/ref&gt; are Joseph’s children from a marriage previous to his union with Mary.&lt;ref&gt;''Protoevangelium'' chapters 7&amp;ndash;8.&lt;/ref&gt; However, this text does not explicitly assert Mary's perpetual virginity after the birth of Jesus. 

The &quot;brothers&quot; and &quot;sisters&quot; of Jesus mentioned in the Gospels, and the &quot;James, the Lord's brother&quot;, mentioned in {{bibleverse||Galatians|1:19}}, &quot;the brother of Jesus, who was called Christ, whose name was James&quot;, mentioned by Josephus&lt;ref&gt;[http://religiousstudies.uncc.edu/people/jtabor/james.html Josephus, ''Antiquities'', book 20, chapter 9]&lt;/ref&gt; were thus interpreted by some texts as not being children of Mary. 
====2nd to 4th century====
There was no full consensus on the doctrine of perpetual virginity within the early Church by the end of the second century, e.g. [[Tertullian]] (c.160 – c.225) did not teach the doctrine (although he taught virgin birth), but [[Irenaeus]]  (c.130 – c.202) taught perpetual virginity, along with other Marian themes.&lt;ref name=Rahner896 /&gt; However, wider support for the doctrine began to appear within the next century.&lt;ref name=Rahner896 /&gt; 

[[Origen]] (185-254) was emphatic on the issue of the [[Desposyni|brothers of Jesus]], and stated that he believed them to have been the children of Joseph from a previous marriage.&lt;ref&gt;''The Westminster handbook to Origen'' by John Anthony McGuckin 2004 ISBN 0-664-22472-5 page 150&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Helvidius]] appealed to the authority of [[Tertullian]] against the doctrine of Mary's perpetual virginity, to which [[Jerome]] (c.340-419) replied, of Tertullian, that he was &quot;not a man of the church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Tertullian, Treatises on marriage and remarriage: - Page 160  ed. T. C. Lawler, Walter J. Burghardt - 1951 &quot;Helvidius appealed to the authority of Tertullian in his attack on the Church's doctrine of Mary's perpetual virginity, ... I have nothing else to say except that he was not a man of the Church (Ecclesiae hominem ,non fuisse).&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 4th century, the doctrine of perpetual virginity had been well attested.&lt;ref&gt;L. Gambero, ''Mary and the Fathers of the Church'' trans. T. Buffer (San Francisco: Ignatius, 1991) pp. 97-98; and also for an overview of each source.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, references can be found in the 3rd century writings of [[Hippolytus of Rome]], who called Mary &quot;the tabernacle exempt from defilement and corruption,&quot; &lt;ref name=Ripley264 /&gt; and the 4th century works of [[Athanasius]],&lt;ref&gt;Athanasius, ''Orations against the Arians'' 2.70&lt;/ref&gt; [[Epiphanius of Salamis|Epiphanius]],&lt;ref&gt;Epiphanius of Salamis, ''The Man Well-Anchored'' 120, c.f. ''Medicine Chest Against All Heresies''  78:6&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hilary of Poitiers|Hilary]],&lt;ref&gt;Hilary of Poitiers, ''Commentary on Matthew'' §1:4&lt;/ref&gt; [[Didymus the Blind|Didymus]],&lt;ref&gt;Didymus the Blind, ''The Trinity'' 3:4&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ambrose]],&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose of Milan, ''Letters'' 63:111&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jerome]],&lt;ref&gt;Jerome, ''[[Helvidius|Against Helvetius]]'', 21&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Pope Siricius|Siricius]]&lt;ref&gt;Denziger §91&lt;/ref&gt; continued the attestations to perpetual virginity - a trend that gathered pace in the next century.&lt;ref name=BWell315 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Bromiley271 &gt;''The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia'' by Geoffrey W. Bromiley 1995 ISBN 0-8028-3785-9 page 271&lt;/ref&gt;

===Church Fathers and the Middle Ages===
[[File:Otsy.jpg|thumb|220px|left|The ''[[Church Fathers]]'' in an 11th-century depiction from [[Kiev]]]]
[[John Chrysostom]] (347–407) defended perpetual virginity on a number of grounds, one of which was Jesus' commands to his mother in [[Calvary]]: &quot;Woman, behold your son!&quot; and to his disciple &quot;Behold, thy mother!&quot; in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#19:26|John 19:26-27]].&lt;ref name=MEvangel &gt;''Mary for evangelicals: toward an understanding of the mother of our Lord'' by Tim S. Perry, William J. Abraham 2006 ISBN 0-8308-2569-Xpages 153-154&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''John 11-21'' by Joel C. Elowsky 2007 ISBN 0-8308-1099-4 page 318&lt;/ref&gt; Since the second century these two [[Sayings of Jesus on the cross|statements of Jesus from the cross]] had been the basis of reasonings that Mary had no other children and &quot;from that hour the disciple took her unto his own home&quot; because after the deaths of Joseph and Jesus there was no one else to look after Mary, and she had to be entrusted to the disciple.&lt;ref name=Burke308 &gt;Burke, Raymond L.; et al. (2008). ''Mariology: A Guide for Priests, Deacons, Seminarians, and Consecrated Persons'' ISBN 978-1-57918-355-4 pages 308-309&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Miravalle62 &gt;Mark Miravalle, 1993, I''ntroduction to Mary'', Queenship Publishing ISBN 978-1-882972-06-7, pages 62-63&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time of [[Gregory of Nyssa]] and [[Augustine of Hippo]], with the increased emphasis on Marian piety, a wider role for Mary began to appear in the context of the history of salvation.&lt;ref name=ThemeM2 /&gt; Augustine himself presented a number of arguments in favor of the doctrine of perpetual virginity.&lt;ref&gt;''Augustine through the ages: an encyclopedia'' by John C. Cavadini 1999 ISBN 0-8028-3843-X page 544&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''St. Augustine, Faith, Hope &amp; Charity
 By J. Kuasten, Saint Augustine (Bishop of Hippo.) 1978 ISBN 0-8091-0045-2 page 126&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the 4th century, [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Luke#1:34|Luke 1:34]] (''How shall this be, seeing I know not a man?'') had started to be read as a passage that indicated a &quot;vow of perpetual virginity&quot; on the part of Mary.&lt;ref name=ThemeM2 &gt;''Mary in the New Testament'' edited by Raymond Edward Brown 1978 ISBN 0-8091-2168-9 pages 278-281&lt;/ref&gt; 

The concept of Mary's vow of virginity had already appeared in the Protovangelium (4:1) which asserted that Mary's mother, Anne, gave Mary as a &quot;virgin of the Lord&quot; in service in the Temple, and that Joseph, a widower, was to serve as her guardian (legal protections for women depended on their having a male protector: father, brother, or, failing that, a husband).&lt;ref&gt;''[[Protoevangelium of James]]'' 4, 7, 8-9, 15&lt;/ref&gt; Early in the 7th century, in the ''Short Book on the Perpetual Virginity of Blessed Mary'' [[Isidore of Seville]] connected the [[Mariology|Mariological]] and [[Christology|Christological]] themes by linking the virginity of Mary to the divinity of Christ in a single line of argument.&lt;ref&gt;''The History of Theology: Middle Ages'' by Giulio D'Onofrio, Basil Studer 2008 ISBN 0-8146-5916-0 page 38 &lt;/ref&gt; The [[Lateran Council of 649]], attended by [[Maximus the Confessor]], explicitly affirmed the teaching of Mary's virginity before, during and after birth.&lt;ref name=Rahner896 &gt;''Encyclopedia of theology: a concise Sacramentum mundi by Karl Rahner 2004 ISBN 0-86012-006-6 pages 896-897&lt;/ref&gt; This was further affirmed at the [[Third Council of Constantinople|sixth ecumenical council]] in 680.&lt;ref name=BWell315 &gt;''The Blackwell Companion to Catholicism'' by James Buckley, Frederick Christian Bauerschmidt, Trent Pomplun 2010 ISBN 1-4443-3732-7 page 315&lt;/ref&gt;

Another book, &quot;[[The History of Joseph the Carpenter]]&quot; (7th Century), presents Jesus as speaking, at the death of Joseph, of Mary as &quot;my mother, virgin undefiled&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Saint Joseph: His Life and His Role in the Church Today'' by Louise Bourassa Perrotta 2000 ISBN 0-87973-573-2 page 86&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the centuries the interpretation of Mary as an ever virgin bride of the Lord who had taken a vow of perpetual chastity spread and was in full vogue by the time of [[Rupert of Deutz]] in the 12th century.&lt;ref name=ThemeM2 /&gt; By the 13th century, [[Thomas Aquinas]] had fashioned long and detailed theological arguments in defense of the doctrine and stated that a denial of the perpetual virginity of Mary would be derogatory to the [[perfection of Christ]], an insult to the [[Holy Spirit (Christianity)|Holy Spirit]], and an affront to the dignity of the [[Mother of God]].&lt;ref&gt;''Aquinas on doctrine: a critical introduction'' by Thomas Gerard Weinandy, John Yocum 2004 ISBN 0-567-08411-6 page 95&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Westminster handbook to Thomas Aquinas'' by Joseph Peter Wawrykow 2005 ISBN 0-664-22469-5 page 91&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mary, the Second Eve===
[[File:MCB-mosaicob.jpg|thumb|170 px|13th century [[Byzantine]] [[Eleusa|Eleusa depiction]], of [[Madonna and Child]], [[Athens]]]]
As of the fourth century, in discussing God's plan of salvation, a parallel theme began to appear in which Mary's obedience (''be it unto me according to thy word'' in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Luke#1:38|Luke 1:38]]) and the doctrine of perpetual virginity were counter-positioned against [[Adam and Eve]], just as Jesus' obedience was counter positioned against that of Adam in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Romans#5:12|Romans 5:12-21]].&lt;ref name=ThemeM2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Rahner896 /&gt; 

The concept of Mary as the Second Eve was first introduced by [[Justin Martyr]] around 155 AD.&lt;ref&gt;''What Every Catholic Should Know about Mary'' by Terrence J. McNally 2009 ISBN 1-4415-1051-6 page 185&lt;/ref&gt; In this perspective, which was discussed in detail by [[Irenaeus]], supported by [[Jerome]], and then grew further, the vow of obedience and virginity of  Mary positioned her as the  &quot;Second Eve&quot; as part of the plan of salvation, just as Jesus was positioned as the [[Second Adam]].&lt;ref name=ThemeM2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Rahner896 /&gt; 

The theme developed by the Church Fathers ran parallel to the theme developed by Apostle Paul in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Romans#5:18|Romans 5:18-21]] when he compared Adam's sin with the obedience of Jesus to the will of the Father, all the way to [[Calvary]]: &quot;For just as by the one man’s disobedience the many were made sinners, so by the one man’s obedience the many will be made righteous.&quot;&lt;ref name=Daille &gt;''An exposition of the epistle of Saint Paul to the Philippians'' by Jean Daille 1995 ISBN 0-8028-2511-7 pages 194-195&lt;/ref&gt; In the same manner, Mary's obedience to the statements of the angel, and her adherence to her vow of perpetual virginity was seen as a remedy for the damage caused by Eve.&lt;ref name=Bl64 &gt;''Blessed one: Protestant perspectives on Mary Beverly Roberts Gaventa, Cynthia L. Rigby 2002 ISBN 0-664-22438-5 page 64&lt;/ref&gt;

The Second Eve teaching continued to grew among Catholics, and in discussing perpetual virginity, the 1566 [[Catechism of the Council of Trent]] explicitly taught that while Eve by believing the serpent brought malediction on the human race, Mary by believing the angel brought benediction to mankind.&lt;ref&gt;''The Catechism of the Council of Trent'' Translated Into English by Theodore Alois Buckley, ISBN 1-112-53771-6 pages 45-46 (Article III, Chapter VI, Question IX) [http://books.google.com/books?id=940_AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA45&amp;dq=perpetual+virginity+trent+malediction&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=PpFgTov9MdT54QSAlOFl&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ripley264 &gt;''This Is the Faith'' by Francis J. Ripley 1973 ISBN 0-85244-678-0 page 264&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of the Second Eve has continued to remain part of Catholic teachings, e.g. Pope [[Pius XII]] referred to it in the encyclical [[Mystici Corporis Christi]] and Pope [[John Paul II]] referred to it in a General Audience at the Vatican in 1980.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xii/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-xii_enc_29061943_mystici-corporis-christi_en.html Varican website: ''Mystici Corporis Christi'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/audiences/catechesis_genesis/documents/hf_jp-ii_aud_19800312_en.html Vatican website: ''Pope John Paul II General Audience March 12, 1980]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Protestant Reformation==
The start of the [[Protestant Reformation]] at the beginning of the 16th century did not immediately bring about a rejection of the doctrine of perpetual virginity and several leaders of the Reformation provided varying degrees of support for it, at times without directly endorsing it.&lt;ref name=Ted150 /&gt;&lt;ref name=McKim237 /&gt; 

The early Protestant reformers felt that Scripture required the acceptance of the [[virgin birth of Jesus]], but only permitted the acceptance of perpetual virginity.&lt;ref&gt;''Reformation of church and dogma (1300-1700)'' by Jaroslav Jan Pelikan, 1985, ISBN 0-226-65377-3, p339&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, many Protestant churches stopped teaching the doctrine and other Protestant churches denied it.&lt;ref name=Nally170 &gt;''What Every Catholic Should Know about Mary'' by Terrence J. McNally 2009 ISBN 1-4415-1051-6 page 170&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ted47 &gt;''Christian confessions: a historical introduction'' by Ted Campbell, 1996 ISBN 0-664-25650-3 page 47&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Support by early reformers===
{{Mariology}}
[[Martin Luther]] believed that Mary did not have other children and did not have any marital relations with Joseph. The Latin text of the 1537 [[Smalcald Articles]], written by [[Martin Luther]], used the term &quot;Ever Virgin&quot; to refer to Mary.&lt;ref name=Ted150 &gt;''Christian confessions: a historical introduction'' by Ted Campbell 1996 ISBN 0-664-25650-3 page 150&lt;/ref&gt; The perpetual virginity of Mary was Luther's lifelong belief, even after he rejected other Marian doctrines.&lt;ref name=Ted150 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Luther's Works'', 22:214-215&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Sermon on the Presentation of Christ in the Temple&quot;, ''Luthers Werke'' 52:688- 99,quoted in Jaroslav Pelikan, ''Mary through the Ages'', 158, and [http://www.ntrmin.org/Luthers%20Theology%20of%20Mary.htm#V Martin Luther's Theology of Mary]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Huldrych Zwingli]] directly supported perpetual virginity and wrote: &quot;I firmly believe that  [Mary], ... forever remained a pure, intact Virgin.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Zwingli|first=Ulrich|coauthors=Egli, Emil; Finsler, Georg; Zwingli-Verein, Georg; Zürich|title=Huldreich Zwinglis sämtliche Werke|publisher=C. A. Schwetschke und  Sohn|year=1905|volume=1|page=385|chapter=Eini Predigt von der ewig reinen Magd Maria.|url=http://books.google.com/books?vid=061hIvsQOvuF3d5-UhkJID&amp;id=yYYhD2-6nzQC&amp;pg=RA1-PA385&amp;lpg=RA1-PA385&amp;dq=%22eine+predigt+von+der+ewig+reinen%22|accessdate=2008-07-01|language=[[German language|German]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Like Zwingli, the English reformers also supported the concept of perpetual virginity, but often varied on their reasons for the support.&lt;ref name=McKim237 /&gt; Luther and Zwingli's support of perpetual virginity was endorsed by [[Heinrich Bullinger]] and was included in the 1566 [[Second Helvetic Confession]].&lt;ref name=Blessed119 &gt;''Blessed one: Protestant perspectives on Mary'' by Beverly Roberts Gaventa, Cynthia L. Rigby 2002 ISBN 0-664-22438-5 page 119&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Calvin]] was less emphatic in his open support of the idea, and neither flatly accepted or rejected it.&lt;ref name=McKim237 &gt;''Encyclopedia of the Reformed faith'' by Donald K. McKim, David F. Wright 1992 ISBN 0-664-21882-2 page 237&lt;/ref&gt;  He cautioned against the idea of &quot;impious speculation&quot; on the topic of perpetual virginity.&lt;ref name=Blessed119 /&gt; However, Calvin rejected arguments against Mary's perpetual virginity based on the mention in Scripture of [[Desposyni|brothers of Jesus]] that were interpreted to imply that Mary had other children.&lt;ref&gt;Harmony of Matthew, Mark &amp; Luke, sec. 39 (Geneva, 1562), / From Calvin's Commentaries, tr. William Pringle, Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 1949: “Helvidius displayed excessive ignorance in concluding that Mary must have had many sons, because Christ's 'brothers' are sometimes mentioned” (vol. 2, p. 215); “[On Matt 1:25:] The inference he [Helvidius] drew from it was, that Mary remained a virgin no longer than till her first birth, and that afterwards she had other children by her husband . . . No just and well-grounded inference can be drawn from these words . . . as to what took place after the birth of Christ. He is called 'first-born'; but it is for the sole purpose of informing us that he was born of a virgin . . . What took place afterwards the historian does not inform us . . . No man will obstinately keep up the argument, except from an extreme fondness for disputation.“ (vol. I, p. 107)&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Anglican]] reformers of the 16th and 17th century supported perpetual virginity &quot;on the basis of ancient Christian authority&quot;.&lt;ref name=Ted150 /&gt; In the 18th century, [[John Wesley]], one of the founders of [[Methodism]], also supported the doctrine and wrote that: &quot;... born of the blessed Virgin Mary, who, as well after as before she brought Him forth, continued a pure and unspotted virgin.&quot;&lt;ref name=Ted150 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The works of the Rev. John Wesley, Volume 15'' by John Wesley, Joseph Benson, Published by Thomas Cordeux, London, 1812, &quot;A Letter to a Roman Catholic&quot; page 110 [http://books.google.com/books?vid=OCLC09022224&amp;id=CZEPAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA110&amp;lpg=PA110&amp;dq=wesley+%22letter+to+a+roman+catholic%22]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://wesley.nnu.edu/john_wesley/letters/1749b.htm ''Letter to a Roman Catholic'', July 18, 1749]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later Protestant teachings===
Many current Protestant churches teach the [[virgin birth of Jesus]], without teaching that Mary remained a virgin for the rest of her life.&lt;ref name=Nally170 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Ted47 /&gt;

[[Diarmaid MacCulloch]], a historian of the Reformation, wrote that the reason why the early reformers upheld Mary’s perpetual virginity was that she was &quot;the guarantee of the Incarnation of Christ&quot;, a teaching that was being denied by the same radicals that were denying Mary’s perpetual virginity.&lt;ref&gt;D. MacCulloch, ''The Reformation: a History'' (Penguin Books, 2003) pp. 613-614; cf. Robert Schihl, ''[http://www.ewtn.com/faith/teachings/maryc2.htm The Perpetual Virginity of Mary]'' for an extended list and quotations.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the absence of clear Biblical statements expressing the doctrine, in combination with the principle of ''[[sola scriptura]]'', kept references to the doctrine out of the Reformation creeds and, together with the tendency to associate veneration of Mary with idolatry&lt;ref&gt;D. MacCulloch, ''The Reformation: a History'' (Penguin Books, 2003) pp. 558-63&lt;/ref&gt; and the rejection of [[clerical celibacy]],&lt;ref&gt;see John Calvin's [http://www.vor.org/rbdisk/calvin/ci_html/4_12.htm#4.12.27 ''Institutes of the Christian Religion IV,12,27-28'']&lt;/ref&gt; led to the eventual denial of this doctrine among Protestants, who, thus uncommitted to the doctrine of perpetual virginity, take the &quot;brothers&quot; (ἀδελφοί) οf Jesus mentioned in the New Testament most naturally (but not certainly) to be children of Mary and thus Jesus' half brothers, rather than his cousins or stepbrothers from a postulated previous marriage of Joseph.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., {{cite book |author=David Brown |title=Commentary, Critical and Explanatory, on the Whole Bible |chapter=Commentary on Matthew 13:56 |chapterurl=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/jamieson/jfb.xi.i.xv.html#xi.i.xv-p102.3 |accessdate=2009-01-07 |quote=An exceedingly difficult question here arises—What were these 'brethren' and 'sisters' to Jesus? Were they, ''First'', His full brothers and sisters? or, ''Secondly'', Were they His step-brothers and step-sisters, children of Joseph by a former marriage? or, ''Thirdly'', Were they cousins, according to a common way of speaking among the Jews respecting persons of collateral descent? On this subject an immense deal has been written, nor are opinions yet by any means agreed. For the second opinion there is no ground but a vague tradition, arising probably from the wish for some such explanation. The first opinion undoubtedly suits the text best in all the places where the parties are certainly referred to (Mt 12:46; and its parallels, Mr 3:31; Lu 8:19; our present passage, and its parallels, Mr 6:3; Joh 2:12; 7:3, 5, 10; Ac 1:14). But, in addition to other objections, many of the best interpreters, thinking it in the last degree improbable that our Lord, when hanging on the cross, would have committed His mother to John if He had had full brothers of His own then alive, prefer the third opinion; although, on the other hand, it is not to be doubted that our Lord might have good reasons for entrusting the guardianship of His doubly widowed mother to the beloved disciple in preference even to full brothers of His own. Thus dubiously we prefer to leave this vexed question, encompassed as it is with difficulties.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, some conservative Lutheran scholars such as Franz Pieper (1852–1931) refused to follow the tendency among Protestants to insist that Mary and Joseph had marital relations and children after the birth of Jesus. It is implicit in his ''Christian Dogmatics'' that belief in Mary's perpetual virginity is the older and traditional view among Lutherans.&lt;ref&gt;Francis Pieper, ''Christian Dogmatics'', 4 vols., (St. Louis: CPH, 1950-53), 2:308-09.&lt;/ref&gt; He stated, that  &quot;we should simply hold that (Mary) remained a virgin after the birth of Christ because Scripture does not state or indicate that she later lost her virginity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Scripture does not quibble or speak about the virginity of Mary after the birth of Christ, a matter about which the hypocrites are greatly concerned, as if it were something of the utmost importance on which our whole salvation depended.  Actually, we should be satisfied simply to hold that she remained a virgin after the birth of Christ because Scripture does not state or indicate that she later lost her virginity... But the Scripture stops with this, that she was a virgin before and at the birth of Christ; for up to this point God had need of her virginity in order to give us the promised blessed seed without sin&quot; (That Jesus Christ Was Born a Jew (1523), in ''Luther’s Works,'' American Edition, Walther I. Brandt, ed., Philadelphia, Augsburg Fortress; St. Louis, [[Concordia Publishing House]], 1962, ISBN 0-8006-0345-1 pp. 205-206; cf. James Swam ([http://www.ntrmin.org/Luthers%20Theology%20of%20Mary.htm#V Martin Luther's Theology of Mary]).&lt;/ref&gt; He taught that &quot;Christ, our Saviour, was the real and natural fruit of Mary's virginal womb . . . This was without the cooperation of a man, and she remained a virgin after that&quot;; and that &quot; Christ . . . was the only Son of Mary, and the Virgin Mary bore no children besides Him . . . I am inclined to agree with those who declare that 'brothers' really mean 'cousins' here, for Holy Writ and the Jews always call cousins brothers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Luther's Works, eds. Jaroslav Pelikan (vols. 1-30) &amp; Helmut T. Lehmann (vols. 31-55), St. Louis: Concordia Pub. House (vols. 1-30); Philadelphia: Fortress Press (vols. 31-55), 1955, v.22:23 / Sermons on John, chaps. 1-4 (1539), quoted in [http://www.davidmacd.com/catholic/martin_luther_on_mary.htm Martin Luther on Mary's Perpetual Virginity]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Scripture ==
[[File:Francesco Albani.jpg|thumb|left|180 px|''[[Annunciation|The Annunciation]]'', by [[Francesco Albani]]. &quot;How can this be, for I know not man?&quot;, [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Luke#1:34|Luke 1:34]]]]
Some passages in the [[New Testament]] have been used to voice objections to the doctrine of perpetual virginity, while other passages have been used to support it.

One objection  concerns the mention of brothers and sisters of Jesus,&lt;ref&gt;In its article on &quot;brethren of the Lord&quot;, the Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3) cites {{bibleverse||Mark|6:3|}}, {{bibleverse||Matthew|13:55|}}, {{bibleverse||John|7:3|}}, {{bibleverse||Acts|1:14|}}, {{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|9:5|}} as New Testament verses that mention them.&lt;/ref&gt; who include [[James the Just|James]], [[Joses]] (the form in {{bibleverse||Mark|6:3}}, but &quot;Joseph&quot; in {{bibleverse||Matthew|13:55}}), [[Simon (brother of Jesus)|Simon]], and [[Jude, brother of Jesus|Jude]]. They have been interpreted as children of Joseph and Mary, a view put forward by [[Tertullian]] and perhaps by [[Hegesippus (chronicler)|Hegesippus]], but that, when proposed by [[Helvidius]], met with opposition from [[Jerome]], who was apparently voicing the general Christian opinion at the time.&lt;ref name=ODCC&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3), article &quot;brethren of the Lord&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Jerome held that the &quot;brethren&quot; in question were children of Mary, the mother of James and Joses, named in {{bibleverse||Mark|15:40}} and {{bibleverse-nb||Mark|15:47}}, a sister of Jesus' mother  ({{bibleverse||John|19:25}}),&lt;ref name=ODCC/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church, article &quot;Marys in the NT&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; making them cousins of Jesus. 

Another view, expressed by [[Eusebius of Caesarea|Eusebius]] and [[Epiphanius of Salamis|Epiphanius]], is that they were children of Joseph by an earlier marriage.&lt;ref name=ODCC/&gt; A modern view is that they were children of Cleopas, a brother of Joseph according to Hegesippus, and of &quot;[[Mary of Clopas|Mary]], the mother of James and Joses&quot; seen as sister-in-law, not blood sister of Mary, the mother of Jesus.&lt;ref name=ODCC/&gt; The 1978 book ''Mary in the New Testament: A Collaborative Assessment by Protestant and Roman Catholic Scholars''&lt;ref&gt;[[Raymond E. Brown]], Karl P. Donfried, [[Joseph Fitzmyer]] and John Reumann ed., Philadelphia: Fortress Press, and Mahwah, NJ: Paulist Press, 1978&lt;/ref&gt; concluded that &quot;it cannot be said that the New Testament identifies them (the &quot;brothers and sisters&quot; of Jesus) without doubt as blood brothers and sisters and hence as children of Mary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://campus.udayton.edu/mary/Rossier.html François Rossier: The &quot;Brothers and Sisters&quot; of Jesus: Anything New?]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{bibleverse||Matthew|1:25}} states that Joseph had no marital relations with Mary &quot;until&quot; (ἕως οὗ ) she had borne Jesus. Writers such as R.V. Tasker&lt;ref&gt;Tasker, R.V., ''The Gospel according to Saint Matthew'' (InterVarsity Press 1961), p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; and D. Hill&lt;ref&gt;Hill D., The Gospel of Matthew, p80 (1972) Marshall, Morgan and Scott:London&lt;/ref&gt; argue that this implies that Mary and Joseph had customary marital relations after the birth of Jesus. Others, such as K. Beyer, point out that Greek ἕως οὗ after a negative &quot;often has no implication at all about what happened after the limit of the 'until' was reached&quot;,&lt;ref name=Brown132&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?ei=2WBjTsXVCMLG8QPs0rmQCg&amp;ct=result&amp;id=Dd1XAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=brown+birth+messiah&amp;q=implication#search_anchor Raymond E. Brown, ''The Birth of the Messiah'' (Doubleday 1999 ISBN 978-0-385-49447-2), p. 132]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Raymond E. Brown]] observes that &quot;the immediate context favors a lack of future implication here, for Matthew is concerned only with stressing Mary's virginity before the child's birth&quot;.&lt;ref name=Brown132/&gt;

[[File:Gentile, polittico di valle romita, crocefissione, brera, milano.jpg|thumb|157 px|''Woman behold your son!''. A [[Stabat Mater (art)|Stabat Mater]] depiction by [[Gentile da Fabriano]], c. 1400]]
On the other hand, Mary's response to the angel, when told that she will conceive, &quot;How will this be, since I am a virgin?&quot;, has been interpreted, at least since the time of [[Gregory of Nyssa]], as indicating that Mary had taken a lifelong vow of virginity, even in marriage:
:For if Joseph had taken her to be his wife, for the purpose of having children, why would she have wondered at the announcement of maternity, since she herself would have accepted becoming a mother according to the law of nature?&lt;ref&gt;Gregory of Nyssa, ''On the Holy Generation of Christ'', 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

This interpretation, although upheld by many, is rejected by writers such as Howard Marshall.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It is impossible to see how the text can yield this meaning&quot; (Howard Marshall, I.,  The Gospel of Luke (Paternoster Press 1978), p. 68).&lt;/ref&gt; and is considered implausible by Raymond E. Brown.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, ''The Birth of the Messiah'', p. 304&lt;/ref&gt;

A passage used to support the doctrine of perpetual virginity is of the [[sayings of Jesus on the cross]], i.e. the pair of commands first to his mother &quot;Woman, behold your son!&quot; and then to his disciple &quot;Behold, thy mother!&quot; in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/John#19:26|John 19:26-27]].&lt;ref name=Burke308 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Miravalle62 /&gt;&lt;ref name=KBaker334 &gt;''Fundamentals of Catholicism'' by Kenneth Baker 1983 ISBN 0-89870-019-1 pages 334-335&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Gospel of John]] then states that &quot;from that hour the disciple took her unto his own home&quot;. Since the time of the [[Church Fathers]] this statement has been used to reason that after the death of Jesus there was no one else in the immediate family to look after Mary, and she had to be entrusted to the disciple given that she had no other children.&lt;ref name=Burke308 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Miravalle62 /&gt;&lt;ref name=KBaker334 /&gt; This passage was one of the arguments [[Pope John Paul II]] presented in support of perpetual virginity.&lt;ref name=Miravalle62 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pope John Paul II's General Audience of 28 August 1996, printed in ''[[L'Osservatore Romano]]'', Weekly Edition in English, 4 September 1996 [http://www.ewtn.com/library/papaldoc/jp960828.htm The article at EWTN]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/audiences/1996/documents/hf_jp-ii_aud_19960828_it.html Vatican website: ''Pope John Paul II's General Audience of 28 August 1996'' (in Italian)]&lt;/ref&gt; John Paul II also reasoned that the command &quot;Behold your son!&quot; was not simply the entrustment of Mary to the disciple, but also the entrustment of the disciple to Mary in order to fill the maternal gap left by the death of her only son on the cross.&lt;ref&gt;''[[L'Osservatore Romano]]'', Weekly Edition in English, 30 April 1997, page 11 [http://www.ewtn.com/library/papaldoc/jp2bvm49.htm Article at EWTN]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/audiences/1997/documents/hf_jp-ii_aud_23041997_en.html Vatican website: ''Pope John Paul II's General Audience of 28 April 1997''] reprinted in ''[[L'Osservatore Romano]]'', Weekly Edition in English, 30 April 1997, page 11&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islamic perspective==
{{See also|Islamic views of Mary}}
In [[Sura]] 19,&lt;ref&gt;[[s:The Holy Qur'an/Maryam|The Holy Qur'an: Maryam (Mary), Sura 19 (Translation by A. Yusuf Ali)]]&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Qur'an]] declares that Jesus was the result of a virgin conception (verses 20-22), and some extend this to mean perpetual virginity of Mary.&lt;ref name=Emir &gt;''The Truth about Islam &amp; Jesus'' by John Ankerberg, Emir Caner 2009 ISBN 0-7369-2502-3 page 65 [http://books.google.com/books?id=-XgH1R2AhbgC&amp;pg=PA65&amp;dq=%22Perpetual+virginity%22+of+Mary+islam&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0oVcTonHAs7DtAaN56G6Dw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Perpetual%20virginity%22%20of%20Mary%20islam&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''What Every Catholic Should Know about Mary'' by Terrence J. McNally 2009 ISBN 1-4415-1051-6 page 161 [http://books.google.com/books?id=IlJRXgcBVvoC&amp;pg=PA161&amp;dq=Perpetual+virginity+of+Mary+islam&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=n4VcTsLwB8vfsga65enPDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Perpetual%20virginity%20of%20Mary%20islam&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt; There is no clear doctrinal belief one way or another as to whether she retained her virginity after Jesus' birth.&lt;ref&gt;''Women in the Qur'ān, traditions, and interpretation'' by Barbara Freyer Stowasser. Oxford University Press: 1994, pp. 78-70, 163.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Virgin Mary in Islamic tradition and commentary&quot; by J. I. Smith et. al., published in the ''Muslim World'' (Hartford, Conn.) v. 79 (July/October 1989) p. 161-87&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Islam]] Jesus and Mary were the only two children not be touched by Satan at the moment of their birth, for God placed a veil between them and Satan.&lt;ref&gt;Rodwell, J. M. '''The Koran'''. 2009 ISBN 0-559-13127-5 page 505&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Qur'an]] says that Jesus was the result of a virgin birth. The account of the annunciation and birth of Jesus is provided in [[Sura]] 3 and 19 of The Qur'an, where an angel is sent to announce that Mary should expect to bear a son, despite being a virgin.&lt;ref name=Sarker &gt;Sarker, Abraham.''Understand My Muslim People''. 2004 ISBN 1-59498-002-0 page 260&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Wikipedia-Books|Mary and Mariology}}
*[[Anglican Marian theology]]
* [[Immaculate Conception]]
*[[Lutheran Marian theology]]
*[[Roman Catholic Mariology]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Virgin Mary}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Perpetual Virginity Of Mary}}
[[Category:Marian dogmas]]
[[Category:Anglican theology and doctrine]]
[[Category:Catholic theology and doctrine]]
[[Category:Lutheran theology|Mariology]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox theology]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[fr:Virginité perpétuelle de Marie]]
[[id:Keperawanan Abadi Maria]]
[[it:Verginità perpetua di Maria]]
[[ko:평생 동정인 마리아]]
[[nl:Broers en zussen van Jezus]]</text>
      <sha1>10mx33841ndd3qhlysdtvqihr8n6396</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
