<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Persecution of Christians</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25074</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522250257</id>
      <parentid>522249735</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T23:07:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ian.thomson</username>
        <id>2489738</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid POV revision by [[Special:Contributions/68.32.216.42|68.32.216.42]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="159982">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{About|acts committed against Christians because of their faith|negative attitudes towards Christians|Anti-Christian sentiment}}
[[Image:Dirce.jpg|thumb|300px|''A Christian Dirce'', by [[Henryk Siemiradzki]]. A Christian woman is martyred under [[Nero]] in this re-enactment of the myth of [[Dirce]] (painting by [[Henryk Siemiradzki]], 1897, [[National Museum, Warsaw]]).]]
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:SpanishLeftistsShootChrist.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Anti-clerical]]s shooting at statue of Christ, [[Cerro de los Ángeles]] (Hill of the Angeles), [[Getafe]] (south of Madrid). King [[Alfonso&amp;nbsp;XII]] had consecrated the nation to the [[Sacred Heart of Jesus]] at the spot on 30&amp;nbsp;May 1919&lt;ref&gt;Burns, Paul and Alban Butler, [http://books.google.com/books?id=LM3tKD5nAJEC&amp;dq Lives of the Saints: Supplement of New Saints and Blesseds] 2005 Liturgical Press&lt;/ref&gt;]] --&gt;

'''Persecution of Christians''' can be traced both [[History of Christianity|historically]] and in the [[Christianity in the 21st century|current century]]. [[Early Christians]] were persecuted for their [[Faith in Christianity|faith]], at the hands of both [[Persecution of Christians by the Jews|Jews]] from [[Split of early Christianity and Judaism|whose religion Christianity arose]], and the [[Persecution of Christians in the Roman Empire|Roman Empire]] which controlled much of the [[Early centers of Christianity|land early Christianity was distributed across]]. This continued from the [[Christianity in the 1st century|1st century]] until the early [[Christianity in the 4th century|4th]], when the religion was legalized by the [[Edict of Milan]], eventually becoming the [[State church of the Roman Empire]]. Michael Gaddis wrote:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The Christian experience of violence during the pagan persecutions shaped the ideologies and practices that drove further religious conflicts over the course of the fourth and fifth centuries... The formative experience of martyrdom and persecution determined the ways in which later Christians would both use and experience violence under the Christian empire. Discourses of martyrdom and persecution formed the symbolic language through which Christians represented, justified, or denounced the use of violence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/?id=JGEibDA8el4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=There+is+no+crime+for+those+who+have+Christ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title=There is no crime for those who have Christ: Religious Violence in the Christian Roman Empire |first=Michael |last=Gaddis |year=2005 |publisher=University of California Press |isbn=978-0-520-24104-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Christian missionaries]] as well as the neophytes that they converted to Christianity have been the target of persecution, many times to the point of being [[Martyrdom|martyred for their faith]].
There is also a history of individual [[Christian denominations]] suffering persecution at the hands of other Christians under the charge of [[Heresy in Christianity|heresy]], particularly during the 16th century [[Protestant Reformation]].

In the 20th century, Christians have been persecuted by [[Islam|Muslim]] groups, and by [[state atheism|atheistic states]] such as the [[USSR]] and [[North Korea]]. Currently (as of 2012), as estimated by the Christian missionary organisation [[Open Doors]] UK, an estimated 100 million Christians face persecution, particularly in [[List of Muslim-majority countries|Muslim dominated countries]] like, [[Iran]] and [[Saudi Arabia]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Open Doors]]: [http://www.opendoorsuk.org/resources/country_profiles.php The worst 50 countries for persecution of Christians]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Open Doors: [http://www.opendoors-de.org/downloads/wvi/weltverfolgungsindex2012.pdf Weltverfolgungsindex 2012], p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; Christians in Pakistan are reportedly being subjected to a [[genocide]] by Pakistani [[Taliban]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://ibnlive.in.com/news/guest-article-after-the-malala-yousafzai-shooting-can-shock-therapy-free-pakistan/300253-56.html After the Malala Yousafzai shooting, can shock therapy free Pakistan? ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibtimes.com/problem-pakistan-814969 The Problem Of Pakistan]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/pakistan-should-be-on-the-genocide-watch-list-us-think-tank/1/222213.html Pakistan should be on the genocide watch list: US think tank] &lt;/ref&gt; They also face persecution in [[state atheism|atheistic states]] like North Korea in which there is no religious freedom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opendoorsuk.org/resources/persecution/#concern 'Open Doors' World Watch List], ''[[Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung]]'' [http://www.faz.net/IN/INtemplates/faznet/default.asp?tpl=common/zwischenseite.asp&amp;dx2={E9AD956B-EF89-5A99-E249-8040B2BE952C}&amp;rub={E3C3C617-6BD4-497B-8E43-BEC78289CFD1} 23 January 2010]. Jonathan Fox and Shmuel Sandler, ''Separation of Religion and State in the Twenty-First Century: Comparing the Middle East and Western Democracies'', 2005, The City University of New York. (dead link)&lt;/ref&gt; A recent study, cited by the [[Vatican]], reported that 75 out of every 100 people killed due to religious hatred were Christian.&lt;ref&gt;Aid to the Church in Need, Religious Freedom in the World – Report 2010; Conference Persecution of Christians&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/secretariat_state/2011/documents/rc_seg-st_20110302_religious-freedom_en.html |title=Statement by the Holy See at the 16th Ordinary Session of the Human Rights Council on Religious Freedom |publisher=Vatican.va |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Status of religious freedom}}

==Antiquity==
{{see also|Persecution of Christians in the Roman Empire}}

===Persecution of Christians in the New Testament===
{{main|Persecution of Christians in the New Testament}}
[[Early Christianity]] began as a sect among early [[Jews]] and according to the New Testament account, [[Pharisees]], including [[Paul of Tarsus]] prior to his conversion to Christianity, persecuted early Christians. The early Christians preached a Messiah which did not conform to the expectations of the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;Wand, John Williams Charles [http://books.google.com/books?id=ci2hvwXqlKMC&amp;vq=contents&amp;dq A History of the Early Church to AD 500], p. 12, Routledge 1990&lt;/ref&gt; However, feeling that he was presaged in [[Isaiah]]'s [[Suffering Servant]] and in all of Jewish scripture, Christians had been hopeful that their countrymen would accept their vision of a [[New Jerusalem|New Israel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; Despite many individual conversions, a [[Rejection of Jesus|fierce opposition]] was found in their countrymen.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;Wand, John Williams Charles [http://books.google.com/books?id=ci2hvwXqlKMC&amp;vq=contents&amp;dq A History of the Early Church to AD 500], p. 13, Routledge 1990&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Caravaggio-Crucifixion of Peter.jpg|thumb|200px|''The Crucifixion of St. Peter'' by [[Caravaggio]]]] Dissention began almost immediately with the teachings of [[Saint Stephen|Stephen]] at Jerusalem (unorthodox by contemporaneous Jewish standards), and never ceased entirely while the city remained.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; A year after the [[Crucifixion of Jesus]], Stephen was stoned for his alleged transgression of orthodoxy,&lt;ref name=&quot;Characteristics Of The Early Church&quot;&gt;Burke, John J., [http://books.google.com/books?id=o2W01eeEzaoC&amp;dq Characteristics Of The Early Church], p.101, Read Country Books 2008&lt;/ref&gt; with [[Paul of Tarsus|Saul]] (who later converted and was renamed ''Paul'') heartily agreeing.

In 41 AD, when [[Agrippa I]], who already possessed the territory of Antipas and Phillip, obtained the title of ''King of the Jews'', in a sense re-forming the [[Herodian kingdom|Kingdom of Herod]], he was reportedly eager to endear himself to his Jewish subjects and continued the persecution in which [[James the Lesser]] lost his life, Peter narrowly escaped and the rest of the apostles took flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;

After Agrippa's death, the Roman procuratorship began (before 41 they were [[Prefects]] in [[Iudaea Province]]) and those leaders maintained a neutral peace, until the procurator Festus died and the high priest Annas II took advantage of the power vacuum to attack the Church and executed [[James the Greater]], then leader of [[Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem|Jerusalem's Christians]].&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; The New Testament states that [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]] was himself imprisoned on several occasions by Roman authorities, stoned by Pharisees and left for dead on one occasion, and was eventually taken as a prisoner to Rome. [[St. Peter|Peter]] and other early Christians were also imprisoned, beaten and harassed. A Jewish revolt, spurred by the Roman killing of 3,000 Jews, led to the destruction of Jerusalem in 70 AD, the end of sacrificial Judaism (until the [[Third Temple]]), and the disempowering of the Jewish persecutors; the Christian community, meanwhile, having fled to safety in the already pacified region of [[Pella, Jordan|Pella]].&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; The early persecution by the Jews is estimated to have a death toll of about 2,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Characteristics Of The Early Church&quot;/&gt; The Jewish persecutions were trivial when compared with the brutal and widespread persecution by the Romans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Characteristics Of The Early Church&quot;/&gt;

Of the eleven remaining [[Twelve Apostles|apostles]] ([[Judas Iscariot]] having killed himself), only one—[[John the Apostle]], the son of Zebedee and the younger brother of the Apostle James—died of natural causes in exile. The other ten were reportedly martyred by various means including beheading, by sword and spear and, in the case of Peter, crucifixion upside down following the execution of his wife. The Romans were involved in some of these persecutions.

The [[New Testament]], especially the [[Gospel of John]], has traditionally been interpreted as relating Christian accounts of [[Rejection of Jesus#Jewish rejection|the Pharisee rejection of Jesus]] and accusations of [[Responsibility for the death of Jesus|the Pharisee responsibility for his crucifixion]]. The [[Acts of the Apostles]] depicts instances of early Christian persecution by the [[Sanhedrin]], the Jewish religious court of the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Acts|4:1–22}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Acts|5:17–42}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Acts|6:8–7:60}}, {{bibleverse-nb||Acts|22:30–23:22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Walter Laqueur argues that hostility between Christians and Jews grew over the generations. By the 4th century, [[John Chrysostom]] was arguing that the Pharisees alone, not the Romans, were responsible for the murder of Christ. However, according to Laqueur: &quot;Absolving [[Pilate]] from guilt may have been connected with the missionary activities of early Christianity in Rome and the desire not to antagonize those they want to convert.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Walter Laqueur]] (2006): ''The Changing Face of Antisemitism: From Ancient Times to the Present Day'', Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-530429-2. p.46-48&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

At least by the 4th century, the consensus amongst scholars is that persecution of Christians by Jews has been traditionally overstated; according to James Everett Seaver,&lt;ref&gt;[http://vlib.iue.it/carrie/texts/carrie_books/seaver/text.html The Persecution of the Jews in the Roman Empire (300–428)] by James Everett Seaver. University of Kansas Publications, 1952. Humanistic Studies, No. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Much of Christian hatred toward the Jews was based on the popular misconception... that the Jews had been the active persecutors of Christians for many centuries... The... examination of the sources for fourth century Jewish history will show that the universal, tenacious, and malicious Jewish hatred of Christianity referred to by the church fathers and countless others has no existence in historical fact. The generalizations of patristic writers in support of the accusation have been wrongly interpreted from the fourth century to the present day. That individual Jews hated and reviled the Christians there can be no doubt, but there is no evidence that the Jews as a class hated and persecuted the Christians as a class during the early years of the fourth century.}}

===Persecution of early Christians in the Roman Empire===
{{Main|Persecution of Christians in the Roman Empire}}

====Persecution under Nero, 64–68 AD====
{{Main|Great Fire of Rome}}

The first documented case of imperially supervised persecution of the Christians in the [[Roman Empire]] begins with [[Nero]] (37–68). In 64 AD, a [[Great Fire of Rome|great fire broke out in Rome]], destroying portions of the city and economically devastating the Roman population. Nero himself was suspected as the arsonist by [[Suetonius]],&lt;ref&gt;Nero Ch 38&lt;/ref&gt; claiming he played the lyre and sang the 'Sack of Ilium' during the fires. In his ''Annals'', [[Tacitus]] (who claimed Nero was in Antium at the time of the fire's outbreak), stated that &quot;''to get rid of the report, Nero fastened the guilt and inflicted the most exquisite tortures on a class hated for their abominations, called Christians'' [or Chrestians&lt;ref&gt;In the earliest extant manuscript, the second Medicean, the ''e'' in &quot;Chrestianos&quot;, Chrestians, has been changed into an ''i''; cf. Gerd Theißen, Annette Merz, ''Der historische Jesus: ein Lehrbuch'', 2001, p. 89. The reading ''Christianos'', Christians, is therefor doubtful. On the other hand, Suetonius (Claudius 25) uses the same &quot;e&quot; transliteration of the Greek Krystos, meaning the anointed one, and associates it with a troublemaker among the Jews&lt;/ref&gt;] ''by the populace''&quot; (Tacit. ''Annals'' XV, see [[Tacitus on Jesus]]). Suetonius, later to the period, does not mention any persecution after the fire, but in a previous paragraph unrelated to the fire, mentions punishments inflicted on Christians, defined as men following a new and malefic superstition. Suetonius however does not specify the reasons for the punishment, he just listed the fact together with other abuses put down by Nero.&lt;ref&gt;Nero 16&lt;/ref&gt;

====Persecution from the 2nd century to Constantine====
By the mid-2nd century, mobs could be found willing to throw stones at Christians, and they might be mobilized by rival sects. The [[Persecution in Lyon]] was preceded by mob violence, including assaults, robberies and stonings (Eusebius, ''Ecclesiastical History'' 5.1.7).

Further state persecutions were desultory until the 3rd century, though [[Tertullian]]'s ''[[Apologeticus]]'' of 197 was ostensibly written in defense of persecuted Christians and addressed to Roman governors.&lt;ref&gt;Tertullian's readership was more likely to have been Christians, whose faith was reinforced by Tertullian's defenses of faith against rationalizations.&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;edict of [[Septimius Severus]]&quot; familiar in Christian history is doubted by some secular historians to have existed outside Christian [[martyrology]].

The first documentable Empire-wide persecution took place under [[Maximinus Thrax]], though only the clergy were sought out. It was not until [[Decius]] during the mid-century that a persecution of Christian laity across the Empire took place. Christian sources aver that a decree was issued requiring public sacrifice, a formality equivalent to a testimonial of allegiance to the Emperor and the established order. Decius authorized [[roving commission]]s visiting the cities and villages to supervise the execution of the sacrifices and to deliver written certificates to all citizens who performed them. Christians were often given opportunities to avoid further punishment by publicly offering sacrifices or burning incense to Roman gods, and were accused by the Romans of impiety when they refused. Refusal was punished by arrest, imprisonment, torture, and executions. Christians fled to safe havens in the countryside and some purchased their certificates, called ''libelli.'' Several councils held at [[Carthage]] debated the extent to which the community should accept these lapsed Christians.

Some early Christians sought out and welcomed martyrdom. Roman authorities tried hard to avoid Christians because they &quot;goaded, chided, belittled and insulted the crowds until they demanded their death.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Ide|first1=Arthur Frederick|authorlink1=Arthur F. Ide|last2=Smith|first2=John Paul|authorlink2=John Paul Smith|title=Martyrdom of Women: A Study of Death Psychology in the Early Christian Church to 301 CE|year=1985|publisher=Tangelwuld|location=Garland|isbn=978-0-930383-49-7|page=21}} apud {{cite book|last1=deMause|first1=Lloyd|authorlink1=Lloyd deMause|title=The Emotional Life of Nations|year=2002|publisher=Karnac|location=New York|isbn=1-892746-98-0|chapter=Ch. 9. The Evolution of Psyche and Society. Part III.|chapterurl=http://primal-page.com/ps3.htm|accessdate=6 September 2011|quote=Both Christians and Jews &quot;engaged in a contest and reflection about the new-fangled practice of martyrdom,&quot;&lt;sup&gt;191&lt;/sup&gt; even unto suicide. Jesus, too, says John, really committed suicide, and Augustine spoke of &quot;the mania for self-destruction&quot; of early Christians.&lt;sup&gt;192&lt;/sup&gt; Roman authorities tried hard to avoid Christians because they &quot;goaded, chided, belittled and insulted the crowds until they demanded their death.&quot;&lt;sup&gt;193&lt;/sup&gt; One man shouted to the Roman officials: &quot;I want to die! I am a Christian,&quot; leading the officials to respond: &quot;If they wanted to kill themselves, there was plenty of cliffs they could jump off.&quot;&lt;sup&gt;194&lt;/sup&gt; But the Christians, following Tertullian’s dicta that &quot;martyrdom is required by God,&quot; forced their own martyrdom so they could die in an ecstatic trance: &quot;Although their tortures were gruesome, the martyrs did not suffer, enjoying their analgesic state.&quot;&lt;sup&gt;195&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;191. Daniel Boyarin, Dying for God: Martyrdom and the Making of Christianity and Judaism. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1999, p. 40.&lt;br&gt;192. Arthur J. Droge and James D. Tabor, A Noble Death: Suicide and Martyrdom Among Christians and Jews in Antiquity. San Francisco: HarperSanFrancisco, 1992, p. 5.&lt;br&gt;193. Arthur F. Ide, Martyrdom of Women: A Study of Death Psychology in the Early Christian Church to 301 CE. Garland: Tangelwuld, 1985, p. 21.&lt;br&gt;194. Ibid., p. 136.&lt;br&gt;195. Ibid., pp. 146, 138.}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Droge and Tabor, &quot;in 185 the proconsul of Asia, Arrius Antoninus, was approached by a group of Christians demanding to be executed. The proconsul obliged some of them and then sent the rest away, saying that if they wanted to kill themselves there was plenty of rope available or cliffs they could jump off.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Droge|first1=Arthur J.|authorlink1=Arthur J. Droge|last2=Tabor|first2=James D.|authorlink2=James D. Tabor|title=A Noble Death: Suicide and Martyrdom Among Christians and Jews in Antiquity|year=1992|month=November|publisher=HarperSanFrancisco|location=San Francisco|isbn=978-0-06-062095-0|page=136}} Misquoted as Groge and Tabor (1992:136) by C. Douzinas in {{cite book|last1=Closs Stephens|first1=Angharad|authorlink1=Angharad Closs Stephens|last2=Vaughan-Williams|first2=Nick|authorlink2=Nick Vaughan-Williams|coauthors=C. Douzinas|title=Terrorism and the Politics of Response|url=http://books.google.nl/books?id=C2cAF2OQ7RkC&amp;pg=PA198&amp;dq=groge+and+tabor+1992+cliffs+jump+off&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=groge%20and%20tabor%201992%20cliffs%20jump%20off&amp;f=false|year=2009|publisher=Routledge|location=Oxon and New York|isbn=978-0-415-45506-0|page=198}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such seeking after death is found in [[Tertullian]]'s ''Scorpiace'' or in the letters of [[Saint Ignatius of Antioch]] but was certainly not the only view of martyrdom in the Christian church. Both [[Polycarp]] and [[Cyprian]], bishops in Smyrna and Carthage respectively, attempted to avoid martyrdom.

====The Great Persecution====
{{Main|Diocletian Persecution}}
[[Image:Jean-Léon Gérôme - The Christian Martyrs' Last Prayer - Walters 37113.jpg|thumb|280px|right|''The Christian Martyrs' Last Prayer'', by [[Jean-Léon Gérôme]] (1883).]]

The persecutions culminated with [[Diocletian]] and [[Galerius]] at the end of the third and beginning of the 4th century. The [[Great Persecution]] is considered the largest. Beginning with a series of four edicts banning Christian practices and ordering the imprisonment of Christian clergy, the persecution intensified until all Christians in the empire were commanded to sacrifice to the gods or face immediate execution. Over 20,000 Christians are thought to have died during Diocletian's reign. However, as [[Diocletian]] zealously persecuted Christians in the Eastern part of the empire, his co-emperors in the West did not follow the edicts and so Christians in Gaul, Spain, and Britannia were virtually unmolested.

This persecution lasted, until [[Constantine I]] came to power in 313 and legalized Christianity. It was not until [[Theodosius I]] in the later 4th century that Christianity would become the official religion of the Empire. Between these two events [[Julian the Apostate|Julian II]] temporarily restored the traditional Roman religion and established broad religious tolerance renewing Pagan and Christian hostilities.

The conditions under which [[martyrdom]] was an acceptable fate or under which it was suicidally embraced occupied writers of the early Christian Church. Broadly speaking, martyrs were considered uniquely exemplary of the Christian faith, and few early saints were not also martyrs.

The ''New Catholic Encyclopedia'' states that &quot;Ancient, medieval and early modern hagiographers were inclined to exaggerate the number of martyrs. Since the title of martyr is the highest title to which a Christian can aspire, this tendency is natural&quot;. Estimates of Christians killed for religious reasons before the year 313 vary greatly, depending on the scholar quoted, from a high of almost 100,000 to a low of 10,000.

===Persecutions of early Christians outside the Roman Empire===
[[Image:William Holman Hunt - A Converted British Family.jpg|right|300px|thumb|''[[A Converted British Family Sheltering a Christian Missionary from the Persecution of the Druids]]'', a scene of persecution by druids in ancient Britain painted by [[William Holman Hunt]].]]

In 341, the [[Zoroastrian]] [[Shapur II]] ordered the massacre of all Christians in the [[Persia]]n [[Sassanid Empire]]. During the persecution, about 1,150 [[Assyrian Christian]]s were martyred under Shapur II in [[Assuristan]] (Sassanid ruled Assyria).&lt;ref&gt;http://ocafs.oca.org/Caption.asp?FSID=101122&lt;/ref&gt; In the 4th century, the [[Thervings|Terving]] King [[Athanaric]] began persecuting Christians, many of whom were killed.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Heather &amp; John Matthews, ''Goths in the Fourth Century'', pp. 96ff&lt;/ref&gt;

==Persecution of Christians during the Middle Ages==
===Persecution of Christians by Persians and Jews during Roman-Persian Wars===
According to Antiochus Strategos, a 7th century monk in Palestine, shortly after the Persian army entered Jerusalem in 614, unprecedented looting and sacrilege took place. Church after church was burned down alongside the innumerable Christian artifacts, which were stolen or damaged by the ensuing arson. Given that Khosrau II generally practiced religious tolerance and did deem Christians respectfully, it is not known why Shahrbaraz ordered such a massacre. One reason could simply have been Shahrbaraz's rage at the resistance that had been offered by Jerusalem's Christian populace.
Accounts from early Christian chroniclers suggest that 26,000 Jewish rebels entered the streets of the city. Some Jerusalem Christians were taken captive, gathered together and murdered in mass by Jews. The Greek historian Antiochus Strategos writes that captive Christians were gathered near Mamilla reservoir and the Jews offered to help them escape death if they &quot;become Jews and deny Christ&quot;. The Christian captives refused, and the Jews in anger had purchased the Christians from Persians and massacred them on spot. Antiochus writes:
Then the Jews... as of old they bought the Lord from the Jews with silver, so they purchased Christians out of the reservoir; for they gave the Persians silver, and they bought a Christian and slew him like a sheep.

According to Antiochus, the total Christian death toll was 66,509, of which 24,518 corpses were found at Mamilla, many more than were found anywhere else in the city. Other manuscripts suggest less where found at Mamilla 4518 or 4618 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=THE PERSIAN CONQUEST OF JERUSALEM (614 CE) – AN ARCHAEOLOGICAL ASSESSMENT|url=http://www.bibleinterp.com/articles/pers357904.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Other sources give a figure of 60,000 slain. The Jews destroyed the Christian churches and the monasteries, books were burnt and monks and priests killed. According to Israeli archeologists, there was no destruction of churches. A mass burial grave at Mamilla cave was discovered in 1989 by Israeli archeologist Ronny Reich.

The massacre appeared to have happened after Christians revolted a few months after the capture of Jerusalem. They were able to briefly retake the city for 19 days before the walls where breached. Killing the new ruler of Jerusalem the Exilarch Nehemiah ben Hushiel and his &quot;council of the righteous&quot; and dragging their bodies through the streets. Christians in this time period had allied themselves with the Eastern Roman Empire. Archaeological evidence does not currently support the idea that churches were burnt. Christian sources may well have reason to exaggerate the extent of the massacre as they would later in 628 massacre, forcible convert and expel the Jews. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Persian conquest of Jerusalem in 614CE compared with Islamic conquest of 638CE|url=http://www.eretzyisroel.org/~jkatz/The%20Persian%20conquest%20of%20Jerusalem%20in%20614CE%20compared%20with%20Islamic%20conquest%20of%20638CE.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Persecution of Christians in the early and medieval Caliphates===
In general, Christians subject to Islamic rule were allowed to practice their religion with some notable limitations, see [[Covenant of Umar I|Pact of Umar]].
As [[People of the Book]] they were awarded [[dhimmi]] status (along with [[Jews]] and [[Mandeans]]), which, although inferior to the status of Muslims, was more favourable than the plight of adherents of non-[[Abrahamic faith]]s such as [[Zoroastrianism|Zoroastrians]] and [[Paganism|Pagans]].

At times, anti-Christian pogroms occurred. Under [[sharia]], non-Muslims are obligated to pay [[jizya]] taxes, which contributed a significant proportion of income for the Islamic state and persuaded many Christians to convert to Islam (Stillman (1979), p.&amp;nbsp;160.). According to the [[Hanafi]] school of sharia, the testimony of a non-Muslim (such as a Christian) was not considered valid against the testimony of a Muslim. Other schools differed. Christian men were not allowed to marry a Muslim woman under sharia. Muslim men on the other hand were allowed to marry Christian women.
Christians under Islamic rule had the right to convert to Islam or any other religion, while a [[murtad]], or apostate of Islam, faced severe penalties or even [[hadd]], which could include the death penalty.

[[Tamerlane]] instigated large scale massacres of Christians in [[Mesopotamia]], [[Persia]], [[Asia Minor]] and [[Syria]] in the 14th century AD. Most of the victims were indigenous [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]], [[Arameans]] and [[Armenians]], members of the [[Assyrian Church of the East]] and [[Orthodox Churches]], which led to the decimation of the hitherto majority Assyrian population in northern Mesopotamia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Khanbaghi|first=Aptin|title=The fire, the star and the cross: minority religions in medieval and early modern Iran|year=2006|publisher=I.B.Tauris|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=7iAbUEaXnfEC&amp;pg=PA87}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Medieval Christian persecution of heresy===
In the medieval period the Roman Catholic Church moved to suppress the [[Cathar]] heresy, the [[Pope]] having sanctioned a [[Albigensian Crusade|crusade against the Albigensians]], during the course of which the massacre of [[Béziers]] took place, with between seven and twenty thousand deaths. Papal legate [[Arnaud Amalric]], when asked how Catholics could be distinguished from Cathars once the city fell, famously replied, &quot;Kill them all, God will know His own.&quot; Over the twenty-year period of this campaign an estimated 200,000 to 1,000,000 people were killed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,897752-2,00.html Massacre of the Pure], [[Time (magazine)|Time]], 28 April 1961&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat0.htm#Crusades |title=European Wars, Tyrants, Rebellions and Massacres (800–1700 CE) |publisher=Users.erols.com |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John Huss]], a [[Bohemia]]n preacher of reformation, was burned at the stake on 6 July 1415. [[Pope Martin V]] issued a bull on 17 March 1420 which proclaimed a [[crusade]] &quot;for the destruction of the [[Wycliffites]], [[Hussite]]s and all other [[heresy|heretic]]s in Bohemia&quot;.

The [[Crusades]] in the Middle East also spilled over into conquest of [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]] Christians by Roman Catholics and attempted suppression of the Orthodox Church. The [[Waldenses]] were as well persecuted by the Catholic Church, but survive up to this day.

==Early Modern period (1500 to 1815)==
===Reformation===
[[File:Contemporary illustration of the Auto-da-fe held at Validolid Spain 21-05-1559..jpg|thumb|right|260px|[[Auto-da-fé]] of Valladolid, Spain, in which fourteen Christians were burned at the stake for their [[Lutheran]] faith, on 21 May 1559&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=R9da-SlbN4UC&amp;pg=PA177&amp;lpg=PA177&amp;dq=valladolid+spain+burning+lutherans&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ebbeg0_cBH&amp;sig=lfkihjEjEdP-aE8E1ZXr06A6S4c&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=7jqAT-zeKYLW2gXZlrHpBg&amp;ved=0CCMQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=valladolid%20spain%20burning%20lutherans&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The Reformation led to a long period of warfare and communal violence between Catholic and [[Protestant]] factions, leading to massacres and forced suppression of the alternative views by the dominant faction in much of Europe.

====Anti-Catholic====
{{Main|Anti-Catholicism}}

Anti-Catholicism officially began in 1534 during the [[English Reformation]]; the [[Act of Supremacy]] made the King of England the 'only supreme head on earth of the Church in England.' Any act of allegiance to the latter was considered treason. It was under this act that [[Saint Thomas More|Thomas More]] was executed. [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]]'s scorn for [[Jesuit]] [[missionaries]] led to many executions at [[Tyburn]]. As punishment for the rebellion of 1641, almost all lands owned by [[Irish people|Irish Catholics]] were confiscated and [[Cromwellian Plantation|given to Protestant settlers]]. Under the [[Penal Laws (Ireland)|penal laws]] no Irish Catholic could sit in the [[Parliament of Ireland]], even though some 90% of Ireland's population was native Irish Catholic when the first of these bans was introduced in 1691.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.umn.edu/irishlaw/offices.html Laws in Ireland for the Suppression of Popery] at University of Minnesota Law School&lt;/ref&gt; Catholic / Protestant strife has been blamed for much of &quot;[[The Troubles]]&quot;, the ongoing struggle in [[Northern Ireland]].

This attitude was carried to the English colonies in America, which eventually became the United States. In these colonies, Catholicism was introduced with the settling of [[Maryland]] in 1634; this colony offered a rare example of [[religious toleration]] in a fairly intolerant age, particularly amongst other English colonies which frequently exhibited a quite militant [[Protestantism]]. (See the [[Maryland Toleration Act]], and note the pre-eminence of the Archdiocese of [[Baltimore]] in Catholic circles.) However, at the time of the [[American Revolution]], Catholics formed less than 1% of the population of the thirteen colonies.

====Anti-Eastern Orthodox====
In 1656, [[Macarios III Zaim]], who was the [[Patriarch of Antioch|Greek Patriarch of Antioch]], lamented over the atrocities committed by the [[Polish people|Polish]] [[Catholics]] against followers of [[Greek Orthodoxy]]. Macarios was quoted as stating that seventy or eighty thousand followers of Eastern Orthodoxy were killed under hands of the Catholics. Greek Patriarch Macarios desired Turkish sovereignty over Catholic subjugation, stating: &lt;blockquote&gt;God perpetuate the [[Ottoman Empire|empire of the Turks]] for ever and ever! For they take their impost, and enter no account of religion, be their subjects Christians or Nazarenes, Jews or Samaritians; whereas these accursed Poles were not content with taxes and tithes from the brethren of Christ...&lt;ref&gt;The preaching of Islam: a history of the propagation of the Muslim faith By Sir Thomas Walker Arnold, pg. 134–135&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Anti-Protestant====
{{Main|Anti-Protestantism}}
[[Image:Francois Dubois 001.jpg|thumb|200px|The Bartholomew's Day massacre]]

Anti-Protestantism originated in a reaction by the Catholic Church against the [[Protestant Reformation]] of the 16th century. Protestants were denounced as heretics and subject to persecution in those territories, such as Spain, Italy and the Netherlands, by the [[Inquisition]], in which the Catholics were the dominant power. This movement was orchestrated by Popes and Princes as the [[Counter Reformation]]. This resulted in religious wars and eruptions of sectarian hatred such as the [[St Bartholomew's Day Massacre]] of 1572.

====Persecution of the Anabaptists====
{{Main|Anabaptist}}

When the disputes between Lutherans and Roman Catholics gained a political dimension, both groups saw other groups of religious dissidents that were arising as a danger to their own security. The early &quot;Täufer&quot; (lit. &quot;Baptists&quot;) were mistrusted and rejected by both religio-political parties. Religious persecution is often perpetrated as a means of political control, and this becomes evident with the [[Treaty of Augsburg]] in 1555. This treaty provided the legal groundwork for persecution of the Anabaptists.

===China===
Beginning in the late 17th century, Christianity was banned for at least a century in China by [[Emperor Kangxi]] of the [[Qing Dynasty]] after the [[Pope]] forbade [[Roman Catholicism in China|Chinese Catholics]] from [[Veneration|venerating]] their relatives or [[Confucius]].&lt;ref name=Ye_Xiaowen&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.china.org.cn/english/features/45466.htm |title=Mr. Ye Xiaowen, China's Religions Retrospect and Prospect, Hong Kong, 19 February 2001 |publisher=China.org.cn |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Boxer Rebellion]], anti Christian Boxers, and Muslim [[Kansu Braves]] serving in the Chinese army attacked Christians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=CBOpWiyl4NsC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;dq=muslim+baron+von+ketteler#v=onepage&amp;q=muslim%20baron%20von%20ketteler&amp;f=false|title=A traveller's history of China|author=Stephen G. Haw|year=2003|publisher=Interlink Books|page=172|isbn=1-56656-486-7|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=tvZwAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=muslim+baron+von+ketteler&amp;dq=muslim+baron+von+ketteler|title=The modern history of China|author=Henry McAleavy|year=1967|publisher=Praeger|page=165|isbn=|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=rcdkmohiuuQC&amp;pg=PA80&amp;dq=kansu+braves&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=kansu%20braves|title=The Atlantic monthly, Volume 113 By Making of America Project|author=Sterling Making of America Project|year=1914|publisher=Atlantic Monthly Co.|location=|page=80|isbn=|pages=|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Northern Expedition, the Kuomintang incited anti-foreign, [[anti-Western sentiment]]. Portraits of [[Sun Yat-sen]] replaced the crucifix in several churches, KMT posters proclaimed- &quot;Jesus Christ is dead. Why not worship something alive such as Nationalism?&quot;. Foreign missionaries were attacked and anti foreign riots broke out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YkREps9oGR4C&amp;dq=chiang+kai-shek+democracy&amp;q=emocracy+absolutely+impossible#v=onepage&amp;q=portraits%20crucifixes%20anti&amp;f=false|title=Chiang Kai Shek: China's Generalissimo and the Nation He Lost|author=Jonathan Fenby|year=2005|publisher=Carroll &amp; Graf Publishers|location=|page=126|isbn=0-7867-1484-0|pages=|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Northern Expedition, in 1926 in Guangxi, Muslim General [[Bai Chongxi]] led his troops in destroying Buddhist temples and smashing idols, turning the temples into schools and Kuomintang party headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tCA9AAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=accused+chiang+feudal&amp;q=muslim#v=onepage&amp;q=pai%20smashing%20idols%20decapitating%20statues&amp;f=false|title=Region and nation: the Kwangsi clique in Chinese politics, 1925–1937|author=Diana Lary|year=1974|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=|page=98|isbn=0-521-20204-3|pages=|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was reported that almost all of Buddhist monasteries in Guangxi were destroyed by Bai in this manner. The monks were removed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=LxDUeWdMubkC&amp;pg=PA146&amp;dq=bai+chongxi+buddhist+temples#v=onepage&amp;q=bai%20chongxi%20buddhist%20temples&amp;f=false|title=Toward a modern Chinese Buddhism: Taixu's reforms|author=Don Alvin Pittman|year=2001|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|location=|page=146|isbn=0-8248-2231-5|pages=|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bai led a wave of anti foreignism in Guangxi, attacking American, European, and other foreigners and missionaries, and generally making the province unsafe for foreigners. Westerners fled from the province, and some Chinese Christians were also attacked as imperialist agents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=tCA9AAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=accused+chiang+feudal&amp;q=muslim#v=snippet&amp;q=missionary%20crowd&amp;f=false|title=Region and nation: the Kwangsi clique in Chinese politics, 1925–1937|author=Diana Lary|year=1974|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=|page=99|isbn=0-521-20204-3|pages=|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
[[Tokugawa Ieyasu]] assumed control over Japan in 1600. Like [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]], he disliked Christian activities in Japan. The [[Tokugawa shogunate]] finally decided to ban Catholicism, in 1614 and in the mid-17th century it demanded the expulsion of all European missionaries and the execution of all converts. This marked the end of open Christianity in Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mullins&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| last = Mullins
 | first = Mark R.
 | year = 1990
 | title = Japanese Pentecostalism and the World of the Dead: a Study of Cultural Adaptation in Iesu no Mitama Kyokai
 | journal = Japanese Journal of Religious Studies
 | volume = 17
 | issue = 4
 | pages = 353–374 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Shimabara Rebellion]], led by a young [[Kirishitan|Japanese Christian]] boy named [[Amakusa Shiro|Amakusa Shiro Tokisada]], took place in 1637. After the [[Hara Castle]] fell, the shogunate's forces beheaded an estimated 37,000 rebels and sympathizers. Amakusa Shirō's severed head was taken to [[Nagasaki, Nagasaki|Nagasaki]] for public display, and the entire complex at Hara Castle was burned to the ground and buried together with the bodies of all the dead.&lt;ref&gt;Naramoto, p. 401.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the Christians in Japan continued for two centuries to maintain their religion as [[Kakure Kirishitan]], or hidden Christians, without any priests or pastors. Some of those who were killed for their Faith are venerated as the [[Martyrs of Japan]].

Although Christianity was later allowed during the [[Meiji era]], Christians were again persecuted during the period of [[State Shinto]], and even in the 21st century Christians are often expected to work on Sundays and Christmas.

===India===
{{Main|Anti-Christian violence in India}} {{Main|Anti-Christian violence in Karnataka}}

[[Image:JamalabadFortPassage.jpg||thumb|right|The [[Jamalabad|Jamalabad fort]] route. Mangalorean Catholics had traveled through this route on their way to [[Seringapatam]]]]

In spite of the fact that there have been relatively fewer conflicts between Muslims and Christians in India in comparison to those between Muslims and Hindus, or Muslims and Sikhs, the relationship between Muslims and Christians have been occasionally turbulent. With the advent of European colonialism in India throughout the 16th, 17th and 18th centuries, Christians were systematically persecuted in a few Muslim ruled kingdoms in India. Modern day persecution also exists carried out by Hindu nationalists. A report by Human Rights Watch stated that there is a rise of anti-Christian violence due to Hindu nationalism and Smita  Narula, Researcher, Asia Division of Human Rights Watch stated &quot;Christians are the new scapegoat in India's political battles. Without immediate and decisive action by the government, communal tensions will continue to be exploited for political and economic ends.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hrw.org/en/news/1999/09/29/anti-christian-violence-rise-india&lt;/ref&gt;

Perhaps the most infamous acts of anti-Christian persecution by Muslims was committed by [[Tippu Sultan]], the ruler of the [[Kingdom of Mysore]] against the [[Mangalorean Catholic]] community from [[Mangalore]] and the erstwhile [[South Canara]] district on the southwestern coast of India. Tippu was widely reputed to be anti-Christian. The captivity of Mangalorean Catholics at [[Seringapatam]], began on 24 February 1784 and ended on 4 May 1799.&lt;ref name=&quot;dajser&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.daijiworld.com/chan/achievers_view.asp?a_id=28 |title= Deportation &amp; The Konkani Christian Captivity at Srirangapatna (1784 Feb. 24th Ash Wednesday) |accessdate=29 February 2008 |publisher=[[Daiji World|Daijiworld Media Pvt Ltd Mangalore]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bakur Manuscript reports him as having said:
''&quot;All Musalmans should unite together, and considering the annihilation of infidels as a sacred duty, labor to the utmost of their power, to accomplish that subject.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;Lobo&quot;/&gt;
Soon after the [[Treaty of Mangalore]] in 1784, Tippu gained control of Canara.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Forrest|1887|pp=314–316|Ref=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; He issued orders to seize the Christians in Canara, confiscate their estates,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|The Gentleman's Magazine|1833|p=[http://books.google.com/books?id=CnSrSlq_ckcC&amp;printsec=titlepage#PPA388,M1 388]|Ref=ge}}&lt;/ref&gt; and deport them to Seringapatam, the capital of his empire, through the [[Jamalabad|Jamalabad fort]] route.&lt;ref name=&quot;dm&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.dioceseofmangalore.org/history.asp
|title= Christianity in Mangalore
|accessdate=30 July 2008
|publisher=[[Roman Catholic Diocese of Mangalore|Diocese of Mangalore]]|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080622155343/http://www.dioceseofmangalore.org/history.asp |archivedate = 22 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were no priests among the captives. Together with Fr Miranda, all the 21 arrested priests were issued orders of expulsion to Goa, fined Rs 2 lakhs, and threatened death by hanging if they ever returned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lobo&quot;/&gt;

Tippu ordered the destruction of 27 Catholic churches. Among them were the Church of Nossa Senhora de Rosario Milagres at [[Mangalore]], Fr Miranda's Seminary at [[Monte Mariano]], Church of Jesu Marie Jose at [[Omzoor]], Chapel at [[Bolar]], Church of Merces at [[Ullal]], Imaculata Conceiciao at [[Mulki, India|Mulki]], San Jose at [[Perar]], Nossa Senhora dos Remedios at [[Kirem]], Sao Lawrence at [[Karkal]], Rosario at [[Barkur]], Immaculata Conceciao at [[Baidnur]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lobo&quot;&gt;[http://74.125.153.132/search?q=cache:Vxbcseuc9SIJ:www.kinnigoli.com/%3Fapp%3Darticle%26mode%3Dview%26uid%3D11+Sarasvati's+Children+Peter+Prabhu&amp;cd=3&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=in Sarasvati's Children], Joe Lobo&lt;/ref&gt; All were razed to the ground, with the exception of ''Igreja da Santa Cruz Hospet'' also known as [[Hospet Church]] at Hospet,owing to the friendly offices of the Chauta Raja of [[Moodbidri]].&lt;ref name=&quot;escdemo&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.daijiworld.com/chan/exclusive_arch.asp?ex_id=129
|title= Monti Fest Originated at Farangipet – 240 Years Ago! |accessdate=28 April 2009 |author= John B. Monteiro |publisher= Daijiworld Media Pvt Ltd Mangalore}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Sir Thomas Munro, 1st Baronet|Thomas Munro]], a Scottish soldier and the first collector of Canara, around 60,000 of them,&lt;ref name=&quot;bow2&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bowring|1997|p=[http://books.google.com/books?id=jrL3wXQ2-rYC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA126,M1 126]|Ref=bow}}&lt;/ref&gt; nearly 92&amp;nbsp;percent of the entire Mangalorean Catholic community, were captured, only 7,000 escaped. [[Francis Buchanan-Hamilton|Francis Buchanan]] gives the numbers as 70,000 captured, from a population of 80,000, with 10,000 escaping. They were forced to climb nearly {{convert|4000|ft|m}} through the jungles of the [[Western Ghats|Western Ghat]] mountain ranges. It was {{convert|210|mi|km}} from Mangalore to Seringapatam, and the journey took six weeks. According to British Government records, 20,000&amp;nbsp; of them died on the march to Seringapatam. According to James Scurry, a British officer, who was held captive along with Mangalorean Catholics, 30,000&amp;nbsp;of them were forcibly converted to Islam. The young women and girls were forcibly made wives of the Muslims living there.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Scurry|Whiteway|1824|p=[http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;id=SMoEAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=The+Captivity,+Sufferings+And+Escape+of+James+Scurry+Who+Was+Detained+a+Prisoner+During+Ten+Years+In+The+Dominions+of+Hyder+Ali+and+Tippu+Saheb&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=web&amp;ots=WGA2GSphYR&amp;sig=pEPIz1kdtvB8Vup3mSQWy9n-JNA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=result#PPA103,M1 103]|Ref=jam}}&lt;/ref&gt; The young men who offered resistance were disfigured by cutting their noses, upper lips, and ears.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Scurry|Whiteway|1824|p=[http://books.google.com/books?id=SMoEAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage#PPA104,M1 104]|Ref=jam}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Mr. Silva of [[Gangolim]], a survivor of the captivity, if a person who had escaped from Seringapatam was found, the punishment under the orders of Tippu was the cutting off of the ears, nose, the feet and one hand.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/prakashjm45/seringapatnam2.html&amp;date=2009-10-26+03:08:21 Account of a Surviving Captive, A Mr. Silva of Gangolim] (Letter of a Mr. L.R. Silva to his sister, a copy of which was given by an advocate, M.M. Shanbhag, to the author, Severino da Silva, and reproduced as Appendix No. 74: ''History of Christianity in Canara'' (1965))&lt;/ref&gt;

The Archbishop of Goa wrote in 1800, ''&quot;It is notoriously known in all Asia and all other parts of the globe of the oppression and sufferings experienced by the Christians in the Dominion of the King of Kanara, during the usurpation of that country by Tipu Sultan from an implacable hatred he had against them who professed Christianity.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;Lobo&quot;/&gt;
[[File:James Scurry.jpg|thumb|left|The British officer [[James Scurry]], who was detained a prisoner for 10 years by Tipu Sultan along with the Mangalorean Catholics]]
Tippu Sultan's invasion of the [[Malabar Coast]] had an adverse impact on the [[Saint Thomas Christian]] community of the Malabar coast. Many churches in Malabar and [[Cochin]] were damaged. The old Syrian Nasrani seminary at Angamaly which had been the center of Catholic religious education for several centuries was razed to the ground by Tippu's soldiers. Many centuries-old religious manuscripts were lost forever. The church was later relocated to Kottayam where it still exists to this date. The Mor Sabor church at Akaparambu and the Martha Mariam Church attached to the seminary were destroyed as well. Tippu's army set fire to the church at Palayoor and attacked the Ollur Church in 1790. Furthernmore, the Arthat church and the Ambazhakkad seminary was also destroyed. Over the course of this invasion, many Saint Thomas Christians were killed or forcibly converted to Islam. Most of the coconut, arecanut, pepper and cashew plantations held by the Saint Thomas Christian farmers were also indiscriminately destroyed by the invading army. As a result, when Tippu's army invaded Guruvayur and adjacent areas, the Syrian Christian community fled Calicut and small towns like Arthat to new centres like Kunnamkulam, Chalakudi, Ennakadu, Cheppadu, Kannankode, [[Mavelikkara]], etc. where there were already Christians. They were given refuge by Sakthan Tamburan, the ruler of Cochin and Karthika Thirunal, the ruler of Travancore, who gave them lands, plantations and encouraged their businesses. Colonel Macqulay, the British resident of Travancore also helped them.&lt;ref name= Bernard &gt;K.L. Bernard, ''Kerala History '', pp. 79&lt;/ref&gt;

Tippu's persecution of Christians also extended to captured British soldiers. For instance, there were a significant amount of forced conversions of British captives between 1780 and 1784. Following their disastrous defeat at the [[battle of Pollilur]], 7,000 British men along with an unknown number of women were held captive by Tippu in the fortress of Seringapatnam. Of these, over 300 were circumcised and given Muslim names and clothes and several British regimental drummer boys were made to wear ''[[ghagra cholis]]'' and entertain the court as ''nautch'' girls or dancing girls. After the 10 year long captivity ended, James Scurry, one of those prisoners, recounted that he had forgotten how to sit in a chair and use a knife and fork. His English was broken and stilted, having lost all his vernacular idiom. His skin had darkened to the swarthy complexion of [[negro]]es, and moreover, he had developed an aversion to wearing European clothes.&lt;ref&gt;William Dalrymple ''White Mughals'' (2006) p28&lt;/ref&gt;

During the surrender of the Mangalore fort which was delivered in an armistice by the British and their subsequent withdrawal, all the [[Mestizos]] and remaining non-British foreigners were killed, together with 5,600 Mangalorean Catholics. Those condemned by Tippu Sultan for treachery were hanged instantly, the gibbets being weighed down by the number of bodies they carried. The Netravati River was so putrid with the stench of dying bodies, that the local residents were forced to leave their riverside homes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lobo&quot;/&gt;

Besides Historical persecution there have been several attacks in Modern day India carried out mainly by Hindu radicals such as the waves of attacks in Karnataka where attacks were directed against Christian churches and prayer halls in Karnataka by the [[Bajrang Dal]], with the [[B. S. Yeddyurappa|ruling BJP government]] accused of involvement. The violence started from 14 September 2008 when about 20 churches were vandalized in [[Mangalore]], [[Udupi]], [[Chikkamagaluru]], and in other districts of Karnataka. Minor violence was later reported from the border state of [[Kerala]]. Also in Gujarat where 22 churches were burnt or destroyed, and another 16 damaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;MANAS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Anti-Christian Violence in India|url=http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/southasia/History/Current_Affairs/Current_affairs.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Anti-Christian violence also flared up in Orissa which was triggered by the killing of [[Graham Staines]] who was an [[Australian]] missionary working with the [[Evangelical Missionary Society of Mayurbhanj]], an Australian missionary society.  On the night of 22 January 1999, he was sleeping in his [[station wagon]] when it was set afire.  Graham and his two sons, ten-year-old Philip and six-year-old Timothy, were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7166297.stm|title=  Indian minister in Orissa visit|date=2 January 2008|accessdate=18 September 2008 | work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dara Singh (murderer)|Dara Singh]], a Hindu fanatic from [[Etawah]] in [[Uttar Pradesh]], was arrested for the crime. On 22 September 2003 a court appointed by the [[Central Bureau of Investigation]] sentenced Dara Singh to death and 12 others to life imprisonment for the murders.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hinduonnet.com/fline/fl2021/stories/20031024003902400.htm The Staines case verdict]&lt;/ref&gt;

===French Revolution===
{{Main|Dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution|Revolt in the Vendée}}
[[File:MassacrePrincessLamballe.jpg|thumb|240px|[[September Massacres]], 1792]]
The Dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution is a conventional description of a campaign, conducted by various [[Robespierre]]-era governments of France beginning with the start of the [[French Revolution]] in 1789, to eliminate any symbol that might be associated with the past, especially the [[Monarchy of France|monarchy]].

The program included the following policies:&lt;ref&gt;Latreille, A. FRENCH REVOLUTION, New Catholic Encyclopedia v. 5, pp. 972–973 (Second Ed. 2002 Thompson/Gale) ISBN 0-7876-4004-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;SPIELVOGEL, Jackson [http://books.google.com/books?id=ni4PSpOxb6MC&amp;dq Western Civilization: Combined Volume] p. 549, 2005
Thomson Wadsworth&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tallet, Frank [http://books.google.com/books?id=aL4lsWdd-rAC&amp;dq Religion, Society and Politics in France Since 1789] p. 1, 1991 Continuum International Publishing&lt;/ref&gt;

* the deportation of clergy and the condemnation of many of them to death,
* the closing, [[desecration]] and pilaging of churches, removal of the word &quot;saint&quot; from street names and other acts to banish Christian culture from the public sphere
* removal of statues, plates and other iconography from places of worship
* destruction of crosses, bells and other external signs of worship
* the institution of revolutionary and civic cults, including the [[Cult of Reason]] and subsequently the [[Cult of the Supreme Being]],
* the large scale destruction of religious monuments,
* the outlawing of public and private worship and religious education,
* forced marriages of the clergy,
* forced abjurement of priesthood, and
* the enactment of a law on 21 October 1793 making all nonjuring priests and all persons who harbored them liable to death on sight.
[[File:Fusillades de Nantes.jpg|thumb|240px|Mass shootings at Nantes, 1793]]
The climax was reached with the celebration of the Goddess &quot;Reason&quot; in [[Notre Dame de Paris|Notre Dame]] Cathedral on 10 November.

Under threat of death, imprisonment, military conscription or loss of income, about 20,000 constitutional priests were forced to abdicate or hand over their letters of ordination and 6,000 – 9,000 were coerced to marry, many ceasing their ministerial duties.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Tallet, Frank [http://books.google.com/books?id=aL4lsWdd-rAC&amp;dq Religion, Society and Politics in France Since 1789] p. 10, 1991 Continuum International Publishing&lt;/ref&gt; Some of those who abdicated covertly ministered to the people.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt; By the end of the decade, approximately 30,000 priests were forced to leave France, and thousands who did not leave were executed.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Gwynne [http://books.google.com/books?id=VjXHmc6Z5ZcC&amp;pg=PA45&amp;lpg=PA45&amp;dq=dechristianisation+of+france+during+the+french+revolution&amp;source=web&amp;ots=8NNRjFA4Fr&amp;sig=CpEiqD7wOPrORg7aWTcHX4CnL7w The French Revolution: Rethinking the Debate] p.96 1993
Routledge, ISBN 0-415-05466-4&lt;/ref&gt; Most of France was left without the services of a priest, deprived of/liberated from the [[sacraments]] and any nonjuring priest faced the [[guillotine]] or deportation to [[French Guiana]].&lt;ref&gt;Tallet, Frank [http://books.google.com/books?id=aL4lsWdd-rAC&amp;dq Religion, Society and Politics in France Since 1789] p. 11, 1991 Continuum International Publishing&lt;/ref&gt;

The March 1793 conscription requiring [[Vendée|Vendeans]] to fill their district's quota of 300,000 enraged the populace, who took up arms as &quot;The Catholic Army&quot;, &quot;Royal&quot; being added later, and fought for &quot;above all the reopening of their parish churches with their former priests.&quot;&lt;ref name=Jones-52-53&gt;Joes, Anthony James [http://books.google.com/books?id=buHXFDFdeoQC&amp;dq Resisting Rebellion: The History and Politics of Counterinsurgency] 2006 University Press of Kentucky ISBN 0-8131-2339-9. [http://books.google.com/books?id=buHXFDFdeoQC&amp;pg=PA53&amp;cad=1_1&amp;sig=ACfU3U2D11vTELzIqW-huFbUKO4yuc_axw p. 52-53]&lt;/ref&gt; A massacre of 6,000 Vendée prisoners, many of them women, took place after the battle of [[Savenay]], along with the drowning of 3,000 Vendée women at Pont-au-Baux and 5,000 Vendée priests, old men, women, and children killed by drowning at the [[Loire River]] at [[Nantes]] in what was called the &quot;[[Drownings at Nantes|national bath]]&quot; – tied in groups in barges and then sunk into the Loire.&lt;ref&gt;[[Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition]] &quot;[http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Wars_Of_The_Vendee Wars Of The Vendee]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=12:01AM BST 27 September 2007 Comments |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/global/main.jhtml?xml=/global/2007/09/27/schools-teaching-children-france.xml |title=What are the educational options for British children moving to France? |publisher=Telegraph |date=27 September 2007 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DB1231F934A25755C0A96F948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all |title=In a Corner of France, Long Live the Old Regime |publisher=New York Times |date=17 June 1989 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |first=James M. |last=Markham}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With these [[Mass murder|massacres]] came formal orders for forced evacuation; also, a '[[scorched earth]]' policy was initiated: farms were destroyed, crops and forests burned and villages razed. There were many reported atrocities and a campaign of mass killing universally targeted at residents of the [[Vendée]] regardless of combatant status, political affiliation, age or gender.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.genocidetext.net/gaci_origins.pdf |title=Jones, Adam Genocide: A Comprehensive Introduction p.7 (Routledge/Taylor &amp; Francis Publishers Forthcoming 2006) |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; By July 1796, the estimated Vendean dead numbered between 117,000 and 500,000, out of a population of around 800,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content.cdlib.org/xtf/view?docId=ft2h4nb1h9&amp;doc.view=content&amp;chunk.id=d0e1419&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;anchor.id=0&amp;brand=eschol |title=Three State and Counterrevolution in France by Charles Tilly |publisher=cdlib.org |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?sec=travel&amp;res=950DE1DC123AF93AA35754C0A96F948260 |title=Vive la Contre-Revolution! |publisher=New York Times |date=9 July 1989 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |first1=Alice |last1=Furlaud}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McPhee, Peter [http://www.h-france.net/vol4reviews/mcphee3.html Review of Reynald Secher, A French Genocide: The Vendée] H-France Review Vol. 4 (March 2004), No. 26&lt;/ref&gt; Some historians call these mass killings the first modern [[genocide]], specifically because intent to exterminate the Catholic Vendeans was clearly stated,&lt;ref&gt;Jonassohn, Kurt and Karin Solveig Bjeornson ''Genocide and Gross Human Rights Violations'' p. 208, 1998, [[Transaction Publishers]], ISBN 0-7658-0417-4.&lt;/ref&gt; though others have [[War in the Vendée#Accusation of genocide|rejected these claims]].

==Modern era (1815 to 1989)==
===Ottoman Empire===
{{Main|Armenian genocide|Assyrian genocide|Greek genocide}}
In 1842 [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]] living in the mountains of [[Hakkari]] in south east [[Anatolia]] faced a massive unprovoked attack from Ottoman forces and [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]] irregulars, which resulted in the death of tens of thousands of unarmed Christian Assyrians.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;http://aua.net/assyrians/genocide/genocide_presentation.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

A major massacre of [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]] and [[Armenians]] in the [[Ottoman Empire]] occurred between 1894 and 1897 AD by [[Ottoman Empire|Turkish]] troops and their [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]] supporters during the rule of [[Sultan]] [[Abdul Hamid II]] (the [[Hamidian massacre]]). The motives for these massacres were an attempt to reassert [[Pan-Islamism]] in the Ottoman Empire, resentment at the comparative wealth of the ancient indigenous Christian communities, and a fear that they would attempt to secede from the tottering Ottoman Empire. Assyrians and Armenians were massacred in [[Diyarbakir]], [[Hasankeyef]], [[Sivas]] and other parts of Anatolia and northern Mesopotamia, by Sultan Abdul Hamid II. These attacks caused the death of tens of thousands of Assyrians and Armenians and the forced &quot;Ottomanisation&quot; of the inhabitants of 245 villages. The Turkish troops looted the remains of settlements and these were later stolen and occupied by Muslim [[Kurds]]. Unarmed Christian women and children were raped, tortured and murdered.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

The [[Young Turks]] government of the collapsing [[Ottoman Empire]] in 1915 persecuted [[Eastern Christianity|Christian]] populations in [[Anatolia]], [[Persia]] and Northern [[Mesopotamia]]. The onslaught by the Ottoman army, including Kurdish and Circassian irregulars resulting in an estimated 2.1 million deaths, divided between roughly 1.2 Million [[Armenian Apostolic Church|Armenian Christians]], 0.75 million [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]] and 0.3 million [[Greek Orthodox Christians]], a number of [[Georgians]] were also killed. The Genocide led to the devastation of ancient indigenous Christian peoples who had existed in the region for thousands of years.&lt;ref&gt;The Plight of Religious Minorities: Can Religious Pluralism Survive? – Page 51 by United States Congress&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Armenian Genocide: Wartime Radicalization Or Premeditated Continuum – Page 272 edited by Richard Hovannisian&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Not Even My Name: A True Story – Page 131 by Thea Halo&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Political Dictionary of Modern Middle East by Agnes G. Korbani&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soviet Union and Warsaw Pact Countries===
{{Further|Persecution of Christians in the Soviet Union|Persecution of Christians in Warsaw Pact countries}}

After the Revolution of 1917, the Bolsheviks undertook a massive program to remove the influence of the [[Russian Orthodox Church]] from the government while outlawing antisemitism in Russian society, and promoting state [[atheist]]. Tens of thousands of churches were destroyed or converted to other uses, and many members of clergy were murdered, including public executions and imprisonment for what the government termed &quot;anti-government activities.&quot; An extensive education and propaganda campaign was undertaken to convince people, especially the children and youth, to abandon religious beliefs. This persecution resulted in the intentional murders of sixty million Orthodox followers in the 20th century by the Soviet Union.

This persecution spread not only to the Orthodox, but also other groups, such as the [[Mennonite]]s, who largely fled to [[the Americas]].&lt;ref name=sovmenno&gt;{{cite web|author=Ruslan V. Olkhovskiy |url=http://www.artukraine.com/commcrimes/inferno.htm |title=Soviet persecution of Mennonites, 1929–1941 |publisher=Artukraine.com |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before and after the October Revolution of 7 November 1917 (25 October Old Calendar) there was a movement within the Soviet Union to unite all of the people of the world under Communist rule (see [[Communist International]]). This included the Eastern European bloc countries as well as the Balkan States. Since some of these Slavic states tied their ethnic heritage to their ethnic churches, both the peoples and their church were targeted for ethnic and political genocide by the Soviets and its form of [[State atheism]].&lt;ref&gt;President of Lithuania: Prisoner of the Gulag a Biography of [[Aleksandras Stulginskis]] by Afonsas Eidintas Genocide and Research Center of Lithuania ISBN 9986-757-41-X / 9789986757412 / 9986-757-41-X pg 23 &quot;As early as August 1920 [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]] wrote to [[E. M. Skliansky]], President of the Revolutionary War Soviet: &quot;We are surrounded by the greens (we pack it to them), we will move only about 10–20 versty and we will choke by hand the [[bourgeoisie]], the clergy and the landowners. There will be an award of 100,000 rubles for each one hanged.&quot; He was speaking about the future actions in the countries neighboring Russia.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christ Is Calling You: A Course in Catacomb Pastorship by Father [[George Calciu]] Published by Saint Hermans Press April 1997 ISBN 978-1-887904-52-0&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviets' official religious stance was one of &quot;religious freedom or tolerance&quot;, though the state established atheism as the only scientific truth (see also the Soviet or committee of the All-Union Society for the Dissemination of Scientific and Political Knowledge or [[Znanie]] which was until 1947 called [[Society of the Godless|The League of the Militant Godless]] and various [[Intelligentsia]] groups).&lt;ref&gt;History of the Orthodox Church in the History of Russian Dimitry Pospielovsky 1998 St Vladimir's Press ISBN 0-88141-179-5 pg 291&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A History of Marxist-Leninist Atheism and Soviet Antireligious Policies, Dimitry Pospielovsky Palgrave Macmillan (December 1987) ISBN 0-312-38132-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Peris Storming the Heavens: The Soviet League of the Militant Godless Cornell University Press 1998 ISBN 978-0-8014-3485-3&lt;/ref&gt; Criticism of atheism was strictly forbidden and sometimes resulted in imprisonment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Sermons to young people by Father George Calciu-Dumitreasa. Given at the Chapel of the Romanian Orthodox Church Seminary |publisher=The Word online. Bucharest |url=http://www.orthodoxresearchinstitute.org/resources/sermons/calciu_christ_calling.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the more high profile individuals executed include [[Benjamin of Petrograd|Metropolitan Benjamin of Petrograd]], Priest and scientist [[Pavel Florensky]] and Bishop [[Gorazd (Pavlik) of Prague|Gorazd Pavlik]].

The Communist regime confiscated church property, ridiculed religion, harassed believers, and propagated atheism in the schools. Actions toward particular religions, however, were determined by State interests, and most organized religions were never outlawed. It is estimated that 500,000 Russian [[Orthodox Christians]] were [[martyred]] in the [[gulag]]s by the Soviet government, not including torture or other [[Christian denominations]] killed.&lt;ref&gt;World Christian trends, AD 30-AD 2200, p.230-246 Tables 4–5 &amp; 4–10 By David B. Barrett, Todd M. Johnson, Christopher R. Guidry, Peter F. Crossing NOTE: They define 'martyr' on p235 as only including christians killed for faith and excluding other christians killed&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=April 2010}}

Some actions against Orthodox priests and believers along with [[execution]] included [[torture]] being sent to [[gulags|prison camps]], [[sharashka|labour camps]] or [[Psikhushka|mental hospitals]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;Father Arseny 1893–1973 Priest, Prisoner, Spiritual Father. Introduction pg. vi – 1. St Vladimir's Seminary Press ISBN 0-88141-180-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Washington Post Anti-Communist Priest Gheorghe Calciu-Dumitreasa by Patricia Sullivan Washington Post Staff Writer Sunday, 26 November 2006; Page C09 http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/11/25/AR2006112500783.html&lt;/ref&gt;
The result of [[state atheism|state sponsored atheism]] was to transform the Church into a persecuted and martyred Church. In the first five years after the Bolshevik revolution, 28 bishops and 1,200 priests were executed.&lt;ref name=Ostling&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ostling |first=Richard |title=Cross meets Kremlin |journal=TIME Magazine |date=24 June 2001 |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,150718,00.html |accessdate=3 July 2007 | work=Time}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Christ the Savior Cathedral Moscow from a bridge.jpg|thumb|[[Cathedral of Christ the Saviour (Moscow)|Christ the Savior Cathedral Moscow]] after reconstruction]]
The main target of the anti-religious campaign in the 1920s and 1930s was the Russian Orthodox Church, which had the largest number of faithful. A very large segment of its clergy, and many of its believers, were shot or sent to labor camps. Theological schools were closed, and church publications were prohibited. In the period between 1927 and 1940, the number of Orthodox Churches in the Russian Republic fell from 29,584 to less than 500. Between 1917 and 1940, 130,000 Orthodox priests were arrested.
The widespread persecution and internecine disputes within the church hierarchy lead to the seat of [[Patriarch of Moscow]] being vacant from 1925 to 1943.

After Nazi Germany's attack on the Soviet Union in 1941, Joseph Stalin revived the Russian Orthodox Church to intensify patriotic support for the war effort. By 1957 about 22,000 Russian Orthodox churches had become active. But in 1959 Nikita Khrushchev initiated his own campaign against the Russian Orthodox Church and forced the closure of about 12,000 churches. By 1985 fewer than 7,000 churches remained active.&lt;ref name=Ostling/&gt;

In the Soviet Union, in addition to the methodical closing and destruction of churches, the charitable and social work formerly done by ecclesiastical authorities was taken over by the state. As with all private property, Church owned property was confiscated into public use. The few places of worship left to the Church were legally viewed as state property which the government permitted the church to use. After the advent of state funded universal education, the Church was not permitted to carry on educational, instructional activity for children. For adults, only training for church-related occupations was allowed. Outside of sermons during the celebration of the divine liturgy it could not instruct or evangelise to the faithful or its youth. Catechism classes, religious schools, study groups, Sunday schools and religious publications were all illegal and or banned. This caused many religious tracts to be circulated as illegal literature or [[samizdat]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated1/&gt; This persecution continued, even after the death of Stalin until the [[dissolution of the Soviet Union]] in 1991. Since the fall of the Soviet Union, the Russian Orthodox Church has recognized a number of [[New-martyr|New Martyrs]] as saints, some executed during [[Mass operations of the NKVD]] under directives like [[NKVD Order No. 00447]].

===19th and 20th century Mexico===
{{Main|Persecution of Christians in Mexico}}
[[Image:Miguel Pro.gif|thumb|[[Blessed Miguel Pro]], arms spread in the form of a cross, was killed for his faith by the government in Mexico.]]
In the 19th century, Mexican President [[Benito Juárez]] confiscated church lands. The [[Mexican government]]'s campaign against the Catholic Church after the [[Mexican Revolution]] culminated in the 1917 constitution which contained numerous articles which Catholics perceived as violating  their civil rights: outlawing monastic religious orders, forbidding public worship outside of church buildings, restricted religious organizations' rights to own property, and taking away basic civil rights of members of the clergy (priests and religious leaders were prevented from wearing their habits, were denied the right to vote, and were not permitted to comment on public affairs in the press and were denied the right to trial for violation of [[anticlerical]] laws). When the first embassy of the Soviet Union in any country was opened in Mexico, the Soviet ambassador remarked that &quot;no other two countries show more similarities than the Soviet Union and Mexico&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Krauze, Enrique, [http://books.google.com/books?id=sMIUcsUVyzsC&amp;pg=PA418&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false ''Mexico: biography of power : a history of modern Mexico, 1810–1996''], p. 418, Harper Collins 1998&lt;/ref&gt;

When the Church publicly condemned the anticlerical measures which had not been strongly enforced, the atheist President [[Plutarco Calles]] sought to vigorously enforce the provisions and enacted additional anti-Catholic legislation known as the Calles Law. At this time, some in the United States government, considering Calles' regime [[Bolshevik]], started to refer to Mexico as &quot;Soviet Mexico&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Richards, Michael D. [http://books.google.com/books?id=rdAGt7QYKHoC&amp;pg=PA30&amp;lpg=PA30&amp;dq=%22soviet+mexico%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=gA_lkRyafi&amp;sig=Zwqh7YFrAQWG5ZfF7-8WlcCE2RY ''Revolutions in World History''] p. 30 (2004
Routledge) ISBN 0-415-22497-7&lt;/ref&gt;

Weary of the persecution, in many parts of the country a popular rebellion called the [[Cristero War]] began (so named because the rebels felt they were fighting for Christ himself). The effects of the persecution on the Church were profound. Between 1926 and 1934 at least 40 priests were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated5&quot;&gt;Van Hove, Brian [http://www.ewtn.com/library/HOMELIBR/FR94204.TXT ''Blood-Drenched Altars''] Faith &amp; Reason 1994&lt;/ref&gt; Where there were 4,500 priests serving the people before the rebellion, in 1934 there were only 334 priests licensed by the government to serve fifteen million people, the rest having been eliminated by emigration, expulsion and assassination.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated5&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Scheina, Robert L. [http://books.google.com/books?id=8aWQ_7oKJfkC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;lpg=PA33&amp;dq=cristero+war+priests+killed&amp;source=web&amp;ots=YNDpLM2ukb&amp;sig=YWccvtnJKnSpaI15bTHCOX3zoyc#PPA33,M1 ''Latin America's Wars: The Age of the Caudillo, 1791–1899''] p. 33 (2003
Brassey's) ISBN 1-57488-452-2&lt;/ref&gt; By 1935, 17 states had no priest at all.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ramón Eduardo Ruiz|Ruiz, Ramón Eduardo]] [http://books.google.com/books?id=AfdjWl1xKpwC&amp;pg=PA392&amp;dq=Tom%C3%A1s+Garrido+Canabal&amp;as_brr=3&amp;sig=HkfPtdqMt3qrdcMuprgfjnfnq60 ''Triumphs and Tragedy: A History of the Mexican People''] p.393 (1993 W. W. Norton &amp; Company) ISBN 0-393-31066-3&lt;/ref&gt; In the second Cristero rebellion (1932), the Cristeros took particular exception to the socialist education, which Calles had also implemented but which President Cardenas had added to the 1917 Mexican Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;Sanderson, Steven E., [http://books.google.com/books?id=sXvjHWFI1_AC&amp;pg=PA102&amp;dq#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Agrarian populism and the Mexican state: the struggle for land in Sonora], p. 102, Univ. of California Press 1981&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Matthew Butler [http://books.google.com/books?id=aROKUlyB21cC&amp;pg=PA201&amp;dqi#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false Popular piety and political identity in Mexico's Cristero Rebellion], p. 201&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-Mormonism===
{{Main|Anti-Mormonism}}

The [[Latter Day Saint Movement]], ([[Mormons]]) have been persecuted since their founding in the 1830s. This persecution drove them from New York and [[Ohio]] to [[Missouri]], where they continued to suffer violent attacks. In 1838, Gov. [[Lilburn Boggs]] declared that Mormons had made war on the state of Missouri, and &quot;must be treated as enemies, and must be exterminated or driven from the state&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Feldman&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/01/06/magazine/06mormonism-t.html?pagewanted=1&amp;ei=5124&amp;en=92f33bb3ad8525e6&amp;ex=1357448400&amp;partner=permalink&amp;exprod=permalink |title=What Is It About Mormonism? |date=6 January 2008 |first=Noah |last=Feldman |publisher=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At least 10,000 were expelled from the State.  In the most violent of the altercations at this time, the [[Haun's Mill massacre|Haun's mill Massacre]], 17 were murdered by an anti-Mormon mob and 13 were wounded.&lt;ref&gt;http://seminary.lds.org/manuals/church-history-institute-student-manual/chft-16-20-16.asp&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Missouri Executive Order 44|Extermination Order]] sign by Governor Boggs was not invalidated until 25 June 1976, 137 years after being signed.

The Mormons subsequently fled to [[Nauvoo, Illinois|Nauvoo]], Illinois, where hostilities again escalated. In Carthage, Ill., where [[Joseph Smith]] was being held on the charge of treason, a mob stormed the jail and killed him. Smith's brother, Hyrum, was also killed. After a [[succession crisis (Latter Day Saints)|succession crisis]], most united under [[Brigham Young]], who organized an evacuation from the United States after the federal government refused to protect them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Smith | first = Joseph Fielding | authorlink = Joseph Fielding Smith | title = Church History and Modern Revelation | volume = 4 | pages = 167–173 | publisher = [[Deseret Book]] | date= 1946–1949 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 70,000 [[Mormon pioneers]] crossed the [[Great Plains]] to settle in the [[Salt Lake Valley]] and surrounding areas. After the [[Mexican-American War]], the area became the US [[Utah Territory|territory of Utah]]. Over the next 46 years several actions by the federal government were directed against Mormons in the [[Mormon Corridor]], including the [[Utah War]], [[Morrill Anti-Bigamy Act]], [[Poland Act]], ''[[Reynolds v. United States]]'', [[Edmunds Act]], and [[Edmunds-Tucker Act]].

===Madagascar===
Queen [[Ranavalona I]] (reigned 1828–1861) issued a royal edict prohibiting the practice of [[Christianity]] in [[Madagascar]], expelled British missionaries from the island, and sought to [[Persecution of Christians in Madagascar|stem the growth of conversion]] to Christianity within her realm. Approximately 60–80 Malagasy citizens were put to death during this period as a consequence of their refusal to recant their Christian faith.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}} Far more, however, were punished in other ways: many were required to undergo the ''[[tangena]]'' ordeal, while others were condemned to hard labor or the confiscation of their land and property, and many of these consequently died. The tangena ordeal was commonly administered to determine the guilt or innocence of an accused person for any crime, including the practice of Christianity, and involved ingestion of the poison contained within the nut of the tangena tree (''[[Cerbera odollam]]''). Survivors were deemed innocent, while those who perished were assumed guilty. [[Malagasy people|Malagasy]] Christians would remember this period as ''ny tany maizina'', or &quot;the time when the land was dark&quot;.  Persecution of Christians intensified in 1840, 1849 and 1857; in 1849, deemed the worst of these years by British missionary to Madagascar W.E. Cummins (1878), 1,900 people were fined, jailed or otherwise punished in relation to their Christian faith, including 18 executions.&lt;ref name = Sunday&gt;{{Cite document | last = Cousins | first = W.E. | contribution = Since 1800 in Madagascar | year = 1877–1878 |volume = 1 | title = The Sunday Magazine for Family Reading | pages = 405–410 | place = London | publisher = Daldy, Isbister &amp; Co}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spain===
==== Anti-Catholicism ====
[[Image:SpanishLeftistsShootStatueOfChrist.jpg|thumb|right|250px|&quot;Execution&quot; of the [[Sacred Heart of Jesus]] by a republican firing squad.&lt;ref&gt;Ealham, Chris and Michael Richards, [http://books.google.com/books/cambridge?id=ypBS6N0aFJgC&amp;pg=PA80&amp;dq=%22most+famous+ritual+destruction%22 The Splintering of Spain], p. 80, 168, Cambridge University Press, 2005, ISBN 0-521-82178-9, ISBN 978-0-521-82178-0&lt;/ref&gt; The image was originally published in the London ''[[Daily Mail]]'' with a caption noting the &quot;Spanish Reds' war on religion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://orpheus.ucsd.edu/speccoll/swphotojournalism/m629-f02-19.html Shots of War: Photojournalism During the Spanish Civil War]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{Main|Red Terror (Spain)}}

Persecution of Catholics mostly, before and at the beginning, of the Spanish Civil war (1936–1939), involved the murder of almost 7,000 priests and other clergy, as well as thousands of lay people, by sections of nearly all the leftist groups because of their faith.&lt;ref name=&quot;links.jstor.org&quot;&gt;[[Julio de la Cueva]], [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-0094%28199807%2933%3A3%3C355%3ARPATAR%3E2.0.CO%3B2-O &quot;Religious Persecution, Anticlerical Tradition and Revolution: On Atrocities against the Clergy during the Spanish Civil War&quot;] ''Journal of Contemporary History'' 33.3 (July 1998): 355.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Payne, Stanley G., [http://libro.uca.edu/payne2/payne26.htm A History of Spain and Portugal] p. 647&lt;/ref&gt; The Republican government which had come to power in Spain in 1931 was strongly anti-Catholic, prohibiting religious education – even in private school, prohibiting any education by [[religious institute]]s, seizing Church property and expelling the [[Jesuits]] from the country. On 3 June 1933 [[Pope Pius XI]] issued the encyclical [[Dilectissima Nobis]], in which he described the expropriation of all Church buildings, episcopal residences, parish houses, seminaries and monasteries. By law, they became property of the Spanish State, to which the Church had to pay rent and taxes to continuously use these properties. &quot;Thus the Catholic Church is compelled to pay taxes on what was violently taken from her&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dilectissima Nobis, 9–10&lt;/ref&gt; Religious vestments, liturgical instruments, statues, pictures, vases, gems and similar objects necessary for worship were expropriated as well or desecrated.&lt;ref&gt;Dilectissima Nobis, 12&lt;/ref&gt; Numerous churches and temples were destroyed by burning, after they were nationalized. All private schools run by Catholic religious institutes were expropriated. The purpose was to create solely secular schools there instead.&lt;ref&gt;Dilectissima Nobis, 21&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Pius XI]], who faced similar persecutions in the USSR and Mexico, called on Spanish Catholics to defend themselves against the persecution with all legal means.

During the Spanish Civil War of 1936–1939, and especially in the early months of the conflict, individual clergymen and entire religious communities were executed by leftists, which included communists and anarchists. The [[Martyrs of the Spanish Civil War|death toll of the clergy]] alone included 13 bishops, 4,172 diocesan priests and seminarians, 2,364 monks and friars and 283 nuns, for a total of 6,832 clerical victims.&lt;ref name=&quot;links.jstor.org&quot;/&gt;

In addition to murders of clergy and the faithful, destruction of churches and desecration of sacred sites and objects were widespread. On the night of 19 July 1936 alone, some fifty churches were burned.&lt;ref&gt;David Mitchell, ''The Spanish Civil War'' (New York: Franklin Watts, 1983), 45.&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Barcelona]], out of the 58 churches, only the Cathedral was spared, and similar desecrations occurred almost everywhere in Republican Spain.&lt;ref&gt;David Mitchell, ''The Spanish Civil War'' (New York: Franklin Watts, 1983), 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

Exceptions were [[Biscay]] and [[Guipuscoa]] where the [[Christian Democratic]] [[Basque Nationalist Party]], after some hesitation, supported the Republic while halting persecution in the areas held by the [[Basque Government]].
All Catholic churches in the Republican zone were closed{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}. The desecration was not limited to Catholic churches, as synagogues and Protestant churches were also pillaged and closed. Some small Protestant churches were spared.&lt;ref&gt;Payne, Stanley [http://books.google.com/books?id=KPgPFqXub14C&amp;vq Franco and Hitler: Spain, Germany, and World], p. 215, 2008 Yale Univ. Press&lt;/ref&gt;

The terror has been called the &quot;most extensive and violent persecution of Catholicism in Western History, in some way even more intense than that of the [[Dechristianisation of France during the French Revolution|French Revolution]].&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated3&quot;&gt;Payne, Stanley [http://books.google.com/books?id=KPgPFqXub14C&amp;vq Franco and Hitler: Spain, Germany, and World], p. 13, 2008 Yale Univ. Press&lt;/ref&gt;
The persecution drove Catholics to the Nationalists, even more than would have been expected, as these defended their religious interests and survival.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated3&quot;/&gt;

==== Anti-Protestantism ====
In [[Francisco Franco|Franco's]] [[authoritarian]] [[Spanish State]] (1936–1975), Protestantism was deliberately marginalized and persecuted. During the Civil War, Franco's regime persecuted the country's 30,000&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot;&gt;Payne, Stanley [http://books.google.com/books?id=JGoqcg22N4gC&amp;dq Spanish Catholicism: An Historical Overview], p. 186 ,1984 [[University of Wisconsin Press]]&lt;/ref&gt;
Protestants, and forced many Protestant pastors to leave the country. Once authoritarian rule was established, non-Catholic Bibles were confiscated by police and Protestant schools were closed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,772711,00.html | work=Time | title=Religion: Protestant Persecution | date=21 April 1941 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the 1945 Spanish Bill of Rights granted freedom of ''private'' worship, Protestants suffered legal discrimination and non-Catholic religious services were not permitted publicly, to the extent that they could not be in buildings which had exterior signs indicating it was a house of worship and that public activities were prohibited.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wood, James Edward [http://books.google.com/books?id=pKEUoZinc6wC&amp;dq Church and State in the Modern World], p. 3, 2005 Greenwood Publishing&lt;/ref&gt;

While the Catholic Church was declared official and enjoyed a close relation to the state, parts of the Basque clergy harbored [[Basque nationalism|nationalist ideas]] opposed to Spanish centralism and were persecuted and imprisoned in a &quot;[[Concordate jail]]&quot; reserved for criminal clergy.

===Nazi Germany===
Hitler and the Nazis had widespread support from traditional Christian communities, mainly due to a common cause against the anti-religious German Bolsheviks. Once in power, the Nazis moved to consolidate their power over the German churches and bring them in line with Nazi ideals. Many historians say that Hitler had a general covert plan, which some say existed even before the Nazis' rise to power, to destroy Christianity within the Reich, which was to be accomplished through control and subversion of the churches and to be completed after the war.&lt;ref name=a4&gt;Sharkey, [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DB1F39F930A25752C0A9649C8B63 Word for Word/The Case Against the Nazis; How Hitler's Forces Planned To Destroy German Christianity], New York Times, 13 January 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://org.law.rutgers.edu/publications/law-religion/nurinst1.shtml The Nazi Master Plan: The Persecution of the Christian Churches], Rutgers Journal of Law and Religion, Winter 2001, publishing evidence compiled by the O.S.S. for the Nuremberg war-crimes trials of 1945 and 1946&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Roger Griffin|Griffin, Roger]] ''Fascism's relation to religion'' in Blamires, Cyprian, [http://books.google.com/books?id=nvD2rZSVau4C&amp;dq World fascism: a historical encyclopedia, Volume 1], p. 10, ABC-CLIO, 2006: “There is no doubt that in the long run Nazi leaders such as Hitler and Himmler intended to eradicate Christianity just as ruthlessly as any other rival ideology, even if in the short term they had to be content to make compromises with it.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[George Lachmann Mosse|Mosse, George Lachmann]], [http://books.google.com/books?id=_cyR3QyuSdIC&amp;dq Nazi culture: intellectual, cultural and social life in the Third Reich], p. 240, Univ of Wisconsin Press, 2003: &quot;Had the Nazis won the war their ecclesiastical policies would have gone beyond those of the German Christians, to the utter destruction of both the Protestant and the Catholic Church.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bendersky, Joseph W., [http://books.google.com/books?id=ATCXucbTYX0C&amp;dq A concise history of Nazi Germany], p. 147, Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2007: “Consequently, it was Hitler’s long rang goal to eliminate the churches once he had consolidated control over his European empire.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[William L. Shirer|Shirer, William L.]],  [http://books.google.com/books?id=sY8svb-MNUwC&amp;dq Rise and Fall of the Third Reich: A History of Nazi Germany], p. p 240, Simon and Schuster, 1990: “And even fewer paused to reflect that under the leadership of Rosenberg, Bormann and Himmler, who were backed by Hitler, the Nazi regime intended eventually to destroy Christianity in Germany, if it could, and substitute the old paganism of the early tribal Germanic gods and the new paganism of the Nazi extremists.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Jack Fischel|Fischel, Jack R.]],  [http://books.google.com/books?id=EzBZP92xwUUC&amp;dq Historical Dictionary of the Holocaust] , p. 123, Scarecrow Press, 2010: “The objective was to either destroy Christianity and restore the German gods of antiquity or to turn Jesus into an Aryan.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dill, Marshall,  [http://books.google.com/books?id=xRrGP7L9_hEC&amp;dq Germany: a modern history] , p. 365, University of Michigan Press, 1970: “It seems no exaggeration to insist that the greatest challenge the Nazis had to face was their effort to eradicate Christianity in Germany or at least to subjugate it to their general world outlook.”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wheaton, Eliot Barculo  [http://books.google.com/books?ei=Nu-6TrqBLOaTiQKL5dy2Dg&amp;ct The Nazi revolution, 1933–1935: prelude to calamity:with a background survey of the Weimar era], p. 290, 363, Doubleday 1968: The Nazis sought to &quot;to eradicate Christianity in Germany root and branch.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The Third Reich founded their own version of Christianity called [[Positive Christianity]] which made major changes in its interpretation of the [[Bible]] which said that [[Jesus Christ]] was the son of God, but was not a Jew and claimed that Christ despised Jews, and that the Jews were the ones solely responsible for Christ's death. Thus, the Nazi government consolidated religious power, using allies to consolidate Protestant churches into the [[Protestant Reich Church]]. The [[syncretist]] project of Positive Christianity was abandoned by 1940.

Dissenting Christians went underground and formed the [[Confessing Church]], which was [[Kirchenkampf|persecuted]] as a subversive group by the Nazi government. Many of its leaders were arrested and sent to concentration camps, and left the underground mostly leaderless. Church members continued to engage in various forms of resistance, including hiding Jews during the [[Holocaust]] and various attempts, largely unsuccessful, to prod the Christian community to speak out on the part of the Jews.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

The Catholic Church was suppressed in Poland. Between 1939 and 1945, an estimated 3,000 members, 18% of the Polish clergy,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;Craughwell, Thomas J., [http://www.catholicculture.org/library/view.cfm?recnum=472 The Gentile Holocaust] Catholic Culture. Retrieved 18 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; were murdered; 1,992 of which died in concentration camps. In the annexed territory of ''Reichsgau Wartheland'', it was even harsher than elsewhere. Churches were systematically closed, and most priests were either killed, imprisoned, or deported to the [[General Government]]. The Germans also closed seminaries and convents persecuting monks and nuns throughout Poland. In [[Pomerania]], all but 20 of the 650 priests were shot or sent to concentration camps. 80% of the Catholic clergy and five of the bishops of Warthegau were sent to concentration camps in 1939. In the city of [[Breslau]] (''Wrocław''), 49% of its Catholic priests were killed, and in [[Chełmno]], 48%. 108 of them are regarded as blessed martyrs.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt; Among them, [[Maximilian Kolbe]] was canonized as a saint.

Not only were Polish Christians persecuted by the Nazis, in the [[Dachau concentration camp]] alone, 2,600 Catholic priests from 24 different countries were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt; Outside mainstream Christianity, [[Persecution of Jehovah's Witnesses|Jehovah's Witnesses]] were direct targets of the Holocaust, for their refusal to swear allegiance to the Nazi government. Many Jehovah's Witnesses were given the chance to deny their faith and swear allegiance to the state, but few agreed. Over 12,000 Witnesses were sent to the concentration camps, and estimated 2,500–5,000 died in the Holocaust.{{cn|date=October 2012}}

In the aftermath of the assassination of [[Reinhard Heydrich]], Nazi authorities repressed the [[Czechoslovak Orthodox Church]] which had given aid to the assassins.{{cn|date=October 2012}} 

After the war ended, captured Nazi documents indicated that in the event of a [[Operation Sea Lion|Nazi victory against the United Kingdom]], German authorities would have outlawed the [[Church of England]] and decimated its clergy.{{fact|date=October 2012}}{{clarify|&quot;decimate&quot; suggests reducing by 10% or some similar number. Does the article mean &quot;annihilate&quot;?|date=October 2012}}

===Jehovah's Witnesses===
{{main|Persecution of Jehovah's Witnesses}}
[[Image:Buchenwald Slave Laborers Liberation.jpg|thumb|The [[Buchenwald concentration camp]] is one of the camps in which Jehovah's Witnesses prisoners were labored.]]
Since [[Charles Taze Russell]]'s [[Jehovah's Witnesses|Bible Students]] group had formed after the [[American Civil War]] there was no formal position on military service till 1914, when the body came out against military service. [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] are forbidden by their religion to engage in violence, or to join the military.

In Nazi Germany in the 1930s and early 1940s, Jehovah's Witnesses refused to renounce political neutrality and were [[Persecution of Jehovah's Witnesses in Nazi Germany|placed in concentration camps]] as a result. The Nazi government gave detained Jehovah's Witnesses the option of release by signing a document indicating renouncement of their faith, submission to state authority, and support of the German military.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.holocaust-trc.org/PRJW.htm ''Persecution and Resistance of Jehovah's Witnesses During the Nazi-Regime'', Michael Berenbaum]&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian Hans Hesse said, &quot;Some five thousand Jehovah's Witnesses were sent to concentration camps where they alone were 'voluntary prisoners', so termed because the moment they recanted their views, they could be freed. Some lost their lives in the camps, but few renounced their faith&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Hesse|first=Hans|title=Persecution and resistance of Jehovah's Witnesses during the Nazi regime, 1933–1945|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mcxD0qxHMO0C|accessdate=6 April 2011|year=2001
|publisher=Berghahn Books|isbn=978-3-86108-750-2|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005433 JEHOVAH'S WITNESSES: PERSECUTION 1870–1936] on the [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]] website.&lt;/ref&gt;

Political and religious animosity against Jehovah's Witnesses has at times led to [[mob action]] and [[government]] oppression in various countries, including [[Human rights in Cuba|Cuba]], the [[Persecution of Jehovah's Witnesses in the United States|United States]], [[Persecution of Jehovah's Witnesses in Canada|Canada]] and [[Religion in Singapore#Christianity|Singapore]]. The religion's doctrine of political neutrality has led to imprisonment of members who refused conscription (for example in [[United Kingdom|Britain]] during [[World War II]] and afterwards during the period of compulsory [[national service]]).

==Current situation (1989 to present)==
According to [[Pope Benedict XVI]], Christians are the most persecuted group in the contemporary world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20101216/ap_on_re_eu/eu_vatican_religious_persecution | author=Frances D'Emillo |title=Pope calls Christians the most persecuted
 |agency=Associated Press |date=16 December 2010 |accessdate=7 January. 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the World Evangelical Alliance, over 200 million Christians are denied fundamental human rights solely because of their faith.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.worldevangelicals.org/lausanne/data/resources/IJRF_2008_Vol_1_Issue_1.pdf| author=Godfrey Yogarajah |title=Disinformation, discrimination, destruction and growth: A case study on persecution of Christians in Sri Lanka |publisher=[[International Institute for Religious Freedom]] |date= Vol 1, Issue 1, 2008|accessdate=24 April. 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Persecutions occur in North Korea, many Muslim countries, India, China, Vietnam, and the Philippines.

===Muslim world===
{{See also|Conversion of non-Muslim places of worship into mosques}}

====Afghanistan====
{{See also|Christianity in Afghanistan}}

In [[Afghanistan]], [[Abdul Rahman (convert)|Abdul Rahman]], a 41-year-old citizen, was charged in 2006 with rejecting Islam ([[Apostasy in Islam|apostasy]]), a crime punishable by death under [[Sharia]] law. He has since been released into exile in the West under intense pressure from Western governments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/4823874.stm | work=BBC News | title=Afghan on trial for Christianity | date=20 March 2006 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/7BB654F1-7D5C-4E7D-B251-28A6E20A461D.htm Al Jazeera English – Archive – Afghan Convert's Trial Put In Doubt&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2008, the [[Taliban]] killed a British charity worker, [[Gayle Williams]], &quot;because she was working for an organisation which was preaching Christianity in Afghanistan&quot; even though she was extremely careful not to try to convert Afghans.&lt;ref name=Ind2110&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/killed-for-being-christian-967668.html Killed for being Christian], [[The Independent]], 21 October 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

====Albania/Kosovo====
{{See also|Persecution of Serbs and other non-Albanians in Kosovo|Pogrom in Kosovo}}

====Algeria====
{{See also|Christianity in Algeria}}

On the night of 26–27 March 1996, seven [[monks]] from the monastery of [[Tibhirine]] in [[Algeria]], belonging to the [[Roman Catholic]] [[Trappist]] Order of [[Cistercian]]s of the Strict Observance (O.C.S.O.), were kidnapped in the [[Algerian Civil War]]. They were held for two months, and were found dead on 21 May 1996. The circumstances of their kidnapping and death remain controversial; the [[Armed Islamic Group]] (GIA) claims responsibility for both, but the then French military attaché, retired General [[Francois Buchwalter]], reports that they were accidentally killed by the Algerian army in a rescue attempt, and claims have been made that the GIA itself was a [[wikt:cat's-paw|cat's paw]] of Algeria's secret services ([[Département du Renseignement et de la Sécurité|DRS]]).

Islamists looted, and burned to the ground, a [[Pentecostalism|Pentecostal]] church in [[Tizi Ouzou]] on 9 January 2010. The pastor was quoted as saying that worshipers fled when local police left a gang of local rioters unchecked.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | first=The Associated Press | last= | title=Protestant Church Burned in Algeria | url=http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/2010/01/11/world/AP-AF-Algeria-Burned-Temple.html| work=New York Times | publisher=nytimes.com | location=New York, New York | pages= | date=11 January 2010 | id= | accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Egypt====
{{See also|Persecution of Copts}}
{{Modern persecution of Coptic Christians}}
While the Egyptian government does not have a policy to persecute Christians, it discriminates against them and hampers their freedom of worship. Its agencies sporadically persecute Muslim converts to Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;persec&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.persecution.org/suffering/countryinfodetail.php?countrycode=7 |title=Persecuted Countries &quot; Persecution of Christians &amp; Persecuted Churches |publisher=Persecution.org |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government enforces [[Hamayouni Decree]] restrictions on building or repairing churches. These same restrictions, however, do not apply to mosques.&lt;ref name=&quot;persec&quot;/&gt;

The government has effectively restricted Christians from senior government, diplomatic, military, and educational positions, and there has been increasing discrimination in the private sector.&lt;ref name=&quot;persec&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=catholic.org /&gt; The government subsidizes media which attack Christianity and restricts Christians access to the state-controlled media.&lt;ref name=&quot;persec&quot;/&gt;

In [[Egypt]] the government does not officially recognize conversions from Islam to Christianity; because certain interfaith marriages are not allowed either, this prevents marriages between converts to Christianity and those born in Christian communities, and also results in the children of Christian converts being classified as Muslims and given a Muslim education.&lt;ref name=&quot;persec&quot;/&gt; The government also applies religiously discriminatory laws and practices concerning clergy salaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;persec&quot;/&gt;

Foreign missionaries are allowed in the country only if they restrict their activities to social improvements and refrain from proselytizing. The [[Coptic Christianity|Coptic]] [[Pope Shenouda III]] was internally exiled in 1981 by President [[Anwar Sadat]], who then chose five Coptic bishops and asked them to choose a new pope. They refused, and in 1985 President [[Hosni Mubarak]] restored Pope Shenouda III, who had been accused of fomenting interconfessional strife. Particularly in Upper Egypt, the rise in extremist [[Islamist]] groups such as the [[Gama'at Islamiya]] during the 1980s was accompanied by attacks on Copts and on Coptic churches; these have since declined with the decline of those organizations, but still continue. The police have been accused of siding with the attackers in some of these cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/589977.stm |title=Funerals for victims of Egypt clashes |publisher=BBC News |date=4 January 2000 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many colleges dictate quotas for Coptic students, often around 1 or 2% despite the group making up 15% of the country's population. There is also a separate tax-funded education system called Al Azhar, catering to students from elementary to college level, which accepts no Christian Coptic students, teachers or administrators.

Hundreds of Christian Coptic girls have been kidnapped and forcibly converted to Islam, as well as being victims of rape and forced marriage to Muslim men.&lt;ref name=catholic.org&gt;{{cite web|author=Catholic Online |url=http://www.catholic.org/international/international_story.php?id=33483 |title=The Copts: Persecuted Christians of Egypt By Mounir Bishay 5/6/2009 |publisher=Catholic.org |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|reason=need secular source for veracity|date=January 2010}}

On 2 January 2000, at least 21 [[Christians]] were killed by [[Muslims]] in the Al [[Kosheh Massacres]] in southern Egypt. Christian properties were also burned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/2000/januaryweb-only/43.0a.html |title=Egypt's Christians seek answers after deadly riots |publisher=Christianitytoday.com |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|reason=need secular source for veracity|date=January 2010}}

In April 2006, one person was killed and twelve injured in simultaneous knife attacks on three Coptic churches in Alexandria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4909378.stm |title=Knife attacks on Egypt churches |publisher=BBC News |date=14 April 2006 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2008, several thousand Muslims attacked a Coptic church in a suburb of Cairo on the day of its inauguration, forcing 800 Coptic Christians to barricade themselves in.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Catholic Online |url=http://www.catholic.org/international/international_story.php?id=30779 |title=Thousands of Muslims Attack Coptic Church in Cairo |publisher=Catholic.org |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2009, two [[Christian]] men were shot dead and another was injured by [[Muslim]] men after an [[Easter]] vigil in the south of [[Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/8007919.stm |title=BBC: Christians killed in Egypt feud |publisher=BBC News |date=20 April 2009 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 September 2009, a Muslim man, Osama Araban, beheaded a [[Copts|Coptic Christian]] man in the village of [[Bagour]], and injured 2 others in 2 different villages. He was arrested the following day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.coptsunited.com/Details.php?I=6&amp;A=52 |title=Muslim Man Beheads Christian in Egypt |publisher=Copts United |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the eve of 7 January 2010, Copts were going out of Mar-Yuhanna (St. John) church in [[Nag Hammadi massacre|Nag Hammadi]] city when three [[Muslim]] men in a car near the church opened fire killing 8 [[Christians]] and injuring another 10.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wataninet.com/ArticleDetails.aspx?A=25557 |title=News article from Egyptian newspaper Watani |publisher=Wataninet.com |date=10 January 2010 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/8444851.stm |title=News article |publisher=BBC News |date=7 January 2010 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2011 New Year's Eve, as [[Christians]] were leaving a [[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria|Coptic Orthodox Church]] in the city of [[Alexandria]] after a New Year's Eve service a car bomb exploded in front of the Church killing more than 20 and injuring more than 75.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Yolande Knell Middle East specialist |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12101748 |title=Egypt bomb kills 21 at Alexandria Coptic Church |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=1 January 2011 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Saleh |first=Yasmine |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSTRE6BU2VR20110101 |title=Reuters – Bomb kills 21 at Egypt Church |publisher=Reuters.com |date= 1 January 2011|accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Yolande Knell Middle East specialist |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12103248 |title=Egypt's president calls for unity after church bombing |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=1 January 2011 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7 May 2011, an armed group of Islamists, attacked and set fire to two churches including [[Saint Menas]] Coptic Orthodox Christian Church and the Coptic Church of the Holy Virgin, in [[Cairo]]. The attacks resulted in the deaths of 12 people and more than 230 wounded. It is reported that the events were triggered by a mixed marriage between a Christian woman and a Muslim man.&lt;ref&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/africa/05/08/egypt.clashes/?hpt=T2 State TV: At least 12 killed, 232 wounded in clashes at Cairo church], CNN.com, 8 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2012, [[Dahshur]]'s entire Christian community, which some estimate to be as many as 100 families, fled to nearby towns due to sectarian violence.  The violence began in a dispute over a badly ironed shirt, which in turn escalated into a fight in which a Christian burned a Muslim to death, which in turn sparked a rampage by angry Muslims, while the police failed to act.  At least 16 homes and properties of Christians were pillaged, some were torched, and a church was damaged during the violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Riot leaves christians&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/riot-leaves-egyptian-village-christians-16930420 | title=Riot leaves an Egyptian village without Christians | publisher=ABC News | agency=Associated Press | date=4 August 2012 | accessdate=5 August 2012 | author=El Deeb, Sarah}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Indonesia====
{{See also|Christianity in Indonesia}}

In January 1999&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Islamism's Other Victims: The Tragedy of East Timor |publisher=FrontPage Magazine |date=25 November 2002 |url=http://archive.frontpagemag.com/readArticle.aspx?ARTID=20986 |accessdate=1 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Ethno-religious violence in Indonesia: from soil to God. Volume 18 of Routledge contemporary Southeast Asia series
|last=Wilson
|first=Chris
|year=2008
|page=103
|publisher=Psychology Press
|isbn=978-0-415-45380-6
|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=XLQJqs6QTaAC&amp;pg=PA103}}&lt;/ref&gt; tens of thousands died when Muslim gunmen terrorized Christians who had voted for independence in [[East Timor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Faith: A History of Christianity
|last=Moynahan
|first=Brian
|year=2003
|page=728
|publisher=Random House, Inc.
|isbn=978-0-385-49115-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Indonesia]], religious conflicts have typically occurred in [[Western New Guinea]], [[Maluku Islands|Maluku]] (particularly [[Ambon Island|Ambon]]), and [[Sulawesi]]. The presence of Muslims in these regions is in part a result of the ''[[transmigrasi]]'' program of population re-distribution. Conflicts have often occurred because of the aims of radical [[Islamist]] organizations such as [[Jemaah Islamiah]] or [[Laskar Jihad]] to impose [[Sharia]],&lt;ref&gt;[www.persecution.org/whitepapers/indonesia-2002-06-01.html ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1955918.stm |title=Muslim mob attacks Indonesia Christians |publisher=BBC News |date=28 April 2002 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with such groups attacking Christians and destroying over 600 churches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.persecution.org/suffering//countryinfodetail.php?countrycode=6 |title=United States Commission on International Religious Freedom Report |publisher=Persecution.org |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006 three Christian girls were beheaded as retaliation for previous Muslim deaths in Christian-Muslim rioting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Stephen Fitzpatrick, Jakarta correspondent |url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,20867,20726085-2703,00.html |title=Beheaded girls were Ramadan 'trophies' |publisher=Theaustralian.news.com.au |date=9 November 2006 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The men were imprisoned for the murders, including Jemaah Islamiyah's district ringleader Hasanuddin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.voanews.com/english/archive/2007-03/2007-03-21-voa20.cfm?CFID=191805742&amp;CFTOKEN=75125546 Islamic Militants in Indonesia Jailed for Beheading Christian Girls]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On going to jail, Hasanuddin said, &quot;It's not a problem (if I am being sentenced to prison), because this is a part of our struggle.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/6473897.stm |title=Indonesians jailed for beheadings |publisher=BBC News |date=21 March 2007 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later on November 2011, another attack from Islamic community happen in Ambon. Muslims set fire to several Christian houses, forcing the occupants to leave the buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Profil Gereja, Jakarta correspondent |url=http://www.international.kabargereja.tk/2011/09/ambon-violent-clashes-between-christian.html |title= Ambon Violent Clashes Between Christian and Muslims, Triggered by Provocative Text Message |publisher=international.kabargereja.tk |date=11 September 2011 |accessdate=25 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In December 2011, a second church in [[Bogor]], [[West Java]] was ordered to halt its activities by the local mayor. Another Catholic church had been built there in 2005. Previously a Christian church, GKI Taman Yasmin, had been sealed. Local authorities refused to lift a ban on the activities of the church, despite an order from the [[Supreme Court of Indonesia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= |title=Second Bogor Church Under Threat by Officials in Indonesia |date=23 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Local authorities have persecuted the Christian church for three years. While the state has ordered religious toleration, it has not enforced these orders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2011/12/24/3-years-gki-yasmin-church-remains-victim-absence-state.html |title=3 years on, GKI Yasmin church remains victim of absence of the state |date=24 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Aceh Province]], the only province in [[Indonesia]] with autonomous Islamic Shari'a Law, 20 churches in [[Aceh Singkil Regency|Singkil Regency]] face threat of demolition due to gubernatorial decree requires the approval of 150 worshippers, while the ministrial decree also requires the approval of 60 local residents of different faiths. On 30 April 2012, all the 20 churches (17 Protestant churches, 2 Catholic churches and one place of worship belonging to followers of a local nondenominational faith) have been closed down by ordered from the Acting Regent which also ordered members of the congregations to tear down the churches by themselves. Most of the churches slated for demolition were built in 1930s and 1940s, and now the regency only has 2 churches open, both built after 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2012/06/12/20-churches-aceh-face-threat-demolition.html |title=20 churches in Aceh face threat of demolition |date=12 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2012/06/13/regent-orders-churches-closed-destroyed-aceh.html |title=Regent orders churches closed, destroyed in Aceh |date=13 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Iran ====
{{See also|Christianity in Iran}}

Though [[Iran]] recognizes [[Assyrian people|Assyrian]] and [[Armenian people|Armenian]] Christians as ethnic and religious minorities (along with [[Jews]] and [[Zoroastrians]]) and they have representatives in the [[Majlis of Iran|Parliament]], after the [[Iranian Revolution|1979 Revolution]], Muslim converts to Christianity (typically to Protestant Christianity) have been arrested and sometimes executed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Iran Religious and Ethnic Minorities: Discrimination in Law And Practice|publisher=Human Rights Watch|year=1997|url=http://www.hrw.org/reports/1997/iran/Iran-05.htm|accessdate =22 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Youcef Nadarkhani]] is an Iranian Christian pastor who was arrested on charges of Apostasy in October 2009 and was subsequently sentenced to death. In June 2011 the Iranian Supreme Court overruled his death sentence on condition that he recant, which he refused to do. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Iranian Pastor Youcef Nadarkhani's potential execution rallies U.S. Christians |first= Adelle M. |last= Banks |url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/on-faith/us-christians-rally-around-iranian-pastor/2011/09/28/gIQA11YJ5K_story.html |newspaper= [[The Washington Post]] |date= 28 September 2011 |accessdate=5 October 2011 |quote= Religious freedom advocates rallied Wednesday (Sept. 28) around an Iranian pastor who is facing execution because he has refused to recant his Christian faith in the overwhelmingly Muslim country. |archiveurl= http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/?url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/on-faith/us-christians-rally-around-iranian-pastor/2011/09/28/gIQA11YJ5K_story.html&amp;title=Iranian%20Pastor%20Youcef%20Nadarkhani's%20potential%20execution%20rallies%20U.S.%20Christians |archivedate= 7 October 2011 |deadurl= yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a reversal on 8 of September 2012 he was acquitted of the charges of apostasy and extortion, and sentenced to time served for the charge of  &quot;propaganda against the regime,&quot; and immediately released. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Christian Pastor Youcef Nadarkhani Acquitted of Apostasy, Released |url= http://www.iranhumanrights.org/2012/09/nadarkhani-2/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iraq====
{{See also|Christianity in Iraq}}

According to [[UNHCR]], although Christians (almost exclusively ethnic [[Assyrian people|Assyrians]] and [[Armenians]]) represent less than 5% of the total Iraqi population, they make up 40% of the refugees now living in nearby countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Sabah |first=Zaid |url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2007-03-22-christians-iraq_N.htm |title=Christians, targeted and suffering, flee Iraq |publisher=Usatoday.com |date=23 March 2007 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Northern Iraq remained predominantly [[Assyrian people|Assyrian]], [[Aramaic]] speaking and [[Christian]] until the destructions of [[Tamerlane]] at the end of the 14th century. The [[Assyrian Church of the East]] has its origin in what is now South East [[Turkey]] and [[Assuristan]] (Sassanid [[Assyria]]). By the end of the 13th century there were twelve [[Nestorian Church|Nestorian]] dioceses in a strip from [[Peking]] to [[Samarkand]]. When the 14th-century Muslim warlord of Turco-Mongol descent, [[Timur]] (Tamerlane), conquered [[Persia]], [[Mesopotamia]] and [[Syria]], the civilian population was decimated. Timur had 70,000 [[Church of the East|Assyrian Christians]] beheaded in [[Tikrit]], and 90,000 more in [[Baghdad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mertsahinoglu.com/research/14th-century-annihilation-of-iraq/ |title=14th century annihilation of Iraq |publisher=Mertsahinoglu.com |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nupi.no/cgi-win/Russland/etnisk_b.exe?Assyrian NUPI – Centre for Russian Studies&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 16th century, Christians were half the population of Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unhcr.org/cgi-bin/texis/vtx/iraq?page=news&amp;id=461e5a644 UNHCR | Iraq]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1987, the last Iraqi census counted 1.4 million Christians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.aspx?reportid=61897 |title=Christians live in fear of death squads |publisher=Irinnews.org |date=19 October 2006 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were tolerated under the [[secular]] regime of [[Saddam Hussein]], who even made one of them, [[Tariq Aziz]] his deputy. However persecution by Saddam Hussein continued against the Christians on an ethnic, cultural and racial level, as the vast majority are Mesopotamian Aramaic speaking Ethnic Assyrians (aka [[Chaldo-Assyrians]]). The Assyrian -Aramaic language and written script was repressed, the giving of Hebraic/Aramaic Christian names or [[Akkadian]]/[[Assyrio-Babylonian]] names forbidden(Tariq Aziz real name is Michael Youhanna for example), and Saddam exploited religious differences between Assyrian denominations such as [[Chaldean Catholics]], [[Assyrian Church of the East]], [[Syriac Oryhodox]] and [[Ancient Church of the East]]Many . Assyrians were ethnically cleansed from their towns and villages under the Anfal Campaign in 1988.

Recently, Chaldo-Assyrian Christians have seen their total numbers slump to about 500,000 to 800,000 today, of whom 250,000 live in [[Baghdad]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Jonathan Steele in Mosul |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/pope/story/0,,1961207,00.html |title='We're staying and we will resist' |publisher=Guardian |date= 30 November 2006|accessdate=29 June 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; An exodus to the neighboring countries of [[Syria]], [[Jordan]] and [[Turkey]] has left behind closed parishes, seminaries and convents. As a small minority, who until recently were without a militia of their own, Assyrian Christians have been persecuted by both [[Shi’a]] and [[Sunni]] Muslim militias, [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]] Nationalists, and also by criminal gangs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lee |first=Andrew |url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1606015,00.html |title=Iraq's Christians Flock to Lebanon |publisher=Time.com |date=2 April 2007 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,270377,00.html |title=Christians Fleeing Violence in Iraq |publisher=Foxnews.com |date=7 May 2007 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=February 2012|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Assyrian Christians are departing for their ancestral heartlands in the [[Nineveh plains]] around Mosul. Assyrian militias have recently been set up to protect villages and towns&lt;ref&gt;http://www.assyrianamericancoalition.org/documents/policy/AtTheTippingPoint-NPProvinceSolutionFull.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iraqdemocracyproject.org/policy_alert_2.html&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 21 June 2007, the [[UNHCR]] estimated that 2.2 million Iraqis had been displaced to neighboring countries, and 2 million were displaced internally, with nearly 100,000 Iraqis fleeing to Syria and Jordan each month.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/meast/06/20/damon.iraqrefugees/index.html |title=Iraq refugees chased from home, struggle to cope |publisher=Cnn |date=20 June 2007 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/world/middleeast/articles/2006/11/03/un_nearly_100000_flee_iraq_monthly/ U.N.: 100,000 Iraq refugees flee monthly]. Alexander G. Higgins, ''[[Boston Globe]]'', 3 November 2006&lt;/ref&gt; A 25 May 2007 article notes that in the past seven months only 69 people from [[Iraq]] have been granted [[refugee]] status in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Ann McFeatters: [http://www.seattlepi.com/opinion/317322_mcfeatters27.html Iraq refugees find no refuge in America]. ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' 25 May 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, [[Chaldean Catholic Church|Chaldean]] Catholic priest Fr. [[Ragheed Aziz Ganni]] and subdeacons Basman Yousef Daud, Wahid Hanna Isho, and Gassan Isam Bidawed were killed in the ancient city of [[Mosul]].&lt;ref name=&quot;frragheed&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.independent.co.uk/people/obituaries/article2655894.ece |title=Fr Ragheed Ganni – The Independent (14 June 2007) |publisher=News.independent.co.uk |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011 |location=London |deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=February 2012|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fr. Ragheed Aziz Ganni was driving with his three deacons when they were stopped and demanded to convert to Islam, when they refused they were shot.&lt;ref name=&quot;frragheed&quot; /&gt; Six months later, the body of [[Paulos Faraj Rahho]], archbishop of [[Chaldean Catholic Archeparchy of Mosul|Mosul]], was found buried near [[Mosul]]. He was kidnapped on 29 February 2008 when his bodyguards and driver were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/7271828.stm | work=BBC News | title=Who are the Chaldean Christians? | date=13 March 2008 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2004, five churches were destroyed by bombing. Tens of thousands of Christians fled the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1101040927-699409,00.html Time magazine:Iraq's persecuted Christians] retrieved 13 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2007/11/29/60minutes/main3553612.shtml |title=CBS |publisher=CBS News |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010-11-01 was an attack on the ''Our Lady of Salvation'' [[Syriac Catholic]] [[cathedral]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/news/world/middleeast/articles/2010/11/01/baghdad_church_siege_ends_with_52_dead/ &quot;Iraqi Christians mourn after church siege kills 58&quot;] Boston.com, 2010-11-01. Retrieved 11 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
of [[Baghdad]], [[Iraq]], that took place during Sunday evening [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]] on 31 October 2010. The attack left at least 58 people dead, after more than 100 had been taken hostage. The [[al-Qaeda]]-linked [[Sunni]] insurgent group&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/e239159e-5c6a-11db-9e7e-0000779e2340.html &quot;Call for Sunni state in Iraq&quot;.] ''[[Financial Times|ft.com]]'', 2006-10-15. Retrieved 2010-11-07. Registration required.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Islamic State of Iraq]] claimed responsibility for the attack; though Shia cleric Ayatollah Ali al-Sistani and Iraq's highest Catholic cleric condemned the attack, amongst others.

====Lebanon====
{{See also|Christianity in Lebanon}}

The war in Lebanon saw a number of massacres of both Christians and Muslims. Among the earliest was the [[Damour massacre|Damour Massacre]] in 1976 when Palestinian militias attacked Christian civilians. According to an eyewitness: The attack took place from the mountain behind &quot;It was an apocalypse,&quot; [said Father Mansour Labaky, a Christian Maronite priest who survived the massacre at Damour:] 'They were coming, thousands and thousands, shouting &quot;Allahu Akbar! (God is great!) Let us attack them for the Arabs, let us offer a holocaust to Mohammad!&quot;, And they were slaughtering everyone in their path, men, women and children.'&lt;ref&gt;''Israel undercover: secret warfare and hidden diplomacy in the Middle East'' by Steve Posner, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=yIoyu17AUJ8C&amp;dq=Allahu |title=Babylon or Jerusalem? By Jan Willem van der Hoeven p. 54 |publisher= |date= 1 September 1993|accessdate=29 June 2011|isbn=978-1-56043-114-5|author1=Hoeven|first1=Jan Willem van der}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ict.org.il/Articles/tabid/66/Articlsid/291/currentpage/4/Default.aspx |title=PLO Policy towards the Christian Community during the Civil War in Lebanon |publisher=ICT |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The persecution in Lebanon combined sectarian, political, ideological, and retaliation reasons. The [[Syria|Syrian regime]] was also involved in persecuting Christians as well as Muslims in Lebanon.

In 2002, a currently unidentified gunman killed Bonnie Penner Witherall at a prenatal clinic in [[Sidon, Lebanon]]. She had been [[proselytizing]] and attempting to convert Muslims to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1DE1E39F936A15752C1A9649C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all Killing Underscores Enmity Of Evangelists and Muslims], New York Times, 25November 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Malaysia====
{{See also|Christianity in Malaysia|Freedom of religion in Malaysia}}

In [[Malaysia]], although Islam is the official religion, Christianity is mostly tolerated.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} However, to be a member of the majority race (the [[Malay people|Malays]]), one is legally required to be a Muslim.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} If a non-Muslim marries a Muslim, they are legally required to convert to Islam.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} There has been a debate over whether Malaysia is a liberal [[Islamic state]] or a very religious [[secular state]].{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}

Christians are forbidden to proselytize Muslims. Only Muslims are allowed to proselytize.  In the 21st century, Christians have been accused of proselytizing Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Malaysian Muslims Hold Anti-Conversion Rally|publisher=Jakarta Globe|year=2011|url=http://www.thejakartaglobe.com/seasia/malaysian-muslims-hold-anti-conversion-rally/473394|accessdate =23 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pakistan====
{{See also|Christianity in Pakistan}}

In [[Religion in Pakistan|Pakistan]] 1.5% of the population are [[Christianity in Pakistan|Christian]]. [[Pakistani law]] mandates that &quot;[[Blasphemy law in Pakistan|blasphemies]]&quot; of the [[Qur'an]] are to be met with punishment. Ayub {{sic|hide=y|Masih}}, a Christian, was convicted of blasphemy and sentenced to death in 1998. He was accused by a neighbor of stating that he supported British writer [[Salman Rushdie]], author of ''[[The Satanic Verses]]''. Lower appeals courts upheld the conviction. However, before the [[Pakistan Supreme Court]], his lawyer was able to prove that the accuser had used the conviction to force {{sic|hide=y|Masih's}} family off their land and then acquired control of the property. {{sic|hide=y|Masih}} has been released.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/rt_pakis.htm |title=Religious Intolerance In Pakistan |publisher=Religioustolerance.org |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2001, gunmen on motorcycles opened fire on a Protestant congregation in the [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]], killing 18 people. The identify of the gunmen are unknown. Officials think it might be a [[ban (law)|ban]]ned Islamic group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/1624223.stm |title=Christians massacred in Pakistan |publisher=BBC News |date=28 October 2001 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2002, five people were killed in an attack on a church in [[Islamabad]], including an American schoolgirl and her mother.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Fuhail |first=Rana |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/pakistan/1388121/Five-killed-as-grenades-are-thrown-into-church.html |title=Five killed as grenades are thrown into church |publisher=Telegraph |date=18 March 2002 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2002, masked gunmen stormed a Christian missionary school for foreigners in Islamabad, six people were killed and three injured. None of those killed were children of foreign missionaries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/pakistan-militants-kill-six-in-christian-school-attack-639030.html |title=Pakistan militants kill six in Christian school attack |publisher=Independent |date=6 August 2002 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2002, grenades were thrown at a church in the grounds of a Christian hospital in north-west Pakistan, near Islamabad, killing three nurses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/pakistan-militants-kill-three-nurses-after-launching-grenade-attack-on-churchgoers-639404.html |title=Pakistan militants kill three nurses after launching grenade attack on churchgoers |publisher=Independent |date=10 August 2002 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 September 2002 two terrorists entered the &quot;Peace and Justice Institute&quot;, [[Karachi]], where they separated Muslims from the Christians, and then murdered seven Christians by shooting them in the head.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.domini.org/openbook/pak20020925.htm |title=Gunmen 'execute' Pakistan Christians |publisher=Domini.org |date=25 September 2002 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/2281191.stm |title=Fears of Pakistan's Christians |publisher=BBC News |date=25 September 2002 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |first=Kathryn |last=Westcott}}&lt;/ref&gt; All of the victims were Pakistani Christians. Karachi police chief Tariq Jamil said the victims had their hands tied and their mouths had been covered with tape.

In December 2002, three young girls were killed when hand grenade was thrown into a church near Lahore on Christmas Day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/thousands-mourn-girls-in-pakistan-church-attack-612075.html |title=Thousands mourn girls in Pakistan church attack |publisher=Independent |date=27 December 2002 |accessdate=29 June 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2005 3,000 militant Islamists attacked Christians in Sangla Hill in Pakistan and destroyed [[Roman Catholic]], [[Salvation Army]] and United [[Presbyterian]] churches. The attack was over allegations of violation of blasphemy laws by a Pakistani Christian named Yousaf {{sic|hide=y|Masih}}. The attacks were widely condemned by some political parties in Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.missio-aachen.de/menschen-kulturen/nachrichten/Sangla_Hill_attack_continues_to_draw_condemnation.asp |title=Asien, Pakistan: Sangla Hill attack continues to draw condemnation |publisher=Missio-aachen.de |date=2 December 2005 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 June 2006 a Pakistani Christian stonemason, Nasir Ashraf, was working near [[Lahore]] when he drank water from a public facility using a glass chained to the facility. He was assaulted by Muslims for &quot;Polluting the glass&quot;. A mob developed, who beat Ashraf, calling him a &quot;Christian dog&quot;. Bystanders encouraged the beating and joined in. Ashraf was eventually hospitalized.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldnetdaily.com/news/article.asp?ARTICLE_ID=51859 Christian beaten for drinking water], Worldnet Daily&lt;/ref&gt;

One year later, in August 2007, a Christian missionary couple, Rev. Arif and Kathleen Khan, were gunned down by militant Islamists in [[Islamabad]]. Pakistani police believed that the murders was committed by a member of Khan's parish over alleged sexual harassment by Khan. This assertion is widely doubted by Khan's family as well as by Pakistani Christians.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/24/nyregion/24missionary.html | work=The New York Times | title=Killing of Missionary Couple in Pakistan Leaves Tears and Questions Stateside | first=Elizabeth | last=Dwoskin | date=24 September 2007 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kxnet.com/getArticle.asp?ArticleId=157762&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2009, six [[Christians]], including 4 women and a child, were burnt alive by [[Muslim]] militants and a [[church (building)|church]] set ablaze in [[Gojra]], Pakistan when [[2009 Gojra Riots|violence]] broke out after alleged desecration of a [[Qur'an]] in a wedding ceremony by Christians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/8179823.stm Pakistan Christians die in unrest], [[BBC]], 1 August 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asianews.it/news-en/Eight-Christians-burned-alive-in-Punjab-15943.html AsiaNews.it] Retrieved 5 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 8 November 2010, a Christian woman from [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab Province]], [[Asia Bibi|Asia Noreen Bibi]], was sentenced to death by hanging for violating Pakistan's blasphemy law. The accusation stemmed from a 2009 incident in which Bibi became involved in a religious argument after offering water to thirsty Muslim farm workers. The workers later claimed that she had blasphemed the Prophet Muhammed. As of 8 April 2011, Bibi is in solitary confinement. Her family has fled. No one in Pakistan convicted of blasphemy has ever been executed. A cleric has offered $5,800 to anyone who kills her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/2010/12/14/132031645/christian-s-death-verdict-spurs-holy-row-in-pakistan |title=Christian's Death Verdict Spurs Holy Row In Pakistan |publisher=NPR |date=14 December 2010 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2035196,00.html | work=Time | title=In Pakistan, Christianity Earns a Death Sentence | date=4 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 March 2011, the only Christian Minister in the Pakistan government was shot dead. [[Shahbaz Bhatti]], [[Ministry of Minorities (Pakistan)|Minister for Minorities]], was in his car along with his niece. Around 50 bullets struck the car. Over 10 bullets hit Bhatti. Before his death he had publicly stated that he was not afraid of the Taliban's threats and was willing to die for his faith and beliefs. He was targeted for opposing the anti-free speech [[Blasphemy law in Pakistan|&quot;blasphemy&quot; law]], which punishes insulting Islam or its Prophet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-south-asia-12617562] Pakistan Minorities Minister Shahbaz Bhatti shot dead, 2 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; A fundamentalist Muslim group claimed responsibility.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestar.com/news/world/article/947146--gunmen-kill-sole-christian-minister-in-pakistan-government Gunmen kill sole Christian minister in Pakistan government] Toronto Star, 2 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Saudi Arabia====
[[File:Christian Bypass.jpg|thumb|300px|&quot;Non-Muslim Bypass:&quot; Non-Muslims are barred from entering [[Mecca]]. An example of [[religious segregation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Yousseff |last=Ibrahim |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Assignment Forbidden To Some |url=http://www2.nysun.com/article/48233 |work= |publisher=[[New York Sun]] |date=8 February 2007 |accessdate=27 April 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Pilgrimage presents massive logistical challenge for Saudi Arabia |url=http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/2001/hajj/stories/logistics/index.html |work= |publisher=CNN |year=2001 |accessdate=27 April 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080315162733/http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/2001/hajj/stories/logistics/index.html |archivedate = 15 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{See also|Christianity in Saudi Arabia|Freedom of religion in Saudi Arabia}}

[[Saudi Arabia]] is an [[Islamic state]] that practices [[Wahhabism]] and restricts all other religions, including the possession of religious items such as the Bible, crucifixes, and Stars of David.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianpost.com/article/20070810/28848_Bibles,_Crucifixes_Not_Allowed_into_Saudi_Arabia.htm |title=Bibles, Crucifixes Not Allowed into Saudi Arabia |publisher=Christianpost.com |date=10 August 2007 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christians are arrested and lashed in public for practicing their faith openly.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.persecution.org/suffering/countryinfodetail.php?countrycode=23 Persecuted Countries: Saudi Arabia – Persecution.org – [[International Christian Concern]]&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Strict [[sharia]] is enforced. Muslims are forbidden to convert to another religion. If one does so and does not recant, they may be executed.{{Citation needed|reason=former ref was from mirror site|date=January 2010}}&lt;!---while this may be interpreted to cover &quot;any&quot; religion, it really only applies to Christians since they are the only ones that ever try to convert anyone---&gt;

====Somalia====
{{See also|Christianity in Somalia}}

In [[Somalia]] 25 November 2010 Nurta Mohamed Farah, age 17. was shot and killed after fleeing her parents home where she had endured much torture and drugging, by them, in hopes that she would renounce her faith in Jesus Christ.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Somali Teenage Girl Shot to Death for Embracing Christ&quot; http://www.compassdirect.org/english/country/somalia/29407/&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sudan====
{{See also|Christianity in Sudan}}

In Sudan, it is estimated that over 1.5 million Christians have been killed by the [[Janjaweed]], the Arab Muslim militia, and even suspected [[Islamists]] in northern Sudan since 1984.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/geno_su.htm |title=Currently active cases: Sudan |publisher=Religioustolerance.org |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It should also be noted that Sudan's several [[civil wars]] (which often take the form of genocidal campaigns) are often not only or purely religious in nature, but also ethnic, as many black Muslims, as well as Muslim Arab tribesmen, have also been killed in the conflicts.

It is estimated that as many as 200,000 people had been taken into [[slavery]] during the [[Second Sudanese Civil War]]. The slaves are mostly [[Dinka people|Dinka]] people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iabolish.org/slavery_today/in_depth/sudan-genocide.html War and Genocide in Sudan]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Coe |first=Erin |url=http://journalism.nyu.edu/pubzone/livewire/archived/the_lost_children_of_sudan/ |title=The Lost Children of Sudan |publisher=Journalism.nyu.edu |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Tunisia====
{{See also|Christianity in Tunisia}}

Since the [[Tunisian revolution]] of 2011, there has been religious violence consisting of Muslim attacks on Christians in Tunisia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://global.christianpost.com/news/video-tunisian-man-beheaded-for-converting-to-christianity-video-78063/ | title=Tunisian Man Beheaded For Converting to Christianity | author=Lawrence D. Jones | publisher=The Christian Post | date= 14 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Turkey====
{{See also|Christianity in Turkey}}

In modern [[Turkey]], the [[Istanbul pogrom]] was a state-sponsored and state-orchestrated [[pogrom]] that compelled Greek Christians to leave [[Istanbul]], the first Christian city in violation to the [[Treaty of Lausanne]] (see [[Istanbul Pogrom]]). The issue of Christian genocides by the Turks may become a problem, since Turkey wishes to join the [[European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Lucia Kubosova |url=http://euobserver.com/9/22331/?rk=1 |title=&quot;MEPs back Armenia genocide clause in Turkey report&quot; by Lucia Kubosova, published by '&amp;#39;EU Observer'&amp;#39; on 5 September 2006 |publisher=Euobserver.com |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Ecumenical Patriarchate of Constantinople]] is still in a difficult position. Turkey requires by law that the [[Ecumenical Patriarch]] must be an [[Greeks|ethnic Greek]], holding Turkish citizenship by birth, although most of the [[Greeks in Turkey|Greek minority]] has been expelled. The state's expropriation of church property and the closing of the Orthodox [[Halki seminary|Theological School of Halki]] are also difficulties faced by the Church of Constantinople. Despite appeals from the United States, the [[European Union]] and various governmental and non-governmental organizations, the School remains closed since 1971. In November 2007, a 17th century chapel of ''Our Lord's Transfiguration'' at the Halki seminary was almost totally demolished by the Turkish forestry authority.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asianews.it/index.php?l=en&amp;art=10827&amp;size=A Halki’s Chapel of the Transfiguration left in ruins] AsiaNews.it, 17 November 2007&lt;/ref&gt; There was no advanced warning given for the demolition work and it was only stopped after appeals by the [[Ecumenical Patriarch Bartholomew I of Constantinople|Ecumenical Patriarch]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ekathimerini.com/4dcgi/_w_articles_politics_100013_16/11/2007_90155 Monastery on Halki wrecked] Kathimerini, English Edition, 16 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Persecution of Christians has continued in modern Turkey. On 5 February 2006, the Catholic priest [[Andrea Santoro]] was murdered in [[Trabzon]] by a student influenced by the reactions following the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/0,1518,437512,00.html|publisher=Der Spiegel Online|title=Goldenes Kreuz unter der Bluse|date=17 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 18 April 2007, 3 Christians were murdered in the [[Bible publishing firm murders in Malatya, Turkey|bible publishing firm]] in [[Malatya]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/world/0,1518,478074,00.html |title=Der Spiegel, Three Killed at Bible Publishing Firm |publisher=Spiegel.de |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/worldservice/programmes/newshour/news/story/2007/04/070419_turkey_slayings.shtml |title=Christians Killed in Turkey |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=19 April 2007 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; coincidentally, the hometown of [[Mehmet Ali Ağca]], the assassin who shot and wounded [[Pope John Paul II]] on 13 May 1981. In December 2007, Adriano Franchini, a catholic priest of the [[Order of Friars Minor Capuchin|Capuchin order]] in Turkey, was stabbed in the stomach after Sunday mass. Franchini led the church of the [[Virgin Mary]] in [[Ephesus]].&lt;ref&gt;[Priest stabbed after Sunday mass in Turkey] The Guardian, 17 December 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus=====
[[Turkish invasion of Cyprus|Turkey invaded Cyprus]] in 1974. The United Nations has documented their systematic destruction of churches of the [[Church of Cyprus]] from 1974 though 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cyprusembassy.net/home/index.php?module=page&amp;pid=22 |title=Official Website of the Embassy of the Republic of Cyprus in Washington D.C |publisher=Cyprusembassy.net |date= |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianpost.com/article/20080428/the-last-church-standing-in-north-cyprus/index.html |title=The Last Church Standing in North Cyprus |publisher=Christianpost.com |date=28 April 2008 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many churches were vandalized and their artifacts stolen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elginism.com/20110110/3444/ Cyprus’s attempts to reclaim artefacts looted from churches] Elginism.com, 10 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Church mosaics and frescoes were removed and ended up in Europe’s black market or sold openly in specialist stores and auction-houses. Some churches were demolished and some have had their use changed to mosques and stables.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcw.gov.cy/mcw/da/da.nsf/DMLlooting_en/DMLlooting_en?OpenDocument The looting of cultural heritage in occupied Cyprus] Department of Antiquities, Ministry of Communications and Works, Government of the Republic of Cyprus&lt;/ref&gt;

====Yemen====
{{See also|Christianity in Yemen}}

Three Christian missionaries were killed in their hospital in Jibla, [[Yemen]] in December 2002. A gunman, apprehended by the authorities, said that he did it &quot;for his religion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/2614091.stm US missionaries murdered in Yemen] BBC. 30 December 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other countries with large Muslim populations====
=====India=====
{{See also|Christianity in India}}

Muslims in India who convert to Christianity have been subjected to harassment, intimidation, and attacks by Muslims. In [[Jammu and Kashmir]], the only Indian state with a Muslim majority, a Christian convert and missionary, Bashir Tantray, was killed, allegedly by militant Islamists in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.speroforum.com/site/article.asp?id=6705 Christian convert from Islam shot dead in Kashmir],''SperoNews''.&lt;/ref&gt;
A Christian priest, K.K. Alavi, a 1970 convert from Islam,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;IN SEARCH OF ASSURANCE&quot; by K. K. Alavi [www.the-good-way.com/eng/article/a16.htm#7.0 online]&lt;/ref&gt; thereby raised the ire of his former Muslim community and received many death threats. An Islamic terrorist group named &quot;The [[NDF India|National Development Front]]&quot; actively campaigned against him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.christianexaminer.com/Articles/Articles%20Jan06/Art_Jan06_07.html Convert from Islam in India Remains on Death List],'''Christian Examiner'''&lt;/ref&gt; In the southern state of India, [[Kerala]], [[2010 hand chopping incident in Kerala|Islamic Terrorists chopped off the hand of Professor T.J.Joseph due to allegation of blasphemy of prophet]].

=====Nigeria=====
{{See also|Christianity in Nigeria}}

In the 11 Northern states of [[Nigeria]] that have introduced the Islamic system of law, the [[Sharia]], sectarian clashes between Muslims and Christians have resulted in many deaths, and some churches have been burned. More than 30,000 Christians were displaced from their homes [[Kano]], the largest city in northern Nigeria.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nigeria Christian / Muslim Conflict|url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/war/nigeria-1.htm|date=27 April 2005|accessdate=5 June 2007|publisher=GlobalSecurity.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Boko Haram]] conducts terrorist attacks against Christians.

=====Philippines=====
{{See also|Christianity in the Philippines}}

In the Philippines, the [[Moro Islamic Liberation Front]] and [[Abu Sayyaf]] has attacked and killed Christians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://persecution.org/Countries/philippines.html Philippines-Christian Persecution in Philippines]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hindu extremism in India===
{{Main|Anti-Christian violence in India}}
{{See also|Religious violence in Orissa}}

The [[Sangh Parivar]] and related organisations have stated that the violence is an expression of &quot;spontaneous anger&quot; of &quot;vanvasis&quot; against &quot;[[Forced conversion|forcible conversion]]&quot; activities undertaken by missionaries. These claims have been disputed by Christians&lt;ref name=&quot;WBE&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author = Low, Alaine M.; Brown, Judith M.; Frykenberg, Robert Eric (eds.) | title = Christians, Cultural Interactions, and India's Religious Traditions | publisher = W.B. Eerdmans | location = Grand Rapids, Mich | year = 2002| page = 134| isbn = 0-7007-1601-7| oclc =| doi =| accessdate =23 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; a belief described as [[myth]]ical&lt;ref name=&quot;CPFVM173&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Ram Puniyani|title=Communal Politics: Facts Versus Myths|publisher=SAGE|location=|year=2003|page=173|isbn=0-7619-9667-2|oclc=|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[propaganda]] by Sangh Parivar;&lt;ref name=&quot;CPFVM176&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Ram Puniyani|title=Communal Politics: Facts Versus Myths|publisher=SAGE|location=|year=2003|page=176|isbn=0-7619-9667-2|oclc=|doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Parivar objects in any case to all conversions as a &quot;threat to national unity&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;VE&quot;&gt;{{cite book| author = Subba, Tanka Bahadur; Som, Sujit; Baral, K. C (eds.)| title = Between Ethnography and Fiction: Verrier Elwin and the Tribal Question in India| publisher = Orient Longman| location = New Delhi| year = 2005| pages =| isbn = 81-250-2812-9| oclc =| doi =| accessdate =23 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Religious scholar Cyril Veliath of [[Sophia University]] stated that the Hindu attacks on Christians were the work of individuals motivated by &quot;disgruntled politicians or phony religious leaders&quot; and where religion is concerned the typical Hindu is an &quot;exceptionally amicable and tolerant person (...) Hinduism as a religion could well be one of the most accommodating in the world. Rather than confront and destroy, it has a tendency to welcome and assimilate.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CyrilVeliath&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Veliath|first=Cyril |date=Summer 2004|title=Hinduism in Japan|journal=Inter-Religio |publisher=[[Sophia University]]|location=Tokyo Japan|volume=45|pages=23–24|url=http://www.nanzan-u.ac.jp/SHUBUNKEN/publications/miscPublications/I-R/pdf/45-Veliath.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Rudolf C Heredia, religious conversion was a critical issue even before the creation of the modern state. Whereas [[Nehru]] wanted to establish a &quot;a secular state in a religious society&quot;&lt;ref&gt;André Malraux. Anti-Memoirs. New York: Bantam. 1970&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gandhi]] opposed the Christian missionaries calling them as the remnants of colonial Western culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/Opinion/Sunday_Specials/Book_Mark/Changing_Gods_Rethinking_Conversion_in_India/articleshow/2695708.cms |title=TOI |publisher=Timesofindia.indiatimes.com |date=13 January 2008 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He claimed that by converting into Christianity, Hindus have changed their nationality.&lt;ref&gt;Rudolf C Heredia. Changing Gods: Rethinking Conversion in India. Penguin Books. 2007. ISBN 0-14-310190-0&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[USCIRF|its controversial annual human rights reports]] for 1999, the [[United States Department of State]] criticised India for &quot;increasing societal violence against Christians.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Expressindia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=US rights report slams India for anti-Christian violence|url=http://www.expressindia.com/news/ie/daily/19990227/ige27064.html|date=27 February 1999|accessdate=17 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report listed over 90 incidents of anti-Christian violence, ranging from damage of religious property to violence against Christians pilgrims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Expressindia&quot;/&gt; In 1997, twenty-four such incidents were reported.&lt;ref name=&quot;CPFVM167&quot;&gt;{{cite book| author = Ram Puniyani| title = Communal Politics: Facts Versus Myths| publisher = SAGE| location =| year = 2003| page = 167| isbn = 0-7619-9667-2| oclc =| doi =| accessdate =}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recent waves of anti-conversion laws in various Indian states passed by some states is claimed to be a gradual and continuous institutionalization of [[Hindutva]] by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labour of the US State Department.&lt;ref&gt;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/371954.cms TOI on International Religious Freedom Report 2003], released by the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights and Labour of the US State Department&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2006, Madhya Pradesh government passed legislation requiring people who desire to convert to a different religion to provide the government with one-month's notice, or face fines and penalties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/5215696.stm |title=Conversions harder in India state 26/07/2006 |publisher=BBC News |date=26 July 2006 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2006, the [[Chhattisgarh]] State Assembly passed similar legislation requiring anyone who desires to convert to another religion to give 30 days' notice to the district magistrate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Mohammad |first=Faisal |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/5246328.stm |title=Christian anger at conversion law 04/08/2006 |publisher=BBC News |date=4 August 2006 |accessdate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===China===
{{See also|Christianity in China}}

The communist government of the People's Republic of China tries to maintain tight control over all religions, so the only legal Christian Churches ([[Three-Self Patriotic Movement]] and [[Chinese Patriotic Catholic Association]]) are those under the [[Communist Party of China]] control. Churches which are not controlled by the government are shut down, and their members are imprisoned.{{citation}}

In 2009, Christians must worship in registered, regulated churches. According to the Jubilee Campaign, an interdenominational lobby group, about 300 Christians caught attending unregistered [[Chinese house church|&quot;house churches&quot;]] were in jail in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/3993857.stm China's Christians suffer for their faith] BBC, 9 November 2004. Retrieved 25 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Gong Shengliang, head of the South China Church, was sentenced to death in 2001. Although his sentence was commuted to a jail sentence, [[Amnesty International]] reports that he has been tortured.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;/&gt;

===North Korea===
{{See also|Religion in North Korea#Christianity|Freedom of religion in North Korea}}

North Korea leads the list of 50 countries where Christians are persecuted at current time according to a watch list by [[Open Doors]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.opendoorsusa.org/persecuted-christians/persecuted-country-profiles/ |author=Open Doors |title=Country Profiles. The 50 countries in which the worst Christian persecution exists| date=January 2011 |accessdate=5 January. 2011|authorlink=Open Doors}}(Archived by WebCite at http://www.webcitation.org/5vVlgKN1j)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indochina region===
{{See also|Christianity in Vietnam|Christianity in Laos|Religion in Cambodia#Christianity|Christianity in Burma|Christianity in Thailand|Freedom of religion in Vietnam|Freedom of religion in Laos|Freedom of religion in Cambodia|Freedom of religion in Burma|Freedom of religion in Thailand}}

The establishment of [[French Indochina]] once led to a high Christian population. Regime changes throughout the 19th and 20th centuries led to some increased persecution of minority religious groups. Killings, torture or imprisonment and forced starvation of local groups are common in parts of Vietnam and Laos, especially in more recent years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=AFP|first=Google|title=Laos, Vietnam troops kill four Hmong Christians: NGO|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5idxNnRhkVWwnlTrzWBGgekWQhYLQ|accessdate=6 May 2011|newspaper=Agence France-Presse|date=15 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Christianity|Human rights}}
* [[Persecution by Christians]]
* [[Anti-Christian sentiment]]
* [[Christian Solidarity Worldwide]]
* [[International Christian Concern]], a Christian human rights NGO whose mission is to help persecuted Christians
* [[Open Doors]]
* [[Religious intolerance]]
* [[Religious persecution]]
* [[Religious pluralism]]
* [[Voice of the Martyrs]]
* [[2010 East Texas Church Burnings]]&lt;!--seems local IMO. Maybe in a new US article?---&gt;
* [[:Category:Christian martyrs]] &lt;!-- do not remove the : inside the brackets --&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
* ''Changing Gods: Rethinking Conversion in India''. Rudolf C Heredia. Penguin Books. 2007. ISBN 0-14-310190-0
* [[William Hugh Clifford Frend|W.H.C. Frend]], 1965. ''Martyrdom and Persecution in the Early Church''
* ''Let My People Go: The True Story of Present-Day Persecution and Slavery'' Cal. R. Bombay, Multnomah Publishers, 1998
* ''Their Blood Cries Out'' Paul Marshall and Lela Gilbert, World Press, 1997.
* ''In the Lion's Den: Persecuted Christians and What the Western Church Can Do About It'' [[Nina Shea]], Broadman &amp; Holman, 1997.
* ''This Holy Seed: Faith, Hope and Love in the Early Churches of North Africa'' Robin Daniel, (Chester, Tamarisk Publications, 2010: from www.opaltrust.org) ISBN 095385634
* ''In the Shadow of the Cross: A Biblical Theology of Persecution and Discipleship'' Glenn M. Penner, Living Sacrifice Books, 2004
* ''Catholic Martyrs of the Twentieth Century: A Comprehensive World History'' by Robert Royal, Crossroad/Herder &amp; Herder; (April 2000). ISBN 0-8245-1846-2
* ''Islam's Dark Side – The Orwellian State of Sudan'', The Economist, 24 June 1995.
* ''Sharia and the IMF: Three Years of Revolution'', SUDANOW, September 1992.
* ''Final Document of the [[Synod]] of the Catholic Diocese of Khartoum'', 1991. [noting &quot;oppression and persecution of Christians&quot;]
* ''[[Human Rights]] Voice'', published by the Sudan Human Rights Organization, Volume I, Issue 3, July/August 1992 [detailing forcible closure of churches, expulsion of priests, forced displacement of populations, forced [[Islamisation]] and [[Arabisation]], and other repressive measures of the Government].
* [[Walid Khalidi|Khalidi, Walid]]. &quot;''All that Remains: The Palestinian Villages cupied and Depopulated by Israel in 1948.''&quot; 1992. ISBN 0-88728-224-5.
* ''Sudan – A Cry for Peace'', published by [[Pax Christi]] International, Brussels, Belgium, 1994
* ''Sudan – Refugees in their own country: The Forced Relocation of Squatters and Displaced People from Khartoum'', in Volume 4, Issue 10, of News from Africa Watch, 10 July 1992.
* ''Human Rights Violations in Sudan'', by the Sudan Human Rights Organization, February 1994. [accounts of widespread torture, ethnic cleansing and crucifixion of pastors].
* ''Pax Romana statement of Macram Max Gassis, Bishop of [[Al-Ubayyid|El Obeid]]'', to the Fiftieth Session of the UN Commission on Human Rights, Geneva, February 1994 [accounts of widespread destruction of hundreds of churches, forced conversions of Christians to Islam, [[concentration camps]], genocide of the [[Nuba]] people, systematic rape of women, enslavement of children, torture of priests and clerics, burning alive of pastors and catechists, crucifixion and mutilation of priests].
* The Persian conquest of Jerusalem in 614CE compared with Islamic conquest of 638CE

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://www.persecution.org [[International Christian Concern]]: Daily News on Christian Persecution around the World]
* [http://www.compassdirect.org/ compassdirect.org: news from the frontlines of persecution]
* [http://www.copts.net/index.asp Coptic Christians persecuted in Egypt]
* [http://www.montagnard-foundation.org/ Montagnard Foundation supporting Christians persecuted in Vietnam, Laos and Cambodia]
* [http://www.iabolish.org Anti-Slavery organization]
* [http://iupjournals.org/jss/jss4-2.html &quot;The Vengeance of the Jews Was Stronger Than Their Avarice: Modern Historians and the Persian Conquest of Jerusalem in 614&quot;] by Elliott Horowitz (Jewish Social Studies Volume 4, Number 2)
* [http://www.moshiach.com/action/ About the Noahide Laws]
* [http://www.angelusonline.org/Article490-thread-order1-threshold0.phtml On the persecution of Catholics in Mexico]
* [http://people.vanderbilt.edu/~james.p.burns/chroma/saints/Persecution.html Graeme Clark, &quot;Christians and the Roman State 193–324&quot;]
* [http://www.ryanspencerreed.com/ Photojournalist's Account] – Images of Sudan's persecution
* [http://www.espoohsrk.fi/html/vainotut.htm Tietoa vainotuista suomeksi – Espoon helluntaikirkon sivut – Information about persecution in Finnish'']
* [http://www.persecution.in Daily updates about Christian persecution in India'']
* [http://www.fourthcentury.com/notwppages/persecution-timeline.htm Chronology of the Persecution of Christians from 299–324]
* [http://www.persecution.com Voice of the Martyrs, USA]
* [http://www.eretzyisroel.org/~jkatz/The%20Persian%20conquest%20of%20Jerusalem%20in%20614CE%20compared%20with%20Islamic%20conquest%20of%20638CE.pdf The Persian conquest of Jerusalem in 614CE compared with Islamic conquest of 638CE]

{{Persecution of Christians}}
{{Religious persecution}}
{{Christian History}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Persecution Of Christians}}
[[Category:Anti-Christianity| ]]
[[Category:Persecution of Christians| ]]
[[Category:Persecution by Muslims]]

[[ar:اضطهاد المسيحيين]]
[[ca:Persecució dels cristians]]
[[cs:Pronásledování křesťanů]]
[[da:Kristenforfølgelse]]
[[de:Christenverfolgung]]
[[es:Persecución a los cristianos]]
[[eo:Persekutado de Kristanoj]]
[[fr:Persécutions des chrétiens]]
[[fy:Kristenferfolging]]
[[hr:Progoni kršćana]]
[[id:Penganiayaan terhadap orang Kristen]]
[[it:Persecuzione dei cristiani]]
[[la:Persecutio Christianorum]]
[[nl:Christenvervolgingen]]
[[pl:Prześladowania chrześcijan]]
[[pt:Perseguição aos cristãos]]
[[simple:Persecution of Christians]]
[[ckb:چەوساندنەوەی مەسیحییەکان]]
[[sh:Progoni kršćana]]
[[fi:Kristittyjen vainot]]
[[te:క్రైస్తవులపై అకృత్యాలు]]
[[th:การเบียดเบียนคริสต์ศาสนิกชน]]</text>
      <sha1>ktz0v2anrwc88ie8qyjy420l5wofjzx</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
