<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Philosophy of religion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23003</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520174967</id>
      <parentid>520173745</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T22:17:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JimWae</username>
        <id>61906</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>sacred language is an &quot;entire language&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24915">{{Multiple issues
 | refimprove=October 2008
 | original research=October 2008
 | essay=September 2011
}}
{{Philosophy of religion (sidebar)}}
'''Philosophy of religion''' is a branch of [[philosophy]] concerned with questions regarding [[religion]], including the nature and [[existence of God]], the examination of religious experience, analysis of religious vocabulary and texts, and the relationship of [[religion and science]].&lt;ref&gt;Alston, William P. &quot;Problems of Philosophy of Religion.&quot; Encyclopedia of Philosophy. New York: Macmillan Publishing Co., 1967.&lt;/ref&gt;  It is an ancient discipline, being found in the earliest known [[manuscripts]] concerning philosophy, and relates to many other branches of philosophy and general thought, including [[metaphysics]], [[logic]], and [[history]].&lt;ref&gt;Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, [http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/philosophy-religion/#FieSig &quot;Philosophy of Religion.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Philosophy of religion is frequently discussed outside of [[academia]] through popular books and debates, mostly regarding the existence of God and [[problem of evil]].

The philosophy of religion differs from [[religious philosophy]] in that it seeks to discuss questions regarding the nature of religion as a whole, rather than examining the problems brought forth by a particular belief system. It is designed such that it can be carried out dispassionately by those who identify as [[religious belief|believers]] or non-believers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Evans|first=C. Stephen|title=Philosophy of Religion: Thinking about Faith|publisher=InterVarsity Press|year=1985|pages=16|isbn=0-87784-343-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==As a part of metaphysics==
[[Image:Aristotle.jpg|thumb|100px|Aristotle]]
Philosophy of religion has classically been regarded as a part of metaphysics. In [[Aristotle]]'s ''Metaphysics'', he described [[Primum movens|first causes]] as one of the subjects of his investigation. For Aristotle, ''the'' first cause was the [[Aristotle#Aristotle.27s Four Causes|unmoved mover]], a being which set the universe into motion without itself being in motion,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abu.nb.ca/courses/grphil/philrel/aristotle.htm Aristotle], Professor Barry D. Smith, Crandall University&lt;/ref&gt; which has been read as God, particularly when Aristotle's work became prevalent again in the Medieval West. This Prime Mover, first cause, argument later came to be called [[natural theology]] by [[rationalism|rationalist]] philosophers of the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. Today, philosophers have adopted the term ''philosophy of religion'' for the subject, and typically it is regarded as a separate field of specialization, although it is also still treated by some, particularly [[Catholicism|Catholic]] [[philosopher]]s, as a part of metaphysics.

In the historical relationship between metaphysics and philosophy of religion, the traditional objects of religious discussion have been very special sorts of entities (such as gods, angels, supernatural forces, and the like) and events, abilities, or processes (the creation of the universe, the ability to do or know anything, interaction between humans and gods, and so forth). Metaphysicians (and [[ontology|ontologists]] in particular) are focused on understanding what it is for something to ''exist'' — what it is for something to be an entity, event, ability, or process. Because many members of religious traditions believe in things that exist in profoundly different ways from more everyday things, objects of religious belief both create particular philosophical problems and define central metaphysical concepts.

==Questions asked==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2011}}
[[Image:Kierkegaard.jpg|thumb|100px|Kierkegaard]]
[[Theology|Theologians]], distinct from philosophers of religion, often consider the existence of God as [[axiomatic]] or self-evident and explain, justify or support religious claims by rationalization or [[intuition (philosophy)|intuitive]] metaphors. In contrast, philosophers of religion examine and critique the epistemological, logical, aesthetic and ethical foundations inherent in the claims of a religion. Whereas a theologian elaborates  rationally or experientially on the nature of God, a philosopher of religion is more interested in asking what may be knowable and opinable regarding religion's claims.{{cn|date=May 2012}}

Other questions studied in the philosophy of religion include what, if anything, would give us good reason to believe that a miracle has occurred, what is the relationship between faith and reason, what is the relationship between morality and religion, what is the status of religious language, and does petitionary prayer (sometimes still called ''impetratory prayer'') make sense?

Going beyond metaphysics, the philosophy of religion also addresses questions in areas such as [[epistemology]], [[philosophy of language]], [[philosophical logic]], and [[moral philosophy]]. See also [[world view]].

==What is God?==
[[File:Religious syms.svg|thumb|250px|Religious symbols, from left to right:&lt;br /&gt;row 1: [[Christianity]], [[Judaism]], [[Hinduism]]&lt;br /&gt;row 2: [[Islam]], [[Buddhism]], [[Shinto]]&lt;/br /&gt;row 3: [[Sikhism]], [[Bahai]], [[Jainism]]]]
Among those who believe in supernatural beings, some believe there is just one God ([[monotheism]]), while others, such as [[Hinduism|Hindus]], believe in many different deities ([[polytheism]]) while maintaining that all are manifestations of one God. Hindus have a widely followed monistic philosophy that can be said to be neither [[Advaita Vedanta|monotheistic nor polytheistic]]. Within these two broad categories (monotheism and polytheism) there is a wide variety of possible beliefs. For example, among the monotheists [[Deism|deists]] believe that the one God is like a watchmaker who wound up the universe and does not intervene further in the universe, and some [[Theism|theists]] believe that God continues to be active in the universe. [[Ignosticism|Ignostics]] object that a coherent definition of God must be presented before the question of the existence of God can be meaningfully discussed. 

Buddhism deals less with metaphysics and more with ontological questions and is generally not concerned with the existence of a creator God but focuses on a state called [[Nirvana (concept)|Nirvana]] (see also [[Mu (negative)|Mu]]).

==Rationality of belief==
{{Main|Existence of God}}
[[Image:St-thomas-aquinas.jpg|thumb|100px|Aquinas]]

===Positions===
The second question, &quot;Do we have any good reason to think that God does or does not exist?&quot;, is equally important in the philosophy of religion. There are several main positions with regard to the existence of God that one might take:

#  [[Theism]] - the belief in the existence of one or more divinities or deities.
##  [[Pantheism]] - the belief that God exists ''as'' all things of the cosmos, that God is one and all is God; God is immanent.
##  [[Panentheism]] - the belief that God encompasses all things of the cosmos but that God is greater than the cosmos; God is both immanent and transcendent.
##  [[Deism]] - the belief that God does exist but does not interfere with human life and the laws of the universe; God is transcendent.
##  [[Monotheism]] - the belief that a single deity exists which rules the universe as a separate and individual entity.
##  [[Polytheism]] - the belief that multiple deities exist which rule the universe as separate and individual entities.
##  [[Henotheism]] - the belief that multiple deities may or may not exist, though there is a single supreme deity.
##  [[Henology]] - believing that multiple avatars of a deity exist, which represent unique aspects of the ultimate deity.
#  [[Agnosticism]] - the belief that the existence or non-existence of deities is currently unknown or unknowable, or that the existence of a God or of gods cannot be proven.
#  [[Atheism]] - the rejection of [[belief]] in the [[Existence of God|existence of deities]].&lt;ref name=ref1/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ref2&quot;/&gt;
##[[Strong atheism]] is specifically the position that there are no [[deity|deities]].&lt;ref name=RoweRoutledge/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;about_atheism_strong_weak&quot;/&gt;
##[[Weak atheism]] is simply the absence of belief that any deities exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;about_atheism_strong_weak&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=religioustolerance/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;dagobert&quot;/&gt;

There are not mutually exclusive positions.  For example, [[agnostic theism|agnostic theists]] choose to believe God exists while asserting that knowledge of God's existence is inherently unknowable.  Similarly, [[agnostic atheism|agnostic atheists]] reject belief in the existence of all deities, while asserting that whether any such entities exist or not is inherently unknowable.

===Natural theology===
The attempt to provide proofs or arguments for the existence of God is one aspect of what is known as ''natural theology'' or the ''natural theistic project''.  This strand of natural theology attempts to justify belief in God by independent grounds. There is plenty of philosophical literature on faith (especially [[fideism]]) and other subjects generally considered to be outside the realm of natural theology.  Perhaps most of philosophy of religion is predicated on natural theology's assumption that the existence of God can be justified or warranted on rational grounds.  There has been considerable philosophical and theological debate about the kinds of proofs, justifications and arguments that are appropriate for this discourse.&lt;ref&gt;see eg [[Antony Flew]], [[John Polkinghorne]], [[Keith Ward]] and [[Richard Swinburne]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The philosopher [[Alvin Plantinga]] has shifted his focus to justifying belief in God (that is, those who believe in God, for whatever reasons, are rational in doing so) through [[Reformed epistemology]], in the context of a theory of warrant and proper cognitive function.

Other reactions to natural theology are those of Wittgensteinian philosophers of religion, most notably [[D. Z. Phillips]]. Phillips rejects &quot;natural theology&quot; and its evidentialist approach as confused, in favor of a grammatical approach which investigates the meaning of belief in God. For Phillips, belief in God is not a proposition with a particular [[truth value]], but a form of life.  Consequently, the question of whether God exists confuses the logical categories which govern theistic language with those that govern other forms of discourse (most notably, scientific discourse).  According to Phillips, the question of whether or not God exists cannot be &quot;objectively&quot; answered by philosophy because the categories of truth and falsity, which are necessary for asking the question, have no application in the religious contexts wherein religious belief has its sense and meaning. In other words, the question cannot be answered because it cannot be asked without entering into confusion. As Phillips sees things, the job of the philosopher is not to investigate the &quot;rationality&quot; of belief in God but to elucidate its meaning.

===Analytic philosophy of religion===
As with the study of ethics, early analytic philosophy tended to avoid the study of philosophy of religion, largely dismissing (as per the logical positivists view) the subject as part of metaphysics and therefore meaningless.&lt;ref&gt;(a notable exception is the series of [[Michael Foster (philosopher)|Michael B. Forest]]'s 1934-36 [[Mind (journal)|''Mind'' articles involving the Christian doctrine of creation and the rise of modern science).]]&lt;/ref&gt;  The collapse of [[logical positivism]] renewed interest in philosophy of religion, prompting philosophers like [[William Alston]], [[J. L. Mackie|John Mackie]], Alvin Plantinga, [[Robert Merrihew Adams]], Richard Swinburne, and Antony Flew not only to introduce new problems, but to re-open classical topics such as the nature of [[miracle]]s, theistic arguments, the problem of evil, (see [[existence of God]]) the rationality of belief in [[God]], concepts of the nature of God, and many more.&lt;ref&gt;Peterson, Michael et al. (2003). ''Reason and Religious Belief''&lt;/ref&gt;

Plantinga, Mackie and Flew debated the logical validity of the ''free will defense'' as a way to solve the problem of evil.&lt;ref&gt;Mackie, John L. (1982). ''The Miracle of Theism: Arguments For and Against the Existence of God''&lt;/ref&gt; Alston, grappling with the consequences of analytic philosophy of language, worked on the nature of religious language. Adams worked on the relationship of faith and morality.&lt;ref&gt;Adams, Robert M. (1987). ''The Virtue of Faith And Other Essays in Philosophical Theology''&lt;/ref&gt; Analytic epistemology and metaphysics has formed the basis for a number of philosophically-sophisticated theistic arguments, like those of the [[reformed epistemology|reformed epistemologists]] like Plantinga.

Analytic philosophy of religion has also been preoccupied with [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], as well as his interpretation of [[Søren Kierkegaard]]'s philosophy of religion.&lt;ref&gt;Creegan, Charles. (1989). ''Wittgenstein and Kierkegaard: Religion, Individuality and Philosophical Method''&lt;/ref&gt; Using first-hand remarks (which would later be published in ''[[Philosophical Investigations]]'', ''Culture and Value'', and other works), philosophers such as [[Peter Winch]] and [[Norman Malcolm]] developed what has come to be known as ''contemplative philosophy'', a Wittgensteinian school of thought rooted in the &quot;Swansea tradition&quot; and which includes Wittgensteinians such as [[Rush Rhees]], Peter Winch and D. Z. Phillips, among others. The name &quot;contemplative philosophy&quot; was first coined by D. Z. Phillips in ''Philosophy's Cool Place'', which rests on an interpretation of a passage from Wittgenstein's &quot;Culture and Value.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, D. Z. (1999). ''Philosophy's Cool Place.'' Cornell University Press. The quote is from Wittgenstein's ''Culture and Value'' (2e): &quot;My ideal is a certain coolness. A temple providing a setting for the passions without meddling with them.''&lt;/ref&gt; This interpretation was first labeled, &quot;Wittgensteinian Fideism,&quot; by Kai Nielsen but those who consider themselves Wittgensteinians in the Swansea tradition have relentlessly and repeatedly rejected this construal as caricature of Wittgenstein's considered position; this is especially true of D. Z. Phillips.&lt;ref&gt;{{sep entry|fideism|Fideism}}&lt;/ref&gt; Responding to this interpretation, [[Kai Nielsen (philosopher)|Kai Nielsen]] and [[D.Z. Phillips]] became two of the most prominent philosophers on Wittgenstein's philosophy of religion.&lt;ref&gt;Nielsen, Kai and D.Z. Phillips. (2005). ''Wittgensteinian Fideism?''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Problem of evil==
{{Main|The problem of evil|Theodicy}}

==Major philosophers of religion==
{{Main|List of philosophers of religion}}
&lt;!--

&quot;The burden of evidence lies with the editor who adds or restores material. All quotations and any material challenged or likely to be challenged must be attributed to a reliable, published source using an inline citation.&quot; - [[wp:v]]

{|width=100%
|-valign=top
|width=33%|
*[[Abhinavagupta]]
*[[Adi Shankara]]
*[[Avicenna]] (also known as Ibn Sina)
*[[Ramanuja]]
*[[Madhvacharya]]
*[[Marilyn McCord Adams]]
*[[Robert Merrihew Adams|Robert Adams]]
*[[William Alston]]
*[[Anselm of Canterbury]]
*[[Averroes]] (also known as Ibn Rushd)
*[[Thomas Aquinas]]
*[[Augustine of Hippo]]
*[[Anicius Manlius Severinus Boethius]]
*[[Giordano Bruno]]
*[[Joseph Butler]]
*[[Gordon Clark]]
*[[Samuel Clarke]]
*[[Sarah Coakley]]
*[[Lady Anne Finch Conway|Anne Conway]]
*[[William Lane Craig]]
*[[René Descartes]]
*[[Pseudo-Dionysius]]
*[[Herman Dooyeweerd]]
*[[Paul Draper (philosopher)|Paul Draper]]
*[[Mircea Eliade]]
*[[Erasmus|Desiderius Erasmus]]
*[[Al-Farabi]] (also known as Alpharabius)
*[[Siddartha Gautama]]
*[[Confucius]]
*[[Lao Tzu]]
*[[Al Ghazali]] (also known as Algazel)
*[[Yehuda Halevi]]
*[[Charles Hartshorne]]
*[[Ibn al-Haytham]] (also known as Alhazen)
*[[Heraclitus]]
*[[John Hick]]
*[[Mohamed Osman Elkhosht]]
*[[David Hume]]
|width=33%|
*[[Peter van Inwagen]]
*[[Iqbal|Allama Iqbal]]
*[[William James]]
*[[Immanuel Kant]]
*[[Walter Kaufmann (philosopher)|Walter Kaufmann]]
*[[Anthony Kenny]]
*[[Ibn Khaldun]]
*[[Marcus Borg]]
*[[Søren Kierkegaard]]
*[[Al-Kindi]] (also known as Alkindus)
*[[Nishida Kitaro]]
*[[Ruhollah Khomeini]]
*[[Nishitani Keiji]]
*[[Harold Kushner]]
*[[Swami Krishnananda]]
*[[C. S. Lewis]]
*[[Gottfried Leibniz]]
*[[Knud Ejler Løgstrup]]
*[[J. L. Mackie]]
*[[Maimonides]]
*[[Nicolas Malebranche]]
*[[Jean-Luc Marion]]
*[[Michael Martin (philosopher)|Michael Martin]]
*[[Herbert McCabe]]
*[[Alister E. McGrath]]
*[[Thomas V. Morris]]
*[[Nagarjuna]]
*[[Milarepa]]
*[[Dogen|Dogen Zenji]]
*[[Ibn al-Nafis]]
*[[Friedrich Nietzsche]]
*[[William of Ockham]]
*[[Rudolph Otto]]
*[[William Paley]]
*[[Blaise Pascal]]
*[[D. Z. Phillips]]
|width=33%|
*[[Philo of Alexandria]]
*[[Alvin Plantinga]]
*[[Plotinus]]
*[[John Polkinghorne]]
*[[Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan]]
*[[Fakhr al-Din al-Razi]]
*[[William L. Rowe]]
*[[Bertrand Russell]]
*[[Mulla Sadra]]
*[[Duns Scotus]]
*[[Swami Sivananda]]
*[[Ninian Smart]]
*[[Abdolkarim Soroush]]
*[[Baruch Spinoza]]
*[[Melville Y. Stewart]]
*[[Shahab al-Din Suhrawardi]]
*[[Richard Swinburne]]
*[[Denys Turner]]
*[[Peter Vardy]]
*[[Vasubandhu]]
*[[Keith Ward]]
*[[William Whewell]]
*[[Nicholas Wolterstorff]]
*[[Keith Yandell]]
*[[Ramakrishna]]
*[[Vivekananda]]
*[[René Guénon]]
*[[René Girard]]
*[[Frithjof Schuon]]
*[[Hossein Nasr|Seyyed Hossein Nasr]]
*[[Friedrich Wilhelm Joseph Schelling|F.W.J. Schelling]]
*[[Paul Tillich]]
*[[Ahmad Rafique]]
*[[Ibn Arabi]]
*[[Zarathustra]]
|}
--&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Philosophy|Religion}}
*[[Comparative theology]]
* [[Evolutionary origin of religions]]
* [[Evolutionary psychology of religion]]
* [[Issues in Science and Religion]]
* [[Major world religions]]
* [[Theodicy]]
* [[Theology]]
* [[Theories of religion]]
* [[Worldview]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2|refs=
&lt;ref name=ref1&gt;
{{Cite encyclopedia |first=Kai |last=Nielsen |authorlink=Kai Nielsen (philosopher) |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]] |title=Atheism |url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/40634/atheism |year=2010 |quote=Atheism, in general, the critique and denial of metaphysical beliefs in God or spiritual beings.... Instead of saying that an atheist is someone who believes that it is false or probably false that there is a God, a more adequate characterization of atheism consists in the more complex claim that to be an atheist is to be someone who rejects belief in God for the following reasons (which reason is stressed depends on how God is being conceived)... | accessdate=2011-04-09 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=ref2&gt;
{{Cite encyclopedia |title=Atheism |first=Paul |last=Edwards |authorlink=Paul Edwards (philosopher) |publisher=MacMillan Reference USA (Gale)|editor=Donald M. Borchert |origyear=1967 |year=2005 |edition=2nd |encyclopedia=[[Encyclopedia of Philosophy|The Encyclopedia of Philosophy]] |volume=Vol. 1 |page=359 |isbn=978-0-02-865780-6 |quote=On our definition, an 'atheist' is a person who rejects belief in God, regardless of whether or not his reason for the rejection is the claim that 'God exists' expresses a false proposition. People frequently adopt an attitude of rejection toward a position for reasons other than that it is a false proposition. It is common among contemporary philosophers, and indeed it was not uncommon in earlier centuries, to reject positions on the ground that they are meaningless. Sometimes, too, a theory is rejected on such grounds as that it is sterile or redundant or capricious, and there are many other considerations which in certain contexts are generally agreed to constitute good grounds for rejecting an assertion. |ref=harv}}(page 175 in 1967 edition)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=RoweRoutledge&gt;
{{cite encyclopedia
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=lnuwFH_M5o0C&amp;pg=PA530&amp;lpg=PA530&amp;dq=atheism+routledge#v=onepage&amp;q=atheism%20routledge&amp;f=false |first=William L. |last=Rowe |authorlink=William L. Rowe |encyclopedia=[[Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy]] |title=Atheism |year=1998 |editor=Edward Craig | isbn=978-0-415-07310-3 | publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis
|quote=As commonly understood, atheism is the position that affirms the nonexistence of God. So an atheist is someone who disbelieves in God, whereas a theist is someone who believes in God. Another meaning of &quot;atheism&quot; is simply nonbelief in the existence of God, rather than positive belief in the nonexistence of God. ...an atheist, in the broader sense of the term, is someone who disbelieves in every form of deity, not just the God of traditional Western theology.
| accessdate=2011-04-09
|ref=harv}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=religioustolerance&gt;[[Religioustolerance.org]]'s short article on [http://www.religioustolerance.org/atheist4.htm Definitions of the term &quot;Atheism&quot;] suggests that there is no consensus on the definition of the term. [[Simon Blackburn]] summarizes the situation in [[The Oxford Dictionary of Philosophy]]: &quot;Atheism. Either the lack of belief in a god, or the belief that there is none&quot;. Most dictionaries (see the OneLook query for [http://www.onelook.com/?w=atheism&amp;ls=a &quot;atheism&quot;]) first list one of the more narrow definitions.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;dagobert&quot;&gt;
{{Cite book |url=http://www.ditext.com/runes/a.html |title=Dictionary of Philosophy |first=Dagobert D.(editor) |last=Runes |authorlink=Dagobert D. Runes |year=1942 edition |publisher=Littlefield, Adams &amp; Co. Philosophical Library |location=New Jersey |isbn=0-06-463461-2 |quote=(a) the belief that there is no God; (b) Some philosophers have been called &quot;atheistic&quot; because they have not held to a belief in a personal God. Atheism in this sense means &quot;not theistic&quot;. The former meaning of the term is a literal rendering. The latter meaning is a less rigorous use of the term though widely current in the history of thought | accessdate=2011-04-09}} – entry by [[Vergilius Ferm]]
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;about_atheism_strong_weak&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|last=Cline |first=Austin |title=Strong Atheism vs. Weak Atheism: What's the Difference? |url=http://atheism.about.com/od/atheismquestions/a/strong_weak.htm |year=2006 |publisher=[[about.com]] | accessdate=2011-04-09}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Further reading==
*''Al-Nawawi Forty Hadiths and Commentary'', by Arabic Virtual Translation Center; (2010) ISBN 978-1-4563-6735-0 (Philosophy of Religion from an Islamic Point of View)
* The [http://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/LPSG/ London Philosophy Study Guide] offers many suggestions on what to read, depending on the student's familiarity with the subject: [http://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/LPSG/Religion.htm Philosophy of Religion]
* William L. Rowe, William J. Wainwright, ''Philosophy of Religion: Selected Readings,'' Third Ed.  (Florida: Harcourt Brace &amp; Company, 1998)
* [http://www.journals.cambridge.org/res Religious Studies] is an international journal for the philosophy of religion. It is available online and in print and has a fully searchable online archive dating back to Issue 1 in 1965. It currently publishes four issues per year.

==External links==
*{{PhilPapers|category|philosophy-of-religion}}
*{{InPho|taxonomy|2425}}
*{{SEP|philosophy-religion}}
*{{IEP|category/m-and-e/religion/}}
* [http://advertadam.blogspot.com/2011/02/religion-or-mythology.html Religion or Mythology'''?!!!''']
* [http://www.galilean-library.org/manuscript.php?postid=43793 An introduction to the Philosophy of Religion] by Paul Newall.
* [http://users.ox.ac.uk/~worc0337/phil_topics_religion.html Philosophy of Religion] Useful annotated index of religious philosophy topics.
* [http://www.philosophyofreligion.info/ Philosophy of Religion .Info] Introductory articles on philosophical arguments for and against theism.
* [http://www.csu.edu.au/research/apra/ The Australasian Philosophy of Religion Association]

{{Religion topics}}
{{philosophy of religion|state=expanded}}
{{Philosophy topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Philosophy Of Religion}}
[[Category:Philosophy of religion| ]]
[[Category:Philosophy by field|Rel]]

[[ar:فلسفة الدين]]
[[az:Din fəlsəfəsi]]
[[cs:Filosofie náboženství]]
[[da:Religionsfilosofi]]
[[de:Religionsphilosophie]]
[[et:Religioonifilosoofia]]
[[es:Filosofía de la religión]]
[[fa:فلسفه دین]]
[[fr:Philosophie de la religion]]
[[hr:Filozofija religije]]
[[is:Trúarheimspeki]]
[[it:Filosofia della religione]]
[[he:פילוסופיה של הדת]]
[[hu:Vallásfilozófia]]
[[mk:Филозофија на религијата]]
[[mn:Шашны философи]]
[[nl:Godsdienstfilosofie]]
[[ja:宗教哲学]]
[[no:Religionsfilosofi]]
[[pl:Filozofia religii]]
[[pt:Filosofia da religião]]
[[ru:Философия религии]]
[[simple:Philosophy of religion]]
[[sk:Filozofia náboženstva]]
[[sr:Филозофија религије]]
[[sh:Filozofija religije]]
[[fi:Uskonnonfilosofia]]
[[sv:Religionsfilosofi]]
[[tr:Din felsefesi]]
[[uk:Філософія релігії]]
[[zh:宗教哲学]]</text>
      <sha1>e3jf5tnafmm1q7jiywcflmq5zh9iixl</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
