<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pietism</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>180781</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515513797</id>
      <parentid>510376620</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-01T19:51:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Artimaean</username>
        <id>9045306</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* See also */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22463">[[File:Philipp Jacob Spener.jpg|thumb|240px|[[Philipp Jakob Spener]] (1635–1705) known as the &quot;Father of Pietism&quot;.]]

'''Pietism''' (from the word [[piety]]) was a movement within [[Lutheranism]], lasting from the late 17th century to the mid-18th century and later. It proved to be very influential throughout [[Protestantism]] and [[Anabaptist|Anabaptism]], inspiring [[Anglicanism|Anglican]] priest [[John Wesley]] to begin the [[Methodism|Methodist movement]] and [[Alexander Mack]] to begin the [[Schwarzenau Brethren|Brethren]] movement. The Pietist movement combined the Lutheranism of the time with the [[Calvinism|Reformed]] emphasis on individual piety and living a vigorous [[Christianity|Christian]] life.&lt;ref&gt;In places, such as parts of England and America, where pietism was frequently juxtaposed with [[Roman Catholicism]], Catholics also became naturally influenced by pietism, helping to foster a stronger tradition of congregational hymn-singing, including among pietists who converted to Catholicism and brought their pietistic inclination with them, such as [[Frederick William Faber]].&lt;/ref&gt;  Though pietism shares an emphasis on personal behavior with the [[Puritan]] movement, and the two are often confused, there are important differences, particularly in the concept of the role of religion in government.&lt;ref&gt;Calvinist Puritans believed that government was ordained by God to enforce Christian behavior upon the world; pietists see the government as a part of the world, and believers were called to voluntarily live faithful lives independent of government.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forerunners==
{{lutheranism}}
As forerunners of the Pietists in the strict sense, certain voices had been heard bewailing the shortcomings of the Church and advocating a revival of practical and devout Christianity. Amongst them were [[Christian mysticism|Christian mystic]] [[Jakob Böhme]] (Behmen); [[Johann Arndt]], whose work, ''True Christianity'', became widely known and appreciated; [[Heinrich Müller (theologian)|Heinrich Müller]], who described the [[baptismal font|font]], the [[pulpit]], the [[Confession (religion)|confession]]al and the [[altar]] as &quot;the four dumb idols of the Lutheran Church&quot;; theologian [[Johann Valentin Andrea]], court chaplain of the landgrave of Hesse; [[Schuppius]], who sought to restore to the Bible its place in the pulpit; and [[Theophilus Grossgebauer]] (d. 1661) of Rostock, who from his pulpit and by his writings raised what he called &quot;the alarm cry of a watchman in [[Zion|Sion]].&quot;

{{17th Century Scholasticism}}

===Founding===
The direct originator of the movement was [[Philipp Jakob Spener]]. Born at Rappoltsweiler in [[Alsace]], France on 13 January 1635, trained by a devout godmother who used books of devotion like Arndt's ''True Christianity'', Spener was convinced of the necessity of a moral and religious reformation within German Lutheranism. He studied theology at [[Strasbourg]], where the professors at the time (and especially Sebastian Schmidt) were more inclined to &quot;practical&quot; Christianity than to theological disputation. He afterwards spent a year in [[Geneva]], and was powerfully influenced by the strict moral life and rigid ecclesiastical discipline prevalent there, and also by the preaching and the piety of the [[Waldensian]] professor Antoine Leger and the converted [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] preacher [[Jean de Labadie]].

During a stay in [[Tübingen]], Spener read Grossgebauer's ''Alarm Cry'', and in 1666 he entered upon his first pastoral charge at [[Frankfurt]] with a profound opinion that the Christian life within Evangelical Lutheranism was being sacrificed to zeal for rigid [[Lutheran orthodoxy]]. Pietism, as a distinct movement in the German Church, was then originated by Spener by religious meetings at his house (''collegia pietatis'') at which he repeated his sermons, expounded passages of the [[New Testament]], and induced those present to join in conversation on religious questions that arose.  In 1675 Spener published his ''Pia desideria'' or ''Earnest Desire for a Reform of the True Evangelical Church'', the title giving rise to the term &quot;Pietists&quot;.  This 
was originally a pejorative term given to the adherents of the movement by its enemies as a form of ridicule, like that of &quot;Methodists&quot; somewhat later in England.

In ''Pia desideria'', Spener made six proposals as the best means of restoring the life of the Church:

#the earnest and thorough study of the Bible in private meetings, ''ecclesiolae in ecclesia'' (''&quot;little churches within the church&quot;'').
#the Christian priesthood being universal, the laity should share in the spiritual government of the Church
#a knowledge of Christianity must be attended by the practice of it as its indispensable sign and supplement
#instead of merely didactic, and often bitter, attacks on the heterodox and unbelievers, a sympathetic and kindly treatment of them
#a reorganization of the theological training of the universities, giving more prominence to the devotional life
#a different style of preaching, namely, in the place of pleasing rhetoric, the implanting of Christianity in the inner or new man, the soul of which is faith, and its effects the fruits of life.

This work produced a great impression throughout Germany, and although large numbers of the [[Lutheran Orthodoxy|orthodox Lutheran]] theologians and pastors were deeply offended by Spener's book, its complaints and its demands were both too well justified to admit of their being point-blank denied.{{cn|date=September 2012}} A large number of pastors immediately adopted Spener's proposals.

===Early leaders===
[[File:A Tidemand-Haugianerne.jpg|thumb|[[Haugean]] Pietist [[Conventicle]]. Painting by [[Adolph Tidemand]], 1852]]
In 1686 Spener accepted an appointment to the court-chaplaincy at [[Dresden]], which opened to him a wider though more difficult sphere of labor. In [[Leipzig]] a society of young theologians was formed under his influence for the learned study and devout application of the Bible. Three magistrates belonging to that society, one of whom was [[August Hermann Francke]], subsequently the founder of the famous orphanage at [[Halle, Saxony-Anhalt|Halle]] (1695), commenced courses of expository lectures on the Scriptures of a practical and devotional character, and in the [[German language]], which were zealously frequented by both students and townsmen. The lectures aroused, however, the ill-will of the other theologians and pastors of Leipzig, and Francke and his friends left the city, and with the aid of [[Christian Thomasius]] and Spener founded the new [[University of Halle]]. The theological chairs in the new university were filled in complete conformity with Spener's proposals. The main difference between the new Pietistic Lutheran school and the orthodox Lutherans arose from the Pietists' conception of Christianity as chiefly consisting in a change of heart and consequent holiness of life. Orthodox Lutherans rejected this viewpoint as a gross simplification, stressing the need for the church and for sound theological underpinnings. 

Spener died in 1705; but, the movement, guided by Francke, fertilized from Halle the whole of Middle and North Germany. Among its greatest achievements, apart from the philanthropic institutions founded at Halle, were the revival of the [[Moravian Church]] in 1727 by [[Nicolaus Ludwig Zinzendorf|Count von Zinzendorf]], Spener's godson and a pupil in the Halle School for Young Noblemen, and the establishment of Protestant missions.
{{USALutherans}}
Spener's stress on the necessity of a new birth and on a separation of Christians from the world, (see [[Asceticism]]), led to exaggeration and fanaticism among some followers.  Many Pietists soon maintained that the new birth must always be preceded by agonies of repentance, and that only a regenerated theologian could teach theology, while the whole school shunned all common worldly amusements, such as dancing, the theatre, and public games. Some would say that there thus arose a new form of justification by works.  Its ''ecclesiolae in ecclesia'' also weakened the power and meaning of church organization. Through these extravagances a reactionary movement arose at the beginning of the 18th century; one leader was [[Valentin Ernst Löscher]],  [[Superintendent (ecclesiastical)|superintendent]] at Dresden.

===Later history===
[[File:Der breite und der schmale Weg 2008.jpg|thumb|''The Broad and the Narrow Way'', a popular German Pietist painting, 1866]]
As a distinct movement, Pietism had its greatest strength by the middle of the 18th century;  its very individualism in fact helped to prepare the way for the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] (''Aufklärung''), which would take the church in an altogether different direction.  Yet some would claim that Pietism contributed largely to the revival of Biblical studies in Germany and to making religion once more an affair of the heart and of life and not merely of the intellect.  It likewise gave a new emphasis on the role of the laity in the church.  Rudolf Sohm claimed that &quot;It was the last great surge of the waves of the ecclesiastical movement begun by the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]]; it was the completion and the final form of the Protestantism created by the Reformation. Then came a time when another intellectual power took possession of the minds of men.&quot; [[Dietrich Bonhoeffer]] of the German [[Confessing Church]] framed the same characterization in less positive terms when he called Pietism the last attempt to save Christianity as a religion:  Given that for him religion was a negative term, more or less an opposite to [[revelation]], this constitutes a rather scathing judgment.  Bonhoeffer denounced the basic aim of Pietism, to produce a &quot;desired piety&quot; in a person, as unbiblical.

Pietism is considered the major influence that lead to the creation of the &quot;[[Prussian Union (Evangelical Christian Church)|Evangelical Church of the Union]]&quot; in [[Prussia]] in 1817.  The King of Prussia ordered the Lutheran and Reformed churches in Prussia to unite; they took the name &quot;Evangelical&quot; as a name both groups had previously identified with.  This union movement spread through many German lands in the 1800s.  Pietism, with its looser attitude toward confessional theology, had opened the churches to the possibility of uniting. The unification of the two branches of German Protestantism sparked the [[Prussian_Union_(Evangelical_Christian_Church)#Quarrels_over_the_Union|Schism of the Old Lutherans]]. Many Lutherans, called [[Old Lutherans]] formed [[free church]]es or immigrated to the United States and [[Australia]] where they formed one of the bodies who formed the [[Lutheran Church of Australia]].  (Many immigrants to America that agreed with the union movement formed German Evangelical Lutheran and Reformed congregations, later to be gathered as the [[Evangelical Synod of North America]], which is now a part of the [[United Church of Christ]].)

Pietism was a major influence on [[John Wesley]] and others who began the [[Methodism|Methodist movement]] in 18th century [[Great Britain]]. John Wesley was influenced significantly by Moravians (e.g., [[Zinzendorf]], [[Peter Boehler]]) and Pietists connected to Francke and Halle Pietism. The fruit of these Pietist influences can be seen in the modern [[United Methodist Church|American Methodists]] and members of the [[Holiness movement]]. 

Pietism did not die out in the 18th century, but was alive and active in the Evangelischer Kirchenverein des Westens (later [[Evangelical Church in Germany|German Evangelical Church]] and still later the Evangelical and [[Reformed churches|Reformed Church]].) The church president from 1901 to 1914 was a pietist named Dr. Jakob Pister. A discussion of some of the earlier pietist influence in the Evangelical and Reformed church can be found in Dunn et al., &quot;A History of the Evangelical and Reformed Church&quot; Christian Education Press, Philadelphia, 1962. Further commentary can be found by Rev. Dr. Carl Viehe under Pietism, Illinois Trails, Washington County. Some vestiges of Pietism were still present in 1957 at the time of the formation of the United Church of Christ.

However, in the 19th century, there was a revival of confessional Lutheran doctrine, known as the [[Neo-Lutheranism|neo-Lutheran]] movement. This movement focused on a reassertion of the identity of Lutherans as a distinct group within the broader community of [[Christianity|Christians]], with a renewed focus on the [[Book of Concord|Lutheran Confessions]] as a key source of Lutheran doctrine. Associated with these changes was a renewed focus on traditional doctrine and liturgy, which paralleled the growth of [[Anglo-Catholicism]] in England.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Scherer, James A. | title= The Triumph of Confessionalism in Nineteenth-Century German Lutheran Missions | journal=Missio Apostolica | year=1993 | volume=2 | pages= 71–78 | url=http://www.lsfmissiology.org/Essays/SchererTriumphofConfessionalism.pdf | format= }} {{dead link|date=March 2010}} This is an extract from Scherer's 1968 Ph.D. thesis, &quot;Mission and Unity in Lutheranism&quot;. Scherer was Professor of World Mission and Church History at the Lutheran School of Theology at Chicago until his retirement.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some writers on the history of Pietism – e.g. Heppe and [[Albrecht Ritschl|Ritschl]] – have included under it nearly all religious tendencies amongst Protestants of the last three centuries in the direction of a more serious cultivation of personal piety than that prevalent in the various established churches. Ritschl, too, treats Pietism as a retrograde movement of Christian life towards Catholicism. Some historians also speak of a later or modern Pietism, characterizing thereby a party in the German Church which was probably at first influenced by some remains of Spener's Pietism in [[Westphalia]], on the [[Rhine]], in [[Württemberg]], and at Halle and [[Berlin]].

The party was chiefly distinguished by its opposition to an independent scientific study of theology, its principal theological leader being Hengstenberg, and its chief literary organ the ''Evangelische Kirchenzeitung''.

Pietism also had a strong influence on contemporary artistic culture in Germany; though unread today, the Pietist [[Johann Georg Hamann]] held a strong influence in his day. Pietist belief in the power of individual meditation on the divine – a direct, individual approach to the ultimate spiritual reality of God – was probably partly responsible for the uniquely metaphysical, idealistic nature of German Romantic philosophy.

In modern societies where Pietism has had a profound impact its religious foundations are no longer apparent. '''Atheistic pietism''' is a term used by [[Asgeir Helgason]] to describe a pietistic (moralistic) approach to life without religion. “We have denied the existence of God but kept the pietistic rules”. Atheistic pietism has been suggested by Helgason,&lt;ref&gt;*[http://www.arh.blog.is/blog/arh/entry/164003 Ateistisk pietism]&lt;/ref&gt; to be one of the characteristics (traits) of the modern day Swedish national spirit. The term is first known to have been used by [[William Hurrell Mallock|W.H. Mallock]] in 1879.

Economic historian Murray Rothbard sees modern [[Progressivism]] as essentially a [[deistic]] form of Pietism. &lt;ref&gt;*[http://mises.org/daily/2225]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Radical Pietism===
{{main|Radical Pietism}}

Some of the primary leaders of Radical Pietism were:
* [[Gerhard Tersteegen]]
* [[Gottfried Arnold]]
* [[Hochmann von Hochenau]]

Also relevant is:
* The [[Berleburg Bible]]

===Reformed Pietism===
* [[Jean de Labadie]] and the [[Labadists]]
* [[Precisianist]]
* Federalists

===Württemberg Pietism===
* [[Otterbeins]]
* [[Johann Albrecht Bengel]]
* [[Friedrich Christoph Oetinger]]
* [[Blumhardts]]

===Descendants===
* [[Wesleyanism]]
* [[Methodism]]
* [[Evangelical Covenant Church]]
* [[Schwarzenau Brethren]]
* [[Holiness movement]]
* [[Pentecostalism]]

==See also==

{{multicol}}
* [[Adolf Köberle]]
* [[Barbara Juliana, Baroness von Krüdener]]
* [[Behmenism]]
* [[Carl Olof Rosenius]]
* [[Catholic Charismatic Renewal]]
* [[Church of the Brethren]]
* [[Erik Pontoppidan]]
* [[Evangelical Covenant Church]]
* [[Evangelical Free Church of America]]
* [[Friedrich Christoph Oetinger]]
* [[Friedrich Hölderlin]]
* [[George Rapp|Johann Georg Rapp]]
* [[Hans Adolph Brorson]]
* [[Hans Nielsen Hauge]]
* [[Haugean]]
* [[Johann Georg Hamann]]

{{multicol-break}}

* [[Harmony Society]]
* [[Henric Schartau]]
* [[Immanuel Kant]]
* [[Johann Albrecht Bengel]]
* [[Johann Conrad Dippel]]
* [[Johannes Kelpius]]
* [[Laestadianism]]
* [[Methodism]]
* [[Mission Covenant Church of Sweden]]
* [[Moravian Church]]
* [[Philipp Jakob Spener]]
* [[Theologia Germanica]]
* [[Wesleyanism]]
* [[Templers (religious believers)]]
* Nicolaus Ludwig, [[Count von Zinzendorf]]
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
Amongst older works on Pietism are 
*[[Johann Georg Walch|JG Walch]], ''Historische und theologische Einleitung in die Religionsstreitigkeiten der evangelisch-lutherischen Kirche'' (1730);
*[[Friedrich August Tholuck|A Tholuck]], ''Geschichte des Pietismus und des ersten Stadiums der Aufklärung'' (1865);
*[[Heinrich Schmid (theologian)|H Schmid]], ''Die Geschichte des Pietismus'' (1863);
*[[Max Goebel|M Goebel]], ''Geschichte des christlichen Lebens in der Rheinisch-Westfälischen Kirche'' (3 vols., 1849–1860).

The subject is dealt with at length in 
*[[Isaak August Dorner|JA Dorner]]'s and W Gass's ''Histories of Protestant theology''.

More recent are 
*[[Heinrich Heppe|Heppe]]'s ''Geschichte des Pietismus und der Mystik in der reformierten Kirche'' (1879), which is sympathetic;
*[[Albrecht Ritschl|A Ritschl]]'s ''Geschichte des Pietismus'' (5 vols., 1880–1886), which is hostile; and
*[[Eugen Sachsse|C Sachsse]], ''Ursprung und Wesen des Pietismus'' (1884).

See also 
*[[Friedrich Wilhelm Franz Nippold|Fr. Nippold]]'s article in ''Theol. Stud. und Kritiken'' ( 1882), PP. 347?392;
*[[Hans von Schubert|H. von Schubert]], ''Outlines of Church History'', ch. xv. (Eng. trans., 1907); and
*[[Carl Mirbt]]'s article, &quot;Pietismus,&quot; in Herzog-Hauck's ''Realencyklopädie für prot. Theologie u. Kirche'', end of vol. xv.

The most extensive and current edition on Pietism is the four-volume edition in German, covering the entire movement in Europe and North America

*'''Geschichte des Pietismus (GdP)'''
Im Auftrag der Historischen Kommission zur Erforschung des Pietismus herausgegeben von Martin Brecht, Klaus Deppermann, Ulrich Gäbler und Hartmut Lehmann 
* ''Band 1:'' Der Pietismus vom siebzehnten bis zum frühen achtzehnten Jahrhundert. In Zusammenarbeit mit Johannes van den Berg, Klaus Deppermann, Johannes Friedrich Gerhard Goeters und Hans Schneider hg. von Martin Brecht. Goettingen 1993. / 584 p.
* ''Band 2:'' Der Pietismus im achtzehnten Jahrhundert. In Zusammenarbeit mit Friedhelm Ackva, Johannes van den Berg, Rudolf Dellsperger, Johann Friedrich Gerhard Goeters, Manfred Jakubowski-Tiessen, Pentii Laasonen, Dietrich Meyer, Ingun Montgomery, Christian Peters, A. Gregg Roeber, Hans Schneider, Patrick Streiff und Horst Weigelt hg. von Martin Brecht und Klaus Deppermann. Goettingen 1995. / 826 p.
* ''Band 3:'' Der Pietismus im neunzehnten und zwanzigsten Jahrhundert. In Zusammenarbeit mit Gustav Adolf Benrath, Eberhard Busch, Pavel Filipi, Arnd Götzelmann, Pentii Laasonen, Hartmut Lehmann, Mark A. Noll, Jörg Ohlemacher, Karl Rennstich und Horst Weigelt unter Mitwirkung von Martin Sallmann hg. von Ulrich Gäbler. Goettingen 2000. / 607 p.
* ''Band 4:'' Glaubenswelt und Lebenswelten des Pietismus. In Zusammenarbeit mit Ruth Albrecht, Martin Brecht, Christian Bunners, Ulrich Gäbler, Andreas Gestrich, Horst Gundlach, Jan Harasimovicz, Manfred Jakubowski-Tiessen, Peter Kriedtke, Martin Kruse, Werner Koch, Markus Matthias, Thomas Müller Bahlke, Gerhard Schäfer (†), Hans-Jürgen Schrader, Walter Sparn, Udo Sträter, Rudolf von Thadden, Richard Trellner, Johannes Wallmann und Hermann Wellenreuther hg. von Hartmut Lehmann. Goettingen 2004. / 709 p.

Key works in English
*F. Ernest Stoeffler: ''The Rise of Evangelical Pietism''. Studies in the History of Religion 9. Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1965.
*F. Ernest Stoeffler: ''German Pietism During the Eighteenth Century''. Studies in the History of Religion 24. Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1973.
*F. Ernest Stoeffler, ed.: ''Continental Pietism and Early American Christianity''. Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 1976.
*Brown, Dale: ''Understanding Pietism'', rev. ed. Nappanee, IN: Evangel Publishing House, 1996.
*Daniel L. Brunner: ''Halle Pietists in England: Anthony William Boehm and the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge''. Arbeiten zur Geschichte des Pietismus 29. Göttingen, Germany: Vandenhoeck and Ruprecht, 1993.
*Douglas H. Shantz: ''Between Sardis and Philadelphia. The Life and World of Pietist Court Preacher Conrad Broeske''. Leiden: Brill, 2008.

==External links==
*[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/encyc09.html?term=Pietism New Schaff-Herzog Encyclopedia of Religious Knowledge, Vol. IX: Pietism]
*[http://www.wlsessays.net/node/525 After Three Centuries – The Legacy of Pietism by E.C. Fredrich]
*[http://www.wlsessays.net/node/961 Literary Landmarks of Pietism by Martin O. Westerhaus]
*[http://www.wlsessays.net/node/853 Pietism’s World Mission Enterprise by Ernst H. Wendland]
*{{CathEncy|wstitle=Pietism}}

{{1911}}

[[Category:History of Lutheranism]]
[[Category:Lutheran theology]]
[[Category:Methodism]]
[[Category:Christian theological movements]]
[[Category:Radical Pietism| Pietism]]

[[ar:تقوية]]
[[bg:Пиетизъм]]
[[ca:Pietisme]]
[[cs:Pietismus]]
[[da:Pietisme]]
[[de:Pietismus]]
[[et:Pietism]]
[[el:Πιετισμός]]
[[es:Pietismo]]
[[eo:Pietismo]]
[[eu:Pietismo]]
[[fr:Piétisme]]
[[ko:경건주의]]
[[io:Pietismo]]
[[id:Pietisme]]
[[ia:Pietismo]]
[[is:Heittrúarstefna]]
[[it:Pietismo]]
[[he:פייטיזם]]
[[ka:პიეტიზმი]]
[[hu:Pietizmus]]
[[nl:Piëtisme (kerkgeschiedenis)]]
[[ja:敬虔主義]]
[[no:Pietisme]]
[[nn:Pietisme]]
[[pl:Pietyzm]]
[[pt:Pietismo]]
[[ro:Pietism]]
[[rm:Pietissem]]
[[ru:Пиетизм]]
[[sk:Pietizmus]]
[[sl:Pietizem]]
[[fi:Pietismi]]
[[sv:Pietism]]
[[uk:Пієтизм]]
[[zh:虔敬主义]]</text>
      <sha1>53u9dndxbb1rc78i2d9p3hi3hqxgwut</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
