<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Political religion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>795400</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521319184</id>
      <parentid>521319136</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T06:37:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>108.66.1.150</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Revolutionary France */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18261">{{Politics}}
The theory of '''political religion''' concerns governmental [[ideology|ideologies]] whose cultural and political backing is so strong that it they are said to attain power equivalent to those of a [[state religion]], to which they often exhibit significant similarities in both theory and practice.&lt;ref&gt;Gentile, Emilio: ''Politics as Religion'' (2006) Princeton University Press&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to basic forms of politics, like parliament and elections, it also holds an aspect of [[sanctification|Sacralization]] related to the institutions held within the regime and provides also the inner measures traditionally considered to be a religious territory, such as [[Ethics]], [[Value (personal and cultural)|Values]], [[Symbol]]s, [[Mythology|Myths]], [[Ritual]]s and for example a national [[liturgy|Liturgical]] calendar. Political religions generally vie with existing traditional religions, and try, if possible, to replace or eradicate them.  The term was given new attention in the United States by the political scientist Hans Maier.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;Maier, Hans and Jodi
Bruhn [http://books.google.com/books?id=Wozo1W7giZQC&amp;dq Totalitarianism and Political Religions], p. 108, 2004 Routledge&lt;/ref&gt;

The term is sometimes treated as synonymous with [[civil religion]], {{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} but although some scholars use the terms as equivalent, others see a useful distinction, using &quot;civil religion&quot; as something weaker, which functions more as a socially unifying and essentially conservative force, where a political religion is radically transformational, even [[apocalypse|apocalyptic]].&lt;ref&gt;Gentile, Emilio: ''Politics as Religion'' (2006) Princeton University Press, s.xxii&lt;/ref&gt;

The term is sometimes used outside academia, often with meanings tangential to or opposite to the sociological usage (for example, applying it to a church), with the use intended as a derogatory description of excessive adherence to something political or ideological. Even when used correctly, supporters of an ideology will generally reject the application of the term &quot;political religion&quot;.{{Citation needed|date = May 2010}}

==Overview==
The term ''political religion'' draws on the aspects of religion which can be found in certain secular ideologies. The scientific schools practicing the study on religious aspects of politics include at least [[Political science]] (for example [[William E. Connolly|William Connolly]]), [[Sociology]] ([[Christoph Deutschmann]]), [[History]] ([[Emilio Gentile]]), [[Theology]] ([[Oliver O'Donovan]]) and [[Psychology]]. A political religion often occupies the same ethical, psychological and sociological space as a traditional religion, and as a result it often displaces or co-opts existing religious organizations and beliefs. The most central definition of a political religion is the [[Sacralization]] of politics, for example an overwhelming religious feeling when serving one`s country, as in the case of the [[Founding Fathers of the United States|Founding Fathers]].&lt;ref&gt;Morris, Benjamin Franklin: ''The Christian Life &amp; Character of the Civil Institutions of the United States; Developed in the Official and Historical Annals of the Republic'' (1864) Philadelphia: George W. Childs&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gentile, Emilio: ''Politics as Religion'' (2006) Princeton University Press, p.22&lt;/ref&gt; Although a political religion may co-opt existing religious structures or symbolism, it does not itself have any independent [[spirituality|spiritual]] or [[theocratic]] elements - it is essentially secular, using religion only for political purposes, if it does not reject religious faith outright.&lt;ref&gt;For a different opinion on this important distinction, see Angela Astoria Kurtz, &quot;God, not Caesar: Revisiting National Socialism as 'Political Religion'&quot; in ''History of European Ideas'', Vol. 35; No. 2 (June 2009)&lt;/ref&gt; Typically a political religion is considered to be [[Secularity|secular]], but more radical forms of it are also [[Transcendental]] .&lt;ref&gt;Angela Astoria Kurtz, &quot;God, not Caesar:  Revisiting National Socialism as 'Political Religion'&quot; in ''History of European Ideas'', Vol. 35; No. 2 (June 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gentile, Emilio: ''Politics as Religion'' (2006) Princeton University Press, p.20&lt;/ref&gt;

The first scholars to use the concept of political religion (or synonyms such as &quot;secular religion&quot;, &quot;lay religion&quot; or &quot;public religion&quot;) were Protestant and Catholic intellectuals and theologians, such as Luigi Sturzo, Adolf Keller, [[Paul Tillich]], Gerhard
Leibholz, Waldemar Gurian, [[Eric Voegelin]], [[Raymond Aron]] and [[Walter Benjamin]].&lt;ref name=gentile-chapter3-4&gt;Gentile, Emilio: ''Politics as Religion'' (2006) Princeton University Press, chapters 3-4&lt;/ref&gt; They saw it as a response to the existential void and [[Nihilism]] caused by [[modernity]], [[mass society]] and the rise of a bureaucratic state, and in political religions &quot;the rebellion against the religion of God&quot; reached its climax.&lt;ref name=gentile-chapter3-4/&gt; They also described them as ‘pseudo-religions’, ‘substitute religions’, ‘surrogate religions’, ‘religions manipulated by man’ and ‘anti-religions’.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/14690760500099770 |title=Political Religion: A Concept and its Critics - A Critical Survey |first=Emilio |last=Gentile |journal=Totalitarian Movements and Political Religions |volume=6 |number=1 |page=25 |doi=10.1080/14690760500099770}}&lt;/ref&gt; The secularization of the twentieth century had created a void which could be filled by an ideology claiming also a hold on ethical and identitetical matters as well, making the political religions based on totalitarianism, universalism and messianic missions (such as [[Manifest Destiny]]&lt;ref&gt;Gamble, Richard: ''Savior Nation: Woodrow Wilson and a gospel of service'' (2001) Humanitas vol.XIV, nro.1&lt;/ref&gt;) possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Griffin, Roger p. 7&quot;&gt;Griffin, Roger [http://books.google.com/books?id=FSgODum-CTUC&amp;dq Fascism, Totalitarianism and Political Religion], p. 7 2005Routledge&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gentile, Emilio: ''Politics as Religion'' (2006) Princeton University Press, chapters 2-4&lt;/ref&gt;

Yale political scientist, [[Juan Linz]] and others have noted that secularization of the twentieth century had created a void which could be filled by a total ideology, making the political religions of totalitarianism possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Griffin, Roger p. 7&quot;/&gt;

==Typical aspects==
Key qualities often (not all are always strongly present) shared by religion (particularly [[cult]]s) and political religion include
*Structural
** differentiation between self and ''other'', and demonisation of ''other'' (in theistic religion, the differentiation usually depends on adherence to certain dogmas and social behaviours; in political religion, differentiation may be on grounds such as nationality, social attitudes, or membership in &quot;enemy&quot; political parties, instead)
** a transcendent leadership, either with [[messiah|messianic]] tendencies, often a charismatic figurehead;
** strong, hierarchical organisational structures
** the control of education, in order to ensure the security, continuation and the veneration of the existing system.

*Belief
** a coherent belief system for imposing symbolic meaning on the external world, with an emphasis on security through faith in the system;
** an intolerance of other ideologies of the same type
** a degree of [[utopianism]]
** the belief that the ideology is in some way natural or obvious, so that (at least for certain groups of people) those who reject it are in some way &quot;blind&quot;
** a genuine desire on the part of individuals to convert others to the cause
** a willingness to place ends over means - in particular, a willingness to use violence and fraud
** fatalism - a belief that the ideology will inevitably triumph in the end

Not all of these aspects are present in any one ''political religion''; this is only a list of some common aspects.

===Suppression of religious beliefs===
Political religions vie with existing religions, and try, if possible, to replace or eradicate them.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;  Loyalty to other entities, such as a church or a deity are often seen to interfere with loyalty to the political religion.  The authority of potential religious leaders also presents a threat to the authority of the political religion.  As a result, some or all religious sects are either suppressed or banned. An existing sect may be converted into a [[state religion]], but dogma and personnel may be modified to suit the needs of the party or state. Where there is suppression of religious institutions and beliefs, this might be explicitly accompanied by [[atheism|atheistic]] doctrine as in [[state atheism]].

[[Juan Linz]] has posited the [[Separation of church and state#Friendly and hostile separation|friendly form of separation of church and state]] as the counterpole of political religion but describes the hostile form of separation of church and state as moving toward political religion as found in totalitarianism.&lt;ref&gt;Maier, Hans and Jodi
Bruhn [http://books.google.com/books?id=Wozo1W7giZQC&amp;dq Totalitarianism and Political Religions], p. 110-111, 2004 Routledge&lt;/ref&gt;

===Absolute loyalty===
[[Loyalty]] to the state or political party and acceptance of the government/party ideology is paramount.  Dissenters may be expelled, ostracized, discriminated against, imprisoned, &quot;re-educated&quot;, or killed.  [[Loyalty oath]]s or membership in a dominant (or sole) political party may be required for employment, government services, or simply as routine.  Criticism of the government may be a serious crime.  Enforcements range from ostracism from one's neighbors to execution. In a fundamental political religion you are either with the system or against the system.

===Cult of personality===
{{Main|Cult of personality}}
A political religion often elevates its leaders to near-godlike status.  Displays of leaders in the form of posters or statues may be mandated in public areas and even private homes. Children may be required to learn the state's version of the leaders' biographies in school.

==Historical cases==
=== Revolutionary France ===
{{main|Cult of Reason|Cult of the Supreme Being}}
[[File:Fête de l'Etre suprême 2.jpg|thumb|right|320px|''The Festival of the Supreme Being'', by Pierre-Antoine Demachy.]]
Revolutionary France was well noted for being the first state to [[State atheism|reject religion altogether]]. Radicals intended to replace Christianity with a new state religion, or an atheistic ideology. [[Maximilien Robespierre]] rejected atheistic ideologies and intended to create a new religion. Churches were closed, and Catholic Mass was forbidden.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sullivan-county.com/identity/shanda.htm&lt;/ref&gt;The Cult of the Supreme Being was well known for its derided festival, which lead to the [[Thermidorian reaction]] and the fall of Robespierre.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, p. 345. (''A Cultural History of the French Revolution'')&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Fascism ===
{{main|Fascism|Fascist symbolism}}

==== Italian fascism ====
{{main|Italian fascism}}

According to [[Emilio Gentile]], &quot;Fascism was the first and prime instance of a modern political religion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674784758 |title=The Sacralization of Politics in Fascist Italy |publisher=Harvard University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;This religion sacralized the state and assigned it the primary educational task of transforming the mentality, the character, and the customs of Italians. The aim was to create a 'new man,' a believer in and an observing member of the cult of Fascism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gentile&quot;&gt;Gentile, ''The Sacralization of Politics in Fascist Italy'', p.ix.&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The argument &lt;nowiki&gt;[that fascism was a ‘political religion’]&lt;/nowiki&gt; tends to involve three main claims: I) that fascism was characterized by a religious form, particularly in terms of language and ritual; II) that fascism was a sacralized form of totalitarianism, which legitimized violence in defence of the nation and regeneration of a fascist 'new man'; and III) that fascism took on many of the functions of religion for a broad swathe of society.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://staff.bath.ac.uk/mlsre/ReflectionsonFascismandReligion.htm |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080918095346/http://staff.bath.ac.uk/mlsre/ReflectionsonFascismandReligion.htm |archivedate=September 18, 2008 |title=Reflections on Fascism and Religion |first=Roger |last=Eatwell |journal=Totalitarian Movements and Politics Religions |volume=4 |number=3 |year=2003 |pages=145–166 |doi=10.1080/14690760412331329991}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Nazism ====
{{main|Nazism|Nazi mysticism}}

&quot;Among committed [Nazi] believers, a mythic world of eternally strong heroes, demons, fire and sword - in a word, the fantasy world of the nursery - displaced reality.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;burleigh&quot;&gt;Burleigh, ''The Third Reich'', (London: Macmillan, 2000) pp.8-9.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Heinrich Himmler]] was fascinated by the occult, and sought to turn the [[SS]] into the basis of an official state cult.&lt;ref name=&quot;sscult&quot;&gt;N. Goodrick-Clarke, ''The Occult Roots of Nazism'' (Wellingborough: the Aquarian Press, 1985), and P. Levenda, ''Unholy Alliance'' (New York: Continuum, 2002).&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Leninism ===
{{POV|date=October 2012}}
{{main|Leninism}}
Klaus-Georg Riegel, in his article &quot;Marxism-Leninism as a political religion&quot;, said &quot;Lenin's utopian design of a revolutionary community of virtuosi as a typical political religion of an intelligentsia longing for an inner-worldly salvation, a socialist paradise without exploitation and alienation, to be implanted in the Russian backward society at the outskirts of the industrialised and modernised Western Europe.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;riegel&quot;&gt;Riegel, Klaus-Georg. 2005. [http://www.informaworld.com/10.1080/14690760500099788Marxism-Leninism as a political religion]. Totalitarian Movements and Political Religions. 6(1):97-126.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Statism in Shōwa Japan ===
{{main|Statism in Shōwa Japan}}

==Modern examples==
===North Korea===
{{main|Juche}}
The North Korean government has promulgated [[Juche]] as a political alternative to traditional religion. The doctrine advocates a strong nationalist propaganda basis and is fundamentally opposed to [[Christianity]] and [[Buddhism]], the two largest religions on the Korean peninsula. Juche theoreticians have, however, incorporated religious ideas into the state ideology.  According to government figures, Juche is the largest political religion in [[North Korea]]. The public practice of all other religions is overseen and subject to heavy surveillance by the state.

===Turkmenistan===
During the long rule of president [[Saparmurat Niyazov]] large pictures and statues of him could be seen in public places in [[Turkmenistan]]. In an interview with the television news program &quot;60 Minutes&quot;, Niyazov said the people of Turkmenistan placed them there voluntarily because they love him so much, and that he did not originally want them there. In addition, he granted himself the title &quot;Türkmenbaşy&quot;, meaning &quot;Leader of all Ethnic Turkmens&quot; in the [[Turkmen language]]. A book purportedly authored by Niyazov, ''[[Ruhnama]]'' (&quot;Book of the Soul&quot;) was required reading in educational institutions and was often displayed and treated with the same respect as the [[Qur'an]]. The study of Ruhnama in the academic system was scaled down but to some extent continued after Niyazov's death (in 2006), as of 2008.

==See also==
{{Columns-list|3|
* [[History of political Islam in Iran]]
* [[Civil religion]]
* [[Secular religion]]
* [[Statolatry]]
* [[State atheism]]
* [[American civil religion]]
}}

==Footnotes==
&lt;!-- Dead note &quot;1&quot;: Gentile, &quot;Political Religion: A Concept and its Critics - A Critical Survey,&quot; ''Totalitarian Movements and Political Religions'', Vol. 6, No. 1, p.25.  --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* Eric Voegelin (1986), ''The Political Religions'', (Lewiston, N.Y.: E. Mellen Press, 1986; 1st German ed. 1938)
* Emilio Gentile and Keith Botsford (Translator) (1996), ''The Sacralization of Politics in Fascist Italy'', Harvard University Press
* Emilio Gentile (2005), &quot;Political Religion: A Concept and its Critics - A Critical Survey,&quot; ''Totalitarian Movements and Political Religions'', Volume 6, No. 1
* Emilio Gentile (2006) ''Politics as Religion'', Princeton University Press, Princeton &amp; Oxford
* Klaus Vondung (2005), [http://taylorandfrancis.metapress.com/index/XK876M348664W76P.pdf &quot;National socialism as a political religion: Potentials and limits of an analytical concept&quot;], ''Totalitarian Movements &amp; Political Religions'' 6(1)
* Wolfgang Hardtwig (2001) [http://www.ghi-dc.org/bulletin28S01/b28hardtwigframe.html &quot;Political Religion in Modern Germany: Reflections on Nationalism, Socialism, and National Socialism&quot;], ''Bulletin of the German Historical Institute'', Volume 28
* [[Jacques Ellul]],The New Demons. Trans. C. Edward Hopkin. New York: Seabury, 1975. London: Mowbrays, 1975.

==External links==
* ''[http://www.blackwell-compass.com/subject/religion/section_home?section=reco-political Political Religions]'' section of ''[http://www.blackwell-compass.com/subject/religion/ Religion Compass]''
*[http://belfercenter.ksg.harvard.edu/project/57/religion_in_international_affairs.html Initiative on Religion in International Affairs] at Harvard
*[http://www.cfr.org/religion Religion and Foreign Policy Initiative] Council on Foreign Relations.
* Conference on ''[http://mosseprogram.wisc.edu/pdfs/Tort_PolRelig_brochure.pdf Political religions in the modern era]'', University of Wisconsin-Madison, 7–9 May 2004
* ''Totalitarian Movements &amp; Political Religions'', [http://taylorandfrancis.metapress.com/openurl.asp?genre=journal&amp;issn=1469-0764 &quot;Special Issue: Political Religions as a characteristic of the 20th century&quot;], Volume 6 Number 1/June 2005, Taylor &amp; Francis (requires subscription)

{{Religion topics}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Political Religion}}
[[Category:Religion and politics]]
[[Category:Ideologies]]
[[Category:Secular religion]]

[[ar:الدين السياسي]]
[[de:Politische Religion]]
[[sv:Politisk religion]]</text>
      <sha1>c3nww5k18qb8ekuvmrczx6vb9j1af2v</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
