<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pontifex Maximus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>81677</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521118741</id>
      <parentid>518854217</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T22:19:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bumm13</username>
        <id>63286</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Roman Republic */ minor markup fix</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41230">[[File:August Labicana Massimo Inv56230.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Augustus]] as Pontifex Maximus&lt;br&gt;''([[Via Labicana Augustus]])'']]

The '''''Pontifex Maximus''''' ([[Latin]], literally: &quot;greatest [[pontiff]]&quot;) was the high priest of the [[College of Pontiffs]] (''[[Collegium (ancient Rome)|Collegium]] Pontificum'') in [[ancient Rome]]. This was the most important position in the [[Religion in ancient Rome|ancient Roman religion]], open only to [[Patrician (ancient Rome)|patricians]] until 254 BC, when a [[plebeian]] first occupied this post. A distinctly religious office under the early [[Roman Republic]], it gradually became politicized until, beginning with [[Augustus]], it was subsumed into the Imperial office. Its last use with reference to the emperors is in inscriptions of [[Gratian]]&lt;ref name=lacus&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Pontifex.html Pontifex Maximus] LacusCurtius retrieved August 15, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; (reigned 375–383) who, however, then decided to omit the words &quot;pontifex maximus&quot; from his title.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Gratian.&quot; Encyclopædia Britannica. 2008. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. 3 Feb. 2008  &lt;http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9037772&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=livius&gt;[http://www.livius.org/pn-po/pontifex/maximus.html Pontifex Maximus] Livius.org article by Jona Lendering retrieved August 21, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

The word &quot;pontifex&quot; later became a term used for Christian bishops,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In the matter of hierarchical nomenclature, one of the most striking instances is the adoption of the term pontifex for a bishop&quot; ([http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0009-8353(196602)61%3A5%3C193%3AMUOA%3E2.0.CO%3B2-B Paul Pascal: ''Medieval Uses of Antiquity''] in The Classical Journal, Vol. 61, No. 5 [Feb., 1966], pp. 193–197).&lt;/ref&gt; including the Bishop of Rome,&lt;ref&gt;[http://webu2.upmf-grenoble.fr/Haiti/Cours/Ak/Constitutiones/Thessalonique.htm Edictum Gratiani, Valentiani et Theodosii de fide catholica, 27 February 380;] cf. [http://www.bartleby.com/61/89/P0438900.html The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition. 2000:] &quot;Pontiff: 1a. The pope. b. A bishop. 2. A pontifex.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and the title of &quot;Pontifex Maximus&quot; was applied within the [[Roman Catholic Church]] to the [[Pope]] as its chief bishop. It is not included in the Pope's official titles,&lt;ref&gt;[[Annuario Pontificio]] (Libreria Editrice Vaticana, 2012 ISBN 978-88-209-8722-0), p. 23*&lt;/ref&gt; but appears on buildings, monuments and coins of popes of [[Renaissance]] and modern times.

==Etymology==
{{Priesthoods of ancient Rome}}
According to the usual interpretation, the term ''pontifex'' literally means &quot;bridge-builder&quot; (''pons'' + ''facere''); &quot;maximus&quot; literally means &quot;greatest&quot;. This was perhaps originally meant in a literal sense: the position of bridge-builder was indeed an important one in Rome, where the major [[bridge]]s were over the [[Tiber]], the sacred river (and a deity): only prestigious authorities with sacral functions could be allowed to &quot;disturb&quot; it with mechanical additions. However, it was always understood in its symbolic sense as well: the pontifices were the ones who smoothed the &quot;bridge&quot; between gods and men (Van Haeperen).

The interpretation of the word ''pontifex'' as &quot;bridge-builder&quot; was that of [[Dionysius of Halicarnassus]] and [[Marcus Terentius Varro]], while [[Plutarch]] derived the word from Old Latin ''potis'' meaning a powerful or absolute master, while others took it to come from ''potis facere'' in the sense of &quot;able to sacrifice&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=1qljAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA81&amp;lpg=PA81&amp;dq=etymology+of+the+word+pontifex&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=62Igwq4l5Z&amp;sig=I3V8cD5kI3eKZftujaygY3f_FpA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=VNxrUJieH8aEhQf_-IGgDA&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=etymology%20of%20the%20word%20pontifex&amp;f=false Nathaniel Hooke, ''The Roman History'' (1830), vol. I, p. 81]&lt;/ref&gt; The last derivation is mentioned also by Varro, who rejected it,&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=xQd82l39KX4C&amp;pg=PA195&amp;lpg=PA195&amp;dq=etymology+of+the+word+pontifex&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=RQB3ZwzlC-&amp;sig=5fwwXy4ievyYMFUSZB0-OGimJ4M&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=yd5rUPOkGMKwhAfd64DoBg&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=etymology%20of%20the%20word%20pontifex&amp;f=false Mary Beard, John North, Simon Price (editors), ''Religions of Rome'' (Cambridge University Press 1998 ISBN 978-0-52145646-3), vol. 2, p. 195]&lt;/ref&gt; but it was the view of Pontifex Maximus Quintus Scaevola.&lt;ref name=Lanciani&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=hcQETIDrjBwC&amp;pg=PA54&amp;lpg=PA54&amp;dq=etymology+of+the+word+pontifex&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=55-I67i8xB&amp;sig=5wGd-VkqiztTKI42U5dbrhf4rKc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=UelrULecCYrOhAejtYGIBw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=etymology%20of%20the%20word%20pontifex&amp;f=false Rodolfo Lanciani, ''New Tales of Ancient Rome'' (Kessinger Publishing 2005 (reprint) ISBN 978-1-41790821-9), p. 54]&lt;/ref&gt; Others have held that the word was originally ''pompifex'' (leader of public processions).&lt;ref name=Lanciani/&gt; The word ''pons'' originally meant &quot;way&quot; and ''pontifex'' would thus mean &quot;maker of roads and bridges&quot;.&lt;ref name=Lanciani/&gt; Another opinion is that the word is a corruption of a similar-sounding but etymologically unrelated [[Etruscan language|Etruscan]] word for ''[[priest]]''.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}} Yet another hypothesis&lt;ref&gt;First proposed by  F. Ribezzo in  &quot;Pontifices 'quinionalis sacrificii effectores&quot; , ''Rivista Indo-Greco-Italica di Filologia-Lingua-Antichità'' '''15''' 1931 p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; considers the word as a loan from the Sabine language, in which it would mean a member of a college of five, from Osco-Umbrian ''ponte'', five.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Greek πέντε&lt;/ref&gt; This explanation takes into account the fact that the college was established by Sabine king Numa Pompilius and the institution is Italic: the expressions ''pontis'' and ''pomperias'' found in the [[Iguvine Tablets]] may denote a group or division of five or by five. The pontifex would thence be a member of a sacrificial college known as ''pomperia'' (Latin ''quinio'').&lt;ref&gt;For a review of the proposed hypotheses cfr. J. P. Hallet &quot;Over Troubled Waters: The Meaning of the Title Pontifex&quot; in ''Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association'' '''101''' 1970 p. 219 ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origins in the Regal period==
The ''Collegium Pontificum'' (College of Pontiffs) was the most important priesthood of ancient Rome. The foundation of this sacred college and the office of Pontifex Maximus is attributed to the second [[king of Rome]], [[Numa Pompilius]].&lt;ref name=Livy&gt;[[Livy]], ''[[Ab urbe condita]]'', 1:20&lt;/ref&gt; Much of what is known about the [[Kingdom of Rome|Regal period in Roman history]] is semi-legendary or mythical. The ''[[Collegium (ancient Rome)|Collegium]]'' presumably acted as advisers to the ''[[King|rex]]'' (king) in religious matters. The ''collegium'' was headed by the ''pontifex maximus'', and all the ''pontifices'' held their office for life. But the pontifical records of early Rome were most likely destroyed when the city was sacked by the Gauls in 387 BC, and the earliest accounts of Archaic Rome come from the literature of the [[Roman Republic|Republic]], most of it from the 1st century BC and later.

According to the [[Augustus|Augustan]]-era [[Roman historiography|historian]] [[Livy]], [[Numa Pompilius]], a [[Sabine]], devised Rome's system of religious rites, including the manner and timing of sacrifices, the supervision of religious funds, authority over all public and private religious institutions, instruction of the populace in the celestial and funerary rites including appeasing the dead, and expiation of prodigies. Numa is said to have founded Roman religion after dedicating an altar on the [[Aventine Hill]] to [[Jupiter (mythology)#Epithets of Jupiter|Jupiter Elicius]] and consulting the gods by means of [[augur]]y.&lt;ref name=Livy/&gt; Numa wrote down and sealed these religious instructions, and gave them to the first Pontifex Maximus, [[Numa Marcius]].

==Roman Republic==
{{main|College of Pontiffs}}
In the [[Roman Republic]], the Pontifex Maximus was the highest office in the [[Religion in ancient Rome|state religion of ancient Rome]] and directed the College of Pontiffs. According to Livy, after the overthrow of the monarchy, the Romans created the priesthood of the ''[[rex sacrorum]]'', or &quot;king of sacred rites,&quot; to carry out certain religious duties and rituals previously performed by the king. The ''rex sacrorum'' was explicitly deprived of military and political power, but the ''pontifices'' were permitted to hold both [[Roman magistrate|magistracies]] and military commands.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abacus.bates.edu/~mimber/Rciv/public.relig.htm Roman Public Religion] Roman Civilization, bates.edu retrieved August 17, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

The official residence of the Pontifex Maximus was the ''Domus Publica'' (&quot;State House&quot;) which stood between the House of the [[Vestal Virgin]]s and the [[Via Sacra]], close to the [[Regia]], in the [[Roman Forum]]. His religious duties were carried out from the Regia. Unless the ''pontifex maximus'' was also a magistrate at the same time, he was not allowed to wear the [[toga praetexta]], i.e. toga with the purple border. In artistic representations, he can be recognized by his holding an iron knife ''(secespita)''&lt;ref name=livius/&gt; or the ''[[patera]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://employees.oneonta.edu/farberas/arth/ARTH200/politics/aurelian_panels.html Panel Reliefs of Marcus Aurelius and Roman Imperial Iconography] State University of New York, College at Oneonta retrieved Sept. 14, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; and the distinctive robes or toga with part of the mantle covering the head ''([[Glossary of ancient Roman religion#capite velato|capite velato]])'', in keeping with Roman practice.

The Pontifex was not simply a priest. He had both political and religious authority. It is not clear which of the two came first or had the most importance. In practice, particularly during the late Republic, the office of Pontifex Maximus was generally held by a member of a politically prominent family. It was a coveted position mainly for the great prestige it conferred on the holder; [[Julius Caesar]] became pontifex in 73 BC and pontifex maximus in 63 BC.

The major Republican source on the pontiffs would have been the theological writings of [[Varro]], which survive only in fragments preserved by later authors such as [[Aulus Gellius]] and [[Nonius Marcellus]]. Other sources are [[Cicero]], [[Livy]], [[Dionysius of Halicarnassus]], [[Valerius Maximus]], [[Plutarch]]'s ''Life of Numa Pompilius'', [[Sextus Pompeius Festus|Festus]]' summaries of [[Verrius Flaccus]], and in later writers, including several of the [[Church Fathers]]. Some of these sources present an extensive list of everyday prohibitions for the Pontifex Maximus; it seems difficult to reconcile these lists with evidence that many Pontifices Maximi were prominent members of society who lived normal, non-restricted lives.

===Election and number===
The number of Pontifices, elected by ''co-optatio'' (i.e. the remaining members nominate their new colleague) for life, was originally five, including the ''pontifex maximus''.&lt;ref name=lacus/&gt;&lt;ref name=livius/&gt; The ''pontifices'', moreover, could only come from the old nobility, the patricians. However, in 300 BC/299 BC the ''lex Ogulnia'' opened the office of Pontifex Maximus to public election and permitted the ''[[plebs]]'' (plebeians) to be co-opted as priests, so that part of the exclusivity of the title was lost. But it was only in 254 BC that Tiberius Coruncanius became the first plebeian Pontifex Maximus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livius.org/li-ln/livy/periochae/periochae016.html Titus Livius Ex Libro XVIII] Periochae, from livius.org retrieved August 16, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The ''lex Ogulnia'' also increased the number of pontiffs to nine (the ''pontifex maximus'' included). In 104 BC the ''lex Domitia'' prescribed that the election of all pontiffs would henceforward be voted by the ''comitia tributa'' (an assembly of the people divided into voting districts); by the same law, only 17 of the 35 tribes (chosen by lot) of the city could vote. The law's promulgator, L. Domitius Ahenobarbus, was shortly afterwards elected Pontifex Maximus after the death of the incumbent Metellus Dalmaticus:  something of a personal revenge because, the previous year, he had expected to be co-opted as a pontiff to replace his late father, but the pontifical college had appointed another candidate in his place.  The office's next holder, Q. Mucius Scaevola, was also elected under the same law, though without controversy or opposition since he was a former consul and long-serving pontiff. This law was abolished in 81 BC by [[Lucius Cornelius Sulla|Sulla]] in his dictatorship, in the ''lex Cornelia de Sacerdotiis'', which restored to the great priestly colleges their full right of ''co-optatio'' (Liv. Epit. 89; Pseudo-Ascon. in Divinat. p102, ed. Orelli; Dion Cass. xxxvii.37). Also under Sulla, the number of pontifices was increased to fifteen, the ''pontifex maximus'' included, and Sulla nominated [[Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius]] as the next holder of the office - the only truly unelected Pontifex Maximus in history, since even the other pontiffs did not get a vote in the matter. In 63 BC, the law of Sulla was abolished by the tribune [[Titus Labienus]], and a modified form of the ''lex Domitia'' was reinstated providing for election by ''comitia tributa'' once again: [[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]] followed Ahenobarbus's precedent by being elected by public vote, although Caesar at least had previously been a pontiff. Marcus Antonius later restored the right of ''co-optatio'' to the college (Dion Cass. xliv.53), in time for the election of [[Marcus Aemilius Lepidus (49 BC)|Marcus Aemilius Lepidus]]. Also under [[Julius Caesar]], the number of pontifices were increased to sixteen, the pontifex maximus included - possibly because Caesar's own long absences from Rome necessitated the appointment of a deputy pontiff for those occasions when fifteen needed to be present?  The number of pontifices varied during the Empire but is believed to have been regular at fifteen.&lt;ref name=lacus/&gt;

===Extraordinary appointment of dictators===
The office came into its own with the abolition of the monarchy, when most sacral powers previously vested in the King were transferred either to the Pontifex Maximus or to the [[Rex Sacrorum]], though traditionally a (non-political) [[Roman dictator|dictator]] (see also: [[basileus]], [[interrex]]) was formally mandated by the Senate for one day, to perform a specific rite.

According to Livy in his &quot;History of Rome&quot;, an ancient instruction written in archaic letters commands: &quot;Let him who is the [[Roman dictator|Praetor Maximus]] fasten a nail on the Ides of September.&quot; This notice was fastened up on the right side of the Temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus, next to the chapel of Minerva. This nail is said to have marked the number of the year. It was in accordance with this direction that the consul Horatius dedicated the Temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus in the year following the expulsion of the kings; from the Consuls the ceremony of fastening the nails passed to the Dictators, because they possessed greater authority. As the custom had been subsequently dropped, it was felt to be of sufficient importance to require the appointment of a Dictator. L. Manlius was accordingly nominated but his appointment was due to political rather than religious reasons. He was eager to command in the war with the Hernici. He caused a very angry feeling among the men liable to serve by the inconsiderate way in which he conducted the enrolment. At last, in consequence of the unanimous resistance offered by the tribunes of the plebs, he gave way, either voluntarily or through compulsion, and laid down his Dictatorship. Since then, this rite has been performed by the Rex Sacrorum.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url = http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/ancient/romrelig3.html#Livy
|title = History of Rome
|accessdate = 2006-08-23
|author = Livy (Titus Livius)
|last = Livius
|first = Titus
|authorlink = halsall@murray.fordham.edu
|work = Ancient History Sourcebook:
Accounts of Roman State Religion, c. 200 BCE – 250CE
|publisher = (public domain)© Paul Halsall, August 1998, Fordham University
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Duties====

The main duty of the Pontifices was to maintain the ''[[Glossary of ancient Roman religion#pax deorum|pax deorum]]'' or &quot;peace of the gods.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://patriot.net/~carey/afa/latinclub/persecution.htm The Roman Persecution of Christians] By Neil Manzullo February 8th , 2000 Persuasive Writing, retrieved August 17, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everything2.com/index.pl?node_id=993031 Pax Deorum] everything2.com retrieved August 17, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://encarta.msn.com/encnet/refpages/RefArticle.aspx?refid=761568005 &quot;Roman Mythology&quot;], Microsoft [[Encarta Online]] Encyclopedia 2006. Retrieved August 17, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

The immense authority of the sacred college of pontiffs was centered on the Pontifex Maximus, the other pontifices forming his ''consilium'' or advising body. His functions were partly sacrificial or ritualistic, but these were the least important. His real power lay in the administration of ''jus divinum'' or divine law;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.m-w.com/dictionary/jus+divinum jus divinum], Merriam–Webster Online Dictionary retrieved August 24, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; the information collected by the pontifices related to the Roman religious tradition was bound in a ''corpus'' which summarized [[dogma]] and other concepts.  The chief departments of ''jus divinum'' may be described as follows:
#The regulation of all expiatory ceremonials needed as a result of pestilence, lightning, etc.
#The consecration of all temples and other sacred places and objects dedicated to the gods.
#The regulation of the calendar; both astronomically and in detailed application to the public life of the state.
#The administration of the law relating to burials and burying-places, and the worship of the ''Manes'' or dead ancestors.
#The superintendence of all marriages by conferratio, i.e. originally of all legal patrician marriages.
#The administration of the law of adoption and of testamentary succession.
#The regulation of the public morals, and fining and punishing offending parties.

The pontifices had many relevant and prestigious functions such as being in charge of caring for the state archives, the keeping the official minutes of elected magistrates (see ''[[Fasti]]'') and list of magistrates, and they kept the records of their own decisions (''commentarii'') and of the chief events of each year, the so-called &quot;public diaries&quot;, the ''[[Annales maximi]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/POL_PRE/PONTIFEX.html Pontifex], Encyclopædia Britannica, 1911 Ed.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Pontifex Maximus was also subject to several taboos. Among them was the prohibition to leave Italy. Plutarch described [[Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica Serapio]] (141–132 BC) as the first to leave Italy, after being forced by the Senate to do so, and thus break the sacred taboo. [[Publius Licinius Crassus Dives Mucianus]] (132–130 BC) was the first to leave Italy voluntarily. Afterwards it became common and no longer against the law for the Pontifex Maximus to leave Italy. Among the most notable of those who did was [[Julius Caesar]] (63–44 BC).

[[File:Coin Julius Caesar Pontifex Maximus.PNG|thumb|[[Denarius]] depicting Julius Caesar as Pontifex Maximus]]
The Pontifices were in charge of the [[Roman calendar]] and determined when [[Intercalation (timekeeping)|intercalary months]] needed to be added to synchronize the calendar to the seasons. Since the Pontifices were often politicians, and because a Roman magistrate's term of office corresponded with a calendar year, this power was prone to abuse: a Pontifex could lengthen a year in which he or one of his political allies was in office, or refuse to lengthen one in which his opponents were in power. This caused the calendar to become out of step with the seasons; for example, Caesar's crossing of the [[Rubicon]] in January 49 BC actually took place in mid-autumn. Under his authority as Pontifex Maximus, [[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]] introduced the calendar reform that created the [[Julian calendar]], with a fault of less than a day per century, and which remained the standard till the [[Gregorian calendar|Gregorian]] reform in the 16th century. It also, coincidentally, made 46 BC, the year of Julius's third [[consulship]], 445 days long.

==Roman Empire==
After Julius Caesar's assassination in 44 BC, his ally [[Marcus Aemilius Lepidus (49 BC)|Marcus Aemilius Lepidus]] was selected as Pontifex Maximus. Though Lepidus eventually fell out of political favor and was sent into exile as [[Augustus]] consolidated power, he retained the priestly office until his death in 13 BC, at which point Augustus was selected to succeed him and given the right to appoint other pontifices. Thus, from the time of Augustus, the election of pontifices ended and membership into the sacred college was deemed a sign of imperial favour.&lt;ref name=livius/&gt; With this attribution, the new office of Emperor was given a religious dignity and the responsibility for the entire Roman state cult. Most authors contend that the power of naming the Pontifices was not really used as an ''instrumentum regni'', an enforcing power.

From this point on, ''Pontifex Maximus'' was one of the many titles of the Emperor, slowly losing its specific and [[historical powers]] and becoming simply a referent for the sacral aspect of imperial duties and powers. During the Imperial period, a promagister (vice-master) performed the duties of the ''pontifex maximus'' in lieu of the emperors whenever they were absent (Van Haeperen). In post-Severan times (post AD 235), the small number of pagan senators interested in becoming pontiffs led to a change in the pattern of office holding. In Republican and Imperial times no more than one family member of a gens was member of the [[College of Pontiffs]], nor did one person hold more than one priesthood in this collegium. However, these rules were obviously loosened in the later part of the 3rd century AD. In periods of joint rule, at first only one of the emperors bore this title, as it occurred for the first time during the reign of [[Marcus Aurelius]] and [[Lucius Verus]], when only Marcus Aurelius was ''pontifex maximus'', but later two ''pontifices maximi'' could serve together, as [[Pupienus and Balbinus]] did in 238 — a situation unthinkable in Republican times. In the [[crisis of the Third Century]], usurpers did not hesitate to claim for themselves the role not only of Emperor but of Pontifex Maximus as well. Even the early Christian Emperors continued to use it; it was only relinquished by [[Gratian]], possibly in AD 376 at the time of his visit to Rome,&lt;ref&gt;Van Haeperen&lt;/ref&gt; or more probably in 383 when a delegation of pagan senators implored him to restore the Altar of Victory in the Senate House.&lt;ref&gt;A. Cameron, &quot;Gratian's Repudiation of the Pontifical Robe&quot; ''The Journal of Roman Studies'' 58 (1968), 96–102 – the confusion in dates arises from Zosimus, who writes that it was repudiated at Gratian's accession, impossible from epigraphic and literary references&lt;/ref&gt;

==Roman Catholic use of the title==
[[File:Welt-Galleria T001 bn.jpg|thumb|[[Pope Clement XI]], with the title ''Pontifex Maximus'']]
When [[Tertullian]], a [[Montanism|Montanist]], furiously applied the term to some bishop with whom he was at odds (either [[Pope Callixtus I]] or Agrippinus of Carthage),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?q=Sullivan+%22Agrippinus+bishop%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books&amp;tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1 Francis Aloysius Sullivan, ''From Apostles to Bishops'' (Paulist Press 2001 ISBN 978-0-8091-0534-2), p. 165]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?q=Wilhite+%22much+scholarly%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books&amp;tbm=bks&amp;tbo=1 David E. Wilhite, ''Tertullian the African'' (De Gruyter, Walter 2007 ISBN 978-3-11-019453-1), p. 174]&lt;/ref&gt; ''c.'' 220, over a relaxation of the Church's penitential discipline allowing repentant adulterers and fornicators back into the Church, it was in bitter irony:

{{quote|In opposition to this [modesty], could I not have acted the dissembler? I hear that there has even been an edict sent forth, and a peremptory one too. The &quot;Pontifex Maximus,&quot; that is the &quot;bishop of bishops,&quot; issues an edict: &quot;I remit, to such as have discharged [the requirements of] repentance, the sins both of adultery and of fornication.&quot; O edict, on which cannot be inscribed, &quot;Good deed!&quot; ... Far, far from Christ's betrothed be such a proclamation!|Tertullian|''On Modesty'' ch. 1}}

It is not clear if the word ''Pontifex'', the word used in Latin for the Jewish high priest, as in {{bibleverse||John|11:49}} and {{bibleverse||Hebrew|5:1}}, was commonly used by early 3rd-century [[Christianity]], as it was later, to denote a [[bishop]].

The last traces of Emperors being at the same time chief pontiffs are found in inscriptions of [[Valentinian I]], [[Valens]], and [[Gratian]] (Orelli, Inscript. n1117, 1118). From the time of [[Theodosius I]] (r. 379–395), the emperors no longer appear in the dignity of pontiff, but the title was later applied to the Christian bishop of Rome.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/65/po/pontifex.html Pontifex Maximus], Columbia Encyclopedia Sixth Edition.  2001–05., bartleby.com retrieved August 15, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In 382, the Emperor Gratian, at the urging of [[Ambrose]], removed the [[Altar of Victory]] from the Forum, withdrew the state subsidies that funded many pagan activities and formally renounced the title of Pontifex Maximus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.roman-emperors.org/gratian.htm Emperor Gratian] Roman Emperors retrieved August 15, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; It is said that [[Pope Damasus I]] was the first Bishop of Rome to assume the title,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bringyou.to/apologetics/a104.htm Pontifex Maximus] Mark Bonocore retrieved August 15, 2006. This seems to be based on the [http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/theodcodeXVI.html Theodosian Code, XVI.i.2], which refers to Pope Damasus merely as a ''pontifex'', not as the ''pontifex maximus''. [http://www.hermetic.com/sabazius/clergy_egc.htm The Christian Apostolic Succession, The Role and Function of Thelemic Clergy in Ecclesia Gnostica Catholica], retrieved 22 August 2006, states that Damasus refers to himself as ''Pontifex Maximus'' in a petition to the Emperor for judicial immunity, but gives no source for this statement.&lt;/ref&gt; Other sources say that the use of such titles by bishops, including the Bishop of Rome, came later.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Christian emperors relinquished the title Pontifex Maximus as too closely tied with the pagan past (Schimmelpfennig, 34). Bishops, including the bishop of Rome, ''sometime thereafter'', began to make use of pontifex as a title for themselves&quot; ([http://faculty.cua.edu/Pennington/Medieval%20Papacy/BeethamPaperOne.html John D. Beetham, Papal Prerogatives and Titles, [[5 September]] 2001] (emphasis added).&lt;/ref&gt; The title pontifex continued to be a title for both the bishop of Rome and other bishops.  In Emperor Theodosius's edict ''[http://webu2.upmf-grenoble.fr/Haiti/Cours/Ak/Constitutiones/Thessalonique.htm De fide catholica]'' of 27 February 380, enacted in Thessalonica and published in Constantinople for the whole empire, by which he established Catholic Christianity as the official religion of the empire, he referred to Damasus as a ''pontifex'',&lt;ref&gt;Unlike ''episcopus'' (from [[Greek language|Greek]] {{lang|grc|ἐπίσκοπος}}), the word used for the bishop from the Greek-speaking East, ''pontifex'' is a word of  purely [[Latin]] derivation.&lt;/ref&gt; while calling Peter an ''episcopus'' : &quot;... the profession of that religion which was delivered to the Romans by the divine Apostle Peter, as it has been preserved by faithful tradition and which is now professed by the ''Pontiff'' Damasus and by Peter, ''Bishop'' of Alexandria ... We authorize the followers of this law to assume the title Catholic Christians ...&quot; Some see in this an implied significant differentiation, but the title ''pontifex maximus'' is not used in the text; ''pontifex'' is used instead: &quot;... quamque ''pontificem'' damasum sequi claret et petrum alexandriae ''episcopum''...&quot; (Theodosian Code XVI.1.2; and Sozomen, &quot;Ecclesiastical History&quot;, VII, iv.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://ancientrome.ru/ius/library/codex/theod/liber16.htm
|title = IMPERATORIS THEODOSIANI CODEX Liber Decimus Sextus
|accessdate = 2006-12-04
|author = Emperor Theodosius I
|format = web
|publisher = ancientrome.ru
}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

The Encyclopædia Britannica says that [[Pope Leo I]] (440–461) assumed the title ''Pontifex Maximus'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-214716 Papacy] Encyclopædia Britannica. 2006. Encyclopædia Britannica Premium Service. 5 Sept. 2006&lt;/ref&gt; while other sources say [[Pope Gregory I|Gregory I]] (590–604) was the first pope to employ the title in a formal sense.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblestudy.org/basicart/where-did-catholic-pope-title-of-authority-originate.html Where did Catholic Pope's title of authority originate?]&lt;/ref&gt; or on the contrary that [[Pope Siricius]] (384–399) assumed the title.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.ie/books?id=0s916kVyH1gC&amp;pg=PA107&amp;lpg=PA107&amp;dq=%22pontifex+maximus%22+pope+siricius&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=cO2QHXvR1l&amp;sig=ROhUi0c2F5kOvWwPsVR50Jy9AvE&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=8wa-S6y6AqKVOJ2b3dgJ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CBEQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22pontifex%20maximus%22%20pope%20siricius&amp;f=false Alf Droy, ''Wake Up! The Lord Is Returning'', p. 107]&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church'' says that it was in the 15th century (when the [[Renaissance]] stirred up new interest in ancient Rome) that &quot;Pontifex Maximus&quot; became a regular title of honour for Popes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church (Oxford University Press 2005 ISBN 978-0-19-280290-3), article ''Pontifex Maximus''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Benedictus XVI pont max pontif I.jpg|thumb|300px|Gate to the Vatican inscribed ''Benedictus XVI Pont[ifex] Max[imus] Anno Domini MMV Pont[ificatus] I'' (&quot;[[Benedict XVI]], Supreme Pontiff, in the year of Our Lord 2005, in the first year of his pontificate&quot;)]]
While the title ''Pontifex Maximus'' has for some centuries been used in inscriptions referring to the Popes, it has never been included in the official list of papal titles published in the [[Annuario Pontificio]], which instead includes &quot;Supreme Pontiff of the whole Church&quot; (in Latin, ''Summus Pontifex Ecclesiae Universalis'') as the fourth official title, the first being &quot;Bishop of Rome&quot;.

The terms ''pontifex maximus'' and ''summus pontifex'' were for centuries used not only of the Bishop of Rome but of other bishops also.  Hilary of Arles (d. 449) is styled &quot;summus pontifex&quot; by Eucherius of Lyons (P. L., L, 773), and Lanfranc is termed &quot;primas et pontifex summus&quot; by his biographer, Milo Crispin (P. L., CL, 10); they were doubtless originally employed with reference to the Jewish high-priest, whose place the Christian bishops were regarded as holding each in his own diocese (I Clement 40), but from the 11th century they appear to be applied only to the Pope.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12260a.htm#V Catholic Encyclopedia: Pope, Titles]&lt;/ref&gt; The Roman title of &quot;Pontifex Maximus&quot; was rendered in Greek inscriptions and literature of the time as &quot;ἀρχιερεύς&quot; (literally, &quot;high priest&quot;|)&lt;ref&gt;[[Polybius]] 23.1.2 and 32.22.5; ''Corpus Inscriptionum Atticarum'' 3.43, 3.428 und 3.458&lt;/ref&gt; or by a more literal translation and order of words as &quot;ἀρχιερεὺς μέγιστος&quot; (literally, &quot;greatest high priest&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Corpus Inscriptionum Graecarum'' 2.2696 and 3.346; [[Plutarch]] ''Numa'' 9.4&lt;/ref&gt; The term &quot;ἀρχιερεύς&quot; in the [[Septuagint]] text of the [[Old Testament]] and  is used in the [[New Testament]] to refer to the Jewish high priest.

The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church says that it was in the 15th century that &quot;Pontifex Maximus&quot; became a regular title of honor for Popes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Baiocco 1795.jpg|thumb|Papal coin of [[Pius VI]] from the 1700s, with the title ''Pontifex Maximus'' on the reverse]]
The title of &quot;Pontifex Maximus&quot;, which is now applied to the pope, though not included in his official list of titles, thus has a very ancient history, dating back to the times of the [[Roman Republic]]. The only title applied to the Pope that has a longer documented history is the word &quot;pope&quot; itself (in Greek, &quot;πάππας&quot;), which is found already in the time of [[Homer]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus:text:1999.01.0135:book=6:card=48 Odyssey, VI, 57]&lt;/ref&gt; This title likewise is not included in the official list of his titles, but is used in official documents (such as the headings of [[encyclical]]s and similar documents) far more commonly than the title &quot;Pontifex Maximus&quot;, which is in practice used in little more than inscriptions of buildings.

*The title ''Pontifex Maximus'' was briefly used, from 1902 to 1906, by the head of the [[Philippine Independent Church]].

==Tradition of sovereign as high priest==
{{main|Caesaropapism}}
The practice of religious and secular authority united in the sovereign has a long history. In ancient [[Athens]], the [[Archon basileus]] was the principal religious dignitary of the state; according to legend, and as indicated in his title of &quot;Basileus&quot; (meaning &quot;king&quot;), he was supposed to inherit the religious functions of the king of Athens in earlier times.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.albany.edu/faculty/lr618/1mnsac.html Myth Notes;] [http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Archon 1911 Encyclopædia Britannica: Archon;] [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9009298/archon Encyclopædia Britannica Online: Archon]&lt;/ref&gt;

Eastern traditions, from the ancient Egyptian to the Japanese, carried the concept even further, according their sovereigns demigod status.

With the adoption of Christianity, the Roman emperors took it on themselves to issue decrees on matters regarding the Christian Church. Unlike the Pontifex Maximus, they did not themselves function as priests, but they acted practically as head of the official religion, a tradition that continued with the [[List of Byzantine Emperors|Byzantine Emperors]]. In line with the theory of [[Moscow]] as the [[Third Rome]], the [[Russia]]n [[Tsar]]s exercised supreme authority over the [[Russian Orthodox Church]].

With the [[English Reformation]], the sovereign of England became [[Supreme Governor of the Church of England]] and insisted on being recognised as such. Much the same occurred in other countries affected by the [[Protestant Reformation]].

Even in countries where there was no formal break with the [[Holy See]], various sovereigns assumed similar authority. An example is [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor]], whose ecclesiastical policy is described in the [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08508b.htm Catholic Encyclopedia article on him.]

A secular equivalent of the ruler as head of religion is that of the [[philosopher king]], based on a notion in [[Plato's Republic]].

==Incomplete list of ''Pontifices Maximi''==
*753 BC to 712 BC – Duties and power of office (even if perhaps not the title) held by the [[Kings of Rome]]
*712 BC – [[Numa Marcius]]
*...
*509 BC – C.[[Papirius (pontifex)|Papirius]]  (Dionys.Halik. III, 36.4)
*...
*449 BC – [[Furia (gens)|Quintus Furius]] (Liv. III, 54.5; Asconius 77C has M.Papirius)
*431 BC – A.[[Cornelius Cossus]], winner of the ''spolia opima'' (Liv. IV, 27.1)
*420 BC – [[Minucia (gens)|Spurius Minucius]]&lt;ref&gt;T. Robert S. Broughton, ''The Magistrates of the Roman Republic'' (1952).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Livy|Titus Livius]], ''[[Ab Urbe Condita (book)|Ab Urbe Condita]]'' iv. 44, Plutarch ''Inim.Util.''6.&lt;/ref&gt;
*390 BC – [[Follius Flaccinator]] ;  M.Folius (Flaccinator)  (Liv. V, 41.3)
*...
*334 BC – [[Cornelius Callissa]] ;  correctly P.Cornelius Calussa
*c.330 BC - P. Cornelius Scapula (cos.325), ''AE'' 1967,19 (''MRR'' III, 70) 4th century BC sarcophagus inscription found in Rome:  P.CORNELIO P.F. SCAPOLA PONTFEX MAX.  Before this text was found Livy's consul of 325-4 BC P.Cornelius Scapula was usually emended to P.Cornelius Scipio

*304 BC – Cornelius Barbatus, ''possibly [[Lucius Cornelius Scipio Barbatus]]''
*...
*254 BC – [[Tiberius Coruncanius]]
*243 BC – [[Lucius Caecilius Metellus (died 221 BC)|Lucius Caecilius Metellus]] (d. 221 BC)
*220 BC – [[Lucius Cornelius Lentulus Caudinus]] (d. ca 213 BC)
*212 BC – [[Publius Licinius Crassus Dives (consul 205 BC)|Publius Licinius Crassus Dives]] (d. 183 BC),
*182 BC – [[Gaius Servilius Geminus]] (d. 180 BC), the cognomen Geminus is false
*179 BC – [[Marcus Aemilius Lepidus (187 BC)|Marcus Aemilius Lepidus]] (d. 151 BC)
*150 BC – [[Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica Corculum]] (d. 141 BC)
*?141 BC – [[Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica Serapio]] (d. 132 BC [[Pergamum]], [[Asia Minor]])
*131 BC – [[Publius Licinius Crassus Dives Mucianus]] (killed in battle 131 BC, [[Asia Minor]])
*130/29 BC – [[Publius Mucius Scaevola]]  (d. 120/115 BC)
*119/14 BC – [[Lucius Caecilius Metellus Dalmaticus]] (died 107 BC)
*106 BC - Q. Servilius Caepio (cos. 106), exiled 104, murdered in Rome 87
*103 BC – [[Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus (consul 96 BC)|Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus]] (d. 91 BC)
*90 BC – [[Quintus Mucius Scaevola Pontifex]] murdered in Rome 82 BC
*81 BC – [[Quintus Caecilius Metellus Pius]] (d. 64 BC)
*63 BC – [[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]] (d. 44 BC)
*44 BC – [[Marcus Aemilius Lepidus (49 BC)|Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, triumvir]] (d. 13 BC),
*6 March 12 BC – [[Augustus]]
*12 BC to AD 376 – Held by the [[Concise list of Roman Emperors|Emperors]]

From some indeterminate later date to present, the title &quot;Pontifex Maximus&quot; is applied to the [[List of Popes|Popes]].

==In popular culture==
* In [[C. S. Lewis]]'s Christian novel ''[[The Voyage of the Dawn Treader]]'', [[Aslan]] refers to himself as &quot;the great Bridge-Builder&quot;, a close translation of ''Pontifex Maximus''.
* In the [[dispensationalism|dispensationalist]] fiction series ''[[Left Behind (series)|Left Behind]]'', the character Cardinal [[Peter Mathews (Left Behind)|Peter Mathews]] is named Pontifex Maximus of the &quot;[[Enigma Babylon One World Faith]]&quot;, established by [[Nicolae Carpathia]], [[Global Community]] Supreme [[Potentate]] and [[Antichrist]].
* In [[Robert Silverberg]]'s [[Majipoor series]], the ''Pontifex'' is an important authority figure that represents the religious bureaucracy in the system of shared powers that control the fictional planet.
* In the [[X Universe]]'s game series, the leader of the Paranid alien race is also referred to as &quot;Pontifex Maximus&quot;. In the game series, the Paranid are notorious for their extremist religious beliefs.

==See also==
* [[List of Pontifices maximi]] for an incomplete annotated version of this list.
* [[Pontiff]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Pontifex.html article ''Pontifex'' in Smith's Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities]
*[http://www.hostkingdom.net/rome.html#Pontifex List from republican times]
*[http://www.unrv.com/culture/pontifex-maximus-list.php Annotated Pontifex Maximus list]
*[http://www.tyndale.cam.ac.uk/Egypt/ptolemies/chron/roman/roman_consuls.htm List of roman consuls ('''Fasti consulares''') 300 BC–AD 60] at http://www.tyndale.cam.ac.uk/Egypt/ptolemies/chron/chronology.htm – in the list of consuls the column on the right (Pontifex Maximus) lists those that are known in this period.
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12260a.htm#V ''Catholic Encyclopedia'':] Pope, section V. Primacy of Honour: Titles and Insignia

{{Roman religion}}
{{Ancient Rome topics}}

[[Category:Republican holders of the role of pontifex maximus| ]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman religion]]
[[Category:Ancient Roman titles]]
[[Category:Latin religious phrases]]
[[Category:Religious leadership roles]]
[[Category:Papal titles]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Superlatives in religion]]

{{Link FA|mk}}

[[az:Böyük pontifik]]
[[be:Вялікі пантыфік]]
[[be-x-old:Вялікі пантыфік]]
[[bg:Понтифекс максимус]]
[[ca:Pontífex Màxim]]
[[da:Pontifex maximus]]
[[de:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[et:Pontifeks]]
[[el:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[es:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[fr:Pontifex maximus]]
[[hr:Pontifex maximus]]
[[id:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[is:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[it:Pontefice massimo (storia romana)]]
[[he:פונטיפקס מקסימוס]]
[[jv:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[la:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[hu:Pontifex maximus]]
[[mk:Понтифекс максимус]]
[[ms:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[nl:Pontifex maximus]]
[[ja:最高神祇官]]
[[no:Pontifex maximus]]
[[oc:Pontifex maximus]]
[[pl:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[pt:Pontifex maximus]]
[[ro:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[ru:Великий понтифик]]
[[simple:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[sh:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[fi:Pontifex maximus]]
[[sv:Pontifex maximus]]
[[tr:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[uk:Pontifex Maximus]]
[[zh:大祭司 (古罗马)]]</text>
      <sha1>esfh5em3d8tel30qc4iz2clxm223148</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
