<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rastafari movement</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>42132</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522441611</id>
      <parentid>522441599</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-11T06:26:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/202.51.189.26|202.51.189.26]] to version by CommonsDelinker. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1328168) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="86153">{{Rastafari}} 
The '''Rastafari movement''', or '''Rasta''', is a spiritual movement. It arose in the 1930s in [[Jamaica]], a country with a predominantly [[Christianity|Christian]] culture where 98% of the people were the [[black people|black]] [[African]] descendants of [[Atlantic slave trade|slaves]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oneworldmagazine.org/focus/etiopia/rasta.html |title=Rastafari, roots and Ideology |publisher=OneWorld Magazine |date= |accessdate=2010-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DreadJesus&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cesnur.org/testi/rasta.htm |title=&quot;Dread Jesus&quot;: A New View of the Rastafari Movement |publisher=Cesnur.org |date= |accessdate=2010-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its adherents worship [[Haile Selassie I]], Emperor of [[Ethiopia]] (ruled 1930–1974), as [[Jesus]] [[Incarnation|incarnate]], the [[Second Advent]], or the reincarnation of Jesus. Members of the Rastafari movement are known as Rastas, or Rastafari. The movement is sometimes referred to as &quot;Rastafarianism&quot;, but this term is considered derogatory and offensive by some Rastas, who, being highly critical of &quot;isms&quot; (which they see as a typical part of &quot;Babylon culture&quot;), dislike being labelled as an &quot;ism&quot; themselves.&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of African and African-American Religions'' p. 263 by [[Stephen D. Glazier]], 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

The name ''Rastafari'' is taken from ''Ras Tafari'', the [[regnal name|pre-regnal]] title of [[Haile Selassie I]], composed of [[Amharic language|Amharic]] ''Ras'' (literally &quot;Head&quot;, an Ethiopian title equivalent to [[Duke]]), and Haile Selassie's pre-regnal given name, Tafari.  Rastafari are generally distinguished for asserting the doctrine that Haile Selassie I, the former and final [[Emperor of Ethiopia]], is another [[incarnation]] of the Christian God, called [[Jah]].&lt;ref&gt;''Jah'' the Rasta name for God incarnate, from a shortened form of ''[[Jehovah]]'' found in {{bibleverse||Psalms|68:4|KJV}} in the [[King James Version]] of the [[Bible]]&lt;/ref&gt; Most see Haile Selassie I as ''Jah'' or ''Jah Rastafari'', who is the [[second coming]] of [[Jesus Christ]] onto the earth, but to others he is simply God's chosen king on earth.

The Rastafari movement encompasses themes such as the [[entheogen|spiritual use]] of [[cannabis (drug)|cannabis]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Dread&quot;&gt;Dread, The Rastafarians of Jamaica, by Joseph Owens ISBN 0-435-98650-3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Ganja Complex: Rastafari and Marijuana'' by Ansley Hamid (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; and the rejection of western society, called [[Babylon]] (from the [[Babylon (New Testament)|metaphorical Babylon]] of the [[Christian]] [[New Testament]]). It proclaims [[Africa]] (also &quot;[[Zion#Usage by the Rastafari movement|Zion]]&quot;) as the original birthplace of mankind, and from the beginning of the movement the call to [[repatriation]] to Africa for the descendants of those slaves forced into [[exile]] in the West by the [[Atlantic slave trade]] has been a central theme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/rastafari/beliefs/beliefs_1.shtml |title=Rastafarian beliefs |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2009-10-09 |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rasta also embraces various [[Afrocentrism|Afrocentric]] and [[Pan-African]] social and political aspirations,&lt;ref name=&quot;Dread&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=ChantingBabylon/&gt; such as the sociopolitical views and teachings of Jamaican publicist, organizer, and [[black nationalist]] [[Marcus Garvey]] (also often regarded as a prophet). Another theme is [[Royal family|Royalty]], with Rastas seeing themselves as African royalty and using [[English honorifics|honorifics]] such as Prince or King in order to give royalty to their names.

Rastafari is not a highly organized [[religion]]; it is a movement and an ideology. Many Rastas say that it is not a &quot;religion&quot; at all, but a &quot;Way of Life&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=t-VVY9-aVYoC&amp;pg=PA151&amp;dq=rastafari+%22way+of+life%22+religion |title=The anthropology of religious conversion&amp;nbsp;– Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2010-02-01|isbn=978-0-7425-1778-3|author1=Buckser, Andrew|author2=Glazier, Stephen D|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many Rastas do not claim any sect or denomination, and thus encourage one another to find faith and inspiration within themselves, although some do identify strongly with one of the &quot;[[mansions of Rastafari]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;— the three most prominent of these being the ''Nyahbinghi'', the ''Bobo Ashanti'' and the ''Twelve Tribes of Israel''.

Today, awareness of the Rastafari movement has spread throughout much of the world, largely through interest generated by [[reggae]] music, especially the major international success of Jamaican singer/songwriter [[Bob Marley]] (1945–1981). By 1997, there were, according to one estimate, around one million Rastafari faithful worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;''Chanting Down Babylon'' p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2001 Jamaican census, 24,020 individuals (less than 1 percent of the population) identified themselves as Rastafarians.&lt;ref name=&quot;state2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2007/90259.htm |title=Jamaica |publisher=[[Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor]] (US  State Department)|date=2007-09-14 |accessdate=2010-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other sources have estimated that in the 2000s they formed &quot;about 5 percent of the population&quot; of Jamaica,&lt;ref&gt;Reuters AlertNet ([[Reuters Foundation]]):[http://www.alertnet.org/thefacts/countryprofiles/216645.htm?v=details Jamaica] (citing &quot;NI World Guide 2003/2004&quot;); ''The world guide: a view from the south'', [[New Internationalist]] Publications, 2005, [http://books.google.com/books?ei=1ETNTK_bCtTNjAevpqzXBw&amp;ct=result&amp;id=qertAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=rastafarians+per+cent#search_anchor p. 312] (&quot;Rastafarians 5 per cent&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt; or have conjectured that &quot;there are perhaps as many as 100,000 Rastafarians in Jamaica&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Read: ''Jamaica''. [[Lonely Planet]], 2006 [http://books.google.com/books?id=8ISJuvdhdgAC&amp;pg=PA38#v=snippet&amp;q=rastafarians%20in%20jamaica&amp;f=false p. 38]&lt;/ref&gt;

==World-views and doctrines==
===Jah===
{{rquote|right|... Ethiopia shall soon stretch out her hands unto God.| [[Psalms]] 68:32}}
Rastafari are [[monotheism|monotheists]], worshipping a singular God whom they call [[Jah]]. Jah is the term in the &quot;K.J.V.&quot; (King James Version of the Bible), Psalms 68. Rastas see Jah as being in the form of the [[Holy Trinity]], that is, Father, Son and the Holy Spirit. Rastas say that Jah, in the form of the Holy Spirit (incarnate), lives within the human, and for this reason they often refer to themselves as &quot;I and I&quot;. Furthermore, &quot;I and I&quot; is used instead of &quot;We&quot;, and is used in this way to emphasize the equality between all people, in the belief that the Holy Spirit within all people makes them essentially one and the same.

====The Trinity====
Rasta doctrines concerning the Trinity include stressing the significance of the name &quot;Haile Selassie&quot;, meaning &quot;Power of the Trinity&quot; or &quot;Might of the Trinity&quot; or powerful trinity in [[Ge'ez]]—the name given to Ras Tafari upon his baptism, and later assumed as part of his regal name at his November 2, 1930, coronation by the Ethiopian Orthodox Church.

====Haile Selassie====
[[File:Addis Ababa-8e00855u.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Ethiopian Emperor [[Haile Selassie I of Ethiopia]], considered by Rastas to be Christ.]]

[[Haile Selassie I of Ethiopia|Haile Selassie I]] (1892–1975) was the Emperor of [[Ethiopia]] from 1930 to 1974. Rastas claim that he will lead the righteous into creating a perfect world, called &quot;[[Zion]]&quot;. Zion would be the ultimate paradise for Rastas.

The future capital city of Zion is sometimes put forward as the [[New Jerusalem]] ([[Lalibela, Ethiopia]]), the very Habitation of the Godhead (Trinity) creator, Rastafari. Prophetic verses of the Hebrew [[Bible]] such as ([[Book of Zephaniah|Zephaniah]] 3:10 &quot;From beyond the rivers of Ethiopia My worshipers, the daughter of My dispersed ones, shall bring my offering.&quot;) have been interpreted as subtly hinting that the messianic king will be in Ethiopia, and the people will come from the rest of the world beyond its rivers.

Rastas may say that Haile Selassie's coming was prophesied from [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] to the [[Book of Revelation]].  Genesis, Chapter 1: &quot;God made man in His own image.&quot; [[Psalm 2]]: &quot;Yet I set my Holy king/ On My Holy hill of Zion,&quot; which is identified by them as Jesus Christ. Psalm 87:4–6 is also interpreted as predicting the coronation of Haile Selassie I. During his coronation, Haile Selassie was given many of the same titles used in the Bible: &quot;King of Kings&quot;, &quot;Elect of God&quot;, &quot;Conquering Lion of the Tribe of Judah the Author of Mankind&quot;, &quot;the Power of Authority&quot;, etc., are just some of more than 38 titles and anointments placed on Selassie.  He also received acclaim from various Christian and Muslim leaders and
clergy for the work he performed towards establishing world peace and the brotherhood of mankind. This is one of the primary reasons he is held to be God incarnate. Rastas also refer to Selassie as &quot;His Imperial Majesty&quot; (or the acronym thereof, HIM) and &quot;Jah Rastafari&quot;.

According to tradition, Haile Selassie was the 225th in an unbroken line of Ethiopian monarchs of the [[Solomonic dynasty|Solomonic Dynasty]]. This dynasty is said to have been founded in the 10th century BC by [[Menelik I]], the son of the Biblical [[King Solomon]] and Makeda, the [[Queen of Sheba]], who had visited Solomon in Israel. [[1 Kings]] 10:13 claims &quot;And King Solomon gave unto the Queen of Sheba all her desire, whatsoever she asked, beside that which Solomon gave her of his royal bounty. So she turned and went to her own country, she and her servants.&quot; On the basis of the Ethiopian national epic, the ''[[Kebra Negast]]'', Rastas interpret this verse as meaning she conceived his child, and from this, conclude that African people are among the true children of Israel, or Jews. [[Beta Israel]] black Jews have lived in Ethiopia for centuries, disconnected from the rest of Judaism; their existence has given some impetus to Rastafari, as they believe it validates their assertion that Ethiopia is Zion{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}.

The death of Haile Selassie I is a topic of some debate amongst Rastafari.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dread&quot;/&gt; Some Rastas consider this a partial fulfillment of prophecy of the &quot;Temporary Messianic Kingdom&quot; found in the apocalyptic [[2 Esdras]] 7:28. Some believe that Selassie's 1975 reported death was a hoax. It has also been claimed that he entered the monastery and will return to liberate his followers and vanquish all evil, restoring his creation. &quot;Rastafari's reaction to Selassie's ‘death’ was summed up by Bob Marley's song &quot;Jah Live&quot;, which declares emphatically that &quot;God cannot die&quot;. (RASTAFARI- THE NEW CREATION' by Barbara Makeda Blake Hannah, p.&amp;nbsp;41)

For Rastafari, Haile Selassie remains their God and their King.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barrett252&quot;&gt;''The Rastafarians'' by Leonard E. Barrett, p. 252.&lt;/ref&gt; They see Selassie as being worthy of worship, and as having stood with great dignity in front of the world's press and in front of representatives of many of the world's powerful nations, especially during his appeal to the [[League of Nations]] in 1936, when he was still the only independent black monarch in Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barrett252&quot; /&gt; From the beginning the Rastas decided that their personal loyalty lay with Africa's only black monarch, Selassie, and that they themselves were in effect as free citizens of Ethiopia, loyal to its Emperor and devoted to its flag representing the Solomonic Dynasty prior to the [[Ethiopian Civil War|Communist coup]].

=====Yashew=====
Acceptance of the Jesus-incarnate status of Qedamawi Haile Selassie  is Rastafari doctrine, as is the notion of the corruption of his teachings by secular, Western society, figuratively referred to as ''Babylon''. For this reason, they believe, it was prophesied in the [[Book of Revelation]]—&quot;''And I heard the number of them which were sealed: and there were sealed a hundred and forty and four thousand of all the tribes of the children of Israel.''&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;rev&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Various
|title=The Bible
|year=1611
|edition=King James
|chapter=7:4
|url=http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=%20Revelation%207:4-8&amp;version=9;
|isbn=0-665-89961-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;—that Jesus would return with a new name that would be inscribed on the foreheads of 144,000 of his most devoted servants. Rastas hold that they represent this fulfillment based on their experience in the light of Haile Selassie's return and coronation as the King of Kings on 2 November 1930, whom they see as the second coming of Jesus or the coming of the holy spirit, and therefore [[Jah]], onto the [[Earth]]. Thus the great messiah king whom the [[Jew]]s are still waiting for has indeed now returned to earth, according to the Rastas.

Rastas feel that the way Western Society (or Babylon) has commonly depicted the GodHead as white for centuries to be colonial and racist.

===Zion vs. Babylon===
Rastas assert that [[Zion#Rastafari movement|Zion]] (i.e., Africa, especially Ethiopia) is a land that Jah promised to them. To achieve this, they reject modern [[western world|western society]], calling it &quot;[[Rastafarian vocabulary#Other words|Babylon]]&quot;, which they see as entirely corrupt due to materialism and greed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dread&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=ChantingBabylon&gt;''Chanting Down Babylon'' pp. 342–43.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Edmonds54&gt;Edmonds, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Babylon&quot; is considered to have been in rebellion against &quot;Earth's Rightful Ruler&quot; (Jah) ever since the days of the Biblical king [[Nimrod (king)|Nimrod]].

[[Image:Mount-Zion-Jamaica.JPG|thumb|Mount Zion in Jamaica]]

Rastas claim that they are the real [[Children of Israel]]. The Rastafari seek to validate a link between Ethiopia and Israel, pointing to the title [[Lion of Judah]], and their goal is to repatriate to ''Mount Zion'', that is, Africa. (Rasta [[reggae]] is peppered with references to Zion; among the best-known examples are the [[Bob Marley]] songs '&quot;[[Zion Train]]&quot; and &quot;[[Iron Lion Zion]]&quot;).

====Paradise====
Many Rastafari are physical [[immortality|immortalists]] who maintain that the chosen few will continue to live forever in their current bodies. This is commonly called &quot;Life Everliving&quot;. ''Everliving'' in [[Iyaric]] replaces the term &quot;everlasting&quot; to avoid the &quot;negative wordsound&quot; of ''last'' implying an end. Rastas say their life will never have an end, but will be everliving, with Jah as king and [[Amharic]] the official language. Rastas strongly reject the idea that heaven is in the sky, or is a place where dead people go to&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/rastafari/customs/music.shtml |title=Rastafarian music - Nyabingi |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2009-10-09 |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; and instead see heaven as being a place on Earth, specifically Ethiopia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/birmingham/content/articles/2007/06/15/rastafarian_feature.shtml |title=Life as a Rasta woman |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=1961-07-23 |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Afrocentrism===
[[Afrocentrism]] is another central facet of Rastafari culture. They teach that [[Africa]], in particular [[Ethiopia]], is where Zion, or paradise, shall be created. As such, Rastafari orients itself around African culture.
Rastafari holds that evil society, or &quot;Babylon&quot;, has been [[white race|white]]-dominated since the rise of [[Rome]], and has committed such acts of aggression against the African people as the [[Atlantic slave trade]].

Rastafari developed among poor [[Jamaica]]ns of African descent who felt oppressed and that society was apathetic to their problems. [[Marcus Garvey]] was a keen proponent of the &quot;[[back to Africa]]&quot; movement, advocating that all people of the black race should return to their ancestral homeland of Africa, and worship the Creator &quot;through the spectacles of Ethiopia&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Marcus Garvey, 1921, ''Universal Negro Improvement Association Papers'' p. 603.&lt;/ref&gt;.

In an October 1963 speech before the [[United Nations]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nazret.com/history/him_un.php Haile Selassie address to the United Nations], Oct 6, 1963.&lt;/ref&gt; (which provided the lyrics for the [[Carlton Barrett]] and Bob Marley song &quot;[[War (Bob Marley song)|War]]&quot;), Haile Selassie made the following statement:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Last May, in Addis Ababa, I convened a meeting of Heads of African States and Governments. In three days, the thirty-two nations represented at that Conference demonstrated to the world that when the will and the determination exist, nations and peoples of diverse backgrounds can and will work together. In unity, to the achievement of common goals and the assurance of that equality and brotherhood which we desire.On the question of racial discrimination, the Addis Ababa Conference taught, to those who will learn, this further lesson:
That until the philosophy which holds one race superior and another inferior is finally and permanently discredited and abandoned; That until there are no longer first-class and second-class citizens of any nation; That until the colour of a man's skin is of no more significance than the colour of his eyes; That until the basic human rights are equally guaranteed to all without regard to race; That until that day, the dream of lasting peace and world citizenship and the rule of international morality will remain but a fleeting illusion, to be pursued but never attained; And until the ignoble and unhappy regimes that hold our brothers in Angola, in Mozambique and in South Africa in subhuman bondage have been toppled and destroyed; Until bigotry and prejudice and malicious and inhuman self-interest have been replaced by understanding and tolerance and good-will; Until all Africans stand and speak as free beings, equal in the eyes of all men, as they are in the eyes of Heaven; Until that day, the African continent will not know peace. We Africans will fight, if necessary, and we know that we shall win, as we are confident in the victory of good over evil.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

He concluded this speech with the words, &quot;We must become members of a new race, overcoming petty prejudice, owing our ultimate allegiance not to nations but to our fellow men within the human community.&quot;

Rastafari learn and know [[Amharic]],  both because this was the language of Haile Selassie I, and in order to further their identity as Ethiopian. There are reggae songs written in Amharic.

===The Promised Key===
{{nosources|section|date=September 2012}}
The Rastafari Movement was founded by Leonard Percival &quot;Gong&quot; Howell in 1932. Leonard P. Howell was a Mystic Jamaican born in  the hills of Clarendon, Jamaica in 1898. Howell left Jamaica as a youth  traveling the world over returning to Jamaica from the United States of America on November 17, 1932. He had taken voluntary deportation after his application for citizenship was denied. On his return to Jamaica, he was appalled at the standard of living of the enslaved African people who were now being released from plantation slavery. They were poor, penniless and desolate after hundreds of years of British and Spanish slavery, hungry, suffering yaws, cholera and yellow fever. The governing British were unwilling to help the former slaves and doctors' fees were far more than the majority could afford. Despite being officially freed of slavery, many black Jamaicans were left with no option but to work in the jobs they had previously carried out as slaves, at very low wages. Colonialism left the people with a very low self-image in 1932 Colonial Jamaica. Their knowledge of their ancestral roots in Africa and African royalty had been lost to them through hundreds of years of slavery. Leonard P. Howell saw it as his task to rebuild the broken men and women, his people. He wrote &quot;The Promised Key&quot; the doctrine of Rastafari in Accara, Ghana and many other works which were burnt by the colonial government References :-Daily Gleaner Jamaica, The First Rasta by Helen Lee

He had attended the Coronation of Emperor Haile Selassie and Empress Menen in Ethiopian on November 2, 1930 and knew what the crowning of the Emperor and Empress signified to all African People. Leonard P. Howell had audiences with the Emperor Haile Selassie when he was Supreme Regent of Ethiopia.

Rasta began with Leonard P. Howell and his street preaching to lift the spirits of the enslaved black men and women from Kingston to St Thomas. He was very popular, had a bakery along with his skills as a Naturopathic Doctor which he sustained himself his people and his children. He was tried for sedition in St Thomas,  Jamaica, in the case cause celebre of the assizes. He spoke out against the wrongs of the crown and colonial Jamaica against the men women and children of Africa stolen, sold and enslaved in Jamaica for hundreds of years. He called for International Salvation for all peoples globally while on trial for his life. Howell was found guilty and sentenced to two years imprisonment. On his return, the Rastafari Movement faced a Moraunt Bay rebellion of their own as they were attacked, beaten and robbed for days by the police, Christian populace spurred on by the colonial planters and their acolytes. Days later buses were sent into this tense criminal situation and the Rastafari people and Leonard P. Howell returned to Kingston where he purchased the old abandoned colonial estate at Pinnacle. At Pinnacle, The Rastafari Movement grew and was self-sufficient and self-reliant. However, the settlement was continually raided, robbed, burnt with many incarcerations by the colonial police with their ultimate aim being the fragmentation and destruction of the Rastafari Movement. The Colonial Records, Spanish Town archives

The ''[[Kebra Nagast]]'', the national epic of [[Ethiopia]], is also taken as important amongst many Rastas.  The ''Kebra Nagast'' is an Ethiopic text describing, in greater detail  the relationship between [[King Solomon]] and [[Queen of Sheba]].

===Ceremonies===
There are two types of Rasta religious ceremonies: Reasoning and Groundation.

;Reasoning
A &quot;reasoning&quot; is a simple event where the Rastas gather, smoke [[cannabis (drug)|cannabis]] (&quot;ganja&quot;), and discuss. The person honored by being allowed to light the herb says a short sentence beforehand, and the ganja is passed in a clockwise fashion except in times of war when it is passed counterclockwise, it is used to reason with Jah.

;Groundation
A &quot;groundation&quot; (or &quot;grounation&quot;) or &quot;binghi&quot; is a [[holy day]];&lt;ref name=&quot;jhbradley3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.capetowntocairo.com/travelogue/house-of-judah-nyabinghi-rastafarian-grounation-in-khayalethu-south-township-south-africa-1.htm|title=House of Judah Nyabinghi Rastafarian Grounation in Khayalethu South Township, South Africa|last=Bradley|first=John H. |date=June 2009|work=Cape Town to Cairo Website|publisher=CapeTowntoCairo.com|accessdate=2009-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; the name &quot;binghi&quot; is derived from &quot;[[Nyabinghi]{literally &quot;Nya&quot; meaning &quot;black&quot; and &quot;Binghi&quot; meaning &quot;victory&quot;(Hopkins 259)}]&quot;, believed to be an ancient, and now extinct, order of militant blacks in eastern Africa that vowed to end oppression. Binghis are marked by much dancing, singing, feasting, and the smoking of ganja, and can last for several days.

In public gatherings, Rastafari often say the following standard prayer, with several variants, comparable to the [[Lord's Prayer]]:

:&quot;Princes and princesses shall come forth out of Egypt, Ethiopia now stretch forth her hands before Jah. O Thou God of Ethiopia, Thou God of Thy Divine Majesty, Thy Spirit come into our hearts, to dwell in the paths of righteousness. Lead and help I and I to forgive, that InI may be forgiven. Teach I and I Love and loyalty on earth as it is in Zion, Endow us with Thy wisemind, knowledge and Overstanding to do thy will, thy blessings to us, that the hungry might be fed, the sick nourished, the aged protected, the naked clothed and the infants cared for. Deliver I and I from the hands of our enemy, that I and I may prove fruitful in these Last Days, when our enemy have passed and decayed in the depths of the sea, in the depths of the earth, or in the belly of a beast. O give us a place in Thy Kingdom forever and ever, so we hail our majesty Haile Selassie I, Jehovah God, Rastafari, Almighty God, Rastafari, great and powerful God Jah, Rastafari. Who sitteth and reigneth in the heart of man and woman, hear us and bless us and sanctify us, and cause Thy loving Face to shine upon us thy children, that we may be saved, Selah.&quot;

When lighting a [[chalice (pipe)|chalice]], the following, shorter invocation is often used: &quot;Glory be to the Father and to the Maker of Iration, as it were in the Iginning, is now an shall be foriva, world without end, SELAH.&quot;

Some important dates when groundations may take place are:
* January 7&amp;nbsp;– Ethiopian Orthodox Christmas
* March 25&amp;nbsp;– The birthday of Empress Menen
* April 21&amp;nbsp;– The anniversary of Haile Selassie's visit to Jamaica. Also known as [[Grounation Day]].
* May 25&amp;nbsp;– African Liberation Day
* June 16&amp;nbsp;- The birthday of Leonard P. Howell (founder)
* July 23&amp;nbsp;– The birthday of Emperor Haile Selassie
* August 17&amp;nbsp;– The birthday of Marcus Garvey
* September 11&amp;nbsp;– [[Ethiopian New Year]]
* November 2&amp;nbsp;– The coronation of Haile Selassie

===Places of worship===
[[File:Image HaileSelassieIthefirst.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Haile Selassie I]]
Generally, Rastas assert that their own bodies are the true church or [[temple]] of God, and so see no need to make temples or churches out of physical buildings. However, some Rastafarians have created temples, as some call spiritual meeting centers in international communities with large Rastafarian populations.

===Sects and subdivisions===
{{Main|Mansions of Rastafari}}

There are three main sects or orders of Rastafari today: the Nyahbinghi Order, Bobo Ashanti and the Twelve Tribes of Israel. All agree on the basic principles of
the divine status of Haile Selassie and the importance of black images of divinity. Many
Rastafari do not belong to any sect.

====Nyahbinghi Order====
The Nyahbinghi Order (also known as Haile Selassie I Theocratical Order of the Nyahbinghi  Reign) is the oldest of all the Rastafari mansions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/rastafari/subdivisions/nyahbinghi.shtml |title=The Nyahbinghi Order |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2009-10-12 |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was named after Queen Nyahbinghi of Uganda, who fought against colonialists in the 19th century. The Nyahbinghi Order holds steadfast to ancient biblical values. They consume nothing that harms their body ( drugs, pork, etc., taken from the bible Deuteronomy 14:8 - The pig is also unclean; although it has a split hoof, it does not chew the cud. You are not to eat their meat or touch their carcasses. ) because the body is the temple and the church ( 1 Corinthians 6:19-20 - Do you not know that your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit, who is in you, whom you have received from God?  You are not your own; 20 you were bought at a price.  Therefore honor God with your body  ). The Nyahbinghi Order is a non-violent order that calls upon God's power to execute judgement upon all black and white &quot;downpressors&quot; (oppressors).  This is the oldest of the orders{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} and it focuses mainly on Haile Selassie, Ethiopia, and the eventual return to Africa. It is overseen by an Assembly of Elders.

====Bobo Ashanti====
Bobo Ashanti was founded by Prince [[Charles Edwards (Rastafarian)|Emanuel Charles Edwards]] in Jamaica in 1958.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/rastafari/subdivisions/boboshanti.shtml |title=Bobo Shanti (Bobo Shanti Congress or Ethiopia Black International Congress) |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2009-10-21 |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Bobo&quot; means black and &quot;Ashanti&quot; refers to the Asante ethnic group in Ghana, from which this sect believes Jamaican slaves are descended. Members of Bobo Ashanti are also known as Bobo Dreads.

In belief, Bobo Dreads are distinguished by their worship of Prince Emmanuel (in addition to Marcus Garvey and Haile Selassie) as a reincarnation of Christ and embodiment of Jah; their emphasis on the return to Africa (&quot;repatriation&quot;); and their demands for monetary reimbursement for slavery.

Members of the Bobo Ashanti order wear long robes and tightly wrapped turbans around their dreads. They adhere closely to the Jewish Law, including the observance of [[seventh-day Sabbath]] from sundown Friday to sundown Saturday and hygiene laws for menstruating women. They live separately from Jamaican society and other Rastafarians, growing their own produce and selling straw hats and brooms. They often carry brooms with them to symbolize their cleanliness.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

====Twelve Tribes of Israel====
The Twelve Tribes of Israel sect was founded in 1968 by [[Vernon Carrington|Dr. Vernon &quot;Prophet Gad&quot; Carrington]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/rastafari/subdivisions/twelvetribes.shtml |title=Twelve Tribes of Israel |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2009-10-12 |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the most liberal of the Rastafarian orders and members are free to worship in a church of their choosing. Each member of this sect belongs to one of the 12 Tribes (or Houses), which is determined by birth month and is represented by a color. The Standard Israelite calendar begins in April. The 12 tribes being Reuben, Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Zebulun, Gad, Asher, Joseph, Naphtali, Dan, and Benjamin. Judah being the tribe which all tribes are stemmed from. Joseph, Naphtali, Dan, and Benjamin, all stem from Asher. There are two &quot;lost&quot; tribes known as Manasseh and Ephraim which stem from Joseph. Bob Marley was from the tribe of Joseph, and Haile Selassie from the tribe of Judah.  These Rastafarians consider themselves more of an [[ethnicity]] rather than religion.   They don't have to be dreadlocked or turbaned.   They can be bald or short-haired like that of  [[Bantu]]s, or they can wear  [[afro]]s like that of [[African-Americans]], a style that originated in the 1970s.    They're mostly clean-shaven, although they're sometimes bearded or have neatly trimmed mustaches.

[[File:Flag of Ethiopia (1897).svg|thumb|250px|The [[flag of Ethiopia]] as was used during Selassie's reign. It combines the conquering lion of Judah, symbol of the Ethiopian monarchy, with green, yellow, and red, which would later be adopted by many African nations, becoming [[pan-African colors]].]]

====The Howellites and The Ethiopian Salvation Society====
{{unreferenced section|date=May 2012}}
The Howellites are the Iciency of The Rastafari Movement/Ethiopian salvation Society  which was grounded by [[Leonard Percival Howell]] in 1932. Many of them came with their parents from Trinityville, St Thomas Jamaica to Pinnacle or were born at Pinnacle. All these people were forsaken by society and were ill with yaws and cholera due to colonial neglect. They lived at Pinnacle, the First Industrial Mission, which was the most thriving society in the Caribbean.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}} While life was good at Pinnacle Settlement, they were constantly harassed, abused, imprisoned, beaten and had their property stolen by the colonial and post independence governments of Jamaica.{{The First Rasta by Helen Lee, The Colonial Records Spanish Town |date=May 2012}} In fact Leonard Percival Howell,The Founding Father of the Rastafari Movement was imprisoned and sent to Bellvue Mental Hospital over 50 times. This was the strategy of the colonial government to destroy The Rastafari Movement because many at Pinnacle sought power and money which caused them to form separate cliques in search of personal benefit. The Howellites have no locks since The Rastafari Movement was not grounded in locks. They are very good natured and loving people who love to reason with the yutes.{{The First Rasta by Helen Lee|date=May 2012}} They keep their meetings monthly on the first Sunday at the church in Tredeger Park. Pinnacle was purchased by Leonard Percival Howell and his wife Teneth Bent Howell using all their savings including their jewelry and monies saved from Mr. Howell's bakery businesses. The Pinnacle settlement was raided constantly by the colonial forces and finally burnt and destroyed in 1956. Mr Howell remained at Pinnacle living under the government radar.

===Lion===
{{main|Lion of Judah}}

The Lion of Judah is an important symbol to Rastas, for several reasons. The lion appears on the Imperial Ethiopian flag, used in Haile Selassie I's Ethiopia. In addition, the [[Ge'ez]] title ''Mo`a Anbesa Ze'imnegede Yihuda'' (&quot;Conquering Lion of the Tribe of Judah&quot;) has been applied to Ethiopian Emperors since time immemorial, traditionally beginning with [[Menelik I]], said to be the son of king Solomon (c. 980 BC).  It is unknown whether [[John of Patmos]] was aware of this ancient Ethiopian title when he penned it into the ''Book of Revelation'' 5:5, in reference to the returned Messiah.

===Rastafari and other Abrahamic faiths===
Some Rastafari choose to classify their movement as [[Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church|Ethiopian Orthodox Christianity]], [[Protestant Christianity]], or [[Judaism]]. Rastafari typically hold that standard translations of the Bible incorporate changes, or were edited for the benefit of the power structure, and one common idea is that half the Bible story has never been told.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://litigation-essentials.lexisnexis.com/webcd/app?action=DocumentDisplay&amp;crawlid=1&amp;doctype=cite&amp;docid=33+U.C.+Davis+L.+Rev.+1333&amp;srctype=smi&amp;srcid=3B15&amp;key=17c388bf08ab72be7444d1a3b278ea3f |title=PERFORMING LATCRIT: Half the Story Has Never Been Told: Popular Jamaican Music as Antisubordination Praxis |publisher=Litigation-essentials.lexisnexis.com |date= |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rastas see the lost half of the Bible, and the whole of their lost [[culture]], represented in the [[Ark of the Covenant]], a repository of African wisdom they say is located in Ethiopia.

===Spiritual use of cannabis===
[[File:Cannabis sativa Koehler drawing.jpg|thumb|left|[[Cannabis]]]]
{{See also|Spiritual use of cannabis}}
For Rastas, smoking [[cannabis (drug)|cannabis]], usually known as herb, weed, sinsemilla (Spanish for without seeds), or ganja (from the [[Sanskrit]] word Ganjika, used in ancient India), is a spiritual act, often accompanied by Bible study; they consider it a [[sacrament]] that cleans the body and mind, heals the soul, exalts the consciousness, facilitates peacefulness, brings pleasure, and brings them closer to Jah. They often burn the herb when in need of insight from Jah. Cannabis remains illegal in Jamaica and most of the world and this has caused friction between Rastas and modern societies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abutler1.stu.cofc.edu/ |title=Ganja: Its Move from Society to Religion in the 1960s |publisher=Abutler1.stu.cofc.edu |date= |accessdate=2012-02-27}}{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The burning of the herb is often said to be essential, &quot;For it will sting in the hearts of those that promote and perform evil and wrongs.&quot; By the 8th century, cannabis had been introduced by Arab traders to Central and Southern Africa, where it is known as &quot;[[Cannabis sativa|dagga]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hamid, ''The Ganjah Complex: Rastafari and Marijuana'', introduction, p. xxxii.&lt;/ref&gt; and many Rastas say it is a part of their African culture that they are reclaiming.&lt;ref&gt;''Chanting Down Babylon'', p. 130 ff.&lt;/ref&gt; It is sometimes also referred to as &quot;the healing of the nation&quot;, a phrase adapted from Revelation 22:2.&lt;ref&gt;''Rastafari and Other African-Caribbean Worldviews'' by Barry Chevannes, p. 35, 85; Edmonds, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[indentured labour|migration]] of many thousands of [[Hindu]]s and [[Muslim]]s from [[British India]] to the Caribbean in the 20th century may have brought this culture to Jamaica. Many academics point to Indo-Caribbean origins for the ganja sacrament resulting from the importation of Indian migrant workers in a post-abolition Jamaican landscape. &quot;Large scale use of ganja in Jamaica... dated from the importation of indentured Indians...&quot;(Campbell 110). Dreadlocked mystics [[Dreadlocks#Hinduism|Jata]], often [[asceticism|ascetic]] known as [[sadhu]]s or Sufi [[Qalandar]]s and [[Derwish]]es, have smoked cannabis from both [[Chillum (pipe)|chillums]] and coconut shell [[hookah]]s in [[South Asia]] since the ancient times. Also, the reference of &quot;chalice&quot; may be a transliteration of &quot;jam-e-qalandar&quot; (a term used by [[Sufi]] ascetics meaning 'bowl or cup of [[qalandar]]') . In South Asia, in addition to smoking, cannabis is often consumed as a drink known as [[bhang]] and most qalandars carry a large wooden pestle for that reason. Bhang is often produced in large vessels at [[dargah]] gatherings known as &quot;shaam-e-qalandar&quot;. During these gatherings large [[Naqareh|kettle drum]]s known as [[Naqareh|naggara]] are played or alternatively, the [[Dhol]]. It is known Qalandri dhamaal. Both groups, the [[Qalandar]]'s and [[Sadhu]]'s were lumped together by the British as [[faqeer]]s. They are still frowned upon by the industrious population and are considered &quot;dreadfull&quot;. Yet they are considered holy men by many. Both groups practice either some sort of [[chilla nashini]] or [[yoga]] in remote jungles, mountains or [[charnel ground]]s in which ganja aids to put a veil on the worldly &amp; to transcend the various societal [[Fads and trends|trends]] and pressures. It is also used to induce a state of euphoria and trance by some in conjunction with drumming, dance or whirling.&lt;ref&gt;''Arrow of the Blue-Skinned God: Retracing the Ramayana Through India'', Jonah Blank, p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to many Rastas, the [[Legal issues of cannabis|illegality of cannabis]] in many nations is evidence that [[persecution of Rastafari]] is a reality. They are not surprised that it is illegal, seeing it as a powerful substance that opens people's minds to the truth&amp;nbsp;— something the Babylon system, they reason, clearly does not want.&lt;ref&gt;Edmonds, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; They contrast it to alcohol and other drugs, which they feel destroy the mind.&lt;ref&gt;''Chanting Down Babylon'', p. 354.&lt;/ref&gt;

They hold that the smoking of cannabis enjoys Biblical sanction, and is an aid to meditation and religious observance. Among Biblical verses, Rastas quote as justifying the use of cannabis:
* [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] 1:11 &quot;And God said, Let the earth bring forth grass, the herb yielding seed, and the fruit tree yielding fruit after his kind, whose seed is in itself, upon the earth: and it was so.&quot;
* Genesis 1:29 &quot;And God said, Behold, I have given you every herb-bearing seed, which is upon the face of all the earth, and every tree, in the which is the fruit of a tree yielding seed; to you it shall be for meat.&quot;
* Genesis 3:18 &quot;... thou shalt eat the herb of the field.&quot;
* [[Psalms]] 104:14 &quot;He causeth the grass to grow for the cattle, and herb for the service of man.&quot;
* [[Book of Proverbs|Proverbs]] 15:17 &quot;Better is a dinner of herbs where love is, than a stalled ox and hatred therewith.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bible.cc/proverbs/15-17.htm |title=Proverbs 15:17 Better a meal of vegetables where there is love than a fattened calf with hatred |publisher=Bible.cc |date= |accessdate=2010-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Revelation 22:2 &quot; the river of life proceeded to flow from the throne of God, and on either side of the bank there was the tree of life, and the leaf from that tree is for the healing of the nations.&quot;

According to some Rastafari&lt;ref&gt;''Marijuana and the Bible'', published by the Ethiopian Zion Coptic Church&lt;/ref&gt; and other scholars, the [[cannabis (etymology)|etymology of the word &quot;cannabis&quot;]] and similar terms in all the languages of the Near East may be traced to the Hebrew &quot;qaneh bosm&quot; קנה-בשם, which is one of the herbs that God commanded Moses to include in his preparation of [[holy anointing oil|sacred anointing perfume]] in Exodus 30:23; the Hebrew term also appears in [[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]] 43:24; [[Book of Jeremiah|Jeremiah]] 6:20; [[Book of Ezekiel|Ezekiel]] 27:19; and [[Song of Solomon|Song of Songs]] 4:14. Deutero-canonical and canonical references to the patriarchs [[Adam (Bible)|Adam]], [[Noah]], [[Abraham]], and [[Moses]] &quot;burning incense before the Lord&quot; are also applied, and many Rastas today refer to cannabis by the term &quot;ishence&quot;&amp;nbsp;— a slightly changed form of the English word incense. It is also said that cannabis was the first plant to grow on [[King Solomon]]'s grave.

In 1998, [[Attorney General of the United States]] [[Janet Reno]] gave a legal opinion{{citation needed|date=May 2012}} that Rastafari do not have the religious right to smoke marijuana in violation of the United States' [[War on drugs|drug laws]]. The position is the same in the United Kingdom, where, in the Court of Appeal case of R. v. Taylor [2002] 1 Cr. App. R. 37, it was held that the UK's prohibition on cannabis use did not contravene the right to freedom of religion conferred under the [[European Convention on Human Rights|Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms]].

On January 2, 1991, at an international airport in his homeland of [[Guam]], Ras Iyah Ben Makahna (Benny Guerrero) was arrested for possession and importation of marijuana and seeds. He was charged with importation of a controlled substance. The case was heard by the US 9th Circuit Court November 2001, and in May 2002 the court had decided that the practice of Rastafari sanctions the smoking of marijuana, but nowhere does the religion sanction the importation of marijuana. Guerrero's lawyer Graham Boyd pointed out that the court's ruling was &quot;equivalent to saying wine is a necessary sacrament for some Christians but you have to grow your own grapes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;See: Case No. 00-71247 United States Court of Appeals, Ninth Circuit www.ca9.uscourts.gov/coa/newopinions.nsf/55215A562F6A670188256BC7005C6CC5/$file/0071247.pdf?openelement&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2008, however, the [[Court of Cassation (Italy)|Italian Supreme Court]] ruled that Rastafari may be allowed to possess greater amounts of cannabis legally, owing to its use by them as a sacrament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idUSL1041616220080710 |title=Rasta pot smokers win legal leeway in Italy |publisher=Reuters |date=2008-07-10 |accessdate=2010-02-01 | first=Phil | last=Stewart}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.aol.com/story/_a/rasta-smoker-wins-appeal-of-marijuana/n20080711112609990016 AOL News&amp;nbsp;– Rasta smoker wins appeal of marijuana conviction]{{Dead link|date=February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Politics==
Rastafari culture does not encourage mainstream political involvement. In fact, in the early stages of the movement most Rastas did not [[vote]], out of principle. Ras [[Sam Brown (Rasta)|Sam Brown]] formed the Suffering People's Party for the Jamaican elections of 1962 and received fewer than 100 votes. In the election campaign of 1972, [[People's National Party]] leader [[Michael Manley]] used a prop, a walking stick given to him by Haile Selassie, which was called the &quot;Rod of Correction&quot;, in a direct appeal to Rastafari values.

In the famous free [[One Love Peace Concert]] on April 22, 1978, [[Peter Tosh]] lambasted the audience, including attending dignitaries, with political demands that included [[Legality of cannabis|decriminalising]] [[cannabis (drug)|cannabis]]. He did this while smoking a [[Joint (cannabis)|spliff]], a criminal act in Jamaica. At this same concert, [[Bob Marley]] led both then-Prime Minister [[Michael Manley]] and opposition leader [[Edward Seaga]] onto the stage; and a famous picture was taken with all three of them holding their hands together above their heads in a symbolic gesture of peace during what had been a very violent election campaign.

In 1996, the International Rastafari Development Society was given [[Consultative Status|consultative status]] by the [[United Nations]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/documents/ecosoc/docs/1996/e1996-102.htm |title=UN Report of the Committee on Non-Governmental Organizations |publisher=Un.org |date= |accessdate=2010-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Equality===
:''&quot;He [the Almighty] taught us that all human beings are equal regardless of sex, national origin and tribe. And He also taught us all who seek Him shall find Him.&quot;'' -- Haile Selassie I, Dec. 1968 interview with Dr. [[Oswald Hoffman]] on 'The Lutheran Hour'.

Per Haile Selassie's consistent lifelong message, Rastas tend to be firm adherents to the proposition that in the eyes of Jah, all men and women deserve equal and just rights, treatment and respect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A734924 |title=Rastafarianism |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; With both King Alpha and his Queen Omega as shining examples, Rasta ''bredren'' and ''sistren'' (collectively ''idren'') seek to emulate kings and queens according mutual respect and dignity. It is this belief in equality among Rastas that allows race to be overlooked. Simply because one is white does not mean it can not be a Rasta. All people are equal, regardless of race, because all people are children of Jah.

However, in terms of sexual orientation, there are many in the Rastafari movement (like most other biblical religions) who consider homosexual behaviour to be a Babylon-promoted [[sin]] against the Creator (see [[LGBT rights in Jamaica]]), and therefore question organized homosexual activists' demands for their lifestyle to enjoy &quot;equality&quot; with more traditional, reproductive lifestyles. The Bobo Ashanti mansion has been noted for this; with other mansions it tends to vary.

==Culture==
===Language===
{{Main|Rastafari vocabulary}}
Rastas assert that their original [[African languages]] were stolen from them when they were taken into captivity as part of the slave trade, and that English is an imposed [[colonialism|colonial]] [[language]]. Their remedy has been the creation of a modified vocabulary and [[Dialects of English|dialect]] known as &quot;Iyaric&quot;, reflecting their desire to take language forward and to confront the society they call Babylon.

Some examples are:
* &quot;[[I-tal]]&quot;, derived from the word vital and used to describe the diet of the movement which is taken mainly from Hebrew dietary laws.
* &quot;Overstanding&quot;, which replaces &quot;understanding&quot; to denote an enlightenment which places one in a better position.
* &quot;Irie&quot; (pronounced &quot;eye-ree&quot;), a term used to denote acceptance, positive feelings, or to describe something that is good.
* &quot;Upfulness&quot;, a positive term for being helpful
* &quot;Livication&quot;, substituted for the word &quot;dedication&quot; because Rastas associate dedication with death.
* &quot;Downpression&quot;, used in place of &quot;oppression&quot;, the logic being that the pressure is being applied from a position of power to put down the victim.

One of the most distinctive modifications in Iyaric is the substitution of the pronoun &quot;I and I&quot; for other pronouns, usually the first person. &quot;I&quot;, as used in the examples above, refers to Jah; therefore, &quot;I and I&quot; in the first person includes the presence of the divine within the individual. As &quot;I and I&quot; can also refer to us, them, or even you. It is used as a practical linguistic rejection of the separation of the individual from the larger Rastafari community, and Jah himself.

Rastafari say that they reject -isms. They see a wide range of -isms and schisms in modern society, for example communism and capitalism, and want no part in them. For example, [[Haile Selassie]] himself was an [[anti-communist]] during the [[cold war]], and was deposed by a [[Marxist]] coup. Rastafarians would reject [[Marxism]] as part of the Babylonian system or, at the very least, just another version of western [[Humanism]]. They especially reject the word &quot;Rastafarianism&quot;, because they see themselves as &quot;having transcended -isms and schisms&quot;. This has created conflict between some Rastas and some members of the academic community studying Rastafari, who insist on calling this faith &quot;Rastafarianism&quot; in spite of the disapproval this generates within the Rastafari movement. Nevertheless, the practice continues among scholars, though there are also instances of the study of Rastafari using its own terms.&lt;ref&gt;Professor Rex Nettleford, Ceremonial Address on Behalf of University of West Indies to &quot;Marley's Music: Reggae, Rastafari, and Jamaican Culture&quot; conference, in ''Bob Marley: The Man and His Music'' (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diet===
{{Main|Ital}}
Many Rastas eat limited types of meat in accordance with the dietary Laws of the [[Old Testament]]; they do not eat [[shellfish]] or pork. Others abstain from all meat and flesh whatsoever, asserting that to touch meat is to touch [[death]], and is therefore a violation of the [[Nazirite]] vow. (A few make a special exception allowing fish, while abstaining from all other forms of flesh.) However, the prohibition against meat only applies to those who are currently fulfilling a [[Nazirite]] vow (&quot;Dreadlocks Priesthood&quot;), for the duration of the vow. Many Rastafari maintain a [[vegan]] or [[vegetarian]] diet all of the time. Food approved for Rastafari is called [[ital]]. The purpose of fasting (abstaining from meat and dairy) is to cleanse the body in accordance to serving in the presence of the &quot;Ark of the Covenant&quot;.

Usage of [[alcohol]] is also generally deemed unhealthy to the Rastafari way of life, partly because it is seen as a tool of Babylon to confuse people, and partly because placing something that is pickled and fermented within oneself is felt to be much like turning the body (the Temple) into a &quot;cemetery&quot;.{{citation needed|date=May 2012}}

In consequence, a rich alternative cuisine has developed in association with Rastafari tenets, eschewing most synthetic additives, and preferring more natural vegetables and fruits such as coconut and mango. This cuisine can be found throughout the Caribbean and in some restaurants throughout the western world.

Some of the Houses (or &quot;Mansions&quot; as they have come to be known) of the Rastafari culture, such as the Twelve Tribes of Israel, do not specify diet beyond that which, to quote Christ in the New Testament, &quot;Is not what goes into a man's mouth that defile him, but what come out of it&quot;. Wine is seen as a &quot;mocker&quot; and strong drink is &quot;raging&quot;; however, simple consumption of beer or the very common [[roots wine]] are not systematically a part of Rastafari culture this way or that. Separating from Jamaican culture, different interpretations on the role of food and drink within the religion remains up for debate. At official state banquets Haile Selassie would encourage guests to &quot;eat and drink in your own way&quot;.

===Locks===
{{Main|Dreadlocks}}
[[File:Buju Banton (Apollo theater, 2007).jpg|thumb|200px|Buju Banton performing at New York's Apollo theater during the 26th International Reggae &amp; World Music Awards (IRAWMA).]]
The wearing of dreadlocks is very closely associated with the movement, though not universal among, nor exclusive to, its adherents. Rastas maintain that locks are supported by [[Leviticus]] 21:5 (&quot;They shall not make baldness upon their head, neither shall they shave off the corner of their [[beard]], nor make any cuttings in the flesh.&quot;) and the ''[[Nazirite]] vow'' in [[Book of Numbers|Numbers]] 6:5 (&quot;All the days of the vow of his separation there shall no razor come upon his head: until the days be fulfilled, in the which he separateth himself unto the Lord, he shall be holy, and shall let the locks of the hair of his head grow.&quot;).

It has been suggested (e.g., Campbell 1985) that the first Rasta locks were copied from Kenya in 1953, when images of the independence struggle of the feared [[Mau Mau Uprising|''mau mau'' insurgents]], who grew their &quot;dreaded locks&quot; while hiding in the mountains, appeared in newsreels and other publications that reached Jamaica. However, a more recent study by Barry Chevannes&lt;ref&gt;Barry Chevannes, 1998 ''Rastafari and Other African-Caribbean Worldviews'', chapter 4&lt;/ref&gt; has traced the first hairlocked Rastas to a subgroup first appearing in 1949, known as Youth Black Faith.
[[File:Dreadlocked rasta.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Man with thick locks.]]

There have been ascetic groups within a variety of world faiths that have at times worn similarly matted hair. In addition to the [[Nazirite]]s of Judaism and the [[sadhu]]s of Hinduism, it is worn among some sects of [[Sufi]] Islam, notably the Baye Fall sect of [[Mouride]]s,&lt;ref&gt;''Islamic Society and State Power in Senegal'', p. 167 by Leonardo Alfonso Villalón 1995&lt;/ref&gt; and by some [[Ethiopian Orthodox]] [[monk]]s in Christianity,&lt;ref&gt;Neil J. Savinsky in ''Chanting Down Babylon'' pp. 133, 143 fn.#37; citing David Buxton, ''The Abyssinians'', p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; among others. Some of the very earliest Christians may also have worn this hairstyle; particularly noteworthy are descriptions of [[James the Just]], &quot;brother of Jesus&quot; and first Bishop of Jerusalem, whom [[Hegesippus (chronicler)|Hegesippus]] (according to Eusebius&lt;ref&gt;Eusebius of Caesarea, ''The Ecclesiastical History'', book 2, chapter 23&lt;/ref&gt; and Jerome) described as a Nazirite who never once cut his hair. The length of a Rasta's locks is a measure of wisdom, maturity, and knowledge in that it can indicate not only the Rasta's age, but also his/her time as a Rasta.

Also, according to the Bible, [[Samson]] was a Nazarite who had &quot;seven locks&quot;. Rastas argue that these &quot;seven locks&quot; could only have been dreadlocks,&lt;ref&gt;The Kebra Negast: The Lost Bible of Rastafarian Wisdom and Faith, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; as it is unlikely to refer to seven strands of hair.

Locks have also come to symbolize the [[Lion of Judah]] (its mane) and rebellion against Babylon. In the [[United States]], several public schools and workplaces have lost lawsuits as the result of banning locks. [[Safeway Inc.|Safeway]] is an early example, and the victory of eight children in a suit against their [[Lafayette, Louisiana]] school was a landmark decision in favor of Rastafari rights.  More recently{{when|date=May 2011}}, a group of Rastas settled a federal lawsuit with the Grand Central Partnership in New York City, allowing them to wear their locks in neat ponytails, rather than be forced to &quot;painfully tuck in their long hair&quot; in their uniform caps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=The Associated Press |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/ny_local/2009/08/08/2009-08-08_rastafarians_win_suit_allowing_them_to_bare_dreadlocks_at_work.html |title=Rastafarians win suit allowing them to bare dreadlocks at work |publisher=Nydailynews.com |date=2009-08-08 |accessdate=2010-02-01 | location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rastafari associate dreadlocks with a spiritual journey that one takes in the process of locking their hair (growing hairlocks). It is taught that patience is the key to growing locks, a journey of the mind, soul and spirituality. Its spiritual pattern is aligned with the Rastafari movement. The way to form natural dreadlocks is to allow hair to grow in its natural pattern, without cutting, combing or brushing, but simply to wash it with pure water.

For the Rastas the [[razor]], the [[scissors]] and the [[comb]] are the three Babylonian or Roman inventions.&lt;ref&gt;cf. ''Chanting Down Babylon'' p. 32; ''The Kebra Nagast: The Lost Bible of Rastafarian Wisdom and Faith'' by Gerlad Hausman p. 48; ''Rastafarianism''by Gerhardus Cornelis Oosthuizen p. 16; ''An Educator's Classroom Guide to America's Religious Beliefs and Practices'' p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; So close is the association between dreadlocks and Rastafari, that the two are sometimes used synonymously. In reggae music, a follower of Rastafari may be referred to simply as a &quot;dreadlocks&quot; or &quot;natty (natural) dread&quot;.

As important and connected with the movement as the wearing of locks is, though, it is not deemed necessary for, or equivalent to, true faith. Popular slogans, often incorporated within reggae lyrics, include: &quot;Not every dread is a Rasta and not every Rasta is a dread...&quot;; &quot;It's not the dread upon your head, but the love inna your heart, that mek ya Rastaman&quot; (Sugar Minott); and as [[Morgan Heritage]] sings: &quot;You don't haffi dread to be Rasta...&quot;, and &quot;Children of Selassie I, don't lose your faith; whether you do or don't have your locks 'pon your head...&quot; Some Rastafarians may eschew dreadlocks,&lt;ref&gt;[http://jamaica-gleaner.com/gleaner/20080427/out/out1.html ''&quot;You don't have to grow your hair to be a Rasta. It's in your heart, not how you look,&quot;''], [[Courtenay Griffiths]] quoted in the Jamaica-Gleaner&lt;/ref&gt; either as a means of avoiding persecution or for practical reasons, especially in as they may be a liability in many industrial jobs as it may get trapped in machinery.
Many non-Rastafari of African descent wear locks as an expression of pride in their ethnic identity, or simply as a hairstyle, and take a less purist approach to developing and grooming them. The wearing of dreads also has spread among people of other ethnicities, including those whose hair is not naturally suited to the style, and who sometimes go to great lengths to form them. Locks worn for stylish reasons are sometimes referred to as &quot;bathroom locks&quot;, to distinguish them from the kind that are purely natural. Rasta purists also sometimes refer to such dreadlocked individuals as &quot;wolves&quot;, as in &quot;a wolf in sheep's clothing&quot;, especially when they are seen as trouble-makers who might potentially discredit or infiltrate Rastafari.&lt;ref&gt;''Chanting Down Babylon'', p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the spread of dreadlocks in popular culture, they have even appeared in the comic book medium, most notably The [[X-Men]]'s [[Bishop (comics)|Bishop]] and the [[Dread &amp; Alive]] comic book series.

===Green, Gold, and Red===
[[File:AfricanAmerica.svg|thumb|Flag of the United States, re-colored with the colors of the Rastafarian flag.]]
[[File:Rasta Man Barbados.jpg|thumb|left|Rastaman in [[Barbados]], wearing the Rastafarian colors of green, gold, red and black on a [[rastacap]].]]
The Rastafarian colours of green, gold and red (sometimes also including black) are very commonly sported on Rastafarian flag, badges, posters etc. The green, gold and red are the colors of the [[Ethiopian flag]] and show the loyalty Rastafari feel towards the Ethiopian state in the reign of King Selassie. The red, black and green were the colors used to represent Africa by the [[Marcus Garvey]] movement. Red is said to signify the blood of martyrs, green the vegetation and beauty of Ethiopia, and gold the wealth of Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=iesWzLHb_GUC&amp;pg=PA134 |title='&amp;#39;Chanting Down Babylon: the Rastafari reader'&amp;#39;, p. 134 |publisher=Books.google.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-02-01|isbn=978-1-56639-584-7|author1=Murrell, Nathaniel Samuel|author2=Spencer, William David|author3=McFarlane, Adrian Anthony|year=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=u0P24iQ0LRAC&amp;pg=PA156 |title=An educator's classroom guide to America's religious beliefs and practices, p. 156 |publisher=Books.google.co.uk |date= 2007-04|accessdate=2010-02-01|isbn=978-1-59158-409-4|author1=Hubbard, Benjamin Jerome|author2=Hatfield, John T|author3=Santucci, James A}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Music===
{{Music of Jamaica}}
[[Music]] has long played an integral role in Rastafari, and the connection between the movement and various kinds of music has become well known, due to the international fame of [[reggae]] musicians such as [[Bob Marley]] and [[Peter Tosh]].

[[Niyabinghi chants]] are played at worship ceremonies called [[grounation]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;jhbradley3&quot;/&gt; that include drumming, chanting and dancing, along with [[prayer]] and ritual [[cannabis smoking|smoking]] of [[cannabis (drug)|cannabis]]. The name ''Nyabinghi'' comes from an [[East Africa]]n movement from the 1850s to the 1950s that was led by people who militarily opposed European [[imperialism]]. This form of nyabinghi was centered around [[Muhumusa]], a healing woman from [[Uganda]] who organized resistance against [[Germany|German]] colonialists. In Jamaica, the concepts of Nyabinghi were appropriated for similar anti-colonial efforts, and it is often danced to invoke the power of [[Jah]] against an oppressor.

African music survived [[slavery]] because many slaveowners encouraged it as a method of keeping morale high.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}} Afro-Caribbean music arose with the influx of influences from the native peoples of Jamaica, as well as the European slaveowners.

Another style of Rastafari music is called ''[[burru]]'' drumming, first played in the Parish of [[Clarendon, Jamaica]], and then in [[Kingston, Jamaica|West Kingston]]. Burru was later introduced to the burgeoning Rasta community in Kingston by a Jamaican musician named [[Count Ossie]]. He mentored many influential Jamaican ska, rock steady, and reggae musicians. Through his tutelage, they began combining New Orleans [[R&amp;B]], folk [[mento]], [[jonkanoo]], [[kumina]], and revival zion into a unique sound. The burru style, which centers on three drums&amp;nbsp;— the bass, the alto [[fundeh]], and the repeater&amp;nbsp;— would later be copied by hip hop DJs.&lt;ref name=JeffChang&gt;Jeff Chang ''Can't Stop, Won't Stop.'' 2005: St. Martin's Press. pp. 24–25.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Reggae====
{{Main|Reggae}}
[[Image:Bob-Marley-in-Concert Zurich 05-30-80.jpg|thumb|Reggae musician [[Bob Marley]] did much to raise international awareness of the Rastafari movement]]
Reggae was born amidst poor blacks in [[Trenchtown]], the main ghetto of [[Kingston, Jamaica]], who listened to radio stations from the [[United States]]. Jamaican musicians, many of them Rastas, soon blended traditional Jamaican folk music and drumming with American R&amp;B, and jazz into [[ska]], that later developed into reggae under the influence of soul.

Reggae began to enter international consciousness in the early 1970s, and Rastafari mushroomed in popularity internationally, largely due to the fame of [[Bob Marley]], who actively and devoutly preached Rastafari, incorporating [[Niyabinghi chants|Nyabinghi]] and Rastafarian chanting into his music, lyrics and album covers. Songs like &quot;Rastaman Chant&quot; led to the movement and reggae music being seen as closely intertwined in the consciousness of audiences across the world. Other famous reggae musicians with strong Rastafarian elements in their music include [[Peter Tosh]], [[Freddie McGregor]], [[Toots &amp; the Maytals]], [[Burning Spear]], [[Black Uhuru]], [[Lincoln Thompson|Prince Lincoln Thompson]], [[Bunny Wailer]], [[Prince Far I]], [[Israel Vibration]], [[The Congos]], [[Adrian Nones]], [[Cornell Campbell]], [[Dennis Brown]] and hundreds more.

;Reggae music expressing Rasta doctrine
The first reggae single that sang about Rastafari and reached Number 1 in the Jamaican charts was ''Bongo Man'' by [[Little Roy]] in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Lamaar, Radio 2&lt;/ref&gt; Early Rasta [[reggae]] musicians (besides [[Bob Marley|Marley]]) whose music expresses Rastafari doctrine well are [[Peter Tosh]], [[Bunny Wailer]] (in ''Blackheart Man''), [[Prince Far I]], [[Linval Thompson]], [[Ijahman Levi]] (especially the first 4 albums), [[Misty-in-Roots]] (''Live''), [[The Congos]] (''Heart of the Congos''), [[The Rastafarians]], [[The Abyssinians]], [[Culture (band)|Culture]], [[Big Youth]], and [[Ras Michael]] And The Sons Of Negus. The Jamaican [[jazz]] [[percussionist]] [[Count Ossie]], who had played on a number of ska and reggae recordings, recorded albums with themes relating to Rasta history, doctrine, and culture.

Rastafari doctrine as developed in the 1980s was further expressed musically by a number of other prominent artists, such as [[Burning Spear]], [[Steel Pulse]], [[Third World]], [[The Gladiators (band)|The Gladiators]], [[Black Uhuru]], [[Aswad (band)|Aswad]], and [[Israel Vibration]]. Rastafari ideas have spread beyond the Jamaican community to other countries including Russia, where artists such as [[Jah Division]] write songs about Jah, and South Africa where [[Lucky Dube]] first learned reggae music from [[Peter Tosh]] recordings. Afro-American [[Punk rock|punk]] band [[Bad Brains]] are notable followers of the Rastafari movement and have written songs (&quot;I Against I&quot;, etc.) that promote the doctrine.

In the 21st century, Rastafari sentiments are spread through [[roots reggae]] and dancehall, subgroups of reggae music, with many of their most important proponents promoting the Rastafari religion, such as [[Capleton]], [[Sizzla]], [[Anthony B]], [[Barrington Levy]],  [[Jah Mason]], [[Pressure (singer)|Pressure]], [[Midnite]], [[Natural Black]], [[Luciano (singer)|Luciano]], [[Cocoa Tea (singer)|Cocoa Tea]], [[Jah Cure]] and [[Richie Spice]]. Several of these acts have gained mainstream success and frequently appear on the popular music charts. Most recently artists such as [[Damian Marley]] (son of Bob Marley), [[Alborosie]] and [[Million Stylez]] have blended hip-hop with reggae to re-energize classic Rastafari issues such as social injustice, revolution and the honour and responsibility of parenthood using contemporary musical style.

Berlin-based dub techno label &quot;[[Basic Channel]]&quot; has subsidiary labels called &quot;[[Rhythm &amp; Sound (record label)|Rhythm &amp; Sound]]&quot; and &quot;Burial Mix&quot; whose lyrics strongly focus on many aspects of Rastafari culture and ideology, including the acceptance of Haile Selassie I. Notable tracks include &quot;Jah Rule&quot;, &quot;Mash Down Babylon&quot;, &quot;We Be Troddin'&quot;, and &quot;See Mi Yah&quot;.  Irish singer-songwriter [[Sinéad O'Connor]] released two rastafari/roots reggae CDs{{spaced ndash}}&quot;[[Throw Down Your Arms]]&quot; and &quot;[[Theology (album)|Theology]]&quot;.

===Film===
{{Expand section|date=March 2010}}
There are several Jamaican films important to the history of Rastafari, such as ''[[Rockers (1978 film)|Rockers]]'', ''[[The Harder They Come]]'', ''[[Land of Look Behind]]'', ''[[Countryman (film)|Countryman]]'' and ''[[Babylon (film)|Babylon]]''.

==History==
===Ethiopian world view===
Before Garvey, there had been two major circumstances that proved conducive to the conditions that established a fertile ground for the incubation of Rastafari in Jamaica: the history of resistance, exemplified by the [[Maroon (people)|Maroons]], and the forming of an Afrocentric, Ethiopian [[world view]] with the spread of such religious movements as [[Bedwardism]], which flourished from the 1890s to the 1920s. These groups had long carried a tradition of what musician [[Bob Marley]] referred to as &quot;resisting against the system&quot;.

====Marcus Garvey====
{{Main|Marcus Garvey}}
[[File:Marcus Garvey 1924-08-05.jpg|thumb|right|240px|Marcus Garvey]]
Rastas see Marcus Mosiah Garvey as a prophet, with his philosophy fundamentally shaping the movement, and with many of the early Rastas having started out as [[Garveyism|Garveyites]]. He is often seen as a second [[John the Baptist]]. One of the most famous prophecies attributed to him involving the coronation of Haile Selassie I was the 1927 pronouncement &quot;Look to Africa, for there a black king shall be crowned,&quot; although an associate of Garvey's, [[James Morris Webb]], had made very similar public statements as early as 1921.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rastaites.com/repatriationnews/09repatriation.htm ]{{Dead link|date=February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://rastaites.com/news/hearticals/IRIEbarbados.htm IRIE Barbados Groundation Report&lt;!--Bot-generated title--&gt;]{{Dead link|date=February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marcus Garvey promoted [[Black Nationalism]], [[black separatism]], and [[Pan-Africanism]]: the belief that all black people of the world should join in brotherhood and work to decolonise the continent of Africa&amp;nbsp;— then still controlled by the white colonialist powers.

He promoted his cause of black pride throughout the 1920s and 1930s, and was particularly successful and influential among lower-class blacks in Jamaica and in rural communities. Although his ideas have been hugely influential in the development of Rastafari culture, Garvey never identified himself with the movement. Garvey was even critical of Haile Selassie for leaving Ethiopia at the time of the Italian Fascist occupation, &quot;[[Hailie Selassie]] is the ruler of a country where black men are chained and flogged...He will go down in history as a great coward who ran away from his country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;E. David Cronon, ''Black Moses'', University of Wisconsin Press, Madison, (1955) 1966, p.162&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, his Universal Negro Improvement Association disagreed with [[Leonard Howell]] over Howell's teaching that Haile Selassie was the Messiah. Rastafari nonetheless may be seen as an extension of Garveyism. In early Rasta folklore, it is the ''[[Black Star Line]]r'' (actually a shipping company bought by Garvey to encourage repatriation to [[Liberia]]) that takes them home to Africa.

===Other early written foundations===
Although not strictly speaking a &quot;Rastafari&quot; document, the ''[[Holy Piby]]'', written by [[Robert Athlyi Rogers]] from [[Anguilla]] in the 1920s, is acclaimed by many Rastafarians as a formative and primary source. Robert Athlyi Rogers founded an Afrocentric religion known as &quot;Athlicanism&quot; in the US and West Indies in the 1920s. Rogers' religious movement, the Afro-Athlican Constructive Church, saw Ethiopians (in the Biblical sense of all Black Africans) as the chosen people of God, and proclaimed Marcus Garvey, the prominent Black Nationalist, an apostle. The church preached self-reliance and self-determination for Africans.

The [[Royal Parchment Scroll of Black Supremacy]], written during the 1920s by a preacher called [[Fitz Balintine Pettersburg]], is a surrealistic stream-of-consciousness polemic against the white colonial power structure that is also considered formative, a [[wikt:palimpsest|palimpsest]] of Afrocentric thought.

The first document to appear that can be labelled as truly Rastafari was [[Leonard P. Howell]]'s ''[[The Promise Key]]'', written using the pen name G.G. [for ''Gangun-Guru''] Maragh, in the early 1930s. In it, he claims to have witnessed the Coronation of the Emperor and Empress on 2 November 1930 in [[Addis Ababa]], and proclaims the doctrine that H.I.M. Ras Tafari is the true Head of Creation and that the King of England is an imposter. This tract was written while Howell was jailed on charges of sedition.

===Emergence===
[[File:Selassie restored.jpg|thumb|right|Selassie I in the 1930s]]
Emperor [[Haile Selassie I]] was crowned &quot;King of Kings, Elect of God, and Conquering Lion of the Tribe of Judah&quot; in [[Addis Ababa]] on November 2, 1930. The event created great publicity throughout the world, including in Jamaica, and particularly through two consecutive ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine articles about the coronation (he was later named ''Time'''s [[Time Magazine Person of the Year|Person of the Year]] for 1935, the first Black person to appear on the cover), as well as two consecutive ''[[National Geographic (magazine)|National Geographic]]'' issues around the same time. Haile Selassie almost immediately gained a following as both God and [[Monarch|King]] amongst poor Jamaicans, who came to be known as Rastafarians, and who looked to their Bibles, and saw what they believed to be the fulfilling of many prophecies from the book of [[Book of Revelation|Revelation]]. As Ethiopia was the only African country to be free from colonialism, and Haile Selassie was the only black leader accepted among the kings and queens of Europe, the early Rastas viewed him with great reverence.

Over the next two years, three Jamaicans who all happened to be overseas at the time of the coronation, each returned home and independently began, as street preachers, to proclaim the divinity of the newly crowned Emperor as the returned Christ,&lt;ref name=Barrett81&gt;''The Rastafarians'' by Leonard E. Barrett, pp. 81–82&lt;/ref&gt; arising from their interpretations of Biblical prophecy and based partly on Haile Selassie's status as the only African monarch of a fully independent state, with the titles ''King of Kings'' and ''Conquering [[Lion of Judah]]'' ([[Book of Revelation|Revelation]] 5:5).

First, on 8 December 1930, [[Archibald Dunkley]], formerly a seaman, landed at [[Port Antonio]] and soon began his ministry; in 1933, he relocated to Kingston where the ''King of Kings Ethiopian Mission'' was founded. [[Joseph Hibbert]] returned from [[Costa Rica]] in 1931 and started spreading his own conviction of the Emperor's divinity in Benoah district, [[Saint Andrew Parish, Jamaica|Saint Andrew Parish]], through his own ministry, called ''Ethiopian Coptic Faith''; he too moved to Kingston the next year, to find [[Leonard Howell]] already teaching many of these same doctrines, having returned to Jamaica around the same time. With the addition of [[Robert Hinds]], himself a Garveyite and former Bedwardite, these four preachers soon began to attract a following among Jamaica's poorer classes, who were already beginning to look to Ethiopia for moral support.

===Leonard Percival Howell===
{{Main|Leonard Howell}}
Leonard Percival Howell, who has been described as the &quot;First Rasta&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;''The First Rasta: Leonard Howell and the Rise of Rastafarianism'' by Helene Lee, 1999&lt;/ref&gt; became the first to be [[Persecution of Rastafari|persecuted]], charged with [[sedition]] for refusing loyalty to the [[Monarch|King]] of [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|Great Britain and Ireland]], [[George V of the United Kingdom|George V]]. The [[United Kingdom|British]] [[government]] would not tolerate Jamaicans loyal to Haile Selassie in what was then a British colony. When he was released, he formed a [[settlement (intentional community)|settlement]] called Pinnacle, at St. Catherine in [[Jamaica]] in 1939 on {{convert|500|acre|km2}} of land which attracted as many as 4,000 people.&lt;ref&gt;''Rastafari: From Outcasts to Culture Bearers'' by Ennis Barrington Edmonds, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.jamaica-gleaner.com/gleaner/20070228/letters/letters3.html |title=Sligoville heritage |publisher=Jamaica Gleaner |date=2007-02-28 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reports surfaced that the Rastas were urging the communities around them not to pay taxes to the government.  In 1941, the police raided the community and   Howell and his followers were sent to prison.  After they got out they tried to resurrect the Pinnacle community, but the police kept raiding it.  The raids by colonial and post colonial forces destroyed the Pinnacle, and dispersed the dispossessed Rastafari  into the slums of Jamaica.&lt;ref&gt;Rhythms of Resistance: Histories of Musical Opposition and Affirmation from Around the World, composed by David McMurray, edited by Tom Tucker ISBN 978-1-4266-3533-5  p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;

===Visit of Selassie I to Jamaica===
Haile Selassie I had already met with several Rasta elders in [[Addis Ababa]] in 1961, giving them gold medals, and had allowed West Indians of African descent to settle on his personal land in [[Shashamane]] in the 1950s. The first actual Rastafarian settler, Papa [[Noel Dyer]], arrived in September 1965, having hitch-hiked all the way from England.

[[Haile Selassie]] visited [[Jamaica]] on April 21, 1966. Approximately one hundred thousand Rastafari from all over Jamaica descended on [[Norman Manley International Airport|Kingston airport]], it having been announced that Selassie was coming to visit them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neurope.eu/articles/21-April--Today-in-History/100364.php |title=21 April&amp;nbsp;– Today in History |publisher=New Europe Issue 882 |date=21 April 2010 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; They waited at the airport smoking a great amount of cannabis and playing drums. When Haile Selassie arrived at the airport he delayed disembarking from the aeroplane for an hour until [[Mortimer Planno]], a well-known Rasta, personally welcomed him. From then on, the visit was a success. [[Rita Marley]], Bob Marley's wife, converted to the Rastafari faith after seeing Haile Selassie; she has stated that she saw [[stigmata]] appear on his person, and was instantly convinced of his divinity.

The great significance of this event in the development of the Rastafari movement should not be underestimated. Having been outcasts in society, they gained a temporary respectability for the first time. By making Rasta more acceptable, it opened the way for the commercialisation of reggae, leading in turn to the further global spread of Rastafari.

Because of Haile Selassie's visit, April 21 is celebrated as [[Grounation Day]]. It was during this visit that Selassie I famously told the Rastafari community leaders that they should not immigrate to Ethiopia until they had first liberated the people of Jamaica. This dictum came to be known as &quot;[[liberty|liberation]] before [[repatriation]]&quot;.

===Walter Rodney===
In 1968, [[Walter Rodney]], a Guyanese national, author, and professor at the University of the West Indies, published a pamphlet titled ''The Groundings with My Brothers'' which among other matters, including a summary of African history, discussed his experiences with the Rastafari. It became a benchmark in the Caribbean [[Black Power]] movement. Combined with Rastafarian teachings, both philosophies spread rapidly to various Caribbean nations, including [[Guyana]], [[Trinidad and Tobago]], [[Dominica]], and [[Grenada]]. 

Rodney influenced his followers, according to Tafari:
“In his powerful ‘Black Power’ synthesis, Rodney brought together the Rastafarian and Marxist theses in a new ideological trinity of race, class and culture; i.e., a rejection of white imperialism (race); the assumption of power by the black masses (class); and the redefinition of the society in the image of the blacks (culture)

==Rastafari around the world==

There are Rasta communities all around the world.

===Botswana===
In Botswana, a prevalent Rastafarian community exists and was profiled in the documentary ''Runaway Slave''.

===Democratic Republic of Congo===
There is a substantial number of Rastas, Federation des Rastas du Congo, or FERACO that make up Ndjili Kinshasa, DRC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7--AGUBIcAc |title=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Côte d'Ivoire (Ivory Coast)===
Ivory Coast residing [[Alpha Blondy]] is one of the best known African Rasta musicians. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classical-reggae-interviews.org/bob.htm Bob Marley's Music is a big prayer], Classical Reggae Interviews, Alpha Blondy.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japan===
A small but devoted Rasta community developed in Japan in the late 1970s and early 1980s.{{citation needed|date=April 2012}} Rasta shops selling natural foods, reggae recordings, and other Rasta-related items sprang up in Tokyo, Osaka, and other cities. For several years, &quot;Japan Splashes&quot; or open-air reggae concerts were held in various locations throughout Japan.

===Malawi===
There is a Rastafarian community in [[Malawi]] as well. They have had influences in the music industry in Malawi where reggae remains a popular form of music. Malawian reggae band, The [[Black Missionaries]], continues to propagate the rastafarian culture and issues in Malawi. They have featured at the [[Lake of Stars|Lake of Stars Music Festival]], an international music festival which features international artists including many of Malawi's reggae artists. They have also brought Malawia-style reggae to the international scene through their performance abroad, including in the United States.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}} One of Malawi's most popular reggae singers is [[Lucius Banda]], who was outspoken against the autocratic state of [[Kamuzu Banda]] and later became a minister in the government.

Another outspoken Malawian Reggae artist, [[Evison Matafale]] known as 'The prophet' was imprisoned in Malawi and later died under police custody in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/1682708.stm | work=BBC News | title=Malawian farewell to 'the prophet' | date=2001-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rastafarians have also been involved in the political scene, particularly in their efforts to legalise Chamba in Malawi. [[Malawi Gold]] (Chamba), remains one of Africa's most potent cannabis leaves and has gained notoriety internationally for its potency. The Rastafarians use it for religious reasons. It remains currently illegal in Malawi.

===South Africa===
The House of Judah Community in Azania and other areas of South Africa has some of the largest and most prominent Rastafarian communities, and a Nyabinghi Groundation is regularly held.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.openafrica.org/participant/house-of-judah-rastafarian-community |title=House of Judah (Rastafarian Community) |deadurl=no |accessdate=10 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
According to the [[2001 United Kingdom Census]] there are 5000 Rastafarian people living in [[England and Wales]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/rastafari/ataglance/glance.shtml |title=BBC Rastafari at a glance |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2009-10-02 |accessdate=2012-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; the majority of whom live in [[London]] and are of [[British Jamaican|Jamaican]] origin. [[Cannabis]] is a [[List of controlled drugs in the United Kingdom#Class B drugs|Class B Drug]] in the United Kingdom and its use for religious reasons is also prohibited.

In [[London]], [[St Agnes Place]] contained a Rastafari place of worship until its occupants were evicted in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6549515.stm |title=UK &amp;#124; Anger amid Rastafarian temple raid |publisher=BBC News |date=2007-04-12 |accessdate=2010-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fairfield House, Bath]] where His Imperial Majesty Emperor Haile Selassie I lived during his five years in exile, has a community of Rastafari which regularly meets to maintain the garden and hold events. The Facebook group &quot;Rastafarians and Friends of Fairfield House&quot; keeps members up to date with goings on there. While events attract Rastafarians from around the UK, much of the core membership are drawn from areas of Bristol, where there is a growing number of Rastafarians centered around the Jamaican community of [[St Pauls, Bristol| St Pauls]]

===United States===
{{main|Rastafari movement in the United States}}
Rastafarian people started arriving in the [[United States]] in large numbers in the 1960s and '70s mostly from [[Jamaica]].{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

==See also==
* [[Awake Zion]]
* [[Ethiopian suit]]
* [[List of topics related to Black and African people]]
* [[One hitter (smoking)]]
* [[Religious and spiritual use of cannabis]]
* [[Vegetarianism and religion]]
* [[Mutabaruka]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

* Experience, by [[Lincoln Thompson]]
* Soul Rebels: The Rastafari, by William F Lewis
* Rastafari: A Way of Life, by Tracy Nicholas ISBN 0-948390-16-6
* Book of Memory: A Rastafari Testimony, composed by Prince Elijah Williams and edited by Michael Kuelker ISBN 0-9746021-0-8
* Complete Idiot's Guide to World Religions, by Toropov, Brandon ISBN 0786588405{{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (5) does not correspond to calculated figure.}}

==External links==
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20060829153306/religiousmovements.lib.virginia.edu/nrms/rast.html Rastafarianism] Scholarly profile at the Religious Movements Homepage (University of Virginia)
* [http://www.rastafarispeaks.com/articles/history.html A Sketch of Rastafarian History by Norman Reddington]
* [http://www.black-king.net/ Rastafari Actuality]
* {{YouTube|Mgln_ngAa6U|House of Judah Nyabinghi Rastafarian Grounation&amp;nbsp;— John H. Bradley}}
* [http://etudescaribeennes.revues.org/3665 Rastafari: Alternative Religion and Resistance against &quot;White&quot; Christianity] by Jérémie Kroubo Dagnini for Etudes caribéennes, n°12, 2009
* [http://www.jpanafrican.com/docs/vol3no4/3.4RememberingRasta.pdf Remembering Rasta Pioneers: An Interview with Barry Chevannes] by Jérémie Kroubo Dagnini for the Journal of Pan African Studies, vol.3, n°4, 2009
{{Religion in Jamaica}}
{{Religion topics|state=collapsed}}
{{Simple living}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rastafari Movement}}
[[Category:Rastafari movement| ]]
[[Category:Cannabis culture]]
[[Category:Groups claiming Jewish descent]]
[[Category:Monotheistic religions]]
[[Category:New religious movements]]
[[Category:Religion in Jamaica]]
[[Category:Religious organizations using entheogens]]

{{Link FA|eo}}

[[af:Rastafarianisme]]
[[ar:راستافارية]]
[[ast:Movimientu rastafari]]
[[az:Rastafari hərəkatı]]
[[be:Растафары]]
[[be-x-old:Растафарыянства]]
[[bg:Растафари]]
[[ca:Rastafarisme]]
[[cs:Rastafariánství]]
[[cy:Rastaffariaeth]]
[[da:Rastafarianisme]]
[[de:Rastafari]]
[[et:Rastafarianism]]
[[el:Ρασταφαριανισμός]]
[[es:Movimiento rastafari]]
[[eo:Rastafaria movado]]
[[eu:Rastafari mugimendu]]
[[fr:Mouvement rastafari]]
[[ga:Gluaiseacht Rastafárach]]
[[gd:Rastafarachd]]
[[gl:Movemento rastafari]]
[[ko:라스타파리 운동]]
[[hy:Ռաստաֆարական շարժում]]
[[hr:Rastafarijanstvo]]
[[id:Gerakan Rastafari]]
[[it:Rastafarianesimo]]
[[he:ראסטפארי]]
[[ka:რასტაფარი]]
[[ht:Mouvman rastafari]]
[[lv:Rastafari]]
[[lt:Rastafarizmas]]
[[hu:Rasztafariánus mozgalom]]
[[mk:Растафаријанство]]
[[nl:Rastafari]]
[[nds-nl:Rastafarianisme]]
[[ja:ラスタファリ運動]]
[[no:Rastafarianerne]]
[[nn:Rastafarianismen]]
[[koi:Растафари]]
[[nds:Rastafari]]
[[pl:Ruch Rastafari]]
[[pt:Movimento rastafári]]
[[ro:Mișcarea Rastafari]]
[[ru:Растафарианство]]
[[simple:Rastafari movement]]
[[sk:Rastafariánstvo]]
[[sl:Rastafarijanstvo]]
[[sr:Растафаријанство]]
[[sh:Rastafarijanstvo]]
[[fi:Rastafari]]
[[sv:Rastafari]]
[[ta:ராஸ்தஃபாரை]]
[[th:ขบวนการราสตาฟารี]]
[[tr:Rastafarianizm]]
[[uk:Растафаріанство]]
[[zh-yue:拉斯特法里]]
[[zh:拉斯特法里运动]]</text>
      <sha1>fhqijo1xi01zoylmnv8t09u3uinvw1a</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
