<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rebbe</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>166683</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516191938</id>
      <parentid>515879038</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-05T18:40:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ratzd'mishukribo</username>
        <id>1378652</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Links to names of Hasidic Rebbes by name of geographic region */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23952">{{Dablink|This article describes the social functions of Chasidic leadership. The Chasidic theory of leadership is described in the article [[Tzadik]]&lt;br /&gt;For specific or other uses of &quot;Rebbe&quot;, see [[Rebbe (disambiguation)]] }}
{{Multiple issues|refimprove = September 2009|unreliable sources = September 2011}}

{{Judaism}}
'''Rebbe''' (רבי) {{IPAc-en|ˈ|r|ɛ|b|ə}},&lt;ref&gt;Oxford Dictionary of English, Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary&lt;/ref&gt; which means ''master, teacher, or mentor,'' is a [[Yiddish]] word derived from the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] word [[Rabbi]]. In accordance with Yiddish pronunciation norms, the stress is on the first syllable and the final vowel is sometimes reduced to a [[schwa]], but is other times pronounced &quot;ee.&quot;

Whilst Rebbe is a term that refers to many leaders of Jewry, 'Rebbe' or 'Rebbi' when mentioned in the [[Talmud]] is a reference to the redactor of the [[Mishna]], Rabbi [[Yehuda HaNasi]]. In common parlance of modern times, the term 'The Rebbe' is often used by [[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidim]] to refer to the leader of a Hasidic movement, for example, by [[Lubavitcher]] Hasidim referring to their Rebbe, Rabbi [[Menachem Mendel Schneerson]].

==Usage==

Today ''Rebbe'' has three meanings:
# The leader of a ''[[Chasidic Judaism|Chasidus]]'' (Chasidic movement) is called a ''rebbe''. His followers would address him as &quot;The ''Rebbe''&quot; or refer to him when speaking to others as &quot;the ''Rebbe''&quot; or &quot;my ''Rebbe''&quot;. He is referred to by others as the ''Rebbe'' of a particular ''Chasidus''. It is this definition that is the focus of this article. In Hebrew, a Chasidic Rebbe is often referred to as an ''[[Honorifics in Judaism#Admo.22r|admor]]'', which is an abbreviation for '''''Ad'''oneinu, '''Mo'''reinu, ve'''R'''abbenu'' (&quot;Our Master, our Teacher, and our Rebbe&quot;). In writing, this title is placed before the name of the ''Chasidus'', as in &quot;Admor of Belz&quot;; while the title ''Rebbe'' comes after the name of the ''Chasidus'' when used as an adjective, as in &quot;Lubavitcher Rebbe,&quot; &quot;Amshinever Rebbe,&quot; and every Rebbe of every Chassidic Dynasty.
# A person's main [[Rosh Yeshiva]] such as the Rebbe's &quot;Little Gaon&quot; Rabbi Goldberg Rosh Yeshivah of Hadar HaTorah of Crown Heights Brooklyn New York, May He Live many long and healthy years... or mentor, who teaches him/her Torah and gives guidance, is referred to as &quot;my ''Rebbe''&quot;.
# [[Yeshiva]] students or ''[[cheider]]'' (elementary school) students, when talking to their Teacher, would address him with the [[Honorifics in Judaism|honorific]] ''Rebbe''. We also refer to him when speaking to our classmates as &quot;The ''Rebbe''&quot; or when speaking to others as &quot;my ''Rebbe''&quot;.

In the ''[[Litvishe]]'' world, when not referring to a Chasidic ''Rebbe'', the word may be pronounced &quot;Rebbee&quot;.  Sephardic Jews may pronounce it as &quot;Ribbi&quot;.

==Terminology and origin==

Rebbe come from the Hebrew word rav, meaning great, and might mean the equivalent of &quot;my master.&quot;  It was an honorific originally given to those who had [[Smicha]] at the beginning of the first millennium, though because vowels were not written at the time, it is impossible to know if it was pronounced rah-bee or r-bee.  The English word rabbi directly comes from this form.  In Yiddish, the word became reb-eh (now commonly spelled rebbe) or just reb.

The Sages of the [[Mishnah]] known as the ''[[Tannaim]]'', from the 1st and 2nd centuries of the common era, were known by the title ''Rabbi'', for example Rabbi [[Akiva]] and Rabbi [[Simeon bar Yohai|Shimon bar Yochoy]]. Rabbi [[Judah haNasi|Yehudah haNasi]], the leader of Jewry in Mishnaic Times, was simply called ''Rabbi'', meaning &quot;''The'' Rebbe of the Generation&quot;.

The Sages of the [[Talmud]] known as the ''[[Amoraim]]'' from the 3rd, 4th and early 5th centuries, those born in the [[Land of Israel]], are called ''Rabbi''; those born in the [[diaspora]] are known by the title ''[[Rav]]''.

The [[Lubavitch]]er chasidim have a tradition that the Hebrew letters that make up the word rebbe are also an acronym for &quot;'''R'''osh '''B'''nei '''Y'''isroel&quot;, meaning &quot;a spiritual head of the [[Children of Israel]]&quot;. 

[[Image:Rabbiofzidichov.JPG|right|thumb|Rebbe [[Naftali Tzvi Labin of Zidichov]]]]

==Distinctions between ''Rebbe'' and ''Rav''==

A Rebbe is sometimes distinct from a '[[Rav]]' or 'Rov' who is an authoritative Halachic decider and leader of a Jewish, often Chassidic, community) in that a significant function of a Rav is to answer questions of ''[[Halacha]]'' (Jewish law). A Chasid has a Rebbe as a spiritual guide and to go and sometimes an additional Rav for a ruling on an issue of Halachah, Jewish law.

''Chasidim'' use the term to denote someone that they perceive not only as the religious leader of their congregation, but as their spiritual adviser and mentor. A rebbe is someone whose views and advice are accepted not only on issues of religious dogma and practice, but in all arenas of life, including political and social issues.

Sprouting ''Chasidim'' use the concept of a (non-Chasidic) Rebbe. Example: &quot;I will ask my Rebbe, Rabbi Ploni (so-and-so), for advice about this personal matter.&quot;

As a rule, among all Chasidim, Rebbe is referred to in Hebrew as &quot;''Admor''&quot;, an abbreviation for Adoneinu Moreinu V'Rabeinu, Our Master Our Teacher Our Rebbe, which is now the modern Hebrew word in Israel for &quot;rebbe&quot; (pl. admorim).

==Hasidic Rebbe==

A '''Rebbe''' is generally taken to mean a great leader of a [[Hasidic Judaism|Hasidic]] [[List of Hasidic dynasties|dynasties]], also referred to as  '''Grand Rabbi''' in English or an '''ADMOR''', a [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] abbreviation for '''A'''doneinu'''-Mo'''reinu-ve'''R'''abbeinu'' (&quot;our lord/master, teacher/guide and rabbi/teacher&quot;).

Rabbi [[Israel ben Eliezer|Yisroel Baal Shem Tov]], the founder of Hasidism is regarded by Hasidim, as the first Hasidic rebbe.

During his lifetime he was referred to mainly as &quot;The holy one&quot; rather than as &quot;Rebbe,&quot;  and his disciples were &quot;[[Maggid|magidim]]&quot; or &quot;preachers&quot;, such as the [[Mordechai Twersky|Magid of Chernobyl]] or the [[Magid of Mezritsh]].

The first &quot;rebbe&quot; to be known as such was the Baal Shem Tov's grandson, Rabbi Boruch of [[Medzhibozh (Hasidic dynasty)|Mezhbizh]] who was referred to as &quot;The Rebbe&quot; during his lifetime. After him, those who rose to positions of leadership and their successors began to be called ''rebbe''. The title gradually came to suggest a higher spiritual status.

Each Hasidic group refers to its leader as &quot;the rebbe&quot;.

[[Hannah Rachel Verbermacher]], also known as the [[Maiden of Ludmir]] or the &quot;Ludmirer Moyd&quot;, was the only female rebbe in the history of the [[Hasidism|Hasidic]] movement; she lived in the nineteenth century in Ukraine and Israel.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.yivoencyclopedia.org/article.aspx/Maiden_of_Ludmir&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=K4WylwfJNOoC&amp;dq=biography+maiden+ludmir&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s&lt;/ref&gt;

Outside of Hasidic circles the term &quot;Grand Rabbi&quot; has been used to refer to a rebbe. The practice became widespread in America in the early 1900s when Hasidic rebbes began to emigrate to the United States and was derived from the [[German language|German]] ''Grossrabbiner''.

==Relationship of hasidim to their rebbe==

A [[Hasidic Judaism|hasidic]] rebbe is generally understood to be an exceptionally righteous person (called a &quot;[[tzaddik]]&quot;). According to [[Kabbalah]] (and particularly the chasidic understanding of Kabbalah), the world is sustained on the &quot;shoulders&quot; of several exceptionally righteous people in a generation ''(tzaddikim)''. These people are understood to have perfected their personal service of God to such an extent that they become literally and physically aware of God. These righteous people's perception (of both spiritual and physical, not to mention temporal matters) transcends the apparent boundaries of existence, such that a Rebbe will appear to be able to &quot;see the future,&quot; or at least have strong insight into the life and trials of another. Furthermore, a rebbe is said to be able to affect divine providence.

As a result, hasidim in some hasidic circles seek their rebbe's advice for a variety of concerns: spiritual, physical, and even business concerns. Furthermore, many people seek the blessing ''(brocho)'' of a rebbe (and a chosid will specifically seek the blessing of his own rebbe) for anything from minor (and all the more so major) physical troubles, to grand spiritual concerns. Many famous and common stories of a rebbe's intervention involve women who successfully seek a rebbe's blessing for fertility so that they can conceive after having been barren for many years.

Given a rebbe's physical awareness of God, and the Rebbe's transcendent perception of Godliness, many hasidim take special care to observe the specific and sometimes minute practices of their Rebbe. Even things that seem mundane may nonetheless be seen by chasidim as incredibly significant. For example, [[Chabad|Lubavitch]]er hasidim frequently shape their fedoras to match the way that the Lubavitcher Rebbe shaped his hat-which was more flat than many others. Many [[Skver]]er hasidim (of the Skverer Rebbe in [[New Square]]) wear their [[peyos]] identical to those of the Skverer Rebbe. While hasidim do not always follow the specific practices of their rebbe, the rebbe is able to create practices that may be specific and unique to his hasidim. For example, Rabbi Aaron Roth (''Reb Areleh'', as he was called) the first rebbe of [[Toldos Aharon|Shomer Emunim]], told his hasidim to pause frequently while eating their meals in order to keep them from overindulging.

A hasid will usually love his rebbe like a close family member, if not more so. But the degree and nature of this belief varies depending on the movement. In some movements the hasidim believe that their rebbe is the &quot;''tzadik hador''&quot; (greatest and holiest saint of the generation) and would regard any thought that detracts from his perfection and holiness as heresy. Other sects lessen this idealization to some degree or another. Since many rebbes are sons-in-law or students of other rebbes, it makes sense that they would view themselves as subordinate to those other rebbes. Nonetheless, their hasidim remain loyal to them because of their special loyalty, a family connection, or a belief that a specific ''[[tzaddik]]'' (though there may be others of greater spiritual stature) connects best with one's soul. For example, the [[Kosov (Hasidic dynasty)|Kosov]]er Rebbe makes yearly pilgrimages to the [[Tosh (Hasidic dynasty)|Tosher]] Rebbe. Nonetheless, his followers remain very loyal to him.

==Functions==
{{prose|section|date=September 2011}}
There are some functions which are exclusively the domain of hasidic rebbes:
* Reading ''[[kvitel|kvitlach]]''
* Leading a ''[[Tish (Hasidic celebration)|tish]]''

Others are not exclusive to Hasidic rebbes, but are often an important part of their role:
* Participating in family celebrations of the hasidim, such as weddings and ''[[bris]]im'' (circumcision ceremony)
* Performing mitzvos etc. in the presence of their hasidim, such as kindling the [[Chanuka]] lights and drawing water to bake [[matzo]]s with
* Leading the prayers on Shabbos, Holy Days and other special occasions
* Delivering learned or inspirational discourses (in [[Chabad]] Hasidut, this is one of the main roles of a Rebbe)

===''Kvitlach''===
{{main|kvitel}}
A rebbe has times when Hasidim (and other petitioners) may come for a private audience.
A ''kvitel'' (Yiddish for &quot;note&quot;, plural ''kvitlach'') is a note with the name of the petitioner and a short request for which the rebbe is asked to pray. The formula in which a person's name is written is one's own Hebrew name, the son/daughter of one's mother's Hebrew name, such as ''Shimon ben Rivkah'' (Simeon the son of Rebecca). Hasidim believe that rebbes read supernaturally &quot;between the lines&quot; of a ''kvitel'', and in every Hasidic movement there are numerous anecdotes relating how the rebbe saw things that were not written in the ''kvitel''. In most Hasidic groups, the ''kvitel'' is written by the rebbe's ''[[gabbai]]'' (secretary), however sometimes the petitioner writes it on his own. Usually, but with some exceptions, a ''[[pidyon]]'' (redemption) of cash is customarily handed to the rebbe under the ''kvitel'', however this is not obligatory. This is considered to be the [[Conduit (spiritualism)|conduit]] through which the blessing is given, and a redemption for the soul of the petitioner. (&quot;A gift makes its receiver glad&quot; is given as an explanation: a blessing only comes from a joyous heart.) It is also customary to tip the gabbai, although this too is not obligatory.

[[Image:bostonertischbeitar.jpg|right|thumb|The Bostoner Rebbe ''feert [[Tish (Hasidic celebration)|tish]]'' in his synagogue in [[Beitar Illit]]]]

===''Tish''===
{{main|Tish (Hasidic celebration)}}
A rebbe conducts a ''tish'' ({{lang-yi|פֿירט טיש}}: ''feert tish'', literally, &quot;table&quot;)—a (communal festive) meal with highly mystical overtones—on [[Shabbat]] and other occasions. At a tish, the rebbe distributes ''shirayim'' (lit. remnants) to the Hasidim seated at or gathered round the table.  When a gathering similar to a ''tish'' is led by a rabbi who is not a rebbe, it may be referred to as a ''botte'' (esp. amongst groups from Romania) or ''sheves achim''.

==Hasidic movements==
{{importance-section|date=September 2011}}
In [[Israel]], some of the best known Hasidic groups are those of [[Belz (Hasidic dynasty)|Belz]], [[Boston (Hasidic dynasty)|Boston]], [[Chabad-Lubavitch]], [[Ger (Hasidic dynasty)|Ger]], [[Karlin (Hasidic dynasty)|Karlin]], [[Kaliv]], [[Nadvorna (Hasidic dynasty)|Nadvorna]], [[Slonim (Hasidic dynasty)|Slonim]], [[Vizhnitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Vizhnitz]], and [[Dushinsky (Hasidic dynasty)|Dushinsky]], each having their own Rebbe. Some of the larger or better known chasidic groups in the [[United States|United States of America]] are [[Bobov (Hasidic dynasty)|Bobov]], [[Chabad-Lubavitch]], [[Klausenburg (Hasidic dynasty)|Klausenburg]], [[Chabad Lubavitch|Lubavitch]], [[Munkacs (Hasidic dynasty)|Munkatch]], [[Puppa (Hasidic dynasty)|Puppa]], [[Satmar (Hasidic dynasty)|Satmar]], [[Skulen (Hasidic dynasty)|Skulen]], [[Skver (Hasidic dynasty)|Skver]], [[Chernobyl (Hasidic dynasty)|Tshernobl]]. A more complete list of chasidic groups can be found [[List of Hasidic dynasties|here.]]

Some Hasidic rebbes have thousands of followers, or disciples, called Hasidim, whilst others may number only a few hundred. Some rebbes have only a title, but do not have a following beyond their own family members and a few congregants in their [[synagogue]]s. Rebbes often have a [[synagogue]] or [[Beth midrash|beis medrash]] (study hall) where they pray, learn, and interact with their Hasidim.

Rebbes are usually called by the [[Yiddish language|Yiddish]] name of the geographic region in which they or their predecessors gained prominence: e.g., the first Bobover Rebbe lived in [[Bobowa]], [[Poland]], the first Skulener Rebbe lived in [[Sculeni]], [[Bessarabia]], the first Munkatcher Rebbe in [[Munkacs]], [[Ukraine]] and the first Bostoner Rebbe, served as a rebbe in [[Boston]], Massachusetts.

The [[Breslov (Hasidic group)|Breslover]] Hasidim do not have a living rebbe, but continue to follow the previous rebbe of the movement. In the case of Lubavitch, this is Rabbi [[Menachem Mendel Schneersohn]]; in the case of Breslov, it is the founder of the group, Rabbi [[Nachman of Breslov]].

==Links to names of Hasidic Rebbes by name of geographic region==
{{laundry|date=September 2011}}
[[Aleksander (Hasidic dynasty)|Alexander]] • [[Alesk (Hasidic dynasty)|Alesk]] • [[Amshinov (Hasidic dynasty)|Amshinov]] • [[Anipoli (Hasidic dynasty)|Anipoli]] • [[Apta (Hasidic dynasty)|Apt]] • [[Ovruch|Avritch]] • [[Belz (Hasidic dynasty)|Belz]] • [[Berditchev (Hasidic dynasty)|Berditchev]] • [[Beregsaz (Hasidic dynasty)|Beregsaz]] • [[Biala (Hasidic dynasty)|Biala]] |  [[Błażowa|Bluzhov]] • [[Bobov]] • [[Bohush (Hasidic dynasty)|Bohush]] • [[Boston (Hasidic dynasty)|Boston]] • [[Boyan (Hasidic dynasty)|Boyan]] • [[Burshtin (Hasidic dynasty)|Burshtin]] • [[Chabad-Lubavitch]] • [[Osrov-Henzin (Hasidic dynasty)#Outline of Ozharov dynasty|Chentshin]] • [[Chernobyl (Hasidic dynasty)|Chernobyl]] • [[Chernivtsi|Chernovitz]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)|Cheshenov]] • [[Chortkov (Hasidic dynasty)|Chortkov]] • [[Chust (Hasidic dynasty)|Chust]] • [[Cleveland (Hasidic dynasty)|Cleveland]] • [[Dej|Deyzh]] • [[Dinov (Hasidic dynasty)|Dinov]] • [[Dombrov (Hasidic dynasty)|Dombrov]] • [[Drohobych|Drohobitch]] • [[Ropshitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Dzikov]] • [[Faltichan (Hasidic dynasty)|Faltichan]] • [[Ger (Hasidic dynasty)|Ger]] • [[Ropshitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Glogov]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)#Offshoots|Gorlitz]] • [[Grodzisk]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)#Offshoots|Grybov]] • [[Chernobyl (Hasidic dynasty)|Hornsteipel]] • [[Chernobyl (Hasidic dynasty)|Hornostaypil-Milwaukee]] • [[Hosiatyn|Husiatyn]] • [[Izhbitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Izhbitz]] • [[Kalov (Hasidic dynasty)|Kalov]] • [[Kaminka (Hasidic dynasty)|Kaminka]] • [[Kapust (Hasidic dynasty)|Kapust]] • [[Karlin (Hasidic Dynasty)|Karlin-Stolin]] • [[Kashou (Hasidic dynasty)|Kashou]] • [[Kerestir (Hasidic dynasty)|Kerestir]] • [[Klausenberg (Hasidic dynasty)|Klausenberg]] • [[Slonim (Hasidic dynasty)#Outline of Slonimer dynasty|Kobrin]] • [[Koidanov (Hasidic dynasty)|Koidanov]] [[Komarno (Hasidic dynasty)|Komarno]] • [[Apta (Hasidic dynasty)|Kopyczynitz]] • [[Korec|Korets]] • [[Koson (Hasidic dynasty)|Koson]] • [[Kosov (Hasidic dynasty)|Kosov]] • [[Menachem Mendel of Kotzk|Kotsk]] • [[Kozhnitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Kozhnitz]] • [[Kozlov (Hasidic dynasty)|Kozlov]] • [[Kretchenif (Hasidic dynasty)|Kretchenif]] • [[Spinka (Hasidic dynasty)#Lineage of Spinka Rebbes of the Horowitz Family|Krula]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)#Offshoots|Kshanov]] • [[Kutna (Hasidic dynasty)|Kutna]] • [[Kazimierz Dolny|Kuzmir]] • [[Łańcut|Lantzhit]] • [[Slonim (Hasidic dynasty)#Outline of Slonimer dynasty|Lechovitsh]] • [[Lelov (Hasidic dynasty)|Lelov]] • [[Liozna (Hasidic dynasty)|Liozna]] • [[Liske (Hasidic dynasty)|Liske]] • [[Karlin (Hasidic dynasty)#Outline of Lineage of Karliner Dynasty|Lutsk]] • [[Machanovka (Hasidic dynasty)|Machnovka]] • [[Makarov (Hasidic dynasty)|Makarov]] • [[Makove (Hasidic dynasty)|Makove]] • [[Manestrishtze (Hasidic dynasty)|Manestrishtze]] • [[Mattersdorf]] • [[Ropshitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Melitz]] • [[Medzhibozh (Hasidic dynasty)|Mezhbizh]] • [[Milwaukee]] • [[Modzitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Modzitz]] • [[Mogelnitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Mogelnitz]] • [[Nadvorna (Hasidic dynasty)#Dynasty|Mosholu]] • [[Munkacs (Hasidic dynasty)|Munkatch]] • [[Muzhay (Hasidic dynasty)|Muzhay]] • [[Nadvorna (Hasidic dynasty)|Nadvorna]] • [[Narol (Hasidic dynasty)|Narol]] • [[Naszód|Nassod]] • [[Shmelke of Nikolsburg|Nikolsburg]] • [[Mińsk Mazowiecki|Novominsk]] • [[Ostrof (Hasidic dynasty)|Ostrof]] • [[Osrov-Henzin (Hasidic dynasty)|Ozharov]] • [[Karlin (Hasidic dynasty)#Pinsk-Karlin|Pinsk-Karlin]] • [[Pilzno (Hasidic dynasty)|Pilzno]] • [[Pittsburg (Hasidic dynasty)|Pittsburgh]] • [[Porisov (Hasidic dynasty)|Porisov]] • [[Premishlan (Hasidic dynasty)|Premishlan]] • [[Przemyśl|Pshemish]] • [[Pshevorsk (Hasidic dynasty)|Pshevorsk]] • [[Przysucha|Pshischa]] • [[Puppa (Hasidic dynasty)|Pupa]] • [[Rachev (Hasidic dynasty)|Rachev]] • [[Rachmastrivka (Hasidic dynasty)|Rachmastrivka]] • [[Radomsko|Radomsk]] • [[Radoshitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Radoshitz]] • [[Izhbitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Radzin]] • [[Ratzfert]] • [[Menachem Mendel of Rimanov|Rimanov]] • [[Rimnitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Rimnitz]] • [[Rizhin (Hasidic dynasty)|Rizhin]] • [[Ropshitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Ropshitz]] • [[Sadigura (Hasidic dynasty)|Sadigura]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)|Sanz]] • [[Ropshitz (Hasidic dynasty)#Lineage|Sasregen]] • [[Sassov (Hasidic dynasty)|Sassov]] • [[Satmar]] • [[Moshe Zvi of Savran|Savran]] • [[Serdahel]] • [[Seret (Hasidic dynasty)|Seret]] • [[Shedlitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Shedlitz]] • [[Shenitza (Hasidic dynasty)|Shenitza]] • [[Shepetivka]] • [[Shidlovtza (Hasidic dynasty)|Shidlovtza]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)#Offshoots|Shinova]] • [[Shotz (Hasidic dynasty)|Shotz]] • [[Shpikov (Hasidic dynasty)|Shpikov]] • [[Shtefanesht (Hasidic dynasty)|Shtefanesht]] • [[Skole|Skolye]] • [[Skula (Hasidic dynasty)|Skula]] • [[Skulen (Hasidic dynasty)|Skulen]] • [[Skver (Hasidic dynasty)|Skver]] • [[Slonim (Hasidic dynasty)|Slonim]] • [[Sochatchov (Hasidic dynasty)|Sochatshov]] • [[Spinka (Hasidic dynasty)|Spinka]] • [[Stanislav (Hasidic dynasty)|Stanislav]] • [[Ropshitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Stitshin]] • [[Strashelye (Hasidic dynasty)|Strashelye]] • [[Stretin (Hasidic dynasty)|Stretin]] • [[Strikov (Hasidic dynasty)|Strikov]] • [[Ropshitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Strizov]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)#Offshoots|Stropkov]] • [[Nadvorna (Hasidic dynasty)#Dynasty|Strozhnitz]] • [[Sudylkov (Hasidic dynasty)|Sudylkov]] • [[Sulitza (Hasidic dynasty)#Lineage|Sulitza]] • [[Tshenstechov (Hasidic dynasty)|Tshenstechov]] • [[Tshenstkovitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Tshenstkovitz]] • [[Temesvár|Temishvar]] • [[Chernobyl (Hasidic dynasty)|Tolno]] • [[Toltchav (Hasidic dynasty)|Toltchav]] • [[Tosh (Hasidic dynasty)|Tosh]] • [[Trisk (Hasidic dynasty)|Trisk]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)#Offshoots|Tshokava]] • [[Vien (Rabbinical dynasty)|Vien]] • [[Vizhnitz (Hasidic dynasty)|Vizhnits]] • [[Warka|Vurka]] • [[Ivano-Frankivs'k|Yeruslav]] • [[Zhvill (Hasidic dynasty)|Zhvill]] • [[Yitzhak Aharon Korff|Zhvil-Mezhbuz]] • [[Zidichov (Hasidic dynasty)|Zidichov]] • [[Naftali Tzvi Labin of Zidichov|Zidichov-Beregsaz]] • [[Apter Rebbe|Zinkov]] • [[Sanz (Hasidic dynasty)#Sanz-Zhmigrod|Zhmigrod]] • [[Zolochiv|Zlotchiv]] • [[Nadvorna (Hasidic dynasty)#Dynasty|Zutchke]] • [[Zychlin (Hasidic dynasty)|Zychlin]]

===Rebbes with non-eponymous dynasties===
[[Bobov (Hasidic dynasty)#Outline of Bobov's Hasidic rabbinical lineage|Bikovsk]] •  [[Elimelech of Lizhensk|Lizhensk]] • [[Yaakov Yitzchak of Lublin|Lublin]] • [[Dov Ber of Mezeritch|Mezritch]] • [[Kalonymus Kalman Shapira|Piasetzne]] • [[Shpola]]

===Hasidim without a living rebbe===
[[Breslov (Hasidic dynasty)|Breslov]] • [[Chabad|Lubavitch]] • [[Malachim (Hasidic group)|Malochim]]

===Rebbes not related to Baal Shem Tov Hasidism===

[[Baruch Ashlag|Ashlag]] • [[Dorog (Hasidic dynasty)|Dorog]] • [[Dushinsky (Hasidic dynasty)|Dushinsky]] • [[Baruch Ashlag#His Successors|Dzirka]] • [[Erlau (Hasidic Dynasty)|Erlau]] • [[Nitra (Hasidic dynasty)|Nitra]] •  [[Mishkenos HoRoim (Hasidic dynasty)|Mishkenos HoRoim]] • [[Shomer Emunim (Hasidic dynasty)|Shomer Emunim]] •  [[Toldos Aharon (Hasidic dynasty)|Toldos Aharon]] • [[Toldos Avrohom Yitzchok (Hasidic dynasty)|Toldos Avrohom Yitzchok]]

==See also==
*[[Tzadik]]
*[[Hasidic philosophy]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://chabad.org]
*[http://video.google.com/videosearch?q=rebbe Over 1,000 videos of rebbes]
*[http://www.chabad.org/search/keyword.asp?kid=1576&amp;scope=6198 The Role of a Rebbe and the Rebbe-Chossid Relationship] chabad.org
*[http://tzaddikim.blogspot.com/ Torah sources about the concept of a rebbe]

[[Category:Hasidic rebbes| ]]
[[Category:Hebrew words and phrases]]
[[Category:Orthodox rabbinic roles and titles]]
[[Category:Yiddish words and phrases]]

[[be-x-old:Рэбэ]]
[[de:Admor]]
[[es:Rebe]]
[[fr:Rebbe]]
[[it:Rebbe]]
[[he:אדמו&quot;ר]]
[[lt:Rebe]]
[[nl:Rebbe]]
[[ja:レベ]]
[[pl:Rebe]]
[[pt:Rebe]]
[[ru:Ребе]]
[[fi:Rebbe]]
[[sv:Rebbe]]
[[yi:אדמו&quot;ר]]</text>
      <sha1>rrzynyacvmrji1tsqk70asa9tbiks9d</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
