<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Religion in India</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10710364</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521757563</id>
      <parentid>521757390</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T00:57:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>209.53.168.233</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Demographics */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="78312">{{About|Republic of India's religious demographics|religions originating in the Indian subcontinent|Indian religions}}
[[Image:Bangalore Monument .jpg|thumb|160px|A Statue of Hindu deity [[Shiva]].]]
[[Image:BuddhaTwang.jpg|thumb|160px|A Statue of [[Gautama Buddha|the Buddha]].]]
[[Image:Gomateswara.jpg|thumb|150px|A Statue of [[Jain]] deity [[Bahubali]].]]
[[File:Sikh Gurus with Bhai Bala and Bhai Mardana.jpg|thumb|145px|A rare [[Tanjore painting|Tanjore]]-style painting from the late 19th century depicting the ten Sikh Gurus with [[Bhai Bala]] and [[Bhai Mardana]].]]
India is the birthplace of four of the [[Major religious groups|world's major religious traditions]]; namely [[Hinduism]],  [[Buddhism]], [[Jainism]] and [[Sikhism]].

Throughout its [[history of India|history]], [[religion]] has been an important part of the country's culture. Religious diversity and [[Religious toleration|religious tolerance]] are both established in the country by [[Law of India|law]] and [[Tradition|custom]]. A vast majority of Indians associate themselves with a religion.

According to the 2001 census,&lt;ref name=&quot;census2001&quot;&gt;[http://www.censusindia.gov.in/Census_Data_2001/India_at_glance/religion.aspx Census of India, 2001]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hinduism]] is the majority religion with 80.5% of the [[Demographics of India|population of India]]. [[Islam in India|Islam]] (13.4%), [[Christianity]] (2.3%), [[Sikhism]] (1.9%), [[Buddhism]] (0.8%) and  [[Jainism]] (0.4%) are the other minor religions followed by the people of India. This diversity of religious belief systems existing in India today is a result of, besides existence and birth of [[Indian religion|native religions]], assimilation and social integration of religions brought to the region by traders, travelers, immigrants, and even invaders and conquerors.

[[Zoroastrianism]] and [[Judaism]] also have an ancient history in India and each has several thousand Indian adherents. India has the largest population of people adhering to Zoroastrianism and [[Bahá'í Faith]] anywhere in the world.
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Chary
  | first = Manish
  | title =  India: Nation on the Move: An Overview of India's People, Culture, History, Economy, IT Industry, &amp; More
  | publisher = [[iUniverse]]
  | year = 2009
  | page = 31
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=vjI6IZt8tuwC&amp;pg=PA31
  | isbn = 90-412-2315-8 {{Please check ISBN|reason=Check digit (8) does not correspond to calculated figure.}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Smith
  | first = Peter
  | title =  An introduction to the Baha'i faith
  | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]]
  | year = 2008
  | page = 94
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=z7zdDFTzNr0C&amp;pg=PA94
  | isbn = 978-0-521-86251-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Many other world religions also have a relationship with Indian spirituality, like the Baha'i faith which recognizes [[Buddha|Lord Buddha]] and [[Krishna|Lord Krishna]] as manifestations of God Almighty.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

Indian diaspora in the West have popularized many aspects of [[Hindu philosophy]] like [[yoga]] (meditation), [[Ayurvedic medicine]], [[divination]], [[karma]] and [[reincarnation]] to a great extent.&lt;ref&gt;P. 225 ''Essential Hinduism'' By Steven Rosen&lt;/ref&gt; The influence of Indians abroad in spiritual matters has been significant as several organizations such as the [[International Society for Krishna Consciousness|Hare Krishna movement]],  the [[Brahma Kumari]]s, the [[Ananda Marga]] and others spread by Indian spiritual figures.

The Muslim population in India is the third largest in the world. The shrines of some of the most famous saints of [[Sufism]] like [[Moinuddin Chishti]] and [[Nizamuddin Auliya]] are in India and attract visitors from all over the world.&lt;ref&gt;Pg 80,81 The sacred and the feminine: imagination and sexual difference By Griselda Pollock, Victoria Turvey Sauron&lt;/ref&gt; India is also home to some of the most famous monuments of Islamic architecture like the [[Taj Mahal]] and the [[Qutb Minar]]. Civil matters related to the community are dealt with by the Muslim Personal Law, and constitutional amendments in 1985 established its primacy in family matters.&lt;ref&gt;Pg 156, Religious Politics and Secular States: Egypt, India, and the United States By Scott W. Hibbard - Johns Hopkins University Press, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Constitution of India]] declares the nation to be a [[secularism in India|secular]] republic that must uphold the right of citizens to freely worship and propagate any religion or faith (with activities subject to reasonable restrictions for the sake of morality, law and order, etc.).&lt;ref&gt;[http://lawmin.nic.in/legislative/Art1-242%20(1-88).doc The Constitution of India Art 25-28]. Retrieved on 22 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://indiacode.nic.in/coiweb/amend/amend42.htm |title=The Constitution (Forty-Second Amendment) Act, 1976 |accessdate=2007-04-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Constitution of India also declares the right to [[freedom of religion]] as a [[Fundamental Rights in India|fundamental right]].

Citizens of India are generally tolerant of each other's religions and retain a secular outlook, although inter-religious marriage is not widely practiced. Inter-community clashes have found little support in the social mainstream, and it is generally perceived that the causes of religious conflicts are political rather than ideological in nature.&lt;ref&gt;Pg 211, 21st Century India : View and Vision By By - A.P. Thakur &amp; Sunil Pandey&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{Main|Indian religions}}
{{See also|Religious thinkers of India|Indian philosophy}}

===Evolution of Hinduism in India===
[[File:Mohenjo-daro Priesterkönig.jpeg|thumb|right|100px|&quot;Priest King&quot; of [[Indus Valley Civilization]]]]
Hinduism is often regarded as the oldest religion in the
world,&lt;ref&gt;P. 484 ''Merriam-Webster's Encyclopedia of World
Religions'' By Wendy Doniger, M. Webster, Merriam-Webster,
Inc&lt;/ref&gt; with roots tracing back to prehistoric
times,&lt;ref&gt;P. 169 ''The Encyclopedia of Religion'' By Mircea
Eliade, Charles J. Adams&lt;/ref&gt; or 5000 years.  Over time, Brahmanism gradually became Hinduism.  Hinduism was spread through parts of Southeastern Asia, China, Korea, and Japan.  Hindus worship a god with different forms. (Vishnu the preserver is an important Hindu deity.)&lt;ref&gt;P. 22
''The Complete Idiot's Guide to Geography'' By Joseph Gonzalez, Michael
D Smith, Thomas E. Sherer&lt;/ref&gt; Evidence attesting to [[prehistoric religion]] in the Indian &quot;subcontinent&quot; derives from scattered [[Mesolithic]] rock paintings depicting dances and rituals. [[Neolithic]] pastoralists inhabiting the [[Indus River]] Valley buried their dead in a manner suggestive of spiritual practices that incorporated notions of an afterlife and belief in magic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heehs_2002_39&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Heehs|2002|p=39}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Other [[South Asian Stone Age]] sites, such as the [[Bhimbetka rock shelters]] in central [[Madhya Pradesh]] and the [[Kupgal petroglyphs]] of eastern Karnataka, contain rock art portraying religious rites and evidence of possible ritualised music.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Ancient Indians made 'rock music' |publisher=BBC News |date=19 March 2004 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/3520384.stm |accessdate=2007-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Harappa]]n people of the [[Indus Valley Civilization]], which lasted from 3300 to 1700 BCE and was centered around the [[Indus River|Indus]] and [[Ghaggar-Hakra River|Ghaggar-Hakra]] river valleys, may have worshiped an important [[mother goddess]] symbolising fertility.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Fowler|1997|p=90}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Excavations of Indus Valley Civilization sites show seals with animals and &quot;fire‑altars&quot;, indicating rituals associated with fire. A ''[[linga]]-[[yoni]]'' of a type similar to that which is now worshiped by Hindus has also been found.
[[File:New Delhi Temple.jpg|left|thumb|175px|[[Akshardham (Delhi)|Akshardham]], largest [[Hindu temple]] in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/5000/largest-hindu-temple|title=Largest Hindu temple|publisher=guinnessworldrecords.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/noinclude&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/galleries/hindutemple/|title=World's largest Hindu Temple|publisher=bbc.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/noinclude&gt;]]

Hinduism's origins include cultural elements of the Indus Valley Civilization and other Indian civilizations. The oldest surviving text of Hinduism is the [[Rigveda]], produced during the [[Vedic period]] and dated to 1700–1100 BCE.{{cref|γ}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Oberlies_1998_155&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Oberlies|1998|p=155}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During the Epic and [[Purana|Puranic]] periods, the earliest versions of the epic poems ''[[Ramayana]]'' and ''[[Mahabharata]]'' were written roughly from 500–100 BCE,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Goldman|2007|p=23}}.&lt;/ref&gt; although these were orally transmitted for centuries prior to this period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rine28&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Rinehart|2004|p=28}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Mahabodhitemple.jpg|thumb|right|100px|[[Buddhist]] [[Mahabodhi Temple]]]]
After 200 CE, several schools of thought were formally codified in [[Indian philosophy]], including [[Samkhya]], [[Yoga]], [[Nyaya]], [[Vaisheshika]], [[Purva-Mimamsa]] and [[Vedanta]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Radhaxviii-xxi&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Radhakrishnan|Moore|1967|p=xviii–xxi}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hinduism, otherwise a highly theistic religion, hosted [[atheism in Hinduism|atheistic schools]]; the thoroughly [[materialism|materialistic]] and anti-religious philosophical [[Cārvāka]] school that originated in India around the 6th century BCE is probably the most explicitly atheistic school of Indian philosophy. Cārvāka is classified as a ''[[nastika]]'' (&quot;heterodox&quot;) system; it is not included among the six schools of Hinduism generally regarded as orthodox. It is noteworthy as evidence of a materialistic movement within Hinduism.&lt;ref name=&quot;Radha227&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Radhakrishnan|Moore|1967|pp=227–249}}&lt;/ref&gt; Our understanding of Cārvāka philosophy is fragmentary, based largely on criticism of the ideas by other schools, and it is no longer a living tradition.&lt;ref name=&quot;RChatterjee55&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Chatterjee|Datta|1984|p=55}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Other Indian philosophies generally regarded as orthodox include [[Samkhya|Classical Samkhya]] and [[Mimamsa|Purva Mimamsa]].

=== Rise of Shramana Religions ===
[[File:Palitana.jpg|thumb|left|120px|[[Palitana]] [[List of Jain temples|Jain Temples]].]][[Mahavira]] the 24th Jain Tirthankara (599–527 BC, though possibly 549–477 BC), stressed five vows, including ''[[ahimsa]]'' (non-violence) and ''[[asteya]]'' (non-stealing). [[Gautama Buddha]], who founded Buddhism, was born to the [[Shakya]] clan just before [[Magadha]] (which lasted from 546–324 BCE) rose to power. Buddha is said to be a descendant of Brahmin Sage Angirasa in many Buddhist texts.&lt;ref&gt;''The Life of Buddha as Legend and History'', by Edward Joseph Thomas&lt;/ref&gt; His surname was 'Gautama', some scholars like Dr. Eitel connect it to the Brahmin Rishi Gautama.&lt;ref&gt;P. 95 ''A Record of Buddhistic Kingdoms'' By James Legge&lt;/ref&gt; His family was native to the plains of [[Lumbini]], in what is now southern [[Nepal]]. [[Buddhism in India|Indian Buddhism]] peaked during the reign of [[Asoka the Great]] of the [[Mauryan Empire]], who patronized Buddhism following his conversion and unified the Indian subcontinent in the 3rd century BCE. He sent missionaries abroad, allowing Buddhism to spread across Asia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heehs_2002_106&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Heehs|2002|p=106}}.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Buddhism in India|Indian Buddhism]] declined following the loss of royal patronage offered by the [[Kushan Empire]] and such kingdoms as [[Magadha]] and [[Kosala]].
[[File:Jama Masjid is the largest mosque in India. Delhi, India..jpg|thumb|right|140px|The [[Jama Masjid, Delhi|Jama Masjid]] in [[Delhi]] is one of the world's largest [[mosques]].]]

Some scholars think between 400 BCE and 1000 CE, Hinduism expanded as the [[decline of Buddhism in India]] continued.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC ethics2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=The rise of Jainism and Buddhism |work=Religion and Ethics—Hinduism: Other religious influences |publisher=BBC |date=26 July 2004 |accessdate=2007-04-21 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/hinduism/history/history_2.shtml }}&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhism subsequently became effectively extinct in India.

=== Bhakti Movement ===
During the 14-17th centuries,  when North India was under Muslim rule, The [[bhakti movement|''bhakti'' movement]] swept through
Central and Northern India, initiated by a loosely associated group of
teachers or ''[[Sant Mat|sants]]''. [[Chaitanya Mahaprabhu]], [[Vallabhacharya]],
[[Surdas]], [[Meera Bai]], [[Kabir]], [[Tulsidas]], [[Ravidas]],
[[Namdeo]], [[Tukaram]] and other mystics spearheaded the Bhakti
movement in the North. They taught that people could cast aside the
heavy burdens of ritual and caste, and the subtle complexities of
philosophy, and simply express their overwhelming love for God. This
period was also characterized by a spate of devotional literature in
vernacular prose and poetry in the ethnic languages of the various
Indian states or provinces. Bhakti movement spawned into several different movements all across North and South India.

During the Bhakti Movement, many Hindu groups regarded as outside the traditional Hindu caste system followed Bhakti traditions by worshipping/following saints belonging to their respective communities. For example, Guru Ravidas was a [[Chamar]] of Uttar Pradesh; Guru Parsuram Ramnami was a [[Chura]] of Chhatisgarh; and Maharishi Ram Naval was a [[Bhangi]] of Rajasthan.
Several of these saints, in their lifetime, even went to the extent of fighting conversion from foreign missionaries and only encouraging Hinduism within their communities. For example, in Assam tribals were led by Gurudev Kalicharan Bramha of the Brahmo Samaj; in Nagaland by Kacha Naga; and in Central India by Birsa Munda, Hanuman Oaron, Jatra Bhagat and Budhu Bhagat.

=== Sikhism ===
[[Guru Nanak]] (1469–1539) was the founder of [[Sikhism]]. The [[Guru Granth Sahib]] was first compiled by the fifth Sikh guru, [[Guru Arjan Dev]], from the writings of the first five Sikh gurus and others saints who preached the concept of universal brotherhood, including those of the Hindu and Muslim faith. Before the death of [[Guru Gobind Singh]], the [[Guru Granth Sahib]] was declared the eternal guru. [[Sikhism]] recognizes all humans as equal before [[Waheguru]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Akal Ustat]], Verse 85-15-1&lt;/ref&gt; regardless of colour, caste or lineage.&lt;ref&gt;[[Akal Ustat]], verse 3 to 4&lt;/ref&gt; Sikhism rejects the beliefs of idol worship and circumcision.

=== Introduction of foreign religions ===

==== Introduction of Christianity ====
{{Main|Christianity in India}}
[[File:Kerala Backwaters3.jpg|thumb|rightt|Interior of [[St. Thomas Syro-Malabar Catholic Church, Palayur]], the oldest Christian church in India and one of the seven founded by St. Thomas the Apostle in 52 AD]]
The works of scholars and [[Eastern Christianity|Eastern Christian]] writings claim that Christianity was introduced to India by [[Thomas the Apostle]], who visited [[Muziris]] in [[Kerala]] in 52 AD and baptized [[Cochin Jews|Kerala's Jewish settlements]] who are known as [[Saint Thomas Christians]] (also known as Syrian Christians or Nasrani) today.&lt;ref name=&quot;GPress&quot;&gt;Medlycott, A E. 1905 &quot;India and the Apostle Thomas&quot;; Gorgias Press LLC; ISBN 1-59333-180-0.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lbrown&quot;&gt;Leslie Brown, (1956) The Indian Christians of St. Thomas. An Account of the Ancient Syrian Church of Malabar, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press 1956, 1982 (repr.)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Puthiakunnel, (1973) &quot;Jewish colonies of India paved the way for St. Thomas&quot;, The Saint Thomas Christian Encyclopedia of India, ed. George Menachery, Vol. II.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Origin of Christianity in India - A Historiographical Critique by Dr. Benedict Vadakkekara. (2007). ISBN 81-7495-258-6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nasrani.net/2007/02/13/kerala-syrian-christian-the-tomb-of-the-apostle-persian-church-syond-of-diamper-coonan-cross-oath-divisions/ |title=Kerala Syrian Christians, Apostle in India |publisher=nasrani.net |accessdate=25 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the exact origins of Christianity in India remain unclear, there is a general scholarly consensus that Christianity was rooted in India by the 3rd century AD, including some communities who used [[Syriac]] liturgically, and it is a possibility that the religion's existence there extends to as far back as the 1st century.&lt;ref&gt;See Jones, Arun, &quot;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=mjIVn4IX69oC&amp;pg=PA93#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Christianity in South Asia]&quot; in Farhadian (ed.), ''Introducing World Christianity'' (Blackwell Publishing, 2012), p. 93. For a more thorough treatment of the topic which affirms Jones' claims, and for the use of Syriac, see Frykenberg, Robert Eric, ''Christianity in India: From Beginnings to the Present'' (Oxford University Press, 2008).  See also the earlier Neill, Stephen, ''A History of Christianity in India'' (Cambridge University Press, 1984), pp. 48-49.  Neill takes it as certain that Christianity was established in India by the 6th century and also affirms the possibility of the [[Saint Thomas Christians|St. Thomas tradition]] being true.&lt;/ref&gt;
Christianity in India has different denominations, like [[Roman Catholicism]], [[Oriental Orthodox]] Christianity and [[Protestantism]].

[[Roman Catholic]] is a denomination practiced by over 17.3 million people in India which represents less than 2% of the total population. Most Catholics reside in South India. [[Goa]] is home to Roman Catholics. The state known for its Christian population.
&lt;ref&gt;[http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0044-9202(1979)11%3A1%3C80%3ARAMISI%3E2.0.CO%3B2-Z Israel J. Ross. Ritual and Music in South India: Syrian Christian Liturgical Music in Kerala. Asian Music, Vol. 11, No. 1 (1979), pp. 80-98]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.bibleforu.com/storyofindia.htm
|title=The Story of India
|author=
|publisher=www.bibleforu.com
|accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MIR&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.indianmirror.com/religions/reli6.html
|title=Christianity
|author=
|publisher=India Mirror
|accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Christianity was introduced to Indians twice. Possibly in the 1st century by [[Thomas the Apostle|St. Thomas]], and by Europeans. Europeans brought Catholicism in the 13th century ([[Portuguese people|Portuguese]]) and [[Protestantism]] in the 18th century (British and American missionaries).
It became popular following [[European colonies in India|European colonisation]] and [[List of Protestant missionaries in India|Protestant missionary efforts]].
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://old.mbconf.ca/mb/mbh3509/christin.htm
|title=Christianity in India
|author=
|publisher=M.B. Herald, Vol. 35, No. 9
|accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:St Thomas Christians divisions.svg|thumb|center|400px|Relationship of the [[Nasrani]] groups]]

==== Advent of Islam ====
{{See also|Islam in India}}

Though Islam came to India in the early 7th century with the advent of Arab traders, it started to become a major religion during the [[Muslim conquest in the Indian subcontinent]]. {{Citation needed|date=September 2012}} Islam's spread in India mostly took place under the [[Delhi Sultanate]] (1206–1526) and the [[Mughal Empire]] (1526-1858), greatly aided by the mystic [[Sufism|Sufi]] tradition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=chandru |url=http://www.southasiaanalysis.org/%5Cpapers10%5Cpaper924.html |title=SUFISM IN INDIA: Its origin, history and politics |publisher=Southasiaanalysis.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Communalism ===
Communalism has played a key role in shaping the religious history of modern India. As an adverse result of the [[British Raj]]'s [[divide and rule]] policy, [[British India]] was [[Partition of India|partitioned]] along religious lines into two states—the Muslim-majority [[Dominion of Pakistan]] (comprising what is now the [[Pakistan|Islamic Republic of Pakistan]] and the [[Bangladesh|People's Republic of Bangladesh]]) and the Hindu-majority [[History of the Republic of India|Union of India]] (later the Republic of India). The 1947 [[Partition of India]] instigated rioting among Hindus, Muslims, and Sikhs in Punjab, Bengal, Delhi, and other parts of India; 500,000 died as a result of the violence. The twelve million refugees that moved between the newly founded nations of India and Pakistan composed one of the largest mass migrations in modern history.{{cref|Δ}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Symonds_1950_74&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Symonds|1950|p=74}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Since its independence, India has periodically witnessed large-scale violence sparked by underlying tensions between sections of its majority Hindu and minority Muslim communities. The Republic of India is secular; its government recognizes no official religion.

== Demographics ==
{{See also|Hinduism in India|Islam in India|Christianity in India|History of Buddhism in India|Sikhism in India|Jainism in India|History of the Jews in India|Parsi people|Bahá'í Faith in India| Tribal religions in India|Irreligion in India}}
{|  class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin:0 0 1em 1em;&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#f8eaba; text-align:center;&quot;|
&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
; Religion in India
&lt;/div&gt;
|-
|              
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Om.svg|[[Hinduism]]
File:Allah-eser2.png|[[Islam]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;               
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:ChristianityPUA.svg|[[Christians]]
File:Faravahar.svg|[[Faravahar]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:HarrNishaan.jpg|[[Harr Nishaan]]
File:Jain Prateek Chihna.jpg|[[Jain Prateek Chihna]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
|-
|
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:St. Thomas Cross.jpg|[[Nasrani Menorah]]
Image:Christian prayers in tamil on palm leaves.jpg|A set of 15th- or 16th-century palm-leaf manuscripts containing [[Tamil language|Tamil-language]] Christian prayers.
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Dharma Wheel.svg|[[Dharmachakra]]
Image:Khanda1.svg|[[Sikhism|Sikhism]]
&lt;/gallery&gt; 
|-
|}

[[Hinduism]] is an ancient religion (although Hinduism is diverse, with [[monotheism]], [[henotheism]], [[polytheism]], [[panentheism]], [[pantheism]], [[monism]], [[Atheism in Hinduism|atheism]], [[agnosticism]], and [[gnosticism]] being represented&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Rogers| first = Peter|title = Ultimate Truth, Book 1| publisher = AuthorHouse| year = 2009| page = 109| url = http://books.google.com/?id=e3kf6GtwaT0C&amp;pg=PA109| isbn = 978-1-4389-7968-7 | ref = harv | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Chakravarti| first = Sitansu| title = Hinduism, a way of life| publisher = Motilal Banarsidass Publ.| year = 1991| page = 71| url = http://books.google.com/?id=J_-rASTgw8wC&amp;pg=PA71| isbn =  978-81-208-0899-7 | ref = harv | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;EBpolytheism&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-38143/polytheism |title=Polytheism|accessdate= 2007-07-05 |year=2007 |work= Encyclopædia Britannica |publisher= Encyclopædia Britannica Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last = Pattanaik| first = Devdutt| title = The man who was a woman and other queer tales of Hindu lore| publisher = Routledge| year = 2002| page = 38| url = http://books.google.com/?id=Odsk9xfOp6oC&amp;pg=PA38| isbn = 978-1-56023-181-3 | ref = harv | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;), and Hinduism is also the largest religious grouping in India; its 828 million adherents (2001) compose 80.5%&lt;ref name=&quot;census2001&quot;/&gt; of the population. The term ''Hindu'', originally a geographical description, derives from the [[Sanskrit]], ''Sindhu'', (the historical appellation for the Indus River), and refers to a person from the ''land of the river Sindhu''{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}.

[[File:Islam in India.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Muslims]] praying in a [[mosque]] in [[Srinagar]], [[Jammu and Kashmir]].]]
[[Islam]] is a [[monotheism|monotheistic]] religion centred around the belief in one God and following the example of [[Muhammad]]. It is the largest minority religion in India. According to the 2001 census, India is home to 138 million Muslims,&lt;ref name=&quot;censusindia.gov.in&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.censusindia.gov.in/Census_Data_2001/Census_Data_Online/Social_and_cultural/Religion.aspx |title=Census of India - Socio-cultural aspects |publisher=Censusindia.gov.in |date= |accessdate=2011-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; the world's [[Islam by country|third-largest Muslim population]] after those in [[Islam in Indonesia|Indonesia]] (210 million)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Civil Islam: Muslims and Democratization in Indonesia |year=2000 |last=Hefner |first=RW |pages=xviii |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn=0-691-05047-3 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=tc6AcVGgLsEC}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Islam in Pakistan|Pakistan]] (166 million); they compose 13.4% of the population.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIA&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=CIA Factbook: India |work=CIA Factbook |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/in.html |accessdate=2007-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Muslims represent the majority in [[Jammu and Kashmir]] and [[Lakshadweep]],&lt;ref name=&quot;web123&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.webindia123.com/religion/indiafacts.htm |title=Religion in India |accessdate=2007-04-18 |work=Religion, webindia123.com |publisher=Suni Systems (P) Ltd }}&lt;/ref&gt; and high concentrations in the [[states and territories of India|states]] of [[Andhra Pradesh]], [[Uttar Pradesh]], [[Bihar]], [[West Bengal]], [[Assam]], and [[Kerala]].,&lt;ref name=&quot;web123&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;COI_2001&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title= Census of India 2001: Data on Religion |url= http://www.censusindia.gov.in/Census_Data_2001/Census_data_finder/C_Series/Population_by_religious_communities.htm |accessdate= 2007-12-31 |publisher= Office of the Registrar General, India}}&lt;/ref&gt; There has been no particular census conducted in India with regards to sects, but sources suggest the largest denomination is [[Sunni Islam]]&lt;ref name=&quot;state.gov&quot;&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2003/24470.htm International Religious Freedom Report 2003]. By the [[United States Department of State]]. Retrieved on April 19, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; with a substantial minority of [[Shiite Muslims]].  Indian sources like [[Times of India]] and [[Daily News &amp; Analysis|DNA]] reported [[India]]n [[Shiite]] population in mid-2005–2006 between 25% and 31% of entire Muslim population of India, which accounts them in numbers between 40&lt;ref name=&quot;timesofindia.indiatimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/lucknow/Shia-women-too-can-initiate-divorce/articleshow/334804.cms|title=Shia women too can initiate divorce| publisher=[[The Times of India]] |date=November 6, 2006| accessdate=2010-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 50 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report_talaq-rights-proposed-for-shia-women_1062327 |title=Talaq rights proposed for Shia women| publisher=Daily News and Analysis, www.dnaindia.com |date=5 November 2006| accessdate=2010-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; of a total of 157 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;state.gov&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://twocircles.net/2009oct08/india_third_global_muslim_population_1_57_bn.html|title= India Third in Global Muslim Population| publisher=[[Twocircles.net]] |accessdate=2010-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Santhome Basilica.jpg|thumb|left|200px|The [[San Thome Basilica]], a 16th-century RC Shrine in [[Chennai]](Madras).Christianity is the second largest religion in the southern state of [[Tamil Nadu]].]]
[[Christianity]] is a [[Monotheism|monotheistic]] religion centred on the life and teachings of [[Jesus]] as presented in the [[New Testament]]; it is the third largest religion of India, making up 2.3% of the population. [[Thomas the Apostle|St. Thomas]] is credited with introduction of Christianity in India. He arrived in [[Malabar (Northern Kerala)|Malabar]] in AD 52.&lt;ref name=nasrani&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nasrani.net/2007/02/16/st-thomas-tradition-the-indian-sojourn-in-foreign-sources/ |title=NSC NETWORK – Early references about the Apostolate of Saint Thomas in India, Records about the Indian tradition, Saint Thomas Christians &amp; Statements by Indian Statesmen |publisher=Nasrani.net |date= |accessdate=2011-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;missick&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Mar Thoma: The Apostolic Foundation of the Assyrian Church and the Christians of St. Thomas in India|author=Stephen Andrew Missick| publisher=Journal of Assyrian Academic studies|url=http://www.jaas.org/edocs/v14n2/missick.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stapostle.org/index2.php?area=about&amp;data=sthomasbio |title=St. Thomas the Apostle Catholic Church - Naperville, IL |publisher=Stapostle.org |date= |accessdate=2011-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christians comprise a majority in [[Nagaland]], [[Mizoram]], and [[Meghalaya]] and have significant populations in [[North-East India]], [[Goa]] and [[Kerala]].

[[File:Prayer flag col.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Prayer flags above the buddhist monastery (''[[gompa]]'') of Tanze, in the Kurgiakh Valley. The wind is believed to propagate prayers printed on the flags.]]
[[Buddhism]] is a dharmic, [[nontheism|nontheistic]] religion and philosophy. Buddhists form majority populations in the Indian states of [[Arunachal Pradesh]], and the [[Ladakh]] region of Jammu and Kashmir and a large minority (40%) in [[Sikkim]]. Around 8 million Buddhists live in India, about 0.8% of the population.&lt;ref name=&quot;censusindia.gov.in&quot;/&gt;

[[Jainism]] is a non-theistic Dharmic religion and philosophical system originating in [[Iron Age India]]. Jains though compose 0.4% (around 4.2 million) of India's population, they are the most richest, highly educated religion in whole of India. They are mainly concentrated in the states of [[Gujarat]], [[Rajasthan]], [[Maharashtra]], Karnataka, Uttar Pradesh, Madhya Pradesh, Bihar, Haryana, Punjab, Orissa, Tamil Nadu.&lt;ref name=web123/&gt; Although Jainism is usually believed to be atheistic/non-theistic, Paul Dundas writes, &quot;''While Jainism is, as we have seen, atheist in the limited sense of rejection of a creator god and the possibility of the intervention of such a being in human affairs, it nonetheless must be regarded as a theist religion in the more profound sense that it accepts the existence of a divine principle, the parmatman, often in fact referred to as 'God' (e.g. ParPr 114-16), existing in potential state within all beings''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dundas, P. 110-1 ''The Jains''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Paul Dundas]] writes that most British judges of the 19th century &quot;had no doubts about the independent nature and origin of Jainism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dundas, P. 5 The Jains&quot;&gt;Dundas, P. 5 ''The Jains''&lt;/ref&gt; In 1847, one judge wrote that [[Religious minority|religious minorities]] like [[Jain]]s, [[Parsi]]s, and Sikhs &quot;Had nothing or next to nothing in common with brahmanical worship&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dundas, P. 5 The Jains&quot;/&gt; Another judge noted in 1874 that Jains could not be subject to Hindu law because &quot;the term Hindoos means persons within the purview of the [[shastra]]s, which shastras are at the bottom of Hindu law. If a person is out of that purview, Hindoo law cannot be applied to him&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dundas, P. He adds the term &quot;Jain-hindu&quot; was an 'unhappy and artificial compromise&quot;.

[[Sikhism]] began in sixteenth century [[North India]] with the teachings of [[Guru Nanak Dev|Nanak]] and nine successive human [[Sikh Gurus|gurus]]. As of 2001, there were 19.2 million [[Sikhism in India|Sikhs in India]]. [[Punjab (India)|Punjab]] is the spiritual home of Sikhs, and is the only state in India where Sikhs form a majority. There are also significant populations of Sikhs in neighboring [[New Delhi]] and [[Haryana]].

[[File:Bahai-house-of-worship-delhi2.jpg|thumb|left|200px|A popular Bahá'í House of Worship in Delhi, India, located at {{Coord|28|33|11.46|N|77|15|35.10|E}}]]

                                                     [[Parsis]] As of the census of 2001, [[Parsi people|Parsis]] (followers of [[Zoroastrianism]] in India) represent approximately 0.006% of the total population of India,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|last=Bose|first=Ashish et al.|date=2004-12-04|title=Growth of the Parsi population in India|location=Mumbai|publisher=Government of India: National Commission for Minorities|page=3|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; with relatively high concentrations in and around the city of [[Mumbai]]. Parsis number around 61,000 in India with high concentrations in Mumbai according to 2001 census. There are several tribal religions in India, such as [[Donyi-Polo]]. [[Santhal]] is also one of the many tribal religions followed by the [[Santhal]] people who number around 4 million but only around 23,645 follow the religion. About 2.2 million people in India follow the [[Bahá'í Faith]], thus forming the largest community of Bahá'ís in the world.&lt;ref name=bahaiindia&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bahaindia.org/ |title=The Bahá'ís of India |accessdate=2007-04-18 |work=bahaindia.org |publisher=National Spiritual Assembly of the Bahá'ís of India }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Kochi Jewish Synagogue C.jpg|thumb|left|200px|The interior of the [[Paradesi Synagogue]] in Cochin.]]
[[Judaism]] is also present in India, a [[monotheistic]] religion from the [[Levant]]. There is today a very small community of Indian Jews. There were more Jews in India historically, including the [[Cochin Jews]] of [[Kerala]], the [[Bene Israel]] of [[Maharashtra]], and the [[Baghdadi Jews]] near [[Mumbai]]. In addition, since independence two primarily proselyte Indian Jewish communities in India: the [[Bnei Menashe]] of [[Mizoram]] and [[Manipur]], and the [[Bene Ephraim]], also called '''Telugu Jews'''.  Of the approximately 95,000 Jews of Indian origin, fewer than 20,000 remain in India. Some parts of India are especially popular with Israelis, swelling local Jewish populations seasonally.

Around 0.07% of the people did not state their religion in the 2001 census.

[[Ravidassia]], a religion started by a saint of 15th century [[Guru Ravidass]] has grown by his spiritual belief and lessons of universal brotherhood, tolerance, message of love your neighbour. He is by far the most revered among the scheduled castes, especially dalits of Northwest and Central India. Today their population stood at around 16.2% of India's total population. Most of them are found in Norther Indian states and among them in Punjab. Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh has been treated as religious home to the lakhs of devotees of Ravidassia Religion and deserves to be one of the place visited by Ravidassias during the Guru [[Ravidas Jayanti]] in February from all over the world.

=== Statistics ===

[[File:India religion map 1909 en.jpg|thumb|right|Map of the [[British India|British Indian Empire]] in 1909, shaded by prevailing religion.{{See also|Demographics of India}}]]
;Population trends for major religious groups (1961–2001)
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
! Religious&lt;br /&gt;group
! Population &lt;br&gt;% '''1961'''
! Population &lt;br&gt;% '''1971'''
! Population &lt;br&gt;% '''1981'''
! Population &lt;br&gt;% '''1991'''
! Population &lt;br&gt;% '''2001'''
|-
! style=&quot;background:#e5bca6;&quot;| [[Hinduism|Hindu]]
| 83.45% || 82.73% || 82.30% || 81.53% || 80.46% 
|-
! style=&quot;background:#bdbf97;&quot;| [[Islam|Muslim]]
| 10.69% || 11.21% || 11.75% || 12.61% || 13.43% 
|-
! style=&quot;background:#a69a8e;&quot;| [[Christianity|Christian]]
| 2.44% || 2.60%  || 2.44% || 2.32% || 2.34% 
|-
! | [[Sikhism|Sikh]]
| 1.79% || 1.89%  || 1.92% || 1.94% || 1.87% 
|-
! style=&quot;background:#f6e4a0;&quot;| [[Buddhism|Buddhist]]
| 0.74% || 0.70%  || 0.70% || 0.77% || 0.77% 
|-
! style=&quot;background:#b4a28e;&quot;| [[Animism|Animist]], others
| 0.43% || 0.41% || 0.42% || 0.44% || 0.72% 
|-
! | [[Jainism|Jain]]
| 0.46% || 0.48%  || 0.47% || 0.40% || 0.41% 
|}
{{-}}
The following is a breakdown of India's religious communities:

;Characteristics of religious groups (2001 census)
{| class=&quot;sortable wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:auto;&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
! Religious&lt;br /&gt;group
! Population&lt;br /&gt;%
! [[Population growth|Growth]]&lt;br /&gt;(1991–2001)
! [[Sex ratio]]&lt;br /&gt;(total)
! [[Literacy]]&lt;br /&gt;(%)
! [[Labor force|Work participation]]&lt;br /&gt;(%)
! Sex ratio&lt;br /&gt;(rural)
! Sex ratio&lt;br /&gt;(urban)
! Sex ratio&lt;br /&gt;(child) 
|-
! style=&quot;background:#e5bca6;&quot;| [[Hinduism|Hindu]]
| 80.46% || 20.3% || 931  || 65.1% || 40.4% || 944  || 894  || 925
|-
! style=&quot;background:#bdbf97;&quot;| [[Islam|Muslim]]
|13.43% || 29.3% || 936  || 59.1% || 31.3% || 953  || 907  || 950
|-
! style=&quot;background:#a69a8e;&quot;| [[Christianity|Christian]]
| 2.34% || 22.6%  || 1009 || 80.3% || 39.7% || 1001 || 1026 || 964
|-
! | [[Sikhism|Sikh]]
| 1.87% || 18.2%  || 893  || 69.4% || 37.7% || 895  || 886  || 786
|-
! style=&quot;background:#f6e4a0;&quot;| [[Buddhism|Buddhist]]
| 0.77% || 18.2%  || 953  || 72.7% || 40.6% || 958  || 944  || 942
|-
! style=&quot;background:#b4a28e;&quot;| [[Animism|Animist]], others
| 0.72% || 103.1% || 992  || 47.0% || 48.4% || 995  || 966  || 976
|-
! | [[Jainism|Jain]]
| 0.41% || 26.0%  || 940  || 94.1% || 32.9% || 937  || 941  || 870
|}
na]]

== Irreligion ==
{{Main|Irreligion in India}}

Though followed by a minor portion of the Indian population, [[irreligion]] (including [[atheists]], [[agnostics]], and [[humanists]]) has a strong tradition in India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | first = Robert
 | last = Evans
 | title = Atheists, Humanists Push Campaign for 'Darwin Day'
 | agency = [[Reuters]]
 | date = 12 February 2004
 | quote = In India, where humanism and atheism have a strong tradition and are not so distant from traditional Hindu thought, which rejects &quot;ultimate truths,&quot; rationalists are alarmed at the rise of an aggressively militant version of Hinduism.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Dentsu Communication Institute Inc, Japan Research Center (2006), 6.6% of Indians stated that they had no religion.&lt;ref name=&quot;dentsu&quot;&gt;{{ja icon}} http://www2.ttcn.ne.jp/~honkawa/9460.html '''English source requested'''&lt;/ref&gt;

== Law ==
{{Main|Constitution of India|Fundamental Rights, Directive Principles and Fundamental Duties of India|Secularism in India|Indian religion#Status in the Republic of India}}
The preamble to the [[Constitution of India]] proclaimed India a &quot;sovereign socialist secular democratic republic&quot;. The word ''secular'' was inserted into the Preamble by the [[Forty-second Amendment Act of 1976]]. It mandates equal treatment and tolerance of all religions. India does not have an official state religion; it enshrines the right to practice, preach, and propagate any religion. No religious instruction is imparted in government-supported schools. In [[S. R. Bommai vs. Union of India]], the [[Supreme Court of India]] held that secularism was an integral tenet of the Constitution.&lt;ref name=hinduswami&gt;{{cite journal |author=Swami, Praveen |date=1 November 1997 |title=Protecting secularism and federal fair play |journal=Frontline |volume=14 |issue=22 |url=http://www.hinduonnet.com/fline/fl1422/14220170.htm |accessdate=2007-04-17 |ref=harv |authorlink=Praveen Swami }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Fundamental Rights in India#Right to freedom of religion|right to freedom of religion]] is a [[fundamental right]] according to the Indian Constitution. The Constitution also suggests a [[uniform civil code]] for its citizens as a [[Directive Principles in India|Directive Principle]].&lt;ref&gt;[[wikisource:Constitution of India/Part IV|Constitution of India-Part IV Article 44 Directive Principles of State Policy]]&lt;/ref&gt;  This has not been implemented until now as Directive Principles are Constitutionally unenforceable. The Supreme Court has further held that the enactment of a uniform civil code all at once may be counterproductive to the unity of the nation, and only a gradual progressive change should be brought about (''Pannalal Bansilal v State of Andhra Pradesh, 1996'').&lt;ref name=hinduiyer&gt;{{cite news |author=Iyer VRK |title=Unifying personal laws |url=http://www.hindu.com/2003/09/06/stories/2003090600831000.htm |work=Opinion |publisher=[[The Hindu]] |date=6 September 2003 |accessdate=2007-04-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Maharishi Avadesh v Union of India (1994)'' the Supreme Court dismissed a petition seeking a writ of [[mandamus]] against the government to introduce a common civil code, and thus laid the responsibility of its introduction on the [[Legislature of India|legislature]].&lt;ref name=rediffarvind&gt;{{cite news |first = Arvind |last=Lavakare |title=Where's the Uniform Civil Code? |url=http://www.rediff.com/news/2002/may/21arvind.htm |work=rediff.com |publisher=Rediff.com India Limited |date=21 May 2002 |accessdate=2007-04-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Major religious communities not based in India continue to be governed by their own personal laws. While Muslims, Christians, Zoroastrians, and Jews have personal laws exclusive to themselves; Hindus, Jains, Buddhists and Sikhs are governed by a single personal law known as [[Modern Hindu law|Hindu personal law]]. Article 25 (2)(b) of the [[Constitution of India]] states that references to Hindus include &quot;persons professing the Sikh, Jain or Buddhist religion&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bakshi1996&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Bakshi|first=P M|title=Constitution Of India|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=QmxuAAAACAAJ|accessdate=15 July 2010|year=1996|publisher=Universal Law Publishing Co.P Ltd.|isbn=978-81-7534-003-9|page=41}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore the [[Hindu Marriage Act of 1955]] defines the legal status of Jains, Buddhists and Sikhs as legal Hindus but not &quot;Hindus by religion&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Diwan1981&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Diwan|first=Paras|title=Modern Hindu law: codified and uncodified|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-tPXOgAACAAJ|accessdate=15 July 2010|year=1981|publisher=Allahabad Law Agency}}&lt;/ref&gt; The only Indian religion exclusively covered under the secular (&quot;civil&quot;) law of India is [[Brahmoism]] starting from Act III of 1872.

== Aspects ==
Religion plays a major role in the Indian way of life.&lt;ref name=&quot;PRC_2002&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://people-press.org/reports/display.php3?ReportID=167 |title=Among Wealthy Nations ... U.S. Stands Alone in its Embrace of Religion |publisher=The Pew Research Center for the People and the Press |date=19 December 2002 |accessdate=2007-06-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rituals, worship, and other religious activities are very prominent in an individual's daily life; it is also a principal organiser of social life. The degree of religiosity varies among individuals; in recent decades, religious orthodoxy and observances have become less common in Indian society, particularly among young urban-dwellers.

=== Rituals ===
[[File:Flood puja.jpg|thumb|A ''[[Puja (Hinduism)|puja]]'' performed on the banks of the overflowing [[Shipra River]] in [[Ujjain]] during the [[Climate of India#Monsoon|summer monsoon]].]]
&lt;!--[[File:Ladakhdance.jpg|thumb|[[Tibetan Buddhism|Tibetan Buddhist]] dancers celebrate [[Tsechu]] near the [[Lamayuru]] [[Gompa|Monastary]] in western [[Ladakh]].]]--&gt;

The vast majority of Indians engage in religious rituals on a daily basis.&lt;ref name=religiouslife&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.religionsofindia.org/loc/india_religious_life.html
| title = Religious Life
| accessdate = 2007-04-19
| work = Religions of India
| publisher = Global Peace Works
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050301062310/http://religionsofindia.org/loc/india_religious_life.html |archivedate = March 1, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most Hindus observe religious rituals at home.&lt;ref name=locceremonies&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+in0055)
| title = Domestic Worship
| accessdate = 2007-04-19
|month=September | year=1995
| work = Country Studies
| publisher = The Library of Congress
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Observation of rituals greatly vary among regions, villages, and individuals. Devout Hindus perform daily chores such as worshiping [[Puja (Hinduism)|puja]], fire scrifice called [[Yajna]] at the dawn after bathing (usually at a family shrine, and typically includes lighting a lamp and offering foodstuffs before the images of deities), recitation from religious scripts like [[Vedas]], [[Puranas]] singing hymns in praise of gods etc.&lt;ref name=locceremonies/&gt;

A notable feature in religious ritual is the division between purity and pollution. Religious acts presuppose some degree of impurity or defilement for the practitioner, which must be overcome or neutralised before or during ritual procedures. Purification, usually with water, is thus a typical feature of most religious action.&lt;ref name=locceremonies/&gt; Other characteristics include a belief in the efficacy of sacrifice and concept of merit, gained through the performance of charity or good works, that will accumulate over time and reduce sufferings in the next world.&lt;ref name=locceremonies/&gt;

Devout Muslims offer [[Salah#The five daily prayers|five daily prayers]] at specific times of the day, indicated by ''[[adhan]]'' (call to prayer) from the local mosques. Before offering prayers, they must ritually clean themselves by performing ''[[wudu]]'', which involves washing parts of the body that are generally exposed to dirt or dust. A recent study by the [[Sachar Committee]] found that 3-4% of Muslim children study in ''[[madrasa]]s'' (Islamic schools).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Chishti S, Jacob J |title=Sachar nails madrasa myth: Only 4% of Muslim kids go there |work=[[The Indian Express]] |url=http://www.indianexpress.com/sunday/story/17677.html |date=1 December 2006 |accessdate=2007-04-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diet===
{{See also|Vegetarianism and religion|Fasting}}
Dietary habits are significantly influenced by religion. Almost one-third of Indians practice lacto-[[vegetarianism]];&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hinduonnet.com/2006/08/14/stories/2006081403771200.htm The food habits of a nation] [[The Hindu]]&lt;/ref&gt; it came to prominence during the rule of [[Emperor Ashoka]] of the [[Maurya Empire]], a promoter of Buddhism.&lt;ref name=&quot;JT_Thakrar_2007-04-22&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/fl20070422x4.html |title=Japanese warm to real curries and more |work=[[Japan Times]] |last=Thakrar |first=Raju |date=22 April 2007 |accessdate=2007-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Charlton|2004|p=91}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Vegetarianism is much less common among [[Diet in Sikhism|Sikhs]] and almost uncommon among [[Muslim]]s, [[Christian]]s, [[Bahá'í]]s, [[Parsis]] and [[Jews]].&lt;ref name=hindueatsurvey&gt;{{cite news
 | first = Yogendra
 | last = Yadav
 | coauthors =Sanjay Kumar
 | title =  The food habits of a nation
 | url = http://www.hinduonnet.com/2006/08/14/stories/2006081403771200.htm
 | work = hinduonnet.com
 | publisher = The Hindu
 | date = August 14, 2006
 | accessdate = 2007-04-21
 | language =
 | quote =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jainism requires monks and laity, from all its sects and traditions, to be vegetarian.Furthermore, the religion also bars jains from eating any vegetable that involves digging it from the ground. This rule, therefore, excludes potatoes, sweet potatoes, carrots, garlic, peanuts, raddish etc. from Jain diet. Hinduism bars beef consumption, while Islam bars pork.

=== Ceremonies ===
[[File:Hindu marriage ceremony offering.jpg|thumb|A Hindu marriage.]]

Occasions like birth, [[Indian wedding|marriage]], and death involve what are often elaborate sets of religious customs. In Hinduism, major life-cycle rituals include ''[[annaprashan]]'' (a baby's first intake of solid food), ''[[upanayanam]]'' (&quot;sacred thread ceremony&quot; undergone by upper-caste youths), and ''[[shraadh]]'' (paying homage to a deceased individual).&lt;ref name=loclifecycle&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+in0056)
| title = Life-Cycle Rituals
| accessdate = 2007-04-19
|month=September | year=1995
| work = Country Studies: India
| publisher = The Library of Congress
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=shraddha&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://banglapedia.search.com.bd/HT/S_0516.htm | title = Shraddha
|last=Banerjee |first=Suresh Chandra | accessdate = 2007-04-20 | work = [[Banglapedia]]
| publisher = Asiatic Society of Bangladesh }}&lt;/ref&gt; For most people in India, the betrothal of the young couple and the exact date and time of the wedding are matters decided by the parents in consultation with [[astrologer]]s.&lt;ref name=loclifecycle/&gt;

Muslims practice a series of life-cycle rituals that differ from those of Hindus, Jains, and Buddhists.&lt;ref name=locislamtrad&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+in0059)
| title = Islamic Traditions in South Asia
| accessdate = 2007-04-19
|month=September | year=1995
| work = Country Studies: India
| publisher = The Library of Congress
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several rituals mark the first days of life—including whispering call to prayer, first bath, and shaving of the head. Religious instruction begins early. Male [[circumcision]] usually takes place after birth; in some families, it may be delayed until after the onset of puberty.&lt;ref name=locislamtrad/&gt;

Marriage requires a payment by the husband to the wife and the solemnisation of a marital contract in a social gathering.&lt;ref name=locislamtrad/&gt; On the third day after burial of the dead, friends and relatives gather to console the bereaved, read and recite the Quran, and pray for the soul of the deceased.&lt;ref name=locislamtrad/&gt; Indian Islam is distinguished by the emphasis it places on shrines commemorating great Sufi saints.&lt;ref name=locislamtrad/&gt;

=== Pilgrimages ===
{{See also|Hindu pilgrimage sites in India|Buddhist pilgrimage sites in India}}
[[File:Kumbh Mela 2001.jpg|thumb|The largest religious gathering ever held on Earth, the 2001 [[Kumbh Mela|Maha Kumbh Mela]] held in [[Prayag]] attracted around 70 million Hindus from around the world.]] Many Hindu families  has their own family patron deity or the ''[[kuladevata|Kuladaivat]]''.{{sfn|Hassan|1920|pp=110–111}} This deity is common to a lineage or a clan of several families who are connected to each other through a common ancestor.{{sfn|Hassan|1920|pp=110–111}}{{sfn|Walunjkar|pp=285–287}} The [[Khandoba]] of Jejuri is an example of a Kuladaivat of some Maharashtrian families; he is a common Kuladaivat to several castes ranging from Brahmins to [[Dalit]]s.{{sfn|Government of Maharashtra|1962|p=}} The practice of worshiping local or territorial deities as Kuladaivats began in the period of the [[Yadava dynasty]].{{sfn|Walunjkar|pp=285–287}} Other family deities of the people of Maharashtra are [[Bhavani]] of [[Tuljapur]], [[Mahalakshmi Temple, Kolhapur|Mahalaxmi]] of [[Kolhapur]],  [[Renuka]] of [[Mahur, Maharashtra|Mahur]], and [[Venkateswara|Balaji]] of Tirupati. 
[[File:Maramon convention.JPG|thumb| Maramon Convention, the largest annual Christian gathering in Asia, organized by the Mar Thoma Church.]]
India hosts numerous pilgrimage sites belonging to many religions. Hindus worldwide recognise several Indian holy cities, including [[Allahabad]], [[Haridwar]], [[Varanasi]], [[Ujjain]], [[Rameshwaram]] and [[Vrindavan]]. Notable temple cities include [[Puri]], which hosts a major [[Jagannath]] temple and [[Rath Yatra]] celebration; [[Tirumala - Tirupati]], home to the [[Tirumala Venkateswara Temple]]; and [[Katra, Jammu and Kashmir|Katra]], home to the [[Vaishno Devi]] temple.

The [[Himalaya]]n towns of [[Badrinath]], [[Kedarnath]], [[Gangotri]], and [[Yamunotri]] compose the ''[[Char Dham]]'' (''four abodes'') pilgrimage circuit. The [[Kumbh Mela]] (the &quot;pitcher festival&quot;) is one of the holiest of Hindu pilgrimages that is held every four years; the location is rotated among Allahabad, Haridwar, [[Nashik]], and [[Ujjain]].

Among the [[Buddhist pilgrimage#The Eight Great Places|Eight Great Places]] of Buddhism, seven are in India. [[Bodh Gaya]], [[Sarnath]] and [[Kushinagar]] are the places where important events in the life of Gautama Buddha took place. [[Sanchi]] hosts a Buddhist [[stupa]] erected by the emperor [[Ashoka]]. Several Tibetan Buddhist sites in the Himalayan foothills of India have been built, such as [[Rumtek Monastery]] and [[Dharamsala, Himachal Pradesh|Dharamsala]].

For Muslims, the ''Dargah Shareef'' of Khwaza [[Moinuddin Chishti]] in [[Ajmer]] is a major pilgrimage site. Other Islamic pilgrimages include those to the Tomb of Sheikh [[Salim Chishti]] in [[Fatehpur Sikri]], [[Jama Masjid, Delhi|Jama Masjid]] in Delhi, and to [[Haji Ali Dargah]] in Mumbai. [[Dilwara Temples]] in [[Mount Abu]], [[Palitana]], [[Pavapuri]], [[Girnar]] and [[Shravanabelagola]] are notable pilgrimage sites ([[tirtha]]) in Jainism.

The [[Harmandir Sahib]] in [[Amritsar]] is the most sacred [[gurdwara]] of Sikhism, while the [[Bahá'í House of Worship#Delhi, India|Lotus Temple]] in Delhi is a prominent house of worship of the Bahá'í faith. 

Relatively new pilgrimage sites include the [[samadhi]] of [[Meher Baba]] in [[Meherabad]], which is visited by his followers from around the world &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ambppct.org/events/inhisservice/IHS_NL_11_June.pdf &quot;In His Service: A Newsletter From Meherabad&quot;]. June 2011. Myrtle Beach: Sheriar Press. p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Saibaba]] temple in [[Shirdi]].
&lt;ref&gt;[S Srinivas - Journal of Contemporary Religion, 1999 - Taylor &amp; Francis]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Minority Beliefs and Sects===

Hinduism contains many different sub-cultures just like most other religions. The major aspects outlined above hold true for the majority of the Hindu population, but not all. Just as each state is home to an individual language, Hinduism harbors various sub-cultures whose traditions may or may not be shared by other Indians. A sect from Gujarat called the ''Prajapatis'' for example, hold water as the sacred ornament to every meal. Before and after a meal, an individual is expected to pour water in the palms of their right hand and sip the water three times.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;R. Blake Michael - The Origins of Virasaiva Sects, 1992 - Motilal Banarsidass Pub&lt;/ref&gt; This is often seen as a purification gesture: food is regarded as being holy and every individual must purify themselves before touching their food.

Other minor sects in India carry no specific name, but they are uniquely identified by the last names of each family. This convention is used more frequently in South India than North India. For example, a relatively prominent sect in southern India prohibits making important decisions, commencing new tasks, and doing other intellectually or spiritually engaged actions after sunset. Historians believe that this tradition was derived from the concept of [[Rahukaalam]], in which Hindus believe that a specific time period of the day is inauspicious. Stringent family beliefs are thought to have led to the development of a more constrained religious hierarchy.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.astrojyotish.com/rahu-kalam/&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, this belief was extended to discourage taking major actions and even staying awake for long periods of time after sunset. Examples of families which follow this tradition include ''Gudivada'', ''Padalapalli'', ''Pantham'', and ''[[Kashyap]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

== Religion and politics ==
{{See also|Status of religious freedom in India}}

[[File:Takht Shri Hazoor Sahib Gurudwara Nanded.JPG|right|250px|thumb|[[Takht Sri Hazur Sahib]], [[Nanded]], built over the place where Guru Gobind Singh was cremated in 1708, the inner chamber is still called ''Angitha Sahib''.]]

=== Politics ===
Religious ideology, particularly that expressed by the [[Hindutva]] movement, has strongly influenced [[Politics of India|Indian politics]] in the last quarter of the 20th century. Many of the elements underlying India's [[casteism]] and [[communalism (South Asia)|communalism]] originated during the rule of the [[British India|British Raj]], particularly after the late 19th century; the authorities and others often politicised religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Makkar|1993|p=141}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Indian Councils Act 1909]] (widely known as the Morley-Minto Reforms Act), which established separate Hindu and Muslim electorates for the Imperial Legislature and provincial councils, was particularly divisive. It was blamed for increasing tensions between the two communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Olson|Shadle|1996|p=759}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the high degree of oppression faced by the lower castes, the [[Constitution of India]] included provisions for [[affirmative action]] for certain sections of Indian society. Growing disenchantment with the [[Hindu caste system]] has led thousands of [[Dalits]] (also referred to as &quot;Untouchables&quot;) to embrace Buddhism and Christianity in recent decades.&lt;ref name=bbcdalit&gt;{{cite news |title=Dalits in conversion ceremony |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6050408.stm |work=BBC News |date=14 October 2006 |accessdate=2007-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, many states ruled by the [[Bharatiya Janata Party]] (BJP) introduced laws that made them more difficult; they assert that such conversions are often forced or allured.&lt;ref name=bjpdalit&gt;{{cite journal |date=May 1–15, 2006 |title=Constitution doesn’t permit forced conversions: Naqvi |journal=BJP Today |volume=15 |issue=9 |url=http://www.bjp.org/today/may_0106/may_0106_p_30.htm |accessdate=2007-04-20 |format= – &lt;sup&gt;[http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=intitle%3AConstitution+doesn%E2%80%99t+permit+forced+conversions%3A+Naqvi&amp;as_publication=BJP+Today&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_yhi=&amp;btnG=Search Scholar search]&lt;/sup&gt; |ref=harv |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070921113541/http://www.bjp.org/today/may_0106/may_0106_p_30.htm |archivedate = September 21, 2007}} {{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The BJP, a ]] party, also gained widespread media attention after its leaders associated themselves with the [[Ayodhya debate|Ram Janmabhoomi movement]] and other prominent religious issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ludden|1996|pp=64–65}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A well known accusation that Indian political parties make for their rivals is that they play vote bank politics, meaning give political support to issues for the sole purpose of gaining the votes of members of a particular community. Both the [[Indian National Congress|Congress Party]] and the BJP have been accused of exploiting the people by indulging in vote bank politics. The [[Shah Bano case]], a divorce lawsuit, generated much controversy when the Congress was accused of appeasing the Muslim orthodoxy by bringing in a parliamentary amendment to negate the [[Supreme Court of India|Supreme Court's]] decision. After the [[2002 Gujarat violence]], there were allegations of political parties indulging in vote bank politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | author = Times News Network
 | title = Togadia wants parties to stop 'vote bank politics'
 | url = http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/4806609.cms
 | work = indiatimes.com
 | publisher = Times Internet Limited
 | date = 25 March 2002
 | accessdate = 2007-04-20
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During an election campaign in [[Uttar Pradesh]], the BJP released an inflammatory CD targeting Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6538445.stm |title=BJP protests in campaign CD row |work=BBC News |date=9 April 2007 |accessdate=2007-05-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This was condemned by the [[Communist Party of India (Marxist)]] as playing the worst kind of vote bank politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;PD_2007&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=BJP’s true colours exposed once again |journal=People's Democracy |publisher=Communist Party of India (Marxist) |url=http://pd.cpim.org/2007/0415/04152007_edit.htm |date=15 April 2007 |accessdate=2007-05-27 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Caste politics in India|Caste-based politics]] is also important in India; caste-based discrimination and the [[Reservation in India|reservation system]] continue to be major issues that are hotly debated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chadha_2006&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Chadha M |title=Despair of the discriminated Dalits |publisher=BBC News |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6211532.stm |date=5 December 2006 |accessdate=2007-06-03 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Giridharadas_2006&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Giridharadas A |title=Turning point in India's caste war |publisher=International Herald Tribune |url=http://www.iht.com/articles/2006/04/21/business/QUOTAS.php |date=22 April 2006 |accessdate=2007-06-03 |ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Education ===
Several political parties have been accused of using their political power to manipulate educational content in a [[historical revisionism|revisionist]] manner. During the [[Janata Party]] government (1977–1979), the government was accused of being too sympathetic to the Muslim viewpoint. In 2002, the BJP-led [[National Democratic Alliance (India)|NDA]] government tried to change the [[National Council of Educational Research and Training]] (NCERT) school textbooks through a new National Curriculum Framework.&lt;ref name=&quot;delhi1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Mukherjee M, Mukherjee A |format=PDF |title=Communalisation of education: the history textbook controversy |publisher=Delhi Historians' Group |url=http://www.sacw.net/India_History/DelHistorians.pdf |month=December |year=2001 |accessdate= 2007-06-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some media referred to it as the &quot;saffronisation&quot; of textbooks, saffron being the colour of BJP flag.&lt;ref name=&quot;delhi1&quot;/&gt; The next government, formed by the UPA and led by the Congress Party, pledged to de-saffronise textbooks.&lt;ref name=report2005&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2005/51618.htm |title= International Religious Freedom Report 2005|accessdate= 2007-06-03 |author=Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor |date=November 8, 2005|work=2005 Report on International Religious Freedom |publisher= U.S. State Department}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hindu groups alleged that the UPA promoted Marxist and pro-Muslim biases in school curricula.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Upadhyay R |title=The politics of education in India: the need for a national debate |publisher=South Asia Analysis Group |url=http://www.saag.org/%5Cpapers3%5Cpaper299.html |date=21 August 2001 |accessdate=2007-06-03 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20051217091426/http://www.saag.org/papers3/paper299.html |archivedate = December 17, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Upadhyay R |title=Opposition in India: in search of genuine issues |publisher= South Asia Analysis Group |url=http://www.saag.org/%5Cpapers2%5Cpaper107.html |date=26 February 2000 |accessdate=2007-06-03 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20051217072319/http://www.saag.org/papers2/paper107.html |archivedate = December 17, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Conflicts ===
{{Main|Religious violence in India}}
{{see also|Religious conflicts in India}}
[[File:Calcutta 1946 riot.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Aftermath of Hindu-Muslim clashes in Calcutta following the 1946 Direct Action Day.]]

Communal conflicts have periodically plagued India since it became independent in 1947. The roots of such strife lie largely in the underlying tensions between sections of its majority Hindu and minority Muslim communities, which emerged under the Raj and during the bloody [[Partition of India]]. Such conflict also stems from the competing ideologies of [[Hindu fundamentalism]] versus [[Islamic fundamentalism]] and [[Islamism]]; both are prevalent in parts of the Hindu and Muslim populations.

Alongside other major Indian independence leaders, [[Mahatma Gandhi]] and his ''shanti sainiks'' (&quot;peace soldiers&quot;) worked to quell early outbreaks of religious conflict in [[Bengal]], including riots in [[Kolkata|Calcutta]] (now in [[West Bengal]]) and [[Noakhali District]] (in modern-day Bangladesh) that accompanied [[Muhammad Ali Jinnah]]'s [[Direct Action Day]], which was launched on 16 August 1946. These conflicts, waged largely with rocks and knives and accompanied by widespread looting and arson, were crude affairs. Explosives and firearms, which are rarely found in India, were far less likely to be used.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shepard|1987|pp=45–46}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ahmedabad riots1.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Many of [[Ahmedabad]]'s buildings were set on fire during the [[2002 Gujarat violence]].]]
&lt;!--[[File:Blue star akal takht.jpg|thumb|left|135px|The bullet- and shell-riddled [[Akal Takht]] after [[Operation Blue Star]].]]--&gt;

Major post-independence communal conflicts include the [[1984 Anti-Sikh riots]], which followed [[Operation Blue Star]] by the [[Indian Army]]; heavy artillery, tanks, and helicopters were employed against the [[Khalistan movement|Sikh partisans]] inside the [[Harmandir Sahib]], causing heavy damage to Sikhism's holiest [[Gurdwara]]. According to the Indian government estimations, the assault caused the deaths of up to 100 soldiers, 250 militants, and hundreds of civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nichols_2003&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |title=The Politics of Assassination: Case Studies and Analysis |last=Nichols |first=B |journal=Australasian Political Studies Association Conference |year=2003 |url=http://www.utas.edu.au/government/APSA/BNichols.pdf|format=PDF |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This triggered [[Indira Gandhi]]'s assassination by her outraged Sikh bodyguards on 31 October 1984, which set off a four-day period during which Sikhs were massacred; The [[Government of India]] reported 2,700 Sikh deaths however human rights organizations and newspapers report the death toll to be 10,000-17,000. In the aftermath of the riot, the [[Government of India]] reported 20,000 had fled the city, however the [[PUCL]] reported &quot;at least&quot; 50,000 displaced persons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mukhoty 1984&quot;&gt;{{Cite document |title=Who are the Guilty ? | last =Mukhoty | first =Gobinda | last2 =Kothari | first2 =Rajni |url=http://www.sacw.net/aii/WhoaretheGuilty.html |year=1984 |publisher=[[People's Union for Civil Liberties]] |ref=harv |postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most affected regions were neighborhoods in [[Delhi]]. Human rights organizations and the newspapers believe the massacre was organized.&lt;ref name=&quot;Watch/Asia(U.S.)1994&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Watch/Asia|first1=Human Rights|last2=(U.S.)|first2=Physicians for Human Rights|title=Dead silence: the legacy of human rights abuses in Punjab|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Dx7b8w6snbsC&amp;pg=PA13|accessdate=29 July 2010|date=1994-05|publisher=Human Rights Watch|isbn=978-1-56432-130-5|page=10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The collusion of political officials in the massacres and the failure to prosecute any killers alienated normal [[Sikhs]] and increased support for the [[Khalistan movement]]. The [[Akal Takht]], the governing religious body of [[Sikhism]], most definitely considers the killings to be a [[genocide]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/1984-riots-were-Sikh-genocide-Akal-Takht/Article1-572372.aspx|title=1984 riots were 'Sikh genocide': Akal Takht - Hindustan Times|date=July 14, 2010|work=Hindustan Times|accessdate=17 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other incidents include the 1992 [[Bombay Riots]] that followed the demolition of the [[Babri Mosque]] as a result of the [[Ayodhya debate]], and the [[2002 Gujarat violence]] that followed the [[Godhra Train Burning]]—in the latter, more than 2,000 Muslims were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;HRW_2006_265&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Human Rights Watch|2006|p=265}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Terrorist activities such as the [[2005 Ram Janmabhoomi attack in Ayodhya]], the [[2006 Varanasi bombings]], the [[2006 Jama Masjid explosions]], and the [[11 July 2006 Mumbai Train Bombings]] are often blamed on communalism. Lesser incidents plague many towns and villages; representative was the killing of five people in [[Mau]], [[Uttar Pradesh]] during Hindu-Muslim rioting, which was triggered by the proposed celebration of a Hindu festival.&lt;ref name=&quot;HRW_2006_265&quot;/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;'''Major religious riots, since Independence'''&lt;/center&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; &quot;text-align:left;font-size:100%;&quot;|
|-
!  style=&quot;height:17px; background:#f75d59; color:#fdeef4; width:100px;&quot;| Year
! ! style=&quot;background:#f75d59; color:#fdeef4; width:140px;&quot;| Riot
! ! style=&quot;background:#f75d59; color:#fdeef4; width:130px;&quot;| State / Region
! ! style=&quot;background:#f75d59; color:#fdeef4; width:150px;&quot;| Cause
! ! style=&quot;background:#f75d59; color:#fdeef4; width:330px;&quot;| Aftermath
|-
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| &lt;center&gt;1984&lt;/center&gt;
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[1984 anti-Sikh riots|Anti Sikh riots]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Delhi]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Indira Gandhi assassination|Assassination of Indira Gandhi]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Government of India]] reported 2,700 [[Sikh]] deaths and 20,000 displaced. [[PUCL]] and newspapers report death toll to be 10,000-17,000 and &quot;at least&quot; 50,000 displaced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mukhoty 1984&quot;&gt;{{Cite document |title=Who are the Guilty ? | last =Mukhoty | first =Gobinda | last2 =Kothari | first2 =Rajni |url=http://www.sacw.net/aii/WhoaretheGuilty.html |year=1984 |publisher=[[People's Union for Civil Liberties]] |ref=harv |postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| &lt;center&gt;1992-1993&lt;/center&gt;
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Bombay Riots]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Mumbai]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Demolition of Babri Masjid|Demolition]] of [[Babri Mosque|Babri Masjid]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !|  900 people dead
|-
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| &lt;center&gt;2002&lt;/center&gt;
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[2002 Gujarat violence|Gujarat Riots]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Gujarat]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Godhra train burning]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| Per the Gujarat government, 1,044 people were killed - 790 Muslims and 254 Hindus{{citation}}. Most independent groups report 2,000 - 5,000 killed in these riots, most of them Muslims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | chapter = OVERVIEW OF THE ATTACKS AGAINST MUSLIMS | title = &quot;We Have No Orders To Save You&quot; – State Participation and Complicity in Communal Violence in Gujarat | author = Smita Narula | publisher = Human Rights Watch |month=April | year=2002  | url = http://hrw.org/reports/2002/india/India0402-03.htm#P597_107979| accessdate= 4 February 2011 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}, {{cite news | title = Mob used bulldozer to raze heritage mosque | publisher = Indian Exress |date=13 March 2002 | url = http://www.indianexpress.com/india-news/ie20020314/top7.html| accessdate= 4 February 2011 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police records list 298 dargahs, 205 mosques, 17 temples and three churches as damaged in the months of March and April.&lt;ref name=&quot;TOI-28-Apr-2002&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title = More fall prey to police firings in Gujarat | author = Sanjay Pandey |work=Times of India |location=India |date=28 April 2002 | url = http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/8283550.cms| accessdate= 4 February 2011 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| &lt;center&gt;2008&lt;/center&gt;
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Religious violence in Orissa|Kandhamal riots]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Kandhamal district]], [[Orissa]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Murder of Swami Lakshmanananda]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| Over 20 killed and over 12,000 displaced
|-
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| &lt;center&gt;2012&lt;/center&gt;
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[2012 Assam violence]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| [[Assam]]
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| Murder of four former [[Bodo Liberation Tigers]] men in [[Kokrajhar]] by Bengali Muslim settlers{{Citation needed|{{subst:August 2012}}|date=August 2012}}
|! style=&quot;background:#fff; color:#000;&quot; !| 77 killed and over 17,000 displaced (as of 8 August 2012)
|}

==Notes==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|group=note}}

===Footnotes===
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
* {{cnote|α|The data exclude the Mao-Maram, Paomata, and Purul subdivisions of [[Manipur]]'s [[Senapati district]].}}
* {{cnote|β|The data are &quot;unadjusted&quot; (without excluding [[Assam]] and [[Jammu and Kashmir]]); the 1981 census was not conducted in Assam and the 1991 census was not conducted in Jammu and Kashmir.}}
* {{cnote|γ|Oberlies (1998, p. 155) gives an estimate of 1100 BCE for the youngest hymns in book ten. Estimates for a ''terminus post quem'' of the earliest hymns are far more uncertain. Oberlies (p. 158), based on &quot;cumulative evidence&quot;, sets a wide range of 1700–1100 BCE. The [[EIEC]] (s.v. [[Indo-Iranian languages]], p. 306) gives a range of 1500–1000 BCE. It is certain that the hymns post-date [[Proto-Indo-Iranian|Indo-Iranian]] separation of ca. 2000 BCE. It cannot be ruled out that archaic elements of the Rigveda go back to only a few generations after this time, but philological estimates tend to date the bulk of the text to the latter half of the second millennium.}}
* {{cnote|Δ|According to the most conservative estimates given by Symonds (1950, p. 74), half a million people perished and twelve million became homeless.}}
* {{cnote|ε|Statistic describes resident Indian nationals up to six years in age.}}
&lt;/div&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Charlton
 | given1=SEM
 | year=2004
 | title=Comparing Asian Politics: India, China, and Japan
 | publisher=Westview Press
 | isbn=0-8133-4204-X
 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=ipZ56S3boE8C
 | author1=Charlton, Sue Ellen M
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite document
 | surname1=Chatterjee
 | given1=S
 | surname2=Datta
 | given2= D
 | year=1984
 | title=An Introduction to Indian Philosophy
 | publisher=[[University of Calcutta]]
 | edition=8th
 | id=ASIN: B0007BFXK4
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Fowler
 | given1=JD
 | year=1997
 | title=Hinduism: Beliefs and Practices
 | publisher=Sussex Academic Press
 | isbn=1-898723-60-5
 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=RmGKHu20hA0C
 | author1=Fowler, Jeaneane D
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Goldman
 | given1=RP
 | year=2007
 | title=The Ramayana of Valmiki: An Epic of Ancient India
 | publisher=Princeton University Press
 | isbn=0-691-06663-9
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Heehs
 | given1=P
 | year=2002
 | title=Indian Religions: A Historical Reader of Spiritual Expression and Experience
 | publisher=New York University Press
 | location=New York
 | isbn=0-8147-3650-5
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Human Rights Watch
 | year=2006
 | title=Human Rights Watch World Report 2006
 | publisher=Seven Stories Press
 | isbn=1-58322-715-6
 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=eXmogaDhd20C
 | author1=Press, Seven Stories
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Ludden
 | given1=DE
 | year=1996
 | title=Contesting the Nation: Religion, Community, and the Politics of Democracy in India
 | publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press
 | isbn=0-8122-1585-0
 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=jEUdPqYQjhoC
 | author1=Ludden, David E
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Makkar
 | given1=SPS
 | year=1993
 | title=Law, Social Change and Communal Harmony
 | publisher=ABS Publications
 | isbn=81-7072-047-8
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite document
 | surname1=Oberlies
 | given1=T
 | year=1998
 | title=Die Religion des Rgveda
 | publisher=Wien
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Olson
 | given1=JS
 | surname2=Shadle
 | given2= R
 | year=1996
 | title=Historical Dictionary of the British Empire
 | publisher=Greenwood Press
 | isbn=0-313-29367-8
 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=-YwDfm1pFF8C
 | author1=Olson, James Stuart
 | author2=Shadle, Robert
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Radhakrishnan
 | given1=S
 | surname2=Moore
 | given2= CA
 | authorlink=Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan
 | year=1967
 | title=A Sourcebook in Indian Philosophy
 | publisher=Princeton University Press
 | isbn=0-691-01958-4
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Rinehart
 | given1=R
 | year=2004
 | title=Contemporary Hinduism: Ritual, Culture, and Practice
 | publisher=ABC-Clio
 | isbn=1-57607-905-8
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite book
 | last1=Shepard
 | given1=MA
 | title=Gandhi Today: A Report on Mahatma Gandhi's Successors
 | year=1987
 | publisher=Shepard Publications
 | isbn=0-938497-04-9
 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=DQyPbvLvK_sC
 | author1=Shepard, Mark
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
* {{Cite document
 | surname1=Symonds
 | given1=R
 | title=The Making of Pakistan
 | year=1950
 | publisher=[[Faber and Faber]]
 | ref=harv
 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
&lt;/div&gt;

== External links ==
;Religions  in India
* {{cite web |title=History of Religions in India |work=www.indohistory.com |url=http://www.indohistory.com/religions.html |accessdate=2008-01-01 }}

;Statistics
* {{cite web |title=Census of India 2001: Data on religion |work=Government of India (Office of the Registrar General) |url=http://www.censusindia.gov.in |accessdate=2007-05-28 }}

;Reports
* {{cite web |title=International Religious Freedom Report 2006: India |work=United States Department of State |url=http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2006/71440.htm |accessdate=2007-05-28 }}

{{Asia in topic|Religion in}}
{{Life in India}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Religion In India}}
[[Category:Religion in India| ]]

[[bn:ভারতের ধর্মবিশ্বাস]]
[[cs:Náboženství v Indii]]
[[da:Religion i Sydasien]]
[[es:Religión en la India]]
[[fr:Religions en Inde]]
[[hi:भारत में धर्म]]
[[ja:インドの宗教]]
[[pl:Religie w Indiach]]
[[pt:Religiões da Índia]]
[[ru:Религия в Индии]]
[[sk:Indické náboženstvá]]
[[sr:Религије Индије]]
[[sv:Lista över religioner i Indien efter delstat och befolkningsandel]]
[[ta:இந்தியாவிலுள்ள மதங்கள்]]
[[te:భారతదేశంలో మతం]]
[[zh:印度宗教]]</text>
      <sha1>0dh1ilzg4tuhnggs8pa5bzib4rosrvr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
