<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Religion in the United States</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>532793</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522113089</id>
      <parentid>522107479</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T03:09:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JDefauw</username>
        <id>15130401</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Belief in the existence of a god */ Clearer.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="87865">{{About|the current status of religion in the United States|information about the historical role of religion|History of religion in the United States}}
{{Culture of the United States}}

'''Religion in the United States''' is characterized by a diversity of religious beliefs and practices.  Various religious faiths have flourished, as well as perished, in the United States. Religions that span the country's [[multiculturalism|multicultural]] immigrant heritage, as well as those founded within the country, have led the United States to become one of the most religiously diverse countries in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= A New Religious America : the World's Most Religiously Diverse Nation|last=Eck |first=Diana |authorlink= |coauthors= |year= 2002|publisher= HarperOne|location= |isbn= 978-0-06-062159-9 |page=432 |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
A majority of Americans report that religion plays a &quot;very important&quot; role in their lives, a proportion unique among [[developed nation]]s.&lt;ref name=pewreligion&gt;{{cite web |title= U.S. Stands Alone in its Embrace of Religion |work= Pew Global Attitudes Project |url= http://pewglobal.org/reports/display.php?ReportID=167 |accessdate= 2007-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The majority of Americans (73%) identify themselves as Christians and about 20% have no religious affiliation.&lt;ref name=pew2012&gt;[http://www.pewforum.org/Unaffiliated/nones-on-the-rise.aspx The Pew Forum - “Nones” on the Rise]&lt;/ref&gt; According to the American Religious Identification Survey (ARIS), those who identify themselves as Catholics make up about 25% of the adult population, while &quot;other Christians&quot; account for another 51%.&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt;  The same survey says that other religions (including, for example, [[Judaism]], [[Buddhism]], [[Islam]], and [[Hinduism]]) collectively make up about 4% of the adult population, another 15% of the adult population claim no religious affiliation, and 5.2% said they did not know, or they refused to reply.&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt;  According to another survey, 36 percent of Americans state that they attend services nearly every week or more.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pewforum.org/Asian-Americans-A-Mosaic-of-Faiths-overview.aspx The Pew Forum on Religion &amp; Public Life - Asian Americans: A Mosaic of Faiths]&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite a high level of religious adherence, only 9% of Americans in a 2008 poll said religion was the most important thing in their life, compared with 45% who said family was paramount in their life and 17% who said money and career was paramount.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://02varvara.wordpress.com/2010/07/27/poll-shows-that-only-a-few-americans-consider-religious-faith-an-important-part-of-life/ |title=Poll Shows that Only a Few Americans Consider Religious Faith an Important Part of Life « Voices from Russia |publisher=02varvara.wordpress.com |date=2010-07-27 |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
From early colonial days, when some English and German settlers came in search of religious freedom, America has been profoundly influenced by religion.&lt;ref&gt;Sydney Ahlstrom, ''A Religious History of the American People'' (Yale UP, 2nd ed. 2004) ISBN 0-300-10012-4&lt;/ref&gt;  That influence continues in American culture, social life, and politics.&lt;ref&gt;Kevin M. Schultz, and Paul Harvey, &quot;Everywhere and Nowhere: Recent Trends in American Religious History and Historiography&quot;, ''Journal of the American Academy of Religion'', March 2010, Vol. 78 Issue 1, pp. 129–162&lt;/ref&gt; Several of the original [[Thirteen Colonies]] were established by settlers who wished to practice their own religion within a community of like-minded people: the Massachusetts Bay Colony was established by English [[Puritan]]s (Congregationalists), Pennsylvania by British [[Religious Society of Friends|Quakers]], Maryland by English [[Roman Catholicism in the United Kingdom|Catholics]], and Virginia by English [[Anglicans]].

The text of the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] to the country's [[United States Constitution|Constitution]] states that &quot;Congress shall make no law respecting an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the free exercise thereof; or abridging the freedom of speech, or of the press; or the right of the people peaceably to assemble, and to petition the Government for a redress of grievances.&quot; It guarantees the [[Free Exercise Clause of the First Amendment|free exercise]] of religion while also preventing the government from establishing a [[state religion]]. The [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] has also interpreted this as preventing the government from having any authority in religion.

==Freedom of religion==
Although some New England States continued to use tax money to fund local Congregational churches into the 1830s, the United States was the first nation to have no official state-endorsed religion.&lt;ref&gt;Feldman, Noah (2005). ''Divided by God''. Farrar, Straus and Giroux, pg. 10 (&quot;For the first time in recorded history, they designed a government with no established religion at all.&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;

Modeling the provisions concerning religion within the [[Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom]], the framers of the Constitution rejected any religious test for office, and the First Amendment specifically denied the federal government any power to enact any law respecting either an establishment of religion or prohibiting its free exercise, thus protecting any religious organization, institution, or denomination from government interference. The decision was mainly influenced by European Rationalist and Protestant ideals, but was also a consequence of the pragmatic concerns of minority religious groups and small states that did not want to be under the power or influence of a national religion that did not represent them.&lt;ref&gt;Marsden, George M. 1990. ''Religion and American Culture.'' Orlando: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, pp. 45–46.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Abrahamic religions==

===Baha'i Faith===
{{Main|Bahá'í Faith by country#United States}}
[[Image:Willmette how.jpg|thumb|[[Bahá'í House of Worship (Wilmette, Illinois)|Bahá'í House of Worship]], (built 1953) in Wilmette, Illinois is the oldest still existing Bahá'í House of Worship in the world and the only one in the United States.]]
The United States has perhaps the second largest Bahá'í community. It was established in 1894 by Ibrahim Kheiralla, a Syrian Bahá'í immigrant who later left the main group and founded a rival movement.&lt;ref&gt;Melton, ''Encyclopedia of American Religions'' (2003) pp. 992–995&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
{{Main|Christianity in the United States}}

The largest religion in the US is [[Christianity]], practiced by the majority of the population (76% in 2008&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt;). From those queried, roughly 51.3% of Americans are [[Protestants]], 23.9% are [[Catholicism|Catholics]], 1.7% are [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints membership statistics (United States)|Mormons]] (the name commonly used to refer to members of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]), and 1.7% have affiliations with various other [[Christian]] denominations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pew&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://religions.pewforum.org/pdf/affiliations-all-traditions.pdf |title= Religious Composition of the U.S. |publisher= Pew Forum on Religion &amp; Public Life |work= U.S. Religious Landscape Survey |year= 2007 |accessdate= 2010-11-29}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news |title= US religious identity is rapidly changing |url= http://www.boston.com/news/nation/articles/2008/02/26/us_religious_identity_is_rapidly_changing/ |work= The Boston Globe |first= Michael |last= Paulson |date= 2008-02-26}} Boston Globe&lt;/ref&gt; Christianity was introduced during the period of [[European colonization of the Americas|European colonization]].

According to the 2011 [[Yearbook of American and Canadian Churches]], from which members in the United States are combined with Canadian members, and of the [[National Council of Churches]], the five largest denominations are:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ncccusa.org/news/100204yearbook2010.html |title=News from the National Council of Churches |publisher=Ncccusa.org |date=2010-02-12 |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*The [[Catholic Church]], 68,503,456 members
*The [[Southern Baptist Convention]], 16,160,088 members
*The [[United Methodist Church]], 7,774,931 members
*[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]], 6,058,907 members
*The [[Church of God in Christ]], 5,499,875 members

[[File:Crys-ext.jpg|thumb|200px|left|[[Crystal Cathedral]], a former Protestant [[megachurch]] in [[California]] that suffered severe financial problems. The property has been sold to the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Orange]].]]

The Southern Baptist Convention, with over 16 million adherents, is the largest of more than 200&lt;ref name=&quot;Gaustad&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gaustad|1962}}.&lt;/ref&gt; distinctly named Protestant denominations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sbcec.net/bor/2007/2007SBCAnnual.pdf Annual of the 2007 Southern Baptist Convention]&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2007, members of [[Evangelicalism | Evangelical Churches]] comprise 26.3% of the American population, while another 18.1% belong to [[mainline Protestant]] churches, and 6.9% belong to historically [[black church]]es.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pew&quot;/&gt;

Due to its large population and history, the United States has numerically more Christians and Protestants than any other country in the world. Other countries, however, have [[Christianity by country|higher percentages of Christians]] and Protestants within their total populations.

Beginning in the 17th century, [[Northern European]] peoples introduced [[Protestantism]]. Among Protestants, [[Anglicanism|Anglicans]], [[Baptist]]s, [[Puritans]], [[Presbyterianism|Presbyterians]], [[Lutheranism|Lutherans]], [[Religious Society of Friends|Quaker]]s, and [[Moravian Church|Moravians]] were the first to settle in the US, spreading their faith in the new country.

[[File:Salt Lake Temple, Utah - Sept 2004-2.jpg|thumb|200px|The [[Salt Lake Temple]] in Salt Lake City, Utah]]

Beginning in the 16th century, the Spanish (and later the French and English) introduced Catholicism. From the 19th century to the present, Catholics came to the US in large numbers due to immigration of the [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanics/Latinos]], [[Irish Americans|Irish]], Highland Scots, [[Italian American|Italians]], Dutch, Flemish, [[Polish American|Polish]], [[French American|French]], [[Portuguese American|Portuguese]], [[Hungarian people|Hungarians]], [[German Americans|Germans]], [[Lebanese American|Lebanese]], and other ethnic groups. 

Greek, Ukrainian, Russian, Central and Eastern European, Middle Eastern, Ethiopian, and South Indian immigrants brought [[Eastern Orthodoxy]] and [[Oriental Orthodoxy]] to the United States. These branches of Christianity have since spread beyond the boundaries of ethnic immigrant communities and now include multi-ethnic membership and parishes.

Since the foundational settlements, American Christians have developed in their own paths. During the [[Great Awakening]]s interdenominational [[evangelicalism]] and [[Pentecostalism]] emerged, along with new Protestant denominations such as [[Adventism]], and non-denominational movements such as the [[Restoration Movement]] (which over time separated into the [[Churches of Christ]], the [[Christian churches and churches of Christ]], and the [[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)]]), the Watchtower Bible and Tract Society, commonly referred to as [[Jehovah's Witnesses]], and [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]], also commonly referred to as [[Mormonism]].

[[File:Basilica of the National Shrine of the Immaculate Conception.jpg|thumb|200px|left|The [[Basilica of the National Shrine of the Immaculate Conception]] in Washington, D.C., is the largest Catholic church in the United States.]]

The strength of various sects varies greatly in different regions of the country, with rural parts of the South (except [[Louisiana]] and the [[Gulf Coast]], and the [[Hispanic]] community, which both consist mainly of Catholics), having many evangelicals but very few Catholics, while urbanized areas of the north Atlantic states and [[Great Lakes]], as well as many industrial and mining towns, are heavily Catholic, though still quite mixed, especially due to the heavily Protestant African-American communities. As of 1990, nearly 72% of the population of Utah was Mormon, as well as 26% of neighboring Idaho.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web |url= http://www.adherents.com/largecom/com_lds.html |title= Largest Latter-day Saint Communities (Mormon/Church of Jesus Christ Statistics) |date= 2005-04-12 |publisher= adherents.com}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Lutheranism is most prominent in the [[Upper Midwest]], with North Dakota having the highest percentage of Lutherans (35% according to a 2001 survey.&lt;ref name=&quot;religious survey&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.gc.cuny.edu/faculty/research_briefs/aris/key_findings.htm |title= American Religious Identification Survey |work= Exhibit 15 |publisher= The Graduate Center, City University of New York |accessdate= 2006-11-24}}
&lt;/ref&gt;)

Despite its status as the most widespread and influential religion in the US, Christianity has undergone a continuous relative decline in demographics. While the absolute number of Christians rose from 1990 to 2008 as the overall population increased, the actual percentage of Christians dropped from 86.2% to 76.0%.&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt; A nationwide telephone interview of 1,002 adults conducted by [[The Barna Group]] found that 70% of American adults believe that God is &quot;the all-powerful, all-knowing creator of the universe who still rules it today&quot;, and that 9% of all American adults and 0.5% [[Mosaic Generation|young adults]] hold to what the survey defined as a &quot;biblical worldview&quot;.&lt;ref name='barna'&gt;
{{cite news |title= Barna Survey Examines Changes in Worldview Among Christians over the Past 13 Years |date= 2009-03-06 |publisher= [[The Barna Group]] |url= http://www.barna.org/barna-update/article/12-faithspirituality/252-barna-survey-examines-changes-in-worldview-among-christians-over-the-past-13-years |accessdate= 2009-06-26 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Islam===
{{Main|Islam in the United States}}
[[File:Islamic Center of Washington - 2551 Massachusetts Avenue NW.jpg|thumb|The [[Islamic Center of Washington]] in the nation's capital is a leading American Islamic Center.]]
American Islam effectively began with the arrival of African slaves. It  is estimated that about 10% of African slaves transported to the United  States were Muslim.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHC.islam&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://nationalhumanitiescenter.org/tserve/twenty/tkeyinfo/islam.htm |title= Islam in  America: From African Slaves to Malcolm X |first= Thomas  A. |last= Tweed |publisher= National Humanities Center |accessdate= 2009-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most, however, became Christians, and the United States did not have a significant Muslim population until the arrival of immigrants from Arabic and East Asian Muslim areas.&lt;ref&gt;Kambiz GhaneaBassiri, ''A History of Islam in America: From the New World to the New World Order'' (Cambridge University Press; 2010) pp. 59–94&lt;/ref&gt; Islam gained a higher profile through the [[Nation of Islam]], a religious group that appealed to black Americans after the 1940s; its prominent converts included [[Malcolm X]] and [[Muhammad Ali]].&lt;ref&gt;Mattias Gardell, ''In the Name of Elijah Muhammad: Louis Farrakhan and The Nation of Islam'' (Duke University Press, 1996)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;C. Eric Lincoln, ''The Black Muslims in America'' (3rd ed. Eerdmans, 1994)&lt;/ref&gt; The first Muslim elected in Congress was [[Keith Ellison (politician)|Keith Ellison]] in 2006,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2006/11/08/politics/main2163201.shtml First Muslim Elected to Congress] CBS News. Retrieved 2009-11-22.&lt;/ref&gt; followed by [[Andre Carson]] in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/domesticNews/idUSN1164415020080312 Second Muslim elected to Congress] Reuters. Retrieved 2009-11-22.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Islamic Center of America.png|left|thumb|200px|The [[Islamic Center of America]] in [[Dearborn, Michigan]] is the largest mosque in the United States]]
Research indicates that Muslims in the US are generally more assimilated and prosperous than Muslims in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.projectmaps.com/AMP2004report.pdf |title=Zogby phone survey |publisher=Projectmaps.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www1.voanews.com/english/news/a-13-Muslims2006-09-10-voa17.html |title= America's Muslims after 9/11 |publisher= Voice of America}}&lt;/ref&gt; Surveys also suggest, however, that they are less assimilated than other American subcultural and religious communities, especially after the 9/11 terrorist attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Muslim Americans&quot;&gt;[http://pewresearch.org/assets/pdf/muslim-americans.pdf Muslim Americans] Pew Research Center. Retrieved 2009-07-03.&lt;/ref&gt; Like other subcultural and religious communities, the Islamic community has generated its own political organizations and charity organizations.

===Judaism===
{{Main|American Jews}}
After Christianity, Judaism is the next largest religious affiliation in the US, though this identification is not necessarily indicative of religious beliefs or practices.&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt; A significant number of people identify themselves as [[American Jews]] on ethnic and cultural grounds, rather than religious ones. For example, 19% of self-identified American Jews believe God does not exist.&lt;ref name=Harris2003&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.harrisinteractive.com/harris_poll/index.asp?PID=408 |title=While Most Americans Believe in God, Only 36% Attend a Religious Service Once a Month or More Often |publisher=Harrisinteractive.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2001 ARIS study projected from its sample that there are about 5.3&amp;nbsp;million adults in the American Jewish population: 2.83&amp;nbsp;million adults (1.4% of the U.S. adult population) are estimated to be adherents of Judaism; 1.08&amp;nbsp;million are estimated to be adherents of no religion; and 1.36&amp;nbsp;million are estimated to be adherents of a religion other than Judaism.&lt;ref name=ARISJew &gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.gc.cuny.edu/faculty/research_briefs/aris/religion_identity.htm |title= RELIGION AND IDENTITY: HISPANICS &amp; JEWS |accessdate= 2008-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ARISKEY&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.gc.cuny.edu/faculty/research_briefs/aris/key_findings.htm |title= American Religious Identification Survey |accessdate= 2007-12-25}}&lt;br /&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.gc.cuny.edu/faculty/research_briefs/aris.pdf |title= American Identification Survey, 2001 |publisher= The Graduate Center of the City University of New York New York |date= 2001-12-19 |author= Kosmin, Mayer &amp; Keysar |format= PDF |accessdate= 2007-12-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; ARIS 2008 estimated about 2.68 million people (1.2%) in the country identify Judaism as their faith.&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt; 
[[Image:Touro external.png|thumb|[[Touro Synagogue]], (built 1759) in Newport, Rhode Island has the oldest still existing synagogue building in the United States.]]
Jews have been present in what is now the US since the 17th century, though large scale immigration did not take place until the 19th century, largely as a result of persecutions in parts of [[Eastern Europe]].  The Jewish community in the United States is composed predominantly of [[Ashkenazi Jews]] whose ancestors emigrated from [[Central Europe|Central]] and [[Eastern Europe]]. There are, however, small numbers of older (and some recently arrived) communities of [[Sephardi Jews]] with roots tracing back to 15th century [[Iberian Peninsula|Iberia]] (Spain, Portugal, and North Africa).  There are also [[Mizrahi Jews]] (from the Middle East, [[Caucasus|Caucasia]] and [[Central Asia]]), as well as much smaller numbers of [[Ethiopian Jews]], [[Indian Jews]], [[Kaifeng Jews]] and others from various smaller [[Jewish ethnic divisions]].  Approximately 25% of the Jewish American population lives in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Jewish Community Study of New York |publisher= United Jewish Appeal-Federation of New York |year= 2002 |url= http://www.ujafedny.org/atf/cf/%7BAD848866-09C4-482C-9277-51A5D9CD6246%7D/JCommStudyIntro.pdf |format= PDF |accessdate= 2008-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
According to a 2007 survey conducted by the Pew Forum on Religion and Public life, of the 1.7% of the U.S. adult population who are affiliated with the Jewish religion, 43% said they were Reform Jews, 31% said they were Conservative Jews, and 10% said they were Orthodox Jews.&lt;ref name=ciafact&gt;{{Cite web|title=CIA Fact Book |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/us.html |publisher= CIA World Fact Book |year= 2002 |accessdate= 2007-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pewstudy&quot;/&gt;  A 2009 study estimated the Jewish population (including both those who define themselves as Jewish by religion and those who define themselves as Jewish in cultural or ethnic terms) to be between 6.0 and 6.4 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.census.gov/compendia/statab/2011/tables/11s0077.pdf |url= http://www.jewishdatabank.org/Reports/Jewish_Population_in_the_United_States_2010.pdf |year= 2009 |author= Ira M. Sheskin and Arnold Dashefsky, University of Miami and University of Connecticut |title=Jewish Population of the United States, 2009 |publisher= Mandell L. Berman North American Jewish Data Bank in cooperation with the Association for the Social Scientific Study of Jewry and the Jewish Federations of North America}} The authors concluded the 6,543,820 figure was an over-count, due to people who live in more than one state during a year.&lt;/ref&gt; According to a study done in 2000 there were an estimated 6.14 million Jewish people in the country, about 2% of the population.&lt;ref name=ARDA2000/&gt; 

[[File:Congregation Shearith Israel 001.JPG|left|thumb|[[Congregation Shearith Israel]], (founded 1655) in New York is the oldest Jewish congregation in the United States.]]

According to the 2001 [[National Jewish Population Survey]], 4.3&amp;nbsp;million [[American Jewish]] adults have some sort of strong connection to the Jewish community, whether religious or cultural.&lt;ref name=NJPS&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.ujc.org/content_display.html?ArticleID=83784 |title= 2001 National Jewish Population Survey}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jewishness is generally considered an [[ethnic]] identity as well as a [[religious]] one. Among the 4.3&amp;nbsp;million American Jews described as &quot;strongly connected&quot; to Judaism, over 80% have some sort of active engagement with Judaism, ranging from attendance at daily prayer services on one end of the spectrum to attending [[Passover Seder]]s or lighting [[Hanukkah]] candles on the other. The survey also discovered that Jews in the [[Northeastern United States|Northeast]] and [[Midwest]] are generally more observant than Jews in the [[South]] or [[West]]. Reflecting a trend also observed among other religious groups, Jews in the Northwestern United States are typically the least observant.

Beginning in the 1960's, a worldwide movement among previously secular Jews, called ''[[Baal teshuva movement|baalei teshuva]]'' (&quot;returners&quot;, returning to a more religious, in most cases, Orthodox, style of observance) has had a noticeable presence in America.&lt;ref&gt;Lisa Aiken, The Baal Teshuva Survival Guide (Rossi Publications, 2009), pp. 1-3&lt;/ref&gt; It is uncertain how widespread or demographically important this movement is at present. &lt;!--- this is too uncertain to use | The U.S. has approximately the same number of people with Jewish heritage as does [[Israel]]. ---&gt;

Among  American Jews actively observing their faith, 33%  belong to  Orthodox synagogues, 32%  are affiliated with the Conservative tradition, 28% belong to Reform congregations, 3% are Reconstructionists, and 4% belong to some other tradition.{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}
{{clear}}

==Dharmic religions==

===Buddhism===
{{Main|Buddhism in the United States}}
[[File:Lightmatter Hsi Lai Temple 4.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Hsi Lai Temple]] (lit. Coming West Temple), a [[Buddhist]] [[monastery]] in Los Angeles, California]]

[[Buddhism]] entered the US during the 19th century with the arrival of the first immigrants from [[Eastern Asia]]. The first Buddhist temple was established in San Francisco in 1853 by [[Chinese Americans]].

During the late 19th century Buddhist missionaries from Japan came to the US. During the same time period, US intellectuals started to take interest in Buddhism.

[[File:Ballard Kadampa Buddhist Temple 01.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Tibetan Buddhism|Tibetan Buddhist]] temple in [[Seattle, Washington]]]]

The first prominent US citizen to publicly convert to [[Buddhism]] was [[Henry Steel Olcott]]. An event that contributed to the strengthening of Buddhism in the US was the [[Parliament of the World's Religions]] in 1893, which was attended by many Buddhist delegates sent from India, China, Japan,Vietnam, [[Thailand]] and [[Sri Lanka]].

The early 20th century was characterized by a continuation of tendencies that had their roots in the 19th century. The second half, by contrast, saw the emergence of new approaches, and the move of Buddhism into the mainstream and making itself a mass and social religious phenomenon.

Many foreign associations and teachers—such as [[Soka Gakkai]] and [[Tenzin Gyatso]] (the 14th [[Dalai Lama]] for [[Tibetan Buddhism]]{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}})—started to organize missionary activities, while US converts established the first Western-based Buddhist institutions, temples and worship groups.

Estimates of the number of Buddhists in the United States vary between 0.5%&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt; and 0.9%,&lt;ref name=ReligFreedom-UnivVirginia&gt;{{cite web |url= http://religiousfreedom.lib.virginia.edu/nationprofiles/United_States/rbodies.html |title= The Religious Freedom Page |publisher= University of Virginia Library}}&lt;/ref&gt; with 0.7% reported by both the CIA&lt;ref name=ciafact /&gt; and PEW.&lt;ref name=Pew /&gt;

===Hinduism===
{{Main|Hinduism in the United States}}
[[File:Malibu Hindu Temple 1.jpg|thumb|200px|Detail of [[Malibu Hindu Temple]] in [[California]]]]

The first time [[Hinduism]] entered the US is not clearly identifiable. However, large groups of Hindus have immigrated from India and other Asian countries since the enactment of the [[Immigration and Nationality Act of 1965]]. During the 1960s and 1970s Hinduism exercised fascination contributing to the development of [[New Age]] thought. During the same decades the [[International Society for Krishna Consciousness]] (a [[Vaishnavite]] [[Hindu reform]] organization) was founded in the US.

According to recent surveys, estimates for Hindus in the US suggest they number nearly 800 thousand people or about 0.4% of the total population.&lt;ref name=ARISKEY /&gt;&lt;ref name=pewstudy&gt;{{cite web |url= http://religions.pewforum.org/pdf/report-religious-landscape-study-full.pdf |title= Religious Composition of the U.S. |publisher= Pew Forum on Religion &amp; Public Life |work= U.S Religious Landscape Survey |date= February 2008 |accessdate= 2012-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- a lot of detail for a lede!!! How about: Non-Christian religions (in descending order: Judaism, Buddhism, Islam, Hinduism, and other) collectively make up about 5.5% of the adult population according to ARIS --&gt;

In 2004 the [[Hindu American Foundation]]—a national institution protecting rights the Hindu community of US—was founded.

===Jainism===
{{Main|Jainism in the United States}}
[[File:Jain Temple -02 by Jain Center of Greater Phoenix (JCGP).jpg|thumb|200px|[[Jain Center of Greater Phoenix]] (JCGP)]]

Adherents of [[Jainism]] first arrived in the United States in the 20th century. The most significant time of Jain immigration was in the early 1970s. The United States has since become a center of the Jain Diaspora. The [[Federation of Jain Associations in North America]] is an umbrella organization of local American and Canadian Jain congregations to preserve, practice, and promote [[Jainism]] and the Jain Way of Life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jaina.org/?page=AboutJAINA |accessdate=2012-01-16 |title=About JAINA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sikhism===
{{Main|Sikhism in the United States}}
[[Image:Gurdwara Sahib El Sobrante.jpg|thumb|[[Sikh Center of San Francisco Bay Area]], a Sikh gurdwara in El Sobrante, California.]]
Around 1900, the state of [[Punjab (British India)|Punjab]] of British India was hit hard by British practices of [[mercantilism]]. Some Sikhs emigrated to the United States to work on farms in California.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infinityfoundation.com/mandala/h_es/h_es_korit_histical.htm#Pioneers The Pioneers, America, &quot;A historical perspective of Americans of Asian Indian origin 1790-1997&quot;] October 31, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

The first Sikh [[Gurdwara]] in America was built in [[Stockton, California]] in 1912.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stocktongurdwarasahib.com/ Stockton Gurdwara, America, &quot;Stockton California&quot;] October 31, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==No religion==
{{Main|Irreligion in the United States}}
This group includes atheists, agnostics and people who describe their religion as “nothing in particular&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pewforum.org/Topics/Religious-Affiliation/Unaffiliated/ Unaffiliated - Pew Forum]&lt;/ref&gt;

“Unaffiliated” does not necessarily mean “non-religious.” Some people who are unaffiliated with any particular religion express religious beliefs (such as belief in God or reincarnation) and engage in religious practices (such as prayer or meditation).

===Agnosticism, atheism, deism and humanism===
A 2001 survey directed by Dr. Ariela Keysar for the City University of New York indicated that, amongst the more than 100 categories of response, &quot;no religious identification&quot; had the greatest increase in population in both absolute and percentage terms. This category included [[atheist]]s, [[agnostic]]s,  [[humanism|humanist]]s, and others with no theistic religious beliefs or practices. Figures are up from 14.3&amp;nbsp;million in 1990 to 34.2&amp;nbsp;million in 2008, representing a proportionate increase from 8% of the total in 1990 to 15% in 2008.&lt;ref name=ARIS2008/&gt; Another nation-wide study puts the figure of unaffiliated persons at 16.1%.&lt;ref name=pewstudy /&gt;

In the [[United States]], Enlightenment philosophy (which itself was heavily inspired by deist ideals) played a major role in creating the principle of religious freedom, expressed in Thomas Jefferson's letters and included in the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution]]. [[Founding Fathers of the United States|American Founding Fathers, or Framers of the Constitution]], who were especially noted for being influenced by such philosophy of deism include Thomas Jefferson, Benjamin Franklin, [[Cornelius Harnett]], [[Gouverneur Morris]], and [[Hugh Williamson]]. Their political speeches show distinct deistic influence. Other notable Founding Fathers may have been more directly deist. These include [[Thomas Paine]], [[James Madison]], possibly [[Alexander Hamilton]], and [[Ethan Allen]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.ethanallenhomestead.org/history/oracle.htm#excerpts
|title= Excerpts from Allen's ''Reason The Only Oracle Of Man''
|publisher=Ethan Allen Homestead Museum}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2006 nationwide poll, [[University of Minnesota]] researchers found that despite an increasing acceptance of religious diversity, [[atheists]] were generally distrusted by other Americans, who trusted them less than Muslims, recent immigrants and other minority groups in &quot;sharing their vision of American society&quot;. They also associated atheists with undesirable attributes such as criminal behavior, rampant materialism, and cultural elitism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.asanet.org/press/20060503.cfm |title= Atheists Are Distrusted |date= May 3, 2006 |accessdate= 2010-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://abcnews.go.com/Technology/story?id=1786422&amp;page=1 |title= Who's Counting: Distrusting Atheists |date= April 2, 2006 |accessdate= 2010-02-16 |first= John Allen |last= Paulos |publisher= ABC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the same study also reported that &quot;The researchers also found acceptance or rejection of atheists is related not only to personal religiosity, but also to one's exposure to diversity, education and political orientation--with more educated, East and West Coast Americans more accepting of atheists than their Midwestern counterparts.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;UMN News&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www1.umn.edu/news/news-releases/2006/UR_RELEASE_MIG_2816.html |title= Atheists identified as America's most distrusted minority, according to new U of M study |publisher= UMN News |accessdate= 2006-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some surveys have indicated that doubts about the existence of a god were growing quickly among Americans under 30.&lt;ref&gt;[http://religion.blogs.cnn.com/2012/06/12/pew-survey-doubt-of-god-growing-quickly-among-millennials/ Pew survey: Doubt of God growing quickly among millennials] retrieved 2012-06-13&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 March 2012, American Atheists sponsored the Reason Rally in Washington D.C.  This was followed by the American Atheist Convention at the Bethesda North Marriott and Convention Center in Bethesda, MD.  Organizers called the estimated crowd of 8,000-10,000 the largest-ever gathering of nonbelievers in one place.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/03/24/atheist-rally_n_1377443.html  Atheists Rally On National Mall] retrieved 2012-07-25&lt;/ref&gt;

====Belief in the existence of a god====
Various polls have been conducted to determine Americans' actual beliefs regarding a god:
* A 2006 CBS News Poll of 899 U.S. adults found that 76% of those surveyed believed in a god, while 9% believed in &quot;some other universal spirit or higher power&quot;, 8% believed in neither, and 1% were unsure.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}
* A 2007 [[Gallup Poll]] found that 86% of Americans believe in a god, with 8% saying they are not sure, and 6% saying they don't believe in a god.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gallup.com/poll/147887/americans-continue-believe-god.aspx More Than 9 in 10 Americans Continue to Believe in God] retrieved 2012-10-05&lt;/ref&gt;
*According to a 2008 ARIS survey, belief in god varies considerably by region. The lowest rate is in the West with 59% reporting a belief in God, and the highest rate in the South at 86%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.gallup.com/poll/109108/Belief-God-Far-Lower-Western-US.aspx |title= Belief in God Far Lower in Western U.S. |author= Newport, Frank |publisher= [[The Gallup Organization]] |date= 2008-07-28 |accessdate= 2010-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Mark Chaves, a Duke University professor of sociology, religion and divinity, found that 92% of Americans believed in God in 2008, but that significantly fewer Americans have great confidence in their religious leaders than a generation ago.&lt;ref&gt;[http://today.duke.edu/2011/08/chaves according to Mark Chaves]&lt;/ref&gt;
* A 2008 survey of 1,000 people concluded that, based on their stated beliefs rather than their religious identification, 69.5% of Americans believe in a personal God, roughly 12.3% of Americans are [[atheist]] or [[agnostic]], and another 12.1% are deistic (believing in a higher power/non-personal God, but no personal God).&lt;ref name= ARIS2008/&gt;
* A late 2009 online Harris poll of 2,303 U.S. adults (18 and older)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= What People Do and Do Not Believe in |date= 2009-12-15 |work= Harris Interactive |url= http://www.harrisinteractive.com/vault/Harris_Poll_2009_12_15.pdf |accessdate= 2011-05-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; found that &quot;82% of adult Americans believe in God&quot;, the same number as in two earlier polls in 2005 and 2007. Another 9% said they did not believe in God, and 9% said that they were not sure.  It further concluded, &quot;Large majorities also believe in miracles (76%), heaven (75%), that Jesus is God or the Son of God (73%), in angels (72%), the survival of the soul after death (71%), and in the resurrection of Jesus (70%). Less than half (45%) of adults believe in Darwin’s theory of evolution but this is more than the 40% who believe in creationism..... Many people consider themselves Christians without necessarily believing in some of the key beliefs of Christianity.  However, this is not true of born-again Christians. In addition to their religious beliefs, large minorities of adults, including many Christians, have &quot;pagan&quot; or pre-Christian beliefs such as a belief in ghosts, astrology, witches and reincarnation.... Because the sample is based on those who agreed to participate in the Harris Interactive panel, no estimates of theoretical sampling error can be calculated.&quot;
*A 2010 Gallup poll found 80% of Americans believe in a god, 12% believe in a universal spirit, 6% don't believe in either, 1% chose &quot;other&quot;, and 1% had no opinion. This is down only slightly from the 1940s, when Gallup first asked this question.
*A 2010 Gallup poll found 92% of Americans said yes to the question &quot;Do you believe in God?&quot;, while 7% said no and 1% had no opinion.
*A 2012 Pew Research Center survey found that doubts about the existence of a god have grown rapidly among younger Americans, with 68% telling Pew they never doubt God’s existence, a 15-point drop in just five years. In 2007, 83% of American millennials said they never doubted God’s existence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://religion.blogs.cnn.com/2012/06/12/pew-survey-doubt-of-god-growing-quickly-among-millennials/ Pew survey: Doubt of God growing quickly among millennials] retrieved 2012-06-13.  See also {{Cite web|url=http://religion.blogs.cnn.com/2012/06/12/pew-survey-doubt-of-god-growing-quickly-among-millennials/|author=Merica, Dan|title=Pew Survey: Doubt of God Growing Quickly among Millennials| publisher=CNN|date=2012-06-12|accessdate=2012-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*A 2012 WIN-Gallup International poll showed that 5% of Americans considered themselves &quot;convinced&quot; atheists, which was a fivefold increase from the last time the survey was taken in 2005, and 5% said they did not know or else did not respond.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wingia.com/web/files/richeditor/filemanager/Global_INDEX_of_Religiosity_and_Atheism_PR__6.pdf Religiosity and Atheism] retrieved 2012-10-05&lt;/ref&gt;

==Others==
Many other religions are represented in the United States, including [[Shinto]], [[Caodaism]], [[Thelema]], [[Santería]], [[Kemetism]], [[Roman polytheistic reconstructionism|Religio Romana]], [[Mesopotamian religion|Kaldanism]], [[Zoroastrianism]], [[Haitian Vodou|Vodou]], and many forms of [[New Age]] spirituality.

===Native American religions===
{{Main|Native American religion}}

[[Native American religion]]s historically exhibited much diversity, and are often characterized by [[animism]] or [[panentheism]].&lt;ref&gt;Utter, Jack. ''American Indians: Answers to Today’s Questions''. 2nd edition. University of Oklahoma Press, 2001. P. 145.&lt;/ref&gt; The membership of Native American religions in the 21st century comprises about 9000 people.&lt;ref&gt;Or about .003% of the U.S. population of 300 million. {{Cite book|author=James T. Richardson|title=Regulating Religion: Case Studies from Around the Globe|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=U6opyVE_IYkC&amp;pg=PA543|year=2004|publisher=Springer|page=543}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Neopaganism===
{{Main|Neopaganism}}
Neopaganism in the United States is represented by widely different [[List of Neopagan movements|movements and organizations]].  The largest Neopagan religion is [[Wicca]], followed by [[Neo-Druidism]].&lt;ref&gt;Introduction to Pagan Studies - Page 151, Barbara Jane Davy - 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Encyclopedia of Magic and Alchemy - Page 84, Rosemary Guiley - 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Other neopagan movements include [[Germanic Neopaganism]], [[Celtic Reconstructionist Paganism]], [[Hellenic Polytheistic Reconstructionism]], and [[Semitic Neopaganism]].

====Druidry====
According to the American Religious Identification Survey (ARIS), there are approximately 30,000 druids in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Trinity ARIS 2008; [http://prog.trincoll.edu/ISSSC/DataArchive/Access.asp Trinity ARIS 2001]&lt;/ref&gt; Modern Druidism came to North America first in the form of fraternal Druidic organizations in the nineteenth century and orders such as the Ancient Order of Druids in America were founded as distinct American groups as early as 1912. In 1963, the [[Reformed Druids of North America]] (RDNA) was founded by students at [[Carleton College]], [[Northfield, Minnesota]]. They adopted elements of Neopaganism into their practices, for instance celebrating the festivals of the [[Wheel of the Year]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Adl06|Adler 2006]]. pp. 337-339.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Wicca====
Wicca advanced in North America in the 1960s by [[Raymond Buckland]], an expatriate Briton who visited Gardner's Isle of Man coven to gain initiation.&lt;ref&gt;Scottish witchcraft: the history &amp; magick of the Picts - Page 246, Raymond Buckland - 1991&lt;/ref&gt; [[Universal Eclectic Wicca]] was popularized in 1969 a diverse membership drawing from both [[Dianic Wicca|Dianic]] and [[British Traditional Wicca|British Traditional]] Wiccan backgrounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Wyrmstar, Tamryn | title=Silver Chalice Ancestry | publisher=Tamryn's Abode http://www.angelfire.com/rant/ingwitch/sca.html | url=http://www.angelfire.com/rant/ingwitch/sca.html | accessdate=2008-10-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Thought Movement===
{{Main|New Thought}}
A group  of churches which started in the 1830s in the United States is known under the banner of &quot;[[New Thought]]&quot;. These churches share a [[Spirituality|spiritual]], [[metaphysics|metaphysical]] and [[mysticism|mystical]] predisposition and understanding  of the [[Bible]] and were strongly influenced by the [[Transcendentalist]] movement particularly the work of [[Ralph Waldo Emerson|Emerson]]. Another antecedent of this movement was [[Swedenborgianism]], founded on the writings of [[Emanuel Swedenborg]] in 1787.&lt;ref&gt;William James, [http://etext.virginia.edu/etcbin/toccer-new2?id=JamVari.sgm&amp;images=images/modeg&amp;data=/texts/english/modeng/parsed&amp;tag=parsed&amp;tag=public&amp;part=all &quot;The Varieties of Religious Experience&quot;]. pp. 92-93. New York 1929&lt;/ref&gt; The New Thought concept was named by [[Emma Curtis Hopkins]] (&quot;teacher of teachers&quot;) after Hopkins broke off from [[Mary Baker Eddy]]'s [[Church of Christ, Scientist]].  The movement had been previously known as the Mental Sciences or The Christian Sciences.

===Unitarian Universalism===
{{Main|Unitarian Universalism}}
Unitarian Universalists do not share a [[creed]]; rather, they are unified by their shared search for [[spiritual growth]] and by the understanding that an individual's theology is a result of that search and not obedience to an authoritarian requirement.&lt;ref&gt;(The 4th principle of Unitarian Universalism)[http://www.uua.org/visitors/6798.shtml UUA.org Seven principles]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Taoism===
In 2004 there were an estimated 56,000 [[Taoism|Taoists]] in the US.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adherents.com/rel_USA.html largest religious groups in the US] retrieved 9 October 2012&lt;/ref&gt; Taoism was popularied thoughout the world through Tai Chi Chuang, and includes the practise of martial arts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/taoism/ Taoism at a glance] retrieved 6 October 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

==Major denominations founded in the United States==
* [[Polish National Catholic Church]] – broke from Rome in 1897.
* [[Churches of Christ]]/[[Disciples of Christ]] – a restoration movement with no governing body. The [[Restoration Movement]] solidified as a historical phenomenon in 1832 when [[Restorationism (Christian primitivism)|restorationists]] from two major movements championed by [[Barton W. Stone]] and [[Alexander Campbell (clergyman)|Alexander Campbell]] merged.
* [[Pentecostalism]] – movement which emphasizes the role of the [[Holy Spirit]], finds its historic roots in the [[Azusa Street Revival]] in Los Angeles, California, from 1904 to 1906, sparked by Charles Parham.
* [[Adventism]] – began as an inter-denominational movement. Its most vocal leader was [[William Miller (preacher)|William Miller]], who in the 1830s in [[New York]] became convinced of an imminent [[Second Coming]] of Jesus. The most prominent modern group to emerge from this is the [[Seventh Day Adventists]].
* [[Nation of Islam]] – A sect of Islam, created and followed solely by [[African-Americans]]; redefined  &quot;Allah&quot; as someone &quot;who came in the person of W. D. Fard.&quot;
* [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church) – founded by [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]] in 1830 in the [[Burned Over District]] of upstate New York. Now headquartered in [[Salt Lake City, Utah]].
* [[New Thought|New Thought Movement]] - two of the early proponents of New Thought beliefs during the mid to late 19th century were [[Phineas Parkhurst Quimby]] and the Mother of New Thought [[Emma Curtis Hopkins]]
* [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] – originated with the religious movement known as [[Bible Student movement|Bible Students]], which was founded in Pennsylvania in the late 1870s by [[Charles Taze Russell]].  Loosely connected in its early years with Adventism, with which it shares some similarities.
* [[Scientology in the United States|Scientology]] – founded by [[L. Ron Hubbard]].
* [[Christian Science]] – founded by [[Mary Baker Eddy]].
* [[Reconstructionist Judaism]] – founded by [[Mordecai Kaplan]].
* [[Native American Church]] – founded by [[Quanah Parker]] beginning in the 1890s and incorporating in 1918.
* [[Church Of Satan]] - founded by [[Anton LaVey]] in San Francisco, California, 1966.
* [[Metropolitan Community Church]] – founded by [[Troy Perry]] in Los Angeles, California, 1968.
{{clear}}

==Government positions==
The First Amendment guarantees both the free practice of religion and the non-establishment of religion by the federal government (later court decisions have extended that prohibition to the states).&lt;ref&gt;Deisher, Beth and William Gibbs, eds., ''Coin World Almanac'', Sidney, Ohio: Amos Press, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. [[Pledge of Allegiance]] was modified in 1954 to add the phrase &quot;under God&quot;, in order to distinguish itself from the [[state atheism]] espoused by the [[Soviet Union]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Texas Review of Law and Politics&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |ssrn= 503622 |title= The Pledge of Allegiance and the Limited State |author= Thomas Berg |journal= Texas Review of Law and Politics, Vol. 8, Fall 2003 |quote= The inclusion of “under God” in the Pledge, the report says, “would serve to deny the atheistic and materialistic conceptions of communism with its attendant subservience of the individual.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott A. Merriman&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=l_8VFygyaDYC&amp;pg=PA110&amp;dq=under+God+Pledge+of+Allegiance#v=onepage&amp;q=under%20God%20Pledge%20of%20Allegiance&amp;f=false |title= Religion and the Law in America: An Encyclopedia of Personal Belief and Public Policy |author= Scott A. Merriman |publisher= [[ABC-CLIO]] |quote= The United States, wanting to distinguish itself from the USSR and its atheist positions, went to great extremes to demonstrate that God was still supreme in this country. |accessdate= 2007–10–18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Natalie Goldstein, Walton Brown-Foster&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=1p5qH3FydfgC&amp;pg=PA74&amp;dq=under+God+Pledge+of+Allegiance+state+atheism#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title= Religion and the State |author= Natalie Goldstein, Walton Brown-Foster |publisher= [[Infobase Publishing]] |quote= In the early 1950s, a Presbyterian minister in New York gave a sermon in which he railed against the U.S. Pledge of Allegiance because it contained no references to God. According to the reverend, the American pledge could serve just as well in the atheistic Soviet Union; there was nothing in the U.S. pledge to distinguish it from an oath to the godless communist state. So in 1954, Congress passed a law that inserted the phrase &quot;under God&quot; into the Pledge of Allegiance. |accessdate= 2007–10–18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ann W. Duncan, Steven L. Jones&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=5HnfIZSD2LEC&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=under+God+Pledge+of+Allegiance+state+atheism#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |title= Church-State Issues in America Today: Volume 2, Religion, Family, and Education |author= Ann W. Duncan, Steven L. Jones |publisher= Præger |quote= Including God in the nation's pledge would send a clear message to the world that unlike communist regimes that denied God's existence, the United States recognized a Supreme Being. Official acknowledgement of God would further distinguish freedom-loving Americans from their atheist adversaries. |accessdate= 2007–10–18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various [[President of the United States|American presidents]] have often stated the importance of religion. On February 20, 1955, President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] stated that &quot;Recognition of the Supreme Being is the first, the most basic, expression of Americanism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;John Micklethwait, Adrian Wooldridge&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url= http://books.google.com/books?id=QwtWtGw5B9kC&amp;pg=PT82&amp;dq=American+Legion+Back+to+God#v=onepage&amp;q=American%20Legion%20Back%20to%20God&amp;f=false |title= God Is Back: How the Global Revival of Faith Is Changing the World |author= [[John Micklethwait]], [[Adrian Wooldridge]] |publisher= [[Penguin Books]] |quote= &quot;Recognition of the Supreme Being is the first, the most basic, expression of Americanism,&quot; he decared in a speech launching the American Legion's &quot;Back to God&quot; campaign in 1955. &quot;Without God, there could be no American form of government, nor an American way of life.&quot; |accessdate= 2007–10–18}}&lt;/ref&gt; President [[Gerald Ford]] agreed with and repeated this statement in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;William J. Federer&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=n0ZvE-KPY40C&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=Recognition+of+Supreme+Being+Americanism+Gerald+Ford#v=onepage&amp;q=Recognition%20of%20Supreme%20Being%20Americanism%20Gerald%20Ford&amp;f=false |title= Back Fired |author= [[William J. Federer]] |publisher=Amerisearch |quote= In a National Day of Prayer Proclamation, December 5, 1974, President Gerald R. Ford, quoted President Dwight David Eisenhower's 1955 statement: Without God there could be no American form of government, nor an American way of life. Recognition of the Supreme Being is the first - the most basic - expression of Americanism. |accessdate= 2007–10–18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Statistics==
The U.S. Census does not ask about religion. Various groups have conducted surveys to determine approximate percentages of those affiliated with each religious group. Some surveys ask people to self-identify, while others calculate church memberships. The first table below represents the ranges that have been found.

* [[Christianity]]: (59.9%&lt;ref name=ARDA2000/&gt; to 78.4%&lt;ref name=pewforum /&gt;)
* [[Irreligion in the United States|Unaffiliated]], including [[atheist]] or [[agnostic]] (15.0%&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt; to 37.3%&lt;ref name=ARDA2000 /&gt;)
* [[Judaism]] (1.2%&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt; to 2.2%&lt;ref name=ARDA2000 /&gt;)
* [[Islam]] (0.6%&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Pew /&gt;&lt;ref name=ciafact /&gt;&lt;ref name=ARDA2000 /&gt;)
* [[Buddhism]] (0.5%&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt; to 0.9%&lt;ref name=ReligFreedom-UnivVirginia /&gt;)
* [[Hinduism]] (0.4%)
* Other (1.2% to 1.4%)

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; float:left; font-size:80%;&quot;
|+ style=&quot;font-size:100%&quot; | Religious affiliation in the U.S. (2007)&lt;ref name=pewforum&gt;
{{cite web |url=http://religions.pewforum.org/reports# |title=US Religious Landscape Survey | year=2008 | accessdate=2012-05-13}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Affiliation 
! colspan=&quot;2&quot;|% of U.S. population
|-
| [[Christianity|Christian]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|78.4||2||background:blue}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;|  Protestant
|align=right| '''{{bartable|51.3||2||background:lightblue}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:30px;&quot;| [[Evangelical Protestant]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|26.3||2||background:lightblue}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:30px;&quot;| [[Mainline Protestant]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|18.1||2||background:lightblue}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:30px;&quot;| [[Black church]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|6.9||2||background:lightblue}}
|- 
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Catholic]] 
|align=right| '''{{bartable|23.9||2||background:lightblue}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Mormon]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|1.7||2||background:lightblue}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Jehovah's Witnesses]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|0.7||2||background:lightblue}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Eastern Orthodox]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|0.6||2||background:lightblue}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| Other [[Christian]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|0.3||2||background:lightblue}}
|-
| [[Unaffiliated]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|16.1||2||background:purple}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| Nothing in particular
|align=right| '''{{bartable|12.1||2||background:#A020F0}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Agnosticism|Agnostic]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|2.4||2||background:#A020F0}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Atheism|Atheist]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|1.6||2||background:#A020F0}}
|-
|Non-Christian religions
|align=right| '''{{bartable|4.7||2||background:red}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Judaism]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|1.7||2||background:yellow}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Buddhism]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|0.7||2||background:red}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Islam]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|0.6||2||background:green}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| [[Hinduism]]
|align=right| '''{{bartable|0.4||2||background:red}}
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:15px;&quot;| Other 
|align=right| '''{{bartable|1.2||2||background:orange}}
|-
|Don't know/refused answer
|align=right| '''{{bartable|0.8||2||background:silver}}
|-
| '''Total''' || '''{{bartable|100||2||background:grey}}'''
|-
|}

===Attendance===
[[File:Church or synagogue attendance by state GFDL.svg|thumb|350px|Church or synagogue attendance by state. Data is unavailable for Alaska and Hawaii.]]
[[Gallup poll|Gallup International]] indicates that 41.6%&lt;ref name=Gallup2009/&gt; of American citizens report they regularly attend [[places of worship|religious services]], compared to 15% of [[Culture of France#Religion|French citizens]], 10% of [[Religion in the United Kingdom|UK citizens]],&lt;ref name=bbc20070403&gt;{{cite news |title= 'One in 10' attends church weekly |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/6520463.stm |publisher= BBC News |date= April 3, 2007 |accessdate= 2007-08-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and 7.5% of [[Religion in Australia|Australian citizens]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncls.org.au/default.aspx?docid=2250&amp;track=82083 NCLS releases latest estimates of church attendance], National Church Life Survey, Media release, February 28, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, an online Harris Poll (they stated that the magnitude of errors cannot be estimated due to [[sampling error]]s, [[Non-response bias|non-response]],etc.; 2,010 U.S. adults were surveyed)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.harrisinteractive.com/NEWS/allnewsbydate.asp?NewsID=1130 |title=Harris Interactive survey |publisher=Harrisinteractive.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; found that 26% of those surveyed attended religious services &quot;every week or more often&quot;, 9% went &quot;once or twice a month&quot;, 21% went &quot;a few times a year&quot;, 3% went &quot;once a year&quot;, 22% went &quot;less than once a year&quot;, and 18% never attend religious services.  

[[Church attendance]] varies considerably by state and region. In a 2009 Gallup survey, 41.6% of Americans said that they attended church or synagogue once a week or almost every week. The figures ranged from 63% in [[Mississippi]] to 23% in [[Vermont]].

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|+Weekly Church Attendance by State&lt;ref name=Gallup2009&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/125999/mississippians-go-church-most-vermonters-least.aspx |title=Mississippians Go to Church the Most; Vermonters, Least |publisher=Gallup.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Rank !! State !! Percent
|-
| — ||align=center| '''National average''' || 41.6%
|-
| 1 || {{flag|Mississippi}} || 63%
|-
| 2 || {{flag|Alabama}} || 58%
|-
| 3 || {{flag|Louisiana}} || 56%
|-
| 3 || {{flag|South Carolina}} || 56%
|-
| 3 || {{flag|Utah}} || 56%
|-
| 6 || {{flag|Tennessee}} || 54%
|-
| 7 || {{flag|Arkansas}} || 53%
|-
| 7 || {{flag|North Carolina}} || 53%
|-
| 9 || {{flag|Georgia (U.S. state)|name=Georgia}} || 51%
|-
| 10 || {{flag|Texas}} || 50%
|-
| 11 || {{flag|North Dakota}} || 49%
|-
| 11 || {{flag|Oklahoma}} || 49%
|-
| 13 || {{flag|Kentucky}} || 48%
|-
| 14 || {{flag|South Dakota}} || 47%
|-
| 15 || {{flag|Kansas}} || 46%
|-
| 16 || {{flag|Iowa}} || 45%
|-
| 16 || {{flag|Nebraska}} || 45%
|-
| 18 || {{flag|Indiana}} || 44%
|-
| 18 || {{flag|Minnesota}} || 44%
|-
| 18 || {{flag|Missouri}} || 44%
|-
| 18 || {{flag|Virginia}} || 44%
|-
| 22 || {{flag|New Mexico}} || 43%
|-
| 23 || {{flag|Illinois}} || 42%
|-
| 23 || {{flag|Pennsylvania}} || 42%
|-
| 23 || {{flag|West Virginia}} || 42%
|-
| 26 || {{flag|Idaho}} || 41%
|-
| 26 || {{flag|Ohio}} || 41%
|-
| 28 || {{flag|Florida}} || 40%
|-
| 28 || {{flag|Maryland}} || 40%
|-
| 28 || {{flag|Michigan}} || 40%
|-
| 28 || {{flag|Wisconsin}} || 40%
|-
| 32 || {{flag|Arizona}} || 39%
|-
| 33 || {{flag|Delaware}} || 38%
|-
| 33 || {{flag|New Jersey}} || 38%
|-
| 35 || {{flag|District of Columbia}} || 36%
|-
| 35 || {{flag|Montana}} || 36%
|-
| 37 || {{flag|California}} || 35%
|-
| 37 || {{flag|Colorado}} || 35%
|-
| 37 || {{flag|New York}} || 35%
|-
| 40 || {{flag|Wyoming}} || 34%
|-
| 41 || {{flag|Connecticut}} || 32%
|-
| 41 || {{flag|Rhode Island}} || 32%
|-
| 41 || {{flag|Washington}} || 32%
|-
| 44 || {{flag|Alaska}} || 31%
|-
| 44 || {{flag|Hawaii}} || 31%
|-
| 44 || {{flag|Oregon}} || 31%
|-
| 47 || {{flag|Nevada}} || 30%
|-
| 48 || {{flag|Massachusetts}} || 29%
|-
| 49 || {{flag|Maine}} || 27%
|-
| 50 || {{flag|New Hampshire}} || 26%
|-
| 51 || {{flag|Vermont}} || 23%
|}

==Religion and politics==
{{Main|Religion and politics in the United States}}
[[File:Civil marriage is a civil right.JPG|thumb|right|The U.S. guarantees [[freedom of religion]] and some churches in the U.S. take strong stances on political subjects.]]

In August 2010 67% of Americans said religion is losing influence, compared with 59% who said this in 2006. Majorities of white evangelical Protestants (79%), while mainline Protestants (67%), Black Protestants (56%), Catholics (71%), and the religiously unaffiliated (62%) all agree that religion is losing influence on American life; 53% of the total public says this is a bad thing while just 10% see it as a good thing.&lt;ref&gt;Pew Forum on Religion &amp; Public Life, &quot;Religion Losing Influence in America&quot;, [http://pewresearch.org/databank/dailynumber/?NumberID=1079 online]&lt;/ref&gt;

Politicians frequently discuss their religion when campaigning, and Fundamentalist and Black Protestants are highly politically active. However, to keep their status as tax-exempt organizations they must not officially endorse a candidate. Historically Catholics were heavily [[History of the Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] before the 1970s, while mainline Protestants comprised the core of the [[History of the Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]. Those patterns have faded away—Catholics, for example, now split about 50–50. However, white evangelicals since 1980 have made up a solidly Republican group that favors conservative candidates. Secular voters are increasingly Democratic.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://pewforum.org/docs/?DocID=174 |title=Religion and the 2006 Elections |publisher=Pew Forum |date=2006-12-01 |accessdate=2012-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Only three presidential candidates for major parties have been Catholics, all for the Democratic party:
* [[Alfred E. Smith]] in [[United States presidential election, 1928|presidential election of 1928]] was subjected to anti-Catholic rhetoric, which seriously hurt him in the Baptist areas of the South and Lutheran areas of the Midwest, but he did well in the Catholic urban strongholds of the Northeast.
* [[John F. Kennedy]] secured the Democratic presidential nomination in 1960. In the [[United States presidential election, 1960|1960 election]], Kennedy faced accusations that as a Roman Catholic President he would do as the Pope would tell him to do, a charge that Kennedy refuted in a famous address to Protestant ministers.
* [[John Kerry]] won the Democratic presidential nomination in 2004. In the [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004 election]] religion was hardly an issue, and most Catholics voted for his Protestant opponent.&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/5297138/ 2004 Exit poll]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Joe Biden]] is the first Catholic vice president.&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.npr.org/blogs/politicaljunkie/2009/01/the_first_catholic_vice_presid.html NPR report]&lt;/ref&gt;

The only Jewish major party candidate was [[Joe Lieberman]] in the [[Al Gore|Gore]]-Lieberman [[United States presidential election, 2000|campaign of 2000]] (although [[John Kerry]] and [[Barry Goldwater]] both had Jewish ancestry).

In 2006 [[Keith Ellison (politician)|Keith Ellison]] of Minnesota became the first Muslim elected to Congress; when [[Qur'an oath controversy of the 110th United States Congress|re-enacting his swearing-in for photos]], he used the copy of the [[Qur'an]] once owned by Thomas Jefferson.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Isikoff, &quot;I'm a Sunni Muslim&quot;, [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/16474497/site/newsweek/page/0/ ''Newsweek'' Jan. 4, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

A Gallup Poll released in 2007&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.gallup.com/poll/26611/Some-Americans-Reluctant-Vote-Mormon-72YearOld-Presidential-Candidates.aspx |title= Some Americans Reluctant to Vote for Mormon, 72-Year-Old Presidential Candidates. Strong support for black, women, Catholic candidates |publisher= Gallup News Service |author= Jeffrey M. Jones |accessdate= 2007-12-25 |date= 2007-02-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; indicated that 53% of Americans would refuse to vote for an [[atheist]] as president, up from 48% in 1987 and 1999. In fact, there is a single American congressman who is openly non-theistic, [[Pete Stark]].

The 2012 Republican presidential nominee [[Mitt Romney]] is [[Mormon]] and a member of the [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]. He is the former governor of the state of [[Massachusetts]] and his father [[George W. Romney|George Romney]] was the governor of the state of [[Michigan]]. The Romneys were involved in Mormonism in their states and in the state of [[Utah]].

{{See also|Religious affiliations of United States Presidents|Religious Affiliation in the United States Senate}}

==Membership reported by congregations==

===Christian  bodies===
The table below is based mainly on data  reported by individual denominations to the ''Yearbook of American and Canadian Churches,'' and published in 2011 by the National Council of Churches of Christ in USA. It only includes religious bodies reporting 60,000 or more members. The definition of a member is determined by each religious body.&lt;ref&gt;see [http://www.ncccusa.org/news/110210yearbook2011.html &quot;Trends continue in church membership growth or decline, reports 2011 Yearbook of American &amp; Canadian Churches&quot;], ''News from the National Council of Churches'' (Feb. 14, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Instructions for editing wikipedia tables: http://meta.wikipedia.org/wiki/MediaWiki_User%27s_Guide:_Using_tables --&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Religious body
! Year reported
! data-sort-type=&quot;number&quot; | Places of worship reported
! Membership (thousands)
! Number of ministers
|-
|[[African Methodist Episcopal Church]] || 1999 || &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;sm=n&lt;/span&gt;|| 2,500 || 7,741
|-
|[[African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church]] || 2002 || 3,226 || 1,431 || 3,252
|-
|[[American Baptist Association]] || 1998 || 1,760 || 275 || 1,740
|-
|[[American Baptist Churches USA]] || 1998 || 3,800 || 1,507 || 4,145
|-
|[[Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America]] || 1998 || 220 || 65 || 263
|-
|[[Armenian Apostolic Church]] || 1998 || 28 || 200 || 25
|-
|[[Assemblies of God]] || 2009 || 12,371 || 2,914 || 34,504
|-
|[[Baptist Bible Fellowship International]] || 1997 || 4,500 || 1,200 || -
|-
|[[Baptist General Conference]] || 1998 || 876 || 141 || -
|-
|[[Baptist Missionary Association of America]] || 1999 || 1,334 || 235 || 1,525
|-
|[[Christian and Missionary Alliance]], The || 1998 || 1,964 || 346 || 1,629
|-
|Christian Brethren ([[Plymouth Brethren]]) || 1997 || 1,150 || 100 || -
|-
|[[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)]] || 1997 || 3,818 || 879 || 3,419
|-
|[[Christian churches and churches of Christ]] || 1998 || 5,579 || 1,072 || 5,525
|-
|Christian Congregation, Inc., The || 1998 || 1,438 || 117 || 1,436
|-
|[[Christian Methodist Episcopal Church]] || 1983 || 2,340 || 719 || -
|-
|[[Christian Reformed Church in North America]] || 1998 || 733 || 199 || 655
|-
|[[Church of God in Christ]] || 1991 || 15,300 || 5,500 || 28,988
|-
|[[Church of God of Prophecy]] || 1997 || 1,908 || 77 || 2,000
|-
|[[Church of God (Anderson)|Church of God (Anderson, Indiana)]] || 1998 || 2,353 || 234 || 3034
|-
|[[Church of God (Cleveland, Tennessee)]] || 1995 || 6,060 || 753 || 3,121
|-
|[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (Mormons) || 2006 ||13,010 || 5,779 || 39,030
|-
|[[Church of the Brethren]] || 1997 || 1,095 || 141 || 827
|-
|[[Church of the Nazarene]] || 1998 || 5,101 || 627 || 4,598
|-
|[[Churches of Christ]] || 1999 || 15,000 || 1,500 || 14,500
|-
|[[Conservative Baptist Association of America]] || 1998 || 1,200 || 200 || -
|-
|[[Community of Christ]] || 1998 || 1,236 || 140 || 19,319
|-
|[[Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria|Coptic Orthodox Church]] || 2003 || 200 || 1,000 || 200
|-
|[[Cumberland Presbyterian Church]] || 1998 || 774 || 87 || 634
|-
|[[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal Church]] || 1996 || 7,390 || 2,365 || 8,131
|-
|[[Evangelical Covenant Church]], The || 1998 || 628 || 97 || 607
|-
|[[Evangelical Free Church of America]], The || 1995 || 1,224 || 243 || 1,936
|-
|[[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]] || 1998 || 10,862 || 5,178 || 9,646
|-
|[[Evangelical Presbyterian Church (United States)|Evangelical Presbyterian Church]] || 1998 || 187 || 61 || 262
|-
|[[Free Methodist Church]] of North America || 1998 || 990 || 73 || -
|-
|Full Gospel Fellowship || 1999 || 896 || 275 || 2,070
|-
|[[General Association of General Baptists]] || 1997 || 790 || 72 || 1,085
|-
|[[General Association of Regular Baptist Churches]] || 1998 || 1,415 || 102 || -
|-
|[[U.S. Conference of Mennonite Brethren Churches]] || 1996 || 368 || 82 || 590
|-
|Grace Gospel Fellowship || 1992 || 128 || 60 || 160
|-
|[[Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America]] || 1998 || 523 || 1,955 || 596
|-
|[[Independent Fundamental Churches of America]] || 1999 || 659 || 62 || -
|-
|[[International Church of the Foursquare Gospel]] || 1998 || 1,851 || 238 || 4,900
|-
|[[International Council of Community Churches]] || 1998 || 150 || 250 || 182
|-
|[[International Pentecostal Holiness Church]] || 1998 || 1,716 || 177 || 1,507
|-
|[[Jehovah's Witnesses]] || 2011 || 13,309 || 1,200 || -
|-
|[[Lutheran Church - Missouri Synod]], The || 1998 || 6,218 || 2,594 || 5,227
|-
|[[Mennonite Church USA]] || 2005 || 943 || 114 || -
|-
|[[National Association of Congregational Christian Churches]] || 1998 || 416 || 67 || 534
|-
|[[National Association of Free Will Baptists]] || 1998 || 2,297 || 210 || 2,800
|-
|[[National Baptist Convention of America, Inc.]] || 1987 || 2,500 || 3,500 || 8,000
|-
|[[National Baptist Convention, USA, Inc.]] || 1992 || 33,000 || 8,200 || 32,832
|-
|[[National Missionary Baptist Convention of America]] || 1992 || - || 2,500 || -
|-
|[[Old Order Amish]] Church || 1993 || 898 || 81 || 3,592
|-
|[[Orthodox Church in America]] || 1998 || 625 || 28 || 700
|-
|[[Pentecostal Assemblies of the World]], Inc. || 1998 || 1,750 || 1,500 || 4,500
|-
|[[Pentecostal Church of God]] || 1998 || 1,237 || 104 || -
|-
|[[Presbyterian Church in America]] || 1997 || 1,340 || 280 || 1,642
|-
|[[Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.)]] || 1998 || 11,260 || 3,575 || 9,390
|-
|[[Progressive National Baptist Convention]], Inc. || 1995 || 2,000 || 2,500 || -
|-
|[[Reformed Church in America]] || 1998 || 902 || 296 || 915
|-
|[[Religious Society of Friends]] (Conservative) || 1994 || 1,200 || 104 || -
|-
|[[Roman Catholic Church]] || 2002 || 19,484 || 66,404 || -
|-
|[[Orthodox Church in America Romanian Episcopate|Romanian Orthodox Episcopate]] || 1996 || 37 || 65 || 37
|-
|[[The Salvation Army|Salvation Army]], The || 1998 || 1,388 || 471 || 2,920
|-
|[[Serbian Orthodox Church]] || 1986 || 68 || 67 || 60
|-
|[[Seventh-day Adventist Church]] || 1998 || 4,405 || 840 || 2,454
|-
|[[Southern Baptist Convention]] || 1998 || 40,870 || 16,500 || 71,520
|-
|[[United Church of Christ]] || 1998 || 6,017 || 1,421 || 4,317
|-
|[[United Methodist Church]], The || 1998 || 36,170 || 8,400 || -
|-
|[[Wesleyan Church]], The || 1998 || 1,590 || 120 || 1,806
|-
|[[Wisconsin Evangelical Lutheran Synod]] || 1997 || 1,240 || 411 || 1,222
|}

===ARDA survey===
The [[Association of Religion Data Archives]] (ARDA) surveyed congregations for their memberships. Churches were asked for their membership numbers. Adjustments were made for those congregations that did not respond and for religious groups that reported only adult membership.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.thearda.com/mapsReports/rcms_notes.asp |title= ARDA Sources for Religious Congregations &amp; Membership Data |publisher= [[Association of Religion Data Archives|ARDA]] |year= 2000 |accessdate= 2010-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; ARDA estimates that most of the churches not responding were black Protestant congregations. Significant difference in results from other databases include the lower representation of adherents of 1&gt; all kinds (62.7%), 2&gt;Christians (59.9%) 3&gt;Protestants (less than 36%); and the greater number of unaffiliated (37.3%).

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right; font-size:85%&quot;
|+ align=top | Religious groups
|-
! align=left | Religious group !! number&lt;br /&gt;in year&lt;br /&gt;2000 !! % in&lt;br /&gt;year&lt;br /&gt;2000
|-
| align=left | Total US pop year 2000 || 281,421,839 || 100.0%
|-
| align=left | Evangelical Protestant || 39,994,852 || 14.2%
|-
| align=left | Mainline Protestant || 26,091,321 || 9.3%
|-
| align=left | Protestant (evangelical+mainline) || 66,086,173 || 23.5%
|-
| align=left | Catholic || 62,035,042 || 22.0%
|-
| align=left | Orthodox || 989,106 || 0.4%
|-
| align=left | adherents (unadjusted) || 141,364,420 || 50.2%
|-
| align=left | unclaimed || 140,057,419 || 49.8%
|-
| align=left | adjustment for non-responses (mostly black Protestant congregations) || 35,112,928 || 12.5%
|-
| align=left | total adherents (adjusted) || 176,477,348 || 62.7%
|-
| align=left | non-affiliated (unclaimed - adjustment) || 104,944,491 || 37.3%
|-
| align=left | other - including Mormon &amp; Christ Scientist|| 12,254,099 || 4.4%
|-
| align=left | The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints (Mormon, LDS) || 4,224,026 || 1.5%
|-
| align=left | other - excluding Mormon || 8,030,073 || 2.9%
|-
| align=left | Jewish estimate || 6,141,325 || 2.2%
|-
| align=left | Buddhist estimate || 2,000,000 || 0.7%
|-
| align=left | Muslim estimate || 1,559,294 || 0.6%
|-
| align=left | Hindu estimate || 1,110,000 || 0.4%
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| Source: [[Association of Religion Data Archives|ARDA]]&lt;ref name=ARDA2000&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.thearda.com/mapsReports/reports/US_2000.asp |title= The Association of Religion Data Archives (ARDA), Year 2000 Report |publisher= [[Association of Religion Data Archives|ARDA]] |year= 2000 |accessdate= 2011-06-04}}  Churches were asked for their membership numbers. ARDA estimates that most of the churches not reporting were black Protestant congregations.
&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==ARIS findings regarding self-identification==&lt;!---[[American Religious Identification Survey]] redirects here ---&gt;
[[File:Religions of the US.PNG|thumb|350px|Plurality of religious preference by state, 2001. Data is unavailable for [[Alaska]] and [[Hawaii]].]]
[[File:Religions by State.PNG|thumb|350px|Percentage of religion against average, 2001.]]
[[File:Religious Belief in USA-states.png|thumb|350px|Percentage of state populations that identify with a religion rather than &quot;no religion&quot;, 2001.]]
The United States government does not collect religious data in its census. The survey below, the American Religious Identification Survey (ARIS) 2008, was a random digit-dialed telephone [[statistical survey|survey]] of 54,461 American residential households in the [[contiguous United States]]. The 1990 sample size was 113,723; 2001 sample size was 50,281.

Adult respondents were asked the [[open-ended question]], &quot;What is your religion, if any?&quot; Interviewers did not prompt or offer a suggested list of potential answers. The religion of the spouse or partner was also asked. If the initial answer was &quot;Protestant&quot; or &quot;Christian&quot; further questions were asked to probe which particular denomination. About one third of the sample was asked more detailed demographic questions.

'''Religious Self-Identification of the U.S. Adult Population: 1990, 2001, 2008'''&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Figures are not adjusted for refusals to reply; investigators suspect refusals are possibly more representative of &quot;no religion&quot; than any other group.

{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;
|+ align=bottom | '''Source:ARIS 2008'''&lt;ref name=ARIS2008&gt;{{cite web |url= http://b27.cc.trincoll.edu/weblogs/AmericanReligionSurvey-ARIS/reports/ARIS_Report_2008.pdf |format= PDF |title= AMERICAN RELIGIOUS IDENTIFICATION SURVEY (ARIS) 2008 |author=Barry A. Kosmin and Ariela Keysar |year= 2009 |publisher= Trinity College |location= Hartford, Connecticut, USA |accessdate= 2009-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
! Group&lt;br /&gt; || 1990&lt;br /&gt;adults&lt;br /&gt;x 1,000&lt;br /&gt; || 2001&lt;br /&gt;adults&lt;br /&gt;x 1,000&lt;br /&gt; || 2008&lt;br /&gt;adults&lt;br /&gt;x 1,000&lt;br /&gt; || &lt;br /&gt;Numerical&lt;br /&gt;Change&lt;br /&gt;1990–&lt;br /&gt;2008&lt;br /&gt;as %&lt;br /&gt;of 1990&lt;br /&gt; || 1990&lt;br /&gt;% of&lt;br /&gt;adults&lt;br /&gt; || 2001&lt;br /&gt;% of &lt;br /&gt;adults&lt;br /&gt; || 2008&lt;br /&gt;% of&lt;br /&gt;adults&lt;br /&gt; || change&lt;br /&gt;in % of&lt;br /&gt;total&lt;br /&gt;adults&lt;br /&gt;1990–&lt;br /&gt;2008&lt;br /&gt;
|-
| align=left | Adult population, total || 175,440 || 207,983 || 228,182 || 30.1% || || || ||
|-
| align=left | Adult population, Responded || 171,409 || 196,683 || 216,367 || 26.2% || 97.7% || 94.6% || 94.8% || −2.9%
|-
! style=&quot;text-align:left&quot; | '''Total Christian''' || 151,225 || 159,514 || 173,402 || 14.7% || 86.2% || 76.7% || 76.0% || −10.2%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Catholic''' || 46,004 || 50,873 || 57,199 || 24.3% || 26.2% || 24.5% || 25.1% || −1.2%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:5px;&quot;| '''non-Catholic Christian''' || 105,221 || 108,641 || 116,203 || 10.4% || 60.0% || 52.2% || 50.9% || −9.0%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Baptist''' || 33,964 || 33,820 || 36,148 || 6.4% || 19.4% || 16.3% || 15.8% || −3.5%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Mainline Christian''' || 32,784 || 35,788 || 29,375 || −10.4% || 18.7% || 17.2% || 12.9% || −5.8%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Methodist'' || 14,174 || 14,039 || 11,366 || −19.8% || 8.1% || 6.8% || 5.0% || −3.1%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Lutheran'' || 9,110 || 9,580 || 8,674 || −4.8% || 5.2% || 4.6% || 3.8% || −1.4%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Presbyterian'' || 4,985 || 5,596 || 4,723 || −5.3% || 2.8% || 2.7% || 2.1% || −0.8%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Episcopal/Anglican'' || 3,043 || 3,451 || 2,405 || −21.0% || 1.7% || 1.7% || 1.1% || −0.7%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''United Church of Christ'' || 438 || 1,378 || 736 || 68.0% || 0.2% || 0.7% || 0.3% || 0.1%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Christian Generic''' || 25,980 || 22,546 || 32,441 || 24.9% || 14.8% || 10.8% || 14.2% || −0.6%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Christian Unspecified'' || 8,073 || 14,190 || 16,384 || 102.9% || 4.6% || 6.8% || 7.2% || 2.6%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Non-denominational Christian'' || 194 || 2,489 || 8,032 || 4040.2% || 0.1% || 1.2% || 3.5% || 3.4%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Protestant – Unspecified'' || 17,214 || 4,647 || 5,187 || −69.9% || 9.8% || 2.2% || 2.3% || −7.5%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Evangelical/Born Again'' || 546 || 1,088 || 2,154 || 294.5% || 0.3% || 0.5% || 0.9% || 0.6%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Pentecostal/Charismatic''' || 5,647 || 7,831 || 7,948 || 40.7% || 3.2% || 3.8% || 3.5% || 0.3%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Pentecostal – Unspecified'' || 3,116 || 4,407 || 5,416 || 73.8% || 1.8% || 2.1% || 2.4% || 0.6%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Assemblies of God'' || 617 || 1,105 || 810 || 31.3% || 0.4% || 0.5% || 0.4% || 0.0%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Church of God'' || 590 || 943 || 663 || 12.4% || 0.3% || 0.5% || 0.3% || 0.0%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Other Protestant Denominations''' || 4,630 || 5,949 || 7,131 || 54.0% || 2.6% || 2.9% || 3.1% || 0.5%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Churches of Christ'' || 1,769 || 2,593 || 1,921 || 8.6% || 1.0% || 1.2% || 0.8% || −0.2%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Jehovah's Witness'' || 1,381 || 1,331 || 1,914 || 38.6% || 0.8% || 0.6% || 0.8% || 0.1%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Seventh-Day Adventist'' || 668 || 724 || 938 || 40.4% || 0.4% || 0.3% || 0.4% || 0.0%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Mormon/Latter Day Saints''' || 2,487 || 2,697 || 3,158 || 27.0% || 1.4% || 1.3% || 1.4% || 0.0%
|-
! style=&quot;text-align:left&quot; | '''Total non-Christian religions''' || 5,853 || 7,740 || 8,796 || 50.3% || 3.3% || 3.7% || 3.9% || 0.5%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Jewish''' || 3,137 || 2,837 || 2,680 || −14.6% || 1.8% || 1.4% || 1.2% || −0.6% 
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Eastern Religions''' || 687 || 2,020 || 1,961 || 185.4% || 0.4% || 1.0% || 0.9% || 0.5%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:40px;&quot;| ''Buddhist'' || 404 || 1,082 || 1,189 || 194.3% || 0.2% || 0.5% || 0.5% || 0.3%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''Muslim''' || 527 || 1,104 || 1,349 || 156.0% || 0.3% || 0.5% || 0.6% || 0.3%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| '''New Religious Movements &amp; Others''' || 1,296 || 1,770 || 2,804 || 116.4% || 0.7% || 0.9% || 1.2% || 0.5%
|-
! style=&quot;text-align:left&quot; | '''None/ No religion, total''' || 14,331 || 29,481 || 34,169 || 138.4% || 8.2% || 14.2% || 15.0% || 6.8%
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:left; text-indent:20px;&quot;| ''Agnostic+Atheist'' || 1,186 || 1,893 || 3,606 || 204.0% || 0.7% || 0.9% || 1.6% || 0.9%
|-
! style=&quot;text-align:left&quot; | '''Did Not Know/ Refused to reply''' || 4,031 || 11,300 || 11,815 || 193.1% || 2.3% || 5.4% || 5.2% || 2.9%
|}

'''Highlights:'''&lt;ref name=ARIS2008 /&gt;
# The ARIS 2008 survey was carried out during February–November 2008 and collected answers from 54,461 respondents who were questioned in English or Spanish.
# The American population self-identifies as predominantly Christian but Americans are slowly becoming less Christian.
#* 86% of American adults identified as Christians in 1990 and 76% in 2008.
#* The historic Mainline churches and denominations have experienced the steepest declines while the non-denominational Christian identity has been trending upward particularly since 2001.
#* The challenge to Christianity in the U.S. does not come from other religions but rather from a rejection of all forms of organized religion.
# 34% of American adults considered themselves &quot;Born Again or Evangelical Christians&quot; in 2008.
# The U. S. population continues to show signs of becoming less religious, with one out of every seven Americans failing to indicate a religious identity in 2008.
#* The &quot;Nones&quot; (no stated religious preference, atheist, or agnostic) continue to grow, though at a much slower pace than in the 1990s, from 8.2% in 1990, to 14.1% in 2001, to 15.0% in 2008.
#* Asian Americans are substantially more likely to indicate no religious identity than other racial or ethnic groups.
# One sign of the lack of attachment of Americans to religion is that 27% do not expect a religious funeral at their death.
# Based on their stated beliefs rather than their religious identification in 2008, 70% of Americans believe in a personal God, roughly 12% of Americans are atheist (no God) or agnostic (unknowable or unsure), and another 12% are deistic (a higher power but no personal God).
# America's religious geography has been transformed since 1990. Religious switching along with Hispanic immigration has significantly changed the religious profile of some states and regions. Between 1990 and 2008, the Catholic population proportion of the New England states fell from 50% to 36% and in New York it fell from 44% to 37%, while it rose in California from 29% to 37% and in Texas from 23% to 32%.
# Overall the 1990–2008 ARIS time series shows that changes in religious self-identification in the first decade of the 21st century have been moderate in comparison to the 1990s, which was a period of significant shifts in the religious composition of the United States.

==Ethnicity==
The table below shows the religious affiliations among the [[ethnic]]ities in the United States, according to the [[Pew Forum]] 2007 survey.&lt;ref name=PewFoum&gt;[http://religions.pewforum.org/pdf/report-religious-landscape-study-full.pdf U.S.Religious Landscape Survey] Pew Forum (February 2008). Retrieved 2009-01-02.&lt;/ref&gt; People of [[African American|Black]] ethnicity were most likely to be part of a formal religion, with 85% percent being Christians. Protestant denominations make up the majority of the Christians in the ethnicities.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Religion
! White
! Black
! Asian
! Other/mixed
! Latino
|-
|'''Christian''' || '''78%''' || '''85%''' || '''45%''' || '''69%''' || '''84%'''
|-
|Protestant || 53% || 78% || 27% || 51% || 23%
|-
|Catholic || 22% || 5% || 17% || 14% || 58%
|-
|Mormon || 2% || &lt;0.5% || 1% || 2% || 1%
|-
|Jehovah's Witness || &lt;0.5% || 1% || &lt;0.5% || 1% || 1%
|-
|Orthodox || 1% || &lt;0.5% || &lt;0.5% || 1% || &lt;0.5%
|-
|Other || &lt;0.5% || &lt;0.5% || &lt;0.5% || 1% || &lt;0.5%
|-
|'''Other religions''' || 5% || 2% || 30% || 9% || 2%
|-
|Jewish || 2% || &lt;0.5% || &lt;0.5% || 1% || &lt;0.5%
|-
|Muslim || &lt;0.5% || 1% || 4% || 1% || &lt;0.5%
|-
|Buddhist || 1% || &lt;0.5% || 9% || 1% || &lt;0.5%
|-
|Hindu || &lt;0.5% || &lt;0.5% || 14% || 1% || &lt;0.5%
|-
|Other world religions || &lt;0.5% || &lt;0.5% || 2% || &lt;0.5% || &lt;0.5%
|-
|Other faiths || 1% || &lt;0.5% || 1% || 5% || &lt;0.5%
|-
|'''Unaffiliated''' (including atheist and agnostic)|| 16% || 12% || 23% || 20% || 14%
|}

==See also==
* [[Freedom of religion in the United States]]
* [[Fundamentalist Christianity]]
* [[Historical religious demographics of the United States]]
* [[Irreligion in the United States]]
* [[Religion in United States prisons]]
* [[Religious affiliations of United States Presidents]]
* [[Separation of church and state in the United States]]
* [[United States religious history]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
* {{cite book |last= Buck |first= Christopher |title= Religious myths and visions of America: how minority faiths redefined America's world role |publisher= Praeger Publishers |location= Westport, Connecticut |year= 2009 |isbn= 978-0-313-35959-0 |url= http://books.google.com/?id=E8Cd5sfApM4C }}.
* [[Miguel A. De La Torre|De La Torre, Miguel A.]], ''Encyclopedia on Hispanic American Religious Culture'' 2 vol, ABC-CLIO Publishers, 2009.
* {{Cite document |last= Gaustad |first= Edwin |authorlink= Edwin Gaustad |title= Historical atlas of religion in America |publisher= [[Harper &amp; Row]] |year= 1962 |ref= harv |postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt;}}.
* Gordon, Melton, J.  ''Encyclopedia of American Religions'' (7th ed. Thomson, 2003) 1408pp
* Hill, Samuel S., Charles H. Lippy, and Charles Reagan Wilson, eds. ''Encyclopedia of Religion in the South'' (2005)
* Lippy, Charles H., ed. ''Encyclopedia of the American Religious Experience'' (3 vol Scribners, 1988)
* National Council of the Churches of Christ. ''Yearbook of American Churches: 2010'' (2010)
* Putnam, Robert D.,  and David E Campbell ''American Grace: How Religion Divides and Unites Us'' (2010) [http://www.amazon.com/American-Grace-Religion-Divides-Unites/dp/1416566716/ excerpt and text search]
* Queen, Edward L. et al. eds, ''Encyclopedia of American Religious History'' (3rd ed. 3 vol, Facts on File, 2009)

==External links==
* [http://www.thearda.com Association of Religion Data Archives]
* [http://www.americanreligionsurvey-aris.org/ 2008 ARIS Survey]
* [http://www.cnn.com/2008/LIVING/wayoflife/02/25/religion.survey.ap/index.html?iref=mpstoryview CNN Article on 2008 Pew Results], 2/25/2008
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/09/11/AR2006091100459.html Religious Affiliation Underestimated in U.S., Study Shows]
* [http://www.valpo.edu/geomet/geo/courses/geo200/religion.html Map Gallery of Religion in the United States]
* http://www.adherents.com/rel_USA.html#religions
* U.S. Census [http://www.census.gov/prod/www/religion.htm links] and [http://www.census.gov/compendia/statab/cats/population/religion.html Statistical Abstract - ARIS Data - PDF &amp; XLS (Excel)]
* [http://lermanet.com/cisar/usa/040101.htm USA - Population statistics by religion]
* [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=7422542 Is America Too *** Religious?]—from [[NPR]].
* [http://ibcsr.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=120:none-of-the-above-the-non-religious-in-america&amp;catid=25:research-news&amp;Itemid=59 None of the above: the growth of the &quot;non-religious&quot;] - from IBCSR.
* [http://ibcsr.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=123:religious-not-spiritual&amp;catid=25:research-news&amp;Itemid=59 Religious, not spiritual] article on religiosity vs. spirituality in America.
*[[Charles Reagan Wilson]], [http://southernspaces.org/2004/overview-religion-and-us-south &quot;Overview: Religion and the U.S. South&quot;], ''Southern Spaces'', March 16, 2004.
*[http://www.usatoday.com/news/religion/2009-03-09-ARIS-faith-survey_N.htm USA Today Interactive Tables - Shifting Religious Identitites] and [http://www.usatoday.com/news/graphics/pew-religion-08/flash.htm Topography of faith]
*[http://www.religioustolerance.org/rel_rate.htm How many people go regularly to weekly religious services?] - From Religious Tolerance website.
*[http://connectakron.uakron.edu/bliss/research/archives/2004/Religious_Landscape_2004.pdf The American Religious Landscape and Political Attitudes: A Baseline for 2004.] 

{{Life in the United States}}
{{United States topics}}
{{North America topic|Religion in}}

&lt;!-- dummy edit --&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Religion In The United States}}
[[Category:Religion in the United States| ]]
[[Category:Religious demographics]]

[[es:Religión en los Estados Unidos]]
[[eo:Religio en Usono]]
[[fa:مذهب در ایالات متحده آمریکا]]
[[fo:Átrúnaður í USA]]
[[fr:Religion aux États-Unis]]
[[ko:미국의 종교]]
[[it:Religioni negli Stati Uniti d'America]]
[[ja:アメリカ合衆国の宗教]]
[[pt:Religião nos Estados Unidos]]
[[ru:Религия в США]]
[[fi:Uskonto Yhdysvalloissa]]
[[tr:ABD'de din]]
[[vi:Tôn giáo tại Hoa Kỳ]]
[[zh:美国宗教]]</text>
      <sha1>i9sgufgv39xfa4850j8wercnorb7lre</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
