<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Religious intolerance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>54944</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520680136</id>
      <parentid>520677905</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-31T01:29:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Moe Epsilon</username>
        <id>327589</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edit(s) by [[Special:Contributions/98.19.36.56|98.19.36.56]] using [[WP:STiki|STiki]],</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11183">{{Discrimination sidebar}}

:''This article is about intolerance'' '''by''' or '''between''' ''religious communities or by communities of specific practices.''
:''For intolerance'' '''of''' ''religion  itself, see [[Antireligion]], [[Irreligion]], and [[State atheism]]''.

'''Religious intolerance''' is [[Toleration|intolerance]] against another's religious beliefs or practices or lack thereof.

==Definition==
The mere statement on the part of a religion that its own beliefs and practices are correct and any contrary beliefs are incorrect in itself constitutes intolerance (i.e., ideological intolerance).{{fact|date=September 2012}} On the other hand, religious tolerance would mean that each person is free to chose his own faith and no other person would have a right to pass opinions on the faith of an other person. While Christianity may be the faith of A, Islam may be the faith of B. If A or B try to tell each other that the other is on the way to hell then that would be intolerance.
Religious intolerance, rather, is when a group (e.g., a society, religious group, non-religious group) specifically refuses to tolerate practices, persons or beliefs  on religious grounds (i.e., intolerance in practice).

==Historical Perspectives==
According to the 19th century British historian [[Arnold Toynbee]], for a religious establishment to persecute another religion for being &quot;wrong&quot; ironically puts the persecuting religion in the wrong, undermining its own legitimacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Toynbee|first=Arnold|title=A Study of History: Abridgment of Volumes I - VI|year=1947|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=New York, NY|isbn=0-19-505081-9|editor=Dorothea Grace Somervell|page=300|chapter=Failure of Self-Determination}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contemporary attitude and practice==
{{Weasel|date=June 2009}}
The [[constitution]]s of some countries contain provisions expressly forbidding the state from engaging in certain acts of religious intolerance or preference within its own borders; examples include The [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First Amendment]] of the [[United States]] [[United States Constitution|Constitution]] - (the exception being &quot;manifest destiny&quot; which was manufactured by the prevailing powers as well as the church, to suspend this &quot;right&quot; for all North American indigenous peoples, most notably during the 1800s and well into the 1900s. This is evidenced by the brutality of the infamous boarding schools designed to &quot;kill the Indian; save the man&quot; by erasing all manner of religious practice, language, culture, traditions, and beliefs). Article 4 of the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|Basic Law]] of [[Germany]], Article 44.2.1 of the [[Constitution of Ireland|Constitution]] of [[The Republic of Ireland]], Article 40 of the [[Estonia]]n Constitution,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/en00000_.html ''&quot;Estonia - Constitution&quot;''], ICL Document 28 June 1992, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Article 24 of the [[Constitution of Turkey|Constitution]] of [[Turkey]] and Article 36 of the [[Constitution of the People's Republic of China|Constitution]] of the [[People's Republic of China]], Article 3 Section 5 of the 1987 [[Constitution of the Philippines]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thecorpusjuris.com/laws/constitutions/8-philippineconstitutions/70-1987-constitution.html 1987 Constitution of the Republic of the Philippines], [http://thecorpusjuris.com CorpusJuris], retrieved 24 September 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 

Other states, whilst not containing constitutional provisions directly related to religion, nonetheless contain provisions forbidding discrimination on religious grounds (see, for example, Article 1 of the [[France|French]] [[Constitution of France|Constitution]], article 15 of the [[Canada|Canadian]] [[Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms|Charter of Rights and Freedoms]] and article 40 of the [[Constitution of Egypt|Constitution]] of [[Egypt]]). These constitutional provisions do not necessarily guarantee that all elements of the state remain free from religious intolerance at all times, and practice can vary widely from country to country. 

Other countries, meanwhile, may allow for religious preference, for instance through the establishment of one or more [[state religion]]s, but not for religious intolerance. [[Finland]], for example, has the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church of Finland]] and [[Finnish Orthodox Church]] as its official state religions, yet upholds the right of free expression of religion in article 11 of its [[Constitution of Finland|constitution]]. 

Some countries retain laws forbidding [[defamation]] of religious belief. Some retain laws forbidding all forms of [[blasphemy]] (e.g., [[Germany]] where, in 2006, [[Manfred van H.]] was convicted of blasphemy against [[Islam]]). This is seen by some as official endorsement of religious intolerance, amounting to the criminalization of religious views. The connection between intolerance and blasphemy laws is closest when the laws apply to only one religion. In [[Pakistan]] blasphemy directed against either the tenets of the [[Qur'an]] or the Prophet [[Mohammed]] is punishable by either life imprisonment or death. [[Apostasy]], the rejection of one's old religion, is also criminalized in a number of countries, notably [[Afghanistan]] with [[Abdul Rahman (convert)|Abdul Rahman]] being the first to face the [[Capital punishment|death penalty]] for converting to [[Christianity]].

The [[United Nations]] upholds the right to free expression of religious belief in articles and 18 and 19 of the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] while article 2 forbids [[discrimination]] on the basis of religion. Article 18 also allows for the freedom to change religion. The Declaration is not legally binding, however the [[United States]] chose in 1998 to pass the International Religious Freedom Act, creating the [[United States Commission on International Religious Freedom|Commission on International Religious Freedom]], and mandating that the United States government take action against any country found to violate the religious freedoms outlined in the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/laws/majorlaw/intlrel.htm &quot;International Religious Freedom Act of 1998&quot;], 27 January 1998, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[European Convention on Human Rights]], which is legally binding on all [[European Union]] states (following the passage of the [[Human Rights Act 1998]] in the [[United Kingdom]]), makes restricting the rights of an individual to practice or change their religion illegal in article 9, and discrimination on the basis of religion illegal in article 14. 

In its 2000 annual report on international religious freedom, the U.S. [[State Department]] cited [[China]], [[Myanmar]], [[Iran]], [[Iraq]] and [[Sudan]] for persecuting people for their religious faith and practices.  The report, which covers July 1999 through June 2000, details U.S. policy toward countries where religious freedom is violated in the view of the U.S. State Department.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uscirf.gov/mediaroom/press/2000.html &quot;United States Commission on International Freedom of Religion&quot;], Press Releases 2000, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[advocacy group]] [[Freedom House]] produced a report entitled &quot;Religious Freedom in the World&quot; in 2000 which ranked countries according to their religious freedom. The countries receiving a score of 7, indicating those where religious freedom was least respected, were [[Turkmenistan]], [[Iran]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Sudan]], [[Myanmar]] and [[North Korea]]. [[China]] was given a score of 6 overall, however [[Tibet]] was listed separately in the 7 category. Those countries receiving a score of 1, indicating the highest level of religious freedom, were [[Estonia]], [[Finland]], [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]], the [[Netherlands]], [[Norway]] and the [[United States]].

Within those countries that openly advocate religious tolerance there remain debates as to the limits of tolerance. Some individuals and religious groups, for example, retain beliefs or practices which involve acts contrary to established law, such as the use of [[Cannabis (drug)|cannabis]] by members of the [[Rastafari movement]], the religious use of [[eagle]] [[feathers]] by non-[[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] (contrary to the [[eagle feather law]], 50 CFR 22), or the practice of [[polygamy]] amongst [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|Mormons]] in the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;[http://scriptures.lds.org/en/od/1 &quot;Official Declaration&quot;], Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, 6 October 1890, retrieved 25 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The precise definition of &quot;religion&quot;, and to which groups it applies, can also cause controversy, for example the case of [[Scientologists]] who have all rights of religious freedom but complain that the highest court decided not to grant the status of a [[Non-profit organization]] in several states. Attempts to legislate against acts of religious intolerance amongst citizens frequently come up against issues regarding the [[freedom of speech]]; whilst in [[France]] being convicted of incitement to religious hatred can carry a maximum of 18 months in prison. An attempt to pass a similar law by [[Tony Blair]]'s [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour]] government in the [[United Kingdom]] had to be dropped in April, 2006 after criticism that it restricted free speech. In [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]], [[Australia]] the [[Racial and Religious Tolerance Act 2001]] makes illegal &quot;conduct that incites hatred against, serious contempt for, or revulsion or severe ridicule of, that other person or class of persons&quot; on the grounds of religious belief.{{citation needed|date=January 2012}}

==See also==
{{div col}}
*[[Antireligion]]
*[[Antitheism]]
*[[Demonization]]
*[[Fundamentalism]]
*[[Heterosexism]]
*[[Homophobia]]
*[[Religious controversies]]
*[[Religious discrimination]]
*[[Religious freedom]]
*[[Religious paranoia]]
*[[Religious tolerance]]
*[[Toleration]]
*[[Violence against LGBT people]]
{{div col end}}

'''Specific religions:'''
{{div col}}
*[[Anti-Catholicism]]
*[[Anti-cult movement]]
*[[Anti-Hinduism]]
*[[Anti-Judaism]]
*[[Anti-Mormonism]]
*[[Anti-Semitism]]
*[[Christianophobia]]
*[[Islamophobia]]
*[[Islamism]]
*[[Persecution of Baha'is]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

== Further reading ==
* Garth Blake, &quot;Promoting Religious Tolerance in a Multifaith Society: Religious Vilification Legislation in Australia and the UK.&quot; ''The Australian Law Journal'', 81 (2007): 386-405.

==External links==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/4075442.stm &quot;New Effort to Ban Religious Hate&quot;, BBC News, 11 June 2005] retrieved 25 May 2007

{{Religious persecution}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Segregation by type|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Religious Intolerance}}
[[Category:Religious discrimination]]
[[Category:Religious persecution]]
[[Category:Religion and society]]

[[ar:تعصب ديني]]
[[es:Intolerancia religiosa]]
[[it:Intolleranza religiosa]]
[[pl:Dyskryminacja religijna]]
[[pt:Intolerância religiosa]]
[[fi:Uskonnollinen syrjintä]]</text>
      <sha1>qgreo2efols1caqf57lf4kajzhaddps</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
