<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Religious persecution</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>175923</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522225726</id>
      <parentid>522222627</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T19:55:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Penbat</username>
        <id>1179151</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26305">{{POV|date=December 2011}}
{{Globalize|date=January 2010}}

{{Discrimination sidebar}}
'''Religious persecution''' is the systematic mistreatment of an individual or group of individuals as a response to their [[Religion|religious beliefs or affiliations]] or lack thereof.

The tendency of societies or groups within society to alienate or repress different subcultures is a recurrent theme in human history. Moreover, because a person's religion often determines to a significant extent his or her morality and personal identity, religious differences can be significant cultural factors.

Religious persecution may be triggered by religious bigotry (i.e. the denigration of practitioners' religions other than those of the oppressors) or by the State when it views a particular religious group as a threat to its interests or security. At a societal level, this [[dehumanization]] of a particular religious group may readily turn into violence or other forms of persecution. Indeed, in many countries, religious persecution has resulted in so much violence that it is considered a [[human rights]] problem.

==Forms==
Religious persecution can be considered the opposite of [[freedom of religion]]. Religious persecution may also affect [[Atheism|atheists]] in that they may be denounced as being [[amoral]] or be persecuted by the religious on the grounds that they are godless.

Often it is the alleged [[persecution]] of individuals within a group - in the attempt to maintain their religious identity, or the exercise of power by an individual or organization - that causes members of a religious group to suffer. Persecution in this case may refer to confiscation or destruction of property, incitement to hate, arrest, imprisonment, beatings, torture, and execution.

Denial of civil rights on the basis of religion is most often described as [[religious discrimination]], rather than religious persecution.

===Ethnicity===

Other acts of violence, such as [[war]], [[torture]], and [[ethnic cleansing]] not aimed at religion in particular, may nevertheless take on the qualities of religious persecution when one or more of the parties involved are characterized by religious homogeneity; an example being when conflicting populations that belong to different [[ethnic groups]] often also belong to different religions or denominations. The difference between religious and ethnic identity might sometimes be obscure (see: [[Ethnoreligious]]); cases of [[genocide]] of the 20th century cannot be explained in full by citing religious differences.&lt;ref&gt;Still, cases such as the [[Greek genocide]], the [[Armenian Genocide]], the [[Assyrian Genocide]] or the current [[Darfur conflict]] (see: [[Janjaweed]]){{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} are sometimes seen as religious persecution and blur the lines between ethnic and religious violence.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Nazi]] [[antisemitism]] provides another example of the contentious divide between ethnic and religious persecution, because [[Nazi propaganda]] tended to construct its image of Jews as race, and de-emphasized Jews as being defined by their religion. [[The Holocaust|The Shoah]] made no distinction between secular Jews, atheistic Jews, [[Orthodox Judaism|orthodox Jews]] and Jews that had converted to Christianity.

{{See also|Religion in Nazi Germany}}

==Cases==
The descriptive use of the term religious persecution is rather difficult. Religious persecution has taken place at least since the [[Classical antiquity|antiquity]], and has happened in different historical, geographical and social contexts. Until the 18th century, some groups were nearly universally persecuted for their views about religion, such as atheists,&lt;ref name=&quot;onfray&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Onfray|first=Michel|others=Leggatt, Jeremy (translator) |title=Atheist manifesto: the case against Christianity, Judaism, and Islam |publisher=Arcade Publishing|year=2007|page=|isbn=978-1-55970-820-3|url=http://books.google.com/?id=QpEAYMo7pFkC&amp;pg=PA24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jews&lt;ref name=Flannery /&gt; and zoroastrians.&lt;ref name=&quot;hj303&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last =Hinnells|first =John R.|title =Zoroastrians in Britain: the Ratanbai Katrak lectures, University of Oxford 1985|url=http://books.google.com/?id=E4l0J5bf3GYC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q=|pages=336|year=1996|edition=Illustrated|publisher =Oxford University Press|isbn =0-19-826193-4, 9780198261933|p=303}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early modern England===
One period of religious persecution which has been studied extensively is [[Early modern period|early modern]] England, since the rejection of religious persecution, now common in the [[Western world]], originated there. The English 'Call for Toleration' was the turning point in the [[Christian debate on persecution and toleration]], and early modern England stands out to the historians as a time in which literally &quot;hundreds of books and tracts were published either for or against religious toleration.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coffey00-14&quot;&gt;Coffey 2000: 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--This time has been debated thoroughly by historians, whereas, for the obvious reason of the over-abundance of material, historians generally avoid writing books on the whole of human history. reword?--&gt;

The most ambitious chronicle of that time is [[Wilbur Kitchener Jordan|W.K.Jordan]]'s [[Masterpiece|magnum opus]] ''The Development of Religious Toleration in England, 1558-1660'' (four volumes, published 1932-1940). Jordan wrote as the threat of [[fascism]] rose in Europe, and this work is seen as a defense of the fragile [[Value (personal and cultural)|values]] of [[humanism]] and [[Toleration|tolerance]].&lt;ref&gt;Coffey 2000, 2&lt;/ref&gt; More recent introductions to this period are ''Persecution and Toleration in Protestant England, 1558–1689'' (2000) by [[John Coffey]] and ''Charitable hatred. Tolerance and intolerance in England, 1500-1700'' (2006) by Alexandra Walsham. To understand why religious persecution has occurred, historians like Coffey &quot;pay close attention to what the persecutors said they were doing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Coffey00-14&quot;/&gt;

====Ecclesiastical dissent and civil tolerance====
No religion is free from internal dissent, although the degree of dissent that is tolerated within a particular religious organization can strongly vary. This degree of diversity tolerated within a particular church is described as ''ecclesiastical tolerance'',&lt;ref&gt;John Coffey (2000), p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; and is one form of [[religious toleration]]. However, when people nowadays speak of religious tolerance, they most often mean ''civil tolerance'', which refers to the degree of religious diversity that is tolerated within the state.

In the absence of civil toleration, someone who finds himself in disagreement with his congregation doesn't have the option to leave and chose a different faith - simply because there is only one recognized faith in the country (at least officially). In modern western [[Civil law (legal system)|civil law]] any citizen may join and leave a religious organization at will; In western societies, this is taken for granted, but actually, this legal [[separation of Church and State]] only started to emerge a few centuries ago.

In the [[Christian debate on persecution and toleration]], the notion of civil tolerance allowed Christian theologians to reconcile Jesus' commandment to [[Expounding of the Law#Love for enemies|love one's enemies]] with other parts of the [[New Testament]] that are rather strict regarding dissent within the church. Before that, theologians like [[Joseph Hall (bishop)|Joseph Hall]]&lt;!--or [[Thomas Thorowgood]] in protestant England--&gt; had reasoned from the ecclesiastical intolerance of the early Christian church in the New Testament to the civil intolerance of the Christian state.&lt;ref&gt;John Coffey (2000), p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Religious uniformity in early modern Europe=====
{{Main|Religious uniformity}}

By contrast to the notion of civil tolerance, in [[early modern Europe]] the subjects were required to attend the [[state church]]; This attitude can be described as ''territoriality'' or ''[[religious uniformity]]'', and its underlying assumption is brought to a point by a statement of the Anglican theologian [[Richard Hooker]]: &quot;There is not any man of the Church of England but the same man is also a member of the [English] commonwealth; nor any man a member of the commonwealth, which is not also of the Church of England.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''The Works of Richard Hooker'', II, p. 485; quoted after: John Coffey (2000), p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;

Before a vigorous debate about religious persecution took place in England (starting in the 1640s), for centuries in Europe, religion had been tied to territory. In England there had been several [[Act of Uniformity|Acts of Uniformity]]; in continental Europe the Latin phrase &quot;[[cuius regio, eius religio]]&quot; had been used. Persecution meant that the state was committed to secure religious uniformity by coercive measures, as eminently obvious in a statement of [[Roger L'Estrange]]: &quot;That which you call persecution, I translate Uniformity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;quoted after Coffey (2000), 27&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in the 17th century writers like [[John Locke]], [[Richard Overton]] and Roger William broke the link between territory and faith, which eventually resulted in a shift from territoriality to religious voluntarism.&lt;ref name=Coffey58&gt;Coffey 2000: 58.&lt;/ref&gt; It was Locke, who, in his [[A Letter Concerning Toleration|Letter Concerning Toleration]], defined the state in purely secular terms:&lt;ref name=Coffey57&gt;Coffey 2000: 57.&lt;/ref&gt; ''&quot;The commonwealth seems to me to be a society of men constituted only for the procuring, preserving, and advancing their own civil interests.&quot;''&lt;ref name=Locke89&gt;John Locke (1698): [[A Letter Concerning Toleration]]; [http://oregonstate.edu/instruct/phl302/texts/locke/locke2/locke-t/locke_toleration.html Online edition]&lt;/ref&gt; Concerning the church, he went on: ''&quot;A church, then, I take to be a voluntary society of men, joining themselves together of their own accord.&quot;''&lt;ref name=Locke89 /&gt; With this treatise, John Locke laid one of the most important intellectual foundations of the [[separation of church and state]], which ultimately led to the [[secular state]].

====Persecution for heresy and blasphemy====
{{Main|Heresy}}
{{Main|Blasphemy}}
{{See also|Christian heresy|Heresy in Orthodox Judaism}}

The persecution of beliefs that are deemed schismatic is one thing; the persecution of beliefs that are deemed heretic or blasphemous is another. Although a public disagreement on secondary matters might be serious enough, it has often only led to [[religious discrimination]]. A public renouncement of core elements of a religious doctrine under the same circumstances, on the other hand, would have put one far greater danger. While a [[dissenter]] from its official Church was only faced with fines and imprisonment in Protestant England, six people were executed for heresy or blasphemy during the reign of [[Elizabeth I of England|Elizabeth I]], and two more in 1612 under [[James I of England|James I]].&lt;ref name=&quot;John Coffey 2000, p. 26&quot;&gt;John Coffey (2000), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, heretical sects like Cathars, Waldensians and Lollards were brutally suppressed in western Europe, while, at the same time, Catholic Christians lived side-by-side with 'schismatic' Orthodox Christians after the [[East-West Schism]] in the borderland of eastern Europe.&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin j. Kaplan (2007), ''Divided by Faith, Religious Conflict and the Practice of Toleration in Early Modern Europe'', p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;

====Persecution for political reasons====
More than 300 Roman Catholics were put to death by English governments between 1535 and 1681 for treason, thus for secular than religious offenses.&lt;ref name=&quot;John Coffey 2000, p. 26&quot;/&gt; In 1570, [[Pope Pius V]] had issued the [[Papal bull|bull]] ''[[Regnans in Excelsis]]'', which absolved Catholics from their obligations to the government.&lt;ref&gt;Coffey 2000: 85.&lt;/ref&gt; This dramatically worsened the situation of the Catholics in England. English governments continued to fear [[Popish Plot]]. An English act of government from the year 1585 declared that the purpose of [[Jesuit]] missionaries who had come to Britain was &quot;to stir up and move sedition, rebellion and open hostility&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Coffey 2000: 86.&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently Jesuit priests like [[Saint John Ogilvie]] were hanged. This somehow contrasts with the image of the [[Elizabethan era]] as the time of [[William Shakespeare]], but compared to the antecedent [[Marian Persecutions]] there is an important difference to consider. [[Mary I of England|Mary I]] had been motivated by a religious zeal to purge heresy from her land, and during her short reign from 1553 to 1558 about 290 Protestants&lt;ref&gt;Coffey 2000: 81.&lt;/ref&gt; had been burned at the stake for heresy, whereas [[Elizabeth I of England]] &quot;acted out of fear for the security of her realm.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Coffey 2000: 92.&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Contemporary=====
Although his book was written before the [[September 11 attacks]], John Coffey explicitly compares the English fear of a [[Popish Plot]] with the contemporary [[Islamophobia]] in the [[Western world]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Like the extremist Islamic clerics who today provide inspiration for terrorist campaigns, the [Catholic] priests could not be treated like men who only sought the spiritual nourishment of the flock.&quot; Coffey 2000: 38&amp;39.&lt;/ref&gt; Among the Muslims imprisoned in the [[Guantanamo Bay detention camp]] there also were [[Mehdi Ghezali]] and [[Murat Kurnaz]] who could not have been found to have any connections with terrorism, but had traveled to [[Afghanistan]] and [[Pakistan]] because of their religious interests.

===Early persecution of and by monotheisms===
According to Jewish tradition, [[monotheism|monotheistic]] [[Judaism]] arose in [[Egypt]] under the direction of [[Moses]]. Among the [[Ten Commandments]] of that religion was one that forbade the worship of any other god than [[Yahweh]]; this led to conflict when [[Roman Empire|Imperial]] [[Rome]] extended its reach into the [[Middle East]].

Early [[Christianity]] also came into conflict with the Roman Empire, and may have been more threatening to the established polytheistic order than had been Judaism, because of the importance of [[evangelism]] in Christianity. Under [[Nero]], the Jewish exemption from the requirement to participate in public cults was lifted and Rome began to actively persecute monotheists.  This persecution ended in 313 C.E. with the [[Edict of Milan]], and Christianity was made the official religion of the empire in 380 C.E.. By the eighth century Christianity had attained a clear ascendancy across Europe and neighboring regions, and a period of consolidation began marked by the pursuit of [[heretics]], [[heathens]], [[Jews]], [[Muslims]], and various other religious groups.

{{See also|Historical persecution by Christians|Persecution of Ancient Greek religion|Persecution of Christians}}

===Persecutions of Jews===
{{Main|Persecution of Jews|Religious antisemitism}}
Major component of Jewish history, persecutions have been committed by Seleucids,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=452&amp;letter=S |title=Seleucidæ |publisher=JewishEncyclopedia.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; ancient Greeks,&lt;ref name=Flannery&gt;Flannery, Edward H. ''The Anguish of the Jews: Twenty-Three Centuries of Antisemitism''. Paulist Press, first published in 1985; this edition 2004, pp. 11–2. ISBN 0-8091-2702-4. [[Edward Flannery]]&lt;/ref&gt; Christians (Catholics, Protestants and Orthodox), Muslims, Nazis, etc. Some of the most important events constituting this history include the [[1066 Granada massacre]], the [[Persecution of Jews in the First Crusade]] (by Catholics but against papal orders, see also : [[Sicut Judaeis]]), the [[Alhambra Decree]] after the [[Reconquista]] and the creation of the [[Spanish Inquisition]], the publication of [[On the Jews and Their Lies]] by [[Martin Luther]] which initiated the Protestant antisemitism and strengthened German antisemitism, the [[pogrom]]s and [[the Holocaust]].

===Persecutions of atheists===
{{Main|Discrimination against atheists}}
Used before the 18th century as an insult,&lt;ref name=&quot;laursen&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Laursen|first=John Christian |coauthors=Nederman, Cary J.|title=Beyond the Persecuting Society: Religious Toleration Before the Enlightenment  |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|year=1997|page=142|isbn= 978-0-8122-1567-0|url=http://books.google.com/?id=r2j6ZHgXZWkC&amp;pg=PA142}}&lt;/ref&gt; atheism was punishable by death in ancient Greece, in ancient Israel,&lt;ref&gt;Deuteronomy 13:6-11&lt;/ref&gt; in Christian countries during the Middle Ages and in Muslim countries. Today, Atheism is a crime in Iran, Saudi Arabia, Indonesia,&lt;ref name=&quot;Jakarta Globe&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = ‘God Does Not Exist’ Comment Ends Badly for Indonesia Man | url = http://www.thejakartaglobe.com/news/god-does-not-exist-comment-ends-badly-for-indonesia-man/492370 | accessdate = 2012-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan and some other Muslim countries.

===Persecution of minorities in Islamic lands===
Victims of Muslim persecution include [[Persecution_of_Jews#Muslim_and_Arab_antisemitism|Jews]], [[Persecution of Christians#Muslim world|Christians]], [[Persecution_of_Zoroastrians|Zoroastrians]], [[Persecution_of_Hindus#During_Islamic_rule_of_the_Indian_sub-continent|Hindus]], [[Persecution_of_Buddhists#Persecution_by_Muslims|Buddhists]], [[Persecution of Bahá'ís|Bahá'ís]], and [[Persecution_of_Atheists#Islamic_countries|Atheists]] with detailed description in articles according to victim classification. Muslim persecution of fellow Muslims include as victims [[Persecution of Shia Muslims|Shia]], [[Sufism#Persecution|Sufi]], and [[Ottoman persecution of Alevis|Alevis]].

===State atheism===
{{Main|State atheism}}

State atheism has been defined by David Kowalewski as the official &quot;promotion of [[atheism]]&quot; by a [[government]], typically by active suppression of [[religious freedom]] and practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kowalewski1980&quot;&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/128810 Protest for Religious Rights in the USSR: Characteristics and Consequences], David Kowalewski, ''Russian Review'', Vol. 39, No. 4 (Oct., 1980), pp. 426–441, Blackwell Publishing on behalf of The Editors and Board of Trustees of the Russian Review&lt;/ref&gt;  It is a [[misnomer]] referring to a government's [[anti-clericalism]], which opposes religious institutional power and influence, real or alleged, in all aspects of public and political life, including the involvement of religion in the everyday life of the citizen.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopædia Britannica, ''Anticlericalism'' (2007 Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.)&lt;/ref&gt;

State atheism was first practised during a brief period in [[Revolutionary France]] and repeated only in [[Mexican Revolution|Revolutionary Mexico]] and some [[communist states]].  The Soviet Union had a long history of state atheism,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Greeley2003|Greeley (2003)]].&lt;/ref&gt; in which social success largely required individuals to profess atheism, stay away from churches and even vandalize them; this attitude was especially militant during the middle Stalinist era from 1929-1939.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Pospielovsky1998|Pospielovsky (1998)]]:257.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Miner2003|Miner (2003)]]:70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Davies1996|Davies (1996)]]:962.&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union attempted to suppress religion over wide areas of its influence, including places like central Asia,&lt;ref&gt;[[#Pipes1989|Pipes (1989)]]:55.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Socialist People's Republic of Albania]] under [[Enver Hoxha]] went so far as to officially ban all religious practices.&lt;ref name=&quot;Elsie 2000:18&quot;&gt;[[#Elsie2000|Elsie (2000)]]:18.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bahá'ís in Iran===
{{Main|Persecution of Bahá'ís}}

The [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'ís]] are Iran's largest religious minority, and Iran is the location of one of the largest Bahá'í populations in the world. Bahá'ís in Iran have allegedly been subject to unwarranted arrests, false imprisonment, beatings, torture, unjustified executions, confiscation and destruction of property owned by individuals and the Bahá'í community, denial of employment, denial of government benefits, denial of civil rights and liberties, and denial of access to higher education.

More recently, in the later months of 2005, an intensive anti-Bahá'í campaign was conducted by Iranian newspapers and radio stations. The state-run and influential [[Kayhan]] newspaper, whose [[managing editor]] is appointed by Iran's supreme leader, [[Ali Khamenei|Ayatollah Khamenei]] [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4308203.stm], ran nearly three dozen articles defaming the Bahá'í Faith. Furthermore, a confidential letter sent on October 29, 2005 by the Chairman of the Command Headquarters of the Armed Forced in Iran states that the Supreme Leader of Iran, [[Ali Khamenei|Ayatollah Khamenei]] has instructed the Command Headquarters to identify people who adhere to the Bahá'í Faith and to monitor their activities and gather any and all information about the members of the Bahá'í Faith. The letter was brought to the attention of the international community by Asma Jahangir, the [[Special Rapporteur (UN)|Special Rapporteur]] of the [[United Nations Commission on Human Rights]] on freedom of religion or belief, in a March 20, 2006 press release [http://www.unhchr.ch/huricane/huricane.nsf/view01/5E72D6B7B624AABBC125713700572D09?opendocument].

In the press release the Special Rapporteur states that she &quot;is highly concerned by information she has received concerning the treatment of members of the Bahá'í community in Iran.&quot; She further states that &quot;The Special Rapporteur is concerned that this latest development indicates that the situation with regard to religious minorities in Iran is, in fact, deteriorating.&quot;
[http://www.unhchr.ch/huricane/huricane.nsf/view01/5E72D6B7B624AABBC125713700572D09?opendocument].

===Persecution of the Serers===
{{main|Serer religion|Serer history (medieval era to present)|The Battle of Fandane-Thiouthioune}}
{{Quote box
|width     = 30em
|border    = 1px
|align     = right
|bgcolor   = #F6F0E5
|fontsize  = 90%
|title_bg  = 
|title_fnt = 
|title     = 
|quote     = &quot;Today, the Serer retain much of their old culture, customs and traditions. In fact, it's not uncommon to hear how Serer culture has survived through the centuries in spite of all the forces which tried to destroy it.&quot;
|salign    = left
|source    = [[Godfrey Mwakikagile]],&lt;ref name=&quot; Mwakikagile &quot;&gt;[[Godfrey Mwakikagile|Mwakikagile, Godfrey]], &quot;Ethnic Diversity and Integration in The Gambia: The Land, The People and The Culture,&quot; (2010), p 241, ISBN 9987-9322-2-3&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
Persecution of the [[Serer people]] of [[Senegal]], the [[Gambia]] and [[Mauritania]] is multifaceted, and include both religious and ethnic elements. Religious and ethnic persecution of the Serer people dates back to the 11th century when [[War Jabi|King War Jabi]] usurped the throne of [[Tekrur]] (part of present-day Senegal) in 1030, and by 1035, introduced [[Sharia law]] and forced his subjects to submit to [[Islam]].&lt;ref&gt;Clark, Andrew F., &amp; Phillips, Lucie Colvin, &quot;Historical Dictionary of Senegal&quot;. ed: 2, Metuchen, New Jersey : Scrarecrow Press (1994) p 265&lt;/ref&gt; With the assistance of his son (Leb), their [[Almoravid]] allies and other [[Ethnic groups in Senegal|African ethnic groups who have embraced Islam]], the Muslim coalition army launched [[jihad]]s against the Serer people of Tekrur who refused to abandon [[Serer religion]] in favour of Islam.&lt;ref&gt;Page, Willie F., &quot;Encyclopedia of African history and culture: African kingdoms (500 to 1500)&quot;, pp 209, 676. Vol.2, Facts on File (2001), ISBN 0-8160-4472-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Streissguth, Thomas, &quot;Senegal in Pictures, Visual Geography&quot;, Second Series, p 23, Twenty-First Century Books (2009), ISBN 1-57505-951-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Oliver, Roland Anthony, Fage, J. D., &quot;Journal of African history&quot;, Volume 10, p 367. Cambridge University Press (1969)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Godfrey&quot;&gt;Mwakikagile, Godfrey, &quot;Ethnic Diversity and Integration in The Gambia: The Land, The People and The Culture,&quot; (2010), p 11, ISBN 9987-9322-2-3&lt;/ref&gt;  The number of Serer deaths are unknown, but it triggered the exodus of the Serers of Tekrur to the south following their defeat, where they were granted asylum by the [[Lamane#The Great Council of Lamanes|Serer Lamanic Class]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Godfrey&quot;/&gt; Persecution of the Serer people continued from the [[medieval era]] to the 19th century, resulting in [[the Battle of Fandane-Thiouthioune]]. From the 20th to the 21st centuries, persecution of the Serers is less obvious, nevertheless they are the object of scorn and prejudice.&lt;ref&gt;Abbey, M T Rosalie Akouele, &quot;Customary Law and Slavery in West Africa&quot;, Trafford Publishing (2011), pp 481-482, ISBN 1-4269-7117-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mwakikagile&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Christian privilege]]
*[[Human rights abuses]]
*[[Persecution]]
*[[Religious abuse]]
*[[Religious cleansing]]
*[[Religious intolerance]]
*[[Religious police]]
*[[Religion and violence]]
*[[Spiritual abuse]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*John Coffey (2000), ''Persecution and Toleration in Protestant England 1558-1689'', Studies in modern History, Pearson Education

==External links==
*[http://www.ohchr.org/english/issues/religion/index.htm United Nations] - Special Rapporteur of the Commission on Human Rights on freedom of religion or belief
*[http://www.uscirf.gov/ United States Commission on International Religious Freedom]
*http://www.unhchr.ch/huricane/huricane.nsf/view01/5E72D6B7B624AABBC125713700572D09?opendocument
*[http://atheism.about.com/od/religiousintolerance/ About.com section on Religious Intolerance]
*[http://www.state.gov/documents/organization/72238.pdf U.S. State Department 2006 Annual Report on International Religious Freedom]

{{Religious persecution}}
{{Discrimination}}
{{Criticism of religion}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Religious Persecution}}
[[Category:Religiously motivated violence in the United States]]
[[Category:Religious persecution| ]]
[[Category:Religion and society]]
[[Category:Religious pluralism]]

[[ar:اضطهاد ديني]]
[[da:Religiøs forfølgelse]]
[[de:Religiöse Verfolgung]]
[[hu:Vallásüldözés]]
[[ja:宗教的迫害]]
[[no:Religiøs forfølgelse]]
[[zh:宗教迫害]]
[[fr:Persécutions religieuses]]</text>
      <sha1>0vjica1kvo28sjfljm9hzwcfrg6byn4</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
