<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Responsa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>154976</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519177785</id>
      <parentid>519177559</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-22T10:18:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>174.118.114.80</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8012">'''Responsa''' ([[Latin]]: plural of ''responsum'', &quot;answers&quot;)  comprise a body of written decisions and rulings given by [[legal scholar]]s in response to questions addressed to them.

==In the Roman Empire==

[[Roman law]] recognised ''responsa prudentium'', i.e. the responses and thoughts of jurists, as one of the sources of &quot;[[Ius scriptum]]&quot; (written law), along with laws originating from magistrates, from the Senate or from the emperor.

A particularly well-known and highly influential example of such responsa was the Digesta (or Digests), in 90 books, principal work of the prominent Second Century jurist [[Salvius Julianus]]. This was a systematic treatise on civil and praetorian law, cited by many later Roman legal writers, which has been described as “''A comprehensive collection of responsa on real and hypothetical cases; in general, it followed the edictal system... With Iulianus, the Roman jurisprudence reached its apogee.''” &lt;ref&gt;&quot;Salvius Iulianus&quot; in Adolf Berger, ''Encyclopedic Dictionary of Roman Law'', American Philosophical Society, 1953, p. 552&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the Roman Catholic Church==
In the Roman Catholic Church, a responsum is an answer given by the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]] on certain matters pertaining to faith and morals. The Holy Office is the sole and exclusive doctrinal organization which has the right to give responsa. Recent doctrinal documents which contain relevant responsa are [http://www.vatican.edu/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20070629_commento-responsa_en.html Commentary on Responsa ad quaestiones], [http://www.ourladyswarriors.org/teach/ordisace2.htm Responsum ad Dubium Concerning the Teaching Contained in Ordinatio Sacerdotalis] and [http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/cfaith/documents/rc_con_cfaith_doc_20070801_risposte-usa_en.html Responses to Certain Questions of the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops Concerning Artificial Nutrition and Hydration]

==In Judaism==
{{Main| History of responsa}}
{{Further|Oral law|Halakha|Posek}}
In [[rabbinic literature]], the '''Responsa''' are known as ''She'elot ve-Teshuvot'' ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]]:  '''שאלות ותשובות''' &quot;questions and answers&quot;) and  comprise the body of written decisions and rulings given by [[Posek|poskim]] (&quot;deciders of Jewish law&quot;).

Judaism's responsa constitute a special class of [[rabbinic literature]], to be distinguished from the [[Rabbinic literature#Meforshim|commentaries]] (''meforshim'')—devoted to the exegesis of the [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]], the [[Mishnah]], the [[Talmud]]—and from [[Halakha#Codes of Jewish law|the codes of law]] which delineate the rules for ordinary incidents of life.

The responsa literature covers a period of 1,700 years—the mode, style and subject matter have changed as a function of the travels of the Jewish people and of the development of other halakhic literature, particularly the codes. See [[History of Responsa]].

Responsa play a particularly important role in [[Halakha|Jewish law]]. The questions forwarded are usually practical, and often concerned with new contingencies for which no provision has been made in the [[Halakha#Codes of Jewish law|codes of law]], and the responsa thus supplement the codes. They therefore function as a source of law, almost as [[stare decisis|legal precedent]], in that they are consulted by later [[posek|decisors]] in their rulings; they are also, in turn, incorporated into subsequent [[Halakha#Codes of Jewish law|codes]]. See [[Posek]]; [[Halakha#Sources and process|The sources and process of Halakha]].

In addition to requests for [[posek|Halakhic rulings]], many of the questions addressed were theoretical in character, particularly amongst the earlier responsa. The responsa accordingly contain rulings on [[ethics]], [[Business ethics#Jewish business ethics|business ethics]], the [[philosophy of religion]], [[astronomy]], [[mathematics]], [[history]], [[geography]], as well as interpretations of passages in the [[Bible]], the [[Mishnah]], the [[Talmud]] and the [[Midrash]]. Thus, while early [[rabbinic literature|Jewish literature]] has few historical works, many notes on the [[Jewish history|history of Judaism]] have been introduced into the responsa.

Responsa thus contain valuable information about the [[culture]] of the Jews and the people among whom they lived. Information may also be gleaned about the moral and social relations of the times, occupations, the household, [[minhag|customs]], expressions of joy and of sorrow, and recreations and even games. Older responsa are also important for readings and emendations of the [[Mishnah]] and the [[Talmud]].

==In Islam==
{{Unreferenced section|date=June 2007}}
{{Expert-subject|Islam|date=November 2008}}
A similar use of responsa (here called [[fatwā]]) is found in [[Islam]]. The [[mufti]] is a member of the Islamic scholarly class ([[ulamā]]) who form the Muslim religious establishment. In Islam, the term muftī is largely restricted to [[Sunni]]sm, and has both a formal and informal use, the former for state-appointed officials who gave rulings on matters concerning the state or the public, the latter for individuals who respond to their followers or to others.

Nowadays, questions can be asked via the [[Internet]], where sites have sprung up offering legal advice.{{citation needed|date=January 2012}}

In [[Shia]]ism, fatwa is also used. There personal devotion to specific clergy is mandatory for believers. High-ranking members of the [[ulama]] class achieve the status of marja' al-taqlīd (pl. marāji'), that is, &quot;the point to which imitation returns&quot;: in other words, they pronounce on religious matters, especially legal ones, and the rest of mankind are muqallid or imitators, who do nothing without the mandate of their specific marja'. There are very few marāji' at any time, though on a number of occasions since the 19th century, the title has come to rest on a single individual for the entire Shia world. There are larger numbers of Shia clergy with the rank of mujtahid, who are empowered to give independent opinions on religious matters. Traditionally, as in Judaism, the answers of marāji' and mujtahids are collected in a compilation called Risāla-yi su'āl va javāb ([[Farsi]]) or &quot;Epistle of Questions and Answers&quot;.

There is generally greater latitude for Shia ulamā, insofar as the principle of independent reasoning (ijtihād, from the same root as mujtahid) in matters of religious law remains valid in Shi'i jurisprudence, whereas it is deemed to have ended in Sunnism as far back as the 10th century (though it is now reckoned that this perception of the [[desuetude]] or &quot;closing of the door&quot; of ijtihad did not always apply).

==Bibliography==

* M. Elon, ''Jewish Law'', Jerusalem 1975

==References==
*[http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=576&amp;letter=S She'elot U-Teshubot], jewishencyclopedia.com
*[http://95.1911encyclopedia.org/H/HE/HEBREW_LITERATURE.htm Hebrew Literature], 1911encyclopedia.org . No such page found. October 22, 2012

&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
* [http://www.biu.ac.il/JH/Responsa/ The Bar Ilan Responsa project]
* [http://www.halachabrura.org/alephlink.htm#שות Orthodox Responsa Index] Non-English language article. Accessed October 22, 2012
* [http://learn.jtsa.edu/topics/diduknow/lgresponsa/ The Responsa of Professor Louis Ginzberg] No such article found - October 22, 2012
* [http://www.responsafortoday.com/ Masorti and Conservative Jewish responsa] Non-English language article. Accessed October 22, 2012
*[http://data.ccarnet.org/resp/tindex.html Topical index of non-binding Reform Jewish responsa]

[[Category:Rabbinic legal texts and responsa| ]]
[[Category:Article Feedback 5]]
[[Category:Oral Torah]]

[[ar:جواب شرعي]]
[[bg:Респонса]]
[[de:Response (Judentum)]]
[[fr:Responsa]]
[[it:Responsa]]
[[he:שאלות ותשובות]]
[[pl:Responsy]]
[[pt:Responsa]]
[[ru:Респонсы]]</text>
      <sha1>5j7cq2kohe7behlrbbpfv46pb0pkihn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
