<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Resurrection</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26447</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521388641</id>
      <parentid>520192079</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T18:18:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dinkleberg4474</username>
        <id>17794850</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31242">{{Other uses}}

[[File:Plaque resurrection dead VandA M.104-1945.jpg|thumb|300px|Plaque depicting saints rising from the dead.]]
'''Resurrection''' ([[anglicized]] from Latin ''resurrectio'') is the concept of a [[organism|living being]] coming back to life after [[death]]. It is largely a religious concept, where it is used in two distinct respects —a belief in the resurrection of individual [[soul]]s that is current and ongoing ([[Idealism (Christian eschatology)|Christian idealism]], [[realized eschatology]]), or else a belief in a singular &quot;[[Resurrection of the Dead]]&quot; event at the [[End of the world (religion)|end of the world]]. Most eschatologies believe in a [[universal resurrection]], wherein all people from all history are resurrected. The Resurrection of the Dead is a standard [[eschatological]] belief in the [[Abrahamic religions]]. In a number of ancient religions, a [[life-death-rebirth deity]] is a deity which dies and resurrects. The [[Death of Jesus|death]] and [[resurrection of Jesus]] is a central focus of [[Christianity]].

The [[soul]] is believed by some to be the divine and [[Immortality of the soul|immortal]] part of the human being, and some believe it is the actual vehicle by which people are resurrected.&lt;ref&gt;[[Gregory of Nyssa]]: &quot;On the Soul and the Resurrection:&quot; &quot;However far from each other their natural propensity and their inherent forces of repulsion urge them, and debar each from mingling with its opposite, none the less will the soul be near each by its power of recognition, and will persistently cling to the familiar atoms, until their concourse after this division again takes place in the same way, for that fresh formation of the dissolved body which will properly be, and be called, resurrection.&quot; http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf205.x.iii.ii.html&lt;/ref&gt;
However, theological debate ensues with regard to what kind of resurrection is factual —either a ''spiritual'' resurrection with a [[spirit]] body (i.e. [[Heaven]]), or a material resurrection with a restored [[human body]].&lt;ref&gt;As in the [[Apostle's Creed]]: &quot;I believe in the Holy Spirit, the holy catholic Church, the communion of saints, the forgiveness of sins, the resurrection of the body, and life everlasting.&quot;; [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12792a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia: General Resurrection]: &quot;Resurrection is the rising again from the dead, the resumption of life. The [[Fourth Lateran Council]] (1215) teaches that all men, whether [[Chosen people#Christianity|elect]] or [[reprobate]], &quot;will rise again with their own bodies which they now bear about with them&quot; (chapter &quot;''Firmiter''&quot;). In the language of the [[creeds]] and professions of faith this return to life is called resurrection of the body (''resurrectio carnis, resurrectio mortuoram, anastasis ton nekron'') for a double reason: first, since the [[Immortality of the soul|soul cannot die]], it cannot be said to return to life; second the [[heretical]] contention of [[Hymenaeus (Ephesian)|Hymeneus and Philitus]] that the [[Scriptures]] denote by resurrection not the return to life of the body, but the rising of the soul from the death of [[Christian views on sin|sin]] to the life of [[Grace (Christianity)|grace]], must be excluded.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; While most Christians believe Jesus' resurrection was in a material body, a very small minority believe it was spiritual.&lt;ref&gt;R. C. Symes: &quot;According to [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]], the resurrection transformed Jesus into the Christ, the Son of God and Savior of the world. Christ's resurrected body was not a resuscitated physical body, but a new body of a spiritual/celestial nature: the animal body comes first and then the spiritual body (1 Cor. 15:46). Paul never says that the earthly body becomes immortal.&quot; http://www.religioustolerance.org/symes01.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;4Jehovah.org &quot;Watchtower Society claims that Jesus did not raise His physical human body, but rather an invisible spirit—the archangel Michael. They state: &quot;...in his resurrection he ‘became a life-giving spirit.’ That was why for most of the time he was invisible to his faithful apostles… He needs no human body any longer… The human body of flesh, which Jesus Christ laid down forever as a ransom sacrifice, was disposed of by God’s power.”—“Things in Which it is Impossible for God to Lie,” pp. 332, 354&quot; http://4jehovah.org/jehovahs-witness-resurrection.php#t1b&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gospel-mysteries.net/resurrection-theories.html&lt;/ref&gt;

There are documented rare cases of the return to life of the [[Clinical death|clinically dead]] which are classified scientifically as examples of the [[Lazarus syndrome]], a term originating from the Biblical story of the [[Resurrection of Lazarus]].

==Ancient religions in the Near East==
{{See also|Life-death-rebirth deity}}
The concept of resurrection is found in the writings of some ancient non-Abrahamic religions in the Middle East. A few extant [[Egyptian language|Egyptian]] and [[Canaan]]ite writings allude to [[Life-death-rebirth deity|dying and rising gods]] such as [[Osiris]] and [[Baal]]. Sir [[James Frazer]] in his book ''[[The Golden Bough]]'' relates to these dying and rising gods,&lt;ref&gt;Sir [[James Frazer]] (1922). ''The Golden Bough: A Study in Magic and Religion'' Ware: Wordsworth 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; but many of his examples, according to various scholars, distort the sources.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jonathan Z. Smith]] &quot;Dying and Rising Gods&quot; in Mircea Eliade (ed.) ''The Encyclopedia of Religion: Vol. 3''. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster Macmillan 1995: 521-27.&lt;/ref&gt; Taking a more positive position, Mettinger argues in his recent book that the category of rise and return to life is significant for the following deities: Ugaritic [[Baal]], [[Melqart]], [[Adonis]], [[Eshmun]], [[Osiris]] and [[Tammuz (deity)|Dumuzi]].&lt;ref&gt;Mettinger, ''Riddle of Resurrection'', 55-222.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ancient Greek religion==
In [[ancient Greek religion]], a number of men and women were made physically [[Immortality|immortal]] as they were resurrected from the dead. [[Asclepius]] was killed by Zeus, only to be resurrected and transformed into a major deity. [[Achilles]], after being killed, was snatched from his funeral pyre by his divine mother [[Thetis]] and resurrected, brought to an immortal existence in either Leuce, [[Elysium|Elysian plains]] or the [[Fortunate Isles|Islands of the Blessed]]. [[Memnon (mythology)|Memnon]], who was killed by Achilles, seems to have a received a similar fate. [[Alcmene]], [[Castor and Pollux|Castor]], [[Heracles]], and [[Melicertes]], were also among the figures sometimes considered to have been resurrected to physical immortality. According to [[Herodotus]]'s [[Histories (Herodotus)|Histories]], the seventh century BC sage [[Aristeas of Proconnesus]] was first found dead, after which his body disappeared from a locked room. Later he found not only to have been resurrected but to have gained immortality.

Many other figures, like a great part of those who fought in the [[Trojan war|Trojan]] and Theban wars, [[Menelaus]], and the historical pugilist [[Cleomedes of Astupalaea]], were also believed to have been made physically immortal, but without having died in the first place. Indeed, in Greek religion, immortality originally always included an eternal union of body and soul. The philosophical idea of an [[immortal soul]] was a later invention, which, although influential, never had a breakthrough in the Greek world. As may be witnessed even into the Christian era, not least by the complaints of various philosophers over popular beliefs, traditional Greek believers maintained the conviction that certain individuals were resurrected from the dead and made physically immortal and that for the rest of us, we could only look forward to an existence as disembodied and dead souls.&lt;ref&gt;[[Erwin Rohde]] ''Psyche: The Cult of Souls and Belief in Immortality among the Greeks''. New York: Harper &amp; Row 1925 [1921]; [[Dag Øistein Endsjø]]. ''Greek Resurrection Beliefs and the Success of Christianity.'' New York: Palgrave Macmillan 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

This traditional religious belief in physical immortality was generally denied by the Greek philosophers. Writing his ''Lives of Illustrious Men'' ([[Parallel Lives]]) in the first century CE, the [[Middle Platonism|Middle Platonic]] philosopher [[Plutarch]]'s chapter on [[Romulus]] gave an account of his mysterious disappearance and subsequent deification, comparing it to traditional Greek beliefs such as the resurrection and physical immortalization of Alcmene and Aristeas the Proconnesian, &quot;for they say Aristeas died in a fuller's work-shop, and his friends coming to look for him, found his body vanished; and that some presently after, coming from abroad, said they met him traveling towards Croton.&quot; Plutarch openly scorned such beliefs held in traditional ancient Greek religion, writing, &quot;many such improbabilities do your fabulous writers relate, deifying creatures naturally mortal.&quot;

The parallel between these traditional beliefs and the later resurrection of Jesus was not lost on the early Christians, as [[Justin Martyr]] argued: &quot;when we say … Jesus Christ, our teacher, was crucified and died, and rose again, and ascended into heaven, we propose nothing different from what you believe regarding those whom you consider sons of Zeus.&quot; (''1 Apol.'' 21). There is, however, no belief in a general resurrection in ancient Greek religion, as the Greeks held that not even the gods were able to recreate flesh that had been lost to decay, fire or consumption. The notion of a general resurrection of the dead was therefore apparently quite preposterous to the Greeks. This is made clear in [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]]'s [[Areopagus]] discourse. After having first told about the resurrection of Jesus, which makes the Athenians interested to hear more, Paul goes on, relating how this event relates to a general resurrection of the dead:
{{quote|
&quot;Therefore having overlooked the times of ignorance, God is now declaring to men that all everywhere should repent, because He has fixed a day in which He will judge the world in righteousness through a Man whom He has appointed, having furnished proof to all men by raising Him from the dead.&quot; Now when they heard of the resurrection of the dead, some began to sneer, but others said, `We shall hear you again concerning this.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Acts%2017:30-32;&amp;version=49 Acts 17:30-32]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Judaism==
{{main|Jewish eschatology}}
There are three explicit examples in the [[Hebrew Bible]] (Tanakh) of people being resurrected from the dead:
* The prophet [[Elijah]] prays and God raises a young boy from death ([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Kings%2017:17-24;&amp;version=49; 1 Kings 17:17-24])
* [[Elisha]] raises the son of the Shunammite woman ([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Kings%204:32-37;&amp;version=49; 2 Kings 4:32-37]); this was the very same child whose birth he previously foretold ([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Kings%204:8-16;&amp;version=49; 2 Kings 4:8-16])
* A dead man's body that was thrown into the dead Elisha's tomb is resurrected when the body touches Elisha's bones ([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Kings%2013:21;&amp;version=49; 2 Kings 13:21])

According to Herbert C. Brichtothe, writing in Reform Judaism's [[Hebrew Union College]] Annual, the family tomb is the central concept in understanding biblical views of the [[afterlife]].  Brichtothe states that it is &quot;not mere sentimental respect for the physical remains that is...the motivation for the practice, but rather an assumed connection between proper sepulture and the condition of happiness of the deceased in the afterlife&quot; According to Brichtothe, the early [[Israelites]] apparently believed that the graves of family, or tribe, united into one, and that this unified collectivity is to what the [[Biblical Hebrew]] term [[Sheol]] refers. Although not well defined in the Tanakh, Sheol in this view was a subterranean underworld where the souls of the dead went after the body died.  The [[Babylonians]] had a similar underworld called [[Aralu]], and the [[Greeks]] had one known as [[Hades]].  For biblical references to Sheol see Genesis 42:38, Isaiah 14:11, Psalm 141:7, Daniel 12:2, Proverbs 7:27 and Job 10:21,22, and 17:16, among others. According to Brichtothe,  other Biblical names for Sheol were: Abaddon (ruin), found in Psalm 88:11, Job 28:22 and Proverbs 15:11;  Bor (the pit), found in Isaiah 14:15, 24:22, Ezekiel 26:20; and Shakhat (corruption), found in Isaiah 38:17, Ezekiel 28:8.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kin, Cult p.8&quot;&gt;Herbert Chanon Brichto &quot;Kin, Cult, Land and Afterlife - A Biblical Complex&quot;, Hebrew Union College Annual 44, p.8 (1973)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Christianity==
In [[Christianity]], resurrection most critically concerns the [[Resurrection of Jesus]] Christ, but also includes the resurrection of [[Judgment Day]] known as the [[Resurrection of the Dead]] by those Christians who subscribe to the [[Nicene Creed]] (which is the majority or [[Mainstream Christianity]]), as well as the resurrection miracles done by Jesus and the prophets of the [[Old Testament]].

===Resurrection of Jesus===
{{main|Life-death-rebirth deity|Resurrection of Jesus|Easter|Resurrection appearances of Jesus}}
Many Christians regard the resurrection of Jesus as the central doctrine in Christianity.  Others take the [[Incarnation (Christianity)|Incarnation of Jesus]] to be more central; however, it is the [[Miracles of Jesus|miracles]] &amp;mdash; and particularly his Resurrection &amp;mdash; which provide validation of his incarnation. According to Paul, the entire Christian faith hinges upon the centrality of the resurrection of Jesus and the hope for a life after death. The [[Paul of Tarsus|Apostle Paul]] wrote in his first letter to the Corinthians:
{{quote|
&quot;If only for this life we have hope in Christ, we are to be pitied more than all men.  But Christ has indeed been raised from the dead, the first fruits of those who have fallen asleep.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Corinthians%2015:19-20;&amp;version=49; Corinthians 15:19-20]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Nearly all Christians - Catholic, Orthodox and Protestant and adherents of the Assyrian Church of the East - accept the resurrection of Jesus as a real historical event, and condemn the denial of the physical reality of the resurrection as a [[heresy]]. [[Docetism]], the heresy that denied the death and subsequent resurrection of Jesus by emphasizing that Jesus was only God and not man, was condemned by [[Proto-orthodox Christianity]]{{Who|date=November 2010}} in the late 1st to early 2nd century.

===Resurrection miracles===
[[File:Bonnat01.jpg|thumb|250px|right|''The Resurrection of Lazarus'', painting by [[Leon Bonnat]], France, 1857.]]
{{Main|Miracles of Jesus#Resurrection of the dead}}
During the [[Ministry of Jesus]] on earth, before his [[Crucifixion of Jesus|crucifixion]], he commissioned his [[Twelve Apostles]] to, among other things, raise the dead.&lt;ref&gt;Not in the [[Great Commission]] of the resurrected Jesus, but only in the so-called [[Matthew 10|''Lesser Commission'']] of Matthew, specifically {{bibleverse||Matthew|10:8}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[New Testament]], Jesus is said to have raised several persons from death. These resurrections included the daughter of [[Jairus]] shortly after death, a young man in the midst of his own [[funeral]] procession, and [[Lazarus of Bethany|Lazarus]], who had been buried for four days. According to the [[Gospel of Matthew]], after Jesus's resurrection, many of the dead [[saint]]s came out of their tombs and entered [[Jerusalem in Christianity|Jerusalem]], where they appeared to many.

Similar resurrections are credited to Christian [[twelve apostles|apostles]] and saints. [[Saint Peter|Peter]] allegedly raised a woman named [[Dorcas]] (called Tabitha), and [[Saul of Tarsus|Paul]] revived a man named Eutychus who had fallen asleep and fell from a window to his death, according to the book of [[Acts of the Apostles|Acts]]. Proceeding the apostolic era, many saints were said to resurrect the dead, as recorded in Orthodox Christian hagiographies.{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}

===Resurrection of the Dead===
{{main|Christian eschatology#Resurrection of the dead}}
Christianity started as a religious movement within 1st-century Judaism (late [[Second Temple Judaism]]), and it retains the [[Pharisaic]] belief in the [[Pharisees#The afterlife|afterlife and Resurrection of the Dead]].  Whereas this belief was only one of many beliefs held about the [[World to Come]] in Second Temple Judaism, and was notably rejected by the [[Sadducees]], this belief became dominant within [[Early Christianity]] and soon included an insistence on the resurrection of the flesh, against [[gnostic]] teachings that flesh was evil. Most modern [[Christian churches]] continue to uphold the belief that there will be a final [[resurrection of the dead#Christianity|Resurrection of the Dead]] and [[World to Come#Christian eschatology|World to Come]], perhaps as prophesied by the [[Apostle Paul]] when he said: &quot;...he hath appointed a day, in the which he will [[Last judgment|judge the world]]...&quot; ([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=acts%2017:30-31;&amp;version=NASB Acts 17:31] KJV) and &quot;...there shall be a resurrection of the dead, [[Universal resurrection|both of the just and unjust]].&quot; ([http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Acts%2024:14-16;&amp;version=NASB Acts 24:15] KJV). Most also teach that it is only as a result of the [[Atonement in Christianity|atoning work of Christ]], by [[Grace in Christianity|grace]] through [[Faith in Christianity|faith]], that people are spared [[eternal punishment]] as [[divine judgment]] for their [[sins]].

Belief in the Resurrection of the Dead, and Jesus Christ's role as judge, is codified in the [[Apostles' Creed]], which is the fundamental creed of Christian [[baptismal]] faith. The [[Book of Revelation]] also makes many references about the [[Judgment Day|Day of Judgment]] when the dead will be raised up.

===Platonic philosophy===
In Platonic philosophy and other Greek philosophical thought, at death the soul was said to leave the inferior body behind. The idea that Jesus was resurrected spiritually rather than physically even gained popularity among some Christian teachers, whom the author of [[1 John]] declared to be [[antichrist]]s. Similar beliefs appeared in the early church as [[Gnosticism]]. However, in Luke 24:39, the resurrected Jesus expressly states &quot;behold my hands and my feet, that it is I myself.  Handle me and see, for a spirit does not have flesh and bones as you see I have.&quot;

==Islam==
{{Main|Qiyama}}
Belief in the &quot;Day of Resurrection&quot;, ''[[Qiyamah|Yawm al-Qiyāmah]]'' ({{lang-ar|يوم القيامة}}) is also crucial for Muslims. They believe the time of ''Qiyāmah'' is preordained by God but unknown to man. The trials and [[tribulation]]s preceding and during the ''Qiyāmah'' are described in the Qur'an and the [[hadith]], and also in the commentaries of [[Ulema|scholars]]. The Qur'an emphasizes [[Resurrection of the Dead|bodily resurrection]], a break from the [[pre-Islamic Arabia]]n understanding of death.&lt;ref&gt;See:
* &quot;Resurrection&quot;, ''The New Encyclopedia of Islam'' (2003)
* {{Cite encyclopedia | title=Avicenna | encyclopedia=Encyclopaedia of Islam Online | ref=harv }}: Ibn Sīnā, Abū ʿAlī al-Ḥusayn b. ʿAbd Allāh b. Sīnā is known in the West as &quot;Avicenna&quot;.
* {{Cite encyclopedia | title=Qiyama | encyclopedia=Encyclopaedia of Islam Online | author=L. Gardet | ref=harv }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Zen Buddhism==
There are stories in [[Buddhism]] where the power of resurrection was allegedly demonstrated in Chan or [[Zen]] tradition. One is the [[legend]] of [[Bodhidharma]], the Indian master who brought the [[Ekayana]] school of India to China that subsequently became Chan Buddhism.

The other is the passing of Chinese Chan master [[Fuke Zen|Puhua]] (J., Fuke) and is recounted in the Record of [[Linji Yixuan|Linji]] (J., [[Rinzai]]). Puhua was known for his unusual behavior and teaching style so it is no wonder that he is associated with an event that breaks the usual prohibition on displaying such powers. Here is the account from Irmgard Schloegl's &quot;The Zen Teaching of Rinzai&quot;.

{{quote|
&quot;One day at the street market Fuke was begging all and sundry to give him a robe. Everybody offered him one, but he did not want any of them. The master [Linji] made the superior buy a coffin, and when Fuke returned, said to him: &quot;There, I had this robe made for you.&quot; Fuke shouldered the coffin, and went back to the street market, calling loudly: &quot;Rinzai had this robe made for me! I am off to the East Gate to enter transformation&quot; (to die).&quot; The people of the market crowded after him, eager to look. Fuke said: &quot;No, not today. Tomorrow, I shall go to the South Gate to enter transformation.&quot; And so for three days. Nobody believed it any longer. On the fourth day, and now without any spectators, Fuke went alone outside the city walls, and laid himself into the coffin. He asked a traveler who chanced by to nail down the lid.

The news spread at once, and the people of the market rushed there. On opening the coffin, they found that the body had vanished, but from high up in the sky they heard the ring of his hand bell.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Schloegl, Irmgard; tr. &quot;The Zen Teaching of Rinzai&quot;. Shambhala Publications, Inc., Berkeley, 1976. Page 76. ISBN 0-87773-087-3.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Disappearances (as distinct from resurrection)==
{{See also|Entering heaven alive}}
As knowledge of different religions has grown, so have claims of bodily disappearance of some religious and mythological figures.  In [[ancient Greek religion]], this was a way the gods made some physically immortal, including such figures as [[Cleitus]], [[Ganymede (mythology)|Ganymede]], [[Menelaus]], and [[Tithonus]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Erwin Rohde]] ''Psyche: The Cult of Souls and Belief in Immortality among the Greeks''. New York: Harper &amp; Row 1966.[1921]; [[Dag Øistein Endsjø]]. ''Greek Resurrection Beliefs and the Success of Christianity.'' New York: Palgrave Macmillan 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In his chapter on [[Romulus]] from [[Parallel Lives]], [[Plutarch]] criticises the continuous belief in such disappearances, referring to the allegedly miraculous disappearance of the historical figures Romulus, [[Cleomedes of Astypalaea]], and [[Croesus]]. In ancient times pagan similarities were explained by the early Christian writers, such as [[Justin Martyr]], as the work of demons and Satan, with the intention of leading Christians astray.&lt;ref&gt;Justin Martyr, ''Dialogue with Trypho'' (ca 147-161 A.D.) Catholic University Press, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

In somewhat recent years it has been learned that [[Gesar]], the Savior of [[Tibet]], at the end, chants on a mountain top and his clothes fall empty to the ground.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alexandra David-Neel]],and Lama Yongden, ''The Superhuman Life of Gesar of Ling'', Rider, 1933, While still in oral tradition, it is recorded for the first time by an early European traveler.&lt;/ref&gt; The body of the first Guru of the [[Sikh]]s, [[Guru Nanak Dev]], is said to have disappeared and flowers were left in place of his dead body. There is a [[Dome of the Rock|traditional spot]] in [[Jerusalem]] where the [[Prophets of Islam|Prophet]] [[Muhammad]] mounted the steed Al-[[Buraq]] and [[Isra and Mi'raj|ascended to]] [[Jannah|Heaven]] in the night.

[[FitzRoy Somerset, 4th Baron Raglan|Lord Raglan]]'s [[FitzRoy_Somerset,_4th_Baron_Raglan#The_Hero|Hero Pattern]] lists many religious figures whose bodies disappear, or have more than one [[sepulchre]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Otto Rank]], [[FitzRoy Somerset, 4th Baron Raglan|Lord Raglan]], and [[Alan Dundes]], ''In Quest of the Hero'', Princeton University Press, 1990&lt;/ref&gt; B. Traven, author of ''[[The Treasure of the Sierra Madre]]'', wrote that the [[Inca]] [[Virococha]], walked away on the top of the sea and vanished.&lt;ref&gt;B. Traven, ''The Creation of the Sun and Moon'', Lawerence Hill Books, 1977&lt;/ref&gt; It has been thought that teachings regarding the purity and incorruptibility of the hero's human body are linked to this phenomenon. Perhaps, this is also to deter the practice of disturbing and collecting the hero's remains. They are safely protected if they have disappeared.&lt;ref&gt;See: Michael Paterniti, ''Driving Mr. Albert: A Trip Across America with Einstein's Brain'', The Dial Press, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

The first such case mentioned in the Bible is that of [[Enoch (ancestor of Noah)|Enoch]] (son of [[Jared (ancestor of Noah)|Jared]], great-grandfather of [[Noah]], and father of [[Methuselah]]). Enoch is said to have lived a life where he &quot;walked with God&quot;, after which &quot;he was not, for God took him&quot;. (Genesis 5:1-18)&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse-lb||Genesis|5:18-24|HE}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Deuteronomy]] (34:6) [[Moses]] is secretly buried. [[Elijah]] vanishes in a whirlwind [[2 Kings]] (2:11). After hundreds of years these two earlier Biblical heroes suddenly reappear, and are seen walking with Jesus, then again vanish. [[Gospel of Mark|Mark]] (9:2-8), [[Gospel of Matthew|Matthew]] (17:1-8) and [[Gospel of Luke|Luke]] (9:28-33). The last time he is seen, [[Gospel of Luke|Luke]] (24:51) alone tells of Jesus leaving his disciples by ascending into the sky.

==Zombies==
{{Main|Zombie}}
A zombie ([[Haitian Creole]]: ''zonbi''; [[North Mbundu language|North Mbundu]]: ''nzumbe'') can be either a fictional [[undead]] monster or a person in an entranced state believed to be controlled by a ''[[bokor]]'' or wizard. These latter are the original zombies, occurring in the [[West African]] [[West African Vodun|Vodun]] religion and its American offshoots [[Haitian Vodou]] and [[Louisiana Voodoo|New Orleans Voodoo]].

Zombies became a [[Zombies in popular culture|popular device]] in modern [[horror fiction]], largely because of the success of [[George A. Romero]]'s 1968 film ''[[Night of the Living Dead]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/7280793.stm |title = Zombie maestro lays down the lore  |accessdate = 2009-10-01 |author = Smith, Neil |publisher = BBC News | date=March 7, 2008 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; and they have appeared as plot devices in various books, films and in television shows. Zombie fiction is now a sizeable sub-genre of horror, usually describing a breakdown of civilization occurring when most of the population become flesh-eating zombies – a [[zombie apocalypse]]. The monsters are usually hungry for human flesh, often specifically brains. Sometimes they are victims of a fictional [[pandemic]] illness causing the dead to reanimate or the living to behave this way, but often no cause is given in the story.

==See also==
* [[1 Corinthians 15]]
* [[Information-theoretic death]]
* [[Omega Point (Tipler)]]
* [[Near death experience]]
* [[Cryonics]]
* [[Suspended animation]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [[Dag Øistein Endsjø]]. ''Greek Resurrection Beliefs and the Success of Christianity.'' New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2009.
* [[Nikolai Fyodorovich Fyodorov]]. ''Philosophy of Physical Resurrection'' 1906.
* [[Edwin Hatch]]. ''Influence of Greek Ideas and Usages Upon the Christian Church'' (1888 Hibbert Lectures).
* [[Alfred J Hebert]]. ''Raised from the Dead: True Stories of 400 Resurrection Miracles''
* Lange, Dierk. [http://books.google.de/books?id=syATJKcx5A0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=lange,+kingdoms&amp;hl=de&amp;ei=N_-fTYqhL82Vswam6KzoAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false &quot;The dying and the rising God in the New Year Festival of Ife&quot;], in: Lange, ''Ancient Kingdoms of West Africa'', Dettelbach: Röll Vlg. 2004, pp.&amp;nbsp;343–376.
* [[Richard Longenecker]], editor. ''Life in the Face of Death: The Resurrection Message of the New Testament''. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1998.
* Tryggve Mettinger. ''The Riddle of Resurrection: &quot;Dying and Rising Gods&quot; in the Ancient Near East'', Stockholm: Almqvist 2001.
* [[Markus Mühling]]. ''Grundinformation Eschatologie. Systematische Theologie aus der Perspektive der Hoffnung''. Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2007, ISBN 978-3-8252-2918-4, 242–262.
* [[George Nickelsburg]]. ''Resurrection, Immortality, and Eternal Life in Intertestmental Judaism''. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1972.
* [[Pheme Perkins]]. ''Resurrection: New Testament Witness and Contemporary Reflection''. Garden City: Doubleday &amp; Company, 1984.
* [[Erwin Rohde]] ''Psyche: The Cult of Souls and Belief in Immortality among the Greeks''. New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1925 [1921].
* [[Charles H. Talbert]]. &quot;The Concept of Immortals in Mediterranean Antiquity&quot;, ''Journal of Biblical Literature'', Volume 94, 1975, pp 419–436
* [[Charles H. Talbert]]. &quot;The Myth of a Descending-Ascending Redeemer in Mediterranean Antiquity&quot;, ''New Testament Studies'', 22, 1975/76, pp 418–440
* {{cite book
 |author=Frank J. Tipler
 |year=1994
 |title=The Physics of Immortality: Modern Cosmology, God and the Resurrection of the Dead
 |location=New York
 |publisher=[[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]]
 |isbn=0-19-851949-4
}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Resurrection}}
* [http://www.archeosofica.org/en/content/view/180/37/ Properties and Endowment of Resurrected Bodies according to the Bible]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12789a.htm Resurrection of Jesus Christ] - Catholic Encyclopedia
* [http://www.firstthings.com/article/2007/01/the-life-of-the-world--15 Article on resurrection in the Hebrew Bible.]
* [http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=233&amp;letter=R Jewish Encyclopedia: Resurrection]
* [http://www.orthodoxphotos.com/readings/threshold/occult.shtml The enticement of the Occult: Occultism examined by a scientist and Orthodox Priest]
* [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-18159992.html?refid=hbw_rd Rethinking the resurrection.(of Jesus Christ)(Cover Story) Newsweek, April 8th 1996, Woodward, Kenneth L.]
* [http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-76 ''Dictionary of the History of Ideas'':] Death and Immortality, Resurrection, Reincarnation

[[Category:Miracles]]
[[Category:Mythemes]]
[[Category:Mythology]]
[[Category:Afterlife]]
[[Category:Religious belief and doctrine]]
[[Category:Science fiction themes]]
[[Category:Latin loanwords]]

[[als:Auferstehung]]
[[bg:Възкресение]]
[[ca:Resurrecció]]
[[cs:Vzkříšení]]
[[da:Opstandelse]]
[[de:Auferstehung]]
[[es:Resurrección]]
[[eo:Reviviĝo]]
[[fa:رستاخیز]]
[[fr:Résurrection]]
[[fy:Opstanning]]
[[gd:Aiseirigh]]
[[gl:Resurrección]]
[[hr:Uskrsnuće]]
[[id:Kebangkitan]]
[[it:Risurrezione]]
[[he:תחיית המתים]]
[[kn:ಪುನರುತ್ಥಾನ]]
[[sw:Ufufuko]]
[[lb:Operstéiung]]
[[lt:Prisikėlimas]]
[[hu:Feltámadás]]
[[mk:Воскресение]]
[[nl:Opstanding]]
[[ja:復活 (キリスト教)]]
[[no:Oppstandelse]]
[[pl:Zmartwychwstanie]]
[[pt:Ressurreição]]
[[rue:Воскресїня]]
[[ru:Воскресение из мёртвых]]
[[sq:Ringjallja]]
[[simple:Resurrection]]
[[sr:Васкрсење]]
[[sh:Vaskrsenje]]
[[fi:Ylösnousemus]]
[[sv:Uppståndelse]]
[[tl:Muling pagkabuhay]]
[[uk:Воскресіння]]
[[zh-yue:復活]]
[[zh:復活]]</text>
      <sha1>hub87a6aqz5mekcafpk7ij3v8p059fs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
