<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Resurrection of Jesus</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26414</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522092353</id>
      <parentid>519636731</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T00:24:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>67.197.237.15</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Luke */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="64886">[[File:Noel-coypel-the-resurrection-of-christ-1700.jpg|thumb|right|Resurrection of Christ by [[Noel Coypel]], 1700, using a [[Resurrection of Jesus in Christian art|hovering depiction]] of Jesus.]] 

The '''resurrection of Jesus''' is the Christian belief that [[Jesus Christ]] returned to life on the Sunday following the Friday on which he was [[Crucifixion of Jesus|executed by crucifixion]]. It is a central tenet of [[Faith in Christianity|Christian faith]] and [[Christian theology|theology]] and part of the [[Nicene Creed]]: &quot;On the third day he rose again in accordance with the Scriptures&quot;. &lt;ref&gt;Updated version of the Nicene Creed added at [[First Council of Constantinople]] in 381 AD, in Norman Tanner, ''New Short History of the Catholic Church'', page 33 (Burns &amp; Oates, 2011). ISBN 978-0-86012-455-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Matthew Henry]] pointed out that [[Book of Hosea|Hosea]] 6:2 ''seems to have a further reference to the resurrection of Jesus Christ; and the time limited is is expressed by two days and the third day, that it may be a type and figure of Christ's rising on the third day, which he is said to do according to the scriptures, according to this scripture; for all the prophets testified of the sufferings of Christ and the glory that should follow''.&quot; From, Dr Robert A. Morey, ''The Bible, Natural Theology and Natural Law: Conflict Or Compromise?'', page 95 (Christian Scholars Press, 2010). ISBN 978-1-60957-143-6&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[New Testament]], after the Romans crucify Jesus, he is [[Entombment of Christ|anointed and buried in a new tomb]] by [[Joseph of Arimathea]] but God raises him from the dead&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Acts|2:24}}, {{bibleref2|Romans|10:9}},  {{bibleref2|1Cor|15:15}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|2:31–32}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|3:15}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|3:26}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|4:10}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|5:30}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|10:40–41}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|13:30}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|13:34}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|13:37}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|17:30–31}}, {{bibleref2|1Cor|6:14}}, {{bibleref2|2Cor|4:14}}, {{bibleref2|Gal|1:1}}, {{bibleref2|Eph|1:20}}, {{bibleref2|Col|2:12}}, {{bibleref2|1Thess|1:10}}, {{bibleref2|Heb|13:20}}, {{bibleref2|1Pet|1:3}}, {{bibleref2|1Pet|1:21}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he [[Resurrection appearances of Jesus|appears to many people]] over a span of forty days before his [[Ascension of Christ|ascension to Heaven]], to [[Session of Christ|sit]] at the [[Right Hand of God]]. Christians celebrate the [[resurrection]] of Jesus on [[Easter Sunday]], the third day after [[Good Friday]], the day of his crucifixion. [[Computus|Easter's date]] corresponds roughly with [[Passover]], the Jewish observance associated with [[the Exodus]], that is fixed for the night of the [[Full moon]] near the time of the [[equinox]]. &lt;ref&gt;Tamara Prosic, ''The Development And Symbolism Of Passover Until 70 CE'', page 65 (T &amp; T Clark International, 2004).
 ISBN 0-8264-7087-4&lt;/ref&gt;

The resurrection story appears in more than five locations in the [[Christian Bible|Bible]]. In several episodes in the [[Four Gospels]] Jesus [[Jesus predicts his death|foretells his coming death]] and resurrection, which he states is the plan of [[God the Father]].&lt;ref&gt;''Dictionary of Premillennial Theology'' by Mal Couch 1997 ISBN 0-8254-2410-0 page 127&lt;/ref&gt; Christians view the resurrection of Jesus as part of the plan of [[Salvation (Christianity)|salvation]] and [[Redeemer (Christianity)|redemption]] by [[Atonement in Christianity|atonement for man's sin]].&lt;ref&gt;''Great Preaching on the Resurrection'' by Curtis Hutson 2000 ISBN 0-87398-319-X pages 55-56&lt;/ref&gt; There are other accounts of the death of Jesus, notably in the [[Judaism's view of Jesus|Jewish]] and [[Jesus in Islam|Islamic]] traditions. Not all of these accounts include the resurrection.

Skeptical scholars have questioned the historicity of the resurrection story for centuries; for example, &quot;nineteenth- and early-twentieth-century biblical scholarship dismissed resurrection narratives as late, legendary accounts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Empty Tomb: Jesus Beyond the Grave  |editor1-first=  Robert M.|editor1-last= Price|editor1-link= Robert M. Price |editor2-first=  Jeffrey Jay|editor2-last= Lowder| year= 2005|publisher= Prometheus Books|location= Amherst|isbn= 1-59102-286-X|pages= front flap}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of contemporary scholars express doubts about the historicity of the resurrection accounts and have debated their origin,&lt;ref&gt;Michael Martin &quot;Skeptical Perspectives on Jesus' Resurrection&quot; chapter 18 in ''The Blackwell Companion to Jesus'' edited by Delbert Burkett 2011 ISBN 978-1-4443-2794-6&lt;/ref&gt; and some other scholars consider the biblical accounts of Jesus' resurrection as derived from the experiences of Jesus' followers and of [[Apostle Paul]].&lt;ref name = &quot;ActJJesus&quot;&gt;[[Robert W. Funk|Funk, Robert W.]] and the [[Jesus Seminar]]. ''The acts of Jesus: the search for the authentic deeds of Jesus.'' HarperSanFrancisco. 1998. &quot;What do we really know about Jesus&quot; p. 527–534.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Sanders 15&quot;&gt;Sanders, E. P. The historical figure of Jesus. Penguin, 1993. Epilogue: the resurrection. p. 276–281.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Death of Jesus}}
==New Testament Events==
In the [[New Testament]] there are three groups of events that surround the death and resurrection of Jesus: ''[[Crucifixion of Jesus|Crucifixion and burial]]'': wherein Jesus is placed in a new tomb following his death, ''[[Empty Tomb|discovery of the empty tomb]]'' and the ''[[Resurrection appearances of Jesus|resurrection appearances]]''. The New Testament does not include an account of the &quot;moment of resurrection&quot; and in the [[Eastern Church]] icons do not depict that moment, but show the [[Myrrhbearers]], and depict scenes of salvation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stagg2&quot;&gt;Stagg, Evalyn and Frank. ''Woman in the World of Jesus.'' Philadelphia: Westminster Press, 1978, p. 144–150.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vladimir Lossky, 1982 ''The Meaning of Icons'' ISBN 978-0-913836-99-6 page 185&lt;/ref&gt;

===Burial===
{{Main|Entombment of Christ}}
All four Gospels state that, on the evening of the crucifixion, [[Joseph of Arimathea]] asked Pilate for the body of Jesus, and that, after Pilate granted his request, he wrapped Jesus' body in a [[Shroud of Turin|linen cloth]] and [[Descent from the Cross|laid it]] in a [[Tomb of Jesus|tomb]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Matthew|15:57–61|TNIV}}, {{bibleref2|Mark|15:42–47|TNIV}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|23:50–56|TNIV}}, {{bibleref2|John|19:38–42|TNIV}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was in accordance with [[613 Commandments|Mosaic Law]], which stated that a person hanged on a tree must not be allowed to remain there at night, but should be buried before sundown.&lt;ref&gt;R. E. Brown, ''The Virginal Conception and Bodily Resurrection of Jesus'' (New York: Paulist Press, 1973) pp. 147; cf. {{bibleref2|Deuteronomy|21:22–23|TNIV}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Pologenie vo grob.jpg|thumb|left|[[Epitaphion|''Lamentation at the Tomb'']], 15th century.]]
In Matthew, Joseph was identified as &quot;also a [[Disciple (Christianity)|disciple]] of Jesus;&quot; in Mark he was identified as &quot;a respected member of the council ([[Sanhedrin]]) who was also himself looking for the [[Kingdom of God]];&quot; in Luke he was identified as &quot;a member of the council, good and righteous, who did not consent to their purpose or deed, and who was looking for the Kingdom of God'&quot; and in John he was identified as &quot;a disciple of Jesus.&quot;

The [[Gospel of Mark]] states that when Joseph asked for Jesus' body, Pilate was shocked that Jesus was already dead, and he summoned a centurion to confirm this before dispatching the body to Joseph. John recorded that Joseph was assisted in the burial process by [[Nicodemus]], who brought a mixture of myrrh and aloes and included these spices in the burial cloth as per Jewish customs.

===Death state of Christ during the 3 days===
{{see also|Intermediate state}}
The following are further New Testament comments on the death of Christ and resurrection after his time in the tomb:

The apostle Peter delivers a sermon fifty days after the resurrection in which he states: &quot;Brothers, I can tell you confidently that the patriarch David died and was buried, and his tomb is here to this day. But he was a prophet and knew that God had promised him on oath that he would place one of his descendants on his throne. Seeing what was ahead, ''he spoke of the resurrection of the Christ, that he was not abandoned to the grave, nor did his body see decay. God has raised this Jesus to life, and we are all witnesses of the fact.''&quot;{{Bibleref2c|Acts|2:29-31}}

As written in the [[Book of Revelation]]: &quot;When I saw him, I fell at his feet as though dead. Then he placed his right hand on me and said: 'Do not be afraid. I am the First and the Last. I am the Living One; '''I was dead''' (Greek ''egonomen nekros''), and behold '''I am alive for ever and ever!''' And I hold the keys of death and Hades.&quot;{{Bibleref2c|Rev.|1:17-18}}

[[1 Peter]] also states: &quot;It is better, if it is God's will, to suffer for doing good than for doing evil. ''For Christ died for sins once for all'', the righteous for the unrighteous, to bring you to God. ''He was put to death in the body but made alive by the Spirit'', through whom also he went and preached to the spirits in prison.&quot; (i.e., He descended into [[Hades]] after his death),{{Bibleref2c|1Peter|3:18-20|ESV|1 Pet 3:18-20}} which describes Jesus as preaching to the &quot;spirits in prison who disobeyed long ago&quot;.

This passage, along with the phrase in 1 Peter that God did &quot;not leave his soul in Hades,&quot;{{Bibleref2c|Acts|2:31}} is the theological basis behind the statement &quot;He descended into Hades&quot; in the [[Apostles' Creed]]. The death state of Christ was considered by theologians such as [[Thomas Aquinas]] and related in traditions such as the [[Harrowing of Hell]].

===Tomb discovery===
{{Main|Empty tomb|Myrrhbearers}}
[[File:Fra Angelico 019.jpg|thumb|Women at the empty tomb, by [[Fra Angelico]], 1437-1446.]]
Although no single Gospel gives an inclusive or definitive account of the resurrection of Jesus or his appearances, there are four points at which all four Gospels converge:&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Mark|16:1–8|TNIV}}, {{bibleref2|Matthew|28:1–8|TNIV}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|24:1–12|TNIV}}, and {{bibleref2|John|20:1–13|TNIV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

# Attention to the stone that had closed the tomb 
# The linking of the empty tomb tradition and the visit of the women on &quot;the first day of the week;&quot;
# That the risen Jesus chose first to appear to women (or a woman) and to commission them (her) to proclaim this most important fact to the disciples, including Peter and the other apostles;
# The prominence of [[Mary Magdalene]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Stagg2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Setzer, Claudia. &quot;Excellent Women: Female Witness to the Resurrection.&quot; ''Journal of Biblical Literature,'' Vol. 116, No. 2 (Summer, 1997), pp. 259–272&lt;/ref&gt; 

Variants have to do with the precise time the women visited the tomb, the number and identity of the women; the purpose of their visit; the appearance of the messenger(s)—angelic or human; their message to the women; and the response of the women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stagg2&quot; /&gt;

All four Gospels report that women were the ones to find the tomb of Jesus empty, although the number varies from one ([[Mary Magdalene]]) to an unspecified number. According to Mark and Luke, the ''announcement'' of Jesus' resurrection was first made to women. According to Matthew and John, Jesus actually ''appeared'' first to women (in Mark 16:9 and John 20:14 to Mary Magdalene alone).&lt;ref name=&quot;Stagg2&quot; /&gt; &quot;Whereas others found woman not qualified or authorized to teach, the four Gospels have it that the risen Christ commissioned women to proclaim to men, including Peter and the other apostles, the resurrection, foundation of Christianity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stagg2&quot; /&gt;

In the Gospels, especially the [[Synoptic Gospels|synoptics]], women play a central role as eyewitness at Jesus' death, entombment, and in the discovery of the empty tomb. All three synoptics repeatedly make women the subject of verbs of seeing,&lt;ref&gt;Richard Bauckham, ''Jesus and the Eyewitnesses'' (Eerdmans Publishing Company: Cambridge, 2006), p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; clearly presenting them as eyewitnesses.&lt;ref&gt;B. Gerhardsson, 'Mark and the Female Witnesses', in H. Behrens, D. Loding, and M. T. Roth, eds., ''Dumu-E2-Dub-Ba-A'' (A. W. Sjöberg FS; Occasional Papers of the Samuel Noah Kramer Fund 11; Philadelphia: The University Museum, 1989), pp. 219–220, 222–223; S. Byrskog, ''Story as History—History as Story'' (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum Neuen Testament Jerusalem Talmud 123; Tübingen: Mohr, 2000; remprinted Leiden: Brill, 2002), pp. 75–78; Richard Bauckham, ''Jesus and the Eyewitnesses'' (Eerdmans Publishing Company: Cambridge, 2006), p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Resurrection appearances of Jesus===
{{Main|Resurrection appearances of Jesus}}

After the discovery of the empty tomb, the Gospels indicate that Jesus made a series of appearances to the disciples. These include the appearance to the disciples in the [[Cenacle|upper room]], where [[Thomas (apostle)|Thomas]] did not believe until he was invited to put his finger into the holes in Jesus' hands and side;{{bibleref2c|John|20:24–29||Jn 20:24-29}} the ''[[Road to Emmaus appearance]]'';{{bibleref2c|Luke|24:13–32||Lk 24:13-32}} and beside the [[Sea of Galilee]] to encourage [[Saint Peter|Peter]] to serve his followers.{{bibleref2c|Jn|21:1–23}} His final appearance is reported as being forty days after the resurrection [[Ascension of Jesus Christ|when he ascended]] into [[heaven]]{{bibleref2c|Lk|24:44–49}} where he remains with God the Father and God the Holy Spirit until the [[Second Coming of Christ]].

Soon after, on the [[road to Damascus]], [[Paul of Tarsus]] converted to Christianity based on a vision of Jesus and later, became one of Christianity's foremost [[missionary|missionaries]] and theologians.{{bibleref2c|1Cor|15:6||1 Cor 15:6}}

==Christian tradition==
[[File:Turin plasch.jpg|thumb|[[Secondo Pia]]'s 1898 negative of the image on the [[Shroud of Turin]] has an appearance suggesting a positive image. It is used as part of the devotion to [[Holy Face of Jesus]].]]
The resurrection of Jesus has long been central to Christian faith and appears within diverse elements of the Christian tradition, from feasts to artistic depictions to religious relics. In Christian teachings, the sacraments derive their saving power from the passion and resurrection of Christ, upon which the salvation of the world entirely depends.&lt;ref&gt;''The encyclopedia of Christianity, Volume 5'' by Erwin Fahlbusch, Jan Milic Lochman, Geoffrey William Bromiley, John Mbiti 2008 ISBN 0-8028-2417-X page 490&lt;/ref&gt;

An example of the interweaving of the teachings on the resurrection with Christian relics is the application of the concept of &quot;miraculous image formation&quot; at the moment of resurrection to the [[Shroud of Turin]].  Christian authors have stated the belief that the body around whom the shroud was wrapped was not merely human, but divine, and that the image on the shroud was miraculously produced at the moment of resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;Charles S. Brown, 2007 ''Bible &quot;Mysteries&quot; Explained'' ISBN 0-9582813-0-0 page 193&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Rinaldi 1972, ''The man in the Shroud'' ISBN 0-86007-010-7 page 45&lt;/ref&gt; Quoting [[Pope Paul VI]]'s statement that the shroud is &quot;the wonderful document of His Passion, Death and Resurrection, written for us in letters of blood&quot; author Antonio Cassanelli argues that the shroud is a deliberate divine record of the five stages of the Passion of Christ, created at the moment of resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;Antonio Cassanelli, 2001 ''The Holy Shroud: a comparison between the Gospel narrative of the five stages of the Passion'' ISBN 0-85244-351-X page 13&lt;/ref&gt;

===Easter===
{{Main|Easter}}
Easter, the preeminent feast that celebrates the resurrection of Jesus, is clearly the earliest Christian festival.&lt;ref&gt;''Foundations of Christian Worship'' by Susan J. White 2006 ISBN 0-664-22924-7 page 55&lt;/ref&gt; Since the earliest Christian times, it has focused on the [[Redemption (theology)|redemptive act]] of God in the death and resurrection of Christ.&lt;ref&gt;''Mercer dictionary of the Bible'' by Watson E. Mills, Roger Aubrey Bullard 1998 ISBN 0-86554-373-9 page 224&lt;/ref&gt;

Easter is linked to the [[Passover]] and [[Exodus from Egypt]] recorded in the [[Old Testament]] through the [[Last Supper]] and [[Passion (Christianity)|crucifixion]] that preceded the resurrection. According to the New Testament, Jesus gave the Passover meal a new meaning, as he [[Jesus predicts his death|prepared himself and his disciples]]  for his death in the [[Cenacle|upper room]] during the Last Supper. He identified the loaf of bread and cup of wine as symbolizing [[Body of Christ|his body]] soon to be sacrificed and [[Blood of Christ|his blood]] soon to be shed. {{bibleref2|1co|5:7|NIV|1 Corinthians|5:7}} states, &quot;Get rid of the old yeast that you may be a new batch without yeast—as you really are. For Christ, our Passover lamb, has been sacrificed&quot;; this refers to the Passover requirement to have no yeast in the house and to the allegory of Jesus as the [[Lamb of God|Paschal lamb]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2||John|1:29}}, {{bibleref2||Revelation|5:6}}, {{bibleref2|1Pe|1:19||1 Peter 1:19}}, {{bibleref2|1Pe|1:2||1 Peter 1:2}}, and the associated notes and Passion Week table in {{Cite book|editor=Barker, Kenneth|title=Zondervan NIV Study Bible|publisher=[[Zondervan]]|location=[[Grand Rapids]]|year=2002|isbn=0-310-92955-5|page=1520}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Resurrection and Redemption===
In the teachings of the [[Apostolic Age|apostolic Church]], the resurrection was seen as heralding a [[World to Come|new era]]. Forming a theology of the resurrection fell to [[Apostle Paul]]. It was not enough for Paul to simply repeat elementary teachings, but as {{bibleref2|Hebrews|6:1|NIV}} states, &quot;go beyond the initial teachings about Christ and advance to maturity&quot;. Fundamental to Pauline theology is the connection between Christ's Resurrection and [[Redemption (theology)|redemption]].&lt;ref&gt;''The creed: the apostolic faith in contemporary theology'' by Berard L. Marthaler 2007 ISBN 0-89622-537-2 page 361&lt;/ref&gt; Paul explained the importance of the resurrection of Jesus as the cause and basis of the hope of Christians to share a similar experience in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/1 Corinthians#15|1 Corinthians 15:20-22]].

[[File:Nicaea icon.jpg|thumb|[[Constantine I|Emperor Constantine]] and [[bishop]]s with the [[Niceno-Constantinopolitan Creed|Creed of 381]].]]
The teachings of [[Apostle Paul]] formed a key element of the Christian tradition and theology. If the cross stands at the center of Paul's theology, so does the Resurrection: unless the one died the death of ''all'', the ''all'' would have little to celebrate in the resurrection of the one.&lt;ref&gt;''Theology of Paul the Apostle'' by James D. G. Dunn 2003 ISBN page 235&lt;/ref&gt; Paul taught that, just as Christians share in Jesus' death in baptism, so they will share in his resurrection&lt;ref name = &quot;Ehrman 2006&quot;/&gt; for Jesus was designated the [[Son of God]] by his resurrection.{{bibleref2c|Rom|1:4}}&lt;ref name = &quot;Ehrman 2006&quot;&gt;Ehrman, Bart. Peter, Paul, and Mary Magdalene: The Followers of Jesus in History and Legend. Oxford University Press, USA. 2006. ISBN 0-19-530013-0&lt;/ref&gt; In [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/1 Corinthians#15|1 Corinthians 15:20-22]] Paul states:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
But Christ really has been raised from the dead. He is the first of all those who will rise. Death came because of what a man did. Rising from the dead also comes because of what a man did. Because of Adam, all people die. So because of Christ, all will be made alive.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The [[Apostolic Fathers]], discussed the death and resurrection of Jesus, including [[Ignatius of Antioch|Ignatius]] (50−115),&lt;ref&gt;Ignatius makes many passing references, but two extended discussions are found in the [[Letter to the Trallians]] and the [[Letter to the Smyrnaeans]].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Polycarp]] (69−155), and [[Justin Martyr]] (100−165). Following the [[Constantine I and Christianity|conversion of Constantine]] and the liberating [[Edict of Milan]] in 313, the [[First seven Ecumenical Councils|ecumenical councils]] of the 4th, 5th and 6th centuries, that focused on [[Christology]] helped shape the Christian understanding of the redemptive nature of Resurrection, and influenced both the development of its iconography, and its use within Liturgy.&lt;ref&gt;''The Resurrection and the icon'' by Michel Quenot 1998 ISBN 0-88141-149-3 page 72&lt;/ref&gt;

Belief in bodily resurrection was a constant note of the Christian church in antiquity. And nowhere was it argued for more strongly than in North Africa. [[Saint Augustine]] accepted it at the time of his conversion in 386.&lt;ref&gt;''Augustine: ancient thought baptized'' by John M. Rist 1996 ISBN 0-521-58952-5 page 110&lt;/ref&gt; Augustine defended Resurrection, and argued that given that Christ has risen, there is [[Resurrection of the Dead]].&lt;ref&gt;''Augustine and the Catechumenate'' by William Harmless 1995 ISBN 0-8146-6132-7 page 131&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Augustine De doctrina Christiana'' by Saint Augustine, R. P. H. Green 1996 ISBN 0-19-826334-1 page 115&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, he argued that the death and resurrection of Jesus was for the salvation of man, stating: &quot;to achieve each resurrection of ours, the savior paid with his single life, and he pre-enacted and presented his one and only one by way of sacrament and by way of model.&lt;ref&gt;''The Trinity'' by Saint Augustine (Bishop of Hippo.), Edmund Hill, John E. Rotelle 1991 ISBN 0-911782-96-6 page 157&lt;/ref&gt;

The 5th century theology of [[Theodore of Mopsuestia]] provides an insight into the development of the Christian understanding of the redemptive nature of Resurrection. The crucial role of the sacraments in the mediation of salvation was well accepted at the time. In Theodore's representation of the [[Eucharist]], the sacrificial and salvific elements are combined in the &quot;One who saved us and delivered us by the sacrifice of Himself&quot;. Theodore's interpretation of the Eucharistic rite is directed towards the triumph over the power of death brought about by the Resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;''Adventus Domini: eschatological thought in 4th-century apses and catecheses'' by Geir Hellemo 1997 ISBN 90-04-08836-9 page 231&lt;/ref&gt;

The emphasis on the salvific nature of the Resurrection continued in Christian theology in the next centuries, e.g., in the 8th century Saint [[John of Damascus]] wrote that: &quot;...When he had freed those who were bound from the beginning of time, Christ returned again from among the dead, having opened for us the way to resurrection&quot; and Christian iconography of the ensuing years represented that concept.&lt;ref&gt;Vladimir Lossky, 1982 ''The Meaning of Icons'' ISBN 978-0-913836-99-6 page 189&lt;/ref&gt;

===Depictions of the Resurrection===
{{Main|Resurrection of Jesus in Christian art}}
[[File:Anastasis Pio Christiano Inv31525.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Chi Rho]] with a wreath symbolizing the victory of the Resurrection, above Roman soldiers, ca. 350.]]
In the [[Catacombs]] of Rome, artists just hinted at the Resurrection by using images from the Old Testament such as  the fiery furnace and Daniel in the Lion's den. Depictions prior to the 7th century generally used secondary events such as the [[Myrrhbearers]] at the tomb of Jesus to convey the concept of the Resurrection. An early symbol of the resurrection was the wreathed [[Chi Rho]], whose origin traces to the victory of [[emperor Constantine I]] at the [[Battle of the Milvian Bridge]] in 312, which he attributed to the use of a cross on the shields of his soldiers. Constantine used the Chi Rho on his standard and his coins showed a [[labarum]] with the Chi Rho killing a serpent.&lt;ref&gt;''Understanding early Christian art'' by Robin Margaret Jensen 2000 ISBN 0-415-20454-2 page 149&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of a wreath around the Chi Rho symbolizes the victory of the Resurrection over death, and is an early visual representations of the connection between the [[Crucifixion of Jesus]] and his triumphal resurrection, as seen in the 4th century [http://www1.georgetown.edu/centers/liturgy/envisionchurch/40399.html sarcophagus of Domitilla] in Rome. Here, in the wreathed [[Chi Rho]] the death and resurrection of Christ are shown as inseparable, and the Resurrection is not merely a happy ending tucked at the end of the life of Christ on earth. Given the use of similar symbols on the [[Aquila (Roman)|Roman standard]], this depiction also conveyed another victory, namely that of the Christian faith: the Roman soldiers who had once arrested Jesus and marched him to [[Calvary]] now walked under the banner of a resurrected Christ.&lt;ref&gt;''The passion in art'' by Richard Harries 2004 ISBN 0-7546-5011-1 page 8&lt;/ref&gt;

The cosmic significance of the Resurrection in Western theology goes back to [[Saint Ambrose]] who in the 4th century said that &quot;In Christ the world has risen, heaven has risen, the earth has risen&quot;. However, this theme was only developed later in Western theology and art. It was, a different matter in the East where the Resurrection was linked to redemption, and the renewal and rebirth of the whole world from a much earlier period. In art this was symbolized by combining the depictions of the Resurrection with the [[Harrowing of Hell]] in icons and paintings. A good example is from the [[Chora Church]] in Istanbul, where [[John the Baptist]], [[Solomon]] and other figures are also present, depicting that Christ was not alone in the resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;''Images of redemption: art, literature and salvation'' by Patrick Sherry 2005 ISBN 0-567-08891-X page 73&lt;/ref&gt; The depiction sequence at the 10th century [[Hosios Loukas]] shows Christ as he pulls Adam, followed by Eve from his tomb, signifying the salvation of humanity after the resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;''Heaven on Earth: art and the Church in Byzantium'' by Linda Safran 1998 ISBN 0-271-01670-1 page 133&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historicity and origin of the narrative==
{{Main|Historicity and origin of the Resurrection of Jesus}}

[[File:5part-icon.jpeg|thumb|5 part resurrection [[icon]], [[Solovetsky Monastery]], 17th century.]]
The earliest Christians [[kerygma|proclaimed]] Jesus as the risen Christ. The first Christians may be defined as those followers of Jesus who, after his crucifixion, proclaimed him as the risen lord.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ehrman 2006&quot;/&gt; The earliest Christian scriptures place Jesus' resurrection at the center of religious faith. The preaching and letters of [[Apostle Peter]] in the [[Acts of the Apostles]] and the [[Pauline Epistles|letters of Paul]] declared that Jesus died, was raised by God and the apostles are witnesses to this resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Acts|2:14-40}}; {{Bibleref2-nb|Ac|3:11-12}}; {{Bibleref2-nb|Ac|4:5-12}}; {{Bibleref2-nb|Ac|5:29-32}}; {{Bibleref2-nb|Ac|10:34-42}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Géza Vermes]] who considers the Resurrection one of the fundamental and intriguing concepts of the Christian faith has presented eight possible theories to explain the Resurrection of Jesus. These theories fall between two extremes, ranging from a total denial of the Resurrection to absolute belief in it. The six variants include the theft of the body, recovery from a coma and a spiritual non-bodily resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Resurrection: History and Myth |last= Vermes|first= Geza|year= 2008|publisher= Doubleday|location= New York|isbn= 978-0-7394-9969-6|page= xv}} Original in italics.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Resurrection: History and Myth |authorlink=Géza Vermes|last= Vermes|first= Geza|year= 2008|publisher= Doubleday|location= New York|isbn= 978-0-7394-9969-6|page= 141}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Vermes dismisses the &quot;two extremes&quot;, stating that they &quot;are not susceptible to rational judgment&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Resurrection: History and Myth |authorlink=Géza Vermes|last= Vermes|first= Geza|year= 2008|publisher= Doubleday|location= New York|isbn= 978-0-7394-9969-6|page= 141}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Various arguments against the historicity of the Resurrection have been presented, e.g. the number of other historical figures and gods with similar death and resurrection accounts.&lt;ref name=&quot;RMB 14&quot;&gt;[[Robert M. Price]], &quot;The Empty Tomb: Introduction; The Second Life of Jesus.&quot; In {{cite book |title= The Empty Tomb: Jesus Beyond the Grave  |editor1-first=  Robert M.|editor1-last= Price|editor1-link= Robert M. Price |editor2-first=  Jeffrey Jay|editor2-last= Lowder| year= 2005|publisher= Prometheus Books|location= Amherst|isbn= 1-59102-286-X|page= 14}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref label|C|c|none}} According to Peter Kirby, &quot;many scholars doubt the historicity of the empty tomb.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Kirby, &quot;The Case Against the Empty Tomb&quot;, In {{cite book |title= The Empty Tomb: Jesus Beyond the Grave  |editor1-first=  Robert M.|editor1-last= Price|editor1-link=  Robert M. Price |editor2-first=  Jeffrey Jay|editor2-last= Lowder| year= 2005|publisher= Prometheus Books|location= Amherst|isbn= 1-59102-286-X|page= 233}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref label|A|a|none}} However according to a survey done by [[Gary Habermas]]; 75% of both conservative and non-conservative New Testament scholars accept arguments in favor of the empty tomb.&lt;ref&gt;Gary Habermas Experiences of the Risen Jesus [http://www.garyhabermas.com/articles/dialog_rexperience/dialog_rexperiences.htm Link]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert M. Price]] claims that if the resurrection could, in fact, be proven through science or historical evidence, the event would lose its miraculous qualities.&lt;ref name=&quot;RMB 14&quot;/&gt; [[Helmut Koester]] writes that the stories of the resurrection were originally epiphanies and that the more detailed accounts of the resurrection are secondary and not based on historical records.&lt;ref&gt;Helmut Koester, ''Introduction to the New Testament, Vol. 2: History and Literature of Early Christianity.'' Walter de Gruyter, 2000. p. 64-65.&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to R. A. Burridge, the majority consensus among biblical scholars is that the genre of the Gospels is a kind of ancient biography and not myth.&lt;ref&gt;Burridge, R. A. (2006). Gospels. In J. W. Rogerson &amp; Judith M. Lieu (Eds) ''The Oxford Handbook of Biblical Studies.'' Oxford: Oxford University Press. p. 437&lt;/ref&gt; [[E.P. Sanders]] argues that a plot to foster belief in the Resurrection would probably have resulted in a more consistent story, and that some of those who were involved in the events gave their lives for their belief. &lt;ref&gt;&quot;Jesus Christ.&quot; Encyclopædia Britannica, 2007. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. 10 Jan. 2007&lt;/ref&gt; [[James D.G. Dunn]] has stated that, while the apostle Paul's resurrection experience was &quot;visionary in character&quot; and &quot;non-physical, non-material&quot;, the accounts in the Gospels are very different.&lt;ref&gt;James D.G. Dunn, ''Jesus and the Spirit: A Study of the Religious and Charismatic Experience of Jesus and the First Christians as Reflected in the New Testament.'' Eerdmans, 1997. p. 115, 117.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biblical accounts==
{{Christianity}}

===Background===
In 1st century BC, debates existed among Jewish religious groups. The [[Pharisees]] believed in [[Resurrection of the Dead#Judaism|Resurrection of the Dead]], and the [[Sadducee]]s did not. The Sadducees did not believe in an [[afterlife]], but the Pharisees believed in a literal resurrection of the body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last =Pecorino | first = Philip | title = Section 3. The Resurrection of the Body | work = Philosophy of Religion | publisher = Dr. Philip A. Pecorino | year = 2001 | url = http://www2.sunysuffolk.edu/pecorip/SCCCWEB/ETEXTS/PHIL_of_RELIGION_TEXT/CHAPTER_7_SOULS/Resurrection.htm | accessdate = 2007–09–13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sadducees, politically powerful religious leaders, rejected the afterlife, angels, and demons as well as the Pharisees oral law. The Pharisees, whose views became [[Rabbinic Judaism]], eventually won (or at least survived) this debate. The promise of a future resurrection appears in the Torah as well as in certain Jewish works, such as the [[Life of Adam and Eve]], ''c'' 100 BC, and the Pharisaic book [[2 Maccabees]], ''c'' 124 BC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harris&quot;&gt;[[Stephen L Harris|Harris, Stephen L.]], Understanding the Bible. Palo Alto: Mayfield. 1985.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Torah]], the Jewish scriptures and the [[Old Testament]] of the Bible, it was the promise of God to provide an eternal liberating king in the line of [[King David]] of Bethlehem.&lt;ref&gt;2 Samuel 7:12, Psalm 132:11, Psalm 89:3&lt;/ref&gt; [[Apostle Peter]] used this reasoning to argue for the significance of the resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;Acts 2:30&lt;/ref&gt; The Apostle Paul also connects Jesus' death and resurrection with a fulfilment of scripture.{{Bibleref2c|1Cor|15:3-4|NIV|1 Cor 15:3-4}}

===Paul's epistles===
The earliest written records of the death and resurrection of Jesus are the letters of Paul, which were written around two decades after the death of Jesus,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/religion/story/oral.html L. Michael White, ''Importance of the Oral Tradition'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barnett, Paul, ''The Birth Of Christianity: The First Twenty Years (After Jesus)''{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and show that within this time frame Christians believed that it had happened. Some scholars suppose that these contain early Christian [[creed]]s and creedal [[hymn]]s, which were included in several of the [[New Testament]] texts and that some of these creeds date to within a few years of Jesus' death and were developed within the [[Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem|Christian community in Jerusalem]].&lt;ref&gt;A basic text is that of Oscar Cullmann, available in English in a translation by J. K. S. Reid titled, ''The Earliest Christian Confessions'' (London: Lutterworth, 1949)&lt;/ref&gt; Though embedded within the texts of the New Testament, these creeds are a distinct source for early Christianity.

* {{bibleref2|Romans|1:3–4|NIV}}: &quot;...concerning his Son, who was descended from David according to the flesh and designated the Son of God in power according to the Spirit of holiness by his resurrection from the dead, Jesus Christ our Lord.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wolfhart Pannenberg, ''Jesus—God and Man'' translated Lewis Wilkins and Duane Pribe (Philadelphia: Westminster, 1968) pp. 118, 283, 367; Neufeld, ''The Earliest Christian Confessions'' (Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1964) pp. 7, 50; C. H. Dodd, ''The Apostolic Preaching and its Developments'' (Grand Rapids: Baker, 1980), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{bibleref2||2Tim|2:8|NIV|2 Timothy 2:8}}: &quot;Remember Jesus Christ, raised from the dead, this is my Gospel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bultmann, ''Theology of the New Testament'' vol 1, pp. 49, 81; Joachim Jeremias, ''The Eucharistic Words of Jesus'' translated Norman Perrin (London: SCM Press, 1966) p. 102&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{bibleref|1Cor|15:3–7|NIV|1 Corinthians 15:3-7}}: &quot;... that Christ died for our sins in accordance with the Scriptures, that he was buried, that he was raised on the third day in accordance with the Scriptures&quot;

These appearances include those to prominent members of Jesus' ministry and the later Jerusalem church, including [[James the brother of Jesus]] and the apostles, naming the [[Apostle Peter]] (Cephas). The creed also makes reference to appearances to unidentified individuals. According to the [[Acts of the Apostles]] and Paul's [[Letter to the Galatians]], he had contact with at least two of the named witnesses of the creed, James and Peter.{{Bibleref2c|Gal|1:18-20}}
[[Hans Von Campenhausen]] and [[A. M. Hunter]] have separately stated that the creed text passes high standards of historicity and reliability of origin.&lt;ref&gt;Hans Von Campenhausen, &quot;The Events of Easter and the Empty Tomb&quot;, in ''Tradition and Life in the Church'' (Philadelphia: Fortress, 1968) p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Archibald Hunter, ''Works and Words of Jesus'' (1973) p. 100&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gospel narratives===
====Mark====
Just after sunrise on the day after the Sabbath three women, Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of James, and Salome, come to anoint Jesus' body, wondering how they can roll the rock away from the tomb; but they find the rock already rolled aside and a young man in white inside; he tells them that Jesus is risen, and that they should tell Peter and the disciples that he will meet them in Galilee, &quot;just as he told you.&quot; The women run away and tell no-one.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Mark+16&amp;version=NIV Mark 16]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Matthew====
Just after sunrise on the day after the Sabbath two women, Mary Magdalene and &quot;the other Mary,&quot; came to look at the tomb. Accompanied by an earthquake, an angel comes down from Heaven and rolls the rock aside from the tomb. The angel tells them not to be afraid, but to tell the disciples that Jesus is risen and will meet them in Galilee. The women are joyful and set out to tell the disciples the good news, but Jesus appears and tells them not to be afraid, and tells them that he is risen and that they should tell the disciples that they will see him in Galilee. The disciples go to Galilee, where they see Jesus.

The soldiers guarding the tomb are terrified by the angel, and inform the chief priests; the priests and elders bribe them to spread a lie that the disciples have stolen the body, &quot;[a]nd this story has been widely circulated among the Jews to this very day.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew%2028&amp;version=NIV Matthew 28]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Luke====
Just after sunrise on the day after the Sabbath a number of women (Mary Magdalene, Joanna, and Mary the mother of James) come to anoint Jesus' body. They find the stone rolled away and the tomb empty. Suddenly two men stand beside them. The men tell them Jesus is risen. The women tell the disciples, but the disciples do not believe them, except for Peter who runs to the tomb. Peter finds the grave-clothes in the empty tomb and goes away, wondering.

The same day Jesus appears to two of his followers on the road to Emmaus. They fail to recognise him until he breaks bread and gives thanks, and he then vanishes. The two go at once to Jerusalem where they find the disciples exclaiming over Jesus' appearance to Peter. As they tell their story Jesus appears to them all. They are afraid, but he invites them to touch his body, eats with them, and explains the prophecies which are fulfilled in him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Luke+24&amp;version=NIV Luke 24]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Acts====
(The Acts of the Apostles is presented as a continuation of the Gospel of Luke)
Jesus appeared to the Apostles for forty days, giving many proofs that he was alive, and instructing them not to leave Jerusalem until they were baptised with the Holy Spirit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Acts+1&amp;version=NIV Acts 1]&lt;/ref&gt;

====John====
Early on the day after the Sabbath, before sunrise, Mary Magdalene visits the tomb and finds the stone rolled away. She tells Peter and &quot;the beloved disciple,&quot; who run to the tomb and find the grave-clothes, then go home. Mary sees two angels and then Jesus, whom she does not recognise. Jesus tells her to tell the disciples that he is ascending to the Father, and Mary tells the disciples she has seen the Lord.

That evening Jesus appears among them, despite locked doors, and gives them power over sin and forgiveness of sin. A week later he appears to [[doubting Thomas]], who has not believed, but when Thomas is instructed to touch the [[Holy Wounds|wounds of Jesus]] he says, &quot;My Lord and my God!&quot; Jesus replies: &quot;Because you have seen me, you have believed; blessed are those who have not seen and yet have believed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=John+20&amp;version=NIV John 20]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theological significance==
[[File:Resurrected Jesus two Maries.jpg|thumb|130px|left|Stained glass of Resurrection with two Marys at a [[St. Matthew's German Evangelical Lutheran Church|Lutheran Church]], South Carolina.]]

In Christian theology, the resurrection of Jesus is a foundation of the Christian faith.{{bibleref2c|1co|15:12-20||1 Cor 15:12-20}} {{bibleref2c|1Peter|1:3|HCSB|1 Pet 1:3}} Christians, through faith in the working of God{{bibleref2c|Colossians|2:12||Col 2:12}} are spiritually resurrected with Jesus, and are [[Redemption (theology)|redeemed]] so that they may walk in a new way of life.{{bibleref2c|Rom|6:4}} As [[Paul the Apostle]] stated: &quot;If Christ was not raised, then all our preaching is useless, and your trust in God is useless.&quot;{{bibleref2c|1Cor|15:14|NLT|1 Cor 15:14}} The death and resurrection of Jesus are the most important events in [[Christian Theology]]. They form the point in scripture where Jesus gives his ultimate demonstration that he has power over life and death, thus he has the ability to give people [[Eternal life (Christianity)|eternal life]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|John|3:16}}, {{bibleref2|John|5:24}}, {{bibleref2|John|6:39-40}}, {{bibleref2|John|6:47}}, {{bibleref2|John|10:10}}, {{bibleref2|John|11:25–26}}, and {{bibleref2|John|17:3}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Terry Miethe, a Christian philosopher at Oxford University, stated, &quot;&amp;thinsp;'Did Jesus rise from the dead?' is the most important question regarding the claims of the Christian faith.'&amp;thinsp;&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Terry Miethe in Did Jesus Rise from the Dead? The Resurrection Debate, ed. Terry Miethe (San Francisco: Harper and Rw,1987), xi. Quoted by [[Michael Martin (philosopher)|Michael Martin]], &quot;The Resurrection as Initially Improbable.&quot; In  {{cite book |title= The Empty Tomb: Jesus Beyond the Grave  |editor1-first=  Robert M.|editor1-last= Price|editor1-link=  Robert M. Price |editor2-first=  Jeffrey Jay|editor2-last= Lowder| year= 2005|publisher= Prometheus Books|location= Amherst|isbn= 1-59102-286-X|page= 44}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[Bible]], &quot;God raised him from the dead,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Acts|2:24}}, {{bibleref2|Romans|10:9}}, {{bibleref2|1Cor|15:15|1 Corinthians 15:15}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|2:31–32}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|3:15}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|3:26}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|4:10}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|5:30}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|10:40–41}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|13:30}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|13:34}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|13:37}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|17:30–31}}, {{bibleref2|1Cor|6:14|1 Corinthians 6:14}}, {{bibleref2|2Cor|4:14|2 Corinthians 4:14}}, {{bibleref2|Gal|1:1}}, {{bibleref2|Eph|1:20}}, {{bibleref2|Col|2:12}}, {{bibleref2|1Thess|1:10}}, {{bibleref2|Heb|13:20}}, {{bibleref2|1|Pet|1:3||1 Peter 1:3}}, {{bibleref2|1Pet|1:21|NIV|1 Pet 1:21}}&lt;/ref&gt; he [[Ascension of Jesus Christ|ascended to heaven]], to the &quot;[[Session of Christ|right hand of God]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleref2|Mark|16:19}}, {{bibleref2|Luke|22:69}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|2:33}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|5:31}}, {{bibleref2|Acts|7:55–56}}, {{bibleref2|Romans|8:34}}, {{bibleref2|Eph|1:20}}, {{bibleref2|Col|3:1}}, {{bibleref2|Hebrews|1:3}}, {{bibleref2|Hebrews|1:13}}, {{bibleref2|Hebrews|10:12}}, {{bibleref2|Hebrews|12:2}}, {{bibleref2|1Pe|3:22|NIV|1 Pet|3:22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and will [[Second Coming|return again]]{{bibleref2c|Acts|1:9–11}} to fulfill the rest of [[Messianic prophecy]] such as the [[Resurrection of the dead]], the [[Last Judgment]] and establishment of the [[Kingdom of God]]; see also [[Messianism]] and [[Messianic Age]].&lt;ref&gt;The ‘‘Parousia’‘ is the term used in the Bible, see [http://www.blueletterbible.org/cgi-bin/strongs.pl?strongs=3952 Strong's G3952] for details, which includes the [[Joseph Henry Thayer|Thayer's]] Lexicon definition: &quot;In the N.T. especially of ''the advent'', i.e.,the future, visible, ''return'' from heaven of Jesus, the Messiah, to raise the dead, hold the last judgment, and set up formally and gloriously the kingdom of God.&quot; According to the [[Bauer lexicon]]: &quot;of Christ, and nearly always of his Messianic Advent in glory to judge the world at the end of this age.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Some modern scholars use the belief of Jesus' followers in the resurrection as a point of departure for establishing the continuity of the historical Jesus and the proclamation of the [[early church]].&lt;ref&gt;Reginald H. Fuller, ''[[The Foundations of New Testament Christology]]'' (New York: Scribners, 1965), p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carl Jung]] suggests that the crucifixion-resurrection account was the forceful spiritual symbol of, literally, God-as-[[Yahweh]] becoming God-as-[[Job (Biblical figure)|Job]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Carl Jung|Jung, Carl]], ''[[The Answer to Job]]'' [http://jmm.aaa.net.au/articles/4801.htm online excerpt]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Apostle Paul]] wrote that: &quot;If there is no resurrection of the dead, then Christ has not been raised; if Christ has not been raised, then our preaching is in vain and your faith is in vain...If Christ has not been raised, your faith is futile&quot;. (I Cor 15:13–14, 17).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Resurrection: History and Myth |last= Vermes|first= Geza|year= 2008|publisher= Doubleday|location= New York|isbn= 978-0-7394-9969-6|page= xv}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Many scholars have contended that in discussion on the resurrection, Apostle Paul refers to a rabbinic style transmission of an early authoritative tradition that he received and has passed on to the church at Corinth. For this and other reasons, it is widely believed that this creed is of pre-Pauline origin.&lt;ref&gt;Neufeld, ''The Earliest Christian Confessions'' (Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1964) p. 47; Reginald Fuller, ''The Formation of the Resurrection Narratives'' (New York: Macmillan, 1971) p. 10; Wolfhart Pannenberg, ''Jesus—God and Man'' translated Lewis Wilkins and Duane Pribe (Philadelphia: Westminster, 1968) p. 90; Oscar Cullmann, ''The Earlychurch: Studies in Early Christian History and Theology'', ed. A. J. B. Higgins (Philadelphia: Westminster, 1966) p. 64; Hans Conzelmann, ''1 Corinthians'', translated James W. Leitch (Philadelphia: Fortress 1969) p. 251; Bultmann, ''Theology of the New Testament'' vol. 1 pp. 45, 80–82, 293; R. E. Brown, ''The Virginal Conception and Bodily Resurrection of Jesus'' (New York: Paulist Press, 1973) pp. 81, 92&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Most Fellows of the Jesus Seminar concluded that this tradition dates to before Paul's conversion, ''c'' AD 33. [[Robert W. Funk|Funk, Robert W.]] and the [[Jesus Seminar]]. ''The acts of Jesus: the search for the authentic deeds of Jesus.'' HarperSanFrancisco. 1998. &quot;Empty Tomb, Appearances &amp; Ascension&quot; p. 449-495.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Geza Vermes]] writes that the creed is &quot;a tradition he [Paul] has inherited from his seniors in the faith concerning the death, burial and resurrection of Jesus&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Geza Vermes (2008) ''The Resurrection''. London, Penguin: 121-2&lt;/ref&gt;  The creed's ultimate origins are within the Jerusalem apostolic community having been formalised and passed on within a few years of the resurrection.&lt;ref&gt;see Wolfhart Pannenberg, ''Jesus—God and Man'' translated Lewis Wilkins and Duane Pribe (Philadelphia: Westminster, 1968) p. 90; Oscar Cullmann, ''The Early church: Studies in Early Christian History and Theology'', ed. A. J. B. Higgins (Philadelphia: Westminster, 1966) p. 66–66; R. E. Brown, ''The Virginal Conception and Bodily Resurrection of Jesus'' (New York: Paulist Press, 1973) pp. 81; Thomas Sheehan, ''First Coming: How the Kingdom of God Became Christianity'' (New York: Random House, 1986) pp. 110, 118; Ulrich Wilckens, ''Resurrection'' translated A. M. Stewart (Edinburgh: Saint Andrew, 1977) p. 2; Hans Grass, ''Ostergeschen und Osterberichte'', Second Edition (Gottingen: Vandenhoeck und Ruprecht, 1962) p. 96; Grass favors the origin in Damascus.&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Barnett writes that this creedal formula, and others, were variants of the &quot;one basic early tradition that Paul &quot;received&quot; in Damascus from Ananias in about 34 [CE]&quot; after his conversion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul Barnett 2009&quot;&gt;Paul Barnett, ''Finding the Historical Christ'' (After Jesus Volume 3), Eerdmans, 2009. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;But Christ really has been raised from the dead. He is the first of all those who will rise. Death came because of what a man did. Rising from the dead also comes because of what a man did. Because of Adam, all people die. So because of Christ, all will be made alive.&lt;ref&gt;(as in [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/1 Corinthians#15:22|1 Corinthians 15:20-22]])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Paul's views went against the thoughts of the Greek philosophers to whom a bodily resurrection meant a new imprisonment in a corporeal body, which was what they wanted to avoid; given that for them the corporeal and the material fettered the spirit.&lt;ref&gt;''Meditation and Piety in the Far East'' by Karl Ludvig Reichelt, Sverre Holth 2004 ISBN 0-227-17235-3 page 30&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, Paul believed that the newly resurrected body would be a heavenly body; immortal, glorified, powerful and pneumatic in contrast to an earthly body, which is mortal, dishonored, weak and psychic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+Corinthians+15%3A42-49&amp;version=NIV Corinthians 15:42-49] with commentary by Dale B. Martin, ''The Corinthian Body'', Yale University Press, 1999. ISBN 0-300-08172-3 p. 126 in particular.&lt;/ref&gt; According to theologian [[Peter Carnley]], the resurrection of Jesus was different from the [[Resurrection of Lazarus]] as: &quot;In the case of Lazarus, the stone was rolled away so that he could walk out.... the raised Christ didn't have to have the stone rolled away, because he is transformed and can appear anywhere, at any time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rn/nationalinterest/stories/2000/121991.htm National Interest - Archbishop Peter Carnley]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to international scholar Thorwald Lorenzen, the first Easter led to a shift in emphasis from faith &quot;in God&quot; to faith &quot;in Christ.&quot; Today, Lorenzen finds &quot;a strange silence about the resurrection in many pulpits.&quot; He writes that among some Christians, ministers and professors, it seems to have to have become &quot;a cause for embarrassment or the topic of apologetics.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lorenzen&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|pp.3-4}} It has been argued that many Christians neglect the resurrection because of their understandable pre-occupation with the Cross.&lt;ref name=&quot;Warnock&quot;&gt;Warnock, Adrian Raised With Christ, Crossway 2010 http://raisedwithchrist.net&lt;/ref&gt; However, the belief in Jesus' physical resurrection remains the single doctrine most accepted by Christians of all denominational backgrounds.

Groups such as [[Jews]], [[Muslims]], [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]]s, and other non-Christians, as well as some [[Liberal Christianity|liberal Christians]], dispute whether Jesus actually rose from the dead. Arguments over death and resurrection claims occur at many religious [[debate]]s and [[interfaith|interfaith dialogues]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lorenzen&quot;&gt;Lorenzen, Thorwald. ''Resurrection, Discipleship, Justice: Affirming the Resurrection of Jesus Christ Today.'' Macon, Georgia: Smyth &amp; Helwys, 2003, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gnostics==
[[Gnosticism|Gnostics]] did not believe in a literal physical resurrection. &quot;For the gnostic any resurrection of the dead was excluded from the outset; the flesh or substance is destined to perish. 'There is no resurrection of the flesh, but only of the soul', say the so-called [[Archontics]], a late gnostic group in Palestine.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Kurt Rudolph, ''Gnosis: The Nature &amp; History of Gnosticism'', page 190 (T &amp; T Clark Ltd, 1970, second and expanded edition, 1980; 1998). ISBN 0-567-08640-2 &lt;/ref&gt;

==Non-Christian views==
Some other religions include their own descriptions of Jesus which may not include his resurrection.

[[File:Holy sepulchre exterior.jpg|thumb|The [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]] now occupies the traditionally ascribed location of Jesus' death and burial.]]

===Judaism===
{{main|Judaism's view of Jesus}}
Jesus was Jewish, but Christianity split with Judaism in the 1st century, and the two faiths have differed in their theology since. According to the ''[[Toledot Yeshu]]'', the body of Jesus was [[Stolen body hypothesis|removed]] in the same night by a gardener named Juda, after hearing the disciples planned to steal the body of Jesus. &lt;ref&gt;Michael J. Cook, &quot;Jewish Perspectives on Jesus&quot;, in Delbert Burkett (editor), ''The Blackwell Companion to Jesus'', pages 221-223 (Blackwell Publishing Ltd., 2011). ISBN 978-1-4051-9362-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gary R. Habermas, ''The Historical Jesus: Ancient Evidence for the Life of Christ'', page 205 (Thomas Nelson, Inc., 2008). ISBN 0-89900-732-5&lt;/ref&gt; However, ''Toledot Yeshu'' is not considered either canonical or normative within [[rabbinic literature]].&lt;ref&gt;Dan, Joseph (2006). &quot;Toledot Yeshu&quot;. In Michael Berenbaum and Fred Skolnik. Encyclopaedia Judaica. 20 (2nd ed.) pp. 28–29&lt;/ref&gt; Van Voorst states that ''Toledot Yeshu'' is a medieval document set without a fixed form which is &quot;most unlikely&quot; to have reliable information about Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;Van Voorst, Robert E (2000). ''Jesus Outside the New Testament: An Introduction to the Ancient Evidence'' WmB Eerdmans Publishing. ISBN 0-8028-4368-9 page 128&lt;/ref&gt; The Blackwell Companion to Jesus states that the Toledot Yeshu has no historical facts as such, and was perhaps created as a tool for warding off conversions to Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;Michael J. Cook ''Jewish Perspectives on Jesus'' Chapter 14 in the &quot;The Blackwell Companion to Jesus&quot; edited by Delbert Burkett 2011 ISBN 978-1-4443-2794-6&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Islam===
{{main|Islamic view of Jesus' death}}
Muslims believe that Jesus son of Mary was a holy prophet with a divine message. The [[Islamic view of Jesus' death|Islamic perspective]] is that Jesus was not crucified and will be resurrected to the world at the end of times. &quot;But Allâh raised him up to Himself. And Allâh is Ever All-Powerful, All-Wise&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Qur'an]], [[Sura 4]]:158&lt;/ref&gt; The Quran says in Surah An-Nisa [Ch004:Verse157] &quot;And because of their saying, &quot;We killed Messiah 'Îsâ (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary), the Messenger of Allâh,&quot; – but they killed him not, nor crucified him, but it appeared so to them, and those who differ therein are full of doubts&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Qur'an]], [[Sura 4]]:157&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery of art==
:''For a larger gallery, please see'': [[Commons:Structured gallery of Resurrection of Christ|Resurrection gallery]]
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Resurrection.JPG|[[Piero della Francesca]], 15th century
File:Resurrection of Christ and Women at the Tomb by Fra Angelico (San Marco cell 8).jpg|[[Fra Angelico]], 1440-1441
File:Rafael - ressureicaocristo01.jpg|[[Raphael]], 1449-1502
File:Der-Auferstandene 1558.jpg|[[Lucas Cranach the Younger|Lucas Cranach]], 1558
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Chronology of Jesus]]
* [[Dying god]]
* Tomb of Jesus:
** The [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]], the ground on which the church stands is venerated by most Christians as [[Golgotha]], the [[Calvary|Hill of Calvary]], where the [[New Testament]] says that [[Jesus]] was [[crucifixion|crucified]]. This tomb is venerated as the tomb of Christ by the [[Catholic Church]], [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox churches]], and [[Oriental Orthodoxy|Oriental Orthodox churches]].
** The [[Garden Tomb]], discovered in the 19th century, considered the actual site of Jesus' grave by some Protestant Christians.
** [[Talpiot Tomb]], discovered in 1980, subject of the controversial documentary ''[[The Lost Tomb of Jesus]]''

==Notes==
{{refbegin}}
:'''a.'''{{Note label|A|a|none}} In a note, Kirby states, &quot;A very abbreviated list of twentieth-century writers on the NT who do not believe that the empty tomb is historically reliable: [[Marcus Borg]], [[Günther Bornkamm]], [[Gerald Bostock|Gerald Boldock Bostock]], [[Rudolf Bultmann]], [[Peter Carnley]], [[John Dominic Crossan]], Stevan Davies, [[Maurice Goguel]], [[Michael Goulder]], Hans Grass, Charles Guignebert, [[Uta Ranke-Heinemann]], Randel Helms, Herman Hendrikx, Roy Hoover, [[Helmut Koester]], [[Hans Küng]], [[Alfred Loisy]], [[Burton L. Mack]], Willi Marxsen, [[Gerd Lüdemann]], [[Norman Perrin]], [[Robert M. Price]], Marianne Sawicki, [[John Shelby Spong]], Howard M. Teeple, and John T. Theodore.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Empty Tomb: Jesus Beyond the Grave  |editor1-first=  Robert M.|editor1-last= Price|editor1-link=  Robert M. Price |editor2-first=  Jeffrey Jay|editor2-last= Lowder| year= 2005|publisher= Prometheus Books|location= Amherst|isbn= 1-59102-286-X|pages= 256–257}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:'''b.'''{{Note label|B|b|none}} Cavin continues &quot;...&amp;nbsp;even on the assumption of their complete historical reliability&amp;nbsp;... This assumption, of course, is rightly dismissed in light of contemporary New Testament scholarship.&quot;
:'''c.'''{{Note label|C|c|none}} [[Robert M. Price]] points to the accounts of [[Adonis]], [[Appollonius of Tyana]], [[Asclepius]], [[Attis]], [[Empedocles]], [[Hercules]], [[Osiris]], [[Oedipus]], [[Romulus]], [[Tammuz]], and others.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert M. Price]], &quot;The Empty Tomb: Introduction; The Second Life of Jesus.&quot; In {{cite book |title= The Empty Tomb: Jesus Beyond the Grave  |editor1-first=  Robert M.|editor1-last= Price|editor1-link= Robert M. Price |editor2-first=  Jeffrey Jay|editor2-last= Lowder| year= 2005|publisher= Prometheus Books|location= Amherst|isbn= 1-59102-286-X|pages= 14–15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*{{Cite book|last=Newbigin|first=Lesslie|title=The Gospel In a Pluralist Society |publisher=Eerdmans|year=1989|url=
http://books.google.com.au/books?id=q6tEnRYaHI8C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Gospel+In+a+Pluralist+Society&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=VQcsTsCbN-WTmQXNuI26Dw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=book-thumbnail&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC8Q6wEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}

*{{Cite book|last=Allison|first=D.C.|title=Matthew: A Shorter Commentary|publisher=T&amp;T Clark|year=2004|url=
http://books.google.com.au/books?id=m_OShrBh0I0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Allison+Matthew:+a+shorter+commentary&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=3JhbZuNeHr&amp;sig=ulv8E5JvTUptKjXgawpI6xe7Mxg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=eeKoTemXIIaAvgP506CHCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}

*{{Cite book|last=France|first=R.T|title=The Gospel of Matthew|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2007|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=0ruP6J_XPCEC&amp;pg=PA11&amp;lpg=PA11&amp;dq=R.+T.+France+The+Gospel+of+Matthew&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Mv8agcJpcz&amp;sig=y37MWE4KbVmqjhAO1wUP5DfKHUc&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=5yakTYfyPIu0vgOL9tGGCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}

*{{Cite book|last=Burkett|first=Delbert Royce|title=An introduction to the New Testament and the origins of Christianity|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2002|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=EcsQknxV-xQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=An+introduction+to+the+New+Testament+and+the+origins+of+Christianity+Delbert+Royce+Burkett&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Xhm8Cv3-Rt&amp;sig=ksYatWvw5-XTeGATwmuD8-xiWn4&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qM-3TMPTHsqycI7cicEM&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBQQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Gospel%20of%20Matthew&amp;f=false}}

==Further reading==
===Theological===
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12789a.htm The resurrection of Jesus Christ], ''[[Catholic Encyclopedia]].''

===Historical===
==== Pro-Resurrection ====
''Articles:''&lt;!-- Maximum of 5 --&gt;
* Habermas, Gary, &quot;Explaining Away Jesus' Resurrection: The Recent Revival of Hallucination Theories&quot;  &quot;Christian Research Journal/ vol.23 no.4, 2001 http://www.garyhabermas.com/articles/crj_explainingaway/crj_explainingaway.htm
* [[Gary Habermas|Habermas, Gary]], &quot;Resurrection Research from 1975 to the Present: What are Critical Scholars saying?&quot; ''Journal for the Study of the Historical Jesus'', Jun2005, Vol. 3 Issue 2, p135-153 http://www.garyhabermas.com/articles/J_Study_Historical_Jesus_3-2_2005/J_Study_Historical_Jesus_3-2_2005.htm
* [[Tom Wright (theologian)|Wright, N.T.]], &quot;Resurrecting Old Arguments: Responding to Four Essays&quot;, ''Journal for the Study of the Historical Jesus'', Jun2005, Vol. 3 Issue 2, p209-231. http://www.ntwrightpage.com/Wright_Old_Arguments.htm
* Holding, James Patrick. &quot;Robert Price's 'By This Time He Stinkith': A Critique http://www.tektonics.org/lp/pricer06.html
* Habermas, Gary, http://www.garyhabermas.com/books/inbook_to-everyone-an-answer/habermas_case-for-xp-res.htm &quot;The Case for Christ's Resurrection&quot; an essay in ''To Everyone an Answer: A Case for the Christian World View'' ed. Francis Beckwith, William Lane Craig, and J.P. Moreland, 180-198. Downers Grove, IL: published by InterVarsity Press, 2004

''Books:''&lt;!-- Maximum of 5 --&gt;
* Hays, Steve. &quot;This Joyful Eastertide: A Critical Review of 'The Empty Tomb'&quot; http://www.triapologia.com/hays/ThisJoyfulEastertide.pdf
* [[Richard Bauckham|Bauckham, Richard]]. ''Jesus and the Eyewitnesses: The Gospels as Eyewitness Testimony.'' Wm. B. Eerdman's, 2008.
* * Eddy, Paul and [[Greg Boyd (theologian)|Boyd, Greg]]. ''The Jesus Legend: A Case for the Historical Reliability of the Synoptic Jesus Tradition.'' Baker Academic, 2007
* [[Dag Øistein Endsjø|Endsjø, Dag Øistein]]. ''Greek Resurrection Beliefs and the Success of Christianity.'' New York: Palgrave Macmillan 2009.
* Habermas, Gary and [[Michael Licona|Licona, Michael]], ''The Case for the Resurrection of Jesus'', Kregel Publications, 2004.
* [[N.T. Wright|Wright, N. T.]], ''The Resurrection of the Son of God'', Fortress Pr, 2003.
* Licona, Michael, ''The Resurrection of Jesus: A New Historiographical Approach'', IVP Academic, 2010.

====Skeptical====
''Articles:''&lt;!-- Maximum of 5 --&gt;
* Crossley, James G.. &quot;Against the Historical Plausibility of the Empty Tomb Story and the Bodily Resurrection of Jesus: A Response to N.T. Wright&quot;,''Journal for the Study of the Historical Jesus'', Jun2005, Vol. 3 Issue 2, p171-186
* [[Robert M. Price|Price, Robert M.]], ''[http://www.infidels.org/library/modern/robert_price/stinketh.html By This Time He Stinketh: The Attempts of William Lane Craig to Exhume Jesus]''. 1997.

''Books:''&lt;!-- Maximum of 5 --&gt;
* Robert M. Price and Jeffery Jay Lowder, ''The Empty Tomb: Jesus Beyond the Grave (ISBN 1-59102-286-X)'', 2005
* [[John Shelby Spong|Spong, John Shelby]], ''Resurrection: Myth or Reality? '', 1995

===Dialogues===
* Craig, William Lane, ''Jesus' Resurrection: Fact or Figment?: A Debate Between William Lane Craig and Gerd Ludemann''. IVP Academic, 2000.
* Is There Historical Evidence for the Resurrection of Jesus?: A Debate between William Lane Craig and Bart D. Ehrman (transcript) [http://www.holycross.edu/departments/crec/website/resurrection-debate-transcript.pdf] [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FhT4IENSwac (video)]
* Stewart, Robert B. ''The Resurrection of Jesus: John Dominic Crossan And N.T. Wright in Dialogue'', 2006
* &quot;Did Jesus Rise from the Dead?&quot; A Debate Between William Lane Craig and Richard Carrier (audio) http://www.apologetics315.com/2009/03/richard-carrier-vs-william-lane-craig.html
* &quot;Did Jesus of Nazareth Rise from the Dead?&quot; A Debate Between Robert Price and William Lane Craig (audio) http://www.philvaz.com/CraigPriceDebate.mp3

==External links==
{{Commons category|Resurrection of Christ}}

&lt;center&gt;
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 0 1em 1em; font-size: 90%;&quot;
! style=&quot;background: #ccf; text-align: center;&quot; | Major [[Chronology of Jesus|events]] in [[Jesus]]' life in the [[Gospels]]
|-
| style=&quot;font-size: 99%;&quot; |
[[Nativity of Jesus|Nativity]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Child Jesus|Childhood]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Baptism of Jesus|Baptism]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Temptation of Christ|Temptation]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Sermon on the Mount]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Transfiguration of Jesus|Transfiguration]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[The Last Supper|Last Supper]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Passion (Christianity)|Passion]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Crucifixion of Jesus|Crucifixion]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; Resurrection &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Harrowing of Hell|Hell]] &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; [[Ascension of Jesus Christ|Ascension]]
|}
&lt;/center&gt;
{{Easter}}
{{Christianityfooter}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Resurrection Of Jesus}}
[[Category:Jesus]]
[[Category:Resurrection of Jesus|Resurrection of Jesus]]
[[Category:Christian miracle narrative]]
[[Category:Christian theology]]
[[Category:Glorious Mysteries]]

{{Link FA|hr}}

[[ar:قيامة يسوع]]
[[az:İsanın dirilməsi]]
[[be:Уваскрэсенне Ісуса Хрыста]]
[[bs:Isusovo uskrsnuće]]
[[ca:Resurrecció de Jesús]]
[[da:Jesu opstandelse]]
[[de:Auferstehung Jesu Christi]]
[[el:Ανάσταση του Χριστού]]
[[es:Resurrección de Jesús]]
[[fr:Résurrection de Jésus]]
[[ko:예수의 부활]]
[[hr:Uskrsnuće Isusa Krista]]
[[id:Kebangkitan Yesus]]
[[it:Risurrezione di Gesù]]
[[he:תחיית ישו]]
[[sw:Ufufuko wa Yesu]]
[[mk:Исусово воскресение]]
[[nl:Dood en herrijzenis van Christus#De opstanding]]
[[pt:Ressurreição de Jesus]]
[[ro:Învierea Domnului]]
[[ru:Воскресение Иисуса Христа]]
[[sl:Jezusovo vstajenje]]
[[sr:Isusovo uskrsnuće]]
[[sh:Isusovo vaskrsenje]]
[[fi:Jeesuksen ylösnousemus]]
[[sv:Jesu uppståndelse]]
[[ta:இயேசுவின் உயிர்த்தெழுதல்]]
[[th:การคืนพระชนม์ของพระเยซู]]
[[uk:Воскресіння Христа]]
[[vi:Sự Phục sinh của Chúa Giê-xu]]
[[zh:耶稣复活]]</text>
      <sha1>i1ti1iwys2yuaa5csq22mqtvf1s5veo</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
