<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Romanian Orthodox Church</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>384458</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520489383</id>
      <parentid>517304818</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-29T21:16:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>41.133.0.21</ip>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25746">{{Infobox Orthodox Church
|show_name = Romanian Orthodox Church&lt;br&gt;(Romanian Patriarchy)
|image = [[Image:BOR CoA.png|250px]]
|caption = Coat of arms
|founder = (as metropolis of Romania)&lt;BR&gt;[[Nifon]], [[Carol I of Romania|Carol I]]&lt;BR&gt;
(as patriarchy of Romania)&lt;BR&gt;[[Miron Cristea]], [[Ferdinand I of Romania|Ferdinand I]]
|independence = 1872
|recognition=  25 April 1885
|primate= [[Patriarch Daniel of Romania|Patriarch Daniel]], [[Patriarch of All Romania]] 
|headquarters= [[Dealul Mitropoliei]], [[Bucharest]]
|territory= {{ROU}}&lt;br&gt;{{MDA}}
|possessions={{SRB}}&lt;br&gt;{{HUN}}&lt;br&gt;Western and Southern Europe;&lt;br&gt;Germany, Central and Northern Europe;&lt;br&gt;Americas;&lt;br&gt; Australia and New Zealand
|language=[[Romanian language|Romanian]]
|population= 16,367,267 in Romania;&lt;ref&gt;2011 Romanian census.&lt;/ref&gt; 720,000 in Moldova&lt;ref name=&quot;Basarabia&quot;/&gt;
|website= http://www.patriarhia.ro/
}}
The '''Romanian Orthodox Church''' (''Biserica Ortodoxă Română'' in [[Romanian language|Romanian]]) is an [[autocephalous]] [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox]] church.  It is in [[full communion]] with other Eastern Orthodox churches, and is ranked [[Eastern Orthodox Church organization|seventh]] in order of precedence. The [[Primate (religion)|Primate]] of the church has the title of [[Patriarch]]. Its jurisdiction covers the territory of [[Romania]], with [[diocese]]s for Romanians living in nearby [[Moldova]], [[Serbia]] and [[Hungary]], as well as diaspora communities in Central and Western Europe, North America and Oceania.

It is the only Eastern Orthodox church using a [[Romance language]]. The majority of people in [[Romania]] (16,367,267, or 85.9% of the population, according to the 2011 census data&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.recensamantromania.ro/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/TS8.pdf 2011 census data on religion]&lt;/ref&gt;) belong to it, as well as some 720,000 [[Moldova]]ns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Basarabia&quot;&gt;{{ro icon}} [http://www.ziua.net/news.php?data=2008-01-31&amp;id=3053 &quot;Biserica Ortodoxă Română, atacată de bisericile 'surori'&quot; (&quot;The Romanian Orthodox Church, Attacked by Its 'Sister' Churches&quot;], ''Ziua'', 31 January 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The Romanian Orthodox Church is  the second-largest in size behind the [[Russian Orthodox Church]].

Adherents of the Romanian Orthodox Church sometimes refer to it as ''Dreapta credinţă'' (&quot;right/correct belief&quot; or &quot;true faith&quot;; compare to Greek ὀρθὴ δόξα, &quot;straight/correct belief&quot;).

==History==
{{see also|History of Christianity in Romania}}
[[File:Ortodocsi Transilvania 1850.png|thumb|Orthodox believers in Transylvania according to the 1850 census]]
[[File:Ortodocsi Romania (1930).png|thumb|Orthodox believers in Romania according to the 1930 census]]
[[File:Ortodocsi Romania (2002).png|thumb|Orthodox believers in Romania according to the 2002 census]]
===The Church in the Kingdom of Romania===
In 1859, the Romanian principalities of [[Moldavia]] and [[Wallachia]] formed the modern state of Romania. The hierarchy of the Orthodox churches tends to follow the structure of the state. Therefore, shortly afterwards, in 1872, the Orthodox churches of the former principalities, the [[Metropolitan of Ungro-Wallachia|Metropolis of Ungro-Wallachia]] and the [[Metropolis of Moldavia and Bukovina|Metropolis of Moldavia]], decided to unite to form the Romanian Orthodox Church. 

The [[1866 Constitution of Romania]] declared the Orthodox Church to be &quot;independent of any foreign hierarchy&quot;, but it was a law passed in 1872 that declared the church to be &quot;autocephalous&quot;. After a long period of negotiations with the [[Patriarchate of Constantinople]], the latter finally recognized in 1885 the Metropolis of Romania, which was raised to the rank of Patriarchy in 1925.&lt;ref&gt;Keith Hitchins, ''Rumania 1866-1947'', Clarendon Press, 1994, p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;

===Communist period===
[[File:420 Conducatorii de partid si de stat.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Nicolae Ceauşescu]] and other Party officials visit [[Neamţ Monastery]] in 1966.]]
{{main|Romania Anti-Religious Campaign}}
Assessing the attitude of the Romanian Orthodox Church towards the [[Communism in Romania|Communist regime]] is difficult due to restricted access to ecclesiastical and relevant state archives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presidency.ro/static/ordine/RAPORT_FINAL_CPADCR.pdf|title=Raport final|author=[[Presidential Commission for the Study of the Communist Dictatorship in Romania]], pp. 446-447|year=2006|publisher=Romanian Presidency|language=Romanian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.revista22.ro/despartirea-apelor-biserica-si-securitatea-4069.html|title=Despărțirea apelor: Biserica și Securitatea|author=Mihail Neamțu|publisher=[[Revista 22]]|date=2007-10-17|language=Romanian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, as an institution it was more or less tolerated by the [[Marxist–Leninist atheism|Marxist–Leninist atheist]] regime, though controlled through &quot;special delegates&quot; and excluded from the public space; the regime generally focused on individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presidency.ro/static/ordine/RAPORT_FINAL_CPADCR.pdf|title=Raport final|author=[[Presidential Commission for the Study of the Communist Dictatorship in Romania]], p. 453|year=2006|publisher=Romanian Presidency|language=Romanian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its members' actions, both laity and clergy, range broadly from opposition to the regime and [[martyrdom]], to survival, silent consent or collaboration. Not only the limited access to the [[Securitate]] and Party archives or the events' recentness, but the particularities of each individual and situation, the understanding each had about how their own relation with the regime could influence others and how it actually did, make such a task cumbersome.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presidency.ro/static/ordine/RAPORT_FINAL_CPADCR.pdf|title=Raport final|author=[[Presidential Commission for the Study of the Communist Dictatorship in Romania]], pp. 455-56|year=2006|publisher=Romanian Presidency|language=Romanian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See {{cite web|url=http://www.ziua.net/display.php?id=206475&amp;data=2006-09-02|author=George Enache|title=Biserica Ortodoxă Română și Securitatea|publisher=[[Ziua]]|language=[[Romanian language|Romanian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Romanian Communist Party]], which gained power at the end of 1947, initiated mass purges that decimated the Orthodox hierarchy. Three archbishops died suddenly after expressing opposition to government policies, and thirteen more &quot;uncooperative&quot; bishops and archbishops were arrested.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramet19&quot;&gt;Ramet, Pedro and Ramet, Sabrina P. ''Religion and Nationalism in Soviet and East European Politics'', p.19-20. Duke University Press (1989), ISBN 0-8223-0891-6.&lt;/ref&gt; A May 1947 decree imposed a mandatory retirement age for clergy, allowing authorities to pension off old-guard holdouts. The 4 August 1948 Law on Cults institutionalised state control of episcopal elections and packed the Holy Synod with Communist supporters.&lt;ref name=&quot;democ&quot;&gt;Lavinia Stan and Lucian Turcescu, ''Religion and Politics in Post-communist Romania'', Oxford University Press, 2007. ISBN 0-19-530853-0.&lt;/ref&gt; In exchange for subservience and enthusiastic support for state policies, as well as 2,500 church buildings and other assets from the now-outlawed [[Romanian Church United with Rome, Greek-Catholic|Romanian Greek-Catholic Church]], the government provided salaries for bishops and priests, and financial subsidies for the publication of church books, calendars and theological journals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramet278&quot;&gt;Sabrina P. Ramet, &quot;Church and State in Romania before and after 1989&quot;, in Carey, Henry F. ''Romania Since 1989: Politics, Economics, and Society'', p.278. 2004, Lexington Books, ISBN 0-7391-0592-2.&lt;/ref&gt; By weeding out the anti-communists and setting up a pro-regime and secret police-infiltrated Union of Democratic Priests (1945), the party endeavoured to secure the hierarchy's cooperation. By January 1953 some 300-500 Orthodox priests were being held in concentration camps, and after Patriarch [[Nicodim Munteanu|Nicodim]]'s death in May 1948, the party succeeded in having the ostensibly docile [[Justinian Marina]] elected to succeed him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramet19&quot;/&gt;

As a result of measures passed in 1947-48, the 2,300 elementary schools operated by the church were closed, as were its 24 high schools, its academy of sacred music, three divinity schools, and 13 of its 15 theological seminaries. A new campaign struck the church in 1958-62 when more than half its remaining monasteries were closed, more than 2,000 monks forced to take secular jobs, and about 1,500 clergy and lay activists arrested (out of a total of up to 6,000 in the 1946-64 period&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramet278&quot;/&gt;). Throughout this period Patriarch Justinian was careful to say the right things and avoid giving offence to the government;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramet20&quot;&gt;Ramet 1989, p.20.&lt;/ref&gt; indeed the hierarchy claimed the arrests were not due religious persecution.&lt;ref name=&quot;democ&quot;/&gt;

The church's situation began to improve in 1962, when relations with the state suddenly thawed, an event that coincided with Romania's pursuit of an independent foreign policy course that saw the élite use nationalism to secure its position against Soviet pressure. The Romanian Orthodox Church, as an intensely national body which had made significant contributions to Romanian culture from the 14th century, was a natural partner. As a result of this second co-optation, now as an ally, the church was able to recover dramatically. Its diocesan clergy numbered about 12,000 in 1975, and by then it was already publishing eight high-quality theological reviews, including ''Ortodoxia'' and ''Studii Teologice''. Orthodox clergymen consistently supported the [[Nicolae Ceauşescu|Ceauşescu]] régime's foreign policy, refrained from criticism of domestic policy, and upheld the Romanian line against the Soviets (over Bessarabia) and the Hungarians (over Transylvania). As of 1989, two metropolitan bishops even sat in the [[Great National Assembly]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramet20&quot;/&gt; The church maintained its silence when some two dozen historic Bucharest churches were demolished in the 1980s, and when plans for [[Systematization (Romania)|systematization]] (including the destruction of village churches) were announced.&lt;ref&gt;Ramet 2004, p. 279.&lt;/ref&gt; A notable dissenter was [[Gheorghe Calciu-Dumitreasa]], imprisoned for a number of years and expelled from Romania in June 1985 after signing an open letter criticizing and demanding an end to the regime's violations of human rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramet278&quot;/&gt;

In order to fit its new circumstances, the Orthodox Church constructed a new ecclesiology to justify its subservience to the state in supposed theological terms. The &quot;Social Apostolate&quot; doctrine, developed by Patriarch Justinian, declared that the church owed its allegiance to the secular government and should be of service to that government. This notion inflamed conservatives, who were purged by [[Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej]], Ceauşescu's predecessor and a friend of Justinian's. The Social Apostolate called on clerics to become active in the People's Republic, laying the foundation for the church's submission to and collaboration with the state. Fr. Vasilescu, an Orthodox priest, tried to ground the Social Apostolate in the Christian tradition, citing [[Augustine of Hippo]], [[John Chrysostom]], [[Maximus the Confessor]], [[Origen]] and [[Tertullian]]. Based on this alleged tradition, Vasilescu concluded that Christians owed submission to their rulers because it was God's will. With recalcitrants removed from office, remaining bishops adopted a servile attitude, endorsing Ceauşescu's concept of nation, supporting his policies, and applauding his ideas about peace.&lt;ref&gt;Ramet 2004, p.280.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Collaboration with the Securitate===
{{Main|Clerical collaboration with Communist secret services}}
After the [[1989 Romanian Revolution]], the Church never admitted of willingly collaborating with the régime, but several Romanian Orthodox priests have admitted publicly after 1989 that they have collaborated with and/or were informers for the [[Securitate]], the Romanian [[Communist]] [[secret police]]. A prime example was Bishop [[Nicolae Corneanu]], the [[Metropolis of Banat|Metropolitan]] of [[Banat]], who admitted his efforts on the behalf of the [[Romanian Communist Party|Communist Party]], and denounced clergy activity with the Communists, including his own, as &quot;the Church's prostitution with the Communist régime&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;democ&quot;/&gt;

===After 1989===
[[Image:Iconpeter.jpg|thumb|right|[[Romania]]n icon of [[St. Peter]]]]
As Romania made the transition to a democracy, the Church was freed from state control, though the State Secretariat for Religious Denominations maintains control over a number of aspects of the church property, finances and administration. The state funds the church in proportion of religious adherents based on census returns&lt;ref&gt;A world survey of religion and the state, By [[Jonathan Fox]], pg. 167&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;the religion's needs&quot; which is considered to be an &quot;ambiguous provision&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://romania.usembassy.gov/2008_irf.html 2008 International Religious Freedom report by the US Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor]&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, the state pays for the salaries of priests, deacons and prelates and the pensions of those who have retired, as well as expenses related to non-religious personal. This applies to all state-recognised religions.

The state also provides support for church construction and dilapidations with a preference towards the Orthodox parishes.&lt;ref&gt;Law and religion in post-communist Europe By Silvio Ferrari, W. Cole Durham, Elizabeth A. Sewell pg.253&lt;/ref&gt; The state funds all the expenses of the Orthodox seminaries and colleges including teachers and professor salaries with compensation as civil servants.

Since the fall of Communism, [[Romanian Church United with Rome, Greek-Catholic|Greek-Catholic Church]] leaders have claimed that the Eastern Catholic community is facing with a cultural and religious wipe-out: the Greek-Catholic churches are allegedly destroyed by the Orthodox Church representatives, whose actions are supported and accepted by the Romanian authorities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.hotnews.ro/stiri-top_news-5709439-the-romanian-greek-catholic-community-facing-cultural-and-religious-wipe-out-ndash-letter-secretary-state-hillary-clinton.htm The Romanian Greek-Catholic Community is facing a cultural and religious wipe-out – letter to US Secretary of State Hillary Clinton]&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Church in Moldova===
The Romanian Orthodox Church also has jurisdiction over a minority of believers in [[Moldova]], who belong to the [[Metropolis of Bessarabia]], as opposed to the majority, who belong to the [[Moldovan Orthodox Church]], under the Moscow Patriarchate. In 2001 it won a landmark legal victory against the Government of Moldova at the [[Strasbourg]]-based [[European Court of Human Rights]].

This means that despite current political issues, the Metropolis of Bessarabia is now recognized as &quot;the rightful successor&quot; to the [[Metropolitan Church of Bessarabia and Hotin]], which existed from 1927 to 1944, when it was dissolved, its canonical territory being put under the jurisdiction of the [[Russian Orthodox Church|Russian Orthodox Church's Moscow Patriarchate]] in 1947.

==Organization==
{{See also|List of members of the Holy Synod of the Romanian Orthodox Church}}

[[File:Romanian Orthodox Church EN.svg|thumb|right|250px|Romanian Orthodox Church organization (as established in 2011)]]

The Romanian Orthodox Church is organized as the Romanian [[Patriarchate]]. The highest hierarchical, canonical and dogmatical authority of the Romanian Orthodox Church is the [[Holy Synod]].

There are six [[Metropolitanate]]s and ten [[archbishopric]]s in Romania, and more than twelve thousand priests and deacons, servant fathers of ancient altars from parishes, monasteries and social centres. Almost 400 monasteries exist inside the country for some 3,500 monks and 5,000 nuns. Three ''Diasporan Metropolitanates'' and two ''Diasporan Bishoprics'' function outside Romania proper. As of 2004, there are, inside [[Romania]], fifteen theological universities where more than ten thousand students (some of them from [[Bessarabia]], [[Bukovina]] and [[Serbia]] benefiting from a few Romanian fellowships) currently study for a doctoral degree. More than 14,500 churches (traditionally named &quot;lăcaşe de cult&quot;, or worshiping places) exist in Romania for the Romanian Orthodox believers. As of 2002, almost 1,000 of these were either in the process of being built or rebuilt.

==Relations with other Orthodox jurisdictions==
Most [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox]] [[autocephalous]] churches, including the Romanian, maintain a respectful spiritual link to the [[Ecumenical Patriarch]], currently [[Patriarch Bartholomew I|Bartholomew I]].

In December 2007 [[Russia]]n [[State Duma|Duma]] [[United Russia]]’s [[Member of Parliament|MP]] [[Konstantin Zatulin]] accused the Romanian Orthodox Church of “[[proselytism]]” against the [[Russian Orthodox Church]] in Moldova (and [[Transnistria]]) with the aim of annexing these territories into Romania.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.regnum.ru/english/927412.html Romanian Patriarchate’s activity aimed at Moldova’s absorption by Romania: Konstantin Zatulin], ''[[REGNUM News Agency]]'', December 5, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Famous theologians==
[[Dumitru Stăniloae]] (1903–1993) is considered one of the greatest Orthodox theologians of the 20th century, having written extensively in all major fields of Eastern Christian [[systematic theology]]. One of his other major achievements in theology is the 45-year-long comprehensive series on Orthodox spirituality known as the Romanian [[Philokalia]], a collection of texts written by classical Byzantine writers, that he edited and translated from Greek.

[[Archimandrite]] [[Ilie Cleopa]] (1912–1998), elder of the Sihastria Monastery, is considered one of the most representative spiritual fathers of contemporary Romanian Orthodox monastic spirituality.&lt;ref&gt;Electronic version of ''Dicţionarul teologilor români'' (''Dictionary of Romanian Theologians''), Univers Enciclopedic Ed., Bucharest, 1996, retrieved from [http://biserica.org/WhosWho/DTR/I/IlieCleopa.html http://biserica.org/WhosWho/DTR/I/IlieCleopa.html].&lt;/ref&gt;

==List of Patriarchs==
{{Main|Patriarch of All Romania}}

*[[Miron Cristea|Miron]] (1925–1939)
*[[Nicodim Munteanu|Nicodim]] (1939–1948)
*[[Justinian Marina|Justinian]] (1948–1977)
*[[Iustin Moisescu|Iustin]] (1977–1986)
*[[Teoctist Arăpaşu|Teoctist]] (1986–2007)
*[[Patriarch Daniel of Romania|Daniel]] (since 2007)

==Current leaders of the Church==
The chair is currently held by [[Daniel Ciobotea|Daniel I]], Archbishop of [[Bucharest]], Metropolitan of Ungro-Vlachia (Muntenia or [[Wallachia]] and Dobrogea or [[Dobruja]]) and Patriarch of All of the Romanian Orthodox Church, ''Locum Tenens'' of Caesarea in Cappadocia.
*[[Teofan Savu]], Metropolitan of [[Metropolis of Moldavia and Bukovina|Moldavia and Bukovina]] [http://www.mmb.ro/en/index.php?pagina=11]
*[[Laurenţiu Streza]], Metropolitan of [[Transylvania]], [http://mitropolia-ardealului.ro/]
*[[Andrei Andreicut]], Metropolitan of [[Cluj County|Cluj]], [[Maramureş (historical region)|Maramureş]] and Salaj
*[[Nicolae Corneanu]], Metropolitan of the Banat
*[[Irineu Popa]], Metropolitan of Oltenia
*[[Petru Păduraru]], Metropolitan of [[Metropolis of Bessarabia|Bessarabia]]
*[[Iosif Pop]], Archbishop of Paris and Metropolitan of France, Western and Southern Europe [http://www.mitropolia-paris.ro/ ]
*[[Serafim Joantă]], Metropolitan of Germany and Central Europe
*[[Nicolae Condrea]], the Most Reverend Archbishop of [[Romanian Orthodox Archdiocese of America and Canada|America and Canada]]

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:TimisoaraCatedrala.jpg|[[Timişoara Orthodox Cathedral|Orthodox cathedral]] in [[Timişoara]], [[Romania]]
File:Murescatedrala.jpg|Orthodox cathedral in [[Târgu Mureş]], [[Romania]]
File:RO IS Metropolitan orthodox cathedral.jpeg|[[Metropolitan Cathedral, Iaşi|Metropolitan Cathedral]] in [[Iaşi]], the largest Orthodox church in [[Romania]]
File:Galati cathedral.jpg|Orthodox cathedral in [[Galaţi]], [[Romania]]
File:BisericaDinMioveni.jpg|Orthodox cathedral in [[Mioveni]], [[Romania]]
File:Sârbi Josani.jpg|Orthodox church in [[Sârbi Susani church|Sârbi Josani]], [[Romania]]
File:Voronet church.jpg|Orthodox church in [[Voroneţ Monastery|Voroneţ]], [[Romania]]
File:Tmiklos1.jpg|Orthodox church in [[Nikolinci]], [[Serbia]]
File:Biserica din Densus - Pasztor.jpg|[[Romano-Gothic]] Orthodox church in [[Densuş Church|Densuş]], [[Romania]]
File:CJROothodox.jpg|Orthodox cathedral in [[Dormition of the Theotokos Cathedral, Cluj-Napoca|Cluj-Napoca]], [[Romania]]
File:Prodromos-2.jpg|Orthodox church in [[Prodromos (Mount Athos)|Prodromu]], [[Greece]]
File:Lugojchurch.jpg|Baroc Orthodox cathedral in [[Lugoj]], [[Romania]]
File:Man Curtea de Arges.SV.jpg|Orthodox church in [[Curtea de Argeş Cathedral|Curtea de Argeş]], [[Romania]]
File:Neamt monastery 1.cristibur.jpg|Orthodox church in [[Neamţ Monastery|Vânători-Neamţ]], [[Romania]]
File:Horezu.jpg|Orthodox church in [[Horezu Monastery|Horezu]], [[Romania]]
File:2006 0610CoziaExterior20565.JPG|Orthodox church in [[Cozia Monastery|Călimăneşti-Căciulata]], [[Romania]]
File:Kapella jenskoi gimnazii bernardazzi.jpg|[[Neoclassic Byzantine]] Orthodox cathedral in [[St. Teodora de la Sihla Church|Chişinău]], [[Moldova|Republic of Moldova]]
File:Patriarchenpalast Bukarest.jpg|The [[Palace of the Patriarchate|Palace of the Romanian Patriarchate]] (the former Palace of the Assembly of Deputies (''Adunarea Deputaţilor''))]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[Romanian People’s Salvation Cathedral]]
*[[Patriarch of All Romania]]
*[[List of Romanian Orthodox monasteries]]
*[[Romanian Orthodox icons]]
*[[Frumuşeni Mosaics]]
*[[Byzantium after Byzantium]]
*[[Religion in Romania]]
*[[Orthodox Church of France]]
*[[Orthodox Church in America Romanian Episcopate]]
*[[List of members of the Holy Synod of the Romanian Orthodox Church]]
*[[Religious education in Romania]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.patriarhia.ro/ Romanian Patriarchy]
*[http://www.mmb.ro/ The Metropolitanate of Moldavia and Bucovina and the Archdiocese of Iaşi]
* {{ro icon}} [http://roboam.com/identitate/boscorodirea.htm Boscorodirea]
*[http://www.crestinism-ortodox.ro/ Archdiocese of Bucharest]
* {{ro icon}} [http://www.biserica.org/Publicatii/2003/NoX/13_index.html Portal Ortodox Românesc]
* {{ro icon}} [http://www.patriarh.ro Romanian Patriarchs]
*{{en icon}} [http://www.centruldepelerinaj.ro/index.php?&amp;lang=en Pilgrimage Centre in Iaşi, Romania]
*[http://www.cnewa.org/ecc-bodypg-us.aspx?eccpageID=19&amp;IndexView=toc Article on Romanian Orthodox Church on CNEWA website]

===Romanian Orthodoxy outside Romania===
*[http://www.starlightsite.co.uk/keston/kns/2002/020410MO-01.htm Moldova: Government Fails in Bessarabian Church Appeal]
*[http://sim.law.uu.nl/SIM/CaseLaw/hof.nsf/0/75f3ea9f6eb9d125c1256b22002f59fb?OpenDocument ''Metropolitan Church of Bessarabia and Others v. Moldova'']
*{{fr icon}} [http://www.mitropolia-paris.ro/ Romanian Orthodox Metropolitanate of Western and Southern Europe]
*{{ro icon}}/{{de icon}} [http://www.mitropolia-ro.de/ Romanian Orthodox Metropolitanate of Germany and Central Europe]
*{{ro icon}}/{{fr icon}} [http://www.egliseroumaine.com/noi-dvs/primire/primire.htm Romanian Church of Paris]

{{BORDioceses}}
{{Orthodoxy}}
{{Orthodox Christianity in Europe}}
{{Romanian religions}}

{{commons category|Romanian Orthodox Church}}

[[Category:Eastern Orthodoxy by country|Europe]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox church bodies and patriarchates]]
[[Category:Christianity in Romania]]
[[Category:Romanian Orthodox Church| ]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1872]]
[[Category:Members of the World Council of Churches]]
[[Category:Eastern Orthodox organizations established in the 19th century]]
[[Category:Christian denominations, unions, and movements established in the 19th century]]

{{Link GA|ca}}

[[af:Roemeens-Ortodokse Kerk]]
[[ar:الكنيسة الرومانية الأرثوذكسية]]
[[frp:Égllése ortodoxe de Roumanie]]
[[be:Румынская праваслаўная царква]]
[[bg:Румънска православна църква]]
[[ca:Església Ortodoxa Romanesa]]
[[cs:Rumunská pravoslavná církev]]
[[de:Rumänisch-Orthodoxe Kirche]]
[[et:Rumeenia Õigeusu Kirik]]
[[es:Iglesia ortodoxa rumana]]
[[eo:Rumana Ortodoksa Eklezio]]
[[fr:Patriarcat de Roumanie]]
[[ga:Eaglais Cheartchreidmheach na Rómáine]]
[[gl:Igrexa Ortodoxa Romanesa]]
[[ko:루마니아 정교회]]
[[id:Gereja Ortodoks Rumania]]
[[it:Chiesa ortodossa rumena]]
[[ka:რუმინეთის მართლმადიდებელი ეკლესია]]
[[la:Ecclesia Orthodoxa Dacoromanica]]
[[hu:Román ortodox egyház]]
[[mk:Романска Православна црква]]
[[nl:Roemeens-orthodoxe Kerk]]
[[ja:ルーマニア正教会]]
[[no:Den rumensk-ortodokse kirke]]
[[pl:Rumuński Kościół Prawosławny]]
[[pt:Igreja Ortodoxa Romena]]
[[ro:Biserica Ortodoxă Română]]
[[ru:Румынская православная церковь]]
[[simple:Romanian Orthodox]]
[[sk:Rumunská pravoslávna cirkev]]
[[sr:Румунска православна црква]]
[[sh:Rumunska pravoslavna crkva]]
[[fi:Romanian patriarkaatti]]
[[sv:Rumänsk-ortodoxa kyrkan]]
[[tr:Romanya Ortodoks Kilisesi]]
[[uk:Румунська Православна Церква]]
[[zh:罗马尼亚正教会]]</text>
      <sha1>8fou4h5c0ibo8l5kmfzddsykzg71fng</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
