<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sabbath mode</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6747989</id>
    <revision>
      <id>512019457</id>
      <parentid>511892723</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-12T14:41:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vonfraginoff</username>
        <id>361018</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Refrigerator */ remove purple prose</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4391">{{Merge from|Shabbat module|date=December 2011}}
'''Sabbath mode''', also known as '''Shabbos mode''' (Ashkenazi pronunciation) or '''Shabbat mode''', is a feature in many modern [[home appliances]], including [[oven]]s and [[refrigerator]]s, which is intended to allow the appliances to be used (subject to various constraints) by Shabbat-observant [[Jew]]s on the [[Shabbat]] and [[Jewish holiday]]s.

Jews are forbidden from doing [[Activities prohibited on Shabbat|creative work on the Shabbat]]. Observant Jews interpret this to include doing things such as making a fire, preparing food or even closing a switch or pressing an electronic button.

== Appliances ==
=== Oven ===
While raw food may not be cooked on the Shabbat, food that was already cooked beforehand may be kept warm until mealtime. On some holidays, food may be cooked fresh, but turning the heat on is prohibited. In the past, the problem could be solved simply by lighting a stove or oven before the day began, and using its heat over the course of the day. In recent decades, however, appliance manufacturers have instituted a safety feature that automatically shuts off the heat after a number of hours. This renders the appliance useless for those who observe these religious laws.

When an oven is in Shabbat mode, the standard six- or twelve-hour automatic shutoff is overridden, and all lights and displays (for example, a light that might go on when the door is opened) are disabled.

In more recently designed ovens, Shabbat mode will often feature the ability to adjust the temperature of the oven without any feedback to the operator of the oven. This is not relevant to the Shabbat, but is useful on some holidays, when adjusting the heat is allowed, but changing a digital readout on the control panel is not, according to the prevailing Orthodox opinion and the minority Conservative view.

With some Shabbat mode ovens that are controlled using a keypad to set the temperature, there is a random delay triggered after a button is pressed before the temperature change takes place.

In June 2008, a number of prominent [[poskim]] signed a public pronouncement (Kol Koreh) stating that it was unequivocally forbidden to raise or lower the temperature by reprogramming on [[Yom Tov]] using the [[Star-K]] approved Shabbat Mode feature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theyeshivaworld.com/news/General+News/19228/Preventing+Transgression:+Gedolei+HaPoskim+Asur+Shabbos+Mode+on+Ovens.html|title=Preventing Transgression: Gedolei HaPoskim Asur Pressing Buttons on ‘Shabbos Mode Ovens’ on Yom Tov|date=2008-06-05|accessdate=2009-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The pronouncement referred to the long-held lenient opinion of [[Moshe Heinemann|Rabbi Moshe Heinemann]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.star-k.org/cons-appl_kitch.htm|title=Regarding Star-K certified Shabbath Mode ovens|date=2008-06-06|accessdate=2009-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a minority opinion that should not be relied upon (Daas Yachid).&lt;ref&gt;Rabbi Heinemann was not mentioned by name.&lt;/ref&gt; However, it has been pointed out that Rabbi Heinemann's opinion is fully consistent with the rulings of [[Shlomo Zalman Auerbach|Rabbi Shlomo Zalman Auerbach]].

=== Refrigerator ===
A Shabbat mode refrigerator includes, at a minimum, the ability to disable all lights or other electrical activity from occurring when the refrigerator door is opened. Some Shabbat mode refrigerators include a timer for the compressor so that opening the door, which will normally indirectly cause the compressor to turn on as the temperature rises, will have no effect on the electrical operation of the appliance.

=== Lamp ===
{{Main|Shabbat lamp}}

A [[Shabbat lamp]] is a special lamp that has movable parts to expose or block out its light so it can be turned &quot;on&quot; or &quot;off&quot; while its power physically remains on.

== See also ==
* [[Activities prohibited on Shabbat#The thirty-nine activities|39 categories of activity prohibited on Shabbat]]
* [[Blech]]
* [[Cholent]], especially the section on serving hot foods on Shabbat
* [[Grama (halacha)]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* http://www.wordspy.com/words/Sabbathmode.asp
* http://www.star-k.org/kashrus/kk-cooking-SM.htm
* [http://www.patentgenius.com/patent/5808278.html An early Sabbath mode patent in the USPTO database: #5,808,278]

{{Shabbat}}

[[Category:Cooking appliances]]
[[Category:Shabbat innovations]]</text>
      <sha1>mzl6isg9djzrp3t7nmvmprzmi8mmr2c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
