<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sabbath in Christianity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26671</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520105433</id>
      <parentid>520102957</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T12:34:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tonicthebrown</username>
        <id>2191333</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>good faith, but POV and unnecessary</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="47358">''For other uses, see [[Biblical Sabbath]], [[Sabbath in seventh-day churches]], [[Shabbat]], [[High Sabbath]], and [[Sabbath year]].
[[File:Ten Commandments Monument.jpg|thumb|right|190px|A [[Ten Commandments]] monument which includes the command to [[Remember the Sabbath and keep it holy|&quot;Remember the Sabbath day, to keep it holy&quot;]].]]
{{Portal|Christianity}}

In [[Christianity]], [[Sabbath]] is a weekly day of [[leisure|rest]] or religious observance, derived from [[Biblical Sabbath]] ({{lang-he|[[wikt:שַׁבָּת|שַׁבָּת]]}}, ''shabbâth'', {{StrongHebrew|7676}}, meaning intensive &quot;repose&quot;).

By the 2nd century AD, the observance of a corporate day of worship on the first day (Sunday, or Saturday night) had become commonplace, as attested in the [[patristics|patristic writings]].&lt;ref name=Bauckham2&gt;{{cite book|chapter=The Lord's Day|first=R.J.|last=Bauckham|title=From Sabbath to Lord's Day|editor1-first=Don A|editor1-last=Carson|year=1982|pages=221–50|publisher=Wipf &amp; Stock Publishers/Zondervan|editor-link=Don Carson|isbn=978-1-57910-307-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; For such worshipers the term &quot;[[Lord's Day]]&quot; came to mean the first day or Sunday. From the [[Christianity in the 4th century|4th century]] onwards, Sunday worship has also taken on the observance of Sunday rest in some Christian traditions, such as the [[Puritans]] of the 16th and 17th centuries. Among these &quot;first-day Sabbatarians&quot;, Sunday worship and/or rest eventually became synonymous with a first-day &quot;Christian Sabbath&quot;.

Seventh-day Sabbath observance, i.e., resting from hard labor from sunset to sunset on the seventh day (from Friday to Saturday), similarly to ''[[Shabbat]]'' in Judaism, is practiced by [[Seventh-day Sabbatarians]],

[[Non-Sabbatarianism]], the principle of [[Christian liberty]] from being bound to physical Sabbath observance, has significant historical support. Non-Sabbatarians focus on Sabbath's [[typology (theology)|typological]] meaning, i.e., its representation of present or future spiritual rest in Christ.

==Biblical tradition==
{{Main|Biblical Sabbath}}
As ''shabath'' (rest), Sabbath was first described in the Biblical account of the seventh day of [[Genesis creation narrative|Creation]] ({{Bibleverse||Gen.|2:2-3}}). Observation and remembrance of Sabbath is one of the [[Ten Commandments]] (the fourth in the [[Eastern Orthodox]] and most [[Protestant]] traditions, the third in [[Roman Catholic]] and [[Lutheran]] traditions). Most people who observe first-day or seventh-day Sabbath regard it as having been instituted as a &quot;perpetual [[Covenant (Biblical)|covenant]] [for] the [[children of Israel|people of Israel]]&quot; and [[proselytes]] ({{Bibleverse||Ex.|31:13-17}}, {{Bibleverse||Ex.|23:12}}, {{Bibleverse||Deut.|5:13-14}}), a sign in respect for the day during which [[God]] rested after having completed Creation in six days ({{Bibleverse||Gen.|2:2-3}}, {{Bibleverse||Ex.|20:8-11}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Packer|first=J.I.|authorlink=J. I. Packer|title=A Quest for Godliness: The Puritan Vision of the Christian Life|publisher=Crossway Books|edition=1st U.S. trade paperback|year=1994|location=[[Wheaton, Illinois]]|pages=233–44|url=http://books.google.ca/books?id=FxGiTGxd_M0C&amp;pg=PA238&amp;dq=%22Matthew+henry%22,++%22sanctification+of+the+sabbath%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=904fToigEsPb0QHptaHWAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Matthew%20henry%22%2C%20%20%22sanctification%20of%20the%20sabbath%22&amp;f=false|isbn=0-89107-819-3|quote=A weekly memorial of creation 'to be observed to the glory of the Creator, as an engagement upon ourselves to serve him, and an encouragement to us to trust in Him who made heaven and earth. By the sanctification of the Sabbath, the Jews declared that they worshipped the God who made the earth. ...' So speaks that entirely representative latter-day Puritan Matthew Henry.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[New Testament]], Jesus debates the Jews about the topic of Sabbath observance and declares that the [[Son of Man]] is [[Lord of Sabbath]] (e.g., {{Bibleverse||Mk.|2:21-28}}). Early [[Jewish Christians]] such as [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]] the Apostle [[Paul the Apostle and Judaism|visit the synagogue]] on Sabbath ({{Bibleverse||Acts|13:13-14}}). The New Testament [[epistle]]s contain Sabbath teachings interpreted variously by Christians as affirming seventh-day rest, first-day worship, and/or freedom from legalistic requirements to observe days.

The following textual evidence for first-day assembly is usually combined with the notion that the rest day should follow the assembly day to support first-day Sabbatarianism. On the first day of the week (usually considered the day of [[First Fruits#Biblical|Firstfruits]]), after Jesus has been raised from the dead ({{Bibleverse||Mk.|16:9|NIV}}), he appears to [[Mary Magdalene]], [[Saint Peter|Peter]], [[Cleopas]], and others. &quot;On the evening of that first day of the week&quot; (Roman time), or the evening beginning the second day (Hebrew time), the resurrected Jesus appears at a meeting of ten apostles and other disciples ({{Bibleverse||Jn.|20:19|NIV}}). The same time of the week &quot;a week later&quot; (NIV) or, more literally, &quot;after eight days again&quot; inclusive (KJV), Jesus appears to the eleven apostles and others ({{Bibleverse||Jn.|20:26}}). After Jesus ascends ({{Bibleverse||Ac.|1:9}}), on the feast of [[Pentecost]] or [[Shavuot]] (the 50th day from Firstfruits and thus usually calculated as the first day of the week), the Spirit of God is given to the disciples, who baptize 3,000 people into the apostolic fellowship. Later, on one occasion in [[Troad|Troas]], the early Christians meet on the first day (Hebrew) to break bread and to listen to Christian preaching ({{Bibleverse||Ac.|20:7}}). Paul also states that the churches of [[Corinth]] and [[Galatia]] should set aside donations on the first day for collection ({{Bibleverse|1|Cor.|16:2}}). [[Didache]] 14:1 (AD 70-120?) contains an ambiguous text, translated by Roberts as, &quot;But every Lord's day gather yourselves together, and break bread, and give thanksgiving&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[Didache]]|chapter=14:1|url=http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/didache-roberts.html|publisher=Early Christian Writings|others=Roberts, trans}}&lt;/ref&gt; the first clause in Greek, &quot;[[wikt:κατά|κατά]] {{lang|grc|[[wikt:κυριακήν|κυριακήν]]}} [[wikt:δέ|δέ]] [[wikt:κύριος|κυρίου]]&quot;, literally means &quot;On the Lord's of the Lord&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Holmes, M|title=The Apostolic Fathers: Greek Texts and English Translations}}&lt;/ref&gt; and translators supply the elided noun (e.g., &quot;day&quot;, &quot;commandment&quot; (from 13:7), or &quot;doctrine&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Strand, Kenneth A.|title=The Sabbath in Scripture and History|pages=347–8|location=[[Washington, D.C.]]|publisher=Review and Herald Publishing Association|year=1982}} In {{cite book|author=Morgan, Kevin|title=Sabbath Rest|pages=37–8|year=2002|publisher=TEACH Services, Inc}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gleason Archer]] regards this as clearly referring to Sunday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Archer|first=Gleason L|title=An Encyclopedia of Bible Difficulties|authorlink=Gleason Archer|page=114|url=http://www.tsbalan.com/books/Difficulties.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Breaking bread may refer to [[communion (Christian)|Christian fellowship]], [[agape feast]]s, or [[Eucharist]] (cf. {{Bibleverse||Ac.|2:42}}, {{Bibleverse-nb||Ac.|20:7}}). Other interpreters believe these references do not support the concept of transfer of the seventh-day rest, and some add that they do not sufficiently prove that Sunday observance was an established practice in the primitive New Testament church.

==Origin of Sunday rest==
{{Main|Early Christianity}}
Though the majority observance of Christian Sabbath is as Sunday rest, this development was gradual. In the 2nd century, the observance of a corporate day of worship on the first day (Sunday, or Saturday night) had become commonplace as attested in the patristic writings. For such worshipers the term &quot;Lord's Day&quot; came to mean the first day or Sunday. From the 4th century onwards, Sunday worship has also taken on the observance of Sunday rest in some Christian traditions, such as the Puritans of the 16th and 17th centuries. Among these &quot;first-day Sabbatarians&quot;, Sunday worship and/or rest eventually became synonymous with a first-day Christian Sabbath.

===Seventh-day rest===
In the first centuries, the first day, being made a festival in honor of Christ's resurrection, received attention as a day of religious services and recreation, but seventh-day Sabbath rest was still observed by &quot;almost all churches&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crcbermuda.com/reference/ellen-white-books-g-m/great-controversy/1899-chap-3-an-era-of-spiritual-darkness|title=The Great Controversy|page=52|authorlink=Ellen G. White|first=Ellen G|last=White}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=socrates&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/26015.htm|title=Church History, Book V|author=[[Socrates Scholasticus]]|quote=For although almost all churches throughout the world celebrate the sacred mysteries on the sabbath of every week, yet the Christians of Alexandria and at Rome, on account of some ancient tradition, have ceased to do this. The Egyptians in the neighborhood of Alexandria, and the inhabitants of Thebaïs, hold their religious assemblies on the sabbath, but do not participate of the mysteries in the manner usual among Christians in general: for after having eaten and satisfied themselves with food of all kinds, in the evening making their offerings they partake of the mysteries.}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to classical sources, widespread seventh-day Sabbath rest by Gentile Christians was also the prevailing mode in the 3rd and 4th centuries.&lt;ref name=socrates/&gt;&lt;ref name=sozomen/&gt;

===Nonobservance===
Early Christian observance of both spiritual seventh-day Sabbath and Lord's Day assembly is evidenced in [[Ignatius of Antioch|Ignatius]]'s letter to the [[Magnesia on the Maeander|Magnesians]] ca. 110.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Epistle to the Magnesians|author=Ignatius|authorlink=Ignatius of Antioch|volume=9|url=http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/text/ignatius-magnesians-roberts.html|publisher=Early Christian Writings}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bauckham/&gt; Ambiguity arises due to textual variants. The only extant Greek parent manuscript of the letter, the ''Codex Mediceus Laurentius'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.textexcavation.com/epistlesignatius.html|first=Bart|last=Ehrman|authorlink=Bart Ehrman|pages=214–5|volume=1|edition=Loeb|title=The Apostolic Fathers}}&lt;/ref&gt; says, &quot;Those who had walked in ancient practices attained unto newness of hope, no longer observing Sabbath, but living according to the Lord's life ...&quot; (''kata kyriaken zoen zontes'').&lt;ref name=guy&gt;{{cite book|title=&quot;The Lord's Day&quot; in the Letter of Ignatius to the Magnesians|first=Fritz|last=Guy|publisher=La Sierra College|url=http://www.auss.info/auss_publication_file.php?pub_id=371&amp;journal=1&amp;type=pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; The expanded Pseudo-Ignatian version of Magnesians, possibly from the middle of the [[Christianity in the 3rd century|3rd century]], rewrites this passage to make &quot;Lord's&quot; refer to the first day (the variant textual reading of ''kata kyriaken zontes'', &quot;living according to the Lord's&quot;, is supported by the medieval Latin manuscript ''Codex Caiensis 395'', ''&quot;secundum Dominicam viventes&quot;'').&lt;ref name=guy/&gt;&lt;ref name=laverdiere&gt;{{cite book|title=The Eucharist in the New Testament and the Early Church|first=Eugene|last=LaVerdiere|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=j1BjjBe4dL4C&amp;pg=PA154|pages=144, 154, 201|publisher=Liturgical Press|year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pseudo-Ignatius amplified this point by combining weekly observance of spiritual seventh-day Sabbath with the Lord's assembly: &quot;Let us therefore no longer keep the Sabbath after the Jewish manner, and rejoice in days of idleness .... But let every one of you keep the Sabbath after a spiritual manner, rejoicing in meditation on the law, not in relaxation of the body, admiring the workmanship of God, and not eating things prepared the day before, nor using lukewarm drinks, and walking within a prescribed space, nor finding delight in dancing and plaudits which have no sense in them. And after the observance of the Sabbath, let every friend of Christ keep the Lord's [Day, ''Dominicam''] as a festival, the resurrection-day, the queen and chief of all the days.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Ignatius|title=Epistle to the Magnesians|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.v.iii.ix.html|volume=9|authorlink=Ignatius of Antioch|publisher=Christian Classics Ethereal Library}}&lt;/ref&gt; If Pseudo-Ignatius dates as early as 140, its admonition must be considered important evidence on 2nd-century Sabbath and Lord's Day observance.&lt;ref name=guy/&gt;

The 1st-&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=A.T|last=Robertson|title=Redating the New Testament}}&lt;/ref&gt; or 2nd-century [[Epistle of Barnabas]] or [[Pseudo-Barnabas]] on {{Bibleverse||Is.|1:13}} regards &quot;Sabbaths of the present age&quot; as unacceptable in favor of one spiritual seventh-day Sabbath that ushers in &quot;[[the eighth day (Christian)|the eighth day]]&quot; and commencement of a new world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|others=Staniforth, Maxwell, trans|title=[[Epistle of Barnabas]]|volume=15}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-2nd century, [[Justin Martyr]], who attended worship on the first day,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Justin Martyr|title=First Apology|volume=67|authorlink=Justin Martyr}}&lt;/ref&gt; wrote about the cessation of Sabbath observance and stated that Sabbath was enjoined as a temporary sign to Israel because of Israel's sinfulness,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=[[Dialogue with Trypho]]|author=[[Justin Martyr]]|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.viii.iv.xxi.html|volume=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; no longer needed after Christ came without sin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=[[Dialogue with Trypho]]|author=[[Justin Martyr]]|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.viii.iv.xxiii.html|volume=23}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tertullian]] (early 3rd century) also said &quot;to [us] Sabbaths are strange&quot; and unobserved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=[[Tertullian]]|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf03.iv.iv.xiv.html|title=On Idolatry|volume=14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sunday rest===
The origin of Sunday worship in the 1st or 2nd century remains a debated point. Often first-day worship (Sunday morning or Saturday night) was practiced alongside observance of seventh-day Sabbath rest&lt;ref name=Bauckham&gt;{{cite book|chapter=Sabbath and Sunday in the Post-Apostolic Church|first=R.J.|last=Bauckham|title=From Sabbath to Lord's Day|editor1-first=Don A|editor1-last=Carson|year=1982|publisher=Wipf &amp; Stock Publishers/Zondervan|pages=252–98|editor-link=Don Carson|isbn=978-1-57910-307-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was a widespread Christian tradition by the 2nd century;&lt;ref name=Bauckham2/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See [[Bardaisan]] (c. 154), [[Cyprian]] (c. 200), and [[Victorinus of Pettau]] (c. 280).&lt;/ref&gt; over time, Sunday thus came to be known as Lord's Day and, later, a rest day.

On March 7, 321, the [[Constantine I and Christianity|Roman Emperor Constantine]] issued a decree making Sunday a day of rest from labor, stating:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Joseph Cullen|last=Ayer|title=A Source Book for Ancient Church History|location=[[New York City]]|publisher=Charles Scribner's Sons|year=1913|volume=2.1.1.59g|pages=284–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{quote|All judges and city people and the craftsmen shall rest upon the venerable day of the sun. Country people, however, may freely attend to the cultivation of the fields, because it frequently happens that no other days are better adapted for planting the grain in the furrows or the vines in trenches. So that the advantage given by heavenly providence may not for the occasion of a short time perish.}} 

Some church authorities opposed widespread seventh-day Sabbath observance as a [[Judaizing]] tendency.&lt;ref name=Bauckham/&gt; For example, the [[Council of Laodicea]] (canon 29) required Christians to separate from Jewish laws and traditions, stating that Christians must not Judaize by resting on Sabbath, but must work that day and then, if possible, rest on the Lord's Day, and that any found to be Judaizers were declared [[anathema]] from Christ.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.viii.vii.iii.liv.html|title=The Seven Ecumenical Councils|publisher=Christian Classics Ethereal Library}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was consistent with Constantine's personal position towards Jewry,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=[[Eusebius]]|title=Life of Constantine|Constantine's letter to the churches respecting the Council at Nicæa. 'Constantinus Augustus, to the churches: .... Let us then have nothing in common with the detestable Jewish crowd; for we have received from our Saviour a different way.'|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/25023.htm|volume=3|chapter=17-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;test&quot;&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/26015.htm CHURCH FATHERS: Church History, Book V Chapter 22 (Socrates Scholasticus)].&lt;/ref&gt; which has been described by the primitive Christianity movement as being [[anti-Semitic]], [[antinomian]], and [[persecution]] of seventh-day observers.{{citation needed|date=April 2012}} Simultaneously [[Rabbinical Judaism]] was distinguishing itself from primitive Christianity.

==Middle ages==
{{See also|Law in Christianity}}
[[Augustine of Hippo]] followed the early patristic writers in spiritualizing the meaning of the Sabbath commandment, referring it to eschatological rest rather than observance of a literal day. However, the practice of Sunday rest increased in prominence throughout the early Middle Ages.&lt;ref name=Bauckham3/&gt; [[Thomas Aquinas]] taught that the [[Ten Commandments|Decalogue]] is an expression of [[natural law]] which binds all men, and therefore the Sabbath commandment is a moral requirement along with the other nine. Thus Sunday rest and Sabbath became increasingly associated.&lt;ref name=Bauckham3&gt;{{cite book|chapter=Sabbath and Sunday in the Medieval Church in the West|first=R.J.|last=Bauckham|title=From Sabbath to Lord's Day|editor1-first=Don A|editor1-last=Carson|year=1982|pages=299–310|publisher=Wipf &amp; Stock Publishers/Zondervan|editor-link=Don Carson|isbn=978-1-57910-307-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protestantism===
[[File:Recreation ground on the Isle of Raasay - geograph.org.uk - 1476596.jpg|thumb|260px|A recreation ground on [[Raasay]] displaying a sign &quot;Please do not use this playing field on Sundays&quot;.]]
{{see also|Abrogation of Old Covenant laws}}

According to Bauckham, the reformers [[Martin Luther]] and [[John Calvin]] repudiated the idea that Christians are bound to obey the Mosaic law, including the fourth commandment of the Decalogue concerning Sabbath, although they followed Aquinas's concept of natural law. They viewed Sunday rest as a civic institution established by human authority, which provided an occasion for bodily rest and public worship.&lt;ref name=Bauckham4&gt;{{cite book|chapter=Sabbath and Sunday in the Protestant Tradition|first=R.J.|last=Bauckham|title=From Sabbath to Lord's Day|editor1-first=Don A|editor1-last=Carson|year=1982|pages=311–42|publisher=Wipf &amp; Stock Publishers/Zondervan|editor-link=Don Carson|isbn=978-1-57910-307-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his work against the [[Antinomians]], Luther rejected the idea that he had taught the abolition of the Ten Commandments.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Luther, ''Wider die Antinomer'' (''Against the Antinomians''), secs. 6, 8, in his Sämmtliche Schriften, ed. by Joh[ann] Georg Walch, Vol. 20 (St. Louis: Concordia, 1890), cols. 1613, 1614. German.&lt;/ref&gt; Another Protestant Reformer, [[John Wesley]], stated &quot;This 'handwriting of ordinances' our Lord did blot out, take away, and nail to His cross. (Colossians 2:14.) But the moral law contained in the Ten Commandments, and enforced by the prophets, He did not take away .... The moral law stands on an entirely different foundation from the ceremonial or ritual law .... Every part of this law must remain in force upon all mankind and in all ages.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;John Wesley, &quot;Sermons on Several Occasions,&quot; 2-Vol. Edition, Vol. I, pages 221, 222.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sunday Sabbatarianism became prevalent amongst both the continental and English Protestants over the following century. A new rigorism was brought into the observance of the Christian Lord's Day among the 17th-century [[Puritan]]s of England and Scotland, in reaction to the laxity with which Sunday observance was customarily kept. Sabbath ordinances were appealed to, with the idea that only the [[Bible|word of God]] can bind men's consciences in whether or how they will take a break from work, or to impose an obligation to meet at a particular time. Their influential reasoning spread to other denominations also, and it is primarily through their influence that &quot;Sabbath&quot; has become the colloquial equivalent of &quot;Lord's Day&quot; or &quot;Sunday&quot;. Sunday Sabbatarianism is enshrined in its most mature expression, the [[Westminster Confession of Faith]] (1646), in the [[Calvinist]] theological tradition. Chapter 21, ''Of Religious Worship, and the Sabbath Day'', sections 7-8 read: {{quote|7. As it is the law of nature, that, in general, a due proportion of time be set apart for the worship of God; so, in his Word, by a positive, moral, and perpetual commandment binding all men in all ages, he hath particularly appointed one day in seven, for a Sabbath, to be kept holy unto him: which, from the beginning of the world to the resurrection of Christ, was the last day of the week; and, from the resurrection of Christ, was changed into the first day of the week, which, in Scripture, is called the Lord’s day, and is to be continued to the end of the world, as the Christian Sabbath.&lt;br&gt;8. This Sabbath is then kept holy unto the Lord, when men, after a due preparing of their hearts, and ordering of their common affairs beforehand, do not only observe a holy rest, all the day, from their own works, words, and thoughts about their worldly employments and recreations, but also are taken up, the whole time, in the public and private exercises of his worship, and in the duties of necessity and mercy.}} The confession holds that not only is work forbidden in Sunday, but also &quot;works, words, and thoughts&quot; about &quot;worldly employments and recreations.&quot; Instead, the whole day should be taken up with &quot;public and private exercises of [one's] worship, and in the duties of necessity and mercy.&quot;

Strict Sunday Sabbatarianism is sometimes called &quot;[[Puritan]] Sabbath&quot;, often contrasted with &quot;Continental Sabbath&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Marsden|first=George|author-link=George Marsden|title=Understanding Fundamentalism and Evangelicalism|year=1991|publisher=[[Eerdmans]]|page=25|url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=3NBLzpLP4NgC&amp;pg=PA25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The latter follows the [[Continental Europe|continental]] [[Reformed churches|reformed]] [[Reformed Christian confessions of faith|confessions]], such as the [[Heidelberg Catechism]], which emphasize rest and worship on the [[Lord's Day]], but do not forbid recreational activities.&lt;ref&gt;[[Heidelberg Catechism]], Q &amp; A 103.&lt;/ref&gt;

Though first-day Sabbatarian practice declined in the 18th century, the [[evangelical awakening]] in the 19th century led to a greater concern for strict Sunday observance. The founding of the [[Lord's Day Observance Society]] in 1831 was influenced by the teaching of Daniel Wilson.&lt;ref name=Bauckham4/&gt;

==Modern first-day churches==
{{See also|Lord's Day}}

===Roman Catholicism===
In 1998 [[Pope John Paul II]] wrote an [[apostolic letter]] ''Dies Domini'',&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_letters/documents/hf_jp-ii_apl_05071998_dies-domini_en.html&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;on keeping the Lord's day holy&quot;. He encourages Catholics to remember the importance of keeping Sunday holy, urging that it not lose its meaning by being blended with a frivolous &quot;[[Workweek|weekend]]&quot; mentality.

In the [[Western Catholic]] Church, &quot;Sabbath&quot; is a synonym of &quot;[[Lord's Day]]&quot; (Sunday), which is kept in commemoration of the [[resurrection of Christ]], and celebrated with the [[Eucharist]] (Catholic Catechism 2177).&lt;ref name=ccc/&gt; It is also the day of [[leisure|rest]]. Lord's Day is considered both the first day and &quot;[[the eighth day (Christian)|the eighth day]]&quot; of the [[seven-day week]], symbolizing both first creation and new creation (2174).&lt;ref name=ccc&gt;U.S. Catholic Conference 1997, pp. 580–6.&lt;/ref&gt; Roman Catholics view the first day as a day for assembly for worship (2178, {{Bibleverse||Heb.|10:25}}),&lt;ref name=ccc/&gt; but consider a day of rigorous rest not obligatory on Christians ({{Bibleverse||Rom.|14:5}}, {{Bibleverse||Col.|2:16}}).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sabbath|work=The Catholic Encyclopedia|year=1913|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13287b.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Catholics count the prohibition of servile work as transferred from seventh-day Sabbath to Sunday (2175-6),&lt;ref name=ccc/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ten Commandments|work=The Catholic Encyclopedia|year=1913|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13287a.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; but do not hinder participation in &quot;ordinary and innocent occupations&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sabbatarians|work=The Catholic Encyclopedia|year=1913|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13287a.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cardinal Gibbons affirmed Sunday Sabbath as a sign of the Roman Catholic Church's sufficiency as guide: {{quote|Now the Scriptures alone do not contain all the truths which a Christian is bound to believe, nor do they explicitly enjoin all the duties which he is obliged to practice. Not to mention other examples, is not every Christian obliged to sanctify Sunday and to abstain on that day from unnecessary servile work? Is not the observance of this law among the most prominent of our sacred duties? But you may read the Bible from Genesis to Revelation, and you will not find a single line authorizing the sanctification of Sunday. The Scriptures enforce the religious observance of Saturday, a day which we never sanctify.|''Faith of Our Fathers'', Cardinal Gibbons, p. 72 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.cathcorn.org/foof/8.html|author=Gibbons, James|title=Faith of Our Fathers|chapter=VIII. The Church and the Bible|page=72}}&lt;/ref&gt;|}}

===Lutheranism===
[[Lutheranism|Lutheran]] founder [[Martin Luther]] stated &quot;I wonder exceedingly how it came to be imputed to me that I should reject the law of Ten Commandments...Whosoever abrogates the law must of necessity abrogate sin also.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Martin Luther, Spiritual Antichrist|pages=71–2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lutheran [[Augsburg Confession]], speaking of changes made by Roman Catholic Pontiffs, states: &quot;They refer to the Sabbath-day as having been changed into the Lord's Day, contrary to the Decalog, as it seems. Neither is there any example whereof they make more than concerning the changing of the Sabbath-day. Great, say they, is the power of the Church, since it has dispensed with one of the Ten Commandments!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;The [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/275/275-h/275-h.htm Augsburg Confession], 1530 A.D. (Lutheran), part 2, art 7, in Philip Schaff, the Creeds of Christiandom, 4th Edition, vol 3, p64&lt;/ref&gt; Lutheran church historian Augustus Neander&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/neander_a Biography of Augustus Neander]&lt;/ref&gt; states &quot;The festival of Sunday, like all other festivals, was always only a human ordinance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Augustus Neander, &quot;History of the Christian Religion and Church,&quot; Vol. 1, page 186&lt;/ref&gt;

Lutheran writer [[Marva Dawn]] keeps a whole day as Sabbath, advocating for rest during any weekly complete 24-hour period&lt;ref&gt;Dawn 2006, pp. 55–6.&lt;/ref&gt; and favoring rest from Saturday sunset to Sunday sunset,&lt;ref&gt;Dawn 1989, Appendix. In {{cite book|last=Bacchiocchi|first=Samuele|authorlink=Samuele Bacchiocchi|title=The Sabbath Under Crossfire: A Biblical Analysis Of Recent Sabbath/Sunday Developments|publisher=Biblical Perspectives|url=http://sdanet.org/atissue/sabbath/bacchiocchi.htm|year=1998|chapter=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; but regarding corporate worship as &quot;an essential part of God's Sabbath reclamation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dawn 2006, pp. 69–71.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Baptists===
The Baptist Church Manual states &quot;We believe that the law of God is the eternal and unchangeable rule of His moral government.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Baptist Church Manual, Article 12&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other Protestants===
The founder of the [[Moody Bible Institute]] states, &quot;Sabbath was binding in Eden, and it has been in force ever since. This fourth commandment begins with the word 'remember,' showing that the Sabbath already existed when God wrote the law on the tables of stone at Sinai. How can men claim that this one commandment has been done away with when they will admit that the other nine are still binding?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;D.L. MOODY, &quot;Weighed and Wanting,&quot; page 47&lt;/ref&gt;

Organizations that promote Sunday Sabbatarianism include [[Day One Christian Ministries]].

===Latter Day Saints===
{{see also|Sacrament meeting|Worship services of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints}}
In 1831, [[Joseph Smith]] published a revelation commanding his related movement, the formative [[Church of Christ (Latter Day Saints)|Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]], to go to the house of prayer, offer up their sacraments, rest from their labors, and pay their devotions on the Lord's day (D&amp;C 59:9–12). [[Latter-day Saints]] believe this means performing no labor that would keep them from giving their full attention to spiritual matters (Ex. 20:10). LDS prophets have described this as meaning they should not shop, hunt, fish, attend sports events, or participate in similar activities on that day. Elder [[Spencer W. Kimball]] taught that mere idle lounging on Sabbath does not keep the day holy, and that Sabbath calls for constructive thoughts and acts ([[Miracle of Forgiveness]], pp.&amp;nbsp;96–97).

Latter-day Saints are encouraged to prepare only simple foods on Sabbath (D&amp;C 59:13, Is. 58:13) and believe the day is only for righteous activities. In most areas of the world, Latter-day Saints worship on Sunday, but in parts of the world where traditional Sabbath is on another day, such as in [[Israel]] or in [[Saudi Arabia]], Latter-day Saints observe local Sabbath.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lds.org/study/topics/sabbath?lang=eng LDS.org - Study by Topic - Sabbath]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Seventh-day Sabbath==
[[File:Sabbatarian Meeting House.jpg|thumb|right|Oldest Sabbatarian Meeting House in America ([[Seventh Day Baptist]]), built in 1729 in [[Newport, Rhode Island]], now owned by [[Newport Historical Society]].]]
{{Main|Sabbath in seventh-day churches}}
{{See also|Saturday|List of Sabbath-keeping churches}}

===Apostolic history===
The Bible records that the followers of Christ kept the seventh-day Sabbath that immediately followed the crucifixion of Jesus ({{bibleverse||Luke|23:52-56|}}).

In the 4th century, [[Socrates Scholasticus]] (''Church History, Book V'') stated:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/26015.htm|title=Church History, Book V|author=[[Socrates Scholasticus]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{quote|For although almost all churches throughout the world celebrate the sacred mysteries on the sabbath of every week, yet the Christians of Alexandria and at Rome, on account of some ancient tradition, have ceased to do this. The Egyptians in the neighborhood of Alexandria, and the inhabitants of Thebaïs, hold their religious assemblies on the sabbath, but do not participate of the mysteries in the manner usual among Christians in general: for after having eaten and satisfied themselves with food of all kinds, in the evening making their offerings they partake of the mysteries.}}

In the 5th century, [[Sozomen]] (''Ecclesiastical History, Book VII''), referencing Socrates Scholasticus, added to this description:&lt;ref name=sozomen&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/26027.htm|title=Ecclesiastical History, Book VII|author=[[Sozomen]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{quote|Assemblies are not held in all churches on the same time or manner. The people of Constantinople, and almost everywhere, assemble together on the Sabbath, as well as on the first day of the week, which custom is never observed at Rome or at Alexandria. There are several cities and villages in Egypt where, contrary to the usage established elsewhere, the people meet together on Sabbath evenings, and, although they have dined previously, partake of the mysteries.}}

===Pre-Reformation===
Seventh-day Sabbath was observed at least sporadically by a minority of groups during the Middle Ages. An Eastern body of Christian Sabbath-keepers mentioned from the 8th century to the 12th is called Athenians (&quot;touch-not&quot;) because they abstained from uncleanness and intoxicating drinks, called Athinginians in Neander: &quot;This sect, which had its principal seat in the city of Armorion, in upper Phrygia, where many Jews resided, sprung out of a mixture of Judaism and Christianity. They united baptism with the observance of all the rites of Judaism, circumcision excepted. We may perhaps recognize a branch of the older Judaizing sects.&lt;ref&gt;Neander, fourth period, 6, 428.&lt;/ref&gt;

Cardinal Hergenrother says that they stood in intimate relation with Emperor Michael II (AD 821-829), and testifies that they observed Sabbath.&lt;ref&gt;Kirchengeschichte, I, 527&lt;/ref&gt; As late as the 11th century Cardinal Humbert still referred to the Nazarenes as a Sabbath-keeping Christian body existing at that time. But in the 10th and 11th centuries, there was a great extension of sects from the East to the West. Neander states that the corruption of the clergy furnished a most important vantage-ground on which to attack the dominant church. The abstemious life of these Christians, the simplicity and earnestness of their preaching and teaching, had their effect. “Thus we find them emerging at once in the eleventh century, in countries the most diverse, and the most remote from each other, in Italy, France, and even in the Harz districts in Germany.” Likewise, also, “traces of Sabbath-keepers are found in the times of Gregory I, Gregory VII, and in the twelfth century in Lombardy.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://dedication.www3.50megs.com/historyofsabbath/hos_twentyone_b.html#027 See quotation of Strong’s Cyclopedia, New York, 1874, I, 660]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-Reformation===
Seventh-day Sabbatarianism was advocated in England by John Traske (1586–1636) and Thomas Brabourne, whose ideas gave rise to the [[Seventh-day Baptists]].

===Seventh-day churches===
{{See also|Seventh-day Adventist worship|Armstrongism}}
The [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]] arose in the mid-19th century in America, having inherited seventh-day Sabbatarianism from the Seventh-day Baptists.

Fundamental Belief # 20 of the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]] states: {{quote|The beneficent Creator, after the six days of Creation, rested on the seventh day and instituted the Sabbath for all people as a memorial of Creation. The fourth commandment of God's unchangeable law requires the observance of this seventh-day Sabbath as the day of rest, worship, and ministry in harmony with the teaching and practice of Jesus, the Lord of the Sabbath. The Sabbath is a day of delightful communion with God and one another. It is a symbol of our redemption in Christ, a sign of our sanctification, a token of our allegiance, and a foretaste of our eternal future in God's kingdom. The Sabbath is God's perpetual sign of His eternal covenant between Him and His people. Joyful observance of this holy time from evening to evening, sunset to sunset, is a celebration of God's creative and redemptive acts. (Gen. 2:1-3; Ex. 20:8-11; Luke 4:16; Isa. 56:5, 6; 58:13, 14; Matt. 12:1-12; Ex. 31:13-17; Eze. 20:12, 20; Deut. 5:12-15; Heb. 4:1-11; Lev. 23:32; Mark 1:32.)|Seventh-day Adventist Fundamental Beliefs&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adventist.org/beliefs/fundamental/index.html Seventh-day Adventist Fundamental Beliefs]&lt;/ref&gt;|}}

The [[Worldwide Church of God]] ([[Armstrongism]]) taught seventh-day Sabbath observance. The [[United Church of God]] teaches seventh-day Sabbath observance.

Seventh-day Protestants regard Sabbath as a day of rest for all mankind and not Israel alone, based on Jesus's statement, &quot;the Sabbath was made for man&quot; (i.e., purposed for humankind at the time of its creation, {{Bibleverse||Mark|2:27|NIV}}, cf. {{Bibleverse||Heb.|4|NIV}}), and on [[Sabbath in Christianity#Epistles|early-church Sabbath meetings]]. Seventh-day Sabbatarianism has also been criticized as an effort to combine [[Old Testament]] laws, practiced in Judaism, with [[Christianity]], or to revive the [[Judaizers]] of the [[Epistles]] or the [[Ebionite]]s.

===Eastern Christianity===
{{Multiple issues|section=yes|unreferenced=October 2010|original research=October 2010}}
The [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox]] church distinguishes between &quot;Sabbath&quot; (Saturday) and &quot;Lord's Day&quot; (Sunday), and both continue to play a special role for the faithful. Many parishes and monasteries will serve the [[Divine Liturgy]] on both Saturday morning and Sunday morning. The church never allows strict fasting on any Saturday (except [[Holy Saturday]]) or Sunday, and the fasting rules on those Saturdays and Sundays which fall during one of the fasting seasons (such as [[Great Lent]], [[Apostles' Fast]], etc.) are always relaxed to some degree. During Great Lent, when the celebration of the Liturgy is forbidden on weekdays, there is always Liturgy on Saturday as well as Sunday. The church also has a special cycle of Bible readings ([[Epistle]] and [[Gospel]]) for Saturdays and Sundays which is different from the cycle of readings allotted to weekdays. However, the Lord's Day, being a celebration of the Resurrection, is clearly given more emphasis. For instance, in the [[Russian Orthodox Church]] Sunday is always observed with an [[All-Night Vigil]] on Saturday night, and in all of the Orthodox Churches it is amplified with special hymns which are chanted only on Sunday. If a [[feast day]] falls on a Sunday it is always combined with the [[Octoechos (liturgy)|hymns for Sunday]] (unless it is a [[Great Feast]] of the Lord). Saturday is celebrated as a sort of [[leave-taking]] for the previous Sunday, on which several of the hymns from the previous Sunday are repeated.

In part, Orthodox Christians continue to celebrate Saturday as Sabbath because of its role in the history of salvation: it was on a Saturday that Jesus &quot;rested&quot; in the [[Holy Sepulchre|tomb]] after his [[Passion (Christianity)|work on the cross]]. For this reason also, Saturday is a day for general [[prayer for the dead|commemoration of the departed]], and special [[Pannikhida|requiem hymns]] are often chanted on this day.

The [[Ethiopian Orthodox]] church (part of the [[Oriental Orthodox]] communion, having about 40 million members) observes both Saturday and Sunday as holy, but places extra emphasis on Sunday.

===Eschatology===
{{See also|Seventh-day Adventist eschatology}}

==Non-Sabbatarianism==
{{Main|Non-Sabbatarianism}}
[[Justin Martyr]], writing in the 2nd century, rejected the need to keep literal seventh-day Sabbath, arguing instead that &quot;the new law requires you to keep the sabbath constantly.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|author=Justin Martyr|title=[[Dialogue with Trypho]] 12:3|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf01.viii.iv.xii.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, [[Irenaeus]] wrote that the Christian &quot;will not be commanded to leave idle one day of rest, who is constantly keeping sabbath&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=[[Irenaeus]]|title=Demonstration of the Apostolic Preaching|volume=96|year=late 2d cen.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Tertullian]] argued &quot;that we still more ought to observe a sabbath from all servile work always, and not only every seventh-day, but through all time&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|author=Tertullian|title=Adv. Jud. 4:2|url=http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/anf03.iv.ix.iv.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; This early metaphorical interpretation of Sabbath applied it to the entire Christian life.&lt;ref name=Bauckham/&gt; Augustine, Luther and Calvin taught that the Sabbath commandment of the Decalogue is not binding on Christians as a legal requirement. Other historical non-Sabbatarians from more recent times include the Anglicans [[Peter Heylin]], [[William Paley]] and [[John Milton]]; the nonconformist [[Philip Doddridge]]; the [[Quaker]] [[Robert Barclay]]; and [[Congregationalist]] [[James Baldwin Brown]].&lt;ref name=Bauckham4/&gt;

==Other definitions==
{{Main|Seven-day week}}
By [[synecdoche]] the term &quot;Sabbath&quot; in the [[New Testament]] may also mean simply a &quot;[[se'nnight]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Strong's Concordance]].&lt;/ref&gt; or seven-day week, namely, the interval between two Sabbaths. [[Jesus]]'s parable of the [[Pharisee and the Publican]] describes the [[Pharisee]] as fasting &quot;twice a week&quot; (Greek ''dis tou sabbatou'', literally, &quot;twice of the Sabbath&quot;).

{{Main|High Sabbaths}}
Seven annual Biblical festivals, called by the name ''miqra'' (&quot;called assembly&quot;) in Hebrew and &quot;[[High Sabbath]]&quot; in English, serve as supplemental testimonies to Sabbath. These are recorded in the books of [[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] and [[Deuteronomy]] and do not necessarily occur on Sabbath. They are observed by Jews and a minority of Christians. Three of them occur in spring: the first and seventh days of [[Passover (Christian holiday)|Passover]], and [[Pentecost]]. Four occur in fall, in the seventh month, and are also called ''Shabbaton'': [[Feast of Trumpets (Christian holiday)|Trumpets]]; [[Christian observances of Yom Kippur|Atonement]], &quot;Sabbath of Sabbaths&quot;; and the first and eighth days of [[Christian observances of Jewish holidays#Feast of Tabernacles|Tabernacles]].

{{Main|Shmita}}
The year of ''[[Shmita]]'' (Hebrew שמיטה, literally, &quot;release&quot;), also called Sabbatical Year, is the seventh year of the seven-year agricultural cycle mandated by the [[Torah]] for the [[Land of Israel]]. During ''Shmita'', the land is to be left to lie fallow. A second aspect of ''Shmita'' concerns debts and loans: when the year ends, personal debts are considered nullified and forgiven.

{{Main|Shabbat}}
Jewish ''[[Shabbat]]'' is a weekly day of rest cognate to Christian Sabbath, observed from sundown on Friday until the appearance of three stars in the sky on Saturday night; it is also observed by a minority of Christians. Customarily, ''Shabbat'' is ushered in by lighting [[candle]]s shortly before sunset, at [[halakhic]]ally calculated times that change from week to week and from place to place.

{{Main|New moon}}
The [[new moon]], occurring every 29 or 30 days, is an important separately sanctioned occasion in Judaism and some other faiths. It is not widely regarded as Sabbath, but some [[Hebrew Roots|Messianic]] and [[Pentecostal]] churches, such as the native New Israelites of Peru and the [[Creation Seventh Day Adventist Church]], do keep the day of the new moon as Sabbath or rest day, from evening to evening. New-moon services can last all day.

{{Main|Day of the Vow}}
In [[South Africa]], Christian [[Boer]]s have celebrated December 16, now called the [[Day of Reconciliation]], as annual Sabbath (holy day of thanksgiving) since 1838, commemorating a famous Boer victory over the [[Zulu Kingdom|Zulu]].

{{Main|Millennialism}}
Many early Christian writers from the 2nd century, such as [[pseudo-Barnabas]], [[Irenaeus]], [[Justin Martyr]] and [[Hippolytus of Rome]] followed [[rabbinic Judaism]] (the ''Mishna'') in interpreting Sabbath not as a literal day of rest, but as a thousand-year reign of Jesus Christ, which would follow six millennia of world history.&lt;ref name=Bauckham/&gt;

{{Main|Blue law}}
Secular use of &quot;Sabbath&quot; for &quot;rest day&quot;, while it usually refers to Sunday, is often stated in [[North America]] to refer to different purposes for the rest day than those of [[Christendom]]. In ''[[McGowan v. Maryland]]'' (1961), the [[Supreme Court of the United States]] held that contemporary [[Maryland]] [[blue law]]s (typically, Sunday rest laws) were intended to promote the secular values of &quot;health, safety, recreation, and general well-being&quot; through a common day of rest, and that this day coinciding with majority Christian Sabbath neither reduces its effectiveness for secular purposes nor prevents adherents of other religions from observing their own holy days.

==References==
First-day:
*{{cite book|last=Dawn|first=Marva J.|authorlink=Marva Dawn|title=Keeping the Sabbath Wholly: Ceasing, Resting, Embracing, Feasting|location=[[Grand Rapids]]|year=1989}}
*{{cite book|last=Dawn|first=Marva J.|authorlink=Marva Dawn|title=The Sense of the Call: A Sabbath Way of Life for Those Who Serve God, the Church, and the World|year=2006}}
*{{cite book|title=Catechism of the Catholic Church|edition=2d|publisher=[[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]]|location=[[New York City]]|year=1997|author=United States Catholic Conference, Inc.|chapter=You Shall Love the Lord Your God with All Your Heart, and with All Your Soul, and with All Your Mind, Article 3, The Third Commandment|at=2168–2195}}

Seventh-day:
*{{cite book|last=Bacchiocchi|first=Samuele|authorlink=Samuele Bacchiocchi|title=From Sabbath to Sunday|publisher=Pontifical Gregorian University Press; Biblical Perspectives|year=1977|url=http://www.biblicalperspectives.com/books/sabbath_to_sunday/}}
*{{cite book|last=Bacchiocchi|first=Samuele|authorlink=Samuele Bacchiocchi|title=Divine Rest for Human Restlessness|publisher=Biblical Perspectives|date=June 1980|url=http://www.biblicalperspectives.com/books/rest_restlessness/|isbn=978-99946-1-024-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Bacchiocchi|first=Samuele|authorlink=Samuele Bacchiocchi|title=The Sabbath Under Crossfire: A Biblical Analysis Of Recent Sabbath/Sunday Developments|publisher=Biblical Perspectives|url=http://sdanet.org/atissue/sabbath/bacchiocchi.htm|year=1998}}
*{{cite book|last=Ford|first=Desmond|authorlink=Desmond Ford|title=The Forgotten Day|year=1981}}
*{{cite book|last=Strand|first=Kenneth A., ed.|title=The Sabbath in Scripture and History|date=July 1982|isbn=978-0-8280-0037-6|location=[[Washington, D.C.]]|publisher=Review and Herald Publishing Association}}
*{{cite book|last=Tonstad|first=Sigve K.|title=The Lost Meaning of the Seventh Day|date=November 2009|isbn=978-1-883925-65-9|location=[[Berrien Springs, Michigan]]|publisher=Andrews University Press|url=http://universitypress.andrews.edu/catalog.php?key=199}}

Non-Sabbatarian:
*{{cite book|title=Sabbatarianism Re-examined|authorlink=Robert Brinsmead|last=Brinsmead|first=Robert|publisher=Verdict Publishing 4:4|date=June 1981|url=http://www.exadventist.com/Home/Articles/sabbatarian/tabid/452/Default.aspx}}
*{{cite book|last=Ratzlaff|first=Dale|authorlink=Dale Ratzlaff|first2=Don|last2=Muth|first3=Richard|last3=Tinker|first4=Richard|last4=Fredericks|title=Sabbath in Christ|year=2003|origyear=1990}}

Varying:
*{{cite book|title=From Sabbath to Lord's Day|editor1-first=Don A.|editor1-last=Carson|year=1982|publisher=Wipf &amp; Stock Publishers/Zondervan|editor-link=Don Carson|isbn=978-1-57910-307-1}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Time in religion and mythology}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sabbath in Christianity}}
[[Category:Christian law]]
[[Category:Judeo-Christian topics]]
[[Category:Old Testament theology]]
[[Category:Ancient Christian controversies]]
[[Category:Christian theology]]
[[Category:Sabbath]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[fr:Sabbat (christianisme)]]
[[hr:Šabat u kršćanstvu]]
[[ia:Sabbato christian]]
[[nl:Sabbat (christendom)]]
[[ru:Суббота в христианстве]]
[[sh:Šabat u kršćanstvu]]
[[th:วันสะบาโต]]</text>
      <sha1>a0di4udvjw516pesvnufr4fjsecaoco</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
