<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sabians</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>324638</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518215667</id>
      <parentid>518137855</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-16T23:20:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Editor2020</username>
        <id>6046894</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/173.32.229.119|173.32.229.119]] ([[User talk:173.32.229.119|talk]]) to last version by Ibrahim ebi</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30136">{{about||the Canadian cymbal manufacturing company|Sabian (company)|the ancient people living in what is now Yemen|Sabaeans|the followers of [[Sabbatai Zevi]]|Sabbateans|the pre-Roman [[Ancient peoples of Italy|Italic]] tribe of [[Latium]]|Sabine|the modern Iraqi religious minority|Mandaeism|}}
The '''Sabians''' ({{lang-ar|'''صابئة'''}}) of Middle Eastern tradition were a [[monotheistic]] [[Abrahamic religion|Abrahamic]] religious group mentioned three times in the Quran with the [[people of the Book]], &quot;the Jews, the Sabians, and the Christians.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Lewis The Jews of Islam 1987 page 13&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''[[hadith]]'', they are described merely as converts to Islam,&lt;ref&gt;e.g. Sahih Bukhari Book #7 Hadith #340, Book #59 Hadith #628, and Book #89 Hadith #299 etc.&lt;/ref&gt; but interest in the identity and history of the group increased over time, and discussions and investigations about the Sabians begin to appear in later Islamic literature.

==In the Quran==
The Qur'an mentions briefly the Sabians in three places and the [[Hadith]] provide additional details as to who they were:

{{quote|
*&quot;Surely those who believe, and those who are Jews, and the Christians, and the Sabians, whoever believes in Allah and the Final Day and does good, they shall have their reward from their Lord, and there is no fear for them, nor shall they grieve.&quot; {{Cite quran|2|62}}
*&quot;Surely those who believe and those who are Jews and the Sabians and the Christians whoever believes in Allah and the Final Day and does good-- they shall have no fear nor shall they grieve.&quot; {{Cite quran|5|69}}
*&quot;Surely those who believe and those who are Jews and the Sabeans and the Christians and the Magians and those who associate (others with Allah)-- surely Allah will decide between them on the day of resurrection; surely Allah is a witness over all things.&quot; {{Cite quran|22|17}}}}

==In later Islamic sources==
According to Muslim authors, Sabians followed the fourth book of Abrahamic tradition, the ''[[Zabur]],'' which was given to the [[Prophets in Islam|prophet]] [[Islamic views on David|King David]] of [[Ancient Israel]] according to the Qur'an. The &quot;Zabur&quot; is identified by many modern scholars as the [[biblical]] Book of [[Psalms]]. Most of what is known of them comes from [[Ibn Wahshiyya]]'s ''The Nabatean Agriculture'', and the translation of this by [[Maimonides]].

Other classical Arabic sources include the ''[[Fihrist]]'' of [[Ibn al-Nadim]], (c. 987), who mentions the ''Mogtasilah'' (&quot;Mughtasila,&quot; or &quot;self-ablutionists&quot;), a sect of Sabians in southern Mesopotamia who counted El-Hasaih as their founder&lt;ref&gt;[[Daniel Chwolsohn]], ''Die Sabier,'' 1856, I, 112; II, 543, cited by Salmon.&lt;/ref&gt; and academics agree that they are probably the enigmatic &quot;Sobiai&quot; to whom [[Elcesaites|Elchasai]] preached in Parthia. According to [[Daniel Chwolsohn]] (1856) they appear to have gravitated around the original pro-Jewish [[Hanputa]] of [[Elchasai]] out of which the [[Antisemitism|miso-Judaic]] prophet [[Mani (prophet)|Mani]] seceded and are identified therefore as the pro-Torah ''Sampsaeans'' but also less accurately with the anti-Torah [[Mandaeism|Mandaeans]]. They were said by [[Khalil Ibn Ahmad]] (d.786) to believe that they &quot;belonged&quot; to the prophet [[Noah]].&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Khalil ‘ibn Ahmad&quot;&gt; [[Khalil Ibn Ahmad]] (d. 786-787 CE), who was in Basra before his death, wrote: “The Sabians believe they belong to the prophet Noah, they read Zaboor, and their religion looks like Christianity.” He also states that &quot;they worship the angels.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Some{{Who|date=August 2011}} supposed that they influenced the practices of the Hellenic [[Godfearers]] (''theosebeis'' {{Lang-el|Θεοσεβεῖς}}) while their [[angelology]] (based around the movements of the [[Sun]], [[Moon]], [[Mars]], [[Mercury (planet)|Mercury]], [[Jupiter]], [[Venus]] and [[Saturn]]) found its greatest development in the community which was based in the [[Harran]] region of south-eastern [[Anatolia]] and northern [[Syria]]. [[Ibn al-Qayyim]] distinguished them as the Sabians of Harran from the south Mesopotamian ''Sābi'ūna Hunafā''.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

==Etymology==
There has been much speculation as to the origins of the religious endonym from this practice. [[Judah Segal|Segal]] (1963)&lt;ref&gt;[[Judah Benzion Segal]], The Sabian Mysteries. The planet cult of ancient Harran, Vanished Civilizations, ed. by E. Bacon, London 1963&lt;/ref&gt; argued that the term Sābi'ūn derives from the Syriac root ''S-b-' '', referring to conversion through [[Mikvah|submersion]].&lt;ref&gt;The city of the Moon god: religious traditions of Harran p112  Tamara M. Green - 1992 &quot;Segal was inclined to believe that the root of the word Sabian was Syriac. Rejecting the notion that it means baptizer ... Even if the etymology proposed by Segal is correct, nevertheless the question of how Muhammad learned about these ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The Syriac (and Hebrew) nouns derived from this root refer to [[proselyte]]s, both &quot;[[Judaisers]]&quot; — non-converts who followed certain basic rules of [[Judaism]] — and early [[Christianity|Christian]] converts of non-Jewish origin and practice. These latter were called ''Theosebeians'' &quot;[[God-fearer]]s&quot;, ''Sebomenoi'' &quot;Believers&quot;, or ''Phobeomenoi'' ({{lang|el|Φοβεόμενοι}}) &quot;pious ones&quot; in Greek sources. The Greek etymology of ''sebomai'' ({{lang|el|σέβομαι}}), applied to the proselytes, is in the word ''eusebian'' ({{lang|el|εὐσέβειαν}}), meaning a kind of godliness and reverence or worshipfulness. {{Or|date=July 2011}}

According to Islamic scholars, the word Sābi'ūna (Sabian) is derived from the verb ''saba’a'', which refers to the action of leaving one religion and entering another.&lt;ref name=&quot;scholars&quot;&gt;[http://www.islam-qa.com/index.php?ref=49048&amp;ln=eng&amp;txt=Sabians He is asking about the Sabians: who were they and what were their beliefs?], ''Islam Q&amp;A'', retrieved April 23, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
:[[Muhammad ibn Jarir al-Tabari|Tabari]] said: ''as-Sābi'ūn''  is the plural of ''Sābi''', which means &quot;proselyte&quot; who has left his original religion, or anyone who has left the religion that he used to follow and joins another. The [[Arabs]] called such a person Sābi'.

Sabians practiced initiation through submersion in water, intended to harken to the [[inundation]] of the world during the deluge of the time of Noah which cleansed man's sinful nature from the face of the earth.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

==Overview==
In the later ninth century CE, Arab authors focused upon the origins of the &quot;Abrahamic&quot; Sabians from the &quot;Hellenistic&quot; Sabians{{clarify|date=February 2012}} and went into much detail on the Harranian period before the time of [[Abraham]]. Most of this knowledge was translated in 904 CE from Syriac sources into the book called &quot;The Nabatean Agriculture&quot; by [[Ibn Wahshiyya]]; [[Maimonides]] considered it an accurate record of the beliefs of the Sabians, whose role as a pre-Judaic monotheistic movement he commented on at length.{{Citation needed|date= October 2011}}

Despite substantial and clear documentation about both kinds of Sabians spanning many centuries from sources as diverse as [[Greek people|Greek]] [[Christian]], [[Arabic language|Arabic]] Muslim, Arabic and Persian [[Bahá'í]], as well as Jewish sources and documents, the actual nature of the Sabians has remained a matter of some heated debate among Orientalists. Therefore, &quot;Sabian&quot; has been used mistakenly in many literary references for decades and though, the spelling &quot;Sabian&quot; usually refers to one of the [[People of the Book]] mentioned in the [[Qur'an]], it is also used by the [[Mandaeans]] under the variation of &quot;Sabaean&quot; detailed below. The variation &quot;Sabean&quot; has been employed in English to distinguish the ancient Harranian group, but the usage is not universal.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

The confusion of Sabaeans and Sabians began with [[Marmaduke Pickthall]]'s spelling mistake in his translation of the [[Qur'an]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}} The word &quot;[[Sabaeans]]&quot; comes from a completely different root spelling, beginning with the Arabic letter &quot;Sin&quot; instead of the Arabic letter &quot;Sad&quot;. The Sabaeans were in fact the people of ancient [[Sheba|Saba]] in [[Yemen]] who scholars {{Who|date= October 2011}} have shown to have no connection to the Sabians of the Qur'an, except for their Ansar tribe, which practiced Qur'anic Sabianism.{{Citation needed|date= October 2011}}
 
[[Al-Biruni]] (writing at the beginning of the eleventh century CE) said that the '&quot;real Sabians'&quot; were &quot;the remnants of the [[Jew]]ish tribes who remained in [[Babylonia]] when the other tribes left it for [[Jerusalem]] in the days of [[Cyrus the Great|Cyrus]] and [[Artaxerxes]]{{dn|date=August 2012}}. According to [[Ethel Drower]] (1937) these remaining tribes ... adopted a system mixed up of Magism and [[Judaism]].'&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.farvardyn.com/mandaean.php Extracts from Ethel Stefana Drower - 1937, ''Mandaeans of Iraq and Iran,'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islamic reference==
The recent debate on who the Sabians were is directly connected to how to best translate the following verses from the [[Qur'an]] out of the original Arabic.

The Sabians existed before [[Muhammad]], and are said to have read from a book called the ''[[Zabur]]'' (&quot;[[Psalms]]&quot;). They came under [[Islamic]] rule about 639 CE. At that time in history they were described as [[Greeks|Greek]] [[immigrants]]{{Citation needed|date = February 2007}} but were grouped together with the [[Nabataeans]].

Many [[Islamic]] [[writers]] from the period of about 650 CE onward gave further descriptions of  the Sabians. They wrote that the Sabians lived in [[Iraq]] around [[Sawad]], [[Kutha]] and [[Mosul]] and they &quot;wash themselves with water&quot;, had &quot;long hair&quot;, and &quot;white gowns&quot;.{{Citation needed|date = February 2007}} They had a [[monotheistic]] faith with religious literature (the [[Zabur]]) and acknowledged the prophets. Their [[theology]] resembled that of [[Judaism]] and [[Christianity]] yet were neither, nor were they [[Magians]].

With regard to their beliefs, [[Ibn al-Qayyim]] said: &quot;The people differed greatly concerning them, and the imams were unsure about them because they did not have enough knowledge of their beliefs and religion.&quot; Al-Shaafa’i said: &quot;Their case is to be examined further; if they resemble the Christians in basic matters but they differ from them in some minor issues, then the ''[[jizya]]'' is to be taken from them. But if they differ from them in basic issues of religion then their religion cannot be approved of by taking the ''jizya'' from them.&quot; And he elaborated elsewhere: &quot;They are a kind of Christian,&quot; a view consistent with a comment about some of them mentioned in [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'i]] writings.{{Citation needed|date= October 2011}}

Ibn al-Qayyim said: &quot;The Sabians are a large nation among whom are both blessed and doomed. They are one of the nations who are divided into believers and disbelievers, for the nations before the coming of the Prophet (Peace and Blessings of Allāh be Upon Him) were of two types, ''[[kafir|kāfir]]'' nations all of whose people were doomed and among whom were none who were blessed, such as the idol-worshippers and the [[Magians]]; and others who were divided into those who were blessed and those who were doomed, namely the [[Jews]], [[Christians]] and Sabians.&quot;{{Citation needed|date = October 2011}}

According to Islamic scholars,&lt;ref name=&quot;scholars&quot;/&gt; they did not reject the [[Prophets of Islam]] but neither did they regard it as obligatory to follow them. In their view Whoever followed (the Prophets) may be blessed and saved, but whoever follows a path similar to that of the Prophets ''by virtue of one's own reasoning'' is also blessed and saved, even if one did not follow the Prophets in specific terms. In their view the call of the Prophets was true but there was ''no one specific route'' to salvation. They believed that the universe had a Creator and Sustainer, Who is Wise and above any resemblance to created beings, but many of them, or most of them, (i.e. the Sabians of Harran) said: we are unable to reach Him without intermediaries, so we have to approach Him through the mediation of spiritual and holy Bud Asaf who are pure and free of any physical elements and who are above place and time, rather they are created pure and holy.

[[Abd al-Rahman Ibn Zayd]] (d. 798 CE) wrote: &quot;The Sābi'ūn say that their religion is a religion to itself and they live near [[Mosul]] (jazirat al-mawsil) and believe in only one God.&quot; He also wrote that they have: &quot;no cult though their main belief is '[[Shahada|La ilaha il Allāh]]'.&quot;  He also remarked that: &quot;the Sābi'ūn did not believe in the Prophet Muhammad (in the same way as his followers did), yet the polytheists were known to say of the Prophet and his companions 'these are the Sabians' comparing them to them.&quot;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abd al-Rahman ‘ibn Zayd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Wahb ‘ibn Munabbih&quot;&gt;
[[Wahb Ibn Munabbih]] (d 728-732 CE), who was originally from Iran, wrote: &quot;The Sabians believe 'La ilaha il Allāh' but they do not have canonical law.&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Mujahid ‘ibn Jarir&quot;&gt;Mujahid ‘ibn Jarir (d 722 CE) wrote: &quot;The Sabians have no distinctive religion but is somewhere between [[Judaism]] and [[Magianism]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; following the Din of Noah&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Khalil ‘ibn Ahmad&quot;/&gt;
as a sect who read the [[Zabur]]&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Abul ‘Ailya&quot;&gt;Abul ‘Ailya said: “The Sabis are a sect of people of the Scripture who recite the [[Zaboor]].”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abu Hanifah&quot;&gt;[[Abu Hanifah]] (d.767 CE) who is the founder of the [[Hanafite]] school of [[Islamic Law]] wrote: &quot;The Sabians read [[Zaboor]] and are between Judaism and Christianity.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; akin to Christianity.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abd ‘Allah ‘ibn al-‘Abbas&quot;&gt;‘Abd ‘Allah ‘ibn al-‘Abbas (lived about 650 CE) wrote: &quot;The religion of the Sabians is a sect of Christianity.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; They appear to be between [[Judaism]] and [[Magianism]]&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Ibn Abi Nujayh&quot;&gt;‘Ibn Abi Nujayh (d749) wrote: &quot;The Sabians were between [[Judaism]] and [[Magianism]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Suddi&quot;&gt;Suddi (d745 CE) also wrote: &quot;The Sabian religion is between [[Judaism]] and [[Magianism]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; but are in fact closer to Judaism.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Awza’&quot;&gt;‘Awza’ (d.773 CE) a representative of the ancient Syrian school of religious studies wrote: &quot;The Sabians are between Judaism and Christianity.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Malik ‘ibn ‘Anas&quot;&gt;Malik ‘ibn ‘Anas (d795) wrote: &quot;The Sabians are between Judaism and Christianity...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Ahmad ‘ibn Hanbal&quot;&gt;
[[Ahmad Ibn Hanbal]] (d. 855 CE) the [[Iman of Baghdad]] wrote: &quot;The Sabians are a sect of Christianity or Judaism.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Sābi'ūn recognise the practice of Muhammad in going to the caves prior to his inspiration, as in accordance with the Sabi quest for Tawheed Hunafa' and, in general, many similarities with the Sabians meant Muhammad and his companions were often considered to have been Sabians.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Ibn Jurayi&quot;&gt;
[[Ibn Jurayi]] (who lived in the 8th century) also wrote: The Sabians are in [[Sawad]] and are between the Magians, Christians, or Jews.  He also wrote that the polytheists said of Mohammed: “He is a Sabian”.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abd al-Rahman ‘ibn Zayd2&quot;&gt;
[[Abd al-Rahman Ibn Zayd]] (d798 CE) wrote: &quot;The prophet and his companions are referred to as 'these are the Sabians' comparing Mohammed to the Sabians.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Most specifically this was because of the Sabian shahada “La ilaha ila Allāh”.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abd al-Rahman ‘ibn ‘Zayd3&quot;&gt;‘Abd al-Rahman ‘ibn ‘Zayd (d.798 CE) wrote: &quot;The polytheists used to say of the prophet and his companions ‘these are the Sabians’ comparing them to them, because the Sabians who live Jaziartal-Mawsil (today known as Iraq) would say ‘La ilaha ila Allah’.&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Rabi’ah ‘ibn ‘Ubbad&quot;&gt;
[[Rabiah Ibn Ubbad]] (who lived at the same time as Mohammed) wrote:
&quot;I saw the prophet when I was a pagan. He was saying to the people, ‘if you want to save yourselves, accept that there is no God but Allāh’ At this moment I noticed a man behind him saying ‘he is a sabi.’ When I asked somebody who he was he told me he was ‘Abu Lahab, his uncle.&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Ata ‘ibn Abi Rabah&quot;&gt;Both [[Ibn Jurayi]] (d. 767) and [[Ata Ibn Abi Rabah]] (d.732) wrote: &quot;I saw the prophet when I was a pagan. He was saying to the people, ‘If you want to save yourselves, accept that there is no God but Allāh.’ At this moment I noticed a man behind him saying ‘He is a sabi.’ When I asked somebody who he was he told me he was ‘Abu Lahab, his uncle' Of the relationship between the Sabians who lived in Sawad (in Iraq) and Muhammad it is mentioned that the polytheists of Mecca were heard to say of Muhammad &quot;he has become a Sabian.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The root-meaning of the word &quot;Sabian&quot; (from which they derive Seboghatullah) means [[proselyte]], and is identical in usage with the Greek words for [[Godfearer]]s ''sebomenoi'', ''theosebes'', ''phobeomenoi''.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Abu ‘Abdultah&quot;&gt;[[Abu Abdultah]] said: &quot;The word saba’a means “The one who is a Proselyte.”&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Characteristics of the Sabi religion===
[[Sābi'ūn]] knew God as the ''Rabb al-'alihah'' (lord of gods) and '''ilah al-'alihah (god of gods)'' and speak to angels in their meditations,&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Hasan al-Basri A&quot;&gt;[[Hasan al-Basri]] (d.728 CE) wrote: &quot;the Sabian religion resembles the [[Magi]]ans and they worship angels.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; each of whom they believe dwell in different stars, which has led to the erroneous beliefs among some that Sābi'ūn worship angels while others derogatorily call them star-worshipers (and so it is said in [[Arabic]] ''saba'at al-nujūm'', meaning &quot;the stars appeared&quot;). [[Sābi'ūn]] read from the ''[[Zaboor]]'' (as with the Slavonic [[Subbotniki]] or Psaltirschiki) and use the sun for a [[qiblah]], facing the equator at mid day.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Abul ‘Ailya&quot;&gt;[[Abul Ailya]] said: “The Sabis are a sect of people of the Scripture who recite the [[Zabur]].”&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abu Hanifah&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Hasan al-Basri B&quot;&gt;Hasan al-Basri (d728 CE) wrote: &quot;They read the [[Zaboor]] and pray facing a [[qiblah]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Qatadah ‘ibn Di’amah A&quot;&gt;Qatadah ‘ibn Di’amah (d736 CE) wrote:&quot;they pray towards the sun.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Their fundamental teaching is ''La ilahah il Allah'' (there is no god but Allah),&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abd al-Rahman ‘ibn Zayd&quot;&gt;‘[[Abd al-Rahman ‘ibn Zayd]] (d. 798 CE) wrote: &quot;The Sābi'ūn say that their religion is a religion to itself and they live near [[Mosul]] (jazirat al-mawsil) and believe in only one God.&quot; He also wrote that they have: &quot;… no cult though their main belief is “La ilaha il Allah”.&quot; He also remarked that: &quot;the Sābi'ūn did not believe in the Prophet Mohammed (in the same way as his followers did), yet the polytheists were known to say of the Prophets and his companions “these are the Sabians” comparing them to them.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Wahb ‘ibn Munabbih&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abd al-Rahman ‘ibn ‘Zayd3&quot;/&gt; but besides this ardent unitarianism, Sābi'ūn are quite akin to Christians.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abd ‘Allah ‘ibn al-‘Abbas&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Al-Shaafa’i&quot;&gt;[[Al-Shaafai]] said: &quot;Their case is to be examined further; if they resemble the Christians in basic matters but they differ from them in some minor issues, then the [[jizya]] is to be taken from them. But if they differ from them in basic issues of religion then their religion cannot be approved of by taking the jizya from them.&quot; And he elaborated elsewhere: &quot;They are a kind of [[Christian]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hanif]] Sabians are more universal, looking to [[Noah]] as their prophet of the [[Dīn]].&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Khalil ‘ibn Ahmad&quot;/&gt;Sābi'ūn have five daily prayers&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Qatadah ‘ibn Di’amah B&quot;&gt;Qatadah ‘ibn Di’amah (d736 CE) wrote: &quot;The Sabians worship [[angel]]s, read [[Zaboor]], pray five ritual prayers.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; (though Zohar can join Asr while Maghrib can join Isha giving the appearance of three). They believe in all prophets, reiterating the Din of Noah and, not in the same way as the Muslims, believe in the [[Seal of the prophets]].&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;Ziyad ‘ibn ‘Abihi&quot;&gt;Ziyad ‘ibn ‘Abihi (d. 672 CE) who was the governor of Iraq during the first Umayyad caliph Mu'awiyah wrote: &quot;The Sabians believe in the prophets and pray five times daily.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; They also fast for 30 days.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;‘Abdul al-Zanad&quot;&gt;‘Abdul al-Zanad (d.747 CE) wrote: &quot;The Sabians are from “[[Kutha]]” in [[Iraq]], they believe in prophets, fast 30 days in a year, and pray 5 times daily towards the [[Yemen]].&quot; (NB &quot;towards the Yemen&quot; is equivalent to facing south)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- '''In the book &quot;History of the Muslim New edition of the writings and research [[Hamka|Prof Dr.Hamka]]&quot; under the heading of nations before the birth of Muhammad pages 83;'''

''told it's true this group is a group of Arabs in the community. This group have called 'Sabi'ah. Their belief that the star pocket and space, is confident that this something seala, movements and silence, walking and cessation of all the stringed instruments and related to the course of the stars. That's why the face of each star is no name, no dignity, and there are homes that are determined for each performance.To sun is home, for months there is his house, so also Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, Venus, Mercury and the others, and every star that is idol the like. Venus or Venus, the god of beauty, so he still found the idol of Venus was the Roman state, too bad the broken hand side, is a very beautiful woman. From there the religion Sabi'ah apparently taking it. But there is more to enlarge the group of states Sabi'ah Mecca, pilgrimage, sacred game ban, do not like to eat pork, and do not want marriage of kinship; similar to the beliefs of Muslims.'' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10310695-sejarah-umat-islam Sejarah Umat Islam - Prof. Dr. Hamka, RM80.00 (1939 -1961)]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''In the book &quot;The pastor asked, Muslim students say&quot;'''

''They have seven prayers, which correspond to five times of prayer of the Muslims, the sixth is the Duha prayer, which is also available on the Muslims. The different of this ruling voluntary prayers in the Muslims. The seventh time was just six o'clock at night. They also have a corpse in prayer, without bowing and prostration. Their fasting month of the year, like the Muslims, but time is from the tribe last night until sunset. Such fasting is quite similar to the fasting Muslims.''&lt;ref&gt;Dr.Abdul Muta'al As Sa'idy. Limaza Ana Muslim? Paster Asked, and Muslim Student replied, Maktab al adab-Jamamizat Kaherah,Mesir: ISBN : 967-999-88-4-3&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;

==Non Islamic sources==
===Maimonides===
Although too late to be of relevance in identifying the sect mentioned in the Qur'an, [[Maimonides]] wrote about the Sabians, {{lang-he|'''צבאים'''}}{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}. Based upon a book called ''The Nabataean Agriculture'' which Maimonides translated, Maimonides' ''Guide for the Perplexed'' describes the Sabians in quite some detail. They were questioned by [[Caliph]] [[al-Ma'mun]] of [[Baghdad]] in 830 CE, according to [[Abu Yusuf Absha al-Qadi]], about what protected religion they belonged to. Not being Muslim, Christian, Jewish or Magian, the caliph told them they were nonbelievers and would have to become Muslims or adherents of one of the other religions recognized by the Qur'an by the time he returned from his campaign against the Byzantines or he would kill them.&lt;ref&gt;(Churton p. 26)&lt;/ref&gt;  The Harranians consulted with a lawyer who suggested that they find their answer in the Qur'an II.59 which made it clear that Sabians were tolerated. It was unknown what was intended by Sabian and so they took the name.&lt;ref&gt;[[Tobias Churton]] pp. 26-7)&lt;/ref&gt;

These newly-dubbed Harranian Sabians acknowledged [[Hermes Trismegistus]] as their prophet and the ''[[Corpus Hermeticum]]'' as their sacred text, being a group of [[Hermeticism|Hermeticists]]. Validation of Hermes as a prophet comes from his identification as [[Idris]] (i.e. [[Enoch (ancestor of Noah)|Enoch]]) in the Qur'an (19.57 and 21.85).&lt;ref name=&quot;Churton p. 27&quot;&gt;(Churton p. 27)&lt;/ref&gt;

The Harranian Sabians played a vital role in Baghdad and the rest of the Arab world from 856 until about 1050; playing the role of the main source of [[Greek philosophy]] and [[science]] as well as shaping the intellectual life. The most prominent of the Harranian Sabians was [[Thabit ibn Qurra]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Churton p. 27&quot;/&gt;

===A Yezidi writer===
The [[Yezidi]], and later French citizen and Vice-Consul at [[Mosul]], [[Nicolas Siouffi]] in his ''Études sur la religion des Soubbas ou Sabéens, leurs dogmes, leurs moeurs'' (Paris: Imprimerie Nationale, 1880) claimed to have identified 4,000 Sabians in the [[Soubbha]]s. This was well received by the Theosophist [[G. R. S. Mead]],&lt;ref&gt;[[G. R. S. Mead]] ''Gnostic John the Baptizer: Selections from the Mandaean John-Book'' p137 &quot;... the French Vice-Consul at Mosul, estimated them at some 4000 souls in all ( Etudes sur la Religion des Soubbas ou Sabéens, Paris, 1880). These were then to be found chiefly in the neighbourhood of Baṣra aud Kút. Siouffi's estimate, &quot;&lt;/ref&gt; but received critical reviews from scholars.&lt;ref&gt;The Edinburgh review 1880 Sydney Smith &quot;Admitting M. Siouffi's ignorance and his teacher's possible dishonesty, these are scarcely sufficient to account for the origin of all the traditions and beliefs described in the * Etudes sur la religion ' des Soubbas. ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===In the Bahá'í writings===
The Sabians are also mentioned in the literature of the [[Bahá'í Faith]]. These references are brief for the most part, once describing a group who believe in [[Jesus]]&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot;&gt;&quot;they do expect the manifestation of Jesus&quot; (á'ín-i Sábi'ín by Ruhu'llah Mihrabkhani)&lt;/ref&gt;). [[`Abdu'l-Bahá]] has one brief reference where he describes Seth as one of the &quot;sons of Adam&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=`Abdu'l-Bahá |authorlink=`Abdu'l-Bahá |origyear=1912 |year=1982 |title=The Promulgation of Universal Peace |edition=Hardcover |publisher=Bahá'í Publishing Trust |location=Wilmette, Illinois, USA |isbn=0-87743-172-8 |url=http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/ab/PUP/pup-111.html#pg365 |pages=365}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Bahá'u'lláh]] in a [[Tablet (religious)|Tablet]] identifies Idris with Hermes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Bahá'u'lláh | origyear=1873-92 | year=1994 | title=Tablets of Bahá'u'lláh Revealed After the Kitáb-i-Aqdas | publisher=Bahá'í Publishing Trust | location=Wilmette, Illinois, USA |isbn=0-87743-174-4 | url=http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/b/TB/tb-10.html#pg152 | pages=152}}&lt;/ref&gt; He does not, however, specifically name Idris as the prophet of the Sabians.

==Modern critical scholarship==
Possible identifications for the Sabians include [[Mandaean]]s and [[Harranian]]s. Jaakko Hämeen-Anttila (2002, 2006) notes that in the marsh areas of Southern Iraq there was a continuous tradition of Mandaean religion, but also another pagan, or &quot;Sabian,&quot; centre in the tenth-century Islamic world centred on [[Harran]].&lt;ref&gt;Jaakko Hämeen-Anttila in ''Ideologies as intercultural phenomena'' p90 ed. Antonio Panaino, Giovanni Pettinato, International Association for Intercultural Studies of the [[MELAMMU]] Project - 2002 &quot;... that in the marsh areas of Southern Iraq there was a continuous tradition of Mandaean religion, but it seems to have been totally neglected in scholarship that there was another pagan, or Sabian, centre in the tenth-century Islamic world, in the countryside of Iraq (sawad) around Baghdad&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; These pagan &quot;Sabians&quot; are mentioned in the [[Nabataean corpus]] of [[Ibn Wahshiyya]].&lt;ref&gt;Jaakko Hämeen-Anttila 2002 First, the books of the Nabatean corpus themselves claim to be translations from &quot;ancient Syriac&quot; (eg Filaha 1:5) made by Ibn Wahshiyya and transmitted to a student of his, Ibn az-Zayyat. The real authors of, eg, Filaha, according to...&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The Sabians, who were pagans in the Middle East, were identified with two groups, the Mandaeans and the Harranians. The Mandaeans lived in Iraq during the 2nd century A.D. As they continue to do today, they worshipped multiple gods, or &quot;light personalities.&quot; Their gods were classified under four categories:  &quot;first life,&quot;  &quot;second life,&quot; &quot;third life&quot; and &quot;fourth life.&quot;  Old gods belong to the &quot;first life&quot; category. They summoned deities who, in turn, created &quot;second life&quot; deities, and so forth.

==Citations==
{{primary sources|section|date = March 2011}}

{{reflist|group = note}}

==References==
Churton, Tobias. ''The Golden Builders: Alchemists, Rosicrucians, and the First Freemasons''. New York: Barnes and Noble, 2002.

{{Reflist}}

==External links==
For various theories on the Sabians please see the following:
*[http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/RON_SAC/SABIANS.html 1911 article]
*[http://www.ricerchefilosofiche.it Articles on Sebomenoi &amp; Sabians]
*[http://leocaesius.blogspot.com/2004/05/as-i-noted-below-there-are-at-least.html Inner Haran]
*[http://www.dinlertarihi.com/dosyalar/makaleler/sinasigunduz/problems%20on%20the%20muslim.htm Problems on Understanding The Muslim Sabians as Mandaeans*  Sinasi Gündüz]
*[http://essenes.net/yazdanism.html Religious context for the Sabians of Harran]
*[http://www.sabianassembly.org  The Sabian Assembly]

[[Category:Abrahamic religions]]
[[Category:Monotheistic religions]]

[[ar:صابئة]]
[[de:Sabier]]
[[es:Sabeos (grupo religioso)]]
[[fa:صابئین]]
[[fr:Sabéisme]]
[[it:Sabei]]
[[ja:サービア教徒]]
[[pl:Sabejczycy (Lud Księgi)]]
[[pt:Sabeísmo]]
[[ru:Сабии]]
[[tr:Sâbiîlik]]</text>
      <sha1>ofgr9sl677w4ws7tl3xnnfb8qknvm0t</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
