<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Saint</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28436</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521437406</id>
      <parentid>521437220</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-05T00:30:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pinethicket</username>
        <id>9674144</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/64.180.217.101|64.180.217.101]] ([[User talk:64.180.217.101|talk]]) to last version by Gerakibot</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36948">{{For||Saint (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|Sainthood|the Tegan and Sara album|Sainthood (album)}}
[[Image:Simon ushakov last supper 1685.jpg|thumbnail|250px|In traditional [[Christian]] [[Christian art|iconography]], saints are often depicted as having [[Halo (religious iconography)|halos]], which is a symbol of their holiness. Note that [[Judas Iscariot|Judas]] is depicted without a halo.]] 

A '''saint''' is one who has been recognized for having an exceptional degree of [[sacred|holiness]], sanctity, and [[virtue]]. While the English term &quot;saint&quot; originated in Christianity, the term is now used by historians of religion &quot;in a more general way to refer to the state of special holiness that many religions attribute to certain people,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR&quot; /&gt; with the Jewish [[Tzadik]], the Islamic [[wali]], the Hindu [[rishi]] or [[guru]], and the Buddhist [[arahat]] or [[boddhisatva]] also referred to as saints. Depending on the religion, saints are recognized either through official church recognition or by popular acclaim (see [[Folk saints]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR&quot;&gt;&quot;Historians of religion have liberated the category of sainthood from its narrower Christian associations and have employed the term in a more general way to refer to the state of special holiness that many religions attribute to certain people. The Jewish ''hasid'' or ''tsaddiq'', the Muslim ''waliy'', the Zoroastrian ''fravashi'', the Hindu ''rsi'' or ''guru,'' the Buddhist ''arahant'' or ''bodhisattva,'' the Daoist ''shengren,'' the Shinto ''kami'' and others have all been referred to as saints.&quot;{{cite book|title=Thomson Gale Encyclopedia of Religion|editor=Lindsay Jones|publisher=Macmillan Reference USA|date=2005|edition=Second|volume=Sainthood|pages=8033|language=TG}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ben-Ami1998&quot;&gt;&quot;Veneration of saints is a universal phenomenon. All monotheistic and polytheistic creeds contain something of its religious dimension... &quot; {{cite book|author=Issachar Ben-Ami|title=Saint Veneration Among the Jews in Morocco|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Hk9wCuiT7bEC&amp;pg=PA13|accessdate=7 September 2012|year=1998|publisher=Wayne State University Press|isbn=978-0-8143-2198-0|page=13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Christianity]], &quot;saint&quot; has a wide variety of meanings, depending on its usage and the denomination. In some denominations, &quot;saint&quot; refers to any believer who is &quot;in Christ&quot;, and in whom Christ dwells, whether in [[Heaven (Christianity)|heaven]] or in earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wycliffe&quot;&gt;''Wycliffe Bible Encyclopedia'', &quot;saint&quot;, ISBN 0-8024-9697-0, &quot;Christians in general are 'saints' in NT usage, and the term is common in reference to the inclusive membership of a local church . . . Other references in the NT equate Christians in general with 'saints' . . . All these are identified as saints because they are in Christ Jesus.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In Orthodox and Catholic teachings, all Christians in heaven are considered to be saints, but some are considered to be worthy of higher honor, emulation, or veneration, with official church recognition given to some saints through canonization or glorification.&lt;ref name=bebis&gt;Bebis G ''[http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith8044 The Saints of the Orthodox Church] at Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America, New York&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cat2&gt;[http://www.scborromeo.org/ccc/p123a9p5.htm Catechism of the Catholic Church (Second Edition)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==General characteristics==
The term in English was originally used in Christianity, though historians now use the term for those who are considered worthy of veneration for their holiness or sanctity in all major religions.&lt;ref name=&quot;EoR&quot; /&gt;

Many religions use similar concepts, but different terminology, to venerate individuals worthy of honor in some way, e.g., see [[Hindu saints]]. [[John A. Coleman]] [[Society of Jesus|S.J.]], [[Graduate Theological Union]], [[Berkeley, California|Berkeley]],&lt;ref&gt;Hawley, John Stratton, ed. ''Saints and Virtues'', Berkeley: [[University of California Press]], 1987. p. 239&lt;/ref&gt; wrote that saints across various cultures and religions have the following [[family resemblance]]s:
# exemplary model;
# extraordinary teacher;
# [[Thaumaturgy|wonder worker]] or source of benevolent power;
# [[Intercession of saints|intercessor]];
# a life often refusing material attachments or comforts;
# possession of a special and [[revelation|revelatory]] relation to the [[holy]].&lt;ref&gt;[[John A. Coleman|Coleman, John A.]] [[Society of Jesus|S.J.]] &quot;Conclusion: after sainthood&quot;, in Hawley, John Stratton, ed. ''Saints and Virtues'' Berkeley: [[University of California Press]], 1987. pp 214-217&lt;/ref&gt;

While there are parallels between these (and other) concepts and that of sainthood, each of these concepts has specific meanings within a given religion. Also, [[new religious movement]]s have sometimes taken to using the word in cases where the people so named would not be regarded as saints within mainstream Christianity. Some of the [[Cao Dai#Saints|Cao Dai saint]]s and [[saints of Ecclesia Gnostica Catholica]] are examples of such.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

The [[anthropologist]] &lt;ref&gt;Hawley, John Stratton, ed. ''Saints and Virtues'' Berkeley: [[University of California Press]], 1987. page 239&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lawrence Babb]] in an article about [[Sathya Sai Baba]] asks the question &quot;Who is a saint?&quot;, and responds by saying that in the symbolic infrastructure of some religions, there is the image of a certain extraordinary spiritual king's &quot;miraculous powers&quot;, to whom frequently a certain moral presence is attributed. These saintly figures, he asserts, are &quot;the focal points of spiritual force-fields&quot;, exerting &quot;powerful attractive influence on followers but touch the inner lives of others in transforming ways as well.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Lawrence Babb|Babb, Lawrence A.]] &quot;Sathya Sai Baba's Saintly Play&quot;, in Hawley, John Stratton, ed. ''Saints and Virtues'' Berkeley: [[University of California Press]], 1987. pp 168-170&lt;/ref&gt;

== Christianity ==
=== Anglicanism ===

{{Main|Saints in Anglicanism}}
{{Refimprove section|date=October 2009}}
In the [[Anglican Communion]] and the [[Continuing Anglicanism|Continuing Anglican]] movement, the title of Saint refers to a person who has been elevated by popular opinion as a pious and holy person. The saints are seen as models of holiness to be imitated, and as a 'cloud of witnesses' that strengthen and encourage the believer during his or her spiritual journey ({{bibleverse||Hebrews|12:1|KJV}}). The saints are seen as elder brothers and sisters in Christ.  Official Anglican creeds recognise the existence of the saints in heaven.

So far as invocation of the saints is concerned,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eskimo.com/~lhowell/bcp1662/articles/articles.html#22 Article XXII ]&lt;/ref&gt; one of the [[Church of England]]'s [[Thirty-Nine Articles|Articles of Religion]] &quot;Of [[Purgatory]]&quot; condemns &quot;the Romish Doctrine concerning...(the) Invocation of Saints&quot; as &quot;a fond thing vainly invented, and grounded upon no warranty of Scripture, but rather repugnant to the Word of God&quot;.  However, each of the 44 member churches in the [[Anglican Communion]] are free to adopt and authorise their own official documents, and the Articles are not officially normative in all of them (e.g., The Episcopal Church USA, which relegates them to &quot;Historical Documents&quot;). Anglo-Catholics in Anglican provinces using the Articles often make a distinction between a &quot;Romish&quot; and a &quot;Patristic&quot; doctrine concerning the invocation of saints, permitting the latter.

In [[high-church]] contexts, such as [[Anglo-Catholicism]], a saint is generally one to whom has been attributed (and who has generally demonstrated) a high level of holiness and [[sanctity]]. In this use, a saint is therefore not a [[belief|believer]], but one who has been transformed by virtue. In [[Roman Catholicism]], a saint is a special sign of God's activity. The veneration of saints is sometimes misunderstood to be worship, in which case it is derisively termed &quot;hagiolatry&quot;.

Some Anglicans and Anglican churches, particularly Anglo-Catholics, personally ask prayers of the saints.  However, such a practice is seldom found in any official Anglican liturgy. Unusual examples of it are found in The Korean Liturgy 1938, the liturgy of the Diocese of Guiana 1959 and The Melanesian English Prayer Book.

Anglicans believe that the only effective Mediator between the believer and God the Father, in terms of redemption and salvation, is God the Son, [[Jesus]] [[Christ]].  Historical Anglicanism has drawn a distinction between the intercession of the saints and the invocation of the saints.  The former was generally accepted in Anglican doctrine, while the latter was generally rejected.  There are some, however, in Anglicanism, who do beseech the saints' intercession.  Those who beseech the saints to intercede on their behalf make a distinction between &quot;mediator&quot; and &quot;intercessor&quot;, and claim that asking for the prayers of the saints is no different in kind than asking for the prayers of living Christians. [[Anglo-Catholicism|Anglican Catholics]] understand sainthood in a more [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] or [[Orthodoxy|Orthodox]] way, often praying for intercessions from the saints and celebrating their feast days.

According to the [[Church of England]], a saint is one who is sanctified, as it translates in the Authorised King James Version (1611) [[2 Chronicles]] 6:41 &lt;blockquote&gt;
Now therefore arise, O {{LORD}} God, into thy resting place, thou, and the ark of thy strength: let thy priests, O {{LORD}} God, be clothed with salvation, and let thy saints rejoice in goodness.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the Bible, only one person is expressly called a saint: &quot;They envied Moses also in the camp, and [[Aaron]] the saint of the {{LORD}}.&quot; ({{bibleref|Psalms|106:16-18|9}}) The apostle [[Paul the apostle|Paul]] declared himself to be &quot;less than the least of all saints&quot; in {{bibleref|Ephesians|3:8|9}}.

=== Eastern Orthodoxy ===
{{further2|[[Glorification]]}}

In the [[Eastern Orthodox]] Church a saint is defined as anyone who is in [[Heaven]], whether recognized here on earth, or not.&lt;ref name=bebis/&gt; By this definition, [[Adam and Eve]], [[Moses]], the various [[prophet]]s, except for the [[angels]] and [[archangels]] are all given the title of &quot;Saint&quot;. Sainthood in the Orthodox Church does not necessarily reflect a moral model, but the communion with God: there are countless examples of people who lived in great sin and became saints by humility and repentance, such as [[Mary of Egypt]], [[Moses the Black|Moses the Ethiopian]], and of course [[Saint Dismas|Dysmas]], the repentant thief who was crucified. Therefore, a more complete definition of what a saint is, has to do with the way that saints, through their humility and their love of humankind, saved inside them the entire Church, and loved all people.

Orthodox belief considers that [[God]] reveals his saints through answered prayers and other miracles.&lt;ref name=bebis/&gt; Saints are usually recognized by a local community, often by people who directly knew them. As their popularity grows they are often then recognized by the entire church. The formal process of recognition involves deliberation by a synod of bishops.&lt;ref name=bebis/&gt; If successful, this is followed by a service of Glorification in which the Saint is given a day on the church calendar to be celebrated by the entire church.&lt;ref&gt;Frawley J ''[http://www.oca.org/FS.NA-Document.asp?ID=83 The Glorification of the Saints in the Orthodox Church]'' at Orthodox Church in America, Syosset, New York&lt;/ref&gt; This does not, however, make the person a saint; the person already was a saint and the Church ultimately recognized it.

It is believed that one of the ways the holiness (sanctity) of a person is revealed, is through the condition of their relics (remains).{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} In some Orthodox countries (such as Greece, but not in Russia) graves are often reused after 3 to 5 years because of limited space. Bones are washed and placed in an [[ossuary]], often with the person's name written on the skull. Occasionally when a body is exhumed something miraculous is reported as having occurred; exhumed bones are claimed to have given off a fragrance, like flowers, or a body is reported as having remained free of decay, despite not having been embalmed (traditionally the Orthodox do not [[embalm]] the dead) and having been buried for some years in the earth.

The reason relics are considered sacred is because, for the Orthodox, the separation of body and soul is unnatural.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} Body and soul both comprise the person, and in the end, body and soul will be reunited; therefore, the body of a saint shares in the &quot;Holiness&quot; of the soul of the saint.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} As a general rule only [[clergy]] will touch relics in order to move them or carry them in procession, however, in [[veneration]] the faithful will kiss the relic to show love and respect toward the saint. Every [[altar]] in every{{Dubious|date=April 2011}} Orthodox church contains relics, usually of [[martyr]]s. Church interiors are covered with the [[Icons]] of saints.

Because the Church shows no true distinction between the living and the dead (the saints are considered to be alive in Heaven), saints are referred to as if they were still alive. Saints are venerated but not worshipped. They are believed to be able to intercede for salvation and help mankind either through direct communion with God, or by personal intervention.

In the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], the title [[Wiktionary:ὅσιος|Ὅσιος]], ''Hosios'' (f. Ὁσία ''Hosia'') is also used. This is a title attributed to saints who had lived a [[monastery|monastic]] or [[Hermit|eremitic]] life, and it is equal to the more usual title of &quot;Saint&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}}

=== Mormons (Latter-day Saints) ===
{{Refimprove section|date=October 2009}}

The beliefs within [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church) with regard to saints are similar but not quite the same as to the Protestant tradition described below. In the New Testament the saints are all those who have entered into the Christian covenant of baptism. The qualification &quot;latter-day&quot; refers to the doctrine that members are living in the &quot;latter days&quot;, before the [[Second Coming of Christ]], and is used to distinguish the members of the LDS Church, which considers itself the restoration of the ancient Christian church.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |last= Smith |first= Joseph Jr |authorlink= Joseph Smith Jr |title= Pearl Of Great Price |url= http://lds.org/library/display/0,4945,106-1-2-1,FF.html |postscript= &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Therefore members are often referred to as &quot;[[Latter-day Saints]]&quot; or &quot;LDS&quot;, and among themselves as &quot;Saints&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;M. Russell Ballard, [http://lds.org/ldsorg/v/index.jsp?hideNav=1&amp;locale=0&amp;sourceId=9bb42bce258f5110VgnVCM100000176f620a____&amp;vgnextoid=2354fccf2b7db010VgnVCM1000004d82620aRCRD &quot;Faith, Family, Facts, and Fruits&quot;], ''Ensign'', Nov 2007, 25–27&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Oriental Orthodox ===
The [[Syriac Orthodox]], [[Coptic Orthodox]], [[Ethiopian Orthodox]], [[Eritrean Orthodox]], [[Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church]] and [[Armenian Apostolic]] churches do accept the existence of saints, but officially recognize them via their own individual processes.  For example, the [[Pope of the Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria]] canonizes saints, through the approval of that church's Holy Synod. A requirement of the Coptic Orthodox faith is that at least 50 years must pass from a saint's death to his canonization, and the Coptic Orthodox Pope must follow that rule.

=== Protestantism ===
{{Refimprove section|date=October 2009}}
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Priesthood of all believers]] --&gt;
{{main|Saints in Protestantism}}
{{further2|[[Priesthood of all believers]]}}
[[File:AugsburgConfessionXXIOfTheWorshipoftheSaints.JPG|thumb|&quot;Scripture does not teach calling on the saints or pleading for help from them. For it sets before us Christ alone as mediator, atoning sacrifice, high priest, and intercessor.&quot;—[[Augsburg Confession]], Article XXI.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=ig5PF6Tf07UC&amp;pg=PA59&amp;dq Augsburg Confession, Article 21, &quot;Of the Worship of the Saints&quot;]. trans. Kolb, R., Wengert, T., and Arand, C. Minneapolis: [[Augsburg Fortress]], 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

In many [[Protestantism|Protestant]] churches, the word &quot;saint&quot; is used more generally to refer to anyone who is a [[Christian]]. This is similar in usage to [[Paul the Apostle|Paul]]'s numerous references in the New Testament of the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lds.org/ldsorg/v/index.jsp?hideNav=1&amp;locale=0&amp;sourceId=bcfb12ca67c20110VgnVCM100000176f620a____&amp;vgnextoid=32c41b08f338c010VgnVCM1000004d82620aRCRD &quot;Beloved of God, Called to Be Saints&quot;], ''New Testament Gospel Doctrine Teacher's Manual''. The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, Salt Lake City, Utah. p. 150. lds.org. Retrieved on November 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In this sense, anyone who is within the [[Body of Christ]] (i.e., a professing Christian) is a 'saint' because of their relationship with Christ Jesus. Many Protestants consider [[Intercession of saints|prayers to the saints]] to be [[idolatry]] as an application of divine worship that should be given only to God himself is being given to other believers, dead or alive.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.philvaz.com/apologetics/p38.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Many Protestants sects also consider the practice to be similar to [[necromancy]] as the dead are believed to be awaiting resurrection, unable to do anything for the living saint.

Within some Protestant traditions, &quot;saint&quot; is also used to refer to any [[born again Christianity|born-again Christian]]. Many emphasise the traditional [[New Testament]] meaning of the word, preferring to write &quot;saint&quot; to refer to any believer, in continuity with the doctrine of the [[priesthood of all believers]].

==== Lutheranism ====
{{further|Calendar of Saints (Lutheran)|Liturgical calendar (Lutheran)}}

In the [[Lutheranism|Lutheran Church]], all Christians, whether in heaven or on earth, are regarded as saints.  However, the church still recognizes and honors specific saints, including some of those recognized by the Catholic Church, but in a qualified way: according to the [[Augsburg Confession]],&lt;ref&gt;A Confession of Faith Presented in Augsburg by certain Princes and Cities to His Imperial Majesty Charles V in the Year 1530&lt;/ref&gt; the term &quot;saint&quot; is used in the manner of the Roman Catholic Church only insofar as to denote a person who received exceptional grace, was sustained by faith and whose good works are to be an example to any Christian. Traditional Lutheran belief accounts that prayers ''to'' the saints are prohibited, as they are not mediators of redemption.&lt;ref&gt;[[Apology of the Augsburg Confession]] XXI 14-30&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Smalcald Articles]]-II 25&lt;/ref&gt; But, Lutherans do believe that saints pray for the Christian Church in general.&lt;ref&gt;[[Apology of the Augsburg Confession]] XXI 9&lt;/ref&gt; [[Philip Melancthon]], the author of the Apology of the Augsburg Confession, approved honoring the saints by saying they are honored in three ways: 1. By thanking God for examples of His mercy; 2. By using the saints as examples for strengthening our faith; 3. By imitating their faith and other virtues.&lt;ref&gt;[[Apology of the Augsburg Confession]] XXI 4-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lcms.org/ca/www/cyclopedia/02/display.asp?t1=s&amp;word=SAINTS.VENERATIONOF Lutheran teaching]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Augsburg Confession]] XXI 1&lt;/ref&gt;
The Lutheran Churches also have [[Calendar of Saints (Lutheran)|liturgical calendars]] in which they honor individuals as saints.

==== Methodism ====
{{further2|[[Saints in Methodism]]}}

While Methodists as a whole do not practice the [[patronage]] or [[veneration]] of saints, they do honor and admire them.  Methodists believe that all Christians are ''saints'', but mainly use the term to refer to bibilical people, Christian leaders, and martyrs of the faith. Many Methodist churches are named after saints, such as the [[Twelve Apostles]], [[John Wesley]], etc.  Although, most are named after geographical locations associated with an early circuit or prominent location.  Some Methodist congregations observe [[All Saints Day]] if they follow the liturgical calendar.  Many encourage the study of saints, that is, the biography of holy people.  The 14th Article of Religion in the United Methodist Discipline states, &quot;The Romish doctrine concerning purgatory, pardon, worshiping, and adoration, as well of images as of relics, and also invocation of saints, is a fond thing, vainly invented, and grounded upon no warrant of Scripture, but repugnant to the Word of God.&quot;  John Wesley, the theological father of world Methodism, did not practice or permit Roman Catholic practices associated with the veneration of the Virgin Mary or prayers to saints.


=== {{anchor|Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic|Catholicism}} Roman Catholicism ===
{{Further|Roman Catholic calendar of saints}}
One Roman Catholic website states that &quot;There are over 10,000 named saints and [[List of blesseds|beatified people]] from history, the Roman Martyrology and Orthodox sources, but no definitive head count&quot;.&lt;ref name=COL&gt;[http://www.catholic.org/saints/faq.php All About Saints] at Catholic Online (USA) FAQs- Saints and Angels&lt;/ref&gt;

Rev. [[Alban Butler]] published ''Lives of the Saints'' in 1756, containing 1,486 saints. The latest edition of this work, edited by Father Herbert Thurston, S.J., and British author Donald Attwater, contains the lives of 2,565 saints.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,862347,00.html | work=Time | title=Religion: 2,565 Saints | date=1956-08-06 | accessdate=2010-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Monsignor Robert Sarno, an official of Vatican's Congregation for the Causes of Saints, expressed that it is impossible to say the exact number of saints.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2010/04/04/sunday/main6362140.shtml | work=CBS News | title=Keeping Saints Alive | date=2010-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Catholic Church teaches that it does not, in fact, make or create saints. Rather, it recognizes them.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kofc.org/un/catechism/getsection.action?part=1&amp;sec=2&amp;chap=3&amp;art=9&amp;parasec=3&amp;subsec=2&amp;hdr=0&amp;par=828&amp;paratype=a The Catechism of the Catholic Church] From the Knights of Columbus website&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Catholic Church|Church]], the title of Saint refers to a person who has been formally [[canonization|canonized]] (officially recognized) by the Catholic Church, and is therefore believed to be in [[Heaven]].

By this definition there are many people believed to be in [[Heaven]] who have not been formally declared as saints (most typically due to their obscurity and the involved process of formal canonization) but who may nevertheless generically be referred to as saints. All in Heaven are, in the technical sense, saints, since they are believed to be completely perfect in holiness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholic-pages.com/saints/explained.asp What is a saint?] Vatican Information Service, 29 July 1997&lt;/ref&gt; Unofficial devotions to uncanonized individuals take place in certain regions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.citizendium.org/wiki/ Folk_saint] from [[Citizendium]]&lt;/ref&gt; Sometimes the word &quot;saint&quot; is used to refer to Christians still sojourning here on earth.&lt;ref name=cat2/&gt;

In his book, ''Saint of the Day'', editor Leonard Foley, OFM, says this of saints: &quot;[Saints'] surrender to God's love was so generous an approach to the total surrender of Jesus that the Church recognizes them as heroes and heroines worthy to be held up for our inspiration. They remind us that the Church is holy, can never stop being holy and is called to show the holiness of God by living the life of Christ.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;''Saint of the Day'' edited by Leonard Foley, OFM, (Cincinnati: St. Anthony Messenger Press, 2003), xvi. ISBN 0-86716-535-9&lt;/ref&gt;

In his book, on ''Making Saints'', author [[Kenneth L. Woodward]] notes the following: &lt;blockquote&gt;A saint is always someone through whom we catch a glimpse of what God is like—and of what we are called to be. Only God &quot;makes&quot; saints, of course. The church merely identifies from time to time a few of these for emulation. The church then tells the story. But the author is the Source of the grace by which saints live. And there we have it: A saint is someone whose story God tells.&lt;ref name=&quot;Woodward13&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Making Saints: How the Catholic Church Determines Who Becomes a Saint, Who Doesn't, and Why |last=Woodward |first=Kenneth L. |authorlink= |year=1996 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |location=New York |isbn=0684815303 |page=13 |accessdate=August 9, 2012 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=JImU5EZo7O8C&amp;lpg=PA13&amp;pg=PA13#v=onepage&amp;q=%22A%20saint%20is%20someone%22&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The [[veneration]] of saints, in [[Latin]], ''cultus'', or the &quot;cult of the saints&quot;, describes a particular popular devotion or abandonment to a particular saint or saints.  Although the term &quot;[[worship]]&quot; is sometimes used, it is intended in the old-sense meaning to honor or give respect (''[[dulia]]''). According to the Catholic Church, Divine Worship is properly reserved only for God (''[[latria]]'') and never to the saints.&lt;ref&gt;Scully, Teresita '' [http://www.americancatholic.org/features/customs/rosary/mary_worship.asp Do Catholics Worship Mary?]'' on American Catholic.org&lt;/ref&gt; They can be asked to intercede or pray for those still on earth,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholic.com/library/Intercession_of_the_Saints.asp The Intercession of the Saints] on Catholic.com&lt;/ref&gt; just as one can ask someone on earth to pray for them.

A saint may be designated as a [[patron saint]] of a particular cause or profession, or invoked against specific illnesses or disasters, sometimes by popular custom and sometimes by official statements of the [[Magisterium]].&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Catholic Encyclopedia (1913)/Patron Saints|Patron Saints]] from Catholic Encyclopedia (1913) on Wikisource.org&lt;/ref&gt; Saints are not thought to have power of their own, but only that granted by God. [[Relics]] of saints are respected in a similar manner to holy images and [[icons]].  The practices of past centuries in venerating relics of saints for healing is taken from the early Church.&lt;ref&gt;Acts 19:11-12&lt;/ref&gt;

For example, an American [[deacon]] claimed in 2000 that Blessed [[John Henry Newman]] interceded with God to cure him. The American, Jack Sullivan, asserted that after addressing Newman he was cured of spinal stenosis in a matter of hours. In 2009, a panel of theologians concluded that Sullivan's recovery was the result of his prayer to Newman. According to the Catholic Church, to be deemed a miracle, &quot;a medical recovery must be instantaneous, not attributable to treatment, disappear for good.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jenna Russell, &quot;Marshfield man's prayer an answer in sainthood query&quot;, ''The Boston Globe'' April 28, 2009, B1,4.&lt;/ref&gt;

Once a person has been declared a saint, the body of the saint is considered holy.&lt;ref name=newadv&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12734a.htm Relics] Catholic Encyclopedia on NewAdvent.org&lt;/ref&gt; The remains of saints are called holy [[relics]] and are usually used in churches. Saints' personal belongings may also be used as relics.&lt;ref name=newadv /&gt; Some of the saints have a [[saint symbology|symbol]] that represents their life.

In Church tradition, a person who is seen as exceptionally holy can be declared a saint by a formal process, called [[canonization]].  Formal canonization is a lengthy process often taking many years, even centuries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/saints/index_saints_en.html Table of the Canonizations during the Pontificate of His Holiness John Paul II] on Vatican.va&lt;/ref&gt;

The first step in this process is an investigation of the candidate's life, undertaken by an expert. After this, the report on the candidate is given to the bishop of the area and more studying is done. It is then sent to the Congregation for the Causes of Saints in Rome.&lt;ref name=how6191 /&gt;

If the application is approved, the person may be granted the title of &quot;Venerable&quot;.&lt;ref name=how6191&gt;[http://people.howstuffworks.com/question6191.htm How Stuff Works]&lt;/ref&gt; Further investigations may lead to the candidate's [[beatification]] and given title of &quot;Blessed.&quot;&lt;ref name=how6191 /&gt;
At a minimum, two important miracles are required to be formally declared a saint.  These miracles must be posthumous.
&lt;ref name=how6191 /&gt; Finally, when all of this is done the [[Pope]] canonizes the saint.&lt;ref name=how6191 /&gt;

== Other religions ==
The use of the term &quot;saint&quot; is not exclusive to Christianity. In many religions, there are people who have been recognized within their tradition as having fulfilled the highest aspirations of religious teaching. In English, the term saint is often used to translate this idea from many [[world religions]].

=== African Diaspora ===
{{Main|Afro-American religion}}

Cuban [[Santería]], [[Haitian Vodou]], Brazilian [[Umbanda]] and [[Candomblé]], and other similar [[syncretism|syncretist]] religions adopted the Catholic saints, or at least the images of the saints, and applied their own spirits/deities to them.  They are worshiped in churches (where they appear as saints) and in religious festivals, where they appear as the [[deity|deities]].  The name ''santería'' was originally a pejorative term for those whose worship of saints deviated from Catholic norms.

=== Buddhism ===
{{Main|Buddha|Bodhisattva}}

Buddhists hold the [[Arhat]]s and [[Arahant]]s in special esteem, as well as Bodhisattvas and Buddhas.

=== Discordianism ===
{{Main|Discordianism}}

In Discordianism, anyone, living or dead, or even anything can be named a saint. Anyone may canonize anything or anyone else as everyone, whether they are aware of it or not, is a [[pope]] in the [[POEE]]. This is because &quot;moral perfection isn't necessary for Discordian Sainthood. You just have to suffer a lot.&quot;

=== Hinduism ===
{{Main|Hindu saints}}

There are individuals who have been described as being Hindu saints, most of whom have also been more specifically identified by the terms [[Sant]], [[Mahatma]], [[Paramahamsa]], or [[Swami]], or with the titles ''[[Sri]]'' or ''Srila''.

=== Islam ===
{{Main|Wali}}

The Arabic term ''wali'' (Arabic ولي, plural Awliyā' أولياء) is commonly translated into English as &quot;Saint&quot;. However, the ''wali'' should not be confused with the Christian tradition of sainthood. A prominent early scholar of Sunni Islamic beliefs, [[Ahmad ibn Muhammad al-Tahawi]], mentioned in his book &quot;Al-Aqidah At-Tahawiya&quot;:

''We do not prefer any of the '''saintly men''' among the Ummah over any of the Prophets but rather we say that any one of the Prophets is better than all the awliya' put together. We believe in what we know of Karamat, the marvels of the awliya' and in authentic stories about them from trustworthy sources.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.masud.co.uk/ISLAM/misc/tahawi.htm''&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike Prophets and Messengers, the ''awliya'' can be either male and female. One of the best known female saints is [[Rabia Basri|Rabi`a al-Adawiyya]].

It is widely regarded{{citation}} in [[Islam]] that the saint of saints is [[Ali Ibn Abi Talib]], the cousin of Prophet [[Muhammad]]. Most Sufi orders, [[Tarikah]]s, originate through his teachings. 

In [[Sufism]], the major ''wali'' are considered masters in the art of spiritual purification. Many [[Muslims]] hold the [[Hadrat]] (literally Presence, a title of saints) in esteem.

Scholars have also noted the parallels between the regard for some [[Sufism|Sufi]] figures in popular Muslim observance and Christian ideas of sainthood. In some Muslim countries there are shrines at the tombs of Sufi saints, with the observation of festival days on the anniversary of death, and a tradition of miracle-working.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Saint and Sufi in Modern Egypt|author= Michael Gilsenan|year=1973|publisher=Oxford|isbn=0-19-823181-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Judaism ===
{{Main|Tzadik}}

The term ''Tzadik'' &quot;righteous&quot;, and its associated meanings, developed in [[Rabbinic literature|Rabbinic thought]] from its Talmudic contrast with ''[[Hasidim|Hasid]]'' (&quot;Pious&quot; honorific), to its exploration in [[Musar literature|Ethical literature]], and its esoteric spiritualisation in [[Kabbalah]]. In [[Hasidic Judaism]], the institution of the Tzadik assumed central importance, combining former elite mysticism with social movement for the first time.

=== Sikhism ===
{{refimprove section|date=April 2012}}
The concept of [[Sant Mat|sant]] or [[bhagat]] is found in North Indian religious thought including [[Sikhism]]. Figures such as [[Kabir]], [[Guru Ravidass|Ravidas]], [[Guru Nanak Dev|Nanak]], and others are widely regarded as belonging to the Sant tradition. Some of their mystical compositions are incorporated in the [[Guru Granth Sahib]]. The term &quot;Sant&quot; is still sometimes loosely applied to living individuals in the Sikh and related communities.{{citation needed|date=April 2012}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Saints}}
{{Col-begin}}{{Col-break}}
* [[Calendar of saints]]
* [[Communion of Saints]]
* [[Congregation for the Causes of Saints]]{{Nb5}}{{Nb5}}
* [[Coptic saints]]
* [[Gnostic saint]]
* [[Hagiography]]
* [[Icon]]
* [[Intercession of saints]]
{{Col-break}}
* [[List of canonizations]]
* [[List of saints]]
* [[List of Jesuit Saints]]
* [[List of Russian saints]]
* [[Martyrology]]
* [[Patron saint]]
* [[Tzadik]]
{{Col-end}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
* Beyer, Jürgen, et al., eds. ''Confessional sanctity (c. 1550 - c. 1800)''. Mainz: Philipp von Zabern, 2003.
*[[Siglind Bruhn|Bruhn, Siglind]]. ''Saints in the Limelight: Representations of the Religious Quest on the Post-1945 Operatic Stage''. Hillsdale, New York: Pendragon Press, 2003. ISBN 978-1-57647-096-1.
* Cunningham, Lawrence S. ''The Meaning of Saints''. San Francisco: Harper &amp; Row, 1980.
* Hawley, John Stratton, ed. ''Saints and Virtues''. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1987.
* Jean-Luc Deuffic (éd.), ''Reliques et sainteté dans l'espace médiéval'' [http://perso.orange.fr/pecia/Revue%208-11%20bis.htm]
* O'Malley, Vincent J. &quot;Ordinary Suffering of Extraordinary Saints&quot;, 1999. ISBN 0-87973-893-6
* Perham, Michael. ''The Communion of Saints''. London: Alcuin Club / SPCK, 1980.
* Watchtower Bible and Tract Society. ''Insight on the Scriptures: Volume 1''. Brooklyn,: Watch Tower Bible and Tract Society, 1988.
* Woodward, Kenneth L. ''Making Saints''. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1996.

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last=Trigilio (PhD, ThD)|first=Rev. John|title=Saints for Dummies|year=2010|isbn=978-0-470-53358-1|pages=363|coauthors=Rev. Kenneth Brighenti, PhD}}
*{{cite book|last=Hebert (S. M.)|first=Albert|title=Saints Who Raised the Dead: True Stories of 400 Resurrection Miracles|publisher=TAN Books|location=Illinois|isbn=0-89555-798-3|pages=335}}

==External links==
{{Commons category| Saints}}
{{Wiktionary}}
* [http://saintsquotes.net/ Inspirational Quotes from the Saints]
* [http://saints.sqpn.com/today-on-the-calendar/ Today's Saints on the Calendar]
* http://www.oodegr.com/english/istorika/britain/British_saints.htm
*[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/singleitem/collection/p15324coll10/id/1245/rec/420 Saints and Their Legends: A Selection of Saints from Michael the Archangel to the Fifteenth Century]
* [http://www.om-guru.com Biographies of Saints and Gurus in the Indian Tradition]

{{Clear}}
{{canonization}}

[[Category:Saints| ]]
[[Category:Sainthood| ]]
[[Category:Titles and occupations in Hinduism]]
[[Category:Religious terminology]]

[[ang:Sanct]]
[[ar:قديس]]
[[be:Святы]]
[[be-x-old:Сьвяты]]
[[bg:Светец]]
[[br:Sant]]
[[ca:Sant]]
[[cs:Svatý]]
[[cy:Sant]]
[[da:Helgen]]
[[de:Heiliger]]
[[et:Pühak]]
[[el:Άγιος]]
[[es:Santo]]
[[eo:Sanktulo]]
[[eu:Santu]]
[[fa:قدیس]]
[[fr:Saint]]
[[gd:Naomh]]
[[gl:Santo]]
[[xal:Бодь]]
[[ko:성인 (종교)]]
[[hr:Svetac]]
[[io:Santo]]
[[id:Santo]]
[[ia:Sancto]]
[[is:Dýrlingur]]
[[it:Santo]]
[[he:קדוש (נצרות)]]
[[jv:Santo]]
[[ka:წმინდანი]]
[[sw:Mtakatifu]]
[[la:Sanctus]]
[[lv:Svētais]]
[[li:Heilige]]
[[hu:Szent]]
[[mk:Светец]]
[[mr:संत]]
[[arz:قديس]]
[[nl:Heilige (christendom)]]
[[ja:聖人]]
[[no:Helgen]]
[[nn:Helgen]]
[[nrm:Saint]]
[[pl:Święty]]
[[pt:Santo]]
[[ro:Sfânt]]
[[qu:Santu]]
[[ru:Святой]]
[[sco:Saunt]]
[[sq:Shenjtori]]
[[simple:Saint]]
[[sk:Svätec]]
[[sl:Svetnik]]
[[sr:Светац]]
[[sh:Svetac]]
[[fi:Pyhimys]]
[[sv:Helgon]]
[[tl:Santo]]
[[ta:புனிதர்]]
[[th:เซนต์]]
[[tr:Azîz]]
[[uk:Святі]]
[[vec:Santo]]
[[vi:Thánh (Kitô giáo)]]
[[wa:Sint]]
[[war:Santo]]
[[zh:圣人]]</text>
      <sha1>f29ldk8hwo1uj81r2kqm0dt9j14k0zy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
