<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sanskrit</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27698</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522350695</id>
      <parentid>522081971</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T16:42:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mf1004</username>
        <id>10062163</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Revival attempts */ Latest developments on the topic</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="85413">{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
{{Infobox language
|name = Sanskrit
|nativename = {{lang|sa|संस्कृतम्}} ''{{IAST|saṃskṛtam}}''
|pronunciation = {{IPA-sa|sə̃skɹ̩t̪əm|}}
|region = [[Greater India]]
|speakers = 14,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Census&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://censusindia.gov.in/Census_Data_2001/Census_Data_Online/Language/Statement5.htm|title=Comparative speaker's strength of scheduled languages − 1971, 1981, 1991 and 2001|work=Census of India, 2001|publisher=Office of the Registrar and Census Commissioner, India|accessdate=31 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=2001
|familycolor = Indo-European
|fam2 = [[Indo-Iranian languages|Indo-Iranian]]
|fam3 = [[Indo-Aryan languages|Indo-Aryan]]
|script = No native script.&lt;ref name=&quot;banerji&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last = Banerji|first = Suresh|title = A companion to Sanskrit literature: spanning a period of over three thousand years, containing brief accounts of authors, works, characters, technical terms, geographical names, myths, legends, and twelve appendices|year = 1971|page = 672|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=JkOAEdIsdUs|isbn = 978-81-208-0063-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Written in [[Devanagari|Devanāgarī]], various [[Brāhmī script|Brāhmī]]-[[Brahmic family of scripts|based]] alphabets, [[Thai alphabet|Thai]] in  vocabularies, and [[Romanization of Sanskrit|Latin script]]
|nation = {{IND|India}}, [[Uttarakhand]]&lt;br /&gt;one of the 22 [[scheduled languages of India]]
|iso1 = sa
|iso2 = san
|iso3 = san
|image = The_word_संस्कृतम्_(Sanskrit)_in_Sanskrit.svg
|imagealt = The word Sanskrit (संस्कृतम्) written in Sanskrit. Displayed in the Sarai font for Devanagari.
|imagecaption = The word Sanskrit (संस्कृतम्) written in Devanagari.
|notice = Indic
|notice2 = IPA
}}

'''Sanskrit''' ({{lang|sa|संस्कृतम्}} ''{{IAST|saṃskṛtam}}'' {{IPA-sa|sə̃skɹ̩t̪əm|}}, originally {{lang|sa|संस्कृता वाक्}} ''{{IAST|saṃskṛtā [[Vāc|vāk]]}}'', &quot;refined speech&quot;), is a historical [[Indo-Aryan languages|Indo-Aryan language]], the primary [[liturgical language]] of [[Hinduism]] and a literary and scholarly language in [[Buddhism]] and [[Jainism]].&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot;&gt;[[Buddhism]]: besides [[Pali]], see [[Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit]]&lt;/ref&gt; Today, it is listed as one of the 22 [[Eighth Schedule to the Constitution|scheduled languages of India]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://india.gov.in/govt/documents/english/7thSch-AppV_219-280.pdf |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071004031805/http://india.gov.in/govt/documents/english/7thSch-AppV_219-280.pdf |archivedate=2007-10-04 |title=Indian Constitution Art.344(1) &amp; Art.345 |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2007-10-04 |accessdate=2012-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is an official language of the state of [[Uttarakhand]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/Sanskrit-is-second-official-language-in-Uttarakhand/Article1-499467.aspx |title=Sanskrit is second official language in Uttarakhand – The Hindustan Times |publisher=Hindustantimes.com |date=2010-01-19 |accessdate=2012-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sanskrit holds a prominent position in [[Indo-European studies]].

'''Classical Sanskrit''' is the standard [[Register (sociolinguistics)|register]] as laid out in the grammar of {{IAST|[[Pāṇini]]}}, around the 4th century BCE. Its position in the cultures of [[Greater India]] is akin to that of [[Latin]] and [[Ancient Greek language|Greek]] in Europe and it has significantly influenced most modern languages of the [[Indian subcontinent]], particularly in [[India]], [[Pakistan]], [[Sri Lanka]] and [[Nepal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Staal&quot; /&gt;

The pre-Classical form of Sanskrit is known as [[Vedic Sanskrit]], with the language of the [[Rigveda]] being the oldest and most archaic stage preserved, its oldest core dating back to as early as 1500 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Macdonell|2004|p=?}}&lt;/ref&gt; This qualifies Rigvedic Sanskrit as one of the oldest attestations of any [[Indo-Iranian language]], and one of the earliest attested members of the [[Indo-European language family]], the family which includes English and most European languages.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Burrow|2001|p=?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The corpus of [[Sanskrit literature]] encompasses a rich tradition of poetry and [[Sanskrit drama|drama]] as well as [[Scientific literature|scientific]], technical, [[Hindu philosophy|philosophical]] and [[dharma]] texts. Sanskrit continues to be widely used as a ceremonial language in Hindu religious rituals and Buddhist practice in the forms of [[stotra|hymns]] and [[mantra]]s. Spoken Sanskrit is still in use in a few traditional institutions in India and there are many attempts at [[Sanskrit revival|revival]].

==Name==
The Sanskrit verbal adjective ''{{IAST|sáṃskṛta-}}'' may be translated as &quot;put together, constructed, well or completely formed; refined, adorned, highly elaborated&quot;. It is derived from the root ''{{IAST|saṃ-skar-}}'' &quot;to put together, compose, arrange, prepare&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Monier-Williams|1898|p=1120}}&lt;/ref&gt; where ''{{IAST|saṃ-}}'' &quot;together&quot; (as English ''same'') and ''{{IAST|(s)kar-}}'' &quot;do, make&quot;.

The term in the generic meaning of &quot;made ready, prepared, completed, finished&quot; is found in the [[Rigveda]]. Also in [[Vedic Sanskrit]], as nominalized neuter ''{{IAST|saṃskṛtám}}'', it means &quot;preparation, prepared place&quot; and thus &quot;ritual enclosure, place for a sacrifice&quot;.

As a term for &quot;refined or elaborated speech&quot; the adjective appears only in Epic and Classical Sanskrit, in the [[Manusmriti]] and in the [[Mahabharata]].
The language referred to as ''{{IAST|saṃskṛta}}'' &quot;the cultured language&quot; has by definition always been a &quot;sacred&quot; and &quot;sophisticated&quot; language, used for religious and learned discourse in ancient India, and contrasted with the languages spoken by the people, ''{{IAST|[[Prakrit|prākṛta-]]}}'' &quot;natural, artless, normal, ordinary&quot;.

==History==
[[File:Devimahatmya Sanskrit MS Nepal 11c.jpg|right|thumb|400px|[[Devimahatmya]] [[manuscript]] on palm-leaf, in an early [[Bhujimol]] script, [[Bihar]] or [[Nepal]], 11th century]]

Sanskrit is a member of the [[Indo-Iranian languages|Indo-Iranian]] sub-family of the [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] family of languages. Its closest ancient relatives are the [[Iranian languages]] [[Old Persian]] and [[Avestan]].

In order to explain the common features shared by Sanskrit and other Indo-European languages, many scholars have proposed [[Indo-Aryan migration|migration hypotheses]] asserting that the original speakers of what became Sanskrit arrived in what is now India and [[Pakistan]] from the north-west some time during the early second millennium BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Masica, pp. 36–37&lt;/ref&gt; Evidence for such a theory includes the close relationship of the Indo-Iranian tongues with the Baltic and Slavic languages, vocabulary exchange with the non-Indo-European [[Uralic languages]], and the nature of the attested Indo-European words for flora and fauna.&lt;ref&gt;Masica, p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest attested Sanskrit texts are [[Brahmanical]] texts of the [[Rigveda]], which date to the mid-to-late second millennium BCE. No written records from such an early period survive, if ever existed. However, scholars are confident that the oral transmission of the texts is reliable: they were ceremonial literature whose correct pronunciation was considered crucial to its religious efficacy.&lt;ref&gt;* {{Citation|first=Michael|last= Meier-Brügger|coauthors=Matthias Fritz, Manfred Mayrhofer, Charles Gertmenian (trans.)|title=Indo-European Linguistics|location=Berlin; New York|publisher=Walter de Gruyter|year=2003|isbn=3-11-017433-2|url=http://books.google.com/?id=49xq3UlKWckC|page=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From the Rigveda until the time of [[Pāṇini|{{IAST|Pāṇini}}]] (fl. 4th century BCE) the development of the  early Vedic language may be observed in other Vedic texts: the [[Samaveda]], [[Yajurveda]], [[Atharvaveda]], [[Brahmanas]], and [[Upanishads]]. During this time, the prestige of the language, its use for sacred purposes, and the importance attached to its correct [[enunciation]] all served as powerful conservative forces resisting the normal processes of linguistic change.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=A history of Sanskrit literature|first=Arthur Berriedale |last=Keith|publisher=Motilal Banarsidass|location=Delhi|year=1993|isbn=81-208-0979-3|page=4|url=http://books.google.com/?id=GNALtBMVbd0C}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, there is a clear, five-level linguistic development of Vedic from the Rigveda to the language of the Upanishads and the earliest Sutras (such as [[Baudhayana]]).&lt;ref name=Witzel&gt;M. Witzel, ''Inside the Texts-Beyond the Texts'', Harvard, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;

The oldest surviving Sanskrit grammar is [[Pāṇini|{{IAST|Pāṇini}}]]'s ''{{IAST|Aṣṭādhyāyī}}'' (&quot;Eight-Chapter Grammar&quot;). It is essentially a prescriptive grammar, i.e., an authority that defines correct Sanskrit, although it contains descriptive parts, mostly to account for some Vedic forms that had become rare in {{IAST|Pāṇini}}'s time.

The term &quot;Sanskrit&quot; was not thought of as a specific language set apart from other languages, but rather as a particularly refined or perfected manner of speaking. Knowledge of Sanskrit was a marker of [[social class]] and [[education]]al attainment in ancient India and the language was taught mainly to members of the higher castes, through close analysis of [[Sanskrit grammarians]] such as {{IAST|Pāṇini}}. Sanskrit, as the learned language of Ancient India, thus existed alongside the [[Prakrit]]s (vernaculars), also called [[Middle Indic]] dialects, and eventually into the contemporary modern [[Indo-Aryan languages]].

=== Vedic Sanskrit ===
[[File:Rigveda MS2097.jpg|thumb|300px|''Rigveda'' ([[Vedic chant|padapatha]]) manuscript in [[Devanagari]], early 19th century]]
{{Main|Vedic Sanskrit}}
Sanskrit, as defined by {{IAST|[[Pāṇini]]}}, had evolved out of the earlier &quot;Vedic&quot; form. The beginning of Vedic Sanskrit can be traced as early as 1500–1200 BCE (for [[Rigveda|Rig-vedic]] and [[Indo-Aryan superstrate in Mitanni]]). Scholars often distinguish [[Vedic Sanskrit]] and Classical or &quot;Pāṇinian&quot; Sanskrit as separate 'dialects'. Though they are quite similar, they differ in a number of essential points of [[phonology]], [[vocabulary]], [[grammar]] and [[syntax]]. Vedic Sanskrit is the language of the [[Vedas]], a large collection of hymns, incantations ([[Samhitas]]), theological and religio-philosophical discussions in the [[Brahmanas]] and [[Upanishads]]. Modern linguists consider the metrical hymns of the [[Rigveda]] Samhita to be the earliest, composed by many authors over several centuries of oral tradition. The end of the Vedic period is marked by the composition of the [[Upanishads]], which form the concluding part of the Vedic corpus in the traditional view; however the early Sutras are Vedic, too, both in language and content.&lt;ref name=Witzel/&gt; Around the mid-1st millennium BCE, Vedic Sanskrit began the transition from a first language to a second language of religion and learning.

===Classical Sanskrit===
For nearly 2,000 years, a cultural order existed that exerted influence across [[South Asia]], [[Inner Asia]], [[Southeast Asia]], and to a certain extent, [[East Asia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pollock 2001 393&quot;&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Pollock|2001|p=393}}&lt;/ref&gt; A significant form of post-Vedic Sanskrit is found in the Sanskrit of the [[Hindu Epics]]—the [[Ramayana]] and [[Mahabharata]]. The deviations from {{IAST|[[Pāṇini]]}} in the epics are generally considered to be on account of interference from Prakrits, or &quot;innovations&quot; and not because they are pre-Paninean.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Oberlies|2003|p=xxvii-xxix}}&lt;/ref&gt; Traditional Sanskrit scholars call such deviations ''ārṣa'' (आर्ष), meaning 'of the [[rishi|ṛṣi]]s', the traditional title for the ancient authors. In some contexts, there are also more &quot;prakritisms&quot; (borrowings from common speech) than in Classical Sanskrit proper. [[Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit]] is a literary language heavily influenced by [[Middle Indic]], based on early Buddhist [[prakrit]] texts which subsequently assimilated to the Classical Sanskrit standard in varying degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Edgerton|1953|p=?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to {{Harvcoltxt|Tiwari|1955}}, there were four principal dialects of classical Sanskrit: ''{{IAST|paścimottarī}}'' (Northwestern, also called Northern or Western), ''{{IAST|madhyadeśī}}'' (lit., middle country), ''{{IAST|pūrvi}}'' (Eastern) and ''{{IAST|dakṣiṇī}}'' (Southern, arose in the Classical period). The predecessors of the first three dialects are even attested in Vedic ''{{IAST|[[Brāhmaṇa]]s}}'', of which the first one was regarded as the purest (''{{IAST|Kauṣītaki Brāhmaṇa, 7.6}}).

===Decline===
{{See also|Termination of spoken Sanskrit}}
There are a number of [[sociolinguistic]] studies of spoken Sanskrit which strongly suggest that oral use of Sanskrit is limited, with its development having ceased sometime in the past.&lt;ref&gt;Hock, H. &quot;Language death phenomena in Sanskrit: Grammatical evidence for attrition in contemporary spoken Sanskrit&quot; in ''Studies in the Linguistic Sciences'' v.13 no.2 1983 Dept. of Linguistics, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Dept. of Linguistics&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, says {{Harvcoltxt|Pollock|2001}}, &quot;most observers would agree that, in some crucial way, Sanskrit is [[dead language|dead]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pollock 2001 393&quot;/&gt; He describes it in comparison with the &quot;dead&quot; language of Latin:&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Pollock|2001|p=415}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Both died slowly, and earliest as a vehicle of literary expression, while much longer retaining significance for learned discourse with its [[universalist]] claims. Both were subject to periodic renewals or forced rebirths, sometimes in connection with a politics of translocal aspiration… At the same time… both came to be ever more exclusively associated with narrow forms of religion and priestcraft, despite centuries of a [[secular]] aesthetic.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The decline of Sanskrit use in literary and political circles was likely due to a weakening of the political institutions that supported it, and to heightened competition with vernacular languages seeking literary-cultural dignity.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Pollock|2001|p=416}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was regional variation in the forcefulness of these vernacular movements and Sanskrit declined in different ways across the Indian subcontinent. For example, in [[Kashmir]], [[Kashmiri language|Kashmiri]] was used alongside Sanskrit as the language of literature after the 13th century. Sanskrit works from the [[Vijayanagara Empire]] failed to circulate outside their place and time of composition. By contrast, works in [[Kannada language|Kannada]] and [[Telugu language|Telugu]] flourished.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Pollock|2001|p=414}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite this presumed &quot;death&quot; of Sanskrit and the literary use of vernacular languages, Sanskrit continued to be used in literary cultures in India, and those who could read vernacular languages could also read Sanskrit.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; It did mean that Sanskrit was not used to express changing forms of subjectivity and sociality embodied and conceptualized in the modern age.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Instead, it was reduced to &quot;reinscription and restatements&quot; of ideas already explored, and any creativity in Sanskrit was restricted to hymns and verses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Pollock|2001|p=398}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A notable exception are the military references of [[Nīlakaṇṭha Caturdhara]]'s 17th-century commentary on the [[Mahābhārata]], according to {{Harvcoltxt|Minkowski|2004}}.&lt;/ref&gt; When the British imposed a Western-style education system in India in the nineteenth century, knowledge of Sanskrit and ancient literature continued to flourish as the study of Sanskrit changed from a more traditional style into a form of analytical and comparative scholarship mirroring that of Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Seth|2007|pp=172–175}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Harvcoltxt|Hanneder|2002}} and {{Harvcoltxt|Hatcher|2007}} contest Pollock's characterization, pointing out that modern works continue to be produced in Sanskrit: {{quote|On a more public level the statement that Sanskrit is a dead language is misleading, for Sanskrit is quite obviously not as dead as other dead languages and the fact that it is spoken, written and read will probably convince most people that it cannot be a dead language in the most common usage of the term. Pollock’s notion of the “death of Sanskrit” remains in this unclear realm between academia and public opinion when he says that “most observers would agree that, in some crucial way, Sanskrit is dead”|{{Harvcoltxt|Hanneder|2002|p=294}}}}
{{Harvcoltxt|Hanneder|2009}} argues that modern works in Sanskrit are either ignored or their &quot;modernity&quot; contested. The [[Sahitya Akademi]] has had, since 1967, an [[List of Sahitya Akademi Award winners for Sanskrit|award]] for the best creative work written that year in Sanskrit. In 2009, [[Satyavrat Shastri]] became the first Sanskrit author to win the [[Jnanpith Award]], India's highest literary award.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | newspaper=[[The Indian Express]] | title=Sanskrit’s first Jnanpith winner is a 'poet by instinct' | date=Wednesday, Jan 14, 2009 | url=http://www.indianexpress.com/news/sanskrits-first-jnanpith-winner-is-a-poet-by-instinct/410480/0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===European scholarship===
{{See also|Sanskrit in the West|Sanskrit revival}}
European scholarship in Sanskrit, begun by [[Heinrich Roth]] (1620–1668) and [[Johann Ernst Hanxleden]] (1681–1731),&lt;ref&gt;T. K. John, &quot;Research and Studies by Western Missionaries and Scholars in Sanskrit Language and Literature,&quot; in the St. Thomas Christian Encyclopaedia of India, Vol. III, Ollur[Trichur] 2010 Ed. George Menachery, pp.79 - 83&lt;/ref&gt; is regarded as responsible for the discovery of the [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European]] [[language family]] by [[William Jones (philologist)|Sir William Jones]]. This scholarship played an important role in the development of Western [[philology]], or historical linguistics.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title=A History of Ancient Sanskrit Literature | author=Friedrich Max Müller | authorlink=Max Müller | year=1859 | publisher=Williams and Norgate | page=1 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=6xUAAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[William Jones (philologist)|Sir William Jones]], speaking to the [[Asiatic Society]] in [[Calcutta]] (now [[Kolkata]]) on February 2, 1786, said:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The Sanskrit language, whatever be its antiquity, is of a wonderful structure; more perfect than the [[Greek language|Greek]], more copious than the [[Latin]], and more exquisitely refined than either, yet bearing to both of them a stronger affinity, both in the roots of verbs and in the forms of grammar, than could possibly have been produced by accident; so strong, indeed, that no [[philology|philologer]] could examine them all three, without believing them to have sprung from [[Proto-Indo-European language|some common source]], which, perhaps, no longer exists.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====British attitudes towards Sanskrit====
According to Thomas R. Trautmann, after the 18th-century wave of &quot;Indomania&quot;, i.e. enthusiasm for Indian culture and for Sanskrit, as exemplified in the positions of Orientalist scholars such as [[Sir William Jones]], a certain hostility to Sanskrit and to Indian culture in general began to assert itself in Britain in the early 19th century. The hostility was manifest by a neglect of Sanskrit in British academia, as compared to other European countries, and was part of a general push in favor of the idea that India should be culturally, religiously and linguistically assimilated to Britain as far as possible. Traufmann considers that this British hostility to Sanskrit had two separate and logically opposite sources: one was &quot;British Indophobia&quot;, which he calls essentially a developmentalist, progressivist, liberal, and non-racial-essentialist critique of Hindu civilization as an aid for the improvement of India along European lines. The other was [[race science]], which was a theorisation of the English &quot;''common-sense view''&quot; that Indians constituted a &quot;separate, inferior and unimprovable race&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Trautmann2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Thomas R. Trautmann|title=Aryans and British India|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dhbwDFfE9J8C&amp;pg=PA161|accessdate=4 March 2012|year=2004|publisher=Yoda Press|isbn=978-81-902272-1-6|pages=161–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Phonology==
{{Further|Śikṣā}}
Classical Sanskrit distinguishes about 36 [[phoneme]]s.  There is, however, some [[allophone|allophony]] and the writing systems used for Sanskrit generally indicate this, thus distinguishing 48 [[Phone (phonetics)|sounds]].

The sounds are traditionally listed in the order [[vowel]]s (''Ach''), [[diphthong]]s (''Hal''), [[anusvara]] and [[visarga]], [[Plosive consonant|plosive]]s (Sparśa) and [[nasal stop|nasal]]s (starting in the back of the mouth and moving forward), and finally the [[liquid consonants|liquid]]s and [[fricative]]s, written in [[IAST]] as follows (see the tables below for details):

:{{IAST|a ā i ī u ū ṛ ṝ ḷ ḹ }}; {{IAST|e ai o au}}
:{{IAST|ṃ ḥ}}
:{{IAST|k kh g gh ṅ; c ch j jh ñ; ṭ ṭh ḍ ḍh ṇ; t th d dh n; p ph b bh m}}
:{{IAST|y r l v}}; {{IAST|ś ṣ s h}}
An alternate traditional ordering is that of the [[Shiva Sutra]] of {{IAST|[[Pāṇini]]}}.

===Vowels===
The vowels of Classical Sanskrit written in [[Devanagari]], as a syllable-initial letter and as a [[diacritic]] mark on the [[consonant]] {{lang|sa|प्}} ({{IPA|/p/}}),  pronunciation transcribed in [[International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]], [[IAST]], and approximate equivalent in English:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Letter !! {{lang|sa|प्}} !! IPA !! [[IAST]] !! English equivalent ([[General American|GA]] unless stated otherwise)
|-
| {{Unicode|अ}}||{{Unicode|प}}||{{IPA|/ɐ/}} or {{IPA|/ə/}} ||a|| short [[near-open central vowel]] or [[schwa]]: ''u'' in b'''u'''nny 
|-
| {{Unicode|आ}}||{{Unicode|पा}}||{{IPA|/ɑː/}}||ā||long [[open back unrounded vowel]]: ''a'' in f'''a'''ther ([[Received Pronunciation|RP]])
|-
| {{Unicode|इ}}||{{Unicode|पि}}||{{IPA|/i/}}||i||short [[close front unrounded vowel]]: ''e'' in '''e'''ngland
|-
| {{Unicode|ई}}||{{Unicode|पी}}||{{IPA|/iː/}}||ī||long [[close front unrounded vowel]]: ''ee'' in f'''ee'''t
|-
| {{Unicode|उ}}||{{Unicode|पु}}||{{IPA|/u/}}||u||short [[close back rounded vowel]]: ''oo'' in f'''oo'''t
|-
| {{Unicode|ऊ}}||{{Unicode|पू}}||{{IPA|/uː/}}||ū|| long [[close back rounded vowel]]: ''oo'' in c'''oo'''l
|-
| {{Unicode|ऋ}}||{{Unicode|पृ}}||{{IPA|/r̩/}}||{{Unicode|ṛ}}|| syllabic [[alveolar trill]]: closest to ''er'' in butt'''er''' in rhotic accents
|-
| {{Unicode|ॠ}}||{{Unicode|पॄ}}||{{IPA|/r̩ː/}}||{{Unicode|ṝ}}|| syllabic [[alveolar trill]]: closest to ''ir'' in b'''ir'''d in rhotic accents
|-
| {{Unicode|ऌ}} ||{{Unicode|पॢ}}||{{IPA|/l̩/}}||{{Unicode|ḷ}}|| syllabic [[dental lateral approximant]]: ''le'' in turt'''le'''
|-
| {{Unicode|ॡ}} ||{{Unicode|पॣ}}||{{IPA|/l̩ː/}}||{{Unicode|ḹ}}|| syllabic [[dental lateral approximant]]: longer ''le''
|-
| {{Unicode|ए}}||{{Unicode|पे}}||{{IPA|/eː/}}||e|| long [[close-mid front unrounded vowel]]: ''a'' in b'''a'''ne (some speakers)
|-
| {{Unicode|ऐ}}||{{Unicode|पै}}||{{IPA|/əi/}}||ai|| a long [[diphthong]]: ''i'' in '''i'''ce, ''i'' in k'''i'''te (US, [[Canadian English|Canadian]], and [[Scottish English]])
|-
| {{Unicode|ओ}}||{{Unicode|पो}}||{{IPA|/oː/}}||o|| long [[close-mid back rounded vowel]]: ''o'' in b'''o'''ne ([[Scottish English]])
|-
| {{Unicode|औ}}||{{Unicode|पौ}}||{{IPA|/əu/}}||au|| a long [[diphthong]]: ''ou'' in h''ou''se (Canadian English)
|}

The [[vowel length|long vowels]] are pronounced twice as long as their short counterparts. Also, there exists a third, extra-long length for most vowels, called [[pluti]], which is used in various cases, but particularly in the [[vocative]]. The ''pluti'' is not accepted by all grammarians.

The vowels {{IPA|/e/}} and {{IPA|/o/}} continue as allophonic variants of [[Proto-Indo-Iranian]] {{IPA|/ai/}}, {{IPA|/au/}} and are categorized as diphthongs by Sanskrit grammarians even though they are realized phonetically as simple long vowels. (See above).

Additional points:
* There are some additional signs traditionally listed in tables of the Devanagari script:
** The diacritic {{Unicode|ं}} called ''anusvāra'', ([[IAST]]: {{Unicode|ṃ}}). It is used both to indicate the [[nasalization]] of the vowel in the syllable {{IPA|[◌̃]}} and to represent the sound of a syllabic {{IPA|/n/}} or {{IPA|/m/}}; e.g. {{Unicode|पं}} {{IPA|/pəŋ/}}.
** The diacritic {{Unicode|ः}} called ''visarga'', represents {{IPA|/əh/}} ([[IAST]]: {{Unicode|ḥ}}); e.g. {{Unicode|पः}} {{IPA|/pəh/}}.
** The diacritic {{Unicode|ँ}} called ''chandrabindu'', not traditionally included in Devanagari charts for Sanskrit, is used interchangeably with the ''anusvāra'' to indicate nasalization of the vowel, primarily in Vedic notation; e.g. {{Unicode|पँ}} {{IPA|/pə̃/}}.
* If a lone consonant needs to be written without any following vowel, it is given a ''halanta/virāma'' diacritic below ({{Unicode|प्}}).
* The vowel {{IPA|/aː/}} in Sanskrit is realized as being more central and less back than the closest English approximation, which is {{IPA|/ɑː/}}. But the grammarians have classified it as a back vowel.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Tiwari|1955|p=?}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The ancient Sanskrit grammarians classified the vowel system as [[velar]]s, [[retroflex]]es, [[palatal]]s and [[plosive]]s rather than as back, central and front vowels. Hence {{Unicode|ए}} and {{Unicode|ओ}} are classified respectively as palato-velar (a+i) and labio-velar (a+u) vowels respectively. But the grammarians have classified them as [[diphthong]]s and in prosody, each is given two ''mātrās''. This does not necessarily mean that they are proper diphthongs, but neither excludes the possibility that they could have been proper diphthongs at a very ancient stage (see above). These vowels ''are'' pronounced as long {{IPA|/eː/}} and {{IPA|/oː/}} respectively by learned Sanskrit Brahmans and priests of today. Other than the &quot;four&quot; diphthongs, Sanskrit usually disallows any other diphthong—vowels in succession, where they occur, are converted to [[semivowel]]s according to [[sandhi]] rules.

===Consonants===
[[IAST]] and [[Devanagari]] notations are given, with approximate [[International Phonetic Alphabet|IPA]] values in square brackets.

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Labial consonant|Labial]]&lt;br&gt;ओष्ठ्य&lt;br&gt;oṣṭhya
! [[Labiodental consonant|Labiodental]]&lt;br&gt;दन्त्योष्ठ्य&lt;br&gt;dantyoṣṭhya
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Dental consonant|Dental]]&lt;br&gt;दन्त्य&lt;br&gt;dantya
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Retroflex consonant|Retroflex]]&lt;br&gt;मूर्धन्य&lt;br&gt;mūrdhanya
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Palatal consonant|Palatal]]&lt;br&gt;तालव्य&lt;br&gt;tālavya
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Velar consonant|Velar]]&lt;br&gt;कण्ठ्य&lt;br&gt;kaṇṭhya
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Glottal consonant|Glottal]]
|-
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Plosive consonant|Stop]]&lt;br&gt;स्पर्श&lt;br&gt;sparśa
! [[Aspiration (phonetics)|Unaspirated]]&lt;br&gt;अल्पप्राण &lt;br&gt;alpaprāṇa
| {{Unicode|p}} {{Unicode|प}} {{IPA|[p]}} || {{Unicode|b}} {{Unicode|ब}} {{IPA|[b]}} || || {{Unicode|t}} {{Unicode|त}} {{IPA|[t̪]}} || {{Unicode|d}} {{Unicode|द}} {{IPA|[d̪]}} || {{Unicode|ṭ}} {{Unicode|ट}} {{IPA|[ʈ&amp;thinsp;]}} || {{Unicode|ḍ}} {{Unicode|ड}} {{IPA|[ɖ&amp;thinsp;]}} || {{Unicode|c}} {{Unicode|च}} {{IPA|[c͡ç]}} || {{Unicode|j}} {{Unicode|ज}} {{IPA|[ɟ͡ʝ]}} || {{Unicode|k}} {{Unicode|क}} {{IPA|[k]}} || {{Unicode|g}} {{Unicode|ग}} {{IPA|[ɡ]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|-
! [[Aspiration (phonetics)|Aspirated]]&lt;br&gt;महाप्राण&lt;br&gt;mahāprāṇa
| {{Unicode|ph}} {{Unicode|फ}} {{IPA|[pʰ]}} || {{Unicode|bh}} {{Unicode|भ}} {{IPA|[bʱ]}} || || {{Unicode|th}} {{Unicode|थ}} {{IPA|[t̪ʰ]}} || {{Unicode|dh}} {{Unicode|ध}} {{IPA|[d̪ʱ]}} || {{Unicode|ṭh}} {{Unicode|ठ}} {{IPA|[ʈʰ]}} || {{Unicode|ḍh}} {{Unicode|ढ}} {{IPA|[ɖʱ]}} || {{Unicode|ch}} {{Unicode|छ}} {{IPA|[c͡çʰ]}} || {{Unicode|jh}} {{Unicode|झ}} {{IPA|[ɟ͡ʝʱ]}} || {{Unicode|kh}} {{Unicode|ख}} {{IPA|[kʰ]}} || {{Unicode|gh}} {{Unicode|घ}} {{IPA|[ɡʱ]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Nasal stop|Nasal]]&lt;br&gt;अनुनासिक&lt;br&gt;anunāsika
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| m {{Unicode|म}} {{IPA|[m]}}
|
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| {{Unicode|n}} {{Unicode|न}} {{IPA|[n̪]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| {{Unicode|ṇ}} {{Unicode|ण}} {{IPA|[ɳ&amp;thinsp;]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| ({{Unicode|ñ}} {{Unicode|ञ}} {{IPA|[&amp;thinsp;ɲ]}})
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| {{Unicode|ṅ}} {{Unicode|ङ}} {{IPA|[ŋ]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Semivowel]]&lt;br&gt;अन्तस्थ&lt;br&gt;antastha
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| v {{Unicode|व}} {{IPA|[ʋ]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| y {{Unicode|य}} {{IPA|[j]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Liquid consonant|Liquid]]&lt;br&gt;ढ्रव&lt;br&gt;drava
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| l {{Unicode|ल}} {{IPA|[l̪]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| r {{Unicode|र}} {{IPA|[ɽ]}}{{dubious|date=March 2012}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| [[Fricative consonant|Fricative]]&lt;br&gt;ऊष्मन्&lt;br&gt;ūṣman
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| {{Unicode|s}} {{Unicode|स}} {{IPA|[s̪]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| {{unicode|ṣ}} {{Unicode|ष}} {{IPA|[ʂ]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| {{unicode|ś}} {{Unicode|श}} {{IPA|[ɕ]}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|
|style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| {{unicode|ḥ}} {{Unicode|ः}} {{IPA|[h]}}
|style=&quot;font-weight: normal&quot;| {{unicode|h}} {{Unicode|ह}} {{IPA|[ɦ]}}
|}

The table below shows the traditional listing of the Sanskrit consonants with the (nearest) equivalents in English (as pronounced in [[General American]] and [[Received Pronunciation]]) and Spanish. Each consonant shown below is deemed to be followed by the neutral vowel [[schwa]] ({{IPA|/ə/}}), and is named in the table as such.

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ [[Stop consonant|Stops]]—sparśa
|-
!
![[Unaspirated]]&lt;br&gt;[[Voiceless]] &lt;br&gt;alpaprāṇa śvāsa
![[Aspiration (phonetics)|Aspirated]]&lt;br&gt;[[Voiceless]]&lt;br&gt;mahāprāna śvāsa
![[Unaspirated]]&lt;br&gt;[[Voice (phonetics)|Voiced]] &lt;br&gt;alpaprāṇa nāda
![[Aspiration (phonetics)|Aspirated]]&lt;br&gt;[[Voice (phonetics)|Voiced]] &lt;br&gt;mahāprāna nāda
![[Nasal stop|Nasal]] &lt;br&gt;anunāsika nāda
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
![[Velar consonant|Velar]]&lt;br&gt;kaṇṭhya
|{{Unicode|क}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/kə/}}; English: s'''k'''ip
|{{Unicode|ख}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/kʰə/}}; English: '''c'''at
|{{Unicode|ग}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɡə/}}; English: '''g'''ame
|{{Unicode|घ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɡʱə/}}; similar to English: do'''gh'''ouse
|{{Unicode|ङ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ŋə/}}; English: ri'''ng'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
![[Palatal]]&lt;br&gt;tālavya
|{{Unicode|च}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/cə/}}; English: ex'''ch'''ange
|{{Unicode|छ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/cʰə/}}; English: '''ch'''urch
|{{Unicode|ज}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɟə/}}; English: '''j'''am
|{{Unicode|झ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɟʱə/}}; similar to English: he'''dgeh'''og
|{{Unicode|ञ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|[&amp;thinsp;ɲə]}}; English: be'''n'''ch
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
![[Retroflex]]&lt;br&gt;mūrdhanya
|{{Unicode|ट}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ʈə/}}; English: s'''t'''op
|{{Unicode|ठ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ʈʰə/}}; English: '''t'''op
|{{Unicode|ड}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɖə/}}; English: '''d'''oor
|{{Unicode|ढ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɖʱə/}}; similar to English: a'''dh'''ere
|{{Unicode|ण}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɳə/}}; English: '''n'''ame
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
![[Apical consonant|apico]]-[[Dental consonant|Dental]]&lt;br&gt;dantya
|{{Unicode|त}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/t̪ə/}}; Spanish: '''t'''oma'''t'''e
|{{Unicode|थ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/t̪ʰə/}}; Aspirated {{IPA|/t̪/}}
|{{Unicode|द}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/d̪ə/}}; Spanish: '''d'''on'''d'''e
|{{Unicode|ध}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/d̪ʱə/}}; Aspirated {{IPA|/d̪/}}
|{{Unicode|न}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/n̪ə/}}; Spanish: '''n'''ombre
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
![[labial consonant|Labial]] &lt;br&gt;oṣṭhya
|{{Unicode|प}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/pə/}}; English: s'''p'''in
|{{Unicode|फ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/pʰə/}}; English: '''p'''it
|{{Unicode|ब}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/bə/}}; English: '''b'''one
|{{Unicode|भ}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/bʱə/}}; similar to English: clu'''bh'''ouse
|{{Unicode|म}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/mə/}}; English: '''m'''ine
|}

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Non-Plosives/Sonorants
|-
!
![[Palatal]]&lt;br&gt;tālavya
![[Retroflex]]&lt;br&gt;mūrdhanya 
![[Dental consonant|Dental]]&lt;br&gt;dantya
![[labial consonant|Labial]]/&lt;br&gt;[[glottal consonant|Glottal]] &lt;br&gt;oṣṭhya
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
![[Approximant]]&lt;br&gt;antastha 
|{{Unicode|य}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/jə/}}; English: '''y'''ou
|{{Unicode|र}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɽə/}}; American English: bu'''tt'''er
|{{Unicode|ल}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/l̪ə/}}; Spanish: '''l'''a
|{{Unicode|व}} (labio-dental)&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ʋə/}}; English: '''v'''ase
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
![[Sibilant]]/&lt;br&gt;[[Fricative]] &lt;br&gt;ūṣmang
|{{Unicode|श}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɕə/}}; English: '''sh'''ip
|{{Unicode|ष}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ʂə/}}; Retroflex form of {{IPA|/ʃ/}}
|{{Unicode|स}} &lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/s̪ə/}}; English: '''s'''ame
|{{Unicode|ह}} (glottal)&lt;br&gt;{{IPA|/ɦə/}}; English a'''h'''ead
|}

===Accent===
{{main|Vedic accent}}
Vedic Sanskrit had [[pitch accent]]: Some syllables had a high tone, and the following syllable a falling tone, though through ellipsis a falling tone may occur elsewhere. 

Classical Sanskrit ...
{{Expand list|date=March 2012}}

===Phonology and sandhi===
The Sanskrit vowels are as discussed in the section above. The long syllabic l ({{unicode|ḹ}}) is not attested, and is only discussed by grammarians for systematic reasons. Its short counterpart {{unicode|ḷ}} occurs in a single root only, {{unicode|kḷp}} &quot;to order, array&quot;. Long syllabic r ({{unicode|ṝ}}) is also quite marginal, occurring in the genitive plural of r-stems (e.g. ''{{unicode|mātṛ}}'' &quot;mother&quot; and ''{{unicode|pitṛ}}'' &quot;father&quot; have gen.pl. ''{{unicode|mātṝṇām}}'' and ''{{unicode|pitṝṇām}}''). {{unicode|i, u, ṛ, ḷ}} are vocalic allophones of consonantal {{unicode|y, v, r, l}}. There are thus only 5 invariably vocalic [[phoneme]]s,
:{{unicode|a, ā, ī, ū, ṝ}}.

[[Visarga]] {{unicode|ḥ}} {{Unicode|ः}} is an [[allophone]] of {{unicode|r}} and {{unicode|s}}, and [[anusvara]] {{unicode|ṃ}}, Devanagari {{Unicode| ं}} of any nasal, both in [[pausa]] (i.e., the [[nasalized vowel]]). The exact pronunciation of the three sibilants may vary, but they are distinct phonemes. An aspirated voiced sibilant {{IPA|/zʱ/}} was inherited by [[Indo-Aryan languages|Indo-Aryan]] from Proto-Indo-Iranian but lost shortly before the time of the Rigveda (aspirated fricatives are exceedingly rare in any language). The [[retroflex consonant]]s are somewhat marginal phonemes, often being conditioned by their phonetic environment; they do not continue a [[PIE]] series and are often ascribed by some linguists to the [[substratum|substratal]] influence of [[Dravidian languages|Dravidian]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_go2081/is_/ai_n28679333|title= On the Indo-European origins of the retroflexes in Sanskrit|accessdate  = 8 January 2009| author=Hamp, Eric P.|date = Oct-December 1996| publisher = Journal of the American Oriental Society, The}}&lt;/ref&gt; or other substrate languages. The nasal {{IPA|[ɲ]}} is a conditioned allophone of {{IPA|/n/}} ({{IPA|/n/}} and {{IPA|/ɳ/}} are distinct phonemes—{{unicode|aṇu}} 'minute', 'atomic' [nom. sg. neutr. of an adjective] is distinctive from {{unicode|anu}} 'after', 'along'; phonologically independent {{unicode|/ŋ/}} occurs only marginally, e.g. in {{unicode|prāṅ}} 'directed forwards/towards' [nom. sg. masc. of an adjective]). There are thus 31 consonantal or semi-vocalic phonemes, consisting of four/five kinds of stops realized both with or without aspiration and both voiced and voiceless, three nasals, four semi-vowels or liquids, and four fricatives, written in [[IAST]] transliteration as follows:
:{{unicode|k, kh, g, gh; c, ch, j, jh; ṭ, ṭh, ḍ, ḍh; t, th, d, dh; p, ph, b, bh; m, n, ṇ; y, r, l, v; ś, ṣ, s, h}}
or a total of 36 unique Sanskrit phonemes altogether.

The [[phonology|phonological]] rules which are applied when combining morphemes to a word, and when combining words to a sentence, are collectively called ''[[sandhi]]'' &quot;composition&quot;. Texts are written phonetically, with sandhi applied (except for the so-called ''{{Unicode|padapāṭha}}'').

==Writing system==
[[File:Kashmir Sharada MS.jpg|thumb|240px|[[Kashmir]]i [[Shaivaite]] manuscript in the [[Sharada script]] (c. 17th century)]]
{{about|how Sanskrit came to be written using various systems|details of Sanskrit as written using devanāgari|Devanagari}}
Sanskrit was spoken in an oral society, and the oral tradition was maintained through the development of early classical [[Sanskrit literature]].&lt;ref&gt;Salomon (1998), p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; Writing was not introduced to India until after Sanskrit had evolved into the Prakrits; when it was written, the choice of writing system was influenced by the regional scripts of the scribes. Therefore, Sanskrit has no native script of its own.&lt;ref name=&quot;banerji&quot;/&gt; As such, virtually all of the major writing systems of South Asia have been used for the production of Sanskrit manuscripts. Since the late 19th century, ''[[devanagari|devanāgari]]'' has become the ''de facto'' standard writing system for Sanskrit publication,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Whitney|1889|p=?}}&lt;/ref&gt; quite possibly because of the European practice of printing Sanskritic texts in this script. Devanāgari is written from left to right, lacks distinct letter cases, and is recognizable by a distinctive horizontal line running along the tops of the letters that links them together.

[[Image:My name is 'incomplete third word is the name' (written) in Sanskrit.jpg|thumb|left|240px|My name is 'incomplete third word is the name' (written) in Sanskrit]]

The earliest known inscriptions in Sanskrit date to the 1st century BCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;salomon&quot;&gt;Salomon (1998), p. 86&lt;/ref&gt;  They are in the [[Brāhmī script|Brahmi]] script, which was originally used for [[Prakrit]], not Sanskrit.&lt;ref name=&quot;masica&quot;&gt;
{{Harvcoltxt|Masica|1991|p=135}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  It has been described as a &quot;paradox&quot; that the first evidence of written Sanskrit occurs centuries later than that of the Prakrit languages which are its linguistic descendants.&lt;ref name=&quot;salomon&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
In northern India, there are [[Brāhmī script|Brahmi]] inscriptions dating from the 3rd century BCE onwards, the oldest appearing on the famous [[Edicts of Ashoka|Prakrit pillar inscriptions]] of king [[Ashoka]]. The earliest South Indian inscriptions in Tamil Brahmi, written in early Tamil, belong to the same period. {{Harvcoltxt|Mahadevan|2003|p=?}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  When Sanskrit was written down, it was first used for texts of an administrative, literary or scientific nature.  The sacred texts were preserved orally, and were set down in writing, &quot;reluctantly&quot; (according to one commentator), and at a comparatively late date.&lt;ref name=&quot;masica&quot;/&gt;

Brahmi evolved into a multiplicity of scripts of the [[Brahmic family]], many of which were used to write Sanskrit.  Roughly contemporary with the Brahmi, the [[Kharosthi]] script was used in the northwest of the subcontinent. Later (around the 4th to 8th centuries CE) the [[Gupta script]], derived from Brahmi, became prevalent. From ca. the 8th century, the [[Sharada script]] evolved out of the Gupta script. The latter was displaced in its turn by [[Devanagari]] from ca. the 11/12th century, with intermediary stages such as the [[Siddham]] script. In Eastern India, the [[Bengali language|Bengali]] script and, later, the [[Oriya script]], were used.  In the south where [[Dravidian languages]] predominate, scripts used for Sanskrit include [[Kannada script|Kannada]], [[Telugu script|Telugu]], [[Tamil script|Tamil]], [[Malayalam language|Malayalam]] and [[Grantha script|Grantha]].

[[File:Phrase sanskrit.png|thumb|300px|Sanskrit in modern Indian and other Brahmi scripts. ''May [[Shiva|Śiva]] bless those who take delight in the language of the gods.'' ([[Kalidasa]])]]

=== Romanization ===
{{Main|Devanagari transliteration}}
Since the late 18th century, Sanskrit has been [[transliteration|transliterated]] using the [[Latin alphabet]]. The system most commonly used today is the [[IAST]] (International Alphabet of Sanskrit Transliteration), which has been the academic standard since 1888/1912. [[ASCII]]-based transliteration schemes have evolved due to difficulties representing Sanskrit characters in computer systems. These include [[Harvard-Kyoto]] and [[ITRANS]], a transliteration scheme that is used widely on the Internet, especially in Usenet and in email, for considerations of speed of entry as well as rendering issues. With the wide availability of [[Unicode]]-aware web browsers, IAST has become common online.

It is also possible to type using an [[alphanumeric keyboard]] and transliterate to devanagari using software like Mac OS X's international support.

European scholars in the 19th century generally preferred Devanagari for the transcription and reproduction of whole texts and lengthy excerpts. However, references to individual words and names in texts composed in European languages were usually represented with Roman transliteration. From the 20th century onwards, due to production costs, textual editions edited by Western scholars have mostly been in [[Romanized]] transliteration.

==Grammar==
{{Main|Sanskrit grammar}}

===Grammatical tradition===
{{Main|Sanskrit grammarians}}

Sanskrit grammatical tradition ('''{{unicode|vyākaraṇa}}''', one of the six [[Vedanga]] disciplines) began in late [[Vedic India]] and culminated in the '''{{unicode|[[Aṣṭādhyāyī]]}}''' of {{unicode|[[Pāṇini]]}}, which consists of 3990 sutras ([[circa|ca.]] 5th century BCE). About a century after {{unicode|[[Pāṇini]]}} (around 400 BCE) Kātyāyana composed Vārtikas on Pāṇinian sũtras. [[Patañjali]], who lived three centuries after Pāṇini, wrote the ''{{unicode|[[Mahābhāṣya]]}}'', the &quot;Great Commentary&quot; on the {{unicode|Aṣṭādhyāyī}} and Vārtikas. Because of these three ancient [[Sanskrit grammarians]] this grammar is called '''Trimuni Vyākarana'''. To understand the meaning of sutras Jayaditya and Vāmana wrote the commentary named Kāsikā 600 CE. Pāṇinian grammar is based on 14 [[Shiva]] sutras (aphorisms). Here whole Mātrika ([[alphabet]]) is abbreviated. This abbreviation is called Pratyāhara.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Abhyankar|1986|p=?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Verbs===
{{Main|Sanskrit verbs}}
Sanskrit has ten classes of [[verb]]s divided into in two broad groups: [[athematic]] and [[Vowel stem|thematic]]. The thematic verbs are so called because an ''a'', called the [[theme vowel]], is inserted between the stem and the ending. This serves to make the thematic verbs generally more regular. [[exponent (linguistics)|Exponents]] used in verb [[grammatical conjugation|conjugation]] include [[Prefix (linguistics)|prefix]]es, [[suffix]]es, [[infix]]es, and [[reduplication]]. Every root has (not necessarily all distinct) zero, [[guna|{{Unicode|guṇa}}]], and [[vrddhi|{{Unicode|vṛddhi}}]] grades. If V is the vowel of the zero grade, the {{Unicode|guṇa}}-grade vowel is traditionally thought of as a + V, and the {{Unicode|vṛddhi}}-grade vowel as ā + V.

The verb [[Grammatical tense|tenses]] (a very inexact application of the word, since more distinctions than simply tense are expressed) are organized into four 'systems' (as well as [[gerund]]s and [[infinitive]]s, and such creatures as [[intensive]]s/[[frequentative]]s, [[desiderative]]s, [[causative]]s, and [[benedictive]]s derived from more basic forms) based on the different stem forms (derived from verbal roots) used in conjugation. There are four tense systems:
*Present ([[Present tense|Present]], [[Imperfect]],{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;!--the imperfect is past tense. Might this be the [[imperfective]]?--&gt; [[Imperative mood|Imperative]], [[Optative mood|Optative]])
*[[perfect (grammar)|Perfect]]
*[[Aorist]]
*[[Future]] ([[Future tense|Future]], [[Conditional mood|Conditional]])

===Nouns===
{{Main|Sanskrit nouns}}
Sanskrit is a highly [[inflection|inflected]] language with three [[grammatical gender]]s (masculine, feminine, neuter) and three numbers (singular, plural, [[dual grammatical number|dual]]). It has eight [[grammatical case|cases]]: [[nominative case|nominative]], [[vocative case|vocative]], [[accusative case|accusative]], [[instrumental case|instrumental]], [[dative case|dative]], [[ablative case|ablative]], [[genitive case|genitive]], and [[locative case|locative]].

The number of actual [[declension]]s is debatable. [[Pāṇini]] identifies six ''karakas'' corresponding to the nominative, accusative, dative, instrumental, locative, and ablative cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chass.utoronto.ca/epc/srb/cyber/man3.html |title=Utoronto.ca |publisher=Chass.utoronto.ca |date= |accessdate=2012-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pāṇini defines them as follows (Ashtadhyayi, I.4.24–54):

# ''Apadana'' (lit. 'take off'): &quot;(that which is) firm when departure (takes place).&quot; This is the equivalent of the ablative case, which signifies a stationary object from which movement proceeds.
# ''Sampradana'' ('bestowal'): &quot;he whom one aims at with the object&quot;. This is equivalent to the dative case, which signifies a recipient in an act of giving or similar acts.
# ''Karana'' (&quot;instrument&quot;) &quot;that which effects most.&quot; This is equivalent to the instrumental case.
# ''Adhikarana'' ('location'): or &quot;substratum.&quot; This is equivalent to the locative case.
# ''Karman'' ('deed'/'object'): &quot;what the agent seeks most to attain&quot;. This is equivalent to the accusative case.
# ''Karta'' ('agent'): &quot;he/that which is independent in action&quot;. This is equivalent to the nominative case. (On the basis of Scharfe, 1977: 94)

===Personal pronouns and determiners===
{{Main|Sanskrit pronouns and determiners}}
Sanskrit [[pronouns]] are declined for [[grammatical case|case]], [[grammatical number|number]], and gender. The pronominal [[declension]] applies to a few adjectives as well. Many pronouns have alternative [[enclitic]] forms.

The first and second [[Grammatical person|person]] pronouns are declined for the most part alike, having by [[analogy]] assimilated themselves with one another. Where two forms are given, the second is [[enclitic]] and an alternative form. [[Ablative]]s in singular and plural may be extended by the syllable -''tas''; thus ''mat'' or ''mattas'', ''asmat'' or ''asmattas''. Sanskrit does not have true third person pronouns, but its demonstratives fulfill this function instead by standing independently without a modified [[substantive]].

There are four different [[demonstrative]]s in Sanskrit: ''tat'', ''etat'', ''idam'', and ''adas''. ''etat'' indicates greater proximity than ''tat''. While ''idam'' is similar to ''etat'', ''adas'' refers to objects that are more remote than ''tat''. ''eta'', is declined almost identically to ''ta''. Its paradigm is obtained by prefixing ''e-'' to all the forms of ''ta''. As a result of ''[[sandhi]]'', the masculine and feminine singular forms transform into ''{{IAST|eṣas}}'' and ''{{IAST|eṣã}}''.

The enclitic pronoun ''ena'' is found only in a few oblique cases and numbers. Interrogative pronouns all begin with ''k-'', and decline just as ''tat'' does, with the initial ''t-'' being replaced by ''k-''. The only exception to this are the singular neuter [[nominative]] and [[accusative]] forms, which are both ''kim'' and not the expected ''*kat''. For example, the singular feminine [[genitive]] [[interrogative]] pronoun, &quot;of whom?&quot;, is ''{{IAST|kasyãḥ}}''. [[Indefinite pronoun]]s are formed by adding the participles ''api'', ''cid'', or ''cana'' after the appropriate interrogative pronouns. All relative pronouns begin with ''y-'', and decline just as ''tat'' does. The correlative pronouns are identical to the ''tat'' series.

In addition to the pronouns described above, some [[adjective]]s follow the pronominal declension. Unless otherwise noted, their declension is identical to ''tat''.
*''eka'': &quot;one&quot;, &quot;a certain&quot;. (singular neuter nominative and accusative forms are both ''ekam'')
*''anya'': &quot;another&quot;.
*''sarva'': &quot;all&quot;, &quot;every&quot;. (singular neuter nominative and accusative forms are both ''sarvam'')
*''para'': &quot;the other&quot;. (singular neuter nominative and accusative forms are both ''param'')
*''sva'': &quot;self&quot; (a reflexive adjective). (singular neuter nominative and accusative forms are both ''svam'')

===Compounds===
{{Main|Sanskrit compounds}}
One other notable feature of the nominal system is the very common use of nominal compounds, which may be huge (10+ words) as in some modern languages such as [[German language|German]] and [[Finnish language|Finnish]]. Nominal compounds occur with various structures, however morphologically speaking they are essentially the same. Each noun (or adjective) is in its (weak) stem form, with only the final element receiving case inflection. The four principle categories of nominal compounds are:&lt;ref name=LennartWarnemyr&gt;Lennart Warnemyr. {{Citation | title = ''An Analytical Cross Referenced Sanskrit Grammar''}} [http://www.warnemyr.com/skrgram/grammar/morphology/compounds.html Compounds]&lt;/ref&gt;

; {{unicode|[[Dvandva]]}} (co-ordinative)
: These consist of two or more [[noun]] stems, connected in sense with 'and'. Examples are ''rāma-lakşmaņau''—Rama and Lakshmana, ''rāma-lakşmaņa-bharata-śatrughnāh''—Rama, Lakshmana, Bharata and Satrughna, and ''pāņipādam''—limbs, literally hands and feet, from pāņi = hand and pāda = foot.
; [[Tatpurusha|{{unicode|Tatpuruṣa}}]] (determinative)
: There are many {{Unicode|tatpuruṣas}}; in a {{Unicode|tatpuruṣa}} the first component is in a case relationship with another. For example, a doghouse is a dative compound, a house ''for'' a dog; other examples include instrumental relationships (&quot;thunderstruck&quot;) and locative relationships (&quot;towndwelling&quot;).
; {{unicode|[[Karmadhāraya]]}} (descriptive)
: A compound where the relation of the first member to the last is [[apposition]]al, [[Substantive adjective|attributive]] or [[adverbial]]; e.g., uluka-yatu (owl+demon) is a demon in the shape of an owl. {{unicode|Karmadhārayas}} are considered by some to be {{unicode|tatpuruṣas}}.&lt;ref name=LennartWarnemyr /&gt;
; {{unicode|[[Bahuvrīhi]]}} (possessive/exocentric)
: Bahuvrīhi compounds refer to a compound noun that refers to a thing which is itself not part of the compound. For example the word bahuvrīhi itself, from bahu = much and vrīhi = rice, denotes a rich person—one who has much rice.

===Syntax===
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}
Because of Sanskrit's complex [[declension]] system the [[word order]] is free.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | last=Staal|first=J.F.|authorlink=Frits Staal | title=Word Order in Sanskrit and Universal Grammar | url=http://books.google.com/?id=VqihQhNkqu4C&amp;pg=PA28&amp;lpg=PA28&amp;dq=free+order | publisher=Springer Science &amp; Business | isbn=978-90-277-0549-5 | year=1967}}&lt;/ref&gt; In usage, there is a strong tendency toward [[subject–object–verb|subject–object–verb (SOV)]], which was the original system in place in Vedic prose. However, there are exceptions when word pairs cannot be transposed.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | last=Gillon|first=B.S | date= March 25, 1996 | journal=Indian linguistics | issn=0378-0759 |volume=57 | title=Word order in Classical Sanskrit | url=http://cat.inist.fr/?aModele=afficheN&amp;cpsidt=2875140 |issue=1–4 | page=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Numerals===
The numbers from one to ten:

# {{IAST|éka-}}
# {{IAST|dva-}}
# {{IAST|tri-}}
# {{IAST|catúr-}}
# {{IAST|páñcan-}}
# {{IAST|ṣáṣ-}}
# {{IAST|saptán-}}
# {{IAST|aṣṭá-}}
# {{IAST|návan-}}
# {{IAST|dáśan-}}

The numbers one through four are declined. '''Éka''' is declined like a pronominal adjective, though the dual form does not occur. '''Dvá''' appears only in the dual. '''Trí''' and '''catúr''' are declined irregularly:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|
!colspan=&quot;3&quot;| Three
!colspan=&quot;3&quot;| Four
|-
! Masculine !! Neuter !! Feminine !! Masculine !! Neuter !! Feminine
|-
! Nominative
| tráyas || {{Unicode|trī́ṇi}}&lt;/font&gt; || tisrás || catvā́ras || catvā́ri || cátasras
|-
! Accusative
| trīn || {{Unicode|trī́ṇi}}&lt;/font&gt; || tisrás || catúras || catvā́ri || cátasras
|-
! Instrumental
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| tribhís
| {{Unicode|tisṛ́bhis}}&lt;/font&gt;
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| catúrbhis
| {{Unicode|catasṛ́bhis}}
|-
! Dative
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| tribhyás
| {{Unicode|tisṛ́bhyas}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| catúrbhyas
| {{Unicode|catasṛ́bhyas}}
|-
! Ablative
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| tribhyás
| {{Unicode|tisṛ́bhyas}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| catúrbhyas
| {{Unicode|catasṛ́bhyas}}
|-
! Genitive
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;|{{Unicode|triyāṇā́m}}
| {{Unicode|tisṛṇā́m}}&lt;/font&gt;
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| {{Unicode|caturṇā́m}}
| {{Unicode|catasṛṇā́m}}
|-
! Locative
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| {{Unicode|triṣú}}
| {{Unicode|tisṛ́ṣu}}
|colspan=&quot;2&quot;| {{Unicode|catúrṣu}}
| {{Unicode|catasṛ́ṣu}}
|}

==Influence==

=== Modern-day India ===

====Influence on vernaculars====
Sanskrit's greatest influence, presumably, is that which it exerted on [[languages of India]] that grew from its vocabulary and grammatical base; for instance, [[Hindi]] is a &quot;Sanskritized register&quot; of the [[Khariboli dialect]]. However, all modern [[Indo-Aryan languages]], as well as [[Munda languages|Munda]] and [[Dravidian languages]], have borrowed many words either directly from Sanskrit (''[[tatsama]]'' words), or indirectly via middle Indo-Aryan languages (''[[tadbhava]]'' words).&lt;ref name = Staal&gt;{{Harvnb|Stall|1963|p=272}}&lt;/ref&gt; Words originating in Sanskrit are estimated to constitute roughly fifty percent of the vocabulary of modern Indo-Aryan languages,&lt;ref name=Chatterji&gt;{{Harvnb|Chatterji|1942}}, cited in {{Harvnb|Stall|1963|p=272}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the literary forms of (Dravidian) [[Malayalam]] and [[Kannada language|Kannada]].&lt;ref name = Staal/&gt; [[Literary]] texts in Telugu are [[lexically]] Sanskrit or Sanskritized to an enormous extent, perhaps seventy percent or more.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title = Classical Telugu Poetry | author1=Velcheru Narayana Rao | author2=David Shulman | edition=2 | publisher=The Regents of the University of California | page=3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sanskrit is prized as a storehouse of scripture and as the language of prayers in [[Hinduism]]. Like [[Latin]]'s influence on European languages and [[Classical Chinese]]'s influence on East Asian languages, Sanskrit has influenced most Indian languages. While vernacular prayer is common, Sanskrit [[mantra]]s are recited by millions of Hindus, and most temple functions are conducted entirely in Sanskrit, often Vedic in form. Of modern day Indian languages, [[Nepali language|Nepali]], [[Bengali language|Bengali]], [[Assamese language|Assamese]], [[Konkani language|Konkani]] and [[Marathi language|Marathi]] still retain a largely Sanskrit and Prakrit vocabulary base, while Hindi and Urdu tend to be more heavily weighted with [[Arabic language|Arabic]] and [[Persian language|Persian]] influence.  The Indian national anthem, [[Jana Gana Mana]], is written in a literary form of Bengali (known as ''sadhu bhasha''); it is Sanskritized to be recognizable but is still archaic to the modern ear. The national song of India, [[Vande Mataram]], which was originally a poem composed by Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay and taken from his book called '[[Anandamath]]', is in a similarly highly Sanskritized Bengali. [[Malayalam language|Malayalam]], [[Telugu language|Telugu]] and [[Kannada language|Kannada]] also combine a great deal of Sanskrit vocabulary. Sanskrit also has influence on Chinese through [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] Sutras. Chinese words like 剎那 ''chànà'' (Devanāgarī: क्षण ''{{IAST|kṣaṇa}}'' 'instantaneous period of time') were borrowed from Sanskrit.

====Revival attempts====
{{Main|Sanskrit revival}}
The 1991 and 2001, [[census of India]] recorded 49,736 and 14,135 persons, respectively, with Sanskrit as their [[first language|native language]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Census&quot;/&gt; Since the 1990s, efforts to revive spoken Sanskrit have been increasing. Many organizations like the ''Samskrta Bharati'' are conducting Speak Sanskrit workshops to popularize the language. The state of [[Uttarakhand]] in India has ruled Sanskrit as its second official language. The ''[[CBSE]]'' (Central Board of Secondary Education) of India has made Sanskrit a third language (though it is an option for the school to adopt it or not, the other choice being the state's own official language) in the schools it governs. In such schools, learning Sanskrit is an option for grades 5 to 8 (Classes V to VIII). This is true of most schools affiliated to the [[Indian Certificate of Secondary Education|ICSE]] board too, especially in those states where the official language is [[Hindi]]. [[Sudharma]], the only daily newspaper in Sanskrit has been published out of [[Mysore]] in India since the year 1970. Since 1974, there has been a short daily news broadcast on state-run [[All India Radio]]. In October 2012 noted social activist [[Hemant Goswami]] filed a [[writ]] petition in the [[Punjab and Haryana High Court]] for declaring Sanskrit as a 'Minority' language, so that it could enjoy special protection as available to minorities under the [[Constitution of India]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/writ-petition-for-according-sanskrit-mi-30530/ |title=Writ Petition on Sanskrit |publisher=JD Supra |date=2012-10-15 |accessdate=2012-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thefinancialworld.com/newsdetails.aspx?newsid=93992&amp;pageid=5 |title=PIL seeks minority status for Sanskrit |publisher=The Financial World|date=2012-10-15 |accessdate=2012-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://goimonitor.com/story/mother-language-sanskrit-needs-urgent-protection |title=Mother language 'Sanskrit' needs urgent protection |publisher=GoI Monitor|date=2012-11-08 |accessdate=2012-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Indian newspapers have published reports about several isolated villages, where, as a result of recent revival attempts, large parts of the population, including children, are learning Sanskrit and are even using it to some extent in everyday communication:
#[[Mattur]] in [[Karnataka]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/msid-1199965,curpg-1.cms |title=This village speaks gods language – India – The Times of India |publisher=Timesofindia.indiatimes.com |date=2005-08-13 |accessdate=2012-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
#Mohad, District: Narasinhpur, Madhya Pradesh
#Jhiri, District: Rajgadh, [[Madhya Pradesh]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/News/madhyapradesh/Sanskrit-boulevard/Article1-339234.aspx |title=Sanskrit boulevard |publisher=Hindustan Times |date=2008-09-20 |accessdate=2012-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
#Kaperan, District: Bundi, Rajasthan
#Khada, District: Banswada, Rajasthan
#Ganoda, District: Banswada, [[Rajasthan]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chitrapurmath.net/sanskrit/sanskrit_lifestyle.htm Chitrapurmath.net] [http://www.hindu.com/fr/2009/07/31/stories/2009073150380200.htm Thehindu.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
#Bawali, District: Bagapat, Uttar Pradesh
#Shyamsundarpur, District: Kendujhar, [[Orissa]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allvoices.com/contributed-news/5574755-orissas-sasana-village-home-to-sanskrit-pundits |title=Orissa's Sasana village – home to Sanskrit pundits! ! |publisher=Allvoices.com |date=2010-04-09 |accessdate=2012-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Symbolic usage===
In the Republic of India, in Nepal and [[Indonesia]], Sanskrit phrases are widely used as [[motto]]es for various educational and social organizations (much as [[Latin]] is used by some institutions in the West). The motto of the Republic is also in Sanskrit.

====India====
; [[Republic of India]]: ''''{{lang|sa|सत्यमेव जयते}}'''' ''[[Satyameva Jayate]]'' &quot;Truth alone triumphs&quot;
; [[Supreme Court of India]]: ''''{{lang|sa|यतो धर्मस्ततो जयः}}'''' ''Yato Dharmastato Jayaha'' &quot;Whence [[dharma]], thence victory&quot;
; [[Goa]]: ''''{{lang|sa|सर्वे भद्राणि पश्यन्तु मा कश्चिद्दुःखभाग्‌भवेत्}}'''' ''Sarve Bhadrāni Paśyantu Mā Kaścid Duhkhabhāg bhavet'' &quot;May all perceive good, may not anyone attain unhappiness&quot;&lt;ref&gt;See the [[:File:Seal of Goa.png|seal of the Government of Goa]]&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[Life Insurance Corporation of India]]: ''''{{lang|sa|योगक्षेमं वहाम्यहम्}}'''', ''Yogakshemam Vahāmyaham'' &quot;I shall take care of welfare&quot; (taken from the [[Bhagavad Gita]])&lt;ref&gt;See e.g. [[:File:LIC Logo.svg]]&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[Indian Navy]]: ''''{{lang|sa|शं नो वरुणः}}'''' ''Shanno Varuna'' &quot;May [[Varuna]] be peaceful to us&quot;
; [[Indian Air Force]]: ''''{{lang|sa|नभःस्पृशं दीप्तम्}}'''' ''{{IAST|Nabhaḥ-Spṛśaṃ Dīptam}}'' &quot;Touching the Sky with Glory&quot; (from [[Bhagavad Gita]]: XI, Verse 24)&lt;ref&gt;[http://indianairforce.nic.in/show_page.php?pg_id=132 The IAF Motto], Official website&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[Mumbai Police]]: ''''{{lang|sa|सद्रक्षणाय खलनिग्रहणाय}}'''' ''Sadrakshanaaya Khalanigrahanaaya'' &quot;For protection of the good and control of the wicked&quot;
; [[Indian Coast Guard]]: ''''{{lang|sa|वयं रक्षामः}}'''' ''Vayam Rakshāmaha'' &quot;We protect&quot;&lt;ref&gt;See [http://indiancoastguard.nic.in/cgbanner5.bmp banner] on [http://indiancoastguard.nic.in/ Indian Coast Guard website]&lt;/ref&gt;
; [[All India Radio]]: ''''{{lang|sa|बहुजनहिताय बहुजन‍सुखाय‌}}'''' ''Bahujana-hitāya bahujana-sukhāya'' &quot;For the benefit of all, for the comfort of all&quot;
; [[Rajputana Rifles]]: ''''{{lang|sa|वीरभोग्या वसुन्धरा}}'''' ''Veerabhogya Vasundhara'' &quot;The earth is fit to be ruled by the brave&quot;

====Other countries====
; [[Nepal]]: ''''{{lang|sa|जननी जन्मभूमिश्च स्वर्गादपि गरीयसी}}'''' ''Janani Janmabhūmisca Svargādapi garīyasi'' &quot;Mother and motherland are greater than heaven&quot;
; [[Indonesian Navy]]: ''''{{lang|sa|जलेष्वेव जयामहे}}'''' ''Jalesveva Jayamahe'' &quot;On the sea we are victorious&quot;
; [[Aceh Province]]: ''''{{lang|sa|पञ्चचित}}'''' ''Pancacita'' &quot;Five Goals&quot;

Many of the post–Independence educational institutions of national importance in India and Sri Lanka have Sanskrit mottoes. For a fuller list of such educational institutions, see [[List of educational institutions which have Sanskrit phrases as their mottoes]].

===Interaction with other languages===
{{Further|Silk Road transmission of Buddhism|Hinduism in Southeast Asia|Indianized kingdom|Sanskritisation}}
Sanskrit and related languages have also influenced their [[Sino-Tibetan]]-speaking neighbors to the north through the spread of [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] texts in translation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|van Gulik|1956|p=?}}&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhism was spread to China by [[Mahayana|Mahayanist]] missionaries sent by Emperor Ashoka mostly through translations of [[Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit]] and Classical Sanskrit texts, and many terms were transliterated directly and added to the Chinese vocabulary. (Although Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit is not Sanskrit, properly speaking, its grammar and vocabulary are substantially the same, both because of genetic relationship, and because of conscious implementation of Pāṇinian standardizations on the part of composers. Buddhist texts composed in Sanskrit proper were primarily found in philosophical schools like the [[Madhyamaka]].) The situation in Tibet is similar; many Sanskrit texts survive only in Tibetan translation (in the [[Tanjur]]).

In [[Southeast Asia]], languages such as [[Thai language|Thai]] and [[Lao language|Lao]] contain many [[loan word]]s from Sanskrit, as do [[Khmer language|Khmer]], [[Vietnamese language|Vietnamese]] to a lesser extent, through Sinified hybrid Sanskrit. For example, in Thai, the [[Raavana|Rāvana]]—the emperor of [[Sri Lanka]] is called 'Thosakanth' which is a derivation of his Sanskrit name 'Dashakanth' (&quot;of ten necks&quot;). 

Many Sanskrit loanwords are also found in [[Austronesian languages]], such as [[Javanese language|Javanese]] particularly the [[Old Javanese|old form]] from which nearly half the vocabulary is derived from the language.&lt;ref&gt;See [[:id:Daftar kata serapan dari bahasa Sansekerta dalam bahasa Indonesia|this page]] from the [[Indonesian Wikipedia]] for a list&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvcoltxt|Zoetmulder|1982|p=ix}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other Austronesian languages, such as [[Malay language|traditional Malay]], [[Indonesian language|modern Indonesian]], also derive [[List of loan words in Indonesian#From Sanskrit|much of their vocabulary]] from Sanskrit, albeit to a lesser extent, with a large proportion of words being derived from [[Arabic language|Arabic]].  Similarly, [[Philippine languages]] such as [[Tagalog]] have [[List of Tagalog loanwords#Sanskrit|many Sanskrit loanwords]], although more are derived from [[Spanish language|Spanish]].

A Sanskrit loanword encountered in many Southeast Asian languages is the word ''[[bahasa|bhāṣā]]'', or spoken language, which is used to mean language in general, for example ''bahasa'' in [[Malay language|Malay]], [[Indonesian language|Indonesian]] and [[Tausug language|Tausug]], ''basa'' in  [[Javanese language|Javanese]], [[Sundanese language|Sundanese]], and [[Balinese language|Balinese]]'', ''phasa'' in [[Thai language|Thai]] and [[Lao language|Lao]], ''bhasa'' in [[Burmese language|Burmese]], and 'phiesa'' in [[Khmer language|Khmer]].

===Usage in modern times===
{{See also|Sanskrit in the West}}
Many of India's and Nepal's scientific and administrative terms are named in Sanskrit, as a counterpart of the western practice of naming scientific developments in Latin or Greek.{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}} The [[Integrated Guided Missile Development Program|Indian guided missile program]] that was commenced in 1983 by [[DRDO]] has named the five missiles (ballistic and others) that it has developed as [[Prithvi missile|Prithvi]], [[Agni missile system|Agni]], [[Akash missile|Akash]], [[Nag missile|Nag]] and [[Trishul missile|Trishul]]. India's first modern fighter [[aircraft]] is named [[HAL Tejas]].

Recital of Sanskrit [[shloka]]s as background chorus in films, television advertisements and as slogans for corporate organizations has become a trend. The opera ''[[Satyagraha (opera)|Satyagraha]]'' by [[Philip Glass]] uses texts from the ''Bhagavad Gita'', sung in the original Sanskrit.

Recently, Sanskrit also made an appearance in Western pop music in two recordings by [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]]. One, &quot;Shanti/Ashtangi&quot;, from the 1998 album ''[[Ray of Light]]'', is the traditional [[Ashtanga Vinyasa Yoga]] chant referenced above set to music. The second, &quot;Cyber-raga&quot;, released in 2000 as a B-side to Madonna's album ''[[Music (Madonna album)|Music]]'', is a Sanskrit-language ode of devotion to a higher power and a wish for peace on earth. The climactic battle theme of ''[[The Matrix Revolutions]]'' features a choir singing a Sanskrit prayer from the [[Brihadaranyaka Upanishad]] in the closing titles of the movie. Composer [[John Williams]] featured choirs singing in Sanskrit for ''[[Indiana Jones and the Temple of Doom]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.filmtracks.com/titles/temple_doom.html |title=Indiana Jones and the Temple of Doom (John Williams) |publisher=Filmtracks |date=2008-11-11 |accessdate=2012-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in ''[[Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace]]''.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

The [[Sky1]] version of the title sequence in season one of ''[[Battlestar Galactica (2004 TV series)|Battlestar Galactica 2004]]'' features the [[Gayatri Mantra]], taken from the [[Rig Veda]] (3.62.10). The composition was written by miniseries composer [[Richard Gibbs]].

Sanskrit has also seen a significant revival in [[PRC|China]].  Musicians such as [[Sa Dingding]] have written [[popular songs|pop songs]] in Sanskrit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio3/worldmusic/a4wm2008/2008_sa_ding_ding.shtml ''BBC - Awards for World Music 2008 - Asia/Pacific''], broadcast on [[BBC Radio 3]] and [[BBC Four]] television.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scientific facts on Sanskrit==
Most European languages have their roots in Sanskrit.{{Dubious|date=November 2012}} Many English words have Sanskrit origins. It is regarded to be one of the most scientific langauages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sanskrit Language, The Most Scientific, Ancient, Spiritual : Prof. Dean Brown|url=http://www.ibtl.in/video/6376/sanskrit-language-the-most-scientific-ancient-spiritual-prof-dean-brown}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dubious|date=November 2012}} 

===Computational linguistics===
There have been suggestions to use Sanskrit as a [[metalanguage]] for knowledge representation in e.g. [[machine translation]], and other areas of [[natural language processing]] because of its relatively high regular structure.&lt;ref&gt;First suggested by {{Harvcoltxt|Briggs|1985}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is due to Classical Sanskrit being a regularized, [[Linguistic prescription|prescriptivist]] form abstracted from the much more complex and richer [[Vedic Sanskrit]]. This leveling of the grammar of Classical Sanskrit began during the Brahmana phase, and had not yet completed by the time of Pāṇini, when the language had fallen out of popular use.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

==See also==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;
* [[Avestan]]
* [[Devanagari]]
* [[Grantha|Grantha Script]]
* [[Indo-European languages]]
* [[International Alphabet of Sanskrit Transliteration]]
* [[Languages of India]]
* [[Sanskrit literature]]
* [[Sanskrit numerals]]
&lt;/div&gt;

==Notes==

=== Footnotes ===
&lt;references group=&quot;note&quot; /&gt;

=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{Citation
|last=Abhyankar
|first=Kashinath V.
|title=A dictionary of Sanskrit Grammar,
|series=Gaekwad's Oriental Series
|volume=134
|year=1986
|place=Baroda
|publisher=Oriental Institute
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Briggs
|first=Rick
|year=1985
|title=Knowledge Representation in Sanskrit and Artificial Intelligence (PDF)
|url=http://www.aaai.org/ojs/index.php/aimagazine/article/viewArticle/466
|journal=AI Magazine
|volume=6
|issue=1
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Burrow
|first=T.
|title=Sanskrit language
|publisher=Motilal Banarsidass
|year=2001
|isbn=81-208-1767-2
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Chatterji
|first=Suniti Kumar
|authorlink=Suniti Kumar Chatterji
|title=Indo-Aryan and Hindi
|publisher=Firma K. L. Mukhopadhyay
|year=1960
|isbn=
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Edgerton
|first=F.
|title=Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit grammar and dictionary
|year=1953
|place= New Haven
|publisher=Yale University Press
}}
*{{Citation
|last=van Gulik
|first=Robert
|authorlink=Robert van Gulik
|title=Siddham; an essay on the history of Sanskrit studies in China and Japan
|year=1956
|place=Nagpur
|publisher=International Academy of Indian Culture
|isbn=81-7742-038-0
}}
*{{citation
|doi=10.1023/A:1021366131934
|last=Hanneder
|first=J.
|year=2002
|title=On &quot;The Death of Sanskrit&quot;
|journal=Indo-Iranian Journal
|volume=45
|issue=4
|pages=293–310(18)
|url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/n5380t62066168r7/
}}
*{{citation
|last=Hanneder
|first=J.
|year=2009
|contribution=Modernes Sanskrit: eine vergessene Literatur
|title=Pāsādikadānaṃ : Festschrift für Bhikkhu Pāsādika
|editor-last=Straube
|editor-first=Martin
|editor3-last=Steiner
|editor3-first=Roland
|editor6-last=Soni
|editor8-first=Jayandra
|editor4-last=Hahn
|editor-first4=Michael
|editor-last5=Demoto
|publisher=Indica et Tibetica Verlag
|pages=205–228
|url=http://indologica.de/drupal/?q=node/749
}}
*{{citation
|last=Hatcher
|first=Brian A.
|year=2007
|title=Sanskrit and the morning after
|journal=Indian Economic &amp; Social History Review
|accessdate=2010-09-15
|volume=44
|issue=3
|pages=333–361
|url=http://ier.sagepub.com/content/44/3/333.abstract
|doi=10.1177/001946460704400303
}}
*{{Citation
|last=MacDonell
|first=Arthur Anthony
|authorlink=Arthur Anthony Macdonell
|title=[[s:A History of Sanskrit Literature|A History of Sanskrit Literature]]
|year=1900
|publisher=Kessinger Publishing (2004)
|location=
|isbn=1-4179-0619-7
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Mahadevan
|first=I
|title=Early Tamil epigraphy from the earliest times to the sixth century Common Era |place=Chennai/Cambridge
|year=2003
}}
*{{Citation
 |last=Masica
 |first=Colin
 |authorlink=Colin Masica
 |year=1991
 |title=The Indo-Aryan Languages
|place= Cambridge
 |publisher=Cambridge University Press
 |isbn=978-0-521-29944-2
 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=J3RSHWePhXwC
}}
*{{Citation
|doi=10.1177/001946460404100402
|last=Minkowski
|first=Christopher
|title={{IAST|Nīlakaṇṭha's}} instruments of war: Modern, vernacular, barbarous
|year=2004
|journal=The Indian Economic and Social History Review
|volume=41
|issue=4
|pages=365–385
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Monier-Williams
|first=Monier
|authorlink=Monier Monier Williams
|year=1898
|title=A Sanskrit-English Dictionary
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Oberlies
|first=Thomas
|title=A Grammar of Epic Sanskrit
|year=2003
|publisher=Walter de Gruyter
|isbn=3-11-014448-4
}}
*{{Citation
|doi=10.1017/S001041750100353X
|last=Pollock
|first=Sheldon
|authorlink=Sheldon Pollock
|year=2001
|title=The Death of Sanskrit
|journal=Comparative Studies in Society and History
|volume=43
|issue=2
|pages=392–426
|url=http://www.columbia.edu/itc/mealac/pollock/sks/papers/death_of_sanskrit.pdf
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Pollock
|first=Sheldon I.
|authorlink = Sheldon Pollock
|year=2006
|title = The language of the gods in the world of men: Sanskrit, culture, and power in premodern India
|publisher=[[University of California Press]]
|isbn=978-0-520-24500-6
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Staal
|first=J.F.
|authorlink=Frits Staal
|title=Sanskrit and Sanskritization
|journal=The Journal of Asian Studies
|volume=22
|issue=3
|pages=261–275
|year=1963
|doi=10.2307/2050186
|publisher=Association for Asian Studies
|jstor=2050186}}
*{{Citation
|last=Tiwari
|first=Bholanath
|title=भाषा विज्ञान (Bhasha Vijnan)
|year=1955
|isbn=0-7007-1382-4
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Warder
|first=A.K.
|authorlink=A. K. Warder
|year=1972
|title=Indian kāvya Literature
|volume=1
|series=Literary Criticism
|place=Delhi
|publisher=Motilal Banarsidass
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Whitney
|first=William Dwight
|authorlink=William Dwight Whitney
|year=1889
|title=Sanskrit Grammar: Including both the Classical Language and the Older Dialects
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=VHYKAAAAIAAJ
|publisher=Breitkopf &amp; Härtel
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Zoetmulder
|first=Petrus Josephus
|authorlink=Petrus Josephus Zoetmulder
|year=1982
|title=Old Javanese-English dictionary
|place=[[The Hague]]
|publisher=Nijhoff
}}
* {{Citation
|title=Indian epigraphy: a guide to the study of inscriptions in Sanskrit, Prakrit, and the other Indo-Aryan languages
|first=Richard
|last=Salomon
|location=New York
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|year=1998
|isbn=0-19-509984-2
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=XYrG07qQDxkC
}}
*{{Citation
|title=The Original Pronunciation of Sanskrit
|first=Ulrich 
|last=Stiehl
|location=Germany
|publisher=Verlag Forkel 
|year=2011
|isbn=978-3-7719-0086-1, 978-3-7719-0085-4, 978-3-87081-539-4 
|url=http://www.lit-on.de/v/artikel/sanskrit-kompendium/
}}

==Further reading==

=== Introductions ===
*{{Citation
|last=Cameron
|first=Bruce
|title=Sanskrit Pronunciation
|isbn=1-55700-021-2
|year=1992
|publisher=Theosophical Univ Press
|location=S.l.
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Coulson
|first=M.
|title=Teach Yourself Sanskrit
|isbn=0-340-85990-3
|year=2003
|publisher=Teach Yourself
|location=London
}}
*{{Citation
|last=Goldman
|first=Robert P.
|title={{Unicode|Devavāṇīpraveśikā: An Introduction to the Sanskrit Language}}
|isbn=0-944613-40-3
|year=1999
|publisher=Center for South Asia Studies, University of California
|location=Berkeley
}}
* {{Citation
|last=Kale
|first=M. R. (Moreshwar Ramchandra)
|title=A Higher Sanskrit Grammar
|isbn=81-208-0178-4
|year=1988
|origyear=1894
|publisher=Motilal Banarsidass
|location=Delhi
|url=http://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/scans/KALEScan/disp1/index1.php?sfx=png
}}
* {{Citation
|last=Macdonell
|first=Arthur Anthony
|title=A Sanskrit Grammar for Students
|isbn=81-246-0094-5
|year=1997
|publisher=D.K. Printworld
|location=New Delhi
}}
* {{Citation
|last=Maurer
|first=Walter Harding
|title=The Sanskrit Language: An Introductory Grammar and Reader
|isbn=0-7007-1382-4
|year=2000
|publisher=Curzon Press
|location=Richmond, Surrey
}}
*{{citation
|last=Seth
|first=Sanjay
|year=2007
|title=Subject Lessons: The Western Education of Colonial India
|publisher=Duke University Press
|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=QU9glkC4ceMC
}}
* {{Citation
|last=Shastri
|first=Vagish
|title=Conversational Sanskrit
|isbn=81-85570-12-4
|year=2000
|publisher=Vāgyoga Chetanāpitham
|location=Varanasi
}}
* {{Citation
|last=Monier-Williams
|first=Monier
|authorlink=Monier Monier-Williams
|title=A Practical Grammar Of The Sanskrit Language Arranged With Reference To The Classical Languages Of Europe For The Use Of English Students
|year=1846
|publisher=W. H. Allen &amp; co.
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=REQhAAAAMAAJ
}}

=== Grammars ===
*Whitney, William Dwight ''The Roots, Verb-Forms and Primary Derivatives of the Sanskrit Language: (A Supplement to His Sanskrit Grammar)''
*Wackernagel, Debrunner, ''[[Altindische Grammatik]]'', Göttingen.
**vol. I. [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN1421247127&amp;id=mWaIUMIoUvkC&amp;dq=Altindische Phonology] [[Jacob Wackernagel]] (1896)
**vol. II.1. [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN1421247100&amp;id=qql6RRqTAuIC&amp;dq=Altindische Introduction to morphology, nominal composition], Wackernagel (1905)
**vol. II.2. nominal suffixes, J. Wackernagel and Albert Debrunner (1954)
**vol. III. nominal inflection, numerals, pronouns, Wackernagel and Debrunner (1930)
*Delbrück, B. ''[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN1421246880&amp;id=_-9K_xT8OBAC&amp;dq=Altindische Altindische Tempuslehre]'' (1876)

=== Dictionaries ===
*[[Otto Böhtlingk]], Rudolph Roth, ''Petersburger Wörterbuch'', 7 vols., 1855–75
*Otto Böhtlingk, ''Sanskrit Wörterbuch in kürzerer Fassung'' 1883–86 (1998 reprint, Motilal Banarsidass, Delhi)
*[[Manfred Mayrhofer]], ''Kurzgefasstes etymologisches Wörterbuch des Altindischen'', 1956–76
*Manfred Mayrhofer, ''Etymologisches Wörterbuch des Altindoarischen'', 3 vols., 2742 pages, 2001, ISBN 3-8253-1477-4

==External links==
{{Prone to spam|date=April 2012}}
{{Z148}}&lt;!--     {{No more links}}

       Please be cautious adding more external links.

Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising. 

     Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed.   

 See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.

If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on
the article's talk page, or submit your link to the relevant category at 
the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) and link there  using {{Dmoz}}.

--&gt;
{{Interwiki|code=sa}}
{{WikisourceWiki|code=sa}}
{{Wiktionary category|category=Sanskrit language}}
{{Wikibooks|Sanskrit}}
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.montclair.edu/RISA/d-studies.html Academic Courses on Sanskrit Around The World]
*[http://samskrita-bharati.org/ Samskrita Bharati], organization promoting Sanskrit
*[http://www.user.uni-hannover.de/nhtcapri/sanskrit-alphabet.html Sanskrit Alphabet] in Devanagari, Gujarati, Bengali, and Thai scripts with an extensive list of Devanagari, Gujarati, and Bengali conjuncts

===Software===
{{Main|Help:Multilingual support (Indic)}}
* [http://www.oopslite.com/software/nepali_keyboard.html Romanized Nepali Unicode Keyboard] developed by OOPSLite Technologies
* [http://baraha.com/ Sanskrit transliteration software] with font conversion to Latin and other Indian Languages

===Sanskrit documents===
*[http://sanskritdocuments.org/home.html Sanskrit Documents] — Documents in ITX format of Upanishads, Stotras etc. and a metasite with links to translations, dictionaries, tutorials, tools and other Sanskrit resources.
*[http://uwest.edu/sanskritcanon/index.html Digital Sanskrit Buddhist Canon]
*[http://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/ebene_1/fiindolo/gretil.htm Gretil: Göttingen Register of Electronic Texts in Indian Languages] — a cumulative register of the numerous download sites for electronic texts in Indian languages.
*[http://www.granthamandira.com/index.php?show=home Gaudiya Grantha Mandira] — A Sanskrit Text Repository. This site also provides encoding converter.
*[http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/index.htm Sanskrit texts at Sacred Text Archive]
*[[Digital Library of India]] at [http://www.new.dli.ernet.in/ Ernet.in] and [http://dli.iiit.ac.in/ IIIT.in] — scanned/OCRed copies of public-domain books

===Primers===
*[http://sanskritdocuments.org/learning_tutorial_wikner/index.html A Practical Sanskrit Introductory by Charles Wikner]
*[http://chitrapurmath.net/sanskrit/sanskrit.asp Sanskrit Self Study] by Chitrapur Math
*[http://warnemyr.com/skrgram/ An Analytical Cross Referenced Sanskrit Grammar] By Lennart Warnemyr

{{Languages of India}}
{{Languages of South Asia}}
{{Indo-Iranian languages}}
{{Buddhism topics}}

[[Category:Sanskrit| ]]
[[Category:Ancient languages]]
[[Category:Classical languages of India]]
[[Category:Indo-Aryan languages]]
[[Category:Subject–object–verb languages]]
[[Category:Languages written in Devanagari]]

{{Link GA|no}}
[[pa:ਸੰਸਕ੍ਰਿਤ ਭਾਸ਼ਾ]]
[[kbd:Санскрит]]
[[af:Sanskrit]]
[[als:Sanskrit]]
[[am:ሳንስክሪት]]
[[ar:لغة سنسكريتية]]
[[an:Sanscrito]]
[[as:সংস্কৃত]]
[[ast:Sánscritu]]
[[az:Sanskrit]]
[[bn:সংস্কৃত ভাষা]]
[[zh-min-nan:Hoân-gí]]
[[be:Санскрыт]]
[[be-x-old:Санскрыт]]
[[bh:संस्कृत]]
[[bcl:Sanskrito]]
[[bg:Санскрит]]
[[bar:Sanskrit]]
[[bo:ལེགས་སྦྱར་སྐད།]]
[[bs:Sanskrit]]
[[br:Sañskriteg]]
[[ca:Sànscrit]]
[[ceb:Pinulongang Sanskrito]]
[[cs:Sanskrt]]
[[cy:Sansgrit]]
[[da:Sanskrit]]
[[de:Sanskrit]]
[[dv:ސަންސްކްރިއްތް]]
[[et:Sanskriti keel]]
[[el:Σανσκριτική γλώσσα]]
[[es:Sánscrito]]
[[eo:Sanskrito]]
[[eu:Sanskrito]]
[[fa:زبان سانسکریت]]
[[hif:Sanskrit]]
[[fr:Sanskrit]]
[[fy:Sanskryt]]
[[ga:An tSanscrait]]
[[gl:Lingua sánscrita]]
[[gan:梵語]]
[[gu:સંસ્કૃત ભાષા]]
[[hak:Fan-vun]]
[[xal:Эндкгин келн]]
[[ko:산스크리트어]]
[[hy:Սանսկրիտ]]
[[hi:संस्कृत भाषा]]
[[hr:Sanskrt]]
[[io:Sanskrita linguo]]
[[ilo:Sanskrito]]
[[bpy:সংস্কৃত]]
[[id:Bahasa Sanskerta]]
[[ia:Sanscrito]]
[[is:Sanskrít]]
[[it:Lingua sanscrita]]
[[he:סנסקריט]]
[[jv:Basa Sangskreta]]
[[kn:ಸಂಸ್ಕೃತ]]
[[ka:სანსკრიტი]]
[[kk:Санскрит]]
[[kw:Sanskrytek]]
[[rw:Igisansikiriti]]
[[sw:Kisanskrit]]
[[kv:Санскрит]]
[[ku:Sanskrît]]
[[la:Lingua Sanscrita]]
[[lv:Sanskrits]]
[[lt:Sanskritas]]
[[lij:Lengua sànscrïa]]
[[li:Sanskriet]]
[[lez:Санскрит]]
[[lmo:Lengua sanscrita]]
[[hu:Szanszkrit nyelv]]
[[mk:Санскритски јазик]]
[[mg:Sanskrity]]
[[ml:സംസ്കൃതം]]
[[mr:संस्‍कृत भाषा]]
[[arz:سانسكريتى]]
[[ms:Sanskrit]]
[[mn:Санскрит хэл]]
[[my:သင်္သကရိုက်ဘာသာ]]
[[nah:Sanscritotlahtōlli]]
[[nl:Sanskriet]]
[[ne:संस्कृत]]
[[new:संस्कृत]]
[[ja:サンスクリット]]
[[no:Sanskrit]]
[[nn:Sanskrit]]
[[oc:Sanscrit]]
[[or:ସଂସ୍କୃତ ଭାଷା]]
[[pnb:سنسکرت]]
[[ps:سانسګریت ژبه]]
[[km:សំស្ក្រឹត]]
[[pms:Sànscrit]]
[[nds:Sanskrit]]
[[pl:Sanskryt]]
[[pt:Sânscrito]]
[[ro:Limba sanscrită]]
[[qu:Sanskrit simi]]
[[rue:Санскріт]]
[[ru:Санскрит]]
[[sah:Санскрит]]
[[sa:संस्कृतम्]]
[[sco:Sanskrit]]
[[scn:Lingua sanscrita]]
[[simple:Sanskrit]]
[[sk:Sanskrit]]
[[sl:Sanskrt]]
[[ckb:زمانی سانسکریت]]
[[sr:Санскрит]]
[[sh:Sanskrit]]
[[su:Basa Sangsakerta]]
[[fi:Sanskrit]]
[[sv:Sanskrit]]
[[tl:Wikang Sanskrito]]
[[ta:சமசுகிருதம்]]
[[roa-tara:Lènga sanscrite]]
[[tt:Санскрит]]
[[te:సంస్కృతము]]
[[th:ภาษาสันสกฤต]]
[[tr:Sanskritçe]]
[[uk:Санскрит]]
[[ur:سنسکرت]]
[[za:Vahfan]]
[[vi:Tiếng Phạn]]
[[war:Sinanskrit]]
[[yi:סאנסקריט]]
[[zh-yue:梵文]]
[[bat-smg:Sanskrita kalba]]
[[zh:梵语]]</text>
      <sha1>0bqipw21tjkns0xux1e4y0netb1dkvd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
