<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Scofield Reference Bible</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>187679</id>
    <revision>
      <id>509525081</id>
      <parentid>509523673</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-28T01:04:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John Foxe</username>
        <id>1306479</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 496354585 by Dwats012: misunderstanding. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6488">The '''''Scofield Reference Bible''''' is a widely circulated [[study Bible]] edited and annotated by the American Bible student [[Cyrus I. Scofield]], that popularized [[dispensationalism]] at the beginning of the 20th century.  Published by [[Oxford University Press]] and containing the traditional [[Protestant]] [[King James Version]] of the Bible, it first appeared in 1909 and was revised by the author in 1917.&lt;ref&gt;The title page listed seven &quot;consulting editors&quot;: Henry G. Weston, [[James M. Gray]], [[W.J. Erdman]], [[Arthur Tappan Pierson|A.T. Pierson]], W. G. Moorehead, [[Elmore Harris]], and [[Arno Clemens Gaebelein|A. C. Gaebelein]]. &quot;Just what role these consulting editors played in the project has been the subject of some debate.  Apparently Scofield only meant to acknowledge their assistance, though some have speculated that he hoped to gain support for his publication from both sides of the millenarian movement with this device.&quot; Ernest Sandeen, ''The Roots of Fundamentalism: British and American Millenarianism, 1800-1930'' (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1970), 224.&lt;/ref&gt;   

The Scofield Bible had several innovative features. Most important, it printed what amounted to a commentary on the biblical text alongside the Bible instead of in a separate volume.&lt;ref&gt;The Scofield Bible was the predecessor of the &quot;very successful marketing trend&quot; of orienting Bible study tools to average laymen. Mangum &amp; Sweetnam, 172.&lt;/ref&gt; It also contained a cross-referencing system that tied together related verses of Scripture and allowed a reader to follow biblical themes from one chapter and book to another. Finally, the 1917 edition also attempted to date events of the Bible. It was in the pages of the Scofield Reference Bible that many Christians first encountered Archbishop [[James Ussher]]'s calculation of the [[Ussher chronology|date of Creation]] as 4004 BC; and through discussion of Scofield's notes, which advocated the &quot;[[Gap Creationism|gap theory]],&quot; [[Christian fundamentalism|fundamentalists]] began a serious internal debate about the nature and chronology of [[Genesis creation myth|creation]].&lt;ref&gt;It should be noted that Ussher's dates and the gap theory are &quot;not completely congruous with one another,&quot; Ussher's dates implying a [[Young Earth creationism|young earth]], and the &quot;gap&quot; between the first two verses of Genesis—as well as Scofield's allowance of the [[Day-Age creationism|day-age]] theory—suggesting the possibility of an [[Old Earth creationism|old earth]]. Mangum &amp; Sweetnam, 97.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Scofield Bible was published only a few years before World War I destroyed the cultural optimism that had viewed the world as entering a new era of peace and prosperity; and the post-World War II era saw the creation in Israel of a homeland for the Jews.  Thus, Scofield's [[premillennial|premilliennialism]] seemed almost prophetic. &quot;At the popular level, especially, many people came to regard the dispensationalist scheme as completely vindicated.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mangum &amp; Sweetnam, 179.&lt;/ref&gt; Sales of the Reference Bible exceeded two million copies by the end of World War II.&lt;ref&gt;Gaebelein, 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Scofield Reference Bible promoted [[dispensationalism]], the belief that between creation and the [[Last Judgment|final judgment]] there were seven distinct eras of God's dealing with man and that these eras were a framework for synthesizing the message of the Bible.&lt;ref&gt;Magnum &amp; Sweetnam, 188-195. &quot;Historically speaking, The Scofield Reference Bible was to dispensationalism what Luther's ''[[Ninety-Five Theses]]'' was to Lutheranism, or Calvin's ''[[Institutes of the Christian Religion|Institutes]]'' to Calvinism.&quot; (195).&lt;/ref&gt; It was largely through the influence of Scofield's notes that dispensationalism grew in influence among fundamentalist Christians in the United States. Scofield's notes on the [[Book of Revelation]] are a major source for the various timetables, judgments, and plagues elaborated by popular religious writers such as [[Hal Lindsey]], [[Edgar C. Whisenant]], and [[Tim LaHaye]];&lt;ref&gt;Mangum &amp; Sweetnam, 218.&lt;/ref&gt; and in part because of the success of the Scofield Reference Bible, twentieth-century American fundamentalists placed greater stress on [[eschatology|eschatological]] speculation. Opponents of biblical fundamentalism have criticized the Scofield Bible for its air of total authority in biblical interpretation, for what they consider its glossing over of biblical contradictions, and for its focus on eschatology.&lt;ref&gt;Bruce Bawer, ''Stealing Jesus: How Fundamentalism Betrays Christianity'' (New York: Three Rivers Press, 1997).&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1917 Scofield Reference Bible is now in the [[public domain]], continues to be published, and is &quot;consistently the best selling edition&quot; in the United Kingdom and Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;Mangum &amp; Sweetnam, 201.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1967, Oxford University Press published a revision of the Scofield Bible with a slightly modernized KJV text and a muting of some of the tenets of Scofield's theology.&lt;ref&gt;Mangum &amp; Sweetnam, 201. &quot;The continuing popularity of the 1917 notes may reflect the preference of the purchasers for the original and ''full-strength'' Scofield.&quot; Mangum &amp; Sweetnam suggest the popularity of the 1917 edition may also reflect a strong commitment to the KJV translation.&lt;/ref&gt; The Press continues to issue editions under the title ''Oxford Scofield Study Bible'', and there are translations into French, German, Spanish, and Portuguese. For instance, the [[French language|French]] edition published by the Geneva Bible Society is printed with a revised version of the [[Louis Segond]] translation that includes additional notes by a Francophone committee.&lt;ref&gt;Mangum &amp; Sweetnam, 202-03.  Some of the notes have also appeared in Korean and Polynesian.&lt;/ref&gt; 

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*[[Arno Clemens Gaebelein|Arno C. Gaebelein]], ''The History of the Scofield Reference Bible'' (Our Hope Publications, 1943)
*R. Todd Mangum and Mark S. Sweetnam, ''The Scofield Bible: Its History and Impact on the Evangelical Church'' (Colorado Springs: Paternoster Publishing, 2009)

==External links==
*[http://www.studylight.org/com/srn/ Searchable text] of the 1917 version of the '' Scofield Reference Bible'' reference notes.

[[Category:1909 books]]
[[Category:Study Bibles]]
[[Category:Christian fundamentalism]]
[[Category:Authorized King James Version editions]]
[[Category:1909 in religion]]

[[de:Scofield-Bibel]]
[[zh:司可福串注圣经]]</text>
      <sha1>qqrzbpu76cea7dyrmm32fj3nis111s2</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
