<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Second Vatican Council</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28134</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521817365</id>
      <parentid>521083085</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-07T12:46:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>121.54.58.130</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Scripture and divine revelation */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41175">{{Lead too short|date=April 2012}}
{{Infobox Ecumenical council
| bodystyle    = more to love
| council_name = Second Vatican Council
| council_date = {{start date|1962}}–{{end date|1965}}
| accepted_by  = [[Catholic Church]]. Not accepted by [[Sedevacantists]] and [[Marcel Lefebvre|Lefebvrists]].
| previous     = [[First Vatican Council]]
| next         =
| convoked_by  = [[Pope John XXIII]]
| presided_by  = [[Pope John XXIII]], [[Pope Paul VI]]
| attendance   = up to 2625&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.catholic-hierarchy.org/event/ecv2.html |title=Second Vatican Council |author=David M. Cheney |work=Catholic-Hierarchy |accessdate=2011-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| topics       = The Church in itself, in relation to [[ecumenism]] and other religions, in relation to the modern world, renewal, liturgy, etc.
| documents    = Four Constitutions:
* ''[[Dei Verbum]]'' (Dogmatic Constitution on Divine Revelation)
* ''[[Lumen Gentium]]'' (Dogmatic Constitution on the Church)
* ''[[Gaudium et Spes]]'' (Pastoral Constitution on the Church in the Modern World)
* ''[[Sacrosanctum Concilium]]'' (Constitution on the Sacred Liturgy)
nine decrees:
* ''[[Ad Gentes]]'' (Decree on the Church's Missionary Activity)
* ''[[Apostolicam Actuositatem]]'' (Decree on the Apostolate of the Laity)
* ''[[Christus Dominus]]'' (Decree on the Pastoral Office of Bishops in the Church)
* ''[[Inter Mirifica]]'' (Decree on the Means of Social Communication)
* ''[[Optatam Totius]]'' (Decree on the Training of Priests)
* ''[[Orientalium Ecclesiarum]]'' (Decree on the Catholic Oriental Churches)
* ''[[Perfectae Caritatis]]'' (Decree on the Up-to-date Renewal of Religious Life)
* ''[[Presbyterorum Ordinis]]'' (Decree on the Life and Ministry of Priests)
* ''[[Unitatis Redintegratio]]'' (Decree on Ecumenism)
Three declarations:
* ''[[Dignitatis Humanae]]'' (Declaration on Religious Liberty)
* ''[[Gravissimum Educationis]]'' (Declaration on Christian Education)
* ''[[Nostra Aetate]]'' (Declaration on the Church's Relations with Non-Christian Religions)
}}
[[image: Second Vatican Council by Lothar Wolleh 005.jpg|thumb|Interior of St. Peter's]]
[[image: Second Vatican Council by Lothar Wolleh 007.jpg|thumb|Second Vatican Council]]
[[image: Second Vatican Council by Lothar Wolleh 003.jpg|thumb|The Fathers Second Vatican Council]]
[[image: Second Vatican Council by Lothar Wolleh 004.jpg|thumb|Dispersion of the Fathers Second Vatican Council]]
The '''Second Vatican Council''' ([[Latin language|Latin]]: '''Concilium Oecumenicum Vaticanum Secundum''' or informally known as '''Vatican II''') addressed relations between the [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholic Church]] and the modern world. It was the twenty-first [[Ecumenical Council]] of the Catholic Church and the second to be held at [[Saint Peter's Basilica]] in the [[Vatican City|Vatican]]. The council, through the [[Holy See]], formally opened under the [[pontificate]] of [[Pope John XXIII]] on 11 October 1962 and closed under [[Pope Paul VI]] on 8 December 1965.  

Of those who took part in the council's opening session, four have become [[pope|pontiffs]] to date: Cardinal Giovanni Battista Montini, who on succeeding Pope John XXIII took the name of [[Pope Paul VI|Paul VI]];  Bishop Albino Luciani, the future [[Pope John Paul I]]; Bishop Karol Wojtyła, who became [[Pope John Paul II]]; and Father Joseph Ratzinger, present as a theological consultant, who became [[Pope Benedict XVI]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NCEp563&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= |first= |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |editor=Faculty of Catholic University of America |encyclopedia=[[New Catholic Encyclopedia]] |title=Vatican Council II |edition=1 |year=1967 |month= |publisher=[[McGraw-Hill]] |volume=XIV |location=New York |isbn= |oclc=34184550 | pages=563 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Alberig 2005 69&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Alberigo | first = Giuseppe | coauthor=Sherry, Matthew| title = A Brief History of Vatican II | page=69 | publisher = Orbis Books | location = Maryknoll | year = 2006 | isbn = 1-57075-638-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Throughout the 1950s, theological and biblical studies of the Catholic Church had begun to sway away from the [[neo-scholasticism]] and [[biblical literalism]] that the reaction to [[Modernism (Roman Catholicism)|Catholic modernism]] had enforced since the [[First Vatican Council]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}} This shift could be seen in theologians such as [[Karl Rahner]], [[Society of Jesus|S.J.]], Michael Herbert, and [[John Courtney Murray|John Courtney Murray, SJ]] who looked to integrate modern human experience with church principles based on Jesus Christ, as well as others such as [[Yves Congar]], [[Pope Benedict XVI|Joseph Ratzinger]] and [[Henri de Lubac]] who looked to an accurate understanding of scripture and the early [[Church Fathers]] as a source of renewal (or ''[[Nouvelle Theologie|ressourcement]]'').

At the same time the world's bishops faced tremendous challenges driven by political, social, economic, and technological change. Some of these bishops sought new ways of addressing those challenges. The [[First Vatican Council]] had been held nearly a century before but had been cut short when the [[Italian Army]] entered the city of [[Rome]] at the end of [[Italian unification]]. As a result, only deliberations on the role of the Papacy and the congruent relationship of faith and reason were completed, with examination of pastoral issues concerning the direction of the Church left unaddressed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Back 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Bokenkotter | first = Thomas | title = A Concise History of the Catholic Church | publisher = Image | location = New York | year = 2005 | isbn = 0-385-51613-4 | page=337}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Hahnenberg | first = Edward | title = A Concise Guide to the Documents of Vatican II | publisher = Saint Anthony Messenger Press | location = City | year = 2007 | isbn = 0-86716-552-9 | page=44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Pope John XXIII]], however, gave notice of his intention to convene the Council on 25 January 1959, less than three months after his election in October 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;Back 3&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Alberigo | first = Giuseppe|coauthor=Sherry, Matthew| title = A Brief History of Vatican II | publisher = Orbis Books | location = Maryknoll | year = 2006 | isbn = 1-57075-638-4 | page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; This sudden announcement, which caught the Curia by surprise, caused little initial official comment from Church insiders. Reaction to the announcement was widespread and largely positive from both religious and secular leaders outside the Catholic Church,&lt;ref name=&quot;Back 6&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Alberigo | first = Giuseppe|coauthor=Sherry, Matthew| title = A Brief History of Vatican II | publisher = Orbis Books | location = Maryknoll | year = 2006 | isbn = 1-57075-638-4 | pages=4–7}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the council was formally summoned by the [[apostolic constitution]] ''[[Humanae Salutis]]'' on 25 December 1961.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://ncronline.org/NCR_Online/archives2/2002d/100402/100402d.htm | title = Vatican II: 40 years later | publisher = [[National Catholic Register]]}}{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Vatican 1961&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://asv.vatican.va/en/doc/1961.htm | title = 1961}}{{dead link|date=July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In various discussions before the Council actually convened, Pope John often said that it was time to open the windows of the Church to let in some fresh air.&lt;ref name=&quot;Back 4&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Sullivan | first = Maureen | title = 101 Questions and Answers on Vatican II | publisher = Paulist Press | location = New York | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-8091-4133-7 | page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; He invited other Christians outside of the Catholic Church to send observers to the Council. Acceptances came from both the [[Protestantism|Protestant]] denominations and [[Eastern Orthodoxy|Eastern Orthodox]] churches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Back 5&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Sullivan | first = Maureen | title = 101 Questions and Answers on Vatican II | publisher = Paulist Press | location = New York | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-8091-4133-7 | page=21 }} There has been speculation that the Vatican somehow assured the Russian Orthodox Church that Communism and the Soviet State were topics that would not be raised at the Council. However, in chapter IV, The External Climate (Albiergo, The History of Vatican II, Vol. 1, p. 404), J.O. Beozzo states that the real issue was the desire of the Russian Orthodox to be invited directly, instead of through the Ecumenical Patriarch in Turkey.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chronology==
===Preparation===
Preparations for the Council took more than two years, and included work from 10 specialised commissions, people for mass media and Christian Unity, and a Central Commission for overall coordination. These groups, composed mostly of members of the [[Roman Curia]], produced 987 proposed constituting sessions, making it the largest gathering in any council in church history. (This compares to Vatican I, where 737 attended, mostly from Europe.)&lt;ref name=&quot;NCE Prep 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Sullivan | first = Maureen | title = 101 Questions and Answers on Vatican II | publisher = Paulist Press | location = New York | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-8091-4133-7 |page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Attendance varied in later sessions from 2,100 to over 2,300. In addition, a varying number of ''periti'' ({{lang-la|&quot;experts&quot;}}) were available for theological consultation—a group that turned out to have a major influence as the council went forward. Seventeen Orthodox Churches and Protestant denominations sent observers.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCEp563&quot;/&gt; More than three dozen representatives of other Christian communities were present at the opening session, and the number grew to nearly 100 by the end of the 4th Council Sessions.

===First period: 1962===
====Opening====
Pope John XXIII opened the Council on 11 October 1962 in a public session and read the declaration [[Gaudet Mater Ecclesia]] before the Council Fathers.

13 October 1962 marked the initial working session of the Council. That day's agenda included the election for members of the ten conciliar commissions. Each would have sixteen elected and eight appointed members, and were expected to do most of the work of the Council.&lt;ref name=&quot;S1-1&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Bokenkotter | first = Thomas | title = A Concise History of the Catholic Church | publisher = Image | location = New York | year = 2005 | isbn = 0-385-51613-4 | page=413}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It had been expected that the members of the preparatory commissions, where the Curia was heavily represented, would be confirmed as the majorities on the conciliar commissions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alberigo 2005 24&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Alberigo | first = Giuseppe|coauthor=Sherry, Matthew| title = A Brief History of Vatican II | publisher = Orbis Books | location = Maryknoll | year = 2006 | isbn = 1-57075-638-4 | page=24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Sullivan 2002 27&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Sullivan | first = Maureen | title = 101 Questions and Answers on Vatican II | publisher = Paulist Press | location = New York | year = 2002 | isbn = 0-8091-4133-7 | page=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Senior French Cardinal [[Achille Liénart]] addressed the Council, saying that the bishops could not intelligently vote for strangers.  He asked that the vote be postponed to give all the bishops a chance to draw up their own lists.  German Cardinal [[Josef Frings]] seconded that proposal, and the vote was postponed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sullivan 2002 27&quot; /&gt; The very first meeting of the Council adjourned after only fifteen minutes.&lt;ref name=&quot;S1-3a&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Hahnenberg | first = Edward | title = A Concise Guide to the Documents of Vatican II | publisher = Saint Anthony Messenger Press | location = City | year = 2007 | isbn = 0-86716-552-9 | page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|What is needed at the present time is a new enthusiasm, a new joy and serenity of mind in the unreserved acceptance by all of the entire Christian faith, without forfeiting that accuracy and precision in its presentation which characterized the proceedings of the Council of Trent and the First Vatican Council. What is needed, and what everyone imbued with a truly Christian, Catholic and apostolic spirit craves today, is that this doctrine shall be more widely known, more deeply understood, and more penetrating in its effects on men’s moral lives. What is needed is that this certain and immutable doctrine, to which the faithful owe obedience, be studied afresh and reformulated in contemporary terms. For this deposit of faith, or truths which are contained in our time-honored teaching is one thing; the manner in which these truths are set forth (with their meaning preserved intact) is something else. -Blessed Pope John XXIII (Opening address to the Council)}}

====Commissions====
The bishops met to discuss the membership of the commissions, along with other issues, both in national and regional groups, as well as in gatherings that were more informal. The ''schemata'' from the preparatory sessions were thrown out, and new ones were created.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCEp563&quot;/&gt; When the council met on 16 October 1962, a new slate of commission members was presented and approved by the Council.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alberigo 2005 24&quot; /&gt; One important change was a significant increase in membership from Central and Northern Europe, instead of countries such as Spain or Italy.  More than 100 bishops from Africa, Asia, and Latin America were Dutch or Belgian and tended to associate with the bishops from those countries.  These groups were led by Cardinals [[Bernardus Johannes Alfrink]] of the [[Netherlands]] and [[Leo Jozef Suenens|Leo Suenens]] of [[Belgium]].&lt;ref name=&quot;S1-5&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Sullivan | first = Maureen | title = 101 Questions and Answers on Vatican II | publisher = Paulist Press | location = New York | year = 2002 | ISBN = 0-8091-4133-7 | page=28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Issues====
After adjournment on 8 December, work began on preparations for the sessions scheduled for 1963. These preparations, however, were halted upon the death of [[Pope John XXIII]] on 3 June 1963, since an ecumenical council is automatically interrupted and suspended upon the death of the Pope who convened it, until the next Pope orders the council to be continued or dissolved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P17.HTM |title=CIC can. 340 - Code of Canon Law|publisher=Vatican.va |date= |accessdate=2012-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pope Paul VI]] was elected on 21 June 1963 and immediately announced that the Council would continue.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCE S2&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= |first= |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |editor=Faculty of Catholic University of America |encyclopedia=[[New Catholic Encyclopedia]] |title=Vatican Council II |url= |edition= |date= |year=1967 |month= |publisher=McGraw-Hill |volume=XIV |location=New York |id= |isbn= |oclc=34184550 |doi= |pages=565–566 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second period: 1963===
[[File:Konzilseroeffnung 1.jpg|250px|thumb|right|The opening of the Second Session of Vatican II]]
In the months prior to the second period, Pope Paul VI worked to correct some of the problems of organization and procedure that had been discovered during the first period. This included inviting additional lay Catholic and non-Catholic observers, reducing the number of proposed schemata to seventeen (which were made more general, in keeping with the pastoral nature of the council) and later eliminating the requirement of secrecy surrounding general sessions.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCE S2&quot;/&gt;

Pope Paul's opening address on 29 September 1963 stressed the pastoral nature of the council, and set out four purposes for it:
* to more fully define the nature of the Church and the role of the bishop;
* to renew the Church;
* to restore unity among all Christians, including seeking pardon for Catholic contributions to separation;
* and to start a dialogue with the contemporary world.

During this period, the bishops approved the constitution on the liturgy (''[[Sacrosanctum Concilium]]'') and the decree on the media of social communication (''[[Inter Mirifica]]''). Work went forward with the schemata on the Church, bishops and dioceses, and ecumenism. On 8 November 1963, [[Josef Frings]] criticized the [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith|Holy Office]], and drew an articulate and impassioned defense by its Secretary, [[Alfredo Ottaviani]]. This exchange is often considered the most dramatic of the council. (Cardinal Frings's theological advisor was the young Joseph Ratzinger, now [[Pope Benedict XVI]], who would later, as Cardinal, head the same department of the Holy See.)  The second period ended on December 4.
[[image: Second Vatican Council by Lothar Wolleh 001.jpg|thumb|right|240px|Pope Paul VI]]

===Third period: 1964===
In the time between the second and third periods, the proposed schemata were further revised on the basis of comments from the council fathers. A number of topics were reduced to statements of fundamental propositions that could gain approval during the third period, with postconciliar commissions handling implementation of these measures. Eight religious and seven lay women observers were invited to the sessions of the third period, along with additional male lay observers.

During this period, which began on 14 September 1964, the Council Fathers worked through a large volume of proposals. Schemata on ecumenism (''[[Unitatis Redintegratio]]''), the official view on Protestant and Eastern Orthodox &quot;separated brethren&quot;, the Eastern Rite churches (''[[Orientalium Ecclesiarum]]''), and the Dogmatic Constitution of the Church (''[[Lumen Gentium]]'') were approved and promulgated by the Pope.

Schemata on the life and ministry of priests and the missionary activity of the Church were rejected and sent back to commissions for complete rewriting. Work continued on the remaining schemata, in particular those on the Church in the modern world and religious freedom. There was controversy over revisions of the decree on religious freedom and the failure to vote on it during the third period, but Pope Paul promised that this schema would be the first to be reviewed in the next period.

Pope Paul closed the third period on November 21 by announcing a change in the [[Eucharistic fast]] and formally reaffirming [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]] as &quot;[[Mother of the Church]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCE S3&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= |first= |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |editor=Faculty of Catholic University of America |encyclopedia=[[New Catholic Encyclopedia]] |title=Vatican Council II |url= |edition= |date= |year=1967 |month= |publisher=McGraw-Hill |volume=XIV |location=New York |id= |isbn= |oclc=34184550 |doi= |pages=566–567 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fourth period: 1965===
Eleven schemata remained unfinished at the end of the third period, and commissions worked to give them their final form. Schema 13, on the Church in the modern world, was revised by a commission that worked with the assistance of laymen.

Pope Paul VI opened the last period of the Council on 14 September 1965 with the establishment of the [[Synod of Bishops (Catholic)|Synod of Bishops]]. This more permanent structure was intended to preserve close cooperation of the bishops with the Pope after the council.

The first business of the fourth period was the consideration of the decree on religious freedom, ''[[Dignitatis Humanae]]'', one of the more controversial of the conciliar documents. The vote was 1,997 for to 224 against, a margin that widened even farther by the time the bishop's final signing of the decree.  The principal work of the rest of the period was work on three documents, all of which were approved by the council fathers.  The lengthened and revised pastoral constitution on the Church in the modern world, ''[[Gaudium et Spes]]'', was followed by decrees on missionary activity, ''[[Ad Gentes]]'' and the ministry and life of priests, ''[[Presbyterorum Ordinis]]''.

The council also gave final approval to other documents that had been considered in earlier sessions. This included decrees on the pastoral office of bishops (''[[Christus Dominus]]''), the life of persons in religious orders (expanded and modified from earlier sessions, finally titled ''[[Perfectae Caritatis|Perfectæ Caritatis]]''), education for the priesthood (''[[Optatam Totius]]''), Christian education (''[[Gravissimum Educationis]]''), and the role of the laity (''[[Apostolicam Actuositatem]]'').

One of the more controversial documents{{Citation needed|date=November 2011}} was ''[[Nostra Aetate]]'', which stated that the Jews of the time of Christ, taken indiscriminately, and all Jews today are no more responsible for the death of Christ than Christians.

{{quote|True, the Jewish authorities and those who followed their lead pressed for the death of Christ; still, what happened in His passion cannot be charged against all the Jews, without distinction, then alive, nor against the Jews of today. Although the Church is the new people of God, the Jews should not be presented as rejected or accursed by God, as if this followed from the Holy Scriptures. All should see to it, then, that in catechetical work or in the preaching of the word of God they do not teach anything that does not conform to the truth of the Gospel and the spirit of Christ.  Furthermore, in her rejection of every persecution against any man, the Church, mindful of the patrimony she shares with the Jews and moved not by political reasons but by the Gospel's spiritual love, decries hatred, persecutions, displays of anti-Semitism, directed against Jews at any time and by anyone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Pope Paul VI | first = | authorlink=Pope Paul VI | date=1965-10-28 | title=Declaration on the relation of the Church to non-christian religions - Nostra Aetate | location=Holy See | url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_decl_19651028_nostra-aetate_en.html | accessdate=2009-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{See also|Christian-Jewish reconciliation|Relations between Catholicism and Judaism}}

A major event of the final days of the council was the act of Pope Paul and Orthodox [[Patriarch Athenagoras]] of a [[Catholic-Orthodox Joint declaration of 1965|joint expression of regret]] for many of the past actions that had led up to the [[East-West Schism|Great Schism]] between the western and eastern churches.

&quot;''The old story of the [[Samaritan]] has been the model of the spirituality of the council''&quot; (Paul VI., address, Dec. 7): On 8 December, the Council was formally closed, with the bishops professing their obedience to the Council's decrees. To help carry forward the work of the Council, Pope Paul:
*had earlier formed a Papal Commission for the Media of Social Communication to assist bishops with the pastoral use of these media;
*declared a jubilee from 1 January to 26 May 1966 to urge all Catholics to study and accept the decisions of the council and apply them in spiritual renewal;
*changed in 1965 the title and procedures of the Holy Office, giving it the name of the Sacred [[Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith]], as well as the titles and competences of other departments of the Roman curia;
*made permanent the secretariates for the Promotion of Christian Unity, [[Pontifical Council for Interreligious Dialogue|for Non-Christian Religions]], and for Non-Believers.&lt;ref name=&quot;NCE S4&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last= |first= |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |editor=Faculty of Catholic University of America |encyclopedia=[[New Catholic Encyclopedia]] |title=Vatican Council II |url= |edition= |date= |year=1967 |month= |publisher=McGraw-Hill |volume=XIV |location=New York |id= |isbn= |oclc=34184550 |doi= |pages=567–568 |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Issues==
===Ecclesiology===
Perhaps the most famous and most influential product of the council is the Dogmatic Constitution on the Church, ''[[Lumen Gentium]]''.

In its first chapter, titled ''&quot;The Mystery of the Church,&quot;'' is the famous statement that &quot;the sole Church of Christ which in the Creed we profess to be one, holy, catholic and apostolic, which our Saviour, after His Resurrection, commissioned Peter to shepherd, and him and the other apostles to extend and direct with authority, which He erected for all ages as 'the pillar and mainstay of the truth.' This Church, constituted and organized as a society in the present world, [[&quot;Subsistit in&quot; in Lumen Gentium|subsists in]] the Catholic Church, which is governed by the successor of Peter and by the bishops in communion with him&quot; (Lumen Gentium, 8). The document immediately adds: &quot;Nevertheless, many elements of sanctification and of truth are found outside its visible confines.&quot;

===Liturgy===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[St. Peter Cathedral, Erie]] --&gt;
{{Main|Sacrosanctum Concilium}}
[[image: Second Vatican Council by Lothar Wolleh 006.jpg|thumb|Leaving St. Peter's Basilica]]
[[image: Second Vatican Council by Lothar Wolleh 008.jpg|thumb|Bishops Leaving St. Peter's]]
One of the first issues considered by the council, and the matter that had the most immediate effect on the lives of individual Catholics, was the revision of the liturgy. The central idea was that there ought to be greater lay participation in the liturgy.  In the mid-1960s, permissions were granted to celebrate most of the Mass in vernacular languages, including the [[Canon of the Mass|Canon]] from 1967 onwards.&lt;ref&gt;Historically speaking, &quot;Latin Mass&quot; could be applied also to the various forms of [[Pre-Tridentine Mass]] from about the year 370, when, according to the [http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-67437 Encyclopaedia Britannica Online], the Church in Rome changed from [[Greek language|Greek]] to Latin.&lt;/ref&gt;

Neither the Second Vatican Council nor the subsequent [[Mass of Paul VI|revision]] of the [[Roman Missal]] abolished Latin as the liturgical language of the Roman Rite: the official text of the Roman Missal, on which translations into vernacular languages are to be based, continues to be in Latin, and Latin can still be used in the celebration.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Except in the case of celebrations of the Mass that are scheduled by the ecclesiastical authorities to take place in the language of the people, Priests are always and everywhere permitted to celebrate Mass in Latin&quot; ([http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/ccdds/documents/rc_con_ccdds_doc_20040423_redemptionis-sacramentum_en.html ''Redemptionis sacramentum'', 112]).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scripture and divine revelation===
{{Main|Dei Verbum}}
The council sought to revive the central role of Scripture in the theological and devotional life of the Church, building upon the work of earlier popes inSaints, Doctordmportance of Sacred Scripture as attested by [[Providentissimus Deus]] by [[Pope Leo XIII]] and the writings of the ds, and Popes throughout Church history but also approved historically conditioned interpretation of Scripture as presented in Pi by the bishops. The Church was to continue to provide versions of the Bible in the &quot;[[vernacular|mother tongue]]s&quot; of the faithful, and both clergy and laity were to continue to make Bible study a central part of their lives. This affirme crafting a modern approach to Scriptural analysis and interpretation. A new approach to interpretation was approve the ius XII's 1943 encyclical [[Divino Afflante Spiritu]].

===Bishops===
The role of the bishops of the Church was brought into renewed prominence, especially when seen collectively, as a college that has succeeded to that of the [[twelve apostles|Apostles]] in teaching and governing the Church. This college was headed by the [[Pope|successor of St. Peter]].

==Legacy==
{{Main|Post Vatican II history of the Catholic Church|Spirit of Vatican II}}
&quot;By the spirit of Vatican II&quot; is meant to promote the teachings and intentions attributed to the Second Vatican Council in ways not limited to literal readings of its documents, but not in contradiction to the &quot;letter&quot; of the Council&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home.comcast.net/~icuweb/c02206.htm |title=James Hitchcock, The History of Vatican II, Lecture 6: The Effects of Council Part II |publisher=Home.comcast.net |date= |accessdate=2012-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Avery Dulles]], [http://www.americamagazine.org/content/article.cfm?article_id=2810 Vatican II: The Myth and the Reality]&lt;/ref&gt; (cf. [[Paul the Apostle|Saint Paul's]] phrase, &quot;the letter kills, but the Spirit gives life&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleverse|2|Corinthians|3:6|NIV}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The spirit of Vatican II is invoked for a great variety of ideas and attitudes. Bishop [[John Tong Hon]] of [[Hong Kong]] used it with regard merely to an openness to dialogue with others, saying: &quot;We are guided by the spirit of Vatican II: only dialogue and negotiation can solve conflicts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gheddo |first=Piero |url=http://www.asianews.it/index.php?l=en&amp;art=15126 |title=Gianni Criveller, Bishop John Tong of Hong Kong, &quot;man of dialogue,&quot; but with &quot;non-negotiable principles&quot; |publisher=Asianews.it |date= |accessdate=2012-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast, [[Michael Novak]] described it as a spirit that &quot;sometimes soared far beyond the actual, hard-won documents and decisions of Vatican II. ... It was as though the world (or at least the history of the Church) were now to be divided into only two periods, pre-Vatican II and post-Vatican II. Everything 'pre' was then pretty much dismissed, so far as its ''authority'' mattered. For the most extreme, to be a Catholic now meant to believe more or less anything one wished to believe, or at least in the sense in which one personally interpreted it. One could be a Catholic 'in spirit'. One could take ''Catholic'' to mean the 'culture' in which one was born, rather than to mean a creed making objective and rigorous demands. One could imagine Rome as a distant and irrelevant anachronism, embarrassment, even adversary. Rome as 'them'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aei.org/basicPages/20031124161414312 |title=Introduction to The Open Church (Millennium Edition) |date=2003-11-24 |accessdate=2012-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such views of the Second Vatican Council were condemned by the Church's hierarchy, and the works of theologians who were active in the Council or who closely adhered to the Council's aspect of reform (such as [[Hans Küng]]) have often been criticized by the Church for espousing a belief system that the hierarchy considers radical and misguided. As Dei Verbum reads, “Therefore, following in the footsteps of the Council of Trent and of the First Vatican Council, this present council wishes to set forth authentic doctrine on divine revelation and how it is handed on…”, Vatican II did not deny previous councils correctness.

To mark the fiftieth anniversary of the beginning of Vatican II, in October 2011, the Vatican's website and many other Catholic news organizations announced that the Pope Benedict XVI, had made the period from October 2012 to the end of November 2013 (the [[Solemnity of Christ the King]]) a &quot;Year Of Faith&quot; in a solemn declaration, and ordered all parishes and religious institutions to find some manner during that Year of celebrating and reaffirming the Creed (there are now two main Creeds- the shorter [[Apostle's Creed]] and the lengthier Niceno-Constantopolitan, or [[Nicene Creed]].  The Nicene creed is recited at each Mass, and both are listed and examined in the landmark 1994 [[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]; they serve as fundamental declarations that a catechumen or a baptized Catholic identifies with the Church).

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book | last = Kelly | first = Joseph F. | title = The Ecumenical Councils of the Catholic Church: a History | publisher = Liturgical Press | location = Collegeville | year = 2009 | isbn = 0-8146-5376-6 }}
* {{cite book | last = Orsy | first = Ladislas | title = Receiving the Council: Theological and Canonical Insights and  Debates | publisher = Liturgical Press | location = Collegeville | year = 2009 | isbn = 0-8146-5377-4 }}
* {{cite  book|last=O'Malley|first=John W.|title=What Happened at Vatican  II|publisher=Harvard University Press|year=2008|isbn=978-0-674-03169-2}}
* {{cite book|last=[[Ralf van Bühren|Bühren]]|first=[[Ralf van Bühren|Ralf van]] |title=Kunst und Kirche im 20. Jahrhundert. Die Rezeption des Zweiten Vatikanischen Konzils|publisher=Schöningh|location=Paderborn|isbn=978-3-506-76388-4|language=German|year=2008}}
* {{cite book|last=Bredeck|first=Michael|title=Das Zweite Vatikanum als Konzil des Aggiornamento : zur hermeneutischen Grundlegung einer theologischen Konzilsinterpretation|publisher=Schöningh|location=Paderborn |year=2007|isbn=978-3-506-76317-4 |language=German}}
* {{cite book | last = Linden | first = Ian | title = Global Catholicism: diversity and change since Vatican II| publisher = Hurst and Co | location = 41 Great Russell St, London | year = 2009 | isbn = 978-1-85065-957-0|page=337 }}
* {{cite book|last=Sinke Guimarães|first=Atila|title=In the Murky Waters of Vatican II|publisher=MAETA|location=Metairie|isbn=1-889168-06-8|year=1997}}
* {{cite book|last=[[Romano Amerio|Amerio]]|first=[[Romano Amerio|Romano]]|title=Iota Unum|publisher=Sarto House|location=Kansas City|isbn=0-9639032-1-7|year=1996}}
* {{cite book|last=Gherardini|first=Brunero|title=Sull'indole pastorale del Vaticano II: una valutazione. In: Concilio Vaticano II, un concilio pastorale. Analisi storico-filosofico-teologica, ed. Serafino Lanzetta|publisher=Casa Mariana Editrice |location=Frigento, Italy |isbn=978-88-905611-2-2|year=2011}}
* {{cite book | last = Likoudis | first = James | title = The Pope, the Council, and the Mass | publisher = Emmaus Road Publishing | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-1-931018-34-0 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Catholicism}}
{{Commonscat|Second Vatican Council}}
;Vatican texts
*[http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/index.htm Vatican II Texts from the Vatican]
*[http://www.therealpresence.org/eucharst/vat/clrp_vii.htm Overview of the Decrees of the Council]
*[http://www.ewtn.com/expert/answers/vatican_ii_docs.htm Vatican II Texts from the Eternal Word Television Network]
*[http://www.christusrex.org/www1/CDHN/v1.html Vatican II Texts from Christus Rex]
*[http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/01_10_1962-1965-_Concilium_Vaticanum_II.html Council Vatican II's Multilingual Opera Omnia]
*[http://www.conciliaria.com/ Conciliaria: Fifty Years Ago Today at the Second Vatican Council] (Reporting and original source documents from the Council)
*Official documents of the Second Vatican Council - Constitutions
** {{cite journal|last=Pope Paul VI|authorlink=Pope Paul VI|date=1965-12-07|title=Pastoral Constitution On The Church In The Modern World - Gaudium et Spes|location=Holy See|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_cons_19651207_gaudium-et-spes_en.html|accessdate=2009-01-01}}
** {{cite journal|last=Pope Paul VI|authorlink=Pope Paul VI|date=1965-12-07|title=Constitutio Pastoralis De Ecclesia In Mundo Huius Temporis - Gaudium Et Spes|location=Holy See|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19651207_gaudium-et-spes_lt.html|accessdate=2009-01-01|language=Latin}}
** {{cite journal|last=Pope Paul VI|authorlink=Pope Paul VI|date=1965-11-18|title=Dogmatic Constitution On Divine Revelation - Dei Verbum|location=Holy See|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19651118_dei-verbum_en.html|accessdate=2009-01-01}}
** {{cite journal|last=Pope Paul VI|authorlink=Pope Paul VI|date=1965-11-18|title=Constitutio Dogmatica De Divina Revelatione - Dei Verbum|location=Holy See|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19651118_dei-verbum_lt.html|accessdate=2009-01-01|language=Latin}}
** {{cite journal|last=Pope Paul VI|authorlink=Pope Paul VI|date=1964-11-21|title=Dogmatic Constitution On The Church - Lumen Gentium|location=Holy See|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19641121_lumen-gentium_en.html |accessdate=2009-01-01}}
** {{cite journal|last=Pope Paul VI|authorlink=Pope Paul VI|date=1964-11-21|title=Constitutio Dogmatica De Ecclesia - Lumen Gentium|location=Holy See|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19641121_lumen-gentium_lt.html |accessdate=2009-01-01|language=Latin}}
** {{cite journal|last=Pope Paul VI|authorlink=Pope Paul VI|date=1964-11-21|title=Constitution on the sacred liturgy - Sacrosanctum Concilium |location=Holy See|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19631204_sacrosanctum-concilium_en.html|accessdate=2009-01-01}}
** {{cite journal|last=Pope Paul VI|authorlink=Pope Paul VI|date=1964-11-21|title=Constitutio De Sacra Liturgia - Sacrosanctum Concilium |location=Holy See|url=http://www.vatican.va/archive/hist_councils/ii_vatican_council/documents/vat-ii_const_19631204_sacrosanctum-concilium_lt.html|accessdate=2009-01-01|language=Latin}}

;Commentary
*[http://www.vatican2voice.org/2need/need.htm Why was Vatican II needed? Why we need it today.]
*[http://www.christendom-awake.org/pages/ianker/vatican2.html What did the Second Vatican Council do for us?]
*[http://eutopia.cua.edu/printarticle.cfm?ID=81 The Spirit of Vatican II, Jubilee Optimism, and the Oath against Modernism]
*[http://www.franciscan-archive.org/apologetica/rupture.html The Neo-Modernist Rupture in the Council and in the New Rites, Part I]
*[http://www.franciscan-archive.org/apologetica/incommut.html Part II: The Incommutability of Ecclesiastical Tradition]
*[http://www.christendom-awake.org/pages/jsaward/lightofnations1.htm Making the True Vatican II Our Own]
*[http://www.catholicapologetics.info/modernproblems/vatican2/vatican.htm What are Roman Catholics to think of Vatican II? On the doctrinal authority of the pastoral council. By Fr. Raymond Taouk.]
*[http://www.centreleonardboyle.com/Tradition-Magisterium.html Church-Tradition-Magisterium, by Brunero Gherardini. Vatican II in the light of Tradition and Magisterium of the Catholic Church.]
*[http://www.centreleonardboyle.com/PastoralCVII.html On the Pastoral Nature of Vatican II: An Evaluation, by Brunero Gherardini]. English translation of 'Sull'indole pastorale del Vaticano II' (Frigento, Italy, 2011).
*[http://www.centreleonardboyle.com/Supplica.html Petition to the Holy Father Benedict XVI for a review of Vatican II] by Brunero Gherardini. Advocates a qualified study of Vatican II in view of a possible reassessment.
*[http://www.centreleonardboyle.com/Neededdiscussion.html The Ecumenical Vatican Council II. A Much Needed Discussion] by Brunero Gherardini. ISBN 9788890177064 The book was written &quot;to stop the conventional hand-clapping and any preconceived interpretation of Vatican II and to open a far-ranging debate on its historical, theological, and dogmatic significance&quot; (Brunero Gherardini, 'Il discorso mancato' (Lindau 2011) p. 48).   
{{Catholicism}}
{{History of the Roman Catholic Church|state=collapsed}}
{{Ecumenical councils}}
[[Category:1960s]]
[[Category:20th century in Italy]]
[[Category:Ecumenical councils|Vatican II]]
[[Category:Pope John XXIII]]
[[Category:Pope Paul VI]]
[[Category:Second Vatican Council]]

[[ar:المجمع الفاتيكاني الثاني]]
[[ast:Conceyu Vaticanu II]]
[[bg:Втори ватикански събор]]
[[ca:Concili del Vaticà II]]
[[ceb:Ikaduhang Konsilyong Batikano]]
[[cs:Druhý vatikánský koncil]]
[[da:Det andet Vatikankoncil]]
[[de:Zweites Vatikanisches Konzil]]
[[et:II Vatikani kirikukogu]]
[[es:Concilio Vaticano II]]
[[eo:Dua Vatikana Koncilio]]
[[eu:Vatikanoko II. kontzilioa]]
[[fr:IIe concile œcuménique du Vatican]]
[[gl:Concilio Vaticano Segundo]]
[[ko:제2차 바티칸 공의회]]
[[hr:Drugi vatikanski sabor]]
[[id:Konsili Vatikan II]]
[[it:Concilio Vaticano II]]
[[he:ועידת הוותיקן השנייה]]
[[jv:Konsili Vatikan II]]
[[sw:Mtaguso wa pili wa Vatikani]]
[[la:Concilium Vaticanum Secundum]]
[[lt:II Vatikano susirinkimas]]
[[hu:Második vatikáni zsinat]]
[[ml:രണ്ടാം വത്തിക്കാൻ സൂനഹദോസ്]]
[[nl:Tweede Vaticaans Concilie]]
[[ja:第2バチカン公会議]]
[[no:Andre Vatikankonsil]]
[[pl:Sobór watykański II]]
[[pt:Concílio Vaticano II]]
[[ro:Conciliul Vatican II]]
[[ru:Второй Ватиканский собор]]
[[sq:Këshilli i dytë Vatikanor]]
[[scn:Cuncìliu Vaticanu Secunnu]]
[[simple:Second Vatican Council]]
[[sk:Druhý vatikánsky koncil]]
[[sl:Drugi vatikanski koncil]]
[[sr:Drugi vatikanski sabor]]
[[sh:Drugi vatikanski koncil]]
[[fi:Vatikaanin toinen kirkolliskokous]]
[[sv:Andra Vatikankonciliet]]
[[tl:Ikalawang Konsilyo Vaticano]]
[[ta:இரண்டாம் வத்திக்கான் பொதுச்சங்கம்]]
[[tr:İkinci Vatikan Konsili]]
[[uk:Другий Ватиканський собор]]
[[vi:Công đồng Vaticanô II]]
[[war:Ikaduha nga Konsilyo Vaticano]]
[[zh:第二次梵蒂岡大公會議]]</text>
      <sha1>ff43orn8ebz7kushhj4i8mhpwbrr53r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
