<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Second Coming</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28554</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521912272</id>
      <parentid>520956110</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T00:11:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FrescoBot</username>
        <id>9021902</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/Links|link syntax/spacing]] and minor changes</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42431">{{Other uses}}
{{Eschatology}}
[[File:Second Coming of Christ window.jpg|thumb|200px|The ''Second Coming of Christ'' stained glass window at [[St. Matthew's German Evangelical Lutheran Church]] in Charleston, South Carolina.]]

In [[Christianity]] and [[Islam]], the '''Second Coming of Christ''', the '''second advent''', sometimes called the '''''[[parousia]]''''', is the anticipated return of [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]] to Earth. The Second Coming belief is based on prophecies found in the [[canonical gospels]] and in most [[Christian eschatology|Christian]] and [[Islamic eschatology|Islamic eschatologies]]. Christians generally believe the anticipated event is predicted in [[Jesus and Messianic prophecy|biblical messianic prophecies]]. Views about the nature of Jesus' Second Coming vary among [[Christian denominations]] and sometimes among individual Christians.

Most [[English versions of the Nicene Creed in current use]] include the following beliefs about Jesus: &quot;...he [[Ascension of Christ|ascended into heaven]] and is [[Session of Christ|seated]] at the [[Right Hand of God|right hand]] of the [[God the Father|Father]]. He will come again in glory to [[Last judgment|judge the living and the dead]], and [[Kingdom of God|his kingdom]] will have no end. ... We look for the [[resurrection of the dead]], and the life of the [[world to come]]. [[Amen]].&quot;

== Terminology ==
[[Image:Icon second coming.jpg|thumb|left|200px||Greek icon of Second Coming, c.1700]]
{{Jesus|state=collapsed}}
Several different terms are used to refer to the second coming of Christ.

===Epiphany===
In the New Testament the Greek word ἐπιφάνεια (''epiphaneia'', appearing) is used five times to refer to the return of Christ.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blueletterbible.org/lang/lexicon/lexicon.cfm?Strongs=G2015&amp;t=KJV NT usage]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Or|reason=I don't see where it says it means the return of christ, although the ref is odd, maybe i'm misreading?|date=March 2012}}

===Parousia===
{{main|Parousia}}
The [[Novum Testamentum Graece|Greek New Testament]] uses the Greek term ''parousia'' (παρουσία, meaning &quot;arrival&quot;, &quot;coming&quot;, or &quot;presence&quot;) twenty-four times, seventeen of them concerning Christ.&lt;ref name=G3952&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blueletterbible.org/cgi-bin/strongs.pl?strongs=3952 |title=Strong's G3952 |publisher=Blueletterbible.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The word is also used six times referring to individuals: Stephanas, Fortunatus and Achaicus {{bibleref2c|1Co|16:17|esv|1Co.16:17}}, [[Titus]]{{bibleref2c|2Co.|7:6-72}} and of Paul himself {{bibleref2c|2Co.|10:10}} {{bibleref2c|Phil|1:26}} {{bibleref2c-nb|Phil|2:12}} and one time referring to the &quot;coming of the [[Man of Lawlessness|lawless one]]&quot;.{{bibleref2c|2Thes|2:9}}

The [[etymology]] of Greek word ''parousia'' is related to ''para'' &quot;beside&quot; ''[[ousia]]'' &quot;presence&quot;. In English &quot;parousia&quot; always has a special, Christian, meaning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/parousia |title=Merriam Webster.com |publisher=Merriam Webster.com |date=2007-04-25 |accessdate=2009-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Definitions ===
{{Gospel Jesus|state=collapsed}}
In [[Joseph Henry Thayer|Thayer's]] Lexicon, the Greek word ''parousia'' is defined as [[Strong's Concordance|Strong's]] ''G3952'':
{{quote|
...In the N. T. [New Testament] esp. [especially] of ''the advent'', i.e., the future, visible, ''return'' from heaven of Jesus, the [[Messiah]], to raise the dead, hold the last judgment, and set up formally and gloriously the kingdom of God.&lt;ref name=G3952/&gt;}}

And in the [[Bauer lexicon|Bauer-Danker Lexicon]]:
{{quote|
...of Christ, and nearly always of his Messianic Advent in glory to judge the world at the end of this age.}}

And in the [[Catholic Encyclopedia]] article on [[General Judgment]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08552a.htm |title=CATHOLIC ENCYCLOPEDIA: General Judgment (Last Judgment) |publisher=Newadvent.org |date=1910-10-01 |accessdate=2009-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- NOTE: this is a direct quote from the source, please resist the urge to &quot;make improvements&quot; --&gt;
{{quote|In the New Testament the second Parousia, or coming of Christ as Judge of the world, is an oft-repeated doctrine. The Saviour Himself not only foretells the event but graphically portrays its circumstances ({{bibleref2|Matthew|24:27}} sqq. &lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[Olivet discourse]]&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt;; {{bibleref2-nb||Matthew|25:31}} sqq. &lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[The Sheep and the Goats|Judgment of the Nations]]&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt;). The Apostles give a most prominent place to this doctrine in their preaching ({{bibleref2|Acts|10:42}},{{bibleref2-nb||Acts|17:31}}) and writings ({{bibleref2|Romans|2:5-16}}; {{bibleref2-nb|Romans|14:10}}; {{bibleref2|1Cor|4:5||1 Cor. 4:5}}; {{bibleref2|2Cor|5:10||2 Cor. 5:10}}; {{bibleref2|2Tim|4:1||2 Tim. 4:1}}; {{bibleref2|2Thess|1:5||2 Thess 1:5}}; {{bibleref2|James|5:7}}). Besides the name Parusia (parousia), or Advent ({{bibleref2|1Cor|15:23||1 Cor. 15:23}}, {{bibleref2|2Thes|2:1-9||2 Thes. 2:1-9}}), the second coming is also called Epiphany, ''epiphaneia'', or Appearance ({{bibleref2|2Thes|2:8||2 Thes. 2:8}}; {{bibleref2|1Tim|6:14||1 Tim. 6:14}}; {{bibleref2|2Tim|4:1||2 Tim. 4:1}}; {{bibleref2|Titus|2:13}}) and Apocalypse (apokalypsis), or Revelation ({{bibleref2|2Thess|2:7||2 Thess. 2:7}} {{bibleref2|1Peter|4:13||1 Pet. 4:13}}). The time of the second coming is spoken of as &quot;that Day&quot; ({{bibleref2|2Tim|4:8||2 Tim. 4:8}}) &quot;the day of the Lord&quot; ({{bibleref2|1Thess|5:2||1 Thess. 5:2}}), &quot;the day of Christ&quot; ({{bibleref2|Phil|1:6}}), &quot;the day of the [[Son of Man]]&quot; ({{bibleref2|Luke|17:30}}), and &quot;the last day&quot; ({{bibleref2|John|6:39-40}}).}}

Adolf Deissmann (1908)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Light from the Ancient East:The New Testament Illustrated by Recently Discovered Texts of the Graeco-Roman World |year=1908 |author=Adolf Deissmann}}&lt;/ref&gt; showed that the Greek word &quot;parousia&quot; was used as early as the 3rd century BC to describe the visit of a king or dignitary to a city arranged in order the show his magnificence to the people. The Roman Advent Coins struck by the cities of Corinth and Patras for Nero's visit reveals the correspondence between the Greek &quot;parousia&quot; and the Latin &quot;Adventus&quot; and their relationship to the Greek word &quot;epiphany&quot; that means &quot;appearing&quot;.

==Signs of Christ's return==
{{See also|Maranatha}}
The [[Book of Acts]] states:
{{quote|
Now when He had spoken these things, while they watched, He was taken up, and a cloud received Him out of their sight. And while they looked steadfastly toward heaven as He went up, behold, two men stood by them in white apparel, who also said, &quot;Men of Galilee, why do you stand gazing up into heaven? This same Jesus, who was taken up from you into heaven, will so come in like manner as you saw Him go into heaven.&quot; |Acts 1:9-11}}

Other signs:
# The coming of Christ will be instantaneous and worldwide. &quot;For as the lightning comes from the east and flashes to the west, so also will the coming of the Son of Man be.&quot; —Matthew 24:27
# The coming of Christ will be visible to all. &quot;Then the sign of the Son of Man will appear in heaven, and then all the tribes of the earth will mourn, and they will see the Son of Man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory.&quot; —Matthew 24:30
# The coming of Christ will be audible. &quot;And He will send His angels with a great sound of a trumpet, and they will gather together His elect from the four winds, from one end of heaven to the other.&quot; —Matthew 24:31
# The resurrection of the righteous will occur. &quot;For the Lord Himself will descend from heaven with a shout, with the voice of the archangel, and with the trumpet of God. And the dead in Christ will rise first.&quot; —1 Thessalonians 4:16
# In one single event, the saved who are alive at Christ's coming will be caught up together with the resurrected to meet the Lord in the air. &quot;Then we who are alive and remain shall be caught up together with them in the clouds to meet the Lord in the air. And thus we shall always be with the Lord.&quot; —1 Thessalonians 4:17

==Christian views==
{{Christian Eschatology|state=collapsed}}
{{Main|Christian eschatological views}}

===1st century===
According to historian [[Charles Freeman (historian)|Charles Freeman]], [[early Christians]] expected Jesus to return within a generation of his death. The non-occurrence of the second coming surprised the early Christian communities, but they quickly began to understand Christ's warning not to speculate &quot;the day or the hour.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, Charles. ''The Closing of the Western Mind: The Rise of Faith and Fall of Reason'', p. 133. Vintage. 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|
Children, it is the last hour; and just as you heard that [[Antichrist]] is coming, even now many antichrists have appeared; from this we know that it is the last hour.|{{Bibleref2|1John|2:18||1 John 2:18}}}}

===Catholic and Orthodox===
{{See also|Katechon}}

Most [[English versions of the Nicene Creed in current use]] include the following beliefs about Jesus: &quot;...he [[Ascension of Christ|ascended into heaven]] and is [[Session of Christ|seated]] at the [[Right Hand of God|right hand]] of the [[God the Father|Father]]. He will come again in glory to [[Last judgment|judge the living and the dead]], and [[Kingdom of God|his kingdom]] will have no end. ... We look for the [[resurrection of the dead]], and the life of the [[world to come]]. [[Amen]].&quot;

It is the traditional view of [[Catholics]] and [[Orthodox Christians]], preserved from the early Church, that the second coming will be a sudden and unmistakable incident, like &quot;a flash of lightning&quot;.{{Bibleref2c|Mt|24:27}} They hold the general view that Jesus will not spend any time on the earth in ministry or preaching.&lt;ref name=&quot;orthodoxphotos%252Ecom&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.orthodoxphotos.com/readings/sign/coming.shtml |title=Jesus is Coming Soon |publisher=Orthodoxphotos.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.allexperts.com/q/Catholics-955/Catholic-views-End-Times.htm |title=Catholics: Catholic views on End Times?, end time prophecy, end time prophecies |publisher=En.allexperts.com |date=2006-10-05 |accessdate=2009-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also agree that the ministry of the [[Antichrist]] will take place right before the Second Coming.&lt;ref name=&quot;orthodoxphotos%252Ecom&quot; /&gt;

Respected Orthodox layman Alexander Kalomiros explains the original Church's position regarding the Second Coming in [http://www.orthodoxpress.org/parish/river_of_fire.htm River of Fire] and [http://www.roacusa.org/Catechism/AGAINST%20FALSE%20UNION.pdf Against False Union], stating that those who contend that Christ will reign on earth for a thousand years &quot;do not wait for Christ, but for the Antichrist.&quot; The idea of Jesus returning to this earth as a kingly is a heretical concept to the Church, equated to &quot;the expectations of the Jews who wanted the Messiah to be an earthly King.&quot; The Church instead teaches that which it has taught since the beginning—Christ will not return to earth, rather the Kingdom of Heaven, the New Jerusalem, will be established through the [[General Resurrection]].

===Preterism===
{{Main|Preterism}}
The position associating the Second Coming with [[Christianity in the 1st century|1st century events]] such as the [[Siege of Jerusalem (70)|destruction of Jerusalem and of the Jewish Temple in AD 70]] is known as [[Preterism]].&lt;ref&gt;1) Future Survival, Chuck Smith, The Word for Today, Costa Mesa, CA 1978, page 17

2) The Life of Jesus Critically Examined, Dr. David Friedrich Strauss, Sigler Press, Ramsey, NJ 1994, page 587

3) Jesus and The Last Days, George Murray, Hendrickson Pub., Peabody, Mass. 1993, pages 443-444

4) The Quest of the Historical Jesus, Dr. Albert Schweitzer, Macmillian, NY, 1968, page 240

5) Last Days Madness, Gary DeMar, American Vision Inc., Atlanta, GA 1994, page 114

6) The Parousia, Stuart Russell, T. Fisher Unwin Pub., London, 1887, page 84

7) The Decline &amp; Fall of the Roman Empire, Edward Gibbon, Penguin Books, NY 1985, page 276

8) Apocalypse of The Gospels, Milton Terry, (1819), chapter 18 reprinted and its pages renumbered in 1992 by John Bray, PO Box 90129, Lakeland, FL 33804, pages 34 &amp; 38
&lt;/ref&gt;

Some preterists see this &quot;coming of the Son of Man in glory&quot; primarily fulfilled in Jesus' death on the cross. They believe the apocalyptic signs are already fulfilled including &quot;[[Crucifixion eclipse|the sun will be dark]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;compare {{bibleref2|Mark|13:24}} to {{bibleref2|Mark|15:33}}&lt;/ref&gt; the &quot;powers ... will be shaken,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;compare {{bibleref2|Mark|13:25}} to {{bibleref2|Mark|14:63}} and {{bibleref2|Mark|15:5}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;then they will see&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;compare {{bibleref2|Mark|13:26}} to {{bibleref2|Mark|15:31}} and {{bibleref2-nb|Mark|15:39}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Yet some critics note many are missing such as &quot;But the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night, in which the heavens will pass away with a great noise, and the elements will melt with fervent heat; both the earth and the works that are in it will be burned up.&quot; (2 Peter 3:10)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.whitehorsemedia.com/articles/?d=27 Preterism Part 1]&lt;/ref&gt; And &quot;Then the sign of the Son of Man will appear in heaven, and then all the tribes of the earth will mourn, and they will see the Son of Man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory.&quot; (Matthew 24:30)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.whitehorsemedia.com/articles/?d=61 Preterism's Proof Texts Analyzed]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some, such as [[Jerome]], interpret the phrase &quot;this generation&quot; to mean lifetime of the Jewish race; however, if Jesus meant &quot;race&quot; he would have used ''genos'' (race) not ''genea'' (generation).&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.ca/books?id=tAO3ZU78I-0C&amp;pg=PA24 Is Jesus Coming Soon? By Gary DeMar, p. 24]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;1) Matthew, Douglas Hare, John Knox Press, Louisville, Kentucky, 1993, p. 281

2) The Gospel According to Saint Matthew, Alan Hugh M'Neile, Macmillan &amp; Co., London 1949, p. 354-355

3) The Broadman Bible Commentary, Vol. 8, Clifton Allen, ed., Broadman Press, Nashville, TN 1969, p. 221

4) Critical and Exegetical Hand-Book To The Gospel of Matthew, Heinrich Meyer (1883), Alpha Pub., Winona Lake, IN 1980, p. 426

5) The Gospel According to Matthew, R.T. France, Eerdmans, Grand Rapids, MI, 1985, p. 346

6) A Commentary on The Gospel According to St. Matthew, Floyd Filson, Adam &amp; Charles Black Pub., London,  1960, p. 257

7) Hard Sayings of the Bible, W. Kaiser, P. Davids, F.F. Bruce, M. Brauch, InterVarsity Press, Downers Grove, Ill, 1996, pp. 445-448

8) Bible Commentary, Vol. 1, Charles Scribner's Sons, NY 1901, p. 144

9) The Imperial Bible Dictionary, Vol. II, Rev. [[Patrick Fairbairn]], Blackie &amp; Son, London, 1885, p. 352

10) The Great Tribulation, David Chilton, Dominion Press, Ft. Worth, TX 1987, p. 3

11) The Quest of the Historical Jesus, Dr. Albert Schweitzer, Macmillian, NY, 1968, p. 22

12) Apocalypse of The Gospels, Milton Terry (1819), chapter 18 reprinted and its pages renumbered in 1992 by John Bray, PO Box 90129, Lakeland, FL 33804, p. 34

13) The Parousia, J. Stuart Russell, T. Fisher Unwin Pub., London, 1887, p. 85
&lt;/ref&gt; However, most scholars don't think Jesus spoke Greek, but instead that he [[Aramaic of Jesus|spoke Aramaic]].

===Mainline Protestant===
[[File:The Last Judgement. Jean Cousin..jpg|thumb|right|300px|''The [[Last Judgment]]'', by [[Jean Cousin the Younger]] (c. late 16th century)]]
{{See also|Mainline Protestant}}

The many denominations of Protestantism have differing views on the exact details of Christ's second coming. Only a handful of Christian organizations claim complete and authoritative interpretation of the typically symbolic and prophetic biblical sources. A common thread is the belief that Jesus will return to judge the world and to establish the kingdom of God (fulfilling the rest of Messianic prophecy).

A short reference to the second coming is contained in the [[Nicene Creed]], a prominent Christian statement of faith: &quot;He [Jesus] shall come again in glory to judge the living and the dead; and His kingdom shall have no end.&quot; An analogous statement is also in the biblical Pauline Creed, in {{bibleref2|1Cor|15:23||1 Corinthians 15:23}}.

Some [[Lutheran]], [[Anglican Communion|Anglican]] and [[United Methodist]] [[liturgy|liturgies]] proclaim the [[Memorial Acclamation|Mystery of Faith]] to be: &quot;Christ has died, Christ is risen, Christ will come again.&quot;

[[Adam Clarke]] writing in 1825, gave a time line ending in 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot;sacred-texts&quot;&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/bib/cmt/clarke/dan007.htm sacred-texts.com: Daniel 7 verse 25 in Context] &lt;/ref&gt;

Generally, mainline Protestant Christianity does not offer predictions on the date of the second coming, though some may form their own ideas of how and where it will happen.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

===Seventh-day Adventists===
{{main|Seventh-day Adventist eschatology}}
Fundamental Belief # 25 of the Seventh-day Adventist Church states
{{Quote|
The second coming of Christ is the blessed hope of the church, the grand climax of the gospel. The Saviour's coming will be literal, personal, visible, and worldwide. When He returns, the righteous dead will be resurrected, and together with the righteous living will be glorified and taken to heaven, but the unrighteous will die. The almost complete fulfillment of most lines of prophecy, together with the present condition of the world, indicates that Christ's coming is imminent. The time of that event has not been revealed, and we are therefore exhorted to be ready at all times. (Titus 2:13; Heb. 9:28; John 14:1-3; Acts 1:9-11; Matt. 24:14; Rev. 1:7; Matt. 24:43, 44; 1 Thess. 4:13-18; 1 Cor. 15:51-54; 2 Thess. 1:7-10; 2:8; Rev. 14:14-20; 19:11-21; Matt. 24; Mark 13; Luke 21; 2 Tim. 3:1-5; 1 Thess. 5:1-6.)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adventist.org/beliefs/fundamental/index.html Seventh-day Adventists Fundamental Beliefs]&lt;/ref&gt;|}}

===Jehovah's Witnesses===
Jehovah's Witnesses rarely use the term &quot;second coming&quot;, preferring the term &quot;presence&quot; as a translation of ''parousia''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Appendix 5B Christ's Presence (Parousia)&quot;, ''New World Translation - Large Reference Edition'', ©Watch Tower 1984 (orig 1950)&lt;/ref&gt; They believe that Jesus' comparison of ''&quot;the presence of the Son of man&quot;'' with ''&quot;the days of Noah&quot;'' at [http://www.watchtower.org/e/bible/mt/chapter_024.htm?bk=mt;chp=24;vs=37-39;citation#bk37 Matthew 24:37-39] and [http://www.watchtower.org/e/bible/lu/chapter_017.htm?bk=lu;chp=17;vs=26-30;citation#bk26 Luke 17:26-30] suggests a duration rather than a moment of arrival.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Presence&quot;, ''Insight on the Scriptures - Volume 2'', ©1988 Watch Tower, page 677&lt;/ref&gt;

Jehovah's Witnesses believe that biblical chronology points to 1914&lt;ref&gt;&quot;1900 onward—Skirts Splattered With Blood&quot;, ''Awake!'', November 8, 1989, ©Watch Tower, page 22&lt;/ref&gt; as the start of Christ's &quot;presence&quot;, which continues until Armageddon. Other biblical expressions they correlate with this period include &quot;the time of the end&quot; (Dan 12:4), &quot;the conclusion of the system of things&quot; (Matt 13:40,49; 24:3) and &quot;the last days&quot; (2 Tim 3:1; 2 Peter 3:3)&lt;!-- Note that preceding Scriptural citations are needed since these terms are far from universal across various Bible translations. --&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Keep Jehovah's Day Close in Mind&quot;, ''The Watchtower'', September 1, 1997, page 21&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;‘No Peace for the Wicked Ones’&quot;, ''The Watchtower'', July 1, 1987, page 13&lt;/ref&gt; Witnesses believe Christ's [[millennialism|millennial reign]] begins after Armageddon.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;There Is a Future for the Dead&quot;, ''The Watchtower'', April 1, 1968, page 200&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints===
{{see|Second Coming (LDS Church)}}
Latter-day Saints believe that Christ shall return as its written in the Bible. Jeffrey R. Holland, one of the Twelve Apostles wrote &quot;I testify that Jesus Christ is the literal, living Son of our literal, living God. This Jesus is our Savior and Redeemer who, under the guidance of the Father, was the Creator of heaven and earth and all things that in them are. I bear witness that He was born of a virgin mother, that in His lifetime He performed mighty miracles observed by legions of His disciples and by His enemies as well. I testify that He had power over death because He was divine but that He willingly subjected Himself to death for our sake because for a period of time He was also mortal. I declare that in His willing submission to death He took upon Himself the sins of the world, paying an infinite price for every sorrow and sickness, every heartache and unhappiness from Adam to the end of the world. In doing so He conquered both the grave physically and hell spiritually and set the human family free. I bear witness that He was literally resurrected from the tomb and, after ascending to His Father, to complete the process of that Resurrection, He appeared, repeatedly, to hundreds of disciples in the Old World and in the New. I know He is the Holy One of Israel, the Messiah who will one day come again in final glory, to reign on earth as Lord of lords and King of kings.&quot; [http://www.lds.org/ldsorg/v/index.jsp?vgnextoid=2354fccf2b7db010VgnVCM1000004d82620aRCRD&amp;locale=0&amp;sourceId=d2552bce258f5110VgnVCM100000176f620a____&amp;hideNav=1 Full text]

Notably Latter-day Saints have particularly distinct and specific interpretations as to various signs presented in the [[Book of Revelation]].

=== Esoteric Christian teachings ===
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Last Judgment]] and [[Rosicrucian Fellowship]] --&gt;

:''See also: [[Last Judgment#Esoteric Christian tradition|Last Judgment (Esoteric Christian tradition)]]''

In [[Rosicrucian]] [[esoteric Christian]] teaching, there is a clear distinction between the cosmic Christ, or Christ without, and the Christ within.&lt;ref&gt;[[The Rosicrucian Fellowship]], ''[http://www.rosicrucian.com/zineen/pamen016.htm Eastern and Western Spiritual Alternatives]''&lt;/ref&gt; According to this tradition, the Christ within is regarded as the true Saviour who needs to be born within each individual&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Galatians|4:19}}&lt;/ref&gt; in order to evolve toward the future Sixth [[Root Race|Epoch]] in the Earth's [[etheric plane]], that is, toward the &quot;''new heavens and a new earth''&quot;:&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|2Pet|3:13}}, {{Bibleref2-nb|2Pet|3:7}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''[[New Galilee (Sixth Epoch)|New Galilee]].''&lt;ref&gt;[[Max Heindel|Heindel, Max]], ''[http://www.rosicrucian.com/hkc/hkceng01.htm How Shall We Know Christ at His Coming?]'', May 1913 (stenographic report of a lecture, [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]), ISBN 0-911274-64-2&lt;/ref&gt; The Second Coming or Advent of the Christ is not in a physical body,&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|1Cor|15:50}}, {{Bibleref2|John|18:36}}&lt;/ref&gt; but in the new ''soul body'' of each individual in the [[etheric plane|etheric region]] of the planet&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|2Cor|5:1-3}}, Greek &quot;politeuma&quot; [commonwealth], &quot;Our commonwealth is in heaven ...&quot;: {{Bibleref2|Philippians|3:20-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; where man &quot;shall be caught up in the clouds to meet the Lord in the air.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Matthew|24:30}}, {{Bibleref2|1Thess|4:17}}, {{Bibleref2|Acts|1:10-11}}, {{Bibleref2|1John|3:2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;day and hour&quot; when this event shall be, as described in the Bible, is not in the human knowledge domain.&lt;ref&gt;{{Bibleref2|Matthew|24:23-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The esoteric Christian tradition teaches that first there will be a preparatory period as the [[Sun]] enters [[Aquarius (astrology)|Aquarius]] by precession: the coming [[age of Aquarius]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rosicrucian.com/zineen/magen119.htm The Aquarian Age] (cf. {{Bibleref2|1Cor|2:6-16}})&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dispensationalists===
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2011}}
{{Main|Dispensationalism}}
{{See also|Premillennialism}}
Dispensationalists believe:

# The coming of Christ will be instantaneous and worldwide. &quot;For as the lightning comes from the east and flashes to the west, so also will the coming of the Son of Man be.&quot; ~ [[Gospel of Matthew]] 24:27
# The coming of Christ will be visible to all. &quot;Then the sign of the Son of Man will appear in heaven, and then all the tribes of the earth will mourn, and they will see the Son of Man coming on the clouds of heaven with power and great glory.&quot; Matthew 24:30
# The coming of Christ will be audible. &quot;And He will send His angels with a great sound of a trumpet, and they will gather together His elect from the four winds, from one end of heaven to the other.&quot; Matthew 24:31

==Last Day counterfeits==
{{Main|Antichrist|False Prophet}}
Many Christians {{Who|date=November 2011}} believe there will be a great deception before the coming of Christ.  In Matthew 24 [[Jesus]] states
{{Quote|
For at that time there will be great tribulation, such as has not been since the beginning of the world until now, nor ever will be. And if those days had not been shortened, no one would be saved; but for the sake of the elect they will be shortened. If anyone says to you then, 'Look, here is the Messiah!' or, 'There he is!' do not believe it. False messiahs and false prophets will arise, and they will perform signs and wonders so great as to deceive, if that were possible, even the elect. |Matthew 24:21, 24 (NAB)|}}

{{Quote|
These false Christs will perform great signs and are no ordinary people &quot;For they are spirits of demons, performing signs, which go out to the kings of the earth and of the whole world, to gather them to the battle of that great day of God Almighty.&quot; (Revelation 16:14) Satan's angels will also appear as godly clergymen, and Satan will appear as an angel of light.&lt;ref name=&quot;The United States In Bible Prophecy&quot;&gt;[http://www.amazingfacts.org/FreeStuff/BibleStudies/StudyGuides/tabid/105/ctl/ViewMedia/mid/453/IID/2-21/LNG/en/SC/R/Default.aspx?7=The-USA-in-Bible-Prophecy. The United States In Bible Prophecy] See Item # 15&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;For such are false apostles, deceitful workers, transforming themselves into apostles of Christ. And no wonder! For Satan himself transforms himself into an angel of light. Therefore it is no great thing if his ministers also transform themselves into ministers of righteousness, whose end will be according to their works.&quot; |2 Corinthians 11:13-15)|}}

{{Quote|
As the crowning act in the great drama of deception, Satan himself will impersonate Christ. The church has long professed to look to the Saviour's advent as the consummation of her hopes. Now the great deceiver will make it appear that Christ has come. In different parts of the earth, Satan will manifest himself among men as a majestic being of dazzling brightness, resembling the description of the Son of God given by John in the Revelation. (Revelation 1:13-15). The glory that surrounds him is unsurpassed by anything that mortal eyes have yet beheld. The shout of triumph rings out upon the air: &quot;Christ has come! Christ has come!&quot; The people prostrate themselves in adoration before him, while he lifts up his hands and pronounces a blessing upon them, as Christ blessed His disciples when He was upon the earth. His voice is soft and subdued, yet full of melody. In gentle, compassionate tones he presents some of the same gracious, heavenly truths which the Saviour uttered; he heals the diseases of the people, and then, in his assumed character of Christ, he claims to have changed the Sabbath to Sunday, and commands all to hallow the day which he has blessed.|''The Great Controversy'', p. 624&lt;ref&gt;The Great Controversy Chapter Entitled &quot;The Time Of Trouble&quot;, Ellen White, p. 624-625&lt;/ref&gt;|}}

==Specific date predictions and claims==
{{Main|Predictions and claims for the Second Coming of Christ}}
{{see also|List of messiah claimants|Olivet discourse#Imminence}}

A number of specific dates have been suggested for the Second Coming of Christ. Some of these predictions have passed many decades ago and some are decades away.

Victor J. Stenger notes that Jesus is recorded as saying, &quot; ...there are some standing here, which shall not taste death, till they see the Son of Man coming in his kingdom &quot;, {{bibleverse||Matt|16:28}}. He makes similar predictions in four other places in the Gospels; {{bibleverse||Mark|9:1}}, {{bibleverse||Mark|13:30}}, {{bibleverse||Matt|24:34}}, {{bibleverse||Luke|9:27}}. When the coming did not happen within the life-times of his disciples, as Jesus prophesied, Christianity changed its emphasis to the Resurrection and promise of eternal life.&lt;ref&gt;Chapter 2, ' The Folly of Faith ' p54 in  &quot; The New Atheism &quot; by [[ Victor J. Stenger]], published 2009 by Prometheus Books, ISBN 978-1-59102-751-5&lt;/ref&gt;

==Non-Christian viewpoints==
===Judaism===
{{Main|Judaism's view of Jesus}}
{{See also|Rejection of Jesus}}
[[Judaism]] believes that Jesus is one of the false [[Jewish Messiah claimants]] because he failed to fulfill any [[Jewish messianism|Messianic prophecies]], which include:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
#Build the Third Temple (Ezekiel 37:26-28).
#Gather all Jews back to the Land of Israel (Isaiah 43:5-6).
#Usher in an era of world peace, and end all hatred, oppression, suffering and disease. As it says: &quot;Nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall man learn war anymore.&quot; (Isaiah 2:4)
#Spread universal knowledge of the God of Israel, which will unite humanity as one. As it says: &quot;God will be King over all the world ― on that day, God will be One and His Name will be One&quot; (Zechariah 14:9).&lt;ref name=simmons&gt;[[Shraga Simmons|Simmons, Rabbi Shraga]], [http://www.aish.com/jw/s/48892792.html &quot;Why Jews Don't Believe in Jesus&quot;], [[Aish.Com]]. Accessed December 22, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Regarding the Christian idea that these prophecies will be fulfilled during a &quot;second coming,&quot; ''[[Ohr Somayach, Jerusalem|Ohr Samayach]]'' states &quot;we find this to be a contrived answer, since there is no mention of a second coming in the Jewish Bible. Second, why couldn't G-d accomplish His goals the first time round?&quot;&lt;ref name=ohr&gt;[http://ohr.edu/ask_db/ask_main.php/2637/Q1/ &quot;Why Jews Don't Believe in Jesus&quot;], [[Ohr Somayach, Jerusalem|Ohr Somayach]] - ''Ask the Rabbi''. Accessed December 22, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Rabbi [[David Wolpe]] believes that the Second Coming was &quot;grown out of genuine disappointment&quot; and invented by Christians to theologically compensate for Jesus' death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.beliefnet.com/story/28/story_2892_2.html |title=Why Jews Don't Accept Jesus |publisher=Beliefnet.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
===Islam===
{{Main|Jesus in Islam|Islamic eschatology}}
Muslims believe that Isa (Jesus) will return at a time close to the end of the world. The Qur'anic verse they allude to as an indicator to Isa's future return is as follows:&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI-Isa&quot;&gt;&quot;Isa&quot;, Encyclopedia of Islam&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|
{{Quran-usc|43|61|q=And he (Isa) shall be a Sign (for the coming of) the Hour (of Judgment): therefore have no doubt about the (Hour), but follow ye Me: this is a Straight Way.}}}}

According to Islamic tradition, Isa's descent will be in the midst of wars fought by the ''[[Mahdi]]'' (''lit''. &quot;the rightly guided one&quot;), known in [[Islamic eschatology]] as the redeemer of Islam, against the ''[[Dajjal|al-Masīh ad-Dajjāl]]'' (&quot;false messiah&quot;) and his followers.&lt;ref name=&quot;S209&quot;&gt;Sonn (2004) p. 209&lt;/ref&gt; Isa will descend at the point of a white arcade, east of [[Damascus]], dressed in yellow robes—his head anointed. He will then join the ''Mahdi'' in his war against the ''Dajjal''. Isa, considered in Islam as a Muslim (one who submits to God) and one of God's messengers, will abide by the Islamic teachings. Eventually, Isa will slay the ''Dajjal'', and then everyone from the [[People of the Book]] (''ahl al-kitāb'', referring to Jews and Christians) will believe in him. Thus, there will be one community, that of Islam. {{Hadith-usc|muslim|usc=yes|41|7023}}

{{Hadith-usc|bukhari|usc=yes|3|43|656}}: Narrated [[Abu Hurairah]]:

{{quote|
&quot;Allah's Apostle said, &quot;The Hour will not be established until the son of Mary (Mariam) (i.e. Isa) descends amongst you as a just ruler, he will break the cross, kill the pigs, and abolish the Jizya tax. Money will be in abundance so that nobody will accept it (as charitable gifts).&quot;}}

After the death of the ''Mahdi'', Isa will assume leadership. This is a time associated in Islamic narrative with universal peace and justice. Islamic texts also allude to the appearance of [[Gog and Magog#Qur'an|Ya'juj and Ma'juj]] (known also as Gog and Magog), ancient tribes which will disperse and cause disturbance on earth. God, in response to Isa's prayers, will kill them by sending a type of worm in the napes of their necks.&lt;ref name=&quot;S209&quot;/&gt; Isa's rule is said to be around forty years, after which he will die. Muslims will then perform the ''[[Salat al-Janazah]]'' (funeral prayer) for him and bury him in the city of [[Medina]] in a grave left vacant beside [[Muhammad]].&lt;ref name=&quot;EoI-Isa&quot;/&gt;

====Ahmadiyya====
[[File:Hadhrat Mirza Ghulam Ahmad2.jpg|thumb|[[Mirza Ghulam Ahmad]]]]
{{main|Jesus in Ahmadiyya Islam}}
The [[Ahmadis]] believe that the promised Mahdi and Messiah (being one and the same person) has already arrived in the person of [[Mirza Ghulam Ahmad]] (1835–1908).

The ''[[hadith]]'' (sayings of the Islamic Prophet [[Muhammad]]) and the [[Bible]] indicated that Isa would return during the latter days. Islamic tradition commonly depicts that Isa, upon his second coming, would be an ''Ummati'' (Muslim) and a follower of Muhammad and that he would revive the truth of Islam rather than fostering a new religion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usc.edu/dept/MSA/fundamentals/hadithsunnah/abudawud/037.sat.html#037.4310 Sunan Abi Dawud, Kitab Al-Malahim, Book 37, Number 4310]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ahmadiyya movement interpret the Second Coming of Isa prophesied as being that of a person &quot;similar to Isa&quot; (''mathīl-i ʿIsā'') and not his physical return, in the same way as [[John the Baptist]] resembled the character of the biblical prophet [[Elijah]] in Christianity. Ahmadis believe that Ghulam Ahmad demonstrated that the prophecy in Muslim and Christian religious texts were traditionally misunderstood to suggest that Jesus of Nazareth himself would return, and hold that Jesus had survived the crucifixion and had died a natural death. Ahmadi's consider [[Mirza Ghulam Ahmad|the founder of the movement]], in both his character and teachings to be representative of Jesus, and subsequently he attained the same spiritual rank of Prophethood as Jesus. Thus, Ahmadis believe this prediction was fulfilled and continued by his movement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alislam.org/library/books/promisedmessiah/index.htm?page=63 “A Prophet Like Unto Moses”], The Promised Mehdi and Messiha, by Dr. Aziz Ahmad Chaudhry, Islam International Publications Limited&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;muslim.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.muslim.org/bookspdf/fourques.pdf The Four Questions Answered], by Mirza Ghulam Ahmad, AAIIL 1996&lt;/ref&gt;
===Baha'i Faith===
[[Bahá'u'lláh]] claimed to be the Return of Christ. Followers of the [[Bahá'í Faith]] believe that the fulfillment of the prophecies of the second coming of Jesus, as well as the prophecies of the [[Maitreya]] and many other religious prophecies, were begun by the [[Báb]] in 1844 and then by [[Bahá'u'lláh]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title = Studies in Modern Religions, Religious Movements and the Bābī-Bahā'ī Faiths | editor = Sharon, Moshe | chapter = The eschatology of Globalization: The multiple-messiahship of Bahā'u'llāh revisited | first = Christopher | last = Buck | isbn = 90-04-13904-4 | location = Boston | publisher = Brill | year = 2004 | pages = 143–178}}&lt;/ref&gt; They commonly compare the fulfillment of Christian prophecies to Jesus' fulfillment of Jewish prophecies, where in both cases people were expecting the literal fulfillment of apocalyptic statements.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://www.bci.org/prophecy-fulfilled/ Prophecy-Fulfilled ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bahai-library1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Stephen |last=Lambden |url=http://bahai-library.com/bsr/bsr09/9B3_lambden_armageddon.htm |title=Catastrophe, Armageddon and Millennium: some aspects of the Bábí-Baha'i exegesis of apocalyptic symbolism |publisher=Bahai-library.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hinduism===
In modern times some traditional Indian religious leaders have since moved to embrace Jesus as an [[Avatar]], or incarnation, of God.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.harekrishnatemple.com/bhakta/chapter27.html |title=Krishna and Jesus Christ |publisher=Harekrishnatemple.com |date= |accessdate=2009-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In light of this, the Indian guru [[Yogananda|Paramahansa Yogananda]], author of ''[[Autobiography of a Yogi]]'', scribed an extensive commentary on the Gospels published in the two-volume set ''The Second Coming of Christ: The Resurrection of the Christ Within You''.&lt;ref&gt;Yogananda, Paramahansa. ''The Second Coming of Christ: The Resurrection of the Christ Within You.'' Self-Realization Fellowship, 2004. '''ISBN''' 978-0876125557&lt;/ref&gt; In the tradition of the [[Gnostic Gospels]], the book offers a mystical interpretation of the Second Coming in which it is understood to be an inner experience, something that takes place within the individual heart.

Stating that &quot;Paramahansa Yogananda was sent to the West by Jesus Christ himself&quot; with the said intent to &quot;restore the original Christian teachings among his followers&quot;, in ''Revelations of Christ'' [[Swami Kriyananda]], Yogananda's disciple and Ex-minister of the [[Self-Realization Fellowship]], provides a distilled commentary on the life and teachings of Christ, all of which is meant to serve as an anticipatory primer to Yogananda's more philosophically nuanced treatment in ''The Second Coming of Christ''. Turning directly to The Bible, Kriyananda argues for a more scripturally mature Christianity in which The Second Coming is treated not in terms of a profane materialism - one which favors a literal, physical and subsequently anti-spiritual resurrection - but rather unfolds in accordance with the more spiritual aspirations of The Book of Luke; for &quot;Neither shall they say, Lo here! or, lo there! for, behold, the kingdom of God is within you.&quot; (Luke 17:21)

Thus Hinduism's consideration of itself as an Eastern extension of the Christian Gospel, however, is neither unique to Yogananda or his disciple, Swami Kriyananda. Similarly, [[Srila Prabhupada]], author [[Bhagavad Gita As It Is]] and founder of the [[Hare Krishna Movement]], has propounded the same pluralistic, nonsecular view: that &quot;'Christ' is another way of saying Krsta and Krsta is another way of pronouncing [[Krishna]], the name of God.&quot; Stating that &quot;A son may call his father 'Father', but the father also has a specific name. Similarly, God is the general name of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, whose specific name is Krishna&quot;, &quot;Therefore&quot;, he writes, &quot;whether you call God 'Christ', 'Krsta', or 'Krishna', ultimately you are addressing the same Supreme Personality of Godhead. &quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://krishna.org/christ-and-krishna-the-name-is-the-same/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Theosophy===
In January 1946, [[Theosophy|Theosophist]] [[Alice A. Bailey]] prophesied that Christ (who is regarded by Theosophists as being identical with the being known by Theosophists as the ''[[Maitreya (Theosophy)|Maitreya]]'') would return &quot;sometime after AD 2025&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bailey, Alice A. Page 530&quot;&gt;Bailey, Alice A. ''The Externalisation of the Hierarchy'' New York:1957 Lucis Publishing Co. Page 530&lt;/ref&gt;
== See also ==
* [[Christian eschatology]]
* [[Life of Jesus in the New Testament]]
* [[List of people who have claimed to be Jesus]]
* [[Realized eschatology]]
* [[The Second Coming (poem)|&quot;The Second Coming&quot;]], a poem by [[William Butler Yeats]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==
* Explanatory text in ''[[The New Jerusalem Bible]]'' (1990). Doubleday. ISBN 0-385-14264-1
* [[C. S. Lewis|Lewis, C.S.]] (1960). ''[[The World's Last Night and Other Essays]].'' Harcourt Brace Jovanovich. ISBN 0-15-698360-5
* Markus Mühling, ''Grundinformation Eschatologie. Systematische Theologie aus der Perspektive der Hoffnung'', Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, Göttingen 2007, ISBN 978-3-525-03619-8, 221–241
* [[Max Heindel|Heindel, Max]], ''How Shall We Know Christ at His Coming?'', May 1913 (stenographic report of a lecture, [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]), ISBN 0-911274-64-2 [http://www.rosicrucian.com/hkc/hkceng01.htm www]
* [[James Stuart Russell]]. ''The Parousia, A Careful Look at the New Testament Doctrine of the Lord's Second Coming''
* [http://www.amazingfacts.org/FreeStuff/BibleStudies/StudyGuides/tabid/105/ctl/ViewMedia/mid/453/IID/2-8/LNG/en/7/The-Ultimate-Deliverance/SC/R/Default.aspx The Ultimate Deliverance]
* Swedenborg, E. ''The Consummation of the Age; the Coming of the Lord; and the New Heaven and New Church'', Chapter 14 in [http://swedenborgdigitallibrary.org/contets/tcrtc.html ''The True Christian Religion Containing the Universal Theology of The New Church Foretold by the Lord in Daniel 7; 13, 14; and in Revelation 21; 1,2''] (Swedenborg Foundation 1952)

==External links==

*[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf207.ii.xix.html &quot;Lecture XV: On the Clause, And Shall Come in Glory to Judge the Quick and the Dead; Of Whose Kingdom There Shall Be No End.&quot;], delivered by [[Cyril of Jerusalem]] in the mid-4th century.

{{Christianityfooter|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Second Coming Of Christ}}
[[Category:Apocalypticism]]
[[Category:Biblical phrases]]
[[Category:Christian eschatology]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Christianity-related controversies]]
[[Category:Esoteric Christianity]]
[[Category:Islamic eschatology]]

[[af:Wederkoms]]
[[bg:Второ пришествие на Христос]]
[[ca:Parusia]]
[[cs:Parusie]]
[[de:Parusie]]
[[el:Δευτέρα Παρουσία]]
[[es:Parusía]]
[[fr:Parousie]]
[[ko:재림]]
[[id:Kedatangan Kedua Yesus Kristus]]
[[ia:Parousia]]
[[it:Seconda venuta]]
[[he:הביאה השנייה]]
[[ka:მეორედ მოსვლა]]
[[nl:Wederkomst van Jezus]]
[[ja:再臨]]
[[pl:Paruzja]]
[[pt:Segunda vinda de Cristo]]
[[ro:A Doua Venire a lui Iisus Hristos]]
[[ru:Второе пришествие Иисуса Христа]]
[[sq:Ardhja e Dytë e Jezusit]]
[[sk:Parusia]]
[[fi:Jeesuksen toinen tuleminen]]
[[sv:Kristi återkomst]]
[[ta:கிறிஸ்துவின் இரண்டாம் வருகை]]
[[uk:Друге Пришестя]]
[[zh:耶稣再临]]</text>
      <sha1>n1qxqpfopcei642lf0nap4iyb7y1qpa</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
