<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Second Great Awakening</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43268</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522116966</id>
      <parentid>522112968</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T03:37:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>72Dino</username>
        <id>2439235</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/108.88.4.143|108.88.4.143]] ([[User talk:108.88.4.143|talk]]) to last version by StAnselm</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23813">The '''Second [[Great Awakening]]''' was a [[Protestant]] revival movement during the early 19th century in the [[United States]]. The movement began around 1790, gained momentum by 1800, and, after 1820 membership rose rapidly among Baptist and Methodist congregations, whose preachers led the movement. It was past its peak by the 1840s.

The Second Great Awakening expressed [[Arminianism|Arminian theology]], by which every person could be saved through revivals. It enrolled millions of new members in existing evangelical denominations and led to the formation of new denominations. Many converts believed that the Awakening heralded a new [[Millennialism|millennial age]]. The Second Great Awakening stimulated the establishment of many reform movements designed to remedy the evils of society before the [[Second Coming]] of Jesus Christ.&lt;ref name=&quot;Timothy&quot;&gt;Timothy L.  Smith, ''Revivalism and Social Reform: American Protestantism on the Eve of the Civil War'' (1957)&lt;/ref&gt;

People at the time talked about the Awakening; historians named the Second Great Awakening in the context of the [[First Great Awakening]] of the 1730s and '40s and of the [[Third Great Awakening]] of the late 1850s to early 1900s.

[[File:Growth of Denominations in America 1780 to 1860.jpg|thumb|450px|During the Second Great Awakening, church membership rose sharply.]]

==Spread of revivals==
===Burned-over district===
In the early nineteenth century, upstate [[History of New York|New York]] was called the &quot;[[burned-over district]]&quot; because of the numerous revivals that crisscrossed the region.&lt;ref&gt;Whitney R. Cross, ''The Burned-over District: The Social and Intellectual History of Enthusiastic Religion in Western New York, 1800-1850'' (1951)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Judith Wellman, ''Grassroots Reform in the Burned-over District of Upstate New York: Religion, Abolitionism, and Democracy'' (2000) [http://www.amazon.com/Grassroots-Reform-Burned-over-District-Upstate/dp/0815337922/ excerpt and text search] &lt;/ref&gt;

===Frontier and Tidewater South===
On the [[American Frontier]], evangelical denominations sent missionary preachers and exhorters out to the people in the backcountry, which supported the growth of membership among [[Methodism|Methodists]] and [[Baptists]]. Revivalists' techniques were based on the [[camp meeting]], with its Scottish [[Presbyterian]] roots. Most of the Scots-Irish immigrants before the American Revolutionary War settled in the backcountry of Pennsylvania and down the spine of the Appalachian Mountains.&lt;ref&gt;On Scottish influences see Long (2002) and Elizabeth Semancik, &quot;Backcountry Religious Ways&quot; at [http://xroads.virginia.edu/~ug97/albion/areligio.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

These denominations were based on an interpretation of man's spiritual equality before God, which led them to recruit members and preachers from a wide range of classes and all races. Baptists and Methodist revivals were successful in some parts of the [[Tidewater (geographic term)|Tidewater]] in the South, where an increasing number of common planters, [[Plain Folk of the Old South|plain folk]], and slaves were converted. 

===Adventism===
The [[Adventism|Advent]] Movement emerged in the 1830s and 1840s in North America, and was preached by ministers such as [[William Miller (preacher)|William Miller]], whose followers became known as [[Millerism|Millerites]]. The name refers to belief in the soon [[Second Advent of Jesus]] (popularly known as the [[Second coming]]) and resulted in several major religious denominations, including [[Seventh-day Adventist Church|Seventh-day Adventists]] and [[Advent Christian Church|Advent Christians]].&lt;ref&gt;Gary Land, ''Adventism in America: A History'' (1998) &lt;/ref&gt;

===Church membership soars===
[[File:1839-meth.jpg|thumb|left|350px|1839 Methodist camp meeting]]
The Methodist circuit riders and local Baptist preachers made enormous gains; to a lesser extent the [[Presbyterians]] gained members, particularly with the [[Cumberland Presbyterian Church]] in frontier areas. Among the new denominations that grew from the religious ferment of the Second Great Awakening are the [[Churches of Christ]], [[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)]], [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (nicknamed the Mormons), the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]], and the [[Evangelical Christian Church in Canada]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sydney&quot;&gt;Sydney E. Ahlstrom, ''A Religious History of the American People'' (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Melton's Encyclopedia of American Religions'' (2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Frontier===
In the newly settled frontier regions, the revival was implemented through camp meetings. These often provided the first encounter for some settlers with organized religion, and they were important as social venues. The camp meeting was a religious service of several days' length with multiple preachers. Settlers in thinly populated areas gathered at the camp meeting for fellowship as well as worship. The sheer exhilaration of participating in a religious revival with crowds of hundreds and perhaps thousands of people inspired the dancing, shouting, and singing associated with these events. The revivals followed an arc of great emotional power, with an emphasis of the individual's sins and need to turn to Christ, restored by a sense of personal salvation. Upon their return home, most converts joined or created small local churches, which grew rapidly.&lt;ref&gt;Dickson D. Bruce, Jr., ''And They All Sang Hallelujah: Plain Folk Camp-Meeting Religion, 1800–1845,'' (1974)&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the early camp meetings took place in July 1800 at [[Gasper River]] Church in southwestern Kentucky. A much larger gathering was held at [[Cane Ridge, Kentucky]] in 1801, attracting perhaps as many as 20,000 people. Numerous [[Presbyterianism|Presbyterian]], Baptist and Methodist ministers participated in the services. Thanks to such leaders as [[Barton W. Stone]] (1772–1844) and [[Alexander Campbell (clergyman)|Alexander Campbell]] (1788–1866), the camp meeting revival became a major mode of church expansion for the Methodists and Baptists.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2005&quot;&gt;Douglas Foster, et al., ''The Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement'' (2005)&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Cumberland Presbyterian Church]] emerged in Kentucky. Cane Ridge was also instrumental in fostering what became known as the [[Restoration Movement]]. This was made up of non-denominational churches committed to what they saw as the original, fundamental Christianity of the New Testament. They were committed to individuals' achieving a personal relationship with Christ. Churches with roots in this movement include the [[Churches of Christ]], [[Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)]], [[Evangelical Christian Church in Canada]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Sydney&quot; /&gt; and the [[Christian churches and churches of Christ]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2005&quot;/&gt;

===Restoration Movement===
{{see|Restorationism (Christian primitivism)}}
The idea of restoring a &quot;primitive&quot; form of Christianity grew in popularity in the U.S. after the [[American Revolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Allen &amp; Hughes 1988&quot;&gt;C. Leonard Allen and Richard T. Hughes, ''Discovering Our Roots: The Ancestry of the Churches of Christ,'' Abilene Christian University Press, 1988, ISBN 0-89112-006-8&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|89–94}} This desire to restore a purer form of Christianity without an elaborate hierarchy contributed to the development of many groups during the Second Great Awakening, including the [[History of the Latter Day Saint movement|Mormons]], [[Baptists in the United States|Baptists]] and [[Shakers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Allen &amp; Hughes 1988&quot;/&gt;{{rp|89}}  Several factors made the restoration sentiment particularly appealing during this time period:&lt;ref name=&quot;Allen &amp; Hughes 1988&quot;/&gt;{{rp|90–94}}

*To immigrants in the early 19th century, the land in the United States seemed pristine, edenic and undefiled – &quot;the perfect place to recover pure, uncorrupted and original Christianity&quot; – and the tradition-bound European churches seemed out of place in this new setting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Allen &amp; Hughes 1988&quot;/&gt;{{rp|90}}
*A primitive faith based on the Bible alone promised a way to sidestep the competing claims of the many denominations available and for congregations to find assurance of being right without the security of an established national church.&lt;ref name=&quot;Allen &amp; Hughes 1988&quot;/&gt;{{rp|93}}

The Restoration Movement began during, and was greatly influenced by, the Second Great Awakening.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Great Awakenings&quot;&gt;Douglas Allen Foster and Anthony L. Dunnavant, ''The Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Christian Churches/Churches of Christ, Churches of Christ'', Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2004, ISBN 0-8028-3898-7, ISBN 978-0-8028-3898-8, 854 pages, entry on ''Great Awakenings''&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|368}}  While the leaders of one of the two primary groups making up this movement, [[Thomas Campbell (clergyman)|Thomas Campbell]] and [[Alexander Campbell (clergyman)|Alexander Campbell]], resisted what they saw as the spiritual manipulation of the camp meetings, the revivals contributed to the development of the other major branch, led by [[Barton W. Stone]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Great Awakenings&quot;/&gt;{{rp|368}}  The Southern phase of the Awakening &quot;was an important matrix of Barton Stone's reform movement&quot; and shaped the evangelistic techniques used by both Stone and the Campbells.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Great Awakenings&quot;/&gt;{{rp|368}}

===Culture and society===
[[Congregational church|Congregationalists]] set up missionary societies to evangelize the western territory of the northern tier.  Members of these groups acted as apostles for the faith, and also as educators and exponents of northeastern urban culture. Publication and education societies promoted Christian education; most notable among them was the [[American Bible Society]], founded in 1816. Social activism influenced [[abolitionism|abolition]] groups and supporters of the [[Temperance movement|temperance]] movement.  They began efforts to reform prisons and care for the handicapped and mentally ill. They believed in the perfectibility of people and were highly moralistic in their endeavors. The Second Great Awakening served as an &quot;organizing process&quot; that created &quot;a religious and educational infrastructure&quot; across the western frontier that encompassed social networks, a religious journalism that provided mass communication, and church-related colleges.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Great Awakenings&quot;/&gt;{{rp|368}}

===Ritual and theology===
Long (2002) notes that since the 1980s, scholars have connected American religious camp meetings to [[Holy Fair|Scottish holy fairs]] of the 17th–18th centuries. Formerly they were thought to have originated in the unique conditions of the American frontier experience. The great wave of [[Ulster Scots people|Scots-Irish]] immigrants to the colonies before the [[American Revolution]] brought such traditions with them.

Long examines the sacramental theology in communion sermons given by [[James McGready]] in Kentucky during the first decade of the 19th century. McGready's sermons demonstrated adherence to reformed theology, a [[Calvinist]] understanding of salvation, and a sacramental emphasis. A central theme of McGready's sermons was that of believers' meeting Christ at the communion table.

===Slaves and free blacks===
Baptists and Methodists in the South preached to slaveholders and slaves alike. Conversions and congregations started with the [[First Great Awakening]], resulting in Baptist and Methodist preachers being authorized among slaves and free blacks more than a decade before 1800. Free blacks in Philadelphia left a Methodist church because of its discrimination. By the late eighteenth century, they founded the first African Episcopal Church and first [[African Methodist Episcopal]] (AME) churches in Philadelphia. In 1816, several AME congregations joined in association to establish the AME denomination, the first independent black denomination in the United States. Soon after that, the [[African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church]] (AME Zion) was founded as another denomination in New York City. 

Early Baptist congregations were formed by slaves and free blacks in South Carolina and Virginia.  Especially in the Baptist Church, blacks were welcomed as members and as preachers. By the early 19th century, independent black congregations numbered in the several hundred in some cities of the South, such as [[Charleston, South Carolina]], and Richmond and [[Petersburg, Virginia]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Raboteau&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=C3AQUK-6A2cC&amp;pg=PA188&amp;lpg=PA188&amp;dq=Gillfield+Baptist+Church,+Petersburg,+VA&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=U6q91GTWul&amp;sig=yi0EVoIuLJ9WhNUg3YeqcVkoKBY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=11&amp;ct=result#PPA189,M1 Albert J. Raboteau, ''Slave Religion: The 'Invisible Institution' in the Antebellum South''], New York: Oxford University Press, 2004, p. 137, accessed 27 Dec 2008&lt;/ref&gt; With the growth in congregations and churches, Baptist associations formed in Virginia, for instance, as well as Kentucky and other states.

The revival also inspired slaves to demand freedom. In 1800, out of black revival meetings in Virginia, a plan for slave rebellion was devised by [[Gabriel Prosser]], although the rebellion was discovered and crushed before it started.&lt;ref&gt;Alan Brinkley, ''The Unfinished Nation'', p 168&lt;/ref&gt; Despite white attempts to control independent black congregations, especially after the [[Nat Turner]] Uprising of 1831, a number of black congregations managed to maintain their separation as independent congregations in Baptist associations. State legislatures passed laws requiring them always to have a white man present at their worship meetings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Raboteau&quot; /&gt;

== Prominent figures ==
* [[Richard Allen (bishop)|Richard Allen]], founder, [[African Methodist Episcopal Church]]
* [[Lyman Beecher]], [[Presbyterian]]
* [[Alexander Campbell (clergyman)|Alexander Campbell]], Presbyterian, and early leader of the [[Restoration Movement]]
* [[Thomas Campbell (clergyman)|Thomas Campbell]] Presbyterian, then early leader of the [[Restoration Movement]]
* [[Peter Cartwright (exhorter)|Peter Cartwright]], [[Methodist]]
* [[Lorenzo Dow]], Methodist
* [[Timothy Dwight IV]], [[Congregationalist]]
* [[Charles Grandison Finney|Charles Finney]], Presbyterian, but anti-[[Calvinist]]
* [[William Miller (preacher)|William Miller]], [[Millerism]], forerunner of [[Adventism]]
* [[Asahel Nettleton]], [[Reformed churches|Reformed]]
* [[Joseph Smith]], [[Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (Mormons)
* [[Barton Stone]], Presbyterian non-Calvinist, then early leader of the [[Restoration Movement]]
* [[James Brainerd Taylor]] (no relation to [[Nathaniel William Taylor]]), [[Reformed]], mentored by [[Asahel Nettleton]]
* [[Nathaniel William Taylor]], heterodox Calvinist
* [[Ellen G. White]], Seventh-day Adventist Church

The great revival quickly spread throughout Kentucky, Tennessee and southern [[Ohio]]. Each denomination had assets that allowed it to thrive on the frontier. The Methodists had an efficient organization that depended on itinerant ministers, known as [[circuit rider (religious)|circuit rider]]s, who sought out people in remote frontier locations. The circuit riders came from among the common people, which helped them establish rapport with the frontier families they hoped to convert.

The Second Great Awakening exercised a profound impact on American religious history.  The numerical strength of the Baptists and Methodists rose relative to that of the denominations dominant in the colonial period—the [[Anglicans]], [[Presbyterians]], [[Congregational church|Congregationalists]], and [[Reformed churches|Reformed]]. Efforts to apply Christian teaching to the resolution of social problems presaged the [[Social Gospel]] of the late 19th century.

The United States was becoming a more culturally diverse nation in the early-to-mid-19th century, and the growing differences within American Protestantism reflected and contributed to this diversity. The Awakening influenced numerous reform movements, especially [[abolitionists]].

==Political implications==
In the midst of shifts in theology and [[church polity]], American Christians began progressive movements to reform society during this period. Known commonly as [[Religious Reform in Antebellum America|antebellum reform]], this phenomenon included reforms in [[temperance movement|temperance]], [[women's rights]], [[abolitionism]], and a multitude of other questions faced by society.&lt;ref&gt;Alice Felt Tyler, ''Freedom's Ferment: Phases of American Social History from the Colonial Period to the Outbreak of the Civil War'' (1944)&lt;/ref&gt;

The religious enthusiasm of the Second Great Awakening was echoed by the new political enthusiasm of the [[Second Party System]].&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Meardon, &quot;From Religious Revivals to Tariff Rancor: Preaching Free Trade and Protection during the Second American Party System,&quot; ''History of Political Economy,'' Winter 2008 Supplement, Vol. 40, pp 265-298&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians stress the understanding common among participants of reform as being a part of God's plan. As a result, local churches saw their roles in society in purifying the world through the individuals to whom they could bring salvation, and through changes in the law and the creation of institutions. Interest in transforming the world was applied to mainstream political action, as temperance activists, antislavery advocates, and proponents of other variations of reform sought to implement their beliefs into national politics. While religion had previously played an important role on the American political scene, the Second Great Awakening highlighted the important role which individual beliefs would play.&lt;ref name=&quot;Timothy&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
*[[Abolitionism]]
*[[Adventist]]
*[[Advent Christian Church]]
*[[Seventh-day Adventist Church]]
*[[Burned-over district]]
*[[Christian revival]]
*[[Christianity in the 19th century]]
*[[Day-year principle|Day-Year principle]]
*[[First Great Awakening]]
*[[William Miller (preacher)]]
*[[Millerites]]
*[[Restoration Movement]]
*[[Temperance movement]]
*[[Third Great Awakening]]
*[[Fourth Great Awakening]]
{{Historical Christian theology}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Abzug, Robert H. ''Cosmos Crumbling: American Reform and the Religious Imagination'' (1994) (ISBN 0-195-04568-8)
* Ahlstrom, Sydney. ''A Religious History of the American People'' (1972)  (ISBN 0-385-11164-9)
* Billington, Ray A.  ''The Protestant Crusade.''  New York:  The MacMillian Company, 1938.
* Birdsall Richard D. &quot;The Second Great Awakening and the New England Social Order&quot;, ''Church History'' 39 (1970): 345–364. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3163469 in JSTOR]
* Bratt, James D. &quot;Religious Anti-revivalism in Antebellum America&quot;, ''Journal of the Early Republic'' (2004) 24(1): 65–106. ISSN 0275–1275 Fulltext: in Ebsco.
*Brown, Kenneth O. ''Holy Ground; a Study on the American Camp Meeting.'' Garland Publishing, Inc., 1992.
*Brown, Kenneth O. ''Holy Ground, Too, the Camp Meeting Family Tree.'' Hazleton: Holiness Archives, (1997).
* Bruce, Dickson D., Jr. ''And They All Sang Hallelujah: Plain Folk Camp-Meeting Religion, 1800–1845'' (1974)
* Butler Jon. &quot;Enthusiasm Described and Decried: The Great Awakening as Interpretative Fiction&quot;, ''Journal of American History'' 69 (1982): 305–325. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1893821 in JSTOR], highly influential essay
* Butler Jon. ''Awash in a Sea of Faith: Christianizing the American People.'' 1990.
* Carwardine, Richard J. ''Evangelicals and Politics in Antebellum America.'' Yale University Press, 1993.
* Carwardine, Richard J. &quot;The Second Great Awakening in the Urban Centers: An Examination of Methodism and the 'New Measures'&quot;, ''Journal of American History'' 59 (1972): 327–340.  [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1890193 in JSTOR]
*  Conforti; Joseph A. '' Jonathan Edwards, Religious Tradition and American Culture'', (1995).
* Cott, Nancy F. &quot;Young Women in the Second Great Awakening in New England,&quot; ''Feminist Studies,'' Vol. 3, No. 1/2 (Autumn, 1975), pp.&amp;nbsp;15–29 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3518952 in JSTOR]
* Cross, Whitney, R. ''The Burned-Over District: The Social and Intellectual History of Enthusiastic Religion in Western New York, 1800–1850'', (1950).
* Foster, Charles I. ''An Errand of Mercy: The Evangelical United Front, 1790–1837'', University of North Carolina Press, 1960.
* Griffin, Clifford S.  &quot;Religious Benevolence as Social Control, 1815–1860&quot;, ''The Mississippi Valley Historical Review'', Vol. 44, No. 3. (Dec., 1957), pp.&amp;nbsp;423–444. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1887019 in JSTOR]
* Hambrick-Stowe, Charles. ''Charles G. Finney and the Spirit of American Evangelicalism.''  (1996).
*  Hankins, Barry.  ''The Second Great Awakening and the Transcendentalists.'' Greenwood, 2004.
* Hatch Nathan O. ''The Democratization of American Christianity'' (1989).
* Johnson, Charles A. &quot;The Frontier Camp Meeting: Contemporary and Historical Appraisals, 1805–1840&quot;,  ''The Mississippi Valley Historical Review'', Vol. 37, No. 1. (Jun., 1950), pp.&amp;nbsp;91–110. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1888756 in JSTOR]
* Kyle III, I. Francis. ''An Uncommon Christian: James Brainerd Taylor, Forgotten Evangelist in America's Second Great Awakening'' (2008). See [http://www.uncommonchristian.com/ Uncommon Christian Ministries]
* Long, Kimberly Bracken. &quot;The Communion Sermons of James Mcgready: Sacramental Theology and Scots-Irish Piety on the Kentucky Frontier&quot;, ''Journal of Presbyterian History'', 2002 80(1): 3–16. Issn: 0022-3883
* Loveland Anne C. ''Southern Evangelicals and the Social Order, 1800–1860'', (1980)
* Marsden George M. ''The Evangelical Mind and the New School Presbyterian Experience: A Case Study of Thought and Theology in Nineteenth-Century America'' (1970).
* [[John A. Matzko|Matzko, John A.]] &quot;The Encounter of the Young Joseph Smith with Presbyterianism,&quot; ''[[Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought]]'' 40/3, 2007.
* [[William G. McLoughlin|McLoughlin William G.]] ''Modern Revivalism'', 1959.
* [[William G. McLoughlin|McLoughlin William G.]] ''Revivals, Awakenings, and Reform: An Essay on Religion and Social Change in America, 1607–1977'', 1978.
* Noll; Mark A. ed. ''God and Mammon: Protestants, Money, and the Market, 1790–1860'' (2002).
* Posey, Walter Brownlow. ''The Baptist Church in the Lower Mississippi Valley, 1776–1845'' (1957)
* Raboteau, Albert. ''Slave Religion: The &quot;invisible Institution' in the Antebellum South'', (1979)
* Roth Randolph A. ''The Democratic Dilemma: Religion, Reform, and the Social Order in the Connecticut River Valley of Vermont, 1791–1850'', (1987)
* Shiels Richard D. &quot;The Second Great Awakening in Connecticut: Critique of the Traditional Interpretation&quot;, ''Church History'' 49 (1980): 401–415. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3164815 in JSTOR]
* Smith, Timothy L. ''Revivalism and Social Reform: American Protestantism on the Eve of the Civil War'' (1957)

{{Restoration Movement}}
{{Christian History}}

[[Category:Restoration Movement]]
[[Category:History of Christianity in the United States]]
[[Category:Christian revivals]]
[[Category:19th-century Christianity]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]

[[ca:Segon Gran Despertar]]
[[cs:Druhé velké probuzení]]
[[es:Segundo Gran Despertar]]
[[eo:Dua Granda Vekiĝo]]
[[fr:Second grand éveil]]
[[hu:Második nagy ébredés]]
[[nl:Second Great Awakening]]
[[ja:第二次大覚醒]]
[[pt:Segundo Grande Despertar]]
[[simple:Second Great Awakening]]
[[sv:Andra stora väckelsen]]
[[zh:第二次大覺醒]]</text>
      <sha1>ivo34pojvpujqu3m1v92tstlnwvicef</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
