<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Shabbat</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28809</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520162898</id>
      <parentid>520162440</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-27T20:34:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>58.165.134.144</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 517941484 by [[Special:Contributions/Hearfourmewesique|Hearfourmewesique]] ([[User talk:Hearfourmewesique|talk]]) Even Ashkenazim keep original Hebrew spellings for words of Hebrew origin.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29198">{{About|the rest day in Judaism|Sabbath in the Bible|Biblical Sabbath|the Talmudic tractate|Shabbat (Talmud)|other uses|Sabbath in seventh-day churches|and|first-day Sabbath}}
[[File:Shabbat Candles.jpg|290px|thumb|Shabbat candles]]
{{Judaism}}
'''Shabbat''' ({{he|שַׁבָּת}}, [[Ashkenazi Hebrew|Ashkenazi pronunciation]]: '''Shabbos''', {{lang-yi|שבת}}, &quot;rest&quot; or &quot;cessation&quot;) is the seventh day of the [[Jewish]] [[seven-day week|week]] and the Jewish day of rest. On Shabbat, Jews recall the [[Genesis creation narrative]] in which God creates the Heavens and the Earth in six days and rests on the seventh. Shabbat observance also entails refraining from a range of [[activities prohibited on Shabbat]], such as lighting a fire and cooking.

According to [[halakha]], Shabbat is observed from a few  minutes before sunset on [[Friday]] evening until the appearance of three stars in the sky on Saturday night.&lt;ref&gt;[[Shulchan Aruch]], [[Orach Chayim]] 293:2&lt;/ref&gt; Shabbat is ushered in by lighting candles and reciting a blessing. Traditionally, three [[Seudat mitzvah#Seudat Shabbat and Seudat Yom Tov|festive meals]] are eaten; on Friday night, Saturday morning, and late Saturday afternoon. Friday night dinner begins with [[kiddush]] and a blessing recited over two loaves of [[challah]]. Shabbat is a festive day when Jews are freed from the regular labors of everyday life. It offers an opportunity to contemplate the spiritual aspects of life and spend time with family.

==Etymology==
{{details|Sabbath etymology}}
The word Shabbat derives from the Hebrew verb ''shavat''. Although frequently translated as &quot;rest&quot; (noun or verb), another accurate translation of these words is &quot;ceasing [from work]&quot;, as resting is not necessarily denoted. The related modern Hebrew word ''shevita'', ([[labor strike]]), has the same implication of active rather than passive abstinence from work. The notion of active cessation from labor is also regarded as more consistent with an [[omnipotent]] [[Names of God in Judaism|God]]'s activity on the seventh day of [[Genesis creation myth|Creation according to Genesis]].

==Biblical sources==
{{details|Biblical Sabbath}}
Shabbat is given special status as a holy day at the very beginning of the [[Torah]] in {{bibleverse||Genesis|2:1–3|HE}}. It is first commanded after [[the Exodus]] from Egypt, in {{bibleverse||Exodus|16:26|HE}} (relating to the cessation of [[manna]]) and in {{bibleverse||Exodus|20:8–11|HE}} (as the fourth of the [[Ten Commandments]]). Shabbat is commanded and commended many more times in the [[Torah]] and Tanakh; special [[korban|sacrifices]] are to be offered on the day. Shabbat is also described by the prophets [[Isaiah]], [[Jeremiah]], [[Ezekiel]], [[Hosea]], [[Amos (prophet)|Amos]], and [[Nehemiah]].

==History==
The traditional Jewish position is that unbroken seventh-day ''Shabbat'' originated among the Jewish people, as their first and most sacred institution.&lt;ref name=landau&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.archive.org/stream/sabbath00land/sabbath00land_djvu.txt|title=The Sabbath|author=Landau, Judah Leo|publisher=Ivri Publishing Society, Ltd|accessdate=2009-03-26|location=[[Johannesburg, South Africa]]|pages=2, 12}}&lt;/ref&gt;. The [[Moses|Mosaic]] tradition usually quotes an origin in [[creation according to Genesis|Biblical creation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcea.org.au/articles/the_westminster_confession/the_origin_of_the_sabbath/|title=The Origin of the Sabbath|author=Graham, I. L.|publisher=[[Presbyterian Church of Eastern Australia]]|year=2009|accessdate=2009-03-26}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; though some suggest some obscure, later, naturalistic origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/303554/Jewish-religious-year/34908/The-Sabbath|title=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]|chapter=Jewish religious year: The Sabbath|year=2009|accessdate=2009-03-26|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Online|quote=Scholars have not succeeded in tracing the origin of the seven-day week, nor can they account for the origin of the Sabbath.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seventh-day ''Shabbat'' did not originate with the [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptians]], to whom it was unknown;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13287b.htm|title=[[The Catholic Encyclopedia]]|author=Bechtel, Florentine|chapter=Sabbath|volume=13|location=[[New York]]|publisher=Robert Appleton Company|year=1912|accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other origin theories based on the day of [[Saturn]], or on the [[planets]] generally, have also been abandoned.&lt;ref name=orr&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Tn4PAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA2630&amp;lpg=PA2630|title=The International Standard Bible Encyclopedia|editor=Orr, James|page=2630|chapter=Sabbath: Critical Theories|author=Sampey, John Richard|publisher=Howard-Severance Company|year=1915|accessdate=2009-08-13|editor-link=James Orr (theologian)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first non-Biblical reference to the Sabbath is in an [[ostracon]] found in excavations at [[Mesad Hashavyahu]], which is dated 630 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.cojs.org/cojswiki/Mezad_Hashavyahu_Ostracon%2C_c._630_BCE|title=Mezad Hashavyahu Ostracon, c. 630 BCE|accessdate=2012-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some point to Jewish contact with Babylonians who celebrated every seventh day as a &quot;holy-day&quot;, also called an &quot;evil day&quot; (meaning &quot;unsuitable&quot; for prohibited activities). On these days officials were prohibited from various activities and common men were forbidden to &quot;make a wish&quot;, and at least the 28th was known as a &quot;rest-day&quot;.{{citation needed|date=October 2012}} The ''[[Universal Jewish Encyclopedia]]'' advanced a theory of [[Assyriologist]]s like [[Friedrich Delitzsch]]&lt;ref name=landau/&gt; (and of [[Marcello Craveri]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Craveri, Marcello|title=The Life of Jesus|publisher=Grove Press|year=1967|page=134}}&lt;/ref&gt; that ''shabbat'' originally arose from the [[lunar cycle]] in the [[Babylonian calendar]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=1943|title=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia: An authoritative and popular presentation of Jews and Judaism since the earliest times|volume=5|page=410|editor=Landman, Isaac|chapter=Holidays|author=Joseph, Max|others=Cohen, Simon, compiler|publisher=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia, Inc|editor-link=Isaac Landman}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=1943|title=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia: An authoritative and popular presentation of Jews and Judaism since the earliest times|volume=9|page=295|editor=Landman, Isaac|chapter=Sabbath|author=Joseph, Max|others=Cohen, Simon, compiler|publisher=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia, Inc|editor-link=Isaac Landman}}&lt;/ref&gt; containing four weeks ending in Sabbath, plus one or two additional unreckoned days per month.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=1943|title=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia: An authoritative and popular presentation of Jews and Judaism since the earliest times|volume=10|page=482|editor=Landman, Isaac|chapter=Week|author=Cohen, Simon|others=Cohen, Simon, compiler|publisher=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia, Inc|editor-link=Isaac Landman}}&lt;/ref&gt; The difficulties of this theory include reconciling the differences between an unbroken week and a lunar week, and explaining the absence of texts naming the lunar week as ''Shabbat'' in any language.&lt;ref name=orr/&gt;

==Status as a holy day==
[[File:GOOD SHABBES -.jpg|thumb|Reciting blessing over Shabbat candles]]
The Tanakh and [[siddur]] (Jewish prayer book) describe Shabbat as having three purposes:
#To commemorate the Israelites' [[the Exodus|redemption from slavery]] in [[ancient Egypt]];
#To commemorate [[Names of God in Judaism|God's]] [[Creation according to Genesis|creations of the universe]]; on the seventh day God rested from (or ceased) his work;
#As a &quot;taste&quot; of [[Olam Haba]] (the [[Messianic Age]]).
Judaism accords Shabbat the status of a joyous holy day. In many ways, Jewish law gives Shabbat the status of being the most important holy day in the Jewish calendar:
*It is the first holy day mentioned in the Bible, and God was the first to observe it with the cessation of [[Creation according to Genesis|Creation]] (Genesis 2:1–3).
*[[Jewish services|Jewish liturgy]] treats the Shabbat as a &quot;bride&quot; and &quot;queen&quot; (see [[Shekhinah]]).
*The [[Sefer Torah]] is read during the [[Torah reading]] which is part of the Shabbat morning services, with a longer reading than during the week. The Torah is read over a yearly cycle of 54 ''[[Parsha|parshiyot]]'', one for each Shabbat (sometimes they are doubled). On Shabbat, the reading is divided into seven sections, more than on any other holy day, including [[Yom Kippur]]. Then, the [[Haftarah]] reading from the Hebrew prophets is read.
*A tradition states that the [[Jewish Messiah]] will come if every Jew properly observes two consecutive Shabbatot.&lt;ref&gt;[[Shabbat (Talmud)|Shabbat]] 118&lt;/ref&gt;
*The punishment in ancient times for desecrating Shabbat ([[stoning]]) is the most severe punishment in Jewish law.&lt;ref&gt;See e.g. Numbers 15:32–36.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Friday night rituals==
According to Jewish law, Shabbat starts a few minutes before sunset. Candles are lit at this time. It is customary in many communities to light the candles 18 minutes before sundown and most printed Jewish Calendars adhere to this custom. The Kabbalat Shabbat service is a prayer service welcoming the arrival of Shabbat.  Before Friday night dinner, it is customary to sing two songs, one &quot;greeting&quot; the Shabbat angels into the house&lt;ref&gt;Shabbat 119b&lt;/ref&gt; and the other consisting of [[Book of Proverbs|Proverbs]] 31:10-31, praising the woman of the house for all the work she has done over the past week. After blessings over the wine and challah, a festive meal is served. Singing is traditional at Sabbath meals.

==Shabbat rituals==
Shabbat is a day of celebration as well as [[Jewish services|prayer]]. It is customary to eat three festive meals: Dinner on Shabbat eve (Friday night), lunch on Shabbat day (Saturday), and a third meal, known as ''[[Seudah Shlishit]]'', in the late afternoon (Saturday).

Many Jews attend synagogue services on Shabbat even if they do not do so during the week. Services are held on Shabbat eve (Friday night), Shabbat morning (Saturday morning), and late Shabbat afternoon (Saturday afternoon).

With the exception of [[Yom Kippur]], which is referred to in the Torah as the &quot;Shabbat of Shabbats&quot;, days of public fasting are postponed or advanced if they coincide with Shabbat. Mourners sitting ''[[shivah]]'' (week of mourning subsequent to the death of a spouse or first-degree relative) outwardly conduct themselves normally for the duration of the day and are forbidden to display public signs of mourning.

According to [[Rabbinic literature]], God via the Torah commands Jews to ''observe'' (refrain from forbidden activity) and ''remember'' (with words, thoughts, and actions) the Shabbat, and these two actions are symbolized by the two [[Shabbat candles]] which are lit 18 to 40 minutes (&quot;Tosefet Shabbat&quot;) before the onset of Shabbat by Jewish women, usually the mother/wife, though men who live alone are required to do so themselves. It is customary to light two candles, although some families light more, sometimes in accordance with the number of children.&lt;ref&gt;[[Shulchan Aruch]], [[Orach Chaim]] 261.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although most Shabbat laws are restrictive, the fourth of the [[Ten Commandments]] in [[Book of Exodus|Exodus]] is taken by the [[Talmud]] to allude to the ''positive'' commandments of the Shabbat. These include:
*Honouring Shabbat (''kavod Shabbat''): Preparing for the upcoming Shabbat by bathing, having a haircut, and cleaning and beautifying the home (with flowers, for example). On Shabbat itself, wearing festive clothing and refraining from unpleasant conversation. It is customary to avoid talk about money or business matters on Shabbat.&lt;ref&gt;Derived from {{bibleverse||Isaiah|58:13–14|HE}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Recitation of ''[[Kiddush]]'' over a cup of [[kosher wine|wine]] at the beginning of the first and second Shabbat meals, or at a reception after the conclusion of morning prayers (see [[list of Jewish prayers and blessings]])
[[File:Shabbat Challos.jpg|right|200px|thumb|Two homemade [[whole wheat flour|whole-wheat]] challahs covered by traditional [[embroidery|embroidered]] Shabbat [[challah cover]].]]
*Eating three festive meals. Meals begin with a blessing over two loaves of bread (''[[lechem mishneh (bread)|lechem mishneh]]''), usually a braided [[challah]], which is symbolic of the double portion of [[manna]] which fell for the Jewish people during their 40 years in the desert after the [[The Exodus|Exodus]] from [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]]. It is customary to serve meat or fish, and sometimes both, for the Shabbat evening and morning meals. The third meal, eaten late Shabbat afternoon, is called ''[[Seudah Shlishit]]'' (literally, &quot;Third Meal&quot;). This is generally a light meal and may be [[parve]] or [[dairy]].
*Enjoying Shabbat (''oneg Shabbat''): Engaging in pleasurable activities such as eating, singing, spending time with the family and marital relations.
[[File:Havdal.jpg|right|thumb|Observing the closing ''[[Havdalah]]'' ritual in 14th-century Spain.]]
*Recitation of ''[[Havdalah]]'' at the conclusion of Shabbat at nightfall (over a cup of wine, and with the use of fragrant spices and a candle).

==Prohibited activities==
{{see also|Activities prohibited on Shabbat}}
===39 Melakhot===
[[Halakha|Jewish law (halakha)]] prohibits doing any form of ''melakhah'' (מְלָאכָה, plural ''melakhot'') on Shabbat, with some exceptions. Though ''melakhah'' is commonly translated as &quot;work&quot; in [[English language|English]], a better definition is &quot;deliberate activity&quot; or &quot;skill and craftmanship&quot;. There are 39 categories of prohibited activities (''melakhot'') listed in [[Mishnah]] [[Shabbat (Talmud)|Tractate Shabbat]]  Chapter 7, Mishna 2).

Different streams of Judaism view the prohibition on work in different ways. Observant [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] and [[Conservative Judaism|Conservative]] Jews refrain from performing the prohibited activities. These prohibited activities are [[exegesis|exegetically]] derived – based on juxtaposition of corresponding Biblical passages – from the kinds of work that were necessary for the construction of the [[Tabernacle (Judaism)|Tabernacle]]. They are not directly listed in the Torah; elsewhere, the Mishnah observes that &quot;the laws of Shabbat [...] are like mountains hanging by a hair, for they are little Scripture but many laws&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Chagigah]] 1:8.&lt;/ref&gt; Many [[Rabbinic literature|religious scholars]] have pointed out that these labors have in common activity that is &quot;creative,&quot; or that exercises control or dominion over one's [[environment (biophysical)|environment]].

The 39 categories of ''melakhah'' are: ploughing earth, sowing, reaping, binding sheaves, threshing, winnowing, selecting, grinding, sifting, kneading, baking, shearing wool, washing wool, beating wool, dyeing wool, spinning, weaving, making two loops, weaving two threads, separating two threads, tying, untying, sewing stitches, tearing, trapping, slaughtering, flaying, tanning, scraping hide, marking hides, cutting hide to shape, writing two or more letters, erasing two or more letters, building, demolishing, extinguishing a fire, kindling a fire, putting the finishing touch on an object and transporting an object between the private domain and the public domain, or for a distance of 4 [[cubit]]s within the public domain.

Each ''melakhah'' has derived prohibitions of various kinds. There are, therefore, many more forbidden activities on the Shabbat; all are traced back to one of the 39 above principal ''melakhot''.

Given the above, the 39 ''melakhot'' are not so much activities as &quot;categories of activity.&quot; For example, while &quot;winnowing&quot; usually refers exclusively to the separation of [[chaff]] from [[cereal|grain]], and &quot;selecting&quot; refers exclusively to the separation of debris from grain, they refer in the Talmudic sense to any separation of intermixed materials which renders edible that which was inedible. Thus, filtering undrinkable [[water]] to make it drinkable falls under this category, as does picking small bones from [[fish]]. (''[[Gefilte fish]]'' is one solution to this problem.)

===Use of electricity===
{{main|Electricity on Shabbat}}
Orthodox and some Conservative authorities rule that it is prohibited to turn [[electricity|electric]] devices on or off as falling under one of the 39 categories of work (''melakhot''). However, the authorities are not in agreement about exactly which category (or categories) this would fall under. One view is that tiny sparks are created in a switch when the circuit is closed, and this would constitute &quot;lighting a fire&quot; (category 37). If the appliance is one whose purpose is for light or heat (such as an incandescent lightbulb or electric oven) then the lighting or heating elements may be considered as a type of fire; if so, then turning them on constitutes both &quot;lighting a fire&quot; (category 37) and &quot;cooking&quot; (a form of baking, category 11), and turning them off would be &quot;extinguishing a fire&quot; (category 36).

Another view is that a device which is plugged into an electrical outlet of a wall becomes part of the building, but is nonfunctional while the switch is off; turning it on would then constitute &quot;building&quot; and turning it off would be &quot;demolishing&quot; (categories 35 and 34). Some schools of thought consider the use of electricity to be forbidden only by [[Rabbinical law|rabbinic injunction]], rather than because it violates one of the original categories.

A common solution to the problem of electricity involves pre-set timers ([[Shabbat clock]]s) for electric appliances, to turn them on and off automatically, with no human intervention on Shabbat itself.  Some Conservative authorities&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Neulander | first1 = Arthur | year = 1950 | title = The Use of Electricity on the Sabbath | url = | journal = Proceedings of the Rabbinical Assembly | volume = 14 | issue = | pages = 165–171 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Adler | first1 = Morris | last2 = Agus | first2 = Jacob | last3 = Friedman | first3 = Theodore | year = 1950 | title = Responsum on the Sabbath | url = | journal = Proceedings of the Rabbinical Assembly | volume = 14 | issue = | pages = 112–137 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Klein, Isaac. ''A Guide to Jewish Religious Practice.'' The Jewish Theological Seminary of America: New York, 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; reject altogether the arguments for prohibiting the use of electricity.  Some Orthodox also hire a &quot;[[shabbas goy]]&quot;, a gentile to turn light switches on and off on Shabbat.

===Automobiles===
{{main|Driving during Shabbat}}
Orthodox and many Conservative authorities completely prohibit the use of automobiles on Shabbat as a violation of multiple categories include &quot;igniting a fire&quot; (category 37), &quot;extinguishing a fire&quot; (category 36) and &quot;transferring between domains&quot; (category 39). However, the Conservative movement's [[Committee on Jewish Law and Standards]] permits driving to a synagogue on Shabbat, as an emergency measure, on the grounds that if Jews lost contact with synagogue life they would become lost to the Jewish people.

A halachically authorized [[Shabbat module]] added to an [[Mobility scooter|Amigo]] power operated vehicle may be used on the observance of Shabbat for those with walking limitations. Often referred to as a Shabbat scooter or [[Amigo Mobility International Inc|Amigo]] Shabbat, it is manufactured by Zomet Institute in Israel, each Shabbat module application is individually inspected and certified by a Zomet representative.  It is intended only for individuals whose limited mobility is dependent on a POV/scooter or automobile consistently throughout the week.

===Shomer Shabbat===
{{main|Shomer Shabbat}}
The term ''shomer Shabbat'' is used for a person (or organization) who adheres to Shabbat laws consistently. The ''shomer Shabbat'' is an archetype mentioned in Jewish songs (e.g., ''Baruch El Elyon'') and the intended audience for various treatises on Jewish law and practice for ''Shabbat'' (e.g., ''Shemirat Shabbat ke-Hilkhata'').

===Technology in the service of Shabbat===
When there is an urgent human or medical need which is life-threatening violating the rules is ok. It is also possible to perform seemingly &quot;forbidden&quot; acts by modifying the relevant technology to such an extent that no law is actually violated. An example is the &quot;[[Sabbath elevator]]&quot;. In this mode, an elevator will stop automatically at every floor, allowing people to step on and off without anyone having to press any buttons, which would normally be needed to work. ([[Dynamic braking]] is also disabled if it is normally used, shunting energy collected from downward travel, and thus the gravitational potential energy of passengers, into a [[resistor]] network.) This prevents &quot;violation&quot; of the Shabbat prohibition against doing &quot;useful work.&quot; Many rabbinical authorities consider the use of such elevators by those who are otherwise capable as a &quot;violation&quot; of the Shabbat, with such workarounds being for the benefit of the frail and handicapped and not being in the spirit of the day.

Many observant Jews avoid the prohibition of &quot;carrying&quot; in the absence of an [[eruv]] by making their [[Key (lock)|keys]] into a [[tie bar]], or part of a [[Belt (clothing)|belt]] buckle or [[brooch]]. The key thereby becomes a legitimate article of [[clothing]] or [[Jewellery|jewelry]], which may be worn, rather than carried. Some also use an elastic band which has clips on both ends, and keys are placed between them as an integral link in the band, which may then be considered a belt.

In recent years, the [[Shabbat lamp]] has been developed to allow a light in a room to be turned on/off at will while the electricity remains on. A special mechanism blocks out the light when the off position is desired without violating Shabbat.

==Permitted desecration==
{{details|pikuach nefesh}}
In the event that a human [[life]] is in danger (''[[pikuach nefesh]]''), a Jew is not only allowed, but required,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israel21c.org/briefs/8-saved-during-qshabbat-from-hellq 8 saved during &quot;Shabbat from hell&quot;] (January 17, 2010) in [http://www.israel21c.org/ ''Israel 21c Innovation News Service''] Retrieved 2010–01–18&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3835327,00.html ZAKA rescuemission to Haiti 'proudly desecrating Shabbat'] Religious rescue team holds Shabbat prayer with members of international missions in Port au-Prince. Retrieved 2010–01–22&lt;/ref&gt; to violate any Shabbat law that stands in the way of saving that person, excluding murder, idolatry, and forbidden sexual acts. The concept of life being in danger is interpreted broadly: for example, it is mandated that one violate the Shabbat to bring a woman in active labor to a hospital. Lesser, rabbinic restrictions are often violated under much less urgent circumstances (a patient who is ill but not critically so).

{{cquote2|&quot;We did everything to save lives, despite Shabbat. People asked, 'Why are you here? There are no Jews here', but we are here because the Torah orders us to save lives… We are desecrating Shabbat with pride…&quot;|Mati Goldstein, commander of the Jewish [[ZAKA]] rescue-mission to [[2010 Haiti earthquake]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ynews&quot;&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3835327,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Various other legal principles closely delineate which activities constitute desecration of the Shabbat. Examples of these include the principle of ''shinui'' (&quot;change&quot; or &quot;deviation&quot;): A severe violation becomes a non-severe one if the prohibited act was performed in a way that would be considered abnormal on a weekday. Examples include writing with one's non-dominant hand (according to many rabbinic authorities). This legal principle operates ''bedi'avad'' (''[[ex post facto]]'') and does not cause a forbidden activity to be permitted barring extenuating circumstances.

==Liberal views==
Generally, adherents of [[Reform Judaism|Reform]] and [[Reconstructionist Judaism]] believe that the individual Jew determines whether to follow Shabbat prohibitions or not. For example, some Jews might find activities, such as writing or cooking for [[leisure]], to be enjoyable enhancements to Shabbat and its holiness, and therefore may encourage such practices. Many Reform Jews believe that what constitutes &quot;work&quot; is different for each person, and that only what the person considers &quot;work&quot; is forbidden.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shamash.org/lists/scj-faq/HTML/faq/18-04-17.html|title=Soc.Culture.Jewish Newsgroups Frequently Asked Questions and Answers|page=18.4.7|date=2003-09-04|accessdate=2009-03-27|author=Faigin, Daniel P.|publisher=[[Usenet]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Radical Hungarian-born [[Reform movement in Judaism|Reform]] rabbi Ignaz Einhorn even shifted his congregation's Shabbat worship to Sundays.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Meyer, Michael|title=Response to Modernity: A History of the Reform Movement in Judaism|location=[[New York]]|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=1988|pages=162ff|isbn=0-19-505167-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More rabbinically traditional Reform and Reconstruction Jews believe that these ''halakhot'' in general may be valid, but that it is up to each individual to decide how and when to apply them. A small fraction of Jews, in the Progressive Jewish community, accept these laws much the same way as Orthodox Jews.

==Encouraged activities==
All [[Jewish denominations]] encourage the following activities on Shabbat:
*Reading, studying and discussing [[Torah]] and commentary, [[Mishnah]] and [[Talmud]], learning some [[Halakha]] and [[Midrash]].
*[[Synagogue]] attendance for [[Jewish services|prayers]];
*Spending time with other Jews and socializing with family, friends and guests at Shabbat meals (''hachnasat orchim'', &quot;hospitality&quot;);
*Singing ''[[zemirot]]'', special songs for the Shabbat meal (commonly sung during or after a meal)
*Marital relations between husband and wife&lt;ref&gt;Shulkhan Arukh, Orach Chaim 280:1&lt;/ref&gt;
*Sleeping

==Special Shabbats==
{{main|Special Shabbat}}
The [[Special Shabbat]]s are the Shabbats that precede important [[Jewish holiday]]s: e.g. ''Shabbat ha-Gadol'' is the Shabbat preceding [[Passover]], ''Shabbat Zachor'' is the Shabbat preceding [[Purim]], and ''Shabbat Teshuva'' is the Shabbat preceding Yom Kippur.

==Sabbath adaptation==
{{main|Christian Sabbath}}
Most [[Christian]]s do not observe a Saturday Shabbat, but instead observe a weekly day of worship on [[Sunday]], which is often called the &quot;[[Lord's Day]]&quot;.

Several Christian denominations, such as the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]], the [[Seventh Day Baptist]]s, and the [[True Jesus Church]], observe [[seventh-day Sabbath]]. This observance is celebrated from Friday sunset to Saturday sunset. Some of [[Messianic Judaism]] considers its Sabbath to be kept according to Jewish doctrinal tradition, while most of [[Rabbinic Judaism]] disagrees.

The principle of weekly Sabbath also exists in other beliefs: compare the [[Babylonian calendar]], the [[Buddhist]] ''[[uposatha]]'', the [[Islam]]ic ''[[jumu'ah]]'', the [[Neopagan]] [[Wheel of the Year|sabbat]], the [[Unification Church]] [[Ahn Shi Il]], and the parody-religion [[Pastafarian]] weekend.

==See also==
*[[Baqashot]]
*[[Jewish holidays]]
*[[Jewish services#Prayer on Shabbat (Sabbath)|Jewish services for Sabbath]]
*[[Moed]]
*[[Sabbath breaking]]
*[[Sabbath in Christianity]]
*[[Sabbath mode]]
*[[Shabbos goy]]
*[[Karaite Judaism#The Shabbat|Shabbat in Karaism]]
*[[Sabbath in Seventh-day Adventism]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|sabbath}}
{{Commons category|Shabbat}}
*[http://www.torah.org/advanced/shulchan-aruch/ocarchives.html A detailed summary of the laws of Shabbat] from Torah.org, based on the [[Shulchan Aruch]]
* Admiel Kosman: [http://www.daat.ac.il/daat/ktav_et/maamar.asp?ktavet=2&amp;id=1411 The structure of Hilkhot Shabbat according to RaMBaM and the later halakhic literature].  In: Limudim. Ktav-Et virtualit le-Inyane Hinukh we-Hora`ah, (Sivan 2012), no. 4.


{{Shabbat}}
{{Jewish holidays}}
{{Time in religion and mythology}}

[[Category:Shabbat| ]]
[[Category:Working time]]

{{Link FA|de}}

[[af:Sabbat]]
[[als:Schabbat]]
[[arc:ܫܒܬܐ (ܝܗܘܕܝܘܬܐ)]]
[[ba:Шаббат]]
[[bg:Шабат]]
[[bar:Schabbat]]
[[ca:Sàbat]]
[[ceb:Shabat]]
[[cs:Šabat]]
[[cy:Shabbat]]
[[da:Sabbat]]
[[de:Sabbat]]
[[es:Sabbat]]
[[eo:Ŝabato]]
[[eu:Sabbat]]
[[fa:شبات]]
[[fr:Chabbat]]
[[gl:Shabat]]
[[hak:Ôn-sit-ngit]]
[[ko:안식일]]
[[hr:Šabat]]
[[id:Sabat]]
[[it:Shabbat]]
[[he:שבת]]
[[sw:Sabato]]
[[lv:Sabats]]
[[lt:Šabas]]
[[li:Sabbat]]
[[hu:Nyugalomnap]]
[[ms:Shabbat]]
[[nl:Sjabbat]]
[[ja:安息日]]
[[no:Sabbat (jødisk)]]
[[nn:Sjabbát]]
[[oc:Shabat]]
[[nds:Sabbat]]
[[pl:Szabat]]
[[pt:Shabat]]
[[ro:Șabat]]
[[ru:Шаббат]]
[[simple:Shabbat]]
[[sk:Šabat]]
[[sl:Šabat]]
[[sr:Šabat]]
[[sh:Šabat]]
[[fi:Sapatti]]
[[sv:Sabbat]]
[[tl:Sabado (Hudaismo)]]
[[ta:ஓய்வு நாள் (யூதம்)]]
[[tr:Sebt / Şabat]]
[[uk:Шабат]]
[[yi:שבת]]
[[bat-smg:Šabs]]
[[zh:安息日]]</text>
      <sha1>9e45h9yge32nwf47of6alt03v6aq6rv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
