<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Shofar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>97150</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517727461</id>
      <parentid>516339391</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-14T11:58:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sburke</username>
        <id>163811</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Requesting pronunciation.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26189">{{For|the academic journal|Shofar (journal)}}{{For|the Shofar Organization|Amnon Yitzhak}}
{{Lead too short|date=October 2011}}
[[File:Shofar.JPG|thumb|A small shofar]]
A '''shofar'''{{Pronunciation-needed}}&lt;!-- as IPA --&gt; ({{lang-he|שופר}}) is a [[horn (anatomy)|horn]], traditionally that of a [[sheep|ram]], used for [[Judaism|Jewish]] religious purposes. Shofar-blowing is incorporated in [[synagogue]] services on [[Rosh Hashanah]] and [[Yom Kippur]].
Shofar come in a variety of sizes.

== Bible and rabbinic literature ==
{{Refimprove section|date=February 2012}}
[[File:AlphonseLévy Shofar.jpg|left|thumb|Shofar (by Alphonse Lévy) Caption says: &quot;To a good year&quot;]]
The ''shofar'' is mentioned frequently in the [[Hebrew Bible]], the [[Talmud]] and [[rabbinic literature]]. The blast of a shofar emanating from the thick cloud on [[Biblical Mount Sinai|Mount Sinai]] made the [[Israelites]] tremble in awe (Exodus 19:16).

The shofar was used to announce holidays (Ps. lxxxi. 4), and the [[Jubilee (biblical)|Jubilee year]] (Lev. 25:9). The first day of the seventh month ([[Tishri]]) is termed &quot;a memorial of blowing&quot; (Lev. 23:24), or &quot;a day of blowing&quot; (Num. 29:1), the shofar. They were for signifying the start of a war (Josh. 6:4; Judges 3:27; 7:16, 20; I Sam. 8:3). Later, it was also employed in processions (II Sam. 6:15; I Chron. 15:28), as musical accompaniment (Ps. 98:6; comp. ib. 47:5) and eventually it was inserted into the temple orchestra by David (Ps. 150:3). Note that the 'trumpets' described in Numbers 10 are a different instrument, described by the Hebrew word 'trumpet' ({{lang-he|חצוצרה}}; ḥaṣoṣrah), not the word for shofar ({{lang-he|שופר}}).

The [[Torah]] describes the first day of the seventh month (1st of Tishri = Rosh ha-Shanah) as a ''zikron teruˁah'' ({{lang-he|זכרון תרועה}}; memorial of blowing; Lev. xxiii) and as a ''yom teruˁah'' ({{lang-he|יום תרועה}}; day of blowing; Num. 29). This was interpreted by the Jewish sages as referring to the sounding of the shofar.

In the [[Temple in Jerusalem]], the shofar was sometimes used together with the [[trumpet]]. On New Year's Day the principal ceremony was conducted with the shofar, which instrument was placed in the center with a trumpet on either side; it was the horn of a [[wild goat]] and straight in shape, being ornamented with gold at the [[mouthpiece (brass)|mouthpiece]]. On fast days the principal ceremony was conducted with the trumpets in the center and with a shofar on either side. On those occasions the shofarot were [[Domestic Sheep|rams' horns]] curved in shape and ornamented with silver at the mouthpieces. On Yom Kippur of the [[Jubilee (Biblical)|jubilee year]] the ceremony was performed with the shofar as on New Year's Day. 

On Rosh Hashanah and other full holidays (Day of Atonement, Ingathering of the harvest ([[Sukkot]]), Passover and the Feast of Weeks – Pentecost) a single Priest perfected two sacrifices in honor of the full holiday, (Note that festivals such as Hanukah and Purim, are not considered full holidays requiring an extra sacrifice). On Rosh Hashanah, something special occurred during the special sacrifice. Arguably two Shofar Sounders played the long notes and one Trumpet player played the short note. Accordingly, Rosh HaShanah is called Yom Teruah (the day of the blast) Otherwise, the Trumpets had &quot;top billing.&quot; Rosh Hashanah27a, supports this claim: &quot;Said Raba or it may have been R. Joshua B. Levi: What is the scriptural warrant for this? – Because it is written, &quot;With trumpets and the sound of the Shofar shout ye before the King in the Temple, we require trumpets and the sound of the Shofar; elsewhere not.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Sidney B. Hoenig, Origins of the Rosh Hashanah Liturgy, The Jewish Quarterly Review, New Series, Vol. 57, The Seventy-Fifth Anniversary Volume of the Jewish Quarterly Review (1967), pp. 312-331. •  Published by: University of Pennsylvania Press. http://www.jstor.org/stable/1453499. Accessed December 31, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Indeed, on Yom Kippur, the Shofar was sounded to announce the [[Jubilee (biblical)|Jubilee Year]] (every 50 years, Jews were granted  forgiveness, debts were forgiven, indentured Israelites were granted freedom, and the fields &quot;shall become owned by the priests.&quot; Shofar first indicated in Yovel (Jubilee Year -  Lev. 25:8-13). Indeed, in Rosh Hashanah 33b, the sages ask why the Shofar sounded in Jubilee year.  Further support{{clarify|post-text=support of what?|date=February 2012}} is found in Rosh Hashanah 29a, where the Talmud talks of trumpets for sacrifices but Shofar in the Jubilee Year does not apply to priests who are exempt from the obligations of the jubilee. Perhaps,{{cn|date=February 2012}} we have the first mention of Shofar Sounding by non-Priests. Perhaps the first distancing away from the Sacrificial Cult.{{cn|date=February 2012}}

Otherwise, for all other special days, the Shofar is sounded shorter and two special silver Trumpets announced the sacrifice. When the trumpets sound the signal, all the people who were within the sacrifice prostrate themselves, stretching out flat, face down and on the ground.

The shofar was blown in the times of [[Joshua]] to help him capture [[Jericho]]. As they surrounded the walls, the shofar was blown and the Jews were able to capture the city. The shofar was commonly taken out to war so the troops would know when a battle would begin. The person who would blow the shofar would call out to the troops from atop a hill. All of the troops were able to hear the call of the shofar from their position because of its distinct sound.{{cn|date=February 2012}}

=== Post-Biblical times ===

In [[post-Biblical]] times, the shofar was enhanced in its religious use because of the ban on playing musical instruments as a sign of mourning for the destruction of the temple. (It is noted that a full orchestra played in the temple.) The shofar continues to announce the New Year,&lt;ref&gt;Kitzur Shulchan Aruch 128:2&lt;/ref&gt; and the new moon,{{Dubious|date=November 2011}}, to introduce [[Shabbat]],{{Dubious|date=November 2011}} to carry out the commandment to sound it on Rosh Hashanah, and to mark the end of the day of fasting on Yom Kippur once the services have completed in the evening.&lt;ref&gt;Kitzur Shulchan Aruch 133:26&lt;/ref&gt; Secular uses have been discarded (see a notable exception in a section [[#National liberation|further down]]).&lt;ref&gt;Judith Kaplan Eisenstein, Heritage of Music, New York: UAHC, 1972, pp. 44–45.&lt;/ref&gt;

The shofar is primarily associated with Rosh Hashanah. Indeed, Rosh Hashanah is called &quot;Yom T’ruah&quot; (or &quot;Yom Teruah&quot;) (the day of the shofar blast). In the [[Mishnah]] (book of early rabbinic laws derived from the [[Torah]]), a discussion centers on the centrality of the shofar in the time before the destruction of the second temple (70 AD). Indeed, the shofar was the center of the ceremony, with two silver trumpets playing a lesser role. On other solemn holidays, fasts, and new moon celebrations, two silver trumpets were featured, with one shofar playing a lesser role. The shofar is also associated with the [[Jubilee (biblical)|jubilee year]] in which, every fifty years, Jewish law provided for the release of all slaves, land, and debts. The sound of the shofar on Rosh Hashanah announced the jubilee year, and the sound of the shofar on Yom Kippur proclaimed the actual release of financial encumbrances.

The [[halakha]] (Jewish law) rules that the shofar may not be sounded on Shabbat due to the potential that the ba’al tekiyah (shofar sounder) may inadvertently carry it which is in a class of forbidden Shabbat work.&lt;ref&gt;Rosh HaSHannah 29b&lt;/ref&gt; The historical explanation is that in ancient Israel, the shofar was sounded on Shabbat in the temple located in Jerusalem. After the temple’s destruction, the sounding of the shofar on Shabbat was restricted to the place where the great [[Sanhedrin]] (Jewish legislature and court from 400 BCE to 100 C.E.) was located. However, when the Sanhedrin ceased to exist, the sounding of the shofar on Shabbat was discontinued.&lt;ref&gt;Kieval, The High Holy Days, p.&amp;nbsp;114&lt;/ref&gt;

The shofar says, &quot;Awake, sleepers
from your sleep, and slumberers arise from your slumber!&quot;  Mishneh Torah, Laws of Repentance 3:4.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.divreinavon.com/pdf/Anticipation_Consummation.pdf The Shofar: Impetus to Anticipation &amp; Consummation&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mitzvah ===

The Sages indicated that the [[mitzvah]] was to hear the sounds of the shofar. They went so far as to consider a shofar blown into a pit or cave and to decide whether a person who hears the original sound or the echo has fulfilled the mitzvah. Mishnah (Rosh Hashanah 27b). The Shulchan Aruch sums up that if the hearer hears the reverberation, the mitzvah is not valid. However, if the listener perceives the direct sounds, he fulfils the mitzvah.&lt;ref&gt;Mishnah Berurah 587:1–3&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, most modern halakhic authorities hold that hearing a shofar on the radio or the Internet would not be valid to satisfy the mitzvah because &quot;electronically reproduced sounds do not suffice for mitzvot that require hearing a specific natural sound. . . . However, one should consult a competent rabbi if an unusually pressing situation arises, as some authorities believe that performing mitzvot through electronically reproduced sound is preferable to not performing them at all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.yasharbooks.com/Gray.html Chaim Jachter and Ezra Frazer, Gray Matter volume 2 [http://www.yasharbooks.com/grayexcerpt2.pdf pp. 237-244], &quot;Fulfilling Mitzvot Through Electronic Hearing Devices&quot;. ISBN 1-933143-10-X&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[halakha|Jewish law]] women and minors are exempt from the commandment of hearing the shofar blown (as is the case with any positive, time-bound commandment), but they are encouraged to attend the ceremony.

If the Baal Tekiyah (shofar sounder) blows with the intention that all who hear will perform the mitzvah, then anyone listening—even someone passing by—who intends to hear the Shofar can perform the mitzvah because the community blower blows for everybody. If the listener stands still, it is presumed he intends to hear.&lt;ref&gt;Mishnah Berurah 590:9&lt;/ref&gt; If one hears the blast but with no intention of fulfilling the mitzvah, then the mitzvah has not been fulfilled.

=== Qualifications ===

The expert who blows (or &quot;blasts&quot; or &quot;sounds&quot;) the shofar is termed the ''Tokea'' (lit. &quot;Blaster&quot;) or ''Ba'al T'qiah'' (lit. &quot;Master of the Blast&quot;). Being a Ba'al T'qiah (shofar sounder) is an honor. Every male Jew is eligible for this sacred office, providing he is acceptable to the congregation. &quot;The one who blows the shofar on Rosh Hashanah . . . should likewise be learned in the Torah and shall be God-fearing; the best man available.&quot; If a potential choice will cause dissension, he should withdraw his candidacy, even if the improper person will be chosen.&lt;ref&gt;[[Shulkhan Arukh]] 3:72&lt;/ref&gt; If a blind blower was dismissed, but the community did not find a blower as proficient, he should be appointed as community blower.

The Shulchan Aruch discusses who is fit to blow the shofar on behalf of a congregation: 
* Anyone not obligated to fulfill the mitzvah of sounding the shofar cannot fulfill the commandment for (cover) another whose duty it is to perform the mitzvah.
* Although a woman (who is exempt from this mitzvah because it is time bound) may not blow the shofar for men (whose duty it is to perform the mitzvah), a female ''Ba'alat'' T'qiah may intone the shofar for herself and other women. Similarly, she may say a blessing over the mitzvah even though it is not mandatory (the requisite blessing contains the words &quot;asher kid'shanu b'mitzvotav v’tzivanu&quot;, &quot;who sanctified us with His commandments [mitzvot] and commanded us to ...&quot;, but women are not commanded in this mitzvah).
* Only a freeman (not even a slave who will become free in the next month) can be a Ba'al T'qiah.&lt;ref&gt;Shulchan Aruch, Orach Chaim 589:1-6&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Ba'al T'qiah'' shall abstain from anything that may cause ritual contamination for three days prior to Rosh Hashanah.&lt;ref&gt;[[Shulkhan Arukh]] 3:73&lt;/ref&gt;

== Shape and material ==
=== Choice of animal ===

[[File:2005 04 27 1582 Dall Sheep.jpg|thumb|right|A [[Dall sheep|Dall Sheep]] with horns.]]According to the Talmud, a shofar may be made from the horn of any animal from the [[Bovid]]ae family except that of a cow &lt;ref&gt;Rosh Hashanah, 26a&lt;/ref&gt; although a ram is preferable.&lt;ref&gt;Mishnah Berurah 586:1&lt;/ref&gt; Bovidae horns are made of [[keratin]] (the same material as human toenails and fingernails). An [[antler]], on the other hand, is not a horn but solid bone. Antlers cannot be used as a shofar because they cannot be hollowed out.

There is no requirement for ritual slaughter (shechita), and theoretically, the horn can come from a non-kosher animal because under most interpretations of Jewish law the shofar is not required to be ''muttar be-fikha'' (literally: permissible in your mouth); the [[mitzvah]] is hearing the shofar, not eating the animal it came from.&lt;ref&gt;Mois Navon, “The Hillazon and the Principle of ‘Mutter be-Fikha’”, The Torah u-Madda Journal, October 2001, www.yutorah.org/_shiurim/%2FTU10_Navon.pdf, March 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The shofar falls into the category of ''tashmishei mitzvah'', objects used to perform a mitzvah that do not themselves have inherent holiness.&lt;ref&gt;Megillah 26b&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, because horn is always inedible, it is considered ''afra be-alma'' (mere dust) and not an unkosher substance.&lt;ref&gt;Avot 67b&lt;/ref&gt;

The Elef Hamagan (586:5) delineates the order of preference: 1) curved ram; 2) curved other sheep; 3) curved other animal; 4) straight—ram or otherwise; 5) non-kosher animal; 6) cow. The first four categories are used with a ''bracha'' (blessing), the fifth without a ''bracha'', and the last, not at all.&lt;ref&gt;Elef Hamagen, Rabbi Shemarya Hakreti, edited by Aharon Erand, Jerusalem: Mekitzei Nirdamim, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Construction ===

[[File:Jemenittisk sjofar av kuduhorn.jpg|thumb|left|256px|A shofar made from the horn of a [[Greater kudu]], in the [[Teimanim|Yemenite Jewish]] style.]]
In practice two species are generally used: the [[Ashkenazi]] and [[Sefardi]] shofar is made from the horn of a domestic [[sheep|ram]], while a Yemeni shofar is made from the horn of a [[Greater Kudu|kudu]]. A Moroccan Shofar is a flat Shofar with no curves besides the main curve.
A crack or hole in the shofar affecting the sound renders it unfit for ceremonial use. A shofar may not be painted in colors, but it may be carved with artistic designs ([[Shulkhan Arukh]], [[Orach Chayim]], 586, 17). Shofars (especially the Sephardi shofars) are sometimes plated with silver across part of their length for display purposes, although this invalidates them for use in religious practices.

The horn is flattened and shaped by the application of heat, which softens it. A hole is made from the tip of the horn to the natural hollow inside. It is played much like a [[Europe]]an [[brass instrument]], with the player blowing through the hole, causing the air column inside to vibrate. [[Sephardi]] shofars usually have a carved mouthpiece resembling that of a European [[trumpet]] or [[Horn (instrument)|French horn]], but smaller. Ashkenazi shofars do not. 

Because the hollow of the shofar is irregular in shape, the [[harmonic]]s obtained when playing the instrument can vary: rather than a pure perfect fifth, [[interval (music)|intervals]] as narrow as a fourth, or as wide as a sixth may be produced.

== Sounds ==
[[File:ShofarSound.JPG|thumb|right|A man demonstrates sounding a shofar at a synagogue in Minnesota.]]

=== Biblical commandment ===

The ''T'qiah'' and ''teruah'' sounds mentioned in the [[Bible]] were respectively [[Bass (sound)|bass]] and [[Treble (sound)|treble]].{{speculation-inline}} The t'qiah was a plain deep sound ending abruptly; the teruah, a [[trill (music)|trill]] between two t'qiahs. These two sounds, constituting a single unit of shofar sounding, were rendered three times during a service added specially for [[Rosh HaShanah]]: first in honor of [[God]]'s Kingship (malchiot); next to recall the [[Binding of Isaac|near sacrifice of Isaac]], in order to cause the congregation to be remembered before [[God]] (zichronot); and a third time to comply with the precept regarding the shofar (shofrot).{{Citation needed|date=November 2011}}

The word t'ruah (a broken sound) appears three times in the Bible in the context of the shofar, from which the Talmud&lt;ref&gt;Rosh HaShannah 34a&lt;/ref&gt; derives the rule that three such sounds must be made. In addition, other verses connect the word t'qiah (an unbroken sound) to t'ruah twice, thus leading the Talmud to rule that each t'ruah must be preceded and followed by a t'qiah, leading to a total of nine blasts (t'qiah-teruah-t'qiah three times).

Over time doubts arose as to the correct sound of the teruah. The [[Talmud]] is uncertain whether it means a moaning/groaning or a [[staccato]] beat sound.&lt;ref&gt;Rosh HaShannah 34a&lt;/ref&gt; A system of three sounds was therefore devised to account for all the possibilities:
* ''Sh'varim'' is composed of three connected short sounds.
* ''Teruah'' is a series of nine very short notes divided into three disconnected or broken sequences of three notes each. The nine notes of the teruah is equal the three notes of the sh'varim in duration.
* ''T'qiah'' is slightly longer than the length of either the sh'varim or the teruah.&lt;ref&gt;Mishnah Berurah 590:13&lt;/ref&gt; 

The doubt as to the nature of the Biblical teruah, whether it was simply a broken moan (sh'varim), a staccato (teruah) or both (sh'varim-teruah), necessitates three near-repetitions to make sure of securing the correct sound. The sequence of the shofar blowing is thus:
# T'qiah, sh'varim-t'ruah, t'qiah
# T'qiah, sh'varim, t'qiah
# T'qiah, teruah, and then a final blast of 't'qiah g'dolah which means &quot;big tekiah,&quot; held as long as possible. 

This series is also known by its acronyms: ''TaShRaT, TaShaT, TaRaT,'' respectively.

When blowing the sh'varim-teruah, the t'qiah is lengthened to be slightly longer the duration of the sh'varim and the teruah together.&lt;ref&gt;Mishnah Berurah 590:14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kitzur Shulchan Aruch 129:13&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some opinions require trebling the series, based on the mention of teruah three times in connection with the seventh month (Lev. xxiii, xxv; Num. xxix), and also on the above-mentioned division of the service into malchiyot, zichronot, and shofarot.

To fulfill all of the opinions and criteria above, a total of thirty blasts are sounded, the minimum number required today:
* Tashrat three times, yielding twelve blasts
* Tashat three times, yielding nine
* Tarat three times, yielding nine

Alternatively, although fewer opinions are satisfied, some communities sound a single series of ''Tashrat-Tashat-Tarat'' without trebling. This may also fulfill the required total of thirty blasts, if t'qiah is counted as one note, sh'varim three, and teruah nine.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Shofar-Call to Action.&quot; Chabad.org. &lt;http://www.chabad.org/holidays/JewishNewYear/template_cdo/aid/4837/jewish/Shofar.htm&gt;. Accessed 6 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Regardless, all halachic authorities&lt;ref&gt;Kitzur Shulchan Aruch 129:17, et al.&lt;/ref&gt; teach that one should follow one's community's custom.

=== Modern practice ===

It is customary to hear 100 or 101 sounds in the synagogue, although the minimum requirement is to hear 30 sounds.

The shofar is sounded just before, during and after the [[Musaf]] prayer on [[Rosh HaShanah]]. For the sounding just before Musaf, after the Torah reading, relevant verses from the Bible are recited, followed by two blessings: one on the Biblical commandment of &quot;hearing the sound of the shofar&quot; and the blessing of [[Shehecheyanu]]. After that, thirty shofar blasts are sounded. In the [[Musaf]] prayer itself, the shofar is sounded three times during the silent prayer, and then again three times during the leader's repetition. For each of these soundings, ten appropriate selections from the Bible are recited, followed by a benediction, followed finally by a series of ten shofar blasts. After leader's repetition of the Musaf prayer is completed, a final series of ten (or eleven, depending on the community's custom) shofar blasts are sounded, yielding a total of 100 or 101 blasts. (Some communities do not blow the shofar during the silent Musaf prayer, instead blowing the 30 blasts after the leader's repetition.) After the service is over, it is customary to blow another series of thirty blasts &quot;to confuse the [[Satan|Adversary]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;machzor-arizal&quot;&gt;Siddur im Dach, pp. 493; Machzor l'Rosh HaShanah al pi Nusach HaArizal, et al.&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
According to the Sephardic tradition, a full 101 blasts are sounded, corresponding to the 100 cries of the [[mother of Sisera]], the captain of [[Jabin|Jabin's]] army who did not return home after being killed by the [[Yael]] (Judges 5:28). One cry is added to symbolize the legitimate love of a mother mourning her son.&lt;ref&gt;Kitov, Eliyahu. &quot;One Hundred Sounds.&quot; Chabad.org. &lt;http://www.chabad.org/holidays/JewishNewYear/template_cdo/aid/4387/jewish/100-Sounds.htm&gt;. Accessed 6 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Use in modern times ==
=== Religion ===

The shofar is used mainly on [[Rosh Hashanah]] and [[Yom Kippur]]. It is blown in [[synagogue]]s to mark the end of the fast at Yom Kippur, and blown at four particular occasions in the prayers on Rosh Hashanah. Because of its inherent ties to the Days of Repentance and the inspiration that comes along with hearing its piercing blasts, the shofar is also blown after morning services for the entire month of [[Elul]], the last month of the Jewish civil year and the sixth of the Jewish ecclesiastical year. It is not blown on the last day of month, however, to mark the difference between the voluntary blasts of the month and the mandatory blasts of the holiday. Shofar blasts are also used during penitential rituals such as [[Yom Kippur Katan]] and optional prayer services called during times of communal distress. The exact modes of sounding can vary from location to location.

In an effort to improve the skills of shofar blowers, an [http://www.shofarcorps.org International Day of Shofar Study] is observed on Rosh Chodesh Elul, the start of the month preceding Rosh Hashanah.

=== National liberation ===

During the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] and the [[United Kingdom|British]] rule of [[Jerusalem]], Jews were not allowed to sound the shofar at the [[Western Wall]]. After the [[Six Day War]], Rabbi [[Shlomo Goren]] famously approached the Wall and sounded the shofar. This fact inspired [[Naomi Shemer]] to add an additional line to her song ''[[Jerusalem of Gold]]'', saying: &quot;a shofar calls out from the [[Temple Mount]] in [[Old City (Jerusalem)|The Old City]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jerusalemofgold.co.il/ JERUSALEM OF GOLD] accessed 9 Dec. 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Non-religious musical usage ===
[[File:Alvin Curran plays shofar at CJM window 2009.jpg|thumb|Alvin Curran plays shofar at CJMSF window 2009]]
The shofar is sometimes used in Western [[european classical music|classical music]]. [[Edward Elgar]]'s [[oratorio]] ''[[The Apostles (Elgar)|The Apostles]]'' includes the sound of a shofar blowing, although other instruments, such as the [[flugelhorn]], are usually used instead.

In pop music, the shofar is used by the Israeli [[Oriental metal]] band [[Salem (Israel band)|Salem]] in their adaptation of &quot;''Al Taster''&quot; [[psalm]]. The late trumpeter [[Lester Bowie]] played a shofar with the [[Art Ensemble of Chicago]]. In the film version of the musical ''[[Godspell (film)|Godspell]]'', the first act opens with cast member [[David Haskell]] blowing the shofar. In his performances, Israeli composer and singer [[Shlomo Gronich]] uses the shofar to produce a very wide range of notes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abrahamfund.org/main/siteNew/index.php?page=129&amp;action=sidLink&amp;stId=1131 The Abraham Fund Initiatives::Press Clips - Crossing the Middle Eastern Tightrope&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1988 Rome-based American composer [[Alvin Curran]]'s project ''Shofar'' features the shofar as a virtuoso solo instrument and in combination with sets of natural and electronic sounds. In [[Jerry Goldsmith]]'s scores to the film [[Alien (film)|''Alien'']] and Planet of the Apes, the shofar is part of the orchestration. [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] used a shofar played by  [[Yitzhak Sinwani]] on the ''Confessions Tour'' and the album  [[Confessions on a Dance Floor]] for the song ''Isaac'', based on [[Im Nin'alu]].

== See also ==
* [[Rosh Hashanah]]
* [[Binding of Isaac]]
* [[Dung-Dkar]]
* [[Shankha]]

== Further reading ==
* Arthur l. Finkle, [http://web.archive.org/web/20091026132651/http://geocities.com/afinkle221 Shofar Sounders Reference Manual], LA: Torah Aura, 1993

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
* Arthur L. Finkle, ''Easy Guide to Shofar Sounding'', LA: Torah Aura, 2003
* [http://www.hearingshofar.com] ''Hearing Shofar: The Still Small Voice of the Ram's Horn'' by Michael T. Chusid, a three volume compendium of shofar information.

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Shofar}}
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Shofar}}
* [http://www.shulchanarach.com/ ''Shulkhan Arukh''] limited English translation includes Rosh Hashanah chapters 585-590 regarding the shofar.


{{High Holidays}}
{{Jewish life}}
[[Category:Ancient Hebrew musical instruments]]
[[Category:Natural horns]]
[[Category:Hebrew words and phrases]]
[[Category:High Holy Days]]
[[Category:Jewish ritual objects]]
[[Category:Rosh Hashanah]]
[[Category:Israeli musical instruments]]
[[Category:Animal products]]

[[ar:شوفار]]
[[bg:Шофар]]
[[bar:Schofar]]
[[ca:Xofar]]
[[cs:Šofar]]
[[da:Shofar]]
[[de:Schofar]]
[[es:Shofar]]
[[fa:شوفار]]
[[fr:Chophar]]
[[id:Shofar]]
[[it:Shofar]]
[[he:שופר]]
[[hu:Sófár]]
[[ms:Shofar]]
[[nl:Sjofar]]
[[ja:ショファー]]
[[no:Sjofar]]
[[nn:Sjofár]]
[[oc:Shofar]]
[[pl:Szofar]]
[[pt:Shofar]]
[[qu:Kipa]]
[[ru:Шофар]]
[[sl:Šofar]]
[[fi:Šofar]]
[[sv:Shofar]]
[[tr:Şofar]]
[[uk:Шофар]]
[[yi:תקיעת שופר]]</text>
      <sha1>evjxxn9x91yq4e882ht6rmf81riabcq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
