<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Shrine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>465979</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521697453</id>
      <parentid>521697437</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T17:42:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/213.120.33.138|213.120.33.138]] to version by 64.30.125.105. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1318400) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22808">{{Dablink|Note: &quot;shrine&quot; is also used as a conventional translation of the &quot;Jinja&quot; ([[Shinto shrine]]).}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2011}}
[[File:Gorskii 03982u.jpg|thumb|180px|The shrine of the [[Hodegetria]] at the [[Assumption Cathedral in Smolensk]], [[Russia]], photographed by [[Sergey Prokudin-Gorsky]] (1912).]]
[[File:shrine at repulse bay to tin hau.jpg|thumb|180px|Shrine to [[Mazu (goddess)|Tin Hau]] at [[Repulse Bay]], [[Southern District, Hong Kong|Southern District]], [[Hong Kong]].]]
[[File:John William Waterhouse - The Shrine.JPG|thumb|180px|right|''The Shrine'', [[Oil painting|Oil on canvas]], by [[John William Waterhouse]] (1895).]]

A '''shrine''' ({{lang-la|scrinium}} &quot;case or chest for books or papers&quot;; [[Old French]]: ''escrin'' &quot;box or case&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=shrine&amp;searchmode=none Etymology Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt; is a holy or sacred place, which is dedicated to a specific [[deity]], [[ancestor worship|ancestor]], [[hero]], [[martyr]], [[saint]], [[Daemon (mythology)|daemon]] or similar figure of awe and respect, at which they are [[veneration|venerated]] or [[worship]]ped. Shrines often contain [[Cult image|idol]]s, [[relic]]s, or other such objects associated with the figure being venerated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefreedictionary.com/shrine Definition of shrine]&lt;/ref&gt; A shrine at which [[votive offering]]s are made is called an [[altar]]. Shrines are found in many of the world's religions, including [[Christianity]], [[Islam]], [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]], [[Wicca]], [[Chinese folk religion]] and [[Shinto]], as well as in secular and non-religious settings such as a war memorial.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-149256642.html Aso wants Yasukuni as nonreligious war memorial]&lt;/ref&gt; Shrines can be found in various settings, such as [[Church (building)|churches]], [[temple]]s, [[cemetery|cemeteries]], or in the home, although [[portable shrine]]s are also found in some cultures.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/asia/p/portable_shrine.aspx British Museum Portable Tibetan Shrine]&lt;/ref&gt;

A shrine may become a focus of a [[cult image]].

==Types of shrines==
[[File:Bankfield Museum 024.jpg|thumb|left|150px|[[China|Chinese]] [[Buddhism|Buddhist]] household shrine 1850–1860, [[Bankfield Museum]]]]

===Temple shrines===
Many shrines are located within buildings designed specifically for worship, such as a [[Church (building)|church]] in Christianity, or a [[Hindu temple|mandir]] in Hinduism. A shrine here is usually the centre of attention in the building, and is given a place of prominence. In such cases, adherents of the faith assemble within the building in order to venerate the deity at the shrine.

===Household shrines===
Historically, in [[Hinduism]], [[Buddhism]] and [[Roman Catholicism]], and also in modern faiths, such as [[Neopaganism]], a shrine can commonly be found within the home or shop.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.downtownexpress.com/de_198/buddhistshrines.html Shrines in shops in Chinatown]&lt;/ref&gt; This shrine is usually a small structure or a setup of pictures and figurines dedicated to a deity that is part of the official religion, to [[ancestor worship|ancestors]] or to a localised [[household deity]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gualalaarts.org/Exhibits/Gallery/2009-10HouseholdShrines.html Gualala Arts – Household Shrines]&lt;/ref&gt;

Small household shrines are very common among the [[Chinese people|Chinese]] and people from [[South Asia|South]] and [[Southeast Asia]], whether Hindu, Buddhist or Christian. Usually a small lamp and small offerings are kept daily by the shrine. Buddhist household shrines must be on a shelf above the head; Chinese shrines must stand directly on the floor.

===Yard shrines===
Small outdoor yard shrines are found at the places of many peoples, following various religions, including historically, [[Idolatry in Christianity|Christianity]]. Many consist of a statue of [[Christ]] or a [[saint]], on a pedestal or in an alcove, while others may be elaborate booths without ceilings, some include paintings, statuary, and architectural elements, such as walls, roofs, glass doors and ironwork fences, etc.

In the United States, some Christians have small yard shrines; some of these resemble side altars, since they are composed of a statue placed in a niche or [[grotto]]; this type is colloquially referred to as a ''[[bathtub madonna]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholichomeandgarden.com/front_yard_shrines.htm Front Yard Shrines]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious shrines==
Shrines are found in most, though not all, religions. As distinguished from a [[temple]], a shrine usually houses a particular [[relic]] or [[cult image]], which is the object of [[worship]] or [[veneration]], or is constructed to set apart a site which is thought to be particularly holy, as opposed to being placed for the convenience of worshippers. Shrines therefore attract the practice of [[pilgrimage]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-destinations.com/sacred-sites/catholic-shrines.htm Sacred Destinations]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uga.edu/islam/turkmen.html Shrine Pilgrimage in Turkmenistan]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
Shrines are found in many, though not all, forms of [[Christianity]]. [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]], the largest denomination of Christianity,&lt;ref&gt;[[Roman Catholic Church|Wikipedia Roman Catholic Church]]&lt;/ref&gt; has many shrines, as do [[Orthodox Christianity]] and [[Anglicanism]].

[[File:Bac.Catherine.Cercueil.jpg|thumb|Catholic shrine: glass coffin of [[Catherine Labouré|Saint Catherine Labouré]]]]
In the [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] Code of [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Canon law]], canons 1230 and 1231 read: &quot;The term shrine means a church or other sacred place which, with the approval of the local [[Ordinary (officer)|Ordinary]], is by reason of special [[Catholic devotions|devotion]] frequented by the faithful as [[pilgrim]]s. For a [[National Shrine|shrine to be described as national]], the approval of the [[Episcopal Conference]] is necessary. For it to be described as international, the approval of the [[Holy See]] is required.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ourladyswarriors.org/canon/c1205-1253.htm Sacred Places]&lt;/ref&gt;

Another use of the term &quot;shrine&quot; in colloquial Catholic terminology is a niche or alcove in most – especially larger – churches used by parishioners when praying privately in the church. They were also called [[Altar|Devotional Altar]]s, since they could look like small [[Altar|Side Altar]]s or [[bye-altar]]s. Shrines were always centered on some image of Christ or a saint – for instance, a statue, painting, mural or mosaic, and may have had a [[reredos]] behind them (without a [[Church tabernacle|Tabernacle]] built in).

However, [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]] would not be celebrated at them; they were simply used to aid or give a visual focus for prayers. Side altars, where Mass could actually be celebrated, were used in a similar way to shrines by parishioners. Side altars were specifically dedicated to [[Blessed Virgin Mary|The Virgin Mary]], [[Saint Joseph]] as well as other saints.

A [[Nativity scene|nativity set]] could also be viewed as a shrine, as the definition of a shrine is any holy or sacred place.

===Islam===

==== Sunni Islam ====
According to the classical chief sources of legislation and jurisprudence in orthodox Sunni Islam, primarily the [[Quran]] and [[Hadith]] texts (and notably the practice of the [[Salafi]] school of thought and early Muslims), it is understood to be totally forbidden to build structures over graves based on the legal evidences where the Prophet Muhammad ordered to demolish all the structures over graves and forbade acts of worship at the graveyards (aside from the funeral prayer) including calling upon other than Allah. It is commonly misunderstood that the grave of the Prophet is an exception to this rule however historically the grave was originally located in the home of [[Aisha]] and the Mosque was extended over and the grave incorporated due to lack of space for the growing number of worshipers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://islamqa.info/en/ref/65944
 | title=Why is the Prophet’s grave in his mosque even though it is forbidden to take graves as places of worship?
 | publisher=Islamqa.info}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Flickr - omar chatriwala - Greeting the prophet.jpg|thumb|180px|Muslims stop to offer greetings at the grave of the Prophet [[Muhammad]] in [[Medina]]'s [[Al-Masjid al-Nabawi|Al Masjid al Nabawi]]]]
* It was narrated that Abu’l-Hayaaj al-Asadi said: ‘Ali ibn Abi Taalib said to me: “Shall I not send you on the same mission as the Messenger of Allah sent me? Do not leave any statue without erasing it, and do not leave any raised grave without leveling it.”  (Narrated by Muslim, 969).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last = Muslim
 | first =
 | title = Muslim, 969
 | publisher = 
 | year =
 | page = 
 | isbn =  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
* It was narrated that he (peace and blessings of Allaah be upon him) said: “May Allah curse the Jews and the Christians, for they took the graves of their Prophets as places of worship.” ‘Aa’ishah (may Allaah be pleased with her) said, “He was warning against what they had done.” (Narrated by al-Bukhaari, 1330 and by Muslim, 529).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last = Bukhari
 | first =
 | title = Bukhari, 1330
 | publisher = 
 | year =
 | page = 
 | isbn =  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last = Muslim
 | first =
 | title = Muslim, 529
 | publisher = 
 | year =
 | page = 
 | isbn =  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

* And when Umm Salamah and Umm Habeebah told him about a church in which there were images, he (peace and blessings of Allaah be upon him) said: “When a righteous man died among them, they would build a place of worship over his grave and put those images in it. They are the most evil of mankind before Allaah.” (Saheeh, agreed upon. Narrated by al-Bukhari, 427 and by Muslim, 528).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last = Muslim
 | first =
 | title = Muslim, 528
 | publisher = 
 | year =
 | page = 
 | isbn =  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last = Bukhari
 | first =
 | title = Bukhari, 427
 | publisher = 
 | year =
 | page = 
 | isbn =  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

* And he (peace and blessings of Allaah be upon him) said: “Those who came before you took the graves of their Prophets and righteous people as places of worship. Do not take graves as places of worship – I forbid you to do that.” (Narrated in his Saheeh by Muslim, 532, from Jundab ibn ‘Abd-Allaah al-Bajali).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
 | last = Muslim
 | first =
 | title = Muslim, 532
 | publisher = 
 | year =
 | page = 
 | isbn =  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

* From Surah Al Jinn (72:18) &quot;The places of worship are for Allah (alone): So do not invoke anyone beside Allah.&quot;

There is a clear prohibition of raising the grave in the name of venerating the dead as it may lead to Shirk such as accounted in the story of the people of [[Noah]], from Surah An Nuh 71: 23 it is quoted;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“And they have said: ‘You shall not leave your gods, nor shall you leave Wadd, nor Suwâ’, nor Yaghûth, nor Ya’ûq, nor Nasr (these are the names of their idols).&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Ibn Abbas commented on this saying, ''“These are the names of the pious people from among them. Following their deaths, Shaytan inspired their people to erect status in the place where they used to sit, and to call them with their names. They did so, however at this point, they were not worshiped until that generation died and the new generation deviated.”''&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[File:Data Durbar.jpg|thumb|180px|The Data Durbar Shrine Lahore Pakistan.]]
However in contrast to this, throughout parts of the Islamic world there has developed a deep cultural tradition of shrine veneration. Although classically in orthodox Islam it is prohibited to worship or engage in acts of worship surrounding graves; various movements and sects took the stance that it is permitted to supplicate with the 'Tawasul' or intercession of the deceased pious person (Sufi/Wali). For these groups, shrines hold a notable position and considered as places to seek spiritual guidance. Most venerated shrines are dedicated to various [[Sufi]] Saints and are widely scattered throughout the Islamic world. For them it is seen as a tradition to commemorate the death of the Saint, by holding festivals at his tomb to commemorate his life. In several countries, the local shrine is a focal point of the community, with several localities named specifically for the local saint.

In some parts of the Islamic world, such as in Pakistan, these festivals are multi-day events and even draw members of the Hindu and Christian minority who often revere the Muslim saint, such as in the case of the famous Lal Baz Qalandar shrine in Sindh, Pakistan – an important example of religious syncretism that blurs the distinction between members of different religions. Sufi shrines in Bangladesh, India, and Pakistan are also host to a night of commemoration by Mehfil Samaaa (Qawali) and 'Zikr' every Thursday. Some academics assert that such practices were influenced by Hinduism long ago when Muslims and Hindus co-existed in the sub-continent.

In Turkey, the famous [[Sufi]] [[Whirling Dervishes]] perform their whirling at the shrine of Jalal-ud-Din Rumi in [[Konya]], while in Morocco and Algeria, brotherhoods of Black African Sufis, the Gnouia, perform elaborate songs at the shrines of their Saints.

Numerous shrines were once located in Saudi Arabia in its initial days. However, due to the revival of Islamic orthodoxy by [[Muhammad ibn Abd al-Wahhab]] (strongly clinging to the [[Hadith]] texts and [[Quran]]) against developed cultural practices they were destroyed by local authorities who identified them as sources of [[Shirk]] and of being reprehensible innovations in Islam or '[[Bid‘ah]]'. Other important Shrines were once found in Central Asia, but many were destroyed by the Soviets.

==== Shia Islam ====
[[File:Kerbela Hussein Moschee.jpg|thumb|180px|Pilgrims outside the Shrine of Imam Hussain ibn Ali in Karbala, Iraq.]]
Shia's have several shrines dedicated to various religious figures important in their history, and several elaborate shrines are dedicated to Shia Saints and religious figures, most notably in  Kerbala, Najaf, and Samarra in Iraq, and Qum and Mashad in Iran. Other important Shia shrines are located in Mazar-e-Sharif (&quot;the Noble Shrine&quot;) in Afghanistan, and in Damascus, Syria.

=== Bahá'í ===
[[File:TerracesBenGurion.jpg|180px|thumb|right|The [[Shrine of the Báb]] and its [[Terraces (Bahá'í)|Terraces]] on [[Mount Carmel]], [[Haifa]].]]
The two most well-known [[Bahá'í Faith|Bahá'í]] shrines serve as the resting places for the respective remains of the two central figures of the Bahá'í Faith, the [[Báb]] and [[Bahá'u'lláh]]. They are the focal points of a [[Bahá'í pilgrimage]]:
* The [[Shrine of the Báb]] in [[Haifa]], [[Israel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sbab&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = https://bahai.bwc.org//pilgrimage/Intro/visit_3.asp | title = Shrine of the Báb | accessdate = 2009-02-03 | year = 2007 | publisher = Bahá'í World Centre | author = Bahá'í World Centre}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Shrine of Bahá'u'lláh]] in [[Acre, Israel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sbahaullah&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = https://bahai.bwc.org//pilgrimage/Intro/visit_2.asp | title = Shrine of Bahá'u'lláh | accessdate = 2009-02-03 | year = 2007 | publisher = Bahá'í World Centre | author = Bahá'í World Centre}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Buddhism===
[[File:Shrine outside Wat Phnom.jpg|thumb|180px|Buddhist shrine just outside [[Wat Phnom]]]]
In [[Buddhism]], a shrine refers to a place where veneration is focused on the [[Gautama Buddha|Buddha]] or one of the [[bodhisattva]]s. Monks, nuns and laypeople all give offerings to these revered figures at these shrines and also [[meditation|meditate]] in front of them.

Typically, Buddhist shrines contain a statue of either the Buddha, or (in the [[Mahayana]] and [[Vajrayana]] forms of Buddhism), one of the various bodhisattvas.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.buddhamind.info/leftside/actives/shrine.htm&lt;/ref&gt; They also commonly contain candles, along with offerings such as flowers, purified water, food, and incense. Many shrines also contain sacred relics, such as the alleged [[Relic of the tooth of the Buddha|tooth of the Buddha]] held at a shrine in [[Sri Lanka]].

Site-specific shrines in Buddhism, particularly those that contain relics of deceased buddhas and revered monks, are often [[Buddhist architecture|designed in the traditional form]] known as the [[stupa]].

===Germanic paganism===
In [[Germanic paganism]], types of shrines were employed, but terms for the shrines show some level of ambiguity:
*''[[Hörgr]]s'', which may have originally exclusively referred to &quot;holy places&quot;, whereas its Old English cognate ''hearg'' could mean &quot;[[Sacred grove|holy grove]]&quot; and/or &quot;temple, idol&quot;&lt;ref name=SIMEK156&gt;[[Rudolf Simek|Simek, Rudolf]] (2007), translated by Angela Hall. ''Dictionary of Northern Mythology'', page 156. [[Boydell &amp; Brewer|D.S. Brewer]]. ISBN 0-85991-513-1&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[Vé (shrine)|Vé]]s'' (Old Norse) or ''wēohs'' (Old English), referring to either a types of shrines or sacred enclosures. The term appears in [[skald]]ic poetry and in place names in [[Scandinavia]] (with the exception of [[Iceland]]), often in connection with a [[List of Germanic deities|Norse deity]] or a geographic feature. The name of the Norse god [[Vili and Vé|Vé]], refers to the practice.&lt;ref name=NORSEGOD&gt;[[Rudolf Simek|Simek, Rudolf]] (2007), translated by Angela Hall. ''Dictionary of Northern Mythology'', page 335. [[Boydell &amp; Brewer|D.S. Brewer]]. ISBN 0-85991-513-1. and Orchard, Andy (1997). ''Dictionary of Norse Myth and Legend'', page 173. [[Orion Publishing Group|Cassell]]. ISBN 0-304-34520-2&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hinduism===
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2009}}
In [[Hinduism]], a shrine is a place where a god or goddess is worshipped. Shrines are typically located inside a temple known as a [[Hindu temple|mandir]], though many Hindus also have a household shrine as well. Sometimes a human is venerated at a Hindu shrine along with a deity, for instance the 19th century religious teacher [[Ramakrishna|Sri Ramakrishna]] is venerated at the [[Ramakrishna Temple]] in [[Kolkata]], [[India]].

Central to a Hindu shrine is a statue of a deity, which is known as a [[murti]]. Hindus believe that the deity that they are worshiping actually enters and inhabits the murti. This is given offerings like candles, food, flowers, and incense. In some cases, particularly among devotees of the goddess [[Kālī]] in northern India, [[animal sacrifice|animals are sacrificed]] to the deity (animal sacrifice is not a part of [[Hinduism]]).

At a mandir, the congregation often assembles in front of a shrine, and, led by priests, give offerings and sing devotional hymns.

===Taoism===

The line between a [[temple]] and a shrine in [[Taoism]] is not fully defined;  shrines are usually smaller versions of larger Taoist temples or small places in a [[home]] where a [[taijitu|yin-yang]] emblem is placed among peaceful settings to encourage meditation and study of Taoist texts and principles.  Taoists place less emphasis on formalized attendance and ritualized worship than other [[Asia]]n religions;  formal temples and structures of worship came about in Taoism mostly in order to prevent losing adherents to [[Buddhism]].&lt;ref name=ORGTAO&gt;''Facts and Details - Organized Taoism'', http://factsanddetails.com/china.php?itemid=92&amp;catid=3 Retrieved 2008-10-28.&lt;/ref&gt;  Frequent features of Taoist shrines include the same features as full temples, often including any or all of the following features : [[garden]]s, running water or fountains, small burning [[brazier]]s or candles (with or without [[incense]]), and copies of Taoist texts such as the [[Tao Te Ching]], [[Zhuangzi (book)|Zhuangzi]] or other texts by [[Lao Tzu]], [[Chuang Tzu]] or other Taoist [[sage]]s.{{Disambiguation needed|date=February 2012}}  

As with all Taoist worship, Taoist shrines are organized around a sense of appreciation of [[nature]] and surroundings that inspire meditation on, and living in accordance with, the [[Tao]] (&quot;Way&quot; or &quot;Path&quot;, a concept of living harmoniously with one's natural surroundings and [[Natural environment|environment]]) and the Three Jewels Of Taoism (different from Buddhism's concept of Three Jewels) - [[compassion]], [[moderation]], and [[humility]].

==Secular shrines==
In the United States and some other countries, [[landmark]]s may be called &quot;historic shrines.&quot; Notable shrines of this type include:
* [[Alamo Mission in San Antonio|The Alamo]]
* [[Fort McHenry]]
* [[Touro Synagogue]] in [[Newport, Rhode Island]]
* [[Shrine of Remembrance]], a [[war memorial]] in [[Melbourne]], [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria, Australia]]
* [[Shrine of Remembrance, Brisbane|Shrine of Remembrance]], a [[war memorial]] in [[Brisbane]], Australia.

[[Hall of fame|Halls of fame]] also serve as shrines into which single or multiple individuals are inducted on the basis of their influence upon regions, cultures or disciplines. [[Bust (sculpture)|Busts]] or full-body statues are often erected and placed alongside each other in commemoration.

By extension the term ''shrine'' has come to mean any place (or virtual cyber-place) dedicated completely to a particular person or subject such as the [[Shrine of the Sun]] in [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]].{{cite web | url=http://www.cmzoo.org/aboutZoo/history/willRogersShrine.asp | title=Will Rogers Shrine of the Sun | publisher=Artsopolis Network | accessdate=December 30, 2011}}

==See also==
*[[List of shrines]]
*[[Makeshift memorial]]
*[[Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine]]
*[[Holiest sites in Islam (Shia)]]
*[[Holiest sites in Islam (Sunni)]]
*[[Shrines to the Virgin Mary]]
*[[Numen]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Shrines}}
*[http://www.historyfish.net/shrines/british_shrines.html Shrines of British Saints by J. Charles Wall. Full Text + Illustrations.]
*[http://www.gcatholic.com/churches/shrine.htm GigaCatholic]
*[http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/pk_pandita/hari_parbat.html&amp;date=2009-10-26+00:36:44 Hari Parbat]
*[http://insite.religioustraveldirectory.com/10-top-catholic-shrines-in-the-u-s/ Top Catholic Shrines in the U.S.]
{{Room}}

{{Private revelation}}

[[Category:Shrines| ]]

[[ar:مزار]]
[[ca:Santuari]]
[[cs:Svatyně]]
[[cy:Creirfa]]
[[de:Schrein]]
[[eml:Santüäri]]
[[es:Santuario (edificio)]]
[[eu:Santutegi]]
[[fr:Sanctuaire]]
[[fy:Skryn]]
[[id:Mazbah]]
[[it:Santuario]]
[[sw:Patakatifu]]
[[la:Sanctuarium]]
[[lmo:Santüari]]
[[nl:Schrijn]]
[[ja:聖堂]]
[[pt:Santuário]]
[[ru:Рака]]
[[simple:Sacred site]]
[[sh:Svetište]]
[[th:ศาลเจ้า]]
[[uk:Рака]]</text>
      <sha1>iehhy08sju14wg5zacl8ue0nxyl8e7s</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
