<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Siddur</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28370</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517727637</id>
      <parentid>493895045</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-14T12:00:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sburke</username>
        <id>163811</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Requesting pronunciation.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25902">{{Judaism}}
A '''''siddur'''''{{Pronunciation-needed}}&lt;!-- as IPA --&gt; ({{lang-he|סדור}}; plural סדורים '''''siddurim'''''{{Pronunciation-needed}}&lt;!-- as IPA --&gt;) is a [[Judaism|Jewish]] [[prayer book]], containing a set order of [[List of Jewish prayers and blessings|daily prayers]]. This article discusses how some of these prayers evolved, and how the ''siddur'', as it is known today has developed. A separate article, [[Jewish prayer]], discusses the prayers that appear in the ''siddur'', and when they are said.

==History of the siddur==
The earliest parts of Jewish prayer book are the ''[[Shema Yisrael]]'' (&quot;Hear O Israel&quot;) ([[Deuteronomy]] 6:4 ''et seq''), and the [[Priestly Blessing]] ([[Book of Numbers|Numbers]] 6:24-26), which are in the [[Torah]]. A set of eighteen (currently nineteen) blessings called the ''Shemoneh Esreh'' or the ''[[Amidah]]'' ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], &quot;standing [prayer]&quot;), is traditionally ascribed to the [[Great Assembly]] in the time of [[Ezra]], at the end of the Biblical period. 

The name ''Shemoneh Esreh'', literally &quot;eighteen&quot;, is an historical anachronism, since it now contains nineteen blessings. It was only near the end of the [[Second Temple]] period that the eighteen prayers of the weekday Amidah became standardized. Even at that time their precise wording and order was not yet fixed, and varied from locale to locale. Many modern scholars believe that parts of the Amidah came from the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] [[apocrypha]]l work [[Ben Sira]]. 

According to the [[Talmud]], soon after the destruction of the [[Temple in Jerusalem]] a formal version of the Amidah was adopted at a rabbinical council in [[Yavne]], under the leadership of Rabban [[Gamaliel II]] and his colleagues. However, the precise wording was still left open. The order, general ideas, opening and closing lines were fixed. Most of the wording was left to the individual reader. It was not until several centuries later that the prayers began to be formally fixed. By the [[Middle Ages]] the texts of the prayers were nearly fixed, and in the form in which they are still used today.

The siddur was printed by [[Soncino family (printers)|Soncino]] in Italy as early as 1486, though a siddur was first mass-distributed only in 1865 {{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}. The siddur began appearing in the [[vernacular]] as early as 1538. The first - unauthorized - English [[translation]], by Gamaliel ben Pedahzur (a [[pseudonym]]), appeared in London in 1738; a different translation was released in the United States in 1837.&lt;ref&gt;[http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1176152818456 Power and Politics: Prayer books and resurrection | Jerusalem Post&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Creating the siddur===
Readings from the [[Torah]] (five books of Moses) and the [[Nevi'im]] (&quot;Prophets&quot;) form part of the prayer services. To this framework various Jewish sages added, from time to time, various prayers, and, for festivals especially, numerous hymns.

The earliest existing codification of the prayerbook was drawn up by Rav [[Amram Gaon]] of Sura, Babylon, about 850 CE. Half a century later Rav [[Saadia Gaon]], also of Sura, composed a siddur, in which the rubrical matter is in [[Arabic language|Arabic]]. These were the basis of Simcha ben Samuel's [[Machzor Vitry]] (11th century France), which was based on the ideas of his teacher, [[Rashi]]. Another formulation of the prayers was that appended by [[Maimonides]] to the laws of prayer in his [[Mishneh Torah]]: this forms the basis of the Yemenite liturgy, and has had some influence on other rites.  From this point forward all Jewish prayerbooks had the same basic order and contents.

Two authoritative versions of the Ashkenazi siddur were those of Shabbetai Sofer in the 16th century and Seligman Baer in the 19th century; siddurim have also been published reflecting the views of [[Jacob Emden]] and the [[Vilna Gaon]].

===Different Jewish rites===
{{main|Nusach}}
[[File:Sibir1.jpg|thumb|150px|left|[[Nusach Ashkenaz]] Siddur prayer book from [[Irkutsk]], Russia, printed in 1918]]
There are differences among, amongst others, the [[Sephardic law and customs#Liturgy|Sephardic]] (including [[Spanish and Portuguese Jews|Spanish and Portuguese]]), [[Yemenite Jews|Teimani]] (Yemenite),
[[Hasidic Judaism|Chasidic]], [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazic]] (German-Polish), [[Italian Jews#Italian rite Jews|Bené Roma or Italkim]] and [[Romaniotes|Romaniote]] (Greek, once extending to Turkey and perhaps the southern Italian peninsula) liturgies.  Most of these are slight differences in the wording of the prayers; for instance, Oriental Sephardic and some Hasidic prayer books state &quot;חננו מאתך חכמה בינה ודעת&quot;, &quot;Graciously bestow upon us from You wisdom (''[[Chokhmah (Kabbalah)|ḥochmah]]''), understanding (''[[Binah (Kabbalah)|binah]]'') and knowledge (''[[daat]]'')&quot;, in allusion to the [[Kabbalah|Kabbalistic]] [[sefirot]] of those names, while the Nusach Ashkenaz, as well as [[Spanish and Portuguese Jews|Western Sephardic]] and other Hasidic versions retain the older wording &quot;חננו מאתך דעה בינה והשכל&quot;, &quot;Graciously bestow upon us from You knowledge, understanding, and reason&quot;.  In some cases, however, the order of the preparation for the Amidah is drastically different, reflecting the different halakhic and kabbalistic formulae that the various scholars relied on in assembling their siddurim, as well as the minhagim, or customs, or their locales.

Some forms of the Sephardi rite are considered to be very overtly [[Kabbalah|kabbalistic]], depending on how far they reflect the ritual of [[Isaac Luria]].  This is partly because the [[Tetragrammaton]] frequently appears with varying vowel points beneath the letters (unpronounced, but to be meditated upon) and different Names of God appear in small print within the final hei (ה) of the Tetragrammaton.  In some editions, there is a Psalm in the preparations for the [[Amidah]] that is printed in the outline of a [[Menorah (Temple)|menorah]], and the worshipper meditates on this shape as he recites the psalm.

The Ashkenazi rite is more common than the Sephardi rite in America. While Nusach Ashkenaz does contain some kabbalistic elements, such as acrostics and allusions to the sefirot (&quot;To You, God, is the greatness [gedullah], and the might [gevurah], and the glory [tiferet], longevity [netzach],...&quot; etc.), these are not easily seen unless the reader is already initiated.  It is notable that although many other traditions avoid using the poem &quot;Anim Zemiroth&quot; on the Sabbath, for fear that its holiness would be less appreciated due to the frequency of the Sabbath, the poem is usually sung by Ashkenazi congregations before concluding the Sabbath [[Musaf]] service with the daily psalm.  The ark is opened for the duration of the song.

Hasidim, though usually ethnically Ashkenazi, usually use liturgies with varying degrees of Sephardic influence, such as [[Nusach Sefard]] and [[Nusach Ari]], in order to follow the order of the prayers set by [[Rabbi Isaac Luria]], often called &quot;Ari HaKadosh&quot;, or &quot;The Holy Lion&quot;.  Although the Ari himself was born Ashkenazi, he borrowed many elements from Sephardi and other traditions, since he felt that they followed Kabbalah and [[Halacha]] more faithfully.  The Ari did not publish any siddur, but orally transmitted his particular usages to his students with interpretations and certain meditations.&lt;ref&gt;Nusach HaAri Siddur, published by Merkos L'Inyonei Chinuch.&lt;/ref&gt;  Many siddurim containing some form of the Sephardic rite together with the usages of the Ari were published, both by actual Sephardic communities and for the use of Hasidim and other Ashkenazim interested in Kabbalah.  In 1803, Rabbi [[Schneur Zalman of Liadi]] compiled an authoritative siddur from the sixty siddurim that he checked for compliance with Hebrew grammar, Jewish law, and Kabbalah: this is what is known today as the &quot;Nusach Ari&quot;, and is used by Lubavitch Hasidim.  Those that use Nusach HaAri claim that it is an all-encompassing nusach that is valid for any Jew, no matter what his ancestral tribe or identity, a view attributed to the [[Maggid of Mezeritch]].

The [[Mahzor]] of each rite is distinguished by hymns (''[[piyyut]]im'') composed by authors (''payyetanim''). The most important writers are [[Yose ben Yoseh]], probably in the 6th century, chiefly known for his compositions for [[Yom Kippur]]; [[Eleazar Kalir]], the founder of the payyetanic style, perhaps in the 7th century; [[Saadia Gaon]]; and the Spanish school, consisting of [[Joseph ibn Abitur]] (died in 970), [[ibn Gabirol]], [[Isaac Gayyath]], [[Moses ibn Ezra]], [[Abraham ibn Ezra]] and [[Judah ha-Levi]], Moses ben Nahman ([[Nahmanides]]) and [[Isaac Luria]].  In the case of Nusach HaAri, however, many of these High Holiday piyyutim are absent: the older piyyutim were not present in the Sephardic rite, on which Nusach HaAri was based, and the followers of the Ari removed the piyyutim composed by the Spanish school.

==Complete versus weekday siddurim==

Some siddurim have only prayers for weekdays; others have prayers for weekdays and [[Shabbat]] (Jewish Sabbath). Many have prayers for weekdays, Shabbat, and the three Biblical festivals, [[Sukkot]] (the feast of Tabernacles), [[Shavuot]] (the feast of weeks) and [[Pesach]] (Passover). The latter are referred to as a ''Siddur Shalem'' (&quot;complete siddur&quot;).

==Variations and additions on holidays==
There are many additional liturgical variations and additions to the siddur for the ''Yamim Noraim'' (The &quot;Days of Awe&quot;; High Holy Days, i.e. ''Rosh HaShanah'' and ''Yom Kippur''). As such, a special siddur has developed for just this period, known as a ''[[mahzor]]'' (also: ''machzor''). The ''mahzor'' contains not only the basic liturgy, but also many ''piyutim'', Hebrew liturgical poems.  Sometimes the term ''mahzor'' is also used for the prayer books for the three pilgrim festivals, Pesach, Shavuot and Sukkot.

==Popular siddurim==
Below are listed many popular siddurim used by religious Jews.
[[File:Siddurim.JPG|thumb|350px|Variety of popular Siddurim.]]
===Ashkenazi Orthodox===
{{Main|Ashkenazi Jews | Orthodox Judaism}}

*''Siddur Ha-Shalem'' (a.k.a. the ''Birnbaum Siddur'') Ed. [[Philip Birnbaum]]. The Hebrew Publishing Company. ISBN 0-88482-054-8 (Hebrew-English)
*''The Metsudah Siddur: A New Linear Prayer Book'' Ziontalis. (Hebrew-English)
*''The Authorised Daily Prayer Book of the British Commonwealth'', translation by Chief Rabbi Sir [[Jonathan Sacks]] (the new version of &quot;[[Simeon Singer|Singer]]'s Prayer Book&quot;) (Hebrew-English)
*''The [[Artscroll]] Siddur'', Mesorah Publications (In a number of versions including an interlinear translation and fairly popular today.) (Hebrew, Hebrew-English, Hebrew-Russian, Hebrew-Spanish, Hebrew-French)   The &quot; great innovation&quot; of the   Artscroll was that it was the first siddur &quot; made it possible for even a neophyte ba’al teshuvah (returnee to the faith) to function gracefully in the act of prayer, bowing at the correct junctures, standing, sitting and stepping back&quot; at the correct place in the service. &quot;&lt;ref&gt;A New Dialogue With The Divine, May 26, 2009, Jewish Week, [[Jonathan Rosenblatt]]  [http://www.thejewishweek.com/viewArticle/c39_a15840/News/International.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Siddur [[Rinat Yisrael]]'', ''Hotsa'at Moreshet'', [[Bnei Brak]], Israel. (In a number of versions, popular in Israel.) (Hebrew)
*''Siddur Siach Yitzchak'' (Hebrew)
*''Siddur Tefilas Kol Peh'' (Hebrew)
*''Siddur Tefilas Sh'ai'', Feldheim Publishers : Israel/NewYork (Hebrew)
*''Siddur HaGra'' (reflecting views of the [[Vilna Gaon]])
*''Siddur Aliyos Eliyahu'' (Popular among followers of the Vilna Gaon who live in Israel and abroad) (Hebrew)
*''Siddur Kol Bo'' (Hebrew)
*''[[Koren Siddur|Koren Sacks Siddur]]'' (Hebrew-English), [[Koren Publishers Jerusalem]]: based on latest Singer's prayer book, above (described as the first siddur to &quot;pose a fresh challenge to the ArtScroll dominance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jta.org/news/article/2009/04/02/1004210/orthodox-publisher-challenged-by-modern-orthodox Artscroll facing challenge from Modern Orthodox, April 5, 2009, JTA]&lt;/ref&gt;)

===Sephardic===
{{Main|Sephardic law and customs}}

====Spanish and Portuguese Jews====
{{Main|Spanish and Portuguese Jews}}

''(Characterised by relative absence of [[Kabbalah|Kabbalistic]] elements:)''

*''Book of Prayer: According to the Custom of the Spanish and Portuguese Jews'' [[David de Sola Pool]], New York: Union of Sephardic Congregations, 1979
*''Book of Prayer of the Spanish and Portuguese Jews’ Congregation, London. Volume One: Daily and occasional prayers.'' Oxford (Oxford Univ. Press, [[Vivian Ridler]]), 5725 - 1965.

====Greek, Turkish and Balkan Sephardim====
''(Usually characterised by presence of [[Kabbalah|Kabbalistic]] elements:)''
*''Siddur Zehut Yosef'' (Daily and Shabbat) According to the Rhodes and Turkish Traditions, Hazzan Isaac Azose, Seattle, Washington: Sephardic Traditions Foundation, 2002

====North African Jews====
''(Usually characterised by presence of [[Kabbalah|Kabbalistic]] elements:)''
*''Siddur Od Abinu Ḥai'' ed. Levi Nahum: Jerusalem (Hebrew only, Livorno text, Libyan tradition)
*''Mahzor Od Abinu Ḥai'' ed. Levi Nahum (5 vols.): Jerusalem (Hebrew only, Livorno text, Libyan tradition)
*''Siddur Vezaraḥ Hashemesh'', ed. [[Chalom Messas|Messas]]: Jerusalem (Hebrew only, Meknes tradition)
*''Siddur Ish Matzliaḥ'', ed. Mazuz, Machon ha-Rav Matzliah: B'nei Brak (Hebrew only, Djerba tradition)
*''Siddur Farḥi'' (Hebrew with Arabic translation, Egypt)
*''Siddur Tefillat ha-Ḥodesh'', ed. David Levi, Erez : Jerusalem (Hebrew only, Livorno text, Moroccan, Algerian and Tunisian traditions)[http://www.orvishua.org.il/heb/books/dif.php]
*''Siddur Patah Eliyahou'', ed. Joseph Charbit, Colbo: Paris (Hebrew and French, Moroccan, Algerian and Tunisian traditions)[http://www.librairie-du-progres.com/shopdisplayproducts.asp?id=1458&amp;cat=La+Pri%E8re+Juive]
*''Mahzor Zechor le-Avraham'', Yarid ha-Sefarim : Jerusalem (Based on the original ''Zechor le-Abraham'': Livorno 1926, Hebrew only, Moroccan, Algerian and Tunisian traditions, days of awe only)
*''Siddur Darchei Avot'' (Moroccan)
*''Siddur Oro shel Olam''

====Middle Eastern Mizrachim (Sephardim)====
''(Usually characterised by presence of [[Kabbalah|Kabbalistic]] elements:)''

=====[[Syrian Jews|Syrian]]=====
*''The Aram Soba Siddur: According to the Sephardic Custom of Aleppo Syria'' Rabbi Moshe Antebi, Jerusalem: Aram Soba Foundation, 1993
*''Siddur Abodat Haleb / Prayers from the Heart'' Rabbi Moshe Antebi, Lakewood, New Jersey: Israel Book Shop, 2002
*''Kol Yaacob'': Sephardic Heritage Foundation, New York, 1990.
*''Bet Yosef ve-Ohel Abraham'': Jerusalem, Manṣur (Hebrew only, based on Baghdadi text)
*''Orḥot Ḥayim'', ed. Yedid: Jerusalem 1995 (Hebrew only)
*''Siddur Kol Mordechai'', ed. Faham bros: Jerusalem 1984 (minhah and arbit only)
*''Abir Yaakob'', ed. Haber: Sephardic Press (Hebrew and English, Shabbat only)
*''Orot Sephardic Siddur'', Eliezer Toledano: Lakewood, New Jersey, Orot Inc. (Hebrew and English: Baghdadi text, Syrian variants shown in square brackets)
*''Maḥzor Shelom Yerushalayim'', ed. Albeg: New York, Sephardic Heritage Foundation 1982

=====Israeli, following Rabbi [[Ovadia Yosef]]=====
*''Ohr V’Derech Sephardic Siddur''
*''Siddur Yeḥavveh Daat''
*''Siddur Avodat Ha-shem''
*''Siddur Ḥazon Ovadia''
*''Siddur L'maan Shmo''

=====Edot Hamizrach (Iraqi)=====
*''Tefillat Yesharim'': Jerusalem, Manṣur (Hebrew only)
*''Siddur Od Yosef Ḥai''
*''Kol Eliyahu'', ed. [[Mordechai Eliyahu]]
*''Siddur [[Rinat Yisrael]]'' - (Edot Hamizrach edition), ''Hotsa'at Moreshet'', [[Bnei Brak]], Israel. (Hebrew)

===Yemenite Jews (Teimanim)===
{{Main|Yemenite Jews}}

====Baladi====

*''Siddur Tiklal: Tzalach Yihiyeh'' Ben Yehuda, 1800
*''Siddur Tiklal: Torath Avoth'' [http://www.chayas.com/temanbooks.htm]
*''Siddur Siaḥ Yerushalayim: Rabbi [[Yosef Qafiḥ]]/Kapach''  [http://www.chayas.com/temanbooks.htm]
*''Tiklal Ha-Mefoar (MAHARITS)'' Nusahh Baladi, Meyusad Al Pi Ha-Tiklal Im Etz Hayim Ha-Shalem Arukh Ke-Minhag Yahaduth Teiman: Bene Berak : Or Neriyah ben Mosheh Ozeri, [2001 or 2002] [http://www.indiana.edu/~libsalc/daym/he_nt200408hebrew.htm]

====Shami====

*''Siddur Tefillat HaḤodesh - Beit Yaakov'', Nusaḥ Sepharadim, Teiman, and Edoth Mizraḥ
*''Siddur Kavanot HaRashash, [[Shalom Sharabi]]'', Publisher: Yeshivat HaChaim Ve'Hashalom

===Chassidic Siddurim===
*''Siddur [[Tehillat HaShem]]'' (the version currently used by [[Chabad-Lubavitch]])
*''Siddur [[Torah Or]]'' (the Alter Rebbe's original edition)
*''[[Nusach Sefard]]'' Siddurs

===Conservative Judaism===
{{Main|Conservative Judaism}}

*''Sabbath and Festival Prayer Book'' Ed. [[Morris Silverman]] with [[Robert Gordis]], 1946.  USCJ and RA
*''Weekday Prayer Book'' Ed. [[Morris Silverman]], 1956. USCJ
*''Weekday Prayer Book'' Ed. Gershon Hadas with Jules Harlow, 1961, RA.
*[[Siddur Sim Shalom]] Ed. [[Jules Harlow]]. 1985, 980 pages, RA and USCJ.
*''Siddur Sim Shalom for Shabbat and Festivals'' Ed. Lawrence Cahan, 1998, 816 pages. RA and USCJ.
*''Siddur Sim Shalom for Weekdays'' Ed. Avram Israel Reisner, 2003, 576 pages.  RA and USCJ.
*''Siddur Va'ani Tefilati'' Ed. [[Simchah Roth]], 1998, 744 pages. Israeli Masorti Movement and Rabbinical Assembly of Israel. Hebrew.
*''Va'ani Tefilati: Siddur Yisre'eli'' Ed. Ze'ev Kenan, 2009, 375 pages. Israeli Masorti Movement and Rabbinical Assembly of Israel. Hebrew.
*[[Siddur Lev Yisrael]] Ed. [[Cheryl Magen]], 1998, 432 pages. [[Camp Ramah]]. Hebrew.

===Progressive and Reform Judaism===
{{Main|Reform Judaism}}
*''Ha-Avodah Shebalev'', The prayer book of The Israel Movement for Progressive Judaism, Ed. The Council of Israel Progressive Rabbis (MARAM), 1982
*''The Companion to Ha-Avodah Shebalev'' published by Congregation Har-El Jerusalem in 1992 to help English-speaking immigrants and visitors; Hebrew pages from the original ''Ha-Avodah Shebalev'', English translations from ''[[Gates of Prayer|Gates of Prayer: The New Union Prayer Book]]'' with additional translations by Adina Ben-Chorin.
*''Seder ha-Tefillot: Forms of Prayer'': Movement for Reform Judaism, London 2008, ISBN 0-947884-13-0; ISBN 978-0-947884-13-0 Official prayer book of the Reform movement in Britain
*''Liberal Jewish Prayer Book'': Vol. 1 (Services for Weekdays, Sabbaths, Etc.), 1926, 1937; Vol. 2 (Services for The Day of Memorial {Rosh Hashanah} and The Day of Atonement), 1923, 1937; Vol. 3 (Services for Passover, Pentecost, and Tabernacles), 1926; all published by the Liberal Jewish Synagogue, London, U.K.
*''Service of the Heart: Weekday Sabbath and Festival Services and Prayers for Home and Synagogue'', [[Union of Liberal and Progressive Synagogues]], London, 1967
*''Gate of Repentance: Services for the High Holidays'', [[Union of Liberal and Progressive Synagogues]], London, 1973
*''[[Vetaher Libenu]]'': Purify Our Hearts, Congregation Beth El, Sudbury, MA 1980
*''Siddur Lev Chadash'', [[Union of Liberal and Progressive Synagogues]], UK, 1995.
*''Machzor Ruach Chadashah'', [[Union of Liberal and Progressive Synagogues]], London, 2003.
*''Olat Tamid: Book of Prayers for Jewish Congregations''
All of the following published by the [[Central Conference of American Rabbis]]:
*''[[Union Prayer Book]], vol. 1 (Sabbath, Festivals, and Weekdays)'', 1895, 1918, 1940; ''vol. 2 (High Holidays)'', 1894, 1922, 1945
*''[[Gates of Prayer]]: The New Union Prayer Book'', 1975
*''Gates of Repentance: The New Union Prayer Book'', 1978, 1996
*''Gates of Prayer for Shabbat and Weekdays: A Gender Sensitive Prayerbook'', 1994
*''[[Mishkan T'filah]]'' [Tabernacle of Prayer]'': A Reform Siddur, 2007''
*''Mishkan T'filah for Gatherings'': A Reform Siddur, 2009
*''Mishkan T'filah for Travelers'': A Reform Siddur, 2009

===Reconstructionist Judaism===
{{Main|Reconstructionist Judaism}}
[[Image:DSCN0301.JPG|200px|thumb|''Kol Haneshamah: Shabbat Vehagim'']]
*Prayer Books edited by Rabbi Mordecai Kaplan and others:
**''Sabbath Prayer Book'', Jewish Reconstructionist Foundation, 1945
**''High Holiday Prayer Book'' (Vol. 1, Prayers for Rosh Hashanah; Vol. 2, Prayers for Yom Kippur), Jewish Reconstructionist Foundation, 1948
**''Supplementary Prayers and Readings for the High Holidays'', Jewish Reconstructionist Foundation, 1960
**''Festival Prayer Book'', Jewish Reconstructionist Foundation, 1958
**''Daily Prayer Book'', Jewish Reconstructionist Foundation, 1963
*''Hadesh Yameinu (Renew our days): a book of Jewish prayer and meditation'', edited and translated by Rabbi Ronald Aigen. Montreal (Cong. Dorshei Emet), 1996.
*Kol Haneshamah Prayerbook series, ed. David Teutsch:
**''Erev Shabbat: Shabbat Eve'', Reconstructionist Press, 1989
**''Shirim Uvrahot: Songs, Blessings and Rituals for the Home'', Reconstructionist Press, 1991
**''Shabbat Vehagim: The Sabbath and Festivals'', Reconstructionist Press; 3rd edition (August 1, 1998)
**''Limot Hol: Daily Prayer Book'', Reconstructionist Press; Reprint edition (September 1, 1998)
**''Kol Haneshamah: Prayers for a House of Mourning'', Jewish Reconstructionist Federation (October 10, 2001)
**''Kol Haneshamah: Mahzor Leyamim Nora'Im'', Fordham University Press; Bilingual edition (May 1, 2000)

===Digital Options===

====[[iPhone]]====
*''[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/siddur-sdwr-zmanim-luach-minyanim/id286478367?mt=8 Siddur]'' RustyBrick
*''[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pocket-isiddur-jewish-siddur/id297619512?mt=8 Pocket iSiddur]'' Paul Abraham Jaimovich
*''[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/siddur-nusach-ari/id299058477?mt=8 Siddur Nusach Ari]'': Dovid Zirkind, JewishContent.org
*''[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/esh-siddur-s-sydwr/id402409610?mt=8 Esh Siddur]'': Elyahu Sheetrit
*''[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/siddur-hd-for-ipad-sdwr-zmanim/id376005314?mt=8 Siddur HD (iPad)]'': RustyBrick

====[[Android (operating system)|Android]]====
*''[https://market.android.com/details?id=il.avimak.TehillatHashem Siddur Tehillat Hashem]'' Avraham Makovetsky
*''[https://market.android.com/details?id=com.karriapps.smartsiddurlite Smart Siddur Lite]'' Karri Apps
*''[https://market.android.com/details?id=siddur.sfaradi.forfree Siddur Sfaradi]'' RobertR
*''[https://market.android.com/details?id=com.saraandshmuel.anddaaven AndDaaven Siddur]'' S Popper

====[[Blackberry]]====
*''[http://www.jewishcontent.org/pda/blackberry/ JewishContent.org]''
*''[http://www.hebrewinhand.com/ Hebrew In Hand]''

==See also==

*[[The Transliterated Siddur]]
*[[Jewish services]]
*[[Nusach]]
*[[Amidah]]
*[[List of Jewish prayers and blessings]]
*[[Amram Gaon]]
*[[Eleazar Kalir]]
*[[Siddur of Saadia Gaon]]
*[[Torah database]]s (for electronic Hebrew texts of the siddur with vowels)
*[[Sephardic law and customs]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*''Jewish Liturgy: A Comprehensive History'', [[Ismar Elbogen]], [[Jewish Publication Society]], 1993.  This is the most thorough academic study of the Jewish liturgy ever written.  Originally published in [[German language|German]] in 1913, and updated in a number of [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] editions, the latest edition has been translated into English by Raymond P. Scheindlin.  This work covers the entire range of Jewish liturgical development, beginning with the early cornerstones of the siddur; through the evolution of the medieval piyyut tradition; to modern prayerbook reform in Germany and the United States.
*Joseph Heinemann &quot;Prayer in the Talmud&quot;, Gruyter, New York, 1977
*''Kavvana: Directing the Heart in Jewish Prayer'', Seth Kadish, [[Jason Aronson]] Inc., 1997.
*''The Encyclopedia of Jewish Prayer'' Macy Nulman, Jason Aronson Inc.,1993. Provides in one volume information on every prayer recited in the Ashkenazi and Sephardic traditions.  Arranged alphabetically by prayer, this book includes information on the prayers, their composers and development, the laws and customs surrounding them, and their place in the service.
*Jakob J. Petuchowski &quot;Contributions to the Scientific Study of Jewish Liturgy&quot; Ktav, New York, 1970
*Goldschmidt, ''Meḥqare Tefillah u-Fiyyut'' (On Jewish Liturgy): Jerusalem 1978
*Wieder, Naphtali, ''The Formation of Jewish Liturgy: In the East and the West''
*Reif, Stefan, ''Judaism and Hebrew Prayer'': Cambridge 1993. Hardback ISBN 978-0-521-44087-5, ISBN 0-521-44087-4; Paperback ISBN 978-0-521-48341-4, ISBN 0-521-48341-7
*Reif, Stefan, ''Problems with Prayers'': Berlin and New York 2006 ISBN 978-3-11-019091-5, ISBN 3-11-019091-5
*''The [[Artscroll]] Siddur'', Ed. [[Nosson Scherman]], Mesorah Publications. A popular [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] prayerbook with running commentary.  The amount of commentary varies by version.
*''[[The Authorised Daily Prayer Book of the British Commonwealth]]'', translation by Rabbi Eli Cashdan. An [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox]] prayerbook widely used in the UK and other [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries.
*[[s:he:סידור האש|Siddur HaEsh (of Fire)]] in Hebrew Wikibooks
*Amidah, entry in the Encyclopaedia Judaica, Keter Publishing
*[http://aleph500.huji.ac.il/nnl/dig/books_tef.html JNUL Digitized Book Repository], page with links to facsimile prayer books from 1475 to 1981
*[http://sidduraudio.com Siddur Audio], website with text and audio of selections from the Siddur
[[Category:Siddur| ]]

[[af:Siddur]]
[[ba:Сидур]]
[[ceb:Siddur]]
[[cs:Sidur]]
[[da:Siddur]]
[[de:Siddur]]
[[es:Sidur]]
[[fr:Siddour]]
[[it:Siddur]]
[[he:סידור]]
[[lad:Sidur]]
[[lt:Sidur]]
[[nl:Siddoer]]
[[ja:シッドゥール]]
[[no:Siddur]]
[[nn:Siddúr]]
[[pl:Sidur]]
[[pt:Sidur]]
[[ro:Siddur]]
[[ru:Сиддур]]
[[sr:Сидур]]
[[sh:Sidur]]
[[fi:Siddur]]
[[sv:Siddur]]
[[tr:Sidur]]
[[yi:סידור]]</text>
      <sha1>6p5kn6uu6pm88ydakqp0rv92vlgcs07</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
