<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Spiritual (music)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>185514</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522380281</id>
      <parentid>522365904</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T20:42:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wahoofive</username>
        <id>204565</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 522365904 by [[Special:Contributions/CJKAllstar|CJKAllstar]] ([[User talk:CJKAllstar|talk]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15133">{{redirect|Spirituals|the David Murray album|Spirituals (album)}}
{{Infobox music genre
|bgcolor=goldenrod
 |color=white
 |name=Spiritual
 |stylistic_origins=[[Work song]], [[Hymn#Christian tradition|Christian hymns]]
 |cultural_origins=[[History of slavery in the United States|Enslaved Africans in the U.S.]]
 |instruments=[[Vocal]]
 |popularity=
 |derivatives=[[Blues]], [[gospel music]]
 |subgenrelist=
 |subgenres=
 |fusiongenres=
 |regional_scenes=
 |other_topics=
}}

'''Spirituals''' (or '''Negro spirituals'''&lt;ref name=scholarship&gt;[http://www.negrospiritual.org/ The &quot;Negro Spiritual&quot; Scholarship Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=singers&gt;[http://newdeal.feri.org/library/ae36.htm The Negro Spiritual Singers]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=heritage&gt;[http://www.allaboutjazz.com/php/news.php?id=19476 Negro Spirituals Heritage Day]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=workshop&gt;[http://www.thenegrospiritualworkshop.com/ The Negro Spiritual Workshop]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=negrospirituals&gt;[http://www.negrospirituals.com/ negrospirituals.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=songsofsurvival&gt;[http://www.jsfmusic.com/Uncle_Tom/Tom_Article3.html Negro Spirituals: Songs of Survival]&lt;/ref&gt;) are religious (generally [[Chritianity|Christian]]) songs that were created by [[Slavery|enslaved]] [[African people]] in the United States.

==Terminology and origin==
The term ''spiritual'' is derived from ''spiritual song.'' The [[King James Bible]]'s translation of [[Ephesians]] 5:19 is: &quot;Speaking to yourselves in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody in your heart to the Lord.&quot; The term &quot;spiritual song&quot; was often used in the black and white Christian community through the 19th century (and indeed much earlier), and &quot;spiritual&quot; was used as a noun to mean, according to the context, &quot;spiritual person&quot; or &quot;spiritual thing&quot;, but not specifically with regard to song. ''Negro spiritual'' first appears in print in the 1860s,&lt;ref name=atlantic&gt;[http://www.theatlantic.com/issues/1867jun/spirit.htm Negro Spirituals] by Thomas Wentworth Higginson, ''The Atlantic'', June 1867.&lt;/ref&gt; where slaves are described as using ''spirituals'' for religious songs sung sitting or standing in place, and ''spiritual shouts'' for more dance-like music. 

Musicologist [[George Pullen Jackson]] extended the term ''spiritual'' to a wider range of folk hymnody, as in his 1938 book ''White Spirituals in the Southern Uplands'', but this does not appear to have been widespread usage previously. The term, however, has often been broadened to include subsequent arrangements into more standard European-American hymnodic styles, and to include post-emancipation songs with stylistic similarities to the original Negro spirituals. 

Although numerous rhythmical and sonic elements of Negro spirituals can be traced to African sources, Negro spirituals are a musical form that is indigenous and specific to the religious experience in the United States of Africans and their descendants. They are a result of the interaction of music and religion from Africa with music and religion of European origin. Further, this interaction occurred only in the United States. Africans who converted to Christianity in other parts of the world, even in the [[Caribbean]] and [[Latin America]], did not evolve this form.&lt;ref name=stompingblues&gt;{{cite book 
|last= Murray 
|first= Albert 
|title= Stomping the Blues 
|publisher= Da Capo 
|location=New York 
|year= 1976 
|isbn= 0-306-80362-3 
|pages = 64&amp;ndash;65}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religious significance==
{{listen
|filename=Gospel Train.ogg
|title=&quot;The Gospel Train&quot;
|description=&quot;[[The Gospel Train]]&quot; published by the [[Fisk Jubilee Singers]] in 1872 and performed by the [[United States Navy Band]]'s Sea Chanters ensemble
}}
Negro spirituals were primarily expressions of religious faith. Some may also have served as socio-political protests veiled as assimilation to white American culture. They originated among [[History of slavery in the United States|enslaved Africans]] in the [[United States]]. [[Slavery]] was introduced to the British colonies in the early 17th century, and enslaved people largely replaced [[indentured servant]]s as an economic labor force during the 17th century. In the United States, these people would remain in bondage for the entire 18th century and much of the 19th century. Most were not fully emancipated until the ratification of the [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Thirteenth Amendment to the Constitution]] in 1865.

===Suppression of indigenous religion===
{{refimprove|date=August 2012}} 
During slavery in the United States, there were systematic efforts to de-Africanize the captive Black workforce. Slaves were forbidden from speaking their native languages, and were generally converted to Christianity.

Because they were unable to express themselves freely in ways that were spiritually meaningful to them, enslaved Africans often held secret religious services. During these “bush meetings,” worshipers were free to engage in African religious rituals such as [[spiritual possession]], speaking in tongues and shuffling in counterclockwise [[ring shout]]s to communal shouts and chants. It was there also that enslaved Africans further crafted the impromptu musical expression of [[Field holler|field songs]] into the so-called &quot;line singing&quot; and intricate, multi-part harmonies of struggle and overcoming, faith, forbearance and hope that have come to be known as ''Negro spirituals''.

Restrictions were placed on the religious expression of slaves. Rows of benches in places of worship discouraged congregants from spontaneously jumping to their feet and dancing. The use of musical instruments of any kind often was forbidden, and slaves were ordered to desist from the &quot;paganism&quot; of the practice of spiritual possession.

However, several traditions rooted in Africa continue to the present day in African-American spiritual practices. Examples include the &quot;call and response&quot; style of preaching in which the speaker speaks for an interval and the congregation responds in unison in a continual pattern throughout the sermon. The &quot;call and response&quot; is often accompanied by instruments and sounds much like a song. Speaking in tongues is a persistent practice, as is &quot;shouting.&quot; Shouting may involve anything from jumping in one place repeatedly, running through the sanctuary, raising hands and arms in the air, shouting traditional praise phrases, or being &quot;slain in the spirit&quot; (fainting). The locations and the era may be different; but the same emphasis on combining sound, movement, emotion, and communal interaction into one focus on faith and its role in overcoming struggles, whether as an individual or a people group, remain the same.

===Replacement with Christianity===
The lyrics of Christian spirituals reference symbolic aspects of Biblical images such as [[Moses]] and Israel's [[The Exodus|Exodus]] from Egypt in songs such as &quot;[[Michael Row the Boat Ashore]]&quot;.

Christian [[hymns]] and songs were very influential on the writing of African-American spirituals. Slave composers took material from older songs, such as Christian hymns, and the Bible to create something entirely new and special to the culture. Spirituals were not simply different versions of hymns or Bible stories, but rather a creative altering of the material; new melodies and music, refashioned text, and stylistic differences helped to set apart the music as distinctly African-American.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Southern | first = Eileen | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = The Music of Black Americans | publisher = W.W. Norton and Company | date = | location = New York | pages = 172–177 | url = | doi =  | isbn = 0-393-95279-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

There is also a duality in the lyrics of spirituals. They communicated many Christian ideals while also communicating the hardship that was a result of being an African-American slave. The spiritual was often directly tied to the composer's life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.negrospirituals.com/history.htm |title=History |accessdate=2010-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a way of sharing religious, emotional, and physical experience through song.

==Claims of coded messages==
Many internet sources and popular books claim that songs such as &quot;[[Wade in the Water]]&quot; contained explicit instructions to fugitive slaves on how to avoid capture, and on which routes to take to successfully make their way to freedom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.localdial.com/users/jsyedu133/Soulreview/Understandingpages/coded.htm Coded Slave Songs]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Wade in the Water&quot; allegedly recommends leaving dry land and taking to the water as a strategy to throw pursuing bloodhounds off one's trail. &quot;[[The Gospel Train]]&quot;, &quot;[[Song of the Free]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Swing Low, Sweet Chariot]]&quot; are likewise supposed to contain veiled references to the [[Underground Railroad]], and many sources assert that &quot;[[Follow the Drinking Gourd]]&quot; contained a coded map to the Underground Railroad. The authenticity of such claims has been challenged as speculative, and critics have pointed to the apparent lack of primary source material in support of them.&lt;ref name=songstory&gt;{{cite book 
|last= Kelley 
|first= James 
|title= Song, Story, or History: Resisting Claims of a Coded Message in the African American Spiritual &quot;Follow the Drinking Gourd&quot;
|publisher= The Journal of Popular Culture 41.2 (April 2008): 262-80.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.followthedrinkinggourd.org/|title=Follow the Drinking Gourd: A Cultural History|accessdate=2008-05-05|last=Bresler|first=Joel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Collections==

===Jubilee Singers of Fisk University===
In the 1850s, Reverend Alexander Reid, superintendent of the Spencer Academy in the old [[Choctaw Nation of Oklahoma|Choctaw Nation]], hired some enslaved Africans from the Choctaws for some work around the school. He heard two of them, &quot;[[Wallace Willis|Uncle Wallace]]&quot; and &quot;Aunt Minerva&quot; Willis, singing religious songs that they had apparently composed. Among these were &quot;Swing Low, Sweet Chariot&quot;, &quot;[[Steal Away|Steal Away to Jesus]]&quot;, &quot;The Angels are Coming&quot;, &quot;I'm a Rolling&quot;, and &quot;Roll Jordan Roll&quot;. Later, Reid, who left Indian Territory at the beginning of the Civil War, attended a musical program put on by a group of Negro singers from [[Fisk University]]. They were singing mostly popular music of the day, and Reid thought the songs he remembered from his time in the Choctaw Nation would be at least as appropriate. He and his wife transcribed the songs of the Willises as they remembered them and sent them to Fisk University.

The [[Jubilee Singers]] put on their first performance singing the old captives' songs at a religious conference in 1871. The songs were first published in 1872 in a book entitled ''Jubilee Songs as Sung by the Jubilee Singers of Fisk University'', by [[Theodore F. Seward]]. Wallace Willis died in 1883 or 1884. 

Over time, the pieces the Jubilee Singers performed came to be arranged and performed by trained musicians. In 1873, [[Mark Twain]], whose father had owned slaves, found Fisk singing to be &quot;in the genuine old way&quot; he remembered from childhood. By contrast an anonymous 1881 review in the ''Peoria Journal'' said: “they have lost the wild rhythms, the barbaric melody, the passion….[T]hey smack of the North….” Some fifty years later, [[Zora Neale Hurston]] in her 1938 book ''The Sanctified Church'' criticized Fisk singers, and similar groups at Tuskegee and Hampton, as using a &quot;Glee Club style&quot; that was &quot;full of musicians' tricks&quot; not to be found in the original Negro spirituals, urging readers to visit an &quot;unfashionable Negro church&quot; to experience real Negro spirituals.

===Other collections===
A second important early collection of lyrics is ''[[Slave Songs of the United States]]'' by [[William Francis Allen]], [[Charles Pickard Ware]], and [[Lucy McKim Garrison]] (1867).

A group of lyrics to Negro spirituals was published by Colonel [[Thomas Wentworth Higginson]], who commanded a regiment of former slaves during the Civil War, in an article in ''The Atlantic Monthly''&lt;ref name=atlantic /&gt; and subsequently included in his 1869 memoir ''Army Life in a Black Regiment'' (1869).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=bn3Zu5rVn-oC&amp;printsec=frontcover#PPA199,M1
|title=Army Life in a Black Regiment|publisher=|accessdate=2008-03-03|last=Higginson|first=Thomas Wentworth|isbn=9781582183596|date=2001-04-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The latter half of the 20th century saw a resurgence of the Spiritual. This trend was impacted strongly by composers and musical directors such as [[Moses Hogan]] and [[Brazeal Dennard]].

==See also==
*[[History of slavery in the United States]]
*[[Deep River Boys]]
*[[Religious music]]
*[[African-American music]]
*[[Gospel music]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Nash, Elizabeth (2007). &quot;Autobiographical Reminiscences of African-American Classical Singers, 1853-Present&quot;. Lewiston: Edwin Mellen Press. ISBN 0-7734-5250-8&lt;!--this is a collection of essays on spirituals--&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.spiritualsproject.org The Spirituals Project]
* [http://ctl.du.edu/spirituals Sweet Chariot: the story of the spirituals]
* [http://www.tnstate.edu/library/digital/FISK.HTM Fisk Jubilee Singers]
* [http://www.library.upenn.edu/special/gallery/anderson/av/index.html Marian Anderson: A Life in Song]
* [http://imslp.org/wiki/User:Clark_Kimberling/Historical_Notes_1 Historical Notes on African American melodies], including 75 Negro spirituals with downloadable arrangements for solo instrument
* [http://www.gospelscore.com Free Gospel scores]

===Audio samples===
* [[Media:Colored quartet.pharoah's army got drowned EDIS-SRP-0198-12.ogg|Listen to &quot;Pharaoh's Army Got Drowned,&quot; artists unknown (765 KB)]]
* ''[http://www.loc.gov/folklife/Gordon/sideAbandA1.html#rolltheoldchariotalong Gordon Collection]''; performed by unknown persons in the Bay Area of California in the early 1920s
* [[Media:DeepDowninMyHeart.ogg|Download recording]] of &quot;Deep Down in My Heart&quot;, from the Library of Congress' [http://www.loc.gov/folklife/Gordon/sideBbandB1.html Gordon Collection]; performed by W. M. Givens in [[Darien, Georgia]], on about March 19, 1926

{{Americanrootsmusic}}
{{Christian music articles}}
{{clr}}

[[Category:Christian music genres]]
[[Category:Song forms]]
[[Category:American folk music]]
[[Category:Gospel music genres]]
[[Category:Slavery in the United States]]
[[Category:African-American culture]]

[[bg:Спиричуъл]]
[[ca:Espiritual negre]]
[[cs:Spirituál (hudba)]]
[[de:Negro Spiritual]]
[[et:Spirituaal]]
[[el:Σπιρίτσουαλς]]
[[es:Espiritual]]
[[eo:Nigrula preĝokanto]]
[[fo:Negro Spirituals]]
[[fr:Negro spiritual]]
[[fy:Negrospirituals]]
[[hr:Spiritual (glazba)]]
[[it:Spiritual]]
[[he:ספיריטואלז]]
[[ka:სპირიჩუელზი]]
[[lv:Spiričuels]]
[[hu:Spirituálé]]
[[nl:Negrospiritual]]
[[ja:スピリチュアル]]
[[no:Negro Spirituals]]
[[nn:Negro spirituals]]
[[pl:Negro spirituals]]
[[pt:Spiritual]]
[[ro:Negro spiritual]]
[[ru:Спиричуэлс]]
[[simple:Negro spiritual]]
[[sh:Spiritual]]
[[fi:Negrospirituaali]]
[[sv:Spiritual]]</text>
      <sha1>btly9ynkg28m38rdt9j8kxp262jcw95</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
