<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Spirituality</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28387</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521387443</id>
      <parentid>521386778</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-04T18:09:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ian.thomson</username>
        <id>2489738</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid unsourced revision by [[Special:Contributions/130.15.164.153|130.15.164.153]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29500">{{Distinguish|Spiritualism}}
{{unreliable sources|date=June 2012}} 

{{Spirituality-sidebar}}

'''Spirituality''' is the concept of an ultimate or an alleged immaterial [[reality]];&lt;ref&gt;Ewert Cousins, preface to Antoine Faivre and Jacob Needleman, ''Modern Esoteric Spirituality'', Crossroad Publishing 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; an [[Involution (philosophy)|inner path]] enabling a person to discover the essence of his/her being; or the &quot;deepest values and meanings by which people live.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Philip Sheldrake, ''A Brief History of Spirituality'', Wiley-Blackwell 2007 p. 1-2&lt;/ref&gt; [[Spiritual practice]]s, including [[meditation]], [[prayer]] and [[contemplation]], are intended to develop an individual's inner life. Spiritual experiences can include being [[connected]] to a larger reality, yielding a more comprehensive [[self]]; joining with other individuals or the [[human]] [[community]]; with [[nature]] or the [[cosmos]]; or with the [[Divinity|divine]] realm.&lt;ref&gt;Margaret A. Burkhardt and Mary Gail Nagai-Jacobson, ''Spirituality: living our connectedness'', Delmar Cengage Learning, p. xiii&lt;/ref&gt; Spirituality is often experienced as a source of inspiration or orientation in life.&lt;ref&gt;Kees Waaijman, Spirituality: forms, foundations,methods Leuven: Peeters, 2002  p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; It can encompass [[belief]] in immaterial realities or experiences of the [[immanent]] or [[transcendence (religion)|transcendent]] nature of the world.

==Definition==
Traditionally, many religions have regarded spirituality as an integral aspect of [[religious experience]]. Among other factors, declining membership of organized religions and the growth of [[secularism]] in the [[Western culture|western world]] have given rise to a broader view of spirituality.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Hogan (2010). ''The Culture of Our Thinking in Relation to Spirituality''. Nova Science Publishers: New York.&lt;/ref&gt; The term &quot;spiritual&quot; is now frequently used in contexts in which the term &quot;religious&quot; was formerly employed; compare [[William James|James]]' 1902 lectures on the &quot;Varieties of Religious Experience&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;James, W. (1985). The varieties of religious experience. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press. (Original work published 1902)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gorsuch, R.L., &amp; Miller, W. R. (1999). Assessing spirituality. In W. R. Miller (Ed), Integrating spirituality into treatment (pp. 47-64). Washington, DC: American Psychological Association.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Secular spirituality]] emphasizes [[humanistic]] ideas on [[moral character]] (qualities such as love, [[compassion]], patience, tolerance, forgiveness, contentment, responsibility, harmony, and a concern for others&lt;ref name=Dalai/&gt;{{rp|22}})  - aspects of life and human experience which go beyond a purely materialist view of the world without necessarily accepting belief in a supernatural reality or divine being. Spiritual practices such as mindfulness and meditation can be experienced as beneficial or even necessary for human fulfillment without any supernatural interpretation or explanation.  Spirituality in this context may be a matter of nurturing thoughts, emotions, words and actions that are in harmony with a belief that everything in the universe is mutually dependent; this stance has much in common with some versions of Buddhist spirituality. A modern definition is as follows: 
{{Quote|&quot;Spirituality exists wherever we struggle with the issues of how our lives fit into the greater scheme of things. This is true when our questions never give way to specific answers or give rise to specific practices such as prayer or meditation. We encounter spiritual issues every time we wonder where the universe comes from, why we are here, or what happens when we die. We also become spiritual when we become moved by values such as beauty, love, or creativity that seem to reveal a meaning or power beyond our visible world. An idea or practice is &quot;spiritual&quot; when it reveals our personal desire to establish a felt-relationship with the deepest meanings or powers governing life.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fuller, Robert C. [http://www.beliefnet.com/Entertainment/Books/2002/07/Spiritual-But-Not-Religious.aspx?p=2 Spiritual, But Not Religious]. beliefnet.com. Retrieved on: 2011-12-03&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The [[psychology of religion]] uses a variety of metrics to measure spirituality.&lt;ref name=kapuscinski10&gt;{{cite journal |author=Afton N. Kapuscinski &amp; Kevin S. Masters |year=2010 
 |title=The current status of measures of spirituality: A critical review of scale development 
 |journal=[[Psychology of Religion and Spirituality]] |publisher=[[American Psychological Association]] |volume=2 |issue=4 |pages=191–205 
 |doi=10.1037/a0020498 |issn=1941-1022 |pmid=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spiritual path==
In a wide variety of traditions, spirituality is seen as a path toward one or more of the following: a higher state of awareness, perfection of one's own being, wisdom, or communion with [[God]] or with [[creation myth|creation]]. [[Plato]]'s [[Allegory of the Cave]], which appears in book VII of [[The Republic (Plato)|The Republic]], is a description of such a journey, as are the writings of [[Teresa of Avila]]. The [[Vedas]] and [[Upanishads]] also describe such a path of transformation.{{cn|date=August 2012}}

Disciplines such a path entail may include [[meditation]], [[prayer]], and the contemplation of [[sacred text]]s; [[ethic]]al development.&lt;ref name=Dalai/&gt; Love and/or compassion are often described as the mainstay of spiritual development.&lt;ref name=Dalai/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kalchuri, Bhau: ''Meher Prabhu: Lord Meher, the Biography of the Avatar of the Age [[Meher Baba]]'', Volume Eight, Manifestation, Inc., 1986, p. 22987.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religion==
Whilst the terms ''spirituality'' and ''religion'' both relate to a search for an Absolute or [[God]], there are also differences in their usage. Religion implies a particular faith tradition that includes acceptance of a metaphysical or supernatural reality;&lt;ref name=Dalai&gt;Dalai Lama, ''Ethics for the New Millennium'', NY:Riverhead Books, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|22}}, whereas spirituality is not necessarily bound to any particular religious tradition. Thus  [[William Irwin Thompson]] suggested that &quot;religion is the form spirituality takes in a civilization.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Time Falling Bodies Take to Light: Mythology, Sexuality, and the Origins of Culture|last=Thompson|first=William Irwin|authorlink=William Irwin Thompson|isbn=978-0-312-16062-3|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=u3nB0NpAX60C|year=1981|publisher=St. Martin's Griffin|page=103|pages=280}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Those who speak of spirituality outside of religion often define themselves as ''[[SBNR|spiritual but not religious]]'' and generally believe in the existence of different &quot;spiritual paths,&quot; emphasizing the importance of finding one's own individual path to spirituality. According to one poll, about 24% of the United States population identifies itself as spiritual but not religious.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.beliefnet.com/News/2005/08/Newsweekbeliefnet-Poll-Results.aspx#spiritrel&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Catholic Church]], spirituality is generally seen as an integral part of religion, as much for the laity as for the 'religious' (i.e. those who have taken vows to the Church). There is a variety of [[charism]]s that emphasize particular ways to serve God and humanity. See [[Catholic spirituality]], [[Ignatian spirituality]]. For [[Anglican]] spirituality, see [[Anglican devotions]].

==Science==
{{See also|Relationship between religion and science}}

Since the [[Science in the Age of Enlightenment|scientific revolution]], the relationship of science to religion and spirituality has developed in complex ways.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gascoigne|first=John|title=Cambridge in the Age of the Enlightenment: Science, Religion and Politics|year=1988|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge|pages=300}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=SandR&gt;{{cite book|last=Brooke|first=John Hedley|title=Science and religion: some historical perspectives|year=1991|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historian [[John Hedley Brooke]] describes wide variations: &quot;the natural sciences have been invested with religious meaning, with antireligious implications and, in many contexts, with no religious significance at all.&quot;&lt;ref name=SandR/&gt;{{rp|16}} The popular notion of antagonisms between science and religion&lt;ref&gt;Applebaum, Wilbur. ''Encyclopedia of the scientific revolution: from Copernicus to Newton'' Volume 1800 of Garland reference library of the humanities. Psychology Press, 2000 ISBN 0-8153-1503-1, ISBN 978-0-8153-1503-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;R. Cruz Begay, MPH, DrPH, ''Science And Spirituality'' March 2003, Vol 93, No. 3 | American Journal of Public Health 363 American Public Health Association&lt;/ref&gt; has historically originated with &quot;thinkers with a social or political ax to grind&quot; rather than with the natural philosophers themselves.&lt;ref name=SandR/&gt;{{rp|13}} Though physical and biological scientists today avoid [[supernatural]] explanations to describe [[nature|reality]]&lt;ref&gt;Clarke, Steve. Naturalism, Science, and the Supernatural in ''Sophia'' From the issue entitled &quot;Special APRA Issue&quot; Volume 48, Number 2, 127-142, {{doi|10.1007/s11841-009-0099-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dawkins, R. (1986). The blind watchmaker. New York: Norton.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stroud, B. (2004). The charm of naturalism. In M. De Caro &amp; D. Macarthur (Eds.), Naturalism in question (pp. 21–35). Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; (see [[naturalism (philosophy)|naturalism]]), many scientists continue to consider science and spirituality to be complementary, not contradictory.&lt;ref&gt;Richardson, W. Mark. ''Science and the spiritual quest: new essays by leading scientists'' Psychology Press, 2002 ISBN 0-415-25767-0, ISBN 978-0-415-25767-1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Giniger, Kenneth Seeman &amp; Templeton, John. ''Spiritual evolution: scientists discuss their beliefs''. Templeton Foundation Press, 1998. ISBN 1-890151-16-5, ISBN 978-1-890151-16-4&lt;/ref&gt; [[neuroscience|Neuroscientists]] are trying to learn more about how the brain functions during reported spiritual experiences.&lt;ref&gt;Alper, Matthew, ''The &quot;God&quot; Part of the Brain: A Scientific Interpretation of Human Spirituality and God'' Sourcebooks, Inc., 2008 ISBN 1-4022-1452-9, ISBN 978-1-4022-1452-3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Talan, Jamie ''Science Probes Spirituality'' February/March 2006: Scientific American Mind. [http://www.sciamdigital.com/index.cfm?fa=Products.ViewIssuePreview&amp;ARTICLEID_CHAR=FE043ADA-2B35-221B-65500BA1D8EBA2F7]&lt;/ref&gt;

During the twentieth century the relationship between science and spirituality has been influenced both by [[Freud]]ian psychology, which has accentuated the boundaries between the two areas by accentuating [[individualism]] and [[secularism]], and by developments in [[particle physics]], which reopened the debate about [[Relationship between religion and science|complementarity]] between scientific and religious discourse and rekindled for many an interest in [[holistic]] conceptions of reality.&lt;ref name=SandR/&gt;{{rp|322}} These holistic conceptions were championed by [[New Age]] spiritualists in a type of [[quantum mysticism]] that they claim justifies their spiritual beliefs,&lt;ref name='Capra'&gt;{{Cite document | last = Capra | first = Fritjof | authorlink = Fritjof Capra | coauthors = | title = The Tao of Physics: an exploration of the parallels between modern physics and Eastern mysticism, 3rd ed. | publisher = Shambhala Publications | date = 1991 (1st ed. 1975) | location = Boston, MA | pages = | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = 0-87773-594-8 | postscript = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Laszlo, Ervin, &quot;CosMos:A Co-creator's Guide to the Whole World&quot;, Hay House, Inc, 2008, ISBN 1-4019-1891-3, pg. 53-58&lt;/ref&gt; though [[quantum mechanics|quantum physicists]] themselves on the whole reject such attempts as being [[pseudoscience|pseudoscientific]].&lt;ref&gt;Sheremer, Michael, Quantum Quackery in Scientific American (January 2005), 292, 34. {{doi|10.1038/scientificamerican0105-34}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Silverman, Mark P. ''Quantum superposition: counterintuitive consequences of coherence, entanglement, and interference'' Frontiers collection. Springer, 2008 ISBN 3-540-71883-4, ISBN 978-3-540-71883-3. p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal well-being==
In keeping with a general increase in interest in spirituality and [[alternative medicine|complementary and alternative treatments]], prayer has garnered attention among some [[behavioral science|behavioral scientists]]. Masters and Spielmans&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1007/s10865-007-9106-7 | last1 = Masters | first1 = K.S. | last2 = Spielmans | first2 = G.I | year = 2007 | title = Prayer and health: review, meta-analysis, and research agenda | url = | journal = Journal of Behavioral Medicine | volume = 30 | issue = 4| pages = 329–338 | pmid = 17487575 }}&lt;/ref&gt; have conducted a [[meta-analysis]] of the effects of distant [[Intercession|intercessory]] prayer, but detected no discernible effects.

Spirituality has played a central role in [[self-help]] movements such as [[Alcoholics Anonymous]]: &quot;...if an alcoholic failed to perfect and enlarge his spiritual life through work and self-sacrifice for others, he could not survive the certain trials and low spots ahead....&quot;&lt;ref&gt;'''Alcoholics Anonymous''', p.14-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Philosophers across many traditions, from [[Stoicism]] to [[Buddhism]], have suggested that a [[spiritual practice]] is essential for [[Emotional well-being|personal well being]]. Such practices do not necessarily include a belief in supernatural beings. Contemporary authors, too, suggest that spirituality develops [[inner peace]] and forms a foundation for [[happiness]]. [[Meditation]] and similar practices may help any practitioner cultivate his or her [[introspection|inner life]] and character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wilkinson|first=Tony|title=The lost art of being happy : spirituality for sceptics|year=2007|publisher=Findhorn Press|location=Findhorn|isbn=1844091163}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{verify credibility|date=June 2012}} &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Browner|first=Matthieu Ricard ; translated by Jesse|title=Happiness: A guide to developing life's most important skill.|year=2003|publisher=Little Brown|location=New York|isbn=0316167258|edition=1st pbk. ed.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Near-death experience (NDE)==
{{Main|Near death experience}}
If [[consciousness]] exists apart from the body, which includes the brain, one is attached not only to the material world, but to a non-temporal (spiritual) world as well. This thesis is considered to be analyzed by testing the reports from people who have experienced [[death]]. However, some researchers consider that NDEs are actually [[Rapid eye movement sleep|REM]] intrusions triggered in the [[Human brain|brain]] by traumatic events like [[cardiac arrest]].&lt;ref&gt;http://science.howstuffworks.com/science-life-after-death.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sacredness==
Social scientists have defined spirituality as the search for &quot;the [[sacred]],&quot; where &quot;the sacred&quot; is broadly defined as that which is set apart from the ordinary and worthy of veneration. Spirituality can be sought not only through traditional organized religions, but also through movements such as the [[feminist theology]] and ecological spirituality (see [[Green politics]]). Spirituality is associated with [[mental health]], managing [[substance abuse]], [[marriage|marital]] functioning, [[parenting]], and [[life skills|coping]]. It has been suggested that spirituality also leads to finding purpose and [[meaning of life|meaning in life]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PP11&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
  | last = Snyder
  | first = C.R.
  | author-link = C. R. Snyder
  | last2 = Lopez
  | first2 = Shane J.
  | title = Positive Psychology
  | publisher = Sage Publications, Inc.
  | year = 2007
  | chapter = 11
  | isbn = 0-7619-2633-X
  | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

==Origin==
See [[Timeline of religion]] and [[Evolutionary origin of religions]]

==History==
{{See also|History of religion}}

Words translatable as 'spirituality' first began to arise in the 5th century and only entered common use toward the end of the Middle Ages.&lt;ref&gt; Jones, L. G., &quot;&quot;A thirst for god or consumer spirituality? Cultivating disciplined practices of being engaged by god,&quot; in L. Gregory Jones and James J. Buckley eds., Spirituality and Social Embodiment, Oxford: Blackwell, 1997, 3-28, p4, n4.&lt;/ref&gt; Spiritual innovators who operated within the context of a religious tradition often became [[marginalized]] or suppressed as [[heresy|heretics]] or separated out as [[Schism (religion)|schismatics]]. In these circumstances, [[anthropologist]]s generally treat so-called &quot;spiritual&quot; practices such as [[shamanism]] in the sphere of the religious, and class even non-traditional activities such as those of Robespierre's [[Cult of the Supreme Being]] in the province of religion.&lt;ref&gt;Jordan, David, &quot;The Revolutionary Career of Maximilien Robespierre&quot;, University of Chicago Press, 1989, ISBN 0-226-41037-4, pg. 201&lt;/ref&gt;

Eighteenth-century [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] thinkers, often opposed to [[clericalism]] and skeptical of religion, sometimes came to express their more emotional responses to the world under the rubric of [[Sublime (philosophy)|&quot;the Sublime&quot;]] rather than discussing &quot;spirituality&quot;. The spread of the ideas of [[modernity]] began to diminish the role of religion in society and in popular thought.{{citation needed|date=June 2011}} [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]] (1803–1882) was a pioneer of the idea of spirituality as a distinct field.&lt;ref&gt;Schmidt, Leigh Eric. ''Restless Souls : The Making of American Spirituality''. San Francisco: Harper, 2005. ISBN 0-06-054566-6&lt;/ref&gt; Important early 20th century writers who studied the phenomenon of spirituality, and their works, include [[William James]], ''[[The Varieties of Religious Experience]]'' (1902), and [[Rudolph Otto]], especially ''[[The Idea of the Holy]]'' (1917). {{citation needed|date=June 2011}} The distinction between the spiritual and the religious became more common in the popular mind during the late 20th century with the rise of [[secularism]] and the advent of the [[New Age]] movement.  Authors such as [[Chris Griscom]] and [[Shirley MacLaine]] explored it in numerous ways in their books. [[Paul Heelas]] noted the development within New Age circles of what he called &quot;seminar spirituality&quot;:&lt;ref&gt;Paul Heelas, ''The New Age Movement: The Celebration of the Self and the Sacralization of Modernity''. Oxford: Blackwell, 1996, page 60. Cited in [[Anthony Giddens]]: ''Sociology''. Cambridge: Polity, 2001, page 554.&lt;/ref&gt; structured offerings complementing [[consumerism|consumer]] choice with spiritual options.

==Study==
In the late 19th century a Pakistani scholar [[Khwaja Shamsuddin Azeemi]] wrote of and taught about the science of [[Islamic]] spirituality, of which the best known form remains the [[Sufi]] tradition (famous through [[Rumi]] and [[Hafiz Shirazi|Hafiz]]) in which a spiritual master or [[Pir (Sufism)|''pir'']] transmits spiritual discipline to students.&lt;ref&gt;
Azeemi,K.S., &quot;Muraqaba: The Art and Science of Sufi Meditation&quot;. Houston: Plato, 2005. (ISBN 0-9758875-4-8), Pg. xi&lt;/ref&gt;

Building on both the [[Western mystery tradition|Western esoteric tradition]] and [[theosophy]],&lt;ref&gt;Olav Hammer, ''Claiming Knowledge: Strategies of Epistemology from Theosophy to the New Age'', ISBN 90-04-13638-X&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rudolf Steiner]] and others in the [[anthroposophy|anthroposophic]] tradition have attempted to apply systematic methodology to the study of spiritual phenomena,&lt;ref&gt;Robert McDermott, ''The Essential Steiner'', ISBN 0-06-065345-0, pp. 3-4&lt;/ref&gt; building upon [[ontological]] and [[epistemological]] questions that arose out of [[transcendental philosophy]].&lt;ref&gt;Jonael Schickler, ''Metaphysics as Christology: An odyssey of the Self from Kant and Hegel to Steiner'' (Ashgate New Critical Thinking: 2005) pp. 138ff&lt;/ref&gt; This enterprise does not attempt to redefine natural science, but to explore inner experience – especially our thinking – with the same rigor that we apply to outer (sensory) experience.

==See also==
{{Portal|Spirituality}}
{{refbegin|3}}
* [[Afterlife]]
* [[Deities]]
* [[Parapsychology]]
* [[Quantum mysticism]]
* [[Reason]]
* [[Religion]]
* [[Skepticism]]
* [[Spiritual But Not Religious]]
* [[Supernatural]]
* [[Superstition]]
* [[Awareness]]
{{refend}}

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*''A Course in Miracles''. 2nd ed., Mill Valley: Foundation for Inner Peace, 1992, ISBN 0-9606388-9-X.
*[[Khwaja Shamsuddin Azeemi|Azeemi, K.S.]]''Muraqaba: The Art and Science of Sufi Meditation''. Houston: Plato, 2005. (ISBN 0-9758875-4-8)
* {{cite book |author= [[Meher Baba|Baba, Meher]]|title= ''[http://www.ambppct.org/meherbaba/Book_Files/POL.pdf The Path of Love]''|publisher=Sheriar Press |location=Myrtle Beach, S.C. |year=2000 |pages= |isbn=1-880619-23-7 |oclc= |doi= |accessdate=}}
*Bjelica, Drago ''The Bible For The New Age'' ([http://thebibleforthenewage.com Online]). 2009.
*Bolman, L. G., and Deal, T. E. ''Leading With Soul''. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass, 1995.
*Borysenko, J. ''A Woman's Journey to God''. New York: Riverhead Books, 1999.
*Cannon, K. G. ''Katie's Canon: Womanism and the Soul of the Black Community''. New York: Continuum, 1996.
*Cappel, Constance, Dera Poetry, Philadelphia, PA: Xlibris, 2007.
*Cheroff, Seth, ''The Manual For Living''. CO Spirit Scope, 2008.
*{{Cite book|last=Clift|first=Jean Dalby|authorlink=Jean Dalby Clift|year=2008|title=The Mystery of Love and the Path of Prayer|isbn=978-1-4404-6637-3}}
*Deloria, V., Jr. ''[[God is Red]]''. 2d Ed. Golden, Co: North American Press, 1992, ISBN 1-55591-904-9.
*Dillard, C. B.; Abdur-Rashid, D.; and Tyson, C. A. &quot;''My Soul is a Witness''.&quot; ''International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education 13'', no. 5 (September 2000): 447-462.
*Dirkx, J. M. &quot;''Nurturing Soul in Adult Learning''.&quot; in ''Transformative Learning in Action''. ''New Directions for Adult and Continuing Education'' No. 74, edited by P. Cranton, pp.&amp;nbsp;79–88. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass, 1997.
*Downey, Michael. ''Understanding Christian Spirituality''. New York: Paulist Press, 1997.
*Eck, Diana L. ''A New Religious America''. San Francisco: Harper, 2001.
*Elkins D.N. et al. (1998)Toward a humanistic-phenomenological spirituality: definition, description and measurement. ''Journal of Humanistic Psychology'' 28(4), 5-18
*English, L., and Gillen, M., eds. ''Addressing the Spiritual Dimensions of Adult Learning''. ''New Directions for Adult and Continuing Education'', No. 85. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass, 2000.
* Goddart, Michael. Spiritual Revolution: A Seeker's Guide; 52 Powerful Principles for Your Mind &amp; Soul, DeVorss, 1997.
*Haisch, Bernard ''The God Theory: Universes, Zero-point Fields, and What's Behind It All'', ([http://www.thegodtheory.com/preface.html Preface]), Red Wheel/Weiser, 2006, ISBN 1-57863-374-5
*{{Cite journal | last1 = Hein | first1 = David | year = 1997 | title = Christianity and Traditional Lakota / Dakota Spirituality: A Jamesian Interpretation | url = | journal = The McNeese Review | volume = 35 | issue = | pages = 128–38 }}
*Hein, David, and Edward Hugh Henderson, editors. ''Captured by the Crucified: The Practical Theology of Austin Farrer''. New York and London: Continuum / T &amp; T Clark, 2004. About the spiritual theology of [[Austin Farrer]]; includes chapter on &quot;Farrer's Spirituality&quot; by [[Diogenes Allen]].
*Hein, David, and Charles R. Henery, editors. ''Spiritual Counsel in the Anglican Tradition''. Eugene, OR: Wipf &amp; Stock; Cambridge, UK: James Clarke &amp; Co., 2010.
*Holtje, D. (1995). ''From Light to Sound: The Spiritual Progression''. Temecula, CA: MasterPath, Inc. ISBN 1-885949-00-6
*{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1046/j.1365-2648.1998.00519.x | last1 = Martsolf | first1 = D.S. | last2 = Mickley | first2 = J.R. | year = 1998 | title = The concept of spirituality in nursing theories: differing world-views and extent of focus | url = | journal = Journal of Advanced Nursing | volume = 27 | issue = 2| pages = 294–303 | pmid = 9515639 }}
* {{Cite journal | doi = 10.1007/s10865-007-9106-7 | last1 = Masters | first1 = K.S. | last2 = Spielmans | first2 = G.I | year = 2007 | title = Prayer and health: review, meta-analysis, and research agenda | url = | journal = Journal of Behavioral Medicine | volume = 30 | issue = 4| pages = 329–338 | pmid = 17487575 }}
*[[Harold W. Percival|Percival, Harold W.]] Thinking and Destiny, ISBN 0-911650-06-7
*Perry, Whitall N. ''A Treasury of Traditional Wisdom: An Encyclopedia of Humankind’s Spiritual Truth''. Louisville: Fons Vitae books, 2000, ISBN 1-887752-33-1
*Ram Chandra(Shajahanpur). ''Reality at Dawn''.
*Roberts, Jane (1974). ''The Nature of Personal Reality''. Prentice-Hall. reprinted (1994) Amber-Allen Publishing. ISBN 1-878424-06-8
*Sri Nisargadatta Maharaj, ''I Am That'', Acorn Press, 1990, ISBN 0-89386-022-0
*Schmidt, Leigh Eric. ''Restless Souls : The Making of American Spirituality''. San Francisco: Harper, 2005. ISBN 0-06-054566-6
*{{cite journal |title=Spirituality in the academy
|author=Sandra M. Schneiders |authorlink=Sandra M. Schneiders |journal=[[Theological Studies (journal)|Theological Studies]] |publisher= |volume=50 |issue=4 |pages=676–697
|url=http://pao.chadwyck.com/articles/displayItem.do?QueryType=articles&amp;QueryIndex=journal&amp;ResultsID=1307059952A444264&amp;ItemNumber=3&amp;BackTo=journalid&amp;BackToParam=QueryType=journals|ItemID=3258|year=1989|doi= |issn=0040-5639}}
*{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1080/09518390500298188 | last1 = Shahjahan | first1 = R. A. | year = 2005 | title = Spirituality in the academy: Reclaiming from the margins and evoking a transformative way of knowing the world | url = | journal = International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education | volume = 18 | issue = 6| pages = 685–711 }}
*{{Cite journal | doi = 10.1353/rhe.0.0166 | last1 = Shahjahan | first1 = R.A. | year = 2010 | title = Toward a spiritual praxis: The role of spirituality among faculty of color teaching for social justice | url = | journal = [[The Review of Higher Education]] | volume = 33 | issue = 4| pages = 473–512 }}
*{{cite book |title=Spirituality and history: Questions of interpretation and method
|last=Sheldrake |first=Philip |authorlink=Philip Sheldrake |year=1998
|publisher=Orbis |location=Maryknoll, NY |isbn=1-57075-203-6
|url=http://www.amazon.com/Spirituality-History-Questions-Interpretation-Method/dp/1570752036/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1310081301&amp;sr=1-1}}
*Steiner, Rudolf, ''How to Know Higher Worlds: A Modern Path of Initiation''. New York: Anthroposophic Press, (1904) 1994. ISBN 0-88010-372-8
*Steiner, Rudolf, ''Theosophy: An Introduction to the Supersensible Knowledge of the World and the Destination of Man''. London: Rudolf Steiner Press, (1904) 1994
*Spenard, Michael (April 11, 2011) [http://www.memeoid.net/books/Spenard/Dueling_with_Dualism-Spenard.pdf &quot;Dueling with Dualism: the forlorn quest for the immaterial soul&quot;], essay. An historical account of mind body duality and a comprehensive conceptual and empirical critique on the position. ISBN 978-0-578-08288-2
*Thompson, William Irwin, ''The Time Falling Bodies Take to Light: Mythology, Sexuality, and the Origins of Culture'' (New York: St. Martin's Press, 1981).
*Wapnick, Kenneth, ''The Message of A Course in Miracles''. Roscoe, NY: Foundation for A Course in Miracles, 1997, ISBN 0-933291-25-6.
*Wakefield, Gordon S.(ed.), ''A Dictionary of Christian Spirituality''. London: SCM, 1983.
*Wilkinson, Tony, ''The Lost Art of Being Happy - Spirituality for Sceptics'' Findhorn Press 2007, ISBN 978-1-84409-116-4
*Zagano, Phyllis ''Twentieth-Century Apostles: Contemporary Spirituality in Action'' (Collegeville, MN: Liturgical Press, 1999)
*Zagano, Phyllis &quot;Woman to Woman: An Anthology of Women's Spiritualities (Collegeville, MN: Liturgical PRess) 1993.
*Zajonc, Arthur, ''The New Physics and Cosmology Dialogues with the Dalai Lama''. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004,ISBN 0-19-515994-2.

==External links==
{{wikiquote|Spirituality}}
{{Wikiversity|Spirituality}}
*[http://www.dmoz.org/Society/Religion_and_Spirituality/ Religion and Spirituality at the Open Directory Project]

{{religion topics}}

[[Category:Spirituality| ]]
[[Category:Positive psychology]]

[[ar:روحانية]]
[[bs:Duhovnost]]
[[br:Speredelezh]]
[[ca:Espiritualitat]]
[[cs:Spiritualita]]
[[da:Spiritualitet]]
[[de:Spiritualität]]
[[es:Espiritualidad]]
[[eo:Spiriteco]]
[[fa:معنویت]]
[[hif:Spirituality]]
[[fr:Spiritualité]]
[[fur:Spiritualitât]]
[[ko:영성]]
[[hi:आध्यात्मिकता]]
[[hr:Duhovnost]]
[[is:Andleg viðleitni]]
[[it:Spiritualità]]
[[he:רוחניות]]
[[sw:Maisha ya kiroho]]
[[ky:Рухийлик]]
[[lb:Spiritualismus]]
[[lt:Dvasingumas]]
[[mr:अध्यात्म]]
[[ms:Kerohanian]]
[[mn:Спиритуалити]]
[[nl:Spiritualiteit]]
[[new:अध्यात्मवाद]]
[[ja:スピリチュアリティ]]
[[no:Åndelighet]]
[[ps:روحانيت]]
[[pl:Duchowość]]
[[pt:Espiritualidade]]
[[ru:Духовность]]
[[sq:Spiritualiteti]]
[[simple:Spirituality]]
[[sl:Duhovnost]]
[[sr:Duhovnost]]
[[sh:Duhovnost]]
[[fi:Hengellisyys]]
[[sv:Andlighet]]
[[tl:Espirituwalidad]]
[[ta:ஆன்மிகம்]]
[[tr:Spiritüalizm]]
[[uk:Духовність]]
[[war:Espiritualidad]]
[[yi:גייסטליכקייט]]
[[bat-smg:Dvasingoms]]
[[zh:靈性]]</text>
      <sha1>l3cp3pihpo506liwwvv86wpfh4g6jty</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
