<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Stations of the Cross</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>337401</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519408338</id>
      <parentid>519408222</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-23T15:54:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MPSchneiderLC</username>
        <id>14801983</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Gallery */ Fixing style/layout errors - forgot to change wikilinks</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19006">[[File:StationXII.JPG|thumb|250px|The 12th Station of the Cross - Jesus dies on the Cross. [[St. Raphael's Cathedral (Dubuque)|St. Raphael's Cathedral]], [[Dubuque, Iowa|Dubuque]], [[Iowa]].]]
'''Stations of the Cross''' (or '''Way of the Cross'''; in [[Latin]], '''Via Crucis'''; also called the '''[[Via Dolorosa]]''' or '''Way of Sorrows''', or simply, '''The Way''') is a series of artistic representations, very often sculptural, depicting [[Christ Carrying the Cross]] to [[Crucifixion of Jesus|his crucifixion]] in the final hours (or [[Passion (Christianity)|Passion]]) of [[Jesus]] before he died, and the devotions using that series to commemorate the Passion, often moving physically around a set of stations.  The vast majority of [[Roman Catholic]] churches now contain such a series, typically placed at intervals along the side walls of the [[nave]]; in most churches these are small plaques with [[relief]]s or paintings, simpler than most of the examples shown here.  The tradition as chapel devotion began with [[St. Francis of Assisi]] and extended throughout the [[Roman Catholic Church]] in the medieval period. It is commonly observed in [[Lutheranism]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.trinitycamphill.org/Way%20of%20the%20Cross/Introduction.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://pastorzip.blogspot.com/2007/04/stations-of-cross.html&lt;/ref&gt; and amongst the Anglo-Catholic wing of [[Anglicanism]]. It may be done at any time, but is most commonly done during the Season of [[Lent]], especially on [[Good Friday]] and on Friday evenings during Lent.

==History==
[[File:HK 16th Caine Rd 60405 lob.JPG|thumb|left|Typical placement, in [[Hong Kong Catholic Cathedral of the Immaculate Conception|Hong Kong Catholic Cathedral]]]]
[[File:SantCompostela64.jpg|thumb|left|10th Station of the Cross - Jesus is stripped of His garments &lt;br /&gt;[[Cathedral of Santiago de Compostela]], Spain.]]
The Stations of the Cross originated in pilgrimages  to [[Jerusalem]].  A desire to reproduce the holy places in other lands seems to have manifested itself at quite an early date. At the monastery of Santo Stefano at Bologna a group of connected chapels was constructed as early as the 5th century, by [[St. Petronius]], Bishop of Bologna, which was intended to represent the more important shrines of Jerusalem, and in consequence, this monastery became familiarly known as &quot;Hierusalem.&quot; These may perhaps be regarded as the germ from which the Stations afterwards developed, though it is tolerably certain that nothing that we have before about the 15th century can strictly be called a Way of the Cross in the modern sense.  Although several travelers who visited the Holy Land during the twelfth, thirteenth, and 14th centuries (e.g. [[Riccoldo da Monte di Croce]], [[Burchard of Mount Sion]], [[James of Verona]]),&lt;ref name=THURSTON&gt;[http://www.archive.org/stream/stationsofcrossa00thuruoft/stationsofcrossa00thuruoft_djvu.txt THURSTON, Herbert: The Stations of the Cross]&lt;/ref&gt; mention a &quot;Via Sacra,&quot; i.e., a settled route along which pilgrims were conducted, there is nothing in their accounts to identify this with the Way of the Cross, as we understand it.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}  The devotion of the [[Via Dolorosa]], for which there have been a number of variant routes in Jerusalem, was probably developed by the [[Franciscans]] after they were granted administration of the Christian holy places in Jerusalem in 1342.  

The earliest use of the word &quot;stations,&quot; as applied to the accustomed halting-places in the Via Sacra at Jerusalem, occurs in the narrative of an English pilgrim, William Wey, who visited the Holy Land in the mid-15th century, and described pilgrims following the footsteps of Christ to the cross. In 1521 a book called Geystlich Strass was printed with illustrations of the stations in the Holy Land.&lt;ref name=THURSTON/&gt;

During the 15th and 16th centuries the Franciscans began to build a series of outdoor shrines in Europe to duplicate their counterparts in the Holy Land.  The number of stations varied between seven and thirty; seven was common. These were usually placed, often in small buildings, along the approach to a church, as in a set of 1490 by [[Adam Kraft]], leading to the Johanneskirche in [[Nuremberg]].&lt;ref&gt;Schiller, Gertrud,  ''Iconography of Christian Art, Vol. II'', p. 82, 1972 (English trans from German), Lund Humphries, London, ISBN 0-85331-324-5&lt;/ref&gt;  A number of rural examples were established as attractions in their own right, usually on attractive wooded hills.  These include the [[Sacro Monte di Domodossola]] (1657) and [[Sacro Monte di Belmonte]] (1712), and form part of the [[Sacri Monti of Piedmont and Lombardy]] World Heritage Site, together with other examples on different devotional themes.  In these the sculptures are often approaching life-size and very elaborate.  In 1686, in answer to their petition, Pope Innocent XI granted to the Franciscans the right to erect stations within their churches.  In 1731, Pope Clement XII extended to all churches the right to have the stations, provided that a Franciscan father erected them, with the consent of the local bishop.  At the same time the number was  fixed at fourteen.  In 1857, the bishops of England were allowed to erect the stations by themselves, without the intervention of a Franciscan priest, and in 1862 this right was extended to bishops throughout the church.&lt;ref&gt;''The Catholic Encyclopedia'' (1907)s.v. &quot;The Way of the Cross.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spiritual significance==
The object of the Stations is to help the faithful to make a spiritual pilgrimage of prayer, through meditating upon the chief scenes of Christ's sufferings and death.  It has become one of the most popular devotions for Roman Catholics, and is often performed in a [[Acts of reparation|spirit of reparation]] for the sufferings and insults that Jesus endured during His Passion.&lt;ref&gt;Ann Ball, 2003 ''Encyclopedia of Catholic Devotions and Practices ''ISBN 087973910X&lt;/ref&gt;

In his [[encyclical]] letter, ''[[Miserentissimus Redemptor]]'', on reparations, [[Pope Pius XI]] called [[Acts of Reparation to Jesus Christ]] a duty for Catholics and referred to them as &quot;''some sort of compensation to be rendered for the injury''&quot; with respect to the sufferings of Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/pius_xi/encyclicals/documents/hf_p-xi_enc_08051928_miserentissimus-redemptor_en.html ''Miserentissimus Redemptor''], Encyclical of [[Pope Pius XI]]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Pope John Paul II]] referred to [[Acts of Reparation]] as the &quot;''unceasing effort to stand beside the endless crosses on which the Son of God continues to be crucified''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Pope John Paul II, [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/letters/2000/documents/hf_jp-ii_let_20001021_riparatrici_en.html Letter to Cardinal Fiorenzo Angelini, for the 50th anniversary of the Benedictine Sisters of Reparation of the Holy Face], 27 September 2000 (Vatican archives)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Stations==
===Traditional form===
[[File:Normandie Manche Avranches3 tango7174.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|Collected enamel set, Notre-Dame-des-Champs, Avranches]]
The early set of seven scenes was usually numbers 2,3,4,7,6 and 14 from the list below.&lt;ref&gt;Schiller, 82&lt;/ref&gt;  The standard set from the 17th to 20th centuries has consisted of 14 pictures or sculptures depicting the following scenes:
#[[Sanhedrin Trial of Jesus|Jesus is condemned to death]]
#Jesus carries His cross
#Jesus falls the first time
#Jesus meets [[Blessed Virgin Mary|His mother]]
#[[Simon of Cyrene]] helps Jesus to carry the cross
#[[Saint Veronica|Veronica]] wipes the face of Jesus
#Jesus falls the second time
#Jesus meets the women of Jerusalem
#Jesus falls the third time
#Jesus is stripped of his garments
#[[Crucifixion of Jesus|Crucifixion]]: Jesus is nailed to the cross
#Jesus dies on the cross
#Jesus is taken down from the cross ([[Deposition of Christ|Deposition]] or [[Lamentation of Christ|Lamentation]])
#Jesus is [[Entombment of Christ|laid in the tomb]].

Although not traditionally part of the Stations, the [[Resurrection of Jesus]] is sometimes included as a fifteenth station.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = The Official Web Site for the Archdiocese of Detroit | accessdate=2012-02-13 | url=http://www.aodonline.org/aodonline-sqlimages/stationsofthecross/stations.pdf | quote=In some contemporary Stations of the Cross, a fifteenth station has been added to commemorate the Resurrection of the Lord.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = Fr. William Saunders | accessdate = 2009-04-04 | url = http://www.ewtn.com/library/ANSWERS/STCROSS.HTM | quote = Because of the intrinsic relationship between the passion and death of our Lord with His resurrection, several of the devotional booklets now include a 15th station, which commemorates the Resurrection. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scriptural Way of the Cross===
{{Main|Scriptural Way of the Cross}}

Out of the fourteen traditional Stations of the Cross, only eight have clear scriptural foundation. Stations 3, 4, 6, 7, and 9 are not specifically attested to in the gospels (in particular, no evidence exists of station 6 ever being known before medieval times) and Station 13 (representing Jesus's body being taken down off the cross and laid in the arms of His mother Mary) seems to embellish the gospels' record, which states that Joseph of Arimathea took Jesus down from the cross and buried him. To provide a version of this devotion more closely aligned with the biblical accounts, [[Pope John Paul II]] introduced a new form of devotion, called the [[Scriptural Way of the Cross]] on [[Good Friday]] 1991. He celebrated that form many times but not exclusively at the [[Colosseum]] in [[Rome]].&lt;ref&gt;Joseph M Champlin, ''The Stations of the Cross With Pope John Paul II'' Liguori Publications, 1994, ISBN 0-89243-679-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pope John Paul II,  [http://www.pcf.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/speeches/documents/hf_jp-ii_spe_20000421_via-crucis_en.html Meditation and Prayers for the Stations of the Cross at the Colosseum], Good Friday, 2000&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, [[Pope Benedict XVI]] approved this set of stations for meditation and public celebration: They follow this sequence: 

# Jesus in the Garden of Gethsemane,
# Jesus is betrayed by Judas and arrested,
# Jesus is condemned by the [[Sanhedrin]],
# [[Denial of Peter|Jesus is denied by Peter]],
# Jesus is judged by Pilate,
# Jesus is scourged and crowned with thorns,
# Jesus takes up His cross,
# Jesus is helped by Simon to carry His cross,
# Jesus meets the women of Jerusalem,
# Jesus is crucified,
# Jesus promises His kingdom to the repentant thief,
# Jesus entrusts Mary and John to each other,
# Jesus dies on the cross,
# Jesus is laid in the tomb.

==Modern usage==
[[File:Cristo caído (Nicola Fumo, San Ginés, Madrid) 01.jpg|thumb|left|Fallen Christ sculpture by [[Nicolò Fumo]], 1698.]]
The devotion may be conducted personally by the faithful, making their way from one station to another and saying the prayers, or by having an officiating celebrant move from cross to cross while the faithful make the responses. The stations themselves must consist of, at the very least, fourteen wooden crosses, pictures alone do not suffice, and they must be blessed by someone with the authority to erect stations.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15569a.htm&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dubious|date=January 2010}}

In the Roman Catholic Church, [[Pope John Paul II]] led an annual public prayer of the Stations of the Cross at the Roman [[Colosseum]] on Good Friday. Originally, the Pope himself carried the cross from station to station, but in his last years when age and infirmity limited his strength, John Paul presided over the celebration from a stage on the [[Palatine Hill]], while others carried the cross. Just days prior to his death in 2005, Pope John Paul II observed the Stations of the Cross from his private chapel. Each year a different person is invited to write the meditation texts for the Stations. Past composers of the Papal Stations include several non-Catholics. The Pope himself wrote the texts for the [[Great Jubilee]] in 2000 and used the traditional Stations.
[[File:Ulm Neu-Ulm Lebendiger Kreuzweg 2011 Bild 11.JPG|thumb|right|Station 5: [[Simon of Cyrene]] helps Jesus carry the Cross, [[Good Friday]] procession 2011 at [[Ulm]], [[Germany]]]]
The celebration of the Stations of the Cross is especially common on the Fridays of Lent, especially [[Good Friday]]. Community celebrations are usually accompanied by various songs and prayers. Particularly common as musical accompaniment is the  [[Stabat Mater]].  At the end of each station the [[Adoramus Te]] is sometimes sung. The Alleluia is also sung, except during Lent.

Structurally, [[Mel Gibson]]'s 2004 film, ''[[The Passion of the Christ]]'', follows the Stations of the Cross.&lt;ref&gt;[http://old.usccb.org/movies/p/thepassionofthechrist.shtml Review], United States Conference of Catholic Bishops, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; The fourteenth and last station, the Burial, is not prominently depicted (compared to the other thirteen) but it is implied since the last shot before credit titles is Jesus resurrected and about to leave the tomb.

==Debates==
[[File:WallfahrtskircheMussenhausenKreuzwegStation10.jpg|thumb|Station 10 from a [[Rococo]] German church]]
===Place of Christ's resurrection===
Some modern liturgists&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | isbn = 978-0-06-065338-5 | page = 1222 | last = McBrien | first = Richard P.  | coauthors = Harold W. Attridge | title = The HarperCollins encyclopedia of Catholicism | year = 1995 }}&lt;/ref&gt; say the traditional Stations of the Cross are incomplete without a final scene depicting the [[empty tomb]] and/or the [[resurrection of Jesus]], because Jesus' rising from the dead was an integral part of His salvific work on earth.  Advocates of the traditional form of the Stations ending with the body of Jesus being placed in the tomb say the Stations are intended as a meditation on the [[Atonement in Christianity|atoning]] death of Jesus, and not as a complete picture of His life, death, and resurrection.  

The [[Stations of the Resurrection]] (also known by the Latin name of ''Via Lucis'') are used in some churches at [[Easter]]tide to meditate on the Resurrection and [[Ascension of Jesus Christ]].

===Ukrainian Byzantine Catholic Church===
As part of a process of de-Latinization, the Ukrainian Byzantine Catholic Church eliminated the devotion of the Stations of the Cross{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}. In response to this, a schismatic group called the [[Priestly Society of Saint Josaphat|Society of Saint Josaphat]] (SSJK) has formed with a seminary of its own in [[Lviv]] with thirty students at present{{Citation needed|date=February 2012}}.

==Music==
[[Franz Liszt]] wrote a ''Via Crucis'' for choir, soloists and piano or organ or harmonium in 1879.  [[David Bowie]] regarded his 1976 song, &quot;[[Station to Station (song)|Station to Station]]&quot; as &quot;very much concerned with the stations of the cross.&quot;&lt;ref name=Q97X&gt;{{Citation | last=Cavanagh | first=David | title=ChangesFiftyBowie | journal=[[Q (magazine)|Q magazine]] | year=1997 | month=February | pages=52–59}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Michael Valenti (known predominantly as a Broadway composer) wrote, with librettist Diane Seymour, an oratorio depicting the fourteen Stations of the Cross entitled &quot;The Way.&quot; It was premiered in 1991.  [[Stefano Vagnini]]'s 2002 modular oratorio, ''Via Crucis'',&lt;ref&gt;Falcon Valley Music Ed., Stefano Vagnini, ''Via Crucis'', Rome, Italy, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; composition for organ, computer, choir, string orchestra and brass quartet, depicts the fourteen Stations of the Cross.

As the Stations of the Cross are prayed during the season of Lent in Catholic churches, each station is traditionally followed by a verse of the Stabat Mater, composed in the 13th century by Franciscan Jacopane da Todi.

==Gallery==

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Stations of the Cross Church of St Casimir 01 AB.jpg|Stations in [[Church of St. Casimir the Prince]]
Image:Crucifixion from the Stations of the Cross.jpg|From [[The Cloisters]] in [[New York City]]. 
Image:14._Station03114.JPG|Station in [[Upper Swabia]], [[Germany]]
Image:Fuensantawaycross.JPG|Station in Fuensanta [[Sanctuary]], [[Murcia]], [[Spain]]
Image:Sacre Coeur - Stations du Chemin de Croix.jpg|Elaborate 19th century stations I and II, [[Basilique du Sacré-Cœur, Paris|Sacré-Coeur]] Paris 
Image:5267-20080122-jerusalem-tomb-of-jesus.jpg|Tomb of Jesus
Image:Stations at SHAS.jpg|The students at [[Sacred Heart Apostolic School]] praying the Stations of the Cross on [[Good Friday]], 2009
&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: Image:Hoar Cross 055.JPG|Second Station in [[The Church of the Holy Angels, Hoar Cross]], [[Staffordshire]] {{Deletable image-caption|1={{subst:#time:l, j F Y| + 7 days}}|date=February 2012}} --&gt;
Image:Droga krzyżowa we Woźnikach.jpg|14th Station at the Franciscan Monastery in [[Woźniki]], [[Poland]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

== See also ==
{{Devotions to Christ}}
* [[Acts of Reparation to Jesus Christ]]
* [[Life of Jesus in the New Testament]]
* [[Sacri Monti of Piedmont and Lombardy]]
* [[Our Lady of Sorrows|Seven Sorrows of Mary]]
* [[The Station of the Cross]], a Roman Catholic-affiliated radio branding

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Stations of the Cross}}
*[http://www.via-crucis.net/ 14 black and white watercolors in a multilingual Way of the Cross]
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15569a.htm &quot;Way of the Cross&quot;] article from ''[[The Catholic Encyclopedia]]''
*[http://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/documents/index_via-crucis_en.html A list of recent Via Crucis used by The Vatican on Good Fridays.].
*[http://www.usccb.org/nab/stations.htm Alternate Stations of the Cross as celebrated by Pope John Paul II on Good Friday 1991]

{{Catholic Prayers}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stations Of The Cross}}
[[Category:Stations of the Cross| ]]
[[Category:Cross symbols]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic Church art by subject]]
[[Category:Christian iconography]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic devotions]]
[[Category:Franciscan spirituality]]
[[Category:Sorrowful Mysteries]]
[[Category:Christian terms]]
[[Category:Crucifixion of Jesus in art]]

[[als:Kreuzweg]]
[[bcl:Bisita Altares]]
[[ca:Via Crucis]]
[[cs:Křížová cesta]]
[[de:Kreuzweg]]
[[es:Viacrucis]]
[[eo:Via crucis]]
[[fr:Chemin de croix]]
[[gl:Viacrucis]]
[[ko:십자가의 길]]
[[hr:Križni put (molitva)]]
[[id:Jalan Salib]]
[[it:Via Crucis]]
[[la:Via Crucis]]
[[lb:Kräizwee]]
[[lt:Kryžiaus kelias]]
[[li:Kruusweeg]]
[[lmo:Via Crucis]]
[[hu:Keresztút]]
[[ml:കുരിശിന്റെ വഴി]]
[[nl:Kruisweg (religie)]]
[[ja:十字架の道行き]]
[[pl:Droga krzyżowa]]
[[pt:Via Crúcis]]
[[ru:Крестный путь]]
[[sc:Via Crucis]]
[[sk:Krížová cesta]]
[[sl:Križev pot]]
[[sh:Križni put]]
[[sv:Korsvägsandakt]]
[[ta:சிலுவைப் பாதை]]
[[th:มรรคาศักดิ์สิทธิ์]]
[[uk:Хресна дорога]]
[[vi:Đàng Thánh Giá]]
[[zh:苦路]]</text>
      <sha1>6ehme3guzn2ka9ebo9n8xewazy32c26</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
