<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Superstition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21173144</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521129613</id>
      <parentid>521128701</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T23:48:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Slightsmile</username>
        <id>11737418</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[Help:Reverting|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/2602:306:C57A:CC80:D9D3:B0B4:5BD5:FADA|2602:306:C57A:CC80:D9D3:B0B4:5BD5:FADA]] ([[User talk:2602:306:C57A:CC80:D9D3:B0B4:5BD5:FADA|talk]]) to last version by 92.233.37.122</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15627">{{Other uses}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Paranormal}}
[[File:HamsaS.jpg|thumb|200px|Clay [[hamsa]] on a wall, believed to protect the inhabitants of the house from harm]]

'''Superstition''' is a belief in [[supernatural]] [[causality]]: that one event leads to the cause of another without any physical process linking the two events, such as astrology, omens, witchcraft, etc., that contradicts natural science.&lt;ref name =vyse21&gt;{{cite book|last=Vyse|first=Stuart A|title=Believing in Magic: The Psychology of Superstition|year=2000|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford, England|isbn=978-0-1951-3634-0|pages=19–22}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Opposition to superstition was a central concern of the intellectuals during the 18th century [[Age of Enlightenment]]. The [[philosophes]] at that time ridiculed any belief in [[miracle]]s, [[revelation]], [[Magic (paranormal)|magic]], or the supernatural, as &quot;superstition,&quot; and typically included as well much of Christian doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Wilson|first1=Helen Judy|last2=Reill|first2=Peter Hanns|title=Encylopedia of the Enlightenment|publisher=Facts on File Inc|location=New York|isbn=0-8160-5335-9|page=577|quote=…equating all Christian beliefs except those accessible to unaided reason with superstition…}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The word is often used pejoratively to refer to [[religion|religious]] practices (e.g., [[Haitian Vodou|Voodoo]]) other than the one prevailing in a given society (e.g., Christianity in western culture), although the prevailing religion may contain just as many supernatural beliefs.&lt;ref name=&quot;vyse21&quot; /&gt; It is also commonly applied to beliefs and practices surrounding [[luck]], [[prophecy]] and [[spiritual being]]s, particularly the belief that future events can be foretold by specific unrelated prior events.&lt;ref&gt;Vyse (2000: 5; 52)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etymology==
{{wiktionary|superstition}}
The word ''superstition'' is first used in English in the 15th century, modelled after an earlier French ''superstition''.
The earliest known use as an English noun occurs in ''[[Friar Daw's Reply]]'' (ca. 1420), where the ''[[cardinal sin|foure general synnes]]'' are emumerated as ''[[sedition|Cediciouns]], supersticions, [[gluttony|þe glotouns]], &amp; [[pride|þe proude]].'' 
The French word, together with its Romance cognates (Italian ''superstizione'', Spanish ''supersticion'', Portuguese ''superstição'', Catalan ''superstició'') continues Latin ''superstitio''.
From its first use in the [[Classical Latin]] of [[Livy]] and [[Ovid]] (1st century BC), the term is used in the pejorative sense it still holds today, of an excessive fear of the gods or unreasonable religious belief, as opposed to ''[[:wikt:religio|religio]]'', the proper, reasonable awe of the gods. 

While the formation of the Latin word is clear, from the verb ''[[:wikt:supersto#Latin|super-stare]]'', &quot;to stand over, stand upon; survive&quot;, its original intended sense is less than clear. 

It can be interpreted as &quot;‘standing over a thing in amazement or awe&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;orig. a standing still over or by a thing; hence, amazement, wonder, dread, esp. of the divine or supernatural.&quot; Charlton T. Lewis, Charles Short, [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=superstitio&amp;fromdoc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0059 A Latin Dictionary].
&lt;/ref&gt; but other possibilities have been suggested, e.g. the sense of ''excess'', i.e. overscrupulousness or over-ceremoniousness in the performing of religious rites, or else the ''survival'' of old, irrational religious habits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Oxford Latin Dictionary |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1982 |location=Oxford, England}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Turcan |first=Robert |others=Nevill, Antonia (trans.) |title=The Cults of the Roman Empire |publisher=Blackwell |location=Oxford, England |year =1996 |pages=10–12 |isbn=0-631-20047-9}}. {{cite book |title=Oxford English Dictionary |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford, England |year=1989 |edition=Second|quote=The etymological meaning of L. superstitio is perhaps ‘standing over a thing in amazement or awe.’ Other interpretations of the literal meaning have been proposed, e.g., ‘excess in devotion, over-scrupulousness or over-ceremoniousness in religion’ and ‘the survival of old religious habits in the midst of a new order of things’; but such ideas are foreign to ancient Roman thought.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Cicero]] derived the term from the term ''superstitiosi'', lit. those who are &quot;left over&quot;, i.e. &quot;survivors&quot;, &quot;descendants&quot;, connecting it with excessive anxiety of parents in hoping that their children would survive them to perform their necessary funerary rites.&lt;ref&gt;[[Cicero]], ''[[De Natura Deorum]] '''II''', 28 (32), quoted in {{cite book |last=Wagenvoort |first=Hendrik |authorlink=Hendrik Wagenvoort |title=Pietas: selected studies in Roman religion |publisher=Brill |location=Leiden, Netherlands |year=1980 |page=236 |isbn= 978-90-04-06195-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Latin verb ''superstare'' itself is comparatively young, being &quot;perhaps not ante-[[Augustan literature (ancient Rome)|Augustan]]&quot;, first found in [[Livy]], and the meaning &quot;to survive&quot; is even younger, found in late or ecclesiastical Latin, for the first time in [[Ennodius]]. The use of the noun by Cicero and Horace thus predates the first attestation of the verb.{{cn|date=June 2012}}

The term ''superstitio'', or ''superstitio vana'' &quot;vain superstition&quot;, was applied in the 1st century to those religious cults in the [[Roman Empire]] which were officially outlawed. 
This concerned the religion of the [[druid]]s in particular, which was described as a ''superstitio vana'' by [[Tacitus]], and [[Early Christianity]], outlawed as a ''superstitio Iudaica'' in AD 80 by [[Domitian]].

==Superstition and religion==
{{See also|Evolutionary psychology of religion|Evolutionary origin of religions}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Goddess Kaali.jpg]] --&gt;
Greek and Roman [[Polytheism|polytheists]], who modeled their relations with the gods on political and social terms, scorned the man who constantly trembled with fear at the thought of the gods, as a slave feared a cruel and capricious master. Such fear of the gods was what the Romans meant by &quot;superstition&quot; (Veyne 1987, p.&amp;nbsp;211). 
&lt;!--this is a mistake by Chambers, perhaps interesting for [[Desdemona]], but irrelevant here:
 (''[[Desdemona#Etymology|deisidaimonia]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Martin|first=Dale B.|title=Inventing superstition: from the Hippocratics to the Christians|year=2004|publisher=Harvard University Press|location=Cambridge, MA|isbn=0-674-01534-7|page=80}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=chambers&gt;{{cite web|last=The Earl of Shaftesbury|first=Antony Cooper|title=Chambers's Cyclopaedia of English Literature, Volume 2|url=http://books.google.ch/books?id=pc8iAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22denoted+the+lady+superstitious+(deisidaimonia%22&amp;dq=%22denoted+the+lady+superstitious+(deisidaimonia%22&amp;hl=de&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=o_zpToGjJ-7E4gSnlJSQCQ&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA|work=Advice to an Author|publisher=W. &amp; R. Chambers, Limited|accessdate=28 March 2011|author=Robert Chambers|coauthors=David Patrick (New Edition)|location=London &amp; Edinburgh|page=170|language=English|year=1902|quote=[Beginning with a quote from Othello, Act 1. Scene III:] 'This to hear Would Desdemona seriously incline.' ...But why, amongst his Greek names, he should have chosen one [that] denoted the lady superstitious (deisidaimonia in Greek means superstition) I can't imagine...}}&lt;/ref&gt;) 
--&gt;

In his ''[[Prelude on the Babylonian Captivity of the Church]]'', [[Martin Luther]] (who called the papacy &quot;that fountain and source of all superstitions&quot;) accuses the popes of superstition:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;For there was scarce another of the celebrated bishoprics that had so few learned pontiffs; only in violence, intrigue, and superstition has it hitherto surpassed the rest. For the men who occupied the Roman See a thousand years ago differ so vastly from those who have since come into power, that one is compelled to refuse the name of Roman pontiff either to the former or to the latter.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.godrules.net/library/luther/NEW1luther_b5.htm&lt;/ref&gt;”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The current ''[[Catechism of the Catholic Church]]'' considers superstition to be [[sin]]ful in the sense that it denotes a lack of [[trust (sociology)|trust]] in the [[divine providence]] of [[God]] and, as such, is a violation of the first of the [[Ten Commandments]], defining superstition as &quot;a perverse excess of religion&quot; (para. #2110).
The ''Catechism'' attempts to dispel commonly held preconceptions or misunderstandings about Catholic [[doctrine]] relating to superstitious practices:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Superstition is a deviation of religious feeling and of the practices this feeling imposes. It can even affect the worship we offer the true God, e.g., when one attributes an importance in some way magical to certain practices otherwise lawful or necessary. To attribute the efficacy of prayers or of sacramental signs to their mere external performance, apart from the interior dispositions that they demand is to fall into superstition. Cf. ''{{bibleref|Matthew|23:16–22}}'' (para. #2111)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Superstition and folklore==
{{Main|Folk belief}}
As discussed above, the term ''superstition'' contrasts with the term ''religion'', by definition referring to what are seen as excessive or false religious behavior as opposed to a standard of proper or accepted religious standard.
In this sense, European [[folk belief]] fell under the definition of superstition inasmuch as it contrasted with Christian theology and liturgy.
With the development of [[folklore studies]] in the late 18th century, use of the derogatory term ''superstition'' was sometimes replaced by the neutral term &quot;folk belief&quot;.
Both terms remain in use; thus, describing a practice such as the [[crossing fingers]] to nullify a promise as &quot;folk belief&quot; implies a neutral description from the perspective of ethnology or folklore studies, while calling the same thing a &quot;superstition&quot; implies its rejection as irrational.

==Superstition and psychology==
{{main|magical thinking|placebo|effective theory}}
In 1948, behavioural psychologist [[B.F. Skinner]] published an article in the ''Journal of Experimental Psychology'', in which he described his pigeons exhibiting what appeared to be superstitious behaviour. One pigeon was making turns in its cage, another would swing its head in a pendulum motion, while others also displayed a variety of other behaviours. Because these behaviours were all done ritualistically in an attempt to receive food from a dispenser, even though the dispenser had already been programmed to release food at set time intervals regardless of the pigeons' actions, Skinner believed that the pigeons were trying to influence their feeding schedule by performing these actions. He then extended this as a proposition regarding the nature of superstitious behaviour in humans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Skinner |first=B. F. |year=1948 |url=http://psychclassics.yorku.ca/Skinner/Pigeon/ |title='Superstition' in the Pigeon |journal=Journal of Experimental Psychology |volume=38 |issue=2 |pages=168–172 |doi=10.1037/h0055873 |pmid=18913665 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Skinner's theory regarding superstition being the nature of the pigeons' behaviour has been challenged by other psychologists such as Staddon and Simmelhag, who theorised an alternative explanation for the pigeons' behaviour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Staddon |first=J. E. |lastauthoramp=yes |last2=Simmelhag |first2=V. L. |year=1971 |title=The 'supersitition' experiment: A reexamination of its implications for the principles of adaptive behaviour |journal=Psychological Review |volume=78 |issue=1 |pages=3–43 |doi=10.1037/h0030305 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite challenges to Skinner's interpretation of the root of his pigeons' superstitious behaviour, his conception of the [[reinforcement|reinforcement schedule]] has been used to explain superstitious behaviour in humans. Originally, in Skinner's animal research, &quot;some pigeons responded up to 10,000 times without reinforcement when they had originally been conditioned on an ''intermittent reinforcement'' basis.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;schultz&quot;&gt;Schultz &amp; Schultz (2004, 238).{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compared to the other reinforcement schedules (e.g., fixed ratio, fixed interval), these behaviours were also the most resistant to [[extinction (psychology)|extinction]].&lt;ref name=&quot;schultz&quot;/&gt; This is called the ''partial reinforcement effect'', and this has been used to explain superstitious behaviour in humans. To be more precise, this effect means that, whenever an individual performs an action expecting a reinforcement, and none seems forthcoming, it actually creates a sense of persistence within the individual.&lt;ref&gt;Carver &amp; Scheier (2004, 332).{{full}}&lt;/ref&gt; This strongly parallels superstitious behaviour in humans because the individual feels that, by continuing this action, reinforcement will happen; or that reinforcement has come at certain times in the past as a result of this action, although not all the time, but this may be one of those times.

From a simpler perspective, [[natural selection]] will tend to reinforce a tendency to generate weak associations. If there is a strong survival advantage to making correct associations, then this will outweigh the negatives of making many incorrect, &quot;superstitious&quot; associations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=The evolution of superstitious and superstition-like behaviour |journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences |author=Kevin R. Foster |coauthor=[[Hanna Kokko]] |url=http://journals.royalsociety.org/content/v61648mh87863528 |doi=10.1098/rspb.2008.0981 |year=2009 |volume=276 |page=31 |pmid=18782752 |issue=1654 |pmc=2615824 |pages=31–7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{wikiquote}}
{{wiktionary}}
{{Commons category|Superstitions}}
{{Wikisource}}

* [[Baseball superstition]]
* [[Faith healing]]
* [[Folk religion]]
* [[Friday the 13th]]
* [[Heaven]] and [[Hell]]
* [[Luck]]
* [[Magical thinking]]
* [[Numbers in Chinese culture]]
* [[Post hoc ergo propter hoc]]
* [[Religion]]
* [[Sailors' superstitions]]
* [[Taboo]]
* [[Theatrical superstitions]]
* [[Witch window]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.life.com/gallery/52091/where-superstitions-come-from#index/0 Where Superstitions Come From] — slideshow by ''[[Life magazine]]''

[[Category:Superstitions| ]]
[[Category:Luck]]
[[Category:Magic (paranormal)]]

[[ar:خرافة]]
[[ca:Superstició]]
[[cv:Тĕшмĕш]]
[[cs:Pověra]]
[[da:Overtro]]
[[de:Aberglaube]]
[[et:Ebausk]]
[[es:Superstición]]
[[eo:Superstiĉo]]
[[eu:Sineskeria]]
[[fa:خرافه]]
[[fr:Superstition]]
[[gl:Superstición]]
[[gu:અંધવિશ્વાસ]]
[[ko:미신]]
[[hi:अंधविश्वास]]
[[hr:Praznovjerje]]
[[io:Superstico]]
[[is:Hjátrú]]
[[it:Superstizione]]
[[he:אמונה טפלה]]
[[jv:Gugon tuhon]]
[[sw:Ushirikina]]
[[la:Superstitio]]
[[lv:Māņticība]]
[[lb:Awerglawen]]
[[lt:Prietaras]]
[[hu:Babona]]
[[ml:അന്ധവിശ്വാസങ്ങൾ]]
[[mzn:خرافه]]
[[nl:Bijgeloof]]
[[ne:अन्धविश्वास]]
[[ja:迷信]]
[[nn:Overtru]]
[[oc:Cresenças popularas]]
[[pl:Przesąd]]
[[pt:Superstição]]
[[ro:Superstiție]]
[[ru:Суеверие]]
[[sq:Supersticioni]]
[[simple:Superstition]]
[[sk:Povera]]
[[sr:Сујеверје]]
[[fi:Taikausko]]
[[sv:Vidskepelse]]
[[tl:Pamahiin]]
[[ta:மூடநம்பிக்கை]]
[[th:ความเชื่อโชคลาง]]
[[tr:Batıl inanç]]
[[uk:Забобон]]
[[vi:Mê tín]]
[[wa:Doûce croeyance]]
[[zh:迷信]]</text>
      <sha1>i6aqwm72d2ysbd3yuhtdfwnoknevd8r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
