<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Syllabus of Errors</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>305907</id>
    <revision>
      <id>511387824</id>
      <parentid>504404585</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-08T15:20:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EmausBot</username>
        <id>11292982</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>r2.7.3) (Robot: Adding [[no:Syllabus errorum]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11087">{{expandlead|date=January 2012}}
The '''''Syllabus of Errors''''' ({{lang-la|'''Syllabus Errorum'''}}) was a document issued by [[Holy See]] under [[Pope Pius IX]] on December 8, 1864, [[Feast of the Immaculate Conception]], on the same day as the Pope's [[encyclical]] ''[[Quanta Cura]]''.

== Format ==
The Syllabus was made up of phrases and paraphrases from earlier papal documents, along with index references to them, and presented as a list of &quot;condemned propositions&quot;.  For instance, in condemning proposition 14, &quot;Philosophy is to be treated without taking any account of supernatural revelation&quot;, the Syllabus asserts the truth of the contrary proposition &amp;mdash; that philosophy should take account of supernatural revelation.  The Syllabus does not explain why each particular proposition is wrong, but it cites earlier documents to which the reader can refer for the [[Pope]]'s reasons for saying each proposition is false.  With the exception of some propositions drawn from Pius' encyclical ''[[Qui pluribus]]'' of November 9, 1846, all the propositions were based on documents that postdated the shocks to the Pope and the [[papacy]] of the [[Revolutions of 1848]] (see [[Italian unification]]).

The Syllabus was divided into ten sections which condemned as false various statements about these topics:

* [[pantheism]], [[philosophical naturalism|naturalism]], and absolute [[rationalism]], Propositions 1-7; 
* moderate rationalism, Propositions 8-14;
* [[indifferentism]] and [[Latitudinarian|latitudinarianism]], Propositions 15-18;
* [[socialism]], [[communism]], [[secret society|secret societies]], [[Bible Society|Bible societies]], and liberal [[clergy|cleric]]al societies, a general condemnation;
* the [[Christian Church|church]] and its rights, Propositions 19-38 (defending temporal power in the [[Papal States]], which were overthrown six years later;
* civil society and its relationship to the church, Propositions 39-55;
* natural and Christian [[ethics]], Propositions 56-64;
* [[Christian]] [[marriage]], Propositions 65-74;
* the [[Temporal power (Papal)|civil power]] of the sovereign Pontiff in the [[Papal States]], Propositions 75-76 and
* modern [[liberalism]], Propositions 77-80.

==Some statements of condemnation==
Statements the encyclical condemned as false include the following:

*&quot;human reason, without any reference whatsoever to God, is the sole arbiter of truth and falsehood, and of good and evil&quot; (No. 3) 
*&quot;All the truths of religion proceed from the innate strength of human reason; hence reason is the ultimate standard by which man can and ought to arrive at the knowledge of all truths of every kind.&quot; (No. 4) 
*&quot;in the present day it is no longer expedient that the Catholic religion should be held as the only religion of the State, to the exclusion of all other forms of worship.&quot; (No. 77) 
*&quot;Protestantism is nothing more than another form of the same true Christian religion, in which form it is given to please God equally as in the Catholic Church&quot; (No. 18).  
*&quot;the Church ought to be separated from the State, and the State from the Church.&quot; (No. 55)
*&quot;every man is free to embrace and profess that religion which, guided by the light of reason, he shall consider true.&quot; (No. 15) and that &quot;it has been wisely decided by law, in some Catholic countries, that persons coming to reside therein shall enjoy the public exercise of their own peculiar worship.&quot; (No. 78)
*&quot;the Roman Pontiff can, and ought to, reconcile himself, and come to terms with, progress, liberalism and modern civilization.&quot; (No. 80) (cf [[Jamdudum cernimus]])

==Reactions==
===Non-Catholics===
Within the [[Protestantism|Protestant]] world, reactions were uniformly negative.  In 1874 the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[Leader of the Opposition (United Kingdom)|Leader of the Opposition]] [[William Ewart Gladstone]] published a tract entitled ''The Vatican Decrees in their bearing on Civil Allegiance: A Political Expostulation'', in which he said that after the Syllabus: 

:. . . no one can now become (Rome's) convert without renouncing his moral and mental freedom, and placing his civil loyalty and duty at the mercy of another.

The government of [[France]] briefly tried to suppress the circulation of the encyclical and the ''Syllabus'' within its borders; it forbade priests to explain the Syllabus from the pulpit, though newspapers were allowed to discuss it from a [[secular]] point of view.

===Catholics===
The document met with a mixed reception among Catholics; many accepted it wholeheartedly, others wanted a clarification of some points, and still others were as shocked as their Protestant neighbors by the apparent broad scope of the condemnations.

Catholic [[Apologetics|apologists]] such as [[Félix Dupanloup]] and [[John Henry Newman]] said that the ''Syllabus'' was widely misinterpreted by readers who did not have access to or did not bother to check the original documents of which it was a summary.  The propositions listed had been condemned as erroneous opinions ''in the sense and context in which they originally occurred''; without the original context, the document appeared to condemn a larger range of ideas than it actually did.  Thus it was asserted that no critical response to the ''Syllabus'' which did not take the cited documents and their context into account could be valid (Newman 1874).  Newman writes:&lt;ref&gt;[[Francis A. Sullivan]], ''Creative Fidelity'', ISBN 0-8091-3644-9, p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Syllabus then has no dogmatic force; it addresses us, not in its separate portions, but as a whole, and is to be received from the Pope by an act of obedience, not of faith, that obedience being shown by having recourse to the original and authoritative documents, (Allocutions and the like,) to which the Syllabus pointedly refers.  Moreover, when we turn to those documents, which are authoritative, we find the Syllabus cannot even be called an echo of the Apostolic Voice; for, in matters in which wording is so important, it is not an exact transcript of the words of the Pope, in its account of the errors condemned, just as would be natural in what is an index for reference.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the wake of the controversy following the document's release, Pius IX referred to it as &quot;raw meat needing to be cooked.&quot; However, others within the church who supported the syllabus disagreed that there was any misinterpretation of the condemnations.

==Sources cited==
The Syllabus cited a number of previous documents that had been written during Pius' papacy. These include : [[Qui Pluribus]], [[Maxima quidem]], [[Singulari quadam]], [[Tuas libenter]], [[Multiplices inter]], [[Quanto conficiamur]], [[Noscitis]], [[Nostis et nobiscum]], [[Meminit unusquisque]], [[Ad Apostolicae]], [[Nunquam fore]], [[Incredibili]], [[Acerbissimum]], [[Singularis nobisque]], [[Multis gravibusque]], [[Quibus quantisque]], [[Quibus luctuosissimis]], [[In consistoriali]], [[Cum non sine]], [[Cum saepe]], [[Quanto conficiamur]], [[Jamdudum cernimus]], [[Novos et ante]], [[Quibusque vestrum]] and [[Cum Catholica]].

==Subsequent history==

Further thoughts in the same vein were expressed in Pius' encyclical of 21 November 1873, ''[[Etsi multa]]'' (&quot;On the Church in Italy, Germany, and Switzerland&quot;), which is often appended to the ''Syllabus.''  There Pius condemned current liberalizing anti-clerical legislation in [[History of South America|South America]] as &quot;a ferocious war on the Church.&quot;

In 1907 [[Lamentabili Sane]] was promulgated, a &quot;''Syllabus condemning the errors of the Modernists''&quot;, being a list of sins that might be made by scholars engaged in [[biblical criticism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.papalencyclicals.net/Pius10/p10lamen.htm Lamentabili Sane text 1907]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Some think that the political or [[dogma]]tic propositions of the Syllabus may be abrogated by later documents coming from the [[Second Vatican Council]] in 1962.  Others argue that this view results from an excessively broad interpretation of statements that had a narrower sense in their original context, and from contrasting the [[Infallibility of the Church|infallible]] documents of the ecumenical council with papal statements that were not infallible because they were not addressed to the whole church.  

English historian E.E.Y. Hales argues that:
:&quot;[T]he Pope is not concerned with a universal principle, but with the position in a particular state at a particular date.  He is expressing his &quot;wonder and distress&quot; (no more) that in a Catholic country (Spain) it should be proposed to disestablish the Church and to place any and every religion upon a precisely equal footing. ..... Disestablishment and toleration were far from the normal practice of the day, whether in Protestant or in Catholic states.&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | last1 = Hales | first1 = E.E.Y.   | title = THE CATHOLIC CHURCH in the MODERN WORLD: A Survey from the French Revolution to the Present | publisher = Doubleday  | year= 1958}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Footnotes ==
&lt;references /&gt;

== External links ==
*[http://www.ewtn.com/library/PAPALDOC/P9SYLL.HTM The Syllabus of Errors] online text
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14368b.htm A. Haag, &quot;Syllabus&quot;] in the Catholic Encyclopedia (1912)
*[http://www.newmanreader.org/works/anglicans/volume2/gladstone/section7.html John Henry Newman's discussion of the Syllabus in ''Difficulties of Anglicans''] volume 2 (1874)
*[http://www.victorianweb.org/religion/Gladstone___Vatican.html Excerpt from Gladstone's ''The Vatican Decrees in Their Bearing on Civil Allegiance: a Political Expostulation''] at [[Victorian Web]]
*[http://www.seattlecatholic.com/article_20030103_Differing_from_Other_Councils.html Explains how &quot;apparent contradictions&quot; between the Syllabus and Vatican should be reconciled.]
*[http://www.catholic.com/magazine/articles/the-syllabus-the-controversy-and-the-context The Syllabus, the Controversy, and the Context] in This Rock Magazine January 2009

== Further reading ==
* ''Pio Nono: A Study in European Politics and Religion in the Nineteenth Century'', by E.E.Y. Hales (P.J. Kenedy, 1954)
* ''The Catholic Church in the Modern World'' by [[E.E.Y. Hales]] (Doubleday, 1958)
* {{Cite journal  | last = Utt  | first = Walter C.  | title = Quanta Cura and the Syllabus of Errors  | journal = Liberty  | volume = 55  | issue = 6, November-December  | pages = 12, 13, 32–34  | publisher = Review and Herald Publishing Association  | location = Washington, D. C.  | year = 1960  | url = http://www.adventistarchives.org/docs/LibM/LibM19600601-V55-06__C.pdf#view=fit  | accessdate = June 24, 2011}}

[[Category:Works by Pope Pius IX]]
[[Category:Catholic theology and doctrine]]
[[Category:Contemporary Italian history]]
[[Category:History of the Papacy]]
[[Category:1864 works]]
[[Category:1864 in religion]]

[[cy:Syllabus Errorum]]
[[de:Syllabus Errorum]]
[[es:Syllabus]]
[[fr:Syllabus (pape Pie IX)]]
[[it:Sillabo]]
[[nl:Syllabus Errorum]]
[[ja:誤謬表]]
[[no:Syllabus errorum]]
[[pl:Syllabus Errorum]]
[[ru:Силлабус]]
[[sv:Syllabus]]
[[wa:Sillabusse des ereurs]]</text>
      <sha1>fnc2a9ocbrzvkhphrpg880fhurno4fy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
