<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Synagogue</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>48559</id>
    <restrictions>move=:edit=</restrictions>
    <revision>
      <id>522321581</id>
      <parentid>522321569</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T12:16:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contributions/46.65.56.162|46.65.56.162]] to version by Yabti. False positive? [[User:ClueBot NG/FalsePositives|Report it]]. Thanks, [[User:ClueBot NG|ClueBot NG]]. (1327141) (Bot)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32293">{{redirect|Shul|places in Iran|Shul, Iran (disambiguation){{!}}Shul, Iran}}
{{Jews and Judaism sidebar|religion}} 
A '''synagogue''' (from [[Greek language|Greek]]: {{lang|grc|συναγωγή}} [[transliteration|transliterated]] ''synagogē'', meaning &quot;assembly&quot;) is a [[Jew]]ish or [[Samaritan]] house of prayer.&lt;ref&gt;When broken down, the word could also mean &quot;learning together&quot; (from the Greek συν ''syn'', together, and αγωγή ''agogé'', learning or training).&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
Synagogues have a large hall for prayer (the main sanctuary) with an Ark holding Torah scrolls,  and can also have smaller rooms for study and sometimes a social hall for occasions as well as offices for bookkeeping. Some have a separate room for [[Torah study]], called the ''[[beit midrash]] (Sfard) &quot;[[beis midrash]] (Ashkenaz)''—{{lang|he|בית מדרש}} (&quot;House of Study&quot;).

Synagogues are [[consecrated]] spaces intended for the purpose of prayer; however, a synagogue is not necessary for worship. Communal Jewish worship can be carried out wherever ten Jews (a ''[[minyan]]'') assemble. Worship can also be carried out alone or with fewer than ten people assembled together. However, there are certain prayers that are communal prayers and therefore can be recited only by a minyan. Except in [[Reform movement in Judaism|Reform Judaism]], a synagogue is not viewed as replacing the long-since destroyed [[Temple in Jerusalem|Temple]] in [[Jerusalem]].

[[Israelis]] use the [[Hebrew]] term ''bet knesset'' (assembly house). [[Ashkenazi Jews|Jews of Ashkenazi]] descent have traditionally used the [[Yiddish language|Yiddish]] term &quot;shul&quot; (cognate with the [[German language|German]] ''Schule'', school) in everyday speech. [[Spanish and Portuguese Jews]] call the synagogue an ''esnoga''. [[Persian Jews]] and [[Karaite Judaism|Karaite Jews]] use the term ''[[kenesa]]'', which is derived from [[Aramaic language|Aramaic]], and some [[Arabic language|Arabic]]-speaking Jews use ''knis''. Some Reform and Conservative Jews use ''temple''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.templemenorahmiami.org/ An example of a conservative synagogue styled &quot;temple&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.tbespringfield.org/bethel/ An example of a conservative synagogue styled &quot;temple&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Greek language|Greek]] word ''synagogue'' is a good all-around term, used in [[English language|English]] (and [[German language|German]] and [[French language|French]]), to cover the preceding possibilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jewfaq.org/shul.htm |title=Judaism 101: Synagogues, Shuls and Temples |publisher= Jewfaq.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Synagogues often take on a broader role in modern Jewish communities and may include additional facilities such as a catering hall, [[kosher]] kitchen, [[religious school]], [[library]], [[day care center]] and a smaller chapel for daily services.

==Etymology and translations==
The use of the Greek term ''synagogue'' originates in the [[Septuagint]] where it sometimes translates the Hebrew word for assembly, {{lang|he|קהל}} ''kahal''. In modern Hebrew a synagogue is called either a {{lang|he|בית כנסת}} ''beyt knesset'', meaning &quot;house of assembly&quot;; {{lang|he|בית תפילה}} or ''beyt t'fila'' (also written as ''bet tepilla'' &lt;ref name=&quot;Meyers&quot;&gt;Meyers Eric M (1992) 'Synagogue' in 'The anchor Bible Dictionary' vol 6 pp 252-253&lt;/ref&gt;), meaning &quot;house of prayer&quot;, in Yiddish {{lang|yi|שול}} ''shul'', from the German for &quot;school,&quot; and in Ladino {{lang|lad|אסנוגה}} ''esnoga''. In the Hebrew term ''bet tepilla'' Beth means &quot;house&quot; and tepilla (תפילה) means &quot;prayer&quot;. &lt;ref name=&quot;Greenberg&quot;&gt;Greenberg, Moshe. Biblical Prose Prayer: As a Window to the Popular Religion of Ancient Israel. Berkeley:  University of California Press,  1983. http://library.northsouth.edu/Upload/Biblical%20Prose%20Prayer.pdf &lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Beth Tepilla&quot; is derived from the cognate verb, &quot;hitpallel&quot;  (פּליל)  &lt;ref name=&quot;Greenberg&quot;/&gt; which is also spelled as pa^li^yl (pronounced: paleel) which implies &quot;estimate, judge, render a verdict&quot; thus &quot;hitpallel&quot; means &quot;to pray&quot; or &quot;to seek a judgment for oneself&quot; or &quot;to plead&quot;. Here the underlying meaning of &quot;tepilla&quot; or &quot;prayer&quot; is a conception of petitionary prayer that has a sense of judgment or a &quot;plea&quot; in the court of judgment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Greenberg&quot;/&gt; This reduces the word root to *P*L*L as &quot;intervene, interpose&quot; and the act of intervention is an act of *P'LiLah*. (Note: the first two letters of the word &quot;plea&quot; are also PL). The Hebrew cognate word &quot;hitpallel&quot; gives a rendering to Beth Tepilla or synagogue as a &quot;house of prayer&quot; or as a &quot;house to plead&quot;.

==Origins==
[[Image:ZodiacMosaicTzippori.jpg|thumb|left|Mosaic in the [[Tzippori Synagogue]]]]
[[Image:Ruins of the Ancient Synagogue at Bar'am.jpg|thumb|Ruins of the ancient synagogue of [[Kfar Bar'am]]]]

There is a wide variety of speculative theories about the origins of the synagogue (in the sense of purpose-built spaces for worship, or rooms originally constructed for some other purpose but reserved for formal, communal prayer), some of which date the origins as early as the eighth century BCE or the time of the [[Babylonian captivity]] (sixth century BCE). The earliest archeological remains of a synagogue building on the island of [[Delos]] in the Aegean indicate a late second-century or possibly mid-first century BCE date of construction, while earlier inscriptions and papyri have been discovered in Egypt, commencing with the third century BCE.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Levine |first=Lee |title=The Ancient Synagogue: The First Thousand Years |origyear=2000 |publisher=[[Yale University Press]] |location=New Haven, Conn. |isbn=0-300-10628-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of very early [[Palestinian synagogues]] date from the 1st-century CE.  A synagogue dating from between 75 and 50 BCE has been uncovered at a Hasmonean-era winter palace near [[Jericho]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archaeology.org/9807/newsbriefs/israel.html Archaeology.org&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;], Israel's Oldest Synagogue&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishsf.com/content/2-0-/module/displaystory/story_id/8390/edition_id/159/format/html/displaystory.html Jewishsf.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  More than a dozen Second Temple era synagogues have been identified by archaeologists.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pohick.org/sts/index.html |title=Second Temple Synagogues |publisher=Pohick.org |date=2010-09-08 |accessdate=2012-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although synagogues existed a long time before the destruction of the [[Second Temple]] in 70 CE, communal worship during the time the Temple still stood centered around the ''[[korban]]ot'' (&quot;sacrificial offerings&quot;) brought by the ''[[Kohen|kohanim]]'' (&quot;priests&quot;) in the [[Temple in Jerusalem|Holy Temple]]. The all-day [[Yom Kippur]] service, in fact, was an event in which the congregation both observed the movements of the ''kohen gadol'' (&quot;the high priest&quot;) as he offered the day's sacrifices and prayed for his success.

At the end of the Second Temple era, [[Rabbi]] [[Yohanan ben Zakkai]], promulgated the idea of creating individual houses of worship in whatever locale Jews found themselves. This contributed to the continuity of the Jewish people by maintaining a unique identity and a portable way of worship despite the destruction of the Temple, according to many historians.

==Architectural design==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Hechal Yehuda.jpg|thumb|left|[[Hechal Yehuda Synagogue]], [[Tel Aviv]]]] --&gt;
{{Main|Synagogue architecture}}
Although there are some standard laws which govern the layout of a synagogue, there is no set architectural design and therefore exteriors and interiors of synagogues vary greatly. Historically, synagogues were built in the prevailing architectural style of their time and place. Thus, the synagogue in [[Kaifeng|Kaifeng, China]] looked very like Chinese temples of that region and era, with its outer wall and open garden in which several buildings were arranged. The styles of the earliest synagogues resembled the temples of other sects of the eastern Roman Empire. The surviving synagogues of medieval Spain are embellished with [[mudéjar]] plasterwork.  The surviving medieval synagogues in [[Budapest]] and [[Prague]] are typical [[Gothic architecture|Gothic]] structures.  

The emancipation of Jews in European countries not only enabled Jews to enter fields of enterprise from which they were formerly barred, but gave them the right to build synagogues without needing special permissions, so synagogue architecture blossomed. Large Jewish communities wished to show not only their wealth but also their newly acquired status as citizens by constructing magnificent synagogues. These were built across Europe and in the United States in all of the historicist or revival styles then in fashion. Thus there were [[Neoclassical architecture|Neoclassical]], [[Neo-Byzantine]], [[Romanesque Revival]] [[Moorish Revival]], [[Gothic Revival]], and [[Greek Revival]].  There are [[Egyptian Revival]] synagogues and even one [[Mayan Revival]] synagogue. In the 19th century and early 20th century heyday of historicist architecture, however, most historicist synagogues, even the most magnificent ones, did not attempt a pure style, or even any particular style, and are best described as eclectic. In the post World War II era, synagogue architecture abandoned historicist styles for modernism.

==Interior elements==
[[Image:BialyBimah.JPG|right|thumb|[[Bimah]] at the [[Bialystoker Synagogue]] with Torah Ark in background.]]
[[File:Łańcut synagoga 08.jpg|left|thumb|Bimah of the [[Łańcut Synagogue]]]]

All synagogues contain a ''[[bimah]]'' also written as ''[[bema]]'' &lt;ref name=&quot;Sonne&quot;&gt;Sonne Isaiah (1962) 'Synagogue' in The Interpreter's dictionary of the Bible vol 4, New York: Abingdon Press pp 476-491, 488&lt;/ref&gt;, a table from which the Torah is read, and a desk for the prayer leader. The name and use for 'bema' is traced back to Ezra's reading of the Torah &quot;on a wooden pulpit&quot; (Neh 8:4-5) &lt;ref name=&quot;Sonne&quot;/&gt;

The Torah ark, (Hebrew: ''Aron Kodesh''—ארון קודש) (called the  ''heikhal''—היכל [temple] or ''by [[Sephardim]]) is a cabinet in which  the [[Torah]] scrolls are kept.

The ark in a synagogue is positioned in almost always such a way that those who face it, face towards [[Jerusalem]]. Thus, sanctuary seating plans in the Western world generally face [[Mizrah|east]], while those east of Israel face west. Sanctuaries in Israel face towards Jerusalem. Occasionally synagogues face other directions for structural reasons; in such cases, some individuals might turn to face Jerusalem when standing for prayers, but the congregation as a whole does not.

The ark is reminiscent of the [[Ark of the Covenant]] which contained the tablets with [[Ten Commandments]]. This is the holiest spot in a synagogue, equivalent to the [[Holy of Holies]]. The ark is often closed with an ornate curtain, the ''{{lang|he-Latn|[[parochet]]}}'' {{lang|he|פרוכת}}, also written as ''Paroket'' or ''Parokta'' (from [[Aramaic]]) meaning &quot;veil&quot; or &quot;Curtain&quot; or 'screen' &lt;ref name=&quot;Sonne&quot;/&gt; which hangs outside or inside the ark doors.

A large, raised, reader's platform  called the ''{{lang|he-Latn|[[bimah]]}}'' ({{lang|he|בימה}}) by Ashkenazim and ''{{lang|he-Latn|[[tebah]]}}'' by Sephardim, where the Torah scroll is placed to be read.  Is a feature of all synagogues.  In Sephardi synagogues it is also used as the prayer leader's reading desk.

Other traditional features include a continually lit lamp or lantern, usually electric in contemporary synagogues, called the ''{{lang|he-Latn|[[ner tamid]]}}'' ({{lang|he|נר תמיד}}), the &quot;Eternal Light&quot;,  used as a reminder of the western lamp of the [[Menorah (Temple)|menorah]] of the [[Temple in Jerusalem]], which remained miraculously lit always.  Many have an elaborate chair named for the prophet [[Elijah]] and only sat upon during the ceremony of [[Brit milah]]. Many synagogues have a large seven-branched  candelabrum commemorating the full [[Menorah (Temple)|Menorah]].  Most contemporary synagogues also feature a lectern for the rabbi.

A synagogue may be decorated with artwork, but in the Rabbinic and Orthodox tradition, three-dimensional sculptures and depictions of the human body are not allowed, as these are considered akin to idolatry. 

Until the 19th century,  an [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazi]] synagogue, all seats most often faced the 'Torah Ark. In a [[Sephardi Jews|Sephardi]] synagogue, seats were usually arranged around the perimeter of the sanctuary, but when the worshippers stood up to pray, everyone faced the Ark.   In Ashkenazi synagogues The [[Torah]] was read on a reader's table located in the center of the room, while the leader of the prayer service, the ''{{lang|he-Latn|Hazzan}}'', stood at his own lectern or table, facing the Ark.  In Sephardic synagogues, the table for reading the Torah was commonly placed at the opposite side of the room from the Torah Ark, leaving the center of the floor empty for the use of a ceremonial procession carrying the Torah between the Ark and the reading table.

===Denominational differences===
[[Image:Emanu-elNYjeh.JPG|thumb|New York's Reform [[Congregation Emanu-El of New York|Temple Emanu-El]]]]
Orthodox synagogues feature a partition ({{lang|he-Latn|[[mechitzah]]}}) dividing the men's and women's seating areas, or a separate women's section located on a balcony.

The German Reform movement which arose in the early 19th century made many changes to the traditional look of the synagogue, keeping with its desire to simultaneously stay Jewish yet be accepted by the host culture.

The first Reform synagogue, which opened in [[Hamburg]] in 1811, introduced changes that made the synagogue look more like a [[Church (building)|church]]. These included an [[Organ (music)|organ]] to accompany the prayers (even on [[Shabbat]], when musical instruments are proscribed by [[halakha]]), a choir to accompany the ''Hazzan'', and vestments for the synagogue rabbi to wear.&lt;ref&gt;Rabbi Ken Spiro. [http://www.aish.com/literacy/jewishhistory/Crash_Course_in_Jewish_History_Part_54_-_Reform_Movement.asp Aish.com], &quot;Crash Course in Jewish History Part 54 - Reform Movement&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In following decades, the central reader's table, the [[bimah]], was moved to the front of the Reform sanctuary—previously unheard-of{{Citation needed|date=April 2008}} in Orthodox synagogues. The rabbi now delivered his [[sermon]] from the front, much as the [[Christianity|Christian]] [[Minister (Christianity)|ministers]] delivered their sermons in a church. The synagogue was renamed a &quot;temple&quot;, to emphasize that the movement no longer looked forward to the rebuilding of the Temple in Jerusalem.{{Citation needed|date=April 2008}}

==Synagogue offshoots==
Since Orthodox Jews prefer to collect a minyan (a quorum of ten) rather than pray alone, they  commonly assemble at pre-arranged times in offices, living rooms, or other spaces when these are more convenient than formal synagogue buildings.  A room or building that is used this way can become a dedicated  small synagogue or prayer room.   Among Ashkenazi Jews they are traditionally called  ''{{lang|yi-Latn|[[shtiebel]]}}'' ({{lang|yi|שטיבל}}, pl. ''{{lang|yi-Latn|shtiebelekh}}'' or ''{{lang|yi-Latn|shtiebels}}'', Yiddish for &quot;little house&quot;), and are found in Orthodox communities worldwide.

Another type of communal prayer group, favored by some contemporary Jews, is the ''[[Chavurah]]'' (חבורה, pl. ''chavurot'', חבורות), or prayer fellowship. These groups meet at a regular place and time, usually in a private home.  In [[classical antiquity|antiquity]], the [[Pharisees]] lived near each other in ''chavurot'' and dined together to ensure that none of the food was unfit for consumption.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alan F. Segal]], ''Rebecca's Children: Judaism and Christianity in the Roman World'', [[Harvard University Press]], 1986, 125.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Great synagogues==
[[File:Berlin Neue Synagoge Innenansicht BusB.jpg|thumb|Interior view of the [[New Synagogue (Berlin)]]]]
[[Image:Belz World Center Inside.jpg|thumb|Interior of the [[Belz Great Synagogue]] in Jerusalem.]]

During the 19th and early 20th century, it was fairly common for Jewish communities, particularly in Europe, to construct very large, showpiece synagogues. These edifices were intended not simply to accommodate worshipers, but to serve as emblems of Jewish participation in modern society.  For this purpose, they were built to be not merely large, but architecturally impressive. Even small cities had elaborate synagogues of this type, albeit smaller than the synagogues of Vienna and New York. They are often designated as ''The Great Synagogue of...'', or, in Russia, ''The Choral Synagogue.'' These notable synagogues include; the [[Portuguese Synagogue (Amsterdam)]], the [[Great Synagogue of Rome]], the [[New Synagogue (Berlin)]], the [[Leopoldstädter Tempel]], the [[Grand Choral Synagogue]] (St. Petersburg), the [[Great Synagogue (Sydney)]], the [[Moscow Choral Synagogue]], the [[Great Synagogue of Florence]], the [[Great Synagogue, Plzeň]], the [[Great Synagogue (Warsaw)]], the [[Orthodox synagogue in Košice|Košice Orthodox Synagogue]], the [[Novi Sad Synagogue]], the [[Szeged Synagogue]],&lt;ref&gt;1340 seats, the synagogue is 48 meters long, 35 meters wide and 48.6 meters high,&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Sofia Synagogue]] and the [[Great Synagogue of Oran]].

==World's largest synagogues==
* The largest synagogue in the world is probably the [[Belz Great Synagogue]], in Jerusalem, Israel, whose main Sanctuary seats 6,000. Construction on the edifice lasted for over 15 years.
* The next largest or possibly largest may be the [[Satmar (Hasidic dynasty)|Satmar]] synagogue in [[Kiryas Joel]], New York, which is said to seat 5,500 to 7,000 people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jpi.org/holocaust/hlchp7a.htm |title=Jewish Professionals Institute (JPI) - Holocaust Thesis Chapter 7 |publisher=JPI |date= |accessdate=2012-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The largest synagogue in Europe is the newly constructed Bratzlav Center at the graveside of Rabbi Nahman of Bratzlav in [[Uman]], [[Ukraine]], which seats up to 6,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.breslov.com/uman/summer99.html |title=Synagogue of the Ukraine, Update Summer 1999 |publisher=Breslov.com |date=1999-06-08 |accessdate=2012-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Dohány Street Synagogue]] in [[Budapest]], Hungary, seats 3,000, and has an area of 1200 m² and height of 26 m (apart from the towers which are 43 m). {{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* [[Kehilas Yetev Lev D'Satmar (Williamsburg, Brooklyn)]] seats between 2,000 to 4,000 congregants.
* The [[New Synagogue (Berlin)|New Synagogue]] in [[Berlin]], [[Germany]] seats 3,200 people.
* [[Temple Emanu-El of New York]], a [[Temple|Reform Temple]] is located in New York City, with an area of 3,523 m², seating 2,500.
* The [[Great Synagogue (Plzeň)|Great Synagogue]] in [[Plzeň]], [[Czech Republic]] is the second biggest synagogue in Europe, can seat more than 2000, area of 1680 m² and height of 45 m (apart from the towers which are 65 m). 
* [[Congregation Shaare Zion]], an Orthodox Sephardic synagogue located in [[Brooklyn, New York]], is the largest [[Syrian Jewish]] congregation in New York City. It is attended by over 2,000 worshipers on weekends.
* The [[Wilshire Boulevard Temple]] in [[Los Angeles, California]] seats 1,850.
* The [[Great Synagogue (Jerusalem)|Great Synagogue]] in [[Jerusalem]], [[Israel]] seats 1,400.
* [[Temple Emanu-El (Miami Beach, Florida)]] located in [[Miami Beach, Florida]] seats approximately 1,400.
* The [[Szeged Synagogue]] is located in [[Szeged]], Hungary, seats 1,340 and has height of 48.5 m.
* The KAM Isaih Israel Synagogue in [[Chicago, Illinois]] seats 1,300.
* The [[Sofia Synagogue]] is located in [[Sofia]], [[Bulgaria]], seating about 1,200.
* The [[Grand Choral Synagogue]] in [[St. Petersburg]], [[Russia]] seats 1,200.

==World's oldest synagogues==
{{Main|Oldest synagogues in the world}}
[[Image:Sardis Synagogue courtyard.JPG|right|thumb|The [[Sardis]] Synagogue in [[Manisa]], [[Turkey]]. The synagogue was a section of a large bath-gymnasium complex, which was in use for 450–500 years.]]
[[Image:Duraeuropa-1-.gif|thumb|right|[[Fresco]] at the [[Dura-Europos synagogue]], illustrating a scene from the [[Book of Esther]], 244 CE.]]

* The oldest [[Samaritan]] synagogue, the [[Delos Synagogue]] dates from between 150 and 128 BCE, or earlier and is located on the island of [[Delos]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pohick.org/sts/delos.html |title=Delos |publisher=Pohick.org |date= |accessdate=2012-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Jericho Synagogue]], the oldest, securely dated, mainstream Jewish synagogue in the world was built between 70 and 50 BCE at a royal winter palace near [[Jericho]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pohick.org/sts/jericho.html |title=Jericho |publisher=Pohick.org |date=1998-03-29 |accessdate=2012-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The oldest synagogue fragments are stone synagogue dedication inscriptions stones found in middle and lower [[Egypt]] and dating from the 3rd century BCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://www.pohick.org/sts/egypt.html Pohick.org&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;], Egypt&lt;/ref&gt;
* The 2nd and 3rd century CE [[Dura-Europos synagogue]] in [[Syria]] is better preserved than other, older synagogues that have emerged from archaeological digs.
* The [[Paradesi Synagogue]] is the oldest synagogue in the [[Commonwealth of Nations]], located in Kochi, [[Kerala]], in India. It was built in 1568 by the Malabar Yehudan people or [[Cochin Jewish]] community in the Kingdom of Cochin. Paradesi is a word used in several Indian languages, and the literal meaning of the term is &quot;foreigners&quot;, applied to the synagogue because it was historically used by &quot;White Jews&quot;, a mixture of Jews from Cranganore, the Middle East, and European exiles. It is also referred to as the Cochin Jewish Synagogue or the Mattancherry Synagogue. The synagogue is located in the quarter of Old Cochin known as Jew Town and is the only one of the seven synagogues in the area still in use.
* [[Old New Synagogue]] in [[Prague]] is the world's oldest active synagogue and therefore also the oldest synagogue still in use in Europe.
* [[Jew's Court]], Steep Hill, [[Lincoln, England]] is arguably the second oldest synagogue in Europe in current use.
* [[Kahal Zur Israel Synagogue]], [[Recife]], Brazil is the oldest synagogue in the [[Americas]].
{{clear}}
=== Oldest synagogues in the United States ===
[[Image:Sinagoga-kahal-zur-israel-recife.jpg|thumb|right|1636 - The [[Kahal Zur Israel Synagogue]], located in [[Recife]] on the site of the oldest synagogue in the Americas.]]
[[Image:Touro Synagogue, Newport, RI.jpg|thumb|right|[[Touro Synagogue]], the [[Oldest synagogues in the United States|oldest surviving synagogue building]] in the U.S.]]

{{Main|Oldest synagogues in the United States}}
* [[Congregation Shearith Israel]], 1655, is the oldest congregation in the United States, its present building dates from 1897.
* The [[Touro Synagogue]] in [[Newport, Rhode Island]], is the oldest Jewish house of worship in North America that is still standing. It was built in 1759 for the [[Jeshuat Israel]] congregation, which was established in 1658.

==Other famous synagogues==
* The [[Rashi Shul]], built in 1175 and razed on [[Kristallnacht]] in 1938, was painstakingly reconstructed using many of the original stones. It is still in use as a synagogue.
* The [[Synagogue of El Transito]] of [[Toledo, Spain]], was built in 1356 by [[Samuel ha-Levi]], treasurer of [[King Pedro I]] of [[Crown of Castile|Castile]]. This is one of the best examples of [[Mudéjar]] architecture in Spain. The design of the synagogue recalls the [[Nasrid]] style of architecture that was employed during the same period in the decorations of the [[Alhambra]] palace in [[Granada]] as well as the [[Great Mosque of Córdoba]]. Since 1964, this site has hosted a Sephardi museum.
* The [[Hurva Synagogue]], located in the [[Jewish Quarter (Jerusalem)|Jewish Quarter]] of the [[Old City (Jerusalem)|Old City]] of [[Jerusalem]], was Jerusalem's main Ashkenazi synagogue from the 16th century until 1948, when it was destroyed by the [[Arab Legion]] several days after the conquest of the city.  After the [[Six-Day War]], an arch was built to mark the spot where the synagogue stood. A complete reconstruction, to plans drawn up by architect [[Nahum Meltzer]], opened in March 2010.
* The [[Great Synagogue of Oran]], [[Algeria]], built in 1880, but converted into a mosque after [[Algerian independence]] when all [[Algerian Jews]] were driven into exile.
* The [[Barbados]] [[Nidhe Israel Synagogue]] (&quot;Bridgetown Synagogue&quot;), located in the capital city of [[Bridgetown]], was first built in 1654. It was destroyed in the [[hurricane]] of 1831 and reconstructed in 1833.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.planetware.com/bridgetown/synagogue-bar-mi-syn.htm |title=Planetware.com |publisher=Planetware.com |date= |accessdate=2012-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Snoa]] in [[Willemstad, Curaçao]], [[Netherlands Antilles]] was built by Sephardic Portuguese Jews from Amsterdam and Recife, Brazil. It is modeled after the Esnoga in Amsterdam. Congregation [[Mikvé Israel-Emanuel|Mikvé Israel]] built this synagogue in 1692; it was reconstructed in 1732.
* The [[Bialystoker Synagogue]] on New York's [[Lower East Side]], is located in a landmark building dating from 1826 that was originally a [[Methodist Episcopal Church]]. The building is made of stone quarried locally on [[Pitt Street]], [[Manhattan]]. It is an example of [[Federalist architecture]]. The ceilings and walls are hand-painted with [[zodiac]] [[fresco]]s, and the sanctuary is illuminated by {{convert|40|ft|m|sing=on}} stained glass windows. The [[bimah]] and floor-to-ceiling ark are handcarved.
* The [[Great Synagogue of Florence]], '''Tempio Maggiore''', Florence, 1874–82, is an example of the magnificent, cathedral-like synagogues built in almost every major European city in the 19th century and early 20th century.
* [[Boston]]'s 1920 [[Vilna Shul]] in [[Massachusetts]] is a rare surviving intact [[Immigrant Era]] synagogue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vilnashul.org |title=Vilnashul.org |publisher=Vilnashul.org |date=2010-10-22 |accessdate=2012-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Cymbalista Synagogue]] is an example of modern architecture and new thinking in synagogue design - designed by Mario Botta, it accommodates Orthodox, Conservative, and Reform congregations in one structure and promotes dialogue and interaction&lt;ref&gt;[[Cymbalista Synagogue and Jewish Heritage Center]]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Berlin Neue Synagoge 2005.jpg|The [[New Synagogue (Berlin)|New Synagogue]] in [[Berlin]], [[Germany]].
Image:Moscow Choral Synagogue.jpg|The [[Moscow Choral Synagogue|Choral Synagogue]] in [[Moscow]], [[Russia]]. 
Image:EsnogaAmsterdam.jpg|The [[Portuguese Synagogue (Amsterdam)|Portuguese Synagogue]] in [[Amsterdam]], [[Netherlands]].
Image:Great Synagogue Plzen CZ general view.JPG|The [[Great Synagogue]] of [[Plzeň]], [[Czech Republic]].	 
Image:Frankfurt Hauptsynagoge 1885.jpg|The main synagogue of the city of [[Frankfurt am Main]] ([[Germany]]) before the [[Kristallnacht]]. 
Image:Köln synagoge pano.jpg|The [[Roonstrasse Synagogue]] in [[Cologne]], [[Germany]].
Image:Lesko synagoga.jpg|The [[Lesko Synagogue]] in [[Lesko]], [[Poland]].
Image:Besht Shul1 Medzhibozh.jpg|The [[Baal Shem Tov]]'s shul in [[Medzhybizh]], [[Ukraine]] (c. 1915). The original was destroyed, but has now been rebuilt.
Image:Belz hasidic synagogue.jpg|The [[Belz (Hasidic dynasty)|Belzer]] synagogue of [[Belz]], [[Ukraine]]. The synagogue no longer exists.
Image:Synagoge auf Gelaende der Universtaet Tel Aviv.jpg|The [[Cymbalista Synagogue and Jewish Heritage Center]] at [[Tel Aviv University]].
Image:Kherson-Synagogue01.jpg|The synagogue of [[Kherson]], [[Ukraine]].
image:Istanbul_Ashkenazi_Sinagogue_Interior.JPG|The [[Ashkenazi Synagogue of Istanbul]], [[Turkey]]. The synagogue was founded in 1900.       
Image:Central Synagogue Lex jeh.jpg|The [[Central Synagogue]] on [[Lexington Avenue]] in [[Manhattan]], [[New York City]], [[United States of America]].
Image:SynaStPersburgExt.JPG|The [[Grand Choral Synagogue]] of [[St. Petersburg]], [[Russia]]
Image:Jewish_synagouge_kochi_india.jpg| The [[Paradesi Synagogue]] in Kochi, [[Kerala]], India 
Image:Kiev34.jpg| The Synagogue in Podol district, [[Kiev]], [[Ukraine]]
Image:Great Synagogue of Rome 01.JPG|[[Great Synagogue of Rome]], [[Italy]]
Image:Shaarai Torah Worcester.jpg[[Shaarai Torah Synagogue (Worcester, Massachusetts)|Mother Synagogue of Worcester]]
File:RoyLindmanAbuhavSynagogueZefatIsrael 001.jpg|[[Abuhav synagogue]], Israel
File:Sofia Synagogue.jpg|[[Sofia Synagogue]], Bulgaria
File:Alte Synagoge Erfurt.JPG|The [[Erfurt Synagogue]] is the oldest synagogue in [[Europe]]
Image:Keneseth Eliyahu Synagogue of Bombay.jpg|[[Knesset Eliyahoo]], a 150-year-old Jewish Synagogue in Fort, [[Mumbai]], [[India]]
File:Synagogue in the city of Subotica, rooftops.jpg|[[Subotica Synagogue]] 1902. Secession style. [[Subotica]], [[Serbia]] Formerly part of the [[Austria-Hungary]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Judaism|Architecture}}
*[[Beth midrash]]
*[[Jewish services]]
*[[List of synagogues]]
*[[Shtiebel]]
*[[Siddur]]
*[[Synagogue architecture]]

==References==

{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Synagogue}}
* [http://www.slovak-jewish-heritage.org Guide to synagogues and other Jewish heritage sites in Slovakia]
* [http://www.guidepostusa.com/Listing.aspx?58538 B'Nai Israel Synagogue on GuidepostUSA]
* Joseph Tabory, [http://www.daat.co.il/daat/bibliogr/tavori-2.htm A list of articles on Synagogues (in various languages)], in [http://www.daat.co.il/index.htm Daat.col.il]
*[http://www.eldridgestreetsynagogue.org/ Eldridge Street Synagogue]
*[http://www.torahindex.com/sites/RavPealim/en/shul.htm picture of Aron Kodesh in Rav Pealim Beit Knesset]
*[http://comparethesynagogue.webs.com/ Webs.com]
*[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/32881567/ns/us_news-faith MSN.com], Synagogue doubles as mosque during Ramadan
* {{Wikisource-inline|list=
** {{CathEncy|wstitle=Synagogue|author=Walter Drum|noicon=x}}
** {{Cite EB1911|Synagogue|short=x|noicon=x}}
** {{Cite NIE|Synagogue|year=1905|noicon=x}}
** {{Cite Easton's|wstitle=Synagogue|noicon=x}}
}}

{{Jews and Judaism}}

[[Category:Synagogues| ]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

{{Link FA|fr}}

[[als:Synagoge]]
[[ar:كنيس]]
[[an:Sinoga]]
[[ast:Sinagoga]]
[[az:Sinaqoq]]
[[ba:Синагога]]
[[be:Сінагога]]
[[be-x-old:Сынагога]]
[[bg:Синагога]]
[[bar:Synagogn]]
[[bs:Sinagoga]]
[[br:Sinagogenn]]
[[ca:Sinagoga]]
[[cs:Synagoga]]
[[cy:Synagog]]
[[da:Synagoge]]
[[de:Synagoge]]
[[et:Sünagoog]]
[[el:Συναγωγή]]
[[es:Sinagoga]]
[[eo:Sinagogo]]
[[eu:Sinagoga]]
[[fa:کنیسه]]
[[fo:Sýnagogur]]
[[fr:Synagogue]]
[[fy:Synagoge]]
[[gd:Sìonagoga]]
[[gl:Sinagoga]]
[[ko:시나고그]]
[[hi:यहूदी मंदिर]]
[[hr:Sinagoga]]
[[io:Sinagogo]]
[[id:Sinagoga]]
[[ia:Synagoga]]
[[is:Sýnagóga]]
[[it:Sinagoga]]
[[he:בית כנסת]]
[[jv:Sinagoga]]
[[ka:სინაგოგა]]
[[kk:Синагога]]
[[sw:Sinagogi]]
[[ku:Kinîşt]]
[[mrj:Синагога]]
[[lad:Sinagoga]]
[[lbe:ХӀавра]]
[[la:Synagoga]]
[[lv:Sinagoga]]
[[lb:Synagog]]
[[lt:Sinagoga]]
[[li:Synagoge]]
[[hu:Zsinagóga]]
[[mk:Синагога]]
[[ml:ജൂതപ്പള്ളി]]
[[mr:सिनेगॉग]]
[[ms:Saumaah]]
[[mwl:Sinagoga]]
[[nl:Synagoge]]
[[ja:シナゴーグ]]
[[no:Synagoge]]
[[nn:Synagoge]]
[[nrm:Sŷnnagogue]]
[[oc:Sinagòga]]
[[pnb:شول]]
[[pap:Snoa]]
[[pl:Synagoga]]
[[pt:Sinagoga]]
[[ro:Sinagogă]]
[[ru:Синагога]]
[[sq:Sinagoga]]
[[scn:Sinagoga]]
[[simple:Synagogue]]
[[sk:Synagóga]]
[[sl:Sinagoga]]
[[sr:Синагога]]
[[sh:Sinagoga]]
[[fi:Synagoga]]
[[sv:Synagoga]]
[[tl:Sinagoga]]
[[ta:தொழுகைக் கூடம் (யூதம்)]]
[[tt:Синагога]]
[[th:สุเหร่ายิว]]
[[tr:Sinagog]]
[[uk:Синагога]]
[[ur:شول]]
[[vi:Hội đường Do Thái giáo]]
[[war:Sinagoga]]
[[yi:שול]]
[[bat-smg:Sinaguoga]]
[[zh:猶太會堂]]</text>
      <sha1>65mbqnkuq6aje9l2gj77w382ewnvts7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
