<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:East–West Schism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1240824</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522395400</id>
      <parentid>522303497</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T22:45:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Student7</username>
        <id>2745211</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Issue with lede */ yes to Montalban</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="194832">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1= 
{{WikiProject Christianity |class=C |importance=Top 
 |theology-work-group=yes |theology-importance=Top 
 |catholicism=yes |catholicism-importance=High 
 |eastern-orthodoxy=yes |eastern-orthodoxy-importance=Top 
 |core-topics-work-group = yes |core-topics-importance=Top
}}
{{WikiProject European history |class=c |importance=high }}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages |class=C |importance=High }}
{{WP1.0|class=C|category=category|VA=yes|WPCD=yes}}
}}
{{On this day |date1=2005-12-07|oldid1=30302760 }}
{{Off topic warning}}
{{Archive box |search=yes |bot=MiszaBot I |age=1 |units=month |index=/Archive index |
* [[Talk:East–West Schism/Archive 1|Archive 1]] &lt;small&gt;(Dec 2004 – Jan 2009)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:East–West Schism/Archive 2|Archive 2]] &lt;small&gt;(January–March 2009)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[/Archive 3|Archive 3]] &lt;small&gt;(March–December 2010)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[/Archive 4|Archive 4]] &lt;small&gt;(January–December 2011)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[/Archive 5|Archive 5]] &lt;small&gt;(February 2012 – )&lt;/small&gt;
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 5
|minthreadsleft = 5
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:East–West Schism/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}

== Disagreement with changes ==

Why is Esoglou making changes to Eastern Orthodox positions and content and playing games with how Eastern Orthodox [[Vladimir Lossky]] is in the article. No talkpage comments no discussion. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=518418890][[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 00:55, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:I did not change even one word of what the article says of Vladimir Lossky.  I did remove the phrase &quot;Orthodox theologians such as (Lossky)&quot;, which isn't sourced, since the citation is Lossky's alone and without a page number (indeed a Google Book search within the book for the quoted phrase &quot;God in uncreated essence&quot; said the phrase is not in the book).  I am still unaware that &quot;Orthodox theologians such as&quot; is &quot;Eastern Orthodox teaching or practice&quot;, but if that phrase is shown to be indeed Eastern Orthodox teaching or practice, I will humbly apologize for my ignorance.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:52, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
::Change is not change up is down right is wrong and remove is not a change. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 14:19, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Esoglou's restriction was &quot;Esoglou will not make article edits regarding Eastern Orthodox teaching or practice.&quot; How is Esoglou's question above here not a vio. As indeed it is Eastern Orthodox teaching and practice that [[Vladimir Lossky]] is an Orthodox theologian. [http://oca.org/in-memoriam/olivier-clement], [http://www.svots.edu/content/archbishop-canterbury-receives-honorary-doctorate-st-vladimir%E2%80%99s]. Again Esoglou violates his restrictions and nobody does anything. Again Esoglou shows he is completely ignorant of the positions of the Eastern Orthodox and has no problem acting from that ignorance to misrepresent the Eastern Orthodox and rewrite the Eastern Orthodox to fit his Roman Catholic POV. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 14:42, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
::::Both Esoglou and LoveMonkey are free to discuss these matters on talk pages. A change in a mention of Lossky appears to be something that Esoglou shouldn't do. Since eastern and western are closely interwined in this article it is best if E and LM will propose any changes like this first on the talk page before making them. [[User:EdJohnston|EdJohnston]] ([[User talk:EdJohnston|talk]]) 14:59, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::This change, which was among many that I made at the same time, did not deny that Lossky is an Orthodox theologian.  It is obvious that he is.  I wouldn't dream of denying it.  ''And I did not in fact deny it''.  But, while I accept EdJohnston's ruling and advice, I do not myself believe that the Eastern Orthodox Church teaches that Lossky is an Orthodox theologian, and I do not desire to make changes in Wikipedia statements about the teaching or practice of the Eastern Orthodox Church.  With his [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=518418890&amp;oldid=518368992 blanket revert] LoveMonkey changed a great many Wikipedia statements about the teaching of the Roman Catholic Church, but I think that action must be ignored, as must also his [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Filioque&amp;diff=518436464&amp;oldid=517786824 complete removal] elsewhere of one such statement, which he afterwards restored. Nor, in my opinion, is it worth making a fuss over [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=518426965&amp;oldid=518418890 his minor edit] concerning [[Latin Patriarch]]s, although that obviously concerned the teaching or practice of the Roman Catholic Church - much more obviously, I think, than that the edit LoveMonkey has complained of concerns either the teaching or the practice of the Eastern Orthodox Church.  So I make no counter-charge against LoveMonkey.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 15:44, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
::And that is the extent of it. No punishment no threats on his talkpage that he might be in violation. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk%3ALoveMonkey&amp;diff=419139467&amp;oldid=417712842] Total bias and B.S. Esoglou has done this now how many times? Yet nothing happens. NOTHING. Here's an example. I posted a link above from [[Saint Vladimir's Orthodox Theological Seminary]] saying it gave the Archbishop of Canterbury [[Rowan Williams]] (on his visit to the school )an honorary doctorate for Rowans work on Vladimir Lossky [http://www.svots.edu/content/archbishop-canterbury-receives-honorary-doctorate-st-vladimir%E2%80%99s]. So no one should be alarmed by Esoglou saying something like &quot;I do not myself believe that the Eastern Orthodox Church teaches that Lossky is an Orthodox theologian&quot; [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AEast%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=518530718&amp;oldid=518523810]no alarms that this editor is now admitting that they do not believe that the Eastern Orthodox Church teaches that Lossky is an Orthodox theologian. And that their edit removed mention of Lossky as such. No alarm no reprimand. Nothing. As for the Roman Catholic church killing and conquering the Eastern Orthodox and their territories, lands  and then by force imposing conversion and Papal rule on the Eastern Orthodox, as encapsulated under the historical templates [[Latin Patriarch]]s and or the [[Latin Empire]] a few things.[[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 15:51, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
*)The creation of the Latin Empire and why it is important and why Roman Catholic POV edit warring editors like Richard and Esoglou wish to either remove it's mention and or diminish it as much as Wikipedia will allow them.
::*)The existence of the [[Latin Patriarch]]s and the [[Latin Empire]] ([[Frankokratia]]) show that the Roman Catholic church collectively benefited from and exploited the [[Fourth Crusade]] and [[Siege of Constantinople (1204)|Sacking of Constantinople]]. This directly contradicts the idea put forward by the Roman Catholic church that the entire evil committed against the Eastern Orthodox Christians by the Roman Catholic crusaders was not the Roman Catholic churches fault and or that the Roman Catholic church did not condom it. It shows very clearly how the Roman Catholic church specifically exploited the events to impose on the Eastern Orthodox the power of Pope and the West and it's practices and doctrine. As it also shows that the Roman Catholic church did not try and REVERSE what had been done but rather exploited it. '''As after the [[Siege of Constantinople (1204)|Sacking of Constantinople]] the crusaders did not just leave, the Roman Catholic clergy actually moved in and took over. ''' Thats pretty damn important to give people a perspective and understanding of the extent of what actually happened. 
::*)The imposing of Latin Empire onto the Eastern Orthodox shows that there was a long long long history of Western Roman Catholics warring against the Eastern Orthodox. As people here like to point to things like the [[Massacre of the Latins]] but miss that [[William II of Sicily]] in 1185 sacked Thessalonica as retaliation for that (see [[Eustathius of Thessalonica]] which is a little hard to get the EO side of history in general considering the Roman Catholic crusaders destroyed the [[library of Constantinople]]). This for people whom might have missed it means that the Roman Catholic church warred on exploited and killed Eastern Orthodox Christians long before any Crusade and that the goal of the Roman Catholic church (as such) was finally obtained (at least from an Eastern Orthodox perspective) by the establishment of the Latin Empire and it's Latin Patriarchs. Example of Western '''double-cross'''. The West double crossed the East when it tried to with force, make the Eastern Orthodox recite the filioque, and or put the filioque in the Eastern Orthodox's recitation of the Nicene Creed (in Greek mind you not Latin) in the East, not simply accept that the West said it, but to make the Greeks say it as well. [[Pope Nicholas III]] indeed tried that very thing after promising that they would not do that exact thing (after the East agreed to reconciliation). And after the Eastern Orthodox accepted the Roman Catholic using the filioque modification in the Creed as recited in the West.. [http://books.google.com/books?id=auT8VbgOe48C&amp;pg=PA137&amp;lpg=PA137&amp;dq=sang+the+creed+with+the+filioque+in+greek&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=oQ7nvBnBBX&amp;sig=i727rDkHUzOr_LnoUdWQ0IkrJlo&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=gGnRTsPyGIXu2gWf0dn0DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=sang%20the%20creed%20with%20the%20filioque%20in%20greek&amp;f=true] 
::*)How is it that the Pope was sorry for and said that the Fourth Crusade was a bad thing and yet setup a Latin Speaking Patriarch in [[Hagia Sophia]] after converting the church to a Roman Catholic church (if East and West are Christian what conversion was really needed). How is it that the Popes and the West was so against what had happened to the Eastern Orthodox by way of the Fourth Crusade, that after the Fourth Crusade rather than leave and try and clean up they instead CONQUERED? And CONQUERED MORE causing a set of wars (The Eastern Orthodox rebelling and removing them from their lands). There is allot of fabricating documents by the Roman Catholic church (the [[donation of Constantine]] for example) and killing and warring and double crossing that simple is missing from the article. Right now the article tries to sell the Roman Catholic non-sense that the Roman Catholic church really are misunderstood, never did nothing wrong and the Eastern Orthodox are just but hurt about a bunch of things that happened so long in the past (like [[Catholic clergy involvement with the Ustaše]]) that the Eastern Orthodox are just being big babies. There is no attempt at the higher ups in the Roman Catholic church to tell their parishioners the truth about this and that it has been going on and continues to go on to this very day.  Christians confess their sins and atone for them. They don't cover them up and lie about it. They don't tell other Christian groups that they have murdered (for a non Orthodox one see [[St. Bartholomew's Day massacre]]) and slandered in the past that they have no justification for being traumatized for what happened in the past nor do they have a right to their grievances. When the establishment of the Latin Empire further drained the Eastern Empire of men and resources so desperately needed to fight off the on coming Muslims. Of course this is without mentioning that the Westerners like [[Orban]] actually helped the Muslims successfully win against the Eastern Orthodox in the [[Fall of Constantinople|fall of Constantinople]]. 
::*)Esoglou and Richard are here to make sure that people don't find out the Eastern Orthodox side of these conflicts and that the Roman Catholic church can continue to not have to answer for the things that this schism represent as historical events that happened in the past. They are here to keep people ignorant and misrepresent the Eastern Orthodox perspective. It's easier to make labels to marginalize and discredit people. Like labeling Eastern Orthodox Christians activities when they know this past and speak out about it as [[Anti-Catholicism]] [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Catholicism#Orthodox_Christianity]. Even though the word [[catholic]] is Greek in pedigree and origin, now Greek people can't even use their own words. Steal kill kill, how Christian.  The Latin Empire is a very important part of the pattern of behavior exhibited by the Roman Catholic church that DIRECTLY influences the Eastern Orthodox in their rejection of the supposed attempts at reconciliation by the Roman Catholic church. Here's is Richard deleting sourced content showing that the Roman Catholic church has tried to force the Eastern Orthodox to recite their creed with the filioque included. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Filioque&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=466792941] Richard has no justification for this (which is one of maybe thousands) of him and Esoglou censoring and silencing history and exorcising it from Eastern Orthodox subjects and articles they have no business white washing here on Wikipedia. And administrator Ed Johnston has helped out with them pulling this, quote a bit.  [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 19:40, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
-------------------
LoveMonkey has indulged once again in a long rant in which he maligns Esoglou, EdJohnston and myself.  It's too bad his passion for this topic comes with so much invective and vitriol because, if we could get past all that, he actually has some valid points.  I reiterate that much of the seminal work on Wikipedia's articles on [[History of the Eastern Orthodox Church]] was done by me in response to LoveMonkey's complaints that [[History of Christianity]] didn't adequately address the history of the Orthodox Church.  This effort dates back to 2007.  I remain committed to presenting the Eastern Orthodox POV to the extent that I am able.  I only wish that progress could be made in a collegial and collaborative manner rather than in this atmosphere of conflict and contention which makes the effort quite unpleasant.

For example, LoveMonkey points to this [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Filioque&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=466792941 edit] as an example of &quot;deleting sourced content showing that the Roman Catholic church has tried to force the Eastern Orthodox to recite their creed with the filioque included.&quot;  A look at the edit summary that I left reveals that my comment was &quot;First step towards tightening up this section; leave history in the &quot;historical&quot; section; this section should focus on &quot;recent theological perspectives&quot;&quot;  I don't remember the details of that particular edit but I do remember feeling that the section on &quot;Recent theological perspectives&quot; had too much history in it and that a section titled &quot;Recent theological perspectives&quot; should focus on &quot;recent&quot; developments that were &quot;theological&quot; in nature and not events that were further back in history.  In brief, I was only trying to reorganize the content of the article into appropriate sections rather than leaving the article to be a mish-mash of text that had no relation to the actual section headings.

That said, I think it is worthwhile for Wikipedia to address what LoveMonkey calls the &quot;long long long history of Western Roman Catholics warring against the Eastern Orthodox.&quot;  We might even want to consider an article dedicated to that topic although it would have to be more NPOV than LoveMonkey's rant above (i.e. it should not assume that the history is uniformly &quot;Western Roman Catholics beating up on defenseless and oppressed Eastern Orthodox&quot;.  If &quot;history is written by the victors&quot; and the Catholics were the victors (with the help of the Muslims), then Wikipedia should ensure that the history of the losers (i.e. the Eastern Orthodox) is also told.  However, we must make sure that any such coverage is NPOV. 
--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 18:52, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

:::::Yes boys and girls what Richard just posted nullifies all these historical things from happening and all of his actions here on wikipedia. '''Restore the edit you removed from the filioque article''' if you think its in the wrong spot don't edit war and remove it, no just move it, you can place it anywhere you think it is appropriate and you could have done that in the first place. Be warned everyone, don't hold your breath. Richard edit wars under all kinds of guises and loves to demean people by threatening RFCs [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AFilioque&amp;diff=466792314&amp;oldid=466652973] and calling their comments rants. Maybe Ed Johnston can go and put another threat, warning on my talkpage and pat ol Ricky here on the back. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 18:55, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:As mentioned before on this page, the [[Fourth Crusade]] which ended with the sacking of Constantinople was originally not sanctioned by Rome. (Skipping a long prequel), the pope had excommunicated a number of the Crusaders leaders for (essentially) &quot;going rogue.&quot; When confronted with the fait accompli of the &quot;restoration&quot; of Constantinople to the Latin realm, he rescinded the excommunications and presumably was happy with the unexpected result. But the original intent, and agreement with the Vatican, was Jerusalem. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 19:40, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
:::What's your point? How does what you say mean that the outcome of the Fourth Crusade and the Latin Empire are any different? If the Pope thought them (the consequences) bad then by your own accord rescind anything then? That undoes the whole Latin Empire (Frankocratia) history? You know it doesn't, it does cheapen all of these wrongs including peoples' lose of sons and daughters Eastern Orthodox human lives. And those of Byzantine Empire are not allowed to have grievances nor does it speak to the modern manifestations of these events in how the Eastern Orthodox consider the brutality of Western Christianity all the way down to the bombing of Kosovo and the vilification of the Serbs. However it is easier to see that wars for the West can be justified by lies even against &quot;other&quot; Christians. [http://rmiglobal.org/2012/01/11/erasing-balkan-christianity-old-orthodox-churches-in-kosovo-bombed-to-ruin/] As anyone familiar with the [[Crimean War]] for example knows what Western Christianity has done repeatedly to Eastern Christians with the help of the Muhammadan and for the sake of Muhammadan [http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,78937,00.html]. Lets not forget [http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=21672&amp;Cr=ICJ&amp;Cr1#.UIWyjGcYr3U]. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:56, 22 October 2012 (UTC)

== Quartodecimanism section controversy ==

With Esoglou's edits today on the Quartodecimanism section of the article [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=518467157&amp;oldid=518430883] can anyone tell why the Quartodecimanism should be mentioned? Let me guess, '''no you can't''' and therefore it would make sense that such non-sense be taken out of the article and I am beyond tried and sure that Esoglou would just love to jump at the chance to remove it. When will people ban this disruptive POV pushing editor from the Eastern Orthodox and Roman Catholic overlapping articles? For pulling underhanded things like this. Esoglou loves to feign ignorance to the heightening of frustration, that his actions are causing and that la la la I can't understand or hear you is justification for the things he pulls. Let me explain what Esoglou did. The Quartodecimanism is a controversy because the [[Pope Victor I|Pope of Rome Victor I]] went against [[Polycarp]] and by proxy the Apostle John (Polycarp was John's disciple) and the entire Middle Eastern churches and their tradition of Pascha.&lt;br&gt; 
&lt;br&gt;
Or in as plain an English as I can muster you have [[Pope Victor I]] saying that the Rome Church does not have to follow the traditions of the Apostles, the churches they established in the East, and those Apostle's disciples either. The Roman Catholic church does what it wants and does not have to listen to the Eastern churches that are actually in the bible and what they established by way of the Apostles. Quartodecimanism  is just one example of that type of behavior. So there you have the Roman Catholic church breaking with Apostolic tradition. Now read what Esoglou did to that section in the article and see if you can see that this pattern of behavior is actually fully articulated in what Esoglou has contributed? It isn't, as a matter of fact what Esoglou put in the article makes it look like the Roman Catholic church and Western Christian's don't use the word Easter and that they call passover the same thing that the Eastern Churches call it, Pascha when in fact there are plenty of Roman Catholics and Protestants alike that have never heard of the holiday as anything but Easter. Why is Esoglou allowed to confuse things like this? Over and over and over and over again. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:48, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

:It appears that Esoglou's edit is establishing that the Eastern Churches and Western Churches have differed on points of theology going all the way back to the earliest days of Christianity.  The assertion seems to be to imply that the seeds of the East-West schism go back much further than is usually discussed in history books.  I readily admit to being an ignoramus on this subject but, to me, this smacks of original research and I would like to see a citation that mentions the Quartodecimanism controversy in the context of the East-West schism.

:However, LoveMonkey goes a bit too far in his rant about Easter and Pascha.  I have to confess that in the 40 years since I was baptized a Catholic, I never learned the word &quot;Pascha&quot; and have never seen it as such.  I agree that most Catholics and Protestants might have to think a bit before they could place that word.  However, it is a regular part of the Catholic liturgy to talk of the &quot;Paschal lamb&quot; and the &quot;Paschal sacrifice&quot;.  We recognize these terms to correlate Jesus' death by crucifixion with the sacrifice of the Passover lamb.  It is difficult to speak of Protestants as a group but the idea that Easter and Passover are related through the symbolism of the Last Supper as a Passover meal and the sacrifice of Jesus as a substitute for the Paschal lamb is quite commonplace in most mainline Protestant denominations.  If you don't believe me, look at the articles on [[Easter]] and [[Paschal mystery]].

:Where Western Christians are more likely to get confused is the possible connection of Easter with [[Ēostre]], a Germanic pagan goddess.  A purist would condemn the conflation of Pascha with Eostre and the introduction of pagan symbols such as Easter bunnies and Easter eggs.  Perhaps it is the fault of Arius or Aquinas that such pagan interpolations have been allowed to occur. 

:--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 05:12, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Or perhaps Roman Catholic POV pushing editors on Wikipedia. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 19:00, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
::Excuse me, Richard, but you really don't need to cushion your well-founded criticisms of LoveMonkey's good-faith but wildly mistaken claims by at the same time criticizing me, this time for supposedly having indulged in original research in a Wikipedia article.  What did I change in the edit that LoveMonkey complains of?  Only this: I supplied reliable-source citations for three statements that have been in the article at least since [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East–West_Schism&amp;oldid=369155157 20 June 2010] (I haven't considered it worth my while checking back beyond 500 edits ago), and for which LoveMonkey took it into his head yesterday to demand supporting citations.  The basis (if it can be called a basis) for his complaint is my having supplied sources for the statement that Easter is called &quot;Pascha&quot; in both Greek and Latin.  I cited [http://books.google.com/books?id=ZP_f9icf2roC&amp;pg=PA308&amp;lpg=PA308&amp;dq=Easter+Pascha+Latin&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=CGS4MapSEa&amp;sig=Xz_5L7Io_cMemXRyD0GopZbSDFA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NJ1_UM_JHsS5hAe7kID4Dw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Easter%20Pascha%20Latin&amp;f=false this source] for the statement about both languages together and, for good measure, I cited two more for Greek: [http://books.google.com/books?id=qHaYlukmLvgC&amp;pg=PA216&amp;lpg=PA216&amp;dq=Easter+%CE%A0%CE%AC%CF%83%CF%87%CE%B1+in+Greek&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=_cb55DWUe9&amp;sig=yKGWiJDhkTdaANrCJ0IC9v5e5r8&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=xpp_UNOoDorNhAeOv4HwBw&amp;ved=0CEwQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Easter%20%CE%A0%CE%AC%CF%83%CF%87%CE%B1%20in%20Greek&amp;f=false this] and [http://books.google.com/books?id=LZ1o4Pi_KKkC&amp;pg=PA108&amp;lpg=PA108&amp;dq=Papaloizos+Easter+%CE%A0%CE%AC%CF%83%CF%87%CE%B1&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=RRMbwKxmRn&amp;sig=EITAOBrGs3XPQ5g8ZTjt4JcNj-4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=y5l_UIaQNsXRhAfE7ID4AQ&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Papaloizos%20Easter%20%CE%A0%CE%AC%CF%83%CF%87%CE%B1&amp;f=false this].  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:03, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Esoglou, my complaint of OR was not inspired by a desire to balance criticism of LoveMonkey with criticism of you.  The two criticisms were meant to be independent although they relate to the same text.  I confess that I have not researched the edit history to understand who is responsible for what text.  It may well be, as you assert, that you were just providing citations for existing text that someone else wrote.  So... rather than accusing you of conducting OR, let me say &quot;the inclusion of the Quartodecimanism controversy here smacks of OR&quot; regardless of whether it was you or someone else that introduced it.  I wrap this whole discussion with the disclaimer that I know very little on this topic and I am seeking to be educated on it.

:::That said, my understanding is that the East-West schism did not so much occur in 1054 as it was the culmination of events starting several centuries before and continuing for a few centuries afterward.  However, I think the mention of a late-second century controversy (Quartodecimanism controversy) may be inappropriate given that it arose before Constantinople was even a city.  Since I am not intimately familiar with the literature on the East-West schism, I am willing to accept the possibility that some scholars might point to the Quartodecimanism controversy as an example of early frictions between the Eastern and Western churches or that it might have been invoked by either the East or the West as an example of how the other side went off the rails.  I'm just saying that I'd like to see a citation to a reliable source who says this.

:::--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 15:58, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
::::Some of this stuff is not easy to follow. Thanks to Pseudo-Richard for a clear explanation. It appears that Wikipedia already has a plausible-looking article on [[Quartodecimanism]]. It is up to the editors here to reach consensus on whether Quartodecimanism is relevant enough to the East-West schism to deserve mention here as being part of the history of that schism. The article has asserted this [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East–West_Schism&amp;oldid=268170460#History for at least three years] and as of 2009 had no citations at all for this claim. It also used to say that the Rebaptism controversy of ca. 250 was part of the history of the schism. [[User:EdJohnston|EdJohnston]] ([[User talk:EdJohnston|talk]]) 16:53, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::::There ya go Ed same old same old. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 19:00, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::May I recall to everyone that LoveMonkey's complaint against me was, LoveMonkey said, with regard to [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=518467157&amp;oldid=518430883 this particular edit by me,] a complaint that he put under the heading &quot;Esoglou's confusing and obfuscating of the Quartodecimanism section controversy&quot;.  The mention of the Quartodeciman controversy in the article has nothing whatever to do with me, being introduced on [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East–West_Schism&amp;diff=258516516&amp;oldid=258359364 17 December 2008] by a certain &quot;Orthotheo&quot;, who, as his name perhaps suggests and as [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/Orthotheo his edits] indicate more clearly, appears to be a natural ally of LoveMonkey.  I have no objection to the rest of you discussing the appropriateness of Orthotheo's insertion, but please recognize that the complaint against me that this section was originally about is quite baseless, and that the confusion and obfuscation evident in the discussion (&quot;some of this stuff is not easy to follow&quot;) was in no way created by me.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 18:28, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::I apologize for having credited LoveMonkey's description of Esoglou's edit instead of believing my own eyes when looking at the edit.  It does seem that Esoglou did not rewrite the text and that any evisceration of the text, if it happened at all, was perpetrated much earlier.  However, we should not be looking for the criminal who changed the text but rather we should be looking at the question of whether the Quartodecimanism and Rebaptism controversies should be mentioned in this article (as EdJohnston suggested).  We should ask whether scholars mention these controversies when discussing the East-West schism.  I found a quote from Philip Voerding's &quot;The Trouble with Christianity&quot; that makes this assertion.  I am not convinced that it is relevant but at least we have one reliable source that asserts that it is.  I also have a quote from another source that suggests that it is not.[http://books.google.com/books?id=cL5lAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA307&amp;lpg=PA307&amp;dq=Quartodeciman+Orthodox&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=EPK5FlN8RR&amp;sig=UW7b1AglvTrTmzvzErOOq5j1tJg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=JY-BUNTNAorW9ASD34GgDQ&amp;ved=0CGEQ6AEwCTgU#v=onepage&amp;q=Quartodeciman%20Orthodox&amp;f=false]
{{outdent}}
And my account still stands as Ed is right now suggesting that the section be removed. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 19:00, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:No... I was the one who suggested that the text be removed and EdJohnston was just saying that we editors should come to a consensus on whether or not that was appropriate.  I had difficulty finding reliable sources who made the linkage between the Quartodeciman controversy and the East-West Schism but I did finally find one in Voerding's book &quot;The Trouble with Christianity&quot;.  I have added Voerding as a reference.  If you can provide other sources that make this linkage, I would appreciate it. {{unsigned|Richardshusr}}
::Hey but no one should be bothered by any of the other concerns I posted. Funny though with as much text, editors have posted here on the article talkpage they could have done allot to add some of these concerns into the article. But they keep saying that they are just too busy to contribute and yet not too busy to make excuses. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 19:16, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:::This page already contains difficult issues. They may take patience to resolve. At various times I've been frustrated by either Esoglou or LoveMonkey. At the moment there is some criticism due to both parties. Esoglou seems to have tried out a bold edit instead of first asking for feedback on talk. In response, LoveMonkey reverted and then made a hard-to-understand speech on the talk page suggesting various bad intentions by Esoglou. (&quot;The Roman Catholic church does what it wants and does not have to listen to the Eastern churches that are actually in the bible..&quot;)  I encourage both of you not to personalize issues. Thank you, [[User:EdJohnston|EdJohnston]] ([[User talk:EdJohnston|talk]]) 19:53, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
::::I am accustomed to baseless accusations by LoveMonkey, and Richard has withdrawn his accusation, but what bold edit do you, Ed, think I tried out.  I merely gave sources that showed that Easter is called ''Pascha'''in both Greek and Latin, a statement that LoveMonkey had tagged with &quot;citation needed&quot;.  What was bold about that?  The link to my edit was given right at the start by LoveMonkey.  Please look it up.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:13, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::I was thinking of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East–West_Schism&amp;diff=518467157&amp;oldid=518430883 this edit]. I need to withdraw my comment about that, because the matter is too confusing. Nonetheless I'm not seeing the urgency of your making a direct edit to the article in controversial areas without asking for comment on Talk first. I assume you've been adequately notified that this article is controversial. The original 'citation needed' was a bit strange because why would anyone dispute about the word for Easter in different languages. The person who placed the 'citation needed' may have been inexact. [[User:EdJohnston|EdJohnston]] ([[User talk:EdJohnston|talk]]) 20:40, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::That is precisely the edit in question.  What is controversial about the Latin and Greek for &quot;Easter&quot;?  The Latin for &quot;Easter&quot; is ''Pascha'' and nothing else, the Greek for &quot;Easter&quot; is Πάσχα (transliterated ''Pascha'') and nothing else.  You surely don't mean that every time LoveMonkey asks for a citation on such an obvious and objectively non-controversial matter, I may not provide a citation, but must instead initiate on the Talk page a section beginning: &quot;Please, I would like to enter on the article page information related only to language translation and not a matter of either Eastern Orthodox or Roman Catholic doctrine, so as to answer a question that has been put there by an editor who must think that, his question not being a matter of either Eastern Orthodox or Roman Catholic doctrine, ''he'' need not raise it on the Talk page&quot;!  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 21:18, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
::::And yet the Roman Catholic church still uses the word Easter [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/homilies/2012/documents/hf_ben-xvi_hom_20120407_veglia-pasquale_en.html].. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 00:18, 20 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::LoveMonkey placed a citation-needed tag on the statement that Easter is called &quot;Pascha&quot; in both Greek and Latin.  I responded to the request for citations, never dreaming that anybody other than LoveMonkey would object to this action for the good of Wikipedia.  Imagine an encyclopedia maintaining a question mark over so clear and undisputed a fact!  Should I have instead removed the tag and given as edit summary &quot;Please don't try to pick a quarrel over whether the sky is blue&quot;?  (This is obviously just an ironic rhetorical question.)  LoveMonkey did object.  I thought that the best course of action was simply not to reply to so baseless an objection.  But two other editors let themselves be persuaded by it, in one case in spite of a cautiously expressed appeal I had made, in view of past experience: &quot;Perhaps it is best to let the discussion on that page play out and not intervene, at least not at an early stage.&quot;  Their intervention forced me to protest against their condemnation of me for providing citations for something that is objectively non-controversial and that anyone can easily check by, for instance, Google Translate.  I am not sure that both condemnations have even now been withdrawn.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:33, 20 October 2012 (UTC)
::;Esoglou violated his edit restrictions that has been established. Esoglou has no respect for anything POV but his own. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 12:55, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

== Mention of Quartodeciman controversy ==

Mention of the Quartodeciman controversy in this article arose out of an edit by Leadwind on [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East–West_Schism&amp;diff=199837152&amp;oldid=199580504 21 March 2008] stating: &quot;Prior to the official start of the schism, Eastern and Western Christians had a history of difference and disagreement ''dating back to the second century''.&quot;  When the phrase I have italicized was questioned (by me) on the grounds of lack of evidence of trouble between Rome and the East (as a whole) that far back, Orthotheo responded with the example of the Quartodeciman controversy.  If Leadwind's claim is not maintained, the mention of the controversy will go too.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:55, 20 October 2012 (UTC)

I have never heard of nor see how the source Richard just added to the article is conformed to WP:VS. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=518752463&amp;oldid=518587097]. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 19:56, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:Yuh... I found Voerding's book via Google search.  I had my doubts about adding that source especially since the publisher is AuthorHouse which suggests that it could be self-published but since it was the only non-blog source I could find that linked Quartodecimanism to the East-West schism, I added it pending further research.  I am happy to withdraw that reference in favor of more reliable sources.--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 21:35, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
::Mention of this book, apparently by a Muslim (&quot;PBUH&quot;), which has been objected to on reliable-source grounds and has not been defended, can surely be removed.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 06:29, 21 October 2012 (UTC)
::::Perhaps this has been known to you all along but I only just figured out yesterday that &quot;PBUH&quot; stands for &quot;Peace Be Upon Him&quot;.  Of course, if I had bothered to consult Wikipedia, I would have figured that out much earlier cuz there's an article titled [[PBUH]]. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 23:12, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
:::But, if we remove the source, it leaves the assertion that it supports unreferenced and therefore also subject to removal.  I am OK with removing it since no one has stepped forward with a more reliable source.  If LoveMonkey will agree to its removal, we should go ahead and do it. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 15:14, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
:From reading our article on the [[First Council of Nicaea]] (AD 325) it seems that the Quartodeciman controversy was a minor footnote even then. (See [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Council_of_Nicaea#cite_note-47 this reference]). Also, it is hard to read the events of Nicaea as showing any East-West difference of opinion. It appears that Nicaea was trying to resolve a controversy among churches in Asia. Higher-quality sources would need to be found if they are going to persuade the editors here that the Quartodeciman stuff is part of the East-West schism. [[User:EdJohnston|EdJohnston]] ([[User talk:EdJohnston|talk]]) 17:42, 21 October 2012 (UTC)
:As I said in my 8 December 2008 objection to Leadwind's edit, the disagreement was between Rome (not the West as a whole) and a mere part of the East (and, I could have added but didn't, there were disagreements also between Rome and certain parts of the West).  When Orthotheo thought he had answered my objection with his reference to the Quartodeciman dispute, I thought it best to say no more.  Any repetition of my objection could have provoked a defence of Orthotheo's edit by another editor who will do me a favour, if now he allows the claim of a second-century East-West divide to be removed.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:37, 21 October 2012 (UTC)

::Agreed.  It seems we are waiting for LoveMonkey's agreement.  (Although we don't NEED his agreement, it would be nice to have a true consensus.  Since he himself has questioned Voerding as a reliable source, perhaps he will concede that it is not at all easy to find reliable sources to support Orthotheo's assertion that the Quartodeciman controversy is related to the East-West schism.  In truth, I half expected LoveMonkey to bring forth a quote from Lossky or Romanides but, if none can be found from such strident anti-Catholic writers, then we should consider that the linkage between the Quartodeciman controversy and the East-West schism is more likely a popular notion than a scholarly one. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 15:14, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
::Object. [[Christos Yannaras]] mentions it. I have to find the book. I believe it is the Western Identity one. As it is obvious that it is beyond time consuming and disgusting to try and contribute. It is editors like Esoglou and Richard whom make wikipedia a nightmare and I dare anybody to take a look at some of the things Wikipedia has allowed them to pull on other editors here whose only crime was not agreeing with their Roman Catholic POV. [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Filioque/Archive_4], [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Theoria], [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Theoria/Archive_1], [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Baptism/Archive_4#WP:RS_againh], [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Primacy_of_the_Bishop_of_Rome], [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Papal_infallibility/Archive_3], [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Esoglou&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=497973930], [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Esoglou&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=497973930], [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Eastern_Orthodox_%E2%80%93_Roman_Catholic_theological_differences] No matter how many wiki here will find an excuse to not be even handed.   [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 19:14, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
:::I suppose we must wait for LoveMonkey to present (within a reasonable time) the promised reliable source that not merely ''mentions'' the Victor-Polycrates dispute (there are many such reliable sources) but ''states that there is a relationship between that dispute and the East-West schism'' (which Richard, no doubt rightly, says is not at all easy to find).  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 19:56, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::Nope. I am here on the talkpage and that's it I am tired of wasting time to only get my opinion ignored and my contributions removed. There are sources and they need to be found and that's the whole reason I requested them. However you both are not of the cut to be doing the edits that you have been doing here. Just like the disasters you've committed with your edit warring (article like theoria and Eastern Orthodox- Catholic differences) you're making wikipedia a mess. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 21:03, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::Sounds like a declaration of no intention to present any reliable source linking the Victor-Polycrates dispute with the East-West schism.  But I doubt if the matter is important enough for resisting LoveMonkey's will.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:25, 23 October 2012 (UTC)
::Sounds like Esoglou doesn't care if something is right or not. Nor to actually do some work and find out for himself. No that would mean he might have to do something other than push his Roman Catholic POV. As it has been said time and time again Esoglou doesn't even read or know the works of Orthodox theologians or the Orthodox POV he spends his time creating and or pushing original research against Orthodox theologians. Post here that you actually tried to source the passage as it was. Instead of doing another drive by like it looks right now. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 19:03, 23 October 2012 (UTC)


My assessment is that the entire beginning of the &quot;History&quot; section is sorely deficient and that even a &quot;rewrite&quot; would not help.  What's needed is an entire block of text (perhaps 2-3 paragraphs) that summarizes the history of the schism and devotes an entire paragraph to explaining the roots of the schism including the early divisions of the church and the existence of early schisms.  Unfortunately, this is an effort that will require at least a few hours of work and I don't have that available at the moment so I will simply state that I think this needs to be done.  I am likely to begin work on this over at [[

History of the East–West Schism]] and then bring a summary over here when I'm done.  But I can't do it now as real-world obligations preclude my taking on this task at the moment. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 18:07, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
:If someone wanted to make a formal complaint about the deliberately provocative attitude of LoveMonkey, inappropriate for a Wikipedia editor, there would be enough evidence on this page alone.  I won't.  Nor, as I said, do I feel like devoting serious time to this article when I find myself blamed for simply providing a requested citation (which required no study) in addition to the usual burden of having to read through a logorrhoea of complaints against what western Europeans did to his homeland (including even, of all things, the Crimean War, as if that were a cause of the schism this article is about) and, for instance, against the English language for applying the word &quot;Easter&quot; to a Christian celebration, a matter that he would do better to take up with the Orthodox Church in America (see [http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/faithandlife/pasch.pdf this] and [http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith7070 this] and [http://oca.org/orthodoxy/the-orthodox-faith/worship/the-church-year/post-easter-sundays this)] and with Greek Orthodox metropolitans such as [http://www.orthodoxresearchinstitute.org/articles/fasts_feasts/makarios_tillyrides_celebrate_easter.htm this].  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:29, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
::Agreed as to sufficiency of evidence and the rambling and often pointless logorrhea.  Also agreed that it's not worth the effort to seek sanctions.  Far easier to ignore it and carry on with substantive efforts to improve this and other articles. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 23:07, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

===Citation request===

It appears that LoveMonkey's original citation request was regarding the term &quot;Easter&quot;.  Esoglou has provided citations although this seems not to be satisfactory to LM.  At the end of the day, there seems to be little or no evidence that a dispute about Easter vs. Pascha is at all relevant to the East-West schism and so the citations seem odd and out-of-place in this article.  I would be inclined to remove them but, in the current situation, that seems ill-advised.

The more substantive question is whether the Quartodeciman controversy should be mentioned in this article at all.  LoveMonkey claims that &quot;there are sources to be found&quot; but implies that he will not provide them.  Unless we are willing to accept Voerding as a reliable source, the Quartodeciman text is unsupported and subject to removal.  I'm inclined to do that but I am waiting to understand whether LoveMonkey prefers to keep the text or to have it removed.  If he would like it kept, then perhaps he can provide us a quote from Yannaras.  If he is OK to remove it, then that is easily done.

--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 16:54, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

:Post here the policy for removing text from an article. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 18:59, 23 October 2012 (UTC)
::That would be [[WP:V]]: &quot;Any material that requires a source but does not have one may be removed&quot;. [[User:EdJohnston|EdJohnston]] ([[User talk:EdJohnston|talk]]) 19:47, 23 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::Let me confirm somethings just so they are posted here. 
:::::This article is about the last schism between East and West.
:::::Quartodeciman was a schism between the Eastern Churches and the Western Churches[http://books.google.com/books?id=Jg3XrcuLeqsC&amp;pg=PA65&amp;lpg=PA65&amp;dq=Quartodeciman+schism+Polycrates&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Hv-tVwEu-6&amp;sig=CKYG4ppDWRR0rmfqSBmCYCU5MZE&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=kO2GUN2xN4Kc9QTr_YCIAg&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Quartodeciman%20schism%20Polycrates&amp;f=false]
:::::The Quartodeciman schism has no obvious relation to the East West schism because there is no source that refers to Quartodeciman schism as a schism between Eastern and Western Christianity. Thats because the issue is about the Pope and the authority of the Pope causing a schism not the actual 14th as the name pulls this bigger issue away from.
:::::Thanks to the brilliant editors Eoglou and Richard we are now to believe that no such person as [[Hippolytus of Rome]] existed. That no person named Photios I of Constantinople ever mentioned this Hippolytus.[http://www.feed7.com/ad-203680-87/Hippolytus-of-Rome-170-235-A-D-Photios-I-of-Constantinople-d], [http://books.google.com/books?id=taagmnUcsD8C&amp;pg=PT815&amp;lpg=PT815&amp;dq=Quartodeciman+Photios+I+of+Constantinople&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=kzobHjrJIW&amp;sig=8-lXYQ4INggZu8zsqcujsPrHluc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=pO-GUKSwC5Lo9gS-woDAAw&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA] I wonder what the term &quot;Emergence of a Monarch-Bishop&quot; might be referring to.[http://www.amazon.com/Hippolytus-Roman-Church-Third-Century/dp/9004102450/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1351020144&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=9004102450] 
:::::People have nothing to do but educate these two disruptive editors. Now note that Photios would be enough but then people here editing haven't read Photios or are being ignorant of Eastern Orthodox theologians and their works these two would have known about sources saying these kinds of things. IF THEY KNEW WHAT THEY WERE TALKING ABOUT IN THE FIRST PLACE. [http://books.google.com/books?id=5kJpIPi2rSgC&amp;pg=PA19&amp;lpg=PA19&amp;dq=Quartodeciman+Photios+I+of+Constantinople&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=MWWSMez7Ee&amp;sig=FdRi0vCXEcsP-SlK4m8o7-lffKk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=pO-GUKSwC5Lo9gS-woDAAw&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Quartodeciman%20Photios%20I%20of%20Constantinople&amp;f=false]
:::::But again Esoglou and Richard can come here and be disruptive and post all kinds of ignorant theory and attack other editors and be lazy and waste time and delete content and argue with all kinds of disruptive behavior and make other editors hate wikipedia because admins here will not curtain the crap that they pull.  
::::::::Here it is specifically, about [[Pope Victor I]] Patriarch of Rome...
:::::::::::::::::&quot;But this did not please all the bishops. And they besought him to consider the things of peace, and of neighborly unity and love. Words of theirs are extant, sharply rebuking Victor.
:::::::::::::::::'''Among them was Irenæus, who, sending letters in the name of the brethren in Gaul over whom he presided, maintained that the mystery of the resurrection of the Lord should be observed only on the Lord’s day. He fittingly admonishes Victor that he should not cut off whole churches of God which observed the tradition of an ancient custom.'''&quot; [[Eusebius of Caesarea]] (Church History, V, xxiv) 
:::::The section needs to reflect that its more than something called Quartodeciman it was about the Pope overstepping and being rebuked. The issue being a history of the Pope of Rome not being infallible and not being considered the last word and not being considered senior to the [[Patriarch of Antioch]] [[Irenaeus]]. Not the word Quartodeciman which misses my original point.
:::::The issue is that in the situation that has gotten labelled here Quartodeciman people can see why the Eastern Church would deny things like the Primacy of Pope and how the Western church did not have the final say by way of things like [[Papal infallibility]] or whatever and that a council in the East (not called nor attended by the Patriarch of Rome, Pope mind you) would decide this issue and others and that even other Saints and Patriarchs acted contrary to what the Roman Catholic church would have people believe. I can not fix the crazy section nor how it keeps being made more and more crazy. However some sort of mention of this would be proper to the article. But I won't again hold my breath to count on Esoglou and or Ricky to be educated enough about these things to handle them properly. Please note that some of these sources are Western and appear to be ignorant of the idea that Eastern Christians in the bible and in their culture have no history of calling Pascha, Easter.[[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:19, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

{{outdent}} The Eusebius quote is a primary source.  We should find a secondary source that quotes Eusebius in the context of discussing the Great Schism.  McGuckin would be great.  

Without a secondary source, pointing to an earlier schism and saying, &quot;See! That example of papal overstepping is one of the precursors of the Great Schism&quot; is original research.  Philip Voerding points to the Quartodeciman controversy but doesn't say much about it other than to point to it.  And we're not so confident about Voerding being a reliable source.  Does McGuckin mention the Quartodeciman controversy in the context of discussing the Great Schism?  Is it common for Orthodox theologians to mention the Quartodeciman controversy?  BTW, I noticed that neither the Quartodeciman controversy nor Eusebius are mentioned in the article on [[Supremacy of the Roman Pontiff]].  That article seems like an obvious place to mention this topic.
--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 20:41, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

:More B.S. [[Eusebius of Caesarea]] was historian and in quoting Irenaeus if a primary source. What does that make Irenaeus? [http://books.google.com/books?id=dTHudoOLh6UC&amp;pg=PT1640&amp;lpg=PT1640&amp;dq=Quartodeciman+Photios+I+of+Constantinople&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Ll-KljU9Oz&amp;sig=spotb7RuOlsmIzenU5JIDfRfTyo&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=pO-GUKSwC5Lo9gS-woDAAw&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwAw] &quot;We ought to obey God not men.&quot; [http://www.vision.org/visionmedia/article.aspx?id=532] [[Polycrates of Ephesus]]... Read the article here on wiki about Polycrates of Ephesus. Let me guess though Ed is AWOL or MIA again and all of this pedantic wrangling Ed Johnston here endorses and will help to enforce. Like I said real ignorant people here fighting to push that ignorance and they get their way with the help of admins here. I am just wasting my time. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:56, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

::There are more than 1000 admins on Wikipedia.  If you wish, you can ask another one to step in and adjudicate.  Or you can issue a [[WP:RFC|Request for Comment]].  Or you can go to the [[WP:RSN|Reliable Source Noticeboard]].  Stop whining and take steps towards [[WP:DR|Dispute Resolution]] if you feel you are unable to reach consensus here.  Or just provide a source that is dated after 1054.  A source from the 20th or 21st century would be preferable. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 21:12, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

::::You are beyond arrogant. Stop screwing up and telling me what to do. Since when is an historian NOT a valid source. Making up the rules and adhering to the ones you like. Go get these people and read them..Your education is not my responsibility. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 02:07, 24 October 2012 (UTC)

::The Allen Brent book on Hippolytus looked promising at first but, after reading the Customer Review, I am not convinced that it is relevant.  There is no direct mention of the Great Schism in the review.  This is the essence of original research.  Wikipedia editors are not allowed to point to things &quot;A&quot; and &quot;B&quot; that they think are related and then write article text that says &quot;A and B are related.&quot;  We must find a reliable source that says that. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 21:19, 23 October 2012 (UTC)
:::More edit warring. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 02:07, 24 October 2012 (UTC)

I found another source, a book by Tom Streeter but alas it is also published by [[AuthorHouse]] which, according to Wikipedia, is a self-publishing house.  Thus, neither the Voerding book nor the Streeter book are qualified as reliable sources.  I looked at McGuckin and he does mention the Quartodeciman controversy but his [http://books.google.com/books?id=KLIFfmipXcoC&amp;pg=PA32 text] doesn't really link this controversy to the Great Schism.  Despite all the abuse and invective from LoveMonkey charging all sorts of bad intentions and incompetence on my part, I am inclined to believe that the Quartodeciman controversy is considered by at least some Orthodox as an example of early papal overreaching.  I hope that some editor will find a reliable source that we can use to support the text in question. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 05:45, 24 October 2012 (UTC)

Here is another source - a book on [http://books.google.com/books?id=IeH4OKYflbkC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=East-West+schism+origins&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=VGaNt8xCLu&amp;sig=oqpk3G6WzUW5TWJSGB1uO2N8YoY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=twCIUK7CJo7-8ATHvIHgBg&amp;ved=0CFYQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=East-West%20schism%20origins&amp;f=false Papal Primacy] by Klaus Schatz, a German Jesuit priest.  Schatz does not link the Quartodeciman controversy to the Great Schism but he does point to it as one of the &quot;first attempts on the part of the Roman Church to assume responsibility for the whole Church&quot;.  He notes that &quot;these first initiatives encountered resistance and ended in failure.  Rome did not succeed in maintaining its position against the contrary opinion and praxis of a significant portion of the church.&quot;.  He concludes his discussion by saying &quot;there was no enduring breach of communion between Rome and the Churches of Asia Minor&quot;.

My take on all this is that the Quartodeciman controversy cannot be one of the seeds of the Great Schism because there was too much later ecclesiological development, most notably that the pentarchy doesn't exist yet and doesn't begin to be recognized as such until the 4th century.  The Quartodeciman controversy is, however, one of the precursors of papal primacy which is a core issue in the Great Schism.  

I think our current text is inadequate and even misleading.  The current text reads as follows:

: In the centuries immediately before the schism became definitive, a few short schisms between Constantinople and Rome were followed by reconciliations. Even during the period of Early Christianity, part of the East (Western Anatolia) was in disagreement with Pope Victor I over Quartodecimanism, holding that Easter (called Pascha in both Greek[8][9] and Latin)[10] should be celebrated at the full moon, like the Jewish Passover, not on the following Sunday.[11][12] 

To a reader who is not well-versed in the history of the Church, this text might be read to suggest that the Quartodecimanism controversy was an early disagreement between Constantinople and Rome.  Moreover, &quot;Early Christianity&quot; is a period far removed from &quot;the centuries immediately before the schism became definitive&quot;.  So, I think we need a rewrite of this paragraph to better communicate the relative chronological positions of the various events being discussed.  Also, Schatz mentions the baptism of heretics as another early example of Rome asserting its primacy.  In order to better follow the most reliable source that we have at the moment, we should mention both controversies as well as Schatz's assessment that Rome did not succeed in its attempt to use its primacy to impose its opinion on other churches.

--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 15:27, 24 October 2012 (UTC)

:While you may be right, aren't you nonetheless getting into rather deep water, when you link the East-West Schism with what some writers see as early examples of Rome asserting its primacy?  There are those who interpret even the first-century Letter of Clement, written to a church in Greece, as an example of Rome asserting its primacy.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:18, 24 October 2012 (UTC)

::It is clear that Rome's claims of primacy are very much at the root of the East-West schism.  The question (to my mind, anyway) is whether the East always objected to all such claims or only started objecting at a later date as those claims became more assertive and insistent.  (Kind of like saying &quot;we don't mind that you claim primacy as long as you agree with us&quot;)

::There are two separate but related questions here: when did Rome start asserting its primacy and when and to what extent did other bishops (especially those in the East) begin objecting to Rome's claims?  I don't expect all scholars to agree in answering these questions.  Our text should reflect the diversity of opinions on these questions.  My problem is that I am not well-versed enough in the field to know what the different answers are and who the main proponents of each answer are.  I have been told that Google Books is a poor research tool and I admit that it is.  A more defensible approach would be to have the text written by an editor who is well-acquainted with the scholarly views on this topic.  Unfortunately, at the moment, all we have is me (an ignoramus) and LoveMonkey who asserts that there are sources but has not been forthcoming in sharing them with us. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 21:50, 24 October 2012 (UTC)
:::In order to make a link between the East-West Schism and refusals by eastern bishops of a much earlier date to accept the authority of the Roman church (which of course wasn't the whole of the West), would you not have to show that such refusals were more significant than those by western bishops?
:::I don't feel just now like studying the question that you are dealing with.  It would bring me into yet another conflict with an editor who at one point writes: &quot;Can anyone tell why the Quartodecimanism should be mentioned? Let me guess, no you can't and therefore it would make sense that such non-sense be taken out of the article&quot;; and then later claims that there are mysterious reliable sources that support the mention here of a disagreement between a Western bishop and an Eastern bishop, a disagreement speedily smoothed over.
:::Should the antecedents be limited to instances of rivalry between Constantinople (alone) and Rome (alone), beginning with the 381 First Council of Constantinople and culminating in the 1054 spat?
:::Google Books is a poor research tool only in the sense that a library is a poor research tool.  It gives you access to many books, but you have to sift them and pay heed only to the authoritative ones.  Questia and the like give authoritative sources alone, but only, I have found, a limited number of them on any particular topic and, usually, not the one you want.  I still wonder if the other two Questia-like services for which, in view of the picture you and Ed have presented of me, I did not dare apply, would be better than Questia.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:38, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

== Easter vs. Pascha ==

Some Orthodox Christians discourage the use of the word Easter, believing that the term has roots in pagan rites of the spring equinox and overtones of fertility. Most English speakers are unaware of the etymological origins of Easter, however, and use it without any sense of pagan connotations, and so Easter is also used by many Orthodox English speakers. [http://orthodoxwiki.org/Pascha] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:00, 19 October 2012 (UTC)
:The above text is quoted verbatim from the OrthodoxWiki.  I note that the lead sentence of the article states &quot;Pascha (Greek: Πάσχα), also called Easter, is the feast of the Resurrection of the Lord.&quot;  There is not a separate article in the OrthodoxWiki on Easter; rather [http://orthodoxwiki.org/Easter Easter] redirects to [http://orthodoxwiki.org/Pascha Pascha] which suggests that these are considered one and the same topic (i.e. it is not asserted that there is a Western holy day called &quot;Easter&quot; which is distinct from the Orthodox holy day called &quot;Pascha&quot;).  Thus, we are not talking about two different things but rather two different names for the same thing and whether the appropriate translation for &quot;Pascha&quot; is &quot;Passover&quot; or &quot;Easter&quot;.  Since the vast majority of English speakers will recognize [[Passover]] to be a Jewish holiday, using &quot;Passover&quot; instead of &quot;Easter&quot; would be confusing without significant explanation which would amount to POV-pushing (i.e. the POV would be &quot;yes, we know the vast majority of you don't use these words this way but YOU ARE WRONG and we are teaching you THE RIGHT WAY to use these words&quot;).  Wikipedia should not presume to know how language &lt;i&gt;should&lt;/i&gt; be used nor should it seek to impose such &quot;right usage&quot; upon the public at large.--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 18:01, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

&quot;I hear occasionally from someone who sometimes accuses the Orthodox Church of being &quot;foreign&quot;, and so unsuitable for the British. A few days ago he sent me a card saying &quot;the word in English is Easter&quot;. My reply was &quot;the word in Greek (and, therefore, English), is Pascha&quot;.&quot;
[http://www.orthodoxresearchinstitute.org/articles/fasts_feasts/harper_pascha_easter.htm] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 00:09, 20 October 2012 (UTC)
:... which goes to confirm that the Greek for &quot;Easter&quot; is Πάσχα.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:00, 20 October 2012 (UTC)
::::No it doesn't. The article by Fr. Michael Harper is named -IT IS PASCHA NOT EASTER! 
&quot;But let the Orthodox stick to the right word, which is &quot;Pascha&quot;. Let us use it in our own circles, and discard the pagan word &quot;Easter&quot;. We should do this — not to be different, but to be truthful.&quot;[http://www.orthodoxresearchinstitute.org/articles/fasts_feasts/harper_pascha_easter.htm] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 02:16, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
:LoveMonkey, I don't see why you imagine anybody objects to the Orthodox (more strictly, &quot;some Orthodox Christians&quot;) calling the feast &quot;Pascha&quot; or whatever they choose.  And, whether you were aware of it or not, your quotation did confirm what I had already produced clear evidence for: that Greeks (of whatever confession) call the feast &quot;Πάσχα&quot; (as the French call it &quot;Pâques&quot;, Germans &quot;Ostern&quot;, Italians &quot;Pasqua&quot;, Portuguese &quot;Páscoa&quot;, Spaniards, who apply &quot;Pascua&quot; to other Christian feasts as well, &quot;Pascua de Resurrección&quot;, Danes &quot;Påske&quot;, Dutch &quot;Pasen&quot;, Finns &quot;pääsiäinen&quot; ...).  Your quotation did explicitly state: &quot;The word in Greek ... is Pascha.&quot;
:I presume your silence means you do not object to removal of the claim that the dispute between Victor of Rome and Polycrates of Ephesus about the date for celebrating the feast was a prelude to the East-West schism, as discussed above.  Its removal will leave it clear that the East-West schism originated in a Constantinople-Rome dispute, preceded by shorter schisms between those two sees.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 09:30, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
::Thank you, Esoglou, for the mention of the more direct etymological linkage to Pascha in European languages other than English and German.  I knew much of that but had not thought of it.  What is the official language of the Catholic Church?  Latin.  What is the word for Easter in Latin?  I trust it is &quot;Pascha&quot; or something close to it.  So, despite the introduction of Eostre into the lay celebration of the feast in some cultures, there is little point in focusing on that as a theological or ecclesiological difference.  Truly, it is long past time to put this non-issue to rest.  There are enough true issues between East and West that there is no need to manufacture artificial controversies for the sole purpose of heaping baseless accusations against the other side.  Next, we will no doubt be hearing complaints about Christmas trees and Santa Claus. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 15:24, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::No the word pascha translates to &quot;passover&quot;. The word Easter does not. Again Roman Catholic POV pushing editors here don't have to listen as they have free reign. I will state the obvious. This is a different section and this is not a continuation of what is above. 
:::&quot;We need to realise also that there is no equivalent word for &quot;Easter&quot; in the Greek language, for one simple but important reason, the word is an Anglo-Saxon word for a pagan festival. The word in its original use is entirely pagan. According to the English Church historian Bede, it derives from a pagan spring festival in honour of Eastra or Ostara a Teutonic goddess.&quot; [http://www.orthodoxresearchinstitute.org/articles/fasts_feasts/harper_pascha_easter.htm] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 18:25, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
::::What Greek Christians celebrate in church under the name &quot;Πάσχα&quot; is a Christian feast, even if etymologically the word once signified a Jewish festival.  Saying that they celebrate a non-Christian Jewish festival would be maligning them.  What English-speaking Christians celebrate in church under the name &quot;Easter&quot; is a Christian feast, even if etymologically the word once signified a non-Christian festival of spring.  Saying that they celebrate a non-Christian pagan festival &lt;s&gt;would be&lt;/s&gt; is maligning them.
::::Since the English language is not one of the causes of the East-West schism, discussing the proper English term for the &quot;Christian festival and holiday celebrating the resurrection of Jesus Christ on the third day after his crucifixion at Calvary as described in the New Testament&quot; (as the Wikipedia article [[Easter]] calls it) is off topic here.  Go and raise it at [[Talk:Easter]].  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:00, 22 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::What the Eastern Orthodox celebrate is called pascha or passover it's not called Easter. There it is in Greek, Hebrew and English. It's not called Easter nor has the word pascha ever been translated to Easter by the Greeks there is no word for Easter in the Greek language. I just sourced that. This is the type of nonsense that is called obfuscating and has nothing to do with getting the correct perspective needed in this article. At point again are we saying that the Roman Catholic teachings on their Pope have no bearing and or are not a factor in the East West schism. Richard is saying that now too. Talk about revisionism and original research.  [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:52, 23 October 2012 (UTC)

=== Which Apostles called pascha Easter where in the Greek bible is the word Easter? ===
&lt;br&gt;
::&quot;But let the Orthodox stick to the right word, which is &quot;Pascha&quot;. Let us use it in our own circles, '''and discard the pagan word &quot;Easter&quot;.[http://www.orthodoxresearchinstitute.org/articles/fasts_feasts/harper_pascha_easter.htm]'''
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
::::::Or how Esoglou gets it both ways. The Roman Catholic church can call it Easter and yet almost never refer to it as Pascha but Esoglou can say they call it pascha, when the Vatican calls it Easter. [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/homilies/2012/documents/hf_ben-xvi_hom_20120407_veglia-pasquale_en.html]As always Esoglou presumes. And you put words in my mouth. As an POV pusher this is a common tactic of yours. My point above is the same here in this section. The West calls it Easter they do not as common practice call it Pascha. Too confuse the two is edit warring by way of [[obfuscating]] as some of Ed Johnston's comments quite clearly indicate that he is confused. Esoglou loves to argue outrageous points in order to frustrate contributors and get them to leave wikipedia. Here's a talkpage archive full of this back and forth between Richard and Esoglou and two other editors here. [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Filioque/Archive_4] Not once was either Richard or Esoglou called to task by wikipedia admins here for edit warring. NOT ONCE.

::::::As Esoglou and Richard and the various of their like, seem to use this very same argument when referring to the Roman Catholic church as the Catholic church. But then don't allow other people to use the same rational. And administrators here help them and punish people whom oppose them. It has been said a long time ago that Western Christianity has killed God (God is dead and we the faithful are the ones that killed him, Nietzsche, this is proof of that). And that Western Christianity will fight for that right and to this day wars against the Orthodox. These things that Roman Catholic editors on here do in the name of God harm all Christians. But some are so deceived. [http://books.google.com/books?id=lHIRAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=Orthodoxy+and+the+West:+Hellenic+self-identity+in+the+modern+age&amp;dq=Orthodoxy+and+the+West:+Hellenic+self-identity+in+the+modern+age&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=0wtgtm4F4W&amp;sig=r2vm2KKuImm_ZWcsHUEMNNzF6Yw&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=OXuFUKORD5CC9gSV4oHgDA&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 17:15, 22 October 2012 (UTC)

=== Only Roman Catholic concerns are real, anybody else's are rants ===
This is the official standard set by the example here of Esoglou and Richard and enforced by Ed Johnston. As Esoglou and Richard can claim all sides to an argument and shut out any opposition and Ed enforces it and will not punish either editors if they violate (repeatedly) any edit restrictions established. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 17:38, 22 October 2012 (UTC)

It is a shame that this is true. I admire conviction, but a 'cause' is not the concern of Wikipedia editors.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 10:42, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

=== Catholic Encyclopedia ===

It might be instructive to read what the Catholic Encyclopedia has to say about &quot;Easter&quot;.  Although the following text does not raise any new substantive points that Esoglou and I have not already made, it goes to show that our arguments have a solid foundation and are not being made &quot;out of thin air&quot;.

:The English term, according to the Ven. Bede (De temporum ratione, I, v), relates to Estre, a Teutonic goddess of the rising light of day and spring, which deity, however, is otherwise unknown, even in the Edda (Simrock, Mythol., 362); Anglo-Saxon, eâster, eâstron; Old High German, ôstra, ôstrara, ôstrarûn; German, Ostern. April was called easter-monadh. The plural eâstron is used, because the feast lasts seven days. Like the French plural Pâques, it is a translation from the Latin Festa Paschalia, the entire octave of Easter. The Greek term for Easter, pascha, has nothing in common with the verb paschein, &quot;to suffer,&quot; although by the later symbolic writers it was connected with it; it is the Aramaic form of the Hebrew pesach (transitus, passover). The Greeks called Easter the pascha anastasimon;Good Friday the pascha staurosimon. The respective terms used by the Latins are Pascha resurrectionis and Pascha crucifixionis. In the Roman and Monastic Breviaries the feast bears the title Dominica Resurrectionis; in the Mozarabic Breviary, In Lætatione Diei Pasch Resurrectionis; in the Ambrosian Breviary, In Die Sancto Paschæ. The Romance languages have adopted the Hebrew-Greek term: Latin,Pascha; Italian, Pasqua; Spanish, Pascua; French, Pâques. Also some Celtic and Teutonic nations use it: Scottish, Pask; Dutch, Paschen; (The correct word in Dutch is actually Pasen) Danish, Paaske; Swedish, Pask; even in the German provinces of the Lower Rhine the people call the feast Paisken not Ostern. The word is, principally in Spain and Italy, identified with the word &quot;solemnity&quot; and extended to other feasts, e.g. Sp., Pascua florida, Palm Sunday; Pascua de Pentecostes, Pentecost; Pascua de la Natividad, Christmas; Pascua de Epifania,Epiphany. In some parts of France also First Communion is called Pâques, whatever time of the year administered. 

:[Catholic Encyclopedia entry on [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/05224d.htm Easter]]

--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 15:39, 24 October 2012 (UTC)

===Pagan influences on Christianity===

Easter is from the same Germanic root word that gives us Estrogen (sometimes written Oestrogen). I have run into a number of non-Christians who use &quot;Easter&quot; as a basis for arguing that Christianity simply acquired a lot of pagan conventions.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 10:45, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

:The pagan influence on (Western) Christianity is discussed (lightly) in the article titled [[Christianity and Paganism]].  That article could be improved significantly.  The treatment of pagan influences on Western Christianity is discussed very lightly and doesn't even mention explicitly Easter, [[Easter bunny|Easter bunnies]], or [[Christmas tree]]s.  Interestingly, Christmas trees are a more recent development than I had thought them to be and are not so obviously pagan in origin although there are pagan analogues.  Also, I had thought to include [[Easter egg]]s in the above list but according to the Wikipedia article on that topic, this is a custom that arose among early Christians in Mesopotamia.  I also always thought that Easter was the Christian equivalent to a vernal equinox (spring) festival but the Wikipedia article informs me that it is the Feast of the Annunciation that is the Christian equivalent.  We are also told by the Wikipedia article that the [[nativity of John the Baptist]] is the Christian equivalent of pagan midsummer festivals.  I note that none of this is sourced so I am relying on Wikipedia here and that is not always a sound thing to do.

:At the end of the day, however, the question is whether the feast called &quot;Easter&quot; in English is the same feast called &quot;Pascha&quot; in Latin and Greek as well as in a number of Western European languages.

:In the U.S., the Orthodox holiday called Pascha in Greek is referred to as the &quot;Orthodox Easter&quot;, a fact which will no doubt enrage LoveMonkey.  I've never heard anyone object to that equivalence before.  Could someone provide a reliable source that asserts that these are two different holidays?

:--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 15:36, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

:::Richard, by &quot;Orthodox Easter&quot; do Americans mean rather the feast celebrated on the date given by the Julian calculations, which in some years put it as much as 5 weeks later than the Gregorian calculations?  In that case, the Eastern Orthodox in Finland do not celebrate Orthodox Easter!  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:49, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

::::Very funny.  I suspect Orthodox Christians in the U.S. say &quot;Orthodox Easter&quot; because it is more comprehensible than to say &quot;Easter as calculated by the Julian calendar&quot;.  Being an ignoramus, it took me a while to understand that most Orthodox (except for the Finnish and Estonian Churches and the Old Calendarists) use the Revised Julian calendar except when computing the date of Easter in which case most Orthodox use the Julian calendar.  (I hope I got that right.  If not, I trust someone will educate me as to where I got it wrong.) --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 08:03, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

::Here is Ricky again tell me now how to feel about something. He simply can't just make a statement. My point was that there is within Orthodoxy (as I posted above) a movement to resist calling Passover, Easter. CNN and all kinds of Western media can misrepresent the Orthodox Church to their hearts content and that will not change what the link and Priest said above nor will all of Ricky's nonsense postings. Look the West covered [[Pussy Riot]] and how terrible it was for them to go to jail. But you don't see the other things they did BEFORE the final prank they pulled that got them in jail. As the Western media did not tell people in the West that these girls (as [[Voina]]) had staged an orgy in public in a museum in broad day light (see [[Fuck for the heir Puppy Bear!]]) nor went into a supermarket and stuff a chicken into their whatever ([[Voina#How_to_Snatch_a_Chicken]])....Almost absolutely no one would support them after they found out about what this group of people actually have been doing. It is easier to with hold the complete information from people to make it all black and white and make these people heroes of things they don't even believe in. It is the why to that, Western people should look into. Anyway saying that because the West misrepresents and then pointing it out does not justify engaging in that behavior. As Richard, Ricky here just loves to either show his ignorance and or play on other peoples to justify his POV pushing and covering for Esoglou. Go back and read the link I posted above. It already addressed all of Ricky's comments. For the record this kind of disinformation is common place and a regular almost daily occurrence. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:59, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

::::I didn't tell you how to feel; I guessed how you would feel and it appears that I guessed correctly.  That said, I have now read Fr. Harper's essay and he does not assert that there are two different holidays but rather that the Western celebration of Easter has been corrupted with chocolate eggs and Bunny rabbits and the like.  He further asserts that the Orthodox should eschew the use of the word &quot;Easter&quot; in favor of the word &quot;Pascha&quot;.  He is welcome to hold his own opinion and to propagate it to the faithful such as will hear his word.  However, the English word for the holy day is &quot;Easter&quot; and that is the word that should be used in this article.  I rather expect that most Orthodox would consider Easter (corrupted as it is) to be the same holy day as Pascha but, as I've said elsewhere, whether that is true or not is not relevant to this article.  

::::This issue could perhaps be introduced into the article on [[Easter]] if appropriate sources are provided.  The opinion of one Orthodox priest is not likely to be considered an adequate source.  

::::I note that there is not a separate article on [[Pascha]] as an Orthodox holiday as distinguished from [[Easter]].  There is an article about [[Passover (Christian holiday)]] which I rather doubt is what LoveMonkey is referring to.  

::::As an aside, I wonder if Fr. Harper will next propose that the Orthodox use the Greek word for Christmas instead of the English word &quot;Christmas&quot; since the Western celebration of that holy day has also been corrupted by Christmas trees and all sorts of commercial trappings that have nothing to do with celebrating the birth of Christ.  Right language is critical to right thinking and right belief.  Nonetheless, I suspect that Fr. Harper and LoveMonkey are tilting at windmills on this one but only time will tell whether the exhortations of Fr. Harper and others of a similar mind will take root and cause a change in linguistic usage.

::::--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 07:39, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::But we are supposed to care that you don't like being called Ricky. You don't &quot;feel&quot; like it. Someone queue that audible nightmare of a song from the 70's called [[Feelings (song)|Feelings]], for Richie-ard here. You don't care that you keep moving the goal posts and that frustrates editors and contributors and from my ample experience here dealing with you (and Esoglou) and have come to my attitude toward you because you are dense and WP:CAN NOT HEAR ME and do not listen to reason. At the end of the day what difference does that make to tell you since WP:YOU CAN'T HEAR ME? As for your &quot;Western word for it as it is used&quot;, argument, NOPE, doesn't work the Western word for Pascha is Pass Over not Easter. [http://www.thefreedictionary.com/Pasch] Again because Richard thinks that, all of the sudden that makes it so, never that the Orthodox source says otherwise. No it's what Richard or Esoglou say (the Orthodox are not entitle to their perspective unless it agrees with Richard and Esoglou's) and they will shot down your sources open an RFC on you and call down the admins. EVEN IF YOU ARE RIGHT. Why it's all up to Richard who is valid or invalid who is to be used and not used and Wikipedia policy is here for him to abuse in whatever way he likes. Never-mind that the section needs to be rewritten to speak the real co-relation of the moment in time of the churches development and how that feeds directly into the Eastern POV on the schism as a whole. I have to sit here and argue for, in order to have the article actually reflect historical truths as the Eastern Christians don't translate Pascha into Easter. If it gets translated into English it gets translated as Pass Over.  

::::::As the Eastern Christian don't use the word Easter. As the Eastern Christians say that [[Polycrates of Ephesus]] is an example from history in ink that shows where there was no Papal infallibility (between the churches in history) that the Pope was not treated or considered by the whole church to be of the importance that he is now in the Roman Catholic church. And that more that the filioque that the position of the Pope is and will remain unacceptable to the Eastern Christians. And will remain the main thing that keeps the churches separate. As it is obvious to anyone following this that the Roman Catholic church will not atone for any of it's changes and or mistakes. Why if the Pope was to be treated with Primacy would (as important a Saint as they could be) of all people St Irenæus step up and reprimand [[Pope Victor I]]? This is before any Ecumenical council, this is long before the existence of Constantine. Why is the point (which is referred to by [[Eusebius]]) not being reflected in the article correctly. As Polycrates' letter has been used as proof against the argument that the Churches in Asia Minor accepted the authority of the bishops at Rome. Why is this missing as to play the games of Richard and Esoglou people are to believe that the Role of Pope in the Church of Rome play no part of in the East-West schism. This is the proper way that the Quartodecimanism controversy should be included in the article. Not the hake job incoherent nightmare that the section contains right now. But I have to point this out to editors like Richard and Esoglou who come here hacking and arguing when they are very much ignorant of the subject that they are editing on at least from this perspective I have pointed out. Why are they allowed to do this knd of thing?  [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:13, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

===Movement to NOT use Wikipedia as a forum for advocacy===

LoveMonkey wrote &quot;there is within Orthodoxy (as I posted above) a movement to resist calling Passover, Easter &quot;.  It would be useful to refer to [[WP:NOT]] here.  Wikipedia is not the place to advocate new trends even if those trends are justified.  Wikipedia should use terms as they are understood in common parlance.  Furthermore, this is the English Wikipedia.  As unfortunate as the etymology may be, the name of the holy day in English is unquestionably &quot;Easter&quot;.  It is time to leave it at that.  If it is desired to remove the word &quot;Pascha&quot; from the text, I would have no objection to that.  English readers are more likely to be confused by mention of &quot;Pascha&quot; than they would be if they simply read &quot;Easter&quot; with no further qualifications.  --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 00:36, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

:I was [[WP:BOLD|bold]] and removed the reference to Pascha for the reasons explained in my above comment and in the edit summary.  This is the English Wikipedia; policy is to use the English term unless the foreign language term is more widely known.  &quot;Pascha&quot; is not more widely known than &quot;Easter&quot;; hence, we should use &quot;Easter&quot;.  My apologies.  I had not read the all the Talk Page comments carefully enough and I had not read the link to the essay by Fr. Michael Harper.  As LoveMonkey has explained, this is a &quot;movement&quot; and Fr. Harper has expounded the rationale behind it.  The fact that it is a &quot;movement&quot; suggests that it is not widely adopted as of yet by the Orthodox and certainly not by English-speakers, Catholic, Protestant or non-Christian.  Thus,  I don't agree with Fr. harper and I do not concede that the proper English translation of &quot;Pascha&quot; is &quot;Pascha&quot;; rather I continue to maintain that the proper English translation of &quot;Pascha&quot; when referring to the Orthodox celebration is &quot;Easter&quot;.  However, as I've said above, this equivalence is not helpful to the flow of the text in this article and so the best approach is to agree not to draw any distinction or equivalence at this particular point in the article.  --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 03:37, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
::Your removal of the phrase is fine with me.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 09:30, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
:::If the POV is part of a division between the two parties named in the article, then it is essentially part of the subject of this article. Rather any of us like it or not. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 15:36, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
::::If you believe that the distinction between &quot;Easter&quot; and &quot;Pascha&quot; is a significant contribution to the continuing schism, I think you need a better source than Father Harper who doesn't even say that it is (although he sort of implies &lt;s&gt;it&lt;/s&gt; that it might make some contribution).  I haven't heard of this issue being raised as one of the points to be resolved by the Joint Theological Commission (whatever its official name is).  Nor have I heard of it being mentioned by the likes of Bishop Kallistos (Ware) or Romanides or Lossky or Yannaras.  If you could provide a quote from any of those or a Metropolitan or someone with substantial stature in the Orthodox community, I would be much more receptive to including it in the article.  FWIW, there are plenty of Western Christians that consider Christmas and Easter to have pagan roots.  A small minority even refuse to celebrate either holiday because of their pagan roots.  The vast majority of Western Christians are unlikely to know or care about this issue.  Whether that's important or not is a matter of opinion that rests on relative priority. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 17:44, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::I think WP:YOU DON'T HEAR ME. I think that the most neutral and NPOV term one could use is Pascha. And not Easter which is not used in the East. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 14:00, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

== A note on personal names ==

I'm not quite sure what LoveMonkey intends by using the name &quot;Ricky&quot; to refer to me.  It does seem that he uses it mostly when he is attacking me and, in particular, belittling me so I am inclined to surmise that the use of the diminutive is part of an oblique personal attack on me.  This technique seems rather petty but, so far, I've just let it slide as there isn't enough time and energy in a day to react to all the crap that he sends my way.  

However, on the off chance that his use of the name is not intended to be offensive, I will point out that it is at least odd if not downright rude to use a variant of someone's name when there has been no indication that the variant is normally used by the person and his acquaintances to refer to himself.  FWIW, I have gone by &quot;Richard&quot; or &quot;Rich&quot; most of my life and have generally discouraged other variants.  My aunt used to call me &quot;Ricky&quot; when I was a child.  I used to call my son &quot;Ricky&quot; when he was a child but now that he is a teenager, he discourages it.  For now, he prefers &quot;Richie&quot;.  Some adults go by &quot;Ricky&quot; (e.g. [[Ricky Martin]]); that is their prerogative.  I do not.

--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 08:13, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

:Richard, Ricky, Richie here has just deleted large chunks of the article is here marginalization people's opinions as &quot;rants&quot; and now can't be called &quot;Ricky&quot;. Well there's priority for you. An entire section on the talkpage dedicated to calling him Richie or Ricky. But lets not let the article or the content of articles here on wikipedia and the quality of those article get addressed lets waste time about calling Richard, Ricky or Richie.. I have so many better things to do. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 15:41, 26 October 2012 (UTC)




::Yuh... you are welcome to keep calling me &quot;Ricky&quot; if you like.  There's no policy against doing so.  I just wanted to let you know that I don't much care for it.  Now that you have indicated that you are doing so intentionally, at least I now know that for sure and can take offense or not as I choose.  I just didn't want to let it fester as a hidden cause of irritation if you had no intention of offending.  Since you now know it bothers me and you choose to continue, we now understand each other and any ill-will that this behavior engenders is intentional and not unwitting or accidental, so let's let this discussion rest. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 17:38, 26 October 2012 (UTC)
::::: And you are welcome to leave my contributions alone and stop hacking up my contributions. 17:54, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

== Contentious editing ==

How is the edits that Richard made to my contributions to this article today constructive? 
*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=519977710&amp;oldid=519974699] can Richard please leave my contributions alone? If there are issues with them please post them first here to the talkpage. Is Richards comments that they he made in his edits clearly shows that he can not hear me nor can he understand and therefore until he does I would like to have an administrator here make modification to my contributions because again. Richard on purpose seeks to minimize as much as he can, what the Roman Catholic church here has done and on what magnitude they have done it. And if Ed Johnston will allow to remove and silence, censure it completely. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 17:43, 26 October 2012 (UTC)

::In a word, &quot;No&quot;.  The text in question was written in such atrocious English that it was an embarrassment to leave them in the article in their current state.  If you feel that your text is appropriate to Wikipedia's standards of English prose, then I think we need to take this to the next step in [[WP:DR|dispute resolution]] which, I believe, is a content RFC.  That's not intended as a threat.  RFC's are not weapons, they are tools to widen the group of editors looking at an issue.  A user RFC asks for comments on a user's conduct and admittedly is often used as a weapon.  A content RFC requests comments on article text and is also often used as a weapon but I am not trying to use it as one here.  I'm not even objecting to the content (yet).  It's just that the text in question doesn't even constitute properly formed English sentences (i.e. with a main subject and a main verb).  The verbiage is so garbled that I hesitate to copyedit it as I am not certain of the meaning that you wish to convey.  I can guess at about 80% of your intended meaning but I think it is better for you to rewrite the text than for me to attempt it.  I said as much in my edit summary and in the commented out text which I left in the article text to facilitate your revision of it. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 08:34, 28 October 2012 (UTC)

For reference:

I commented out the following text:

:As the incidents more that being a matter of custom or dogma or theological matters are said to reflect that the Churches in Asia Minor did not accept the authority of the bishops of Rome. As in the initial part of the conflict c.190AD - 196AD between the disciple of St [[John the Apostle]], St [[Polycarp]] along with St [[Irenaeus]] and Bishop [[Polycrates of Ephesus]] reprimanded [[Pope Victor I]] for overstepping his authority and mishandling the matter in general.

and left the following comment with the commented out text:

:Commenting out text which lacks the syntactic structure for properly formed sentences in English.  In its current form, the text is almost at the point of being incoherent.  The intended meaning is not quite clear enough to allow copyediting and thus I leave it to the original author of this text to rewrite this text. Additionally, I note that the following text makes claims that are not supported by the quote from Eusebius and thus would need additional support in order to be included.  I'm not saying the claims are false, simply that the claims are not supported by the quoted text.

I will note that, aside from the atrocious writing, there are also problems with sourcing and a &quot;citation needed&quot; tag will probably be forthcoming to request a secondary source for these assertions.
--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 08:41, 28 October 2012 (UTC)

:Beh... my comments above were perhaps a bit intemperate and for that I apologize with my only excuse being that it was 1:40am local time and I was trying to bang out a response to a comment that I had not seen before and only just saw as I was planning to turn in for the night.  The grammar in the text in question is not quite as bad as I portrayed it and one can sort of pick out the intended meaning.  The larger truth is that I am planning a rewrite of this section and I didn't see the value in working on improving text that was likely to be replaced by new text in the near future.  I beg everyone's patience while I continue researching the topics of monepiscopacy and the monarchical bishop. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 15:33, 28 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::Is this your excuse for edit warring and removing, remarking out my good faith contributions? The original edits I am speaking you did not do at the time you responded with.. You did not even attempt to discuss what you did. You just went and rather than even try and reword (which I suspect is because you are again ignorant of this content) you just remove it from the article? THATS EDIT WARRING. The fact that you are having to research this topic while you attack me and remove my contributions I would hope people would see as an admission of ignorance on your part. Why are you doing these things when you just admitted that you are not informed? Why Richard now acting like an administrator when his contributions should hold not more weight than anyone else's and that they have to ad her to Wikipolicy more so that to anything else. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:15, 29 October 2012 (UTC)



:::I am having trouble parsing the sentence &quot;The original edits I am speaking you did not do at the time you responded with.&quot; Which &quot;original edits&quot; are you talking about?


:::I confess that after I wrote the comment that I characterized as &quot;intemperate&quot;, I went to bed thinking &quot;you know, I think those sentences DID have a main subject and a main verb&quot; and I started to realize that I had criticized your writing with a problem that I had remembered from other sentences that you had written in the past.  When you are writing quickly without adequate thought to good writing style, you have a bad habit of writing as if you are speaking to someone and that results in some pretty atrocious writing.  I considered whether to get out of bed and correct my error but, given that it was already 2am local time, I decided not to do so.  My error in identifying the specific problem with your writing in the sentences that I commented out doesn't change the fact that the writing was so deficient as to fail the (admittedly low) standards of Wikipedia.  They certainly stuck out like a sore thumb in this article which has at least an average quality of writing througout.  That's why I commented them out.  Are you really wanting to defend the quality of writing in those sentences?

:::Yes, my rationales for editing/removing your contributions range from &quot;deficient English inadequate for Wikipedia standards&quot; to &quot;doesn't fit in this point in the article&quot; to &quot;doesn't fit in this article at all&quot;.  If I can improve your text, I do so.  If I do not think it belongs in a particular section, I move it.  If it doesn't fit in the article, I delete it.  If it does fit but the English is so weak that I can't figure out how to fix it, I comment it out and make it clear what I have done and why.

:::I am not &quot;trying to act like an admin&quot;.  Your edits are not sacrosanct and neither are mine.  The &quot;edit page&quot; used to say something along the lines of &quot;You are not willing to have your contributions edited mercilessly, don't contribute.&quot;  AFAIK, that dictum still stands. 

:::My contributions do not &quot;hold more weight&quot; than yours.  I just believe that a consensus of editors would support my view.  If you believe I have acted inappropriately, you are welcome to appeal to any of the more than 1000 admins of the English Wikipedia.  More properly, you should follow the [[WP:DR|dispute resolution process]] which includes [[WP:3O|third opinions]],[[WP:RFC|Requests for Comment]] and [[WP:MEDCOM|mediation]].  

:::Or, you could just look at what I'm trying to tell you and realize that I am trying to improve the article.  The article has improved dramatically since the days when there were three sentences that were woefully inadequate to describe the early history of the schism.

::::There was no single event that marked the breakdown. In the centuries immediately before the schism became definitive, a few short schisms between Constantinople and Rome were followed by reconciliations. Even during the period of Early Christianity, part of the East (Western Anatolia) was in disagreement with Pope Victor I over Quartodecimanism, holding that Easter (called Pascha in both Greek[8][9] and Latin)[10] should be celebrated at the full moon, like the Jewish Passover, not on the following Sunday.[11][12] See Easter controversy for details.

:::Though it is bold for me to say so, most of the &quot;heavy lifting&quot; in this transformation has been done by me.  I wrote the well-sourced section titled &quot;Origins and causes&quot;, the intro to the &quot;History&quot; section and the subsection titled &quot;Early Catholicism&quot;.  Yes, I have had to do quite a bit of research to do that but that's what Wikipedia editing is about.  The fact that this critical portion of the article lay in such sad shape for so many months suggests that no one else cared enough to do the research and writing to improve it.  Why are you whining about me doing that work?

::::The massive improvement from a one line discussion of the Quartodeciman controversy to a more-or-less well-written section has been accomplished by yourself, myself and Esoglou.  This kind of collaborative editing is exactly how Wikipedia should work with the exception of all the whining, complaining and harsh invective that you seem to specialize in.  If you could eschew that and engage in egoless editing, the process would be far more pleasant and enjoyable.  

::::Wikipedia should [[WP:NOT|not]] be a battleground.  You are long overdue for a [[WP:WQA|Wikiquette alert]].  Just reading through your continuous whining is tiresome.  Get a clue already.  You are a valuable contributor to Wikipedia and we have jointly accomplished a lot to be proud of in the last 5 years of working together.  Why can't you find a way to make this an enjoyable experience instead of an unpleasant one?

--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 16:57, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
&lt;br&gt;
Your edit warring is tiresome and POV pushing costs more time and work that what is and or should be considered acceptable. Look at the amount of conversation I have contributed to the talkpage of this article. It is amazing how you can delete my contributions without conversation on the talkpage argue to remove key historical events from the article that you don't understand and allow Esoglou to distort ancient historians and then claim I need a wiki alert. Who has time for this? [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:49, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

== Actual experience of God ==

I think a citation is needed for the unsourced claim that it is the Orthodox perception that Catholic theologians lack the actual experience of God enjoyed by Eastern Orthodox theologians (such as John Romanides?).  The citation is needed especially, though not solely, because what is claimed is that this is &quot;the&quot; Orthodox perception, not just &quot;an&quot; Orthodox perception.  If the text is not amended, a &quot;citation needed&quot; tag should be added to the paragraph.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:45, 28 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Please stay away from Orthodox subject matter that is your editing restrictions. This is just another of your attempts to side step your restrictions and push your POV. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:16, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
:Would you ever be so good as to provide sourcing for this supercilious claim?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:33, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
::::Go back to the [[Eastern Orthodox – Roman Catholic theological differences]] article and look it up there. You forgetting is your problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Franks, Romans, Feudalism, and Doctrine/''Empirical theology versus speculative theology'', Father John S. Romanides [http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.03.en.franks_romans_feudalism_and_doctrine.02.htm] A basic characteristic of the Frankish scholastic method, misled by Augustinian Platonism and Thomistic Aristotelianism, had been its naive confidence in the objective existence of things rationally speculated about. By following Augustine, the Franks substituted the patristic concern for spiritual observation, (which they had found firmly established in Gaul when they first conquered the area) with a fascination for metaphysics. They did not suspect that such speculations had foundations neither in created nor in spiritual reality. ''No one would today accept as true what is not empirically observable'', or at least verifiable by inference, from an attested effect. So it is with patristic theology. Dialectical speculation about God and the Incarnation as such are rejected. Only those things which can be tested by the experience of the grace of God in the heart are to be accepted. &quot;Be not carried about by divers and strange teachings. For it is good that the heart be confirmed by grace,&quot; a passage from Hebrews 13.9, quoted by the Fathers to this effect.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;The vision of the uncreated light, which offers knowledge of God to man, is sensory and supra-sensory. The bodily eyes are reshaped so they see the uncreated light, &quot;this mysterious light, inaccessible, immaterial, uncreated, deifying, eternal&quot;, this &quot;radiance of the Divine Nature, this glory of the divinity, this beauty of the heavenly kingdom&quot; (3,1,22;CWS p.80). Palamas asks: &quot;Do you see that light is inaccessible to senses which are not transformed by the Spirit?&quot; (2,3,22). St. Maximus, whose teaching is cited by St, Gregory, says that the Apostles saw the uncreated Light &quot;by a transformation of the activity of their senses, produced in them by the Spirit&quot; (2.3.22). Orthodox Psychotherapy Section The Knowledge of God according to St. Gregory Palamas by Metropolitan Hierotheos Vlachos published by Birth of Theotokos Monastery,Greece (January 1, 2005) ISBN 978-960-7070-27-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;As I have indicated, [[Barlaam of Seminara|Barlaam]] insisted that knowledge of God depends not on vision of God but on one's understanding. He said that we can acquire knowledge of God through [[philosophy]], and therefore he considered the prophets and apostles who saw the [[Tabor light|uncreated light]], to be below the philosophers. He called the uncreated light sensory, created, and &quot;inferior to our understanding&quot;. However, St. Gregory Palamas, a bearer of the Tradition and a man of revelation, supported the opposite view. In his theology he presented the teaching of the Church that uncreated light, that is, the [[theoria|vision of God]], is not simply a symbolic vision, nor sensory and created, nor inferior to understanding, but it is deification. Through deification man is deemed worthy of seeing God. And this deification is not an abstract state, but a union of man with God. That is to say, the man who beholds the uncreated light sees it because he is united with God. He sees it with his inner eyes, and also with his bodily eyes, which, however, have been altered by God's action. Consequently theoria is [[theosis|union with God]]. And this union is knowledge of God. At this time one is granted knowledge of God, which is above human knowledge and above the senses.[http://www.pelagia.org/htm/b02.en.orthodox_psychotherapy.06.htm#2k]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The ancient Christian exegets of both East and West whom we identify as Fathers of the Church approached the matter from a more holistic point of view. Their writings were shaped by a particular hermeneutical perspective which they characterized by the name ''theoria''. The expression refers to an 'inspired vision' of divine Truth as revealed in the person of Jesus Christ and in the biblical witness to him. That inspired vision - which itself is an essential part of Holy Tradition - enabled the Fathers to perceive depths of meaning in the biblical writings that escape a purely scientific or empirical approach to interpretation&quot; ([http://books.google.ie/books?id=6r7lQ6np94YC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=breck+bible+interpretation&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=s4rJTJCkDs2eOpDmpLcB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=inspired%20vision&amp;f=false John Breck, ''Scripture in Tradition: The Bible and Its Interpretation in the Orthodox Church'' (St Vladimir's Seminary Press 2001), p. 11).]&lt;/ref&gt;[[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 14:29, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::Also since Esoglou is completely ignorant of it all maybe he should read up on Saint [[Niketas Stethatos]]. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 15:23, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
::Well, it seems that there is no claim by Romanides to have direct experience of God.  Nor is there any such claim by Eastern Orthodox theologians such as Vasily Bolotov, Kallistos Ware, Paul Evodokimov, John Zizioulas, Liveriy Voronov, Vladimir Lossky ...  Shall we agree on that?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:07, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::No, leave the Orthodox sections of the article alone you have made it quite clear that no amount of evidence or valid sourcing will ever be enough to support a position that you oppose. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:43, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Esoglou is ignorant and extremely disrespectful and shows that by how he engages the Eastern Orthodox. Why again should I have to point this out since Esoglou is supposed to know this (what is Orthopraxis about theoria). However I think it is safe that people reading this may not understand what Esoglou is doing here (and has been doing on Wikipedia for a long long time). As Esoglou engaging in these types of arguments and when pointed out with facts or sources that he is wrong.[http://books.google.com/books?id=vkAJtFpXDP0C&amp;pg=PA95&amp;dq=Symeon+Matthew+Kapstein&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3guQUNWdDYbm9ATi5YHYCg&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Symeon%20Matthew%20Kapstein&amp;f=false] [http://www.monachos.net/content/patristics/studies-fathers/67] [http://orthodoxinfo.com/inquirers/hierotheos_difference.aspx] Rather that stopping and letting the other person continue to contribute Esoglou or Lima just goes right on to the next thing he can find to edit war about and continues edit warring. It is a (biblical) tradition when speaking of the vision of God (example St Paul) to speak of the experience as if speaking in 3rd person. It is also as a general rule something you keep to yourself and don't share because having theoria does not bestow a person with privilege or authority per se it is to heal the person as therapeutic first. Anyone wanting a more clear understanding of how someone becomes a [[Starets]] (illuminated persons with theoria, that instructs others) they can read about it in people like St [[Seraphim of Sarov]]. Or how to achieve [[Schema_monk#Great_Schema|Skema]]. 

:::It is safe to assume that [[John Romanides]] for example was called a theologian in Greece by Greeks and that he is a &quot;true&quot; theologian.&lt;ref&gt;In Patristic tradition, theologians are the God-seers. Saint Gregory Palamas calls Barlaam [who attempted to bring Western scholastic theology into the Orthodox Church] a &quot;theologian,&quot; but he clearly emphasises that intellectual theology differs greatly from the experience of the vision of God. According to Saint Gregory Palamas theologians are the God-seers; those who have followed the &quot;method&quot; of the Church and have attained to perfect faith, to the illumination of the nous and to divinisation (theosis). Theology is the fruit of man's cure and the path which leads to cure and the acquisition of the knowledge of God.&lt;/ref&gt;[http://orthodoxinfo.com/inquirers/hierotheos_difference.aspx] It is safe to say that John Romanides met that criteria by having theoria (which is to be a true theologian as also V Lossky did) and not because he got his theology degree from Harvard. As the Monks on Athos do not honor a University degree over and or see it as equivalent to theoria. There is no College degree in Hesychasm and if such a thing were made it would be against the very nature of what [[gnosiology]] is. Esoglou claims to know these things and yet he continues to act in ways that are inappropriate to the traditions he is attacking. He is OK with the Roman Catholic church vilify and or attacking, distorting what is proper or Orthopraxis and respectful in conduct and or behavior in the East as he does not respect or care to learn and understand those traditions as his display here shows today. One does not speak of as Holy a thing as the vision of God as provoked by auto-suggestion or that it is a side show novelty unless of course you are Esoglou. Eoglou appears to want to deny ascetics their asceticism. And this all here is safe to say. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 17:22, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

::::::::::&quot;The Lord considered the chief good to reside in theoria alone ... the other virtues, although we consider them necessary and useful and good, are to accounted secondary because they are all practiced for the purpose of obtaining this one thing: theoria.&quot; St. John Cassian,
::::::For those people reading whom want to know what it is to be cured of the nightmare and emptiness caused by Western Christian theology and want to understand what this is about you should read this book [http://www.amazon.com/Absence-Unknowability-God-Heidegger-Areopagite/dp/0567045323/ref=sr_1_10?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1351618844&amp;sr=1-10]. Anyone whom has read up to page 110 and that page specifically knows that, I have used [[Christos Yannaras]] through out my time trying to contribute to various Orthodox articles here on Wikipedia. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 17:38, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
::Metropolitan [[Hierotheos (Vlachos)]]
**)Theoria is the vision of the glory of God. Theoria is identified with the vision of the uncreated Light, the uncreated energy of God, with the union of man with God, with man's theosis (see note below). Thus, theoria, vision and theosis are closely connected. Theoria has various degrees. There is illumination, vision of God, and constant vision (for hours, days, weeks, even months). Noetic prayer is the first stage of theoria. Theoretical man is one who is at this stage. In Patristic theology, the theoretical man is characterised as the shepherd of the sheep. [http://orthodoxinfo.com/inquirers/hierotheos_difference.aspx]
**)Theosis-Divinisation is the participation in the Uncreated '''grace''' of God. Theosis is identified and connected with the theoria (vision) of the Uncreated Light (see note above). It is called theosis in grace because it is attained through the energy, of the divine grace. It is a co-operation of God with man, since God is He Who operates and man is he who co-operates. [http://orthodoxinfo.com/inquirers/hierotheos_difference.aspx] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 18:22, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
:::That's a lot of words, but it is hard to see what relation they may have to the question.   Do you or do you not believe that the Orthodox theologians John Romanides, Vasily Bolotov, Kallistos Ware, Paul Evodokimov, and John Zizioulas (all are described as Orthodox theologians) have or have had actual experience of God?  I am not attacking them.  Are you?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 18:54, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::WP:YOU CAN'T HEAR ME and this is the same thing you always do, you act like this and don't hear what is being said. If St Paul would not directly speak to the fact that he had theoria 1 Corinthians 2:9 then this tradition is what it is. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 12:57, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::I'm trying to hear you but you don't speak distinctly except when expressing your outright conviction that western theologians (and, it seems, Latin Fathers of the Church) have ''not'' had actual experience of God.  You are not saying clearly whether it is likewise your opinion that eastern Orthodox theologians ''have'' had actual experience of God.  Does your mention of Saint Paul mean that you think they have, like him ({{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|2:9-10|ESV}}, had revealed to them &quot;what no eye has seen&quot;, instead of the ''theoria'' that is described as something actually ''seen''? [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 15:42, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
::Now, read this verse. 2 Corinthians 12:2 Both are Paul. How is that? [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 15:57, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
::Was it not so that Paul was not a disciple of Christ, until after Christ was crucified and resurrected? And gone to heaven? If so Paul never was part of the Christian movement until Christ was already gone from this earth. Is Paul in this not like all whom have come after him in that Paul was not part of Christ's ministry before Christ was crucified and resurrected? Paul is not Jesus nor is Paul the founder of Christianity. Paul is simply a Christian and a most beautiful modeled Christian and human being.
::He is a brother to everyone. Is theoria not what made Saul into Paul? Why then does he not say what his disciple the Areopagite later say about being &quot;out of body&quot; or not and taken to the 3rd heaven as something to gain power over people (hint: 2 Corinthians 12:7)? Your supposed to know all about this. As even St Paul to us is not the same St Paul to you. As he makes no such use of faith in the way the Roman Catholic church has taken him and made it backwards to what Paul actual is and did. He has theoria as a God seerer as what is available to the Orthodox now. Thats anyone whom is in good standing and engaging in the ascetic practices of the Orthodox church. That's what made St Symeon the New Theologian and not a Western Theologian. Again that's anyone monk, clergy layperson, not just an elite. ANYONE. That's not what the Roman Catholics teach and this is why nihilism did not prevail against the Orthodox (see for example [[Father Arseny]]). As it is proper or Orthodox to remain anonymous and not seek earthly power. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:29, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
:::More words, but no reply.  Do you think that John Romanides and the others mentioned have been caught up to the third heaven like Paul?  Is it your opinion that they have had actual experience of God?  You still refuse to answer.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:06, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
::I have answered you refuse to listen. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:08, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
:::With a yes, a no, or a maybe?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:16, 31 October 2012 (UTC)

== Historical ecclesiology ==

I have spent way over the amount of time that I should have allocated this weekend to editing [[East-West schism]] and yet there is much more to do in order to put the Quartodeciman controversy into proper context.  I am going to stop for today so that I can attend to other real-world obligations.


The fly in LoveMonkey's ointment is that it's unclear that Victor was a monarchical bishop.  In fact, some scholars are even suggesting that his excommunication of the Asian churches was actually a move to assert his position as a monepiscopal bishop (i.e. that the real political context was that he was enforcing his power of the Asian Christians residing in Rome).  Monepiscopacy is the concept that there is only one bishop in a diocese and that bishop oversees all the churches within the diocese.


This is why I have spent time building up the historical ecclesiology of the Ignatian tri-partite structure, monepiscopacy and (ultimately) the monarchical bishop.  My goal is to document the emergence of monepiscopacy and the monarchical bishop and point to monepiscopacy as defining the ecclesial structure of the Catholic and Orthodox churches.  I am still exploring the meaning of the &quot;monarchical bishop&quot;.  My uninformed understanding is that this term describes not just the Bishop of Rome but also the power of a Catholic bishop within his diocese.  What I am unclear on is whether Orthodox bishops are &quot;monarchical bishops&quot; within their diocese.  I rather expect that they are.  But, if this is true, we cannot cast the Orthodox rejection of &quot;papal primacy&quot; as a rejection of the concept of the &quot;monarchical bishop&quot; but rather a rejection of the concept of a monarch bishop that rules above other bishops who are monarchs within their diocese.



I would appreciate any feedback to further educate me on these topics.



--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 18:32, 28 October 2012 (UTC)
:&quot;Monarchical bishop&quot; is a term used for the kind of bishop that is clearly pictured in the letters of Ignatius of Antioch, about a century before the time of Victor.  It is argued that, until some time later, Christian churches in other areas were governed not by monarchical bishops but by colleges of equally ranked presbyters/bishops, the two terms being equivalent at the time.  By Victor's time, the monarchical bishop was, it seems, standard not only in the geographical area in which Ignatius was active but generally, including Rome.  In about 180, Irenaeus takes it for granted that there was a succession of (monarchical) &quot;bishops&quot; or &quot;''presiding'' presbyters&quot; in Rome from the time of Peter and he lists them (as &quot;bishops&quot;) in [http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0103303.htm ''Adversus Haereses'', III, 3, 3.]  (I think, without having checked, that the only area that is seriously argued to have lacked monarchical bishops at that time was Alexandria.)  Since then monarchical bishops have been standard in all the churches, Catholic, Eastern Orthodox, Oriental Orthodox, Church of the East, and even more modern groups such as Anglicanism. Of course, that does not mean that the monarchical bishops were not and are not organized into provinces headed by a metropolitan, patriarchates headed by a patriarch, etc.
:The main source for Victor having excommunicated the Quartodecimans is Eusebius.  He clearly pictures Victor as a monarchical bishop and even quotes Irenaeus (in a letter of his, not in ''Adversus Haereses'') as listing Victor's immediate predecessors in the same office, who had taken a more relaxed attitude than Victor towards that minority of Christians who celebrated Easter on full-moon day instead of Sunday.
:So I see no point whatever in bringing the question of the monarchical episcopate into this article.  The monarchical episcopate is common to East and West, not a matter of dispute. And if you cut Victor out, you cut out the whole of the story of the action by him that Irenaeus, according to Eusebius, considered too drastic.
:Does any reliable source say that Victor's action was an antecedent of the East-West schism.  Is the idea that it was an antecedent merely an unsourced synthesis by Wikipedia editors?  If we are to keep it, I think we do need a reliable source that describes it as such.  Even in the second century, the East as a whole condemned the Quartodecimans, without going so far as to excommunicate them.  Eusebius mentions councils held in Palestine, Pontus and Osrhoene and the view expressed by the bishop of Corinth and &quot;a great many others&quot;.  &quot;A unanimous decision&quot;, Eusebius says.  And in the fourth century the Council of Nicaea, the vast majority of whose participants were from the East, definitively excluded the Quartodeciman practice.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:48, 28 October 2012 (UTC)
::You have done something towards justifying the mention of the Victor-Polycrates dispute, but not, I think, towards justifying the (in my opinion confusing and quite extraneous) bringing in of the question of the origin of the monarchical episcopate.  The stress now put on the pretensions of the bishops of Rome ''as part of the prehistory'' will necessitate a compensatory outline of the part played in prehistory by the pretensions of the &quot;ecumenical&quot; patriarchs, a mention of which is at least equally justified.  I must get around to this sometime later.  The historical problem was the clash between these two, wasn't it?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 09:06, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::Wrong. Read Cleenewerck's book it is another example of how this entire schism was started. There is no history of the Patriarch of Rome being a ruler that's what the Emperor was for. Look at what Cleenewerck says about the so called [[Petrine doctrine]] let alone the [[Patrimonium Sancti Petri]]. As if there is anything like the history of [[Pope Julius II]] and the [[Papal States]] like [[Pope Gregory XI]] leading a war like the [[War of the Eight Saints]] or the [[Avignon Papacy]] in the East. There is no history in the East of any Patriarch ever becoming so powerful as to head their own country and have wars over that country and or to as a leader actually war on other countries. To suggest otherwise is simply insane. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:51, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
:::I do believe that the schism was between the See of Rome and &quot;Constantinople&quot; in the sense of the Ecumenical Patriarch rather than between the See of Rome and &quot;Constantinople&quot; in the sense of the Byzantine Emperor.
:::There remains the problem of the absence of a logical connection between the schism and the question of the origin of the monarchical episcopate, which Richard wants included.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:07, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

== NPOV tag ==

LoveMonkey has placed an NPOV tag at the top of the article page.  Putting an NPOV tag on an entire article page is not very helpful as it gives little indication of what the NPOV dispute is about.  If the dispute is about a specific section of the article, then placing a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{POV-section}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag on the relevant section would be much more helpful.  

The following text is taken directly from [[Wikipedia:NPOV dispute]]

&lt;b&gt;[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:NPOVD#How_to_initiate_an_NPOV_debate How to initiate an NPOV debate]&lt;/b&gt;

:If you come across an article whose content does not seem to be consistent with Wikipedia's [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view|NPOV]] policy, use one of the tags below to mark the article's main page. Then, on the article's talk page, make a new section entitled &quot;NPOV dispute [- followed by a section's name if you're challenging just a particular section of the article and not the article as a whole]&quot;. Then, under this new section, clearly and exactly ''explain'' which part of the article does not seem to have a NPOV and why. Make some suggestions as to how one can improve the article. Be active and bold in improving the article.

&lt;b&gt;[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:NPOVD#Adding_a_tag_to_a_page Adding a tag to a page]&lt;/b&gt;

:Please note: This label is meant to indicate that a discussion is still going on, and that the article's content is disputed, and volatile. If you add this template to an article in which there is no relevant discussion underway, you need at least to leave a note on the article's talk page describing what you consider unacceptable about the article. The note should address the troubling passages, elements, or phrases specifically enough to encourage constructive discussion that leads to resolution. In the absence of an ongoing discussion on the article's talk page, any editor may remove this tag at any time.? 
--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 20:29, 28 October 2012 (UTC)

::::I want Richard to explain this piece of original research typical of Esoglou's POV pushing added into the article.
::::::The [[Quartodecimanism|Quartodeciman controversy]] arose because the Christians in the [[Roman province of Asia]] ([[Early centers of Christianity#Western Anatolia|Western Anatolia]]) disagreed, [[Eusebius]] says, with &quot;the churches in the rest of the world&quot;,&lt;ref name=Eusebius23&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf201.iii.x.xxiv.html Eusebius, ''Church History'', chapter 23]&lt;/ref&gt; [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=520280065]
::::::When what Eusebius actually says is &quot;&quot;But it was not the custom of the churches in the rest of the world to end it at this time, as they observed the practice which, from apostolic tradition, has prevailed to the present time, of terminating the fast on no other day than on that of the resurrection of our Saviour.&quot; How is that not original research and POV pushing? [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 18:13, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::::It would be helpful to know what do you think is meant by &quot;It was not the custom of the churches in the rest of the world to end it (i.e. the fast) at this time (i.e. at &quot;the fourteenth day of the moon, on which day the Jews were commanded to sacrifice the lamb, ... whatever day of the week it should happen to be&quot;), as they observed the practice which, from apostolic tradition has prevailed to the present time, of terminating the fast on no other day than on that of the resurrection of our Saviour (Sunday)&quot;.  In what way is that distorted by the expression in the article: &quot;Christians in the Roman province of Asia (Western Anatolia) celebrated Easter at the spring full moon, like the Jewish Passover, while the churches in the rest of the world observed the practice of celebrating it on the following Sunday (&quot;the day of the resurrection of our Saviour&quot;)?  If you would explain what distortion you think you see in it, we could work out a better rendition of it.  Please explain, so that we can dialogue.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:06, 29 October 2012 (UTC)

::Here is Esoglou just today trying to clean up his POV original research posting mess from the article. Because he knows it is unacceptable [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=520446691], what could the both of you be thinking by doing edits like this one to the article? That Eusebius was saying that Polycarp and the Apostle John were out touch with the rest of the world and should then let the world dictate what they establish as tradition which directly contradicts what Eusebius is quoted as saying in the article (i.e. &quot; Victor that he should not cut off whole churches of God which observed the tradition of an ancient custom&quot;). Is this supposed to be in good faith? How is this kind of behavior supposed to be perceived? [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 18:23, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Perhaps this means you no longer insist that what the article says is false to what Eusebius wrote about the difference between the practice in the Roman province of Asia and that in the rest of the world.  If so, thanks.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:07, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
::Or perhaps as usual you are wrong. As your &quot;out of context&quot; quote from Eusebius misrepresented him and it is obvious you have no issue with doing such a thing. As you where exaggerating part of his sentence to make him look like he was taking an extreme position that he never has. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:36, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

If LoveMonkey's NPOV concern is solely related to the sentence above, then the appropriate action would have been to add the &lt;nowiki&gt;{{POV-section}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; to the relevant section rather than applying a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{NPOV}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag to the whole article.  

The current article text reads: &quot;The Quartodeciman controversy arose because Christians in the Roman province of Asia (Western Anatolia) celebrated Easter at the spring full moon, like the Jewish Passover, while the churches in the rest of the world observed the practice of celebrating it on the following Sunday (&quot;the day of the resurrection of our Saviour&quot;)&quot;

Does this resolve the NPOV issue?  If so, the NPOV tag should be removed from the top of the page.  If not, please list any outstanding NPOV issues that should be addressed.

--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 16:52, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
*)The creation of the Latin Empire and why it is important and why Roman Catholic POV edit warring editors like Richard and Esoglou wish to either remove it's mention and or diminish it as much as Wikipedia will allow them.
::*)The existence of the [[Latin Patriarch]]s and the [[Latin Empire]] ([[Frankokratia]]) show that the Roman Catholic church collectively benefited from and exploited the [[Fourth Crusade]] and [[Siege of Constantinople (1204)|Sacking of Constantinople]]. This directly contradicts the idea put forward by the Roman Catholic church that the entire evil committed against the Eastern Orthodox Christians by the Roman Catholic crusaders was not the Roman Catholic churches fault and or that the Roman Catholic church did not condom it. It shows very clearly how the Roman Catholic church specifically exploited the events to impose on the Eastern Orthodox the power of Pope and the West and it's practices and doctrine. As it also shows that the Roman Catholic church did not try and REVERSE what had been done but rather exploited it. '''As after the [[Siege of Constantinople (1204)|Sacking of Constantinople]] the crusaders did not just leave, the Roman Catholic clergy actually moved in and took over. ''' Thats pretty damn important to give people a perspective and understanding of the extent of what actually happened. 
::*)The imposing of Latin Empire onto the Eastern Orthodox shows that there was a long long long history of Western Roman Catholics warring against the Eastern Orthodox. As people here like to point to things like the [[Massacre of the Latins]] but miss that [[William II of Sicily]] in 1185 sacked Thessalonica as retaliation for that (see [[Eustathius of Thessalonica]] which is a little hard to get the EO side of history in general considering the Roman Catholic crusaders destroyed the [[library of Constantinople]]). This for people whom might have missed it means that the Roman Catholic church warred on exploited and killed Eastern Orthodox Christians long before any Crusade and that the goal of the Roman Catholic church (as such) was finally obtained (at least from an Eastern Orthodox perspective) by the establishment of the Latin Empire and it's Latin Patriarchs. Example of Western '''double-cross'''. The West double crossed the East when it tried to with force, make the Eastern Orthodox recite the filioque, and or put the filioque in the Eastern Orthodox's recitation of the Nicene Creed (in Greek mind you not Latin) in the East, not simply accept that the West said it, but to make the Greeks say it as well. [[Pope Nicholas III]] indeed tried that very thing after promising that they would not do that exact thing (after the East agreed to reconciliation). And after the Eastern Orthodox accepted the Roman Catholic using the filioque modification in the Creed as recited in the West.. [http://books.google.com/books?id=auT8VbgOe48C&amp;pg=PA137&amp;lpg=PA137&amp;dq=sang+the+creed+with+the+filioque+in+greek&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=oQ7nvBnBBX&amp;sig=i727rDkHUzOr_LnoUdWQ0IkrJlo&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=gGnRTsPyGIXu2gWf0dn0DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=sang%20the%20creed%20with%20the%20filioque%20in%20greek&amp;f=true] 
::*)How is it that the Pope was sorry for and said that the Fourth Crusade was a bad thing and yet setup a Latin Speaking Patriarch in [[Hagia Sophia]] after converting the church to a Roman Catholic church (if East and West are Christian what conversion was really needed). How is it that the Popes and the West was so against what had happened to the Eastern Orthodox by way of the Fourth Crusade, that after the Fourth Crusade rather than leave and try and clean up they instead CONQUERED? And CONQUERED MORE causing a set of wars (The Eastern Orthodox rebelling and removing them from their lands). There is allot of fabricating documents by the Roman Catholic church (the [[donation of Constantine]] for example) and killing and warring and double crossing that simple is missing from the article. Right now the article tries to sell the Roman Catholic non-sense that the Roman Catholic church really are misunderstood, never did nothing wrong and the Eastern Orthodox are just but hurt about a bunch of things that happened so long in the past (like [[Catholic clergy involvement with the Ustaše]]) that the Eastern Orthodox are just being big babies. There is no attempt at the higher ups in the Roman Catholic church to tell their parishioners the truth about this and that it has been going on and continues to go on to this very day.  Christians confess their sins and atone for them. They don't cover them up and lie about it. They don't tell other Christian groups that they have murdered (for a non Orthodox one see [[St. Bartholomew's Day massacre]]) and slandered in the past that they have no justification for being traumatized for what happened in the past nor do they have a right to their grievances. When the establishment of the Latin Empire further drained the Eastern Empire of men and resources so desperately needed to fight off the on coming Muslims. Of course this is without mentioning that the Westerners like [[Orban]] actually helped the Muslims successfully win against the Eastern Orthodox in the [[Fall of Constantinople|fall of Constantinople]]. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 17:30, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
::*)If Richard wants to resolve the NPOV tag then he should at least make a nominal attempt at reading the Eastern Orthodox side of it and as I have repeatedly suggested that would be covered in this book [http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0615183611/ref=oh_details_o01_s00_i00]. If Richard does not have time or resources then he should not be editwarring and or making demands of other editors here on the article talkpage. As it is not a matter of the Roman Catholic side but the repeated distortions of the Eastern Orthodox side that have caused the tag to get posted. Richard just can't leave the article alone and is pretty much right now WP:OWN. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 17:30, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
------------------------------------------------
:::From anyone else it would be strange to read this complaint that others don't accept at face value the complainant's superabundant presentation of ''an'' Eastern Orthodox view (whether it can be called ''the'' Eastern Orthodox view is debatable) and of often unsourced views of ''some'' Eastern Orthodox about Roman Catholic teaching or practice, as when he inserts an independent section under the heading &quot;Orthodox rebuttal (not exactly a neutral term) of (unspecified) Catholic arguments&quot;.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:00, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
::I have provided sources and names [http://books.google.com/books?id=vkAJtFpXDP0C&amp;pg=PA88&amp;lpg=PA88&amp;dq=vlachos+uncreated+light&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=VEFM1TsqhT&amp;sig=hDM2HkjRquwsR6Gd0qHj9kPYr_k&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NIyRUODxA4aQ8wTEu4DAAw&amp;ved=0CEgQ6AEwCDgK#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false], [http://www.johnsanidopoulos.com/2010/04/saint-nektary-of-optina-and-uncreated.html]
*[[Christos Yannaras]] [http://www.amazon.com/Meaning-Reality-Existence-Communion-History/dp/1936773031/ref=sr_1_2?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1351714929&amp;sr=1-2&amp;keywords=Christos+Yannaras], [http://www.amazon.com/Orthodoxy-West-Hellenic-Self-Identity-Modern/dp/188565281X/ref=sr_1_9?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1351714929&amp;sr=1-9&amp;keywords=Christos+Yannaras], [http://www.amazon.com/Absence-Unknowability-God-Heidegger-Areopagite/dp/0567045323/ref=sr_1_11?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1351714929&amp;sr=1-11&amp;keywords=Christos+Yannaras] 
*[[John Romanides]] [http://www.romanity.org/htm/rom.03.en.franks_romans_feudalism_and_doctrine.03.htm], [http://preachersinstitute.com/2010/10/21/the-works-of-fr-john-romanides/], 
*[[Vladimir Lossky]] [http://www.amazon.com/The-Vision-God-Vladimir-Lossky/dp/0913836192], [http://thebananarepublican.blogspot.com/2009/10/vladimir-lossky-on-patristic.html]
*[[Dumitru Stăniloae]], [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gsDk0M-AE1k], [http://www.academia.edu/1121332/_The_Orthodox_Rejection_of_Doctrinal_Development_], [http://reflectionsforthesoul.com/2012/08/24/meeting-the-divine-light-21/], [http://books.google.com/books/about/Orthodox_Dogmatic_Theology.html?id=-sU80t3ncpgC], 
*[[Hierotheos (Vlachos)]], [http://orthodoxinfo.com/inquirers/hierotheos_difference.aspx], [http://www.stnectarios.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=7&amp;Itemid=8], [http://www.biblio.com/books/477243417.html], [http://books.google.com/books?id=Vy8MAQAACAAJ&amp;dq=inauthor:%22Hierotheos+Vlachos%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=do2RULuEEIPi8gSasYDwDQ&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwBA], [http://books.google.com/books?id=M06PXwAACAAJ&amp;dq=inauthor:%22Hierotheos+Vlachos%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=do2RULuEEIPi8gSasYDwDQ&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwBg], [http://www.stgeorgegreenville.org/OurFaith/Foundation%20of%20Faith/Orthodox%20Life%20Text.pdf] 
*St [[Symeon the New Theologian]], [http://maxwellinstitute.byu.edu/publications/papers/?paperID=7&amp;chapterID=61], [http://www.amazon.com/In-Light-Christ-Theologian-Life-Spirituality-Doctrine/dp/0913836915], []
*St [[Gregory Palamas]], -
*[[Michael Pomazansky]] [http://www.holytrinitymission.org/books/english/dogmatics_pomazansky.htm]
*[[Laurent Cleenewerck]][http://orthocath.wordpress.com/page/2/], 
*St [[Sophrony (Sakharov)]], [http://orthodoxwayoflife.blogspot.com/2010/05/deification-uncreated-light.html]
*[[George C. Papademetriou]], [http://www.goarch.org/ourfaith/ourfaith9284] &lt;br&gt;
*[[George Metallinos]],[http://preachersinstitute.com/2010/10/21/the-works-of-fr-john-romanides/], [http://www.orthodoxytoday.org/articles-2009/Mettalinos-Paradise-And-Hell-According-To-Orthodox-Tradition.php]
This is just a rough start off of the top of my head and I have been consistent about Esoglou. These are people he has never read nor understood because if he did would not say some of the ignorant things like he just did. Esoglou has made it abundantly clear that he will never accept what is presented to him and that he was and is and will remain ignorant. All the while telling people what he knows all about this when he does not know at all. At some point with this kind of disregard to the information and sources and the fact that Esoglou can find no Orthodox to counter what is being said than Esoglou is going to have to be restricted. Each of these theologians and Church representatives teach that the Papacy is wrong each that the primacy is of vision not of men or positions of worldly power. The truth does not come from a Bishop. I could the Laurent Cleenewerck book to source the above all by its lonesome. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:34, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
:[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=520607115&amp;oldid=520606670 &quot;Orthodox ''rebuttal'' of Catholic arguments&quot;] [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 21:18, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
::Esoglou has no idea what Political Hesychasm is...[http://www.amazon.com/Revival-Political-Hesychasm-Contemporary-Orthodox/dp/073914720X].Completely clueless. So what does Esoglou do? He posts a link of where I copied text from the [[Primacy of the Bishop of Rome]] article about the Orthodox's opinion of Roman Catholic arguments. Clueless about the text as it is text I copied and pasted and actually did not write. Esoglou can't hear. Esoglou doesn't understand and that is why Esoglou is allowed to get away with his restriction violations, but no one else is. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 23:10, 31 October 2012 (UTC)
:::This in LM's view completely clueless, ignorant of political hesychasm editor at least did not add here a sourceless new section claiming to &quot;rebut&quot; unspecified arguments.  But enough of this.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 09:11, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
::I section he did not write but copied and pasted from another article. Pay attention Esoglou. Nothing is stopping you from providing a source. Ask Montalban to provide one. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:17, 1 November 2012 (UTC)

== Policy abuse and edit warring ==

Why did neither Richard nor Esoglou properly source and or represent through their editing here what the Quartodeciman was actually about (hint it was not about the specifics of the theology it was about Papal authority). Notice like I said. Esoglou made the section so unreadable and so unclear that the next step was for Esoglou, Richard and then with the blessing of Ed Johnston remove the very vital part of the history of this event and article. Notice also the editors Richard and Esoglou are still putting in distortion of sources and also Richard removed my good faith contributions TWICE. No word from Ed Johnston no threats on their talkpages. Look at the amount of work someone has to do in order to add maybe a paragraph to this article and notice how these two editors are not done and try again savage and distort and marginalize my contributions. Note that they have become so embolden and brazen in their hubris that they don't acknowledge that they have no idea what the issue was really about nor did they bring any real clarification to the article about what the role of Quartodeciman controversy played in the bigger picture of the schism. Here they are on the talkpage causing more non-sense and acting like they are not being destructive and running off Eastern Orthodox editors with this type of behavior. And where are the administrators? Well if I make a mistake I am more that positive all kinds of admins I have never engaged nor seen or hear of will be here to condemn my contributions. And yet with this much editing and wrangling and warring and removing my contributions of good faith that are sourced nothing. This sucks and is far to time consuming for me. This is not the way the process is supposed to be followed and adhered to. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 15:56, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
== There is no history of Augustine's theology being considered theology in the Eastern churches ==

There is no history of Augustine as a theologian and his theology taught as dogmatic Christian theology in the Eastern Churches.
His theology is not taught as Orthodox, general run of the mill Christian theology. Augustine did not attend any Ecumenical councils nor did his mentor. He was not a Greek scholar or even someone whom read, spoke and or could read or write in Greek. His position as being one equal too the Church Father of the Ecumenical councils is not accepted or taught and his theology is not considered Orthodox Christian theology nor is it taught as Orthodox Christian theology that reflects the teachings of the Ecumenical church councils. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 17:26, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
== Attempts by POV pushing editors to force people to commit plagiarism ==

I posted a summary of the section of the book starting on page 147 and ending on 148 of which Richard posted this citation complaint [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=520446691&amp;oldid=520441106] which by doing so engaged in edit warring by policy abuse. This is inflammatory behavior. The book supports the summary of what the intro to that section of the book says. Richard's edit is in vio and is edit warring. As dare anyone to read the link and then read my summary of it and say that the summary I posted is not reflective of source. If the words are correct that is what the talkpage is for. Richard did not post any such objection here on the talkpage. Richard did not try and even read that section of the book nor try and re-word my good faith contribution here on the talkpage into an acceptable passage. Instead he posted a citation request implying that I had lied about what I had posted in that it did not reflect the source I provided. Setting a standard that nothing short of plagiarism would suffice (which Richard has even used to then silence contributions that he did not like in the past that way too).  [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 18:36, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
:While I am not ready to concede that your text accurately represents what Cleenewerck wrote, I will say that my use of the &lt;nowiki&gt;{{failed verification}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag was meant to highlight that support for the article text could not be found on the page given in the citation (i.e. page 157).  I did look backward and forward a few pages but I did not find support for the assertion in the article text.  You are now asserting that the article text is &quot;a summary of the section of the book starting on page 147 and ending on 148&quot;.  Your article text is not an accurate summary of what is Cleenewerck says on pages 147 and 148.  It would seem to me that the text that is most relevant to the argument that you want to make can be found at the bottom of pages 151 and 153.  However, even then, that text does not support the assertion in the the article text that you wrote.  Cleenewerck has written a fairly NPOV treatment of these two incidents (the Epistle of Clement and the Quartodeciman controversy).  His presentation of how Eastern Orthodox view these two incidents is not the same as what you wrote in the article text.  There may be other sources that support what you wrote but Cleenewerck is not one of them. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 20:42, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
Nonsense your edit warring. You purposed that the mention of the Quartodeciman controversy be removed from the article.
:Why?
*(1 Because you are not informed about the subject of the article.
*(2 Because you have never read the Eastern Orthodox side of the schism
*(3 Because you listen to another ignorant person whom has a degree in nothing about both sides of this issue
*(4 Because your pride drives you and you should have stopped edit warring awhile back but you can't.
*(5 Because your side is wrong has done evil things about this and you can't live with that. But you think you can find a way to stop people from find out what the Eastern Orthodox side is.
*(6 All of the above.
Look at all the time and work I had to do to the article to even mildly reflect why the controversy was important. Look all the time I explain just this one thing and all the time it took and then how there was no consensus and WP:YOU CAN'T HEAR ME. 
Look how after all of that you and Esoglou still tried very very hard to distort what happened and what was said by allowing Esoglou to fabricate a position for Eusebius [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=520280065] engaging in a type of Original Research that would get this person in the academic world punished. As Eusebius out of context is not Eusebius. But you are unethical and you look the other way. Time and time again. Since when did Eusebius say that the Eastern Churches were not following their own ancient traditions? [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 13:21, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

POV rules here.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 00:05, 1 November 2012 (UTC)

== Lets make a list ==

I request that Esoglou and Richard post here a list of what books on this subject that they have read. What Eastern Orthodox theological works that they have read (completely). I am going to put this request on Ed Johnston's talkpage as well. I will also list which ever ones I have not already contributed to the article. I think this fair and this is something that needs to be done as Esoglou Richard appear to not be informed on the subject and are editing warring and deleting my contributions and distorting them and putting off important perspectives being put in the article because they don't understand the subject but instead want to fight about it.
*1)[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AEast%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=351581612&amp;oldid=351580655]
[[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 13:54, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

== Refactoring of text ==

Now richard just deleted the entire section I created outright. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=520465666&amp;oldid=520464195] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 18:45, 29 October 2012 (UTC)

:My edit summary read &quot;Refactoring to make for a better flow of ideas&quot;.  Refactoring means moving text around without changing the actual text.  For example, I just refactored your comment above into a new section.  In the case of the edit to which you are objecting, I kept most of the text intact and simply moved it around to fit better into the flow of the article.  When you create an article, a section or even just a block of text in Wikipedia, it is not &lt;i&gt;your&lt;/i&gt; article, section or text.  You have released your contribution under the CC-BY-SA 3.0 License and the GFDL.  Other editors are free to add to, modify or even delete your text.  Your only recourse is the [[WP:DR|Wikipedia dispute resolution process]].  Of course, the first step is to discuss the issue with other editors on the Talk Page.

:So.. let's discuss.  Are you asserting that the article suffers from the refactoring that I did?  If so, why?  My contention is that the article does not benefit from a bunch of short one-paragraph sections.  If nothing else, it makes the TOC too long but, more importantly, it makes the article harder to read because it is harder for the reader to maintain context across sections.  I am not arguing that the current section organization after my refactoring is perfect and final.  As new text is added, the outline structure (as created by section headings) has to change to accomodate the new text.

:--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 20:27, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
:::Since when? Since you are the arbitrator of such? Your the boss of Wikipedia? Have you looked to see why people have stopped contributing to Wikipedia? [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Editor_Retention] Who has the time to educate you? And no one here cares about how you also think you are a copyeditor and how you are trying to use that as cover to delete peoples (that includes Montalban for example) contributions. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 13:38, 30 October 2012 (UTC)
::LoveMonkey - there is a Catholic POV team here. I'm sure that there's a genuine belief that it will gain reward for them in heaven.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 00:03, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
:Halo Montalban, good to see you. I was just going over the concept of cultural identity and that concept as political common ground between good and bad movements like the [[slavophil]] and [[hesychast]] or the [[Ustashe]] or the [[Ton Ton Macoute]]. I must agree with Dostoevsky, this is not between fellow Christians this is a war for the partisans, and the partisans alone. 
:I am no partisan but there is no excuse for this stuff or the catholic encyclopedia's content. As this is not a matter of Christian it's a matter of power and history. Things in the news make allot more sense if people understand most sides, right now it's just easier to act like nothings wrong and get shocked when people actually are angry with you. It's when someone asks &quot;why?&quot; that people might begin to understand one another. MAYBE. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 03:46, 1 November 2012 (UTC)

Speaking of POV - the editorialising here by two Catholics; it's one of the reasons I'm a very confirmed ex-Catholic. That the church needs people to stifle real information demonstrates to the world the veracity of that church's arguments. I'm sure the people doing the POV actually feel that they're doing their church a service. They are not. They are presenting argument as useful as the Donation of Constantine.

I was on an several debate sites recently trying to find out more information about a source catholic apologists refer to; e.g. Catholic blogger PhilVaz refers to this person as &quot;Anglican historian Edward Giles&quot;. But, I can find no information on him. Giles' book &quot;Documents illustrating Papal Authority&quot;

He's not on Wiki. I e-mailed PhilVaz, he couldn't provide info. I went onto a Catholic debate site, they couldn't. I went onto an Orthodox site, and the Catholics there couldn't either. Yet they cite him as an authority.

Also, by the way, the Catholics on both sites also demanded that I set out why I was asking about this person - as if merely raising a query about a Catholic source was suspect.

And yet they continue to use him as a source! Catholic writer, S. Ray calls him a scholar - a person no one knows who he is!!! They simply go on repeating this 'evidence' unchallenged.

Here the endless editorialising by two Catholic contributors is something I use as a tool for demonstrating the lack of depth of Catholic apologetics.

By the way, I'm writing a book on the subject of papal supremacy. At present I have over 82,000 words.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 09:43, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
:::Most excellent. I hope that you follow sobornost (brotherly love) and Dostoevsky and see that fellow Christians in general are not the bad guys at all (regardless of their affiliation). I'd say people in general aren't. It's the leaders whom distort to obtain power that are the problem in that they have corrupted theosis. Even Esoglou and Richard are not seen as evil or bad or wrong only of a way of thought a form of indoctrination if you will. They are our Christian Brothers and this is a family affair. And the only counter to this is to confront them with a different perspective (kicking and screaming all the way) in order for them to be able to come to the truth of it. All heresy is gnosticism in the sense of, [[a priori]] gnosis (Ego driven), schism however is a distortion of dogma and holding to the distortion as truth over a posteriori evidence (i.e. tradition). As the schism is about making the church an earthly power and a political and or government power rather than a place (hospital if you will)  that allows people to escape the world and seek after God. For the seeking after God (to seek the truth of existence) is the real heaven as it is the process theosis that leads from glory to glory. To be Orthodox is to have inner peace (apatheia) and hate no one, of course there are clowns everywhere and Orthodoxy is no exception. Inner peace (apathea) is the final stage of theosis. I am not here out of any malice I am here because it should that the Orthodox side actually have a voice in this since according to Wikipedia articles should be free from one POV and should as much as possible reflect all sides of a given issue. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:41, 1 November 2012 (UTC)

== Esoglou's request for quotation ==

Esoglou put a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{quotation needed}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag on text that I wrote.  So now it is my turn to defend text that attempts to paraphrase what a source (Roger Haight) wrote without plagiarizing his work.  The article text that I wrote attempts to summarize the paragraph that starts at the bottom of page 83 and continues at the top of page 84.  Haight writes &quot;The churches were becoming ever more distant from their origins in space and time. They were growing and with growth came new or false teachings, the sources of controversy and division.&quot;.  Did I stray to far from Haight's meaning?  I confess that I inserted my own understanding of what he wrote but I do not think that I actually added to his meaning but rather I thought I was expanding on what he said so as to avoid using his specific words.  I will add the above quote to the citation but I'd like some feedback as to whether the article text accurately captures Haight's meaning. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 21:10, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
:Oh... I just re-read the text that I wrote and realized that it could be read to mean that &quot;The passage of time also moved (all) Christians farther from the original teachings of the apostles giving rise to teachings that were considered heterodox and sowing controversy and divisiveness within churches and between churches.&quot;  I inserted the word &quot;some&quot; before Christians to make clear that the problem is that &quot;some Christians&quot; were following teachings that were considered heterodox.  Does that address the issue? --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 21:16, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
::Thanks.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 21:20, 29 October 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;History&quot; as catch-all ==

Richard, your broadening the article to questions whose connection to the schism I see as tenuous, such as the origin of the monarchic episcopacy and what you have called &quot;Early Catholicism&quot;, has led, perhaps not unforeseeably, to inclusion also under the same heading of subsections on &quot;''Orthodox'' understanding of Catholicity&quot; and &quot;''Orthodox'' rebuttal of Catholic arguments&quot;.  The italicized words mean that I leave it to people such as you to deal with the inclusion of these as pre-Schism &quot;history&quot;.  I wish you patience.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:45, 30 October 2012 (UTC)

== Esoglou's recent edit ==

I had to revert Esoglou's edit because an error in the citations was breaking the page.  I did not get a chance to read it closely and won't be able to do so right away due to real-world obligations.  However, I am concerned that it is a long edit and I am not convinced that we need so much text on this topic.  In general, this article is already very long and getting longer.  For example, the section on the Quartodeciman Controversy is longish and I have been refraining from making it longer because I think the article is rapidly getting unreadable (if it's not already at that point now).

Once Esoglou fixes the problem that his edit was causing, I'll take another look at the text and evaluate whether we really need that much detail in this article.  I urge everybody else to do the same.

--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 18:41, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
:Sorry for the mistake.  I posted it rather too hurriedly before going away for a short while.  As for length, the solution is to remove the repetitions scattered in disorganized fashion elsewhere.  The growth of the power of the see of Constantinople to primacy over all others in the east and to at least equality with Rome is a topic that deserves, even requires, specific treatment.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 19:51, 1 November 2012 (UTC)
== Issue with lede ==
The introduction doesn't make it clear that the 1st crusade was just 40 years after the schism and also against the Eastern Orthodox. As a matter of fact the lede is a big fat distortion and is very misleading because it does not show that the hostility between East and West was there (throughout the Middle East) before the 1st crusade. It implies that only some people were privy to the schism when in reality the schism was VERY MUCH a hot topic in the Middle East as the Eastern Empire was now fighting the Muhammadian AND the Gothic conquered Western Empire at the same time. And that the schism played a role IN ALL THE CRUSADES. There is no mention of the killing and taking possession of the Holy Sepulchre in the article as the history of the 1st crusade. As it actually occurred instead, it reads real unclear about the 1st crusaders whom TOOK Eastern Orthodox Holy sites and relics FROM Eastern Orthodox taking Orthodox Holy relics (not just from Constantinople) back to Europe. And killing Eastern Orthodox in the 1st crusade. The lede reads like everything was kinda fine until the Massacre of the Latins and the sack of Constantinople. 
------------------
The validity of the Western legates' act is doubtful, since Pope Leo had died, while Cerularius's excommunication applied only to the legates personally.[2] Still, the Church split along doctrinal, theological, linguistic, political, and geographical lines, and the fundamental breach has never been healed, with each side accusing the other of having fallen into heresy and of having initiated the division. The Crusades, the Massacre of the Latins in 1182, the capture and sack of Constantinople in 1204, and the imposition of the Latin Patriarch of Jerusalem and the Latin Patriarchs made reconciliation more difficult.[2] This included the taking of many precious religious artifacts and the destruction of the Library of Constantinople.
------------------
It TOTALLY MISREPRESENTS the role of the schism in all of the Crusades and reads as if the Eastern Orthodox were not victims of any of the crusades but the 4th one. As it is from an Eastern perspective that the Roman Catholics initiated the Crusades against the Orthodox, not just against the Muslims and in later history this was a common ground shared with many Muslims and Eastern Christians (see Patriarch [[John Scholasticus]]). This article could do better to inform people reading it that the crusades were against other Christians not just Muslims. And it would well to anyone interested in history to understand that the schism was also tied to the entire crusade enterprise and that the Muslims were the conquerers to start with and that with the Eastern Roman Empire falling to them that there was some affinity (in the beginning) between East and West. It was not until the schism that the Crusades (all of them in one way shape or fashion) took on a rather European outlook toward the Middle East in general Eastern Christian and Muslim alike. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:52, 2 November 2012 (UTC)

:In fact, I heard a History Channel suggestion (not using them as a RS normally) that the Pope, seeing how fragmented the West was and how they were consuming their resources fighting '''each other''' proposed the 1st Crusade in order to help unify the West. Contrasting with the East which was more or less unified under the Muslims. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 19:51, 7 November 2012 (UTC)



::@Student7, I am confused about what you wrote.  In what sense was the East &quot;more or less unified under the Muslims&quot; at the time of the First Crusade? I presume you meant the &quot;Eastern Orthodox Church&quot; but I can't make sense of your sentence.  --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 20:19, 7 November 2012 (UTC)

&quot;The East at the time of the 1st Crusade&quot; was not unified under the Moslems. &quot;The East&quot; was divided between that which was under Islam and that which fought to avoid that situation.

Certainly the crusades might be seen as unifying the west.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 22:21, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
:Yes. I was (the tv article appeared to be) implying that the Muslims were unified. As everyone knows from looking a map of Western Europe during the same time frame, there were perhaps a hundred duchies, counties, and supposed &quot;kingdoms&quot;, etc. all wasting a great deal of resources fighting each other. I am not that familiar with the structure of the surviving Eastern Roman Empire supporting Eastern Orthodoxy. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 22:45, 10 November 2012 (UTC)

== Confused Catholic apologetics ==

It's rather bemusing the confused Catholic stance towards this, especially the fourth crusade which really drove the nail in the coffin.

Catholics try to make excuses for this, and try to minimalise the pope's involvement in it. And yet the previous pope (John Paul II) apologised for the crusade. Either Catholics believe their pope, or they don't. If they do, then they need to stop making excuses for something he at least came to grips with.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 01:24, 3 November 2012 (UTC)
:::Ah it is really hard to be forgiven for something you don't own up to (as a matter of fact God does not forgive by default one has to ask and one has to atone). It appears that allot of things are just not addressed. How is it that the Eastern Christians don't call their leaders Popes? Well there is no, &quot;how is it&quot;, as one only need to look at what happened this week in Egypt.[http://www.pravoslavie.ru/english/57191.htm] &quot;How is it&quot; that only the Fourth Crusade is really the only one shown here as hostile to the Eastern Orthodox when in reality (and more so than the blank mention of the Northern Crusades) that the Eastern Christians from even before the 1st Crusade were called '''heretics''' it's in the history books.&lt;br&gt; 
:::I have wondered for a long time how this very essential thing is overlooked by Western Christians and their leaders. How are people to reconcile when so much is being denied? So much history and recent history too. Like I keep bringing up things like the [[Crimean War]] no one wants to acknowledge the role that war played in starting World War I. Go ask people how much they know about why there was a World War I. That they know that a Serb assassinated the Austrian-Hungarian King because now that Serbia had finally gotten it's freedom from the Turks all of the sudden the Holy Roman Empire was going to take them over and force them to become part of Europe when all the Slavs wanted was to be their own people and have their own country and not be forced to be part of yet another Empire. People just don't want to talk about it because it puts Europe in a bad light. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 14:26, 5 November 2012 (UTC)
::It's a well-known fact that the first crusaders all swore to follow the Eastern Roman Emperor. Instead as soon as they took lands they made little &quot;Latin&quot; enclaves throughout.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 00:47, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

:::: '''LoveMonkey''' I often see a general dislike from the west towards the east. At the end of WWI the allies had taken Constantinople. It was finally 'free' after 500 years. What did the allies do? Hand it back to the Turks. They then stood by and let the Turks kill off eastern Christians -the Armenians epecially, and Greeks (such as in Smyrna).

They even consider now admitting Turkey into the EU despite Turkey's oppressions in Cyprus.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 00:51, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

:[[List of Greek Orthodox Patriarchs of Alexandria]].  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 18:46, 5 November 2012 (UTC)


I don't know what Esoglou's contribution to this means. I accept that there is a single list of Greek Orthodox Patriarchs in Alexandria. What it's got to do with the pope asking for forgiveness I don't know. Perhaps he is simply wishing to advertise more examples of confused Catholic apologetics???
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 00:47, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

== Unity through division??? ==

The Catholic church recognises at least 3 different primates of the church in Antioch.

They are in effect sponsoring schism.

[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 10:44, 3 November 2012 (UTC)

== What's the issue here with Pope Victor? ==

What's the issue here with Pope Victor?
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 08:24, 4 November 2012 (UTC)

:Hmmmm.... perhaps I am conflating Clement with Victor.  Cleenewerck questions whether Clement was even a &quot;bishop&quot;.  There are some sources who doubt that monepiscopacy had been adopted in Rome by the end of the 1st century.

:I was under the impression that they did not call the Bishop of Rome &quot;Pope&quot; during the ante-Nicene era.  However, I just dug up this source that says:

::&quot;Pope, the title of, formerly given to all bishops. The emperor, in 606, confined it to the bishops of Rome; Hygenus was the first bishop of Rome that took the title, 154; the pope's supremacy over the christian church established by Boniface III, 607.&quot;[http://books.google.com/books?id=xHAwAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA216&amp;dq=first+Pope&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=oQOXUOzYJcX2qQGmkoGYCg&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwATge#v=onepage&amp;q=first%20Pope&amp;f=false &quot;Mnemonika: or, The The tablet of memory&quot;  By William Darby, Edward J. Coale]
:So... since Hygenus predates Victor, I suppose it is reasonable to say &quot;Pope Victor&quot; even though his powers are radically different from the doctrine of the papacy that developed subsequently,  I'll change it back.

:--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 00:21, 5 November 2012 (UTC)

I think you are confusing some issues. Clement is said to have written the Epistle on behalf of all the church of Rome, but he may not have been pope at the time - according to a number of commentators. This does not mean that he did not later become bishop/pope. I agree that there are some sources who might argue that there was no single bishop of Rome at that time.

Furthermore it is irrelevant whether they call him pope at the time. Words are often taken back to mean something before that word was first used. E.g. I can pick up a book on Australian history and it deals with &quot;Australia&quot; before it was called &quot;Australia&quot;. It is simply a common practice.

I still don't know what your issue is.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 00:42, 6 November 2012 (UTC)


Montalban wrote: &quot;I still don't know what your issue is.&quot;  That's OK.  I don't think Esoglou thinks much of my making an issue of this point either.  Probably it's just something I made up in my brain.  Cleenewerck makes it clear that he doesn't think Clement wrote the epistle at all and that it eventually got attributed to Clement because he was so revered in the early Christian community.  He also doesn't seem to like calling Victor &quot;Pope&quot; but he may not be representative of common practice.  Until someone else more knowledgeable wants to demonstrate that it is inappropriate to say &quot;Pope Victor&quot;, I will go with the flow and stop being concerned about this point. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 05:16, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
:::Pope is not exclusive to Rome.[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/mar/18/pope-shenouda-the-third] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:29, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
::::This made me smile at the remembrance of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:East–West_Schism&amp;diff=521596063&amp;oldid=521595374 this edit] related to [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:East%E2%80%93West_Schism&amp;diff=521513576&amp;oldid=521510099 this question:] &quot;How is it that the Eastern Christians don't call their leaders Popes?&quot;  Excuse my amusement :-)  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:39, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

Esoglou, I have no idea what your post has to do with anything. I suspect you know something and it's just so obvious to you you think everyone else should see it too.

Pseudo-Richard, I accept that some don't think Clement wrote the Epistle of Clement. Abee Guetee (spelling?) cast doubts on this earlier than the source you refer to. 
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 23:09, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

Esoglou still seems to be writing here for his own amusement. Perhaps a blog page would suit better. I'm not sure what his point is or who he's addressing
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 07:41, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
:Not sure how the comment that &quot;Pope&quot; not exclusive to Rome relates to the East-West Schism. &quot;Pope&quot; just means &quot;father.&quot; This is driven home by Spanish and other Latins calling out &quot;Papa&quot; in audiences with the Pope. So it is &quot;just&quot; a title. Meaningful to believers, like most titles. Orthodox call their priests &quot;Father&quot;, as well. As do Latin Catholics. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 20:00, 9 November 2012 (UTC)

::And yet we Orthodox do not call out priests &quot;Pope&quot;. But anyway, Richard's objection (from what I understand of it) is we can't call someone a pope before that term was first used for that office. I have pointed out that it is a regular thing to back-date terms. As an objection, it seems rather pointless.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 05:02, 10 November 2012 (UTC)
:::I support Student7's view on the lack of any clear relation to the East-West Schism of the remark that the title &quot;Pope&quot; is not exclusive to Rome, which is on the same level as the same editor's earlier remark that the Eastern Christians don't call their leaders Popes.  Richard has long since withdrawn any objection he had to the use of &quot;Pope&quot; for the earliest of those to whom that title is commonly applied, an objection that, whether well or ill founded, was clearly related to the text of this article on the East-West Schism.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:44, 10 November 2012 (UTC)

== Formal reunification ==

I have edited the article. I believe it had said that a formal reunification had been achieved at the Council of Lyons and/or at Florence.

I have not seen any evidence to show that this is so. Certainly the delegates at those conventions may have signed, but as anyone knows something is not formal until it is ratified.

So unless people have evidence that the churches were ''properly'' reunited I think the edit I made should stand
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 22:22, 4 November 2012 (UTC)
:I think most people understand &quot;formal&quot; in the dictionary sense and contrast what is merely formal with what is substantial, but some may indeed understand the word as Montalban does.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:44, 5 November 2012 (UTC)

Of course it helps to reduce this to my opinion only - it helps Esoglou to pretend that he has the majority on side, but we're not merely talking about a general (dictionary) definition, but specifically relating to a type of treaty. And of course if it were just me, and my opinion I'm sure Esoglou can provide any evidence that a formal union was actually achieved
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 00:36, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
::Exactly Montalban. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:33, 6 November 2012 (UTC)


I take it Esoglou has no evidence???? The &quot;everyone knows&quot; argument doesn't work (it's called ''vox populi'' and is a logical fallacy)
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 07:44, 7 November 2012 (UTC)

==Statute of Limitations on time to complain?==
A paragraph reads &quot;Towards the end of the 2nd century, Victor, the Bishop of Rome, attempted to resolve the Quartodeciman controversy by excommunicating churches in the Roman province of Asia. This incident is cited by some Orthodox Christians as the first example of overreaching by the Bishop of Rome and resistance of such by Eastern churches. Laurent Cleenewerck suggests that this could be argued to be the first fissure between the Eastern and Western churches.(footnote)&quot;

But the point here is, did anyone complain about meddling '''then'''? Complaining '''now''' seems a tad tardy IMO. 

I think there are other instances of Roman meddling prior to Constantine establishing a second Patriarchy in the &quot;New Rome.&quot; Not sure they are all here. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 22:32, 7 November 2012 (UTC)

The problem is understanding &quot;cutting off&quot;

For the Catholic church you have to be in communion with the Pope to be Catholic therefore if the pope cut you off your cut-off from the entire Catholic Church.

However this assumes that this was the position at the time of Pope Victor.

It may have been that way, but not necessarily.

Cutting off, by Victor may have been where like where Australia cuts off relations with the US, but both are still in the United Nations. The act of cutting off relations does not equate to expulsion from the 'universal' body.

There are instances where others were 'cut off' from each other – e.g. Meletius of Antioch was not in communion with Rome and Alexandria but was still chosen to head an ecumenical council.

As to complaining, well Irenaeus and other bishops complained AT THAT TIME. It says so in Eusebius, that Victor's actions were not to the liking of the bishops.

[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 00:47, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
:I do not wish to go properly into a discussion of this matter and will make only two remarks:
:#Victor's action was not the only case of one Christian bishop cutting off communion with another.  A possible difference lies in Eusebius's description of Victor's action as attempting to cut certain churches off &quot;from the common unity&quot;.  This perhaps does not have to be interpreted as a claim to universal jurisdiction, however much both proponents ''and'' opponents of papal primacy (such as certain editors here) would like to see it that way.  Could it be seen as a reference to the fact that the practice in the province of Asia was different from that in, as Eusebius said, &quot;the rest of the world&quot;?  Irenaeus complained about breaking unity with an important minority over the question, not about any supposed &quot;meddling&quot; in affairs of no concern to bishops like Victor.  
:#The Letter of Clement to the church in Corinth, also mentioned in the article, was not seen by anyone as &quot;meddling&quot;, least of all by the church in Corinth, which used to read the letter regularly.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:31, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
::Montalban below attacks some &quot;Catholic argument&quot; that is not in the article, which says instead that &quot;''Orthodox'' apologists&quot; point to the Victor episode as an example of &quot;claims by Rome to papal primacy and rejection by Eastern Churches thereof&quot;.  I don't question that some unspecified Montalban-like &quot;Orthodox apologists&quot; hold that view, nor do I wish to go off-topic to discuss some &quot;Catholic argument&quot; or other.  It is best just to hand the matter back to Student7.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 14:17, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

If there were five people united, they'd have a common unity. If anyone of them broke off with any other, then the common unity would be ended. They'd be 'cut off from the common unity'.

There's real signs why the Catholic argument doesn't work

One is Cardinal Newman trying to explain why in the first 3 centuries there's NO EVIDENCE of papal supremacy. Catholics of course want to argue here all points at once; that there's no evidence (because papal supremacy was never questioned) and that there is evidence.

Two is that Victor, if he felt this matter was so important utterly failed to have his way. Catholics of course try to have all arguments at once, that it was an important issue (to demonstrate papal supremacy), and that it wasn't (in order to excuse the fact Victor didn't get unity of calculation of the calendar).

The churches of Asia Minor continued in their ways until a general council ruled. And by that time Quartodecimanism was more a heresy as they adopted other Jewish rituals.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 11:43, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

I take it then that Esoglu doesn't have an opinion derived from the article regarding whether Victor was supreme pontiff of all the church, or not.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 22:29, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

== Earliest signs of the growing schism ==

The article text reads &quot;Although Catholic apologists have typically pointed to the 7th century controversy over the Filioque and the 9th century schism of [[Photios]] as the earliest signs of the growing schism,...&quot;  Esoglou has put a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{citation needed}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; tag on this text.  I believe Cleenewerck said something along these lines but I'll have to check.  However, Cleenewerck is not the most reliable of authors; EdJohnston has pointed out that he appears to be writing for a popular audience as he is not cited by other scholars.

More importantly, I'd like to understand what Esoglou's concern is here so that I can research in the direction of his concern.
--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 00:22, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
:Experience indicates that a Wikipedia editor's use of the word &quot;typically&quot; usually betrays an original-research generalization.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:28, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
::Yeh, OK... I can't find the source for the Catholic side of the assertion although I remember substituting &quot;Catholic apologists&quot; for &quot;Catholic theologians&quot; because I didn't care for the implication that dating the origin of the schism as a theological point rather than a historical one.  That said, a review of sources in Google Books suggests that a fuller explication is needed than the sentence in question.  I will work on it. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 16:08, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
:::Thank you, Richard.  I think the phrase &quot;most sources agree that&quot; could simply be omitted, but I also think nobody would question it.  Not even me. :-)  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:45, 9 November 2012 (UTC)

-----

Or, maybe Esoglou can provide evidence for something???


[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 02:31, 9 November 2012 (UTC)

Esoglou, I believe you need to set out what it is you're concerned about

[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 11:00, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
::Montalban, Esoglou is setting an inappropriate criteria. If they don't like it they will attack it and they will try and attack it and second guess it to pieces. Esoglou and Richard are not here to make a Wikipedia article. They are here to protect the Roman Catholic POV about this issue. However they are not here to protect it by providing the POV from validate sources and then allowing people to read that and draw their own conclusions.&lt;br&gt;
::NO.&lt;br&gt;
::They are here attacking the Orthodox position and it's sources RATHER THAN LEAVING THEM ALONE. And also making on the spot original research. Cleenewerck is an Orthodox source (and a pro-ecumenist one at that, so even Cleenewerck is not something the average Orthodox christian will espouse to) Esoglou has edit restrictions that say Esoglou doesn't get to edit and or depict the Orthodox side of this issue. Richard can't leave the article alone. Now why is that. I'll tell you this. If people read this issue and one, don't pick a bias on the front end and or two get mad their side is wrong and [[poison the well]]. 
&lt;br&gt;
::'''They will see that the Roman Catholic side had no business telling the other churches of the Middle East that it should rule them and that it could make policy and theological changes unilaterally without Council.''' If people are able to see both sides then it will not be logic or respect or fairness that they would use to validate siding with the Roman Catholic side of this. Because that is why the schism happened. The Eastern Churches did not invade the West. If you notice this entire conflict has been ''in the East''. The Roman Catholics had no business putting the strangle hold on the Eastern Roman Empire rather that be for the Venetians or Charlemagne. How is it that the Roman Catholic position so far has been to hid that the very churches (communities) that Jesus came from reject them? How is anything that they might say counter that reality?
&lt;br&gt; 
::How delusion does someone have to be? I mean you have European &quot;scholars&quot; telling these different ethnic groups that they don't understand their own cultural identity, history and languages. That Europe has to give them that. Think about how ignorant this whole side of it is. Here is a very obvious and ugly truth of just how ignorant the Western Christian side is. Go out and ask them if they know who Plato and Aristotle is. They will say yes. Ask them to name you just one living and breathing Greek philosopher that they know of. If they are honest they will tell you that there are no more or that they do not know if any even still exist. Or they might just say that European philosophers carried that on since the East fell to Islam and that philosophy died out or the new stupidest one of all that the philosophical tradition was destroyed by Christianity with the death of (fill in the blank, [[Hypatia]]) etc etc. They will not be able to tell you who [[Christos Yannaras]] is. The problem is in the bigger picture that Christianity as having been taken over by the West is dying. And the nihilism that failed to over take Orthodoxy is now what is coming in and over taking Western Christianity. By way of sobornost the Orthodox can only do so much but the mind hustle of  human reason (a-priori) validation of the existence of God is coming to an end. In the East it simply never was to begin with. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 16:44, 9 November 2012 (UTC)


This would seem to be the case as Esoglou has made a number of comments here which, when I ask for details are met with silence. I see him requesting citations over and over again but offers no evidence whatsoever when requested.


The really weird thing is that such people think that they are doing their church some kind of service - whereas in truth the opposite is happening. People reading these discussions will see an utter lack of conviction not only to the rules of this site, but also in actually discussing any valid concern. It's like a major advertisement saying &quot;Catholicism cannot stand criticism&quot;.
[[User:Montalban|Montalban]] ([[User talk:Montalban|talk]]) 04:58, 10 November 2012 (UTC)

== Canon 9 ==

The article text reads &quot;This has been interpreted as conferring on the see of Constantinople a greater privilege than what any council ever gave Rome (Johnson) or as of much lesser significance than that (Hefele).&quot;  What are the references to Johnson and Hefele in parentheses?  The citation is to Schaff whose note to Canon 9 asserts the first part of the sentence.  If I am interpreting the article text as the author intended, it appears that Johnson and Hefele have differing opinions as to how much privilege Canon 9 conferred upon the see of Conatantinople.  If I got the intended meaning right, the presentation of the idea could be improved.  In particular, the attribution to Johnson and Hefele in parentheses is an unorthodox way of presenting sources in Wikipedia.  Use of &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/now.iki&gt; tags is preferred.--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 17:02, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
:You are right.  The shorthand was too severe.  I must fix it.  ~~~~</text>
      <sha1>2bamz9u4qal56dz0e6rnfsqsvfzogpv</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
