<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Infidel</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2191110</id>
    <revision>
      <id>484434060</id>
      <parentid>483753314</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-28T20:57:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Biraqleet</username>
        <id>14320199</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Part of a Series on Christianity */ re-signed</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15671">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=C|importance=Mid|anglicanism=yes|baptist-work-group=yes|charismatic-christianity=yes|methodism-work-group=yes|catholicism=yes|lutheranism=yes|lutheranism-importance=low|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|oriental-orthodoxy=yes|anglicanism-importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|importance=low|class=c|religion=yes|epistemology=yes}}
{{WikiProject Atheism|class= C|importance=Mid }}
{{WikiProject Religion|class= C|importance=Mid }}
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 2
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Infidel/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Archivebox|auto=yes}}

== New section on Judaism ==

I added a small section on Judaism, just to add references to the corresponding terms, Kofer and Goy/Gentile. There was a discussion as to whether &quot;Goy&quot; was equivalent to &quot;Infidel&quot; - I don't think it is, but it's probably still worth mentioning. Any comments welcome :)

== &quot;Heathen&quot; ==

{{user|213.132.45.37}} has inserted the word &quot;heathen&quot; into the article, in an apparent attempt explain? the phrase &quot;[[gentile]] [[pagan]]s&quot;. Aside from the fact that it means this article copies the source almost word-for-word, what additional information does it impart? [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 00:13, 13 July 2010 (UTC)
::Heathen is the word used in the source, gentile pagan was used as a particular example of a heathen that was primarily implied (gentile pagan). It just appeared that if one or the other were to be used, heathen is more correct. The second sentence that was added was to bring the section in line with the other two which added a modern context.--[[Special:Contributions/213.132.45.37|213.132.45.37]] ([[User talk:213.132.45.37|talk]]) 09:04, 22 July 2010 (UTC)
:::What additional information does &quot;heathen&quot; impart? I can't see any, aside from slavishly copying the source word-for-word. Please explain. Regarding the second sentence, a section on it has been opened above. Please explain ''there'' what it means, since it is not clear, and appears to be factually incorrect. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 12:21, 22 July 2010 (UTC)
::::It appears that &quot;heathen&quot; is the notion or concept of infidels that the source refers to. Pagan gentiles is the redundant portion of the reference that can be done without as one adding no additional information.--[[Special:Contributions/87.210.219.104|87.210.219.104]] ([[User talk:87.210.219.104|talk]]) 13:08, 26 July 2010 (UTC)
:::::On the contrary, the source specifies exactly what it means by heathens - &quot;specifically pagan gentiles&quot;. Therefore, it is the &quot;pagan gentiles&quot; portion of the phrase that is the salient one. Please don't remove wording that clarifies in favor of wording that obfuscates. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 16:42, 26 July 2010 (UTC)
::::::Well if only one is allowed then it would have to be heathens. Pagan gentiles only appears in brackets as an important example of heathens in the judaic view, and not necessarily the only one otherwise it would never have bothered to put in heathen and then also mention pagan gentile in a by the way manner to give an example. The best way to put it would actually be as it appears in this case, with pagan gentiles in brackets, otherwise emphasis is being shifted to where it was not placed in the source.--[[Special:Contributions/87.210.219.104|87.210.219.104]] ([[User talk:87.210.219.104|talk]]) 10:18, 28 July 2010 (UTC)
:::::::No, the source says &quot;specifically pagan gentiles&quot;. &quot;Heathens&quot; is a vague term, which could mean many things, so the source clarifies that when it uses the word here, it means &quot;specifically pagan gentiles&quot;. Rather than use the term even the source itself acknowledges is vague, we'll stick with the specific definition provided by the source. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 12:54, 28 July 2010 (UTC)

== Judeo-Christian? ==

What exactly are the areas of commonalty between the Christian and Jewish concept of god that are not shared by Muslims?  [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 20:27, 14 August 2010 (UTC)
:Sorry, I don't understand the question, or its particular relevant here. As far as I can tell, the Judaism and Islam have nearly identical concepts of God, which differ in significant ways from the Christian view, particularly around the issue of the [[Trinity]] - a central concept in Christianity. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 03:04, 15 August 2010 (UTC)
::The article says ''The term infidel was used by Christians to describe non-Christians or those perceived as the enemies of Christianity, especially to designate monotheists (Muslims) who do not subscribe to the Judeo-Christian concept of God.''  This doesn't make any sense to me, which is what I was trying to indicate with my previous comment. As you say, the Muslim and Jewish concepts of God are much closer to one another than either is to the Christian.  There are other ways that Christianity and Judaism are closer to one another than either is to Islam, but the concept of God is not one of them.  I understand that, in general, Muslims tended to be called Infidels while Jews, so far as I'm aware, generally were not.  But this needs to be reworked. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 05:19, 15 August 2010 (UTC)
:::You're right, it makes little sense. There was an IP editor working on this page who slavishly copied any source that attributed the term's use to an religion besides Islam, and this seems more of the same. I suspect it should be removed, at least from the lead, since it uses archaic terms for Islam (see the quote in the footnote), and appears factually incorrect. Your thoughts? [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 14:43, 15 August 2010 (UTC)
::::Certainly the term &quot;infidel&quot; was once used by Christians to refer to Muslims, and I've generally not seen it so described to refer to Jews.  But the particular wording is odd, even if it's taken from (plagiarized from, in fact) a source.  What archaic terms for Islam are used in the foonotes?  The footnote for the questionable sentence says &quot;Muslims.&quot; [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 19:04, 15 August 2010 (UTC)
:::::Yes, plagiarism was an on-going issue with this editor too (see above). The next sentence in the source (not included in the footnote) is &quot;From the Muhammedan point of view, especially as presented in English fiction and poetry, ''infidel'' often means a Christian&quot;. That's what I meant by &quot;archaic terms for Islam&quot; (actually Muslim). How do you propose this should be re-worded? [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 00:06, 16 August 2010 (UTC)
::::::How about ''The term infidel was used by Christians to describe non-Christians or those perceived as the enemies of Christianity, especially to designate Muslims''? [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 03:36, 16 August 2010 (UTC)
:::::::Looks good to me, but I'd leave out the phrase &quot;to designate&quot;, which I don't think adds much. Why don't you change the lede to that? [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 03:40, 16 August 2010 (UTC)

== Bigotry ==

&quot;While, In the twenty-first century, religious fundamentalism, dividing the world into true believers and the rest, is associated with the growth of religious nationalism, violence, and terrorism.[4]&quot;

My, my, my, how very bigoted. Who makes a blanket association of religious fundamentalism with terrorism? Ignorant bigots, that's who.

What is fundamentalism, other than a popularly-acceptable dirty word, a bad name to label others with? In its only decent sense, religious fundamentalism is the belief that the fundamentals of one's religion are true. In other words, religious people who are not fundamentalists are either hypocrites or idiots. Who but a hypocrite or an idiot would claim to follow a religion the fundamentals of which he did not believe to be correct?

Which people, believing the fundamentals of their religion to be true, act upon that belief by performing terrorist activities? Do Buddhists who believe the traditional understanding of the basis of their religion to be true perform terrorist acts due to that belief? What about Taoists? Do Wiccans? What about Christians who believe that traditional interpretations of their religion to be true? Do they perform terrorist acts due to that belief? How about Confucianists? Moslems? Do Moslems who believe the long-held understanding of their religion to be accurate perform terrorist acts due to their holding that belief? What of Zoroastorism?

Quoting bigots doesn't make their bigoted belief true, nor does it give value to your bigoted agreement with them. &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.235.47.163|67.235.47.163]] ([[User talk:67.235.47.163|talk]]) 04:22, 5 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;

: I removed the sentence, not only because it was poorly written, but because it was neither neutral or relevant to explaining &quot;infidel&quot;.

: However, if you can't argue a point without calling people idiots, maybe you need to reconsider the way you approach things. Calling people idiots just shows an inability on your part to rationalize or reason about your own position; if you could, you would have done that instead of appeal to emotion. So next time keep a level head.

: Since you didn't actually present any argument aside from &quot;You're all stupid listen to me&quot;, there isn't much more to say, except that you misunderstand what &quot;fundamentalist&quot; attempts to define. It doesn't mean &quot;believes the fundamentals&quot;...if that were the case, like you say, it would be redundant for a religious person to say so. If they didn't believe the fundamentals, they would either be deluded in their beliefs or an unbeliever of that faith. But instead of saying &quot;aha, this seems stupid to me, so everyone but me must be stupid and this is wrong&quot;, perhaps you should instead ask &quot;maybe I misunderstand the term&quot;.

: The term just means a person takes the doctrine of their faith literally, without question. That is, a fundamentalist that believes the stories of the [[Book of Genesis]] are true would necessarily believe the universe was created in 6 days. However, a non-fundamentalist could interpret this as a story, rather than a historical account, and accept the universe is about [[Age of the universe|13.75 billion years old]]. They both share the same beliefs about the core of their religion, but don't necessarily share the view that their religious text is an infallible historical account.

: Hope that clarifies, [[User:GManNickG|GManNickG]] ([[User talk:GManNickG|talk]]) 05:35, 5 November 2010 (UTC)

== Archaic? ==

I have removed the two words &quot;chiefly archaic&quot; from the introductory sentence as the word is still in vogue. For example, [http://www.answering-christianity.com/cgi-bin/quran/quran_search.cgi?search_text=infidel&amp;search_type=Exact+String&amp;B1=Search English translations of the Qur'an] will employ the word to refer to non-believers. Moreover, most [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/infidel modern dictionaries] do not classify the word as &quot;archaic,&quot; while they classify other words such as [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Alack++++ &quot;alack&quot;] to be archaic. I hope this helps. With regards, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 03:31, 22 February 2011 (UTC)
:Seems reasonable. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 01:58, 27 February 2011 (UTC)

== Part of a Series on Christianity ==

Should this really be a part of the series on Christianity?  In modern times, the word is almost exclusively associated with Islam. 17:53, 5 February 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Kwyjibear|Kwyjibear]] ([[User talk:Kwyjibear|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kwyjibear|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I actually disagree with the notion that &quot;infidel&quot; is associated with Islam, neither past nor present, or that it is an accurate translation of an Islamic term like &quot;kafir.&quot;  I am not a linguist, but I know of no Islamic or Arabic word which could readily be translated as infidel, a word which is specifically Christian in origin and usage.  You might use it to translate a phrase like &quot;Ghair Mu'min,&quot; that is a none-believing person.  But that is also weak.  A Mu’min in Islamic thought is one of true belief.  A Muslim is one who accepts Islam as a religion, but he or she is not necessarily a Mu’min, as the Qur’an asserts.  Thus, a “Ghair Mu’min” can also be a Muslim and thus you cannot say that it applies to non-Muslims.  Also, a Mu’min can be a non-Muslim from Ahl el-Kitab (People of the Book, i.e. Christians and Jews).  Kafir is more akin to a &quot;denier,&quot; as one who knows the truth but denies it, covers it, or refuses to accept it.  The people of Mecca at the time of Muhammad were considered Kuffar because they knew God existed but refused to acknowledge it in public because it did not serve their interests.  &quot;Mushrik&quot; is translated as &quot;associator,&quot; as one who knows that God exists but associate other deities with Him.  Some fringe Muslims would consider Christians as Mushriks because of their Trinitarian beliefs, but that is contrary to strict Islamic teachings which consider Christians and Jews as fellow believers who might have erred in their interpretations.  “Mulhid” is an atheist.  Islam also has no exact word for idolaters but it must be coined as in “people who worship idols.”
In sum, do not apply Christian concepts arbitrarily to another religion which manifestly differs in its conception of reality.  Islam takes it for granted that humans instinctively know of the existence of God.  If you acknowledge that and form a personal relationship with God (Iman) then you are a Mu’min, if you think other deities exist then you are a Mushrik, if you deny God for self-interest then you are a Kafir, if you deny God because of thinking He is not necessary then you are Mulhid.  Iman, thus, is that aspect of belief which in the West is erroneously associated with religion when for example we say religion is something between you a God.  In Islam, Iman is between you and God, while religion is the personal and social contract for action and a manifestation of that belief.   In Islam there is no true belief in the Christian sense of a true creed, but true belief is when God becomes the object of your action.  On the other hand, there is a true religion in the sense of being the pure and uncorrupted message from God regarding the way humans should conduct their life.  But even in that Muslims allow for variation within limits without being considered heretic. And above all, Islam considers it possible for humans to instinctively formulate a true religion, just like the Hunafaa, and chief among them the patriarch Abraham.[[User:Biraqleet|Biraqleet]] ([[User talk:Biraqleet|talk]]) 20:57, 28 March 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>4xn4hjlvbwomujg8en3kt9v7hjphb7x</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
