<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Nicene Creed</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>22006</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522262477</id>
      <parentid>510259362</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T01:03:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2600:1008:B104:A01D:9C8C:BF2E:AFB1:134A</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Comparison between Creed of 325 and Creed of 381 */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12547">{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=High|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=High|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern-orthodoxy-importance=high |lutheranism=yes|lutheranism-importance=Top |catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=High|religious-texts=yes|religious-texts-importance=High}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Nicene Creed/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Archives |bot=MiszaBot I |age=90 }}

== Spirit vs. Ghost ==

The correct English translation for the Greek word which is pronounced &quot;Pnevma&quot; is &quot;spirit&quot; NOT ghost. I am fluent in modern Greek, Ancient Greek and i am Greek. This is the correct translation. 

Also i am in agreemt with the &quot;Is this a joke&quot; author. The Nicene Creed was indeed formulated by the WHOLE Christian church body as it was prior to the Schism of 1054. However, if anything, it is more Eastern Orthodox than Catholic or protestant since it was created in Nicaea, a Greek city in Asia Minor.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ygkaravas|Ygkaravas]] ([[User talk:Ygkaravas|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ygkaravas|contribs]]) 05:29, 2 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
*That may be so, but the translation is given with reference to a reliable source, [http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/creeds1.iv.iii.html this one], by [[Philip Schaff]]. See [[Wikipedia:Verifiability,_not_truth#But_I_know_the_truth.21|Wikipedia:Verifiability, not truth]]. Thank you. [[User:Drmies|Drmies]] ([[User talk:Drmies|talk]]) 06:24, 2 December 2010 (UTC)
*That may be all well and fine that Philip Schaff, essentially a nobody of the 20th/21st century, decided to use the term &quot;holy Ghost&quot; as opposed to the true translation which has been used for centuries; essentially for as long as the Nicene Creed and the English Language have coexisted. In conclusion, I am not interested in what a 21st century writer or &quot;theologian&quot; whatever you wish to call Philip Schaff claims is the &quot;true&quot; translation; rather I am interested in what indeed IS the true tranlation, passed on through the centuries by the Nicaean and post-Nicaean Church Fathers, the true leaders and shepherds of the Christian faith. Thus it would be much appreciated if this heretical term &quot;holy Ghost&quot; was in fact replaced with the true term &quot;holy Spirit&quot; in MY religion's creed. Thank you &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:74.104.138.178|74.104.138.178]] ([[User talk:74.104.138.178|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/74.104.138.178|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
**And the issue here is that you claim to have access to the &quot;true&quot; translation--precisely that is why, above, I linked to a specific section of a specific essay, [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Verifiability,_not_truth#But_I_know_the_truth.21 &quot;But I ''know'' the truth!&quot;]. It seems you did not have a look at that essay, or at any of our other core guidelines, such as [[WP:V]]. Besides, this is not about how ''your'' religious creed can be appeased. Mine says &quot;ghost&quot;--so what? What matters here is not what you (or I!) think is right, but what the references say. If you have a better one, bring it--that would change the discussion. Right now you are simply disruptively changing text to where it no longer agrees with the references, claiming &quot;I am right.&quot; That's not how Wikipedia works.&lt;p&gt;One more thing: if you get an account, stop editing as an IP. It is confusing, and accusations of sock puppetry are just around the corner. [[User:Drmies|Drmies]] ([[User talk:Drmies|talk]]) 04:51, 3 December 2010 (UTC)

*The Nicene Creed was written first in Greek. This is a fact we can all agree on because it is common knowledge and is stated in the article i believe. The word &quot;πνεῦμα&quot; was a word in the original Nicene creed which I claim translates to &quot;Spirit&quot; (This is also a fact we can agree on since it is also in the Wikipeida article). This is the entry for the Greek word &quot;πνεῦμα&quot; from the &quot;Liddel and Scott Greek Lexicon&quot; the most widely used one, recognized to be the most accurate as well. Not once is the word &quot;Ghost&quot; used. Several times is the word &quot;Spirit&quot; and even &quot;Holy Spirit&quot; used. here it is: 

πνεῦμα πνέω 
I. a blowing, πνεύματα ἀνέμων Hdt., Aesch.: alone, a wind, blast, Trag., etc. 2. metaph., θαλερωτέρῳ πν. with more genial breeze or influence, Aesch.; λύσσης πν. μάργῳ id=Aesch.; πν. ταὐτὸν οὔποτ᾽ ἐν ἀνδράσιν φίλοις βέβηκεν the wind is constantly changing even among friends, Soph. II. like Lat. spiritus or anima, breathed air, breath, Aesch.; πν. βίου the breath of life, id=Aesch.; πν. ἀθροίζειν to collect breath, Eur.; πν. ἀφιέναι, ἀνιέναι, μεθιέναι to give up the ghost, id=Eur.; πνεύματος διαρροαί the wind-pipe, id=Eur. 2. that is breathed forth, odour, scent, id=Eur. III. spirit, Lat. afflatus, Anth.: inspiration, NTest. IV. the spirit of man, id=NTest. V. a spirit; in NTest. of the Holy Spirit, τὸ Πνεῦμα, Πν. ἅγιον:— also of angels, id=NTest.:—of evil spirits, id=NTest.

Please consider changing THE creed, not just MY creed to the TRUE creed. Thank you. [[User:Ygkaravas|Ygkaravas]] ([[User talk:Ygkaravas|talk]]) 05:29, 3 December 2010 (UTC)
:Ἠγαπημένε Ygkaravas, this article states: &quot;The following table juxtaposes the earlier (325 AD) and later (381 AD) forms of this Creed '''in the English translation given in Schaff's work, ''Creeds of Christendom''.'''  In that English translation &quot;Holy Ghost&quot; is used.  We cannot make the article say that Schaff wrote &quot;Holy Spirit&quot;.
:I presume you are familiar enough with the English language to know that &quot;ghost&quot; is still used, even if in a somewhat archaic way, to mean not only φάντασμα, but also πνεῦμα.  Even your lexicon quotation says so: &quot;πν. ἀφιέναι, ἀνιέναι, μεθιέναι to give up the ''ghost''&quot; (emphasis added).
:Your observation is correct with regard to less archaic, more modern English, and if you look up the article [[English versions of the Nicene Creed in current use]], you will find that all modern translations have &quot;Holy Spirit&quot;; the only version with &quot;Holy Ghost&quot; still in use is that of 1662 that continues to be employed in many churches of the Anglican Communion.  So Wikipedia has a whole article registering the fact that you wish to see included.  Δεν είναι σωστό;  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:46, 3 December 2010 (UTC)
::Thanks Esoglou: this is very helpful. I had seen the link to that article, but your reply is much better than I could have formulated it. [[User:Drmies|Drmies]] ([[User talk:Drmies|talk]]) 21:04, 3 December 2010 (UTC)

== Armenian ==

I'm familiar with Latin and Greek as being integral languages in Christianity, as well as Hebrew and Aramaic, but I have no idea why the Armenian text is given such a prominent position.  Can someone explain this? [[User:Bigpeteb|Bigpeteb]] ([[User talk:Bigpeteb|talk]]) 05:51, 15 February 2011 (UTC)
:I think its presence is useful as showing how this ancient church thinks it is right to recite the Nicene Creed with glosses giving further specification of the contents.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:46, 15 February 2011 (UTC)
:: Okay, but why specifically Armenian? And why isn't that explained in the article? And why does the Armenian version get an English translation but the Greek and Latin versions don't? I don't read Greek or Latin any more than I read Armenian, so the Armenian version is not helpful if I have nothing to compare it against. [[User:Bigpeteb|Bigpeteb]] ([[User talk:Bigpeteb|talk]]) 05:06, 18 February 2011 (UTC)
:::I hope my addition to the article answers your queries.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 07:56, 18 February 2011 (UTC)

== Comparison between Creed of 325 and Creed of 381 ==

Problems here. Says that square brackets indicate what the 381 version omits or moves, and the italics indicate what it adds. But going thru these indicators, one cannot reproduce either text unambiguously. Why not just give the two texts side by side?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.2.143.28|64.2.143.28]] ([[User talk:64.2.143.28|talk]]) 21:27, 30 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Also translates &quot;credo&quot; and &quot;pisteuo&quot; as &quot;we believe,&quot; when it is in fact first person singular, &quot;I believe.&quot;  [[Special:Contributions/2600:1008:B104:A01D:9C8C:BF2E:AFB1:134A|2600:1008:B104:A01D:9C8C:BF2E:AFB1:134A]] ([[User talk:2600:1008:B104:A01D:9C8C:BF2E:AFB1:134A|talk]]) 01:03, 10 November 2012 (UTC)

== Profession of Faith ==

&quot;Profession of Faith&quot; right now redirects to the general &quot;Creed&quot; but should come here instead. [[Special:Contributions/72.54.254.49|72.54.254.49]] ([[User talk:72.54.254.49|talk]]) 16:52, 23 December 2011 (UTC)
:I don't think so.  The [[Apostles' Creed]] [http://www.therealpresence.org/essentials/creed/acc01.htm has been called] &quot;The Basic Profession of Faith]].  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 21:16, 23 December 2011 (UTC)

== Alternate Version of the Creed ==

I don't see the actual document on which the text of the creed is based. Do we have actual manuscript of the creed? Or just quotations of later councils?

Theodore of Mopsuestia, few years before Council of Ephesus, in his commentary of Nicene Creed says: &quot;Our Fathers at wonderful council of Nicaea didn't overlook the human nature of our Lord, and because of this added a phrase: 'firstborn of all creation'.&quot;

Today's version of the creed omits this verse, and I think I know why it was removed - it was thought to be Nestorian at Council of Ephesus and that's why bishops removed it.

In any case, this article should at least claim the fact that there are alternate versions of the creed. --[[User:Otherguylb|Otherguylb]] ([[User talk:Otherguylb|talk]]) 21:03, 18 February 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;and&quot; vs &quot;of&quot; ==

There has been a recent edit controversy over using &quot;by the Holy Ghost and the Virgin Mary&quot; vs  &quot;by the Holy Ghost of the Virgin Mary&quot;  If we are going to stick with citing it from Schaff as it is, we must stick with the wording he uses. However, the last editor was correct in saying that the Greek word &quot;kai&quot; translates as &quot;and&quot;. Considering that &quot;the virgin Mary&quot; appears in the genitive, the proper translation would be &quot;and of the Virgin Mary&quot; incorporating both words...  Should we stick with Schaff's translation, or should I try to find a translation that preserves both word usages more faithfully to the original Greek?[[User:ReformedArsenal|ReformedArsenal: ὁ δὲ θεὸς]] 15:51, 25 April 2012 (UTC)
:There is the problem that the Schaff quotation is more than a translation of the two versions: it indicates by italics and by square brackets the differences between the 325 text and the later text; and those differences, not the wording of the translation, are the point of the section.  It would be difficult to find another source that does that.  Translating &quot;σαρκωθέντα ἐκ πνεύματος ἁγίου καὶ Μαρίας τῆς παρθένου&quot; as &quot;was incarnate by the Holy Ghost of the Virgin Mary&quot; is not the only point in Schaff's translation that could be questioned.  Even within that phrase itself, some might ask why does the translation add the definite article (absent in the original) to &quot;πνεύματος ἁγίου&quot;.
::The reason that the definite article is added is because  &quot;πνεύματος ἁγίου&quot; is considered a monadic noun (phrase) which is a &quot;one of a kind noun&quot; that is definite because of what it is, not because of the presence or absence of an article. See:  http://lists.ibiblio.org/pipermail/b-greek/2000-August/012969.html [[User:ReformedArsenal|ReformedArsenal: ὁ δὲ θεὸς]] 17:12, 25 April 2012 (UTC)
:Perhaps one could leave the Schaff quotation untouched and add a (sourced) note about more literal ways of translating one or more words or phrases in the quotation.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:21, 25 April 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ht1rw6apgza8yk3rgq4mc8xvqa6a3ls</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
