<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Orthodox Judaism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>152667</id>
    <revision>
      <id>519510605</id>
      <parentid>493388357</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-24T04:07:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>StuZealand</username>
        <id>12705192</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* &quot;ultra-Orthodox&quot; */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17819">{{User:MiszaBot/config
|algo = old(14d)
|archive = User talk:Example/Archive %(counter)d
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 2
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
}}
{{talkheader|search=yes}}
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{User:WildBot/m01|dabs={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Kaf HaChaim}}, {{User:WildBot/m03|1|canon}}|m01}}
{{User:WildBot/m04|sect={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Baal teshuva#Orthodox outreach organizations|outreach}}|m04}}
__TOC__
== Hasidic Couple photo redux ==

There have been legitimate requests on behalf of the couple to take the photo out of the article. Why the push to keep it in? -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 00:27, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

:Can you prove this? I really don't believe it. Anyhow, Wikipedia is not censored. [[User:Bstone|Bstone]] ([[User talk:Bstone|talk]]) 00:37, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

::Censored, shmensored. Let's be a little normal and reasonable for a second. How would you like if someone surreptitiously took a picture of you while you're reading this and then added the pic to [[frown|this]] article?--''[[User:Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font family:Arial;color:green&quot;&gt;brew&lt;/span&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Arial;color:#2E82F4&quot;&gt;crewer&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Brewcrewer|(yada, yada)]]'' 02:32, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

:::I'd be entertained. You do know many Muslims are incensed that there are paintings of Mohammad on wiki. Yet the policy states it's not censored. [[User:Bstone|Bstone]] ([[User talk:Bstone|talk]]) 02:35, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

::::Okay then, how about if someone takes a pic of your body part and adds it to [[Penis|this]] article? Of course there's a difference, but believe it or not, in the ultra-orthodox hasidic culture, the public posting of this pic is not far removed from my foregoing analogy.

:::: I also don't understand why you have a hard time believing they asked to have the pic removed. Agreed, it's unlikely that they themselves saw the pic, but all it takes is one reader who recognizes them and calls them to tell them the exciting news. 

::::We are not dealing with censoring anything. If someone were to add another pic of another couple nobody will say peep unless they complain as well. 

::::Even if the removal of their pic would violate some sort of WP policy, this would be the ideal situation for the application of some [[WP:IAR|common sense and to ignore all rules]]. --''[[User:Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font family:Arial;color:green&quot;&gt;brew&lt;/span&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Arial;color:#2E82F4&quot;&gt;crewer&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Brewcrewer|(yada, yada)]]'' 02:50, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

So, Bstone, are you accusing me of lying? Whatever happened to assume good faith? [[image:face-grin.svg|25px]]. Regardless, to fulfill the Gemara in Bava Metzia 49a on the pasuk  {{bibleref|Leviticus|19:36|HE}}, ask any OTRS volunteer to look at {{OTRS ticket|1336382|2008020610017499}}. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 03:02, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

:I would have pointed to 19:18: &quot;thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself&quot;. --''[[User:Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font family:Arial;color:green&quot;&gt;brew&lt;/span&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/Brewcrewer|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Arial;color:#2E82F4&quot;&gt;crewer&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Brewcrewer|(yada, yada)]]'' 03:09, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

::I meant the Gemara of {{lang|he|הן שלך}} :) -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 03:16, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

The discussion of this issue the last time made it clear that, although there was indeed a request, it was not possible to verify that the request was made by the couple in question.  So, now we have the whole thing kicked off again by an anonymous/IP edit, an action editors are endorsing with reference to religious views/ideas.  It ought to go without saying that the content of Wikipedia pages is not governed by halacha, and I don't think anyone has produced an argument saying that this photo violates any of Wikipedia's rules.  [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]] ([[User talk:Nomoskedasticity|talk]]) 06:35, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

:::Nomo, I know you have not seen the email trail in OTRS, but I have. The picture is causing distress to the couple and their relatives, there is no reason for it to be in the article. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 15:32, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

:Delete the picture. Enough with it. They most certainly don't want their picture on Wikipedia. If you want, I myself volunteer to have my own picture on Wikipedia, with full shabbos dress (shtreimel, bekitshe). But not with my wife. No chareidi (especially, no chassidishe) woman wants her picture on Wikipedia. It is very reasonable to believe that this couple indeed did complain against this picture. They might very well have a large family in America (or Israel) who include English-speakers with internet access, or maybe colleagues at work or friends anywhere, who informed them of this picture. --[[User:Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha|Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha]] ([[User talk:Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha|talk]]) 10:10, 24 December 2008 (UTC)
::I'm going to suggest, yet again, that we edit Wikipedia according to the rules of Wikipedia, as against some other set of rules.  [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]] ([[User talk:Nomoskedasticity|talk]]) 15:30, 24 December 2008 (UTC)
:::Yes, and [[WP:BLP]] applies to pictures too. There is no harm removing the photo, only in keeping it. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 15:33, 24 December 2008 (UTC)
::::Which part of [[WP:BLP]] does the photo violate?  I know it applies to images, but I'm not sure what provision you're referring to.  [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]] ([[User talk:Nomoskedasticity|talk]]) 15:50, 24 December 2008 (UTC)
:::::&quot;''The possibility of harm to living subjects is one of the important factors to be considered when exercising editorial judgment....This policy applies equally to biographies of living persons and to biographical material about living persons on other pages.''&quot; This image is causing harm to real people for basically no good reason. We even switch out images of people in articles about them if the original image is causing them distress. Here the article isn't even about these people, and the image was taken without their knowledge or permission, and what purpose is it serving here?! -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 15:55, 24 December 2008 (UTC)
::::::The point that was made when this was discussed in ''February'' is that there was precious little reason to believe that the person who contacted Wikipedia on this issue was the couple in question; anyone could send an email message claiming to be those people.  Given that this was the conclusion reached at that point and the photo has remained on the page since then, what has happened ''now'' to suddenly convince everyone that the complaint was real?  As best I can tell, nothing; the only thing that has happened today is that an anonymous/IP editor removed the photo -- and now we're discussing the whole thing again as if we never did before. If you go back to the discussions at the time (on this talk page and others linked in sections above), you will see that there was a bit of a campaign against the photographer - and thus reason to doubt that the people who wrote to Wikipedia were in fact the couple in question.  Again, the question is, what would lead us to a different conclusion ''now''?  [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]] ([[User talk:Nomoskedasticity|talk]]) 16:15, 24 December 2008 (UTC)
:::::::Another e-mail came in to OTRS from the same parties this week. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 16:45, 24 December 2008 (UTC)
::::::::Okay.  And what made it more convincing than the one sent in February? [[User:Nomoskedasticity|Nomoskedasticity]] ([[User talk:Nomoskedasticity|talk]]) 16:53, 24 December 2008 (UTC)
(&lt;-)Having looked at the entire email chain, there is enough corroborating evidence to me (email name corroborates business identity of phone number supplied, for example) to say that this is not connected with the other attempts on Shankbone, but a bona fide request. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 17:22, 24 December 2008 (UTC)

==Removed from article==
I removed this text:
:It should be noted that on January 7, 2009, Hamodia reports that New Jersey attorney Stephen E. Schwartz, Esq., convinced the largest newspaper in New Jersey, the [[Star-Ledger]], to drop the term &quot;ultra-Orthodox&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Avraham Weissman interviews Stephen Schwartz in Ten to One on January 7, 2009, page A3&lt;/ref&gt;

The achievements of a lawyer in changing the terminology practice of his local newspaper are not relevant to the history and definition of Orthodox Judaism.  If there is an article on the various names of Orthodox Jewish groups, and how they relate to each other, then this information could be relevant there.  (Prof. Eli Segal in fact has such a page on his website.) [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]
::However the term ultra-orthodox was created by the Israeli medias to pinpoint groups opposing sionism and nowdays to pinpoint leoumi-dati settlers, not very consistent! True that there are modern-othodoxs, but the others are merely orthodoxs without any extras or ultras :-)--[[User:Ha-y Gavra|Ha-y Gavra]] ([[User talk:Ha-y Gavra|talk]]) 13:03, 1 March 2011 (UTC)

== Stop removing this from the article ==
''Lisa Liel'' is trying to remove this important clarification from the article:
:Both terms are controversial: in some circles, the label &quot;Haredi&quot; is considered pejorative, while others consider the label &quot;ultra-Orthodox&quot; pejorative. Some Haredi Jews have taken to referring to themselves as [[Torah Judaism|Torah Jews]], but this term as well is considered to be a pejorative criticism of all other religious Jewish groups. 

:She incorrectly claims that the term &quot;Torah Judaism&quot; is used by Modern Orthodox Judaism.  ''That is way off base.''  In fact, just link to our article on [[Torah Judaism]] - it clearly states that this term is a Haredi criticism of Modern Orthodox Judaism.  Her edit is not supported by the facts.  (I have done some research; I have yet to find a Modern Orthodox Jewish rabbi who agrees with Ms. Liel.  Modern Orthodox rabbis clearly understand this term to be an attack upon them.  It certainly isn't aimed at secular or Reform Jews.  Even the Conservative Jews are not the target of this term.) [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]])

:: &quot;Torah Judaism&quot; is used by quite a lot of Modern Orthodox Jews, like Rabbi Tovia Singer, a popular radio host on Arutz Sheva radio ( www.israelnn.com ) and author of several books. And if I as a non-Jew know that, so should you. --  [[User:Alexey Topol|Alexey Topol]] ([[User talk:Alexey Topol|talk]]) 23:08, 29 April 2010 (UTC)

::The first sentence in the section &quot;Origin of the Term Orthodox&quot; reads as follows:

::&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;While many Orthodox Jews accept the label &quot;Orthodox&quot;, others reject and criticise it because it was never traditionally applied to Jews who strictly interpreted and followed halakha in ancient times or the Middle Ages. Many Orthodox Jews prefer to call their faith Torah Judaism.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

::This is true.  RK believes otherwise, but it's been my experience with him elsewhere on the Internet that he labels all but the most far-left Modern Orthodoxy (JOFA, YCT, Edah) as Haredi.

:::This is incorrect;   I have never held this position - ever. In any case, please stop the comments about me.  This webpage is '''only''' for discussions about this encyclopedia article.  Discussions about a Wikipedia editor are off-topic. [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]) 

::Basically, he is attempting to introduce an unsourced and demonstrably false claim that &quot;Torah Judaism&quot; is a term used only by Haredim.  And he is further attempting to add his own opinion that this term is considered pejorative by non-Haredim, which is at best [[WP:OR]], and at worst, simple polemicizing on his part.

::I'm by no means Haredi myself, and as RK is well aware, I've been self-identifying as a Torah Jew for years and years. -[[User:LisaLiel|LisaLiel]] ([[User talk:LisaLiel|talk]]) 16:06, 11 January 2009 (UTC)

:::Lisa Liel is incorrect.  I apologize if my comments were somehow unclear.  Lisa, please read this carefully: I never said that the term is ''only'' used by Haredim as an attack against Modern Orthodox Jews.  ''This is not my position''.  Rather, I merely said that the use of the term is controversial among some people.  Ironically, I agree with many of your recent statements, but you seem to have misunderstood mine, and thus see yourself in opposition to someone who agrees with you. [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]])


It is most certainly true that there are a number of Haredi groups which use the term &quot;Torah Jews&quot; to refer to Haredim. For example, the Israeli political party UTJ, ''Yahadut HaTorah''. Also, the related expression ''Olam HaTorah'' is frequently heard in Haredi circles - and when used, this refers to Haredi circles only. The newspaper affiliated with Degel, Yated Ne'eman, also uses it. If you want some examples, see the usage of ''Torah Judaism'' here: [http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=site%3Achareidi.shemayisrael.com+%22Torah+Judaism%22+-United&amp;btnG=Search]. You should be able to discern that in all of these articles, the term &quot;Torah Judaism&quot; refers to Haredi forms only.
As for the second issue: there should indeed be a mentioning of the controversy of &quot;Haredi&quot; vs &quot;Ultra-Orthodox&quot;. The fact that the biggest paper in the state of NJ decided to start using the former instead of the latter is certainly significant. Now if you want to claim that this lawyer is insignificant, fine - just write &quot;A New Jersey lawyer convinced....&quot; instead of writing his full name. But the fact itself is most certainly worthy of being in the article. --[[User:Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha|Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha]] ([[User talk:Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha|talk]]) 16:45, 11 January 2009 (UTC)

:I agree with most of what you say.  I merely think that the terminology of one newspaper in one state is not (at all) relevant for an encyclopedia article! [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]) 17:45, 11 January 2009 (UTC)
::If it were a local paper in some mountain town in Montana, ok, I'd agree. But we're talking about the largest newspaper of NJ here - an area which includes Lakewood, Union City and other areas with a significant Haredi population. It's not just any newspaper, and it isn't just any state. I think that does make it relevant. --[[User:Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha|Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha]] ([[User talk:Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha|talk]]) 08:54, 12 January 2009 (UTC)

:Hey all, my first post in this discussion, but I want to add that this is not one State, but global (the JTA), national (RNA) and mutli-state (NJ, NY, PA).  NJ Attorney Stephen Schwartz is leading the way and the term &quot;ultra Orthodox&quot; is dying.  Since only the term &quot;Orthodox&quot; is left, may I suggest that including this information is not only relevant, but actually clarifies the article.[[User:Sacklerss|Sacklerss]] ([[User talk:Sacklerss|talk]]) 19:57, 5 February 2009 (UTC)
::Are you saying that instead of &quot;ultra-Orthodox&quot;, they now write &quot;Orthodox&quot;? I thought they would have replaced it with &quot;Haredi&quot;. That term seems to gain more mainstream acceptance as of late. --[[User:Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha|Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha]] ([[User talk:Piz d&amp;#39;Es-Cha|talk]]) 22:05, 5 February 2009 (UTC)

== Modern Orthodoxy under attack==
Editors of this article may be interested in the comments here: [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]])
:[[Talk:Modern_Orthodox_Judaism#Modern_Orthodoxy_under_attack Modern Orthodoxy Under Attack]]

== If possible ==

Could someone have a look at the quotebox in the beliefs section, maybe it is just me, but I can only see 6 out of the 13 principles of faith on the page, can someone see if they can sort the box out, as I am unable? [[User:Joshuaselig|Joshuaselig]] ([[User talk:Joshuaselig|talk]]) 14:56, 21 June 2009 (UTC)
:I see all 13 (using Firefox and a resolution of 1280x1024) -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 15:09, 21 June 2009 (UTC)

== Torah including written Law ==

The author wrote: &quot;Orthodox Judaism's central belief is that Torah, including the Written Law, was given directly from God to Moses and applies in all times and places&quot;
See http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/The_Written_Law.html
 Perhaps, the author meant,&quot;Orthodox Judaism's central belief
 is that Torah, including the Oral Law, ...&quot;.
[[User:CreateW|CreateW]] ([[User talk:CreateW|talk]]) 01:02, 10 May 2010 (UTC)

:I agree, I have changed it.  In the future feel free to [[wp:bb|be bold]] and edit it yourself.  [[User:Jon513|Jon513]] ([[User talk:Jon513|talk]]) 11:51, 10 May 2010 (UTC)

==Neo-Orthodoxy link==
In the text, there's a sentence that goes, &quot;...termed the [[Torah im Derech Eretz]] approach, or &quot;[[neo-Orthodoxy]]...&quot; where, as you can see, &quot;neo-Orthodoxy&quot; is interlinked to an article that defines the &quot;Christian&quot; approach to theology in [[Protestantism]] - therefore, it's confusing and has nothing to do with Judaism. I'm removing the offending link.--[[User:Monozigote|Monozigote]] ([[User talk:Monozigote|talk]]) 20:13, 18 March 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;ultra-Orthodox&quot; ==

Why is this term considered by some to be pejorative? I've seen it used in the media where I live (New Zealand) many times and no one seems to bat an eyelid at it. From my POV, 'ultra' simply means the far end of a spectrum. EG, Ultra High Frequency.

Your thoughts please.

[[User:StuZealand|StuZealand]] ([[User talk:StuZealand|talk]]) 04:07, 24 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>srg5rglmppqxoe857hk1zhmvu2oatv5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
