<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Sikhism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>154662</id>
    <revision>
      <id>515125262</id>
      <parentid>514977529</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-29T09:27:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sikh-history</username>
        <id>2305934</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>many sects</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="83300">{{Calm talk}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=20:51, 16 June 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Sikhism/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=59002224

|action2=FAC
|action2date=16:21, 2 July 2006
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Sikhism
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=61696247

|action3=FAR
|action3date=01:28, 17 August 2009
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article review/Sikhism/archive1
|action3result=removed
|action3oldid=306965394

|maindate=August 17, 2006
|currentstatus=FFA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Sikhism|class=B|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject India|class=B|importance=top|punjab=yes|punjab-importance=top|portal=yes}}
{{WikiProject Pakistan|class=C|importance=low|Punjab=y}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=B|category=Philrelig|VA=yes}}
}}
{{Spoken Wikipedia request|Sikhism|Dear Sir, I humbly request that you should make 'Sikhism' an audio recording because Sikhism is one of the world's major religions, and making it an audio recording would allow adherents who are visually impaired the ability to hear about the tenets of their faith and the issues that effect the Sikhs}}
{{archive box|
# [[/Archive 1|December 2002 &amp;ndash; May 2006]]
# [[/Archive 2|May 2006 &amp;ndash; June 2006]]
# [[/Archive 3|June 2006 &amp;ndash; July 2006]]
# [[/Archive 4|July 2006 &amp;ndash; November 2007]]
}}&lt;!--Template:Archivebox ends--&gt;
{{todo|small=yes}}


==What does Sikhism say about...?==
Would someone please tell me, what does Sikhism say about: Apostasy (leaving Sikhism)? Homosexuality? Mixed dancing? Eating pig-meat? Are they  prohibited, discouraged, ignored, allowed, or what? Perhaps they should be mentioned in the article, as things that other monotheistic religions have strong views on --[[User:Hugh7|Hugh7]] ([[User talk:Hugh7|talk]]) 07:47, 26 September 2012 (UTC)
::[[User:Hugh7|Hugh7]], there are LGBT articles on Sikhism and Homsexuality in Wikipedia. [[Diet in Sikhism]] covers the pig meat issue (which is forbidden to Muslims and not Sikhs). Apostasy, Sikhs are not a missionary faith so are based on attraction, so if someone leaves it is up to them. See articles on [[Bhangra]] on mixed dancing. Sikhs have many mixed dancing group. However, vulgerness is not encouraged. Thanks [[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;]] 12:47, 27 September 2012 (UTC)
Thank you. And does Sikhism have no sects? If so, that seems quite remarkable for such a large body of believers. Is there some particular way it is achieved? --[[Special:Contributions/121.72.144.204|121.72.144.204]] ([[User talk:121.72.144.204|talk]]) 10:17, 28 September 2012 (UTC)
:::Sikhism has many sects , [[Akhand Kirtani Jatha]], [[Namdhari]], [[Dam Dami Taksal]], the vast majority however ttake their guidance from the [[Akal Takht]], the temporal authority of the Sikhs. There are many stubs to this article. Please search them. Thanks [[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;]] 09:27, 29 September 2012 (UTC)

==Waheguru Ji Ka Khalsa Waheguru Ji Ke Fateh==
Dearest Sikh Sangat, there is a grave missuse of the Monotheistic word, our religion is clearly described in the English Oxford Dictionary as one of the 5 Monolythic religions (Christian, Muslim,Jew, Bhai Faith and Sikh,) all talk to the same God (Ik-Oankaar.) as a Sikh it is not hard for me to see this and our own teachings, teach us that God appears in many places, can be a beggar or rich person. This may also correct the misconception why Sikhs touch the floor and touch their forehead, ( if Waheguru, God, My Lord, Allah ) what ever your religion calls him, in many different languages, there is only one GOD, and if he has been present in our Gurdwarra, I want to be blessed by the dust off his feet. This is the only dictionary that tells the truth about our sikh religion for me and all Sikhs the truth is paramount. The majority of world dictionaries I have checked, state that Sikhism is an off shoot of Hindu religion, this is a blatant spin by corruption to our God Fearing religions and a further dilution of Sikhism and where it belongs in the world. I have been fighting for many years to have these world dictionaries change and tell the truth. Please look at the British Oxford Dictionary, written before 1947
Angad Singh (Sikh Activist)
Waheguru Ji Ka Khalsa Waheguru Ji Ke Fateh

==Sikhism and women==
:: As in many other religions Sikhism has no guidance for women, even though they do observe it of their own accord. I must enlighten my friends on this Wikipedia that Hinduism is often mistaken for Brahmanism, actually Hinduism is a much wider ideology and cannot be rated as a religion. I, by my studies, have come to a conclusion that Sikhism is a segment of Hinduism as other religions such as Jainism, Buddhism and Brahmanism and many more sects; we may deffer. [[User:Pathare Prabhu|Pathare Prabhu]] ([[User talk:Pathare Prabhu|talk]]) 03:09, 13 April 2011 (UTC)

Its funny that the only people who think that Sikhs are Hindus are Hindus themselves. Sikhs are not Hindus, nor a segment of Hinduism, if we were we would call ourselves as such. ([[Special:Contributions/174.1.80.242|174.1.80.242]] ([[User talk:174.1.80.242|talk]]) 19:50, 5 June 2011 (UTC))

== Monotheistic? ==
Dearest SadhSangat, It is to my humble understanding that the first line of this article is open to a heavy misconception. Firstly, when attempting to understand from Wikipedia's description of Theism: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theism, (read further by clicking the link to &quot;personal god&quot; in the second sentence of that article) It conflicts with my understanding of the teachings in Gurbani, We do not in any way believe in a &quot;personal God&quot;, (Yes the word &quot;God&quot; and &quot;Him&quot; comes up in many English translations of Gurbani however in the original untranslated text, the word &quot;God&quot; or &quot;Him&quot; for that matter, is something that does not come up as far as I have searched) So how can Sikhism be a Mono-Theistic religion?, I see a conflict between the teachings in Gurbani and this definition. Again many of the words in English are open to a high level of misconceptions because they have been simplified and personified from their original Greek and Latin meanings (Which are much deeper), therefore care must be taken when using such words without elaborating. Also changing it to &quot;Non-theistic&quot; would still be open to misconception, so I believe it needs to be elaborated and points illustrated quoting Gurbani instead of leaving it to any &quot;*theistic&quot; definition.
 

Edit: I think &quot;Pantheistic&quot; may fit better, please read: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pantheism

Sat Sri Akal,
[[User:SatveerSinghBhullar|SatveerSinghBhullar]] ([[User talk:SatveerSinghBhullar|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/SatveerSinghBhullar|contribs]]) 01:04, 8 April 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::I agree 100%. Let us take &quot;Mul Mantra&quot; where God is described as Beyond Time and Space and also as Truth. In other sections as mother, father, teacher, air , water. etc etc. If you are going to change it, get a reference to back it up. Thanks--[[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;Sikh-&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;History&lt;/em&gt;]] 08:26, 8 April 2010 (UTC)

::::Sat Sri Akal. Actually I am quite new to Wikipedia (as you can see by this post being out of chronological order compared with the entire discussion :P), I'm not too sure about changing to article myself, I was just bringing this up so that the moderators (if any), and community who assisted in writing this article may change it. Can someone more experienced kindly help to change this.--[[User:SatveerSinghBhullar|SatveerSinghBhullar]] ([[User talk:SatveerSinghBhullar|talk]]) 06:14, 9 April 2010 (UTC)
:Ok leave it with me. Thanks--[[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;Sikh-&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;History&lt;/em&gt;]] 08:22, 9 April 2010 (UTC)

I must say that the current state of the article is still confusing. I have a Christian background and was reading this article as a complete outsider who'd heard nothing about Sikhism aside from the name itself. I found the article very confusing. It starts off by saying it's a monotheistic religion and uses the word &quot;God&quot; a lot but everything it says about this &quot;God&quot; runs against what I (and presumably most non-Indian Christians/Jews/Muslims) understand to be &quot;the God&quot; or even &quot;a god&quot;. I think the beginning of the article should be rewritten to make it clear that what the Sikh believe in is in no way &quot;the God&quot; or &quot;a god&quot; in the sense the terms are understood by western Christians/Jews/Muslims but is something altogether different which is described only by the word &quot;God&quot; because the English language is incapable of capturing the term properly. In fact, thinking about it, it may be preferable to replace the use of &quot;God&quot; with the Latin transcription of a non-English word XXXX linked to an article XXXX that explains that &quot;XXXX is the higher entity believed in by Sikhs. XXXX is not comparable to the notion of &quot;God&quot; as used in western religions. &lt;more description here&gt;&quot;
[[Special:Contributions/93.134.196.70|93.134.196.70]] ([[User talk:93.134.196.70|talk]]) 15:10, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
::Indeed the Sikh concept of God is different from Semitic faiths. The first line of the Sikh Holy Book reads, Ek Onkar, Satnam - There is but one God it's name is truth. God dwells within each and every one of us and it is for us to realise it. Sikhism does not say, IT is the only path, but says there are many paths to God. Thanks [[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;]] 18:04, 8 August 2012 (UTC)

==Editprotected request==&lt;!--title added by Nihiltres when moving section to bottom of page--&gt;
{{[[Template:editprotected|editprotected]]}}&lt;br /&gt;
Sikh and other religon relations must be added into the article for general knowledge and correct information. Wiki admistrators will be contacted to dispute and correct the article. Public demands that information on the following religons and relations should be provided as information in this article.
*Christianity
*Islam
*Hinduism
all information has been provided earlier in history. Requests have been made to revert information on all three religons and relations.
&lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.237.253.131|99.237.253.131]] ([[User talk:99.237.253.131|talk]]) {{{2|}}}&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt;

:{{cross|18}} '''Not done''' - Your request is far too vague. Please either make the request again with specific changes to be made, or edit the article yourself - I unprotected the page as it has been semi-protected for a long time. [[User:Nihiltres|&lt;font color=&quot;#275CA9&quot;&gt;Nihiltres&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;'''{'''&lt;span class=&quot;plainlinks&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Nihiltres|&lt;font color=&quot;#000&quot;&gt;t&lt;/font&gt;]].[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?user=Nihiltres &lt;font color=&quot;#000&quot;&gt;l&lt;/font&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;'''}'''&lt;/sup&gt; 16:48, 16 November 2007 (UTC)

==Sikhism website==
I found a grest sikhism website www.sikhzone.net  that provides information about sikhism, sikhism principles, sikh gurus, gurdwaras and also lets you download pdf gurbani. I think it's worth adding to External Links section.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:The coool|The coool]] ([[User talk:The coool|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/The coool|contribs]]) 10:25, 28 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Questioned external links==
I have removed a couple of external links that appear more to be resources for Sikhs than adding substantively to the article. I request the editors of the article to review these.
*[http://www.sikhnet.com SikhNet.com - community website]
*[http://www.ggssc.org GGSSC.org - Guru Gobind Singh Study Circle - non-profit organization]
The Punjabi radio station and the site offering literature are, I believe, sufficiently far from adding content to the article to qualify for direct removal. [[User:Jackollie|Jackollie]] ([[User talk:Jackollie|talk]]) 00:51, 19 December 2007 (UTC)

==The Last Guru Of Sikhs==
In the article it is written that '''it is believed''' that Guru Gobind Singh confered the title of Guru upon Guru Granth Sahib.And that '''this belief''' finds no mention in Adi Granth or Dasam Granth.I have some obections to the way it is written.
'''firstly''' a 'belief' is something that is held to be true by a group of people and may or may not be true.That Guru gobind Singh installed Guru Granth Sahib as the eternal guru of sikhs is not just a belief,it is a perpetual truth.It has to be understood that the sikh gurus did not formulate a 'municiple law' or rules for conducting life and disputes among their followers. They left that on the sikhs to decide that by way of '''gurmatta''' according to time and changes.Thay were flexible on the approach towards living.Guru Granth Sahib contains the teachings of Sikh Gurus and shows the path to salvation.It does not contains the laws or guidlines for Sikhs.
'''secondly''' the term '''Guru Maaneyo Granth''' was composed by the '''hazuri singhs ''' of Guru Gobind Singh after his departure from this earth.These '''hazuri singhs ( meaning one who is always in the presence of guru)''' were not ordinary mortals.They included the panj piaras and relatives of Guru Gobind Singh and sikhs who were dearer to him.They were highly learned men.Guru Granth Sahib Contains only the Hymns of Sikh Gurus.The work of sikhs is not included in it.
'''thirdly''' Sikhism should not be viewed through the eyes of a Muslim or Jew or a Christian.people of these religions have a codified law contained in their religious text unlike sikhism whose religious text does not contain laws.
A healthy debate is always good and removes many constraints.I hope the questionable sentences in the article are corrected sooner.[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 14:50, 22 December 2007 (UTC)

Waheguru Ji Ka Khalsa Waheguru Ji Ke Fateh
There is no last Guru for the Sikhs. Guru Gobin Singh Sahib appointed our Sri Guru Granth Sahib as our living Guru this subject heading should be changed to accuratly tell the truth as we have a living Guru.
Angad Singh Sikh activist
Waheguru Ji Ka Khalsa Waheguru Ji Ke Fateh  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/180.190.139.218|180.190.139.218]] ([[User talk:180.190.139.218|talk]]) 10:01, 23 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Request to add external link==
I'd like to add this link http://www.vam.ac.uk/collections/asia/asia_features/sikhism/index.html to the article. Do you have any objections? These pages give a broad history of the Sikh faith and show lots of objects and art work associated with Sikhism. [[User:VAwebteam|VAwebteam]] ([[User talk:VAwebteam|talk]]) 12:49, 23 December 2007 (UTC)

==Semi protected==
Wasn't the article semi-protected. What happened to that? I don't see the protected sign! [[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 05:07, 25 December 2007 (UTC)

==Sikhism==
Shouldn't that be the title? [[User:JTBX|JTBX]] ([[User talk:JTBX|talk]]) -Undated

==Edit warring==
If you want to make any major edit, then please discuss before doing so. You have suddenly started doing edits based on your own point of view.Please refrain from doing so.Don't fill this article with names of people who do not belong here. you can add their names in their respective articles. Stop undue POV EDITS on this article.THANKS!![[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 19:31, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
:Do not accuse me of [[WP:VAND|vandalism]] when you clearly do not even know what it is. I do not need to discuss an edit, when I'm rewriting the original POV that was in the article. The section was quite incomplete, as it did not even explain what Operation Blue Star was about. It also states that Operation Blue Star was initiated because of the government's accusations of inciting violence. This is not true. Blue Star was primarily based on the militant occupation in the Golden Temple. Also, your version only refers to the 1984 anti-Sikh riots, but fails to mention other Hindu-Sikh conflicts, in which Sikhs retaliated against Hindus. There was violence on both sides, but the Sikhs were hit especially hard. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 19:55, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
::Go and read some history books before writing on history facts.There was no hindu-sikh riots.Everyone knows that 1984 riots were congress sponsored. what makes you edit something you have no primary knowledge about. What are you sources - obviously some internet site.Wake up my friend.Face the reality.If you have any doubts about the reality than make sure that you visit the office of national human rights commission of india. You are welcome to re-write but without your additions. Your tweaks and minor edits are full of personal views[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 20:23, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
'''&quot;There was violence on both sides, but the Sikhs were hit especially hard&quot;'''. This is your mentality. your feelings for sikhs.your idea of hindu-Sikh relations.I don't need to say more.A person like you, no matter how intelligent, doesn't belong on wiki. [[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 20:36, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
:::When did I say I am not familiar with Operation Blue Star? Please, I have an extensive knowledge of Operation Blue Star. For crying out loud, I wrote the article on [[Bhindranwale]]! Also, you only referred to anti-Sikh riots, but there was also other Hindu-Sikh tensions, in which Sikhs retaliated against Hindus. You honestly think Sikhs didn't do anything in retaliation?? That's what I mentioned in the articles. It's one-sided to say that there were only anti-Sikh riots (and yes I know it was Congress-sponsored; it was backed by Gandhi's supporters), when there were also Sikh against Hindu violence. And please, my stuff comes from books. You can only find Sikh fundamentalist nonsense on the Internet, proclaiming that Bhindranwale was some hero. And don't make [[WP:NPA|personal attacks]]. There was violence on both sides, but Hindu against Sikh violence was far more devastating. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 20:37, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
:Why don't you back up your claims with govt. sources. List the places where violence occured between sikhs and hindus.The number of incidents.Reports from Govt. investigating agencies.Where are you sources.[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 20:42, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
::I never talked about violence in the article. I wrote that there were other Hindu-Sikh tensions, not including the anti-Sikh riots (which was not really orchestrated by Hindus, anyway...it was more political). &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 20:50, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
:::As for your Sikh against Hindu violence, see ''Global Terrorism'' by James and Brenda Lutz [http://books.google.com/books?id=dULlTAe_NwEC&amp;pg=PA76&amp;dq=Hindu+Sikh+tensions+after+Operation+Blue+Star&amp;ei=Iky3R8TKEpHCzASZ9-3KBQ&amp;sig=gzMCwKONdnP53nOveAnFcj844_Y#PPA77,M1 here]. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 20:55, 16 February 2008 (UTC)

:::Thanks for pointing me towards the link.But, going by it, the violence  appears to be govt. sponsored.Also spellings of Indira Gandhi are wrong.It also fails to mention the exact year when hundereds of militant groups sprang up. which was after Bhindranwala. Also where did he make an explicit demand for khalistan. Things like these are best left for politicians. People like us get a bad mouth out of it, sometimes burns too[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 21:10, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
::::A number of sources spell Gandhi as &quot;Ghandi&quot;. I don't know why, but that appears the case. Also, I pointed you to the link because it talks about the Sikh violence against Hindus after Operation Blue Star (how could you forget the airplane bombing?). As for Khalistan, I already removed that from the article. I know Bhindranwale's involvement with Khalistan is a bit clouded; it appears he endorsed it at one time, but he wasn't really the major proponent. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 21:24, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
::::: The airplane bombing was not against Hindus. It was directed against Govt. Also it was carried out by terrorists, and a terrorist does not belong to any religion. Also the canadian Govt. had questioned the role of RAW in that bombing. It is a vicious circle. i don't know if i can make an edit now or not. I will see and do waht i have to do tommorrow. I am tired. Good Day[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 21:41, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
::::::I guess that's a valid point. However, the book does state that there were tensions between the Sikh and Hindu communities. As for Air India Flight 182, the bombing was orchestrated by Babbar Khalsa, a Sikh terrorist group (to my knowledge, there doesn't appear to be any non-Sikhs in the group) that wants to form a separate state. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 21:53, 16 February 2008 (UTC)

Where did the tensions occur.You cannot just provide a ref. from a book. Also the book is about global terrorism, and a clash which is communal in nature is not covered under it. The author is not speclialised on this subject. 

The name of Indira Gandhi or anybody does not belong in article of sikhism. Please remove it. It is enough to state her as prime minister at that time. You provide no govt. sources on alleged hindu-sikh clash. Only a govt. source would be acceptable. Or an eye-witness account. This article is about sikhism and not operation blue star. If you want to add lenghty observations , you can do that in [[Operation Blue Star]] or [[Anti Sikh Riots]]. This article is about the religion, Sikhism. Is any mention has to be made, it should be of a small nature.[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 05:06, 17 February 2008 (UTC)
:Government source? Since when is the government the primary authority on any matter? Also, those actions (Blue Star and such) were of vital importance in modern Sikh history. My additions detail the conflict between Sikhs and Gandhi's Congress government. If this article is really about Sikhism only, then why do you have an entire section titled &quot;Political advancement&quot;. My additions are perfectly legitimate in the scope of this article. Also, the book cited is [[WP:RS|reliable source]]. Each terrorist conflict was examined and thoroughly analyzed as a case study. Also note that the book cites a number of other authoritative sources, exclusively detailing these events. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 05:30, 17 February 2008 (UTC)

To all editors: please refrain from making personal attacks. They are not pleasant to read, even if they are about another editor. I've removed the major attacks, and certain other incivil remarks that were made in this section of the talk page. 

In terms of the dispute, looking at this [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Sikhism&amp;diff=191939737&amp;oldid=191917230 recent-diff], While I agree with Nishkid64 that further explanation of Operation Blue Star is helpful, the referencing should be more aggressive. Even if the source is the same, almost every sentence should have a citation in this section. Alternatively, tightening the expression of the article would no doubt, help.

Despite all this, I'm not sure if this article currently qualifies as an FA, so might sooner or later, reassess this article just to be sure. [[User:Ncmvocalist|Ncmvocalist]] ([[User talk:Ncmvocalist|talk]]) 05:59, 17 February 2008 (UTC)

:thats it! That is why there are so many editors are going haywire to edit it. To get it off FA.Go ahead.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ajjay|contribs]]) 06:11, 17 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
User NishKid64 must answer this
*Why  the govt. sources of a Democratic country like India are not trustable. 
**Read [[WP:RS]]. Scholarly works, like books, are clearly acceptable. I never said govt. sources are not unnacceptable. I only asked why you considered the government the primary source, when there's many scholarly works covered by noted historians and other individuals.
*Why is he using books and not The judicial process and police action, which is first handed.
**Material on Wikipedia is usually attributed to books or other scholarly works. First hand accounts are fine, but they need to be relevant. There are no specific details of incidents in the article, so first hand accounts are not necessary. 
*His claim regarding hindu-sikh riots is vague and does not cite the reports of Law enforcing Agencies, of the place where it occured.
**I said there were Hindu-Sikh tensions. Tension means a strained relationship. This is definitely the case between the Sikhs and Hindus, after Blue Star and the Gandhi assassination. The book mentions these tensions, thus corroborating my statement.
*Is he stating that he has no faith in the Judicial Authority of India, and it has no value.
**You have been misrepresenting everything I have said, and now you're making accusations. What does anything I say have to do with the Indian judicial system?
*He should provide the names of places and subsequent police reports , wherever the clashes occured.
**Why? You said this article isn't supposed to go into specifics. Police reports and places of clashes are very specific.
*Why is he unduly lenghting the section when seperate aricles exist for the matter.
**Why is length a problem? I am adding material that is [[WP:NPOV|neutral]]. The previous versions are either biased (glorifying Bhindranwale, for example) or they were incomplete (no explanation as to what caused Gandhi to order Operation Blue Star; you just stated that the govt. accused Bhindranwale of inciting violence). &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 07:00, 17 February 2008 (UTC)
When he says that the article is about Sikhism and political advencement should not be there, he does not understand the nature of the article. He should not be making it unduly lenghty and include politics of Indira govt.[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 06:42, 17 February 2008 (UTC)
*Politics of Gandhi's government? Blue Star is an army operation, which resulted in the anti-Sikh riots. Without this information, people are going to ask what cause these riots. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 07:00, 17 February 2008 (UTC)
 *In which Sikhs retaliated against Hindus
 *There was violence on both sides, but the Sikhs were hit especially hard
 *I have an extensive knowledge of Operation Blue Star
 *(and yes I know it was Congress-sponsored; it was backed by Gandhi's supporters), 
 *I never talked about violence in the article
 *my stuff comes from books
 *but Hindu against Sikh violence was far more devastating
 *I wrote that there were other Hindu-Sikh tensions, not including the anti-Sikh riots (which   was not really orchestrated by Hindus, anyway...it was more political). 
 *I know Bhindranwale's involvement with Khalistan is a bit clouded; it appears he endorsed it at one time, but he wasn't really the major proponent
 *However, the book does state that there were tensions between the Sikh and Hindu communities
 *Government source? Since when is the government the primary authority on any matter?
 *My additions detail the conflict between Sikhs and Gandhi's Congress government
 *Also note that the book cites a number of other authoritative sources, exclusively detailing these events

These are some of the obsevations by Nishkid. You can read and know who is right or wrong. i think there is a malicious move to get sikhism from FA as is corroborated by ( [[User:Ncmvocalist|Ncmvocalist]] ) 

NishKid if you read my edits to the article  ( where i sated that the present state is neutral) , you will find all the information.I don't know you motive and reason to harp on blue Star with lenghty mentions in Sikhism when the same can be done in [[Operation Blue Star]], to which there is inter-wiki link.[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 07:07, 17 February 2008 (UTC)

 *I never said govt. sources are not unnacceptable
 *There are no specific details of incidents in the article, so first hand accounts are not necessary
 *I said there were Hindu-Sikh tensions. Tension means a strained relationship
 *Why? You said this article isn't supposed to go into specifics. Police reports and places of clashes are very specific
 *you just stated that the govt. accused Bhindranwale of inciting violence). 
 *Politics of Gandhi's government? Blue Star is an army operation
User NishKid is indeed very confused. He must also furnish the govt. report where Bhindranwala was found guilty of violence by a court of Law. Unless convicted by a court, he remains accused and according to Indian law , benefit of doubt goes to the accused.[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 07:19, 17 February 2008 (UTC)
:I'm going to set matters straight, because it appears you fail to see the issues with your edit. Bhindranwale was arrested by police for his suspected involvement in Jagat Narain's death in 1981. Operation Blue Star came three years later, after Bhindranwale and his armed followers barricaded themselves inside the Golden Temple. It was not a result of the government's accusations of inciting violence. There is no transition to Gandhi's assassination. You mention Operation Blue Star and then you go straight to her assassination. Articles are supposed to be thorough. They should be clicking wikilinks to find more information about a particular subject, not because they are absolutely confused what the relevance of the subject is in the context. I provided a short description about Blue Star and the result. I then went to the assassination of Gandhi by her Sikh bodyguards. After that, I wrote that the chain of events led to the anti-Sikh riots and Hindu-Sikh conflicts (it's common knowledge that there have been tensions between Hindus and Sikhs in Punjab; these events just furthered these tensions). &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 07:52, 17 February 2008 (UTC)

&quot;Bhindranwale was arrested by police for his suspected involvement in Jagat Narain's death in 1981. Operation Blue Star came three years later, after Bhindranwale and his armed followers barricaded themselves inside the Golden Temple.&quot;
:What happaned inbetween

::The thoroughness can be explained in [[Operation Blue Star]] , not in Sikhism. 
::*Indira Gandhi's name should not be mentioned. Her role is also equally controversial. You can mention her as the prime minister of the country.
::*The descriptive phrase is too long. It should be short and not long, as is in it's present state.
::*Bhindranwale was arrested, but released by court.(no need to mention)
::*He did not fortify Golden Temple because of this Murder.(-SAME-)
::*He was accused / Suspected / charged by Govt. for violence in Punjab. (-SAME-)
::*You can say there was army action against sikh extremists, who were held responsible for violence in punjab, resulting in operation blue Star followed by assassination of prime minister and anti sikh riots and unconfirmed reports of sikh Hindu clashes as aftermath.[http://books.google.com/books?id=FXRZ1X8BANIC&amp;pg=PA354&amp;dq=indira+gandhi+bhindranwale+Operation+blue+star&amp;output=html&amp;sig=XfN32818dOJ1KdzDE082ESQf1x8][http://books.google.com/books?id=VNs_vX7EGUoC&amp;pg=PA133&amp;dq=indira+gandhi+bhindranwale+Operation+blue+star&amp;output=html&amp;sig=BdtEkWejaEG-RwKDvbU8azP7mlE]
[http://books.google.com/books?id=uLQbAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=indira+gandhi+bhindranwale+Operation+blue+star&amp;dq=indira+gandhi+bhindranwale+Operation+blue+star&amp;output=html&amp;pgis=1]

The issue is more complex than you think. And still going strong. An impartial detailed analysis would take a long time to come. Being an administrator you have more probable cause for deciding about an article than me, now it is upto you how to put it in article , which is about sikh Gurus and their religion.[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 09:03, 17 February 2008 (UTC)

Please don't misrepresent what I have said Ajjay. As the main member of the assessment team for WikiProject India, and with or without this edit warring, I could not automatically see (on a cursory look) how this article qualifies as an FA, unlike many other FAs. However, as there might be an error, I will reassess the article at a later date formally, to ensure that it is up to the standards of what FAs should be under this project. This does not necessarily mean that this article is not a FA, nor that the grade will be stripped. Please refrain from making any further misrepresentations, personal attacks, or the like against or about any editor at Wikipedia, as this may result in you being blocked from editing. I would suggest all editors on this talk page read and follow the tag that is placed at the top of the page about keeping a cool head. Best wishes in improving the article - [[User:Ncmvocalist|Ncmvocalist]] ([[User talk:Ncmvocalist|talk]]) 18:19, 17 February 2008 (UTC)

==Muslim==
Somebody put up &quot;Sikhism was made to kill Muslims&quot; and &quot;If it wasnt for Sikhs India would be known as Hindustan&quot; --[[User:AlexanderTheGreatSikh|AlexanderTheGreatSikh]] ([[User talk:AlexanderTheGreatSikh|talk]]) 23:01, 14 April 2008 (UTC)
that my friend is NOT true. it isnt true because sikhism was made just like many other religion, because they believed another god. but it just ended up that the muslims and sikh's in than than sri guru gobind singh ji's time period that there was severe war.nothing else.:|--[[User:Manvirkaurcheema|Manvirkaurcheema]] ([[User talk:Manvirkaurcheema|talk]]) 15:53, 2 February 2010 (UTC)

==ISI propaganda==
No there were no sikh-hindu clashes anywhere, all violence was between exteremists and govt forces [[User:Jon Ascton|Jon Ascton]] ([[User talk:Jon Ascton|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment was added at 03:36, 7 February 2009 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Problem with reincarnation==
See the page on 'reincarnation' for full article... it is quoted in this page under the Sikhism section: '''Sikhism''' &quot;''In Sikhism reincarnation is totally rejected.[11]''&quot; I am confused... because in this article it seems to be that reincarnation is a fundamnetal belief of Sikhism. Can anyone help? [[User:Hurleyc2008|Hurleyc2008]] ([[User talk:Hurleyc2008|talk]]) 11:38, 15 April 2008 (UTC)
&lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Hurleyc2008|Hurleyc2008]] ([[User talk:Hurleyc2008|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hurleyc2008|contribs]]) 11:29, 15 April 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:(conflicted) The frase has got a reference, so it may be real. [[User:Mojska|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red;font-family:verdana;&quot;&gt;'''MOJSKA'''&lt;/span&gt;]] [[Special:Contributions/Mojska|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:verdana;color:black;&quot;&gt;'''666'''&lt;/span&gt;]] - [[User talk:Mojska|&lt;small&gt;''Leave a message here''&lt;/small&gt;]] 11:31, 15 April 2008 (UTC)
::Sikhism rejects re-incarnation of God or of God in human form or any other manner. It believes in re-birth of humans, but that can be changed with grace of Guru, a person becomes free from all bondages of karma, destiny etc.[[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 13:22, 15 April 2008 (UTC)
Needs expert opinion i think. [[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 13:28, 15 April 2008 (UTC)
:Maybe something is to be found [http://www.allaboutsikhs.com/articles/whence-to-where-and-in-between.html here]. Austerlitz -- [[Special:Contributions/88.75.201.69|88.75.201.69]] ([[User talk:88.75.201.69|talk]]) 19:52, 17 April 2008 (UTC)
==Problem with reincarnation==
See the page on 'reincarnation' for full article... it is quoted in this page under the Sikhism section: '''Sikhism''' &quot;''In Sikhism reincarnation is totally rejected.[11]''&quot; I am confused... because in this article it seems to be that reincarnation is a fundamnetal belief of Sikhism. Can anyone help? [[User:Hurleyc2008|Hurleyc2008]] ([[User talk:Hurleyc2008|talk]]) 11:38, 15 April 2008 (UTC)
&lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Hurleyc2008|Hurleyc2008]] ([[User talk:Hurleyc2008|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Hurleyc2008|contribs]]) 11:29, 15 April 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:(conflicted) The frase has got a reference, so it may be real. [[User:Mojska|&lt;span style=&quot;color:red;font-family:verdana;&quot;&gt;'''MOJSKA'''&lt;/span&gt;]] [[Special:Contributions/Mojska|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:verdana;color:black;&quot;&gt;'''666'''&lt;/span&gt;]] - [[User talk:Mojska|&lt;small&gt;''Leave a message here''&lt;/small&gt;]] 11:31, 15 April 2008 (UTC)
::Sikhism rejects re-incarnation of God or of God in human form or any other manner. It believes in re-birth of humans, but that can be changed with grace of Guru, a person becomes free from all bondages of karma, destiny etc.[[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 13:22, 15 April 2008 (UTC)
Needs expert opinion i think. [[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 13:28, 15 April 2008 (UTC)
:Maybe something is to be found [http://www.allaboutsikhs.com/articles/whence-to-where-and-in-between.html here]. Austerlitz -- [[Special:Contributions/88.75.201.69|88.75.201.69]] ([[User talk:88.75.201.69|talk]]) 19:52, 17 April 2008 (UTC)

Sikhs believe in nothing but (Lord)TRUTH ( encompassing all GOD/Allah / Crist etc). 

===Sayth Nanak1===
The very first two lines of Adi Granth (Sti Gur Bani) outright reject Reincarnation.

* '''''Ikk O Angkarrrrrrrrrrrr stinam krqa purkhu nirbhau nirvyyr.akal muurqi ajoni syyBhng gurprsadi. Jpu. aadi schu, jugadi schu, hyy bhee schu, nanak hose bhe schu '''''(gurmukhi script using english alphabet) 

''An Eternal TRUTH Crafter's (TRUTH's) True profile is.....(TRUTH &amp; followers of nothing but TRUTH has been defined here) 'Creative TRUTH &amp; fearless friend of even enemies of TRUTH.Thou are TRUE Eternal Idol (made up of nothing but TRUTHs) never to reincarnate. Thou are Self Realised through Thy True Language of TRUTHs. Thy Name was, had been, is here &amp; now at this very moment &amp; will ever remain TRUTH.''      

===Sayth Nanak2===
5th Sikh Guru(Nanak) says in Aadi Granth( Sti Gur Bani / True Ideas' Language)

* '''''&quot;kirqam nam kthyy tyry jyhva stinam tyra bla purbla....&quot; '''''(Gurmukhi Script)

'' &quot; This (currupt) tongue is habituated to parrot Thy false names.Thy One &amp; only One True Name is TRUTH (all other are Thy False Names)&quot;'' 

Needless to say that imagining TRUTH(God) to reincarnate or otherwise is absurd.--[[User:AmiBalRaj|AmiBalRaj]] ([[User talk:AmiBalRaj|talk]]) 10:45, 13 May 2009 (UTC)

==Caste in Sikhism?==
I am a punjabi living in Canada and the section about marriages within the Sikh community sparked my interest.  Living within a large Sikh community I always thought that there is caste within Sikhism.  Although all of the Gurus did not beleive in caste it does exist.  There are jatts, khatris, darjis,ramghari, rajputs etc yet the article claims that &quot;Sikhs marry when they are of a sufficient age (child marriage is taboo), and without regard for the future spouse's caste or descent.&quot; I know that Amrit Dhari Sikhs do not beleive in caste (as far as I know they maintain their last names as Singh) but for the rest of the Sikh population it seems like caste (although not as apparent as Hinduism) really does exist. [[User:Unity717|Unity717]] ([[User talk:Unity717|talk]]) 04:46, 23 April 2008 (UTC)
:Spend some more time with you sikh friends who are not prejudiced. And ''jatts, khatris, darjis,ramghari, rajputs etc'' are ethnic groups and not caste groups.[[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 06:49, 23 April 2008 (UTC)

Actually you are wrong, these are castes. Plain and simple. Even though Sikhism is against Caste, it is still practiced, nothing wrong in admitting what is happening even if its wrong. But to just deny it with a wrong statement and pourposely misguiding is wrong. [[User:Gurkhaboy|Gorkhali]] ([[User talk:Gurkhaboy|talk]]) 06:39, 28 March 2009 (UTC)

:Besides if you would like to go in theory, then only an amritdhari sikh is a [true] sikh. Rest are not [speaking theoretically], whatever they like to think. [[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 07:13, 23 April 2008 (UTC)
:There are indeed castes in the Sikh community. You are very much right correct. In fact, the caste system in India appears in all religions in some form or another. What we need to do now is to find [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] that can support this fact about Sikhism. You can [[WP:BB|be bold]] and remove that wrong statement yourself if you so desire. &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[User:DaGizza|Gizza]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:DaGizza|Discuss]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;'' &lt;sup&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/DaGizza|&amp;#169;]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 06:09, 23 April 2008 (UTC)
::The castes in some sikh communities is already mentioned, in the section, [Sikh People]. [[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 06:49, 23 April 2008 (UTC)
Shalimer, I did not intend to portray my Sikh friends as &quot;prejudiced&quot; since they really aren't. In Hinduism khatris and darjis appear as part of the caste system. Ethnicity is something totally different...the wikipedia article about ethnicity claims that ethnicity is based upon ancestry or geneology whereas caste is not based on ethnicity rather on social status (wikipedia article on &quot;caste&quot;).  Sikhism, though a different religion than Hinduism, really does have its roots in Hinduism so it is no surprise that some of the characteristics of Hinduism have carried on into Sikhism.  Caste does exist in Sikhism although it might be to a lesser extent than in Hinduism.  If it didn't exist in Sikhism, young Sikh people could marry anyone who fell under the category &quot;Sikh&quot; YET this does not happen. Also, your statement about Amritdhari Sikhs as &quot;true&quot; Sikhs is quite interesting as well...that is a judgmental statement that is incorrect and disrespectful to the &quot;rest.&quot;  Why is an Amritdhari Sikh better than the rest...even if it is theoretically?  ([[User:Unity717|Unity717]] ([[User talk:Unity717|talk]]) 00:15, 24 April 2008 (UTC))

I started to conduct a search online about sikhism and caste and I found that even matrimonial sites list different groups of Sikhs.  There seems to be quite a division between people who believe there is a caste system versus people who think there is no caste system.  Why do people care about sub groups (a.k.a. caste) when they are about to get married? There must be some type of social implications for a Jatt marrying a non-Jatt for example...if there wasn't, people wouldn't specify which group they belonged to while skimming matrimonial sites. ([[User:Unity717|Unity717]] ([[User talk:Unity717|talk]]) 01:10, 24 April 2008 (UTC))
:Go and read some good books on Sikhism. I am not a preacher. Besides if you want to talk about hinduism and sikhism there is a seperate talk page [[Hinduism and Sikhism]]. When you talk about caste system in India, there is a seperate artcle as well [[Caste system in India]] . And you really amaze me when you say ''jatts'' and ''rajputs'' are not ethnic people, see [[Jat people]] [[Rajput]]. About matrimonial ads, they are about ''people'' who want to get married and not on ''Sikhisms'' practices, it is by a group of people, which does not apply to whole community. Besides prefference for getting maried to a particular ethnic group (caste??) is a matter of choice, not related to religion. When you talk of caste it goes deeper. Getting married according to choices wont make sikhism a caste based religion.  For example, hinduism is also called ''varna ashram Dharam''. Do you know what varna is see [[Varna_in_Hinduism]] and [[Jāti]]. And this time don't search online, read some good books such as [Encyclopedia of Sikhism by Harbans Singh ISBN-10: 8173802041] [[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 03:09, 24 April 2008 (UTC)

Shalimer, since it seems as if you have alot of knowledge about ethnicity and caste within Sikhism could you hook me up with some other resources to check out? Although you may be correct in saying that jatt/rajputs are ethnic groups most mainstream Sikh people see these groups as caste groups. What we need to think about is that the theory behind Sikhism says one thing yet most Sikhs follow/do/believe another thing.  Why the discrepency between theory and reality?  Theoretically, won't reality eventually shape/change theory? If someone walks around Canada - especially high density areas like British Columbia (Surrey) and Ontario (Brampton)- the reality of what is being practiced is actually quite far from what the Gurus wanted.  This topic is very interesting to me so thanks for the great convo! ([[User:Unity717|Unity717]] ([[User talk:Unity717|talk]]) 03:52, 24 April 2008 (UTC)) 

:I dont have a lot of knowledge, only some of it. If the theory is one and practise another, it means those have deviated from the path of gurus [mentioned in article in section {Sikh People} in end]. I would recommend 'The Sikhs in History' by Sangat Singh ISBN-10 8172052758. You might find the reason why there is a difference between theory and practise and whether it can really be considered as such and the reasons. Plus the book uses lot of references from previous historians. [[User:Shalimer|Shalimer]] ([[User talk:Shalimer|talk]]) 04:38, 24 April 2008 (UTC)
 
:In all of India different ethnic groups tend to also be different castes and vice versa. Within each ethnic group, there may be sub-castes, but that is another matter. Because there is a strong correlation between caste and ethnicity, they can almost be considered synonyms. It is also probably why all the non-Hindu religions still have the caste although to a lesser degree. &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[User:DaGizza|Gizza]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:DaGizza|Discuss]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;'' &lt;sup&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/DaGizza|&amp;#169;]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 04:16, 24 April 2008 (UTC)

:Well an interesting fact that I know from [[real life]] experience is that particular Sikh castes would prefer marrying the same caste but Hindus than different Sikh caste. For example, Khatri Sikhs would prefer marrying to Khatri Hindus than to other Sikhs. Not sure is this phenomenon has been written about in any books though. &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[User:DaGizza|Gizza]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;''&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:DaGizza|Discuss]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;'' &lt;sup&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/DaGizza|&amp;#169;]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 01:46, 24 April 2008 (UTC)

==Information to be inserted?==
*[http://www.sikhsangat.com/index.php?showtopic=1007 SikhSangat] :Austerlitz -- [[Special:Contributions/88.72.3.48|88.72.3.48]] ([[User talk:88.72.3.48|talk]]) 19:55, 8 May 2008 (UTC)

==How is this image inappropriate?==
[[User:OneBlood30|OneBlood30]] has twice removed this image: ''&lt;nowiki&gt;[[Image:Sikh Family cropped.jpg|thumb|A Sikh family, the boys wearing the traditional [[Dastar]]]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' ([[:Image:Sikh Family cropped.jpg|see image]]) from the article, claiming that it was not approved, and then that it was not appropriate. The copyright tags appear to be in order, and I do not see what could be considered inappropriate about it. I do not know much abut Sikhism, is it somehow offensive to Sikhs in a way that is not apparent to non-Sikhs? Because the reasoning is not clear, it needs to be discussed instead of just removed. --[[User:Icarus3|Icarus]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User_talk:Icarus3|Hi!]])&lt;/sup&gt; 00:03, 9 May 2008 (UTC)

==Minor edit==
I have made minor changes in 'philosophy and teachings' section. If there is a problem please respond here first. [[User:Turniplp|Turniplp]] ([[User talk:Turniplp|talk]]) 15:23, 12 May 2008 (UTC)

==Killing muslims==
Someone put sikhism was for killing muslims. That is not true. I am a sikh and I love muslims. [[User:Matigues|Matigues]] ([[User talk:Matigues|talk]]) 22:00, 10 June 2008 (UTC)

==Correction==
Someone please correct this appalling act of vandalism (on [[Sikhism]]): &quot;''..Diwali (also known as bandī chōḍ divas)..''&quot;  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jasvinde|Jasvinde]] ([[User talk:Jasvinde|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jasvinde|contribs]]) 13:27, 20 June 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Help needed for article on [[Sikh Rajputs]]==
Someone put a tag on &quot;[[Sikh Rajputs]]&quot; article that it will be deleted in five days etc., this article can not be deleted as Sikh Rajputs exist and most claims made in the article are true as well known to local Indians in Punjab only the need is that some interested and knowledgeable editors with access to proper history books etc. can eventually come forward and develop the article properly in time, quoting credible sources. Foreign born and raised editors with no direct local Indian knowledge are requested not to vandalize it as per their own fastly held thoughts and beliefs. Thanks [[User:Atulsnischal|Atulsnischal]] ([[User talk:Atulsnischal|talk]]) 08:18, 30 August 2008 (UTC)

==editsemiprotected==
{{tlx|editsemiprotected}}
*&quot;Realisation of Truth is higher than all else. Higher still is truthful living&quot;.
*&quot;Realization of Truth is higher than all else. Higher still is truthful living&quot;.

In English, it is more common to use the spelling latter spelling of realization. I AM PROUD TO BR SIKH  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/72.140.1.128|72.140.1.128]] ([[User talk:72.140.1.128|talk]]) 13:51, 6 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:{{notdone}}, as detailed at [[WP:ENGVAR]] Wikipedia does not have a preference between American English (-ize) and British English (-ise) for topics like this that don't have any particular tie to either country - we simply keep it consistent within the article, and don't swap between the two. This article seems to be entirely written in British English (barring one instance of an -ize word which I shall change shortly for consistency) so I think we should leave it as &quot;Realisation&quot;. Thanks for the suggestion anyway! ~ &lt;font color=&quot;#228b22&quot;&gt;[[User:Mazca|'''m'''a'''z'''c'''a''']]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Mazca|'''t''']] | [[Special:Contributions/Mazca|'''c''']]&lt;/sup&gt; 12:22, 7 September 2008 (UTC)
::Sikhism does have a particular tie to India, which uses British English.&amp;mdash;[[User:Chowbok|&lt;span style=&quot;background:black; color:white; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;Chowbok&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Chowbok|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black;&quot;&gt;☠&lt;/span&gt;]] 09:52, 7 March 2011 (UTC)

==Guru-da-Gaddi==
Someone may want to take a look at the new [[Guru-da-Gaddi]] article and see if it can be clarified. Not sure if it should be mentioned in this article. Also, I'm not sure the dates match up with what's in other articles. —[[User:KCinDC|KCinDC]] ([[User talk:KCinDC|talk]]) 18:28, 20 October 2008 (UTC)
:That article is wrong, I'm going to see if it can be deleted--[[User:Profitoftruth85|Profitoftruth85]] ([[User talk:Profitoftruth85|talk]]) 01:15, 8 March 2011 (UTC)

==Alcohol==
All my googling tells me that adherents to Sikhism must avoid the drinking of alcohol. I can't find a reference to this in the article (unless &quot;find&quot; isn't working). Is it true? Can someone who knows please add it? [[User:Kayman1uk|Kayman1uk]] ([[User talk:Kayman1uk|talk]]) 08:54, 29 October 2008 (UTC)
&lt;font color=Blue&gt;mlwr bwxI Bgq rivdws jI kI]&lt;/font Color&gt;

Malaar, The Word Of The Devotee Ravi Daas Jee:
&lt; siqgur pRswid ]
An Upright PenPallllllllllll Now writes further through the grace of SatiGurBani

&lt;font color=Blue&gt;nwgr jnW myrI jwiq ibiKAwq cMmwrM ]]&lt;/font Color&gt;

O humble townspeople, I am obviously just a shoemaker.

&lt;font color=Blue&gt;irdY rwm goibMd gun swrM ]1] rhwau ]]&lt;/font Color&gt;

In my heart I cherish the Glories of the Lord, the Lord of the Universe. ||1||Pause||

&lt;font color=Blue&gt;sursrI sll ik(r)q bwrunI ry sMq jn krq nhI pwnµ ]]&lt;/font Color&gt;

''Even if &lt;font color=Red&gt;'''wine'''&lt;/font color=Red&gt; is made from the water of the Ganges, O Saints, do not drink it.

&lt;font color=Blue&gt;surw ApivqR nq Avr jl ry sursrI imlq nih hoie Awnµ ]1]&lt;/font Color&gt;

''This &lt;font color=Red&gt;'''wine'''&lt;/font color=Red&gt;, and any other polluted water which mixes with the Ganges, is not separate from it. ||1||

&lt;font color=Blue&gt;qr qwir ApivqR kir mwnIAY ry jYsy kwgrw krq bIcwrM ]]&lt;/font Color&gt;

''The palmyra palm tree is considered impure, and so its leaves are considered impure as well.

&lt;font color=Blue&gt;Bgiq Bwgauqu ilKIAY iqh aUpry pUjIAY kir nmskwrM ]2]]&lt;/font Color&gt;

''But if devotional prayers are written on paper made from its leaves, then people bow in reverence and worship before it. ||2||1296

&lt;font color=Blue&gt;myrI jwiq kut bWFlw For FovMqw inqih bwnwrsI Aws pwsw ]]&lt;/font Color&gt;

''It is my occupation to prepare and cut leather; each day, I carry the carcasses out of the city.1297

&lt;font color=Blue&gt;Ab ibpR prDwn iqih krih fMfauiq qyry nwm srxwie rivdwsu dwsw ]3]1]]&lt;/font Color&gt;

''Now, the important Brahmins of the city bow down before me; Ravi Daas, Your slave, seeks the Sanctuary of Your Name. ||3||1||  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:AmiBalRaj|AmiBalRaj]] ([[User talk:AmiBalRaj|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/AmiBalRaj|contribs]]) 11:44, 13 May 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Across the World==
Sikhs lived in India but have spread across the world.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.14.230.131|92.14.230.131]] ([[User talk:92.14.230.131|talk]]) 17:51, 2 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== why the animosity? ==

I was reading this article today and I think it has been edited quite well but I wonder why it is such a big deal to make a connection between sikhism and hinduism and islam? Sikhism began with Guru Nanakji - he was born a hindu so it is obvious that some of his beliefs would be linked with his upbringing. Most religions originate and begin by a person or a group of people who choose a different path. Why is it so hard to understand that Sikhism also has roots from another religion or religions? Understanding this doesn't mean that Sikhism is any less of a religion. It is a great religion that is unique but shares qualities with other religions as well. [[User:Unity717|Unity717]] ([[User talk:Unity717|talk]]) 05:41, 25 February 2009 (UTC)

Its called insecurity. Any proud and knowlegable Sikh knows that its obvious that Sikhsim will have links and origins within Hinduism since that was the ancestral faith of all the Gurus, however, unlike the Christians who have no problem accepting Jewish roots and influences from the ancient religions of Europe, it will only come with time that people in India will realize that there is nothing wrong with accepting connections with an older religion or your ancestral religion, and neither does it lessen the importance of the religion that has stemmed out of it. Its just plain and simple insecurity and ignorance, and also political agendas with no regard for the Gurus teachings or their history. Makes you wonder why its called Har-Mandir, or the Gurus call themselves Gurus....etc etc etc....nothing wrong with having ancient roots, however some people will never realize the wisdom. 

[[User:Gurkhaboy|Gorkhali]] ([[User talk:Gurkhaboy|talk]]) 06:40, 28 March 2009 (UTC)

Sir,

* Sikhism does not believe in any xyz Religion. It believes in nothing but One religion (Lord)TRUTH for all humans. Sikh faith encompasses the universe &amp; the universes beyond. e.g. Sikhs will support beard because beard is a (Lord)TRUTH given Truth.  

* Nothing but ''''''Language of True Thoughts'''''' leading to 'TRUTH alias True God alias True Guru alias True Mother alias True Father alias True Relatives alias True Friends alias True Politicians alias All True objects alias every True thing ....is the Religion Sikhs believe in. 

* '''''True Language of True Thoughts''''' leading to Lord (TRUTH) was, had been, is here &amp; now at this very moment  &amp; will ever remain the faith of '''Khalsa''' (Sikhs). The Term 'Khalsa' itself means Flawless Human being who dwells in the realm of (Lord)TRUTH reflecting &amp; radiating Thy virtues for Humanity to emulate.  

Seeing Sikhism through the prism of non Sikh faiths makes no relevant sense no where. There is One &amp; Only One way of Understanding 'Sikhi' (That is how Sikhs would like their faith to be socially known, in stead of through the anglicized term 'Sikhism'. It rhymes with Nazism &amp; may be with some more  ‘isms’, not really in good taste) .It is by becoming  a Sikh by  Publicly Owning Thy Name……..

'''...Khalsa  ‘Jpu’ Singh....''' 
  
Trying to establish links between any entities in a traditional scholarly way in context of ‘Sikhi’ is futile.  

===Ordains True Thoughts’ Language===
*	Never ever get entangled in fruitless discussions.

*	Do not do things which need not be done.  

*	Listen to everyone but speak nothing but Thy Name (True Thoughts) 

*       Believe in nothing but 'Language of True Thoughts' which leads one to True Humans.

Unlike non Sikh faiths there is nothing really to understand about Sikhi. Sikhi has to be lived through to understand it. It is not possible otherwise. Grammar of True Thoughts' Language  formally documented in One &amp; Only One Scripture of Sikhs is popularly addressed by Sikhs as 'Stigur Granth Sahib'. The Language of Humanity alias (Lord) TRUTH need to be learned, 
Like any language by rigrious practice through Thinking, Speaking,  Singing, Listening to, Believing in, Discussing, Sharing &amp; Finally Documenting for generations to catch on to it with ease. 

Through the grace of Thy '''True Thoughts' Language''' this trivia bit PenPal has tried to humbly submit Thy (not my) thoughts &amp; share them with humanity. Since yours Truly owns nothing but Thy Name, the onus of slipups in this writing goes to non one but Thou (TRUTH)... ha! ha! ha! .     

Hope this helps !   

An Upright PenPalllllllllllllll Creative Khalsa --[[User:AmiBalRaj|AmiBalRaj]] ([[User talk:AmiBalRaj|talk]]) 12:56, 13 May 2009 (UTC) Singh NirV”r ‘Jpu’

== Current events in Punjab and Austria. ==

A user, [[user talk:Morbid Fairy]], whose posting reminds me strongly of [[user talk:Satanoid]], made this change at [[Sikh extremism]].

[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Sikh_extremism&amp;diff=292326667&amp;oldid=292319562 Murder in Austria, Riots in Punjab.]

While it needs a copyedit, it might be worth including in Wikipedia, but it does not have a place in the article about Sikh separatist extremism.[[User:Sinneed|- sinneed]] ([[User talk:Sinneed|talk]]) 23:59, 25 May 2009 (UTC)

==Fifth-largest religion?==

Is Sikhism definitely the fifth-largest religion in the world? If you click on &quot;fifth-largest&quot; you're then taken the [[Major religious groups]] page which looks as though it's suggesting that Judaism is bigger with 10-20 vs. 12-25 million. I appreciate that the range leaves room for ambiguity; with a top estimate value for Sikhism and bottom estimate for Judaism, Sikhism would be bigger (as the source suggests), but with such ambiguity should it be explicitly stated that it is the fifth-biggest? Especially on a feature-quality page. Perhaps the figures on that page just need altering or perhaps it should be reworded such as &quot;is widely regarded as the fifth-largest organized religion in the world&quot;. [[User:Gul e|Gul e]] ([[User talk:Gul e|talk]]) 22:35, 21 July 2009 (UTC)

:* [https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/XX.html US CIA &quot;world fact book&quot; (caveat)]- &quot;Christians 33.32% (of which Roman Catholics 16.99%, Protestants 5.78%, Orthodox 3.53%, Anglicans 1.25%), Muslims 21.01%, Hindus 13.26%, Buddhists 5.84%, Sikhs 0.35%, Jews 0.23%, Baha'is 0.12%, other religions 11.78%, non-religious 11.77%, atheists 2.32% (2007 est.)&quot;
:* [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-78815875.html Wisconsin State Journal 2001]
:* [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-91566938.html &quot;The Book Report&quot; 2002] Looks like 5th.[[User:Sinneed|- sinneed]] ([[User talk:Sinneed|talk]]) 23:52, 21 July 2009 (UTC)
:* [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-79428814.html The Virginian-Pilot (Norfolk, VA) 2001]
:* [http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=DM&amp;p_theme=dm&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0ED3DB7A9CEE124F&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM Dallas Morning News 1999]
:* [http://www.newsweek.com/id/160078 Newsweek 2008]
Reality is all numbers about religions are extremely blurry, as they rely on opinions... if nothing else they rely on the claims of the individual.[[User:Sinneed|- sinneed]] ([[User talk:Sinneed|talk]]) 00:22, 22 July 2009 (UTC)

== Should this page be semi-protected??? ==

This page along with other pages like [[sikh]] and [[List of famous sikhs]] were tried to be vandalised in past few weeks by unregistered users. Many honerable users reverted the edits. So can this page be put on semi-protection??--[[User:Migelot|&lt;font color=&quot;forestgreen&quot;&gt;'''Migelot'''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Migelot|&lt;font color=&quot;Navy&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;'''Talk to me!'''&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 11:37, 23 December 2009 (UTC)

== [[Holidays]]... ==

...are not mentioned on this page. Warmest Regards, :)--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[user:thecurran|thecurran]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; [[user talk:thecurran|Speak your mind]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Special:Contributions/thecurran|my past]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 16:02, 24 December 2009 (UTC)

== Shouldn't their be a section that explains the links and relationship with Hinduism? ==

I tried putting that and it got taken away. [[Special:Contributions/71.105.87.54|71.105.87.54]] ([[User talk:71.105.87.54|talk]]) 08:22, 22
 January 2010 (UTC)

:: And no one is helping here on this. [[Special:Contributions/71.105.87.54|71.105.87.54]] ([[User talk:71.105.87.54|talk]]) 06:11, 1 February 2010 (UTC)
::: Ther are links to other articles. Regards--[[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;Sikh-&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;History&lt;/em&gt;]] 08:51, 3 February 2010 (UTC)

== Question in Second Paragraph ==
* Does anyone know why the word &quot;MAYA&quot; appears in parentheses in the second paragraph?  Is this a term of art that perhaps could be defined or cross-linked?  Or, is this misplaced vandalism?  Context does not provide any clues.  Thanks.  [[User:Saebvn|Saebvn]] ([[User talk:Saebvn|talk]]) 23:16, 15 September 2010 (UTC)

::It is indeed defined, and an important concept in Sikhism; see ''[[Maya (illusion)|Māyā]]''.  Not vandalism, but perhaps the &quot;ALL CAPS&quot; confused things. I've fixed it, although because it seems to me that it would be awkward for the next mention of the term not to be wikified, I've left both instances as links.  I think it works better that way, but if anyone thinks that is a problem, I'm certainly not offended by further efforts to copyedit. [[User:Steveozone|Steveozone]] ([[User talk:Steveozone|talk]]) 04:37, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

== Two last gurus? ==
In the opening two paragraphs:
Paragraph 1 states that the last of ten successive sikh gurus was Guru Granth Sahib. Paragraph 2 indirectly states that there were ten sikh gurus, and that Guru Gobind Singh was the tenth. Are there 11 gurus, or 10? And if we are saying there are 11, why do we say &quot;six of the ten gurus&quot; in paragraph 2? Thanks.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.166.78.9|173.166.78.9]] ([[User talk:173.166.78.9|talk]]) 18:51, 28 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Waheguru Ji Ka Khalsa Waheguru Ji Ke Fateh
Veer Ji Please contact me Angad Singh a.buck.singh@gmail.com
Waheguru Ji Ka Khalsa Waheguru Ji Ke Fateh== SIKH PERSECUTION !!!! ==

I don't know and I can't understand - why there is no separate article on wikipedia regarding the persecution of Sikhs.Sikh Community has faced persecution during Mughal era , British era ,In Independent India and also in different countries for Multiple reasons.It is not surprising to see that there are separate articles of persecution of EVERY major religious group like HINDUS ,JEWS,CHRISTIANS, MUSLIMS,BUDDHISTS ,ZOROASTRIANS, Bahá'ís and Even NON religious people ,There are articles of ethnic persecutions as well.There are even sections for persecution of HOMOSEXUALS. But it does amaze me that there is no article related to persecution of the Sikh community which has faced and survived  ATROCITIES , OPPRESSION,INJUSTICE,DISCRIMINATION ,HOLOCAUSTS ,GENOCIDES, MASSACRES   throughout their history from different Rulers ,Governments, Terrorists, Extremists , Fanatics ,Imperialists and what not? Is this Subject dealt in the PERSECUTION OF HINDUS THEN? AS MANY PEOPLE THESE DAYS SAY THAT SIKHS ARE HINDUS.I think there should be a new section dealing with this Subject in this article and there should be a separate article dealing with the details, timeline ,history and eras of Sikh persecution and a link of that Main article provided in this one.I REQUEST ALL THE People Who Have KNOWLEDGE of SIKH HISTORY And Who Want THE WORLD To Know THE SACRIFICES AND STRUGGLES OF SIKHS, TO CREATE A PAGE WITH THE HEADING &quot;PERSECUTION OF SIKHS&quot;. If you (Whoever monitors and protects the contents of this article) think there should be no Article regarding this then please tell me the reason.WHY?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Justiceboy499|Justiceboy499]] ([[User talk:Justiceboy499|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Justiceboy499|contribs]]) 16:23, 6 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Vandalism ==
This webpage is repeatedly being edited by miscreants and should be locked. Offensive and derogatory statements against the Gurus, calling the faith &quot;pagan&quot;, &quot;terrorist&quot; and &quot;militant&quot;, etc. The article is being edited with these highly offensive terms to cause tensions between communities. Please remove these offensive terms and make sure these people are blocked.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.238.77.121|92.238.77.121]] ([[User talk:92.238.77.121|talk]]) 10:54, 8 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Vegetarianism? ==

:Why are this page and the Sikh page linked to vegetarianism? Sikhism in general has nothing to do with vegetarianism, consumption of meat is allowed.  More here: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vegetarianism_and_religion#Sikhism  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.61.195.236|24.61.195.236]] ([[User talk:24.61.195.236|talk]]) 15:04, 1 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::Hi, if you read the article, in order to have [[WP:Balance]] we have included for the fact their are some vociforous and loud (although small in number), sects that wish to make Sikhism into a Vegetarian offshoot of Vaishnavism. You are correct, that Vegetariansim really has nothing to do with Sikhism. I have changed the template to [[Diet in Sikhism]] Thanks --[[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;Sikh-&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;History&lt;/em&gt;]] 08:26, 2 February 2011 (UTC)

== Fundamental Connections With Islamic Teachings ==

One can see under the heading &quot;Philosophy and Teachings&quot; that the contents are predominantly similar to the intrinsic teachings of Islam, that is, the attributes of God (eternal, indescribable, all knowing, one). I have read that the cloak of Guru Nanak (at Dera Baba Nanak) was inscribed with verses from the Holy Quran and several Arabic prayers.
The following passages are quoted from the third edition of Bala Sahib's Janam Sakhi, printed by the press, Anarkali, Lahore in the early part of this century.
The book Janam Sakhi of Bala Sahib is an authoritative source of Sikhism. Bala was Nanak's constant companion and he accompanied his Master for twenty years during his travels. It is true that in Janam Sakhi one finds much fiction mixed with facts. Bala was a Hindu and after Nanak's death, estrangemant of Sikhism from Islam had started. As such any statement contained in Janam Sakhi in favour of Islam has the weight of a hostile witness.
On page 134 of Janam Sakhi by Bala Sahib, we read, The Quran is divided into thirty sections, proclaim thou, this Quran in the four comers of this world. Declare the glory of one name only for none other is an associate with me. Nanak proclaims the word of God that came to him, thou hast been granted the rank of Sheikh, so thou shouldst abolish the worship of gods and goddesses and the old Hindu idol - temples.
The fundamental article of the Islamic faith, the Kalima, has been given the greatest stress in Janam Sakhi. A few Shaloks (verses) from this Sakhi read:
I have repeated one Kalima, there is none other.
I have repeated one Kalima, there is none other.
Those who repeat the Kalima and are not devoid of the faith, shall not be burned on fire.
Repeat the Holy Kalima of the Prophet, it shall cleanse thee of all sins.
By repeating the Kalima, the punishment of this world, as well as the next is averted.

For further details, and if you can read Urdu, please read the Book &quot;Sat Bachan&quot; by HAzrat Mirza Ghulam Ahmad Qadiani (A.S.). Here is the link (it is a collection of his books, you'll find Sat Bachan from the table of contents) :
http://www.alislam.org/urdu/rk/Ruhani-Khazain-Vol-10.pdf  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/182.177.131.168|182.177.131.168]] ([[User talk:182.177.131.168|talk]]) 05:18, 31 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
==File:Dictation of the Guru Granth Saheb.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Dictation of the Guru Granth Saheb.jpg|File:Dictation of the Guru Granth Saheb.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests November 2011'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 12:17, 21 November 2011 (UTC)
|}

==Sikhs in the British Army==
I've removed this section, which was recently added to the article for several reasons: 
# The section contained [[WP:NOR|original research]], in that it made claims that were not supported by the references. For example: &quot;The [[Battle of Saragarhi]] is considered one of the greatest battles in British military history. [http://www.tribuneindia.com/2007/20070415/spectrum/book2.htm]. 
# Incorrect information. Example: &quot;Sikhs accounted for over 25% of the British soldiers who fought in WW1 and WW2&quot;. A scan of available references suggests that Sikh's were about 22% ''of the Indian Army''. 
# Lack of citations. For example, the previous statement lacked a citation, as did several other significant claims. 
# Incorrect citations. Example: &quot;[http://www.firstworldwar.com/features/lionsofthegreatwar.htm Sikhs of the war]. Abel.&quot; Should be: &quot;Arjan Singh Flora [http://www.firstworldwar.com/features/lionsofthegreatwar.htm Lions of the Great War]. firstworldwar.com&quot;
# The article is about Sikhism (the religion). Not about the military history of Sikhs. 

There are articles about Sikh military history (e.g., [[Sikh Regiment]], [[Punjab Army]]). Also, the articles [[British Indian Army]] and [[Indian Army]] mention Sikhs. These could each be expanded with a well-summarized paragraph on the Sikh contributions to those armies. There could be a new article created called &quot;Sikh military history&quot; which would merge the Sikh Regiment and Punjab Army articles. Comments? [[User:Sunray|Sunray]] ([[User talk:Sunray|talk]]) 20:25, 12 December 2011 (UTC)

:After removing the material above, what is left in the article is in the section on &quot;Growth of Sikhi and Rise of Khalsa&quot;. It needs to be re-written (bearing in mind that the article is about Sikh religion) and properly referenced. I've added &quot;citation needed&quot; tags. [[User:Sunray|Sunray]] ([[User talk:Sunray|talk]]) 20:35, 12 December 2011 (UTC)
==Verification needed - Sikhism and cannabis ==
Editors (mainly IPs) keep adding unsourced material on use of cannabis in Sikhism to [[Religious and spiritual use of cannabis]]. The only two sources in the section (which I have just added in top line) say cannabis is prohibited in Sikhism. Can someone verify the two sources, and/or provide better ones. Or, alternatively, if what the sources say is incorrect, provide sources to support the unsourced bulk of material saying cannabis has religious use in Sikhism. Thanks [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 01:05, 22 February 2012 (UTC)
:: Hi Fellow editor, I don't think it matter whether it is an anon IP. The only thing that matters is that it is a [[WP:Verifiable]] source they have added. Thanks [[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;]] 16:28, 22 February 2012 (UTC)
:::Hi Sikhhistory, No, the other way round, I added the verifiable sources which say Sikhs do not smoke cannabis. The IP was just writing text claiming Sikhs do smoke cannabis. Anyway [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Religious_and_spiritual_use_of_cannabis&amp;curid=2331004&amp;diff=480225530&amp;oldid=478172520 a different IP has now deleted the entire section], which I think is probably right. Can you Sikhhistory, or others, perhaps please add the page to your watchlist in case the IP returns? [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 04:15, 5 March 2012 (UTC)

== Fact or Aspiration? ==

From the second paragraph: &quot;Sikhs embody the qualities of a &quot;Sant-Sipahie&quot;—a saint-soldier.&quot; I do not know that this is false but from just a general knowledge of the human condition I suspect that not all Sikhs live up to this standard, particularly among the young, and that this should be changed to something more verifiable, such as a statement of the expectation or aspiration. Therefore, I have tagged the statement with a &quot;citation needed&quot; tag. 

Also, the mention of &quot;Sant-Sipahie&quot; or &quot;saint-soldier&quot; in the lead paragraphs would suggest that the subject is discussed in more detail in the body of the article, but there is no discussion and only one mention later in the &quot;Prohibitions&quot; section for reasons that are not entirely clear. I should like to learn more about this Sikh quality or aspiration. —[[User:Blanchette|Blanchette]] ([[User talk:Blanchette|talk]]) 22:43, 26 February 2012 (UTC)
::Read page 19 of [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=VtuOZBTkHAMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Philosophy+and+Faith+of+Sikhism&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=uplLT5qZOcn68QOmtZCWDA&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Philosophy%20and%20Faith%20of%20Sikhism&amp;f=false this]. See what you think. Thanks [[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;]] 14:58, 27 February 2012 (UTC)

Thank you for your reply [[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;]]. That book, ''The Philosophy and Faith of Sikhism'' by K. S. Duggal does not appear to support the claim in question, and even if it does, it is, unfortunately, a devotional history and exposition rather than a scholarly one as would be required for Wikipedia, since extraordinary claims require extraordinary evidence. That &quot;Sikhs embody the qualities of a &quot;Sant-Sipahie&quot;—a saint-soldier,&quot; is an extraordinary claim. 

That all eight-year-old Sikh girls embody the qualities of a saint (with the connotations of asceticism that concept seems to have in Sikhism) may be believable, that such girls also embody the qualities of a soldier, would be more of a stretch. That all vigorous and lusty sixteen-year-old Sikh boys are saints would also seem to be an extraordinary claim. If the claim were changed to &quot;Sikhs are expected to embody the qualities of a &quot;Sant-Sipahie&quot;—a saint-soldier,&quot; I would be less inclined to object, but I would still want a scholarly source to support that statement. —[[User:Blanchette|Blanchette]] ([[User talk:Blanchette|talk]]) 21:20, 28 February 2012 (UTC)
:::I was not commenting either way. I personally think it's an aspiration and something that Duggal confirms.On a side note, I didn't think Duggals book was that bad. It has some very good references.[[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;]] 13:14, 29 February 2012 (UTC)

:Thank you for making the change in the article, [[User:Sikh-history|&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:blue;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Bradley Hand ITC;color:goldenrod;font-size:16px&quot;&gt;H&lt;/em&gt;]] — I think you are knowledgeable enough to do so confidently. Of course I would still like to see a citation to the sources of this and the entire paragraph. If you can find this information in the book by K. S. Duggal, please cite that book and page. (I did take the time to look up Duggal, and whatever reservations I have about ''The Philosophy and Faith of Sikhism'', Duggal has many works on Sikhism to his or her credit.) I read most of what was available in the Google preview, specifically pp. 19-31 which include the entire chapter 3, &quot;The Saint-Soldiers&quot; and I saw neither footnotes, inline citations nor any references to the sources of the stories recounted at all, other than a citation of a creation scripture from the &quot;Holy Granth&quot; said to have been quoted by Guru Hargobind. Perhaps the book has endnotes with page numbers linking source citations to the page on which each item is recounted, but if so, I did not see those.  In looking for scholarly sources I discovered that there is an English language ''Encyclopedia of Sikhism'' by Harbans Singh that was published in 1992 by Punjabi University. That might be a good place to look up the statements in this article that still require sources, though the list of sources used already in this article is itself quite extensive. —[[User:Blanchette|Blanchette]] ([[User talk:Blanchette|talk]]) 10:25, 1 March 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;sightless&quot; ==

In the article, the Sikh deity is described as &quot;sightless.&quot; &quot;Sightless&quot; means &quot;blind.&quot; It looks like the appropriate word would be &quot;unseen&quot; or &quot;invisible.&quot; [[User:Bluemonkee|Bluemonkee]] ([[User talk:Bluemonkee|talk]]) 04:52, 20 April 2012 (UTC)

== Counting ==

Just a note to people who have actual knowledge of Sikkhi--the introductory paragraphs say that there are both &quot;over 26 million&quot; and &quot;over 30 million&quot; Sikhs. This may be literally true but it's darn confusing. May I suggest settling on one estimate?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/198.74.13.100|198.74.13.100]] ([[User talk:198.74.13.100|talk]]) 12:55, 8 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;



:: Looks like the introduction has been updated to use &quot;over 30 million&quot; in both places now, but if you follow the citation for the first use of the figure, it's from an article on Adherents.com, that references a 1998 article in the Christian Science Monitor. Especially since the second point in the sentence (that it's a fast-growing religion) is from 2010 (and cites a dead link), we should probably find an updated number. [[User:Kasanax|Kasanax]] ([[User talk:Kasanax|talk]]) 01:35, 6 August 2012 (UTC)

== ''Waheguru'' vs. ''Vāhigurū'' ==

This article uses both spellings. One spelling should be selected and the other removed. —[[User:Designate|Designate]] ([[User talk:Designate|talk]]) 23:54, 5 August 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>0fqjwo1g5b6dbp9t8hdc1zykxe4yjkb</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
