<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Moses</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>18973579</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518960002</id>
      <parentid>518947492</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-21T02:32:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Archiving 2 threads (older than 90d) to [[Talk:Moses/Archive 3]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7395">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=14:09, 4 January 2007
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=98406947

|action2=FAC
|action2date=16:08, 30 July 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Moses/archive1
|action2result=not promoted
|action2oldid=148014053

|action3=GAN
|action3date=12:03, 2 August 2008
|action3link=Talk:Moses/GA1
|action3result=not listed
|action3oldid=229163951

|topic=philrelig
|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1=
{{WikiProject Judaism|importance=Top|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Bible|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=High|saints=yes|saints-importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Islam|Prophets-of-Islam=yes|class=B|importance=mid}}
}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=B|category=Philrelig|small=yes}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Moses/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{archives|auto=long|search=yes|bot=MiszaBot I|age=90|index=/Archive index}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index
|mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=B|listas=Moses}}

== Moses &quot;adrift on the Nile?&quot; ==

I know that's what the source -- the ''1906'' (a bit dated, wouldn't you say?) Jewish Encyclopedia -- says, but it's not what the biblical text (Bible or Torah) says.  Exodus 2 clearly states that Moses' basket was merely placed in the reeds on the bank of the Nile and that's where Pharaoh's daughter found him.  No &quot;harrowing journey down the river&quot; as is typically depicted in Hollywood's offerings. [[Special:Contributions/67.233.242.191|67.233.242.191]] ([[User talk:67.233.242.191|talk]]) 15:08, 12 April 2012 (UTC)

== Eurocentric photos of Moses and Israelites ==

The photos of Moses need to be removed because they are Biblically inaccurate. White skin was the curse God put on Moses' sister, Miriam, when she dared question Moses as a voice of God (if you will). White skin = leprosy (leprous) = a &quot;defiling skin disease.&quot;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Numbers+12&amp;version=NIV See Numbers 12:1-10] See also [http://bible.cc/exodus/4-6.htm Exodus 4:6] when God temporarily turned Moses' hands &quot;leprous...like snow.&quot; These photos included in the article either need to be removed or updated; as they depict Moses &quot;leproused&quot; and with a defiling skin disease. The entire article lacks credibility because of this simple, yet overt and selective ignorance of the scriptures.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Operationnation|Operationnation]] ([[User talk:Operationnation|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Operationnation|contribs]]) 19:50, 20 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:The idea that white skin is a curse equivalent to leprosy would appear to be a delusion shared by no reliable sources, and just as offensive as the 19th century delusion that black skin is a curse. Leprousy is a real  skin disease, and can affect persons of all complexion.  You have provided no good reason to censor historical representations of Moses that are appropriate to a good encyclopedia article.  Even if they portray him as lighter than he actually was, which is indeed quite probable, they still have historiographic and traditional artistic value.  [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 20:05, 20 May 2012 (UTC)

You said: &quot;The idea that white skin is a curse equivalent to leprosy would appear to be a delusion shared by no reliable sources.&quot; Are you saying God is delusional? Please refer to the cited scriptures for the reliable source. You say the photos may be inaccurate, but should remain because they &quot;still have historiographic and traditional artistic value.&quot; This is an encyclopedia article (as you've stated as well), not an art studio. You admit the photos are inaccurate, ignore the citations, but say the photos should remain. If nobody can give a rational, reasonable reason to keep these photos, they either need to be removed or updated. &quot;NPOV is a fundamental principle of Wikipedia and of other Wikimedia projects. This policy is nonnegotiable and all editors and articles must follow it.&quot; These photos misrepresent the facts, are categorically incorrrect, and simply display a Eurocentric idea with &quot;historiographic and traditiona1 artistic value.&quot; [[User:Operationnation|Operationnation]] ([[User talk:Operationnation|talk]]) 20:57, 20 May 2012 (UTC)

::I didn't say God is delusional at all. I said, the idea that white skin is leprousy is [[delusion]]al.  See the difference in the two statements?  It might help your case if you can find an RS making the case that white skin is a disease like leprousy.   Simply pointing at a primary source and expecting us to follow your own peculiar interpretation of it is a kind of [[WP:NOR|Original research]], which is a misuse of primary sources for a synthesis with no secondary sources to back it up.    [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 21:30, 20 May 2012 (UTC)

:::We are having a similar argument at [[Cyrus the Great]] where someone wants to remove a work of art because it may not accurately portray Cyrus's death. The accuracy of a work of art is not a reason not to include it in an article. This has nothing to do with NPOV (which by the way requires the article not to say that Moses was a real person, so we can't base any arguments on the assumption that he was). [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 05:40, 21 May 2012 (UTC)
::::I've removed the tag, this edit[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:The_Protocols_of_the_Elders_of_Zion&amp;curid=19344153&amp;diff=494112982&amp;oldid=493383525] by Operationation is interesting. [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 11:24, 24 May 2012 (UTC)

== Name in different languages in the lead ==

As Moses is seen as a central ancestor of the Hebrews, and his name first appears in Hebrew scriptures, it makes perfect sense giving his name in Hebrew. I don't see the need for any other language, except English, on the English Wikipedia. Versions of his name in Greek and in Arabic are currently given in the lead, and these are hardly relevant as Moses was neither Greek nor Arab. Just as I see no reason to give the English version of his name in the Greek or Arabic Wikipedia, I don't see any reason to include Moses's name in Greek or Arabic here.[[User:Jeppiz|Jeppiz]] ([[User talk:Jeppiz|talk]]) 16:54, 5 July 2012 (UTC)
=== Avigdor ===
:More relevantly than Moses' name in other languages, I think, is Moses' name in Hebrew:  Avigdor--something that finds no mention in this article at all, including in the section specifically devoted to his name, a section linked to even from near the top of [[Avigdor (name)]].  [[Special:Contributions/96.41.249.21|96.41.249.21]] ([[User talk:96.41.249.21|talk]]) 06:33, 28 September 2012 (UTC)

== Painting of Moses with horns ==

Why do you feature the Jusepe de Ribera painting, which depicts Moses with horns? This product of the Inquisiton perpetuates antisemitic myths and is offensive.[[User:Ny10128|Ny10128]] ([[User talk:Ny10128|talk]]) 00:32, 21 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>j5c6losnwvoqlohiwqal679vl8qe6k7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
