<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Book of Mormon</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4488</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522168518</id>
      <parentid>522166970</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T12:40:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FisherQueen</username>
        <id>2179786</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* For inclusion in Category:American fiction */ I suggest that this discussion is resolved.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25772">{{Skip to talk}}
{{talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{notaforum|personal beliefs, nor for [[Apologetics]]/[[Polemic]]s}}
{{controversial}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
 {{WikiProject Religious texts|class=B|importance=High}}
 {{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=High}}
 {{LDSproject|class=B|importance=Top}}
}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=RBP
|action1date=January 19,  2004
|action1link=Wikipedia:Archive/Refreshing brilliant prose - History and religion
|action1result=demoted
|action1oldid=2284269

|action2=GAN
|action2date=17 October 2007
|action2result=not listed
|action2oldid=165296664

|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2011-03-26|oldid1=420716925}}
{{archives|auto=no|search=yes|bot=MiszaBot|age=90|index=/Archive index|&lt;center&gt;[[/Controversies1|1]]*, [[/Controversies2|2]]*, [[/Archive3|3]], [[/Archive 4|4]], [[/Archive 5|5]], [[/Archive 6|6]], [[/Archive 7|7]], [[/Archive 8|8]], [[/Archive 9|9]], [[/Archive 10|10]], [[/Archive 11|11]], [[/Archive 12|12]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;*From from [[Talk:Book of Mormon controversies]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/center&gt;}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 12
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Book of Mormon/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Book of Mormon/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Book of Mormon/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}

== Add [[Jesus of Jerusalem]] reference? ==

*[http://www.christiancourier.com/articles/940-the-birthplace-of-jesus-bethlehem-or-jerusalem ''The Birthplace of Jesus: Bethlehem or Jerusalem?'']
*[http://answers.yahoo.com/question/index?qid=20080823164815AA8Fxdt What city was Jesus born in Jerusalem or Bethlehem?]

*[http://www.mrm.org/jerusalem ''Was Jesus born &quot;at Jerusalem&quot;?'']
*[http://en.fairmormon.org/Book_of_Mormon/Anachronisms/Biblical/Jerusalem_vs_Bethlehem Book of Mormon/Anachronisms/Biblical/Jerusalem vs Bethlehem] 
*[http://www.utlm.org/onlineresources/bibleandbomcontradictions.htm Bible and Book of Mormon Contradictions] 
* http://bookofmormonresearch.org/book-of-mormon-criticisms/alma-710-jesus-born-in-jerusalem-or-bethlehem [Alma 7:10. Jesus Born in Jerusalem or Bethlehem?]

*[[Book of Alma|Alma]] 7: 10 &quot;And behold, he shall be born of Mary, at Jerusalem which is the land of our forefathers, she being a virgin...&quot;  http://www.lds.org/scriptures/bofm/alma/7?lang=eng
*{{Sourcetext |source= Book of Mormon| book= Alma |chapter= 7}}

[[Special:Contributions/99.181.159.115|99.181.159.115]] ([[User talk:99.181.159.115|talk]]) 19:37, 30 July 2012 (UTC)

::These comments don't make clear what changes you are suggesting to our article.  You seem to me to be suggesting that the article should go into much more detail.  The article cannot accommodate such details without (a) becoming inordinately long and (b) wandering far away from its topic which is the nature and history of the Book of Mormon.  [[User:Wanderer57|Wanderer57]] ([[User talk:Wanderer57|talk]]) 03:23, 31 July 2012 (UTC)

== Link # 11 out of order ==

This link # 11 is not working.  It seems it is an important one.

^ a b “The Life and Ministry of Joseph Smith,” Teachings of Presidents of the Church: Joseph Smith, (2007),xxii–25.

[[User:Wanderer57|Wanderer57]] ([[User talk:Wanderer57|talk]]) 15:08, 5 August 2012 (UTC)
:It should work now. [[User:72Dino|72Dino]] ([[User talk:72Dino|talk]]) 15:14, 5 August 2012 (UTC)

== The Hat ==

The historically established method Smith used to create the Book of Mormon, translating Reformed Egyptian into English using seer stones in a hat, is of critical material relevance to the origin and authenticity of the book, as discussed in the linked article, Seer Stones (Latter Day Saints), and the cited source, Translation of the Book of Mormon, and belongs in the lede.

The Mormon Think website pulls together extensive authority establishing that Smith used seer stones to translate the Book of Mormon.  The website says about itself: &quot;Mormonthink.com is a site produced largely by members of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints who are interested in the historical accuracy of our church and how it is being taught to its members and portrayed in the media.&quot;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Lahaun|Lahaun]] [[User:Lahaun|Lahaun]] ([[User talk:Lahaun|talk]]) 03:14, 22 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:My understanding is there may have been other methods of translation, although other editors may have more information than that.  You may feel that the translation method (using seer stones in a hat to block out light) may be &quot;of critical material relevance to the origin and authenticity of the book&quot;, but that is one opinion and does not mean it should be in the [[WP:LEAD|lead section]]. [[User:72Dino|72Dino]] ([[User talk:72Dino|talk]]) 03:42, 22 September 2012 (UTC)

::Why is it &quot;of critical material relevance to the origin and authenticity of the book&quot;? IMO, the only reason that is true is if you are trying to lead the reader to a particular conclusion as opposed to presenting information informally and with a neutral tone. A large number of accounts about the seer stones/Urim and Thummim and the Book of Mormon translation give few details and don't mention the hat (or anything else exactly), and there are other accounts that describe something different than the hat. It's also possible that the process changed over the years. Additionally, that's a lot of specific detail for the lede (which is supposed to summarize the article), details that are not found in the main body of the article. 
::As for the website, [[WP:SPS|anyone can create a webpage]]. There is nothing on that website to indicate that it meets the guidelines for reliable sources ([[WP:RS]]). --[[User:FyzixFighter|FyzixFighter]] ([[User talk:FyzixFighter|talk]]) 04:36, 22 September 2012 (UTC)
:::The addition of the &quot;hat&quot; anecdote represents a trivial piece of information and is therefore inappropriate for the lead.  Whether true or not, it's simply not a critical piece of summary information.  A better place for it would be in a section dedicated to &quot;reported translation process&quot; or something like that which includes all the variants of how Smith allegedly translated, not just the &quot;hat&quot; story.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 11:47, 22 September 2012 (UTC)

:The Mormon apologist web site, &quot;FAIR Mormon: Defending Mormonism by providing well-researched answers to challenging questions within a faithful context,&quot; contains an extensive discussion of Smith's use of seer stones, both generally and in translation of the BOM, which it accepts without serious reservation.  The only controversy FAIR Mormon addresses is whether the LDS Church has attempted to suppress the story and it concludes the church did not attempt suppression.  http://en.fairmormon.org/Joseph_Smith/Seer_stones  Moreover, if anyone has reason to believe that the Mormon Think site is anything other than what it claims to be, please let us know.

:I'm not sure how extant stories about BOM translations that don't mention the hat are relevant.  There are a lot of contemporaneous histories of the first century Roman Empire that fail to mention Jesus Christ, but that is hardly evidence that he did not exist.  As far as I know, all the actual witnesses to Smith's translation said he used the hat, after he lost the interpreter stones.
 
:I think you may be objecting to inclusion of the seer stone story for the same reason I think it's relevant: it raises serious credibility issues.  I think it's important to expound on the rather fantastical circumstances surrounding Smith's discovery of the golden plates and his subsequent translations so the reader has a comprehensive understanding of the origin of Mormon scripture.  (Think of trying to understand Scientology without knowing anything about L. Run Hubbard.)  It goes without saying that NPOV requires inclusion of all relevant information, not just info that paints an individual or organization in a positive light.  I would expect that almost all devout Mormons simply accept and embrace the history of their church as it actually is without attempts to repudiate or gloss over well documented descriptions of the events within that history.

:I'm amenable to addition of a separate section about translation, although I am not familiar with any documented versions of the translation process other than the Urim and Thummim/interpreters and rock in a hat stories.  If they're out there, let's hear about them.  [[User:Lahaun|Lahaun]] ([[User talk:Lahaun|talk]]) 00:45, 23 September 2012 (UTC)

::So, somehow it is ok to say &quot;Smith claimed that the last prophet to contribute to the book, a man named Moroni, buried it in a hill in present-day New York and then returned to earth in 1827 as an angel, revealing the location of the book to Smith and instructing him to translate and disseminate it as evidence of the restoration of Christ's true church in the latter days.&quot; But it would be biased somehow to say he used a hat or some seer stones to translate it? To quote the anime-version of [[Fry (Futurama)|Philip J. Fry]], &quot;The list of things I've heard now contains everything!&quot; It is silly to assume that people will somehow find the method of translation more silly than the rest of the story about the plates. The bias is in the protectiveness that people put around the story as if to tell the story as it was originally told would somehow lead people to disbelieve it. -- [[User:Avanu|Avanu]] ([[User talk:Avanu|talk]]) 01:14, 23 September 2012 (UTC)
:::This article is NPOV, so that means it neither claims that Smith is telling the truth nor does it take an overly aggressive stance on debunking it.  Over the course of several years of discussion and compromise, both Mormons and non-Mormons have come to a consensus on how to approach this sensitive issue without one side offending the other.  The question right here isn't about whether or not the translation technique should be mentioned ''in the body of the article'', but that it is too trivial an issue for the lead, which already contains qualifiers such as &quot;Smith claimed to have done X&quot; rather than just &quot;Smith did X&quot;.  Prepare an appropriately [[WP:RS|referenced]] section that is neutral in tone and it will probably be acceptable for most editors.  But the hat is too trivial an issue for the lead.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 03:14, 23 September 2012 (UTC) 

Any authoritative affirmation of the hat story would be found here:http://www.lds.org/ensign/1993/07/a-treasured-testament - where not only is the process of translating described by one of the leaders of the mormon church, it references multiple journal entries of first hand accounts of those who were there i.e. Emma Smith. This makes it not a trivial issue, but one that should be included in a NPOV as a first hand account of the process of producing the book.
:Write a well-referenced section, by all means, but it is still too peripheral (and its emphasis too POV) to include in the lead.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 19:03, 24 September 2012 (UTC)

== For inclusion in Category:American fiction ==
{{archivetop}}
As [[Historical authenticity of the Book of Mormon|that is the conclusion from communities of experts in archaeology, ethnography, history and genetics]]. Any alternative view is [[WP:FRINGE]] and widely disparaged {{unsignedIP2|12:02, 2 November 2012 (UTC)|49.176.97.135}}
:Religious texts are treated differently than non-religious texts and always have been.  We don't put the Bible in the category of &quot;Middle Eastern fiction&quot;, nor do we put the Bhagavad Gita in the category of &quot;South Asian fiction&quot;, etc.  While those of us who don't believe a particular religious narrative can treat the text like fiction in our personal lives, we don't insult the millions of believers who think the text is literal by placing that text in the overt category of &quot;fiction&quot; here in Wikipedia.  Wikipedia is '''''neutral''''' in such issues, but placing the BOM overtly in a &quot;fiction&quot; category removes that neutrality.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 10:26, 4 November 2012 (UTC)
::Where's the policy that creates such an exception, just to prove you didn't dream it up yourself?[[User:Plausy|Plausy]] ([[User talk:Plausy|talk]]) 06:15, 5 November 2012 (UTC)
::Per [[Historicity of the Book of Mormon]], &quot;the theory that the Book of Mormon is an ancient American history is considered to fall outside academic credibility&quot;. Suppositions that are bereft of academic credibility, in other words those that are [[WP:FRINGE]], will NOT be influential in categorisation as that policy tells us that &quot;a theory that is not broadly supported by scholarship in its field must not be given undue weight&quot;. Such undue weight would be given if we fail to uphold the fiction categorisation.[[User:Plausy|Plausy]] ([[User talk:Plausy|talk]]) 06:38, 5 November 2012 (UTC)
:::Sorry, Plausy, but you will not be able to build any kind of [[WP:CONSENSUS]] for your POV pushing.  Go ahead and try to get a consensus.  Remember that consensus isn't a majority vote, but a &quot;coming together of the minds&quot;.  Be my guest.  But until you get a consensus, you are bound by [[WP:BRD]].  You tried to make your edit, you were reverted, now before editing again you are required by the very policies you are trying to mechanistically apply in an inappropriate place to not edit the article until you have built a consensus.  But unless you are prepared to apply this same process to the Bible, the Upanishads, the Koran, etc. then this might not be your best idea.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 07:07, 5 November 2012 (UTC)
::::I agree that where a prevailing expert consensus is that the work is fiction, and that is the case here, it is to be categorised so. The fringe view to the contrary can be mentioned though not with undue weight. Categorising on the basis of such discredited viewpoints is certainly undue.[[Special:Contributions/49.176.98.239|49.176.98.239]] ([[User talk:49.176.98.239|talk]]) 05:55, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::While this may very well be a &quot;work of fiction&quot; in the eyes of most readers and even most scholars, it is a sacred volume, a religious text, and thus, unlike &quot;The Lord of the Rings&quot; or &quot;Huckleberry Finn&quot;, which are universally considered to be works of fiction, there are tens of millions of Wikipedia readers (including serious scholars) for whom the Book of Mormon is not a work of fiction, but the word of God and a literal historical account.  For Wikipedia to take a position that slaps these tens of millions of readers in the face and declares their sincere religious beliefs to be false is a violation of Wikipedia's [[WP:NPOV]] policy.  Compare this article with [[Book of Jonah]], the story in the Bible of a man being swallowed by a whale.  Please point out to me where that article says, &quot;This is a work of fiction&quot; or where it is included in a category of &quot;Fiction of the ancient Near East&quot;.  Unless you are ready to include the word &quot;fiction&quot; prominently in that article, then you need to back off here.  Religious texts are completely different from the latest James Rollins thriller.  You need to recognize that fundamental distinction in the way we must treat them in Wikipedia.  Like I said, I dare you to try to build a [[WP:CONSENSUS]] on adding &quot;fiction&quot; to this article, either as a word in the text or as a category.  You'll fail, but you are welcome to try.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 15:42, 6 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::Newsflash for you. In a comparison between the confirmed finding of the academic community and a fringe discredited theory we're not 'neutral' and noncommital: we give dignity to the first, including in the scheme of categorisation, and we warn the latter to be exactly what it is. Thanks for effectively confirming there's no policy exception for works of literature that have religious pretensions. And keep on talking about every other article.[[User:Plausy|Plausy]] ([[User talk:Plausy|talk]]) 20:50, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Belligerency will do you no good in building a [[WP:CONSENSUS]], Plausy.  And per [[WP:BRD]] you are required to build a consensus for your edit before reinserting it into the article.  You apparently are ignorant of these Wikipedia policies, as well as [[WP:NPOV]], [[WP:TE]], and [[WP:POINT]].  Until you build a consensus for your edit '''''here on the Talk Page''''', you will continue to be reverted.  If you continue to push your unwarranted and anti-Mormon POV in the article without building a consensus first, you may be subject to blocks on your editing privileges.  I have clearly and unequivocally invited you to pursue the building of a consensus here, but you have failed to attract a single other user to your side (we all know the anon IPs are you).  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 22:57, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::::Just read your edit summary for your last edit (which got you blocked for edit warring).  What &quot;consensus&quot; were you referring to?  You have built no consensus here.  You continuing to push your POV through insults is not a &quot;consensus&quot;.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 23:06, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
::Libraries generally categorize this book under 'religion,' not under 'fiction.'  I'm not sure why we would take the liberty of re-categorizing it.  Religious works of all kinds are generally categorized under 'nonfiction;' I'm not familiar with any system of book organization that calls religious texts 'fiction.'  What source are you using as the basis for this categorization, and why is it more reliable than the Dewey Decimal or Library of Congress categories? -[[User:FisherQueen|FisherQueen]]&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot;&gt; ([[User talk:FisherQueen|talk]] · [[Special:Contributions/FisherQueen|contribs]])&lt;/span&gt; 02:25, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
:::In libraries, where there is only one shelf space for a volume, this book is found either in fiction under the name of its author who copyrighted it or in a reference section. It is NOT a work of scholarship and it is not a book ABOUT the religion built around it. Library categorisation preferences have no influence here as we are bound classify each article into [[Wikipedia:Categorisation#Categorizing_pages|'ALL of the most specific categories to which it logically belongs']]. As referred to and revealed above, a [[fiction|fictional]] categorisation (ie anything based in whole or part upon imagined or nonexistent or unreal things) is one which applies due to the confirmed finding of it being 'outside academic credibility' to assign the work any historographical merit and scientific consensus of its lack of any quality of truthfulness or factuality.[[User:Sciot|Sciot]] ([[User talk:Sciot|talk]]) 12:42, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
::::About the library comment, you're wrong. See [http://catalog.loc.gov/cgi-bin/Pwebrecon.cgi?SC=CallNumber&amp;SEQ=20121108105253&amp;PID=ezP1lGt-vgwElGCtQjDe0W2TQ-d&amp;SA=BX8623+1830 multiple copies] listed at the Library of Congress under the call number BX8623. The BX8623 call number [http://www.loc.gov/catdir/cpso/lcco/ classifies] it as ''Philosophy. Psychology. Religion'' &gt; ''Christian Denominations'' &gt; ''Mormons. Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints''. Also, per [[WP:CAT#Articles]], categorization of articles must be verifiable, should be clear from verifiable information in the article why it was placed in each of its categories, and should be guided by defining characteristics of the subject of the article, ie one that reliable sources commonly and consistently define the subject as having) of the subject of the article. I don't see any of these requirements as having been met in the article or addressed yet in the discussion here. If you want outside third-opinion (one of the dispute resolution paths instead of edit warring), I would suggest asking over at [[WP:RELI]] (or [[WP:NV]] if you want to add this page to that wikiproject). --[[User:FyzixFighter|FyzixFighter]] ([[User talk:FyzixFighter|talk]]) 16:11, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::You've been alerted to the fact that [https://www.sunstonemagazine.com/wp-content/uploads/sbi/articles/132%2022-55.pdf Duffy] acknowledges claims for any truth or factuality in the book to be 'outside academic credibility', and you've had the time to review the article on the books historical [[Historical authenticity of the Book of Mormon|authenticity]], and subarticles on it and the fields of [[Archaeology and the Book of Mormon|archaeology]], [[Genetics and the Book of Mormon|genetics]], and [[Linguistics and the Book of Mormon|linguistics]]  .. and that's a lack of 'verifiable information'. Really?[[User:Sciot|Sciot]] ([[User talk:Sciot|talk]]) 20:56, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::I find it impossible to take you with any degree of seriousness whatsoever, Plausy (you fool no one at all with your [[WP:SOCK|sockpuppet]] named Sciot).  First, your link doesn't go anywhere.  Second, you act like you have some sort of irrefutable argument and you have no argument at all for why a religious text should be classified under &quot;fiction&quot;.  Let me repeat that, you have no argument whatsoever for why a religious text should be labelled as &quot;fiction&quot; when the nation's most prestigious libraries treat religious texts as distinct.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 21:06, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::::@Plausy/Sciot/whatever you want to call yourself today - what part of Duffy (sentence, page number or paragraph) do you feel warrants the category of &quot;fiction&quot;, and don't just quote other WP articles? Also, these edits [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Historical_authenticity_of_the_Book_of_Mormon&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=522131092] [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Book_of_Mormon&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=522131076] are not [[WP:ME|minor edits]]; don't abuse the minor edit mark. --[[User:FyzixFighter|FyzixFighter]] ([[User talk:FyzixFighter|talk]]) 06:03, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::Using the nation's largest university library on-line catalog, the unified catalog of the universities in the University of California system (which includes includes Berkeley, UCLA, UCSB, UCSD and others), the listing for Book of Mormon is [http://melvyl.worldcat.org/search?q=book+of+mormon&amp;fq=&amp;dblist=1708%2C1875%2C143%2C1834%2C1847%2C1271%2C2130%2C1476%2C1525%2C1953%2C1943%2C2233%2C2005%2C2148%2C1941%2C2158%2C239%2C2038%2C2007%2C2006%2C2221%2C2162%2C2164%2C283%2C285%2C638&amp;se=nodgr&amp;sd=desc&amp;start=1&amp;scope=0&amp;qt=back2results&amp;cookie here].  Except for one copy at Berkeley under F835 (&quot;Local History of the United States, and British, Dutch, French, and Latin America&quot;), all other copies in the system are at BX8623.  No copies are cataloged under &quot;Prose Fiction&quot; [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Library_of_Congress_Classification:Class_P,_subclass_PS_--_American_Literature PS370-379].  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 16:43, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::Being that [[WP:CENSOR|we don't ever censor]] just because of the preciousness of some faction's feelings, that academic consensus has to be respected above what is fringe and discredited, and that there is not something about religion which quarantines the character of fictional accounts  - then it wrong to insult the consensus by failure to acknowledge this categorisation.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/165.228.213.43|165.228.213.43]] ([[User talk:165.228.213.43|talk]]) 09:10, 9 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::::::Are you also recommending the Bible and Koran go into fiction categories too? [[Special:Contributions/2001:4479:3A06:82B1:74AB:48B0:B413:E0F8|2001:4479:3A06:82B1:74AB:48B0:B413:E0F8]] ([[User talk:2001:4479:3A06:82B1:74AB:48B0:B413:E0F8|talk]]) 11:54, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::::You clearly don't know what the word &quot;consensus&quot; means in reference to Wikipedia, Plausy (and we're still not fooled by that anon IP you're using now after your second block for edit warring).  Read [[WP:CONSENSUS]] again (if you haven't already).  Consensus exists only within Wikipedia for Wikipedia's purposes.  Consensus is built on each page or for a small group of very closely related articles.  But is it built here, in Wikipedia, through discussion on Talk Pages, not &quot;out there&quot;.  You have zero consensus for your edits here.  You have been reverted multiple times by multiple editors.  And almost all of the editors who are reverting you are actually non-Mormons, so the possibility of getting any support for your changes is vanishingly tiny approaching non-existent.  You are on course to be permanently banned from Wikipedia if you continue your edit warring.  --[[User:Taivo|Taivo]] ([[User talk:Taivo|talk]]) 12:25, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
:'''Suggestion'''.  There is only one person arguing for this course of action, although he is using multiple accounts to do so.  Consensus is clear.  I have indefinitely blocked that user for block evasion, and I suggest that we acknowledge that consensus is clear on this question, close the discussion, and revert edits from any further sockpuppets of this user to help him understand that 'blocked' means he doesn't get to edit any more. -[[User:FisherQueen|FisherQueen]]&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot;&gt; ([[User talk:FisherQueen|talk]] · [[Special:Contributions/FisherQueen|contribs]])&lt;/span&gt; 12:40, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
{{archivebottom}}</text>
      <sha1>oc1416zylaqp1wckwhbqejx184yolgq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
