<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Roman mythology</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>20949390</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514864562</id>
      <parentid>484883597</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-27T19:46:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Banner clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8434)</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11445">{{V0.5|class=B|category=Philrelig}}
{{WikiProject Mythology|class=c|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Classical Greece and Rome|class=C|importance=high}}
{{Archive box|auto=yes}}

==Unsorted text==
To edit the &quot;Topics in Roman Mythology&quot; table, see [[Template:Roman myth]].  That table can also be added to related pages if you want by inserting &lt;nowiki&gt;{{Roman myth}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;  [[User:Bacchiad|Bacchiad]] 22:51, 16 Jul 2004 (UTC)

------
:, partially directed on town's personality.

No one said gods can't also be allegories.  Besides, Augustus was a full-out god after his death, not just a sort of demi-god.  [[User:Bacchiad|Bacchiad]] 07:05, 14 Jul 2004 (UTC)

==Africus for COTW==
I've nominated [[Africus]] for [[Wikipedia:Collaboration of the week|COTW]]. I did this because I felt that the Roman god who is directly responsible for the name of one of our present-time continents deserves more than two lines for his article. If you would like to support, please go to [[Wikipedia:Collaborations of the Week/Africus|its COTW page]] and write your name down on the support list. -- [[User:SoothingR|SoothingR]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[User talk:SoothingR|pour]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 15:53, 13 December 2005 (UTC)

==List of Major Gods==
I changed the listof major gods. It is now a gallery, the reason for this is that in my opinion it is better with pictures. However, I am short of some pictures. 
The previous list looked like this:

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!God/Goddess
!God/Goddess of
|-
|[[Apollo]] ||God of the sun, dancing, festivities, archery and music
|-
|[[Dionysus|Bacchus]] ||God of wine
|-
|[[Ceres]] ||Goddess of the earth
|-
|[[Cupid]] ||God of love
|-
|[[Diana (goddess)|Diana]]||Goddess of the moon and hunting
|-
|[[Fortuna (luck)|Fortuna]]||Goddess of luck
|-
|[[Janus (mythology)|Janus]] ||God of doors
|-
|[[Juno (mythology)|Juno]] ||Queen of the gods
|-
|[[Jupiter (god)|Jupiter]] ||King of the gods
|-
|[[Maia Maiestas|Maia]]||Goddess of growth
|-
|[[Mars (god)|Mars]]||God of war (originally agriculture)
|-
|[[Mercury (mythology)|Mercury]] ||Messenger of the gods
|-
|[[Minerva]] ||Goddess of wisdom
|-
|[[Poseidon|Neptune]] ||God of the sea
|-
|[[Pluto (god)|Pluto]] ||King of the [[Hades|underworld]]
|-
|[[Proserpine]] ||Queen of the [[Hades|underworld]]
|-
|[[Quirinus]]||God of defense &amp; the state
|-
|[[Saturn (mythology)|Saturn]]||God of agriculture
|-
|[[Uranus (mythology)|Uranus]] ||God of the heavens
|-
|[[Venus (mythology)|Venus]] ||Goddess of love
|-
|[[Vesta (mythology)|Vesta]] ||Goddess of hearth
|-
|[[Vulcan (mythology)|Vulcan]] ||God of smithing
|}

If you prefer the old one, above, to thge current please tell me and I'd be happy to change it back. [[User:Sotakeit|Sotakeit]] 20:29, 12 February 2006 (UTC)

I actually much prefer the list above without the pictures. Here is why I feel quite strongly about it: it seems to me that we are confusing the concept of &quot;Roman god&quot; with its depictions in art. A Roman god, whatever it is (or not), is different from the art used to represent it. Moreover, it seems particularly little enlightening (we see basically  a bunch of statues...).[[User:62.203.8.195|62.203.8.195]] 12:42, 28 July 2007 (UTC)
ugihkj
==Parenthetical Problems==
Why do two of the Roman deity use &quot;(god)&quot; or &quot;(goddess)&quot; randomly, while most of them, and all the Greek deity articles, use &quot;(mythology)&quot;? The latter seems preferable, since it avoids needless specificity in disambiguation and can apply accurately to a wider number of articles without possible accusations of POV for stating whether or not a specific being qualifies as a &quot;god&quot;. What's up with this:



I'd fix them myself, but unlike most of the deity pages where a move from (god)/(goddess) to (mythology) was implemented, for some ''bizarre'' reason this one already has &quot;Jupiter (mythology)&quot; and &quot;Pluto (mythology)&quot; as redirects to those two pages. Ick. -[[User:Silence|Silence]] 04:06, 18 February 2006 (UTC)

:Why are they not tagged &quot;_(religion)&quot;? It is only from an &quot;outside&quot; POV that they are myths. It is certainly not true that Papa Roman sat his kids down and said &quot;It is time you learned our mythology, those things we believe in order to understand our world&quot;. I could also support using no tags at all, (as in the case, for example, of [[Amaterasu]]), and glossing the untagged entry on disambiguation pages, as, for example, is the practice here with [[Jesus (disambiguation)|Jesus]]. In short, adding (mythology) to Jupiter et al. but not to Jesus or Amaterasu seems rather POV to me. [[User:Whogue|Whogue]] 07:32, 20 October 2006 (UTC)

::Mythology is not meant as a POV slight.  Remember that mythology does not necessarily mean that something is considered false, but it is not exactly the same as religion, either.  In short, mythology is more about the stories while religion is about beliefs and rituals.  Check the pages on wikipedia pages mythology and religion for more info. [[User:AliaGemma|AliaGemma]] 05:36, 17 April 2007 (UTC)

==Vandalism==

Someone changed the page to &quot;write some damn mythology&quot;.  I changed it back to the previous version.

You don't need to make a comment about it ;) [[User:Putnamehere3145|---As said on this site, &amp;lt;i&amp;gt;The wii version will Have wii compatibility&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;]] ([[User talk:Putnamehere3145|talk]]) 19:27, 28 May 2008 (UTC)
heeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeelp  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.165.65.149|86.165.65.149]] ([[User talk:86.165.65.149|talk]]) 16:04, 4 March 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Mythology and Religion==

It seems to me that a good deal of this article (&quot;Native Roman and Italic gods&quot;, &quot;Foreign gods&quot;, &quot;Major Roman deities&quot;) properly belongs in [[Religion in ancient Rome]]. [[User:Whogue|Whogue]] 08:46, 9 November 2006 (UTC)

Please do not vandalize Wikipedia!!

that's all I ask, it makes people not trust this website [it is very trustworthy!!]  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/98.111.52.38|98.111.52.38]] ([[User talk:98.111.52.38|talk]]) 23:43, 26 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== when it died ==
I really wanted to know when the religion completely died out because there must have been some small out of the way places that kept their beliefs.

== Huh? ==
The beginning of this article sounds sort of like the content on this website
http://www.crystalinks.com/romemythology.html  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/65.29.117.134|65.29.117.134]] ([[User talk:65.29.117.134|talk]]) 23:36, 20 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Yes it does, but it's probably copied from Wikipedia and not the other way around (the end of the text says: References: Wikipedia). [[User:Pax:Vobiscum|Pax:Vobiscum]] 02:20, 14 November 2007 (UTC)

== Early mythology about Roman history ==

The last two paragraphs of the &quot;Early mythology about Roman history&quot; section contain numerous spelling errors (such as &quot;Odisius&quot;, &quot;whorlpool&quot;, etc.), some wording that needs to be rearranged for clarity, as well as the abbreviation &quot;w/&quot; instead of &quot;with&quot; several times. I tried to correct them and to clean it up some, but cannot find how to edit that section anywhere on the page, either by editing the entire page or by editing that section.
[[Special:Contributions/32.97.110.142|32.97.110.142]] ([[User talk:32.97.110.142|talk]]) 20:58, 13 March 2008 (UTC)

== Vandalism ==
The last two paragraphs should not be in the article.  They are obvious vandalism.  I haven't quite figured out the ropes around here, can I just remove the offensive passages?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:PeterCalamy|PeterCalamy]] ([[User talk:PeterCalamy|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/PeterCalamy|contribs]]) 03:57, 30 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
u r gay
now sut up 
and dei  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/209.175.223.10|209.175.223.10]] ([[User talk:209.175.223.10|talk]]) 18:29, 2 April 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:13 year old kids... I'm 13, you don't have to act immature. homophobe. Take out the last two.

==Article needs dedicated editing==

It lacks citation and modern references, so I'll tag accordingly. Style and content are reminiscent of a public lecture by some charming, scholarly old buffer with elbow-patches who means to talk about mythology but loses his way. Really needs some work, and Beard, North and Price's &quot;Religions of Rome&quot; (1998) Cambridge, might be a start. Yes, &quot;Religions&quot;, because the authors elucidate the issues this article attempts to resolve. [[User:Haploidavey|Haploidavey]] ([[User talk:Haploidavey|talk]]) 12:42, 10 August 2009 (UTC)

Also to your point, some of the language sounds rather stodgy.  For example, the first sentence under &quot;Early Roman Mythology&quot; uses the words &quot;dearth&quot; and &quot;panoply&quot;, neither of which are widely understood (other than by context) outside upper-level academic circles. [[User:GalacticCowboy|GalacticCowboy]] ([[User talk:GalacticCowboy|talk]]) 15:44, 30 December 2009 (UTC)hjgjhgjhgj

::Upper-level? You mean you can't expect the average college senior to know them? Wow, if that's true, how sad. (The trouble with 'panoply' here is that it doesn't mean what the user seems to have intended.) To Haploidavey's point, &quot;The Romans had no sequential narratives about their gods comparable to the Titanomachy or the seduction of Zeus by Hera until their poets began to adopt Greek models in the later part of the Roman Republic&quot; … hard to say where to begin to rewrite that into something meaningful.  [[User:Cynwolfe|Cynwolfe]] ([[User talk:Cynwolfe|talk]]) 02:12, 18 August 2010 (UTC)

:::Yes, a splendid beginning. Let's just link to [[Greek mythology]] and be done. Or better, let's rewrite from scratch. [[User:Haploidavey|Haploidavey]] ([[User talk:Haploidavey|talk]]) 15:31, 18 August 2010 (UTC)

== Temporary measures ==

I was at the library the other day, had [[T.P. Wiseman]]'s ''The Myths of Rome'' in my hand, thought, eh, I won't be looking at Roman mythology anytime soon, put it back, and somehow ended up here today. Anyway, I had made some notes from Bremmer and Horsfall's rather idiosyncratic book, which taken alone seem so disproportionate (no [[Horatius at the bridge]]!) that I threw in some other Greatest Hits. I figure if a student ends up here (and they appear to frequently, judging from the juvenile vandalism the article gets), something is better than nothing for now. [[User:Cynwolfe|Cynwolfe]] ([[User talk:Cynwolfe|talk]]) 14:08, 4 February 2011 (UTC)

:Indeed it is. Structure at last, (and &quot;convoluted revisionist genealogy&quot; bodes very well for the future. Lovely phrase).  [[User:Haploidavey|Haploidavey]] ([[User talk:Haploidavey|talk]]) 14:36, 4 February 2011 (UTC)

== Romance mythology ==

That Slavs - a language group - a group of languages. [[Romance languages]] ​​- a group of languages. Is there a &quot;Romance mythology&quot;?</text>
      <sha1>qebsetq7kyhyb30p1iv27py9kvvx059</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
