<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Theoria</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3230501</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510333091</id>
      <parentid>488978334</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-01T21:00:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>205121</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Unexplained deletion of sourced contributions */Substituting template per documentation, replaced: {{Unsigned → {{subst:unsigned using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17968">{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:Theoria/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=C|importance=Mid|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=High|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern-orthodoxy-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=|importance=}}
{{GOCE|user=Paulmnguyen|date=October 17, 2010|old-user-1=Paulmnguyen|old-date-1=September 13, 2010}}
{{archives|auto=long|search=yes|bot=MiszaBot I|age=2|units=months}}

== People here defending wiki hounding ==

This article and also theosis and also Eastern Orthodox Roman catholic theological differences where articles I greatly contributed Eastern Orthodox sources and positions to. BEFORE Esoglou followed me to them after my disagreement with his edit warring behavior on the filioque and the East West schism articles. Richwales has made no public criticism to Esoglou for radically rewriting my contributions and blanket deleting of some them NO ADMINISTRATOR HAS. But some are real quick to jump on my talkpage and post comments about even the slightest possible policy infraction. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk%3ALoveMonkey&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=401680337&amp;oldid=399819880] Wikipedia is not fair in its enforcement of policy and this behavior is ruining the project and running off contributors. '''Anyone can go to Esoglou's talkpage and see people complaining but unlike the rest of us Esoglou has yet to be blocked or even criticized for his behavior.''' [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 20:43, 11 December 2010 (UTC)
:I agree with you.--[[User:Taiwan boi|Taiwan boi]] ([[User talk:Taiwan boi|talk]]) 01:00, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
::I refrain from making counter-accusations [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 11:06, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
::I notice that several Wikipedians have cited as a very strong argument in favour of the candidature of the editor in question the diff that LoveMonkey gives here as a matter of complaint.  That is sufficient answer to the complaint.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:46, 13 December 2010 (UTC)

=== Unexplained deletion of sourced contributions ===
Is [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Theoria&amp;diff=401831571&amp;oldid=401793848 this edit] defensible, which, with no more explanation than &quot;revert again Esoglou radically rewrites blanket deletes Eastern Orthodox opinion Again Esoglou does this with no discussion talkpage in order to push esoglou's RCC POV&quot;, deletes well-sourced contributions, including valid responses to requests for citations?  (It comes from someone who added even more material without prior discussion, including unsourced personal evaluations.)  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 22:06, 11 December 2010 (UTC)
:You have an established record of attacking Eastern Orthodox edits and replacing them with content which is POV, improperly sourced, or misrepresents sources, without a word of discussion with others. I have told you time and time again to confine yourself to edits concerning your own denomination, yet you continue with these disruptive edits. I support LM in this case.--[[User:Taiwan boi|Taiwan boi]] ([[User talk:Taiwan boi|talk]]) 01:00, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
::Now that you have let off your generic steam and repeated your imperious demand (wherever you got authority to make it) that a Wikipedia editor should &quot;confine himself&quot; to matters concerning a single denomination (of what denomination were those whom LoveMonkey deleted: Gregory the Great, Aquinas, Merton, Zagzebski, Harpur? of what denomination was Saint Augustine?), would you please address the particular case?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 11:06, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
:::I am not discussing LoveMonkey's edits because I don't have any dispute with them. I have already made this clear. He does not have a record of misrepresenting the Catholic view. You have a record of misrepresenting the Orthodox view. That is why I tell you once more to  confine yourself to edits concerning your own denomination.&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Taiwan boi|Taiwan boi]] ([[User talk:Taiwan boi|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Taiwan boi|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
::::So, does nobody defend LoveMonkey's deletion?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 14:56, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::::I already have, twice. Please read what I write. I don't see anyone here objecting to it except for you, and your bias against his edits is a matter of record.--[[User:Taiwan boi|Taiwan boi]] ([[User talk:Taiwan boi|talk]]) 15:15, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
::::::::Please give me the diff to at least one of the two times that you defended this deletion by LoveMonkey.  I cannot find them.  I have only found your attack on me, not a defence of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Theoria&amp;diff=401831571&amp;oldid=401793848 this particular deletion.]  Or do you believe that ''anything'' I write, even on, for instance, Thomas Aquinas or Thomas Merton, must necessarily be deleted on sight?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 15:26, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::* [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3ATheoria&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=401869448&amp;oldid=401845375 &lt;big&gt;'''I support LM in this case'''&lt;/big&gt;].
::::::::::* [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3ATheoria&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=401958504&amp;oldid=401935845 I am not discussing LoveMonkey's edits because &lt;big&gt;'''I don't have any dispute with them'''&lt;/big&gt;].--[[User:Taiwan boi|Taiwan boi]] ([[User talk:Taiwan boi|talk]]) 15:41, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::Clear enough: &quot;I am not discussing LoveMonkey's edits ...&quot;  You are not discussing this edit by LoveMonkey.   Perhaps someone else will.  LoveMonkey himself?  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 15:55, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::Please don't be obtuse. I have told you several times that I am discussing this edit by Lovemonkey. I have made this perfectly clear.--[[User:Taiwan boi|Taiwan boi]] ([[User talk:Taiwan boi|talk]]) 16:01, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::::You have told me that you are discussing this edit by LoveMonkey.  You have also told me you are not discussing LoveMonkey's edits.  Let's leave it at that.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:38, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::That is false. I have told you more than once that I supported this edit by LoveMonkey. I never made the contradiction you claim.--[[User:Taiwan boi|Taiwan boi]] ([[User talk:Taiwan boi|talk]]) 16:42, 12 December 2010 (UTC)
:::::::::::::::::The record speaks.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:41, 22 December 2010 (UTC)

== Why a different and distinct article for Eastern Orthodox theoria? ==

Because theoria is not a feeling or some internal epiphany one gets from philosophizing about God (like pagan mysticism i.e. gnosticism). Theoria is God appearing to people LITERALLY. It is to see the uncreated light of God, LITERALLY. This is not taught in Western Christianity. It is the Eastern Christianity theological essential. And that is being buried here by Roman Catholic POV editors. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 03:07, 18 December 2010 (UTC)

OK, listen up ''everyone.''  This POV-pushing, anti-Catholic rhetoric stops here and now.  I was just alerted to this matter and this is supposed to be about Christianity.  You know.  Love, peace, Holy Spirit, Triune God, etc?  Seriously, all of you, just log off for a day or two and calm down.  [[User:PMDrive1061|PMDrive1061]] ([[User talk:PMDrive1061|talk]]) 04:01, 18 December 2010 (UTC)
:Sorry, which &quot;POV-pushing, anti-Catholic rhetoric&quot; is that? Could you identify it please?--[[User:Taiwan boi|Taiwan boi]] ([[User talk:Taiwan boi|talk]]) 04:07, 18 December 2010 (UTC)

''This is addressed to all involved editors:'' Hello. This message is being sent to inform you that there currently is a discussion at [[Wikipedia:Administrators' noticeboard/Incidents]] regarding an issue with which you may have been involved.   &lt;!--Template:ANI-notice--&gt; Thank you. [[User:Drmies|Drmies]] ([[User talk:Drmies|talk]]) 04:16, 18 December 2010 (UTC)
*More precisely: [[Wikipedia:Administrators'_noticeboard/Incidents#Accusation_.28mine.29_of_personal_attacks.2C_uncivil_behavior|this section]]. Thank you. [[User:Drmies|Drmies]] ([[User talk:Drmies|talk]]) 04:18, 18 December 2010 (UTC)
:::Esoglou editwarring just today.
#Diff 1[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Theosis&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=403357012&amp;oldid=403355394]
#Diff 2[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Theosis&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=403358108&amp;oldid=403357616]
#Diff 3[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Theosis&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=403359957&amp;oldid=403359034]
#Diff 4[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Theosis&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=403362144&amp;oldid=403361274] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 15:47, 20 December 2010 (UTC)

== Multiple articles covering Palamism ==

NB: I am NOT, at this time, proposing a merger of any articles.  However, I do think we should look at the inadequacy of coverage of Palamism in multiple articles.

[[Palamism]] used to redirect to [[Tabor Light]] (which was, in my opinion, the wrong place for it to redirect)

In addition to the article on [[Gregory Palamas]], we also have articles on [[Theosis (Eastern Orthodox theology)]],[[Hesychasm]],[[Essence-Energies distinction]] and [[Tabor Light]].

It seems to me that all of these articles (except for the biographical one on Palamas himself) are just parts of the overall doctrine known as Palamism.  We could either merge all of these articles into one big one titled [[Palamism]] or we could at least construct an article titled [[Palamism]] that introduces each of the subtopics in [[WP:SUMMARY|summary style]] and then links to the main article on each subtopic. 

I think that having so many articles gives the reader a fragmented view of Palamism and requires him to find and read several articles in order to construct an integrated and complete picture.  It is much like the four blind men describing different parts of the elephant.

To address this problem, I've created an article titled [[Palamism]].  At the moment, it is not much more than a collection of lead sections plus the section titled &quot;Development of the Doctrine&quot; that I originally assembled for this article from [[Hesychasm]] and[[Gregory Palamas]].  I hope this new article can serve as an &quot;umbrella&quot; summary article for all these detailed articles that describe different parts of the elephant. 

--[[User:Richardshusr|Richard S]] ([[User talk:Richardshusr|talk]]) 21:59, 27 December 2010 (UTC)

:I just happened to look on here after quite some time Richard, and I suggest not even thinking of a merger. The unfortunate situation, as I see it is the following:

::* This article itself looks like it was hit by a hurricane and an earthquake at the same time. I think it was shorter before from what I remember, but in any case, now it seems to have been the subject of a lot of debate. I have not (and will not) even read the debates to see who was saying what, but the article seems to be suffering not from a lack of facts, but the lack of harmony. 

::* The articles on [[Hesychasm]], [[Tabor light]], etc. have somehow been saved from the hurricane and actually help readers. This article is so long and twisted that it does not help any Wikipedia reader in my opinion.

:Therefore, until this disaster has been attended to by the United Nations, the Red Cross and other relief agencies (of which I am not a member) let us let the poor readers have some more usable and shorter articles that can teach them things, instead of inviting them all here. [[User:History2007|History2007]] ([[User talk:History2007|talk]]) 12:59, 10 January 2011 (UTC)
::Yes I say that the article be separated back up and left as a Eastern Orthodox theology article. It is bad enough that Richard and Esoglou as putting their POV on this article. And the [[contemplation]] article covers for the hisoty of the philosophy and its philosophy history what Esoglou has forcing into this article. How is it that one can make any sense of Eastern Orthodox theology when two VERY AGRESSIVE editors whom are not knowable of these subjects is making edits that obfuscate the Greek understanding. I would like to include the randomness of Maixmos and the modern manifestation of those ideas as expressed in the math of Markov and Kolmogorv and Pavle Florovsky and in more modern time Nicholas Metropolis and Taleb. But there can not be a EO Sumbebekos[http://orthodoxinfo.com/inquirers/orth_plato.aspx] article with editors like Esoglou on here obfuscating the subjects so that people can not understand the Eastern Orthodox perspective. These two &quot;editors&quot; have been edit warring against Byzantine philosophy being mentioned in the Gregory Palamas Essence Energy distinction article and why would Orthodox even try with the sarcasm and obfuscating of editors on Wikipedia. [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 15:02, 10 January 2011 (UTC)
:::The article is on ''theoria'', a matter that concerns much more than the Eastern Orthodox Church: as the citations show, it was even being discussed centuries before Christianity.  The article has on the Eastern Orthodox Church's view of ''theoria'' a section two and a half times as long as all the rest of the article together, and which it would be well to cut down in size and make more readable.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 15:53, 10 January 2011 (UTC)
::::At 138kb, the article is way too long and thus could benefit from being split up.  The Eastern Orthodox section is 98kb long and thus is already at the limit of what a long article should be.  My rough rule of thumb is that articles really need to stop growing around 100kb.  
::::This suggests that there could be two articles ([[Theoria (Eastern Orthodox theology)]] and [[Theoria]].  The general article on [[Theoria]] would include a truncated summary of the more specific article on [[Theoria (Eastern Orthodox theology)]].  
::::I acknowledge that History2007 was not complaining about the length of the article but about a lack of cohesion and cogency.  Splitting the article will not necessarily fix that but it may help.  It will at least address LoveMonkey's complaint about material that is unrelated to the Eastern Orthodox concept of theoria.
::::I will also take this opportunity to take exception to my being maligned for interference in articles and discussions that I have not been involved in.
::::--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 16:28, 10 January 2011 (UTC)
Hey, History2007, if you think this article got hit by a hurricane, what do you make of [[Roman Catholic–Eastern Orthodox theological differences]]?  That article makes this article look like it got hit by a dust devil. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 01:25, 11 January 2011 (UTC)

== Proposed move to [[Theoria (Eastern Orthodox Theology)]] ==

Per discussion immediately above, this will allow a split of the current article into two articles: [[Theoria (Eastern Orthodox theology)]] that focuses specifically on Eastern Orthodox theology and [[Theoria]] which covers the general topic of Theoria including a summary of the more detailed article on Theoria from the Eastern Orthodox POV. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 20:45, 10 January 2011 (UTC)
::Oh really, so now you propose it after Esoglou resisted it when Paul M. Nguyen suggested it in October and Esoglou told him NO.[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3ATheoria&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=391453753&amp;oldid=391451988] [[User:LoveMonkey|LoveMonkey]] ([[User talk:LoveMonkey|talk]]) 03:33, 11 January 2011 (UTC)
:::[This constant hostility is getting tiresome.]
:::It would appear that Esoglou misread Paul M. Nguyen's proposal.  Reading Paul's comment carefully, it seems that his use of the word &quot;branching this article&quot; could be interpreted to mean &quot;splitting the article into two&quot;.  Esoglou's reply seemed to interpret Paul's proposal to change the article scope to focus primarily on the Eastern Orthodox view.  
:::Besides, at the time of Paul's proposal, this article was ''only'' 93kb long.  Pretty long in my book but not yet needing immediate attention to split the article.  At 132kb, it has now gone from &quot;very long&quot; to &quot;too long&quot;.  It's time to seriously consider splitting the article.
:::--[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 05:44, 11 January 2011 (UTC)
::::Moreover, I have been known to change my mind when cogent reasons are presented.  However, I am still not convinced that the only remedy for the disproportionate space (c. 72%) that this article gives to the view of theologians of one church is to create for their view an article of its own - this isn't Orthodoxwiki.  I intended to express no opinion here and abstain, but LM seems to be particularly interested in what I think.  I still do not expressly or strongly oppose.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:02, 11 January 2011 (UTC)
:::::Esoglou, if you haven't already seen this [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:LoveMonkey&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=407231944&amp;oldid=407228607 comment] that I made on LoveMonkey's [[User talk:LoveMonkey|Talk Page]], you might wish to read it. --[[User:Pseudo-Richard|Pseudo-Richard]] ([[User talk:Pseudo-Richard|talk]]) 08:25, 11 January 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>r18ab1q087ztmc8n53lavnpf1qpfgqt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
