<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Seven-day week</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>21046989</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517542408</id>
      <parentid>433381083</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-13T08:58:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wikimedes</username>
        <id>5839679</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Found on Tuesday */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17013">{{Astrology project}}
{{WikiProject Time|class=start}}
{{oldafdfull | date = 11 January 2009 | result = '''keep''' | page = 7 Day Week }}

== Continuous since Exodus ==

I have decided to start this discussion due to a number of 'undos' for uncited claims that the seven-day week has been continuous since [[Exodus]], and the [[10 commandments]]. This is not proved and there are justified doubts. Two are; [[Joshua]] and the long/48 hour day, and secondly the [[Counting of the Omer|49 day count]]. 

The Jews are LIVING proof that the seven day week has been continuous since  [[Exodus]], and the [[10 commandments]].  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Yes3232|Yes3232]] ([[User talk:Yes3232|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Yes3232|contribs]]) 08:40, 20 October 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

The Sumerians, prior to [[Exodus]], counted 49 days, attributed the day to [[Gula]], God of Healing, and a sacrifice made (&lt;small&gt;Reference: Hastings, James; John A. Selbie (2003). ''Encyclopedia of Religion and Ethics Part 20.'' Kessinger Publishing. pp. 890. ISBN 766136981, 9780766136984. [http://books.google.com/books?id=qVNqXDz4CE8C http://books.google.com/books?id=qVNqXDz4CE8C].&lt;/small&gt;) This was not 7 weeks. The period of 49 days overlapped the end of a lunar month that contains a leap day or two. So it was normally on the 19th day of the new cycle of weeks. 

And like the Sumerians, the count of the [[passover]] begins from the cycle of the moon.

Now we say 'seven-weeks' which would be easy to count. But this is a modern interpretation of 49 days in the original text.

So for these reasons we are left with reasonable doubt for this to be included in this Article. A citation of Exodus is not good enough. I hope someone can expand this to provide a citation for or against --[[User:Pnb73|Pnb73]] ([[User talk:Pnb73|talk]]) 14:35, 22 January 2009 (UTC)


==Replacement for earlier 7-day week by later 7-day week: Sumerian==
This section seems to be either a well-constructed hoax or [[WP:OR|original research]] as Wiggermann, the cited reference, doesn't '''discuss''' the days of the week ''at all''. The text on pages 8 and 9 of Wiggermann is a primary Sumerian document and its translation into English.  That document does mention seven statues, with their colors, and their identifications with personages from seven cities.  The statutes have additional names using the word day: (1) &quot;day of life&quot; (2) &quot;day of plenty&quot; (3) &quot;day off&quot; (4) &quot;good day&quot; (5) &quot;fair faced day&quot; (6) &quot;righteous day&quot; and (7) &quot;day that gives life to the slain&quot;.
See [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=xYX64ZkwkMIC&amp;pg=PA9 http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=xYX64ZkwkMIC&amp;pg=PA9].  However there is no indication that the word ''day'' is used in the sense of ''day of the week'', as opposed to any of the other meanings that cuneiform symbol can represent. Wiggermann does not elaborate on this. --[[User:Bejnar|Bejnar]] ([[User talk:Bejnar|talk]]) 01:20, 5 February 2010 (UTC)

==Sumerian week==
The article Englund, R. K. (1988) &quot;Administrative Timekeeping in Ancient Mesopotamia&quot; ''Journal of the Economic and Social History of the Orient'' 31(2): pp. 121-185, does not mention any names for the days of the week, although the author does say, in footnote 7 on page 127, ''It is likely that the often noted periods of 7 and 15 days represent not necessarily moon phases, but successive divisions of the 30-day month by 2 required by household administration. This division of the month, moreover, would not be surprising in any synodical calendar in preclassical and classical antiquity, so that there is neither need to recognize magic Babylonian numbers (entirely implausible the suggestion of H. andJ Lewy, HUCA 17 [1942-1943] 19, that the week originated in a Babylonian system of seven wind directions) nor to assume, for instance, a need for dispersed market days, in order to reasonably explain our seven day week.'' Later on pages 161-162, the author says: ''J. Friberg has suggested in ''Scientific American'' 250/2 (February, 1984) 111, that the period recorded in OECT 7, Nr. 94 represented a week of 5 days; considering however that the only other parallel text Nr. 40 records in like fashion a period of 4 days, and that a reasonable reconstruction of the absolute measures of the SE system would, if at all, favor a week of 6 days (corresponding to the sign N39 = 6N30; see below), this proposal cannot be sustained.'' --[[User:Bejnar|Bejnar]] ([[User talk:Bejnar|talk]]) 01:22, 5 February 2010 (UTC)

== Week numbers ==

I'm not too happy with the presentation in the section on week numbers.

Below is some stuff I wrote, based on what's allready there. What do you think?

===== Week numbering systems =====

There are numerous different systems for numbering the weeks of a year. We will here discuss three of these systems.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Usage !! First day of the week !! Last week of each year contains !! Week 1 of each year contains !! Legend for the table below
|-
| ISO 8601, used in most of Europe || Monday || Last Thursday and Dec 28 || Jan 4 and first Thursday || Red frame
|-
| USA &amp; Canada || Sunday || Last Sunday to Dec 31 || Jan 1 to first Saturday || Blue background
|-
| Much of Middle East || Saturday || Last Saturday to Dec 31 || Jan 1 to first Friday || Green frame and text
|}

[[File:Week numbering systems.gif|800px]]

The table in the image indicates the days counted as week 1 by the three week numbering systems (ISO 8601: Red frame; America: Blue background; Middle East: Green frame and text). Each table line represents the period around New Year when January 1st falls on a certain weekday. Non-leap years always begin and end on the same weekday, so a year that begins as shown in one table line ends as shown in the table line below (where the top line is taken to follow the bottom line). Leap years skip down one line extra.

If we only consider the weekdays Monday-Friday, the week numbers throughout the year only differ for years beginning on a Friday or a Saturday (as shown in the first two lines of the table), where the ISO week numbers will be one less than the American week numbers. In years beginning on a Friday, the Middle Eastern week numbers will agree with the American ones, where as in years beginning on a Saturday, they will agree with the ISO numbers.

One further difference is that the ISO system counts the days marked with a red cross in the table as part of a week of the previous or following year; the other two systems avoid this by letting most years begin and end in weeks with less than 7 days. In the ISO system, years that begin or end on a Thursday have a week 53; all other years only have up to week 52. In the other two systems, leap years that begin with a one-day week 1 end with a one-day week 54; all other years only have up to week 53.

From year 1901 to 2099, the Gregorian calendar repeats in cycles of 28 years; the last column in the table indicates one such cycle (year 2000 to 2027). The years 1900 and 2100 are not leap years and hence break this cycle.

===== Weeks assigned twice confusion =====

The table has a column called &quot;Weeks assigned twice&quot; (yes/no), but there's no explanation of what being assigned twice means.  Would somebody please fix that?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jmatxx|Jmatxx]] ([[User talk:Jmatxx|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jmatxx|contribs]]) 06:38, 11 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== conflation of origin in an individual editors cultural horizon and origin in human cultural development ==

Man first observes lunation. Then this may (or may not) be assigned a number of days which is entirely culturally determined. That it is associated with religion is simply a reflection of the historical fact of human development and the preponderance of religion before the rise of scientific and secular culture. The typical divisions range from none to halving, quartering (the subject of this article), to thirds (an asian  norm). The insistence on the exactitude of lunation is specious and appears to reflect some Judeo-Christian simplicity. Proper research will show the facts to be diametrically opposite to this cultural bias which is why I tagged the section in question. For, example, other things being equal, one expects that those adopting quartering will be as likely to give the first as the last day special significance. [[Special:Contributions/72.228.177.92|72.228.177.92]] ([[User talk:72.228.177.92|talk]]) 20:32, 26 August 2010 (UTC)

== Contradiction in origins ==

It is a bizarre contradiction in the origins section that it is first noted that the Babylonians had an adjustment week to fit a seven day week to the lunar cycle then to proclaim the non-existence of records indicating that Babylonians &quot;linked&quot; their system to a quarter of a lunation. The quotation marks are mine as I despise the term &quot;linked&quot; as vague to the point of meaninglessness at best. Quite clearly, if you have the first behavior documented then the second follows as the first is simply a specific iteration of the more general second. BTW, if you disallow electric lights and clocks for a while it becomes plain that timing based upon astronomical events involves no naturalism or any other ism.
[[Special:Contributions/74.241.11.136|74.241.11.136]] ([[User talk:74.241.11.136|talk]]) 13:17, 8 September 2010 (UTC)

I also stumbled over this and I found the mathematical argument -- that 5-day or 10-day-weeks would be have been more plausible -- interesting at first, but naive from a practical point of view, since the [[Lunar phase|lunar quarters]] have a clear visible representation (and are even today still marked in some paper calendars in the Western world).
--[[User:Tromberg|Tromberg]] ([[User talk:Tromberg|talk]]) 05:42, 28 December 2010 (UTC)

== 7 visible objects in the sky... ==

I've just removed a delightful but unsourced addition from the article - revision 394144985 by [[Special:Contributions/86.186.33.184|86.186.33.184]] ([[User talk:86.186.33.184|talk]]). It would be great if someone could find a source and make the style a little more boring - erh, I mean, more encyclopaedic (&quot;voluptuous Venus&quot;, &quot;Ymirday night entertainment&quot;, ...)! Here's the full text:--[[User:Nø|Nø]] ([[User talk:Nø|talk]]) 16:05, 1 November 2010 (UTC)

:''A more obvious pattern, shrouded in the taboos of monotheistic religions, is that the seven-day week arises from the fact that there are seven objects in the solar system visible to the naked eye from Earth – the Sun, the Moon and the five classical naked eye planets: Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus, and Saturn. In early religions, these may have represented the most important Gods, with Monday and Friday usually being linked to the two main matriarchal Goddesses of Motherhood and Love, with the rest being left over for the patriarchal Gods. The pattern can be most clearly seen in the French language which gives us Lundi, from &quot;dies Lunae&quot;, the day of the Moon; Mardi, from &quot;dies Martis&quot;, the day of Mars; Mercredi, from &quot;dies Mercurii&quot;, the day of Mercury; Jeudi, from &quot;dies Jovis&quot;, the day of Jupiter; Vendredi, from &quot;dies Veneris&quot;, the day of Venus; and Samedi, from &quot;dies Saturni&quot;, the day of Saturn. According to this pattern, the final day of the week in French should be Soldi, from &quot;dies Solis&quot;, though it is of course Dimanche, from &quot;dies Dominica&quot;, which is the day of the Lord. Getting back to the English language, the words &quot;Day&quot; and &quot;Deity&quot; may also be related via this ancient primitive religious origin, through the Proto-Indo-European word &quot;dyeu&quot;, meaning &quot;to shine&quot;. In English, you can also see this planetary pattern, if you work through the day-naming scheme of Julius Caesar, in which Germanic Gods and Goddesses were substituted for Roman ones, with Tiu for belligerent Mars, Woden for quicksilver Mercury, Thor for thunderbolt Jupiter, and Freya for voluptuous Venus. Sunday and Monday are fairly obvious inserts for the Sun and the Moon, and because Caesar could identify no Germanic God who was the father of Woden, this leaves us with Saturday named directly after the Roman God Saturn (Greek Cronos), who was the father of Jupiter (Greek Zeus). Let us be thankful that Caesar neglected to uncover Ymir, the father of Woden, otherwise Saturday night entertainment would be Ymirday night entertainment, or more likely through the passage to time, Yumday night entertainment. We must also remember the ancient Greeks too, who used their own God and Goddess names for days of the week, which the Romans later copied and translated into their own equivalent deities. The ancient Greek days were hemera helio, &quot;day of the sun&quot;; hemera selenes, &quot;day of the moon&quot;; hemera Areos, &quot;day of Ares&quot;; hemera Hermu, &quot;day of Hermes&quot;; hemera Dios, &quot;day of Zeus&quot;; hemera Aphrodites, &quot;day of Aphrodite&quot;; and hemera Khronu, &quot;day of Cronus&quot;. No doubt many other ancient early religions and cultures who adopted a seven-day week also used the same pattern to name their own days of the week, especially the Proto-Indo-Europeans.''--[[Special:Contributions/86.186.33.184|86.186.33.184]] ([[User talk:86.186.33.184|talk]])

Granted that some of that was a little imaginative, isn't it generally assumed that the week does reflect the 7 celestial bodies? I can't believe that wasn't already in the article. Didn't it used to be? — [[User:Kwamikagami|kwami]] ([[User talk:Kwamikagami|talk]]) 21:01, 1 November 2010 (UTC)

== &quot;or a week that divided the lunation more accurately using a factor of these number systems, such as a five-day or ten-day week&quot; ==

(look http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division_%28mathematics%29#Division_of_integers )
if 29,5 day phase is divided with remainder, if it is divided by 5, it will give 4.5 days remainder, if with 10 - 9.5 days remainder, so, dividing by 7 gives most little remainder - 1.5 days.
so, where from have got this phrase who has written it? that &quot;it is not immediately apparent why the seven-day week was selected by ancient cultures&quot; ? or this is original research? [[User:Qdinar|Qdinar]] ([[User talk:Qdinar|talk]]) 16:01, 4 February 2011 (UTC)

== sennight? ==

[[sennight]] redirects here, but no explanation... is this a term for &quot;seven days&quot;? --[[User:Androl|androl]] ([[User talk:Androl|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 14:23, 2 March 2011 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I second that question. It seems pretty ridiculous to have a word redirect to an article that does not contain any mention of that word. --[[Special:Contributions/66.41.56.31|66.41.56.31]] ([[User talk:66.41.56.31|talk]]) 22:07, 3 May 2011 (UTC)

:It seems to be a genuine word, parallel to fortnight, dating back to 15th century - [http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/sennight Merriam-Webster]; [http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/sennight Wikitionary].
:But if the redirect is to remain, this word should be mentioned (and preferably bolded) in the lead.--[[User:Nø|Nø]] ([[User talk:Nø|talk]]) 13:13, 9 June 2011 (UTC)

== Lunar phase ==

Seven-day week came from the [[Lunar phase]]. New Moon, First Quarter, Full Moon and Last Quarter: There are nearly 7 days between them! / reliable source: ''Time and the calendars'' (by W.M. O'Neil) [[User:Böri|Böri]] ([[User talk:Böri|talk]]) 13:48, 8 June 2011 (UTC)
:: The name &quot;month&quot; came from the moon... Of course, they knew the lunar phase. (a month = 4 weeks) as easy as like that [[User:Böri|Böri]] ([[User talk:Böri|talk]]) 12:03, 9 June 2011 (UTC)

== Found on Tuesday ==

Hello. I found this in the article on [[Tuesday]] and thought it would be more appropriate here.  I'm not sure how to shoe horn it in to this article, or even if it should be done, so I've copied it here in case someone wants to give it a go.

&lt;blocKquote&gt;The [[weekday heptagram]], i.e. the association of the days of the seven-day week with the seven [[classical planets]],  probably dates to the [[Hellenistic period]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It was with the adoption and widespread use of the seven-day week throughout the Hellenistic world of mixed cultures that this heptagram was created.&quot; [http://www.symbols.com/encyclopedia/29/2916.html Symbol 29:16]&lt;/ref&gt;
Between the 1st and 3rd centuries, the [[Roman Empire]] gradually replaced the eight day Roman [[Roman calendar#Nundinal cycle|nundinal cycle]] with the seven-day week. The astrological order of the days was explained by [[Vettius Valens]] and [[Dio Cassius]]. According to these authors, it was a principle of astrology that the heavenly bodies presided, in succession, over the hours of the day.&lt;/blocKquote&gt;

--[[User:Wikimedes|Wikimedes]] ([[User talk:Wikimedes|talk]]) 08:58, 13 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hulteqjhgyw3e617ccnjzs7oc4lfnxt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
