<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Augustinians</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5323117</id>
    <revision>
      <id>439723009</id>
      <parentid>438458005</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-07-16T03:19:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Daniel the Monk</username>
        <id>10854501</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notation of Dates */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5971">{{talkheader}}
{{Project Catholicism|class=b|importance=high}}



==Problems with [[Hermits of St. Augustine]] page==
I think that the [[Hermits of St. Augustine]] article must merge to this one considering the fact that in April of 1963, the General Fr. Luciano Rubio
decrets that &quot;The Institution will be called from now [[Order of Saint Augustine]] (O.S.A.) in sustitution to &quot;Hermits of Saint Augustine&quot; or &quot;Order of  de Frairs of Hermits of Saint  Augustine (OESA).
The article Hermits of St. Augustine have very high quality information of the order's history. 
what do you think?


==Rule==
I would question the conclusion here that the Rule was not written by Augustine himself.  Certainly there is scholarly debate over its dating, but as far as I am aware that is now mostly considered within the context of his life and other works.  The Rule very closely reflects his own theological concerns and spirituality, and is easily placed as an instruction either for his own monastery in Hippo or for one of the various communities he patronized as a bishop.  Can any major modern scholars or arguments be cited to the contrary?
--[[User:ADMH|ADMH]] 12:50, 28 May 2006 (UTC)

The point is AMDG that you need to post a reference to show this. I went to an Augustinian school (and a novitiate) and I was outraged to see the (arguably Protestant) assertion that the rule is not sourced from Augustine himself. Our mission is to find the references, post them on wiki, and then edit the article to make it more accurate. Our feelings don't matter on wiki. Facts do!
[[User:Njamesdebien|Cor Unum]] 13:05, 29 May 2006 (UTC)

I have been working on this page. Interested in comments from other wikipedians.

cheers
[[User:Njamesdebien|Cor Unum]] 09:32, 11 June 2006 (UTC)

== Removed the School Sister of Notre Dame==
I removed these from the aggregated orders because even though they appear on the official lists of the Auygustinian family (on the order's international website), I cannot find any evidence of the Augustinian rule on their own websites. Decided to be safe rather than sorry. Can anyone help here?


== Admirable job ==
As Wikipedia has grown in authority, so many have added articles that read more like flackery. This is a lovely example of a fact-laden and -constrained article. Kudos. --[[User:Djenner|djenner]] 23:53, 6 March 2007 (UTC)

== 1,000,000 years old? ==

At the end of the Augustinian Ethos section, the article states that the boys choir is 1,000,000 years old.  I doubt that that number is accurate.  What is the real age of the choir?  Someone who is a subject matter expert please correct this error. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/199.1.42.30|199.1.42.30]] ([[User talk:199.1.42.30|talk]]) 14:39, 20 March 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;
: The current edit says it is over ONE THOUSAND years old- which is correct. See the entry on the  monastery for references [[User:Njamesdebien|Cor Unum]] 07:18, 6 May 2007 (UTC)

== Schools ==

I pulled this section out of the [[Merrimack College]] article, as it doesn't seem to fit there.  It points to a subsection of this article that doesn't exist as main article.  Was it removed?  Should it be added?

===The Augustinians in North America===
The [[Augustinians#History in the New World: North America|North American foundation]] of the order was founded in 1796 when Irish friars arrived in Philadelphia. Michael Hurley was the first American to join the Order the following year. Friars established schools, including universities throughout the Americas, including the only two Augustinian institutions of higher learning in the U.S. [[Villanova University]] in [[Villanova, PA]] and [[Merrimack College]] in North Andover, MA.

High Schools were also founded in the U.S. including: [[Austin Preparatory School]]|[[Reading, MA]], [[Malvern Preparatory School]] [[Malvern, PA ]]in 1842, [[St. Rita of Cascia High School]] in [[Chicago, IL]] by 1909, [[St. Augustine High School]] [[San Diego, CA]] in 1922, [[Villanova Preparatory School]] [[Ojai, CA]] in 1925;[[Cascia Hall Preparatory School]] [[Tulsa, OK]] in 1926;[[Monsignor Bonner High School]] Pennsylvania in 1953; [[St. Augustine College Preparatory School]] New Jersey in 1959 and in 1962 [[Providence Catholic High School]] in Illinois.
The educational and spiritual traditions of the Order of Saint Augustine (1244 CE) enrich each of the academic communities.
:Have inserted the above text into the article.--[[User:Felix Folio Secundus|Felix Folio Secundus]] ([[User talk:Felix Folio Secundus|talk]]) 10:36, 23 September 2009 (UTC)

== Cardinal Richard ==

:&quot;The importance of this man in the foundation of the Order cannot be understated&quot;

I think someone probably meant &quot;cannot be overstated&quot;.  Or was Cardinal Richard really that insignificant? [[User:GoldenRing|GoldenRing]] ([[User talk:GoldenRing|talk]]) 18:17, 4 May 2011 (UTC)

== Notation of Dates ==

I noticed that you changed the format of some dates in this article from the standard American usage of Month/Day/Year to the European one of Day/Month/Year. I didn't write that section and so have no vested interest. I am curious, though, as to your reason for so doing. Is there a Wiki rule which requires it? [[User:Daniel the Monk|Daniel the Monk]] ([[User talk:Daniel the Monk|talk]]) 18:54, 8 July 2011 (UTC)

:I changed the date format because the subject is primarily a European-oriented one, and that the dates themselves pre-dated the existence of the nation which created the mdy format.  For those reasons it would be incongruous to have a date format peculiar to the US. [[User:JohnArmagh|JohnArmagh]] ([[User talk:JohnArmagh|talk]]) 19:08, 8 July 2011 (UTC)
:: I have to say that I find that reasoning rather peculiar, but so be it.[[User:Daniel the Monk|Daniel the Monk]] ([[User talk:Daniel the Monk|talk]]) 03:19, 16 July 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>lw2i6ys6vr8t8ykc4yv6im2bv10b2ji</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
