<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Calendar of saints</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>402809</id>
    <revision>
      <id>407143597</id>
      <parentid>381708601</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-01-10T21:43:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zginder</username>
        <id>1262018</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>importance=low in wp:time</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5312">St. Loup's feast day is/was September 1. I have a slide (not scanned yet) of the KL page from a couple of MSs that show that, if it's useful; the one that's in there is nice, but it's not from Sens[[Special:Contributions/24.34.104.12|24.34.104.12]] ([[User talk:24.34.104.12|talk]]) 20:59, 29 March 2009 (UTC)covalence2

:Does anyone fancy working on [[wikipedia:WikiProject Christian liturgical year|WikiProject Christian liturgical year]]? [[User:Garzo|Gareth Hughes]] 11:09, 21 Feb 2005 (UTC)
   maybe...but I have several other projects going so I could probably only help with the few saints and events that I'm otherwise currently working on[[Special:Contributions/24.34.104.12|24.34.104.12]] ([[User talk:24.34.104.12|talk]]) 20:59, 29 March 2009 (UTC)covalence2

{{WikiProject Time|class=start|importance=low}}

{{WikiProject Saints|class=start|importance=top}}
People in France mark the name day -- maybe restricted to catholics though.mOST OF TH EVARY MANY DUDES THAT  ARE catholics elsewhere too?

:Does anyone fancy working on [[wikipedia:WikiProject Christian liturgical year|WikiProject Christian liturgical year]]? [[User:Garzo|Gareth Hughes]] 11:09, 21 Feb 2005 (UTC)

I thought [[Bernard of Clairvaux]]'s feast day was May 28, but he isn't listed here and it isn't mentioned in his article.  Is this because it's untrue or because no one's added it? [[User:TUF-KAT|Tuf-Kat]] 21:26, Apr 20, 2005 (UTC)

== Confusing mishmash of lists ==

In order for it to make sense to include Pauline Catholic festal classifications (Solemnity, Feast, Memorial, Optional Memorial, Commemoration), this list would need to be limited to saints on the Pauline (modern) Catholic calendar, and that particular calendar would also need to be specified: Universal Calendar (for the whole Church), Albuquerque diocesan calendar, Franciscan calendar, etc.  For example, the titular feast of a parish (e.g. St. Patrick's Day for St. Patrick's Church) is raised to the rank of Solemnity, most countries have a national saint (for example, St. George in England) which are not considered &quot;Optional Memorials&quot; for the rest of the Church, etc.  If the goal is an ecumenical Christian liturgical calendar, this could be an aggregation of various more specific calendars.  But I would hate to lose the Universal (RC) Calendar information.  Perhaps a split is in order, perhaps a Portal?  --[[User:Tremont30|Tremont30]] 16:31, 24 October 2005 (UTC)

How about two separate calendars, one with the universal calendar, and a second listing with all the local feasts, either afterwards or as a separate article? I think it's best to keep the Catholic, Orthodox, Anglican, and other calendars separate, since putting them all together might be too confusing. [[User:12.208.18.23|12.208.18.23]] 02:19, 15 April 2006 (UTC)


:I dont think the goal is an ecumenical calendar at all.  If anything, the goal should be to respect the differences among the traditions.  This is an encyclopedia.  We can handle a variety of lists.  And what do you mean by Pauline?  That is not the common nomenclature especially since there are two major Pauline liturgical reforms--Paul V and Paul VI. If you mean Paul VI (which is more correct than Second Vatican Council) it is more proper to say &quot;Roman Missal 1969&quot; or reform of Paul VI.  --[[User:Vaquero100|Vaquero100]] 07:05, 14 May 2006 (UTC)

I've always heard the Tridentine Missal referred to as the Missal of Pius V, not Paul V, who was elected Pope in 1605, well after the 1570 Missal which followed the Council of Trent. &quot;Pauline&quot;, as I've always seen it used refers to the 1969 Missal with its revisions. [[User:PaulGS|PaulGS]] 00:00, 12 July 2006 (UTC)

== December 25: Nativity of the Ford (Christmas) - Solemnity ==

I could be wrong but shouldn't that read 'Lord' rather than 'Ford'?--[[User:Jimmyjrg|Jimmyjrg]] 11:54, 7 February 2006 (UTC)
* Clear vandalism. I reverted that and the other addition on the same edition: Novus ''Porno'' Missae for [[Novus Ordo Missae]] [[User:Monkeycheetah|Monkeycheetah]] 13:33, 7 February 2006 (UTC)

== Only universal calendar ==
Is this only the universal calendar? Or does it include diocesan and congregational traditions? --[[User:Benedikt|Benedikt]] 15:25, 25 February 2006 (UTC)
and to prove this, read on.....  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/83.202.26.100|83.202.26.100]] ([[User talk:83.202.26.100|talk]]) 16:51, 19 October 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Many feast days on Wikipedia Days pages are wrong ==
I've noticed that on Wikipedia's pages for each day of the year, many of the saints' days listed (no doubt in good faith by the editor/s who are doing a good job trying to add to the Holidays and Celebrations section) are not up to standard. Many have the saints' days wrong, and many link to the wrong saint -- sometimes not even to a saint but just a similar word. I'm no expert so I hope someone who is can clean these up. [[User:Alpheus|Alpheus]] 04:08, 14 May 2006 (UTC)

== &quot;Feast&quot; ==

A list of feasts might do with a few words on the topic of feasting, if not a menu suggestion or two.  [[User:Midgley|Midgley]] ([[User talk:Midgley|talk]]) 16:01, 29 August 2010 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ra319wrc9u3tglr57q87cjoar5spdln</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
