<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Number of the Beast (numerology)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5578518</id>
    <revision>
      <id>71775776</id>
      <parentid>71478075</parentid>
      <timestamp>2006-08-25T08:52:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Schutz</username>
        <id>27196</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Unreferenced */ reply</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4113">==Unreferenced==
This article doesn't really need references.  It's claims are self evident.  Take out your caculator and try them out.  You'll see that they are accurate. --[[User:Pmcchesn|Pmcchesn]] 15:39, 5 July 2006 (UTC)

:The claims are self evident, I agree, but are they encyclopedic ? Or, more generally, do they really refer to the &quot;number of the beast&quot; ? It seems to me that they simply refer to the number 666, whatever meaning some people have attached to it. Actually, most of the &quot;properties&quot; of the number are already indicated in [[666 (number)]], so I'll suggest to merge the two articles together. [[User:Schutz|Schutz]] 11:09, 23 August 2006 (UTC)
::All the information contained in this article is now in [[666 (number)]]; if noone disagrees, I'll make a redirect out of it. [[User:Schutz|Schutz]]
:::[[666 (number)]] is a confusing page.  The page in question is better organized and contains only the information relevant to its stated topic, whereas the 666 (number) is really just a listing of trivia without a unifying theme (aside from 666).  [[Number of the Beast (numerology)]] is as &quot;encyclopedic&quot; as 666 (number) and certainly deals with a topic directly related to the perceived mystical aspects of the [[Number of the Beast]].  I see no reason to merge. [[User:Pmcchesn|Pmcchesn]] 18:52, 23 August 2006 (UTC)
::::How do prime numbers and their squares, the natural numbers between 1 and 36 and roman numbers relate to this beast your are talking about ? They are properties of the number 666 and nothing else and if the bible had not mentioned this number, they would exist in exactly the same way; the same is true of any other integer number. If you want to talk about the &quot;perceived mystical aspects&quot; of 666, then you have to cite sources which indicate why these mathematical properties are interesting from the mystical point of view, and not just &quot;random&quot; properties; otherwise, this is [[WP:NOR|original research]]. The only &quot;fact&quot; that is linked with the beast stuff is the joke on the sine; but it is probably not worth having an article just for a joke like this. [[User:Schutz|Schutz]] 19:35, 23 August 2006 (UTC)
:::::I understand your point about this article not really relating to the number's religious connotations, but I don’t think it represents original research.  Its claims are readily verifiable and have been published before (see http://mathworld.wolfram.com/BeastNumber.html).  Furthermore, they are joked about commonly in the mathematical circles I have observed.  
:::::[[Number of the Beast (mathematical properties)]] might be a better title.  However, while I do not personally believe in numerology, I do believe that people attach supernatural significance to the topics discussed in this article.  But I'm not sure that I could find a reference demonstrating this.  Perhaps we should mark the article for deletion and put the decision to a vote with three possible courses of action:

:::::1) Keep the article and title intact.
:::::2) Merge the article to [[666 (number)]]
:::::3) Change the title to Number of the Beast (mathematical properties)

:::::What do you think? [[User:Pmcchesn|Pmcchesn]] 22:46, 23 August 2006 (UTC)
::::::Listing the article for deletion does not strike me as the best solution (since it is not one of the possible courses of action), but given that I don't see where else this could be discuted, I'd say: good idea, let's go for it. Can you do it, or do you want me to do it ? [[User:Schutz|Schutz]] 08:52, 25 August 2006 (UTC)

==Richard==
I grew up in a remote mountain area in China. I started to learn Chinese abacus when I was a little child. My grandpa told me to add up the first 36 numbers. Number 666 is a way to check whether I did correct abacus additions.

==JPII==
I deleted the section called &quot;JPII&quot;.  None of it, including the section's title itself, makes much sense to me.  Perhaps some additional explanation would make it more clear.  However, I believe this article should deal only with the numerical properties of 666 and not be based on any cultural aspects.  There other articles for that.</text>
      <sha1>msj4n6jb2saowl1uce1lv362n80iy6q</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
