<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Original sin</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>22737</id>
    <revision>
      <id>508933133</id>
      <parentid>508933048</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-24T13:37:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jasonasosa</username>
        <id>2644656</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Eastern Christianity/Orthodoxy */ b</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13952">{{talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
 {{WPReligion|class=C|importance=}}
  {{WikiProject Christianity|class=C|importance=high
  |anglicanism=yes|anglicanism-importance=
  |calvinism=yes|calvinism-importance=
  |catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=top
  |eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern orthodoxy-importance=
  |latter-day-saint-movement=yes|latter-day-saint-movement-importance=mid
  |lutheranism=yes|lutheranism-importance=
  |methodism-importance=yes
  |seventh-day-adventist-church=yes|seventh-day-adventist-church-importance=
  |theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=Top
 }}
}}
{{WikiWorld|File:Calvin wikiworld.jpg}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=17:49, 12 Dec 2003
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Original sin
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=2066822

|action2=FAR
|action2date=20:23, 22 May 2004
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article removal candidates/Original sin
|action2result=demoted
|action2oldid=3859867

|currentstatus=FFA
}}
{{Archive box|search=yes|
*[[/Archive 1|August-December, 2006]]
*[[/Archive 2|January 2007-December 2010]] }}

== Universal Infant Salvation argued by some ==

While Augustine argued for original sin and its application to infants, many modern theologians and pastors, including Calvinists, argue for the universal salvation of infants.   As Calvinism would support, salvation is ultimately &quot;not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that showeth mercy&quot; (Romans 9:16). The Bible describes a work of the Holy Spirit (almost certainly regenerative) taking place in the infant lives of Jeremiah the prophet (Jeremiah 1:5) and John the Baptism (Luke 1:15).  While the loss of any infant is certainly a sad event, the eternal state of the infant must be somewhat entrusted to a righteous and holy God who is able to sanctify or not to sanctify infants even in the womb.  Calvinist arguments for universal infant salvation put Calvinists in conflict with their own doctrine of eternal security because universally saved infants could ultimately grow older and lose their salvation and fall away.  

The doctrine of universal infant salvation even has the potential to influence arguments around [[abortion]] by implying that infants are universally, absolutely destined for eternal life in heaven while older children are not.  Arguments affirming both universal infant salvation and abortion would implicitly acknowledge that an unborn life has an eternal soul and an eternal destiny. Jesus Christ: &quot;Ye have heard that it was said of them of old time, Thou shalt not kill; and whosoever shall kill shall be in danger of the judgment: But I say unto you, That whosoever is angry with his brother without a cause shall be in danger of the judgment&quot; (Matthew 5:21-22).
[[Special:Contributions/75.220.10.254|75.220.10.254]] ([[User talk:75.220.10.254|talk]]) 12:08, 27 January 2011 (UTC)

==The doctrine is not found in other religions==
Well, that's what ''they'' say. There might be some mentioning of what Christians would say? Chesterton said: There was one thing the ancient world was certain about and that was the Fall. Thus in my personal view which, to avoid the question, I cannot source otherwise, original sin is the very essence of the Hindu religion and called bad karma - going so far as that Hindus lose the notion of actual sins and thus of the concept of sin at all. Muslims write in the cited source: &quot;Furthermore, Christian and Islamic concepts of sin are virtual opposites with respect to certain nuances.  For example, there is no concept of “sinning in the mind” in Islam; to a Muslim, an evil thought becomes a good deed when a person refuses to act upon it.  Overcoming and dismissing the evil thoughts which forever assail our minds is considered deserving of reward rather than punishment. Islamicly speaking, an evil thought only becomes sinful when acted upon.&quot; And thus they themselves admit that there are evil thoughts, and original sin is somewhat the doctrine of where they come from. (Except the notion that a bad thought is a, venial, sin in itself in general, they are besides basically right about them.) The Judaist source says that man is not inherently sinful, and we all agree with a voice of thunder. But if they say that he sins because he is not perfect, they should accept that Christians have decided to call this imperfection original sin. - I just can't understand why we must dispute not over the Christian Doctrine, but over what some seem to understand as the Christian Doctrine.[[Special:Contributions/77.4.89.113|77.4.89.113]] ([[User talk:77.4.89.113|talk]]) 17:30, 4 February 2011 (UTC)

:Chesterton was a journalist, and frequently wrong. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 11:06, 6 August 2011 (UTC)

== Original-research section ==

&quot;If no source exists for something you want to add to Wikipedia, it is 'original research'&quot;. The section on &quot;humans without original sin&quot; is based on nothing more than an editor's suppositions about the existence today of people not descended from Adam and the relevance of this first supposition to original sin, and also on the editor's own interpretation of Genesis 4 and the supposed relevance of the fossil evidence of the existence of species of the genus homo other than homo sapiens sapiens.  No reliable published source states what this section claims.  Even if true, &quot;all material added to articles must be attributable to a reliable published source&quot;.  See [[WP:OR]].  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 09:55, 11 February 2011 (UTC)

== Proposing: article for serious editing ==

Hello my fellow wiki-editors. Looking over this article, I hate to say it... but there is a lot of content in violation of [[wp:weight]], redundant content in several different places, and sourced content on the verge of [[wp:or]], [[wp:fringe]], [[wp:synth]], or just plain boring for any audience trying to get through this lengthy article, that just has a lot of blah blah blah. I'd really like to call in {{User|PiCo}} on this article. You've impressed upon me in earlier conversations, about how you like to consider what the audience wants to see. If you are able and willing [[User:PiCo]], I would really like to see your hacksaw. :&gt; If you're not up for it, that's okay... as I'm going to be sitting down at the table with {{User|‎Esoglou}} to get some feedback on what it was he wanted to see chopped up. (Gets out meat mincer.) You have the floor. Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 08:18, 20 August 2012 (UTC)
:I have earlier suggested to Jasonasosa a couple of minor (in my opinion) excisions of redundancy that have not yet been put into effect.  I did not suggest increasing the redundancy.  I await developments.  I might perhaps later suggest other reductions.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 16:26, 20 August 2012 (UTC)
::Okay, after looking through much of this article, content for Catholicism is [[wp:undue]], basically dominating the page. '''History of the doctrine''', '''Christian doctrine#Catholicism''', '''Original or ancestral sin''', and '''Rejection of personal guilt#Catholic church''' are all sections that are predominately based on the views of Catholicism. Interestingly, after reveiewing the [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church], the main content for the Catholicism view of Original sin isn't even included on the wikipage. Therefore, based on this source, I've developed a new introduction for the '''Catholicism''' section but I'm hesitant to post it yet, because it is in addition to the page, not a modification of the page and would cause the article to be extremely POV for Catholicism. So...  we have to snip somewhere... What I've noticed is  '''Christian doctrine#Catholicism''' and '''Rejection of personal guilt#Catholic church''' are redundant content and ought to be merged. So here is what I propose:
#Merge '''Christian doctrine#Catholicism''' and '''Rejection of personal guilt#Catholic church''' together.
#Merge '''Eastern Christianity''' and '''Eastern Orthodoxy'''
#Remove title '''Rejection of personal guilt''' altogether, and let the existing subsections fall under '''Christian doctrine'''
#Will supply new introduction for Catholicism based on [http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P1C.HTM Catechism of the Catholic Church 397-401]
#Find ways to identify duplicate Catholicism material and make some reductions, possibly in history section for starters.
::Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 07:50, 22 August 2012 (UTC)
:::I presume you mean: Merge &quot;Rejection of personal guilt#Christianity#Catholic Church&quot; ''into'' &quot;Christian doctrine#Catholicism&quot;, and &quot;Rejection of personal guilt#Christianity#Eastern Orthodoxy&quot; ''into'' &quot;Eastern Christianity&quot; (the particular into the general).  I have already suggested that these two &quot;merge from&quot; sections are practically no more than duplications and could well be eliminated.  The recently added heading &quot;Rejection of personal guilt&quot; itself (which is not the same as &quot;rejection of original sin&quot;) is a repetition of what is said about the doctrines of individual churches (other than classic forms of Protestantism) and the idea could simply be mentioned in the lead.  The Catholic doctrine, being as usual more nuanced and developed than some other beliefs, will for that reason require more space than those others, especially in view of the misrepresentations of it that are sometimes presented.  Indeed, many define their own beliefs not so much in positive terms as being different from what they imagine the Catholic doctrine to be.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 13:30, 22 August 2012 (UTC)
::::Agreed. And do accept my apology if I repeated an idea about how to proceed with editing those sections, as I had to study the information to reach my own conclusion, which happens to be in agreement with what has been suggested by you or others. However, my approach is to &quot;merge&quot; rather than arbitrarily delete sections, just to ensure nothing important is missed. I am also aware that the Catholicism portions will continue to remain larger than the other views, due mostly in part to its doctrinal history. &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 13:40, 22 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::Observations: &quot;Catholicism&quot; as generally understood does not include Eastern Orthodoxy; your change of the heading &quot;Eastern Christianity&quot; to &quot;Eastern Orthodoxy&quot; conflicts with the immediately following text, which speaks not of [[Eastern Orthodoxy]] alone but also of other elements of [[eastern Christianity]]: [[Oriental Orthodoxy]], [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholicism]] and the [[Church of the East]]; sooner or later, probably sooner, some Anglicans will object to your classification of Anglicanism under Protestantism.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 18:58, 22 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::Again: Why is Cassian put under Eastern Orthodoxy?  He wrote in Latin, was a formative influence on Western monasticism ...  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 20:45, 22 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::This is where I need you [[User:Esoglou]] to help me. There is no &quot;again&quot;, because this is the first time I've attempted to modify this article. The Anglicanism section is not ''my'' classification. If you look at the article's history, its been under there forever. Please don't pin on me content that is not mine or has been there before my edits. You've missed diagnosed my edits before, even on the [[Lucifer]] page like this. Given your observations, let me follow your lead. I shall restructure and await your positive critique.  Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 21:08, 22 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::::&quot;Again&quot; referred to an additional comment by me, not to anything you had done.  I apologize for using a phrase open to misinterpretation.  [[User:Esoglou|Esoglou]] ([[User talk:Esoglou|talk]]) 08:32, 23 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::::No worries. &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 13:05, 23 August 2012 (UTC)

===Eastern Christianity/Orthodoxy===
Many of the supporting references that are used in the '''Eastern''' section use Eastern Orthodox sources. Therefore, it is appropriate that this section be titled '''Eastern Orthodoxy'''. The section does not refer to the other traditions in [[Eastern Christianity]]. 

*www.pravoslavieto.com/docs/eng/Orthodox_Catechism_of_Philaret.htm
*www.stmaryorthodoxchurch.org/orthodoxy/articles/2004-hughes-sin.php stmaryorthodoxchurch.org
*www.stmaryorthodoxchurch.org/orthodoxy/articles/2004-hughes-sin.php
*www.gocanada.org/catechism/catorsin.htm
*www.oca.org
*http://fatherstephen.wordpress.com/2010/01/04/do-not-resent-do-not-react-keep-inner-stillness

Thanks, &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User talk:Jasonasosa|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jasonasosa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 13:37, 24 August 2012 (UTC)

== Robin Lane Fox's unauthorized version ==


Re [[User:Wran]]'s [[wp:agf]] edit:

14:18, 23 August 2012‎ Wran (talk | contribs)‎ . . (60,720 bytes) (+129)‎ . . (corrections) updated since my last visit (undo)

''Source for edit:''
{{cite book|last=Fox|first=Robin Lane|title=The unauthorized version : truth and fiction in the Bible|year=2006|publisher=Penguin|location=London|isbn=9780141022963}}

*'''Comment''': I question using [[Robin Lane Fox]]'s book ''unauthorized version'' as a [[wp:reliable]] source in the lede for the following reasons:
# Why is this book published by the [[Penguin Group]] and not by an academic publishing house? ''Penguin'' is known to publish [[Pseudo-scholarship]].
# Why does the source given not have a page number?</text>
      <sha1>2yt623f11ixx6p1fx7jer8qdi9t8zuz</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
