<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Calvinism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7311</id>
    <revision>
      <id>495241105</id>
      <parentid>495236659</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-31T04:17:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>StAnselm</username>
        <id>4007668</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Table */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9425">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=23:46, 23 July 2005
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Calvinism/archive1
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=19443059

|action2=GAN
|action2date=17:05, 19 December 2005
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=31979116

|action3=GAR
|action3date=11:49, 8 August 2006
|action3result=delisted
|action3oldid=67904591

|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{American English}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=Top|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=Top|methodism-work-group=yes|methodism-importance=Top|calvinism=yes|calvinism-importance=Top|core-topics-work-group = yes|core-topics-importance=low}}
{{WP Scotland|importance=High|class=B}}
{{WikiWorld|File:Calvin wikiworld.jpg}}

{{Wikipedia:WikiProject Calvinism/FAQ/MessageBox}}
{{Topic co-ordination link|Calvinism|
*[[Five points of Calvinism]] (and the pages for each point)
**[[Total depravity]]
**[[Unconditional election]]
**[[Limited atonement]]
**[[Irresistible grace]]
**[[Perseverance of the saints]]
*[[History of Calvinist-Arminian debate]]
}}
{{todo}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-08-23|oldid1=5427723|date2=2011-09-13|oldid2=450180671}}
{{archive box|[[Talk:Calvinism/Archive 1|Archive 1]]
[[Talk:Calvinism/Archive 2|Archive 2]]}}

== re: help me understand ==

Calvinism teaches that God predestines people to heaven, and allows the rest to suffer the consequences of their sin. This is not the same as what you're describing, that is called double-predestination, which is a subclass of Calvinist thought (and the minority).

God brings about repentance in the elect by changing their will in such a way that they will turn to him, which no one would do otherwise. So those who are not predestined to heaven would never pray and ask for repentance because without God's changing of their will they would never desire that. So if someone prays and asks for forgiveness it means that their wills have been changed.

Also, your professor's caricature of TULIP is really inaccurate. Here is a bit more accurate presentation than the slanted view your professor gave you (it's really despicable that professors do this. I could give you a slanted picture of Arminian theology that makes it look bad too... but I'm not going to be deceptive about things).

:T - Total Depravity, might be better understood as Total Inability. It means that there is no part of us that is not affected by the fall, and because of that none of us have the ability or desire to turn to God.
:U - Unconditional Election means that God's choice of us as the Elect has nothing to do with anything we do, it is a choice of God that is free from conditioning by us.
:L - Limited Atonement basically means that Jesus' death, although sufficient for all, is only effectual for the elect. This isn't really any different than the Arminian stance, which says that it is only effectual for the elect but just defines how the elect become the elect in a different way. If you believe that Jesus' death DID anything concrete rather than just purchasing the potential for something, then you believe in Limited Atonement
:I - Irresistible Grace is better understood as Effectual Call, which basically means that God accomplishes that which he sets out to do. We always choose exactly what we desire... and never that which we do not desire. Those who are elect have had their wills changed in such that they desire to seek God, those who are left in their sins do that which they desire... namely rebel against God in favor of their own selfish desires.
:P - Perseverance of the Saints means that God's grace is enough to change a person such that they will persist.

Your professor is presenting an inaccurate picture, which is a common underhanded tactic by Arminians who either don't know how to combat the doctrine... or don't care enough to present it accurately. If you're looking for a good resource you could check out &quot;Why I'm not an Arminian&quot; or &quot;For Calvinism.&quot; Both are good, and inexpensive, resources for understanding what Calvinism actually teaches. They also have compainions that explain and defend the Arminian side (primarily by engaging in the same kind of inaccurate presentation that your professor did) called &quot;Why I'm not a Calvinist&quot; or &quot;Against Calvinism&quot; respectively.

[[User:ReformedArsenal|ReformedArsenal]] ([[User talk:ReformedArsenal|talk]]) 15:17, 15 February 2012 (UTC)

== help me understand ==

Please help me understand something.  Regarding Calvinism....am I right in stating that Calvinism believes that God has predestined certain people to Heaven and others to Hell?  If so...does that mean if a person prays and ask for repentance in asking forgiveness of their sins, it doesn't matter because he/she is already predestined to Heaven or Hell?   How can one know if they are one of the chosen ones predestined to Heaven?
thank you
[[User:CLysek1|CLysek1]] ([[User talk:CLysek1|talk]]) 18:46, 6 April 2010 (UTC)

: That doctrine is called &quot;double predestination&quot; -- see [[Predestination (Calvinism)]].

One of my theology professors summarized TULIP as&lt;br&gt;
T = we're scum.&lt;br&gt;
U = God chooses which scum goes to heaven and which to hell.&lt;br&gt;
L = Jesus died only for the heaven-bound scum.&lt;br&gt;
I = God doesn't give the heaven-bound scum a choice in the matter. (Which makes God sound like the [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]]: Resistance is futile, you will be assimilated.)&lt;br&gt;
P = nor does He allow its scumminess to interfere with the process. &lt;br&gt;[[User:Jhobson1|Jhobson1]] ([[User talk:Jhobson1|talk]]) 13:09, 31 May 2010 (UTC)
: Sounds like your professor has a chip on their shoulder about Calvinism. When people characterize Calvinism in this way, they are actually describing [[Hyper-Calvinism]]. – '''[[User:Confession0791|Confession0791]]''' '''[[User_talk:Confession0791|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]''' 03:26, 31 May 2012 (UTC)

== Displayed image of the Good Shepherd - a graven image? ==

Would not the display of such an Ikon be at odds with the Calvinist prescription against the display of graven images and therefore inimical to the subject which it is being used to illustrate? If so it portrays a misleading impression of the article's subject matter.

== Usury ==
&quot;In this view, elements of Calvinism represented a revolt against the medieval condemnation of usury and, implicitly, of profit in general[citation needed]. Such a connection was advanced in influential works by R. H. Tawney (1880–1962) and by Max Weber (1864–1920).&quot;

This is wrong when it comes to Weber. ''The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism'' does not mention usury when it comes to Calvinism at all.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:GeneCallahan|GeneCallahan]] ([[User talk:GeneCallahan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/GeneCallahan|contribs]]) 22:56, 3 March 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Huldrych Zwingli ==

Huldrych Zwingli and Ulrich Zwingli seem to be the same person, shouldn't his name be spelled consistently in the article? [[User:ZARguy|ZARguy]] ([[User talk:ZARguy|talk]]) 14:55, 25 August 2011 (UTC)

:I agree, and I would argue that it should be Huldrych, not because I have any knowledge of how he spelled his name, but because that is the spelling of the wikipedia article about him. [[User:Sterrettc|Sterrettc]] ([[User talk:Sterrettc|talk]]) 00:12, 26 August 2011 (UTC)

:: Thanks! [[User:ZARguy|ZARguy]] ([[User talk:ZARguy|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 06:48, 24 October 2011 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== The Reformed Tradition is more than just Calvinism, even in the sixteenth century. ==

I am concerned that Wikipedia redirects the entire discussion to Calvinism. I am a committed Calvinist myself, but the Reformed theological tradition predates Calvin (certainly in Zwingli and Bucer, and some might argue in Augustine!), and runs in multiple streams, even in Calvin's own day. Is there a possibility of splitting these articles? I just feel this is misleading and unscholarly.

[[User:Johnsonr3|Robert Johnson]] ([[User talk:Johnsonr3|talk]]) 02:53, 31 May 2012 (UTC)
:There is a slight possibility of having [[Reformed tradition]] as a separate article, but it would take a lot of work. The article does already mention quite a few other names (like Bucer and Zwingli) in its second sentence, so I wouldn't say it is misleading. [[User:StAnselm|&lt;b&gt;St&lt;/b&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/StAnselm|Anselm]] ([[User talk:StAnselm|talk]]) 03:05, 31 May 2012 (UTC)

== Table ==

I reworked the &quot;comparison among Protestants&quot; table to flow better and be more readable, but I can't seem to adjust the size to 85% width. Also, should it be converted to a template, since it is on multiple pages? If so, I'm not sure how to do that properly. – '''[[User:Confession0791|Confession0791]]''' '''[[User_talk:Confession0791|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]''' 03:29, 31 May 2012 (UTC)
:Yes, the template is an excellent idea, and I have gone ahead and created it. (From this page - I assume they are all the same.) I don't know about adjusting the width, though. [[User:StAnselm|&lt;b&gt;St&lt;/b&gt;]][[Special:Contributions/StAnselm|Anselm]] ([[User talk:StAnselm|talk]]) 04:17, 31 May 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>2yjssk2riy8lw1esb92yh28iph5q7yg</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
