<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Bhakti</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>463851</id>
    <revision>
      <id>500749585</id>
      <parentid>498791852</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-05T04:29:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CorrectKnowledge</username>
        <id>16012849</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added phil to WikiProject Hinduism.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11828">{{oldpeerreview|archive=1}}
{{WikiProject Hinduism|class=B|importance=Top|vaishnavism=yes|krishna=yes|phil=yes}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|maxarchivesize = 80K
|counter = 1
|algo = old(21d)
|archive = Talk:Bhakti/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{WikiProject India|class=B|importance=High|religion=yes|assess-date=April 2012}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{Archive box|auto=yes}}
----

I removed  the link  'http://www.jkp.org/devotion devotional bhakti' because it can be listed as an example under 'Bhakti movement'. By the way 'devotional bhakti' is a tautology. [[User:Andries|Andries]] 20:08, 10 Feb 2004 (UTC)


Changed meaning from 'loving devotion to the supreme god' to 'devotion to god'. Could also perhaps be changed to just 'devotion'. [[User:Imc|Imc]] 12:56, 2 May 2005 (UTC)

== Refs ==

The additions on &quot;Suddha-bhakti&quot; (unreferenced) and &quot;three stages of Bhakti&quot; (referenced to : Sathya Sai Speaks. Sathya Sai Educational Trust. Prasanthinilayam, A.P. India) need a RS, they seem more on the side of OR. --[[User:Nvineeth|Nvineeth]] ([[User talk:Nvineeth|talk]]) 04:28, 23 May 2009 (UTC)

:I've removed that section - I found one or two other not-really-mainstream references, but it doesn't seem notable enough to include in this article, unless it's in the form of one sentence that says &quot;according to x and y, there are three stages of bhakti, .....&quot;. But even that may be Undue. Just my opinion. [[User:Priyanath|Priyanath]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Priyanath|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 03:06, 27 May 2009 (UTC)

::Did the same for the unreferenced section on ''Suddha-bhakta'', though I appreciate Redheylin's efforts in moving/merging those sections from other articles. What this article really needs is a section on '''Schools'''. [[User:Priyanath|Priyanath]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Priyanath|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 03:10, 27 May 2009 (UTC)

== A few points ==

I note that the article has lost its shape rather and now contains quite a few grammatical errors. Priyanath, the section you removed as &quot;OR&quot; was included in the lede as a resume of the various analyses contained in the article: it is regrettable that it was removed IMO. Wikidas is right to point out that Shaiva, Vaishnava and Shakta are not unique to bhakti, nor are they the most significant division, I think, nor, in any real sense, do they form separate schools or traditions in respect to bhakti itself. The three grades of bhakta were included, though uncited, because I preferred not to destroy altogether a merged page. There is now a &quot;suddha-bhakti&quot; redirect that leads nowhere, which is again unfortunate. If the reference is to be removed then the redirect page ought to be deleted. However, it is possible to reference the idea of different classes or grades of bhakti (eg Gita 7.16 though this does not use the expression &quot;suddha&quot;). I'd prefer not to make these changes myself right away as I do not want to waste any more time on making a good, readable article only to have it screwed around by folk who care more for their pet ideologies than good English, nor to undo others' work in the same way I myself find tiresome. If we could all kindly refer to this talk page, then, and ensure that we end up with something readable? Thanks. [[User:Redheylin|Redheylin]] ([[User talk:Redheylin|talk]]) 02:29, 9 June 2009 (UTC)

PS Please note also that, since this is an English language wiki, if the subject is to exceed its remit as a Hindu religious term then it is going to end up merged with a page such as [[Worship]] - even now, such pages should be linked here. [[User:Redheylin|Redheylin]] ([[User talk:Redheylin|talk]]) 02:36, 9 June 2009 (UTC)

:I would be more than happy to discuss changes. I was equally surprised, considering all the improvements that I had made from this abysmal version of the article[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;oldid=284196431], to see you make such major changes with only short (or no) edit summaries and no discussion. I won't respond to your snarky comments about my ideology and writing, but would rather discuss, with good faith, every change that I made after your work. I'm quite happy to discuss, and see other editors involved. Here is the series of edits I made after your first set of changes:

:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=292586689&amp;oldid=292574445] Removed the three stages of bhakti section, in response to another editor's comment on the talk page that it was OR. I pointed out on the talk page that I had removed it, and am open to discussing it even further than I did.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=292587258&amp;oldid=292586689] Removed the suddha-bhakti section as unreferenced, and after searching for reliable sources without finding anything, I removed it. It can be put back, but will need reliable sources to stay.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=292588428&amp;oldid=292587258] Condensed what was clearly OR/Essay, and also referenced Gita quotes to a more neutral source.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=292592824&amp;oldid=292588428] Formatting, and removed one saint who I admire greatly but who generally isn't notable for his bhakti - that would be Ramana Maharshi.

:Following your second set of edits I made these changes:
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293732584&amp;oldid=293587996] Added back the fuller etymology that you had removed. Most full articles based on Sanskrit words have a dedicated etymology section. The section &quot;Types and classifications&quot; could have a better title.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293733133&amp;oldid=293732584] Minor copy edit that added major clarity to the idea, imo.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293733306&amp;oldid=293733133] Changed the term 'bhakti movement' to 'practice of bhakti', since 'bhakti movement' usually is used by reliable sources to mean the [[Bhakti movement]]. Do a Google Books search and you'll see.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293733729&amp;oldid=293733306] I willingly conceded to Wikidas, who changed the part of this edit regarding 'three main schools of bhakti'. Those three ''are'' the most written about, by far, and should probably be featured in a separate section on &quot;Bhakti schools&quot;, along with other bhakti approaches. I reinserted the very well-referenced and due statement &quot;These schools are not always exclusive of each other—a ''bhakti's'' devotion towards one form of god does not preclude worship of another form.&quot;
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293734396&amp;oldid=293733729] The well-referenced statement already in the body of the article, along with other references that could be found, make it clear that bhakti is not segregated from jnana and karma yogas. Your change made it actually contradict what was later in the article. The 'locus of the human heart' phrase I deleted - is it in the reference that follows? I didn't find it.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293734791&amp;oldid=293734396] The bhakti movement should of course be in the lead, imo.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293736207&amp;oldid=293734791] The scholarly discussion of whether Panini meant Vasudeva as Krishna is arguably weighted more in the direction of 'no'. This was earlier removed from the article entirely by the editor [[User:Dbachmann]] as being undue to even mention the speculation. I'm for leaving it in, with explanation.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293737564&amp;oldid=293736207] These references to the Panini discussion were removed entirely (by you? I don't know), I simply reinserted very good and reliably sourced references.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293739002&amp;oldid=293738313] Minor copy-editing.
:*[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293740314&amp;oldid=293739002] More copy-editing, condensing of quotes.

:Those are the main edits that I did after yours. I gave fairly explicit edit summaries for each. I notice that you are not so much into edit summaries, for example this edit[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;diff=293438563&amp;oldid=293428918] removed 3,000kb of content with the summary &quot;reorder (#2)&quot;. We can both improve in the area.

:I'm fine if those completely unreferenced sections go back into the article, with tags to highlight that they are unreferenced. If I have a pet ideology, it's third-party neutral high quality reliable sources. If you compare the article before[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bhakti&amp;oldid=284196431] I began working on it to the current version, you would see what I mean. Ten references/footnotes, some unreliable, before - fifty-two good references/footnotes after. Nvineeth added many of them, so I'm not taking all the credit, but I am confessing that lack of reliable sources are a pet peeve. But it's really an extraordinary improvement from where it began. 

:If you can be more specific about &quot;grammatical errors&quot;, please do so. Same with any errors that you see in weight or POV. I'm happy to discuss, as you can see from my active participation in previous discussions on this page. I'm also happy to discuss each change that I made and commented on above. Thanks, [[User:Priyanath|Priyanath]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Priyanath|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 04:51, 9 June 2009 (UTC)

== Organization of Sections ==

I think, the order of sections is not logical. I feel &quot;History&quot; should come after &quot;Etymology&quot;, then followed by &quot;Bhakti Yoga&quot;. I propose the following order : Etymology — History — Bhakti Yoga — Types and classifications. Any thoughts on this? --[[User:Nvineeth|Nvineeth]] ([[User talk:Nvineeth|talk]]) 08:04, 10 June 2009 (UTC)

:I'm fine with that. I see etymology sections typically at the beginning. Then the more specific &quot;types&quot; and a possible Bhakti schools, or Bhakti in different religions, section should be at the end. General---&gt;specific being the pattern. [[User:Priyanath|Priyanath]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Priyanath|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 15:12, 10 June 2009 (UTC)
::Seems fine to me even if history bit seems more relevant to a reader. [[User:Wikidas|&lt;span style=&quot; font-weight:bolder; background-color:white; color:#FFCC33; border-bottom:2px solid #FFCC33&quot;&gt;Wikid&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:Wikidas|&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:bolder; border-bottom:0px solid;&quot;&gt;as&lt;i&gt;&amp;#169;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]] 17:04, 10 June 2009 (UTC)

== Bhakti in the age of technology [[User:Pradeep.aradhya|Pradeep.aradhya]] ([[User talk:Pradeep.aradhya|talk]]) 14:23, 12 April 2011 (UTC)pradeep.aradhya ==

I would like to propose an additional section to this page to do with how technology can be relevant to bhakti and trends in that direction. While bhakti is personal technology can be used to facilitate it just like anything else. What is a good course of action on this?

== Bhakti technique ==

I'd recommend adding a section directly linking one to specific bhakti techniques.
One would be www.howtoloveGod.org  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:WalkingwithGod|WalkingwithGod]] ([[User talk:WalkingwithGod|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/WalkingwithGod|contribs]]) 00:45, 18 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links ==

&quot;The Bhaktilive channel&quot; link is just adverts. Would someone who knows how to do so please remove it.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/118.210.54.103|118.210.54.103]] ([[User talk:118.210.54.103|talk]]) 06:36, 22 June 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>kgiwvgm2d7bwde2wm3zfrq8f7geiyd3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
