<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Marriage</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>19733</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522374508</id>
      <parentid>522360409</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-10T19:52:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Trystan</username>
        <id>498704</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Attentive request for the source */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37368">{{talk header}}
{{Controversial3}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Sociology|class=c|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Anthropology|class=c|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Law|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Human rights|class=c|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Family and relationships|class=c|importance=top}}
{{WP1.0|class=C|category=category|VA=yes}}}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 13
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Marriage/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes
}}

== This is a locked article, please improve ==

By including a see also section, which links to other wikipedia articles, like: [[Marriage_in_the_United_States]]&lt;br&gt;~ender 2012-03-17 20:33:PM MST  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/98.165.52.42|98.165.52.42]] ([[User talk:98.165.52.42|talk]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Edit request ==

There is a sentence in the introduction that I think could be slightly improved:
&quot;The act of marriage usually creates normative or legal obligations between the individuals involved.&quot;

The act of marriage also usually confers legal rights (in addition to obligations).  Although, semantically, I'm not sure if these rights derive from the act of marriage, or if they are a secondary result of the formation of a family unit (that IS the result of the act of marriage).  Perhaps this doesn't matter greatly.

I also am not clear on the use of the term &quot;normative&quot; in the sentence, because the lay definition doesn't seem to confer any added information:  Establishing, relating to, or deriving from a standard or norm, esp. of behavior: &quot;negative sanctions to enforce normative behavior&quot;.

Changing the sentence to &quot;The act of marriage usually results in the establishment of legal rights and obligations between the individuals involved.&quot; is the best I could do.

Cheers

[[Special:Contributions/70.179.21.51|70.179.21.51]] ([[User talk:70.179.21.51|talk]]) 18:48, 29 April 2012 (UTC)

Edit Request

In the Introduction, it states that marriage is a legal contract. This is not correct. Marriage is a legal status; but it is not a contract. In contract the terms of the agreement are legally enforceable. In marriage this is not the case.

I suggest that 'contract' be deleted and 'status' inserted.

[[User:Steve hayes|Steve hayes]] ([[User talk:Steve hayes|talk]]) 10:11, 2 May 2012 (UTC)
:The terms of marriage are legally enforceable. You can be forced to cover your spouses debts. You can be forced to support your spouse if you violate the contract. Here in the US, the fact that it is a civil contract is spelled out in just those words in some states' laws ([https://www.revisor.mn.gov/statutes/?id=517.01 here is Minnesota] for example, [http://www.moga.mo.gov/statutes/C400-499/4510000010.HTM and Missouri]); and it's not just a US thing, [http://irishbarrister.com/marriage.html here's a discussion of marriage as a contract in Ireland]. Some dictionaries refer to it as a contract,  [http://legal-dictionary.thefreedictionary.com/marriage here's a law dictionary discussing it as such]. --[[User:NatGertler|Nat Gertler]] ([[User talk:NatGertler|talk]]) 15:45, 2 May 2012 (UTC)
'''Not Done.''' Marriage is a contract. &amp;ndash; [[File:Face-smile.svg|18px|link=]] &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.118em 0.118em 0.118em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;  '''[[User:Teammm|Teammm]]'''&lt;/span&gt; [[User talk:Teammm|&lt;sup&gt;Let's '''Talk'''! :)&lt;/sup&gt;]] 01:01, 3 May 2012 (UTC)

According to the judgement of Fearon v Treanor, New York Court of Appeal 272 NY 268 (1936) 'There are, in effect, three parties to every marriage, the man, the woman and the state.... Marriage is not a contract within the meaning of the provision of the Federal Constitution which prohibits the impairment by the States of the obligation of contracts.The Domestic Relations Law provides in great detail when and how marriage may be entered into, how the relation may be dissolved, the grounds for divorce and annulment, the rights and liabilities of husband and wife, the age at which the relation may be entered into and the class of persons who are disqualified from marrying.' This clearly states that it is not a contract. And it is not. In a contract, a party may apply to a court to have the terms upheld or may be granted compensation. This cannot happen with marriage. One can also see that marriage is not a contract from the fact that parties to marriage have increasingly attempted to create contracts, and the courts, when, on divorce, presented with such contracts have been loathe to recognise them, preferring to uphold divorce law.

````  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/94.2.198.217|94.2.198.217]] ([[User talk:94.2.198.217|talk]]) 06:10, 13 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:First off, no, this does not say marriage is not a contract, merely that it is not a contract ''within the meanings of certain provisions''; that does not mean that it is not a contract within the meanings of other provisions, or within some more general use of language. In fact, if you read Fearon more fully, you'll find: &quot;&quot;Marriage is considered a civil contract [...] It, certainly, does differ from ordinary common law contracts, by reason of its subject-matter and of the supervision which the state exercises over the marriage relation, which the contract institutes&quot;. So even if this were an article specific to U.S. law, which it is not, the Fearon ruling would be proof that, yes, applying the word &quot;contract&quot; is appropriate. --[[User:NatGertler|Nat Gertler]] ([[User talk:NatGertler|talk]]) 06:49, 13 May 2012 (UTC)

::Also, reading comprehension 101, no offense...it merely says that '''marriage is different than other contracts''', in that the States '''can &quot;impair the obligation&quot; of a marriage contract (by divorce or annulment)''', not that it isn't one. &amp;ndash; [[File:Face-smile.svg|18px|link=]] &lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:grey 0.118em 0.118em 0.118em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;  '''[[User:Teammm|Teammm]]'''&lt;/span&gt; [[User talk:Teammm|&lt;sup&gt;Let's '''Talk'''! :)&lt;/sup&gt;]] 09:47, 13 May 2012 (UTC)
:::Also, this article is &quot;Marriage&quot; for the entire world, not just the US or one state.[[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 20:59, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
:::: Articles in Wikipedia should be regarded as derived from (reliable sources) rather than as existing for (someone, something, or even &quot;the entire world&quot;). This is an important distinction that should be considered and used in practice. --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 10:47, 24 August 2012 (UTC)

== Interwiki ==

[[User:Wizikj]] changed the links to Polish language version. That was erroneous, since the article he inserted is rather controverial on Polish laguage project, has been twice selected for deletion recently and primarily deals only with the subject of one form of marriage: monogamous and heterosexual union. Historically, on Polish language wiki the article that deals with the term &quot;Marriage&quot; as a whole was and is [[pl:Małżeństwo (instytucja społeczna)|Marriage (social institution)]]. It would be wrong if we would follow suit and allow ourselfs to be drawn into the useless battle between 'right' and 'wrong' marriages. yours, --[[User:Emanek|emanek]] ([[User talk:Emanek|talk]]) 23:11, 17 May 2012 (UTC)
&lt;div style=&quot;padding-left:2em; &quot;&gt;
The above statement amazes me: really talking about the battle? But who are the soldiers?&lt;br&gt; 
You are posting:
* &quot;marriage as a whole&quot; - show me a source that explicitly defines the term &quot;marriage as a whole&quot;. Does this source is, in your opinion, the article [[marriage]], or maybe [[pl:małżeństwo (instytucja społeczna)]]? I ask rhetorically.
* &quot;article is rather controversial on Polish language project&quot; - whether it is a community opinion or your own, fortified emotionally, personal assessment?
* &quot;has been twice selected for deletion recently&quot; - how do you know that it's they are right? Maybe you're a judge...
Some good advice: I think that you should look carefully beforehand at what you have to say in Wikipedia so as not to depreciate your own position on issues under consideration. --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 09:28, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
&lt;/div&gt;
* What amazes me is the tone and assumption that I am judge of editorial conflicts on Polish language project. No, the history of both articles talk pages speak for itself. What surprises me even more is that as an editor on that project you are rather well aware of it. The article (at the time of my original comments here) was described by it's authors as an article of a  (i quote) 'a monogamous, heterosexual union'. Whether it has changed since - I do not know since I am not following changes on Polish project. Nor am I suggesting who was right or wrong in their conflict on this subject. However, I do know (and assume that you too) that a definition of a marriage in 2012 (as well as in the long history of such unions) is much wider than that of a 'monogamous, heterosexual union'. And my position on issues is rather constant - it is not what I like, but what is and could be sourced. Nonetheless, thank you for your comments and suggestions. Respectfully, --[[User:Emanek|emanek]] ([[User talk:Emanek|talk]]) 20:28, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
:: Hello Emanek, nice to talk to you again :) I would like to give you some facts about the contents of [[pl:małżeństwo]] (marriage) at the time when you placed here your original comment, dated May 17. Well, after checking the revision history, the term &quot;monogamous, heterosexual union&quot; cited by you does not appear in the definition of marriage. I suppose that you were then under a very evocative influence of {{diff|pl:małżeństwo|31242189|31194483|this edit}}, also performed on May 17. This edit has introduced, wrongly, the term &quot;marriage of persons of the opposite sex&quot; in place of the term being defined, ie. &quot;marriage&quot; and was subsequently {{diff|pl:małżeństwo|31560039|31548818|withdrawn}} on June 6, and so after 3 weeks of presence in Wikipedia. The mentioned article perhaps may not is as &quot;verbose&quot; as [[marriage]] but, IMO, honestly inform (in a manner of encyclopaedic, and with no undue comments) about various aspects of marriage, including the very contemporary ones. And so I can't agree with you as to the suggestion that it describes just &quot;monogamous, heterosexual union&quot; – in my opinion it is a wrong assertion, not having its reflection in the content of the said article. You write, moreover, that in 2012 the definition of marriage is &quot;much wider&quot;. And I ask you: how do you understand the term &quot;much wider&quot; in the present context? Perhaps you want to tell me: &quot;a marriage between people of the same sex.&quot; But whether for this reason you must set the definition of marriage as &quot;union of people called spouses that creates kinship&quot;? Maybe so. But looking at the prominent sources such a change is not yet noticeable. Therefore in Wikipedia, based strictly on reliable sources while maintaining an appropriate balance, we should apply such definition: &quot;union of a man and a woman awaiting the birth of their own children.&quot; And just like you, I can say now: my position on these issues is rather stable - this is not what I like, but what is and could be sourced. Sincerely, --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 12:56, 23 August 2012 (UTC)

== Essaypedia ==

Dear colleagues wikipedians, involved in this discussion!

Description specified at the part of the article allocated for a definition generalizes, in some way, the notion of ''essential human relations'' - legal, social, sexual. But I have strong doubts whether this description is a definition of a known concept. And though the phrase &quot;called spouses&quot;, recently added, provides a reference to the well-known term &quot;marriage&quot;, this is, however, too few to argue that it was an attempt to formulate its definition.

Friends, I get the impression that the creation of the definition in this article is the last stage of its development, which is a violation of encyclopedic principle valid on the Wikipedia, ie: first put the term, then get its sourced definition, and finally place an extensive description, if available. Therefore, if you agree that I am right at this point, there's a suspicion of original research in the field of a definition&lt;ref&gt;[[Wikipedia:SYN|Synthesis of published material that advances a position]]&lt;/ref&gt; - and from here it's a short road to breach the principle of a [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view|neutral point of view]].

In addition to the above, I would also like to note the following: while reading the article can not help noticing that its writing style lies in adding content, in a peculiar manner and in any order, from a variety of cited sources. I do not want to go into a detailed discussion, at least not at this time, so as not to blur the essence of my speech.

That is an essay written article. An essay written about the ''essential human relationships'', as I have mentioned above. An essay illustrating only one &quot;point of view&quot;, namely: the subject is not able to be considered at different points of view. And in accordance with such a '''quasi-point of view''', as if to excuse, gives a significant '''quasi-definition'''.

In my opinion the article does not meet the requirement of being encyclopedic which is a fundamental feature of Wikipedia very welcome from the first [[Wikipedia:Five pillars|pillar]]. In other words, the assumption to be encyclopedic had lost here its importance, or yet otherwise a big fish, [[Encyclopedia]], has been killed and in its place was brought to life [[Essaypedia]]. --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 11:54, 9 August 2012 (UTC)
&lt;references/&gt;
:Robsuper, could you please be a bit more precise? I have no idea what exact changes you're advocating here. [[User:Seraphimblade|Seraphimblade]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Seraphimblade|Talk to me]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 16:27, 10 August 2012 (UTC)

&lt;div style=&quot;padding-left:4em; &quot;&gt;
Thanks for your reply, Seraphimblade, I thought that all came out from the event :)
{{Quote | text= What grace may be added to commonplace matters by the power of order and connection. | sign= ''The epigraph from Horace on the title page of the 18th century Encyclopédie''}}

The article provides links, by use of 'Main article' or 'See also' templates, to many other Wikipedia articles related to the concept of'' marriage''. This is an interesting trick, not infringing the rules of Wikipedia, which is used in this case, in my opinion, rather only to a previously assumed (or expected) generality of the content of the article, probably in order to achieve a desired [[wikt:neutral|neutral]] [[wikt:point of view|point of view]] ([[WP: NPOV]]).

Let's ask ourselves at this point an important question: Is that generality of its content and its versatility, even nice to the eye, the intention of the sources cited here? Or at least some of them, and if so which ones? I ask this, because Wikipedia's role, resulting in its rules, is seen as fairness and is assumed as neutral (intermediate between something and something, inert) transfer of information from reliable sources.

I think that in case of certain concepts - those that have extremely common and wide range of use by humans - we should not allow over-generalization (this is relative), or a synthesis of the aspects in one article. If exists commonly accepted fact - known and used by an absolute majority of the people (although this assumption is debatable) - that the definition of the concept already exists, and is supported by reliable sources, respectively important, then let us take this definition and assign it to that term, in the first step.

And only at the second stage let us consider, as for the &quot;site of meaning&quot;, its other aspects. Along with such a pattern of procedure (see: [[encyclopedia]]), you may find that the existence of previously established ''neutrality'' of the article is, to say the least, inappropriate.

Furthermore, the definition now included in the article is a result of &quot;original research in the topic of marriage&quot;. With such established treatment of marriage phenomena, seems natural current layout of this article - a layout that resembles rather article about an object in the geographic space, such as a town.

Personally, I think it is necessary here to put links to related articles in an encyclopedic way possible, which is modest, neutral, not overbearing, without a lengthy introductions and a dubious comments backed by borrowed footnotes.

Therefore I suggest to:
# correct the definition to one that reflects a weighted system of reliable sources.&lt;ref&gt;''Giving due weight and avoiding giving undue weight means that articles should not give minority views as much of, or as detailed, a description as more widely held views.'' From [[WP:DUE]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Neutrality assigns weight to viewpoints in proportion to their prominence.'' From [[WP:BALANCE]]&lt;/ref&gt; For such reason, the definition of the Encyclopedia Britannica seems to be a suitable candidate. Great request at this point: please do not treat the achievements of anthropologists as the main interpretation for the definition of the concept.&lt;ref&gt;''An article should not give undue weight to any aspects of the subject but should strive to treat each aspect with a weight appropriate to its significance to the subject.'' From [[WP:UNDUE]]&lt;/ref&gt;
# give up attempting to obtain generality at &quot;any price&quot;. This means a significant shortening of the article by removing some of the paragraphs, such as those that easily overlap content of the linked article, along with templates 'Main article', or 'See also'.
# remove the parts about religious aspect. Here, I propose only links to related parties, their names are relevant to the content - no need for additional clarification on this page.
# remove the parts about legal aspect - here I offer a very brief introduction and template 'Main Article' for [[Marriage law]].
# remove the section entitled 'History of marriage by culture'. This is subject for serious monograph. Overview of such an issue in a short encyclopedia article is really heroics job.

{{lang-la|Facilius dixit quam fecit}}.

I know it's &quot;easier said than done&quot;, and that what I outlined above is, I suppose, well known to a community involved in the development of this article. I would however demonstrate for some persons that perhaps too easily, enjoying freedom on Wikipedia's pages, take actions not supported by reliable sources and inadequate for the weight diagram of this concept.
--[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 14:29, 14 August 2012 (UTC)
&lt;references/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

== Doesn't make sense ==

&quot;In terms of legal recognition, most sovereign states and other jurisdictions limit marriage to two persons of opposite [[sex]] or [[gender]] in the [[gender binary]], and some of these allow [[Polygyny|polygynous marriage]].&quot; If they limit marriage to two person of the opposite sex, how can some of these allow polygamous marriage? [[User:Acoma Magic|Acoma Magic]] ([[User talk:Acoma Magic|talk]]) 07:57, 12 August 2012 (UTC)
: I agree. Whoever wrote that probably has English as a secondary language. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 08:12, 12 August 2012 (UTC)
:Because polygynous marriage is (in at least some interpretations) not one marriage for more than two people, but simply the on-exclusivity of marriage -- a person is not limited to one marriage. --[[User:NatGertler|Nat Gertler]] ([[User talk:NatGertler|talk]]) 14:15, 12 August 2012 (UTC)
:This &quot;gender binary&quot; stuff is actually a disputed article in a series on transgenderism. Marriage: being re-defined on Wikipedia instead of just defining it for what it has always been.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.92.121.57|24.92.121.57]] ([[User talk:24.92.121.57|talk]]) 07:42, 19 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Hanlon and White Change ==

The line in the article, &quot;In almost all societies, access to women is institutionalized in some way so as to moderate the intensity of this competition.&quot;[18] with a reference to Hanlon and White p. 116 is actually a quote from Duran Bell, &quot;Defining Marriage and Legitimacy,&quot; ''Current Anthropology'' 1, no. 2 (April 1997): 239. I'm not sure about the other two references by Hanlon and White, but that particular attribution is wrong. Please fix it.

[[User:Supersj|Supersj]] ([[User talk:Supersj|talk]]) 22:40, 28 August 2012 (UTC)
:Please, why don't you fix it? [[User:Lova_Falk|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Segoe Print;color:#e75e03&quot;&gt;'''Lova Falk'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Lova Falk|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Segoe Print;color:#336699&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 11:23, 30 August 2012 (UTC)

::I've updated the citation, as well as the other &quot;Hanlon &amp; White&quot; citations, which are all from that Bell article.--[[User:Trystan|Trystan]] ([[User talk:Trystan|talk]]) 18:02, 10 November 2012 (UTC)

== Group marriages and the Caingang / Kaingang people ==

The &quot;History of marriage by culture&quot; section of this article includes 
: Of the 250 societies reported by the American anthropologist George P. Murdock in 1949, only the [[Caingang]] of Brazil had any group marriages at all.&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;{{Cite document|url = http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/247131/group-marriage|title=Group Marriage|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica Online| accessdate = January 28, 2010}}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;

I was curious about that and clicked on &quot;[[Caingang]]&quot;. There's no mention of group marriage in that article. There is [[Talk:Kaingang people#Murdock claims]] where an editor makes a good case that we need better supporting data. The Encyclopædia Britannica article only cites Murdock and also adds &quot;even there the frequency was but 8 percent.&quot;  --[[User:Marc Kupper|Marc Kupper]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Marc Kupper|talk]] 22:50, 6 September 2012 (UTC)

== Polygynous marriage section ==

There's a section about same-sex marriage and another about group marriage. But polygynous marriage, that seems to be recognized in more countries than same-sex and group marrriages, doesn't have a section. I think one should be created. Considering the article is controversial and is semi-protected, I am discussing this here before making any changes to the article.--[[User:Cattus|Cattus]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Cattus|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 11:27, 9 September 2012 (UTC)

== Prepubescent marriage in Iran ==

Sorry for what might seem a provocative heading, but that is exactly the subject, and I see it has already been removed from this article. The reason I raise it now is that a petition is doing the rounds on Facebook, and on investigating I find not only this article (which has already been called an 'unreliable' source by one editor here) [http://frontpagemag.com/2012/frank-crimi/iranian-child-brides-get-younger-and-more-numerous/], but also this article from ''[[International Business Times]]'' [http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/379171/20120830/iran-child-marriage-9-years-old-sharia.htm] which confirms that there is a push being made to legalize marriage to girls as young as nine in Iran. Should this perhaps be included in this article, or at least in [[Child marriage]]? I realize that the editor who previously tried to include this slightly misrepresented the situation by saying such marriages had already been legalized. [[User:Alfietucker|Alfietucker]] ([[User talk:Alfietucker|talk]]) 18:49, 11 September 2012 (UTC)
:As ugly as it may be, child marriage is not something new or different, it's part of the long history of marriage, and it isn't even a current situation in Iran, merely under discussion, so I find it hard to see that that current discussion of one region has a place in the larger marriage article. It would be more up to the editors at [[child marriage]] to judge its appropriateness there; another article that may (or may not, I've not looked that closely) be suited to include the information is [[Persian marriage]]. If there are multiple articles about the push, it may be appropriate to give the campaign its own article. To the extent that child marriage is discussed here, it should be discussed primarily as it exists in general, with specific callouts of individual jurisdictions limited to the extremes (first, youngest, whatever.) --[[User:NatGertler|Nat Gertler]] ([[User talk:NatGertler|talk]]) 19:01, 11 September 2012 (UTC)

::I concur that it should be law already rather than &quot;under discussion.&quot; It seems to me that a general statement could be made under history: &quot;Prepubescent marriage was allowed in the following countries/cultures, under the following circumstances prior to the 20th century (or whatever).&quot; Some general statement.
::But current prepubescent marriage must be illegal under some UN declaration or other. Anyway, IMO, current jurisdictions where it is legal should be named. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 00:00, 17 September 2012 (UTC)

== Reference to section &quot;History of marriage by culture&quot; seems wrong ==

I read page 180 of &quot;in evolution: a study in comparative ethics&quot; (scanned copy at archive.org) and I don't see how the reference supports the statement: - &quot;Although the institution of marriage pre-dates reliable recorded history, many cultures have legends concerning the origins of marriage. The way in which a marriage is conducted and its rules and ramifications has changed over time, as has the institution itself, depending on the culture or demographic of the time.&quot; - The reference only describes some marriage rules in the time of Hammurabi. At best, it is only one example for a broad statement.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.55.214.116|66.55.214.116]] ([[User talk:66.55.214.116|talk]]) 03:50, 13 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Note 77 ==

Note 77 is insubstatial, the author to whom refered offers opinion, and no verifiable facts.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/64.139.120.61|64.139.120.61]] ([[User talk:64.139.120.61|talk]]) 13:43, 17 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Attentive request for the source ==

I would like to draw attention to the fact that the article begins with a characteristic sentence that can be equated as a definition of the term &quot;marriage&quot;, which is described later in this article.&lt;ref&gt;[[Talk:Marriage#Doesn't make sense]], quote: ''(...) Marriage: being re-defined on Wikipedia instead of just defining it for what it has always been.''&lt;/ref&gt; And since we are at Wikipedia we must follow the recommendations requiring direct quotation, particularly in the field of definition, if verifiability of material has been challenged or likely to be challenged (see [[WP:V]]). Therefore I kindly request Wikipedians involved in creating and development of this article to point the source (or sources) that directly supports the following phrase: &quot;marriage is a social union or legal contract between people called spouses that creates kinship&quot;. This phrase as being highly representative in the relevant context without stating its source might be regarded as original research.&lt;ref&gt;[[Talk:Marriage/Archive 9#Kinship]], quote: ''(...) It is an &quot;invented here&quot; Wikipedia definition with no reference or source.''&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[WP:OR]]). I do not want yet insert a template because I prefer to explain the raised issues on the talk page in a quiet friendly atmosphere. --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 12:20, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
&lt;references/&gt;
After six-week waiting for a response I placed now in the article two templates: 'Refimprove' &amp; 'Citation needed span' with the reason defined as &quot;This claim requires an explicit reference to the source of its origin&quot;. Please do not interpret my actions in this case as an attempt to challenge the good will of editors involved in the creation of the article. I still believe that my doubts about the correctness of the sources used for the definition can be explained on the talk page. --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 11:19, 5 November 2012 (UTC)

:The lead has the difficult task of describing something for which there does not exist a widely-accepted definition (as the second sentence says explicitly and the ''Definitions'' section amply demonstrates). The various components of the lead sentence description seem rather uncontentious, so I doubt it will be too hard to find supporting sources.--[[User:Trystan|Trystan]] ([[User talk:Trystan|talk]]) 14:42, 5 November 2012 (UTC)

::Kindly thank you for your response to my entry into the discussion. At the beginning I would like to justify my shortcomings in scope of the English language and ask your pardon and attention when I make mistakes. Before I answer I would at first place think about it thoroughly and only then make the translation into English. --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 21:32, 5 November 2012 (UTC)
::Thus this article begins with a lead sentence that is not a definition, but only a certain generalization of the concept. Am I right? If you agree with me at this point would you be so kind to point me other articles in Wikipedia in where the lack of widely-accepted definition has been resolved in the same, or similar way? --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 13:34, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

:::Off the top of my head, one article I have experience with that also lacks a clear definition is [[Role-playing game]]. Like ''marriage'', there are many theories as to what a role-playing game is exactly, and they don't agree with each other. The lead therefore describes in general terms what an RPG is, but the lead sentence is not sufficient as a definition.--[[User:Trystan|Trystan]] ([[User talk:Trystan|talk]]) 14:44, 6 November 2012 (UTC)

::Article which you point out contains at the very beginning an elegant definition of &quot;role-playing game&quot;. Moreover, what you wrote, &quot;there are many theories as to what a role-playing game is exactly&quot; is, in my humble opinion, rather academic rhetoric, with all my respect. That what you call a leading sentence is an excellent and strictly encyclopedic definition of that concept - while certain continued description (sometimes extensive) is other issue. Encyclopedia which is based on sources - like Wikipedia - should be created according to the scheme: &quot;We should first place the term defined, then acquire its sourced definition and finally give an extended description, if necessary.&quot; --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 19:43, 7 November 2012 (UTC)

:::You may consider the lead sentence of [[Role-playing game]] to be a satisfactory definition, but our reliable sources do not. They explicitly state that there is no simple definition, but rather a collection of attributes which roughly delineate the concept. It is the same with this article. It would make things much simpler for us if the sources agreed upon a clear definition, but it simply isn't the case.--[[User:Trystan|Trystan]] ([[User talk:Trystan|talk]]) 23:07, 7 November 2012 (UTC)

::I noticed that you have used the term &quot;no simple definition.&quot; So I can believe that the main problem here is the complexity, or the shape of definition or in other words: way of defining the concept for the purposes of encyclopedia. And Wikipedia, which itself is a [[compendium]] of the [[Tertiary source|third order]], is based on knowledge acquired from [[WP:PSTS|higher level sources]]. And therefore if someone proves me that we cannot formulate a definition which - let's call it - satisfying everyone or is commonly-accepted, because sources do not provide any such, and some of them announce it's difficult to provide it, then I answer that this is rhetoric in terms of academic eg philosophy - in practice the definition is always available from reliable sources. And now referring directly to your posts makes me to suppose that statement &quot;The variety of role playing games makes it inherently challenging to provide a common definition.&quot; originating from a cited source, you treat as an outset for the actual impossibility to create definition to which you would like assign the (nomen-omen) attribute ''widely-accepted''. Besides this, seems to me also that on the assumption of lack of unanimity of sources and still going forward to this end we make fraud of rules of Wikipedia, namely the attempt to replace the existing and workable definition with certain different formulation, say ''lead sentence''. If you agree with me on this point, please also note that leading sentence can easily drift into the direction of a generalized, or universal definition. In Wikipedia, based strictly on reliable sources, this is unfavorable effect because it reduces the value of its merits, and in the long term can make Wikipedia unreliable partner. Not missed my attention to important words that were used:
::- Like ''marriage'', there are many theories as to ...
::- It is the same with this article...
::They show that in the case of articles &quot;marriage&quot; and &quot;role-playing game&quot; you see relevant similarities as to the method of defining these concepts in Wikipedia. But I think that had our talk concerned the concepts belonging to the same field of knowledge then we could make such assumption, and our discussion would look different. --[[User:Robsuper|Robsuper]] ([[User talk:Robsuper|talk]]) 13:29, 9 November 2012 (UTC)
:::I'm afraid that the only thing that will convince me that it is possible to write a definition that agrees with our reliable sources is for someone do so, and then establish consensus around it. I've  read and reread the sources on this particular point, and no simple solution has occurred to me; they are simply too much in disagreement to simply reconcile. My point in entering this conversation was only to establish that I don't view the lead sentence as a definition, and I am fine with that.--[[User:Trystan|Trystan]] ([[User talk:Trystan|talk]]) 14:38, 9 November 2012 (UTC)

===Sources for lead sentence===
In the interest of addressing the citation needed tag on the lead sentence, I've been looking for [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] to cite. My suggestion is that we change the lead sentence to:

::'''Marriage''' is a  is a social union or legal contract between people called spouses that may establish rights and obligations between the spouses, between the spouses and their children, and between a spouse and their spouse's family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Haviland |first1=William A. |last2=Prins |first2=Harald E. L. |last3=McBride |first3=Bunny |last4=Walrath |first4=Dana  |year=2011 |title=Cultural Anthropology: The Human Challenge |publisher=Cengage Learning |isbn=978-0-495-81178-7 |edition=13th}} ''&quot;A nonethnocentric definition of marriage is a culturally sanctioned union between two or more people that establishes certain rights and obligations between the people, between them and their children, and between them and their in-laws.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt;

This wording expands upon and clarifies the &quot;kinship&quot; wording,  accords generally (as closely as I think is possible) with the various definitions discussed in the article, and flows well into the second sentence, &quot;The definition of marriage varies according to different cultures...&quot; Alternatively, if anyone can suggest a good source for the current &quot;kinship&quot; wording, we could stay with that.--[[User:Trystan|Trystan]] ([[User talk:Trystan|talk]]) 19:52, 10 November 2012 (UTC)
&lt;references/&gt;

== Greek marriage is poorly described and may be wrong ==

The plays of Menander generally refer to a wedding ceremony and this site (http://www.richeast.org/htwm/greeks/marriage/marriage.html) says that a marriage took place over three days.  This flies in the face of the statement on the page that there was not a formal wedding ceremony.  The works of Robert Flaceliere further argue that marriage was a ceremonial activity in Ancient Greece (I can only get to some pages in the google version of the book, so I can't reliably cite the information as I see it without context).  It seems that this section needs some significant improvement.  I am not comfortable with my ability to word it well, however.

[[User:Bfishburne|Bfishburne]] ([[User talk:Bfishburne|talk]]) 15:04, 23 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ry6vx1uv05b5h0oeb7p2ohcpq51qyk6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
