<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Messianic Judaism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>70561</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521125692</id>
      <parentid>513041532</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-02T23:16:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DeknMike</username>
        <id>4569520</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* very confusing article */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34616">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=21:42, 12 February 2008 (UTC)
|action1result=not listed
|action1oldid=190804261

|action2=GAN
|action2date=18:16, 5 August 2008
|action2link=Talk:Messianic Judaism/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=230027485

| action3       = GAR
| action3date   = 23:17, 23 November 2008 (UTC)
| action3link   = Wikipedia:Good article reassessment/Messianic Judaism/2
| action3result = delisted
| action3oldid  =

|currentstatus=DGA
|topic=philrelig
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Christianity |class=B |importance=High 
 |messianic-judaism=yes |messianic-judaism-importance=Top }} 
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Mid|NRM=yes|NRMImp=High}}
}}
{{controversial}}
{{calm talk}}
{{auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=1 |units=month }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 125K
|counter = 23
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Messianic Judaism/Archive  %(counter)d
}}
__TOC__

== very confusing article ==

Pardon me for ignorance, but I think the introduction of this article is very misleading. If I'm not mistaken they are just evangelical christians trying to appropriate jewish rituals and pratices? There are congregations in my city and not a single one of them have jews, yet the article mentions that &quot;Some adherents of Messianic Judaism are ethnically Jewish&quot; and that jews started the movement (while simultaneously claim the movement is just an off-shot of jews for jesus). Isn't the history section very biased? There is no historical or traditional connections between early christianity and mj. And how the criticism section be so small when not a single jewish religious authority recognize them as legitimate, yet they call themselves a jewish religion? [[Special:Contributions/201.29.224.144|201.29.224.144]] ([[User talk:201.29.224.144|talk]]) 20:21, 16 September 2012 (UTC)
: The purpose of the article is education. As the history section indicates, a significant number of what are commonly called christians were - in the first century CE - jewish.  Some within the movement insist on a connection and that paragraph was left in deference to them. As for your observation of a particular congregation acting jewish but not being jewish, that is one problem in the modern movement.  Examination of the wide swath of congregations worldwide finds some to be exclusively jewish, using none of the christian forms, and some on the other end of the spectrum being christian churches who have overlaid some forms of jewish ritual and terms on their services (often Kabala) and calling themselves messianic.  However, the mainstream sections of the movement (MJAA, UMJC, Chosen People, AMC, etc) hold to a conservative or orthodox liturgy and practice, led by jews or mixed-race jews (one gentile parent), which has been modified to incorporate christian beliefs more in line with their interpretation of first century theology.  As for the jewish religious authorities' lack of endorsement, that was also the case in the first century.--[[User:DeknMike|DeknMike]] ([[User talk:DeknMike|talk]]) 23:16, 2 November 2012 (UTC)

== Weasel Words ==

I don't recall any recent discussion of &quot;weasel words&quot;. I will remove the tag for now, but if I am forgetting ongoing issues, please list them here and then restore the tag if necessary. -- [[User:Avraham|Avi]] ([[User talk:Avraham|talk]]) 18:02, 7 June 2012 (UTC)

{{hat|Not about improving the article}}
Can you draw out leviathan with an hook? or his tongue with a cord which you let down?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.16.179.9|24.16.179.9]] ([[User talk:24.16.179.9|talk]]) 05:00, 8 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
{{hab}}
:I fail to see how the above comment makes any sense whatsoever, actually, and support Avi on the removal of the weasel words tag until and unless specific indications of use of weasel words in the text are given. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 18:31, 8 August 2012 (UTC)

::I'm pretty sure I was the one who put the weasel tag there.  I just looked again and I still see the same [[WP:WEASEL]]-y sentences, like:
::*&quot;Some adherents of Messianic Judaism are ethnically Jewish, and many of them argue that the movement is a sect of Judaism&quot;
::*&quot;Some Messianic Jews affirm both the Shema and the Trinity...&quot;
::*&quot;Some Messianic believers profess only a strict view of monotheism, rejecting Trinitarian doctrine, but this is not common.&quot;
::*&quot;Most Messianic Jews, in line with mainstream Christian theology, consider Jesus to be the Messiah and divine as God the Son.&quot;
::*&quot;Many also consider Jesus to be their &quot;chief teacher and rabbi&quot; whose life should be copied.&quot;
::*&quot;Many English-speaking Messianic Jews prefer to refer to Jesus by the Hebrew name &quot;Yeshua&quot; rather than by the English name &quot;Jesus&quot;.&quot;
::*&quot;Certain congregations outside mainstream Messianic Jewish belief do not ascribe divinity to Jesus, with some considering him a man, fathered by the Holy Spirit, who became the Messiah.&quot;
::among others.  Some of these are supported by possibly/probably cherry-picked primary sources like websites of individual congregations.  I'm not really actively editing this article at this time, so I'll leave it up to you guys to determine whether to put the weasel tag back and what to do with these sorts of sentences.  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 19:11, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
:&quot;Some,&quot; &quot;many,&quot; and &quot;certain&quot; are fairly clearly weasel words of a sort. I'm not sure if there have ever been anything like &quot;census numbers&quot; on the MJs, which might be problematic as I'm not sure that there exists a standard &quot;definition&quot; of Messianic Judaism, or whether any polls have been given to the effect of &quot;(X)% of MJ's believe (x).&quot; But let me look to see what I can find. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 19:53, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
I would agree that this is pretty weasly.  &quot;Some&quot; certainly may believe certain things, but that doesn't inform us about how prominent and influential those beliefs are, nor how many the word &quot;some&quot; represents.  Could be 10,000 or could be 4.  [[User:Eastcote|Eastcote]] ([[User talk:Eastcote|talk]]) 23:19, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
:As a self-organizing movement without an heirarchical governing body, there is no clear unifying set of beliefs.  There is also currently scant scholarly research on the movement.  Even finding a count on the number of congregations is problematic, though 10k would be 'some' and 4 would be 'a few' (and thus not worth mentioning).--[[User:DeknMike|DeknMike]] ([[User talk:DeknMike|talk]]) 13:55, 9 August 2012 (UTC)

::If there is &quot;scant scholarly research&quot; to support the claims then we should remove the claims.  We ''depend'' on scholarly research to do our articles.  If the research doesn't exist, per [[WP:OR]], we must not attempt to do it ourselves.  As Jimbo Wals said, [[Wikipedia:No reliable sources, no verifiability, no article|&quot;Zero information is preferred to misleading or false information.&quot;]]  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 14:08, 9 August 2012 (UTC)
:::If there were RS's that specifically said something like &quot;some MJ's believe...&quot; that statement could certainly be included in a direct quotation. Alternately, if RS's were found which said something like for instance, &quot;[[Chosen People Ministries]] and associated groups believe....&quot; that could probably be included as well. Any instances like that, where we could use some sort of specific name or names instead of the weasel words, or where the weasel words could be included in a direct quote, might be acceptable. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 19:56, 9 August 2012 (UTC)

::::The problem with articles like this, as mentioned above, is that there is ''extremely little'' third-party coverage of the specific beliefs and practices that are common within the movement. There are a great deal of web-based Messianic congregations and the like (which [[WP:SELFSOURCE|are acceptable sources for some statements]], but we need to be careful how we word the material), but other than that most of the coverage it gets is from anti-missionary Rabbinic organizations and certain Christian groups. To my knowledge, there really hasn't been an in-depth independent scholarly analysis of the movement.

::::So, in order to make sure that we don't have a dearth of information, we shouldn't (and are not required by any policy or guideline to) discount primary sources entirely. As John Carter said, we just need to be careful about how we use them. The concern over weasel words is a legitimate one, though I'm not sure, with the current sourcing situation, there is a more preferable way to word those statements. [[User:Evanh2008|Evanh2008]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Evanh2008|talk]]&amp;#124;[[Special:Contributions/Evanh2008|contribs]])&lt;/sup&gt; 21:48, 9 August 2012 (UTC)

:::::Evan, again, &quot;Zero information is preferred to misleading or false information.&quot;  [[WP:PRIMARY]] sources are very difficult to use, and nearly impossible to use without a [[WP:SECONDARY]]:  &quot;Unless restricted by another policy, primary sources that have been reliably published may be used in Wikipedia; but only with care, because it is easy to misuse them. '''''Any interpretation of primary source material requires a reliable secondary source for that interpretation.'''''&quot; (emphasis mine)--this is policy.  What is currently in the article right now clearly violates [[WP:PRIMARY]] policy and really must be fixed, for example:
:::::*In ''the lead''(!):  &quot;some within the movement do not hold to Trinitarian beliefs&quot; sourced to primary source [http://jerusalemcouncil.org/articles/apologetics/trinitarianism/ The Jerusalem Council's statement].  I challenge you to read the statement and explain how it supports the article text without interpreting it yourself (doing so is forbidden by policy).
:::::*&quot;Some Messianic Jews affirm both the Shema and the Trinity, by understanding that the phrase &quot;the Lord is One&quot; to be referring to &quot;a differentiated but singular deity,”[71] and &quot;eternally existent in plural oneness.&quot;[72]  Source 71 is an MJ blog, source 72 is a position statement of a particular association of MJ groups, both primary sources, and the article interprets these primary sources against policy by saying they &quot;affirm the Shema and the Trinity.&quot;
:::::*&quot;Worship services are generally held on Friday evenings (Erev Shabbat) or Saturday mornings.[122]&quot;  This is another kind of misuse of WP:PRIMARY.  Source 122 (a dead link now) is to Rick Reinckens' personal website (fails [[WP:SPS]]), and it appears he has since scrubbed the &quot;Messianic Judaism&quot; angle of his site--he appears to now [http://www.godonthe.net/evidence/catholic.htm equate] &quot;Messianic&quot; with &quot;Protestant.&quot;  Assuming the original page can be found, this primary source is generalized to the practices of all of MJism.
:::::and that's just a small sample.  It's very dangerous to use [[WP:PRIMARY]] sources in this way to support religious statements especially, because (as you can see above and in the article), primary statements of religious movement insiders can be inscrutable, and ''must'' be interpreted by a reliable secondary source for us to use them.  In fact, it's beyond &quot;very dangerous,&quot; it is disallowed by policy.  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 15:19, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::Let me first say that this article is a lot better than it used to be. In the past year, Avraham and I and several other editors have made great strides in removing the vast majority of weasel-word statements. But it's still not perfect. This article is chock-full of problems, and you've rightly pointed out a couple of them. Regarding the Jerusalem Council thing, I think it's pretty clear that it's disowning, at least in name, trinitarian beliefs. So based on that, we can say that there is ''at least one'' Messianic congregation that doesn't believe in the Trinity (and there are others). Prior to an edit I made earlier this year, the Jerusalem Council source was being cited to a statement which implied that trinitarian beliefs are ubiquitous within the Messianic movement. That's just flat-out wrong; regardless of how one wants to read the source, it would be an exceptional display of mental gymnastics to infer that, based on a handful of primary sources, we can conclude one thing or another about the beliefs and practices of the entire movement. That's not a matter of interpretation; Jerusalem Council flat out says that their view is that trinitarianism as a theological construct is incompatible with the other views they espouse.

::::::So the alternative, perhaps, is to remove all mention of trinitarianism entirely, until we can get an accurate (that being the key word) appraisal from a reliable secondary source.

::::::As to your second point, without delving deeply into the sources myself (I'll do so soon), I'm not actually seeing the problem. If the sources mention the Shema and the Trinity, it's not interpretation to say that they affirm both. We're just mentioning two things in which they happen to believe in the same sentence.

::::::I agree with your third point entirely, and I think generalization is a major problem with the article, both in the past and as it currently stands. But the root of the problem, as I said before, is the lack of sources. On that note, I think we can all agree that the use of primary sources in this article should be minimized to the degree possible. I see John Carter and Deknmike have mentioned some secondary sources below, of which I was not previously aware. I'll look into it. Thanks. [[User:Evanh2008|Evanh2008]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Evanh2008|talk]]&amp;#124;[[Special:Contributions/Evanh2008|contribs]])&lt;/sup&gt; 00:19, 13 August 2012 (UTC)

== Reception among Jews ==

The ‘Specific response to Messianic Judaism’ subsection within ‘Reception among Jews’ is particularly non-encyclopedic, reading instead like an opposition position paper.-I have condensed the  text but kept all the references.  My edit follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Mainstream Jewish organizations object to the movement using the name “Messianic Judaism” and claim use of the term is misleading; they explain that while Judaism is a messianic religion, its messiah is not Jesus, ,&lt;ref name = &quot;Aish2&quot; /&gt;   .&lt;ref name=&quot;Lotker&quot; /&gt;  &lt;ref name=&quot;OutreachJudaism&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.outreachjudaism.org/about_us.html | title=About Us | accessdate=2010-12-18 | last=Singer| first= Tovia | authorlink = Tovia Singer | year=2006 | publisher=Outreach Judaism |quote=Outreach Judaism is an international organization that responds directly to the issues raised by missionaries and cults, by exploring Judaism in contradistinction to fundamentalist Christianity.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most American Jews see the person of Jesus as a clear dividing line between Christianity and Judaism, and therefore Messianic Judaism is perceived to be incompatible with any form of Jewishness. .&lt;ref name = &quot;Denominations&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kaplan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;JList1&quot;&gt;
*{{Cite book|last= Ariel |first= Yaakov |editor= [[Robert S. Wistrich]] (ed.) |title= Terms of survival: the Jewish world since 1945 |origyear= 1995 |edition= Digital Printing |year= 2005 |publisher=  [[Routledge]] |location= [[New York, New York]] |isbn= 0-415-10056-9 |pages= g. 343 |chapter= Protestant Attitudes to Jews and Judaism During the Last Fifty Years |quote=Evangelical Christians are engaged in aggressive and extensive missionary activity among Jews. Among other results, this has given rise to groups of 'Messianic Jews', of which 'Jews for Jesus' is the most outstanding example. These are actually Jews who have adopted the evangelical Protestant faith and its precepts.|lccn= 9422069}}
*{{Cite web|url= http://judaism.about.com/library/3_askrabbi_o/bl_simmons_messianicjews.htm |title= Messianic Jews, Buddhist Jews |accessdate= 2007-02-14 |last= Simmons |first= Shraga |work= Ask Rabbi Simmons |publisher= [[About.com]] |quote= Yet there are limits to pluralism, beyond which a group is schismatic to the point where it is no longer considered Jewish. For example, everyone considers Messianic Judaism and belief in Buddha as outside of the Jewish sphere.}}
*{{Cite book|last= Schoen |first= Robert |title= What I Wish My Christian Friends Knew about Judaism |accessdate= 2007-02-14 |year= 2004 |month= April |publisher= Loyola Press |location= [[Chicago]] |isbn= 0-8294-1777-X |pages= g. 11 |chapter= Jews, Jesus, and Christianity |chapterurl= http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN082941777X&amp;id=L86LbrUP8LoC&amp;pg=PP1&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=GCsP5mHs5_&amp;dq=What+I+Wish+My+Christian+Friends+Knew+about+Judaism&amp;sig=b-mpgZlQXWm6T1Lu5FwMwU4ndik#PPA11,M1 |quote=The Jewish people believe that when the Messiah comes there will be an end to world suffering.…Jews do not believe, therefore, that the Messiah has come, and they do not recognize Jesus as their savior or as the Son of God.|lccn= 200324404}}
*{{Cite web|url= http://www.messiahtruth.com/response.html |title= Messianic Judaism: A Christian Missionary Movement |accessdate= 2007-02-14 |publisher= Messiah Truth Project |quote=Messianic Judaism is a Christian movement that began in the 1970s combining a mixture of Jewish ritual and Christianity. There are a vast and growing numbers of these groups, and they differ in how much Jewish ritual is mixed with conventional Christian belief. One end of the spectrum is represented by Jews For Jesus, who simply target Jews for conversion to Christianity using imitations of Jewish ritual solely as a ruse for attracting potential Jewish converts. On the other end are those who don't stress the divinity of Jesus, but present him as the &quot;Messiah.&quot; They incorporate distorted Jewish ritual on an ongoing basis.}}
*{{Cite book|last= Ariel |first= David S. |title= What do Jews believe?: The Spiritual Foundations of Judaism |year= 1995  |publisher= [[Schocken Books]] |location= [[New York, New York]] |isbn= 0-8052-4119-1 |pages= g. 212 |chapter= The Messiah |quote=The Jews of the first centuries of the Common Era believed the Messiah had not yet come, while the followers of Jesus—strongly influenced by contemporary Jewish messianism—asserted that he was the Messiah. The belief that the Messiah has arrived and that he is Jesus is the teaching that most acutely divides Judaism from Christianity.|lccn= 943550}}
*{{Cite book|last= Nuesner |first= Jacob |authorlink= Jacob Neusner |others= Donald H. Akerson (forward) |title= A Rabbi Talks With Jesus |origyear= 1994 |url= |accessdate= 2007-02-14 |edition= Revised |year= 2000 |month= February |publisher= [[McGill-Queen's University Press]] |location= [[Canada]] |isbn= 0-7735-2046-5 |pages= 3–4 |chapter= Come, Let us Reason Together |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?visbn=0773520465&amp;id=eI7lR3rleYYC&amp;pg=PP1&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;ots=JE6mNzgIZF&amp;dq=A+Rabbi+Talks+With+Jesus&amp;sig=vO4zKvlOQdmCAEidwqWag5dqhLI#PPA3,M1 |quote=I write this book to shed some light why, while Christians believe in Jesus Christ and the good news of his rule in the kingdom of Heaven, Jews believe in the Torah of Moses and form on earth and in their own flesh God’s kingdom of priests and the holy people. And that belief requires faithful Jews to enter a dissent at the teachings of Jesus, on the grounds that those teachings at important points contradict the Torah. Where Jesus diverges from the revelation by God to Moses at Mount Sinai, he is wrong, and Moses is right.|lccn= 2001339789}}
*{{Cite web
| url = http://www.jcrcny.org/pdf/sdpp/MEETINGTHECHALLENG2.pdf
| title = Meeting the Challenge: Hebrew Christians and the Jewish Community
| accessdate = 2007-02-14
| last = Schiffman
| first = Lawrence H.
| authorlink = Lawrence Schiffman
| year = 1993
| format = PDF
| publisher = Jewish Community Relations Council of New York
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061107233420/http://www.jcrcny.org/pdf/sdpp/MEETINGTHECHALLENG2.pdf |archivedate = November 7, 2006 | quote = Though Hebrew Christianity claims to be a form of Judaism, it is not. It is nothing more than a disguised effort to missionize Jews and convert them to Christianity. It deceptively uses the sacred symbols of Jewish observance…as a cover to convert Jews to Christianity, a belief system antithetical to Judaism.…Hebrew Christianity is not a form of Judaism and its members, even if they are of Jewish birth, cannot be considered members of the Jewish community. Hebrew Christians are in radical conflict with the communal interests and the destiny of the Jewish people. They have crossed an unbreachable chasm by accepting another religion. Despite this separation, they continue to attempt to convert their former coreligionists.
}}
*{{Cite encyclopedia
 | last = Balmer
 | first = Randall Herbert
 | authorlink = Randall Balmer
 | encyclopedia = Encyclopedia of evangelicalism
 | title = Messianic Judaism
 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=Vjwly0QyeU4C&amp;dq=Encyclopedia+of+evangelicalism&amp;pg=PP1&amp;cd=1#PRA1-PA448,M1
 | accessdate = 2007-02-14
 | edition = Rev. and expanded
 | year = 2004
 | month = November
 | publisher = [[Baylor University#Publications|Baylor University Press]]
 | location = [[Waco, Texas]]
 | isbn = 1-932792-04-X
 | lccn = 2004010023
 | pages = 448–449
 | quote = Messianic Jewish organizations, such as Jews for Jesus, often refer to their faith as fulfilled Judaism, in that they believe Jesus fulfilled the Messianic prophecies. Although Messianic Judaism claims to be Jewish, and many adherents observe Jewish holidays, most Jews regard Messianic Judaism as deceptive at best, fraudulent at worst. They charge that Messianic Judaism is actually Christianity presenting itself as Judaism. Jewish groups are particularly distressed at the aggressive evangelistic attempts on the part of Messianic Jews.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Several [[counter-missionary]] organizations, such as [[Outreach Judaism]] and [[Jews for Judaism]] oppose Messianic Judaism on theological grounds, usually from an [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jewish]] perspective.  The [[Central Conference of American Rabbis|Reform Conference]] affirms that claiming that Jesus as savior removes that person from the Jewish community as an apostate. 
&lt;ref name=RELTOL&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/mess_jud4.htm Opposition to Messianic Judaism from the Jewish community] by Robinson, B. ([[Ontario Consultants on Religious Tolerance]])&lt;/ref &gt;  Some, such as Canadian [[B'nai Brith]], consider Messianic activities as antisemitic incidents.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;One of the more alarming trends in [[Anti-Semitism|antisemitic]] activity in Canada in 1998 was the growing number of incidents involving messianic organizations posing as &quot;synagogues&quot;. These missionizing organizations are in fact evangelical Christian proselytizing groups, whose purpose is specifically to target members of the Jewish community for conversion. They fraudulently represent themselves as Jews, and these so-called synagogues are elaborately disguised Christian churches.&quot;{{cite web |url=http://www.bnaibrith.ca/publications/audit1998/audit1998-07.html |year=1998 |title=Audit of Antisemitic Incidents. Missionaries and Messianic Churches }}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name =&quot;Singer_Blade&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:DeknMike|DeknMike]] ([[User talk:DeknMike|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/DeknMike|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:I 100% agree with DeknMike that this section is [[WP:UNDUE]] as it is far too large and detailed.  I generally like the direction of DeknMike's proposed rewrite although some of the wording and details need a bit of work.  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 14:28, 9 August 2012 (UTC)

::While I agree that DeknMike's re-worked version is more succinct, I do not think the principle of [[WP:UNDUE]] applies here.  [[WP:UNDUE]] says that &quot;articles should not give minority views as much of, or as detailed, a description as more widely held views&quot;.  If Messianic Judaism is indeed a form of &quot;Judaism&quot;, then it is the Messianics who hold the &quot;minority&quot; view, and mainstream Judaism that holds the &quot;more widely held view&quot; of what it is to be a Jew.  With this in mind, the core issue of the identification of Messianic Jews as either Christian or Jewish, but not both, deserves more than brief mention.  [[User:Eastcote|Eastcote]] ([[User talk:Eastcote|talk]]) 21:56, 9 August 2012 (UTC)
:::I myself disagree whether DUE applies in the way the above editor implies. The subject of this article is the MJs, not the Jews. While the MJ position would be a minotiry opinion among the Jews, and in articles about Judaism, the MJ position is clearly the majority position among the MJs themselves, I think, and on that basis, for the purposes of this article, their opinion is the majority opinion. It would be different in articles about Judaism per se, of course.Taking that into account, the proposed changes are good, but like Zad68 I think they would need some tweaking before they could be added. Also, having not been particularly involved in the discussion recently, I think it might help if the exact quotations or links were provided for the above claims from the Jewish perspective, because I am myself a bit too lazy to look everything up but I do realize that we want to convey as accurately as possible the opinions of the Jews, and also avoid any OR regarding claims of what &quot;most&quot; Jews think. I'm not sure I see that specifically sourced in the comments, although I might have missed it. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 01:10, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
::::Messianic Judaism is indeed a minority view.  The somewhat extreme analogy to illustrate the point would be the [[Flat Earth Society]].  Certainly, ''among'' Flat Earthers, the majority (unanimous?) view is that the Earth is flat.  That does not make their's a &quot;majority&quot; view in the sense intended by [[WP:UNDUE]], even for purposes of an article specific to that topic.  It is a fringe view.  Granted, matters of belief cannot be proven or disproven by science in the way that the shape of the Earth can.  However, within the whole that is Judaism -- and Messianic Jews claim to be part of that whole -- theirs is certainly a minority view.  The views of the majority within that whole should be represented prominently relative to who is or isn't a Jew.  [[User:Eastcote|Eastcote]] ([[User talk:Eastcote|talk]]) 02:20, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::There would be no justification for trimming away some of the material that is a direct consequence of the naming choices of the movement. A nondescript term was not chosen. Jews are responding to the confusion introduced by a relatively new Abrahamic religion calling itself &quot;Judaism&quot; but embracing as central tenets such concepts as the Messiahship of Jesus. The magnitude of this issue argues against trimming back material relating to it. [[User:Bus stop|Bus stop]] ([[User talk:Bus stop|talk]]) 03:28, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
{{outdent}}Eastcote, and Bus stop, I do indeed mean [[WP:UNDUE]].  For an article to avoid [[WP:UNDUE]], the emphasis the article should give to each viewpoint about the subject needs to be in proportion to the viewpoints found in reliable sources.  By [[WP:UNDUE]] here, I mean that if you were to take all the information reliable sources have to say about the subject, the amount of emphasis the article gives to each viewpoint should be in proportion to the emphasis the sources give--and &quot;emphasis&quot; is often determined by the amount of space the article devotes to the viewpoint.  Nearly one quarter of [[Messianic Judaism]] is taken up with criticism (called &quot;Reception&quot;) of it.  To avoid [[WP:UNDUE]], roughly one quarter of all the information reliable sources have to say about MJism would have to be criticism.  I really don't think this is the case.  Yes, the (nearly) universally negative critical reception MJism has gotten from Judaism (and also several branches of Christianity) is notable and should be included, but it shouldn't take up a quarter of the article.  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 14:49, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
:The fact that there is significant controversy about MJ is itself extremely noteworthy, and it is not undue weight to discuss this.  I agree the criticism should not take over the article, but it should not be minimized.  The &quot;reception&quot; section contains information concerning various controversies within Judaism itself, in Israel, and in the US military.  There are volumes of &quot;sources&quot; out there specific to MJ, but they are generally written by MJ organizations themselves.  MJ is by its nature a proselytising movement, and generates &quot;sources&quot; as part of that proselytising effort.  This has to be taken into account when determining what is or isn't a ''reliable'' source.  Wikipedia does not consider a group's own PR to be necessarily reliable.  There are ample reliable sources (that may or may not address MJ directly) that state that &quot;Jewish&quot; is incompatible with a belief in salvation through Jesus.  The controversy surrounding Jewish identity and MJ is central even to the ''definition'' of MJ.  The weasling discussed above includes phrasing such as &quot;''some'' adherents of Messianic Judaism are ethnically Jewish&quot;.  Does this mean &quot;most&quot; are not?  If MJ defines its members as Jews, yet only &quot;some&quot; are ethnically Jewish, then who are the rest?  Because this question of identity is central to the beliefs of MJ, and also central to controversy concerning them, then controversy and criticism should be relatively prominent.  [[User:Eastcote|Eastcote]] ([[User talk:Eastcote|talk]]) 15:58, 10 August 2012 (UTC)
::I'm not saying zero, I'm saying less, and in proportion with what's found in the reliable sources.
::&lt;p&gt;The self-promoting MJ materials are [[WP:PRIMARY]] and if we could (as discussed in the other section above) get the article to comply with policy by removing so much of the material dependent on primary sources and replace it with secondary-supported material, we could solve that problem.  Fixing the primary issues as pointed out would condense the article, and then the suggested size of the criticism section would make sense.  Both need to happen.  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 16:10, 10 August 2012 (UTC)

:::I agree a discussion of the movement should include note of significant opposition from Judaism and some parts of Christianity.  My point was to remove the copy/paste enumeration of a couple of [[WP:PRIMARY|primary]] source authors providing interpretive claims detailing their organization's opposition to the movement.  I left all references to avoid the appearance that I was conducting a scorched earth revision of the material.--[[User:DeknMike|DeknMike]] ([[User talk:DeknMike|talk]]) 23:46, 12 August 2012 (UTC)

== Available reliable sources ==

As some of you might know, Highbeam Research and other newsbanks have some information available on the subject of the MJs, including most of the academic journal articles on the subjects and several book reviews. I can and will e-mail to anyone who requests them and gives me their e-mail address the reviews and journal articles I can find. I do think in this case it would be useful to have separate articles on the major books on the topic which meet notability, so that we can know the academic views of those books, as well as the material in the academic journals and other highly reliable sources. Like I said, drop me an e-mail with your own e-mail address and I can send anyone who requests it the information I can find. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 17:31, 10 August 2012 (UTC)

:Thanks! That's an excellent source.  I've already read a couple articles I linked from there, including one from the Minneapolis Star Tribune from January 11, 2008, which has the director of organizational development for the Minnesota Council of Churches calling MJ a &quot;denominational no-man's land&quot;  He notes &quot;They call themselves Jewish but the Jews don't accept them. And the Christians don't relate to them. They're a loose band that exists all by themselves.&quot; [http://www.startribune.com/lifestyle/13707616.html?refer=y]  --[[User:DeknMike|DeknMike]] ([[User talk:DeknMike|talk]]) 23:58, 12 August 2012 (UTC)

: Minneapolis' Star Tribune did an article on one of their local Messianic congregations in 2008.  It cites two Messianic rabbis and a pastor with the Minnesota Council of Churches.  The article says &quot;Although the MJAA was founded in 1915, the Messianic movement really came into its own thanks to cultural forces beginning in the late 1960s.&quot;  The article notes that &quot;Jews for Jesus was founded in the mid-1970s, but is not officially associated with either of the national Messianic organizations.&quot; Perhaps that's where some of the confusion lies.  Some people believe that J4J is the penultimate Messianic organization, when in reality it is a Christian missions group staffed primarily by Jews who are friendly to the Messianic movement.  The article also supports the Jewish opposition to the movement paragraph:  &quot;Rothman's parents were shunned by some members of their Conservative Jewish synagogue when he broke away from the fold&quot; and &quot;Messianic Jews are left facing the worst of both religious worlds. They're subject to anti-Semitism by some non-Jews and shunned by some of their fellow Jews. It could be worse. In Israel, Messianic synagogues have been burned down in protest.&quot;  http://www.startribune.com/lifestyle/13707616.html?refer=y --[[User:DeknMike|DeknMike]] ([[User talk:DeknMike|talk]]) 04:44, 28 August 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>77fafe8zevpl7j99q8rn726idmbmrvi</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
