<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ash Wednesday</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2906601</id>
    <revision>
      <id>479371931</id>
      <parentid>479371771</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-02-28T22:34:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/67.142.171.23|67.142.171.23]] - &quot;/* Western Rite Orthodox */ new section&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29362">{{WikiProject Holidays|class=B|importance=High}}
{{ChristianityWikiProject|class=B|importance=High}}
{{talkheader}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-02-09|oldid1=16335597|date2=2006-03-01|oldid2=41759201|date3=2007-02-21|oldid3=109917608|date4=2008-02-06|oldid4=189219815|date5=2009-02-25|oldid5=273249922|date6=2010-02-17|oldid6=344150206|date7=2011-03-09|oldid7=417890351|date8=2012-02-22|oldid8=478335367}}

== Kneeling Day? ==

~~I have been Catholic all my life.  I have never heard of this phrase. Can someone explain it to me? I also find no reference to this in any liturgical rites book.  Does it need to be deleted?~~
::It is a real phrase! It is mostly to do with the divine office and imparticularly [[Lauds]] [[Prime]] and [[Sext]]. Various parts of the liturgy are said kneeling as a sign of penance. 
:::... the penítential days of the liturgical year. These include the ferias of Advent and Lent, most vigils, and Ember Days on which no feast occurs. They are named &quot;kneeling days&quot; because at these times of penance, much of the Office is said kneeling instead of standing, for example, the Preces at all the Hours, the Collect, and so on. Even at High Mass, the congregation is supposed to remain kneeling for parts of the Mass at which they would normally stand, eg. The Collect, the Pater Noster, the Postcommunion. The liturgical colour on a kneeling day should normally be purple.
::Hope this helps. [[User:Oliverkeenan|Oliver Keenan]] 23:03, 10 January 2006 (UTC)

==Fasting==

&quot;It also marks the beginning of the Lenten fast which lasts until Holy Saturday. During this period, Catholics between the ages of 18 and 59 are permitted to consume only one full meal, which may be supplemented by two smaller meals, which together should not equal the full meal.&quot;



This seems unbearably harsh to me - I was raised under the impression that adults were to limit themselves to one full meal &lt;i&gt;per day&lt;/i&gt;. Perhaps there has been a level of reform that snuck by under my radar. If this is the case, I fully support the decision; the level of liberalism in the modern church was becoming absolutely intolerable. It is certainly nothing, I hope, that restriction of meals to once-per-month could not cure. [[User:ChristopherKilbourn|ChristopherKilbourn]] 11:31, 7 February 2006 (UTC)
: XD --[[User:Antelucan|Antelucan]] 00:56, 26 February 2006 (UTC)

:Not only is it harsh, it is wrong. Fasting (along with abstinence) as described is only required, since Vatican II, on Ash Wednesday and Good Friday. On the other Fridays of Lent abstinence is required, that is, not eating meat or meat products. My credentials for saying this? I have been a priest for 35 years. [[User:Caeruleancentaur|Caeruleancentaur]] ([[User talk:Caeruleancentaur|talk]]) 15:36, 25 February 2009 (UTC)
::Well, the point he was making is that the way it was worded, it sounded like adults were permitted to eat only one full meal during the entire 6½-week period! —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 18:23, 25 February 2009 (UTC)

== Lenten Fast ==

Fasting only occurs on Ash Wednesday and Good Friday, NOT every day of Lent.
------------------------------------------
That is a specifically Roman Catholic practice, as they make a distinction between &quot;fasting&quot; and &quot;abstinence.&quot;

:So does Anglicanism [[User:Carolynparrishfan|Carolynparrishfan]] 13:34, 24 February 2006 (UTC)
-----------------------------------------------------------------
''' HAPPY ASH WEDNESDAY ON MARCH 1, 2006. ''' It's 13:44 on Wed Feb 15, 2006 in Solano,Nueva Vizcaya,Philippines.  My site is at http://www.michaelmanalolazo.webitsmart.co.uk  Just Surfing. Thanks.
-------------------------------------------------------
&quot;Happy Ash Wednesday&quot;?  THERE'S an oxymoron if I ever heard one. :)
---------------------------------------------------------------------

Fasting and abstinence don't necessarily mean you shold be sad :) Cecia 
--------------------------------------------------------------
Have a solemn and dignified Ash Wednesday, brothers.
----------------------------------------
Good morning, from a brother in Christ in San Diego, CA, USA.  May your Ash Wednesday bring you quiet reflection and understanding of the holy mysteries.  May it help prepare you for the joy of Easter.  --[[User:Sr.Wombat|Sr.Wombat]] 14:06, 01 March 2006 (UTC)
---------------------------------------
According to the US Council of Bishops, fasting is required on Ash Wednesday and Good friday, and encouraged on other days.
--[[User:Alpharigel|Alpharigel]] 03:15, 24 February 2006 (UTC)


==Current Event==

Why is there a Current Event tag at the top of the page?  It's Ash Wednesday today, but I don't think that merits a &quot;current event&quot; marker. [[User:Elliotreed|Elliotreed]] 04:03, 2 March 2006 (UTC)

== Ash Wednesday and its place in time relative to the date of Easter ==

If Ash Wednesday falls forty-four (44) days before Good Friday, how can it fall just forty (40) days before Easter, which is in fact the Sunday after Good Friday?

______
Sundays are not counted as part of Lent.  It is actually 40 days excluding Sundays.  Ash Wedensday is 46 days before Easter.[[User:Cfortunato|Carlo]] 05:30, 4 March 2006 (UTC)

IS there a reason why this day is on a Wednesday? Why can't it be Ash Monday or Tuesday?

:Because by definition it has to be forty-six days before Easter, which is always on a Sunday. Forty-six days (six weeks plus four days) before any Sunday is always a Wednesday. [[User:Angr|Angr]]/&lt;small&gt;''[[User talk:Angr|talk]]''&lt;/small&gt; 10:19, 18 March 2006 (UTC)

::To put it more precisely: Lent lasts 40 days, but Sundays are not counted when figuring the 40. Get a calendar off the wall and put a piece of paper over the column of Sundays. Now count 40 days backwards from Easter Day, skipping Sundays. You will find that you arrive at the number 40 on the 7th Wednesday before Easter, which is Ash Wednesday. If we figure in the Sundays as well, we find that Ash Wednesday is 46 days before Easter. [[User:MishaPan|MishaPan]] ([[User talk:MishaPan|talk]]) 03:06, 24 March 2008 (UTC)

:::The Eastern Orthodox start Great Lent on a Monday.  This past Monday was the beginning, and Easter/Pascha is the same day on the Eastern and Western Calendars this year.  Does anybody know how they count to arrive at 40 days?  Does Lent officially end on Good Friday for them or something? [[User:Cfortunato|Carlo]] ([[User talk:Cfortunato|talk]]) 04:40, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

::::I'm not Orthodox (anyone with more knowledge are free to correct/add information), but this is how I've understood it: The Orthodox/Eastern fast for Lent is indeed 40 days. However, there are two differences between the Eastern and Western practice: (1) Sundays are always ''included'' in the counting; (2) Lent ends on the Friday before Good Friday. The day after this Friday--i.e. the day before Palm Sunday--is [[Lazarus Saturday]] in the Orthodox church, when this church celebrates the resurrection of Lazarus of Bethany. However, Holy week is still a season of fasting--although ''Lent'' officially ends on Friday night (the eve of Lazarus Saturday). [[User:AxelWN|AxelWN]] ([[User talk:AxelWN|talk]]) 15:15, 7 October 2011 (UTC)


What happens during leap years when an extra day is added? wouldn't that move it off of Wednesday then? if Easter is early enough to put it in Februrary  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.99.219.11|216.99.219.11]] ([[User talk:216.99.219.11|talk]]) 22:07, 12 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:No--nothing happens with Ash Wednesday during leap years; weekdays aren't affected by leap years--the week just goes on, including the 29 February as though nothing has happened. (29 February is always a normal week day, you know. ;)) So this doesn't make a difference: 29 February is included in the 46 days of fasting. As the article says, Ash Wednesday has never been on 29 February and won't be so until 2096. However, there's one factor with Ash Wednesdays and leap years. Next year (2012), Easter Sunday will be on 8 April, as it was in 2007. However, since it's a leap year, Ash Wednesday will take place on 22 February, rather than the 21st as it did in 2007. Good question though. [[User:AxelWN|AxelWN]] ([[User talk:AxelWN|talk]]) 15:15, 7 October 2011 (UTC)

== Headline text ==
If Sundays are not icluded in the Lent Calender, then I assume fasting is out and a good roast is in??? I'm not sure fasting does work, I think you end up irritable and lose concentration/focus. Ok if you have a day off work!! &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/204.104.55.243|204.104.55.243]] ([[User talk:204.104.55.243|talk]]) 16:47, 13 February 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

== ~~HAPPY ASH WEDNESDAY~~ ==

'''~~HAPPY ASH WEDNESDAY~~'''
''Italic text''
''Ash Wednesday,This is my first returning Ash Wednesday since back in my youth.  I know is been a while. However, I decided to contribute to the lessons I learned back in my youth.  I have been surfing the web in search of history on how we honor “Ash Wednesday.”  I am not sure if this is appropriate for this website but It seems to find most of my researches I have done on this website “Wikipedia”, this site has been very informatived, and now I can post to the discussion site. great!
Thank you.  ([[User:Elidiadixon|Elidiadixon]] 00:34, 21 February 2007 (UTC)).''

== Leap Day ==

There are two sentences in the first paragraph about Ash Wednesday falling on a leap day (Feb 29):

&lt;blockquote&gt;Ash Wednesday can fall on Leap Day only during a leap year for which 15 April is Easter Sunday. The next time Ash Wednesday will fall on Leap Day will be in 2096, the first such year since the 1582 adoption of the Gregorian Calendar.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

But it doesn't explain the significance of that - is there any significance? [[User:DeanHarding|DeanHarding]] 05:45, 21 February 2007 (UTC)

I think that they should be moved down to the bottom of the article after the list of dates for Ash Wednesday if it is indeed relevant information. Personally I think it should just go, it might become relevant in 80 years or so. --[[User:82.47.166.66|82.47.166.66]] 07:47, 21 February 2007 (UTC)


Leap day is actually the 25 of Feb not the 29 FEB since it corresponds to a.d. bis vi Kal. Feb.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.99.219.11|216.99.219.11]] ([[User talk:216.99.219.11|talk]]) 23:07, 12 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== How long should the ashes stay on my forehead? ==

Just came back from Ash Wednesday services, and wondering how long the ashes are supposed to stay.  Is it being a bad catholic to remove them once I return to work or home?

Peace to you all during this lenten season. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/65.87.238.124|65.87.238.124]] ([[User talk:65.87.238.124|talk]]) 19:31, 21 February 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

:It's up to you. Some people remove them as soon as they leave church, obeying the dictum of the Gospel Reading of the day: &quot;When you fast, don't look glum or change your appearance, but wash your face&quot; (paraphrasing from memory). Others find it a strong spiritual discipline to leave it on, because it marks you and some people react to it - not always positively. I think both are legitimate, and which one you do is up to you and depends where you are on your spiritual journey. At least, that's MY opinion. [[User:Cfortunato|Carlo]]

Answer:

{{cquote|The priest or minister marks the forehead of each participant with black ashes, in the shape of a cross, which the worshipper traditionally retains until washing it off after sundown.}}


P.S. Happy Ash Wednesday to everyone! [[User:FellowWikipedian|FellowWikip]]&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:FellowWikipedian/Esperanza|e]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User talk:FellowWikipedian|dian]] 19:37, 21 February 2007 (UTC)

== Painting ==

I know that thisis suppose to be an academic article, but being a religious article implies some sensitivity. To that end, I must protest at the seemingly pointless image painting of &quot;Ash Wednesday, after a Carnival&quot;. What? Who cares? Carnival? Inappropriate! It shows a man laying low in what seems to be an alleyway. For all I know, the art has nothing to do with Ash Wednesday. If no one objects within 24hrs, I will remove it.[[User:Tourskin|Tourskin]] 06:06, 22 February 2007 (UTC)

---- I saw the picture just before you removed it.  It was very appropriate.  In New Orleans, Brazil and other locations, Ash Wednesday marks the end of carnival season.  The man in the painting was dressed as if he had been a participant in a carnival parade.  Still in those clothes, he was deep in prayer with the light of daylight (maybe the light of God) shining on him.  The jar at right in the photo perhaps symbolizes what we need to sustain us during our Lenten journey.  I think you should restore the photo.

It looks to me like he's in jail.  As though he got arrested for some shenanigans at Carnival and now on Ash Wednesday he has time to &quot;repent&quot; -- BEHIND BARS.  It is a very amusing painting and entirely appropriate. &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:24.213.57.50|24.213.57.50]] ([[User talk:24.213.57.50|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/24.213.57.50|contribs]]) 14:09, 6 February 2008 &lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned2 --&gt;

== A sentence seems out of place ==

&quot;The Penitential psalms are read.&quot; sentence seems out of place. Should it be moved? I don't know whether this is done by both RC and Anglicans, so I left it alone. 
[[User:Bettyg51|Bettyg51]] 16:48, 22 February 2007 (UTC)BettyG

== Is Nordic custom different? ==

I have a question for anyone that might be able to shed light on where the following tradition came from.

In Iceland Ash Wednesday is celebrated much like Halloween is in the English speaking world - kids go around singing songs in all manner of costumes and beg for candy. This is preceded on Monday and Tuesday by festivities involving the consumption of cream filled buns (Monday is &quot;Bun Day&quot;) and large quantities of salted meat (Tuesday is &quot;Bursting Day&quot;, as in your gut).

What I'm wondering is whether anyone recognizes one or more elements of these seemingly odd traditions (celebrations and feasting don't seem to coincide with what I'm reading about Ash Wednesday in other cultures). Is it a Nordic thing? Has it died out in Scandinavia? Basically: what gives?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/194.144.85.130|194.144.85.130]] ([[User talk:194.144.85.130|talk]]) 15:00, 1 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Information on such practices is found in the article [[Carnival]], which is the last opportunity for feasting and merrymaking before the Lenten season of fasting, sobriety and self-examination begins. In most cultures Carnival ends on [[Shrove Tuesday]] (the day before Ash Wednesday), but from what you write it would seem that in Iceland it continues on Ash Wednesday itself. Continuing the merrymaking on Ash Wednesday does indeed seem to be at odds with the intent of the day. [[User:MishaPan|MishaPan]] ([[User talk:MishaPan|talk]]) 03:16, 24 March 2008 (UTC)

::Alright, I read the about Ash Wednesday in Icelandic. There's another holiday in Iceland two days before Ash Wednesday (Bolludagur). Apparently, Bolludagur used to be very similar to what Ash Wednesday in Iceland is like today, but at some point the two holidays seem to have swapped traditions and now Ash Wednesday is celebrated in the old fashion of Bolludagur.

== Denominations observing Ash Wednesday ==

I propose deleting the &quot;Denominations observing Ash Wednesday&quot; section.

The list appears to be just a grab bag, without objective criteria for either inclusion on the list or the use of &quot;some&quot;.

For example, I suspect that most Presbyterian and Wesleyan churches in Australia are not &quot;among those that mark Ash Wednesday by holding a service&quot;. Why are they on the list and not preceded by &quot;some&quot;? Is it enough that one church in a family of churches anywhere in the world observes Ash Wednesday?

The information about the eastern churches could be retained, as it appears to be more generally applicable.

[[User:Sir rupert orangepeel|Sir rupert orangepeel]] ([[User talk:Sir rupert orangepeel|talk]]) 01:22, 7 January 2009 (UTC)

== What does the priest say? ==

The last line in the introduction that mentions what the priest says while marking the person with the ashes should be deleted. In the next section it is mentioned that actually there are options for the priest. [[User:Caeruleancentaur|Caeruleancentaur]] ([[User talk:Caeruleancentaur|talk]]) 15:31, 25 February 2009 (UTC)

== End of carnival ==

There are two references in the article mentioning that Ash Wednesday is the end of Carnival. This is not really true. Carnival ends at midnight on Tuesday (Mardi Gras). The period of fasting and abstinence begins that same midnight, so there is no way that Ash Wednesday can be construed as a part of Carnival. Carnival ends on the last day of Carnival. Of course, the effects of Mardi Gras might be felt on Ash Wednesday :-) [[User:Caeruleancentaur|Caeruleancentaur]] ([[User talk:Caeruleancentaur|talk]]) 15:46, 25 February 2009 (UTC)

Actually one second after 11:59:59pm Tuesday is 12:00:00 Wednesday (the day changes at that moment)
Midnight Tuesday is on second after 11:59:59pm Monday (24hrs before the time you seem to mean) and therefor Carnival ends just before midnight Wednesday  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.99.219.11|216.99.219.11]] ([[User talk:216.99.219.11|talk]]) 23:15, 12 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Repetitions ==

This article has too many repetitions and half truths. Distinction is not made between the practices of the various faiths. &quot;In most liturgies&quot;; whose? I have some expertise in this area and would be happy to fix the article, if the author would get in touch with me. [[User:Caeruleancentaur|Caeruleancentaur]] ([[User talk:Caeruleancentaur|talk]]) 15:58, 25 February 2009 (UTC)
:It's a wiki. There is no single author to get in touch with you. Just [[WP:be bold|be bold]] and fix it, remembering to cite your [[WP:RS|sources]]. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 18:21, 25 February 2009 (UTC)

If one chose the last moment of any given day on the calendar it could be infintesantly measured as any moment before midnight.  In my opinion, for precisions sake it would be best when describing the division of two days to refer to the limiting of one day by the start of the next.  i.e. 'The events of &quot;Carnival&quot; could be construed to occur outside the practice of Lenten observances, so long as they are concluded up to the moment of midnight the day preceding the comencement of your Lenten observance...' This is only an exaple sentence that I have attempted to put in context of the disscussion.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Timestampd|Timestampd]] ([[User talk:Timestampd|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Timestampd|contribs]]) 21:38, 17 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== why a redirect of &quot;imposition of ashes&quot; ==

i came to wikipedia looking for discussion/explanation of &quot;imposition of ashes.&quot;  however, there is merely a redirect to &quot;ash wednesday&quot; wherein the phrase &quot;imposition of ashes&quot; never appears.  how are they related?   is &quot;imposition of ashes&quot; an anglican/episcopalean phrase?   never heard the phrase before (i'm 50+; non-catholic/episcopalean; not religious) but this year suddenly noticed banners on several new york city churches (not to say i just never noticed in earlier years).  i would expect/understand &quot;application of ashes&quot; but why &quot;imposition&quot;?   article fails to educate me.--[[Special:Contributions/71.183.238.134|71.183.238.134]] ([[User talk:71.183.238.134|talk]]) 18:50, 25 February 2009 (UTC)
:The article could definitely use a discussion, or at least a mention, of the term. The Imposition of Ashes is the point where the priest applies the ashes in the form of a cross to the churchgoer's forehead. The term is certainly used in Anglican and Episcopal churches, and probably in other denominations as well. Why the word &quot;Imposition&quot; rather than &quot;Application&quot; is used, I don't know; but it sounds more solemn to me, while &quot;application&quot; would sound too technical. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] 19:04, 25 February 2009 (UTC)

:Is there any other context in which ''imposition of ashes'' takes on meaning other than Ash Wednesday? [[User:Patsw|patsw]] ([[User talk:Patsw|talk]]) 23:49, 8 March 2009 (UTC)

== Kneeling while receiving ashes ==

The introductory section reads in part:

This paste is used by the priest who presides at the service to make the sign of the cross, first upon his own forehead and then on each of those present who kneel before him at the altar rail. 

This is not necessarily true. Many churches no longer have altar rails and penitents receive the ashes while standing in front of the altar. Also, if other priests or deacons are present, they apply the ashes to each others foreheads instead of self-applying.Furthermore, other Christian faiths without priest also distribute ashes.

I recommend changing the sentence to:

This paste is used by the celebrant who presides at the service to make the sign of the cross on the foreheads of each of those who approach him.

[[User:Wkharrisjr|Wkharrisjr]] ([[User talk:Wkharrisjr|talk]]) 20:28, 25 February 2009 (UTC)wkharrisjr 02/25/2009

== Pagan origin? ==

{{quote|However, some Adventists who do not celebrate Ash Wednesday say that the practice of imposition of ashes is not consistent with Scripture and is of pagan origin.}}

What follows doesn't support this claim.  What follows supports an entirely different claim -- that the ashes may be worn ''hypocritically'' or ''ostentatiously''. {{niv|Matthew|6:16-18|Matthew 6:16-18}} refers to Jewish hypocrites.

Either the text should either have support for the claim, or the claim should be revised to match the supporting statement. [[User:Patsw|patsw]] ([[User talk:Patsw|talk]]) 23:47, 8 March 2009 (UTC)

There's a strong connection with [[Norse mythology]]: &quot;And strange as it may seem, one [[Wednesday]], or [[Odin|Odin's]] day, is specially devoted to him, under the name of 'Ash Wednesday'...&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Walford|first=Edward, and John Charles Cox, George Latimer Apperson|title=The Antiquary, Vol 6.|year=2010|publisher=Bibliolife|isbn=1149882999|pages=260|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=XtgLAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=ash%20wednesday%20odin&amp;pg=PA260#v=onepage&amp;q=ash%20wednesday%20odin&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;.  From the same source, Odin's [[Ash tree]] is the world tree [[Yggdrasil]].  And &quot;The Norse practice of Ash Wednesday goes back several hundred years earlier, when it was done to celebrate the deeds of [[Sigurd]], the hero of the Volsung Saga, a character perhaps better known as Siegfried from the Ring of the Nibelung.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gibson|first=Allyn|title=On Ash Wednesday|url=http://www.allyngibson.net/?p=969|publisher=http://www.allyngibson.net/|accessdate=2010-03-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[User:Drf5n|Drf5n]] ([[User talk:Drf5n|talk]]) 14:51, 9 March 2011 (UTC)

::The blog that you quoted and linked to has this in the comments by the author of said blog: &quot;I wrote this blog post several years ago, based on things I remembered from college several years before that.  And, to be frank, at times, I’ve wondered if that history professor (I was a history major in college) was having a lark.&quot;
::Just because someone said it somewhere in cyberspace doesn't make it a source. [[User:Cfortunato|Carlo]] ([[User talk:Cfortunato|talk]]) 20:26, 9 March 2011 (UTC)
:::Ha! You beat me to it. Let's not put any of that in there as long as we don't have the sources to it. I've asked Allyn what that professor's sources could have been. [[User:Trigaranus|Trigaranus]] ([[User talk:Trigaranus|talk]]) 00:05, 10 March 2011 (UTC)

== National No Smoking Day ==

It's a bit much calling it [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ash_Wednesday&amp;diff=298019415&amp;oldid=298012622 &quot;utterly irrelevant&quot;]. The sources establish the relevance: The date was chosen because quitting smoking ties in with [[Lent#Fasting and abstinence|giving up luxury for Lent]]. You mean because it's not specifically Christian? Or what? [[User:Jnestorius|jnestorius]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Jnestorius|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 00:16, 23 June 2009 (UTC)

== Ritual ==

The standard text for the Catholic Church in the United States for many aspects of liturgy is the ''The Order of Prayer in the Litugy of the Hours and Celebration of the Eucharist'' (or the ''Ordo'' for short). It is published by the [http://www.paulistpress.com/pdfs/info.pdf Paulist Press].  It lists only two formulas for the ritual
* ''Turn away from sin and be faithful to the Gospel.''
* ''Remember, you are dust, and to dust you will return.''
What is the source for the third form given in the article (''Repent and hear the good news.'')? [[User:Patsw|patsw]] ([[User talk:Patsw|talk]]) 00:10, 7 March 2011 (UTC)

:I just checked the various missiles on my shelf as well as this month's Magnificat and didn't see the third quote anywhere, so I removed it. [[User:Cfortunato|Carlo]] ([[User talk:Cfortunato|talk]]) 20:29, 9 March 2011 (UTC)

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Movable/Moveable Feast/Fast ==

The average reader would like a little more clarity on this: the day is claimed to be a Movable [sic] Feast (linking to an article called [[Moveable feast]] - and also a Moveable Fast, [[Moveable fast]].  It's both?  They're the same thing (but two different articles?) and the spelling varies randomly?  I am sure it's all clear to someone who already knows about these things, but it would be encyclopedic to tidy this up and explain it all.[[User:KD Tries Again|KD Tries Again]] ([[User talk:KD Tries Again|talk]]) 04:18, 10 March 2011 (UTC)KD Tries Again
:Good catch.  Feasts and fasts are different things; one involves, well, [[meal|feasting]], and the other involves [[fasting]], i.e. refraining from food.  Ash Wednesday is not and has never been a feast.  [[User:Glenfarclas|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#3B6AA0;color:#EDEDED&quot; vlink=&quot;color:#EDEDED&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;'''Glenfarclas'''&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Glenfarclas|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#003F87&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]) 06:30, 10 March 2011 (UTC)

== Canonical gospels versus Synoptic Gospels ==

The main entry says, &quot;According to the canonical gospels of Matthew, Mark and Luke ...&quot; That should be changed to say, &quot;According to the Synoptic Gospels of Matthew, Mark and Luke ...&quot; Every book in the Bible is canonical. However, the Gospel of John is the one which is not &quot;Synoptic.&quot; The other three Gospels, Matthew, Mark and Luke, when viewed collectively, as they are in the main entry for Ash Wednesday, are Synoptic Gospels, not merely 'canonical gospels.'  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.7.178.186|24.7.178.186]] ([[User talk:24.7.178.186|talk]]) 19:49, 22 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Edit request on 23 February 2012 ==
{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Ash Wednesday begins 40 days of Easter, not 46
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/76.19.120.142|76.19.120.142]] ([[User talk:76.19.120.142|talk]]) 00:48, 23 February 2012 (UTC)
:{{not done}} You are confusing the 40 days of [[Lent]] with how long before Easter Sunday Ash Wednesday occurs, which skips counting the 6 Sundays in between. [[User:Dru of Id|Dru of Id]] ([[User talk:Dru of Id|talk]]) 01:47, 23 February 2012 (UTC)

== History of observance?  History of the imposition of ashes? ==

When did these things start?  How has the observance and practice changed throughout history?
[[Special:Contributions/99.22.228.93|99.22.228.93]] ([[User talk:99.22.228.93|talk]]) 22:04, 23 February 2012 (UTC)

== Western Rite Orthodox ==

Ash Wednesday is also celebrated by Western Rite Orthodox Christians.  I am a member of a western rite parish under the Antiochian Archdiocese (http://www.antiochian.org/) and we will be celebrating Ash Wednesday and the start of Holy Lent tomorrow.  It would be nice if someone included this in the article.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.142.171.23|67.142.171.23]] ([[User talk:67.142.171.23|talk]]) 22:33, 28 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ela4r3n9kpv2s2igmytmpjloclgnm1j</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
