<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Mormonism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5559178</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521749169</id>
      <parentid>521714069</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T23:49:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adjwilley</username>
        <id>1776566</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted to revision 520804242 by 208.81.184.4: Weird blanking. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20861">{{skip to talk}}
{{talk header|noarchive=yes|search=no}}
{{not a forum|personal beliefs, nor for engaging in [[Apologetics]]/[[Polemic]]s}}
{|class=&quot;messagebox standard-talk&quot;
|align=&quot;center&quot; width=5%|
[[Image:Diamond-caution.svg|50px|]]
|'''This topic contains [[Wikipedia:List of controversial issues|controversial issues]]''', some of which have reached a consensus for approach and neutrality, and some of which may be [[Wikipedia:NPOV_dispute|disputed]].  Should you wish to make any substantial changes or additions;
*'''Before''' making any such substantial changes, please carefully read the discussion-page dialogue.
*'''During''' any such changes, please be careful to [[WP:CITE|cite reputable sources]] supporting them, and when submitting your edit, please include an accurate and concise description  in the &quot;Edit summary&quot; field-box.
*'''After''' making any such changes, please also carefully describe the reason(s) for any such changes on the discussion-page.
&lt;small&gt;(This message should only be placed on talk pages, please.)&lt;/small&gt;{{check talk}}
|}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
 {{WikiProject Christianity |class=C |importance=Top}}
 {{LDSproject |class=C |importance=Top }}
 {{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top|NRM=yes|NRMImp=Top}}
}}
{{archive box |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months |indes=/Archive index |search=yes |
# [[Talk:Mormonism/Archive 1|Archive 1]]: Jan 2003 - Jun 2006
# [[Talk:Mormonism/Archived coverup allegations|Archived coverup allegations]]
# [[Talk:Mormonism/Archive 2|Archive 2]]: Jun 2006 - Dec 2006
# [[Talk:Mormonism/Archive 3|Archive 3]]: Jun 2006 - Dec 2006
# [[Talk:Mormonism/Archive 4|Archive 4]]: Sept 2008 – Nov 2010 
# [[/Archive 5|Archive 5]]: 2011 –
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 6
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Mormonism/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}

== Contradiction - is the Community of Christ Mormon? ==

The introduction states &quot;[Mormonism] differs from other Latter Day Saint movement traditions (such as the [[Community of Christ]]) in that it also accepts the [[Pearl of Great Price (Mormonism)|Pearl of Great Price]] as part of its scriptural canon...&quot; This implies that the [[Community of Christ]] is not Mormon, but the introduction there calls them so. Can someone resolve the contradiction? --[[User:KnightMove|KnightMove]] ([[User talk:KnightMove|talk]]) 09:37, 27 June 2012 (UTC)

== New section needed ==

1. As a former LDS, I think the article reads, on the whole, like a brochure a missionary would leave in one's door. It's mighty &quot;glowy&quot; in a lot of places.

2. I think a section comparing the Church to Scientology would be interesting and fruitful. From what I've read of Scientology, they have some very similar aspects that I'd like to read more about, outer space being a springboard.

Thanks, [[User:Wordreader|Wordreader]] ([[User talk:Wordreader|talk]]) 03:19, 23 August 2012 (UTC)

: As a current LDS member I will throw out my thoughts on the Scientology aspect:

:Scientology and Mormonism have some vary basic similarities. They both believe the soul to be eternal. They both believe in eternal progression in one way or another. For each similarity there are a dozens of differences. In Mormon theology the spirit was created by God intentionally. In Scientology the spirit was created because the original spiritual being conceived that there may be other beings, and so it happened. In Mormon theology, one can progress to become like their Father in Heaven through the atonement of Christ. In Scientology one progresses through reincarnation. The Mormons church claims to be a restored gospel through Joseph Smith Jr. Scientology claims to be created by L. Ron Hubbard in a search for the soul. Mormons believe that God is the architect of all things including space. Often the term Kolob is used to identify the name of a star near the throne of God in Mormon theology, which allows for interpretation of God within our own time and space. Mormons believe that they will retain their physical bodies after death. In Scientology, Thetans exist outside of the physical realm in their own universe. After death a Thetan no longer needs the physical body.

:Thus, in my opinion, a section on similarities is not accurate use for Wikipedia. In the same process of logic a Mormon church has similarities with an ice cream shop. Both have sinks and both have refrigerators. Both are made out of standard building materials. These similarities do not necessarily mean that they should be compared against one another in an encyclopedia. This is something that is better left to those who have a bone to pick and have their own web space for linking such minor threads. [[User:Dromidaon|Dromidaon]] ([[User talk:Dromidaon|talk]]) 17:49, 23 August 2012 (UTC)
::Mormonism could be compared with any number of things. Not all comparisons are useful. Comparisons with Christianity, Islam, and Judaism are useful because they are major world religions, and, like Mormonism, all [[Abrahamic religions]]. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:10.2pt&quot;&gt;~[[User:Adjwilley|Adjwilley]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:7pt&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Adjwilley|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 18:03, 23 August 2012 (UTC)

:::Thank you, [[User:Dromidaon|Dromidaon]] ([[User talk:Dromidaon|talk]]). I appreciate your Scientology comments; they're very interesting. [[User:Wordreader|Wordreader]] ([[User talk:Wordreader|talk]]) 19:57, 10 September 2012 (UTC)

== Core Mormonism beliefs ==

Hi. So as you are an LDS member, please clarify/correct what is incorrect in the edit:

Mormon beliefs include the claim that the [[God the Father]], [[Jesus Christ]] and the [[Holy Spirit]] are three separate beings not united under one [[monotheism|monotheistic deity]]. In addition, Mormons believe that [[God the Father]] needed a physical body and is not made of spiritual substance in his own inherent divine nature. Furthermore, Mormon beliefs cite that souls who enter [[Heaven]] someday become deity-like, immortal and divine in equal footing with the [[Holy Trinity]]. Regarding [[soteriology]], Mormon beliefs claim that the [[passion of Jesus Christ]]'s [[crucifixion]] was not enough to merit [[redemption]] and [[salvation]] for humankind.

From what I understand from my teenage years, these beliefs were true and in-line accurate with my own Mormon Fellowship Group.  Because the Patheos website is an impartial website on religious beliefs, and Mr. Ben Wotherington has spent a great deal of time researching and comparing Mormon beliefs along with other [[Abrahamic]] religions. Whatever is inaccurate, please point out so it can be fact-checked and revised as such. [[User:QvisDevs|QvisDevs]] ([[User talk:QvisDevs|talk]]) 17:50, 31 August 2012 (UTC)

{{ec}}
:I recently reverted {{diff|Mormonism|next|510076104|this recent addition}} to the Lead section of the article. It was sourced mainly to blog-like websites. (Note, one website was [[patheos]].com, but the article being cited was from the blogs side of the website.) [[CARM]] was also cited, which is problematic, especially when trying to nail down Mormon beliefs. There also seemed to be a fair amount of unintentional misrepresentation. For instance, a website that said, &quot;[Mormons] believe that they are one in purpose and mission and that they are three separate divine beings.&quot; was supporting a sentence here that said &quot;Mormon beliefs include the claim that the [[God the Father]], [[Jesus Christ]] and the [[Holy Spirit]] are three separate beings not united under one [[monotheism|monotheistic deity]]&quot;. (The website said nothing of monotheism, and to say that Mormons believe the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit aren't united is a large overstatement.) &lt;p&gt;There are a lot of issues mixed into this one edit, so it's probably not a good idea to try to address them altogether. The precise details of where the inaccuracies were is a little complicated, but I can explain what they are if you would like. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:10.2pt&quot;&gt;~[[User:Adjwilley|Adjwilley]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:7pt&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Adjwilley|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 18:04, 31 August 2012 (UTC)
::{{ec}}Also, to clarify, I'm not calling Patheos, or Mr. Wotherington biased. What I am saying is that Mr. Wotheringon's blog post hasn't gone through the rigorous peer-review process that it takes to publish a book or scholarly paper, and he's probably made unintentional mistakes. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:10.2pt&quot;&gt;~[[User:Adjwilley|Adjwilley]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:7pt&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Adjwilley|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 18:17, 31 August 2012 (UTC)
:::NO he hasn't. What are you talking about? Even Mormon believers who commented on his article admit to the accuracy of what he wrote. But they find it unpleasant and attacking their religion. Regardless they even admit that those informations are correct. I was into Mormonism in my High School years and I learned the same thing TOO during my Fellowship meetings. Like I said, if you have nothing to hide, be open with your beliefs. Nobody is trying to nail it down, you just don't want this belief system exposed to its full entirety... what is worse, you're not even willing to meet in the middle to edit what is necessary so that it reflects the full value and vision of Mormon beliefs rather than being a cop out. Enjoy your article. [[User:QvisDevs|QvisDevs]] ([[User talk:QvisDevs|talk]]) 18:23, 31 August 2012 (UTC)

LOL. Now you're just too chicken. I understand that you are this faith which I respect. But you should be proud of what you believe in, and cite them as such rather than disbanding my entire edit. I'm not going to force another edit on this, but its just FUNNY how you see it as trying to &quot;nail Mormonism down&quot;... because its not. If you're really PRO-Mormonism then be proud to state what those beliefs are, and correct them when they are problematic. I'm Catholic and many people disagree with the core beliefs of our faith, but we're not chicken about it... and they are laid out IN DETAIL on Wikipedia, and yes some of those Catholic sources come from Patheos website. You can have your article. [[User:QvisDevs|QvisDevs]] ([[User talk:QvisDevs|talk]]) 18:12, 31 August 2012 (UTC)
:{{ec}}:In my experience wearing one's beliefs on one's sleeve isn't always helpful, and making assumptions about others' beliefs is almost never helpful. I am perfectly willing to discuss this with you. There were multiple problems with the edit, and reverting was easier than trying to pick out all the pieces that were wrong, trying to find better sources for everything, and then [[WP:DUE|getting the balance right]] for the Lead section. Nobody owns this article; I know I don't. Cheers, &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:10.2pt&quot;&gt;~[[User:Adjwilley|Adjwilley]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:7pt&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Adjwilley|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 18:28, 31 August 2012 (UTC)

Horseshit. Then explain what is wrong with the edit. You already said it is an &quot;overstatement&quot; to say that the three beings are separate, but according to Mormon beliefs. THEY ARE, according to them. Why do you make the case against them if that is what they believe? If that is not exactly what they believe then add a sentence to make it CLEAR. but do Explain? otherwise you're just reverting edits because you think its &quot;trying to nail Mormonism down&quot;. seriously. Sure, its &quot;easier&quot; to just revert the edit rather than correct them. What does Wikipedia need you for then?  WOW. [[User:QvisDevs|QvisDevs]] ([[User talk:QvisDevs|talk]]) 18:35, 31 August 2012 (UTC)
:QvisDevs, please [[WP:CIVIL|remain civil]], focus on the ''issues'' instead of the ''editors'', and [[WP:NPA|absolutely stop making personal attacks]]. [[User:Tedder|tedder]] ([[User talk:Tedder|talk]]) 18:39, 31 August 2012 (UTC)

::Sorry I'm Italian. It's just the way things are, but I seriously find it displeasing when people cop out on religious beliefs, rather than get on an open-system platform and just state their beliefs and LET PEOPLE decide for themselves like a democratic way. [[User:QvisDevs|QvisDevs]] ([[User talk:QvisDevs|talk]]) 18:42, 31 August 2012 (UTC)
:::&lt;small&gt;Non c'e' un problema. Capisco che nelle discussioni gli Italiani sono piu' animati rispetto agli Americani.&lt;/small&gt;
:::I'll point out some of the problems, if you like.
::*''&quot;Regarding [[soteriology]], Mormon beliefs claim that the [[passion of Jesus Christ]]'s [[crucifixion]] was not enough to merit [[redemption]] and [[salvation]] for humankind&quot;.'' This is misleading. Early Mormonism had to define itself against Calvinistic views of humans utter incapacity and complete dependence on grace. In reaction, Mormon preachers emphasized good works and moral obligation (i.e. the gospel of James over the gospel of Paul). There are &quot;grace&quot; passages in the Book of Mormon, just like the Bible, but historically these haven't been emphasized as much as the &quot;works&quot; passages. The Mormon view is that part of &quot;accepting&quot; God's grace is to do your best to do good works. The stuff about Christ's passion not being sufficient is incorrect. &lt;small&gt;(I'm liberally paraphrasing Richard Bushman's ''Mormonism: a very short introduction'' page 76. This is what I mean by a peer-reviewed, published source.)&lt;/small&gt;
::*Calling Mormons polytheistic is an oversimplification. Mormons would claim they're monotheistic. Scholars disagree amongst themselves, and many of the best scholars don't even bother categorizing it, though some have called them monolatrists. (This is partly where I was talking about [[WP:UNDUE|undue]] emphasis for the Lead section.)
::*I already pointed out the problems with saying that Mormons believe in separate Gods. It would be more accurate to simply say that Mormons reject Trinitarianism. (BTW, some scholars have categorized Mormons as believing in a [[Social trinity]], which, I believe, was accepted at some point by some Catholic thinkers.)
::*''&quot;Furthermore, Mormon beliefs cite that souls who enter [[Heaven]] someday become deity-like, immortal and divine in equal footing with the [[Holy Trinity]].&quot;'' The problem with this, again, is overstatement. Some Mormons do believe this, but not all. If you cropped off the &quot;equal in footing with the Holy Trinity&quot; part, you'd have a pretty accurate sentence. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:10.2pt&quot;&gt;~[[User:Adjwilley|Adjwilley]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:7pt&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Adjwilley|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 19:10, 31 August 2012 (UTC)

:::It does not matter what &quot;a&quot; LDS believes, what is important is what the LDS Church teaches. &quot;...three separate beings not united under one [[monotheism|monotheistic deity]]&quot;, what does one monotheistic deity mean? Are we talking abaout one essence or substance? Are we talking about one Godhead? The LDS Church teaches there is one Godhead consisting of Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, which are three distinct persons or beings. The LDS Churches has no teaching or philosophical construct to explain an essence or substance that magically makes them one God. They are God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Spirit; three that make one Godhead.
:::The LDS Church teaches that God the Father has a body of flesh and bone. &quot;...is not made of spiritual substance in his own inherent divine nature.&quot; I have no idea what he is trying to say. The LDS Church teaches that God was always God; that he is Spirit with no beginning and no end. That his Spirit is housed in a body of flesh and bone. There was never a time when God was not God. It is the same with Jesus; there was never a time when Jesus was not a member of the Godhead. Jesus also has a body of flesh and bone. The entire purpose of the resurrection was to unite the body with the Spirit in a glorified, perfected state. It would seem if having a body was not important there would be no need for Jesus to have been resurrected or to make it so that each human being could be resurrected. 
:::&quot;Furthermore, Mormon beliefs cite that souls who enter [[Heaven]] someday become deity-like, immortal and divine in equal footing with the [[Holy Trinity]].&quot; This is not accurate or correct and misses entirely the concept of Exaltation as taught by the LDS Church. Let's first look at some orthodox, Christian teaching on becoming gods, called deification, or theosis:
:::* In the second century, Irenaeus, bishop of Lyons (about 130—200), arguably the most important Christian theologian of his time, said that God &quot;became what we are in order to make us what he is himself.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/0103500.htm ''Adversus haereses'', book 5, preface] - ''Factus est quod sumus nos, uti nos perficeret quod et ipse''.&lt;/ref&gt; Irenaeus further stated as follows, &quot;If the Word became a man, It was so men may become gods.&quot;
:::* At about the same time, St. Clement of Alexandria (about 150—215), wrote: ''&quot;Yea, I say, the Word of God became a man so that you might learn from a man how to become a god.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Clement of Alexandria, Exhortation to the Greeks, 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Clement further stated that &quot;if one knows himself, he will know God, and knowing God will become like God. . . . His is beauty, true beauty, for it is God, and that man becomes a god, since God wills it. So Heraclitus was right when he said, 'Men are gods, and gods are men.'&quot;'' St. Clement of Alexandria further stated that &quot;he who obeys the Lord and follows the prophecy given through him . . . becomes a god while still moving about in the flesh.&quot; Athanasius also observed:''&quot;He became man that men might be made gods.&quot;''
:::* St. Cyril of Alexandria says that we &quot;are called 'temples of God' and indeed 'gods', and so we are.&quot;
:::* St. Gregory of Nazianzus implores us to &quot;become gods for (God's) sake, since (God) became man for our sake.&quot;
:::* St. Basil the Great stated that &quot;becoming a god&quot; is the highest goal of all.
:::* Finally, St. Augustine of Hippo (354—430), arguably the greatest of the early Christian Fathers, said: ''&quot;But he himself that justifies also deifies, for by justifying he makes sons of God. 'For he has given them power to become the sons of God' [John 1:12]. If then we have been made sons of god, we have also been made gods.
:::All of the above writers were not just important theologans in Christian orthodoxy, but all (in due time) became revered as saints as a result of the early Church councils. As noted, three (3) of the above Christian Fathers wrote within a time span of less than one hundred years from the period of the apostles. It is blatantly obvious that orthdox Christian teaching is that man may become gods.
:::The LDS Church teaches what the Bible teches: that man, through Jesus Christ's atonement and sacrifice, might become joint-heirs with Christ. What is a joint-heir? Through Christ Grace we are gifted what he inherits. As Christ prayed, we become one as he and the Father are one, full of grace, righteousness, holiness, and purity. 
:::In being made like Christ, the LDS Church teaches that God will always be our God. We will never become God and we will be able to dwell in his presence.
:::The article is neither accurate or correct. He has taken great leaps of logic while minimizing the teachings of the LDS Church. His objective was to find difference and he has forced a great deal of difference without looking at the actual teachings of the LDS Church. -&lt;sup&gt;[[user:Storm Rider|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;01796F&quot;&gt;Storm&lt;/font&gt;''''']]&lt;/sup&gt;[[User talk:Storm Rider#top|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;1C39BB&quot;&gt;Rider&lt;/font&gt;''''']] 08:49, 1 September 2012 (UTC)

== racial views ==

Why doesn't the article mention the racial views of Mormonism. --[[Special:Contributions/41.151.213.189|41.151.213.189]] ([[User talk:41.151.213.189|talk]]) 14:32, 15 October 2012 (UTC)
:You may want to check out [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blacks_and_Mormonism Black people and Mormonism].  -&lt;sup&gt;[[user:Storm Rider|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;01796F&quot;&gt;Storm&lt;/font&gt;''''']]&lt;/sup&gt;[[User talk:Storm Rider#top|'''''&lt;font color=&quot;1C39BB&quot;&gt;Rider&lt;/font&gt;''''']] 12:23, 16 October 2012 (UTC)

== Gold Plates? ==

What happened to the gold plates??  How could something so fundamental be forgotten about?

baden [[Special:Contributions/41.74.221.96|41.74.221.96]] ([[User talk:41.74.221.96|talk]]) 04:38, 24 October 2012 (UTC)
: There has been some chatter about the plates. See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Search?search=gold+plate&amp;prefix=Talk%3AMormonism%2F&amp;fulltext=Search&amp;fulltext=Search If you have good Sources, you can enter the missing information yourself. You are welcome to do so. Sincerely, [[User:GeorgeLouis|GeorgeLouis]] ([[User talk:GeorgeLouis|talk]]) 05:45, 24 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>0loqupnrs2qyrdiawxa6joejtfnff0k</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
