<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Skepticism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>140652</id>
    <revision>
      <id>470141592</id>
      <parentid>470141152</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-01-07T20:31:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DreamGuy</username>
        <id>134756</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Religious Skepticism */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15678">{{skip to talk}}
{{talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{philosophy|class=C|importance=high|epistemology=yes|metaphysics=yes}}
{{WikiProject Psychology|class=C|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Atheism|class=C|importance=high}}
{{Rational Skepticism|class=C|importance=top}}
}}
{{WP1.0|class=C|category=category|VA=yes}} 
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; width=&quot;290px&quot;
|-
!align=&quot;center&quot;|[[Image:Vista-file-manager.png|50px|Archive]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wikipedia:How to archive a talk page|Archives]]
----
|-
|
# [[Talk:Skepticism/Archive1|2002-February 2010]]
|}&lt;!--Template:Archivebox--&gt;

==Spelling==

Before considering spelling changes -- &quot;s'''K'''eptic&quot; versus &quot;s'''C'''eptic&quot; -- please note the spelling of the title of this article, then review and/or add to the discussion below:

*'''[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Skepticism#Spelling_and_the_manual_of_style Spelling and the manual of style]'''



== Order of sections ==

I'm leaning towards reversing the order, and making it philosophical, religious, then scientific.  In addition to being alphabetical, it has some chronological relevance. Thoughts?[[User:Novangelis|Novangelis]] ([[User talk:Novangelis|talk]]) 16:24, 10 February 2010 (UTC)

:Being alphabetical isn't a good reason to reorder them.  Being chronological would make sense if the article was telling the story of skepticism in a chronological manner (I'm not sure that it is).  Placing the Philosophical section first (of the three) makes it (seem) more important.  Is it?  I think for the average reader arriving at this page, the scientific section is of greater relevance.  I would be more interested in dealing with the morefootnotes box at the top.  &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;[[User:Tayste|Tayste]]&lt;/b&gt; ([[Special:Contributions/Tayste|edits]])&lt;/i&gt; 04:28, 12 February 2010 (UTC)
:::I originally changed the order to reflect importance. The average reader will be coming here after hearing skepticism on television, they will be looking for a modern use of the word. They most certainly not be looking for the philosophy of the skeptikoi, since it is about the most obscure thing on wikipedia. I'm sure the WP:LEAD says something about what order they should go in if you wanna look.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:TheThomas|TheThomas]] ([[User talk:TheThomas|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/TheThomas|contribs]]) 12:30, 19 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Skepsis ==

I think there is a connection to [[Skepsis]], is there a way to confirm this? [[User:Paradoctor|Paradoctor]] ([[User talk:Paradoctor|talk]]) 11:40, 4 March 2010 (UTC)

== Skepticism is = &quot; some degree of doubt regarding claims that are elsewhere taken for granted.[2]&quot; ==

Before posting this I attempted to attain a sense of the validity of the reference, by looking at the University the statement originates from yet after doing so I still feel that the following section is irrelevant and should be removed as it adds connotation.

&quot;that are elsewhere taken for granted&quot; [[User:BoredextraWorkvidid|BoredextraWorkvidid]] ([[User talk:BoredextraWorkvidid|talk]]) 07:19, 22 August 2010 (UTC)

== `Philosophical_skeptic` should redirect to `Philosophical_skepticism` rather than `Skepticism` ==

`Philosophical_skeptic` currently redirects to `Skepticism` (this article) rather than `Philosophical_skepticism` as it should do. --[[Special:Contributions/86.143.62.197|86.143.62.197]] ([[User talk:86.143.62.197|talk]]) 18:20, 28 August 2010 (UTC)

== This article has a &quot;C&quot; rating, but is of Vital importance. ==

Though I would prefer to make small changes, this article needs a lot of extra information added. It is about time to just lay down as much information as you can.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:TheThomas|TheThomas]] ([[User talk:TheThomas|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/TheThomas|contribs]]) 12:44, 19 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Religious Skepticism ==

That whole section is particularly poor. I feel it needs completely rewriting but am holding back from doing it myself due to being fairly inexperienced on wikipedia. Some things to note though:
*&quot;Religious skeptics are weighing in on subjects outside the capabilities of science&quot; seems a very strong declaration to make, and one that many would disagree with. Are religious matters necessarily outside the capabilities of science? Are religious skeptics &quot;weighing in&quot;?
*&quot;Religious skeptics are often very critical of the apologetics of one or many religions&quot;. This may be true of the most prominent skeptics, but we are talking about all religious skeptics. This strikes me as bizarre a line as &quot;Communists are very often Russian&quot; would be.
*&quot;Skeptics of christianity etc.&quot; again smacks of generalisation, and ranges from the obvious (of course skeptics don't accept the virgin birth) to the rare (is doubting the historicity of Jesus really typical of skeptics?). The inclusion of biblical innerancy also seems a tad out of place as that isn't part of the dogma for many christians anyway.
*&quot;Skeptics of islam etc.&quot; has the same problems as the above, as well as what seems to be an altered version of a joke in the third bullet point. [[User:Wikiditm|Wikiditm]] ([[User talk:Wikiditm|talk]]) 17:45, 11 December 2010 (UTC)
Removing referance to book about existance of Jesus since it is generally not accepted see http://www.bib-arch.org/reviews/review-end-of-biblical-studies.asp http://www.tektonics.org/af/avalos01.html http://debunkingchristianity.blogspot.com/2009/07/philip-davies-on-end-of-biblical.html along with the claim as overly contravsial without a full article. [[User:RonaldDuncan|RonaldDuncan]] ([[User talk:RonaldDuncan|talk]]) 12:24, 7 January 2012 (UTC)
:Restored reference to book. Those three sources are about the worst you could choose to demonstrate &quot;not generally accepted&quot; - extremely biased sources that themselves are not generally accepted by scholars and a blogspot page... This book was published by a real publisher and has real support. Your personal dislike of it doesn't allow you to remove it from this article, let alone the general topic it was being used as a source for, which can be sourced to tons of other source as well, as shown by articles on Wikipedia about said topic. Your edit comes off looking more like an attempt to censor a viewpoint that responsible encyclopedia editing. [[User:DreamGuy|DreamGuy]] ([[User talk:DreamGuy|talk]]) 20:31, 7 January 2012 (UTC)

== Agnostiscism needs removing and religious skeptiscism needs a rewrite==
The article makes the statement that most skeptics are agnostic. By definition, I am agnostic, but I am also, by definition, an atheist. I fit more in line with the de facto meaning of atheism rather than agnosticism, as agnostisicism generally implies more openness to religion, and much more openness to supernatural claims/psuedoscience, atheism is considered a stronger position. 

Of course, these are my own personal opinions, and have no factual basis; similar to the statements of skeptics being agnostic. I think the word agnostic needs to be purged from the article; it sounds like someone is trying to identify skeptics with their own beliefs, that is, agnosticism. 

Regarding the &quot;religious skepticism section, I believe this should be re-written in an entirely different direction. 

Regarding the bible, the claims listed are okay, and thinks which I do(and I assume most religious skeptics doubt) but It doesn't reflect on the lack of evidence for a deity, afterlife, soul, heaven, hell, telepathy, etc; things which may or may not be based on the bible, but are central to Christian theology. 

I think if one were to list these things, the article would lose neutrality, and would come off(rightly so) as an attack on religion. 

Regarding Islam, the author of this section(assuming there is only one) does not make the same claims about it is he/she does Christianity, while the two religions are very similar. Instead, they list some minor claims and seem to make an appeal to ridicule. 

They also challenge the claim that Islam is of peace. This sounds very much like loaded language. The author does not challenge Christianities status as a religion of peace, while, when adjusted for power and national wealth/development, are similar.(There aren't many southern baptist suicide bombers because they live in a developed nation and the hierarchy don't have the power to get many recruits willing to die, nor do they want to as they live in a developed nation. They, like everyone else, wants to stay comfortable, and because they live in a comfortable place, aren't as willing to do violence.)

I have never made a large contribution to an article, only minor edits; grammar, small facts, or neutrality rewrites. I would like to try to rewrite large parts of this article, salvaging what should be salvaged. 

Hopefully I'll have a good chunk of afternoon some time in the future. If there's someone else who would like to take a section, or even the whole article, or who can think of something else that perhaps needs to be changed, feel free to post it here. 

Thank you for reading. 
[[User:Gottogog|Gottogog]] ([[User talk:Gottogog|talk]]) 16:15, 21 December 2010 (UTC)

You are adopting an unnecessarily narrow view of 'agnostic' here, which means the general recognition that we don't know, and can be applied to all sorts of claims, particularly metaphysical claims, not just the existence of God. The Pyrrhonian sceptics were agnostic about all claims to knowledge, although the Academic sceptics had a more definitely negative view of the prospect of knowledge. See Benson Mates 'The Skeptic Way' Oxford Unversity Press 1996. If you removed accurate references to agnosticism then this would be an example of intrusive and biased editing. [[User:Evenbalance|Evenbalance]] ([[User talk:Evenbalance|talk]]) 15:41, 18 June 2011 (UTC)

== Uncited example in lead ==

The first paragraph of the lead currently makes an uncited assertion regarding the respective beliefs of skeptics and the public at large in the US regarding [[chiropractic]]. This is probably true, but I am not sure why we need an example at all there. Would anyone object were I simply to remove the sentence? - [[User talk:2over0|2/0]] &lt;small&gt;([[Special:Contributions/2over0|cont.]])&lt;/small&gt; 14:20, 8 January 2011 (UTC)
: [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Skepticism&amp;diff=407128424&amp;oldid=406662565 Done]. - [[User talk:2over0|2/0]] &lt;small&gt;([[Special:Contributions/2over0|cont.]])&lt;/small&gt; 19:52, 15 January 2011 (UTC)

==Please vote - A consensus vote as to whether to consider the journal ''Homeopathy'' an RS for physics, science, or medical conclusions ==
A consensus vote as to whether to consider the journal ''Homeopathy'' an RS for phsyics, science, or medical conclusions is happening here[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Homeopathy#Is_Homeopathy_a_reliable_source_for_physics_conclusions.3F]. [[User:PPdd|PPdd]] ([[User talk:PPdd|talk]]) 02:08, 3 February 2011 (UTC)

Vote '''[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Homeopathy#Is_Homeopathy_a_reliable_source_for_physics_conclusions.3F here]'''. -- [[User:BullRangifer|Brangifer]] ([[User talk:BullRangifer|talk]]) 05:03, 3 February 2011 (UTC)

== Atheism? ==

Why is skepticism listed under an atheistic category? Skepticism is in theory the stance of the open-minded not a case of willingly believing in everything - be it disbelief or belief (believing in atheism is still a belief, just as a belief in a supernatural (or otherwise) Deity), therefore it is not an article to do with atheism. Many atheists may put themselves as skeptics, but many skeptics are not necessarily atheists. Because one may question the existence of UFO's etc, doesnt mean one is not religious.
NOTE: Many atheistic skeptics are also extremely aggressive when their 'faith' is questioned. Does anyone know why this is? [[User:Chris of England|Chris of England]]  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/84.12.125.50|84.12.125.50]] ([[User talk:84.12.125.50|talk]]) 12:19, 20 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Atheism is not a &quot;faith&quot; or a &quot;belief&quot;. Many people are atheists because of their skepticism, which is why skepticism and atheism are linked. -- [[User:Scjessey|Scjessey]] ([[User talk:Scjessey|talk]]) 13:08, 20 September 2011 (UTC)

Nicely said, since often skepticism, atheism, ignorant fervent wishfulness and religious fervor are the same beast of mind regardless of the vocabulary involved. I think global Basic Logic lessons might suffice to wipe out blind faith in endless, pure skepticism without reason, at the intelligence level of slime. When so-called scientists based on absence of information leap to alarming conclusions, regardless of the scientific vocabulary involved, they are still being illogical. Skepticism when expressed open-mindedly as you present it, is evidence of a logical mind, developable through formal education and real world practice. Many vapid naysayers behaving with less developed awareness than toddlers call themselves skeptics in an effort to seem smart. Ignoring vast quantities of relevant data and refusing to think is a form of Appeal to Ignorance and accusing from ignorance is a form of the Strawman Fallacy. 

Among the intelligent and open-minded who may have some skepticism in the healthiest sense of questioning, learning, co-developing and working together with informed awareness, and in good-faith without tangible disappointment, we have valid questions in science-informed and faith-experience communities. Religion, normally interpreted as sophisticated guidance rather than recipes for living, has access to symbols and logic which leads human minds. Ignoring religion yet calling oneself a &quot;scientist&quot; amounts to ignoring heat sources in kitchens while claiming to be a chef. Human experience and human perception are valid information sources worth considering, especially when some repetition is visible in the population. For example, law enforcement agencies may keep maps with reported information marked on the map, eventually showing report patterns. Similarly, scientists could note reports of human experiences, see similar patterns and form conjectures based on observed data. Leadership in mind sciences, including developing science-informed observations and descriptions of faith experiences and reasoning, I think might be provided by Joseph LeDoux and Steven Pinker. I do not think we have language sufficiently developed in our human languages for accurate expression of what seems spiritual, such as the resultant experiences sometimes reported after some people have a mild electric current run across their temporal lobes. Meanwhile, having the ability to lead minds with symbols may be an interesting access to power. 

[[User:JenniferProkhorov|JenniferProkhorov]] ([[User talk:JenniferProkhorov|talk]]) 04:04, 31 December 2011 (UTC)

== &quot;Empiricists see empiricism as a pragmatic compromise between philosophical skepticism and [[nomothetic]] science.&quot;   ==

&quot;Empiricists see empiricism as a pragmatic compromise between philosophical skepticism and [[nomothetic]] science.&quot;

It's not clear to me what this sentence means. It would be great if someone could expand or cite it.

-- [[User:Mad with power|Mad with power]] ([[User talk:Mad with power|talk]]) 04:54, 22 October 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hemc95s0ny6vpbervfpytrxxjxulnx0</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
