<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Religious aspects of marriage</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>26353</id>
    <revision>
      <id>453476092</id>
      <parentid>453476054</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-10-02T04:12:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Graham87</username>
        <id>194203</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>moved [[Religious aspects of marriage/Talk]] to [[Talk:Religious aspects of marriage]] over redirect: revert</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2580">Apparently, [[User:Little guru|Little guru]] was the author of the stuff that was previously on this page, the stuff that I deleted.  It remains to be seen whether Little guru will come to understand the ways of wikipedia, but for now it is difficult to distinguish his or her writings from vandalism.  I apologize for calling them that. Guru, this is an encyclopedia, not a compendium of unreadable rambling verbiage.  I'm sorry if that sounds harsh to you.  I'm not implying that you are incapable of writing in an encyclopedic manner.  Perhaps you were simply unaware of our mission here. [[User:Jimbo Wales|Jimbo Wales]]

This page now has the makings of a good entry. I created a new article on Jewish views of marriage, and linked from this one to the new entry.  As for unreadable random verbiage, I'm all for that, as long as it is on their own private website. Its amazing to me that people don't understand what the concept of an &quot;Encyclopaedia is.  [[User:RK|RK]]

RK, I love your page, as always your stuff is awesome.  I think I like the idea of having this page as a page with links to pages for the religious views of various faiths.  My original concept was that we'd put it all on one page, which is why I wrote the &quot;sample&quot; stuff about Christian views.  I'm so far from an expert, though, that I think my stuff should go away as soon as someone writes a real page on Christian views. --[[User:Jimbo Wales|Jimbo Wales]]

==Confucian==
Would [[Confucianism]]'s view on marriage goes on this page? Taoism's? Where do we fit China, since its culture/relgion(s) doesn't entirely fit into the neat compartments of the Western world? ~ [[User:Dpr|Dpr]] 10:07, 14 Jun 2005 (UTC)

== ' during a &quot;Nuptial Mass&quot; ' ==

I removed this statement because the Catholic Sacrament of Marriage is not the same as a Nuptial Mass. A Nuptial Mass is not the sacrament of marriage, it is the sacrament of the eucharist celebrated at the same time as the sacrament of marriage. While it is considered a good thing to have, it is not essential for the marriage to take place. In particular, if a Catholic and non-Catholic are approved by the catholic church to marry, then the Catholic sacrament of Marriage will be celebrated, but a nuptial mass cannot take place -- that is only permitted when both spouses are Catholic. The wording that was here seemed to imply that a catholic marriage and a nuptial mass were one and the same, which they are not! -- Samuel Katinsky
::Thank you so much! Can you help further here  [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass_%28liturgy%29] (cf. 5.1) please?!</text>
      <sha1>0dkio087yl056vbt5dmolpeof8wfh1u</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
