<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Day of the Vow</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>20241404</id>
    <revision>
      <id>443774432</id>
      <parentid>437573083</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-08-08T23:50:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HtonlBot</username>
        <id>14919136</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Replacing {{WikiProject Africa|South Africa=yes}} with {{WikiProject South Africa}}</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4092">{{WikiProject South Africa |class=C |importance=High }}

{{archivetop}}
==Merger Proposal==

'''Result was &quot;no merge.&quot;'''

So, there is a page for the same holiday, but by two different names: [[Day of the Vow]] (pre-1994), and [[Day of Reconciliation]] (post-1994). This seems a bit silly. If I were to describe the history behind the Day of Reconciliation, I feel I'd have to go through the history behind the Day of the Vow. Personally, I feel we should use Day of Reconciliation as the title because it's the current name. However, the relevant content is on Day of the Vow, and should be kept. Day of the Vow could then be a redirect to this content on the other page. (If that makes sense...?) [[User:Warrickball|Warrickball]] ([[User talk:Warrickball|talk]]) 20:25, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

:I think they should stay 2 articles - it's like winter solstice and Christmas ([[Christmas#Winter festivals|pagan to Christian]]): the same date, declared by the new powers that be, for very different celebrations (apartheid to reconciliation‎). -- [[User:Jeandré du Toit|Jeandré]], 2009-01-01[[User talk:Jeandré du Toit|t]]16:19z
::There may be arguments for both options. However, there is a difference between the two, and I suggest that they remain separate. Take into account that the 'Day of the Vow' centers around the vow or covenant. The recent attachment to it, the 'Day of Reconciliation', is in my view not an aspect of the vow. Most who celebrate the 'Day of Reconciliation' will be indifferent to the vow. Futhermore one is a holiday, and the other is a sabbath independent of a holiday that may facilitate it. Nor is the vow an apartheid institution as suggested above. [[User:JMK|JMK]] ([[User talk:JMK|talk]]) 06:53, 19 June 2009 (UTC)
:::Both may fall on they same day, but they exist for different reasons and I suggest they stay separate articles. [[Day of Reconciliation]] should however be expanded as I am sure there is a lot more information that should be there, such as the fact that celebrations are normally held at [[Freedom Park (South Africa)]]. --[[User:NJR ZA|NJR_ZA]] ([[User talk:NJR ZA|talk]]) 07:57, 19 June 2009 (UTC)
::::I believe that they should remain separate because the Day of the Vow/Covenant (Dingane's Day) states the reason for the holiday in its name and the Afrikaner families are faithful to teach the meaning of the day to their children - like they said they would in the vow - but 'The [alleged] Day of Reconciliation' was what many Afrikaners felt was just an attempt to water-down the history of South Africa by changing the name done by the newly elected government. Of course the people in power wouldn't want a national holiday commemorating their own people's defeat by the hands of the Afrikaners and their God. [[User:Invmog|Invmog]] ([[User talk:Invmog|talk]]) 02:16, 28 June 2009 (UTC)
Oppose: Merging them would make as much sense as merging [[Yule]] and [[Christmas]]. [[User:Seb az86556|Seb az86556]] ([[User talk:Seb az86556|talk]]) 13:20, 30 August 2009 (UTC)
:'''Oppose''', it is two different events that just happen to occur on the same date. --[[User:NJR ZA|NJR_ZA]] ([[User talk:NJR ZA|talk]]) 13:49, 30 August 2009 (UTC)

::This discussion has been going on since 2008 with the majority of the few comments against the merger. I'm now closing this and remove the tags. [[User:Seb az86556|Choyoołʼįįhí:Seb az86556]] 17:38, 8 September 2009 (UTC)
{{archivebottom}}

== Original wording of the Vow is not included ==

Could we perhaps include the original 90-100% Dutch version of the vow (the version which it was first written in and the version which appears in the picture.) We could place it under the Afrikaans and English versions, or wherever y'all see fit. I think it would add greatly to have the original wording (and Dutch and Afrikaners can easily comprehend the text.) If no one objects I'll likely try and add it after a week or so, in order to give time for anyone to reply if they'd like to discuss this further. [[User:Invmog|Invmog]] ([[User talk:Invmog|talk]]) 17:36, 29 September 2009 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>degrvh6i8pqowsxmmna9ovb5vtitmas</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
