<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Pseudoscience</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>23768</id>
    <revision>
      <id>522112263</id>
      <parentid>522096195</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-09T03:02:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Archiving 2 threads (older than 60d) to [[Talk:Pseudoscience/Archive 15]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15815">{{Skip to talk}}
{{talk header}}
{{controversial}}
{{not a forum}} 
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{Rational Skepticism|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Pseudoscience|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Sociology|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Alternative medicine|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Alternative Views|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{philosophy|importance=mid|class=B|logic=yes|science=yes}}
{{WikiProject Science}}
}}
{| class=&quot;messagebox standard-talk&quot;
|-
|{{anchor|Notice}}'''Arbitration Ruling on the Treatment of [[Pseudoscience]]'''
In December of 2006 the [[Wikipedia:Requests for arbitration|Arbitration Committee]] created guidelines for how to present pseudoscientific topics in [[Wikipedia:Requests for arbitration/Pseudoscience]].
* '''[[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Pseudoscience#Neutral_point_of_view_as_applied_to_science|Neutral point of view as applied to science]]:''' [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view]], a fundamental policy, requires fair representation of significant alternatives to scientific orthodoxy. Significant alternatives, in this case, refers to legitimate scientific disagreement, as opposed to [[pseudoscience]].
* '''[[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Pseudoscience#Serious_encyclopedias|Serious encyclopedias]]:''' Serious and respected encyclopedias and reference works are generally expected to provide overviews of scientific topics that are in line with respected scientific thought. Wikipedia aspires to be such a respected work.
|-

| '''The four groupings found at [[Wikipedia:Fringe theories#Pseudoscience]]'''
* '''[[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Pseudoscience#Obvious_pseudoscience|Obvious pseudoscience]]:''' Theories which, while purporting to be scientific, are obviously bogus, such as [[Time Cube]], may be so labeled and categorized as such without more.
* '''[[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Pseudoscience#Generally_considered_pseudoscience|Generally considered pseudoscience]]:'''  Theories which have a following, such as [[astrology]], but which are generally considered pseudoscience by the scientific community may properly contain that information and may be categorized as pseudoscience.
* '''[[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Pseudoscience#Questionable_science|Questionable science]]:''' Theories which have a substantial following, such as [[psychoanalysis]], but which some critics allege to be pseudoscience, may contain information to that effect, but generally should not be so characterized.
* '''[[Wikipedia:Requests_for_arbitration/Pseudoscience#Alternative_theoretical_formulations|Alternative theoretical formulations]]''':  Alternative theoretical formulations which have a following within the scientific community are not pseudoscience, but part of the scientific process.
|-

|}
{| class=&quot;messagebox standard-talk&quot;
|-
|{{anchor|Please read before starting}}'''Please read before starting'''
First of all, welcome to Wikipedia's Pseudoscience article. This article  represents the work of many contributors and much negotiation to find consensus for an accurate and complete representation of the topic. 

[[Wikipedia:Welcome, newcomers|Newcomers]] to Wikipedia and this article may find that it's easy to commit a ''[[faux pas]]''. That's OK — everybody does it! You'll find a list of a few common ones you might try to avoid [[Wikipedia:Avoiding_common_mistakes|here]].

A common objection made often by new arrivals is that the article presents the fields it lists as &quot;pseudoscience&quot; in an unsympathetic light or violates Wikipedia's '''Neutral Point of View''' policy ([[WP:NPOV]]). The sections of the [[WP:NPOV]] that apply directly to this article are: 
*'''[[Wikipedia:Neutral_point_of_view/FAQ#Pseudoscience|NPOV: Pseudoscience]]'''
*'''[[Wikipedia:Neutral_point_of_view#Undue_weight|NPOV: Undue weight]]'''
*'''[[Wikipedia:Neutral_point_of_view/FAQ#Making_necessary_assumptions|NPOV: Making necessary assumptions]]'''
*'''[[Wikipedia:Neutral_point_of_view/FAQ#Giving_.22equal_validity.22|NPOV: Giving &quot;equal validity&quot;]].'''
The contributors to the article continually strive to adhere to these to the letter. Also, splitting the article into sub-articles is governed by the [[Wikipedia:POV fork|Content forking]] guidelines.

These policies have guided the shape and content of the article, and new arrivals are strongly encouraged to become familiar with them prior to raising objections on this page or adding content to the article. Other important policies guiding the article's content are No Original Research ([[WP:NOR]]) and Cite Your Sources ([[WP:CITE]]).

Tempers can and have flared here. All contributors are asked to please respect Wikipedia's policy No Personal Attacks ([[WP:NPA]]) and to abide by consensus ([[WP:CON]]).
|-
|'''Notes to editors:'''
#This article uses scientific terminology, and as such, the use of the word 'theory' to refer to anything outside of a recognised scientific theory is ambiguous. Please use words such as 'concept', 'notion', 'idea', 'assertion'; see [[Wikipedia:Words to avoid#Theory]].
#Please use [[Help:Edit summary|edit summaries]].
|}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 250K
|counter = 15
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:Pseudoscience/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{archive box |bot=MiszaBot I |age=2 |units=months |index=/Archive index |search=yes | 
# [[/Archive 1|Antiquity &amp;ndash; Jan 2003]]
# [[/Archive 2|Jan 2003 &amp;ndash; Jan 2006]]
# [[/Archive 3|Jan 2006 &amp;ndash; Apr 2006]]
# [[/Archive 4|Apr 2006 &amp;ndash; May 2006]]
# [[/Archive 5|May 2006 &amp;ndash; June 2006]]
# [[/Archive 6|July 2006 &amp;ndash; Sept. 2006]]
# [[/Archive 7|Sept. 2006 &amp;ndash; Oct. 2006]]
# [[/Archive 8|October 2006]]
# [[/Archive 9|November 2006]]
# [[/Archive 10|November 2006 — Dec 2007]]
# [[/Archive 11|March 2008 – April 2010]]
# [[/Archive 12|March 2010 – December 2010]]
# [[/Archive 13|December 2010 – April 2011]]
# [[/Archive 14|April 2011 – June 2011]]
# [[/Archive 15|May 2011 – ]]
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; 
|leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes |template= 
}}

== Broken Link ==

The first external link: &quot;Checklist for identifying dubious technical processes and products – Rainer Bunge, PhD&quot; should link to a PDF and instead returns a 404. [[User:Brauden|Brauden]] ([[User talk:Brauden|talk]]) 21:17, 5 September 2012 (UTC)

== Too Political ==

I know this is a contentious topic, but there is a lot of overly emotive language on this page. In particular the [[Pseudoscience:Political implications | Political implications]] section is full of non-arguments, i.e. just someones opinion and unrelated broken links. - [[User:Lucaswilkins|Lucaswilkins]] ([[User talk:Lucaswilkins|talk]]) 13:26, 8 September 2012 (UTC)
:I fixed the broken link. -- [[User:Scjessey|Scjessey]] ([[User talk:Scjessey|talk]]) 14:24, 8 September 2012 (UTC)
== Edits to pseudoscience concepts, ==

Re this edit where I added;
&quot;and drinking water to prevent dyhydration[39][40][41]. Examples of a pseudoscience changing to being concidered scientific include surgens washing their hands before surgery[42][43] and the effects of St_John's_wort[44].&quot;

This may seem at first glimpse a little bit silly, but I feel this artical is biased and this is an attempt to nudge it back in the direction of neutrality.
Wikipeadia policy of needing citations for everything, even if a subject has no assesable referance, also struggles to deal with this issue; That something can be true, but it still falls into the pseudoscience catagory due to lack of referance material.
The drinking water to prevent dyhydration is an extreame example, but it does fit the pseudoscience catagory.
Examples of a pseudoscience changing to be proven science should also be included, along with examples of proven science reverting to pseudoscience.
These examples would help define the line where something is either proven science or pseudoscience.

Can whoever reverted this edit please explain why they did so.

[[User:Laughton.andrew|Laughton.andrew]] ([[User talk:Laughton.andrew|talk]]) 23:03, 18 October 2012 (UTC)
:When you post a new section to a talk page, you position it at the bottom of the page, which is the reason I have moved your contribution to here.

:I must add that your idea of pseudoscience changing to science is puzzling. How could something that never existed be a pseudoscience? Like docs not washing their hands! [[User:Moriori|Moriori]] ([[User talk:Moriori|talk]]) 23:55, 18 October 2012 (UTC)

::It can and has been a pseudoscience while a minority noticed the effects of washing hands, based on statistics, but others choose not to believe the evidence, labelling the concept as pseudo-science.
::What exactly are you claiming does not exist ?

::::That nurses/doctors did not wash their hands was due to ignorance, not a pseudoscience. After Semmelweis showed hand-washing could drastically reduce the number of women dying after childbirth, and Lister made surgeons wear gloves and wash their hands, the practice became widespread because it was based on scientifically observed new knowledge which overcame the ignorance. There was no pseudoscience that suddenly became science. [[User:Moriori|Moriori]] ([[User talk:Moriori|talk]]) 00:43, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

::::::For approx 20 years after Semmelweis showed that washing hands reduced fatalitys, it was still considered pseudo-science and many people died as a result.  It is a very good example of pseudoscience becoming science, even if it was only pseudoscience for 20 years. [[User:Laughton.andrew|Laughton.andrew]] ([[User talk:Laughton.andrew|talk]]) 11:49, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

:::::::Wrong. The science began even before the day they first started washing hands. They didn't do it because they wanted to look nice, but because they thought cleanliness was in the best interest of patients, and gradually the scientific method using observation and examination built up a reliable databank of knowledge. The science was there at the very start of the 20 years you mention. It was science, using scientific method. Ignorant people questioning the science did not change it from science to pseudoscience.. [[User:Moriori|Moriori]] ([[User talk:Moriori|talk]]) 00:02, 9 November 2012 (UTC)

::[[Higgs_mechanism]] is pseudoscience until this theory is either proved or disproved. Because it has not been proven does not mean that it is not true, and it does not mean that it does not exist. [[User:Laughton.andrew|Laughton.andrew]] ([[User talk:Laughton.andrew|talk]]) 12:44, 24 October 2012 (UTC)

::You are incorrect. I suggest you carefully read this article about what pseudoscience is. A scientific hypothesis is not pseudoscience; on the contrary it is a normal part of science. [[User:IRWolfie-|IRWolfie-]] ([[User talk:IRWolfie-|talk]]) 12:56, 24 October 2012 (UTC)

::You are partly right, the higgs partical is a grey area and a poor example. It does adhere to a valid scientific method, but also lacks supporting evidence, for the moment. [[User:Laughton.andrew|Laughton.andrew]] ([[User talk:Laughton.andrew|talk]]) 11:49, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

:::I looked at the sources in [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Pseudoscience&amp;diff=518392986&amp;oldid=515315612 Laughton's edit]. They don't mention pseudoscience by name, and they don't seem to describe anything that fits the definition of pseudoscience. --[[User:Enric Naval|Enric Naval]] ([[User talk:Enric Naval|talk]]) 16:20, 24 October 2012 (UTC)
::::Yes I had noticed the OR as well, [[User:IRWolfie-|IRWolfie-]] ([[User talk:IRWolfie-|talk]]) 09:32, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

::::There are a few referances, I will deal with them one by one.
Drinking water to prevent dyhydration.  The reason this claim was not allowed was because it has not been scientifically proven.  The first paragraph defines pseudoscience as, amoungst other things, lacking supporting evidence.  Perhaps someone can enlighten me about the difference.
Surgens washing hands to reduce fatalitys. This lacked plausibility for about 20 years.
[[St_John's_wort]]. The tests to prove or disprove the effects were done to provide supporting scientific evidance either way. Before these tests were done the effects would of fitted the pseudoscince definition in the lack of scientific data definition.

In order to provide examples where pseduoscience has become science, it is by definition necessary to use examples that are no longer referred to as pseduoscience. If they were still regarded as pseduoscience they would not be suitable examples. Can you please explain to me why you would expect to find proven science to be refered to as pseduoscience ?  
[[User:Laughton.andrew|Laughton.andrew]] ([[User talk:Laughton.andrew|talk]]) 11:49, 8 November 2012 (UTC)


::Perhaps unhelpfully, some philosophers have used &quot;pseduoscience&quot; as catch-all jargon for ''not science,'' but in general, its limited to unwarranted pretensions... which raises the related, but separate, issue of an anachronistic portrayal by appeal to [[bivalence]].—[[User talk:Machine Elf 1735|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#00FADE 0.05em 0.05em 0.07em;white-space: nowrap;font-family: Fraktur, Mathematica6, Georgia, sans-serif&quot;&gt;Machine Elf &lt;sup style=&quot;font-size:75%;font-family: Georgia, sans-serif&quot;&gt;1735&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 01:59, 25 October 2012 (UTC)

::::It took me a little while to decipher this, but yes.
The Pseduoscience definition does not mean that something is wrong, just that it has not been proven one way or another.  In the medical field this could simply mean that it is too expensive to prove.[[User:Laughton.andrew|Laughton.andrew]] ([[User talk:Laughton.andrew|talk]]) 12:10, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
:You should read the definition again. Because this is absolutely not what pseudoscience means.--[[User:McSly|McSly]] ([[User talk:McSly|talk]]) 14:01, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
::There is stuff that remains unproven, like [[String theory]], but is not pseudoscience. [[higgs boson]] remained unproven for a long time but it was never considered pseudoscience. I agree with McSly that you need to re-read the definition of pseudoscience. --[[User:Enric Naval|Enric Naval]] ([[User talk:Enric Naval|talk]]) 14:24, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

== How do we know pseudoscience has become science? ==

This brings up an interesting question: how does one note that something traditionally referred to as pseudoscience has joined the mainstream? What if someone writes about the subject in a reputable journal without calling it pseudoscience after someone else calls it pseudoscience? Would that do it?

I note that recently:
:The Swiss government’s recent report on homeopathic medicine affirms that homeopathic treatment is both effective and cost-effective. Homeopathic treatment will be reimbursed by Switzerland’s national health insurance program. The report represents the most comprehensive evaluation of homeopathic medicine ever written by a government. Based on research the Swiss report affirms that homeopathy seems to induce regulatory effects and specific changes in cells or living organisms. The report also reported that 20 of 22 systematic reviews of clinical research testing homeopathic medicines detected at least a trend in favor of homeopathy. 
From: “The Swiss Government’s Remarkable report on Homeopathy,”by Dana Ullman, 2/15/2012, [http://huffingtonpost.com/dana-ullman/homeopathic-medicine-_b_1258607.html]

I expect a government does not qualify as &quot;reputable&quot; around here. Still, understanding that the most avid detractors of a concept will probably go to their graves refusing to accept such changes in status, what is the &quot;trigger&quot; for acceptability of a concept? [[User:Tom Butler|Tom Butler]] ([[User talk:Tom Butler|talk]]) 00:56, 9 November 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1x8skvu81gtlw9nc80z6c1lknly1pum</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
