<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Yahweh</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>22637346</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521617221</id>
      <parentid>521472235</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-06T03:50:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Archiving 2 threads (older than 30d) to [[Talk:Yahweh/Archive 6]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12946">{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{Talkarchive}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 6
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Yahweh/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Ancient Near East|class=B|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=top|jehovah's-witnesses=yes|jehovah's-witnesses-importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=High|Interfaith=yes|InterfaithImp=}}
{{WikiProject Jewish history|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Israel|class=B|importance=mid}}
}}
{{Copied|from=Yahweh|from_oldid=410606936|to=Documentary hypothesis|diff=http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Documentary_hypothesis&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=410862054&amp;oldid=410848423
}}
{{Archive box|search=yes|bot=MiszaBot I|age=1|units=months|
* [[Talk:Yahweh/Archive 1|Archive 1]] &lt;small&gt;(Oct 2001–March 2007)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Yahweh/Archive 2|Archive 2]] &lt;small&gt;(Feb 2007–Jan 2009)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Yahweh/Archive 3|Archive 3]] &lt;small&gt;(Dec 2008–Dec 2009)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Yahweh/Archive 4|Archive 4]] &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Yahweh/Archive 5|Archive 5]] &lt;small&gt;(2011)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Yahweh/Archive 6|Archive 6]] &lt;small&gt;(Mar 2012–)&lt;/small&gt;
}}
{{Audio requested}}
__TOC__

== Wikipedia:Manual of Style (lead section) ==

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOS:BOLDTITLE#Format_of_the_first_sentence

The lead section (also known as the introduction, lead, or lede[1]) of a Wikipedia article is the section before the table of contents and the first heading. The lead serves both as an introduction to the article and as a summary of its most important aspects.

The lead should be able to stand alone as a concise overview of the article. '''It should define the topic, establish context, explain why the subject is interesting or notable, and summarize the most important points—''' ''including any prominent controversies''. The emphasis given to material in the lead should roughly reflect its importance to the topic, ''according to reliable, published sources, and the notability of the article's subject should usually be established in the first few sentences.

While consideration should be given to creating interest in reading more of the article, ''the lead nonetheless should not &quot;tease&quot; the reader by hinting at—but not explaining—important facts that will appear later in the article.'' The lead should contain no more than four paragraphs,''' must be carefully sourced as appropriate''', and should be written in a clear, accessible style with a neutral point of view to invite a reading of the full article.'''

== yet more underhanded attempts to change &quot;god&quot; to &quot;God&quot; ==

I see that someone has again altered the formulation ''the god of Israel'' in the lede to ''&quot;the God of Israel&quot;'', this time in quotes and with a link.  This has obviously been done (in an unnatural way that distorts the text) in an effort to avoid the original formulation ''the god of Israel'', a formulation which I previously showed with numerous examples to conform to the standard format in articles about gods of other religions.  This implied view that Christianity is different from and superior to other religions DOES NOT belong in an encyclopedia.  I showed conclusively, with direct reference to Wikipedia guidelines, that there can be no &quot;informal agreement&quot; that Christianity get special treatment and have different rules applied than other religions in Wikipedia articles.  I consider this repeated changing of ''god'' to ''God'' to be part of a rather underhanded campaign by Christian believers to inject their theological rules and agenda into what is supposed to be a neutral, encyclopedic article, and I call upon other Wikipedia authors to be vigilant in this matter.  One additional piece of evidence I offer to prove that the repeated changes are not neutral or constructive in purpose: the ''&quot;God of Israel&quot;'' link that is obviously being used, in part, to justify the change in formulation does not, in fact, even link to a ''&quot;God of Israel&quot;'' page; it links to the [[National god]] page, which mentions many other gods besides Yahweh/Jehovah.

Here is a link to the archived discussion, which includes links to the pertinent Wikipedia guidelines:  https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Yahweh/Archive_6#Why_is_.22god.22_rendered_as_.22God.22_in_the_lede.3F

Is Wikipedia going to remain a scientific compendium of human knowledge, or is it to quietly become yet another tool for covert religious proselytization?  Let's step up, Wikipedians, to ensure that this grand project remain neutral and encyclopedic in its aims and its tone, giving no special preference to any language, ethnicity, nationality or religion, but paying heed only to fact and reason!   [[User:Heavenlyblue|Heavenlyblue]] ([[User talk:Heavenlyblue|talk]]) 02:53, 2 September 2012 (UTC)
:I wasn't aware that the Israelites were Christians, or that [[Bahá'í Faith]], [[Hinduism]], [[Islam]], [[Judaism]], [[Tengrism]], or [[Zoroastrianism]] were really Christian (all those articles use &quot;God,&quot; capital G).  Hell, even [[Wicca]] capitalizes God, they just put [[Horned God|&quot;horned&quot; in front]].  God with a capital G is used to refer to the transcendent deity of multiple religions throughout this encyclopedia.
:The discussion you bring up does not show you [[WP:IDHT|&quot;I didn't hear that&quot;]] and a [[WP:TE|refusal to accept consensus when it doesn't help you grind your axe]].  Those problems, combined with you singling out Christianity as if there's some Church conspiracy controlling this site are pretty good evidence that '''you''' are the one with the bias here.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 03:05, 2 September 2012 (UTC)

:::First of all, Ian, I suggest that you carefully read the entire discussion, including the archived section!  {https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Yahweh/Archive_6#Why_is_.22god.22_rendered_as_.22God.22_in_the_lede.3F)  It doesn't seem that you have.  Secondly, there can be no valid &quot;consensus&quot; that violates the basic neutrality policies of Wikipedia.  (Again, see the discussion!)  Thirdly, your ad hominem attacks aside, I have very clearly demonstrated that the issue here is that Yahweh/Jehovah is getting ''special treatment'', and that this is a direct violation of Wikipedia policy.  In other words, I am trying to ''remedy'' inappropriate bias.  This is an encyclopedia, and not a work of theology.  How people conceive of their own deities, and what they write in their own books of theology, has no bearing whatsoever on this discussion.  Articles must be neutral and follow guidelines, with no special treatment given to one's own belief system.  Equal treatment for all is not bias, Ian, it is the solution to bias, and it is mandated by Wikipedia policy - in fact, it lies at the heart of it!    [[User:Heavenlyblue|Heavenlyblue]] ([[User talk:Heavenlyblue|talk]]) 00:03, 26 September 2012 (UTC)

::Ian, surely there's a difference between the god of Israel and the God of Israel? Yahweh was the god of Israel in the sense that Khemosh was the god of Moab and Asshur was the god of Assyria: these were the national gods, charged with looking after the various kingdoms to which they were attached. God, on the other hand (the one with a capital letter), is a pretty recent concept arising from (ultimately) Greek philosophy, which came up with the idea that there could only be one, single, ultimate Being. By the 2nd century AD the Christians had decided that this Being was their God; Jews then adopted the concept, and much later so did Muslims. That is God with a capital. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 11:38, 23 September 2012 (UTC)

::: Regardless of his approach, i think PiCo is right. God should only be used with a capital G when it is being used as a proper noun or the name of a specific deity. In the phrase &quot;the god of Israel&quot; god is not being used as a name, it is being used as a common noun (just as PiCo demonstrates). The capitalization of God when used as a general noun referring to a monotheistic deity is a convention that is designed to show respect, but in an encyclopedia those conventions are out of place. There are clear wikipedia guidelines on this. Now, if God is the subject of a sentence and that noun is referring to the god of Israel or Christianity (or any other monotheistic deity) then it is appropriate to use capital G God. PiCo, the development of the use of capital G God is contentious and there is hardly a concensus. Many scholars (including secular and liberal Christian scholars) would disagree with you vehemently, but it is irrelevant. Wikipedia should reflect current usage of terms. [[User:ReformedArsenal|ReformedArsenal]] ([[User talk:ReformedArsenal|talk]]) 12:57, 23 September 2012 (UTC)
::::Those reasons, different from the OP's baseless accusations resulting from his own biases, are acceptable. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 14:14, 23 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::On the contrary, Ian, my arguments have a very solid basis, in fact and in Wikipedia policy.  And a simple look through the article history will show you that there have, indeed, been multiple attempts to violate that policy by inappropriately reverting &quot;small g&quot; to &quot;capital G&quot; forms, even when doing so contorted the text.  For whatever personal reasons of your own, you may not like what I'm saying, but in terms of the rules of encyclopedic writing, you are on the wrong side of this argument.    [[User:Heavenlyblue|Heavenlyblue]] ([[User talk:Heavenlyblue|talk]]) 00:20, 26 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::It would be useful if we could find a source that defines Yahweh - any major dictionary of Judaism or religion should do. That would also settle the /g/ or /G/ argument - just do what the source does. 
:::::::The most relevant policy guideline is this one: ''&quot;Honorifics for deities, including proper nouns and titles, start with a capital letter (God, Allah, the Lord, the Supreme Being, the Great Spirit, the Horned One, Bhagavan)... Common nouns for deities and religious figures are not capitalized (many gods; the god Woden).&quot;'' So &quot;Yahweh&quot; gets a capital (being the equivalent of God, Allah, etc), but &quot;the god of Israel&quot; is a common noun, equivalent to &quot;the god Yahweh&quot;, and so no capital. At least that's my reading.[[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 04:00, 8 October 2012 (UTC)
:::::I changed it to small-g god and removed quote marks.[[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 06:46, 24 September 2012 (UTC)

== unambiguous phonemic pronuciation using the IPA ==

The beginning of the article renders the pronuciation of Yahweh to suffix with &quot;-ay&quot; (ie according to IPA). However, no credible source exists for this pronuciation. It is well-known throughout all Jewish communities that the name ends in an &quot;-ah&quot; (a: according to the IPA) pronunciation, as I myself use it. This was the original intended pronunciation of the suffix &quot;-eh&quot; and &quot;-ay&quot; has been an uknowledgeable accidental from the Christian community, and allowed by the Jewish communities to continue in order to keep the pronunciation among Jews only.

When Middle Eastern words are written with English letters, and they end in “-eh,” the ending sound is the “-ah” sound. Those words can be spelled “-eh” or “-ah.” 

almeh  http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/almeh?s=t 
gallabieh  http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/galabieh?s=ts 
kaffiyeh  http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/kaffiyeh?s=t 
mikveh
 http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/mikveh?s=t 
tabbouleh  http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/tabbouleh?s=t 
zaptieh  http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/zaptieh?s=t 


Yahweh http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Yahweh?s=t

The name of God is a Middle Eastern word. How do you say this word?  

Recommendation: add or use /ʹja:hu:a:/ as the primary pronunciation

&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:YAHUWnathan|YAHUWnathan]] ([[User talk:YAHUWnathan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/YAHUWnathan|contribs]]) 05:55, 6 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Please see [[WP:No original research]]. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 14:11, 6 October 2012 (UTC)

== Opening sentence ==

The opening sentence of an article should give a definition of the subject of the article. The article on Yahweh should define Yahweh: he was a god. More precisely, the god of the Iron Age kingdoms of Israel and Judah. What Yahweh is ''not'', is a word. We have a separate article, [[YHWH]], for discussion of the word. This article should simply say that Yahweh is the god of Israel, as described in the books of the Old Testament. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 05:48, 5 November 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>i64874u5faesv98oqk3h3fwfom1jycs</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
