<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Rabbinic literature</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1867387</id>
    <revision>
      <id>366129707</id>
      <parentid>340119995</parentid>
      <timestamp>2010-06-05T03:08:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Twp</username>
        <id>622902</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added photo request per [[Wikipedia:Requested pictures/Society]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="4187">{{WikiProject Religious texts|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Judaism | class= B | importance= high }}

{{reqphoto|religious subjects}}

In the List?

* [[Tanya]]
* [[Tanya Rabbati]]
: --[[User:Sheynhertz-Unbayg|Sheynhertz]][[User talk:Sheynhertz-Unbayg|&lt;sub&gt;&lt;font lang=yi size=2px color=mediumaquamarine&gt;געשׁ״ך&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;]] 14:57, 21 October 2005 (UTC)

== Redefining the scope of the article ==

I suggest that this article be limited to &quot;Rabbinic literature&quot; in the classic sense: ספרות חז&quot;ל. As in the template.

Other periods and genres would find their places in articles on the [[Geonim]], [[Rishonim]], [[Aharonim]], [[Mefarshim]], etc. [[User:Dovi|Dovi]] 04:36, 12 June 2007 (UTC)

::I concur. [[User:Hanina|חנינא]] ([[User talk:Hanina|talk]]) 04:31, 1 April 2008 (UTC)

== Suggestion ==

Hi,

I'd like to make a suggestion after browsing through some of the pages within this section - they all seem to rely strongly on a knowledge of the Old Testament and Hebrew prases particular to Judaïsm to make heads or tails out of what is being said... Would it be possible when editing pages to try and be mindful of people not yet familiar with the subject matter, by providing a (simplified) explanation of what a new word being introduced means? For example, from [[Esther Rabbah]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;'''Esther Rabbah''' ([[Hebrew]]: '''אסתר רבה''') is the [[midrash]] to the [[Book of Esther]] in the current Midrash editions. From its plan and scope it is apparently an incomplete collection from the rich [[haggadic]] material furnished by the comments on the scroll of Esther, which has been read since early times at the public service on [[Purim]].&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Personally, I don't think that the average person looking for information on Wikipedia will know what either a midrash, haggadic or Purim are. At least, I don't. As a suggestion, I've rewritten this to:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In Judaïsm the books that make up the Tanakh, or Jewish bible, are interpreted in four different ways. '''Esther Rabbah''' ([[Hebrew]]: '''אסתר רבה''') is one such interpretation of the Book of Esther - it is the [[midrash]] to this book. From its plan and scope it is appears to be an incomplete collection from the rich [[haggadic]] material furnished by the comments on the scroll of Esther, which has been read since early times at the public service on the Jewish celebration of [[Purim]].&lt;/blockquote&gt;

However, I feel highly uncomfortable making such edits, knowing that I don't have any expertise on Judaïsm and could be introducing pretty big mistakes without realizing it. Therefor, I leave it at this edit and this suggestion, hoping someone within the Rabbinic Literature project will pick this up.

Regards,
Anonymous / [[Special:Contributions/82.156.55.208|82.156.55.208]] ([[User talk:82.156.55.208|talk]]) 23:18, 7 September 2008 (UTC)

It's a good effort and a good ideal -- but I'm afraid it's problematic. This article seems largely unmodified from the original Jewish Encyclopedia article of 1904, which was a technical encyclopedia of the old school. I'm sure it could benefit from being made more readable, and for incorporating a century worth of scholarship.

I undid your actual edits, however. As used in the lede of this entry, Midrash means rabbinic homiletical commentary. &quot;current Midrash editions&quot; means that this particular work, Esther Rabbah, became the mainstream received commentary at some point, making it parallel to the other volumes in the Midrash Rabbah collection. (The article goes into greater details about when.) 

[[User:Yudel|Yudel]] ([[User talk:Yudel|talk]]) 05:36, 8 September 2008 (UTC)

:Hi Yudel, and thanks for the feedback - so it is as I feared, with regards to introducing mistakes. I do wonder though, should it not be assumed that if something is considered 'the midrash' for a particular book, that it is the most accepted version, as compared to 'a midrash' ? Anyway, I'll keep my hands off the Rabbinic Literature, although my suggestion for editing still stands.~

:Regards,
:Anonymous / [[Special:Contributions/82.156.55.208|82.156.55.208]] ([[User talk:82.156.55.208|talk]]) 11:07, 8 September 2008 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tqfhiavoml3qp0huwd286ojmbtspgz3</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
