<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Anti-Zionism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>81293</id>
    <revision>
      <id>516782064</id>
      <parentid>515956596</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-09T07:38:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Rainbowofpeace</username>
        <id>12150368</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Additional comments to redirect section.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9000">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header}}
{{Round in circles|search=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=High}} 
{{WikiProject Israel|class=B|importance=High}} 
{{WikiProject Jewish history|class = B|importance=High}} 
{{WikiProject Palestine|class=B|importance=Mid}}
}}
{{controversial}}
{{pbneutral}}
{{auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot|age=21|dounreplied=yes}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Anti-Zionism/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Anti-Zionism/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 200K
|counter = 11
|algo = old(21d)
|archive = Talk:Anti-Zionism/Archive  %(counter)d
}}

== Yet some Jews remain anti-Zionist ==

I made IMO a relatively non-controversial [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-Zionism&amp;diff=442983194&amp;oldid=441959368 edit here]. 

Here is the original edit: 

&lt;blockquote&gt;Others contend that to the extent anti-Zionism represents opposition to Israel's existence, it is inherently antisemitic. Yet some Jews remain anti-Zionists.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The &quot;others contend&quot; quote is not supported by any source. This unsourced sentence leads to &quot;Yet some Jews remain anti-Zionist&quot; - sourced from [http://www.jewsnotzionists.org/ Jews Not Zionist], a non-RS that could only be used to describe the views of that organization.

The problem here is that editors are assuming one's ethnic/religious status has some bearing on opposition to Israel's existence. It doesn't. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Anti-Zionism&amp;diff=442983749&amp;oldid=442983194 Roland R] claims my edits is my own synthesis but this is quite the contrary. The whole paragraph is synthesis, and none of it is supported by a third party reliable source. Just because your Jewish doesn't somehow make your opposition to Israel more legitimate. So either my edit should be restored or the whole sentence should be axed until one can find a suitable source to support it. [[User:Wikifan12345|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#6E6D6D&quot;&gt;Wikifan&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Wikifan12345|Be nice]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  09:54, 4 August 2011 (UTC)
:I don't think anyone is suggesting being Jewish makes their opposition more legitimate; rather, the Israeli government or Zionists (as evidenced by this article) quite often accuse opponents of Zionism of being antisemitic. It's a fairly common perception held by many Zionists, as the information in this article shows. (Look at how much attention we've given antisemitism in an article about criticism/opposition regarding a political ideology.) So the thinking is that &quot;if anti-Zionist is so antisemitic, why are so many religious and secular Jews opposed to it?&quot; As well, this article itself has a &quot;Jewish Anti-Zionist&quot; section, so it'd be proper to include something about this under the &quot;Anti-Zionism and antisemitism&quot; section. That's my understanding of why it should be mentioned that many Jews are in opposition to Zionism. I'm assuming some of the citations later used under &quot;Jewish Anti-Zionism&quot; would work. I'll look into it. [[Special:Contributions/98.95.118.106|98.95.118.106]] ([[User talk:98.95.118.106|talk]]) 01:26, 11 February 2012 (UTC)

== Error in Secular section ==

It repeats a lie that Jews returning to their homeland is &quot;colonization.&quot;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Smartian1|Smartian1]] ([[User talk:Smartian1|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Smartian1|contribs]]) 04:25, 12 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:That is not an error or a lie. It is a description backed by [[WP:RS|reliable sources]]. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Papyrus&quot;&gt;[[User:RolandR|RolandR]] ([[User talk:RolandR|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 09:34, 12 October 2011 (UTC)
::Specifically which organization is being accused of antisemitism and being called into question as a non-[[WP:RS]]?—[[User:Biosketch|Biosketch]] ([[User talk:Biosketch|talk]]) 10:05, 15 October 2011 (UTC)
:::It seems to be the [[International Jewish Anti-Zionist Network]]. Their website is certainly a reliable source for their own views. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Papyrus&quot;&gt;[[User:RolandR|RolandR]] ([[User talk:RolandR|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 10:17, 15 October 2011 (UTC)
::::They don't appear to be a notable organization, in which case neither they nor their views merit attention in an encyclopedia article.—[[User:Biosketch|Biosketch]] ([[User talk:Biosketch|talk]]) 11:05, 15 October 2011 (UTC)
:::::That is not true. [[WP:N]] covers the existence of articles, not the content of articles. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 15:53, 15 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::::::And the subject of a Wikipedia article is by definition notable. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Papyrus&quot;&gt;[[User:RolandR|RolandR]] ([[User talk:RolandR|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 18:13, 15 October 2011 (UTC)

== In Prague Jewry is in power ==

I was taken aback by the sentence &quot;In Prague Jewry is in power&quot; in the Anti-Zionist conspiracy theories section. I found it incredible.
Incredible it was. The source seems to be Simon Wiesenthal's book 'Justice not Vengeance'.
In what world is a book, of which the author is a Zionist Jew, a reliable source on anti-Zionism? Not only that, but if it were true this sentence would have to be in an article on antisemitism.
I searched Google for this quote, and it is nowhere to be found.

I can't edit it out of the page, but can someone at least temporarily remove it until it is a proven fact that both the Volkischer Beobachter and Neues Deutschland used this sentence?
The only instance where I found this was a news source directly quoting this article.
That is embarassing.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:DenDelhaize|DenDelhaize]] ([[User talk:DenDelhaize|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/DenDelhaize|contribs]]) 15:46, 1 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; 

&lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Perhaps the picture accompanying this story would be a good illustration of the nature of antizionism.
[http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/148450#.TsiV9VYZ-dk]

== Anti-Zionism and antisemitism ==

As per Shrike's suggestion, I've come to the talk page to discuss the section entitled Anti-Zionism and antisemitism. Originally I blanked the section down, but Shrike rightly suggested that I summarize what the sources say instead. I'll try to get to work on that soon, but if anyone wants to help with it, I'd be grateful. On another note, but related to the same section, is there any reason why both viewpoints aren't given equal attention? I'm assuming it is just an issue with the length of the quotes, and if so, we should keep in mind that we should stay neutral and give fair attention to both sides on this issue. Cheers. [[Special:Contributions/98.95.118.106|98.95.118.106]] ([[User talk:98.95.118.106|talk]]) 20:54, 9 February 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;Definitions&quot; ==

All definitions are either plain wrong or factually disputable. This makes the whole entry unbearable. Without any bias in the motivation for this absolute critic. Thanks [[User:Rmsoran|Rmsoran]] ([[User talk:Rmsoran|talk]]) 20:34, 14 July 2012 (UTC)rmsoran

:Agree. Anti-Zionism is not necessarily opposition to the broadest conceivable definition of Zionism, one that includes all strands of Zionism. For example, Non-Zionist Anti-Post-Zionism would be very extreme: I really think few Anti-Zionists think that Jews, as a nation, have the no right to self-determination - in the way that, say, the [[Greenland|Kalaallit]]s or the [[Sápmi (area)|Sámi]]s have. Or think that Jews have no right to live in the(ir) Holy Land. [[User:Steinberger|Steinberger]] ([[User talk:Steinberger|talk]]) 13:16, 4 October 2012 (UTC)

== Redirects ==

Curently both anti-Israel and Israelophobia lead here. I think there should be a seperate article made to discuss discrimination faced by Israelis around the world and on the international stage and since people refuse to consider definitatively anti-zionism to be that I suggest we create a new article. To start I'm asking for these two terms to not be redirected here. Since people on here claim it is not against Israel but against zionist that shouldn't be a problem.-[[User:Rainbowofpeace|Rainbowofpeace]] ([[User talk:Rainbowofpeace|talk]]) 12:26, 20 September 2012 (UTC)

Also I'm probably not going to name the article either of these but I just think redirects would be better suited to the article I'm thinking &quot;anti-Israeli sentiment&quot; would be best. But I think that redirects here too.-[[User:Rainbowofpeace|Rainbowofpeace]] ([[User talk:Rainbowofpeace|talk]]) 12:28, 20 September 2012 (UTC)

I will take the silence as permission to go ahead.-[[User:Rainbowofpeace|Rainbowofpeace]] ([[User talk:Rainbowofpeace|talk]]) 07:38, 9 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>atpv7fxhgnxcw7cy5vu8qg8z4v9oee6</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
