<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Bahá'u'lláh</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1050359</id>
    <revision>
      <id>514098429</id>
      <parentid>514097576</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-23T01:07:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Smkolins</username>
        <id>358790</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Reverence */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="67545">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=01:22, 6 June 2012
|action1link=Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=495780364
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=philrelig
}}
{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Bahá'í Faith|class=GA|importance=Top}}
{{WPReligion|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WPBiography
|living=no
|class=GA
|listas=Bahaullah
}}}}
{{WP1.0|class=GA|category=category|VA=yes}} 
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-11-12|oldid1=28088987|date2=2011-04-21|oldid2=425077966}}

== Archives ==

#[[/Archive 1]] comments from 2003, Orthodox Bahais, some factual (in)accuracies, Baha'ullah's wives and the picture
#[[/Archive 2]] contains more debate about the picture and the wives
#[[/Archive 3]] about Mirza Yahya and a lot more about the picture
#[[/Archive 4]] Has not been parcelled out to the other archives yet. [[User:Cunado19|Cunado19]] 02:51, 24 July 2005 (UTC)
#[[/Archive 5]] Has not been parcelled out to the other archives yet. [[User:Cunado19|Cunado19]] 17:05, 27 July 2005 (UTC)
#[[/Archive 6]] 06:23, 14 June 2008 (UTC)

The Archives have been reorganised as follows to make it easier to follow the discussion threads:
*[[/Archive Exile]]
*[[/Archive Format]]
*[[/Archive language skills]]
*[[/Archive NPOV]]
*[[/Archive Orthodox]]
*[[/Archive Picture]]
*[[/Archive Wives]]
*[[/Archive Personal_Attacks]]
The original Archives remain unchanged for the time being. --[[User:Occamy|Occamy]] 22:19, 8 Feb 2005 (UTC)
== Family Origin ==
There is a Tablet by Abdu'l-Baha that states that his family comes from &quot;Afghanistan and Iran&quot;  The Tablet is found on page 1 of vol. 4 of Selected Writings of Abdul-Baha (Persian)   &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.3.206.208|75.3.206.208]] ([[User talk:75.3.206.208|talk]]) 08:23, 2 February 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
 

==Photo opinions subpage==
A sub-page [[Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Photo]] has been added to post opinions regarding the photo issue

==Photo edits==
Edited photo to make it collapsible.  This will satisfy both sides of the photo argument (hiding the photo for those offended by it, but making it expandable for those who still choose to view the photo).  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.205.224.64|216.205.224.64]] ([[User talk:216.205.224.64|talk]]) 18:31, 16 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==List of Bahá'u'lláh's names and titles==
[[Rúhíyyih Khanum]] comiled a book with these titles. Would it be an idea to have a list on a separate page? [[User:Wiki-uk|Wiki-uk]] 05:16, 5 October 2006 (UTC)
:I don't think a seperate page is a good idea.  And I'm not too fond of including a list even in this page, unless it can somehow be placed in the prose. -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] 14:58, 11 October 2006 (UTC)
::Agreed. We'd all do well to review [[WP:Notability]]. Obscure information, no matter how interesting, genuinely might not belong in an encyclopedia, even one trying to play one on TV. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] 15:24, 11 October 2006 (UTC)
:::It could become more listcruft, you know. And it depends on the encyclopedia. Wikipedia might not allow it, but a hypothetical Obscuropedia could. [[User:74.38.35.171|74.38.35.171]] 06:42, 1 January 2007 (UTC)
::::It seems to be just as relevant as [[Names of God]], [[99 Names of God in the Qur'an]], etc. As to its obscurity, the invoking of these names is a form of worship in the Bahá'i faith, so I can't say what leads you to label it as obscure, save perhaps that it is obscure to your personal perspective. I don't intend to make the page, but I don't see any reason why it shouldn't be made. [[Special:Contributions/68.127.51.196|68.127.51.196]] ([[User talk:68.127.51.196|talk]]) 05:02, 3 January 2008 (UTC)

==photograph==
Moved comments to [[Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Photo]] [[User:Cunado19|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[image:Bahai star.svg|20px]] - [[User talk:Cunado19|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 06:17, 26 December 2006 (UTC)


== Shrine Image ==

This note is for everyone who is interested in looking for pictures. I believe that the image of the Shrine of Baha'u'llah is very old looking, unclear, poor resolution, and lacking vivid and realistic color. In other words, by replacing the nicer picture with a free use picture, we have sacrificed quality. In fact I should say that it is very sad that we would choose something that looks like a scanner image from the 1970's or 1980's. This is very unprofessional and it shows poor quality standards. My recommendation is that we look for a new image of the shrine, one that does not look dull and old. This does not have to be a copyright image. But please, I think we need a newer replacement. [[User:Nmentha|Nmentha]] 06:27, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

::The only Shrine picture that we have that is free is the current one.  Non-free images of buildings that still exist have been deleted on hundreds of pages, and will be deleted.  The goal of Wikipedia is to provide a ''free'' encyclopedia, and that is why the admins have deleted non-free images, and we must work in the same vein.  If you have a better photo, that can be released under a free license (GFDL, CC) upload one.  -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] 14:11, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

::::The overhead photo of Bahji is still in the article, and is credited to the Baha'i Media Bank. Couldn't we take a better image of the Shrine from there? I thought the one here[http://media.bahai.org/subjects/locations/holy_places_acr/shrin_bahaullah/7139/details] (or one very much like it) had been used before, with proper Fair Use justifications. --[[User:Twilightsojourn|Twilightsojourn]] 08:01, 18 February 2007 (UTC)
:::::Fair use doesn't apply when a building still exists and a photo can be taken of it, or when a free alternative exists.  That there are media bank images still on Wikipedia, doesn't make it right to use more media bank images.  The admins will delete the image when they get to it.  The solution is to find nicer free images. -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] 08:04, 18 February 2007 (UTC)
::::::Ideally, yes. However, if an image is licensed in such a way that allows it to be used for free with proper attribution, there is no legal reason not to do so, unless a better free image can be found. Since the Media Bank images are legal for use here, why shouldn't they be used until a better free image is found? --[[User:Twilightsojourn|Twilightsojourn]] 07:52, 19 February 2007 (UTC)
:::::::Because the admins have already deleted many images from the media bank for specifically not abiding by the [[WP:FUC|fair use criteria]].   These images include some House of Worship pictures, the Shrine of Baha'u'llah pictures, the House of Justice pictures, some maps, the Archives building, the Centre for the Study of the Texts, the Mansion of Bahji, 10 Haparsim Street, the Haifa pilgrim House and others.  That there are some media bank images still left is not reason to add more.  We must try to ubhold Wikipedia standards rather than find exceptions.  Find a free picture. -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] 14:22, 19 February 2007 (UTC)
::::::::I think you misunderstood me, my friend. I had been under the impression that as long as images were licensed for free use in the way the Media Bank images are, that they were allowed on Wikipedia. It appears that the Wikipedia stance on this has changed since I last checked, hence my confusion. I was not suggesting that we should try and &quot;get away&quot; with using Media Bank images when such is discouraged, or not allowed. --[[User:Twilightsojourn|Twilightsojourn]] 01:09, 20 February 2007 (UTC)
I am working on it. However, I am very suprised that we can only find one picture! [[User:Nmentha|Nmentha]] 16:46, 9 February 2007 (UTC)

== Please remove photo ==
Moved comments to [[Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Photo]]. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 19:38, 28 January 2008 (UTC)

I don't even know how to make a wiki editing talk. But truth being said, no Bahá'í text can assure that such a picture is a picture from their prophet.
So, my question is: how accurate can this be? (unsigned)

It is authentic - albeit a rather bad photo - that has never been the point of controversy. The question has been - should it be there at all? The Baha'i position is NO - basically because posting it openly on the web like this is considered to be treating Baha'u'llah's image with disrespect. Many Baha'is (myself included) have been shocked and upset by this, and would honestly rather it were removed. It remains on the page (in spite of being repeatedly deleted, presumably by casual Baha'i editors) because the non-Baha'is want it to remain, and thoughtful Baha'i editors have generally decided that it is not our place to dictate to non-Baha'is how they want to do anything, even to displaying images of Baha'u'llah. Wikipedia is after all a secular site, not a Baha'i one, nor connected in any way with any other religion. Do click on this link [[Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Photo]] if you are really interested - to view some of the (at times heated) controversy around this issue. --[[User:Soundofmusicals|Soundofmusicals]] ([[User talk:Soundofmusicals|talk]]) 23:16, 1 October 2008 (UTC)

The fact of the matter is, religion is not about idols so there is no need to keep this picture up and the fact that it keeps being re-posted means the picture is being posted by someone who doesn't understand the fundamentals of religion in the first place. So if you actually want to know about the baha'i faith go to a legitimate site instead of reading the views of someone willing to disrespect a religion to show their &quot;human right&quot; to copy and paste.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/188.29.174.239|188.29.174.239]] ([[User talk:188.29.174.239|talk]]) 18:33, 17 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

If there was a photo of the prophet Muhammad on a web site like this, there would probably be Muslims on the streets shouting and burning like we see now with the film about Muhammad. And as a result the editor of the web site would feel compelled to remove the photo. But as Baha'i is a peaceful religion Wikipedia editors seems not willing to show due respect and remove the photo.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2.150.51.26|2.150.51.26]] ([[User talk:2.150.51.26|talk]]) 21:55, 22 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;[[Special:Contributions/2.150.51.26|2.150.51.26]] ([[User talk:2.150.51.26|talk]]) 22:28, 22 September 2012 (UTC)
: Actually there are informal uses of representations of the Muhammad - they are just done more tastefully. The picture in question is not owned by Baha'is so Baha'is cannot decide how it is used. A long process was undertaken in which compromise was actually taken. See [[:Talk:Bahá%27u%27lláh/Archive_Picture]]. [[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 00:58, 23 September 2012 (UTC)

== Section positioning ==
Per [[WP:LAYOUT]], the works section is an appendix to the body of the article.  The body includes the extensive discussion of this apparently controversial image.  It seems odd here, and clearly tangential from Wiki guidelines, to move the image to the bottom of the article.  This makes the article go from Lead to Body to Appendage to Body to More Appendages. --[[User:Veritas|Veritas]] ([[User talk:Veritas|talk]]) 05:24, 7 February 2008 (UTC)
:I could see it going either way; before or after the &quot;Works&quot; subsection.  The current &quot;Works&quot; subsection is quite poor, but I don't think its intent was just to be a list of works, but a section describing the types of books, letters, etc that Baha'u'llah wrote.  Regardless, both before or after I think can work.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 05:33, 7 February 2008 (UTC)
::Well if it were to be a general discussion of his writings then, yes, it would belong in the body.  However, that is not what the section is in its current form.  Rather, it serves as an appendix to the biography.  That's why I think it should be brought into standard for of the other biographical articles on Wiki where the body is placed before the publications - for the sake of consistency if nothing else.--[[User:Veritas|Veritas]] ([[User talk:Veritas|talk]]) 05:36, 7 February 2008 (UTC)

==[[Wikipedia:No disclaimers in articles]]==
There should not be a disclaimer in this article. The image should be at the top, along with every other article about anything or anyone. This article is setting a terrible precedent. This needs to be changed. There are no &quot;compromises&quot; in censorship. '''Wikipedia is not censored'''. Period. With this being here, we'll have to do this at [[Muhammad]], as well. We need to be consistent. We'll also have to do this at articles such as [[Prince Albert piercing]]. '''[[User:hmwith|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#999;color:#fff;padding:0 4px&quot;&gt;нмŵוτн&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:hmwith|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#666;padding:0 4px;color:#fff;&quot;&gt;τ&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 02:50, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
:Have to do the same at [[Muhammad]]???? Just have a look at that article will you, and explain to me where the picture of Muhammad is??? '''There isn't one at all!!''' In practice Wikipedia veers to a more gentle version of neutrality, often bowing slightly to group sensitivities without banging the &quot;no POV&quot; drum to the point of making &quot;standardise formats at all costs&quot; a POV in itself. 

:This question is actually a very long running sore - with many people objecting to the picture being there at all, and others feeling, like you, that it should be at the top. The current setup is a sensible compromise, although it obviously does not please everyone.If you really want to wade through all that has been said on the subject then try [[Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Photo]]. Someone will probably move this exchange there actually!! [[User:Soundofmusicals|Soundofmusicals]] ([[User talk:Soundofmusicals|talk]]) 22:46, 16 February 2008 (UTC)

::I didn't say he was on this page... I was referring to pictures of Muhammad on the Muhammad page... and PA piercing on the PA page. That's also your opinion of of Wikipedia's views. Wikipedia doesn't slant it to benefit any specific group of people. If you want the image on the bottom, okay, but there will be no disclaimers. That's unencyclopedic &amp; ridiculous. If one doesn't want to see him, don't look him up in an uncensored, illustrated encyclopedia. '''[[User:hmwith|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#999;color:#fff;padding:0 4px&quot;&gt;нмŵוτн&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:hmwith|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#666;padding:0 4px;color:#fff;&quot;&gt;τ&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 22:51, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
:::Please do not just go editing it out like you did. There has been discussion on this for months, see [[Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Photo]]. [[User:Peter Deer|Peter Deer]] ([[User talk:Peter Deer|talk]]) 23:00, 16 February 2008 (UTC)

::::Thank you, but I'm aware. See my response to your revert [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk%3APeter_Deer&amp;diff=191946488&amp;oldid=190317493 on your talk page]. '''[[User:hmwith|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#999;color:#fff;padding:0 4px&quot;&gt;нмŵוτн&lt;/span&gt;]][[User talk:hmwith|&lt;span style=&quot;background:#666;padding:0 4px;color:#fff;&quot;&gt;τ&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 23:05, 16 February 2008 (UTC)

:How is a [[WP:DISCLAIM|disclaimer]] identical to [[WP:CENSOR|censorship]] which to me would be not having the photo on ''at all''? [[User:Mike4ty4|mike4ty4]] ([[User talk:Mike4ty4|talk]]) 06:58, 3 January 2009 (UTC)

== Replacing missing link ==
I've added [http://www.whoisbahaullah.com/ Who is Baha'u'llah] back in again. From [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_web_page Personal web page]:

&quot;..typical personal web pages contain images, text and a collection of hyperlinks. Many can contain biographical information, résumés, and blogs. Many personal pages will include information about the author's hobbies and pastimes, and information of interest to friends and family of the author.&quot;

On the contrary, Who is Baha'u'llah, is solely devoted to an explanation of the history, teachings and writings of Baha'u'llah. Furthermore, on the [http://www.whoisbahaullah.com/about.html about page], it specifically says:

&quot;The purpose of this site is to enable anyone who is interested to investigate Baha'u'llah's message. In addition to giving an overview of the main aspects of the Faith, it links to a wide range of other information. Because the site is independent of the Baha'i administration, it contains information not found on official sites and presents the faith in a different way to those sites.&quot;

The reason this site is important to include is precisely because it assists in Wikipedia's NPOV policy and provides translations of works by Baha'u'llah that are not provided in the other external links. [[User:Sufisticated|Sufisticated]] ([[User talk:Sufisticated|talk]]) 04:54, 20 May 2008 (UTC)
:&quot;Many personal pages will include information about the author's hobbies and pastimes, and information of interest to friends and family of the author.&quot;
:The website in question, in the &quot;about this site&quot; says:
:&quot;Alison loves to study Baha'u'llah's writings and has a particular interest in the mystical aspects of the Faith. She also studies classical and Qur'anic Arabic, Sufism, and aspects of the other major religions.&quot;
:Judging by the About This Site page, it is the personal site of Alison Marshall. [[User:Peter Deer|Peter Deer]] ([[User talk:Peter Deer|talk]]) 07:52, 20 May 2008 (UTC)
:: In which case, you'd have to remove like references to [http://bahai-library.com/file.php5?file=personal_jonah_winters Jonah Winters' Baha'i Library.] But in the spirit of compromise, I've directed the link to the valuable contribution from the site, which is the index of translations of the Writings. [[User:Sufisticated|Sufisticated]] ([[User talk:Sufisticated|talk]]) 09:11, 20 May 2008 (UTC)
Policy is policy, Alison Marshell's website is not acceptable, as whoisbahaullah clearly states that it is the views of a single individual . As you well know baha'i-library.org is run by no definition a personal website, since it links and aggregrates scholarly works that have been published in other souces. Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 12:30, 20 May 2008 (UTC)
:: Okay, this is my problem. I'm trying to add in an external link to a source that provides translations of some of Baha'u'llah's lesser known works. The best list I have seen on the web of such material is [http://www.whoisbahaullah.com/explore/ Baha'u'llah Explore]. Now these translations are available elsewhere on the web, but they are scattered (see for example, [http://www.h-net.org/~bahai/trans.htm here], [http://www-personal.umich.edu/~jrcole/bhtrans.htm here], [http://www.ojbs.org/ here], [http://www.hurqalya.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/BAHA'-ALLAH/Baha'-Allah.htm here], and [http://bahaistudies.net/kf/translations.html here]). It seems redundant to list all these sites, which also include other materials apart from translations of Baha'u'llah's works, when Alison at Baha'u'llah Explore has done a very good job of collecting them and providing them on her site, a smaller version of Jonah Winters if you will.  Can you give me recommendations  as to how to solve this quandry? [[User:Sufisticated|.o0o.Sufisticated.o0o.]] ([[User talk:Sufisticated|talk]]) 19:01, 20 May 2008 (UTC)
:A personal website is a personal website, and synthesis of other works is considered [[WP:OR|original research]], and not allowed in Wikipedia.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 19:31, 20 May 2008 (UTC)
::I should also note that the three last links that you provided are also personal website; personal translations that haven't been published in a reliable source, and are also not admissible.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 19:34, 20 May 2008 (UTC)

::: I beg to differ Jeff, the translations are all from respected academic authorities in the field of Babi and Baha'i studies, and have been published (not just through official Baha'i administrative channels). [http://www.h-net.org/~bahai/ H-Baha'i], for example, is part of H-Net, which is an international interdisciplinary organization of scholars and teachers. The translations list on [http://www-personal.umich.edu/~jrcole/bhtrans.htm Juan Cole's translation site], list the academic publications the translations have been published in next to each link; likewise there are links to the places of publication for the translations provided by [http://www.hurqalya.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/BAHA'-ALLAH/Baha'-Allah.htm Dr Lambden], and if you click on each translation by Khazeh Fananapazir he provides individual publishing details for each one. Admittedly most of these have been published either through H-Net or the Baha'i Studies Review, but they are important contributions to our English-language repository of the works of Baha'u'llah.[[User:Sufisticated|.o0o.Sufisticated.o0o.]] ([[User talk:Sufisticated|talk]]) 06:26, 21 May 2008 (UTC)

:::I agree with Jeff that personal websites should be discouraged, and in particular I think the Allison Marshal website is unprofessional. The idea that this is an appropriate site to point people for more information is laughable. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 21:01, 20 May 2008 (UTC)

::::The key point about personal websites is that they are not [[WP:RS|reliable]]. Marshall's &quot;translations&quot; should be treated with special care as she, to my knowledge, doesn't have access to authentic texts, nor does she have any training in either Arabic or Persian. She offers no sources for either the original texts nor the translations on any of her sites. That kind of intellectual irresponsibility is ''exactly'' why personal sites are viewed with such a jaundiced eye here. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 22:58, 20 May 2008 (UTC)

::::: The translations that Alison provides on the site, are not her own works MARussellPESE. They are the translations of respected authorities in the field (please see above). I think perhaps there is some confusion over the difference between &quot;being published by a Baha'i publishing body&quot; and being published by any other body including non-Baha'i publishing bodies and individual academics. The latter does not mean they are unreliable, it just means they are not considered 'official' by the Baha'i administration. But for the purposes of Wikipedia that is not a meaningful distinction.[[User:Sufisticated|.o0o.Sufisticated.o0o.]] ([[User talk:Sufisticated|talk]]) 06:26, 21 May 2008 (UTC)

Just a few minor points.  We do allow personal websites when they are the official website of an acknowledged professional researcher or journalist who has been previously published by third-party sources in their field.  (That's a mouthful.) So we would allow say the personal website of [[Ted Koppel]].  On a second note, synthesis is not necessarily [[WP:OR|original research]].  It has to be synthesis which advances a novel position.  &quot;Novel&quot; here not just meaning the simple &quot;new&quot;, since almost all of Wikipedia is &quot;new&quot; synthesis, but rather &quot;Novel&quot; meaning something more like &quot;unusual, obscure, abnormal, remarkable&quot;.  I would recommend a trip to the [[WP:RSN|reliable sources noticeboard]] if the editor seeking to add the material thinks this finding is unwarranted. [[User:Wjhonson|Wjhonson]] ([[User talk:Wjhonson|talk]]) 23:15, 20 May 2008 (UTC)

: Thanks Wjhonson and everyone. I've posted a question up about the reliability of Baha'u'llah Explore at: [[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Reliable_sources/Noticeboard#Question_on_reliability_of_English_translations_of_Baha.27u.27llah.27s_works]][[User:Sufisticated|.o0o.Sufisticated.o0o.]] ([[User talk:Sufisticated|talk]]) 06:57, 21 May 2008 (UTC)
:If the scholars have published their translations, then link to the translations in the scholaly sources, not to a personal website, which cannot guarantee the reliability of the translations. Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 12:32, 21 May 2008 (UTC)
::::As I mentioned previously, Baha'i Explore gathers those scattered links over a variety of URLs and provides them in one direct location. I think I have made a good case for including Baha'u'llah Explore, which directly provides those translations of other scholars' works with their direct permission. I fail to see how it is *not* a reliable site by definition of Wikipedia.[[User:Sufisticated|.o0o.Sufisticated.o0o.]] ([[User talk:Sufisticated|talk]]) 12:48, 21 May 2008 (UTC)

:::::The website is not being used to source statements in the article, it is being used in the external links as a source of further information. I would first ask the question, &quot;what 3 or 4 websites are the most reliable, relevant, and provide useful further reading.&quot; This personal site is definitely not in that group, and the value of her compilation of translations including a few previously untranslated letters is insignificant. The unprofessional nature of the website, including a blog-style layout and personal stories, damages her credibility as a source for further reading. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 15:10, 21 May 2008 (UTC)

== Compliments on an excellent article ==

I read this article with much interest and found it to be excellent.  I also appreciate the civility demonstrated on this talk page.  I hope the photograph dispute can be resolved in such a civil manner.

I do not know what the qualifications (or disqualifications) are to be a featured article, but speaking objectively, I think this article deserves recognition (although I would like to see the photograph dispute resolved first).  However, I am a Baha'i, and so it is difficult to be impartial -- I'd like to see this article have its moment in the sun for personal reasons as well, but my recommendation that it merits being featured is primarily based on it's excellent cross-referencing, language, and informational content.

Another caveat is that I do not know how Baha'i laws would apply in this case.  Is there an admonition that this action would be improper? --[[Special:Contributions/98.25.183.242|98.25.183.242]] ([[User talk:98.25.183.242|talk]]) 17:03, 5 September 2008 (UTC)

:The photograph issue will likely never be resolved to everyone's satisfaction, and an article with such a dispute would never qualify for featured article status. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 01:45, 6 September 2008 (UTC)

== Editations getting deleted?! ==
I have noticed that my editorials have been deleted quite a many times by now.

Here is one Bahai edit. I added a new section but it disappeared into thin air:

'''''Muslims Reaction'''

Bahá'u'lláh is considered to be a dajjaal among the dajjaals that will apear before The Dajjaal(Antichrist). As mentioned in a hadeeth (saying of Prophet Muhammad) in Sahih Bukhari, the Prophet Muhammad (Peace Be Upon Him) said that there will be forty liars (dajjaaloon kadh-dhaaboon), each will claim to be a prophet. The hadeeth continues, and the prophet warns his followers against the Greatest Dajjaal who will deciet people and make them worship him as a god.

Muslim scholars all agree that Bahá'u'lláh is a decietful liar. Since he didn't take back his claim anytime throughout his life, he can easily be a Dajjaal. Based on this information, most Muslims believe that Bahá'u'lláh will be in the Hell-fire (Jahannam) as a punishment for claiming to be a prophet even after he knew he wasn't.''

Thanks for your considerations,

--[[Special:Contributions/77.30.34.154|77.30.34.154]] ([[User talk:77.30.34.154|talk]]) 14:08, 5 January 2009 (UTC)Yahya Al-Shiddazi

:Would you like a similar Christian edit on Muhammad article? People have different religions. Almost everyone follows the religion of their parents. If you had different parents you might be putting edits like that into Muhammad's article. How does that make you feel?  --[[User:Soundofmusicals|Soundofmusicals]] ([[User talk:Soundofmusicals|talk]]) 14:32, 5 January 2009 (UTC)

::Your contributions fail several Wikipedia policies [[WP:NPOV]], [[WP:V]], &amp; [[WP:CS]]. You're clearly trying to present Muslim [[apologia]] into what is supposed to be an [[WP:NOT|encyclopedia]]. — [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 01:09, 6 January 2009 (UTC)

::: Actually, I have figured out both of you are Bahais. That's why you took out my editorial(s). Here's my proof:
''I am a Bahá'í, and have been one since birth. I seem to be following these articles with interest.  — MARussellPESE''
''I am a member of the Baha'i Faith but in many respects a very bad example of what a Baha'i should be. I try anyway.  — Soundsofthemusical''

My edits are perfectly Justified. I will continue to replace my edits untill some ''non-Bahai '''Administrator''' '' advises otherwise.

I believe that all WikiReligion articles should mention the &quot;Reaction of Other Religions&quot; in ''each'' religion article. Once again, thanks for the cooperations.

-Yahya Al-Shiddazi

::Sorry, your additions are far from meeting Wikipedia policies noted above, and not permissible.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 13:46, 6 January 2009 (UTC)

::: I am sorry ''once again'', but I mentioned that I needed a ''non-Bahai '''Administrator''' ''. Jeff3000 is another Bahai! Look:

My religion
I am a proud Baha'i. I have no bias, however. I believe everyone is inclined towards the religion they are born in.

Therefore, I will plead to get a legitimate comment from a real administrator, yet for now, I am adding my section.

Partial Thanks,

Yahya Al-Shiddazi  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/94.98.133.148|94.98.133.148]] ([[User talk:94.98.133.148|talk]]) 14:39, 6 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Another Wikipedia policy is [[WP:AGF|assume good faith]].  Based on that policy, itt has nothing to do with religion, but with the core content Wikipedia policies noted above.  Your additions don't meet those policies.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 15:04, 6 January 2009 (UTC)
::Also, you edited (vandalized) my userpage to note what you wrote above.  Your actions are not quite honest, are they? Regards, -- 15:06, 6 January 2009 (UTC)

::: You are a true Wikipedian! Thanks for commenting politely. Yes, I agree, perhaps it was not quite honest. But it was a little funny...I apologies only to Jeff3000 AND NOT TO ANY OF THE OTHER bahais. Yet I will continue to be monitering the Bahai paged.

-Yahya Al-Shiddazi  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/94.99.55.200|94.99.55.200]] ([[User talk:94.99.55.200|talk]]) 18:16, 6 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Yahya, your accusations of bias based on our affilations are [[WP:NPA|personal attacks]] and not allowed here. If you were not editing from anonymous IP accounts, you'd have been formally warned against this. You can be blocked from editing, even from IP accounts. Please tone it down, stop making personal attacks, stop [[WP:POINT|disrupting this page]] to make your particular point, and [[WP:AGF|assume good faith]]. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 04:13, 7 January 2009 (UTC)

::Yahya, [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User%3AJeff3000&amp;diff=262308210&amp;oldid=257793085 this] vandalization of another editor's user page is totally unacceptable. If anybody needs administrator sanction, it's you. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 04:16, 7 January 2009 (UTC)

== Mountains of Kurdistan and Sulaymaniyah ==

Text on Wikipedia:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
On April 10, 1854 Bahá'u'lláh, leaving his family to the care of his brother Mirza Musa, left with one companion to the mountains of Kurdistan, northeast of Baghdad, near the city of Sulaymaniyah. He later wrote that he left so as to avoid becoming the source of disagreement within the Bábí community, and that his &quot;withdrawal contemplated no return&quot;.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Referenced text:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Factions of Babis formed in Baghdad who were loyal to either
Baha'u'llah or to Azal, and the ensuing jealousies and rancor so disgusted
Baha'u'llah that in 1854 he secretly departed from Baghdad, taking with him only
one companion, a merchant, and went to Kurdistan in the north where he lived the
life of a mystic. After some time, his friend was killed by thieves. The Kurds
practiced the mystical form of Islam known as Sufism, and a branch of the
Naqshbandi Sufis in Sulaymaniyyah heard of Baha'u'llah's piety, inviting him to
their center.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
I don't see any references to a mountain, is this a fact or just added here for dramatic effect?
[[User:Mavromatis|Mavromatis]] ([[User talk:Mavromatis|talk]]) 20:51, 14 January 2009 (UTC)
:see [[Kurdistan]] - &quot;is an extensive plateau and mountainous area&quot;...&quot;Kurds have no friends but the mountains&quot;. [[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 00:20, 15 January 2009 (UTC)
::also specifically [[Sulaymaniyah]] which is mentioned elsewhere as one place in Kurdistan where Baha'u'llah went. [[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 00:23, 15 January 2009 (UTC)
:::which is to say Sulaymaniyah is in &quot;eastern [[Iraqi Kurdistan]]&quot; which is then described as &quot;largely mountainous&quot;. So when you are satisfied, please delete the tag. [[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 00:30, 15 January 2009 (UTC)
I've added the specific reference from &lt;small&gt;{{cite book | last = Smith | first = Peter | year = 2008 | title = An Introduction to the Baha'i Faith | publisher = Cambridge University Press | isbn = 0521862515 | location = Cambridge | pages = 17}}&lt;/small&gt; which states &quot;Baha'u'llah decided to abandon the city to pursue the life of a solitary mystic in the mountains of Kurdistan, leaving his family to the care of Mirza Musa.&quot; Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 00:59, 15 January 2009 (UTC)

== Names of places ==

[[WP:EN]] states that what is prominent in English should be used in Wikipedia as per reliable sources.  The following sources &lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1023189.stm BBC - Timeline: Turkey]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; Room, Adrian, (1993), ''Place Name changes 1900-1991'', Metuchen, N.J., &amp; London:The Scarecrow Press, Inc., ISBN 0-8108-2600-3 p. 46, 86 &lt;/ref&gt; state that Constantinople's name was changed to Istanbul in 1930.  As regards to Edirne/Istanbul, the name of the city in English publications was still Adrianople by 1911 (1911 Encyclopedia Britannica).&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/1911_Encyclop%C3%A6dia_Britannica/Adrianople_(city)&lt;/ref&gt;  Furthermore based on the following source &lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | journals = Essays and Notes on Babi and Baha’i History | first = John | last = Walbridge publisher = H-Net Consortium: Michigan State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;, the city was still called Adrianople by Europeans until the 1920s when Turkey adopted the Roman alphabet.  

It is thus clear that while Baha'u'llah (1860s) was in Constantinople/Istanbul and Adrianople/Edirne the names of the cities in English (not the local language) as per the sources noted above were Constantinople and Adrianople.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 01:10, 15 January 2009 (UTC)

== marriage ==

i have just edited and added some information about his marriage and wives  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mrjames 9999|Mrjames 9999]] ([[User talk:Mrjames 9999|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mrjames 9999|contribs]]) 18:09, 16 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I have removed the content that is either more about the wives, and not Baha'u'llah (since that is not the principle subject of this article) and statements about the wives titles, which is also not the subject of this article.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 18:46, 17 January 2009 (UTC)
::I concur with Jeff3000's reverts. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 21:37, 17 January 2009 (UTC)

== Photograph - Question of TASTE ==

Moved to [[Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Photo]]. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 16:08, 11 April 2009 (UTC)

== Perception ==

I'm not trying to be contumacious but the section regarding Baha'u'llah's declaration is central to the article and subject itself. It is therefore particularly important to be neutral, concise and precise in this paragraph. Using &quot;percieved&quot; can suggest that the subject doubted his own claims or later refuted them and this is clearly not the case. I'm as bad at using weasel words as anyone but in this instance I 'perceive' that we are diluting the clarity with which these statements were made.

I have limited experience in wikipedia and will obviously defer to the judgement of editors who have contributed far more me than me but I have re-edited this section one last time.[[User:Nernst|Nernst]] ([[User talk:Nernst|talk]]) 14:37, 17 May 2009 (UTC)
:I disagree with your assessment.  Being neutral means not stating anything as fact.  Your wording of &quot;that he was a Messenger of God&quot; takes the Baha'i viewpoint that he WAS a Messenger of God while most of the world would disagree.  It's always better to have neutral wording as this article can be very controversial.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 15:16, 17 May 2009 (UTC)

I guess it's a problem of perception ! My previous edits stated that Baha'u'llah SAID he was a Messenger of God. As far as I am aware, this is not in dispute. Baha'is are more likely to agree with his assertion while non-Bahai's (by definition) are not. I would respectfully disagree with your definition of neutral since wikipedia would be lost without facts. Perhaps 'precise' would be a better adjective. I have once again re-edited the section on the assumption that I was not clear previously with my reasoning. If you do feel strongly about it, feel free to change it again. I am certainly grateful for your guidance and view.[[User:Nernst|Nernst]] ([[User talk:Nernst|talk]]) 15:58, 17 May 2009 (UTC)
:I do feel strongly.  I understand where you are coming from, but I disagree with you conclusion.  Not everyone will read it as such, and being on the safe side is always better for neutrality.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 16:03, 17 May 2009 (UTC)
::I concur with Jeff3000. Gramatically &quot;he was&quot; is definitive. &quot;His perception of&quot; is not. [[WP:NPOV]] requires that definitive statements be generally accepted by neutral observers — hence the reliance on [[WP:SECONDARY|secondary sources]] rather than primary one.. Leaving this up to the reader is not what WP is trying to do. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 16:36, 17 May 2009 (UTC)
Do you not think your &quot;warning&quot; was a slight over reaction ? [[User:Nernst|Nernst]] ([[User talk:Nernst|talk]]) 16:23, 17 May 2009 (UTC)
:No, since clearly you didn't know about the rules, and part of the Wikipedia etiquette before asking for administrator action is to warn the other user.  Please read [[Wikipedia:3RR]].  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 16:29, 17 May 2009 (UTC)
::Agree: It wasn't. You're relatively new and the warning was of the lowest level — assuming your good faith and simple misunderstanding. None of us would like to see you take a block for such a reason. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 16:36, 17 May 2009 (UTC)
I am very surprised that telling someone on their homepage that they appear to be involved in an 'edit war' is considered 'low level'. Still I obviously have much to learn about wikipedia. As I have said before I'm happy to go along with the consensus and that appears to be in favor of using &quot;he perceived&quot;, though it doesn't look like I have much choice![[User:Nernst|Nernst]] ([[User talk:Nernst|talk]]) 16:48, 17 May 2009 (UTC)
::'Tis much better than being told that you &quot;are&quot; edit warring and being blocked for it. Blocks are permanent blemishes. [[User:MARussellPESE|MARussellPESE]] ([[User talk:MARussellPESE|talk]]) 17:00, 17 May 2009 (UTC)

:::Having no religious affiliation whatsoever, I look to the language itself, and find myself allied here with [[User:Nernst|Nernst]]. If we are using the statement as an indirect quotation, then did B declare &quot;I am a Messenger of God?&quot;. If he did, then it is fair to so state without further qualification. (The &quot;perceived&quot; part is covered in the lede, and this same approach seems to be what is used in the article on [[Jesus]], for example. There is a difference between assessing a person's claims -which we should do through reliable secondary sources, and not our own choice of unreferenced qualifiers, and presenting what he/she actually said.  To get around the problem, may I suggest that you quote the exact words he used, and then follow with an acceptable translation, or go straight to the acceptable translation? [[User:Bielle|// BL \\]] ([[User talk:Bielle|talk]]) 17:12, 17 May 2009 (UTC)

I did not think or expect the change in question would warrant this level of discussion or response. I suspect, therefore that either my approach or the clique response to it was flawed. I defer to experience and will avoid further contribution in this area. Either of the last 2 edits seems fine [[User:Nernst|Nernst]] ([[User talk:Nernst|talk]]) 18:12, 17 May 2009 (UTC)

:We have strayed far from the point here. To get back to it - from the point of view of Baha'is (and of course Baha'u'llah himself) He was diectly called by God to His mission to become a Manifestation of God. This article, however, is not Baha'i literature, but an attempt at a fair account, from a neutral point of view. We Baha'is are a tiny minority - most people (alas) do not believe Baha'u'llah actually had this mission, even if they admire His teachings, or find inspriration in His life. Hence the word &quot;perceived&quot; - every fair minded person would admit that Baha'u'llah was at least sincere, that is that He believed in his mission himself. This is also something that, at least in this context, Baha'u'llah's own disciples shuld have no problems with. It is NOT a tautology (a word that adds nothing to the meaning of a sentence) - it is certainly not &quot;bad grammar&quot; (whatever that is). It IS worthwhile in that it makes the article read less like a Baha'i tract and more like an encyclopedia article!!--[[User:Soundofmusicals|Soundofmusicals]] ([[User talk:Soundofmusicals|talk]]) 01:42, 18 May 2009 (UTC)

==Reverence==
Hey i wasn't sure how to formally add my opinion to this so i just decided to edit. As a secular web-sight wikipedia has every right to put up the picture of Bahá'u'lláh, however as a Bahai I cannot help but be slightly offended. This is clearly offensive to most Bahais and I see no reason why removing the photograph would damage the neutrality of this web-sight or otherwise weaken the validity of the information conveyed in this article. There can be no doubting that you have the right to put up this photograph. As a secular agent of free speech this right is instilled by nature. Yet with this in mind i would question wikipedia's moral responsibility toward reverence. Is it right and fair to let everyone know and see everything despite its arguable significance or insignificance; despite how it is viewed, interpreted, used or accepted? I do not know the answer to this but i worry that a bad photograph of a highly respected person (or prophet in my view) does not represent enough information about a person to outweigh the offense it brings to so many. 

For years i have referred people who want to find out about the Bahai faith in a secular and unbiased way to wikipedia. I strongly considered it a good way to find well founded and reverently displayed information on the faith. It saddens me however that i cannot in good conscience do this anymore because this websight, while still being mostly neutral, has become disrespectful. In that sense it has become biased toward all those who feel the way I do. Thank you, i seldom edit or contribute to wikipedia discussions but i felt moved to express my opinion in this instance.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/152.12.241.82|152.12.241.82]] ([[User talk:152.12.241.82|talk]]) 00:18, 14 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:There is a whole article about [[Depictions of Muhammad]], and the page on [[Muhammad]] also caused a continual controversy about his images being in the article, and those are not even photographs. Unfortunately for you, there isn't justification to remove the image of Baha'u'llah. You may wish to review the advice of the House of Justice that &quot;there is little, if anything, that can be done&quot; about removing the image from non-Baha'i websites.  [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 01:50, 14 September 2009 (UTC)

What is justification? For the Baha'is there are no justification to post the image of Baha'u'llah on an official site. But you (the administrators of Wikipedia, I guess) have not recognized the station Baha'u'ullah and am not willing to respect the religious sentiments religious peoples, at least not in this case, and consequently see no justification to remove the image. Justification depends on your ideological and/or religious views.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2.150.51.26|2.150.51.26]] ([[User talk:2.150.51.26|talk]]) 22:22, 22 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot—&gt;
: Ideology and religious views in fact _support_ respecting the rules of organizations often. Does obedience to government, as an example, remind you of something? Being honest and truthful requires acknowledging that the picture is not owned by Baha'is and as the House says &quot;there is little, if anything, that can be done&quot;. But see [[:Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Archive_Picture]] for what has been done. ~~~~

== Categories ==

I removed some categories and was [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bahá%27u%27lláh&amp;curid=129778&amp;diff=321641133&amp;oldid=321122976 reverted] by Koavf. The summary on [[WP:CAT]] says, &quot;Categories are for defining characteristics, and should be specific, neutral, inclusive and follow certain conventions.&quot; Being buried in modern day Israel is in no way a defining characteristic of Bah'u'llah. See also [[WP:OVERCAT]], which says, &quot;However, not every verifiable fact (or the intersection of two or more such facts) in an article requires an associated category. For lengthy articles, this could potentially result in hundreds of categories, most of which aren't particularly relevant. This may also make it more difficult to find any particular category for a specific article. Such overcategorization is also known as &quot;category clutter&quot;. 

The removed categories were... Religious writers, Burials in Israel, People from Acre, People of Ottoman Istanbul, Iranian writers, Deaths from infectious disease, and Messianism.

The categories remaining were... 1817 births, 1892 deaths, People from Tehran, Baha'i central figures, Founders of religions, Iranian Prophets, Manifestations of God in the Baha'i Faith, and Iranian prisoners and detainees. 

Please comment. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 17:52, 24 October 2009 (UTC)
:Some of those seem kind of bizarre to have in categories to begin with. &quot;Iranian writers&quot; and &quot;religious writers&quot; seem fine, they're somewhat significant, but &quot;people of Ottoman Istanbul&quot;? Really? He was there for ''three months''. But hey, I don't know what all the policy is regarding this, that's mostly just my input. [[User:Peter Deer|Peter Deer]] ([[User talk:Peter Deer|talk]]) 00:01, 25 October 2009 (UTC)
:I amended the people from istanbul so it was more timelined at least but I thought it was weird. Koavf has been running categories across many many pages. I just through to tweak to section a bit. He also originally included the category clerics which I dumped. I did think Messianism may apply - at least as well as people from Ottoman Istanbul. But these are just some more comments.[[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 17:29, 25 October 2009 (UTC)
:::'''Categories''' I have re-added many&amp;mdash;but not all of the categories that I originally had with the following justifications:
::::[[:Category:Burials in Israel]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; He has a shrine there. It is not merely coincidence that he is buried in Israel; it is a pilgrimage site.
::::[[:Category:Deaths from infectious disease]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; A common category to add alongside &quot;X deaths&quot;.
::::[[:Category:Iranian prisoners and detainees]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; An important period of his life.
::::''[[:Category:Messianism]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; I did not originally add this category.''
::::[[:Category:People from Acre, Israel]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Again, he lived an important period of his life here, so much so that it's a pilgrimage site. This is not incidental.
::::[[:Category:Religious writers]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; Pretty central to his life's work, as he wrote voluminously about religious topics.
:::I think that these categories are entirely reasonable and to be expected from the explanation I have given above. Please let me know if I am missing something here. —[[User:Koavf|Justin (koavf)]]❤[[User talk:Koavf|T]]☮[[Special:Contributions/Koavf|C]]☺[[Special:Emailuser/Koavf|M]]☯ 06:18, 27 October 2009 (UTC)
:::::While some of the new categories are fine, I'm with the other editors in that most are superfluous.  I'm going to remove some of them again, and it seems to be consensus that most are not fine.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 13:15, 27 October 2009 (UTC)
:::::Messianism doesn't make much sense, and religious writers is superseded by founders of religion. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 16:38, 27 October 2009 (UTC)
::::::In what way does messianism not make much sense? I see it has no entry in [[Messianism]] but that seems like an oversight considering [[Messiah#Other_traditions]], [[Kingdom_of_God#Pre-millennial_approaches]], [[End_time#Bah.C3.A1.27.C3.AD_Faith]], [[Eschatology#Bah.C3.A1.27.C3.AD_eschatology]] not to mention ''but in a broader sense claimed to be a messenger from God referring to the fulfilment of the eschatological expectations of Islam, Christianity, and other major religions.''[[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 00:46, 28 October 2009 (UTC)

'''Two in particular''' I still think that [[:Category:People from Acre, Israel]] is important, considering how he lived there for 24 years, accepted pilgrims there, and the foundations of his religious organization were made there. Both this and his imprisonment are mentioned in the lead, implying that they are significant facts about his life and are consequently worthy of category inclusion. —[[User:Koavf|Justin (koavf)]]❤[[User talk:Koavf|T]]☮[[Special:Contributions/Koavf|C]]☺[[Special:Emailuser/Koavf|M]]☯ 07:59, 28 October 2009 (UTC)
:I'm removing these two again.  The category from Acre can be misinterpreted that the person was born there, and he the Iranian prisoner one was for 4 months, so again not again germane for a category.  I think you are misusing the category tree, and you are the only one who is pushing them, so please abide by consensus.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 13:10, 28 October 2009 (UTC)
::'''What?''' What consensus and how am I &quot;misusing the category tree?&quot; I don't even understand what the latter means. —[[User:Koavf|Justin (koavf)]]❤[[User talk:Koavf|T]]☮[[Special:Contributions/Koavf|C]]☺[[Special:Emailuser/Koavf|M]]☯ 18:36, 28 October 2009 (UTC)

:::If the categories aren't used right they become meaningless. Messianism is only tangentially related, since Messianic movements are waiting for a Messiah. If this category belonged it would go on the Baha'i Faith article, but Baha'is are not waiting for a Messiah, they believe he already came. Shoghi Effendi described Baha'u'llah's claims this way... &quot;the Originator of a new 'Universal Cycle'... To Israel He was neither more nor less than the incarnation of the 'Everlasting Father,' the 'Lord of Hosts' come down 'with ten thousands of saints'; to Christendom Christ returned 'in the glory of the Father,' to Shi`ah Islam the return of the Imam Husayn, to Sunni Islam the descent of the 'Spirit of God' (Jesus Christ); to the Zoroastrians the promised Shah-Bahram; to the Hindus the reincarnation of Krishna; to the Buddhists the fifth Buddha...  &quot;
:::Adding Category:Messianism tends to imply a Jewish or Christian context, which ignores the broader claims. The only categories necessary are Cat:Baha'u'llah, Cat:Founders of religion, Cat:People from Tehran, and birth/death years. See the [[KISS principle]] for instructions. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:39, 28 October 2009 (UTC)
::::I accept the KISS principle and the explanation of Messianism - it would require a redefinition I suppose. A well. [[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 23:51, 28 October 2009 (UTC)
:::::'''Okay''' I was never arguing in favor of [[:Category:Messianism]]. —[[User:Koavf|Justin (koavf)]]❤[[User talk:Koavf|T]]☮[[Special:Contributions/Koavf|C]]☺[[Special:Emailuser/Koavf|M]]☯ 05:18, 29 October 2009 (UTC)
::::::Justin, you keep on adding extra categories, while everyone else who has commented here including Peter Deer, Smkolins, Cunado, and myself, don't believe they are germane.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 05:43, 29 October 2009 (UTC)
:::::::'''No''' Smkolins was arguing ''for'' [[:Category:Messianism]]. —[[User:Koavf|Justin (koavf)]]❤[[User talk:Koavf|T]]☮[[Special:Contributions/Koavf|C]]☺[[Special:Emailuser/Koavf|M]]☯ 06:08, 29 October 2009 (UTC)
::::::::Have you seen me remove Messianism, it's the other ones that are problematic, and you keep adding with complete disregard of comments.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 13:17, 29 October 2009 (UTC)

===Prisoner===
Perhaps this cat [[:Category:Prisoners and detainees of the Ottoman Empire]] is better than the 'Iranian prisoners' one. One of the problems with the Iran one is that it doesn't differentiate the pre- and post-modern countries. The Iran of today didn't exist during Baha'u'llah's time, geographically or politically. [[User:Cuñado|&lt;font color=&quot;#AF7817&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] ☼ - [[User talk:Cuñado|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 05:48, 29 October 2009 (UTC)
:'''Sure''' That may make more sense. The fact that he was a detainee is clearly an important part of his biography (again, it is mentioned in the lead.) —[[User:Koavf|Justin (koavf)]]❤[[User talk:Koavf|T]]☮[[Special:Contributions/Koavf|C]]☺[[Special:Emailuser/Koavf|M]]☯ 06:08, 29 October 2009 (UTC)



PLEASE REMOVE THE PICTURE OF BAHA'U'LLAH FROM THIS PAGE, AS A BAHA'I I WAS SHOCKED TO SEE IT AND AM EXTREMELY UPSET. IF THIS IS REALLY A PHOTO OF OUR PROPHET, PLEASE RESPECT OUR BELIEFS AND TAKE IT DOWN.

VERONICA YANAKA - 7/21/2010  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.44.125.196|69.44.125.196]] ([[User talk:69.44.125.196|talk]]) 18:58, 21 July 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Vernonica, your concerns have been echoed for years. If you'll look at [[Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/Photo]] you'll see a long discussion about it. [[User:Smkolins|Smkolins]] ([[User talk:Smkolins|talk]]) 19:32, 21 July 2010 (UTC)

== mirza nuri ==
Isn't mirza nuri the first name and surname of baha'ullah? If so, should husain ali (his middle names) be put out of bold letters?[[User:Iwanttoeditthissh|Iwanttoeditthissh]] ([[User talk:Iwanttoeditthissh|talk]]) 08:39, 15 May 2010 (UTC)

:Persian names don't work quite like that - without going into details. --[[User:Soundofmusicals|Soundofmusicals]] ([[User talk:Soundofmusicals|talk]]) 08:55, 15 May 2010 (UTC)
::I'll go into details. '[[Mirza]]' in this instance is more of a title, denoting that He was a member of the Persian nobility, and 'Nuri' means 'of [[Noor, Iran|Nur]]', where His family was from. In reality, Hussein Ali, informally, is His name, not &quot;Mirza Nuri&quot; as western naming conventions would imply. Thus, it's closer to meaning &quot;Sir Hussain Ali of Nur&quot; than the first and last being names. [[User:Peter Deer|Peter Deer]] ([[User talk:Peter Deer|talk]]) 20:35, 15 May 2010 (UTC)

:::Yes, that is correct Peter Deer. The &quot;i&quot; stands for belonging to something. A bahá'í is a follower of bahá, a bábí is a follower of Báb, etc. And, after consulting a lot of books, if the name had been Hussain Ali Nuri Mirza, the meaning had been ''prince Hussain Ali from the province Nur''. Nowadays Iranians use the same order as in West: Forename Surname.--[[User:Caspiax|Caspiax]] ([[User talk:Caspiax|talk]]) 14:30, 26 July 2011 (UTC)

== Instructions for editing one's css ==

I know that it is possible for a registered editor to add a line to their &quot;css&quot; page that will block a particular image, such as the picture of Bahaullah, from being displayed to themselves. I suspect that some editors would like to have the instructions for doing so displayed in a convenient place on this talk page. Could someone write up the instructions as a FAQ (&quot;How can I block the photograph of Bahá'u'lláh from being displayed to myself?&quot;) and add it to the top of this Talk page? (Not being a Bahai, I personally don't need to have the image blocked for myself, but I think it would be sensible to make it easy for people to avoid having the image displayed to themselves.) --[[User:Metropolitan90|Metropolitan90]] [[User talk:Metropolitan90|(talk)]] 02:39, 21 August 2010 (UTC)

:No, I'm pretty sure it isn't possible. One have to change the [[JavaScript]] (&quot;js&quot;) page writing some code finding images &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/wiki/File:Bahaullah_from_miller.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt; and similar, and then replace them with any image of a personal choice, f.ex. &quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/38/Zeichen_101.svg/80px-Zeichen_101.svg.png&quot;&quot; (Just an example). [[User:Rursus|Rursus]] dixit. ([[User talk:Rursus|&lt;span style=&quot;color: red; background: #FFFF80&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;u&gt;bork&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]!) 11:23, 7 January 2011 (UTC)

== Multiplicity of Wives ==

I enjoyed reading the apologia about the polygamy in the Baha'i Faith, and wonder if would not be appropriate to find a mention of how the subject was handled in Africa when teaching the Baha'i Faith there, which was, that when a man with multiple wives became a Baha'i, no separation or divorce was required, but he could not take another wife.  So, there would be Baha'i families in Africa with multiple wives if the marriage happened before conversion or declaration.
I'm guessing that the reference would be in Lights of Guidance.I'm Nonpartisan 17:11, 7 March 2011 (UTC)

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bah%C3%A1%27u%27ll%C3%A1h%27s_family#Bah.C3.A1.27.C3.AD_apologia  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:I'm nonpartisan|I'm nonpartisan]] ([[User talk:I'm nonpartisan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/I'm nonpartisan|contribs]]) 17:11, 7 March 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:: That seems like it should perhaps be in the [[Baha'i Marriage]] article. [[User:Peter Deer|Peter Deer]] ([[User talk:Peter Deer|talk]]) 15:58, 7 May 2012 (UTC)

== No mention? ==

By the time that Iranians were getting ready to tear down the very foundation of Qajar monarchy in the course of the Constitutional Revolution, Baha'ullah officially sided with Mohammad Ali Shah. His son and successor Abd al-Baha went even further and was knighted by George V and under the British Mandate established the center of his vanity in Haifa.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.80.104.182|24.80.104.182]] ([[User talk:24.80.104.182|talk]]) 09:42, 28 April 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Click on this link [[Political accusations against the Baha'i Faith|Baha'i Faith and Irani Politics]] where this kind of thing is thoroughly discussed.

:I might point out that the Shah you mention was, like most Persian rulers (including the present ones), an enthusiatic if not rabid persecutor of Baha'is, and most certainly never received any &quot;endorsement&quot; from any Baha'i source - and that [[‘Abdu’l-Bahá]] WAS knighted during the British mandate (shortly before he died) for philanthropic work in Haifa during the First World War - at the time he had already been in Haifa for many years having been specifically and deliberately exiled there by the then Shah of Iran and Sultan of Turkey. --[[User:Soundofmusicals|Soundofmusicals]] ([[User talk:Soundofmusicals|talk]]) 14:26, 21 May 2011 (UTC)

== Previous revert ==

I reverted the previous edit for the following reason.  The edit claimed that Baha'u'llah claimed to be God, and that is only partly true.  Baha'u'llah claimed that he was a [[Manifestation of God]], which at times as the station of God, and at times the station of humanity.  Even within certain of his writings he can be seen writing in both voices, such as the [[Summons of the Lord of Hosts]].  This evening when I have more time, I will write a section on it based on multiple secondary sources, and not hand-picking certain primary sources from the previous edit.  I will also include the single secondary source from the previous edit.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 15:25, 1 September 2011 (UTC)

{{Talk:Bahá'u'lláh/GA1}}

== Allegedly ==

Just a note about [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bah%C3%A1%27u%27ll%C3%A1h&amp;curid=28361679&amp;diff=495167145&amp;oldid=493627143 this]. What I want is to get rid of the word &quot;allegedly&quot; per [[WP:ALLEGED]]. Insead of saying &quot;His ancestry can allegedly be traced...&quot; we should attribute the view to whoever is saying it can be traced. For instance, &quot;Baha'i's say that his ancestry can be traced...&quot; The word &quot;allegedly&quot; needs to go. I'd make the change myself, but I'm not familiar enough with the sources to know who's making the claim. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:10.2pt&quot;&gt;~[[User:Adjwilley|Adjwilley]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:7pt&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Adjwilley|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 15:11, 31 May 2012 (UTC)

== Return to Baghdad section ==

The &quot;Return to Baghdad&quot; section seems a little out of order to me. The first paragraph talks about conditions in Baghdad before his return. The second paragraph talks about what he did when he got there, how he rose in status and then got exiled. The third paragraph starts out saying that he lived in Baghdad for 7 years and then talks about what he wrote while he was there. This strikes me as being out of chronological order, but I don't know enough about the subject to fix it. I think the section should end with the exile to Constantinople. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:10.2pt&quot;&gt;~[[User:Adjwilley|Adjwilley]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:7pt&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Adjwilley|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 02:14, 6 June 2012 (UTC)
:The third paragraph is (I think) not meant to be part of the history of that section, but viewing that time in terms of the way Baha'is see his station during that time.  I've deleted some of the text, and moved some of it to the works section.  Regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 05:07, 6 June 2012 (UTC)

== My changes==
I appreciate Adjwilley's changes to the article, and they are definitely improvements.  I have, however, reverted some of the edits which I document below, and the reasoning for them:
#I have reinserted the word ''radical'' to describe the group of Babis who planned the assassination.  The same description is used in the source, and it is important to note that it was a divergent group of Babis, and not the general ones who had that sort of militancy.
#I have added who initiated the violent protests (the government) as it was not organic.
#Added back &quot;While the Báb eliminated the institution of successorship or vicegerency to his movement&quot; because eliminating successorship is quite different that not appointing a successor, and it is well referenced.
I have also tried to fix the &quot;messenger&quot; clarification, and hope it is clearer now.

In regards to some of the comments on the GA sub-page.  The term &quot;Him who God shall make manifest&quot; is sometimes abreviated as HWGSMM.  The acronym could be introduced in the first use and used later on, though I'm not personally a big fan of such acronym usage.
I hope the above explains my changes.  Warm regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 05:07, 6 June 2012 (UTC)
:Thank you. I was hoping that somebody would see the changes and correct me where I went wrong.  I also dislike acronyms and think HWGSMM would not be an improvement. Is there a layman's term that would also work? I think I saw &quot;Promised One&quot; being used at one point. &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:10.2pt&quot;&gt;~[[User:Adjwilley|Adjwilley]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&quot;font-family:times; font-size:7pt&quot;&gt;([[User talk:Adjwilley|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:15, 6 June 2012 (UTC)
::The term ''promised one'' could work.  Warm regards, -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] ([[User talk:Jeff3000|talk]]) 18:28, 6 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tirupdmayd6oylttdd1rb4uhqurpl4o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
