<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Jehovah's Witnesses</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>59005</id>
    <revision>
      <id>521938871</id>
      <parentid>521937380</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-11-08T03:21:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jeffro77</username>
        <id>522013</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Failed predictions wording */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40438">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{controversial}}
{{not a forum}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=23:44, 28 June 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Jehovah's Witnesses/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=61091279

|action2=FAC
|action2date=11:18, 6 July 2006
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Jehovah's Witnesses/archive1
|action2result=not promoted
|action2oldid=62348431

|action3=PR
|action3date=03:55, 11 December 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Jehovah's Witnesses/archive2
|action3result=reviewed
|action3oldid=257166622

|action4=GAN
|action4date=02:49, 31 July 2011
|action4link=Talk:Jehovah's Witnesses/GA1
|action4result=listed
|action4oldid=442290939

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=philrelig
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Christianity |class=GA |importance=Top
 |jehovah's-witnesses=yes |jehovah's-witnesses-importance=Top
 |core-topics-work-group = yes |core-topics-importance=Top
}}
{{WikiProject Religion |class=GA |importance=Top|NRM=yes |NRMImp=Top}}
{{WP1.0 |v0.5=pass |class=GA |importance=high |category=Philrelig }}
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 300K
|counter = 58
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(14d)
|archive = Talk:Jehovah's Witnesses/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes
}}
{{Archive box |bot=MiszaBot I |age=2 |units=weeks |search=yes |root=Talk:Jehovah's Witnesses |auto=yes |index=/Archive index}}

== Intro - wording clarification on who is &quot;shunned&quot; ==

The following might be changed to add the word &quot;baptized members&quot;. Unbaptized members, unbaptized publishers are included in the numbers of Jehovah's Witnesses, in other words, they are &quot;members,&quot; included in the yearbook figure, are not shunned if they leave for any reason. 

This is the line:
Members who formally leave are considered disassociated and are also shunned. Disfellowshipped and disassociated individuals may eventually be reinstated if deemed repentant.

Should more accurately read, 
Baptized members who formally leave are considered disassociated and are also shunned. Disfellowshipped and disassociated individuals may eventually be reinstated if deemed repentant. [[User:Naturalpsychology|Natural]] ([[User talk:Naturalpsychology|talk]]) 09:47, 30 August 2012 (UTC)Natural

:You're right. I changed it. '''Unbaptised publishers''', '''Students of the 'Bible Study' courses''', '''Associates''', '''irregular public visitors''' and '''others''' cannot be shunned at any way. However, unpaptised publishers and associates can temporarily loose some spiritual 'privileges' in congregation's agenda. For example, they can loose ((after 'private reproof by an elder', and after repeating serious sin without remorseful deeds)) possibility to performing on stage and reading or dissertate during the 'Theocratic Ministry School'. They can also lost possibility/privilege (voluntarily taken deeds) like going with other congregation's members to the Ministry (preaching, evangelizing). That are only possible actions on them. (Only if they already have had these privileges). Someone of members might no longer want to talk with them. (on religious topics). But certainly no official shunning or disassociating on those can be taken. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 18:52, 31 August 2012 (UTC)

::Thanks for concurrence on that. 
::Similarly, this line, 

::::Baptized individuals who formally leave are considered disassociated and are also shunned.

::The word &quot;leave&quot; and even &quot;formally leave&quot; can have many connotations. It might imply that anyone who leaves Jehovah's Witnesses and doesn't come back is shunned. Perhaps a clarification in the wording here also would more accurately state the idea the article is trying to convey. 

::Something like, 
:::Baptized individuals who formally disassociate themselves from being one of Jehovah's Witnesses are also shunned. 
[[User:Naturalpsychology|Natural]] ([[User talk:Naturalpsychology|talk]]) 11:14, 2 September 2012 (UTC)Natural
::::The JW term ''disassociation'' refers to not only those who ''choose'' to formally resign, but also to a person whom the Watch Tower Society leaders imagine has taken some action they imagine indicates the person to longer be a member, such as accepting a blood transfusion, attending another church, or having a birthday party (oh, the horror). The ''current'' wording is ''only just'' accurate enough; the suggested wording is less accurate.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 11:45, 2 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::Although I need to agree that meaning of &quot;formally leave&quot; is ambiguous for unknowing readers. In fact, it is a JW jargon. Even neither I do not know precisely what it means, or at least, what shall be suggested meaning by authors. We need to explain there what &quot;formally leave&quot; actually means or we need to change it to something clearly understandable. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 13:13, 4 September 2012 (UTC)

Long version here::::: Baptised individuals/members ... “who forsake/forsook fellow believers community and religious organization of Jehovah's Witnesses, or who runs afoul (=gets into mismatch) with/to (= by means of words or deeds) an order and regulations based on congregation's understanding of the Bible.”... are also shunned. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 13:49, 4 September 2012 (UTC)
:Anything similar to 'forsake' or 'afoul' is a POV judgement.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 15:02, 4 September 2012 (UTC)
::Maybe only for Aussie. Per Google Translate it is precise language without bias. ... You can suggest different wording. I already wrote in edit summary that this sentence shouldn't be considered as suggested wording. Rather as first try to exposure meaning of the phrase &quot;formally leave&quot;. Better to focus on changing current ambiguous wording in article. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 16:10, 4 September 2012 (UTC)
:::I see no ambiguity. The Jehovah's Witnesses may adopt a legalistic approach to deciding who members are and are not permitted to speak to, but it is sufficient for an encyclopedia to say that a person formally leaves or resigns from the religion. The concept of ''formally'' leaving (as opposed to just ceasing association) requires no lengthy description. [[User:BlackCab|BlackCab]] ([[User talk:BlackCab|talk]]) 22:25, 4 September 2012 (UTC)
::::The word &quot;formally&quot; is indeed unclear what it is going on. There is a need for thorough description. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 05:03, 5 September 2012 (UTC)
::::Instead of &quot;leave&quot;, what is unclear too (leave from what, leave from whom, for how long time, how much seriously, etc.), we can use appropriate synonym (give up, relinquish, forsake, abandon, quit, desert, drop). --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 05:03, 5 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::I do not agree that the current wording needs to be changed. Aside from that, most of the alternatives offered have negative connotations&amp;mdash;''give up'', ''forsake'', ''abandon'', ''desert'' in particular are certainly too judgemental. ''If'' there is broader agreement that there is an issue of ''clarity'', then that might warrant a ''longer'' explanation, but would not justify replacing one potentially ambiguous term with a different ambiguous term that has negative implications.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 07:51, 5 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::Can you specify any proves about negative connotations of those words? For example, [&quot;formally leave&quot;] replacing with [&quot;officially abandon&quot;] ... ['its community, beliefs, and the religious organization.'] ... Is it negative? No, it isn't. &lt;sup&gt;Because word 'leave' seems to be time-temporary term instead of more definitive words like 'forsake', 'quit', 'drop', and 'relinquish' ... which they have no negative connotations.&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sub&gt;I can agree that 'give up' and 'desert' might have some negative connotations. But negative convey is only imagined here. For example, a word 'defector' (a noun) has same meaning like these similar words (verbs): ['fall away', 'drop out', 'drop off', 'omit', 'neglect'].&lt;/sub&gt; I think that word ['formally'/'officially'] is in fact unnecessary there, because as we already discussed that [informal/unofficial] [leave/abandon] is not reason for shunning baptised/baptized members. See previous talk threads. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 14:47, 5 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::We must be alert to [[wikt:connotation|connotation]]. Words such as &quot;forsake&quot;, &quot;relinquish&quot;, and &quot;desert&quot; imply that something/someone of value has been left, which wouldn't be neutral. The article lede's use of &quot;formally&quot; was intended to distinguish from &quot;informally leave&quot; (that is, merely becoming inactive); while &quot;formally leave&quot; is imperfect, the expression seems superior to any of the suggested alternatives. I don't believe it's necessary, but any additional explanation would be better parked in the article body rather than further bloating the lede. I've never felt that the sentence ''&quot;Baptized individuals who formally leave are considered disassociated and are also shunned.&quot;'' improves the lede, and would support its removal. Of course, I don't believe that those who feel differently should be threatened with being &quot;reported&quot;. --&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid black;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:AuthorityTam|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#ffffff;background:black;&quot;&gt;AuthorityTam&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;font style=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]][[Special:Contributions/AuthorityTam|…contrib]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 15:46, 5 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::OK. Maybe. I don't make a fuss here. So what about this: ''Baptized individuals who officially resign &lt;del&gt;[abdicate on theirs membership]&lt;/del&gt; and leave from its community and from religious organization of Jehovah's Witnesses, are considered ''disassociated'' and are also shunned &lt;del&gt;as part of [[social exclusion]], [[ostracism]], [[social rejection]], commonly practised by most social, and especially religious, groups.&lt;/del&gt; Baptized individuals which gets into mismatch with an order and regulations based on congregation's rules are typically disfellowshipped and disassociated, and are also shunned. Individuals may eventually be reinstated if deemed repentant.'' .... repair it for grammar and style, if needed, before placing in the article. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 16:30, 5 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::Forgive my guess, but I'm guessing that English is a second language for [[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]]. The current wording in the article lede is:
::::::::::* &lt;small&gt;Congregational disciplinary actions include disfellowshipping, their term for formal expulsion and shunning.[21] Baptized individuals who formally leave are considered disassociated and are also shunned. Disfellowshipped and disassociated individuals may eventually be reinstated if deemed repentant.&lt;/small&gt;
::::::::::That current wording seems superior to recent suggestions. I cannot agree to 'placing in the article' any of what FakTNeviM has just suggested. --&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid black;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:AuthorityTam|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#ffffff;background:black;&quot;&gt;AuthorityTam&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;font style=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:AuthorityTam|talk]][[Special:Contributions/AuthorityTam|…contrib]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 17:34, 5 September 2012 (UTC)

::::::::::::Why not put a footnote to explain what the ambiguous term &quot;formally leave&quot; means.
:::::::::::::e.g. Baptized members &quot;formally leave&quot; Jehovah's Witnesses when writing a letter to the local congregation stating that they no longer wish to be one of Jehovah's Witnesses and to remove their names from the congregation. 
::::::::::::::Anyone who has a question about that term can read the footnote. [[User:Naturalpsychology|Natural]] ([[User talk:Naturalpsychology|talk]]) 10:08, 12 September 2012 (UTC)Natural
:::::::::::::::That might be appropriate, but only if actions ''other'' than a letter of resignation that are also considered to constitute 'formally leaving' (e.g. accepting a blood transfusing, attending another church or celebrating Christmas) were addressed separately.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 10:12, 12 September 2012 (UTC)

@Jeffro77
That is why I previously suggested '''2 sentences'''.
''Baptized individuals who officially resign &lt;del&gt;[abdicate on theirs membership]&lt;/del&gt; and leave from its community and from religious organization of Jehovah's Witnesses, are considered ''disassociated'' and are also shunned.
''Baptized individuals which gets into mismatch with an order and regulations based on congregation's rules are typically disfellowshipped and disassociated, and are also shunned. Individuals may eventually be reinstated if deemed repentant.''

--[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 18:35, 16 September 2012 (UTC)
:I suggested over a month ago that 2 sentences may be warranted.[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AJehovah%27s_Witnesses&amp;diff=506704235&amp;oldid=506694309] However, the existing wording is probably sufficient ''for the lead'', but could possibly be more clearly stated in the body of the article (don't have time to look into this closely right now).--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 08:22, 17 September 2012 (UTC)
::Thus we have some consensus on writing 2 separate sentences. ... &lt;u&gt;First one&lt;/u&gt; would cover those who 'formally leave'. It should be explained in a &lt;u&gt;footnote&lt;/u&gt; what does it stands for common reader. &lt;u&gt;Second one&lt;/u&gt; would cover those who 'break JWs laws or Bible laws in some way and continue without show genuine repentance'. There is many ways how to describe this second group of those who are shunned. I already suggested more different variants of wording, and they were refused so far. Although style and grammar were wrong in some way, meaning is likely understandable. &lt;u&gt;Can YOU, or whoever else, offer actual text of those 2 sentences, please?&lt;/u&gt; &lt;small&gt;(First sentence should be easier, because we can use footnote next to phrase 'formally leave')&lt;/small&gt; It is clear that two different groups of apostates/defectors/deserters are shunned and we need to add that both information into a lede of the article. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 16:46, 17 September 2012 (UTC)
:::I support two sentences&amp;mdash;or a ''single sentence that makes both points''&amp;mdash;''in the body'', though I don't think this is necessary ''in the lead''; also, I'm not sure my agreement necessarily constitutes broader ''consensus'', which needs input from other editors. I don't believe a ''footnote'' would be required; the sentence in the main text should be worded so that it is sufficient for 'the common reader'. It would not be appropriate to make POV claims about supposed 'Bible laws', as interpretations of scripture are highly subjective.
:::The sentence already in the lead suitably describes the situation regarding those who formally leave. The relevant sentence in the body of the article could be replaced with something like, ''Members who ''disassociate'' by writing letters of resignation, or who are considered by elders to have ''disassociated'' through some other action (such as attending another church's services or accepting a blood transfusion) are described in Watch Tower Society literature as wicked and are also shunned.''.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 08:02, 18 September 2012 (UTC)

::::The reference to shunning in the lead section needs no further elaboration. Jeffro's suggested wording for the body of the article is good, though in fact it still doesn't cover all eventualities. ''Shepherd the Flock of God'' (pages 110-112) spells out that a person is deemed disassociated if they:
::::(a) ''make known'' a desire to be known no longer as a JW (preferably in writing, though a verbal statement is acceptable if heard by more than one witness); 
::::(b) join another religious organization and intend remaining with it; 
::::(c)  willingly and unrepentantly take blood; 
::::(d) join or work for a non-neutral organization.
::::Yet this is clearly not an exhaustive list: the elders' handbook says those factors are only ''included'' among possible actions that indicate disassociation. A slight amendment to Jeffro's suggested wording then is: &quot;Members who ''disassociate'' with a statement of resignation, or who are considered by elders to have ''disassociated'' through some other action (such as joining another religious organization or accepting a blood transfusion) are described in Watch Tower Society literature as wicked and are also shunned.&quot; The first part of the sentence covers the concept of taking a &quot;formal&quot; action (that is, explicit and definite); the second covers the unilateral decision of local elders that a person has themselves demonstrated they are no longer willing to conform with church doctrines and is thus deemed disassociated. [[User:BlackCab|BlackCab]] ([[User talk:BlackCab|talk]]) 12:33, 18 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::BlackCab's change regarding joining another church is better, as a JW wouldn't necessarily be shunned for attending a ''single'' service at another church. (''Members/a statement of resignation'' isn't strictly correct grammar.)--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 08:08, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::His (BlackCab's) notice was actually much more informative and valuable than yours. // The same what I told to AuthorityTam also goes for you. Whether someone is 'English-speaking country-born' or he isn't, such sort of 'grammar bullying' could be deemed as disruptive behaviour and would lead to be reported per [[WP:Civility]]. If some sentences are wrong by grammar or style, '''it is more valuable to just correct it''' instead of shouting on other person 'you are stupid'. Even native-born/immigrant/second-generation immigrant/foreign-learner could make mistake. Even if English is someone' 'first language', not everybody has 'A mark' from that subject during school's attendance. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 00:50, 21 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::::BlackCab's wording is only slightly different to mine. Irrespective of the ''specific words'' you chose, your suggested wording ''didn't benefit the article''. It is a false claim that your edits were reverted merely on the basis of poor wording. Your further claim that anyone has called you 'stupid' is untrue. No one 'expects' every editor to be good a particular language; however, a person who is editing in a second language would probably benefit if they paid attention when native speakers suggest something about English wording rather than taking it as an 'attack'.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 04:22, 22 September 2012 (UTC)
::::::::I commented your grammar comment to BlackCab's notice what actions lead to disassociating. // We still do not solve that two issues: How to explain to common reader terms/jargon like 'formally leave' and sentence which should cover those who break JWs laws without genuine repentance. Suggestion? --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 05:28, 22 September 2012 (UTC)

'''btw:''' wikilinks to [[social exclusion]], [[ostracism]], [[social rejection]] were written only for editors' interest here. Shunning in way in which is practised by JWs is nothing new, and is commonly practised by most social, and especially religious, groups. I am ''not'' suggesting to placing these sociological studies' terms to the article.

''about AuthorityTam's response:'' He and everyone else here already known that English is not my mother tongue. His comment seemed like that he imagined that I am now apostate and worthy of his shunning. = Indeed ... Laughing laud and Exceptionally funny. But his refusal tone completely lacked assuming good faith in the subject of rewording. In fact, I only agreed with Naturalpsychology's notice that &quot;formally leave&quot; is unclear statement for JWs-matters unknowledgeable readers (=most of Wikipedia readers). However, after AuthorityTam's irrelevant comment I lost eagerness about this thread.

--[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 18:35, 16 September 2012 (UTC)

== Sociological analysis ==

I was reading this section and was puzzled by some of the wording under the Pew Research Center information.
I clicked on the Pew Research link and from reading the actual site's wording I had a better understanding of some of their research questions.
I would like to have some wording changed so readers of Wikipedia might also understand this better.
The sentence &quot;belief that their religion can only be interpreted one way and that theirs is the only true religion&quot; can be misunderstood.  The actual site has two different questions, &quot;My religion is the one, true faith leading to eternal life&quot; and
&quot;There is only ONE true way to interpret the teachings of my religion.&quot;
I would think to use this site's wording as much as possible would be clearer.
I would like this sentence changed to &quot;....,belief their religion is the one true faith leading to eternal life, belief there is only one true way to interpret the teachings of their religion,..... 

The Research site also provides a pie chart of the data http://religions.pewforum.org/portraits   Then click Select a Tradition. --[[User:Saujad|Saujad]] ([[User talk:Saujad|talk]]) 09:19, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
:I'm not sure your suggested change really alters the meaning. Apart from minor aspects of reversing the order of the two statements and separating the two aspects with a comma, the only other real difference is adding the part about 'eternal life'. Though that aspect could probably be added, I'm not sure it really adds much to the significance of a belief about 'only true religion', as some hope of 'afterlife' (or in some cases, at least being more accepting of death) is generally the point of most religious beliefs anyway. I'll see what other editors think.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 09:35, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
:@Saujad: Personally I think that there isn't any real difference in meaning. However, I made some changes and additions into [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jehovah%27s_Witnesses#Sociological_analysis that section]. Look this [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jehovah%27s_Witnesses&amp;diff=513574789&amp;oldid=513566532 diff]. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 18:53, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
::I have removed some entries that were not actually the highest in the statistics presented by the source; selecting only some details for results that are not actually high''est'' and low''est'' quickly becomes subjective. The claim about JWs having higher concern for the environment than other groups doesn't seem to have any basis in the cited source&amp;mdash;the source actually suggests that fewer JWs expressed that environmental protection is worth the cost than most of the groups surveyed (9 out of 15 groups were higher, and 2 were equal), and they had the highest result for not responding to the question.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 09:15, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
:::'''1)''' Respondents answers in question about 'Environmental protection' are quite fuzzy, because raised question is named ' ''Views About Environmental Protection'' Among Jehovah's Witnesses' while actual possibilities to answer on it are asking for ''environmental laws and regulations'' and not for subject 'protection of the climate' itself. So sorry about that. That was my fault. '''2)''' Homosexuality' and Abortion' questions are answered in by means of ''should be discouraged by society'' thus I replaced word 'opposition to' for more precise word 'discouraging to'. JWs are not 'activists' at all. They are not in opposition to anything or anyone out there. Word 'discourage' is supported by the survey' source. '''3)''' Bible views as a genuine Word of God is in question named 'Literal Interpretation of Scripture Among Jehovah's Witnesses', in which respondents mark off possibilities 'Word of God, literally true word for word' and 'Word of God, but not literally true word for word'. Whether most of them support literal word by word or not, 'only 8 %' JWs marked off other two possibilities. 92 % is by far highest proportion among religions surveyed there. '''//// 4)''' 2nd highest proportion in 'Lower income' could be placed ''too''. Although I am not sure if earning between 30 000 to 75 000 USD should be considered as someone is a poor one. And I have a suspicion if other groups' claiming are 'true', because some respondents 'could lie' in this particular question in aim to higher reputation of their religion. In every case, JWs have 'very low proportion' only in possibilities 75 000+ and 100 000+. 18 % is actually not low, but an 'average proportion' expected within 'general US population' in these very high earnings. '''//// 5)''' I don't think that placing 'very high' and 'very low' proportion is banned. Even if the proportion is not actually 'the highest' and 'the lowest', it is possible to placing such criteria there. It is suitable especially if there is considerably gap in compare with other religious groups. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 00:33, 21 September 2012 (UTC)
::::2) I think 'opposition' carries the thought well enough, but it could be changed to something else; maybe someone else can suggest something. 'Discouraging to' is very awkward wording. No form of 'activism' is necessary for someone to be opposed to something, and JWs don't really merely 'discourage' abortion or homosexuality, which both carry religious sanctions within the group. 3) The claim about JWs having 'by far the highest' is not true. Only 8% of Mormon respondents answered similarly to the other two questions as well. 4) What basis do you have for the claim that respondents of ''other'' groups might ''lie'' about their income; I suppose you don't think any of the JWs would lie though. 5) Not 'banned', but it becomes much more subjective if only some 'high but not highest' aspects of the survey are highlighted.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 04:16, 22 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::I suppose that Mormons had [Holy Book] replaced with 'Book of Mormon' or more directly with quad-books set named 'Standard Works' which includes the Bible. At least Muslims had replaced with Quran. Some other results of the survey are absurd too. There is a notice under graphic tables about Holy Book is replaced for particular religion. Though, this discussion becomes irrelevant. I agree with your explanation that other not highest aspects shouldn't be highlighted in the article. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 05:20, 22 September 2012 (UTC)

Looks better Jeffro77, the old version of the combination of two completely separate questions made it unclear. --[[User:Saujad|Saujad]] ([[User talk:Saujad|talk]]) 09:05, 22 September 2012 (UTC)

== Failed predictions wording ==

I also found the statement under the subject &quot;Failed Predictions&quot; not quite accurate. The statement, &quot;It says that unlike Old Testament prophets, its interpretations of the Bible are not inspired or infallible&quot;  
Generally the Witnesses as well as the Society very much believe their &quot;interpretations of the Bible&quot; are an absolute in many areas, such as their understanding of Bible's use of soul, hell and other teachings.  It is more understood that its writings or publications are not inspired or infallible as the references used as proofs in this sentence states.  Their statements about the end is also understood as not inspired.  I believe changing this to &quot;its printed material are not inspired or infallible&quot;  might fit better.--[[User:Saujad|Saujad]] ([[User talk:Saujad|talk]]) 09:05, 22 September 2012 (UTC)

:Though there are a few core doctrines that haven't changed, most of their beliefs&amp;mdash;including their core eschatology&amp;mdash;has had significant changes. Any JW belief can be changed by the leadership at any time as 'new light'. It is therefore inaccurate to suggest that their interpretations of the Bible are considered absolute.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 16:28, 22 September 2012 (UTC)
::He tried to mention that core doctrines like rejecting Trinity dogma, rejecting Immortality of the soul, rejection of Hell-fire, and few of other teachings remain unchanged for more than Century. Thus we can call it like &quot;...'absolutely true' Present Truth...&quot; teachings of JWs. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 16:45, 22 September 2012 (UTC)
:::It's a fairly arbitrary distinction you're trying to make. They used the cross up until the 1930s, so up until then that could be considered a core doctrine as well. If we were having this conversation in 1931, you would probably include the cross in your list of &quot;'absolutely true' Present Truth&quot;.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 01:14, 23 September 2012 (UTC)
::::I am not trying anything. I just explained you what I understood from Saujad's comment. Anyway, using/banning symbol of a cross within worship was never one of most important doctrines for JWs. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 14:29, 23 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::It certainly is a prominent belief of JWs (now) that Jesus did not die on a cross. You're defining 'important' doctrines as ''the ones that haven't changed'', which is circular reasoning.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 08:00, 24 September 2012 (UTC)
:I partially included Saujad objection into that article section. It isn't limited to 'printed' materials, but covers all 'published' (I guess such word could help cover spoken as well as written 'data') --- 'released' by JWs Governing Body' members, --- and by some its Committees (especially 'The Teaching Committee','The Writing Committee','The Governing Body'). Note: 'The Publishing Committee' is responsible only for 'physical printing' on machines and cannot change provided content. Note: These all branches of [[WTBTS]] are in use just since 1970's and continuously 'develop' and 'adapt' its purpose and work to go. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 16:45, 22 September 2012 (UTC)
::Saujad's objection was incorrect. Many current JW interpretations are quite different from the beliefs of either Russell or Rutherford. The current wording ''its interpretations of the Bible are not inspired or infallible'' is accurate and implicitly refers to any of their teachings whether they are spoken or in print. Elaboration about the various committees in the JW organisational structure is not necessary here.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 01:14, 23 September 2012 (UTC)
:::Elaboration was intended to Saujad and every other unknowledgeable person. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 14:29, 23 September 2012 (UTC)
:::But you deleted part of citation from source. I restored it, and modified in a purpose common reader would easier understand. --[[User:FakTNeviM|FakTNeviM]] ([[User talk:FakTNeviM|talk]]) 14:29, 23 September 2012 (UTC)
::::I didn't delete any ''citations''. However, there is no evidence that OT 'prophets' ever ''actually'' received 'revelations' either, and it doesn't really add anything to the point that JWs don't consider their current teachings to be 'infallible' (though they can only be 'corrected' by the GB). (Their belief that ''Bible writers'' were 'inspired' [by some unstated mechanism] is already covered in the ''Sources of doctrine'' section.)--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 08:00, 24 September 2012 (UTC)

All the references supplied with this sentence are concerning only Witnesses viewpoints on when the End (Armageddon) would occur.  I still believe to insert &quot;interpretation of the Bible&quot; is too general and misleading.  It would appear from this that they don't have strong convictions on their interpretations, which is inaccurate. One reference says concerning mistaken viewpoints of the End are &quot;relatively minor when compared with the vital Bible truths that they have discerned and publicized.&quot; 
I would like to add an example: Billy Graham will his long years as a minister may over time had a changed viewpoint over a specific scripture or even a change over a minor subject but this does not mean he was a change in his theology or how he interprets the Bible.   His core religious beliefs have not changed over the years and he is very firm on his teachings.

I noticed some talk concerning Witnesses' written material vs. oral material.  The written material IS the beliefs of Jehovah's Witnesses. Information giving in a talk is always suppose to be from written material or in the case of an Assembly talk will later come out in more detail in written form.  It is understood an individual speaker may inadvertently add something that is not correct or something that is a personal assumption or a personal feeling. Jehovah's Witnesses believe and teach their written material is their teachings and this is not Inspired of God, unlike the Bible.  There is no need to think that any speaker or any talk that is giving would be any different. [[User:Saujad|Saujad]] ([[User talk:Saujad|talk]]) 19:00, 27 September 2012 (UTC)

What I last wrote did not generate any discussion so I probably did not make myself clear, which I have difficulty doing.
I know this is a minor complaint but it caught my attention of a misstatement and misuse of references.
&quot;stating that its interpretations of the Bible are not inspired or infallible.&quot;   The 'its' in this sentence being the WB&amp;T Society would never make such a statement.  The Society does not use the word 'interpretations' this way, they would never state this.
About interpretations, they say Jehovah is the one who interprets the Bible.  God interprets the Bible for us through the Bible. (If I need to I can find an exact quote.)  This being so from the references supplied what the Society does state is that their writings are not inspired. If something is not crystal clear in the scriptures an additional insertion is considered an assumption or a conjecture not an interpretation. (Like a date of when Armageddon might come) --[[User:Saujad|Saujad]] ([[User talk:Saujad|talk]]) 11:46, 7 October 2012 (UTC)
:It would be a subjective POV to assert that their beliefs about the Bible are anything other than ''interpretations''. The article does not need to (indeed, ''should not'') employ alternative JW jargon or hypothetical claims about God.--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 12:08, 7 October 2012 (UTC)

::Would it be better to state that Jehovah's Witnesses do not believe that the Watchtower's teachings about the Bible are interpretations? The current sentence in question reads:
&quot;The Watch Tower Society rejects accusations that it is a false prophet,[335] stating that its interpretations of the Bible are not inspired or infallible,[336][337][338] and that it has not claimed its predictions were &quot;the words of Jehovah.&quot;
::It could say instead, &quot;The Watch Tower Society rejects accusations that it is a false prophet stating that its teachings are not inspired or infallible, and that it has not claimed its predictions were 'the words of Jehovah'&quot;

::This way wikipedia won't be using Jehovah's Witnesses jargon and at the same time it won't give the impression that Jehovah's Witnesses see the Watchtower's teachings as &quot;interpretations.&quot;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Fordx12|Fordx12]] ([[User talk:Fordx12|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Fordx12|contribs]]) 20:43, 6 November 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:::I have no objection to the wording, but I don't see it as any real improvement on the existing text. I'm not sure what jargon you're referring to. [[User:BlackCab|BlackCab]] ([[User talk:BlackCab|talk]]) 09:49, 7 November 2012 (UTC)

::::I am referring to what Jeffro77 refereed to as &quot;alternative JW jargon.&quot; Saujad stated that the content in question is not properly representative of the source. The watchtower doesn't claim that it's interpretations are infallible, it claims that it's teachings on the &quot;failed predicitons&quot; were never infallible. By using &quot;interpretation&quot; Wikipedia's voice is used to label Jehovah's Witnesses beliefs as merely interpretations, and not teachings. It's not really a major issue, I understand that this is a minor detail, but one that shouldn't be ignored. [[User:Fordx12|Fordx12]] ([[User talk:Fordx12|talk]]) 21:22, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::At no point did I suggest that &quot;interpretations&quot; is JW jargon. Actually, I said quite the opposite: &quot;It would be a subjective POV to assert that their beliefs about the Bible are '''anything other than''' ''interpretations''&quot;. However, simply referring to their ''teachings'' is also acceptable. What is '''not''' appropriate is equating 'JW teachings' (which the WTS can change at whim) with 'Bible teachings' (which are variously interpreted by various groups).--[[User:Jeffro77|&lt;span style='color:#365F91'&gt;'''Jeffro'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style='color:#FFC000'&gt;''77''&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Jeffro77|talk]]) 23:56, 7 November 2012 (UTC)
I did not mean to say that you suggested &quot;interpretations&quot; is JW jargon. I am sorry if that's how my comment came across. I will go ahead and edit the sentence since there are no objections here. [[User:Fordx12|Fordx12]] ([[User talk:Fordx12|talk]]) 03:06, 8 November 2012 (UTC)
:All good. I had considered that you may have intended something else. However, I wanted to clearly state my position for other editors anyway just in case there was some confusion.--03:21, 8 November 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request on 17 October 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}

On the page
{{Main|Jehovah's Witnesses practices}}

&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Please change &quot;The meetings are largely devoted to study of Watch Tower Society literature and the Bible.&quot;
To &quot;The meetings are largely devoted to study of the Bible using Watch Tower Society Literature&quot; 
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/76.75.80.215|76.75.80.215]] ([[User talk:76.75.80.215|talk]]) 20:41, 17 October 2012 (UTC)

:{{notdone}} Make this request on the page the edit is needed on, also please provide a source/reason for changing it. [[User:gwickwire|gwickwire]] &amp;#124; [[User_talk:gwickwire|Leave a message]] 21:51, 17 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8f5ox99apw3x14vxlj2t1rjnflatwp7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
