<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Gabriel</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>163343</id>
    <revision>
      <id>496035698</id>
      <parentid>496011795</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-06-05T01:16:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>OlYeller21</username>
        <id>8199704</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* WP:EL */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42477">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WPOccult|class=B|importance=Mid}}
{{Christianity WikiProject|class=B|importance=|saints=yes|saints-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Death|class=c|importance=mid}}
}}

== Vandalism Alert! ==
Several items in the introduction have been altered.  &quot;Sex Slaves&quot; rather than &quot;messengers&quot;, for example.  These items are intact in the editorial window.  Clearly this needs to be addressed.
:Addressed a long time ago. (Just adding this note to close the issue.) [[User:Jordan Brown|Jordan Brown]] ([[User talk:Jordan Brown|talk]]) 16:15, 8 April 2009 (UTC)
==Removing Material==


&quot;I am new here, I just wanted to say that it is mentioned in the article the Laylat-ul-Qadir or the night of power under section of Gebriel in Islam is in the last ten days of Ramadhan, I just would like to note that though most narrations from the prophet mohammed indicates so and it is likely to be in these ten days, but it is not 100% sure or believed by Muslims that it has to be in the last ten days of Ramadhan, and it may be at any other night through out the year ( you might consider modifying the sentence in the article, thank you).&quot;

[[User:58.69.80.186|58.69.80.186]] 20:04, 6 September 2006 (UTC)
The Archangel Gabriel is The Left Hand of God. He is the ruler of the Cherubim. He is one of the Four Angels of The Most High God on the four sides surrounding the throne of the Almighty(with Michael,Raphael,and Phanuel). He is seated on the left side of God's throne with Metatron. (According to the Book of Enoch)  



The two sections on Gabriel in fiction:
::*In the [[roleplaying game]] Gabriel Knight series by Sierra Entertainment, Gabriel is the name of the main character. In the third game of the series, Gabriel Knight: Blood of the Sacred, Blood of the Damned (1999), Gabriel's ancestor is a roman soldier that assists in the crucifixion of [[Jesus Christ]] later begging for Jesus' forgiveness and swearing the eternal service of his bloodline. This game also expanded on the theme of the book Holy Blood, Holy Grail which first suggested the theory of Jesus fathering Mary Magdalene’s children many years before the Da Vinci Code.
::*A character in &quot;[[The Dead (short story)|The Dead]]&quot;: a short story in the book &quot;[[Dubliners]]&quot; by [[James Joyce]].
::*A character in &quot;[[The Satanic Verses (novel)|The Satanic Verses]]&quot; (Gibreel): a controversial novel by the Anglo-Indian author [[Salman Rushdie]], infamous because of the [[fatwa]] imposed on him by the [[Ayatollah Khomeini]].

''Gabriel'' may be used simply as a name, which then may play off this Gabriel, but unless the fictional character is actually intended to ''be'' this Gabriel, the reference probably doesn't belong here.[[User:The Dogandpony|The Dogandpony]] 17:49, 20 May 2006 (UTC)

==Announcement==
&quot;announce the imanent birth of their children&quot;. Unclear what is meant: Neither of the births were ''imminent'' according to the gospel.&lt;br&gt;
S.

----
'':In [[James Joyce|James Joyce's]] ''[[The_Dead_(short_story)|The Dead]]'', the main character's name is Gabriel.''

I don't see how this has anything directly to do with Gabriel the angel. --[[User:Kwekubo|Kwekubo]] 20:50, 22 September 2005 (UTC)

Almost none of that does. I think we should remove the section.--[[User:Cuchullain|Cuchullain]] 22:32, 17 October 2005 (UTC)

Removed a few things, vide supra. [[User:The Dogandpony|The Dogandpony]] 17:49, 20 May 2006 (UTC)

== Addition of erotic stores from ASSTR ==

*Please see [[Talk:Succubus#Regarding_addition_of_erotic_stories]].  If it gets put to a debate, it should probably affect my edits to this article as well. [[User:Danny Lilithborne|Danny Lilithborne]] 21:43, 4 November 2005 (UTC)

==Comments Made by Anonymous Poster ==
:This amounts to vandalism.  If you want to add that information, do it in an NPOV, manner, make it sound sane, and integrate it into the body of the article.  Raving does not belong anywhere in a Wikipedia article, and in the introduction least of all.  [[User:Neocapitalist|Neocapitalist]] 21:59, 17 November 2005 (UTC)


How the Hell can Gabriel incarnate himself in human form if God refuses to let the Elyonim take the form of the tahtonim due to the incident with the nephilim? Furthermore, how can an Elyon desire a soulmate if the Elyonim only need the love of God? Yeah, this little spontaneity was nothing more than a passing reprieve.
[[User:Jordan Yang|Jordan Yang]] 13:16, 21 December 2005 (UTC)

:I just deleted the last entry. Wikipedia is not a place to advertise religious beliefs in an attempt for &quot;people to get to know angel Gabriel more intimately&quot;. This is an encyclopedia, please make pages accordingly. [[User:Cunado19|&lt;font color=&quot;#d14c04&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[image:Bahaitemplatestar.png|20px]] - [[User talk:Cunado19|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 23:00, 18 November 2005 (UTC)
::Please remember that at Wikipedia, a neutral point of view treats [[Gabriel]] as having the same kind of reality as [[Apollo]], neither more nor less. If you want to &quot;get intimate&quot; with Gabriel, please do it at ''Biblepedia''. --[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] 04:45, 22 December 2005 (UTC)

== removed text ==
Until these are filled in, you can leave them here. [[User:Cunado19|&lt;font color=&quot;#d14c04&quot;&gt;'''Cuñado'''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[image:Bahaitemplatestar.png|20px]] - [[User talk:Cunado19|&lt;font size=&quot;-3&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 07:34, 28 November 2005 (UTC)


===Gabriel in Hebrew Apocrypha===
''To be written''

===Gabriel in Christian Apocrypha===
''To be written''

== Jibreel as a Separate Page ==
Jibreel is huge in Islam, much bigger than Gabriel in Judaism or Christianity. I suggest creating an independent page for it. Had this been done in the past? This has a lot of precedence, eg [[Jesus]] and [[Isa]], [[Moses]] and [[Musa]].--[[User:JBJ830726|JBJ830726]] 02:33, 21 January 2006 (UTC)
:Done. [[User:Palm dogg|Palm_Dogg]] 22:22, 24 January 2006 (UTC)

::I have cleaned up some of the redundant info in [[Gabriel]] and [[Jibreel]], and moved Jibreel to [[Jibril]], which is a more common spelling (try Googleing [angel Jibril] vs. [angel Jibreel]).  I have also linked the article more richly, and added more info about the Arabic forms of the word.  Now let's get some content added to the [[Jibril]] article! --[[User:Macrakis|Macrakis]] 20:27, 7 February 2006 (UTC)



::looking at the written language, they both are not the same since gabri-el with the el in the end used to say god, while the il/eel ending of jibreel seems not to be connecting to god or is my arabic, hebrew and common-sense just so bad?! --[User: Lenin] 15:23, 18 May 2011 (GMT +1)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/79.224.239.68|79.224.239.68]] ([[User talk:79.224.239.68|talk]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Seraph or Archangel? ==
In this specific article, it is stated very quickly that he is an Archangel, whereas he is listed as one of the Seraphs in the Seraph article. Perhaps someone with more knowledge on this matter can fix/clarify this.

:The article [[Seraph]] should explain when names came to be applied to Isaiah's seraphim, and by whom, in the last subsection. The names are part of modern [[angelology]]. The inconsistency is simply inconsistent. --[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] 00:28, 26 January 2006 (UTC)

: I think after going through the discussion on this page there are two or more Gabriels or Jibraal, whatever the names and some are male and some others may be female. If this argument is put up we can understand and sort out the differences. I know for sure there is on reference that rules out possibility of more Gabriels. [[User:Pathare Prabhu|Pathare Prabhu]] ([[User talk:Pathare Prabhu|talk]]) 01:55, 4 March 2011 (UTC)

== Quit messing with the music section! ==
the Gabriels Fallen (band) has relevence in this article! There was a debate over notablity of the band and the final outcome was that it was indeed notable enough to keep their page. Therefore by those same standards the Gabriels Fallen part in the music section should be kept.

:Many users (including me) believe that the band is not notable enough for inclusion in an article about a religious figure. [[User:RexNL|RexNL]] 08:30, 9 March 2006 (UTC)
:The fact that the page was kept (without consensus when it came to a vote) does not mean that the band is notable enough to be cross-referenced.  Wikipedia isn't a place to push local bands.  The &quot;same standards&quot; do not apply here. [[User:Danny Lilithborne|Danny Lilithborne]] 08:34, 9 March 2006 (UTC)

Nobody is &quot;pushing&quot; local bands, they have many songs about the character of Gabriel, people who may want to see different views and theories deserve the '''option''' of finding out more information. There is no harm in this.
::Regardless of if the band is notable or not (which I don't think it is), the band should not be included here.  This page is about Gabriel the angel and it's references '''in''' music. Your band does not sing about Gabriel or about religion, as you specify on your page.  Thus the consensus (the way Wikipedia works) is that your band should not be included.  -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] 13:45, 9 March 2006 (UTC)

The band '''does''' sing about the angel Gabriel, but the band itself (members) is not religious as I specify on my page.
::You need proof to show that, as your word is not [[Wikipedia:Verifiable]]. Furthermore your edits never potray that.  Finally even if the band does sing about Gabriel, I feel it's still not notable enough in my opinion to have it on this page, as by that account any person who talks about Gabriel would have to be included in this page. -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] 15:32, 9 March 2006 (UTC)

But Sting covering an old song about Gabriel is acceptible? I call shenanigans.


==[[Jibril]]==
The [[Jibril]] article has been merged with this, as it contained barely any more data, and this article is already structured to receive it.  Indeed, it was nothing more than an ill-conceived spin-off.[[User:Timothy Usher|Timothy Usher]] 09:33, 30 April 2006 (UTC)
:Ah, Timothy; I see you've launched your crusade (implication intended; how long was that Merge notice active? Two days?) I will await its results with sincere curiosity. &amp;#0151;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Jeremygbyrne|JEREMY]] 10:09, 30 April 2006 (UTC)
::What I was trying to tell you before, you-who-are-ever-so-sensitive, is that your use of the term [[Crusade]] re editors you believe to be Christian is as offensive as if I said (and edit summaried) that you are on a [[Jihad]].  Do you think me so dense as to not notice?

::There is a large discussion behind this, most of which is not so personalized as your comment above.  Please do read it, across all threads - see also [[Talk:Isa]] (which has not and will not be merged despite your assumption on [[User talk:Anonymous editor]] - and respond to the specific points offered therein rather than this generalized, personalized, and arguably offensive notion that I am on a &quot;crusade.&quot;)  Your consideration in this regard is appreciated.[[User:Timothy Usher|Timothy Usher]] 10:20, 30 April 2006 (UTC)
:::What I see on [[Talk:Isa]] is you POV-pushing, and a bunch of other editors objecting. Hardly the basis for a settled consensus. &amp;#0151;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Jeremygbyrne|JEREMY]] 11:09, 30 April 2006 (UTC)

::What's really needed here is a way to redirect to sections.  The section syntax is accepted (see the redirect page), but doesn't actually work.  This is data that really deserves to be in this article, and is not long enough to warrant its own article.  Wikipedia should change the protocol so that we can redirect [[Jibril]] to the section [[Gabriel#Gabriel in Islam|Gabriel in Islam]].  That would be the optimal solution in this instance, and probably many more.[[User:Timothy Usher|Timothy Usher]] 10:28, 30 April 2006 (UTC)
Timothy, I found this : http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Redirect . --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 10:35, 30 April 2006 (UTC)
Timothy, it say &quot;Please note that you can redirect only to articles, not sections in them; although the syntax allows them, they don't work&quot;. --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 10:38, 30 April 2006 (UTC)
:Exactly; section redirects don't work. And unless you want to become a developer, Timothy (how good are your [[LAMP (software_bundle)|LAMP]] skills?), they're unlikely to get a lot of priority in the near future. &amp;#0151;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Jeremygbyrne|JEREMY]] 11:09, 30 April 2006 (UTC)

:: I think this is a good argument Jeremy. We should solve this problem. --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]]

Jeremy, I think you made a quick judgement. We all have good intention here. I am sure about Timothy's intentions. --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 10:29, 30 April 2006 (UTC)
:Aminz, you simply don't speak for all muslim wikipedians. I'll wait to hear what others have to say. &amp;#0151;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Jeremygbyrne|JEREMY]] 11:09, 30 April 2006 (UTC)

:: True, I am not. But please keep in mind that I have good intentions. I only want to avoid misunderstandings of Islam. That's it. --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 11:23, 30 April 2006 (UTC)

::I'm sorry, Jeremy, so Muslim wikipedians (the only ones who count, I presume?) are to now hold a referendum as to whether I operate in good faith?  Explain my hundreds of edits consisting of nothing more than creating templates for Qur'anic and Bukhari cites, then adding them to various articles, some of which (e.g. the [[Sura]]s) no one of any faith has visited in months?  An anti-Muslim plot, no doubt.

::Muslims do not [[WP:OWN|&quot;own&quot;]] Islam-related articles.  You've no right to declare me [[Kafir|unwelcome]] and call all Muslims to condemn me.  We are supposed to be editors of wikipedia, but it's clear that you don't see it that way, and typically, don't really believe others can, either.[[User:Timothy Usher|Timothy Usher]] 11:29, 30 April 2006 (UTC)

:::''&lt;nowiki&gt;[S]o&lt;/nowiki&gt; Muslim wikipedians (the only ones who count, I presume?)'' Certainly not, nor did I say that &amp;mdash; although I ''can'' see how you might read that into what I said. (Please note the presence of punctuation; it provides valuable clues to sense.) ''Explain my hundreds of edits'' I don't know. Camouflage? Seriously, I think you're probably acting in good faith, but I ''know'' you're not considering all the potential problems your behaviour is likely to create. ''You've no right to declare me [[Kafir|unwelcome]] and call all Muslims to condemn me.'' Indeed; nor have I. What I ''have'' done is to alert others to your hasty and ill-considered campaign, which has prevented it doing too much harm. ''We are supposed to be editors of wikipedia, but it's clear that you don't see it that way, and typically, don't really believe others can, either.'' Sorry; I can't parse this. &amp;#0151;&amp;nbsp;[[User:Jeremygbyrne|JEREMY]] 07:16, 1 May 2006 (UTC)

::::Suppose I meant that, those who approach articles looking for a POV conflict (and who could be blamed for this, given the typical atmosphere on articles related to politics and religion?) might find it more natural to assume other editors to be motivated by POV, rather than general scholarship or literary style.  Not that I deny *having* a POV, but it's not the motive behind most of my edits, except insofar as attitudes towards scholarship and style are themselves POV.  When it's pro/anti/neutral vis-a-vis Islam POV, I see no reason to be shy about saying so.  My redirects are motivated by my POV about how wikipedia should organize data generally, and I admit, underlyingly by the idea that we should not introduce religiously-based strife and confusion where none exists.  Whether Jibril is, or is not, the same angel as Gabriel is a wholly artificial and ridiculous dispute, sustained by selective translation (or not), which ought be put to rest asap.

::::This text is duplicated in [[Gabriel]] in its entirety, and reasonably proportionate to the other sections.  The only thing being &quot;defended&quot; here is the Arabic name ''Jibril.''[[User:Timothy Usher|Timothy Usher]] 08:12, 1 May 2006 (UTC)

===Merge?===
All the content in [[Jibril]] appears to be here. Does anyone object to merging and redirecting ''Jibril'' to ''Gabriel''? If so, why? [[User:Tom harrison|Tom Harrison]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Tom harrison|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 12:42, 11 May 2006 (UTC)

== Saints Portal ==
Why should we have this portal here? The article is not about any saints. --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 19:28, 15 May 2006 (UTC)
*Agree, doesn't fit here.  I've removed it. -- [[User:Jeff3000|Jeff3000]] 19:36, 15 May 2006 (UTC)
*Disagree - Gabriel is considered a saint, and [[St Gabriel]] and [[Saint Gabriel]] both redirect here. [[San Gabriel]] also points here. Adding it back in. --[[User:Evrik|evrik]] 20:08, 15 May 2006 (UTC)
*But saints are supposed to be humans, aren't they? --[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 20:19, 15 May 2006 (UTC)
**No. All the Archangels are considered saints. --[[User:Evrik|evrik]] 20:37, 15 May 2006 (UTC)
:::Not in Protestantism.  At least, I've never heard of it.[[User:Timothy Usher|Timothy Usher]] 20:43, 15 May 2006 (UTC)
:::Ahem
*http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=saint+gabriel+presbyterian
*http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=spell&amp;resnum=0&amp;ct=result&amp;cd=1&amp;q=saint+gabriel+episcopal&amp;spell=1
--[[User:Evrik|evrik]] 20:47, 15 May 2006 (UTC)
::::Well, I guess so.  Thanks.[[User:Timothy Usher|Timothy Usher]] 20:58, 15 May 2006 (UTC)
*Makes no sense to me either, but the article states that Catholics consider &quot;St. Gabriel the Archangel, the patron saint of communications workers,&quot; while he [[Saints]] article states that Eastern Orthodoxy includes angels as saints.[[User:Timothy Usher|Timothy Usher]] 20:25, 15 May 2006 (UTC)

* Nor in Islam. But it would be a good addition to the article (Christianity section) &quot;that in Eastern Orthodoxy, Gabriel is a considered as a saint&quot;. The portal at the moment is not well placed. Bringing it to the top might be considered as POV. Maybe it should be moved to the Christianity section or removed from the article.--[[User:Aminz|Aminz]] 21:00, 15 May 2006 (UTC)

* Gabriel, as well as Michael and Raphael are all given the title of &quot;Saint&quot; by Orthodox, Catholic, and Anglican churches. The catholic belief holds that all Christians and Angels are saints. [[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 02:56, 9 August 2010 (UTC)

== Astrology ==
In the zodiac signs, each sign is &quot;assigned&quot; an angel, and aquarius's angel is Gabriel.[[User:Dogmanice|Dogmanice]] 01:58, 16 May 2006 (UTC)

I changed the heading of this section from Astronomy to Astrology/
.

==Come and Hear reference removed==
The Talmud quote is accurate but links to a hate site masquerading as an unbiased source of information. Wikipedia would do well to avoid giving it any legitimacy or authority. In any case, the exact reference (much less a link to it) to Gabriel's speaking Syriac hardly seems a particularly necessary thing to document. [[User:ShalomShlomo|ShalomShlomo]] 23:26, 16 July 2006 (UTC)

==Which Reference?==
I have issue with the reference to Yoma 79A. I just read Yoma 79A and see no mention of Gabriel. Am I missing something, or is that reference just completely wrong? [[User:Clever_Kellom|Clever_Kellom]] 17:48 15 Feb. 2007 (EST)

==The Loose Use of the Term Cult==
The section that describes the Latter-day Saint religion as a cult is unfounded and biased in nature and in no way reflects the religion as a whole.  A cult, by definition, can be expanded to include any religion that is considered to be outside societal norms.  Since this is broad enough that it could be used to define any religion that one does not agree with, it is clearly a word that has no place in a text such as this.  Especially as it describes a religion that is so prominent throughout the world and more closely follows ancient organizations of Christianity than that of the more &quot;accepted&quot; Christian religions. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/67.166.97.195|67.166.97.195]] ([[User talk:67.166.97.195|talk]]) 03:51, 9 January 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

:Outside &quot;societal norms&quot; today might include the doctoring of documents, brainwashing indoctrination, the use of psychological pressure, manipulated cultural isolation, covert activities, induced fear, an atmosphere of implied threat, etc.. Almost all major Christian sects have been guilty of such violations at one time or another. &quot;Cult&quot;, when it is not confined to &quot;outward forms of religious practice&quot;— its original meaning— ''must'' refer to these manipulative practices, or else it's a mere smear word and is an ''authentic'' violation of Wikipedia's neutral point-of-view. In such an atmosphere, unsigned posts by un-logged-in Users assering &quot;bias&quot; do not inspire confidence. --[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] 10:47, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

::If the LDS had started up anytime before the 18th century and anyplace but America they'd have been exterminated as a heresy. While I wouldn't agree with the exterminatoin, I'd certainly understand the accusation of heresy: LDS doesn't look anything like Christianity. It's a new and seperate religion. In the same way, Christianity itself began as a heretical version of Judaism - the Jewish messiah was not and is not regarded as a literal &quot;son&quot; of God. Cults become religions by surviving and growing - someone once said, very cleverly, that a language is a dialect with an army behind it (meaning it that the group of people who control the power of the State will also control which of several dialects is recognised as the norm); the situation vis-a-vis cults and religions is similar. My point being, LDS is now laarge enough to qualify as a religion rather than a cult, but has departed too far from Christianity to be regarded as a Christian denomination. It needs a separate section.[[User:PiCo|PiCo]] 06:53, 24 February 2007 (UTC)


==Sonata Vox Gabrieli==
Added a short bit about the Vox Gabrieli by Sulek. I think this is probably one of the most important
music references. Are there any Trombone nerds out there that know more about this piece?

in the section where u say gabrial comes at last ten day of the holy month of ramdan in Lilat al qadar you translated it to the (night of power) when it is relly the (night of destiny)

==Use in Fiction==
Given the same discussion is being held on the page on Michael and on Uriel, I'd propose that its worthwhile to have a brief on Gabriels and the other Archangels appearances in fiction. While the article deals primarily with religious iconography and theology, the characters appearances in books I think is viable information, as not all &quot;fictional&quot; appearances are necessarily non-spiritual. Paradise Lost, Divine Comedy, etc.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Brinlong|Brinlong]] ([[User talk:Brinlong|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Brinlong|contribs]]) 22:51, 9 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I agree, there are many religious references in the Vertigo Line of Trade Paperbacks.  Many of them follow the general religious philosophy with a fictional spin, obviously but their reference should not be discounted.  Thus, there is a reason why Gabriel was in the movie Constantine because he/she was used in the reference material &quot;Dangerous Habits&quot; from the Hellblazer comic book series.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Endless102|Endless102]] ([[User talk:Endless102|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Endless102|contribs]]) 01:16, 29 June 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Gabriel a male name ==
I will remove this line saying that Gabriel is retrated as Women, thats sound nuts.
If anyone have any question about this, take a look in the the Book of Daniel at 8:15 and you will se that Daniel see Gabriel &quot;as the appearance of a man&quot;. Unless Daniel has something wrong in his understud of male and female we can say that Gabriel looks like a man, at least.

In the true, theres no &quot;Women Angels&quot; on Holy Bible.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/201.95.97.82|201.95.97.82]] ([[User talk:201.95.97.82|talk]]) 18:00, 16 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Latin-Gender==

I think that there is a typo.  At the top of the page, it lists the Latin form between Gabriel and Gavriel as &quot;Gabrielus&quot; but lower down where it lists the Latin forms, it has &quot;Gabrielius&quot; rather than &quot;Gabrielus.&quot;  I am not sure which is correct in this case, but usually in my research of names, the male versions are more apt to have an &quot;-ius&quot; ending than an &quot;-us&quot; ending.

Looking around the net, the Australians tend to use male versions of this name for girls.  If it is straight from the Hebrew, there should be a &quot;-ah&quot; version of the name in the early forms &quot;gavriel&quot;, &quot;gabhriel&quot; and (form used in bible) &quot;gabriyel&quot; because that is the Hebrew ending to make it a female name.

As far as the &quot;like a man&quot; stuff, this goes back to the name &quot;Andrew&quot; (brother of Simon) and its relation to the first half of the name Gabriel.  The early forms of Andrew &quot;Andreas&quot; and &quot;Andreios&quot; were supposed to come from an Aramaic original but they are not sure what.  But there was a big controversy because the Greeks translated both &quot;bala&quot; (meaning husband) and &quot;gbra&quot; (which can refer to either a father or a husband&quot; as &quot;andros/aner&quot; - putting a link between the early forms of Andrew and the the early forms of the first half of Gabriel.  Seems that the two geneologies in the bible are different because one is that of Mary's father (Joseph) and one is of Mary's husband (Joseph).

When you go through the rest of the definitions for both &quot;andros&quot; and &quot;gbra&quot; you find that &quot;like a male&quot; meant that one exhibited qualities deemed &quot;masculine&quot; - such as being &quot;brave&quot; and a &quot;warrior&quot; - and is not, like some websites say, a sign of early planetary visitors.  

- / - gever, geber, gebher  (heb) (from) gavar, gabar, gabhar (heb) (X/X)  gavra, gabra, gbra (aramaic/ semitic)=(orig) adult male, man, (later) mighty man, strong man, protective male, warrior, champion, guardian, (later) male head of the household, person of special position, the power of fertility, (later) husband, father;

(I think that gebher originally referred to a rooster and acquired the other meanings because of two similar sounding words)

- / - andreios (grk) (from) andros (from) aner (from) anhr (grk) (X/X) gavra, gabra, gbra (aramaic/ semitic);

When names pass from language to language, sometimes it has no meaning in the new language so the only alteration is spelling for pronunciation. But most of the time, they either pick something that sounds the same or has a similar meaning as the original. Often in the former case, some punning is going on - sometimes flattering and sometimes decisively not. 22:51, 17 September 2008 (UTC)~ ```23:21, 17 September 2008 (UTC)~

==Reference to Satanic verses ==
A chief character in Salman Rushdie's Satanic verses is unmistakably Gabriel Farishta or Archangel Gabriel. Shouldn't this important piece be mentioned in references in art or in popula culture?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/91.17.242.187|91.17.242.187]] ([[User talk:91.17.242.187|talk]]) 10:45, 22 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

It is the same angel Gabriel being referenced, but you need to get the correct spelling of the actor's name, which was &quot;Gibreel Farishta&quot;.

The Satanic Verses uses many &quot;biblical&quot; names and even references the birth of Christ, which the Koran considers to be a minor prophet.  Maher Arar and Monia Mazigh point out that the some of the same stories exists in both the Koran and the Bible, in reference to a different Joseph, Monia said &quot;... he wanted her to know about the story of Joseph, which in Arabic we say Yussef  but it is the same prophet.&quot; [http://www.cbc.ca/sunday/coverstory_maherarar.html]  Wonder if it would be better to list the biblical/koranic references on the SV page so that when you mention it here, it can link there for more complete information.  23:17, 17 September 2008 (UTC)~~

==Mention of Traditional Roman Catholics==

I think it it important to make mention of [[Traditionalist Catholics|Traditional Roman Catholics]] since they make up a significant minority here in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]] as well as in [[France]], [[Germany]], [[United Kingdom]], and other places around the world. They continue to [[Commemoration (prayer)|commemorate]] St. Gabriel the Archangel on his traditional [[feast day]] of [[March 24]]. [[User:AMC0712|AMC0712]] ([[User talk:AMC0712|talk]]) 17:49, 24 March 2008 (UTC)
:Those traditionalist Catholics who choose to use a calendar of the Roman Church between that of 1922 and that of 1969 do so.  Anyone traditional enough to prefer an earlier calendar, even if they do not go back as far as the [[Tridentine Calendar]] do not.  Surely it is enough to indicate in what calendars Gabriel appears and with what feast day.  [[User:Lima|Lima]] ([[User talk:Lima|talk]]) 15:10, 20 August 2008 (UTC)

== Archangel &amp; Pseudepigraphy Changes? ==

===Archangel===
Gabriel is considered to be an archangel, but the bible never refers to him as one. Michael is the only angel stated to be an archangel.


I'm going to go ahead and tweak the article to say &quot;generally considered an archangel&quot; instead of &quot;is an archangel&quot;
:Catholic, Orthodox, Anglican, and most mainline protestant traditions believe Gabriel to be an archangel. [[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 03:00, 9 August 2010 (UTC)

===Pseudepigraphy===

The last sentence in this section is...


&quot;According to Enoch 70:11-16 states that Michael, Gabriel, Raphael and Phanuel always travel with Yahweh when he moves from His Throne.[citation needed][original research?]&quot;


First off, it's Enoch chapter 71, not 70. And It doesn't state they always follow him, it just says they followed him in that particular instance. It is not a bad generality, by most deductions of reason the head angels would follow God wherever he went, but the verse does not proclaim it as an &quot;always&quot;, like the last sentence specifically states.

Its is significant if you were born on March 24, 1968, a year before they changed the feast days, and as in most catholic countries you are  named after the catholic calendar which says say which saints are celebrating their feast days - Gabriel Bucu (dang!)
Therefore, I'm going to edit that sentence too and make it a bit more open.

yes unless you were born on march 24, 1968, a year before they changed feast days and your name happens to that of your patron saint as in many catholict countries, GABRIEL. whay do they do that?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/203.177.91.162|203.177.91.162]] ([[User talk:203.177.91.162|talk]]) 10:22, 18 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;



Thanks guys [[User:Huperphuff|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Huper Phuff&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User Talk:Huperphuff|&lt;font color=&quot;#D4A017&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:17, 16 July 2008 (UTC).

== Gabriel ==
I always thought The Angel Gabriel was female.[[User:Dumaka|Dumaka]] ([[User talk:Dumaka|talk]]) 14:03, 29 October 2008 (UTC)

If you belive Milton he states in Paradice Lost the Angels are neither male or female and can assume either gender  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Paul9022|Paul9022]] ([[User talk:Paul9022|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Paul9022|contribs]]) 23:32, 7 December 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Christian tradition holds that angels are genderless, but the archangels take on the form f a man. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 02:59, 9 August 2010 (UTC)

==Enoch and Gabriel==
I think this link between Enoch and Gabriel ought to be researched further. For instance, if we agree that Enoch and Metatron are the same, then this would mean that Enoch is the chief of all angels and the creator of Gabriel. Therefore, this would change our entire understanding of the Annunciation/Incarnation story : Enoch sent his daughter Gabriel to announce to Mary that she would conceive a divine Child out of the divine Angel Metatron, who is also Saint Joseph. [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 21:24, 2 April 2009 (UTC)
:Wrong place for that, this is Wikipedia, an encyclopedia which reports what [[WP:RS|reliable]] and [[WP:Verifiable]] sources have written about a subject. You are talking about [[WP:original research]] which has no place here (either in the article or here on the talk page). [[User:Dougweller]]

==Female==
I think Gabriel is popularly rendered as a female archangel, along with Camael, Cassiel, Haniel. In fact, there are at least four female archangels, Gabriel being one of them. [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 21:28, 2 April 2009 (UTC)
:Really?  [[User:Soidi|Soidi]] ([[User talk:Soidi|talk]]) 18:07, 3 April 2009 (UTC)

::According to Christian tradition, Gabriel is a male, as are all the other archangels. --[[User:Willthacheerleader18|Willthacheerleader18]] ([[User talk:Willthacheerleader18|talk]]) 02:58, 9 August 2010 (UTC)

== Trumpet? ==

There's nothing in here about Gabriel blowing the trumpet to announce Judgement Day.  That rather surprises me; in popular usage I would say that is one of the major pieces of angelic lore.  However, I don't know anything near enough about the subject to add anything.  Perhaps somebody could, if only to add a section describing a misconception? [[User:Jordan Brown|Jordan Brown]] ([[User talk:Jordan Brown|talk]]) 16:22, 8 April 2009 (UTC)

== Bahá'í ==
The following text was deleted by an anonymous IP that logged in as &quot;[[Special:Contributions/Mehdieval|Mehdieval]]&quot; just to make this deletion:
''Gabriel also finds mention in the writings of the [[Bahá'í Faith]], most notably in [[Bahá'u'lláh]]'s mystical work ''[[Seven Valleys]]''.''
Very suspicious I am. Should the statement be reinstated and made more explicit?--[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] ([[User talk:Wetman|talk]]) 18:22, 15 June 2009 (UTC)

:I suppose so, yes. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 17:40, 18 June 2009 (UTC)

== Google search ==

After doing a google search for Gabriel, the wikipedia article shows this:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Gabriel also finds mention in the writings of the Bahá'í Faith, most notably in Bahá'u'lláh's mystical work Seven Valleys
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Why is wikipedia or google trying to promote baha'ism? Isn't this faith supposed to be non-preachy? [[User:Faro0485|Faro0485]] ([[User talk:Faro0485|talk]]) 03:30, 4 July 2009 (UTC)

:I don't know what your point is. Google is not set up to deliberately promote anything, and Wikipedia articles should not promote anything and in this case I see no promotion at all. If Gabriel is mentioned in Bahai texts, then it should be included here. Even, as is possible, the inclusion was originally by a member of the faith, it seems to me worthy of inclusion. Do you disagree? [[User:Dougweller|Dougweller]] ([[User talk:Dougweller|talk]]) 07:47, 4 July 2009 (UTC)

== Angel of death ==

[[Death (personification)#In Judaism]] identifies Gabriel as angel of death over kings, but the [[Gabriel]] article does not. Could/should this be added? [[Special:Contributions/92.2.208.239|92.2.208.239]] ([[User talk:92.2.208.239|talk]]) 10:13, 1 April 2010 (UTC)

== Saint Gabriel? ==

I don't think that Gabriel is ever referred as a Saint; no angel is referred like that. Angels are not Saints.
I'm removing the word &quot;Saint&quot; in the text where it refers to the name of the Angel.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/187.160.241.20|187.160.241.20]] ([[User talk:187.160.241.20|talk]]) 17:25, 22 November 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Exagerate number of references ==

Currently there is an statement in the lead section that refers to artistic depictions which is referenced with 7 sources. This has to be improved and make it only one if any. [[Special:Contributions/190.251.100.237|190.251.100.237]] ([[User talk:190.251.100.237|talk]]) 19:19, 20 April 2011 (UTC)

== Garbriel in the movie ''Van Helsing (2004 movie)'' ==

It is revealed by Dracula in the movie that Van Helsing is Gabriel, the left hand of god whom killed Dracula in a battle long ago.
I shall add this to the list ''Radio, film and television''.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/130.225.247.116|130.225.247.116]] ([[User talk:130.225.247.116|talk]]) 18:01, 25 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== New Testament ==

The following should be deleted:

&quot;Believers are expressly warned not to venerate or worship angels in Colossians 2:18-19 and Revelation 19:10.[9]&quot;

This is false as the Revelation of John is expressly written to be the indications given by an Angel (Revelations 1:1). So 19:10 is given as a response to an Angel, not to a &quot;believer&quot;.
Colossians 2:18-19 indicates not to let those who have a mock-humility and &quot;type of angel worship&quot; alongside vanity, deprive you of the spiritual prize. It doesn't give any admonition against venerating angels. (If that were so, the very Revelation of St. John could not be venerated)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.39.36.11|82.39.36.11]] ([[User talk:82.39.36.11|talk]]) 18:21, 20 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== other than catholics ==
the article states that &quot;Christians of the Catholic traditions refer to him as Gabriel the Archangel.&quot; what do other christians call him? I'm lutheran and I have only heard of him as either Gabriel the Archangel, or just The Archangel.[[Special:Contributions/94.145.236.194|94.145.236.194]] ([[User talk:94.145.236.194|talk]]) 11:04, 21 November 2011 (UTC)

== WP:EL ==

There is a large number of external links in the article and per [[WP:EL]], they should be removed.  {{u|Telpardec}} has now removed the tag twice ([http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gabriel&amp;diff=495714882&amp;oldid=495714328][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gabriel&amp;diff=495862616&amp;oldid=495779084]).  I am placing the tag again and asking that a discussion here take place as to why Telpardec or any other user feels that [[WP:EL]] should be ignored. '''[[User:OlYeller21|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#827839;&quot;&gt;Ol&lt;font style=&quot;color:#FBB117;&quot;&gt;Yeller21&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:OlYeller21|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#827839;&quot;&gt;Talktome]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 02:21, 4 June 2012 (UTC)

:Ignored? No. &amp;ndash; There are &lt;u&gt;no&lt;/u&gt; inappropriate external links. An editor making a negative claim has no obligation to prove the negative. Let the editor making the positive &quot;large number&quot; claim produce &lt;u&gt;one&lt;/u&gt; example of what she thinks is an inappropriate external link. The page history shows that since 9 January 2012 when the tag was [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gabriel&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=470355851 first placed], &lt;u&gt;none&lt;/u&gt; of the editors has found a single inappropriate EL. I checked every single link in the body of the article. The links are mostly to Wikipedia articles or images, secondly to citation footnotes, and thirdly, standard parenthetical Bibleref template citations as appropriate. There are no inappropriate external links in this article. IMO the tagging editor needs to self-revert the re-tagging.&lt;br&gt;Thanks. &lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:bold;font-family:Verdana;&quot;&gt;[[User:Telpardec|—Telpardec]] [[User talk:Telpardec|&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:85%;color:#ff6;background:#090;border:3px double;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;TALK&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 22:57, 4 June 2012 (UTC)

*According to the [[Template:External links]] instructions, the tag is to be placed at the top of the &quot;External links&quot; section when it has excessive or inapproapriate links. There are only three (3) links in the ''External links'' section &amp;ndash; hardly excessive &amp;ndash; and they all appear appropriate.
*According to [[WP:ELRC]], (quote) {{xt|Sites that have been used as sources in the creation of an article should be cited in the article, and linked as references, either in-line or in a references section. Links to these source sites are &lt;u&gt;not&lt;/u&gt; &quot;external links&quot; for the purposes of this guideline, and should not normally be duplicated in an external links section.}} (unquote)&lt;br&gt;And (quote) {{xt|The &lt;nowiki&gt;{{external links}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; template is for providing notice that the list of links may have grown to an inappropriate length or contain inappropriate links.}} (unquote)&lt;br&gt;And (quote) {{xt|When an article complies with the relevant standards, then any editor may remove the tags.}} (unquote)

::I think you missed item #2 under [[Wikipedia:External_links#Important_points_to_remember]]: &quot;External links should not normally be used in the body of an article.&quot; 
::Your first point doesn't apply as the issue isn't with the external links sections.  The external links section looks fine to me.
::Your second point is apparently misinterpreted as it clearly states that &quot;sites that have been used as sources ... should be cited in the article and linked '''as references'''.  They are not [[WP:REFERENCE|references]], they are [[WP:EL|external links]].  They are two different things. '''[[User:OlYeller21|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#827839;&quot;&gt;Ol&lt;font style=&quot;color:#FBB117;&quot;&gt;Yeller21&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:OlYeller21|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#827839;&quot;&gt;Talktome]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 23:15, 4 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>h868fvqoui069rgp6b1vpylp028ttod</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
