<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Judaism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>15914</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520662966</id>
      <parentid>520384613</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T23:02:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MagusAmathion</username>
        <id>17745264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Oldest */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51659">{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot|age=30|dounreplied=yes}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1= GAN
|action1date= 2006-03-13
|action1link=
|action1result= listed
|action1oldid= 43662076

|action2= FAC
|action2date= 2006-04-22
|action2link= Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Judaism/archive1
|action2result= failed
|action2oldid= 49558969

|action3= GAR
|action3date= 2007-07-11
|action3result= delisted
|action3oldid= 143893436

|currentstatus= DGA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Bible|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Kabbalah|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Jewish history|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Israel|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=B|category=Philrelig|VA=yes|coresup=yes|importance=Top|small=}}
}}
{{Notice|{{Find sources}}}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav|noredlinks=y}}
|maxarchivesize = 125K
|counter = 21
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(21d)
|archive = Talk:Judaism/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Judaism/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Judaism/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes
}}

== Oldest ==

The lede previously stated Judaism is the oldest surviving monotheistic religion, but Moses did not come until much after Abraham which would make Zoroastrianism older. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 23:12, 1 August 2012 (UTC)
:First, Judaism traces its roots as the &quot;Children of Israel&quot; at least to Jacob (also called Israel), and can show genealogy couple thousand years prior back to Adam. Though the nation did not always follow the one true G-d, monotheistic belief in him by at least a remnant is consistent throughout time.  And then there is the case that Zoroaster - a prophet, not a god - was not born until the 5th Century BCE.--[[User:DeknMike|DeknMike]] ([[User talk:DeknMike|talk]]) 04:25, 2 August 2012 (UTC)
::Yes, I don't think there's any case to be made for Zoroastrianism being older than Judaism (First Temple Judaism, anyway). The time periods just don't match up. Even if you use the critical dating of the Torah having been redacted around the middle of the 1st millennium BCE, the religion itself is indisputably older than Zoroastrianism. [[User:Evanh2008|Evanh2008]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Evanh2008|talk]]&amp;#124;[[Special:Contributions/Evanh2008|contribs]])&lt;/sup&gt; 04:44, 2 August 2012 (UTC)

I have summarily reinstated the statement. This has been discussed many times here and the statement has always been upheld. And it was sourced. Pass a Method should have known better than to remove sourced information from such a well-edited article without establishing consensus first. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 08:41, 2 August 2012 (UTC)

: I have seen many sources state that Zoroastrianism is the oldest monotheistic religion:
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=aySM38aeqSUC&amp;pg=PT137&amp;lpg=PT137&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Pku9QLqSXm&amp;sig=mV2O0Ofoi6hCiA44sImdrnMjkW4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dXMaUO_bK8el0AX1roHgDA&amp;ved=0CDkQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false], This one says Zoroastrianism is older than Judaism
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=fRiX462_Rq0C&amp;pg=PA186&amp;lpg=PA186&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Pxs_qdEEDI&amp;sig=j-B0ZUyCzMp7MbksvSRF7k1yApQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dXMaUO_bK8el0AX1roHgDA&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false] &quot;oldest monotheistic religion&quot;
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ZXOtTk-puR4C&amp;pg=PA31&amp;lpg=PA31&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=V6eVYaF4nD&amp;sig=Bv9U08NDYp23hzKr7Nw_VBdCspk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dXMaUO_bK8el0AX1roHgDA&amp;ved=0CGkQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false], &quot;predates Judaism&quot;
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=OltMzIU1ae0C&amp;pg=PA2&amp;lpg=PA2&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=3riExucNLv&amp;sig=LKOIXRRQp8Nrj5fKtvyN0aFbHlg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dXMaUO_bK8el0AX1roHgDA&amp;ved=0CHYQ6AEwCw#v=onepage&amp;q=%20zoroastrianism&amp;f=false] &quot;first monotheistic religion&quot;
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=VKS_C45BSOAC&amp;pg=PA289&amp;lpg=PA289&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=uLqmcXW4rS&amp;sig=ryAM-fbslt3LxGSk8Z_6I8ZvyGc&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dXMaUO_bK8el0AX1roHgDA&amp;ved=0CHsQ6AEwDA#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false] &quot;first monotheistic religion&quot;
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=cHI3qGaX9DsC&amp;pg=PT831&amp;lpg=PT831&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Kf1Zr5-SCD&amp;sig=DbneepgT0TsKa_3cHINPPE3HJ9g&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dXMaUO_bK8el0AX1roHgDA&amp;ved=0CIIBEOgBMA0#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false] &quot;earliest known monotheistic religion&quot;
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=ixU33FaG_dgC&amp;pg=PA959&amp;lpg=PA959&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=dSg3L04-qo&amp;sig=b4WBu-9xgCXe1QyvgWWLkwDanIE&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dXMaUO_bK8el0AX1roHgDA&amp;ved=0CJoBEOgBMBE#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false] &quot;worlds first monotheistic religion&quot; 
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=dF34veP4IjwC&amp;pg=PA295&amp;lpg=PA295&amp;dq=&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=3o9DNd9dPI&amp;sig=twSpX_8u9t41Nc0EZrGZF3xJ1lk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dXMaUO_bK8el0AX1roHgDA&amp;ved=0CKABEOgBMBI#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false] &quot;first true monotheistic religion&quot;

There are dozens more sources like this but i got tired of searching. I think we should at least reword the current sentence to make it sound more neutral. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 12:44, 2 August 2012 (UTC)

:Pass a Method, please review the Talk page archives. We've discussed this before. —&amp;nbsp;[[User:Malik Shabazz|Malik Shabazz]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Malik Shabazz|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Malik Shabazz|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt; 15:06, 2 August 2012 (UTC)

:: Malik, I've seen the archives but i still think the claim is problematic. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 15:34, 2 August 2012 (UTC)
::: You are free to think what you like. Your thinking something, however, does not necessarily make it the case. There are basically two issues here. One, is Zoroastrianism &quot;monotheistic&quot;? The answer is, only in a way. While they do meet the definition of being a religion which worships only one god, the fact that Angra Mainyu is credited in several of the early texts as having had his own, admittedly smaller and less pleasant, separate creation definitely is sufficient reason for him to qualify as a separate &quot;God&quot; in a sense. That would exclude Zoroastrianism from being able to claim to be monotheistic as per the definition of [[monotheism]] given in the lead of our article on the topic. Also, I note that several of the sources you provide say only &quot;older than Judaism&quot;, which does not necessarily mean that they consider it to be an earlier monotheistic religion, and it would be OR to assert that they do. Also, having not reviewed the reputation of the books linked to, and noting I would have to make a rather extreme effort to even find out the titles and authors, as they weren't provided in the above, something most editors would have known to do, I am far from certain that these sources are necessarily the best sources on the topic. In fact, I can't be sure that they necessarily even meet RS standards. That being the case, I have to say that I know there are several books on Google and elsewhere which are, well, definitely on the fringey side, and it may well be that these are among them. I think that there are serious questions regarding the thought processes of individual editors who seem to assume that articles with this degree of prominence and activity for as long as this article has existed in a developed state would still have contained such significant errors as that editor seems to have assumed, but that is a separate issue. If very high-quality academic sources can be produced which make the statement they seek to add, that would be a different thing. But, to date, I am far less than certain that such have been presented. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 16:31, 2 August 2012 (UTC)

:Hi Pass a Method (yes it turns out I have this article watchlisted too).  I took a look at the sources you provided.  It looks like you did a Google scholar search and then pasted the results without looking at the quality of the sources (or at least this is what I ''hope'' you did!).  After all the experience we both have had focusing on how important it is to evaluate the quality of sources, I have to say I'm a little disappointed.
:For lack of more time, I artibrarily decided to look at just the even-numbered sources you listed:
:*[2] is &quot;Interactive Faith: The Essential Interreligious Community-Building Handbook&quot; by Rev. Bud Heckman.  Heckman is an ordained United Methodist minister, and has graduate degrees from the University of Chicago Divinity School and Boston University’s Division of Religion and Theological Studies, but I could not determine what degrees.  The publisher, SkyLight Paths Publishing, looks to be like a legit publishing house (it isn't a vanity press) but it's not an academic publisher, it publishes books promoting harmony and understanding between faiths.  As far as sources go, it's not terrible, but not great, but is ''by far'' the best source I looked at in the list you provided.  Interestingly, the actual full quote from the book is:
:::&quot;Zoroastrianism is credited to be the oldest monotheistic religion.  Though many scholars fix Zarathustra's date of inception around 1500 BCE, some believe Zarathustra was born as early as 6000 BCE or as late as 700 to 600 BCE.&quot;
::which is quite a bit more qualified than the snip provided.
:*[4] is &quot;The Mysteries Of Mithras: The Pagan Belief That Shaped The Christian World&quot; by Payam Nabarz.  Nabarz is credited with a Ph.D. from Oxford but apparently in medicine (his research is in genetics and cancer) and not religion or history.  He is described as &quot;a Sufi and a practicing Dervish. He is a Druid in the Order of Bards, Ovates and Druids, and a co-founder of its Nemeton of the Stars Grove. Magi Nabarz is a revivalist of the Temple of Mithras, and is working toward becoming a Hierophant in the Fellowship of Isis. He has also worked with the Golden Dawn system, Thelema, Nath Tantra, Wicca, and the Craft&quot; so he seems to be writing as an insider &quot;amateur&quot; (in the classical sense).  The publisher, [[Inner Traditions – Bear &amp; Company]], is not an academic publisher.  In fact it carries such titles as &quot;The Science of Getting Rich,&quot; &quot;Pyramid Power&quot; and variety of eyeybrow-raising fringe and homeopathic medicine topics.  Don't forget that per [[WP:RS]] we're looking for sources with a reputation for fact-checking, and so a publisher of pseudo-scientific works based on theories long since laughed out of town by scientists doesn't give us confidence.  This seems like a very weak source.
:*[6] self-declares that it is at least a partial mirror of Wikipedia and therefore not a reliable source per [[WP:RS]]:  &quot;Thus Wikipedia articles (or Wikipedia mirrors) are not reliable sources for any purpose.&quot;  A 30-second look at it would have revealed this.
:*[8] is &quot;Persephone, Queen of the Dead&quot; by Isadora Marie.  It's self-published by Marie through Dog Ear Publishing, a &quot;print-on-demand self-publishing&quot; company and so fails [[WP:SPS]].  Again, a 30-second look at it would have revealed this.
:Honestly it would have been more considerate of your fellow editors' time if you had done this homework first before throwing this list-o-links up here.  Saying as you did, &quot;there are dozens more sources like this&quot; isn't a compelling argument for changing the article given the quality of the sources provided; and saying &quot;I got tired of searching&quot; also isn't very considerate of your fellow editors' time.
:The BBC source we currently have is (probably) a tertiary source, which isn't ideal for Wikipedia, but to me seems better than any of these sources I've looked at here.  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 19:06, 2 August 2012 (UTC)
::: Zad, i admit im a bit ignorant when it comes to knowing what constitutes a high-quality source. I used to refer to [[WP:REF]] and [[WP:MEDRS]]. Thanks for pointing out [[WP:RS]].  [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 19:14, 2 August 2012 (UTC)
:::: Glad you're not upset, hopefully this is a learning opportunity.
:::: As I'm doing a little more poking around on this, I'm actually beginning to see enough discussion about &quot;the oldest surviving monotheistic religion&quot; in what look like reliable sources to me that there might be a case for putting in a qualifier like &quot;arguably&quot; in the sentence.  I have to do more reading.  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 19:37, 2 August 2012 (UTC)
::::: Like I said myself above, there is a bit of a case here. The question is about the definition of the term &quot;monotheist&quot; - does it mean &quot;worship of one god&quot; or roughly the definition we have in the [[monotheism]] article? By the former definition, it is monotheistic. By the latter, the fact that Angra Mainyu is credited as having separately created his own universe, with which Ahura Mazda's is in opposition, indicates that it doesn't meet the definition in our article. Could that defition be revised? Possibly. Should Zoroastrianism be included in the [[Dualism]] article? I would have to assume yes. Like I pointed out elsewhere, the 2007 World Religions Reference Library article on Zoroastrianism on HighBeam Research site begins its article on Zoroastrianism &quot;Historians remain uncertain about when Zoroastrianism first developed, but many believe that it is older than Judaism. If that belief is correct, then Zoroastrianism is the world's first major monotheistic religion (a religion that worships one god).&quot; It specifically defines monotheism as the worship of one god, not the belief in only one god existing. That quote would qualify Zoroastrianiam as henotheistic, taking into account Angra Mainyu's separate creation and thus qualification as a &quot;god&quot; of some sort, but not necessarily monotheistic as per the definition in our article. I also note that it specifically adds the specific definition of monotheism which has to be used, which is not the definition we use here. Should it be? Maybe, but that discussion would be better placed at that article, not here. The reference works on that same site mentioning monotheism, none of which seem to particularly relate to religion, also tend to use the definition &quot;worship of one god&quot;. But, like I said, they aren't religious reference works. I can and will check the Eliade/Jones encyclopedia on Monday, which doesn't have an article on monotheism available on that site, to check what it says. I think it would be useful if someone checked the various Philosophy reference encyclopedia, and maybe ''Religion Past and Present'' as well for their definitions. But I would think the definition of monotheism according to directly relevant reference sources in religion and philosophy are the ones that should be used here. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 20:23, 2 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::: The article on &quot;monotheism&quot; in ''Encyclopedia Judaica,'' also at Highbeam, begins as follows: &quot;MONOTHEISM , in its literal meaning, oneness of the godhead (i.e., one God). The concept of monotheism is embedded in the domain of religious discourse, and its full and relevant significance must be derived from the connotation which it carries within this domain. Monotheism is usually attributed to biblical faith as its unique and distinct contribution to the history of religious thought. The significance of the word monotheism in its biblical context is taken to lie in the &quot;mono,&quot; in the godhead's being one.&quot; This rather more clearly indicates not the ''worship'' of one god, but the existence of only one God. Granted, it is a ''Jewish'' encyclopedia, and it might understandably reflect Jewish views, but the fact of it indicating the &quot;literal meaning&quot;, as opposed to the apparent figurative menaing of the World Religions Reference Library article, leads me to think that the literal definition probably takes priority over the figurative one, as early cultures tended to be a bit clearer and more literal in their language than later ones. But it does make a claim to being the first monotheism in a way which is in accord with our own article on [[montheism]], so, if that article is taken as accurate, then Judaism ''probably'' qualifies as being the first monotheism, depending on how you define the early history which many archaeologists and historians of religion see as containing some elements of henotheism. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 20:41, 2 August 2012 (UTC)
::::::: This is good analysis John, I'm keen to find out what you can dig up.  The argument I'm seeing isn't even over whether Zoro. is monotheistic or not, but rather whether which started earlier.  Academic estimates as to the starting dates of each religion can have wide ranges, and discussions of which one influenced the other and therefore must have been 'first' make arguments both ways.  And I'd like to avoid having us do the analysis as to whether Zoro. is or is not &quot;monotheistic&quot; or not.  If we can find good RS's that show the argument over whether Zoro. is or isn't monotheistic and show the large range of possible starting dates for it, and how that range overlaps the academic estimates for Judaism, that would be enough to support &quot;arguably.&quot;  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 20:48, 2 August 2012 (UTC)
:::::::: FWIW, the start class article dualism, in the [[Dualism#Duotheism, bitheism, ditheism]] section specifically mentions Zoroastrianism, although that entire section of the article is unsourced, and it is basically supposed to be a summary section of the main start-class [[Dualistic cosmology]] article, which doesn't mention Zoroastrianism at all. Granted, these tend to be less frequently edited articles, but the first maybe serves as an indicator that Zoroastrianism is counted as dualist. If anyone wants to improve those articles above start-class, preferably using reference works, academic works, or both, that would help resolve this controversy as well. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 21:04, 2 August 2012 (UTC)

OK, I have the ''Encyclopedia of Religion'' here. ''Religion Past and Present'' ain't on the shelf. The rather long article on ''Monotheism'' by Theodore M. Ludwig runs from page 6155 to 6162. It has a lot of info, and it does apparently resolve the question, although it will have to perhaps be using complicated language. Ready? Here goes.

p. 6155 - The article starts &quot;Derived from the Greek ''mono'' (&quot;single') and ''theos'' (&quot;God&quot;), the term ''monotheism'' refers to the religious experience and the philosophical perception that emphasize God as one, perfect, immutable, creator of the world from nothing, distinct from the world, all-powerfully involved in the world, personal, and worthy of being worshiped by all creatures. Some forms of monotheism, however, differ about the notions of God as distinct from the world and as personal.&quot; Thus endeth the first page.

p. 6156, from the beginning - &quot;The term ''monotheism'' has generally been used theologically rather than for philosophical or cross-cultural descriptions of religion.&quot; After the better part of a paragraph going into further details of definition, &quot;In the strict sense, ''monotheism'' best describes the idea of God in Judaism, Christianity, and Islam, and in the philosophical systems based on these traditions.&quot; So, monotheism is best applied to Judaism, Christianity, and Islam, of which Judaism is clearly oldest. Score on for Judaism. Then it goes on, &quot;But one may extend the term to include conceptions of deity in certain other traditions such as Zoroastrianism, Sikhism, and some forms of Hinduism and Buddhism, even though these traditions include somewhat different conceptions, such as the existence of evil forces alongside God, the nonpersonal nature of God, God's complete immanence in the world, or the fundamental unreality of the world.&quot; So, the definition can be extended to include others, and of those named Zoroastrianism might be the oldest. Maybe. Later that same page, &quot;Some of the most archaic peoples, such as certain groups in Africa, Australian Aborigines, and the nomadic hunters of Tiera del Fuego, have definite conceptions of a high god associated with the sky who is changeless, invisible, and all-powerful and who gives mortality.&quot; It doesn't indicate exactly which groups are being discussed anywhere in the article, so I couldn't find more info, but I suppose some of them might be argued by some as older. Maybe.

On the next page, 6157, we come to Zoroastrianism. That section starts &quot;Growing from the ancient Indo-Iranian polytheistic tradition, Zoroastrianism unified all divine reality in the high god Ahura Mazda. Zarathustra (Zoroaster), who probably lived sometime between 1700 and 1000 BCE, was a priest who turned against some of the traiditional cultic rituals and procleimed the overthrow of polytheism.&quot; It goes into the theology a little. It then continues, &quot;Conflict is accounted for as the hostility of two primordial spirits: Spenta Mainyu, the good spirit, and Angra Mainyu (Pahl., Ahriman), the evil spirit. Ahura Mazda apparently fathered these two spirits.... It appears, then, that Ahura Mazda cannot be called omnipotent, for the realm of evil is beyond his control; in that sense it may be said that this is not a complete monotheism.&quot; The section concludes, &quot;It is true that later Zoroastrianism brought some of the other gods back into the picture again. But in the teaching of Zarathustra in the ''Gathas'' is found a unique type of monotheism with an ethico-dualistic accent and an eschatological monotheistic fulfillment.&quot; 

Immediately thereafter comes the section heading, &quot;Judaism, Christianity, and Islam,&quot; which begins directly after the heading, &quot;The three religions that generally are held to be the full expressions of monotheism, Judaism, Christianity, and Islam, ... Although it was the fountainhead of this type of monotheism, the religion of ancient Israel was not actually monotheistic in early times. Stories of the patriarch Abraham show that he worshiped the Canaanite high god 'El in a variety of forms in addition to the god of the clan, and when the people of Israel entered into a covenant with the high god Yahveh they did not exclude the existence of other gods.&quot; Toward the end of that page, and the beginning of 6158, it indicates that the &quot;Prophets arose who challenged the polytheistic notion that various gods controlled the functions of nature. Elijah, and Hose, for example, held that it is only Yahveh who has power in all areas of existence, ...&quot;

Got all that? Still awake? Good. Now, to throw in some details not included. I have read in other sources, recently, that the idea put forward above that Ahura Mazda fathered Spent Mainyu and Angra Mainyu was one developed early in the 20th century, to perhaps explain the difficulties, but that since it was proposed the idea has been rejected both by academics and Zoroastrians. I would of course have to find sources for that, if required, but the text itself does indicate that Judaism is the oldest is the oldest of the groups generally held to be &quot;full expressions of monotheism&quot;. So, maybe some parsing of language will have to be done, and I will try to find Religion Past and Present to see what it has to say, but the article does provide a somewhat qualified statement to the effect that Judaism is maybe the oldest &quot;full expressionof monotheism&quot;. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 21:20, 6 August 2012 (UTC)

:Zzzzzzz.... Huh?  TLDR, so what's the answer?  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 04:25, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
: :)  Great work John... really outstanding.  Unfortunately all this really seems to do is muddy the water even a bit more.  We now have:
:*Although Judaism is considered to have origins from centuries before the Second Temple period, during that time it may be considered monolatristic instead of monotheistic.  The more exclusively monotheistic perspective of Judaism is considered to have started around the Second Temple period, around 500 BCE.  So which is the &quot;start date&quot; that we should be considering, the still-part-of-the-history-of-Judaism but apparently not-convincingly-monotheistic pre-Second Temple period, or the later Second Temple period?
:*It appears that Zoroastrianism during its origins isn't considered strictly monotheistic, but over time the attitudes of its followers evolved in a direction towards monotheism.  When did this happen?  Like we had to ask for Judaism:  Which phase of the religion should be considered the &quot;start&quot; for this comparison?
:*When actually was the time period of Zarathustra?  Between 1700 and 1000 BCE?  Some other sources date him even later.  What was the status of Judaism during that time period?
:So what do we do with the article?  There are a couple of options:
:#Do nothing, leave &quot;It is one of the oldest monotheistic religions, and the oldest to survive into the present day.&quot; as-is.
:#*Argument for:  We have a reasonably reliable source that says this explicitly, and all this analsysis is [[WP:OR]] and shouldn't be used anyway.
:#*Argument against:  The reliable source we do have is probably a tertiary source and is oversimplifying it.  There's clearly disagreement about this topic in reliable sources and the reader would be better served by providing the wider range of academic opinions that exist.
:#Mention Zoroastrianism along with it, like:  &quot;It is one of the oldest monotheistic religions, and (along with Zoroastrianism) is one of the oldest to survive into the present day.&quot;
:#*For:  Acknowledges the academic debate
:#*Against:  May open up distracting questions in the reader's mind, &quot;Zoroastrianism?  So which is it?  Why doesn't the article tell me?&quot;
:#Put a qualifier in like, &quot;It is one of the oldest monotheistic religions, and &lt;u&gt;is arguably&lt;/u&gt; the oldest to survive into the present day.&quot;  I would also put in a footnote on &quot;arguably&quot; with a sentence or two of explanation regarding the overlapping ranges of uncertainty of the start dates of the two religions, and also the subjectiveness of the application of the characterization of &quot;monotheistic&quot; by the sources.
:#*For:  Mentions the argument without introducing the distracting detail of mentioning Zoroastrianism.  Leans the argument in the direction of Judaism as the oldest surviving monotheistic religion to about the same degree that reliable sources argue that Zoroastrianism isn't strictly &quot;monotheistic.&quot;  The interested reader can read the footnote.  Conforms with [[WP:ASTONISH]] because I think most people probably think Judaism is the oldest.  (This is my preference.)
:#*Against:  Clumsiest to implement
:#Get rid of the problem by removing the claim altogether,  &quot;It is one of the oldest monotheistic religions.&quot;
:#*For:  Simplest, avoids all [[WP:OR]] issues, eliminates the the whole mess.
:#*Against:  The discussion exists in reliable sources and should be documented; if we don't put anything at all in there, some other editor will put it back.
:Thoughts?  &lt;code&gt;[[User:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#D2691E&quot;&gt;'''Zad'''&lt;/span&gt;]][[User_Talk:Zad68|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#206060&quot;&gt;''68''&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; 04:25, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
* Personally I am for keeping it, as sourced and correct in essence. If anything, just add the word &quot;arguably&quot;. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 08:28, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
** I also think we should add the word &quot;arguably&quot;. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 14:15, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
* The question seems to be about the definition of &quot;monotheism,&quot; which seems to have no clear and universally accepted definition. I would have some problems giving a specific definition of a term which apparently doesn't have one clearly obvious definition people agree on. That being the case, maybe something along the lines &quot;Of the major world religions, Judaism is considered one of the oldest monotheistic religions.&quot; That would allow us to deal with the Australian Aboriginal religions, African religion, and Tierra del Fuego group, none of which are generally counted as &quot;major world religions,&quot; so far as I can tell. I would remove the section about &quot;surviving to this day.&quot; First, that is kinda obvious, and, also, there could be and I think has been a reasonable argument that Judaism has not continued substantially unchanged since the loss of the Temple. That loss changed quite a few things. Also, honestly, I rather doubt anyone who could actually read the article would not know that Judaism still exists, so that statement might be kind of redundant. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 16:33, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
:* I support John Carters proposal too. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 16:39, 8 August 2012 (UTC)
::: John Carter's &quot;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#060;&quot;&gt;Of the major world religions, Judaism is considered one of the oldest monotheistic religions.&lt;/span&gt;&quot; is the most acceptable to me, although I would add that, with the qualifier &quot;Of the major world religions,&quot; the &quot;one of&quot; is not necessary. Thus, &quot;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#060;&quot;&gt;Of the major world religions, Judaism is considered the oldest monotheistic religion.&lt;/span&gt;&quot; (removal of &quot;one of&quot; and the made the final word, &quot;religions&quot;, singular rather than plural). — [[User:Imeriki al-Shimoni|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#60d;font-weight:bold;text-shadow:3px 3px 2px #aaa;&quot;&gt;al-Shimoni&lt;/span&gt;]] ([[User talk:Imeriki al-Shimoni|talk]]) 07:49, 9 August 2012 (UTC)
:::: The reason for the inclusion of the &quot;one of&quot; phrase is basically that Zoroastrianism, although it is admittedly a very small group today, is generally counted as a major world religion due to its long history, significant impact to world religion as a whole, due to it basically introducing linear time into religion, and at least in the past comparatively large numbers. And, as it is arguable whether it or Judaism came first, it could be that Zoroastrianism is the older of the two faiths, both of which are counted as major world religions. Having said that, saying something along the lines of &quot;Judaism is the oldest of the fully monotheistic religions&quot;, that being more or less the terminology used in the EoR, might be acceptable. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 18:26, 9 August 2012 (UTC)

:::::::&lt;s&gt;the early israelites were polytheists, and monotheism came much later. The esrly israelites were not Jews.  The article should reflect this.[[Special:Contributions/90.211.19.178|90.211.19.178]] ([[User talk:90.211.19.178|talk]]) 17:56, 18 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/s&gt; &lt;small&gt;banned sock&lt;/small&gt;

::::::::The ancient [[Israelites]] were probably [[Henotheism|henotheistic]] in their worldview, but I reckon this article is chiefly about modern [[rabbinic Judaism]] than any other expression of this [[ethnic religion]]. |P.S. ''[[Yom Kippur|Gmar chatima tova]]''. [[User:Everything Is Numbers|Everything Is Numbers]] ([[User talk:Everything Is Numbers|talk]]) 16:32, 25 September 2012 (UTC)

There are several problems with the claim. Lets start with weasling to give undue weight. The only reason to mention the blatantly obvious that it's still being practiced today is to provide a reason to say it's the oldest. The next problem you have is verifiability and reliable source. The article is not credited to an author. So it by Anonymous. The next problem is the Publisher. While PBS is a respected broadcaster, I seriously doubt they do any fact checking beyond verifying funds available on a donation check. They are a well known pay for play and publication organization. So would they refuse publication of what is obviously promotional material to a very generous donor group? So there is a perceivable conflict of interest. This is a questionable source at best. 

[[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]]) 18:30, 24 October 2012 (UTC)Magus Amathion

I was right, PBS is not a fact checking publisher. They have editorial standards and policies that producers of content must adhere to. But PBS only reviews content for compliance based on audience feedback or complaint. So if no one complains nothing is checked or reviewed. From what I've read the article cited does not comply with their editorial standards and policies. Read them for yourself. [http://www-tc.pbs.org/about/media/about/cms_page_media/35/PBS%20Editorial%20Standards%20and%20Policies.pdf PBS Editorial Standards and Policies] 

So one way to resolve this is to see if PBS will stand behind the factual integrity of this anonymously authored work the cite is derived from. 
[[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]]) 08:21, 25 October 2012 (UTC)Magus Amathion

Judaism claims a historical continuity spanning more than 3,000 years. It is one of the oldest monotheistic religions,[9] and the oldest to survive into the present day.[10]

Why is this not original research? Both the links in the first sentence lead to Wikipedia pages which cannot be used as a reliable source. Also if this is a claim made by Judaism then it should be supported by Judaic sources, not Wikipedia. This forms a lead in to redundant sentence that makes an exceptional claim that would require multiple sources. That sentence would be most properly condenced to eliminate the redundancy and say, It is the oldest monotheistic religion to survive into the present day. But can the editor find the multiple sources supporting that exceptional claim? 

What makes which of the monotheistic religion is the &quot;oldest&quot; an exceptional claim is that it is also a controversial claim. It is a matter of belief or opinion. So it cannot be stated in a matter of fact way like the grass is green. The volume of archived disputes of this should give an indication, if not serve as proof, that the claim is not generally accepted like the grass is green. I will admit that I have only searched 1 of the archives and found numerous debates on this. But if I search them all, will I find the proverbial ton of bricks? I think this needs to be more neutral to avoid undue weighting and end the enless debate. The claim of being the oldest is so exceptional and controversial. To retain the claim in a credible manner would demand a section explaining the methodology by which that conclusion is reached. Without that section the claim strain credibility. 
[[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]]) 03:26, 27 October 2012 (UTC)Magus Amathion
:The BBC (source 9) and PBS (source 10) have been accepted as [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] for as long as Wikipedia has been active.  Actually read the sentence.  It says &quot;'''one of the''' oldest,&quot; not simply &quot;oldest.&quot;  That part is fine.  As for &quot;oldest to survive to the present day,&quot; you need to actually [[WP:CITE|cite]]  a [[WP:RS|source]] saying Zoroastrianism is older, and then we have to bring in sources saying Judaism is older, and we see what the academic consensus is before deciding purely based on prior reading habits (because everyone tends to choose books that will say what we already accept).  There is no original research in the article: it simply summarizes what those two sources say.  Original research would consist of saying &quot;everything I've read says Zoroastrianism is older&quot; without citing a source, then engaging in a confirmation bias by arguing that otherwise reliable sources are unreliable simply because a complete misreading of them is outside one's prior understanding, then concluding that Zoroastrianism must be older.  I appreciate your concern for this article, but you're going about it the wrong way.  You're trying to prove a point, which is not how things are done on Wikipedia.  You're not presenting sources, which is what editors do.  While removing sources that have obvious problems is appropriate, attempting to find problems where there are none is not how things are done on Wikipedia.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 03:55, 27 October 2012 (UTC)

Ian, Just because you do not find the statement to be a problem that does not mean it is not a problem. The archives clearly show that I am not the only one that has a problem with that exceptional and controversial claim. It is not upon me to show that Zoroastrianism is older. I would have problems with that too for many of the same reasons. The burden is upon the restoring editor to show that Judaism is the oldest with multiple reliable sources. Now about the single source cited. Who is the Author? Also I have posted PBS's policy that shows that they are not a fact checking publisher. At least they do no fact checking before publication. Also this discussion and the archives show that there are multiple POV's on which is the oldest. These multiple views are not represented in the article. So this goes against the core principle of Neutrality. 

To me the first two sentences advances a position that are not properly sourced. The first two links use Wikipedia articles as a tertiary source which is not permitted. The oldest claim is only stated in the last link. There is nothing supporting the statement in the Source aka the work it's self. It is an unsupported statement. The burden is upon the restoring editor to show the reliability of the source being challenged. 

[[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]]) 18:59, 27 October 2012 (UTC)Magus Amathion
:If you really believe that PBS is not a reliable source, you may take your concern to [[WP:RSN]], as large portions of this site will need to be redone if PBS truly is not reliable (and if that is indeed your concern, rather than simply arguing that to change the article, you should bring it up there).  Otherwise, the source is fine, and the statement is sourced.  Again, you've provided no counter sources.  
:Also, your claim that Wikipedia does not allow tertiary sources is absolutely incorrect, see [[WP:PSTS]].  You do not know the reliable sourcing guidelines, and are [[Wikipedia:TE#One_who_disputes_the_reliability_of_apparently_good_source|only arguing against PBS to take down a point you personally disagree with]], for contrary ideas [[Wikipedia:TE#One_who_demands_that_others_find_sources_for_his.2Fher_own_statements|you have yet to provide any sources for]].  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 00:14, 29 October 2012 (UTC)

Ian, First of all at this point I'm going to have to say that I find your continous assertion that because I'm new I don't understand to be rude and unwelcoming. Now, Reliable Sources must be continuously reevaluated for reliability. A broken watch is a reliable source on time twice a day every day. But you can't use that to assume the broken watch is a reliable source on time 24 hours a day. PBS publishes a wide variety of subjects and has had some problem in some areas. [[Bill_Moyers#Allegations_of_bias|Bill Moyers quit his PBS show because of political pressure from a CPB executive.]] You also cannot do the reverse. You cannot assume that because PBS has had some allegations of political bias calling their credibility and reliability into question that they are not a reliable source on all subjects. I have been over the WP policy pages with a fine tooth comb. I have found nothing that says PBS is exempt from reliable source verfication. 

Also there have already been more than enough sources cited on Zoroastrianism being the oldest. There is an attempt to form a new concensus by Zad68. So why would I would want to present yet another source to be picked apart to avoid examining Debresser's Source? Sorry, I'm not taking the bait. I will continue to examine Debresser's source. 

Now as you know a Source is three things. The author, the work it's self and the publisher. Also the burden of evidence is on Debresser as the restoring editor. So I'm asking Debressor the answer three questions about the reliability of the source. 

1) Who is the author? 
2) How can you be sure of the reliability, accuracy and academic quality of the work without knowing who the author is? 
3) Do you have anything that shows that PBS or the Producer of this content is a fact checking publisher? 

[[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]]) 05:18, 29 October 2012 (UTC)Magus Amathion

:Magus, if you have a problem with the sources, please bring the matter to [[WP:RS/N]]. —&amp;nbsp;[[User:Malik Shabazz|Malik Shabazz]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Malik Shabazz|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Malik Shabazz|Stalk]]&lt;/sub&gt; 05:53, 29 October 2012 (UTC)
I have started a thread about this at [[WP:RS/N]]. The consensus there at this point is that PBS is not a reliable source for this statement.
[[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]]) 23:02, 30 October 2012 (UTC)Magus Amathion

== Judas Iscariot ==

So, does Judaism have anything to do with [[Judas Iscariot]], or why is it in that case called Judaism? I'm surprised that I couldn't find anything about it either in the article or in the talk page archives. —[[User:Kri|Kri]] ([[User talk:Kri|talk]]) 13:43, 21 October 2012 (UTC)
: It is called &quot;Judaism&quot; after the [[Tribe of Judah]], which in its turn is named after [[Judah (biblical person)]]. These predate the Judas you mention by 2000 or so years. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 17:14, 21 October 2012 (UTC)
: Judas Iscariot was a Jew, as were all of the other apostles, and Jesus himself. Judas is the Greek form of &quot;Judah&quot;; he was (ultimately) named after the Biblical Judah, as was the Tribe of Judah, and Judaism itself. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 18:36, 21 October 2012 (UTC)

== Confirmation Bias? ==

It seems to me that the page on Judaism is written from a perspective that Judaism is the stele by which all truth about Monotheism is confirmed or denied. Anything that confirms the preexisting belief or claims of Judaism is truth and anything that disputes it is falsehood. I simply do not see the same zeal to question the claims about Judaism as there is to question the claims of Zoroastrianism. There is currently a dispute as to which of the two is the oldest monotheistic religion. This dispute involves both Judaism and Zoroastrianism. But the Zoroastrian page is the only one with dispute notifications. So therefore the Judaism page must be indisputable and immutable. It's everything else in history that is suspect. Is this to preserve and protect the confirmation bias? This defies the basic logic that, barring being self conflicted, there is a minimum of two parties to every dispute. In an open minded and unbiased review of that dispute the claims of both paties must be held as being equally suspect. If not, there is a bias present and that is most likely a confirmation bias coming from preexisting knowledge. 

The preservation and protection of the confirmation bias is also causing contortion in outside subject matter to cause it to conform to the confirmation bias. The pages on Zoroaster and Zoroastrianism defy time, space and logic. You have Zoroastrianism being founded in the 6th Centurt BCE by a prophet that lived in prehistoric times and lived to be 77. So 677 BCE is prehistoric times? Zoroastrianism wasn't founded by Zarathustra? I just don't know what to make of that. So as a means of discerning the truth I look for perceivably unbiased outside observers. In this case it would be the Greek Historians. They have no dog in the fight of what is the worlds oldest monotheistic religion. There are about 6 or 7 that place the time of Zoroaster at 6,000 years before the battle of Troy. Is there there any outside sources that that confirm Judaism being 3,000 years old and being monotheistic at that time? It seems as though you have allowed Judaism and it's history to be presented unquestioningly by it's practioners. This is not a bad thing. It only becomes a bad thing when you do not afford that same right or privilege to Zoroastrians. When you go the extra mile to ensure that the claims of Zoroastrians do not conflict with Judaism and then say only of the two is disputed. When you establish different burdens of proof for the parties to the dispute. 

I think the real problem here is that you are trying to mix Religious doctrines with Scientific principles to come up with the religious equivalent of the Theory of Everything. But you must keep in mind that even in Quantum Mechanics paradox happens. You can have two conflicting statements both of which are true. I think the best way to resolve the conflicts is to seperate the religion from the science and allow the paradox to stand if only to preserve order, logic and rationality. A page about any religion and all associated claims should refeclt the beliefs and history as known by it's practioners. They should also be independant of any other pages. You should not fact check one religion against another. If you have two or more religions claiming to be the first monotheistic religion. So be it! That's a paradox that should be left for the reader to resolve to their own satisfaction. Wikipedia should not appoint themselves Judge, Jury and Executioner in these matters. What if you're wrong? What arises from this is religious debate and that is always centered in belief. Not fact. There is no scientific evidence that proves the existence of any prophet of the elder monotheistic religions. Because of that all debates that arise from them will be confined to belief. 

So I proposes subject matter divisions along these lines. Judaism(Belief)Zorostarianism (Belief)etc. Judaism(History)Zorostarianism (History)etc. Judaism(Scientific Evaluation)Zorostarianism (Scientific Evaluation)etc. But never and at anytime should anything in any successive pages be used to alter the originial statement of belief and history as known by it's practioners on any religion. That should be inviolably preserved. 

[[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]]) 20:23, 22 October 2012 (UTC)Magus Amathion

:The tags are not necessarily meant to say that one article is &quot;fact&quot; and the other is not, but that the tagged sections could stand to be improved to meet our [[WP:RULES|policies and guidelines]].  All Wikipedia does is summarize what we can find in sources, not [[WP:OR|original research]] to establish any sort of [[WP:TRUTH|&quot;Truth&quot;]] (and so there should not be a confirmation bias, which would occur from deciding &quot;this article should say this, let's find sources only for that&quot;).  I can't find any evidence of differences as a result of bias, but rather because of proper following of our [[WP:NPOV|neutrality]] and [[WP:RS|sourcing]] guidelines, an abundance of sources on Judaism and an absence for Zoroastrianism, and slightly different focuses for each article.  The Zoroastrianism article focuses more on the history of the religion than the living one (as a result of most sources taking that focus), while this article focuses on the living form instead of the history of it.  If you examine the [[Jewish history]], [[Origins of Judaism]], and [[Ancient Semitic religion]] articles, which focus on nearly the same periods as the Zoroastrianism article, there's plenty of problematic tags there.  [[WP:WIP|Wikipedia is a work in progress, and not finished]], so it should improve in time as more users with better access to a variety of sources show up, or as better sources are actually written.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 21:44, 22 October 2012 (UTC)

: Also, on Wikipedia it is customary to describe a subject first and foremost from its own, inner perspective, and only then to add academic views, controversies, etc. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 21:53, 22 October 2012 (UTC)

I think I see the source of part of the confusion. If I do a search for Judaism it take you to me to a page that tells of the living religion, as Ian said. If I do a search for Zoroastrianism it take me to a page that tells of the history, as Ian said. So I have to ask, shouldn't the page on Zoroastrianism also tell of the living religion with supporting pages on it's history and origins? I understand that Zoroastrians do much more in the way of promoting the history of the religion. That is mainly to preserve and protect what precious little is left of it. They realized that it was the centralization that allowed it to be easily destroyed. So they now spread it far and wide. But there is also information out there on Zoroastrianism as a living religion. I guess that gathering and presenting that information will be my contribution to the Zoroastrianism page. God knows it needs a lot of work.

I am new here and I will have to read up on your policies for sources. But I can honestly say that if there is a confirmation bias in a source that you cite. That confirmation bias will translate to any derivative works. But I will read up on the links that have been provided. Thank You Very Much.

[[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]]) 06:27, 24 October 2012 (UTC)Magus Amathion

This I have to dispute. 

&quot;and the oldest to survive into the present day.[10]&quot;

The source is a PBS article that does not even mention Zoroastrianism which has also survived into present day. So the source shows a confirmation or myside bias. There's much more to monotheism than Abrahamic monotheism. Also Judaism being the &quot;oldest&quot; is hotly disputed. This is stated as fact. Part of the statement is hotly disputed and the rest is simply untrue.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:MagusAmathion|MagusAmathion]] ([[User talk:MagusAmathion|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/MagusAmathion|contribs]]) 08:58, 24 October 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
: We have discussed this question many times on this talkpage. Feel free to read sections higher up on this page, and on its archives. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 10:09, 24 October 2012 (UTC)
::Wikipedia only sets out to summarize sources, not to prove or disprove any particular thing (in other words, the only &quot;should&quot; is &quot;should summarize the sources&quot;).  If there are not enough sources on a subject, that's not our fault but academia's.  If you have [[WP:RS|reliable sources (as described here)]] which say something the article does not, you're welcome to add on to the article. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 18:43, 24 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mckch00ls6kqz1kph8o7tayaysux1ks</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
