<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Criticism of religion</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2837764</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520560712</id>
      <parentid>520353956</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-30T08:35:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Proxima Centauri</username>
        <id>6913203</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Theodore Beale - Counterarguments to religion as harmful to individuals */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23191">{{skiptotoctalk}}
{{calm talk}}
{{talk header |search=yes }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 5
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Criticism of religion/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months |dounreplied=yes}}
{{controversial}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
 {{WikiProject Philosophy|importance=High|class=B|religion=yes}}
 {{WikiProject Atheism|class=B|importance=High}}
 {{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
 {{WikiProject Christianity
  |importance= mid |class= B
  |core-topics-work-group= yes |core-topics-work-group-importance= 
  |theology-work-group= yes |theology-importance= mid
  |anglicanism= yes |anglicanism-importance= Mid
  |catholicism= yes |catholicism-importance=Mid
  |latter-day-saint-movement= yes |latter-day-saint-movement-importance=mid
  }}
 {{WikiProject Bahá'í Faith|class=B|importance=low}}
 {{WikiProject Islam|class=B|importance=low}}
 {{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=low}}
 {{WikiProject Hinduism|class=B|importance=Low}}
}}
{{todo|small=yes}}
{{clear}}

== POV on this article ==

I realise this is an article on 'criticism of religion', however it is important that opposing cases of equal strength need to be made throughout. There are also a number of rather disturbing statements that pass without comment, for example, &quot;Hitchens also argues that virginity is unhealthy, and can lead to emotional problems&quot; Is Hitchens arguing for child sex? The implications of his statement are severe. 
[[User:Ion Zone|Ion Zone]] ([[User talk:Ion Zone|talk]]) 14:11, 14 March 2012 (UTC)
:I would see nothing wrong with adding a source of a credible critic who is actually responding to Hitchens' point. But Hitchens, who just recently died, was clearly not talking about pedophilia, and I think that you know it. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 00:03, 15 March 2012 (UTC)

== Criticism of religious concepts section problems ==

I am chiming in on the problems in this section. There are a few bullet points and other points which &quot;need citation&quot; from 1-2 years ago and no one has provided any. I will delete these bullet points in 3 days if no one provides citations for these points. Clearly an early editor who wrote much of this section was simply making assertions based on biases and intuitions, not neutrality and references. I have already tried to, broaden the anthropological reality of religions, reduce redundancy, reduce biased terminology, and add reliable references to give adequate contexts in this section and other parts of the article, but I am giving the editors one final chance to provide references for these old points. It seems no one has cared to defend certain points in 1-2 years which means its time to remove many uncited claims not just in this section but in other parts of this article. This is in hopes of reducing bias, and increasing neutrality and citations to make this article better. I will also begin to clean up other sections of this article in a similar manner in 3 days since it is in need of significant revision. [[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 18:51, 21 April 2012 (UTC)
:Thanks for posting in talk so as to give others an opportunity to respond. Although I don't feel very strongly about those particular points, I have a feeling they might indeed be sourceable. I'll try to find sources, but it might take a bit more time than the deadline you are suggesting. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 20:32, 21 April 2012 (UTC)
::Sounds good, if you can find some citations in say about a week or two then that would be good. Is that a good timeline? I really appreciate your interest in trying to make this article better. I am attempting to make this article more accurate and neutral little by little as it seems much of it was neglected by previous editors who simply stuck in their points of views without cleaning up some of their mess (lack of clarity, redundancy, uncited claims, irrelevant entries, hasty generalizations, etc.) perhaps due to negative bias on the contents. [[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 23:58, 21 April 2012 (UTC)
:::Thanks! [[WP:There is no deadline]]. I'll do what I can, and, if worse comes to worse, please just make whatever edits you think best, with the understanding that (of course) I or others may modify them subsequently. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 00:43, 23 April 2012 (UTC)
::Hey Tryptofish, I saw your latest edit. I originally reorganized what you moved to be under the counterarguments to Point 1 on science.  Since Point 2 mentioned the garment example, it seemed more relevant to be put under the counterarguments to point 1.  That is this is how it looked : Point 1, Point 2, Point 3, then right after it Counter Point 1, Counter Point 2 (what you moved), Counter Point 3 (not available). I think what you moved is more relevant where it was before. Maybe counter point 3 will be added in the future. What do you think of this structure? Without Counter Point 2, this section looks really asymmetrical. [[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 05:58, 28 June 2012 (UTC)
:::If we are talking about the Jewish issues of child punishment and garment fabrics (is that it? I'm not sure), I'd almost be tempted to delete the whole thing, as being a kind of POV-pushing for a very specific pair of examples within just one religion, or at least as being UNDUE. I figured I'd compromise by editing out the worst parts and putting it down lower, instead of getting rid of it completely. I don't feel that it really rebuts anything. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 13:41, 28 June 2012 (UTC)
:: The only citation given for point 2 - &quot;Religions often require behaviors that are not sensible&quot; is from Hitchens examples on Jewish garments and child punishment presumably. Hitchens examples were already specific. This is why the counterargument was brought up by someone else and it was put in that same sentence originally - to counter those points about garments and child punishment. Because of this I moved the counterargument lower to leave the critisim points stand independently again. Since this counter argument was aimed at Hitchen's points then that is why I left it within the proximity of this section, just not on the same sentence. Any thoughts?[[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 17:20, 28 June 2012 (UTC)
:::Oh, I didn't see that until now. I can partly agree that it's reasonable to bring those back together, then. But, if I didn't see the connection, neither will a lot of our readers. The section would need to be rewritten (probably a good idea) to move the Hitchens etc material out of the bullet list and into paragraph text, with the rebuttal coming directly after what it rebuts, not coming a couple of paragraphs later. In addition, the rebuttal should not be longer than the original statement. This page is about criticisms of religion, not responses to criticisms of religions, except to the extent that [[WP:NPOV]] requires giving both sides. So either the rebuttal should be shortened, or Hitchens should be quoted more extensively. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 00:31, 29 June 2012 (UTC)
::::I started to make some minor revisions to it, but then I realized a problem. [[WP:SYNTH]] says that we cannot make connections based upon editor opinion, as opposed to based on reliable sources. Seeing the material put back next to what Hitchens said made me realize that an early commentary on the Old Testament could not possibly be responding to Hitchens' writings. (I'm leaving out considerations of prophecy, of course!) Therefore, it is SYNTH to say that those commentaries were a rebuttal of Hitchens' criticisms. I've deleted it entirely, for that reason, although I'd be willing to consider adding something like it back in a more appropriate context. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 23:17, 2 July 2012 (UTC)
::::: Hmmm... That is true. Good catch. Maybe it would be better to reword as ''Historical commentaries have explained the reasoning behind certain norms or customs, which are seen as non-sensible behaviors by some modern critics. For example,  prohibition of mixed fabrics and punishment of the children is explained in [[Rashi]], an early commentary on Jewish literature. Children are punished only if they also commit the same sins as the parents and the mixed fabric prohibition does not apply to all fabrics, but rather refers to a concept called [[Shatnez]], which reserves one specific type of fiber blend for ceremonial purposes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chabad.org/parshah/torahreading.asp?AID=15567&amp;p=5&amp;showrashi=true#v7 Rashi's explanation of the verse] or [http://www.chabad.org/parshah/article_cdo/aid/850586/jewish/Interpolated-Translation.htm#footnoteRef100a850586 Verse 7 here]&lt;/ref&gt; ''  - what do you think? [[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 00:16, 3 July 2012 (UTC)
::::::But that still ends up being SYNTH. The criticisms belong on this page (and the early analyses belong on other pages, dealing with theological discussions), but for editors to present the early analyses as being counterpoints to the criticisms is original research, unless we have a modern secondary source that points to those early analyses explicitly as a rebuttal to modern criticisms. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 00:26, 3 July 2012 (UTC)

:Hey Tryptofish, I think the two sections should be combined since they are related to each other. Both essentially are about dynamics, not rigidity of people's affiliations. In terms of the quote, explicit atheism (dismissal of all gods) is the context of the quote - The way one rejects all other gods one could also reject this one too. But the previous sentence notes that the criticism is &quot;claims of all but one of those religions must be wrong.&quot; That would mean that the more adequate quote would have to say something like &quot;I dismiss all gods except this one&quot; to match the claim in the previous sentence, not dismissal of all. Also since not all religions have gods, I don't think this captures the criticism adequately. I think the criticism is good without the quote and is self explanatory. I hope to consolidate other parts in the article and compound some of the quotes (if they are consistent) in this article since they take up more space than is needed. What do you think? [[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 22:34, 17 July 2012 (UTC)
::Oh, well, I agree to the extent that the quote only captures one part of the criticism, but I don't think that's a reason to delete it. And I reverted your combination of the two sections because I think the sources tend to treat the two kinds of criticism as distinct. I don't see a need to do a lot of consolidation along these lines, so I guess I have low enthusiasm for what you propose, sort of a solution in search of a problem. You'll need to convince me, case by case, that there is superfluous material. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 22:49, 17 July 2012 (UTC)
:::Glad to hear your thoughts on this. How about we do this: we can keep the quote (even though I don't think it is needed or reflects the criticism appropriately), but I don't think it requires the big quotes it has. I think it can be integrated into the section with better flow and so can other &quot;big quotes&quot;. Also, too many quotes and section titles makes the whole article too spread out. I think some of this can be reduced/consolidated. Feel free to revert or re-add things.[[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 23:02, 17 July 2012 (UTC)
::::Take a look through [[:Template:Quote#See also]], where there's a list of ways to format quotations. I agree with you that the big quote marks are kind of over-the-top. There are a couple of ways that give smaller quotes, without having to simply put the quote into plain paragraph text, and they may be good alternatives to consider. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 23:09, 17 July 2012 (UTC)
:::::Hey thanks for the link! I'll use it. The some quotes are good. They just need to be tucked away or highlighted differently. Just by dealing with quotes alone I think this article will at least look better. The other stuff, I'll work on later. [[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 23:29, 17 July 2012 (UTC)
::::::I did a few sections. I removed some unnecessary info to make it more neutral. People don't always need to be introduced in articles over and over - the links to their pages should suffice. I tried doing repeated reference i.e. &lt;ref name=&quot;name&quot; /&gt; but I couldn't introduce a quote in there for some quotes. There were a grip of quotes so far. Only major quotes should be put in a box and minor quotes integrated in the article or tucked with the respective references. Working my way down. I tried &lt;ref name=&quot;name&quot; /&gt; |quote= and other combinations , but it didn't work. Do you know how to do it? I looked at some templates, but no success. Anyways, I'll continue on this tomorrow. If you see anything that needs to change feel free to change. At the moment, I am simply trying to make the article more neutral and structure less bumpy. Too many small paragraphs for example. I think we can combine some.[[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 05:16, 18 July 2012 (UTC)

== Discrimination, Persecution ==

In the negative effects of religion on both individuals and on society I am surprised at the avoidance of discussion about the generation of, and the consequences of, religion-generated discrimination and persecution. The negative aspects on both perpetrators and victims, physical and psychological, are not effectively addressed at all. For example, anti-Semetic passages in the New Testament remain intact in great quantities of Bibles distributed by non-Jewish organizations and individuals, in spite of numerous apologies, denials and objections from both religious and secular sources. These passages are clearly contributors to continuation of bigotry, particularly among people who are poorly informed, and cause severe trauma to Jewish people who feel themselves stigmatized. Jewish children are often bewildered at negative treatment from their peers, often from other children who have primarily vague intolerance fostered by biblical references. Particularly confusing is to hear Christian evangelists declare the Bible inerrant while at the same time apologizing for undeserved archaic intolerance.
[[Special:Contributions/99.127.138.224|99.127.138.224]] ([[User talk:99.127.138.224|talk]]) 17:49, 1 May 2012 (UTC)
:I think that you raise some good points. To add this material to the article, however, we need to be able to cite sources for it. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 00:55, 2 May 2012 (UTC)

== Confucianism - religion ==

The lead writes:

&lt;blockquote&gt;With the existence of diverse categories of religion such as monotheism, polytheism, pantheism, nontheism and diverse specific '''religions''' such as Christianity, Judaism, Islam, Taoism, '''Confucianism,''' Buddhism, and many others; it is not always clear to whom the criticisms are aimed at or to what extent they are applicable to other religions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Confucianism]], although lived by like many religions, is a philosophy, and not a religion. --&lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px dashed;padding:1px 4px 1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User:Activism1234|&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;Activism&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]][[User talk:Activism1234|&lt;font color=&quot;darkred&quot;&gt;1234&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;/small&gt; 01:20, 26 July 2012 (UTC)
:The article on Confucianism, which you linked, makes it clear that debate over whether it is a religion or not is ongoing. Part of the discussion is over the defintion of &quot;religion&quot; itself, and the article indicates that Confucianism does contain several elements taken directly from non-Confucian religious beliefs including ancestor worship and the notion of makling offerings to non-corporial beings. There seems to be little question that, however it is classified, Confucianism holds a place equivalent to religion in the lives of adherents. [[User:TechBear|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;'''TechBear'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &amp;#124; [[User talk:TechBear|Talk]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Contributions/TechBear|Contributions]] 13:18, 26 July 2012 (UTC)
::The historical sources I have studied have often included Confucianism as a &quot;religion&quot; when writing an essay, for example, but have made clear that in reality it is a philosophy and not a real religion, regardless of whether they borrowed stuff from other religions.  Indeed, many Chinese people who were Confucianists did have varying religions.  If the discussion is ongoing, shouldn't that mean we lean towards the safer side, and remove it for now from that sentence?  Look, I'm not a Confucianist, I just saw the lead and noticed it and wanted to bring it up. --&lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px dashed;padding:1px 4px 1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User:Activism1234|&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;Activism&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]][[User talk:Activism1234|&lt;font color=&quot;darkred&quot;&gt;1234&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;/small&gt; 13:27, 26 July 2012 (UTC)
::: Define &quot;real religion,&quot; please, without relying on the [[No true Scotsman]] fallacy. My point is that regardless of whether or not Confucianism is a &quot;real&quot; religion, it has a place in social and personal life akin to religion. I would assert that this is sufficient grounds for including Confucianism in this sidebar. [[User:TechBear|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;'''TechBear'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &amp;#124; [[User talk:TechBear|Talk]] &amp;#124; [[Special:Contributions/TechBear|Contributions]] 15:43, 26 July 2012 (UTC)
::::I don't know what the Scottsman fallacy is, but I'd like to reiterate I don't find this as a controversial hot pressing boilerplate topic that needs to be immediatelly addressed, with many inputs, and heated arguments.  I just want to discuss this in a friendly and polite way, that is all.  The Confuciniasm article does have a nice interesting section on Classification, but it's more accepted, and therefore how the lead is structured, as an ethical and philosophical way to live life.  And using stricter definitions of religion, it certainly isn't one.  Why should we lean towards the more lenient one, rather than the stricter one, or lean towards the fact being there isn't any consensus about it and therefore doesn't deserve our personal opinion in the lead to say that it definitely is a religion?  That's what the sentence says. --&lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px dashed;padding:1px 4px 1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User:Activism1234|&lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;Activism&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;]][[User talk:Activism1234|&lt;font color=&quot;darkred&quot;&gt;1234&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;/small&gt; 16:41, 26 July 2012 (UTC)
::::: Greetings to both editors. I have been watching the exchanges on this and though I agree with TechBear on much of what he says (general anthropology of religion shows that many religions are not like we generally think of them i.e. Hua, Church of Satan, or Raelianism, Unitarian Universalism, and sociologists have spoken of &quot;civil religion&quot;) it is probably best to just take &quot;Confucianism&quot; out of the intro since the intro is just citing examples of &quot;specific&quot; religions and is not meant to be exhaustive. Removing it or not does not really affect the article in any significant way. I will make a bold removal, but if someone thinks it should be re-added, then please go for it.[[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 06:45, 27 July 2012 (UTC)

== Theodore Beale - Counterarguments to religion as harmful to individuals ==

Responding in the book The Irrational Atheist to criticisms that religion is harmful, [[Theodore Beale]] argues that religious individuals tend to be happier and healthier, more likely to have children, and more sexually satisfied than non-religious individuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irrational Atheist&quot;&gt;[[Theodore Beale|Beale, Theodore]] as Vox Day, ''[[The Irrational Atheist]]'', Benbella Books, 2008. ISBN 978-1-933771-36-6&lt;/ref&gt;  '''[[PZ Myers]] has suggested more than once that Beale is extremely unreasonable. &lt;ref&gt;[http://scienceblogs.com/pharyngula/2008/03/12/why-do-we-even-stoop-to-mentio/ Why do we even stoop to mentioning Vox Day?];[http://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2012/06/06/vox-day-is-one-sick-puppy/ Vox Day is one sick puppy];&lt;/ref&gt; Myers also linked to Mark C. Chu-Carroll who criticised Beale similarly. &lt;ref&gt;[http://scienceblogs.com/goodmath/2008/03/12/vox-day-on-women-in-science/ Vox Day on Women in Science]&lt;/ref&gt; These two are the relevant links to PZ Myers.'''
&lt;references/&gt;

The section I emboldened was taken out of the article.  I don't think it was an [[Ad hominem]].  Biologist and academic, [[PZ Myers]] believes Beale is unreasonable and if Myers is right this is a sound reason to reject Beale's arguments.  Can the above text be put back into the article, perhaps with different wording? [[User:Proxima Centauri|Proxima Centauri]] ([[User talk:Proxima Centauri|talk]]) 18:51, 28 October 2012 (UTC)
: Hey Proxima Centauri, I see what you are saying, but the blog citations you entered are mainly focusing about criticism of Vox Day, not criticism of religion. They also do personal attacks on him (ad hominem). Overall, the focus is clearly personal on the citations you put in the article. Therefore, these citations don't belong here, they belong where they already were - in [[Theodore Beale]]'s biography page. If I found a blog cite saying that PZ Meyers is very unreasonable too, I would say that would not be appropriate here also as none of these would be criticisms religion - they would only be criticisms of PZ Meyers. The reason why personal criticisms are not appropriate here is because it could lead to [[WP:coatracking]] and going off topic. 

:I thought maybe the women blog post could be included, but Vox's claim was more of an opinion and Mark Chu-Carroll's rebuttal was merely anecdotal and was clearly focused on Vox as a person and certainly not criticisms of religion or his arguments. That being said, it would actually be appropriate to add a source that focused *mainly* on some criticism of religion or countering Vox Day's arguments, but not Vox himself. The focus of a source here has to be clearly on a topic, argument, or counter, but not on personal distaste. The emphasis and scope given by any source is the key to these criticism pages. Just be careful with blogs since sometimes they are too personal. I hope you are not taking this in a bad way as I mean no harm. You have done some very good entries here. Keep up the good work. Just a few thoughts. --[[User:Ramos1990|Ramos1990]] ([[User talk:Ramos1990|talk]]) 19:14, 28 October 2012 (UTC)
::I'm very busy elsewhere at the moment, I'll come back when I have time. [[User:Proxima Centauri|Proxima Centauri]] ([[User talk:Proxima Centauri|talk]]) 08:35, 30 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>637art01v63w9hhpabyhl57a05eq5t5</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
