<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Dharma</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>574334</id>
    <revision>
      <id>507816991</id>
      <parentid>507816899</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-17T10:13:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/188.220.151.59|188.220.151.59]] - &quot;/* jainism section is terrible */ new section&quot;</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14832">{{Talk header}}
{{User:WildBot/m01|dabs={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Granth}}, {{User:WildBot/m03|1|Shabad}}|m01}}
{{User:WildBot/m04|sect={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Indo-Aryan languages#Contemporary languages|contemporary Indian languages}}|m04}}
{{oldpeerreview|archive=1}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Hinduism|class=B|importance=Top|krishna=yes|phil=yes}}
{{WikiProject Buddhism|class=B|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Zoroastrianism|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Tibetan Buddhism|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Jainism|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|importance=high|class=B|eastern=yes|religion=yes}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=B|category=Philrelig}}
}}

{{User:MiszaBot/config
|maxarchivesize = 80K
|counter = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Dharma/Archive %(counter)d
}}

{{archive box|
[[/Archive 1|2004 –]]
}}

== Why is this page part of Hinduism ==

Hello, I just clicked Dharma in Buddhism and was directed here.  Then I typed Buddahdharma and was again directed here. This page should be representation of all darma related religions.  I will off &quot;WikiProject Hinduism&quot;. [[User:FWBOarticle|FWBOarticle]]

== Hinduism portal shifted ==

There must be dozen of different indian origin religion which use dharma. There is no point and no space to put all of it in intro. Each portal should be placed where each secton of respective religion are. Plus, previous placement was bit biased toward Hinduism. [[User:FWBOarticle|FWBOarticle]]

== Sorry, still bais towards hindus ==

This page is still bais towards hindu concepts of Dharma


== What is Dharma ==

What is DHARM?
 The term Dharma is an Indian spiritual and religious term that means one's righteous duty, or any virtuous path. A Hindu's dharma is affected by a person's age, class, occupation, and gender. In Indian languages it can be equivalent simply to religion, depending on context. The word dharma translates as that which upholds or supports, and is generally translated into English as law.
According to the various Indian religions, such as Hinduism, Buddhism, Jainism, and Sikhism, beings that live in accordance with Dharma proceed more quickly toward dharma yukam, moksha or nirvana (personal liberation). The antonym of dharma is adharma meaning unnatural or immoral.
In traditional Hindu society, dharma has historically denoted a variety of ideas, such as Vedic ritual, ethical conduct, caste rules, and civil and criminal law. Its most common meaning however pertains to two principal ideals: that social life should be structured through well-defined and well-regulated classes (varna), and that an individual's life within a class should be organized into defined stages (ashrama, see dharmasastra).[4]
{{cot|1=Lots of stuff most other editors can't read; stuff that really fails [[WP:NOR]]}}
श्रीर्वै धर्म: , राज्यं वै धर्म: , धर्मणो धारयति ! जै 3.231
            According to Vedic traditions 
“Dharma is that which sustains a welfare state”, and consists of Don’ts and Duties अपने चित्त वृत्तियों में उपलब्ध करो अन्यथा नि:सार रह जावोगे
Cultivate the virtue to gather strength, otherwise you will suffer deprivation
यद्येकवृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि ! अथर्व वेद 5/16/1
यदि द्वि वृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि ! अथर्व वेद 5/16/2
यदि त्रि वृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि ! अथर्व वेद 5/16/3
यदि चतुर्वृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि ! अथर्व वेद 5/16/4
यदि पञ्चवृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि !  अथर्व वेद 5/16/5
üयदि षड्वृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि ! अथर्व वेद 5/16/6
यदि सप्त वृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि !  अथर्व वेद 5/16/7 
üयद्यष्ट वृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि !  अथर्व वेद 5/16/8
यदि नवष्टषोSसि सृजारसोSसि अथर्व वेद 5/16/9
यदि दश वृषोSसि सृजारसोSसि अथर्व वेद 5/16/10  
यद्येकादशोSसि सृजारसोSसि अथर्व वेद 5/16/11

Veda is saying here that there are ten aspects of Dharma.
All of these aspects of Dharma have to be cultivated in your temperament. Leaving out even one of them will render you at default.
वेद के अनुसार यदि धर्म के एक अंग को ही गृहण कर चुके हो  तो नि:सार रह जावोगे, यदि धर्म के दो अंगों को भी गृहण कर चुके हो तो भी नि:सार रह जावोगे. यदि धर्म के दसों अंगों को भी धारण कर चुके हो तो बिना प्रभु भक्ति के नि:सार रह जावोगे.
RV 10.47.6 Dharma comprises of   sustainable duties of people
 प्र सप्तगुमृतधीतिं सुमेधां बृहस्पतिं मतिरच्छा जिगाति ।
य आङ्गिरसो नमसोपसद्यो।Sस्मभ्यं चित्रं वृ षणं रयिं दाः ।। ऋ 10-47-6 

प्रसप्तगुमृतधीतिं सुमेधा- सप्त मर्यादा पालक उत्तम वृत्ति युक्त 
बृहस्पति-  good articulate skills
मतिरच्छा जिगाति  -  invokes good common sense
(Dharma sustains the Society by सप्त मर्यादा seven tenets. These are human values that sustain the society. Vedic Dharma did not entail personal ritualistic procedures for individuals in the society)
The seven tenets that form the Vedic Dharma are spelled out in Atharv Veda as:

सप्त मर्यादा: कवयस्ततक्षुस्तासामिदेकमभ्यं Sहुरो गात् !
आयोर्हस्कम्भ उपमस्य नीदे पथां विसर्गे धरुणेषु तस्थौ !! अथर्व 5/1/6

These seven trespasses are 1.Theiving. 2, Adulterous behavior,3. Anti knowledge activities,4. Abortions,  5. Drunken behavior,6. Habitual addiction to wickedness,7, Giving false evidence 
  
1.	चोरी,2.अगम्यागमन ,3. ब्रह्महत्या,4. भ्रूणहत्या,5. मद्यपान,6.पुन: पुन: पाप कर्म में प्रवृत्ति,7. पाप करके झूट बोलना बोलनाये निषिद्धाचरणा परित्याग रूप सात नियम  बताए गए हैं. इन में से जो एक का भी उल्लंघन करता है वह पापी है. यही सात मर्यादाएं वैदिक दृष्टि से मानव धर्म हैं. यही समाज को धारण कर के प्रलय तक स्थिरता देती हैं.
2.	
 सुख की वृद्धि करने हारा, सब ऐश्वर्य का दाता धर्म है, उस का जो जो लोप करता है उस को विद्वान लोग वृषल समझते हैं : दयानन्द संस्कार विधि 1/5

(धर्म के दस अंग क्या हैं ?)
 मनुस्मृति के अनुसार वृषो हि भगवान्‌ धर्मः। 
 धर्म वही है जो सुख की ऐश्वर्य की वर्षा करता है।
  वृषो हि भगवान्धर्मस्य यः कुरुते ह्यलम्‌ ।
 वृषलं तं विदुर्देवास्तस्माद्धर्मं न लोपयेतऽ ॥ मनु 8-16
 
धर्म लक्षणम्‌ - Creative Duties 
 सकारात्मक आचरण -Positive actions
 धर्मो  मनुष्याः।  Humanity itself is Dharma.
 धर्मो वा अधिपतिः । That which governs a Human is his Dharma
 
&quot; धृति क्षमा दमोऽस्तेय शौचमिन्द्गिय निग्रहः।
    धी विद्या सत्यमक्रोधो दशकं धर्म लक्षणम्‌  ॥&quot; मनुः 6-92
 
धैर्य,क्षमा,असत्प्रवृत्तियों का दमन, चोरी छल कपट त्याग, मन वाणी शरीर की पवित्रता,इन्द्गिय निग्रह, ज्ञानार्जन, सत्यपालन, क्रोध त्याग, ये दश लक्षण धर्म के बताये जाते हैं।)


There are ten attributes of Dharma viz:
 1.धृतिः- Forbearance, Sobriety, Resoluteness
 2.क्षमाः- Forgiveness- covering a wider range of meanings 
            such as Amnesty, Charity, Clemency, Mercy, Non 
            violence
 3.दमोः- Suppression of unbecoming tendencies
 4.अस्तेयं :- To avoid Stealing, Deceit, Dishonesty, Blackmail, Scam
 5.शौच :- Purification- cleanliness, internal &amp; external 
6. इन्द्गियनिग्रहः :- Control over desires
 7. धी :- Cultivation of right mentality by expanding 
         intellect &amp; avoiding negative influences 
 8.विद्या :-   Knowledge, about every thing in this world and beyond
 9.सत्यम्‌ :- Truthfulness
10.अक्रोधो :- Avoiding Anger, Hatred, Unhappiness 
     to Cultivate calmness, happiness

 These ten are the attributes of DHARMA
 
दश आजीविकायें
  &quot; विद्या शिल्पं भृतिः सेवाः गोरक्ष्यं विपणिः कृषिः।
    धृतिर्भैक्ष्यं  कुसीदं  च  दश  जीवनहेतवः  ॥ मनुः 10-116

 सप्त मर्यादा
 
सप्त मर्यादाःकवस्ततक्षुस्तासामिदेकामभ्यं हुरो गात्‌।
 आयोर्हस्कम्भ उपमस्य नीडे पथां विसर्गे ध्रुणेषु तस्थौ ॥ अथर्व 5-1-6
  सात मर्यादाएं
1। चोरी,2ऽगम्यागमन,3।ब्रह्म हत्या, 4भ्रूण हत्या,5।मद्यपान,6।पुनः पुनः पाप कर्म में प्रवृत्ति,7।पाप कर के झूठ बोलना
{{cob}}
&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Subodh1934|Subodh1934]] ([[User talk:Subodh1934|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Subodh1934|contribs]]) 16:32, 2 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Please read the [[WP:RS|reliable sourcing guidelines]], [[WP:NPOV|neutral point of view guidelines]], the [[WP:NOR|no original research guidelines]], and understand that [[WP:SOAPBOX|Wikipedia is not a means of promoting any belief]]. You you state simply what you would like to accomplish here? [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 16:38, 2 May 2011 (UTC)

== The common problem with all spiritual teachings ==

The common problem with all spiritual teachings is that with the author not available for comment all objectivity evaporates. With Hinduism and Hinduism originated teachings (religions are semitic in origin) that is not a particular issue, as at their core subjectivity rains supreme.

As this is only relevant for those who wish, and are cabable, of reaching a deeper understanding of said teachings, I do not expect to see a wikipedia article attempting to explain that. However, for all those reaching this article in search for something more than a basic understanding of the subject or a brush with &quot;dry philosophy&quot;, along with examples of dharma as structure, order, law etc in the introduction, a brief reference should be included hinting to the existence of more profound versions of dharma.

The section that attempts to explain dharma as pertaining to Jainism does the truth a lot more justice by mentioning that &quot;dharma is of two kinds, for the householders and for the monks&quot; As the closest equivalent to a monk, would be referred to as a mystic in Hinduism, an analogous phrase should be included to the introduction.

An alternate suggestion would be to include another version of dharma amongst all those already provided. That of Arya Dharma.
&quot;Arya Dharma 'Noble' Truths): the four central tenets of Buddha's original teachings.&quot;
Quote from &quot;The Oneness/Otherness Mystery&quot; by Sutapas Bhattacharya, in Commentary, page 177.
That is how it appears in the book, with the missing &quot; ( &quot;.
Doing so though, would, in my opinion, simply add to the confusion.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/113.199.145.90|113.199.145.90]] ([[User talk:113.199.145.90|talk]]) 15:55, 21 June 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== jainism section is terrible ==

it doesn't read well and is full of unexplained foreign language.
could someone clean it up please? as it is it adds nothing understandable to the article that has any relevance, and adds nothing to the understanding of jainism either. the hindu and buddhist sections are fine, but a native english speaker familiar with the subject would be a better author (translations of the foreign language would do, barely)
teknotiss (can't be bothered to sign in, too much hassle for just this)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/188.220.151.59|188.220.151.59]] ([[User talk:188.220.151.59|talk]]) 10:12, 17 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>7sicsdk2adffxul76w5v3t8613dbigu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
