<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Book of Genesis</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>12668</id>
    <revision>
      <id>501487016</id>
      <parentid>501352274</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-10T00:58:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MiszaBot I</username>
        <id>3797869</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: Archiving 2 threads (older than 60d) to [[Talk:Book of Genesis/Archive 4]].</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5737">{{WikiProjectBannerShell
|1=
{{WPReligion|class=B|importance=High|Interfaith=yes|InterfaithImp=}} 
{{ChristianityWikiProject|importance=high|class=B}}
{{WikiProject Bible|class=B|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Religious texts|class=B| importance= high}}
{{WikiProject Judaism | class= B | importance= high }}
}}
{{archive box|
*[[Talk:Book of Genesis/archive1|Archive 1]]
*[[Talk:Book of Genesis/archive2|Archive 2]]}}  


{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 150K
|counter = 4
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:Book of Genesis/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== Mythology and Bias ==

Shouldn't this article, just as well as other religious articles (e.g. the article on the [[Vedas]] (and the [[Rigveda]] in specific)), state that this book gives the Mythological account of the creation of the world?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/83.254.115.121|83.254.115.121]] ([[User talk:83.254.115.121|talk]]) 17:35, 12 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:My reading of the Book of Genesis is that it's divided into three parts: mythological, legendary, and quasi-historical. Mythological is everything up to the Tower of Babel. Legendary is the story of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. Quasi-historical is the last third of the book dealing with Joseph.

:In the subsequent Book of Exodus, Moses spends forty years in the wilderness carrying the most sacred object of the Jewish people: the bones of Joseph. In the sixth book of the Bible, the bones of Joseph are finally buried in the Holy Land.

:Every hero needs a lineage of illustrious legendary ancestors, typically three in a row. Alexander the Great had Socrates, Plato, and Aristotle as spiritual ancestors, all three of whom would have been long forgotten if Aristotle hadn't been tutor to Alexander. Similarly, someone needed to establish Joseph's credentials, so they gave him Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. Later, when the tribe of Joseph formed alliance with other tribes, they gave Joseph eleven brothers.

:At least that's one perspective from contemporary (non-Orthodox) Jewish theology. [[User:Zyxwv99|Zyxwv99]] ([[User talk:Zyxwv99|talk]]) 20:29, 21 January 2012 (UTC)

== Edit warring over &quot;In a beginning&quot; or &quot;In the beginning&quot; ==

User Sbeystrom has been repeatedly reverting to his version without regard to the three revert rule which limits edit warring.  That isn't the way decisions can be made on wikipedia in the event of disagreement.  Instead, they can be made on the discussion page here.  You could be blocked from editing for the number of times you have restored your edit in one day after it was reverted by various users. 

You say there are major theological impacts if BERESHYT is translated into English as you say, &quot;In a beginning&quot;.  This is a matter of differing Bible interpretations, so you need more sources to make the case for your favorite interpretation, and the reasons for having more than one interpretation of that verse need to be detailed in the actual article, with information about who has favored one interpretation or the other, and why it is a major &quot;theological impact&quot; if that is indeed what sources say.   My position is that it is irrelevant to the original Hebrew language how one chooses to translate it into modern English since there is no difference in the Hebrew concept between In &quot;the&quot; beginning or In &quot;a&quot; beginning, either one would be expressed the same way in Hebrew without any need to question which one it is.  There is no other way to say &quot;In THE beginning&quot; than BERESHYT so that is why the vast majority of common usage opts for that smoother English rendering. [[User:Til Eulenspiegel|Til Eulenspiegel]] ([[User talk:Til Eulenspiegel|talk]]) 00:24, 8 November 2011 (UTC)

:Til E. is correct. I'd just add that we have perhaps half a dozen good Genesis commentaries in the bibliography, about half of which discuss the name of the book, and every one of those plumps for &quot;in the beginning&quot;. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 23:40, 11 November 2011 (UTC)

== &quot;In fact&quot; ==

I'm a bit concerned over the phrase &quot;Tradition credits Moses as the author of Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers and Deuteronomy, but the books are in fact anonymous and look back on Moses as a figure from the distant past.&quot;  It comes across as &quot;end of story&quot; with no room for debate.  &quot;Tradition&quot; credits Moses as the author because it's believed to be true.  In light of this, unless there's substantial evidence to the contrary, there really shouldn't be any &quot;but...in fact...&quot;  As it is a contrary (and valid) belief, its assertion that the books are anonymously written should indeed be included, but not in a manner that invalidates another set of firmly held beliefs.  Just my two cents.
[[user:Kisaoda]] 12:07, 29 June 2012  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/198.62.73.4|198.62.73.4]] ([[User talk:198.62.73.4|talk]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== CFORK merge candidate ==

FYI, there is an article, which appears to be a CFORK of this one, at [[Noach (parsha)]] which is being considered for deletion. I don't know if there is any content in that article which is worthy of being merged with this one, but if there is, please migrate it over. Thanks! &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 05:33, 9 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>i563stfr5kl139tv52nm6wub44qgehy</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
