<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Shabbat</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>106385</id>
    <revision>
      <id>504909137</id>
      <parentid>498961145</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-07-30T09:43:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>IZAK</username>
        <id>6549</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Discussion about the 54 Shabbat parshas */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31944">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=B|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Israel|class=B|importance=high}}
{{WPReligion|class=B|importance=Top}}
}}

== New Sabbath spinout ==

Having considered the state of Sabbath articles closely, I think there is still one topic to create, namely [[Biblical Sabbath]]. Currently this phrase redirects to the summary article &quot;Sabbath&quot; even though that article includes many other Sabbath adaptations that are not Biblical. A new article would compile the Biblical references to Sabbath in a thorough, orderly way, and give all the main viewpoints and interpretations of each passage (compare [[creation according to Genesis]], [[figs in the Bible]], [[wells in the Bible]], etc.). None of the current articles do either of these, because they are quite rightly focused on Sabbath in this or that mainstream viewpoint. However, the notion of &quot;Sabbath as the Bible describes it, without making judgments in favor of any viewpoint&quot; is a topic frequently discussed but lacking. No need to warn me about POV risks, because I am already on duty policing those. It is just my observation that, very often, a WP editor wants to refer just to that notion, &quot;Biblical Sabbath with essentially no POV&quot;, and has no recourse to do so (as noted, the summary &quot;Sabbath&quot; article is not Biblically limited, and the Biblically based articles give only one POV each). Particularly, there are many links to &quot;Sabbath&quot; that should very clearly, in context, be directed to [[Biblical Sabbath]], and permitting the weaker link is suboptimal and easily remediable. Also, many of the IP contributors to &quot;Sabbath&quot; would do better to have such a separate article; and some of the debates about where to put this or that apologetic (if at all) would be more readily solved if there were a central article. I will be happy to move this forward, but I wanted to get a couple more opinions first, to confirm my belief that this is a good division of topics. Cross-posted to [[Shabbat]], [[Sabbath in Christianity]], and [[Sabbath in seventh-day churches]]. [[User:John J. Bulten/Friends|JJB]] 05:43, 16 March 2009 (UTC)

==Lunar Sabbath/&quot;Some prominent rabbis&quot;==
I've moved the following section to Talk: for further discussion:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Some prominent rabbis believe ''Shabbat'' was originally dependent upon the lunar cycle,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=1943|title=Universal Jewish Encyclopedia|volume=5|page=410. '''9'''. p. 295|editor=Landman, Isaac|chapter=Holidays; Sabbath|author=Joseph, Max}}&lt;/ref&gt; with one or two additional unreckoned days.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=1943|title=Universal Jewish Encyclopedia|volume=10|page=482|editor=Landman, Isaac|chapter=Week|author=Cohen, Simon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
As is obvious, the first sentence is pure [[weasel word]]ed POV. Who are these rabbis? What makes them &quot;prominent&quot;? As it happens, I'm the person on Wikipedia who has written the closest thing to a biography on one of them, [[Congregation Beth Elohim (Brooklyn, New York)#1930s: Landman joins, Great Depression, Lyons dies|Isaac Landman]]. Landman was, in his time, moderately well known known for a combination of things, including his ecumenical work, his political stances, his editing of ''American Hebrew Magazine'', and his publication of his ''New Universal Jewish Encyclopedia''. He was not &quot;prominent&quot; in any particularly scholarly way. The fact that this single, 65 year-old work seems to be the only source for this &quot;lunar sabbath&quot; theory should be a big [[WP:REDFLAG]] to editors here that they are giving [[WP:UNDUE]] weight to a [[WP:FRINGE]] theory. If there are other, scholarly (and more recent) sources that also promote this theory, then I would be happy to re-evaluate. But, as it stands, the material is highly problematic. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 00:07, 24 March 2009 (UTC)
:Hi Jayjg, thanks for that! Actually as you could see I posted that on behalf of a &quot;drive-by&quot; editor who sourced it thoroughly. My goal is simply to collect all POVs, and it seems that two rabbis in a (liberal?) Jewish encyclopedia is a significant POV. I don't think it's useful to classify it as fringe or not. If my words were weasely it's only because I don't know one encyclopedia-publishing rabbi from another. If you'd prefer it as &quot;Two rabbis in NUJE suggest&quot;, that seems to stand scrutiny. Or we could group it with the tag I used later in the Sabbath disambiguator, that, &quot;''In a distinct minority'', some European [[Reform Jews]] have moved Sabbath observances to [[Sunday]]&quot;, which also appears to be an includible POV that should work its way into this article sooner or later.
:While I happen to disagree with Landman's conclusion rather vehemently, I don't think it's a theory that should be totally banished from listing. &quot;Writing for the enemy&quot;, I leave it ripe for the possibility of demolishing itself by its minority status. By the way, a close version of this theory also appears in the landmark ''[[Encyclopedia of Religion and Ethics]]'', as I documented at [[Babylonian calendar#Week]] (ignore the repetition of your objected sentence, of course). They reliably link Sabattu&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt; with Shabbat, but I could not see them coming all-out on Landman's view that the Babylonians came first; but both Landman and ERE give the same calendrical calculation details. Your statement that this &quot;seems to be the only [Jewish] source&quot; is an argument from silence. From what I know of liberalism in various religions, the IP editor's position, that this is an includible POV, seems entirely credible to me. What would you say is proper weight? [[User:John J. Bulten/Friends|JJB]] 03:45, 24 March 2009 (UTC)
::While it is interesting that there may be theories that are, in your view, similar to Landman's, I'm looking for sources that actually have the ''same'' theory. As for an &quot;argument from silence&quot;, the onus in this case is to still find sources that support it - again, please see [[WP:UNDUE]], [[WP:REDFLAG]], and [[WP:FRINGE]]. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 23:29, 24 March 2009 (UTC)
:Well Jay, I hope we're not going to pretend that Judaism is monolithic in some way unlike every other religion. We've established that Landman and his contributors, Joseph and Cohen, believe and propound this POV. I've given further unequivocal evidence that ancient lunar-cycled weeks did in fact exist and were named cognate to ''Shabbat''. The issue of weasel words is easily remedied, as above; while your issues of undue weight, red flags, and fringe theory all seem to me to be the same issue, apparently that you don't believe the POV is significant enough to list in ''any'' article, even the root &quot;Sabbath&quot; article or the Babylonian article, which has very happily contained ''all'' POVs for a long time now. Look, you're saying that the NUJE is an unreliable source, and that burden is really on you, because it would ordinarily be given the benefit of doubt. Really, if you intend to keep this up, it may begin to sound like you refuse WP to report the fact that not all Jews believe in the unbroken ''Shabbat'', as if the much unlikelier claim, monolithic faith, has been proven. [[User:John J. Bulten/Friends|JJB]] 02:50, 25 March 2009 (UTC)
:[[User:Dlabtot]] at [[WP:RSN]] stated that you did not in fact say that the (N)UJE is an unreliable source. Either it's an RS and thus an includible POV, or it's unreliable and thus there is sourceable evidence of its unreliability. Which? I know you're not really saying to delete an RS just because it's turned 65. Also &quot;New&quot; is [http://books.google.com/books?id=Qr9tAAAAMAAJ&amp;pgis=1 not] in the title. If I don't hear back I will reinsert in ''all'' the articles as follows:
''In a minority Jewish view, the ''Universal Jewish Encyclopedia'' states that ''Shabbat'' was originally dependent upon the lunar cycle,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=1943|title=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia: An authoritative and popular presentation of Jews and Judaism since the earliest times|volume=5|page=410|editor=[[Isaac Landman|Landman, Isaac]]|chapter=Holidays|author=Joseph, Max|others=Cohen, Simon, compiler|publisher=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia, Inc}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=1943|title=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia: An authoritative and popular presentation of Jews and Judaism since the earliest times|volume=9|page=295|editor=[[Isaac Landman|Landman, Isaac]]|chapter=Sabbath|author=Joseph, Max|others=Cohen, Simon, compiler|publisher=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia, Inc}}&lt;/ref&gt; with one or two additional unreckoned days.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|year=1943|title=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia: An authoritative and popular presentation of Jews and Judaism since the earliest times|volume=10|page=482|editor=[[Isaac Landman|Landman, Isaac]]|chapter=Week|author=Cohen, Simon|others=Cohen, Simon, compiler|publisher=The Universal Jewish Encyclopedia, Inc}}&lt;/ref&gt;''
{{reflist}}
:: Ummm, in a word, no.  Just because a viewpoint has been published in a reliable source, does not mean it needs to be included. That's why your colleagues are pointing you to [[WP:UNDUE]], which is just a section of [[WP:NPOV]].  Because that is the relevant and applicable [[WP:FIVE|policy]] here. [[User:Dlabtot|Dlabtot]] ([[User talk:Dlabtot|talk]]) 02:26, 26 March 2009 (UTC)

===Proposing an origin paragraph===
Well, I guess I thought that the majority view was obvious. In that case, all you need is a full and balanced paragraph on &quot;origin of ''Shabbat''&quot;. No problem, try my next. [[User:John J. Bulten/Friends|JJB]] 05:21, 26 March 2009 (UTC)
:As Dlabtot has explained, you are presenting a false dichotomy. Please review [[WP:UNDUE]] again. [[User:Jayjg|Jayjg ]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:Jayjg|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 01:14, 27 March 2009 (UTC)

Putting aside all the discussion above, which is important in itself, but I have read and re-read the section on Origin and I find it incomprehensible. I am still trying to work what is the point that is being made.[[User:Ewawer|Ewawer]] ([[User talk:Ewawer|talk]]) 03:38, 27 March 2009 (UTC)
:OK help me understand here. Which proposition is at fault?
*Jewish views on where ''Shabbat'' came from are encyclopedic.
*The ''Shabbat'' article is the proper article for these views to appear on WP.
*These views include an origin at creation (literal/fundamentalist), an origin by Mosaic legislation (conservative), a later temple origin attributed backwards to Moses (liberal), or an origin by adapting a Babylonian custom (textual critical).
:&quot;Undue&quot; only applies if a view is held by &quot;an extremely small (or vastly limited) minority&quot;. You have produced no evidence as to how the views are distributed. I have. What gives?
:I came here and I saw a gap and filled it with sourced material, and weighted it &quot;duly&quot; the second time. Generally the decision goes in favor of retaining properly weighted sourced material rather than deleting it because of unstated rationales. Thank you for your consideration. [[User:John J. Bulten/Friends|JJB]] 14:45, 27 March 2009 (UTC)

::One of the problems, as I see it, is that the article is not about a seven-day week, which has its own article, but about the special status of the Shabbat in the Jewish weekly cycle. In that respect it is a particular issue, not open to a full discussion whether it is appropriate to have those observances, etc. or whether other cultures have other customs etc. As to whether material is sourced or not is immaterial, because it should still fit into the subject matter and scope of an article, not go off on a tangent.[[User:Ewawer|Ewawer]] ([[User talk:Ewawer|talk]]) 17:38, 27 March 2009 (UTC)
:Now it's my turn to have trouble comprehending. But I think it's appropriate for this article to document ''how'' Shabbat came to have special status in the Jewish weekly cycle (and that may involve history that predates the Jewish people). This article has long had a &quot;Biblical source&quot; section, but that section is what WP calls an in-universe description, and is several paragraphs of promotion of only the fundamentalist, literal view (which I happen to hold)— except in the case of people who already have a nonliteral interpretation of the words anyway. The Biblical source needs to be balanced by the other views, and I originally did so in that section, but a separate section is fine. Some of the Biblical source section should be condensed and moved to my new spinout [[Biblical Sabbath]] anyway.
:If a paragraph on some custom's origins actually succeded in opening a new discussion on the appropriateness of the observances, the custom must be pretty weak. ''Shabbat'' is very strong. Similarly, the relationship of ''Shabbat'' to other observances is appropriate to touch on, ''insofar'' as it sheds light on ''Shabbat'' itself and does not create a [[WP:COATRACK]] to cover up other, unduly weighted Sabbath views. So I must reject the idea that these points are tangential. The whole cluster of Sabbath articles has suffered long from delineation errors, and that is what we are all about resolving. Each article should focus on ''all'' aspects relevant to its particular Sabbatical observance, including its origin and its place among other Sabbatical observances. And my paragraph is not about origin of a seven-day week but origin of ''Shabbat'' itself. Now that there is a much better scheme for segregating other observances into their own articles, your concern about tangents has a ready-made solution: true tangents move to their own extant articles. Thank you also for your other improvements, but please watch out for grammar errors. [[User:John J. Bulten/Friends|JJB]] 00:37, 28 March 2009 (UTC)

== International date line ==

We simply ''must'' cover the international date line debate, which is highly relevant from various perspectives, and one of the great debates in modern halacha. This should be either in this article or in a separate split-off. [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]]&amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jfdwolff|&lt;small&gt;T@lk&lt;/small&gt;]] 13:05, 14 June 2009 (UTC)

==Three stars==

Can you elaborate more on how the end-of-Sabbath line is drawn? ''Three stars'' as end-of-Sabbath - are they specific named stars or just ''any'' stars? What happens on cloudy, starless nights? [[Polar night]]s? TIA, [[User:NVO|NVO]] ([[User talk:NVO|talk]]) 19:25, 4 July 2009 (UTC)
::Three stars is symbolic. Shabbat is over when it is dark enough to see several stars. It doesn't matter which ones. Anyway, the rabbis figure out the exact &quot;end of Shabbat&quot; times a year in advance, and all Jewish calendars supply that information, so you don't actually have to look for the stars. And, as you say, it could be cloudy.--[[User:Gilabrand|Gilabrand]] ([[User talk:Gilabrand|talk]]) 16:58, 6 October 2009 (UTC)

==Discussion??==
Should there be a bit of discussion? for example these beliefs are accepted as historic artefacts from a different era - like those concerning safe eating in the desert, clean feet etc. It would add balance to the article to find references to some discussions on the relevance of this stuff to modern life.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.150.48.235|86.150.48.235]] ([[User talk:86.150.48.235|talk]]) 16:23, 6 October 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Serious question: not likely worthy of mention in article though ==

this line &lt;blockquote&gt;Shabbat is the seventh day of the Jewish week and a day of rest in Judaism. Shabbat is observed from sundown Friday until the appearance of three stars in the sky on Saturday night. The exact time, therefore, differs from week to week and from place to place, depending on the time of sunset at each location. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

What are the rules north of the arctic circle, if it is night time always, or conversly day time always. Seems like a dumb question but if there is an actual rule for such a sitiuation it may be informative in the article. I really doubt there is an actual rule for this. [[User:Smitty1337|Smitty1337]] ([[User talk:Smitty1337|talk]]) 22:00, 14 February 2010 (UTC)
:Interesting question. I found [http://www.star-k.org/kashrus/kk-whendoesonepraywhenthereisnoday.htm this site] that addresses the question rather extensively. From a quick skim, one recommendation is that Jews in those areas observe the shabbat times of the location they were in before traveling north of the Arctic Circle. &lt;font face=&quot;Century Gothic&quot;&gt;[[User:Equazcion|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#000080&quot;&gt;'''Equazcion'''&lt;/span&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Equazcion|'''&lt;sup&gt;(&lt;span style=&quot;color:#007BA7&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/sup&gt;''']]&lt;/small&gt; 22:08, 14 Feb 2010 (UTC)&lt;/font&gt;

Guess my question isnt as dumb as i thought lol [[Jewish law in the polar regions]] google found me a wiki article on it....imma go link it here after i read it and make sure its relevent.[[User:Smitty1337|Smitty1337]] ([[User talk:Smitty1337|talk]]) 22:22, 14 February 2010 (UTC)

==Adaptations==
I've removed this para from the article because it's both untrue and unsourced:

''The principle of weekly Sabbath has also been adopted, instituted, or modified in other beliefs: compare the [[Babylonian calendar]], the [[Buddhist]] ''[[uposatha]]'', the [[Islam]]ic ''[[jumu'ah]]'', the [[pagan]] [[Wheel of the Year|sabbat]], the [[Bahá'í calendar]], the [[Unification Church]] [[Ahn Shi Il]], and the parody-religion [[Pastafarian]] weekend.''

I don't know about all of these religions, but I do know it's untrue for the Babylonians and Buddhists. Buddhists don't give any particular note to Sundays or to any other day of the week. As for the Babylon, the influence works the other way round - it was the Jews who adopted Sabbath-observance from the Babylonians. The whole thing is unsourced in any case. Either find sources for each of these, or leave it out. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 02:29, 6 October 2010 (UTC)
:Hi again. The sources are in the individual articles, of which this is a summary. Your bald assertion of who adopted Sabbath from whom is not backed up by those sources. Further, the Buddhist case is a lunar week (usually 7 or 8 days), also related to early Sabbath. Your statement &quot;I do know it's untrue&quot; is not any more sourced than the text you deleted. Also, please don't repeat your deleting (and imbalancing the POV, toward Judeo-Christian in this case) when another party undoes it: that is contrary to [[WP:BRD]] recommendations and is also considered warring. On this article I'll wait to see who else chimes in. [[User:John J. Bulten/Friends|JJB]] 02:55, 6 October 2010 (UTC)
::JJB, the Buddhist cycle isn't based on 7 days, it's based on the phases of the moon - full moon, new moon, and half way between. A 7 day cycle, in contrast, gives exactly 28 days, which means it soon gets out of sync with the lunar cycle (which has 28.25 days). Lunar cycles are based on the fact that the moon is there in the sky - everyone all over the world can see and use it, and they do; no connection with the biblical sabbath is needed, and there's no question of it being an adaptation by one culture from another. As for the babylonian connection, that's in the literature - I think you need to read more widely. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 03:19, 6 October 2010 (UTC)
:::You have just said that the Biblical mathematical week was adopted from the Babylonian lunar week, and also that the lunar week is unquestionably unrelated to the mathematical week. You have also just said that the [[lunation]] of 29.53+ days is actually 28.25 days. [[User:John J. Bulten/Friends|JJB]] 03:45, 6 October 2010 (UTC)
::::The situation is more complicated than that. I'll find some sources for you. (And yes, there are 28 and a quarter days in a lunar month).[[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 04:03, 6 October 2010 (UTC)
:::::I must say the article as a whoile looks pretty good - it could do with some more sources, perhaps, but the topic seems to be well covered. Now that the references to the Babylonians and, of all people, Buddhists, are gone I have no problems with it. But I promised you some sources, which you can use as and if you please: [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=goq0VWw9rGIC&amp;dq=Mercer+Bible+Dictionary&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=bn&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=p9iiTO7HMoWycY31vbcB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=Sabbath&amp;f=false The Mercer Bible Dictionary,] about p.776 for the entry on Sabbath; the [http://books.google.com.au/books?id=3surkLVdw3UC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Oxford+Bible+commentary&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5s4E9q2oZh&amp;sig=6NU_qqp_09wL-Pyxg2XqvwteooI&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=GY-UTIr7DYGfcaT13KQF&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Sabbath&amp;f=false Oxford Bible Commentary] p105 has a brief description of history and the Sabbath and seems to say that it's no longer held that the Jews got it from the Babylonians, so it seems I was wrong on that point. It might be useful to use these and similar modern sources to re-do the small section on the history of Sabbath, but that's up to you. Thanks for removing the piece that offended me (mostly the Buddhism reference) [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 05:36, 6 October 2010 (UTC)

== Further reading section ==

The entire &quot;Further reading&quot; section is real marginal and perhaps should go; there are probably thousands of books about Shabbat history, practices, etc; what's so special about these? --[[User:Jpgordon|jpgordon]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Jpgordon|::==( o )]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 02:44, 14 March 2011 (UTC)

:I agree wholeheartedly. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 03:39, 16 March 2011 (UTC)

:Done. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 02:28, 21 March 2011 (UTC)

:Agree. The important sources should be cited. [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jfdwolff|&lt;small&gt;T@lk&lt;/small&gt;]] 12:42, 21 March 2011 (UTC)

== non-Jews==
Shouldn't there be some mention of Non-Jews not being permitted to keep Shabbos? And that someone who publicly desecrated Shabbos cannot be counted in a minyan?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/174.252.3.157|174.252.3.157]] ([[User talk:174.252.3.157|talk]]) 01:11, 25 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Friday night section ==

What the heck does this mean?

:''Unlike on Shabbat day, one can partake in all the suggested activities on Friday night. There is an idea that the Jews who partake in Shabbat should not only have Shabbat, but they also make Shabbat. Through this opportunity to do all the encouraged activities, Friday night often is when a Jew will &quot;make&quot; Shabbat.[15]''

:''With this idea in mind one might also assert that Friday night is not just a large part of Shabbat, but really is a full half of it.''

It doesn't make much sense to me. --[[Special:Contributions/194.176.105.147|194.176.105.147]] ([[User talk:194.176.105.147|talk]]) 15:24, 30 August 2011 (UTC)

::Whatever it means, ??????, the footnote &quot;[15]&quot; should be in main text as a bracketed primary source &quot;(Shabbat 119b)&quot; not masquerading as a WP:RS &quot;[15]&quot;. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 00:26, 13 September 2011 (UTC)
::: That would go against practice in all Judaism-related articles. In addition, where did you dig up such a rule? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 01:41, 13 September 2011 (UTC)

: I also don't understand what this is supposed to mean. But it seems to me it was rightfully removed. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 01:42, 13 September 2011 (UTC)

== Marital relations ==

This seems somewhat suggestive and possible prurient, not to mention confusing.  Wouldn't it be more sensible just to say 'sexual relations'? [[User:Harburg|Harburg]] ([[User talk:Harburg|talk]]) 18:04, 3 October 2011 (UTC)

:What's wrong with the current version? The sources are quite clear that this is marital/conjugal rather than any kind of contact. [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jfdwolff|&lt;small&gt;T@lk&lt;/small&gt;]] 15:57, 23 October 2011 (UTC)

::To answer your question, [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]], what's wrong with the current version (current as of 6 June 2012, that is) is that it violates [[WP:EUPHEMISM]] – ''if'' &quot;marital relations&quot; here means sex between a husband and wife (I'm not Jewish, so I don't know). If &quot;make love&quot; is a euphemism for sex (the one given as an example in the MOS), certainly &quot;martial relations&quot; is too.

::In order to remove the taint of euphemism, &quot;marital relations&quot; should be changed to &quot;marital sex&quot;, or something similar. Changing it to just &quot;sex&quot; (or &quot;sexual relations&quot;, as [[User:Harburg|Harburg]] suggested) might make it too broad for this context. Someone who is both Jewish (or knows enough about the subject to speak with authority) and is interested in following the MOS advice to avoid euphemism in WP articles should change the wording in this bullet point. I'll copy that bullet both as it stands today and the proposed change here:
::Current:{{quote|
::*Enjoying Shabbat (''oneg Shabbat''): Engaging in pleasurable activities such as eating, singing, spending time with the family and marital relations.}}
::Proposed:{{quote|
::*Enjoying Shabbat (''oneg Shabbat''): Engaging in pleasurable activities such as eating, singing, spending time with the family and marital sex.}}

::I suppose it is possible that &quot;marital relations&quot; is ''not'' used here as a euphemism for sex but as a description of the married relationship in general, and that what is encouraged on Shabbat is for a married couple simply to reflect on how happy they are to be married to one another. In that case, a different term should be used, since, as [[User:Harburg|Harburg]] noted, there is definitely a hint of ''something'' sexual in &quot;marital relations&quot;.

::On second thought, I'm going to assume that [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]]'s statement &quot;The sources are quite clear that this is marital/conjugal ...&quot; means that this ''is'' talking about sex. Therefore, I'm going to make the change I just proposed. If it turns out that someone who knows better says that this bullet point isn't talking about sex at all, then that person can change it to some better phrase – but, please,  one that does not carry the sexual connotation &quot;marital relations&quot; carries.--[[User:Jim10701|Jim10701]] ([[User talk:Jim10701|talk]]) 03:47, 20 June 2012 (UTC)

:::Just as a side note, this exact conversation took place on [[Talk:Tisha_B%27Av#Customs]] this week. Just to make consensus clearer should this issue reemerge, I think the correct decision was made to drop the phrase marital relations as it clearly violated [[WP:EUPHEMISM]]. --[[User:Bachrach44|Bachrach44]] ([[User talk:Bachrach44|talk]]) 06:06, 21 June 2012 (UTC)

:::: The term &quot;marital relations&quot; is clear enough, and is hardly a euphemism. And please, no need to refer to a discussion where nobody commented. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 09:08, 21 June 2012 (UTC)

::::: How is it hardly a euphemism? It's a euphemism for sex (usually), and a confusing one at that. See Jim's comment above where he is unsure if the phrase actually means sex or something else. When it means sex, we need to say sex. When it means something else, we need to say that. It doesn't matter how many people commented here or not, wikipedia policy is very clear on this matter. --[[User:Bachrach44|Bachrach44]] ([[User talk:Bachrach44|talk]]) 09:22, 21 June 2012 (UTC)

::::: Here are some examples I found doing a quick search on wikipedia. On [[tisha b'av]], [[mikvah]], or others it's used in place of the word sex. On [[ketubah]] it's used in place of &quot;living together in the same house&quot;. On [[Conservative Halakha]] it's used in place of &quot;the rules regarding marriage&quot;. On [[Paphnutius of Thebes]] the phrase is used to mean &quot;marriage&quot;. In [[You shall not commit adultery]] I honestly can't tell what it's supposed to mean. Why? Because it's an ambiguous phrase. We need to say what we mean. --[[User:Bachrach44|Bachrach44]] ([[User talk:Bachrach44|talk]]) 09:33, 21 June 2012 (UTC)

:::::In fact, &quot;marital relations&quot; covers it perfectly. Clearly &quot;marital sex&quot; is not a recognised combination, while &quot;sex&quot; without a modifier would imply that any kind of intercourse is encouraged. [[User:Jfdwolff|JFW]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;#124;&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Jfdwolff|&lt;small&gt;T@lk&lt;/small&gt;]] 10:55, 22 June 2012 (UTC)
::::::There isn't really a need to qualify it with &quot;marital&quot; since sex outside of mariage would be banned regardless of the day of the week. &quot;Marital Relations&quot; needs to go. If it is a euphemism for sex then policy says it must change. If it is not a euphemism for sex, then it is a euphemism for some other thing, because if I take it as a literal phrase &quot;Marital Relations&quot; I'm banned from being married on shabbat!? [[User:Smitty1337|Smitty1337]] ([[User talk:Smitty1337|talk]]) 09:02, 23 June 2012 (UTC)

==[[WP:naming conventions (use English)]]==
It looks as if this article title may not be following WP naming policy, or WP:RS such as www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/12962-sabbath etc? [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 19:25, 11 November 2011 (UTC)
:This article is about the Jewish Sabbath. We have a separate article on Sabbath. Shabbat is a term widely used in English language texts to refer to the Jewish Sabbath and is therefore appropriate here.  See [[WP:PRECISION]].--[[User:ArnoldReinhold|agr]] ([[User talk:ArnoldReinhold|talk]]) 20:15, 11 November 2011 (UTC)
::Hi Arnold, thanks, yes of course, but &quot;Jewish Sabbath&quot; (hence [[WP:PRECISION]]) is English, that doesn't bear directly on [[WP:EN]]; is it possible that you or someone else could run a Google Scholar or Google Books advanced search to demonstrate that &quot;Shabbat&quot; is more common than &quot;Sabbath&quot; in English-language [[WP:RS]] when relating to Judaism? It may well be that is, but the Jewish Encyclopedia suggests that it isn't, or at least wasn't in 1911. Anyone willing to check this? [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 01:31, 16 November 2011 (UTC)

== Resistor Network ==

In the section &quot;Technology in the service of Shabbat&quot; the article mentions a &quot;resistor network&quot; to store energy from elevators. I get the general idea, but resistor networks don't store energy. I presume what you are talking about here is some kind of big capacitor or rechargable battery, or maybe even an enormous flywheel. This is a point about physics, not Judaism, but it could stand some reconsideration. [[User:Rob Burbidge|Rob Burbidge]] ([[User talk:Rob Burbidge|talk]]) 00:34, 15 January 2012 (UTC)

== Link to 'Activities prohibited on Shabbat' ==

I added a link under the 'Prohibited activities' section to the 'Activities prohibited on Shabbat' page because for some reason it took me ages to find that particular page from this one and it also seemed to make sense. This is the first time I've edited wikipedia, so hope that was ok and sorry about having to correct what I was doing a couple of times :=]

[[Special:Contributions/118.149.61.13|118.149.61.13]] ([[User talk:118.149.61.13|talk]]) 02:18, 5 April 2012 (UTC)

== Discussion about the 54 Shabbat parshas ==

*'''REQUEST''': Please see the centralized discussion about this subject, relating to sources, links, content, etc at [[Talk:Chayei Sarah (parsha)]]. Thank you, [[User:IZAK|IZAK]] ([[User talk:IZAK|talk]]) 09:43, 30 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>96clzn9gj5wwyw4o5eglem0f97n78nd</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
