<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Doctor of the Church</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5951658</id>
    <revision>
      <id>453521287</id>
      <parentid>427058229</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-10-02T12:30:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CommonsNotificationBot</username>
        <id>14413849</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Notification of possible deletion of [[:commons:File:St-John-of-the-Cross.jpg|File:St-John-of-the-Cross.jpg]] ([[User_talk:ErrantX|feedback]], Version [[User:CommonsNotificationBot/changelog|r92]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12417">{{Christianity WikiProject|class=start|importance=mid|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=mid|Saints=yes|saints-importance=mid|anglicanism=yes|anglicanism-importance=mid}}


== Nationality ==
This column needs major work and changes. St. Basil's nationality most certainly was NOT Turkish. He neither spoke nor understood the language. Furthermore, there were no Turks living in the area at the time, nor was there any Turkish, Ottoman, or Seljuk kingdom, principality, emirate, khanate, province, colony, city or any other kind of unit there at this time. St. Ambrose was NOT Italian. He might have considered himself, and been considered in turn, Roman or Latin, but not Italian.

The table either needs to change the name of the column to something like &quot;Current nation in which place of birth is located&quot; or the information in the column needs to reflect the understanding of nationality/ethnicity that existed at the times of these various saints.

There's also a lot of inconsistency. St. Jerome's nationality is listed as &quot;Dalmatian&quot;, but there is no nation of Dalmatia today. Despite that, this makes good sense as &quot;Dalmatian&quot; more closely corresponds with the ethnic/national categories of his time than &quot;Croatian&quot; or &quot;Serbian&quot; or &quot;Yugoslav&quot;. St. Isidore's nationality of Visigothic likewise fails to correspond with any of today's nationalities, but that's actually not a problem since it does correspond with the nationalities in use at his time. 

My suggestion? In this column, first give the nationality that the person in question most likely would have used to describe himself or herself. Many of these will be more closely tied with place of birth (''natio'') than with current nation states, but that's actually good as it's more accurate. Second, give the name of which of today's nation states this birthplace now lies in. I think, for example, that the first datum for all of the &quot;Italian&quot; saints should NOT be Italy, but rather the name of the republic, empire, kingdom, duchy or whatever they were born in and identified as their nationality. [[User:Interlingua|&lt;font style=&quot;background: #08E8DE &quot; face=&quot;Ariel&quot; color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;'''''Inter'''''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font style=&quot;background: #000000&quot; face=&quot;Ariel&quot; color=&quot;#08E8DE &quot;&gt;'''lingua'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sup&gt; [[User talk:Interlingua|talk]] [[Special:Emailuser/Interlingua|email]]&lt;/sup&gt; 14:29, 31 July 2006 (UTC)

Add to the examples above that Bede can in no sense be described as British. British could mean Brythonic Celtic, i.e. Welsh: he was a Northumbrian Angle. British can also mean a UK citizen post-1707: he lived a thousand years too early for that. I wish I could share the confidence expressed above that nationality could make any sense at all when applied to people who lived before the emergence of nation states. At least we can all accept that St Theresa of Lisieux was French and that's about it.[[User:Sjwells53|Sjwells53]] 20:49, 2 July 2007 (UTC)

:Support - the sense in which ethnicity is being used here is very problematic.  The best designation for the listed individuals who lived in The Roman Empire is probably 'Roman'; this ought to include Gregory the Great as well. The case of Isidore of Seville is absurd.  Isidore was an Hispano-Roman living in the [[Visigoths|Visigothic]] kingdom and so hispano-gothic is the closest ethnic label not spanish.  The question that has not been addressed here is how do we ascribe a contemporary [[Ethnonym|ethnonym]] to a Late Latin speaking bishop living in a kingdom ruled by a German speaking people or to any of the other individuals listed in this article. Geography is not identity and the fact that some time in the past some people lived in the geographical space that one group or another now lives in does not mean that the past people and the current people have some necessary connexion.[[User:Rykalski|Rykalski]] ([[User talk:Rykalski|talk]]) 11:42, 27 June 2008 (UTC)

:Support. Anselm was not Italian. Burgundian by birthplace, or Lombard by heritage would be more accurate. French, Swiss, Germanic, Norman or English also could be used to describe his background as (in)accurately as Italian.[[User:Enon|Enon]] ([[User talk:Enon|talk]]) 08:03, 22 December 2010 (UTC)

== &quot;Traditional Catholics&quot; and women Doctors ==

A user added material claiming that &quot;the traditional Catholics&quot; reject the addition of the three women Doctors from 1970 on. That statement has been progressively toned down, to &quot;''most'' traditional Catholics&quot;, then &quot;''many''&quot;, and finally &quot;''some''&quot;. The effect, though, is to make the statement very weasel-wordish, and in the absence of a reputable source (and a clear definition of who does and who doesn't count as a &quot;traditional(ist) Catholic&quot;), the article is far better off without the statement however phrased, so I have taken the liberty of removing it. [[User:Vilcxjo|Vilĉjo]] 22:06, 30 August 2006 (UTC)

==An Updating==
On this feast of St. Ambrose, I have done some updating to this article.
*Eliminated the reference to the doctors as theologians.  The women doctors were not theologians.
*Eliminated the reference to beatification.  Canonization (formal or equivalent) is necessary.
*Corrected some of the nationality problems &amp; added footnotes where I thought necessary.
*Added more appropriate activities.
*Added a quote pertaining to women doctors.
The references to the honorary titles should be eliminated as they can be confusing.  Some titles are shared by more than one doctor, ''e.g.'', the titles &quot;Doctor Universalis&quot; and &quot;Doctor Venerabilis&quot; are given to both Thomas Aquinas and Albert the Great.  Furthermore, which title is to be given?  Thomas Aquinas has had upwards of ten titles bestowed on him.  If they did, indeed, serve to distinguish, then they would merit inclusion. [[User:68.65.122.80|68.65.122.80]] 17:29, 7 December 2006 (UTC)

==Ordering==
I think the list should be sorted according to birth (or flourishing) dates. As the list is as today, there isn't any criterion for its ordering. [[User:Nivaca|Nivaca]] 20:35, 5 January 2007 (UTC)
:Sounds like a good criterion to me.  [[User:Goldfritha|Goldfritha]] 23:48, 5 January 2007 (UTC)
::Unless it's been edited recently, it's sorted by the year each was named a Doctor. I'd suggest keeping that order, with either year of birth or alphabetical ordering for those years which had multiple Doctors named. [[User:PaulGS|PaulGS]] 00:21, 15 February 2007 (UTC)

==Math==
From the current article:

&quot;The Catholic Church has to date named 33 Doctors of the Church. Of these, the 17 who died before the formal disunion of the Eastern and Western Churches in 1054 are also venerated by the Eastern Orthodox Church. Among these 33 are 25 from the West and 8 from the East; 14 diocesan priests, 16 religious priests and 3 women; 18 bishops, 9 priests, 1 deacon, 2 nuns and 1 lay woman; 24 from Europe, 3 from Africa, 6 from Asia.&quot;

My first question is what the definition of &quot;East&quot; and &quot;West is. My second question is how &quot;18 bishops, 9 priests, 1 deacon, 2 nuns and 1 lay woman&quot; can add up to 33. That seems to add up to 31 to me. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/128.252.107.160|128.252.107.160]] ([[User talk:128.252.107.160|talk]]) 04:21, 13 February 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

The West in Christian history terms refers to that part of the world once [rimarily controlled by the Western Roman Empire, the Latin-speaking world, i.e., roughly, Western Europe. The East refers to that part of the world once controlled by or heavily influenced by the Byzantine Empire -- hence, Eastern Europe and the Middle East, roughly speaking. Western Christianity follows the Roman liturgical tradition (and later, the Protestant traditions), while Eastern Christianity follows the Byzantine, Antiochene, Alexandrian and Armenian traditions -- today the Eastern Rite Catholic, the Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox churches. There are in fact 33 doctors -- the 2 nuns and one laywoman is a bit misleading, as Catherine of Siena was a lay Dominican who later was part of a convent; 19 were bishops (including Popes), 10 were priests, 1 was a deacon, and three were women, all arguably (in some sense) religious sisters.[[User:HarvardOxon|HarvardOxon]] 04:53, 13 February 2007 (UTC)

:Just to muddy the waters, the Oriental traditions consider both the Byzantine and Latin traditions to be Western. In a sense, they're right, as both the Byzantine and Latin traditions draw heavily on the Graeco-Roman philosophical inheritance, while the Oriental Orthodox (and their corresponding Catholic Churches) never adopted it. What fun. [[User:InfernoXV|InfernoXV]] ([[User talk:InfernoXV|talk]]) 13:42, 27 June 2008 (UTC)

== Expansion of list ==

I have included references to groups other than simply the main Roman Catholic Church as per the Holweck source cited. [[User:Warlordjohncarter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:Warlordjohncarter|talk]]) 20:34, 29 December 2007 (UTC)

== Reference to Isaac of Nineveh ==

In my browser the reference to Isaac is in red (not linked), but in Google I find that wikipedia does have an article on someone by thet name. Are the 2 the same?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/41.245.72.131|41.245.72.131]] ([[User talk:41.245.72.131|talk]]) 10:57, 10 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Asterisks in Table Undefined ==

A number of the entries on the table have an asterisk, but the meaning of this is undefined.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/160.109.63.190|160.109.63.190]] ([[User talk:160.109.63.190|talk]]) 16:56, 12 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== St. Ambrose isn't German. St. Ambrose German? Then Albert Einstein is Italian ==

St. Ambrose was a Roman (Roman by race, by culture and even, it must be added, by his carrer); Bishop and moralist as he was, his ethics were a form of Christianized stoic philosophy. He was never ethnically or culturally German. --[[Special:Contributions/93.147.196.234|93.147.196.234]] ([[User talk:93.147.196.234|talk]]) 11:53, 10 April 2011 (UTC)

== Lutherans and Doctors ==

Lutherans recognize and use the term Doctor for the great doctors of East and West.  I also am pretty sure that for the commemoration of Martin Lutheran, the use of the term doctor is not just to note that he had a doctorate but that he was a teacher of the Church in the same way that 'doctor' is used in the rest of the article.  Is there any documentation for the use of doctor in this way?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/98.204.107.173|98.204.107.173]] ([[User talk:98.204.107.173|talk]]) 16:51, 28 April 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== &quot;Little Flower&quot; ==

I have corrected the reference to St. Theresa (of Lisieux) to reflect her correct name in religion and indicated that &quot;Little Flower&quot; is not an official name, but one bestowed on her by the faithful. [[User:Caeruleancentaur|Caeruleancentaur]] ([[User talk:Caeruleancentaur|talk]]) 12:49, 2 May 2011 (UTC)
==File:St-John-of-the-Cross.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:St-John-of-the-Cross.jpg|File:St-John-of-the-Cross.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests - No timestamp given'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 12:30, 2 October 2011 (UTC)
|}</text>
      <sha1>j3ek5auhdp17dgqm9hzy74175i0ghkn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
