<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ethics</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>48099</id>
    <revision>
      <id>517579762</id>
      <parentid>503168678</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-13T14:42:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Airborne84</username>
        <id>9474535</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* New section: defining ethics */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32466">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Philosophy|class=C|importance=Top|ethics=yes|social=yes}}
{{WikiProject Rational Skepticism|class=C|attention=yes|importance=Mid}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=C|category=Philrelig|VA=yes|coresup=yes|WPCD=yes|importance=Mid}}
{{VA|topic=Philosophy|level=2|class=C}}
}}
{{todo}}This Article was the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Philosophy|WikiProject Philosophy]] Collaboration of the Month for September 2005 - [[Template talk:PhilosophyTasks/vote|Vote]] for any future collaboration
[[Talk:Ethics/Archive]]&lt;br&gt;
[[Talk:Ethics/Archive 2]]

__TOC__

==Untitled==
236.87 was done.  Perhaps it should be reverted, there seems to be less information now? --[[User:Paraphelion|Paraphelion]] 06:27, 19 Jan 2005 (UTC)

==add moral falliblism to see also section==
I looked in see also section and it is missing moral fallibilism. I will add it unless people have any problems.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/71.232.93.212|71.232.93.212]] ([[User talk:71.232.93.212|talk]]) 09:44, 22 November 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

===Ethics vs. Politics vs. Religion vs. Practice===
I wonder if this should be adapted slightly to take account of the (reasonably popular) suggestion in moral philosophy that rights are a misleading way of characterising morality?

===Normative ethics===
I've also never come accross the distinction in Normative Ethics between Theories of Conduct and Theories of value; it seems to me that the former is bound to be based on the latter: whether or not your conduct is &quot;good&quot; depends upon which/what value(s) you associate with &quot;good&quot;?

The section on &quot;modern ethics&quot; needs a subsection on virture ethics.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.19.29.203|76.19.29.203]] ([[User talk:76.19.29.203|talk]]) 18:35, 25 March 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Help needed on a parallel ''Ethics'' article==
Unfortunately, someone set up an article parallel to this article on [[Ethics]], in violation of Wikipedia policy.  That parallel article violated NPOV by acting as a blog for one man's personal views, a person that also happens to be hard-banned user.  Please see [[Wikipedia:Votes_for_deletion/Simple view of ethics and morals]] &lt;br&gt;
Thanks for your time. [[User:RK|RK]] 20:20, Apr 8, 2005 (UTC)

== Announcing policy proposal ==


This is just to inform people that I want Wikipedia to accept a general policy that BC and AD represent a Christian Point of View and should be used only when they are appropriate, that is, in the context of expressing or providing an account of a Christian point of view.  In other contexts, I argue that they violate our NPOV policy and we should use BCE and CE instead. See [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view/BCE-CE Debate]] for the detailed proposal. [[User:Slrubenstein|Slrubenstein]]   |  [[User talk:Slrubenstein|Talk ]] 22:55, 15 May 2005 (UTC)

== Existentialism ==

I have changed the article about Jean-Paul Sartre. Sure, he was not alone when developping existentialism, but the best definition of it is his book &quot;L'existentialisme est un humanisme&quot;. No other philosopher had ever defined it really.

Is this a reason to say he was the only existentialist ? Sure not. Can he be considered THE major existentialist ? Definitely.

--[[User:213.103.59.235|213.103.59.235]] 11:26, 19 May 2005 (UTC)

== Series ==

Anyone think we should create a Series/Guide to all the articles to do with ethics, rather like the way [[Green_politics]] is done?  Anybody know how to do this?

What about Kierkegaard? Could he not also be called THE existentialist? Surely he could.

== Series ==
Quote:
''&quot;What about Kierkegaard? Could he not also be called THE existentialist? Surely he could&quot;''

Ya he was a major existentialist, but there were others who may have been more profound than Kierkegaard. but thats just my opinion.

*As an existentialist myself it is my opinion that the difference between Christian existentialism and atheistic existentialism is large enough to render it impossible make a valid choice as to who is THE existentialist. THE Christian one and THE atheistic one is, of course, a far more clear cut matter.
[[User:Sioraf|Sioraf]] ([[User talk:Sioraf|talk]]) 00:32, 15 March 2009 (UTC)

==Science's need for ethics==
I'm of the opinion that the claims made in the article about the importance of ethics in actual sciences, such as biology and ecology are a bit misleading, and are trying to turn fields such as [[bioethics]] into actual science.  Claiming that [[bioethics]] is science is akin to claiming that the universe cares what our current opinions are (see [[naturalistic fallacy]], [[is-ought problem]]).  Rather than state that ethics is &quot;important&quot; to the scientific fields, it might be better to state that ethics &quot;has been extended&quot; into these fields. --[[User:Brian0918|&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;brian0918&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:Brian0918|&lt;font color=&quot;#000000&quot;&gt;&amp;#153;&lt;/font&gt;]] 19:53, 13 Jun 2005 (UTC)

== Critique ==

Section by section:

'''Intro''': Does not summarise the article.

'''History''': just a list of names. Not really distinct from the history of western philosophy - so what is the point of having this section?

'''Definitions''': &quot;at least five&quot; - then lists six. 

'''Ethics in religion''': no more than a link - remove it? Summarise the main articles?

'''Ethics in health care''': Perhaps divide into ethics and medical ethics with summaries of main articles?

'''Ethics in politics''': no such thing... Perhaps link to [[Machiavelli]]?

'''Ethics by case''': needs some serious work - is their a main article for this to link to?

'''Is ethics futile''': what purpose has this section? perhaps move etymology to top?

'''Origins''': original research? Ethology as animal ethics? strange stuff, I think. 

[[User:Banno|Banno]] 11:56, August 23, 2005 (UTC)


Comments on critique from a non-english user:
history: necessary but needs a total revision and ampliation

major theories: please, not write just links to article, you could add a brief definition of each one

futile: agree with banno

why origins is so far from history?


:I agree that the ''history'' section continues to need major work but it remains a necessary part of the article. I think that the ''origins'' section could be brought further up the article (perhaps content merged with history) The ''ethics by case'' section is unclear. Perhaps it should be rewritten as ''ethics in law'' (in keeping with other headings) and just contain a summary of [[casuistry]] for which there is already a well developed article. --[[User:Vincej|Vincej]] 15:45, 31 August 2005 (UTC)

== In ethics and political science. == To promote the common good means to benefit members of the society.

== Online External review Dec 17 2005 ==

[[User:Perspective16]] notes that [http://www.mercatornet.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=199 Michael Cook] has unfavorably characterized this article. --[[User:Ancheta Wis|Ancheta Wis]] 01:07, 19 December 2005 (UTC)

== Disambiguation link to Scientology Ethics ==

I intend to revert the removal of the [[Ethics (Scientology)]] link, probably through a proper, full disambiguation page linked from this article, as per Wikipedia disambiguation guidelines. The removal of the link did not include a reason. --[[User:Davidstrauss|Davidstrauss]] 04:57, 27 January 2006 (UTC)

== Review of Consequentialism ==

I have been working for a couple of months on [[Consequentialism]] and recently submitted it for [[Wikipedia:Peer review/Consequentialism/archive1|peer review]]. If anyone here can offer me any advice as to how to proceed with this article, I would appreciate it greatly. [[User:Ig0774|Ig0774]] 01:31, 10 March 2006 (UTC)

== Moral Problems ==

We are faced with moral problems on a daily basis: Is 30 dollars enough to charge? Is abortion justified under certain circumstances? Should the doctor lie to Grandma about her heart condition? When we think about these things, we usually draw on moral rules that govern our lives. Whether they are rules about business transactions, the value of human life, or simply telling the truth. These rules depend upon certtain principles, and these principles have their basis in the Theological. We can trace almost any ethic to biblical material on morality. The Ten Commandments are basically moral rules for living and behaving responsibility, the sanctity of life, the marriage relationship, and the responsibility of telling the truth. Several applications take place in the book of Exodus. The moral law was the standard of the kind of society that existed in the Old Testament. It's remnant exists in our society today. Moral principles are all inclusive concepts not just applicable to the particular kinds of activities as in Exodus, but universally to every kind of involvement whatever that may be.

== Ethics as a Methodology ==

ETHICS is the name of a computer science Analysis and Design methodology.  Further disambiguation required?

== Business Ethics ==

There are many topics related to business ethics those I think should be discussed here.

Business man - Customer Ethics

Business man - Employee Relations

etc I am not good at this.. just thought this could be discussed

fsds
--


? Add [[Ethical Consumerism]] to the '''see also''' list [[User:88.109.152.209|88.109.152.209]] 00:06, 7 January 2007 (UTC)

== Morals vs Ethics ==

Although similar, and often confused, there is a distinction between morals and ethics. Ethics is a prescriptive code, whereas morals can differ between individuals. I think it would be a good idea to raise this distinction, any objections? [[User:ThePedro|ThePedro]] 01:38, 24 January 2007 (UTC)


== Descriptive Ethics back to a Sub-Head ==

I am quite uncomfortable with promoting descriptive ethics to the same headings as the other main branches of ethics in the opening section, especially since the introduction says there are three main branches, and descriptive is not one of them! I know this is a current discussion in the field, but I don't think this sort of change should be accepted here until it is accepted in the larger philosophical community. It definitely deserves space here, but it should be clearly indicated that this is a novelty, and not something that is generally accepted. I was astonished when my students began talking about descriptive ethics as a &quot;main branch.&quot; Now I see why! [[User:Johnsonr3|Robert Johnson]] 12:09, 1 April 2007 (UTC)

these ethics are rong

== Ethics in Psychology/Ethics in professions ==

Ethics in psychology, especially regarding the subjects of psychological experiments, warrants separate mention from medical ethics.

Ethics in psychology should be renamed psychological ethical theories or something along those lines, as the title implies a discussion of ethical guidelines in psychology. I'm a bit too busy at the moment to write about it, but any discussion of that subject should include reference to Milgram's landmark study and probably Watson's experiment with the baby. I forget the years.


[[User:24.17.211.229|24.17.211.229]] 05:32, 6 June 2007 (UTC)Peter Comerford

== Call me naïve... ==
... but &quot;However, most persons would argue that ethics are overrated.&quot; qualifies as one of the dumbest statements ever to be found on a Wikipedia article which appears to have been written in cold blood... especially in an introduction... removed. [[User:Carl Turner|Carl Turner]] 18:49, 23 June 2007 (UTC)

==[[Ethicism]]?==
I found an article titled [[Ethicism]], which seems to be a neologism describing the practice of ethics, which is, as I see it...ethics. I wonder if anyone is interested in salvaging anything from that (hopelessly POV and OR - filled) article and then having it redirect here. [[User:Chubbles1212|Chubbles]] 04:16, 5 July 2007 (UTC)


== &quot;Choices vs. consequences&quot; section ==

I've just removed the following vague sounding/possible original research from the article:
:''Consequences of personal choices may impact on other people and any associated responsibilities may extend into a wider society. They are major factors in life, as they determine one's relationships with oneself and with others. One's choices often affect one's ethics in a much more grand scheme. Negative choices often create a &quot;numbness&quot; due to familiarity with the negativity (A creates B which perpetuates A, with A being the negative choice and B being the &quot;numbness&quot; due to it), furthering one's negativity. This is known as a downward spiral. In the reverse of this, known as an upward spiral, the same thing occurs but it furthers one's positive aspects; these aspects, whether negative or positive, affect one's life and therefore one's ethics, and so must be largely considered in this article.''

:Scavenge what ye will. &lt;font color=&quot;404040&quot;&gt;[[User:Skomorokh|Skomorokh]]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;''[[User talk:Skomorokh|&lt;em style=&quot;color:#000000;font-style:normal&quot;&gt;incite&lt;/em&gt;]]''&lt;/sup&gt; 03:26, 14 July 2007 (UTC)

==Requested move==
: [[Ethics]] → [[Ethics (disambiguation)]]
: [[Ethics (philosophy)]] → [[Ethics]]
The philosophical topic is the primary topic of the word compared with all the other articles linked from the disambiguation page [[Ethics]], and is reasonably what people expect when they search &quot;ethics&quot;. The user who made the original move in October was thinking &quot;[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Vassyana&amp;diff=179644248&amp;oldid=179592020 practical]&quot;, but this is covered by [[applied ethics]] as linked here, not on the dab page. –[[User talk:Pomte|Pomte]] 09:26, 2 January 2008 (UTC)

:Given what other pages exist, this move seems reasonable to me.  There are other uses not covered on the disambiguation page, however; which makes me wonder whether or not there is room for an [[Ethics]], an [[Ethics (philosophy)]], ''and'' an [[Ethics (disambiguation)]].  But that's something can be dealt with at a later time, I suppose. [[User:Postmodern Beatnik|Postmodern Beatnik]] ([[User talk:Postmodern Beatnik|talk]]) 18:32, 3 January 2008 (UTC)

:: I've performed the requested move.  (I'm not sure if there was some requirement to wait a number of days for debate, but I saw the old [[Ethics]] page in [[CAT:CSD]] and took action.)  Could those editors who maintain this article take care of checking redirects and links and update anything that looks inappropriate?  --[[User:Elkman|Elkman]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Elkman|(Elkspeak)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 01:08, 4 January 2008 (UTC)

::: No double redirects; all fixed by [[User:Computer]] it seems. The vast majority of incoming links are still to [[Ethics]] anyway, so nothing more needs to be done. Thanks. –[[User talk:Pomte|Pomte]] 08:29, 5 January 2008 (UTC)

==Ethics in education==
Could someone please direct me toward an article dealing with ethics in education? Particularly, dealing with role-playing or simulations where the goal of the exercise may be at odds with an ethical system or morality. I looked at the sidebar, but couldn't really find an article that suited my needs. Thanks! [[User:SharkD|SharkD]] ([[User talk:SharkD|talk]]) 23:55, 18 June 2008 (UTC)


==God?==
The section for stoicism refers to the dead 'returning to God'. It isn't explicit that God in this sense is not the Judeo-Christian God. Is there any way we can clear this up to make it less confusing? [[Special:Contributions/75.72.21.38|75.72.21.38]] ([[User talk:75.72.21.38|talk]]) 15:10, 24 January 2009 (UTC)

== Lede is POV? ==

The current lede for this article sounds rather biased toward the ancient Greek concept of ethics being about the search for happiness and the good life:

{{quote|Ethics is a word for a philosophy that encompasses proper conduct and good living. It is significantly broader than the common conception of ethics as the analyzing of right and wrong. '''A central aspect of ethics is &quot;the good life&quot;, the life worth living or that is simply satisfying, which is held by many philosophers to be more important than moral conduct.'''}}

(Emphasis mine.) While certainly Plato, Aristotle and the like were greatly focused on eudaimonia and such, most of medieval and certainly modern ethics was precisely about analyzing right and wrong in; and in contemporary analytic philosophy, even more so, with the development of metaethics.

I happened by here looking for quick links in a discussion about the relation and difference between ethics and morality; and on that note, the article on [[Morality]] has what I think is a much better and less biased summary of ethics, which could serve as the basis of a better lede for this article:

{{quote|Ethics seeks to address questions such as how a moral outcome can be achieved in a specific situation (applied ethics), how moral values should be determined (normative ethics), what morals people actually abide by (descriptive ethics), what the fundamental nature of ethics or morality is, including whether it has any objective justification (meta-ethics), and how moral capacity or moral agency develops and what its nature is (moral psychology).}}

Opinions? --[[User:Pfhorrest|Pfhorrest]] ([[User talk:Pfhorrest|talk]]) 03:23, 17 March 2009 (UTC)

== Proposed reorganization ==

I would like to propose a reorganization of this article into more logical subdivisions of the field of ethics:

*Analytic Ethics or Metaethics
*Normative Ethics (also incorporating what is currently under &quot;Greek Philosophy&quot;, which may be better moved into their respective articles):
**Virtue Ethics (most of what's currently under &quot;Greek philosophy&quot;)
**Consequentialism
**Deontology
*Applied Ethics (also incorporating current subsections like &quot;Relational Ethics&quot; and &quot;Military Ethics&quot;
*Descriptive Ethics
*Moral Psychology

I'm unsure if moral psychology belongs as a subsections descriptive ethics or not, since it is mostly concerned with why people make moral choices (a descriptive, empirical question) rather than more analytic questions like &quot;what is right or wrong&quot; or &quot;what does 'good' mean?&quot; However it does involve some analytic subtopics like the relevance or moral luck, so I'm not sure.

I'm likewise uncertain where to categorize evolutionary ethics; it seems most naturally to belong as a part of moral psychology, and that was the course at uni under which I studied the subject. (Our moral psych course was our only phil course to talk about ev-psych, that is).

Opinions? --[[User:Pfhorrest|Pfhorrest]] ([[User talk:Pfhorrest|talk]]) 22:18, 17 March 2009 (UTC)

I just created an account to suggest something like this myself - there is currently too much weight on Greek ethics and no mention of consequentialism or deontology.  Virtue ethics, deontology, consequentialism and other approaches to ethics have meta-ethical implications, as well as implications for applied ethics, so would it be appropriate to explain the different aspects to ethical study (meta-, normative and applied etihcs) before brief descriptions of the main ethical schools of thought?

*Meta-ethics
*Normative Ethics
*Applied Ethics
*Moral Psychology
*Approaches to Ethics (or something)
**Virtue Ethics
**Consequentialism
**Deontology
**Cultural Relativism
**Ethical Egoism
**Non-cognitivism

Hope this stimulates some debate, anyway.

[[User:Deafpanda|Deafpanda]] ([[User talk:Deafpanda|talk]]) 18:58, 4 May 2009 (UTC)

==Capitalist ethics==
According to [[Arjen Hoekstra]], the current unregulated capitalist/consumerist trading system is unethical. Arjen Hoekstra compares the consumption of products made at such a fashion that it devestates the local environment (bringing people locally in trouble) with[[Handling_stolen_goods|the handling of stolen goods]]. He says that it is &quot;playing innocent while purchasing a bycicle for 10$ of a junkie&quot;. 

Perhaps it can be added in article. The analogy used above (which is I believe very accurate) could be mentioned.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/91.176.1.77|91.176.1.77]] ([[User talk:91.176.1.77|talk]]) 17:25, 4 July 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Orginial research/synthesis in postmodern ethics section? ==
The Postmodern Ethics section seems to contain more speculation than reporting of the various opinions held by scholars of ethics. It definitely has POV problems. [[User:David Delony|David Delony]] ([[User talk:David Delony|talk]]) 16:26, 18 July 2009 (UTC)

== → A Call for Clarity ← ==
O, People! So much arcana here... where's the clarity? More than ever in this day and age, '''Ethics needs to be explained first in lay-terms''' to make it accessible to the majority of people and understandable by corporate executives, politicians and blue-collar workers, not just academic philosophers. Right now, the page reads like a cabal of bankers extollling the subtleties of exotic derivative funds, and not a good explanation of balancing one's checkbook. Perhaps there also needs to be a clear distinction made between '''ethics''' ''as a more objective scientific pursuit of basic human societal systems of law and justice'' and the popular association of '''morals''' with ''highly subjective mores intended to regulate sexual/romantic relationships'' (e.g. religious morality). This page begs for a straightforward '''Abstract''' that any 5-year-old can grok before the two-dollar college words get thrown around so freely, so here's a derivative sample for someone higher on the Wiki food-chain to consider including some version of on the main page:
     &quot;Ethics is a system/science/philosophy of moral principles, values or 
      codes, for guiding the behavior of a person or group. In practical terms, 
      being an ethical person is also referred to as &quot;having a value system&quot;, 
      &quot;possessing virtues&quot;, &quot;knowing right from wrong&quot;, &quot;having principles or ideals&quot;,
      &quot;maintaining good standards&quot; (of behavior) or as &quot;following the dictates of conscience&quot;.
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/66.80.62.59|66.80.62.59]] ([[User talk:66.80.62.59|talk]]) 20:11, 21 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
: I've just given a shot at making the lede a bit more layman-friendly, but I don't think your sample idea there is on the right track. Ethics is not a system of moral principles at all; ethics is the STUDY of systems of moral principles. That's the primary difference between &quot;ethics&quot; and &quot;morals&quot;; the former is the study of the latter. --[[User:Pfhorrest|Pfhorrest]] ([[User talk:Pfhorrest|talk]]) 22:46, 21 November 2009 (UTC)

Ethics lost the few reason that they had ever had after the definition of them made by Kant. Before the categoric imperative, the function of ethics was to guide the human being (a lonely subject) in his or her way of life, to reach the happiness (eudaimonia in aristotelian words). But Kant, with that Christian submission that ruled him, reduced ethics to a thing without any sense, submiting them to the empty concepts of good and evil. If pre-kantian ethics were stupid (just tried to make universal what was not), post-kantian ethics, based in empty values and false altruism (inexistent) are just the worst mental illness of the people.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.203.105.32|81.203.105.32]] ([[User talk:81.203.105.32|talk]]) 20:17, 26 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::Thats called [[psychologism]], simpleton.  [[User:Teetotaler|Teetotaler]]  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.67.81.197|75.67.81.197]] ([[User talk:75.67.81.197|talk]]) 04:54, 27 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== The [[Bad faith]] article needs help from available editors ==

The [[Bad faith]] article needs help from available editors. [[User:HkFnsNGA|HkFnsNGA]] ([[User talk:HkFnsNGA|talk]]) 06:18, 29 January 2011 (UTC)

== Military Ethics Neutrality Disputed ==
&quot;The Department of Defense 5500.7-R (DoD 5500.7-R), serves as the primary regulatory source of ethical standards and conduct to members of the Armed Services (DoD, pg 1). Since this is the only order used, all changes must be made by revision.&quot; I flagged this line on 05/09/2011.

I think this is a fairly obvious non-neutral point of view. Please include citation link, notes that this refers to military ethics in the United States and in formation of ethics regulation in other nation's military organizations. -[[User:AndreisEntaro|Andreis]]  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 05:22, 9 May 2011 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== no ethics between Epictetus and Bentham? ==

was there really no study of ethics between Epictetus ''ob''.135, and Bentham ''ort''. 1748?  --[[User:Richardson mcphillips|Richardson mcphillips]] ([[User talk:Richardson mcphillips|talk]]) 17:05, 9 May 2011 (UTC)

== Vandalism ==

Removed unsourced, non-neutral arbitrary one-line edit from over 50 edits ago under &quot;Stoicism&quot;. [[Special:Contributions/143.107.180.128|143.107.180.128]] ([[User talk:143.107.180.128|talk]]) 17:29, 16 June 2011 (UTC)

== Non-western societies ==

Where is information on ideas of ethics outside the West?  I don't just mean China and India, but also among Australian Aborigines, indigenous tribes of Africa and South America, Native Americans, etc.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.9.112.31|99.9.112.31]] ([[User talk:99.9.112.31|talk]]) 22:06, 26 June 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I agree. There's no reason not to have non-western ethical systems included here. There's not one mention of Buddha or Confucius, let alone a discussion. There's a lot to compare when it comes to this: Confucianism vs. the Peripatetic school when it comes to virtue ethics; Yangism vs. Carvaka vs. Hedonism; Buddhism vs. Epicureanism vs. Mohism; etc.. Right now all there is is a discussion on Mohism. Let's get on this!

Here's some resources to get us started:
*http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-indian-buddhism/
*http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-chinese/
*http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/comparphil-chiwes/
[[User:Dan Cottrell|Dan Cottrell]] ([[User talk:Dan Cottrell|talk]]) 23:56, 18 June 2012 (UTC)

== Virtue ethics ==
I know Epicureanism is considered a form of virtue ethics by scholars, but does that also apply to Cyrenaic hedonism?--[[User:Theconsequentialist|Theconsequentialist]] ([[User talk:Theconsequentialist|talk]]) 23:38, 10 October 2011 (UTC)

== Military Ethics: Remove? ==

The information currently in Military Ethics is nothing of the sort.  Military Ethics is not about the adminstrative decisions faced by any organization, and the inclusion of a reference for one military's ethical baseline is hardly encyclopedic without a lot more meat on the bone.
Rather than try to address it here, I recommed simply linking to a [[Military Ethics]] page, and work from there.
[[User:Haakondahl|Haakondahl]] ([[User talk:Haakondahl|talk]]) 04:05, 18 October 2011 (UTC)

== potential resources ==

From [[Talk:Morality]] ...
* ''A Perfect Moral Storm: The Ethical Tragedy of Climate Change (Environmental Ethics and Science Policy)'' by Stephen Gardiner (Associate Professor in the Department of Philosophy and the Program on Values in Society, University of Washington, Seattle) Publisher: [[Oxford University Press]], USA (May 4, 2011) ISBN-13: 978-0195379440 [http://www.amazon.com/Perfect-Moral-Storm-Ethical-Environmental/dp/0195379446/ref=pd_sim_b_36]

* ''Moral Ground: Ethical Action for a Planet in Peril'' by Editors Kathleen Dean Moore and Michael P. Nelson, publisher [[Trinity University Press]]; 1st Printing edition (August 31, 2010) ISBN-13: 978-1595340665

* ''Ethics of Climate Change: Right and Wrong in a Warming World (Think Now)'' by [[James Garvey (philosopher)|James Garvey]] publisher Continuum (March 21, 2008) ISBN-13: 978-0826497376

* ''A Moral Climate: The Ethics of Global Warming'' by Michael S. Northcott publisher [[Orbis Books]] (October 31, 2007)  ISBN-13: 978-1570757112

See [[global warming]] ([[climate change]]), [[ethics]], [[effects of climate change on humans]] ([[effects of global warming]] in general for non-humans), [[risks to civilization, humans and planet Earth]], [[Climate ethics]], [[Climate justice]]
[[Special:Contributions/99.19.45.187|99.19.45.187]] ([[User talk:99.19.45.187|talk]]) 06:16, 10 December 2011 (UTC)

== The quality of the article and its bibliography ==

I pose the following question to all serious contributors here: Which are the classical works on ethics that are not even mentioned in this article?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/174.91.198.186|174.91.198.186]] ([[User talk:174.91.198.186|talk]]) 02:45, 19 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Hillel's Ethics ==

This subject is lacking a reference to Biblical ethics. Where is mentioned anything about our relationships to one another, without having to introduce the prior concept of right or wrong?

The &quot;Golden Rule&quot; of loving one's neighbor as oneself (Leviticus) is a bit vauge when it comes to ethics, but this idea was later modified so as to be more specific, by Hillel the Elder (about 40 BCE to 50 CE), who said &quot;What is abhorent to yourself do not do to your neighbor, the rest (of the Torah) is commentry, now go and study (it)&quot;. Hillel was the joint head of the Sanhedrin at this time. This answer was in response to a prosylite who taunted Hillel to explain his religion whilst standing on one leg. 

Other religions also have introduced similar ideas, yet what is right or wrong has somehow been developed here without the human relationship side.[[User:Macrocompassion|Macrocompassion]] ([[User talk:Macrocompassion|talk]]) 14:44, 29 June 2012 (UTC)

== What's the difference between religion and ethics ==

Do you know?[[Special:Contributions/119.85.245.239|119.85.245.239]] ([[User talk:119.85.245.239|talk]]) 15:20, 19 July 2012 (UTC)

Yes, religion is a worldly organisation of people who believe in a supernatural creator.  Ethics is a system of belief in, or theory of,  what is right and wrong. Not sure why anyone would not know the difference? Religion can be used as an excuse for advancing one's own ideas about what is right and wrong, but most people see through that. If God told us to kill children , or to cheat and torture, would that make it right?

No, I think most people know that a religion which advocates actions which are wrong has itself got something fundamentally wrong with it. Things aren't right because religion says so, rather what is right is advocated by sensible religions.
[[User:TonyClarke|TonyClarke]] ([[User talk:TonyClarke|talk]]) 19:52, 19 July 2012 (UTC)

== New section: defining ethics ==

I added a section called &quot;Defining ethics.&quot; Seemed like a better title than &quot;Definitions&quot; or &quot;Views&quot;, but maybe there is a better name. I got the section started, but there is plenty of room to expand. This seems to be an area that many people will come to Wikipedia for: to tell the difference between morality and ethics, and what each of them are. Of course, authors such as Peter Singer see no difference between the two, and that can be noted here. More to the point though, there are reliable sources who will define ethics in the same way as Paul and Elder, and those who will define ethics differently. I see the section including all notable points of view on how to define ethics. --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 14:42, 13 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>r6fpf297u7vkq0fl869n6xdhc3f2vyn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
