<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Political religion</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>795516</id>
    <revision>
      <id>460134838</id>
      <parentid>460134757</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-11-11T14:52:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>FINginga</username>
        <id>13321367</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Scientific definitions and references */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13528">{{Talkheader}}

*[[Wikipedia:Votes for deletion/Political religion|July/August 2005 deletion debate]]. See also [[Talk:Civic religion/archive]].

== Statist religion ==

I agreed with the previous suggestion to rename this article &quot;Statist religion&quot;, so I implemented it.  I also agreed that the article needed attention, so I gave it some.

:I have adjusted the article to make it more &quot;political&quot; than &quot;statist&quot; in nature.  A political religion need not have the power of the state on its side.  It can also be extreme adherence to any political dogma or group.[[User:Dogface|Dogface]] 14:37, 7 March 2006 (UTC)

While the text is probably reads more like an encyclopedia article should, and while I've added some facts, I think there are still some serious problems.  First of all, I think the article has lost track of the distinction statist ''religion'' and totalitarianism in general.  Religion or statist indoctrination are certainly a tool of totalitarianism, but I think a lot of other totalitarian-related things have gotten mixed in here.  Or maybe they are not really separable.  In short, I guess some or all of the material here should be merged with [[totalitarianism]] and/or [[authoritarianism]].

I suspect that it will probably require a subject expert or a substantial literature search to have an entire article's worth of information on the religious/dogmatic aspects of totalitarianism.

I also feel that this article, including the text I've written, makes statist religion and totalitarianism sound like a bad thing.  Which of course, I think it is - but if so this runs afoul of Wikipedia's [[Wikipedia:Neutral point of view|NPOV policy]].  It may also be that I'm describing the subject relatively objectively, but it's just so nasty I can't help feeling the article shows it in a bad light.

:I agree with you. The biggest problem is smashing together the moralistic sentiments of the evils some regimes WITH a political religion did, and the actual substance and an object of academic research of the religious aspect in their politics. Scientific objectivity requires analytic precision on that. I intend to make a few changes on that (the small moralistic parts without any reference). [[User:FINginga|FINginga]] ([[User talk:FINginga|talk]]) 12:25, 11 November 2011 (UTC)

Some input from people who have actually lived under one of the regimes named in the stubby case studies section would be incredibly helpful. -- [[User:Beland|Beland]] 05:20, 7 Mar 2005 (UTC)

:Let's be careful in fixing links to the [[civic religion]] redirect page.  ''Some'' of them should point at [[statist religion]], some at [[civil religion]], and perhaps some elsewhere.  And maybe some should be replaced by ''two'' links, one to each article. [[User:Michael Hardy|Michael Hardy]] 22:15, 7 Mar 2005 (UTC)

This article needs a mountain of work - at least it's under the right name now. (&quot;Statist religion&quot; is a neologism, as the tiny number of Google hits shows.)  [[User:Rd232|Rd232]] 13:31, 6 Jun 2005 (UTC)

== Wow ==

&quot;Iraq (historical)
[edit]

China
[edit]

North Korea
[edit]

Nazi Germany
[edit]

Soviet Union (historical)
[edit]

Japan (historical)&quot;

Glad to know the only statist religions that ever existed were enemies of the glorious United States, whose current leader doesn't blend religion with his identity at all.

Genius, the leader of the glorious United States doesn't persecute people who disagree with him.  And I'm not saying the U.S. doesn't promote an uber-patriotic culture, it's just not in the same way as say, oh, North Korea.--[[User:naryathegreat]] | [[User talk:Naryathegreat|(talk)]] 00:24, Mar 23, 2005 (UTC)

:Arguably, it is much worse.  Are you aware of the [[USA PATRIOT Act]], for instance?  Surely you have heard of the [[Religious right]] as well.  Also, see the article on [[Dispensationalism#Dispensationalism_and_United_States_politics|Dispensationalism]]. [[User:Luis Dantas|Luis Dantas]] 03:04, 23 Mar 2005 (UTC)

:That's an argument you can't win.  We don't say the lotus blossoms bloomed better (oh but they do in North Korea) the year George Bush was elected in our country, and we don't force people to be Christian, or else we wouldn't even be hearing cases concerning the constitutionality of displaying the ten commandments.  Honestly that's stupid.  The Religious right is not some kind of uber-religious fascist organization.  the Patriot Act is not quite the same as totalitarianism, I suppose the bill of rights is just something we make-believe with.  You seem to be misunderstanding what goes on in North Korea, where you are FORCED to do these things.  No one is forced to be part of the religious right or become a dispensationalist.-[[User:naryathegreat]] | [[User talk:Naryathegreat|(talk)]] 22:23, Mar 23, 2005 (UTC)

I agree with Dantas and disagree with Narya. This is not an article meant to preach or propagate an ideology, whether its american or not. It´s an article about a scientific field and has substance to be referenced to. FORCING something is´nt a criterion for a religion. [[User:FINginga|FINginga]] ([[User talk:FINginga|talk]]) 12:29, 11 November 2011 (UTC)

==VfD Discussion==
This article was recently nominated for deletion but kept by default of no consensus being reached.  See [[Wikipedia:Votes for deletion/Political religion]] for the archived discussion -- [[User:Francs2000|Francs2000]] | [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Francs2000&amp;action=edit&amp;section=new Talk] [[Image:Flag of the United Kingdom.svg|25px|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]] 15:40, 7 August 2005 (UTC)

==A term is a term==

A term is a term. The thing that the term refers to is not a term.  A political religion is not a term.  The ''term'' &quot;political religion&quot; is a term.  Thus it makes no sense to begin by saying that a political religion is a term. [[User:Michael Hardy|Michael Hardy]] 00:48, 27 August 2005 (UTC)

: True.

: Come on though, there is no difference between a political ideology and a religion... they are the same thing! 
: If anything it's religion that is politics that co-opts faith!
[[Special:Contributions/87.114.3.143|87.114.3.143]] ([[User talk:87.114.3.143|talk]]) 15:22, 27 November 2007 (UTC) Promsan

== Accuracy? ==

&quot;Quintessential examples are Marxism and Nazism, but totalitarianism is not a requirement&quot;

Is this accurate?  Marxism is not a totalitarian system by definition. [[User:24.154.247.181|24.154.247.181]] 03:20, 30 December 2005 (UTC)

:Marxism could be validly considered an archetypal totalitarian system.  All aspects of life are to be subjugated to &quot;the revolution&quot;.  All people are defined in terms of their relationship to &quot;the proletariat&quot; and &quot;the revolution&quot;.  All aspects of life in Marxist countries get re-organized according to &quot;the revolution&quot;. If Marxism is not totalitarian, then Nazism is not totalitarian. [[User:Dogface|Dogface]] 14:03, 2 March 2006 (UTC)

::Democracy could be validly considered an archetypal totalitarian system. All aspects of life are to be subjugated to &quot;free elections&quot;. All people are defined in terms of their relationship to &quot;representatives&quot; and &quot;accountability&quot;. All aspects of life in Democratic countries get re-organized according to &quot;free elections&quot;. If Democracy is not totalitarian, then Nazism is not totalitarian. [[User:Lpetrazickis|Lpetrazickis]] 15:32, 13 October 2006 (UTC)

::I think my previous comment is a bit opaque and unconstructive. I don't think you'll get many arguments about [[Marxism-Leninism]] being a totalitarian system, but [[Marxism]] proper appeared in the early 19th century and wasn't tied to totalitarianism until ML came along. Totalitarianism relates to implementation, not philosophy -- [[Marxism]] may be unimplementable, but it doesn't call for secret police, camps for dissenters, and institutionalized fear.

::It doesn't even call for a one-party state – the first thing [[Bolsheviks]] did after the [[October Revolution]] was hold an election. They lost with 28% of the final vote, so they disbanded the elected body. I don't think any of the original Russian revolutionaries initially intended to set up anything totalitarian. It just turned out that way. The rational thing would have been to abandon the impractical aspects of the philosophy, but they instead went for enforced ideological purity and called it [[Marxism-Leninism]]. That gets you totalitarianism.[[User:Lpetrazickis|Lpetrazickis]] 15:51, 13 October 2006 (UTC)

:::All this theory is cute, but you really have to look at the way things turned out. You can't say ML isn't dictatorial in theory, when it's outcome is dictatorial. And saying that &quot;the original Russian revolutionaries initially intended to set up anything totalitarian. It just turned out that way.&quot; is just disshonest. They might not have intended to set up a totalitarian state, but they did. It didn't &quot;just turn out that way&quot; by itself, they actively made it totalitarian. [[User:ArnoldPlaton|ArnoldPlaton]] ([[User talk:ArnoldPlaton|talk]]) 06:56, 23 April 2010 (UTC)

==Catholicism and Freemasonry==
Many of the original Church-State conflicts of the 18th, 19th and 20th centuries were related to a much deeper conflict between [[Catholicism and Freemasonry]]. For instance, the Church has condemned Masons since 1738, and many prominent secularists such as Thomas Jefferson and Émile Combes have been Freemasons. It would not be a bad thing to mention this with relevant sources, the only problem being that any unexpected mention of Freemasonry is taboo. Also, I noticed that one major difference between American secularism and French/Turkish/Mexican secularism is that the US Grand Lodge masons are usually deists while the French/Turkish/Mexican Grand Orient masons are often agnostic/atheist. [[User:ADM|ADM]] ([[User talk:ADM|talk]]) 04:46, 11 April 2009 (UTC)

== Besmirch of DPRK (&quot;North Korea&quot;)!! ==

North Korea does not possess a state religion this is total propaganda this article must updated to reflect accuracy instead of lie. Read here:
[http://www1.korea-np.co.jp/pk/061st_issue/98091708.htm#Chapter%203:Culture Official DPRK Constitution]
Specifically:
Article 68
Citizens have freedom of religious beliefs. This right is granted by approving the construction of religious buildings and the holding of religious ceremonies.
If wikipedia hopes to be a source of information for the education of the proletariat it must gain an objectivity instead of mindlessly parroting talking points of the white house and western neo-con type interests. It seems many article are written by those working within the US government or hired lackeys thereof to turn wikipedia into a mouthpiece of lies if the quality could be improved to reflect facts than countries who seek to shield their citizens from lies could open access to this site and make it a more widely used resource. Someone please remove flase references to the DPRK from this article!  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:ProgressiveThinker|ProgressiveThinker]] ([[User talk:ProgressiveThinker|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/ProgressiveThinker|contribs]]) 20:49, 8 December 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


==Inclusion of US==
I think the inclusion of the US in here, on the Fear section, seems very odd. I mean you have China, the Soviet Union, Nazi Germany, and then America. One of these things is not like the others, one of these things just does not belong. If one reads the article, you can see that States does not match the aspects of a political religion in any significant way. It seems that according to whoever wrote it that using fear tactics for political use makes you a country with a political religion...which is obviously not true, or you may as well put every country in that section.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.67.52.85|24.67.52.85]] ([[User talk:24.67.52.85|talk]]) 15:28, 30 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Scientific definitions and references ==

I made a few changes. Based on Academic discussion about the meaning of Political religion, few of which I added, I erased the parts about what some regimes WITH a (considered to have a) political religion have done in history and which didn´t have religious substance within. The modern utilization of mass-media, for example, does not count by any definition a criterion of religion. In that case the US would be a totalitarian political religion, which it is not. In any case, there seems to be a serious confusion, by some, between [[Totalitarianism]] and political religion. Both are topics of academic research, but they are DIFFERENT topics, with different concepts and some different researchers. This article is not about totalitarianism, it`s about political religion. The question of totalitarianism has to be taken on page [[Totalitarianism]]. [[User:FINginga|FINginga]] ([[User talk:FINginga|talk]]) 12:43, 11 November 2011 (UTC)
:A notable change I made on the article was to remove a non-referential part on Fear, which did´nt seem to have a single link on religious aspect of politics, but instead a sort of patronizing, intentional mixing of totalitarianism and political religion as a part of preaching against Evil. [[User:FINginga|FINginga]] ([[User talk:FINginga|talk]]) 14:49, 11 November 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>1rn4idhze67pksf5ht31nwzcew3lt9c</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
