<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Religion</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>25885</id>
    <revision>
      <id>520306545</id>
      <parentid>520236276</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-28T19:15:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tryptofish</username>
        <id>7627571</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Parody religions */ comment</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="48790">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{Outline of knowledge coverage|religion}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=19:41, 15 April 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Religion/archive1
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=48356882

|action2=PR
|action2date=22:22, 19 November 2009
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Religion/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=326804209

|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPReligion|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Theology|class=c|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Sociology|class=c|importance=High}}
{{philosophy|importance=high|class=c|religion=yes|ethics=yes}}
{{VA|topic=Philosophy|level=2|class=C}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|core=yes|WPCD=yes|class=C|importance=top|category=Philrelig}}}}
{{onlinesource|year=2006|section={Section}
| author=Andrew Stephens
| title=God of all things
| org=The Age
| url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/in-depth/god-of-all-things/2006/04/08/1143916767108.html?page=fullpage#contentSwap2
| date=9/4/2006}}
{{Pbneutral}}
{{auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot|age=30|dounreplied=yes}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 200K
|counter = 10
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Religion/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Religion/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Religion/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes
}}

== What is the True Definition of &quot;Religion&quot; ? ==

Here in Wiki, religion define as created human culture...... Refereeing to all holy 'Divine Scriptures and Books' this is not the true definition of term &quot;Religion&quot;...Religion is religion, it is not human religion or belief or thought … it is not human made ….. 

All the natural people reject Wiki defition but they accept this defintion:

&quot;a set of beliefs concerning the cause, nature, and purpose of the universe, especially when considered as the creation of a superhuman agency or agencies, usually involving devotional and ritual observances, and often containing a moral code governing the conduct of human affairs&quot; ( http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/religion)   

 
Please share to correct and update universal definition of &quot;Religion&quot; as it is inspired to all Holy Prophets and Messengers.
&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Eajohali|Eajohali]] ([[User talk:Eajohali|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Eajohali|contribs]]) 11:16, April 19, 2012‎&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== Number ==

Avanu said the religion numbers seem high. Well, it is but thats because thats what reliable sources say; i.e. [http://www.adherents.com/ this ref]  by Adherents states they have researched into 4,200 religions. And thats only the ones they have researched. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 15:13, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:The adherents site does NOT say &quot;4,200 religions&quot;. It says &quot;over 4,200 religions, churches, denominations, religious bodies, faith groups, tribes, cultures, movements, ultimate concerns, etc.&quot; Big difference. [[User:Dominus Vobisdu|Dominus Vobisdu]] ([[User talk:Dominus Vobisdu|talk]]) 15:20, 16 August 2012 (UTC)
:: If you read the preceding sentence it says &quot;adherents statistics&quot; and &quot;religious geography citations&quot;. Anyway, this is besides the point because i used a different source in my edit. Do you have a source that disputes the source i used in the article? Do you have a source with different statistics? [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 15:38, 16 August 2012 (UTC)

:::The 4,200 Adherents.com number is quoted widely: Timothy Samuel Shah ''et al'' in ''Rethinking Religion and World Affairs'', page 293; Susan George in ''Religion And Technology in the 21st Century: Faith in the E-world'', page 90; Richard J. Wallace in ''The Lazy Intellectual: Maximum Knowledge, Minimal Effort'', page 237; Sheila Keene-Lund in ''Heaven Is Not the Last Stop: Exploring A New Revelation'', page 456; J. B. Zegalia in ''Impact: The 7 Undeniable and Often Uncontrollable Powers of Influence''; and Claudio Feser in ''Serial Innovators: Firms That Change the World'', page 102. Philosophy professor Kenneth Shouler wrote: [http://books.google.com/books?id=qZrTbY77g3oC&amp;pg=PA1 &quot;Through the ages It can be asserted with confidence that no one knows exactly how many religions there are, although the best estimate is about 4,200.&quot;] On the other hand, religion professor Christopher Hugh Partridge wrote, [http://books.google.com/books?id=7lEFyGiP5r8C&amp;pg=PA351 &quot;In 1987 in South Africa, for example, there were over 4,200 distinct Zionist denominations.&quot;] [[Max Weber]] thought that there were [http://books.google.com/books?id=AwnIIXI6y38C&amp;pg=PA402 hundreds of thousands of religions] starting from the dawn of history. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 17:30, 16 August 2012 (UTC)

::::I don't have a problem with one sentence saying that there are thousands (although I'd rather not see so much reverting). Obviously, it's a matter of how one defines a single religion. If there are sources that say there are that many, I'm OK with that. However, we might be able to reconcile this discussion by putting &quot;According to some estimates,...&quot; at the beginning of the sentence. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 20:02, 16 August 2012 (UTC)

: The relevant sentence in the cited (Samovar, Porter and McDaniel) book appears to be &quot;with thousands of religions, cults, movements, philosophies, and worldviews to choose from....&quot; which is a much broader statement than &quot;There are thousands of religions in the world&quot;. The latter is therefore highly misleading and in the context of this wiki article, of no real value and potentially confusing. I would recommend removing it. On the subject of &quot;4200 religions&quot;, it is true that this figure is cited numerous times (although I suspect re-circulated from a single source) but as shown on the Adherents.com website, 98% of the world population are adherents of the top 22 religions. [[User:Vacarme|Vacarme]] ([[User talk:Vacarme|talk]]) 19:44, 19 August 2012 (UTC)

== Eastern religions and circumsizing religions ==

Is there any web page ?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/120.61.18.32|120.61.18.32]] ([[User talk:120.61.18.32|talk]]) 15:33, 30 August 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:[[Eastern religions]] and [[History of male circumcision]]. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 21:57, 30 August 2012 (UTC)

== Religion and violence ==

Some of the passages in the [[Morality#Morality_and_religion|Morality]] article discuss Religion and violence—specifically the &quot;Empirical Analyses&quot; section. I think empirical analyses of the relationship between religion and violence (e.g., homicide) are more relevant than people's mere opinions. Is there any reason why some of these passages should not be added to the &quot;Religion and violence&quot; section of this article? --[[User:Airborne84|Airborne84]] ([[User talk:Airborne84|talk]]) 03:44, 4 September 2012 (UTC)

== Germanic neopaganism ==

There is a slow [[WP:EW|edit war]] going on about the lead image, whether a particular image should represent [[Germanic neopaganism]] or [[Wikka]]. Whichever the sources indicate it is, please discuss it here on the talk page, and back it up with source material, so we can reach [[WP:Consensus|consensus]]. If the reversions continue, I will ask that the page be full-protected. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 21:37, 15 September 2012 (UTC)

:Some other relevant conversation may be found at [[Talk:Wicca#Third opinion]].  The triple crescent in the file is a [[triquetra]], not a [[triskelion]].  The sources presented to say that the triple crescent is part of Germanic Neopaganism (aside from being [[WP:SPS|self published blogs]] and not [[WP:RS]]) discuss triskelions, *NOT* triquetras.  Triskelions (which the horn of Odin is) are not the same as triquetras (which the triple crescent figure in this page is).
:The file for the image notes that it is a symbol of the triple goddess.  As I point out at [[Talk:Wicca]], [http://books.google.com/books?id=SImTll3uupIC&amp;lpg=PA103&amp;ots=CkOv9OLkTO&amp;dq=triple%20crescent%20wicca&amp;pg=PA103#v=onepage&amp;q=triple%20crescent%20wicca&amp;f=false The Signs and Symbols Bible] by Madonna Gauding notes that the Triple Goddess is sometimes &quot;shown as three crescent moons intertwined with each other&quot; (p.103).  There's a reliable source in favor of the Wicca identification, only [[WP:SPS|self-published sources]] discussing a [[triskelion|completely different symbol]] have been presented for the Germanic Neo-pagan identification. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 23:30, 15 September 2012 (UTC)

::I've found a second source. Just because Wicca USES the symbol doesn't mean it's a Wiccan symbol. if someone takes the cross and uses it for a second religion, is the Cross still Christian? --[[User:OCCullens|OCCullens]] ([[User talk:OCCullens|talk]]) 23:39, 15 September 2012 (UTC)

:::Symboldictionary.net is a Wordpress blog (that plagiarizes old About.com articles, no less), a [[WP:SPS|self-published site]], not a [[WP:RS|reliable source]].
:::We have one RS and the original file calling that triquetra variant Wiccan.  It's not a universal symbol for Wicca, and [[Diane de Poitiers]] (who was probably at least nominally Christian) used it before Wiccans did, but the best ID (given what sources have been presented and the original file's page) is &quot;Wiccan.&quot;
:::The sources you presented so far ([[WP:SPS]] aside) are about triskelions, not triquetras.  This is like getting the [[Eastern cross]] and the [[Tiwaz rune]] mixed up.  Please make sure that future sources meet [[WP:RS|the reliable sourcing guidelines]] and are about triquetras, not triskelions.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 23:48, 15 September 2012 (UTC)

{{double image|right|Triquetra-Vesica.svg|100|Triskel type Amfreville.svg|100|Triquetra ''(left)'' and Triskelion ''(right)''}}
I've shown the two symbols at the right. I'd say the image on this page resembles a Triquetra to the extent that it is made of three interlocking elements, and it resembles a Triskelion to the degree that the elements are at least somewhat serpentine and open-ended. I've read the sources cited by OCCullens and by Ian.thomson, and I'd say that the reliable sourcing points towards the image on the page being a triple crescent, rather than a triple horn, whereas OCCullens' sourcing seems to be about the triple horn. Thus, I think there is a stronger argument for it being Wikka than it being Neo-pagan, but I don't think the arguments are absolute. Is there a basis for saying that the symbol is used by both religions? Or perhaps this is simply a matter where we should not be using this particular image. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 01:24, 16 September 2012 (UTC)
:: How about we use both, as in [[wicca]]/[[germanic neopaganism]] ? [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 01:44, 16 September 2012 (UTC)

:::It's a triquetra in that the sides are equal and centered, even if there are fringe bits (remove those and you have a triquetra).  The triskelion goes off center (and if you remove the fringe bits on an archetypal triskelion, you have three lines pointing out to where the corners of a triangle would be).
:::I would accept a general &quot;neopaganism&quot; as a compromise, but no RSs have been presented for Germanic neopaganism, and none of the sources on Germanic neopaganism presented so far discuss the symbol used on the page. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 03:36, 16 September 2012 (UTC)

::::#There is such a thing as a goddess symbol that doesn't represent Wicca. There are many goddeses and triple goddesses throughout history, most of them predating the 'Wicca' movement. My point is it doesn't matter if the symbol is a goddess symbol or not; that's not a metric of Wiccan-ness.
::::#The emblem of [[Diane_de_Poitiers]] is older than the Wicca movement. Obviously, a symbol ''can'' be considered one that represents a given movement if usage justifies it - regardless of origin. However if usage is the standard, then Wicca is best represented by a pentagram or triquetra.
::::#Looking close to a triquetra doesn't make it one. Many things ''look'' like other things.
::::#The symbol in question isn't very well attested and doesn't have wide usage from either Germanic or Wiccan neopagans. However, it does seem to get confused for other symbols by both parties.
::::My opinion is the the symbol should be changed. It's too dubious and isn't a first choice symbol for representing either group. It should either be turned onto a proper Triple Horn of Odin if it's supposed to represent Germanic neopaganism or changed to a pentagram if it's supposed to represent Wicca. The file description would indicate the latter.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 05:11, 16 September 2012 (UTC)

:::::Personally, I'd rather see a symbol for all of [[Contemporary Paganism]] rather than one for only a single group. ...if we were able to agree on a single symbol.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 05:25, 16 September 2012 (UTC)

::::::OK, I can see two good options here.
::::::#One would be to label it in the image legend with both Wikka and Neopaganism.
::::::#The other would be to stop using this particular image, until someone generates one with a better choice of symbol. We have a group image that used to be in the lead, and is now in the Definitions section, so we could move that one back to the lead until we have a better image to use.
::::::I'd be happy with either of those options. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 18:14, 16 September 2012 (UTC)

:::::::Okay, this is getting stupid. Just because symbols are USED by Wiccans does NOT mean the said symbols are Wiccan. Most, if not all, symbols and beliefs in Wicca are far older than not only Wicca but also most organized religions.--[[Special:Contributions/2602:306:C50F:6FE0:3484:FF1C:540E:9DF6|2602:306:C50F:6FE0:3484:FF1C:540E:9DF6]] ([[User talk:2602:306:C50F:6FE0:3484:FF1C:540E:9DF6|talk]]) 01:00, 17 September 2012 (UTC)

::::::::Please note the emerging consensus before ranting. It's not too far off from what you said.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 11:09, 17 September 2012 (UTC)

::::::::: Tryptofish, i support your first option, naming both. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 10:07, 19 September 2012 (UTC)

{{Outdent}}I'm confused. Wicca is part of Neopaganism. Do you mean label the symbol &quot;Wicca &amp; Germanic Neopaganism&quot; or simply &quot;Neopaganism&quot;?&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 10:47, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
: I mean &quot;Wicca &amp; Germanic neopaganism&quot;. We could use a slash as in &quot;wicca/germanic neopaganism&quot;. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 11:19, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
::The issue I have with including Germanic neopaganism is that no RSs have been brought forward to connect that symbol to that religion (the closest those blogs presented was three crescents interlocking in the middle, not the edges, hence &quot;trikelion, not triquetra&quot;).  Changing the image to a Horn of Odin and the caption to Germanic Neopaganism would work, as would changing the image to a pentagram and saying &quot;Neopaganism,&quot; but so far the RSs only say that symbol has been used by Wiccans.  That it is a minority symbol make changing it one of the better options.
::Actually, I think the whole chart needs to be redone.  We've got three Christian crosses (including the Solar cross which was used by Christians both Gnostic and otherwise, and would not have been used by Jewish Gnostics), and two for Jainism.  The use of the [[Star and crescent]] for Islam is also questionable (it doesn't appear in the Islam article once because it isn't considered sacred within Islam).  The Slavic Neopaganism may also be undue.  While that religion is certainly notable, has it really had the same cultural influence that Taoism or Sikhism have had?  And what order are the symbols in?  They're not in most member to least members, nor alphabetical order.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 17:03, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
:::I think that if we keep this image, we should label it &quot;Wicca/Neopaganism&quot;, leaving out the &quot;Germanic&quot; modifier. But I also think that what Ian says is a good reason to temporarily remove the image, and move the other image back up. Do we really need both of these composites of symbols? I think not. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 22:22, 19 September 2012 (UTC)
::::'Wicca/Neopaganism' can be taken as an implication that 'Wicca' and 'Neopaganism' are interchangeable. I can easily many future bold edits ''correcting'' that.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 00:26, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
:::::For clarification, I think one symbol is best, but this seems to be a bit tricky. I think a different symbol + careful wording is advisable.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 00:33, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
:::I feel the same way, Ian. I've had my eye on that chart for a while. (Unfortunately, there'll be little chance of preserving that pretty 4x4 grid.) Multiple symbols for Christianity, Jainism, &amp; Hinduism seem unnecessary; if we're talk about due weight, where's [[Shenism]]; and symbols for ''multiple'' Neopagan branches is hard to justify. My only problem is that the Neopaganism project can't agree on a single symbol.&lt;br/&gt;A side note: the solar cross is the symbol displayed for {{tl|Gnosticism}}.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 00:26, 20 September 2012 (UTC)

== New religious symbols pic ==

[[File:ReligijneSymbole.png|250px|thumb|Religion symbols, &lt;br /&gt;row 1: [[Christianity]], [[Judaism]], [[Hinduism]], [[Baha'i Faith]]&lt;br /&gt;row 2: [[Islam]], [[Gnosticism]], [[Taoism]], [[Shinto]]&lt;br /&gt;row 3: [[Buddhism]], [[Sikhism]], [[Jainism]], Jainism, &lt;br /&gt;row 4: [[Ayyavazhi]], [[Wicca]], Christian, [[Slavic neopaganism]]]]
I've replaced this 4x4 pic with the 3x3, per above discussion, until if/when we come up with a better 4x4 pic (I think 5x5 might be possible, but it could be hard to see detail).  Issues raised with the 4x4 so far:
# Christian and Jainist symbols were repeated - This is simply a matter of deciding which to remove.  The Christian cross on the bottom isn't as archetypal as the first one, so the frilly one seems the obvious one to remove to me.  As for the Jainist symbols, the Jainism template uses both of those symbols.  I'm inclined to go with the hand instead of the swastika, not simply because of the misuse of that symbol, but because the &quot;backwards&quot; swastika is used by Hindus and Buddhists as well.
# Images are in no sensible order - Alphabetic order or number of adherents would be reasonable, but alphabetic order by the names of the religions will save us the headache of figuring out which religion has the most adherents, as well as arguments with the inevitable POV-pushers who are upset that their religion doesn't have more followers or that some religion they don't like has too many.
# Undue weight on individual branches of Neopaganism, compounded by a lack of appropriate symbol for all of Neopaganism - While the Pentagram does not represent all of Neopaganism, isn't it at least featured as a secondary or tertiary symbol in the majority of Neopagan religions?  And if not, although Wicca isn't necessarily the oldest Neopagan movement, isn't it a forerunner and influence for many other movements?
# Star and Crescent may not be the best symbol for Islam - The Arabic name Allah would probably be better, that's what the sidebar for Islam articles uses.
# [[Chinese folk religion]] not represented - While I'd welcome its presence, I'm not sure what symbol would go here.  The sign for [[Tian]]?

After the removal of the redundant Christian and Jainist symbols and the different Neopagan branches, we're left with three extra slots.  If we can find a symbol for Chinese folk religion, that'd be a good one to include.  Again, though, I can't find anything representative.  I'd also like to suggest the inclusion of [[Zoroastrianism]]'s [[Faravahar]], because of that religion's influence or possible influence on other world religions.  The [[Tengriism|Tengriist]] crescent is what comes to my mind to fill the other slot, but I'm open to other suggestions.

If no one has anything else to say and isn't going to revert me, I'll compile this thing in MS Paint if I don't forget and play Minecraft instead:
*First row: Ayyavazhi lotus, Baha'i star, Buddhist wheel, Christian cross (the plain one)
*Second row: Chinese folk religion symbol of some sort, Gnostic Solar cross, Hindu Om, Islamic name &quot;Allah&quot;
*Third row: Jainist hand, Jewish Magen David, Shinto Torii, Sikh Khanda
*Fourth row: Taoist Taijitu, Tengriist Crescent, Wiccan pentagram, Zoroastrian Faravahar

Again, though, would like other people's input. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 02:18, 20 September 2012 (UTC)

:{{Talkquote|The Christian cross on the bottom isn't as archetypal as the first one, so the frilly one seems the obvious one to remove to me.|Ian.thomson}}'''Agreed, however''' I suggest replacing the [[Equal-Armed Cross]] with [[:File:Christian cross.svg]].{{Talkquote|I'm inclined to go with the hand instead of the swastika, not simply because of the misuse of that symbol, but because the &quot;backwards&quot; swastika is used by Hindus and Buddhists as well.|Ian.thomson}}'''Agreed.''' It's a shame we can't use the main emblem, though.{{Talkquote|...alphabetic order by the names of the religions will save us the headache of figuring out which religion has the most adherents, as well as arguments with the inevitable POV-pushers who are upset that their religion doesn't have more followers or that some religion they don't like has too many.|Ian.thomson}}Members of high population faiths could still get upset their religions don't come first. Still, I '''agree''' this is the most reasonable method available.{{Talkquote|While the Pentagram does not represent all of Neopaganism, isn't it at least featured as a secondary or tertiary symbol in the majority of Neopagan religions? And if not, although Wicca isn't necessarily the oldest Neopagan movement, isn't it a forerunner and influence for many other movements?|Ian.thomson}}Yes and yes.{{Talkquote|Star and Crescent may not be the best symbol for Islam - The Arabic name Allah would probably be better, that's what the sidebar for Islam articles uses.|Ian.thomson}}The [[Star and crescent]] is more recognizable in anglophone and international settings (both of relevance here) as a symbol of Islam.{{Talkquote|Chinese folk religion not represented - While I'd welcome its presence, I'm not sure what symbol would go here. The sign for Tian?|Ian.thomson}}A [[Tian]] character may be the best. Should we ask for input from a related project, perhaps [[Wikipedia:WikiProject China|WikiProject China]]?&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 04:20, 20 September 2012 (UTC)

::If I end up having to make the pic, I'll see if I can fit the whole symbol used in the Jainism template in there.  I will/would use the Christian cross file you linked to, and hope that anyone who takes more initiative than me does so as well.  I think I will hold off until I or someone who hasn't recently fallen off the Minecraft wagon asks Wikiproject China what they think or we find an RS saying &quot;this is a common symbol for Shenism.&quot;  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 04:43, 20 September 2012 (UTC)

[[File:ReligijneSymbole.svg|250px|thumb|Religion symbols, &lt;br /&gt;row 1: [[Christianity]], [[Judaism]], [[Hinduism]], [[Baha'i Faith]]&lt;br /&gt;row 2: [[Islam]], [[Gnosticism]], [[Taoism]], [[Shinto]]&lt;br /&gt;row 3: [[Buddhism]], [[Sikhism]], [[Jainism]], Jainism, &lt;br /&gt;row 4: [[Ayyavazhi]], [[Wicca]], Christian, [[Slavic neopaganism]]]]
{{Outdent}}You'll want to use the SVG version of this file as it is vectorized and uses the Latin Cross [[File:Christian cross.svg|20px]] instead of the Greek Cross [[File:Greek cross.svg|20px]]. [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 19:16, 21 September 2012 (UTC)

:I see the improvement in the cross, but it still has the Wicca/Neopaganism symbol in the bottom row, that we discussed above and that was the reason for removing it from the page. If you could replace that symbol according to the discussion above, that would be very helpful. There are also several other requested improvements, that you can see above. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 19:49, 21 September 2012 (UTC)

::&lt;s&gt;There actually wasn't improvement. The new image is simply an alternate that was already present in the article. We still ''need'' a new image.&lt;/s&gt; &lt;ins&gt; &lt;---(Contributed via my phone. Ignore that.)&lt;/ins&gt; I would pull the SVGs and make it myself, but I'm in the middle of some computer maintenance that will last for the next few days.&lt;br/&gt;If no one has made it by Mon or Tues, I'll make it.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 21:56, 21 September 2012 (UTC)

{{Outdent}}I've asked WP:China for help finding a symbol for Shenism. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 13:22, 24 September 2012 (UTC)
:::As many symbols are shared between Confucianism, Taoism, Shenism...  there is the pentagram representing the five elements, the trigrams (such as on a geomancy compass)... but those have also filtered into Japanese and Korean culture and used natively. -- [[Special:Contributions/76.65.131.248|76.65.131.248]] ([[User talk:76.65.131.248|talk]]) 03:52, 25 September 2012 (UTC)

:Pass a Method suggested on my talk page that [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:DruidismSymbol.PNG this Druid symbol] might be used to fill the gap, and it'd work in the absence of other options.  IIRC, that symbol was associated with (Neo-)Druidry before the 20th century Neopagan movement got underway, which skirts the &quot;influenced by Wicca&quot; issue for the [[Nine Billion Names of God|Nine Billion &lt;s&gt;Names of God&lt;/s&gt; ''Neopagan symbols''.
:What about religious symbols for some of the various African, American, or Australian religions?  [[Vodoun]] is arguably a world religion.  Traditional [[Serer religion]] also uses the pentagram as a religious symbol, should we mention that as well?  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 19:19, 24 September 2012 (UTC)
:: I prefer the Druid symbol. It is used on this notable website [http://www.religioustolerance.org/var_rel.htm] as the last symbol. Druidism is also represented on religious charts of multiple countries. I would avoid mentioning Serer. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 19:34, 24 September 2012 (UTC)
:::Serer religion might be undue weight, but I think we should have something from a traditional African religion.
:::I'm thinking that we may need to go with a some other format besides 4x4, depending on what African symbols we can come up with, and what WP:China finds, if anything. The world religions represented so far tend to be Western or Eastern. Going for something besides 4x4 would also make it easier to use the full size Jainism symbol by having it take up two slots.
:::If we end up with a 5x5 (which would be the most we could do without getting things too crowded), would anyone be opposed to including [[Thelema]]'s and [[Raëlism]]'s hexagrams? They're distinct from each other and the Jewish Magen David. There's also [[:File:Scientology_Symbol_Logo.png|Scientology's ARC and KRC triangles]] and the [[Church of Satan]]'s Goat of Mendes pentagram. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 19:47, 24 September 2012 (UTC)

::::Perhaps 3, 4, 4, &amp; 3 would work.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 23:50, 24 September 2012 (UTC)

::::We're having enough trouble filling a 4x4 grid. Why would we try for 5x5?&lt;br/&gt;I disagree with adding Thelema, Raëlism, Scientology, et cetera. I think we should stay with broad religious movements (e.g. Christianity, Buddhism, Hinduism, Paganism) and those with notable populations. There are many smaller movements that could be added, but even a 5x5 grid wouldn't accommodate all of them. If we cherry pick a few, we'll have a [[WP:DUE|due weight]] problem. What makes ''X'' movements with populations of +100K more notable than any other grouping of movements at said population?&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 00:44, 25 September 2012 (UTC)

:If you're looking for a NorthAmericanNative symbol, why not use the Thunderbird? -- [[Special:Contributions/76.65.131.248|76.65.131.248]] ([[User talk:76.65.131.248|talk]]) 03:44, 25 September 2012 (UTC)

:: The problem with African and other ethnic religions is that they tend to be very syncretic. This might provoke doubts about whether it is truly a seperate religion or a denomination. Such doubts already exist among religions such as Druze etc. This could become a slippery slope with people arguing that i.e. Mormonism should be treated as a seperate religion. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 12:03, 25 September 2012 (UTC)

[[File:Religious symbols-4x4.svg|250px|thumb|Symbols from the twelve World religious movements we've agreed on thus far, in alphabetical order, set on a 4x4 grid.&lt;br/&gt;[[Christianity]], [[Bahá'í Faith]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Buddhism]], [[Daoism]] (Taoism), [[Hinduism]], [[Islam]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Kami-no-michi]] (Shinto), [[Jainism]], [[Judaism]], [[Paganism]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Shenism]] (Chinese Folk Tradition), [[Sikhism]]]]

:::::As promised, here's a new grid based on the discussion thus far. Sorry it took me so long. ...also surprised no one else jumped in after [[User:Richard-of-Earth]].&lt;br/&gt;I removed the duplicates, restored Paganism as a single entry (under an encircled pentagram), added an entry for Chinese Folk Tradition, and ordered everything by name. I took some liberties too. I removed Gnosticism; I felt balance more important than a dead religion that only influences some modern traditions. I called CFT by its shorter lable because it's ''shorter'', translating into only two Chinese characters (a single Tian doesn't look suitable).&lt;br/&gt;Thoughts?&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 10:13, 9 October 2012 (UTC)



{{Outdent}}I almost forget... If we come up with 1 or 2 more solid entries, we can bump it back up to 3x4x4x3. And, anyone with Chinese calligraphy experience should go over my work. As an artist I may be, a Chinese calligrapher I am not.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 10:22, 9 October 2012 (UTC)

: Thanks Sowlos, good work [[User:A ntv|A ntv]] ([[User talk:A ntv|talk]]) 10:26, 9 October 2012 (UTC)

::I was going to add it right now, but I noticed that Shenism and Sikhism are switched.  Otherwise, good work. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 14:46, 9 October 2012 (UTC)

:::Thank you and fixed. I also increased the element size by a bit.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 19:17, 11 October 2012 (UTC)

::::Cool, added right now. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 20:42, 11 October 2012 (UTC)

:::::Thanks! Good work! --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 18:29, 12 October 2012 (UTC)

::::: I have altered the &quot;pagan&quot; dscription because pagan is more of a blanket umbrella term and religious classification than a religion. Also, I recommend filling the gaps whilst adding [http://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=File:Tribann.svg&amp;page=1 Druid] [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Faravahar.svg Zoroastrianism] and [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Flaming_Chalice.png Unitarian Universalism] then you choose a fourth from [[Religious symbolism|here]]. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 04:45, 13 October 2012 (UTC)

:::::: I can agree to add other symbols, but I suggest to avoid symbols without a clear and historical foundation and use. So it is perfectly ok to add the symbols of Zoroastrianism, Unitarian Universalism, Cao Dai, Mormonism, while I object to the symbol of Druid or other minors symbols.--[[User:A ntv|A ntv]] ([[User talk:A ntv|talk]]) 08:22, 13 October 2012 (UTC)

:::::::I'm not sure what you mean by 'clear historical foundation', but I've considered adherence in the millions, presence in many nations around the world, and broad cultural significance as the criteria for what few religions get highlighted. Also, I think sects should be avoided. This is a summary at a glance, not a comprehensive list.&lt;br/&gt;To what {{User|Pass a Method}} said, the consensus was that Paganism deserved mention, but not specifically any encompassed movement. It would lend them undue weight. This is also why, I'm reverting the pentagram label from 'Wicca' back to 'Paganism'. Please remember 'Wicca' is just as much an umbrella-term as 'Paganism'. I have no problem with a 'Paganism/Wicca' label if everyone thinks that's warranted. &lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 12:02, 13 October 2012 (UTC)
::::::::The arrangement of symbols isn't good. The tiny number of followers of the Baha'i Faith are given the most prominence and placed in the top row? I guess placing Islam in the top row besides Christianity will make the arrangement better. [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 14:23, 13 October 2012 (UTC)
{{od}}
We went over this earlier: the two arrangements that made the most sense were alphabetical order and by number of adherents, but alphabetical order is the easier of the two.  Bahai is not given &quot;more prominence&quot; any more than B is a more prominent letter than I. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 15:51, 13 October 2012 (UTC)

:: @Sowlos, i disagree with your interpretation of &quot;due weight&quot;. In most of human history paganism was the most widely practised form of religion. It is only in the past few centuries/past millenia that non-pagan faiths have gained a plurality in followers. Therefore, it is due weight to mention the two most practised pagan religions, Wicca and Druidry.[[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 19:40, 13 October 2012 (UTC)

:::#The grid is not a list of historical and once-major religions. It only represents major ''contemporary'' religions - as it always has. If this was an article on religious history or if we were talking about an image for the history section in this article, I'd be more inclined to agree.
:::#Almost all Pagan denominations are smaller in terms of population, are present in fewer countries, '''and''' are less culturally significant in their primary country than any other religion on that grid. Putting them together implies they're on equal footing, which gives them undue weight. Wicca may be the only Pagan group that can claim otherwise.
:::To be perfectly clear, I ''am'' Pagan. I would love to see several Pagan religions represented on that grid. Previously seeing so many Pagan symbols at the top of Wikipedia's main religion article definitely made me feel good, but this is not about my preferences (nor should it be about yours). Wikipedia articles need to be unbiased, with an international perspective.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 04:52, 14 October 2012 (UTC)
To Ian.thomson: No! It's clearly not in alphabetical order when Christianity is preceding Baha'i Faith and Buddhism. [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 14:02, 15 October 2012 (UTC)
:And if you actually read the thread, and continue reading below, you'll see that that was an accident that is trying to be fixed. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 14:08, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

=== Arbitrary break 0 ===
{{User|Pass a Method}} just changed the naming for some the religions. This annoyed me a bit;  it's been clearly stated above that the order is '''alphabetic'''. ...but I realized none of us know the English alphabet, lol. Since there were already a few order errors, I didn't undo his edit. I'll be able to fix it in a few hours, but in the mean time, I thought I'd bring this here. Are people happy with the naming I used? I was trying to err on the side of endonyms.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 11:39, 14 October 2012 (UTC)

:While endonyms would be nice, I'm kinda leaning towards using whatever the default titles for the articles on those religions (except for Shenism due to spacing issues, which isn't absolutely an endonym either) on the same grounds that we're using the star and crescent for Islam instead of the Arabic word Allah: it's more likely the readership will recognize it.  That said, I didn't mind the other arrangement, either.  [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 12:29, 14 October 2012 (UTC)

::{{Tq|...on the same grounds that we're using the star and crescent for Islam instead of the Arabic word Allah: it's more likely the readership will recognize it.}} Good point.&lt;br/&gt;My plan is to switch from 'Shenism', to 'Chinese Folk Tradition', in the event we get an alternative symbol from [[WP:China]].&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 15:53, 14 October 2012 (UTC)

:I discovered why the order was screwy. Inkscape (what I used for this) likes to reorder objects in some cases when auto-aligning in rows &amp; columns.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 09:34, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

=== Response at [[WT:CHINA]] ===
The [[Shou character]], [[Double Happiness (calligraphy)|Double Happiness]], and upside-down [[Fu character]] characters have been recommended, with the Shou character actually being used in a similar manner to crosses in Christian churches. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 19:55, 13 October 2012 (UTC)

:That is fantastic. I responded over there.&lt;br/&gt;Normally that sort of rfc engenders replies on the source thread, but I'll go to them. I'm adversed to making this type of decision without broad input.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 06:01, 14 October 2012 (UTC)

=== So... New design? ===

Based on input, new discussion, and some concerns Sowlos had, how about this format?

*[[Bahá'í Faith]], [[Buddhism]], [[Christianity]], [[Chinese folk religion]],
*[[Hinduism]], [[Islam]], [[Jainism]], [[Judaism]],
*[[Paganism (contemporary)]], [[Shinto]], [[Sikhism]], [[Taoism]]

Alternately:

*[[Bahá'í Faith]], [[Buddhism]], [[Christianity]],
*[[Chinese folk religion]], [[Hinduism]], [[Islam]],
*[[Jainism]], [[Judaism]], [[Paganism (contemporary)]],
*[[Shinto]], [[Sikhism]], [[Taoism]]

The second would get in the way less, but could also blend in with the &quot;Religions by country&quot; sidebar.
[[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 20:52, 14 October 2012 (UTC)

: I think we should keep the original design, but alphabetic:

:*Baha'i, Buddhism
:*Christianity, Chinese folk relgiion, Hinduism, Islam
:*Jainism, Judaism, Paganism/Wicca, Shinto
:*Sikhism, Taoism
:Like that. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 06:17, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

::Okay. I'll keep it in the cross layout for now, however I still think it needs some more work.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 09:26, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

:::Cross design is also fine.  Will we use the [[Shou character]] for Chinese folk religion, as that one actually has been used almost as an identifying symbol? [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 13:51, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

::::As it stands, yes. The only input we got on [[WP:China]] gave that as choice number one. I assume that means everyone else there agrees - or doesn't care. That still counts as consensus.  I should have time to draw it later today or tomorrow.&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 14:17, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

===Mention Wicca?===
Sowlos, what do you think about usig a slash after paganism as in &quot;Paganism/Wicca&quot;? [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 12:05, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

:As I said, I'll agree if that's what most others here vote for.&lt;br/&gt;It's the only Pagan group large enough to even consider. It comprises about half of all self identified Pagans in the US. I don't have number for the rest of the world but that may bring them in at over one million (my minimum requirement). However, I'm skeptical about giving it special mention. We aren't doing the same for sects of other religions and Wicca ''can'' be defined as such (especially if we list Paganism as a religion whilst Wicca is one of its components).&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 14:37, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

=== Symbol for Islam ===

{{Talkquote|Star and Crescent may not be the best symbol for Islam - The Arabic name Allah would probably be better, that's what the sidebar for Islam articles uses.|Ian.thomson}}
The star and crescent sign isn't considered sacred in Islam (on the contrary, it's sacred in Tengriism and some ancient Mesopotamian polytheistic religions) so it's not suitable, I think. Yes, the name Allah in Arabic orthography is better to be used here and it's used in sidebars for Islam in some other Wikipedia articles, too. Thanks, [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 15:15, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

:Doesn't Islam technically [[Symbols of Islam#Symbols of Islam|have no holy symbol]]?&lt;br/&gt;—&lt;small&gt;[[User:Sowlos|Sowlos]] ([[User talk:Sowlos|talk]])&lt;/small&gt; 15:53, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

: I prefer the star and crescent because firstly its more recognisable. Secondly, the crescent was the symbol of some caliphate coins, Islamic stapmps and the flag of some caliphates.  It was also the symbol on the flag of the first Saudi state, plus it is used on the domes/minarets of several notable mosques, including [[Masjid al-Haram]]. Furthermore, the moon holds a significant place in Islam due to the splitting of the moon, one of the main miracles of Muhammad. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 21:57, 15 October 2012 (UTC) [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 16:24, 15 October 2012 (UTC)
::Pass a Method: its use started only during the [[Ottoman flag|last]] caliphate as a state symbol, probably because of influence from other non-Islamic religions because it's known that early Muslims never used it. And, even the mosques that have the crescent mostly do not have the five-pointed star. Nevertheless, the usage of the star and crescent as an Islamic symbol is rejected by many scholars. The Arabic name &quot;Allah&quot; is a non-controversial symbol for Islam. [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 20:14, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

::Sowlos: that's correct, Islam doesn't have holy symbols. Early Islamic coins, stamps and flags (during the time of Muhammad and during the Rashidun Caliphate, the Umayyad Caliphate and the Abbasid Caliphate) didn't have geometric symbols; the star and crescent symbol was unknown to Muslims back then, even present-day Muslims don't consider this symbol holy. Early Islamic coins and stamps were covered with Arabic writings instead. [[User:Khestwol|Khestwol]] ([[User talk:Khestwol|talk]]) 19:16, 15 October 2012 (UTC)

== Vajrayana ==

''Buddhism, sometimes considered a form of Mahayana, was developed in [[Tibet]] and is still most prominent there and in surrounding regions.''
The word 'developed' is rather misleading here. In the terms of taking something and working with it, yes Vajrayana was developed in Tibet. But the primary source (origins) of Vajrayana is India, with a lot of development centred at [[Nalanda University]]. See [[Vajrayana]] for more details. I have edited the article here accordingly. ([[User:20040302|20040302]] ([[User talk:20040302|talk]]) 08:56, 22 October 2012 (UTC))
:I've reversed the new wording because 1) is not enough syntetic and 2) it is unsourced. Please propone in Talk Page a possible (more short) new language, keeping in mind that this is only a list of still-alive religions, not a summary of their history. [[User:A ntv|A ntv]] ([[User talk:A ntv|talk]]) 09:30, 22 October 2012 (UTC)

::What does 'syntetic' mean, and likewise what does 'propone' mean? If you read the article  [[Vajrayana]] which has plenty of sources, it is quite clear that the currently unsourced content is a total fabrication. WP does not require me to push every edit through the talk page. However, I will provide on-page sources, as I agree that well-sourced material is better suited. ([[User:20040302|20040302]] ([[User talk:20040302|talk]]))

==Parody religions ==
I disagree with 'Parody religions' being placed under 'Secularism and irreligion', because it diminishes the importance and worth of the latter. Also, a Parody religion is by definition a form of ''belief'' (even if it's not taken seriously by its disciples) whereas Secularism and irreligion are concerned with (seriously-held) ''unbelief'' or ''non-belief''. In my view, Parody religion is a form of criticism - it mocks religion - and therefore belongs under the Criticism section or alternatively a section on its own. [[User:Vacarme|Vacarme]] ([[User talk:Vacarme|talk]]) 07:14, 28 October 2012 (UTC)
: I agree with Sowlos that 'Parody religions' shell be placed under 'Secularism and irreligion'. That is because this article is about Religion, and even if it is right to mention different criticism, their space shall be secondary here. IMHO we could place both the subsections 'Secularism and irreligion' and 'Parody religions' under &quot;Related forms of thought&quot;. [[User:A ntv|A ntv]] ([[User talk:A ntv|talk]]) 08:40, 28 October 2012 (UTC)
::I see the parody religions as being a part of irreligion. They really aren't a criticism of religion, in any specific way. The main thing that the [[Flying Spaghetti Monster]] criticizes is the teaching of creationism, rather than religion ''per se''. I guess we could have some philosophical discussions about whether the &quot;unbelief&quot; of secularism and irreligion is a &quot;belief&quot; in a position, or not, but I don't think that really affects how we classify parodies. However, I'd rather not move them under &quot;Related forms of thought&quot;, because they are, arguably, ''un''related forms of thought. Anyway, bottom line, I'd keep the parody section as a subsection of &quot;Secularism and irreligion&quot;. --[[User:Tryptofish|Tryptofish]] ([[User talk:Tryptofish|talk]]) 19:15, 28 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>brrfkhlh6aospt0vr3utvackllytk1p</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
