<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Earth religion</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4906930</id>
    <revision>
      <id>306145288</id>
      <parentid>306144900</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-08-05T04:08:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Shanoman</username>
        <id>1209896</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Please keep: don't delete/merge! */ OK, just had to say something more!</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3583">{{WikiProject Neopaganism|class=Stub|importance=High}}

== Religion vs. spirituality ==

The term I hear much more often than &quot;Earth religion&quot; is &quot;Earth-based spirituality&quot;, especially when talking about Neopagan traditions. Is there any disagreement to moving this article to reflect the more common usage? [[User:Romarin|''rom'']][[User:Romarin/Esperanza|&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;'''''a'''''&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:Romarin|''rin'']] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Romarin|[''talk'' ]]]&lt;/small&gt; 01:11, 12 July 2006 (UTC)

Moving it to &quot;New Age&quot; doesn't make as much sense to me as moving it into &quot;Neopaganism&quot; which is more specifically encompassing of Nature-centered spirituality.  In principle, this article could be retitled and reordered to be a page on &quot;religion and nature&quot; in a more general sense, which would include a listing of belief systems which are more Nature-centered or oriented.  Addressing religious beliefs concerning nature has become a more well-known topic particularly with the popularity of 'being green' in the United States.  As it stands now, this article is not of much use.  [[Special:Contributions/12.206.20.30|12.206.20.30]] ([[User talk:12.206.20.30|talk]]) 20:37, 11 March 2008 (UTC)


New age and paganism are NOT the same.. Paganism would be OLD age in that context.
What is more.. NEO-paganism does not exist, it's a slag therm invented by other beliefsystems to ridiculize nature based religions. please don't use it !  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/212.178.157.228|212.178.157.228]] ([[User talk:212.178.157.228|talk]]) 07:37, 8 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Please keep: don't delete/merge! ==

Although I'm sure it could be expanded a bit and vastly improved in countless other ways, I really don't see anything at all wrong with just leaving it more or less a &quot;stub&quot; to help flesh out the term &quot;Earth religion&quot;.  Maybe it could be retitled &quot;Earth religion and spirituality&quot;, but I think simply substituting it with &quot;Earth Spirituality&quot; is over-simplistic and would leave out some of the meaning. Although modern paganism may be seen at least to some extent as an outgrowth of the Theosophy/New Age movement and often overlaps with it, I think most people see them as mostly or entirely distinct from each other, thus they each deserve their own separate articles (man, I can remember back in 2005, there were TONS of articles about pagan/magical subjects on Wikipedia; massive deletion and/or merging has starkly curtailed it since then).  Some pagan reconstructionist purists ridicule wicca for being mostly modern and artificial (either a new mixture of lots of preexisting beliefs or else just completely made-up), and some of those individuals (perhaps also from [[Thelema]], [[Chaos magic]]*, et. al.) might attack earth-and-nature friendly religion just in order to advance their own personal idiosyncratic agenda (of unfettered egoism, will-to-power, fascism, or whatever).  Nevertheless, in a certain way of thinking, ALL instances of paganism today are neopagan (except for those truly practicing family traditions); even the reconstructionists (because if the paleo-pagan faith had never completely died out, there would be no need to reconstruct it!).  [[User:Shanoman|Shanoman]] ([[User talk:Shanoman|talk]]) 00:39, 5 August 2009 (UTC)

&lt;small&gt;* - I have nothing against those who practice these---or even satanism---provided they are NOT totalitarian, authoritarian, misanthropic, or force-initiating in ANY major way!&lt;/small&gt;</text>
      <sha1>949yq4b5xvrokoxrasn89w0r0676dhu</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
