<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ramadan</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1082595</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518994277</id>
      <parentid>514354266</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-21T09:30:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tommy symbol</username>
        <id>12514466</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Original research</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="79088">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Islam|class=Start|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Holidays|class=Start}} 
}}
{{onlinesource|year=2004|section=October 2004
| title=Ramadan: Muslims annual month of fasting, prayer begins this week
| date=9 October 2004
| org=Virgin Islands Daily News
| url=http://www.virginislandsdailynews.com/index.pl/article_features?id=7607792}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-10-15|oldid1=6790900|date2=2005-10-04|oldid2=24760000|date3=2006-09-23|oldid3=77328418|date4=2007-09-12|oldid4=157468809|date5=2007-09-13|oldid5=157312006|date6=2008-08-31|oldid6=235313153|date7=2008-09-01|oldid7=235684083|date8=2009-08-21|oldid8=309249405|date9=2009-08-22|oldid9=309137355|date10=2010-08-10|oldid10=378124116|date11=2010-08-11|oldid11=378373018|date12=2011-08-01|oldid12=442545373|date13=2012-07-20|oldid13=503230618}}
{{Backwardscopy
|author = Miller, F. P., Vandome, A. F., &amp; McBrewster, J.
|year = 2009
|title = Eid ul-Fitr: Eid ul-Fitr, Hari Raya Aidilfitri, Islam in China, Islamic calendar, Muslim holidays, Iftar, Eid al-Adha, Ramadan, Takbir, Zakat, Chaand Raat, Salwar kameez, Zakat al-fitr
|org = Alphascript Publishing
|comments = {{OCLC|468809420}}, ISBN 9786130016548.
|bot = LivingBot
}}
{{Archivebox|[[/Archive 1]]}}

== Duplicated section ==

The &quot;Prayer and reading of the Qur'an&quot; section shows up twice, this is a minor issue, but I don't know how to fix it.  Also there is a reference to Muhammad that says:  &quot;...Quran was sent down to Muhammad (peace be upon him)&quot; and I wonder if the &quot;(peace be upon him)&quot; belongs in the context of a wikipedia article?  Just minor things.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Codeles|Codeles]] ([[User talk:Codeles|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Codeles|contribs]]) 13:21, 4 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== When? ==

thia is  not ot much of a probelmThis page doesn't mention when Ramadan is, or where one can look to find out.
:Try reading the first line of the article.  It clearly tells you that Ramadan takes place in the month of Ramadan and links you to an article about that month, i.e [[Ramadan (calendar month)]], which explains in detail all you could ever want to know. [[Special:Contributions/86.144.147.182|86.144.147.182]] ([[User talk:86.144.147.182|talk]]) 23:22, 10 August 2008 (UTC)
::That's clear once it's explained, but I must admit that when I read the article I wondered how I could find out the dates for a given year. Could perhaps an explanation be added {e.g. &quot;Ramadan is an Islamic religious observance that takes place during the ninth month of the Islamic calendar... In the western calendar, the dates [with link to relevant part of the article on the Isalmic calendar] of Ramadan vary, moving forward about 10 days each year...&quot; (or something like that)}? Just a thought. [[User:Ondewelle|Ondewelle]] ([[User talk:Ondewelle|talk]]) 22:42, 19 July 2009 (UTC)
:::Thanks to ecjmartin for the addition. :-) [[User:Ondewelle|Ondewelle]] ([[User talk:Ondewelle|talk]]) 19:16, 20 July 2009 (UTC)
::::You're welcome!  Glad to help!! - [[User:Ecjmartin|Ecjmartin]] ([[User talk:Ecjmartin|talk]]) 19:46, 20 July 2009 (UTC)

Another query:

In the article, it mentions the prophet Muhammed and after each use there is the phrase &quot;Peace be upon him (PBUH)&quot;.   

FROM THE WIKI ARTICLE: Peace be upon him:

&quot;Peace be upon him is a phrase that Muslims often say after saying (or hearing) the name of a prophet of Islam...&quot;

Surely this is not needed in an encyclopedic article as the author of the encylcopedia is not deemed to be Islamic.  I suggest the deletion of the PBUH after each mention of the prophets' name.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.147.235.92|86.147.235.92]] ([[User talk:86.147.235.92|talk]]) 12:21, 1 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Just becase one is not a Muslim doesnt give them the right to be insulting. The PBUH is a blessing. If Muslims say it and because they will be the ones that read this most of all I think this should stay. Please. The only way muslims will respect you and your beliefs is if you respect them and their beliefs. You've already seen the results of ignoring this. [[User:Zero2001|Zero]] ([[User talk:Zero2001|talk]]) 17:24, 1 September 2008 (UTC)

So what about respecting the fact that a lot of people do not regard Muhamad as a prophet ? Respect has to be two ways, and Wikipedia should remain neutral ground, don't you think ? --[[User:Donvinzk|Donvinzk]] ([[User talk:Donvinzk|talk]]) 18:26, 1 September 2008 (UTC)

Besides we also say ''Alay-he Salam'' (Sorry if its written wrong. Its hard to write Arabic in English) after uttering the names of Hazrat Isa (Jesus), Musa (Moses), Ibrahim (Abraham) and all the other Prophets that came before. It means roughly the same thing I think. A Blessing. If we can show our respect for them then you should show respect for ours. [[User:Zero2001|Zero]] ([[User talk:Zero2001|talk]]) 17:29, 1 September 2008 (UTC)
:[[Wikipedia:MOSISLAM]] [Manual of Style (Islam-related articles)] explains the standards for Wikipedia dealing with Islamic patterns of blessing persons &amp; cetera... '''&lt;font color=#BA55D3&gt;[[User:Emilyzilch|ناهد/(Nåhed)]]''' &lt;sub&gt;''[[User_Talk:Emilyzilch|speak!]]''&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 21:21, 1 September 2008 (UTC)

Very well then. I was just suggesting this. Your decision. If the Holy Prophet could endure the other Quraish twisting his name then I can endure this. Just be aware that others might not take this so kindly. Even though I urge them to ignore this. [[User:Zero2001|Zero]] ([[User talk:Zero2001|talk]]) 05:03, 2 September 2008 (UTC)

Zero, what you are asking for is absurd. I'm a Muslim and I have to ask you, if someone wrote a perfect sirah of the Prophet(saw) but didn't use honorifics in their book, would you then tell people to not read it? If you did, I would say you are in the wrong. In the same way Holy Prophet(saw) could endure abuse, the &quot;others&quot; you mention should learn to cool themselves, especially on such petty grounds such as this. WWHPD.[[Special:Contributions/76.27.195.4|76.27.195.4]] ([[User talk:76.27.195.4|talk]]) 01:25, 2 September 2011 (UTC)

* Ramadan startes when people can see the cresent moon...once it has been seen, the priests and shieks say when it is time to fast then u begin fasting...it ends after 30 days  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|.140.46.38|72.140.46.38]] ([[User talk:72.140.46.38|talk]]) 23:31, 2 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Mess ==

Parts of this article is a mess. Someone with more knowledge of Ramadan than me should take a look. For instance, you can find sentences like this:
''Before the Fasts of Holy Ramadan were made obligatory by Allah Almighty, Holy Prophet PBUH used to fast on 10th of Moharram, as on this Date Pharaoh drowned in the Sea,but after the revelation from Allah Almighty, Holy Prophet PBUH left the Fast of 10th Muharram and started Fasting during the Month of Ramadan and asked his followers to observe fast during the Holy Month.
''
I have deleted a big chunk of text copied directly from a copyrighted site, and removed som PBUH's. [[User:Ramskjell|Ramskjell]] ([[User talk:Ramskjell|talk]]) 12:29, 1 September 2008 (UTC)

GOOD EDITS. I read this article and found it informative and (as and atheist) not proselytizing. However, there are studies that show weight gain during Ramadan in some communities (Maghreb). I will try to find this interesting item and any others like it, to include. [[Special:Contributions/98.218.149.74|98.218.149.74]] ([[User talk:98.218.149.74|talk]]) 15:06, 1 September 2008 (UTC)

Thank you for removing all those 'PBUH's.  With all due respect to the Muslim writers, if I write about Jesus I don't think the reader wants to see a big 'PRAISE JESUS!' every time I mention his name.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.102.24.106|67.102.24.106]] ([[User talk:67.102.24.106|talk]]) 23:46, 2 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

This article is a mess - agree - and needs to be cleaned up!--[[User:Cladding|Cladding]] ([[User talk:Cladding|talk]]) 09:11, 20 September 2008 (UTC)

''However, there are studies that show weight gain during Ramadan in some communities (Maghreb). I will try to find this interesting item and any others like it, to include.''
Well, has there any one told you that Ramadan was made for entering a modeling pagent? look, the purpose of Ramadan is the equality between rich and poor people, patience, feeling what others feel, solidarity and many other things. When you end your fast it's up to you whether you eat healthy food or junk food.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/41.208.82.97|41.208.82.97]] ([[User talk:41.208.82.97|talk]]) 17:30, 2 October 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== The Peace of Ramadan ==

It is told that in the Month of Ramadan. Muslims are forbidden from fighting. Muslims Armies that were on march used to make camp and move not one step further untill Ramadan was over. The only exception to this rule is when muslims are attacked during this month. Since they are devoted to peace during this month and attacking them causes disruption of that peace, The Muslims are commanded to only fight in case someone attacks them in this holy month. I cant quite remember the verse No. that says this. Can any body else do so. If the verse is found. Please add this information to the Article. For I remember it stated that the Muslims are commanded that if they are attacked during this month they must retaliate with full force to discourage further attempts. However, some of the terrorist muslims have forgotten this and so they continue fighting during this holy month. This is a grave sin. Please. Find the verse. Add this info. Everyone must be warned. The Muslims so that they may stop and The Non Muslims so that they may respect our way of life and not attack us during this holy month, the results could be devastating. This Command of Peace is the Reason Pakistani Government is offering Cease Fire to the Militants in Swat. [[User:Zero2001|Zero]] ([[User talk:Zero2001|talk]]) 17:24, 1 September 2008 (UTC)

== Pagan Origin of Ramadan ==

I wonder if its important to note the pagan origin of Ramadan, which is a pre-Islamic festival. I believe it mentions this in the Koran, that Ramadan was an ancient time of peace - also many Islamic scholars allude to the pagan origin. I think if we mention the pagan origin of Christmas or Easter, I think by rights it necessary. We need to fair and equal to all religions, as they are all of the same value - and as an athiest I see it important to show that all religions aren't God-inspired, but socio-politically and culturally inspired, and are formedthrough syncretism. [[User:Madkafir]]  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.2.175.117|82.2.175.117]] ([[User talk:82.2.175.117|talk]]) 13:35, 2 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:: I have never heard of there being a pagan origin for &quot;Ramadan&quot;.  Ramadan is the name of the month and existed before Islam, as opposed to Christmas and Easter which are *holidays* derived from pagan festivals.  Fasting during Ramadan was mandated by Muhammad.  [[User:Inf fg|Inf fg]] ([[User talk:Inf fg|talk]]) 14:50, 5 September 2008 (UTC)

== Forced on Muslims by criminal law ==

This article portrays well the self-improvement ideas of Ramadan.  However, it fails to state that observance is forced, and that in many countries, anyone who does not obey (for example, if you drink water during the day) may be severely beaten and/or imprisoned by police.  Certainly no one would argue with its 'spirituality' if it were solely a voluntary personal effort.  Unfortunately, it is not.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.102.24.106|67.102.24.106]] ([[User talk:67.102.24.106|talk]]) 23:43, 2 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
Yes sadly it happens. Ramadan is the best time to get in touch with God. To do this one must accept it from the bottom of his/her heart not having it forced onto them. And yet the extremists still do this and other cases similar to this. My God punish them!  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.67.253.203|24.67.253.203]] ([[User talk:24.67.253.203|talk]]) 21:28, 3 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Actually, no body would be beaten nor imprisoned by government in an Islamic country if he/she committed the crime of eating and/or drinking during a Ramadan day unless such a thing happened in public. It's all about demonstrating respect to God's orders, the sacred month and other Muslims feelings as they would be fasting hoping to be rewarded by God who '''''ordered and obligated''''' them to fast on that day. Possibly, if someone would suddenly appear on road devouring a piece of donut in Ramadan before sunset just because of his/her inability to accept to fast from the bottom of his/her little tender heart, then a person like this may be punished and blamed by civilian individuals before the arrival of police. Ramadan is the best time to get in touch with God. As for this reason, it is the best opportunity to obey him and fast so that he may forgive us and eliminate all our evil sins. Otherwise, we would be causing the increase of his anger, as instead of getting more in touch with him we show disrespect and mockery with Islamic rituals in Islamic countries [[Special:Contributions/195.229.241.171|195.229.241.171]] ([[User talk:195.229.241.171|talk]]) 17:17, 30 September 2008 (UTC).
:My.... do you see any difference between encyclopedic neutral description and religious speech? &quot;It happens that the people who don't follow  the fasting rules may be severely beaten and/or imprisoned by police or lynched by the mob&quot;. End of story. The sort of your explanation about the heart and being in touch - it's only your opinion. Let's keep cold and neutral here. [[User:Merewyn|Merewyn]] ([[User talk:Merewyn|talk]]) 10:35, 8 August 2011 (UTC)
:: Merewyn, this is a talkpage, not an article. Please allow people to express themselves as they like.
:: As to the subject at hand. If this can be sourced, then we should have it in the article. Anybody here who can come up with something? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 10:40, 8 August 2011 (UTC)

:::Exactly! I agree with both of you. So changes have been made to ensure wikipedia's Ramadan page remains more accurately encyclopedic, as we all seem to concur here.[[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]]) 22:21, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

== Undue weight ==

I added an undue weight tag to the section concerning a single instance of controversy in a US school. If there is evidence for this being a widespread issue, then it can probably stay but if this is the only instance, it's a bit out of place given this is an article on a rather core issue of the Islamic faith. It would probably be better suited for an article on religious freedoms in the US or something of that sort [[User:Nil Einne|Nil Einne]] ([[User talk:Nil Einne|talk]]) 10:28, 15 September 2008 (UTC)

Ramadan Events-
Please note that the surah revealed on Layla-a-tul-Qadr is Al-Alaq, 96:1-19, where the Angel Gabriel asked the prophet to read in the name of Allah, and the prophet replied that he could not. Surah Qadr talks about this night, but was not revealed on this night.  Source:  quaranexplorer.com.  I am not sure about the other surah, but I think it's wrong.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Interestedparty5|Interestedparty5]] ([[User talk:Interestedparty5|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Interestedparty5|contribs]]) 19:17, 24 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Expansion request - Health impact ==

Two questions:
: ''Question one'' - What level of participation is expected and generally received of the ill and infirm in various parts of the Islamic world and what differences exist between Sunni &amp; Shi'ia practices when fasting? http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/09/27/AR2008092702592_pf.html implies that such differences exist, but doesn't go into depth.
: ''Question two'' - What impact if any does this have on the health of the population at large and hospital admission rates, be it negative or be it positive?
Just curious, [[User:MrZaius|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;'''MrZaius'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:MrZaius|'''&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;''']]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:05, 25 September 2008 (UTC) ''Questions updated, [[User:MrZaius|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;'''MrZaius'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:MrZaius|'''&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;''']]&lt;/sup&gt; 10:26, 28 September 2008 (UTC)''

::I don't know the answer to your first question but as for the second, if a person starts to have health problems they are to break the Fast. The purpose of the Fast is not to put people into hardship. [[User:Dumaka|Dumaka]] ([[User talk:Dumaka|talk]]) 16:36, 9 April 2009 (UTC)

:::1st Q: just the same. it only differs from country to country on the basis of religious culture and not by the islamic practices in itself (i.e: some societies find it O.K. while others don't)

:::2nd Q: the islamic world is a pretty shitty place that lives in the middle ages so don't expect any fancy statistics to be around.--[[User:Awanta|7amada&amp;#39;sback:)]] ([[User talk:Awanta|talk]]) 11:23, 13 September 2009 (UTC)

== Spelling Change Of This Page ==

Please move this page to a correctly spelled page. 

I, along with many Muslims who want Arabic words to be pronounced correctly, would greatly appreciate it if this page was moved to another page called Ramadaan. 
[[User:Soleado|Soleado]] ([[User talk:Soleado|talk]]) 21:26, 2 October 2008 (UTC)
:I disagree. The spelling without letter doubling is far more often used in English. The lead clearly writes the word in Arabic with a clear transliteration pointing out the classically long vowel. — [[User:Garzo|Gareth Hughes]] ([[User talk:Garzo|talk]]) 20:41, 5 October 2008 (UTC)
::Disagree, I've never ever seen anyone spell it &quot;Ramadaan&quot; before. '''&lt;font color=#BA55D3&gt;[[User:Emilyzilch|ناهد/(Nåhed)]]''' &lt;sub&gt;''[[User_Talk:Emilyzilch|speak!]]''&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 21:23, 5 October 2008 (UTC)
::I've seen it a little, but still disagree. See WP's guidelines on Arabic usage (esp. regarding primary transliterations) at [[WP:MOS-AR]]. /[[User:Ninly|Ninly]] ([[User talk:Ninly|talk]]) 21:25, 5 October 2008 (UTC)

== Ramadan in space, polar regions ==

Dear all
After the intense discussion about the first muslim in space during ramadan, I have checked many websites how he handled the prayer times. Sadly I found differnent answers, one said he did not have to fasten because he is on a journey, other said that he should use the times of makkah and some were claiming that he saw the moon in differnt shapes--&gt; so no fasting. Interestingly is that similar questions and answers are discussed in the case of muslims living in the polar regions. Can anyone find reliable answers and sources?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/134.147.121.244|134.147.121.244]] ([[User talk:134.147.121.244|talk]]) 22:02, 12 August 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:How many muslims live in polar regions? Not so many. Therefore this question is not so important. If you live in polar regions and want to Ramadan, then pick the nearest muslim country and adjust your watch to that countries time. Or better, come to where it's not so lousy cold. --[[Special:Contributions/92.74.31.46|92.74.31.46]] ([[User talk:92.74.31.46|talk]]) 15:08, 8 September 2009 (UTC)

::There are quite a few muslims living in the Nordic countries, where the sun sets for a pretty short while in the summer. So when Ramadan falls in the summer, there will be practical problems, having to stay up late or wake up very early if one wants to eat only after sunset and before dawn. [[User:TorLillqvist|TorLillqvist]] ([[User talk:TorLillqvist|talk]]) 09:59, 8 September 2010 (UTC)

:::Read this article [http://www.saudiaramcoworld.com/issue/201201/ramadan.in.the.farthest.north.htm] saying that after hotly debating this issue, and asking Mecca, they (in [[Tromsø]]) decided to follow [[Mecca]] sunrise/sunset when they have none.--[[User:BIL|BIL]] ([[User talk:BIL|talk]]) 19:41, 1 July 2012 (UTC)
::::Good source! it will help to develop the popular culture of this article. Regards :)--[[User:Omer123hussain|Omer123hussain]] ([[User talk:Omer123hussain|talk]]) 13:35, 29 July 2012 (UTC)

== Ramadan 2009 ==

This entry was recently cleaned up. As Ramadan approaches yet again it will be flooded with amendments, additions and external links of a commercial nature. I have tweaked a few phrases for grammar and included viable sourced citations for already existing copy. I have also removed recently added links to Ramadan timetables.
The External Links section was removed recently so there is no viable location for such links and they don't really belong in an encyclopeadic entry. If people want to find timetables, they will on Google, no doubt.

The page still needs work with layout and general grammar improvements as well as some of the statements still needing viable sources (reputable outlets, news mediums, journals, books and religious texts) and sections needing expanding or moving around a little as some of it gets a little repetitive. I will work on that as I can. 

I will also try and keep an eye on this page as are others, to ensure it remains neutral, up-to-date and non-vandalised. Your viewpoints will assist. thanks.
[[User:UK 007|UK 007]] ([[User talk:UK 007|talk]]) 11:32, 18 August 2009 (UTC)

The new additions and random edits by unregistered users are coming in thick and fast now that Ramadan has begun. This entry is okay in term sof contacts but could be neatened up and expanded on in areas. It definitely needs to be edited to sound more like an encyclopedia entry as suggested. The content however is so far compact and largely fact based, though some citations are still needed. Will try and work on language of entry.
[[User:UK 007|UK 007]] ([[User talk:UK 007|talk]]) 10:47, 21 August 2009 (UTC)

Could someone fix the large blank gaps left by image insertion please? Thanks. [[User:UK 007|UK 007]] ([[User talk:UK 007|talk]]) 10:53, 24 August 2009 (UTC)

== Ramadan 1980 ==

Hello, I am wondering in which day/month did ramadan start in the year 1980. Any help with this is highly appreciated. Thanks for responding. --[[Special:Contributions/66.186.34.211|66.186.34.211]] ([[User talk:66.186.34.211|talk]]) 13:27, 4 September 2009 (UTC)

Ramadan's first day is usually disputed among Islamic countries. if you want an approx. date just add 11 days for every year from now to 1980 and you will get you date  --[[User:Awanta|7amada&amp;#39;sback:)]] ([[User talk:Awanta|talk]]) 11:24, 13 September 2009 (UTC)

== God or Allah? ==

(God is not the correct translation of ALLAH)

I note that an IP user has changed all instances of the word God in the article to Allah.  While my understanding is that it's technically accurate, is it acceptable usage?  My concern, especially considering some of the anti-Muslim sentiment in the US, is that it might be seen as bias in violation of [[WP:NPOV]].  My first impulse is to revert all such changes, but I want to gain consensus first. [[User:N5iln|Alan]] ([[User talk:N5iln|talk]]) 13:46, 20 September 2009 (UTC)
:[[Allah]] is the Muslim name for God. This is an article concerning a holy month in the Muslim faith. It uses the appropriate term as defined in the [[Qu'ran]]. To me, it would be POV to put God, just to appease any anti-Muslim feeling, irrespective of where it originates. [[User:AlexandrDmitri|-- Александр Дмитрий (Alexandr Dmitri)]] ([[User talk:AlexandrDmitri|talk]]) 13:54, 20 September 2009 (UTC)
::That's the information I was looking for.  I'll leave the article as it stands.  [[User:N5iln|Alan]] ([[User talk:N5iln|talk]]) 14:32, 20 September 2009 (UTC)

::: [[Allah]] is not the Muslim name for God - it is the Arabic name for God. Even Christian speakers of Arabic use the name Allah when referring to God.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.57.132.91|74.57.132.91]] ([[User talk:74.57.132.91|talk]]) 02:24, 1 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Ramadan 2010 ==

This entry goes untouched most of the year and then gets attacked annually around Ramadan time by people plugging all kinds of commercial Ramadan services, personal religious article blogs and websites. I suggest all acts of vandalism or cheap promotional publicity attempts by immediately removed and reverted, especially if users and guests fiddle with the main verified and reliable sources of this article which have been in good standing for the last few years and replace them with an near identical source confirmation but on a personal or less verifiable source site. 

I've just re-instated a long-term BBC link which verifies information in the first paragraph but for some reason was replaced with someone's personal page in the last two days. [[Special:Contributions/94.14.70.76|94.14.70.76]] ([[User talk:94.14.70.76|talk]]) 02:18, 4 August 2010 (UTC)

* Hi, I've just cleaned up a few random recent links which are appearing purely to promote e-boosk and websites but don't add anything new or aren't aources well. External links are creeping in as references too. Will keep a watch [[User:UK 007|UK 007]] ([[User talk:UK 007|talk]]) 09:42, 9 August 2010 (UTC)

== Cultural aspects of Ramadan ==

There are a lot of Cultural aspects of Ramadan not mentioned in the article. I'll list sources about them that I find while surfing the internet:
#[http://arabnews.com/lifestyle/sidelights/article99741.ece Ramadan series fever] A lot of TV shows broadcast in ramadan.
Anyone who has any more links please add them.--[[User:Diaa abdelmoneim|Diaa abdelmoneim]] ([[User talk:Diaa abdelmoneim|talk]]) 07:52, 12 August 2010 (UTC)

== Removed &quot;Also&quot; section ==

Text removed:

:The political and military implications of Ramadan are often ignored, due to the fact that the holiday leads up to the celebration of the Battle of Badr of March 17, 624 when Mohammed scored his first military victory by defeating the Quraysh tribe that had rejected his claim to be a Prophet. From this first victory, Islam gained the resources and religious fervor that would sweep the Arabian peninsula, eventually spreading into Asia, Africa and Europe.

If anyone can see the relevance of this to the article, could they at least reword it to make plain how it helps and cite it. As it stands it's just obscure and unintegrated. [[User:Cb6|JohnHarris]] ([[User talk:Cb6|talk]]) 18:10, 26 August 2010 (UTC)

== Fasting question ==

I understand Ramadan requires fasting from sunrise to sunset.  But does it make any requirement on ''breaking'' fast?  Is it required to start eating/drinking immediately at sunset?  -- [[User:AvatarMN|AvatarMN]] ([[User talk:AvatarMN|talk]]) 02:08, 28 August 2010 (UTC)

== The start of Ramadan ==

[[Ramada#The_start_of_Ramadan | This material]] really needs to be fleshed out more. A pretty good definition is given, followed by a nod to the controversy surrounding it. But the BBC article:

[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/practices/ramadan_1.shtml BBC - Religions - Islam: Ramadan]

gives much more in-depth information surrounding the nuances of this controversy. Perhaps we can get someone with more familiarity on this subject to expound on this a bit more (with some good citations, as well). Thanks in advance!! [[User:WDavis1911|WDavis1911]] ([[User talk:WDavis1911|talk]]) 04:14, 10 September 2010 (UTC)

I removed the portion containing Prophet (p) and replaced it with prophet, this is not something that should be listed in an online encyclopedia. --Wes  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/112.164.171.198|112.164.171.198]] ([[User talk:112.164.171.198|talk]]) 07:01, 27 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Possible Vandalism in Intro? ==

Hey, I don't do much editing on wikis, so I wouldn't know how to tag this, but I do believe that someone vandalised the introduction to Ramadan, specifically after the reference to footnotes 3 and 4. At the very least, it's poorly written, and uncited. [[Special:Contributions/70.51.168.155|70.51.168.155]] ([[User talk:70.51.168.155|talk]]) 23:14, 5 June 2011 (UTC)

Don't forget that it sounds like the Pastafarian holiday of Ramendan!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.139.158.156|75.139.158.156]] ([[User talk:75.139.158.156|talk]]) 07:18, 2 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Ramadan among immigrants to North ==

There are large muslim communities in the northern countries, like Sweden or Norway. How do they celebrate Ramadan when it happens in the summer and the sunset is at 11 pm, with sunrise already at 1 am? Do they REALLY don't eat or drink for 22 hours?? There must be some alternative solutions for them and it must be explained in the Encyclopedia. Similarly, for the winter time with extremely short days, traditionally considered Ramadan becomes just a break between breakfast and lunch. What then?  [[User:Merewyn|Merewyn]] ([[User talk:Merewyn|talk]]) 17:13, 2 August 2011 (UTC)

@Merewyn,
It sounds harsh, but they must fast even for 22 hours if its possible. But around these time they have the summer vacation like many countries. Thus some of them are having the Ramadan abroud. But many stay in the Northern countries and fast there. Conclusion: They must have ALOT of patience and willpower :)
Ore they can use the Meccan times. Wich will ease their fasting. [[Special:Contributions/86.80.208.136|86.80.208.136]] ([[User talk:86.80.208.136|talk]]) 12:33, 18 August 2011 (UTC)

== &quot;Ramadan FAQ&quot;? ==

How can this be a quoted source for anything?  Why don't I create a Ramadan Fan Page and we can quote that?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/41.140.50.123|41.140.50.123]] ([[User talk:41.140.50.123|talk]]) 03:53, 25 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Daylight Hours ==

The phrase &quot;daylight hours&quot; seems simple enough but having been in Egypt during the Ramadan just finished, I heard several different interpretations of what that means. I am confused and came here for clarification - but found none.

Relatedly, how would a Muslim cope above the Arctic Circle if Ramadan fell during winter?
[[User:Tesspub|Tesspub]] ([[User talk:Tesspub|talk]]) 09:57, 1 September 2011 (UTC)

:&quot;Daylight Hours&quot; refers to the time between the start of [[Fajr]] [[salah|prayer]] and sunset. &quot;Fajr&quot; prayer starts at dawn, so the time for fasting is about an hour and a half before sunrise up until sunset.
:In regards to Muslims  living in places such as the Arctic Circle, there are various approaches. One approach is to not fast and instead feed a poor person for each day of missed fasting. This option is provided in the [[Qur'an]] itself. &quot;...And upon those who are able [to fast, but with hardship] - a ransom [as substitute] of feeding a poor person [each day]. And whoever volunteers excess - it is better for him. But to fast is best for you, if you only knew.&quot; - Qur'an 2:184 (Sahih International translation). Other options, as provided by some scholars, is to use the dawn and sunset times of a nearby city that has daylight and nighttime. Alternatively, according to other scholars, one can simply use the dawn and sunset times of [[Mecca]]. [[User:SOW93|SOW93]] ([[User talk:SOW93|talk]]) 05:34, 1 August 2012 (UTC)

== 2:185 quote == 

salamlaykum. 

What do you think of replacing the current English trans. of sura 2:185 in this article with Yusuf Ali's?

YUSUFALI: Ramadhan is the (month) in which was sent down the Qur'an, as a guide to mankind, also clear (Signs) for guidance and judgment (Between right and wrong). So every one of you who is present (at his home) during that month should spend it in fasting, but if any one is ill, or on a journey, the prescribed period (Should be made up) by days later. Allah intends every facility for you; He does not want to put to difficulties. (He wants you) to complete the prescribed period, and to glorify Him in that He has guided you; and perchance ye shall be grateful.

or even the Sahil International trans.:

The month of Ramadhan [is that] in which was revealed the Qur'an, a guidance for the people and clear proofs of guidance and criterion. So whoever sights [the new moon of] the month, let him fast it; and whoever is ill or on a journey - then an equal number of other days. Allah intends for you ease and does not intend for you hardship and [wants] for you to complete the period and to glorify Allah for that [to] which He has guided you; and perhaps you will be grateful.

(source: http://quran.com/2/185) 

If not, then at least replace the word God with Allah. The former has different meanings in English and should not be used. God does not have a strict monotheistic meaning in the English vernacular like Allah does. 

 &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.84.68.252|24.84.68.252]] ([[User talk:24.84.68.252|talk]]) 00:37, 15 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: Strange, that there are so diverse translations of one and the same verse. These two translations say different things! Secondly, although the word &quot;God&quot; in itself is not necessarily monotheistic in English, in this article it obviously refers to &quot;God&quot; as understood in Islam, so there is no ambiguity. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 13:35, 16 April 2012 (UTC)

== Recent edits ==

Recent edits by {{User|BuckLava}} and/or/who is maybe an IP user are not up to Wikipedia standards: 1. they use capitals in the middle of sentences 2. they use all kinds of additions like &quot;blessed be his name&quot; 3. they seems to be interested more in bringing the reader to be a Ramadan keeping Muslim rather than give neutral information.

I know that it is about a month to the beginning of the Ramadan, and I am afraid we are going to see more of this the coming time. So please, editors, be alert here. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 23:02, 11 July 2012 (UTC)

What is that you fear?[[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]]) 22:23, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

== &quot;Wikipedia's goal is to compile the sum of all human knowledge into a Web-based, free content encyclopedia.&quot; :) ==

Response to posting by Debresser (talk) 23:02, 11 July 2012 (UTC):

Mr. Debresser, being that you are a four-year veteran perhaps it has been quite some time since you felt any need to review the guidelines for talk pages and the goal of Wikipedia. This is understandable. Therefore, I encourage you to take a quick moment to compare your approach towards me with the [[Wikipedia:Talk page guidelines]], so that you can be a bit more merciful when others contribute sources that you personally may not like, but in no way conflict with anyone's [[Wikipedia:Contributing to Wikipedia]]... especially for someone like myself who is new here (just a few days old).

Thus, even for a few-days-old rookies -- like myself -- to Wikipedia, the two links above are easy enough to abide by.

Nobody's perfect, and so, just as mistakes are inherent in life, so too are they on here, and so, of course, I will not hold it against you.

Regards,

BuckLava  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/BuckLava|contribs]]) 09:04, 14 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: Thank you for not holding anything against me. But unencyclopedical edits will be reverted nevertheless. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 18:44, 14 July 2012 (UTC)
: I may add that your edits today were good edits, in the sense of &quot;encyclopediality&quot;. Also, I appreciate your addition of sources.

== Section on health effects: POV? ==

The section on Health effects only mentions positive effects of fasting. I suppose there must be megative effects as well. For example, Even wikiislam.net gives a long list of negative effects: [http://wikiislam.net/wiki/Adverse_Effects_of_Islamic_Fasting] .
Is there anyone with more expertise in this area who could find reliable sources and try to make it more neutral? [[Special:Contributions/94.103.219.216|94.103.219.216]] ([[User talk:94.103.219.216|talk]]) 17:35, 21 July 2012 (UTC)

: Wikiislam is an extremely biased anti-Islam source with no scientific backings and should NOT be used as a reference for anything. The section on the health effects of Ramadan cite legitimate scientific studies, so any negative effects of the Ramadan fast should be cited with legitimate scientific studies. [[User:SOW93|SOW93]] ([[User talk:SOW93|talk]]) 08:17, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

:: Apart from the question of bias, there is a more serious problem with that site, regarding Wikipedia's WP:RS|&quot;reliable sources&quot;]] policy: &quot;Anyone can create a website or pay to have a book published, then claim to be an expert in a certain field. For that reason self-published media—whether books, newsletters, personal websites, '''open wikis''', blogs, personal pages on social networking sites, Internet forum postings, or tweets—are largely not acceptable.&quot;
:: There is another side to this issue though. The &quot;health effects&quot; mentioned are a by-product of [[fasting]], 'not'' of the Ramadan. Therefore, they belong in the article about fasting, and having them here is misleading. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 23:37, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

::: Thank you for pointing out that Wikiislam is an anti-islam site, I should have noticed that. Anyway, I did not mean it to be used as a reference, but rather as as an indicator that there might be other opinions. I still do not believe that it's impossible to find any negative effect of fasting. Hence my request whether someone could find more reliable sources on this, which still stands. [[Special:Contributions/94.103.219.111|94.103.219.111]] ([[User talk:94.103.219.111|talk]])

As Ramadan implies fasting, and a particular kind of fasting in terms of rules and duration, I think it would be good to have the health effects on this page.[[Special:Contributions/158.64.77.102|158.64.77.102]] ([[User talk:158.64.77.102|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 16:40, 31 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: As a reply to this user I shall quote myself: &quot;There is another side to this issue though. The &quot;health effects&quot; mentioned are a by-product of [[fasting]], 'not'' of the Ramadan. Therefore, they belong in the article about fasting, and having them here is misleading.&quot; [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 16:48, 31 July 2012 (UTC)
::I dont know that this is true. Ramadan is more than just fasting, it is fasting for an extended number of consecutive days. Impacts on health due to that surely belong in this article. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 17:58, 31 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:: There are a few points here. One, and this I do not know, how often are people with what in the US are called &quot;pre-existing health conditions&quot; obliged to observe the Ramadan fast in general? For some people, and here I'm thinking of some forms of diabetics, I know that in other churches they are given a waiver from observing some fasts based on those health conditons. Such individuals might clearly suffer from a regular fast of any sort, let alone one of such a staggered nature as this one. Alternately, are there within the Muslim community instructions for how to observe the fast in such a way as to minimize impact on health? On that subject I confess ignorance. That would however raise questions regarding whether any possible health complications are specifically due to the fast, or are perhaps due to individuals observing the fast in a way which might be perhaps in some cases excessive or counterproductive. If they due to perhaps irrational application of the fast conditions, that should possibly be taken into account as well. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 18:53, 31 July 2012 (UTC)

== Regarding the &quot;Origin of Ramadan section&quot; ==

If one percent of the planet disputes something or offers one &quot;research&quot; opinion, does this merit it having a section on a page?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/BuckLava|contribs]]) 23:49, 21 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: It definitely shouldn't. And having seen/read the sources used for that section, I see that one source is vague while the other source is clearly biased (written by someone trying to entice Muslims to leave Islam). The second source (referenced as source #27) also makes no sense. It attributes Ramadan to &quot;pagan&quot; origins without offering proof, while calling Sabians (a monotheistic group) &quot;pagans&quot; which in and of itself shows the author's lack of knowledge on this subject. Furthermore, the entire section itself makes no sense. &quot;Ramadan was observed by the pagan Arabs&quot; (paraphrasing)? Of course it was. Ramadan is the 9th lunar month. Obviously the pagan Arabs observed a 9th lunar month. I propose deletion for this section on the grounds of nonsensical suggestions made in the section and on the grounds of a lack of (legitimate) sources for the section. [[User:SOW93|SOW93]] ([[User talk:SOW93|talk]]) 08:15, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

I concur. Not becuase you feel it is clearly biased, but rather because it is biased from a scientific, encyclopedic perspective. [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]]) 21:25, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

: The statement &quot;Ramadan was observed by the pagan Arabs&quot; obviously does not mean that they had a 9th month, but that the month of Ramadan was marked by the pagan Arabs in much the same way as Islam marks the month of Ramadan. If you do not understand a text correctly, don't be too hasty to decide the problem is with the text. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 23:45, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

As already observed in the third previous paragraph, there is an obvious flaw in identifying all Sabians as pagan. The dispute arises from Maimonides' account that Harranian Sabians did not self identify as Sabians until threatened by Caliph al-Ma'mun in 830 CE. This would've been long before Ibn al-Nadim's 10th century survey of regional religions (in &quot;al-Fahrisit&quot;), but after the observation by Abu Zanad in 747 CE that &quot;at least one Mandaean community located in northern Iraq observed Ramadan&quot; (wording from Dr. Rafat Amari's web article). If Abu Zanad's writtings have indeed been correctly translated and he intended to signify the Mandaeans rather than the Harranians, then it is quite ambiguous as to which of these two groups possessed the oldest lineage of observing the ceremonies of Ramadan. Saying that Ramadan was a &quot;pagan&quot; ceremony is dependent upon attributing the origin to the pagan Harranians rather than the monotheist Mandaeans. This is very possible, but not certain. For the time being, I propose to disclose this ambiguity by modifying the sentence mentioning Ramadan as a pagan ceremony. Rather, I believe it preferable to state that the ceremony was performed by either/both of monotheist Mandaeans and/or pagan Harranians. [[User:A.Aboumrad|A.Aboumrad]] ([[User talk:A.Aboumrad|talk]]) 21:57, 18 August 2012 (UTC)

: This is a deviation from the source, which unambiguously uses the word &quot;pagan&quot;. Also, Mandaeism is not as unambiguously monotheistic as you state it is, and the few things I know about it do not make the claim of pagan rites farfetched. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 01:12, 19 August 2012 (UTC)

: The article by Dr. Amari uses &quot;pagan&quot; in its terminology, but is this an appropriate description for both groups called Sabians?. Moreover, it is clear that the &quot;Ramadan and Its Roots&quot; article has a clear anti-Islamic agenda (as do other of Dr. Amari's works) and his own conclusions are perhaps less reliable than material which he himself sources. That Ramadan originates in pagan ceremonies is the claim of Dr. Amari alone, while his Arabic sources appear to show merely that different groups in the Middle East practiced it during the early centuries of Islamic dominance. I agree that pagan origins are not farfetched, as you said, but just because something is not &quot;far-fetched&quot; does not mean that it is confidently certain. This looks more like a &quot;chicken or the egg&quot; situation. As for the Mandaeans, their religious beliefs indeed have some ambiguity, but for the Qur'an itself to call them &quot;people of the book&quot; lends itself to classifying them alongside the other monotheistic religions rather than Hellenistic or Arabic polytheism. Also, there is not a single prophet of the Mandaeans which comes from outside of the Judean lineage. I realize that I'm splitting hairs with semantics here, but such a loaded term as &quot;pagan&quot; ought not to be applied indiscriminately. You are quite reluctant to admit Mandaeans to be monotheists (or at least &quot;not-pagan&quot;), yet very hasty in assuming that &quot;if pagans fasted during Ramadan in the 10th century, they must have been the originators.&quot; The evidence is far from conclusive, and this claim ought to be given as possibility or theory, at best. I stand by my most recent modification, but I would love to have additional opinions on this. [[User:A.Aboumrad|A.Aboumrad]] ([[User talk:A.Aboumrad|talk]]) 04:09, 19 August 2012 (UTC)

: I agree with the points you make, that 1. the source seems to have an agenda, and 2. that the nature of Mandaeism is not clear-cut. In addition, let me add that I appreciate your personal knowledge of the matter, and the fact that you understand the importance of discussion. Perhaps we should start looking for a better source, and see what comes up. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 09:29, 19 August 2012 (UTC)

== Non-Muslim forcing insignificant dissention to be broadcast with its own section heading un-encyclopedic ==

The title speaks for itself.

Dispute about Ramadan is insignificant, merits more mention than the opinion of one citation and is not helping inform anyone who needs wikipedia to be informed. Rather, the inclusion of insignificant items, as when an overwhelming number of verifiable items are given back seat to one or two opinionated citations, dilutes the purpose of Wikipedia.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/BuckLava|contribs]]) 21:07, 22 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

If someone were to type in &quot;origin of Ramadan&quot; in a search engine, this is what they would be subject to. Is this really an accurate depiction of what Ramadan is today? [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]]) 21:23, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

: What is the meaning of the title of this section &quot;Non-Muslim forcing insignificant dissention to be broadcast with its own section heading un-encyclopedic&quot; and of the first sentence? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 23:47, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

== Section ==

Debresser said that the body already mentions what i aded, but it doesn't. That section does nto state fasting is obligatory, and says nothing about the ill or travelling. Furthermore i think this desrves mention in the lede because it mentions the conditions for fasting. This is lde-worthy. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 21:25, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

: I quote &quot;It becomes compulsory for Muslims to start fasting when they reach puberty, so long as they are healthy, sane and have no disabilities or illnesses. The elderly, the chronically ill, and the mentally ill are exempt from fasting&quot;. We see here repeatedly the ill. And I quote again &quot;Also, those traveling (musaafir) are exempt&quot;. So here we have travelers. I recommend reading the article before you start editing and discussing it. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 01:07, 23 July 2012 (UTC)
  
Ignore anyone who detests your religion and single-handedly insists on reverting your changes. Trust me, it's worked wonders for the fidelity of the Ramadan page since I joined Wikipedia just for the sake of improving this one page and taken major advantage of SEO.! If you saw what it was before, you'd have been disgusted at how un-encyclopedic it was.  Slowly, but surely, honest, well-intended, moderate persons like us have the duty to ensure information is concise, relevant and properly cited by the sources that originated the ways Ramadan is currently fasted and has been fasted for over 1400 years. When someone types in &quot;origin of ramadan&quot; now, they get a more accurate idea of what they need to know, not &quot;the name of ramadan is in some dispute&quot; as debresser had preferred and continuously reverted the page to. So, like I said, ignore anyone who sounds biased and detests clarity in explaining Islam-related subjects to English readers and also try to avoid using the word &quot;Islamic&quot;. Instead try to use words that are not innovated from English like &quot;Muslim&quot; and &quot;Islam&quot; as appropriate when discussing a topic or word originating from Arabic or Islam, as this will inherently make the topic more encyclopedic.

Best wishes as you sinerely intend to add clarity to the page and make it easily to read and understand what [[Ramadan]] is relevantly all about.[[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]]) 22:14, 22 July 2012 (UTC)

: Whom did you mean by &quot;anyone who detests your religion&quot;? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 01:02, 23 July 2012 (UTC)

::: Debresser, you have not explained why that sentence is not lede-worthy. I think its lede-worthy information because it demonstrates who should fast and who should not. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 01:45, 23 July 2012 (UTC)
:::: Those are already details, and as such should be kept in the section on fasting. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 07:24, 23 July 2012 (UTC)

== Origin of Ramadan shifted to logical place... the beginning!  ==

Beware the revert-mad touch of Debresser that is guised under dedication to spelling and grammar. It is inevitable. Clarity on Muslim-related sections to be more encyclopedic is not consistent with his persistent contributions to this page.

KEEP AN EYE OUT and you will see exactly what I mean.

: Do you have any specific problem with my edits? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 23:48, 22 July 2012 (UTC)
: It is a disgrace that such an important article like this had spelling mistakes, superfluous words and sentences, unencyclopedic paragraphs, bad Wikipedia markup (references, internal links, tags, etc.), and no internal order in sections. If 1 billion Muslims can't take care of that, then one Jew can. :) And I think I did quite a good job of it, especially to the hopelessly mixed up &quot;origins&quot; section. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 00:40, 23 July 2012 (UTC)

::LOL, I'm glad the word Ramadan has been on your mind more often this year than perhaps any year before. As one of the 1.6 billion (be accurate and encyclopedic when making references that are verifiable) I just joined Wikipedia and I agree the English-speaking community of Muslims has done a poor, poor job with basic English grammar (although the same page in their native tongues seems to be just fine). Thanks for your amazingly dedicated care to the grammar and spelling of the &quot;Ramadan&quot; page. Your obvious zeal to ensure that the planet Earth reads a properly spelled, properly cited, properly organized page about a pillar of Islam cannot be questioned! On behalf of the 1.6 billion Muslims world-wide, I want to publicly thank you, Mr. Debresser! :) [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]]) 01:10, 24 July 2012 (UTC)

::: I am glad we can laugh about this. Let's work together to make this article better! [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 06:14, 24 July 2012 (UTC)

I see somebody removed the paragraph about the origin of the word &quot;Ramadan&quot;. That paragraph was unsourced and vague, but in general I think it would be important to have something about this. Is there something sourced we can add there? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 06:19, 24 July 2012 (UTC)

==Peaceable editing==
There is really no reason to have anything other than reasoned debate on this talk page.  The article needs to be about Ramadan, it should not express an opinion about Ramadan though it may report on significant opinions of others.   Therefore it should be possible to reach agreement on content regardless of the creed - or lack thereof - of the contributors.  Making ''ad hominem'' arguments is not only contrary to the spirit of Wikipedia (and most religions) but also a complete waste of time,and I encourage editors to abjure such arguments. 

While I am ignorant of any detail of the subject, let me address some of the points in the above sections:

# Poorly capitalized sentences and stylistic variations at odds with the MoS should not be held against an editor, but quietly corrected, and where appropriate, a friendly note left for the editor in question.
# What is feared is primarily that the article moves from being a neutral and reasonably well written encyclopaedic article into something else.
# If one percent of the planet disputes something, then almost certainly it should be noted, that would be the population of a large country.
# &quot;Origin of Ramadan&quot;   should certainly ''not'' be a reflection of what Ramadan is today.
# Do not &quot;ignore anyone who sounds biased&quot; but rather listen to all, compare the merits of the statements themselves, not of those who propose them.

Keep editing! ''[[User:Rich Farmbrough|Rich]]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Rich Farmbrough|Farmbrough]]'', &lt;small&gt;01:35, 23 July 2012 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

== Copy edit in the lead ==

I made some correction in the lead with good faith, citing of sources is required, the article is overloaded with multiple sections, need to merge the sections with related one. Regards :)--[[User:Omer123hussain|Omer123hussain]] ([[User talk:Omer123hussain|talk]]) 20:07, 26 July 2012 (UTC)

: I think it is good to have separate sections as much as possible for different subjects. Which sections would you want to merge here? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 00:54, 27 July 2012 (UTC)

:: I don't user wikipedia much, but look harder - the duplicate content is in a paragraph directly adjacent.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.72.170.247|70.72.170.247]] ([[User talk:70.72.170.247|talk]]) 01:21, 27 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::*The section '''Practices during Ramadan''' shall be renamed as '''Practices''' all the sub-sections in this can be made as side heading only and shall include '''lailatul qadr''' and '''end of ramadan'''.
:::*The section '''cultural aspects''' may be renamed with '''popular culture''' and need to expanded.
:::*The section '''Origin''' shall be move to top and renamed as '''etimology'''. Regards :)--[[User:Omer123hussain|Omer123hussain]] ([[User talk:Omer123hussain|talk]]) 13:05, 29 July 2012 (UTC)

::::I agree with DeBresser and the other's comment about duplicate content. With too many random changes by different users, however, the disorganization will persist. After the page has been semi-protected (which is long over due for such an important annual global topic), then we can have a better chance of avoiding &quot;duplicate content&quot;, improved organization, etc.[[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]]) 16:33, 29 July 2012 (UTC)

== Should fasting criteria be in the lede? ==
{{archive top|result=There is no consensus onto the wording of the sentence.  Specifically, whether to include the who and exclusions.  There is, however, consensus to mention fasting in some form in the lead.  I would suggest more discussion take place about the actual words keeping [[WP:LEAD]] in mind and specifically that the lead should summarize the article with appropriate weight.  The question everyone should ask themselves is: &quot;Is what we are including in the lead as important or more important than what we are no including?&quot;--v/r - [[User:TParis|T]][[User_talk:TParis|P]] 18:03, 10 September 2012 (UTC)}}
Do you support or oppose adding the criteria for fasting be in the lede? Specifically this sentence [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ramadan&amp;diff=503688318&amp;oldid=503680068] [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:11, 27 July 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' The criteria for fasting is an important aspect of islam. For example in Islamic countries the only public places where fast food is served openly during midday hours is generally in airports and similar travel-related venues, or in health-relaed locations such as hospitals. Another important reason to include it is because when it comes to fasting all the different sects diagree on several issues, including the timing, moon-sighting methods, application of tarawih etc. But the criteria for fasting (adulthood, health, travelling) all sects appear to agree on. Noneheless Debresser wants to keep this in the article body only. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grely&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;paprus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:11, 27 July 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''', If it were a long and arbitrarily legalistic set of criteria, I'd be opposed, but it seems like we already have a succinct wording, and the information 'who' is at least as relevant as the information 'what' the fast entails and 'when' the fast happens that's already included. [[User:Darryl from Mars|Darryl from Mars]] ([[User talk:Darryl from Mars|talk]]) 16:32, 28 July 2012 (UTC)
*&lt;s&gt;'''Comment'''&lt;/s&gt;: The article as it stands has roughly seven sections of information, and right now a two-paragraph lead. I think that it would not be unreasonable in this instance to expand the lead to perhaps even five paragraphs, but I would not myself seek to go into any specific details about specific content regarding details of one aspect, even if it is one of the most important aspects, until the lead were expanded and a clearer idea of what information is not yet included is available. In summary, this is, I guess, a provisional &quot;no', which might become a &quot;yes&quot; later once the lead is a more comprehensive summary of the contents. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 20:23, 28 July 2012 (UTC)
:*'''Oppose''' - as per Debresser's comments below. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 20:30, 29 July 2012 (UTC)
*'''Oppose strongly for two reasons''' That Ramadan involves fasting is very important, and should be in the lead. The details of who yes and who not, should be kept in the section. Because they are just that: details. And a second reason why I find that we can not have this in the lede, is because there are different opinions and customs in these details, and that for sure should not be in the lede. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]])
** Thats a false statement. Can you tell me which part of my addition is controversial, including a source for that claim? There is arguably a consensus in the Muslim community on this issue. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 23:52, 28 July 2012 (UTC)
:: Pass a Method, we all know that you want the details to be in the text, but to go from that to accusing me of making false statements, is not nice of you. Not only are there differing opinions, and I am sure you yourself are aware of them, but we have even seen them here on Wikipedia in this article. I must admit, that I am not inclined to flook through all the many edits of the last month and find them. But just have a look at [http://www.al-islam.org/encyclopedia/chapter7/3.html this article], and you see that there are many different opinions about all of the categories for exemtion. QED. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]])
::: Nothing in that source contradicts my proposed sentence. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 10:49, 29 July 2012 (UTC)
::::And nothing necessarily ''supports'' the proposed sentence, either. One is as important as the other. So, basically, the only reason given to include the information is the opinions of editors. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 20:30, 29 July 2012 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' because it is not the matter to be discussed in the lead, It shall be discussed in the section, as said above it has different point of views by multiple schools of Muslims. We shall concentrate to include in the lead about popular culture, first revelation of Quran, since when Ramadn fasting is declared obligatory, the first battle of Islam which was fought in this month, etc. Involving in who is supposed to and who is not will complicate the lead. Regards :)--[[User:Omer123hussain|Omer123hussain]] ([[User talk:Omer123hussain|talk]]) 13:21, 29 July 2012 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' Mention that it is the month of fasting is important. Criteria for such fasting is additional explanatory information that can wait for the body of the article. -- [[User:Danielklotz|DanielKlotz]] ([[User talk:Danielklotz|talk]] ·  [[Special:Contributions/Danielklotz|contribs]]) 15:14, 29 July 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' -- '''Darryl from Mars''' summed it up concisely. In addition, Ramadan is the most famous consecutive-numbered-days-of-fasting in the world, and has been so for over 1400 years. Therefore, this unique context, warrants a brief mention of such info, one might argue. If we can just semi-protect the page from overzealous newbies, unfamiliar with the best practices of wikipedia editting, then as-is, the section poses no problems, I argue. Thanks, 16:40, 29 July 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/BuckLava|contribs]])
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
*'''Support''' It is entirely appropriate. It is short, neutral and expanded upon later in the article. It does not overload the lead with superfluous detail. Remember that some readers will only read the lead to get an overview of the topic and will only visit the detailed sections if they are interested enough. [[User:Jschnur|Jschnur]] ([[User talk:Jschnur|talk]]) 03:16, 3 August 2012 (UTC)
::'''Comment'''  [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] you seem to have created your own [[Catch-22]] because the lead will never be a more comprehensive summary of the contents without this inclusion. [[User:Jschnur|Jschnur]] ([[User talk:Jschnur|talk]]) 03:39, 3 August 2012 (UTC)
:::Actually, pardon me for saying that I think that is misleading. My point was that there are seven existing subsections of the article, and at present two paragraphs of lead. It is not necessarily problematic to say that the seven sections could be expanded to perhaps five paragraphs with the inclusion of the major points of each. And, honestly, if one reads the comments below about how it is problematic to apply these standards in polar zones and elsewhere, inclusion of this information without the necessary qualifiers is itself problematic. So, yes, expand to five paragraphs possibly, ensuring that the essential data of each of the seven sections is included first. Then determine on that basis where and how in the lead to include information of this type, which needs some qualification regarding how it is applied in various regions, and whether the necessary text to present that clearly and completely might be excessive, even for a fully developed lead. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 17:34, 3 August 2012 (UTC)
'''Question''': For those opposed, what is your opinion of this page's structure: [[Yom Kippur]]?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/BuckLava|contribs]]) 17:06, 29 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Please see [[WP:OTHERSTUFFEXISTS]]. The content of other articles is not necessarily a guide for the content in this article. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 20:30, 29 July 2012 (UTC)
:'''Oppose per Debresser''': that it involves fasting, yes; how the shariah details who is and isn't to fast, no. [[User:JohnChrysostom|St&amp;nbsp;'''John&amp;nbsp;Chrysostom''']]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:JohnChrysostom|Δόξα]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[[Special:Contributions/JohnChrysostom|τω&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;Θεώ&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 04:49, 1 August 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' It is entirely appropriate as per comment by ''Jschnur'' above; ditto comments by ''BuckLava''; in the Interfaith movement, Ramadan is principally perceived as a time of fasting and community meals when the fast is broken. [[User:Whiteguru|Whiteguru]] ([[User talk:Whiteguru|talk]]) 02:46, 13 August 2012 (UTC)
*'''Support''' - the fact that it is obligatory is sufficiently relevant to rate a mention in the lede, and thus the criteria/exceptions for the obligation are also relevant to mention. The [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ramadan&amp;diff=503688318&amp;oldid=503680068 proposed wording] is brief, to the point, and appropriate. [[User:Mitch Ames|Mitch Ames]] ([[User talk:Mitch Ames|talk]]) 15:12, 17 August 2012 (UTC)
===Comments===
Can someone show me anywhere on this page where this idea has already been discussed? I see no evidence of any such discussion regarding this subject on the talk page here at all. In general, we are supposed to try to see if the parties involved can reach some sort of agreement first, before calling in others. I see no evidence of that here, and I think it is generally considered poor form to not try to reach an agreement before calling in outside parties. On that basis, I have to question the basis for this RfC, without any sort of prior discussion on the talk page here. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 22:17, 27 July 2012 (UTC)
: It is discussed :under the heading &quot;section&quot; [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:PassaMethod|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 11:59, 28 July 2012 (UTC)
:: You are right, and you have my apologies. I compliment you in this instance, and retract the comment above. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 14:12, 28 July 2012 (UTC)
I think this is a somewhat difficult question as what &quot;fasting&quot; means goes beyond the three things mentioned in the lead. Among the things prohibited while fasting is smoking, which isnt mentioned at all. And, depending on how strict you might be, some consider things like swearing to also break ones fast. Im not really sure where I stand on the question of how much detail on the actual fast is necessary in the lead. But the way it is currently constructed makes it seem like those are '''the''' three things observant Muslims abstain from while fasting. That isnt accurate. &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 20:59, 28 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
{{archive bottom}}

== Protection ==

After all these years, this page is open to '''vandalism'''? Are you kidding me? This page should be granted '''semi-protection status'''.

As a word, '''Ramadan''' is commonly known today, around the world as one associated with '''the month when Muslims fast'''. It's prominence is entirely due to the growth and presence of observing '''Muslims''' among the 1.5 billion+ community today from the few hundreds back in the 7th century. It is one of the '''Pillars of Islam'''. It should not be subject to anonymous vandalism for even a moment.

Therefore, I propose it be granted &quot;semi-protection&quot; status.

So how do we go about making that happen?

Thanks! [[User:BuckLava|BuckLava]] ([[User talk:BuckLava|talk]]) 16:25, 29 July 2012 (UTC)

: No page is &quot;granted&quot; protected status (of whatever level). If we have to protect a page, that is not considered a bone. We protect articles only because of vandalism, and consider that a loss. Because we on Wikipedia would like everybody to be able to freely edit Wikipedia articles. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 21:18, 29 July 2012 (UTC)

::Here's the policy, [[Wikipedia:Protection policy]]. This article gets little vandalism and there is no way it is going to be protected. [[User:CambridgeBayWeather|CambridgeBayWeather]] ([[User talk:CambridgeBayWeather|talk]]) 23:22, 29 July 2012 (UTC)

== Arctic circle, etc. ==

So, if a Muslim moves to Nome, AK, do they just starve to death? 

This is a serious question that some prejudiced person just decided to delete as an &quot;unworthy comment&quot; -- it's a bloody ''question.'' The article addresses situations wherein someone is sick, menstruating, etc, but not one in which it is simple impractical to observe. At a certain latitude, the sun will not set during '''all of Ramadan.''' This would seem to make it impossible to observe, or alternately could be taken as a general rule that if one is to follow the tenets of Islam, one must not move to, for instance, Nome, Alaska.

Do not delete this with prejudice. Asking a question is NOT an &quot;unworthy comment&quot; and how ''dare'' anyone suggest it is?

[[Special:Contributions/98.248.89.169|98.248.89.169]] ([[User talk:98.248.89.169|talk]]) 23:26, 30 July 2012 (UTC)
:Questions are best asked at the [[WP:Reference desk]], but no, an observant Muslim would not starve to death if he or she lived in such a place. Different sources say different things, but all of them (that I have seen) agree that a person who is in a place where the sun does not set should follow the schedule of another location (I've seen a source saying to follow the fajr/maghrib schedule of Mecca, and I've seen a source say to follow the schedule of the closest place where the sun does set). &lt;small style=&quot;border: 1px solid;padding:1px 3px;white-space:nowrap&quot;&gt;'''[[User talk:Nableezy|&lt;font color=&quot;#C11B17&quot;&gt;nableezy&lt;/font&gt;]]''' - 23:36, 30 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:: IP editor 98.248.89.169, please cool down a little. The question was added by the same editor who wrote &quot;You all need to be tolerant of everyone, even people who think you should be dead.&quot; and right behind it. Therefore it was removed. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 23:55, 30 July 2012 (UTC)
::: The IP brings up a reasonable point about how the fast has to, at times, be interpreted given unusual circumstances. I presume the same question would apply to a Muslim astronaut.This is one of the reasons I think it makes sense to not add an unqualified description of the nature of the fast in the lead, because adding it would give the impression that it would apply in these cases, and that would be counterproductive. [[User:John Carter|John Carter]] ([[User talk:John Carter|talk]]) 00:32, 31 July 2012 (UTC)

::::There was a news report on this the other day but it's behind a paywall. Basically the guy was living in [[Yellowknife]] and said that some people follow the hours used in Mecca, while others used the times from [[Edmonton]]. There is another report on it [http://www.muslimnews.co.uk/news/news.php?article=22945 here]. [[User:CambridgeBayWeather|CambridgeBayWeather]] ([[User talk:CambridgeBayWeather|talk]]) 03:37, 4 August 2012 (UTC)

== 'jews waited to unlettered prophet' ==

In the section about the 'origin of the ramadan' it was mentioned that the jews who migrated to madina waited to an 'unlettered prophet' (obviously implying Muhammad pbuh). The source for this statment is the Hadith. This is clearly POV, since the Hadith is clearly a bias source on this matter since Muhammad was 'unlettered' so it is pretty clear comes to gives him more legitimacy as a prophet. If there is no other information supporting this statment I dont see a reason to leave it there. Also, it has nothing to do to the subject of the section.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/77.228.199.87|77.228.199.87]] ([[User talk:77.228.199.87|talk]]) 17:40, 2 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: Why would Jews await a prophet, let alone an unlettered one? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 18:05, 2 September 2012 (UTC)

== Wording ==

Per TParis's statement above, input on the specific wording of the paragraph is welcome. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 14:14, 12 September 2012 (UTC)
: What paragraph is this comment referring to? [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 20:10, 18 September 2012 (UTC)
:: Either the first or second. [[User:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;Tahoma&quot;&gt;Pass a Method&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Pass a Method|&lt;font color=&quot;grey&quot; face=&quot;papyrus&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 18:44, 21 September 2012 (UTC)
::: If this note is related to any of the sections above, please place it there. Otherwise, it is completely unclear what your are talking about with this post. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 21:33, 23 September 2012 (UTC)

== Original research in Pre-Islamic observation of Ramadan sections== 

&quot;Abdel Allah ibn Zakwan Abi al-Zanad claims that Ramadan originally had roots in India and the Middle East. He said that it is evident from Abu Zanad writings, that Ramadan was a pagan ceremony practiced by the Sabians, whether they were Mandaeans or Harranians.&quot; 

I find this additions to be of original research , to advance a position not directly and explicitly supported by the source (According to Wikipedia Policies and Guidelines) .

see Extended content:
{{Collapse top}}
Wikipedia policy state that: Any material that is challenged or likely to be challenged must be supported by a reliable source(for example, Oxford University Press, Britannica Online Encyclopedia). Material for which no reliable source can be found is considered original research. '''The only way you can show your edit is not original research''' is to cite a reliable published source that contains the same material. Even with well-sourced material, '''if you use it out of context, or to advance a position not directly and explicitly supported by the source,''' its original research .

Wikipedia articles should be based on '''reliable''', published secondary sources'''(for example, Oxford University Press, Britannica Online Encyclopedia )and, to a lesser extent, on tertiary sources. '''Material based purely on primary sources '''should be avoided. All interpretive claims, analyses, or synthetic claims about primary sources must be referenced to a secondary source, rather than to the original analysis of the primary-source material. '''Self-published material, whether on paper or online, is generally not regarded as reliable'''.
{{Collapse bottom}}
'''it should be noted '''that an adversary Web sites to Islam ( Runned by an organization with an adversary goal ) is not a reliable sources (including its books , authors , unless supported by a reliable source . 

Further information: 
Wikipedia:Identifying reliable sources
see Extended content:
{{Collapse top}}

What counts as a reliable source

The word &quot;source&quot; in Wikipedia has three meanings: the work itself (a document, article, paper, or book), the creator of the work (for example, the writer), and the publisher of the work (for example, Oxford University Press). All three can affect reliability.

Articles should be based on reliable, third-party, published sources '''with a reputation for fact-checking and accuracy'''.
{{Collapse bottom}}[[User:Tommy symbol|Tommy symbol]] ([[User talk:Tommy symbol|talk]]) 09:30, 21 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tg2k9nci1qsmjtzpozl5p8y8y4fdghr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
