<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Devil</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>173659</id>
    <revision>
      <id>510313705</id>
      <parentid>503031700</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-01T18:42:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Koavf</username>
        <id>205121</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Opposite of devil */Substituting template per documentation, replaced: {{unsigned → {{subst:unsigned using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21151">{{Talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell |1=
 {{WikiProject Christianity|importance=High|class=C|attention=yes}}
 {{WikiProject Judaism|class=C|importance=Mid}}
 {{WikiProject Islam|class=C|importance=Mid}}
 {{WikiProject Religion|class=C|LeftHandPath=yes|importance=top}}
 {{WikiProject Occult|class=C|importance=high}}
 {{WikiProject Horror|class=C|importance=high}}
}}
{{todo}}
{{archivebox |search= yes |
# [[Talk:Devil/Archive 1| 2003 – August 2006]]
# [[Talk:Devil/Archive 2|September 2006 – December 2010]]
# &lt;!--[[Talk:Devil/Archive 3|AJanuary 2011 – ???]]--&gt;
}}

__TOC__

== Reference title incorrect ==

Hi, I don't have editing rights, but notice that the title of reference 18 is incorrect. It currently reads &quot;Do You Believe in a Devil? He is a saint.&quot; This appears to have been vandalised. The correct title is simply, &quot;Do You Believe in a Devil?&quot; and the link leads directly to an electronic version of a booklet with this title. Christadelphians do NOT believe that the devil is a saint. The booklet was never entitled this, and does not say anything remotely like this.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/203.45.194.102|203.45.194.102]] ([[User talk:203.45.194.102|talk]]) 05:31, 21 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;



== Sup with that Mayor Hall picture? ==
What's the story behind that? I hate articles that have photos with no explanation and what's going on.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/114.77.208.218|114.77.208.218]] ([[User talk:114.77.208.218|talk]]) 14:39, 18 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Readability ==

Horus is victorious over Set and Ausar, being brought back from the dead becomes lord of the underworld.

should read:

Horus is victorious over Set; and Ausar (being brought back from the dead) becomes lord of the underworld.

The difference is that it is not one sentence, but two separate sentences connected by a common thought, thus the semi-colon, and the parenthesis.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.43.18.19|75.43.18.19]] ([[User talk:75.43.18.19|talk]]) 18:21, 13 June 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Supernatural or superhuman? ==

I propose to change the adjective &quot;supernatural&quot; in the first rows with the adjective &quot;superhuman&quot;.
See the talk page of the article Deity for the matter.
I paste that here:

“01:02, 11 June 2011 Mann jess (talk | contribs) (17,010 bytes) (Undid revision 433634278 by 87.19.60.51 (talk) No. Lots of things are &quot;superhuman&quot;. This is explicitly &quot;supernatural&quot;. Please don't [[WP:EW discuss on talk.) (undo)”

Supernatural means over-the-nature and more specifically *not part of the nature*.
Let me quote the article:

“natural phenomena as lightning, floods, storms, other 'acts of God', and miracles are attributed to them”

Miracles are things unexplicated by science (ethimologically it is synonym of wonder). Admitting deities, angels and so on exist, are these beings out-of-our-comprehension (in their particular conformation) or *not part of nature*? (note 1)

We must free the field from a &quot;neo-positivistic&quot; vision of nature. What is out-of-our-comprehension is not unnatural, and even if it should refer to other-than-human beings, it does not mean they are less *part of nature* than us.

About the other part it explains by itself. It says about ruling on natural phenomena, they are a deep inside *part of nature*.
I shall be more clear.
Juppiter rules on thunders and so on, Thanatos on death, Dike on justice, Robigus on rust, they have power on these things but it means their abilities and their specific nature are over-human-abilities and over-human-nature (superhuman - and also -maybe not forever- out-of-our-comprehension), not they are not *part of nature* like us.

Ultimately the whole concept of the so called &quot;supernatural&quot; must be revised.
note 1: Semele, mother of Dionisus, asked to Juppiter to let her see him in his deity form. The myth tells she was disintegrated.

Mormegil [[Special:Contributions/87.19.77.115|87.19.77.115]] ([[User talk:87.19.77.115|talk]]) 03:01, 11 June 2011 (UTC)

:Hi 87.19. We've been using this definition for a while, and we'd need sources to modify our fundamental definition. Generally speaking, I'm not sure that changing &quot;supernatural&quot; to &quot;superhuman&quot; is an improvement in describing the term, in part because lots of things are &quot;superhuman&quot;; Indeed, anything with abilities 'above' that of humans could be seen as such. Biological enhancements are one example, which clearly don't qualify as a &quot;Diety&quot;. Supernatural, on the other hand, implies that a Diety is beyond nature itself, unlike the everyday things we encounter. Personally, I find this to be a more compelling definition. If you can find a source which supports your proposal, however, we would be able to discuss such a change to the lead. &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 03:22, 11 June 2011 (UTC)

::A source? Dictionary?

::&quot;superhuman
::–adjective
::1. above or beyond what is human; having a higher nature or greater powers than humans have: a superhuman being.
::2. exceeding ordinary human power, achievement, experience, etc.: a superhuman effort.&quot;
::www.dictionary.com

::The 1st definition is (also) a deity. The 2nd, regarding deities, is what a deity can do.

::Bye, Mormegil [[Special:Contributions/87.19.77.115|87.19.77.115]] ([[User talk:87.19.77.115|talk]]) 04:56, 11 June 2011 (UTC)

:::No, we need a source for &quot;Diety&quot;. Not a source for &quot;superhuman&quot;. &amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; [[User:Mann_jess|&lt;b&gt;Jess&lt;/b&gt;]]&lt;span style=&quot;margin:0 7px;font-variant:small-caps;font-size:0.9em&quot;&gt;&amp;middot; [[Special:Contributions/Mann_jess|&amp;Delta;]][[User_talk:Mann_jess|&amp;hearts;]]&lt;/span&gt; 15:05, 11 June 2011 (UTC)

::::God
::::noun

::::1 (in Christianity and other monotheistic religions) the creator and ruler of the universe and source of all moral authority; the supreme being.
::::2 - (god)(in certain other religions) a '''superhuman''' being or spirit worshipped as having power over nature or human fortunes; a deity:a moon god, the Hindu god Vishnu
::::  - an image, animal, or other object worshipped as divine or symbolizing a god.
::::  - used as a conventional personification of fate:he dialled the number and, the gods relenting, got through at once

::::excerpt from http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/God
::::see the link for deepening (I stripped just the first two definitions, bold highlighting is mine).

::::Bye, Mormegil [[Special:Contributions/87.18.196.100|87.18.196.100]] ([[User talk:87.18.196.100|talk]]) 22:27, 11 June 2011 (UTC)

:::::If anyone has not anything to reply, I shall procede with the below amendetion in a week or a little more:

:::::&quot;A deity is a recognized preternatural or '''superhuman''' immortal being, who may be thought of as holy, divine, or sacred, held in high regard, and respected by believers, often religiously referred to as a god.

::::::The demi-urges are considered by Aquinas, Summa Theologiae, 50 Case 6 as being something of a halfway house, neither fully divine nor fully human, and, moreover, heirarchised within that structure. His argument fails to reconcile the ostensible contradiction, in that being spiritual beings they have no scope for upping their game, but not being God they have infinite scope for improvement. That then opens the door to the concept of the fallen angel, with the distinction that the doctrine of salvation is for men, whose Original Sin was second-hand/indirect, being mediated by Satan, unlike the demons, whose sin was overt rebellion. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:188.29.13.121|188.29.13.121]] ([[User talk:188.29.13.121|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/188.29.13.121|contribs]]) 09:01, 24 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:::::Deities are depicted in a variety of forms, but are also frequently expressed as having human form. Some faiths and traditions consider it blasphemous to imagine or depict the deity as having any concrete form. They are usually immortal, and are commonly assumed to have personalities and to possess consciousness, intellects, desires, and emotions similar to those of humans.

:::::'''They have power over one or more aspects of nature and/or human fortunes.''' Such natural phenomena as lightning, floods, storms, other 'acts of God', and miracles are attributed to them, and they may be thought to be the authorities or controllers of various aspects of human life (such as birth or the afterlife). Some deities are asserted to be the directors of time and fate itself, to be the givers of human law and morality, to be the ultimate judges of human worth and behavior, and to be the designers and creators of the Earth or the universe.&quot;

:::::Bold highlightins are the amendations. Maybe I shall do further wiki formatting like links and others.

:::::Bye, Mormegil [[Special:Contributions/87.19.76.137|87.19.76.137]] ([[User talk:87.19.76.137|talk]]) 18:52, 20 June 2011 (UTC)

Well, we are talking about Deities, but the dichotomy supernatural/superhuman is the same.

Mormegil [[Special:Contributions/87.19.77.127|87.19.77.127]] ([[User talk:87.19.77.127|talk]]) 04:34, 30 June 2011 (UTC)

:It's worth examining Aquinas in detail, as he brings together the often contentious early fathers' theology with Aristotelianism, building the baseline off which everything else works. He considers the demi-urges (Summa Theologiae, 50 Case 6) as being something of a halfway house, neither fully divine nor fully human, and, moreover, heirarchised within that structure. His argument fails to reconcile the ostensible contradiction, in that being spiritual beings they have no scope for upping their game, but not being God they have infinite scope for improvement, but plumps for the latter. That then opens the door to the concept of the fallen angel, with the distinction that the doctrine of salvation is for men, whose Original Sin was second-hand/indirect, being mediated by Satan, unlike the demons, whose sin was overt rebellion - therefore, they may be the worst case of all, neither empowered (the doctrine of the Harrowing of Hell - again a needful link) nor capable of fulfillling any potential. He continues in the specific case of the diabolical (Summa 80 onwards).

:The second point to bring out is that none the less there is very little applied demonology until an understanding was needed for the medical catastrophes of the second half of the fourteenth century, which came within a gnat's whisker of reducing civilisation to the stone age - indeed, it did in some areas. From then on in we get the Totentanz culture exploding, from Bosch to the early puritans, and the later witch crises. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:188.29.13.121|188.29.13.121]] ([[User talk:188.29.13.121|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/188.29.13.121|contribs]]) 09:01, 24 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

== Edit request from Mushyhuz, 13 September 2011 ==
{{resolved}}
{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Under the Title &quot;Islam&quot; the third line has the following sentence &quot;According to Muslim theology, Iblis was expelled from the grace of God when he disobeyed God by choosing not to pay homage to Adam, the father of all mankind.&quot;

Kindly Change the part the father of all mankind to the creator of all mankind. As per Islamic belief God is not the &quot;father&quot; but &quot;creator&quot; of mankind

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Mushyhuz|Mushyhuz]] ([[User talk:Mushyhuz|talk]]) 00:36, 13 September 2011 (UTC)
:I apologise if I'm mistaken, but I believe you're misreading the line.  It is Adam, not God, who is being referred to as the father of all mankind.  [[User:Adrian J. Hunter|Adrian&amp;nbsp;'''J.'''&amp;nbsp;Hunter]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Adrian J. Hunter|talk]]•[[Special:contributions/Adrian J. Hunter|contribs]])&lt;/sup&gt; 09:05, 13 September 2011 (UTC)

[[User:Mushyhuz|Mushyhuz]] ([[User talk:Mushyhuz|talk]]) 21:39, 13 September 2011 (UTC) Oh yes! you're right! sorry I didn't get that.
:No worries, easily done. {{=)}} [[User:Adrian J. Hunter|Adrian&amp;nbsp;'''J.'''&amp;nbsp;Hunter]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Adrian J. Hunter|talk]]•[[Special:contributions/Adrian J. Hunter|contribs]])&lt;/sup&gt; 00:24, 14 September 2011 (UTC)

== Edit request from TheSpoilerCeaseth, 29 September 2011 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Much &quot;Satanic&quot; lore does not originate from actual Satanists, but from Christians. Best-known would be the [[medieval]] [[folklore]] and [[theology]] surrounding [[demons]] and [[witches]]. A more recent example is the [[Satanic ritual abuse]] scare of the 1980s – beginning with the memoir ''[[Michelle Remembers]]'' – which depicts Satanism as a vast (and unsubstantiated) conspiracy of elites with a predilection for [[child abuse]] and [[human sacrifice]]. This genre regularly describes Satan as actually appearing in person in order to receive worship.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.religioustolerance.org/satanism.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

SHOULD BE CHANGED TO THE FOLLOWING:

&quot;Satanic lore&quot; originates from those who state that they worship him, and their teachers. Best-known would be the [[folklore]], and said [[theology]] surrounding [[demons]] and [[witches]]. A more recent example is the [[Satanic ritual abuse]] scare of the 1980s – beginning with the Victoria, British Columbia, Canada memoir ''[[Michelle Remembers]]'' – which depicts Satanism as a vast conspiracy of elites with a predilection for [[child abuse]] and [[human sacrifice]]. This genre could describe Satan as actually appearing in person, or spirit, in order to receive worship or voice, etc.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.religioustolerance.org/satanism.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The person of God, is, at times, depicted alongside these stories as the the final inquisitor, or as the devil himself behind the horror.

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:TheSpoilerCeaseth|Michael Anthony Furtado]] ([[User talk:TheSpoilerCeaseth|talk]]) 01:15, 29 September 2011 (UTC)

: Changing ''Much &quot;Satanic&quot; lore does not originate from actual Satanists, but from Christians.'' to ''&quot;Satanic lore&quot; originates from those who state that they worship him, and their teachers.'' would be inaccurate. --[[User:Jean Calleo|Jean Calleo]] ([[User talk:Jean Calleo|talk]]) 05:11, 29 September 2011 (UTC)

:: 1. Please substantiate with references. OTO and their ilk have done more than a certain amount to build the Wheatley-Hammer imagery of the 1960s onwards by publishing [[Aleister Crowley|Crowley]]'s works. [[Dennis Wheatley|Wheatley]] knew that circle (indeed lunched with Crowley), so that correction is sui generis indefensible. This angle should include the alchemical &quot;Massacre of the innocents&quot; which includes [[Marc Dutroux|Dutroux]] (a snitch managed by members of OTO's Abraxas sect), [[Gilles de Rais]] (who explained it), and [[Ian Huntley]], who tried to study the subject in prison.

:: 2. On the other hand, there is the well-documented contretemps that much paedophilia stems from within the Church itself, and would be instantly denied as the work of the Devil by the said body, and that the terms of reference were pretty much defined by the Christian fundamentalist wing, as you suggest. Given that the meme's reference is saliently defined by that, it becomes hard to deny the likely need to have a dualist reply covering both angles.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/188.29.13.121|188.29.13.121]] ([[User talk:188.29.13.121|talk]]) 09:24, 24 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Satan in Hinduism ==

Hinduism has also got the concept of Satan.Many people say that Hinduism is a religion without  the concept of Saitan.Every religion says the one and the same but in different manner.Hinduism says that there is existence of two things in this world.The GOOD and the EVIL.Sree Devi is a goddess in Hinduism,Where as Mu Devi is regarded as the Goddess of evil(Satan) in Hinduism.Mu Devi was once a God who became Satan later on.This Mu Devi misguides people to do ill things.Mu Devi wants people to worship her instead of worshipping God...  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/122.174.40.22|122.174.40.22]] ([[User talk:122.174.40.22|talk]]) 02:17, 22 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Hasty generalizations about religions aren't acceptable. Also, Satan is a Jewish and Christian figure. He isn't in Hinduism, but he would be in other religions which borrow from Christianity, just as Christianity borrowed from Judaism. [[User:Oct13|Oct13]] ([[User talk:Oct13|talk]]) 16:59, 3 April 2012 (UTC)

== Satan as the serpent of Eden ==

“Satan is often identified as the serpent who convinced Eve to eat the forbidden fruit; thus, Satan has often been depicted as a serpent. Though this identification is not present in the Adam and Eve narrative, this interpretation goes back at least as far as the time of the writing of the book of Revelation, which specifically identifies Satan as being the serpent (Rev. 20:2).”

Strictly speaking, is this true? As far as I can tell, Revelation doesn’t specifically identify Satan as being the same serpent who spoke to Eve in the Garden of Eden, certainly not in any translation that I’ve ever come across. Revelation could well be alluding to the serpent from Genesis but it doesn’t specifically identify Satan as being that same serpent.

Some examples of the verse in question:

“And he laid hold on the dragon, that old serpent, who is the Devil, and Satan, and bound him a thousand years.”

“He seized the dragon, that ancient serpent, who is the devil, or Satan, and bound him for a thousand years.”

“He seized the dragon, the old serpent, which is the devil and Satan, and bound him for a thousand years,”

I think that something like this would be more appropriate: Satan is often identified as the serpent who convinced Eve to eat the forbidden fruit; thus, Satan has often been depicted as a serpent. Though this identification is not present in the Adam and Eve narrative, this interpretation goes back at least as far as the time of Justin Martyr, who, in his Dialogue with Trypho, specifically identified Satan as being the serpent of Eden.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/78.148.156.230|78.148.156.230]] ([[User talk:78.148.156.230|talk]]) 22:08, 3 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Devils, plural ==

This article leaves no scope for plural &quot;devils&quot;. It's monodiabolic as [[God]] merely tends toward monotheistic (because the latter includes much discussion of gods).

[[Devils]] does not redirect here and the only plural &quot;See also&quot;, [[Hierarchy of devils]] does redirect to Classification of demons. So the second illustration with its fitting caption &quot;Devils - a fresco detail from the Rila Monastery&quot; is inappropriate for the article. --[[User:P64|P64]] ([[User talk:P64|talk]]) 16:33, 21 May 2012 (UTC)
:The line between demons and devils is blurry, so there's bound to be some overlap. This article concerns the concept of an evil antagonist to god(s), and there can be more than one. &amp;mdash; &lt;b&gt;[[User:HandThatFeeds|&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Comic Sans MS; color:DarkBlue;cursor:help&quot;&gt;The Hand That Feeds You]]&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:HandThatFeeds|Bite]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/b&gt; 17:07, 21 May 2012 (UTC)

:: The article needs some rewrite in order to fit plural lowercase &quot;devils&quot;. For example, see [[God]]. --[[User:P64|P64]] ([[User talk:P64|talk]]) 19:51, 21 May 2012 (UTC)

== Opposite of devil ==

1. what is the antonym of devil ?
2. if devils are bad then who is good ?
3. Are human beings devil ?
&lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nilakantha08|Nilakantha08]] ([[User talk:Nilakantha08|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nilakantha08|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
:The answers to those questions depends entirely on which religious tradition you're discussing.  There are different views, even within the same religion. [[User:Ian.thomson|Ian.thomson]] ([[User talk:Ian.thomson|talk]]) 22:34, 18 July 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>e4ehfyid8joo90rhe9tuk5gv1bl2u6o</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
