<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Pentecostalism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>40175</id>
    <revision>
      <id>490024560</id>
      <parentid>489757010</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-30T22:18:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ltwin</username>
        <id>5808672</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* running the aisles */ Ooops</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="47822">{{Round in circles|search=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=B|importance=Top|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=Top|charismatic-christianity=yes|core-topics-work-group = yes|core-topics-importance=Top|charismatic-christianity-importance=Top|methodism-work-group=yes|methodism-importance=Top}}
{{WPReligion|class=B|importance=Top|NRM=yes|NRMImp=High}}
}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=21:45, 1 Mar 2004
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Archived nominations/Index/June 2003 to January 2004#Pentecostalism
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=2753691

|action2=FAC
|action2date=18:01, 19 June 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Pentecostalism/archive1
|action2result=not promoted
|action2oldid=138962203

|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{archive box|
* [[Talk:Pentecostalism/Archive 1|Talk:Pentecostal]]
* [[Talk:Pentecostalism/Archive 2|2003-2008]]
* [[Talk:Pentecostalism/Archive 3|2009, 2010]]
* [[Talk:Pentecostalism/Archive 4|Archive 4]]
* [[Talk:Pentecostalism/Archive 5|Archive 5]]
}}


== Sect ==

I object to the use of the euphemism &quot;Pentecostalism is a renewal movement within Christianity&quot;. Pentecostalism is not a renewal movement, it is a sect, plain and simple. Here is the definition of sect, from Wikipedia: &quot;A sect is a group with distinctive religious, political or philosophical beliefs. Although in the past it was mostly used to refer to religious groups, it has since expanded and in modern culture can refer to any organization that breaks away from a larger one to follow a different set of rules and principles.&quot;

Under this definition, pentecostalism is a sect. My first edit was reversed under the argument that &quot;the word sect has a negative connotation&quot; (really a failed attempt at maintaining a non-neutral point of view). It is NOT Wikipedia's role to use euphemism and distortion of the truth to prevent some people being offended. If it is a sect, describe it as such.

Also, notice I used the word &quot;sect&quot;, not &quot;cult&quot;.
[[Special:Contributions/76.10.152.216|76.10.152.216]] ([[User talk:76.10.152.216|talk]]) 05:35, 13 August 2010 (UTC)

:&quot;Under this definition, pentecostalism is a sect,&quot; ~ yeah along with every other Christian tradition. It is also a movement. It is also described as a &quot;renewal&quot; movement. I see know reason to change a perfectly fine introductory sentence because one person insists on using a word which in the vernacular can sometimes carry negative connotations. [[Wikipedia:If it ain't broke, don't fix it|If it ain't broke, don't fix it]]. &quot;Renewal movement&quot; is not a euphemism. It is an accurate description. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 05:49, 13 August 2010 (UTC)

:I am not getting into an edit war with you. Put simply the word &quot;sect&quot; is not acceptable per Wikipedia guidelines. The relevant guideline is the one on  [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (words to watch)#Contentious labels|Contentious labels]]. This guideline says in part: 

::{{Quote box4
|quote  = &lt;big&gt;'''... cult, racist, perverted, sect, fundamentalist, heretic, extremist, denialist, terrorist, freedom fighter, pseudo-, -gate, controversial ...'''&lt;/big&gt;
|width  = 70%
|align  = center
}}

::&quot;Biased labels, particularly when the label is negative&amp;mdash;such as calling an organization a ''cult'', an individual a ''racist'', or a sexual practice a ''perversion''&amp;mdash;are best avoided unless widely used by reliable sources to describe the subject, in which case use in-text attribution.&quot; 

:Therefore, I will be removing the word &quot;sect&quot; from this sentence. If you would like to discuss ways to improve the on the term &quot;renewal movement&quot; I'm happy to discuss it with you. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 06:06, 13 August 2010 (UTC)

I also do not wish for an edit war. There was an edit conflict which prevented me from posting this:
::I think this whole article only describes Pentecostalism superficially, and fails to explain how Pentecostalist churches work and what are the psychological effects of Pentecostalism. Those characteristics seem to be missing in the article. Discouragement of questioning, doubt, and dissent. Mind-numbing techniques (such as speaking in tongues). Inducing guilt in order to control. Members enrolling family members; if reluctant to, ties are cut, relationships broken. Unquestioning obedience and submission to the group, both actions and thoughts. Group &quot;love&quot; and acceptance becomes dependent upon obedience and submission. etc. etc. I fear I would be unable to neutrally edit the article to convey those points, having gone through this hell myself. So I will not start an edit war. But I hope these words will remain on this talk page and may be able to help at least one person reading them.[[Special:Contributions/76.10.152.216|76.10.152.216]] ([[User talk:76.10.152.216|talk]]) 06:12, 13 August 2010 (UTC)

:::What you have to understand about Pentecostalism is that it is extremely diverse. I am sorry to here that you were hurt. I'm Pentecostal too and I've been lucky to see what true Pentecostalism looks like, where there isn't a control factor. I'm aware of Pentecostal &quot;churches&quot; which exhibit characteristics which you describe but I know of many non-Pentecostal religious groups that also have those same problems. I'm glad you are out of that situation, but I would just bare in mind that Pentecostalism is a very diverse movement and you could have two Pentecostal churches right down the street from each other and they be nothing alike. I literally experienced this when my church was at its old location. Not four lots down the street was a Pentecostal Holiness Church and my church had nothing in common with them at all. I'm not trying to convert you, I'm just saying don't put all Pentecostals in one box. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 06:22, 13 August 2010 (UTC)

::::It is true that I should be careful to not overgeneralize. But is it normal that I find no mention AT ALL in the article of the psychological abuse that goes on in at least SOME of those churches (well I can only speak for one) ? Are there no valid sources which we could include in just a section in the article ?  I admit that I must not overgeneralize, and I trust that even though you are Pentecostalist yourself, you will agree that this article should include, in a dedicated section perhaps, relevant documented cases of cult-like activities in Pentecostalism. If fact, of all people, Pentecostalists should have no objection to the frauds being denouced, as they hurt the Church's image in addition to people and families. [[Special:Contributions/76.10.152.216|76.10.152.216]] ([[User talk:76.10.152.216|talk]]) 06:39, 13 August 2010 (UTC)

:::::Do I have a problem with that? No, not necessarily. And there has not been an attempt to whitewash the article. It's just that I'm really the only editor that focuses alot of attention on this page on a regular bases and I've just never come across any studies or articles which have dealt with this. 

:::::The problem we have is how to do that in a way which 1) doesn't give undo weight, and 2) recognizes and reflects the fact that there are many individual Pentecostal congregations out there and many small fringe groups out there also. What I'm trying to say is that while there are abuses in some churches, it is not the majority of Pentecostal churches and movements. We have to distinguish between the many different Pentecostal groups out there. If for example a source were to criticize a specific denomination, then criticism should be directed to that groups article. There is also the issue of the fact that many Pentecostal groups criticize and mistrust one another. For example, many classical Pentecostals think that &quot;physical manifestations&quot; are not appropriate and may not even be Spirit directed and they do not associate with churches where those things occur. So you also have to consider fringe groups that call themselves Pentecostal but that even most Pentecostals do not associate with. 

:::::So in theory I have know problem incorporating claims made in reliable and verified sources about abuses by Pentecostal churches. But I'm adamant about it not transforming into an outrageous collection of every negative, reactionary, ignorant, and baseless assertion out there from people, especially [[cessationist]] Christians, who to this day believe that Pentecostalism is a cult. Sorry for the rant. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 19:04, 13 August 2010 (UTC)

::::::From the article: &quot;When charismatics are included with Pentecostals the number increases to nearly a quarter of the world's two billion Christians.&quot; In light of this fact, in no way can anyone justify calling Pentecost a sect or cult. If one wants to point out abberant behaviour or cultic practices, what about other groups (Seventh-Day adventists and David Koresh, or the Roman Catholic Church and pedophile priests, etc. etc.)? Does Pentecost and the Charismatic movement have problems? Surely. But I object to any attempt to degrade the movement as a whole and portray it as an illegitimate religious group. [[User:Mmlj4|Mmlj4]] ([[User talk:Mmlj4|talk]]) 17:03, 2 September 2010 (UTC)

:::::::Your argument is totally irrevelant. First, whether a single person or everyone on Earth adheres to a religion does not justify defining it as a cult* (see 3rd point below) or not. What matters is only how the movement behaves. Second, I don't understand why you mention David Koresh here. Branch Davidian is already described as a sect on Wikipedia; no one objected to the use of this word based on it's &quot;negative connotation&quot; over there. * Third, the objection to an attempt to degrade the movement as a whole is understandable, but that is no longer my intention. Please re-read the previous paragraphs. After discussion with Ltwin, I have suggested that a dedicated section somewhere in the article address the psychosocial problematics I have explained here, that are found in some Pentecostalism churches. In no way does that equate portraying the whole of Pentecostalism to a cult. [[Special:Contributions/76.10.161.207|76.10.161.207]] ([[User talk:76.10.161.207|talk]]) 09:30, 20 September 2010 (UTC)

::::::::Whether ''sect'' is used in those articles are irrelevant as well and a violation of Wikipedia guidelines on contentious labels. Also it doesn't make since in this article anyway where the opening paragraph clearly defines what Pentecostalism is anyway. The word doesn't really offer any definition that is missing from the article currently—except a negative connotation. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 20:19, 20 September 2010 (UTC)

:::::::::I fail to understand why we are still discussing this. Our discussion was going on good terms. Mmlj4 percieved a threat, specifically an attempt to degrade Pentecostalism as a whole. My answer to him was to illustrate that it was not my intention. With your agreement, I wish to re-center the discussion on the previous point you brough up; let's drop the whole &quot;sect&quot; debate. We were discussing about the possibility of adressing certain issues with regard to certain practices already enumerated occuring in some Pentecostalist churches. If I understood Ltwin correctly, he/she agrees to a Criticism section provided it is properly sourced and is not given undue weight. Now, knowing that we all, myself included, do not wish to engage in baseless religion-bashing, and that such a section in the article would not negatively portray Pentecostalism as a whole but instead allow people to better differentiate and understand the extent of the variety in rituals, norms and practices within a subset of Pentecostalist churches, it could only positively contribute to the article. But, it could also go against your personal interpretation of the Church's practices. Still, Mmlj4, do you agree to the inclusion of such a section in the article ? [[Special:Contributions/76.10.156.172|76.10.156.172]] ([[User talk:76.10.156.172|talk]]) 05:01, 21 September 2010 (UTC)

::::::::::SECT: I can understand why some people would want to call Pentecostalism a 'sect' and I am well aware that there are a great deal of people who have had very negative experiences in such churches, however Pentecostalism is a widespread branch of Christianity.  I have personal experience of cult like behaviour in 2 pentecostal churches however it is also fair to say that any denomonation within Christendom could also have abusive leaders.  Recent teachings from the New Apostolic Reformation should rightly be seen as heretical because they are inconsistent with what the church has taught and practiced for 1900 years. [Unsigned comment by [[Special:Contributions/124.180.115.15|User:124.180.115.15]] 14:49, 26 April 2011]

:Calling Pentecostalism a &quot;sect&quot; is problematic for two reasons:
:*''&quot;sect&quot;'' means a partial or full split-off from another mainstream Christianity, what is &quot;mainstream&quot; in Christianity? &quot;Mainstream&quot; is IMHO [[WP:POV|a biased view]] – my current stand point is that each and every denomination whatsoever in '''Christianity''' is heterodox from at least one another denomination,
:*''&quot;sect&quot;'' '''have''' a connotation &quot;destructive&quot; which in extreme cases translates to &quot;cult&quot;,
:''&quot;renewal movement&quot;'' is more neutral, and ''a little'' true unless it emerged as a way within one self-labeled &quot;orthodox&quot; Christianity to remove deviations and conserve the system so that no changes could be made. English (and any natural language) is not precise enough to allow us to create more precise nominal phrases than that, especially in the bewildered sphere of religion, where misleading catch-phrases are as numerous as in the computer market. [[User:Rursus|Rursus]] dixit. ([[User talk:Rursus|&lt;span style=&quot;color: red; background: #FFFF80&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;u&gt;bork&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]!) 09:51, 15 December 2011 (UTC)

::I agree, &quot;renewal movement&quot; is a perfectly accurate term. It's even used by people who study the movement, such as the [[http://pewforum.org/Christian/Evangelical-Protestant-Churches/Spirit-and-Power.aspx Pew Forum's survey on Pentecostalism]]. It was removed to accommodate one user's objections. I'll add it back in. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 17:12, 15 December 2011 (UTC)

::: The same Wikipedia article quoted at the start of this section states 'The historical usage of the term sect in Christendom has had pejorative connotations, referring to a group or movement with heretical beliefs or practices that deviate from those of groups considered orthodox.' Some parts of the Christian mainstream church consider pentecostalism to be a sect (possibly inferred by Pope Benedict's comments &quot;Faced with a new form of Christianity, which is spreading with overpowering missionary dynamism, sometimes in frightening ways, the mainstream Christian denominations often seem at a loss....This is a form of Christianity with little institutional depth, little rationality and even less dogmatic content, and with little stability. This worldwide phenomenon poses a question to us all: what is this new form of Christianity saying to us, for better and for worse?&quot;)  - which is rather ironic considering the early church was considered to be a Jewish sect (&quot;But we desire to hear from you what you think; for concerning this sect, we know that it is spoken against everywhere&quot;).  Given the WP article definition then the use of 'cult' in the context of this article has the potential to be read and considered as a POV statement and should be avoided. Form, Movement, style, .... &lt;font color=&quot;#009000&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;cursor: w-resize&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;[[User:Johnmarkh|johnmark†]][[User talk:Johnmarkh|talk to me]]&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 00:33, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

==Tongues and Salvation==
[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Pentecostalism&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=387958236&amp;oldid=387891919I reverted this edit from Topsaint]. His edit was sourced; however, he has misunderstood the sources he cites. Let me explain. He cited [http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/Pentecostalism.aspx#1O95-Pentecostalism The Concise Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church]; however, I read nothing which states that Pentecostals view tongues or a Pentecostal-like baptism experience as necessary or essential to salvation. The closest thing I can see is the following, &quot;Its adherents emphasize the corporate element in worship (often marked by great spontaneity) and '''lay stress on the practice of the gifts''' listed in 1 Cor. 12 and 14 and recorded Acts (e.g. '''speaking in tongues or glossolalia''', divine [spiritual] healing, and exorcism) '''and on possession of these gifts by all true believers'''.&quot; Of course &quot;lay stress on . . . possession of these gifts&quot; is not the same thing as saying &quot;you must have these gifts to be saved.&quot;

Topsaint also cited Arrington's Pneuma article. On page 1-2, he writes, &quot;In one sense, every believer has the presence of the Holy Spirit. . . . One cannot be a Christian without having the Spirit, which is the same as being indwelt by the Spirit.&quot; The conclusion of the article on page 9 states:

:&quot;There is a real sense in which regenerated persons have the Spirit. To be indwelt by the Spirit at regeneration is one thing, but to be baptized or filled with the Spirit is quite another. Regeneration is accompanied by the indwelling presence of the Holy Spirit, but being filled with the Spirit is distinct from His previous work in regeneration. Viewed in its inception the fulness of the Spirit must be considered as the initial &quot;filling&quot; with ''glossolalia'' as the normative sign of the experience.&quot;

Therefore, Arrington clearly distinguishes being indwelt by the Spirit which is the state of every regenerated or saved person and being filled with the Spirit which is the state of those who have received the Pentecostal baptism in the Holy Spirit. Tell me where that says that one is not regenerated unless having been baptized with the Spirit or having spoken in tongues? [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 18:52, 30 September 2010 (UTC)

==&quot;''Singing'' in the Spirit&quot; vs &quot;''Speaking'' in the Spirit&quot;==
I hope not to offend but I changed &quot;singing in tongues&quot; to &quot;speaking in tongues&quot;.[[User:Marrik666|Marrik666]] ([[User talk:Marrik666|talk]]) 17:33, 14 October 2010 (UTC)

:You didn't offend. This is the encyclopedia that anyone can edit. However, I was interested in the change. I reverted it back to &quot;singing in the spirit&quot; as this is a term that has been mentioned in academic sources and a term that I as a Pentecostal have heard used. I've never heard or read of corporate singing in tongues referred to as &quot;speaking&quot;. That would be grammatically nonsensical. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 18:06, 14 October 2010 (UTC)

I understand but I've been raised Pentacostal since I was 3. In my family and church, it was always refered to as &quot;speaking&quot; in tongues after the experience in the upper room in the book Acts. I think it was chapter 2. The whole tongues of fire thing. Please respond.[[User:Marrik666|Marrik666]] ([[User talk:Marrik666|talk]]) 00:36, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

:Yes when one &quot;speaks&quot; in tongues it is referred to as speaking in tongues. What is being referred to is a practice which is not &quot;speaking&quot; but &quot;singing&quot;—literally singing in tongues. It has been referred to as &quot;singing in the Spirit&quot; since [[Azusa Street]]. This term has been used by Pentecostals as much as speaking in tongues has. Cecil M. Robeck Jr. in ''The Azusa Street Mission and Revival: The Birth of the Global Pentecostal Movement'' provides good descriptions of singing in the Spirit. Pages 151-152 he quotes Arthur Osterberg who gives the following description:

:{{quote|We would all sing a song or chorus, and everyone would join in. Then choruses would break out here and there, and some would be singing in tongues and some in English – and the harmony was wonderful. Once in a while a soprano voice would leap out and you would hear it above the whole congregation. Then it would be mingled with other voices and it all formed a beautiful harmony. Then the singing would stop short and everyone would start praising the Lord, some speaking in an undertone in tongues, some clapping their hands in praise to God. No one who has ever heard a congregation singing under the unction of the Spirit could ever forget or mistake it.}}

:In the same pages, Robeck quotes a news reporter,

:{{quote|A colored woman with the voice of a Patti began singing in a tongue which probably never before was heard. Her voice was joined by a contralto of great depth and richness, but singing another tongue. Others took up the chant, each after her own tune and ‘tongues,’ till the building was vocal with the tones of golden mellowness. They say that the Holy Ghost tunes their voices.}}

:On page 149, Robeck says it goes by different name: &quot;singing in the Spirit&quot;, &quot;singing in tongues&quot;, the &quot;heavenly anthem&quot;, the &quot;heavenly chorus&quot; or &quot;heavenly choir&quot;, and the &quot;chorus of tongues&quot;.

:Please also note 1 Corinthians 14:15, &quot;So what shall I do? I will pray with my spirit, but I will also pray with my mind; ''I will sing with my spirit, but I will also sing with my mind''.&quot; Also note that what his happening is corporate ''singing'' in tongues. It's not simply speaking in tongues. Hope that helps. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 02:31, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

:Something that may also interest you is a practice which occurred in the [[early Christian church]] beginning from the 4th century with the decline of the vocal gifts of the spirit in the church to the 9th century. It was called ''jubilation'' and [[St. Augustine]] describes it this way:

:{{quote|
*What is jubilation? Joy that cannot be expressed in words. Yet the voice expresses what is conceived in the heart and cannot be explained in words. This is jubilation.
*To manifest his joy, the man does not use words that can be pronounced or understood, but bursts forth into sounds of exaltation without words.
*Where speech does not suffice… they break out into singing on vowel sounds, that through this means the feeling of the soul may be expressed, words failing to explain the heart’s conceptions.&quot;}}

:For more on ''jubilation'', see [http://www.sfspirit.org/articles/9709/article1.htm here]. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 03:07, 17 December 2010 (UTC)

Maybe we should just say &quot;also called speaking&quot; to the article? That sounds reasonable to me.[[User:Marrik666|Marrik666]] ([[User talk:Marrik666|talk]]) 23:42, 18 January 2011 (UTC)
Also read Acts chapter 2 I think.[[User:Marrik666|Marrik666]] ([[User talk:Marrik666|talk]]) 18:51, 19 February 2011 (UTC)

== Eschatological beliefs ==

What percentage of pentecostals prescribe to the doctorine of [[dispensationalism]]? If it's rather high, I believe it should be included in the article. --'''[[User:Confession0791|Confession0791]]''' '''[[User_talk:Confession0791|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]''' 07:04, 10 November 2010 (UTC)

:Generally, Pentecostals do believe in dispensationalism, if by that you mean that God deals with humanity in different ways at different times and that this current dispensation, that of the church, is soon coming to an end. It will culminate with the rapture of the church and the seven year tribulation followed by the millennial reign of Christ. If that's what you mean then yeah. I would think its almost pretty universal among classical Pentecostals. However, not all Pentecostals are members of classical denominations and their beliefs can be quite diverse, but many non-classicals adhere to dispensationalism also. Pentecostals have historically emphasized that the revival of [[spiritual gifts]] was a sign of the end times, but this has lessened with the passage of time. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 07:19, 10 November 2010 (UTC)
::How can that be included in the article? --'''[[User:Confession0791|Confession0791]]''' '''[[User_talk:Confession0791|&lt;sup&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]]''' 07:23, 10 November 2010 (UTC)

:::I added a brief statement at the end of the &quot;Beliefs and practices&quot; section. Pentecostal eschatology probably does deserve its own section because it was central to the beginning of the movement and still is an important part of Pentecostal identity. Pentecostalism was born at a time when there was high expectancy that Christ would soon return. Its missionary emphasis derives from this belief. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 07:29, 10 November 2010 (UTC)

== Possible gaps ==

Could someone write something about the importance of Pentecostalism in Africa, and its continuing growth there? Same goes for Brazil and the Caribbean.

Perhaps the obvious needs to be stated more strongly - within the United States and the UK (and other territories?) Pentecostal congregations often draw many or most of their members from the black community of the country.

Could someone also comment on attitudes to material prosperity in Pentecostalism? I can't recollect any source, but I've read/heard that even in early Pentecostalism there was a strong belief in the pursuit of material success, presumably through - in varying proportions - industriousness on the part of the believer, and compliance with the will of God in the expectation that blessings would follow. That's not to say that undiluted Prosperity Theology is the norm within Pentecostalism, of course.

(As a secular being, I'd humbly suggest that the belief in Doing Well might be expected to appeal to a segment of society that 100 years ago was largely poor and routinely mistreated. I add that as something to be considered for article purposes - not to provoke.)

Regards to all,
[[User:Notreallydavid|Notreallydavid]] ([[User talk:Notreallydavid|talk]]) 06:25, 24 March 2011 (UTC)

:Hi, wow you've brought up alot. 
:1) One of the problems is the highly confused categories of global charismatic Christianity today. Should this article be about classical Pentecostalism or also include non-classical movements that have more in common with charismatic groups? But you are right, global Pentecostalism needs to be better included in this article.
:2) I'm not sure your assertion that (in the United States at least) that Pentecostalism is primarily a black movement. I think much of this stereotype comes from the differences in worship culture of white and black Pentecostal churches. White Pentecostals tend to have less emotional services and may place less emphasis on their Pentecostal affiliation which gives the impression that they are a generic evangelical non-denominational church. Perhaps we should consider creating specific pages for each country's movement, such as [[Pentecostalism in the United Kingdom]]?
:3) Your point about material prosperity is interesting. From what I've read, there was not a &quot;a strong belief in the pursuit of material success.&quot; In fact, there was often an assumption that po:verty implied greater spirituality. However, there was a definite belief that the believer should be diligent and &quot;industrious&quot; when it came to spreading the Gospel. It was taught that if one stepped out in faith to evangelize, do missionary work, or to pursue a preaching ministry that God would provide the funds and supplies that one needed. This is one reason why many early Pentecostal evangelists did not ask for funds but relied on unsolicited donations.
:There was always a strong belief that God would keep his promises and that he would provide for his people, but this is not the same as saying that prosperity theology as it is known today was taught from the beginning. The fact is that the majority of the early Pentecostals were from the lower classes. What they meant by &quot;God will meet my needs&quot; was quite different than what you hear today. The classical Pentecostals have quite strongly disapproved of the prosperity gospel. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 15:48, 24 March 2011 (UTC)
:I intend to work on this article more. I'm focusing on the Beliefs section right now, but this article definitely needs a History section of greater quality. Feel free to help improve the article. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 15:48, 24 March 2011 (UTC)

==Revised &quot;Salvation&quot; section==
I have revised the &quot;Salvation&quot; section. However, in doing so I wondered should the two teachings on sanctification be included in this section or should it be explained in the &quot;Classical Pentecostalism&quot; section which explains the difference between Wesleyan and non-Wesleyan Pentecostalism? What do others think? [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 01:09, 31 March 2011 (UTC)

==NPOV dispute==
This article needs substantial work. The claims of believers should be stated as claims, not facts. [[User:Ptet|Ptet]] ([[User talk:Ptet|talk]]) 09:05, 27 January 2012 (UTC)

:There is no NPOV violations. I will comment on each of your changes one by one.
:1) Pentecostalism is a renewal movement[1] within Christianity that places special emphasis on '''what believers say is''' a direct personal experience of God through the baptism in the Holy Spirit, has an eschatological focus, and is an experiential religion.[2] 
::It is not necessary to say &quot;what believers say is&quot; because Wikipedia never says &quot;this direct personal experience of God is real.&quot; We are describing a religion which places emphasis on a direct personal experience of God. There is no judgement as to whether such an experience is real or psychological or divine or whatever. 
:2)Pentecostalism's emphasis on '''what it claims are &quot;spiritual gifts&quot;''' places it within Charismatic Christianity, a broad grouping of Christians who have accepted some Pentecostal teachings on Spirit baptism and spiritual gifts. 
::First, &quot;spiritual gifts&quot; should not be in quotation marks. It is a theological term and category widely used. Second, while we should say &quot;Pentecostals claim/believe spiritual gifts are real and from God,&quot; it is unnecessary to use claim/believe in this instance because all that is being commented on is the emphasis that Pentecostals place on the theological topic of spiritual gifts. That is not in doubt. No one doubts that Pentecostals place an emphasis on spiritual gifts as defined by Pentecostals and the wider Christian theological community. 
::Think about it this way. Wikipedia would never say at [[Catholicism]], &quot;Catholicism's emphasis on '''what it claims are sacraments''' place it within sacramental Christianity.&quot; Encyclopedias never phrase things like this. In fact, you have now created an actual NPOV violation because you are making a judgement as to whether Catholics actually have sacraments! 
:3)While '''the figure of Jesus''' Christ and his '''claimed''' redemptive work are at the center of Pentecostal theology, that redemptive work is believed to provide for a fullness of the Holy Spirit of which believers in Christ may take advantage.
::While I don't have a problem with the phrase &quot;the figure of Jesus Christ,&quot; I don't understand why you insert &quot;claimed&quot; here. Must we put a &quot;claim&quot; after every religious statement, even when there is no judgement being made as to whether something is true or not. We can say, &quot;Pentecostals believe in the redemptive work of Jesus Christ&quot; without implying that the redemptive work of Jesus Christ is something real or verifiable. What is verifiable is that Pentecostals believe it. We cannot verify the redemptive work of Christ, but we what Pentecostals believe. 
:Adding &quot;believes&quot; or &quot;claims&quot; after every descriptive statement just for the fact of proving a point is repetitive, ridiculous and destructive to prose. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 19:07, 27 January 2012 (UTC)

::I disagree. I am not expecting every claim of Pentacostalism to be preceded by &quot;claimed&quot; or something equivalent - it is the tone of the writing which is not neutral. There is also nothing in this article about any controversies surrounding pentecostalism - which surely are notable. (There is this quote left without comment or challenge: &quot;Some most remarkable miracles have been reported from the use of this method.&quot; Which healings are these?). Hopefully someone with more time than I can do some work on this. You are welcome to disagree - and perhaps to take care of my concerns by adding a controversies section? [[User:Ptet|Ptet]] ([[User talk:Ptet|talk]]) 17:23, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

::::That sentence &quot;Some most remarkable miracles have been reported from the use of this method,&quot; is found within a large quote which is not even talking about &quot;proof&quot; that miracles accompany prayer cloths. That quote is describing the Pentecostal practice of using prayer cloths. Why would we exclude from the article the fact that Pentecostals believe that things like prayer and prayer cloths can produce miracles? No one is saying that they do. We are only saying that Pentecostals believe they do. Why would we need to find examples of proof of these miracles when we aren't trying to prove that it happens? Once again, we are only describing that Pentecostals believe they happen! [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 18:52, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

:::There is a &quot;controversies&quot; subsection in the Early revivals section. I don't know what other controversies there would need to be added. Within Christianity, Pentecostalism is widely accepted today by non-Pentecostals. And outside of Christianity, people are going to have disagreements with Christianity in general. --[[User:Musdan77|Musdan77]] ([[User talk:Musdan77|talk]]) 17:46, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

You are &quot;not aware&quot; of any controversies surrounding modern Pentecostalism?  Perhaps [[Google|http://www.google.co.uk/search?q=pentecostalism+controversial]] can help. If you really are &quot;not aware&quot; of this, fair enough, but I hope we can therefore agree this article needs more work. [[User:Ptet|Ptet]] ([[User talk:Ptet|talk]]) 18:50, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

:So basically you are saying that the article is non-neutral because we haven't written what you want us to? Should we be able to read your mind?? This is the encyclopedia that anyone can edit. What controversies would you put in the article? What controversies are you talking about. A movement as vast as Pentecostalism surely has many controversies. So what is it that you want put in the article??? [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 18:54, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

No, this article is non-neutral because it has been written (from what I can see) by Pentacostals with no interest in providing relevant information which might show the movement in a less-than-flattering light. I'll make some suggested changes I hope next week when I have the time, but the type of things you might like to cover if you wish are (a) the recent research on speaking in tongues which shows that it is similar across many non-Christian traditions; (b) controversies over &quot;aggressive&quot; proselytising from within the movement, especially in Asia and South America; (c) controversies over claims of claimed faith healings; and (d) arguments within the movement over perceived &quot;modernisation&quot;. &quot;A movement as vast as Pentecostalism surely has many controversies.&quot; Indeed - so let this article deal with them, even in summary. [[User:Ptet|Ptet]] ([[User talk:Ptet|talk]]) 19:16, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

:If you think the article lacks in an area, you write about that topic. You don't slap a NPOV tag on an article accusing editors of bias. Maybe we are writing based on the sources we are aware of and the interests we have. No one is stopping you from editing the article, however, nitpicking over including words such as &quot;claim&quot; and &quot;believe&quot; in every sentence does not improve the article. 
:(a) there is an article on [[speaking in tongues]] where this can be (and is) discussed. This article is about Pentecostalism, not about other religions. 
:(b) ok as long as the contributions follow [[WP:Verifiability]], [[WP:No original research]], and [[WP:Reliable Sources]] then go for it. 
:(c) once again, go for it as long as it follows Wikipedia guidelines
:(d) once again, go for it as long as it follows Wikipedia guidelines.
:Please, can we stop with the accusations of editor bias. This article is a work in progress, can it be better? Yeah. Is it complete? Not really. The parts of the history section are a mess. Your proposal b could go in the &quot;Denominations and adherents&quot; section or even the history section or we could expand the eschatology section to cover the missiological emphasis of Pentecostalism and the consequences this has via &quot;aggressive&quot; proselytism. Your proposal c would fit nicely in the section on divine healing. Your proposal d would be a good addition to the later part of the history sections. I think the sections on speaking in tongues could mention briefly the similarities with other religions, but it should not be voluminous as there is an article on [[speaking in tongues]] which can cover this. We can work together, you don't have to label the article as POV crap to get things done. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 20:09, 28 January 2012 (UTC)

Thanks for your thoughtful comments. I do think that the POV question is valid - some of this article reads (no offence) like a brochure - but we're all here to pull together so I'll remove my POV for now and make changes to the main article when I get the chance - unless someone else wants to have a go. Pentecostalism is a fascinating movement followed by many millions of people, and I'm sure it deserves a more knowledgable person than me to add to what is already a through and interesting entry here. [[User:Ptet|Ptet]] ([[User talk:Ptet|talk]]) 11:05, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

:Can you tell what parts sound like a &quot;brochure&quot; to you? [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 14:06, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

The first sentences of the first and third paragraphs, for example. Without quite a bit of background knowledge, I think they read like jargon.The section &quot;Baptism with the Holy Spirit&quot; reads like one of those articles by a corporation which tells me how great the corporation is. The sentence &quot;Some of these are immediate while others are enduring or permanent&quot; repeats a claim of Pentacostals as fact. The section on &quot;Tongues and interpretation&quot; tells me what Pentacostals claim without any background or even neutral information. In fact, skimming through it now much of it reads like an &quot;introduction to Pentacostalism&quot;, not an encyclopaedia article. That said, the article is packed with information which is a good thing - it is (to me) not written in a neutral, encyclopaedic tone. Compare and contrast the entry on &quot;Islam&quot;.It's packed with information and (again to me) has a neutral tone and does not sound like it's a Muslim telling me the history of his religion. I appreciate &quot;tone&quot; is often subjective - but that's why  we have the gift of POV flags and talk pages. Seriously, I am not criticising the formidable knowledge of the subject of Pentacostalism that the authors of this article show, nor their sincerity in getting that information across... I just don't see that the article is as neutral and as balanced as one expects from Wikipedia. [[User:Ptet|Ptet]] ([[User talk:Ptet|talk]]) 20:02, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

::For the Spirit Baptism section, I read that sentence you point out together with the preceding sentence which says, &quot;'''Pentecostals expect''' certain results following baptism with the Holy Spirit.&quot; Then follows the sentence, &quot;Some of these are immediate while others are enduring or permanent.&quot; So, any qualification to the second sentence would sort of be redundant since the results being mentioned have already been placed within Pentecostal expectations. At least that is the way I read it. 
::Concerning the &quot;Tongues and Interpretation&quot; section, you write, &quot;The section on &quot;Tongues and interpretation&quot; tells me what Pentacostals claim without any background or even neutral information.&quot; Exactly what &quot;background&quot; should be provided? What would be &quot;neutral information&quot; besides what is already mentioned? [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 06:10, 30 January 2012 (UTC)

:On that opening sentence, I tend to agree about the technical terminology (I avoid the loaded word &quot;jargon&quot;).  The lead of a WP article should aim to communicate with the general reader, so should aim for clarity, even at the risk of loss of some precision at that point.  It currently says:
::&quot;Pentecostalism is a renewal movement within Christianity that places special emphasis on a direct personal experience of God through the baptism in the Holy Spirit, has an eschatological focus, and is an experiential religion.&quot;
:I would propose reducing it to something like:
::&quot;Pentecostalism is a renewal movement within Christianity that places special emphasis on a direct personal experience of God through the baptism in the Holy Spirit.&quot;
:so avoiding the obscure (to the general reader) terms &quot;eschatological&quot; and &quot;experiential&quot; in the article lead.

:Regarding glossolalia: I was surprised that the term was not wikilinked to the WP article.  I've corrected that, linking it twice: the first occurrence in the article (standard WP policy) and the first occurrence within the section that primarily deals with the topic.

:Ptet mentions &quot;...the recent research on speaking in tongues which shows that it is similar across many non-Christian traditions&quot;.  That's why I've made the links above.  (I'm sure the previous omissions of the wikilinks are simply oversights.)  But I'm also curious to Ptet's mention of such research being recent.  I'm no expert whatsoever on these matters; but I had thought that the presence of glossolalia in other religions was well-established ages ago.  The [[glossolalia]] article itself covers this.  (Actually, it probably doesn't cover it very well!  But that's a topic for its talk page, rather than this one.) [[User:Feline Hymnic|Feline Hymnic]] ([[User talk:Feline Hymnic|talk]]) 23:09, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

::Ptet has drawn attention to the third paragraph (beginning &quot;Pentecostalism's emphasis on the spiritual gifts...&quot;).  Myself, I didn't see anything particularly jargon-like in them.  But I do worry about another aspect.  The terms &quot;charismatic&quot;, &quot;pentecostalism&quot; and &quot;pentecostal&quot; (particularly when that last is viewed in its denominational meaning) are overlapping but considerably different.  So the quoting of numbers of adherents needs to be done carefully to avoid confusion.  Even the BBC reference, not itself the origin of the figures, has some confusion of terminology within itself, stating &quot;During the last three decades of the twentieth century Pentecostalism grew very strongly and there are now over 250 million Pentecostals around the world.&quot;  Are their &quot;Pentecostalism&quot; and &quot;Pentecostal&quot; words describing the same thing?  To which does their figure of &quot;250 million&quot; really apply?  So I would suggest that this third paragraph could benefit from revision.  Does it need to say anything at all about numbers?  (Probably it should.) If so, what entity or entities should it try to enumerate?  Pentecostal denominations?  Pentecostalism?  Charismatic adherents (whatever that means)?  ...  [[User:Feline Hymnic|Feline Hymnic]] ([[User talk:Feline Hymnic|talk]]) 23:26, 29 January 2012 (UTC)

:::&quot;I would propose reducing it to something like: 'Pentecostalism is a renewal movement within Christianity that places special emphasis on a direct personal experience of God through the baptism in the Holy Spirit.' so avoiding the obscure (to the general reader) terms 'eschatological' and 'experiential' in the article lead.&quot;
:::'''Agree''' (1) Most Christian denominations believe in eschatology -- one way or another. It's not something that's exclusive to Pentecostalism. But if it is going to be there, it should be linked to [[Christian eschatology]]. (2) I've never heard the phrase &quot;experiential religion&quot; in my life, and nowhere in that article does it mention Pentecostalism or Charismaticism. --[[User:Musdan77|Musdan77]] ([[User talk:Musdan77|talk]]) 00:59, 30 January 2012 (UTC)

::::I agree that the lead sentence could be simplified. About the numbers, it is confusing because today there is so much overlap between Pentecostal and charismatics. The BBC reference isn't exactly the best source for this anyway. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 06:10, 30 January 2012 (UTC)

:OK. I've just simplified the opening sentence.  And I'm just about to remove the numbers thing also.  Not only does the BBC reference seem somewhat ambiguous, but the &quot;Pew Forum&quot; reference seems to be very vague in what, in reality, is being enumerated. [[User:Feline Hymnic|Feline Hymnic]] ([[User talk:Feline Hymnic|talk]]) 22:00, 31 January 2012 (UTC)

==Fundamentalism category==

Someone, not me, added a category fundamentalism and had this reverted today. Pentecostalism is not fundamentalism, but there are as clear associations between the two labels as between the christian right label and pentecostalism that has been  allowed. What is the rationale for removing that label? Should we also remove Christian Right for the same reason?

Well, first off, Pentecostals are not Fundamentalists. There are clear differences. As to why it was removed, I don't know since I was not the editor to remove it. However, I can give two reasons on my own:

1) If we were to add it, we should at least get the article right. It should be [[Christian Fundamentalism]].
2) [[Christian Fundamentalism]] is already linked in the section 1930-1959. Therefore, there is no point in adding the term to the See also section. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 14:07, 5 April 2012 (UTC)

: Fair enough if it is already linked, I did not check that. However whilst I noted that Pentecostals are not Fundamentalists, I have known a significant number of pentecostals who do claim the label for themselves. It seems no more inappropriate than &quot;Christian Right&quot; which is also a label many claim for themselves, although many pentecostals are very far from the right wing of politics. Anyhow, as we have the link you mention, I will pipe down now.
[[User:Sirfurboy|Sirfurboy]] ([[User talk:Sirfurboy|talk]]) 17:19, 5 April 2012 (UTC)

==running the aisles==

A revert of an edit that removed redundancy looks odd to me. The text reads:

The &quot;[[running the aisles]]&quot; and the &quot;Jericho march&quot; are also traditional Pentecostal practices. The Jericho march, a form of corporate worship, involves a congregation marching with loud shouts of prayer and singing.&lt;ref name=Crossroads85-86&gt;Poloma, Margaret M. ''The Assemblies of God at the Crossroads'', pg. 85-86.&lt;/ref&gt; Another practice in some Pentecostal churches is [[running the aisles]].

i.e. first sentence has &quot;the running the aisles... is also a traditional...&quot; and last sentence &quot;another practis ... is running the aisles&quot;. That is redundant. If you wish to separate running the aisles from the jericho march, the first one should go. I will make that edit now.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Sirfurboy|Sirfurboy]] ([[User talk:Sirfurboy|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Sirfurboy|contribs]]) 09:28, 29 April 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Oops. I edit this page all the time and cant' believe I missed that! I only saw the removal of running the aisles and assumed the editor was saying that the Jericho march and running the aisles were the exact same thing! Anyway, I have no problem with your edit. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 22:18, 30 April 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>eq1hf3kbpkhzm7f0jxy3vmppzq98eju</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
