<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Mysticism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>106514</id>
    <revision>
      <id>494050533</id>
      <parentid>493952458</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-23T21:13:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John Carter</username>
        <id>3358555</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Top importance for Religion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22866">{{Talk header}}
{{User:WildBot/m04|sect={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Tao Te Ching#Translations of the title|te, de}}|m04}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{Spirituality project|class=B|importance=High}}
{{WPReligion|class=B|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|importance=mid|class=c|religion=yes}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=B|category=Philrelig|coresup=yes|VA=yes|WPCD=yes}}}}

==Archives==

*[[/Archive 1]]

==To Do list ==
{{todo|1}}

==Essay &quot;Overview&quot; moved here from article, possibly contains usable fragments==

&quot;'''Overview'''&quot; 
{{original research|date=September 2011}}
Mysticism, referred to as [[spirituality]] in the [[Catholic Church]], refers to beliefs and practices that go beyond the liturgical and devotional forms of worship of mainstream faith, often by seeking out inner or [[esoteric]] meanings of conventional religious doctrine, and by engaging in spiritual practices such as breathing practices, prayer, contemplation and meditation, along with chanting and other activities designed to heighten spiritual awareness. For example, [[Kabbalah]] (based in [[Judaism]]) seeks out deeper interpretations of the [[Torah]] and other mystical works, and may conduct spiritual practices based in [[Meditation]], [[Theurgy]], or [[Alchemy]], as well as song, dance, prayer, and talmudic study, accordingly, as is done in many other mystical traditions. [[Sufism]] (in [[Islam]]) extends and amplifies the teachings of the [[Quran]], most famously through their devotional musicians dancing Zhikrs and singing Qawwalis. [[Vedanta]] reaches for the inner teachings of Hindu philosophy encapsulated in the [[Vedas]], and many students of both Shaivite Tantric schools within Hinduism, as well as Shakta Tantrics, along with usually more mainstream-oriented Vaisnaivas, will use the symbolism and mythologies of their gods and goddessess, to take the initiate home to their highest awareness, via mystical practices designed and proven for these purposes. Often mysticisms center on the teachings of individuals who are considered to have special [[insight]], and in some cases entire non-mystical (doctrine-based) faiths have arisen around these leaders and their teachings, with few or no mystical practitioners remaining.

Mystics hold that there is a fundamental, indescribable essence, a No-Thing That Is All Things, the Unmanifested that manifests the Manifested; and that it underlies and gives birth to all the phenomena (realities) of our existence. (In physics, it is called a field, in Taosim, the Tao, in Hinduism, Brahman, in Christianity, God.  This One Being exists behind or beneath the observable, day-to day world of phenomena, and that in fact the ordinary world is superficial or [[epiphenomenal]]. 

Different faiths have differing relationships to mystical thought. Hinduism has many mystical sects, in part due to its historic reliance on gurus (individual teachers of insight) for transmission of its philosophy. Mysticism in Buddhism is largely monastic, since most Buddhists consider [[jhana]] (meditation) to be an advanced technique used only after many lifetimes.&lt;ref&gt;Alexander Wynne, ''The origin of Buddhist meditation''. Routledge, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  Mysticism in [[Abrahamic religion]]s is largely marginalized, from the tolerance mainstream Muslims grant to Sufism to the active fears of [[cult]]ism prevalent among western Christians, with Chasidic Kabbalists of Judaism being the notable exceptions. Mystics generally hold to some form of [[immanence]], since their focus on direct realization obviates many concerns about the afterlife, and this often conflicts with conventional religious doctrines. Mystical teachings are passed down through transmission from teacher to student, though the relationship between student and teacher varies: some groups require strict obedience to a teacher,  others carefully guard teachings until students are deemed to be ready, in others a teacher is merely a guide aiding the student in the process.  However, none of the truly Great Mystics ever require strict obedience, knowing that that interferes both with the fundamental nature of the spirit as free, and with the development within the student of his own wisdom and power of discernment.  

Mysticism may make use of canonical and non-canonical religious texts, and will generally interpret them [[hermeneutic]]ally, developing a philosophical perspective distinct from conventional religious interpretations. Many forms of mysticism in the modern world will adapt or adopt texts from entirely different faiths&amp;mdash;[[Vivekananda]] in Vedanta, for instance, is noted for his assertions that all religions are one. As a rule, mysticisms are less concerned with religious differences and more concerned with individual development. What mysticism is most concerned with, however, is having the most effective set of practices to attain enlightened consciousness and union with God. Not much else beyond this matters to a dedicated mystic, who focuses on the inner realms: mind-breath, non-thinking awareness, and so on. Mystics are not too concerned with the opinions or the religious tools of their more conservative religious compatriots. For a true mystic, the important thing is his results in achieving his mystical goals.

::::: end of 'Overview' essay ---
::::: feel free to recycle any of it (find refs, structure with headings, write coherent prose) [[User:Chiswick Chap|Chiswick Chap]] ([[User talk:Chiswick Chap|talk]]) 09:06, 28 October 2011 (UTC)

==Mysticism in Buddhism (again, undue weight at the moment, could be re-added if other religions' have similar sections==

Buddhism includes a vast array of scriptures, beliefs, traditions and practices. Many of these are not overtly mystical. Yet, some doctrines within Mahayana and Tantric Buddhism have a strong flavour of mysticism. Pre-eminent amongst these are the teachings of [[Dzogchen]] and of the [[Tathagatagarbha]]. Both of these doctrines indicate the presence of a hidden, deathless core reality within each being&amp;mdash;variously called the [[Buddha Nature]], Buddha Matrix,  Awakened Mind, Mind Essence, Dzogchen or Mahamudra&amp;mdash;which needs to be recognized and ‘entered into’. This Essence of Mind is empty of tangible substance and is resistant to the intellect’s efforts to conceptualise or ‘model’ it, but it is supremely Aware and filled with benevolence and compassion. Writing on this theme, [[Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche|Lama Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche]] explains the Buddha’s teaching on the ultimate nature of the Awakened Mind (‘bodhicitta’), stating:

{{quote|‘What is ultimate bodhicitta? It is truly free from all mental constructs, like space; it cannot be indicated by any analogy whatsoever. It falls into no extreme or category; it is beyond mental constructs. It is the unity of emptiness and compassion; it is empty like space. Yet it is loving and compassionate, open and clear. That is ultimate bodhicitta …According to [[Mahamudra]], the essence is nonarising, its expression is unceasing, and its manifestation is the unity of these two. According to Dzogchen, the essence is empty, the nature is cognizant or luminous and the compassion is the unity of these two.’&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche |coauthors=Erik Pema Kunsang (translator) |title=Union of Mahamudra and Dzogchen: A Commentary on The Quintessence of Spiritual Practice, The Direct Instructions of the Great Compassionate One |year=2004 |publisher=North Atlantic Books |quote= |pages=188–189| url= |isbn=9627341215 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the same work, Chökyi Nyima writes that the essence of the mind is not a concrete thing, yet is not to be viewed as non-existent; nor is it a multitude of things or just one thing. It is an essence that could be called the ‘I’ or the Ground of all that is:

:''&quot;It is not found to be a concrete thing … Yet it is not nonexistent, since your mind is vividly awake. It is not a singularity, because it manifests in manifold ways. Nor is it a plurality, because all these are of one essence. There is no one who can describe its nature … It may be given many kinds of names such as “mind essence”, “I”, or the “all-ground”. It is the very basis of all of samsara and nirvana.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche |coauthors=Erik Pema Kunsang (translator) |title=Union of Mahamudra and Dzogchen: A Commentary on The Quintessence of Spiritual Practice, The Direct Instructions of the Great Compassionate One |year=2004 |publisher=North Atlantic Books |quote= |pages=122–125| url= |isbn=9627341215 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

This spiritual essence is not something that has to be developed or created: it is primordially present within each being. It constitutes the inner ‘bodies’ or aspects of the Buddha found in every person.  Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche writes:

{{quote|‘Since primordial time, these have been one’s natural possession, intrinsic and inherent to one’s being. We learn that these kayas are not something which one achieves or which occurs through the compassion of the buddhas … It cannot be produced through applying the key points of Dharma [religious] practice. One has possessed them since the very beginning. The kayas are absolutely inherent to oneself, to one’s own nature. The kayas exist spontaneously within oneself. Their presence is not a product of blessings or something slowly produced through practice. One cannot create or manufacture one’s enlightened essence through one’s own intelligence or through study of the teachings. One possesses them primordially. The sutras and tantras all agree on this point.’&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche |coauthors=Erik Pema Kunsang (translator) |title=Union of Mahamudra and Dzogchen: A Commentary on The Quintessence of Spiritual Practice, The Direct Instructions of the Great Compassionate One |year=2004 |publisher=North Atlantic Books |quote= |page=114| url= |isbn=9627341215 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the Tathagatagarbha tradition of Buddhism, this enlightened essence is called the Buddha Nature or (in the [[Mahaparinirvana Sutra]]) the Self (see [[atman (Buddhism)]]). It is the essential, indestructible nature of all beings, but is covered over by moral and mental contamination. Once that is removed, the inner ‘treasure’ of one’s true nature stands revealed in its full radiance and one becomes ‘Buddha’. In the [[Nirvana Sutra]], the Buddha teaches:

‘”Self” means the matrix-of-one-gone-thus [i.e. Buddha Nature]. The basic constituent of a one-gone-thus [i.e. Buddha] indeed exists in all sentient beings, but it also is obstructed by types of afflictive emotions. While existing in them, sentient beings cannot see it … The Buddha-nature of sentient beings is, for example, like a treasure of jewels under a poor woman’s house, like a diamond on a powerful being’s forehead, and like a universal emperor’s spring of ambrosic water.’&lt;ref&gt;Professor [[Jeffrey Hopkins (Tibetologist)|Jeffrey Hopkins]], ''Mountain Doctrine: Tibet’s Fundamental Treatise on Other-Emptiness and the Buddha Matrix'', Snow Lion Publications, New York, 2006, pp. 53-54&lt;/ref&gt;

Elucidating this notion of the Buddha Nature or Buddha Matrix, Professor [[Jeffrey Hopkins (Tibetologist)|Jeffrey Hopkins]] comments:

‘The basis [of the spiritual life] is the ground on which the spiritual path acts to rid it of peripheral obstructions, thereby yielding the fruit of practice. The basis is the matrix-of-one-gone-thus [Buddha Nature], which itself is the thoroughly established nature, the uncontaminated primordial wisdom empty of all compounded phenomena&amp;mdash;permanent, stable, eternal, everlasting. Not compounded by causes and conditions, the matrix-of-one-gone-thus [Buddha Nature] … is not something that did not exist before and is newly produced; it is self-arisen.’&lt;ref&gt;Professor Hopkins, op. cit., p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

One specific mysticism of Buddhism is union with [[Dharmakaya]] through [[jhana]]. [[Dharmakaya]] is both the wisdom body of The Buddha, for one, and is also the omnipresent Mind. This unbegotten and immortal essence within each being is called the Dharma-kaya&amp;mdash;Body of Truth&amp;mdash;or Buddha Within (as Dr. Shenpen Hookham has termed it).&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Shenpen Hookham, ''The Buddha Within'', [[State University of New York Press]], New York, 1991&lt;/ref&gt; Its nature is described in the ''[[Samadhiraja Sutra]]'', where the Buddha states:

‘the Body of the Tathagata [i.e. Buddha] should be defined as … having its essence identical with Space, invisible, surpassing the range of vision&amp;mdash;thus is the Absolute Body to be conceived.
Inconceivable, surpassing the sphere of thought, not oscillating between bliss and suffering, surpassing the illusory differentiation, placeless, surpassing the voice of those aspiring to the Knowledge of Buddhi, essential, surpassing passions, indivisible, surpassing hatred, steadfast, surpassing infatuation, explained by the indications of emptiness, unborn, surpassing birth, eternal from the standpoint of common experience, undifferentiated in the aspect of Nirvana, described in words as ineffable, quiescent in voice, homogenous with regard to conventional Truth, conventional with regard to the Absolute Truth&amp;mdash;Absolute according to the true teaching.’&lt;ref&gt;Dr. Konstanty Regamey, ''Philosophy in the Samadhirajasutra'', Motilal Banarsidass, 1990, pp. 86-88&lt;/ref&gt;



==Does anyone else think the article is long and rambling?== 
I got the article down from 81 000 bytes to 76 600 bytes,  but resisted minimising it more because I wanted some consensus before I went about doing anything drastic. At best the article is long and rambling.. at worst it is incomprehensible. Also, I think much of the information on this page is 'spirituality'. 'Mysticism' is the unique experience of God.. 'spirituality' is the system of thought and practice. [[User:Tjpob|Tjpob]] ([[User talk:Tjpob|talk]]) 08:42, 19 April 2011 (UTC)

:It does appear to have gotten a bit essay-ish, not to mention confused.  Also, the article is missing the point - a mysticism is a belief system that holds (as a core principle) that proper spiritual/moral understanding cannot be attained through the the human intellect, but only by ''getting past'' intellect to a deeper form of perception of reality.  I'm not averse to a major rewrite, but I don't want to lose any useful material that's tucked in amidst the overgrowth, so maybe we should talk a bit before whipping out the weed-eater.--[[User_talk:Ludwigs2|&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkblue;font-weight:bold&quot;&gt;Ludwigs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-weight:bold&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:49, 19 April 2011 (UTC)

:Yes. I ended up on this page following links from Chabad through several similar pages, attempting to find a concise explanation understandable to the non-scholar. I think the article could have stopped with the introduction. Mysticism is a concept, not a practice. If both is insisted, the practices should be separated out somehow and the writing should be directed more toward a general audience.[[User:Samtha25|Samtha25]] ([[User talk:Samtha25|talk]]) 02:13, 19 September 2011 (UTC)

=== The previous definition of Mysticism was succinct. ===
&quot;Mysticism is the pursuit of communion with, identity with, or conscious awareness of
an ultimate reality, divinity, spiritual truth, or God through direct experience, intuition, instinct or insight.&quot;

This definition was all encompassing and precise.  [[User:Mystickunoichi|Mystickunoichi]] ([[User talk:Mystickunoichi|talk]]) 15:14, 23 April 2011 (UTC)

=== Not only 'Long and Rambling', but Unsupported ===
The article needs a major rewrite, if not a [[WP:TNT]], for 4 reasons:

# It's long and rambling ... to the point of incomprehensibility (&quot;entheogens&quot; - eh?)
# It's a prohibited [[WP:ESSAY]], or worse, lots of random essays
# It's Unsupported [[WP:OR]] for most of its length --- 33 citations for 84,000 bytes, anybody?
# Oh, and some (much? most?) of the unsupported material is [[WP:COPYVIO]]

Join me - [[WP:Be Bold]] - it's time for some [[Slash-and-burn]] agriculture on this article. [[User:Chiswick Chap|Chiswick Chap]] ([[User talk:Chiswick Chap|talk]]) 13:18, 27 October 2011 (UTC)

* OK - I located the source of most of the trouble (but not the perpetrator): simple COPYRIGHT VIOLATION with text taken from Webster's Online Dictionary, http://www.websters-online-dictionary.org/definitions/Mysticism. 
:: The text has come down from 84,248 to 36,925 bytes. Oh my. 
:: The article now needs reorganisation, and then the gaps need to be filled in. But first I shall check for any more COPYVIO. [[User:Chiswick Chap|Chiswick Chap]] ([[User talk:Chiswick Chap|talk]]) 15:43, 27 October 2011 (UTC)

== No, I do NOT think the previous description of Mysticism was long and rambling at all. ==

It was a breadth first spectrum of the Mysticism of the major religions.
Not unlike Religious Studies 283.3 Comparative Mysticism in University.
Looking forward to a reinstatement of the Buddhist section. It was quite informative. [[User:Mystickunoichi|Mystickunoichi]] ([[User talk:Mystickunoichi|talk]]) 19:27, 25 November 2011 (UTC)

:: Hallo. Well, firstly I should say that nearly everything that I removed was a straight copyright violation - it seemed to ramble because it had simply been pasted in, in quantity, with no thought for whether it fitted the context. We can't put it back as it doesn't belong to us - it was straightforward theft. 
:: Secondly, its removal left several tricky problems - the remaining fragments didn't make up a coherent story; and there was a sizeable and quite reasonably-written chunk on Buddhism which could either go into another article - new or existing, or (perhaps) could be reinstated alongside matching sections on the other major religions to avoid imbalance. 
::Therefore, among other things, I made it explicit (above) that the Buddhism section was here in waiting. Since I didn't have the time, energy and possibly skill to create the matching sections, and nobody else has so far volunteered, there the matter has rested. I wouldn't like to see the Buddhism section back in the article until we have the other sections to balance it. If you'd like to write them...? Alternatively, we could make it into a separate article and link it from here? Note that there is a table entry for Buddhism already, and that provides links to 3 articles on mystical forms of Buddhism, so there is already quite good coverage on Wikipedia (we don't have to try to say everything on one page, fortunately). [[User:Chiswick Chap|Chiswick Chap]] ([[User talk:Chiswick Chap|talk]]) 19:58, 25 November 2011 (UTC)

== Non-Objective ==

The following is non-objective: &quot;is the knowledge of, and especially the personal experience of, states of consciousness, i.e. levels of being, beyond normal human perception, including experience and even communion with a supreme being&quot;

Ayn Rand made a pretty good objective meaning of Mysticism:

What is mysticism? Mysticism is the acceptance of allegations without evidence or proof, either apart from or against the evidence of one’s senses and one’s reason. Mysticism is the claim to some non-sensory, non-rational, non-definable, non-identifiable means of knowledge, such as “instinct,” “intuition,” “revelation,” or any form of “just knowing.”  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Billegge|Billegge]] ([[User talk:Billegge|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Billegge|contribs]]) 19:54, 17 December 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Ayn Rand is not a very good source for a definition of mysticism. [[User:Yworo|Yworo]] ([[User talk:Yworo|talk]]) 18:35, 1 January 2012 (UTC)

== suggested article to expand the content in the section mysticism in world traditions ==

Hello. I'm from south america and I like to study the topic. There's an organization in USA that is dedicated to mysticism and from it's website I found an article that I consider that might be helpful to expand the section about literary forms used by mystics and the information about world traditions:
http://www.centerforsacredsciences.org/publications/the-mystical-core-of-the-great-traditions.htm

I leave the link. I think that somebody interested in the topic may find it useful and informative. I leave to the editors the option to consider this article or not.
--Daniel  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/190.31.39.163|190.31.39.163]] ([[User talk:190.31.39.163|talk]]) 00:30, 12 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Section on 'Contrasts' ==

The following section was unreferenced and has been deleted piecemeal for that reason. However, all of its constituents contain bluelinks to other articles so it should be quite possible to find reliable sources for each of them.

That leaves open the question of whether the section or parts of it are worth saying in this article. So here is the material if anybody wishes to work on it: [[User:Chiswick Chap|Chiswick Chap]] ([[User talk:Chiswick Chap|talk]]) 06:46, 13 May 2012 (UTC)

===&quot;Contrast with other concepts&quot;===

*&quot;[[Esotericism]], like mysticism, holds that there are insights known only to few, but unlike mysticism holds that they can be learnt and transmitted without special experiences.&lt;sup&gt;[''[[wikipedia:Citation needed|citation needed]]'']&quot;&lt;/sup&gt;

*&quot;[[Paranormal|&quot;Paranormal]] experiences, like mystical experiences, are held to be non-ordinary, but unlike them are not [[noetic]], ie, leading to deep insights about the nature of reality.&lt;sup&gt;[''[[wikipedia:Citation needed|citation needed]]'']&lt;/sup&gt;&quot;

*&quot;An attitude of religious [[faith]] is generally one that values holding to certain beliefs in the ''absence'' of confirmation, including revelatory experiences. Religions may also be hostile to claims of special insights by individuals, some mystics having been punished for [[heresy]].&lt;sup&gt;[''[[wikipedia:Citation needed|citation needed]]'']&lt;/sup&gt;&quot;

*&quot;Scientific [[empiricism]] only accepts reproducible and publicly verifiable experiences as evidentiary.&lt;sup&gt;[''[[wikipedia:Citation needed|citation needed]]'']&lt;/sup&gt;&quot;
-----------(end of quoted section)--------------

== Yoga ==

Asanas and yoga need to be included somewhere in the article.  [[User:Buekerc1|Buekerc1]] ([[User talk:Buekerc1|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Buekerc1|contribs]]) 01:43, 23 May 2012 (UTC)
:: Yes; actually Yoga was in the table, but I've added a ref for it and also added an entry in the list with a mention of Asanas too. [[User:Chiswick Chap|Chiswick Chap]] ([[User talk:Chiswick Chap|talk]]) 07:29, 23 May 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gy5b1474rj6oo2fd3dpqkv1ze540dkq</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
