<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Supernatural</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>63947</id>
    <revision>
      <id>494056882</id>
      <parentid>492172019</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-05-23T21:59:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John Carter</username>
        <id>3358555</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>C class for Religion</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="80740">{{WikiProject Paranormal|class=C}}
{{Spirituality project|class=C|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; width=&quot;270px&quot;
|-
!align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|[[Image:Vista-file-manager.png|50px|Archive]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wikipedia:How to archive a talk page|Archives]]
----
|- style=&quot;font-size: 90%&quot;
|
# [[/Archive 1|Supernaturalization 1 (May 2003)]]
# [[/Archive 2|Supernaturalization 2 (May 2003)]]
# [[/Archive 3|Creeping supernaturalization (May 2003)]]
# [[/Archive 4|July 2002 – June 2003]]
# [[/Archive 5|June 2003 – June 2004]]
|}&lt;br clear=&quot;left&quot;/&gt;

==Who's Gina Pisani?==
Is the mention of some &quot;Gina Pisani&quot; in the first sentence some sort of joke? Is still Wikipedia so easily vandalized? 
[[Special:Contributions/93.32.255.193|93.32.255.193]] ([[User talk:93.32.255.193|talk]]) 02:21, 16 November 2009 (UTC)

==Religion and the Supernatural==

I think this article makes a big assumption in some points that supernatural realities and religious worldviews are identical. Furthermore it uses the word in many different ways confusing to the reader. For example, a genetically modified organism could be considered &quot;supernatural&quot; as it is completely above the natural order. Also, the point about Hindu vs christian eschatology has nothing to do with the existence or nonexistence of a supernatural realm; it seems like a lot of these points are thoughts that individuals here have had d not hardline philosophy. I think the article needs to be cleaned up. [[Special:Contributions/68.60.53.141|68.60.53.141]] ([[User talk:68.60.53.141|talk]]) 08:37, 6 July 2008 (UTC)

a genetically modified organism isn't &quot;above the natural order&quot;, it's simply pushing the envelope as far as what has manifested so far in the world. It's completly natural and as big a part of this world as we and any other form of life, the only real difference being that it was &quot;forced&quot; into being rather than spontaneously appearing. Supernatural phenomena relates to aspects of the world that are beyond the physical reality without being, according to those who believe in such things, in direct conflict with the fabric of reality or &quot;how things work&quot;. It's breaking the rules while playing by them. Genetic modification is replicating a process that occurs constantly in nature by it's self.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.224.63.34|81.224.63.34]] ([[User talk:81.224.63.34|talk]]) 11:20, 3 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== NPOV policy and proofs ==

NPOV says scientific and mathematical proofs are far more universally accepted than supernatural ones, from which it follows that scientific and mathematical proofs are more powerful than supernatural ones (for whatever reason). You and Wesley will agree that the proofs for &quot;Jesus Christ is the son of God&quot; (rejected by Jews, Muslims, Buddhists, etc) are far less universally accepted than the proofs for &quot;pi is irrational&quot; and &quot;the earth is spherical&quot; (accepted by Jews, Muslims, Buddhists, etc). ''Different people and different cultures find different sorts of proofs convincing.'' If different people and different cultures find different proofs convincing, then [[Pythagorean theorem|Pythagoras's theorem]] (as we call it) would not have convinced the very different people and cultures of Europe, India, China, etc for the past 2500+ years. But it has. And I'd still like to see a similarly spectacular modern equivalent of Elijah's miracle. Please add it to the Wikipedia if it isn't already here. [[Our Lady of Fatima]] is, but I presume that doesn't convince you either. This is my suggested NPOV addition to the article or one of its offshoots:

=== Supernaturalism and Proof === 

:Many supernaturalists assert that it is possible to prove certain facts about the supernatural to a very high degree of certainty or even with perfect certainty. However, different supernaturalist groups have proofs that contradict: even within the single religion of Christianity, although different groups will agree that infallible supernatural proof is possible, they will then use their infallible supernatural proofs to reach contradictory supernatural conclusions. Some Catholics, for example, claim that papal [[infallibility]] can be proved beyond doubt; some Protestants and Orthodox Christians that it can be '''dis'''proved beyond doubt. Within the religious family known as the [[Abrahamic religion]]s, Muslims, Jews, and Christians all agree that some supernatural facts can be proved beyond doubt, and then disagree about what those supernatural facts are. It is apparent, therefore, that proof within supernaturalism is of a different order to proof within mathematics and naturalistic science. In mathematics, proofs can be established permanently and universally and once established are accepted by all mathematicians throughout the world, regardless of race, ethnicity, and culture (see for example [[Pythagorean theorem]]). In science, the strength of a proof is proportional to the strength of the evidence put forward for it, and the strongest proofs are again accepted by all or a vast majority of scientists throughout the world, regardless of race, ethnicity, and culture (see for example the winners of the [[Nobel Prize in Physics]]). Because no single supernatural proof has ever been accepted universally across racial, ethnic, and cultural boundaries in the way many thousands of mathematical and scientific proofs have been, many skeptics, some of whom nevertheless accept the existence of the supernatural, would therefore argue that proof is impossible within supernaturalism. Some skeptical supernaturalists, such as [[Unitarian Universalism|Unitarian]]s and adherents of [[process theology]], further argue that God could not allow certain knowledge of his existence, nature, and purposes, because certain knowledge would remove the need for believers to exercise their [[free will]] and individual judgment.

''NPOV says scientific and mathematical proofs are far more universally accepted than supernatural ones, '' &amp;mdash; J.  Jacquerie, You continue to say this as though it means something important, but it it's not a clear statement.  By trying to use this article (and a few others) to explain yourself, you are risking turning this into even more about you and your views.  The paragraph you are proposing is more puff.  [[User:Mkmcconn|Mkmcconn]] 14:10 12 Jul 2003 (UTC)

Ah, you illustrate your articles! (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argumentum_ad_populum). This is an ad populum fallacy.  Because everyone agrees apon a premise, it must be true and the more people agree upon the premise, the truer it is.  It leads to absurdity of course (if everyone agreed that the world was flat, it would becomes so). teggers 080207

== Proof of Supernaturalism ==

This [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Tunguska_event#Occam.27s_Razor.3F Wikipedia entry] is fascinating proof of the supernatural. An extension of these very profound proofs exist in regard to the [http://ablebodiedman.blogspot.com/  Tunguska Event.] which should be included in the article and made available for the cognitive Wikipedia  audience. It makes it very difficult to be NPOV in regard to supernaturalism.

we are not here to &quot;prove&quot; whether or not there exists supernatural phenomena, we're here to convey information deemed important by the wikipedia standards. As far as proof goes for supernatural going-ons, the fact that someone yet has to explain something and describe how it came to be is far from proof that it's part of a supernatural world view.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.224.63.34|81.224.63.34]] ([[User talk:81.224.63.34|talk]]) 11:23, 3 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:LOL &quot;This extraordinarily powerful flash of lightning succeded the movement towards the earth of a visible body. If the rationales here are to be correct then, it stands to reason the identity of the body should be Satan himself!&quot; Why not Stalin? Either way, creoblogs ≠ [[WP:RS]]. . [[User:Dave souza|dave souza]], [[User talk:Dave souza|talk]] 11:43, 3 February 2009 (UTC)

== Most people believe in some form of supernaturalism ==

Most people and cultures believe in some form of supernaturalism; it is far more universally accepted than atheism and [[materialism]]. Your statements about [[papal infallibility]] reflect a deep misunderstanding of this debate; that question is not something Christians try to prove or disprove, it is a dispute about the tradition of the Church has always been; it's primarily an historical and doctrinal question. Mathematicians and scientists also disagree with each other about specific questions. Someone makes a new discovery or proposes a new formula or theorem, and it takes a while before everyone or most people accept it. I still remember when my high school physics teacher announced that a recent discovery made on a space shuttle mission meant that all the high school physics textbooks would need to be rewritten. I also recall an astronomer vigorously disputing the distance of quasars from us, though he was in the minority. Things aren't as cut and dry as you suggest. [[User:Wesley|Wesley]] 16:21 14 Jul 2003 (UTC)

:''Your statements about [[papal infallibility]] reflect a deep misunderstanding of this debate; that question is not something Christians try to prove or disprove, it is a dispute about the tradition of the Church has always been; it's primarily an historical and doctrinal question.'' A dispute between churches that is primarily an historical and doctrinal question. There's a ''rara avis''. Try these simple steps: 1) follow the link you provided to [[papal infallibility]] and find External Links; 2) Follow the external link &quot;CATHOLIC ENCYCLOPEDIA: Infallibility - historical treatment&quot;; 3) Scroll down the page till you come to the heading: &quot;PROOF OF PAPAL INFALLIBILITY FROM HOLY SCRIPTURE&quot;, where you'll read:

::From Holy Scripture, as already stated, the special proof of the pope's infallibility is, if anything, stronger and clearer than the general proof of the infallibility of the Church as a whole, just as the proof of his primacy is stronger and clearer than any proof that can be advanced independently for the Apostolic authority of the episcopate. 

:4) Finally, scroll down the page a little more until you come to the heading &quot;PROOF OF PAPAL INFALLIBILITY FROM TRADITION&quot;. But according to you &quot;that question is not something Christians try to prove or disprove&quot;. And your statements about atheism and materialism reflect a deep misunderstanding of this debate: science entails neither atheism or materialism, but I understand why you introduced them ''ex nihilo''. I won't bother responding to the rest. [[User:Jacquerie27|Jacquerie27]] 22:32 14 Jul 2003 (UTC)

:: Thank you for pointing out the Roman Catholic proof of papal infallibility; clearly I was mistaken in that point. The reason I introduced atheism and materialism is that they both appear to be very natural and direct consequences of your POV, that science can make no allowance for anything supernatural. Perhaps I should have used the word &quot;naturalism&quot; instead. The point is that many people the world over do accept a number of scientific and mathematical axioms as being true, while also believing in some kind of supernatural being(s) or activities. [[User:Wesley|Wesley]] 16:18 15 Jul 2003 (UTC)

::: Well, if you don't know much about Catholicism it's understandable you hadn't come across that. ''...very natural and direct consequences of your POV, that science can make no allowance for anything supernatural''. It's not my POV: it's science. Atheism and materialism claim to account for everything; science doesn't (yet). ''The point is that many people the world over do accept a number of scientific and mathematical axioms as being true, while also believing in some kind of supernatural being(s) or activities.'' Yes, but my point is that they accept different and contradictory supernatural proofs but the same scientific and mathematical proofs. Science and mathematics are genuinely catholic; Catholicism, like all other forms of supernaturalism, isn't. [[User:Jacquerie27|Jacquerie27]] 21:53 17 Jul 2003 (UTC)

''Scientists counter that if this is so, then believers in supernaturalism themselves would be utterly incapable of witnessing any supernatural phenomenon or miracles; all human senses are limited by the laws of physics, and can only sense events occuring in the natural, physical world.''

:I think this is POV and should be cut: if supernature exists it could interfere or interact with the laws of physics and the natural world, which are not perfectly known and not necessarily fixed; second, supernature wouldn't necessarily have to act thru the human senses in any case: it could affect the brain or mind directly. [[User:Jacquerie27|Jacquerie27]] 21:53 17 Jul 2003 (UTC)

Can I change 'Arguments in favour of supernaturality' to 'Arguments in favour of the existance of the supernatural', as the same for against?

== Many scientists and mathematicians ==

I keep on bumping into scientists who particularly suffer from the preconception that science reveals objective truth.  Never mind. If you think it is defensive or offensive, remove the comment. ([[User:20040302|20040302]] 13:36, 29 Apr 2004 (UTC))

== Removed paragraphs ==

I just removed the following paragraphs, because they are about the social causes of religious persecution. They are quite off-topic for an article on the supernatural. Most books on the Christian religion don't discuss the supernatural in general, and most books on the supernatural never even allude to this topic. This discussion's presence here is more a cause of the personal interests of contributors, but probably not a good editorial placing. If you want, we can move these paragraphs to an appropriate article. We can always mention this subject within this article, and link to the article where this topic is more appropriately discussed. [[User:RK|RK]]

* Because the truth of supernatural claims cannot be objectively tested, disputes about them often lead to [[schism]] and [[persecution]]. The [[philosophy|philosopher]] [[Bertrand Russell]] pointed this out in his essay &quot;An outline of Intellectual Rubbish&quot;:

:''The most savage controversies are those about matters as to which there is no good evidence either way. Persecution is used in theology, not in arithmetic, because in arithmetic there is knowledge, but in theology there is only opinion. So whenever you find yourself getting angry about a difference of opinion, be on your guard; you will probably find, on examination, that your belief is going beyond what the evidence warrants.''

*Examples:
**The [[Great Schism]]s among Christians were the culmination of centuries of disagreement concerning the powers of the [[Pope]] to decide doctrine. No objective standard for resolving these differences has been agreed upon, then or since. It may be argued, then, that only the abandonment of the competing supernatural claims can possibly lead to the resolution of differences.
**The [[Thirty Years War]] was justified as a defense of inviolable privileges granted by God to the [[Roman Catholic Church]] and the Catholic Emperor, over against the Protestant claims of God's grant of the rights of nations and of self-government according to the Bible.
**For centuries, Christians angered and frustrated by the refusal of [[Jew]]s to acknowledge [[Jesus]] as the [[Messiah]] have considered the Jews to be especially guilty of the [[crucifixion]] of Christ, cursed and deserving of suffering (see [[decide]]).  Other folk-religious beliefs about alliances between the Jews and Satan, and similar terrifying [[conspiracy theory|conspiracy theories]], have fueled hatred and cruelty toward the Jewish people, and have produced a special indifference to Jewish suffering.

== Arguments in favor of supernaturality ==

There are currently eight &quot;arguments against supernaturality&quot; and four counter-arguments (&quot;arguments in favour of supernaturality&quot;), yet two of the latter include counter-counter-arguments!  This is hardly fair, so I have removed the counter-counter arguments.

In the last &quot;argument in favor&quot; I have corrected some of the information and removed redundancy.&lt;br/&gt;
[[User:Philip J. Rayment|Philip J. Rayment]] 14:20, 2 Oct 2004 (UTC)

:We usually don't remove text from an article to create balance. The Wikipedia way is generally to ''add'' text to maintain balance.  Otherwise our articles are trimmed, and then trimmed again, and then trimmed again....  In this case we find many arguments against supernaturalism, but few for it.  I would think the proper response would be too add more arguments for belief in the supernatural, if any more arguments actually exist. [[User:RK|RK]] 00:29, Oct 3, 2004 (UTC)
ghosts are true cause i saw a ghost doing a ghost poo
:Thank you for that observation, but Wikipedia has a firm policy against [[Wikipedia:original research|original research]], so I doubt we can add that to the article. [[User:JRM|JRM]] · [[User talk:JRM|Talk]] 10:50, 14 August 2005 (UTC)
:Nice.

== Seeking expert eyes on [[Natasha Demkina]] ==

Hi all. I'd like to ask you, as people familiar with topics on or related to paranormal activity, to review the work at [[Natasha Demkina]], &quot;the girl with X-ray eyes&quot;, which has been undergoing a tug-of-war between a primary source and one of his critics. I've tried to bring it to at least NPOV but apparently I muddled the technicalities and there are still sourcing needs.

Would appreciate your comments -- the article is currently under protection but I think it can be taken out shortly.

TIA, - [[User:KeithTyler|Keith D. Tyler]] [[User_talk:KeithTyler|&amp;para;]] 21:24, 15 December 2005 (UTC)

== Arguments Against ==

The last paragraph stated that believing in supernatural explanations for burning bushes is lazy. I changed it, but it's my opinion it's still a bit lousy. So if anyone cares to look at it, it could use a better NPOV explanation of how science deals with seemingly supernatural phenomena. [[User:71.10.236.201|71.10.236.201]] 21:04, 6 June 2006 (UTC)

:I tried to clean it up a bit; not sure if it's an improvement. [[User:Noclevername|Noclevername]] 21:38, 13 February 2007 (UTC)

I wish I could be more constructive than just tossing stones at this, but...this is really bad! Is it just me, or does the whole article read like an atheist having an argument with a strawman of his own creation? Don't they have Internet forums for that sort of stuff? Some of it is just laughable; &quot;Scientists say...&quot; What scientists? It looks like someone was just making it up as they went along. Perhaps a more appropriate title for this would be; &quot;Strawman Arguments in Favour of Atheism&quot;.

[[User:Steve Lowther|Steve Lowther]] 08:08, 25 February 2007 (UTC)

Totally agree with the above, and I'm an atheist.  This article is ridiculous but I too cant be more constructive than to point it out.  Religion and &quot;the supernatural&quot; are NOT synonymous, for one.  

: Certainly religion and the supernatural are not exactly synonymous. But supernatural religion and the supernatural are synonymous. And it is certainly a good approximation that the vast majority of religions are supernatural and that the vast majority of supernaturalists are religious. [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] 14:18, 17 September 2007 (UTC)

Second, an argument against &quot;the supernatural&quot; shouldnt be that &quot;all religions or none must be true&quot; as this presumption assumes complete knowledge of the nature of reality.  How do we really know that both reincarnation and an &quot;afterlife&quot; cant coexist? Or that neither exist? Or that one is more plausible than the other? 

: You would have a point if that were the argument. The argument is not that all must be &quot;true&quot; or not &quot;true&quot;. But that standards for acceptance or rejection should be applied fairly. You see it is all too common and depressing just how often supernaturalists make &quot;truth&quot; claims using arguments that they would reject under similar circumstances when applied to other supernatural religions. In fact they do it all the time. [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] 14:18, 17 September 2007 (UTC)

&quot;Arguments against the supernatural&quot; should actually be *strong* arguments.  Some strong arguments would be sociological explanations for why certain superstitions are universal.  Scientific explanations for specific phenomenon. 

: A &quot;*strong*&quot; argument appears to be nothing more than an argument that you personally think is &quot;*strong*&quot;. So what? [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] 14:18, 17 September 2007 (UTC)

Science has the laborious task of disproving presumed supernatural events one by one.  There cant really be a blanket &quot;argument against the supernatural&quot;  THats just not high science works.

: Science has no such task. Perhaps people who are interested in debunking supernatural claims have such a task but scientists as a group are not interested in showing why superstitious explanations of reality are not very good, but in finding explanations of reality that actually can be shown to have the ability to predict reality before the fact. That is because that is how you get the recognition of your peers. Scientists cite papers that help them further their work. Not debunk work they have no interest in. [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] 14:18, 17 September 2007 (UTC)

  Ironically, thats how FAITH works and it seems more and more atheists are really just those in search of some kind of anti-religion rather than those truly committed to science and fair minded analysis.  Depressing.

: Have a care. This may be more a reflection of you than anything else. [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] 14:18, 17 September 2007 (UTC)

I adjusted the strange wording of the second point in Arguments Against, but would like to include specific instances of Supernatural critics referencing [[methodological naturalism|methodological naturalism]] similar to [http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Kitzmiller_v._Dover_Area_School_District/4:Whether_ID_Is_Science#4._Whether_ID_is_Science|this]  [[User:BurntSynapse|BurntSynapse]] ([[User talk:BurntSynapse|talk]]) 20:16, 25 July 2010 (UTC)

== (Possibly unintentional) Vandalism ==

Somebody is editing the Supernatural page and insisting on inserting long, unwieldy, opinionated, and misspelled paragraphs about science and its virtues. While science is indeed a wonderful subject to bring into this page, you needn't vent your worship of it here; and if you must, please at least do so concisely and with good [[irony|spelling]]. -RSR 11-06-06 02:42 PM MST

== Basic Definition of &quot;Supernatural&quot; ==
The opening paragraph of this Wikipedia entry states that: 

&quot;The supernatural (Latin: super- &quot;exceeding&quot; + nature) refers to forces and phenomena which are not observable in nature, and therefore beyond verifiable measurement. If a phenomenon can be demonstrated, it can no longer be considered supernatural&quot;

This is quite obviously untrue. Let's pretend for a minute that poltergeists exist, and one day you see one. Since you have just observed a ghost, does that imply by definition that ghosts are a natural phenomenon, rather than a supernatural one?

This appears to leave us with quite an unhelpful definition of the term &quot;supernatural&quot; (one that appears to reflect instead Kant's distinction between the Phenomenal and the Noumenal).

Traditionally, the term &quot;supernatural&quot; has been used to describe things that may well be observable in nature, but which have ''causes'' that lie outside the natural order.

:This is a good point and well points out what happens when one confuses the phenomenon with the explanation. All cases of purported supernatural events are natural events that are explained using supernatural constructs. Such supernatural constructs are claimed to have properties that are a-priori beyond the natural. However this does not preclude that for those same purported supernatural events that completely natural explanations could also account for the phenomenon. In the end it boils down to which explanation one prefers and what is the criterion being used to choose. The supernaturalist usually prefers the supernatural explanation not because of how well it explains the phenomena and predicts future phenomena of its kind but usually by how well that supernatural explanation makes them feel. In the end this is the difference between a naturalist and a supernaturalist. Scratch any supernaturalist and their reasons for preferring such explanations is based on the &quot;joy&quot; it brings them. [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] 16:28, 4 April 2007 (UTC)

Have thought about this for some time. Naturalism vs Supernaturalism debate is significantly muddied, here and elsewhere, by a purely semantic problem. That is, until you have adequately defined what is natural, in other words, the LIMITS of naturalism, then any attempt at defining what is “super” to that, is going to run into all sorts of difficulties. Consider Arthur C. Clarke’s epigram: Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. In the 1930s, New Guinea natives saw planes and white people for the first time, and it was an experience that totally shocked them (It was the only such encounter to be filmed). Later, those natives set up a “cargo cult” in which they built air strips etc, and waited for the large metal birds to descend and give them all that precious booty. There are still some adherents to this cult. It is a worldview that has a mythical base explaining all the events since that apocalyptic day. Unfortunately, it is all wrong. Still, it does show that it is hard to put limits on what is natural or not. And if we can’t do that then how can we clearly delinate between the two worlds. 

The movie 2001, often regarded as being a “God Concept” movie in fact has nothing in it that is “supernatural” at all. The obelisk is the sentinel of a very advanced extraterrestrial race. In a way, it is like the whole human race has an experience akin to the one the New Guineans experienced. Science fiction, by definition, does not busy itself with fantasy and magic, but on the other hand, who is to say what a magical event might be? Suppose for a moment that there is in reality a God who created the Universe. Now suppose that that being is actually a representative of an extremely advanced race. Perhaps so advanced that they can create universes the way we can computer simulations. These ideas are seriously considered by cosmologists. It could be even said that some Christian groups come close to such materialistic formulations of the Godhead. For example, I believe that the Mormons believe our God dwells on another planet as part of a community, and has a wife and family. If so, is he a supernatural being, or just a very advanced one, as Clarke would hold?

On the other hand, I am not satisfied in my own mind that I have actually nutted this out properly. Science fiction works on visions of (essentially) natural and material worlds, but the concepts of things like “fairy land” and suchlike seems to lie outside this. “Lord of the Rings” does not look or feel like science fiction, even though Tolkein and now Peter Jackson have gone to great lengths to give the people and communities dealt with there as much detail and history as possible. Yet, there are various moral concepts that take over the landscape here. Perhaps, it is the idea that good and evil have an ontological reality that makes these to be essentially supernatural and religious works. The idea that good and evil are not just interpretations but realities in the Universe. [[User:Myles325a|Myles325a]] 05:34, 15 April 2007 (UTC)

Webster’s dates the word “supernatural” to the 15th century.  I suspect that the word supernatural came about when people started questioning miracles.  That century and the century prior to that presented great challenges to people who accepted the major religion of Europe. It saw endless war, great plagues, papal schism, peasant uprisings, a deeply corrupt clergy and the creation of Protestantism. My guess is that a great deal of distrust was created at the time regarding miracles and the claims of the church and I suspect that the term “supernatural” was coined to place these claims above examination. (An interesting semi-fictional account of that time can be found in &quot;A Distant Mirror&quot;, Tuchman, Barbara, Alfred A, Knopf 1978) [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] ([[User talk:Gkochanowsky|talk]]) 19:19, 17 November 2007 (UTC)

:Important discussion to be having.  The term 'supernatural' is not very old (a few hundred years?).  Perhaps the huge chasm between 'nature' and 'super-nature' is not so wide?  Perhaps there's more to nature than we know?  - Dale Campbell

::The etymology suggests that the concept of &quot;supernatural&quot; developed alongside a new understanding of &quot;natural.&quot;  But that is neither here nor there.  Myles raises several interesting points but the only way to address them is by complying with NPOV and NOR.  This means we need verifiable sources for definitions of &quot;supernatural&quot; and my bet is that there are a variety of definitions reflecting different notable points of view, and all notable points of view should be represented and correctly identified.  The opening definition, however flawed it may seem to us, may be - ''may be'' one verifiable point of view and we should include it whether we like it or not.  The question is not whether it makes sense to us, but whether it can be linked to a verifiable point of view. [[User:Slrubenstein|Slrubenstein]]   |  [[User talk:Slrubenstein|Talk]] 20:11, 17 November 2007 (UTC)

== Article Rename ==
Do any of you perhaps think that this article might be renamed 'The supernatural'? The reason I say this is that when you say, 'Supernatural,' you generally mean the adjective. The noun form is almost always (I believe) indicated by adding a definite article in front, thus, 'The supernatural'. It seems to make more sense to me. Thanks for considering, [[User:Vlmastra|Vlmastra]] 22:47, 4 January 2007 (UTC)

== Why argue? ==

Supernatural things can't be explained. Why argue?? &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/71.235.41.119|71.235.41.119]] ([[User talk:71.235.41.119|talk]]) 01:41, 23 January 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

:Why argue?  Because many things once called &quot;supernatural&quot; have turned out to be very explainable and part of a coherent world, and therefore &quot;natural&quot;.  [[Ball lightning]] comes to mind as an example. (&quot;Despite over 10,000 sightings of the phenomenon, ball lightning has often been regarded as nothing more than a myth, fantasy, or hoax...&quot;)
:There are always &quot;things that aren't explained yet&quot;.  But the term &quot;supernatural&quot; shouldn't be used to cover all of them.  [[Nanobes]] are not yet explained, but to say they're &quot;supernatural&quot; implies they will ''never'' be explained, and that's counterproductive.  It would be more accurate to say these things are &quot;The Unexplained&quot;. --signed, ThinkFest &lt;!-- ThinkFest --&gt;

:Some folk's laziness and low IQs regarding their not knowing nor not caring what  their talking about can be explained.  [[User:Andrew Homer|Andrew Homer]] 07:19, 23 January 2007 (UTC)

::Don't insult that poster. Pity him if you must, but in a civil way. (they're, not their) [[User:Noclevername|Noclevername]] 23:26, 13 February 2007 (UTC)

I think you are re correcting the above sentence when it doesnt need to be corrected, the sentence with `their` is right, as it refers to the person, the verb that you are trying to correct is wrong as it doesnt refer to `their`, what you are trying to correct is `they`re`, short for `they are`.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ndod|Ndod]] ([[User talk:Ndod|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ndod|contribs]]) 23:47, 20 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::And your point is...? If it is unexplained, then they are right in asserting a mystery. [[User:Mike4ty4|mike4ty4]] 07:38, 21 March 2007 (UTC)

:The clash we're seeing in this discussion is not just between &quot;the people who don't want to believe&quot; vs. &quot;the people who want to believe&quot;.  It's also between &quot;people with very lax standards of evidence and reasoning,&quot; and &quot;people with stricter and more sophisticated standards.&quot;  It's not fair to assume all such people are &quot;lazy&quot; or &quot;stupid&quot;.
:Consider that there are still places on earth where teaching rationalism will earn you, not just  ostracism from your community, but a death sentence.
:Obviously, nobody wants to be told that they're lacking the tools of reasoning, but it's true;  reasoning is not a deity-granted innate ability.  It's a skill, just like plumbing and doing gymnastics.  It's a set of tools that needs to be taught. Some people can stand on one leg; some people can do cartwheels; some people do Olympic parallel bar routines.  ''It's the same with reasoning.''
:One of those &quot;tools&quot; is the idea, &quot;Demand evidence of causality.&quot;  By and large, &quot;supernatural&quot; concepts are still with us because they're upheld without (for instance) the standard of &quot;causality&quot; as well as &quot;correlation&quot;.  For example, some people will accept that &quot;God's anger with gay people&quot; was the cause of the flooding of New Orleans.  Yes, there is a correlation-- 'there are homosexuals in New Orleans'-- but no evidence of a causal link.  All there is, is a coincidence, and somebody loudly declaring something unpopular in their community to be the  'cause'.  This makes no more sense than attributing the great [[San Francisco earthquake]] to gambling parlors.
:Principles of rational thought such as &quot;the demand for evidence of causality&quot; deserve to be disseminated.  Sometimes the word 'argument' doesn't mean fruitless mutual yelling.  With a little rationalist  training, it can mean 'presenting the most credible explanation you know for why you prefer a particular conclusion.' --signed, ThinkFest

==????==
I can't make heads or tails of the last paragraph under &quot;Arguments against&quot;; It seems to be saying that if you hold ''one'' supernatural belief, but don't believe ''all'' of them, then that somehow proves them all automatically false. WhaHuh?? What kind of twisted pseudologic is that? I'd have an easier time believing in the supernatural than in that conclusion. To whoever wrote that mess, as a rational skeptic, I beg of you: please don't be on our side. That was ''painful'' to read. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Noclevername|Noclevername]] ([[User talk:Noclevername|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Noclevername|contribs]]) 23:24, 13 February 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

:It's gotten bigger and wordier, but no clearer. [[User:Noclevername|Noclevername]] 04:48, 16 March 2007 (UTC)
:: Sorry about that but it was intended to show that most supernaturalists hold their supernatural beliefs dishonestly. It makes no attempt nor does it claim to &quot;prove&quot; that supernaturalism is not the &quot;Truth&quot;. As such it is an argument against supernaturalism at least for those that try to be honest. For others that do not endeavor to be honest in their &quot;beliefs&quot; if not their thinking I can see where it might be very confusing. [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] 16:33, 4 April 2007 (UTC)

::: No offense, but that paragraph is a disaster.  And I don't mean structurally, I mean the basic premise.  I agree with the first comment.  &quot;Arguments against the supernatural&quot; should be a listing of presumed supernatural phenomena that have been proven natural by science.  The last paragraph as it stands is essentially a faith based argument with no basis in empirical evidence.  Two unproveable, unobservable states can both easily be equally valid within the framework of reality.  We don't have perception after death, therefore we can't (as rational thinkers) make absolute statements about what is or is not possible following the termination of life.  Oblivion, noncorporeal existance, reincarnation? None are proveable or disproveable and neither is setting up arbitrary rules like &quot;all or nothing must be true&quot;.  To go one step farther, perhaps what happens following death is determined by the will of the individual.  Perhaps human consciousness exists on some quantum level and, following the termination of physical function, that quantum signature is either imprinted on a new physical incarnation or drawn off to some alternate reality depending on which way it gravitates naturally.  Crazy? Maybe.  But you can't disprove that, it's somewhat based on theoretical physics, and it would allow for the possibility of both an afterlife and reincarnation.  Please just kill that last paragraph.

==&quot;Science cannot approach the supernatural&quot;==

I added a &quot;citation needed&quot; tag to the statement &quot;science cannot approach the supernatural.&quot; I don't necessarily disagree but I wish to see attribution so I can evaluate how widely accepted this statement is, by whom, and why. The [[scientific method]] article does not mention the supernatural. Cheers. [[User:Schmitty120|Schmitty120]] 21:14, 8 April 2007 (UTC)

::Schmitty: after seeing your comments on the [[Evolution]] talk page, I clicked over to your user page and was compelled to follow it here.  Your comments at [[Evolution]] and now this comment above seem to imply that you might benefit from reviewing what [[scientific method|science]] is.  No citation is required to support this statement: the definition of science necessarily excludes the supernatural, although the definition of WHAT is &quot;supernatural&quot; is often defined by the limitations of technology at the time.  Science is a '''method''' that requires repeatable ways of collecting objective measurements to test falsifiable hypotheses.  If you can do that about ANYTHING, then that &quot;anything&quot; is not supernatural.  For example, there would have been times in human history when things like radio and microwaves, X-rays, viruses, and even the atom were &quot;supernatural&quot; because humans did not yet possess the tools or knowledge to measure them under the scientific method.  Things like ghosts, gods, and &quot;psychic phenomena&quot; will remain supernatural until (and unless) a day arrives that we are able to design repeatable ways of collecting objective measurements to test falsifiable hypotheses about them.  Science cannot approach the supernatural because science, as a method of inquiry, is not equipped to.  You can't mow a lawn with a sewing machine.  You can't address the supernatural using science. [[User:TxMCJ|TxMCJ]] 16:10, 7 May 2007 (UTC)
:::I think the statement is inappropriate on different grounds. You make the point that some things that are today science that would once have been (and to some still seem) supernatural. To then say science cannot approach the supernatural gives an incorrect impression that what is currently considered supernatural can ''never'' be explained by science (this is not the actual statement, but the wording could easily be interpreted like that). They may be outside current knowledge, but may later be explainable. [[Scientific method]] can be used to test claims even if the  reasons for the results cannot explained by a non-supernatural means. The supernatural and scientific knowledge effectively meet at the moment on discovery/realisation where some thing goes from being an unexplained phenomenon to a principle that there are rules to; these rules are discovered and/or refined by the use of scientific method. The two do meet as the use of science to expand knowledge causes the supernatural to recede. --[[User:Nate1481|Nate]] 10:34, 8 May 2007 (UTC)

::::Okay, I concede the point, though I won't reverse my edits right away since Nate appears to still have objections. [[User:Schmitty120|Schmitty120]] 02:41, 9 May 2007 (UTC)

:::::Can you point me at the edits in question to see if it can be rephrased? --[[User:Nate1481|Nate]] 09:20, 9 May 2007 (UTC)

::::::Well, this is the particular one we were actually talking about [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Supernatural&amp;diff=121265002&amp;oldid=121009148]. I also made numerous changes in a wave of edits here. [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Supernatural&amp;diff=122810727&amp;oldid=121765586]. Good luck. [[User:Schmitty120|Schmitty120]] 14:19, 9 May 2007 (UTC)

:::And not to mention that nobody '''''wants''''' to make the necessary ''effort'' to ''develop'' such real experiments, etc. (or even to try to see if they are in fact impossible and thus said &quot;supernatural&quot; phenomena would remain totally irrelevant to the &quot;real&quot; world) since no &quot;scientists&quot; believe in the stuff in the first place (and they don't bother to look for the stuff either.). Saying that science &quot;cannot&quot; approach suggests it will ''never'' approach it. [[User:Mike4ty4|mike4ty4]] 00:16, 20 May 2007 (UTC)

&lt;- Honestly seems tagged on there, and think the article is better off without it. --[[User:Nate1481|Nate]] 15:28, 9 May 2007 (UTC)

:Another problem that didn't seem to get mentioned is that this would entail that supernatural phenomena are totally impossible to observe, as observation would constitute some sort of &quot;data&quot; having been gathered, and thus any report of a &quot;supernatural&quot; phenomenon being &quot;observed&quot; would be a logical contradiction in terms. How can you observe something you can't observe? It's like saying 1 = 0. It makes no sense. If ghosts or other &quot;supernatural&quot; phenomena exist then they would not be &quot;supernatural&quot; since observations of them have been reported (this does not say whether ghosts are spirits or not, it would just rule out them as being &quot;supernatural&quot; under this definition.). So it seems this is not a good definition. Supernatural phenomena would be totally unknown, and thus there would be no reason to even consider the concept in the first place. &quot;Phenomenon&quot; itself would be an invalid descriptor since it implies the ability to observe the thing, so &quot;supernatural phenomenon&quot; would be an oxymoron. If it can be observed, then it would not be &quot;supernatural&quot;. Period. So if ghosts, etc. exist and people really have seen them, they are not &quot;supernatural&quot;, PERIOD. So this is pretty much a useless definition. [[User:Mike4ty4|mike4ty4]] 00:16, 20 May 2007 (UTC)
::All supernatural activity, if proved, is no longer supernatural in definition, so it is technically impossible to capture or enforce beliefs in supernatural activity, a better word would be [[unexplained]] or [[paranormal]], am i correct?

What would you do if you were suddenly in touch with a 'sixth' sense for example one day you felt as if you had a telepathic experience(s)?  Wouldn't that be 'supernatural' in a way and possibly suggestive of some 'god' or otherworldly experience or at least a very strange one? Now it could be the 'cargo plane phenomenon' verse god(s)/spirits-or not. Perhaps there is something to it - 'god(s)' and 'ghosts/spirits' and even more in some 'dimension' or place that as yet is undefined by science. Perhaps we just might not have the ability to find it with our present technology and our limited human capacity for understanding. Maybe there are some people who have had 'sixth' sense experiences. I disagree that it is technically impossible to capture beliefs in 'supernatural'activity unless its added that its true only by present experimental methods and at the present time. Scientists have studied geese - see Princeton Sixth Sense Study that were able to migrate by sensing magnetic fields and another study that proved certain sharks sensed prey by electrical feedback. These were senses previously undiscovered but once found shed light on unexplained behavior. Perhaps a particular sense(s) may one day be discovered with people who have experiences with the 'supernatural'. It may seem like a long shot but science has to admit that knowledge is an ongoing endeavor and what is the unknown today is tomorrow's truth. Thank god (pun intended) those geese weren't waiting for science to prove that they could find their way home. The tough part in all this is keeping a reasonably open mind despite the unknown and the frivolous. There might even be different degrees of 'supernatural' with 'god' turning out to be plausibly explained or eternally outside of our efforts. I like unexplained better than paranormal as it lends itself to the sideshow.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.11.134.202|67.11.134.202]] ([[User talk:67.11.134.202|talk]]) 09:07, 20 February 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Unsourced==
Added an &quot;Unreferenced&quot; tag to the whole article 11 April 2007. This is an important article with a lot of forward statements that need to be supported with references. Later on I may add more specific citation needed tags. Cheers. [[User:Schmitty120|Schmitty120]] 13:24, 11 April 2007 (UTC)
:Removed tag today. [[User:Schmitty120|Schmitty120]] 19:49, 9 May 2007 (UTC)
:Added NPOV tags to the sections &quot;Competing Explanations and Criteria of Preference&quot; and &quot;Alleged instances of supernaturalization,&quot; because they were written with a naturalist POV. The former section makes supernaturalists look like idiots for choosing comfortable but irrational explanations for phenomena. It's watered down with some weaselly &quot;mays&quot; and &quot;some peoples,&quot; but this just makes it more boring to read without removing the POV. At the very least some sources are needed for the claim that pervades this article, that the science cannot work with the supernatural. The naturalistic POV at the end of the latter section is, I think, fairly obvious and again, cries out for attribution or deletion. Cheers. [[User:Schmitty120|Schmitty120]] 22:39, 13 April 2007 (UTC)

:::In regards your comments on &quot;Competing Explanations and Criteria of Preference&quot; are you ignoring that both points of view are presented? Certainly the term supernatural begs the term natural. Those could and often do represent opposing points of view, but as is pointed out in that section there are many that embrace both depending of course on thier criteria of preference. Exactly what bias are you talking about? [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] 01:38, 17 September 2007 (UTC)

==Cleanup==
I decided to add a cleanup tag today, which will hopefully attract some helpful attention. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Schmitty120|Schmitty120]] ([[User talk:Schmitty120|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Schmitty120|contribs]]) 19:19, 14 April 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

Under Cleanup I would submit the following paragraph from Section 1.  It is wordy, muddled, stream of consciousness.  It is terrible 6th grade writing and terrible amateur philosophy.

&quot;So, if something 'supernatural' exists, it must by definition not be supernatural. And only magical thinking that power could come from where power could not come from could contend otherwise. i.e. a contradiction in itself. The question is where may power come from, or if there are other as of yet confirmed or understood places where power comes from. i.e. likewise, for if bigfoot is found and confirmed, he will not be mysterious or supernatural. In the past, people doubted the existence of the rhinoceros. There is little present belief in the existence of the Unicorn. Certainly there may always be things outside of the realm of human understanding, or as of yet unconfirmed and dubious in existence, and some might term these 'supernatural.'&quot;  [[User:Talkingtomypocket|Talkingtomypocket]] 02:09, 1 July 2007 (UTC)


...SUPERNATURAL: What happened in ancient times, where does History explain a supernatural. If something is concluded as definite,as with an addition of &quot;so-far&quot; or anything resembling that, then could there be another attempt to see something more of. &quot;Perhaps a meaning of Super&quot;. 
  A Natural if for sure something understandable a perceived through notice and or accountability. Though when there is a figuration that may exist to have allowed something to happen then this could be a phenomenal occurrence. I represent occurrence for that may have existence during the time of figuration.
Example how far back does a science go. Even when a term such as science is not used, it is a happening that a figuration of something and or even a knowledge occurrence, which may even be something of just a calculation that something may occur is in a conduct. Finishing with my Example. The figuration of how the Earth 'has been created' is again a determination of factors through in which a study and a degree of time has been passed. In a somewhat conclusion to this affect as to perhaps advice others of is also the recommendation of what has not been concluded. Although what appears as a bases idea of how the earth is created is an essential, there is the fact that how that was a matter in conduct, also the matter of conduct of how the natural became natural. 
In study and review of this attempt is the basic conclusion of water, air, dirt, and other mineral products evaluated form the earth. Though the supernatural thing here may be how this occurred. In some resolution and yet still a study there is the mention of a great boom or explosion. This in itself may even have been a represented theory in the past. Though explaining it is yet a, &quot;figuration yet to be asserted.

Here is a theory that in some views God is a supernatural. Question, and in perception of a term in existing manner &quot; Supernatural&quot;. If this term did not exist then it is for certain that another then would represent a view of God. Just a suggestion here. In the past and this may theorize as a long time ago, there were a people perhaps amongst other people. In this thought 'amongst is the representation of a, lets say the term for now is tribe' these people built things and manufactured perhaps idealistic situations to support them. Such materials could be a bowl that would withstand the flames as to not crack all the time. A supporting roof that lasted a long time, a wheel for instance. These recommendations are through people, these people have names. For instance Noah is claimed to have lived 900 plus years. Could this venture be that the name Noah lived for this long along with the remedy of Noah. Getting back to to the prior of time when I described the creations of the wheel, roof, and bowl. These people were in a sense worshiped. This terming may have been used in a different way,&quot;worshiped&quot; for instance it may have been another term or perhaps even a feeling, and this could go on for a long period of time. Then there's schooling, this continues, again a term perhaps not used. Though in reference with schooling or a learning degree is the matter of usage. There were the young whom would do the things that were done and it would go over and over like this. Time has passed and many of these people would pass on. To remember these people it was a good reason to be associated with them through a degree, such as a reference. Perhaps this was a name of something. Now lets say through the years there were amongst these people a variety of names, perhaps to represent. What would be in conclusion to a society to reference a deity amongst them all and have the teachings go on through again another degree. This degree could be value or some form of category. Today we may call it a book or a descriptive allowance. I am now involved with all the names in this theory of time, and some small degree I am to relate it as a time of a beginning. A beginning amongst many and in sense to be of self. When in consideration of this organ-izational stance and even a maturity what would a or the recognition be. In Law we have &quot;Law&quot; In a Town we have &quot;town' in Distance we have :Distance&quot; and end we have 'end'. These representations are a conclusion of theory and or standard's. God may in retrospect represent the past present and future.

As well as a supernatural may represent a past present and future. The reason why is existence. What about the fact that if a child is caught under a vehicle and all of a sudden the parent gets a supernatural strength to save to child, whatever the case is, which perhaps would be an exertion, this would be a consideration of a supernatural phenomenon. I use &quot;phenomenon because again that to has to be explained. Though in retrospect this supernatural exercise is of the past present and future, yet still. We have the existence of the person doing the extraordinary factor. The existence is somewhat allowing the capability. This could be a practice, or physical belonging of the person. Then we have the present and actuality of performance. Then we have the future, the explanation, all representing a supernatural situation.[[User:D.G.DeL-Dorchester Mass|David George DeLancey]] ([[User talk:D.G.DeL-Dorchester Mass|talk]]) 21:12, 24 March 2010 (UTC)     

 end'

== Religion as a science??? ==

Did you all ever stop to wonder whether or not religion is a science.   A record keep of supernatural events that can't be catagorized into the mainstream deffinition of 
science.  Repetative events.  For example the buhdist belive that through medition and
pondering a state of higher egsitance can be obtained, science has proven that &quot;finding
yourself&quot; , the modern term, leads to more fullfilling life and heallthier lives at that.
scientifically when poeple get struck by lightning weird things happen to their brain
and bodies, some good and some not so good. maybe the buhdist route might take a little
longer but it is probbible safer.  Similair teachers are within both christs &quot;life 
everlasting&quot; teaching and in the hindu realms as well.  Babalonyan scholars thought the
Hebrew bible was an amazing conglomeration of sociology in both personal and cultural 
context.  But thats how they get you huh.  After you start to explore the Realities of 
the religions that have survived and quite a few don't.  you start to understand how and 
why religion is there in the first place.  To understand that which in not understood.
I belive in god for what its worth.

::Frankly, I don't think that believing without evidence adequate to the claim is worth ''anything''.  A religion fails to qualify as science when it ''requires'' or even merely ''hints'' to anybody that they shouold accept something with no future possibility of questioning.
::No, I never stopped to wonder if religions were science, because it seemed very obvious to me that they're not.  Scientists are required to account for both evidence at the time of their writing, plus all evidence that comes along later.  Countless religions once claimed that a deity hurled lightning bolts.  When the theory of electricity and clouds came along, those who maintained &quot;belief&quot; in Thor, Zeus, and Wotan  were obstacles to accuracy.  In the mere 200(?) years science has been around (science didn't exist prior to the 1600's) the ancient religions have been challenged and have lost, over and over again.  Racism, slavery, arranged marriage, and monarchy were all supported by unprovable religious views.  Racism, slavery, arranged marriage, and monarchy did not fall until people demanded better answers.

::(There are times when I wish science was, itself, a religion, with a deity.  I'm really grateful to it for the abolition of racism, slavery, arranged marriage, and monarchy.  The profound emotions of my gratitude and my respect will probably just have to go to waste.  Drats.)

::The more neurologists figure out how thinking and memory and emotions actually work, the more the 'spirit' believers have to look elsewhere for worthy evidence-- Science demands there has to be more than &quot;I just can't believe it happens because of a brain and hormones like oxytocin.&quot;  Should we ''not'' research how the conscious functions because we should be happy with the common religious explanation that we all have a &quot;soul&quot;?

::A religion fails to qualify as science when it fails to subject itself to peer review.  A religion fails to qualify as science if it fails to require that published information cite a pedigree to permit independent checking of its accuracy.  A religion fails to qualify as science  when it fails to write why its leading competitors could &quot;get things so wrong&quot;.  The list of differences goes on and on.  Science has rules called the [[scientific method]].

::Okay, ''maybe'' some religions began as honest attempts to explain things way-back-when.  But, science is alot more than merely &quot;trying to explain things&quot;.  It also includes, being willing to let concepts go, not ordering people to &quot;believe&quot;, as many religions do.  Science says, &quot;Belief has to be rightfully earned-- and '''keep on being earned'''-- in the face of new information.&quot;  &quot;Belief&quot;, for a scientifically-minded person, means commitment to an idea-- but only so long as the idea is supportable.  Scientists have to be faithless, abandoning theories when there are better ones.  I prefer not to use the word &quot;faithless&quot; here.  I'd rather remain &quot;faith-free&quot;.  Faith is adherence to an idea in spite of evidence against it.  (If there ''was'' evidence, it wouldn't be &quot;faith&quot;, it'd be &quot;a conclusion.&quot;)
(--ThinkFest)

:: To answer what I think is your question, religion and science are generally considered to operate in different realms, with different methodologies.  Religion operates through introspection , received teaching and appeal to ancient texts.  Religious teaching is usually established by a hierarchy, promulgated from authorities to ordinary people, and rarely changes, regardless of human progress. That's why it's called religious &quot;dogma&quot;. Science operates though observation of natural phenomena, and attempts to explain and predict by developing principles or &quot;laws&quot; that encompass the observations and provide a basis for understanding them.  While science has its hierarchies and cherished principles, these are all ultimately subject to new findings, deeper understanding and new principles that encompass and extend the old.   Religion does not do this.  This is not to say that psychological or social insights cannot be gained from religious practice, but as a method for finding truth about the natural world, religion doesn't even come close to science.  [[User:Talkingtomypocket|Talkingtomypocket]] 23:39, 1 July 2007 (UTC)

::While understanding that religion and science are different ways of approaching the world, you seem to be interested in similarities among world religions.  I can recommend two of the classic texts in the field, both available on Amazon.
::The Perennial Philosophy  by Aldous Huxley
::The Varieties of Religious Experience by William James
::You can look at the Wikipedia articles on Huxley and James to get a feeling for these guys. These were some cool old dudes.  [[User:Talkingtomypocket|Talkingtomypocket]] 23:53, 1 July 2007 (UTC)

== Controversy Section ==

Why does this article start with the Controversy, before anyone has a chance to understand what supernatural even is?

Secondly, I had to quit reading because there was more in the article about Materialism, than there was about Supernatural. Hegelian Dialectic does not inform, but clouds the actual topic.

Third, since the article has be usurped and is about Materialism (nominally, marginally, about Supernatural) then we need to examine Materialism's follies. Materialism is a subjective view of the universe, starting with bias, and ending with the same bias (&quot;I think only the physical universe exists&quot;). Hence Materialism belies itself. 
I could go on. Can we make this article about Supernatural, please? [[Special:Contributions/99.161.154.162|99.161.154.162]] ([[User talk:99.161.154.162|talk]]) 17:52, 11 June 2008 (UTC)

OK, I have tried to improve section 1, paragraph 2, the part after the quotes. Please examine my edits.  I have also eliminated references to Superman and Wolverine as these are purely fictional, not supernatural.  [[User:Talkingtomypocket|Talkingtomypocket]] 00:39, 2 July 2007 (UTC)

== &quot;Many claimed supernatural phenomena vanish when they are examined closely.&quot;  ==

Usually the phenomenon doesn’t vanish. The grill cheese sandwich with what looks like a likeness of Jesus is still there. It is usually the case that the explanation of the phenomena in terms of a specific version of the supernatural is found to be inadequate or inferior in predictive power to other explanations. This article as well as many others in Wikipedia suffers from a lack of distinction between the phenomena and a specific explanation. [[User:Gkochanowsky|Gkochanowsky]] ([[User talk:Gkochanowsky|talk]]) 18:11, 11 December 2007 (UTC)
: Agreed!  WP needs to be more objective in its NPOV.  ''Supernatural'' is more of a lack of explanation than an explanation. [[User:Mike0001|Mike0001]] ([[User talk:Mike0001|talk]]) 21:16, 14 February 2008 (UTC)

== Restored NPOV ==

I noticed a bias in the Arguments For and Against sections and have removed it.   [[User:Mike0001|Mike0001]] ([[User talk:Mike0001|talk]]) 21:13, 14 February 2008 (UTC)

I think thats a good idea[[User:Tutonite|Tutonite]] ([[User talk:Tutonite|talk]]) 04:00, 3 March 2008 (UTC)

== The Supernatural is Not Real ==

I am going to end this argument: God is not real, and that is final. The supernatural is not real either, because the definition of the word &quot;supernatural&quot; means &quot;anything that breaks the laws of nature and/or physics&quot;.--[[Special:Contributions/98.199.76.184|98.199.76.184]] ([[User talk:98.199.76.184|talk]]) 08:17, 29 July 2008 (UTC)
:I realise it's a while since the above comment was posted, and that replying to it probably doesn't qualify as improving the article.  There again, this sort of reasoning is often applied by atheists and other sceptics when arguing against the existence of paranormal phenomena and gods and the like, and given their claims to a greater rationality I think it's important to highlight the faulty logic involved in ''this particular argument''.  (I should declare that I am a polytheist myself, but don't intend this comment to be taken as an argument for the existence of any given phenomenon.)

:98.199.76.184 is quite correct to say that &quot;the supernatural is not real&quot;.  By definition, anything that exists - and is therefore real - is natural.  Because nature encompasses everything that exists, nothing exists that is outside of nature.  Nature is all things that are real, and nothing unreal exists.  Logic allows us to say that if there is no evidence for something there is no reason to assume its existence.  However, it's backwards logic to declare something supernatural and then use the fact that it's been so declared as evidence that it doesn't exist. - [[User:Laterensis|Laterensis]] ([[User talk:Laterensis|talk]]) 07:32, 20 August 2009 (UTC)

== Arguements against a Supernatual reality ==

&quot;Many suggested supernatural phenomena vanish when they are examined closely. There have been, for example, various studies on astrology, most of them with negative results[7][8][9][10][11](a single positive result cannot outweigh many negative ones, as it can be expected by mere chance).&quot;

: Ok here is something to ponder, ... as per the previous statement a single affirmattive answer cannot outweigh multiple negative ones... What does that make math? Because we all know that 2+2=4, 3*3=9, 100/4=25, and 3-2=1. Also that none of the following are corect 2*2=5, 6+5=12, 10/2=3, and 6-6=1. Personaly, I belive that arguement has no legs to stand on. 

--[[User:Integraracer1989|Integraracer1989]] ([[User talk:Integraracer1989|talk]]) 13:38, 5 August 2008 (UTC)Integraracer1989 09:36 EDT  20080805

: A bit too late, but I couldn't resist answering this one. Your logic is completely flawed. The statement says that more negative than positive studies/evaluations on a claim/a set of claims (like astrology) means that the claim(s) are wrong. Saying that 2*2=5 isn't even evaluating anything. If you say it's evaluating the &quot;correctness&quot; of mathematics ... it's not. Mathematics is not a claim. Like science, it's a method, a way of doing things. --[[User:Wj32|wj32]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Wj32|t]]/[[Special:Contributions/Wj32|c]]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:51, 1 March 2009 (UTC)

==Cdesign proponentsist==
&quot;[[William A. Dembski|William Dembski]] writes: &quot;For the theist attempting to understand nature, God as creator is fundamental, the creation is derivative, and nature as the physical part of creation is still further downstream&quot;.[http://acs.ucsd.edu/~idea/dembskivantill.htm] {{Dead link|date=July 2008}}&quot; While he's better qualified as a theologian than as a mathematician or scientist, he's not a reliable source, so I've removed it. . . [[User:Dave souza|dave souza]], [[User talk:Dave souza|talk]] 13:30, 27 October 2008 (UTC)

: It also isn't clear in that context what he's saying and there are UNDUE issues since he isn't a major theologian. Good call. [[User:JoshuaZ|JoshuaZ]] ([[User talk:JoshuaZ|talk]]) 02:52, 28 October 2008 (UTC)
==Merge with paranormal?==
According to the first sentences of [[Supernatural]] and [[Paranormal]], the difference is that the former describes &quot;entities, events or powers &amp;hellip; that &amp;hellip; lack any clear scientific explanation&quot; while the latter describes &quot;unusual experiences that lack any obvious scientific explanation.&quot;  As it stands these distinctions do not seem sufficiently clear-cut to warrant keeping these articles separate, which would argue for merging them.  If however there is a substantive difference then it needs to be brought out more clearly in the first sentence of each article.  At present Wikipedia is in effect claiming that they're essentially the same thing without explaining why they need two articles.  --[[User:Vaughan Pratt|Vaughan Pratt]] ([[User talk:Vaughan Pratt|talk]]) 03:46, 20 December 2008 (UTC)
:Any objections to merging [[Supernatural]] with [[Paranormal]]?  One obvious objection is that there's a nontrivial amount of material in both articles, which will take some work to reconcile.  --[[User:Vaughan Pratt|Vaughan Pratt]] ([[User talk:Vaughan Pratt|talk]]) 11:30, 7 January 2009 (UTC)

::Might be possible to be merged after one missing differentiator is properly formulated in both articles. Namely, from the scientific perspective, supernatural is something totally beyond control e.g. miracles, thus lack the possibility of scientific verification through repetition, while as in the context of paranormal e.g. ghost hunting, some sort of communication is under consideration at least. --[[User:Marttir|Marttir]] ([[User talk:Marttir|talk]]) 23:02, 15 March 2009 (UTC)

&quot;Arguments in favor of a supernatural reality&quot;
- I feel kind of cheated. No argument was actually presented!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/80.217.64.175|80.217.64.175]] ([[User talk:80.217.64.175|talk]]) 17:49, 19 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::Could you please specify your wish in more detail? Reality is something that comes from the nature, unlike supernatural. For me, supernatural reality is absurd like the question, what was before time? --[[User:Marttir|Marttir]] ([[User talk:Marttir|talk]]) 20:18, 21 March 2009 (UTC)

== What about this contention? ==

See link: [http://www.ukresident.com/forums/index.php?showtopic=91321 A Secondary World with codes]
--[[User:Ved036|Ved from Victoria Institutions]] ([[User talk:Ved036|talk]]) 17:33, 17 March 2009 (UTC)

== This article is hopelessly confused ==

This article requires a sharp etymological account of the term &quot;supernatural&quot;.  When was it first used?  How has it been applied?  And so on.
Is the term &quot;supernatural&quot; contemporary with natural philosophy (BCE 15th 16th) as it would seem to be?  If
so, it stands against the developing structures of explanation of natural philosophy,
which became science.  It would then indeed be a term used to either denigrate
or denote a phenomena that was yet to be explained by natural philosophy and, later, science.  This surely cannot be an article that deals with the profundity of ontology, since the term &quot;supernatural&quot; is so caught up in an embattled relationship with burgeoning science.

But the whole is confused anyway.  It is not clear that the topic deals with science, and science is confused with materialism/physicalism at different points.  Science is not, as I think some other contributors have pointed out, the same thing as materialism - one (science) is a practice, the other (materialism) is a philosophical stance that may explain such a practice in metaphysical terms.  Surely the purpose of the article is to define the term &quot;supernatural&quot; and give examples of its usage, not organise a horse-race between science and religion or ghosts or whatever else is being proposed here.

The admittedly weighty debates that people are understandably keen on engaging with should occur in the talk section on the &quot;ontology&quot; entry.  [[Special:Contributions/121.45.57.202|121.45.57.202]] ([[User talk:121.45.57.202|talk]]) 15:06, 13 April 2009 (UTC)

:But if you make proposals about improvements, then there is '''hope''' for the article!(?) [[User:Rursus|Rursus]] dixit. ([[User talk:Rursus|&lt;span style=&quot;color: red; background: #FFFF80&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;u&gt;bork&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]!) 11:34, 6 January 2011 (UTC)

== Deletion of 'A word for unexplained events' ==
This view is essentially subset of the following &quot;Another part of a larger nature&quot; (the title of which should probably be changed).
Lynn Thorndike's thesis concerns Christian Europe during the early middle ages, during which time the scientific method was not in use.  Many Greek schools of thought, such as the Epicurean school, considered the universe as primarily a natural phenomenon centuries before the scientific method.  Similarly, early Buddhism also denied supernatural and magical explanations.  I am deleting this view as it is redundant and in error by merit of being too culturally specific (if it is valid at all).[[Special:Contributions/24.80.229.203|24.80.229.203]] ([[User talk:24.80.229.203|talk]]) 00:13, 25 June 2009 (UTC)

==Odd questions about landscape features==
I know its probably not the place to ask, but I don't care -- I don't want to eff with wikipedia's forums. Some years ago I came across a book talking about the man-made phenomena of placing buildings in a series of towns, i.e. a church with a tall steeple in the center of town, so that they line up with a similar tall building in the next town, which lines up with a structure on a hilltop nearby, and so on. What's the name of this? You can draw a perfectly straight line through the series of markers, and they can go for many many miles. Apparently there are a number of places in the UK where this can be observed. Maybe this is more of an occult question than a supernatural one? --[[User:RyanTee82|RyanTee82]] ([[User talk:RyanTee82|talk]]) 08:34, 31 October 2009 (UTC)

== Last bullet in the 'Arguments against' section ==

&quot;Humans in good mental health are capable of '''simulating perceptions that do not exist'''. This is commonly known as Hallucinations in the sane.&quot;

And then, your definition of 'hallucination':

&quot;A hallucination, in the broadest sense, is a '''perception''' in the absence of a stimulus.&quot; 

So is a hallucination a perception or not, Wikipedia?

I would have to deduce on my own (because Wikipedia fails to explain why this last bullet is an argument against the supernatural), that the only reason this is even in the article is in an attempt to suggest that religious visions can be explained by naturally (i.e. they are just 'hallucinations in the sane'). Considering Wikipedia's unattended bias towards all things secular, it would make sense that there such a specific agenda exists. But since credibility (or what is left of it) is on the line, the agenda is to remain as subtle as possible. It's almost like an art form. Wikipedia is just one giant easel.

Don't you realize that you're not kidding anyone with this site? Anyone with a reasonably developed intellect can quite easily find major philosophical flaws in the majority of content Wikipedia hosts. Is this site meant to appeal only to those who cannot think critically? Those kind of people no one cares about anyway, so what is the point of such a site? What does it matter if you can brainwash the dumb?

==The edit referring to the Haitian earthquake as supernatural seems inappropriate==

A recent edit holds that &quot;Some Christian religious evangelists and news commentators, like Pat Robertson and Bill OReilly&lt;nowiki&gt;[sic]&lt;/nowiki&gt;, have stated that the massive earthquakes (such as the Haitian Earthquake in January 2010) were caused due to a 'pact' made with the Christian Devil.&quot;

This is not factual and is poorly worded. Bill O'Reilly disagrees with Robertson's claims that Haiti is cursed [http://www.billoreilly.com/show?action=viewTVShow&amp;showID=2515 [Summary of Bill O'Reilly show 2515.]]. And although Robertson did make such a comment as a part of an attempt to drum up sympathy and support for a relief effort, it seems a distortion of his remarks to present them as saying this devil is Christian. According to other sources, the Haitians who were involved in the 1791 voodoo rite referred to by Robertson also believed they were invoking an enemy of the Christian deity [http://thelouvertureproject.org/index.php?title=Bois_Ca%C3%AFman [Bois Caïman]]. So it was not an appeal that was made from a Christian perspective either.

Furthermore, the edit, by using &quot;some&quot;, seems to claim that this view is somewhat widespread among evangelists and news commentators, and lends more weight than seems appropriate. I see little evidence that this view is not unique to Robertson. It just seems based on the idea that there are some people who will believe anything and thus that additional support for any idea can be assumed. I think &quot;at least one&quot; would be better than &quot;some&quot;, and it would probably be better to leave off the quantifier altogether and simply attribute the belief to Robertson.

It also seems unbalanced to refer to Robertson's belief in the substance and supernatural consequences of the voodoo rite without also referring to other sources about the 1791 rite itself and to Haitian beliefs about its supernatural consequences, and also to the many (including Bill O'Reilly) who have dismissed the supernatural link with the recent earthquakes. Why present only Robertson's side of the story? And why present it at all if such short shrift is to be given to any of the more widely-held views of the historical events?

In my opinion, it is a hard example to present with disinterest given the gravity of recent circumstances. Maybe the edit should simply be undone.
--[[User:Mazzula|Mazzula]] ([[User talk:Mazzula|talk]]) 23:14, 18 January 2010 (UTC)

:Removed along with other unsourced stuff. Tagged several sections as unsourced. [[User:Vsmith|Vsmith]] ([[User talk:Vsmith|talk]]) 02:43, 29 January 2010 (UTC)

== The term &quot;supernatural&quot; in Christian Theology? ==

Some words about what the theology of different Christian churches considers supernatural or not, would be very welcome. -- [[Special:Contributions/92.229.155.131|92.229.155.131]] ([[User talk:92.229.155.131|talk]]) 13:05, 29 April 2010 (UTC)
I believe supernatural also means Angel Or Demon for a small fact that humans are not the only things in space or this planet @ all. I certainly belive it can also mean Vampires and things of that nature. I also see that no one else w/ all this knowledge wants to explain this to us @ all because they believe human are stupid and will never find a loop hole to these meanings. I/we can outsmart them all.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jarrice|Jarrice]] ([[User talk:Jarrice|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jarrice|contribs]]) 06:27, 24 April 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Why is half the article focused on Catholicism ==

Half of this article (or more) is dedicated to Catholic views about supernaturalism.  Does anyone else find that ridiculous?  If it's not ridiculous, then can someone please explain why so much space is devoted to Catholic views?  Where are the Islam views or the Buddhist views if we're going to devote so much space to the religious aspect of supernaturalism?  NPOV much?  [[User:SuperAtheist|SuperAtheist]] ([[User talk:SuperAtheist|talk]]) 12:55, 3 November 2011 (UTC)

:No, ridiculous how? ''History''. Would you prefer an article half the size? What Buddhist and Muslim views do Buddhists and Muslims consider supernatural? What is the not–religious aspect and what POV would that be, exactly?—[[User talk:Machine Elf 1735|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#00FADE 0.05em 0.05em 0.07em;white-space: nowrap;font-family: Fraktur, Mathematica6, Georgia, sans-serif&quot;&gt;Machine Elf &lt;sup style=&quot;font-size:75%;font-family: Georgia, sans-serif&quot;&gt;1735&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:57, 3 November 2011 (UTC)

== What does this sentence mean? ==

&quot;the metaphysical considerations can be difficult to approach as an exercise in philosophy or theology because any dependencies on its antithesis, the natural, will ultimately have to be inverted or rejected. &quot;

[[User:Peterdjones|1Z]] ([[User talk:Peterdjones|talk]]) 13:02, 25 January 2012 (UTC)

:That more recent theology wouldn't tend to emphasize the term, nor would modern philosophy embrace the term in connection with historically relevant topics in metaphysics. At first approximation, the supernatural being the antithesis of the natural, both understood in contradistinction (in this context, as opposed to unnatural, etc).
:Apart from anthropic considerations, the natural, as a synonym for ''existence'' or the Universe, (multiverse or what not), doesn't call for a supernatural in any obvious way. But for social/historical or polemic reasons, the term is suggestive of this dichotomy (again, where applicable). The difference would seem to be one of ontological inequality: characteristically, that in some way (preferably inexplicable) the existence (or being) of the natural is derivative of, created by, dependent upon or otherwise inferior to (below) the supernatural. And of course, from a different perspective, that the supernatural is nothing more than a fiction. Allowing that fictions exist in some way, (e.g. $), it would likewise be as a derivation, creation, dependency or anyway, wholly supervene upon the natural.
:Historically, the two perspectives were sympatico with natural philosophy/science being the study of what happens under the heavens, and theology the study of that which is above, (somewhat figuratively). What would be a syncretic “mystery” remix of Plato's “world of Forms”, not that I mean to imply anything, the [[Ship of Theseus]] comes to mind. 
:So, to ground the natural in the supernatural, a scholastic theologian might start with various natural world analogs, but any logical dependency would have to be inverted. Not unlike the notion of pulling oneself up by one's bootstraps, any suggestion it's meant literally would be rejected.—[[User talk:Machine Elf 1735|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#00FADE 0.05em 0.05em 0.07em;white-space: nowrap;font-family: Fraktur, Mathematica6, Georgia, sans-serif&quot;&gt;Machine Elf &lt;sup style=&quot;font-size:75%;font-family: Georgia, sans-serif&quot;&gt;1735&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 13:13, 26 January 2012 (UTC)

== Reverted bold deletion ==

I'm not sure what was meant by [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Supernatural&amp;diff=492081256&amp;oldid=491190458 off-topic], but that's clearly not the case.—[[User talk:Machine Elf 1735|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#00FADE 0.05em 0.05em 0.07em;white-space: nowrap;font-family: Fraktur, Mathematica6, Georgia, sans-serif&quot;&gt;Machine Elf &lt;sup style=&quot;font-size:75%;font-family: Georgia, sans-serif&quot;&gt;1735&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 08:48, 12 May 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>k5w2wznfcfj2wrdoybopn6su5kgmbpr</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
