<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Doctrine and Covenants</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1475191</id>
    <revision>
      <id>485468241</id>
      <parentid>483532769</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-04T07:26:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dimadick</username>
        <id>24198</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7299">{{Talk header}}
{{notaforum|personal beliefs, nor for [[Apologetics]]/[[Polemic]]s}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
 {{WikiProject Latter Day Saint movement|class=B|importance=high}}
 {{WikiProject Religious texts|class=B|importance=high}}
}}

==See also==
I pulled this, because I think this line is a bizarre bit of trivia that is not important to the article:  
:''The Doctrine and Covenants'' is often abbreviated as &quot;D&amp;C&quot; which many within Mormonism dislike because the abbreviation is also used for a medical procedure, [[dilation and curettage]], related to [[abortion]].  --[[User:John Hamer|John Hamer]] 02:04, 7 Feb 2005 (UTC)

I pulled this, because the source was not cited and the statement could not be verified.
:In 1876, the original Section 101 was removed{{Fact|date=April 2008}}.  Written and adopted in Joseph Smith's absence, it had included the text:
::&quot;Inasmuch as this Church of Christ has been reproached with the crime of fornication, and polygamy: we declare that we believe that one man should have one wife; and one woman but one husband, except in the case of death, when either is at liberty to marry again.&quot;  
:Replacing this section is the current Section 132, which discusses the now-discontinued doctrine of [[plural marriage]].
--[[User:Caysyka|Caysyka]] 12:17, 26 Nov 2006

There should be information in the article on what version if any the [[FLDS]] church uses. [[User:69.234.53.82|69.234.53.82]] 07:19, 14 February 2007 (UTC)

==Fair use rationale for Image:Doctrine&amp;Covenants.jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:Doctrine&amp;Covenants.jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in Wikipedia articles constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:Doctrine&amp;Covenants.jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is other other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 01:38, 3 June 2007 (UTC)

==Why LDS Church and CofC removed Lectures on Faith==
In the lead paragraphs, an editor ([[User:Jgstokes|Jgstokes]]) keeps providing a &quot;reason&quot; that the Lectures on Faith were removed from the D&amp;C. The &quot;reason&quot; provided by the editor is the reason given later in the article for the LDS Church removal, but this is not necessarily the same reason it was removed by the Community of Christ. The &quot;reason&quot; for removal should be left to the discussions of the D&amp;C in each individual church, not in the lead paragraph, since both the LDS Church and the Community of Christ removed the doctrine section of the D&amp;C independently and at different times.

This article is for the D&amp;C as published by both the LDS Church and Community of Christ (as well as other churches), which is perhaps the source of the confusion. It is not just about the LDS Church D&amp;C. [[User:Snocrates|Snocrates]] 04:38, 20 December 2007 (UTC)

==Section 103 of 1835 Edition==
The article claims that two sections were removed from the LDS edition of the D&amp;C after the 1835 edition: section 101 and 103. Though there were 103 sections in the 1835 edition, the final section was numbered 102. An error during preparation for publication resulted in two sections labeled 66. I can't find any reference to a section besides 101 that was removed in LDS editions subsequent to 1835.

:Please re-write your edit without the LDS POV re: S.101. Remember that what is there currently was written by consensus of editors from varying backgrounds. Any changes need references. Thanks. Best, [[User:A Sniper|A Sniper]] ([[User talk:A Sniper|talk]]) 22:11, 26 December 2008 (UTC)

::This section of the article is to discuss the LDS publication of the D&amp;C. The LDS rationale for removing 101 is appropriate here. Section 101 was removed at the same time as section 132 was added because 132 superseded 101. Stating that 101 is controversial is not a neutral point of view; rather I attempt to show why it is controversial--because the church later adopted plural marriage. Also, you need to find a reference for the assertion that section 103 was removed. Only section 101 was removed. Stating otherwise is incorrect (unless you can find a reference). [[Special:Contributions/66.182.78.73|66.182.78.73]] ([[User talk:66.182.78.73|talk]]) 20:23, 3 January 2009 (UTC)

==Section 160 (CofC)==
We're missing an external link to section 160 of the Community of Christ edition. All the other sections are linked to. Does anyone know why this is or where we can get a link to section 160? I can't find one on the CofC website. [[User:Good Olfactory|Good Ol’factory]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Good Olfactory|(talk)]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:44, 3 July 2008 (UTC)

:I don't know why that link is missing. I looked several months ago when I noticed the same thing, but had no success digging it up. Looked again today, same result. Perhaps it is no longer consider part of the COC canon. Sorry I can't be more help.--[[User:Jgstokes|Jgstokes-We can disagree without being disagreeable]] ([[User talk:Jgstokes|talk]]) 23:12, 4 July 2008 (UTC)

== FLDS &amp; AUB? ==
I think it might be valuable to included what version of the D&amp;C that is used by the [[FLDS]] and [[Apostolic United Brethren|AUB]].  I believe the contents of both of these sects D&amp;C is slightly different than the SLC-based church.  If anyone has a source of this information, perhaps it can be added. [[User:Surv1v4l1st|Surv1v4l1st]] ([[User talk:Surv1v4l1st|talk]]) 00:49, 22 February 2009 (UTC)

== date sorting ==

I want to re-sort the list of Doctrines and Covenants chronologically, but it seems to sort based of the alphabetical spelling of the date. Can this be fixed???  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.162.156.99|99.162.156.99]] ([[User talk:99.162.156.99|talk]]) 04:20, 8 January 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Fixed it myself. [[Special:Contributions/99.162.156.99|99.162.156.99]] ([[User talk:99.162.156.99|talk]]) 08:15, 8 January 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ry30wotmutvtjoa91k5e88jvc1i4ati</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
