<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Parousia</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3739257</id>
    <revision>
      <id>258563654</id>
      <parentid>258563327</parentid>
      <timestamp>2008-12-17T12:36:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ambrosiaster</username>
        <id>7751874</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* I'm terribly sorry */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3538">The Jehovah's Witnesses belief is based simply on what Jesus himself stated in Matthew 24, refering to the signs of the times, or more correctly &quot;the signs of your coming/presence&quot;

:Matt 24:3 And as he sat upon the mount of Olives, the disciples came to him privately, saying, Tell us, when shall these things be? and what shall be the sign of your coming/presence, and of the conclusion of the world? 4And Jesus answered and said unto them, Take heed that no man deceive you. 5For many shall come in my name, saying, I am Christ; and will deceive many.  6And you will hear of wars and rumours of wars: see that you are not troubled: for all these things must take place, but the end is not yet.
:7For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom: and there shall be food shortages, and pestilences, and earthquakes, all over the earth. 8All these are the beginning of distress.
:9Then shall they deliver you up to be afflicted, and shall kill you: and you will be hated in all nations for my name's sake. 
:10And then many shall stumble, and shall betray one another, and shall hate one another.  11And many false prophets shall rise, and shall deceive many. 12And because lawlessness will increase, the love of many will grow cold. 
:13But he that endures to the end will be saved. 
:14And this good news of the kingdom shall be preached in all the world for a witness to all nations; and then the end shall come. 

Seeing as how these are all happening NOW should be of great concern to all Christians.  The question you would want to ask yourself is, Am I waiting for him to come and show himself, or am I living in accord with righteous requirements?  Because if we are just waiting, we are missing the signs.  And regardless if you are calling it a &quot;coming&quot; or a &quot;presence&quot; one thing is true, if someone &quot;comes&quot; they are going to &quot;arrive&quot;, and they will be &quot;present.&quot; ''(unsigned by [[User:Jamais]])''

---- 
It is not useful to forward Parousia to second coming. Parousia is usually used as a term to describe the expectance of the early Christian who awaited the second coming in their life time. --[[User:Benedikt|Benedikt]] 20:16, 31 May 2006 (UTC)
*Parousia = Second Coming.  All the various beliefs about it (when people though it was going to happen, etc.) can be described in [[Second Coming]].  It's better to have it at one article, it's less confusing that way.  --&lt;b&gt;[[User:JW1805|JW1805]]&lt;/b&gt; &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:JW1805|(Talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 03:41, 1 June 2006 (UTC)

==This is not a Jewish term==
Please don't put that in.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:LisaLiel|LisaLiel]] ([[User talk:LisaLiel|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/LisaLiel|contribs]]) 01:07, 6 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==I'm terribly sorry==
I'm terribly sorry, however, this phrase is, indeed, synonymous with the 'Second Coming'. All other encyclopedias, including Britannica and the Catholic Encyclopedia, have an immediate redirect to 'Second Coming' when Parousia is searched. Whether or not an obscure denomination of Christianity believes it to be otherwise, Roman Catholic, Protestant, and Eastern Orthodox dogma (roughly, oh... 98% of Christendom) believes it to be this way. If you feel that this subject needs to be touched upon, make an article entitled, 'The Parousia as Perceived by Jehovah's Witnesses'. That is all. -- [[User:Ambrosiaster|Ambrosiaster]] ([[User talk:Ambrosiaster|talk]]) 12:34, 17 December 2008 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>3vylldoyj466b0t8pdzzeyf7phn54rk</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
