<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Counter-Reformation</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4869556</id>
    <revision>
      <id>444997250</id>
      <parentid>444997092</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-08-15T16:40:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Underalms</username>
        <id>950352</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41988">{{WikiProject Christianity|class=Start|importance=High|theology-work-group=yes|theology-importance=High|catholicism=yes|catholicism-importance=High}}


==End of article is wanting==

This article is in need of a &quot;summary and legacy&quot; section at the end.  This article ends very abruptly and I think its inappropriate for a period of history that had so many reaching effects.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/205.172.134.23|205.172.134.23]] ([[User talk:205.172.134.23|talk]]) 20:56, 18 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==A lot of work to do here==
Wow, there is a lot of work to do here.  The treatment of Trent is very poor.  It should be outlined briefly by sessions without such sweeping statements with a POV tone.  Since Trent had numerous sessions over the course of several decades, it should be a recurring subheading.  There is so much material here that it should be first decided whether to organize it chronologically or thematically.  Previously, the structure was a real mess with Trent as a heading following be Reforms as a heading with the &quot;Reforms section being a continuation of the Trent discussion.  It is even confusing to describe it! this is gay how you can change this all you want.

Anyway, am chipping away at this, if anyone out there is interested, give me a holler!--[[User:Vaquero100|Vaquero100]] 00:36, 4 May 2006 (UTC)

== 
I've deleted the signed comment suggesting this page be moved.  If the move is uncontroversial, just do it.  If you expect the move to be controversial, follow the procedure described at [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]].  --[[User:Stebulus|Stebulus]] 03:28, 12 June 2006 (UTC)

==Requested move to Catholic Reformation==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived debate of the {{{type|proposal}}}. &lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/font&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the debate was no consensus for the move --[[User:Philip Baird Shearer|Philip Baird Shearer]] 22:06, 22 June 2006 (UTC)

I would like to propose that this article be moved to &quot;Catholic Reformation.&quot;  There are several good reasons for this.
First, it was a reform in the Church.  &quot;Counter Reformation&quot; makes it sound like it was anti-reform, which is clearly not true.  Second, &quot;Counter Reformation&quot; also makes it sound like it was only a response to the &quot;Protestant Reformation.&quot;  This is only partially true.  Many of the reforms of the Catholic Reformation are not particularly related to Luther or his successors.  These aspects include: the profound spiritual movements of the spanish mystics and the French school of spirituality as well as the development of the seminary syste
--[[User:Vaquero100|Vaquero100]] 07:51, 24 May 2006 (UTC)

[[Counter-Reformation]] → '''[[Catholic Reformation]]''' &amp;mdash; The term &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; implies that the movement was anti-reform.  &quot;Catholic Reformation&quot; is the more accurate term as it describes a reform within the Catholic Church.  This has become the academically accepted term. --[[User:Vaquero100|Vaquero100]] 05:48, 12 June 2006 (UTC)

===Survey===

*I '''support''' such a move, for the reason that ''Catholic Reformation'' is the preferred term among many scholars today. [[User:Maestlin|Maestlin]] 14:52, 24 May 2006 (UTC)

*'''Oppose strongly''': The term Counter Reformation is by far the most commonly used term in English for this historic movement. Even the Catholic Encylcopedia uses the term Counter Reformation as an article title. Even if there is a growing movement among '''some''' scholars as some above suggest to use Catholic Reformation the term has not established itself in common usage. This is an encyclopedia and it seems more fitting of an encyclopedia to use the commonly used term for an event. I think using the title Counter Reformation with a mention of the term Catholic Reformation in the first paragraph is sufficient - this is also what Encyclopedia Britannica does. I certainly see no reason to abandon the more commonly used term as the article title for one that is far less used. --[[User:Westee|Westee]] 13:24, 31 May 2006 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' Counter Reformation is the common name. --[[User:Philip Baird Shearer|Philip Baird Shearer]] 16:41, 13 June 2006 (UTC)
*'''Strongly Support'''  Catholic Reformation is the term currently favored by academics and Counter-Reformation is a misnomer at best.  As a reform movement within Catholicism, Catholic Reformation is the only term that makes sense.  Those searching for Counter-Reformation will find the article without difficulty by redirect.   --[[User:Vaquero100|Vaquero100]] 19:17, 13 June 2006 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per Westee. [[User:Duja|Duja]] 10:27, 14 June 2006 (UTC)
*'''Support''' The renaming does make sense, and is used. Popular culture uses Counter reformation, but popular culture also uses AD/BC dates, and at wikipedia many editors have pushed that issue as well. Catholic Reformation is the NPoV term, IMHO. [[User:Dominick|Dominick]] [[User_talk:dominick|&lt;sup&gt;(TALK)&lt;/sup&gt;]] 14:03, 14 June 2006 (UTC)
* '''Strongly support''' per Vaquero100. [[User:GrumpyTroll|'''Grumpy Troll''']] [[User talk:GrumpyTroll|&lt;sup&gt;(talk)&lt;/sup&gt;]] 16:59, 14 June 2006 (UTC).
* &lt;s&gt;'''oppose'''&lt;/s&gt; '''abstain''' &lt;s&gt;When we encourage editors to use veifiable referenced material, it is suggested that we use an unrefferenced title! (or at least far less referenced)&lt;/s&gt; [[User:ClemMcGann|ClemMcGann]] 17:16, 14 June 2006 (UTC)
*'''Very strong oppose''' I had never even ''heard'' the term &quot;Catholic Reformation&quot; before coming to this talk page. It is quite commonly referred to as the Counter-Reformation even by [[Richard McBrien|Catholic scholars]]. [http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060653043/ref=pd_lpo_k2_dp_k2a_2_txt/103-2336020-4411849?%5Fencoding=UTF8] —'''[[User:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;Mi&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:MiraLuka/Userboxes|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot;&gt;a&lt;/font&gt;]]''' 01:05, 15 June 2006 (UTC)
*:Comments moved to discussion section below. —'''[[User:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;Mi&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:MiraLuka/Userboxes|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot;&gt;a&lt;/font&gt;]]''' 01:57, 15 June 2006 (UTC)
* '''Oppose''' Counter-Reformation is the most common in both popular usage and scholarship.--[[User:Aldux|Aldux]] 18:04, 16 June 2006 (UTC)
* '''weak support''' The name &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; is generic and must go.[http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=893825][http://www.danielpipes.org/comments/19648][http://www.ppionline.org/ndol/ndol_ci.cfm?kaid=125&amp;subid=163&amp;contentid=252286][http://www.baptist2baptist.net/b2barticle.asp?ID=227][http://www.boydell.co.uk/43832089.HTM].  Where the article should go is less clear.  The term most familiar to me is actually &quot;Catholic Counter-Reformation.&quot;  &quot;Catholic Reformation of the 16th Century&quot; might work too.  [[User:Gimmetrow|Gimmetrow]] 23:58, 18 June 2006 (UTC)
*'''Weak oppose''' - I personally feel that Catholic Reformation is more accurate and seems to be gaining usage among (admittedly, most catholic) scholars. However, it has not yet even come close to overtaking Counter-Reformation in common usage. Perhaps once the next generation of text books comes out with the new name, then we should change it. A redirect and a bold in the intro (as exist now), I strongly support. Perhaps a more thourough discussion of the name within the article would be appropriate, as a side note. [[User:Savidan|savidan]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:Savidan|(talk)]] [[Wikipedia:Esperanza|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#008000;&quot;&gt;(e@)&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 03:27, 19 June 2006 (UTC)

===Discussion===

'''Comment''' Would anyone object if the circular redirect and signed comment were removed from the front page? [[User:Maestlin|Maestlin]] 16:16, 31 May 2006 (UTC)

I just removed the signed comment without reading your comments here. --[[User:84.153.53.206|84.153.53.206]] 17:13, 31 May 2006 (UTC)

A singular voice of opposition is not enough to justify ceasing the question.  --[[User:Vaquero100|Vaquero100]] 00:31, 10 June 2006 (UTC)

:'''Vaquero100''', suggesting a move is a legitimate action and there are procedures for doing so. There are templates for signalling all sorts of problems with articles. But editorial comments about the article, like yours, do not belong in the article itself. They belong on the talk page. Part of Wikipedia's policy is to avoid or at least minimize self-reference in the text of articles. Removing your comment does not mean anyone is putting an end to the question, because the question is properly inquired here, on the talk page. [[User:Maestlin|Maestlin]] 16:00, 12 June 2006 (UTC)

Excuse me if this has already been addressed, but what do recent undergraduate history texts call it? [[User:Tom harrison|Tom Harrison]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Tom harrison|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:10, 13 June 2006 (UTC)


'''Moved from survey section''' I had never even ''heard'' the term &quot;Catholic Reformation&quot; before coming to this talk page. It is quite commonly referred to as the Counter-Reformation even by [[Richard McBrien|Catholic scholars]]. [http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060653043/ref=pd_lpo_k2_dp_k2a_2_txt/103-2336020-4411849?%5Fencoding=UTF8] —'''[[User:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;Mi&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:MiraLuka/Userboxes|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot;&gt;a&lt;/font&gt;]]''' 01:05, 15 June 2006 (UTC)
:'''Additional note''': A Google search gives 631,000 results for &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; and 99,000 for &quot;Catholic Reformation.&quot; —'''[[User:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;Mi&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:MiraLuka/Userboxes|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot;&gt;a&lt;/font&gt;]]''' 01:05, 15 June 2006 (UTC)

:::Sorry, I don't see the relevance of this page. [[User:Maestlin|Maestlin]] 19:45, 14 June 2006 (UTC)

:::Regarding the google hits, the term &quot;counter-reformation&quot; is very generic. Searching for &quot;counter-reformation&quot; + &quot;catholic&quot; (so that it at least has some relation to catholicism) drops the hits to 338,000 results. Note [http://www.boydell.co.uk/43832089.HTM ''The Arts of the Anglican Counter-Reformation'']. [[User:Gimmetrow|Gimmetrow]] 16:27, 22 June 2006 (UTC)

Maestin, you have cited the most controversial and least repected of &quot;Catholic theologians.&quot;  Read again more closely [[Richard McBrien]]'s article and you will see he is listed as a dissident and his principal work is banned for use with college students.  --[[User:Vaquero100|Vaquero100]] 20:11, 14 June 2006 (UTC)

:::I didn't cite it, someone who didn't sign their comments did. Please review the history of the talk page. The only thing I wrote is &quot;Sorry, I don't see the relevance of this page,&quot; referring to the link to some amazon.com review. [[User:Maestlin|Maestlin]] 20:32, 14 June 2006 (UTC)

:::What is the source for the claim that his principle work is banned? (PS the &quot;Additional note&quot; below is not by me either.) [[User:Maestlin|Maestlin]] 23:30, 14 June 2006 (UTC)

::::Sorry about that, that was me who forgot to sign. And this is perhaps a better link [http://www.amazon.com/gp/sitbv3/reader/ref=sib_dp_pt/103-2336020-4411849?%5Fencoding=UTF8&amp;asin=0060653043]. The book I linked to uses &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; in one of its section titles, and actually throughout the whole thing (I own a copy). And, as his article says, McBrien is a professor of theology at [[University of Notre Dame|Notre Dame]], he can't be as horrible as you seem to think he is. —'''[[User:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;Mi&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:MiraLuka/Userboxes|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot;&gt;a&lt;/font&gt;]]''' 01:05, 15 June 2006 (UTC)
::::''More links'' The [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04437a.htm Catholic Encyclopedia] uses &quot;Counter-Reformation.&quot; The [http://www.vatican.va/phome_en.htm official Vatican site] uses both.[http://vatican.mondosearch.com/search_en.aspx?query=%22counter-reformation%22][http://vatican.mondosearch.com/search_en.aspx?query=%22counter-reformation%22] —'''[[User:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;Mi&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:MiraLuka/Userboxes|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot;&gt;a&lt;/font&gt;]]''' 02:14, 15 June 2006 (UTC)


Count at least one other supporter for this proposal.  Know that he is not a Catholic, but a firm believer that this movement was a response to Humanism before it was a response to Protestantism (a response to Humanism which counted among its tennets a rejection of intercessors, and therefore the Catholic Church).  
Another thing: why is there no mention of catechism in an article about the Catholic Reformation?

:I don't think whether or not this was a reaction to the Reformation is at issue here. We're determining what this event is most usually called, not whether or not we think the name fits. From the [[WP:NAME|Wikipedia naming conventions]]: (emphasis mine)
:*&quot;article naming should give priority to what the '''majority of English speakers would most easily recognize'''&quot;
:*&quot;Names of Wikipedia articles should be optimized for readers over editors; and for a '''general audience over specialists'''.&quot;
:*&quot;Use the '''most common name''' of a person or thing that does not conflict with the names of other people or things.&quot;
:—'''[[User:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;Mi&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:MiraLuka|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;]][[User:MiraLuka/Userboxes|&lt;font color=&quot;Red&quot;&gt;a&lt;/font&gt;]]''' 05:50, 18 June 2006 (UTC)
&lt;/div&gt;

I know this is late but I support the change. [[User:Arthurian Legend|Arthurian Legend]] ([[User talk:Arthurian Legend|talk]]) 00:52, 13 December 2007 (UTC)

== Counter Reformation vs. Catholic Reformation ==

'''Counter Reformation''':
&lt;br&gt;GOAL: 
&lt;br&gt;to take back what the Catholic Church lost to Protestantism.
&lt;br&gt;PROBLEM: 
&lt;br&gt;Protestants didn't come back to the Catholic Church
&lt;br&gt;WANTED:
&lt;br&gt;One main church
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;VS
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;'''Catholic Reformation''':
&lt;br&gt;GOAL: 
&lt;br&gt;to reform Catholic Church (hence the name &quot;Catholic reformation&quot;)
&lt;br&gt;PROBLEM: 
&lt;br&gt;Popes aren't calling meetings because they are scared their authority will be lowered, 
&lt;br&gt;Finally decide that they will call [[Council of Trent]] because Protestantism is spreading fast!
&lt;br&gt;WANTED:
&lt;br&gt;Reform in Catholic Church
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;[[User:71.138.91.40|71.138.91.40]] 03:01, 11 October 2006 (UTC)AP STUDENT in HS

== NPOV? ==

The widely-used term &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; usually means not only the spiritual reformation of the Catholic Church, but also the violent trials to destroy the protestant movement. E.g. the Hugenots Wars and the Thirty Years War are usually seen as a part of the Counter-Reformation.

In this article, the war violence of the catholic powers is not mentioned at all. The protestants are named &quot;sects&quot;, and their eventual return to catholicism is described as fully peaceful. (In the reality, there were hundreds of thousands of victims.)

The article should be completed in this direction, or marked as non-NPOV. (I myself cannot do it because of my poor English.)

--[[User:M.m.h|M.m.h]] 13:07, 5 January 2007 (UTC)

:Hmmm... this comment has been sitting here without a response for four months.  I think M.m.h makes a valid point.  Unfortunately, this is not an area of expertise for me.  M.m.h, if you will attempt to write some text that addresses these issues, I will be glad to copyedit for you and insert it into the article.

:--[[User:Richardshusr|Richard]] 00:03, 9 May 2007 (UTC)

::I will try it to change the first information, so that both the main definitions of the term would be mentioned. --[[User:M.m.h|M.m.h]] 13:48, 27 May 2007 (UTC)

Sadly, I think that linking the term &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; to the violence due to [[religious intolerance]] between both Protestants and Catholics (who were equally guilty of such violence as were royalty who wished to excuse mass-murder under religious justifications) is a distraction.  Some actually believe that the [[Jesuits]] are sworn enemies of Protestantism willing to do whatever it takes to demolish the Protestant sects.  I know about this because someone from my church tried to excuse his admittedly anti-papist prejudice using such &quot;reasoning.&quot;

Protestants right after the Reformation were just as guilty of murdering Catholics as Catholics were of murdering Protestants.  Back then, folks in Europe were not as educated as they are today.  The [[Gutenberg Press]] was recently invented, and [[Martin Luther]]'s protest was just starting to get attention.  To slur present-day Catholics by using the past is akin to blaming German babies most recently born for the [[Holocaust]].  In other words, it is wholly inaccurate.

--[[User:Kulturvultur|Kulturvultur]] 04:46, 21 May 2007 (UTC)

: Numbers game, dude. Picture two groups, one that is relatively small (think less than 1/10 the size of the other at first) and one that is, comparatively, quite large. The big one is bent on imposing the options of destruction or assimilation on the smaller group; the smaller group is more focused on survival. And if that's not working so well, escape to America. (And yes, they go on to commit genocide there...but this is about Catholics and Protestants and what they did to each other). As far as that goes, it's not right for you to say Protestants and Catholics were doing the same exact things to each other. It's not accurate. That's a lie. You'll go back to talking about size disparity as soon as you feel like it does good things for you, but when you're on this topic you want to avoid it all of a sudden. How nice for you.

You are not right. It is not the question to blame somebody, but to describe the term as exactly as possible. At present, only one point of view, or one of several definitions is described. We should at least discern between (1) the counter-reformation as a movement within the catholic church and (2) the counter-reformation as a historical period. --[[User:M.m.h|M.m.h]] 13:48, 27 May 2007 (UTC)

: The Counter-reformation and the religious wars were not as linked as you think. The Huegnot war and the Thirty years war were initiated for purely political resons. This is seen by the fact that Henry of Navre, the Protestant King of France converted to Catholicism and that a century later Catholic France fought against Catholic HRE in favor of the protestant powers. Cite your references before making absurd suggestions that the religious wars were linked. I can't see any POV issues here. The counter-reformation was the peaceful way to bring Protestants back to Rome; the religious wars were politically motivated wars with a secondary objective of changing the religion of the vanquished. [[User:Tourskin|Tourskin]] ([[User talk:Tourskin|talk]]) 07:02, 13 December 2007 (UTC)

::You are mixing the concepts. I do not speak about religious wars only, but about the ''violent'' recatholization of some parts of Europe, not only ''during'', but also ''after'' the Thirty Years War in Bohemian lands, or a lot of local processes earlier. There was mostly no peaceful return of Protestants back to Rome. And there is a lot of sources about it, almost every book on history of that period, read e.g. '''http'''://'''www.tourmycountry.com/austria/history7.htm''' (it cannot be linked here): ''&quot;From around 1600, they launched a campaign called the counterreformation, which consisted of violent prosecutions and the expulsion of protestants (Salzburg expelled protestants in two waves, too)...&quot;'' (this was the first one in Google, you can find a lot of others).
::As I have written above, the concept &quot;counter-reformation&quot; is widely used not for the &quot;peaceful way etc.&quot;, but for the whole historical period of (mostly violent) recatholization in Europe. --[[User:Mmh|Mmh]] ([[User talk:Mmh|talk]]) 09:47, 11 May 2009 (UTC)

== Unsourced statement removed ==

I have removed the following statement, as it was tagged &quot;citation needed&quot; for several months.
*''This examination of the Copernican theory was a factor in starting the [[scientific revolution]] outside the Catholic Church, which banned the study of Galileo's works until the mid-eighteenth century.''
If anyone can find a source to back up this statement, feel free to re-add it. —[[User:Angr|'''An''']][[User talk:Angr|''gr'']] &lt;sup&gt;[[User:Angr/If|If you've written a quality article...]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:32, 25 December 2007 (UTC)

== Expand... ==

Can we expand [[Counter-Reformation#Spiritual Movements]]. I believe it's necessary for that's short it provides very little information. You only said about that [[Spirituali]], but that there are so many other movements have sprung up, including those seen on the introduction part of the article. -[[User:Pika ten10|Pika ten10]] ([[User talk:Pika ten10|talk]]) 06:38, 5 January 2008 (UTC) Well, I expanded. The Spirituali had according to the Wikipedia article here, Zero influence, so why include them? I could name 100 persons equally unimportant at that time --[[User:Ambrosius007|Ambrosius007]] ([[User talk:Ambrosius007|talk]]) 14:09, 8 July 2008 (UTC)

== Art ==

I'm surprised that there's nothing in the article about Counter-Reformation painting or other art forms except music, or the wider cultural project of the Counter-Reformation.  There is a separate entry on [[The Reformation and art]] which discusses both Protestant and Catholic art, but perhaps there should be a brief summary in this article.  I added a reference to the &quot;See also&quot; at the bottom, but that's not a substitute for a proper mention of visual arts, literature, etc, in the article body.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/193.172.19.20|193.172.19.20]] ([[User talk:193.172.19.20|talk]]) 17:41, 6 February 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: I don't know if that was an explicit part of the Counter-reformation. [[User:Tourskin|Tourskin]] ([[User talk:Tourskin|talk]]) 19:03, 8 April 2008 (UTC)

There should be something more here. -- [[User:Secisek|Secisek]] ([[User talk:Secisek|talk]]) 19:07, 8 April 2008 (UTC)
::Certainly there should; the Council of Trent made a number of specific pronouncements on both painting and music, which were both seen as part of the CR effort, and these had considerable influence on the development of these arts. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 15:53, 16 June 2008 (UTC)

== Oddity: counter-reformation reformation ==
Being a &quot;protestant&quot;, I cannot avoid criticise the idiotic term &quot;counter-reformation&quot;. OK, a reformation to counter reformations? The best way to counter-reform is to refuse to do anything... Isn't it instead a reformation in parallel, inspired by (the bad sides, mostly) of protestant reformation? This is '''my''' criticism, but shouldn't the name of the article be  &quot;''Roman-Catholic Revival''&quot;? Counter-reformation seems to be a bad term, since it gives the false reactionary impression about a constructive and progressive spiritual work. (??) ''&lt;span style=&quot;color: #800000; background-color: #FFFFA0; padding: 1px 2px 3px 2px&quot;&gt;Said: [[User:Rursus|&lt;span style=&quot;color: blue&quot;&gt;Rursus&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Rursus|&lt;span style=&quot;color: #800000&quot;&gt;☻&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;'' 09:33, 15 May 2008 (UTC)
:I agree that the term is - as you say - &quot;idiotic&quot;;  It should be ''Catholic Reformation'', there are plenty of references here: [http://solomon.dlcr.alexanderstreet.com//] [[User:ClemMcGann|ClemMcGann]] ([[User talk:ClemMcGann|talk]]) 09:55, 15 May 2008 (UTC)

==Requested move==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of the proposal. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the proposal was '''no move'''. [[User:JPG-GR|JPG-GR]] ([[User talk:JPG-GR|talk]]) 02:57, 23 June 2008 (UTC)

[[Counter-Reformation]] → [[Catholic Reformation]] — I see that this has been discussed here before, but it has been a while.  In my experience, Catholic Reformation is the scholarly norm; rejecting the earlier understanding (mostly originating among 19th protestant scholastic historians) that the reforms of Trent and the Jesuits were entirely reactionary.  I realize that this scholarly consensus is not necessarily reflected in online usage (i.e., g-hits), but most online sources are based on the 19th/early 20th cent. scholarship that has passed into the public domain. [[User:Pastordavid|Pastordavid]] ([[User talk:Pastordavid|talk]]) 18:28, 15 June 2008 (UTC) —[[User:Pastordavid|Pastordavid]] ([[User talk:Pastordavid|talk]]) 18:28, 15 June 2008 (UTC)

===Survey===
:''Feel free to state your position on the renaming proposal by beginning a new line in this section with'' &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;*'''Support'''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; ''or'' &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;*'''Oppose'''&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;'', then sign your comment with'' &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;~~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt;''. Since [[Wikipedia:Polling is not a substitute for discussion|polling is not a substitute for discussion]], please explain your reasons, taking into account [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions|Wikipedia's naming conventions]].''

*'''Support.''' See rationale above. [[User:Pastordavid|Pastordavid]] ([[User talk:Pastordavid|talk]]) 18:28, 15 June 2008 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' PD may well be right when it comes to church history, but &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; still is much the commoner term among general historians and eg art historians in my experience, so should be used by us under [[WP:COMMON]]. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 15:47, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
*'''Support''' - I agree with Pastordavid's argument. The redirect will still take people to the article from Counter-Reformation. -- [[User:Bpmullins|BPMullins]] | [[User talk:BPmullins|Talk]] 17:21, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' ''Counter-Reformation'' is the historic and more common term and there is no reason to use another term. I agree it was  &quot;Catholic&quot; and was a &quot;reform&quot; -- but so were many others reforms in church history before and since (such as Vatican II). To name it &quot;the Catholic Reformation&quot; as if that is ''the'' common or ''the'' clear term fails on both counts. --[[User:Carlaude|Carlaude]] ([[User talk:Carlaude|talk]]) 19:02, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. See [[WP:BIAS]]. The term &quot;counter-reformation&quot; was coined by Protestants who perceived their reformation as &quot;first.&quot; And Catholics as &quot;second.&quot; This tends to be an English language bias for the same reason. The term &quot;counter-&quot; was not used by Catholics who were mostly non-English speakers until the 20th century. We have generally used terms acceptable to the group we are talking about. i.e. We no longer term countries as &quot;backwards&quot; but &quot;developing.&quot; [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 21:30, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' Counter-Reformation is the more common term used and as per the policy [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions]] we should use what the greatest number of English speakers should recognise and that names should 'be optimized for readers over editors, and for a general audience over specialists'. Counter-Reformation is the name that a general audience will most recognise so should be used. [[User:Davewild|Davewild]] ([[User talk:Davewild|talk]]) 21:54, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' Google Books has 10,180 results for [http://books.google.com/books?q=%22counter+reformation%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books &quot;counter reformation&quot;], but only 1191 results for [http://books.google.com/books?q=%22catholic+reformation%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books &quot;catholic reformation&quot;]. [[User:Mcferran|Noel S McFerran]] ([[User talk:Mcferran|talk]]) 03:06, 17 June 2008 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' Per Mcferran and Carlaude. [[User:Guliolopez|Guliolopez]] ([[User talk:Guliolopez|talk]]) 11:38, 17 June 2008 (UTC)

===Discussion===
:''Any additional comments:''
''&quot;In my experience, Catholic Reformation is the scholarly norm.&quot;'' Sources please?  Also, while the scholarly norm may have changed, an encyclopedia should reflect more general usage for a wider audience. — &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid blue;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#fef;background:navy;&quot;&gt;''' AjaxSmack '''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 03:21, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
:Certainly.  Below is what I could quickly pull off my shelf.  I would argue that where a NPOV title is used in contrast to an additional widely used title, that is the purpose of redirects. [[User:Pastordavid|Pastordavid]] ([[User talk:Pastordavid|talk]]) 15:38, 16 June 2008 (UTC)
{{collapse top|Some sources, collapsed for readability}}
*Bruce Shelly, ''Church History in Plain Language'' 2nd ed.(Word Pub, 1995) 272: &quot;Some historians have intrepreted the Catholic Reformation as a counter-attack against Protestantism; others have described it as a genuine revival of Catholic piety with few thoughts of Protestantism.  The truth is the movement was both a Counter Reformation, as Protestants insist, and a Catholic Reformation, as Catholics argue.&quot;
*[[Alister McGrath]], ''Christian Theology'' 1st ed (Blackwell, 1994) 62: &quot;Catholic Reformation. The term is often used to refer to the revival within Roman Catholicism ... It is, however, becoming increasingly clear that the Roman Catholic church countered the Reformation partly by reforming itself from within, in order to remove the grounds of criticism.  In this sense, the movement was a reformation within the Roman Catholic church as much as it was a reaction against the Protestant Reformation.&quot;
*G. Gassman &amp; S. Hendrix, ''Fortress Introduction to the Lutheran Confessions'' (Fortress, 1999) 205: from the glossary; &quot;Counter-Reformation. A term formerly used for sixteenth century Roman Catholic reform as a whole, but now applied to Catholic reform only insofar as it rejected and reacted to the Protestant Reformation.&quot;
*Peter Marshall, &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; in ''Encyclopedia of Christianity&quot; ed. John Bowden (Oxford, 2005) 290: &quot;By convention, this process is known as the Counter-Reformation, though some scholars prefer Catholic Reformation, in order to make the point that it was more than just a negative reaction to the threat of Protestantism, and that early shoots of renewal could be detected before anyone had heard of Martin Luther.&quot;
{{collapse bottom}}
::The google searches linked in the survey above go to my point.  Where as the dates in the googles search for counter reformation are ''predominently'' prior to, say, 1980, the dates in the search for Catholic Reformation are all current scholarship.  The shift has occured in the scholarly community, leaving a minority using Coutner-Reformation, because it is seen to be an inherently biased and POV term. [[User:Pastordavid|Pastordavid]] ([[User talk:Pastordavid|talk]]) 13:25, 17 June 2008 (UTC)
:::It is irresponsible to make such claims without some evidence.  Google Books would suggest the contrary.  When one limits to works published between 1990 and 2008 one finds 1364 results for [http://books.google.com/books?as_q=&amp;num=10&amp;btnG=Google+Search&amp;as_epq=counter+reformation&amp;as_oq=&amp;as_eq=&amp;as_libcat=0&amp;as_brr=0&amp;lr=&amp;as_vt=&amp;as_auth=&amp;as_pub=&amp;as_sub=&amp;as_drrb=c&amp;as_miny=1990&amp;as_maxy=2008&amp;as_isbn= &quot;counter reformation&quot;] and 642 results for [http://books.google.com/books?as_q=&amp;num=10&amp;btnG=Google+Search&amp;as_epq=catholic+reformation&amp;as_oq=&amp;as_eq=&amp;as_libcat=0&amp;as_brr=0&amp;lr=&amp;as_vt=&amp;as_auth=&amp;as_pub=&amp;as_sub=&amp;as_drrb=c&amp;as_miny=1990&amp;as_maxy=2008&amp;as_isbn= &quot;catholic reformation&quot;]. I am convinced that &quot;Catholic Reformation&quot; will at some point in the future be the dominant term - but it isn't yet. [[User:Mcferran|Noel S McFerran]] ([[User talk:Mcferran|talk]]) 17:02, 17 June 2008 (UTC)
::::I'm sorry to appear to be irresponsible.  I certainly thought that what I provided above was a portion of evidence.  The scholars - all published by extremely  [[WP:RS|reputible publishing houses]], all speak of Counter Reformation as a term that is increasingly passing out of use, precisely because of the concerns I have outlined.  Google books is in many ways helpful, in many ways represents a self-selected portion of what is out there.  As I said, what I found of interest in the google book searches is the spread of the dates: in a very unscientific glance at usage, in the first 50 results of each search, 58% of the uses of &quot;Catholic Reformation&quot; come from sources published 1995 or later; 68% of the uses of &quot;Counter Reformation&quot; come from before 1995.  I am not arguing (and don't think I have argued) that you will find more sources that use &quot;Catholic Reformation.&quot;  My argument is, and has been, that &quot;Counter Reformation&quot; is inherently POV, which is reflected in the consistingtly increasing number of scholars abandoning this usage; and that a neutral article title is paramount. Thus, from [[WP:NPOV]]: ''Sometimes the article title itself may be a source of contention and polarization. This is especially true for descriptive titles that suggest a viewpoint either &quot;for&quot; or &quot;against&quot; any given issue. A neutral article title is very important because it ensures that the article topic is placed in the proper context. Therefore, encyclopedic article titles are expected to exhibit the highest degree of neutrality. The article might cover the same material but with less emotive words, or might cover broader material which helps ensure a neutral view (for example, renaming &quot;Criticisms of drugs&quot; to &quot;Societal views on drugs&quot;). Neutral titles encourage multiple viewpoints and responsible article writing.''  [[User:Pastordavid|Pastordavid]] ([[User talk:Pastordavid|talk]]) 20:35, 17 June 2008 (UTC)
:::::&quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; is not &quot;an inherently POV term&quot;. It means &quot;against the Reformation&quot;, which it was, when we understand &quot;Reformation&quot; to refer to the Protestant Reformation, which in common English usage it does. There's nothing POV about that either: &quot;re-formation&quot; is a perfectly descriptive word. The Counter-Reformation may have been a Catholic Reformation, but there is no reason to regard the former term as &quot;POV&quot; and no reason for scholars to cease using it. [[User:Srnec|Srnec]] ([[User talk:Srnec|talk]]) 04:23, 18 June 2008 (UTC)
That one of your cited sources reads: ''&quot;Counter-Reformation...By convention, this process is known as the Counter-Reformation, though some scholars prefer Catholic Reformation&quot;'' seems to support the current title for the article.  ''Cf.'' some scholars prefer the [[War for Southern Independence]] for the less accurate and POV [[American Civil War]] but Wikipedia opts for the common name. — &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid blue;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#fef;background:navy;&quot;&gt;''' AjaxSmack '''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 04:39, 18 June 2008 (UTC)
::::::It certainly does - which one is that? [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 13:45, 18 June 2008 (UTC)
:::::::Peter Marshall, &quot;Counter-Reformation&quot; in ''Encyclopedia of Christianity'' quoted in the collpased box above. — &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid blue;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User talk:AjaxSmack|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#fef;background:navy;&quot;&gt;''' AjaxSmack '''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 07:59, 20 June 2008 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the proposal.  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;

Revision as of 17:55, 26 February 2009 (edit) (undo)
75.165.18.28 (talk)

Removing the unsourced text: &quot;In the end of the Reformation Martian Luther announced, at his death bed, that they were better off under the church.&quot;

As it has nothing to do with the article, and a reasonably sourced blog entry denies it: http://beggarsallreformation.blogspot.com/2007/01/did-luther-recant-on-his-deathbed.html

[[User:FlowRate|FlowRate]] ([[User talk:FlowRate|talk]]) 03:20, 11 April 2009 (UTC)

== Title change definitely needed ==

Leaving the title &quot;Counter Reformation&quot; on the pretext that it is &quot;commonly used&quot; is equivalent to naming an article &quot;America&quot; instead of &quot;The United States of America&quot;, &quot;Flu&quot; instead of &quot;Influenza&quot;, or &quot;Aryan&quot; instead of &quot;Indo-European&quot;...

To start with, the Protestant Reformation is itself a misnomer. A &quot;reform&quot; in any community, society, or organization is something initiated by existing leadership, using existing channels, in accordance with existing rules - e.g. Catholic Reformation this article deals with, Gorbachev's reforms in the USSR, Deng Xiaoping's reforms in China, healthcare reforms made by governments, education reforms etc. But when some lower-ranking members of any organization claim authority and take things into their own hands locally, capture buildings, expulse their superiors etc - this is should be called a mutiny, rebelion, etc.
What if someone today enters, say, a City Hall, throws out all the officials and starts issuing &quot;reforms&quot;? Will we consider that guy a &quot;reformer&quot;???
Thus, correct names would be &quot;Protestant Revolt&quot; and &quot;Catholic Reformation&quot;.
But even though Protestants incorrectly (as discussed above) called their movement a &quot;Reformation&quot;, it should not prevent us from accurately describing the events of this article as a &quot;Catholic Reformation&quot;, for the second wrong will not make things right.

Wikipedia should be primarily concerned with its titles be as accurate and as descriptive as possible, and not use titles generated by old-days political propaganda, just because they are &quot;popular&quot;, especially as it is possible for everyone searching for &quot;Counter Reformation&quot; to be directed to &quot;Catholic Reformation&quot;.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Vox Veritatae|Vox Veritatae]] ([[User talk:Vox Veritatae|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Vox Veritatae|contribs]]) 10:53, 30 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:There should be two articles: '''Catholic reformation''' with the contents of this article, and '''Counter-Reformation''' about the time-period called so generally by the historians (see the discussion above and under). The term &quot;reformation&quot; is a generally accepted term of history science (not as only colloquial &quot;flu&quot; etc.). --[[User:Mmh|Mmh]] ([[User talk:Mmh|talk]]) 06:30, 24 October 2009 (UTC)

== Counter-Reformation ==

The Wikopedia article on the counter-reformation must include a major section on the attacks by Catholics on Protestants. The Shorter Oxford English Dictionary defines &quot;counter-reformation&quot; as &quot;... the movement in the Church of Rome which followed on the Prostetant Reformation.&quot; This sense of the term is wider than and not synonymous with The Catholic Revival or the Catholic Reform as the first line of the article suggests. The Oxford definition certainly reflects the approach taken in my university course on European history. I fear that the authors in the WikiProject Catholicism are slanting the article towards the views of the Roman Catholic Church. This is a disservice to the entire Wikopedia undertaking. [[Special:Contributions/24.108.224.158|24.108.224.158]] ([[User talk:24.108.224.158|talk]]) 19:31, 18 August 2009 (UTC)

:Were you able to write such a section? I have already written the same argument above, but my English is not good enough to write it. --[[User:Mmh|Mmh]] ([[User talk:Mmh|talk]]) 10:27, 29 August 2009 (UTC)

::during the reformation, everyone attacked everyone, except some radicals. It was only after the Wars of Religion, where the idea of tolerance came about. the counter/catholic-reformation article should focus on the changes in the Catholic Church. one thing I hate about wikipedia, is every time someone sees a bias, they accuse some obvious group, really that is unnecessary. Heretics were executed long before the council of trent, so, yes it occurred during the time period of the counter-reformation. If you view the counter-reformation as the Roman Catholic Church's response to and attempt to stop the Protestant Reformation, then yes it should be all about prosecution of protestants. however, and this is the reason that scholar's call it the Catholic Reformation, it is the Catholic version of the Protestant Reformation. The Catholic-Reformation should be seen as Catholic's saying to themselves, the protestants raise some good points. [[Special:Contributions/67.176.160.47|67.176.160.47]] ([[User talk:67.176.160.47|talk]]) 05:56, 31 March 2010 (UTC)

In Council of Trent Section, it says: &quot;as epistle of st. James states...&quot;, is St. james stands for Authorized King James Version for Bible? if so why it is not linked to the specified page? also where is the citation?, which epistle?, the number of chapter and sentence?? thx [[User:Wafaashohdy|Wafaashohdy]] ([[User talk:Wafaashohdy|talk]]) 11:24, 20 March 2011 (UTC)

== Devotional, Observantine, and Legalist traditions ==

There are references in the article to devotional, observantine, and legalist traditions, but these are not defined.  The links are to either to dictionary definitions of devotion and legalism, or to Franciscans in the case of observantine (an article in which the word &quot;observantine&quot; does not occur).  What are these words referring to in the context of this article?  If observantine is a synonym for Fransiscan, I don't understand what is the specifically Fransiscan influence on the development of the Jesuits.  [[User:Underalms|Underalms]] ([[User talk:Underalms|talk]]) 16:40, 15 August 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>eizbzq8kjhgfporv9sayxp434orrp9z</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
