<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Religion in Germany</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1711641</id>
    <revision>
      <id>489616670</id>
      <parentid>489606076</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-28T12:44:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Angr</username>
        <id>157842</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Map of Christian denominations 2008 */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6052">{{WikiProject Religion|class=start|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Germany | class =Start | importance = Mid
| B-Class-1 = 
| B-Class-2 = 
| B-Class-3 = 
| B-Class-4 = 
| B-Class-5 = 
}}
{{archive box|
# [[/Archive 1|December 2006 to April 2011]]
}}

The article should explain that the opinion of the mainstream churchs about cults and new religious movements is influential in Germany. Otherwise it sounds like just an opinion of one religous group about another religious group which should be removed because irrelevant here. [[User:Andries|Andries]] ([[User talk:Andries|talk]]) 06:11, 27 August 2011 (UTC)

To quote from an article: &quot;Those who are concerned about the limitations of religious freedom in Germany should, therefore, consider not only the structure of the legal and political system; it is also necessary to pay attention to the cultural dimensions of society, and to the attitudes and moods that affect social action and the working of the institutions.&quot; (http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0SOR/is_3_64/ai_109568884/pg_4/?tag=mantle_skin;content). The mainstream churches' opinions are politically influential for the religious history of the country. To really explain this one may start with the [[Thirty Years' War]]. Or learn about the rights of the mainline churches as statutory organizations, e. g. to give religious education at state schools. &lt;i&gt;Just one example&lt;/i&gt;, German kids have to prepare presentations about ''Sekten'' for religion or ethics class and attending these classes is mandatory. --[[User:Rafflesiapricei|Rafflesiapricei]] ([[User talk:Rafflesiapricei|talk]]) 19:20, 13 September 2011 (UTC)

==Jehovah's Witnesses and Mormons==
I don't know how religious science views them, but public opinion and mainline churches classify those groups as ''Sekten'' rather than as Christians in Germany. For example [[http://www.sektenausstieg.net/ Netzwerk Sektenausstieg e.V. - Dokumentation und Forum über Zeugen Jehovas, Mormonen und andere Sekten]] --[[User:Rafflesiapricei|Rafflesiapricei]] ([[User talk:Rafflesiapricei|talk]]) 13:18, 14 September 2011 (UTC)
:Hmm... that particular page doesn't mention Mormons and JWs at all, but [http://www.sektenausstieg.net/sekten-doku this page] from the same group categorizes the organizations they cover into &quot;Zeugen Jehovas&quot;, &quot;Mormonen&quot;, &quot;Sekten&quot;, and &quot;Neuapostolische Kirche&quot;, suggesting they do not consider JW, Mormons, and NAC to be Sekten ''strictu sensu''. [[User:Angr|Angr]] ([[User talk:Angr|talk]]) 18:33, 14 September 2011 (UTC)
:: The page lists &quot;Zeugen Jehovas&quot;, &quot;Mormonen&quot; and &quot;Neuapostolische Kirche&quot;, as ''specific examples'' of Sekten and does most of its work providing critical information especially about these groups . If you have a page on apples, pears and fruit, it doesn't say that apples and pears are not fruit.  
:: The &quot;theological&quot; definition of ''Sekte'' [http://www.hilfe24.de/01_sekten.htm] &quot;A religious body, especially one that has separated from a larger denomination&quot; seems to correspond to [[sect]]. The &quot;common&quot; definition referring to &quot;groups or organizations using subtle methods of mind control to make people dependent of them&quot; seems to correspond to [[cult]]. ''Sekte'' means both. &quot;Zeugen Jehovas&quot;, &quot;Mormonen&quot; and &quot;Neuapostolische Kirche&quot; are ''Sekten'' in the theological definition and are publicly agreed to be ''Sekten'' in the common definition too. Listing only Hare Krishnas and Ananda Marga as examples of  ''Sekten'' implies that groups that refer to themselves as Christian cannot be labelled as ''Sekte''. Especially with Jehovah's Witnesses this is not the case.--[[User:Rafflesiapricei|Rafflesiapricei]] ([[User talk:Rafflesiapricei|talk]]) 12:46, 26 October 2011 (UTC)
::: There are cultural differences in addition to linguistic ones. In the United States (and maybe other English-speaking countries as well), I don't think most people would seriously consider the Jehovah's Witnesses and the Mormons ''cults'' (as opposed to, say, the [[Branch Davidians]] and the [[Peoples Temple]], both of which are nominally Christian but definitely considered cults), but in Germany the JWs and the Mormons are not as well known and not as widespread and may therefore be regarded with more skepticism than in the U.S. (If you consider Mormons Christians, then the LDS Church is the 4th largest Christian denomination in the U.S.; if you don't consider them Christians, then they're the largest non-Christian religion in the U.S., there being more Mormons than Jews there.) The Scientologists are also widely considered a cult in Germany (and they don't fit the &quot;separated from a larger denomination&quot; part of the theological definition of ''Sekte''), while views on them vary more greatly in the U.S. So from the point of view of the English speakers likely to be reading this article, it may be jarring to see JWs and Mormons called cults, even if that seems quite natural to Germans. (And yes, if someone listed &quot;Apples, pears, and fruit&quot; on a page, I would think they were suggesting that apples and pears aren't fruit. They should say &quot;Apples, pears, and other fruit&quot;.) [[User:Angr|Angr]] ([[User talk:Angr|talk]]) 18:11, 26 October 2011 (UTC)

== Map of Christian denominations 2008 ==

I don't think this map is very accurate because the lines between catholicism and protestantism don't follow the borders of modern German states. For example, the state of Baden-Württemberg is roughly half predominantly catholic and half predominantly EKD protestant. I think this one is more accurate:http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Europe_religion_map_en.png -- [[Special:Contributions/77.184.40.192|77.184.40.192]] ([[User talk:77.184.40.192|talk]]) 10:56, 28 April 2012 (UTC)
:The 1895 map further down the page does a better job of showing exactly where Catholicism and Protestantism are most prevalent. I think it's still pretty accurate within the boundaries of modern Germany, but it doesn't reflect the numbers of irreligious people. [[User:Angr|Angr]] ([[User talk:Angr|talk]]) 12:44, 28 April 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gwd7a624nga5fw7bmyz321s92oftyh9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
