<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Pre-existence</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2997128</id>
    <revision>
      <id>458533090</id>
      <parentid>458484377</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-11-01T21:47:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LittleOldManRetired</username>
        <id>14519210</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Preparatory re-sequencing of text in article */ new section</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5828">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=B|Interfaith=yes}}
{{ChristianityWikiProject |importance= low |class= start |latter-day-saint-movement=yes |latter-day-saint-movement-importance= Low}}

==Pre-existance in Sufism ==

Although a vague idea of pre-existance can be extracted from various Sufi writings the beliefs mentioned in the article are not beliefs of all sufis , please mention which branches of Sufism hold these beliefs , thanks [[User:Pasha Abd|Pasha Abd]] 20:20, 25 October 2005 (UTC)

== Beforelife ==

The top of the pre-existence page suggests that the article might be merged with Beforelife, but the latter article doesn't exist.

==Merge==

I agree that this should be merged. There is no reason to keep this a separate article. [[User:Str1977|Str1977]] [[User talk:Str1977|&lt;sup&gt;(smile back)&lt;/sup&gt;]] 12:36, 19 June 2007 (UTC)

== POV ==

The bit about NDEs at the bottom is very non-NPOV, as it seems to offer an opinion that &quot;NDEs offer a premonition of the afterlife&quot;. [[User:212.84.96.86|212.84.96.86]] 23:52, 8 July 2007 (UTC)

== LDS Doctrines ==

I've added a paragraph in brackets explaining some things that people would probably not otherwise know, and helping them to understand how the modern LDS Church probably sees things.  If it is not desirable to have that there in brackets (I'm fine with it being there like that) then if someone could re-write the article there incorporating this information (or at least without making it seem like the modern LDS church ''changed'' the doctrines from how they used to be (as they do not believe this), then that would be great. [[User:Shoreu|Shoreu]] 07:19, 10 July 2007 (UTC)

== Jewish Pre-mortal Life and Immortal Souls ==

I would really like to see some sources on the Jews not believing in a pre-mortal life and immortal souls before the Greeks and whatever.  Is this knowledge, or just knowledge that there are no current records of such suitable for such a claim in an encyclopedia fit for all denominations?  Basically, I want to know if there is anything in ''Jewish'' records that specifically refutes the possibility; specifically, I want to know about records that took place during times when the Jews followed the then living prophets of the Bible.  Anyway, the Old Testament does not seem to refute the possibility; in fact, it seems to support it, to me.  Also, does Jews in this context refer just to those from the tribe of Judah, or does it refer to all of the house of Israel and the ancestors of Jacob (Isaac, Abraham, etc.)? [[User:Shoreu|Shoreu]] 07:39, 10 July 2007 (UTC)

== Restructuring the article ==

The intro section seems to be quite good and succinct.  The body of the article could probably be improved by an historically-oriented sequenced presentation, for example, beginning with [[Urreligion|Primitive religion]]s,

followed by Hinduism's [[reincarnation]],

and the belief of [[Ancient Egyptian religion]] about the origin and nature of the spirits of human beings and gods,

explicit suggestive texts from the Old Testament (Abrahamic religion), those suggestive of support for the possibility and those suggestive of denial of it,

texts of [[Zoroastrianism]],

then [[Chinese philosophy]],

[[Hindu philosophy]],

Greek philosophers like [[Plato]] and [[Plotinus]],

Buddhism's [[Bodhisattva]]s,

key [[History of philosophy|Roman philosophers]] (BCE),

Christian New Testament texts, those suggestive of support for the possibility and those suggestive of denial of it,

Talmud and [[Kabbalah]],

early Christian writers like [[Origen]] and [[Tertullian]],

[[Alchemy|Alchemists]] like [[Celsus]] and [[Paracelsus]],

the decision of Christian Ecumenical Council(s) on the issue,

[[Islam]] (Qur'an, Islamic writers),

[[Maimonides]],

[[Thomas Aquinas]] (in particular the ''[[Summa Theologica]]''),

the [[Reformation]],

the [[Enlightenment]] period,

New England [[Transcendentalism|Transcendentalists]] like [[Henry David Thoreau]] and [[Walt Whitman]]—

''and only then'' present the views of [[Mormonism]] and [[Western esotericism]], in their actual historical context.

The present section on Mormonism could be abbreviated to the best highlights from that tradition.  It seems to me that it's too extensive right now in its present form for inclusion in a general article on &quot;pre-existence&quot; and probably belongs more to a separate article on the subject of [[Mormonism|Mormon beliefs]], and it's inclusion here as part of the development of Christianity is somewhat problematical—the historical sequencing as suggested here would be more neutral.

Finally, I'm not sure whether or not [[Transhumanism]]'s view(s) would fit. --[[User:LittleOldManRetired|LittleOldManRetired]] ([[User talk:LittleOldManRetired|talk]]) 13:38, 1 November 2011 (UTC)

== Preparatory re-sequencing of text in article ==

I went ahead with a preliminary re-sequencing of statements in the article without changing them (they're verbatim as written), revising only the order in which they appear in the text, and according to a more historical chronology (like re-collating a loose stack of numbered-pages of a manuscript that accidentally dropped off a desk onto the floor and got mixed up).  I'll leave the revised article just as it is for now, to give you guys a chance to look at the suggestion I made above, and compare the preliminary result, and make whatever other changes and corrections you think the article needs.  Meanwhile—''I'm going to take a break'' ('bout a week).

&quot;''Citations needed''&quot;—Some of the citations needed in the text can be gotten from the list of External link articles. (Read 'em and you'll find 'em.) I just didn't think this is the time to do that, yet. --[[User:LittleOldManRetired|LittleOldManRetired]] ([[User talk:LittleOldManRetired|talk]]) 21:46, 1 November 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>q1vqiq7ryqlx5865hx63rlegulb3ro9</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
