<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Methodism</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>161379</id>
    <revision>
      <id>489666017</id>
      <parentid>489236691</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-04-28T18:59:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Carl.bunderson</username>
        <id>511766</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16473">{{ChristianityWikiProject|class=C|importance=Top|methodism-work-group=yes|methodism-importance=Top|core-topics-work-group = yes|core-topics-importance=low|arminianism=yes|arminianism-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Religion|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-02-28|oldid1=6718487|date2=2005-02-28|oldid2=16332581|date3=2006-02-28|oldid3=41630857}}
{{archive box|
* [[Talk:Methodism/Archive 1|Everything before 2009]]
}}

== Unreferenced Sections ==
I notice that two &quot;Unreferenced Section&quot; tags have been there for over a year.  The facts presented in these paragraphs are adequately covered by the works mentioned in the reference section.  Do we need to cite a particular page of a particular book to verify facts that are reported in so many works and are generally accepted as being mainstream history?  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 21:21, 26 January 2009 (UTC)

:It would be better by far to give real citations for these sections. That would be the ideal. On the other hand, the user who added the tags has fewer than 100 contribs, and made no effort whatsoever to explain why any of the info in the sections might be wrong. I think it would be perfectly fine to remove the tags. But again, that doesn't mean we shouldn't reference the sections. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 19:48, 29 January 2009 (UTC)

:I went ahead and removed the tags. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 04:03, 1 February 2009 (UTC)

== Primitive Methodism ==

The American section mentions William Hammet's American Primitive Methodists who evidently pre-date the British Primitive Methodist Church (which joined with Wesleyans etc to form the British Methodist Church in 1932).  Are the original American Primitive Methodists still in existence, or is there an offshoot of the British Primitive Methodist Church still functioning in the USA (as implied in the paragraph on British Methodism)?  Do current American Primitive Methodists trace their origins to William Hammet, or to [[Lorenzo Dow]], [[William Clowes]] and [[Hugh Bourne]]? [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 18:12, 22 July 2009 (UTC)

==Improvements to the article==
I would like to go over some ideas for improvement. Here are some:

1) The lead

The current lead doesn't really give a good overview of Methodism. It seems to focus most attention on history, particularly early history with John Wesley.

2) History

The sections &quot;Wesleyan Revival&quot; and &quot;Missions to America&quot; should be subsections under a single &quot;History&quot; heading. This history section would need to be expanded such as adding sections on further development of Methodism in and outside of Britain and USA. The spread of Methodism to other countries should be told. Also recent history of Methodism should be addressed to.

3) Methodism in the United States

Perhaps this should be its on article with a summary remaining as a section here?

What does anyone else think? I'm not familiar enough with Methodism to materially contribute to the article, but I'm willing to help organize and copy edit. [[User:Ltwin|Ltwin]] ([[User talk:Ltwin|talk]]) 23:35, 19 January 2010 (UTC)

I agree with your points on the lead section.  It doesn't really serve to explain what methodism is adequately.  Perhaps should start with a couple of lines of what it is, and how it is different from other religions/forms of christianity.

[[Special:Contributions/38.112.100.2|38.112.100.2]] ([[User talk:38.112.100.2|talk]]) 16:53, 9 July 2010 (UTC)

::I agree we could say more, but Methodism is diverse and differs little (on average) from other branches of Christianity.  Perhaps we could mention the emphasis on [[Arminianism]] as opposed to the Anglican emphasis on [[Calvinism]], but this is described later in the article.  The phrase &quot;a movement of Christianity&quot; sums up what Methodism is, and if we start describing how one branch of Methodism differs from other denominations, then we are not representing the whole diversity of the movement.  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 20:09, 9 July 2010 (UTC)

::: ''(later)'' I see that Thomas Paine has changed &quot;a movement of Christianity&quot; to &quot;a Christian denomination&quot;, and I don't really disagree except that perhaps we should say &quot;a group of denominations&quot;, and to point out that this definition excludes the original meaning of the word as a movement within the Anglican denomination.  I'm not sure to what extent the [[episcopal]] Methodism of America can be regarded as the same denomination as the non-episcopal British Methodism, but I suppose a broad brush could paint them together.  What does anyone else think?  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 22:00, 4 August 2010 (UTC)

[[Special:Contributions/69.251.35.81|69.251.35.81]] ([[User talk:69.251.35.81|talk]]) 01:18, 3 May 2011 (UTC)The article mentions Salvation Army as being started by the Methodist.  It was actually Edgar Helms who was Methodist who started Goodwill Industries, now know as Goodwill Industries International.  See www.Goodwill.org for more information.

:Thanks for the link.  I hadn't heard of Goodwill Industries.  Do they operate only in North America?  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 07:53, 3 May 2011 (UTC)

Hi, Yes Goodwill Industries operates in North America but also is expanding to international location.  The website Goodwill.org should have more information.  I worked at Goodwill Industries International a while ago, the company was reaching out to Italy and Asia.  Sorry I don't know the details more than that, wasn't my area.  Edgar Helms created Goodwill Industries and was a Methodist.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.33.123.25|68.33.123.25]] ([[User talk:68.33.123.25|talk]]) 01:20, 23 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Denomination vs. Movement==
Methodism is not a denomination.  A denomination is an &quot;identifiable religious body under a common name, structure, and doctrine&quot; according to the Wikipedia article on denominations.  The [[United Methodist Church&quot;, &quot;Free Methodist Church, and &quot;African Methodist Episcopal Church&quot; are all denominations that follow Methodist doctrine.  A movement is a group of denominations that hold similar beliefs and may come from the same source.  For example, the Evangelical Lutheran Church in America and the Lutheran Church-Missouri Synod are denominations.  Both are part of Lutheranism, a movement within Christianity that can trace its origins back to the 1517 Protestant Reformation led by Martin Luther.  [[User:KitHutch|KitHutch]] ([[User talk:KitHutch|talk]]) 21:27, 5 August 2010 (UTC)
:Yes, I agree that &quot;movement&quot; is the better term.  I'm pleased to see that it has been changed back.  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 18:41, 11 September 2010 (UTC)

==Greek Orthodox NOT Armenian==

The Church is Greek Orthodox in outlook, not &quot;Armenian.&quot; Since the Creeds of Ancient Armenia were developed in the context of the Greek Eastern Roman Empire (Byzantium). Also, why is there no mention of the following in this article?


&lt;nowiki&gt; &quot;We believe it would not be right for us to administer either Baptism or the Lord's Supper unless we had a commission so to do from those Bishops whom we apprehend to be in a succession from the Apostles.&quot;[63] – Rev. John Wesley, A.D. 1745&lt;/nowiki&gt;

In 1763, Greek Orthodox bishop Erasmus of Arcadia, who was visiting London at the time,[64] consecrated Rev. John Wesley a bishop,[65][66] and ordained several Methodist lay preachers as priests, including John Jones.[67][68] In light of Wesley's episcopal consecration, the Methodist Church can lay a claim on apostolic succession, as understood in the traditional sense.[69] Since the Rev. John Wesley ordained and sent forth every Methodist preacher in his day, who preached and baptized and ordained, and since every Methodist preacher who has ever been ordained as a Methodist was ordained in this direct &quot;succession&quot; from Wesley, then the Methodist Church teaches that it has all the direct merits coming from apostolic succession.[70] --[[User:Nikoz78|Nikoz78]] ([[User talk:Nikoz78|talk]]) 16:53, 11 September 2010 (UTC)

:Methodism is neither [[Armenian]] nor [[Greek Orthodox]] in outlook.  The article links to &quot;[[Arminian]]&quot; which is a theological position (believing that anyone is free to accept God's salvation, as opposed to a [[Calvinist]] position that restricts salvation to &quot;the elect&quot;), not a link to any other church.  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 18:35, 11 September 2010 (UTC)

I understand that, my apologies for not making myself clear. The concept of Free Will is Greek Orthodox in origin (&quot;Byzantine&quot;), not Armenian. See: [[Greek Orthodox Church]], specifically... 

&quot;Historically, the term Greek Orthodox has also been used to describe all Eastern Orthodox Churches, since &quot;Greek&quot; in &quot;Greek Orthodox&quot; can refer to the Greek heritage of the Byzantine Empire.[20][21][22] During eight centuries of Christian history most major intellectual, cultural, and social developments in the Christian church took place within the Empire or in the sphere of its influence,[23][24][25]  thus most parts of the liturgy, traditions, and practices of the church of Constantinople were adopted by all, and still provide the basic patterns of contemporary Orthodoxy.[26][27][28] However, the appellation &quot;Greek&quot; was '''abandoned by Slavic and other national orthodox churches''' in connection with their peoples' national awakenings, from as early as the 10th century A.D.[29][30][31][32][33]&quot;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Nikoz78|Nikoz78]] ([[User talk:Nikoz78|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Nikoz78|contribs]]) 15:24, 13 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Yes, I think the concept of &quot;Free Will&quot; pre-dates Christianity, and even Judaism. I was interested in your link between Methodism and the Orthodox Church, and in your history of Eastern Orthodoxy, and your cite from [[Apostolic succession]].  I think this is probably more important to the American Methodist Church, since there are no Methodist bishops in the UK.  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 15:58, 13 September 2010 (UTC)

== Oldest Church  ==

The German Wikipedia [here: http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%84gidienkirche_%28Erfurt%29 and here: http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methodistische_und_Wesleyanische_Kirchen] provides the information, that the oldest church (worldwide!) used by Methodists is the Aegidienkirche in Erfurt (Thuringia, Germany). If that's true, it sure is a fact worth mentioning! [[Special:Contributions/194.95.117.68|194.95.117.68]] ([[User talk:194.95.117.68|talk]]) 09:36, 2 May 2011 (UTC)

:I very much doubt whether this information can be verified in any meaningful way (in fact I'm sure that someone somewhere will be able to prove the statement to be false), so I would oppose adding it to our article.  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 15:58, 2 May 2011 (UTC)

== Contradiction? ==

&quot;The original Methodist body led by Wesley was known as the Wesleyan Methodist Church.&quot; How can this be reconciled with the statement that the Methodists remained within the Churchof England until after John Wesley's death? --[[User:Ross Burgess|rossb]] ([[User talk:Ross Burgess|talk]]) 07:45, 26 June 2011 (UTC)

:The whole paragraph was slightly confused.  I've made a couple of alterations, but it could probably benefit from further improvement.  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 18:59, 27 June 2011 (UTC)

== Vandalism in History Section - Philippines ==

I am deeply concerned about the [[vandalism]] that is recently attacking this article. I see how some unregistered user tried to delete a history of a new group in the Philippines and if not continued to mutilate information. There must be a move to protect this and the Wikipedia as a whole. [[User:Chris Eilers|Christian Eilers]] ([[User talk:Chris Eilers|talk]]) 23:16, 8 February 2012 (UTC)
:There is rather too much detail of the controversy (for a general article on Methodism).  Perhaps a reference would help.  I'd recommend shortening the paragraph.  [[User:Dbfirs|''&lt;font face=&quot;verdana&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;D&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#00ccff&quot;&gt;b&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#44ffcc&quot;&gt;f&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;66ff66&quot;&gt;i&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44ee44&quot;&gt;r&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;44aa44&quot;&gt;s&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt;'']] 12:41, 10 February 2012 (UTC)

== Largest mainline Christian denomination in South Africa ==

The article states &quot;The Methodist Church of Southern Africa is the largest mainline Christian denomination in South Africa&quot;. The numbers I have seen refute this. Is there evidence for this claim?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/208.51.23.195|208.51.23.195]] ([[User talk:208.51.23.195|talk]]) 13:31, 21 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:It looks cited to me. [[User:Carl.bunderson|carl bunderson]] [[User talk:Carl.bunderson|(talk)]] [[Special:Contributions/Carl.bunderson|(contributions)]] 18:59, 28 April 2012 (UTC)

==File:FrancisAsbury.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:FrancisAsbury.jpg|File:FrancisAsbury.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests March 2012'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.
To take part in any discussion, or to review a more detailed deletion rationale please visit the relevant [[commons:File:FrancisAsbury.jpg|image page (File:FrancisAsbury.jpg)]]

''This is Bot placed notification, another user has nominated/tagged the image'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 17:34, 19 March 2012 (UTC)
|}</text>
      <sha1>6ihj3646pzq8pxiss0jbikjq12ev50r</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
