<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Tallit</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1132241</id>
    <revision>
      <id>439906571</id>
      <parentid>439894302</parentid>
      <timestamp>2011-07-17T06:55:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Debresser</username>
        <id>6999039</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Fix tags.</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12147">{{WikiProject Judaism | class= B | importance= high }}
{{WikiProject Jewish culture}}
{{Old merge full |otherpage=Tallis |date=&lt;February 20, 2011&gt; |result= to go on with the Merger |talk=Tallit katan}}

164.83.229.20, why did you take out the qualification about some Ashkenazi groups wearing talitot from 13?[[User:MOE37x3|MOE37x3]] 18:22, 4 Nov 2004 (UTC)

From what I know, the toga was a distinctively roman piece of clothing, so I changed the paragraph that said it was of Greek origin. If I'm wrong, please correct me. --[[User:222.13.236.80|222.13.236.80]] 12:40, 18 September 2005 (UTC)

== Hebrew  ==

The two Hebrew words in parentheses, given with different transliterations, are in fact the same word, vowel points and all.[[User:Benami|Benami]] 08:38, 30 December 2005 (UTC)
:fixz0r3d!  [[User:TShilo12|Tom]]&lt;font color=&quot;#008000&quot;&gt;[[Wikipedia:Esperanza|e]]&lt;/font&gt;[[User:TShilo12|r]][[User talk:TShilo12|&lt;sup style=&quot;font-variant: small-caps; color: #129dbc!important;&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 05:08, 13 January 2006 (UTC)

== Historical Section ==

The material given here is interesting, but no sources are cited. The author who has contributed here writes a bit too informally and in too personal a style for an encyclopedia, with sentences like, &quot;There is much confusion among the masses.&quot;   Would someone care to rewrite?  Could the author provide some sources, beyond biblical references.   --[[User:Metzenberg|Metzenberg]] 11:25, 8 May 2006 (UTC)

== Some thoughts ==

I replaced the former photo of a rabbi with a tallit.  I thought it was confusing, since it was a Sukkot photo with the four species as well, but explaining sukkot and what he has in his hands is really beyond the scope here.  In it's place, I added the photo of men wearing tallitot at the wall. 

I must say, all the discussion of pronunciation is a bit too technical.  Is it really part of the scope of this article?  In practice, I find that the Ashkenazi Hebrew (or Yiddish) still gets used a lot, sometimes in almost an ironic or funny way.  People say &quot;tallises&quot; in the worst Yinglish even though they know better, the way they say &quot;yontiff&quot; or &quot;shabbus&quot;. Would anybody have a problem with making this more informal?

== Reform Judaism ==
Section doesn't seem to have anything to do with the status of the tallit (by either gender) in Reform Judaism. Section seems to be solely about the Women of the Wall (presented in a non-NPOV way) What does this specific group have to do with the general subject Tallit, or Tallit within Reform Judaism. If the section is relevant it's not current -- the Israeli Supreme Court issued a ruling.

--as I do attend a Reform Temple, I can say that the men do wear Tallitot today, they may not always have in the movement today tradition is making a fervent comeback withing messianic Judaism, from JEWISH LIVING URJ PRESS --[[User:Teacherbrock|Teacherbrock]] ([[User talk:Teacherbrock|talk]]) 07:14, 1 February 2011 (UTC)

== Masculine or Feminine Word? ==

Tallitot appears feminine, and Tallaisim appears masculine.  What is the noun's gender?

--[[User:Jndrline|Jndrline]] 18:39, 25 May 2006 (UTC)

:The word ''talléth'' was feminine with ''-oth'' in plural in Mediaeval [[Sephardi Hebrew]] and masculine with ''-im'' in plural in Mediaeval [[Ashkenazi Hebrew]]. In modern Israeli Hebrew, the word is generally considered feminine, but in the two expressions ''tallit gadol'' and ''tallit katan'', the masculine endings of Mediaeval Ashkenaz are kept. In modern Sephardi Hebrew, usage varies between the traditional ''tallét gedolá'' and ''tallét ketanná'' and the standard Israeli ''tallít gadól'' and ''tallít katán''. -- [[User:Olve|Olve]] 21:53, 25 May 2006 (UTC)

:: Thank you.  Such a complete and well-rounded answer.  I suspected that they retained their gender according to whichever pronunciation was being used, but I had never heard of such a thing, so I assumed it might have had something to do with a [[Yiddish]]-ism.

::My question actually came up with the examples you gave of a tallis katan - [[ger tzedek|someone]] said tallitot katanot, and it completely threw me.  I had never heard any adjectives applied to the object, and so I had never thought to ask the question until this person put it in plural.  I figured the answer might prove one of the ethnic pronounciations more &quot;correct&quot; over the other; I'm glad it doesn't.  Good to know.  Thanks again.

::--[[User:Jndrline|Jndrline]]

== the diferance between wool and cotton ==

is there a halachik diferance between wool and cotton? if someone can put it up (with all opinions) it would be great

:1st, remember to sign all comments with 4~. 2nd, the difference is that, by halachoh, only wool and linen garments need to have Tzitzis. See '''The Alter Rebbe's siddur'''. Thats why, to be mehader the mitzvoh, you should wear wool or linen tzitzis and tallis.  [[User:Shaul avrom|Shaul avrom]] 19:35, 16 August 2006 (UTC)

::Any other sources for this? (I don’t have that siddur and cannot access it from this part of Norway.) It is clearly not the general understanding of the miṣvá... -- [[User:Olve|Olve]] 15:39, 27 October 2006 (UTC)

Yes, but it is not so cut and dry. According to Sephardic custom as recorded by the Beis Yosef in SHulchan Aruch only wool and linen require titzis d'raisa, and others require them drabbanan. The rhema in his comments to this mentions that all garments require tzitizis draita. That's the normal Ashkenazi view, with acharonim coming down both ways. The Baal HaTanya, author of Shulchan Aruch HaRav and the Siddur mentioned above, rules leniently as mentioned. So does the Kitzur Shulchan Aruch. General practice among most ashkenazim is to rule stringently. (The debate is whether it is draisa or d'rabbanan not whether there is a requirement.) Mishnah Berurah rules stringently. (Meaning he rules it a draisa, which is stringent because if you are in a market place wrapped in only a tallis that requires tzitzis draisa, and you see the tzitzis are torn, you have to immediately throw it off and run home naked. If it were a drabanan you could keap it on till you got home.)To put something up with ALL opinions would overpower the article. We are 600 years into the age of the Acharonim. [[User:Basejumper|Basejumper]] 19:06, 16 July 2007 (UTC)
::Holy cow! Isn't it good women don't wear a tallis. Otherwise they might have to undress in public and run naked through the marketplace yelling gevalddddd.--[[User:Gilabrand|Gilabrand]] 19:15, 16 July 2007 (UTC)
Yeah, a draisa commandment is pretty heavy in Judaism. WIth your example however, women also have a draisa commandment to cover themselves up in public, whereas for men most of it is drabbanan, so even if they had a commandment to wear tzitzis on a four cornered garment, it would work out that they should keap it on because running naked for them is violating several commandments &quot;DOn't place a stumbling block,&quot; &quot;You shall be holy,&quot; and &quot;Let no unchaste thing be seen among you,&quot; not to mention others. I mentioned the running naked because that situation is discussed in Brachos; but truthfully, you'd also have the option of ripping the corner of your garment so it would be rounded, though a rounded rip would be difficult without a scissor or knife's help. [[User:Basejumper|Basejumper]] 17:21, 17 July 2007 (UTC)

== paragraph about women and circumcision ==

The following paragraph was added by an anonymous editor:
 The core of the issue is what the tallit and tzitzit symbolize. Tzitzit were commanded
 to be tied to the corners of the four-cornered garment worn by men. The four-cornered
 garment is the tallit. The tzitzit were to be a reminder of The Almighty's covenant with
 His people (remember, the covenant is with the circumcised, and the circumcised extend it
 to their wives and children). With the covenant comes protection. During the Birkat
 HaKohanim (Blessing from the Priests of The Temple, or in modern times a rabbi), it is
 customary for the husband/father to extend his tallit, and thus the covenant and protection
 to his wife and children, symbolizing his accountability for how he teaches his family.
 This accountability is because of the events in Bereishit (Genesis) chapter three. One
 mitzvah (commandment) is for men and women to abstain from wearing what pertains to the
 opposite gender. There is no scriptural reference of a woman wearing a four-cornered
 garment, or a woman undergoing B'rit Milah.
I don't understand this paragraph: how can women undergo ''b'rit milah'' in the traditionally accepted sense of that term, for instance? Any clarification would be welcome. For now, though, I have removed this paragraph from the article so that we can work on it here, if we so desire. I believe this is the best way of keeping the article encyclopedic and relatively controversy-free. --[[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] 22:23, 29 August 2007 (UTC)

== Halakhoth for creation of taleth ==

If someone who knows the halakhoth, that would make an excellent addition to this article... [[User:TShilo12|Tomer]][[User talk:TShilo12|&lt;sup style=&quot;font-variant: small-caps; color: #129dbc!important;&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/sup&gt;]] 15:24, 3 October 2008 (UTC)

== Burial section applies to all?? ==

This section states that traditionally all Jews are buried in tallitot. Traditionally, isn't it just Jewish men who are buried in a tallit? Are some women buried in them now?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Deutne|Deutne]] ([[User talk:Deutne|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Deutne|contribs]]) 23:05, 9 October 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: As far as I know it is still only men. If anybody knows of a practise otherwise, please speak out. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 22:25, 13 June 2009 (UTC)

== Prayer Shawl redirect ==

Why does &quot;prayer shawl&quot; redirect to this page? While a tallit is a prayer shawl of course, not all prayer shawls are tallits. 

My ladies knitting group makes prayer shawls as gifts, and not one of us, nor the gift receivers are of the Jewish faith. (no prejudice intended or inferred please, merely an observation)

Catholics, Greek Orthodox and others use prayer shawls. 

So, why the redirect?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Tristara|Tristara]] ([[User talk:Tristara|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Tristara|contribs]]) 08:53, 15 January 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: I agree, Methodists use them too. It is not just a Jewish thing. [[User:Tarheelz123|Tarheelz123]] ([[User talk:Tarheelz123|talk]]) 23:52, 3 June 2009 (UTC)

== Various prayers ==

I was surprised to read that sephardi Jews wear a tallit during mincha or ma'ariv. As far as I know, a tallit is worn during shacharit and
# by the shaliach tzibur during mincha and ma'ariv, not only with Sephardi Jews but by Ashkenazi Jews as well;
# by mekubalim when they pray mincha in tefillin (like Rabeinu Tam or Shimusha Rabba);
# during ma'ariv on Yom Kippur by all.
[[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 22:35, 13 June 2009 (UTC)

== Merge from [[Talis bag]] ==
{{Discussion top|1=The result was '''merge''' from [[Talis bag]]. --[[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] ([[User talk:Makaristos|talk]]) 01:33, 6 October 2009 (UTC)}}
'''Merge''' as [[Talis bag]] is not notable enough for a separate page. [[User:Chesdovi|Chesdovi]] ([[User talk:Chesdovi|talk]]) 16:43, 24 September 2009 (UTC)

* Obvious agree with merge. [[User:Debresser|Debresser]] ([[User talk:Debresser|talk]]) 17:13, 24 September 2009 (UTC)
* No question: merge. [[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] ([[User talk:Makaristos|talk]]) 19:16, 24 September 2009 (UTC)
* Is this is even worth discussing? Of course: '''Merge'''--[[User:Eliscoming1234|Eliscoming1234]] ([[User talk:Eliscoming1234|talk]]) 22:16, 24 September 2009 (UTC)
'''Merge completed.''' --[[User:Makaristos|Makaristos]] ([[User talk:Makaristos|talk]]) 01:28, 6 October 2009 (UTC)
{{Discussion bottom}}</text>
      <sha1>bvxpve1ou54tqrfltgo7f8ek88cvngt</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
