<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Toward the Light</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>226004</id>
    <revision>
      <id>334648404</id>
      <parentid>331923487</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-12-29T01:21:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sverre avnskog</username>
        <id>2359777</id>
      </contributor>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3150">

That looks about right now, &quot;said to be&quot; is better than the too-doubting &quot;claimed&quot;, &quot;supposed&quot;, &quot;alleged&quot; I'd tried out, I think. And the &quot;according to the publisher&quot; part was a very nice touch, though it would be nice to know the relationship between [[Johanne Elisabeth Agerskov]] and [[Michael Agerskov]], assuming there is one, or a &quot;(no relation)&quot; comment after his name if not. You see two people mentioned with the same last name, you tend to wonder about these things. And thanks for the message! -- [[User:JohnOwens|John Owens]] 22:14 May 12, 2003 (UTC)

==The three golden fruits==
This section is teeming with unverifiable claims of contact with the transcendental world. I tried to clean up some of it and tag areas that could use some work. There should be a succinct (and encyclopedic) way of stating that the account listed in that section is the claim of Agerskov, and not presented here in Wikipedia as fact.

&quot;According to Agerskov, the first &quot;golden fruit&quot; turned out to be a collection of poems written by deceased Danish poets. Johanne Agerskov's spirit learned the poems by heart during her sleep...&quot; makes it sound as though only the first statement is a claim, while the rest is all verified. Any ideas on improving this? [[User:WDavis1911|WDavis1911]] 03:06, 21 September 2007 (UTC)

== unverifiable ==

This is not meant to be verifiable info by normal means.  Even the authors are somewhat irrelevant.  This is a work that should be read by all and through their conscience determine if the information would be worth using for themselves.  This is just a personal note but I have seen the proof of truth about the info relayed and know it to be true.  I could care less about trivial historic matters when I know the information provided will change the world for the good.  I see so many get caught up in the &quot;verifiable&quot; details that they pass up what they need to know for spiritual progression.  If you will, read at least the first group of Q and A's and the speech of Christ and you will find out what you need to know.  Your decision does not require verifying the authors or their experiences.  They are not trying to start a religion or gain followers, only relay this help for humanity.    
[http://thelightuniversal.org]  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.228.92.1|69.228.92.1]] ([[User talk:69.228.92.1|talk]]) 01:17, 16 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;



== Photos ==
Someone has removed the photos from this article without making any comments about why the pictures have been deleted. I have now put them back in the text, and if anyone wants to remove them again, I hope he/she will explain why this is done. There has been some controversy in Denmark about the publishing of photos of Johanne Agerskov, but pictures of here can be seen many places on the internet, so I see no reason whatsoever to not publish her picture on wikipedia.--[[User:Sverre avnskog|Sverre avnskog]] ([[User talk:Sverre avnskog|talk]]) 01:21, 29 December 2009 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>2kawtjeq1yp21ci5qwp9s4vuepo68ja</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
