<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Documentary hypothesis</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>66995</id>
    <revision>
      <id>509873764</id>
      <parentid>497089609</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-30T03:23:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>PiCo</username>
        <id>437761</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* What is the source material? */</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29258">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Bible|class=C|importance=Top}}
{{ChristianityWikiProject|importance=Low|class=C}}
{{mergedfrom|Torah redactor|date=March 2011}}
{{Copied|from=Yahweh|from_oldid=410606936|to=Documentary hypothesis|diff=http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Documentary_hypothesis&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=410862054&amp;oldid=410848423}}

}}
{{ArticleHistory
| action1       = GAN
| action1date   = 12 December 2005
| action1result = listed
| action1oldid  = 30851137

| action2       = GAR
| action2date   = 9 August 2006
| action2link   = Talk:Documentary hypothesis/Archive 2#Delisted GA
| action2result = delisted
| action2oldid  = 68306110

| currentstatus = DGA
}}
{{Archive box|search=yes|
* [[Talk:Documentary hypothesis/Archive 1|Archive 1]] &lt;small&gt;(Oct 2002–Oct 2003)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Documentary hypothesis/Archive 2|Archive 2]] &lt;small&gt;(Nov 2003–Aug 2006)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Talk:Documentary hypothesis/Archive 3|Archive 3]] &lt;small&gt;(May 2006–May 2009)&lt;/small&gt;
}}
__TOC__
{{Clear}}


== Repetitions that don't conflict ==

I am editing the following because of gross inaccuracies or otherwise easily explainable situations:
:''&quot;Exodus 38:26 mentions &quot;603,550 men over 20 years old included in the census&quot; immediately after passage of the Red Sea, while Numbers 1:44-45 cites the precisely identical count, &quot;The tally of Israelites according to their paternal families, those over 20 years old, all fit for service. The entire tally was 603,550&quot;, in a census taken a full year later, &quot;on the first [day] of the second month in the second year of the Exodus&quot; (Numbers 1:1);&quot;''
:In actuality, the first mention of the census in Ex 38:26 occurs after the construction of the tabernacle (which Numbers agrees with), some 24 chapters after the red sea crossing.  I have kept only the fact that the same census is mentioned in two different books.
:''Moses' wife, though often identified as a Midianite (and hence Semitic), appears in the tale of Snow-white Miriam as a &quot;Cushite&quot; (Ethiopian), and hence black;''
:Moses' Cushite wife in Numbers 12 is unnamed and most likely refers to an extra-biblical event, and thus should not be confused with his Midianite wife Zipporah from Exodus 2, judging from gross disparity in chronology (i.e. why would Miriam and Aaron choose to bring up the issue of a foreign born wife many years after the fact?).  At the time, it was not out of the ordinary for a man to have multiple wives.  
[[User:Clown|Clown]] ([[User talk:Clown|talk]]) 01:00, 5 January 2011 (UTC)
::You're right, Clown. Despite all the contrary evidence, however, I don't think the secular administrators with this page on their watch lists will let us make critical edits. [[User:Wekn reven i susej eht|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;'''Wekn '''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;purple&quot;&gt;'''reven i susej eht'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Wekn reven i susej eht|Talk•]] [[Special:Contributions/Wekn reven i susej eht|Follow]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 15:26, 7 June 2011 (UTC)

== Taking Issue with the Documentary Hypothesis ==

discussion removed from artice:

[Taking Issue with the Documentary Hypothesis:  despite the excellent work of the author of this article, it should be noted that &quot;The Documentary Hypothesis&quot; (i.e., the Pentateuch is a compostie of 4 separate sources) while once accepted by the vast majority of Biblical scholars - is now only taught/promoted in universities and mainline/liberal seminaries in the United States.  While the vast majority of scholars (except for orthodox Jewish and Christian ones) still reject Mosaic authoriship, the Documentary Hypothesis has (to the best of my knowledge) been rejected by European scholars, and is no longer taught as a valid theory in Tubingen, Oxford, Cambridge, Edinburough, Aberdeen, Toulouse, Paris, or any of the more prestigious Biblical Studies programs throughout Europe.  Unfortunately, I have no citations or references for this except my own memory from my Masters program from 14 years ago, and that was from lectures and studies in the basic coursework, and not in my specialty, which is early Christianity, so please, consider the source, and check into the facts on your own.]&lt;small&gt;—The preceding comment was added by [[User:210.4.139.129|210.4.139.129]] ([[User talk:210.4.139.129|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/210.4.139.129|contribs]]) 10:54, 19 February 2007  (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

:There are sources citing DH as the most accepted hypothesis. Are there sources citing DH as no longer the most accepted hypothesis? The trick is that some people like to play up differences between today's version of DH and the 100-year old version. Do scholars say that the consensus has &quot;collapsed&quot;? If not, we should cite our sources and describe DH as the most-accepted hypothesis. [http://ccat.sas.upenn.edu/rs/2/Judaism/jepd.html Documentary Hypothesis][[User:Leadwind|Leadwind]] 21:43, 21 September 2007 (UTC)

::I think the problem is that the term &quot;documentary hypothesis&quot; has two meanings - Wellhausen's 4-document hypothesis, and at the same time any hypothesis that sees the Torah's origins in independent documents, no matter how many they may be. It boiols down to a difference between &quot;hypothesis&quot; and &quot;model&quot; - Wellhausen put forward a specific and influential hypothesis using a documentary model, while Van Seters, according to what he himself says on the subject, has been championing a hypothesis which uses a fragmentary model - i.e., not any kind of documentary hypothesis, even though others have decribed him as using a reduced documentary hypothesis because he refers to a J-author and a D-author. The big and crucial difference, as Van Seters explains it, is that he (Van Seters) vehemently rejects the concept of the Redactor, the &quot;deus ex-machina&quot; demanded by the logic of the DH to explain how the four documents came to be combined. If there were no Redactor, we'd be facing today an OT equivalent of the Four Gospels. Yet while the Redactor is a logical necessity, there's no actual evidence of his handiwork (says Van Seters). Anyway, to answer the point you make in your final sentence, every scholar who has produced a new theory outside the documentary model has begun with an explanation of why he felt it necessary to do so. The major names are mentioned in the final section of the article. The article tries to explain that Wellhausen is only one version of the documentary hypothesis, albeit the most widely known and most influential. It also explains, in the final section, how the acceptance of Wllhausen collapsed - basically, people came to accept that the redactor was a problem as much as a solution, a theoretical figure demanded by the hypothesis but not evidenced by the text itself. This was one of Friedman's concerns, to show just what the Redactor had contributed, thus answering these critics, but his revised hypothesis hasn't been widely accepted. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] 11:09, 22 September 2007 (UTC)

There is much in this section that I believe to be incorrect. The DH is in fact accepted by nearly every major university in BOTH the USA and Europe. A statement was even made here that it is not longer taught at Cambridge or Oxford. This is a false statement. Oxford does indeed teach the DH in its current Faculty of Theology department and even encourages students to submit specimen papers on the subject in its &quot;Handbook for Bachelor of Theology&quot;. Cambridge has in its theological department a course in Old Testament studies called &quot;Reading the Old Testament&quot; in which students are asked to study Dom Henry Wansbrough's &quot;Introduction to Genesis&quot; which includes a discussion of the DH. Cambridge students are encouraged to write, as one of their required essays for this class, a paper on the &quot;two flood accounts&quot; as shown by the DH. Wansbrough's &quot;Introduction to Genesis&quot; can be read online here, and as you can see, like most scholars, he has a very favorable opinion of the DH:

http://users.ox.ac.uk/~sben0056//bkl-genesis1.htm

The DH has certainly not undergone any kind of &quot;collapse&quot;.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Cws51923|Cws51923]] ([[User talk:Cws51923|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Cws51923|contribs]]) 17:43, 1 December 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

No, the DH has not collapsed. However, there have been some interesting non-confessional challenges to it. One is the sort of &quot;literary critique&quot; that purports to show, at least with respect to Genesis, that the book is a literary unit and that the parallels between purportedly different sources are stronger than their differences. (E.g. Rendsburg, Gary - ''The Redaction of Genesis'') Anyway, I don't think a discussion of this topic is complete without non-straw-man versions of its critics being presented. --[[User:Stormj|Stormj]] ([[User talk:Stormj|talk]]) 04:49, 22 January 2012 (UTC)

== BC/BCE ==

&quot;...  and consensus for the change with other editors.&quot;

I don't care what convention is used, whether BC or BCE. I do object to someone making a change in violation of standards. I'm not going to give in to the temptation to continuing an edit war. I'm giving you the chance to stand up for your opinion. But if you don't want to gather a &quot;consensus for the change&quot; .... [[User:TomS TDotO|TomS TDotO]] ([[User talk:TomS TDotO|talk]]) 13:25, 16 August 2009 (UTC)

The change wasn't in violation of standards because the article used both BC and BCE dating styles. I chose BC because it was first used and there was need for consistency [[Special:Contributions/66.31.110.254|66.31.110.254]] ([[User talk:66.31.110.254|talk]]) 13:44, 19 August 2009 (UTC)

:Thank you. I agree that it is preferable to have the article use a uniform style. As the article stands now, however, there are only two places where the BC style is used, under [[Documentary hypothesis#The beginnings of the documenary hypothesis]], where it says, &quot;the reign of Josiah in 621 BC&quot;; and under [[Documentary hypothesis#After Wellhausen]], where it says, &quot;in the first millennium BC&quot;. Elsewhere, there are many uses of the BCE style. Just on the basis of numbers, it would superficially seem preferable to change the two cases of BC to BCE. As I said, however, I don't care, but unless there is some reason not to, I suggest that these two instances be so changed. What I do strongly feel about is that we try to keep cool about it, and let's discuss it before acting unilaterally. I realize that some people feel strongly one way or the other, but let's not attribute bad faith to the other side. [[User:TomS TDotO|TomS TDotO]] ([[User talk:TomS TDotO|talk]]) 14:58, 19 August 2009 (UTC)

== Early date of P - consequences for Ezekiel? ==

The text says that Friedmann and Kaufmann argue for P dating from Hezekiah instead of Post Exilic. 

With Post Exilic P the religious laws in the text evolve as follows
#[[Ritual Decalogue]] (J)/ [[Covenant Code]] (E)
#[[Deuteronomic Code]] (D)
#Implications of the Book of Ezekiel
#[[Holiness Code]] (H = early layer of P)
#[[Priestly Code]] (later layer of P)

but if you put P in Hezekiah's time it becomes (leaving out the priestly code and ezekiel):
#Ritual Decalogue (J)/ Covenant Code (E)
#Holiness Code (H = early layer of P)
#Deuteronomic Code (D)

So where do Friedmann and Kaufmann put
*Implications of the Book of Ezekiel
*[[Priestly Code]] (later layer of P)

in relation to the Deuteronomic Code (D), and how is that rectified with the date of Ezekiel?

[[User:Newman Luke|Newman Luke]] ([[User talk:Newman Luke|talk]]) 16:40, 24 October 2009 (UTC)

== The Amber Witch link itself is weasel ==

There is no mention in the Amber Witch Hoax article to DH or even the idea behind DH.  This is weaselly link to suggest that the DH is also a hoax.  These topics are not related.  &lt;span style=&quot;color:Purple&quot;&gt;—&lt;/span&gt; '''[[User:Fcsuper|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#006699&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#6666FF&quot;&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#666699&quot;&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#336633&quot;&gt;u&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#006699&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#6633FF&quot;&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#9966FF&quot;&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;]]'''&lt;sup&gt; ([[:User talk:Fcsuper|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Olive&quot;&gt;How's That?&lt;/span&gt;]], [[Special:Contributions/Fcsuper|&lt;span style=&quot;color:Teal&quot;&gt;That's How!&lt;/span&gt;]])&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sub&gt;([http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Exclusionism &lt;span style=&quot;color:Maroon&quot;&gt;Exclusionistic&lt;/span&gt;] [http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Immediatism &lt;span style=&quot;color:Red&quot;&gt;Immediatist&lt;/span&gt;] ) &lt;/sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:Purple&quot;&gt;—&lt;/span&gt;  17:45, 17 January 2010 (UTC)

:[[The Amber Witch#Background]] has a discussion which begins: &quot;The author's intention had been to set a deliberate &quot;trap for the disciples of David Strauss and his school who pronounced the scriptures of the Old and New Testament to be a collection of legends from historical research assisted by internal evidence&quot;.[8]&quot; I am ''not'' defending the idea that the Amber Witch Hoax was an appropriate attack on the DH (and certainly not that the DH is itself a hoax), but merely that it is a mildly interesting topic in the history of the idea, at least worth passing reference. [[User:TomS TDotO|TomS TDotO]] ([[User talk:TomS TDotO|talk]]) 19:17, 17 January 2010 (UTC)

::Nobody is interested in The Amber Witch? [[User:TomS TDotO|TomS TDotO]] ([[User talk:TomS TDotO|talk]]) 12:28, 21 January 2010 (UTC)

:::The Amber Witch Hoax was an attack upon scholars of the [[Historical Jesus]], not upon scholars of the [[Documentary Hypothesis]]  [[User:Revanneosl|Revanneosl]] ([[User talk:Revanneosl|talk]]) 13:39, 1 October 2011 (UTC)

== Proposal to redirect [[Ritual decalogue]] to [[Covenant code]] ==

Please see my proposal [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Ritual_Decalogue#Proposal_to_redirect here] and comment/vote.  Thanks, [[User:Slrubenstein|Slrubenstein]]   |  [[User talk:Slrubenstein|Talk]] 15:46, 11 July 2010 (UTC)

== Support for Mosaic authorship ==

Are we really supposed to take seriously a reference which supports Mosaic authorship by saying that with God all things are possible? [[User:TomS TDotO|TomS TDotO]] ([[User talk:TomS TDotO|talk]]) 15:39, 31 August 2010 (UTC)
:Lacking any positive support for this reference, I'll revert the addition. [[User:TomS TDotO|TomS TDotO]] ([[User talk:TomS TDotO|talk]]) 16:03, 1 September 2010 (UTC)

== Blenkinsopp book? ==

This sentence says: &quot;Whybray's questions pertaining to the documentary hypothesis, however, have been largely answered[citation needed] by Joseph Blenkinsopp.&quot; Then we have a whole para about Blenkinsopp's answer. Much as I admire Blenkinsopp, this really needs a source - does anyone know what we're referring to? [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 11:37, 12 October 2010 (UTC)

== Figure ==

We currently have this figure on the DH view re the development of the Torah:
[[File:Modern document hypothesis.svg|thumb|240px|Diagram of the Documentary Hypothesis.
{|style=&quot;background:none&quot;
|&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;||includes most of Leviticus
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|&lt;sup&gt;†&lt;/sup&gt;||includes most of Deuteronomy
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|&lt;sup&gt;‡&lt;/sup&gt;||&quot;''Deuteronomic history''&quot;: Joshua, Judges, 1 &amp; 2 Samuel, 1 &amp; 2 Kings
|}]]

It's someone's personal work, and I think them for the effort they've put into it, but I believe it's a little bit not quite right in places. It puts J and E side by side, as if they came from the same time, when the theory holds that J was slighly earlier; and it seems to have D earlier than P, when the classic view has them the other way round. It also has a set of boxes for the Deuteronomistic history, which is really a separate if related issue. I wonder if anyone  feels like either revising it or finding a free source we can use? [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 23:40, 27 October 2010 (UTC)


== Restoring a missing section of this article ==
There was a large section of this article that was deleted.  The opinions of many Bible scholars were wiped out and replaced with this pious statement: &quot;but none doubted the truth of the tradition.&quot;  But this claim is simply incorrect. 

That is why it is important to restore the deleted section. Critical academic study of the Torah's origins began in classical rabbinic Judaism, what some call Orthodox Judaism, centuries before Wellhausen - and as the sources quoted herein state, the existence of such views are explicitly recognized by Orthodox rabbis.  In fact, the sources given within the article name an entire book on the academic, critical text study of the Torah, Bible and rabbinic literature from an Orthodox Jewish point of view.

[[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]) 17:41, 20 December 2010 (UTC)

:The &quot;pious statement&quot; is a quote from Gordon Wenham, a respected (and not fundamentalist) scholar. Wenham was talking about the difference between traditional and modern attitudes - before Astruc scholars didn't question or care who wrote the bible. You mention early Jewish scholars, but people like Ibn Ezra are very few and far between - the exception, and a very rare one. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 10:26, 7 January 2011 (UTC)

==The heart of this article was cut out: Now restored==
Today, the vast majority of Bible scholars believe that the Torah is a composite document, edited together from a variety of earlier sources. (This view is also accepted as correct by all rabbis and scholars in non-Orthodox forms of Judaism, and by many priests and scholars in many forms of Christianity.) Why would anyone believe this?  Shouldn't this article describe the reasoning behind the people who hold this point of view?

In point of fact, this article used to do just that.  There was a section, ''Major areas considered to support the documentary hypothesis include''.  Just as importantly, this article used to note that: &quot;Many portions of the Torah seem to imply more than one author. Doublets and triplets repeat stories with different points of view.&quot; This is a hugely important point.  While at one point this article featured these sections front and center, for years, a while back somone cut out this section, leaving the article hanging in mid-air, presenting complicated views without summarizing the major textual reasons for people having such views.  As such, I have restored this section. [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]) 20:28, 20 December 2010 (UTC)

:I've cut this out, not because I disagree with it (I agree), but because I believe it to be unnecessary. The idea that the Torah is a composite is universal - there's no need to argue for it. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 10:23, 7 January 2011 (UTC)

::I strenuously disagree.  I have worked in general education and religious education, and I can tell you that this impression is incorrect.  A great many Christians deny the essentials of the documentary hypothesis, possibly the majority of Christians in the world! And so do many Jews, including nearly all of the Orthodox Jewish community.  Most people I have discussed the Bible with, in fact, simply assume that the Torah is more or less directly from Moses, even if they are agnostics or atheists. [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]) 16:57, 7 January 2011 (UTC)

One must take it on faith that there are many authors. There is no need to argue this point.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.92.138.14|68.92.138.14]] ([[User talk:68.92.138.14|talk]]) 03:01, 30 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Removing all the evidence and logic is a very bad idea==
The latest edits to this article, [[Documentary Hypothesis]], removes the summary of reasons that scholars believe that the Torah is a composite document. I am concerned, because a few years ago, some Orthodox Jewish, and traditional Christians, made these same types of edits - to make it look like the documentary hypothesis is less likely to be correct, and that fundamentalist teachings were more likely to be certainly true.

Because of the huge amount of material deleted by PiCo, all that is left of this article are various ideas that the Torah is composite...but without a good summary of the logical reasons why.  I think that it is important for us to summarize the logic and textual evidence. If we do not have this, then I can assure that this article will be (mis)used to &quot;prove&quot; that there isn't a serious case to accept that the Torah is composite. Rather, it will (as it has been before) be used to &quot;prove&quot; that the Torah is unitary and (mostly) unchanged since the time of Moses,

&lt;i&gt;The majority of Wikipedia readers have little to no knowledge about this subject. &lt;/i&gt; Your averge person really believes that the Torah is, more or less, a unitary document, and many are willing to accept that it was probably written by Moses himself, plus or minus textual errors tha have accumulated over the milennai. In fact, &lt;i&gt;even many agnostics believe this.&lt;/i&gt; For many people, the debate is about whether or not God literally inspired prophets to write the Bible, or whether God exists at all. 

Right now this article focuses on the technical details, but lacks the general reasoning for it's very existence. [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]) 16:54, 7 January 2011 (UTC)

: I'm concerned about this too. Look how much information was deleted without any discussion at all: http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Documentary_hypothesis&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=406464971&amp;oldid=406130103. I think we should revert these changes (as numerous as they are, many are just deletions and re-wordings), and not do it again until things are discussed. Yay or nay? [[User:GManNickG|GManNickG]] ([[User talk:GManNickG|talk]]) 22:34, 13 January 2011 (UTC)

==What does the phrase &quot;Documentary Hypothesis&quot; mean?==
I'd like to reiterate this point. Many people here seem to believe that the term &quot;documentary hypothesis&quot; refers to Wellhausen's 4-document hypothesis.  But this is incorrect. Rather, Wellhausen's hypothesis is merely the first of a number of modern ideas about the textual origin of the Torah.  

Outside of fundamentalist Christian and jewish communities, mainsteram academics (and non-fundamentalist Jews and Christians) use the phrase &quot;documentary hypothesis&quot; to describe any hypothesis that sees the Torah's origins in independent documents, no matter how many they may be. Also note that many, if not most, modern day views are loosely related to Wellhausen's basic concept of J, E, P and D. In other words, although his specific ideas are denied today, his general outline is still considered to be a good model by many scholars today.
[[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]) 20:35, 20 December 2010 (UTC)

:Wellhausen wasn't the first to propose a documentary hypothesis, and I believe the article makes this clear. He merely put forward the most exhaustive, conclusive case for documents over the other two competing hypotheses - the supplementary hypothesis and the fragmentary hypothesis. Note that Wellhausen put forward &quot;a&quot; hypothesis, not &quot;the&quot; hypothesis - his version had 4 sources, but Astruc's had only 2 sources. In the 20th century the E source has been so severely criticised that modern versions of the hypothesis frequently propose only 3 sources. Nor are modern theories using the symbolic language of JEPD (more often JPD without E) necessarily documentary in nature - many regard D as a document, but J and P as editorial work over several centuries. (Unless they're Tommy Thompson). [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 10:21, 7 January 2011 (UTC)

::I am not sure of why you wrote this. Maybe I was unclear. Just to be clear, these are points on which we ''agree''. [[User:RK|RK]] ([[User talk:RK|talk]]) 13:42, 7 January 2011 (UTC)

== Merger proposal ==

I've suggested that [[Torah redactor]] be merged into this article. It has been unsourced or poorly sourced for nearly a year and discusses mainly the same content in some more detail. [[Special:Contributions/134.29.231.11|134.29.231.11]] ([[User talk:134.29.231.11|talk]]) 18:31, 24 February 2011 (UTC)

:merge performed as there was no discussion.[[Special:Contributions/173.141.251.43|173.141.251.43]] ([[User talk:173.141.251.43|talk]]) 10:15, 14 March 2011 (UTC)

I've now suggested that [[JE]] be merged into this article. [[JE]] is quite short and discusses the documentary hypothesis in more detail. That detail should be here, I think. [[Special:Contributions/134.29.231.11|134.29.231.11]] ([[User talk:134.29.231.11|talk]]) 20:26, 15 March 2011 (UTC)

*'''Support merge.''' I don't think &quot;Documentary hypothesis&quot; is the most common meaning of &quot;JE&quot;, which should be a disambiguation page linking to this one. [[User:Jokestress|Jokestress]] ([[User talk:Jokestress|talk]]) 06:03, 25 March 2011 (UTC)
*'''Support merge.''' Because of the similarity of the two and the concreteness of this article compared to [[Torah redactor]]. &lt;i style=&quot;text-shadow:lime 0.2em 0.2em 0.4em;&quot;&gt;[[User:Wekn reven i susej eht|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;'''Wekn '''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Wekn reven i susej eht|&lt;font color=&quot;lawngreen&quot;&gt;'''TAKN'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 17:28, 11 June 2012 (UTC)

== DH 'universally accepted' Wenham ref ==
Is it appropriate to cite Wenham as authority for 'universal acceptance' for the DH [http://www.biblicalstudies.org.uk/article_pentateuch_wenham.html] , when he actually writes 'by the mid-twentieth century it was almost universally accepted. But in the 1970s this cosy consensus began to be disturbed.'? He then documents four areas of disagreement with and challenge to DH, which the article partly addresses, but the selective quote does not quite represent the situation accurately.
[[User:Cpsoper|Cpsoper]] ([[User talk:Cpsoper|talk]]) 11:37, 30 March 2011 (UTC)
:Maybe you're right - the full sentence in our article says: ''&quot;The hypothesis dominated biblical scholarship for much of the 20th century, and, although increasingly challenged by other models in the last part of the 20th century, its terminology and insights continue to provide the framework for modern theories on the origins of the Torah.&quot;'' Wenham (who's a very respectable scholar by the way - no problem in that area) does say pretty explicitly that the DH dominated the field for much of the C.20th, but it would be hard to source the rest of the sentence to that article. It happens to be true, but the source doesn't support it. Feel free to look around for something better. (Wenham does support the sentence indirectly, as he talks at length about the use of terms such as P and J and accepts without question that the Torah has complex origins and multiple authors, but he doesn't explicitly say so). [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 06:45, 31 March 2011 (UTC)
::Sorry, I see now you were talking about a different sentence. You made a good edit there. [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 06:48, 31 March 2011 (UTC)

== Bullet item for 'Redactor' ==

There was a left-over bullet item for 'Redactor' which was an internal link to a now-deleted section [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Documentary_hypothesis&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=438748116&amp;oldid=437940452]; I've removed it since a) it didn't point anywhere and b) its inclusion in the list made it seem (to my admittedly untutored eye) that &quot;R&quot; was one of five sources postulated by Wellhausen; I don't know if that's true or not but I'm guessing if the section 'Redactor' was removed as unreferenced it probably wasn't.  But please do correct me (or at least the article) if I'm incorrect. Thanks. [[User:BrideOfKripkenstein|BrideOfKripkenstein]] ([[User talk:BrideOfKripkenstein|talk]]) 06:05, 29 December 2011 (UTC)

==What is the source material?==
Several hundred years of work by people who speak several different languages.
Which bible did each of them use?
Hebrew?
Ancient Greek?
German?
King James? A combination?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/75.15.208.130|75.15.208.130]] ([[User talk:75.15.208.130|talk]]) 05:20, 5 June 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Please specify and clarify your comment. &lt;i style=&quot;text-shadow:lime 0.2em 0.2em 0.4em;&quot;&gt;[[User:Wekn reven i susej eht|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;'''Wekn '''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Wekn reven i susej eht|&lt;font color=&quot;lawngreen&quot;&gt;'''TAKN'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;
::Like Wekn, I'm not suere what you mean. In the hope that this clarifies matters: The Old Testament was written almost entirely in Hebrew, the New Testament in the form of Greek common in the region in the first century CE; an important Greek translation of the Hebrew Old Testament was made in the last few centuries before Christ and is still the bible used by the Orthodox Christian churches. Both Testaments were translated into Latin round 500 CE, and then into various European languages from about 1500 on (the translators used the oldest texts they could find, usually the Hebrew text used by Jews for the Old Testament and old Greek texts for the New). [[User:PiCo|PiCo]] ([[User talk:PiCo|talk]]) 03:23, 30 August 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>7knivk8bn5il4gzhh0vpmalj2qr6dqn</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
