<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.8.xsd" version="0.8" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <base>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.21wmf3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Bhakti movement</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>449154</id>
    <revision>
      <id>518092044</id>
      <parentid>518091957</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-10-16T09:54:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hoverfish</username>
        <id>2086471</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Bhakti named cult in articles */ corr</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6425">{{WikiProject Hinduism|class=Start|importance=Mid|vaishnavism=yes|krishna=yes}}

There are a lot more and older bhakti movements than chaitanya Mahaprabhu. 
[[User:Andries|Andries]] 14:22, 31 January 2004 (UTC)

:We should delete this page or just redirect it to [[bhakti yoga]]. --[[User:LordSuryaofShropshire|LordSuryaofShropshire]] 22:22, Apr 2, 2004 (UTC)

::But if we don't, we should take out everything relevant to teachers of Krishna Bhakti from the Rama Bhakti section. Also, the Rama Bhakti section should not be completely separate from the Vaishnava Bhakti section, because they aren't mutually exlusive categories. The largest Vaishnava monastic organization is the Ramanandi, whose members are Rama Bhaktas. --[[User:Raimmmmm|Raimmmmm]] 19:44, 13 February 2007 (UTC)

:::This article rambles quite a bit and requires a clean-up. I agree that Rama-bhakti should not be so segregated from Vaishnava bhakti as many Vaishnavas worship Rama and Krishna, or Rama as an avatar of Vishnu, or Sita and Rama as their dearmost Ishta-devas. Chaitanya Mahaprabhu had disciples who were also Rama bhaktas ([http://vedabase.net/cc/adi/17/69/en1]). Ys, [[User:GourangaUK|Gouranga(UK)]] 09:26, 14 February 2007 (UTC)

==Medieval Islamic rule &amp; Bhakti Movement==
There is a sentence in the introduction of Bhakti movement which states that &quot;Islamic rulers were pressing public to convert religion from Hindu to Islam&quot; - to this I have added citation needed because there is difference between political tyranny &amp; socio-religious developments. Though I do not deny inter-relation between two, but Bhakti movement was not just response to that tyranny. It has very larger background - like opposition to rituals, social division on caste lines &amp; Brahman dominance. So, it is inappropriate to call Bhakti movement as response to Islamic politcal tyranny which in fact defeats the whole purpose of Bhakti movement. Please refer Bipin Chandra's India's Struggle for Independence book (Chapter - Socio-religious reforms) this chapter clearly rejects concept that Medieval Muslim tyranny was anyway related to religious reforms. [[User:Javalkoti|Javalkoti]] ([[User talk:Javalkoti|talk]]) 16:40, 7 July 2012 (UTC)

==New name?==
How about we re-name this article to [Bhakti (History)] or [History of the Bhakti movements] or similar? Much of the information included is chronological rather than philosophical and it would then make sense as a partner-page to the other bhakti articles. Best Wishes, [[User:GourangaUK|Gouranga(UK)]] 15:45, 14 February 2007 (UTC)
:May be re-organizing the set of articles
:1. [[bhakti movement]] that describes the philosophies and types (e.g. shaiva and vaishnava)
:2. [[list of bhakti movements]]
:3.  [[history of bhakti movements]]
:4. merging [[bhakta]] into [[bhakti]]
:[[User:Andries|Andries]] 20:57, 9 September 2007 (UTC)

==Shaiva, Shakta, etc Bhakta movements?==

Headings in this article, and to a lesser extent content, seem largely Vaishnava. comes across as undue weight. --[[User:Simon D M|Simon D M]] ([[User talk:Simon D M|talk]]) 18:58, 10 January 2008 (UTC)

== vague and incomplete ==

The article is vague, not to the point, incomplete and small emphasis on Bhakti Movement.

Bhakti Movement was started during the period of Delhi Sultanate.It's earliest known exponent is Ramanuja, who flourished in 12th century

others included Nimbarka, Madhava , Ramanand , Chaitanya who is considered one of the greatest saint of Bhakti movement, Namadeva , and Kabir. The founder of Sikhism , Guru Nanak is also considered to be a part of this movement.[[User:Ajjay|Ajjay]] ([[User talk:Ajjay|talk]]) 09:54, 18 January 2008 (UTC)

==Links to gurus==
::Just to let every one know. I will be taking out the listing of Bhakti Tirtha Swami from the vaishnava bhakti Acharya list on the article on Sat. 08 March 08'. I do not think that some one should put their personal guru in a list of Maha-gurus/Acharyas.    [[User:zeuspitar|zeuspitar]] Govinda Ramanuja dasa 19:24, 06 March 2008 (UTC)

:::By any chance...who put Bhakti tirtha swami in the list of vaishnava bhakti acharyas? Who is the one who puts these ISKON gurus on articles? It seems that no one knows their history. We should take out PERSONAL gurus and just leave Maha-acharyas like Sankarycharya, Ramanujacharya, Madhvacharya and Caitanya Maha-Prabhu. And thats it.     [[User:zeuspitar|zeuspitar]] Govinda Ramanuja dasa 19:24, 06 March 2008 (UTC)

::::I agree in regards to the link to Bhakti Tirtha Swami and have removed it. It was added some time ago by another editor. I see no reason why he should be singled out amongst other devotional teachers and Swamis. In terms of notability I believe that the link to Bhaktivedanta Swami is relevant as the organisation he founded is of historical significance in terms of the spread of bhakti, as are his published writings on the subject. Regards, [[User:GourangaUK|Gouranga(UK)]] ([[User talk:GourangaUK|talk]]) 21:01, 7 March 2008 (UTC)

:::I agree also with you on Prabhupada...Absolutely. I forgot to list His name in the postings above.[[User:zeuspitar|zeuspitar]] Govinda Ramanuja dasa 18:24, 07 March 2008 (UTC)

== Puthandu ==

Puthandu nothing to do with hinduism as it is celebarated by all tamils regardless of religion.Eventhough tamil calendar is influenced by sanskrit currently the new years date has been changed from chithirai to thai following Thiruvallivar andu Tamil calendar(unsanskritised)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/175.140.43.10|175.140.43.10]] ([[User talk:175.140.43.10|talk]]) 14:05, 27 January 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Bhakti named cult in articles ==

Although there is nothing wrong with the original meaning of the word &quot;[[cult]]&quot;, its current popular use and implications are mostly negative. I corrected one chance instance of &quot;cult&quot; to &quot;movement&quot; but then I made a search for &quot;Bhakti cult&quot; [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?search=Bhakti+cult&amp;button=&amp;title=Special%3ASearch] and found that the use of this term is frequent. I do not feel adequate to go about making such changes on my own, so I bring this issue up here in case there is a consensus to effect such changes. [[User:Hoverfish|Hoverfish]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Hoverfish|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:52, 16 October 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>8okruadhgvfq34zscl445kajk3uwfx7</sha1>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
